<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4087</transcript-id>
    <title>TEXT OF THE PRIME MINISTER&#039;S ADDRESS AT THE OPENING OF THE AUSTRALIAN-AMERICAN ASSOCIATION FESTIVAL</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/03/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004087.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER P76/ 58 i<br />
FOR PRESS MARCH 26. 1976<br />
TEXT OF THE PRIME MINISTER'S ADDRESS AT THlE OPENING OF THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN-AMERICAN ASSOCIATION FESTIVALThe<br />
American revolution 200 years ago marked a tremendous victory<br />
for men and women who wanted to be free free to control the<br />
affairs of their own country and their own lives.<br />
Men and women around the world fighting for freedom still look to<br />
the United States because of that revolution as an inspiration.<br />
Men such as Alexander Solzenitsyn remind us that freedom is still<br />
an idea with the power to inspire men to greatness, still a potent<br />
idea for change on behalf of human dignity.<br />
In the two hundred years since the American revolution Americans<br />
have used their freedom to build through generations of pioneering<br />
work and effort the most prosperous country in the world.<br />
America has used her prosperity to undertake the most generous<br />
programmes of aid in the history of the world from the great<br />
aid programmes to the Soviet Union after the First World War,<br />
through Marshall Aid to its present programmes, the United States<br />
has been a force for decency and humanity in the world.<br />
America's freedom has not come cheaply. It has been defended many<br />
times in war. It has been tested many times at home. Few nations<br />
have been so open to scrutiny, so self-critical, as the United States.<br />
Abuses which in other less open societies would remain hidden from<br />
the world have been ferreted out and held up to exposure by citizens<br />
relentless in their pursuit of human dignity-, arid by a free press<br />
with a great tradition of journalism. Time and again Americans<br />
have been shocked it seems by what they have learned about<br />
themselves facts they could only have learned because they are<br />
free. Invariably, it seems Americans have moved slviftly to right<br />
the wrongs and eradicate abuses.<br />
Dictatorships and police states have, of course, used the information<br />
revealed by a free press as weapons to attack arid discredit the<br />
United States. It is as well to remind ourselves that the free<br />
society of the United States existed long before those Governments<br />
came into being. It will long survive them.<br />
Australia shares and is proud to share close bonds of friendship<br />
with the United States.<br />
Australia's development as a nation is part of the same great<br />
movement of people from Europe that gave birth to the United States.<br />
Inevitably, we have shared many experiences during that history<br />
in peace as well as in war, since that day in 1792 when the first<br />
American ship to visit Australia '' The Philadelphia"' sailed<br />
into Port Jackson.<br />
In those days American traders apparently made a good living by<br />
selling spirits to the Australian colonists. As a revolutionary<br />
country they appear to have exported a revolutionary spirit.<br />
Their own revolution, as I recall, was fought on tea. Our first rebellion<br />
was fought on rum. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
During the nineteenth century Australians and Americans showed a<br />
striking willingness to help each other in the search for gold.<br />
In 1849-50 many thousands left Sydney for California in the search<br />
for gold. The Australians efforts were not entirely appreciated<br />
arid the rapid emigration from Australia was halted by a vigorous<br />
" Sydney Coves Go Home" movement anid by the discovery of gold in<br />
Australia. Between 1851-56 10,000 people came to Australia from<br />
the United States, thus repaying us in full measure for our<br />
interest in American gold.<br />
Marny famous names in Australian history came from or via the United<br />
States: George Chaffey the pioneer of irrigation in Australia;<br />
J. C. Williamson -who became in his day perhaps the<br />
leading theatrical entreprener<br />
of the British Empire;<br />
King O'Malley one of our most colorful politicians;<br />
Walter Burley Griffin-the designer of our National Capital<br />
The Founding Fathers of the Australian Federation of course, looked<br />
to the United States for help in drawing up the Australian Constitution.<br />
From the United States, we borrowed the idea of Federalism itself,<br />
arid the concepts of a Senate and a High Court to intrepret the<br />
Constitution. The American Senate is, of course, more powerful<br />
than ours though the Australian. Senate is not without some<br />
useful powers.<br />
It must be understood that between countries which have such beliefs<br />
in common there will inevitably grow up links that are different<br />
that are deeper and more enduring than would develop between<br />
nations of quite disparate traditions.<br />
Defence links we have with the United States are based on our own<br />
independent assessment that we have interests in common with the<br />
United States that we can advance by joining closely together.<br />
There may have been some doubts in recent times whether Australia<br />
had departed from her state as an aligned nation. Let me state<br />
unequivocally, that Australia is an aligned nation we are arn ally<br />
of the United States and will remain so.<br />
Because we are an ally of the United States, that does not mean that<br />
we support every American action in the world.<br />
But being an ally does imply that the major objectives of both<br />
countries are similar the defence of free societies where men<br />
and women can choose their own destinies.<br />
An important part of our role as an ally is that we should form<br />
our own independent judgements and speak frankly to the United States<br />
about our concerns where they exist. But when we do disagree,<br />
our views will be expressed in proper terms, arid in the proper<br />
way, and not shouted across the seas.<br />
Being an ally does not mean that we caninot form very close relations<br />
with other countries. We will speak with all countries, seek<br />
cooperative relations with all countries, regardless of ideology.<br />
We have close anid friendly relations with Indonesia and olther<br />
countries in south East Asia. Our decisions affect their I'utiure<br />
and their decisions, our future. Great power politics affect us<br />
both. We will seek to strengthen anid build on these relationships. / 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
Being an ally means that Australia has an important role to play as<br />
an independent and responsible voice in international affairs.<br />
Irrational and unreasoned criticism does nothing to help the United<br />
States in performing its critically important role in securing<br />
world peace. I fear that it has sometimes deterred the United<br />
States from doing what needs to be done.<br />
As the world's greatest free power an immense responsibility falls<br />
on the United States, a responsibility not just to provide an<br />
effective counter in the balance of world power, but a responsibility<br />
to provide a lead to the democratic peoples of the world.<br />
A great power like the United States cannot expect to be loved and<br />
won't be loved. What any great power should look for is to be<br />
respected. The vital thing is that the United States should do<br />
those things which only the world's greatest free country can do.<br />
If it fails to do this, not only American security but the security<br />
of all of us will be at risk.<br />
The important thing is not what people in other countries say, but<br />
whether the United States is prepared to do those things which are<br />
necessary for the stability and security of the world.<br />
As a democracy, as a free country, our alliance with the United<br />
States is accompanied by a warm friendship.<br />
It gives me very great pleasure to ask you ladies and gentlemen<br />
to rise and drink with me the toast: " To continuing friendship<br />
between the two nations". </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
