<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4573</transcript-id>
    <title>INDUSTRY TALKS ON PETROL RETAILING, 1 DECEMBER 1977</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/12/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004573.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
JAUSTIRAIJA<br />
PRIME MIlNISTER<br />
r oR T1nss I' T) ECP. M1BR .1977<br />
INDUSTRY. TALKS ON PI-TROI, RY-ThILING<br />
the P'rime Minister, Malcolm Praser, * met with representatives<br />
6f the Western Australian AUtoMobile Chamber . of Coimmerce in)<br />
Perth ycnterday.<br />
The representatives of the Chamber raisea with the Prime Minister<br />
the problem8 faced by service station proprintors, including<br />
price discrimination by wholesale nuppliers, and the difficult<br />
contractual conditions under whichi thcy operate.-<br />
They claimed there was a process of~ vertical integration proceding<br />
with the oil companicp. retailing direct through their own<br />
outletEs at. pr-i ces beplow the wholesale price~ charged to competing<br />
service stations.<br />
The Prime Minister said that hie understood the cliff iculties<br />
faced by small service stations in maintaining their position<br />
in the industry. lie welcomed thc view expressed by the Chamber<br />
representatives that they had commwon interest with the government<br />
in keeping the price of petrol, to the consumer as low as posidble.<br />
After the next mieeting of the Oil Indurtry Marketing<br />
Consultative Committee in December, the Government will bring<br />
together suppliers and retailers under the auspices of the<br />
Covernmcnt to examine how more eqiuitable distribution and marketing<br />
polioies could he developed.<br />
These discussions will examine the problems on a nationzA basis.<br />
That meeting will lie asked to examine:<br />
1. Whether Trade Practices Act should be varied to rcmeay<br />
allegjed discriminatory pricing practices in the industey<br />
alleqcci discrimination inherent in terms and conditions<br />
of contracts between oil companies and lessees.<br />
2. A~ ction that might he appropriate in concert with States to<br />
prosecute a rationalisation prorarme.<br />
3. Development of more equitable distribution and ma~ rketing polici C<br />
following discussion of this matter by the Consultative<br />
Committee. ./ 2 </p>
<p>* 1<br />
2.<br />
The ( overnment believes that the problems can he solved by<br />
agreement within the industry, M* wcver, if agreement is riot<br />
reached, it should he understood by all the parties to the<br />
discussions that the Government can legislate to achieve a<br />
fair solution, although such legislation might require the<br />
cooperation of the. States. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
