<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11375</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                 THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                 OFFICIALLY OPEN NEWCASTLE AND HUNTER                 BUSINESS CHAMBER&#039;S NEW OFFICE                                             </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/07/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Subjects: economic indicators and prospects for the Hunter</p>
<p> Region; $2.5 million investment in a call centre for Impulse</p>
<p> Airlines; BHP closures</p>
<p>E&amp;OE....................</p>
<p>Thank you very much Rob Chenery. To David Simmons, to Bishop Hirst,</p>
<p> to the Lord Mayor, my colleague Senator John Tierney and any other</p>
<p> parliamentary colleagues, ladies and gentlemen.</p>
<p>It is a special privilege and pleasure for me to be here this morning</p>
<p> to open these new offices. I think this is either the third or fourth</p>
<p> visit that I paid to the Newcastle area in the little over three years</p>
<p> that I have been Prime Minister. And the one very simple thing that</p>
<p> I want to say to you this morning is to convey a message of optimism</p>
<p> and hope and a very positive message about the future.</p>
<p>The fact that this building is being opened and the fact that it's</p>
<p> being opened to service and provide as a headquarters for a very large</p>
<p> regional business organisation is itself a demonstration of the commitment</p>
<p> that many men and women in business are making to the future of Newcastle</p>
<p> and the Hunter Region.</p>
<p>And in his introductory speech, Rob Chenery spoke of the new Newcastle</p>
<p> and the new Hunter Region. And I think they are very apt and very</p>
<p> relevant words and they are the words behind which a community should</p>
<p> coalesce.</p>
<p>This part of Australia has a very rich history. This part of Australia</p>
<p> is seen by the rest of Australia still in a particular stereotype.</p>
<p> That is understandable and there's nothing to be ashamed of about</p>
<p> that stereotype or about that past. But like so many other communities</p>
<p> in Australia the world is changing and what is important for communities</p>
<p> is to hold onto the good things from the past but by the same token</p>
<p> change and embrace where it is necessary. And I have certainly found</p>
<p> on my visits to Newcastle over the last few years that there is a</p>
<p> determination on the part of the local community to do exactly that.</p>
<p>The economic indicators for the Hunter Region are very strong. The</p>
<p> prospects for new investment and new industry are extremely positive.</p>
<p> And I have found in the contact that I have had with people in business</p>
<p> in this area that they are filled with optimism. They understand the</p>
<p> challenges that exist, they know that there are areas of difficulty</p>
<p> and hurt and loss and deprivation but above all they are looking forward</p>
<p> to a more diverse future. And I think the opportunities that are here</p>
<p> not only in continuing areas of manufacturing and mining but also</p>
<p> in the service industries and in new areas of manufacturing endeavour</p>
<p> I think those opportunities are significant.</p>
<p>Now, this morning is not, as Rob and David correctly said, it is not</p>
<p> an occasion or a forum for a litany of announcements of this or that.</p>
<p> I merely remind this audience of an announcement I made last night</p>
<p> of an in-principle commitment by the Federal Government to a $2.5</p>
<p> million investment in a call centre for Impulse Airlines. It will</p>
<p> be subject to certain conditions but I understand from discussion</p>
<p> with the company those conditions will be able to be met. And that</p>
<p> will lead to the generation of some 70 to 80 jobs directly and more</p>
<p> jobs indirectly.</p>
<p>Of itself not a huge announcement but one of a number which add to</p>
<p> the diversification of the employment base and the business opportunities</p>
<p> of this area. And a few days ago my colleague, John Moore the Defence</p>
<p> Minister, announced that Boeing was the successful contractor for</p>
<p> the early warning system. And much of the infrastructure for that</p>
<p> will be centered around Williamtown. And when you add together the</p>
<p> various investments that are going to be made in the aerospace industry</p>
<p> in and around Williamtown they will make a very significant contribution</p>
<p> to the diversification and change in the employment opportunities</p>
<p> and the business base of the region.</p>
<p>Now, all of this is occurring against the background of a national</p>
<p> economy that is performing extremely well. And it's important that</p>
<p> we understand that the national economy is in good shape. We are enjoying</p>
<p> the strongest growth of any industrialised nation in the world. We</p>
<p> have inflation and interest rates that are at a 30 year low. Nationally,</p>
<p> we have had strong employment growth with an unemployment rate nationally</p>
<p> which is lower than it's been for 10 years. We have very high levels</p>
<p> of business investment and lamb notwithstanding we have even increased</p>
<p> our exports to the United States - but I emphasise lamb notwithstanding.</p>
<p>So it is, generally speaking, a very positive picture. And it's a</p>
<p> picture that ought to fill Australians as a whole with a great deal</p>
<p> of sense of optimism. We were able to stare down the worst Asian economic</p>
<p> downturn in 30 or 40 years. And in all the visits that I have paid</p>
<p> to the city of New York, which is the financial capital of the world,</p>
<p> in the various positions I have occupied, the visit I paid last week</p>
<p> found me receiving more than on any other occasion a universal acceptance</p>
<p> that Australia was doing well. And a universal belief that the economic</p>
<p> policies that were being followed at the present time were delivering</p>
<p> results that were very positive.</p>
<p>Now, I mention all of those things not in any kind of triumphal sense</p>
<p> but I think it's important to be realistic. It's important to recognise</p>
<p> difficulty where it exists but it's also important not to be so overwhelmed</p>
<p> with the negative side of things that you lose sight of the positive.</p>
<p> And there's a very good national story to be told and there's an increasingly</p>
<p> good regional story to be told in Newcastle and the Hunter. And it's</p>
<p> important that people in this room tell it. It's important that I</p>
<p> tell it. But it's also important that we understand that there are</p>
<p> fellow Australians in this community who are suffering hurt and alienation.</p>
<p> And I understand that and I have just come from a discussion with</p>
<p> the Prime Minister's Taskforce on Newcastle that I established a couple</p>
<p> of years ago that is jointly chaired by Rob Chenery and Kevin Maher</p>
<p> of the Australian Workers' Union. And that Taskforce has kept in regular</p>
<p> touch with me. We discussed this morning a number of proposals relating</p>
<p> to improved access to employment support services after the redundancies</p>
<p> take place at BHP in September.</p>
<p>So hand-in-hand with recognising and extolling and drawing attention</p>
<p> to the employment opportunities and the business opportunities that</p>
<p> are growing I also recognise that there are amongst the people of</p>
<p> Newcastle those and their families who are seeing things more difficult</p>
<p> and are having harder times and are suffering loss that other sections</p>
<p> of the community aren't. And a community that brings together the</p>
<p> commitment of the Federal Government, the State Government, of the</p>
<p> union movement, of the business community, of the churches and of</p>
<p> philanthropic individuals. A community that can get all of those together</p>
<p> in what I might call a grand social coalition to tackle community</p>
<p> problems is a community that will look after difficult areas but equally</p>
<p> to reach out and to build new prosperity and to build new opportunities.</p>
<p>And I have sought in the time that I have been Prime Minister to work</p>
<p> closely with the New South Wales Government, to put aside any political</p>
<p> differences, to recognise that it's important for both of us to work</p>
<p> together in relation to issues that affect Newcastle. We might disagree</p>
<p> on other matters but when it comes to helping people through difficult</p>
<p> times it's incumbent on governments at a State and federal level to</p>
<p> work together as closely as possible.</p>
<p>But this is a very important day for the business community of Newcastle.</p>
<p> And Philip Holt, the National Director of your organisation, reminded</p>
<p> me that today was the culmination of something that had started in</p>
<p> 1917 or 1918 and he showed me the minute book. And he said, if you</p>
<p> thought you'd completed a long journey with the GST you are only just</p>
<p> beginning. And I think it's a reminder of how things change or in</p>
<p> a sense but how they really stay the same. And it has been, I know,</p>
<p> a collaborative effort between many people that have brought the business</p>
<p> elements of this community together.</p>
<p>But it is a special part of Australia. It has a very diverse base.</p>
<p> It's history is steeped in manufacturing and mining. That is still</p>
<p> part of its future but the future is broader and more diverse. And</p>
<p> it's important that the rest of Australia understands that that future</p>
<p> is broader and more diverse. And it's important that the rest of Australia</p>
<p> understand the spirit of this part of the world. It's one that I have</p>
<p> been visiting on a regular basis long before I became Prime Minister</p>
<p> and one with which I am very familiar.</p>
<p>So I was therefore very pleased indeed to be invited to come here</p>
<p> again to open these new premises. To congratulate the people of Newcastle,</p>
<p> to congratulate the Business Chamber on its commitment to entrepreneurial</p>
<p> activity and private enterprise which is the foundation of the prosperity</p>
<p> of any community and without which prosperity is impossible. I congratulate</p>
<p> the businessmen and women whatever their businesses are on the contribution</p>
<p> that they are making to the community and pulling the appropriate</p>
<p> cord to declare these premises duly open. Thank you.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
