<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10642</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                  THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                RADIO 5DN WITH JEREMY CORDEAUX</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/07/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...................................................................................................</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>It is with great pleasure that we welcome the Prime Minister of</p>
<p>   Australia John Howard. Good morning.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Good morning Jeremy.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>Nice to talk to you. Now, this backflip of Mal Colston's.</p>
<p>   I took it that you had it more or less in the bag. Was it is a total</p>
<p>   surprise when he voted against the Bill?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No it wasn't. At no stage did he promise that he would. We</p>
<p>   hoped he might. Some of his behaviour indicated that he might, but</p>
<p>   we've got this on-going problem in the Senate. We've had</p>
<p>   one hand tied behind our back ever since we were elected two-and-a-quarter</p>
<p>   years ago and that is we're in a minority in the Senate and</p>
<p>   we never know until the last minute whether we are going to get</p>
<p>   vital legislation through and this was no exception. But we are</p>
<p>   not daunted. We will try again, because this is a good policy for</p>
<p>   Australia. If we can sell the rest of Telstra we can massively reduce</p>
<p>   the Federal Government's debt and we'll have the money</p>
<p>   to provide much needed communications facilities for rural Australia.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>I'm sure government was never meant to be easy but I'm</p>
<p>   sure it wasn't meant to be this hard. In retrospect, should</p>
<p>   you perhaps have gone a little bit easier on Mal Colston, maybe</p>
<p>   accepted his vote, maybe buttered him up a bit?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, we were supportive of his nomination at Deputy President</p>
<p>   back in 1996, but I don't want to comment on his court case.</p>
<p>   I don't think it is fair that people comment. And one of the</p>
<p>   things that should be said is that the personal vitriol that's</p>
<p>   been heaped on him by the Labor Party has been quite disgusting.</p>
<p>   I've never read such malicious hateful language for years,</p>
<p>   and I just can't believe that politics should be conducted</p>
<p>   in this country in that fashion. We'll continue to talk to</p>
<p>   Senator Colston. He's got concerns about services in Queensland</p>
<p>   and that's legitimate  he's a Senator for Queensland.</p>
<p>   I'm going to try through my Minister, Senator Alston, to talk</p>
<p>   to him again. We'll certainly put the legislation back. We</p>
<p>   don't get anything the first time around in the Senate. We</p>
<p>   don't get anything at all of any consequence the first time</p>
<p>   around in the Senate. And the Australian public is being treated</p>
<p>   to another example of just how difficult it is when you have a Government</p>
<p>   with one hand tied behind its back. But we'll continue to pursue</p>
<p>   good policies for the country and this is certainly one of them.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>Well Richard Alston said that you would only bring the Telstra</p>
<p>   sale bill back to the Senate before the next election if it was</p>
<p>   assured of success. How could you be assured of success?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, this is something that we would have to talk about with the</p>
<p>   Senator and with others, and we're continuing on with our plans</p>
<p>   to release the tax policy when it is completed, and the suggestions</p>
<p>   that in some way the defeat of Telstra bill over the weekend has</p>
<p>   upset our election plans assume that there were election plans.</p>
<p>   Well, election plans are news to me. I haven't decided when</p>
<p>   the next election is going to be. It could be as late as March or</p>
<p>   April of next year, or it could be earlier. </p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>I read all of that. You know, "Howard loses early poll momentum"</p>
<p>   and all the rest of it. I would have imagined that if you had a</p>
<p>   gut feeling for the way in which the people of Australia are thinking,</p>
<p>   that a mandate from the people of Australia as soon as possible</p>
<p>   for the sale of Telstra will be just what the doctor ordered.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, exactly. I mean, there is absolutely no reason why we couldn't</p>
<p>   go to the next election with this policy, which we will if we don't</p>
<p>   get it through before then, saying that if we are re-elected we</p>
<p>   will try and sell the remaining two-thirds of Telstra and use the</p>
<p>   proceeds to massively reduce Australia's national debt and</p>
<p>   spend a small part of the proceeds on much needed communications</p>
<p>   improvements in rural Australia. And if we win the election we will</p>
<p>   go back to the Senate and say the Australian public has given us</p>
<p>   a mandate, and we'll say to the Labor Party in the Senate,</p>
<p>   don't you now have an obligation to respect the wishes the</p>
<p>   Australian public and to pass the legislation. And we'll just</p>
<p>   keep trying until we succeed and given that we don't have a</p>
<p>   majority in the Senate, that is all we can do. And I want the Australian</p>
<p>   public to know that we do not intend to be put off from trying by</p>
<p>   the obstructionist tactics of the Labor Party and the Democrats</p>
<p>   and the Australian Greens in the Senate.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>Mal Colston seems to hang his rejection of the Bill on broken promises</p>
<p>   after the sale of one-third of Telstra. Do you know what he is talking</p>
<p>   about?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>We've had those concerns investigated and the information</p>
<p>   I have is that about 95% of the commitments that were made late</p>
<p>   in 1996 have been honoured, but we'll obviously examine that</p>
<p>   further and I want him to know that we are concerned to ensure that</p>
<p>   all of the commitments that were made by Telstra are honoured in</p>
<p>   full. </p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>It's obvious that you're keen to mend some fences in</p>
<p>   the bush and to win the bush, to win rural Australia back again.</p>
<p>   Now that you've sort of offered a whole lot of goodies',</p>
<p>   if the sale of Telstra had gone through, there's quite an expectation</p>
<p>   there, isn't there? That's not going to go away easily.</p>
<p>   Even if you can't get this thing through, there's going</p>
<p>   to be, I guess what I'm saying is, maybe you've exacerbated</p>
<p>   the discontented instead of placating them?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I don't think so Jeremy. One of the goodies', as</p>
<p>   you call it, that was announced last week was the new digital phone</p>
<p>   service. Now that will go ahead quite independently of the sale</p>
<p>   of the two-thirds of Telstra. That's something that's</p>
<p>   being funded by Telstra itself. The tax package will be very good</p>
<p>   for the Australian bush and I ask rural people to have a very careful</p>
<p>   look at the taxation package and they will find that what we're</p>
<p>   offering in that area is more beneficial to them than is being offered</p>
<p>   by the Labor Party or One Nation, who appear to have formed an unholy</p>
<p>   alliance to oppose not only the sale of Telstra, but also taxation</p>
<p>   reform.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>Well will your inability - maybe inability- to sell Telstra, how</p>
<p>   is that going to effect the tax package?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Jeremy, it doesn't effect it at all. </p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>Not at all?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, there's been a mistaken claim that in some way the tax</p>
<p>   package was based on the sale of Telstra. It's not.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>Well certainly the ratings, international ratings agencies are</p>
<p>   going to react probably adversely to Australia to the knock-back</p>
<p>   in the Senate.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, what the rating agency was doing was saying that it would</p>
<p>   be good for the Australian economy if two-thirds of Telstra were</p>
<p>   sold, and it's right. It would be good for the economy because</p>
<p>   we'd be able to massively reduce the Federal Government's</p>
<p>   debt and we'd be able to start the 21st century</p>
<p>   virtually free of Federal Government debt. Now that is a tremendous</p>
<p>   boost because when you have less debt you don't have such a</p>
<p>   high interest bill and the money you would otherwise spend on interest</p>
<p>   you spend on schools, and roads, and hospitals, and public services.</p>
<p>   And the people who are voting down the sale of Telstra are really</p>
<p>   voting for less expenditure on schools, and roads, and hospitals.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>You're pretty sure that the vast majority of people in Australia</p>
<p>   want the sale of Telstra. Why not go to the people earlier rather</p>
<p>   than later and get this whole thing...I mean it must be hell</p>
<p>   of a frustration for you personally. PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well there's no guarantee though, Jeremy, even if we went</p>
<p>   to an election in which you fought it entirely on one or two issues.</p>
<p>   There's no guarantee, that even if we win that election, that</p>
<p>   we can then get the legislation through the Senate.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>Yeah, but they'd knock it back at their peril surely.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, they didn't adopt that attitude after the last election.</p>
<p>   We went to the last election promising to sell one-third of Telstra.</p>
<p>   We won that election overwhelmingly and immediately the Labor Party</p>
<p>   and the Democrats said we don't care about the verdict of the</p>
<p>   Australian people. We will frustrate and delay and destruct the</p>
<p>   Government's programme.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>So what's your thinking on the election timing now?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Jeremy, I haven't made up my mind. We can have the election</p>
<p>   as late as May, of April or May of next year. It could be earlier.</p>
<p>   It could be before the end of the year. I have not made up my mind,</p>
<p>   and I just say again that all those claims that I had a plan to</p>
<p>   go at this or that time, they were not plans that were based on</p>
<p>   anything I'd said, or anything I'd decided. I want to</p>
<p>   have the election at the right time for the country. We will of</p>
<p>   course release our tax package before the election is called and</p>
<p>   we will of course give people a reasonable time to have a look at</p>
<p>   the taxation package before we call the election. Because we want</p>
<p>   time to explain its benefits to all sections of the Australian community</p>
<p>   and there will be benefits for families, there will certainly be</p>
<p>   benefits for rural Australia and there will be an overall benefit</p>
<p>   for the Australian economy because it will be a fairer system.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>Yeah. I see that in The Australian today the unions are</p>
<p>   talking about a vow to campaign against the GST. That there is a</p>
<p>   definite threat that the union movement would force a wages break</p>
<p>   out if a goods and services tax was introduced.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, such a break out would only be justified if workers were</p>
<p>   worse of as a result of our tax reform. Workers will not be worse</p>
<p>   off as a result of our tax reform and I'd say to trade unionists</p>
<p>   in Australia: before allowing your unions to waste your union dues</p>
<p>   on partisan political campaigns, have a look at our tax package,</p>
<p>   calculate the benefits and then say to the union delegate, "don't</p>
<p>   you dare waste my money trying to stop something that will help</p>
<p>   me".</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>Yes, well that's provided the unions don't want to play</p>
<p>   politics, if the unions want to represent the best interests of</p>
<p>   their members as opposed to the best interests of the opposition.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>All I'm asking is that trade unionists have a look at what</p>
<p>   is in the policy. If they believe they are going to be worse off,</p>
<p>   well, they are therefore entitled to campaign against it, but no</p>
<p>   reasonable man or woman will be able to conclude that after they've</p>
<p>   looked at the package.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>So you've got a Cabinet meeting today and tomorrow and the</p>
<p>   word around is that the tax package is very very close to being</p>
<p>   released. Would you comment on that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, I never comment on what Cabinet discusses. We are well advanced</p>
<p>   on the tax package but there's still work to be done, and I</p>
<p>   won't fix on a date for release until everything has been completed.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>How is it shaping up?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It's shaping up very well, and the Australian public will</p>
<p>   like it. It won't be revolutionary but it will certainly be</p>
<p>   new and different and fairer. It involves a lot of political commitment</p>
<p>   and courage but my responsibility is to do things that I believe</p>
<p>   are good for the country, not things that are politically beneficial</p>
<p>   to me  things that are very good for Australia. And that's</p>
<p>   what I'm trying to do, and I'm ignoring those who say</p>
<p>   "don't take risks, don't do anything". That's</p>
<p>   not the way to win support in the Australian community.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>No, I think that you got a great vote for change and for action</p>
<p>   at the last election.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>There would have been - we certainly did - and there would have</p>
<p>   been a lot more change earlier if we hadn't have had an obstructive</p>
<p>   Senate. I mean, look how long it took us to get the Wik legislation</p>
<p>   through, and I want to thank Senator Harradine for the very constructive</p>
<p>   role that he played, and he also played a constructive role in relation</p>
<p>   to the Telstra legislation. Senator Harradine takes the wholly legitimate</p>
<p>   view for an independent for a minor party person in the Senate,</p>
<p>   that the Government of the day has a right to expect passage of</p>
<p>   the legislation which is central to its programme, and he's</p>
<p>   always tried to cooperate in that fashion. The Labor Party on the</p>
<p>   other hand takes a blindly obstructive view. It's not supported</p>
<p>   us on any major issue. It's opposed us on Native Title, it</p>
<p>   opposed us on Telstra, it opposed all the measures we took to clean</p>
<p>   up the budget deficit we inherited. Now, that's playing politics,</p>
<p>   it's not paying any regard to the national interest.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>I saw one report on the weekend that said you would rather resign,</p>
<p>   that you were quite prepared to put your job on the line over tax</p>
<p>   reform. What's the context of that remark?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, the context of that remark is that if the political path</p>
<p>   for me is to do nothing, in order to allegedly win political popularity,</p>
<p>   well, I'm unwilling to do it. I mean, I am not going to....</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>... going to say that tax reform, that tax relief is unpopular,</p>
<p>   I mean, that would be silly.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, of course it would be silly to say that. But there's</p>
<p>   a view in the community that tax reform equals only a goods and</p>
<p>   services tax. Now, that view is wrong but until our package comes</p>
<p>   out, people are not going to be persuaded that it's wrong.</p>
<p>   When our tax package comes out they will see that the GST replaces</p>
<p>   other indirect taxes, they will see that personal tax has been cut,</p>
<p>   they will see tax benefits for people with families, they will see</p>
<p>   other changes that are beneficial to the Australian economy.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>Are you able to give me a clue on what sort of taxes - will you</p>
<p>   get rid of payroll tax, capital gains tax, I guess the FID and BAD</p>
<p>   and things like that. Are you going to completely clear the decks....?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I don't think anybody should be surprised if, for example,</p>
<p>   the wholesale tax is completely abolished. I don't think anybody</p>
<p>   should be the least bit surprised at that, but as to the others</p>
<p>   I don't think I'll add to the speculation at this stage.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>There was a rumour that you were going to look after perhaps the</p>
<p>   GST and personal tax and do something about corporate tax later</p>
<p>   down the track?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, what we are going to do in relation to business tax is to</p>
<p>   lay out a framework for change and involve ourselves in a process</p>
<p>   of consultation. Once again, I don't think I'll add any</p>
<p>   further to the speculation, but reforming the corporate tax structure</p>
<p>   is part of the equation but we want to do it in a way that involves</p>
<p>   the business community, particularly the small business community.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>Yes, I was talking on Thursday and Friday about this ATSIC conference</p>
<p>   at Cable Beach that ended up costing the taxpayer $150,000 of the</p>
<p>   salary, or the fee to Pat Dodson of something like a thousand dollars</p>
<p>   a day, just for organising, just for getting it on paper I would</p>
<p>   assume. I see that the Government is going to have a look at ATSIC</p>
<p>   with regard to the way in which these conferences are charged for?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes, John Herron is pursuing that. That kind of thing, if it is</p>
<p>   true, is quite unacceptable. It makes people angry. That money would</p>
<p>   be better spent on improving Aboriginal health than on conferences,</p>
<p>   and John Herron has said that he is going to examine it, and I totally</p>
<p>   support his efforts to do so.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>Well, I would imagine that this is just the tip of the iceberg.</p>
<p>   I guess there are all sorts of other examples of profligate waste...?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, when we came into Government we put some auditing and accounting</p>
<p>   procedures into ATSIC and we made savings of millions of dollars.</p>
<p>   We were concerned about waste in that area. We were criticised but</p>
<p>   we went ahead nonetheless and we have significantly reduce waste</p>
<p>   in that area, just as we have in many other areas. We are saving</p>
<p>   something like $27 million or $28 million a week through cracking</p>
<p>   down on welfare fraud and we've done a very strong job in that</p>
<p>   area because we understand the anger of people who are working hard</p>
<p>   to paying their taxes, when they see the system ripped off by anybody,</p>
<p>   and that is not just people in the ATSIC area but people in social</p>
<p>   security generally. We are the representatives of the ordinary honest</p>
<p>   taxpayer who wants that sort of thing stopped.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>Totally agree. Now you had a win with the cheaper CDs but as you</p>
<p>   may have heard, I'm not sure whether you did or not in Macquarie</p>
<p>   News at 8.30am, the entertainment industry or the recording industry</p>
<p>   is prepared to launch a public relations campaign against your Government</p>
<p>   at the election.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes, I'm aware of that and this is going to be a case of the</p>
<p>   industry backed by the multinational companies fighting the Government</p>
<p>   who's backing the interests of the ordinary Australian public.</p>
<p>   We are on the side of cheaper CDs, we are on the side of greater</p>
<p>   competition. This a particularly strong policy for young people,</p>
<p>   but not just for young people, but young people are those in the</p>
<p>   community who especially value their CDs and the opportunity to</p>
<p>   have access to them at cheaper prices, and why shouldn't they.</p>
<p>   You've got to remember that the present system has delivered</p>
<p>   a stranglehold to the multinational companies. And all we are asking</p>
<p>   for is competition, and as far as the local industry is concerned,</p>
<p>   we understand their worries about adjusting to the new system, that's</p>
<p>   why we are giving them $10million to help the local music industry.</p>
<p>   I mean, we recognise that there is some adjustment involved and</p>
<p>   we are prepared to provide them with $10 million over a period I</p>
<p>   think of three years, to help them in that process of adjustment.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>Prime Minister I'm just looking at this wonderful picture</p>
<p>   of you, I think at the ABC with Farouk...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>With Farouk!</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>Tell me, are you really superstitious?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No I'm not superstitious but I was struck by the humour of</p>
<p>   it all. There was Farouk, he did have white socks, but he wasn't....</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>But he was in the ABC!</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes, he was. But I didn't blame the ABC. The lady who got</p>
<p>   me my morning cup of tea as a walked down was very charming and</p>
<p>   she looks after Farouk everyday and it was a great shot and quite</p>
<p>   an amusing incident.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>Jack Holder, who I think has written to you, he is a campaigner</p>
<p>   to see to it that these sort of bills that Paul Keating passes onto</p>
<p>   the taxpayer as a former Prime Minister, that there's some</p>
<p>   sort of a feeling on the expenses of former Prime Ministers. Have</p>
<p>   you thought about that anymore...?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, we did make a change a couple of years ago. We put a limit</p>
<p>   on the number of plane trips that all ex-politicians could take</p>
<p>   in relation to their entitlement. There was previously an unlimited</p>
<p>   entitlement and we put a limit I think of 25 trips a year. I believe</p>
<p>   that former Prime Ministers are entitled to reasonable provision.</p>
<p>   They have, after all, whatever their political views are, they have</p>
<p>   served the country for a long period of time, but I obviously believe</p>
<p>   that all former Prime Ministers, and all former Ministers should</p>
<p>   exercise restraint and when they don't exercise restraint,</p>
<p>   well, people are entitled to have a go at them.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>Prime Minister thank you for your time. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
