<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9822</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP SPEECH AT THE OPENING OF THE NEW VICTORIAN COLLEGE OF THE ARTS BUILDINGS, MELBOURNE, 2 NOVEMBER 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/11/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009822.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
SPEECH AT THE OPENING OF THE NEW VICTORIAN COLLEGE OF THE<br />
ARTS BUILDINGS, MELBOURNE, 2 NOVEMBER 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
We hear a lot about economic development and about growth. But when<br />
I come to places like this we just had a little tour through the Art School and<br />
through the Television and Film School and I often think that when a country<br />
gets a chance to reflect upon itself, when one's development is to such a<br />
point that there is actually a premium and a value on reflecting upon yourself<br />
and thinking about the essence of who you are and what you have become<br />
and what you might be, well then I think you are starting to really make it.<br />
That is, it is not all about widgets and making things, or boring holes in the<br />
ground, or growing paddocks full of wheat we can do all those things.<br />
The world is out there making widgets these days, some make them better<br />
than others, some more innovative than others, some more competitive than<br />
others. But in a lot of the countries we compete with, the one thing they are not doing<br />
is they are not doing this and that is, I think, one of the things that marks us<br />
out as a society and why we should always have a premium on the arts which<br />
are about, of course, the mind and the soul and the heart and the things that<br />
are dear to us all. And I have often thought that anyone that has ever had an<br />
emotional connection with the arts could never forsake it, could never leave it<br />
off, never not support it. And we were just reminded, if ever so briefly by<br />
Natalie Christie's rendition of those two Strauss songs, what distilled genius<br />
always means you know the things that are up there with the sublime, that<br />
are just under the subliminal barrier, that haven't quite got through it, but are<br />
so close to doing it that it doesn't matter.<br />
So I thank you very much for the introduction and the songs. I have often<br />
thought that it has always been a great pleasure for people to write songs in<br />
German because it is such a great speaking language and I often think what<br />
I could have done in the House of Representatives with it. It is one of those<br />
things that lends itself to some poetry. Well with English you have got to<br />
really work hard at it. </p>
<p>But I am very pleased to be here today because we have got Jeffrey making<br />
a nuisance out of himself this morning in the press and in Federal politics you<br />
are always swatting blowflies. I mean you are always trying to blow them,<br />
shake them, off. But I am glad that Dick is here to remind us what an old<br />
fashioned Liberal he is. He has always had his heart in the right place and<br />
his head in the right place and I think we have, all of us, always appreciated<br />
him and the things which Louise said about his role here.<br />
I think that national governments should think about such things as the arts<br />
and culture. Not because it is the thing to do, it is the thing we can't be<br />
without and that in undertakings such as this it takes a long time to build<br />
an institution like the Victorian College of the Arts. It doesn't happen<br />
overnight, it happens with a long gestation, it happens with performance,<br />
it happens with commitment. It takes a long time for something like this to<br />
grow and, therefore, when a national government gets involved with it you<br />
know that if you can basically provide some of that financial and moral<br />
support to an institution which is already up and running, you can actually do<br />
a lot more with it.<br />
So it is more than a pleasure to be involved here, with the Victorian College<br />
of the Arts, and to be engaged with others today in opening these new and<br />
refurbished buildings housing the school of Film and Television, the School of<br />
Art and, of course, the Library and the Student Union.<br />
I mean these things are always about, in the end, assets of the Australian<br />
people and I am very pleased that they are in the State of Victoria, which has<br />
given so much to this country in terms of its art and its artists. And, of course,<br />
so many people famous Australians and famous artists have had their<br />
association and their connections with the VCA and its predecessor schools,<br />
such as Tom Roberts and Fred Williams and Clifton Pugh and<br />
Suzanne Johnston and Gillian Armstrong and Geoff Wright and<br />
Richard Lowenstein just to name a few. So there is a very deep heritage<br />
here and one that I think we should be very solid in supporting.<br />
Now we introduced this Creative Nation statement last year, it was<br />
$ 250 million expenditure on the arts and $ 100 million, I think, of it now has<br />
been spent and that is starting to percolate its way through the Australian arts<br />
community. And we are in the course of establishing the National Academy of Music here<br />
in Melbourne to provide a training centre of excellence in Australia for young<br />
musicians of outstanding talent and I think that is going to be a significant<br />
thing. We have established the Australian Foundation for Culture and Humanities<br />
here in Melbourne with a budget of over $ 6 million for three years with,<br />
as I said, that distinguished Victorian Dick Pratt as its Chair and I know you<br />
know that he has already given $ 3 million himself to it, which must be the<br />
biggest single private donation to the arts in our history, I think. </p>
<p>But it is not the money so much we appreciate. We appreciate that because<br />
it is about raising private finance. But what we appreciate most about that<br />
gesture is it is not simply a snip from a very large cheque book, but it is rather<br />
the importance and the meaning which it has from somebody who knows how<br />
important the arts are. I think that is appreciated as much as the money<br />
in fact more.<br />
We are funding the Australian Ballet School and through the<br />
Australia Council we are supporting the Australian Ballet which, of course, is<br />
headquartered here in Melbourne as well as the Melbourne Theatre<br />
Company, Circus Oz and the Victorian State Opera. And I am very proud that<br />
the Government has been able to contribute to this development here.<br />
Now, I might just say a couple of things about Jeffrey because I don't want to<br />
leave him out. He has got this ad this morning which, even for Jeffrey, is<br />
quite a nasty little ad. It says ' why is Mr Keating punishing the Victorian arts<br />
community?' And he has got the Victorian College of the Arts, School of Film<br />
and Television, recurrent spending $ 1.3 million; capital spending $ 35 million<br />
and equipment maintenance $ 35 million. That is the spending for 1994/ 95,<br />
but if you take it over the period of the development which is 1991/ 92 to<br />
1993/ 94 we have spent $ 16 million here and this more than favourably<br />
compares with the $ 10 million and not the $ 14 million in Sydney's Australian<br />
Film, Television and Radio School which, of course, was established during<br />
John Gorton's period, way back there.<br />
Jeffrey is playing a very seedy little game here and we don't expect this sort<br />
of thing from Victoria and I think he has been comparing notes with Richard<br />
Court or reading from the Bjelke Petersen style manual. I notice the other<br />
day when I went into Treasury Place that Jeffrey has got his new offices done<br />
up like the Reichstag down the back of the building. He has got flags decked<br />
off it all over the place. His Casino awash with money, I mean his and Ron<br />
and Lloyd's casino, but of course there is no money for the arts. Victoria<br />
spends less money on the arts per capita than any other State. He has got<br />
no money for the arts, no money for public transport, no money to run an<br />
ambulance service, no money for lavatories on railway stations but he keeps<br />
increasing the capacity of the Casino to gather up the earnings of Victorians<br />
and he keeps selling off everything that moves. Every public asset in place,<br />
but he has got no money for the basic amenities of the civilised society. I<br />
often think that these casinos are a tax on the poor and a massive blight on<br />
Australia and this one is a massive blight on Victoria. To cover his<br />
embarrassment about having no money for the arts and no money for this<br />
college because he gave it, basically I think some land and that was not<br />
much, he decides to spend a very large sum of government money to tell<br />
some untruths about the Commonwealth.<br />
The truth about Jeffrey is he is becoming a worried man and he should be.<br />
He runs one of the nastiest ouffits in the country which is nearly as nasty as<br />
Richard Court's. There are a lot of questions being asked about Melbourne<br />
and around Australia about this government and I don't think trying to sell the<br />
Commonwealth short on the arts is a way around the problem. </p>
<p>I rather like Jeffrey on occasions, but I don't like him today at all. We have<br />
spent $ 18 or $ 19 million here and $ 16 million of it has come from the<br />
Commonwealth. As I said $ 11 million for the new School of Film and<br />
Television and $ 5 million for the refurbishment of the Art School and as well<br />
as those other important cultural identities which have come here, but more<br />
importantly than all of this is that we are developing arts institutions of<br />
substance and of depth and this will stick to Australia like nothing else.<br />
Whenever we get a chance to put some public money into the arts, you've got<br />
now a lot of critics of public commitment to the arts and that is fair enough<br />
and we need some more private funding of the arts, but it still is important, I<br />
think, for a country to put a premium on what it is doing a premium on itself,<br />
on its identity, on its culture and to make that commitment and I think that<br />
every Premier and Prime Minister who have made commitments to the arts in<br />
the past have always understood this and have understood how important it<br />
is. It is why Australia can stamp itself out as a unique country which has got<br />
good values and good belief and why we are, as a civilised country, it is<br />
important for us to focus on these things.<br />
These days all the artistic disciplines of this institution are represented on this<br />
four hectare site in the heart of Melbourne's art precinct, even that is<br />
important. We are in the new building of the School of Film and Television<br />
which in another life was the famous Swinburne Film and Television School.<br />
I was interested to see some of the work just in a very brief visit I had before<br />
coming down here and to know as we know that in a country like ours the<br />
premium is going to be on the ideas we generate on the products we<br />
generate which have got ideas and intellectual content that we are not going<br />
to be in there competing with low labour cost countries on low value added<br />
products or products without value adding, but rather on things which have<br />
got these important artistic and intellectual components to them. I think what<br />
we are seeing is a measure of, you know just walking through the Art School,<br />
just seeing what people have done in-particular sectors whether it be in<br />
landscape, painting or just painting objects or people or situations. It is all a<br />
focus on trying to distil the essence of the country, of ourselves as a people.<br />
These are the things, I think, which will travel. We are an English speaking<br />
country and a large part of the worlds market in entertainment and art is<br />
generated from countries such as Australia and it is one of the things that we<br />
can do well and that is why the Government invested quite a lot of money in<br />
multi media. Moving again as we move from theatre to film, from film now to<br />
multi media and seeing that will generate a lot of creativity because I think the<br />
more we increase the milieu of creativity, however it spins off in whatever<br />
discipline, the greater the critical mass, of course, the better it is for the sort<br />
of things we produce and that we are famous for.<br />
I always think of those people who look at our productivity or GOP per capita<br />
or whatever measure it might be and we do alright in all these things, but<br />
there is never a premium in any of this sort of thing as I said earlier which a<br />
lot of countries do not do and really don't understand and haven't put the<br />
premium on it. </p>
<p>So, I regard this as being another very solid addition to the capital stock, but<br />
rather the creative stock of our institutions and our country and you have just<br />
got to get such a good feeling about Australia now. Here we are towards the<br />
end of the century, the place is growing strongly, we have licked the scourge<br />
of inflation, we are now on the edge of the fastest growing part of the world,<br />
we are much more confident about who we are now, about our identity, we<br />
are more proud about the country than we have ever been and our children<br />
have an education, by and large, across the board which was not true when<br />
most of us were at school and the sheer capacity to do new things, the<br />
excitement of it is profound. I have never in nearly 30 years of public life<br />
struck a more exciting period than this. These are the things that excitement<br />
is made of.<br />
I have just come away from quaffing down a red wine over on the Southbank,<br />
which is definitely not a Jeffrey creation, it is one of yours and it is just<br />
another measure of the way in which this great city is growing intellectually,<br />
culturally and every other way in the middle of one of the important<br />
international festivals of the world. That is so successful this year too.<br />
Wherever you go in Australia you find this all around the country now. This<br />
burgeoning of intellectual thought, of enjoyment, of pride in our culture and<br />
pushing out the envelope of the things that we might be able to do. This is<br />
what this institution is about and it is a very proud day, I think, for all of those<br />
who have been involved with it. Those who have supported it over the years,<br />
those who have helped it grow, those who have directed it, to know that the<br />
product of it the statistician may not be able to measure, but we all know in<br />
the end it will be a more important measure than almost any other thing the<br />
statistician is able to measure.<br />
Thank you for having me along, to be involved in the declaration, of the<br />
opening of these important buildings.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
