<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3864</transcript-id>
    <title>SECOND READING SPEECH BY HON EG WHITLAM QC MP, TASMAN BRIDGE RESTORATION BILL (NO 2) 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/08/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003864.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SECOND READING SPEECH BY<br />
HON. E. G. WHITLAM, M. lP.<br />
TASMAN BRIDGE RESTORATION BILL ( NO, 2) 1975<br />
HONOURABLE MEMBERS WILL RECALL THAT ON<br />
APRIL 1975 I INTRODUCED A BILL TO PROVIDE FOR THE<br />
RESTORATION OF THE TASMAN BRIDGE FOLLOWING ITS COLLAPSE<br />
INTO THE DERWENT RIVER AFTER THE S. S, " LAKE ILLAWARRA"<br />
HAD COLLIDED WITH IT, THE BILL WAS PASSED BY BOTH<br />
HousEs OF THE PARLIAMENT AND RECEIVED THE ROYAL ASSENT<br />
ON 19 MAY 1975. THE TASMAN BRIDGE RESTORATION ACT 1975<br />
PROVIDED FOR THE ESTABLISHMENT OF A JOINT TASMAN BRIDGE<br />
RESTORATION COMMISSION TO SUPERINTEND AND DIRECT THE<br />
COMBINED SALVAGE AND REBUILDING OPERATIONS.<br />
HONOURABLE MEMBERS WILL-ALSO RECALL THAT<br />
SHORTLY AFTER THE DISASTER THE AUSTRALIAN AND TASMANIAN<br />
CJVERNMENTS AGREED TO ESTABLISH A JOINT EXPERT ADVISORY<br />
COMMITTEE ON A SECOND DERWENT CROSSING. THIS COMMITTEE<br />
HAS SUGGESTED THAT CONCURRENTLY WITH REPAIRS TO THE TASMAN<br />
BRIDGE, PROVIS-GN COULD BE MADE FOR IT TO BE WIDENED TO<br />
PROVIDE A FIFTH TRAFFIC LANE,<br />
IT IS PROPOSED TO MAKE USE OF THE ROADWAY<br />
BOTH ON THE EASTERN AND WESTERN SIDE OF THE GAP FOR<br />
FABRICATION OF SOME ELEMENTS OF THE NEW SUPERSTRUCTURE AND<br />
FOR ERECTION WORK. IT IS THEREFORE NECESSARY FOR THE<br />
WIDENING AND RECONSTRUCTION WORK TO BE CLOSELY CO-ORDINATED<br />
AND IT IS CONSIDERED ESSENTIAL FOR BOTH PROJECTS TO BE* UNDER<br />
THE CONTROL OF THE ONE AUTHORITY IN ORDER TO AVOID DTFFICULTIES<br />
WHICH COULD ARISE IF TWO AUTHORITIES WERE TO BE OPERATING IN<br />
THE SAME AREA AT THE SAME TIME.<br />
ACCORDINGLY, I AGREED WITH THE PREMIER OF<br />
TASMANIA THAT THE WORK INVOLVED IN WIDENING THE BRIDGE SHOULD<br />
BE UNDERTAKEN BY THE TASMAN BRIDGE RESTORATION COMMISSION AND<br />
THAT THE GOVERNMENT OF AUSTRALIA WOULD MEET THE COST OF THIS<br />
WORK ESTIMATED TO BE $ 3 M. / 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
THE BILL NOW BEFORE THE HOUSE PROVIDES FOR<br />
APPROVAL OF A SUPPLEMENTARY AGREEMENT BETWEEN AUSTRALIA<br />
AND TASMANIA TO STRUCTURALLY MODIFY THE'TASMAN BRIDGE TO<br />
ACCOMMODATE FIVE LINES OF TRAFFIC CONCURRENTLY WITH THE<br />
RESTORATION OF THE BRIDGE TO FULL OPERATIONAL CONDITION,<br />
THE AGREEMENT EMPOWERS THE COMMISSION TO<br />
PERFORM ANY FUNCTIONS ADDITIONAL TO ITS PRESENT ROLE<br />
TO ENABLE IT TO COMPLETE ITS TASK, SUBJECT TO THE<br />
SAME CONDITIONS AND POWERS IT EXERCISES UNDER THE TASMAN<br />
BRIDGE RESTORATION ACT .1975. I SHOULD POINT OUT TO<br />
HONOURABLE 7iMBERS THAT FUNDS FOR THIS WORK ARE PROVIDED<br />
IN ApRoPR:. ATION L! LL ( No, 2) 1975/ 1976 UNDER DIVISION 964<br />
iHE WORKS PROPOSED WILL GREATLY ENHANCE THE<br />
CARRYING CAPACITY OF THE TASMAN BRIDGE WHEN RECONSTRUCTION<br />
COMPLETED AND WILL DO MUCH TO REDUCE TRAFFIC CONGESTION IN<br />
THE PERIOD BETWEEN RECONSTRUCTION OF THE TASMAN BRIDGE AND<br />
COMPL , TION OF CONSTRUCTION OF A SECOND CROSSING,<br />
I COMMEND THE BILL TO THE HOUSE, ITEM 03,<br />
IS </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
