<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7433</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER PARLIAMENTARY LUNCHRON FOR PRIME MINISTER LEE KUAN YEW CANBERRA - 16 NOVEMBER 1988</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/11/1988</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007433.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
( 0<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
PARLIAMENTARY LUNCHEON FOR PRIME MINISTER LEE KUAN YEW<br />
CANBERRA 16 NOVEMBER 1988<br />
Last year I had the honor of an invitation to visit<br />
Singapore-to deliver th ' e annual Singapore Lecture. It was<br />
an invitation I was very pleased to accept, and I chose as<br />
my theme " The Challenge of Change in the Asia/ Pacific<br />
Region". AS I told my audience on that occasion, there could be few<br />
more appropriate places than Singapore to discuss the<br />
challenge of change in our region. For in many ways<br />
Singapore is a model of the region's increasing importance<br />
in the global economy; it has proven itself a paragon of<br />
flexibility in the face of changing circumstances.<br />
Ladies and gentlement, today it is our very great pleasure<br />
to welcome the man whose leadership and vision has been<br />
crucial, over a long and distinguished career, in making<br />
Singapore one of the success stories of our times. There<br />
can be no question that our guest today, Prime Minister Lee<br />
Kuan Yew, is one of the great figures of our region, and of<br />
the Commonwealth, and it is indeed an honour and a pleasure<br />
to welcome him and his party to Canberra today.<br />
Prime Minister, this Bicentennial year has been a year of<br />
celebration for Australia, a year in which we have received<br />
many distinguished visitors from all corners of the world.<br />
But let me say that your visit looms large on our<br />
Bicentennial calendar, and we welcome you today as a special<br />
friend of Australia.<br />
It has been gratifying to note during the course of the year<br />
that the friendship between our two countries and peoples<br />
has been underlined repeatedly by Singapore's participation<br />
in Bicentennial events, including Expo 88 in Brisbane, the<br />
International Bicentennial Trade Fair in Melbourne and,<br />
most recently, at the Aerospace Exposition in Sydney.<br />
3472 </p>
<p>Prime Minister, during your time in government you have seen<br />
profound changes take place both in Singapore and in<br />
Australia : the development of Singaporean nationhood, and<br />
the emergence of the Singaporean economy as a powerful force<br />
in an increasingly dynamic region and, for our part, our<br />
transition from an inward-looking, protectionist, sometimes<br />
xenophobic presence perched on the edge of Asia to a nation<br />
more thoroughly and effectively enmeshed in the<br />
opportunities and challenges of regional development.<br />
Under your leadership, Singapore has always been at the<br />
forefront of this regional dynamism. Apart from brief<br />
downturns this decade, you have maintained consistently high<br />
growth rates over the last twenty-five years, and your per<br />
capita income has risen rapidly to become one of the highest<br />
in Asia.<br />
I quote such achievementslin order to comment on the means<br />
by which they have been achieved in particular, to note<br />
that your prosperity has been underpinned by an open<br />
approach to international trade, * with virtually no tariffs<br />
and a strong exposure to international market forces. That<br />
Singapore is a leading trading nation is a testament both to<br />
your own leadership and to the drive and commitment of your<br />
people. As you reminded us this morning, Singapore's total<br />
trade is three times its GDP.<br />
At a time when so much needs to be done in cutting back<br />
protectionism and discriminatory policies in the<br />
international economy, the Singapore experience bears<br />
witness to the advantages of a competitive export-oriented<br />
approach to economic growth.<br />
Of course our two economies have very different economic<br />
resources and specialisations. But in an interdependent<br />
world, open, diversified trade for both of us is the key to<br />
enhanced prosperity.<br />
our recognition in Australia of that fact has led us to<br />
undertake a broad-ranging program of structural reform. Our<br />
policies of deregulation and trade liberalisation are<br />
intended to place Australia's manufacturing and services<br />
sectors in a better position to join with Singapore and the<br />
other countries of the region in a more integrated<br />
comme rcial relationship.<br />
In other words, Australia increasin gly recognises that our<br />
future prospeqts depend on our continued ability to'enmesh<br />
ourselves successfully in this region. As my colleague,<br />
John Button, the Minister for Industry, Technology and<br />
Commerce said to you this morning in our talks, over the<br />
last five years Australia's attitude to trade with the.<br />
Asia-Pacific region has transformed from a perception of<br />
threats to a perception of opportunities. 3473 </p>
<p>In the early 1950' s, less than 20 per cent of our exports<br />
were to the countries on the western rim of the Pacific.<br />
Today 54 per cent of Australia's exports are destined to<br />
these countries, which in turn provide 41 per cent of our<br />
imports. Among ASEAN nations Singapore is our largest<br />
trading partner, with two-way trade exceeding two billion<br />
Australian dollars in 1987/ 88.<br />
In a time when we may be seeing the emergence of trading<br />
blocs which could have long-term effects on the multilateral<br />
trading system, Australia and Singapore have a common<br />
interest in strengthening multilateralism and contributing<br />
thereby to economic growth and stability for all countries.<br />
Mr Prime Minister, I have concentrated thus far on economic<br />
and trade issues. In so doing I do not wish to understate<br />
the many global and regional issues that are of shared<br />
concern to us both.<br />
As Australia's ASEAN dialogue partner, Singapore has a key<br />
role in our relations with ASEAN which is now entering its<br />
third decade as one of the most successful regional<br />
organisations in the world.,<br />
You and I have discussed many times the issues of a<br />
continuing United States' presence in the Western Pacific<br />
and I know that you are a strong supporter of that presence.<br />
I am also very pleased to note your steadfast support for<br />
the Five Power Defence Arrangements and for a continuing<br />
active Australian defence presence in the region.<br />
Singapore, as a signatory to the Nuclear Non-Proliferation<br />
Treaty, shares Australia's views about the vital importance<br />
of the Treaty and the need to make every effort to prevent<br />
the spread of nuclear weapons. And our officials are<br />
discussing. Australia's suggested exploration of a regional<br />
effort against the proliferation of chemical weapons<br />
There are many political problems that remain in the region.<br />
We need to face continuing problems in Indo-China, with a<br />
just and lasting resolution to the Cambodia question only<br />
now possibly beginning to emerge, and, with the question of<br />
the refugee outflow from Indo-China still to be resolved.<br />
There is uncertainty in Burma.<br />
There is also however, some cause for optimism, with a more<br />
favourable super-power relationship, an emerging Sino-Soviet<br />
dialogue, continued economic growth in the region and<br />
democratic reform underway in the Republic of Korea.<br />
Singapore's voice in the affairs of the region is always<br />
listened * to with respect.<br />
I was very pleased to note, for example, that in your visit<br />
to Fiji last week, you spoke on the value of racial<br />
tolerance and inter-ethnic harmony. This is an issue in<br />
which you have taken an unyielding and consistent stand in<br />
many international forums, not least in Commonwealth<br />
deliberations on South Africa.<br />
,14 </p>
<p>Singapore has long been regarded as a model of a successful<br />
multicultural society. That success is due in considerable<br />
measure to your own efforts. As in economic matters, your<br />
success in this regard provides a valuable example for the<br />
Asia-Pacific region.<br />
Mr Prime Minister,<br />
Singapore and Australia have traditionally maintained an<br />
excellent dialogue on all issues international, regional<br />
and bilateral no matter how difficult they may be.<br />
Healthy regional relations depend not only on the free flow<br />
of goods and services, but also on the free flow of ideas,<br />
both directly and through the media.<br />
You and I have met many tires in many parts of the world.<br />
we have discussed, dissected, argued over and agreed on many<br />
issues, but always as partners and always as friends.<br />
That partnership and friendship is one that I personally<br />
value. It is one that is valued by all Australians and it<br />
is one which I believe is of benefit to Singapore as well.<br />
It is against this background that Hazel and I are pleased<br />
to have you and Mrs Lee with us today. Your visit allows us<br />
to repay something of the friendship you have shown towards<br />
Australia over your many years as Prime Minister of<br />
Singapore. It seems only fitting that as our Bicentennial<br />
year draws to a close we should receive you as our special<br />
guest. 34 7<br />
Lan~ ocri~--_ II_ </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
