<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1891</transcript-id>
    <title>MESSAGE FROM THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. JOHN GORTON, FOR NATIONAL HEART WEEK  30 JUNE 1968</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/06/1968</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001891.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
MESSAGE FROM THE PRIME MINISTER, Li<br />
MR. JOHN GORTON, FOR NATIONAL HEART WEEK JUNE 1968<br />
A message from the Prime Minister commending " National<br />
Heart Week" will be telecast throughout Australia. tonight ( Sunday).<br />
The National Heart Foundation's special week of community<br />
education will begin tomorrow ( 1 July).<br />
Following is the text of Mr. Gorton's message:-<br />
" Australia ranks among the leading nations of the world in standards<br />
of living and in the rate of scientific, cultural and industrial growth.<br />
It also shares the distinction if so it can be called of one of the<br />
highest rates of heart disease in the world. This disease is still<br />
Australia's number one killer accounting for about forty per<br />
cent of all deaths, and for one-third of the deaths of men in middle<br />
age. The National Heart Foundation of Australia leads the Australian<br />
effort to meet this challenge. It is fighting on many fronts through<br />
its research programme, through its rehabilitation units and through<br />
its professional and community education activities.<br />
" National Heart Week" is a special effort to tell all Australians of<br />
how to reduce the toll. Through the press, on television and over<br />
the radio and by other means, the Foundation will be giving a message<br />
of hope and action during the coming week.<br />
The Heart Foundation will tell what activities and strains increase<br />
the risk of heart disease, and of relatively simple measures to<br />
reduce those risks. It will tell how to overcome the handicaps of<br />
heart disease should it strike. It is a message for all, Young and<br />
old, men and women, and I commend it to u" </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
