<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8055</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH ALAN JONES, RADIO 2UE, 9 JULY 1990</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/07/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008055.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH ALAN JONES, RADIO 2UE,<br />
9 JULY 1990<br />
E O E PROOF ONLY<br />
JONES: The Prime Minister, Mr Hawke, has broken many<br />
records during his Prime Ministership and since his<br />
accession to the leadership of the Labor Party. In March<br />
this year he became the only Labor leader in Australian<br />
political history to ever be elected to lead his Party<br />
for a fourth term in office. Today another milestone.<br />
At the end of today he will have served 2,678 days in<br />
office which is a hell of a lot. I think it's seven<br />
years and four months and so many days and that will make<br />
him equal to Malcolm Fraser as the country's longest<br />
serving Prime Minister. When he wakes tomorrow he will<br />
be on to the 2,679th day to make him the second longest<br />
serving Prime Minister to Sir Robert Menzies. He's<br />
denied he's aiming to break Menzies' record he'd have<br />
5,000 days to go, but he reckons he is going to lead the<br />
Party to the fifth Federal poll. Anything is possible.<br />
The Prime Minister is on the line. Prime Minister, good<br />
morning. PM: Morning, Alan.<br />
JONES: Congratulations from all our listeners and from<br />
everybody else. A very important and significant<br />
milestone. PM: Thank you very much indeed, Alan.<br />
JONES: A little bit of history created over the weekend<br />
as well, I guess, with Navratilova and West Germany, so<br />
you're part of all that.<br />
PM: Yes, it's been a big weekend for them hasn't it?<br />
JONES: Did you pick the winners?<br />
PM: No, but a mate of mine was brilliant in regard to<br />
the tennis. He took six to one Navratilova early in the<br />
business and then was able to lay off with Zina<br />
Garrison and so he was, he was looking pretty.<br />
JONES: I notice I just had an interview before you came<br />
on air about a man who's a psychiatrist at the Cumberland<br />
Hospital who tells us that we're outlaying more money </p>
<p>than ever before on gambling. I suppose you'd say I'm<br />
into that they've got a bit of yours haven't they?<br />
PM: Well, I find it very relaxing. It's one thing that<br />
keeps me sane, I think, being able to turn off on the<br />
horses every now and again.<br />
JONES: You're not after Menzies' record surely, that's-<br />
PM: No, no.<br />
JONES: Could I just ask you a couple of questions<br />
because we just wanted to congratulate you, but a couple<br />
of questions I suppose not necessarily involving<br />
themselves in the day to day detail. I was interested<br />
that in the opening of the Premiers Conference two weeks<br />
ago, you described Australia as the most over-governed<br />
country in the world which was a consistent theme that<br />
you used in the Boyer Lectures now many years ago.<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
JONES: Do you find there will be scope within your Prime<br />
Ministership to advocate the abolition of the States or<br />
is that something that you would like to get involved in<br />
once you cease being Prime Minister? Is there a case for<br />
that?<br />
PM: The case I put in the Boyer Lectures in 1979, but I<br />
know that in my political lifetime, Alan, I would think<br />
for some time beyond that it's not realistically on the<br />
agenda. I've simply said, and I think there wouldn't be<br />
a single Australian that would disagree with me, that if<br />
now, at the end of the 20th century, you were starting<br />
from scratch and writing a Constitution which was<br />
appropriate for the Australia that was approaching the<br />
21st century, you wouldn't have exactly the same sort of<br />
arrangements that were regarded as appropriate by the six<br />
colonies reluctantly agreeing to come together at the end<br />
of the 19th century.<br />
JONES: There is massive duplication isn't there?<br />
PM: Well, if you just think about it, look at the number<br />
of Houses of Parliament we've got with the six States<br />
that's 11 Houses of Parliament, because Queensland has<br />
only got one, there's 11 there, then you've got the<br />
Parliament in the Northern Territory and then you've got<br />
the Capital Territory here. So there's<br />
JONES: Thirteen.<br />
PM: Thirteen plus two Federal, there's fifteen. You've<br />
got fifteen Houses of Parliament for 17 million people.<br />
JONES: It's a joke isn't it? </p>
<p>PM: Well, it's on that basis that I say that Australia<br />
is the most over-governed country in the world.<br />
JONES: But is there nothing we can do about it?<br />
PM: Well, ultimately Australians have got it in their<br />
own hands as to what they do, but what, I want to be a<br />
practical deliverer of change if I can and what I've<br />
suggested and I'll be making a major speech next week<br />
about this, Alan is I think the obligation is upon the<br />
leadership of the Federal Government and of the State<br />
Governments to come together and to see how we make this<br />
existing system work better and I think that really<br />
involves two things, as I'll be spelling out in my<br />
speech. Firstly, it involves getting the evidence,<br />
seeing how we look at the way we often duplicate<br />
functions, overlap the things we do and see if we can't<br />
get a better way of dividing up functions between us.<br />
That is simply by agreement between the Commonwealth and<br />
the States and not forgetting local government as well<br />
and, secondly, to see if we can get together, that is the<br />
States and the Commonwealth Government and the major<br />
political parties, a better approach to the question of<br />
Constitutional change and if we do those two things, as<br />
I've said, in the last century, at that last decade, the<br />
1890s, they took all of that ten years then to prepare<br />
the Constitution which came into effect at the<br />
beginning of this century. I think we ought to use this<br />
last decade of the 1990s to see if successively we can't<br />
get Australia into better shape to cope with what's going<br />
to be an extremely competitive, tough, difficult 21st<br />
century. JONES: Well if I could just take that one final thing,<br />
better shape, because you've got to go and so have we,<br />
but monetary policy, without getting ourselves embroiled<br />
in ideological argument or, indeed, political argument.<br />
People like Button and Walsh, on the one hand, or public<br />
servant people like Charles and Phillips on the other,<br />
have been arguing that perhaps we ' ye gone too far on this<br />
high interest rate strategy. Now the job figures are<br />
looking bad, there are more and more people out of work,<br />
perhaps 10,000 small businesses a month going down the<br />
drain. Is there a sensitivity in Canberra to the<br />
dramatic problems that ordinary Australians are facing<br />
and how much longer can they endure this interest rate<br />
strategy without really discernible benefit?<br />
PM: Well, yes, there is sensitivity to it. We may be<br />
physically remote. But I can assure you there is a total<br />
sensitivity to the problems, but there's also the<br />
sensitivity particularly to what the alternative would be<br />
for this country if we did not lower the level of demand.<br />
Because if we didn't lower the level of demand which has<br />
all these implications that you are talking about,<br />
rightly, Alan, but if we didn't do that then, of course,<br />
the economy would collapse. We just can't go on as a<br />
country consuming more than we produce. </p>
<p>JONES: But doesn't the current account figure each month<br />
demonstrate that we're not being successful at reducing<br />
demand? We've still got this export/ import imbalance<br />
PM: Well the implication of that is, as you'll<br />
appreciate, the logical implication of that is that the<br />
tight monetary policy has to go on until we do.<br />
JONES: How much longer do you think people can endure<br />
that? PM: Well, the answer again is<br />
JONES: I mean, what I'm saying, I suppose I'm saying to<br />
you isn't there a more satisfactory mix?<br />
PM: There are only three arms of policy, without<br />
sounding like the jargon-ridden economist, there are only<br />
three arms of policy. That's a fiscal one, that's what<br />
you do with taxes and your budget, that's one. Secondly,<br />
there's wages policy and third, there is wages policy,<br />
fiscal policy and monetary policy.<br />
JONES: But couldn't we encourage people to save? This<br />
is what the big debate is about isn't it? I mean, you<br />
and Paul Keating<br />
PM: We've done more to encourage people to save than had<br />
ever been done before because with the arrangements with<br />
regard, made in regard to people providing for their own<br />
retirement through the superannuation provisions, there<br />
is now undergoing a massive increase in the allocation of<br />
funds by the Australian people to superannuation,<br />
massive. More than anything that's ever happened before.<br />
JONES: But what about something like no tax on the<br />
interest that's accrued from savings? That would be a<br />
tremendous incentive to save, to stop spending.<br />
PM: Yes, but everyone has looked at that, including the<br />
Opposition who ran around with it remember when,<br />
earlier last year, when the then leader, Andrew Peacock,<br />
went on his initial dry run for the election. He said<br />
this is the salvation and, of course, we then exposed all<br />
the weaknesses in that and they've looked at it since and<br />
they know, both sides of politics, we know and the<br />
Opposition know that the, without it's too detailed to<br />
go into it all<br />
JONES: Yes, sure.<br />
PM: The offsetting disadvantages to it are so great that<br />
neither side of politics is putting it forward as a<br />
realistic JONES: Alright, well the only other way you can get out<br />
of difficulty that we're in, really, I suppose, is to </p>
<p>work harder, to produce more. What if Bob Hawke went on<br />
television and said look, I've talked to everybody around<br />
the traps and I've talked to people at the races and I'm<br />
just saying to you tonight in a couple of minutes we've<br />
all got to get off our butts and work harder, everyone of<br />
us and outline how that should happen. I mean, the only<br />
way we can get out of the debt, isn't it, is to sell off<br />
the farm, borrow more or work harder? Now the first two<br />
options are hopeless. The third option seems to be to<br />
produce more. We're not actually doing as much as we<br />
might as a nation, are we?<br />
PM: We can always do more, that's right. But<br />
Australians shouldn't sell themselves short by easy<br />
propaganda. If you look at the statistics that cover the<br />
performance of Australians over this decade, there has<br />
been a significant productivity performance.<br />
Australians, by world standards generally, and in<br />
manufacturing industry now, in particular, are doing<br />
well. They can do better. They always can and I accept<br />
that, you know, people ought to work even harder than<br />
they do, but it's not a question of just working harder.<br />
It's basically a question of working smarter and that's<br />
why we've got to get the right technology in here, we've<br />
got to be prepared to upgrade the equipment and the<br />
capital with which we operate and that's why Australians<br />
let me make this point strongly and I'll do it until<br />
the day I die Australians must not be xenophobic. They<br />
must not say that we're good enough to do everything in<br />
this tough competitive world on our own resources. We<br />
have to be prepared to have the best of foreign capital<br />
and investment into this country, so that we can combine<br />
the talents of Australian workers with the best<br />
technology and equipment in the world. If we want to do<br />
the worst thing we possibly can, for our kids and their<br />
kids, Alan, what we'll do is succumb to the cheap and<br />
easy anti foreign approach that unfortunatly I see<br />
emerging in this country.<br />
JONES: Well, a bit of it from your own mates in<br />
Queensland lending a little bit of that. You might give<br />
Wayne Goss a bit of a kick in the head.<br />
PM: Mate, I have made my position clear to my friends in<br />
Queensland and elsewhere and I will take on anyone,<br />
whether they be in my Party or elsewhere, because I know<br />
that for the kids of today who are going to be the<br />
Australians of the next century, the absolute essential<br />
for them is that we get as much of the best into this<br />
country from overseas that we can, so that we are able to<br />
take on the rest of the world. If we don't we'll go down<br />
and down and down.<br />
JONES: Well just one thing on that. Look 2,678 days PM,<br />
it's a hell of a lot of time to be running the show, how<br />
did we get so crook? I mean that a hell </p>
<p>6<br />
PM: No, no, come on. Don't just be an Australian<br />
knocker JONES: No, I'm not a knocker<br />
PM: No, but you look at the statistics that were there<br />
in the papers the other day. Unfortunately you'd have to<br />
search with a microscope to see them played up, but there<br />
was a set of statistics the other day that showed if you<br />
take the measure of wellbeing, which is not simply, not<br />
simply gross domestic product and population, but taking<br />
into account the whole range of things which determine<br />
the quality of life and the standard of life, Australia<br />
was well up there in the top countries of the world<br />
JONES: But it's a Christopher Skase form of wellbeing<br />
isn't it? It's the big jets and the big expenses on<br />
someone elses dough and eventually you are found out and<br />
you've got absolutely nothing, got the backside out of<br />
your pants<br />
PM: On the contrary, it's not. If you look at the issue<br />
of education. That's not a Christopher Skase sort of<br />
indicia, but Australia now in this decade, has brought<br />
itself up from one where only a fraction, less than a<br />
third of our kids, were going on and staying on in<br />
school, to one now where we're up to about two thirds.<br />
Now that has been a dramatic transformation of this<br />
country. The Australia that goes last decade of the<br />
century is up with the higher level of education before<br />
JONES: Are we living beyond our means?<br />
PM: I said that earlier, I said that earlier, we cannot<br />
go on with a situation where like, in the previous year,<br />
we have an eight per cent increase in consumption, and a<br />
four per cent in production<br />
JONES: If what what you say, if what you just said<br />
before is right, and I'm sure people agree that we have<br />
got to be smarter, then the agency of that smartness, are<br />
our teachers now MP's got an increase from $ 55,000 by<br />
about 20 per cent, there is not a teacher in the country<br />
getting 55 grand. Do you reckon out there a smart<br />
teacher, a good teacher, is better for us in 1990 than a<br />
good MP? If so have you got any dough to help ameliorate<br />
the problem of teachers?<br />
PM: We were the ones, it was the Federal Government who<br />
took the lead with the States recently, in setting that<br />
national standard of 37,000 which was<br />
JONES: But you didn't come good with the money.<br />
PM: As far as we're concerned we will be supplementing<br />
the States as we indicated and promised. We'll be<br />
supplementing them. Education is not primarily a<br />
function under the Constitution of the Commonwealth </p>
<p>JONES: You'll help in teachers' salaries, with money?<br />
PM: We have been and we will continue to. But we took<br />
the view, Alan, that you've got in this area to be taking<br />
a long term view. If you're talking about investment in<br />
this country being important as it is, and we've got<br />
physical investment up to the highest proportion of our<br />
gross domestic product that it's ever been, remember<br />
that, and which will start to pay off more, but if you<br />
are talking about investment, education is the biggest<br />
investment of all. And that's why we have transformed it<br />
from one in three to two in three of our kids staying on,<br />
where we've enormously increased the number of places in<br />
universities and our higher forms of education because<br />
that's what's going to change this country ultimately and<br />
that's what's being done now to bring this country up to<br />
a level which can compare with the best in the world.<br />
JONES: OK. Alright Prime Minister, I only wanted to<br />
talk to you, we've gone on a little bit, but<br />
congratulations in anticipation of tomorrow. I've no<br />
doubt you'll be with us tomorrow as Australia's second<br />
longest serving Prime Minister. History is very hard to<br />
make and very hard to stand on its head. It's not<br />
without significant application of your own, a good deal<br />
of leadership, not a lot of luck and you've done it fine<br />
and done yourself proud and your family and everybody<br />
else. So we congratulate you for that. Look forward to<br />
talking to you again.<br />
PM: Alan, could I thank you for that and say that in all<br />
that time while we've had a few arguments, robust<br />
arguments and differences of opinion, I've always<br />
appreciated and it's made easier in a way, the discharge<br />
of this responsibility that people like yourself,<br />
particularly yourself, are prepared to talk about issues<br />
in a constructive way. I've appreciated it very much.<br />
JONES: You're most welcome Prime Minister. We'll talk<br />
again. PM: Thank you very much.<br />
ends. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
