<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4159</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER AT A BANQUET GIVEN BY JAPANESE PRIME MINISTER</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/06/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004159.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER AT A BANQUET GIVEN BY<br />
JAPANESE PRIME MINISTER. 17th June, 1976.<br />
" Mr. Prime Minister let me begin by saying that I and My<br />
Government place very great value on this visit to one of<br />
the truly significant countries in the world.<br />
Japan is, in many important respects, a unique country. in<br />
the last quarter century its economy has expanded at a rate<br />
unprecedented in human history. While becoming one of the<br />
two most technologically advanced countries in the world, Japan<br />
has, to a remarkable extent, preserved its distinct cultural<br />
heritage. Living in one of the world's most tense international situationsin<br />
North East Asia Japan has renounced nuclear weapons.<br />
It has renounced them, although it is as well equipped to<br />
produce them as anyone else, and though the other three great<br />
powers involved have them.<br />
Mr. Prime Minister Australian contacts with Japan stretch<br />
back over a century, from the time of the entry of modern Japan<br />
into the outside world. It has to be conceded that these<br />
contacts were of a limited and simple kind.<br />
In the 1860' s for exam . ple, two enterprising gentlemen arrived in<br />
Japan from Australia. After a successful entry into the publishing<br />
business, one of them became the recognised father of the<br />
vernacular press in Japan.<br />
The first Japanese arrivals in Australia came somewhat later,<br />
but by the end of the 19th century some thousands of Japanese<br />
were engaged in the pearl, b~ che-de-mer and sugar industries<br />
in Australia's north.<br />
Things have moved on a long way since those days, Mr. Prime<br />
Minister. The occasion which brings us together here tonightthe<br />
signature of a Treaty of Friendship and Co-operation between<br />
our two countries testifies to this.<br />
Mr. Prime Minister, to speak in terms of celebrating an end or of<br />
welcoming a beginning has a pleasantly dramatic ring.-Yet this<br />
treaty also represents neither an end nor a beginning, but a most<br />
significant step forward in a continuing relationship. It did not<br />
spring suddenly out of the ground, but emerged naturally from a<br />
relationship which has grown and prospered over the last two<br />
decades. It was brought into being by the mutual recognition ./ 2 </p>
<p>that the relationship has now reached the stage where certain<br />
things need to be formally recognised and other dimensions need<br />
to be added to that relationship.<br />
Today, Mr. Prime Minister, our two countries have become, by<br />
very different routes, two of the very few stable and prosperous<br />
democracies in the world.<br />
Our prosperity owes more than a little to the mutually beneficial<br />
trade which has developed between us. We know that you are<br />
concerned, as we-certainly are, to create the conditions of<br />
dependability and predictability which will allow this trade to<br />
develop and thrive further. These conditions have not always been<br />
present in the past, and it is one of the main purposes of the<br />
treaty to put this right and to keep it right. I believe we<br />
both clearly recognise that the mutual benefits accruing from<br />
the steady growth of this relationship,, on an equitable basis,<br />
far outweigh any short-term unilateral advantage.<br />
Mr. Prime Minister, both our societies are free societies,<br />
committed to democratic institutions and the rule of law. We<br />
both believe in the efficacy of private enterprise. We both<br />
live by trade. We both have a common concern to promote and<br />
maintain the stability which trade requires.<br />
For all these reasons, both our countries have found alliance<br />
with the United States, the world's major democratic power, to<br />
be natural and congenial. The Australian Government believes<br />
that a continuation of the American role in our region is a key<br />
element in the maintenance of peace and stability. We also believe<br />
that the best way of ensuring that continuation is for us to<br />
demonstrate that we ourselves take the security and stability<br />
of the region seriously. We are acting on, and we shall continue<br />
to act on, that belief.<br />
Mr. Prime Minister the dimension of our relationship which<br />
usually receives the greatest attention is, quite understandably,<br />
the economic one. We shall be discussing that at length during<br />
the next day or so, and I shall be speaking about it publicly.<br />
So I would like to spend the remainder of my time tonight looking<br />
at the cultural aspect of our relationship.<br />
I know that you will agree with me that if our relationship is<br />
to deepen and our co-operation to extend, we must take steps to<br />
understand each other better not merely at the level of<br />
government but at every level. There are real differences of<br />
cultural, and, unfortunately, real areas of mutual ignorance to<br />
be overcome.<br />
Yours is a very ancient culture. one of your great sources of<br />
strength has been your capacity to maintain its continuity and<br />
vitality while experiencing one of the most remarkable transitions<br />
in recorded history. Your success in moving from a feudal and<br />
self-absorbed society to a modern and outward-turning one with<br />
unprecedented pace and purpose was largely due to it.<br />
Our culture is also a vital and, I believe, a creative one. But<br />
it is much younger and has had to struggle to emerge from the<br />
shadow of a great European culture, to establish its own identity. e. / 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
It is not easy for two such societies to understand each other<br />
fully. But until we break down the national stereotypes which<br />
exist and replace them with genuine understanding, our<br />
relationship will not achieve its full potential. Our recognition<br />
of this truth is embodied in the Australia-Japan Agreement<br />
which was signed in 1974.<br />
It is also the premise underlying the establishment of the<br />
Australia-Japan Foundation by my Government this year.<br />
The Foundation's activities will focus on personal contact<br />
spanning the whole spectrum of society language, history,<br />
social and political ideas and institutions, the arts, economic<br />
and industrial organisations.<br />
It would be a mistake to expect quick, spectacular results<br />
from these ventures. But their long term benefits will, I am<br />
sure, be of very great importance.<br />
Greater understanding cannot guarantee agreement, but it can<br />
remove many unnecessary disagreements and make existing agreement<br />
more meaningful.<br />
These new initiatives by my Government will go hand in hand<br />
with the fast growing interest of Australia's younger generation<br />
in Japan and Japanese culture. Australia already has a<br />
higher percentage of students learning Japanese than other<br />
countries. I have long believed that there was great value to<br />
us both in encouraging the learning of the Japanese language in<br />
Australia. While I was Minister for Education I took an interest in the<br />
establishment of a committee to prepare proposals for the<br />
development of the teaching of Asian languages in Australian<br />
schools. I am pleased to say that there are now over 6,000<br />
students studying the Japanese language in Australian schools<br />
a six-fold increase since 1969.<br />
Mr. Prime Minister you have been generous in your time. We<br />
will be having ample discussions on these and other matters<br />
during my visit. Let me therefore conclude by again thanking<br />
you and your Government most warmly for your hospitality and<br />
again stressing the very great importance we attach to our<br />
friendship with you and the Japanese people".<br />
o000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
