<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1869</transcript-id>
    <title>CANBERRA REMARKS TO PRESS ON DEPARTURE FROM FAIRBAIRN AIRPORT  5 JUNE 1968</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/06/1968</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001869.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
VLS. T TO SOUTH-EAST ASIA 1968<br />
CANBERRA<br />
REMARKS TO PRESS ON DEPARTURE FROM<br />
FAIRBAIRN AIRPORT JUNE 1968U<br />
Q. Prime Minister, have you any comment on the<br />
shooting of Senator Robert Kennedy?<br />
PM: Well, it's awfully hard to think of what to say in<br />
circumstances where a man who has had his brother assassinated<br />
has been attacked in this brutal way. All I can say is that it<br />
makes me feel sick in the stomach that this can go on. It really<br />
is horrifying.<br />
Q. Mr Prime Minister, on this present trip, is there one<br />
thing you hope above all else you will be able to achieve?<br />
PM: No, I wouldn't say that. I think the main object of<br />
this trip is to meet the rulers of the countries to which I will be<br />
going, and to demonstrate that just as my predecessor had a<br />
continuing interest in Asia and the people who are ruling it, so do<br />
1, his successor, as representative of Australia, have the same<br />
interest. I think it will be helpful to know the individuals and I<br />
think it will be helpful to demonstrate that there has been not the<br />
slightest variation of our interest in the region.<br />
Q. Have you had any reaction so far of your forthcoming<br />
visit'? H-ave you heard of any reaction in South-East Asia?<br />
PMV: Do you mean for it or against it?<br />
Q. For it.<br />
PM: N' o I haven't heard any reaction, except very pleasant<br />
messages from the people I am going to visit, saying how glad<br />
they are and how much they are looking forward to the visit.<br />
Q. Sir, are you likely to indicate to Tunku Abdul Rahman<br />
that you might continue to keep Australian troops in Malaysia<br />
after 1971?<br />
PM: I wouldn't dream of commenting on what I am going to<br />
talk about to the various people I am going to talk to, particularly<br />
on matters of policy. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
