<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2547</transcript-id>
    <title>INTERVIEW - WITH LAURIE OAKES, MELBOURNE SUN NEWS-PICTORIAL, CANBERRA - 9 MARCH 1972</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/03/1972</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002547.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
INTERVIEW<br />
With Laurie Oakes, Melbourne Sun News-Pictorial, Canberra.<br />
9 March 1972<br />
Q The first thing I would like to ask is how do you sum up<br />
your first year as Prime Minister<br />
PM I've found it a very difficult year, mainly because so<br />
many events have occurred beyond the control of myself and<br />
the Government, and they've been of such an unpredictable<br />
kind that we have found great difficulty in achieving the<br />
objectives we've wanted to achieve., As an example, I felt<br />
in December that we had the problem of wage increases just<br />
about under control. And then, to my horror there was an<br />
increase in the State Electricity Commission wages in<br />
Victoria, followed by other changes Which could very easily<br />
spread to other parts of Victoria and the rest of Australia.<br />
If this happened, and we were unable to-isolate the increasesl<br />
it could be of great damage to the community. THis is but<br />
one example. I could give you many others. Now we are taking<br />
strong action to ensure that the flow-on is reduced to a<br />
minimum, and we ask all sections of the community to exercise<br />
moderation. In this we're giving the leadership.<br />
Nonetheless, I feel that this is a strong economy,,<br />
soundly based, and providing only we can reduce increases<br />
in wages and industrial lawlessness to manageable proportions,<br />
I think we can look forward to the future with a great deal<br />
of satisfaction. As to the way it's affected me personally, of course I<br />
worry about what is happening, and I happen to be in very<br />
good physical condition and I can take the knocks pretty<br />
well, absorb them easily, and get on with the job as best<br />
I can.<br />
Q Sir, You've always had a reputation for hard work;<br />
What sort of hours do you find-you've had to work over theyears<br />
PM I've always been a hard worker, that's true; never<br />
as hard as I work now because I have very little time either<br />
for myself or for that matter for my family. And all too<br />
, frequently I have to get in touch with my Wife when she's<br />
in Sydney with the kids, and ask her to come up as I'd<br />
rather she was with me than at home. I work even in the car<br />
when I' going back to The Lodge or I'm going : home in<br />
Sydney, and I get along with probably four and a half to<br />
five hours sleep a night.<br />
Q You've been the centre of controversy since you took<br />
over the job. Does that affect your family life or you<br />
personally<br />
PM It affects my family life to this extent that I don't<br />
see a great deal of my children other than at weekends. As<br />
I've said, unless I persuade my wife to come to Canberra, </p>
<p>PM can'It. I don't see her anywhere as much as I should. She<br />
thinks it's a big responsibility to be with the kids,<br />
particularly as they're now going to school.<br />
Q Does criticism worry you or Mrs McMahon<br />
PM I doesn't worry her so much she's the philosophical<br />
person, and she usually tries to calm me down by saying<br />
' Look, you know you've had a lot of experience, and you're<br />
doing your best. Keep going because, in time, the Australian<br />
people will recognise the honesty of purpose, and the<br />
effectiveness with which you are carrying out your policies.'<br />
I think too, that I'm able to take the knocks much better now<br />
than I was able to take them three or five years ago.<br />
Q Do you worry about personal popularity? Is that<br />
important Has it become so in the years<br />
PM When I first read the reviews, it does worry me, but<br />
I recognise that if I continue to worry about them, it will<br />
prevent me working in a most effective way. So I'WL able<br />
after a night's sleep to forget them, and then ask wh ' at can<br />
I do, or what is theproper course to follow in order to-:<br />
get the economy going again properly, particula. rly to reduce<br />
unemployment, and to handle the problems of industrial<br />
lawlessness.<br />
Q What do you regard as your mistakes. Is there anything<br />
you'd do differently if you had the year over again<br />
PM If I had the year over again, on the economic front,<br />
I would have taken action somewhat more quickly to increase<br />
the prospects of the growth of demand. Too, I would like<br />
the Parliamentary Council to have been able to give us<br />
legislation relating jfo conciliation and arbitration and<br />
arbitration in the Public Service field. We've been<br />
working on the changes for a long time, but regrettably,<br />
we are not able to get the legislation as quickly as we<br />
want it. The next most important point is, of course, that<br />
we want growth to go on because through growth we reduce<br />
unemployment, and I'm sure we'll see in the February<br />
figures to be reduced soon that there has been a quite<br />
substantial drop in registrant for employment, but above<br />
all, I want to be put in a position where so many of<br />
our social policies can be carried into effect. UNTIL<br />
we get growth, and we get control of inflation, it's<br />
difficult to do all we want to do0 Whether it happens to be<br />
in education, medical health and hospitals, better life,<br />
better quality of living, and the assistance we'd want to<br />
give the States so that they can improve the life of the<br />
urban dweller all these things we believe in and we live<br />
for, but regrettably we have to consider them against the<br />
background that unless we bring inflation and industrial<br />
lawlessness under control, then we can create gjreater<br />
difficulties in the future, and off-set many of the things<br />
we've already done0<br />
But I think if you look at our record of performance,<br />
and one day I'd like to see this published in the media,<br />
0 0/ 3 </p>
<p>PM con't I think you just admit that the record has been unbelievably<br />
good, against the background of the difficulties we've<br />
faced.<br />
Q What would you regard as the major achievement, on that<br />
subject Which one is most important to you<br />
PM I think the first major achievement was that we have<br />
created a better feeling between the Commonwealth and the<br />
States, and'the best example: I can give is at the last<br />
Premiers' Conference when they went home satisfied, and<br />
I believe it was a personal attribute to the Government.<br />
But secondly, you should look at a large range of policy<br />
issues that we have introduced, as for example, the<br />
the changes we've made on education, capital assistance<br />
to the State schools, per capita assistance to the independent<br />
schools. THe assistance we've given in order to assist<br />
nursing home accommodation, and the aboroigines all of<br />
these matters, and I've said T've documented them, and<br />
I'll give you a copy of the document that we've got where<br />
you can isolate these issues. What we've tried to do<br />
is get a realisation that we're one people, one group of<br />
Australians, all trying to pull together, in the interests<br />
of each and every one of us, rather than think that we have<br />
conflicting groups who are fighting one another, each one<br />
trying to get an advantage for itself, rather than to act<br />
in common interest. THis is the sort of ideal I've set<br />
myself and I only hope that we'll be able to do more to<br />
restore confidence, and if we can restore confidence and<br />
reduce the rate of wage increases, I KNOW that first we'll<br />
get a healthy economy, and based on a economy, we'll do<br />
so many of the thi ' ngs that the public want us to do,<br />
and which will then be easy to do.<br />
Q Overall then, was the year frustrating or satisfying<br />
obviously, there's a bit ofboth<br />
PM In many ways it's been satisfying, but in far too<br />
many ways it's been frustrating for the reasons I gave<br />
you when I answered the first question.<br />
May I again, if I may, emphasise the point, it might<br />
have been made sufficiently already, that we have an<br />
economy that is basically sound. If there was some increase<br />
in consumption expenditure, we would really be running along<br />
at a pace that I can regard as satisfactory, and we wouldn't<br />
have to worry about unemployment, and we'd be able to do<br />
much more in order to meet the needs of the people and<br />
the true aspirations of Australians.<br />
Q And so you obviously blame the economy largely for the<br />
bad problems or the low patch at the moment<br />
PM T~ e low patch at the moment; I believe, it is the lack<br />
on consumption demand and the impact it has had on employment<br />
which has become an emotional issue. Associa~ elhe<br />
with that we had other troubles such as, for example, rise<br />
in prices of BHP which swamped the praise we received for<br />
the Premiers' Conference, and, I must emphasise again, that<br />
industrial lawlessness does create doubts in the minds of<br />
people and indecision. So there is a combination of circumstances<br />
and I wouldn't like to just isolate one and say<br />
that the difficultiies can be related to that single item. </p>
<p>There are some ' critics who say that your personal<br />
performance has got something to do with it. Does this<br />
worry you are you tackling that<br />
Firstly I don't belive it because whenever a decision<br />
has to be made, I think I'll MAKE IT. And I've had a record<br />
of decision making and on too many occasions I've been accused<br />
not a question of being indecisive, but a question of being<br />
too decisive as for example when I handled the waterside<br />
workers as the Minister for Labour with all -the changes<br />
that were made when I was the Treasurer Somebody's got<br />
to tell ME where I'm indecisive. But I've got to make one<br />
comment that I do believe in teamwork, and I do believe<br />
in permitting the Ministers to administer effectively their<br />
own portfolio. But when the decision has to be made, I can<br />
assure you I will make it. To give you a current example,<br />
there has been criticism, and I believe understandable<br />
criticism about our failure to intervene in the postal workers'<br />
problem. I would have taken action, but I was advised by<br />
all of the technical advisers I could collect together<br />
there was no effective action we could take. So, we are<br />
amending, we are putting down a Bill to amend the Act today.<br />
THis has been our problem. And it's been with us since<br />
Federation. '* BUt if ever there was a case of decisiveness<br />
THIS IS ITo Similarly too, you could take the case if you<br />
like, of the amalgamation of the three metal unions. Here<br />
again is decisive action by us. People have to tell me in t<br />
pretty plain terms_. if they will, where-tY17s Government has<br />
acked decisiveness. If I could go on to another onae, dd<br />
I matae-tThSclear not so long ago, that on the changes in<br />
the exchange rate, it was said that we delayed, and we got<br />
unfavourable publicity. We did delay and we did get unfavourable<br />
publicity, but I was more concerned in making the right<br />
decision and after I had heard the arguments from all members<br />
of Cabinet, I came down strongly in favour of appreciating<br />
against the US$ by 6.32%. I stuck to tha. t decision until the<br />
end and that decision was accepted by CAbinet. AND it was the<br />
right decision 0 So I'd like people to tell me where I haven't<br />
made decisions, then I'd be able to argue with them and<br />
naturally enough if theywere right, of course I'd accept the<br />
fact that they're right, and I think that you can take it fr T<br />
my answers in the House, and my answers on television, that<br />
I never hesitate to say what I think is the truth even though<br />
I believe frequently it can lead to criticism of myself. But<br />
I believe the truth is of paramount importance.<br />
THe GAllup Poll shows the Government down to 40% of the<br />
vote. How do you plan to reverse this between now and the<br />
election We started in November to stimulate the economy by easing<br />
up on bank control to permit relative freedom on the part of<br />
the banks to be able to lend. o At the Pr'emiers' Conference<br />
we gave a big stimulus to the economy, to try to give confidence<br />
to the manufacturers by restoring the investment allowance and<br />
then subsequently giving them a renewal of the research and<br />
development allowance. In other words, trying to prove to<br />
them that they were not forgotten We recognise that manufacturers<br />
have to play a very big part not only in increasing opportunities<br />
for employment, but I believe, in creating conditions of<br />
confidence as well. We have started, and I make it more than<br />
9 9 9) </p>
<p>clear that if we found that more had to be done, we wouldn't<br />
hesitate to take further action, and this is the view of the<br />
Treasurer and my own view.<br />
Q What about the DLPO THey've been making increasingly<br />
hostile sta~ tements. Are you doing anything ' to get them back<br />
on side?<br />
PM The DLP has view which are largely the same as the<br />
Governments on many aspe-cts of policy , particularly defence,<br />
Our hostility to communism, the way in which our left-wing<br />
unions can create problems for industry and have caused more<br />
strikes than is tolerable. And my relationship with them until<br />
recently have been particularly good . There was one difference<br />
of opinion and that is the amalgamation of the three unions.<br />
Mr Lynch has explained the Government position which is shared<br />
by the great mass of my own Party, and I hope of course to be<br />
able to indicate to them where we stand on this one issue that<br />
really divides us because we are just as worried as they are<br />
about the power of the-left= wing unions and we are considering<br />
changes to the Act which will be announced by the -Minister for<br />
Labour and National Service which should show the DLP that<br />
our feelings about the problems are much the same as theirs<br />
are Where we differ is not in objectives, but in means of<br />
achieving those objectives.<br />
Q I notice somewhere this morning that you met Senator<br />
Gair last night0 Was that part of this arrangement?<br />
PM No, I had to see him over the Bill that is to be introduced<br />
today0 And we did discuss, but not in a profound nor in-depth<br />
way the difference of opinion between the two of us on the<br />
matter of amalgamation, and the way we looked at the future0<br />
Q If you'd known a year ago what you know now, would you<br />
still have wanted the job<br />
PM Yes I would0 I believe that everyone, particOdlarly<br />
a person in a position like my own, should be prepared to<br />
dedicate himself to the interests of the nation. I think I've<br />
done that, and even though it's difficult, frustrating, and<br />
deprives you of the ability to have a proper family life, I<br />
still would want to accept the position, and do the best I<br />
could.<br />
Q Prime Minister, what do you predict for the next year<br />
PM For the whole of this year<br />
Q For ihe next twelve months<br />
PM I think the biggest problem we face is one of cominunicatin,<br />
in trying to show the people what we have done, and to be able<br />
to answer the various kinds of criticism0 So I'm looking at<br />
ways and means of getting a better communication. I was able<br />
to go on television on Sunday night, and I believe that had a<br />
good impact over a very wide area0 I'~ m now considering the<br />
quesiton of radio interviews once a fortnight or once every </p>
<p>three weeks, I haverit made up my mind yet, so that I can go<br />
to the people with sort of armchair talks and to be able to<br />
explain in--depth policy, and to be able to answer publicly<br />
why we've taken certain action and answer any criticism that<br />
there might be. I think that if the people know the reasons<br />
they would be satisfied, and quickly our popularity will be'<br />
restored. And I want all my colleagues in the Ministry, in<br />
the Cabinet and in ' the Party room to join with me in this<br />
massive effort because I'm sure we can provide the right sort<br />
of Government I believe, that the Labor Party, dominated as<br />
it is by a Federal Executive and an ALC Conference, will be<br />
dangerous for us and deprive the Australian people<br />
of the freedoms that they treasure and that we in the Liberal/<br />
Country Party treasure too. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
