<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8521</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ KEATING MP PRESS CONFERENCE - BANGKOK, CANBERRA 20 MAY 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/05/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008521.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRAN~ SCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P Ji KEATING, MP<br />
PRESS CONFERENCE BANGKOK, CANBERRA, 20 KAY 1992<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
PM: I have just got a few minutes so I want just to give<br />
you a comment on the situation in Thailand. I would<br />
like to begin by saying that I take this opportunity<br />
on behalf of all Australians to express our horror<br />
at the actions which have lead to this needless loss<br />
of life In Bangkok. We are appalled at the wide<br />
spread use of excessive force by the Thai military,<br />
and our Embassy in Thailand is monitoring the<br />
situation. And I urge the Thai Government to ensure<br />
that the troops act with maximum restraint to avoid<br />
further bloodshed. Could I also say that as a<br />
result of the actions that have been taken to date<br />
by the Thai military, the Government is, in response<br />
to that action, withdrawing 20 Australian soldiers<br />
from the Special Air services Regiment and 11 C130<br />
Aircrew which were deployed to Thailand on May 5 for<br />
training with the Royal Thai Special Warfare<br />
Command. We think it is incongruous that in these<br />
circumstances Australian military personnel be<br />
training with Thai personnel while the Thai military<br />
are taking this action against their citizens. So<br />
we are withdrawing that Special Air Services<br />
Regiment and the air crew that accompany them.<br />
Could I also say that the Acting Minister for<br />
Foreign Affairs and Trade, John Kerin, will be<br />
closely monitoring developments and we will be<br />
looking at our relations with Thailand in the light<br />
of how the situation unfolds.<br />
Does that mean, Prime Minister, that you are<br />
prepared to downgrade our diplomatic relationship<br />
with them if necessary? </p>
<p>PM: Well I think we will just put the Whole relationship<br />
under review. I think one can see the tragic<br />
contrast between the developments in Thailand over<br />
the last period, the recent years of prosperity and<br />
stability, with what's happening now. We have<br />
sought, through both aid and advice, to make<br />
Thailand a better place for the Thai people to live<br />
and we take that responsibility seriously. But<br />
because of this violence we will examine the whole<br />
relationship.<br />
J: Prime Minister are you considering suspending<br />
economic aid as well as military?<br />
PM: Not at this stage. I have made clear in the past<br />
that there can be a linkage to State-sponsored<br />
violence, but the aid is, after all, humanitarian<br />
aid and economic aid. It is aid for the people of<br />
Thailand, it is not for the Generals. And again,<br />
the aid tap can't be turned just on and off over<br />
night. It's projects, and it's goods and services,<br />
and so in our examination of aspects of the<br />
relationship we will examine the aid program as<br />
well.<br />
J: Has any thought been given to bringing the<br />
Ambassador back for consultations?<br />
PM: Well I think it is important that there is somebody<br />
there who we can speak to and who is also in a<br />
position to address the Government, and so I think<br />
the Ambassador is in an important place at the<br />
moment.<br />
J: There have been some allegations by commentators in<br />
Thailand that the violence has been premeditated<br />
rather then just a response of a volatile situation.<br />
What's your reading of the situation?<br />
PM: I don't think I can give you a reading on that.<br />
J: How do you respond to the Oppositions claim that the<br />
Government's response has been slow?<br />
PM: Look, Dr Hewson jumps on everything these days. Any<br />
event and he has a silly press statement out five<br />
minutes later dictated over 8 portable phone<br />
somewhere. I mean the fact is, Dr Blewett issued a<br />
statement yesterday, it was not clear until late<br />
yesterday what the general situation was. Our<br />
Ambassador was not in a position to give us an<br />
indication, and I think our response will be both<br />
timely and firm.<br />
J: Mr Keating what sort of political pressure can we<br />
put on to Bangkok to stop </p>
<p>Pm: well I think international opinion, including the<br />
opinion of neighbours, is going to matter io all<br />
countries. And the fact that I am saying that we<br />
are appalled by the violence, that we express our<br />
horror at the action of seeing the military of this<br />
country shooting down citizens is about as strong a<br />
position as we could say or take.<br />
J: Does it concern you that very few, if any, of<br />
Thailand's ASEAN neighbours have publicly criticised<br />
the Thai military over its actions? Is it an<br />
indication to you of just how hard it is going to be<br />
to enmesh Australia in the region?<br />
PM: Well I think, I have said this to the House and I<br />
will say it again, we will be giving our views about<br />
violation if we see a violation of human rights no<br />
matter where it occurs or how it occurs. One of the<br />
things I have been saying in recent times that our<br />
traditions, and our respect for these things will<br />
not be diminished by any wish we may have to become<br />
more closely enmeshed with the region. But again,<br />
you can't tar the region either with these sorts of<br />
problems.<br />
J: Are these the only Australian troops in Thailand?<br />
PM: yes.<br />
J: The Thai Officers in Australia at the moment could<br />
that be a second level of response, to send them<br />
home?<br />
PM: well there is a clear incongruity about Australian<br />
Military Officers in a country where these<br />
violations are occurring and in training with the<br />
service which is actually perpetrating. This is not<br />
the case here, and I think that widely fits into a<br />
general thought, or review of the relationship in<br />
the broad.<br />
J: What was your personal reaction when you saw the<br />
footage on TV?<br />
PM: Well I couldn't be anything but appalled by it. You<br />
really hardly believe it is happening.<br />
J: Will you support an international arms embargo<br />
against Thailand?<br />
PM: Look, this has happened 24 hours ago, so before you<br />
start getting declaratory about all these things, we<br />
will have the whole relationship looked at.<br />
J: Do you accept the arrangement which gave the Left<br />
the next vacancy in your ministry? </p>
<p>I -t.<br />
4<br />
PM: Look, I didn't come here for a general press<br />
conference, my friend, I see enough of you, not as<br />
much 88 I am sure you would like me to Bee Of YOU,<br />
but I have got an ERC Meeting that should have taken<br />
place 35 minutes ago, so I better go.<br />
J: Prime Minister will you be sending your views direct<br />
to the Thai Prime Minister?<br />
PM: Well our view has been communicated already by our<br />
Ambassador and any amplification of that view will<br />
be sent directly, exactly.<br />
J: ! If the killing stops will the military exercises<br />
resume?<br />
PM: They are not going to be resuming because they have<br />
been brought back to Australia. And before any<br />
other military exercises obviously will take place,<br />
the whole relationship will have to be changed,<br />
clarified, and settled.<br />
J: I8 the information you're getting suggesting that<br />
the military may be prepared to compromise, or is<br />
your information suggesting that the crack-down will<br />
continue? I<br />
PM: Well it is not clear as to whether or not more<br />
violence will be perpetrated in the course of this<br />
day. I can't give you an answer. But nor can I give<br />
you the view that it won't be. It was sporadic, and<br />
has ceased. That unfortunately may not be true.<br />
ENDS </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
