<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2153</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS:  P.M.NO 91/1969   A NEW YEAR MESSAGE TO THE NATION FROM THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. JOHN GORTON</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>31/12/1969</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002153.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS: P. M. NO. 91,' 1969<br />
A NEW* YEAR MESSAGE TO THE NATION<br />
From the Prime Mlinister, Mr. John Gorton<br />
Today we begin a new decade as well as a year of<br />
special significance to all Australians.<br />
For we will, in this year, celebrate the bicentenary<br />
of Captain Cook's discovery of a completely undeveloped land and<br />
we will begin a decade of development unparalleled in Australia's<br />
past history. I believe that this decade will see us grow in strength<br />
and wealth as our industry expands and our population grows.<br />
I believe that this decade will see a final and successful<br />
attack on the poverty in our midst.<br />
I believe that our increasing wealth will make possible<br />
greater opportunities for all and will open the way to the individual<br />
to develop his talents to the utmost and to find self expression and<br />
satisfaction in his chosen sphere of work.<br />
The prospects are glittering. We will need to increase<br />
our capacity to defend what we build; we will need to help other<br />
countries; above all we will need to work together to attain what<br />
time and circumstances now make pos sible.<br />
And if we do this but only if we do this 1970 will be<br />
a year of achievement and the 1970' s a memorable decade.<br />
I wish all Australians every happiness and success in<br />
the New Year, and throughout the new decade.<br />
CANBERRA 31 December 1969 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
