<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2799</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S MESSAGE TO MRS GANDHI ON INDIA&#039;S NATIONAL DAY</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/01/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002799.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
NQ DATE<br />
M/ 27 26 January 1973<br />
PRIME MINISTER'S MEDSSAGE TO MRS GANDHI<br />
ON INDL' ' S NATIONAL DI-Y<br />
The following is the text of a special mFessage from<br />
the Prime Minister, Mr E. G. Whitlam, to the Prime Minister<br />
of India, Mrs Indira Gandhi, on the occasion of India's<br />
commemoration of Republic Day, 26 January:<br />
" On behalf of the Australian Government and people,<br />
I would like to convey my warmest greetings to you and the<br />
people of India on the occasion of India's commemoration of<br />
Republic Day. We in Australia are aware of your continuing efforts<br />
0 to improve the welfare and prosperity of your people, and of<br />
the many problems which you face in this great task.<br />
Australia has been involved in assisting India in<br />
its long-range agricultural development programmes, amongst<br />
other things through the provision of stud cattle and the<br />
establishment of a sheep breeding project at Hissar.<br />
At the request of your Government, we have now<br />
decided to expand this programme by establishing a dairy<br />
cattle breeding farm adjacent to the sheep project at<br />
F-issar, a subsidiary farm in Assam and a semen p.' oduction<br />
c ntre. The expansion of these activities is an earnest<br />
of our desire to contribute to your endeavours. / 2 </p>
<p>On this national day, which we share, I should like<br />
to emphasise the importance that I place on Australia's close<br />
relationship with India, and my determination to expand and<br />
consolidate the ties between our two peoples.<br />
I believe that our Governments have many ideals and<br />
interests in common, dedicated as they are to peace and 0<br />
progress in the region of South and South-East Asia.<br />
Finally, on thV Republic Day, may I wish you and the<br />
Indian people continued progress and prosperity in the coming<br />
year." 0 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
