<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4963</transcript-id>
    <title>SUMMARY OF ABC&#039;S &#039;NEWSVOICE&#039;</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/02/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004963_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
ni-c<br />
PRIWE M4INISTER 22 FEBRUARY 1979<br />
from the Press Office<br />
Summary of ABC õ " Newsvoice".<br />
A Vietnamese deputy foreign minister has told newsmen in<br />
Hanoi that the Chinese are gearing up for a bigger attack.<br />
Vietnam is reported to have acknowledged the loss of Lao Cai, a<br />
provincial capital which fell to the Chinese on Tuesday.<br />
Since capturing Lao Cai, the Chinese have pushed another<br />
8 kilometers down the Red River towards Hanoi, 28 kilometers<br />
inside Vietnam.<br />
On the eastern fronts, heavy Chinese attacks threaten the<br />
provincial capital Gao Bong and Lang Son. Vietnam is<br />
said to have deployed one regiment to the Northeastern front.<br />
China's invasion of Vietnam has drawn sharp criticism from<br />
the U. S. Senate Foreign Relations Committee.<br />
In major review of affairs at home and abroad, the Prime<br />
Minister told Parliament today of his concern about events<br />
in Vietnam and other world trouble spots. Spoke optimistically<br />
about Australia's economic prospects in the year ahead.<br />
Report from Duncan Fairweather on Prime Minister's speech.<br />
Mr. Fraser interviewed.<br />
Leader of the Opposition, Mr. Hayden, shared Mr. Fraser's<br />
optimism about Australia's economic prospects, but not<br />
the policies the Government was employing to realise them.<br />
Mr. Hayden interviewed: " There is plenty of room for<br />
optimism about this country. It is a great country, great<br />
people, enormous resources potential and we have risen to<br />
great heights through the diligence and intelligence and<br />
creativity of our people, but they need the right sorts of<br />
policies and what I've been saying is that we need a change<br />
of policy to make sure it is an optimistic year. As I<br />
pointed out in the Parliament today, there are a very long<br />
list of similar statements from the Prime Minister, right<br />
from 1975 on. They have yet to be fulfilled. The latest<br />
statements on what the Government is doing with interest<br />
rates and the supply of money from the banks and so on<br />
indicates that things are going to be a bit tighter".<br />
Figures released today showing food prices soared in<br />
January. Food group index went up by average of 2 percent<br />
in Australia's seven capital cities, the highest monthly<br />
increase for 18 months.<br />
The largest manufacturing sector in Australia, the Metal<br />
Trades Industry, today released a survey indicating increased<br />
business confidence. Survey shows employment in the<br />
metal industry is stabilising and predicts moderate to<br />
substantial improvements in general business and employment<br />
for the remainder of the year. National Director of<br />
the Metal Trades Industry Association, Mr. Ken Fry, interviewed.<br />
Federal Opposition has accused the Government of misleading<br />
country people about the benefits of a domestic satellite.<br />
Senator Susan Ryan said today the Government was promising<br />
more than it could deliver. Senator Ryan interviewed. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
New York, detectives are blaming gang fighting over the<br />
control of illegal drug sales for murders of seven people.<br />
Is biggest murder incident in New York's history.<br />
000---1 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
