<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>19134</transcript-id>
    <title>More than 1000 jobs on offer at Liverpool Jobs Expo</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/03/2013</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Sydney</p>
<p>More than 1000 jobs and training opportunities are up for grabs today at the Australian Government Jobs and Skills Expo at the Whitlam Leisure Centre in Liverpool.</p>
<p>Today's Liverpool Expo puts local job seekers in touch with employers, training organisations and industry representatives.</p>
<p>This is a great chance for local job seekers and businesses from throughout south -west Sydney to come together and explore local job opportunities.</p>
<p>Amongst the many jobs on offer are opportunities from apprenticeships in a number of different trades to jobs in hospitality and retail.</p>
<p>From truck driving and construction to childcare and hospitality – whoever you are, there are great job and training opportunities at the Jobs and Skills Expo.</p>
<p>The Gillard Government understands that breaking into the workforce can be difficult. This Expo is a practical way of making the search for a job a bit easier.</p>
<p>With more than 80 exhibitors at the Liverpool Jobs and Skills Expo, job seekers are encouraged to come armed with their resumes to take advantage of this unique opportunity to do months' worth of job searching in a single day.</p>
<p>The Gillard Government's Jobs and Skills Expos are achieving real results for job seekers across the country – this is the 71st Jobs and Skills Expos we have delivered and we know that they work because we've now seen more than 25,000 Australians find employment at an Expo, and many thousands more sign up for training opportunities.</p>
<p>To place a job vacancy or to find out more about the Australian Government Jobs and Skills Expos call 13 11 58 or go to <a href="http://www.humanservices.gov.au/expos">www.humanservices.gov.au/expos</a></p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
