<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>583</transcript-id>
    <title>CRICKETERS CLUB OF NSW - SHEFFIELD TEAM DINNER - HELD AT SYDNEY ON 18TH AUGUST 1962 - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R G MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/08/1962</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000583.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CRICETERS CLUB OF N. SW, SHEFFIELD TEAM DINNER?<br />
BELD AT SYDNEY ON 18TH AUGUST, 196.2<br />
Speech by the PilMe Minister, the Rt. Hon. R. G. Menzig-s<br />
Sir, I think it is quite ridiculous for me to<br />
interrupt a programme so full of gaiety, I am entirely<br />
willing to resign instantly in favour of Jim Burke. ( Laughter)<br />
And not politically. ( Laughter) But I've been enjoying this.<br />
As a matter of fact, when he said that the lightmeter<br />
showed zero minus 05 or whatever it was, it reminded me<br />
at once of a time when I was in England and, oddly enough,<br />
went to a Test Match ( Laughter). I arrived in London. I told<br />
my wife and my daughter who were with me that they could enjoy<br />
themselves in their own fashion in London, but I was off to<br />
Trent Bridge the following day and I stayed en route at<br />
Coventry and the next morning I was driven up to Trent Bridge,<br />
This was the time when Lindsay Hassett made a century, but<br />
that was before I arrived and Alec Bedser was having a wonderful<br />
time. And all the way from Coventry to Nottingham, the<br />
drizzle came down; the little bits of fog hung on the bushes<br />
on the side of the road, When I arrived at Trent Bridge at<br />
about 11 it was so dark you could hardly see the other side<br />
of the street. I was received very courteously by the<br />
President of the Club who was the Duke of Portland whom I have<br />
known in his earlier manifestation before he became the Duke<br />
and those of you who remember the present Duke of Portland will<br />
know that he is a stage Duke you know, he says exactly what<br />
you would expect a stage Duke to say ( Laughter).<br />
He couldn't have been more civil. He took me upstairs<br />
into a room and there was a little balcony outside it looking<br />
across the ground and he said to me, knowing that I was an<br />
Australian, " Would you like a drink, what?" and I said, " 1Wells<br />
not normally at this time of the morning, but what did you<br />
say Sir?" and he said, " Would you like a drink?" " Well," i I<br />
said " on the whole, I think I will." ( Laughter) He accommodated<br />
me wih a drink and then I went and peered over the little<br />
balcony. You could tell that there were people there on the<br />
other side, but there was no distinction of faces or anything<br />
of that kind. There were two melancholy-looking piles of<br />
sawdust; it was as dark as a dog's mouth you see. And at a<br />
quarter past eleven, refreshed suitably I said, " You krow<br />
Duke, I seem to be unlucky because I did hope to see tht; play<br />
today and on Monday and I have no hope. He said, " What do<br />
you mean, what?" ( Laughter) " Well " 1 1 said, " when do you<br />
expect play to begin?" He said " ialf past eleven, what",<br />
you see, And I said to him, " It~ s twenty past eleven and yo0u<br />
really can't see the other side of the ground." I said, " In 1<br />
Australia, there wold~ be any play under these conditions,"<br />
and he looked at me with ducal contempt ( Laughter) and said,<br />
" My dear fellow, if we didntt play in this light at Trent<br />
Bridge, we'd never play at all." ( Laughter) And sure enough,<br />
at 11, 0 out came the English fieldsmen and disappeared into<br />
the murk ( laughter) and out came a procession of Australian<br />
batsmen and they disappeared into the murk ( Laughter). They<br />
reappeared pretty quickly. I always remember poor Neil Harvey,<br />
that lovely batsman, just doing one of those tucking-it-roundthe-<br />
corner shots, and when he peered through the murk, he found<br />
he had been caught ( Laughter) so he was off and by the end of<br />
the day the match was a mess. Soafter all this zero minus, this<br />
is a story entirely for Australian consumption. so0o@ s00. </p>
<p>2<br />
I was also very amused P11 come to the real. topic<br />
in a moment because I made a note of it here, Oh yes<br />
somebod. y was talking about great feats of batzam-nship and Ca<br />
reference was made by you, Sir, to Dainty Ironmonger, A<br />
fine bowler, but a batsman who, in my opinion, and I am<br />
speaking as a Victorian now, has always been gravely underrated.<br />
( Laughter) Because in the great year when Larwood<br />
was wreaking death and destruction and Dainty Ironmonger who<br />
was batting at the Richmond end came into bat my impression<br />
was that he shut his eyes and dealt a stout blow at the first<br />
ball that came along and it bent the pickets at cover point,<br />
And this was a marvellous stroke, It was greatly received by<br />
the populace and, many years afterwards, I am sitting up with<br />
the great in the Committee box at the Melbourne ground, than<br />
which there is nothing more lordly ( Laughter) and I looked down<br />
and I savw Dainty Ironmonger I was going to say talking to<br />
Jack Ellis, but you won't misunderstand me Jack was talking<br />
to him ( Laughter) and I thought thiO ought to be fun, so I<br />
went over and butted in, and this interrupted Jack ( Laughter)<br />
who because he was a friend of rmine and for other reasons,<br />
fell silent for a minute, This let me get in and I said,<br />
" Dainty, I have always wanted to ask you, when you struck that<br />
magnificent cover-drive off Larwxood at the M. C. C. that day<br />
you remember it?" and he said, " Too right" ( Laughter) I said,<br />
" Now I want to ask you, as man to man, when you hit the ball,<br />
were your eyes shut?" and he looked at me and said, " Too<br />
right" ( Laughter), Then of course, Jack resumed the conversation<br />
( Laugnter), A very interesting piece of cricket hist" ory<br />
I think. Anyhow, my job tonight is to propose the Toast of the<br />
Team and this is very difficult for a decent, devout, Victorian<br />
( Laughter) to have to come along here. It becomes so painfully<br />
repetitive, to congratulate New South Wales on winning the<br />
Sheffield Shield, once more, once more, once more, And I<br />
want to say that, although I am a great admirer of the team, I<br />
don't think you need excite yourselves unduly. There's one<br />
simple reason why you win the Shield, not entirely fair, but<br />
it's quite simple,, You chaps win the Shield because you've<br />
got practically the entire Australian Eleven playing ( Laughter).<br />
Well, of course down in Victoria, we don't care for this.<br />
( Laughter) No that we would replace you in the Australian<br />
Eleven not for a moment, but we do occasionally pray for<br />
something to happen that will enable an Australian Eleven to<br />
have all its stars, or most of them, from Victoria and t'ien<br />
the Victorian Cricket Association will snap out of it and<br />
give a dinner for the Sheffield Shield team ( Laughter) to<br />
congratulate them on victory. And if I am still alive, which<br />
seems improbable ( Laughter), I'll be there.<br />
You know, it's a very good thing for Australian cricket<br />
that there is such a place as New South Wales. That's quite<br />
true, Politically, I wouldn't generalise on that matter,,<br />
There have been times in my political life when I though<br />
I could live without Sydney or die with it, ( Laughter) Thut<br />
in cricket, you have in this State made the most tremendous<br />
contribution to what I will alwrays maintain is the greatest<br />
game in the world, ( Hear, hear) ( Applause). There are<br />
certain mechanical reasons for it, perhaps. Would you mind<br />
if I suggested one or two of them to you?<br />
I have always thought as the grand final of the<br />
football in Melbourne is conducted on a mud-patch, which not<br />
uncommonly happens, well on in September, and the following<br />
day they bring out the harrows and they run the harrows over<br />
it and they do a little top-dressing, they roll it out and<br />
o0 * 0 .0. a0. a */ 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
pray for rain and if it doesnit r'ain they water the pitch<br />
y7ou know. And after a whi: le, people are playing cricket on<br />
it0 But in Victoria it's quite common when the first Sheffield<br />
Shield match comes along for interstate batsmen to be batting<br />
having had perhaps one innings in a Club match, whereas over<br />
here by the end of September, the cricket bats are out I<br />
see the boys on the spare allotments, I see t-hem, in Moore Park<br />
and therefore you are always able to beat the season as we see<br />
the season in the South. Now I am not complaining about that,<br />
This is very good because it means from the point of vie, i of<br />
Australia you have a certain number of distinguished cricketers<br />
who are in form and in practice. Now that's a very good thing,~<br />
The second thing that I have always complained a<br />
little about is when people have said to me, " You know, the<br />
Victorian batsmen they are very good, they are very good.<br />
You know, useful fellows ' to have in a side but a bit stodgy.<br />
I have even heard Jim Buirke say that ( Laughter) " tA bit stodgy,<br />
you know, a bit defensive" and I have frequently thought to<br />
myself, having looked at a number of crickiet grounds here, that<br />
on the whole yours tend to be a little smaller than ours and<br />
that is partly because of our particular game of football as<br />
compared with rugby, And I think that psychologically, this<br />
has something to do with it because if he boundary doesnt<br />
look quite so far away a fellow will have a go at it, but<br />
in the vast arenas of 4ctoria, he looks through the murk of<br />
the early Victorian summer and he says, " Well, if I can just<br />
push that past point, we might get a couple." Isn't that right,<br />
Arthur? But of course these creatures they just say phtttl<br />
and before you can say " knife" it has hit the pickets and it<br />
is practically self-fielded because it is so near the pitch,<br />
Anyhow that's all just a bigoted, bitter, Victorian point of<br />
view, ILaughter) All I know is that it isn't for nothing that you<br />
have the Sheffield Shield, It certainly isn't because in<br />
these last years, in most of which critical onlookers have been<br />
saying, " Ah cricket is not what it used to be-' you know, I<br />
hate those iellows, There never was anybody as good as so and<br />
so and so and so, All nonsense. To me there was never<br />
anybody as good as the fellow who is out there now ( Hear,<br />
hear) performing. Each man I am looking at and enjoying, and<br />
I hate these bumbling commentators who live in the past,<br />
It's a hateful thing, But here, year after year, you have<br />
been producing and showing the very backbone of Austral: an<br />
international cricket and I cculd stand up here for an hour<br />
and talk about eight or ten of them and never say a word that<br />
anybody would disagree with. But in particular, if you will<br />
allow me to say so, you have been able to make a remarkable<br />
contribution, int~ rnatioiially, to cricket because you have<br />
produced two people Ian Craig and Richie Benaud, whose place<br />
in cricket history 1S9 I believe, quite assured. ( Hear hear)<br />
( Applause) IItave been a politico for a long time and f have<br />
had defeats and victories and large majorities and small<br />
majorities but if there is one thing that I have learned it is<br />
that the first condition of ultimate success is to produce a<br />
sense of morale in your team. ( Hear, hear)<br />
And if Ian will allow me to say so, this is his<br />
eat contribution to modern cricket history in Australia<br />
Applause) as a field captain, as a man who, in some mysterious<br />
fashion almost magical fashion, always takes the offensive.<br />
I've sat up in my lordly box more than once and have watched<br />
him conduct a manoeuvre on the field so &amp;; vastatingly good,<br />
0 00 0.60V4 </p>
<p>4~ e<br />
so aggressively brilliant that even before it succeeded<br />
knew that it would, This is something quite remarkable<br />
and it is made all the more remarkable because, unhappily,<br />
the cricket of our great opponent L. nd I hope always our<br />
great opponent on the cricket field has tended a little<br />
to being defensive, Well, we are not to be beaten,, And it<br />
is a bad thing to start off any contest by saying " Well<br />
I'm not going to be beaten."' It is so important io staR<br />
off by saying, " We are going to win" and this is the difference<br />
between defensive tactics and aggressive3 tactics and aggressive<br />
tactics have paid off,<br />
And Richie Benaud occupies a place in the history<br />
of cricket not only as a New South Welshman not only fur<br />
this team with such success, but in the history of international<br />
cricket which I really believe is unique in my time, and if<br />
it is unique in my time, it is tuique because he has always<br />
had the spirit of resourceful at-tack studying every batsman<br />
who comes in, I saw him get Trevor Lailey caught by himself<br />
off square leg one day by a masterly piece of psychology,<br />
Because the moment Bailey came in I happened to say to the<br />
fellow next to meI " You know, Bailey rather likes to tickle<br />
one quietly round the corner to get off the mark and the<br />
bowling won't help this and he'll get a bit fed up with it,"<br />
This chap came in, flanked himself at short square leg, the<br />
bowling went on and of course, finally even Baileyts<br />
patience was exhausted ( Laughter) and up she went and there<br />
we were, Can't be very easy to be the captain of a cricket<br />
team. I've been the captain of a political team for a long<br />
time and believe me, it s not child's play ( Laughter) though<br />
everybody else thinks it is ( Laughter) and of course, that'S<br />
true about the captain of a team, Everybody understands it,<br />
on the whole, rather better than he does but, at the same<br />
time, looking back over these years, I can't imagine a more<br />
just result than the one that we've been able to produce to<br />
you, the celebration of this enormous period of years of<br />
success, I would just like to say I am very glad to see<br />
here tonight Sid Smith. I am sorry he's been on the sick<br />
list. I sit up with him whererer I manage to arrive at the<br />
Sydney Cricket Ground, tear myself away from the embraces<br />
of the Trustees. I like to sit tip with Sid Smith and t-ommy<br />
Howard and listen to the old and bold telling me about these<br />
matters and as a rulu, at the other end of the Committee<br />
box, there Is a man called Webb. You know the chap Webb?<br />
He's a Q0C. ( Laughter) An argumentative character if ever<br />
there was one, If somebody does a straight drive and it<br />
runs under the sight boards he's quite prepared to say, " Now,<br />
if it ran under the sight board, but it didn't actually reach<br />
the pickets, would it be a four'?" ( Laughter) And he will<br />
argue about that for the next hour. I always refuse to<br />
argue with him0 I wonder if I could just, before I concj~ ude,<br />
say this to you, There's an intimate association between<br />
cricket and the law,, I am reminded of this by Webb? Q40Co<br />
I have had one or two very curious experiences in which my<br />
devotion to cricket has come not amiss. I remember many<br />
years ago when the late Sir Leo Cussen who was a very<br />
distinguished Supreme Court Judge in Victoria and who was<br />
President-of the M. COCO in Melbourne was down at a Test<br />
Match and I wanted to be there too, but a solicitor in the<br />
03a00a80 a 000 a/ </p>
<p>country had taken an Opinion from me abcout four weeks before,<br />
about some problem of a by-1aw relating to bees and how far<br />
they were to be allowed to fly ( 1Leughter) or one of those<br />
things that country municipalities love so much and I had<br />
written an Opinion and it said that in my opinion the by-law<br />
was invalid and that the conviction of his client was wrong<br />
and that he ought to apply for an Orde-? to Review. An<br />
application for an Order to Review at that time, I think, in<br />
Victoria had to be made within thirty days of conviction and<br />
my country solicitor forgot about it. It was getting near<br />
Christmas and he forgot about the clock until the very last<br />
moment when he suddenly sent down all the affidavits to his<br />
Melbourne agent and said h" You must get Mr. Menzies to apply<br />
for an Order Nisi," 1 and ?; is was the last day. Sir Leo<br />
Cussen beamed at me and said, " I seem to remember, Menzies<br />
therets a rule that if Counsel can assure the Judge that all<br />
the papers are cr, the file and mentions the case, the application<br />
will be treated as in time and can then be adjourned<br />
for a fortnight, is that right?" and I said, " Yes Your<br />
Honour, that is precisely the position as I understand it,"<br />
" Very well he said " I accept your assurance. You. mention<br />
the case, f adjourn It for a fortnight. Get my Associate to<br />
make a note of the name, will you if it occurs to you, In<br />
the meantime, isn't this chap bowling well." ( Laughter)<br />
I always remember that with great pleasure. And could I,<br />
without wearying you, tell you another?<br />
We had a County Court Judge in Victoria who<br />
had actually played for Australia, rather fleetingly, many<br />
years before, He wasn't a very good lawyer. He was a<br />
charming man. He had a rather pedantic attachment to what<br />
he was pleased to regard as good English and therefore he<br />
was occasionally difficult, You had one like that here in<br />
New South Wales. ( Laughter) But many years ago in my<br />
County Court days, I knew that this Judge was devoted to<br />
cricketl c'nooks it all came back to my mind the other day<br />
when I was dandling the White Leghorns down at the Exhibitionand<br />
roses, and it was very important to know what a judgets<br />
-prejudices are, i~ f I may say so, before you appear before<br />
hi: m, So down from the country came a case for me; there<br />
was an argument about a contract and my solicitor produced<br />
a client who was as dull as a man could comfortably be.<br />
( Laughter) You couldn't get a consecutive statement out of<br />
him on anything. He was a decent chap. I've no doubt that,<br />
basically, he had the right ideas but you just couldn'~ t et<br />
anything sensible from him and it was very troublesome,<br />
We went up into court, I knowing as little<br />
about my client's case as possible, in consequence and the<br />
plaintiff Counsel opened hiis case and he called thirteen<br />
witnesses and tUhey were good. I cross-examined them with<br />
all the skill that I could command, but on the whole I thought<br />
they did rather well, and at the end of the day when all<br />
their witnesses had been called I had no witness except<br />
this derelict client of mine ( Laughter) the Judge, the<br />
ex-cricketer, said to me, " Well, Mr. Menzies, you know, I<br />
dontt want to discourage you but I am very impressed by the<br />
case for the plaintiff." 1 Ana I said, with that innocent<br />
air that I am thankful to say always characterised me<br />
( Laughter), I said, " Your Honour I appreciate that, but<br />
I beg of you, Sir, suspend your judgment until you have<br />
heard my case. I am certain, Sir4 that you will be impressed<br />
by it," And he said, " Certainly and we adjourned, Then<br />
I said to the solicitor, " Bring that fellow down to my<br />
. o o. o/ 6 </p>
<p>6<br />
chambers again, will YOU" and we had anothier session. I<br />
coul -dn't discovrer what he thought he was talking about, so<br />
finally I proclaimed my usual gambits when I was before thi s<br />
Judge,, I said, " Itccuse me, Mr. So and So "-he came from<br />
the Bullarook Forest or somewhere near Ballarat, you know<br />
I said, " Excuse me, but do you keep fowls?" 1 He said, " What<br />
do you mean?" I said, " Can you tell a White Leghorn from a<br />
Buff Orpington or a Wyandotte?" " O01 no," he said. " The wife<br />
keeps a few chooks but I wouldn't know what they were" I said,<br />
" Forget about the fowls. ( Laughter) Second : Do you grow<br />
roses?" " Oh well," he says. " I don't kniow. The Missus has<br />
got one or two, I thinik,&amp; I said, " Well, could you tell a<br />
Frau Carl from a La Belle France, or whatever it is?" 1 And<br />
he said, " Oh, no, come off it." ( Laughter) I said, " Out with<br />
the roses.'" So, greatly despairing I said to him, " Cricket,<br />
Did you ever play cricket?" He said. " Oh, now youtee talking."<br />
He said, " I played for Ballarat and District against Ivo<br />
. Blights Eleven." I said, 4' 1Ah, wonderful) What, 1882 or something?"<br />
He said, " Yes" I said, " Conference concluded.<br />
Thank you, Take him away. Keep him right overnight." ( Laughter)<br />
Next morning, I opened the case as well as I could,<br />
called my wretched client, who was all over the place and I<br />
finally said, " Well now, witness, I am going to ask you about<br />
the date on which this particular conversation occurred. And<br />
I know His Hcnour appreciates that it is not easy to remember<br />
a date, Now, of course, if I were to ask you to remember the<br />
da~ te on which you played for Ballarat and District against Ivo<br />
Blights Eleven ( L9aughter) naturally that would be differ'ent,,"<br />
And the Judge turned rouna and said, " What's that? Is that<br />
right? Did you play Well, well 11 he said, and hitched<br />
around his chair and for the next hal hour thay exchanged<br />
ideas ( Laughter) about this fast-bowler, and whether that<br />
spinner was really turning the ball, and my fellow turned out<br />
to have made twentysix runs a very admirable innings9Jm<br />
you Inow ( Lau. ghter) and had taken a couple of wickets and<br />
by thLi. time, of course, I had sat down like the cat thai swallowed<br />
the canary. My opponent, very properly, got up to cross-examine,<br />
and the Judge said, " Well, Mr. McGuiness, of course I want to<br />
make it clear that you have a perfect right to cross-examine this<br />
witness. I will be the last man to deny you your rights, but<br />
I think I should tell you before you do that in the whole of my<br />
j udicial caraer I have never been so impressed by a witness<br />
( Laughter) as I have by Mr. So and So." Whfiether it was just or<br />
unjust, I'll never know ( Laughter).<br />
Sir, those two anecdotes are quite irrelevant to<br />
the task of the evening, but really, when I get among my friends<br />
the cricketers who have given me more pleasure than perhaps<br />
any other people in the world in a leisure that is not too<br />
frequent, I become d little reminiscent and a little talkative,<br />
I am indebted to the cricketers of my own time for so much<br />
happiness. I am particularly indebted to this magnificent New<br />
South Wales team which has once more won the Sheffield Shield<br />
and which, as it now stands9 is probably capable of taking on<br />
any international team in the world,, And that's a great performance,<br />
~ hsis a great event and I have loved it and I want<br />
you all to join with me in drinking the health of the team and<br />
in particular, the health of this talented and courageous man,<br />
Richie Benaud, who captained it and who is one of the great<br />
captains in cricket history, ( Hear, hear) </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
