<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8538</transcript-id>
    <title>MESSAGE FROM THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON PJ KEATING MP TO THE BENKSIA ENVIRONMENTAL FOUNDATION AWADRS 1992 MELBOURNE, ON WORLD ENVIRONMENT DAT 5 JUNE 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/06/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008538.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL: I. L Ju . i : 41~ I: C1,-<br />
MESSAGE FROM THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP,<br />
TO THE BAKKSIA ENVIRONMENTAL FOUNDATION AWARDS 1992,<br />
MELBOURNE, ON WORLD ENVIRONMENT DAY, 5 JUNE 1992<br />
welcome to this gathering on world Environment Day.<br />
Today we might reflect on any number of environmental<br />
issues. In 1992 the most important task is perhaps less one of<br />
recognising the challenge than arriving at an effective<br />
way of meeting it.<br />
To do that we need to overcome the sort of polarisation<br />
which too often debilitates the debate.<br />
No doubt there have been faults on all sides, but the<br />
first principle is protection.<br />
It is no longer acceptable to cast those who believe in<br />
ecologically sustainable development and environmental<br />
protection as spoilers opposed to everything, and<br />
without viable alternatives.<br />
Sustainable development La a viable alternative it may<br />
well be a viable imperative.<br />
Those who are charged with being_ anti-joqbs, because they<br />
want strict controls on pollution,_ greenhouse ga! s<br />
emissions, production aiid disposal of-waste material, or<br />
certain development proposals controls, might well reply<br />
that they are In fayntir of a higher standard of living.<br />
It is simply not a matter of jobs versus environment.<br />
We do not need to lower our environmental standards to<br />
get greater economic grow Lh.<br />
As business is discovering, the environment is an<br />
economic growth area.<br />
It is not a case of our being unable to afford to protect<br />
the environment. Rather, we cannot afford to degrade it.<br />
This World Environment Day is an appropriate time to<br />
remind ourselves that our huge environmental losses in<br />
Australia have been economic losses, with economic costs. </p>
<p>TEL: S J un It -31 NO' -Li I-<br />
2<br />
For the benefit of this generation and those to come, we<br />
have to develop a new sense of common national purpose, a<br />
new willingness to work cooperatively towards national<br />
goals and national solutions.<br />
There is no greater goal than developing a now<br />
relationship with the environment.<br />
That, I think should be the message on this World<br />
Environment Day -that, and our congratulations to the<br />
winners of the Banksia Awards.<br />
Thank you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
