<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>22715</transcript-id>
    <title>Opening of the Promenade D&#039;Australie, Paris</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/04/2000</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE  ……………………………………………………………………</p>
<p>To Mayor Tiberi, the Mayor of Paris, to Mayor Galy-Dejean, distinguished guests, ladies and gentlemen and particularly I acknowledge the presence of the Australian Ambassador to France, Mr John Spender.</p>
<p>It is a great pleasure for me to be here today on behalf of the Australian Government and the Australian people and to acknowledge with gratitude the gesture of the city of Paris in naming this promenade after Australia, and in so doing honouring the very close links that exist between our two nations and our two peoples.</p>
<p>Here on the promenade we have for example a stature of that great French navigator La Perouse, who history records arrived in Sydney, only six days after the British Captain Phillip established the first European settlement in Australia at Botany Bay in 1788.  Next year, 2001 will mark the 200th Anniversary of the departure of another great French navigator Baudin for the unknown southern oceans.</p>
<p>But the links that exists between our two societies have been developed over the last two hundred years, we have fought together in two world wars in defence of democracy and in defence of freedom.  And the links of course go into the modern world.</p>
<p>One of the many things I am doing here in Paris is bringing attention to the economic relationship that already exists between Australia and France and the great potential there is to develop that relationship in an even deeper way in the years ahead.</p>
<p>Those links of course take account of the great respect Australia and Australians have for the contribution of France and French culture to the civility of life not only here in Europe but all around the world.  Australians have long regarded Paris as something of a mecca for all of those who want to better understand what French culture and what the history of this great country has brought to the world.  It is undeniably a beautiful city and the opportunity of again visiting Paris is one that fills me and my wife with great pleasure.  </p>
<p>We share a great deal in common, our two nations and our two societies.  We work together in democracy and in harmony.  We also compete very vigorously on the sporting field, on occasions France winning and on other occasions, most recently Australia winning.  </p>
<p>And in the rain we learn to shorten our speeches.  </p>
<p>Can I say to you Mr Mayor and to all of the lovely people of Paris and the wonderful people of France that Janette and I are delighted to be here again?  We thank you very warmly for the honour that you have done our country in dedicating this wonderful walkway, the Promenade d’Australie.  It is a marvellous contribution to the deep association between our two communities and long may many French men and women and many Australians visiting Paris and visiting France enjoy the promenade and are reminded of the very close and real links that exist between our two societies.  </p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
