<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4271</transcript-id>
    <title>LORD MAYOR&#039;S BANQUET - MELBOURNE</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/11/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004271.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
INFORKATION A14D STATE RELATIONS<br />
DIVISION<br />
PRIME -MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 9 November 1976<br />
LORD MAYOR' S BANQUET MELBOURNE<br />
I am delighted honoured -to have been invited to attend<br />
this banquet, which is the pre-eminent annual banquet<br />
of the City of Melbourne. It is the occasion on which the<br />
Lord Mayor of Melbourne can speak to the City of Melbourne<br />
and to the State of Victoria.<br />
It is an occasion attended by the Governor, the Chief Justice,<br />
and this year by the representative of the Premier.<br />
Out of the generosity of the City of Melbourne even Prime Ministers,<br />
are, on occasion, provided with a platform from which to respond<br />
to the toast to the Commonwealth and to speak briefly.<br />
Since I find myself tonight with a platform, I hope it will not<br />
be taken as an impertinence if I say a few words about the<br />
concept of this dinner. The first thing that strikes one about<br />
this dinner is the illustrious character of its guest list.<br />
It is a guest list which I know you have striven to make<br />
ecumenical even to the extent of inviting Hawthorn<br />
football club supporters. But then, I suppose this year you<br />
did not really have a choice in the matter.<br />
In recent years, the guest list for this banquet has attracted<br />
considerable comment. I am sure that we are all very pleased<br />
to see so many of the leading women in our community here this<br />
evening. Their presence expresses the judgement that this<br />
banquet pre-eminently . hould express the unity of our community.<br />
It is no reflection on the City of Melbourne or on you, my Lord<br />
Mayor, that there are few if any representatives of the trade<br />
union movement here tonight. Yet their absence, is I believe,<br />
very much to be regretted.<br />
This year, many of us have had to think very deeply about<br />
Australia and the direction in which we want Australia to go.<br />
The kind of Australia we will pass onto our children and our<br />
grandchildren will very much depend on those of us here.<br />
It will also depend equally greatly on many who are not here.<br />
Australia is a country currently facing significant challenges<br />
challenges which arise both from serious economic circumstances<br />
and from inevitable social change. I do not need to spell out<br />
in detail what these challenges are we are all too familiar<br />
with them. ./ 2 </p>
<p>Whether we get on top of inflation, whether we can beat<br />
unemployment, whether Australia becomes a country where people<br />
treat each other with tolerance and mutual respect all<br />
these depend on the commitment and attitudes of people right<br />
throughout our community and around Australia.<br />
One of the great qualities about Australia has been the way in<br />
which Australians have traditionally recognised the common<br />
gond between them and the over-riding importance this bond<br />
has over any differences of opinion that might exist.<br />
There are unfortunately some people today who strive<br />
to divide Australians from each other who seek personal gain from<br />
stirring up conflict and divisiveness in the community who<br />
strive to use economic difficulties and social issues to attack<br />
our democratic institutions.<br />
Fortunately, these people are a tiny minority. There is nothing<br />
that will more certainly ensure that they remain a minority<br />
than a widespread -recognition that the future of all Australians<br />
is bound up together.;<br />
I have said on a number of occasions this year, that the<br />
responsibility for ensuring a return to prosperity falls on all<br />
sections of the Australian people.<br />
But the unity of Australians extends beyond the interests we<br />
all have in economic recovery. It is a unity whlichi geniunely extends<br />
to all the major issues with which we as politicians deal whether<br />
we are talking about the position of women in the community,<br />
about opportunities for disadvantaged minorities, about the problems<br />
of the retired, or about the small businessmen. The unity of<br />
interest about which I am speaking extends even into those difficult<br />
problems that arise with changing social values.<br />
In each of these matters all of us those here tonight and<br />
those not here have an over-riding concern in common that all<br />
Australians,, whoever they may be of whatever sex, race, age 0<br />
should be treated with full regard to their personal dignity and<br />
with respect for their right to seek to realise their goals in their<br />
own way.<br />
If principles such as these guide our actions I believe we will not<br />
go far wrong in the way we handle any of the problems that<br />
confront us. Of course, we cannot take for granted that these<br />
basic values will always find expression we know, indeed,<br />
only too well from experience that they are often not expressed.<br />
That instead, some Australians are confronted by intolerance,<br />
discrimination, social privilege and lack of concern and<br />
unfortunately, by efforts to sow division within Australia.<br />
This brings me back to my earlier remarks, and to the imperinence<br />
that I referred to.<br />
A banquet such as this can pre-eminently symbolise the real unity<br />
in our community leading women, trade union leaders, community<br />
leaders of all kinds. 3 </p>
<p>The future of Melbourne, of Victoria, of Australia depends<br />
on them all.<br />
This dinner can truly help to symbolise the unity of our<br />
community. I hope that it will increasingly do so in future years.<br />
We cannot avoid the great task of ensuring that the true<br />
unity of Australia prevails over particular differences of opinion.<br />
I believe it is important that we all take every opportunity<br />
to stress our common interests and our common concerns and<br />
take a resolute stand against those who seek to divide.<br />
It has been an excellent dinner enjoyed by us all.<br />
I have been most interested in your remarks, Lord Mayor,<br />
and most grateful for your invitation.<br />
000oo00000 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
