<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3331</transcript-id>
    <title>NOTES FOR THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. E.G. WHITLAM, Q.C., M.P., UNIVERSITY OF SYDNEY UNION CENTENARY DINNER, 19 JULY 1974</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/07/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003331.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
' 7'<br />
NOTES FOR THE PRIME MINISTER, MR, E, G. WHITLAM, M. P,,<br />
UNIVERSITY OF SYDNEY UNION CENTENARY<br />
DINNER, 19 JULY 1974<br />
1, THIS IS THE FIRST UNION I EVER JOINED. I BECAME A STUDENT<br />
MEMBER IN 1935 AND A LIFE MEMBER IN 1947. So I'VE BEEN A<br />
UNIONIST FOR 39 YEARS LONGER THAN BOB HAWKE. AND I'VE NEVER<br />
SEEN A MORE ELEGANT, DISTINGUISHED AND PROSPEROUS UNION MEETING<br />
THAN THIS, IT'S A PITY YOU'RE NOT AFFILIATED WITH THE LABOR<br />
PARTY. 2. I WISH CLYDE CAMERON WERE HERE THIS EVENING. THIS MUST<br />
BE THE ONLY UNION THAT HAS NEVER BEEN ON STRIKE DURING THE<br />
PAST 100 YEARS, YOU HAVEN'T EVEN HAD A WORK-TO-RULE.<br />
3, THE UNIVERSITY OF SYDNEY UNION IS AN AMALGAMATION OF THE<br />
SYDNEY UNIVERSITY UNION AND THE SYDNEY UNIVERSITY'WOMEN'S<br />
UNION, THAT DIDN'T HAPPEN UNTIL 1972, 1972 WAS A GREAT<br />
YEAR FOR ALL OF US INDEED THE YEAR OF LIBERATION, IT TOOK<br />
23 YEARS FOR MY PARTY TO COME TO POWER, IT TOOK 98 YEARS<br />
FOR YOUR UNION TO BE CONSUMMATED<br />
4, IT WAS VERY UNSATISFACTORY FOR ME TO BE IN ONE UNION<br />
AND MY WIFE IN ANOTHER, WE HAD CONSTANT DEMARCATION DISPUTES.<br />
As YOU KNOW, THE GOVERNMENT HAS TRIED SEVERAL TIMES TO<br />
PASS LEGISLATION FOR UNION AMALGAMATIONS. WE HAVE BEEN BLOCKED<br />
BY THE SENATE, THE SYDNEY UNIVERSITY SENATE IS A MUCH MORE<br />
ENLIGHTENED BODY THAN THE SENATE IN CANBERRA, IT'S 120 YEARS<br />
OLD. SOME OF OUR CANBERRA SENATORS WOULD FEEL VERY MUCH AT HOME THER </p>
<p>-2-<br />
6, YOUR CONSTITUTION SAYS: " THE OBJECTS OF THE UNION SHALL<br />
BE TO PROVIDE A COMMON MEETING GROUND FOR MEMBERS,,,,; TO<br />
PROVIDE DINING AND REFRESHMENT SERVICES; TO PROVIDE CONVENIENCES,<br />
SERVICES AND AMENITIES FOR MEMBERS; TO PROVIDE SOCIAL, CULTURAL<br />
AND RECREATIONAL FACILITIES; TO PROMOTE THE INTELLECTUAL, CULTURAL<br />
AND SOCIAL DEVELOPMENT OF ITS MEMBERS BY DEBATES AND ACTIVITIES,,,,<br />
IT SOUNDS LIKE A VERY GOOD DESCRIPTION OF PARLIAMENT,<br />
No WONDER I FIND THE UNION SO CONGENIAL,<br />
7, ALTHOUGH THE UNION WAS FORMED IN 1874 ITS CONSTITUTION<br />
WAS NOT ADOPTED UNTIL 1911, IT JUST GOES TO SHOW THAT WE<br />
CAN GET ALONG WITHOUT A CONSTITUTION IF WE TRY,<br />
8. I REGRET TO SAY THAT I WAS NOT A VERY GOOD UNIONIST IN<br />
MY DAYS AT UNIVERSITY, MY PROLETARIAN INSTINCTS WERE NOT WELL<br />
DEVELOPED, I TOOK NO PART IN UNION DEBATES, INTER-COLLEGIATE<br />
DEBATES WERE MORE IN MY LINE, LOOKING BACK THROUGH THE OLD<br />
UNION RECORDER, HOWEVER, I FIND THAT SEVERAL OF MY DISTINGUISHED<br />
CONTEMPORARIES WERE PROMINENT IN DEBATES AND UNION AFFAIRS, </p>
<p>-3-<br />
THERE WAS TALBOT DUCKMANTON, WHOSE POLISHED ACCENTS<br />
ASSURED HIM OF A GREAT CAREER IN RADIO. THERE WAS BRUCE<br />
MILLER, WHO WAS A RADIO ANNOUNCER BEFORE ATTAINING HIS<br />
PRESENT EMINENCE AT THE AAA. U THERE WAS HERMAN BLACK;<br />
HE ALSO MADE HIS NAME ON RADIO. SIR HERMAN WAS A GENERATION<br />
BEFORE HIS TIME. HE WOULD HAVE RIVALLED JOHN LAWS AND BOB<br />
ROGERS ON TALK-BACK PROGRAMS$<br />
THERE WAS DONALD HORNE, WHO WAS GATHERING NOTES FOR<br />
A BOOK ON " THE EDUCATION OF YOUNG DONALD", J. H. WOOTTENO<br />
NOW PROFESSOR OF LAW IN ANOTHER PLACEo AND JIM PLIMSOLL.<br />
THE UNION WAS A HOT-BED OF RADICALISM IN THOSE DAYS.<br />
MY POLITICS, OF COURSE, WERE WELL TO THE LEFT OF THEIRS.<br />
IMUST HAVE BEEN INFLUENCED By ENOCH POWELL.<br />
9. Two OF THE GREAT PERSONALITIES IN THE UNION'S HISTORY<br />
WERE PROFESSOR E. R. HOLME ( WHOM WE KNEW AS ' SUNNY' HOLME)<br />
AND PROFESSOR F. A. TODD. I HAD THE GOOD FORTUNE TO BE<br />
TAUGHT. BY BOTH OF THEM. E. R. HOLME WAS my ENGLISH PROFESSOR<br />
AND F. A. TODD GAVE ME SOME ACQUAINTANCE WITH LATIN.<br />
THE UNIVERSITY WAS A DIFFERENT PLACE IN MY DAY.<br />
IT WAS A MUCH STUFFIER AND MORE CONSERVATIVE INSTITUTION.<br />
IT WAS QUIETER AND VERY MUCH SMALLER. WOMEN STUDENTS WERE<br />
DECIDEDLY IN THE MINORITY. INOTICE THAT DESPITE YOUR<br />
AMALGAMATION YOU HAVE YET TO ELECT A WOMAN AS PRESIDENT<br />
OF THE UNION. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
