<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9327</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J.KEATING, MP OPENING THE JUSTICE FORUM,PARLIAMENT HOUSE,CANBERRA, 22 AUGUST 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/08/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009327.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Kr<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
PLEASE CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING, MP<br />
OPENING THE JUSTICE FORUM, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA,<br />
22 AUGUST 1994<br />
Last October, the Government commissioned a major report on reform of our<br />
legal system.<br />
We did that because the Australian public was losing confidence in our legal<br />
system.<br />
We have in place a system of government that gives Australians access to<br />
universal health care, quality education, improved training opportunities,<br />
affordable child care, and a safety net of benefits and pensions.<br />
But if we are to count ourselves as one of the world's truly great social<br />
democracies we need to ensure Australians have appropriate access to their<br />
legal system.<br />
We asked the Access To Justice Committee, chaired by Ronald Sackville,<br />
how to enhance access to justice and make the legal system fairer, more<br />
efficient and more effective.<br />
And that's just what the committee's done. It's an excellent report and for that<br />
our thanks go to Ronald and his fellow committee members.<br />
This Justice Forum is a very important part of the consultative process arising<br />
out of the Access to Justice Report. And I very much see your attendance<br />
here today as evidence that, like the Government, you want to see<br />
Australians regain confidence in their legal system.<br />
Later this year, we will take another important step down the reform path<br />
when I deliver the Government's Justice Statement. </p>
<p>We are committed to access to justice and equality before the law. The<br />
Statement will ensure that we put in place the sort of justice system<br />
Australians expect and deserve.<br />
One area where we can make a start is with the criminal law.<br />
Over the course of this Labor Government, Australia has led the world in<br />
designing laws to combat organised crime. But we have been let down by the<br />
provisions of our criminal laws, which are fragmented and vary between the<br />
States and Territories.<br />
If we are to reduce the chances of criminals escaping justice by exploiting<br />
technicalities in the law, if we are to ensure fairness and consistency, if we<br />
are to reduce legal costs, we need a uniform, simplified and reformed criminal<br />
law a Model Criminal Code that all Australians can understand.<br />
I want to see the Commonwealth implement the Model Criminal Code well<br />
before 2001 so that the States can have ample opportunity to have the Code<br />
up and running on a national basis by the target date of 2001.<br />
1 think it's also time to supplement traditional, reactive enforcement strategies<br />
with a more sophisticated emphasis on prevention, and to deal more<br />
effectively with the underlying causes of criminal behaviour.<br />
And I applaud the recently announced intention of Premiers and Chief<br />
Ministers to meet later this year to discuss a concerted approach to<br />
combating crime.<br />
Clearly, the Commonwealth is ideally placed to accept a leadership and<br />
coordinating role in issues of such importance for all Australians.<br />
That's why we have been directly involved with the States and Territories in<br />
developing new policies on issues such as firearms and domestic violence,<br />
which deal with anti-social activity at the community level.<br />
Co-operation between governments, law enforcement agencies and the<br />
community is the key to controlling crime.<br />
The Commonwealth will continue to support consultative arrangements that<br />
lead to effective national crime prevention programs. We will sponsor<br />
research into the causes of crime and the development of appropriate<br />
preventive strategies.<br />
The aim is to build a safer Australia.<br />
We will work in partnership with the States and Territories, the profession and<br />
the judiciary to facilitate reform. </p>
<p>With my firm support, the Attorney-General and the Minister for Justice are<br />
identifying the barriers to accessible justice and developing a major legal<br />
reform package to make access to justice a reality for all Australians.<br />
Let me say a few words about those areas where I think we can really make a<br />
difference.<br />
A major barrier to justice is its cost.<br />
The cost of justice excludes most Australians from using a lawyer or the<br />
courts to enforce or defend their rights.<br />
That's not acceptable.<br />
Freeing up the legal market is one way to reduce costs.<br />
We are working with the States and Territories to reform the legal profession.<br />
We want it to become more competitive, more accountable, and geared to the<br />
needs of the people it serves.<br />
Extending the Trade Practices Act to the professions under a national<br />
competition policy would ensure that consumers and competitors in the legal<br />
market enjoy the same protection available to people in other sectors.<br />
Other reforms would make the legal services market more flexible.<br />
Lifting restrictions on advertising would allow consumers the best possible<br />
information on the services they need.<br />
Improving regulations for the disclosure of fees and for the independent<br />
assessment of costs would protect consumers.<br />
The ability to opt for contingency fees would extend access to the legal<br />
system. More difficult areas, such as opening up areas of work reserved to lawyers,<br />
also need further examination.<br />
The Council of Australian Governments will consider in February 1995 reform<br />
proposals to make the profession more accountable and accessible than ever<br />
before.<br />
We are not talking about leaving the cost of justice purely to market forces.<br />
Legal aid is another important factor in the cost equation.<br />
An effective national legal aid scheme remains central to the Government's<br />
social justice strategy. </p>
<p>As the major provider of legal aid funding, the Commonwealth has a clear<br />
leadership role to play. We can and should influence the way legal aid<br />
funding is directed.<br />
Of course, it is vital that legal aid reform is achieved in a true partnership with<br />
the other key players the States and the legal profession. Successful<br />
reform depends as much on their contribution as on ours.<br />
Proposals for contingency fee arrangements with private lawyers could meet<br />
some of the need of middle Australia for legal assistance.<br />
And litigation lending funds and legal expenses insurance also have a place<br />
in giving Australians a fair go when they need legal assistance.<br />
How we spend our legal aid dollars must also reflect our commitment to<br />
equality before the law. We must ensure that, in practice, the legal system<br />
delivers justice evenhandedly and does not enshrine inequality.<br />
This means making concrete commitments to fix the inherent biases in the<br />
system. Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander peoples and people from non-English<br />
speaking backgrounds face particular difficulties and fears when dealing with<br />
our legal system.<br />
They should have access to interpreters and information in a language they<br />
understand and they should be dealt with in a culturally sensitive manner.<br />
Cultural sensitivity also requires knowledge and training. The Government is<br />
supporting cross-cultural training initiatives by the Australian Institutes of<br />
Judicial Administration to promote this.<br />
Women should have greater access to appropriate and affordable advice and<br />
support about the legal problems that affect them.<br />
And the specific problems faced by Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander<br />
women in gaining access to legal aid must also be addressed.<br />
These reforms are fundamental if we are to ensure all Australians have<br />
access to justice.<br />
Every day in our courts people test their rights under the law. Matters that<br />
have the potential to touch us all are often under dispute.<br />
The establishment of important legal precedents, for example, in human<br />
rights, consumer protection and environmental law must be supported.<br />
Improving access to justice must also include reforms to the means we have<br />
available for resolving disputes in short, more choice is needed. </p>
<p>While access to our courts must, of course, remain available to all, it is clear<br />
that many cases would be better resolved without resort to expensive and<br />
adversarial court action.<br />
In family law, for example, the Government has begun a fundamental shift<br />
away from litigation towards a simple and more affordable process of<br />
mediation and counselling in appropriate cases.<br />
We must work to expand alternatives to litigation, while ensuring that dispute<br />
resolution remains just and fair.<br />
Of course, reforms should also continue to be achieved in the courts. I am<br />
very interested in proposals for the development of court charters which<br />
would set out the courts' commitments to ' user-friendliness' and the delivery<br />
of accessible justice.<br />
Clearly, we all support the need for reform. And I think I can safely say that<br />
we are all committed to rebuilding Australians' faith in their legal system.<br />
I wish you well in your deliberations over the next two days and am pleased<br />
to declare the Justice Forum open. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
