<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>23492</transcript-id>
    <title>Interview with Mark Ferguson, Seven News, Network Seven</title>
    <prime-minister>Abbott, Tony</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130918 - 20150915</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/05/2014</release-date>
    <release-type>Transcript</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects>Budget 2014.</subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p><strong>MARK FERGUSON:</strong></p>
<p>Prime Minister Tony Abbott joins us live now on <em>Seven News. </em>Prime Minister, people here in Rouse Hill and across many parts of Sydney are asking why you’ve broken key election promises. Do you owe many of those who voted for you an apology?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER:</strong></p>
<p>Look, I owe everyone who voted for the Government strong leadership and an honest Budget and this is a Budget which honestly tackles the difficulties that we’ve got as a nation.</p>
<p>Under Labor, for too long, we were like someone who was paying the mortgage on the credit card. We were living beyond our means as a government, as a nation and we have to change that and change started with last night’s Budget.</p>
<p><strong>MARK FERGUSON:</strong></p>
<p>But Prime Minister, leadership is all about trust. Do you accept many now have the right to question your honesty and your credibility?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER:</strong></p>
<p>What we’re doing is not designed to make things politically easier for the Government. What we’re doing is designed to make things economically better for our country and that is the ultimate bond of trust between people and their leaders: can you trust the leadership of the country to do what is necessary to keep the country strong? I think that the country was looking for leadership and I think they found leadership with last night’s Budget.</p>
<p><strong>MARK FERGUSON:</strong></p>
<p>Prime Minister, if your co-payment for GP visits and aged pension changes are blocked in Parliament, will you call a new election?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER:</strong></p>
<p>Let’s be very clear, Mark. The co-payment for GP visits was Labor policy and there are Labor frontbenchers who think it makes sense. Let’s also make it clear that there are no cuts to pensions; what we are proposing is that in 2017, after the next election, the pension will be indexed by CPI. So yes, it will grow more slowly, but at the moment we are paying pensions and benefits with borrowed money. We can’t sustain these things and the most compassionate thing you can do for everyone, particularly pensioners, is to make the pension sustainable for the long-term.</p>
<p><strong>MARK FERGUSON:</strong></p>
<p>Ok Prime Minister. On a busy evening, we appreciate your time. Thank you.</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER:</strong></p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
