<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>317</transcript-id>
    <title>LAYINO FOUNDATION UTONE OF NEW FISHER LIBRARY BULLING UNIVERSITY OF SYDNEY 12TH MAY 1961 SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE RT. HON. R.G MENZIES G.H</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/05/1961</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000317_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
UHIV23Xñ jj2K 031911 IX. 111 4Y. i6<br />
I want to say, Siz, that I am very grateful to you for<br />
what you have said about me, and about my Government. I think It<br />
proper that 1 should also reind all of you hore today that what<br />
hats been done could not have been don* without the most extensive<br />
financial co-operation on the part of the State Oovornent<br />
bnoause the now era, as I like to think It in In univeraiy life<br />
whioh began with the Murray Rport# and the ZA0ption of the<br />
Murray Reprtg imposed great burdens if we accepted them, on the<br />
Commonvoalth and on the S3tatel and I think it is a very remarkable<br />
thing# worth remembering, that all the Oovernments, in Australia<br />
ooncerned and Indeed all parties conoerned, acoopted those<br />
rosponsibIl itien, which of course* as you know, are not growing<br />
lese As a result of the Murray Commission we round ourselves<br />
called upon to find a sum of money which was staggering to me<br />
arud I cani only assume, catastrophic to the Treasury. Juat we<br />
Wallowed three times and in a snail voice siaid " Yes* and my<br />
state oolleasusg I have no doubt, swallowed five times and In a<br />
small voice said " Yes* and then we appointed a Universities'<br />
Comission, under as mild-mannered a collection of bandits as I<br />
have ever come across In my life, When they made their<br />
reoomendations for the next trienniu I ns one of the bandits<br />
horet) when they made their recommendations i'or the next triennium<br />
well, they were roughly twice what they had been when we swallowed<br />
three times and said " Y~ es" . so this time we swallowed six times<br />
and uaid " Yes".<br />
Suit theso are, of course, light-heasrted ruxarks about a<br />
very, very remarkable period of development,. The development In<br />
the university's field has been and Is of course eoing to be so<br />
phenomenal that one would almost have oxpoctod It to Datisfy the<br />
demand, Jut of course It won't; It won't because circumstances<br />
in Auistralia. are such that the demand for tertiary education is<br />
grwing much more rapidly than the population Itself* Buit all<br />
this is a pood thing, thoujh It poses the most tremendous problems<br />
not only in terms of money but In terms of trained and adequate<br />
teachers and enquirers. There Is a tremendous challenge to<br />
education In Australia.<br />
Now when one thinks of a University one, of course<br />
thinks of a Variety of methods, but for myself I would like to<br />
say that I think that not only is a fine library the heart of a<br />
university, but In a real sense It is the University. One<br />
cannot imagine a university without a library of such quality and<br />
of such extent that the sager students in their thousands will<br />
not be prepared to find sustenance In It and enooura ement in it.<br />
A~ library is a marvellous thing, and books are marvellous things,<br />
Carlyle, you know, saids " In books lie the soul of the whole past<br />
time, t? e articulate audible voice of the past when the uoy and<br />
material substance of it has altogether vanished like a dream".<br />
Nov that was, I think, a remarkable observation in 011eroes and<br />
Hero-worship He was thinking of books primarily as the<br />
repository of the mind and expe., ienoe of men in past days. He<br />
was speakIng as an historiang and I am very ; lad that lie was,<br />
bucause a university that loses Its sense of history a student<br />
who has no sonsis of history is only half a university or half a<br />
student. And so, if a ligrary is to be the repository of the<br />
past forms and experienc, of men, It must be an adequate one. </p>
<p>I know that in my days at the University of Melbourne,<br />
if I may refer to so humble a foundation In your presenoo a<br />
JrnIversity that was once decorated by the Vice-Chancellor<br />
himself In our time a library was a small affair rather dark.<br />
I romenter it so wells a bit ding a few students coming in and<br />
peering at the book-shelves and jetting as near as possible to the<br />
window to get a little light, and a magnificent person oalled<br />
idward Ilippius Jrombyq who wore a beard, presiding at a desk and<br />
being ; reatly shocked every time someone dropped a volume of tho<br />
Law reports on to the floor# an art whiob I acquired theni and<br />
which turned out later on to be extraordinarily useful when<br />
appearing beflore a somewhat somnolent High Court,<br />
Nowv ir it is saidt and one, can quite understanid it,<br />
* Awe't we putting up too many libraries; aren't we setting up<br />
too many of these ,, reat places?" And the comment is a oomment<br />
niot to be surprised at beoause I believe in reoent times, almost<br />
In the last few years, there has beon a greater burgeoning of<br />
library buildinj and equipment in Australia than at any other time<br />
in our history. I doubt whether it can be matched In any other<br />
* ountry of our population. Tharefore people of economical minds,<br />
which distinguishes them* of course* very sharply Vrou economists<br />
the word is quite different but people of economical mids will<br />
say to uss " Wells why spend all this money on a university library<br />
when only over thero you have a National 6ibrary?" : ust as I said<br />
at Canberra University$ people say ' Vhy spend all this money on a<br />
University Library when you are already devoting your attention to<br />
the preliminary planning of at great National Library in Canberra?"<br />
The answer Is that no University can do its work, and<br />
above all a University so tremendously over-. crowded as this In In<br />
torms of numbers, no University can do Its work if It doea Its<br />
library vori Its study of books, at a distance, The book must be<br />
with the stu~ ntg the facilities for work must be in my opinion,<br />
instant facilities because$ unless students have Improved a great<br />
deal since my time, It doesn't take more than a mile and a half for<br />
enthusiasm to evaporate, You want the Library on the spot and,<br />
of course, If you have It on the spot, It must be the best kind of<br />
Golleotion of books and of documents, that you can possibly achieve;<br />
it It isn't, then the great student, then the great resuarch<br />
scholar, the man or woman full of ambition to probe more and more<br />
into the knowledge of some matter will find himself or herself<br />
leaving lustralia and going to where all these resources are<br />
available, We will tend to lose some of our best students,<br />
. Ehereas on the other hand if w have here on the spot a library<br />
of extensiveness and signIficance and value, selectivity, then we<br />
. fill not only maintain our own students and keep themt but we will<br />
gather students from other places and that is very important for<br />
Australia because for somebody In Australia to omue to a library<br />
that has great resources from some other part of Australia involves<br />
a relatively small journey, but for Australian students to have to<br />
go to the great repositories in the world involves not only large<br />
sums of money, but many, many thousands of miles of travel. This<br />
Is, one of those thing inm which ve ought to aim at beinu as selfoontainied<br />
in resouros as we possibly can be.<br />
There is, of course# one aspect of that matter that<br />
perhaps I ought to refer too I do not think, myself, for the<br />
reasons I have given you, that there Is any Inoonsistencr between<br />
having a great library here and another one three miles away , a<br />
public library. Not at all., jut there will be ; reat trouble for<br />
us In getting what we ought to jet for our resources if our<br />
libraries are allowed to be unduly competitive for scarce resources.<br />
-do det the idea oqoasionally, don't we, lookcing at the<br />
book-. shops, that the flood of books now pouring out over the world </p>
<p>3.<br />
is phenomenal. Your reforenoee 31r, to the statemnent in<br />
Soclosiasticus is very much appropriate, because evenr then they<br />
thought that writings published, in the sons in which they were<br />
published then, vwr pretty plentiful and rather exceeded the<br />
scope of one man's work or lit.; but today we got the idea that<br />
books and reoords are flooding out on the world, and no doubt they<br />
are, but of the books we need as students, of the publioations we<br />
need as students, there will always be in our time a supply smaller<br />
than the demand because as all the new countries come to lifa, as<br />
all their inteliectual processes begin to deliver, so will they<br />
more and more be demanding then* precious resources In the world*<br />
If we# therefore, are going to do our best for the nation,, as<br />
apart from one univeruity,, we will need to have the alosest oooperation<br />
between all the universities and other libraries In<br />
Australia so that we may do the best that we can for the resources<br />
that we haves Nov Jir, the only other thing Viat I want to tiay is<br />
this# This library is named after one of~ the ; roat original far.<br />
soelng benefactors in this dtate, I venture to say that Noew South<br />
dales and, In particular, Sydney has been very fortunate In having<br />
0 thhaidn gisn otfh e thaiss t kminedn , whAo nhd adw hUatI mthgenya tihoanv e, a tndI ~ tfh oirneks, i ghsht owann d two huo s bIegsan<br />
that every man' s collection of books and papers may itself, though<br />
private today, have something to contribute to a groat library in<br />
the future, and that poes particularly f'or documsents.<br />
0 Now I want to make a confession to you: I am more<br />
addicted to the waste-pape: basket than I ought to be; and I have<br />
no doubt that many times I have thrown things into the waste-p<br />
basket which would havre made screams of rage aome from Mro -oe<br />
4hite, the Comonwealth Librarian$ If he had seen me engaojd mint.<br />
A= he one looks back and thinks of all the pamphlets that<br />
have been published, the various occasional documents that have<br />
bea pblished In Australia -what would an ordinary private<br />
Xisn interested In political history, for example what would<br />
he # Weto have on his shelves a complete, set of all the paphets<br />
that wore published, in the nineties, In the great period ofth<br />
campaigns for Federation . well I wasn't engaged In political<br />
affairs in those days but if I had been I an sure that I would<br />
have read them and said KRubbishl" and put It In the waste-paper<br />
basket; or If It suited Xy book, 04hatts splondidt" I must lend it<br />
to my neighbour" -from who It would never return. And so both<br />
ways they have gone,, I want to say that I believe that It In the<br />
duty of all people * fltaged' In affairs to try to contribute not<br />
am boring autobiogrpy because that would be mostly Ra ayhov,<br />
mostly self-justifying aniw, but to contribute something of<br />
contemporary observation oithe e tents of the country and the<br />
events thiat people theuisel rs have witnessed, be : ause a greoat library<br />
Is the one that contains mises, almost myiads, of documnts of<br />
pwofbund interest to the a lar, and not only to the scholar of the<br />
htmaities but to the saie tist, to the man who, an a scientist must,<br />
not only proceed on his experimental work In the laboratory but<br />
whio also must reach out gather Mion all round the world the<br />
written product of the wolof others.<br />
Sol Sir, it is a pod thing that this is the Fisher<br />
Library, because he, set us an example in that field. It Is &amp; good<br />
thing for this Univeralty o have this groat library, whioh will<br />
provide facilities for, I pe, eager students in their thousands<br />
for maby, many years to c It Ina ood thing for the Gtate of<br />
VNew South Wales that this hould happen, but above all I venture<br />
to say, It In a good thin for Australia, beoause It ; W be oneS<br />
more contribution to = kin Australia more and more a centre, in<br />
civilised life, of intelligent researah, of cultivated understanding<br />
and of eagerness for greater knowledge* </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
