<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11324</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                 THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                 SYDNEY A CENTRE FOR GLOBAL FINANCIAL SERVICES                 GRAND HYATT HOTEL                 NEW YORK, USA</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/07/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE.................</p>
<p>Thank you very much Richard Holbrooke for those very kind words of</p>
<p> welcome. I feel very honoured that a person who's had such a very</p>
<p> distinguished and effective, as far as achieving outcomes for the</p>
<p> long-term benefit of humanity, contribution and role in the diplomatic</p>
<p> life, not only of the United States but also of the free world, should</p>
<p> be here today and I thank him very warmly for those words of introduction.</p>
<p>Can I, before I say what I wanted to say in relation to the common</p>
<p> purpose we all have in being here, how grateful I am for so many people</p>
<p> in the investment community in Australia and in the United States</p>
<p> who have worked hard to put this gathering together and in particular</p>
<p> to Peter Charlton and Maurice Newman and many others who have worked</p>
<p> with them.</p>
<p>This is a great time to be showcasing the Commonwealth of Australia.</p>
<p> And I am also delighted that the Premier of New South Wales, Bob Carr,</p>
<p> the Labor Premier of New South Wales is with us today. And as the</p>
<p> Liberal Prime Minister of Australia I welcome him in particular to</p>
<p> make the point to our American friends that this is a united bipartisan</p>
<p> Australian effort.</p>
<p>We believe that we have a great story to tell about many things that</p>
<p> have been done to make our nation more competitive and economically</p>
<p> stronger than it has been at any time in the 25 to 30 years that I</p>
<p> have been in public life. You have heard a great deal this morning</p>
<p> particularly from my ministerial colleague, Joe Hockey, who has specific</p>
<p> responsibility in my Government for promoting Australia as a world</p>
<p> financial centre. And also from Ted Evans, the Secretary of our Treasury.</p>
<p> You have heard of the micro-detail of where the Australian economy</p>
<p> sits, of how in getting taxation reform through the national Parliament</p>
<p> we have put in place the fifth pillar of major economic reconstruction</p>
<p> and economic change of the Australian economy over the last 15 to</p>
<p> 20 years.</p>
<p>Twenty years ago the Australian economy was far more cloistered, far</p>
<p> more closed, far more insular, far more regulated, far less worldly</p>
<p> than it is as we near the end of this millennium. We hadn't then deregulated</p>
<p> our financial system. We didn't allow in foreign banks, we didn't</p>
<p> have a floating exchange rate, we entertained the absurd delusion</p>
<p> that the central bank could control the level of interest rates. All</p>
<p> of that sounds fanciable, amusing and quaint and old-fashioned now</p>
<p> with the experience of the last 20 years. But I mention it to indicate</p>
<p> the distance that's been traveled and in doing it I have never been</p>
<p> reluctant in a number of areas to acknowledge the contribution of</p>
<p> prime ministers and others from the other side of politics in Australia.</p>
<p> Because without the bipartisan support for financial deregulation</p>
<p> and tariff reform in the 1980s and early 1990s the Australian economy</p>
<p> now would not be as strong as it is.</p>
<p>In recent years two or three other great reforms have been achieved.</p>
<p> One of those, of course, is in the space of two to three years to</p>
<p> turn a very large budget deficit into a very healthy surplus. And</p>
<p> I am particularly proud of the fact that Australia now has the lowest</p>
<p> level of government debt, the GDP ratio, of any OECD country. And</p>
<p> it is one of the great ambitions of our Government and particularly</p>
<p> of my Treasurer, Peter Costello, who has made such a great contribution</p>
<p> to this process for us to begin the early years of the next century</p>
<p> essentially free of net Commonwealth debt. And as a legacy and as</p>
<p> a contribution to future generations I can't think of a more practical</p>
<p> and finer one.</p>
<p>The changes in the Australian labour market in the last few years</p>
<p> have also been quite marked. One of the sometimes negative perceptions</p>
<p> of our country a few years ago was that we didn't have particularly</p>
<p> tranquil industrial relations. I am happy to emphasise the fact that</p>
<p> last year the number of industrial disputes was the lowest in 86 years.</p>
<p> But, of course, of all the reforms that we have undertaken none has</p>
<p> been bigger and one will have greater and more far reaching consequences</p>
<p> than, of course, the reforms to our taxation system that finally passed</p>
<p> into law only a few weeks ago and will come into effect on the 1st</p>
<p> of July next year.</p>
<p>Not only do those reforms sweep away a very old-fashioned and rickety,</p>
<p> indirect tax system and replace it with a simpler more comprehensive</p>
<p> indirect tax system that will be of great benefit to our exporters</p>
<p> and will also provide significant benefits in reduced business costs</p>
<p> to all of our domestic business operations. And it will also provide</p>
<p> very significant reductions in personal income tax for middle income</p>
<p> earners. And will also importantly provide to the States of Australia</p>
<p> which, under our federal system, have the ongoing responsibility for</p>
<p> police services, public hospitals, government schools, roads and all</p>
<p> of those social provisions that are so very important. It will provide</p>
<p> to the States of Australia a guaranteed source of revenue to fund</p>
<p> those obligations and those responsibilities.</p>
<p>But I think one of the more important things about the achievement</p>
<p> of that tax reform is that it has given to the Australian community</p>
<p> and to the political process in our country a belief that if you persevere</p>
<p> long enough you can achieve fundamental reform. There is sometimes</p>
<p> in all of our societies a sense in which the system is so burdened</p>
<p> with complexity and so burdened with checks and balances desirable</p>
<p> as those checks and balances may be. But there is so many of them</p>
<p> and they proliferate so much that you can't really ever achieve fundamental</p>
<p> reform. And I think the faith of the Australian people in the capacity</p>
<p> of our political process to achieve that fundamental reform has been</p>
<p> of enormous value.</p>
<p>The strongest message, of course, that comes out of Australia over</p>
<p> the last 12 months is the fact that we were able to stare down the</p>
<p> Asian economic collapse. And if I can encapsulate what I want to say</p>
<p> to you today, if I want to convey to you a metaphor for what Australia</p>
<p> has been able to achieve and what Australia represents at the moment</p>
<p> it is the fact that we were able to do that. And I don't mind saying</p>
<p> to you that it surprised just about everybody, myself included. A</p>
<p> couple of years ago if you'd have said to me: will we be able to survive</p>
<p> the Asian downturn? I'd have said regretfully I think it will adversely</p>
<p> affect us at some time before the end of 1998. Now, of course, it</p>
<p> didn't and there are a number of reasons for it. A lot of the reasons</p>
<p> are to be found in the reforms that I have mentioned because today's</p>
<p> strength is always the product of yesterday's reforms. As tomorrow's</p>
<p> strengths will be the product of today's reforms.</p>
<p>A lot of the credit for the successful management of our economy over</p>
<p> the last year ought to be given to the very skillful management of</p>
<p> our exchange rate policy by the Reserve Bank of Australia which I</p>
<p> think has done an outstanding job and we have seen during this period</p>
<p> of time the authorities in Australia working together in a very efficient</p>
<p> and a very effective way. And it bodes well in my mind for the future</p>
<p> conduct of public policy in so many of these areas.</p>
<p>But in public life and in policy making you never really get to the</p>
<p> top of the hill. You scale a hill and then there's another one on</p>
<p> the horizon and there are other challenges to be undertaken. And the</p>
<p> purpose of this conference, and certainly the purpose of my remarks,</p>
<p> is not to in any sense dwell upon or luxuriate in what may have been</p>
<p> achieved over the last few years but rather to tell all of you that</p>
<p> our process of reform has by no means been finished. And having completed</p>
<p> the, what I might call, the retail side of our taxation reform process,</p>
<p> of having got our goods and services tax established, the next big</p>
<p> thing, and this is of very particular relevance to the central goal</p>
<p> of this conference, is to complete the process of business taxation</p>
<p> reform.</p>
<p>Now, there are many reasons that make Australia particularly but not</p>
<p> only Sydney, of course, an attractive location as a world financial</p>
<p> centre. Undoubtedly our economic strength is one of those. Undoubtedly</p>
<p> our marvelous way of life, the congeniality of Australia as a place</p>
<p> in which to live and to raise children. The great social and political</p>
<p> stability, the fact that we speak the English language, the fact that</p>
<p> we have a culturally diverse and linguistically skilled population</p>
<p> who have deep and enduring family and people-to-people links with</p>
<p> the nations of South East Asia. There are some 300,000 - 400,000 people</p>
<p> living in Sydney, for example, who are ethnically Chinese from various</p>
<p> parts of South East Asia as well as from mainland China to give you</p>
<p> an example of the diversity of the Australian community, particularly</p>
<p> of the Sydney community.</p>
<p>We, of course, have a very clear set of rules relating to corporate</p>
<p> governance. We have a very well regulated and prudentially supervised</p>
<p> banking system. We have also, as Australians, had one characteristic</p>
<p> and Richard talked earlier about the affinity that exists between</p>
<p> the peoples of the United States and the people of Australia. And</p>
<p> one of the things that we have in common with our American friends</p>
<p> is that we have a fascination for new technology. And all of my life</p>
<p> I have been conscious of the fact that if something new comes on the</p>
<p> market, some new product, Australians literally devour it. And that</p>
<p> is why we have a mobile phone and internet take-up which is second</p>
<p> only to that of the United States and in some aspects of communications</p>
<p> reform in advance of that of the United States. And this is tremendously</p>
<p> important to the sort of exercise that we are engaged in today, it</p>
<p> is tremendously important to the capacity of our country to provide</p>
<p> the people, to provide the infrastructure and the wherewithal to be</p>
<p> an effective world financial centre.</p>
<p>Now, all of those things are very attractive, they are very nice and</p>
<p> they'll get a tick but, of course, they are only part of the story.</p>
<p> And I recognise that in the end the competitiveness of our business</p>
<p> taxation system will count for a great deal more than some of those</p>
<p> other things attractive though they are. And if you can get all of</p>
<p> them together and if you can tick every single one of the boxes then</p>
<p> you really do have a very compelling case. And that is why I want</p>
<p> to tell you today in very unambiguous terms that I know that what</p>
<p> we do in relation to the business tax reform process will be the ultimate</p>
<p> determinant of how successful we are in the years immediately ahead</p>
<p> of us in achieving the goal that so many of us have in common.</p>
<p>Now, a number of the changes we have already put through the national</p>
<p> Parliament including the abolition of stamp duty on share transactions</p>
<p> and the removal of the Financial Institutions Duty make a contribution</p>
<p> towards removing some of the impediments. But the recommendations</p>
<p> to come out of the Ralph review which we will have in our hands by</p>
<p> the end of this month and how the Government reacts to those recommendations</p>
<p> will be of crucial significance and importance in determining whether</p>
<p> or not we realise those goals.</p>
<p>I know that in a globalised world you really have to have a tax system</p>
<p> that, as far as possible, makes the choice between an investment in</p>
<p> the United States and an investment in Australia neutral. And while</p>
<p> that choice is not neutral and whilst it is tilted in favour of the</p>
<p> United States whether by operation of our capital gains tax or by</p>
<p> operation of our tax laws to deny to those funds and those other accumulations</p>
<p> of capital in this country that have a tax free status a similar treatment</p>
<p> in Australia then that is going to act as a disincentive. And that</p>
<p> is why I recognise as Prime Minister that how we react to the recommendations</p>
<p> in respect of capital gains tax in particular will determine how much</p>
<p> more attractive we can make investment in Australia.</p>
<p>There is little doubt in my mind that our present capital gains tax</p>
<p> does act as a disincentive in a number of areas and if we are really</p>
<p> serious about the exercise on which we are all collectively embarked</p>
<p> today then some fundamental changes will need to be made in that area.</p>
<p> And they will bulk very large in the considerations that we have.</p>
<p> I am particularly conscious of the many representations that have</p>
<p> been made to me over the years about the absence of a more realistic</p>
<p> capital gains tax approach to script exchanges. I am aware of the</p>
<p> break that is seen in the existing capital gains tax regime on the</p>
<p> accumulation of venture capital. And I am conscious of a number of</p>
<p> the other disincentives that that tax represents in relation to decisions</p>
<p> that are being made as to whether an investment should occur in Australia</p>
<p> or an investment should be retained in the United States or an investment</p>
<p> that is made elsewhere.</p>
<p>So putting all of that together, ladies and gentlemen, I know that</p>
<p> if we are to realise the goal that we want and it's not an end that</p>
<p> we pursue as an end in itself, there is no particular virtue in its</p>
<p> own right of being able to say that Sydney has become a world financial</p>
<p> centre or Australia has become a world financial centre. But if you</p>
<p> have responsibility for governing a nation which has achieved a great</p>
<p> deal and has demonstrated its economic strength and its economic capacity</p>
<p> but is nonetheless a nation which needs to build on successful industries</p>
<p> in areas such as mining and manufacturing and primary production.</p>
<p> By adding value to those industries, particularly in the service sector,</p>
<p> where you believe we have a capacity to perform effectively in one</p>
<p> of the areas where you most naturally turn your attention is the area</p>
<p> of financial services.</p>
<p>And if we can add to the undoubted generic strengths that I described</p>
<p> earlier in my speech a modernisation of the Australian taxation system</p>
<p> that removes some of the inhibitions that now exist, that recognises</p>
<p> that in a global economy with seamless transfers of capital matched</p>
<p> increasingly by seamless transfers of jobs that unless you are able</p>
<p> to have a taxation regime that removes the impediments between this</p>
<p> or that location you have no capacity at all to build upon the undoubted</p>
<p> generic strengths that I and other speakers have been canvassing.</p>
<p>So the central message I wanted to convey to you at this luncheon,</p>
<p> ladies and gentlemen, is that, yes, over the last few years Australia</p>
<p> has been a country of growing economic strengths and self-confidence.</p>
<p> A country, I believe, which has received an enormous national psychological</p>
<p> boost out of the fact that we were able to do something most of us</p>
<p> thought we couldn't do and that is avoid significant impact from the</p>
<p> Asian economic downturn. And nations, in many respects, are like individuals</p>
<p> and like communities. We are governed on some occasions by reason,</p>
<p> we are governed on some occasions by predictability, we are governed</p>
<p> on some occasions by instinct and we also enjoy tremendous fillips</p>
<p> and tremendous boosts from a psychological point of view.</p>
<p>And I can't overestimate to you today the boost that being able to</p>
<p> beat that Asian downturn has represented in the Australian psyche.</p>
<p> And wherever you go in our country you find that sense of excited</p>
<p> achievement that we have been able to do something that we really</p>
<p> deep down didn't think we were going to be able to do. We are not</p>
<p> totally sure that we have every explanation as to why we have done</p>
<p> it. I mean, confident government ministers, of course, list instinctively</p>
<p> and proudly the immediate contributions that their portfolios have</p>
<p> made to that magnificent achievement and they are encouraged by their</p>
<p> Prime Minister to do so.</p>
<p>But there are a lot of things to do with our national make-up that</p>
<p> have produced it but it has meant that we have a sense of ourselves</p>
<p> and a sense of what we have been able to achieve that I haven't found</p>
<p> in our country for a very long period of time. And for that reason,</p>
<p> as well as many others, now is a time for us to not, out of any sense</p>
<p> of complacency or any sense of smugness to say, well gee, isn't that</p>
<p> terrific let's enjoy ourselves for the next few years. There is no</p>
<p> sense of that in Australia. There is a sense that we have become a</p>
<p> 'can do' country. There is a sense that we have challenges that we</p>
<p> tackle in a practical way.</p>
<p>We have a great base for being a world financial centre and I have</p>
<p> described that several times but we also, I think, now maturely recognise</p>
<p> that if we are to go further we have to make some very specific changes</p>
<p> to provide some very specific incentives particularly in a number</p>
<p> of taxation areas. And this conference is about communicating Australia's</p>
<p> strengths. It's about absorbing the concerns that potential investors</p>
<p> may have, it is about, of course, demonstrating a common commitment</p>
<p> we all have to a free enterprise system and it is about, of course,</p>
<p> demonstrating just how much we all live in a global financial environment.</p>
<p>Can I conclude my remarks by returning to a theme that Richard Holbrooke</p>
<p> touched upon in his very gracious introduction and that is the affinity</p>
<p> which exists between our two societies. In any close relationship</p>
<p> we will have our differences and there has been some well publicised</p>
<p> differences in recent days regarding one of our fine export products.</p>
<p> And it, of course, is a source of some irritation to our country that</p>
<p> that should have occurred and we don't in any way resile from or apologise</p>
<p> from the fierce criticism that we have tended to the American administration</p>
<p> regarding that.</p>
<p>But Richard spoke very warmly and very appropriately of the values</p>
<p> and attitudes that bind us together and those values, of course, are</p>
<p> infinitely more enduring than those things that tend on occasions</p>
<p> to cause disputation and to push us apart. And I am immensely proud</p>
<p> as the Prime Minister of Australia to be able to speak at this luncheon</p>
<p> today to talk a little of what my country has achieved and to be able</p>
<p> very genuinely to say that I speak for both sides of Australian politics</p>
<p> in saying that we share the sense of that national achievement. That</p>
<p> we are working together overseas to achieve something more for Australia.</p>
<p> I think by dint of what it has particularly achieved in the Australian</p>
<p> economic firmament there is an emphasis quite properly on the city</p>
<p> of Sydney but it is very much as a representative of the entire Australian</p>
<p> nation.</p>
<p>And on that note can I conclude by saying to all of you that Richard's</p>
<p> reference to the Olympic Games was very apposite. Can I say that the</p>
<p> preparations for the Olympic Games are in great shape and full credit</p>
<p> to SOCOG. I think Sydney will do those games on its ear. I think they</p>
<p> will be one of the most remembered Olympic Games of the modern era.</p>
<p> I think Sydney is superbly suited and superbly prepared. The facilities</p>
<p> are very well advanced.</p>
<p>I invite all of our American friends to visit our country for the</p>
<p> Games and it will be for a sports loving and sports crazy nation an</p>
<p> absolute gourmet delight of sporting celebration and a great way for</p>
<p> a proud and committed nation to welcome the world and to showcase</p>
<p> its remarkable way of life and its remarkable sense of national purpose.</p>
<p> Thank you.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
