<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10462</transcript-id>
    <title>Northern Territory Election</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>31/08/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010462.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I congratulate Shane Stone and the Country Liberal Party for their rousing victory in the Northern Territory election.</p>
<p>It is a personal triumph for the Chief Minister who has now an emphatic mandate in his own right.</p>
<p>The CLP's success is a measure of their goodwill with the Territory community and is overwhelmingly due to the good government that the CLP has delivered since the Territory achieved self-government.</p>
<p>My Government remains committed to statehood for the Northern Territory. I look forward to working with Shane Stone in achieving this shared goal.</p>
<p>The result does carry some national messages.</p>
<p>The first of these is the complete contempt which Territorians have dismissed Kim Beazley's tawdry attempt to smear Shane Stone with a false charge of racism. Not only did the CLP increase its majority, but the CLP vote rose markedly in many remote areas with heavy enrolments of Aboriginal Australians.</p>
<p>Those Australians are more interested in jobs and a secure future than irresponsible and dishonest political labels.</p>
<p>Furthermore, the result is all the more encouraging because of Shane Stone's strong endorsement of my Government's 10-point plan to respond to the Wik decision.</p>
<p>As the Chief Minister remarked today, the present Native Title Act works for no one. The Government's legislative response to be introduced this week will provide a balanced and fair outcome for all Australians.</p>
<p>31 August 1997</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
