<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5435</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS AT THE OPENING OF THE WARRNAMBOOL JOB CENTRE</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/09/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005435.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PROME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA FRIDAY 12 SEPTEMBER 1980<br />
ADDRESS AT THE OPENING OF THE WARRNAMiBOOL JOB CENTRE<br />
Thank you for the invitation to be with you today. My pleasure<br />
in being here is two-fold. In the first place, it is always<br />
good to be in Wannon and Wqarrnambool. Secondly, I am delighted<br />
that the reason for my being here is to open this job centre,<br />
for it represents further evidence of the important work being<br />
done by the Commionwealth Employment Service.<br />
This Centre is one of a new breed of offices equipped to meet<br />
the employment needs of employers and job seekers in the<br />
It is spacious, attractive and functional, designed to provide<br />
the best possible environment for all those who use the<br />
Commonwealth Employment Service.<br />
The Warrnambool Job Centre is part of an ongoing modernisation<br />
programme for the a programme which was approved by the<br />
Commonwealth Government in 1977 following the Norgard Report.<br />
We are now in the third year of our modernisation and improvement<br />
plan. And in the past three years, more than 120 offices have<br />
been equipped to meet new standards. Some of the offices are new;<br />
others, like this one, have been moved to an improved location.<br />
Some have been upgraded on an existing site.<br />
In this financial year, it is proposed to open another 12 new<br />
off ices and ' to relocate another 40. To meet all the objectives<br />
of the the Government has allocated more than $ 82 million<br />
in this financial year. But the improved facilities we see here<br />
are only part of the Government's commitment to upgrading the<br />
C. E. S. into a modern manpower organisation.<br />
An equally important part is that we are providing better, faster<br />
and more effective service to employers and job seekers alike,<br />
through, improved management structures and systems, an increase<br />
in staffing and a high priority for staff training, innovations<br />
in methods such as " job self service", and, extensive promotional<br />
exercises. This is even more important when one considers that today the<br />
Commonwealth Employment Service is a far flung operation with<br />
around 400 outlets, not only in the metropolitan centres, but<br />
also in some of the most isolated areas in Australia. It is the<br />
Government's belief that these improvements will add immeasurably<br />
to the success of the operations of the C. E. S. .2 </p>
<p>* Figures establish the role of the C. E. S. as a provider of<br />
important s ervices. In 1978/ 79, it placed more than 507,000<br />
job seekers throughout Australia,'. and last financial year this<br />
increased to almost 530,000. Indeed, the C. E. S. now fills<br />
per cent of vacancies notified. But it is much more than an<br />
agency that finds jobs and people to fill them. It is also a<br />
vital cog in the delivery of the Government's manpower programmes<br />
which are readily available to those who need them.<br />
These programmes have an essential role to play in Australia's<br />
future both at a local and national level. Their aim is to<br />
provide Australians, especially young Australians, with the<br />
skills needed to secure employment; and to make sure that there<br />
are enough people with the right skills available to meet the<br />
industrial expansion and development that is now underway in<br />
Australia. For there is no doubt that, throughout the country,<br />
we can see signs of a new appreciation of Australia's potential.<br />
And the immense development programme which is already underway<br />
is testimony to the confidence that domestic and overseas<br />
investors have in Australia and its future. But the realisation<br />
of our vast resource potential will require a skilled labour<br />
force; and our manpower programmes are a direct investment by the<br />
Government in providing these skills, especially for young<br />
Australians. The Government is determined that its initiatives should assist<br />
as many Australians as possible to play a significant and<br />
rewarding role in Australia's future. As proof of our increased<br />
commitment, in the current financial year, we have provided over<br />
$ 138 million for our manpower, training and youth support programmesan<br />
increase of 22 per cent on last year's expenditure. This brings<br />
to over $ 600 million the amount spent on these schemes sinca we<br />
came to office.<br />
The scope of the programmes is indicated by the fact that over<br />
570,000 Australians have been assisted by them in the past four<br />
years; and, during this financial year, 236,000 are expected to<br />
be assisted. They are designed to meet a variety of needs, from<br />
those of individuals and special groups, to those directed to<br />
industry as a whole. " Craft", the Commonwealth rebate for<br />
apprentices' full-time training, has boosted the intake and<br />
retention of apprentices.<br />
This year expenditure under this programme will be increased<br />
through a number of special trade training schemes designed to<br />
train skilled labour for areas where the need now exists; and to<br />
meet the demands of Australia's future industrial development.<br />
For levels of skill other than those regarded as trades, the<br />
tNEAT scheme enables unemployed people to train in occupations<br />
where there is an unsatisfied demand. " NEAT" also provides<br />
specific training assistance to disadvantaged groups such as<br />
aboriginals and-the handicapped.<br />
The national Aboriginal employment strategy has been successful<br />
and next year, in support of the international year of the<br />
disabled person, a national employment strategy for the handicapped<br />
will be mounted. Many employers already train or want to train<br />
their present workforce. </p>
<p>The " training in industry and comxnerce. programme" aids and<br />
stimulates the development of training programmes through all<br />
sections of industry and commerce including small business.<br />
The Government is also concerned that, because of a lack of<br />
qualifications or experience, a significant number of people<br />
face considerable problems in gaining employment. As a result,<br />
the " Special Youth Employment Programme" provides assistance for<br />
employers to take on young people and give them the experience<br />
needed to compete more successfully on the open labour market.<br />
Other young people are hampered by illiteracy and numeracy<br />
problems and have been helped by courses funded under the<br />
" Employment Programme for Unemployed Youth".<br />
Many unemployed young people have taken advantage of the community<br />
Youth Support Scheme which enables young people to maintain an<br />
orientation towards work in an environment of community service<br />
which is helpful and supportive. The Government has also recognised<br />
the importance of a comprehensive approach to the particular needs<br />
of young people. This is the essence of the school-to-work<br />
transition programme which we announced last year and to which we<br />
have committed $ 150 million for the next five years.<br />
The Scheme recognises the importance of appropriate education,<br />
training and work experience in enabling young people to make a<br />
smooth transition from school to work. A key element in the<br />
programme is to make sure young people receive occupational<br />
information and guidance while they are still at school. And in<br />
1980/ 81, the Government will provide over $ 1.6 million on careers<br />
information; and careers libraries will be supplied to all<br />
secondary schools throughout Australia together with special<br />
careers information for migrants. And this new Job Centre, with<br />
its Work Information Centre and its improved facilities for<br />
counselling, will add to the information and opportunities available<br />
to young people and school leavers in this area.<br />
Overriding the importance of these initiatives is the Government's<br />
determination, through its economic strategy, to provide the<br />
foundation for long term and continuing improvement in employment.<br />
This strategy is already working. In July 1980 there were 212,000<br />
more people in work than was the case 12 months ago. The Government's<br />
policy will continue to stress the encouragement of productive<br />
employment through, building the fundamental strength of the economy,<br />
assistance under the transition from school-to-work programme,<br />
and further assistance to those in need through the Government's<br />
manpower and training schemes.<br />
But it cannot be overstated that no long term benefit can be<br />
achieved by those who pretend that " make-work" schemes are the<br />
answer to the unemployment problem. They have failed in Australia<br />
before; and they have failed overseas. They add to the size of<br />
Government and to the size of deficits and both of these have been<br />
shown to damage the economy and jeopardise employment opportunity.<br />
Indeed, they have been the source of higher inflation from which<br />
many of our unemployment problems originate.<br />
But it cannot be st~ cessed too strongly that the<br />
Government's initiatives need the support of the whole community<br />
and, in particular, the union movement, employers and the education<br />
system. </p>
<p>The union movement in Australia has a poor record of concern<br />
for the unemployed. There is no-one in our community so<br />
forgotten by the union movement as the person without a job.<br />
In the present campaign seeking higher and higher wages and<br />
fewer hours at work, the union leadership is making the prospects<br />
of employment for those out of a job even more remote.<br />
The selfish pursuit of excessive benefits for those who have jobs<br />
contributes nothing to the problems faced by those who are out of<br />
employment. . Indeed, the unemployed are forgotten<br />
and unrepresented by militant union leadership, Employers<br />
too must be encouraged to respond to the Government's initiatives,<br />
by offering vacancies and training opportunities to young<br />
Australians, by making the best use of their talents, and encouraging<br />
them through their difficulties, and, in these ways, assisting<br />
young people to play their role in Australia's development.<br />
In other words, Government initiatives need to be supported by<br />
constructive attitudes of people and groups within the community<br />
and this is especially so of the education system itself. Too<br />
many young people have been disappointed and disadvantaged by<br />
Australia's education system.-For too long, in periods of high<br />
employment, the education system existed in something of a vacuum.<br />
Those who were no good at school left and got a job; those who<br />
were good at school stayed on and got a better job. In this way,<br />
education was independent of the workforce. Rarely was it placed<br />
under a microscope. NOW, many people in the community are doing<br />
just this. And, in many instances, what they see they do not like.<br />
Today, more<br />
money is being spent on education then ever before. Pupil/ teacher<br />
ratios are lower than they have ever been. Yet the value, . the<br />
direction and competence of the education system is being increasinglyquestioned.<br />
And the questioning is coming from all sections of<br />
the community. Students are themselves sensing the irrelevance of<br />
much that is happening in education, with the result that a<br />
declining proportion are completing high school. For too long<br />
there has been too much emphasis on academic structures; too little<br />
emphasis on practical skills; too much disregard for the attitudes<br />
and values that will enable young people to play a productive role<br />
in the adult world. In other instances, courses lack content,<br />
discipline and evaluation.<br />
Times are changing. A new and more demanding reality confronts<br />
young people today. Education has an obligation to prepare young'<br />
people for that reality. If it does that successfully, it will<br />
contribute significantly to the initiatives that are needed from<br />
all sections of the community to equip young people for the future<br />
role they are to play in Australia's future. The Government's<br />
manpower and training initiatives are designed to see that thisrole<br />
is productive and rewarding for all young Australians. And<br />
this new Centre, along with many of its kind throughout Australia,<br />
will improve the services and the opportuniti es that are available<br />
for job seekers. of course, ultimately, the effectiveness of the<br />
C. E. S. as a national manpower agency depends upon its support at<br />
local level. </p>
<p>-However well located and appointed the Job Centre may be, what<br />
' it needs most is the confidence of its local community, employers<br />
and job seekers, schools, civic leaders, State and local government<br />
agencies and community groups. I know that the 11arrnambool office<br />
enjoys this support and its success in tChe past is evidence of<br />
this. For example, the $ 1,000 rebate payable under the Craft<br />
Scheme for training of additional apprentices has been well accepted<br />
by Warrnambool firms, leading to 110 employers in this area<br />
increasing their intake of apprentices during; 1979/ 80. In addition,<br />
the Special Youth Employment Training Programme has been a*<br />
-contributing factor in assisting young people to improve their<br />
skills.<br />
And in the past 12 months, over 250 young people in this area<br />
have received employment skills by training through this scheme.<br />
Among the innovations offered to this Job Centre is the concept<br />
of " job self service". The concept is quite simple. Job vacancies<br />
are posted on the self service boards after they are notified to<br />
the Warrnambool Job Centre by local employers. Jobs notified to<br />
C. B. S. officers for surrounding districts, such as Hamilton,<br />
Portland and other western district centres, are also listed on<br />
the boards along with selected vacancies from the Melbourne<br />
metropolitan area.<br />
This concept is designed to bring suitable job seekers and employers<br />
together as quickly and as effectively as possible. It allows<br />
individuals to check the full range of vacancies available at any<br />
one time. When a person feels suitably qualified for a listed<br />
job, the C. E. S. officer can make the appropriate arrangements for<br />
an interview with the employer. Through job self service and its<br />
placement action, the Warrnambool Job Centre found employmnent for<br />
1,750 job seekers in Warrnambool and surrounding areas in the<br />
past 12 months. And the response by major employers in the area<br />
to the facilities provided by the Job Centre is encouraging and<br />
commendable. I point out, in passing, that the Warrnambool<br />
Regional Office of the Department of Social Security, which I<br />
opened in 1971, will now be co-located with this C. B. S. job centre.<br />
This will enable the Social Security office to beccme fully<br />
decentralised, administering a full range of benefits, pensions<br />
and allowances for those who are eligible in the electorates of<br />
Wannon, Warrnambool and western province. Both these facilities<br />
are designed to increase the efficiency with which necessary<br />
government services are administered. And this efficiency is<br />
greatly increased by the localised and personal service that these<br />
offices will now be able to provide.<br />
I have no doubt that the Job Centre, like many of its kind<br />
throughout Australia, will assist significantly those in our<br />
community who are actively seeking employment. These facilities<br />
demonstrate the Government's determination to play its part.<br />
I am sure that this new facility will be a valuable asset for<br />
the people and the industry in this district. And I have much<br />
pleasure in declaring it officially open.<br />
000----</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
