<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11682</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER            THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP            ADDRESS AT CIVIC RECEPTION            JOONDALUP, WESTERN AUSTRALIA</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/02/2000</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE..........................................................................................</p>
<p>Well thank you very much Mal. To Senator Alan Eggleston, to my State,</p>
<p> ministerial and parliamentary colleagues, to the Mayor John Bombak, and</p>
<p> to all the councillors, and all the other community leaders and guests.</p>
<p> It is a delight to be in what I understand to be one week the fastest</p>
<p> growing area of Australia, the next week just the second fastest growing</p>
<p> area. Competing with I understand the Albert Shire in Queensland for that</p>
<p> honour, and therefore being a part of Australia that has particular challenges,</p>
<p> particular needs, but also a real contribution to make in the tradition</p>
<p> of many of they pioneering elements of Western Australian history.</p>
<p>But before I say something specific about this part of Australia, and</p>
<p> something specific about the electorate of Moore, can I take the opportunity</p>
<p> of addressing a few remarks to the fact that right at the moment Major</p>
<p> General Peter Cosgrove is returning home to Australia from his tour of</p>
<p> duty as the commander of the INTERFET force in East Timor. And I know</p>
<p> that I speak for every Australian in expressing my admiration for the</p>
<p> tremendous job he did, and the tremendous job done by the men and women</p>
<p> of the Australian Defence Force in East Timor. Of all the things that</p>
<p> I have done in the time that I have been Prime Minister none has quite</p>
<p> imbued me with a sense of deep and almost limitless pride in this country</p>
<p> and its people than the experience I had in saying farewell to those men</p>
<p> and women in Townsville and Darwin, and then visiting them in East Timor.</p>
<p> And I want on behalf of every Australian to say thank you for a job well</p>
<p> done, to express our gratitude that we lost no people in battle although</p>
<p> unfortunately one died in hospital of non-combat reasons. But it has been</p>
<p> a remarkable operation and one that has brought tremendous credit to this</p>
<p> country, and particular credit to General Cosgrove. It was an occasion</p>
<p> when Australia stood up for the right thing. We have a long and proud</p>
<p> military tradition but it's not a belligerent or triumphal military</p>
<p> tradition. It's a military tradition through which we are prepared</p>
<p> to defend people who are being oppressed and we're prepared as a</p>
<p> nation to do the right thing. And I think those men and women did us proud</p>
<p> and they will in an appropriate way be openly and publicly welcomed home</p>
<p> at a parade in Sydney and a parade in Townsville to be organised in April.</p>
<p> And there'll also be a special function in Parliament House on the</p>
<p> 7th of March.</p>
<p>And can I also say that that expression of gratitude is extended with</p>
<p> equal sincerity to the men and women of the Australian Federal Police.</p>
<p> I had the opportunity of meeting most of the Australian Federal Police</p>
<p> who'd served in East Timor at a reception in Parliament House only</p>
<p> ten days ago. And many of those men and women experienced some of the</p>
<p> most dangerous days of the events that unfolded in East Timor and they</p>
<p> are equally deserving of our gratitude and praise, and they share with</p>
<p> the men and women of our defence force the distinction of having represented</p>
<p> this country so effectively and so well over past months.</p>
<p>Can I say that it's a great delight to be in Mal Washer's electorate</p>
<p> because Mal is a very enthusiastic effective representative of the people</p>
<p> of the division of Moore. He's only been a member since the 1998</p>
<p> election, but in the time that he's been in federal parliament, in</p>
<p> a very quiet but effective way, he's brought a common sense understanding</p>
<p> of the challenges and the experiences of a rapidly growing outer metropolitan</p>
<p> area of Australia. I'm often asked what is the best thing about being</p>
<p> Prime Minister of Australia. And I unhesitatingly say that the best thing</p>
<p> about being Prime Minister of Australia is that one has the opportunity</p>
<p> on an almost daily basis of meeting a new and different group of Australians</p>
<p> as you travel around the country. Yesterday morning as I reminded myself</p>
<p> on the way out I went for an early morning walk in Canberra, we then had</p>
<p> a Cabinet meeting in Nowra on the South Coast of New South Wales, I then</p>
<p> went back to Sydney in the evening for dinner, and I came over to Western</p>
<p> Australia this morning and I'm spending two-and-a-half days here.</p>
<p> And that's an opportunity to meet different groups of people in a</p>
<p> short space of time in different parts of Australia. And there are different</p>
<p> areas that have different challenges. We talk a lot now quite properly</p>
<p> about some of the challenges facing people in remote rural communities</p>
<p>  the bush as we lovingly call it. And the bush properly so called</p>
<p> I suppose does encapsulate our idea of people who live in small communities,</p>
<p> many of whom are suffering the ravages of low commodity prices, and drought</p>
<p> and all the difficulty that afflicts those communities.</p>
<p>But the outer metropolitan areas of Australia, although the scale and</p>
<p> the dimension of the challenge is different nonetheless have particular</p>
<p> needs and particular challenges. The need to provide infrastructure services,</p>
<p> the need to provide additional police and hospital services. I was talking</p>
<p> to the, I think the correct expression is district inspector, well that's</p>
<p> what I would have called it when I was at public school in Sydney all</p>
<p> those years ago, and she was describing to me the challenges of some 43</p>
<p> or 44 schools, primary schools in this area which has a young population.</p>
<p> And I know how important the provision of education is for a growing community</p>
<p> and that's one of the reasons why at a federal level we have endeavoured</p>
<p> to provide the optimum level of choice for people in education. Education</p>
<p> is very important to every Australian family. Providing people with the</p>
<p> choice whether they send their children to government schools or non-government</p>
<p> schools, and increasingly to provide people with choice within the government</p>
<p> sector. As I drove past the large number of new housing estates it's</p>
<p> a reminder to me of the importance I suppose of keeping interest rates</p>
<p> at a tolerable level. There'd be a lot of new home buyers in the</p>
<p> electorate of Moore wouldn't there Dr Washer? And I'm constantly</p>
<p> reminded of Mal just how important it is to keep interest rates as low</p>
<p> as possible. And I'm very very pleased to say that one of the things</p>
<p> that we have been able to do, and I don't want to make this a very</p>
<p> political address, but I can't you know, resist one tiny commercial,</p>
<p> one tiny plug. One of the things that we have been able to do very effectively</p>
<p> is to get interest rates down from stratospheric levels that they were</p>
<p> at some 8 or 10 years ago. And that is tremendously important to people</p>
<p> who are paying off a home.</p>
<p>But I think the most important thing about this gathering is that it</p>
<p> reminds me very much of something that I've spoken of a lot since</p>
<p> I've been Prime Minister, and that is the notion of a social coalition.</p>
<p> We have a lot of debate in our society about who does what best. There</p>
<p> are some people who believe that everything should be done by the government,</p>
<p> and there are some people who believe that nothing should be done by the</p>
<p> government. Some people think that once the government starts to do something,</p>
<p> whether it's the federal government, the State government or the</p>
<p> local government, then problems start. Now of course neither of those</p>
<p> propositions is correct. It is ludicrous to think that the government</p>
<p> can do everything because governments are not built and made, and of their</p>
<p> character they're not very good at for example running businesses.</p>
<p> They're not very good at doing things that you need an entrepreneurial</p>
<p> or business spirit to succeed at. But on the other hand governments have</p>
<p> very important functions. Unless you have government support for basic</p>
<p> services such as health and education and police, and defence, then of</p>
<p> course you can't have a civil and you can't have a humane, and</p>
<p> you can't have a society that we want to live. And what I have tried</p>
<p> to do in so many areas of my responsibilities as Prime Minister is to</p>
<p> promote the idea of a social coalition. And that very simply says that</p>
<p> when we have a problem in our community we should try and tackle that</p>
<p> problem by bringing together the resources of the government, the resources</p>
<p> of the business community, the energy and commitment of individuals, and</p>
<p> also the resources and commitment of our great welfare organisations and</p>
<p> volunteer groups within our society. And those groups all coalescing and</p>
<p> each contributing what they do best you can hope to solve our problems.</p>
<p> And it's not a question of saying well we'll leave all of that</p>
<p> to the government, or all of that to the business community, or all of</p>
<p> that to a local welfare group. And I've tried in a number of areas</p>
<p> to enlist not only the compassion and the coal face experience of welfare</p>
<p> organisations, but also their contribution to the development of policy.</p>
<p> I reminded myself when I came here this afternoon that the chairman of</p>
<p> two organisations that are making a major input to social policy under</p>
<p> my government are Salvation Army officers. One of them Major Brian Watters</p>
<p> is the chairman of my national council on drug issues, and the other is</p>
<p> Captain David Eldridge of Victoria who is the chairman of the Youth Homelessness</p>
<p> Task Force that I established within four weeks of becoming Prime Minister</p>
<p> in 1996.</p>
<p>I not only seek the human contribution of those great organisations who</p>
<p> do so much in our society, but I also seek their policy contribution because</p>
<p> the coal face experience they have of dealing with human sadness, of human</p>
<p> challenge and of human despair is not only relevant in terms of responding</p>
<p> to the needs of individuals, but it's also very relevant in helping</p>
<p> to develop government policy. We went through a period of time some years</p>
<p> ago when everybody thought you could solve every problem by turning to</p>
<p> the government. Then we had a bit of a reaction to that and people thought</p>
<p> you could solve every problem by the government getting out of everything.</p>
<p> But I think we've now sort of got a happy medium where people see</p>
<p> that there is a limited but strategic role for governments within our</p>
<p> community. And I see it represented here today. I see all the elements</p>
<p> of that social coalition.</p>
<p>Our country at the present time is experiencing at a national level a</p>
<p> great deal of prosperity. We are very strong economically, we have lower</p>
<p> inflation, lower interest rates, stronger budget positions, a stronger</p>
<p> international economic presence than we've had in many decades. But</p>
<p> that doesn't mean to say there aren't people in our community</p>
<p> that still need help. There are a lot. And there are people who aren't</p>
<p> sharing in the same way as others in that national prosperity. And it's</p>
<p> the obligation of a civilised decent society to see that that prosperity</p>
<p> is spread around as far as possible. And it's also the obligation</p>
<p> of a government at a national level and at a State level and at a local</p>
<p> level to press ahead with much needed reforms, sometimes to do it in the</p>
<p> face of fierce opposition and criticism. We at the moment are very strongly</p>
<p> committed to taxation reform, and we're not going to go back on that.</p>
<p> We're not going to weaken or tire in our commitment to that because</p>
<p> we think it is good in the end for the whole Australian community. We</p>
<p> may differ and argue as a community about this or that aspect. But at</p>
<p> the end of the day if you believe that a reform is going to make your</p>
<p> country stronger and better you'll persevere with that reform. And</p>
<p> that applies whether you're the Prime Minister, you're the premier,</p>
<p> or whether you're the mayor of the local municipality or city. And</p>
<p> that is very much how I see my responsibilities as Prime Minister. Australia</p>
<p> is a federation. We work best with a large geographical area having a</p>
<p> federal government, a State government and a local government. And each</p>
<p> of us has got to be accountable. We can't have a society where whenever</p>
<p> one area of government gets into trouble it tries to blame the other.</p>
<p> We've each got to be accountable. If we make a mess of something</p>
<p> at a federal level you're entitled to blame us. If you're State</p>
<p> government doesn't do something right at a State level you should</p>
<p> blame them, and the same thing applies at a local level. We each have</p>
<p> important responsibilities. And it's the best way of running a country</p>
<p> as geographically large as Australia. You can't make all the decisions</p>
<p> in Canberra. All the wisdom doesn't reside there any more than all</p>
<p> the wisdom in Western Australia resides in Perth, or all the wisdom in</p>
<p> New South Wales resides in Sydney. The founding fathers of this country</p>
<p> weren't wrong when they devised a federal system of government and</p>
<p> decided to keep the States and to keep the structure of a decentralised</p>
<p> nation when we federated in 1901. And that is why part of, I believe a</p>
<p> very important part, of my responsibilities as Prime Minister is to visit</p>
<p> the centres of municipal and local government, and to have an opportunity</p>
<p> like this to greet the leaders of the local community and through that</p>
<p> to get a better understanding of some of the challenges and some of the</p>
<p> problems of this community.</p>
<p>Can I simply conclude by saying it's great to be with Mal in his</p>
<p> electorate. I wish him well. I commend him very warmly to you as a very</p>
<p> very energetic and effective representative in the national parliament.</p>
<p> Can I thank all of you for the contribution that you are making towards</p>
<p> a better Australia. Each in your own way whether you're the mayor</p>
<p> of a city, whether you run the local Lions Club, the local State Emergency</p>
<p> Service, a local sporting organisation, a local church, or any other local</p>
<p> group, each of you in your own way is making a contribution to a more</p>
<p> civilised and more decent and happy, and more harmonious Australian community,</p>
<p> And that is what in the end of the day you want in this country. We want</p>
<p> a harmonious cohesive civilised society, and each of you are playing a</p>
<p> very major role here in Joondalup in building that goal and achieving</p>
<p> that end. Thank you. </p>
<p>[Ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
