<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4158</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER BASIC TREATY SIGNING CEREMONY</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/06/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004158.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH GIVEN BY PRIME MINISTER<br />
BASIC TREATY SIGNING CEREMONY 17 JUNE 1976<br />
This is an occasion born of goodwill and mutual interests.<br />
On Australia's part this Treaty is a recognition of the high<br />
respect we have for Japan and of the confidence we place in<br />
Japan for the future.<br />
The signing of this Basic Treaty of Friendship and Co-operation<br />
marks the deepening relationship between Australia and Japan.<br />
That relationship has developed over many years. This Treaty<br />
provides a firm basis for its future growth.<br />
In the past Australia and Japan have been linked largely by<br />
our commercial ties ties which are of great benefit to us<br />
both. The Treaty recognises the importance of our commercial<br />
interdependence, and our mutual interests in each being a<br />
reliable supplier to and market for the other. The Treaty is<br />
an indication of our mutual desire to secure and strengthen that<br />
relationship.<br />
Australia welcomes also the prospect of broadening our relationsbeyond<br />
the purely commercial to scientific, cultural, education<br />
and other fields.<br />
Two peoples whose futures are as closely linked as ours ought to<br />
have a deeper understanding of each other.<br />
Committed as we are to democratic institutions and to respect for<br />
each person, increased contact across the range of interests of<br />
our peoples can be expected to strengthen understanding of each other.<br />
As an indication of our desire to see these links develop we have<br />
recently established the Australia-Japan Foundation. We place<br />
great importance on its work. The Foundation will conduct<br />
programmes aimed at expanding the links between the people of<br />
Australia and Japan.<br />
The Treaty also commits both countries to facilitating travel<br />
between us.<br />
The Treaty does not imply, in any sense, an exclusive relationship.<br />
Both Japan and Australia have an increasingly important role to<br />
play in the future in the Asia-Pacific region. The greater<br />
understanding and the closer ties between the two countries should be<br />
used to benefit the countries of the Western Pacific and strengthen<br />
peace and security in the Asia-Pacific region. our relationship 2/ </p>
<p>-2-<br />
should develop for the common good of all the peoples of the<br />
region. It is with a sense of very great satisfaction, Mr. Prime Minister,<br />
that I am signing this Treaty on behalf of the Australian<br />
Government and the Australian people.<br />
ooOoo---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
