<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6297</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY PRIME MINISTER, MR RJL HAWKE, AT OPENING OF RICHMOND CAMPAIGN, MURWILLUMBAH, WEDNESDAY 25 JANUARY 1984</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/01/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006297.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY ii 1BARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY PRIMIE MINISTER, DIR. R. J. L. HAWKE,<br />
AT OPENING OF RICHMOND CAMPAIGN, MURWILLUMBAH-,<br />
WEDNESDAY 25 JANUARY 1984<br />
THE THREE IMPORTANT BY-ELECTIONS TO BE HELD ON<br />
18TH FEBRUARY FOR RICHMOND AND HUGHES IN NEW SOUTH WALES<br />
AND CORANGAMITE INI VICTORIA FALL ALMOST AT THE END OF<br />
THE FIRST YEAR OF THE LABOR GOVERNMENT THE PEOPLE OF<br />
AUSTFRALIA CHOSE SO CONVINCINGLY ON THE FIFTH OF MARCH 1983.<br />
WE WEL-COME TrHE OPPORTUNITY TO CONTRAST OUR PERFORMANCE<br />
IN OUR FIRST YEAR WITH THE RECORD OF OUR PREDECESSORS, IN ALL<br />
THEIR SE\ VEN WASTED, AND ULTIMATELY DISASTROUS, YEARS,<br />
WE WELCOME THE OPPORTUNIT-Y TO RESTATE OUR GOALS<br />
FOR AUSTRALIA IN THE YEARS AHEAD FOR THE TERM' OF THIS<br />
PARLIAMENT AND FAR BEYOND.<br />
AND WE WELCOME THE OPPORTUNITY WHICH THESE<br />
BY-ELECTIONS OFFER FOR A PUBLIC SCRUTINY AND A PUBLIC<br />
ACCOUNTING AS TO THE ROLE AND RECORD OF OUR POLITICAL<br />
OPPONENTS; BECAUSE IN OUR SYSTEM, THE STANDARDS AND.<br />
INTEGRITY OF OPPOSITION LEADERSHIP ARE A VITAL FACTOR IN<br />
ITS PROPER AND EFFECTIVE OPERATION.<br />
THESE BY-ELECTIONS OCCUR ALMOST A YEAR TO THE<br />
DAY THAT I HAD THE HONOUR TO DELIVER THE POLICY SPEECH<br />
ON BEHALF OF THE AUSTRALIAN LABOR PARTY AT THE SYDNEY<br />
OPERA HOUSE ON THE SIXTEENTH OF FEBRUARY 1983. </p>
<p>AND I SAY, WITHOUT QUALIFICATION, THAT NO<br />
GOVERNMENT IN THE HISTORY OF AUSTRALIA HAS MOVED SO<br />
PROMPTLY AND SO EFFECTIVELY TO HONOUR THE UNDERTAKINGS<br />
WE GAVE TO THE PEOPLE OF AUSTRALIA ONLY ONE YEAR AGO.<br />
IT HAS BEEN A CONTINUING PROCESS OF HONOURING<br />
OUR PROMISES, BOTH IN THE SPIRIT AND IN4 THE LETTER,<br />
IT HAS BEEN A DOUBLE PROCESS OF IMPLEMENTING<br />
SPECIFIC UNDERTAKINGS, ONE BY ONE, AND AT THE SAME TIME,<br />
WORKING STEADILY TOWARDS OUR GREATER GOALS AND WIDER<br />
VISION FOR AUSTRALIA AND AUSTRALIANS, WHEREVER THEY LIVE.<br />
AND ALTHOUGH OUR PR01POSALS WERE PUT FORWARD IN<br />
THE CONTEXT OF OUR FIRST PARLIAMENT A THREE-YEAR PROGRAMTHE<br />
OVERWHELMING MAJORITY NEARLY 90 PERCENT OF THEM<br />
HAVE BEEN FULLY HONOURED OR SET IN TRAIN WITHIN OUR FIRST<br />
YEAR. IREPEAT: THIS IS A RECORD OF PERFORMANCE<br />
UNEXCELLED IN THE HISTORY OF AUSTRALIA.<br />
THAT PERFORMANCE IS AL. L THE MORE REMARKABLE IN<br />
THE CONTEXT OF THE CONSTRAINTS AND BURDENS AND THE<br />
FRUSTRATIONS IMPOSED ON US AND ON AUSTRALIA ITSELF BY<br />
THE ECONOMIC MESS WE INHERITED FROM OUR OPPONENTS IN<br />
GOVERNMENT AND BY THEIR SPOIL. ING TACTICS IN THE SENATE<br />
IN OPPOSITION. 1 1/ 3 </p>
<p>THIS IS NOT A TIME WHEN AUSTRALIANS ARE IN A<br />
MOOD TO RAKE OVER THE PAST, OR TO INDULGE IN RECRIMINATIONS,<br />
THE SURVEYS SHOW THIS IS A TIME OF THE HIGHEST<br />
OPTIMISM, AND, I BELIEVE, THE HIGHEST NATIONAL SELFCONFIDENCE<br />
SINCE AT LEAST 1973,<br />
IN A WAY THAT WE HAVE NOT KNOWN FOR MORE THAN<br />
A DECADE, AUSTRALIANS WHATEVER THEIR POLITICAL ALLEGIANCES<br />
ARE LOOKING TO THE FUTURE, AND LOOKING TO THAT FUTURE WITH<br />
WELL-FOUNDED CONFIDENCE.<br />
BUT NEVERTHELESS, IT'S JUST NOT POSSIBLE TO MAKE<br />
AN INTELLIGENT JUDGMENT OF OUR GOVERNMENT'S RECORD, AND<br />
AUSTRALIA'S PERFORMANCE IN OUR FIRST YEAR, WITHOUT PUTTING<br />
IT INTO THE CONTEXT, WITHOUT RECALLING WHAT WE FACED WHEN<br />
THE PEOPLE OF AUSTRALIA PUT US INTO GOVERNMENT ON THE<br />
FIFTH OF MARCH 1983,.<br />
AMONG OTHER THINGS, WE INHERITED A PROJECTED.<br />
BUDGET DEFICIT OF $ 9.6 BILLION, AS AGAINST THE $ 6 BILLION<br />
DEFICIT CLAIMED BY OUR PREDECESSORS DURING THE ELECTION<br />
CAMPAIGN. s / 4 </p>
<p>IT WAS ON THE BASIS OF THOSE OFFICIAL, SOLEMN,<br />
ASSURANCES BY THE THEN PRIME MINISTER, THE THEN TREASURER,<br />
NOW THE DEPUTY LEADER OF THE LIBERAL PARTY THE THEN<br />
MINISTER FOR INDUSTRY AND COMMERCE, NOW THE LEADER OF THE<br />
OPPOSITION, AND THE THEN MINISTER FOR DEFENCE, NOW THE<br />
LEADER OF THE NATIONAL PARTY, THAT WE INCLUDED IN OUR<br />
TOTAL PACKAGE FOR ECONOMIC RECOVERY, A PROPOSAL FOR THE<br />
CUTS IN PERSONAL TAXATION.<br />
AS SOON AS SOMETHING OF THE TRUTH ABOUT THE REAL<br />
STATE OF AFFAIRS AND THE ENORMOUS BLOW-OUT OF THE BUDGET<br />
DEFICIT BEGAN TO EMERGE DURING THE CAMPAIGN, WE WARNED THE<br />
PEOPLE OF AUSTRALIA ABOUT ITS INEVITABLE IMPLICATIONS FOR<br />
THAT PARTICULAR PROPOSAL AT LE. AST IN OUR FIRST BUDGET.<br />
THAT WAS THE ONLY RESPONSIBLE COURSE. IT WAS<br />
THE ONLY COURSE OF INTEGRITY.<br />
THEN OF COURSE, AFTER THE ELECTION, THE ENORMITY<br />
OF THE CONCEALMENT, AND THE ENORMOUSNESS OF THE PROJECTED<br />
BUDGET DEFICIT, WAS AT LAST REVEALED.<br />
AND IT WAS IN THAT CONTEXT THE CONTEXT OF A<br />
PROJECTED BUDGET DEFICIT OF $ 9.6 BILLION THAT WE HAD TO<br />
UNDERTAKE OUR PLEDGE TO BRING ABOUT NATIONAL RECOVERY AND<br />
NATIONAL RECONSTRUCTION IN AUSTRALIA. </p>
<p>AND SIDE BY SIDE WITH THAT DAUNTING TASK, WE<br />
HAD TO UNDERTAKE THE IMPLEMENTATION OF THE SPECIFIC<br />
PLEDGES I HAD MADE TO THE PEOPLE OF AUSTRALIA ON BEHALF<br />
OF THE AUSTRALIAN LABOR PARTY THE IMPLEMENTATION OF<br />
LABOR'S PROGRAM OF REFORM, PROGRESS AND EQUITY.<br />
AND NOW, ALMOST ON THE FIRST ANNIVERSARY OF<br />
THE PRESENTATION OF THAT PROGRAM TO THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE,<br />
JUST LET'S BRIEFLY RUN THROUGH A CHECKLIST OF THE PROMISES<br />
AGAINST THE PERFORMANCE.<br />
AT THE OUTSET OF THAT SPEECH A YEAR AGO, I<br />
SAID THIS:<br />
" THE FIRST PLEDGE I NOW MAKE, A COMMITMENT WHICH<br />
EMBRACES EVERY OTHER UNDERTAKING, IS THAT EVERYTHING<br />
WE DO AS A GOVERNMENT WILL HAVE THE ONE GREAT GOALTO<br />
REUNITE THIS GREAT COMMUNITY OF OURS, TO BRING<br />
OUT THE BEST WE ARE TRULY CAPABLE OF, TOGETHER, AS<br />
A NATION, AND BRING AUSTRALIA TOGETHER TO WIN OUR.<br />
WAY THROUGH THE CRISIS INTO WHICH THE POLICIES OF<br />
THE PAST AND THE MEN OF THE PAST HAVE PLUNGED OUR<br />
COUNTRY." AND NOW A SHORT YEAR ON, I BELIEVE I CAN SAY,<br />
WITH COMPLETE CONVICTION AND SINCERITY, THAT WE HAVE<br />
FULFILLED THAT UNDERTAKING; AND THAT THE NEW SPIRIT OF<br />
OPTIMISM AND CONFIDENCE WHICH IS SO MANIFESTLY ABROAD / 6 </p>
<p>THROUGHOUT AUSTRALIA AND AMONG ALL SECTIONS OF THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN COMMUNITY, IS THE EVIDENCE THAT WE HAVE<br />
FULFILLED THAT PLEDGE.<br />
WE PROMISED THAT THE WHOLE BASIS OF OUR<br />
ECONOMIC POLICY WOULD BE TO MAKE A COMBINED ATTACK<br />
ON THE TWIN PROBLEMS OF UNEMPLOYMENT AND INFLATION<br />
SIMULTANEOUSLY. THAT IS EXACTLY WHAT WE ARE DOING.<br />
WE UNDERTOOK TO ESTABLISH THE PRICES AND<br />
INCOMES POLICY, AS AN EXTENSION IN THE FIELD OF NATIONAL<br />
ECONOMIC POLICY OF THE PRICES r" ND INCOMES ACCORD<br />
ALREADY REACHED BETWEEN THE AUSTRALIAN LABOR PARTY AND<br />
THE AUSTRALIAN COUNCIL OF TRADE UNIONS. THE ACCORD IS<br />
WORKING, BECAUSE ALL THE PRINCIPAL PARTIES TO THE<br />
ACCORD ARE DETERMINED THAT IT SHALL WORK. ,/ 7 </p>
<p>UNDER THE AC-CORD THE GOVERNMENT IS COMMITTED TO<br />
ANNUALLY REVIEW INCOME TAX SCALES SO THAT THE TAX BURLEN<br />
WILL NOT RISE AUTOMATICALLY WITH INFLATION,<br />
IN THE AUGUST BUDGET my GOVERNMENT WILL AIM TO DO<br />
TWO THINGS: TO CONTAIN THE BUDGET DEFICIT AND TO PROVIDE,<br />
TO THE EXTENT WE ARE ABLE, SIGNIFICANT INCOME TAX REDUCTIONS<br />
TO LOWER AND MIDDLE INCOME EARNERS,<br />
THESE TAX REDUCTIONS WOULD ENCOURAGE THE COMMUNITY<br />
GENERALLY AND THE TRADE UNION MOVEMENT SPECIFICALLY TO CONTINUE<br />
TO MAINTAIN THEIR COMMITMENT TO THE ACCORD AS THEY HAVE BEEN<br />
DOING SO WELL TO DATE.<br />
WE UNDERTOOK TO ESTABLISH THE ECONOMIC PLANNING ADVISORY<br />
COUNCIL, THE COUNCIL IS NOW OPERATI; NG EFFECTIVELY#<br />
WE PROMISED TO RESTORE ECONOMIC GROWTH TO THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN ECONOMY, THAT IS BEING ACHIEVED,<br />
DURING THE LAST FINANCIAL YEAR -FOR WHICH THE<br />
PREVIOUS GOVERNMENT WAS RESPONSIBLE -THERE WAS NEGATIVE<br />
ECONOMIC GROWTH THE ECONOMY WAS -GOING BACKWARDS,<br />
THAT WAS THE LEGACY OF SEVEN YEARS OF CONSERVATIVE<br />
MISRULE. BUT THROUGH THIS FINANCIAL YEAR WE EXPECT ECONO0MIC<br />
GROWTH APART FROM FARM PRODUCTION OF ABOUT 6 PER CENT, AND<br />
TOTAL ECONOMIC GROWTH INCLUDING THE RURAL SECTOR OF ABOUT<br />
8 PER CENT. CLEARLY THIS IS A DRAMATIC TURNAROUND, </p>
<p>ECONOMIC RECOVERY IS ALREADY OCCURRING.<br />
19814 IT WILL BECOME EVEN STRONGER.<br />
WE PROMIS'ED TO ARREST THE DECLINE IN EMPLOYMENT<br />
THAT WAS OCCURRING UNDER THE PREVIOUS GOVERNMENT.<br />
THAT HAS BEEN DONE.<br />
OVER 150,000O NEW JOBS HAVE BEEN CREATED SINCE<br />
WE CHANGED THE COURSE OF ECONOMIC POLICY AT THE ECONOMIC<br />
SUMMIT IN APRIL, UNEMPLOYMENT HAS ALREA\ DY STARTED TO FALL.<br />
WE PROMISED TO CREATE 500., 000 NEW JOBS IN OUR<br />
FIRST THREE YEARS OF GOVERNMENT. WE ARE WELL ON TARGET.<br />
WE PROMISED TO REDUCE INFLATION. THAT IS BEING<br />
ACHIEVED. INFLATION IS NOW BELOW DOUBLE DIGIT RATES AND<br />
WILL CONTINUE TO FALL.<br />
THE ECONOMIC HEALTH of: AUSTRALIA IS BEING RESTORED.<br />
WE PROMISED AN ACCELERATED CAPITAL WORKS PROGRAM.<br />
THAT HAS BEEN DONE. 1/ 9 </p>
<p>PROGRAM. WE PROMISED TO0 ESTABLISH THE COMMUNITY WORKS<br />
THAT HAS BEEN DONE,<br />
WE PROMISED THE DEVELOPMENT OF A PRIVATE SECTOR<br />
ASSISTANCE PROGRAM. THAT HAS BEEN DONE.<br />
WE UNDERTOOK TO ESTABLISH THE JOBS ONi ROADS PROGRAM.<br />
THAT HAS BEEN DONE.<br />
BUSINESS, W4E OFFERED SUPPORT AND ENCOURAGEMENT FOR SMALL<br />
THAT PROGRAM IS BEING PROGRESSIVELY IMPLEMENTED,<br />
WE PROMISED A PETROL PRICE REDUCTION. IT' S HAPPENED.<br />
WE PROMISED A MASSIVE BOOST FOR THE HOUSING AND<br />
CONSTRUCTION INDUSTRY, WE HAVE PROVIDED IT.<br />
WE PLEDGED ASSISTANCE FOR FIRST HOME BUYERS TO<br />
BRIDGE THE DEPOSIT GAP, WE HAVE GIVEN IT.<br />
WE SAID *, WE WOULD M. AIN! TAIN A VIABLE STEEL<br />
INDUSTRY IN AUSTRALIA. WE FULFILLED THAT PLEDGE.<br />
WE GAVE UNDERTAKINGS ON ASSISTANCE TO THE MOTOR<br />
VEHICLE INDUSTRY. WE ARE HONOURING THOSE UNDERTAKINGS.<br />
WE GAVE UNDERTAKINGS FOR SUPPORT FOR NEW TECHNOLOGY<br />
INDUSTRIES. THOSE UNDERTAKINGS ARE BEING HONOURED, ' in </p>
<p>IN THE SOCIAL WELFARE FIELD, WE UNDERTOOK TO BRING<br />
THE BASIC PENSION RATE PROGRESSIVELY UP To 25 PERCENT OF<br />
AVERAGE MALE WEEKLY EARNINGS. THAT PROMISE IS WELL ON<br />
SCHEDULE, WE HAVE HONOURED OUR PROMISE TO CUT THE LAG ON<br />
PENSION ADJUSTMENTS, ACCORDING TO CPI MOVEMENTS, FROM<br />
FOUR MONTHS TO ONE MONTH.<br />
WE HAVE HONOURED OUR PROMISE TO INDEX PENSIONER<br />
FRINGE BENEFITS. WE HAVE HONOURED OUR PROMISE ON THE INCREASE OF<br />
UNEMPLOYMENT BENEFITS,<br />
WE ARE IMPLEMENTING OUR PROMISE TO DEVELOP THE<br />
CHILDREN'S SERVICES PROGRAM.<br />
FROM THE 1ST FEBRUARY, MEDICARE WILL OPERATE<br />
AND AT LAST THERE WILL BE A RETURN TO THE BASIC PRINCIPLE<br />
OF THE RIGHT OF ALL AUSTRALIANS TO HEALTH SERVICES ACCORDING<br />
TO THEIR MEDICAL NEEDS.<br />
ALL OUR UNDERTAKINGS ON EDUCATION, INCLUDING<br />
OUR ASSURANCES TO THE PARENTS Of: NON-GOVERNMENT AND<br />
GOVERNMENT SCHOOLS ALIKE, ARE BEING HONOURED.<br />
OUR SPORTS AND RECREATION PROGRAM IS BEING FULLY(<br />
IMPLEMENTED. </p>
<p>SO TOO ARE OUR UNDERTAKINGS OF SUPPORT FOR THE<br />
ARTS; OUR UNDERTAKINGS ON BROADCASTING AND COMMUNICATIONS,<br />
ESPECIALLY AS THEY AFFECT THE RURAL AND MORE REMOTE<br />
COMMUNITIES OF AUSTRALIA; OUR SUPPORT FOR THE TOURIST<br />
INDUSTRY, EVERY UNDERTAKING WE MADE TO THE ABORIGINAL<br />
PEOPLE OF AUSTRALIA IS BEING HONOURED.<br />
WE HAVE PASSED THE ANTI-DISCRIMINATION LEGISLATION,<br />
AS !' ROMISED. WE ARE HONOURING OUR COMMITMENTS TO ELECTORAL<br />
REFORM, LAW REFORM, AND PUBLIC SERVICE REFORM,<br />
IN TWO GREAT AREAS OF REFORM CONSTITUTIONAL<br />
REFORM AND TAX REFORM WE HAVE HAD TO STRUGGLE AGAINST THE<br />
SPOILING TACTICS OF THE OPPOSITrION IN THE SENATE.<br />
IN THE POLICY SPEECH A YEAR AGO,, I COMMITTED A<br />
LABOR GOVERNMENT TO WIPE OUT TAX AVOIDANCE AND TAX EVASION,<br />
I NOW REAFFIRM OUR UTTER COMMITMENT TO THAT PURPOSE.<br />
THE MANDATE GIVEN BY THE PEOPLE OF AUSTRALIA A YEAR AGO ON<br />
THAT ISSUE, WAS CLEAR AND POWERFUL.<br />
YET THREE TIMES, AN OPPORTUNISTIC COALITION IN<br />
THE SENATE HAS FRUSTRATED VHE CLEAR WILL OF THE AUSTRALIAN_<br />
PEOPLE NOT JUST THE ELECTED AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT BUT THE<br />
WILL OF THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE IN THIS REGARD, TO A COST<br />
TO THE AUSTRALIAN TAXPAYERS OF MORE THAN4 $ 300 MILLION. </p>
<p>AND THAT ISSUE AN ISSUE OF FIRST RATE IMPORTANCE<br />
TO THE WELFARE OF AUSTRALIA ENCAPSULATES THE DIFFERENCE<br />
BETWEEN THE LABOR GOVERNMENT OF AUSTRALIA AND THE PRESENT<br />
OPPOSITION IN THE AUSTRALIAN PARLIAMENT,<br />
ON THE ONE HAND, YOU HAVE AN AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT<br />
DETERMINED TO HONOUR ITS UNDERTAKINGS TO THE PEOPLE OF<br />
AUSTRALIA, AND DOING SO I REPEAT IN A WAY NEVER EXCELLED<br />
OR INDEED, NEVER EQUALLED BY ANY, GOVER1NMENT IN THE HISTORY<br />
OF AUSTRALIA, ON THE OTHER HAND, AN OPPOSITION OF OPPORTUNISM,<br />
CYNICISM, NEGATIVISM AND, IN THE FINAL ANALYSIS, AN<br />
OPPOSITION OF IRRESPONSIBILITY AND LACK OF INTEGRITY,<br />
THE IMPLICATIONS OF THE POLICIES OF THIS OPPOSITION<br />
WHAT PASSES FOR THEIR POLICIES AND WHAT PASSES FOR AN<br />
OPPOSITION -GO FAR BEYOND THE LOSS OF $ 300M THEY HAVE<br />
INFLICTED ON THE ORDINARY, DECENT TAXPAYERS OF AUSTRALIA BY<br />
THEIR MISCHIEF-MAKING IN THE SENATE.<br />
THEY HAVE OPPOSED THE BUDGET MEASURES W~ E HAVE<br />
HAD TO TAKE AND AS A RESPONSIBLE GOVERNMENT, WERE OBLIGED<br />
TO TAKE TO REDUCE THE BUDGET DEFICIT THE INHERITED<br />
BUDGET DEFICIT AND TO KEEP INTEREST RATES DOWN AND REDUCE<br />
INFLATION, ./ 13 </p>
<p>THAT IS, THEY HAVE OPPOSED AT EVERY STEP OUR<br />
EFFORTS TO HONOUR OUR CENTRAL COMMITMENT TO THE PEOPLE<br />
OF AUSTRALIA TO FIGHT UNEMPLOYMENT AND INFLATION<br />
SIMULTANEOUSLY AND TO ACHIEVE A SUSTAINABLE ECONOMIC RECOVERY<br />
A RECOVERY THAT WON'T BE LOST IN ANY NEW BOUT OF INFLATION<br />
OR ANY BALANCE OF PAYMENTS CRISIS.<br />
IF ONE COULD TAKE THE LEADER OF THE OPPOSITION<br />
SERTOUSLY, THE COST OF THEIR OBJECTIONS TO THE MEASURES<br />
WE HAVE HAD TO TAKE AS A RESPONSIBLE GOVERNMENT, WOULD B3E<br />
$ 1.6 BILLION IN THE CURRENT BUDGET AND $ 3 BILLION IN A FULL YEAR.<br />
AND THIS AT A TIME WHEN BUSINESS IS AT LAST,<br />
IN RESPONSE TO OUR GOVERNMENT'S POLICIES, BEGINNING TO<br />
RECOVER FROM THE WORST RECESSION FOR FIFTY YEARS, AND WHEN<br />
THE FARMING COMMUNITY IS STRUGGLING BACK TO ITS FEET AFTER<br />
THE WORST DROUGHT IN HISTORY.<br />
AND IT'S THAT SORT OF GROSS IRRESPONSIBILITY<br />
THAT EXPLAINS COMPLETELY WHY THIS OPPOSITION LACKS ANY<br />
CREDIBILITY WHATSOEVER NOT ONLY WITH THE AUSTRAL. IAN PEOPLE<br />
AS A WHOLE, BUT IN THE TWO GREAT AREAS WHICH THE LIBERALS<br />
AND THE NATIONALS USED TO CLAIM AS THEIR SPECIAL CONSTITUENCYTHE<br />
GREAT BUSINESS COMMUNITY OF AUSTRALIA, AND THE GREAT<br />
RURAL SECTOR OF AUSTRALIA,<br />
CREDIBILITY IS AN ISSUE IN THESE BY-ELECTIONSTHE<br />
CREDIBILITY OF POLICIES; AND CREDIBILITY IN LEADERSHIP, </p>
<p>I AM NOT HERE TO INDULGE IN PERSONALITIES, EVEN<br />
AT THE EXPENSE OF THE NEW LEADER OF THE NATIONAL PARTY,<br />
BUT THE RELATIONS BETWEEN THE NATIONAL PARTY AND<br />
THE LIBERAL PARTY ARE NOW SUCH THAT THE NATIONAL PARTY'S<br />
CHOICE LAST WEEK HAS HUGE IMPLICATIONS FOR THE COALITION;<br />
AND IT HAS SERIOUS IMPLICATIONS FOR THE WAY IN WHICH THE<br />
COUNTRY PEOPLE OF AUSTRALIA ARE GOING TO BE REPRESENTED<br />
IN THE NATIONAL PARLIAMENT.<br />
BECAUSE, MR SINCLAIR'S ELECTION PUTS THE FINAL<br />
SEAL ON THE SELL-OUT OF THE COUNTRY PEOPLE OF AUSTRALIA BY<br />
THE NATIONAL PARTY A SELL-OUT OF WHICH MR SINCLAIR HAS<br />
BEEN THE PRIME ARCHITECT AND THE PRIME MOVER FOR A DECADE.<br />
THE NATIONAL PARTY HAS LONG CEASED TO REPRESENT<br />
THE TRUE INTERESTS OF AUSTRALIA'S FARMING AND RURAL COMMUNITY,<br />
THEY HAVE SOLD OUT THE AUSTRALIAN FARMER. IT GOES MUCH<br />
DEEPER THAN THE DROPPING OF THE TIME-HONOURED " COUNTRY PARTY"<br />
NAME. THEY NOW REPRESENT ONLY THE BIG INTERESTS MAINLY<br />
FOREIGN INTERESTS WHICH BACK THEM FINANCIALLY.<br />
AND AS I SAY, IN THAT PROCESS, MR SINCLAIR HAS<br />
LED THE WAY, AS TO THE LIBERAL PARTY AND ITS RELATIONS WITH<br />
THE RURAL COMMUNITY, LET ME REMIND YOU OF THE POINT I MADE<br />
IN OUR RURAL POLICY SPEECH DURING THE MARCH CAMPAIGN </p>
<p>A POINT THAT IS AS VALID TODAY AS IT WAS A YEAR AGO,<br />
THE LIBERAL PARTY OF AUSTRALIA, AT ITS NATIONAL COUNCIL OF<br />
MAY 1982 PLACED ON ITS BOOKS A RESOLUTION WHICH THREATENS<br />
THE EXISTENCE OF EVERY NATIONAL MARKETING AUTHORITY IN<br />
AUSTRALIA, THAT RESOLUTION CALLS FOR THE DISMANTLING OF<br />
ALL THE EFFECTIVE POWERS OF THE MARKETING BOARDS ON THE<br />
GROUNDS THAT THEY ARE CONTRARY TO LIBERAL PHILOSOPHY, THAT<br />
RESOLUTION OF DESTRUCTION IS STILL ON THEIR BOOKS.<br />
AFTER THE ROUT IN QUEENSLAND, THE LIBERAL PARTY<br />
IS MORE THAN EVER A SECTIONAL AND CITY-BASED RUMP,<br />
BUT THE NATIONAL PARTY, ESPECIALLY UNDER ITS NEW<br />
LEADERSHIP, HAS ORIENTED ITSELF JUST AS MUCH TO THE BIG<br />
CITY INTERESTS WHICH FILL THEIR COFFERS.<br />
IT IS AFTER ALL A SYDNEYSIDER, NOT A LOCAL WHO<br />
WILL CONTEST THIS SEAT FOR THE NATIONAL PARTY,<br />
SO FOR THE RURAL COMMUNITY OF AUSTRALIA, THERE IS<br />
JUST NO CREDIBILITY LEFT IN THE POLICIES OR LEADERSHIP'OF<br />
EITHER OF THE COALITION PARTIES,<br />
AND AS FOR THE NATIONAL PARTY, ITS NEW LEADER HAS<br />
BEEN THE SUBJECT OF THE MOST DAMNING, DEVASTATING, COMPLETE<br />
AND COMPREHENSIVE JUDICIAL INDICTMENT OF HIS PERSONAL AND<br />
POLITICAL CREDIBILITY EVER DELIVERED UPON A LEADING<br />
PARLIAMENTARIAN IN THE HISTORY OF AUSTRALIA, / 16 </p>
<p>16.<br />
BUT IN A SENSE WHICH TRANSCENDS PERSONALITIES.,<br />
THE SINCLAIR AFFAIR ENCAPSULATES SO MUCH THAT WAS WRONG AND<br />
DAMAGING IN THE APPROACH OF THE COALITION TO THE AFFAIRS<br />
OF THIS NATION. THEY SOUGHT TO DIVIDE AND RULE.<br />
THEIRS IS THE POLITICS OF DELIBERATE DIVISION,<br />
THE POLITICS OF CONFRONTATION.<br />
FOR MOST OF THE DECADE UP TO THE 5TH OF MARCH 1983<br />
THERE HAD BEEN TOO MUCH OF THE SETTING OF AUSTRALIAN AGAINST<br />
AUSTRALIAN, GROUP AGAINST GROUP, REGION AGAINST REGION.<br />
AND IT WAS BECAUSE A CLEAR MAJORITY OF AUSTRALIANS<br />
AUSTRALIANS EVERYWHERE, CITY AND COUNTRY DWELLERS ALIKE<br />
SAW THE DAMAGE BEING DONE TO THE VERY FABRIC ECONOMIC,<br />
INDUSTRIAL AND SOCIAL OF THIS NATION, THAT THEY DECISIVELY<br />
REJECTED THE POLITICS OF CONFRONTATION, THE POLITICS OF<br />
DIVISION AND ITS AUTHORS ON THE 5TH OF MARCH 1983.<br />
AND I BELIEVE THAT EVERYTHING THAT HAS HAPPENED<br />
SINCE THE 5TH OF MARCH SHOWS THE TRUTH OF WHAT WE OF THE<br />
LABOR PARTY SAID DURING THE CAMPAIGN THAT THERE IS A BETTER<br />
WAY THE LABOR WAY AND AUSTRALIANS CAN BE BROUGHT<br />
TOGETHER, WE CAN WORK TOGETHER AND TOGETHER WE CAN BUILD A<br />
BETTER AUSTRALIA FOR OURSELVES IN OUR OWN TIME, AND FOR<br />
THE GENERATION TO COME. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
