<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10137</transcript-id>
    <title>THE HON.JOHN MOORE MINISTER FOR INDUSTRY, SCIENCE AND TOURISM</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/10/1996</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010137.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
JOINT MEDIA RELEASE<br />
The Hon. John Howard<br />
Prime Minister<br />
The Hon. Tony Rundle<br />
Premier<br />
The Hon. John Moore<br />
Minister for Industry, Science and Tourism<br />
Friday, 18 October 1996 253196<br />
An independent review of Tasmania's industry and employment opportunities will be<br />
conducted by The Hon. Peter Nixon AO. The study will update a report produced by<br />
Sir Bede Callaghan in 1977 and assist the Federal and State Governments to develop strategies<br />
and policies for optimising Tasmania's economic growth.<br />
The decision to conduct the review follows representations by Tasmanian coalition members<br />
during the election campaign and the recent announcement of Federal Government funding in<br />
the Budget on August<br />
The appointment of Mr Nixon, a former senior Federal Mnister, was announced jointly today<br />
by the Prime Mnister, John Howard, the Premier of Tasmania, Tony Rundle and the Minister<br />
for Industry, Science and Tourism, John Moore in Hobart.<br />
The Prime Minister said that he was pleased that Mr Nixon had agreed to chair the review.<br />
" Mr Nixon is an eminent Australian with extensive experience in industry and government,"<br />
Mr Howard said. " He is well placed to lead such an important inquiry and draw together the<br />
diverse issues being considered in this study."<br />
Mr Rundle said the study was of critical importance to Tasmania.<br />
" The broad terms of reference will include analysis of the potential for new industries and the<br />
expansion of existing industries in Tasmania.<br />
" This review will provide the State with information essential for the future economic<br />
development of Tasmania. The inquiry Secretariat will be based in the Department of Premier<br />
and Cabinet in Hobart and will have access to all the information it needs for the review," he<br />
said. 1686 </p>
<p>Mr Moore said Tasmania's contribution to Australia was important, and that the review would<br />
enable the State's special circumstances and natural advantages to be evaluated.<br />
" The new study will provide advice to both Governments on how Tasmania can best use its<br />
resources," he said.<br />
The review is being funded by a Budget allocation of $ 150,000 from Mr Moore's portfolio. It<br />
is expected Mr Nixon will be able to report back to Mr Rundle and Mr Moore by 30 June<br />
1997.<br />
Mr Nixon said he was delighted to have been asked to conduct such an important study.<br />
" I look forward to gathering views from the community and government and developing them<br />
into a report which will be of significance to the people of Tasmania," he said.<br />
The terms of reference and Mr Nixon's curriculum vitae are attached.<br />
Contact: David Gazard Peter Hazelwood Cheryl Cartwright<br />
CNM304 Mr Howard's Office Mr Rundle's Office Mr Moore's Office<br />
06/ 2777744 0362/ 333464 06/ 2777580 1687<br />
II </p>
<p>TERMS OF REFERENCE<br />
I The study is to inquire into and report on industry development and employment in<br />
Tasmania. It will draw on and update a previous study, chaired by Sir Bede Callaghan,<br />
which reported in June 1977.<br />
2 The study will:<br />
a identify areas or sectors in which the Tasmanian economy has or can develop<br />
a sustainable competitive advantage, and the resultant opportunities for and<br />
impediments to sustainable employment growth;<br />
b identify issues to be addressed by all governments and the private sector to<br />
facilitate sustainable economic and employment growth in Tasmania;<br />
c advise on strategies to assist Tasmania to increase its international<br />
competitiveness and export performance, and on appropriate consultative<br />
arrangements between governments and industry.<br />
3 Specific issues to be addressed by the inquiry will include:<br />
a strategies to increase investment in Tasmanian industries and firms<br />
b opportunities for value-adding to Tasmania' s resource industries, taking<br />
account of environmental, community and social issues<br />
c the potential for non-resource industries ( including elaborately transformed<br />
manufactures, eco-tourism and location neutral high technology industries) to<br />
develop in Tasmania, and strategies to facilitate their development<br />
d the impact of competitive reforms and how they may be better progressed,<br />
taking account of their implementation nationally and the Commonwealth's<br />
international obligations<br />
e strategies to promote Tasmania nationally and internationally as a source of<br />
goods and services and as a location for investment<br />
f strategies to implement the inquiry's recommendations.<br />
4 The study will take into account relevant Commonwealth policies and other sources of<br />
information, such as relevant Industry Commission Reports.<br />
The inquiry will consult with the State and Commonwealth Governments to enable the<br />
study to reflect the latest views, information and statistics from government<br />
departments and agencies in its report.<br />
6 The inquiry will report jointly to the Commonwealth Minister for Industry, Science and<br />
Tourism and the Treasurer of Tasmania.<br />
7 The inquiry will aim to report by 30 June 1997.<br />
1688 II </p>
<p>U CURRICULUM VITAE<br />
HON. PETER J. NIXON, AO<br />
Retired from Parliament<br />
Minister for Primary Industry<br />
Minister for Transport ( including Aviation)<br />
Postmaster-General<br />
Minister for Shipping and Transport<br />
Minister for Interior<br />
Member House of Representatives I1I March 1983<br />
1979-83<br />
1975-79<br />
1975 1971-72<br />
1967-7 1<br />
196 1-83<br />
CONFERENCES, DELEGATIONS AND VISITS<br />
Attended OECD Agriculture Ministers' Conference, Paris in March 1980; New Delhi, Dacca, Jakarta.<br />
Australia-Japan Ministerial Meeting, 1972, 1977, 1979 and 198 1; and World Food Council Meeting,<br />
Novi Sad, Yugoslavia, 1981 and Acapulco, Brazil, 1982. Ministerial Transport Councils in Belgrade,<br />
Greece and Paris. South Pacific Forum New Zealand, Western Samoa and New Guinea.<br />
Negotiated first Agricultural Accord when guest of Government of People's Republic of China, 198 1.<br />
DIRECTORSHIPS Chairman Chairman<br />
Chairman/ Director<br />
Director Director Director Chairman 1995) Southern Cross Broadcasting ( 1984<br />
Gippsland and Northern Co. Ltd ( 1983-92)<br />
Associated Container Transport Australia ( December 1983-92 retired)<br />
Emery Worldwide Advisory Board ( 1983-88)<br />
Linfox Corporation ( 1988<br />
Budget Corporation ( 1988-9 1)<br />
Interstate Rail Services Committee ( November 1994 December<br />
PERSONAL Born Orbost, 22 March 1928<br />
Educated at Orbost, Wesley College, Melbourne<br />
Grazier, ' Macclesfield', Orbost<br />
Married Sally J. T. Dahlsen, Bairnsdale, Victoria<br />
Three children Joanne, Mark and Christopher<br />
Member, Institute of Public Affairs<br />
Commissioner, Australian Football League ( 1984-9 1)<br />
Trustee, Melbourne Cricket Ground ( 1986-91)<br />
Freeman City Jakarta, Athens<br />
Officer Order of Australia ( 1993)<br />
Chairman, Weary Dunlop Statue Appeal ( 1993-95)<br />
Chief Commissioner, East Gippsland Shire ( 1995<br />
CLUBS Melbourne Club<br />
Australian Club<br />
V. R. C.<br />
V. A. T. C.<br />
* M. C. C HOBBIES Racing Fly Fishing<br />
El 1689 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
