<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1067</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS:  P.M.NO. 25/1965  ECONOMIC CONSULTATIONS STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/02/1965</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001067_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
6 5/ 005<br />
FOR PRESS P. M. No. jœ<br />
ECONOMIC CONSULTATIONS<br />
Statement by the Prime Mini. ster the Rt. Hon. Sir Robert Menzies<br />
The Prime Minister and senior Ministers<br />
had discussions this afternoon on the economic situation<br />
with representatives of a group of national organisations<br />
representing industry and commerce. After the meeting the<br />
Prime Minister Sir Robert Menzies, said that this had been<br />
a further meeting in the series of discussions commenced by<br />
the Government three years ago to obtain a first-hand account<br />
of current and prospective developments in the different<br />
sectors of the economy. Sir Robert said that these talks allowed<br />
Ministers to get the up-to-date views of those directly<br />
engaged in commerce and industry. The talks had again<br />
proved most useful for this purpose.<br />
Representatives who attended the meeting<br />
were Mr. H. G. Ferrier, President Associated Chambers of<br />
Manufactures of Australia<br />
Mr. L. Atkinson, President, Associated Chambers of<br />
Commerce of Australia<br />
Mr. A. F. Havard, President, National Farmers' Union of<br />
Australia.<br />
Mr. J. P. Heffernan, President, Australian Primary Producers?<br />
Union.<br />
Mr. T. L. Bull, President, Australian ! oolgrowers' and<br />
Graziers' Council<br />
Mr. L. H. Heaslip, Vice-President, Australian Wool and<br />
Meat Producerst Federation.<br />
Mr. N. A. Jackson, Chairman, Australian Bankers' Association<br />
Mr. V. T. dwards, President, Master Builders' Federation<br />
of Australia.<br />
Mr. N. W. Lawrance, President, Federal Chamber of Automotive<br />
Industries<br />
Mr. G. McCowan, President, Australian Council of Retailers.<br />
This evening, Ministers will meet with<br />
representatives of the A. C. T. U. and on Thursday there will be<br />
separate meetings with the Manufacturing Industries Advisory<br />
Council and the Export Development Council.<br />
CANBEA, 1i<br />
24-th February, 1965 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
