<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4740</transcript-id>
    <title>INTERVIEW WITH RADIO JOURNALISTS, 19 JUNE 1978</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/06/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004740.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
INTERVIEW WITH RADIO JOURNALISTS<br />
QUESTION: You've been talking extensively overseas about<br />
trade. Tonight you are addressing the Confederation of<br />
Australian Industry. What news have you got for Australian<br />
businessmen and industry?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I will be telling them the results as I see<br />
it of the visit overseas. I will also be indicating the<br />
importance of the trade negotiations to Australia. We are<br />
a very significant trading nation with a higher proportion<br />
of our national wealth dependent upon trade than most<br />
countries and therefore what happens, our capacity to get<br />
access to markets, is of enormous consequence to everyone<br />
in this country. ' Our trade with many countries has of course<br />
been expanding very greatly with Japan, with Korea, with<br />
many countries in Asia. In these areas we are not up against<br />
the sorts of non-tariff barriers and discriminatory trading<br />
practices which we have seen in Europe and that's why Europe<br />
I suppose, is taking so much attention. There you have<br />
over 200 million of the most affluent, technologically advanced<br />
people in one trading group that the world has ever seen and<br />
they have been using discriminatory trading practices which<br />
in many cases have damaged Australia's industries very<br />
severely. My government is the first Australian government<br />
to try to redress that situation and I believe it should have<br />
been undertaken before.<br />
QUESTION: Both Mr. Lynch and Mr. Robinson in recent speeches<br />
have poited out the possibility of cutbacks in areas of<br />
Government spending the coming Budget and Mr. Robinson noted<br />
health, education and welfare. Today, at that Conference of<br />
Australian industries, Sir Roderick Carnegie virtually said that<br />
cutbacks in these areas were essential. Is this on the line?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I think you should know me better than to<br />
get me to speculate on what is going to be or not<br />
going to be in the Budget.<br />
QUESTION: There has been-speculation, Prime Minister, with<br />
respect sir, in today's press, that the Government will cut<br />
public spending by at least $ 400 million in the Budget.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I've got no doubt there will be speculation<br />
in the press and there will go on being speculation, but I<br />
don't think you expect me to comment on the speculation about<br />
particular areas of expenditure so far as the Budget is<br />
concerned. The Treasurer will make a Budget speech at a certain<br />
time.<br />
QUESTION: Are we heading for a tough budget?.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:. I thought this-interview was basically about<br />
the visit overseas and what it meant and about trade and you<br />
turn immediately to domestic matters. I think let's see if<br />
there are other questions on trade matters which are of great<br />
concern to many Australian industries,, including that<br />
Confederation with whom I will be talking to tonight. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
QUESTIO N: Prime Minister, could I put it this way? In<br />
your tas overseas, did you get any emphasis which suggests<br />
you should change your economic financial ( inaudible)<br />
in other words, does Australia do you think Australia should<br />
have to perhaps stimulate some sections of the domestic<br />
economy to provide employment opportunities?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: The strongest and healthiest economies<br />
are probably Germany's and Japan's, of the major trading<br />
countries. There are other smaller economies that are in<br />
a healthy position with low rates of inflation and wherever<br />
I went, I found respect, in the business and commercial world,<br />
the policies of Germany and Japan. I also found a growing<br />
respect for Australia's policies and maybe not far off<br />
( break in tape) because you know it's very easy to spend<br />
an extra few hundred million dollars on a particular program<br />
within a particular country but if that is going to drive out<br />
domestic investment, overseas investment, you know you could<br />
spend $ 300. million or $ 400 million on particular programs<br />
and -alter the perceptions of your own economy and by so doing<br />
lose maybe $ 1000 million in domestic and overseas investment.<br />
Now if that occurred it would be a very bad bargain, and it's<br />
certainly not a course that my Government will embark upon.<br />
QUESTION: So job creation schemes just aren't-on?<br />
PRIME ; MINISTER: You know quite well that we spend great<br />
sums in the job training schemes and re-training programs<br />
through Tony Street's Department, but the broad thrust of<br />
the Government's economic policies are going to be pursued.<br />
QUESTION: Prime Minister, there's been considerable criticism<br />
Tiere in Australia, and though I may say ' there is a lack-of hard news<br />
stories from overseas from some of the reporters travelling<br />
with you. Do you really think you can justify this trip to<br />
the Australian, and to Australia generally?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I have not the slighest doubt at all. If<br />
you got to the stage when the Prime Minister goes overseas<br />
he's got to bring back a basketfull of goodies to Australia,<br />
well then that's a very odd circumstance and its not something<br />
that often, if ever, happens. But we are in a situation, where<br />
1978 is a year of very very great importance for Australia<br />
as a trading nation. This is the year in which the Multilateral<br />
Trade Negotiations will come to a conclusion. Many Australian's<br />
mightn't understand it, but this total year of trade talks<br />
began five years ago. It's been going on and nations are<br />
now on the home strait. What happens at Geneva over the next<br />
few weeks will determine the pattern of world trade maybe for<br />
the rest of this century. It will determine whether there will<br />
be an opening up of the closed markets to agricultural products.<br />
A little later in the year there will be decisions determining<br />
whether or not there's better access, better trade conditions<br />
for commodities in the developing world and so the pattern for<br />
years ahead is being set in this year, 1978, and we are very<br />
close to final decisions. It's terribly important that<br />
Australia's view, be known, that Australia's view be understood<br />
and I think that there's an obligation on the Australian / 3 </p>
<p>INTERVIEW WITH RADIO JOURNALISTS 1 UE17<br />
3-<br />
PRIME MINISTER: ( continued) government to press its view<br />
in th~ e strongest possible way. Now I've used this analogy before<br />
but you never know when extra weight, put on the side of<br />
reason and common sense, in a particular argument, will make<br />
all the difference between success and failure. We know quite<br />
well the limitations of Australia's power and the limitations<br />
of Australia's influence but if an argument is evenly balanced<br />
a bit of extra weight on the right side, on the side of reason<br />
and commonsense,, can make all the difference between success<br />
and failure. And believe me, the difference between success<br />
and failure at these trade talks in Geneva will affect the<br />
livelihood, the well-being of every Australian for many years<br />
to come and therefore its not only desirable, I think its<br />
a positive duty to express Australia's view as strongly and<br />
as forcefully as possible.<br />
QUESTION: ( Inaudible)<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I think there are some signs, yes. Some signs<br />
that are good, one or two signs that concern me greatly. The<br />
Unite States has said, again, that they will walk away from<br />
these negotiations unless agriculture is part of it. Now that's<br />
a good thing and they've said it with a great force. In addition,<br />
the discussion I had with Mr. Jenkins as President of the<br />
Commission was more constructive that I thought it might have<br />
been. He made it perfectly plain that while he's saying, and<br />
the Commission has said to us, that Australia's problems can<br />
be resolved, should be resolved, in the Multilateral Trade<br />
Negotiations, he also said that it will not be realistic so<br />
far as we are concerned unless it opens up the possibility and<br />
the reality of trade in beef, for example to take that<br />
as one of matter of pre-eminent concern into the European<br />
community market. That is virtually saying that we know for<br />
there to be a reasonable result, there's got to be a market<br />
for Australian beef in Europe. Now it finally comes out, it's<br />
too early to judge and I will believe it when I see it on the<br />
ink, as it were, on the final document. But that seemed to me<br />
to be a recognition that there had to be concessions, that there<br />
had to be movement and I haven't seen that kind of recognition<br />
coming out of the European-Commission before. So those two<br />
things are on the plus side. In addition of course, the United<br />
Kingdom, the Germans and the Italians, have all taken the view<br />
that is inherently in support of the kind of views that we've<br />
been putting and indicated that they are prepared to support<br />
and will support us. Herr ,1the German Foreign<br />
Minister, will be Chairman of the Council of Ministers of<br />
the European Community over the next six months and he said<br />
during his period as Chairman, he wants to work particularly<br />
closely with Australia and again, try and achieve the circumstances<br />
in which there will be success. Again, that's on the plus side.<br />
On the debit side, there is a bid by European countries to break<br />
down the most-favoured nation principle which I believe has been<br />
of the utmost importance to middle-ranking, smaller nations,<br />
developing nations and you will understand that the most-favoured<br />
nation principle is one that means you've got to treat all your<br />
trading partners equally. That if you have quotas on imports,<br />
it's got to be global quota, that you are not allowed to aiim<br />
at one particular country and say we don't want any more of your<br />
goods. .1<br />
19 JUNE 1978 </p>
<p>INTERVIEW WITH RADIO JOURNALISTS 1 UE17<br />
-4-<br />
PRIME MINISTER: ( continued) They are now talking about<br />
selective, a better word would be discriminatory, safeguards<br />
which would give the national governments the power to be<br />
selective, to be discriminatory in what they do; give them<br />
the power to point to a particular nation and say your goods<br />
are damaging our trade, you've got to stop exporting to us,<br />
you've got to reduce exports to us. That power in the hands<br />
of a national government I think is one that will be<br />
extraordinarily dangerous. It would be going back to the<br />
trading policies of the 1930' s and the most favoured nation<br />
principle is one which is of enormous consequence to countries<br />
such as Australia and one which we intend to fight to try and<br />
keep through those trade forums, even though we know that there<br />
is very significant weight on the other side of the argument<br />
with major. European countries wanting to break down the principle.<br />
QUESTION: You said that unless agricultural products are<br />
taken into consideration at the MTN then Am~ erica is prepared to<br />
withdraw. If Australia feels that it should withdraw, would<br />
you expect America to support Australia and therefore withdraw<br />
at the same time?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I can't guarantee that the circumstances that<br />
would require our withdrawal are precisely the same as those<br />
that would involve the United State's withdrawal. We both have<br />
an interest in agriculture. The United States has a particular<br />
interest in some matters which are of concern to important<br />
areas of Congress. They have at the same time said that they'll<br />
support the Australian viewpoint but while there is great<br />
similarity of view, I can't say down to the last point it is<br />
absolutely identical. 1<br />
_ QUESTION: ( Inaudible)... . hope that they would?<br />
PRIME MINIS TER: Of course we would hope that they would, but<br />
what can be said with complete accuracy -and great strength, is<br />
that the United States have indicated that they will give<br />
great support and weight to the Australian point of view.<br />
9UUESTION: Prime Minister, if I could briefly bring you again<br />
back oe you are back now, the Premier's Conference is coming<br />
up what sort of offer will the Federal Government be making<br />
to the Premiers or will in fact the Federal Government be telling<br />
the Premiers to tighten their belts and look after themselves?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: We will be coming to this Thursday and Friday<br />
of thiis week and I've got no doubt there will be a-good deal<br />
said about during those days by the Commonwealth and by the<br />
Premiers. I think it would be I hate to spoil it by entering<br />
the debate today.<br />
QUESTION: Prime Minister, one other domestic subject beef.<br />
Just how urgent do you think the PJT Inquiry should be?<br />
19 JUNE 1978 </p>
<p>INTERVIEW WITH RADIO JOURNALISTS. 19 JUNE 1978<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I have asked for a report on these matters;<br />
i4hat stage it's got to, what technical matters are holding it<br />
up and until I've had that report I'm not in a position really<br />
to give you a substantive reply. I had a brief discussion<br />
with Ian Sinclair about this morning but I've noted with<br />
concern the reports of a -a sort of a-profit rip-off down<br />
the chain and we had some time ago determined that there ought<br />
to be an inquiry into meat prices, into beef pricing policies<br />
and what I've seen over recent days makes me all the more<br />
convinced that that's necessary. I hope that we can get the<br />
matter launched as quickly as possible but I can't make a<br />
judgement about when that will be until I have been fully<br />
a dvi se d.<br />
QUESTION: Just 6ne final point on the Premier's Conference,<br />
if I col ( inaudible)..<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well, there is no harm in persistence but I<br />
can't guarantee that my answer will change.<br />
QUESTION: Should the Premiers expect a fairly, if you like,<br />
non-reply from the Federal Government?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: The Premiers can expect a stance from the<br />
Australian Government that is completely atuned to Australia's<br />
economic needs. That is completely atuned the requirements<br />
of 1978 and to our determination to capitalise on the hard-won<br />
gains in the Australian economy over the last two and a half<br />
years. We've got inf'lation . down, the underlying trend is<br />
down. We don't intLend that that will be reversed. People<br />
overseas are starting to look upon the Australian economy with<br />
great favour. A number of countries are saying we wish-we<br />
could have done as well in overcoming economic ills and getting<br />
inflation down. They obviously don't say that privately,<br />
but they do say it they don't say it publicly but they do<br />
say it privately in conversation and there is respect for the<br />
determination and steadfastness that we have had in the<br />
pursuit of policies. Now this is meaning that countries are<br />
starting to look to Austra-lia as a favoured one for investment<br />
once again. People from Britain have for the first time in<br />
years invested in Commonwealth Securities. Now that says<br />
something about the Australian economy and the way it is<br />
being managed and it would be foolish in the extreme if we<br />
were to upset this by a change of course, by undue relaxation<br />
in policy because, I've made the point before and I made it<br />
overseas,, it's very easy for a Government to spend a few<br />
hundred million dollars listing out a budget in an effort to<br />
try and provide greater government employment but if in doing<br />
that, you alter the perceptions of your own economy, you cast<br />
or cause some doubts about the way in which people see your<br />
own economy and thereby lose say many times more than that<br />
three or four hundred million in a desperate from your own<br />
people, or from overseas then that's a very bad bargain for<br />
the country concerned it would be a bad bargain for Australia<br />
and while you might have more people on a government payroll,<br />
you'd have less people employed overall. That's not the sort<br />
of bargain that my government intends to undertake and I hope<br />
you wouldn't want us to. / 6 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
