<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4134</transcript-id>
    <title>CHRIST CHURCH CATHEDRAL OPENING</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/05/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004134.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
IjA. USTRALIAE 2<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS MAY 29, 1976<br />
/ Y&amp; T 67Y<br />
CHRIST CHURCH CATHEDRAL OPENING<br />
Today's ceremony-is not only an act of faith by the<br />
Church of England. In its own way, this project-symbolises<br />
Darwin's recovery from Cyclone Tracy, and the determiniation<br />
to build a better city.<br />
It reflects the faith of the citizens of DarwYin in the future.<br />
Thnere must have been many who doubted whether Darwin could<br />
ever rise again after the devastation of the cyclone. It<br />
is a measure of the determination of the former residents<br />
of Darwin and their affection for the city that so many have<br />
ratu. rned to help in the rebuilding.<br />
I understand that 7: he population is now only 8000 short<br />
of what it was on Chnristmas Eve 1974. The loss of the<br />
old Christ Church was one of the sad losses of the disaster.<br />
It had been one of Darwin's oldest buildings-it had<br />
stood for 72 years when the cyclone struck. In its<br />
build'ing it had sy,--bolised the diversity of people who had<br />
built Darwin. Its stone had been hewn by Chinese. Now<br />
a new cathedral church is being commenced, but it will<br />
have, links with the old Darwin. The ruins of Christ Church<br />
will be in c orporated in the new cathedral complex.<br />
I hope that the new church which will rise on this site will be<br />
a vital part of the new city. It will seat 300 worshippers<br />
and provide facilities for community activities, conferences<br />
and wedding receptions.<br />
1understand also that some thought is being given to<br />
setting up a cathedral choir school as part of this church<br />
complex.-Fund raising appeals will be launched next<br />
month in the Northern Territory and the rest of Australia to<br />
ehlp meet the cost of building the-new cathedral church.<br />
I urge strong support for these appeals. I am sure they<br />
will be supported.<br />
I am very conscious that it is the wish of the people of Darwin<br />
that the city should be rebuilt as quickly as possible. 2 </p>
<p>People. throughout Australia want to see Darwin rise again<br />
and soon. That is certainly the wish of the Commonwealth<br />
Government. Through the efforts of citizens, private<br />
enterfrise, the Housing Commission and the Reconstruction<br />
Commission the city is once more taking shape.<br />
The result of the efforts of individuals and private<br />
enterprise in rebuilding Darwin are plain for all to see.<br />
Nearly 2000 residents have commenced rebuilding their homes,<br />
250 have already completed them. Most business premises<br />
have been restored the recent auction sale of industrial<br />
land in Darwin suggests that private industry has confidence<br />
in the future of the city.<br />
The kind of city the new Darwin becomes will depend, in the<br />
end, on the commitment, the work, the willingness to cooperate<br />
of the people of Darwin. Government, can, and is, helping<br />
to establish the framework for the new city. It can offer<br />
aid and assistance. It can help to ensure that th. physical<br />
development provides a decent context for the life of the<br />
people. But the new Darwin, like the old, will in the end<br />
be the product of the people who live in it, and their<br />
attitudes to one another.<br />
The Federal Government is determined, for its part, to do what<br />
it. can to see thac che rebuilding of Darwin proceeds as<br />
quickly as possible.<br />
To aid this process we have increased the financial assistance<br />
for reconstruction in the next financial year. We believe<br />
that all Australians wish to see this done. I believe<br />
that the Commonwealth Government's funding of the Darwin<br />
Business Relief Loan Fund and the concessional 6 percent home<br />
rebuilding scheme have helped to inject confidence into the<br />
city. I hope it will not seem too much out of place on an<br />
occasion such as this if I mention some of the details,<br />
financial an, otherwise, or what has been done and what is<br />
proposed. The opportunity for me to mention these matters directly<br />
to the people of Darwin comes all too rarely. Nearly $ 3.5 million<br />
of low interest loans has been advanced to 223 small businesses<br />
to boost commerce and industry. Approvals for the home rebuilding<br />
scheme have now passed 500, with a total value of $ 14.7 million.<br />
During the current financial year the people of Australia,<br />
through the Darwin Reconstruction Commission will have spent<br />
$ 110 million. I have been advised by my colleague, Mr Adermann<br />
that this will rise to $ 139.5 million next year.<br />
Three new homes a day are now being completed for the Reconstruction<br />
Commission. The rate of construction will accelerate in the<br />
months ahead. More than $ 16 million has been spent since<br />
Cyclone Tracy on weather proofing and repairs to private<br />
and government buildings and on cleaning up the debris and<br />
making damaged homes safe. / 3 </p>
<p>The Darwin Reconstruction Commission is also responsible<br />
for the restoration and upgrading of the whole range of<br />
government services a community like Darwin needs, including<br />
the new Casuarina Hospital..<br />
$ 44-million has been spent this financial year on new and<br />
rebuilt homes. $ 5 millionhas been spent on education<br />
facilities and $ 8 million on public health and welfare.<br />
The city's basicjinfrastructure and community facilities<br />
have largely been reestablished. We are all indebted to<br />
the members and staff of the Darwin Reconstruction Commission.<br />
A major contribtuion in overcoiming the accommmodation<br />
oroblem in Darwin is also being made by the Northern<br />
Territory Housing Commission.<br />
In 1975/ 76 the Commission was provided with $ 13 million.<br />
In 1976/ 77 this will rise to $ 21.2 million. The<br />
Housing Commission has commenced construction of 360 new<br />
houses. 100 have already been completed. 105 f<br />
have been commenced, 49 are completed. Permanent<br />
repairs have begun on 118 houses. In addition, the Northern<br />
Territory Port Authority has spent $ 1 million this financial<br />
year rehabilitating and upgrading Darwin's port facilities.<br />
The amount that being spent on the reconstruction<br />
b-the people of Au. stralia through Government and through<br />
private activities shown the priority we all place on<br />
having a new city here that we can all be proud of.<br />
Darn, of course, has a new role to look forward to with<br />
the movement of Territory towards statehood. We are<br />
moving quickly to give effect. to this undertaking. A Bill<br />
to amend the Nort-rn Territory ( Administration) Act has<br />
already been introduced into the Federal Parliament.<br />
When enacted this Bill will pave the way for the transfer of<br />
executive ' Rowers to the Legislative Assembly.<br />
My colleague the Minister for the Northern Territory is in<br />
regular contact with the majority leader, Dr Letts, and<br />
the executive members of the Assembly. I am confident<br />
that the Legislative Assembly will soon assume responsibility<br />
for a number of functions of Government in the Northern Territory.<br />
The success of these-measures will depend very largely on the<br />
good will and common sense of our Federal and local legislators<br />
and administrators. It will also depend significantly<br />
on the development of commerically viable industries which<br />
will generate incomes and revenue within the Northern Territory.<br />
The potential and the Territory is exciting. 1Within weeks<br />
of assuming office, the Minister for the Northern Territory<br />
ended a long period of stagnation and frustration in the minerals<br />
area by issuing new mining exploration leases and offshore<br />
permits. ./ 4 </p>
<p>The development of the region's:. minerals depends<br />
very much on our ability to contain inflation and<br />
rising costs. Possibly not part of Australia has been<br />
more adversely affected by inflation than the Territory.<br />
The Government is determined to restore economic<br />
responsibility to Australia and to our relations with<br />
' our trading partners, the natural markets for our minerals<br />
and metals as well as our agricultural and pastoral exports.<br />
The Territory unquestionably has a great future. The<br />
rebirth of Darwin shows what is possible where people<br />
commit themselves to a goal and dedicate themselves to<br />
realising it. Great tasks like this are never easy.<br />
The work is often frustrating and difficult. I doubt<br />
if anything that is worthwhile can ever be otherwise.<br />
I started off by talking about an act of faith by the<br />
Church of England. We all share a faith that by<br />
cooperating together we can build a country which will<br />
ensure decent lives for all its people. The new cathedral<br />
complex will be a symbol of that cooperation between<br />
people that we all seek.<br />
I congratulate all who are associated with the rebuilding<br />
of the Church. 000000000 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
