<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1145</transcript-id>
    <title>THE THIRD COMMONWEALTH AND EMPIRE LAW CONFERENCE SYDNEY N.S.W  24TH AUGUST 1965  SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/08/1965</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001145_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
THE THIRD COMMONWEALTH AND EMPIRE LAWJ CONFE] RENCE<br />
24TH AUGUST. 1965<br />
Speech by th~ e PriLme Minister? the Rt. Hon. Sir Rober~ t Menzies<br />
My Lords, Your Excellencies and Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
I think my task this morning is to declare this<br />
Conference open, but as I was once a lawyer, now a politician,<br />
it is obviously expected that I should make a speech with<br />
enough brevity to save the day for you.<br />
I want to make two confessions at the outset.<br />
The first will be preceded by a statement. You see their<br />
lordships and their honours gathered here. They don't always<br />
appear in robes of that kind and when I walked in this<br />
morning, Mr. Kerr said to me, " All the judges have been to<br />
church" in a rather accusing way I thought,, ( Laughter) because<br />
I had been flying down from Canberra and they had been to<br />
church to which I made a reply which I want to repeat. I<br />
mentioned it to one or two of the judges outside and I had<br />
very little appreciation. I said, " Under those circumstances,<br />
I would have expected them to be in the odour of sanctity,<br />
but all I can smell is mothballs." ( Laughter)<br />
Now, Sir, as you have pointed out, this is not a<br />
political conference. We are here as lawyers and I am delighted<br />
to find myself in the company of so many lawyers because I<br />
confess to-you that the law was my first love and remains my<br />
last. I have always regarded politics as a somewhat untimely<br />
interruption in my enjoAnt of law.<br />
So this isn't a political conference as you have said.<br />
It is a gathering of lawyers, and I venture to say it is a very<br />
timely event, particularly in this confused period of modern<br />
history where the rule of law and the institutions of the law<br />
are both under challenge. I begin by saying that because I<br />
think we ought to face up to that fact that there is a challenge<br />
to the law, a challenge to the institutions of the law. And<br />
I hope, Sir? that whatever vastly important matters of detail<br />
may be considered at this conference that the great principles<br />
will not be entirely forgotten.<br />
Now I suppose most of us lawyers were brought up on<br />
A. V. Dicey and we know a little, in words, about his two great<br />
principles of the sovereignty of Parliament and the rule of<br />
law. Well, his principle of the sovereignty of Parliament I<br />
don't need to take very much time about because it is by no means<br />
of universal application. He was writing about Great Britain<br />
with no written Constitution and evolved position for the<br />
institution of government and he was able to -say, with<br />
substantial accuracy, thal Parliament was all-powerful, was<br />
sovereign. This is not, of course wholly true in Australia.<br />
We have a written Constitution. that's an advantage that every<br />
lawyer here will appreciate. ( Laughter) And under that written<br />
constitution, you have what might be called roughly a division<br />
of sovereignty between the Commonwealth and the States, and even<br />
then, as we all know, it is by no means complete, because as the<br />
Constitution now stands, there are certain thin sthat can't be<br />
done either by the Comnonealthar the States, The immortal Section<br />
92 of the Constitution has taken care of that, to give only one<br />
example. ov. / 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
Therefore, Sir, chie principle of the sovereignty of<br />
Parliament is not one that we can become eloquent about in afterdinner<br />
speeches when we are seeking to state what the elements are<br />
in common in the Commonwealth because that is not one of them.<br />
And I am not complaining about that. There are very many newlyindependent<br />
countries in the world who don't, as yet, or there are<br />
some who don't as yet have a Parliament in our sense, or for that<br />
matter of course, recognise its sovereignty. Parliament and the<br />
authority of Parliament and the pirty system and the conflicts<br />
which precede the choice of a Parliament and the proceedings of<br />
Parliament, these are all rather peculiar to some countries<br />
including our own in Australia but not of universal validiiy,<br />
because whatever the sovereigniy of' Parliament does mean in any<br />
country, if it can be used as an expression at all it must<br />
connote the authority of Parliament over the executive by its<br />
power to dismiss or to reject.<br />
W'ell, Sir, put that on one side because I don't want<br />
to dwJll on it. It is no longer a matter of common existence,<br />
it is no longer a common factor in all Commonwealth countries<br />
though I hope some day it will be.<br />
What about the rule of law. I turn to that because<br />
to me and I am sure to you the rule of law is the vital<br />
element in a hiigh civilisation, and we as lawyers, I venture to<br />
say, are bound in conscience to battle to establish it and to<br />
maintain it. The rule of law has many aspects familiar to<br />
lawyers. They may not be too familiar to those who are not.<br />
But there are two aspects of the matter to which I, for one,<br />
attach immense importance. One is that there sh-ould be punishment<br />
or restraint of anybody only After ordinary proceedings<br />
before the ordinary courts, so that we all know that wie are not<br />
going to be punished for something, we are not going to be put<br />
under physical restraint in relation to some matter unless we<br />
have gone or been taken before the courts, the ordinary courts,<br />
and there have applied to us the law which applies to all other<br />
people. This is to be contrasted with arbitrary power. There<br />
are still symptoms of it in the world preventive detention by<br />
the executive. This is, of course, the very antithesis of the<br />
rule of law. The second aspect of it is involved in the first,<br />
that because of the rule of law no man is above the law everybody<br />
in the country from the most highly-placed dowm to the<br />
most insignificant, if you care to put it that way they are both<br />
under the law, ñ iot one of them above it; subject Zo the<br />
ordinary law and the ordinary tribunals.<br />
Now, Sir, that is so important-it is a matter to<br />
which much attention still has to be direded in many countries<br />
of the world, but it is of prime importance and you notice that<br />
involved in it is the position of the courts and of the people.<br />
I just want to say this to you that the courts, the courts of<br />
law in this country, in any other country represented at this<br />
conference, must be authoritative and strong, and I just want to<br />
remind all barristers who are here that an authoritative and<br />
strong court requires a strong judge but it also requires strong<br />
advocacy. This is sometimes forgotten. In my own time, I<br />
have been some terrible performances of advocacey, apparently a / 3 </p>
<p>-3<br />
subconsciously based on the idea that the judge will have to<br />
decide it anyhow and that's his business. A weak barrister,<br />
an ill-prepared one or that utter curse, if I may say so,<br />
who either can't distinguish between a strong argument and a<br />
weak one or lacks the decision to select and concentrate, he<br />
is a curse that one. WIe've all heard him before today. He<br />
harms his client but he also harms the judge because the judge<br />
has not been given the assistance that every judge must look<br />
for when he knows that he has to determine an issue between the<br />
parties. One other remark I would like to make to you because<br />
I have been warned to be brief. Lawyers, if I may say so to all<br />
of them, must avoid a narrow outlook. I don't mean to say chat<br />
I am asking people not to concentrate on the work in hand<br />
because I know that is the very essence of legal practice, but<br />
they are not to achieve a narrow outlook. It is a good thing<br />
to find time for thinking, for example, about the relations<br />
between the law and life in a cnanging world. The reilations<br />
between law and life, the law not being something desiccated<br />
and detached, unrelated to the life of human beings constantly<br />
to see it against a human background. And therefore, while<br />
remaining concerned with the interpretation of the law and its<br />
application the application of the law to the facts lawyers<br />
really should find time and and mental energy to influence law<br />
reform, for example, in substance as well as in procedure, and<br />
this is to be achieved, partly by professional action, and under<br />
some circumstances by political action.<br />
I'll just add one word about political action. A<br />
well-furnished lawyer is a gro3t asset in any Parliament and<br />
if he be a well-furnished lawyer, he will be listened to in any<br />
Parliament. If he can add to the techniques that he has<br />
acquired in court and in the study, a wider warmth and variety<br />
of human contacts in other words, gets the feeling of<br />
politics and the sense of a Parliament, which is a peculiar<br />
place but rather the same all over the world-you must get<br />
the feel of it if he can do this that weli-furnished lawyer,<br />
he can come to great prominence and influence and have his<br />
opportunity from time to time to do something about the reform<br />
of the law in the light of changing circumstances in a very<br />
rapidly changing world.<br />
Sir, in my own time, in my thirty years in Canberra<br />
. it is hard to believe, looking at my boyish countenance that<br />
thirty-one years ago I was Attorney-General of Australia, and<br />
therefore I have had all that time since and in that time<br />
there have been too few of the people that I have been<br />
describing, too few well-furnished lawyers coming into<br />
politics, not too many. It is a cheap cynicism that I always<br />
try to correct when I hear people saying, " Oh, there are too<br />
many lawyers in politics". W4ell, I suppose it may depend on<br />
how you define ' lawyer", but I started off by talking about<br />
somebody, the desirable person, a well-furnished lawyer. All<br />
I can say is that my own Parliament would be much better off<br />
if we had more than we have and it would be a disaster if we<br />
had less. Now, that little homily I don't lik-a making<br />
speeches before lunch and I daresay you don't like listening<br />
to them ( Laughter) but there is no escape this time because<br />
here I am, and when I have heard a few more speeches that will<br />
be of very great interest to me, I must set about getting back<br />
to Canberra in time to be cross-examnined at half-past two at<br />
Question Time, and so I declare this Conference open. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
