<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>374</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH AT THE WHEAT RESEARCH INSTITUTE, NARRABRI,</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/09/1961</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000374_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R. G. MENZIES<br />AT THE WHEAT 1HESE. RCH INSTITUTE, NARRABRI,<br />FRIDAY 29TH SEPTMBER, j.<br />Sir, and ladies and gentlemen:<br />I have been listening to the Chairman's speech with great interest<br />and it has left me with a very, very clear impression that he is rather<br />favourably disposed to the wheat industry. ( Laughter) 1 hope he will correct<br />me if I have the wrong idea.<br />But one error he certainly fell into: he seemed to tnink that this<br />was one of the rare occasions on which I could hear about the wheat industry.<br />I have been sitting in Parliament, man and boy, one Parliament or another, for<br />31 years, or 32 years, and I have never heard about anything else except the<br />wheat industry' And I don't suppose I will fail to hear about it in future.<br />As a imatter of fact I have been looking forward to this very much<br />because though I belong to that group of people sometimes referred to as " city<br />slickF. rs", being a lawyer by trade, I was born in the Mallez, in the middle of<br />the wheat country and wheat wo: the commodity I heard most about for the first<br />12 or 14 years of my life. I am old enough to remember the great drought of<br />1902 when in our district 2 inches of rain fell in the year, and that at the<br />wrong time. By the time summer was well on there was no grass, dead or alive,<br />and the north winds blew, and the sand came up out of the sandy loam and<br />deposited itself over any object that it 2ncountered, These were tremendous<br />experiences for people.<br />But I can also remember, as a small boy, an occasion when up from<br />Melbourne came an agricultural expert from the Department of Agriculture and<br />he was a very good man, indeed. On all counts a man of considerable<br />authority. But in those days of course I am sure it isn't so now wheat<br />farmers looked rather suspiciously at scientific gentlemen from the city. And<br />he went out and had a field day and I remember, as a small boy of abcut 9,<br />hanging around at the fringe of a group of about 20 or 30 or 40 farmers and he<br />was explaining to them the great importance in that partiualar soil of the use<br />of superphospLates. This was the first time that any of us, or any of those<br />listening had ever heard of them even as short a time ago as that. This,<br />Sir, was regarded wi-h immense reserve. 1" Wlhat's this new-fangled business"<br />" How much does it cost?" " How much do you need to use?" And he was explaining<br />to them that in their particular circumstances 1 cwt. night be a good idea.<br />Three or four farmers, who were the most advanced, daided to give it a go, but<br />in some moderation. So they put on half a hundredweight. But as a result of<br />putting on half a hundredweight they so improved their yield that other people<br />began to look on and be interested and to follow the example, But as you, Sir,<br />know, it literally takes years in the ordinary course of events for ideas of<br />that kind to be commonly accepted; and profitably acted upon.<br />It is, after all, not so very long ago, is it, that we began to have<br />our first great investigators in the breeding of strains of wheat? forget<br />sometimes about these great men. Many people today have forgotten about<br />Farrar. And yet Farrar began his experiments about 6 years before I was born,<br />And when I was, at the time I am talking about, 9 or 10, or 11 years old, I<br />can remember the enormous results that accrued when Federation wheat came into<br />general use Federation and Darts Imperial and these strains that had been<br />bred as rust resistant strains. Not entirely successful in the long run, but<br />with a tremendous, immediate impact on what occurred. And ever since then you<br />have had dedicated men going on with their work in the investigation of wheat.<br />You have had, particularly in recent times, the tremendous novel attention, I<br />rather think it is, given to the chemistry of the soil things which once<br />were regarded as acting according to some immutable law of nature. You can't<br />interfere with that: you fallow and you sow and you have a stubble and there<br />it is. But time goes on and research is finally winnirng its battle in the<br />minds of the industry and of the men w. o run the industry itself. This to me<br />is a tremendously important thing because by research you bring about changes<br />for the better; by research you accelerate progress, you improve production,<br />you improve quality, you nake yourself more competent to meet the demands of<br />the world.</p>
<p>And you need to, because the world is changing around us every<br />minute. I don't merel. y refer to the fact that there are threats of war, or<br />the circumstances even of the last few weeks which give the whole world cause<br />for arj. ety. But you take a problem that at this very moment our officials<br />are discussing overseas, the problem of the Common Market, I am not going<br />into any detail about this matter because a good deal has already been said<br />about it. But the wheat industry, it is quite clear, can be affected by<br />Great Britain going into the Common Aarket. It may aliaust be a certainty that<br />the old pattern of trade in wheat won't remain unaltered. I don't know.<br />Wve are all going to do our best to preserve it, and to improve it. But nobody<br />can say what is going to be the outcome of discussions in which Great Britain<br />ir negotiating with six countries of Europe and at the same time negotiating<br />with every country in the Commonwealth.<br />So that you have all these cross discussions and cross negotiations.<br />,1l these talks will go on a long time, a very long time. But from our point<br />of view what we have to get into our minds is this: that this is one more<br />proof that it is a changing world, that it isn't the old lines that ccn be<br />followed quite so simply, that it is undoubtedly true that if the wheat<br />industry is to go on being one of the most valuable significant industries in<br />iustralia we must find new mall. ets for wheat, we must find new methods of<br />cheapening the production of wheat, new methods of getting the greatest<br />possible value from the land, maybe new methods of marketing, I don't know.<br />But above all things we must find new millions of people in the world who<br />will want to buy from us. That is true of wheat. It is true of every other<br />agricultural product in Australia, but it is particularly true of wheat becauL<br />wheat, in the agricultural field, is one of our great major undertakings.<br />Therefore, Sir, I want to make clear that all the discussions that<br />will occur about the Common Market are not just arguments between politicians,<br />between people who are making a business deal about some commodity or other.<br />They are that; but they are far more than that. These are discussions which<br />remind us that for Australia, growing at the rate at which Australia is growing,<br />we must never rest until we have increased our markets all round the world. We<br />can, because most of the people in the world today live at a standard of living<br />immeasurably lower than any we know. But as time goes on, as help is extended,<br />as great international schemes bear fruit, the standard of living among the<br />millions in Asia and Africa will rise; and so will their demand for the kind<br />of thing that we produce so well in Australia. Therefore markets, markets,<br />markets we must look for them. But we mustn't fall into the error of<br />thinking that all you have to do is to find the market and all other things<br />will be added to you. The fact is that, though it is vital to find the markes<br />it is equally vital to fill it when you find it, to produce the goods for that<br />market. I have had some experience myself of people who took a few orders on<br />some trade mission this is fine but when orders came in by way of followup<br />the supplies were short. We must be able to supply every market that we<br />can find. That brings us back, once more, to the problem of research because<br />research is, in its nature, a slow business. Science doesn't proceed by a<br />series of brilliant improvisations. Above all agricultural science, the kind<br />of thing that is going to be done here, requires patient work and testing and<br />examination year by year. Research is a slow, painstaking thing, aiming at<br />a peat percentage of accuracy and a testinr. of results under every<br />conceivable circurstance. Therefore there is no time to be lost about<br />starting research, no time to be lost about encouraging it.<br />Let me remind you of this: when we were younger, a great deal<br />younger, there was a disposition to think that scicntists had alr. ost reached<br />their limit. They knew some of the broad principles of science, but so far<br />as the land was concerned, well, everybody knew what type of soil it was,<br />everybody knew, in the appropriate areas of Australia, that he ought to have<br />a three-year rotation and that in the black-soil country he wouldn't need one<br />at all I only discovered that during the Gwyder by-election. But you know,<br />all sorts of people knew all sorts of things and that was the end of knowledge.<br />But what has happened in Australia? What miracles have occurred? Whoever<br />thought, only a few years ago, of the trace elements work that has gone on in<br />Australia, of hundreds and hundreds of thousands of acres re-claimed from<br />uselessness into high productivity, either pastoral or agricultural? Nobody<br />ever thought of it only a f'c years ago. AWhoever thought, as I said, a few<br />years before I was born ii-yself, of the breeding of strains of whnt in order to</p>
<p>produce certain results which would avoid damage in the field? Somebcdy<br />thought of them. Somebody got on with them. I venture to say that the man<br />who goes onto a farm today, if he is prepared to take advantage of the<br />knowledge that is available to him, will go on twice as well equipped from the<br />beginning, as his father was. Then, if he can add to that, as much work as his<br />father did, as much enthusiasm as his father had, well there is no limit to<br />what may result from it.<br />Sir, I don't need, I hope, to say any more to satisfy you that it is<br />no mere formality for me to come here. I think this is a great enterprise. I<br />am perfectly certain that without this foundation, and other places in which<br />woik of this kind is being done in Australia, we will net be able to take our<br />place in the world of international commerce in wheat that we must be prtpared<br />to take as the world changes around us. So that in the name of our orn<br />country, in the name of new and expanding markets, in the name of that necessay<br />efficiency which will reduce costs mounting otherwise to thc point of<br />destruction, in the name of all those things I call this Foundatio:ñ blet9ed. I<br />think this is a splendid business.<br />I wasn't entirely su. prised to hear my friend the Chairman throw out a<br />broad hint of a financial kind I'm accustomed to that. I always say, " Yes,<br />my dear fellow, you must drop me a line about it". Oetween ourselves they never<br />forgot. But we will put that on one side. -e happen to be a modest<br />contributor to this thing. But that this thing is good, that this thing is,<br />in its nature, essential I don't for a moment doubt. It is a very great honour<br />to me, a very great privilege, to be here, to say something to you, however<br />briefly, and to declare it open. ( Applause)</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
