<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10775</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                  THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                  RADIO INTERVIEW                  FRAN KELLY - RADIO NATIONAL, ABC</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/06/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE....................................................</p>
<p>KELLY:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, Pauline Hanson has again accused Aboriginal Australians</p>
<p>   of getting preferential treatment in Government funding. She says</p>
<p>   she'll campaign against the existence of native title and she</p>
<p>   has warned that Aboriginal Australians and the United Nations are</p>
<p>   plotting to establish taxpayer funded Aboriginal states. Are these</p>
<p>   sentiments racist?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I've read the speech she made last night and I've</p>
<p>   got to say it is not only an inaccurate, dishonest speech, but it</p>
<p>   verges on the deranged in various places. I said all along that</p>
<p>   whenever she says something that is wrong or against the interests</p>
<p>   of Australia I will attack it. And in a sense she has done the political</p>
<p>   debate in Australia a great service by delivering the speech because</p>
<p>   she has actually put down in black and white, in writing, her views,</p>
<p>   rather than relying on a series of one-liners and nudges and winks</p>
<p>   and inferences and general attitudes. And what she says about this</p>
<p>   United Nations declaration is wrong on four counts. Firstly, it's</p>
<p>   a draft declaration, is therefore not legally binding. It's</p>
<p>   not a treaty. Secondly, the Australian Government has not conspired</p>
<p>   as she suggests to keep it secret from the Australian public. If</p>
<p>   she had bothered to turn up to Parliament more frequently than she</p>
<p>   does, she would have known that one of the first things my Government</p>
<p>   did was to introduce an open, accountable treaty making process.</p>
<p>   We require treaties to be tabled in Parliament. We require a far</p>
<p>   more open process. We have, as a Government, significant reservations</p>
<p>   about this draft declaration. We have not approved it. We are not</p>
<p>   in the business of trying to tear the heart out of the Australian</p>
<p>   nation. It is not....to be involving the United Nations discussion</p>
<p>   is not a treacherous sell-out of the Australian people. Now, you</p>
<p>   ask me is it racist. The strict definition of a racist is somebody</p>
<p>   who believes that his or her race is superior to other races. Now,</p>
<p>   what she is doing, of course, is, I think, on this particular issue</p>
<p>   and what she said in this speech is appealing to irresponsible racist</p>
<p>   sentiment in the Australian community. It is a very irresponsible</p>
<p>   speech and the more it is analysed the more reason there will be</p>
<p>   for people not supporting her.</p>
<p>KELLY:</p>
<p>So she is racist in this context?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I've said, I mean, she is fanning racist sentiment.</p>
<p>   Now, let's not sort of, I mean, you and I had a discussion</p>
<p>   about the definition of a racist before we came on air and I think</p>
<p>   we agree that a racist, strictly speaking, is somebody who believes</p>
<p>   one race is superior to another. But by using this sort of language</p>
<p>   she is, I believe, appealing to racist sentiment. And can I also</p>
<p>   take the opportunity of saying that I saw an observation by Richard</p>
<p>   Court in the paper this morning that one of the problems is that</p>
<p>   there's been a vacuum left by the failure of the Senate to</p>
<p>   pass the Native Title Amendment Act. If our Native Title Bill had</p>
<p>   been passed by the Democrats and the minority parties and the Labor</p>
<p>   Party in the Senate, this native title issue would now be off the</p>
<p>   national agenda. And it wouldn't be possible for people like</p>
<p>   Mrs Hanson to run around Australia saying that native title is going</p>
<p>   to lead to taxpayer funded Aboriginal states within Australia. Now</p>
<p>   I mean that is just plain hysterical nonsense.</p>
<p>KELLY:</p>
<p>Okay, if it's hysterical nonsense, if it's a deranged</p>
<p>   account and if she is fanning racist sentiment, will you now declare</p>
<p>   that the Federal Liberal Party will not give her any preferential</p>
<p>   treatment when it comes to preferences?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look Fran, I have said on that issue that that will be dealt with</p>
<p>   in the normal processes of the Party and I am not going to say any</p>
<p>   more. I would remind you, however, that at the last election the</p>
<p>   Labor Party, in my seat of Bennelong and in Mr Beazley's seat</p>
<p>   of Brand, gave Australians Against Further Immigration, who have</p>
<p>   now in Victoria merged with One Nation to form a single party, gave</p>
<p>   preferences to that party ahead of the Liberal Party. What the Labor</p>
<p>   Party has done in relation to the preference issue is to adopt a</p>
<p>   stunt and to elevate it into a huge national issue. Now, parties</p>
<p>   from time immemorial, major parties, have allocated preferences</p>
<p>   towards the end of their ticket in a fairly hit-or-miss fashion.</p>
<p>   You know that and so does Mr Beazley.</p>
<p>KELLY:</p>
<p>Isn't it a bit different here because what we see is One Nation</p>
<p>   with a big block of votes, for instance, in this Queensland election?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Fran, I will deal with the, if I may, we're in the middle</p>
<p>   of this Queensland election. I will deal with the Federal electoral</p>
<p>   implications of preference allocation at the right time.</p>
<p>KELLY:</p>
<p>But at the moment in the middle of the Queensland election you</p>
<p>   are not uncomfortable with the fact that some One Nation candidates</p>
<p>   may be elected with the help of Liberal and National Party preferences?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I don't believe that will happen. I am certainly not</p>
<p>   uncomfortable with the stance that the Queensland Coalition has</p>
<p>   taken in the Queensland election campaign. Their enemy is the Labor</p>
<p>   Party and I take the opportunity of saying to a lot of decent people</p>
<p>   who might be thinking of voting for One Nation because they may</p>
<p>   feel economically insecure. If you go ahead and do so you would</p>
<p>   be voting for a party whose leader has a very, very flimsy grasp</p>
<p>   on reality in relation to certain issues, is prepared to deliberately</p>
<p>   misrepresent the position of my Government. When she talks about</p>
<p>   native title she has missed the large number of Parliamentary debates</p>
<p>   on native title and if our position on native title which was a</p>
<p>   moderate, middle-of-the-road position. We are prepared to give certainty</p>
<p>   to Australian farmers and pastoralists and indeed, if our position</p>
<p>   on native title had been adopted months ago by the Senate this would</p>
<p>   no longer be a major issue in Australian politics and the people</p>
<p>   who have got to carry the major responsibility for it still being</p>
<p>   on the agenda are the Australian Labor Party, the Australian Democrats</p>
<p>   and others in the Senate who have voted our compromise bill down,</p>
<p>   I mean, what they have done is to create the opportunity for the</p>
<p>   sort of speech that was made last night to be made.</p>
<p> KELLY:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, just before we move off this issue, yesterday you welcomed</p>
<p>   ex-ABC broadcaster Rod Henshaw as the new Liberal Candidate for</p>
<p>   the Federal Seat of Dickson. Last night Pauline Hanson said that</p>
<p>   Rod Henshaw compered the launch of One Nation in Ipswich and shared</p>
<p>   a lot of her views. Are people who share her views welcome candidates</p>
<p>   for the Liberal Party?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I understand that Rod Henshaw at the time was a paid broadcaster</p>
<p>   MC.</p>
<p> KELLY:</p>
<p>Does that make it all right?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Hang on, let me finish. He's also, as I understand, compered</p>
<p>   four occasions or award nights for Wayne Goss. He's done some</p>
<p>   work for Kim Beazley. He told my office that her observation about</p>
<p>   his sharing her views on a lot of issues was rubbish but if you</p>
<p>   want to know Rod Henshaw's views, I am quite happy, as a former</p>
<p>   ABC broadcaster he would be delighted to be interviewed by you.</p>
<p> KELLY:</p>
<p>If I could just move onto tax now, Prime Minister. On the one hand</p>
<p>   your promise to never, ever introduce a GST had a shelf life of</p>
<p>   three years, or one term of Parliament. Why should voters think</p>
<p>   that your latest promise, that the rate of a GST will not rise,</p>
<p>   should have a life any longer than that?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well Fran, I am putting my position in front of the Australian people</p>
<p>   before an election. There can be no more open, transparent way to</p>
<p>   conduct public affairs in this country, to say, this is our policy,</p>
<p>   if you like it vote for it, if you don't, vote against it.</p>
<p>   There is all the world of difference between that and what the Labor</p>
<p>   Party did in 1993 when they promised not to introduce a GST before</p>
<p>   the election, and after the election they introduced their own version</p>
<p>   of a GST. I mean, are you seriously saying that somebody can never</p>
<p>   change their mind?</p>
<p> KELLY:</p>
<p>No, what I am saying is I understand that.</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I am glad you acknowledge that people are entitled to change their</p>
<p>   mind.</p>
<p> KELLY:</p>
<p>But won't voters then also be led to think now that you might</p>
<p>   change your mind about the rate of a GST?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No they won't, because they will know that if I do have a change</p>
<p>   of mind about anything, and I certainly, I am obviously referring</p>
<p>   to the promises I made before 1996, I will put that change to the</p>
<p>   public but my position simply is this, Fran, that we are going to</p>
<p>   the next election with a detailed tax reform policy and that detailed</p>
<p>   tax reform policy will be out in the open. If people like it, they</p>
<p>   can vote for it. If they don't they can vote against it.</p>
<p> KELLY:</p>
<p>When will it be out in the open? You have promised on several occasions</p>
<p>   that the tax package will be released well before the next election.</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Fran, that, with respect, is just a wasted question. You know I</p>
<p>   am not in a position to say when it is going to be announced.</p>
<p> KELLY:</p>
<p>But it will be well before the next election?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It will be announced in plenty of time for people to digest it before</p>
<p>   they vote.</p>
<p> KELLY:</p>
<p>If an election was going to be held in August...</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Fran, don't waste my time asking those sort of hypothetical</p>
<p>   questions.</p>
<p> KELLY:</p>
<p>The latest Newspoll out today has support for a GST fading. Does</p>
<p>   that concern you?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No it doesn't. I haven't seen the detail of that poll</p>
<p>   but I imagine the question was just a straight question - are you</p>
<p>   in favour of a GST or not? Now if it is, then I am not surprised</p>
<p>   that people say no to that. I mean, I am not in favour of a GST</p>
<p>   on top of the present tax structure and we won't introduce</p>
<p>   it. I would only be in favour of a broad based, indirect tax if</p>
<p>   it involved the abolition of the wholesale sales tax, at least,</p>
<p>   and significant cuts in personal income tax. It has never been and</p>
<p>   it never will be our policy to put a GST on top of the existing</p>
<p>   tax structure.</p>
<p> KELLY:</p>
<p>You have said in Parliament that the Australian people will either</p>
<p>   believe you or they will believe Labor. In a sense, do both sides</p>
<p>   have a bit of a credibility problem coming into this and is that</p>
<p>   really the whole, part of the contributing factor to the rise in</p>
<p>   One Nation stocks, the credibility problems, the baggage that both</p>
<p>   major parties carry?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I think One Nation supporters are made up of three distinct</p>
<p>   groups. I think there are a group of people in the community who</p>
<p>   are racially motivated on some issues. That's one distinct</p>
<p>   group. I think she got a few voters out of my strong stance on guns</p>
<p>   and I am not going to compromise that stance, not under any circumstances</p>
<p>   and I make that very plain to her and to her supporters on that</p>
<p>   issue. The third group is a much larger one, are really just ordinary</p>
<p>   decent Australians who are attracted by one line solutions. They</p>
<p>   feel economically insecure. They think she has got the answers because</p>
<p>   she is different.</p>
<p> KELLY:</p>
<p>And they don't believe the promises of the major parties?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think it's more that they are, they have been knocked around</p>
<p>   by life. They predominantly live in regional Australia. They feel</p>
<p>   economically insecure and there are no easy solutions to many of</p>
<p>   these problems and she comes along and says, look it's all</p>
<p>   the fault of the foreigners and it's all the fault of the Aborigines</p>
<p>   and it's all the fault of somebody else. And they say, maybe</p>
<p>   that's right, we'll give her a go. Now the advantage in</p>
<p>   one sense of what she did last night in making a detailed speech</p>
<p>   was to expose her flimsy knowledge, to expose just how erratic is</p>
<p>   the line of argument that she's using on some issues and I</p>
<p>   think in that sense it's a warning to people who are contemplating</p>
<p>   voting for her that she has absolutely no solutions and I particularly</p>
<p>   in the context of the Queensland election, would say to those Coalition</p>
<p>   people who may be thinking of voting for her, it is a wasted vote.</p>
<p>   She has no answers. She has an insecure grasp of reality, in fact,</p>
<p>   and you ought to support the Borbidge Government which is really</p>
<p>   the only conservative alternative on offer. I mean, it's a</p>
<p>   Beattie Government or a Borbidge Government and if you are a conservative</p>
<p>   voter in Queensland and you want a conservative Government, you</p>
<p>   ought to vote for Borbidge.</p>
<p> KELLY:</p>
<p>Prime Minister; thank you.</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
<p>ENDS</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
