<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1332</transcript-id>
    <title> FOR PRESS: P.M.NO. 59/1966 MEETING BETWEEN THE PRIME MINISTERES OF AUSTRALIA AND NEW ZEALAND</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/06/1966</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001332.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS P. M. No. 59/ 1966<br />
MEETING BETWEEN THE PRIME MINISTERS OF AUSTRALIA<br />
AND NEW ZEALAND<br />
Mr. Holt and Mr. Holyoake met at Parliament House<br />
this morning, this being their first meeting as Prime Ministers.<br />
After talks lasting more than two hours, they<br />
lunched together with the New Zealand High Commissioner, Mr.<br />
Hazlett. Most of the discussion between the Prime Ministers<br />
was in the defence and foreign policy field. They went over some<br />
of the matters which will be engaging the SEATO Council during<br />
the week, but concentrated rather more on a joint consideration<br />
of the developments and the outlook in South-East Asia as viewed<br />
from Australia and New Zealand. Viet Nam and Indonesia were<br />
included in this survey. The Prime Ministers discussed not only<br />
the joint military operations in which Australia and New Zealand<br />
are engaged, but also the economic advancement of the area which<br />
they each recognise as being of first importance to the future<br />
stability and peace of Asia. They discussed also Mr. Holt's recent<br />
visit to South Viet Nam, Thailand, Malaysia and Singapore, and the<br />
impressions which Mr. Holt drew from it.<br />
Britain's defence position in South-East Asia came<br />
into the discussion. There was agreement by the Prime Ministers<br />
that a firm, continuing British presence is important, not only<br />
in terms of its defence significance, but in terms of the<br />
advantages which it will have for long term world stability and<br />
for Britain's own world role.<br />
They discussed Commonwealth affairs in the light<br />
of the Prime Ministers' Conference under consideration for later<br />
this year. Brief discussions occurred also in the context of<br />
the increasingly close trade relations developing out of the<br />
New Zealand/ Australia Free Trade Area arrangements.<br />
The Prime Ministers also covered the current<br />
economic situation in their respective countries.<br />
CAINBERRA<br />
26th June, 1966<br />
Later this afternoon, Mr. Holt will receive brief official<br />
calls from the Foreign Ministers of the Philippines, Thailand<br />
and Viet Nam. They will call on him individually.<br />
A. EGILETON<br />
Press Secretary to Prime Minister.<br />
26/ 6766 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
