<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4250</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS AT THE SENATE BANQUET GIVEN BY THE PRESIDENT OF THE REPUBLIC OF INDONESIA</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/10/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004250.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS FRI 8 OCTOBER 1976<br />
ADDRESS AT THE STATE BANQUET GIVEN BY THE PRESIDENT OF<br />
THE REPUBLIC OF INDONESIA<br />
It is an honour for me to visit Indonesia as a guest of<br />
the Indonesian Government and people, at your personal<br />
invitation. In your recent speech to the House of People's Representatives,<br />
on Independence Day this year, you spoke of your deep concern<br />
that Indonesia build up the production of its farms and<br />
factories, you spoke also of the visible signs of achievement.<br />
The new Palapa satellite system for domestic communication<br />
symbolises the progress Indonesia has made under your leadership.<br />
The importance of communications is just as great in relations<br />
between countries. We need to continue the habit of close<br />
and frank communication, and by doing so, create an atmosphere<br />
which makes difficult the development of dicisive issues.<br />
When there is a firm basis for mutual understanding, these<br />
issues can be handled in the calm atmosphere of discussion<br />
as between friends. This is why it is important that contacts<br />
at all levels between Australia and Indonesia should be encouraged.<br />
There exists already a broad range of contact and cooperation.<br />
This is reflected not only by growing economic investment in<br />
Indonesia by Australian firms, but also by extensive<br />
Government to Government cooperation that covers a broad<br />
range of matters.<br />
I hope and confidently believe that this relationship will<br />
consolidate with time and that it will always be beneficial<br />
to both nations.<br />
There is a growing cultural awareness in Australia of<br />
Indonesia which has been promoted in large measure by the depth,<br />
richness and diversity of Indonesia's culture.<br />
At the same time, Australian culture has also become more<br />
accessible to other countries.<br />
Indonesia and other countries of the region have seen exhibitions<br />
of Australian art, photography, graphi cs and Aboriginal art<br />
and crafts. </p>
<p>Performing groups have visited Indonesia, including the<br />
Australian Marionette Theatre, an orchestra of young players<br />
from the Sydney Coiiservatorium of Mvusi~ c and smaller musical<br />
groups. Libraries of[ Australiani books have been given to<br />
universities and other learned institutions. The small<br />
Australian cultural centre in Jakarta also makes its<br />
contribution. We are planning to increase its activities.<br />
Australians have increasingly had the opportunity to appreciate<br />
examples of Indonesian culture, in particular we remember a visit<br />
paid to several Australian states by Misi Kesenian, a<br />
talented company of Indonesian dancers and musicians last<br />
year. The Australian Government was happy to assist with<br />
their tour.<br />
Perhaps even more important in the longer term, some twelve<br />
thousand Australian school children now learn Bahasa Indonesian<br />
a three fold increase in the last decade.<br />
This means that at some time in the near future, if not already,<br />
Australia will be the largest Indonesian speaking nation<br />
in the world outside Indonesia itself.<br />
The next generation in Australia will be able to talk to the<br />
youth of Indoiesia in Indonesian. Surely this augurs well for the<br />
future of our relationship.<br />
Mr President, you have steered your nation through a most<br />
difficult period, with great skill. It is today, a more<br />
prosperous and respected nation because of your leadership.<br />
The hospitality you have extended to us has been greatly<br />
appreciated. Our discussions have already been very valuable<br />
in extending our understanding of each other' s views.<br />
I l. ook forward to continuing our talks tomorrow.<br />
000000000 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
