<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9203</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON PJ KEATING MP, INTERVIEW WITH FRAN KELLY ABC RADIO &quot;PM&quot; PROGRAM WEDNESDAY, 27 APRIL 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/04/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009203.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING, MP<br />
INTERVIEW WITH FRAN KELLY, ABC RADIO " PM" 1 PROGRAM,<br />
WEDNESDAY, 27 APRIL 1994<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
FK: Prime Minister, the last minute save of Abogriginal health funds last<br />
night, why did you undercut the normal budget process like that?<br />
PM: Because I think that that is one of the things that Prime Ministers do<br />
make sure the system works properly and I think that we hadn't<br />
maximised our opportunities in this area, and a further consideration of<br />
it has meant there will be a massive improvement in the funding of<br />
Aboriginal health in this country.<br />
FK: It has been reported today that Graham Richardson rang you and<br />
lobbied hard for you to intervene. Did he persuade you to persuade<br />
ERC?<br />
PM: That is totally without foundation. That is just a bit of Press Gallery<br />
corridor nonsense. Largely, what has been allocated last night is what<br />
would have been allocated, I think, had Graham Richardson remained<br />
the Minister. And the important thing is that -weare-going to see a<br />
huge increase in the program funding to around nearly $ 500 million<br />
dollars over the period.<br />
FK: But that is a long way short of the $ 800 million..<br />
PM: But Graham's submission was never ever for $ 800 million.<br />
FK: Where did that figure come from?<br />
PM: Well again, it was floating around. What has come out is what would<br />
have come out, but I have got to say, though, let me just say a couple<br />
things here about Dr Hewson in this matter. He did a press doorstop </p>
<p>this morning saying that I have lied to Senator Richardson, that I am<br />
lying. He has this very unpleasant habit of calling people liars. It<br />
seems to be his principal political tactic these days. Now, this is a<br />
fellow who said in the Times on Sunday 1987, " I live in fear of some<br />
Ministries, Aboriginal Affairs and Veterans Affairs, are wastes of my<br />
talents." Now, this is an area of policy which he said was a waste of<br />
his talents, he said that I had raised expectations in the Redfern<br />
speech about Aboriginal policy, but never delivered on them. We<br />
delivered Mabo in full, more then the Aboriginal community would have<br />
expected at the time. And as the Bills passed the Parliament Dr<br />
Hewson said it was a day of shame. This is a man without judgement<br />
and without integrity. Now, can I just say that as far as the<br />
Government is concerned that the things which we think can sensibly<br />
be done, these programs have got to be delivered on the ground. So,<br />
this is a big boost, but the important thing is it will be a boost which is<br />
also delivered effectively and efficiently.<br />
FK: It is a boost to funds, but people are still saying today that you have let<br />
them down. Expectations were raised, the figure, whether it was right<br />
or not, around was $ 800 million dollars. No one ever stepped in to say<br />
that that was not right.<br />
PM: But look, numbers around Press Gallery discussions and corridor<br />
conversation that has no Cabinet authorisation, for which a submission<br />
has never been lodged, has no status whatsoever. I mean, what has<br />
happened here is what would have happened in terms of the<br />
Governments general intentions about this area. And I must say<br />
Carmen Lawrence did a first class job in arguing the case in full<br />
Cabinet and the ERC yesterday.<br />
FK: How much of your decision to step in and get the funds boosted was a<br />
desire on your part to protect Carmen Lawrence from what would have<br />
been a very public defeat in virfuallfy the firsv-action.<br />
PM: Carmen doesn't need any protection whatsoever. I noticed some<br />
people jumped all over it. Some of the lower life's of the West<br />
Australian got all over it. But apart from that she doesn't need any<br />
help from me. She did well and effectively with a difficult brief. I mean,<br />
I made her the Minister for Human Services and Health, this is an<br />
agenda which was being developed by a former Minister and she has<br />
run with it with panache and alacrity.<br />
EK: What exactly did you promise Graham Richardson? He said at his<br />
final press conference that you had given your word that his package<br />
on Aboriginal health was safe. What was the promise?<br />
PM: That the broad outlines of the medical program and environmental<br />
health program would be funded in the budget. </p>
<p>FK: So the criticism today from people like AMA President, Brendan<br />
Nelson.<br />
PM: Well I thought he was complimentary.<br />
FK: He said, as I understand, he said it was a cruel hoax on Aboriginal<br />
people, this letting down their expectations.<br />
PM: These are all the people who wanted to damn Mabo. I mean, Dr<br />
Hewson stood in the Parliament and voted it down shamefully without<br />
a reason, and then, as it passed, calling it a day of shame. Remember<br />
he was recently up crying crocodile tears over Vietnam Veterans,<br />
today it is over Aboriginals. This is a fellow who said, ' I live in fear of<br />
some Ministries, Aboriginal Affairs and Veterans Affairs are a waste of<br />
my talents'. He says, when things are going well for the Government,<br />
he says the Government is running scared. I notice today in the<br />
Bulletin David McNicoll saying and he says With things going well<br />
for the Government, it seemed almost incredible that the Hapless<br />
Hewson emerged from his " retreat" and announced on television that<br />
the Keating Government was " running scared". Has Hewson no<br />
minders? Or doesn't he take any notice of advice?" Well, I can<br />
only say dead right.<br />
EK: Well, things are going well for the Government at the moment on the<br />
economy. There was a beautiful set of numbers again for you today<br />
with an inflation rate of 1.4 per cent for the year, with things going so<br />
well will you be able to fund the White Paper spending from growth<br />
without tax increases in the Budget?---<br />
PM: I'm not here to run through the White Paper numbers, but the<br />
Government's record of fiscal consolidation is second to none in the<br />
OECD over a decade. I mean, it's not what we say, it's what we do<br />
that matters. Can I just say about the inflation rate though, it is a<br />
tremendous outcome; .4 per cent for the quarter and 1'. 4 per cent for<br />
the year and, I think what it does clearly show is that the bond market<br />
has lost credibility as a guide to inflationary expectations. With<br />
everyone playing the game; business, the workforce producing a CPI<br />
as low as the only people not playing the game are the financial<br />
markets.<br />
FK: Why the decision not to go ahead with the jobs levy?<br />
PM: You will have to wait and see what's in the package. I said on election<br />
night, that this Government was governing for all Australians; that we<br />
wouldn't leave the unemployed behind; that we'd put an arm up and<br />
pull them up. When I said, that Dr Hewson said if he does that he will<br />
pull the rest of us down. I am not going to be deflected by John<br />
Hewson's callousness and we set in train the Green Paper processes<br />
and we have now considered it to produce a Wh-tef Pap'e That White </p>
<p>Paper will maintain the momentum of the economic changes which<br />
Australia has and in doing it sweep along all those areas of the<br />
economy that need support and that will be including outside of<br />
physical resources in the area of those who are long-term unemployed.<br />
That, I think, is a proper social and economic objective of a Labor<br />
Government, indeed any government, and the doing of it is something<br />
which will make this a country more economically efficient and more<br />
equitable.<br />
EK: What about the Medicare levy? Carmen Lawrence indicated before<br />
last week that a sm all rise in-the Medicare levy was probably a good<br />
idea to fund some health measures, yet now we hear no rise in the<br />
Medicare levy. Why not?<br />
PM: Again Fran, you will have to wait and see what's in the Budget, but can<br />
I just say this about these measures governments can resort to<br />
revenue measures of this kind. We have modestly increased the levy<br />
since 1983, but the public, I think, have always got to take the view<br />
that what comes in return is a quantum improvement or at least a<br />
qualitative improvement in the circumstance of their health and<br />
welfare. Therefore, occasions for increasing the levy have to be<br />
occasions where there are changes of that variety.<br />
FK: And there's not those kinds of changes right now? There's certainly<br />
plenty of changes being called for.<br />
PM: I think I'll have to say to you, you'll have to wait and see what's in the<br />
Budget.<br />
FK: The Opposition are saying today it is clear the Budget will include<br />
hundreds of millions dollars worth of increased taxes are they right?<br />
PM: I'm not confirming their nonsense. Here they are flat out holding<br />
themselves together. They are now having crisis meetings twice a<br />
week to try and keep themselves together and as Mr McNicoll<br />
described him " the Hapless Mr Hewson" is flat out staying afloat. So, I<br />
think he should wait and see what's in the Budget and then he can<br />
have all the time he likes to make judgements about it.<br />
FK: Just finally Prime Minister on South Africa. Black Africans are voting<br />
for the first time today. Australia has played a fairly significant role in<br />
getting to this point. How do you feel watching black Africans casting<br />
their votes?<br />
PM: I think it is very moving to see television coverage of voters lining up<br />
for South Africa's first non-racial elections. There was a nice picture<br />
on the front page of Ne1sorL. Man~ ela's niece going through the novel<br />
experience of voting. Things seem to be going peacefully and not<br />
withstanding the problems of the recent bombings and this must be a </p>
<p>tribute to the political leadership of the country and most particularly<br />
Mr Mandela. We are contributing as you know to the Commonwealth<br />
Electoral Office Task Force in monitoring the activities of the national<br />
peace keeping force and we have got, as you know, two former Prime<br />
Minister's who will represent Australia at the inauguration. So, you are<br />
right, we have a lot in this, we have had a very firm policy on apartheid<br />
and South Africa for a long period of time and it is very pleasing to see<br />
the course of democracy that that country is taking.<br />
FK: Prime Minister, thank you.<br />
PM: Thank you, Fran.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
