<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7864</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, 21 DECEMBER 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/12/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007864.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER7<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, 21<br />
DECEMBER 1989<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
PM; Just a statement, no questions?<br />
JOURNALIST: What did Mr Bush have to say to you this<br />
morning when he called you, Mr Prime Minister?<br />
PM: Well he explained the circumstances of the military<br />
intervention by the United States. Of course, let me say<br />
that the Government regrets any circumstances where<br />
intervention by a military force occurs. However, I want<br />
to make it clear as I did to President Bush when he rang<br />
me this morning, that we do understand the circumstances<br />
under which the United States did intervene. It will be<br />
appreciated that on the 15th December the Panamanian<br />
National Assembly which is of course under the control<br />
of General Noriega -declared Panama to be in a state of<br />
war with the United States and gave full powers in those<br />
circumstances to General Noriega. The following day an<br />
unarmed, off-duty American serviceman was killed and this<br />
was followed by the harassment of other United States<br />
personnel, including threats to the wife of one of those<br />
personnel. Those were circumstances which were such that<br />
S the United States believe they couldn't tolerate any<br />
longer. The White House has outlined and the President<br />
confirmed to me the limited aims of the intervention.<br />
They are firstly, to safeguard American lives. Secondly,<br />
to restore democracy in Panama and further, of course, to<br />
protect the integrity of the Panama Treaty obligations.<br />
The position is that the organisation of American States<br />
and the other governments including Australia, have<br />
rejected the Noriega regime. There will be no intention<br />
of course, for the United States to stay in there for any<br />
longer period than to achieve the limited and specific<br />
objectives which they have outlined. It's also<br />
significant to understand I believe, that the Panamanian<br />
representatives who were elected by democratic processes<br />
in May of this year have indicated their support for the<br />
Untied States action and those representatives, as we<br />
understand, have been sworn in as the legitimate<br />
representatives of Panama. Now those are the<br />
circumstances, some of which of course we were publicly<br />
aware of and which have been now confirmed to me by<br />
George Bush in the personal conversation he initiated<br />
with me this morning. I repeat that the Government of<br />
Australia regrets any circumstances where this sort of </p>
<p>.1r M VVorr-z cF~ nn -rct. 1 o--~ or r, i 9 v: o<br />
2<br />
military intervention is necessary but in the<br />
circumstances we understand the necessity that was<br />
perceived by the President and the Administration of the<br />
United States to take this action.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, have you had any advice on<br />
whether any Australian citizens might be in Panama at the<br />
moment? PM:. I've had no specific advice of any I guess it's<br />
certain that there would be some Australian citizens<br />
there. But I've had no advice of any in danger.<br />
JOURNALIST: Did you receive any information of Noriega's<br />
whereabouts? PM: No. At this stage the President was not aware. He<br />
said that to use his language there were any number<br />
-of rabbit-holes into which he may have been able to<br />
scurry. of course it is the intention of the United<br />
States to apprehend him and of course if possible to take<br />
him to the United States to face the drug charges that<br />
are levelled against him there.<br />
JOURNALIST: Will Australia be taking any diplomatic<br />
initiatives in support of the American action?<br />
PM: Well I would think that a clear statement I've made<br />
of an understanding of the position is to be seen and is<br />
intended to be seen as supportive.<br />
JOURNALIST: inaudible<br />
PM: No. I prefaced by the remarks I made here that we<br />
regret any circumstances that do arise where military<br />
intervention occurs and of course there'll be many<br />
circumstances in which one wouldn't support it. But I<br />
have indicated that we do understand that in the<br />
circumstances with which the President of the United<br />
States was faced, they had no alternative. I mean you<br />
have the situation where unanimously the Panamanian<br />
National Assembly declared Panama in a state of war with<br />
the United States. I may say that the President<br />
indicated to me that the fact of them declaring<br />
themselves at war with the United States hadn't induced a<br />
great sense of panic in the United States but when that<br />
was followed as it was, by the killing of an off-duty and<br />
unarmed American serviceman and then significant<br />
harassment of other United States personnel and including<br />
threats of a sexual nature to the wife of an American<br />
citizen, then a position had been reached in the context<br />
of that declaration of a state of war where the United<br />
States felt it could not tolerate that position any<br />
longer. And of course what we've got to understand is<br />
that there were these elections in May which were<br />
internationally observed and the observers indicated that<br />
those elected had been elected as a result of proper<br />
Z I P I Z 9 1 1 Z: p 1 NO VQZ7 r, 0Z </p>
<p>0 0 V V 0 r = q J<br />
3<br />
process. That process was overthrown, rejected by<br />
General Noriega.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, in May Senator Evans said<br />
there will be serious issues of principle if America were<br />
to turn up intervention his words a notch or two.<br />
There have been certain things that have changed since<br />
then but aren't there still issues of Panamanian<br />
sovereignty involved here?<br />
PM: You have a situation in line with what the Foreign<br />
Minister said. I mean I don't think anyone is going to<br />
say that a declaration of a state of war on the part of<br />
Panama is an insignificant circumstance,. a very<br />
significant change of circumstance. But as the President<br />
said, that of itself was not enough to initiate action.<br />
But when following that state of intention on the state<br />
of war on the part of Panama against the United States<br />
was then followed by the absolutely inexcusable killing<br />
of an off-duty and unarmed American serviceman, you have<br />
a very, very significant change of circumstances.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, did President Bush indicate<br />
what he would think was an acceptable time for the US to<br />
be-in Panama?<br />
PM: He indicated that he didn't want to be in there any<br />
longer than was necessary to achieve the limited<br />
objectives. ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
