<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10777</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                  THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                DOORSTOP INTERVIEW - SYDNEY</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/12/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE.............................................................................................</p>
<p>Like millions of Australians over the past four days I have followed</p>
<p>   with anxiety and despair the tragic events in the Sydney-to-Hobart</p>
<p>   yacht race, and on behalf of the government I want to express my</p>
<p>   condolences to the families of those who died, they lost their lives</p>
<p>   following a sport they loved but the loss will nonetheless be very</p>
<p>   heavy for their families.</p>
<p>I also want to express on behalf of the entire nation my immense</p>
<p>   admiration for the rescue operation that was mounted. The Australian</p>
<p>   Maritime Safety Authority, which had overall responsibility for</p>
<p>   it, performed its task magnificently and I don't think there'd</p>
<p>   be an Australian who watched a television set over the last 48 hours</p>
<p>   that wouldn't be filled with admiration for those men and women</p>
<p>   who went down to winch the sailors, the yachtsmen, to safety. The</p>
<p>   way in which people in our volunteer services, our navy our police</p>
<p>   and all the rescue operators private and public the way in which</p>
<p>   they continually risked their lives to help others is something</p>
<p>   that fills me with great respect and admiration and I want on behalf</p>
<p>   of a very grateful nation and I know the families of many people</p>
<p>   who've been rescued to express my respect and my profound admiration</p>
<p>   for the professionalism and the bravery of the efforts that they</p>
<p>   undertake They yet again remind all of us of how dependant we are</p>
<p>   on many people who put their lives on the line to help us carry</p>
<p>   on our daily lives and to pursue the sporting activities and the</p>
<p>   pleasures that we all love. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard are you keen to see an inquiry investigate this tragedy?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I thought the inquiries that have been established by the Cruising</p>
<p>   Yacht Club of Australia and also the coronial inquiry are adequate,</p>
<p>   I am quite certain that they will get to the bottom of anything</p>
<p>   that needs to be investigated. I think it's important to have</p>
<p>   a calm examination and to leave it to those who organise the event</p>
<p>   and the normal authorities to investigate things rather than calling</p>
<p>   for special separate inquiries.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Don't you think there should be a public inquiry?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think what is proposed is suitable. The coroner will inquire</p>
<p>   in the normal way and I don't think it's appropriate for</p>
<p>   me to be suggesting anything else.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do you think, considering the weather conditions were known a day</p>
<p>   in advance the race may... possibly should have been called off?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look, I have every sympathy for the organisers of the race when</p>
<p>   something terrible like this happens. People immediately say well</p>
<p>   this or that should have been done. I'm not a yachtsman, I</p>
<p>   have to respect the views of people who are and who understand the</p>
<p>   sea. It sounds pretty sensible to me that the only principle you</p>
<p>   can work by is that each skipper is in command of his own ship and</p>
<p>   he alone has to decide what that boat is going to do and I'm</p>
<p>   persuaded by that.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, how did you feel when you first heard reports that there</p>
<p>   could have been up to 10 people missing and boats missing?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I was, like everybody else, I was terribly upset and disturbed.</p>
<p>   And it's...I mean the Sydney-to-Hobart yacht race is part</p>
<p>   of the Christmas New Year period of Australia, it's part of</p>
<p>   our way of life and these people have lost their lives following</p>
<p>   a sport they love. That doesn't make it any easier for their</p>
<p>   families and I think it's just a miracle, for which we should</p>
<p>   be very thankful, that more lives weren't lost and the people</p>
<p>   you can thank for that are very much the people in the rescue operations.</p>
<p>   I think they are magnificent. They risk their lives in a quite unselfish</p>
<p>   way and they deserve our thanks.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Does it cast a cloud over the race in the future?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER</p>
<p>Oh look, I don't think so. I...it's a tragedy but</p>
<p>   there are many, tens of thousands of Australians who are very keen</p>
<p>   sailors and yachtsmen and they'll go on and they'll want</p>
<p>   to go on and that's...and I'm quite sure they're...those</p>
<p>   who have been touched by this tragedy would want them to go on.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, on another matter, the situation in Yemen, what do we</p>
<p>   know about that, and will you be making any government to government</p>
<p>   talks about it?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, the Foreign Minister will be saying something about it this</p>
<p>   morning, I know that tragically an Australian has been killed, apparently</p>
<p>   in crossfire between his captors and the army of the Yemen federation.</p>
<p>   Apparently there were two Australians who were kidnapped by an Islamic</p>
<p>   extremist group that's having a running battle with the Yemeni</p>
<p>   authorities and tragically an Australian has lost his life as a</p>
<p>   result. Now the Foreign Minister will be pursuing the matter very</p>
<p>   vigorously with the government of the Yemen. It should stressed,</p>
<p>   of course, that the group responsible is a group that's very</p>
<p>   antagonistic to the government in that country and is regarded as</p>
<p>   a terrorist group in that country. But I do take the opportunity</p>
<p>   of issuing a general reminder to Australians travelling overseas</p>
<p>   to seek consular advice if they are in any doubt as to areas they</p>
<p>   visit. The Department of Foreign Affairs regularly advises people</p>
<p>   against travelling to certain parts of the world because certain</p>
<p>   parts of the world are dangerous and I just think it's important</p>
<p>   that people understand that and that if they do take risks and travel</p>
<p>   to areas that are dangerous then tragic events could unfold.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[inaudible] hostages, kidnappings, but we've never had a death</p>
<p>   before. Do you think the Yemen security forces mishandled this?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, Australians have lost their lives at the hands of terrorist</p>
<p>   organisations before. This is not the first time it's happened.</p>
<p>   It may have been the first time in that particular country but Australians</p>
<p>   have lost their lives in many countries at the hands of terrorist</p>
<p>   activities and I mean the point is nonetheless valid that people</p>
<p>   should be advised by the Department of Foreign Affairs about what</p>
<p>   places are safe to travel to and which aren't. I'll take</p>
<p>   2 more questions.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister are you going to be speaking to Mr Thomson about</p>
<p>   his comments that the Olympics should perhaps end in 2004 which</p>
<p>   have antagonised IOC members, Mr Gosper and Mr Coates.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No I'm not. He's a backbencher, he's entitled to</p>
<p>   express his view.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Is it not up to the Sports Minister now to be speaking about...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>He's entitled as a backbencher to express a view, I mean it's</p>
<p>   obviously not a view shared by the government but he's entitled</p>
<p>   to express his view and I won't be speaking to him, no.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister do you know whether the rescue attempt in Yemen</p>
<p>   was a result of the kidnappers' starting to kill their hostages</p>
<p>   as the Yemeni officials say?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I'm not advised of that at this stage so I can't answer</p>
<p>   yes or no about that, I just don't know. I'm getting information</p>
<p>   and I think you ought to put a tab on Mr Downer's news conference</p>
<p>   later this morning.</p>
<p> [ENDS]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
