<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10717</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                JOINT PRESS CONFERENCE WITH                THE NEW ZEALAND PRIME MINISTER                THE HON JENNY SHIPLEY MP                PHILLIP STREET, SYDNEY</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/02/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE.............................................</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER HOWARD:</p>
<p>Ladies and gentlemen, I'd like to start this news conference</p>
<p> by saying how delighted I am to have had the opportunity of welcoming</p>
<p> Mrs Shipley on her first visit overseas and her first visit to Australia</p>
<p> as New Zealand Prime Minister.</p>
<p>The relationship between our two countries is longstanding. It's</p>
<p> extremely close. It's very important to my Government. It's</p>
<p> very important to me, as I know it is to Mrs Shipley and her Government.</p>
<p>The bilateral relationship is in exceptionally fine fettle. In recent</p>
<p> days we've had a number of discussions, both personally and over</p>
<p> the telephone, regarding the contribution that each of our countries</p>
<p> is making to the possible coalition military operation in the Middle</p>
<p> East. We're working together very closely.</p>
<p>The goal would be for the closest possible cooperation between the</p>
<p> two countries in the ANZAC tradition. The practicalities of that,</p>
<p> of course, are things that need to be fully worked out and resolved</p>
<p> by ourselves and each of us in discussion with the United States.</p>
<p>There can be little doubt that, from both our perspectives, we hope</p>
<p> that a peaceful settlement at this late hour is still possible. And</p>
<p> we certainly hope that the peace mission of the United Nation's</p>
<p> Secretary-General achieves results.</p>
<p>On the economic front, of course, New Zealand is a very important</p>
<p> trading partner for Australia. The economic relationship embodied</p>
<p> in CER, which will be 15 years old this year, has been very valuable</p>
<p> to both Australia and New Zealand. The cultural and social and human</p>
<p> links between our two countries are also exceptionally close. And</p>
<p> I know that this visit has made a very important contribution to reinforcing</p>
<p> the strength of the bilateral relationship. I particularly have welcomed</p>
<p> the opportunity of meeting Jenny Shipley so early in her prime ministership.</p>
<p>We've had the opportunity, as well as dealing with the political</p>
<p> and economic issues that I've canvassed, we've also had</p>
<p> the chance of comparing some of our approaches to social policy, particularly</p>
<p> in the area of what I call, mutual obligation, and what is called</p>
<p> in New Zealand by another title, and in other countries, by other</p>
<p> titles again. But I couldn't emphasise too strongly the importance</p>
<p> of the association. The Trans-Tasman link is in very good shape. The</p>
<p> relationship, both politically and at a human level, is very warm.</p>
<p> And I know that all Australians and all New Zealanders will want both</p>
<p> governments to work together very closely in the years ahead.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER SHIPLEY:</p>
<p>Well, I too have welcomed the opportunity to meet Prime Minister Howard.</p>
<p> As he has said, there is no closer relationship or more special relationship,</p>
<p> from New Zealand's point of view, than with our Australian Trans-Tasman</p>
<p> partner. We have much in common. And the CER has been a highly successful</p>
<p> mutual relationship for 15 years now and we've had useful discussions</p>
<p> as to what we can do together to extend the advantages that that has</p>
<p> offered both of us.</p>
<p>On the issue of our international and regional responsibilities, while</p>
<p> New Zealand is a small country, it is one that has always sought to</p>
<p> do its share. And the recent decision to deploy troops to Iraq is</p>
<p> something that has been important to New Zealand and, in my view,</p>
<p> to New Zealanders.</p>
<p>It is our hope that we will be able to work as an ANZAC force. New</p>
<p> Zealanders and Australians have had a great history of being extremely</p>
<p> successful. And I'm pleased to say that our defence people are</p>
<p> working through to see if that is actually possible. And perhaps we'll</p>
<p> be in a position, in a few days, to confirm one way or another if</p>
<p> that's able to be achieved.</p>
<p>There are many things that can be done to progress our advantages</p>
<p> in a regional sense and I valued the opportunity to speak with the</p>
<p> Prime Minister on those issues. I also valued the opportunity to get</p>
<p> his update on the impact of the Asian economic circumstance, not only</p>
<p> on the Australian economy, but to try and make an assessment as to</p>
<p> the flow-on effects for the New Zealand economy. And that's been</p>
<p> a useful aspect of my trip to Australia.</p>
<p>I look forward to this ongoing relationship. While New Zealand looks</p>
<p> outwardly toward the world economies, we seek to be competitive. Australia</p>
<p> will, as far as I can tell, continue to be our most important partner</p>
<p> in both human and in trading terms. And I look forward to advancing</p>
<p> that relationship.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, General Baker said on Wednesday that he had concerns about</p>
<p> the ability of New Zealand [inaudible] defence terms. Was that discussed</p>
<p> today and do you agree with those claims?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER HOWARD:</p>
<p>Well, the defence aspect of our relationship was discussed. New Zealand's</p>
<p> defence contribution is a matter, of course, to be determined by the</p>
<p> New Zealand Government, as Australia's defence contribution is</p>
<p> something to be determined by the Australian Government. And we had</p>
<p> a very candid discussion about this issue. But what New Zealand does</p>
<p> in relation to defence matters is a matter for the Government of that</p>
<p> country.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Do you agree with General Baker, Prime Minister?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER HOWARD:</p>
<p>Well, I've said that what New Zealand does is a matter for New</p>
<p> Zealand.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Mrs Shipley, did you think the General's comments were, perhaps</p>
<p> [inaudible]...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER SHIPLEY:</p>
<p>I do not intend to take them either personally, from our country's</p>
<p> point of view, or allow them to be taken out of context. I don't</p>
<p> believe anyone is questioning New Zealand's competency in defence</p>
<p> terms. Our forces are as professional as any you would find worldwide,</p>
<p> within the capacities that they have. I accept that there will be</p>
<p> a debate about our capacity as a nation to contribute regionally.</p>
<p> And the Government made clear, prior to last year, that we were to</p>
<p> expand our investment in our Defence Force. There is an additional</p>
<p> $72 million per annum for each of the next five years, in operational</p>
<p> terms, plus $300 million of capital going into our defence forces.</p>
<p> And for a little country, with the population the size of Sydney,</p>
<p> we think that is a reasonably significant reflection of both our ability</p>
<p> to contribute and also the necessity from our own point of view. I</p>
<p> accept that this will be a matter that will be discussed on an ongoing</p>
<p> basis between our colleagues here in Australia, but New Zealand does</p>
<p> understand that we must do our share regionally. And we believe our</p>
<p> White Paper on defence is a very significant change of direction,</p>
<p> from New Zealand's point of view, that can only be viewed as</p>
<p> positive.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, given Mrs Shipley's saying there will be a debate</p>
<p> on New Zealand's capacity, do you think an ANZAC force in the</p>
<p> Gulf is desirable from Australia's point of view?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER HOWARD:</p>
<p>If we can achieve it, yes.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>What is the achievement?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER HOWARD:</p>
<p>Well, there's just some practical, logistical things involved</p>
<p> that the objective of working together very closely is a very desirable</p>
<p> one and we both want to achieve it. But there need to be things worked</p>
<p> out with the Americans and ourselves at a practical level. And could</p>
<p> I just take the opportunity of saying, as the Prime Minister of Australia,</p>
<p> that the personal competence and the fighting capacity of the New</p>
<p> Zealand defence forces is something that Australians have long admired.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>With the troubles in Indonesia, do you think Australia should possibly</p>
<p> concentrate more on that than [inaudible] so far away [inaudible]...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER HOWARD:</p>
<p>It is quite possible to keep your eye on a number of games at the</p>
<p> same time. It is quite possible to deal with different situations.</p>
<p> We are paying very close attention to what's happening in Indonesia.</p>
<p> We have a close relationship with Indonesia and I have a lot of regard</p>
<p> for what President Soeharto has achieved in that country. And I don't</p>
<p> think anybody should jump to conclusions either about his authority</p>
<p> within Indonesia or the fact that the country still, in the medium</p>
<p> and longer term, has very bright prospects. It would be a huge mistake</p>
<p> for people to allow what is now happening in Indonesia to cloud their</p>
<p> medium longer term view of what that country can achieve. It is going</p>
<p> through a fearful economic hammering at the present time. And that</p>
<p> is an occasion for friends of Indonesia, like Australia, to be understanding,</p>
<p> to be comprehending, to contribute the knowledge of our relationship</p>
<p> with Indonesia to the understanding of other countries. Australia's</p>
<p> understanding of Indonesia is special because of where we are and</p>
<p> the way in which the history of that relationship has evolved. And</p>
<p> we can bring insights and provide advice to others larger than ourselves</p>
<p> which they themselves cannot draw from their own sources.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, have you given any thought to giving any help, on a military</p>
<p> basis, to the Indonesians and what sort of help that might be?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER HOWARD:</p>
<p>Well, we certainly haven't discussed the appointment of any forces,</p>
<p> no. Such an eventuality simply hasn't arisen. Of course not.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Given the bilateral agreement you have with Indonesia...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER HOWARD:</p>
<p>Well, that issue has not come across my desk. It has not come to my</p>
<p> attention. It has not been discussed by me with anybody.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Mrs Shipley, when do you expect to have some sort of a feeling for</p>
<p> what process has to be gone through for this [inaudible] are we talking</p>
<p> days, weeks?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER SHIPLEY:</p>
<p>No, no, days. And it will be much clearer very soon. As soon as there</p>
<p> is something to announce, I'm sure that that will be made clear.</p>
<p> Can I say, beyond that it is very unlikely that we will be commenting</p>
<p> from a New Zealand point of view. Once those arrangements are established,</p>
<p> I think, we need to allow the forces to get on and do what they've</p>
<p> been sent there to do. And we will not be speculating everyday on</p>
<p> either what they are doing or where they are.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>So this places New Zealand troops under Australian command?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER SHIPLEY:</p>
<p>Those matters are most certainly not clarified yet and as soon as</p>
<p> they we will let you know.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, did Mr Howard raise with the [inaudible]...?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER SHIPLEY:</p>
<p>We discussed the frigate issues. I actually raised it because I know</p>
<p> it's a matter of interest to the Australians. And I've made</p>
<p> it very clear that the New Zealand Government reserves the right to</p>
<p> make this decision when it's appropriate. As you'll be aware,</p>
<p> the Minister of Defence was in Australia two weeks ago talking both</p>
<p> with the Minister and the companies involved. They are likely to bring</p>
<p> further information to New Zealand later this year. And if it warrants</p>
<p> further consideration, then that is when the Cabinet will consider</p>
<p> it.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Mrs Shipley, did you discuss issues like - I know that [inaudible]</p>
<p> work-for-the-dole scheme - did you talk about that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER SHIPLEY:</p>
<p>We certainly have. As the Prime Minister has said, western countries,</p>
<p> like our own, are grappling with how we'll get the best out of</p>
<p> our people, create the best opportunities and deliver social programmes</p>
<p> in a fair way that doesn't make things worse for folk but rather</p>
<p> better. I was very interested in what the Australian Government has</p>
<p> done with the 18 to 21 and 24 year olds, equally, I think there's</p>
<p> some interest in some of the things we are doing. And we've agreed</p>
<p> that we will keep an open dialogue on both what we're doing and</p>
<p> how we can mutually benefit from that work.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Could you see a work-for-the-dole scheme coming in to New Zealand?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER HOWARD:</p>
<p>We are already planning, as part of the coalition agreement, a work-for-income</p>
<p> support strategy, both looking at people's work capacity rather</p>
<p> than the fact that they are simply unemployed or sick is a new focus</p>
<p> of New Zealand's work. And certainly work for payments and community</p>
<p> contribution are actively under consideration, indeed, they've</p>
<p> been announced to be implemented this year.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Had you discussed the health of the Coalition Government in New Zealand</p>
<p> with...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER SHIPLEY:</p>
<p>With Prime Minister Howard?</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>With Mr Howard?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER SHIPLEY:</p>
<p>We certainly discussed the political environment, but not in detail.</p>
<p> I am very confident that the New Zealand Coalition is going to survive</p>
<p> well. We announced our programme for the year on Tuesday. I think</p>
<p> it's as ambitious a programme as we've seen from a New Zealand</p>
<p> government in both economic and social terms. And we're both</p>
<p> committed as parties to deliver it.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, you said the discussion on defence was robust. Did</p>
<p> you make...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER HOWARD:</p>
<p>No, I don't think I used the word robust. That's yours Catherine.</p>
<p> I think I said frank or candid, but...</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Did you actually discuss General Baker's comments? Did you seek</p>
<p> to clarify them and did you talk directly about New Zealand's</p>
<p> defence funding?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER HOWARD:</p>
<p>We had a discussion within the parameters that I've already described.</p>
<p> And the view I have is that what New Zealand does in the area of defence</p>
<p> is a matter, of course, for the New Zealand Government.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Well, in that case, did General Baker go too far?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER HOWARD:</p>
<p>Well my answer is that I've given it.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Mrs Shipley, given your discussions with Mr Howard today on the economic</p>
<p> effects of the Asian events, what do you think the Asian crisis will</p>
<p> do for New Zealand and the growth of the region?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER SHIPLEY:</p>
<p>At the moment the best advice we've got is that we're still</p>
<p> expecting around 2.7 per cent growth in our country. I think it's</p>
<p> very soon to try and make an actual assessment and the Cabinet is</p>
<p> looking at contingency plans for if the growth tracks and tax tracks</p>
<p> alter dramatically. It's very likely, in our opinion, that the</p>
<p> secondary effects of this may not be seen until next year rather than</p>
<p> this year. But the New Zealand Government has been kept very well</p>
<p> informed. At this stage, because of some other domestic activity including</p>
<p> tax cuts and a de-mutualisation of AMP, we believe that domestic economic</p>
<p> growth will still be strong in New Zealand which, in fact, will allow</p>
<p> us to ride-out some of the pressure that the Asian change will impose.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Mrs Shipley, the Australian Federal Treasury now believes that the</p>
<p> Asian downturn will knock 0.5 per cent off Australia's GDP growth</p>
<p> in the next financial year. Will this have an on-flow impact to New</p>
<p> Zealand?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER SHIPLEY:</p>
<p>We have a range of contingency plans both ways, in terms of 0.5 or</p>
<p> one per cent. And as I said to you, the Ministers are being kept well</p>
<p> briefed on this matter and we do have contingency plans for spending</p>
<p> tracks if they are required. The Government does intend to keep the</p>
<p> New Zealand books in surplus and we have plans at foot that, if necessary,</p>
<p> can be implemented in order to achieve that.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER HOWARD:</p>
<p>And I don't think, just the sake of complete accuracy, the Australian</p>
<p> Federal Treasury did say that. I think what the Australian Federal</p>
<p> Treasury said was a number of things and that was the interpretation</p>
<p> put on it by the Sydney Morning Herald if I'm correct.</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
<p>[Ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
