<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3816</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON EG WHITLAM QC MP, AT THE OPENING OF THE NEW PRINCIPAL OFFICE IN VICTORIA OF THE COMMONWEALTH BANKING CORPORATION, MELBOURNE, 8 JULY 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/07/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003816.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE PRIfME MINISTER,<br />
THE HON, E. G. WHITLAM, MP,<br />
AT THE OPENING OF THE NEW PRINCIPAL OFFICE IN VICTORIA<br />
OF THE COMOi'OWEALTHl BAINKING CORPORATION<br />
MELBOURNE, 8 JULY 1975 ' 1a<br />
* 1<br />
IT IS A VERY GREAT HONOUR TO BE OPENING<br />
THIS SPLENDID NEW BUILDING OF THE COMMONWEALTH BANKS IN<br />
VICTORIA. I HAVE ALWAYS KNOWN THAT MELBOURNE WAS THE GREAT<br />
FINANCIAL AND BANKING CAPITAL OF AUSTRALIA, AT LEAST<br />
THAT'S WHAT THEY SAY IN MELBOURNE, AND AS YOU KNOW.<br />
IN ANY SORT OF FINANCIAL TRANSACTION I LIKE TO GET WITH<br />
THE STRENGTH, OF COURSE MELBOURNE DOESN'T HAVE EVERYTHING<br />
-HER OWN WAY BECAUSE THREE OF THE GREAT BANKS OF AUSTRALIA<br />
INCLUDING THE BIGGEST AND THE OLDEST HAVE THEIR<br />
HEADQUARTERS IN SYDNEY. NEVERTHELESS THERE ARE THREE<br />
SOTHER BANKS WIjTH THEIR HEADQUARTERS IN MELBOURNE.<br />
So THE SCORE IS PRACTICALLY EVEN. CERTAINLY<br />
THIS EXCELLENT EDIFICE, THIS MOST IMPOSING AND GRACEFUL<br />
STRUCTURE, WILL MARK A NEW CHAPTER IN THE LONG<br />
AND SUCCESSFUL HISTORY OF THE COMMONWEALTH BANKS OF<br />
AUSTRALIA, '' r </p>
<p>2a<br />
IT WAS HERE-IN COLLINS STREET, NOT FAR<br />
FROM THIS SITE, THAT THE COMMONWEALTH BANK OPENED ITS<br />
FIRST OFFICE INj 1912., THAT WAS THE BEGINNING OF A<br />
MAGNIFICENT VENTURE, A SUPERB EXAMPLE OF COMPETITIVE<br />
PUBLIC ENTERPRISE THAT HAS BROUGHT ENORMOUS BENEFITS<br />
TO THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE. A LABOR GOVERNMENT THE<br />
GOVERNMENT LED BY* ANDREW FISHER -INTRODUCED THE COMMONWEALTH<br />
BANK BILL IN NOVEMBER 1911. LET ME QUOTE SOME WORDS FROM<br />
FISHER'S SPEECH: " A NATIONAL BANK IS A NECESSITY.* IT WILL<br />
DO THE GOVERNMENT' S BUSINESS HERE AND IN,<br />
LONDON-BETTER THAN ANY OTHER BANK COULD DO<br />
IT. TIME AND EXPERIENCE WIL L SHOW HOW ITS<br />
FUNCTIONS MAY BE EXTENDED. WE CAN REST<br />
ASSURED THAT IF THIS PROPOSAL, WHICH IS NEW<br />
IN MANY IMPORTANT FEATURES, IS A SUCCESS,<br />
ALL PARTIES WILL ULTIMATELY LAY CLAIM<br />
TO A SHARE OF THE HONOUR OF HAVING BROUGHT<br />
IT INTO EXISTENCE. earn </p>
<p>3.<br />
FISHER SPOKE WIFH GREAT FORESIGHT OF THE<br />
WAY fHE B A KS' FUNCTIONS COULD BE EXTENDED. CERTAINLY,<br />
1' iIT1 Ox WITHOIJT THE ASSISTANCE OF GOVERNMENTS, THE<br />
BANKS' ACTIVITIES HAVE EX" PANDED. IN 1949 THERE WERE<br />
18 PRIVATE TRADING BANKS IN AUSTRALIA TODAY THERE<br />
ARE 13, INCLUDING THE 7 MAJOR ONES. WHEN THE LIBERALS<br />
CAME TO OFFICE THE COMMONWEALTH BANKS' TRADING BUSINESS<br />
WAS ONE OF THE SMALLEST OF THE AUSTRALIAN BANKS;<br />
WHEN THEY LEFT OFFICE IT WAS THE SECOND LARGEST. THE<br />
SAVINGS BANK IS AUSTRALIA'S BIGGEST INSTITUTIONAL LENDER<br />
FOR HOUSING, SINCE 1964 IT HAS ADVANCED MORE THAN<br />
$ 2000 MILLION TO FINANCE HOMES FOR MORE THAN 300,000<br />
AUSTRALIAN FAMILIES, LAST YEAR IT HAD MORE THAN<br />
7 MILLION ACTIVE . ACCOUNTS WITH A TURNOVER IN TRANSACTIONS<br />
OF MORE THAN $ 16,000 MILLION. THERE IS NO NEED FOR ME<br />
TO WEARY YOU WITH LARGE FIGURES. YOU WILL HEAR ENOUGH<br />
OF THEM TOMORROW. THE POINT IS SIMPLY THAT THE COMMONWEALTH<br />
BANK HAS BECOME THE MOST POPULAR, THE MOST TRUSTED,<br />
THE MOST GENEROUS OF ALL FINANCIAL INSTITUTIONS IN AUSTRALIA.<br />
/ 4 </p>
<p>THE GOVERNMENT BELIEVES IT IS TIME<br />
TO DO NOW WHAT ANDREW FISHER ENVISAGED AND EXTEND THE BANK'S<br />
FUNCTIONS TO NEW FIELDS. IT HAS ALWAYS BEEN THE<br />
GOVERNMENT'S POLICY TO ' INCREASE THE COMPETITIVENESS OF<br />
THE COMMONWEALTH BANKING CORPORATION. THROUGHOUT ITS<br />
0 HISTORY THE BANK HAS NOT BEEN PERMITTED TO ENTER THE<br />
HIRE PURCHASE OR FINANCE FIELD. ITS COMPETITORS HAVE<br />
o BEEN UNDER NO SUCH RESTRAINT. MANY OF THEM ESTABLISHED*<br />
H IRE PURCHASE INTERESTS IN THE 1950' s. WE SHALL ALLOW<br />
THE COMMONWEALTH BANKTT O JOIN THE PRIVATE TRADING BANKS<br />
IN AFFORDING HIRE PURCHASE-SERVICES. THIS MATTER HAS BEEN<br />
UNDER STUDY BY THE CORPORATION AND THE GOVERNMENT FOR<br />
SOME TIME# THE GOVERNMENT AND THE BOARD OF THE<br />
0CORPORATION HAVE NOW AGREED THAT COMMONWEALTH BANKS<br />
SHOULD ESTABLISH A FINANCE COMPANY SUBSIDIARY TO BE<br />
OWNED JOINTLY BY THE COMMONWEALTH SAVINGS BANK AND THE<br />
COMMONWEALTH TRADING BANK. THE COMPANY WILL BE IN<br />
OPERATION BEFORE THE END OF THE YEAR. I </p>
<p>THE COMPANY WILL BE PROVIDING SERVICES<br />
SIMILAR TO THOSE NORMALLY AVAILABLE FROM FINANCE<br />
COMPANIES, INCLUDING HIRE PURCHASE, PERSONAL LOANS,<br />
LEASE FINANCING AND COMMERCIAL LENDING. IT WILL ENABLE<br />
THE COMMONWEALTH BANKS TO MATCH SERVICES PROVIDED BY<br />
D OTHER BANKS THROUGH THEIR AFFILIATED FINANCE. COMPANIES<br />
AND PROMOTE FURTHER COMPETITION IN THE BANKING AND<br />
3FINANCE SECTORS1 SHOULD ADD THAT THE PROPOSED FINA NCE<br />
COMPANY WILL HAVE NO ADVANTAGES IN RESPECT TO TAXATION<br />
AND OPERATIONAL ASPECTS COMPARED WITH OTHER BANK-AFFILIATED<br />
FINANCE COMPANIES, IT WILL COMPETE ON AN EQUAL BASIS.<br />
THE ESTABLISHMENT OF THE COMPANY SHOWS THE. GOVERNMENT'S<br />
DETERMINATION THAT THE COMMONWEALTH BANKS SHOULD NOT BE AT<br />
A DISADVANTAGE COMPARED WITH THE OTHER BANKS AND SHOULD<br />
MATCH THE SERVICES OF OTHER BANKS. IT IS THE GOVERNMENT'S<br />
O INTENTION THAT ALL BANK CUSTOMERS SHOULD RECEIVE ADEQUATE<br />
AND COMPREHENSIVE SERVICES AT REASONABLE COST. THE<br />
COMMONWEALTH BANKS PLAY AN IMPORTANT ROLE IN THE PROCESS,<br />
IN THIS CONTEXT, I REMIND YOU OF THE COMMONWEALTH<br />
BANKING CORPORATION'S ANNOUNCEMENT IN MAY THAT IT COULD<br />
ENTER THE TRAVEL BUSINESS, ACQUIRE TRAVEL AGENCIES, AND<br />
PROVIDE FULL TRAVEL SERVICES TO CUSTOMERS. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
