<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9507</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J.KEATING MP DOORSTOP, BRANDENBURG GATE BERLIN, 9 MARCH 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/03/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009507.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL: 1Mr 9 No. 003 P. 01/ 01<br />
U) 1<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
DOORSTOP, BRANDENBURG G ATE BERLIN, 9 MARCH 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
PM: I would just say that It Is always a matter, a great feeling of history to<br />
be In Berlin. to be with the Mayor In this, what may be and probably<br />
will be the city which more than any other typifies the new Europe.<br />
The reconstruction of Germany, the reunification, the draw from the<br />
East, the prospect of a United States of Europe, I suppose, the future<br />
of this city as much as any other, its future says as much about that<br />
as any other city in Europe. And, with the reunification and with the<br />
Federal Government coming here there is a chance to repair Berlin's<br />
broken heart and I think that is something we all look forward to. So,<br />
I appreciate the welcome that the Mayor has given us, to see the<br />
reconstruction of the city and this famous place here, the<br />
Brandenburg Gate and Paniser Platz, to see Berlin come to life again<br />
as the central city of the German state,<br />
J: Mr Keating, what about the future of Australia?<br />
PM: The future of Australia at the moment is we have just passed<br />
560,000 jobs In two years. That is a record in the western world, I<br />
think, for employment growth and that is not a bad fuure.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
