<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5218</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/12/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005218.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR MEDIA ' SUNDAY 16* DECEMBER 1979<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
At the end of the decade and as we stand at the doorway to the<br />
next, Australians are entitled to feel every confidence about<br />
the prospects ahead. We have emerged from the 70s with conditions<br />
right for sustained growth in the 1980s. The 70s were not without<br />
their difficulties. We went through a few turbulent years.<br />
In the early part of the decade the economy was placed under<br />
stresses which it was unable to bear. But through all the<br />
setbacks the essential strength and conviction of the Australian<br />
people prevailed. The durability and adaptability of our<br />
institutions was reasserted. In many ways, the 70s was a watershed<br />
decade in the history of this nation. The hard lessons<br />
learned from it were telling ones.<br />
It was brought home to all Australians that raging inflation<br />
attacked and weakened the very fabric of our society; that wage<br />
explosions led to unemployment; that governments could not go on<br />
spending and tossing money around like chaff. The great lesson<br />
was that responsible government had to learn to say " no".<br />
Responsible government should control its spending so it doesn't<br />
have to resort to the printing press. The 70s too saw many of<br />
our traditional values and attitudes come into question. There<br />
was growing disenchantment with our education system. There was.<br />
an awareness that education should be more closely related to the<br />
labour market, and that greater emphasis be placed on technical<br />
skills. our young people asserted themselves and played a more<br />
creative and constructive role than we have seen in the past.<br />
Family life in Australia changed. We saw an increasing<br />
participation by women in the workforce, and a marked decline in<br />
Australia's birth-rate. The family., however, remains central to<br />
our way of life. Family obligations and responsibilities are as<br />
important as ever they were. Indeed, at a time when a number of<br />
young people are finding it difficult to make the transition<br />
from school to work, the family has a greater responsibility and<br />
a greater role.<br />
In welfare, it became clear in the early 70s that failure to<br />
manage the economy effectively had serious long-term effects on<br />
the poor, the sick, the aged, the underprivileged, and the<br />
unemployed. on the credit side, the 70s also saw an increased<br />
consciousness of the need for our aboriginal people to take their<br />
rightful place in Australian society. </p>
<p>2<br />
There was too, a new awareness of our heritage and of our history,<br />
and the value to us of the many people from overseas who made<br />
Australia their home. Their cultures and their traditions have<br />
enhanced Australian society. A new balance developed in our<br />
society between the need to conserve, and the need to change.<br />
The 70s saw us grow and mature as a nation. We cemented our place<br />
in the world as an independent, middle-ranking power with good<br />
relations with many countries in the developed and in the<br />
developing world. Over the past four years your Government has<br />
pursued a sound, forward-looking economic policy which has<br />
restored confidence and has put in place a strong and efficient<br />
base from which growth in the 80s can take off.<br />
There is now nothing we as a nation cannot achieve if we play our<br />
cards right. We have created the economic environment for a great<br />
program of national development which will underpin that growth.<br />
Without sustained economic growth, Australia can never build the<br />
kind of nation we all want for our children, and theirs. Without<br />
growth we can't create more jobs; we can't meet our welfare<br />
requirements; we can't support generously the arts, culture and<br />
sports. Without growthl-we can't as a nation provide the way of<br />
life which maximises personal freedom, individualism, opportunity<br />
and self-advancemcent.<br />
With a continuation of our policies and programs, I am confident<br />
that we can march boldly into the 1980s, and get on with the<br />
business of building a great nation.<br />
It is up to Australians, working together, and having confidence<br />
in themselves and in each other, to make the most of this country<br />
for ourselves and for our children. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
