<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>22296</transcript-id>
    <title>John Perrin  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/05/2006</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I was deeply saddened to learn of the death of John Perrin, my personal adviser on social policy issues.</p>
<p>Over the past nine years John played an indispensable role in helping to shape the Government's social policy agenda and our social coalition approach to improving Australian society through partnerships between government, individuals, business and the community.</p>
<p> He assisted in driving many of the major social policy reforms of the Government including Tough on Drugs, welfare and Medicare improvements, Stronger Families and Communities, family relationship centres and Community Business Partnerships. More recently, John along with others,  played an active role in putting mental health at the forefront of the Government's policy agenda.</p>
<p> John developed very productive relationships with many stakeholders and interest groups in the social policy field across Australia. He brought their views in to government and helped to establish trust and respect through his excellent working relationships and understanding of their issues and concerns.</p>
<p> Not only did John work to improve Australia's social policies, he was both an advocate for and a living example of the social coalition in his own local community in Canberra.  He was an active member of the Radford College Parents and Friends Association, and was on the school's Health Committee for three years. He was also an active member of the Gungahlin congregation of the Uniting Church, and Chairman of the Canberra Region Presbytery Finance Committee of the Uniting Church.  In all of these forums he used his understanding and expertise gained in government to help the local community.</p>
<p>John was a long standing and highly respected member of the Australian Government public service before he joined my staff in 1997, having worked in the Australian Bureau of Statistics, the Department of the Treasury and the Department of the Prime Minister and Cabinet.</p>
<p>I join his many friends and colleagues, including those in my office, who worked so closely with him, in sending our best wishes and condolences to his wife Debbie, son Richard, father Heber and his sister Jenny.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
