<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18763</transcript-id>
    <title>New world-class prostate research centre for Sydney </title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/08/2012</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Sydney</p>
<p>Prime Minister Julia Gillard, Deputy Prime Minister Wayne Swan and Minister for Health Tanya Plibersek today announced Sydney would have a new centre of excellence to research and treat prostate cancer.</p>
<p>The centre will be Australia's third Prostate Cancer Research Centre, located in the Kinghorn Cancer Centre at the St Vincent's Research Precinct in Darlinghurst, Sydney.</p>
<p>Speaking at the opening of the Kinghorn Cancer Centre, the Prime Minister said the new prostate cancer research facility would bring together both clinical and research expertise in a joint initiative between the prestigious Garvan Institute, St Vincent's &amp; Mater Hospitals, and the St Vincent's Prostate Cancer Centre.</p>
<p>This world-leading centre will be dedicated to improving diagnostic tests, screening tools and treatments for prostate cancer patients.</p>
<p>Ground breaking research will be rapidly translated from bench to bedside, meaning that people will get the best care based on the very latest evidence.</p>
<p>Deputy Prime Minister Wayne Swan said that prostate cancer was the most commonly diagnosed non-skin cancer in Australia, with around 21,000 new cases a year diagnosed. </p>
<p>Mr Swan said Prostate cancer takes the lives of too many Australian men every year and that ensuring Australia remained a world leader in prostate cancer research was very important, as is the need to raise awareness amongst men of the need to get tested.</p>
<p>Australia punches above its weight in cancer research. The third Australian Prostate Cancer Research Centre will ensure that we continue to do so.</p>
<p>The centre will work closely with the two existing Australian Prostate Cancer Research Centres at Epworth Hospital, Melbourne and Queensland University of Technology, Brisbane.</p>
<p>Together, these three centres will save lives.</p>
<p>Minister for Health Tanya Plibersek said the new centre builds on the Gillard Government's unprecedented investment to reduce the burden of cancer in Australia.</p>
<p>The Gillard Government's has committed $2.5 billion to build a world-class cancer care system to improve the detection and treatment of cancer, and, through the nation-building Health and Hospitals Fund, establish a network of regional cancer centres and accommodation facilities.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
