<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2051</transcript-id>
    <title>DIRECTOR-GENERAL FOR ROYAL VISIT</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/05/1969</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002051.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
E MBA RGO: Not for publication, broadcasting or telecasting before<br />
midnight Monday 19 May 1969<br />
FOR PRESS: P. M. No. 40/ 1969<br />
DIRECTOR-GENERAL FOR ROYAL VISIT<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, Mr. John Gorton<br />
Lieutenant-General Sir Reginald Pollard, K. B. E.<br />
C. B., I D. So. 0., has been appointed to take charge of the planning<br />
of the visit to Australia next year by Her Majesty The Queen and<br />
His Royal Highness The Duke of Edinburgh. Sir Reginald Pollard<br />
will be the Director-General.<br />
Arrangements are being made with the Premiers<br />
for an early meeting with the State Directors to discuss the<br />
preparation of a detailed programme for consideration by Her<br />
Majesty. As announced on 28 January The Queen and The Duke of<br />
Edinburgh will visit Australia in March and April of 1970. They<br />
will take part in the celebrations of the bi-centenary of Captain<br />
Cook's voyage, and will visit the Australian Capital Territory,<br />
New South Wales, Queensland, Victoria and Tasmania.<br />
Sir Reginald Pollard retired from the Army in 1963<br />
after a long and distinguished career which culminated in his<br />
appointment as Chief of the General Staff in 1960. Sir Reginald<br />
Pollard held the appointments of General Officer Commanding<br />
Eastern Command 1957-1960 and Quarter master -General<br />
1954-1957.<br />
CA NBERRA<br />
19 May 1969 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
