<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9319</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P J KEATING, MP LAUNCH OF THE &quot;AUSTRALIAN STUDENT TRAINEESHIP FOUNDATION&quot;,GOSFORD,17 AUGUST 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/08/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009319.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
At'<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
LAUNCH OF THE " AUSTRALIAN STUDENT TRAINEESHIP<br />
FOUNDATION", GOSFORD,<br />
17 AUGUST 1994<br />
Well let me say it's great to be out of Canberra and here in Gosford on the<br />
New South Wales Central Coast.<br />
I hope you don't mind if I begin by referring to another launch that took place<br />
yesterday. Yesterday, I launched the international television production " The Global<br />
Economy" a distance learning production, put together by the ABC,<br />
Monash University and the Open Learning Agency.<br />
One of the great things about that production, and Open Learning in general,<br />
is that it allows anyone who wishes to enrol in a distance learning course to<br />
do so regardless of background, prior experience, or educational<br />
qualifications. What Open Learning does is to bring higher education to those who want it<br />
it's flexible and it's customer-focused.<br />
It's a similar story with the Australian National Traineeship Foundation which<br />
we announced in the Whit6&amp; Paper on Employment and Growth, Working<br />
Nation. But whereas the Open Learning initiative is focused on those Australians in<br />
higher education, this initiative is focused on younger Australians in years 11<br />
and 12.<br />
The whole aim of the Foundation is to get schools and industry together to<br />
combine work experience with high quality vocational training.<br />
It's about equipping our senior schools students with the skills they'll need if<br />
they are to have satisfying and rewarding jobs in an increasingly competitive<br />
global economy. </p>
<p>We want to see senior school students with recognised vocational skills as<br />
part of their standard school program.<br />
This is a fundamental shift in Australia's approach to vocational education<br />
and training. It's a shift that will benefit the careers and life chances of<br />
thousands of young Australians.<br />
But to make the shift we need leadership in our local communities, and<br />
particularly from industry.<br />
To help chart the way, a number of outstanding Australians, each with a<br />
strong background in the vocational training field, have agreed to serve as<br />
members on the Foundation's Board. And it's a great pleasure to welcome<br />
the Board members who are with us today.<br />
I won't refer to each Board member individually, but let me just mention how<br />
pleased I am that John Goodman will chair the Board.<br />
John has had extensive industry experience as Chairman and Chief<br />
Executive of Baulderstone Hornibrook. He has also had extensive<br />
involvement in promoting education and training for young people through his<br />
Chairmanship of the Dusseldorp Foundation which has pioneered student<br />
traineeships. One of the most important things about this Board is that the majority of its<br />
members are from industry.<br />
This is critical because under the Foundation, it will be industry, and not<br />
government, that has control over the funding for entry level training.<br />
It will be industry, and not government, that has responsibility for selecting<br />
the training to be undertaken.<br />
And it will be industry, not government, that provides the work experience that<br />
will make the training meaningful.<br />
Under the Foundation, local management committees, chaired by industry<br />
and with majority industry membership, will be able to choose the most<br />
appropriate forms of training from a range of public and private sources.<br />
Students will acquire the skills that industry needs because industry will teach<br />
them. So why are we doing this?<br />
In the White Paper, we were at pains to stress that Australia's future depends<br />
on the ideas, skills, and knowledge of our workforce. </p>
<p>As we said then, if Australia is to be a nation with a high value-added exportoriented<br />
economy generating rewarding jobs for all Australians who want<br />
them, we must find new and more effective ways of equipping the workforce<br />
of tomorrow with the skills they will need.<br />
The fact remains that despite great gains in the last decade that have seen<br />
school retention rates almost double, around 14 per cent of young people still<br />
drop out of school.<br />
The risk is that these people might be left behind as we head towards a new<br />
century. I don't want that to happen. I want us to approach the new century with<br />
confidence, but above all else, with one another, together, as an inclusive<br />
society, as an Australian community.<br />
That's the philosophy that underpinned Working Nation. And that's what we<br />
are giving expression to today through the launch of this Foundation.<br />
Student traineeships must be quality courses that enable young people to<br />
find satisfying and rewarding jobs.<br />
But while the traineeships are important, it's what they lead to that really<br />
counts. So, why come here to Gosford? Why not announce this new initiative in<br />
Sydney, Melbourne, or Canberra?<br />
Well, I suppose we could have travelled to a number of places in Australia<br />
there are many innovative and successful student traineeships already<br />
underway right around the country.<br />
We could have travelled to Alcoa's plant in Geelong, where student trainees<br />
complete their Victorian Certificate of Education at the same time they<br />
complete 16 engineering modules.<br />
But the reason we've decided to come here to Gosford is because the Central<br />
Coast TRAC Program is one of the most successful in Australia and thaimakes<br />
it the best place to launch the Australian Student Traineeship<br />
Foundation. Run from this shopping centre, the Central Coast TRAC is independently<br />
managed and operated by a joint industry, school and TAFE committee.<br />
Not only does industry help develop the TRAC curriculum, it also contributes<br />
towards the running costs for the program both financially and through<br />
assistance in kind many of the businesses represented here today have<br />
trainees working with them. </p>
<p>But it's a real joint effort: the local newspaper, the Central Coast Express,<br />
plays its part by providing a weekly student profile free of charge and the<br />
local councils and Rotary clubs also chip in with their support for the program.<br />
And the reason why the Central Coast TRAC program succeeds, why all of<br />
the TRAC students who left school last year are in full-time jobs, is because<br />
of the combined efforts of the schools, the students, TAFE, industry and the<br />
wider community.<br />
It's a story of students with initiative and enthusiasm responding to<br />
opportunities created by leaders in the local community.<br />
It's the story of S teven Macarthur who participated in the TRAC program in<br />
1993 and earlier this year beat more than 1,500 other applicants in gaining a<br />
hospitality traineeship at the Sydney Hilton.<br />
And it's also a story with an international profile thanks to Lesley Tobin,<br />
Nichole Ford and Natalie Cruikshank. Last month, these three women the<br />
TRAC coordinator, a TRAC student, and a TRAC workplace supervisor<br />
attended the Second International Conference on Education Business in<br />
Paris. There, they presented the Central Coast TRAC as a best practice<br />
model for school industry partnerships.<br />
That's a great achievement, particularly for someone like Nichole who only a<br />
short time ago was on the verge of quitting school. It's the sort of<br />
achievement that deserves to be celebrated.<br />
What we want to do now with this new Foundation is to have stories like this<br />
one echo right around Australia.<br />
Through the student traineeships we want to encourage more young people<br />
to stay on at school and acquire the skills they need for the jobs of tomorrow.<br />
Let me finish up on the important theme of leadership. By launching the<br />
Foundation what we are hoping to tap into is the vast leadership reserves<br />
that lie within our local communities, in our local schools but primarily in our<br />
local business communities.<br />
As the recent Mcinsey report on regional development pointed out,<br />
leadership within a regional community is often the key reason why one<br />
region prospers while another fails.<br />
It's that sort of leadership that has been exercised here on the New South<br />
Wales Central Coast. </p>
<p>I congratulate all those associated with the Central Coast TRAC program and<br />
I take great pleasure in formally launching the Australian Student Traineeship<br />
Foundation what I think is a truly major step in vocational training in this<br />
country.'<br />
Thank you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
