<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5360</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/05/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005360.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
The executive of the Australian Olympic Federation, against<br />
the strongest possible advice of the Government, has decided<br />
by a 6 to 5 vote to send an Olympic team to Moscow.<br />
The executive is plainly uneasy about its own decision.<br />
The way Mr Grange announced the decision pointed to a conflict<br />
of interest duty to Australia against duty to the Olympics.<br />
It is plain that that 6 who voted for Moscow placed their<br />
duty to the Olympics above their duty to Australia. The<br />
Government had said it was a matter of the highest national<br />
importance one that touched the national interest and the<br />
future security of this nation.<br />
The decision is wrong. It remains wrong.<br />
It fills me with great sadness because it is a decision taken<br />
for today regardless of its impact on tomorrow, next year and<br />
the years beyond. It is a decision in the interests of a small<br />
band of Olympic athletes. It is a decision contrary to the interests of<br />
hundreds of thousands of young Australian men and women and of<br />
all other Australians who will not be going to Moscow.<br />
There were many of those who competed in the Berlin Olympics<br />
of 1936, who paid the supreme sacrifice after the World War<br />
began in 1939. In that war, tens df millions of people were<br />
killed. It could soeasily have been stopped in the middle<br />
30s if Britain, France and the United States had understood<br />
what it was all about.<br />
Now, the United States and major countries of Europe are-trying<br />
to avoid making the same tragic mistakes in the eaily part of<br />
the 1980s that were made ndhe latter part of the 1930s.<br />
Determination and support of their own people, courage in the<br />
face of difficultly, and a clear and direct understanding of<br />
what it is all about is essential to the leadership of free<br />
nations. It is essential if the world is to tread a peacefful<br />
path through the interrational dangers tHat lie ahead.<br />
The Australian Olympic Committee could have contributed to this<br />
ove. rall purpose. They could have said to themselves: " What does<br />
playing games in Moscow really mean?". / 2<br />
Z-IRRORV r/ Z4--Iq </p>
<p>2<br />
We have stated repeatedly how the Soviets will use the decision.<br />
Those nations who compete in Moscow will be regarded as not firmly<br />
opposed to Soviet expansion. What athletes and officials think<br />
of that is irrelevant. That is how the Soviets will depict it.<br />
They will therefore be enboldened. They will be encouraged to<br />
say:" We invaded Afghanistan. We moved our armies into that<br />
non-aligned, inoffensive country, and the Western World has not<br />
exacted a price".<br />
How a majority of. the 11 men of the executive of the Olympic<br />
movement could place games in Moscow above this vast and large<br />
national interest, I cannot understand. I fail totally to<br />
comprehend how 11 good Australians, as they are, can take such<br />
a short term view of life, of their future, of their obligations<br />
to this nation.<br />
Perhaps the issues became confused in Australia because Mr Hayden<br />
started supporting an effective boycott and then opposed it.<br />
The governments of the nations of our region, of New Zealand<br />
supported by the Labor opposition in New Zealand were all<br />
strongly in support of the boycott.<br />
It needs to be clearly understood that there is an effective<br />
boycott in place. A boycott must be measured, not by the<br />
numbers of nations who attend, orby the numbers who stay away,<br />
but by the sporting strength of those athletes who attend, or<br />
who stay away.<br />
The. great sporting nations the United States, Canada,<br />
Germany and Japan are staying away. They are supported by other countries<br />
such as Kenya, of notable athletic prowess, a number of others<br />
from Africa and the Islamic world, and by nearly every other nation from<br />
our part of the world China, Japan, South Korea, Thailand, Hong Kong<br />
Singapore, Indonesia, Malaysia, Pakistan and Fiji. That beyond<br />
doubt, constitutes an effective boycott.<br />
Medals won in Moscow will be devalued medals. But again, the<br />
tragedy may be that even those who. win medals, a short time<br />
after the event, may well wish that they had not attended, may<br />
well wish that they. had not won. They will not carry the mark<br />
of pride, excellence, normally associated with the Olympics.<br />
They will be the " 1980 medals", which will carry a connotation<br />
all of their own.<br />
Some people have said thcat if the Government feels so st-rongly<br />
why does it not direct the Olympic Federation. If we had the<br />
forrnal power to so if it had been our responsibility<br />
of course we would have. But Olympic Federations have been<br />
established independent of government. They have been busy<br />
asserting their independence. In Australia, by that very<br />
assertion, they themselves carry that responsibility to act<br />
not only as Olympic administrators, but also as Australians.<br />
They have told Australia which they put first. It is a sad<br />
and tragic decision. Young athletes do not remember of course,<br />
what happened in dte 1930s, it was before their time. That cannot<br />
be said of the majority of the Olympic Federation executive<br />
most of whom lived through that time.; </p>
<p>3-<br />
I think wie all know; that the views I have had of Soviet<br />
explansionism are not new. My concerns and fears about the use towhIich<br />
the Soviet Union might ultimately put its inilit,--nmirTht.<br />
havre been expressed many times over many years. They were often<br />
stated when it was an unpopular view. I regret they havJe all too<br />
titagically been proved right. That gives me no pleasure<br />
at all.<br />
Let me make the point strongly. Australia is not an insignificant<br />
nation. If members of that Olympic executive thought that an<br />
Australian decision did not matter in the wider equation, then<br />
they are wrong. Australia is not only a cireat sportincj nation,<br />
we are a middle ranking power.<br />
We hav'. 2 alw.. ays been a firm ally of t groec; Cat naL. Lons fighting<br />
for world freedom and independence. In this insLanCe, our historyN<br />
and our future placed obligations upon us which should have dema-nded<br />
a. certain decision of the Olympic executive.<br />
That they forgot their history and denied Australia's future,<br />
that they forgot Australia's role, in the taking of this decision<br />
compounds the tragedy, because I know they are all good Australians.<br />
While an acceptance had to be lodged with the Soviets by 24 May,<br />
thE! Olympic Executive could still reverse that decision any<br />
tine until shortly before the Games begin. I would not be<br />
surprised to see the position of additional European sporting<br />
bodies move at a later date to non-attendance in Moscow.<br />
In a number of countries, there is a good deal of disquiet about<br />
the decisions to attend.<br />
In Australia, the passage of time has not diminished the strength<br />
of the Government's view. We never thought we were embarking<br />
on a popular path, trying to persuade a great sporting nation<br />
like Australia to stay away from the Olympic Games.<br />
It was bound to have opponents, but we were impelled lto take<br />
our stand because we believe it to be right because we believe<br />
it to be necessary in the discharge of our responsibilities to<br />
every Australian.<br />
Let me ask one final question. How many7 lives is a medal worth?<br />
How many people have to be killed by Soviet armies before we will<br />
have total unity in this country on whether or not to compete in<br />
Moscow. The Government puts Australia before the Olympics. I ask-all<br />
Australians to do just that. There is still time. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
