<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7402</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER COMMONWEALTH PARLIAMENTARY CONFERENCE CANBERRA - 22 SEPTEMBER 1988</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/09/1988</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007402.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Jj, UI) I( KI(<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
COMMONWEALTH PARLIAMENTARY CONFERENCE<br />
CANBERRA 22 SEPTEMBER 1988<br />
Distinguished guests,<br />
Ladies and gentlemen<br />
This year, Australia celebrates two hundred years of<br />
European settlement of this continent.<br />
This anniversary has given the Australian people the<br />
opportunity to celebrate their achievements, and the<br />
achievements of their forefathers, in building a free,<br />
prosperous and harmonious community in this land. And we<br />
celebrate too the achievements of the Aboriginal people who<br />
settled and cared for this land for more than 40,000 years<br />
before 1788.<br />
As part of our bicentennial celebrations, we have been<br />
delighted to be visited by so many of our friends from<br />
overseas not just the tourists who are appreci ating the<br />
tremendous appeal of Australia as a holiday destinationj not<br />
just the business people who are realising Australia's<br />
potential as a source of exports and a place for investment<br />
and joint ventures; but also the Government leaders,<br />
ministers and parliamentarians who have visited us.<br />
It is for this reason that the 34th Commonwealth<br />
Parliamentary Conference is an important event for<br />
Australians. You are all very welcome guests.<br />
Visits such as yours serve to strengthen the already strong<br />
ties of friendship that exist at the Government level -and<br />
by extension, that exist at the people-to-people levelbetween<br />
Australi&amp; and the rest of the world.<br />
One of the highlights of the Bicentennial year was he<br />
opening of this new and permanent Parliament House which<br />
will serve as the home for the Parliament of the<br />
Commonwealth of Australia for the next two centuries and<br />
more. 2179 </p>
<p>It is a building, we say modestly, which is a magnificent<br />
parliamentary home. It's already become a major attraction<br />
for Australian and overseas visitors. This Great Hall and<br />
the other formal spaces of this building have already served<br />
as the focus for the formal hospitality extended to the<br />
Heads of Government and Heads'of State who have visited<br />
Australia for the Bicentenary.<br />
Most importantly, this new building provides the most<br />
tangible sort of proof that Australians place great and<br />
enduring value on the system of parliamentary democracy.<br />
Australians know the truth that people are best governed<br />
when they govern themselves. It is from the people, through<br />
the institution of Parliament, that Governments derive<br />
legitimacy and it is through those Parliamentary<br />
institutions that democratic Governments remain responsive<br />
to the public will.<br />
This Parliament reflects the diversity of the entire<br />
Australian society and responds to the needs of the whole<br />
Australian community.<br />
So in our Bicentennial year, in this new Parliamentary<br />
building, we are proud hosts indeed to this Conference.<br />
As parliamentarians all, we have a heavy responsibility on<br />
our shoulders.<br />
It is the responsibility to conduct ourselves in our<br />
Parliaments, in our communities and in the world at largein<br />
such a way as to build up rather than erode the stature<br />
of the institution of parliament..<br />
It is the responsibility to honour those who have fought in<br />
war and in peace to build and to ensure the survival of the<br />
democratic principle.<br />
It is the responsibility to understand the danger of taking<br />
that principle for granted in a world in which so many<br />
people live subjected to despotism, in many cases never<br />
having experienced the liberties and dignities of a<br />
democratic society.<br />
As members of parliament we are o f course separated by<br />
differences of individual and party opinion. But long after<br />
those legitimate differences have been resolved or<br />
forgotten, the institution of parliament must live on.<br />
So our greatest obligation, our heaviest responsibility is<br />
to ensure that our parliaments do endure, that they are not<br />
eroded, are not allowed to wither, and do not succumb to<br />
those forces which seek to repress diversity of view point<br />
and which seek to suppress liberty of expression.<br />
My emphasis tonight on diversity is appropriate in view of<br />
the diversity of the Commonwealth of which we are all<br />
members. 2180 </p>
<p>Just as Parliamelits promote tolerance and understanding by<br />
bringing together people of different backgrounds,<br />
circumstances and views, so is this true of the Commonwealth<br />
at large.<br />
There can surely be no more disparate group of nations than<br />
those that compose the Commonwealth itself. We represent<br />
nations of every part of the world, of every continent, of<br />
different traditions.<br />
As Prime Minister, I have the pleasure every two years of<br />
attending the Commonwealth Heads of Government meetings. I<br />
am very much looking forward to next year's meeting in Kuala<br />
Lumpur, which will be my fourth CHOGM. At each meeting I<br />
have been impressed by the determination shown by leaders to<br />
come together in a constructive way to address issues of<br />
international significance.<br />
This ability of the Commonwealth to bring together<br />
individuals and nations of extraordinary diversity is<br />
apparent of course at all levels, not just Head of<br />
Government. Your conference this week is a significant and<br />
valuable example.<br />
There are always people who claim that out of such diversity<br />
can only come weakness and an overall approach based on the<br />
lowest common denominator.<br />
But the continuing resilience and relevance of the<br />
Commonwealth puts the lie to such claims.<br />
One need look no further than the Commonwealth's activity in<br />
regard to Southern Africa.<br />
In Zimbabwe, the Commonwealth was instrumental in the<br />
negotiating process which culminated, as it should have,<br />
with the majority black population gaining power.<br />
In South Africa, the Commonwealth has played an important<br />
role in the struggle to destroy the abhorrent system of<br />
apartheid. Australia was proud to offer the services of our<br />
former Prime Minister Malcolm Fraser for the Eminent Persons<br />
Group on southern Africa and while the group's work was<br />
disregarded by the intransigent South African government, we<br />
remain convinced that the negotiating concept they proposed<br />
provides the best basis for a settlement in the region.<br />
I want to express my confidence in the Commonwealth's work.<br />
I am confident we are working in the only acceptable way<br />
towards the only acceptable goal and I am confident that<br />
our work and pressure, together with the work and pressure<br />
of other people of good will in the world will be<br />
rewarded, eventually, with success.<br />
We can only hope that the South African authorities will<br />
come to their senses in time to avert catastrophe. As we<br />
have said before, the authorities could begin this process<br />
by immediately and unconditionally releasing Nelson Mandela. -2 18.1 </p>
<p>4.<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen lL<br />
For the success of occasions such as this, and of the<br />
programs which result from them, much credit is due to the<br />
Commonwealth Secretariat, and our Secretary General, Sonny<br />
Ramphal. In his three terms in office as secretary General, Sonny<br />
Ramphal has contributed greatly to the well-being of the AlIT<br />
Commonwealth family and to developing and maintaining<br />
Commonwealth initiatives. He is now looking to move on at The<br />
the end of his current term in 1990 and I take this cr1<br />
opportunity to pay tribute to the leadership he has shown nex<br />
aver his years in office. Ban<br />
This cannot of course be a campaign speech, but you would Dem<br />
not be unaware that we believe there is a candidate for this cau<br />
position who, because of his experience in the Australian<br />
parliamentary tradition and the wider Commonwealth, has Au&amp;<br />
impeccable credentials. 27-<br />
None of our many visitors to this magnificent new Set<br />
Parliamentary complex during our Bicentennial year is more w<br />
welcome than you are, our fellow parliamentarians from ba<br />
around the Commonwealth. N i<br />
Pak<br />
We welcome you, and wish you well in the remainder of your<br />
deliberations and for the rest of your stay with us in Set<br />
Australia. 34!<br />
I now propose a toast to our distinguished visitors to thetr<br />
34th Commonwealth Parliamentary Conference. IM~ ie'<br />
ex to r e<br />
Wi ci. del wi me, b r<br />
Ile Co0 cui<br />
2182 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
