<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3716</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S INTERVIEW ON CHANNEL 10&#039;S &#039;IN SESSION&#039; PROGRAM - 21 APRIL 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/04/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003716.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
104<br />
PRIME MINISTER'S INTERVIEW ON CHANNEL<br />
" IN SESSION" PROGRAM<br />
21 April, 1975<br />
Interviewer: Prime minister, your visit to Peru will be the<br />
first by an Australian Prime Minister to South America. Do<br />
you think that this is an area that perhaps we have neglected<br />
for far too long?<br />
Mr. Whitlam: I think so. I don't say that South America<br />
is central to Australia's economic or political concern but<br />
it is important and Peru is the country in South America<br />
from which the discoverers of Australia set out. It will be<br />
quite a symbolic thing for the first visit by an Australian<br />
Prime Minister to South America to take place in Peru.<br />
Interviewer: In terms of Peru, Sir, are there any bi-lateral<br />
issues that you will be raising with the Heads of Government<br />
there? Mr. Whitlam: I think the things where we find ourselves most<br />
in association are in matters concerning the law of the sea.<br />
Peru is possibly the biggest fishing country in the world and<br />
it has been in the fore-front in asserting the right of a<br />
coastal State to exercise jurisdiction and control over the<br />
neighbouring sea and sea-bed.<br />
Interviewer: After Peru, you go to Kingston for the Common~ jealth<br />
Heads of Government Conference. What issues will Australia ' be<br />
raising at that Conference?<br />
Mr. Whitlam: It's not so much what we will be raising. There<br />
are agenda items in which we will all be participating. I'm<br />
to follow the President of Zambia in discussing African matters<br />
which are mainly political matters. We will be there together<br />
for a full week. The Heads of Government and in some cases,;<br />
Heads of State from the 34 Commonwealth countries and most of<br />
them are in-the South Pacific or around or in the Indian Ocean.<br />
So this is a body which is very important indeed to Australia's<br />
concerns political or economic.<br />
Interviewer: The Commonwealth has often been questioned as<br />
far as its role is concerned. Do you think it can play a<br />
meaningful role in terms of the -1970' s?<br />
Mr. Whitlam: Oh yes. I have never doubted th~ e usefulness of<br />
the Commonwealth. After all, if you get 34 countries regularly,<br />
every 1 5 or 2 years, Conferring large or small, European, African,<br />
Asian, Carribean, developing, Christian, Moslem, Animist, all<br />
freely and equally discussing things, then this will have an </p>
<p>affect in all those bodies where each of us has to vote.<br />
The great virtue of the Commonwealth is everybody is free,<br />
equally to express his views. There is no other body in<br />
the world which has that advantage. Now this means that<br />
at least we understand each other very much better when we<br />
go to the United Nations General Assembly or the various<br />
specialised agencies at the United Nations and have to move<br />
motions or vote on motions.<br />
Interviewer: Do you think that the Commonwealth does have<br />
any issue, for example, that really does pull them together<br />
other than the fact that they are all members of the Commonwealth?<br />
Is there any common ground that can be struck<br />
between the members?<br />
Mr. Whitlam: They are very diverse. Historically there is<br />
the common grouqd that they were all, at one stage or another,<br />
recently or sometimes quite a long distance back, ruled by<br />
Britaini so there is a certain respect for the institutions<br />
which Britain established around the world. Even if countries<br />
depart from the standards, there is still a hankering to return<br />
to them. The fact that there should be eldcted law-makers,<br />
P the fact that there should be responsible rulers, the fact<br />
that there should be impartial judges, the fact that there<br />
should be an honest Public Service all these things are<br />
British traditions and all the members of the Commonwealth<br />
respect them and try with various degrees of success, to carry<br />
them out.'<br />
Interviewer: But can it really achieve anything consjidering<br />
that it only meets every two years the Commonwealth Heads<br />
of State?<br />
Mr. Whitlam: The fact that all these people 34 countriesthe<br />
Leaders of them, take a full week off, to discuss these<br />
things, even if it is every 1 or two years, demonstrates the<br />
importance that each of them attaches to this association.<br />
There is really no body, no organisation in the world which<br />
is better calculated to promote understanding and tolerance<br />
and in fact, practical initiatives. It doesn't take votes on<br />
any proposals but there is a very useful discussion of issues.<br />
Another great virtue of it is that while there are about five<br />
developed countries Britain, Canada, Australia, New Zealand<br />
and Singapore there is a very great range, political, economic,<br />
geographic range of developing countries and this is very valuable<br />
an interchange of views. In so many organs of the United Nations<br />
and elsewhere, people line up as developed or developing countries.<br />
There is a tussle, there is a confrontation'and there is frustration.<br />
Here, you can at least make some-progress to getting an understanding.<br />
Of course there are some matters disarmament, development, trade<br />
and in fact a great number of social and cultur~ al matters which<br />
concern them all. </p>
<p>Interviewer: After Kingston you fly to Washington. This will<br />
be the second time you have met President Ford within a period<br />
of six months. What are the bi-lateral issues that are likely<br />
' to be raised in your meeting with the President?<br />
Mr. Whitlam: There might be any number of matters, but I<br />
imagine that the immediate ones will be questions such-as South<br />
East Asia and resources.<br />
Interviewer: One of the points that may be raised, would it<br />
be ANZUS?<br />
Mr. Whitlam; The ANZUS Treaty Meeting is taking place while we<br />
are in Jamaica. The Foreign Ministers will be attending that.<br />
Interviewer: Are there any other issues that are likely to come<br />
up in te* rms of defence pacts between Australia and the United States?<br />
Mr. Whitlam: No, I think ANZUS is one of the very few defence<br />
pacts in the world which is still current and still regularly<br />
discussed by its members.<br />
Interviewer: No doubt you will be putting forward Australia' s<br />
views on recent events in South East Asia, especially in<br />
Cambodia Mr. Whitlam: Oh yes, but I'll also of course be wanting to<br />
hear the views of the Administration and Congress. 4<br />
Interviewer%. You feel that perhaps the meeting with President Ford<br />
will be able to clear up a number of points in terms<br />
Mr. Whitlam: Obviously it will be useful for me to hear from<br />
the President directly what he feels is the present situation<br />
or likely developments and he may be interested in hearing what<br />
our assessments are. Of course, also I'm meeting the Foreign<br />
Relations Committee -of the U. S. Senate and the International<br />
Relations Committee of the House of Representatives.<br />
Interviewer: On your European trip, you made the point that<br />
middle countries, like Australia, had the right to make their<br />
opinions known to the big powers. Is this a continuation of<br />
that point?<br />
Mr. Whitlam: Yes. Very obviously Australia is as important<br />
as any other country in the Southern Hemisphere and we are<br />
very important in our location, particularly in regard to<br />
South East Asia and the developing world. There are very </p>
<p>many diplomatic and economic matters, where Australia's view,<br />
Australia's attitude is very important.<br />
Interviewer: Are there any differences between Australia and<br />
the United States which you may be attempting to clear up in<br />
your talks with President Ford?<br />
Mr. Whitlam: I don't think there are any questions where there<br />
are any misunderstandings and so on. Very clearly there are<br />
different emphases in Australia itself and also in the United<br />
States herself on a considerable number of diplomatic and resources<br />
matters. It is absurd to think that there is a single United<br />
States view or a single Australian view. It is impossible to<br />
expect this. As you know there are differences in the Australian<br />
Parliament, there are differences in the U. S. Congress and<br />
between the Administration and the Congress. These things, in<br />
our context and in their's, can be discussed in quite a rational'<br />
S and useful manner.<br />
Interviewer: I'm looking forward to accompanying you Sir.<br />
MMrr.. WWhhititllaamm:: WWeellll II'' mm llooookkiinngg ffoorrwwaarrdd ttoo sseeee hhooww yyoouu bbeehhaavvee.. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
