<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2255</transcript-id>
    <title>VISIT TO NEW GUINEA 1970 - KIETA, BOUGAINVILLE: LOCAL GOVERNMENT COUNCILS - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR JOHN GORTON - 10 JULY 1970</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/07/1970</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002255.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
JUL 1970 VJSIT TO NEW GUINEA 1970<br />
KIETA, BOUGAINVILLE LOCAL GCVERNMENT COUNCILS<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister, I/ r. J ohn Gorton JULY 1970<br />
I would like to thank the Me mber, Mr. Paul Lapun, for the kind things<br />
which he has said about what Australia has done in general and about the small part<br />
which I was able to play in the time of the troubles, so that between us we were able<br />
to overcome those troubles.<br />
I really cannot give an answer on whether a road to a particular locality<br />
will be built yes or no I cannot do that at this stage. All .1 can say is if the<br />
suggestions for this road, and possibly for otherroads, isputtorheAdministration-ard<br />
I am sure you would be the man to put them to the A--ministration then they can<br />
be fully considered along with other development proposals which would have to be<br />
decided on the basis of economics a.-d developing priorities.<br />
On the second question which you raised, that of trying to see that local<br />
businessmen would have their own businesses in the town of Arawa, I understand<br />
that it has already been agreed by the Administration that the Development Bank<br />
will make loans to local people for businesses in that town subject only to a decision<br />
as to whether they are likely to be a good businessman. That, of course, applies<br />
to whoever loans are made, but we want to see as many local businessmen as<br />
possible with their own businesses in this new town which is being properly planned<br />
and properly built.<br />
Also we want to ensure that the greatest possible equity is held by local<br />
people in developments at Arawa. I have seen a list of a number of projects in<br />
which the Administration want to see at least 49 per cent equity owned by the local<br />
people, whether it is a garage, an hotel a variety of businesses of that kind<br />
where we will certainly offer and seek to provide at least a 49 per cent equity.<br />
I know that there are some people how many I don't know but there are<br />
sume people who wish to secede from the Territory of Papua and New Guinea. I<br />
think that it would be bad for the people of Bougainville if this should now happen.<br />
I think that as a part of a much bigger unit, the future of the people of Bougainville<br />
will be oetter. There will be bigger markets for the produce of Bougainville, there<br />
will be the advantages that the people of Bougainville can go to other parts of the<br />
Territory and get work there, join the Administration there, There are all the<br />
advantages which a large unit gives to the people as distinct from a smaller unit.<br />
Also as the industry of the other part of the Territory grovw and develops, as<br />
perhaps oil is discovered on the mainland, then while Bougainville remains in the<br />
Territory, she will share in all those advantages. And that means her individual<br />
people will share in those advantages.<br />
Australia itself is a Federation of six different states, and Australia<br />
is strong and each state is the stronger because it is a part cf that Federation.<br />
If the State were out by itself, it would be weak in all ways, or weaker in all ways, / 2<br />
L </p>
<p>and it would be to the detriment of the people of that state in Australia. And I think<br />
the people of Bougainville should think of this and see whether it does not apply to<br />
the people of Bougainville as well.<br />
In any case, I suggest that it is much too early to try and reach any<br />
decision on this subject now. I think there should be much more thought given to it<br />
by the people of Bougainville, much more discussion, meditation on the advantages<br />
of secession, recognition of the disadvantages of secession, talk amongst the older<br />
men and the younger people. And that should go on for some long time. Time<br />
enough to make significant decisions on something of this kind when thetime of<br />
independence of the Territory comes. In the meantime, let there be proper<br />
discusbion among the people of Bougainville.<br />
Meanwhile, Members elected to the House of Assembly from Bougainville<br />
will now have much more opportunity to influence decisions, and the Ministerial<br />
Members and Assistant Ministerial Members will have much more ooportunity to<br />
influence decisions. And they can get up when they are elected by their people here,<br />
they can get up in the House of Assembly and speak for the people here and they<br />
can say " We want this road" or " We want that harbour" or " We want that wharf",<br />
and they can put the views of their people in the same way as Members of Parliament<br />
from the different States do in Australia.<br />
That does not mean, of course, that every time one of these requests<br />
is raised, it will be met. But it does mean that the wishes of the people of<br />
Bougainville will be able to be known all throughout the Territory. I know the<br />
Members you have elected and they are pretty good Members and they speak out<br />
strongly for the people of Bougainville.<br />
So I think it is too soon yet to talk about referendums for secession.<br />
I think, as I said before, there should be much more time for discussion amongst<br />
the people here. And I say this and you know it is true. It is nothing to me if<br />
Bougainville is independent. It is nothing to Australia if Bougainville is independent.<br />
I don't say what I say because it is of some advantage to me or to Australia but<br />
because I believe it is of advantage to the people of Bougainville, and I want them to<br />
have a lot more time to make up their own minds about it.<br />
I think that is all I have to say on those subjects except to express<br />
the hope that now that much more authority has been given to Ministerial Members,<br />
the Administrator's Executive Council and to the House of Assembly, and decisions<br />
that were formerly made in Canberra will now be made in the Territory, that this<br />
will help to develop the capacity for running the Territory amongst all the peoples<br />
of the Territory and that they will all go forward together, helping each other, and<br />
with Australia giving help as long as it's wanted, to build up a better life, a<br />
better economic life for all the people. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
