<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2711</transcript-id>
    <title>RELEASE OF COMMONWEALTH LAND ON SYDNEY HARBOUR FORESHORES - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT HON WILLIAM MCMAHON CH MP</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/11/1972</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002711.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRAUSTRAIAISTE<br />
FOR PRESS: R. I. No. 96/ 1972<br />
RELASEOF COMMONWAEALTH LAND ON SYDN4EY<br />
HARBOUR FORESHORES<br />
Statement by the Prime 1Hinister, the Rt. Hon. William<br />
Mclalon, C. H. MP.<br />
For some time n~ ast the Commonwealth has been<br />
discussing with the State of New South Wales the release of<br />
substantial areas of Commonwealth land on Sydney Harbour<br />
foreshores, so far held mainly for defence purposes.<br />
The nature of the Commonwealth use has tended to<br />
keep the areas relatively undeveloped, at least in comparison<br />
to neighbouring lands so intensively developed commercially.<br />
The Commonwealth has been conscious of the growing<br />
community awareness of the need for open parkland in a crowded<br />
metropolis, particularly such scenic Land as much of the<br />
Commonwealth foreshiore land is. A critical examination of<br />
the use to wqhich the land is beinci out has been made to see<br />
to what extent it can be released for community use and<br />
benefit. I had previously announced that, as a result of<br />
this review, the Commonwealth was willing to release to the<br />
State a total of about 550 acres of land at ' North Head,<br />
South Head, Dobroyd Point and Middle Head.<br />
The land is to be used only for creating natural<br />
parkland and the Commonwealth will retain the right to resume<br />
possession in an emergency.<br />
Following further consideration by the Government,<br />
I am now able to say that the firm basi3 of the Commonwealth's<br />
offer to the State, which the Premier has advised is<br />
acceptable to him, is as follows: </p>
<p>2.<br />
NORTH HEAD: The Commonwealth will make available aporoximately<br />
half of its holding of 639 acres, including a strip for a scenic<br />
drive between the land retained and the ocean front. The<br />
Commonwealth will retain the balance of the quarantine station<br />
and the School of Artillery.<br />
SOUTH HEAD: The Commonwealth can release immediately an area<br />
of about eight acres on the headland, plus a narrow strip to<br />
provide access from Cliff Street. The Commonwealth is also<br />
prepared to make a further area available on leasehold bringing<br />
the total to about 33 acres of the 78 acres held by the<br />
Commonwealth. DOBROYD POINT: The Commonwealth will transfer its entire<br />
holding of some 115 acres to the State.<br />
MIDDLE HEAD: About 80 acres can be transferred now and a<br />
further 35 acres may be released later, subject to continued<br />
occupancy by the Commonwealth's School of Pacific<br />
Administration. Most of these lands are available now for public<br />
use. It will, however, take a little time to complete<br />
transfers to enable the State to include these lands in the<br />
proposed Sydney Harbour Foreshores Iational Park.<br />
I am sure that my fellow residents in Sydney, and<br />
the many visitors to the city, will welcome the availability<br />
of these lands as natural parkland.<br />
I am also able to say that the Commonwealth has<br />
also agreed to return to the State another harbour facility.<br />
I refer to the Man O'War steps at Bennelong Point to be used<br />
for ferry services to the Onera House.<br />
CANBERRA, November 1972 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
