<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1054</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: PM 14/1965 - PETROLEUM PRODUCTS PRICING PROPOSALS - STATEMENT BY THE ACTING PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. J MCEWEN</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/02/1965</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001054.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
65/ 011.<br />
FOR PRESS P g. No., 14/ 1965<br />
PETROIZUM 1" RODUCTS PRICING PROPOSALS<br />
Statement by the Actinig Prime Minister, the Rt. Hon. J. McEwen<br />
Satisfactory discussions were held today between<br />
Commonwealth and State Ministers on the Commonwealtht a pricing<br />
proposals for petroleum products.<br />
This was announced today by the Acting Prime Minister,<br />
Mr. 51. McEwen, following a meeting in Canberra with State Ministers.<br />
The proposals were put forward by the Com1yonwealth in<br />
pursuance of the Prim~ e Ministeris election promise to do something<br />
Sabout the burden placed upon rural costs by the higher prices of<br />
Vpetroleum products in remote areos.<br />
As indicated in the Prime Minister's election speech,<br />
action by the Commonwealth in this field calls for thle co-operation<br />
of the States and of the oil companies.<br />
The development of a practical scheme for giving<br />
effect to this undertaking has required a great deal of study by<br />
the Commonwealth Departments concerned and long negoti. ations with<br />
the oil industry and discussions with State officials.<br />
Commonwealth proposals elaborated as a result of this<br />
work were today considered by the State and-Commonwealth Ministers,<br />
and State Ministers agreed to recomnmend to their respective<br />
Governments the adoption of a scheme, the essential features of<br />
which are as follows<br />
The scheme w.-ill apply to motor spirit, power kerosene,<br />
automotive distillate, aviation gasoline and aviation<br />
turbine kerosene.<br />
The scheme will be given effect to by Commonwealth and<br />
State legislation.<br />
In broad terms, the scheme will work as follows.<br />
Subsidy will be paid in respect of sales of the<br />
petroleum products in country locations which, on<br />
June, 1961+, were recognised distribution points<br />
and at which the wholesale price exceeded by more<br />
than 4+ d. the capital city wholesale price. The rates<br />
of subsidy in respect of these locations will be based<br />
on the wholesale prices ruling there on 31st December,<br />
1961+. There will be provision for t'ie determination<br />
of subsidy rates in respect of distribution centres<br />
wihich have or shall come into existence after<br />
June, 1964,. It is intended that the provisions shall<br />
cover consumers in remote areas.<br />
Rates of subsidy in the Northern Territory and the<br />
Australian Capital Territory will be related to<br />
Sydney prices.<br />
The oil industry will undertake to pass on to the<br />
purchasers in reduction of its wholesale prices the<br />
full benefit of all subsidy received. 9 e a./ </p>
<p>-2<br />
The Minister for Customs and Excise, Senator Anderson,<br />
will be responsible for the administration of the<br />
scheme. Distributors of petroleum products will be<br />
registered. The actual payments of subsidy will be<br />
made to registered distributors by the States. Claims<br />
for subsidy will be examined by officers of the<br />
Commonwealth Department of Customs and Excise, acting<br />
under the authority of the State legislation,<br />
The rates of subsidy, as initially determined, will not<br />
be varied to take account of day-to-day changes in circumstances.<br />
Consequently, should costs of distribution change, the wholesale<br />
Sri ce at some locations may come to differ by more or less than<br />
d. from the city price.<br />
After discussion, the Commonwealth undertook to make a<br />
general review of the rates of subsidy after the scheme has been<br />
in operation for three years.<br />
The necessary Commonwealth legislation will be introduced<br />
in the coming Session of Parliament and the States will be asked<br />
to introduce legislation as soon as practicable. The scheme will<br />
come into operation shortly after the necessary State legislation<br />
has been passed. It is hoped that it will be in operation by<br />
1st October. Mr. McEwen added that the Commonwealth Government was<br />
pleased at the helpful and co-operative approach adopted today<br />
by the States and by the oil companies in recent discussions.<br />
The following Ministers attended the conference<br />
The Rt. Hon. J. Mc~ qen, Acting Prime Minister<br />
The Rt. Hon. H. E. Holt, Treasurer<br />
The Hon. D. E. Fairbairn, Minister for Bationa1<br />
The Hon, B. M. Snedden, Attorney-General<br />
Senator the Hon. Ken Anderson, Minister for Customs and<br />
Excise.<br />
New South Wales: The Hon. J. 5. Maloney, Minister for Labour<br />
and Industry<br />
Victoria : The Hon. V. F. Wilcox, Minister for Imiaigration and<br />
Assistant Attorney-General<br />
Queensland : The Hon. T. A. Hiley, Treasurer<br />
The H~ on. G. VW. W. Chalk, Minister for Transport<br />
South Australia The Hon. Sir Thomas Pla yford, Premier<br />
Western Australia : The Hon. J. F. Craig, Minister for<br />
Transport<br />
Tasmania : The Hon. E. E. Reece, Premier<br />
The Hon. R. F. Fagan) Attorney-General.<br />
CANBERRA, February, 1965, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
