<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9639</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J.KEATING MP AND THE DEPUTY PRIME MINISTER, THE HON KIM BEAZLEY MP, PRESS CONFERENCE, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, 20 JUNE 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/06/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009639.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
AND THE DEPUTY PRIME MINISTER, THE HON KIM BEAZLEY MP,<br />
PRESS CONFERENCE, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, 20 JUNE 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
PM Well, I am very happy to announce that the Labor Party has a new<br />
Deputy Leader and the Labor Government has a new Deputy Prime<br />
Minister in Kim Beazley. He was elected unanimously and with broad<br />
acclaim in the Caucus and I noted I didn't need to because<br />
everybody understood that the seamlessness of the change, Brian<br />
Howe's gracious resignation and Kim's unanimous election speaks<br />
volumes for the unity and sense of purpose which the Government<br />
has, the collective spirit and the genuine good will that was in<br />
evidence today. I spoke in the room about the continuity in the Labor<br />
Party and the fact that such a change and the manner of such a<br />
change actually means something. In our Party which is a very<br />
clannish organisation, personal relationships and the nature of this<br />
change does matter and it matters to us and I am delighted that Kim's<br />
father could be here on this occasion, purely by accident I'm told, and I<br />
made the point that the oldest Labor Party in the world has this<br />
continuity. When I first came here Kim senior was a member here and he took<br />
John Curtin's place in the House of Representatives in 1945. At that<br />
stage, he and I used to have discussions about my friendship with<br />
Jack Lang who had attended Henry Parkes' rallies in the Sydney<br />
Domain and with other leading people in NSW such as McKell and you<br />
can see that continuity. And then, of course, I got know Kim before he<br />
came to Parliament and now we have had a Parliamentary life together<br />
and he has a long and distinguished record as a Minister from 1983,<br />
sharing this period with me and his colleagues.<br />
So, that continuity is there and in our Party continuity and sense of<br />
history and commitment to common ideals matters and the mood and<br />
sentiment and good naturedness of our relations together matter to us<br />
as well. At any rate can I say this is a very strong result for the<br />
Government. It makes the Government strong with a young man as a<br />
Deputy Prime Minister who's had enormous and extensive experience. </p>
<p>I think it is a very strong outcome for the State of Western Australia<br />
who, again, have kept that great tradition of supplying significant<br />
people to Labor Governments that have been there at the critical<br />
turning points of the nation and Labor's history and I welcome Kim's<br />
election as Deputy Prime Minister.<br />
I look forward enormously to working with him. I think that this verve<br />
and commitment that he will bring to the job and also as he is from his<br />
state of origin Western Australia means I think again a sense of us<br />
looking at the country and going at the problems with imagination and<br />
vigour can only be reindorsed as a consequence of tonight's election.<br />
So for my very public congratulation to him and I now invite Kim to<br />
speak to you and say a few things to him and maybe ask him some<br />
questions.<br />
KB Well thanks very much Paul it is a great honour, a great opportunity. I<br />
had an opportunity in the Caucus room, just a moment ago, to pay<br />
tribute to Brian Howe's service, the extraordinary role that he has<br />
played over a lengthy period of time now in the Labor Government as<br />
a person with very clear cut comprehension of the social needs of the<br />
nation and a real capacity in Cabinet to make a difference in argument<br />
on the detail of policy issues.<br />
I ought here to say how deeply flattered and grateful I am at the<br />
opportunity to serve with Paul as Prime Minister. This is a government<br />
with vision, it is now unique, I think, in the political process of this<br />
country, it is also a government with policies. And the fact that we<br />
have a very clear sense of direction, that we have an understanding of<br />
the needs of our nation. That those needs go very much to the issues<br />
of survival in an international community in which there is nobody who<br />
feels that this is a country owed to living It is a tough hard fight for the<br />
nation and it requires people with both vision, clarity and the<br />
toughness and will to carry that through and the honestly to declare<br />
their intent to the Australian people as to what there is intended in the<br />
relationship between Government and the Australian people. I think,<br />
from my point of view, my job is to listen as well as speak, to absorb<br />
what those in the community wish to say to us about their experiences<br />
and how they see life. I regard it as a particular challenge to get out<br />
amongst our working people, the families to point out the social safety<br />
net, the industrial safety net that has been put in to protect them. I<br />
also feel that I do have a special role in the medium size and small<br />
states.<br />
The great engine of the political process in this country does reside in<br />
the suburbs of our great cities of Sydney and Melbourne. There is no<br />
question about that but in many ways the forward development of the<br />
nation is a product of what is going on in smaller and medium sized<br />
states, particularly my home state of Western Australia and<br />
Queensland. And I do regard myself as having a special role to play<br />
there in conveying the direction of the Government and ensuring that </p>
<p>our message, our concerns have got across and that the concerns of<br />
the people who are on the receiving end of Government policies and<br />
directions have got across to us.<br />
J Prime Minister you spoke about continuity in the Labor Party. Do you<br />
now see Mr Beazley as perhaps your national successor?<br />
PM Well, I mean I want to make certain first and foremost that if he is to<br />
succeed me at whatever point that is that he succeeds in<br />
Government. I think that's what we are both about: winning the next<br />
election. They are always hard to win in Australia, as it ought to be. I<br />
mean the public insists that the parties deliver quality to them in terms<br />
of policies and obviously Kim's standing in the Party, his record as a<br />
Minister in now so many senior portfolios and now his endorsement<br />
unanimously as Deputy Prime Minister makes him, if you like, the<br />
obvious person in the longer haul. We want that to be a longer haul<br />
but that matter, of course, is up to the people as it should be in a<br />
democracy.<br />
J What about the career of Carmen Lawrence now, how would you<br />
characterise her future prospects?<br />
PM I think her future prospects are as good as the day she arrived here,<br />
probably better now she has got the experience of time under her belt<br />
in terms of health. She has a very large domestic portfolio<br />
responsibility and anyone in the Labor Party who in any way damages<br />
the Coalition will always be in for a personal attack. This has been<br />
true of Whitlam, it has been true of Neville Wran, it has been true of<br />
me, it will be true of her: anyone who can do them damage. So<br />
extending the arm of the executive in Western Australia to try to prey<br />
into the business of the opposing party shouldn't become a norm in<br />
Australian Politics and shouldn't be rewarded. And she is, in standing<br />
up against that sort of behaviour, standing up for all of us who believe<br />
that there are protocols in this country to observe and there are<br />
decencies which the Western Australian Government has not been<br />
prepared to observe. Were I to announce a royal commission into the<br />
goings on of the former Fraser Cabinet here they would be outraged<br />
as we are outraged by the Court Government's behaviour. I think the<br />
public have already given us the answer of what they think about that<br />
and that is not very much. Premier Court's standing has fallen<br />
dramatically in recent times. This is one of the reasons for it and the<br />
vindication of the high standing of which he is held.<br />
So, I think, she can take this in her stride and go on about her great<br />
public career in the cause of the Australian people and in the cause of<br />
Labor.<br />
J: Mr Beazley, do you see yourself as the natural successor to Mr<br />
Keating? </p>
<p>PM: I don't see myself in any position other than I have already announced<br />
previously. I see that as an interesting issue for the next century. I<br />
think we are blessed in the Labor Party with a whole variety of<br />
alternative leaders of which I happen to be one, but that situation has<br />
not changed as a result of any events today.<br />
J: Mr Beazley, in the past you and Mr Keating haven't always seen eye to<br />
eye. I think the Telecom battle was one, I think you were the chief<br />
numbers person for the previous Prime Minister, how are you going to<br />
get on now?<br />
PM: I'm glad he wasn't so good at that at the time.<br />
KB: I don't think you could say that it was an outstanding success, if that<br />
was true. We have always got on extremely well in Government and<br />
prior to our being in Government. I first met Paul, when I used to come<br />
over on regular visits as a youngster really and he was a young man in<br />
Parliament and my father used to point him out to me as the person to<br />
watch and I have been watching him ever since and have been very<br />
impressed with the process.<br />
J: Mr Beazley, when did you find out the Deputy's job would be vacant<br />
and what were your reasons for standing?<br />
KB: Well, there had been a few rumours around as you are well aware.<br />
There was something run in the press over the weekend and there had<br />
been some discussion, I understand, around the preselection<br />
processes in Victoria. But, I don't think I was aware of anything final<br />
really, until last night on that from recollection.<br />
J: Mr Keating, do you have any regrets that it wasn't a woman, given<br />
Labor's affirmative action policy, wasn't a woman who became the<br />
Deputy?<br />
PM: No, but we don't have an affirmative action policy for the leadership.<br />
We are a mature party, we have a very big role to play and perform<br />
and these positions will always fall to the people the Caucus believe<br />
are best to fill them. I think, this is always a matter of choice for any<br />
member of the Party and all the members chose, in a sense, Kim and<br />
those who decided not to stand, if they were ever going to stand,<br />
chose Kim by their actions and that includes Carmen Lawrence. I do<br />
want to see a greater participation by women in the affairs of the<br />
Parliamentary Labor Party and I think there is no doubt if there is no<br />
formal affirmative action policy being undertaken by the Caucus, there<br />
is certainly an informal policy and that is to try to promote women to<br />
the Ministry and to the Cabinet and when the moment is the moment to<br />
positions of leadership. On this occasion, the Caucus took the view<br />
that Kim was the most experienced person and given his record here,<br />
it is very hard to argue that point. </p>
<p>J: Mr Keating, will you give an undertaking that if you win the next<br />
election, you will stay the full term?<br />
PM: There is no point in winning elections to give them away. I have kept<br />
making this point over and over. A lot of you want me to trade in<br />
months or periods of this Parliament, I keep telling you I don't want to<br />
do that.<br />
J: Mr Keating, did you ever contemplate in thinking about this change of<br />
deputy leadership as an opportunity for a reshuffle given..<br />
PM: This matter came, and I said to you this morning, from Brian Howe's<br />
own view that he thought that this was the time for him not to nominate<br />
again for his selection for the seat of Batman and having made that<br />
decision thought about whether the Party's interest would be advanced<br />
by him staying as Deputy Prime Minister as Lionel Bowen stayed as<br />
Deputy Prime Minister until the poll. He thought, in these<br />
circumstances, it was better to resign his position and it was, as Kim<br />
said a moment ago, only really yesterday that he came to that<br />
decision. So, there has been no forethought about ministerial<br />
changes, but the point is that the Cabinet and the Ministry are working<br />
well and as I said to you this morning, we have just produced a surplus<br />
Budget, I think, about our fourth in our history. The Coalition never<br />
ever produced one. We have introduced that massive change to<br />
retirement income and savings in the Budget, Kim presided over with<br />
root and branch examination of the expenditure programs with there<br />
gross savings of the order of about $ 1.5 billion and you know more<br />
recently we have had the Justice Statement released by the Attorney-<br />
General and Minister for Justice with imagination, I think, and flair.<br />
And, the structure for the republic the proposal that I put down the<br />
Government has been doing many things and I hope doing them well.<br />
So, there is no argument around and no need therefore for us to be<br />
talking about a major reshuffle of the Government.<br />
J: Prime Minister, will you be making another visit to Queensland before<br />
the State poll?<br />
PM: Probably, I will.<br />
J: Given the achievements you have just been talking about, you must be<br />
disappointed you are not getting a bigger kick out of the polls then?<br />
PM: Well, it depends on what you think a poll registers. What you think a<br />
poll registers and how you read it. I think, just look at the position we<br />
are in at this stage of the last Parliament and we had other people<br />
making similar observations, there is a much closer gap between<br />
parties now and you can't ever, I think, assume that the Australian<br />
public will take, as a government, a party that won't say what its<br />
policies are. That somebody who stands for nothing. I mean, I think<br />
the last month has made it clear that John Howard is out of his age </p>
<p>and out of his depth with the problems which Australia faces now. This<br />
is not lost on the public.<br />
J: Mr Beazley, you said that the Labor Party had a range of alternative<br />
leaders and the events of today hadn't changed that, Mr Keating also<br />
made you the more obvious alternative in the long run, do you think it<br />
has made you the more obvious alternative?<br />
KB: I wouldn't disagree with anything that Paul says, but I think this is a<br />
show that has real strength across the breadth of it. This is one of the<br />
principle differences between ourselves and our political opponents.<br />
We have any one of a number of people who could be made Prime<br />
Minister, they have none. They have not got the bottom to them to<br />
form a decent Cabinet. They have not got the capacity to carry the<br />
foreign relations of this country. They have not got the capacity to<br />
carry the very considerable requirements and difficulties there are in<br />
fitting into a Budget with what we have available to us essential<br />
social protection for the communities. So, we actually have a huge<br />
range of people who are alternatives and a whole lot who don't feature<br />
very much in the press, but are sitting there waiting in the wings. I am<br />
not that much different in age from the Prime Minister and he is going<br />
to continue for a very long period of time.<br />
PM: We are happy, of course, to take questions. This is an occasion of<br />
some celebration for us, we don't want to truncate it, but nor do we<br />
want to stay on pointlessly or needlessly. Is there anything else you<br />
might want to ask? If not, thank you indeed. Let me take the<br />
opportunity of shaking your father's hand ( Kim Beazley Snr).<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
