<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6277</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE IN GOA, 27 NOVEMBER 1983</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/11/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006277.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Ij3AU STRA " A<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
E. O. E. PROOF ONLY<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE IN GOA 27 NOVEMBER 1983<br />
PM: Well, you' re aware of the resolution on Cyprus which<br />
JOURNALIST: I don't think we've got the actual working on<br />
PM: I don't think I'm actually entitled to give the working<br />
of it, but I can give you the essence of it. It involved a<br />
condemnation of the attempts to create a secessionist state<br />
and endorsement of Security Council resolution 541 and we<br />
support of the independence of sovereignty and territorial<br />
integrity unity and non-alignment for the Republic of Cyprus.<br />
We agreed to establish a special Cpmmonwealth action group<br />
on Cyprus at a high level and this is to assist in security<br />
Security Council resolution 541.<br />
JOURNALIST: What does high level mean, Prime Minister?<br />
PM: Well, I was just going to say I would come back to that.<br />
I~ t's deliberately left open because it's anticipated that<br />
it might at different times consist of different levels. For<br />
instance, probably before we leave Delhi ( inaudible) the<br />
Prime Ministers of the five countries Australia, Guyana,<br />
India, Nigeria and Zambia will have the first meeting and<br />
then it will be taken up subsequently at different levels,<br />
perhaps by Prime Ministers at. certain times, perhaps by officials<br />
high officials.<br />
JOURNALIST: Were you approached to go ahead or did you volunteer?<br />
PM: No, I didn't volunteer.<br />
JOURNALIST: INAUDIBLE<br />
PM: would be a very good member of such a committee and we<br />
were more than pleased to be invo]. ved for three reasons. one<br />
the general importance of it. Two because of our large<br />
community, the Cypriot conmmunity i~ n Australia. Three we have<br />
had a continuing presence there in Cyprus with the police<br />
contingency force. So when we were nominated for it I was quite<br />
happy to accept.<br />
PM: That's Cyprus. / 2 </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: clarification of You just talked<br />
about the word " in association" with the United Nations.<br />
What does that mean precisely? How will it operate at the<br />
United Nations?<br />
PM: Well, let me go backwards and it may give you some<br />
indication. Before the CHOGM conference Ramphal, the<br />
Secretary-General had been in discussions with the<br />
and it was indicated that it would be helpful if the<br />
Commonwealth would involve itself and so under the<br />
Security Council resolution 541 the Secretary-General is<br />
required to use his good offices for the purpose of trying<br />
to bring the resolution and he clearly believes that the<br />
Commonwealth Cyprus being a member of the Commonwealth<br />
may be able to have some influence in assisting him in the<br />
exercise of his good offices, so it would be a matter of<br />
judgernent between the Commonwealth and the UN Secretary-<br />
General as to just how it would operate.<br />
JOURNALIST: You can't say anything more than that at this<br />
stage?<br />
PM: They had a drafting group. The officers came back with<br />
a ~ draft and in the draft there was work. And it was accepted.<br />
Anything further on Cyprus?<br />
Because a lot of time has been taken up on Grenada. It has<br />
been interesting to me to see the processes of the Commonwealth<br />
in action here. The debate, as you know, started in New Delhi<br />
on the late morning, Thursday morning and went through to<br />
the Thursday afternoon session. It was a very tense, dramatic<br />
thing and to me one of the most interesting discussions I have<br />
ever been involved in. Essentially you have the African<br />
states expressing a grave concern about the invasion and taking<br />
the view that the United States exercise, the Caribbean states<br />
who got involved saying very strongly that it was their<br />
initiative and they were basically apprehensive about the<br />
threat that was posed to the rest of the East Caribbean by the<br />
events that had-been taking place prior to the invasion. You<br />
would have thought by the end of the day in New Delhi that it<br />
would have been to get any sort of common position. We<br />
came down here and had a further lengthy debate and then<br />
there was a drafting committee which consisted of representatives<br />
of the Caribbean including those'who hadn't supported hadn't<br />
been involved in the debate and others that were and Zimbabwe.<br />
They came back with a draft which we commenced to consider last<br />
night at about quarter past seven. It was thought that it might<br />
be capable of being fixed up quite quickly and in fact it went<br />
on . till about 9 o'clock. We were supposed to finish at 8. By<br />
9 in fact agreement was reached and I can say quite seriously<br />
that I think it was a fairly impressive achievement at the end<br />
to get again I really can't go into the in Delhi, but I<br />
can say that it did involve the Commonwealth leaders saying<br />
that it referred to our readiness to give sympathetic<br />
consideration to requests for assistance from Grenada in the<br />
context of the the civilian administration is operating and<br />
/ 3 </p>
<p>it is operating free from outside pressures and the presence<br />
of foreign troops. In that situation if they want<br />
assistance at all the Commonwealth would be prepared to<br />
give sympathetic consideration to that.<br />
JOURNALIST: That depends on on Thursday<br />
PM: Yes, well, the wording to the administration operating<br />
free of external interference, pressure or the presence of<br />
foreign forces. And there is reference to the readiness of<br />
the Caribbean states or countries in the East Caribbean<br />
community to assist in the maintenance of order so what you're<br />
essentially looking at is a gradual transition of the<br />
emergence of this, the Grenadan administration, perhaps<br />
assisted by forces from the actual Caribbean states to help<br />
maintain order, withdrawal of foreign troops and in that sort<br />
of context some sort of assistance.<br />
JOURNALIST: Does it avoid condemning the United States<br />
specifically? PM: Yes, the United States doesn't get named.<br />
JOURNALIST: What sort of assistance is envisaged? What sort<br />
of people would<br />
PM: Well, what you can say is that there would be no troops,<br />
n-o forces. We said from the beginning we weren't interested in<br />
that and that is not contemplated. Now, you could conceivably<br />
have some people involved in of police forces. That is a<br />
possibility. Or you could conceivably have some small<br />
supervisory body to oversee an election. The important thing<br />
to say is no troops.<br />
JOURNALIST: In terms of the Australian Government's position<br />
on this issue, have you changed your assessment of the whole<br />
Grenada invasion as a result of these talks?<br />
PM: No, we said that if we had been consulted in advance<br />
we would have counselled against invasion before the exhaustion<br />
of other possibilities and that would remain our position.<br />
What we have to say is that when you listen to the<br />
persons for Antigua, Barbados and Dominica, St Lucia, when you<br />
listen to those countries who were involved and I think that<br />
this is a comment fairly generally I mean I'm not<br />
myself. You couldn't help but be impressed by the integrity<br />
and intensity of their feelings and I think that is their<br />
concern, what was involved, and not only what had happened to<br />
Grenada, but the possible to some of their own countries.<br />
And I think that the fact that you are able to get a<br />
communique in the terms which you have got, is a reflection of<br />
how widely that was felt around the table. There is no doubt<br />
that they wanted it to happen. And putting it the other way,<br />
you could not sustain the conclusion that this was some<br />
United States plan forced upon some unwilling countries in the<br />
area. / 4 </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: In terms of our own interpretation of this<br />
communique on Grenada, it seems fairly clear that in fact<br />
the Caribbean nations have prevailed against the African<br />
criticism, if you go back to the start of the debate.<br />
I mean, do you think that is a fair comment?<br />
PM: Well, you know, there is more emphasis in the communique<br />
on the understanding of the position put by the Caribbeans<br />
and what they a~ re now saying is and I think the phrase is<br />
used there well this is a time now for reconstruction and<br />
not recrimination. I think that phrase is actually used.<br />
. I'm not going to give you the whole document but the<br />
emphasis should be on reconstruction and not recrimination.<br />
So, what they are saying is OK we've got our views and in the<br />
first part of the document there is a resolution you'll see<br />
reference to the fact that the individuals put their view,<br />
their own view, in the Security Council. They have said that<br />
and so they can refer back to that if they want to. They are<br />
now saying well, what do we do about the future. And I think<br />
it is fair enough to say that the Caribbean states would<br />
obviously not have agreed to this unless they were satisfied<br />
with the position they put be adequately taken into<br />
account and I think it has.<br />
JOURNALIST: I'd really like to check on just a bit of a<br />
tangent we understand some of the West Indian leaders may<br />
have gone off to the cricket. Now do you know if they've<br />
gone? PM: Today? Well, they did raise the question in New Delhi<br />
and then again yesterday as to whether in fact they could go.<br />
They had indicated that it would be regarded as some sort of<br />
insult by people to have been so close if they didn't in fact<br />
go. It was not a point of view which received widespread<br />
sympathy and I would think, particularly when it was pointed out<br />
that it would take an hour to fly. I was not interested at any<br />
stage, but I would have thought that for them the attractiveness of it<br />
started to diminish a bit when it was pointed out that it would<br />
take an hour to fly from Goa to Bombay and then it would take at<br />
least an hour and a half from the airport at Bombay to the ground.<br />
Whether in fact some of them have gone of f early or not, I don't<br />
know. JOURNALIST: Do you think that these CHOGM meetings are<br />
excessively long? cut down--to be out of the country for<br />
nine days for CHOGM alone?<br />
PM: Yes, fair question. I'd like to see them shorter. I can<br />
s ay that because you are quite right. It: is a long time to be<br />
out of the country. You've got to take the example we've had<br />
particularly in this CHOGM of Grenada. It is not a thing<br />
which would have lent itself to an easy resolution. If you<br />
consider how it has been spread out. The preliminary discussion<br />
formally camne on Thursday and you get down here and all of a<br />
sudden we then had further formal discussions and then a<br />
working committee and then coming back. When you've got an<br />
item like Grenada that is probably going to take a fair spread<br />
of time and it would be difficult to see how it could have been<br />
handled any inorc expeditiously than. it was, I guess. If you<br />
didn' t hiave Grenaida type si tuatiotis I think you proba-bly couldc </p>
<p>shorten them somewhat. It would be desirable, I think.<br />
JOURNALIST: Would that be getting rid of the retreat or<br />
reducing executive sessions?<br />
PM: I think there is an argument for keeping the retreat. I<br />
have had the opportunity here of having a number of interesting<br />
bilateral discussions which quite obviously are easy to be<br />
done in an environment like this. So I would see some case<br />
not for abolishing the retreat. But, even perhaps lengthening<br />
the retreat, but making sure that in the retreat structure<br />
you had, as we have had, quite a bit of formal meeting. I<br />
have heard expressions from a number of people that they thought<br />
it was a case for shortening of it and, you know, that is<br />
my sort of prima facie view.<br />
JOURNALIST: Can we just ask you on the basis of the experience<br />
you have had so far at your first CHOGM, just what sort<br />
of utility you think there is in the Commonwealth as a forum<br />
to put it bluntly, what extent you have wasted your time as<br />
opposed to having the capacity to do something constructive?<br />
PM: I certainly it is not a waste of time. I think, if you<br />
just look at this CHOGM, that you see evidence of its<br />
effectiveness in a number of ways. Take Grenada, for instance.<br />
I think that the international and domestic discussion, by<br />
which I mean in each country the domestic discussion can be<br />
changed. I think in the international apprehension can be<br />
changed by the fact that here you have had the Caribbean<br />
countries the majority of whom supported the actions those<br />
who didn't and African groups who were obviously very<br />
critical of the United States. Now, all the groups sat down<br />
together, listened to the exposition of what was involved<br />
and have come up with an agreed position. It seems to me that<br />
it must affect the understanding and debate about the issue.<br />
It is very difficult to see how you could have got that in<br />
anything out of the Commonwealth context. Cyprus again it<br />
seems to me that the fact that you've got a pretty diverse<br />
group of people again a document condemning the UBI, giving<br />
support to Kyprianou, but then importantly going on to<br />
establish a group which will work with the United Nations<br />
and may have a better chance of operating the United Nations and<br />
trying to resolve that issue. That seems to me to be very much<br />
a plus. So, there's two examples. In respect of the more<br />
general issues, like internationd1 security and disarmament,<br />
we ' ye got to wait and see what sort of a document we can come up<br />
with on that. Although there is one point specifically that<br />
I referred to which is going to be mentioned in that and is<br />
also mentioned in the Grenada document, and that is the question<br />
of the security of small states and the Commonwealth is going<br />
to set up a study group to look at this question of the security<br />
of small states to see whether in the Commonwealth context there<br />
are some things that may be able to be done which addresses that<br />
problem. Now, it's too early to say whether anything will come<br />
out of it, but it's obviously a genuine area of concern and the<br />
Commonwealth does seem to be a body which consistently looks<br />
at that issue and it may be able to come up wiL. h something. / 6. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Will Australia be represented on that<br />
PM: There is no decision yet about that would be done, at<br />
T-east initially, within the Commonwealth Secretariat, I would<br />
think and then<br />
JOURNALIST: chairing the economic discussions on the<br />
retreat, continuing on from your Friday<br />
PM: I've had well, this is an item of news interest, I suppose,<br />
wihat I'm going to go through now. Specifically I have indicated<br />
to Mr. Mugabe of Zimbabwe, to Kenneth Kuanda of Zambia and<br />
. Nyere of Tanzania that Australia will make available<br />
additional wheat aid. The details of that will be worked out.<br />
I'll get those three together to have some preliminary<br />
discussions with officials in New Delhi, then we'll take it up<br />
and try to finalise that quite quickly because they are<br />
suffering from a very significant drought in their area. Their<br />
crops have been substantially reduced and each of those three<br />
leaders have expressed their gratitude to us for that action.<br />
I had quite a long discussion with Nyere about the problems<br />
in their economy, as I have with others, and it is that sort<br />
of discussion rather than going onto the global type of things<br />
that I addressed in the meeting in Delhi on Friday. It has<br />
been very interesting to have those sort of talks.<br />
JOURNALIST: Have you spoken to Mrs. Thatcher since your<br />
contribution on Friday?<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
JOURNALIST: Who have you had the bilateral meetings with<br />
specifically? PM: Well, I've had three that I've just mentioned. I've had<br />
talks with President Kyprianou of Cyprus. I've had talks with<br />
from Western Samoa on talks we had at the Pacific Forum<br />
in Canberra and talks with Michael. Somare and Pierre Trudeau<br />
said he wanted to have a yarn to me. I'll take the opportunity<br />
of doing that today.<br />
JOURNALIST: Have you decided what is going to happen with<br />
CHOGRM PM. That is still to come up.<br />
JOURNALIST: Where is the next CHOGM? Have they decided that yet?<br />
PM: No, that hasn't come up for discussion yet and there is<br />
nothing definite about any of these, but there are possibilities<br />
that are being floated around. Trinidad was mentioned as one<br />
of the possibilities wasn't it?<br />
Bahamas.<br />
PM: Bahamas and Trinidad and Canada and Lhen just yesterday there<br />
was some mention vaguely that Fiji could be. Now, that will be<br />
picked up obviously before we leave. / 7 </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: What has happened to the suggestion of Trudeau<br />
going to Peking? Is that on or not on?<br />
PM: JOURNALIST: There was a suggestion last night that Trudeau<br />
was going to Peking.<br />
PM: Well, he said to me at the opening meeting that he as it<br />
sodnow, he was going to be meeting the Premier in Canada<br />
in middle to late January and he indicated that he would go<br />
there before then if he could and I believe he is assuming<br />
that possibility and I think he may be going before.<br />
interjections<br />
PM: Has it been<br />
Well, yes, I think he's going next week.<br />
JOURNALIST: He's going tonight.<br />
PM: Well, I knew that, but I just didn't want to say it if he<br />
hadn JOURNALIST: Can we ask you what is your reaction to Trudeau's<br />
tri-p to Peking? Do you think it can be useful in this sort<br />
of thing he is trying to pursue?<br />
PM: Yes, obviously it has the possibility of being useful.<br />
of CHOGM and for hours now we've got to get them all to<br />
agree and I just don't know ~ hat the chances of that are, but<br />
I wish him well.<br />
JOURNALIST: foreign policy. After this meeting with<br />
Commonwealth leaders, do you think you might shift the focus<br />
a little bit more towards Africa as a result?<br />
PM: No, I wouldn't think. No, we wouldn't. And in saying, no,<br />
we wouldn't, we-emphasise that we in no sense have said we<br />
didn't maintain a very real interest in what was happening in<br />
Africa and from what I've just said now, there is proof of<br />
that with the additional aid we are going to give to those three<br />
countries. We have made clear from the beginning that we see<br />
a major thrust of our policy as being in the region and nothing<br />
has happened here to change that. But, I repeat, don't carry<br />
the implication that we don't maintain our interest in other<br />
areas. of course we do and it won't be just a formal thing.<br />
When we think we can be of some assistance, we will and that is<br />
evidenced by the fact that Bill Hayden is in January and<br />
February going to the Middle East and then to visit the East<br />
African countries as well. So we've got a proper balance in<br />
these things. I must say in respect of our region, probably<br />
the person I've spent more time with throughtout the conference,<br />
not just here but in Delhi, has been Lee Kuan Yew. We've had a<br />
number of continuing talks and I believe that we've got to<br />
finalise it but when I go to South Korea, Japani, China and<br />
Hong Kong, we will be going into Singapore on the way. </p>
<p>8.<br />
JOURNALIST: On the way there or on the way back?<br />
PM: On the way, I would think.<br />
JOURNALIST: Just on that point. In these talks you've had<br />
with Lee, has there been any discussion about the resumption<br />
of the official dialogue between Australia and ASEAN?<br />
PM: No, what we--it was referred to and we just both expect<br />
i-t will flow normally they should have their next meeting<br />
in January and we just assume that the talks will pick up<br />
after that. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
