<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11671</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER            THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP            ADDRESS AT OPENING OF SUMMERLAND            CREDIT UNION OFFICE, OCEAN SHORES                     SUBJECTS: Summerland Credit Union; financial services in the bush; rural       </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/02/2000</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...................................................................................................</p>
<p>Thank you very much Larry, ladies and gentlemen.</p>
<p>I am here as I think you all know as part of an almost week long visit</p>
<p> to rural and regional parts of Australia to learn more of the opportunities</p>
<p> as well as the problems and challenges of that part of our country.</p>
<p>I have certainly learnt or have confirmed for me, I understood it before</p>
<p> but there's nothing quite like having it driven home in many face-to-face</p>
<p> discussions. But one of the things that people in the region value most</p>
<p> of all is the maintenance and expansion of basic services and whether</p>
<p> those basic services are provided by the Government, provided by the private</p>
<p> sector or provided through a cooperative effort of the two the outcome</p>
<p> is the same. That is the community has a better service, has an enhanced</p>
<p> opportunity of access to those services.</p>
<p>And one of the areas of great concern to people in the region is to have</p>
<p> adequate access to financial services. And the opening of this Credit</p>
<p> Union here in Ocean Shores today will improve the availability of financial</p>
<p> services in this part of Australia. Today is not an exercise in simply</p>
<p> maintaining an existing service level it's an exercise in increasing</p>
<p> and improving an existing service level.</p>
<p>And this has been made possible by the efforts of the Summerland Credit</p>
<p> Union which has made such an enormous contribution to this part of Australia.</p>
<p> And it's also been made possible as a result of the improved regulatory</p>
<p> environment of the credit union that came out of the Wallis inquiry. The</p>
<p> Wallis inquiry which really updated the Australian financial systems was</p>
<p> established by the Government just after we were elected in 1996. And</p>
<p> the recommendations of that inquiry have largely been adopted. And one</p>
<p> of those recommendations was to give credit unions enhanced access to</p>
<p> chequeing and other facilities, to have them more closely linked to the</p>
<p> payment system. In other words, to enhance the role, the viability and</p>
<p> therefore the capacity of credit unions throughout Australia.</p>
<p>And increasingly as we go around Australia we find credit unions replacing</p>
<p> the role that was performed by banks. We see because of the change in</p>
<p> the flexibility in Australian financial systems we see new opportunities</p>
<p> opening up for credit unions. And I applaud the credit union movement</p>
<p> and I congratulate the Summerland Credit Union in particular for the initiative</p>
<p> that is displayed genuinely and particularly for the initiative that is</p>
<p> being displayed here in Ocean Shores.</p>
<p>But in addition to that, the Government itself recognised that apart</p>
<p> from improving the regulatory climate and therefore making the expansion</p>
<p> of the credit union movement possible the other thing the Government has</p>
<p> done is to provide some $70 million out of the proceeds of the sale of</p>
<p> the second part of Telstra to finance the establishment throughout Australia</p>
<p> of 500 rural transaction centres.</p>
<p>And these are clusters of services. I opened the first one of them in</p>
<p> Eugowra which is near Parkes in New South Wales, a town of probably 500</p>
<p> or 600 people. I opened it up in the old Westpac banking chamber. And</p>
<p> the facilities that this transaction centre contained were basic financial</p>
<p> services, Medicare easy claim facilities, Internet services, copying facilities</p>
<p> and also provision for the establishment of other facilities.</p>
<p>Now, what these rural transaction centres will do is to provide on a</p>
<p> cooperative basis in small country communities around Australia a capacity</p>
<p> for the local community with seed money from the Federal Government to</p>
<p> bring basic services back to rural Australia.</p>
<p>So when you have the combination of the credit union bringing new services</p>
<p> to Australia and you have these rural transaction centres bringing services</p>
<p> back to rural Australia I think you can actually see the beginning of</p>
<p> turning around of the changes that have occurred. So having local facilities</p>
<p> is important for any local community and people want a sense of local</p>
<p> identity. This is a very nice part of the world in which to live, it deserves</p>
<p> basic services and the credit union movement is to be congratulated. And</p>
<p> Summerland Credit in particular is to be congratulated for the initiative</p>
<p> and the foresight and the commitment it is making to this community. And</p>
<p> from now on there will be a new enhanced local financial facility in this</p>
<p> part of the world. It's been made possible essentially by the credit</p>
<p> union movement but in turn the changes we made to the financial system</p>
<p> created the right environment and the right climate for the credit union</p>
<p> movement to expand.</p>
<p>I therefore wish the Summerland Credit Union well. I congratulate it.</p>
<p> I thank it for the contribution that it's making to the local community</p>
<p> and I have great pleasure in declaring the Summerland Credit Union here</p>
<p> in Ocean Shores officially open for business. Thank you.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
