<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3095</transcript-id>
    <title>GRANTS TO FILM MAKERS, ETC</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/12/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003095.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO: 6. pni 7/ 12/ 73<br />
1_, AL! SiHAXL L<br />
PRIME MINISTER PRESS STATEMENT NO. 157<br />
7 DECEMBER 1973<br />
GRANTS TO FILM MAKERS, ETC.<br />
The Chairman of the Film and Television Board of the<br />
Australian Council for the Arts, Mr Phillip Adamis, announced<br />
today that the Prime Minister had approved grants totalling<br />
$ 102,660 to a variety of film and television artists.<br />
These include grants for two projects dealing with<br />
aborigines, a grant to enable inmates of Parramatta gaol to<br />
study script writing and one to help revive a publication<br />
devoted to film making.<br />
Both the Melbourne and the Sydney Film-makers Co-operatives<br />
received grants.<br />
This brings the year's total film and television grants<br />
approved by the Prime Minister to $ 583,480.<br />
CANBERRA. A. C. T. </p>
<p>LIST OF GRANTS<br />
SCRIPT DEVELOPMENT AD RESEARCH<br />
DAVID BAZER. To develop a screenplay from the novel, Salute to the Great<br />
McCarthy. $ 3800<br />
GEORGE PUGH. To develop an outline to treatment stage. $ 200<br />
MONA BRAND. To enable the applicant to work with a script supervisor to write<br />
the screen play of either Christmas Goose or The Ghost of Grey Gables. $ 1450<br />
RON BUMNEY. To enable the applicant to develop a script to screen play stage<br />
either Impossible Burden or another script of his own choice. $ 600<br />
GEOFFREY PORTVANN. To enable the applicant and writer Ron Harrison to develop<br />
a screen play from the stage play Father Dear Come Over Here. $ 1834<br />
GEORGE DICK. To research and write the treatment of a TV pilot for a proposed<br />
series of six 30 min. episodes. $ 465<br />
BEWICK HACK. Script development and research br an historical and educational<br />
film based on Lawrence Hargreaves. $ 600<br />
RALPH MARSDEN. To develop a script outline to treatment stage. $ 450<br />
JOIIH POOLEY. To develop a script outline to treatment stage. $ 400<br />
DANIEL HUGHES. To develop a script outline to treatment stage. $ 400<br />
PARRAMATTA GAOL ( The Harris Bush Drama Society). To enable a professional<br />
script editor ( Harold Lander) to work regularly with a group of writers in<br />
the gaol over a period of 30 weeks. $ 2000<br />
TILM AND TELEVISION PRODUCTTON<br />
GEOFFREY BARDON. To make a 30 min. documentary studying aboriginal artists of<br />
Papunya Aboriginal settlement via Alice Springs. $ 5000<br />
IETER DRUMMOID. To make a film about the Nomads, a tribe of Aborigines of the<br />
Pilbarra region of ! North-lest Australia, who are mining successfully for tin.<br />
$ 6563 ( Interest free loan)<br />
MICHAEL PRICE. To make a 15 min. film which looks at the activities of groups<br />
and organisations demanding a greater control over their daily lives. $ 2000<br />
JOHNI HUGHES. To make a 30 min. film on the subject of racism in Australian<br />
society. $ 2500<br />
GEIERAL PRODUCTION<br />
JOIH BIRD. To cover the cost of processing, inter-nogative and workprint of<br />
camera footage shot by the McCubbin-Bonython Expedition. $ 476<br />
EDIE VAN DER MADDEN. To enable a sound track to be put on a 23 rin. animated<br />
film Alladin. $ 6372 ( Interest free loan)<br />
CINEMA PAPERS. To assist with the first issu, of a new film publication called<br />
Cinema Papers. $ 11600 ($ 10000 grant, $ 1600 interest free loan)<br />
THE ARTS COUNCIL OF AUSTRALIA ( Victoria). To assist with the presentation of<br />
Australian films on a tour of Victoria. $ 2000 ( Guarantee against loss)<br />
WARWICK ROBBINS. The Film and Television Board and the Film and Television<br />
School wish to jointly assist the applicant on a study tour of overseas community<br />
access video centroe. c2500 </p>
<p>AUSTRALIAN FILM IINSTITUTE. For video research and instruction to Ungarie School,<br />
NSW and community by S Varga and J Kirk. $ 700<br />
AUSTRALIAN! FILM INSTITUTE. For undertaking modifications on vidoo equipment<br />
through Swinburne College of Technology for use in community access video<br />
situations. $ 1250<br />
AUSTRALIAN FILM INSTITUTE ( Research on overseas films for the Vincent Library).<br />
For research on overseas films for use as reference by the Vincent Library: by<br />
Albie Thorns and Barrett Hodsdon. $ 400<br />
AUSTRALIAN FILM INSTITUTE. For assistance to the Melbourne Film-makers' Cooperative<br />
in leasing and renovating promises for the exhibition of films and<br />
allied facilities. The interest-free loan is to be repaid within three years.<br />
$ 19000 ($ 14000 grant, $ 5000 interest-free loan).<br />
SYDNEY FILMMAKERS' CO-OPERATIVE. For assistance to the Sydney Filmmakers'<br />
Co-operative for administrative costs, salaries, theatre rental and advertising,<br />
$ 15000<br />
T! E FILM SECPLdTARIAT. Payment to the Film Secretariat for the services of a<br />
librarian for collating references to Australian film productions and allied<br />
materials for the George Lugg Library. $ 4000<br />
AUSTRALIAN COUNCIL FOR CHILDRLIIS FILMS AND TELEVISION. For the purchase and<br />
distribution of prints of overseas childrens' films. $ 10000<br />
PATRICIA CLARE. For development of a script for an animated story film. $ 1050 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
