<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8981</transcript-id>
    <title>INTV PRIME MINISTER KEATING</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/09/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008981.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
NINE NETWOIRK AUSTRALIA LIMI'I: ED<br />
A C. N. 009 071 167<br />
SUITE 114 PRISS GALLERY PARLIAMENT HOUSE<br />
CANDEkRA A. C. T. 2600 AUSTRALIA<br />
TELEPHONF.: ( nW) 273 3300 FACSIMILE: ( 06) 273 3097<br />
SUNDAY092026-09-93<br />
INTV Prime Minister Keating<br />
Compere Jim Waley:<br />
Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating:<br />
Laurie Oakes: Prime Minister Keating flew back into Canberra early<br />
this morning, after a two week trip to the US, Britain,<br />
Ireland and France. His last stop, Monte Carlo, to<br />
bolster our Olympic bid.<br />
Before leaving there, hlie gave his first comprehensive<br />
interview on what's been an unusually productive<br />
fortnight for a travelling Australian leader.<br />
Paul Keating is talking with SUNDAY's Political Editor,<br />
Laurie Oakes.<br />
Mr Keating, welcome to SUNDAY.<br />
Good, Laurie.<br />
Winning the 2000 Olympics for Sydney is a big finish to<br />
an overseas trip for a Prime Minister. But now the<br />
excitement's abated a bit, I mean, can we afford it?<br />
T00ON St7: 8 26' d@ S'LZ_<br />
WIN TV<br />
Subject: </p>
<p>Paul Keating:<br />
Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating:<br />
Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating: We can more than afford it. I think it's a substantial<br />
international endorsement of what we've become as a<br />
nation. Because I think were we not as we are, and as<br />
we're going to be that is an externally oriented<br />
country, which has got a real scnse of democracy and<br />
good values we wouldn't have won this decision.<br />
So, I think, in terms of the directions which Australia's<br />
been going in the last ten years, the Olympic, the TOC<br />
decision, in a sense, endorses those directions.<br />
But can you guarantee that ordinary taxpayers won't<br />
have to dig deeper into their pockets?<br />
I think on the net balance of things, probably in<br />
economic terms, Australia will end up in front. The key<br />
point is it will show the world Australia as we now are,<br />
as a multi-cultural country, a successful independent<br />
country. And I think by then, this is seven years away,<br />
we will be much more part of the Pacific, the Asia<br />
Pacific, and we'll be I think, even more clear about our<br />
identity than we are this very week.<br />
Now, obviously, this will lead to some upsurge of<br />
nationalism patriotism, I suppose. Do you think that<br />
will give the republican movement a kick along?<br />
I think it will, probably, yes I think it will. And I<br />
think it deserves to, because I think that it is important<br />
2<br />
/ Z0Od TOO* ON St7: 8 i6* dGS*! </p>
<p>that when the world conmes to see us, as i t will in such a<br />
concentrated way, we're there, you know, having a<br />
much clearer idea about ourselves, you know, and more<br />
confidence in ourselves.<br />
Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating:<br />
Laurie Oakes-<br />
Paul Keating:<br />
Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating: Could we have a President by then?<br />
That's a possibility, it is. Somecbody's got to open the<br />
Games. It's normally the Head of State. I think the<br />
world would wonder, would they not, if Australia's<br />
Gaines are opened by the Constitutional head of another<br />
nation. The question of Mabo and reconciliation between<br />
Aboriginal and non-Aboriginal Australians<br />
presumably the Olympics have a bearing on that, too?<br />
I think they have a very large bearing.<br />
But can you get there? You've got the Deputy<br />
Opposition Leader, the Deputy Coalition Leader,<br />
Tim Fischer, talking about Aborigines being ungrateful<br />
for the money that's spent on them. I mean, that's the<br />
sort of thing the world will look at, I would have<br />
thought, when the Games are on.<br />
I don't think the IOC would have endorsed that view,<br />
you see, that's the point. I think a lot of politicians in<br />
Australia are going to have to scrub up their: views.<br />
3<br />
TOOO0N StV2? 26* dGS </p>
<p>Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating: And if the world's actually invested in Australia and<br />
this is a good decision by the IOC, an important<br />
international decision. Because there was a big contest<br />
here between China and Australia, and it. was the values<br />
of Australia which carried the day. In the end it was the<br />
values of Australia which carried the day. If those<br />
values are compromised by the sort of paltry views of<br />
some people in the political system, that will not be<br />
good for us.<br />
There are political implications, aren't there. I know<br />
that the New South Wales Labor Party is concerned that<br />
John Fahey will call an election on the strength of the<br />
Olympic decision. Does that worry you?<br />
Well, I don't think, I think John Fahey has, frankly,<br />
more sense than to try and exploit this decision in a<br />
personal way. This was a group effort. Laurie, the<br />
thing about it was it should inject a lot of confidence<br />
in the people. It's one thing that the Government, me<br />
and others, saying look, we're going quite well, we've a<br />
very large leap in terms of our economny, we've made a<br />
huge leap into Asia, we're now trying to sort of APEC,<br />
we're trying to sort out our place in the world and<br />
there's a lot of pessimism in Australia. I think this<br />
decision should provide a basis for confidence for<br />
people. We're actually doing better than many people<br />
think we are. 4<br />
TOODON SV: 8 26, dasU ] J31 </p>
<p>Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul K~ eating: Well, related to that, I guess, the running theme of your<br />
trip in Washington, London, Ireland and France was<br />
trade the GATT negotiations your concern about<br />
European attempts to breach the Blair House Agreement.<br />
Do you think you got anywhere?<br />
I think so. One thing is clear, that there's no doubt, I<br />
mean, the centrepiece of my visit was the meeting with<br />
President Clinton. That went well in my terms I<br />
hope, and I think, in his. And that it wasn't about,<br />
simply about reaffirmation of our defence links, and the<br />
normal things we talk about. What was high on the US<br />
agenda that week I was there was trade, which was high<br />
on our agenda, too. And we've agreed now to kick<br />
APEC along that's Asia Pacific Economic Cooperation<br />
with a meeting that President Clinton is<br />
sponsoring in November in Seattle. And at that meeting<br />
I should hope that we give much more form and<br />
substance to APEC.<br />
Now, that is, in a sense, Australia's bolt-hole. That is<br />
to get this organisation together, to put Australia at a<br />
very large table for the first time.<br />
What we then want to do is overlay that with the GATT'<br />
the General Agreement on Trade and Tariffs, the socalled<br />
Uruguay Round. Now, it is stalling at the<br />
moment because of Frcnch intransigence over the Blair<br />
House Accord, which was an agreemenit freely entered<br />
PSO'd TOO* ON St7: S œ 6~ d2aS* LJ.,-131 </p>
<p>Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating:<br />
Laurie Oakes: between the European Community and United States.<br />
We say the Blair House shouldn't be touched. Special<br />
Trade Representative Cantor says the Blair House<br />
Accord shouldn't be touched, and so does the President.<br />
Now, you seemed to strike a fairly quick rapport with<br />
Bill Clinton. Is it now the sort of relationship where<br />
you feel you can pick up the phone whenever you want<br />
to? Are you likely to do that?<br />
I could he invited me to do that, and I could do that.<br />
Look, I think Americans have fallen on their fret with<br />
Bill Clinton. I think he's a young, fresh, altruistic,<br />
engaging person, and you can see the any<br />
conversation, the detail that he has in his mind on issues<br />
I mean, in our system Ministers are expcctcd to carry<br />
detail in their heads. In the American system this has<br />
not always been a requirement of US Presidents but<br />
he has it, he can talk about fiscal policy, tax policy,<br />
health policy, trade policy. I mean, he's the genuine<br />
article, and I think that we're very lucky that the United<br />
States is led by a person who comprehends these big<br />
problems and trying to marry the big international<br />
responsibilities of the United States on to the domestic<br />
agenda of growth and jobs.<br />
You're seeing him again in Seattle in November. Are<br />
you going to formally invite him to Australia?<br />
TOO* ON SV: S 26* d9S*, </p>
<p>Paul Keating:<br />
Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating:<br />
Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating: I will. I think that's the time to do it. It didn't on this<br />
occasion, because I think it was a get-to-know-you<br />
meeting, arnd I'll be seeing him soon, and I'll be<br />
speaking to him in the meantime. anyway.<br />
Do you think he'll come?<br />
H-e might. I think he might.<br />
Prime Minister, we'll take a break there be back in a<br />
moment.<br />
Prime Minister, you made a very brief visit to France,<br />
really to lay a wreath and remember our World War I<br />
dead but that turned into a trade matter, too. You<br />
attacked the French there, I suppose almost using dead<br />
dig gers as bargaining chips. What made you so angry<br />
when you got to Velarise Breteneau(?)?<br />
Well, you've got to say to yourself, what does it mean?<br />
I mean, here's a hundred odd thousand young<br />
Australians went from one side of the world to the<br />
other, half of them left their lives behind in defence of<br />
France, French liberty and values.<br />
And, you know, I was there with the names of eleven<br />
thousand Australian service mnen and women engraved<br />
on the wall of that place, Velarise Breteneau, and yet in<br />
Paris on a matter which is about international decency<br />
7<br />
TOO* ON SV: 8 œ 6* daS, 2 1331 </p>
<p>and fair play, which does affect Australia materially,<br />
you're flat out getting a point of view registered.<br />
So you've got to say to yourself what does this mean? I<br />
mean, we were there twice. The actual -the<br />
monument was all, the monument which was built in the<br />
early 1 920s after the first World War was all pock<br />
marked with bullet holes from the second World War,<br />
where we were again.<br />
And you've got to say to yourself, well do we rank at<br />
all with these characters? I mean, that is, did it mean<br />
anything to them? Because what you've got we're<br />
not asking, they're saying, oh, we can't affect the<br />
French farm sector. But we've had to make decisions<br />
about tariffs. We've made decisions which affect our<br />
garment industry and our textile industry and footwear<br />
industries, arnd our manufacturing industries. We've<br />
done what's best for Australia, and we've played our<br />
role as international citizens. But this dog-in-the-manger<br />
attitude which France persists in-<br />
Laurie Oakes: They've protested to you, haven't they, about your<br />
comments?<br />
Paul Keating: Oh, no they gave some churlish off-hand remark by<br />
some Deputy Minister. I mean, I've stung them where<br />
it " matters, and that is to say, look, you've got<br />
responsibilities, and we're making you face the fact that<br />
/ S0* d TO000N SV: S 2œ 6' d, 3SZ </p>
<p>if the Round fails, you will wear the responsibility for<br />
Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating:<br />
Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating: Could I ask you about your trip to Balmoral I know<br />
you don't want to say any more about tile meeting with<br />
the Queen than-<br />
Laurie, I don't want to say because, not because I want<br />
to be secretive and evasive. But it is at convention, and<br />
an important one, which the Queen has insisted on<br />
always, that the details of the meeting remain private to<br />
her and the person she's meeting.<br />
Now, she did break that convention by authorising me to<br />
make that statement, which was a very important one,<br />
and I can talk about that.<br />
Well, part of that statement was you said the Queen had<br />
said that she would abide by the inaudible for<br />
Australian Ministers and the decision of the Australian<br />
people. But you'd expect a Constitutional Monarch to<br />
say exactly that, wouldn't you?<br />
Well, yes but she didn't need to authorise me to say<br />
it. I mean,, it could have been that the view from the<br />
Palace was that she would, she would be advised at<br />
least, the Queen would be advised at least to resist such<br />
a change. And being perfectly proper, which I've<br />
always believed the Queen to he, she not only forth-<br />
.9<br />
1000ON S17: 8 26* d@ S </p>
<p>rightly met that position, but auithorised that I should say<br />
Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating:<br />
Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating:<br />
Laurie Oakes: So was she declaring herself a neutral player in this? Is<br />
that how you see. it?<br />
Essentially, what she's authorised me to say is this was<br />
matter for Australians, for Australians to decide, and<br />
that she should abide with any decision made by the<br />
Australian people.<br />
Can I put to you some of the things that British<br />
newspapers reported newspapers that claim good<br />
Palace sources, A whole serics of them. claim that when<br />
it came to the point of telling the Queen about your<br />
republican plans you almost bottled it. In other words<br />
you almost froze up and weren't game.<br />
Now let's not underestimate the gravity of this meeting<br />
and the gravity with which the Queen's staff would<br />
have approached, and did approach this meeting. There<br />
would be no leaks from this meeting.<br />
Now, that's not an accurate reflection of the meeting.<br />
The meeting was cordial, and warm, and utterly<br />
discursive on the substantive issues which took, I think,<br />
seventy five minutes.<br />
Did you almost bottle it?<br />
/ OTd T000N SV: S6' das&gt; I2 : 11331 </p>
<p>Paul Keating:<br />
Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating:<br />
Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating: Well, I said to you it's not an accurate reflection of the<br />
meeting. No, I didn't. I put, as I said before the trip,<br />
my views, courteously, informatively and forth-rightly<br />
and I hope for Her Majesty, helpfully.<br />
They also claim, the British press also claim that you<br />
had a chilly reception that you had to stand outside in<br />
the cold at a barbeque, and got a royal cold shoulder.<br />
I can say, I'm entitled say and I'm sure she should want<br />
me to say that it couldn't have been a warmer meeting.<br />
It couldn't have been a warmer reception in a personal.<br />
family way.<br />
Could I ask you, just we before we finish, about some<br />
domestic issues. You're going back now to, I suppose,<br />
the old problems that you left, some of which are worse.<br />
What about the John Dawkins issue? I mean, is he<br />
showing the strain of this budget battle?<br />
This Government's directions are right, and they have<br />
been right, and we've got to pull those threads together,<br />
and I'm going to call the Cabinet together on Monday<br />
morning to tell them about the trip. And at that meeting<br />
we will have a discussion then also about our budgetary<br />
position, and the budget.<br />
Now, the budget's sense is right. It's aggiegates are<br />
right. We've had a problem with the detail, but the time<br />
11<br />
/ TT* d TOO* ON S7: S 16d@ S 131 </p>
<p>Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating:<br />
Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating:<br />
Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating: has come, I think, for everybody to pass the budget and<br />
for the country to get on with it, because we've got so<br />
many other big things to do.<br />
Now, I think the Treasurer has, not unnaturally, been<br />
left to his own devices while I've been away, to fend off<br />
discussion and argument about the budget, including<br />
dealing with the Independents.<br />
And he felt pretty lonely, I would say.<br />
I've spoken to him a couple of times on the visit, and<br />
not unnaturally in this circumstances because what's<br />
happened here is the Opposition have broken the<br />
convention by not passing the Government's Financial<br />
legislation in the Senate.<br />
B3ut the Treasurer has looked pretty brittle, hasn't he?<br />
publicly talking about resignation. I mean, presumably<br />
he didn't-<br />
Well, If think he was sort of, perhaps, waxing a bit<br />
lyrical about that, but, I mean, we've all done that. from<br />
time to time. This is not a cardinal sin.<br />
Did he talk about resigning about the budget, and again<br />
on the phone with you the other day?<br />
No, no, no -he hasn't, no.<br />
12<br />
Td 1000ON St7: 8 16* d@ S131 </p>
<p>L. a urie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating:<br />
Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating-.<br />
Laurie Oakes: When you call Cabinet together on Monday, will they<br />
bet getting some sort of pep talk from you about the<br />
need now to-<br />
Well, I think, I think, Laurie-<br />
-show more unity, I suppose?<br />
Well, we've invested a lot of time in Mabo, which is<br />
important, and you can see the importance with the<br />
Olympic decision if for no other reason. That is,<br />
beyond the great central reason of reconciliation and<br />
access to land and decency in public decision making in<br />
respcct of Aboriginals. Apart from that, just in termis of<br />
the Olympics, how important that's been. We've<br />
invested a lot of time in that, because Maho is a<br />
revolutionary change in land management and social<br />
justice questions.<br />
But that's now coming together in that legislation. The<br />
budget aggregates are right the directions are right<br />
the budget deficit should conie down. And that's been<br />
presented, and we've trimmed the budget up) in certain<br />
respects without changing its aggregates substantially.<br />
So, yes, we've had a few problems with those, but<br />
they're going into place.<br />
You're looking a bit ragged, aren't you, as a<br />
VT/ 2Pd TOO* ON St7: S 26-daS 13311 </p>
<p>Paul Keating:<br />
Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating: Government and won't that continue while the Senate<br />
is doing what it's doing? Presumably it's not just a<br />
budget problem? They're going to look at all your<br />
major legislation.<br />
Well, I think, providing the Government's convinced of<br />
its policy directions and satisfied with its work, we'll<br />
live with the Senate, and we'll stare the Senate down,<br />
and we'll win the public argument. I mean, that's the<br />
key point.<br />
Prime Minister, thank you very much.<br />
Thank you, Laurie.<br />
ENDS* For private research only. Whilst every effort is made to ensure accuracy for the benefit of our clients,<br />
no legal or other responsibility is taken for errors and omissions.<br />
Transcript by MEDIA MONITORS ACT PTY LTD 14<br />
t71/ Vt * d TOO* ON SV: S 26 d@ S :-113311 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
