<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11366</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER          ADDRESS AT TASMANIAN DIVISION OF THE          LIBERAL PARTY STATE COUNCIL          GRAND CHANCELLOR HOTEL, TASMANIA                                          </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/08/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Subjects: Liberal Party traditions; Liberal achievements; Tony Rundle; Hydro</p>
<p>   policy, Tasmania's debt; Forest industry; Tough on Drugs policy; Gun control;</p>
<p>E&amp;OE....................</p>
<p>  Thank you very much, Shane; to Jim Bowler; to Sue Napier, your Grace; Senator</p>
<p>   Jocelyn Newman, the senior Federal representative from Tasmania and my valued</p>
<p>   Cabinet colleague, my other Parliamentary colleagues, ladies and gentlemen.</p>
<p>  Can I say how happy I am again as Prime Minister to address this State Council,</p>
<p>   this annual gathering, of the Tasmanian Division of the Liberal Party. I</p>
<p>   wish also to extend my great gratitude to Jim for the tremendous work that</p>
<p>   he's done over the past years as President of the Division. I came through</p>
<p>   the Party organisation. I know that the pay is low and the material rewards</p>
<p>   are limited but I also know that the immense satisfaction of fighting for</p>
<p>   something that you believe in and contributing to a cause that you feel</p>
<p>   will better the welfare of the people of Australia is about the most satisfying</p>
<p>   and rewarding thing that you can do. But it hasn't been easy here in Tasmania.</p>
<p>   And I thank you most warmly, Jim. You'll be remembered and the work that</p>
<p>   you've done will be seen quite properly as an immense contribution to the</p>
<p>   Liberal Party cause in Tasmania.</p>
<p>  Can I also join Shane in remarking on the contribution of Tony Rundle. Shane</p>
<p>   was right, he and Tony got away with blue murder on occasions through their</p>
<p>   quiet, whimsical, effective way. I mean, they sort of sat and said nothing</p>
<p>   and they, you know, when one or other of their colleagues was sort of railing</p>
<p>   against the centralists in Canberra, they would say, oh, you know, they</p>
<p>   shouldn't talk to you like that, John, that's shocking but how about such</p>
<p>   and such. They did it very well. They did it very skilfully. But Tony did</p>
<p>   something else at the last election here in Tasmania. And I know it's not,</p>
<p>   in a sense, of much comfort and satisfaction in the political world to say,</p>
<p>   well, you were right but the people didn't understand that. But in the long</p>
<p>   run that does mean something. Because in the long run being in office is</p>
<p>   not about having a white car and having the privilege of being the Premier</p>
<p>   or the Prime Minister and sort of getting welcomed and people saying nice</p>
<p>   things about you. In the long run being in government is about trying to</p>
<p>   do good things for the country or trying to do good things for your State.</p>
<p>   And what Tony Rundle did at the last election was to say what had to be</p>
<p>   said. And what he said in the last election campaign was true then and it's</p>
<p>   even more true a year on. Because every country, every State, every municipality</p>
<p>   is, in the end, master of its own destiny and that implies both privileges</p>
<p>   as well as responsibilities. And Tony was prepared to discharge the ultimate</p>
<p>   responsibility of somebody holding a position of authority and that was</p>
<p>   to tell people what was needed to secure their future even though part of</p>
<p>   the message was not immediately accepted and not immensely palatable. And</p>
<p>   in the long run when the history of this period of Tasmanian politics is</p>
<p>   written people will say that Rundle was right in what he said about the</p>
<p>   State's debt and the he had the courage to state it. I wish you well. I</p>
<p>   wish both you and Carolyn every happiness in the future. I count you as</p>
<p>   a friend and colleague of the highest order and I think you've done a great</p>
<p>   thing by the Tasmanian people and by the Liberal Party here in your State.</p>
<p>  A gathering like this, friends, is an occasion to reflect as well as project</p>
<p>   forward. This is the last Tasmanian State Council of this century, this</p>
<p>   millennium. And it's an occasion, therefore, to reflect on the heritage</p>
<p>   of the Liberal Party. It will be 50 years in December since Robert Gordon</p>
<p>   Menzies and Arthur Fadden led the Coalition to power in 1949. And over that</p>
<p>   50 years there's a lot about the Liberal heritage of which we should be</p>
<p>   immensely proud. We should understand the character of our party. We, in</p>
<p>   the term that I've coined somewhat, we are a broad church. Unlike centre</p>
<p>   right parties in other parts of the world the Liberal Party of Australia</p>
<p>   is the custodian of both the classical Liberal tradition in our society</p>
<p>   as well as the conservative tradition. We are neither a conservative party</p>
<p>   exclusively nor are we a small 'l' Liberal Party exclusively. We are a mix</p>
<p>   of the two. There are things about Australia's history and our past that</p>
<p>   I believe continue to serve us well and should be preserved. There are things</p>
<p>   about our past and there are things about what we do now that need to be</p>
<p>   changed and reformed to provide us a stronger and better future. And the</p>
<p>   art of good statecraft is to choose from the past, from the heritage, from</p>
<p>   the history, those things that are of continuing and enduring value but</p>
<p>   also to recognise that change and reform in other areas is necessary to</p>
<p>   secure stability and to secure progress. And the Liberal Party has always</p>
<p>   been about trying to balance those things. The Liberal Party has always</p>
<p>   been about the liberty of the individual.</p>
<p>  One of the proudest things that I was able to say at the Wentworth Hotel</p>
<p>   on the 2nd of March 1996 when I formally accepted the immense</p>
<p>   privilege that had been conferred upon me and my party at the election,</p>
<p>   at the ballot box that day was that the Liberal Party of Australia was owned</p>
<p>   by no one section of the Australian community.</p>
<p>  We are sympathetic to business. But we are not beholden to business. We</p>
<p>   understand the importance of profit and capitalism but we recognise the</p>
<p>   potential for abuse and excesses that can occur. We recognise that the Government</p>
<p>   has a limited role but nonetheless a strategic role within our community.</p>
<p>   We are not for the government withdrawing from all areas of activity, but</p>
<p>   we are for the government focussing on those areas that properly belong</p>
<p>   to government and that does not normally include commercial activity.</p>
<p>  We're a Party that does not believe in privilege or class. We are a Party</p>
<p>   that honours and respects tradition but also prides itself in sharing the</p>
<p>   great egalitarian tradition of the Australian people. We are increasingly</p>
<p>   a party that represents people who might in another time and another era</p>
<p>   have regarded themselves as traditional supporters of the Labor Party. I</p>
<p>   was immensely satisfied and pleased that in 1996 one of the great features</p>
<p>   of the Coalition's victory on that occasion, was that many of the great</p>
<p>   industrial centers of our country, and the great mining centres of our country,</p>
<p>   historically associated with the Australian Labor Party were in fact returned</p>
<p>   federal members representing the Coalition.</p>
<p>  The city of Broken Hill is represented in the federal parliament by a member</p>
<p>   of the National Party. The city of Mt Isa is represented in the federal</p>
<p>   parliament by a coalition member. The cities of Whyalla and Port Pirie in</p>
<p>   South Australia are represented in the national parliament by a Liberal</p>
<p>   member. And so the list can go on. And I think it is very important that</p>
<p>   as we move into the next millennium, for all of us to understand that we're</p>
<p>   living in a different political world. It's a less ideological political</p>
<p>   world.</p>
<p>  The Australian community, particularly those under 30 are not as beholden</p>
<p>   to ideology as were their parents. They don't see themselves being involved</p>
<p>   in an angry struggle about ideology the way in which their parents may have</p>
<p>   in the 1960s. They are however people who look for positive outcomes. They</p>
<p>   are interested in a political party that delivers results. That can do things</p>
<p>   to make their lives more secure. And I think as we move into the next millennium</p>
<p>   we will see politics shaped less by rigid ideology but nonetheless shaped</p>
<p>   very strongly by basic values and there is a difference.</p>
<p>  Ideology to me has always been something rather rigid imposed from above.</p>
<p>   Whereas values are things that come from the community and in a sense are</p>
<p>   ageless. The instincts of candour and honesty and civil behavior and respect</p>
<p>   for the rights of the individual and the acceptance that in any decent society</p>
<p>   along with rights and privileges go responsibilities and obligations. They</p>
<p>   are values which are quite ageless in my view and embeddable. They will</p>
<p>   be expressed in different ways in different times and political parties</p>
<p>   have a responsibility to respond to those different circumstances.</p>
<p>  So it is important on an occasion like this that we think about what our</p>
<p>   party has achieved. Not only have we been in office for 34 of the last 50</p>
<p>   years, but many of the great breakthroughs that have occurred, the great</p>
<p>   breakthroughs in terms of tolerance and human values and a quality of opportunity</p>
<p>   have occurred under Federal Liberal governments. It was after a federal</p>
<p>   Liberal government that really opened up opportunities for the entire Australian</p>
<p>   population for a university education. And the reforms carried out in that</p>
<p>   area by the Menzies government in the 1950s remained one of the great contributions</p>
<p>   to the expansion of education to the Australian people.</p>
<p>  It was under a coalition government that the white Australia policy was</p>
<p>   ended under the Prime Ministership of Harold Holt. It was under the leadership</p>
<p>   of the Fraser government that was accepted into our country over 150,000</p>
<p>   Indochinese refugees. In fact we took more Indochinese refugees in the 1970s</p>
<p>   on a per capita basis than any country on earth and that was Australia being</p>
<p>   an open hearted, decent spirited country offering a haven to people whose</p>
<p>   lives have been devastated by a long and costly war. It was under a Coalition</p>
<p>   government that we ended one of the great sectarian divides in this country</p>
<p>   when we provided assistance to independent schools and recognised a cornerstone</p>
<p>   of education policy in this country. And that is that every Australian parent</p>
<p>   has the right to choose the form of education that his or her child should</p>
<p>   receive. And that principle was re-endorsed only two or three months ago</p>
<p>   when we announced long-term plans to provide even more choice to Australian</p>
<p>   parents in relation to the education of their children.</p>
<p>  A Coalition government has been responsible for many of the great [tape</p>
<p>   break] and coming up to date we now have a Coalition government presiding</p>
<p>   over and having made a great contribution towards achieving the strongest</p>
<p>   economic conditions that this country has had for more than 30 years. And</p>
<p>   there are many statistics that I could regale you with this morning about</p>
<p>   the strength of our economy. The one that in a persona sense is the most</p>
<p>   heart-warming of all is that in the three-and-a-quarter that we have been</p>
<p>   in government since March of 1996 we have seen a 5.8 percentage point decline</p>
<p>   in the number of young Australians looking for work. And that is the best</p>
<p>   figure of all because in the end a good economy exists to provide good living</p>
<p>   standards and rising job opportunities.</p>
<p>  Our unemployment rate is still too high. It's seven percent nationally.</p>
<p>   It's much higher in Tasmania. It's lower in other parts of Australia. It's</p>
<p>   uneven, it's lumpy. And we still have a long way to go but it's better than</p>
<p>   it's been for the last 10 years. And we've created almost 500,000 jobs in</p>
<p>   the last three and a bit years. And if we can continue our current rate</p>
<p>   of economic growth and, better still, if we can persuade the Senate to pass</p>
<p>   our laws entrenching youth wages and dealing with the unfair burden on small</p>
<p>   business of the unfair dismissal laws then we can hope to drive that unemployment</p>
<p>   rate even lower. And it will be one of the goals of the Government to keep</p>
<p>   doing that. Because the economic strength we have now must be translated</p>
<p>   increasingly in the years ahead towards providing more job opportunities</p>
<p>   for our young people. And those job opportunities will essentially be found</p>
<p>   in private business and the private sector. The strength of the business</p>
<p>   community and the business sector is still the foundation of job generation</p>
<p>   in this country. And that is why the security that the Federal Government,</p>
<p>   the Howard Government and the Rundle Government brought to the timber industry</p>
<p>   in this State was so important because it's a major employer in Tasmania.</p>
<p>   And that is why, as I said to you last night, I'm distributed at the import</p>
<p>   of the amendments that are being proposed in Canberra by our Federal opponents.</p>
<p>   Although, I make it plain to you, there's no way those amendments will be</p>
<p>   accepted by the Government. But the very fact that they're being proposed</p>
<p>   show an indifference towards the long-term economic security of this State.</p>
<p>   At long last I think there in Tasmania we've got a balance between the maintenance</p>
<p>   of a strong industry but also a proper concern for the environmental values</p>
<p>   of the State. And I want that balance preserved, I want it protected and</p>
<p>   I want it secured. And I can assure you on behalf of the Federal Government</p>
<p>   that we'll make absolutely certain that nothing is done to undermine, disturb</p>
<p>   or qualify the agreement that I signed with Tony Rundle covering regional</p>
<p>   forest arrangements in Tasmania and the investment that has been made by</p>
<p>   the industry will be fully honoured and fully protected and the jobs that</p>
<p>   have been created and secured as a consequence of that investment will also</p>
<p>   be fully honoured and fully protected.</p>
<p>  As we survey both the past and the present political scene at this State</p>
<p>   Council gathering we also throw forward naturally to the next millennium.</p>
<p>   What Australia has been able to do over the last three years has been to</p>
<p>   win a new respect, a new admiration around the world. We have important</p>
<p>   goals both nationally and internationally. We seek to build our reputation</p>
<p>   as a 'can do' country, as a country that can convert our inventive capacity</p>
<p>   to commercial benefit and commercial return. A country that has the capacity</p>
<p>   to become not only a regional financial centre but a world financial centre.</p>
<p>   Because the generic assets we have at the moment, a stable government, a</p>
<p>   stable economy, clear laws of corporate behaviour, an incorruptible judiciary,</p>
<p>   well regulated and supervised banks, Australians having a great capacity</p>
<p>   to speak the languages of the region with considerable skill and dexterity,</p>
<p>   all of those things make Australia an increasingly attractive place in which</p>
<p>   to invest and to establish regional service and financial activities. And</p>
<p>   we have great opportunities as we go into the next century to achieve those</p>
<p>   goals.</p>
<p>  And in relation to Tasmania I want to assure you again that the Government</p>
<p>   I lead will continue to have a particular concern for the special requirements</p>
<p>   and the special circumstances of Tasmania. We have, after all, a very good</p>
<p>   record. We gave Tasmania such fundamental programmes as the freight equalisation</p>
<p>   scheme. We've always understood the disabilities of an island State regarding</p>
<p>   transport costs. I don't think anybody can contest the fact that Tasmania</p>
<p>   has been fairly treated out of the Natural Heritage Trust and all the other</p>
<p>   programmes that have come from the sale of the various tranches of Telstra.</p>
<p>   And we'll continue to ensure that Tasmania gets her fair share and gets</p>
<p>   a fair deal. But as I said last night and I repeat this morning, that there</p>
<p>   remains a long-term cloud over the economic future of Tasmania and that</p>
<p>   is the debt of this State which is four times the State average. And until</p>
<p>   the bullet is bitten and something is done about that debt here in Tasmania</p>
<p>   your economic growth will continue to be constrained. And that is why I</p>
<p>   remain compassionately of the view that something must be done about the</p>
<p>   privatisation of the Hydro. I know that's unpopular in some circles in Tasmania.</p>
<p>   I know I will be condemned for saying it. But just as Tony Rundle spoke</p>
<p>   the truth a year ago, I speak the truth this morning when I reassert its</p>
<p>   necessity. Every other State in Australia and nationally is tackling the</p>
<p>   debt problem.</p>
<p>  The South Australian Government struggled to get its electricity authority's</p>
<p>   privatisation legislation the Parliament and succeeded. The Victorian Government</p>
<p>   has massively reduced the debt of that State and lifted the hopes and the</p>
<p>   living standards of Victorians by the action that it's taken. If we can</p>
<p>   secure the sale of the rest of Telstra by the year 2002 we will free Australia</p>
<p>   of net Commonwealth Government debt and that will lay the foundation of</p>
<p>   good circumstances for interest rates in the early years of the next century</p>
<p>   and also provide us the flexibility in time for further reductions in taxation.</p>
<p>   Because if you can rid yourself of the burden of debt the money you otherwise</p>
<p>   use to pay off the debt can be used for either the provision of new services</p>
<p>   or reductions in taxation. And that is why eliminating debt is so tremendously</p>
<p>   important. And just as we had to take action at a national level to achieve</p>
<p>   that outcome and just as the Victorians did it and the South Australians</p>
<p>   have done it and others have done it so it is necessary also for Tasmania</p>
<p>   to do it. I don't say that in any hectoring or insensitive or hard-hearted</p>
<p>   sense. It is a statement of reality. And each must make a contribution to</p>
<p>   solving their own difficulty and their own problem. And I think it remains</p>
<p>   extremely important that that be done.</p>
<p>  The last thing that I want to say to you ladies and gentlemen of a policy</p>
<p>   character is to remind you, as we should always as Liberal's remind ourselves</p>
<p>   that we don't exist just to get the economy right. We don't exist just to</p>
<p>   achieve business and material wellbeing for our community, important though</p>
<p>   that is, because it provides jobs which is a basis of family security. But</p>
<p>   we also exist to achieve great social goals and we've achieved many of those</p>
<p>   over the last three and a quarter years. No audience in Australia would</p>
<p>   know better than you do of the traumatic impact of the Port Arthur tragedy</p>
<p>   which occurred in April of 1996. But we were able to achieve then through</p>
<p>   national gun control legislation is one of the great social achievements</p>
<p>   of the last ten or twenty years.</p>
<p>  I know it was unpopular in some areas, but its long term contribution to</p>
<p>   the security of people is immense and we only have to see the almost daily</p>
<p>   demonstration of the terrifying impact of unlimited access to weapons in</p>
<p>   the United States to realise what an important measure that was borne out</p>
<p>   of the most awful and traumatic tragedy.</p>
<p>  So it is equally that we remain very committed to the ongoing fight against</p>
<p>   the drug menace. We may argue in our community about the margin, about this</p>
<p>   or that approach to fighting the drug problem, but most of us agree as to</p>
<p>   95 percent of what needs to be done. We need to educate young people against</p>
<p>   starting on drugs. We need to remind them of the link between so-called</p>
<p>   soft drugs and hard drugs. That the one leads to the other. And this absurd</p>
<p>   notion that marawana can be consumed without any long-term harm is not only</p>
<p>   clinically implausible and ridiculous, but has been constantly disproved</p>
<p>   by individual experience.</p>
<p>  We need to provide more resources for law enforcement. We need to make it</p>
<p>   very clear that there is no mercy, sympathy or compassion in our community</p>
<p>   for people who traffic out of the human misery of others, which is what</p>
<p>   drug dealers do.</p>
<p>  And finally, of course, we must be compassionate and caring and understanding</p>
<p>   for those people who want to break the drug habit. And I've talked to a</p>
<p>   lot of people who are trying to break the drug habit. I've talked to the</p>
<p>   parents who've lost their children through drug overdoses. And there is</p>
<p>   no more I guess arresting, sobering experience for a person in public life</p>
<p>   to do than to sit down at length to people who've gone through that tragedy</p>
<p>   and it's important that we do that, it's important that we understand it.</p>
<p>   It's very important that we also have in this country a support mechanism</p>
<p>   so that if somebody wants to give up the habit then they get help immediately</p>
<p>   and they don't have to wait a month or two before they get that assistance.</p>
<p>  And at a federal level we have responded. We've put an extra $500 million</p>
<p>   into our Tough On Drugs Strategy. And I wish to public debate focussed on</p>
<p>   all the positive things that the government's of Australia are trying to</p>
<p>   do together - labor and Liberal alike - rather than focus on the fact that</p>
<p>   we may disagree about whether you have a safe injecting room which I don't</p>
<p>   support or whether you have heroine trials which I don't support either.</p>
<p>   I think it would be a good idea if we focussed on the things that we are</p>
<p>   achieving together because there's a lot of collective determination on</p>
<p>   the part of all the governments of Australia to try and do something about</p>
<p>   this dreadful scurge in our community. And it's also important that we keep</p>
<p>   a sense of perspective about Is to remind you as we should always as Liberal's</p>
<p>   remind ourselves that we don't exist just to get the economy right. We don't</p>
<p>   exist just to achieve business and material wellbeing for our community,</p>
<p>   important though that is, because it provides jobs which is a basis of family</p>
<p>   security. But we also exist to achieve great social goals and we've achieved</p>
<p>   many of those over the last three and a quarter years. No audience in Australia</p>
<p>   would know better than you do of the traumatic impact of the Port Arthur</p>
<p>   tragedy which occurred in April of 1996. But we were able to achieve then</p>
<p>   through national gun control legislation is one of the great social achievements</p>
<p>   of the last ten or twenty years.</p>
<p>  I know it was unpopular in some areas, but its long term contribution to</p>
<p>   the security of people is immense and we only have to see the almost daily</p>
<p>   demonstration of the terrifying impact of unlimited access to weapons in</p>
<p>   the United States to realise what an important measure that was borne out</p>
<p>   of the most awful and traumatic tragedy.</p>
<p>  So it is equally that we remain very committed to the ongoing fight against</p>
<p>   the drug menace. We may argue in our community about the margin, about this</p>
<p>   or that approach to fighting the drug problem, but most of us agree as to</p>
<p>   95 percent of what needs to be done. We need to educate young people against</p>
<p>   starting on drugs. We need to remind them of the link between so-called</p>
<p>   soft drugs and hard drugs. That the one leads to the other. And this absurd</p>
<p>   notion that marawana can be consumed without any long-term harm is not only</p>
<p>   clinically implausible and ridiculous, but has been constantly disproved</p>
<p>   by individual experience.</p>
<p>  We need to provide more resources for law enforcement. We need to make it</p>
<p>   very clear that there is no mercy, sympathy or compassion in our community</p>
<p>   for people who traffic out of the human misery of others, which is what</p>
<p>   drug dealers do.</p>
<p>  And finally, of course, we must be compassionate and caring and understanding</p>
<p>   for those people who want to break the drug habit. And I've talked to a</p>
<p>   lot of people who are trying to break the drug habit. I've talked to the</p>
<p>   parents who've lost their children through drug overdoses. And there is</p>
<p>   no more I guess arresting, sobering experience for a person in public life</p>
<p>   to do than to sit down at length to people who've gone through that tragedy</p>
<p>   and it's important that we do that, it's important that we understand it.</p>
<p>   It's very important that we also have in this country a support mechanism</p>
<p>   so that if somebody wants to give up the habit then they get help immediately</p>
<p>   and they don't have to wait a month or two before they get that assistance.</p>
<p>  And at a federal level we have responded. We've put an extra $500 million</p>
<p>   into our Tough On Drugs Strategy. And I wish to public debate focussed on</p>
<p>   all the positive things that the government's of Australia are trying to</p>
<p>   do together - labor and Liberal alike - rather than focus on the fact that</p>
<p>   we may disagree about whether you have a safe injecting room which I don't</p>
<p>   support or whether you have heroine trials which I don't support either.</p>
<p>   I think it would be a good idea if we focussed on the things that we are</p>
<p>   achieving together because there's a lot of collective determination on</p>
<p>   the part of all the governments of Australia to try and do something about</p>
<p>   this dreadful scurge in our community. And it's also important that we keep</p>
<p>   a sense of perspective about it and understand that a percentage of the</p>
<p>   population we're dealing with, although it is too large, is nonetheless</p>
<p>   a minute section of the Australian population.</p>
<p>  And finally can I echo what Shane Stone had to say and that is to express</p>
<p>   my immense gratitude to all of you for the loyalty that you've demonstrated</p>
<p>   to me, to Tony Rundle and, I know, that you are demonstrating to Sue. Sue</p>
<p>   faces a big fight but it's a very winnable fight. I know what it's like</p>
<p>   to be in Opposition - I had a lot of practise, too much practise. I have</p>
<p>   no intention of ever going back to repeat the experience. But one thing</p>
<p>   that you have to do, if I may respectfully say, in Opposition, be it Federal</p>
<p>   or State, is that you have to start fairly early in marking out your territory</p>
<p>   in telling the community about those things for which you stand.</p>
<p>  We all know what Oppositions are against. They're against the Government,</p>
<p>   they're agin the Government and they want to change the Government. We all</p>
<p>   know that. But the big challenge for Oppositions is to tell the Australian</p>
<p>   public or the Tasmanian public why it is they ought to change the Government,</p>
<p>   to tell the public why it ought to vote for them, as well as telling them</p>
<p>   why they should vote against the Government. Now, I know that you and your</p>
<p>   colleagues, Sue, are starting to do that and we'll be very willing to provide</p>
<p>   any help and assistance we can.</p>
<p>  The Australian political scene is more volatile now than it used to be.</p>
<p>   I don't take anything for granted. We're travelling fairly well at the present</p>
<p>   time but that doesn't guarantee that we're going to win the next Federal</p>
<p>   election. Nobody should think that for a moment. We'll win the next Federal</p>
<p>   election if we work hard and we continue to deliver outcomes and people</p>
<p>   continue to believe in us. Then we'll win it. We won't win it because people</p>
<p>   think, oh well, the other crowd's hopeless. That doesn't work as much as</p>
<p>   it used to because we're living in a less ideological world and we have</p>
<p>   to work to win and achieve every vote. And so it is with the State Opposition,</p>
<p>   policy building, policy branding, policy differentiation is tremendously</p>
<p>   important so people know what you are for as well as what you are against.</p>
<p>  But it is a good time to be in government because we're a great sort of</p>
<p>   historical watershed, the turn of the century and the beginning of the third</p>
<p>   Christian millennium. It's a remarkable time to be in government. It's a</p>
<p>   great privilege. It's a great opportunity. And I have that privilege and</p>
<p>   that opportunity essentially because of the loyalty and support of people</p>
<p>   in this room and people like you all over Australia who year in and year</p>
<p>   out, without recognition or reward but </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
