<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5304</transcript-id>
    <title>PRESS CONFERENCE - WELLINGTON, NEW ZEALAND</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/03/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005304.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
S c-,[ f77<br />
PRESS OFFICE TPANSCRIPT FRIDAY, 14ARCH 21 1980<br />
PRESS CONFERENCE WELLINGTON, NEW ZEALAND.<br />
Prime Minister Muldoon:<br />
We have circulated a communique which has attached to it an annex,<br />
and I think perhaps we simply now make ourselves available for<br />
question.<br />
Question: Prime Minister, do you anticipate a further meeting between yourself<br />
and Mr Fraser in the next six to 12 months to review progress?<br />
Prime Minister Muldoon:<br />
Well, if you look to 12 months I would say probably, yes. But the<br />
next ministerial meeting will be what would normally have been the<br />
NAFTA meeting which we are now putting further ahead and thinking in<br />
terms of about the middle of July and that would be in Canberra.<br />
Probably the New Zealand ministers would be Mr Talboys and<br />
Mr Adam Schneider.<br />
Question:<br />
When can you expect to be in a position to Tmak e decisions on an industry by<br />
industry basis a specific decision?<br />
Prime Minister Fraser:<br />
It is not possible, I think, to put a timetable on that. A process<br />
of consultation with State governments and with industries will have<br />
to take place and that could take a little longer in Australia than<br />
New Zealand because doesn't have the complication with States.<br />
And in something of this kind, we would clearly want to carry the<br />
States with us. It will be on the agenda for the Premiers' Conference<br />
but I am not suggesting that Premiers will be able to or will have to<br />
make final decisions at that point. How far we can take it will depend<br />
unon the discussions and consultations up to that time between now<br />
and the end of June. Then when our deputy Prime Ministers meet in<br />
July, they will be able to report on the basis of the discussions up to<br />
that point, the basis of reactions of the States up to that point,<br />
lh* i'. ul it might be possible to get a clearer understanding<br />
of a future time scale.<br />
Question: Prime Minister can you sum up in laymen's terms what you think has<br />
been accomplished today?<br />
Prime Minister Fraser:<br />
Yes, Australia and New Zealand have always had a very close<br />
relationship, and there are many obvious reasons for that. Over the<br />
last several years there has been a real attempt through NAFTA to<br />
bring the trading relationship closer together but it appears that<br />
NAFTA is running up against some difficulties, In a sense, easier<br />
progress under NAFTA has been made. would probably be very<br />
difficult for the trading relationship to become as close as Many<br />
would want under the NAFTA arrangement Therefore, officials really </p>
<p>2-<br />
Prime Minister Fraser: ( cant.)<br />
over much of the last two years, since Mr Talboys visited Nareen in<br />
March of two years ago, and other discussions I had had with the<br />
Prime Mini ster in Lusaka, especially since then, there has been a<br />
very great amount of work undertaken by officials, supervised by<br />
ministers, to try and work out an alternative approach. Now, the<br />
Prime Minister and I believe that there is enough merit in that<br />
alternative approach to have the whole matter put in a number of<br />
specific areas to real and specific study. If what we both hope<br />
proves to be successful, it will represent a watershed in<br />
New Zealand/ Australian relationships. We will, in fact, have ended<br />
up by taking decisions which will, bring the economies and financial<br />
arrangements in both countries much closer together than would ever<br />
have been possible under arrangements existing up to this point.<br />
It will give us both the advantage under those circumstances of the<br />
larger domestic market which in a sense will then be enlarged to<br />
17 18 million rather than being more confined to our own markets.<br />
We don't look upon it as an inward looking arrangement. The objective<br />
is an outward looking one because if the New Zealand and Australian<br />
economies can be stronger as a result of arrangemients we make between<br />
ourselves, then we can better play the part that we would want to<br />
whether it is in the Pacific or South East Asia in terms of broader<br />
trading relaitionships.<br />
The world is becoming more competitive. It is important for both of<br />
us to be able to sell more in the markets of the world, not just to<br />
each other, and greater freedom of trade between New Zealand and<br />
Australia should be providing it is accomplished a good first<br />
step in enabling us both to sell better and more effectively on<br />
world markets. And that leads to a stronger New Zealand and a stronger<br />
Australia. But, if the broad principals that, as we see it, which<br />
seem to be acceptable, if this proves to be acceptable to the two<br />
countries as the detailed studies unfold over the next period, then<br />
we will have launched a venture which will be very important indeed<br />
in the future of New Zealand and in the future of Australia.<br />
Question: Prime Minister, there were quite a few ' ifs' in your comments in<br />
your comments. How difficult is it going to be to get this closer<br />
relationship..?<br />
Prime Minister Fraser:<br />
There have to be ' ifs' because it depends upon studies. But what<br />
we have decided to this point is that we think there is enough in it<br />
of real merit to pursue those studies with vigour and with acommitment<br />
to try and make it all work. _ It is not a standof<br />
f sort of approach that we have. ' J7e be1ieve that Thle approach has<br />
merit, we want to make it work, but detailed studies are needed in the<br />
areas that are highlighted in the statement and in the annex, so that<br />
sound and firm decisions can in fact, be made. In the process of<br />
those studies, obviously industries have to be consulted and in our<br />
case, State governments have to be consulted.<br />
Question: Do you see this as a development of a Pacific economic forum? / 3 </p>
<p>-4<br />
Prime Minister Muldoon:<br />
I don't know that we discussed it precisely in those terms. Obviously<br />
what we were doing today we putting a political content to what has<br />
previously been an officials' discussion, and Mr Fraser and I have<br />
to do that. We have to say -and I use the word ' political' in the<br />
broadest sense--we have to say, is this acceptable to our peopletaking<br />
the Australian and New Zealand people all together, and indeed<br />
separately in the two countries. I think the answer to that is that<br />
it can well be. We have had, certainly in New Zealand I think, very<br />
very good acceptance of the principal. We have had acceptance from<br />
the various interest groups, the farming community, the Manufacturers'<br />
Federation, the public at large there has been a lot of public<br />
interest in it and at this stage, I think the appeal is there.<br />
People in this country want to see a closer economic relationship<br />
with Australia.<br />
Now, today we have answered the question, where are the problems?<br />
Are they insurmountable? The answer to that is no-, they are not<br />
insurmountable. Question: Could I ask Mr Fraser and Mr Muldoon the same thing. It seems to me<br />
that none of what is in this communique is likely to lead to anything<br />
you could describe as economic union. Are the two countries now<br />
backing away from that concept?<br />
Prime Minister Fraser:<br />
It is not backing away because I don't know that there has ever been<br />
proposed. It is true that officials have examined a number of options<br />
that might be open to New Zealand and Australia in pursuing a closer<br />
relationship. It seemed to officials, and it seems to us, that the<br />
approach that is embraced in the communique and in the annex represent<br />
the best opportunity of achieving a much much closer trading relationship<br />
and economic relationship than we have ever had, a closer<br />
relationship than could be achieved inder the present approach.<br />
And that, therefore, is a good and constructi ve thing in its own right.<br />
As I said before, it is designed to strengthen both economies and<br />
enable us to take part in a sometimes difficult world more effectively<br />
than would otherwise be the case. So, I don't think it is really<br />
a realistic way of looking at it to say it is backing away from the<br />
concept it is a tremendous step forward from what we have at the<br />
present time. And I hope it can be lcoke&amp; at in that light.<br />
Question: _ 11r Muldoon, are the difficulties more on the Australian side or on<br />
the New Zealand side?<br />
Prime Minister Muldoon:<br />
You're determined to have these difficulties, aren't you, I couldn't<br />
assess that, we made no formal assessment.<br />
Question: Apart from the provisions of information through the normal diplomatic<br />
channels, this is intended to brief the forum countries and the<br />
ASEAN countries specifically on what you have been talking about today. </p>
<p>3-<br />
Prime Minister Fraser:<br />
No, I think that is a different concept. Here we have got something<br />
that is specific, it has got form to it, and that studies will show<br />
whether we can both put it into effect. And that will depend upon<br />
determination by both governments and it will depend upon a belief<br />
that that closer arrangement will be good for both countries, and I<br />
think we have that belief.<br />
I have said in other forums that the idea of a Pacific community<br />
is a good one, and we are arranging a seminar in Australia as a result<br />
of-discussions that we have had with a number of people in Japan, and<br />
others. It is an idea that has to have shape and form given to it,<br />
and nobody at this point knows what they mean by it. So, it is not<br />
related to it and not part of it.<br />
Question: Mr Muldoon, can we have your assessment of the way you have seen the<br />
developments today?<br />
Prime Minister Muldoon:<br />
I think we have made progress. We have certainly answered the question<br />
that we had-in front of us, and that was, is it worth doing more work?<br />
Does the proposal appear to have sufficient merit to detailed work<br />
with a view to bringing it together, and the answer is yes. In the I<br />
course of the day we have highlighted a number of potential stumbling<br />
blocks and difficulties and I don't propose to indicate what they<br />
are because we have got to find a way around them. I think we come<br />
out of our discussions with optimism that this proposal can be brought<br />
together, while recognising that it will not be easy in every respect.<br />
Question: Is there a time scale for the bringing together of that proposal?<br />
Prime Minister Muldoon:<br />
Not really. The time scale at the moment is to see how much we can<br />
do before the next ministerial meeting and carry on after that<br />
there will be more work required after that. Prime Minister Fraser an~ d<br />
I will meet again in New Delhi in September at least, and we might takE<br />
the opportunity of having a word or two on this at that Regional<br />
Commonwealth Heads of Government Meeting. That, I guess, will be<br />
the next time that we will meet, but if we need any more meetings, we<br />
will have them.<br />
Question: Could you at least give us an idea of the areas of difficulties?<br />
Prime Minister Muldoon:<br />
No. Question: You have put some emphasis on the importance of public acceptance<br />
of what you have been talking about. Could I ask you, and also if I<br />
may, Mr Fraser, what you felt today the talks about whether this<br />
would be acceptable to the public? </p>
<p>-7<br />
Prime Minister Muldoon:<br />
It goes further. It goes further but it is not incompatible with<br />
NAFTA. Question: inaudible?<br />
Prime Minister Muldoon:<br />
I don't think so. It may, as I said, NAFTA may have to, or may, in<br />
fact, develop in line with this, but there is no necessity for<br />
NAFTA to be altered simply because of this. None that I am aware of.<br />
Question: The communique mentions the most favourable treatment possible<br />
for each other's citizens, Was passport control discussed today?<br />
Prime Minister Muldoon:<br />
Just in passing. Obviously it has come up as an issue in Australia<br />
within the last week,. and so we made passing reference to it, but<br />
we are both;-I think, committed to what is in the communique.<br />
Prime Minister Fraser:<br />
Perhaps I could explain that for those who might not be aware<br />
of the background. A Royal Commission into drugs did raise the<br />
prospect of travel across the Tasman, and a possible need, indeed<br />
there is a recommendation related to it, to re-establish a much<br />
greater control than has existed for a long while. The Government<br />
hasn't given that detailed examination yet. We would want to try<br />
and find other ways of achieving the objectives of the Royal Commission<br />
if we can. We will be discussing this amongst ourselves in Australia,<br />
and with the appropriate departments in New Zealand. Our objective<br />
will * be to meet the objectives of the problems indicated by the<br />
Royal Commission, but in a way that at the same time, maintains<br />
the free movement of people. Now, how that is precisely done, you<br />
will have to bear with us for a while, but that is the objective.<br />
In other words, we don't want to go back to a system of passport<br />
controls since, for so long, there has been a free movement. But,<br />
we do have to take account of the considerations of the Royal<br />
Commission. Question: You want more control, but not necessarily of passports?<br />
Prime Minister Fraser:<br />
Let's see. The Royal Commission raised a problem. What we would like<br />
to do is overcome that problem without re-establishing passport<br />
controls and inhibiting the movement of people between New Zealand<br />
and Australia. Now, we hope that is possible. If it is not, we are<br />
going to have to talk to New Zealand about it, and we can't take it<br />
any further than that at the moment.<br />
Question: Was there any agreement to set up formally a study group between the S ./ 8 </p>
<p>Prime Minister Muldoon:<br />
We have sent a message this afternoon to our representatives in these<br />
various countries setting out what we have been doing, and they will<br />
communicate with the governments of the various countries that you<br />
refer to. At this stage, it would not be proposed to send a minister,<br />
but we will certainly keep them close to what is developing.<br />
Question:<br />
Mr Fraser, what differences in the two economies do you see as<br />
causing difficulties in moving towards greater economic closeness?<br />
Prime Minister Fraser:-<br />
I don't think it is difficulties in the two economies,<br />
Question: Differences? Prime Minister Fraser:<br />
Well, I was going to say, it is not differences in the economies as<br />
such. But there are, I suppose when you are trying to bring two<br />
separate countries closer together, there are some things that have<br />
developed over a long period of time, through the course of this<br />
century. where they can be competitive interests,. I think it is<br />
important for Australia to understand. areas of sensitivity for<br />
New Zealand, and for New Zealand to understand areas of sensitivity<br />
for us. These sorts of things will again emerge, and if, as I believe<br />
we have we both have a commitment to making the process work because<br />
we believe it will be advantageous to both countries,. then clearly,<br />
if there are difficulties for one, the others, I believe, would want<br />
to be as helpful as possible in relation to it.<br />
So it is a question of two countries that have grown up in part<br />
competitive, just because we have grown up as two countries. There are<br />
inevitably, therefore, some difficulties in achieving a much closer<br />
economic and trading relationship which is, on the reading of thedocument,<br />
really designed to see that trade can flow across the<br />
Tasman free of tari ff and import licencing barriers. That obviously,<br />
in some areas, involves signficant steps. The consequences of it need<br />
to be assessed very thoroughly and very carefully, and we need to make<br />
sure that there is as broad a consensus as possible in both countries,<br />
that the moves are going to be to the advantage of those countries.<br />
Because the Prime Minister indicated that obviously there can be some<br />
difficulties both countries need to understand that the potential<br />
advantages to both infinitely outweigh a potential difficulty.<br />
Question: There seems to be a suggestion from the Australian side that moves<br />
towards closer economic co-operation are attempts to help solve some<br />
of the economic problems. Has either Prime Minister said that..<br />
Prime Minister Fraser:<br />
I don't know who has made that suggestion, It was a suggestion containe<br />
in a question, but the substance of the question. I would reject as<br />
being . part of Australia's motivation or ideas. I believe it is a proces<br />
that wvill aanable bo) th econornies, both countries, to be economically stronger </p>
<p>6<br />
than they would otherwise be, both countries to be more competitive<br />
than they would otherwise be, and therefore would enable both<br />
countries to sell in world markets more effectively than they otherwis<br />
would. I take that as a large part of the purpose because there is<br />
no ultimate future, Zor New Zealand, 1 or ' us+ trali a in just lookingath<br />
New Zealand/ Australian market whether those markets are regarded as<br />
two or whether it is a combined market. Our futures are basically going<br />
to be outRairri *-and depend upon our capacity to sell in the wider world<br />
markets in many, many countries. The more effectively we can do that,<br />
the better we will advance, both New Zealand and Australia.<br />
Question: Mr Fraser, while you are talking about trade, can I ask your reaction<br />
to the settlement of the wool strike in Australia?<br />
Prime Minister Fraser:<br />
I have got nothing to add to what Mr Nixon said. But I really think it<br />
is a bit of an extraneous subject for the moment.<br />
Question: Mr Fraser, do you see any merit in the establishment of some sort of<br />
permanent secretariat as was proposed in the original Canberra pact?<br />
Prime M1inister Fraser:<br />
I don't want to speak about specifics. I don't think that makes sense<br />
at the moment. The relationship between officials of both countries<br />
is very close, and I think the documents we have before us and the<br />
work that has been done in preparation for the meeting today, indicateE<br />
how well they do, in fact, work. NOW, whether there are any structural<br />
changes of an administrative kind that come out of these relationships<br />
as they move forward, let's wait and see, but let's not prejudge it.<br />
Question: Mr Muldoon, how does one now deal with NAFTA2, Do we assume that it<br />
has been phased out? Do we talk about NAFTA talks any more or what<br />
do we talk about?<br />
Prime Minister Muldoon:<br />
No, we don't assume that is has been phased out, NAFTA is still there,<br />
it is still working, it is very valuable, and it will continue.<br />
These discussions came out of the fact that it was becoming more<br />
and more difficult to expand the scope, the range of NAFTA. I have<br />
seen a number of references, more or less in the terms of the question<br />
that this will replace NAFTA. No, this will supplement NAFTA, and<br />
when we talk of economic union, that is wrong too. This is an exercise<br />
in economic co-operation to extend the area of economic co-operation<br />
between Australia and New Zealand. It will supplement NAFTA and<br />
NAFTA will remain. NAFTA will develop, it may even expand as time<br />
goes by, but it certainly won't phase out or be replaced by what<br />
we are talking about.<br />
Question: How can that be if this,.. inaudible...? .7 </p>
<p>8-<br />
Question: ( cont.)<br />
two countries on passport. inaudible?<br />
Prime Minister Fraser:<br />
It is too early for that at the moment. It is our Royal Commission.<br />
It is relating to our affairs, and we have to work that through, and<br />
at that point, we will be ready to talk with New Zealand about it.<br />
Question: was there any discussion about giving each other favourable treatment<br />
in the development and sharing of energy resources? Given high world prices:<br />
Prime Minister Fraser:<br />
We didn't speak at great length about particular energy matters.<br />
The Prime Minister and I had discussed these matters very briefly<br />
when I was passing through some time ago on the developments that<br />
are occurring in both countries. But it hasn't gone beyond that.<br />
Question: Was there anything that you two Prime Ministers found to disagree<br />
with as a result of discussions that have gone on between the two?<br />
Prime Minister Muldoon:<br />
Disagree with the officials recomnmendations, you mean<br />
Question: Yes. Prime Minister Muldoon:<br />
I wouldn't think too much, no. Of course, bear in mind that both<br />
governments have been close to the officials Ls they have done thi~ s<br />
work and perhaps had some influence on what went into the final<br />
proposals, but, no I think no specific disagreement. As I said<br />
earlier, we highlighted the points of difficulty on which work has<br />
to be done but we are not really at the stage of agreement or<br />
disagreement on detail. We are really at the stage of saying is<br />
it worth going ahead, and the answer is yes. We don't disagree<br />
on that. a </p>
<p>9-<br />
Prime Minister Fraser:<br />
If I could just add briefly to the point the Prime Minister made.<br />
Ministers have been involved in it at different stages, right<br />
throughout . so it is not as though officials are suddenly presenting<br />
something to governments... Indeed,, as a result of officials' talks<br />
a few weeks ago, both cabinets have looked at the matter. As a result<br />
of those examinations, officials were asked to meet again earlier<br />
this week, which they have done. I suppose we were trying to make<br />
sure that when we did meet, most of the wrinkles were out of it.<br />
Prime Minis-ter Muldoon:<br />
I think that is right. There is another area that is where the work<br />
will have to be done, and that is, consultations with interested<br />
parties, interest groups. We would get close to the interest groups<br />
in this country, and I think the same occurred in Australia. But now<br />
we are getting down to more specific considerations there, we will have<br />
to work with the various interest groups.<br />
Question: Mr Fraser, has there been any consultation with the State governments?<br />
Prime Minister Fraser:<br />
Not very much, no. There has been some communication with governments<br />
that have shown an interest and said they want to be consulted, and<br />
up to this point, the answer has been that it is too early, because<br />
we had to make up our minds with New Zealand whether or not we were<br />
going to try and set a process in train. Well, from now of course,<br />
we will be very closely in touch with State governments, and seeking<br />
their support for the concept for the objectives.<br />
Question: Mr Fraser, did you and Mr Muldoon discuss the. question of an Olympic<br />
Games boycott?<br />
Prime Ministe'. r Fraser:<br />
We have discussed that on other occasions.<br />
Question: Did you raise that matter at all?<br />
Prime Minister Fraser:<br />
No, not today. </p>
<p>Question: inaudible<br />
Prime M~ inister Fraser:<br />
Some, yes. But there were some confidential ones amongst them, but<br />
you wouldn't be surprised, though, surely.<br />
Question: What about the non-confidential ones?<br />
Prime Minister Fraser:<br />
I think we have spoken about most of the non-confidential ones.<br />
Prime Minister Muldoon:<br />
I think most of those would come into what we have been talking about<br />
here. The peripheral areas of the trans-Tasman relationship, or the<br />
trans-Tasman economic relationship. I think that covers most of itnot<br />
quite all. There were one or two things that, for particular<br />
reasons, can't be disclosed at the moment. But there is no great<br />
secret about it.<br />
Question: . inaudible...<br />
Prime Minister. Muldoon.:<br />
You're still on these stiibling blocks, area't you. The people<br />
who attend my press conference regularly know that I never permit<br />
them to get to answers by a process of elimination.<br />
Question: Mr Fraser, did you make any suggestions to Mr, Muldoon about economic<br />
policies . inaudible...?<br />
Prime Minister Fraser:<br />
No, why would I ever want to do that?<br />
Prime Minister Muldoon:<br />
My word, if he has got any ideas I would welcome them, along with most<br />
heads of government around the world.<br />
Question: There is mention in the communique of sound economic policies between<br />
the countries.<br />
Prime Minister Muldoon:<br />
That is exactly what we have. 9./. 11 </p>
<p>11<br />
Question: Could I ask you, Mr Muldoon the Prime Minister o0f Australia spoke<br />
about a passport control, and that sort of thing. Could I ask you<br />
just briefly, what do you think of the findings of the Williams<br />
Report, that New Zealanders are notable for their involvement in<br />
large scale activities involving illegal importation of drugs to<br />
Australia, and the trafficking of such drugs in Australia? Why<br />
New Zealanders?<br />
Prime Minister Tluldoon:<br />
T~ blyou had better ask him, he wrote it,<br />
Question: Do you think there is anything special about that * Are you worried<br />
about the reputation of your country?<br />
Prime Minister Muldoon:<br />
No, not really, not in that sense. It is true that a very large<br />
drug ring has recently been broken up or broken itself up by killing<br />
each other,-and it was to some considerable extent, New Zealanders<br />
not entirely, thefh-ad a few Australians working for them. But, no,<br />
I don't think you can move from that to a general theory that<br />
New Zealand is a nation of drug peddlers and drug addicts. In fact,<br />
our involvement with hard drugs is rather less than almost any other<br />
country of our type around the world. You asked me about this report<br />
suggest you ask the man who wrote it.<br />
Question: Does you government have any information on.. . inaudible?<br />
Prime Minister-Muldoon:<br />
A certain amount. Most of it has been made public.<br />
Question:<br />
What did it show?<br />
Prime minister Muldoon:<br />
Well, you read the papers, don't you? You read about these people<br />
who have been killing each other Marty Johnson and those fellows<br />
who change their names to disguise themselves and so on, It is<br />
mainly public knowledge.<br />
Question: Dc you have any.... </p>
<p>12<br />
Prime Minister Muldoon:<br />
I would think that the subject is worth pursuing. Has New Zealand<br />
a reputation as a drug centre? You can make up your own mind on that.<br />
If you asked me about cricket I would be prepared to answer you,<br />
because we have quite a reputation in cricket these days.<br />
Question: Have you got any attitude on the need for more travel control?<br />
Prime Minister Muldoon:<br />
Well, we hope we can avoid it. This goes back to the very beginning<br />
of the history of both countries, and it has always been free passage<br />
across the Tasman. But I hope we can avoid it, but obviously if the<br />
Australian government wants to talk to us about it, as a result<br />
of this report, we would be very happy to talk. We have discussed<br />
it in the past, indeed quite recently.<br />
Prime Minister Fraser:<br />
Well, we hope we can avoid it too. What ever problems might<br />
have arisen, as a result of that report, we hope they can be<br />
solved without them. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
