<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>352</transcript-id>
    <title>PM 39/1961 - UNITED KINGDOM AND EUROPEAN ECONOMIC COMMUNITY - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R G MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>31/07/1961</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000352.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO: For use only after receipt of Macmillan's speech<br />
P. M. No 39/ l961<br />
UNITED KINGDOM AND EUROPEAN ECONOMIC COMMUNITY<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, the Rt. Hon. R. G. ienzies<br />
The British Government has now made a momentous decision<br />
to enter into negotiations with the Members of the European<br />
Economic Community with a view to joining the Community if<br />
satisfactory arrangements can be made to meet the special needs<br />
of the United Kingdom, of the Commonwealth, and of the European<br />
Free Trade Association. A second, and more momentous decision<br />
will become necessary when the negotiations conclude and further<br />
consultation takes place, as it no doubt will, with the other<br />
Commonwealth countries.<br />
I had been madc aware, through messages from the British<br />
Prime Minister, of thl decision of the British Government prior<br />
to the announcement in the House of Commons. Mr. Macmillan's<br />
messages to me covered both the terms of his Governniontts<br />
decision and also the considerations which led his Government to<br />
it. The issues for Australia are pressing and real. We will,<br />
I hope, with the assistance of Great Britain be participants<br />
in a series of negotiations which I believe to be the most<br />
important, in time of peace, in my lifetime. They will demand<br />
of us both wisdor and patience and our constant vigilance,<br />
On the commercial side we have taken the view and have<br />
expressed it strongly, that in the negotiations which will now<br />
take place arrangements to protect our export trade and<br />
commercial interests must be secured. To this end further<br />
consultations of a detailed character on trade and commodity<br />
questions will take place between the United Kingdom and<br />
Commionwealth countries, including Australia, before substantive<br />
negotiations with the European Economic Community begin. When<br />
I those substantive negotiations do begin we will persist in the<br />
presentation of our view that nobody can argue the case for our<br />
export industries half so ioell as we can ourselves.<br />
One of the things Great Britain had to decide is whether<br />
in fact her membership of the Co: mron iMarket would strengthen her<br />
own economy. It is tremendously important to us that her economy<br />
should be strengthened, because if it weakens our own British<br />
ma-rket will suffer.<br />
With respect to preferences we have special arrangements<br />
which are of ii. mense value to us and we regard ourselves as the<br />
Australian Government as having a primary duty to protect those<br />
interests. Therefore we have devoted much time to discussing<br />
them and to pointing out that you cannot turn a preferontial<br />
system upside down without exposing our export indust:. ios such as<br />
wheat, butter, dried fruits etc. to very great danger.<br />
JW have also felt that if the United Kingdom were to<br />
join the Cozmunity it would not be without effect on the close<br />
and individual political relations which characterize the<br />
Commonwealth. The European Economic Community, besides being a<br />
commercial arrangement, is also a great political conception,<br />
working towards something resembling a common political organismn<br />
It could be a tremendous thing for the world to have a cohesive<br />
Europe, but if this common European policy develops with United<br />
Kingdom participation one could hardly say that the Co; monwealth<br />
would remain quite the same. I hope that I may be wrong, but so<br />
it seens to me. </p>
<p>2,<br />
Iwill make a statem~ ent to the Parliament as soon as<br />
possible after it assoribles on Aug-ust 13-th. An opportunity will<br />
be given at that time to debate, these important issues in terms<br />
of Commonwoalth relations and in torms of our trade and econormic<br />
interests. CANBERRA, 31st July, 1961. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
