<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3216</transcript-id>
    <title>AUSTRALIA&#039;S NATIONAL ANTHEM</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/04/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003216.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS STATEMENT NO. 229<br />
18 April 1974<br />
AUSTRALIA'S NATIONAL ANTHEM<br />
" Advance Australia Fair" will be played as the Australian<br />
National Anthem at this year's official Anzac Day ceremony in Canberra.<br />
The Prime Minister announced this in Canberra today.<br />
Mr. Whitlam said he had asked the Minister for Defence to<br />
instruct the Armed Services to play " Advance Australia Fair" on all<br />
appropriate occasions. He had also written to other Ministers<br />
asking them to give similar instructions to all departments and<br />
Government bodies for which they were responsible.<br />
These arrangements were being made following the National<br />
Anthem poll conducted by the Australian Bureau of Statistics.<br />
The results of the poll, which he announced in Parliament on 8<br />
April, clearly indicated that a majorityT of Australians wanted<br />
" Advance Australia Fair'as the National Anthem.<br />
Mr. Whitlam said the poll result accurately reflected<br />
the will of the people. Opinion polls had shown for many years<br />
that an increasing majority of Australians as many as 80 per centwanted<br />
a distinctive Australian anthem to replace " God Save The<br />
Queen". He had promised such an anthem during the last election<br />
campaign. The survey by the Bureau of Statistics was the most<br />
thorough and exhaustive ever conducted. The sam--le was 30 times<br />
as large as the average private opinion poll. Mr. Whitlam said<br />
the enormous response to last year's national anthem competition,<br />
for which more than 1,200 entries were received, showed the depth<br />
of public feeling on this issue. Australia now had a distinctive<br />
and familiar anthem with strong traditional associations.<br />
He stressed that the survey related only to the music<br />
of " Advance Australia Fair". i Words for the tune existed but they<br />
were not regarded as part of the official anthem. The Government<br />
had always taken the view that it was the music that mattered.<br />
Mr. WhitJlam. said he hoped that at all Anzac Day<br />
ceremonies, the opportunity would be taken throughout Australia<br />
to play " Advance Australia Fair" in recognition of the people's<br />
wishes. He added that on occasions when the Queen was present,<br />
or when it was especially important to acknowlege our links with the<br />
Queen as Queen of Australia and Head of the Commonwealth, "' God Save<br />
The Queen" would be Played as well as the National 1\ nthem. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
