<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2934</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, HON EG WHITLAM QC MP, IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES ON 24 MAY 1973, IN PRESENTING THE INTERIM REPORT OF THE AUSTRALIAN COUNCIL FOR THE ARTS</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/05/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002934.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, HON. E. G. WHITLAM,<br />
IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES ON ZI<br />
MAY, 1973, IN PRESENTING THE INTERIM REPORT OF THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN COUNCIL FOR THE ARTS<br />
Mr. Speaker, For the information of Honourable Members, I present the<br />
interim report which I have received from the Australian Council<br />
for the Arts. I ask leave of the House to make a brief statement on this<br />
matter. Sir, in my Policy Speech I indicated that a Labor Party<br />
Government would provide substantially increased support for the<br />
arts. This support would relate to a two-fold objective the<br />
pursuit of excellence and the spread of participation in the arts.<br />
We also proposed to extend the range and effectiveness of that<br />
support by setting up a new and independent Council based on a<br />
series of specialist Boards dealing with different art forms.<br />
When my Government took office, action was taken immediately<br />
to give effect to these policies. At the same time it was important<br />
to honour commitments already entered into by the previous Government<br />
so that there would be no interruption to work already in progress<br />
and planned. Furthermore, it was necessary to get responsible<br />
estimates for the increased activities envisaged and to prepare<br />
legislation for the new Council structure. I therefore decided to<br />
appoint the new Council ( and its constituent Boards) to undertake<br />
these tasks. On 26th January a Council of 24 was appointed, including the<br />
Chairmen of the constituent Boards and others capable of providing<br />
special knowledge of the arts and of the needs of the community<br />
in this field. On 16th February, after receiving advice from the<br />
Chairmen based on consultations in their respective fields, </p>
<p>-2-<br />
I appointed the members of Boards dealing with Theatre, Music,<br />
Visual Arts, Crafts, Literature, and Film and Television. The<br />
Aboriginal Arts Board was appointed later.<br />
I asked the Council to see that existing support for<br />
the arts was not disrupted; to prepare for me a charter for the<br />
new organization and an outline of its operations which would serve<br />
as a basis for legislation; and to let me have urgently budgetary<br />
estimates for the coming year.<br />
These initial arrangements were very flexible. Appointments<br />
to the Council and Boards were for terms of no more than one<br />
or two years to allow for change and development ard to ensure that<br />
the membership could quickly be adapted to any changes in the<br />
structure which might arise from the report of the Council.<br />
The Boards have met a number of times. Some, in defining<br />
the scope of their work, have already proposbd to move into new areas,<br />
to plan further ahead, arid to tackle long-standing issues of importance<br />
to Australian artists such as the Public Lending Right<br />
and copyright. Proposals to extend public enjoyment of and participation<br />
in the arts, to raise the status of artists in the<br />
community and to explore means of opening doorways to the arts for<br />
young people have also received prompt attention.<br />
The Council has now put together this preliminary report<br />
outlining how, in its view, it and the Boards might operate. The<br />
report is based upon the broad objectives of Government policy and<br />
defines the purposes of the Council and its powers and responsibilities<br />
as a statutory corporation. In accordance with the<br />
Government's policies, it provides that the powers of the Council </p>
<p>should be used in ways which will " respect, uphold and promote<br />
the rights of artists to untrammelled freedom in the practice of<br />
their arts". In defining the structure of the Council and Boards<br />
and their inter-related procedures, the report aims to ensure<br />
that artists and others active in the arts are predominant in the<br />
proposed membership, while ensuring adequate consideration of the<br />
interests of the public generally.<br />
The report is not final. The Council has asked me to<br />
authorise its release along with notes on some of the main areas<br />
of differing opinion to organizations and persons interested.<br />
I have told the Council that I am happy to invite organizations<br />
and persons with a special interest in the arts freely to express<br />
their views on the proposals.<br />
Mr Speaker, I welcome the opportunity which this preliminary<br />
report presents to reaffirm the importance which my<br />
Government attaches to the arts. The legislation which will follow<br />
the Council's final report will be designed n'ot merely to improve<br />
the material conditions of those engaged in them and to widen the<br />
range of those who participate but to guarantee to the arts the<br />
independence without which they cannot flourish. Around the world<br />
there are great writers whose works never see the light of day in<br />
their own countries, painters obliged to bend their talents to<br />
political dictation, creative talent. crippled by censorship and<br />
control. The legislation will, we hope, be seen as a charter to<br />
safeguard the integrity of our artists and their works. </p>
<p>-4-<br />
I hope, therefore, that honourable members, as individuals<br />
and as members of appropriate committees of this Parliament, will<br />
study this interim report that we mayhave the benefit of their<br />
wisdom as well as that of all those Australians who value the<br />
arts and see in them, as does my Government, a means to the<br />
enrichment of life for all Australians. Nlt, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
