<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>19208</transcript-id>
    <title>China and Australia Announce Direct Currency Trading</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/04/2013</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Beijing, People's Republic of China</p>
<p>Together with the People's Bank of China, we announce today an agreement to launch direct trading between the Australian Dollar (AUD) and the Chinese Renminbi (CNY).</p>
<p>Direct trading between the two currencies will commence on the China Foreign Exchange Trade System (CFETS) and the Australian foreign exchange market on 10 April 2013.</p>
<p>This is an important step forward in advancing the burgeoning economic relationship between our two countries.</p>
<p>Australia and China will make further efforts to facilitate the development of direct AUD/CNY trading.</p>
<p>As China continues to move its economy towards greater financial openness, Australia stands ready as a key trading partner to work with China and to bring our financial markets closer together.</p>
<p>The development of direct trading between the AUD/CNY will over time help lower currency conversion costs, facilitate the use of CNY and AUD in bilateral trade and investment, and promote financial cooperation between our two countries.</p>
<p>Australian and Chinese banks have been consulted on the proposal and have expressed a willingness to act as market makers to support the direct trading between the AUD/CNY both in Australia and China.</p>
<p>Developing regional markets to the benefit of Australian businesses is an aspiration of the Australia in the Asian Century White Paper.</p>
<p>We will continue to explore opportunities for further financial sector cooperation between China and Australia.</p>
<p>Australian officials will continue to work closely with the Chinese officials to this end. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
