<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3812</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON EG WHITLAM QC MP, AT THE AUSTRALIAN-AMERICAN ASSOCIATION BALL, SYDNEY, 4 JULY 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/07/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003812.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER,<br />
THE HON. E. G, WHITLAM,<br />
AT THE AUSTRALIAN-AM1ERICAN ASSOCIATION BALLA<br />
SYDNEY, 4I JULY 1975<br />
Two YEARS AGO ON 19 JULY 1973 THE PRESIDENT<br />
OF THE UNITED STATES, IN A MESSAGE TO THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
OF AUSTRALIA, INVITED THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE TO JOIN<br />
IN COMMEMiORATING THE AMERICAN REVOLUTION ON ITS<br />
200TH ANNIVERSARY. THE INVITATION SAID IN PART:<br />
" THE PRESIDENT AND PEOPLE OF THE UNITED STATES HOPE<br />
THAT OUR TWO COUNTRIES CAN USE THE OCCASION TO FOSTER<br />
NOT ONLY PERSONAL CONTACTS BUT THE WIDEST POSSIBLE<br />
RANGE OF FRUITFUL INTERCHANGE AMONG PEOPLE<br />
IN THE REALMS BOTH OF IDEAS AND OF ACTIONS." i / 2 </p>
<p>THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT ACCEPTED THAT<br />
INVITATION WITH THE UTMOST READINESS AND PLEASURE.<br />
SO YOUR FUNCTION THIS EVENING COMES ON THE EVE<br />
OF WIDER AND MORE ELABORATE CELEBRATIONS PLANNED<br />
FOR NEXT* YEAR, THOSE CELEBRATIONS WILL HAVE THE<br />
SUPPORT AND ENCOURAGEMENT OF THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
GOVERNMENT IN A NUMBER OF WAYS AND IN A MOMENTI<br />
SHALL SAY SOMETHING OF WHAT WE PROPOSE TO DO.<br />
THE BIRTH OF THE AMERICAN REPUBLIC WAS ONE OF THOSE<br />
WATERSHEDS IN HUMAN HISTORY THAT WILL BE COMMEMORATED<br />
BY. DEMOCRATS EVERYWHERE EXPECIALLY IN ENGLISH-.<br />
SPEAKING COUNTRIES -FOR AS LONG AS DEMOCRACY SURVIVES.<br />
IN TWO CENTURIES NOTHING HAS DIMINISHED THE POWER<br />
AND SPLENDOUR OF THE WORDS OF THE AMERICAN DECLARATION<br />
OF INDEPENDENCE, WITH ITS NOBLE CONFIRMATION OF HUMAN<br />
DIGNITY, ITS UNFORGETTABLE AFFIRMATION OF THE EQUALITY<br />
OF ALL MEN AND THEIR RIGHTS TO LIFE, LIBERTY<br />
AND THE PURSUIT OF HAPPINESS. THOSE WORDS, SO<br />
FAMILIAR, YET FRESH AND IMPERISHABLE, STILL FIRE THE<br />
HEARTS AND MINDS OF MEN -AND THERE WAS NEVER A TIME,<br />
ISUGGEST, WHEN THEIR MESSAGE WAS MORE RELEVANT, MORE<br />
NEEDEDITHAT IT IS TODAY. </p>
<p>I HAVE A NUMBER OF ANNOUNCEMENTS TO MAKE<br />
THIS EVENING, SO I DO NOT WANT TO EXPATIATE FOR LONG<br />
ON THE SENTIMENTS AND VALUES THAT UNDERLIE THIS<br />
ANNIVERSARY. BEYOND QUESTION, THOSE SENTIMENTS, THOSE<br />
VALUES DEMOCRACY, FREEDOM, THE RULE OF LAW ARE<br />
DEEPLY AND PASSIONATELY HELD BY ALL OF US IN THIS ROOM,<br />
AND BY THE VAST MAJORITY OF AMERICAN AND AUSTRALIAN<br />
PEOPLE. BUT THERE IS A SPECIAL SIGNIFICANCE IN THIS<br />
OCCASION BECAUSE IT WILL BE ONE OF THE LAST TIMES<br />
WHEN WE WILL HAVE THE COMPANY -AT LEAST IN HIS<br />
PRESENT CAPACITY -OF A 63REAT AMERICAN, A GREAT<br />
DIPLOMATIST, A GREAT FRIEND OF AUSTRALIA, AMBASSADOR<br />
MARSHALL GREEN. I PAY A SPECIAL TRIBUTE TO HIM. I<br />
FIRST MET HIM v4 1964 IN WASHINGTON AT A PRIVATE<br />
DINNER; NEXT IN JAKARTA, HE WAS APPOINTED UNITED<br />
STATES AMBASSADOR To AUSTRALIA IN 1973, SHORTLY AFTER:.<br />
THE CHANGE OF GOVERNMENT, AT A TIME, ICONFESS, WHEN<br />
IT WAS EASY FOR OUR TWO NATIONS, OLD FRIENDS AS THEY<br />
HAVE ALWAYS BEEN, TO MISUNDERSTAND EACH OTHER't S PURPOSES.<br />
THERE WERE EVEN SOME WHO LABELLED HIM A HATCHET MANI*<br />
WHATEVER THAT MAY MEAN, SUPPOSE THERE ARE TIMES WHEN<br />
ALL OF US MUST USE THE HATCHET, GEORGE WASHINGTON IS<br />
SAID TO HAVE DONE so, BUT I MUST SAY THAT I FOUND HIM<br />
UNFAILINGLY AMIABLE, COURTEOUS, UNDERSTANDING, SYMPATHETIC.<br />
To AUSTRALIA, AND OF COURSE, AN AMBASSADOR OF THE UTMOST<br />
PROFESSIONAL SKILL AND INTELLIGENCE. WE OWE A VERY GREAT<br />
DEAL TO MARSHALL GREEN. No AMERICAN HAS DONE MORE TO<br />
DEVELOP AND STRENGTHEN THE FRIENDSHIP BETWEEN AUSTRALIA AND<br />
THE UNITED STATES, AND TO PLACE THAT FRIENSHIP ON A NEW BASIS<br />
OF MATURITY AND HEALTHY UNDERSTANDING ON BOTH SIDES# </p>
<p>IT IS NOT SO LONG SINCE THERE WAS A GREAT<br />
DEAL OF SILLY AND MISCHIEVOUS TALK IN THIS COUNTRY<br />
ABOUT A STRAINED RELATIONSHIP BETWEEN AMERICA AND<br />
AUSTRALIA. YOU DON'T HEAR THAT TALK ANY MORE, AND<br />
IT WAS NEVER REALLY TRUE, EXCEPT* IN THE MOST SUPERFICIAL<br />
SENSE. OF COURSE IT WAS POSSIBLE TO PLAY UP<br />
ISOLATED STATEMENTS, BUT THE REALLY ENDURING QUALITIES<br />
IN OUR RELATIONSHIP HAVE ALWAYS EXISTED AND HAVE NEVER<br />
BEEN CHALLENGED.-THAT IS NOT TO SAY THAT OUR<br />
RELATIONSHIP IS THE SAME AS IT ALWAYS WAS, IT IS<br />
NOT;~ BUT THE CHANGES IN TONE, * IN QUALITY, IN EMPHASIS,<br />
HAVE BEEN ALTOGETHER BENEFICIAL AND WERE IN FACT<br />
INEVITABLE. NO ONE HAS ACKNOWLEDGED AND DESCRIBED THIS<br />
NEW RELATIONSHIP ONE OF DEEPER MUTUAL RESPECTJ#<br />
OF MATURITY, OF HEALTHY CANDOUR, OF REAL FRIENDSHIP<br />
BASED ON A FRANK RECOGNITION OF OUR PARTICULAR NATIONAL<br />
INTERESTS WITH GREATER ELOQUENCE THAN MARSHALL GREEN.<br />
No ONE HAS DONE MORE TO BRING-ABOUT THESE CHANGES1<br />
OUR RELATIONSHIP IS VERY MUCH STRONGER AS A RESULT.<br />
IT IS RARE THAT I AM ABLE TO QUOTE THE PRESS IN<br />
SUPPORT OF my GOVERNMENT ESPECIALLY THESE DAYS -BUT<br />
I THINK THE FINANCIAL REVIEW PUT THE SITUATION FAIRLY<br />
IN THESE WORDS ON TUESDAY:<br />
" THE AUSTRALIAN-AMERICAN ALLIANCE HAS<br />
WEATHERED THIS FLUID PERIOD REMARKABLY WELL,<br />
A PERIOD IN WHICH ONE SIDE WAS STRUGGLING TO<br />
ESTABLISH A MORE INDEPENDENT IDENTITY AND THE<br />
OTHER TO MAINTAIN ITS POWER AND PRESTIGE IN A<br />
RAPIDLY CHANGING WORLD. sm </p>
<p>i R GREEN ACKNOWLEDGED THIS AND PLAYED A<br />
VERY EXPERIENCED HAND IN CANBERRA. HE WAS<br />
PROFESSIONAL ENOUGH TO REALISE THAT THE<br />
INTERESTS OF BASICALLY LIKE-MINDED NATIONS<br />
WOULD ULTIMATELY TRANSCEND A CHANGE OF GOVERNMENT,<br />
CLASH OF PERSONALITIES AND MINOR DIFFERENCES<br />
IN POLICY<br />
T ACCEPT THAT JUDGMENT. AMBASSADOR GREEN<br />
IS NOW MOVING TO MORE EXALTED LEVELS, BUT WE SHALL<br />
ALL MISS HIM IN AUSTRALIA. WE SHALL WISH HIM WELL.<br />
HE AND I HAVE HAD THE HONOUR TO BE JOINT<br />
PATRONS OF THE AUSTRALIAN-AMERICAN FESTIVAL TO BE<br />
HELD IN SYDNEY NEXT MARCH AND APRIL AS PART OF THE<br />
BICENTENNIAL CELEBRATIONS. FOLLOWING THE MOTTO OF THE<br />
AMERICAN REVOLUTION BICENTENNIAL ADMINISTRATION<br />
" A PAST TO REMEMBER, A FUTURE TO MOULD" THE<br />
FESTIVAL PROMISES TO BE AN EVENT OF TRULY MEMORABLE<br />
IMPORTANCE, A GREAT DEAL OF PLANNING HAS ALREADY<br />
BEEN DONE, AND MUCH-OF IT WILL BE FAMILIAR TO YOU<br />
SCHOOL PAGEANTS, DRAMA, MUSIC AND BALLET PERFORMANCES,<br />
THE " SISTER CITIES" PROGRAM, I COMMEND ALL THOSE<br />
INVOLVED I* N THESE PLANS, TONIGHT, HOWEVER, I WANT<br />
TO MENTION SOME OF THE SPECIFIC PROPOSALS FOR WHICH THE<br />
AUSTRAL: AN GOVERNMENT IS RESPONSIBLE. o. ,/ 6 </p>
<p>FIRST, I HAVE HAD THE HONOUR TO INVITE VICE-PRESIDENT<br />
NELSON-RoCKEFELLER TO VISIT AUSTRALIA FOR THE FESTIVAL.<br />
HE HAS ACCEPTED. I AM HOPEFUL THAT HIS VISIT WILL TAKE<br />
PLACE IN MARCH. SOME '. OF YOU WILL RECALL THAT WE HAD A<br />
VISIT FROM ANOTHER ROCKEFELLER IN MARCH AND APRIL<br />
THIS YEAR THE PRESIDENT OF THE MUSEUM OF MODERN ART<br />
IN NEW YORK, BLANCHETTE ROCKEFELLER. MRS JOHN D.<br />
ROCKEFELLER 111, SISTER-IN-LAW OF THE VICE-PRESIDENTS<br />
A GREAT LADY, THE* MOST ELEGANT OF PATRICIANS!<br />
WE THOUGHT IT ONLY PROPER, IN INTERNATIONAL WOMEN'S<br />
YEAR, THAT THE FEMALE ROCKEFELLER SHOULD* COME HERE FIRST$<br />
( THE MODERN MASTERS EXHIBITION, INCIDENTALLY, ATTRACTED<br />
382,000 VISITORS. THERE'S NOT DOUBT THAT A ROCKEFELLER<br />
CAN PULL IN THE CROWDS).<br />
MUCH CAREFUL THOUGHT HAS BEEN GIVEN TO THE<br />
ROLE AUSTRALIA SHOULD PLAY IN CELEBRATING THE<br />
BICENTENNIAL IN THE UNITED STATES HERSELF, THE GOVERNMENT<br />
HAS BEEN ASSISTED IN THIS BY AN ADVISORY COMMITTEE OF 24<br />
DISTINGUISHED CITIZENS LED BY PROFESSOR MANNING CLARK, A. C.<br />
I NOTICE THAT SOME OF THEM ARE WITH US TONIGHT. ON THEIR<br />
RECOMMENDATION THE GOVERNMENT HAS DECIDED TO ENDOW A<br />
CHAIR OF AUSTRALIAN STUDIES AT HARVARD. PRELIMINARY<br />
TALKS WITH HARVARD HAVE ESTABLISHED THAT THE CHAIR WILL BE<br />
AT RESEARCH LEVEL AND FORM A CENTRE FOR AUSTRALIAN<br />
STUDIES BY OTHER AMERICAN UNIVERSITIES. THERE ARE A<br />
NUMBER OF DETAILS TO BE WORKED OUT. WE SHALL WANT.'<br />
TO TAKE ACCOUNT OF HARVARD'S WISHES IN THIS REGARD. 9 a./ 7 </p>
<p>IT IS HOPE THAT THE ESTABLISHMENT OF THE<br />
CHAIR BE A FIRST STEP ONLY. WE HOPE IT WILL<br />
FORM TE NUCLEUS OF EXPANDED AND CONTINUING ACADEMIC<br />
STUDIES IN AMERICA OF ALL ASPECTS OF AUSTRALIA AND<br />
OF AUSTRALIAN INTERESTS IN A WIDER REGIONAL CONTEXT,<br />
I COMMEND THIS PROPOSAL TO THE GREAT COMPANIES AND<br />
CORP0RAAT-: NS MANY OF WHOSE REPRESENTATIVES ARE HERE<br />
TONIGHT WHICH OPERATE IN OUR TWO COUNTRIES, SOME<br />
OF THEME I TRUST, WILL SEE IN THE CHAIR A FOCAL<br />
POINT F2R FURTHER RESEARCH ENDOWMENTS IN THEIR OWN<br />
NAMES IN DISCIPLINES OF SPECIAL INTEREST TO THEM.<br />
THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT PLANS TO SPONSOR<br />
A FELLOWSHI? PROGRAM TO FACILITATE EXCHANGE VISITS<br />
BY A NON-ACADEMIC CROSS SECTION OF THE COMMUNITY<br />
FARMERS, BUSINESSMEN, CIVIC LEADERS, TRADE UNIONISTS<br />
BETJEEH AUS-? ALIA AND AMERICA, WE SHALL SUPPORT<br />
AN AMERICAN TOUR BY THE AUSTRALIAN YOUTH ORCHESTRA<br />
AND ART, CRAFTS, AND OTHER EXHIBITIONS. WE SHALL<br />
SET ASIDE FUNDS TO ENABLE AUSTRALIANS TO PARTICIPATE IN<br />
SPECIFIC EENTS ARRANGED BY AMERICAN STATES, CITIES<br />
AND INSTITUTIONS. FOR EXAMPLE, THE SMITHSONIAN<br />
INSTITUTION THE BIGGEST MUSEUM COMPLEX IN THE<br />
UNITED STATES AND IN THE WORLD HAS INVITED AN<br />
AUSTRALIAN EXHIBIT TO TOUR ITS CIRCUIT OF MUSEUMS.<br />
WE SHAL. L ACCEPT THIS INVITATION, DRAWING FROM MANY<br />
AUSTRAL: AN MUSEUMS MATERIAL RELATED TO AUSTRALIANAMERICAN<br />
LINKS FROM OUR EARLIEST TIMES TO THE PRESENT DAY. </p>
<p>THERE IS ONE OTHER PROPOSAL I HAVE TO<br />
ANNCUNCE TONIGHT. AMERICANS HAVE MADE MANY<br />
CONTR-SUTIONS TO AUSTRALIAN LIFE. NONE IS MORE<br />
ENDURING OR STRIKING THAN THAT OF WALTER BURLEY<br />
GRIFFIN. SINCE GRIFFIN'S DESIGN FOR CANBERRA WAS<br />
SELECTED IN 1912, THE NATIONAL CAPITAL HAS BECOME<br />
A MCNU-ENT TO HIS VISION AND ARCHITECTURAL SKILL<br />
A GARBE-CITY. GRIFFIN MADE GREAT CONTRIBUTIONS TO<br />
ARCHITECUJRE, LANDSCAPE AND TOWN PLANNING IN<br />
OTHER PARTS OF AUSTRALIA. NOVEMBER 1976 WILL SEE THE<br />
CENTENARY OF HIS BIRTH. THE GOVERNMENT INTENDS TO<br />
HONOUR HIM WITH THE ERECTION OF A MEMORIAL IN CANBERRA.<br />
g-N<br />
THIS WILL ALSO COINCIDE WITH THE BICENTARY CELEBRATIONS.<br />
A COMPETITION WILL BE HELD THIS YEAR TO CHOOSE A DESIGN<br />
FOR THE MEMORIAL, THE MEMORIAL WILL BE SITED ON<br />
THE SUMMIT CF MOUNT AINSLIE. I UNDERSTAND THAT THE<br />
NATIONAL CAPITAL DEVELOPMENT COMMISSION WILL BE<br />
GIVING FURTHER DETAILS OF THE. COMPETITION IN A<br />
STATEMENT THIS EVENING. / 9 </p>
<p>I THANK PROFESSOR MANNING CLARK AND HIS<br />
COMMIF.= E FOR THE TIME THEY HAVE SPENT AND THE WORK<br />
THEY -A-E DONE IN PREPARING PROGRAMS FOR THE BICENTENARY<br />
FESTIVAL. I THANK AMBASSADOR GREEN; MR ALLEN<br />
MOYES, PRESIDENT OF THE AUSTRALIAN-AMERICAN ASSOCIATION,<br />
AN CF= ICER OF THE ORDER FOR AUSTRALIA FOR<br />
" DISTINGUISHED SERVICE OF A HIGH DEGREE IN THE FIELDS<br />
OF A-E-EMENT AND INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS";<br />
MR CHARLES BERNARD, PRESIDENT OF THE AMERICAN<br />
SOCIETY; AND MR BROOKS WILSON, A VICE-PRESIDENT OF THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN-AMERICAN ASSOCIATION AND CHAIRMAN OF THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN-AMERICAN FESTIVAL 1976. I AM HAPPY THAT<br />
THE AUSTRALIIAN' GOVERNMENT WILL BE CONTRIBUTING IN FULL<br />
MEASURE TO AN OCCASION THAT WILL HONOUR THE NOBLEST<br />
IDEALS IN T-E AMERICAN TRADITION AND DEVELOP FURTHER<br />
THE INDISSCLUBLE FRIENDSHIP BETWEEN THE AMERICAN<br />
AND AUSTRALIAN PEOPLES, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
