<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9749</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP THE FIRST FRENCH NUCLEAR TEST </title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/09/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009749.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME-MINISTER 98/ 95<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
THE FIRST FRENCH NUCLEAR TEST<br />
The Australian Government utterly condemns France's nuclear explosion at<br />
Mururoa. By its actions the French Government expresses its contempt for the countries<br />
and people of the region, and for all those who hope and work for a nuclear free<br />
world. Whatever the French Government had in mind by conducting this test, it has<br />
done nothing to enhance the honour of France, and has severely damaged its<br />
international reputation.<br />
Australia will be protesting in the strongest possible terms to France, and<br />
pressing ahead vigorously with our comprehensive program of action aimed at<br />
convincing the French Government to desist from further tests.<br />
I have asked the Minister for Pacific Island Affairs, Mr Bilney, to convey our<br />
protest directly to the French Government during his visit to Padis later this week<br />
as leader of the Australian Parliamentary Delegation on nuclear tests.<br />
As I have said, our protests will not end with the first test. Until the tests stop, we<br />
will continue to remind the French Government that with every test they conduct,<br />
the good name of France is diminished in this part of the world.<br />
I note reports that President Chirac has suggested the number of tests at<br />
Mururoa may be fewer than originally announced. This apparent response to<br />
international protests will not diminish our opposition to each and every nuclear<br />
test in the Pacific. We do not want fewer tests; we want no tests.<br />
DARWIN 6 SEPTEMBER 1995 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
