<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5565</transcript-id>
    <title>NEWS CONFERENCE, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, POLAND, RUNDLE</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/04/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005565.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS OFFICE TRANSCRIPT TUESDAY, ' 0 APRIL 19' 81<br />
NEWS CONFERENCE, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, POLAND&amp;, RUNDLE<br />
Prime Minister<br />
At a number of times over recent months, there have been<br />
Soviet-military manoeuvres and preparations. But I believe<br />
that many people are more concerned about current activities<br />
because other circumstances have to an extent changed. Quite<br />
plainly the Soviet Union's tactic and approach has been to*<br />
bring-2ressure to bear-. on-. the. Polish Governmnent: r to undertake.<br />
rigid actions within Poland t~ o prevent Solidarity, the free*<br />
trade union, gaining independence and gaining significant<br />
power. That seemed to be the Soviet tactic for over a period<br />
of number. of.-months,, but., over, the7. last. two to three -weeks<br />
circumstances seemed to have changed. The last confrontation<br />
between Solidarity and the Polish Government seem to result in<br />
yet another win -for Solidarity and as a result of that the<br />
proposed nat ional strike was called off. But in addition to<br />
that there was revealed at that time divisions between the.<br />
Communist Party and even some talk of what we almost believe<br />
to be democratic elections with more than one candidate standing<br />
and at the same time secret ballots being held. I believe that:<br />
the Soviet Union might well be judging that the Government<br />
of Poland will never exert the kind of pressure on Solidarity<br />
that the Soviet Union would believe to be desirable and<br />
that therefore alters the circumstances, the nature of the<br />
current problems in Poland and the possibilities of Soviet<br />
action. There is information that we have had available<br />
over the last three or four days which is indeed disturbing<br />
and-which'could be the forerunner of military action. That<br />
is not necessarily so and at the moment we do not have the"<br />
firm and hard evidence which would confirm that that is so.<br />
But, I issued the statement I did yesterday because up to this<br />
point, the Soviet Union has shown a degree of restraint which<br />
they did not show in Afghanistan which they had not shown<br />
in Czechoslovakia in earlier occasions, which they had not<br />
shown in Hungary and no doubt that degree of restraint is<br />
based on their own hard headed calculations of the interests<br />
of the Soviet Union and of the Warsaw Pact generally, but<br />
whOther they will continue to make that judgement yet remains<br />
to be seen. Certainly it is a dangerous and difficult situation<br />
and our total sympathy must be with the Polish people because<br />
in their struggle to establish a degree of freedom within a<br />
monolothic Soviet system, I think they know that their own<br />
futures depend upon their own actions. That has been their<br />
experience historically and because of the<br />
circumstances and the nature of the divisions in Europe which<br />
grew out of the last world war,! think it is so on this occass; Lon.<br />
We will obviously be watching events over the last few days<br />
very closely indeed and if there are matters which can be said<br />
publicly, I will certainly see that the Parliament and the<br />
Australian people are informed. ./ 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
Question Sir, did you have a meeting schuduled with Mr Hayden on this<br />
subject ( inaudible)?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
No. Question What was that meeting about?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Look, that has:* nothing to do with this. Nothing at all.<br />
There has been some highly fanciful reporting on that particular<br />
matte=-Question Did you seek a meeting with 14r. Hayden and did you call it off?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
The circumstances that might have made that meeting desirable.<br />
no longer arise.<br />
Question Sir, is there anything the west could. do if the ISoveit Union<br />
does invade Poland?<br />
Prime M--inister<br />
There haye been very close consultations,<br />
-Australia is involved in those consultations. The NATO countries<br />
are obviously in close consultation as to the kind of action<br />
they might believe should be taken. The question of a military<br />
C response as I believe, is not in contemplation because everyone<br />
knows what that would lead to, and this arises out of the rules,<br />
the ground rules, in a sense that were established after<br />
the last world war when there was a clear division in<br />
Europe, east and west, that division I think in the light<br />
of history was a tragic one and a very wrong one and should not<br />
have been established at the time. But it has been established<br />
and I believe the Soviets would know quite well that any<br />
move by the Sovie * t Union or the Warsaw Pact towards the west<br />
would lead to a third world war and military intervention in<br />
the Warsaw Pact area would likewise lead to that same conflict.<br />
I believe that is not in anyone's contemplation, not in<br />
anyone's plan. But there are many actions that can be taken,<br />
I think the time'to make decisions about those would be<br />
after consultation that would occur if the Soviet Union took<br />
the tragic step to invade. A lot of preparations have gone<br />
on. There would be a heavier round of consultations and<br />
discussions. The Australian Foreign Minister, Tony Street,<br />
would be involved and we have taken steps over the last<br />
three months to make ' sure that we will be part of that<br />
process, that we would not be handed a fait accompli, you </p>
<p>-3<br />
know, participate or whatever without being able to contribute<br />
to the discussions.<br />
Question Have you spoken to anyone in Washington directly on this?<br />
Prime Minister.<br />
No. The information they have and that we have as I understand<br />
it, is broadly the same and, as I understand it the concerns<br />
in the western world are fairly commonly shared and I think.~<br />
they are reflected in the media reporting which is not jus.<br />
based on, somethinT that= I-have-said,, or that President Reagan<br />
has said, it seems to be basbd on information that the media<br />
has been able to collect on their own account.<br />
QuestIon., Prime Minister, at the time of Afghanistan you saw the then<br />
Russian Ambassador to express Australia's deep concern.<br />
Do you plan similar action?<br />
Prime minister-.<br />
Oh, he sought a meeting with me and wanted to travel to Nareen<br />
to do so, to explain and reason away the Soviet invasion of<br />
Afghanistan. Now, the Soviet Ambassador knows the Australian<br />
Government's attitude to these particular matters very<br />
plainly and very strongly. So far as we know, on the latest<br />
advice that I have had, that final decision to move troops<br />
in has not yet been made and I think we must pray that it<br />
never will be made, that the degree of restraint that I have<br />
spoken of on behalf of the Soviet Union will continue to be<br />
exercised because the consequences for Europe, for western<br />
Europe, for the east, indeed forthe Soviet Union itself,<br />
will be to a degree unpredictable. And the Soviet Union,<br />
is of course, is in a very real dilemna. If it is correct,<br />
and I believe the evidence points to it, if is correct that<br />
they have now come to a conclusion that the Polish Government<br />
will not exert the degree of pressure on Solidarity that<br />
is necessary to pull back the freedoms that have been gained<br />
and that of course, is necessary consistency and for the<br />
preservation of the monolithic nature of the Soviet empire.<br />
If they have come to the conclusion that the Polish Government<br />
either will not or cannot achieve that, then the Soviet Union<br />
itself is left with a great dileinna. If they allow that<br />
movement towards freedom in Poland to continue, thd degree<br />
of freedom that might well be inconsistent with the preservation<br />
of the Soviet empire and which many believe would certainly<br />
spread to other members of the eastern block and might even<br />
spread to the Soviet Union itself. Now, are they prepared to<br />
tolerate that, to accept that because if so,. the Polish people<br />
have opened the door to possibilities of peace and co-operation<br />
which even a short while ago we would not have dreamt of.<br />
/ 14 </p>
<p>4<br />
But if the Soviet leaders come to the judgement that that<br />
degree of freedom is inconsistent with the maintainence of<br />
the communist system, and on all history that is the<br />
judgement they would come to, then are they going move to<br />
stamp it out and because I believe circumstances have changed<br />
to an extent, military intervention would have-unpredictable<br />
results in eastern Europe. and maybe-even in th. Soviet Union.<br />
Questibn Prime Minister, given their track record, and given:....<br />
the apparent failure of the west to be able to stop events'<br />
in Afghanistan, tor be!-able to get the Russiana tc withdraw,<br />
is it time now, do you think; for the west and countries<br />
like Australia that they will put teeth in their sanctions,<br />
that they will do something positive if the Russians intervene.<br />
Have we reached that stage?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
I believe that the reaction of western Europe, of the United<br />
States, of countries such as: Australia to an invasion of<br />
Poland would be. very substantial indeed. I believe there<br />
would be teeth in the sanctions that would be imposed, but<br />
the consultative processes that have been set in train<br />
basically involve making decisions after the event. There<br />
is in a sense again a dilemna for the west here, they do not<br />
want to take actions which would tend to push the Soviet Union<br />
in a certain direction.<br />
Question<br />
Will you agree sir, that if we fail to take some concerted<br />
action this time, that the Russians will continue to do what<br />
they like.<br />
Prime Minister<br />
I do not think the Russians have done what they liked in all<br />
places. They certainly have in Afghanistan, and I would<br />
certainly agree with you that if they do move their forces<br />
into Poland, then western Europe, the United States, supported<br />
by countries such as Australia, in a very full way will need<br />
to take action and demonstrate much more vigourously than<br />
was the case in relation to Afghanistan, that this is the<br />
kind of behaviour that cannot and will not be tolerated.<br />
For the reasons that I mentioned, I do not believe'that anyone<br />
has in contemplation a military option so don't read that<br />
kind of option into my remarks.<br />
Question<br />
You would embargo ( inaudible)<br />
Prime Minister<br />
I do not want to be lead into it at this point because is does </p>
<p>14 involve the closest consultation between ourselves, the<br />
Europeans, the United States and the processes for that<br />
consultation have already been organised ' if the Soviet should<br />
act. Question How quickly could that response take place?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
I believe the consultations could take place very quickly<br />
indeed. It would be my hope that that consultation would%-,<br />
lead to concerted and joint decisions very quickly indeed..<br />
Question Personal consultations do you mean?<br />
Prime Minister.<br />
I mentioned the Foreign Minister.<br />
Question Have you received any indication yet* on what role Brezhnev i3s<br />
actually playing in Prague? Have you received any indication<br />
of what line he is putting at that conference?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
No, not to this point. His presence in Prague was unexpected.<br />
Indeed, this was something we only recently not long before<br />
he went to Czechoslovakia and this obviously adds to the<br />
significance of the occasion enormously. He apparently arrived<br />
Prague before other leaders and coupled with the other<br />
activities that we have-noted are in process it adds weight<br />
to the concern that I think everyone is feeling at the moment<br />
about the future of Poland and about the nature of Soviet<br />
intentions. </p>
<p>4t Question How serious is the news about Rundle'a'far as the Government's<br />
policies are concerned?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
I do not think it alters the policies at all. Oil search is<br />
expanding significantly. We still want to find substitutes<br />
if we can. It is very unfortunate that this shadow has been<br />
cast over the future of Rundle. There are other shale oil<br />
deposits and we, I think, do not know at this point whether<br />
the same kind of shadow would be over-hanging them. But-I<br />
cannot add anything to the statement that was made yesterday7<br />
We have been'-kept informe. in. recent, weeks. and months of ihe<br />
concerns of the companies in relation to Rundle. We have known<br />
that the costs of development were rising. We have also known<br />
that some of the shale may not be mineable for certain reasons,<br />
technical reasons. It obviously means. that. if the project<br />
does go ahead, it is not going to supply the quantities of oil<br />
that one would have hoped, but it could still be a significant.<br />
project. As 14 am advised, the statement that was issued yesterday<br />
was a balanced one and for the Government's part we are very glad<br />
that it has been. made because we have known of the concerns ifQr<br />
some time and-have believed that those concerns should be made<br />
public. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
