<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10750</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                  THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                  TELEVISION INTERVIEW WITH RAY MARTIN                A CURRENT AFFAIR, CHANNEL NINE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/02/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...............................................</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, thank you for being with us.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Good to be here, Ray. Great studio.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>A great studio. Good back-drop. Can we do this all the time?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Fantastic, yes. Kerry Packer, eat your heart out.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>Tell me about today. I mean, you're obviously...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It was a very moving experience. I was tremendously impressed with</p>
<p>   the welcome I received. The best thing about being Prime Minister</p>
<p>   really is the opportunity to go to different parts of Australia</p>
<p>   and really enjoy meeting different Australians.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>But you said today, afterwards, you said that you'd never</p>
<p>   seen anything like this.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I hadn't. I'd never experienced anything like that</p>
<p>   before. And I have always respected Aboriginal culture, but until</p>
<p>   today I don't think I had understood the depth of feeling that</p>
<p>   the indigenous people have in relation to their culture. I'd</p>
<p>   understood it in an academic sense, but until you actually experience</p>
<p>   something like that, you don't...</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>Lots of ugly things, lots of harsh things said about the Wik debate</p>
<p>   over the last six months. Today it was all generous and welcome</p>
<p>   and you were told, a unique meeting.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes I was. And I think there was a generosity and a free communication</p>
<p>   on both sides. And one of the things that struck me about today</p>
<p>   was that sense that although there are differences, the things that</p>
<p>   bind us together and things we have in common are much more important.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>Could this be, in a sense, John Howard's Road to Damascus</p>
<p>   on land rights?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No. I think that would be quite wrong to see it in that sense.</p>
<p>   I mean, I think our Wik legislation is a fair compromise and I don't</p>
<p>   want there to be any doubt that we remain of the view that that</p>
<p>   is a fair compromise. I think what today has done is to drive home</p>
<p>   to me the depth of feeling about culture held by the indigenous</p>
<p>   people. And I hope on their part, for them to see me as somebody</p>
<p>   who does want to govern for all Australians and that they are a</p>
<p>   special unique part of the Australian community.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>But as you said and as you saw today, this is where the land rights</p>
<p>   battle began, you couldn't doubt the commitment of these people,</p>
<p>   in terms of their culture, as the old men told you this afternoon</p>
<p>   as you sat with them on the church floor. They kept saying there</p>
<p>   is no culture without the land.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, we're not trying to take their land away. </p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>They think you are.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, we're not. What we're trying to do is to establish</p>
<p>   a fair balance between different sections of the Australian community</p>
<p>   who have a love of the land of this country. And that depth of feeling</p>
<p>   is very strong amongst indigenous people. It's also very strong</p>
<p>   amongst pastoralists. And what we're trying to do is to have</p>
<p>   a system which is fair and balanced. We don't want to take</p>
<p>   anybody's land away.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>They also said to you today, those old men at the end there were</p>
<p>   pleading with you saying: our survival depends on you - your decision</p>
<p>   that you and the Parliament make over the next six months will dictate</p>
<p>   our survival.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I didn't quite see it in those terms, Ray. I didn't see</p>
<p>   them as saying that if you go one way on the Native Title Bill we</p>
<p>   won't survive. I mean, that's not right.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>We need your assistance for our culture to survive...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, that's true and they will have our assistance. I mean,</p>
<p>   a way a culture survives is for it to be given full respect and</p>
<p>   for it to be allowed to flourish. Now, that is quite consistent</p>
<p>   with the approach that we're taking in relation to native title.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>One Aboriginal leader asked me today: is the PM here to head-off</p>
<p>   an election on race or to start one?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, that's a silly comment. I came here at the invitation</p>
<p>   of Gatjil Djekurra, the Chairman of ATSIC, and I don't want,</p>
<p>   nor do I expect, there to be an election on race. If we do have</p>
<p>   a double dissolution as a result of the Senate rejecting the Native</p>
<p>   Title Bill then that election will be dominated, in my opinion,</p>
<p>   by other issues.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>But you've heard bishops say that if we have an election on</p>
<p>   race in this country, there'll be blood on the streets.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, that particular bishop I don't think represents the</p>
<p>   entire Christian church in Australia. And I thought that particular</p>
<p>   statement was provocative, uncalled for and very unhelpful to race</p>
<p>   relations in Australia.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, you were asked again today whether you had asked</p>
<p>   for respect for the two laws - the cultural law, the traditional</p>
<p>   law here and the Australian law. Can you live with those?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I think all Australians want all Australians to be equal</p>
<p>   before the law, but they want the law to be administered in a sensitive</p>
<p>   way. And I think the points of collision are not all that great.</p>
<p>   And I think that commonsense can work that out. But you cannot have</p>
<p>   a nation that has two distinct legal systems. But everybody's</p>
<p>   got to be equal before the one law. But you've really got to</p>
<p>   have a law that is administered in a sensitive way and I think there</p>
<p>   are some ways in which that can be done which can avoid some unfortunate</p>
<p>   collisions.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>Very quickly, you announced today a $4.8 million addition to the</p>
<p>   health budget to try and fix Aboriginal eyes. Will we ever solve</p>
<p>   the problem? Hundreds of millions of dollars have been put into</p>
<p>   Aboriginal health and it is worse than it was 20 years ago.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, that is true, in some areas, but this particular thing, which</p>
<p>   will allow the fast distribution of this new drug, azithromycin,</p>
<p>   which is a revolutionary attack on trachoma, which is the major</p>
<p>   cause of blindness amongst indigenous Australians. And, nothing</p>
<p>   of itself is going to solve the problem in one hit but this particular</p>
<p>   drug is really very effective and is one of those golden bullets,</p>
<p>   as a doctor said to me today, in tackling the problems of Aboriginal</p>
<p>   health.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>Last question, just briefly, obviously you want to win the next</p>
<p>   election which would mean you would be Prime Minister when the 2000</p>
<p>   Games come around, how are you going to handle the focus of the</p>
<p>   world on us when they say, yes love the look of Sydney, nice harbour,</p>
<p>   great games but what about the Aborigines, how about their state</p>
<p>   of decay? How are you going to handle that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I don't think the rest of the world is a pessimistic</p>
<p>   as that. I think the rest of the world will see a Government and</p>
<p>   a people genuinely trying, not always succeeding, a great deal of</p>
<p>   goodwill. They will see the participation of indigenous athletes</p>
<p>   in the Australian team. They will see the contribution, increasingly,</p>
<p>   of indigenous people of all walks of Australian life. They made</p>
<p>   a magnificent contribution to the Constitutional Convention. They</p>
<p>   really made a big impact on that and I don't think the rest</p>
<p>   of the world will quite see us in those negative terms.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>All right, thank you for your time. Safe trip home.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>Thank so much.</p>
<p>[Ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
