<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>40128</transcript-id>
    <title>2015 Prime Minister&#039;s Literary Awards winners</title>
    <prime-minister>Turnbull, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20150915 - 20180824</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/12/2015</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The 2015 Prime Minister’s Literary Awards winners have been announced.</p>
<p>The 2015 winning authors are to be commended for sharing these Australian stories which capture the complexity of contemporary life and insightfully reflect on the past.</p>
<p>From a children’s book set on the shores of Gallipoli, to the collected works of a distinguished Australian poet, these books demonstrate the breadth and creativity of Australia’s literary sector.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister’s Literary Awards celebrate the exceptional talent of Australia’s writers, illustrators and historians who are to be congratulated for their contribution to the richness of Australian cultural life.</p>
<p>There was an outstanding body of work shortlisted this year and thanks go to the judging panels for their work in considering 465 entries this year. The judging panels have brought their expertise and a love of books to the awards, resulting in an excellent collection of shortlisted books from which winners have been selected. </p>
<p>The Australian literary sector is highly regarded around the world, and the government recognises and seeks to support the work of the sector, through the Prime Minister’s Literary Awards.</p>
<p>The 2015 Prime Minister’s Literary Awards winners are:</p>
<p>FICTION</p>

<p>The Golden Age, Joan London (Random House Australia)</p>

<p>POETRY</p>
<p>Poems 1957-2013, Geoffrey Lehmann (UWA Publishing)</p>
<p>
PRIZE FOR AUSTRALIAN HISTORY – JOINT WINNERS</p>
<p>Charles Bean, Ross Coulthart (Harper Collins)</p>

<p>The Spy Catchers – The Official History of ASIO Vol 1, David Horner AM (Allen &amp; Unwin)</p>

<p>NON-FICTION – JOINT WINNERS</p>

<p>John Olsen, Darleen Bungey (Harper Collins)</p>

<p>Wild Bleak Bohemia: Marcus Clarke, Adam Lindsay Gordon and Henry Kendall, Michael Wilding (Australian Scholarly Publishing)</p>

<p>YOUNG ADULT FICTION</p>

<p>The Protected, Claire Zorn (University of Queensland Press)</p>

<p>CHILDREN’S FICTION</p>

<p>One Minute’s Silence, David Metzenthen and illustrated by Michael Camilleri (Allen &amp; Unwin)</p>

<p>The Prime Minister's Literary Awards have been recognising excellence in Australian literature since 2008.</p>
<p>Visit <a href="http://www.arts.gov.au/pmla">www.arts.gov.au/pmla</a> for the details of shortlisted books and more information on the Prime Minister’s Literary Awards.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
