<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7395</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER LUNCHEON IN HONOUR OF THE PRIME MINISTER ALEBUA OF THE SOLOMON ISLANDS CANBERRA - 5 SEPTEMBER 1988</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/09/1988</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007395.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
LUNCHEON IN HONOUR OF THE PRIME MINISTER ALEBUA<br />
OF THE SOLOMON ISLANDS<br />
CANBERRA 5 SEPTEMBER 1988<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Parliamentary colleagues<br />
Distinguished guests<br />
Ladies and gentlemen<br />
Australia and the Solomon islands are this year both<br />
celebrating anniversaries.<br />
1988 marks the two hundredth anniversary of the European<br />
settlement of Australia. It also marks the tenth<br />
anniversary of the independence of the Solomon Islands.,<br />
Such anniversaries are important events, both for marking<br />
progress and for looking to the future to what new<br />
achievements lie before us.<br />
And they offer the opportunity for countries to reaffirm<br />
their friendship towards each other.<br />
In the case of our two countries, we have been fortunate in<br />
being able to do so through the recent visit of Australia's<br />
Minister for Trade Negotiations, Michael Duffy, to Honiara<br />
to attend your independence celebrations.<br />
Today we welcome a very distinguished Party making a return<br />
visit. To you, Prime Minister, to Minister Ros6 and<br />
Premier Hagasuramo, may I extend a very warm Australian<br />
welcome and express my wishes for a happy and constructive<br />
visit. And in Australia's Bicentennial Year we warmly welcome your<br />
generous participation in our celebrations.<br />
As you saw yourself during your National Day at Expo 88 last<br />
week, the Pacific village Display is an outstanding-success.<br />
The Solomon Islands Pavilion and the presence of your<br />
national performers are deservedly amongst the highlights of<br />
the village and the display as a whole is one of the<br />
highlights of Expo itself.<br />
1t804 </p>
<p>2.<br />
The building of a traditional canoe alongside the Solomon<br />
Islands Pavilion excited a great deal of interest. I am<br />
told that its launching last week during your visit was<br />
something of a spectacular. I hope you enjoyed the ride[ I<br />
The relationship between Australia and the Solomon Islands<br />
is one that rests on the friendship between our two peoples.<br />
It is a friendship forged in the Second World War, when<br />
Australians and Solomon Islanders fought side by side in<br />
some of the most bitter and devastatimg battles of the<br />
South-west Pacific Campaign.<br />
it is the close bond that led Australians to share the<br />
tragedy your people suffered as a result of cyclone " Namu"<br />
in 1986, and that saw us involved in the daunting task of<br />
reconstruction and rehabilitation. In this connection, I am<br />
delighted that Slim Dusty, one of Australia's greatest<br />
entertainers, whose perfomances in your country did much to<br />
raise funds after the cyclone, is with us today.<br />
We are indeed close neighbours and by close I refer not<br />
only to our geographical proximity but also to our<br />
historical ties and our contemporary capacity to work<br />
together to achieve important shared goals.<br />
We are involved in political co-operation at the regional<br />
and international level over important issues such as<br />
disarmament, economic development and international trading<br />
arrangements, issues of central regional concern.<br />
I look forward to working with you again at the South<br />
Pacific Forum when it meets later this month in Tonga.<br />
On the bilateral front, the relationship includes important<br />
trade and civil aviation natters, including the operation of<br />
joint air service by Qantas and Solomon Islands' Airlines.<br />
Australia has become increasingly involved in helping the<br />
economic development strategies of your Government.<br />
Australia's program of assistance to the Solomon Islands'<br />
concentrates on infrastructure development, education,<br />
training, and most importantly, on activities in the<br />
productive fisheries and forestry sectors of the economy.<br />
And, Mr Prime minister, I might say that your country has<br />
given Australia, and Canberra, a special gift in the<br />
sporting field. Mal Meninga, our great international<br />
Rugby League player, has Solomon island ancestry.<br />
Australia and the Solomon islands also have a long-standing<br />
defence co-operation program.<br />
I was pleased to hear, Prime Minister, that while you were<br />
in Perth on Saturday, you were able to take ceremonial<br />
possession of the patrol vessel " Lata", which was<br />
constructed in Australia as part of our Pacific Patrol Boat<br />
Program. 180Li </p>
<p>I believe the ' Lata" will be an important element in your<br />
policing and protection of your important fisheries<br />
resources, in co-ordination with the Maritime Surveillance<br />
Centre which is supported by the Defence Co-operation<br />
Program. I an also pleased that the " Lata" will participate in the<br />
Bicentennial Naval Salute in Sydney next month.<br />
Prime minister,<br />
I believe the relationship our two countries have forged is<br />
am important one and one of which we cam be proud. But we<br />
need to keep at the hard work of co-operation for the<br />
benefit of our own peoples and in the interest of the region<br />
as a whole.<br />
The relationship should not be taken for granted and I would<br />
like to assure you that Australia does not do so.<br />
We value the opportunity provided by your visit to Australia<br />
to reaffirm our commitment to the people of the Solomon<br />
Islands, and to underline the value we attach to your<br />
friendship.<br />
18 1) </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
