<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8822</transcript-id>
    <title>JOBS NOT GST</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/02/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008822.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
2 ft<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ. KEATING, MP'<br />
JOBS NOT GST<br />
Today's Accord agreement between the Government and the ACTU is an historic<br />
achievement in industrial relations and wages policy.<br />
For the first time both wage increases and the timing of scheduled superannuation<br />
guarantec increases will be contingent on progress in creating jobs and reducing<br />
unemployment.<br />
The Accord poses a clear distinction between economic policies under the<br />
Government, and those proposed by the Opposition.<br />
The Opposition Goods and Services tax will threaten jobs.<br />
The Government's economic policies will create jobs.<br />
I recognise that the task of creating jobs is not easy.<br />
The world economy is growing much more slowly than expected.<br />
Growth in Australia can be accelerated, but it requires determined efforts by<br />
govenment, by business and employees and their representatives.<br />
For its part the Labor government is committed to practical sensible policies to<br />
improve investment and stimulate growth.<br />
These policies include a substantial cut in the company tax, an investment allowance<br />
of up to 20 per cent, investment in public works and infrastructure, and job training<br />
programs. The role of business is to seize the opportunities offered by a favourable tax<br />
environment to increase investment.<br />
And the trade union movement. is now committed to accepting the postponement of<br />
both wage claims and scheduled increases in employer funded superannuation<br />
payments if employment creation falls short of what we believe is an achievable<br />
minimum. </p>
<p>Today's agreement sets a minimum lcvel of employment of 500,000 additional jobs<br />
over three years, progress towards which will become a requirement for scheduled<br />
wage and superannuation increases.<br />
It also embodies the agreement between the Government and the ACTU that wage<br />
movements in coming years will predominantly be negotiated at the workplace level,<br />
in return for productivity increases, and be incorporated in workplace agreements.<br />
Where it is not possible to reach workplace agreements, and subject to progress<br />
towards the objective of bigher employment and the commitment to wage increases<br />
consistent with maintaining our international competitiveness, employees will be able<br />
to apply to the AIRC for arbitrated safety-net wage increases.<br />
The safety-net is primarily for low paid workers.<br />
in the first instance these arbitrated safety-net inr~ eases will be accessible at the<br />
workplace level.<br />
These increases will be accessible only where there is no prospect of further<br />
conciliation or negotiation resulting in a workplace agreement.<br />
In determining the timing and extent of any arbitrated safety-net adjustment, the<br />
Commission will apply its normal criteria and have regard to the circumstances of the<br />
employer and industry concerned.<br />
There will be no double counting. Arbitrated safety-net increases will not apply to<br />
employees receiving wage increases through workplace bargaining.<br />
Any arbitrated safety-net adjustments shall be consistent with the central objective of<br />
promoting sustainable employment growth.<br />
Such increases will be restricted to a maximum of $ 8 available after 1 July 1993.<br />
Subject to progress towards the employment increase there will be scope for two<br />
further adjustments of between S5 and $ 10 from 1 July 1994 and from 1 July 1995.<br />
In recognition of the prevailing condition of the labour market the Government has<br />
also agreed that unemployed people aged 60 and over and who have been unemployed<br />
for 12 months or more will not have to continue to meet the work test. These people<br />
will have the option of continuing to seek work and receive unemployment benefits or<br />
to transfer to a Provisional Age Pension. If they choose the pension option, they will<br />
also have available to them the other benefits enjoyed by age pensioners. The<br />
Government will review the appropriateness of the program in the ligbt of<br />
developments in the economy.<br />
MELBOURNE 19 February 1993 I. I<br />
6543 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
