<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4833</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/09/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004833.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 24 SEPTEM4BER, 1978<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
The announcement of a significant oil find in the Bass<br />
Strait reminds us our country's great natural wealth.<br />
It reminds us that in a very true sense we are a lucky country,<br />
endowed with rich and abundant mineral resources required<br />
by countries throughout the world.<br />
When the Coalition Government was first elected, one objective<br />
was perfectly clear we had to reverse Labor's policies<br />
that had stifled mineral exploration. We had to restore the<br />
mineral industry to its former role and to set about<br />
re-establishing Australia's credibility as a sound and safe<br />
place for investors. Our policies are succeeding.<br />
We nave to look to the industry itself to energetically<br />
seek out opportunities, seek out customers, marshall the<br />
necessary capital and then carry out development.<br />
In Australia there are now a number of significant resource<br />
investment indertakings involving a total cost of about<br />
$ 2 billion now under construction. Some of the major works<br />
are the Gregory and Norwich Park coal projects, expansion<br />
by the Western Australian iron ore producers and further<br />
development of the Bass Strait petroleum reserves.<br />
New capital expenditure in mining is expected to be in excess<br />
of $ 800 million in 1977/ 78, an increase of 70 percent over<br />
the previous year, indicating the success of our policies.<br />
The North West Shelf Gas Project joint. ventures are carrying<br />
out their preliminary design. work. The Gove Partners have<br />
announced their decision to carry out a feasibility study for<br />
the construction of an aluminiumL smelter. An aluminium smelter<br />
at Gladstone is proposed and new bauxite/ alumina projects are<br />
under consideration for south west Western Australia..<br />
Coal continues to provide evidence of its bright future.<br />
Companies have been announcing substantial progress towards<br />
the negotiation of long term, sales contracts for steaming<br />
coal with buyers in Japan, South Korea and Israel. Contracts<br />
have been announced with Japan, Brazil and South Korea to cover<br />
the initial planned production from the Gregory Project.<br />
It's those kinds of investment decisions that demonstrate a<br />
tangible faith and confidence in Australia's future. ./ 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
The mining industry is a great national enterprise. It<br />
provides and will continue to provide wealth,<br />
expansion and jobs for Australians. It will provide jobs<br />
not only for its own industry, but in many other areas which<br />
supply goods and services to the mining industry. But for<br />
private enterprise to take risks and to take the opportunities<br />
the Government also had to restore the basic soundness of<br />
our economy. We had to make our industries more competitive<br />
on world markets. Simply put, it meant an all-out attack<br />
on inflation.<br />
Without control of inflation and without the Government<br />
being seen to act decisively and successfully in the fight<br />
against inflation there could be no basis whatsoever for<br />
confidence among investors and those looking to Australia.<br />
our inflation rate today is now below that of most of our<br />
major trading partners, and it is still falling. The gross<br />
imbalances in the economy that occurred during the Labor<br />
years are slowly being unravelled and corrected. Confidence is<br />
returning within Australia, for we only have to look at the<br />
national share market, where many tens of thousands of<br />
Australians are demonstrating their faith in the future of<br />
their country through the investment of their hard-earned savings.<br />
Companies and investors around the world are also looking again<br />
at Australia with renewed confidence. It is a fact that<br />
Australia is now being compared with West Germany as one other<br />
country where secure and long term investment can take place<br />
in the knowledge that governments are pursuing the right<br />
economic policies.<br />
The decade of the 1980' s will be an exciting one for Australia.<br />
Our country will reap the rewards of a sound economic base and<br />
begin to realise fully our great potential.<br />
To the forefront of this new era in growth and prosperity will<br />
be Australia's great mining industries. In partnership on<br />
a fair sharing basis between local and overseas investors<br />
we will be able to take advantage of our great natural wealth.<br />
Our minerals will be more competitive on world markets because<br />
we will have an economy that is sound, with low inflation,<br />
low interest rates, and a proper balance in all arms of<br />
economic policy.<br />
As a Prime Minister, I share the confidence that many...<br />
thousands of Australian investors are now showing. I share<br />
the increasing confidence of investors and governments around<br />
the world in the performance of this Government.<br />
We have much to be proud of in Australia. Much to look forward<br />
to. Working together with a common purpose, a sense of<br />
cohesion we can 1. fulfill our country's great promise.<br />
0 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
