<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11286</transcript-id>
    <title>VISIT BY THE VIETNAMESE PRIME MINISTER</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/03/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I am pleased to announce that Prime Minister of Vietnam, Mr Phan Van</p>
<p> Khai, will visit Australia from 31 March to 3 April. It will be his</p>
<p> first visit to Australia as Prime Minister.</p>
<p>Mr Khai's visit is an opportunity to discuss issues of common</p>
<p> interest to our countries. We are both members of APEC. We both have</p>
<p> an interest in the earliest recovery of Asian economies and, for that</p>
<p> reason, in economic reform and improved financial sector management</p>
<p> in our region. Vietnam is now a member of ASEAN and as such contributes</p>
<p> to the security and stability of our region.</p>
<p>Australia's economic ties with Vietnam have steadily strengthened.</p>
<p> Some of Australia's largest and most successful corporations</p>
<p> have significant investments in Vietnam. In 1998 our exports to Vietnam</p>
<p> grew to A$386 million, an increase of more than 60 per cent. Two-way</p>
<p> trade between Australia and Vietnam last year exceeded A$1 billion</p>
<p> for the first time.</p>
<p>People-to-people links between Australia and Vietnam are strong. The</p>
<p> Vietnamese-Australian community numbers about 140,000 people. They</p>
<p> have made an outstanding contribution to our growth as a nation culturally</p>
<p> and economically. There are now 4,000 Vietnamese students in Australia</p>
<p>  more than Vietnam has in any other country.</p>
<p>I look forward to Mr Khai's visit as an opportunity for Australia</p>
<p> and Vietnam to explore new areas for growth and cooperation between</p>
<p> us.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
