<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4393</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS AT CAMPAIGN DINNER AT LAUNCESTON - 10 MAY 1977</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/05/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004393.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIE MINIS" I" ER<br />
FOR~ PRESS 10M~ 97<br />
ADDIR. SS. AT CAN. MPATGil DII1RIVR AT[. X2\ 3JINCE8STON<br />
It is good to be in la-unces-bn zaqain. The Bass electoratc-has<br />
a very special place In the heart of all. Liberals.<br />
Just two years ago B3ass voters gave Australia the lead by<br />
elcetIng IYevin Newman in a magnificent by-election victory-<br />
It was one of my f irst duties whien elected Leader of the<br />
Parliamentay Ljiberal Payrty to lead the campaign. That win gave<br />
us all great heart, a-nd sp-uxrcd our efforts, culminiatimy in the<br />
election victory of December 1975, in which Liber~ als won all.<br />
five Tasitanian seatz in, the Hlouse of Representatives, a. 9d wbhich<br />
charged us with the t-ask of restoring thje economy and defeating<br />
inflation.-<br />
Oux task was clear. To gain control over Governnment spcanding<br />
and inflation. To argue for-wage restraint, and to restore*<br />
confidence and strength to the'private sector so t-hat employment<br />
opportunities would be created.<br />
We said from the out~ et this task would take three years. Bt<br />
already we are seeing~ the beginniings of sustained ' growth, and a<br />
reduction in inflation. The Consumer Price Index.-for the Karch<br />
q-uarter showed a rise of only the lowest for a March quarter<br />
in four years.<br />
The most Teliable evidence available to us indicates an inflation<br />
rate of jugt over 10% for the course of 1976. Still too high,<br />
but markedly lower than the inflation rate for the precedinhg two<br />
years. flut further progress will only be made if our policies<br />
are maintained. We have set about holding Governixment zpending . in<br />
the next budget, and estimates for-the coinn year are currently<br />
being subjected to thie most extens~ ive review.<br />
In successive national wage cases3, the Governmnent: has argued for<br />
wagie restraint. However, it is tak-ing a long time to reduce<br />
unemployment because of high inflation, and the fact that rapid<br />
wage increases have priced many people out of the laboux market.<br />
The extent: to which Australians acc'ept wage restraint wi111 largely<br />
determine the extent. to which further reductions in inflation and<br />
unemployme-nt can be achieved in 1977. lin spite of </p>
<p>2-<br />
in spitLe of the severe restraints which we have had to impose on<br />
Government spending, we have taken a number of steps to alleviate<br />
particular problems faced by Tasmania, and to spur Tasmanials<br />
developmnent. We have introduced a freight equalisation scheme which<br />
enables Tasmanian busines. to compete more favourably on interstate<br />
markets. The estimated cost of the northbound scheme this financial<br />
year is almost $ 16 million.' In addition, as I annotinced in George Tow<br />
last November, there will be a southbo-w-id scheme which will operate<br />
retrospectiv; , ely from I. July 1976. ' The linister for Transport,<br />
Mr. Nixon, will be announcing details of' the southbou-nd scheme<br />
The Government recently gave approval to IPEC to import two ai. rcraft<br />
which will considerably increase capacity for the Bass Strait air<br />
freight service. This deci~ sion h as--4-ee n challenged in the High<br />
Court and we await their judgemnen t.'! The Government also approved<br />
the import o~ f two now replacement aircraft by air express.<br />
In Launceston, vin are proceeding with acquisition of the land for<br />
the Australian Maritime College*, and the interim council has been<br />
working actl. vely to get this fine ' project under way.<br />
We have granted a substantial sum for the Invercsk Urban Redevelopment<br />
Scheme; an exciting initiative involving co-op~ eration between the<br />
Cormonwealth, the state, local government, and a community group.<br />
The Con-ionwealth is also spending more than $ 20 million nn the<br />
Launceston Ge-neral Hospital.<br />
In Hobart, the new Advisory Council for Inter-Governmental Relations<br />
is establishing its Secretariat, and the headquarters for our activity<br />
. in the Antarctica is being relocated there. The Government has<br />
contributed $ 36 million to restore the TaSman Bridge and related<br />
works. We have also contributed to the intern ational ly acclaimed<br />
south west National P~ ark.<br />
We recognise that Tasmanian Industry has experienced particularlydifficult<br />
problems in recent times, and we expect to receive within<br />
the next few weeks an interim report from Sir Bede Callaghan who we<br />
commissioned to inqluire into the problems of Tasmanian industry.<br />
I believe that the initiatives which we have taken after only 18<br />
months in office, amply demonstrate the Government's very real<br />
concern with the special problems and needjs of TaSmantia.<br />
Takingail ' the measures I have referred* to, Tasmania has<br />
benefitted by over $ 87 million in capital works and $ 17,000,000<br />
In recurrent expenditure from -the special provisions made for your<br />
state by this Governmevnt. Itwould </p>
<p>-3<br />
I would now liko to turn to refevendums which Australians will<br />
be voti. nq on in 11. days time. It is important that we talk about<br />
this bccause the success of the referendums will make a major<br />
contribution to the coiistitutioia. development of our country.<br />
It will establish whether as a nation we are willing to make<br />
constitutional chanqes which will-introduce major and considered<br />
reformis to improve our constitution<br />
The four const itutional. refeL-en'd.-ws propose fair, sensible and<br />
just Changes to reform the cons,-itution and I am sure that they<br />
will be successful.<br />
In the past, people h ave tended ' to ' vote no on cr-nstitutional<br />
questions. But these referendumus are different, They do not<br />
seek more power for politicians. They do not seek more power<br />
for Can~ orr~ a. They do riot weak~ e" the states. These referendums<br />
meet all the requirements ' Augstral ians have set for consLitutional<br />
changes. The propoosals have been carefully considered-and there has been<br />
extensive consialtation about them. There was detailed discussior<br />
of the principles of. all four referen~ dums at the Hobart Constitutional<br />
Convention last year. The Corruonwealth, all the stateas,<br />
local government, and all the miajor parties, war e represented<br />
at the Convention. The priflcipieB of the four proposals were<br />
adopted overwhelmingly by the Convcntion.<br />
The changes are supported on a bipartisan basis by all the major<br />
federal parties. Each of the four proposails we are now supportin(<br />
' was passed in the House of Representatives without a single<br />
dissenting voice, and each was passed by an overwhelmIng majority<br />
in the Senate.<br />
Putting the four proposals fo. ward is evidence of our concern to<br />
make necessary constitutional reforms, and of our support for<br />
the constitutional convention which was initiated-and this should<br />
be emphasised by t-he states.<br />
The people have to be allowed to vote on these proposals which arc<br />
generally supported and which are sound, otherwise the<br />
Constitutional Convention would be ai meaningless exercise.<br />
Clearly, the issue of constitutional reform is ' more important<br />
than that.<br />
The four changjes are these. First, thiat elections for the Senate<br />
and House of Representatives should be held simnultaneously. it<br />
is simply common sense that elections always be held at t-he same<br />
time, anid that the only time you have to vote in a federal elcctic<br />
is when you have to choose Auatralia'S Goverrnent. This proposal<br />
will maintain and strengthen the Senate. It also means we will<br />
not have to vote in as many federal elections. Otherwise we<br />
could have as many as fouxr elections in the next four years.<br />
If this proposal is not passed, the future of the Senate could<br />
ultimately be put in jeopardy. It is sometimes said that<br />
simultaneous elections can be achieved by bringing the House<br />
of Representatives election forward to coincide with that of<br />
the Senate. Unfortunately, that Is just not practical. At t-he<br />
last election, the two Houses were elected at the same time<br />
because there was a double dissolution. Despite this,. they are<br />
/ now, </p>
<p>-4<br />
now out of phase once again. This is because under the constitution<br />
Senators terns are back-dated to the previous July 1. The term for<br />
the House of Representatives' on the other hand only begins when<br />
Members are sworn in, us3ually some weeks after thle election. This<br />
means that unless the constitution is changed, the only way to bring<br />
the elections together would be repeatedly to cut short the term of<br />
the House of Representatives. The three year term is however<br />
already relatively short. One of the shortest Parliamentary terms<br />
in the dem~ ocratic world. Further reducing it would damage good<br />
Government. Far from weakening the Senate as some have alleged, the simultaneous<br />
elections proposals will strengthen the Senate and itzs capacity to<br />
protect the states. It waa an accident that in 1975 tdiere were bills<br />
enabling the Gover-nor G3eneral to dissolve both flouses and make them<br />
both face tlie people. Had the Senate not been able to face the people'<br />
themselves, so that their actions might be judged, -a number of<br />
Senators would not have agreed to block supply. This attitude was<br />
soundly based because any House of Parliament that sends another lHouse<br />
to the polls, while not itself being judged by the people, will not<br />
survive. A numiber of Senator5 at the time knew this, and as grave<br />
as the errors of the forzmer" Goverinent wiere, these Senators were only<br />
prepared to use the Senate's major power because the Senate would<br />
Itself face the people of Australia and be judged. I myself would<br />
never have sought the blocking of supply from a Senate that would not<br />
itself have also faced the people of Australia. If the Senate was<br />
not In the position to go to the people, there would have becri no<br />
douledissolution, there would have been no election.<br />
The Senate's powers are great, and anyone who wants them to remain a<br />
living reality will campaigni for this proposal and vote for it.<br />
For Lunless the present situation is clianged, I can foresee two<br />
alternative consequences. The Senate might. refuse to check a bad<br />
Government uibless there happened to exist the circumstances which<br />
would permit a double dissolution. Alternatively, if Senators were<br />
to make the House of Representatives go to an election without facing<br />
the people themselves, than thierc wouLd be a public outcry against the<br />
Senate which could lead to thle Senate's powers being restrict-ed,<br />
oraolsed ite o heeaternatives Would be bad for<br />
democratic government, bad for the stato3, batd for Australia.<br />
That is why it is imrportant that this referendi-mn be pasd. it<br />
will-proserve the protect the Senate's. piowers anid hienice protect<br />
the states.<br />
The second referendum proposal io that, whenever a Senator dics or<br />
resigns, he will 413e repl. aced, for the remainder of his term of office,<br />
by a member of the sa-Lie party. Thi~ s w. ll guarantee that your choice<br />
of parties for the Senate canunot be altered by acci. cient or desiqm.<br />
Proportionai. represantatiorz ' for the Senate is intended to make the<br />
Senate represent all sectors of the clector47ate in precisely tho<br />
correct proportic'ns. Yet: under thie constitution now, a Senate<br />
vacancy , can compie# Cte) y change the party balanco. It is funldamental<br />
to our cdemocracy that only thc! people should determine the balance of<br />
thie parties in the Senate. Once this propos al is accepted, the<br />
peoples choice will be preserved until th. ey have an Opportunity to<br />
make another choice at the next elction. / The third<br />
RIP </p>
<p>The third referandumt proposal i~ s that voters in the IN. C. T. and<br />
Northern Territoi. y should have a vote in all fu~ tture referendums.<br />
This is a fu-ndamental right. all other Austral~ ians have. I know<br />
of no rational or reasonable argument for denyinq ' Verritori. ia)<br />
voters this baqic right. Territorial voters have the same<br />
obligations as othier Austrqlians. They pay taxesi, they are<br />
obliged to observe the L-= tws of thc Commonwealbh. rjhoy Vate for<br />
Meombers of Parliament. The outcomne of referendums affect thlent<br />
as much as they do other Austra). an5. our cdemocracy is the<br />
w'eaker until the votors of the Territ-ories have the bagic r'Leht<br />
to vote in referendums rest-ored to them.<br />
The fourth and final rinferendum proposal i~ s to sot a retirinq age fo~ r<br />
federal justices. High Court justices would retire at 70, andv the<br />
retirement age for other Federal Couxt judJgzs would hc, determined<br />
by Parliamnt. The proposal does not aff-ct the terrms of ju\-CqJSC<br />
already appointed to the Bench. There is thus no question of<br />
acting in breach of the existing~ judges terms of appointnient.<br />
This proposal is only reasonable. Post jobst have retirement age_-<br />
anid for good reason. Judge s are as affected by old agf-as the<br />
rest of us. it is only fair that after the age of 70 responsibility<br />
should be handed over to younger people. This is even m., ore<br />
important now that the now systenn of V'ederal Fa-mily Courvt: have<br />
been set up.<br />
All four reforendum proposals are iair, just and reagonable. Tlhey<br />
meet a-1l the requirements for success. They have been extensi-ve). y<br />
considered. They haVe the support of all major fede-ral parties.<br />
They do not Involve more power for Canbezrra. They will ma'Ke the<br />
Constitution work better. The polls show-, that aill referendums have<br />
sig-nificant support in all states. But on,-of the thinqs which has<br />
surprised me is that there is not a great deal of passion about the<br />
rcfereiidums. It has becomre apparent that one of the reasons for<br />
this is that the araiuLnents in favour of the referendums are so<br />
simple, straightfor.-ard and reasonable, that most people cannot<br />
see how contrary argumenmts can bie put. This view is well founded,<br />
but in it liee a danqer. A danger of complacency.<br />
The referendums are important, to the future of Australia, to the<br />
future of our political. system. Those people who think the<br />
referendum propositions should be passed over ca-anot, afford t1o he<br />
complacent. Althiouch the rightness of the referendum proposals is<br />
not in question, e-xccpt on the most specious grownds, the referendums<br />
will not pass themselves. All people who care about conititutiona.<br />
and political reform in this countr-y have a responsibility to work<br />
for the referendums. If we all do this, then the referndums will<br />
be passed, and we will have a better constitution one which will.<br />
serve Australia's needs more effectively now and in the future.<br />
The people of Tasmani~ a have a critical part to pl. ay in the process<br />
of niakIng the Australian constitution, a better docu-ment, in thle<br />
task of improvinq the Australian political system,<br />
In May 1975 you took the lead. I believe you will. do so agai~ n<br />
on 21 May 1977. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
