<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8975</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP DUBLIN - MONDAY, 20 SEPTEMBER 1993</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/09/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008975.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
SPUcZX Y Mn Pa! W IWRRTT WM8TINI " M NO F J'DAT o, U<br />
" M bAIL<br />
O~ ftZIWIO A&amp; Y 20 S3PT= WRf : L103<br />
Let me say it is a pleasure to be in the great city of<br />
Dublin; a rare feeling, as ever, to be in Ireland from<br />
vbenCe Came my own people, so many of my fellow<br />
Australian&amp; and so much of my country and an honour to<br />
address the Dail.<br />
I wanted to cone to Ireland as Prime Hiniater of<br />
Australia for the good reason of history.<br />
While I aim here, I will be talking to the Prime Minister<br />
and other Mnisters end busineas people about tra*,<br />
particularly in relation to the GATT Round. I will be<br />
puttinq a particular point of view.<br />
We are both now players in the international economy and<br />
inevitably we have overlapping economic inttrsts.<br />
We will be talking about investrnt in Australia.<br />
I will be talking about the European Community an4-rA1BB<br />
the forum for economic o-opratioh in the Asia-Pacitregion.<br />
Noecssarily, I want to talk about related social issues,<br />
particulaVy unemployent vhioh to a problem afflicting<br />
both our cow* ttle-d virtually all the develgpe4<br />
cOuntries of the world.<br />
I Vfnt to bear Irish views an these watters and I want to<br />
put my own.<br />
But I am also here for the less tangible but utterly<br />
inescapable and irresivtible attraction of hictory.<br />
Pow. I have a feeling that the people in this chamb.. r<br />
might inwardly gruan every tima a politician of Irish<br />
ancestry a8mes through here and signals that he or she is<br />
going to give them a history lecture.<br />
it would not surprlse an it you are t" Intking here vO g<br />
again, he is going to tell us about the Irish past, or<br />
n J Il 1 C. </p>
<p>-our li~ terary tradition. we is bound to quote Yeats at us:<br />
or tell Usn about 1700 or give Uas hie views on Our<br />
. uaracter.<br />
I would dearly like to $ pare YOU this.<br />
A. s a vcet-colonial couP~ try OUrselv**, soe of us raawsh,-<br />
the preamptions of visitor.<br />
Vat the f at remains tikat Ireland in poasibly unique in<br />
thie world for the hold it has on the conecioushess of<br />
other countries.<br />
I knewoi my rra~ cemsor, Rob Hawk*, e aul~ reesed this<br />
Parliame~ nt several yas ago he spoke about the fseline<br />
he had whan arrived at Shannon Airport he said he<br />
felt he had come home.<br />
Xnud Sob Hawk&amp; is nowhere nlear as Irish as I am. if Bob<br />
felt at homes, It o~ ust he I never left.<br />
And wihen President Rh4" senn nat year made w. hat has<br />
b-M aCluite famous tour of Australia, I fuii.&amp; n myself<br />
unconecioisy repentingq thin * hams at a luncheon in her<br />
honour in Canerra.<br />
because Austr-alian*. do~ feel unoannily at home with the<br />
Irish.<br />
They do feel a qreat arftinity whiah apparftntly transcends<br />
ahetral connections.<br />
Anad * bt see to " e to * peak of the immesane power and<br />
Laportenca of history and semory and lanoquaqe and<br />
culture.-I awk not talking about 9ona quaint showcase of the past.<br />
i am not talking about museiums, Or curioUa 9iAMPsee Or<br />
Cadad agwarian life, or even Coorgian architecture.<br />
X couild ) Look at caargisun arahiteoture all day, myeelf.<br />
3iat the attraotion of Traland is an elemental things it<br />
tuifile a need in us.<br />
It is 611mogt as if one can Say that It Ireland did not<br />
siijat, eountrioa like Auetralla would have to invent it.<br />
knd perhaps we should.<br />
I politician, or oj~ arnu~ mants of all 6apl* exing and<br />
bureaucrats and business people, all those of us in a<br />
postion to inflmenc, pfii ey, xho5uld kniow what it losans<br />
to J~ o'e hi&amp; toi-y and heritage and language and culture.<br />
Yet thoro 1.4 always a tondllnpy in political thought<br />
tovarda' otthocoxy razher than tribes broad and less<br />
readily definied oena* Ae-<br />
SOOON 60: T I </p>
<p>On the way hors via the United States and Britain I war.<br />
r". ding 2~&amp; I O'?. olainow b. ook jh&amp;_ jxj~ h betlevo jo_ or<br />
nojt. At on* Doint. writingj about Wolf Tonia, he says;<br />
one realm~ that his laughter * 1nd his huAianity WOU14<br />
haVe blown all thee away ( he Deania ort~ xoxy,<br />
sectarianism, pi~ rinteno, aant) would h~ ave defiled<br />
Political 1 1be-ty not merely ln term~ s of rnnuart but<br />
of gaiety and tolerance and a great pity and a free<br />
mind and a free heart and a full lift,<br />
OV-nIatin of ecoirse was talkin~ g about Ireland, wrtich I do<br />
not mean~ to do.<br />
X moanf to talk about my own rnouftry.<br />
many ut the Irish who played loadilng parts in~ Tone's<br />
rabe'klion of 1798 were transported to Australia -among<br />
them premlnont lead-ore or the rebellion like Xiohaol<br />
DvVov, . Tcoeaph Holt, James Meehan anld MKiael Hayes.<br />
T might ^ t4d intar alta that a concentratlan of l7VV<br />
veterns, took u~ p lend to tit* fouth-wast of Sydney in ouch<br />
nunhoro a* to earn the place the name of Irichtown.<br />
Yt In now nim11. od Unketown and It is where I was b~ orn,<br />
qrew up andJ spent most of my life.<br />
Zt is my hometown and tho heart of my volitical<br />
oonstituen~ y and the most obvious * thn-to groups thoec<br />
days axe Lebanese and vletname..<br />
" Lo curious thin5 aboo~ it the 3.798 00oNViott in that! in the<br />
Colony Ot NOWi BOUth W9le8 the . xp0Ctati0o that U1069g<br />
Ftble would rebel was never really met.<br />
The px-ofound opportunities for economic Indae" nne<br />
Which Auatralia prnv( ded for mais and women of ordinary<br />
mea&amp;, combined with the liberal hulmanity of individuals<br />
like Governor Macquario, put paid not just to their<br />
rebelliounnoss, but to the notion that tne Irish wiere<br />
born rebels -that they were .* aaa2 hostile to<br />
society.<br />
Or at least it MAU have put paid to tIC hOttn.<br />
ka the Autraliai historian, Patriek O'Farrell, has said,<br />
then myth of rebellion c. entinued but th) e reality vas<br />
generally rather dirrerent.<br />
In 1416 Nichool Hayes, wrote, " There is room here for<br />
sonis millions if they were allowed to * migrate. what a<br />
happiness It-wniid-b&amp; to, the unfortunate Irish tenantry<br />
woes they here to partielpato in tfluae blesQI1ae9." </p>
<p>It has' been' a those In the Correspondence or Miaraflta<br />
ever since.<br />
ekn. hundred years later a huge Oi~ n was erected in<br />
London's AldvYch near the site of Auatralii mouse. it<br />
said-" d tn Australia. you will have a hearty welaone, 4<br />
97norous return tor your energy and enterprise and a<br />
Climate that is the healthiest in the w'owld."<br />
Astral. ia has always hold out this crest promise that<br />
it c~ ould tftke the PoOr and the 6PPV6eSmd And give them<br />
the liborty, eConOMic independence 0X% 4 the material<br />
comforts denied in their own country mind beyond that,<br />
by " onme OblevainquO, winnow troa their hearts and minas<br />
all the ancient bittornae and unreason.<br />
As if Australia could do what a Wolf 1kone. mieght have<br />
done. if thaer has been a ipantinucium theme to Australian<br />
history one MIfA~ tn" It to iperh. a 9! hl one. it there<br />
is one, standard we have set ourselves, It has been how<br />
vell ws have lived up this promis..<br />
The th~ eme begins with th~ e British and Irish convicts. it<br />
follows the trail of hLigration through to the present<br />
4^ v. Tt tincludes not just the Irish but the Italionm andl<br />
Croeke and the Lebanese and % Yews and Latvians and<br />
Vietnamese and the Chinese an* Cambodians.<br />
h'aople, in fact, from more thlan 150 countries or the<br />
world. It has beon a 4ifficult ambition to live uip to.<br />
consider the appellati~ ons the 0O~ mtr bAs gone by over<br />
theyears. it has been known as tharlb~ tter neuntryft, tha<br />
I~ ndof t~ bettor obahoem, the 0working man's<br />
paradise", thte usoial laboratory of the world",<br />
Ohmetravlina Unlimited", and, alkhimugh it was originally<br />
meant ironically, " the LuoXy CountrWy."<br />
Occupying a land * o vast. with such bountifull resources,<br />
such a splendid climate, suoh tree inetitutiona being<br />
heirs to a land seemingly so blessed, MAY be why<br />
1AUozallano are sometimes rather severely melf-aritie~ al,<br />
In MeOt, depending on which columnists one reads and<br />
therm sems to be no consensus even amonj the several. of<br />
Trish extraction one would think sozetim** that we<br />
live in a diabolically Impoverished and inadequate place.<br />
iseaconatant ofTpolitictal auiumt In Autralia and<br />
cultural arcument tnAt we n~ ave ralked to cdeliver our </p>
<p>unlimited oentiali indeed, that our great good fortUne<br />
in paaossln a vast continent had made 49 complacent.<br />
There iA a view, I tninXc. that thome things5 we have<br />
achieved might have been * ere the product or good jucX<br />
than Eloeid wenagemotnt.<br />
Tt Is not a view I share.<br />
With rare OX~ e~ tions, we have delivered liberty. it<br />
material prospeiotty has ocoasionally been hard to come<br />
by, and there have bs~ n enough inetarleem Of Conflict to<br />
indicate that the resentments were not entirely swept<br />
away, kugtrali&amp; has always boon and remains by any<br />
standarda, both a prosperous country and a tolerant~ une.<br />
1 do not know any way to measure the eXtent to Vhich an<br />
i1migirant culture has been responsible for this? how much<br />
it has both obliged us to practise tolaranee and provide<br />
value then.<br />
It's a famillear quetion for mistrais* s how uuh we<br />
are a produot ot our iretzastanees, and how muoh we are<br />
what we have made ourselves tobo<br />
la truths by the ect of mirtion the country was mades<br />
by that voluntary act, end bY then emigrants' ambitions it<br />
was built.<br />
An a politician 2 know that little of a lasting nature<br />
happev'e by virtu&amp; of some latent inoral or pdlitical<br />
torce. AS a general rule we don~' t got blown where we<br />
want to go we have to take ourselves there.<br />
In politics, an in aueb else, it requirets imagination and<br />
a politiCal will which In uy view is the sme as saying<br />
a will to &amp; mercis Political power. hnd that depanda ani<br />
having not just the Irish rebel's sane of in3u. sties, but<br />
the nIneteanth century Irish emjq rant'. ability to<br />
izaqin. a better life. knO to find it.<br />
Indeed I would like to thinc that I had more ot the<br />
qualities of the emigrant.<br />
better a politician who not only confronts an<br />
unsatisfactory reality, but has the wherewithal the<br />
will and the Skill to change it.<br />
Better one willing~ to go toc sea buat not in a boat<br />
withouat erm.<br />
in Australia in the 19806 We embarked on.: voyage of<br />
-conomic ceform. ife deregulated the Icoaomy and opened<br />
it up to the wnrld. </p>
<p>Zn doing this we did what the emigrant does we<br />
confronted necessity.<br />
Had we not done this, tn* modern world and the<br />
opportunities it otters would have pauced uA by.<br />
it took political will. More than will, it took<br />
persuasion and persistence and the ability to resist the<br />
terptntion to turn back.<br />
souetimes it doen feel as It one hau gone to sea in a<br />
boat without oars. Sometimes there are mutineers.<br />
ComettimeB one thinks it would have been vasier to stay<br />
put in the first place.<br />
Those nnnvict vasel* on which the rebels at 1798 made<br />
their voyage sometimos took nearly twelve xuonths to gut<br />
to Australia.<br />
it nuct have felt like an eternity.<br />
The process of economic reform can feel the sae way<br />
one day flyin along with the sails threatening to rip<br />
apart, the next day beaalmed.<br />
And then, of course, theto are the days when the ship is<br />
Lmaouilately on coutne and travelling at a manageable<br />
rate and you are thinking not of home, nor even of the<br />
journey, but of the destination.<br />
The destinatioA wa and remainm an internationally<br />
esmpetitiva Aconomy: which mena, * Uong other things,<br />
one less deipendtnt upon our mineral and agriCultural<br />
couoditi t and more eapaclo of nauufacturing products<br />
for glonal marketw, particularly the markets of the<br />
XaLa-Paifio region which is to say the fastest growing<br />
markets in the world.<br />
Anid we have gone a long way towards reaohing this goal.<br />
Our 9oonomy has been completely transformed. Extprts<br />
have doubled. Service and manufacturing exporti have<br />
more than tripled and are now equal to rural exports.<br />
Our economy is much ore diverce and the fastest growing<br />
setor ot it by far is elaburately transforied<br />
manlUfactures. A decade ago less than half of our exports went to our<br />
own region. Today two-thirds go to east-haia.<br />
Three-quarter* of all hustralian axporta qo to the<br />
Asia-Paoific region, a region of two 1illion people<br />
producing half the world's output and ngagerd in halt the<br />
world's trade.<br />
These Cigures basically desewibe Australia'w ruture.<br />
CNr I.<br />
.1 </p>
<p>They marX the staqg OA the touarney toward3 an economy or<br />
which it will never be possible to say they got it by<br />
chance. It fell into thour 14p.<br />
Zt will only he possible to say that, like the emigrant,<br />
we recognisei necescity when we saw it an~ d we did what<br />
had to be don.<br />
Of course we were not the o nly country in the world to<br />
reform our economy in the 19$ 06. Much that we did was<br />
donle elsewhere in the world as countri.. reelisad that$<br />
in the modern cra, if they d( A not change they Would rall<br />
behind. There It A* o doubt that we have boon served well by the<br />
* cenomIc -ef crmw we ma~ de.<br />
And we are all the better for having Alan made Anial<br />
A large eleaent of the Improved international<br />
Compatitivenamn we achieved was got by mane of an Accord<br />
between thu Government and the trad6 unions.<br />
The Accord dramatleaily Iaduced induiitrial disoutation,<br />
hold wage&amp; to conpetitive levels, made a muajor<br />
contribution to roducinel Iiflatlin to a rate oymong the<br />
lowiet in the OECD, and sponeored a creative and<br />
~ n-operativa eulture in the workrplace which is radigally<br />
increasing level* of productivity.<br />
rmplamenting the concelpt of the social wage in the 19809<br />
mYIaflt that in the 1909 we have a first class h1ealth<br />
system: a qoe. Ia net an extAnalve and sophisticated an<br />
any in the world; legislation attectinij the rights and<br />
well being of womon a* eduanced an any in the world: and<br />
thr~ vugh poaltive government programsa assiating etnic<br />
groaps and encouraging cultural diversity$ a<br />
multicultural society of Infinitely more richness and<br />
strength -including economic atrength.<br />
In other uwds as tho Australian 0overnment has stepped<br />
out of the market plane&amp; in many reg~ ards, it has atepped<br />
inXJj its sooldl responsibilities.<br />
hs I said, we did not put to sea without oars. Or<br />
lifeboats, and a safety net, or expanlded opportunity<br />
including, AS of this year, an a~ t~ n~ ive system of child<br />
oare and a home care allowance.<br />
It i3 essentially for the same reason Lhat w9 have made<br />
thte biggest effort in n'ir history to at last deliver the<br />
baeis* of social-justice ror indigjenous Auatralians.<br />
I seen the rcason of social unity and social justice oC<br />
axtendMd opportimity which new world countrien like our<br />
own are intended to provide. </p>
<p>? or the great casualty of immidgration waa Ahenriainal<br />
kuatralia. " ae dostru1etion of this * xtraordinarl ancient culture,<br />
and the brutality and Injusticee inn Icted an the firet<br />
Astralians can nover really be sat to rights, any more<br />
thaen the injustice and dispoegasslon which occurred int<br />
this cuntry can be.<br />
SUt we Can heal woun~ ga&amp; nM &amp; ar* now Vonaratione from the<br />
hurt and bitterness of the pnot.<br />
We anu Include Aboriginal Australia In the scial<br />
* qasation as clu'ltOuBrieo rw;~ tidll~ be over so<br />
alloh strongqer, and the self-esteem of all Auetralians s0<br />
much greater.<br />
2% seems to me a oarf act example of the fact that<br />
nocasity des not or itself load to change.<br />
There ham been a moral and 9ovial nactsity to rig~ ht<br />
those wrong* Inflicted on Aborsiinal huftalin for<br />
geaneration* what has I" d to chary. Im will. Will and<br />
the imagination noceacary to conceive at uiniathing<br />
bettiaw. Go this last decade of &amp; ustv. allia's national lite has been<br />
a decade of Quite remarkable chance. The newt docada<br />
shows every &amp; sii of keelping up the pace.<br />
knd, if we have laarne4 a lesson in the onurea of the<br />
Sourney# It is that tn* Dace will be best Ypairtairaed and<br />
he ohanq* wilil ho nor&amp; affective it the viaop2. avo<br />
included.<br />
No politloel principle van so thorauvhly confirmed for ae<br />
in recant yea an thin nos that one suoaads boat by<br />
trusting to the people's best feelings. I baslieve it In<br />
thei aamenwtial w~ apn of the political reformer.<br />
Chtange will never be made by hAIt. ng the negwi4~ ive the<br />
cervatism, or myopia, or prejudice or pedantry which<br />
eXists in any society. Then@ e prone tn " Arvvuenea Could<br />
dictate to a ref orw agenda.<br />
Chang vil2l be made by looping over the; ;. byataihing of<br />
Soimething better. Of sill t~ he lesson* f &amp; h emigrant for<br />
the politician this is the moot Lrndmental.<br />
And I bmalLeve it is the leascn conltain"~ in those wvrd* 2<br />
quoted about Wolf Tone thtat political reform moans t6~<br />
entlare 3L*.<br />
It me&amp;" s oftewriq an alterative to cant and narrow<br />
orthodoxyv and a11thie debilIitating' conatre Into in Which<br />
historiyI a fovr wrapping us, and to which o,% aorvative<br />
edIt-interest alwIayt appeals. </p>
<p>Po'itioal reform Means otterinq tq the people wilat<br />
migratlion oftered to the Irish in the hinetaonth<br />
century, to Zurpanm after WorlS war Il, to CImbodian<br />
and Vietnamese in recent tines I lan quite simply the<br />
prosepect of a better life in a better country.<br />
fkrnodm thIrien latnadke. s Me back in turn to those laboons we learn<br />
That if we are drawn to Ireland by the hiatory and the<br />
language and caulture not to Pay by the beauty oC the<br />
Place then goverrments ignore these things at their<br />
peril. Ana tor that reason there is a link between culture and<br />
between the art&amp; and reform, botwen the life of<br />
the mind and refors.<br />
It is Wny, I think like the extension of social policy<br />
the * Xteneien Of policies encouraging cultural<br />
Coveloiakent are eaaential In timac of dramatie economic<br />
change. They feed the national iemainatlon, encouraqe people to<br />
contemplate alternativan and Cf course they soothe the<br />
savage boast in us,<br />
you see vhat lesson&amp; can be drawn from Ireland. seal,<br />
hard, political lessons.<br />
Not that we Vero thinking of Treland when we drw them.<br />
The porallole only begin to present thiemeslves as we<br />
approach the old snores.<br />
Nor were we zninkinq ot Ireland when we thought of the<br />
repubi. 1M.<br />
Rather we vere thinking that we are a ocuntry separated<br />
from these islands ) iy twelve thousand miles and 2Oo yeaiv<br />
Ot experience.<br />
That we era a people eomprisod of poe than 150<br />
nationlities and Cor som tine now we have been<br />
encouargint all of them to retain their cultural<br />
identity.<br />
That our mople live etraordinarily varied lives on an<br />
* Wtr* 6Pinarily varied continent.<br />
And that the time had come in this lae docade of our<br />
first century a* a nation to put a border r'una tins<br />
tapestry of our national li* t * ime e eftchrined the<br />
Ltumigranto traditions ot couraqe and Cai( h together with<br />
those traditions of democracy, tolerance, fair play and<br />
ireatew opportunity uhiah are the haxA traditions of<br />
Australia. </p>
<p>zt seemed to us that a ropibic might acknowledge and<br />
enshrine the values of a people who have been willing to<br />
imagine something better, vLllinq to conrrant the need to<br />
change* to Make their way on a new frontier and who<br />
have learned that these things are beut done together.<br />
And to those Who went to hold back, who fear change, who<br />
say it is not the right time to do this$ we might say<br />
what if our forebears had said this? What if they had<br />
lacked the imagination and the will? What if they had<br />
stayed put?<br />
Well, I would not be an Australian ard nor would most of<br />
the 17 million others.<br />
And I would not have had the extraordinary opportunities<br />
my country has given ne among then the Immeasurable<br />
privilge of coninq to the land of my ancestors as Prime<br />
Minister of Australia and addressing this national<br />
parliament. Thank you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
