<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7524</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF DOORSTOP, JOHN CURTIN HOUSE, 10 MARCH 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/03/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007524.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF DOORSTOP, JOHN CURTIN HOUSE, 10 MARCH 1989<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: Was there any progress last night Sir, on the<br />
Airport question?<br />
PM: There was progress. We went very late but it's an<br />
extraordinary, complex issue and a lot of figures have to be<br />
examined, tested and I think this is an issue of such<br />
importance that the public will expect us to take our time<br />
in making sure that we get it right and that's what I want<br />
to do. So it'll be up for consideration again next week.<br />
JOURNALIST: How much time do you think it'll take?<br />
PM: well as I said yesterday I hope we'll be able to get it<br />
next week, it may take a little bit longer. I hope we can<br />
get it done next week. And of course we've got another<br />
issue on our plate to consider next week too. The question<br />
of the Wesley Vale Pulp Mill so it's a pretty substantive<br />
week. JOURNALIST: will you be discussing Wesley Vale Pulp Mill<br />
today?<br />
PM: In here? At the Executive? No.<br />
JOURNALIST: Are you concerned about ASIO's latest<br />
assessment of the level of spying in Australia?<br />
PM: Well they're saying that given the expansion of the<br />
region that the number of countries may be increasing their<br />
recruitment amongst the community. All I can say is that I<br />
have total confidence in our relevant security<br />
organisations, total confidence.<br />
JOURNALIST: Does it concern you nevertheless that there<br />
seem to be more spies in migrant groups, in emigre<br />
communities? PM: it is, I guess, more likely in any this is not a<br />
phenomenom of Australia. In any community where you have<br />
migrant groups that's you know a possiblity and this mustn't<br />
be used and I hope it's not implicit in your question of<br />
tarring migrants. It's just a fact of life in any country<br />
that that may be the case. our migrants overwhelmingly<br />
have a commitment to this country and as I say on the other<br />
hand I have total confidence in our relevant organisations.<br />
JOURNALIST: If spying is on the increase do you think we<br />
need to increase ASIO? </p>
<p>-2-<br />
PM: Don't let's get carried away that we would be suddenly<br />
overwhelmed by spies. I mean you really want to get these<br />
things into perspective. The resources of our relevant<br />
organisations are appropriate. If there were any need for<br />
change it would be made.<br />
JOURNALIST: What's your reaction to the Auditor-General's<br />
report which was severely critical of the Department of<br />
Aboriginal Affairs and the Aboriginal Development<br />
Commission? PM: Well let me say two things about that. Obviously I<br />
haven't had the chance to read it in detail but that is in<br />
the process of being examined by the relevant Departments.<br />
I will also certainly read it myself as soon as I get the<br />
time, read it in full. But I must say I'm very interested<br />
to see the media reaction, given all the hype that was going<br />
on before, I mean there seems to be the general conclusion<br />
that there's not much gold in it for those who were seeking<br />
to make great ore body out of this.<br />
JOURNALIST: inaudible<br />
PM: Let me finish, let me finish. The other thing to say<br />
is of course this is one of a number of reports that have<br />
been commissioned by the Government and it's not appropriate<br />
therefore to make a detailed response until we've got all<br />
those reports. Now we'll have those I hope before the<br />
Parliament resumes and it'll be my intention to make a<br />
comprehensive statement about this and all relevant reports<br />
then. It's inappropriate to go any further at this stage<br />
and I don't intend to.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you think it clears Charlie Perkins to any<br />
extent? PM: Well I think it's fair to say in that respect that<br />
Charlie Perkins on that report is cleared but I'm not making<br />
any further comment about it for the reasons I've just said.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
