<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5933</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/10/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005933.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
1 L EMBARGO: 5.00pm<br />
P I E M NSSTATL. lE R<br />
FOR MEDIA SUNDAY, 10 OCTOBER 1982<br />
ELECTORATE T'. LK<br />
Now that the Conmmonwealth Games has finished, I want to thank<br />
a great many people for what they havc done for Australia in<br />
making the last 10 days so wonderfully. successful. The Games<br />
brought out the best qualities in Au.:. ralians aind those<br />
qualities came through clearly in th-efforts uand achiev we-: nts<br />
of the thousands of competitors and organisers.. Thcy \ wor: ked<br />
together many of them literally for years to bring off<br />
a magnificent sporting occasion. . And in doing so, : they brought<br />
together the entire Australian nation.<br />
The opening ceremony will stay in the ninds of Australians<br />
for a very long time. There was a friendly and light-hearted<br />
atmosphere as the thousands of school children poured on to the<br />
QEII sports ground tocreate that memorable display of the Plag<br />
and the map of Australia which filled every Australian who saw<br />
it with a feeling of pride in our country . that is difficult to<br />
put into words. The children and the arrangers of the display<br />
deserve great credit. So, too, do the dancers from the<br />
cross-section of national backgrounds who performed at the<br />
opening and who brought home to us the truly multi-cultural<br />
nature of Australian society today.<br />
So many people contributed to the. success of the Games. The<br />
organisers and officials not only in Brisbane but throughout<br />
Australia and the whole Commonwealth. The volunteers who gave<br />
their time and effort willingly for their country, there<br />
were thousands of them. The members of the Australian armed<br />
forces, the ABC, for their exceptional TV coverage in Australia<br />
and around the world. The people of Brisbane for being such good<br />
hosts in the dynamic and colourful city of which they can be<br />
very proud. And, of course, the competitors, our outstanding<br />
Australian team and their dedicated, long suffering coaches,<br />
families and other supporters.<br />
I look back to 1976 when I visited the Australian team at the<br />
Olympic Games in Montreal where we had not won a single gold<br />
medal. The team were depressed; Australiansin general were<br />
disappointed. Intensive training and coaching and a scientific<br />
approach to sport in other countries meant that our athletes<br />
were being left behind. The Government had to decide whether<br />
we would let the world pass us by or whether we would give our<br />
athletes the full-blooded support they needed to win world<br />
victories. </p>
<p>\ ve established the Australian Institute of Snort, it has cost<br />
$ 34 rmillion to build and equip so far, and it has contributed<br />
significantly to Australia's 107 medals this year. Champions<br />
like triple gold medal winner Lisa Curry and marathon winner<br />
Robertde Castella came from the Institute. The Government<br />
gave the Commonwealth Games Association $ 455,000 to help<br />
prepare athletes and to provide them with the international.<br />
competition thatis a vital part of their preparation.<br />
Another $ 200,000 went towards the staging of the S. G. I. O.<br />
Games in Brisbane last year as a warm-up for the Commonwealth<br />
Games itself.<br />
Now there are new targets in our sights. In 1984, the first<br />
Biennial Australia Games is planned for Sydnc! y. Then, later<br />
that year, comes the Los Angeles Olympics. The Government<br />
is providing million to the Australian Olympiic<br />
Federation for the preparation of our athletes.<br />
At the same time this is on top of the continued furicling of<br />
dozens of national sporting organisatiions through the Sports<br />
Development Program and, of course, the Australian Institute<br />
of Sport will grow and develop. Australia's athletes deserve<br />
the support of this nation. In the last 10 day2 they provided<br />
the hard evidence of a dramatic revival of Australia's sporting<br />
ability. They also set a wjonderful exampAle, displaying good<br />
sportsmanship whhther Lhey won or lo! t, and I believe, : epresenting<br />
the true co-operative spirit of the Commonwealth. Our representatives<br />
took the nation with them in the intense national pride and<br />
purpose they exhibited. For that we thank them greatly.<br />
-2-</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
