<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18541</transcript-id>
    <title>Joint Declaration of Centenary of Commemorations of the Canakkale/  Gallipoli Land Battles of 1915 and Associated Cultural Exchanges Between the Government of the Republic of Turkey and the Government of Australia</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/04/2012</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
The governments of the Republic of Turkey and of Australia reaffirmed the strong and friendly bonds that have been generated between their two nations out of the shared tragedy of the First World War. </p>
<p>They reconfirmed the land battles of Çanakkale/Gallipoli during the First World War as a unique example of understanding and respect being forged among their warring soldiers that later contributed considerably to the healing of wounds between the Turkish and Australian nations.</p>
<p>They acknowledged these historical ties are reinforced by continuing community and political links and growing trade between their nations, providing the foundation for a strong and productive bilateral relationship.</p>
<p>In this, the 97th anniversary year of the Çanakkale/Gallipoli land battles, they welcomed the upcoming commemorations for the centenary of these events in 2015 as a significant opportunity to reflect on shared histories and to look to the future of the relationship.</p>
<p>They reiterated their desire to give a new impetus to the existing relationship in view of the centenary commemorations of 2015. </p>
<p>They aimed to expand further the political, economic, and cultural ties between their nations, as well as to encourage increased contacts between their peoples. </p>
<p>Referring to the Action Plan for Cooperation signed by their respective Ministries of Foreign Affairs on 1 February 2011, and determined to exert every effort, in good will, to make the centennial commemorations a success, they decided that:</p>
<p>1. 2015 will be proclaimed as the “Year of Turkey in Australia” and the “Year of Australia in Turkey” and celebrated as Cultural Years, during which a series of activities will be carried out to enhance historical, social and cultural understanding and consciousness between the two nations, with the relevant ministries to coordinate their efforts to this end.</p>
<p>2. Cooperation to identify, develop, approve and carry out schemes to mark the centenary commemoration of the Çanakkale/Gallipoli land battles of 1915 will be encouraged. Proposals submitted by Australian individuals or entities for consideration for the centenary commemorations to be carried out in Turkey will be discussed, assessed and determined primarily by the competent authorities of Australia, and selected eligible proposals will be discussed with the relevant Turkish authorities through diplomatic channels. The same procedure will apply for Turkey's proposed activities to be carried out in Australia.</p>
<p>3. Following the exchange of information on proposed activities, the relevant Turkish and Australian authorities will select and approve the eligible proposals for implementation in their own countries.</p>
<p>4. A joint coordination body may be established, to include the relevant ministries and cultural agencies.</p>
<p>5. Promotional activities as well as protocol and security arrangements on site, including programmes for public and media activities with a view to a successful completion of the centenary commemorations and the activities for the cultural years in 2015 referred above, will be the responsibility of the respective governments.</p>
<p>6. Unless decided otherwise on a case-by-case basis, each government will secure the funding for the activities organised by themselves for the centenary commemorations of 2015 in Turkey or in Australia, as well as the funding for their respective cultural years to be organised in the same year.  </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
