<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4644</transcript-id>
    <title>LOAN COUNCIL BORROWING ARRANGEMENTS, 10 MARCH 1978</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/03/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004644.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
! AUSTRALIA<br />
FOR PRESS 10 March 1978<br />
LOAN COUNCIL BORROWING ARRANGEMENTS<br />
The Prime Minister today announced that he had written to<br />
State Premiers signifying that the Commonwealth would be<br />
prepared to agree to adoption by the Australian Loan Council of<br />
proposed new guidelines for the Council's consideration of<br />
proposals for special additions to the semi-government<br />
borrowing programs approved by it, and for overseas borrowings<br />
by statutory authorities.<br />
It was agreed at the Premiers' Conference on 21 October 1977<br />
that Commonwealth and State officials should prepare a report<br />
on appropriate guidelines for the Loan Council in these areas.<br />
At that Conference, the Prime Minister had made it clear that<br />
the Commonwealth would be prepared to see a more flexible<br />
approach as regards requirements for the financing of necessary<br />
infrastructure investment in the States. The report from<br />
officers had been received and had been under examination by<br />
Governments. The proposed new arrangements, while recognising the Commonwealth's<br />
overriding responsibility in matters of national<br />
economic management, would allow special additions to Loan<br />
council programs where the proposed extra borrowings were necessary<br />
to finance development-related infrastructure normally provided<br />
by the public sector and which could not be accommodated within<br />
the existing Loan Council program. The new arrangements would<br />
also permit appropriate access to overseas financial markets<br />
by local and semi-government authorities and by marketing<br />
authorities wishing to fund stocks held abroad. / 2 ( Over) </p>
<p>2.<br />
The Prime Minister noted that further processes within the Loan<br />
Council would be required before the proposed new guidelines<br />
could be brought into effect.<br />
Mr Fraser noted that the proposed changes recognise that adequate<br />
infrastructure investment is essential to ensure that development<br />
proceeds in Australia and that much of this infrastructure has<br />
to be provided by government authorities. By agreeing to new<br />
arrangements, the Commonwealth is giving further evidence of<br />
its commitment to facilitate projects of significance to the<br />
economic development of Australia. To this end, it was clear<br />
that domestic sources of finance should be augmented as necessary<br />
by recourse to overseas markets. Mr Fraser said that this action<br />
by his Government was a further tangible demonstration of its<br />
desire to co-operate with the States in developing new Federalism.<br />
8 P </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
