<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6723</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH TREVOR WATSON (ABC), PORT MORESBY, 16 SEPTEMBER 1985</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/09/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006723.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
4AUSTRLIA&amp;<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH TREVOR WATSON ( ABC) PORT MORESBY<br />
16 SEPTEMBER 1985<br />
WATSCN: Mr Hawke, what is Australia's response to Mr Mitterand's<br />
invitation to you and other South Pacific leaders to go to Mururoa?<br />
PM: I simply want to say to President Mitterand what I have<br />
said recently and that if he wants to invite the countries of<br />
the region to come to Mururoa so that he can show us how<br />
absolutely safe the tests are then I suggest to the President<br />
that he organise the picking up of all the testing equipment<br />
and taking it back to France and undertake in metropolitan<br />
France this testing which he assures us is so safe.<br />
WATSON: Well, how do you see this invitation?. Is it a<br />
propaganda stunt? Is it contemptuous? How do you see it?<br />
PM: I don't want to talk about contempt. But it seems to me<br />
that the government of France is discerning the truth and that<br />
is that there is a growing pressure amongst the people in the<br />
countries of the Pacific region that we find absolutely<br />
unacceptable, almost obscene, the fact that a metropolitan<br />
European power comes and conducts its nuclear tests in our<br />
region. And at the same they are doing it says that it is<br />
absolutely safe. As I repeat, if it is absolutely safe let<br />
them go and do it their own region.<br />
WATSON: France is not likely to go and do that, though is it?<br />
In fact it is almost certain to stay at Mururoa?<br />
PM: Yes, well one can't be certain just what happens. I know<br />
that early in the 1970s when I assumed the presidency of the<br />
ACTU, when they were conducting atmospheric nuclear testing,<br />
they said they were going to keep on doing that. Well, we led<br />
a world-wide protest on that. And we were told then that that<br />
protest had accelerated the move the underground testing. Well,<br />
I would hope that they would come to understand , the strength,<br />
the growing strength, of the attitudes on this matter.<br />
WATSON: The President's office has said that anyone who opposesI<br />
French interests in the region will be considered to be advers/ f..<br />
How do you react to that?<br />
PM: Well I understand that the French attribute themselves,, to<br />
themselves a great capacity for logic. This is introducing<br />
something quite new into the language and the reasoning of </p>
<p>2.<br />
PM cont: international relations. I ask people to contemplate<br />
what is the logic to what President Mitterand appears to be<br />
saying, that is if you oppose the policy or action of another<br />
nation you are therefore its foe. Now I would suggest to the<br />
President of France and the government of France that they don't<br />
really insult the intelligence of the people of either my country<br />
or the people of the countries of this region by attempting to<br />
introduce that sort of nonsense into the dialogue between nations.<br />
WATSON: Mr Lange doesn't seem to mind being cast in that<br />
adversary role or being considered a foe. How do you feel<br />
about it?<br />
PM: Well, I don't go around looking for enemies and Mr Lange's<br />
reaction is for Mr Lange. I have expressed the reaction of<br />
my Government.<br />
WATSON: Finally then sir, how would you at this moment describe<br />
Australia's relations with France?<br />
PM: Well they are like the curate's egg. In parts good, but in<br />
parts bad because together with the nations of the region, the<br />
signing recently of the South Pacific Nuclear Free Zone Treaty<br />
have made it clear, and we have been for some time, that we<br />
simply do not approve of the actions of the French in this<br />
regard. And so that in that area our relations are not good.<br />
But that doesn't preclude us from being able to have the<br />
cooperation with France and the people of France in other<br />
areas.<br />
WATSON: Would you be prepared to go Paris, as Mr Lange says<br />
he would be, for dicussions with President Mitterand?<br />
PM: Well, I have already done that. I did that in 1983.<br />
ENDS </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
