<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2520</transcript-id>
    <title>ACCESS TO WARTIME GOVERNMENT PAPERS - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR WILLIAM MCMAHON, CH MP</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/01/1972</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002520.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS PM No. 12/ 1972<br />
ACCESS TO WAR-TIME GOVERNMENT PAPERS<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, Mr. William McMahon, CH, MP<br />
The Prime Minister said that, as he had undertaken<br />
on 6 January, the: Government had now given further consideration<br />
to the policy of access to government documents for the<br />
war-time period. The. Government has decided that the 50-year access<br />
rule should in future apply to Cabinet papers, as it has since<br />
December 1970 to the generality of departmental documents.<br />
In addition, the Government has decided that,<br />
because of the special interest in them, the remainder of the<br />
war Cabinet papers ( covering the years 1942 to 1945) should<br />
also be released for public examination.<br />
The war Cabinet papers include papers from the<br />
War Cabinet itself, from the Advisory War Council, from the<br />
full Cabinet and from the Production Executive.<br />
Before the papers can be made available, it will<br />
be necessary to examine them in order to withhold those which,<br />
in accordance with normal archival practice and policy, should<br />
not be released. The categories of papers which will not be released<br />
will be those falling within the following groups<br />
exceptionally sensitive papers, the disclosure of<br />
which would be contrary to the public interest,<br />
whether on security or other grounds ( including the<br />
need to safeguard the revenue);<br />
( ii) documents containing information supplied in<br />
confidence, the disclosure of which would or </p>
<p>-2<br />
might constitute a breach of good faith; and<br />
( iii) documents containing information about individuals,<br />
the disclosure of which would cause distress or<br />
embarrassment to living persons or their immediate<br />
de~ cendants. Access to the Cabinet papers, when released,<br />
will be arranged, as with other archival documents, through the<br />
Commonwealth Archives Office.<br />
When the documents are released, they will be<br />
accompanied by an index to assist searchers to identify the<br />
documents they wish to see. Because the main interest has been<br />
in the war years, the first releases will be of the years 1939<br />
to 1941 in one group. As quickly as possible, papers for the<br />
remainder of the war years will then be released in further groups,<br />
and a similar process will then be followed for such papers as<br />
are available for the pre-war years, commencing in 1919.<br />
The Prime Minister said that it will take some<br />
time to prepare these papers for release. He expected that it<br />
will be possible to make available the first group of those not<br />
in the restricted categories ( covering the years 1939 to 1941)<br />
by about the middle of the year. Further groups of war-time papers,<br />
and later of pre-war papers, will become available as they are<br />
processed. In addition, the Prime Minister said that the<br />
Government had considered the departmental papers for the years<br />
1942 to 1945 which are at present closed except for the preparation<br />
of important works of scholarship. He said the Government<br />
considered that these papers also should become available at the<br />
same time as the Cabinet papers. Because of the vast number / S </p>
<p>-3-<br />
of papers involved, there will be a time lag in satisfying<br />
requests for documents. However, the Government has asked that steps<br />
should be taken to reduce the time required to meet requests.<br />
It has authorised whatever increase in<br />
establishment of the Archives Office is necessary to achieve<br />
this and has asked that the matter be taken up urgently with<br />
the Public Service Board. It has also agreed, as an immediate<br />
step, that the Archives Office may use officers on loan from<br />
other Departments, or seek to employ suitable temporary officers,<br />
such as those recently retired.<br />
The Prime Minister said he believed this step<br />
by the Government to make available Cabinet and other papers<br />
covering the war years, and later the pre-war Cabinet papers,<br />
would be welcomed by the public and in particular by those<br />
involved in work of scholarship and research.<br />
26 January, 1972 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
