<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10684</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                  THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                  RADIO INTERVIEW                GRAEME GILBERT &amp;#150; 2CC</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/08/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE..........................................................................................</p>
<p>GILBERT:</p>
<p>The Prime Minister joins us now. Good morning sir, how are you?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I am very well thank you.</p>
<p>GILBERT:</p>
<p>I can't imagine many people who have gambled so much as you</p>
<p>   are at the moment.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>What is important about this plan is that it is good for Australia's</p>
<p>   future and my responsibility as Prime Minister is at all times to</p>
<p>   take actions that I believe are good for Australia. If I believe</p>
<p>   that tax reform is good for Australia, if I believe that the present</p>
<p>   tax system must be changed to make the Australian economy stronger</p>
<p>   for the 21st century then irrespective of the so-called</p>
<p>   political risk involved for me it is my responsibility to put forward</p>
<p>   that plan. And most Australians believe that the present tax system</p>
<p>   is inadequate and should be changed in a quite fundamental way.</p>
<p>   We in the Government believe that and we have put forward a plan</p>
<p>   that is above everything else we believe will make the Australian</p>
<p>   economy stronger and it therefore will benefit the Australian nation</p>
<p>   into the 21st century.</p>
<p>GILBERT:</p>
<p>Yeah, we probably will only get this one chance of the bite</p>
<p>   in the apple' as it were I would suggest Prime Minister.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think that is true. If Australians really want to throw out the</p>
<p>   present tax system then they really have a clear choice now. We</p>
<p>   are putting forward a plan that will change the system for the better.</p>
<p>   It is not just a tax cut, it's not just a change in the indirect</p>
<p>   tax system, it is an integrated plan which addresses the fundamental</p>
<p>   weaknesses of the present system. It has enormous benefits for Australia's</p>
<p>   overseas trade because there will be no GST on our exports and that</p>
<p>   will reduce the cost of those by about $4.5 billion a year. It will</p>
<p>   be a very great benefit to country Australia, it's for the</p>
<p>   bush because the cost of fuel which is so important in a big country</p>
<p>   will be lower as a result of the arrangements inside the package</p>
<p>   and that is something you can't have without the GST. And,</p>
<p>   of course, there will be benefits for individuals and families far</p>
<p>   outweighing the cost involved in relation of the GST through the</p>
<p>   personal income tax cuts. So it is a total plan. It is not just</p>
<p>   a bit of patching, it's not a band-aid, it's not another</p>
<p>   tinkering at the edges which we have had for years. It is a genuine</p>
<p>   assault on the weaknesses of the present system.</p>
<p>GILBERT:</p>
<p>Now I was absolutely amazed at the weekend, one of the polls, and</p>
<p>   I'll ask you later I suspect we are being a bit over-polled</p>
<p>   in Australia at the moment, but one poll the question: Is</p>
<p>   a GST good for Australia?'47 per cent said yes but then another</p>
<p>   question in that same poll: Should the Opposition allow the</p>
<p>   GST if Howard is re-elected?' 47 per cent said no. How do you</p>
<p>   read those figures? They say yeah it's good but no it shouldn't</p>
<p>   be allowed?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think those polls were internally contradictory. Let's have</p>
<p>   a few more before we get a proper read on what the public is thinking.</p>
<p>   There was another one in the papers this morning that was going</p>
<p>   in a very different direction that showed very strong support for</p>
<p>   the whole plan. My feeling, moving around the country and I have</p>
<p>   done a bit so far, and I have got a lot more ahead of me this week</p>
<p>   is that people know the present system needs changing, they know</p>
<p>   that the former Labor Government had 13 years to fix it and didn't</p>
<p>   and they respect the fact that this Government is trying, is having</p>
<p>   a go at putting forward a plan that will fundamentally improve the</p>
<p>   system, make it fairer into the 21st century.</p>
<p>GILBERT:</p>
<p>Did you find yourself waking up on Friday morning or Saturday or</p>
<p>   Sunday and going: gee, I should have put that in or boy I really</p>
<p>   could have left that one out, or are you still happy with the total</p>
<p>   package?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No I have not gone through that experience. We took months to put</p>
<p>   this plan together. I have never worked on anything as much in my</p>
<p>   political life as I have on this and I was satisfied in the end</p>
<p>   that the balance was right. It does fundamentally reform the system,</p>
<p>   we are not fiddling at the edges. The new GST system is much fairer</p>
<p>   and better and more efficient and better for Australian business</p>
<p>   and therefore for all Australians because it will boost economic</p>
<p>   growth than the existing Wholesale Sales Tax system. The personal</p>
<p>   tax cuts are both necessary and desirable. We have this new top</p>
<p>   rate of 30 per cent in the dollar for everybody on an income between</p>
<p>   $20,000 and $50,000. And that's 60 to 70 per cent of all wage</p>
<p>   and salary earners in Australia. They will never pay more than 30</p>
<p>   per cent at the margin. That is a huge improvement on the present</p>
<p>   system. We have very significant family benefits and very importantly</p>
<p>   we have a lot of protection and a lot of compensation for retired</p>
<p>   people and people on the pension. I mean we are getting rid of provisional</p>
<p>   tax. A lot of self-funded retirees have hated that for years. We</p>
<p>   are bringing in a 30 per cent tax rebate for private health insurance.</p>
<p>   We are boosting the attractiveness of retired people having shares</p>
<p>   in companies. Many of those people on modest incomes don't</p>
<p>   get the full value of those and they will under our plan in the</p>
<p>   future and there's a savings compensation of up to $3,000 untaxed</p>
<p>   for retired people as well. There are lots of benefits loaded into</p>
<p>   this plan for retired people, for pensioners and retired people</p>
<p>   so that they are not just protected against the introduction of</p>
<p>   the Goods and Services Tax but given additional benefits over and</p>
<p>   above the compensation that is necessary to protect them.</p>
<p>GILBERT:</p>
<p>Now you have heard the critics, people have said: oh sure it's</p>
<p>   been guaranteed to be capped at a percentage, the GST in overseas</p>
<p>   countries, and it has crept up and up. I know you have explained</p>
<p>   it but please can we go through it slowly again so that people are</p>
<p>   very clear why are you able to confidently say 10 per cent does</p>
<p>   in fact mean 10 per cent.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well Graeme, what we are going to do is, when it is introduced</p>
<p>   we are going to change the law to say that it can't be varied</p>
<p>   without the unanimous request of the States and Territories, the</p>
<p>   agreement of the Federal Government and the passage of a law through</p>
<p>   both houses of Federal Parliament. Now we will put a law through</p>
<p>   Federal Parliament to that effect. Now, I don't believe that</p>
<p>   that will ever happen.</p>
<p>GILBERT:</p>
<p>I can't see a State government whacking it up.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>And I don't believe that once that is the law of the Commonwealth,</p>
<p>   I don't believe that any future government, combining with</p>
<p>   the Opposition and minor parties in the Senate, is going to agree</p>
<p>   to change that law because there will be such a focus on a government</p>
<p>   that tries to do that. And there will be such pressure on an opposition</p>
<p>   very likely with the minor parties having the numbers in the Senate</p>
<p>   that the likelihood of that occurring is just unimaginable given</p>
<p>   the sort of experience that we have now had over a number of years</p>
<p>   in the interplay between the two houses of Parliament. I mean I</p>
<p>   can't imagine a future Coalition Government proposing to change</p>
<p>   that law and nor can I imagine a future Labor Government with numbers</p>
<p>   in the Senate along with Democrats and whatever else agreeing with</p>
<p>   such a change. I mean to me once that is the law and surely if we</p>
<p>   win the next election the Labor Party and others won't oppose</p>
<p>   it becoming the law because it will give protection to the people,</p>
<p>   I can't ever imagine it altering.</p>
<p>GILBERT:</p>
<p>Well you'd be drawn and quartered wouldn't you and I</p>
<p>   can't imagine you looking forward to that.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well nobody is going to do that. Once it is there and given all</p>
<p>   of the brouhaha that will have followed the introduction I just</p>
<p>   can't see it ever changing.</p>
<p>GILBERT:</p>
<p>I just had a call from a person in Giralang Prime Minister and</p>
<p>   he asks: would taxes be coming off electricity and gas?'</p>
<p>   Are you able to tell him yea or nay on that one?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well our position in relation....the GST will cover electricity.</p>
<p>   What it doesn't apply to is council rates and water rates and</p>
<p>   things like motor registration fees. But if you are running a business</p>
<p>   and you use gas and electricity in it then obviously any GST that</p>
<p>   is paid on electricity bills you would be able to get that back</p>
<p>   from the Tax Office because it is a business input.</p>
<p>GILBERT:</p>
<p>Now later on this morning you are in Queanbeyan, of course, with</p>
<p>   the Federal Member there, Gary Nairn in Eden Monaro talking to truckies</p>
<p>   primarily because in our backyard the capital region backyard, the</p>
<p>   Hume Highway, a lot of heavy transport. What message will you be</p>
<p>   taking to them Prime Minister?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well a very good message because what we are going to do is to</p>
<p>   dramatically reduce the cost of using diesel fuel anywhere in Australia.</p>
<p>   The present excise on diesel fuel is 43 cents a litre and for heavy</p>
<p>   trucks that will come down by 25 cents to 18 cents. And the same</p>
<p>   thing will apply to rail and on top of that the off-road use, farmers</p>
<p>   for example but not only farmers but also tour boat operators and</p>
<p>   ferry operators who use diesel and other comparable fuels, they</p>
<p>   will continue to be completely free of excise. So the fuel savings...the</p>
<p>   savings in fuel costs under this plan are quite spectacular and</p>
<p>   that is very important in Australia because it is a big country</p>
<p>   and a lot of people pay a lot extra because the goods they buy are</p>
<p>   transported over long distances and anything that reduces the cost</p>
<p>   of transporting them over those long distances must be very good</p>
<p>   for them. And then on top of all of that any businessman who uses</p>
<p>   petrol or any fuel, this is not just a heavy truck industry or farmer,</p>
<p>   but any businessman who uses any fuel will find that that fuel is</p>
<p>   cheaper after the plan comes into operation because he'll be</p>
<p>   able to get the GST paid on that fuel back and that will mean that</p>
<p>   every litre of petrol he buys will be 7 cents a litre cheaper </p>
<p>   7 cents a litre cheaper than what it is now because he'll get</p>
<p>   back the GST that he pays on the fuel and the price paid at the</p>
<p>   pump either for him or the ordinary motorist won't go up so</p>
<p>   the benefits for, not only the bush but for business generally but</p>
<p>   particularly the bush because that's where things are carried</p>
<p>   long distances out of this plan are enormous.</p>
<p>GILBERT:</p>
<p>Now if we could just briefly touch on politics in general, at the</p>
<p>   moment your major opponent, Kim Beazley, the poll suggests he won't</p>
<p>   be returned at the next Federal election. If that, in fact, is the</p>
<p>   case and other suggestions are that the counting is already underway</p>
<p>   between Evans and Crean to get that leader's role, who would</p>
<p>   you prefer to be looking across the parliamentary desk at, who would</p>
<p>   make the alternate....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Graeme, I haven't turned my mind to that. I will turn my mind</p>
<p>   to that after the election. My preoccupation at the present time</p>
<p>   is explaining to the Australian public why the Government I lead</p>
<p>   should be returned. Mr Beazley's responsibility when he brings</p>
<p>   out his alternative tax plan will be to convince the Australian</p>
<p>   people that Labor having had 13 years to fix the tax system and</p>
<p>   didn't do so now has the capacity within a couple of weeks</p>
<p>   of us bringing about this imaginative plan to do so. I am concerned</p>
<p>   about choice that the public will make between now and the next</p>
<p>   election. I don't take the public for granted. We have got</p>
<p>   to earn re-election, I believe we have earnt re-election but I don't</p>
<p>   take them for granted. We inherited a deficit of $10.5 billion and</p>
<p>   we have now got it in surplus. We have delivered the lowest interest</p>
<p>   rates in 30 years, we generated 300,000 new jobs, we now have a</p>
<p>   plan that will tackle head-on the weaknesses of the present unfair</p>
<p>   tax system and I will spend my waking hours between now and whenever</p>
<p>   the election is held to explain that plan and other policies and</p>
<p>   ask the Australian people to vote for us again. And I think Mr Beazley's</p>
<p>   responsibility is to explain to the Australian people, how is it</p>
<p>   that having had 13 years and not having fixed the tax system, he</p>
<p>   can fix the tax system by just offering a few tax cuts but not having</p>
<p>   a GST. I mean you can't have it both ways, you are either serious</p>
<p>   about reform or what you are saying to the Australian people is:</p>
<p>   well look we are not interested in tax reform, we'll give you</p>
<p>   a tax cut but we won't sort of do anything serious about reforming</p>
<p>   the system. I think the Australian people are a wake-up to that.</p>
<p>   They will give us marks for having included reform along with tax</p>
<p>   cuts. If we'd have just offered tax cuts and nothing else they'd</p>
<p>   have said: well look you are just like the former Government, you</p>
<p>   are playing....</p>
<p>GILBERT:</p>
<p>It's a total package or nothing at all.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well you are either serious about reforming it or not and everybody</p>
<p>   knows that the present system is not working and it needs change.</p>
<p>   Now we are at least honest and open and courageous enough to offer</p>
<p>   reform and change and offer a total approach. But what Mr Beazley</p>
<p>   will do is say: well look I'll give you some tax cuts but don't</p>
<p>   ask me to reform the wholesale tax system. I mean Mr Beazley wants</p>
<p>   to keep the present system.</p>
<p>GILBERT:</p>
<p>Now people in our region Prime Minister will say that after that</p>
<p>   March '96 election you were serious about trying to downsize</p>
<p>   Canberra. Have we seen the last of the public service downcutting</p>
<p>   and outsourcing and all those other things that cost jobs and prestige</p>
<p>   around here?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I think it is fair to say that in the first two budgets there</p>
<p>   were a number of decisions that were taken that did result in a</p>
<p>   smaller Federal public service, I accept that. In the last budget</p>
<p>   that process wasn't there. We don't, at the moment, we</p>
<p>   don't see the need for further reductions in expenditure. We</p>
<p>   have got the budget back into balance. We have done the hard yards.</p>
<p>   We have got rid of Mr Beazley's blackhole of $10.5 billion.</p>
<p>   I mean he incidentally tried to stop us doing that and now is expressing</p>
<p>   concern about the surplus so according to him we shouldn't</p>
<p>   be in surplus. I mean it's very interesting....</p>
<p>GILBERT:</p>
<p>Yeah it's a funny statement isn't it, don't pay</p>
<p>   the bills.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>.....$10 billion deficit, he's tried to stop us getting</p>
<p>   that into a surplus. He says that we shouldn't really now be</p>
<p>   in surplus yet he says shock horror our tax plan threatens the surplus.</p>
<p>   I mean that is a very, very inconsistent position to have. He is</p>
<p>   the last person to shed crocodile tears over the surplus because</p>
<p>   he tried to stop us getting there, says we shouldn't be there</p>
<p>   but says: oh don't do anything that will threaten it. I think</p>
<p>   that is very contradictory but as far as future spending cuts are</p>
<p>   concerned the present level of Federal Government spending, we don't</p>
<p>   see any need to further reduce it so that is the answer that I would</p>
<p>   give to that question. In any event there's been a very, very</p>
<p>   strong performance by the private sector of the ACT and regional</p>
<p>   economy and the signs are that some of the change in the public</p>
<p>   sector area is now being well and truly taken over by the private</p>
<p>   sector and the ratio between the two is altering and the nature</p>
<p>   of the ACT and surrounds economy is altering and I think altering</p>
<p>   for the better.</p>
<p>GILBERT:</p>
<p>Are you still enjoying this Prime Minister's job?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes I am, I still have a great commitment to do things, to tackle</p>
<p>   problems. I think what the Australian people are tired of in politics</p>
<p>   at the present time is endless debate over personalities and issues</p>
<p>   and not enough focus on providing solutions and tackling problems.</p>
<p>   They are tired of rhetorical debates, they are more interested in</p>
<p>   governments and politicians who offer some solutions. Now not everything</p>
<p>   you put up everybody agrees with but there are a lot of Australians</p>
<p>   who will give marks to a government that is prepared to have a go</p>
<p>   at solving some of our problems. One of the problems Australia has</p>
<p>   at the moment is that we do have an okay, out-of-date taxation system.</p>
<p>   Everybody knows that. Mr Beazley and Mr Evans know that because</p>
<p>   some years ago they themselves supported change but they are too</p>
<p>   frightened to do it now and they think there is more political advantage</p>
<p>   in scoring points off the government. Now we are prepared to put</p>
<p>   forward a comprehensive plan. We are saying to the Australian people:</p>
<p>   you can't have just the good side, you can't just have</p>
<p>   tax cuts without some attempt to fix the problem. We are offering</p>
<p>   both tax relief and tax reform. We are offering both. You can't</p>
<p>   have one, in my view, without the other. You can't ask the Australian</p>
<p>   people to accept tax reform without giving them tax relief.</p>
<p>GILBERT:</p>
<p>Yeah we have got to stop saying: what's in it for us. We've</p>
<p>   got to say: let's look at the country.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well you have got to look at the country's long-term welfare</p>
<p>   but by the same token if you are asking people to accept tax reform</p>
<p>   they are entitled to have something back. And something that eases</p>
<p>   the process of reform and that is what we are offering. But if we</p>
<p>   say to them: look we are just going to give you the reform and nothing</p>
<p>   else I don't think they will be interested. But equally if</p>
<p>   you say to them: well if you can have the tax relief but you don't</p>
<p>   have to have the reform, they'll say: hang on, there's</p>
<p>   a catch in that. Because that is what happened in 1993, Mr Keating</p>
<p>   and Mr Beazley offered tax cuts but no GST. When they got into office</p>
<p>   they took away the tax cuts and they put up all the indirect taxes</p>
<p>   which was just as bad as in terms of impact, worse than the GST</p>
<p>   because there was no compensation for low income earners, the was</p>
<p>   no compensation for the poor.</p>
<p>GILBERT:</p>
<p>Exactly. Prime Minister, I never thought I'd say this but</p>
<p>   I have got to say that news is upon us and I hate to cut you short.</p>
<p>   I have appreciated your time, I know how busy you are. Thank you</p>
<p>   very much for this morning.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Very nice to talk to you.</p>
<p>[ENDS]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
