<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7949</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/03/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007949.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
NATIONAL 9 N1: TWOIK CANBERRA BUREAU<br />
PRESS GALLERY PARLIAMENT HOUSE CANBERRA<br />
P11ONE: ( 062) 73 3300 FAX: 73 3097<br />
Date: 11 March 1990 Time: 0900<br />
Source: National Nine Network Programme: Sunday<br />
Jim Waley: With the result of the Federal Election still<br />
anyone's guess, over the last two Sundays before the poll we are.<br />
talking again with the leaders of both major parties beginning<br />
this morning with the Prime Minister, who is in our Melbourne<br />
studio. The interviewers, Alan Ramsay from the Sydney Morning<br />
Herald and Sunday's political editor, Laurie Cakes.<br />
CAKES: Prime Minister, good morning.<br />
HAWKE: Good morning, Laurie. Good morning, Alan.<br />
CAKES: The coalition this week is re-jigging its campaign. They<br />
are going to focus on the impact of the capital gains tax on<br />
superannuation. New commercial featuring John Howard. They are<br />
circulating a petition calling on the in-coming Government to<br />
abolish the tax. Has the issue got legs?<br />
HAWKE: I believe it has certainly got legs for us.<br />
CAKES: In what way?<br />
HAWKE: Because the facts are quite clear. They were put by<br />
Alan, I think, at the start of the great debate. They haven't<br />
changed and that is that less than 1 per cent of Australian<br />
taxpayears pay capital gains tax. It is the basis of a quite<br />
remarkable statement and I will just read to you because here is<br />
the answer to it all. This is something that was said in 1980<br />
by Professor Russell Matthe ws. He said: ' The essential problem<br />
is to make the rich pay any income tax at all'. That is what he<br />
said. The essential problem is to get the rich to pay any income<br />
tax at all. And the reason why under the Liberals and before we </p>
<p>came in the rich weren't paying any tax basically. It was a<br />
matter of choice because of the absence of a capital gains tax.<br />
OAKES: But what about the question of superannuation funds,<br />
Prime Minister. They don't represent the rich. As I understand<br />
it today the Society of Superannuation Funds is going to issue<br />
a statement giving examples of how the tax affects superannuants.<br />
HAWKE: The facts about the superannuation funds are very, very<br />
simple. When the tax was brought in 1988, 15 per cent tax, the<br />
arrangements there were for that to be offset, at least offset,<br />
by imputation credits. And that is that any superannuation fund<br />
that is properly managed can have a zero position in regard to<br />
the tax on superannuation. The point was to enable<br />
superannuation funds to invest in Australian companies because<br />
as those funds grow we want them to be investing in Australian<br />
enterprises so they can have a net zero position of impact with<br />
the tax and that is well known.<br />
OAKES: But if the society representing those funds are backing<br />
the Liberals are you saying that all funds under that umbrella<br />
are wrongly managed?<br />
HAWKE: We'll see what the superannuation says but I am telling<br />
you quite clearly the facts are that under the tax arrangements<br />
brought in that 15 per cent tax that is imposed is more than<br />
capable of being offset by the imputation credits which the<br />
holders in funds get in terms of the tax already being paid by<br />
the companies. It can be more than offset. And the fact is that<br />
it was the absence of a capital gains tax which meant that<br />
billions of dollars that should be paid by those individuals and<br />
companies in Australia was not being paid. That is what meant<br />
that ordinary taxpayers were paying higher taxes than they need<br />
to. The voters of Australia, I can assure you Laurie and Alan,<br />
are golng to say we do not want a return to the situation of a<br />
pre-Labor Government where the ordinary Australian taxpayer paid<br />
more because the rich, as Professor Russell Matthews said, had<br />
it as a matter of choice wjiether they paid any at all. It is<br />
only with the capital gains tax that you can have equity in the<br />
tax system.<br />
RAMSAY: Prime Minister, interest rates certainly is an issue </p>
<p>with legs.<br />
HAWKE: Yes, it is.<br />
RAMSAY: With only two weeks to go to polling day, the banks<br />
still have not responded to the Government's manipulation of<br />
official rates by lowering mortgage rates. Now are you still<br />
asking voters to take you on trust?<br />
HAWKE: It's not a question of taking me on trust. I guess, if<br />
you like, it is a question of taking the banks on trust. We had<br />
no expectation that during the Election campaign, Alan, they<br />
would bring down mortgage rates. But what they have said is that<br />
the policies of the Government, which involved an initial<br />
lowering of the official rates, they have said that will lead to<br />
a lowering of mortgage rates. That is their statement and,<br />
indeed, it must do because the cost of money to them is coming<br />
down. The choice for the voters is quite clear. The banks are<br />
saying interest rates will come down under the policies of the<br />
Government. Under the Liberals there are two things which must<br />
mean a rise of interest rates. One, the wages explosion, which<br />
they do not deny must occur under their policies and, secondly,<br />
the blowing of the Budget surplus. If you blow your Budget<br />
surplus and have a wages explosion, interest rates must go up.<br />
RAMSAY: But go back to what governments say, what politicians<br />
say. In the 1987 Election campaign you said interest rates would<br />
come down.<br />
HAWKE: No, I didn't.<br />
RAMSAY: They went up, considerably. Why should people believe<br />
you now?<br />
HAWKE: Very simply. We have been through this before. We had<br />
the run on this in the debate. We underestimated and I have<br />
said this. I couldn't have been more open and nor could the<br />
Treasrrer. In 1987-88 we had a $ 15 billion accretion to domestic<br />
demand capacity because of the favourable turn around in the<br />
terms of trade. We all, every economist in the country,<br />
underestimated the strength, of demand that became associated with<br />
that situation. And, as a responsible Government, we had to<br />
bring in tighter monetary policy because if we didn't you would<br />
have had the simple situation that we would have had a totally </p>
<p>unsustainable explosion of imports and the economy would have<br />
collapsed. Life in running a Government, running economic<br />
policy, isn't simply an easy thing of saying: ' Oh well, we won't<br />
take any notice of the changes and the circumstances and we will<br />
just adhere to some concept of the past'. If you are confronted<br />
with an unforeseen explosion of demand than responsible<br />
Government means, if you are concerned about the long-term<br />
equilibrium of the economy, it demands that you take action to<br />
see that that level of consumption is brought back and we have<br />
done it.<br />
RAMSAY: Yes, Prime Minister, but out there a lot of people don't<br />
understand all this and that sounds like a big fat excuse.<br />
HAWKE: Some may, I don't doubt that. But, as you know, Alan,<br />
I have always argued from the beginning of the campaign and,<br />
indeed, before it that I have got greater faith in the<br />
intelligence and the understanding of the Australian electorate<br />
than my opponents and some commentators. I don't believe, for<br />
instance, Alan, that the electorate is going to buy the nonsense<br />
of this last week where Mr Peacock manufactured a $ 14 billion<br />
hole in the Government's forward estimates and said: ' There is<br />
a $ 14 billion hole there' That lasted less than one day but you<br />
see they think they can insult the intelligence of the Australian<br />
electorate. I don't think you can. I think if I tell them that<br />
we had this great explosion of demand which would have ruined the<br />
economy is we hadn't lessened it, I think that the majority of<br />
people will understand and accept it. They won't like the fact<br />
that there had to be higher interest rates. I am not deluding<br />
myself about that. But they will understand that that was<br />
necessary and, they have got to look at the choice. They<br />
have got the banking industry saying that our policies, Alan, are<br />
going-o lead to a reduction in mortgage rates. They know. They<br />
know. Against that you have an explosion of wages which Mr<br />
Peacock has not denied. If you have an explosion of wages and<br />
you blow away our Budget surplus, those two factors together must<br />
mean an increase in interest rates. That is the clear choice<br />
they have got.<br />
OAKES: Mr Hawke, one thing Mr Peacock said during the week was </p>
<p>that election campaigns reminded him of the movie ' Sex, Lies and<br />
Video Tape' without the sex and the video tape. Does it worry<br />
you that you have to tell fibs to people to win their votes?<br />
HAWKE: I don't tell fibs to win their votes.<br />
OAKES: Come on. Alan has already mentioned the 1987 promise<br />
that interest rates would come down and in the same election<br />
campaign you said inflation would come down. Back in 1983 you<br />
promised there would be no capital gains tax. It's a pretty long<br />
list. HAWKE: Okay, let's take them one by one. Let's take the last<br />
one. In 1983 I said there would be no capital gains tax.<br />
OAKES: We've got one.<br />
HAWKE: Laurie, could I finish. I said there would be no capital<br />
gains tax in that Parliament. There wasn't. You have<br />
conveniently overlooked for reasons which I suppose are useful<br />
just for fun the fact that the capital gains tax came in after<br />
the 1984 Election. And in the 1984 Election campaign I<br />
specifically said to the Australian people we will, after this<br />
Election, have a tax summit at which the tax policy to be brought<br />
in will be affected. So, don't give me that business, Laurie.<br />
OAKES: The inflation promise. The interest rates promise. They<br />
all happened within three years. Or virtually within three<br />
years. HAWKE: Okay, let's take the inflation. When we came to office<br />
the inflation rate was 11 per cent. 11 per cent. By 1984-85 we<br />
had halved it. Then we had the collapse of the dollar with the<br />
collapse in terms of trade but it still under that impact didn't<br />
ever get back to anything like 11 per cent. It peaked at 9.8 per<br />
cent and it is coming down. But Treasury said that at the end<br />
of this last year, 5.7 per cent, the underlying rate. We have<br />
never-got anywhere near the 11 per cent inflation rate that I<br />
inherited. So, in the period of the Hawke Government inflation<br />
has been brought down and kept down below the rate it was.<br />
OAKES: But it went up after 1987. After you made the promise.<br />
It didn't go down.<br />
HAWKE: Yes.<br />
OAKES: You can't say that wasn't a fib. </p>
<p>HAWKE: I can because I am saying that we were mistaken. There<br />
is a difference between a fib and an honest mistake shared by<br />
every economist in Australia. Every economist in Australia<br />
public and private, Laurie, as you know underestimated the<br />
strength of demand and that demand pushed up inflation. Okay,<br />
I cannot say to the Australian people I won't say in this<br />
campaign and I have never said in any other that I can predict<br />
with absolute certainty everything that is going to happen in<br />
Australia and overseas. But what I can say with certainty is<br />
that we will have the basic structure of policies. That is, one<br />
of things which----<br />
OAKES: But Prime Minister, if you know that you can't predict<br />
with certainty why did you say inflation will come down, interest<br />
rates will come down. If you knew you couldn't say it with<br />
certainty it was a fib.<br />
HAWKE: No, I don't believe that. I don't believe that is a<br />
correct way of saying it because in respect of all the things<br />
that we could do to affect these rates, we did them. Just as,<br />
at the present time, Laurie, very simple, that a Government or<br />
an alternative Government can do in its power to influence<br />
interest rates and inflation rates are essentially these things:<br />
Wages, and that is fundamentally important. Let me give you the<br />
figures, Laurie, of what has happened in the period we have been<br />
in. In these seven years our predictions about wages rates,<br />
outcome for the next year, have been either on target or we have<br />
somewhat overestimated the outcome. In other words, where we<br />
have predicted wages outcomes we. have been right. So, that is<br />
the basic thing a Government can do. Have control over wages<br />
outcome. We can do it. We have done it in seven years. Out<br />
opponents can't. There will be a wages explosion. The other<br />
thing--that you can fundamentally do is the control of Budget<br />
policy. Now, I have in the last three years had a surplus, a<br />
Budget surplus, of about $ 17 billion. That is the first time<br />
in the history of this couptry that is has been done. Against<br />
that, our opponents will blow the Budget surplus by at least $ 6<br />
billion. So I can say with certainty in regard to the things<br />
that fundamentally determine these outcomes what will occur. </p>
<p>Against that the outlook is appalling under our opponents.<br />
RAMSAY: Prime Minister, a lot of people think that this is a<br />
pretty boring Election campaign. That after seven years you're<br />
boring. Is this a deliberate strategy on the Government's part.<br />
Send people to sleep.<br />
HAWKE: Well, Alan, I'm not trying to send people to sleep and<br />
if I am boring that may be the judgment of some.<br />
RAMSAY: Very laid back, Prime Minister.<br />
HAWKE: Well, I don't know about laid back. Certainly not cocky<br />
or complacent. I believe that this is a campaign in which my<br />
obligation, Alan, is calmly to tell the Australian people where<br />
we've been and the sorts of policies we've been building on for<br />
the creation of a better Australia and, importantly, I thought.<br />
my obligation in the policy speech was to say: ' My fellow<br />
Australians, here is where we are and these are the sorts of<br />
things I have in mind in regard to education, science and<br />
technology, children and so on. All these things that I have in<br />
mind for building a better future'. Now if that's not sexy<br />
and I guess the creation of 50 centres of research is not sexy.<br />
But let me say this it will more than anything that any other<br />
Federal Government has ever done I think determine the quality<br />
of our research and our capacity to be competitive in the future.<br />
Now, it is not sexy and exciting but I wanted to say it. I<br />
intend to do it.<br />
RAMSAY: Prime Minister, though I think that often you look<br />
bored. That a lot of the life has gone out of you in the last<br />
seven years.<br />
HAWKE: Well, Alan, if we want to exchange views about how one<br />
another looks I could say something about how you look but I<br />
don't think that would be very elevating.<br />
RAMSAY-I'm not standing for election, Prime Minister.<br />
HAWKE: No, but you are making judgments about how people look.<br />
RAMSAY: Yes, I am.<br />
HAWKE: I am simply saying have never been more excited, Alan,<br />
about being Prime Minister of this country.<br />
RAMSAY: You don't look it, Prime Minister.<br />
HAWKE: You may say so. But if you want me to be jumping up and </p>
<p>doing a jig then you are going to be disappointed. The sense of<br />
excitment and pride I have about being Prime Minister of the best<br />
country in the world is beyond description. Every day I wake up<br />
and feel just tremendous and indescribable pride about being the<br />
leader of this country. If I wanted to, and if you just gave me<br />
a minute, I would tell you about not only in terms of what we<br />
have done in this country but let me just mention in the last 12<br />
months the leadership given for Australia in the world. In the<br />
world. Firstly, here is Australia having the chemicals weapons<br />
convention. Bringing all the nations of the world and the<br />
industries of the world. Never been done before. Doing what had<br />
never been done before in bringing all the countries of the Asia<br />
and Pacific region. People had talked about it for decades.<br />
Hawke brought them together to get Asia-Pacific economic<br />
cooperation. The Hawke Government taking a lead in trying to get<br />
a break-through for peace in Cambodia. The Hawke Government<br />
taking the lead in the world in saving the Antarctic from mining.<br />
And that is not the end of the list. Now those things give a<br />
sense of great joy and excitment. Now, if I'm not showing those<br />
by jumping up and down and saying I am excited about taking<br />
Australia to the lead in so many areas of world affairs, well,<br />
I don't apologise for it. But I can tell you the excitment is<br />
there.<br />
OAKES: Mr Hawke, one of the things you were excited about in<br />
your policy speech was the extension of fee relief to private<br />
child care centres. What is the cost of that promise?<br />
HAWKE: The total cost of the package is of the order of $ 400m.<br />
OAKES: What about this section of it?<br />
HAWKE: I'll give the section. I haven't got the elements there.<br />
OAKES: You see, there is no asking you. When Ray Braithwaite,<br />
the Opposition front bencher, suggested this six months ago, you<br />
were sneered at by Neal Blewett in Parliament. Neal Blewett said<br />
it is balderdash to suggest that this extension would not<br />
involved very significant additional cost. He talked about it<br />
costing extra hundreds of millions of dollars.<br />
HAWKE: All I can say, Laurie, is that the total cost of the<br />
package which is made up, as you know, of the extension of places </p>
<p>and is made up of fee relief----<br />
OAKES: But according to the ERC score sheet you issued, the<br />
total cost for a full year of the new initiatives in your policy<br />
speech was $ 144m. How can you have an initiative in that that<br />
is worth several hundreds of millions of dollars?<br />
HAWKE: Because our initiatives have been both funded and<br />
expended over three years. That is what the score sheet shows,<br />
Laurie. OAKES: If that is the case then Neal Blewett was talking through<br />
his hat when he was criticising the Opposition.<br />
HAWKE: No, he wasn't. The child care proposals in total in<br />
1991, $ 86.8m; in 1991-92, $ 144.6m and in the third year,<br />
$ 166.5m. There you get, Laurie, the total over three years of<br />
the best part of $ 400m, carefully costed. But before we decided<br />
on one cent of expenditure, whether it was in child care, roads<br />
or anywhere else, we did the savings exercise first. There they<br />
were set out. The savings identified in the February statement<br />
$ 347.7m, $ 547.8m in the second year, $ 602.9m in the third year.<br />
Every savings identified, costed by the Department of Finance.<br />
And then, as I say I have given you the exact figures for child<br />
care, of promis-e that we make totally funded.<br />
OAKES: Prime Minister, we are just about out of time but I find<br />
that is inconsistent with what Neal Blewett said. A final<br />
issue----<br />
HAWKE: No, don't just leave it there. You are talking about<br />
something that was said before in regard to an unspecified,<br />
uncosted, unfunded proposal.<br />
OAKES: It's the same proposal.<br />
HAWKE: No, it's not. That's not good enough, Laurie. What has<br />
happened here is that very specific proposals, very specific<br />
proposals, funded $ 86.8m. You can't get it very much more<br />
specific than that. $ 86.8m in the first year, $ 144.6m in the<br />
second, $ 166.5m in the third. Specifically funded, covered and<br />
out of all that we have doe, Laurie, out of everything that we<br />
have done, still a slight increase in the surplus at the end.<br />
Against that, at least a $ 6 billion hole $ 2.8 billion for their<br />
two-tiered tax, about $ 2 billion in regard to Medicare, $ 800m in </p>
<p>a regard to the whole fund by the Department of Finance, $ 700m for<br />
roads. Over $ 6 billion unfunded.<br />
OAKES: Okay, Prime Minister, you win. Thank you.<br />
HAWKE: Thank you.<br />
Va'Wr apt ~ a i i ~ u y a. he b i~ l<br />
( Transcript by Monitair Pty Limited)<br />
Inquiries to Peter Harvey, Press Gallery, Parliament<br />
House, Canberra. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
