<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6711</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, HON RJL HAWKE AC MP, STAN KELLY MEMORIAL LECTURE, ECONOMIC SOCIETY OF AUSTRALIA, VICTORIAN BRANCH, MELBOURNE, 5 SEPTEMBER 1985</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/09/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006711.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
J~ AUSTIRALI
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER HON. R. J. L. HAWKE, AC, MP<br />
STAN KELLY MEMORIAL LECTURE<br />
ECONOMIC SOCIETY OF AUSTRALIA VICTORIAN BRANCH<br />
MELBOURNE 5 SEPTEMBER 1985<br />
I know of Stan Kelly from a mutual friend between our<br />
two generations, John Crawford. Sir John's Inaugural<br />
Stan Kelly Memorial Lecture in 1977 laid out some ideas<br />
on which we later worked together in the Study Group on<br />
Structural Adjustment.<br />
I like what I know of W~ elly a farmer who gave much of<br />
his life to public administration, including on the<br />
Tariff Board in those terrible years from 1929 to 1940,<br />
and as an adviser to the Commonwealth Prices<br />
Commissioner during and immediately after the war. I<br />
like the way that Stan Kelly recognised the dangers of<br />
excessive protection in a protectionist era, but sought<br />
the moderate and gradual curbing of excesses rather than<br />
impractical, radical changes.<br />
There are many ways in which the steady progress we are<br />
making today in building a more dynamic Australian<br />
economy through increasing its international orientation<br />
is indebted to the work of kelly and a small number of<br />
others, who questioned the role of high protection when<br />
its tide was still rising in Australian political<br />
thought.<br />
One of Stan Kelly's legacies to Australia was, of course<br />
his son Bert. Bert Kelly occupied the tragic place in<br />
Australian history of a farmer who understood the<br />
economic effects of protection, from 1958 sitting on the<br />
back bench of a conservative Government whose trade and<br />
industry policies were run by Jack McEwen. That he<br />
stuck to his guns through all those years with rarely a<br />
ray of hope says a great deal for his strength of<br />
character or, as Mavis would probably say, for his sheer<br />
farm-bred obstinacyl </p>
<p>C<br />
A gathering like this, organised3 by the Victorian Branch of<br />
the Economic Society, is not an occasion for partisan<br />
comment. The only political comment that I will make will be<br />
of ai scientific kind, involving, for example, the testing of<br />
political forecasts.<br />
Five weeks ago I presented the annual forecasting prizes to<br />
the New South Wales Branch of the Economic Society. The New<br />
South Wales Branch was discreet enough to withhold<br />
information on the content of forecasts, but from<br />
conversations with participants it seems that the best<br />
exchange rate predictions a year ago were those which had our<br />
dollar rising by the smallest amounts.<br />
Political forecasting is a bit more accurate. Early this<br />
year I predicted that the ideological tensions within the<br />
Liberal Party would soon erupt into open disputation about<br />
the Leadership. As we all know that prediction, which I<br />
shared with others, has been dramatically proven correct<br />
today. It will be of immense interest now to those of us concerned<br />
with economic policy to see how the ideological forces which<br />
gave rise to today's events manifest themselves in the<br />
opposition's approach to fundamental economic issues.<br />
Over the past few months we have seen the current Opposition<br />
support needs-based welfare then oppose the Assets Test;<br />
support the introduction of more international market<br />
discipline into highly protected Australian industry and then<br />
use its numbers in the Senate to defeat the Kerin Dairy Plan;<br />
support the free play of market forces and then block<br />
legislation designed to take the allocation of petroleum<br />
exploration licences out of the hands of bureaucrats into a<br />
competitive market; and support lower deficits but oppose<br />
attempts to reduce expenditure where it has no strong<br />
justification in economic efficiency or equity, such as with<br />
the Senate's rejection of our amendments to some<br />
more-than-intended Veterans' entitlements resulting from<br />
judicial decisions.<br />
These are the sorts of issues which will test the rhetoric of<br />
the new Opposition leadership. No doubt we will all watch to<br />
see how it acts. Whatever happens in these matters, it has<br />
been the policies of this Government which have turned around<br />
the economy and restored sustained economic growth. I<br />
believe that I am entitled to claim on this record that<br />
Australia's hopes of building a new era of sustained economic<br />
growth depend on the present Labor Government.<br />
This is a heavy responsibility, and one that we accept as the<br />
core of our mandate from the Australian people. Australia can<br />
be a successful society only in the context of sustained<br />
economic growth. The Labor Government is committed to<br />
progress towards ideals that can be broadly described as<br />
social democratic ideals that include equality of </p>
<p>3<br />
opportunity, the removal of poverty, the raising of<br />
living standards for ordinary Australian families, all<br />
within a political framework of individual freedom and<br />
Parliamentary democracy.<br />
None of this can be advanced far without sustained<br />
economic growth.<br />
Only sustained, strong economic growth can reduce<br />
unemployment to acceptable levels.<br />
Only sustained economic growth can support adequate<br />
provision for Australians who, but for the intervention<br />
of Government in directing community resources to them,<br />
would live in intolerable poverty.<br />
And only sustained economic growth can deliver rising<br />
living standards over time for ordinary Australian<br />
families whether through higher pay, or the provision<br />
of the better education, health and social<br />
infrastructure that are essential ingredients of genuine<br />
equality of opportunity.<br />
While growth is essential for progress towards the goals<br />
of Australian social democrats, it is not a goal that<br />
divides Australians politically. Our common interest in<br />
growth allows us to seek consensus on many issues of<br />
economic policy, through analysis of the effectiveness<br />
of policies in promoting growth.<br />
While economic growth is a platform upon which we can<br />
all stand, in a democratic society like Australia, many<br />
interest groups, and coalitions within the electorate,<br />
have the power to determine what is possible in the way<br />
oqf policy innovation legitimately, if often<br />
inconveniently, and sometimes outrageously, to the<br />
detriment of economic growth.<br />
I believe that a social democratic Government in<br />
Australia, a Labor Government is better able to appeal<br />
to the broad national interest in fairness, as well as<br />
the national interest in economic growth, to defeat<br />
vested interests and other barriers to progress.<br />
Various groups in society will use their democratic<br />
powers and rights to veto change that is essential for<br />
growth unless there is widespread acceptance and<br />
understanding that the benefits of growth are<br />
distributed equitably.<br />
For this condition to be met, there must be mechanismsoften<br />
fiscal and other mechanisms directed by Government<br />
to distribute equitably the benefits of growth. And<br />
there must also be mechanisms for community discussion<br />
and consultation within which widespread community </p>
<p>.4<br />
support if you like, consensus can be built for<br />
growth-oriented policies.<br />
So far, the Government's record stands up pretty well.<br />
This looks set to be the third successive year during<br />
which non-farm economic activity has expanded by 5 per<br />
cent or more. Non-farm growth did not reach 5 per cent<br />
during any one of our Liberal National Party<br />
predecessors' years in office. By the end of this year,<br />
the economy will have expanded more in three years than<br />
in seven and a half years under our predecessors.<br />
So far so good.<br />
But the real test is whether strong growth can be<br />
sustained over the long period necessary permanently to<br />
cut the evil of unemployment down to manageable<br />
proportions, and to give all Australians the higher<br />
living standards that our resources and skills have<br />
placed within our reach.<br />
Tonight I will describe some of our thinking about<br />
policies for growth; where we have got to in<br />
implementing new policies; and something of the agenda<br />
for future action. But first I would like to say<br />
something about where we have come from.<br />
Past Performance<br />
Even during what now seem to have been halcyon days of<br />
economic prosperity betweeen the end of the Second World<br />
War and the early 1970s, Australia's growth in real GDP<br />
per capita was unimpressive on a world scale.<br />
During the 1970s Australia's economic performance<br />
deteriorated markedly. Growth in real GDP per capita<br />
averaged only 1.3 per cent for the period 1973 to 1979<br />
and then a bare 0.1 per cent per annum between 1979 and<br />
1982. Simultaneously our inflation and unemployment<br />
rose sharply, proportionately more than in most OECD<br />
countries.<br />
The economic environment in Australia in the postwar<br />
period, and particularly since the early 1970s, has not<br />
been conducive to strong and sustained growth in our<br />
capital stock, employment and productivity.<br />
It is now clear that even the relatively modest growth<br />
performance of the 1950s and 1960s was purchased partly<br />
at the expense of future growth potential. A<br />
significant part of our growth in the early postwar<br />
decades derived from investment to supply protected<br />
domestic markets. The adverse consequences of this were<br />
not evident while the investment itself was taking </p>
<p>place. But it locked much of Australian industry into<br />
fragmented production, high costs, and insulation from<br />
competitive pressures.<br />
In other industrial countries, liberalisation of<br />
manufactured goods trade in the 1960s made these<br />
industries more sensitive to opportunities for expansion<br />
based on exports, for application of superior<br />
technology, and for managerial improvement more<br />
generally.<br />
We can all now see that the inward-looking postwar<br />
development strategies were a mistake.<br />
One of the lessons of the past decade is that we can no<br />
longer carry the costs of mistakes of this kind.<br />
The era of steady strong expansion of total world demand<br />
for the output of our most productive industries, for<br />
example in agriculture and mining, is long past.<br />
There are still opportunities for us in the<br />
international economy which, if utilised effectively,<br />
can support sustained strong growth at home.<br />
But we cannot rely on a rapidly growing world economy or<br />
the discovery of new natural resources to lift our<br />
performance sufficiently to make concerted inroads into<br />
unemployment while, at the same time, maintaining the<br />
living standards of the employed. If ever we were " The<br />
Lucky Country", we cannot afford to remain the<br />
Happy-go-. Lucky Country that Donald Homne described two<br />
decades ago. We must work to create our own success.<br />
Improving Australia's Performance<br />
Sustained strong growth requires consistent and mutually<br />
supportive macro-economic and resource allocation<br />
policies. Both are essential. Weakness in one can<br />
destroy any achievements in the other.<br />
Macroeconomic Environment<br />
The Labor Government set out to lift Australia's<br />
long-term performance at a time when there were major<br />
macro-economic imbalances in the economy.<br />
We deliberately turned our backs on prescriptions that<br />
depended on first correcting these imbalances. We<br />
deliberately rejected fighting inflation first.<br />
As the Treasurer likes to say, we set our sails for<br />
growth, believing that we could best address the<br />
structural imbalances in the process of on-going growth. </p>
<p>-6<br />
But we never did kid ourselves that the structural<br />
imbalances were unimportant.<br />
First, there was the huge prospective budget deficit<br />
amounting to about 5 per cent of prospective GDP for<br />
1983-84.<br />
Second, there was a lack of international<br />
competitiveness across large parts of our export and<br />
import-competing industries, reflecting the combined<br />
effects of entrenched high inflation, deliberate<br />
over-valuation of the Australian dollar ( as acknowledged<br />
by former Prime Minister Malcolm Fraser), and mediocre<br />
productivity performance.<br />
And reflecting all of these factors, there was a huge<br />
current account deficit, at 3.9 per cent of GDP in<br />
1982-83, one of the highest in the OECD, even when<br />
demand was exceptionally weak in the depths of<br />
recession. The large current account deficit was<br />
associated with increases in foriegn debt which<br />
threatened sooner or later to become unsustainable.<br />
Closely related to these structural weaknesses were high<br />
interest rates and high real unit labour costs,<br />
contributing to historically low rates of investment.<br />
All of these factors were in the minds of Paul Keating<br />
and myself, alongside the short-term foreign exchange<br />
crisis, when the dollar was devalued by 10 per cent two<br />
days afte ' r our election to office. Starting with a<br />
large current account deficit, our competitiveness had<br />
to improve if we were to get the economy moving with<br />
expansionary policies.<br />
Under the managed exchange rate system that we<br />
inherited, the initial depreciation did not hold. That<br />
pointed to a weakness in that system, which was removed<br />
decisively with the floating of the dollar in December<br />
1983.<br />
The floating dollar has facilitated the adjustments in<br />
competitiveness that were necessary to support sustained<br />
growth in the Australian economy at rates faster than in<br />
the rest of the world.<br />
Of course, dollar depreciation only converts a balance<br />
of payments problem into both a balance of payments and<br />
an inflation problem, without any sustained improvement<br />
in competitiveness, unless it is supported by moderate<br />
wages growth.<br />
The agreement announced yesterday between the A. C. T. tJ.<br />
and the Government provides the basis for the necessary </p>
<p>71<br />
wage moderation, including through discounting the 1985<br />
C. P. I. increases for indexation purposes by two<br />
percentage points, and delaying and moderating the<br />
claims made in the national productivity case.<br />
Moderate wages growth along these lines is absolutely<br />
necessary to the maintenance of strong growth in our<br />
current circumstances.<br />
Moderate wages growth along these lines is good for all<br />
Australians, but especially those who benefit directly<br />
from the creation of half a million jobs in three years<br />
and continued strong employment growth after that an<br />
economic benefit unrivalled in our history.<br />
Moderate wage growth along these lines represents an<br />
outcome that would be impossible under any alternative<br />
aproach to economic policy in Australia, without the<br />
Prices and Incomes Accord.<br />
The improvements in competitiveness resulting from<br />
depreciation and wage moderation should allow continued<br />
strengthening of the current account of the balance of<br />
payments in the course of strong growth.<br />
It was our confidence in the Accord that permitted us to<br />
embark on expansionary, growth-oriented fiscal and<br />
monetary policies when we came to office.<br />
But from the beginning, it was recognised that the large<br />
fiscal stimulus would need to be hauled in as recovery<br />
strengthened and broadened to the private sector. This<br />
is reflected in the progress we have made in reducing<br />
the budget deficit, by over half to little more than 2<br />
per cent of GDP in the two years to 1985-86.<br />
This progress on the Commonwealth deficit has been<br />
supported by co-operation with the States in the<br />
Premiers' Conference and Loan Council, to reduce the<br />
total public sector borrowing requirement as a<br />
proportion of GDP by over two and a half percentage<br />
points in two years.<br />
Monetary policy has been designed consistently to<br />
support strong growth but not any acceleration of<br />
inflation. The floating dollar has greatly assisted the<br />
implementation of monetary policy towards these<br />
objectives.<br />
Some doubts were expressed earlier this year about<br />
whether monetary policy really was consistent with our<br />
anti-inflationary objectives. The doubts derived<br />
mainly from the distortions that financial deregulation<br />
has introduced into measurement of the monetary<br />
aggregates. The Treasurer and I have put some effort<br />
into explaining our firm monetary policy in recent </p>
<p>8<br />
times, and the doubts have diminished.<br />
Events are vindicating our decision to address<br />
structural imbalances in the course of growth rather<br />
than as a precondition for expansionary policies.<br />
This is evident in the gains that have already been made<br />
on the Budget deficit and competitiveness. Real unit<br />
labour costs are back to the levels of one and a half<br />
decades ago. Interest rates remain high, but at least<br />
the pressures exerted by Government borrowing are<br />
diminishing. The framework of macro-economic policy that has been<br />
established, incorporating the Accord, the floating<br />
dollar and the Trilogy of fiscal commitments, are<br />
delivering settings of wages, monetary and fiscal policy<br />
that are consistent with sustained growth.<br />
It has also removed major areas of uncertainty and<br />
arbitrariness from crucial areas of macro-economic<br />
policy, and thus contributed to a more stable<br />
environment for investment and production decisions.<br />
Private investment remains too low, but is responding to<br />
the improved business environment.<br />
Micro-economic Environment<br />
In addition to the more stable macro-economic conditions<br />
to which I have already referred, there is no doubt that<br />
the low levels of disputation in the context of the<br />
Prices and Incomes Accord have allowed underlying<br />
economic realities to play their proper role in<br />
investment and production decisions.<br />
Most importantly of all, the dramatic recent<br />
improvements in international competitiveness provide<br />
Australia with a unique historical opportunity to lift<br />
its manufacturing and service sectors out of<br />
inward-looking production into the international<br />
economy.<br />
Beyond these ways in which macro-economic outcomes<br />
affect micro-economic performances, we are taking steps<br />
to: improve the environment for productivity growth,<br />
improve the efficiency and effectiveness of the<br />
public sector, and<br />
develop a more outward looking industry policy.<br />
While each of these may be examined separately there are<br />
a number of strong linkages between them. In the past </p>
<p>9<br />
the productivity performance of Australian industry has<br />
been substantially conditioned by an excessively inward<br />
orientation.<br />
The effect of this has been to mute the incentives to<br />
find and exploit world markets which have the greatest<br />
growth potential. It has impeded productivity growth<br />
and led to a decline in competitiveness. It has also<br />
discouraged the development of new products, new<br />
production techniques and new work practices.<br />
Finally it has discouraged flexibility and adaptation in<br />
the organisation of many of our industries.<br />
Introduction of these innovative and dynamic qualities<br />
will provide an impetus to productivity growth.<br />
At the same time industry policy has provided incentives<br />
to pursue profit opportunities by seeking to obtain the<br />
benefits of Government assistance, at the expense of the<br />
creation of new wealth through economically productive<br />
activities. IMPROVING THE ENVIRONMENT FOR PRODUCTIVITY GROWTH<br />
Human Capital Formation and Application<br />
The formation and application of human capital are vital<br />
elements in any strategy to improve and enhance our<br />
economic growth performance. Advances in these areas<br />
are intimately linked to the quality and flexibility of<br />
the labour which is available for use by industry : a<br />
workforce which is highly educated and trained will<br />
facilitate the development, adaptation and diffusion of<br />
more productive techniques and the more flexible and<br />
efficient utilisation of labour and capital by industry.<br />
Changes to our educational and vocational training<br />
systems are necessary. Major reforms initially will<br />
focus on the school sector.<br />
The Karmel Report has emphasised that changes in<br />
curricula, course content, progression and certification<br />
processes are needed if schools are adequately to<br />
fulfill their critical role in the nation's social and<br />
economic development.<br />
The Report acknowledges that a much greater proportion<br />
of young Australians have to complete full secondary<br />
schooling and receive a broad general education, if<br />
young people are to realise their potential and fulfill<br />
their key role in the further social, cultural and<br />
economic development of Australia. A broader school<br />
based education is essential. </p>
<p>The implementation crf Karmel's recommendations for the<br />
school system will complement our traineeship<br />
initiative, announced in the Budget. To complement both<br />
these measures my Government has taken action to reduce<br />
the chances that young people will be precluded for<br />
financial reasons from participating in post compulsory<br />
schooling or training.<br />
Supporting these initiatives, the Government has taken<br />
steps to increase the number of places and improve and<br />
increase the relevance of training within the TAFE<br />
sector and across the range of tertiary institutions.<br />
Innovation, Research and Development<br />
Innovation, technical progress and the development of<br />
export markets depends in large measure on Research and<br />
Development and technology transfer.<br />
Aggregate spending on R&amp; D in Australia is low. While<br />
the Government contribution is commensurate with other<br />
developed countries, industry funding and performance of<br />
R&amp; D is small. The proportion of research funds devoted<br />
to experimental development is low.<br />
Australia has some important advantages in research and<br />
devlopment activity. The education system produces<br />
capable research workers. The cost of R&amp; D in Australia<br />
is not high.<br />
To break down longstanding weaknesses in our applied<br />
research effort, for five years from 1 July this year,<br />
150 per cent of expenditure within Australia will be<br />
deductible for taxation purposes.<br />
We are seeking to improve the manner in which some of<br />
the direct public assistance is provided. Efforts are<br />
being made to increase interaction between industry and<br />
the public research institutions, such as CSIRO and<br />
universities. Remaining weaknesses in our applied technological effort<br />
have much to do with the past development of an inward<br />
looking industrial structure. This has dulled<br />
competitive pressures for adoption of superior<br />
technology. Labour Market<br />
We all agree that adaptable labour markets can assist in<br />
promoting efficient use of capital and labour resources<br />
and their more rapid accommodation to economic change.<br />
The setting of wage differentials has the potential to<br />
influence the efficiency and adaptability of the labour<br />
market. But flexibility in these differentials is less </p>
<p>important the more mobile and flexible is the labour<br />
force itself.<br />
In contemplating labour market reform, we are wise to<br />
recognise that increased wage flexibility contains a<br />
real risk of destabilising aggregate wages and the<br />
conduct of macroeconomic policy. If necessary, we are<br />
prepared to give away the small advantages of marginally<br />
increased relative wage flexibility to preserve the<br />
greater benefit of overall wage moderation.<br />
Taxation and Growth<br />
In the first of my trifecta of Economic Society speeches<br />
this year, to the Canberra Branch in March, I said that<br />
tax reform directed towards improvement in our growth<br />
performance must come to grips with four flaws in the<br />
current taxation system.<br />
To quote from that speech, which was published in the<br />
Economic Record in June:<br />
"[ The tax review] must address the widespread<br />
avoidance and evasion, especially by people with<br />
income well above the Australian average it<br />
must address poverty traps The tax review<br />
must address the unfairness and the associated<br />
effects on work effort of workers on average<br />
incomes paying the current 46 per cent marginal tax<br />
rate on incomes above $ 19,500.<br />
And the review must address the powerful<br />
distortions to resource allocation inherent in a<br />
per cent marginal tax rate cutting in at less than<br />
twice average weekly earnings, within a system that<br />
provides ways for turning taxable income into<br />
untaxed benefits."<br />
While the Government's preferred option did not survive<br />
the Tax Summit, the tax package to be announced soon<br />
will make substantial progess towards these objectives.<br />
It will significantly improve the environment for<br />
economic growth in Australia.<br />
IMPROVING THE EFFICIENCY AND EFFECTIVENESS OF THE PUBLIC<br />
SECTOR Quite apart from its role in establishing the<br />
macro-economic and regulatory environment, the public<br />
sector is such an important feature of the Australian<br />
economy that the efficiency of its own operations has<br />
significant implications for our overall economic<br />
performance. I believe that this Government has gone further than any </p>
<p>12<br />
of its predecessors in scrutinising public expenditures,<br />
with a view to testing their contribution to improved<br />
efficiency in the economy, and improved equity.<br />
The issue of efficiency in public expenditure is<br />
separate from the issue of size. Nevertheless, as a<br />
Government which believes that public expenditure is<br />
necessary for progress towards its key objectives, we<br />
have found the constraints that the trilogy commitments<br />
have imposed on size useful in concentrating attention<br />
on efficiency.<br />
Finance Minister Peter Walsh has made several detailed<br />
statements on our approach so far, and I do not have<br />
time tonight to traverse that ground.<br />
But I believe that I can assert that this year's budget,<br />
with the lowest growth in real outlays for six years,<br />
and reducing the share of Commonwealth expenditure by a<br />
full percentage point, has contributed more to genuine<br />
equity than many more expansive budgets in past years.<br />
The efficiency of public enterprises is also a major<br />
factor in the overall performance of the Australian<br />
economy. Significant progress has been made in rationalising<br />
activites and reducing costs in several major<br />
Commonwealth commercial enterprises. This is the real<br />
task. The issue of " privatisation" is a diversion from<br />
this task.<br />
Commonwealth public enterprises are quantitatively less<br />
important than those of the States.<br />
In recent years the Australian community has been more<br />
critical of charges for electricity, rail and other<br />
services provided by the States, as well as by the<br />
Commonwealth. This is a promising development.<br />
I believe that the Commonwealth Government has<br />
contributed to this change in the climate of community<br />
opinion. We have also made direct representations to<br />
the States on these issues.<br />
One result is a substantially lower rate of increase in<br />
charges, through containment of costs, without increases<br />
in the deficits of State enterprises. </p>
<p>1.3<br />
TOWARDS A MORE DYNAMIC AND OUTWARD LOOKING ECONOMY<br />
It will be clear from what I have already said that I<br />
attach prime importance to increasing the international<br />
orientation of the Australian economy.<br />
Major progress has been made in these last two years,<br />
and the continuation of progress will be a major focus<br />
of our efforts in the years ahead.<br />
our work in this area has many inter-related strands.<br />
One strand is the re-orientation of Australian business,<br />
trade union and community attitudes towards greater<br />
awareness of international opportunities.<br />
I have seen this as one of my special responsibilities<br />
as Prime Minister, and have pursued it in every possible<br />
forum at home and abroad.<br />
It has been assisted by discussion within the Economic<br />
Planning Advisory Council and the Australian<br />
Manufacturing Council.<br />
Community attitudes had begun to change in favourable<br />
ways some years ago, but there has been a major<br />
acceleration under this Government.<br />
A second strand has been the reform of the regulatory<br />
environment which had placed so many inhibitions on<br />
international transactions in the past.<br />
The abolition of exchange controls at the time we<br />
floated the dollar had far-reaching implications for<br />
trade, the full extent of which is poorly understood.<br />
It facilitated the development of new hedging<br />
arrangements, which reduced the risk of specialisation<br />
in production for export.<br />
The floating of the dollar itself reduced uncertainty in<br />
production for export, by providing greater confidence<br />
that any movements in Australian costs that were out of<br />
line with international developments would be<br />
counteracted by currency depreciation.<br />
The entry of new banks with foreign equity, and the<br />
internationalisation of the operations of established<br />
Australian banks, are widening the channels through<br />
which Australian producers are informed of export<br />
opportunities. We have also taken significant steps towards<br />
liberalisation of import trade. Our approach so far has </p>
<p>14<br />
been to address issues industry by industry.<br />
The plans for the passenger motor vehicle, textile,<br />
clothing, footwear and steel industries all involve<br />
substantial liberalisation.<br />
The decisions to use bounties, rather than tariffs, to<br />
protect the production of steel, agricultural<br />
harvesters, machine tools and computers improve the form<br />
and visibility of assistance to those activities.<br />
The deregulation, proposed or underway, of the marketing<br />
arrangements for milk and dairy products, eggs and dried<br />
vine fruit will reduce assistance to industries which<br />
have been very highly protected in the past. The<br />
voluntary restraints on the exports of colour television<br />
sets to this country were abolished last year.<br />
In the service sector, our new guidelines for the<br />
provision of education services to overseas students on<br />
a fee-paying basis open the way for the devlopment of a<br />
new export industry.<br />
The progress in some of these areas has been<br />
considerable.<br />
The removal, on 1 January 1984, of the temporary import<br />
quotas imposed on a range of steel products in 1982, was<br />
a major break from the earlier Australian experience<br />
with temporary quotas becoming permanent. Together with<br />
other elements of the industry plan, it has helped to<br />
make steel production in Australia internationally<br />
competitive, and has opened prospects for expansion<br />
through exports.<br />
Since the mid-1970s, the greatest problems of high<br />
protection in Australia have been in the textiles<br />
clothing and footwear and passenger motor vehicle<br />
industries.<br />
In these industries, improvements in Australia's general<br />
competitive position through depreciation, gradual<br />
liberalisation of imports, and major rationalisation and<br />
increased productivity at home have substantially<br />
reduced protection over the last year.<br />
This is reflected in large reductions in the premium<br />
paid on quota sold by tender.<br />
The third strand in our efforts to increase the<br />
international orientation of Australian industry has<br />
been our active trade policy, designed to build a<br />
climate of confidence in which Australian and overseas<br />
enterprises can interact with each other. </p>
<p>15<br />
Some of our activities have been defensive, as we have<br />
sought to minimise the damage that the trade policies of<br />
the European Economic Community has imposed on our<br />
efficient rural industries, and to ward off United<br />
States pressures upon Japan to divert imports from<br />
efficient Australian suppliers.<br />
The representations that john Kerin and I made in<br />
Brussels early this year were successful in holding the<br />
line against subsidised European beef in our established<br />
Western Pacific markets. We can be reasonably satisfied<br />
with the way Japan has maintained the international<br />
trade rules against bilateral pressures, although we<br />
would like to have done better with beef.<br />
More positively, we have invested considerable effort in<br />
building confidence in trading relationships within our<br />
own region. I myself have been closely involved in<br />
discussions on trade with Heads of Government in all<br />
major countries in our region.<br />
There has been special progress in our relationship with<br />
China. We have been working to build new layers to our<br />
trading relationship with Japan as Japanese industry's<br />
appetite for raw materials has become less voracious.<br />
Significant steps have been taken to build closer<br />
economic ties with the ASEAN countries, the Republic of<br />
Korea, and the developing countries of the South Pacific<br />
Forum. Like the ASEAN countries, we have had to think<br />
about possible responses to suggestions for new free<br />
trade areas that have emanated from the office of the<br />
Special Trade Representative in the United States.<br />
We have established a firm base from which to use<br />
effectively the new competitiveness conferred by the<br />
depreciation of the dollar and the associated commitment<br />
to wage moderation.<br />
The circumstances have come together for us to make now<br />
a permanent break over these next few years with the<br />
inward-looking policies that have been holding us back.<br />
With a new round of Multilateral Trade Negotiations<br />
( MTN) on the horizon, we need to prepare ourselves to<br />
contribute to its successful progression. Admittedly<br />
the benefits we have obtained from previous MTN rounds<br />
have not been encouraging. But this was due in<br />
considerable measure to our lack of credibility in<br />
arguing for general trade liberalisation while seeking<br />
to maintain our own trade barriers.<br />
One of the ways in which we have been preparing for a<br />
new round of negotiations is through the regional<br />
consultations amongst Western Pacific countries which </p>
<p>16<br />
followed suggestions that I made in a speech in Bangkok<br />
in November 1983. The third regional meeting of Senior<br />
Trade officials will take place in Seoul next week.<br />
There is general agreement within the region that these<br />
consultations have been helpful in identifying regional<br />
interests and opportunities for co-operation.<br />
A demonstrated commitment to continue steadily with<br />
domestic liberalisation will greatly add to our<br />
credibility and negotiating position in any MTN round.<br />
Such an approach could be complemented by a preparedness<br />
to pursue trade policy initiatives involving particular<br />
countries or products.<br />
The continuation of domestic liberalisation is in any<br />
case fully justified by the domestic benefits,<br />
independently of the trade policy rewards which it makes<br />
possible. Consistently with our established approach, further<br />
liberalisation, whether it were within a program of<br />
general reductions in assistance or industry by<br />
industry, would be gradual, would be complemented by<br />
appropriate adjustment measures, and might need to be<br />
supported by positive measures to encourage expansion of<br />
more productive activities.<br />
Conclus ions<br />
We have come a long way in these last two and a half<br />
years, but we do not delude ourselves that we are near<br />
the end of our journey.<br />
A new approach to macro-economic policy, based on<br />
fighting inflation and unemployment at the same time<br />
within the framework of the Prices and Incomes Accord,<br />
has brought back strong growth after a decade of<br />
stagnation and decline.<br />
The return of growth has given Australians the heart to<br />
tackle longstanding structural impediments to growth.<br />
We have begun the huge task of reform, guided by our<br />
recognition of the reality that if change is to be<br />
substantial and permanent, it must be gradual, its<br />
consequences must be well understood in the community,<br />
and the whole structure of social and economic policy<br />
must care for Australians who are unable to defend<br />
themselves in the market place.<br />
As I have said, by the end of this year the Australian<br />
economy will have expanded more in three years than in<br />
the preceding eight years. </p>
<p>17<br />
Our current forecasts suggest that by the time the Labor<br />
Government has been in office half as long as its<br />
predecessor, it will have presided over the creation of<br />
twice as many jobs.<br />
But we must go further yet.<br />
The Labor Government, and this generation of<br />
Australians, must expect to be judged in history not by<br />
our success in promoting three or five years of economic<br />
growth stronger than the rest of the world.<br />
The final test of our worth is whether we succeed,<br />
gradually but inexorably, in so transforming the<br />
environment of economic life in Australia, that<br />
sustained growth becomes entrenched, even in these<br />
difficult times for the world economy.<br />
On our performance so far, I reckon that Stan Kelly<br />
would expect us to pass this test. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
