<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10745</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                PRESS CONFERENCE                JERVOISE BAY INDUSTRIAL INFRASTRUCTURE &amp;amp; HARBOUR DEVELOPMENT ANNOUNCEMENT,                JERVOISE BAY, WESTERN AUSTRALIA</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/01/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE....................................................</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p> Thank you very much Hendy Cowan, and the Premier. I don't know</p>
<p> that there's an enormous amount I want to add to what I said</p>
<p> in there. I'm greatly relieved that there are some technical</p>
<p> people here to answer some of the more technical questions, but I</p>
<p> just want to emphasise that it's not only the substance but also</p>
<p> the symbolism of our commitment to this project that's very important.</p>
<p>The Federation Fund was all about national projects of lasting significance</p>
<p> and the project that we've chosen for the first allocation of</p>
<p> support in Western Australia, that's the Jervoise Bay project,</p>
<p> is very much in that category because nothing is of more lasting significance</p>
<p> to Western Australia and to the nation than the resource sector of</p>
<p> this state, the ship building capacity of this state is rapidly becoming</p>
<p> legend and it is making a huge contribution, and to underpin the infrastructure</p>
<p> in the way that this project will do will be of enormous benefit and</p>
<p> it will provide a diversification of the skills base of the area.</p>
<p> It is a diverse infrastructure project. It's not just oil and</p>
<p> gas. It's ship building, it's high tech, it's skills</p>
<p> development and it fits the bill of the infrastructure projects and</p>
<p> it's a very appropriate project to be announced on Australia</p>
<p> Day and I know how much it will please the Deputy Premier because</p>
<p> it's something that's been very dear to his heart for a</p>
<p> very long time.</p>
<p>I can see a smiling Deputy Premier and smiling members of his Department.</p>
<p> I don't want to really say anything more by way of general comment</p>
<p> about it than that.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, it's not a technical question but how do you</p>
<p> personally feel about the concerns of the people out there who say</p>
<p> that this will ruin this stretch of coastline?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It won't. I mean, that's the sort of over the top criticism</p>
<p> of development that does the genuine cause of environmental concern</p>
<p> in Australia a great disservice. We have a process that's already</p>
<p> been initiated by the Western Australian Government to make sure that</p>
<p> those legitimate concerns of environmentalists are met. I mean, we're</p>
<p> not in the business ever of pillaging the environment but we are in</p>
<p> the business of generating jobs and we tried very hard and pretty</p>
<p> successfully to get a balance and that's what Australians want.</p>
<p> They want to look after the environment and they want jobs and they</p>
<p> want development, and you can have all three if you are sensible.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, isn't this just pork-barrelling in the lead up to</p>
<p> the 1998 election?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It would be pork-barrelling if it made no contribution to the future.</p>
<p> That's what pork-barrelling is. Pork-barrelling is when you throw</p>
<p> money after useless projects of transient political importance but</p>
<p> of no lasting benefit to the nation. Now, you only have to look at</p>
<p> this project to realise the description, pork-barrelling, is monstrously</p>
<p> inappropriate. It's almost obscenely inappropriate.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, are you confident of industrial harmony at the site?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I am very confident of industrial harmony and while I am on the subject</p>
<p> of industrial harmony, I saw a bit of paper the other day that in</p>
<p> 1996, the level of industrial disputes in Australia was the lowest</p>
<p> it had been since 1940. In other words, in 1996, the first year of</p>
<p> the Coalition Government, and here in Western Australia in partnership</p>
<p> with a Coalition Government that has done a lot of tremendous work</p>
<p> in industrial reform, first class work in industrial reform, you've</p>
<p> had a 56 year record chalked up so far as a low level of industrial</p>
<p> disputes are concerned. One of the reasons I am very confident is</p>
<p> that the responsible union leadership in this state realises that</p>
<p> it's projects like this that will generate jobs. At the end of</p>
<p> the day, good, intelligent, responsible union leadership wants jobs</p>
<p> for Australians, and this job will generate jobs for Australians and</p>
<p> that's tremendously important.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>(Inaudible)</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, the State Government made a contribution and the private sector</p>
<p> is making a contribution.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, on another matter, Pauline Hanson has criticised the</p>
<p> awarding of Young Australian of the Year and Australian of the Year</p>
<p> to Tan Le and Cathy Freeman respectively. She says it's politically</p>
<p> motivated.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I've heard those remarks. I must say I thought they were not</p>
<p> only inaccurate, they were stupid, they were petty and they're</p>
<p> very divisive remarks being made on Australia Day. Neither of those</p>
<p> awards was the gift of the Federal Government or of any State Government.</p>
<p> Both awards were made by an independent committee. I was informed</p>
<p> of the committee's choices in each case shortly before the announcements</p>
<p> were made. Let me say, I think both of them were excellent choices</p>
<p> and I heard Mrs Hanson's remarks on Perth radio this morning.</p>
<p> They were wildly inaccurate and petty in the extreme. Cathy Freeman's</p>
<p> speech yesterday here in Perth accepting the award was a speech in</p>
<p> which she rejoiced in the fact that she was an Australian and that</p>
<p> she was naturally and properly and understandably proud of her Aboriginal</p>
<p> heritage. Her speech was nothing like what it was described as this</p>
<p> morning by Mrs Hanson on radio and I really think it is a very regrettable,</p>
<p> inappropriate, ugly intervention on Australia Day without any basis</p>
<p> and fact and it's a charge that I completely and utterly reject</p>
<p> in relation to both awards. I think they are both magnificent young</p>
<p> Australians of whom all of us can be immensely proud.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, Cathy Freeman is quoted this morning as supporting</p>
<p> those who are calling for an apology for the stolen generation. What</p>
<p> do you say to that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think her remarks were very understandable.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Also the protesters at your breakfast speech, did you get a message</p>
<p> from those people?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, not particularly, no. I thought it was a very civilised gathering</p>
<p> this morning.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>If Cathy Freeman's remarks are very understandable, does that</p>
<p> give any more sway to the Government's decision not to apologise?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No I think we've stated our position. I think her remarks are</p>
<p> understandable.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, Michael Cobb has decided to quit politics at the next election.</p>
<p> Has he done the right thing?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p> Well, it's always the right thing when you decide where your</p>
<p> future is going to be. I mean, politics is never forever for anybody</p>
<p> and he has decided to retire. I want to thank Michael for the contribution</p>
<p> that he's made as the Federal Member for a very difficult electorate.</p>
<p> He's been a great Member of the National Party . He won a seat,</p>
<p> if any of you understand the political history of that seat, that's</p>
<p> the seat that includes the city of Broken Hill and it's been</p>
<p> held by the National Party in the Federal Parliament for a number</p>
<p> of years and it's quite a remarkable achievement and I wish him</p>
<p> well but it's his decision and I mean, this business of having</p>
<p> a seminar every time somebody decides to retire from politics, or</p>
<p> enter it, is ridiculous. He's decided to go, he's had a</p>
<p> long stint and he's going and I am quite sure that the National</p>
<p> Party will find a very good replacement and the Government will hold</p>
<p> the seat. I will certainly be campaigning to ensure that the Government</p>
<p> does hold the seat.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Will he be a loss to the Government?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think he's made a good contribution to the National Party and</p>
<p> to the Government and I am sorry to see him go and I wish him well.</p>
<p> I particularly admire the contribution that he made to debate inside</p>
<p> the National Party on economic issues through the 1980s. He was a</p>
<p> very strong proponent of sensible economic policies and he was a very</p>
<p> strong proponent of a sensible approach to some of the more divisive</p>
<p> element that occurred in the Coalition in the 1980s and I will be</p>
<p> sorry he's no longer a Member. I can understand why he's</p>
<p> going.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>There are claims, or what do you say to claims that his decision is</p>
<p> more about protecting his superannuation?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look, you can go and talk to other people about that. I don't</p>
<p> know anything about that.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, this morning you spoke about a republic and you spoke</p>
<p> about the symbols changing. What symbols were you referring to?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, what I was talking about... well, if you want to ask me about</p>
<p> the flag, I think I've made it perfectly clear. I don't</p>
<p> favour any changes to the Australian flag.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What symbols were you referring to?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I was talking about symbols generally and what I was saying was that</p>
<p> a nation has, a nation has symbols and a nation also has its substance</p>
<p> and I think both things are important but the substance of a nation,</p>
<p> the character of a nation and what a nation stands for is even more</p>
<p> important than its symbols. Now I think we can debate symbols, we</p>
<p> can debate the flag - it's a free country and if Australians</p>
<p> vote for change to the flag well, it will change. I can tell you,</p>
<p> I am not in favour of change. I can see no argument for change. I</p>
<p> have never seen a flag that comes half anywhere near approaching the</p>
<p> present Australian flag. I am just uncomplicatedly opposed to any</p>
<p> change in the flag.</p>
<p>As far as the republic is concerned, we will be debating that in the</p>
<p> Convention. I gave a very detailed speech in Melbourne on Friday setting</p>
<p> out my conditions. I am totally opposed to an elected Presidency.</p>
<p> I think that would destroy the present Parliamentary system. I think</p>
<p> the present system works extremely well. A lot of people want change.</p>
<p> Let's talk about it and at the end of the day, let's put</p>
<p> it to the Australian people because they will decide these things.</p>
<p> It's a democracy and they will decide the future of this country.</p>
<p> For my part, I see no merit at all in having a new Australian flag.</p>
<p> I think the present one is perfectly acceptable.</p>
<p>No matter what flag or symbol you have, not everybody will agree with</p>
<p> it. We had a vote 20 years ago about a national song and not everybody</p>
<p> voted for Advance Australia Fair but the majority did, so it's</p>
<p> the... I mean, you don't get too worked up about these things.</p>
<p> People have their view. We have a debate, we have a vote and then</p>
<p> it's resolved.</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
<p>[ENDS]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
