<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7486</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER FEDERATION OF PAKISTAN CHAMBERS OF COMMERCE AND INDUSTRY KARACHI - 8 FEBRUARY 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/02/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007486.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
FEDERATION OF PAKISTAN CHAMBERS OF COMMERCE AND INDUSTRY<br />
KARACHI 8 FEBRUARY 1989<br />
Tariq Sayeed, President,<br />
Vice-Presidents. Secretary-General and distinguished members<br />
of the Federation of Pakistan Chambers of Commerce and<br />
Industry,<br />
Ladies and gentlemen,<br />
I am very pleased to be here today, on my first visit to this<br />
vibrant city of Karachi. it is hard to believe that on this<br />
place, one hundred and fifty years ago, stood a small fishing<br />
village. Karachi has played a central role in the growth of this<br />
nation as the first capital of the newly independent Pakistan<br />
from 1947 to 1963.<br />
And above all, Karachi is a trading centre, the largest city<br />
in Pakistan and the hub of the nation's commercial life. As<br />
such, the future vitality of this city is closely linked to<br />
the success of Pakistan in advancing its commercial interests<br />
and in developingx its trading relationship with countries<br />
like Australia.<br />
SSo it is a very great pleasure to be here today and to<br />
discuss our shared trading future with the Karachi members of<br />
the FPCCI.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen,<br />
I would like to speak about two of the challenges that we<br />
face first, our obligation to reform the international<br />
trading system that is stacked against the interests of<br />
efficient agricultural producing economies such as Australia<br />
and Pakistan, and second, our opportunities to build a more<br />
substantial trading relationship between us.<br />
With che impasse reached iii the recent talks in Montreal, we<br />
face a very real crisis. The intransigence of the major<br />
developed economies the United States and the European<br />
Community must over the next few months be replaced by<br />
greater flexibility. </p>
<p>I was heartened to hear yesterday the Pakistani Government<br />
reaffirm its concurrence with the view that the system that<br />
has allowed four decades of export-led global prosperity<br />
will, unless action is taken, be in jeopardy.<br />
We cannot allow that to happen. We must achieve a freer<br />
international trade system.<br />
Australia's efforts, and those of other miembers of the Cairns<br />
Group, have sought to bring long--term advantages to all<br />
agricultural exporting countries, including those in the<br />
developing world. It is a task of fundamental importance for<br />
all those who seek to build global and national prosperity.<br />
Meantime, we must tackle our other challenge building our<br />
bilateral economic relationship.<br />
* Clearly, we can do much to develop what is at present a<br />
modest two-way trade. We should be creative and<br />
forward-looking i~ n identifying new opportunities for such<br />
development. We in Australia are seeking to lessen our reliance on<br />
commodity trade and to diversify our export base to emphasise<br />
manufactured goods, services and technology.<br />
Pakistan is moving in the same direction.<br />
So there are tremendous commercial opportunities for both our<br />
countries beyond the traditional commodities that currently<br />
make up the bulk of our trade.<br />
Australia, for instance, already has an expertise in<br />
high-technology areas such as telecommunications, energy and<br />
animal husbandry which are among the development priorities<br />
for your country.<br />
OAustralian business is already well represented in Pakistan<br />
by the ANZ Banking Corporation, owner of Grindlays, the<br />
biggest foreign banking chain on the subcontinent.<br />
Australian companies have recently put forward proposals for<br />
other activities in Pakistan, including two substantial<br />
projects involving technology transfer.<br />
Telecom Australia is seeking to establish an optical fibre<br />
link between Rawalpindi and Karachi, and the Overseas<br />
Projects Corporation of Victoria, together with Phillips<br />
( Australia) is seeking to install a computerised traffic<br />
system in Karachi.<br />
We are exploring through AUSTRADE whether we can become<br />
involved in the Port Qasim redevelopment. </p>
<p>But Australian efforts in developing commercial relations<br />
with Pakistan are not only focussed on pursuing market<br />
opportunities in your country. We are also assisting<br />
Pakistani enterprises to promote their products to Australia<br />
for example through a trade display focusing on textiles<br />
and clothing held at the International Trade Development<br />
Centres in Sydney and Melbourne last year. Another display,<br />
of engineering products, is to be staged later this year.<br />
It is in recognition of the scope of the business that we can<br />
do that we are expanding our efforts, here in Karachi, by<br />
upgrading the AUSTRADE office in this city.<br />
Prime Minister Bhutto and I yesterday discussed the<br />
desirability of a bilateral trade agreement, and we decided<br />
to begin negotiations forthwith.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen,<br />
These initiatives indicate Australia's enthusiasm to meet the<br />
challenge of developing our economic relationship with<br />
Pakistan. From my discussions with the Government of<br />
Pakistan, I know that they share our commitment to expanding<br />
commercial activity between our two countries.<br />
I was very pleased to hear Prime Minister Bhutto's suggestion<br />
yesterday that a group of Australian businessmen should visit<br />
Pakistan to explore the many commercial opportunities that<br />
exist. I undertook to encourage such a mission and indeed I<br />
certainly expect it will take place later this year.<br />
In the end, the private sector in both countries will<br />
determine the success of our efforts.<br />
Good business, like a good political relationship, is based<br />
on making opportunities, not letting them pass by.<br />
SThe Pakistan Chambers of Commerce and Industry have an<br />
important role to play. We need you to apply to this task<br />
the same commitment and energy that has traditionally<br />
characterised this great city.<br />
I </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
