<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3576</transcript-id>
    <title>THE NETHERLANDS - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER OF THE NETHERLANDS, MR JOOP DEN UYL, AT A DINNER GIVEN IN HONOUR OF THE PRIME MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA IN THE HAGUE ON 4 JANUARY 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/01/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003576.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
The Netherlands<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister of the Netherlands, MrJoop den Uyl,<br />
at a dinner given in honour of the<br />
The Hagueon 4January 1975<br />
The honour and the pleasure of receiving you in<br />
the Netherlands, Mr Prime Minister, Mrs<br />
Whitlam and our other distinguished Australian<br />
guests, is due, no doubt, to the close relations<br />
between our countries and co-operation in various<br />
international fields. May I add that the<br />
pleasure of receiving you at this very moment<br />
has perhaps also something to do with the fact<br />
that there are similarities in the situation of your<br />
Government, Mr Prime Minister, and that of<br />
mine. I am not referring to the fact that some people<br />
have written to you in the past few months that<br />
we had a crisis every week. And I will not suggest<br />
that you are having the same experience.<br />
But there are some resemblances in the situation<br />
of your government and that of mine and I<br />
will point those out later on.<br />
Well, the relationship between our countries<br />
goes back much further than the recent past. I<br />
need not remind you of this. You all know the<br />
Dutch discovered Tasmania, and well we know<br />
you had at least discovered this country before<br />
your present visit, and I am very happy about<br />
that. Well, turning to the Australia of today, we<br />
know that about 150,000 Netherlands<br />
nationals have settled there since 1950, and<br />
have forged even closer ties between us than in<br />
the past. These Dutch immigrants face with you<br />
the tremendous challenges of terrain, climate<br />
and distance in the development of national<br />
resources. If I am not mistaken we were the first<br />
non-Commonwealth country to conclude an<br />
immigration agreement with you. And to be<br />
frank, I feel a little proud that most of my fellow<br />
countrymen have succesfully adapted themselves<br />
to their new surroundings. In fact-I<br />
think-the greater part have adopted Australian Prime Minister of Australia in<br />
citizenship. And, well, some people think that a<br />
Dutchman begins to be a very noble man if he<br />
stops being a Dutchman, so there must be every<br />
hope for you, having so many Dutch people<br />
naturalised as Australians today. I hope and<br />
trust these people continue to be an asset to<br />
both our countries. Important as this may be,<br />
there is more to link our countries in the<br />
present-day world, in spite of the physical distance<br />
that separates us.<br />
With the advent of regular air communications<br />
shortly after the end of the second World War,<br />
there have been numerous contacts during the<br />
period when both our countries were undergoing<br />
a fundamental economic, political and social<br />
transformation. For all the gaps and misconceptions<br />
that inevitably remain, we do know in this<br />
country that Australia is no longer primarily an<br />
exporter of agricultural produce and wool. And,<br />
even, not only the country of kangaroos. We<br />
know that, in addition to strengthening its position<br />
as a supplier of raw materials, Australia has<br />
developed a powerful and sophisticated industrial<br />
base, able to hold its own with other leading<br />
industrial nations.<br />
Dutch enterprise and capital have had a part in<br />
this development. We realise it has been a<br />
modest part. Perhaps too modest. We would<br />
welcome a greater participation in your economy<br />
and this morning we have already discussed<br />
ways to achieve that goal. Both our<br />
countries have had to meet serious challenges.<br />
Australia's outlook and interests were conditioned<br />
by its ties with the British Commonwealth,<br />
its vast geographical area and the<br />
tremendous hardships encountered and overcome<br />
in its initial development. The 33 </p>
<p>Netherlands outlook was conditioned by its<br />
position as a geographically small but densely<br />
populated country in Europe with extensive<br />
overseas dominions. The very fact that we are<br />
such a densely populated country may explain<br />
for example why conservation policies, environ<br />
mental pollution, our concern about scarcity of<br />
national resources, our conviction that new<br />
ways should be opened up in that field are so<br />
much stressed in this country and in its policies<br />
today. Looking to the future from our present postition,<br />
we find ever increasing commercial and political<br />
links within the European Community, of which<br />
the Netherlands forms an intrinsic part. Yet<br />
mental attitudes and world-wide economic<br />
interests inherited from our recent past make us<br />
pay special attention to the relations of Europe<br />
to the outside world. We-I venture to say-we<br />
can always be counted upon to oppose trends<br />
that would make Europe into a closed entity,<br />
turning a blind eye to the problems of others. Hence our special concern for developing countries,<br />
but also for countries like Australia, which<br />
feel that their interests are bound up with those<br />
of the world community.<br />
Both our countries are seeking today a new<br />
social order in our domestic policies and in international<br />
policies. The Government you lead,<br />
Mr Prime Minister, came to power as a result of<br />
the elections of-I believe it was-2 December<br />
1 972. Well, that is something to be jealous of.-<br />
You took over on 5 December. The Government<br />
I represent in the Netherlands was a somewhat<br />
delayed result of the elections of 29 November<br />
1 972, three days before yours, but it took<br />
nearly six months, it was 11 May, before I could<br />
say: I have achieved the same results as you did<br />
after three days. Well, what we might have in<br />
common is a desire to reform and remould society,<br />
but perhaps also a sense of instability.<br />
You had to face the electorate again in May of<br />
last year. I only had to face criticism in Parliament<br />
and in the press but I watched you, you<br />
The Prime Minister of the Netherlands, Mr den Uyl, presiding over talks in The Hague.<br />
M' VC. a I<br />
F . K7~ 7I<br />
34 </p>
<p>are accustomed to peril like me. You have<br />
brought about quite a few changes in the<br />
foreign policy of Australia. You have embarked<br />
on the work for a wider and genuinely represen<br />
tative regional association. In the United<br />
Nations you have adopted an attitude on ' apartheid'<br />
in South Africa broadly in line with that of<br />
Third World countries. You have speeded up<br />
the process of national independence for Papua<br />
New Guinea. The Australian Labor Government<br />
has committed itself to an aid target of 0.7 per<br />
cent of Australia's GNP in the coming decade.<br />
Australia has joined with India, Sri Lanka and<br />
other countries of the region in pressing for the<br />
Indian Ocean to be declared a Nuclear Free<br />
Zone. You have emphasised to the world that<br />
there are Nations of the Pacific and that as such<br />
they have a direct interest in the purpose for<br />
which the ocean is used. You have recognised<br />
the Chinese People's Republic and the North<br />
Viet-Nam government.<br />
In summing up all this, all these changes you<br />
were striving for in foreign policy, I recognise<br />
much of what the Government I represent is<br />
striving for. And it is in many ways surprising to<br />
discover that your Government-acting as it did<br />
from December 72-and my Government acting<br />
from May 73, have been striving to achieve<br />
the same goals in international development.<br />
The Dutch Government has committed itself to<br />
a development aid target of 1.2 per cent of GNP<br />
to be reached in 1976. We are conscious that it<br />
is a very hard road, it is a very ambitious target,<br />
but we think it is necessary to reach it, in our<br />
position in Western Europe and in the world.<br />
We seek to create a critical solidarity in crossing<br />
the bridge between industrial and developing<br />
countries. We want to be a critical member of<br />
NATO, accepting our fundamental partnership<br />
in the Western world and pressing at the same<br />
time for common goals in co-operation with<br />
non-aligned and Third World countries. We<br />
know that there are limits to change. Limits to<br />
change in foreign policy, too, and in the possibilities<br />
of international co-operation. You, Mr<br />
Prime Minister, have been working in political<br />
life for more than a quarter of a century. You<br />
were a Member of Parliament for twenty years<br />
and people experienced in parliamentary life<br />
know that policies of change can only be<br />
realised within small margins. And for my part, I<br />
think that that is political reality and we have to be aware of it. We in this country often speak<br />
about the controversy between North and<br />
South in the world, as being of no less importance<br />
than the controversy between East and<br />
West. It is a good thing ( for us) to know that in<br />
the South there are Western countries-Australia,<br />
New Zealand-which might contribute<br />
substantially to overcoming that controversy<br />
between North and South.<br />
I might add a few words about what that might<br />
mean in our present situation. Today a very<br />
serious challenge faces us both. I am referring to<br />
the energy crisis and the problems connected<br />
with it. Both your country and mine are in a<br />
relatively favourable position as regards energy<br />
resources. But we do not propose to make use of<br />
this position in a grasping, selfish way. It is our<br />
conviction that no country can be permanently<br />
prosperous in a world where the great majority<br />
live in poverty and even in acute hardship. The<br />
same principle of fair shares for all which guides<br />
us within our national boundaries will guide us<br />
in our efforts to lessen the gap in prosperity between<br />
us and the developing countries. That is<br />
why, whatever the difficulties facing us, we<br />
shall not relax our efforts to contribute to the<br />
development of the Third World.<br />
Mr Prime Minister, we have worked closely<br />
together as nations on numerous issues, in the<br />
United Nations and in other international<br />
organisations, with a view to creating conditions<br />
for a better world for all humanity to live in.<br />
When you return to your own country I should<br />
like you to take back this message: There is a<br />
country in Europe, far away across oceans and<br />
continents, which looks upon the world much as<br />
you do, which has stood by at the birth of your<br />
nation and which values numerous precious ties<br />
with it. A country, in short, which is and wants<br />
to remain a friend: the Netherlands. </p>
<p>Speech by the Prime Minister of Australia at a dinner given in his<br />
honour by the Prime Minister of the Netherlands in The Hague on<br />
4 January 1975<br />
I have had frequent occasion on my visit to<br />
Europe to stress the traditional friendship that<br />
Australia enjoys with the countries of Europe. In<br />
few countries are such sentiments more<br />
appropriate or more soundly based than here in<br />
The Netherlands. I greet you, Prime Minister,<br />
not only as a fellow Head of Government and as<br />
the head of a fraternal party, but as the leader of<br />
a nation with an exemplary record of generosity<br />
and goodwill in her dealings with the world. In<br />
few countries is there a keener and more practi<br />
cal conception of the responsibilities of a small<br />
or medium power towards the maintenance of a<br />
stable world order.<br />
The Netherlands has made a contribution to the<br />
less fortunate peoples of the world and to the<br />
welfare and progress of the international community<br />
out of all proportion to her size. An Australian<br />
Prime Minister comes to your country,<br />
seeking not merely a reaffirmation of our bonds<br />
of friendship, but a good example-indeed a<br />
measure of inspiration-to guide us in our own<br />
search for a wise and constructive role as an<br />
independent nation in an increasingly troubled<br />
world. In the history and traditions, and in the contemporary<br />
circumstances of our countries, there is<br />
much to provide a basis for greater co-operation<br />
and understanding. Dutch navigators discovered<br />
the Australian continent in the early<br />
17th century-more than a century before the<br />
British. True it was they found little to interest<br />
them in those days. It was another 300 years<br />
before the Dutch came to Australia in significant<br />
numbers. Since World War II-a conflict in<br />
which Dutch and Australian soldiers fought side<br />
by side-more than 160,000 Dutch migrants<br />
have settled in my country. Their contribution to<br />
the development and enrichment of Australian<br />
society has been immense and irreplaceable.<br />
No migrants are more valued or respected by<br />
the Australian people. Today, the populations of<br />
our two countries and our national incomes are<br />
almost identical. We are both great trading nations. With our common western traditions of<br />
law, social justice and Parliamentary democracy,<br />
we share similar ethical and cultural<br />
values. Each of us aspires to a robust national<br />
independence, to a distinctive voice in world<br />
affairs, yet each of us acknowledges an important<br />
role, and important responsibilities, in international<br />
and regional communities.<br />
I mention these things, not just to illustrate the<br />
strength of our own relationship, which is longstanding<br />
and secure, but to show how two<br />
nations, geograpically remote and with widely<br />
different regional interests, can demonstrate the<br />
growing interdependence of all nations. I believe<br />
this interdependence to be the cardinal<br />
reality of modern international relations. Only<br />
by recognising their interdependence will<br />
nations overcome the complex and daunting<br />
problems confronting us all. Interdependence<br />
implies much more than co-existence, more<br />
even than co-operation: it requires us to acknowledge<br />
that no nation can live to itself, that<br />
the world's problems are global in their nature<br />
and origin, and that solutions will never be<br />
found-they will indeed be made much more<br />
difficult-if nations pursue narrow, inwardlooking<br />
policies, whether in trade or in economic<br />
matters, in military or defensive postures or in<br />
their attitudes to the developing nations. There<br />
has never been a greater need for international<br />
discussion, for the exchange of views, for the<br />
strengthening and enlargement of the world's<br />
agencies for co-operation and consultation. The<br />
survival of the western world-with its free<br />
institutions and its manifold material blessings<br />
-may well depend on the ability of nations to<br />
talk and work together.<br />
I believe this spirit of co-operation must be<br />
sought through a new respect for international<br />
law. It is appropriate that I mention these<br />
thoughts in The Hague, for it is here in your city<br />
that one of the paramount instruments for world<br />
order and international law is based. Australia<br />
has given her warm support to the principles </p>
<p>and objectives of the International Court of<br />
Justice. We believe we must continue to promote<br />
the development of international law. We<br />
must promote its acceptance, not merely as a<br />
means of ending disputes, but as a standard for<br />
international conduct, as a positive embodiment<br />
of the principles of international justice<br />
and human brotherhood. The re-ordering of<br />
political and economic relations which is occurring<br />
throughout the world will inevitably give<br />
rise to strains between states. The challenge<br />
facing us at present is to rise above self-interest<br />
and accept with generosity, with grace and with<br />
responsibility the need to resolve our<br />
differences by peaceful means. It is for these<br />
reasons that I spoke last year in the United<br />
Nations General Assembly of the need to give<br />
greater attention to the role of the International<br />
Court. I urged that the Court's jurisdiction<br />
should be widened and that jurisdiction should<br />
become compulsory and universal. In helping<br />
the Court to enhance its role, our countries share<br />
much common ground. Our delegations at the<br />
United Nations have worked closely together to<br />
this end.<br />
In international affairs, there have been many<br />
other areas of fruitful co-operation between<br />
Australia and the Netherlands. We both give<br />
high priority to the United Nations. We have<br />
effectively co-operated in the General Assembly<br />
on such questions as non-proliferation and<br />
nuclear disarmament: Korea and South-East<br />
Asia: the strengthening of the International<br />
Atomic Energy Agency: the Law of the Sea and<br />
the Environment. We have rejected apartheid<br />
and worked for the elimination of racism and<br />
colonialism, of anarchy and terrorism. We share<br />
a similar outlook on the problems of the under-<br />
The Prime Minister makes an address in The Hague. developed world. We are dedicated to the<br />
independence and development of those countries<br />
which history once made our colonies.<br />
Australia's new emphasis in her foreign policy<br />
on a more outward-looking and independent<br />
role, our greater involvement in Asia and our<br />
region, in no way represents any break with our<br />
history or with our traditional friends and allies<br />
in the Commonwealth, in Western Europe or<br />
the United States. Nor has our vital interest in<br />
their well-being diminished. Western Europe,<br />
for example, is more important than ever in our<br />
vision of the world. The nations of the European<br />
Economic Community now constitute<br />
Australia's second most important trading partner.<br />
We believe a united Europe will strengthen<br />
the democratic forces in the world, and that<br />
Europe's continuing prosperity is essential to<br />
the welfare and progress of all nations.<br />
The Netherlands, as one of the founding states<br />
of the European community, has an essential<br />
and continuing role in the new Europe and in<br />
Australia's relations with Europe. Your great<br />
ports are the essential gateways for our trade<br />
with the whole of this continent. Your businessmen<br />
and investors are deeply involved in<br />
Australia's economic development. Dutch<br />
people have risen to the highest positions of<br />
eminence in Australian commerce, industry<br />
and public life. I think of G. D. Delprat, a former<br />
manager of the Broken Hill Proprietary Company,<br />
Australia's largest corporation, a man<br />
who established our first steel works in Newcastle.<br />
I think of G. J. Dusseldorp, founder of the<br />
Lend Lease Corporation, one of the greatest<br />
development companies in Australia. In this<br />
context I mention a recent initiative to establish<br />
an Australian-Netherlands Association in<br />
Australia which will complement the successful<br />
Netherlands' Australia Institute already established<br />
in this country. I pay tribute to the efforts<br />
to establish the new association and offer my<br />
full support. It will symbolise and strengthen<br />
the long-standing and cordial friendship between<br />
our two countries. That friendship, Mr<br />
Prime Minister, has been deepened and<br />
enriched by my visit to your historic capital and<br />
by our talks together. Australians attach the<br />
highest importance to our good relations, and<br />
honour your nation and its people for their contribution<br />
to a saner, more civilised, more just<br />
and peaceful world. </p>
<p>The Prime Minister speaks at his official welcome to Paris at the Hotel de Ville. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
