<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5837</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER IN HIS PRESENTATION OF THE FIRST GRANT UNDER THE COMMONWEALTH&#039;S NEW HOME DEPOSIT ASSISTANCE SCHEME TO MR AND MRS J POUWELSE OF NORTH SUNSHINE, MELBOURNE</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/06/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005837.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
MI I)' aI 198<br />
6T1~ tfN~ T BY THE PRIMB MiNISTER ON IS PRESENTATION OF THE P1PST<br />
r.. Se1T. uNDERt rHE comm'oNvtEALTiI S NEw 11m DEPosiT. 4hSSISTANCE. SCHEMS<br />
6! A XRS J. POUWELSE OF NORTH SUNSHINE, MELBOUR~ NE<br />
TheIf rneDeposit Assistance Scherne--was.--announcexd-by_ the Government<br />
~ n. l~~ arh. 1982, as an important part of the package of a new<br />
houingAssstance program. This scheme replaces and improves<br />
tpo. tiiformer home savings grant scheme, Funds are being<br />
A&amp; ireoted to those families wh6-wall derive most benefit from<br />
'," isitanve. Under the Hoine Deposit Assi stan ce-Sbreme,* -gWaxpei<br />
dwithiout delay after receipt of an application in time<br />
Po'O. S 6t with the purchase of the applicant's new home.<br />
This 3*. bw scheme provides for grants to be paid to . eoplebxjiing<br />
b ing their first home on. or after 18 March 1982 who have<br />
sA. yed'" t tards their home in certain specified forms ( such as in<br />
~ d building societies).<br />
itagC'grant. under the scheme is a maximum of-$ 2-7500 A'hd--<br />
~ d-ditonai1 assistance is available for families with dependent<br />
chlren a bonus of $ 500 for one child and $ 1,000 for two or<br />
~ orehidren. Mr and Mrs Pouwelse are receiving the full grant<br />
Grants-are availab: le on the basis of $ 1 for each $ 1 of eligible<br />
-comp~ ared with for cach $ 3 under the old scheme.<br />
Vabii*--iD~ 1ts on eligible homes have been removed. under<br />
4C -Q -a cle m the maximum basic grant is made to families with<br />
;ñ~ sixpto 135 per cent of average weekly earnings, tapering<br />
rd At 155 per cent.<br />
i~ eo~ e. w-purehase their first home between 18 March and I Ouly<br />
~ l98apdwc'sefamily earnings in 1980/ 81 were below $ 22,000 should<br />
* n42e'-aoutthe grant. Families planning to buy their first home<br />
Aitb-rtext 12 months and who earn less than $ 25,000 in 1981/ 82<br />
uldalso in~ quire. This means that if your family earnings<br />
re. aibiut $ 4~ 80 per week or less you should inquire. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
