<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8573</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP, PRESS CONFERENCE, AUSTRLIAN HIGH COMMISSION, MONIARA, SOUTH PACIFIC FORUM, 9 JULY 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/07/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008573.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OP THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING M P,<br />
PRESS CONFERENCE, AUSTRALIAN HIGH COMMISSION, MONIARA,<br />
SOUTH PACIFIC FORUM, 9 JULY 1992<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
PM: Well I might just give you a few introductory<br />
comments. I think that's the order of the day. The<br />
first thing I'll say is I found my attendance for<br />
the first time at the Forum a worthwhile experience.<br />
This is the main mechanism for high level dialogue<br />
in the Pacific, and I think it provides a sense of<br />
community to Pacific Island countries, indeed to all<br />
the countries of the Pacific, but there is a place<br />
to rome to talk, and therA is a clear and dAfinablA,<br />
not only sense of community, but community, and that<br />
we've got a forum for sensible discussion of<br />
important political and stratcgic intcrcts.<br />
There was a strong sense at this meeting that the<br />
South Pacific in not immune from rocont dramatic<br />
ohangoo in the world. The environment ic obvioucly<br />
an aro of oonoern here, global warming worrica are<br />
concerns to a number of -Torl m ' cour--ias,<br />
particularly where some don't rise much more than<br />
about 4 metres above sea level, and that's an issue<br />
of concern to them. I was able to announce<br />
yesterday new environmental assistance measures,<br />
which I outlined in a press release, I think that<br />
you have. And that was a matter of great interest<br />
Lv uu mum vC Lheu vumun! Ly hare becauu tley<br />
know thai the things that Australia has already been<br />
doing, in terms of monitoring patterns in tides and<br />
sea patterns and further climate change monitoring<br />
which we'll do by yesterdy-' announcement, was I<br />
think regarded well.<br />
The Forum also welcomed the moratorium on French<br />
nuclear testing in the Pacific. I suggested that<br />
Forum members write formally to President Mitterand.<br />
That suggestion was taken up. The Cook Islands then<br />
suggested that other nuclear powers be written to in<br />
similar terms over nuclear testing, as the French<br />
have said that the longevity of their moratorium<br />
will in part depend upon what other nuclear powers<br />
do in relation to testing. So it was, I suppose,<br />
appropriate that we write not simply formally to the<br />
French but to others. </p>
<p>Today I will sign, on behalf of Australia, the Niue<br />
Treaty on Fisheries Surveillance, which is the<br />
treaty which will provide a cooperative relationship<br />
between countries in surveillance of fisheries, and<br />
means that each will come to the aid of the other in<br />
protecting those fisheries, and in that sense is I<br />
think an i1Wpurtunt treaty.<br />
We expect the Forum to approve a declaration on<br />
regional law enforcement, that's a pledge of<br />
cooperation to address* such issues as drugs, money<br />
laundering and tourism, by improving cooperation in<br />
legal and law enforcement areas.<br />
I've had a number of bilateral meetings with Mr<br />
Bolger yesterday, in the evening I arrived with<br />
Prime Minister Mamaloni, and this morning with Mr<br />
Rabuka, also late yesterday with Mr Tofilau EtifE<br />
Western Samoa, and I may have another one orEWobefore<br />
I leave.<br />
You've already covered, I think, some of the<br />
substance of the meeting I had with Mr Bolger. You<br />
mig~ ht be iini~ tL huwwLilay I had withl Prime<br />
Minister Rabuka this morning. I told him that<br />
Australia welcomes the restoration of representative<br />
Government in Fiji and the continued effort towards<br />
constitutionar1Y-eorm-As a result I told him, and<br />
I am prepared now to be able to tell you, that I<br />
think it is now appropriate to resume defence<br />
cooperation with Fiji. Initially that renewed<br />
defence cooperation will concentrate on maritime<br />
surveillance and training, and will include a<br />
resumption of operational Royal Aukstralian Nvy_<br />
ivisits to Fiji, resumption of aerial maritime<br />
surveillance patrols in and through Fiji's exclusive<br />
economic zone, and also offering Fiji training<br />
places in the joint services military college in<br />
Canberra for the traininzg of Fiji itillLay force<br />
personnel. Prime Minister Rabuka indicated to me that he was<br />
intending to visit Australia privately in September.<br />
I have extended to him an offer to visit Australia<br />
as a guest of the Australian Government, which he<br />
was ver'y ylad Lu 4vuept. So lie shall come in<br />
September. I think Senator Ray is planning a visit<br />
in October. So other defence cooperation can be<br />
discussed on those two occasions.<br />
I think I might leave my introductory remarks at<br />
that.<br />
3: How do you now view the relationship with Fiji, just<br />
summing it up? </p>
<p>PM: I think there is an opportunity for Prime minister<br />
Rabuka to open up a dialogue with the whole Fiji<br />
community about its future, about its constitutional<br />
future, about giving everybody a place in<br />
representative government in Fiji. And one gets<br />
that sense that an opportunity is present. I'd like<br />
to see us maximise that opportunity. And now<br />
they've returned to representative government and he<br />
has made clear his commitment to constitutional<br />
reform and dialogue that this is the time for a<br />
restoration of full relations and cooperation<br />
between us, and can I say, good will.<br />
J: Are you confident that the racial weighting in the<br />
constitution w411 be done away with?<br />
PM: We didn't discuss the constitution in detail, but<br />
sure he believes there is some historic<br />
opportunity to consider Fiji as a community in a<br />
broader sense, as a result of the events of the last<br />
five years. And we in Australia would certainly<br />
welcome that opportunity.<br />
J: Will you be pushing for Fiji to be allowed back into<br />
the Commonwealth?<br />
PM: This is a matter for Fiji, I think, as much as for<br />
anyone else. It's not particularly a matter for<br />
Australia, but naturally we would be sympathetic.<br />
J: Were you able to meet with the Vanuatu Prime<br />
Minister?<br />
PM: No, not yet. I'll probably see him later today I<br />
think.<br />
J: Any change of the position there, Mr Keating?<br />
PM: No, not that I know of, but I'll speak to him later.<br />
J: Prime Minister, how much is the resumption of<br />
military links with Fiji worth in dollar terms?<br />
Pm: I don't know. But I think its worth goes beyond..<br />
it's assessed by the Prime minister and the<br />
Government of Fiji, I'm sure, beyond simply the<br />
monetary value or monetary cost of any operation.<br />
J: Should the review of their constitution not result<br />
in changes, will we change our attitude towards<br />
Fiji?<br />
PM: Why jump to those sort of conclusions? Let's wait<br />
to see what happens.<br />
J: Mr Rabuka's visit in September, is there anything<br />
planned for while he is here? </p>
<p>PH: Well it was for him a private visit, but I'm<br />
extending the offer, the invitation to con* as a<br />
guest of the Government, which he has accepted, So,<br />
no doubt the visit will widen and he will do other<br />
things. I should hope he would.<br />
J: Do you have any concerns about the situation in<br />
ELougainville, even though it was not formally on the<br />
agenda?<br />
PH: Well one always has concerns, naturally, about these<br />
things. I mean there is an armed cessationist<br />
movement on Bougainville which the Papua New Guinean<br />
Governmient is trying to deal with. It's a matter of<br />
concern to us, to the neighbourhood, but I think the<br />
Forum regard it as internal problem for--Papua New<br />
Guinea, as we did.<br />
J: What about the allegations of Australian weaponry<br />
and bullets being used against civiliansT<br />
PM: The Papua New Guinean defence minister and defence<br />
commander have stated publicly that the conditions<br />
under which we provided Iroquoi helicopters have not<br />
been breached. Now we are seeking to establish<br />
whether this is so. Were it to be so, of course, we<br />
would make plain our objection. But I've already<br />
said, and so has the Foreign Minister, that we<br />
expect the conditions under which those equipments<br />
are being provided to be maintained, and adhered to,<br />
and honoured.<br />
3: How are we seeking to establish that, Mr Keating?<br />
PM: The position there is unclear and it's not going to<br />
be easy for it to established, but as quickly as we<br />
can, we will.<br />
3: Will that be through intelligec encies?<br />
PH: Let's say we will try to establish it.<br />
3: How concerned are you about reports of abuse of<br />
human rights in Bougainville?<br />
PM: We've sought an official response to the allegations<br />
made the other day, collected on Bougainville by the<br />
Australian lawyer, Rosemary Gillespi, and it is to<br />
that which we seek a response from the Government ot<br />
Papua New Guinea, a considered response.<br />
J: Doesn't there come a point where it stops being an<br />
internal situation, as we have seen in Dili for<br />
example? </p>
<p>pM: We're hoping that a political settlement can be<br />
arrived at, and in my discussions with Prime<br />
MinisterMamaloni I urged that the quicker a<br />
dialo-cguje e -re-etablishedb etween the Solomon<br />
islands and Papua New Guinea the better, as well.<br />
And I think that when the Government settles down in<br />
Papua Now Guinea after next week's sitting then it<br />
might be possible, and that could help as veil.<br />
J: Isn't it clear that machine gun fire from our<br />
helicopters is consistent<br />
PM: I don't think it's clear, no. The claims may be<br />
made, but whether the aircraft is responding to fire<br />
against itself is not clear. But were it to be<br />
clear that these gun ships are being used in a<br />
offensive manner, this would be contrary to the<br />
conditions under which we have provided them to<br />
Papua New Guinea, and we would then be suggesting to<br />
the Papua New Guinean Government that they be<br />
withdrawn from the service area.<br />
J: Is there anything Australia can do? They can't take<br />
them back?<br />
PM4: No.<br />
J: in your meeting with Mr Bolger did you assure him<br />
whether the New Zealand economy wouldn't be an issue<br />
in the run up to the next election in Australia?<br />
PM: Of course not, he didn't ask for that assurance and<br />
I didn't give it. We're all grown up, and we are<br />
all in the position I thinX, as mature nations, to<br />
discuss issues of substance and political and<br />
economic ideas, whether they have said to emanate or<br />
be part of New Zealand's economic policy or anyone<br />
else's. I mean, this sort of ' thought -police'<br />
routine on our political debate is immature and<br />
silly.<br />
J: Is that what Mr Bolger was suggesting?<br />
PM: No, I don't think so. What he was suggesting, he<br />
thought that some of our Ministers had taken New<br />
Zealand's name in vein. I notice in one report this<br />
morning that he thought I had. I don't think I had,<br />
well I told him not to regard that at all very<br />
seriously, but he might have regarded it more<br />
seriously than I did.<br />
3: The issue of policing arrangements in the region.<br />
How serious a threat are criminal activities, or is<br />
this just a preventative measure? </p>
<p>PM: It's a preventative measure and a cooperative<br />
framework to deal with the problems. These are very<br />
open borders, naturally, and the more willingness<br />
there is on the part of member states to cooperate<br />
with one another in these areas the better.<br />
J: What impact does it have on Pacific tax havens?<br />
PH: Nothing, not in that sense. Our national<br />
governments have laws which cover tax havens, as<br />
Australia does with its Foreign Source Income<br />
Legislation, so that's how we treat income as a<br />
matter for us.<br />
J: Mr Bolger has written to the Governor General of the<br />
Solomon Islands to apologise for being late. Will<br />
you?<br />
PM: No. This is a very small issue. I know some of you<br />
have been sold a line on this by some of the local<br />
journalists on a day short of news. This is<br />
standard tact for the Australian press corps to go<br />
back to irrelevancies.<br />
J: Just domestically, interest rates<br />
PM: I'm not here to discuss this. As I said before I<br />
left, I'm not discussing domestic policy issues.<br />
J: Can you clarify the position on the aviation<br />
agreement that you discussed with New Zealand<br />
yesterday, and to abolish visa-free entyUinto New<br />
Zealand?<br />
PM: Australia would like to arrive at a position where<br />
we have an Australasian airline market. And that<br />
would invol-ve fl-ying domestic terminal to domestic<br />
terminal, rather than through the international<br />
terminals which have always got pressure on them,<br />
and where movements of passengers is delayed by the<br />
processing time, and where generally movements of<br />
aircraft through international terminals can be<br />
delayed by all sorts of extraneous factors. So,<br />
given the fact that New Zealand is closer to the<br />
East Coast of Australia than other parts of<br />
Australia it makes sense, therefore, that we should<br />
have an Australasian airline market. That<br />
necessarily involves being clear about our<br />
emigration procedures, and will inevitably involve<br />
consideration about a common border. So therefore<br />
we would insist that our border not to be a porous<br />
one, or made porous by concessions provided to<br />
people of other countries for access to New Zealand.<br />
And we're saying, I made this point to Prime<br />
Minister Bolger, that I think that there is a lot of<br />
value in, if we are talking about closer economic<br />
relations between Australia and New Zealand, this<br />
must go to services as well as goods. </p>
<p>. Ad one of the most basic services is transportation<br />
of people, obviously. And the more that this can be<br />
regarded as one market, the better, but ipso facto<br />
means that we need to come to some agreements about<br />
the way in which our migration processes are and how<br />
they work. we're just saying that if New Zealand is<br />
considering extending, in a concessional way, non<br />
visa access to New Zealand from other countries then<br />
this would need to be viewed against the backdrop of<br />
what I think would be a huge benefit of an<br />
Australasian airline market.<br />
J: Did Mr Bolger give any undertaking on the issue?<br />
PM: No, but he took the issue on board, I'm sure.<br />
J: Is this the first time this has been raised?<br />
PM: I shouldn't think so. I think that Senator Collins<br />
has probably raised this.<br />
J: Is this an indication that New Zealand has been<br />
moving slowly?<br />
PM: I notice some report in today's Australian about how<br />
this process has been moving slowly. It's gone more<br />
distance in three months than it's gone in forty<br />
years. If some of you had been around a bit longer<br />
you'd know how long this paralysis has been there.<br />
J: Will Australia yield at all with any of the visa<br />
requirements?<br />
PM: Not unless there is a proposal put to us which is<br />
sensible and reasonable. But at this stage I don't<br />
think any have. And we try to run a rational,<br />
sensible, 1i-gigra-inA-policy, and if we were trying<br />
to extend this for the purpose that I mention then<br />
obviously we've got to get some agreement as to how<br />
we extend it.<br />
J: New Zealand has been aware of your concern about<br />
this for some time, there has been a letter to Mr<br />
Hand.<br />
Pm: I don't know whether they have had this process in<br />
hand, or in mind over time. It's not that long ago<br />
it's February that the One Nation Statement was<br />
made, and it was some time after that before we got<br />
down to some of these issues. So, New Zealand is<br />
entitled to consider this sensibly.<br />
J: How did you feel when you saw the plethora of union<br />
Jacks on the flags at the Forum?<br />
PM?. I just make the point that I've made in Australia<br />
that one can't claim to have a unique symbol of<br />
oneself when others have the same symbol. </p>
<p>J: Has anyone raised the issue with you about what<br />
you've had to say on th. flag?<br />
PM: Yes, a couple have said to me that they were very<br />
encouraged about what I had to say, and that this<br />
has praood debato in their own countries about<br />
their own constitutional arrangements, symbols,<br />
standing, et cetera.<br />
J: Did Rabuca give you any tips on setting up a<br />
-Rpubl ic?<br />
PM: I think he's interested in constitutional<br />
government.<br />
J: Can you say which leaders raised the issue of the<br />
flag?<br />
PM4: They're all entitled to their private remarks, I<br />
think.<br />
J: Radio New Zealand, Mr Kfeating, did Prime Minister<br />
Bolger over-react by apologising to the Governor<br />
General?<br />
PM: Look, it's so trifling an issue that it's hardly<br />
worthy of further comment.<br />
J: On plutonium shipments, the Forum has expressed a<br />
view-, what is your own bOpinion about that?<br />
PM: I think that general international safe-guards are<br />
important, particularly with these sorts of<br />
commodities. And I think that Japan, who envisages<br />
having the traffic in this, would be aware of the<br />
concerns of Pacific Island countries, both directly,<br />
communicated bilaterally, and also from the Forum.<br />
And that's how it should be.<br />
Now do you see this region fitting in with<br />
Australia's push into Australasia?<br />
PM: I've said before, and I said yesterday in my opening<br />
remarks, that Australia will always reserve its<br />
right to deal with issues in world forums and play a<br />
role as appropriate, subject to subject, on the<br />
world stage. But the focus of its attention will be<br />
the region in which we live, the increasing focus.<br />
This is true now of our trade, where nearly three<br />
quarters of it, both imports and exports, are with<br />
the Asia-Pacific area, and where we can be I think a<br />
useful influence in this area of the world, and at<br />
the same time give Australians a more secure place<br />
in the region for themselves. And the various<br />
things that Australia does in the Pacific, whether<br />
they be, as you saw yesterday, the Pacific patrol<br />
boat program, or the wharfs program here, or the<br />
climate and sea monitoring programs, or whatever it </p>
<p>might be, I think we can play a useful role, and<br />
that is above simply our bilateral aid arrangements<br />
to various countries. And it's important that they<br />
have an influence on us. So i think you'll see<br />
Australia and Australian foreign policy directed<br />
more expressly to the region, notwithstanding<br />
obvious and genuine concerns and other issues in the<br />
world context.<br />
J: Are there concerns about Australia's relations~ hip<br />
witJh Ja~ pan, as Australia has backed the Forum's<br />
protest to Japan over its plan to ship plutonium?<br />
PM: I don't think the Japanese will be unduly of fended<br />
by press reports from Australia.<br />
but a letter will be signed by the Forum Secretariat<br />
including Australia.<br />
PM: That's right, that's true.<br />
J: How do other nations see Australia as a bully or<br />
as a help?<br />
PM: We're obviously not a bully. How could anyone<br />
sustain the remark that we're a bully. That's a<br />
gratuitous, I know that you don't mean it<br />
gratuitously, but it is a gratuitous remark.<br />
Australia looks for obviously no territorial gain in<br />
its foreign policy. It has, I think, altruistic<br />
objectives in its foreign and aid policies generally<br />
and in the region, and I think its role has been<br />
generally regarded well and appreciated by countries<br />
of the Forum. Just as I was leaving, what delayed<br />
me was Sir Robert Rex from Niue was making what was,<br />
in a sense, his farewell speech, and he reflected<br />
over forty years and said some complimentary things<br />
about Australia and New Zealand in that context.<br />
And I think that would be the general view. There<br />
will always be some matters of difference, I'm quite<br />
certain that some countries think that our treatment<br />
of Papua New Guinean development aid is too<br />
generous, and would prefer some of that to be spread<br />
more widely across the Pacific. You'll find some of<br />
those issues often given vent, but in term~ s of the<br />
general standing of Australia, its motivation, and<br />
thA gonri will tnw~ rds it, I think that's pretty<br />
clear, and pretty much in Australia's favour.<br />
J: we've had one of the closest relationships with<br />
Japan. will you use it to take up the Forum's<br />
protest with them?<br />
Pm: You keep coming back to this like a song. There is<br />
a statement there, and the statement is by the<br />
Forum. it's not for Australia to bilaterally take<br />
the matter up. </p>
<p>J: Some countries have raised it bilaterally, will we?<br />
PM4: I don't think so. I wouldn't be certain of it, I'd<br />
have to ask Senator Evans.<br />
J: Are the resumption of military links with Fiji<br />
immediate or contingent on the September meeting?<br />
PM; No, as far as I'm concerned it's from here out. But<br />
obviously the talks in September and October will<br />
help round out cooperation between us.<br />
J4. We've moved much further than New Zealand in this<br />
relationship. Did you talk about that with Mr<br />
Bolger?<br />
PM: No. New Zealand is free to make its own mind up<br />
about the issues, obviously, and it will.<br />
J: Are you satisfied with the progress that Rabuka has<br />
made?<br />
PM: I think there is a real opportunity here for<br />
improvement for the community of the Fijian people,<br />
and I think there is a lot of good will on the part<br />
of the Prime Minister towards that objective, and I<br />
think it would be counterproductive for Australia to<br />
maintain the position which we have previously held<br />
in the circumstances of five years ago. OK? 7 Thank<br />
you.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
