<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10851</transcript-id>
    <title>JOINT MEDIA STATEMENT             PRIME MINISTER &amp;amp; PREMIER OF WESTERN AUSTRALIA             JERVOISE BAY INFRASTRUCTURE DEVELOPMENT PROJECT</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/01/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Prime Minister John Howard today committed $80 million from the Federation</p>
<p> Fund to the Jervoise Bay Infrastructure Development project - an initiative</p>
<p> which will provide a major boost for the economy and thousands of</p>
<p> jobs for Western Australia.</p>
<p> In a joint announcement with Premier Richard Court, Mr Howard said</p>
<p> the Jervoise Bay development, which was the most advanced maritime</p>
<p> infrastructure project undertaken in WA, could be a fitting symbol</p>
<p> of 100 years of Federation.</p>
<p> "In partnership, the Commonwealth and WA Governments are working</p>
<p> together to generate jobs and provide a valuable piece of infrastructure</p>
<p> which will make a significant and ongoing contribution to Australia</p>
<p> and the national economy," Mr Howard said.</p>
<p> The Jervoise Bay Infrastructure Development is a Federation Fund project.</p>
<p> The Fund is an initiative of the Commonwealth Government - its gift</p>
<p> to the nation to mark the Centenary of Federation in 2001. By financing</p>
<p> major projects of national significance, the fund is building the</p>
<p> infrastructure Australia needs for the coming century.</p>
<p> Mr Court said Jervoise Bay, 13 km south of Fremantle at the northern</p>
<p> end of Cockburn Sound, would be developed as a world-class, maritime</p>
<p> industrial complex.</p>
<p> "The total cost of the project will be in the vicinity of $200</p>
<p> million with Commonwealth, State and private sector investment,"</p>
<p> he said.</p>
<p> The redevelopment will provide protected sites with direct waterfront</p>
<p> access, a heavy capacity wet berth and load out wharf, large manufacturing</p>
<p> areas immediately adjacent to the waterfront and access to navigable</p>
<p> deep water.</p>
<p> "The project will be of enormous significance to the WA economy</p>
<p> and the nation," the Premier said.</p>
<p> It is anticipated that the redeveloped facilities at Jervoise Bay</p>
<p> will accommodate new construction projects valued at $100 million</p>
<p> annually and additional work generated by support, repair and maintenance</p>
<p> activities in the region of $160 million per year.</p>
<p> There will be more than 1,600 direct site employees and over 3000</p>
<p> additional indirect jobs. This is in addition to the 400 jobs generated</p>
<p> during the construction phase.</p>
<p> The development will be a major factor in boosting local content and</p>
<p> involvement in big resource projects.</p>
<p> Mr Court said State Government funding, combined with the Commonwealth's</p>
<p> Federation Fund contribution, would enable the provision of infrastructure</p>
<p> on a scale large enough to take advantage of the strong economic opportunities</p>
<p> presented by the expansion of the oil and gas industry, and the resource</p>
<p> and downstream processing sectors of the WA economy.</p>
<p> "Jervoise Bay offers an excellent site for ship building, repair</p>
<p> and maintenance for fabrication and ocean-based transport within WA</p>
<p> and to interstate and international destinations," the Premier</p>
<p> said.</p>
<p> The project will involve the construction of two breakwaters, dredging</p>
<p> and land reclamation. Cockburn Road is to be realigned to the east</p>
<p> of the Jervoise Bay industrial area to facilitate direct, heavy load</p>
<p> access to waterfront facilities and separate through traffic from</p>
<p> local industrial traffic.</p>
<p> To build on the already highly skilled workforce in the marine and</p>
<p> shipbuilding industry, it is also proposed that the precinct accommodate</p>
<p> a Marine Industry Technology Park which will be progressively developed</p>
<p> on a freehold basis for specific high technology research and development</p>
<p> and manufacturing activities.</p>
<p> Considerable public consultation has already been undertaken as part</p>
<p> of the process of developing the Jervoise Bay master plan and the</p>
<p> State Government is committed to ensuring that all environmental issues</p>
<p> have been addressed before proceeding.</p>
<p> The master plan is currently the subject of a Public Environmental</p>
<p> Review which closes on February 9.</p>
<p> Commonwealth funding is conditional on obtaining the necessary environmental</p>
<p> clearances and the Federal Government will work constructively with</p>
<p> the State Government with a view to integrating Commonwealth advice,</p>
<p> avoiding duplication and arriving at a satisfactory outcome on environmental</p>
<p> heritage issues.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
