<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4715</transcript-id>
    <title>ASSISTANCE TO CATTLE PRODUCERS AFFECTED BY BLUETONGUE VIRUS, 17 MAY 1978</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/05/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004715.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
3J) AUSTRALIA i<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 17 MAY 1978<br />
ASSISTANCE TO CATTLE PRODUCERS<br />
AFFECTED BY BLUETONGUE VIRUS<br />
The Prime Minister has written to the State Premiers seeking<br />
their agreement to sharing the cost of a number of measures<br />
to assist cattle producers financially affected by bluetongue<br />
control measures. The Minister for the Northern Territory has<br />
written to the Majority Leader of the Legislative Assembly<br />
extending a similar cost-sharing proposal to operate from<br />
1 July 1978. Assistance costs in the Northern Territory in<br />
1977/ 78 will be met by the Commonwealth.<br />
It is important that producers' incomes not be eroded any<br />
further as a result of control measures imposed by Commonwealth<br />
and State animal health authorities.<br />
The Prime Minister outlined the program of financial assistance<br />
that has been proposed to the States, and the Northern Territory<br />
Legislative Assembly. The proposed assistance measures comprise:<br />
payments to offset mustering costs during 1978<br />
and for movement of stock in control areas in<br />
the Cape York Peninsula, the Northern Territory<br />
and the Kiinberleys. This assistance would be at<br />
the rate of $ 3 per head with a maximum of<br />
$ 3,000 per property.<br />
payments to compensate for costs of blood testing<br />
of cattle at the rate of $ 5 per head for survey<br />
and surveillance testing and $ 10 per head for<br />
movement testing.<br />
provision of funds in the Northern Territory,<br />
Queensland and Western Australia for the urgent<br />
acquisition of virology laboratory equipment.<br />
The assistance proposed by the Commonwealth is dependent upon<br />
agreement of the relevant States to share costs on a dollar<br />
for dollar basis and to undertake administration of this scheme.<br />
The Prime Minister has asked Premiers to respond to the Commonwealth<br />
Government's offer as a matter of urgency. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
