<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2930</transcript-id>
    <title>REPORT OF AUSTRALIAN SCIENTISTS</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/05/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002930.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
A A I k-RA<br />
No DATE<br />
D/ 31 18 May 1973<br />
REPORT ( F AUSTRALIAN SCIENTISTS<br />
Attached is a cony of the Rlnort of the Australian<br />
scientists who attended the meeting with Frcach scientists in<br />
Canberra from 7 9 May 1973o Agreement between the two<br />
delegations was reached on a number of ooints, and these are<br />
set out in Section A of the attached Rsnort. This section<br />
also annears in the Report of the French delegation.<br />
Both Renorts were tabled in the House of Renresentatives<br />
by the Prime Minister, Mr Whitlam, on 17 May 1973. </p>
<p>MEETING BETWEEN AUSTRALIAN AND FRENCH SCIENTISTS<br />
MAY 7-9, 1973<br />
AT THE AUSTRALIAN ACADEMY OF SCIENCE, CANBERRA<br />
REPORT OF THE AUSTRALIAN SCIENTISTS<br />
Present: Australian Side<br />
Sir Rutherford Robertson<br />
Professor S. T. Butler<br />
Dr D. Metcalf<br />
Professor M. J. D. White<br />
Dr C. H. B. Priestley ( present for two sessions to<br />
Sdiscuss meteorological questions)<br />
French Side<br />
M. le Professeur A. Gauvenet<br />
Dr D. Mechali<br />
SM. J. M. Lavie<br />
M. A. P. Chaussard SECTION A<br />
This section is identical in the two reports.<br />
1. Dose Commitments<br />
There was general agreement that the technical methods<br />
used by the Australian authorities for measuring quantities of<br />
Sradiation fall-out are satisfactory and are in accordance with<br />
Sinternational pr:. ctice. A large degree of agreement was reached<br />
regarding the levels of dose commitment in Australia due to past<br />
French tests. The estimates of those dose commitments in millirads<br />
are as follows ( for strontium-90 and caesium-137, the low figures<br />
are preferred by the French scientists according to their method<br />
of estimation; the Australian scientists' estimates are the<br />
higher figures): </p>
<p>Tyod Thyroid Blood Bn<br />
Element ( young ( odr frigBnWhl<br />
children) children formin cells bd<br />
adults) clsbd<br />
iodine-131 97 9 0 0 0<br />
short-lived 1.5 1.5 1.5 1.5<br />
0 0 4.0-6.2 5.6-8.5 0<br />
caesium-137<br />
( external) 2.0-3.0 2.0-3.0 2.0-3.0 2.0-3.0 2.0-3.0<br />
caesium-137<br />
( internal) 0.9-1.3 0.9-1.3 0.9-1.3 0.9-1.3 0.9-1.3<br />
carbon-14 0.2 0.2 0.2 0.3 0.2<br />
TOTAL ( in round<br />
figures) 102-103 14-15 9-12 10-15 5-6<br />
The estimates of the dose commitments due to all tests<br />
are as follows ( the figures were provided for the meeting by an<br />
Australian government scientist; the values for the French tests<br />
are the higher values from the preceding table):<br />
Thyroid Thyroid Blood<br />
Element ( young ( older frigBone Whole<br />
children) children formin cells bd<br />
adults) clsbd<br />
French tests 103 15 12 15 6<br />
Tests by other<br />
nations 74 54 83 96 52<br />
TOTAL for all<br />
tests 177 69 95 111 58<br />
Both delegations agree with the method which has been used<br />
to obtain these figures.<br />
2. Biological Effects<br />
There was general agreement between both groups that for<br />
certain dose levels, radiation is known to cause damage in humans. </p>
<p>However, there may be a threshold below which lower levels of<br />
radiation have no effect, the action on human beings of low doses<br />
and very low doses such as result from the tests never having been<br />
observed. Current work, for example on the phenomenon of repair by<br />
living cells of damage they have suffered at high doses of radia tion,<br />
suggests that low doses may not cause cancer or genetic defects at<br />
a rate proportional to dose. Novertheless the international<br />
authorities have prudently accepted the hypothesis of direct<br />
C proportionality in order to establish accepted dose limits. Certain<br />
additional factors may operate to reduce significantly the risks<br />
Sbelow those predicted from a simple estimation based on proportionality.<br />
These include the lesser effects of certain types of radiation,<br />
radiation received at low dose rates, or over extended rather than<br />
brief time periods. </p>
<p>4.<br />
SECTION B<br />
The following part of this report is the<br />
sole responsibility of the Australian<br />
scientists.<br />
The Australian scientists stressed that, despite the<br />
uncertainties outlined in the above discussion of biological effects,<br />
the only prudent course in attempting to assess the overall risk to<br />
the Australian population was to assume direct proportionality of all<br />
biological effects to radiation dosage. This is the public health<br />
position taken by the United Nations Scientific Committee on the<br />
Effects of Atomic Radiation and by other recognised authorities.<br />
The Australian population is large enough that even very small linear<br />
estimates of risk, in the region of the radiation doses due to the<br />
French tests, yield finite estimates of deaths due to cancer and<br />
genetic abnormalities. The Australian scientistps believe that it<br />
is necessary to accept such estimrates as realistic and not to take<br />
into account notions of a hypothetical threshold dose below which<br />
damage would rot accur. Assuming a linear relationship between<br />
dose received and using maximum published figures for radiation<br />
risks, it has been calculated that, as a result of past French<br />
atomic tests, a final total of 26 cases of thyroid cancer and<br />
14 cases of leuLkaemia and other cancers could result in the<br />
Australian population. The Australian scientists present believe<br />
that, as a result of the French tests that have already occurred,<br />
there could be a-oproximately one death or serious disability in<br />
Australia from genetic causes during the first generation and 18<br />
deaths in all subsequent generations; these are minimum estimates, </p>
<p>and maximum estimates based on present information ( see the Report<br />
of the Advisory Committee on the biological effects of ionizing<br />
radiation, U. S. National Academy of Sciences, November 1972) would<br />
be approximately 15 times these figures.<br />
The above figures are based on the dose commitment<br />
estimates from the French tests given in the tables in Section A.-<br />
It should be noted that the report of the Academy of Science Committee<br />
estimated the steady radiation effects to Australia from French tests<br />
in the Pacific, assuming continued testing at the French site on a<br />
pattern similar to that of the past seven years, and the harm commitments<br />
given in the report must be interpreted in this light. The<br />
dose commitments for the seven years of French testing in the<br />
Pacific are included in the report. Together with the risk factors<br />
used in the report, these commitments permit a direct computation of<br />
the harm commitments to the Australian population from the past tests.<br />
The Australian scientists drew attention to the additional<br />
harmful effects which would accrue to the Australian population as<br />
a result of the improbable event in which the explosion of a highpowered<br />
bomb was combined with quite exceptional meteorological<br />
conditions giving a high fallout over Australia ( Appendix Academy<br />
Report). Although the levels of radiation due to the French tests<br />
are unlikely to cause a statistically detectable increase in the<br />
frequency of cancer or genetic abnormalities in Australia, it is<br />
emphasised that there should be no unwarranted exposure to radiation.<br />
Further, with the long-lived isotopes produced as the result of nuclear<br />
explosions, the genetic effects on the Australian population, though<br />
small, are cumulative. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
