<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4625</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA, THE RT HON MALCOLM FRASER CH MP, AT THE HILTON HOTEL, SYDNEY, MONDAY 13 FEBRUARY, ON THE OCCASION OF THE OPENING OF THE COMMONWEALTH HEADS OF GOVERNMENT REGIONAL MEETING</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/02/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004625_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
-' MAG UNTIL<br />
-DELIVREPD -Commonwealth Heads of Government<br />
Ron Meeing<br />
Address by the Prime Minister of Australia,<br />
the Rt*. Hon.* Malcolm Fraser, C. H., f M. P<br />
Atth6&amp; Hilton notel S dey, ? londa 13 February,<br />
on the Occasion of the Opening of the<br />
CommnwelthHeads of Government Regional Meeting<br />
In opening this Conference,, I am very-plreased to join -the<br />
* Gover'nor-General;!= welcoming you and wishing you anL enjoyable<br />
and rewarding visit to Autralia.<br />
This mseetin~ g of Comonwealth H{ eads of Government from -the<br />
Asian nd-South-Pacific Region is a notable event. It is not<br />
only-the first such regional eeting-in-the history cqf the<br />
Comonwealth. but it ia also the largest meeting of Heads of.-<br />
~ tbi a; flieing was<br />
sur~ ar atfied<br />
' tht te* u&amp;, et. Lon has baen. taken up so quickly.<br />
No one &amp;-idwi-tie, Com~ monwealth should be surprised that<br />
we bayvite .-g o--be-omnwat' outstand-<br />
I= ' nattrbutes-has been its resilience -its capacity to adapt<br />
represntation. in 1946 thiere were five<br />
member nations# today there are -thirty ai..<br />
Scma_' peciple expr-eased misgivings about enlarging the Common-'<br />
wrealth: beyonl the narr'ow group of five. How wrong they were. In<br />
today Is -world P the original gmrp of -Live could never have hoped<br />
to be as ralevantof c6m-tfuctive as -the thirty six members of the<br />
' contemporary Coson. ealth. </p>
<p>m2<br />
0 the Commonwealth was held together by the similar-Ity<br />
of itz: s iiebers now diversity is the k~ ey.<br />
sever before-have our members been so dispersed over so<br />
nmy cOruer3 of. the earth, represented such a wide cross section<br />
of social and eeonomie development,, participated in so many<br />
Intnational. agencies\* Vhen change of this magnitude takes<br />
-place it Creates4 , impetus for further development.<br />
In taking this initiative we are responding to the compellin1<br />
comnense-of two facts<br />
iwe are a-Tmembers of the Commonwealth and value<br />
highly the opportniti&amp; te Comffonwealth tie<br />
gives . us.. to discus ' vital issues with one another.<br />
or Weare-also. nelghbours in the Asia-South Pacific<br />
igion.<br />
It is natural that the 12 of us,, joined by tisof bistor~ y<br />
geovaphy~ abould come tog-ether to, develop eqn&amp;, strengthen the<br />
im~ igitia witbi<br />
DterttzeyeewthV-12 f aheev oa1ved diatinotive.<br />
style which emphasizes candid exchanges of views among friends of<br />
equal. standing, reconciling differences and building on common<br />
ro&amp;. muh tor' 4U all_ ñ nAenAQtiO'nal-3relatiOnS Were<br />
conhdiuscwtCa yi ~ it~ to tftr h~ g eat challe-<br />
or~ d.<br />
This meeting provides the Commonwealth membera of-tbhis -region<br />
with our first opportunity to use the unique Commonwealth model to<br />
aPt ourselvez to new circumstances and co-operate more effectively-'<br />
-With2 one anothr. This is becoming all the more pressing as each<br />
ya shows more clearly that distance is being eaten awfty an<br />
isolation. is coming. to an end.<br />
We are being drawn together with remark~ able speed, and, as<br />
goeads of Goverrment responsible for'the welfare of our people, we<br />
know we Cann t ignore the implications of our evergrowing inter<br />
dependem e. </p>
<p>We know that there is hardlly anything that one of us can<br />
do for our own economy or security that will not concern another.<br />
We recognise that none can diminish the dignity of one man without<br />
dimnishing the dignity of all-others<br />
J~ oeof us can be visited by calamity, whether due to nature<br />
or the " xisjudgement . of men without it affecting the welfare of<br />
othrs.$ or can any nation improve its position without it holding<br />
oft. hope. for. other nations.<br />
? he reality of our changing world imposes greater obligations<br />
on each of us* Our very presence here ir, evidence of--our comndtmenñ<br />
to explore , every possible way of acting together, whether novel or<br />
not. The-items that fill the agenda of -bur present world are well<br />
known to s2.2 of us.. Poverty, famine, unmzployment, inflation,<br />
erasrgy: Shortage., trade-barri-ers,. growing national indebtedness,<br />
racism-and the, persistence of international conflict.<br />
The impact of these problems has varied greatly because our<br />
2itina vayinsie-in nber si,-in -r-eorce.-Bwt. noae of-us.<br />
~ yar Adt1nzsAl Sues that-engage7 In 8&amp; f-most. profound<br />
way the ingenuity andi goodwill of us all. But our common concerns,<br />
. oir common b6-pe õ ;-za the œ aci that we live in a common regional<br />
. netgborbo .1 ladst tct cu. serh for. i~ olutions -in<br />
this new-forum. Clerl 4&amp;~ s~ onfrqnt*_ th w-emtral ssue bf-the gap between<br />
: icher an orr aions' 6ami i repo eanitngfuly t6 the challenge<br />
of global'inequities. Austrvlia deeply regrets that agreement has not yet been<br />
ached. in the. International-negotiati onol tfe eistablihment -of<br />
~ a co== o 1LUnd to-6tabilise commodity prices.<br />
A c~~ Ofl fund and-the integrated programme on commodities3<br />
can make a significant-contribution to stabilising international1<br />
trade in primary coimodities a stabilisationl at an equitable<br />
-price level which is so Important to the economic progress-of-many<br />
developing c ountries. </p>
<p>We believe developed nations have to show a sense -of<br />
lurge~ y. SX) purpose on this issue. Australia has recently<br />
re-exszined* its own position on this and we hope that there<br />
wllU a œ i-ther-evolution in the views of other developed<br />
n2ations Mhere isa indeed a great need for both developed an~ d<br />
slevalopinri outrie I to reassess their s~ tances. It would<br />
be tragic it we held dogmatically to rtgid-nd-umbendliag<br />
Positions. I hope that our talks here will encourage others<br />
-to u~ ndertake: such -a reassessment.<br />
in the meeting, we will discuss. o. u political environment,<br />
the im~ pact of the international distribution of power in our<br />
region-issues of industrialisation and trade. We will also<br />
aiddress' ourselves to the major problew-&amp; eq energy-scarlity, the<br />
energy requirements of the vJ~ llage and the industrial Metropolis.<br />
In all this there is ample scope for useful and practical<br />
aarteb. a. attgyree. e-e. a n make. te. best possible use<br />
rest.<br />
-b h~ toeto<br />
r~ ontribute to the resolution of the problems we face, and we seek<br />
to om~ plement other forms of association in our region of the<br />
The opportunities of th~ is conference -present a great chal-<br />
' To apply sli2 our energies to these problems;<br />
to explore every possible means of mutual<br />
asBistance; a nd to strive for practical and workmanlike<br />
solutions*..<br />
7his is precisely what the Commonwealtb-stands fox, pnd<br />
this meeting is committed to this goal. </p>
<p>4.5m.-<br />
fay 3: say once again that all Australians join with me in<br />
valcoing you here today. In addition to the Heads of Government,,<br />
we allo welcome-the Comoriwealth Secretary-General. And we, as<br />
the boat-Government, appreciate the contribution which the-<br />
Commonwealth Secretariat-has made* to the arrangements for this<br />
Regiopal. meeting&amp;<br />
inow have great pleasure in formally declaring open this<br />
Firszt Commonwealth Head&amp;-of-Gorment Regional1 Meeting -and'<br />
inviting the-Sec retar-Genera2. to address us.<br />
13 Plebx'uary 1978 Z. 7<br />
7.. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
