<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>24223</transcript-id>
    <title>National Security Statement, Canberra</title>
    <prime-minister>Abbott, Tony</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130918 - 20150915</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/02/2015</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Today, I want to speak to you about keeping our country safe.</p>
<p>I want to speak to you about the threat that we face; the work done already to keep you as safe as we humanly can; and the things still needed to prevent further terrorist attacks.</p>
<p>Today, my colleagues and I are joined by representatives of the Australian Federal Police, the Australian Defence Force, ASIO and agencies like Crimtrac – which helps police and other law enforcement bodies share information.</p>
<p>The men and women in this room are on the frontline of Australia’s fight against terror. </p>
<p>There is no greater responsibility – on me – on the government – than keeping you safe.</p>
<p>This is the responsibility that’s discharged by the men and women in this room.</p>
<p>We know that these are testing times for everyone here – and for everyone sworn to protect democratic freedoms.</p>
<p>The terrorist threat is rising at home and abroad – and it’s becoming harder to combat.</p>
<p>We have seen on our TV screens and in our newspapers the evidence of the new dark age that has settled over much of Syria and Iraq.</p>
<p>We have seen the beheadings, the mass executions, the crucifixions and the sexual slavery in the name of religion.</p>
<p>There is no grievance here that can be addressed; there is no cause here that can be satisfied; it is the demand to submit - or die.</p>
<p>We have seen our fellow Australians – people born and bred to live and let live – succumb to the lure of this death cult.</p>
<p>We have heard the exhortations of their so-called caliphate to kill all or any of the unbelievers.</p>
<p>And we know that this message of the most primitive savagery is being spread through the most sophisticated technology.</p>
<p>By any measure, the threat to Australia is worsening.</p>
<p>The number of foreign fighters is up.</p>
<p>The number of known sympathisers and supporters of extremism is up.</p>
<p>The number of potential home grown terrorists is rising. </p>
<p>The number of serious investigations continues to increase.</p>
<p>During 2014, the Government consulted with our experts – many of whom are in this room today; we talked with our allies; and we worked with the Opposition, to improve Australia’s preparedness for any eventuality.</p>
<p>Last September, the National Terrorist Threat level was lifted to High, which means a terrorist attack is likely.</p>
<p>Critics said we were exaggerating.</p>
<p>But since then, we have witnessed the frenzied attack on two police officers in Melbourne and the horror of the Martin Place siege.</p>
<p>Twenty people have been arrested and charged as a result of six counter terrorism operations conducted around Australia.</p>
<p>That’s one third of all the terrorism-related arrests since 2001 – within the space of just six months.</p>
<p>The judgment to lift the Threat Level was correct.</p>
<p>In proclaiming a caliphate, the Islam-ist death-cult has declared war on the world.</p>
<p>Not only has Australia suffered at the hands of terrorists – but so have Canada, France, Denmark, Iraq, Egypt, Libya, Nigeria, Japan, Jordan, the United Kingdom and the United States.</p>
<p>We have seen the tactics of terrorists evolve.</p>
<p>In the decade after 9/11, our agencies disrupted elaborate conspiracies to attack our electricity supplies, the Grand Final at the MCG and the Holsworthy Army Barracks in Sydney.</p>
<p>Now, in addition to the larger scale, more complex plots that typified the post 9/11 world, such as the atrocities in Bali and London, sick individuals are acting on the caliphate’s instruction to seize people at random and kill them.</p>
<p>Today’s terrorism requires little more than a camera-phone, a knife and a victim. </p>
<p>These lone actor attacks are not new, but they pose a unique set of problems.</p>
<p>All too often, alienated and unhappy people brood quietly.</p>
<p>Feeling persecuted and looking for meaning, they self-radicalise online.</p>
<p>Then they plan attacks which require little preparation, training or capability.</p>
<p>The short lead time from the moment they decide they are going to strike, and then actually undertake the attack, makes it hard to disrupt their activities.</p>
<p>Police do not have the luxury to wait and watch. </p>
<p>They apply their best judgement – and they do so, fully aware that armchair critics, will find fault.</p>
<p>Still, police act because they have enough facts to make an informed judgement. </p>
<p>Some of these raids may not result in prosecution.</p>
<p>But frankly, I’d rather lose a case, than lose a life.</p>
<p>The protection of life must always rank ahead of the prospects of a successful prosecution.</p>
<p>The arrest of two men in Sydney earlier this month, who’d already recorded a pre-attack message, is just one example of how quickly a threat can develop. </p>
<p>I should add that without our Foreign Fighters legislation, it is highly unlikely that these arrests could have been made.</p>
<p>This new terrorist environment is uniquely shaped by the way that extremist ideologies can now spread online.</p>
<p>Every single day, the Islam-ist death cult and its supporters churn out up to 100,000 social media messages in a variety of languages. </p>
<p>Often, they are slick and well produced.</p>
<p>That’s the contagion that’s infecting people, grooming them for terrorism.</p>
<p>Already at least 110 Australians have travelled overseas to join the death cult in Iraq and Syria. </p>
<p>At least 20 of them, so far, are dead.</p>
<p>Even if the flow of foreign fighters to Syria and Iraq stopped today, there’s an Australian cohort of hardened jihadists who are intent on radicalising and influencing others.</p>
<p>The number of Australians with hands-on terrorist experience is now several times larger than those who trained earlier in Afghanistan and Pakistan. </p>
<p>Of that group, two-thirds became involved in terrorist activity back here in Australia. </p>
<p>The signs are ominous.</p>
<p>ASIO currently has over 400 high-priority counter-terrorism investigations. </p>
<p>That’s more than double the number a year ago.</p>
<p>We are not alone in facing such challenges.</p>
<p>The same phenomenon is evident across Europe, in the United States and in South East Asia.</p>
<p>Many of those involved in anti-Western attacks in Indonesia over the last decade are now being released from prison—some neither reformed nor rehabilitated.</p>
<p>Australian and Indonesian agencies will continue to work closely together to tackle extremists – because it is in both our interests to do so.</p>
<p>In Australia and elsewhere, the threat of terrorism has become a terrible fact of life that government must do all in its power to counter.</p>
<p>So far, this is what we have done.</p>
<p>Within weeks of taking office, I asked the Attorney-General to develop a government response to foreign fighters.</p>
<p>Last August, the Government invested $630 million in a range of new counter-terrorism measures.</p>
<p>This funding gives our security agencies the resources they asked for to combat home-grown terrorism and to help prevent Australians participating in terrorism overseas.</p>
<p>The effect of these new measures has already been felt.</p>
<ul><li>Counter-Terrorism Teams now operate at all eight major international airports;</li>
<li>sixty-two additional biometric screening gates are being fast tracked for passengers at airports to detect and deal with people leaving on false passports;</li>
<li>forty-nine extra AFP members are working in Sydney, Melbourne and Canberra on the Foreign Fighter threat;</li>
<li>seven new financial analysts have been engaged to help crack down on terrorist financing;</li>
<li>a new “violent jihadist network mapping unit” in ASIO has been created to improve intelligence agencies’ understanding of the threat facing Australia;</li>
<li>a Foreign Fighters Task Force has been established in the Australian Crime Commission with access to the commission’s coercive powers; and</li>
<li>Last Thursday, the Attorney-General announced a series of measures designed to combat terrorist propaganda online.</li>
<li>We have legislated to cancel the welfare payments of individuals assessed to be a threat to security. </li>
</ul><p>This is not window dressing – as of last September, 55 of the 57 Australian extremists then fighting with terrorist groups in Syria and Iraq had been on welfare.</p>
<p>We have made it easier to ban terrorist organisations which promote and encourage terrorist acts.</p>
<p>We have strengthened the offences of training with, recruiting for and funding terrorist organisations.</p>
<p>We have made it easier to prosecute foreign fighters by making it illegal to travel to a declared area overseas. </p>
<p>Last December, we proscribed travel to Syria’s Al Raqqa province – where the death cult is based – without a legitimate purpose. </p>
<p>We are now looking at listing Mosul district in Ninawa Province, in Iraq, which the death cult also controls.</p>
<p>And we have given ASIO the further power to request an Australian passport be suspended, pending further security assessment - that’s happened eight times so far.</p>
<p>This year, we will consider what further legislation is needed to combat terrorism and keep Australians safe.</p>
<p>But we cannot do it alone.</p>
<p>The Government is working with local communities to counter violent extremism.</p>
<p>I acknowledge the readiness of parents, siblings and community leaders to let the police know about people they think are falling under the death cult’s spell.</p>
<p>Our law enforcement agencies could not operate without their help.</p>
<p>I acknowledge the cooperation the Commonwealth enjoys with all States and Territories on counter-terrorism issues.</p>
<p>That cooperation was highlighted by the Martin Place siege.</p>
<p>Yesterday, Premier Mike Baird and I released the Martin Place Siege Joint Commonwealth - New South Wales Review.</p>
<p>What we learnt from that Review was that there were no major failings of intelligence or process in the lead up to Martin Place. </p>
<p>Everyone did their job as required by law.</p>
<p>But now, there’s more to do.</p>
<p>It’s clear that in too many instances the threshold for action was set too high – and the only beneficiary of that was the Martin Place murderer himself.</p>
<p>For too long, we have given those who might be a threat to our country the benefit of the doubt.</p>
<p>The perpetrator was given the benefit of the doubt when he applied for a visa.</p>
<p>He was given the benefit of the doubt for residency and citizenship.</p>
<p>He was given the benefit of the doubt at Centrelink.</p>
<p>He was given the benefit of the doubt when he applied for legal aid.</p>
<p>And in the courts, there has been bail, when there should have been jail.</p>
<p>This report marks a line in the sand.</p>
<p>There is always a trade-off between the rights of an individual and the safety of the community.</p>
<p>We will never sacrifice our freedoms in order to defend them – but we will not let our enemies exploit our decency either.</p>
<p>If Immigration and Border Protection faces a choice to let-in or keep out people with security questions over them – we should choose to keep them out.</p>
<p>If there is a choice between latitude for suspects or more powers to police and security agencies – more often, we should choose to support our agencies.</p>
<p>And if we can stop hate-preachers from grooming gullible young people for terrorism, we should.</p>
<p>We have already made a start on removing the benefit of the doubt for people who are taking advantage of us.</p>
<p>We’ve introduced legislation to refuse a protection visa to people who destroy evidence of their identity.</p>
<p>And the same applies if you present a bogus document.</p>
<p>This Bill is currently stalled in the Senate. </p>
<p>It’s reasonable. </p>
<p>It’s in our country’s interest. </p>
<p>And I call on all senators to support it.</p>
<p>The Government’s Data Retention Bill – currently being reviewed by the Parliament – is the vital next step in giving our agencies the tools they need to keep Australia safe.</p>
<p>Access to metadata is the common element to most successful counter-terrorism investigations. </p>
<p>It’s essential in fighting most major crimes, including the most abhorrent of all – crimes against children.</p>
<p>Again, I call on Parliament to support this important legislation.</p>
<p>We need to give our agencies these powers to protect our community.</p>
<p>Today, I am releasing the Counter Terrorism review that the Government commissioned last August.</p>
<p>The Review finds that we face a new, long-term era of heightened terrorism threat, with a much more significant ‘home grown’ element.</p>
<p>While the Review did not recommend major structural changes, it did recommend strengthening our counter-terrorism strategy and improving our cooperation with at-risk communities.</p>
<p>The government will carefully consider the findings and act as quickly as possible.</p>
<p>In fact, some recommendations have already been acted upon:</p>
<p>We will ensure returning foreign fighters are prosecuted or closely monitored using strengthened control orders.</p>
<p>We will appoint a National Counter Terrorism Coordinator.</p>
<p>We want to bring the same drive, focus and results to our counter terrorism efforts that worked so well in Operation Sovereign Borders and Operation Bring Them Home.</p>
<p>Over recent months, I spent many hours listening to Australians from all walks of life. </p>
<p>Clearly, people are anxious about the national security threats we face.</p>
<p>Many are angry because all too often the threat comes from someone who has enjoyed the hospitality and generosity of the Australian people.</p>
<p>When it comes to someone like the Martin Place murderer, people feel like we have been taken for mugs.</p>
<p>Australian citizenship is an extraordinary privilege that should involve a solemn and lifelong commitment to Australia.</p>
<p>People who come to this country are free to live as they choose – provided they don’t steal that same freedom from others.</p>
<p>We are one of the most diverse nations on earth – and celebrating that is at the heart of what it means to be Australian.</p>
<p>We are a country built on immigration and are much the richer for it. </p>
<p>Always, Australia will continue to welcome people who want to make this country their home. </p>
<p>We will help them and support them to settle in.</p>
<p>But this is not a one-way street. </p>
<p>Those who come here must be as open and accepting of their adopted country, as we are of them. </p>
<p>Those who live here must be as tolerant of others as we are of them.</p>
<p>No one should live in our country while denying our values and rejecting the very idea of a free and open society.</p>
<p>It’s worth recalling the citizenship pledge that all of us have been encouraged to recite:</p>
<p><em>I pledge my commitment to Australia and its people; whose democratic beliefs I share; whose rights and liberties I respect; and whose laws I will uphold and obey.</em></p>
<p>This has to mean something.</p>
<p>Especially now that we face a home-grown threat from people who do reject our values.</p>
<p>Today, I am announcing that the Government will look at new measures to strengthen immigration laws, as well as new options for dealing with Australian citizens who are involved in terrorism. </p>
<p>We cannot allow bad people to use our good nature against us.</p>
<p>The Government will develop amendments to the Australian Citizenship Act so that we can revoke or suspend Australian citizenship in the case of dual nationals.</p>
<p>It has long been the case that people who fight against Australia forfeit their citizenship.</p>
<p>Australians who take up arms with terrorist groups, especially while Australian military personnel are engaged in Afghanistan and Iraq, have sided against their country and should be treated accordingly.</p>
<p>For Australian nationals, we are examining suspending some of the privileges of citizenship for individuals involved in terrorism.</p>
<p>Those could include restricting the ability to leave or return to Australia, and access to consular services overseas, as well as access to welfare payments.</p>
<p>We will also clamp down on those organisations that incite religious or racial hatred.</p>
<p>No-one should make excuses for Islam-ist fanatics in the Middle East or their imitators here in Australia.</p>
<p>For a long time, successive governments have been concerned about organisations that breed hatred, and sometimes incite violence. </p>
<p>Organisations and individuals blatantly spreading discord and division – such as Hizb ut-Tahrir – should not do so with impunity.</p>
<p>Today, I can confirm that the Government will be taking action against hate preachers.</p>
<p>This includes enforcing our strengthened terrorism advocacy laws.</p>
<p>It includes new programmes to challenge terrorist propaganda and to provide alternative online material based on Australian values.</p>
<p>And it will include stronger prohibitions on vilifying, intimidating or inciting hatred.</p>
<p>These changes should empower community members to directly challenge terrorist propaganda.</p>
<p>I’ve often heard Western leaders describe Islam as a ‘religion of peace’.</p>
<p>I wish more Muslim leaders would say that more often, and mean it.</p>
<p>I have often cited Prime Minister Najib of Malaysia, who has described the Islamist death cult as ‘against God, against Islam and against our common humanity’.</p>
<p>In January, President al Sisi told the imams at Egypt’s al Azhar university that Islam needed a ‘religious revolution’ to sweep away centuries of false thinking.</p>
<p>Everybody, including Muslim community leaders, needs to speak up clearly because, no matter what the grievance, violence against innocents must surely be a blasphemy against all religion.</p>
<p>I can’t promise that terrorist atrocities won’t ever again take place on Australian soil.</p>
<p>But let me give you this assurance:</p>
<p>My Government will never underestimate the threat.</p>
<p>We will make the difficult decisions that must be taken to keep you and your family safe.</p>
<p>We have the best national security agencies and the best police forces in the world. </p>
<p>Our agencies are working together.</p>
<p>All levels of government are working together.</p>
<p>We are doing our duty.</p>
<p>That is what you have a right to expect – and to demand of me and of us.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
