<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10283</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP JOINT PRESS CONFERENCE WITH THE PRIME MINISTER OF THE REPUBLIC OF SINGAPORE MR GOH CHOK TONG SINGAPORE 27 MARCH 1997</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/03/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010283.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP<br />
JOINT PRESS CONFERENCE WITH THE<br />
PRIME MINISTER OF THE REPUBLIC OF SINGAPORE<br />
MR GOH CHOK TONG<br />
SINGAPORE<br />
27 MARCH 1997<br />
E&amp; OE<br />
Prime Minister Goh<br />
Ladies and gentlemen we have had a very good meeting. Our relations are excellent. I<br />
am very happy to have the opportunity to continue our dialogue which we had in Manila.<br />
Basically the foundation of the framework of our bilateral relations are very strong. It's<br />
now for the private sectors of both sides to flesh the framework and we want to<br />
encourage them to do so.<br />
We also discussed developments in the region and we shared our views on how we see<br />
things in the years ahead. We also discussed the international economy and all in all we<br />
have had a good discussion.<br />
Prime Minister Howard<br />
Well I'd like to echo everything that the Prime Minister has said. We, of course, have<br />
had personal exchanges at a political level going back a long time. First of all as fellow<br />
Finance Minister, or Finance Minister and Treasurer at Asian Development Bank<br />
Meetings. We had a very lengthy and enjoyable discussion at the APEC meeting in<br />
Manila last year.<br />
The bilateral relationship is in very fine fettle. It's a very strong bilateral relationship and<br />
I'm delighted that one of the things that we have been able to announce today and<br />
finalise today is the new aviation agreement which will bring great benefits to both<br />
countries and we will each say something in more detail in a moment. But one of the<br />
very valuable things about today's meeting was our ability to talk about our shared<br />
aspirations in relation to APEC. I was most interested in the Prime Minister's views on<br />
both the economic and political future of the region. His views on the important role of<br />
China. I want to congratulate the Prime Minister on his very successful hosting of the World<br />
Trade Organisation meeting here in Singapore in December. It brought great credit both<br />
to him and to Singapore and it was a valuable meeting for us and a very important </p>
<p>reminder to all of the nations of this region of the value, the long term value of trade<br />
liberalisation. And the Prime Minister of Singapore, of course, as the leader of a country<br />
which has practiced trade liberalisation with great energy and great success for a very<br />
long period of time is no stranger to the link between trade liberalisation and job<br />
generation. And it's a message that is required to be repeatedly communicated to the<br />
populations and within the nations of the region. But it has been a very valuable morning<br />
and I want to thank the Prime Minister and I want to thank the Government of Singapore<br />
for having me as their guest and I have invited the Prime Minister, at a time convenient<br />
to him, to visit Australia. He, of course, is no stranger to our country and indeed there<br />
are many citizens of this country and I will be meeting the alumni of Australian<br />
universities from Singapore this afternoon.<br />
The President and his wife were both educated at Adelaide University and as you roam<br />
through these discussions it's a reminder of the very long history of bilateral people links<br />
between Australia and Singapore.<br />
Prime Minister Goh<br />
Before you ask a question perhaps you could state your name and organisation.<br />
Journalist Prime Minister Terry O'Connor from the Australian Associated Press and I ask both of<br />
you was the question of the Australian race debate last year raised ( inaudible)?<br />
Prime Minister Howard<br />
No Journalist Prime Minister Goh, Glenn Milne from the Seven Network just in the light of that<br />
question, I noticed this morning in The Straits Times an article commenting on the<br />
formation of a political party in Australia by the MNP ( inaudible) the race debate. Are you<br />
disappointed that this issue is still running?<br />
Prime Minister Gob<br />
This is Australian politics, I am not disappointed or neither am I glad I think it is<br />
something for the Prime Minister to comment. It is the affairs of his political party not<br />
me. Prime Minister Howard<br />
Free country. People can form political parties. Could I just say, perhaps somebody will<br />
ask me, I wanted to say something about the aviation agreement. So that's just a<br />
reminder as we role on, I don't want to interrupt the flow of questions but somebody<br />
might do that because I gave you the opportunity to do so. </p>
<p>Journalist Prime Minister Goh, Paul Smith from the Ten Network is Australia's race debate still in<br />
any way an issue in Singapore or in Asia?<br />
Prime Minister Goh<br />
No, it's not a big issue I've given my views and there is a television interview. It's<br />
purely domestic politics for Australia But as I explained, we in Singapore would be very<br />
much against bringing race into politics. We would have come up very strongly on<br />
anybody who tries to use race in order to advance his own politics. But for Australia I<br />
have no comments.<br />
Journalist ( inaudible)<br />
Prime Minister Gob<br />
No, in general we exchanged views on how we see developments and both of us believe<br />
that China and the US are now engaged positively in the longer term developments and<br />
that is good for us we encourage it.<br />
Journalist Prime Minister Goh, Matthew Frost from SBS TV News the difficulty that your<br />
country is having with Malaysia at the moment, what's your reaction to the Malaysian<br />
Cabinet decision to freeze bilateral ties?<br />
Prime Minister Gob<br />
Well I think I want to take some time getting to understand the latest reaction before I<br />
give further comments.<br />
Journalist Prime Minister Howard, Glenn Milne from the Seven Network did you discuss the<br />
situation in PNG? Can we have comments from both of you on the current situation?<br />
Prime Minsiter Howard<br />
Well we did. I explained to the Prime Minister of Singapore some of the background. I<br />
talked about the discussions that I had had with Sir Julius Chan in Sydney almost three<br />
weeks ago and put to him the basis of Australian policy in relation to the events of the<br />
last few days. Can I say that both of us were concerned to ensure and we noted with<br />
approval the fact that the elected civilian government remained in control of the<br />
situation. And although as all of you know I and my government have been very critical<br />
of the introduction of mercenaries into the region and made that very plain to Sir Julius<br />
Chan. Equally we were very critical of any suggestion that the military in Papua New<br />
Guinea should assert itself independently of the elected civilian government. Both the </p>
<p>Prime Minister of Singapore and the Prime Minister of Australia are great believers in the<br />
authority of the civilian duly elected government over the military.<br />
Journalist Can you tell us the substance of the aviation agreement and how it will benefit both<br />
countries? Prime Minister Howard<br />
Well the aviation agreement will result in something like 28-30 additional Jumbo flights<br />
from the two countries. It will result in a 100% increase in the freight capacity out of<br />
Australia into Singapore. That incidentally is directly relevant to the supermarket for<br />
Asia strategy being pursued by my government. It's going result in something like a<br />
371/ 2% increase in the traffic flows between the two countries. It really is a first class<br />
agreement and of enormous benefit to both Singapore and Australia and a reminder of<br />
the still burgeoning tourist traffic and the rising number of applications for visitor visas<br />
for Singapore into Australia. I mean, given the size it is a remarkably strong people to<br />
people association.<br />
Journalist Prime Minister, Terry O'Connor from AAP have you been able to quantify the increase<br />
in exports that you can expect from this new aviation agreement?<br />
Prime Minister Howard<br />
Well it's very hard to put a figure on it, I can't. But when you increase your freight<br />
capacity by 100% in a single stroke and one of the goals of Supermarket to Asia strategy<br />
is the capacity to export fresh food into the region. As the Prime Minister reminded we<br />
already have a very impressive share, something like 12% of the fresh food market in<br />
Singapore and that is something that can be built upon. But the greater capacity that this<br />
gives us is very significant but I can't, for obvious reasons, put a dollar figure on it.<br />
Prime Minister Goh<br />
Have a look at this in a very symbolical way. It means that both countries want to have<br />
more trade and investments with one another. When you liberalise your air services<br />
agreement, that is going to lead to further flow in tourism and also in investors going to<br />
Australia and Australians coming to Singapore. Symbolically that's a very important<br />
step which we have taken. ( inaudible) we want to engage each other more positively,<br />
free up our economies and have more trade with one another.<br />
Journalist Prime Minister Goh, Catherine McGrath, Australian Broadcasting Corporation can I<br />
ask you on the Malaysian incident once more. It must be a bit concerning for you to<br />
have the headlines of the ( inaudible) the day John Howard arrives in Singapore<br />
Prime Minister Goh </p>
<p>I'ye given my comments to the gentleman there just now, so I would stick to the same<br />
comments. Journalist How long do you think it might take for the problem to die down?<br />
Prime Minister Gob<br />
Well, I think I will still stick to the same comment. I want to absorb the implications of<br />
all this before I give further comments. Next question.<br />
Journalist Prime Minister Howard, Jim Middleton from ABC Television why did the committee in<br />
the Senate, Senator Calvert chairs decide to move off the Work for the Dole scheme to a<br />
Senate Committee? ( inaudible)<br />
Prime Minister Howard<br />
I think now that I'm in Singapore I should, unlike some others who's name escapes me,<br />
not comment too heavily on domestic politics.<br />
Journalist ( inaudible)<br />
Prime Minister Howard<br />
Well I think Singapore brings in any bilateral exchanges between our two governments<br />
brings a perspective which is different from ours. I'm not saying whether it's better or<br />
worse, it's different. It's not a question of being better or worse but one of the<br />
enormous values for me, particularly as I'm on the way to China, of coming here first is<br />
to hear what a man who's been at the helm of his country's affairs in the region for<br />
longer than I have been at the helm of my country's affairs hear his views on China and I<br />
found them very valuable and as I'm sure in a reciprocal situation he would find mine.<br />
Journalist I wonder if you could give us an indication of the flavour of the discussion abut China?<br />
Prime Minister Howard<br />
Well I think both of us have a very positive view about the role of China in the region.<br />
Both of us believe that China should be engaged in the region. Both of us support the<br />
accession of China to the World Trade Organisation on proper terms. Both of us<br />
recognise the desire of the United States that China be constructively involved in the<br />
region. And one of the messages that I will be repeating to the Chinese government is<br />
that we want China to be a full constructive, positive player in the region. We don't in </p>
<p>any way see China in a negative light in the region, we seen China in a positive light.<br />
And it makes sense from China's point of view, from our point of view, from the regions<br />
point of view that all of us in our different ways encourage that positive engagement.<br />
There will be differences, there will always be some significant differences between China<br />
and Australia on certain issues because we are different societies but our approach is to<br />
focus on the pragmatic practical future interests that we have in common.<br />
Journalist Is there any progress in your attempts to join the ( inaudible)<br />
Prime Minister Howard<br />
Any problems?<br />
Prime Minister Gob<br />
Any progress<br />
Prime Minister Howard<br />
Any progress? Well I certainly want to put on record my appreciation of the support<br />
that's been given to me and my country by the Prime Minister of Singapore. He has<br />
been very helpful, very positive. Our view is that it would be appropriate for Australia to<br />
join that organisation. We're not fretting about whether or not we become a member but<br />
we think we could bring value to the grouping. We do not wish to see groupings of that<br />
kind in any way cut across the way in which APEC brings people from the Pacific area<br />
generally together. It's one of the great strengths of APEC. It is a congruence of<br />
countries that are different geographically, different economically, different in size,<br />
different in so many ways and we wouldn't want other groupings to in any way dilute<br />
that but Singapore has been very positive. We'll keep putting our view on that, but as I<br />
say, although it's important to us it's something over which we're not going to fret.<br />
Journalist Mr Howard, Louise Maher from Radio 2UE given the international interest in the<br />
Sydney 2000 Olympics. Are you concerned at all about the changes in the leadership of<br />
SOCOG? </p>
<p>Prime Minister Howard<br />
Oh look I really don't want to talk about domestic politics and that is very domestic and<br />
although you have to give a liberal interpretation to what is domestic politics as I think I<br />
have, I mean Papua New Guinea is a fairly but I really think something like that or<br />
Work for the Dole in fairness to the Acting Prime Minister, I do think I should avoid<br />
make comments on those things now that I'm out of Australia. Last question.<br />
Journalist Mr Howard one domestic issue that you might not want to pass up on sir what about the<br />
Shadow Ministry reshuffle Kim Beazley reshuffling the deckchairs?<br />
Prime Minister Howard<br />
No, I will pass up on that and with great pre-Easter restraint invite the Deputy Prime<br />
Minister, Acting Prime Minister of Australia to comment on that as I'm sure he will.<br />
Prime Minister Goh<br />
Unless you have an answer to that question I will call the conference to a stop. Have<br />
you got an answer to which they haven't asked a question?<br />
Prime Minister Howard<br />
Thank you. Thank you very much.<br />
Prime Minister Goh<br />
Thank you.<br />
End </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
