<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6971</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE, ABC STUDIO, 4 JULY 1986</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/07/1986</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006971.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL No. it y. 04,07,86 12: 41 P. 01<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFE~ RENCE, -ABC STUDIO,. HOBART<br />
4 JULY 1986<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: money market, why do you think that<br />
PM: Well, I suppose you have got to assume that in some caseso<br />
there are people who believe that they will make a killing out<br />
of what they calculate will be the reaction to such rumours.<br />
NOw, I guess this is the price that you have to pay when you<br />
free up the market. I regret it, that those sort of things<br />
happen, but it is the price you have to pay. I Wish that<br />
there were people in-this area who would show the sort<br />
of responsibility which they demand of others, say particularly<br />
unionists. I guess the same sort of people are saying that<br />
the wharfies are damaging Australia by having a couple of<br />
days strike about superannuation. It would be the same sort<br />
of people who are exercising a great degree of irresponsibility<br />
themselves. JOURNALIST: Do you regret having floated the dollar?<br />
PH: No, of course. We would be paying a much worse<br />
price if we hadn't floated the dollar because the fundamentals<br />
are that there are these changes in the terms of trade which<br />
means we are getting less for what we sell. -And so your exchange<br />
rate has to reflect that. Now, under a floating system that<br />
is happening. The movement has been, as I say, exacerbated to<br />
some extent by, I think, tome degrees of irresponsibility that<br />
have been taking place. Fundamentally, there would have had to<br />
have been an adjustment. Now* if you had had a system of a<br />
continuation of a fixed exchange rate with the Government and<br />
the REserve Blank meeting to fix the rate and trying to sustain<br />
the rate against, those pressures, then it would have imposed<br />
an intolerable pressure upon monetary policy and woul1d havemeant<br />
that interest, rates would have been right through the roof:<br />
So it is appropriate to have a deregulated exchange rate. It is<br />
a pity that to some extent there hasn't been a proper reading<br />
of what is happening in this country. There has been some sort<br />
of expectation that you are, going to produce an instant budget.<br />
What they have got to understand is that the Government is going<br />
through the hard slogging process of reviewing expenditures,<br />
looking at revenues, to bring down a budget on budget nightthe<br />
19th of August which will be the one that is right and<br />
necessary for the conduct of economic policy in this country.<br />
We have got the budget right in ' 83, ' 84, ' 85. We will get<br />
it right again in ' 86. </p>
<p>T N04., 0786 19&gt;: 4 P n') 2.<br />
JOURNALIST: And that rumour about Lhe retirement of Paul<br />
Keating yesterday was, in your words, a " complete bloody furphy"?<br />
PM: A complete furphy. And never any basis for it at all. He<br />
is still an outstanding Treasurer and is still working ceaselessly<br />
to do the job which is necessary to get the right policy settings.<br />
As I say, we have got them right. We have shown the capacity . in<br />
the past. to adjust to-changing economic circumstances. And we<br />
will do it again.<br />
JOURNALIST: You said some harsh words this morning about<br />
Australian companies or management, particularly, being hopeless.<br />
would you like to<br />
PM: Let me put that in its general context. Of course, there<br />
are outstanding managements in this country who have done some<br />
marvellous things. The thing that rather annoys me is that<br />
you have spokesmen, so-called spokesmen, from national employer<br />
organisations like the CAI and so on, getting up and saying<br />
Australia can't compete, our cost structure is too high. Now,<br />
I am not saying that every element of our cost structure is<br />
right, but what I am saying is that those people are talking<br />
bloody nonsense. And it is about time they stopped talking<br />
their country down. Let them come along with me and go and<br />
see as I did on Wednesday this company operating in the<br />
highest area of technology, the most competitive in -the world.<br />
And that Australian company with vigorous, imaginative management<br />
and a co-operative workforce is out there beating the pants off<br />
the rest of the world. Fifty per cent of the world's market<br />
Latk. L, * exw, n nry ri hh -ntinl nrnnnrtinn nf the. marhi<br />
in Ameriud diid in Europe ana thc rot of thu wuLl' œ 0r<br />
pacemakers, heart pacemakers. Now, you can't be operaLing in<br />
a more competitive, tougher area, and they are doing it with<br />
the existing Australian cost structure. And they are out<br />
there winning. By 1990 that -company will have half a billion<br />
dollars worth of sales with 90 per cent of them from exports.<br />
Now what I am saying is that we can do it. It doesn't mean that<br />
we should be complacent or that we should accept that every<br />
element of our existing cost structure is perfect, or every<br />
work practice is right, because they are not. But with what<br />
we have got, we can win. And it is about time that some of<br />
these people with their narrow, vested political perceptions,<br />
Lhey should otop knooking Australia, they Ahnild recognise that<br />
we can 4fnd are winning, when wo chow the right management<br />
initiatives and when you get. the co-operation of the workforce.<br />
If one company, two companies, three companies, if you have got<br />
_-one company this one that I am talking about that has got<br />
150 million dollars worth of sales this year with 90 per cent<br />
exports, going out right there into the heart of the rest of<br />
the world, in America, and in Europe, and beating the rest of<br />
the world. Now if one company can do it in that area and have,<br />
as I say, by 1900, they expect to have half a billion dollars<br />
worth of sales, with 90 per cent of it into export, itcan be<br />
done. And if the business leaders have some sense of commitment<br />
and loyalty to their own country they would be recognising what<br />
could be done what is being done, rather than getting up with<br />
their pacn of complaints. / 3<br />
TEL No. </p>
<p>3.<br />
JOURNALIST: You did seem to be rercrring to management<br />
techniques this morning. You said a lot of Australian companies<br />
should be taken over because the managements are bloody hopeless.<br />
That is pretty tough, isn't it?<br />
PM: And it is pr'etty accurate too. This sort of story that<br />
goes around that there is something intrinsically undesirable<br />
about takeover is a nonsense. I won'It name the* company but there<br />
is -a company in Aus3tralia at the moment which should have done<br />
and it is not BHP because I don't want to give some suggestion<br />
that I am getting into tJ~ at fight a company which is subject<br />
to takeover specL-ulation. Now, in my judgement it would be the<br />
best thing for Australia that could possibly happen if it was<br />
taken over. because it has missed opportunities, it hasn't shown<br />
the imagination that -it should have done. It could have done<br />
much more for competing with imports, it could have done much<br />
more to go out and win exports if it had irnqginative management.<br />
Now, igo. babk because I have been there this week to visit this<br />
company, there are ordinary Australians got together a good team<br />
of management, putting a lot of money into research and developmen<br />
which is what you have got to do, taking advantage of government<br />
schemes which they recognise are amongst the most generous in<br />
the world that we have brought in-to stimulate research and<br />
development. And they are saying now on the basis of the<br />
framework that the Government has created that we can go out<br />
and beat the rest of-. the world. And if, by getting new<br />
management in some of our companies you are going to get<br />
better performance then all Australians should have a vested<br />
initerest in it.<br />
JOURNALIST: What do you expect criticism of the money markets<br />
and manufacturers to achieve? It sounds a bit desperate doesn't<br />
it?<br />
PM: Not desperate at all. I am simply rc.. ponding to a situation<br />
where there is some suggestion that as far as internal Australian<br />
economic policy settings are concerned that there is something<br />
wrong, that that is creating an incapacity for Australians to<br />
perform and compete. And it is essential that that myth be disa<br />
Gover not wtllue. chtosnt maou the usnsto improvi ngth<br />
Itoisrnoet true. Tha osnt manou the casn't o improvintg<br />
policy setting because I would be guilty of a very serious<br />
mistake if I just ' sat complacently back and said everything<br />
as far as Government decisions are right, They are not and<br />
we want to continue to improve them. But what I am trying to<br />
say is that the business spokesmen who try and.. impose upon<br />
the workers of this country the blame for what is happening<br />
and saying look it is the existing cost structure, the existing<br />
union attitudes that is the problems, are being miscreant in<br />
their duty -because we have the lowest level of industrial<br />
disputation that we have had in this country for 20 years. We<br />
have the most competitive position that we have since the end<br />
of the 1960s and that is the official competitive index. So<br />
conditions are there and the get up and go companies are<br />
operating remarkably successfully within that environment. And.<br />
the time has come when we have got to recognise that the world<br />
has made a judgement about what they are going to pay for our<br />
traditional exports for our wool and our wheat and our meat<br />
and those sorts of things which constitute such a high propo<br />
of our traditional exports. Now we have got to recognise that, / 4<br />
TEL No. 04,07-86 12: 45 P ni </p>
<p>ILL No. U4, U(, 8b 12: 45 F. U2 4.<br />
PM contt we have got Lo &amp; LreiLhei and diversify the rest<br />
of our economic base and that is what we are doing. And the<br />
message that 1 want Australian management to get i4 that thei*<br />
colleagues in various areas are showing that in those areas<br />
they can take on the rest of the world and beat them. Now, if<br />
they areprepared to show the same sort of imagination there<br />
are hundred I believe, and indeed literally thousands of<br />
Australian companies that can do the same thing. And if these<br />
companies that I have talked about are doing it in the suosL<br />
competitive, toughest, hi-tech area then it can be done in<br />
others. I am not slating Australian management generally, there<br />
are many of them who are very,. very good. But what I am slating<br />
is this complacency, this preparedness to blame others.-the<br />
workers and so on, or government and say it is all too hard.<br />
it is not all too hard. If we are prepared to work and work<br />
together we can take on and beat the rest of the world and that<br />
is what I am talking about.<br />
JOURNALIST: inaudible question<br />
PM: It is not the Government's fault. We have all got to accept<br />
some responsibility for the ' lucky country' syndrome. I have tri<br />
to say before that if you look at the whole of the post-war<br />
period in this country, we have had it lucky. Immediately<br />
after the war the rest of the world, the devastated war-torn<br />
world, wanted our wheat and our wool and those sort of products<br />
and were prepared to pay the-world for them. Then as the prices<br />
came down there, we had our first mineral boom, and so we were<br />
carried on through that. Then we had a second minerals boom.<br />
But all those lucky country syridrome efœ ecLs are over. And<br />
we have got to understand that they are over. We are not going<br />
to have some bonanza suddenly appear out of there. The cargo<br />
cult mentality. It is gone. What we have. got to do is by our<br />
own efforts, diversity, strengthen, our economy. And that is<br />
what we are doing. It is happening. The capauity is ouL there.<br />
If you get the right management, you will get the co-operation<br />
of the workforce. We have got the incentives there, of assistanc<br />
to enterprise to perform. We have got to recognise that that<br />
is the new game, the new ballgame that we are in. And if we<br />
play it hard and play it co-operatively,, we will win.<br />
JOURNALIST: Commonwealth for the local tax increases?<br />
i-M: ML Gray '. is again bein9cOnsistent. Consiotently untruthful.<br />
He said, he has talked about cuts of a 150 million. He is wrong.<br />
He knows he is lying. I just wish he would stop it. The facts<br />
are that in the last 2 years we have given 62 million dollars<br />
extra, beyond and above what was required by the independent<br />
Commonwealth Grants Commission. He has talked about cuttiny<br />
I0 million, we haven't, We have given 62 million beyond whaL<br />
was required. what is happening to Tasmania aL the moment is<br />
that Mr Gray in his last budget, he knew he had an election<br />
coming up, he had a three per cent real increase in expenditures<br />
He went on a vote buying budget. Irresponsibly. Ana now he<br />
is making Tasmanians pay. We have gone beyond 62 million<br />
what was necessary. And I did it deliberately because I didn't<br />
want to hurt the people of Tasmania. I didn't want to say, as<br />
the Grants Commission said, well that is all they should get.<br />
1 have tried to ease the transition burden. They are still<br />
getting Tasmanians are still getting the highest per capita </p>
<p>TEL No. 04.07.86 12: 46 P. 03<br />
PM cont: revenue from the Commzonwealth of any State. And that<br />
is in part because I deliberately was noL going to allow<br />
them to be hurt as a result of the straight implementation of<br />
that independent Commonwealth Granto Commission. But let me<br />
say this, that the one danger that the people of Tasmania.<br />
have in regard to the questions of . relations with Commonwealth<br />
is the incapacity of their Premier* to speak~ truthfully, to deal<br />
truthfully. ends No. 04.07.86 12: 46 P. 03 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
