<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>24581</transcript-id>
    <title>New drug listing Keytruda to treat melanoma </title>
    <prime-minister>Abbott, Tony</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130918 - 20150915</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/06/2015</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Commonwealth Government will invest $57 million to list breakthrough melanoma drug Keytruda® on the Pharmaceutical Benefits Scheme.</p>
<p>This will improve quality of life for 1,100 Australian patients and make the $150,000 per year treatment affordable.</p>
<p>The listing follows passage of the Government’s PBS reform package through the Senate last week and delivers on our promise to list new medicines as quickly as possible.</p>
<p>It complements $1.3 billion from the 2015/16 Budget for other melanoma medicines as well as drugs to treat breast cancer, blindness and shingles.</p>
<p>Treatment using pembrolizumab (Keytruda®) currently costs patients with metastatic melanoma up to $156,130 per year without taxpayer subsidy through the PBS.</p>
<p>Patients will now pay $6.10 if they are concessional patients or $37.70 for general patients.</p>
<p>Since coming to office, the Commonwealth has now approved 667 new and amended listings to the PBS, with a benefit of almost $3 billion to Australian patients.</p>
<p>This compares with only 331 new listings in Labor’s final term.</p>
<p>Today’s announcement demonstrates the importance of ensuring that spending on existing drugs is as efficient as possible, so breakthrough medicines like Keytruda® can continue to be listed.</p>
<p>Treatment will be made available on the PBS from 1 September, 2015.</p>
<p>All PBS listings are subject to final arrangements being agreed with suppliers of the medicine, including risk share arrangements.</p>
<p>Since coming to office in September 2013, the Commonwealth has listed the following medicines, among others, on the PBS:<br />
                                                                                    <br />
• Soliris (2014) – Atypical Haemolytic-Uraemic Syndrome (rare immune disease) – $63 million – $500,000 per patient if not subsidised through the PBS<br />
• Kayldeco (2014) – Cystic Fibrosis – $174 million – $300,000 per patient if not subsidised through the PBS<br />
• Mekinist (2015) – BRAF-positive Metastatic Melanoma – $437 million – $131,000 per patient if not subsidised through the PBS<br />
• Adcetris (2014) – Lymphoma – $15.2 million – over $110,000 per patient if not subsidised through the PBS<br />
• Perjeta, Herceptin and Kadcyla (2015) – Breast Cancer – $191 million combined – $82,000 per patient if not subsidised through the PBS<br />
• Crizotinib (2015) – Lung Cancer – $60 million – $80,000 per patient if not subsidised through the PBS<br />
• Lemtrada (2015) – Relapsing, Remitting Multiple Sclerosis – $50 million – $70,000 per patient if not subsidised through the PBS<br />
• Abraxane (2014) – Pancreatic Cancer – $92 million – $16,000 per patient if not subsidised through the PBS<br />
• Lucentis (2015) – Retinal Vein Occlusion (RVO) and Diabetic Macular Oedema (DME) (blindness) – $541 million – $10,000 per patient if not subsidised through the PBS</p>
<p>Listing these medicines on the PBS means patients pay just the PBS co-payment, with taxpayers covering the difference in the cost of treatment. For example, a patient using Soliris – which costs $500,000 per patient – now pays just $6.10 if they are a concession card holder or $37.70 if they are a general patient as a result of the drug being listed on the taxpayer-funded PBS.</p>
<p>
28 June 2015<br />
 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
