<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2762</transcript-id>
    <title>BROADCAST ON RADIO AUSTRALIA BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR WHITLAM, CANBERRA, 23 DECEMBER 1972</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/12/1972</release-date>
    <release-type>Broadcast</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002762_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PIZESS 13Tki-': 2I1TT ,1O. 29<br />
22 December 1972<br />
BROALCAST 011 ?. ADIO AU&amp; T2ALIA. BY P EIii INIñ 12.<br />
I. ITLA, CAij. BEiRA, 23 DECEMBER 1972<br />
This is the Prime Minister of Australia, Gough Jhitlam,<br />
speaking to you by the facilities of 2. adio Australia. 2adio Australia<br />
has asked me to make this broadcast so that the millions of people<br />
who know and trust this radio service might get some idea of the<br />
intentions of the new Government which has just been elected here<br />
in Australia. So the first thing I would like to say is about 2adio<br />
Australia itself. My new Government wants ' adio Australia to keep<br />
going exactly in the same way as it has cone in the past years. The<br />
iustralian Government the government which has just been defeated<br />
in the election as much as my own government has never used and<br />
shall never use 2adio Australia as a propaganda machine. There has<br />
never been any difference between our Australian political parties<br />
about this. . adio Australia will continue to be completely<br />
independent, completely free to report the news as it truly is,<br />
Radio Australia is not the voice of the Australian Government.<br />
It is the voice of Australia, and the speakers and writers whose<br />
work you hear are expressing their own views, not the imposed views<br />
of my Government, or any Government. They can do and say what they<br />
like, according to their professional judgement and skills, to bring<br />
you the best, most honest programs.<br />
But there has been a change of Government in Lustralia<br />
a change brought about just by a majority of the Australian people<br />
exercising their choice through the ballot box. The previous Government<br />
had been in power for 23 years; but when the will of the people<br />
became clear on election night, the previous Prime Minister, Mr.<br />
iElciahon, immediately said that the will of the people was clear and<br />
the power of government must therefore be turned over to me and my<br />
party. And it -was done within a few hours completely, quietly,<br />
efficiently. And the great thing about the democratic system is<br />
that this is how it happens. Today, my colleagues of the new<br />
Government and I have working, with us and for us, the whole of<br />
Australia's great and dedicated civil service the same men and<br />
women who have been serving a different Government for 23 years<br />
past, now giving us the same faithful, loyal service they gave<br />
our defeated opponents. </p>
<p>-3-<br />
Yet, in this context, it would be churlish not to<br />
acknowledge our traditional, our deep and abiding relationship with<br />
the United States. In the great essentials, there will, under my<br />
Government, be no decisive change in that relationship. The treaty<br />
bctween Australia, iTew Zecland and the United Stat. as, . thie. JAZUS treaty,<br />
will remain the crucial treaty for Australia, Indeed, we shall try<br />
to make A ITZUS live again, more constructive,, mor-fruitful, more<br />
meaningful, than it has ever been. It is my Government's profound<br />
belief that V ietnam did not end America's role in our noighbourhood;<br />
it ended the destructive part of that role, and we believe a ner,<br />
better and magnificently constructive role lies ahead for the United<br />
States, if only we in this region can help encourage the American<br />
people the most generous, most idealistic people in history to<br />
accept this new role. But it depends on us all of us in this region<br />
as much as on them.<br />
Let me say this I am tremendously confident about the<br />
prospects for our region. There is every chance that over the next<br />
years the rich countries like ustralia, Hew Zoaland, Japan and the<br />
United States will accept greater responsibility in making a determined<br />
and combined attack on the poverty, starvation, illiteracy, that keep<br />
us all b. ack, and lessen all of us as human beings. There will be no<br />
international war in our region in our time. Let us all use this<br />
unparallelled opportunity! Let us make this our objective that<br />
every child now born in our part of the world shall have a chance<br />
for a life without fear, without want, without war. Is this an<br />
impossible goal? Perhaps but why, in the name of reason, in the<br />
name of humanity, should we set our sights at less? Lot us at least<br />
make the attempt. Years ago, I said, in a rather bleak time for my<br />
party, " Let us now begin". For our region I say, with hope and<br />
confidence, " Let us now begin aneow".<br />
CA~ IS. BZjAi A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
