<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2927</transcript-id>
    <title>TASK FORCE ON THE NATIONAL ESTATE</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/05/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002927.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
-AUSlI( ALIA<br />
Press Statement No. 92<br />
16 May, 1973<br />
TASK FORCE ON THE NATIONAL ESTATE<br />
Mr Justice Hope, of the Court of Appeal division<br />
of the Supreme Court of New South Wales, has agreed to act as<br />
Chairman of the Government's proposed Task Force on the<br />
National Estate.<br />
I am grateful to Mr Justice Hope for his ready<br />
agreement to chair this important inquiry and to the Premier<br />
and Government of New South Wales for releasing him for this work.<br />
I pay tribute to the Government of New South Wales for<br />
its ready co-operation in projects of this kind. They have<br />
made available the services of five Justices of the Supreme<br />
Court of New South Wales to participate in commissions of<br />
inquiry initiated by the Australian Government.<br />
It is anticipated that the work of the Task Force<br />
will be conducted by a Committee of seven with a permanent<br />
secretariat supplied by the Departments of Urban and Regional<br />
Development and of the Environment and Conservation. The Committee<br />
will advertise for submissions and hold public hearings in the<br />
States. The work of the Committee is expected to take several<br />
months. In Mr Justice Hope we will have a-Chairman of great<br />
capacity and experience, with a sympathetic understanding of<br />
the problems which the Task Force will face.<br />
The Task Force is needed because increasing numbers of<br />
Australians are concerned to preserve for the enjoyment of<br />
future generations the best buildings of our past and the best<br />
features of our natural environment. This concern is shared<br />
by Governments. The Australian Government is committed to the preservation<br />
and enhancement of the National Estate. The concept of the<br />
National Estate embraces such things as historic buildings and<br />
towns, buildings of architectural merit, major parks, nature<br />
reserves, urban parks, scenic reserves, areas along the coastline<br />
and so on. 2/ </p>
<p>2.<br />
The Task Force will be asked to advise the<br />
Australian Government on any additional measures and policies<br />
which should be applied to preserve and enhance the National<br />
Estate and the role the Australian Government can play in<br />
assisting the implementation of these measures and policies. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
