<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4819</transcript-id>
    <title>WERRIWA CAMPAIGN ADDRESS</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/09/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004819.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO: 7.30 p. m.<br />
A~ jURS L IA<br />
FOR PRESS 14 SEPTEMBER 1978<br />
WERRIWA CA14PAIGN ADDRESS<br />
On Saturday week, 23 September, the people of Liverpool,<br />
Campbelltown, Green Valley, Ingleburn and Narellan have<br />
a great opportunity. You have the opportunity to elect an<br />
absolutely first class man as your Member for Werriwa<br />
Bill Sadler. I know Bill is well-known to many here.<br />
He has long been a leading member of this commiunity, an<br />
Alderman of the Liverpool City Council, a former Deputy Mayor<br />
of Liverpool, and a past editor of the Liverpool Leader and<br />
the Liverpool Champion.<br />
Bill and his wife, Kaye, and their three children have been<br />
residents of Green Valley for the past 15 years. I have no<br />
doubt Bill Sadler would make a fine representative for this<br />
electorate in Canberra. He would be an effective voice in the<br />
Government for your interests just as he has been fighting<br />
for this area for the last 15 years. He would be effective<br />
because he would not be just sitting on the Opposition<br />
benches. As a member of the Government team, he would have<br />
a direct influence on the Government of this country. No other<br />
candidate in this by-election is in that position. Bill would<br />
be having a direct say in your future.<br />
As a member of the Government team he would be sharing in our<br />
task of restoring full economic recovery, or renewing growth and<br />
development in Australia, and of establishing stability,<br />
security and prosperity in which we can all share.<br />
We all know what Australia's potential is. We have the initiative,<br />
the natural resources and the capacity to make Australia the great<br />
country we know it can be, and we now have a government which can<br />
maintain stability and progress through sensible and responsible<br />
economic policies.<br />
When we were first elected just two and a half years ago, our<br />
job was to reverse Australia's downhill slide, to turn back the<br />
alarming increase in inflation and to build a strong, healthy and<br />
prosperous nation for all Australians. We all knew that<br />
this would not be an easy task that tough and difficult<br />
decisions would have to be made in the long-term interests of<br />
this nation. We have taken on that responsibility, and already<br />
Australia has come a long way towards achieving these goals. / 2 </p>
<p>When we came to office inflation was 16 percent and more.<br />
It is now under seven percent. When we came to office,<br />
government spending was out of control. We have restored<br />
responsibility to the management of your government's funds.<br />
When we camne to office, taxation was increasing at an<br />
appalling rate, removing any incentive to work harder or<br />
achieve more. We have slashed taxation to such an extent<br />
that this year even taking into account the temporary increase<br />
in rates, Australians will pay $ 3,000 million less in personal<br />
income tax than they would have paid if the 1975 Hayden tax scales<br />
were still in force. When we came to office, the confidence<br />
of the private sector and of overseas investors had been<br />
shattered. We have worked hard to restore their confidence and<br />
we are now seeing a sharp upturn in business investment.<br />
In the recent Budget we have continued with our strategy to<br />
put Australia's economy back on its feet. Because we have<br />
acted responsibility, because we have kept the deficit down,<br />
and because we have spent every dollar of your taxes carefully,<br />
inflation is likely to be down to five percent or less before<br />
this financial year is out.<br />
A low inflation rate is vital to the future of every person here<br />
tonight. Low inflation means that your savings are not eroded;<br />
low inflation means that businessmen have a greater incentive<br />
to invest in new projects, a greater incentive to create new<br />
jobs for Australians; low inflation clears the way for a drop<br />
in interest rates for home owners, for those of us who have<br />
overdrafts, for businessmen, shopkeepers, and tradesmen.<br />
Low inflation in Australia while inflation is increasing oversea. smeans<br />
Australia can become more competitive in world markets.<br />
Low inflation, through its boost to investment, exports and<br />
business, throughout the country, means healthier private*<br />
enterprise in Australia, and therefore more permanent, lasting<br />
jobs for Australians. Our economic strategy is the only one<br />
which will produce real jobs jobs that will last.<br />
At the same time, we have been taking special steps to tackle<br />
unemployment directly. We have introduced manpower programmes<br />
particularly to assist young people. At the end of June 1978<br />
there were six times as many people being trained under NEAT<br />
as there were at the end of June 1975, and we have<br />
changed NEAT to give a much greater emphasis to on. the job<br />
training training more directly related to industries' needs.<br />
Our programmes to assist young people include the introduction<br />
of a Special Youth Employment and Training Programme.<br />
More than 60,000 young people have already been assisted by this<br />
programme since it was introduced in October 1976, and there are<br />
another 40,000 people in training under the scheme at themoment.<br />
A further 45,000 young people have been assisted under the<br />
Community Youth Support Scheme. We have improved apprenticeship<br />
support programmes, and allocated a greater share of education<br />
resources to technical and further education.<br />
We are improving the capacity of the Commonwealth Employment Servicto<br />
serve people efficiently and promptly. 3 </p>
<p>The combination of our economic strategy and our specific<br />
programmes to help the unemployed offer the only real solution<br />
to the problem of unemployment. Most people have concentrated<br />
on the economic objectives of the Budget, but let's not forget<br />
the great assistance this Budget gives to those in need.<br />
Expenditure on key programmes for the aged, the handicapped, and<br />
children has significantly increased. We have raised-spending<br />
on aged, invalid and widows pensions and supporting parents<br />
benefits by 11 percent. We have increased spending on pensioner<br />
housing by 40 percent. Assistance to organisations providing<br />
facilities for the handicapped is up 37 percent, and the<br />
Handicapped Child's Allowance has been extended to students under<br />
who do not receive an invalid pension. In the case of home<br />
care for the aged, even though the subsidy rate has been varied<br />
to meet greatly increased demand, total spending will increase<br />
14 percent to over $ 10 million. That makes a rise of 83 percent<br />
in home care for the aged in the last three Budgets.<br />
We have also introduced new simplified health arrangements which<br />
cover everyone against serious illness, and protect pensioners<br />
and socially disadvantaged patients against all medical and<br />
hospital fees. From 1 November, the Medibank levy will be<br />
abolished. The Government will pay 40 percent of all scheduled<br />
medical fees and 100 percent once the patient has paid<br />
of the bill. Standard ward treatment in public hospitals will<br />
be available free to all Australians, and pensioners and<br />
the disadvantaged will all receive free medical treatment.<br />
This scheme leaves maximum freedom of choice with the individual,<br />
while at the same time providing complete cover for everyone<br />
against serious illness, and meeting the whole of the health and<br />
medical costs of those most in need.<br />
We are also making the greatest initiative Australia has ever<br />
undertaken to assist our ethnic communities, the people that<br />
have contributed so much to Australian society. Migrants<br />
to Australia have to face extreme psychological and social<br />
stresses loneliness, homesickness, anxiety and, in many cases,<br />
the frustration caused by language difficulties. They have to<br />
cope with a completely new environment, different laws, different<br />
customs. The government is making every effort to see that<br />
the changing needs of migrants are met as effectively as possible,<br />
and recently a review was completed of all programmes and<br />
services for migrants arriving in Australia.<br />
As a result, the government is setting up 16 centres to enable<br />
newly arrived migrants to take part in full. time English and<br />
orientation courses; spending an additional $ 10 million over three<br />
years to teach English to migrant children; upgrading and increasing<br />
English classes for adult migrants; extending the telephone<br />
interpreter services; making more funds available to ethnic groups<br />
and community organisations to employ their own welfare workers,<br />
health workers, and people skilled in assisting their children and<br />
the aged; and establishing a new Institute of multi-Cultural<br />
Affairs to encourage the further growth of our multi-cultural society. </p>
<p>To meet all these new initiatives, the Government will be<br />
spending an additional $ 50 million over the next three years.<br />
These new mig-rant settlement services and improved English<br />
language training will be of great significance for this<br />
electorate. There are many other initiatives in the Budget which have<br />
not gained publicity, but which are designed to increase the<br />
growth and development of our great country. In the<br />
face of these constructive and far sighted policies initiated<br />
by the Government, it is appropriate to ask: What does the<br />
Labor Party offer?<br />
All year, the Labor Party has done everything except come<br />
forward with new policies. They have whined and whinged and<br />
utterly failed to concentrate on the fundamental issues that<br />
really matter. Labor has put forward no constructive<br />
alternative policies of their own. They have suffered an acute<br />
case of policy constipation. They are a Party of no ideas,<br />
no plans, no iriitatives and no hope.<br />
Their problem is that the Australian people told them last December<br />
in the clearest terms possible exactly what they thought of<br />
Labor's negative no hope policies. Now the Labor Party has had<br />
to set up an inquiry to work out where they are going.<br />
All this has been too much for Mr Hayden. Last week he lamented<br />
to some students at Melbourne University that the prospect of<br />
the next decade " is almost terrifying". He said the 1980' s<br />
was the " decade of despair". I can sympathise with Mr Hayden,<br />
the 1980' s certainly will be a decade of despair for the Labor Part,.<br />
The prospects for Australia's growth and development in the<br />
under a Liberal Government are excellent. and the near certainty<br />
of Labor's eclipse during the coming period of stability and<br />
prosperity has driven Labor's leader to despair and desperation.<br />
He has now come forward with a plan which he has bravely called<br />
an " talternative Buc'aet". He would have us believe that his<br />
so-called alternative contains some spark of new thinking by Labor.<br />
A moment's analysis of this sad and desperate document shows<br />
that it is nothing but a second serve of the same old recipe<br />
for economic disaster that Labor concocted in its three years in<br />
office: More public spending, bigger deficits, and more taxes<br />
higher taxes, penal taxes, retrospective taxes, which would hurt<br />
us all. Mr Hayden says he would have a deficit of $ 3.6 billion<br />
a huge deficit in anyone's terms. But in fact the position<br />
is far worse than that, for when his new revenue proposals are exam!-<br />
in detail, it is clear they would raise only a fraction this<br />
year of the amount he claims.<br />
Labor's deficit would in fact be over $ 4.5 billion. * Such a deficit,<br />
far from being the salvation of Australia, would cause lasting<br />
damage, the very damage that the last Labor Government inflicted<br />
on us all. It would accelerate inflation, it would force up interes.<br />
rates: It would undermine our prospects for sustained growth,<br />
and it would destory the confidence of domestic and overseas<br />
investors in the Australian economy. </p>
<p>Mr Hayden's " alternative" contains an extraordinary collection<br />
of tax increases. His solution to our need for further investment<br />
in industry is to abolish the investment allowance altogether.<br />
What is more, he would do it retrospectively, penalising<br />
businessmen, large and small, who last year in good faith installed<br />
new plant and equipment. Nr Hayden's solution to our oil<br />
shortage is to confiscate $ 340 million from the oil companies<br />
the very money they might otherwise be using for essential oil<br />
exploration. His arithmetic is so brillant that he says he<br />
could take $ 340 million from these companies, even though their<br />
total expected after-tax profits this year will be only<br />
$ 300 million.<br />
Mr Hayden's solution for encouraging Australians to show more<br />
enterprise and initiative is to resurrect the old socialist<br />
chestnut of a capital gains tax, the very tax that Labor itself<br />
abandoned in 1974. And just in case there are still a few people<br />
who are still doing well despite all the other tax increases<br />
he wants to impose, Mr Hayden wants to increase the tax rates<br />
for all incomes over $ 25,000. He would raise the maximum<br />
tax rate to 72 cents in the dollar. What a wonderful contribution<br />
that would make to incentive, initiative and investment in this<br />
country.<br />
Labor's problem is that it is motivated by the politics of envy.<br />
It cannot abide success or achievement; it's solution for all<br />
problems is to cut down anyone showing enterprise or achieving<br />
success. This is not the path to a stronger, growing and<br />
prosperous Australia. It is not a path which Australians will<br />
ever accept.<br />
It is high time the people of Werriwa had a representative who<br />
could share in the task of making Australia the great country<br />
we know it can be. The people of Werriwa need a man of<br />
Bill Sadler's experience and compassionate understanding for<br />
their problems. The people of Werriwa need to have a direct<br />
say in the government of this country not just another voice<br />
crying in the wilderness of the Opposition backbenches.<br />
When you come to vote on Saturday week, I ask you to think carefully<br />
about your future. Ladies and gentlemen, the choice in this<br />
election is clear. Will you reject Labor's policies of futility<br />
and fear or will you choose the Liberal Party's policies of growth<br />
and confidence which are policies of success.<br />
Our country is poised to move into a decisive decade. We area<br />
nation of many cultures and many rich traditions. A nation to which<br />
people from all over the world have contributed through a sense<br />
of national unity, of purpose.<br />
With a sense of determination by all Australians, we can build a<br />
better life for everyone. We can achieve a quality of freedom<br />
and of opportunity for individual Australians unequalled anywhere<br />
in the world. We can build a society which meets the fundamental<br />
needs and aspirations of the working men and women of Australia.<br />
The people of Werriwa can help our country move towards that light<br />
on the hill by making Bill Sadler part of the Liberal team in Canberra </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
