<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>40424</transcript-id>
    <title>Remarks following meeting with His Excellency Xi Jinping, President of the People’s Republic of China</title>
    <prime-minister>Turnbull, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20150915 - 20180824</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/09/2016</release-date>
    <release-type>Transcript</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong>Thank you very much Mr President and may I thank you very much for your generous hospitality hosting the G20 here in this beautiful city of Hangzhou. Thank you very much for the very generous hospitality you showed to my wife Lucy and I when we visited you and Madame Peng earlier in the year, in April.</p>
<p>The G20 agenda that you have set is one which I am delighted to say - my Ministers and officials have strongly supported China in addressing the measures that will be so critical to ensure that we have stronger economic growth and more opportunities for people in all of the countries of the G20 - but indeed in the whole world.</p>
<p>The agenda that you have set recognises that the keys to ensuring strong economic growth in both our countries and all the nations are trade, open markets, innovation, investment - especially in infrastructure, enabling infrastructure. Ensuring that we have economic reform behind the border, internal reform that it enables there to be more open access and more opportunity for innovation and trade facilitation agreement, of course being an important of that.</p>
<p>We are very pleased to see that the strong agenda to tackle multinational tax avoidance that began in Brisbane several years ago is being continued and I can assure you that my Government is already enacted and committed to further strong measures to ensure that in this very transformed digital economy, the benefits of which we all enjoy. Nonetheless, we ensure that the people of our country and indeed the people of all countries should ensure that their governments are able to collect the taxes that they need and provide the services that their citizens deserve.</p>
<p>So, it is going to be a very important meeting. Your leadership is appreciated and admired. Above all, we need to ensure that all people understand the benefits of trade, open markets and innovation.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
