<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6857</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, LUNCHEON FOR PRIME MINISTER OF THE REPUBLIC OF KOREA, CANBERRA, 6 MARCH 1986</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/03/1986</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006857.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIM4E MINISTER<br />
LUNCHEON FOR PRIME MINISTER OF THE REPUBLIC OF KOREA<br />
CANBERRA 6 MARCH 1986<br />
Prime minister and M~ rs Lho<br />
I recall with pleasure my visit to Seoul a little over two<br />
years ago. I remember the warmth of the hospitality<br />
extended to me on that occasion. I also recall, Prime<br />
Minister, the bracing temperatures in your otherwise<br />
beautiful country in the depths of February.<br />
We had hoped to welcome President Chun Doo-Hwan to<br />
Australia in 1983, when his visit had to be cancelled as a<br />
result of the tragedy of the Rangoon bombing. We look<br />
forward to seeing him in Australia when circumstances<br />
permit. Mr Prime Minister, I have great pleasure in welcoming you<br />
and your delegation here in Canberra and to Australia<br />
today. Korea is a nation with which Australia has had contact over<br />
a long period. The connection goes back at least to the<br />
early days of this century, when Australian missionaries<br />
went to work in your country. Some 18,000 Australian<br />
servicemen fought in the Korean War and more than 250<br />
Australians lost their lives during those hostilities.<br />
After the war the relationship gradually changed as Korea<br />
itself changed. Our political links remain as firm as ever<br />
but, alongside them, the economic relationship has grown<br />
and become increasingly important to both our countries.<br />
Two-way trade has now reached the level of $ 1.6 billion per<br />
annum. In 1984/ 85 the Republic of Korea was our 8th<br />
largest trading partner, compared with our 14th largest in<br />
1980/ 81. During that period trade between our two<br />
countries grew by over 110%. </p>
<p>2.<br />
Korean exports to Australia of manufactured goods are<br />
approaching annual levels of $ 500 million. They are<br />
welcome to the Australian consumer. They have added to the<br />
range of commodities available on the Australian market and<br />
have enhanced our living standards.<br />
Australia meantime has become a competitive and reliable<br />
supplier of energy and raw materials to Korean industry.<br />
we have also supplied a range of high quality farm products<br />
to your country.<br />
In short, the trading relationship is a mutually beneficial<br />
and complementary one, and there seems no reason why it<br />
should not continue to grow and flourish in the future.<br />
I am aware, of course, of our Korean friends'<br />
dissatisfaction with the imbalance in Australia's favour in<br />
our bilateral trade and of the Korean interest in greater<br />
access to the Australian market.<br />
Concern has also been expressed from the Australian side<br />
about some Korean trading policies which appear to be<br />
restrictive or at odds with the declared objective of<br />
gradually opening the internal market.<br />
It is important for the two sides to work together in a<br />
constructive spirit towards the resolution or management of<br />
these issues. The visit by our Trade Minister, Mr Dawkins,<br />
to Seoul last year was clear evidence of what can be<br />
achieved through this approach to the trade relationship<br />
between both our countries.<br />
Korea and Australia are partners in the Asia-Pacific<br />
region. Australia recognizes Korea's important role and<br />
conspicious efforts directed to achieving economic<br />
co-operation at the inter-Governmental and private sector<br />
levels. In particular, we appreciated Korea chairing the<br />
last meeting of Senior Officers of the Regional Trade<br />
officials. We look forward to the continuation of this<br />
dialogue and to Korea's continued close involvement with<br />
the process.<br />
Australia would like to see a situation where trade flows<br />
continue to expand between our countries. Exports in both<br />
directions have been going up by leaps and bounds, and the<br />
record of the last decade shows that Korean exports have<br />
been increasing considerably faster than those of<br />
Australia. There clearly are ample further opportunities<br />
for both sides to sell a lot more to each other and for<br />
both sides to benefit in consequence.<br />
And it is important to note that the framework for our<br />
trading relations is underpinned by a healthy political<br />
relationship. we share with the Republic of Korea a number<br />
of common political concerns and international perceptions.<br />
we consider ourselves to be one of Korea's reliable friends<br />
and are prepared to play a positive role in helping the<br />
Republic of Korea consolidate its position as an important<br />
actor in the Asia-Pacific region. </p>
<p>I do not need to rehearse here the dangers and complexities<br />
of the Korean peninsula. Despite these, over the past year<br />
and a half we have witnessed noteworthy contacts and<br />
exchanges between North and South.<br />
Australia naturally supports the contacts at Panmunjom and<br />
elsewhere. We were particularly pleased when last year,<br />
for the first time since the division of the peninsula some<br />
forty years ago, North and South were able to agree on an<br />
exchange of visits of separated family members. It is true<br />
that only in this one area, and then only one time, has<br />
there been tangible progress and that it is, therefore,<br />
necessary to remain cautious in our assessments of where<br />
these contacts will lead. Australia, nevertheless, shares<br />
the hopes of countries of goodwill around the world that<br />
the dialogue will continue.<br />
Clearly, in developing the scope for further negotiations<br />
with the North, it is important that there be continued<br />
stable political development in the South. The pace and<br />
timing will necessarily be determined by Korean realities.<br />
It is nevertheless appropriate for me to record here the<br />
firm belief of the Australian community that a democratic<br />
and pluralistic political system is certain to be a source<br />
P of enduring fundamental national strength. For us, we hold<br />
it as an article of faith that a political system that<br />
inspires political participation and support is not<br />
something which detracts from national security but is<br />
rather a key element of that security. It follows that we<br />
wish the Republic of Korea well in its march toward the<br />
announced goal of political modernisation and full<br />
A democratisation.<br />
Mr Prime Minister, our two countries are both looking<br />
forward to special events in 1988, events which mark the<br />
maturity of our countries. In that year Korea will play<br />
Aihost to the most prestigious international sporting event,<br />
the Olympic Games. We are aware of the great efforts your<br />
country is making in preparations for the Games and<br />
Australians look forw ' ard to participating in them. Before<br />
that time we should exploit opportunities to expand<br />
56 exchanges between our two countries in the areas of sport<br />
and sport administration.<br />
For our part, Australia will be celebrating its<br />
.4 bicentenary. Many major events have been planned, some<br />
involving participation from abroad, and we hope that your<br />
country will be able to participate actively in our<br />
. X celebrations. I conclude by again saying how glad my colleagues and I are<br />
to receive the Prime Minister of the Republic of Korea and<br />
Mrs Lho in Canberra. On your return, Mr Prime Minister, I<br />
should be grateful if you could convey our best wishes to<br />
His Excellency President Chun Doo-Hwan.<br />
I now invite guests to join mec in a toast to Prime Minister<br />
st'. Shinyong Lho and to relations between his country and<br />
Australia. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
