<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8395</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP INTERVIEW WITH PAUL LYNEHAM, 7.30 REPORT, JANUARY 29 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/01/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008395.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
is.<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
INTERVIEW WITH PAUL LYNEHAM, 7: 30 REPORT, JANUARY 29 1992<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
LYNEHAM:<br />
program. PM: Prime Minister Paul Keating welcome to the<br />
Thank you Paul.<br />
LYNEHAM: Are you getting used to the title?<br />
PM: It takes a while I think, it takes a while.<br />
LYNEHAM: Is it enjoyable still?<br />
PM: Vezy I think.<br />
LYNEHAM: Why?<br />
LYNEHAM: Well for a start it's the greatest honour I think<br />
any Australian could be paid, to be Prime Minister of the<br />
country and the power of the job means that all of those<br />
options one looks for in public life are available to you.<br />
LYNEHAM: How does it compare to being Treasurer?<br />
PM: I -think the workload's are about comparable but<br />
its a different sort of work. It is more of an overview of<br />
all the responsibilities of the Government and also an<br />
overview of society.<br />
LYNEHAM: Of course your critics would say you'd love to be<br />
the boss wouldn't you?<br />
PM: My critics say I'd love to be the boss?<br />
LYNEHAM: Yes<br />
PM: I mean I have spent 22 years as an apprenticeship<br />
which is reasonably a long time. </p>
<p>3<br />
LYNEHAM: DoCes it make you more interested in a wage tax<br />
trade-off?<br />
PM: Well a wage tax trade-off is the principal reason<br />
why Australian inflation is where it is. The 1989 tax cuts<br />
which were $ 6 billion, I might add, just on $ 30 a week and I<br />
might add without a consumption tax, those tax cuts stopped<br />
Australia from coming out of this recession with inflation<br />
at 8-9%.<br />
LYNEHAM: Well are you interested in another one?<br />
PM: Well they have been very effective but again<br />
there's got to be, time has to be precocious for them.<br />
First of all everyone has to want to do it, including the<br />
trade unions.<br />
LYNEHAM: Have you been on the phone to your mate Bill<br />
Kelty? PM: No, and the other thing is the capacity has got to<br />
be there, the result has got to be there. I mean they were<br />
always done, I hope with a lot of aplomb, all the bits<br />
fitted together at the right moment and the result was we<br />
have now got the lowest inflation in the western world<br />
thanks largely to the Accord with the trade unions.<br />
LYNEHAM: Well thanks largely to the fact that the economy<br />
is in intensive care.<br />
PM: No that's not true. The recession has certainly<br />
deflated prices, but we came out of 1982-3 with a<br />
inflation rate, we are coming out of this recession with an<br />
inflation rate at 1.5% with an underlying rate of about 3%.<br />
The difference is wages policy, the difference is the<br />
Accord, the thing the Liberals don't want and the thing<br />
which has put Australia up the front in the inflation race<br />
world wide.<br />
LYNEHAM: Presumably 1.5% inflation does give you a lot more<br />
room to move now as you contemplate how to prime the<br />
economic pump a bit.<br />
PM: Well obviously with the recession the way it is<br />
the economy can stand some stimulation before we see demand<br />
take off and reach a position where it is beyond where we<br />
would like it to be. So if you are asking me is there scope<br />
to stimulate the economy the answer is yes.<br />
LYNEHAM: If you wanted an immediate boost to business<br />
activities some would say why not let the dollar fall gently<br />
to around 70 cents. Why have the reserve in there propping<br />
it back up from 74 to 75 all the time?<br />
PM: WeL1 I'm not here to give you commentary on the<br />
exchange rate. </p>
<p>-2<br />
LYNEHAM: Do you think getting it in a caucus spill gives it<br />
the legitimacy that you get by going to the people and<br />
actually getting their endorsement though?<br />
PM: I think there's only three Prime Ministers who<br />
have ever become Prime Minister at an election. Bob Hawke<br />
did, Malcolm Fraser didn't, Cough did, Bill McMahon didn't,<br />
John Gorton didn't..<br />
LYNEHAM: Are you really fair dinkum now unless you have<br />
gone to the polls?<br />
PM: Harold Holt didn't, I mean as far as I know all<br />
Australian Prime Ministers bar three became Prime Minister<br />
other than a general election. This is true of Curtin, true<br />
of Chifley.<br />
LYNEHAM: Inflation at 1.5% does this mean we should all<br />
expect lower wages outcomes than the 4.5 5% that's in the<br />
current Budget?<br />
PM: Well, the fact is we have had a better performance<br />
on inflation than was generally believed and while I'm not<br />
sure what the wage outcome for this year will be, obviously<br />
there will be a real increase in wages, that is, with<br />
inflation lower for any given nominal wage, that is, for any<br />
given wage outcome there will be part of that wage outcome<br />
will be a real increase in wages.<br />
LYNEHAM: But should the outcome be so far ahead of the<br />
annual inflation rate?<br />
PM: Well success breeds success, it's the old story,<br />
that is if you can do better you end up with the benefit, if<br />
inflation is low the benefit is higher real wages. If at<br />
the time whenr forecasting that and putting wages together we<br />
believe we'd have inflation down to 1.5% obviously the<br />
nominal wage outcome, or the nominal wage target would have<br />
been lower.<br />
LYNEHAM: But you don't feel inclined to try and ratchet<br />
them down now?<br />
PM: Well it's too late to do that now. The year is<br />
halfway over.<br />
LYNEHAM: It would make a wage tax trade-off a lot less<br />
costly.-though-. wouldn't it?<br />
PM: We" Ll there's no guarantee they will come out at<br />
four and a -half, I mean it just depends on what, I mean<br />
there is a recession out there, wage costs have been held,<br />
the labour market deteriorated for the getting of wages,<br />
even the enterprise bargaining slows up, so we are not<br />
certain what the wage number will be yet. It could be lower<br />
than that. </p>
<p>4-<br />
LYNEHAM: Buat wouldn'It you get a lot of economic bang for<br />
very little bother?<br />
PM: Well the thing is the foreign exchange markets are<br />
quite deep and I think now over the years quite smart, that<br />
is, what they have there is a lot more depth and<br />
understanding than there was in 1984 or 1985 and the<br />
fundamental! 3 will always remain important, I think, for that<br />
market and iLt's a mechanism to keep Australian commerce, thle<br />
Australian economy competitive and what you are talking<br />
about is that the recent depreciation of the exchange rate<br />
has made us more competitive and that's obviously true.<br />
LYNEHAM: But then the Reserve has gone back in and pumped<br />
the dollar back up again.<br />
PM: Well no I mean if a market wants to set a rate,<br />
central banks, I don't believe can resist that rate, this<br />
bank hasn't, and the result is that the place is more<br />
competitive but again part of that has been the interest<br />
rate changes in the period but it also has an attendant<br />
inflation risk and that's got to be borne in mind as well.<br />
LYNEHAM: Butt yesterday's NAB survey for example, suggested<br />
that Australian companies who are operating now at about 76%<br />
capacity wa-s a fair bit of slack in there before you have to<br />
start to worry too much about inflation isn't there?<br />
PM: Well exactly. You are making my point for me.<br />
You asked me before is there a risk' on inflation and on<br />
demand if we stimulate the economy and the answer is minimal<br />
risk given the state of the economy, the state of capacity,<br />
the very point you make.<br />
LYNEHAM: So the dollar could come down, boost our exports<br />
without too much immediate danger of inflation as long as it<br />
is done gently and<br />
PM: Let's leave the dollar out of that. Let's<br />
just say..<br />
LYNEHAM: Well the farmers don' t want to<br />
PM: There is room f or a stimulus. I noticed today<br />
that Dr Hewson, by the way, said there was no room for a<br />
stimulus and. he came up the gobbledegook, yes well if you<br />
want to do structural things which can improve investment<br />
you -have gal: to make savings -somewhere else, but if it is<br />
Budget neutral, in other words if you save what you spend it<br />
has not stimulus to the economy. Now he was trying to brand<br />
that as irrE-sponsible, of course it isn't irresponsible he<br />
is the only one that shares that view, Westpac, Bankers<br />
Trust, Citibank, a whole stack of institutions have made the<br />
point that the economy can stand a stimulus and the<br />
Government's now considering that.<br />
LYNEHAM: But isn't there a balancing act that you have got<br />
to make here. On one hand you have got warnings that there </p>
<p>is a distinct possibility that a dash for growth ahead of<br />
the next election could precipitate a further currency<br />
decline, I mean you have got to do something but do it very<br />
delicately with aplomb as you say<br />
PM: Well we have always done that. I mean I think,<br />
look this Government has husbanded over the years a fiscal<br />
policy which has been the envy of most countries and John<br />
Dawkins and Ralph Willis and I and others have sat in that<br />
room for seven or eight years cutting outlays to get the<br />
size of the public sector down. We have earned ourselves<br />
the room and the judgement to decide how we ought to treat<br />
fiscal policy in a recession and we don't need to be told by<br />
some jock from Citibank or somewhere else that they'll be<br />
watching us if we do that. I mean, frankly, the Government<br />
will be makiLng the judgements around here, we're the best<br />
place to make them. Not only that, we have earned the right<br />
to make them.<br />
LYNEHAN: Yes, but you didn't do too well with the recession<br />
bringing the economy in for a landing at 90 degrees.<br />
PM: Well you might make the same point about the<br />
United States which is in a recession where I'm told that<br />
pessimism about confidence is at lower levels in Australia<br />
about the same as Britain and New Zealand. I mean there was<br />
a stock market crash in 1987, monetary authorities world<br />
wide for a crash larger than 1929 avoided the depression<br />
like 1933 but the result was a recession, but a recession we<br />
will emerge from to a recovery and the main emphasis now has<br />
to be on a recovery.<br />
LYNEHAM: Well you spoke recently of taking economic risks<br />
on inflation and on the current account.<br />
PM: No what I said was in the 180s I always tried to<br />
run Australia faster so that Australians had more jobs than<br />
they would in a place where we were running it more slowly<br />
and with the attendant inflation and current account was<br />
being lower. I said the trick is not to be running the<br />
place slowly with high unemployment and lost opportunities,<br />
the trick : Ls to be running it with faster rates of<br />
employment growth and at the same time lower inflation and<br />
lower current account. In other words doing the hat trick,<br />
and that's basically what the 80s structural change is<br />
about, restructuring in the context of growth. Now in other<br />
countries, such as New Zealand, they restructured in the<br />
context of very. low growth or no growth or contraction.<br />
There result is there is a much higher level of social.<br />
misery. LYNEHAM: But: you have also got the political imperative,<br />
you have got no time at all to spare have you? You have got<br />
to perform the equivalent of the economic loaves and fishes<br />
by the time of the next election?<br />
PM: What I would like to see is a recovery coming<br />
through as eEarly and as strongly as possible. </p>
<p>-6<br />
LYNEHAM: How daring can you be though?<br />
PM: Strong in the sense that it is sustainable in<br />
terms of inf lation and demand and the current account.<br />
Which it can be. I mean we have come a long way, remember<br />
this we have got a cyclical problem with the recession, a<br />
problem with the cycle. But in terms of the structure the<br />
long-run structure, is low-inflation, structural Budget<br />
surpluses, a competitive exchange rate mechanism, all of the<br />
other changes, the wage and profit shares, the changes in<br />
enterprise bargaining, all those competitive, efficiency<br />
things are still there in the structure, for the ' 90s for<br />
Australia, and they are put there by this Government.<br />
LYNEHAM: A lot of it has not rung the bell yet. I mean<br />
waterfront reform. When are importers and exporters going<br />
to see the waterfront companies actually lowering their<br />
charges? PM: That will happen because we have now reduced a<br />
cost for themn substantially.<br />
LYNEHAM: But not for the users.<br />
PM: Let's understand this Paul, the Liberal Party left<br />
us an industrial museum, they left us an industrial museum,<br />
a country of industrial archaeology, from the Rip van Winkle<br />
years of Menzies, we're the ones that had to<br />
internationalise the place and we are the ones who are going<br />
to finish the job. There is a limit to how much macro<br />
economic policy, that's Budget policy, and interest rates<br />
can change thie country and the tax system. We are now into<br />
the micro economy. There are things like ports and wharves,<br />
you know, airlines, telecommunications. They're the things<br />
which are the constraints we are now pushing it through.<br />
Now in contrast what are the Liberals talking about? They<br />
are having a. debate whether we tax income or expenditure.<br />
Well big deal. Big deal! Whether we tax income or<br />
expenditure, not how you get a container between Sydney and<br />
Melbourne, not how you get it across the water..<br />
LYNEHAM: For all we've heard from your Government, if I ant<br />
an importer or an exporter I am still not paying less on the<br />
waterfront? PM: Wel. l you may well be but I mean, that will come<br />
through. Wea have made the -changes. . Whether stevedore<br />
companies have yet passed them on is a moot point, I'm not<br />
sure. LYNEHAM: It's a bit academic unless its...<br />
PM: There is a 40 per cent improvement in the wharves<br />
and we are FLot f inished yet. But I'm just trying to say<br />
this. We're the only ones that have ever tackled the<br />
rutted-in, deep problems. The waterfront issue did not:<br />
arise since we were in office. It's been there for </p>
<p>-7<br />
years. How come the Liberals had 7 years of fice and did<br />
nothing abolut it? How come when Dr Hewson was advising<br />
Treasurer Howard, he said, listen Treasurer, what about that<br />
waterfront and micro reform, what about those airlines,<br />
Treasurer, what about the two airline agreement? What about<br />
Telecommunications reform, what about the structural budget<br />
deficit, wha~ t about the 10 per cent inflation.<br />
LYNEHAM: What about we talk about<br />
PM: These are all the things which we had to tackle.<br />
LYNEHAM: What about we talk about the Morgan Poll. I mean<br />
I know you said you would prefer to operate from behind.<br />
PM: No, I. said I have always enjoyed coming from<br />
behind. LYNEHAM: Well you certainly are aren't you. 28 per cent is<br />
just about terminal isn't it? How can you get from 28 per<br />
cent? PM: Look, I have never been out there chasing<br />
popularity. I have always thought it was important to earn<br />
one's regard, one's respect, and as Prime Minister I will do<br />
my best to earn it.<br />
LYNEHAM: But since the last poll, 7 out of 10 of those who<br />
undecided then have gone against you. That's hardly a trend<br />
you can afford to see kick along is it? 7 out of 10 of them<br />
have given you the thumbs down and gone in for your<br />
disapproval slot.<br />
PM: And which poll is this?<br />
LYNEHAM: Morgan Gallop.<br />
PM: Since the last poll.<br />
LYNEHAM: Yes, since the one before.<br />
PM: Well I-don't know how you read that statistic into<br />
it. LYNEHAM: You~ r approval went up 3, your disapproval went<br />
down 7 and ycour undecided's went down<br />
PM: Well. it. is a . very large. undecided group, and I<br />
hope they decide in my favour.<br />
LYNEHAM: Well 7 out of 10 of them gave you thumbs down.<br />
PM: And I will be doing my best to earn their respect<br />
and regard. And' I will not be picking up shabby policy, I<br />
will not be making decision I am ashamed of, I will not be<br />
selling the place out for a bit of cheap cheers. Now the<br />
point is, I was part of the structural change from<br />
Australia, to take it from that industrial museum to a </p>
<p>-8<br />
country which is part of the modern world and will continue<br />
it, and I'm not going to go into bribes, you know tax<br />
options, and other tomn foolery a la the Liberal Party, i~ n<br />
the process of trying to garner some regard.<br />
LYNEHAM: Are we seeing a new Keating style emerging here as<br />
Prime Minister? I mean you're certainly haven't called<br />
anyone a perfumed gigolo, or a mangy maggot in recent<br />
months. PM: Well I mean again, you use those points Paul, but<br />
you've seen me in Question Time, basically in an educational<br />
role for nearly a decade. Educating the Opposition to<br />
policy and I hope the Press Gallery with forensic answers<br />
which were wrapped in a bit of politics to paint the<br />
picture, and it's always it'Is always the lolly in the<br />
wrapper, its always suited the media to run the wrapper and<br />
drop the lolly. Now the fact is I've used some of those<br />
expressions once or twice in 20 years. Now if you want to<br />
drag out Dr Hewson' s record already you will find something<br />
there. You will find it from..<br />
LYNEHAM: So you have been misunderstood?<br />
PM: No you will even f ind it from John Howard, who I<br />
know wants to keep policy as high or low up about all these<br />
things. But the fact is, this is a clearing house of public<br />
pressures. The House of Representatives. It's where we do<br />
our national business. Now in some countries people decide<br />
issues by shooting themselves across footpaths, or other<br />
kinds of violence. We don't have any of that in our<br />
political scene, fortunately. But we do have a vigorous<br />
debate and I really don't think the media has a right to<br />
score of f it all, report it all with all the colour and<br />
verve and vivacity and technical accomplishment is often the<br />
stock in trade of the Parliament and then pick up the odd<br />
word to say, Oh now, isn't this dreadful. Well of course it<br />
isn't dreadful and you know that in terms of, there is not a<br />
Parliament in the world that takes a nswers without<br />
questions. There'Is not a Government in the world required<br />
without any notice for three quarters of an hour or an hour<br />
a day to answer questions on each subject. That's the level<br />
of general co~ mpetence which obtains here day in and day out,<br />
and it is that which with lif ts the tone of the debate, but:<br />
unfortunately it's not that which is always reported.<br />
LYNEHAM: Well let's talk about one or two of f the cuf f<br />
things . you -have.. said-since you. became Prime Minister. Your<br />
suggestion that Bob Hawke's style was to let others lead for<br />
him which was the antithesis of leadership. Why kick him<br />
like that when he was already<br />
PM: Oh look, I was not seeking to kick him. He made a<br />
point to me, he made a point of trying to say to me that I<br />
should change what he perceived to be my style. I was only<br />
making the point that his style worked well for him, mystyle<br />
is dif ferent and I hope mine works well for me. But </p>
<p>9-<br />
LYNEHAM: that's not just a neutral comment?<br />
PM: I just made that point about Menzies. Menzies put<br />
Australia in the cooler for 30 years. Bob Hawke was the<br />
Prime Minist~ er who took it out and I had the pleasure of<br />
doing a lot of that work with him.<br />
LYNEHAM: He wasn't too pleased by your remark?<br />
PM: Well he might not have been. But his record will<br />
survive that remark and many others.<br />
LYNEHAM: Do you think he is going to retaliate? Do you<br />
expect him to?<br />
PM: I shouldn't think so because I don't think it was<br />
a remark calculated to secure a retaliation or that warrants<br />
one. LYNEHAM: Your other piece of outspokenness was accusing the<br />
Coalition of an anti-Asian bias in wanting the immigration<br />
intake cut. Do you really believe that John Hewson or<br />
Phillip Ruddocc are racists?<br />
PM: No.. I was saying I hope we don't have a repeat of<br />
some of the 88 shenanigans and that I thought that some of<br />
the remarks which have been made in by-elections ran that<br />
risk. Now I didn't refer to any remarks, I didn't name<br />
anybody, I just made that point and I was very pleased to<br />
have Dr Hewson' s assurance that this debate, important as it:<br />
is, will be conducted properly.<br />
LYNEHAN: You don't regret stirring the possum?<br />
PM: Wel. l I have just told you what my motives were.<br />
LYNEHAM: The Statement you are planning will be March now<br />
presumably will it?<br />
PM: Well the timing is yet to be decided.<br />
LYNEHAM: These things usually later than early aren't they?<br />
PM: Well, there's a lot to be done, and there's not,<br />
by any measure, a long time to do it.<br />
LYNEHAM: What's-. the danger that. expectations are starting<br />
to become unrcealistically high and that it could end up a<br />
bit like an anti-climax?<br />
PM: Well it's always a danger with any Government<br />
announcement which is foreshadowed. But you know we've<br />
been, I per~ sonally introduced 8 Budgets and 7 May<br />
statements, -that was 15. About 15 years of Budgetary<br />
presentation crammed into 8. So we have got an idea of<br />
managing expectations and also what a package should<br />
contain. </p>
<p>10<br />
LYNEHAM: And how risky can you afford to be in such a<br />
package? PM: I don't think we need to be risky at all and won't<br />
be. The f act is the Government can do two things here at<br />
once. It can do things to induce a recovery, it can do<br />
things which are of a stimulatory nature to the economy but<br />
which add to a long-term productive capacity of the nation.<br />
In other words, not costly Budget bangs which go up in smoke<br />
but things which have a long-run benefit to the productive<br />
base of the country. We have always got those things right.<br />
And from the Government which produced the first structural<br />
surpluses ever in the nation's history, the first huge<br />
structural surpluses. From that Government you will see no<br />
risky things but well thought through, sensible things which<br />
will serve the nation well.<br />
LYNEHAM: There's a danger isn't there that even if you can<br />
get the economy going again reasonably well many voters will<br />
give you very little thanks because many of them blame you<br />
for causing -the recession in the first place.<br />
PM: Well we also had 8 years of almost unprecedented<br />
growth. We took the workforce from 6 million to currently<br />
to this very day<br />
LYNEHAM: With a million out of work.<br />
PM: No, well we always had 600,000 out of work at any<br />
stage. But -the fact is we created 1.8 million jobs, we lost<br />
300,000 of them. Now that's a great pity, but we had 10 per<br />
cent unemployment in a workforce of 6 million in ' 83. We<br />
have got 10 per cent odd now in a workforce of 7.5 million.<br />
The trick is now to get the economy growing again to take<br />
those new entrants to the workforce. And the increment in<br />
wealth, the wealth of this country which changed between ' 82<br />
and ' 91, has been quite profound, I don't think we have<br />
every seen anything like that in our post-war history. So<br />
they have go-t to see us in the context of the 8 or 10 years<br />
and not just in the context of the stock market crash fall<br />
out, the boom of ' 88-89 which was induced by sharp lifts in<br />
the terms of trade etc.<br />
LYNEHAM: Amazing what not having a job and no opportunities<br />
for your kids can do to the lapse of your memory how<br />
Paul Keating used to be.<br />
PM: . No no. Look the Government regrets the fact that;<br />
there is a recession but if we were now growing as strongly<br />
as we were in ' 88 we would be copping America's exportable<br />
surplus, we would be copping Britain's exportable surplus,<br />
we would have a current account which would make Australians<br />
never forget any of this for the next 20 or 30 years. Now<br />
what I'm hoping is that as we get out of this recession we<br />
can get on wiLth it, recovery and not be burdened down for a<br />
generation as we would be with an irresponsible policy which </p>
<p>11<br />
never made those changes. Now the fact is, the recession is<br />
to be regretted, but let's get out of it.<br />
LYNEHAM: Finally East Timor Prime Minister, isn't it simply<br />
humbug for the Government to be expressing concern f or the<br />
human rights for' the East Timorese, while ruling out one of<br />
their most fundamental human rights, which is the<br />
opportunity for some sort of senseless self-determination?<br />
PM: Well, I think that matter would have been<br />
appropriately taken up perhaps in the middle ' 70s and that<br />
matter, I thiLnk, largely passed Australia by then.<br />
LYNEHAM: Haire we dropped the ball then, and they are then<br />
condemned to suffer now?<br />
PM: We" Ll, I hope not condemned to suffer. That is<br />
that we have deplored the events in Indonesia but at least<br />
we have seen disciplinary action taken by the Indonesian<br />
Government against the people in the military who were not<br />
responsible but who presided over as commanding officers of<br />
the groups of soldiers involved. And we've seen remarks by<br />
President Suharto and the presentation report and the action<br />
which he took upon that presentation which gives us heart to<br />
believe that the final report will be a report of substance<br />
and where clear action will be taken. So in other words we<br />
will see some change of behaviour or light or future<br />
behaviour as a result of this unfortunate occurence.<br />
LYNEHAM: And should it worry our national conscience that<br />
they are ther7e, our northern neighbours without any right to<br />
determine their own future?<br />
PM: Well I mean this is always a problem, I think<br />
Indonesia came at this issue in the ' 70s from what ii;<br />
believed was the post-colonial arrangements in this part of<br />
the world. That's what I think spurred their action at that<br />
time. Rights of self-determination are obviously something<br />
which we have fought for. In fact we f ought for the right<br />
of self -determination for Indonesians themselves in the<br />
1940s. But a lot of water has flowed under the bridge since<br />
that time, and I'm not sure it's a realistic expectation<br />
that Indonesia will surrender control of Timor.<br />
LYNEHAM: Even to the East Timorese?<br />
PM: Even to the East Timorese.<br />
ENDS </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
