<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>17041</transcript-id>
    <title>Prime Minister Transcript of remarks Pre-match reception for the Prime Minister&#039;s XI and West Indies cricket teams The Lodge, Canberra 3 February 2010</title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/02/2010</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Prime Minister's XI is a proud tradition. It was established by one of my predecessors, Robert Gordon Menzies, known affectionately as Ming to many politicians at the time. From the other side of politics to myself, can I say one this which unites all in the political sphere of our nation is a love and passion for cricket, so I honour Menzies for having invented this tradition, and his successors for having sustained it, and one of my predecessors, RJ Hawke, for having revitalised it not so many years ago.</p>
<p>Those of you who are familiar with Parliament House, Canberra - I understand that the PM's XI have been around the building today, is that right, Matt, talking to various people? - you'll see that great, green patch of turf across the top of the building is in fact an elongated wicket. We use it for those purposes. The Prime Minister's courtyard is made of concrete. We also use it for our own practice nets. I think, Matt, you've been out there with me on a previous occasion, and in fact was very gentle when he was batting and I was bowling, because he thought I needed to be treated with appropriate respect - and he just took me for six anyway.</p>
<p>Can I say also that none of us in the political process can claim any prominence in the game at all. All of us are, in fact, lousy, led by myself, but that doesn't diminish our passion for the game and our interest in it.</p>
<p>Chris, your team has proven all the pundits wrong. After a difficult start at the 'Gabba Test, can I just say the subsequent matches in Adelaide and Perth, that absolute nail biter in Perth was absolutely spectacular cricket to watch, and those of us who had the privilege to watch it, in our case on the television, and his stupendous six at the WACA, frankly, you are Captain Entertainment when it comes to cricket and it's great to have you among us.</p>
<p>Here at The Lodge, as I said, this tradition was begun by my predecessor Menzies quite a long time ago. Back in 1963, he had a team here, and as was the convention of the time, he had brought the team to The Lodge on the night before for a cocktail reception. He then decided to give all members of the Prime Minister's XI a solid talking to because many of them, the previous year's game, had got completely smashed at the reception. He then remonstrated and said there'd been poor form and bad behaviour.</p>
<p>However, an eyewitness to the occasion, Don Chipp, then in the Liberal Party, later the founder of the Democrats, recently gone on to meet his maker, however provided an eyewitness account because Chipp, on that occasion, was at the non-striker's end at what was to be the last appearance of the mighty Don himself at a Prime Minister's XI game.</p>
<p>The Don, I was told by someone who played in the game who is here today, got out on the second ball. Don Chipp was at the other end. Chipp in fact relayed this anecdote to everyone about what happened with Menzies' speech, and then said Menzies, having made everyone feel thoroughly ashamed of themselves for their behaviour last year, then began to mix one of what was called Menzies' favourite cocktails, a Menzies Martini, which could basically kickstart a jumbo jet on a bad day, and then, as a consequence of that, they all became entirely merry and out of control for the next day's game as well.</p>
<p>So, those of you from the - I'm fine, mate - those of you from the West Indies, when you are handed a drink this evening, be very relaxed and comfortable about the fact that in fact it is full of Kevin's Tequila Sunrises. It's basically just to put you in a right frame of mind for the game tomorrow.</p>
<p>In the Prime Minister's XI we have no less than eight players who are 25 years or younger, and I note that among those young players we've also got Mitch Marsh. Mitch is fresh back from the Under 19 World Cup, where he captained Australia to victory over the weekend against Pakistan, so well done Mitch.</p>
<p>I see tomorrow we also have Tasmanian George Bailey, who's back again playing on my side. George was the star of the show last year and he was man of the match. He tore the travelling New Zealanders apart with a match-winning 107 not out in 42 degrees heat at the Manuka Oval. So can I just say to you, young George, we expect better of you tomorrow - no pressure. Where are you, mate? He's disappeared! He's over there. No pressure mate. It's okay, just relax, but the benchmark is 107 and we expect some improvement.</p>
<p>I also welcome to The Lodge that mountain of a man who really needs no introduction, of course - our captain, Matt Hayden. Here we have a true legend of the modern game, an absolute legend, full of grit and pride and someone who has proudly worn the baggy green for a long, long time with his own partner in crime, Justin Langer. Justin Langer led the side to victory last year, and Matt - not to place any pressure on you as well - I expect a better performance than last year.</p>
<p>Matt's record both in the long and the short form of the game is as intimidating as the shadow he left on the wicket for bowlers fast and slow for over 15 years representing Australia. He has scored over 8,600 runs in 103 Tests with no less than 30 times making a century, and with an overall average of 50, the mark of absolute greatness, please honour the captain of the Prime Minister's XI, Matt Hayden.</p>
<p>We also attended briefly the same school in Brisbane, myself a little earlier than Matt. I had two years at Marist Brothers Ashgrove and the cricket coach of the team encouraged me to take on the game professionally and go international, but I declined and they made room for Matt instead.</p>
<p>Matt, actually, when you deal with any of the old boys of the school is actually known as an old boy of the school. I'm that other bloke on television.</p>
<p>And now to our tourists. I welcome you, also, to The Lodge. I mentioned to you, Big Bird Joel Garner, joining you tonight as your team manager. Joel, where are you? How could you be missed? I was convinced when we had the photographs before that he was in fact standing on the step behind me. In fact, he was standing down a step, and Joel, you are so much admired in this country. We love your work, we love your form, and you've provided such enormous entertainment to Australian cricket fans over such a long period of time. Welcome to The Lodge.</p>
<p>[Applause]</p>
<p>Chris Gayle, I've made some mention of already. This man is cool personified, and they call me a nerd, mate, so perhaps you and I could just exchange some notes later on, and you could nerd up and I could cool up. Some would regard that as a hopeless proposition. The latter, not the former, mate. His strokeplay is just absolutely extraordinary and it's a joy to watch. I mentioned before his six at the WACA, but can I just say also his 100 runs in 70 deliveries in Perth, and as we understand, the third fastest in Test history - a stunning innings. Congratulations on your extraordinary achievements.</p>
<p>[Applause]</p>
<p>Now, to conclude, can I simply say this - my record as Prime Minister so far in the Prime Minister's XI is one loss and one win. Tomorrow, not wishing to put pressure on anybody gathered in the room, could I simply say I wish to see the PM's XI improve somewhat on the averages, and again, Matt, no pressure.</p>
<p>Seriously, this is a great occasion, it's a great celebration of cricket. To our friends from ACT Cricket and local players younger and older - I saw some young blokes out there before, 12, 13, 14 years old, you too can play like Joel Garner, but we'll be checking your height records later on. Can I say to those who are already active in the local competition here in the ACT, good on you. You represent a great cricketing tradition here in our wider region.</p>
<p>To those from the corporate community who back this occasion, can I thank you for your participation as well.</p>
<p>Cricket's a great celebration of Australia. It's a great celebration of Australian sport. It's a great celebration of international sport. You know, whenever I travel, whether it's in India - I think I see the High Commissioner for India, who I failed to acknowledge before, lovely to have you, High Commissioner - whether it's in Pakistan, whether it's in the Windies, whether it's in the UK, whether it's in New Zealand, or whether it is in South Africa or elsewhere, the unity which comes from this game and our passion for it, I think, speaks for itself.</p>
<p>So here's to a celebration of cricket, here's to a celebration in anticipation of champagne cricket tomorrow, and may the best team win.</p>
<p>I thank you.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
