<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5969</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE ACTING PRIME MINISTER AND TREASURER, THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP - RETRENCHMENT OF 170 BURRAGORANG VALLEY COAL MINERS</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/11/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005969.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
A4 PRESS NO. 238<br />
TREASURER RELE A SE<br />
EMBARGO STATEMENT BY THE ACTING PRIME MINISTER AND TREASURER,<br />
THE HON JOHN HOWARD, MP<br />
RETRENCHMENT OF 170 BURRAGORANG VALLEY COAL MINERS<br />
The Miners' Federation's flat rejection of the<br />
overwhelming decision by Burragorang Valley coal miners<br />
to avoid the sacking of 170 men by sharing their jobs<br />
over a four day working week, shows exactly what is wrong<br />
with the leadership of too many Australian unions.<br />
Mr Howard said the Burragorang Valley miners, in opting<br />
for a four day working week, accepted the fact that<br />
per cent of something is better than 100 per cent of<br />
nothing. The Burragorang miners considered that the Australian<br />
principle of mateship, of sharing the burden, is more<br />
important than protecting the high wages of those in jobs<br />
at the expense of the 170 men who would thereby lose their<br />
jobs.<br />
The reality is that the local coal industry is suffering<br />
from a squeeze on revenue due to reduced overseas demand<br />
and higher production costs resulting from recent wage<br />
rises and massively increased New South Wales Government<br />
transport and handling charges.<br />
The Burragorang Valley miners understand this situation,<br />
having already seen two of their district's mines close<br />
earlier in the year. </p>
<p>2<br />
It is incredible that the Miners' Federation should<br />
justify the rejection of the Burragorang Valley miners'<br />
decision by saying, " There will be no sharing of poverty".<br />
In fact, the miners involved would effectively be reducing<br />
their average weekly earnings for a day shift from $ 469.35<br />
per week, to $ 375.48 per week and for a night shift from<br />
$ 550.60 to $ 440.48 per week a far better wage than most<br />
Australian workers earn in a five day week.<br />
This selfish and irresponsible decision by the Central<br />
Council of the Miners' Federation means that those who are<br />
secure in their jobs are cold bloodedly depriving 170 of<br />
their fellow miners of their right to work.<br />
Unless the attitude of unions like the Miners' Federation<br />
is changed, it is inevitable that the impact of the world<br />
recession on Australia will lead to further considerable<br />
job losses.<br />
These could be avoided, and the ability of employees to<br />
take on more workers would be enhanced, if in the present<br />
difficult circumstances, union leaders accepted the<br />
principles of a wage pause and job sharing.<br />
CANBERRA 24 November 1982 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
