<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1361</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS:  PRE-BUDGET DISCUSSIONS STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. HAROLD HOLT</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/07/1966</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001361.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR 9RESS 65/ 1966<br />
PRE-BUDGET DISCUSSIONS<br />
Statement by thle -Prime Minaister,<br />
Mr Harold Holt<br />
Members of -the Economic Committee of Cabinet had discussions<br />
today with a group of national organisations representing industry<br />
and commerce, and had separate meetings with representatives of<br />
the Manufacturing Industries Advisory Council and the Export<br />
Development Council. The national organisations which participated<br />
in the discussions were the Associated Chambers of Commerce of<br />
Australia, Associated Chambers of Manufactures of Australia,<br />
National Farmers' Union of Australia, Australian Primary Producers'<br />
Union, Australian W( ool Growers' and Graziers' Council, Australian<br />
Wool and Meat Producers' Federation, Australian Bankers'<br />
Association, Master Builders' Federation of Australia, Federal<br />
Chamber of Automotive Industries and the Australian Council of<br />
Retailers. The Prime Minister said that these talks allowed Ministers<br />
to get the up-to-date views of those directly engaged in comaerce<br />
and industry. The present discussions had been particularly<br />
timely as Cabinet would be having discussions during the remainder<br />
of the week on Budget matters, preparatory to the Budget's<br />
presentation in Parliament on August 16th. The Government would<br />
be greatly assisted in its discussions by the viewus and information<br />
presented today.<br />
CANBERRA 18th July, 1966: </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
