<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9079</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ. KEATING MP OPENING OF ARTHUR BOYD RETROSPECTIVE ART GALLERY OF NEW SOUTH WALES TUESDAY 14 DECEMBER 1993</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/12/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009079.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PLEASE CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE1F PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P4. KEATIN( G, MP<br />
OPENING OF ARTHUR BOYD RETROSPECTIVE<br />
ART GALLERY OF NEW SOUTH WALES<br />
TUESD) AY 14 DECEMBER 1993<br />
1 am delighted to bc here this evening at the opening of a long overdue retrospective<br />
exhibition of the work of one of Australia's, not to mention the world's, great living<br />
painters. At the time of Arthur's last retrospective, the critical notice in the Adelaide Advertiser<br />
was accompanied by a special offer of a washing machine for forty nine guineas, which<br />
gives you an idea of how long it has been between drinks.<br />
Thirty years in fact.<br />
That is remarkable in itself. But what is even more remarkahlc is that, at the time or<br />
thec Adelaide retrospective, Arthur had already been painting ror thirty years.<br />
He started painting at a Lime, as one writer has said, when the air was heavy with the<br />
arrogance and respectability of old men, old and tired in spirit and in the handling of<br />
painlt. When some critics were happy to announce that Australian art pointed to the way in<br />
which life should be lived in Australia, with the miaximum of flocks and the minimum<br />
of factories.<br />
A permanent Antipodean arcadia.<br />
We owe Arthur Boyd a large debt for removing Australian art from this rcalm of<br />
provincial complacvency.<br />
With sonmc of the most compelling image., of any painter before or since, he showed us<br />
those factories and the social deprivation which went with them, lie opened our eyes<br />
to the horrors of war. To the plight of indigenous Australians and our callous<br />
disregard for their future. To the threat to our environment. </p>
<p>Like Nolan and Drysdale, whose work was also featured during the 1964 Adelaide<br />
Festival, Arthur Boyd has provided us with new ways of seeing Australia and a new<br />
sense of being Australian.<br />
A warts and all way. A way that. is more complete, and thereby mome valid.<br />
This is not to suggest that Arthur's work is a catechism of grim rectitude. Nothing<br />
could be further from the truth.<br />
As befits such a delightful character, his work is full of jollity, of gentlc mockery and<br />
self deprecation. But at the appropriate time, as I have said, it is serious too.<br />
Someone once said that Arthur Boyd as a painter of the Australian landscape was able<br />
to successfully combine the golden vision of Streeton with the darkness conveyed by<br />
earlier painters such as Buvclot and thereby to show us the hush it rcally was a<br />
thing of menace as well as beauty.<br />
In a more general sense too, he has enabled us to sec the darkness as well as the light<br />
in Australian life. Just as Manning Clark did. Just as novelists like Rodney Hall and<br />
David Malouf are doing.<br />
For the last sixty years, despite the fashions of the moment, he has been there, taking<br />
our spiritual temperature, and offering his prognosis for our national well-being in his<br />
own unique way.<br />
Not hecoring or harassing. Jus opening our cyes to things which wc might have been<br />
otherwise inclined to overlook or sweep under the national carpet.<br />
As he himself has said, he has been concerned with a certain grandeur in things, even<br />
little things. And he has been second to none in helping us to comprehend the<br />
dimensions of that grandeur.<br />
People whose judgment is much morc expert than mine see in Arthur's work a wide<br />
ranige of influences. At times it seems that of itself it is a mini-history of Western art.<br />
But, as Barry Pearce points out in the exhibition catalogue, while he has takcen what he<br />
has needed from European tradition, he has also given back something of his own<br />
which is a sense of our essential difference.<br />
He has brought to Australians, and to the world at large, a sense of the Australian<br />
identity. In this way he has lived up to the credo of the Antipodean Manifesto " in the growth<br />
and transformation of its myths a society achieves its own sense of idcntity. In this<br />
process the artist may play a creative and liberating rol." Y<br />
Other artists have played this role too, but it is hard to recall anyone who has played it<br />
better. </p>
<p>Arthur's own career has so far spanned sixty years.<br />
But when one takes into account his remarkable forbears and talented relations, it is<br />
fair to say that when we eecbrate Arthur's achievements we arc also paying tribute to<br />
the Boyd family. The Boyds have been intimately connected with art and letters in<br />
Australia for well over a century.<br />
And in a country which has only known Lwo centuries of European settlement, such a<br />
family contribution to our history is surely unique.<br />
It is fair to say that, for ordinary Australians, the idea of being grateful for the<br />
existence of partcular faimilies is somewhat a novel idea.<br />
From the early days of the colony we have rejected the idea of a bunyip aristocracy, of<br />
the idea of special status deriving from the inheritance of money, or property or other<br />
privilcgc. But the Boyd family is nothing like that.<br />
Their status derives from the spiritual rather than the material dimension from the<br />
fertility of their imagination, and their ability to convert it by pen, paintbrush or pottcrs<br />
wheel to a vision of ourselves which we otherwise mightn't have had.<br />
Arthur, I'm sure, because he is such a modest and unassuming person, would be the<br />
last person to claim any special status for his family indeed, he would probably reject<br />
it with the same vehcmence that he rejects any ascription of special status for himself.<br />
But he is a special Australian, as the work in this exhibition attests.<br />
And an Australian of rare gencrosity.<br />
Many people here tonight arc probably aware that some of the works in this exhibition<br />
are part of the 1975 Boyd gift to the National Gallery. A gift which played no small<br />
part in getting the Gallery going.<br />
But not enough for the Boyds.<br />
Early this year I met Arthur and Yvonne in the sadder circumstances of a memorial<br />
service to their brother-in-law and great friend, Sir Sidney Nolan.<br />
I was privileged to be able to speak about Si Nolan's legacy to Australia's cultural life,<br />
just as I have been able to do in relation to Arthur today.<br />
And I was able too to announce the Government's acceptance of the girt by Arthur and<br />
Yvonne Boyd of their beloved Bundanon properties.<br />
This was a gift to the nation of profound significance, and one which the<br />
Commonwealth Government was proud to accept and to support. </p>
<p>Subsequently the Bundanon ' Irust was established and we provided $ 5.43 million to<br />
help it bring to reality Arthur Boyd's great vision for Bundanon.<br />
As if that gift wasn't enough, I am plcased to be able to announce tonight that the<br />
Bundanon Trust is to be the beneficiary equally with his children of the copyright in<br />
all of Artur Boyds works.<br />
Arthur's assignment of his copyright means that his support for the work of the Trust<br />
will continue for many ycars to come.<br />
The Bundanon gift is valued in money terms at more than $ 12 million.<br />
I hope that Arthur and Yvonne Boyd's great generosity will be matched by thc rest of<br />
Austalia when the Bundanon Trust commences its major gifts campaign early next<br />
year with my strong support.<br />
All Australians wil have the opportunity to assist Bundanon through the Trust's<br />
Donations, Friends of Bundanon and Merchandising Programs, and I urge them to do<br />
SO. It remains for me to congratulate the Art Gallery or New South Wales for the<br />
tremendous achievement of putting this show together. Edmund Capon, Barry Pearce<br />
and Patricia McDonald have assembled a collection which can more than hold its own<br />
with any of the overseas blockbusters.<br />
And that perhaps gives the truest indication of the achievement of Arthur Boyd.<br />
To a painter who wanted to paint the Great Picture, or if not the great one, then some<br />
very good ones, I can only say in sincere admiration, Arthur, that your wish has been<br />
granted in abundance, and we arc all the better for it.<br />
And now I have great pleasure in declaring the exhibition open. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
