<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>41718</transcript-id>
    <title>Interview with David Koch, Sunrise</title>
    <prime-minister>Turnbull, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20150915 - 20180824</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/08/2018</release-date>
    <release-type>Transcript</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects>Drought relief</subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p><strong>DAVID KOCH:</strong></p>
<p>For more I'm joined by Prime Minister, Malcolm Turnbull who has spent the weekend out in drought-affected areas. Prime Minister thanks for your time.</p>
<p>You've been out there, what advice and suggestions are you getting from the farmers?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER:</strong></p>
<p>Firstly, our farmers are saying thank you to your viewers and Australians who are providing so much support. They really appreciate the love and support that they’re getting. They appreciate the support the Government is providing, the governments. The State Government of course here in New South Wales has reinstated some freight subsidies for fodder and of course, we have increased the Farm Household Allowance substantially, for a couple, by $12,000 a year. That is on top of $16,000 or so for those people who are really doing a tough. That is putting more cash into their household, into their community. We’ve have also provided extra support for mental health services and we are putting money into community grants again, to get some cash moving into those communities.</p>
<p>But look, it’s very tough. You just had a farmer, I was just listening, who described perfectly the real problem that you’ve got. It cost two dollars a day roughly, to keep a cow alive. You spend that money day after day after day and the drought isn't breaking. You run out of money. You sell and then the drought breaks and you can't afford to restock. On the other hand, if you destock too early, obviously you run the risk again of being caught when the drought breaks. So, it's a diabolical choice.</p>
<p><strong>DAVID KOCH:</strong></p>
<p>A couple of things, a couple of things. $12,000 is terrific, the $6,000 now, but the other $6,000 not until March? Why not just pay it all now?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>Well, we’ve decided to pay it in two lumps of $6,000 -</p>
<p><strong>DAVID KOCH:</strong></p>
<p>Why?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>In September and another in March. </p>
<p><strong>DAVID KOCH:</strong></p>
<p>They need it now.</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>I think we’ve decided that those two sums of money - you know, March is not that far away - one in September, one in March -</p>
<p><strong>DAVID KOCH:</strong></p>
<p>Hang on. March is a long way away.</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>But Kochie, there are people -</p>
<p><strong>DAVID KOCH:</strong></p>
<p>When you’re in drought.</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>Kochie there are people that are not going to be qualified, that have not actually qualified in the sense of applied and been granted access to the Farm Household Allowance. So we’ve worked it out with the agencies and this was the best way of delivering it, it’s an administrative issue.</p>
<p><strong>DAVID KOCH:</strong></p>
<p>Okay what about other practical things? Like, we’ve had farmers say; “Lift the restrictions on our access to mulga lands, for feed to cattle”, those sorts of things? States and Federal Government working together just to access more feed or even to subsidise the grain price, the feed price for them?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>Yeah the way the drought cooperation between the feds and the states operate, is that the states are responsible for fodder subsidies, freight subsidies. The Federal Government provides the social welfare support if you like, for families. So, there are freight subsidies in Queensland, and now once again in NSW.</p>
<p>Obviously in times like this, the cost of fodder goes up. You see if you got to source hay from South Australia, that is a long way to haul it to Tamworth. Of course West Australia is going to have a great grain harvest, South Australia looks like it will be pretty good. So, there will be grain. But again, you have got to haul it across country.</p>
<p><strong>DAVID KOCH:</strong></p>
<p>Okay, alright, Prime Minister. Thanks for your time it’s appreciated.</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER:</strong></p>
<p>Thank you very much.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
