<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>150</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS:  STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER COMMONWEALTH SERUM LIBORATORIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/02/1960</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000150.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRI'SS Statement by the Prime Minister<br />
CO&gt;,. 0-O. EALTH SERUM L:' BORATORIES<br />
On Tuesday lI'st Dr. Cameron, the Federal Health Minister,<br />
stated that<br />
1. Certain overseas drug manufacturers were making " feelcrs"'<br />
for taking over the Commonwealth Serum Laboratories.<br />
2. No specific offers had been made.<br />
3. The Commonwealth had not put the laboratories up for sale.<br />
2. The Government had not yet considered the proposals.<br />
These statements were, of course, correct. The names of<br />
the firms making the enquiries were not disclosed. It would be<br />
contrary to proper and normal practice to do so. I should add<br />
that before answering any enquiries on such a matter, Cabinet's<br />
views would need to be obtained. The reason for this is that<br />
an important question of public policy is involved; under such<br />
circumstances it is our practice to secure the views of Cabinet.<br />
One Meclbourne morning newspaper, on Fednesday last, said<br />
that the matter had already been discussed in Cabinet, and<br />
actually claimed to quote my own views. Both statements were<br />
untrue. As it happens, the item has been listed in the normal<br />
way, on a submission prepared by Dr. Cameron last week, for the<br />
next Cabinet meeting, when it will be dealt with.<br />
I should add that the only consideration to be taken into<br />
account will be the best health interests of the Australian<br />
people.<br />
CANBERRA. 1st February, 1960. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
