<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>850</transcript-id>
    <title>FURTHER PAYMENT OF 16.10.0 POUNDS TO THE FORMER PRISONERS OF WAR OF THE JAPANESE</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/11/1963</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000850_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
OR PRESS, P. M. 2o/ 1963<br />
FURTHER PAYMENT OF œ 16.10.0 TO FOR~ MER PRISONERS<br />
OF WAR OF THE JAPANESE<br />
Statement by the-Prime Minister, the Rt. Hon. Sir Robert Menzie õ<br />
The Prime Minister, Sir Robert Menzies today<br />
announced that a final payment of V16.10.0 each would be paid<br />
to former Australian prisoners of war of the Japanese from the<br />
proceeds of realisation of Japanese assets in accordance with<br />
the Peace Treaty with Japan.<br />
In 1952, the Government decided that the proceeds<br />
of realisation of Japanese assets in Australia should be<br />
distributed equally among former prisoners of war of the Japanese,<br />
and a distribution of œ-32 was made, During 1955, the Japanese<br />
Government, in settlement of its obligations under Article 16<br />
of the Peace Treaty paid the sum of Iv sterling to the<br />
International Commi~ tee of the Red Cross in Geneva. Australials<br />
share of these moneys together with the proceeds of the sale of<br />
the Burma-Siam railway and minor amounts from other sources<br />
enabled a second distribution of œ C54 to each ex-prisoner of war<br />
to be made in 1956-7.<br />
A further and final payment has now been received<br />
from the International Committee of the Red Cross and we have<br />
decided that this together with the remainder of the moneys<br />
expected to become available from the realisation of Japanese<br />
assets in Australia, should also be distributed equally between<br />
former prisoners of war, The amount of this distribution will<br />
be œ 16.10.0 per person.<br />
As in the case of former distributions, where a.<br />
prisoner of war has died, either during captivity or since his<br />
release, payment will be made to a dependant or where there is<br />
no dependant to such other person as is entitled toit because<br />
of a particular relationship with the deceased.<br />
A letter containing particulars regarding payment<br />
and a form for completion and return will be sent to the last<br />
recorded address of persons who shared in the previous<br />
distributions or to any new address as may be notified to the<br />
appropriate service Department, Those who have not participated<br />
in previous distributions but consider themselves eligible to<br />
share in the current distribution should contact the relevant<br />
service Department. It is hoped that most of the payments will be made<br />
before Christmas 1963, but this will be possible only if forms<br />
are completed ani returned promptly.<br />
CANBERRA, November, 1963. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
