<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3392</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON EG WHITLAM QC MP, ON HIS VISIT TO MACKAY, 14 SEPTEMBER 1974</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/09/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003392.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
AUSTRALIAN GOVFR-N?, PMP<br />
ASSISTANCE TO MACK~ AY<br />
AND ITS REGION<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PPTMF' ' lINT STER,<br />
THE HON. E. G. WHITLAM, M. P.,<br />
ON HIS VISIT TO MP. CI( AY<br />
14 SEPTEMPEP 1S74<br />
Mlackay is typical of the regions benefiting from<br />
Australian Government policies tc improve local government<br />
services and promote equal opportunities for Australian<br />
citizens wherever they nay live.<br />
While Mackay is one of the richest regions of<br />
Australia and of great importance to the national economy,<br />
the Government has given special attention to its need~ s and<br />
its future development.<br />
one of the most important Labor Government initiatives<br />
has been to empower the Grants Ccmmission to recomnmend<br />
financial assistance to local government bodies. The Government's<br />
objective is to reduce inequalities between regions and to ensure<br />
that people everywhere enjoy the same opportunities and living<br />
standards. Last month the Government accepted ixn full the first<br />
series of grants recommended by the Commission. of the<br />
Australian total of $ 56.3 million, Queensland will receive<br />
$ 8,954,000. Grants to local government in the Mackay region<br />
total $ 397,000, including a grant of $ 64,000 to Mackay City<br />
Council. No strings were attached to these grants. They will<br />
help local government bodies improve community services and<br />
initiate important development projects.<br />
By giving help where it is most needed after careful<br />
and impartial investigation by the Grants Commission the<br />
Government hopes to give people in country-cities and regions<br />
the same standards and amenities as the capital cities. ./ 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
RESOURCES Mackay is the centre of several important industries,<br />
including sugar, coal and beef production. The region produces<br />
more than one-quartar of Australia's sugar.<br />
The Government acknowledges this vital contribution<br />
to the national economy and is Oetermined to assist and<br />
strengthen these industries in every possible way.<br />
Australian exports of sugar are now worth more than<br />
$ 300 million a year. The market remains buoyant. Through<br />
the efforts of Dr Rex Patterson, the Minister for N7orthern<br />
Development, firm overseas markets have been secured for sugar,<br />
with substantial long-term contracts already signed with<br />
Malaysia, ! ingapore, New Zealand and the Republic of Korea.<br />
Negotiations are in progress wi. th China, the United Fingdom<br />
and Japan. The Government is ma}: inq a $ 5 million grant for the<br />
Kinchant Dam to help stabilise sugar-cane production in an<br />
area subject to droughts.<br />
Productivity in the beef industry has risen sharply.<br />
To help meet problems due to world oversupply, the Australian<br />
Government is sending a high-level trade delegation to Brussels<br />
and Tokyo and is seeking consultations with the F. F. C. under<br />
the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade.<br />
The Government will spend $ 24 millio-on beef roads<br />
in Queensland over the next three years.<br />
To further develop the vast coal resources of the<br />
region, the Australian Government has commissioned a report on<br />
the industrial development prospects of the Bowen Coalfields<br />
Basin with special reference to a possible steelworks.<br />
FLOOD RELIEF The Australian Government is providing massive financial<br />
assistance for restoration work following the recent disastrous<br />
floods. Under the Queensland Flcod Relief Act 1974, provision<br />
has been made for Australian Government Assistance of $ 66 million<br />
over a three-year period. 9../ 3 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
