<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3062</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER &amp; MINISTER FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRS, MR R.G. WHITLAM, Q.C., M.P., ON HIS RETURN FROM CHINA AND JAPAN 5 NOVEMBER 1973</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/11/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003062.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
STATV. MENT THE FRI! W E MINIST7fl" &amp; i MINISTER FO1-FOY' IGN AFFAIRS,<br />
NR WijITEA;:, P, ON iiI ' TtiiN iROiv1 CH INA AI. D JAPAN<br />
NOVEMBER 1973<br />
Within the next fdw days I shall be reporting to the<br />
Australian Parliamnent on the results of my visit to China and<br />
Japan. I believe this visit, in the company of several of my<br />
ministerial colleagues, was the most successful and produlctive<br />
overseas mission ever undertaken by an hustralian Government<br />
delegation. We have forged new understandings with two of our<br />
greatest neighbours with Japan, our most important trading<br />
partner, and with China, the most populous nation int the world.<br />
With both countries we have redefined our relationship<br />
to the benefit of both sides and set new perspectives that will<br />
endure for years to come.<br />
Our basic task in Japan was not an easy one. Essentially<br />
it was to explain to the Japanese Government that in the<br />
development of our minerals and energy resources Australia in<br />
future will be the master in her own house. We will not allow<br />
the present proportion of foreign ownership and control of these<br />
resources to increas,-e.<br />
In Tokyo we made this position quite clear. The<br />
Japanese understood it. They accepted it. At the sane time<br />
we reassured Japan that Australia would never deny Japan access<br />
to the raw materials she n~ eds. We will remain a dependable<br />
supplier. That position, too, was understood and welcomed.<br />
I did not go to Japan to carp or complain, as the<br />
Leader 3f. tLh-e Oppositiondid, about Japan's defence spending,<br />
or internal policies. I did not go, as Mr Snedden did, to<br />
incite Japan to a resurgence of militarism. I went to seek new<br />
friendship and understanding.<br />
The fruits of that understanding will be embodied ina<br />
a lasting treaty of friendship and cooperation between the two<br />
countries. For years the Japanese Government sought such a<br />
treaty with Australia. The previous Australian Government<br />
refused to conclu, 4e such a treaty. We have now cleared the way<br />
for negotiations on the Treaty of Nara to begin without delay.<br />
As an example of the kind of cooperation that will flow<br />
from our better relationship, Senator Wriedt obtained most<br />
encouraging indications of Japan's willingness to make long-term<br />
arrangements for the pur'chase of our primary products, especially<br />
wool. I am confident that such arrangements will bring benefits<br />
to both countries.<br />
My visit to China was the first ever mde by an Australian<br />
Prime Minister. It brought great practical benefitsto Australia<br />
as well. as gre at personal satisfaction to me.<br />
It markedt,-e end of a generation of neurotic fears and<br />
lost opportunities. Australia hasR now established a firm and<br />
cordial friendship witha government representing a quarter of<br />
the earth's population. That friendship, I believe, will be<br />
lasting and fruitful. </p>
<p>As a result of my extraordinarily long and thorough 4<br />
discu.; sions with Premier Chou En-lai, Chairman Mao Tse-tung<br />
and o; hei Chinese leaders, the Australian Government now nas<br />
a niuch better knowledge of Chinese attitudes to a whole range<br />
of worldproblems. Such knowledge is essential to the conduct<br />
of a mature, confident and constructive Australian foreign<br />
policy. We are no longer working in the dark. China knows what<br />
we think. We know what China thinks. On many issues such as<br />
nuclear te. ts, the Middle East, Bangladesh and Korea-we frankly<br />
acknowledged andfully explainedour differences.<br />
On many practical issues we madegreat progress.<br />
DrPattersonsecured Chinese agreement to important long-term<br />
contracts for the sale of sugar to China. This arrangement may<br />
well prove to be the biggest commodity deal Australia has made<br />
with anotner country. It followsthe highly valuable wheat<br />
contract with China concluded recently by Dr Cairns.<br />
I believe we are now entering a more enlightened and<br />
productive era in our relations with China. I believe the<br />
great foundations of friendship andcooperation we have laid on<br />
tni: vLsit will stand for y. ars to come. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
