<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2025</transcript-id>
    <title>VISIT TO THE US AND CANADA 1969 - SYDNEY N.S.W. - DEPARTURE PRESS CONFERENCE GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. JOHN GORTON AT MASCOT AIRPORT</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/03/1969</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002025.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
VISIT TO THE US AND<br />
CANADI9<br />
SYDNEY, N. S. W.<br />
DEPARTURE. PRESS CONFERENCE GIVEN BY TH<br />
PRIME MINISTER, MR JOHN, GORTON, AT-M IW%<br />
AIRPORT 29 MARCH 1969<br />
PRIME MINISTER Would you like me to read out the messages we have<br />
sent to the United States and Mrs Eisenhower one was a personal<br />
tribute sent to President Nixon<br />
Q. Could you read the personal tribute to Eisenhower that<br />
you sent to President Nixon?<br />
PM: This was sent by us to President Nixon:<br />
" TODAY ALL AUSTRALIANS ARE SHARING WITH<br />
YOU AND WITH THE AMERICAN PEOPLE A DEEP SENSE OF<br />
GRIEF AT THE DEATH OF GENERAL EISENHOWER.<br />
" WE MOURN HIM AS A LEADER OF MEN WHO<br />
SERVED HIS COUNTRY AS PRESIDENT WITH DEVOTION AND<br />
HONOUR. WE MOURN HIM AS A LEADER IN THE FIGHT FOR<br />
THE FREEDOM OF NATIONS. HE LED THE CRUSADE IN<br />
EUROPE AND BORE THE AWESOME BURDEN OF SUPREME<br />
COMMANDER IN WORLD WAR II WITH COURAGE, SKILL AND<br />
THE HIGHEST QUALITIES OF LEADERSHIP. HE ACCOMPI1SHED<br />
A GREAT VICTORY FOR THE FORCES OF ENLIGHTENMENT<br />
AND HUMAN DIGNITY IN THE WORLD.<br />
" HE RESPONDED TO HIS COUNTRY'S SUMMONS TO<br />
THE HIGHEST OFFICE IN THE LAND WHEN OTHER MEN<br />
MIGHT HAVE SAID ' I HAVE DONE ENOUGH'. AND AS<br />
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES, HE LED THE MOST<br />
POWERFUL OF THE FREE PEOPLES OF THE WORLD AT A<br />
CRUCIAL TIME IN WORLD HISTORY, AFTERWARDS HE<br />
CONTINUED TO DEVOTE HIS GREAT HUMAN RESOURCES TO<br />
THE ISSUES OF HIS TIME.<br />
" AUSTRALIANS, AS DO PEOPLE THROUGHOUT THE<br />
WORLD, SALUTE HIS ACHIEVEMENTS AND MOURN HIS<br />
PASSING.<br />
That is the message thmt we have sent. ,2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
Q. W-har-are-the iain-twpics tharyou. wil1he discussing<br />
when you-meet-members -of-the Administration?<br />
PM: Well now, of course, I will not be able to have<br />
discussions with the President in the way it was planned that we<br />
should have them. But I will still be having talks with the Secretary<br />
of State and with the Secretary of Defence, and I imagine though<br />
this is not yet quite clear with the Secretary of the Treasury.<br />
I wil also be talking to some Presidential aides Mr Kissinger,<br />
for example, and this, I think, will be a most useful preliminary<br />
exercise, though I am sorry that the high level talks will not now<br />
be able to take place. These will be initial talks, and I think they<br />
will be of value for the time when, as I hope in May or June<br />
depending on the President's agenda we can have thle talks<br />
which were scheduled-to have been held this time. Then, of course,<br />
the Canadian visit will go on as planned.<br />
Q. Will you be seeking an assurance that the Americans<br />
will remain in South-East Asia after the Vietnam war ends?<br />
PM: I will be seeking to discover the current thining<br />
of the American Administration in regard to that rather than<br />
seeking assurances or otherwise. I want to try to discover the<br />
actual thinking at the moment.<br />
Q. Will you be discussing the use of nuclear weapons<br />
at Gape Keraudren?<br />
PM: L Well, we never intended to use a nuclear weapon at<br />
Gape Keraudren in Western Aus tr alia. What we had thought would<br />
happen there would be that the Sentinel Mining Company, which hias<br />
iron ore leases, would join with us our own Atomic En ergy<br />
Commission and the United States Atomic Energy Commission in a<br />
feasibility study for the blasting out of a crater which could be<br />
turnedI into a harbour. This is not nuclear weapons in any shape<br />
or form. But it looks as if the Sentinel Mining Company now has<br />
doubts as to the economit feasibility of using such a harbour, having<br />
re-examined the grade of ore and various things of this kind. So<br />
this particular project is probably and I say probably unlikely<br />
to go ahead, but both our own Atomic Energy Commission and the<br />
United States Atomic Energy Commission will be examining whether<br />
there is somewhere on our West or North-West coast a situation<br />
where a harbour is wanted and where this kind of experiment can<br />
take place.<br />
Q. Do you feel that the closenesofte between<br />
Australia and America depends on your/ reiationship with Mr Nixon<br />
the kind of personal friendship you strike up with him?<br />
PM: Not really. But I think the ties between Australia and<br />
the United States probably transcend personal relationships of any<br />
two individuals. I think they can be reinforced considerably if two<br />
individuals, one a Prime Minister and one a President are, as it<br />
were, on the same wavelength, understand each other and trust<br />
each other. I believe this applies to the United States or, for that<br />
matter, to the Uniited Kingdom. / 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
Q. "' DQYWi-tinkthaLxreC&amp; atacks on your personal life<br />
and your lead~ ership will affect your standing in the United States?<br />
PM: I don't think they will at all. There have been two<br />
I think they are part of a campaign. One seemed to be concerned<br />
with some story about I don't want to use names, but I suppose<br />
I have to Miss Minelli, whom I have met once in my life, and who,<br />
in accord with her mother and sister and everybody else concerned,<br />
threw that out the window. The other was an attack which I don't<br />
really thoroughly understand even to this day. It seemed to be<br />
concerned with whether one w. ght to go and visit someone at one<br />
o'clock or half past one, if one is asked to or not. Since there was<br />
no suggestion from even the self -styled accuser, of impropriety, I<br />
am not quite sure what it is all about,<br />
Q. Your talks with Mr Trudeau, of course, will go ahead<br />
as scheduled. Can you elaborate a little on this?<br />
PM: Well, only to this extent that the Canadians have<br />
indicated or Mr Trudeau when I met him in London indicated that<br />
he felt that he and his country should have a closer relationship<br />
with the Pacific area than they had had before. Now, I wculd like<br />
to explore that to see what part of the Pacific area that he is<br />
specifically interested in, to see what form his interest takes.<br />
do notice that he has said something concerning wheat sales, and this,<br />
of course, is of great importance to us in Australia too. These<br />
matters, I think, could be of significance to both our countries<br />
but I only say " could be of significance". They are worth exploring.<br />
Q. I take it, Mr Gorton, there was no chance of having<br />
earlier talks with Mr Nixon?<br />
PM: Oh no. No. He has been touring Europe, and indeed,<br />
originally, I was to be the first political head of state that he was to<br />
talk with or rather head of government that he was to talk with.<br />
Mr Trudeau has spoken to him, but there was no chance of anyb~ ody<br />
really eomi~ g to the United States before. Now, we will have to<br />
fit in the next visit as best we can, and I think from messages I<br />
have received, both President Nixon and myself would like this to be<br />
done as soon as is possible for him and his itinerary and me and<br />
my itinerary, although I would bend mine quite a lot to fit in with<br />
his.<br />
Q. Sir, does this mean, withthe period of mourning<br />
extending to five days , that you are prepared to extend ywur visit to<br />
the United States and Ca n ada<br />
PM: No. I think that the period of mourning for General<br />
Eisenhower would be likely to be more than five days andi I haven't<br />
any intention at the moment of extending the visit. Rather from the<br />
messages that one received, one would be over there examining with<br />
the relevant people whether the meeting that was scheduledto take / 4 </p>
<p>-4-<br />
PM ( Contd.) place this time with the President not with the other Secretaries<br />
but with the President could-possihbly take place in May or early<br />
June, which I would hope.<br />
Q. Sir, do you feel, being one of the first political heads<br />
of state to have talks with President Nixon , that you will play a part<br />
in formulating his ideas as far as South -East Asia is concerned<br />
influencing him before his ideas become hardened, seeing that he<br />
has just come into office?<br />
PM: I would hope, as in the case of talks between reasonable<br />
people, that suggestions could be made by me which would be taken<br />
into consideration by him, and suggestions could be made by him<br />
which would be taken into consideration by me.<br />
Q. Mr Gorton, if I can ask a question on the security<br />
of South-East Asia, do you feel that the recent fighting between Russia<br />
and China has lessened the threat of China to the area?<br />
PM: I think that is a matter of sufficiently high policy and<br />
a matter so impossible to define in any precise way that I couldn't<br />
probably answer that question. There does appear and I say<br />
" tappear" for some time to have been some tension between Russia<br />
and China in the border areas between the two of them, and it has<br />
flared up recently. But what effect that has on the policies of either<br />
country I don't believe we have properly assessed as yet.<br />
Mr Eggleton I think the Prime Minister has an announcement of<br />
special interest to Sydney to make, so would the local Members<br />
concerned come and sit near the PM?<br />
PM: This is an announcemnent which is perhaps of most<br />
interest to people in the Sydney area, and particularly in the area<br />
around Mascot. I have flanking me the three Federal Members who<br />
are concerned with it. They are conccrned with it, if I may say so,<br />
to my cost, because they have taken up so much of my time about<br />
it, because their constituents are concerned with it, and it deals<br />
with the situation of an alternate airport to the one we are sitting<br />
in at the present moment. Now, I will read it to you This is<br />
as a result of an examira tion by the Department of Civil Aviation<br />
and report to myself and it concerns the Towra Point, which is<br />
just across the bay and which has been considered as a possible<br />
site for an alternate airport. I have been in touch with the Department<br />
of Civil Aviation and the Minister of Civil Aviation on this matter.<br />
This is the gist of the announcement </p>
<p>-4-<br />
PM ( Contd.) place this time with the President not with the other Secretaries<br />
but with the President coulcposily take place in May or early<br />
June, which I would hope.<br />
Q. Sir, do you feel, being one of the first political heads<br />
of state to have talks with President Nixon , that you will play a part<br />
in formulating his ideas as far as South -East Asia is concerned<br />
influencing him before his ideas become hardened, seeing that he<br />
has just come into office?<br />
PM: I would~ hope, as in the case of talks between reasonable<br />
people, that suggestions could be made by me which would be taken<br />
into consideration by him, and suggestions could be made by him<br />
which would be taken into consideration by me.<br />
Q. Mr Gorton, if I can ask a question on the security<br />
of South-East Asia, do you feel that the recent fighting between Russia<br />
and China has lessened the threat of China to the area?<br />
PM: I think that is a matter of sufficiently high policy and<br />
a matter so impossible to define in any precise way that 1 couldn't<br />
probably answer that question. There does appear and I say<br />
" 1appear" for some time to have been some tension between Russia<br />
and China in the border areas between the two of them, and it has<br />
flared up recently. But what effect that has on the policies of either<br />
country I don't believe we have properly assessed as yet.<br />
Mr Eggleton I think the Prime Minister has an announcement of<br />
special interest to Sydney to make, so would the local Members<br />
concerned come and sit near the PM?<br />
PM: This is an announcement which is perhaps of most<br />
interest to people in the Sydney area, and particularly in the area<br />
around Mascot. I have flanking me the three Federal Members who<br />
are concerned with it. They are conccrned with it, if 1 may say so,<br />
to my cost, because they have taken up so much of my time about<br />
it, because their constituents are concerned with it, and it deals<br />
with the situation of an alt e~ rnate airport to the one we are sitting<br />
in at the present moment. Now, I will read it to you This is<br />
as a result of an examina tion by the Department of Civil Aviation<br />
and report to myself and it concerns the Towra Point, which is<br />
just across the bay and which has been considered as a possible<br />
site for an alternate airport. I have been in touch with the Department<br />
of Civil Aviation and the Minister of Civil Aviation on this matter.<br />
This is the gist of the announcement </p>
<p>PM ( Contd,); " The community noise problem involved in<br />
-the operation. of jet aircraft in the Towra Point area<br />
would be so severe, that the Minister for Civil Aviation<br />
has advised me that he has decided to direct the<br />
Interdepartmental Committee, convened to consider<br />
the future airport needs of Sydney, to exclude this<br />
site from its consideration,<br />
" While accepting that the advantages which<br />
modern aviation brings to the community as a whole are<br />
considerable, I nevertheless feel that our airport<br />
planning must avoid the imposition of an unacceptable<br />
noise burden on any particular section of the community.<br />
This I believe would be the situation if we went ahead<br />
with jet airport development at Towra Point,<br />
Accordingly I have told the Minister for Civil Aviation<br />
that I concur in his decision not to give further<br />
consideration to possible future jet operations at<br />
Towra Point.<br />
This is of interest, as I say, to people living around this area<br />
and I take this opportunity with my colleagues, who have pressed<br />
it on me so strongly, to make this announcement.<br />
Thank you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
