<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9433</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ KEATING MP SECOND WORLD WAR CIVILIAN MEDAL</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/11/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009433.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER 102Pi4<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ KEATING MP<br />
SECOND WORLD WAR CIVILIAN MEDAL<br />
I am pleased to announce today the establishment of a new Medal the<br />
Civilian Service Medal 1939-1945 which will be awarded to thousands of<br />
Australian civilians who served their country during World War 11.<br />
Final approval for the Medal has now been granted by Her Majesty the<br />
Queen.<br />
The award's aim is to recognise the contribution of those civilians who served<br />
in arduous circumstances in Australia during World War Two in organisations<br />
subject to military-like conditions. Its creation was one of the<br />
recommendations of the Committee of Inquiry into Defence Awards which<br />
reported to the Government earlier this year.<br />
The Government has so far approved four organisations as meeting the<br />
criteria for the award of the Medal. They are:<br />
The Australian Women's Land Army;<br />
The North Australia Railway;<br />
The Civil Constructional Corps; and the<br />
Voluntary Aid Detachment ( for VADs who did not go on to military<br />
service during the War).<br />
Other organisations are under consideration for the Medal and if they are<br />
found to meet the criteria their members will be eligible to receive the award.<br />
All Australians who served in one of these organisations for 180 days or more<br />
may apply for the Medal, to be awarded by the Governor-General on the<br />
recommendation of the Minister for Administrative Services. The Medal will<br />
also be awarded posthumously to next-of-kin, so close relatives of deceased<br />
Australians who served in these organisations may also apply.<br />
It is estimated that around 68,000 people will qualify for the award.<br />
Recipients can choose to have their Medal personally presented by their<br />
local Federal MP or Senator, or have it posted to them. </p>
<p>Designed by Mr Horst Hahn, Chief Engraver of the Royal Australian Mint, the<br />
Civilian Service Medal will be made of bronze. The Medal is ensigned with<br />
the Federation Star and its design features the Southern Cross, symbolising<br />
Australia, and Golden Wattle, symbolising the civilian population combined in<br />
the defence of the nation. The accompanying ribbon will be three broad<br />
vertical bands of opal green, ochre and opal green, separated by two thin<br />
white stripes.<br />
The Civilian Service Medal will be placed immediately under the Police<br />
Overseas Service Medal in the Australian Order of Precedence of Honours<br />
and Awards.<br />
Application forms for the Medal can be obtained from:<br />
electorate offices of Federal MPs and Senators; or<br />
the Medals Validation Unit, Department of Administrative Services,<br />
GPO Box 1331, ACT 2601. Phone: 06 275 3653 or 06 275 3654.<br />
CANBERRA November 1994 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
