<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2977</transcript-id>
    <title>FLEXIBLE WORKING HOURS IN THE AUSTRALIAN PUBLIC SERVICE</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/07/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002977.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
j1% A USTHI, -1Al'-PRESS STATEMENT NO. 115<br />
24 July 1973<br />
FLEXIBLE WORKING HOURPS IN THE AUSTRALIAN PUBLIC SERVICE<br />
In line with the Australian Government policy that<br />
employees should have the right to work in conditions<br />
conducive to the development of full human dignity, the<br />
Public Service Board has issued an information paper to<br />
all departments and staff associations drawing attention<br />
to various experiments which are being conducted with<br />
new patterns in working times. The aim of introducing<br />
flexible working hours is to give staff the maximum<br />
possible freedom to determine their own pattern of<br />
working. I II<br />
Trials of different flexible hours systems are<br />
currently being conducted in areas of the Central Office<br />
of thne Department of Labour in Melbourne, the Regional Office<br />
of the Department of Supply in M~ elbourne and in the N. C. D. C.' s<br />
office in Canberra. Thle Board, departments ' and staff<br />
associations will be monitoring these and future trials<br />
to determine the advantages and disadvantages of alternative<br />
working arrangements before * deciding whether now working<br />
arrangements should be introduced on a more permanent basis<br />
in appropriate areas.<br />
The introduction of flexible working hours i~ n the<br />
Australian Public Service will have both social and efficiency<br />
advantages and is a further step in the formulati -on of an<br />
employment policy which would help people to re. concile<br />
domestic and family responsibilities with a career.<br />
CANB3ERRA. A. C. T.. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
