<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9647</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J.KEATING MP DOORSTOP, INTERCONTINENTAL HOTEL, SYDNEY, 28 JUNE 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/06/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009647.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
DOORSTOP, INTERCONTINENTAL HOTEL, SYDNEY, 28 JUNE 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
J: Prime Minister, you have taken the unusual step of getting a letter<br />
published in Le Monde, why?<br />
PM: As I said, the Government would proselytise on this issue in France.<br />
That is, say to the French people why we think it is not in France's<br />
interest and it is unreasonable that they should continue this program<br />
when the best course of action available for the French nation is to<br />
engage the rest of the world. And, if we want to talk about threats, the<br />
threat to France is not someone dropping a bomb on France, it is<br />
someone dropping a cloud on France a nuclear cloud. From those<br />
old decaying power stations in the Ukraine and in Russia, these are the<br />
real issues that face continental Europe and some sort of Maginot Line<br />
of the 1 990s is not the answer. The answer is engagement. I think we<br />
have tried to say that reasonably. -The other thing, I think, about the<br />
French is, another reason why it gets up our nose is that we don't<br />
expect democracies to behave this way. This is a democracy we have<br />
twice gone to war for. This is a democracy that believes in liberty in a<br />
very profound way and yet it is acting in a colonial way in the Pacific<br />
and while there is no dispute about what is or what isn't French<br />
territory, this is not part of metropolitan France, it is a colonial view and<br />
one expects, in the end of the 20th century, for democracies to behave<br />
in a way which other democracies can approve of.<br />
I suppose it is this which particularly* annoys Australians and annoys<br />
those other people in the world who believe the French are out of line.<br />
J: President Chirac has told his fellow European leaders that the protests<br />
against his decision are irrational your view? </p>
<p>PM: Well, they are not and, I think, the content of my letter to the French<br />
newspaper indicates in a very sober rational way the point of objection<br />
by Australia, but again, we have got to point out what we object to and<br />
what we believe is in France's interest while acknowledging that they<br />
have committed themselves to a limited series of tests and signing the<br />
comprehensive Test Ban Treaty. That will be important, not just to<br />
them, but to all of us.<br />
J: So are you going to target the French electorate now rather than the<br />
French administration?<br />
PM: When I announced last Thursday evening the range of measures which<br />
the Government was prepared to undertake, one of them was<br />
proselytising in France, articulating the government's view about this<br />
subject and this is perhaps the first initiative in this respect.<br />
J: Your letter to the people, is it in any way an admission that the<br />
diplomatic channels have failed?<br />
PM: No, I think, France is a sovereign country, it can make sovereign<br />
decisions. That's not to say they are immune from criticism. This is<br />
one of the ways of indicating that any criticisms that we might make are<br />
reasonable and rational and letting the more critical group of people in<br />
France take account of Australian views first hand.<br />
J: Are you concerned that Robert Ray didn't sign the petition yesterday?<br />
PM: I don't know who has signed the petition and who has not.<br />
J: Prime Minister, President Chirac has said that the French government<br />
will pay the costs of Australian scientists being sent to the test zone,<br />
are we going to take that up?-<br />
PM: We are not in the business of playing games. Any offer we would take<br />
up would be for comprehensive assessment of the site. That is,<br />
comprehensive on site seismic, not being part of some charade about<br />
assessments of the impact upon sub-terranian corals and the rest. It<br />
would have to be, probably, an international effort and it would need to<br />
be completely comprehensive. I don't think there is any chance of the<br />
Franch fobbing anybody off with games about the impact upon<br />
Mururoa, we can establish scientifically what the impact is, if they wish<br />
that to be so. But, the point of objection is the fact that the Cold War<br />
has finished and the thing to get on with is the anti proliferation policies<br />
of those countries who believe that weapons proliferation is a very grim<br />
prospect and that a large part of the problem is actually in the old<br />
Soviet Union and in other parts of Europe. That is the point of<br />
concentration. Not on further developing the existing inventory of<br />
weapons which the French already have. </p>
<p>J: Prime Minister, is Kerry Packer being punished for his support of John<br />
Howard when we are talking about cross media?<br />
PM: No, I think, there is a very clear view on the part of the government that<br />
the cross media rules have produced a lot of diversity. We now have a<br />
radio industry which is almost entirely independently owned from the<br />
newspapers. This was never so in the past. The Macquarie Network<br />
was owned by Fairfax, the other big network was owned by the Herald<br />
and Weekly Times. This is not true today, we have seen other<br />
independent owners of the two big broadsheets The Sydney Morning<br />
Herald and The Age with Conrad Black's group. We are seeing<br />
different ownership in the free to air television stations. So, the<br />
government's cross media rules of the 1980s have worked. What we<br />
have seen is legal devices to move around them, by keeping it clear<br />
that we will allow some ownership, some cross ownership but not where<br />
there is control, not where there is virtually a co-incidence of interests.<br />
This the government sought to do by tightening up its cross media<br />
arrangements yesterday with the 15 per cent. This will apply to Mr<br />
Packer's interest in print as it will to Mr Murdoch's interests in<br />
television.<br />
J: You are not just getting square with Mr Packer?<br />
PM: Well, I was asked that earlier.<br />
J: Are these the last changes to the rules?<br />
PM: As we can see them at the moment, but again, lawyers will always try to<br />
find ways around these things. The question is, is Australia<br />
advantaged by media diversity? And, if the answer to that is in the<br />
affirmative, and I believe it is, then we need a set of rules which bring<br />
this about. Otherwise, simply the convergence of technologies and<br />
corporate financial power will mean that we will have a continuing<br />
concentration of ownership. This the government has resisted and, I<br />
think, resisted successfully. Thank you.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
