<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3201</transcript-id>
    <title>ANIMAL HEALTH LABORATORY - 2 APRIL 1974</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/04/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003201.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER PRESS STATEM~ ENT NO. 209<br />
2 April 1974<br />
ANIMAL HEALTH LABORATORY<br />
The Australian Government has approved a project to provide<br />
major protection for the Australian livestock industry.<br />
It has decided to build a laboratory complex, to be called<br />
the Animal Health Laboratory, at Geelong, Victoria.<br />
The capital cost of the complex is expected to be $ 56 million.<br />
This spending will begin in 1976/ 77 and will be spread over five<br />
years. The laboratory will help provide protection on a national<br />
basis for one of our most important rural industries.<br />
The Australian livestock industry had an estimated gross<br />
value of production in 1972/ 73 of $ 3,000 million. In the same<br />
year the industry's exports were worth an estimated $ 2,000 million.<br />
The laboratory complex will provide protection by performing<br />
the following functions:<br />
" diagnosis of exotic animal disease,<br />
" testing of vaccines required for exotic disease control,.<br />
" research on major virus diseases in Australian animals,<br />
" the production of foot and mouth vaccine if required.<br />
The laboratory complex will be established on the Geelong<br />
Rifle Range, which is owned by the Australian Government.<br />
Compensating arrangements will be made as required for organisations<br />
disadvantaged by the project.<br />
The Australian Health Laboratory will be administered and<br />
operated by the C. S. I. R. O. on behalf of the Australian Government.<br />
Following the establishment of the laboratory a consultative<br />
committee, consisting of C. S. I. R. O. and departmental representatives,<br />
will be formed to assist in the determination of priorities and to<br />
ensure effective liaison on policy matters.<br />
The Consultative Committee will provide an essential link<br />
with the Animal Quarantine Branch of the Department of Health for<br />
the testing of livestock in the proposed off-shore High Security<br />
Animal Quarantine Station. / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
The Commuittee will also provide a liaison channel for<br />
special research, training, diagnosis and epidemiology with the<br />
proposed Bureau of Animal Health in the Department of Primary Industry.<br />
At full operation, the Animal Health Laboratory will employ<br />
a staff of 170 including 25 scientists.<br />
Its annual operating costs will be approximately $ 3 million.<br />
The laboratory would play a vital role in minimising the<br />
impact on the Australian economy of an outbreak of foot and mouth<br />
or other introduced animal disease.<br />
' Should an outbreak of exotic disease occur, the existence<br />
of the laboratory would be vital to any eradication program and would<br />
be an important factor in persuading Australia's trading partners<br />
that eradication had been achieved.<br />
It will also provide a facility for carrying out special<br />
testing for potentially valuable livestock held in quarantine<br />
before they were allowed into Australia for breeding programs.<br />
It will also be a valuable facility for research on virus<br />
diseases endemic in Australia, several of which affect man as well<br />
as livestock. Final design of the laboratory followed a study tour of<br />
overseas microbiological security establishments by a government<br />
evaluation team.<br />
The Geelong site, currently the Geelong Rifle Range, was<br />
chosen following extensive consideration of a wide range of<br />
alternative sites.<br />
The final choice was made on the advice of the Cities<br />
Commission in the light of the Government's policy of developing<br />
specific growth centres and with the approval of the Victorian<br />
Government. A comprehensive environmental impact statement for the site<br />
accompanied the Cabinet submission.<br />
The Department of the Environment and Conservation which<br />
assessed this statement noted the amount of technical detail<br />
supplied and advised that it was satisfied that the environmental<br />
issues of the proposal had been adequately covered.<br />
Because of the extreme precautions built into the design,<br />
there will be no risk to Australian livestock.<br />
The laboratory complex will be technically the most<br />
sophisticated major structure in Australia and the most modern<br />
animal diseases laboratory in the world.<br />
It will operate as a series of integrated engineering systems,<br />
which provide isolation from the external environment. / 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
It features multiple fail-safe devices and procedures<br />
including air locks, shower locks, filter systems of many kinds<br />
and sophisticated waste disposal apparatus.<br />
All air entering or leaving the laboratory will be specially<br />
filtered. The air leaving the high hazard area will be heat steriliscd<br />
to kill virus particles.<br />
Solid wastes will be destroyed or rendered sterile.<br />
Operation of the complex will have no detrimental effects<br />
on the environment. In accordance with overseas practice, the keeping of<br />
susceptible livestock will not be permitted in a buffer zone one<br />
mile in radius around the laboratory.<br />
This will include sheep, cattle, pigs, goats, horses, fowls,<br />
turkeys, geese and ducks.<br />
The Victorian Government has agreed to the relocation of the<br />
trotting and dog-racing track currently in the vicinity by the<br />
time the laboratory is complete in 1981.<br />
The buildi4ng has been designed by a group of specialists<br />
formed within the Department of Housing andConstruction who have<br />
worked in close consultation with C. S. I. R. O. and an expert from<br />
the Department of Health. BACKGROUND INFORMATION<br />
The impact of an outbreak of foot and mouth disease in the<br />
livestock industry would be immediate and far reaching. Much of<br />
our trade in meat and other livestock products would cease and it<br />
would be many months, even years, before normal trade was resumed.<br />
There are many other livestock diseases exotic to<br />
Australia, some as potentially devastating as foot and mouth disease,<br />
others less so, but all capable of seriously affecting our livestock<br />
industries. While Australia has a remarkable record of success<br />
in remaining free of these diseases, there is no certainty that<br />
this situation can be sustained for ever.<br />
It is difficult to escape the conclusion that sooner or<br />
later a major exotic disease of livestock will penetrate our<br />
quarantine barriers. If this were to happen, Australia' s veterinary<br />
authorities would be severely handicapped at present by the<br />
absence of a laboratory possessing a great enough degree of<br />
microbiological security to enable highly infectious material<br />
to 1-c handled in complete safety without risk of escape.<br />
If vaccination became necessary for control and eradication of a<br />
disease, the Animal Health Laboratory would be involved in testing<br />
the potency and safety of the vaccines used. / 4 </p>
<p>4<br />
The Laboratory would be absolutely essential for the<br />
enormous amount of work needed not only to eradicate the<br />
disease but also to demonstrate to other countries that<br />
eradication had been successful. If a situation arose where<br />
overseas trade in meat or some other livestock products had<br />
been suspended as a result of an outbreak of a major disease,<br />
the absence of such a facility could seriously prejudice the<br />
early resuantion of trade with our trading partners.<br />
CANBERRA. A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
