<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2463</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE RT HON W MCMAHON MP ON INTERNATIONAL CURRENCY MINISTERIAL STATEMENT</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/08/1971</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002463_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA<br />
SPEECH BY<br />
The Rt Hon. W. McMAHON, M. P.<br />
ON<br />
INTERNATIONAL CURRENCY<br />
Ministerial Statement<br />
[ From the ' Parliamentary Debates', 26 A ugust 1971]<br />
Mr McMAHON ( Lowe Prime Minister)<br />
The right honourable member for<br />
Melbourne ( Mr Caiwell) has asked that I<br />
make a statement on the measures for the<br />
protection of the United States dollar<br />
announced by President Nixon on 15th<br />
August. As honourable members will be<br />
aware, the situation in the international<br />
currency markets is changing from day to<br />
day -and any assessment of the situation<br />
has to be treated cautiously at this point of<br />
time. ' However, in the view of the importance<br />
of the developments I feel it desirable<br />
to give the House a preliminary<br />
assessment. As honourable members will<br />
know, the present disturbed situation in the<br />
international currency markets was sparked<br />
off by the -announcement of the President<br />
of the United States last week that convertibility<br />
of United States dollars into gold<br />
and other reserve assets was to be suspended,<br />
and a 10 per cent surcharge on all<br />
dutiable imports into the United States,<br />
other than those subject to quotas, was to<br />
be imposed. Both these decisions were<br />
announced by the President to be temporary.<br />
But it was made clear that the removal<br />
of the 10 per cent surcharge, and the<br />
resumption of convertibility of United<br />
States dollar balances, would be dependent<br />
on certain objectives being -achieved by the<br />
United States as a result of negotiation in<br />
the fields of international trade and -finance<br />
and the sharing of defence burdens.<br />
19f2271 As to trade, the President claimed that<br />
American products were at a disadvantage<br />
because of unfair exchange rates. He said<br />
that the import tax would be ended when<br />
the unfair treatment ended. In the field of<br />
finance, the President asserted the need<br />
for a widespread major realignment of<br />
exchange parities, and also for an<br />
improved system of international monetary<br />
arrangements generally. The President also<br />
said that the time had come for other economically<br />
strong nations to bear their fair<br />
share of defending freedom around the<br />
world. This latest disturbance on the international<br />
currency markets is only the most<br />
recent of a long succession of similar disturbances,<br />
centring on one major currency<br />
after another, and sometimes on groups of<br />
currencies. In 1967 we had the disturbances<br />
leading up to the devaluation of<br />
sterling. In 1969, the pressure was transferred<br />
from London to Paris and we had<br />
the devaluation of the French franc * and<br />
the revaluation of the Deutschemark. More<br />
recently, the trouble has centred on the<br />
United States and has been attributable in<br />
large part to the growing balance of payments<br />
deficit of that country. This has led<br />
to a fall in United States official reserves<br />
and a sharp increase in its official shortterm<br />
liabilities. At the same time, there has<br />
been a substantial transfer of United States<br />
dollars on private account into the international<br />
monetary markets of the world. </p>
<p>All this has served to weaken confidence in<br />
the United States dollar on the foreign<br />
exchanges. A number of factors has contributed to<br />
the United States' external deficit. Prominent<br />
among these is the rapid price and<br />
cost inflation in the United States over the<br />
last 5 years. The United States' position<br />
has been exacerbated by the growing competitiveness<br />
of some of its trading partners<br />
and by restraints on the access of United<br />
States' exports to markets abroad. Superimposed<br />
on this has been the heavy<br />
defence burdens of the United States.<br />
Defence expenditure abroad by the United<br />
States has recently been running at the<br />
level of about SUS5 billion annually. One<br />
way and another, the balance of payments<br />
deficit has built up until, in the first half of<br />
this year, the deficit has been running at<br />
an annual rate of SUS23 billion.<br />
It is not surprising, in these circumstances,<br />
that the United States dollar is now<br />
commonly regarded as being ' over valued'.<br />
In other words, the existing exchange<br />
parity for the United States dollar overrates<br />
its international purchasing power. This, of<br />
course, is a matter of critical worldwide<br />
importance because of the pivotal position<br />
in the international monetary system of the<br />
United States dollar.<br />
The United States dollar is the largest of<br />
the reserve currencies in the world today<br />
and many countries have fixed rates of<br />
exchange on the dollar. A great proportion<br />
of international trade and financial transactions<br />
has been settled through the dollar in<br />
the past. And the dollar has been adopted,<br />
along with gold as one of the two basic<br />
units of value in the Bretton Woods<br />
monetary system. Other currencies have<br />
had their par values expressed in terms of<br />
the United States dollar and gold.<br />
There is no doubt that the Bretton<br />
Woods system has made a major contribution<br />
to full employment, economic growth,<br />
and the orderly development of world<br />
trade and financial arrangements in the<br />
post-war period. It has achieved this as -a<br />
result of the adoption of a number of<br />
working principles, not least of which has<br />
been the system of agreed parities of rates<br />
of exchange between participating<br />
countries, adjustable only with the consent<br />
of the International Monetary Fund in the<br />
case of fundamental balance of payments disequilibrium. This system of pegged parities<br />
has been of particular value to smaller<br />
countries as a protection against the prewar<br />
practice of currency manipulation and<br />
competitive depreciations. It has also been<br />
of value to rapidly developing countries<br />
like Australia who do not have access to<br />
the economic dialogues centred on the<br />
United States and Europe.<br />
Nevertheless, no system is proof against<br />
the ravages of time and the Bretton Woods<br />
system is no exception. The need for further<br />
development of the Bretton Woods<br />
arrangements has long been recognised,<br />
and the most recent innovation has been<br />
the establishment of special drawing right<br />
which, in themselves, offer some alternative<br />
to the United States dollar and gold as an<br />
international reserve asset.<br />
Another innovation, and this is very germane<br />
to the present situation, is that the<br />
Executive Board of the Fund ' has been discussing<br />
the case for a greater flexibility in<br />
-the mechanism of exchange rate adjustments.<br />
There is a strong body of opinion<br />
which suggests that the present arrangements<br />
whereby exchange rates should not<br />
vary more than I per cent from parity<br />
should be changed by extending somewhat<br />
the operating limits within which currencies<br />
could be exchanged without being held<br />
to infringe their par values -at the International<br />
Monetary Fund.<br />
The action taken by the United States<br />
last week has short-circuited this debate<br />
and take the question of exchange rate<br />
adjustments into the field of immediate<br />
practical necessity in the foreign exchange<br />
markets. The 10 per cent surcharge on<br />
dutiable imports would, were it to be continued,<br />
strike heavily at the exports of<br />
countries like Japan which have had a<br />
large and growing market in the United<br />
States for goods of the kinds subject to the<br />
surcharge. Through the effect of this on<br />
industries in such centres it would in turn<br />
tend to reduce their demand for materials<br />
supplied by other countries in the normal<br />
course of events. The surcharge is currently<br />
under consideration in the General<br />
Agreement on Tariffs and Trade.<br />
The United States has, however, said<br />
that it sees this trade* action as a means of<br />
securing revaluation of the currencies of<br />
countries which it considers to have an<br />
unwarranted advantage over it in point of </p>
<p>trade competition because of their existing<br />
parities. If and to the extent that other<br />
countries were to revalue their currencies,<br />
the United States dollar would be devalued<br />
in relation to them. The United States<br />
Government has chosen this approach to<br />
its problem in preference to seeking a formal<br />
devaluation of its currency against all<br />
other currencies.<br />
Amongst other things that course would<br />
involve the United States in altering the<br />
value of the dollar in terms of gold. The<br />
President has said that his Government<br />
does not intend to alter the present dollar<br />
price of gold. We have, as yet, no real<br />
idea as to what the final response of other<br />
major countries to the United States initiative<br />
is going to be.<br />
Under the rules of the International<br />
Monetary Fund, the exchange parity of<br />
any country which is a member of the<br />
fund can be altered only if the country<br />
itself seeks a change. It seems reasonable<br />
to suppose that few, if any, major<br />
countries are likely to seek such a change<br />
unless and until other countries take steps<br />
to do so. As yet there is no firm indication<br />
of concerted action amongst major<br />
countries to that end.<br />
On Thursday of last week the Finance<br />
Ministers of the European Economic Community,<br />
meeting in Brussels, failed to reach<br />
agreement on any form of common action<br />
in the matter. The foreign exchange markets<br />
in Europe were closed last week but<br />
have re-opened this week. There have been<br />
no formal revaluations on the dollar but<br />
the majority of European countries have<br />
allowed their buying rates for dollars to<br />
exceed the Monetary Fund limits of 1 per<br />
cent beyond parity with the dollar. In<br />
point of fact, however, the markets so far<br />
this week have been fairly steady on the<br />
dollar and the dollar has fallen in value in<br />
most markets by something in the region<br />
of only 2 per cent to 3 per cent below the<br />
rates ruling before the markets closed.<br />
I want to stress that this is likely to be<br />
an interim situation since it has done<br />
nothing to achieve the more significant realignment<br />
of exchange rates which the<br />
United States, and the Managing Director<br />
of the International Monetary Fund, consider<br />
to be necessary. This fact must be<br />
borne in mind in all our thinking and calculations. If, of course, a number of<br />
major currencies were to seek and obtain<br />
adjustments of their exchange parities<br />
under the International Monetary Agreement<br />
a question could arise as to whether<br />
Australia should seek some such adjustment.<br />
If such a situation were to arise, we<br />
would need to make the most careful<br />
assessment of it from the standpoint of our<br />
own interests both international and<br />
domestic. But no such situation has arisen<br />
yet. We are keeping closely in touch with<br />
developments and studying all possibilities.<br />
At the same time we are preserving for<br />
ourselves the greatest possible scope for<br />
independence of action. If it should come<br />
to a decision whether or not to seek some<br />
alteration of our exchange parity there will<br />
be only one proper basis for decision-the<br />
interests of the Australian economy and<br />
the Australian nation as a whole. Meanwhile,<br />
in the state of uncertainty which<br />
must prevail until the large issues I have<br />
mentioned are crystallised and intentions<br />
on the part of major countries become<br />
clearer, foreign exchange markets are<br />
likely to be very unsettled and changeable.<br />
We may also see large movements of funds<br />
between financial centres. It will be a matter<br />
of adjusting our own exchange dealing<br />
arrangements to meet changing situations<br />
as they arise.<br />
In this state of uncertainty in the foreign<br />
exchange markets it is not possible to settle<br />
on a firm exchange rate for the Australian<br />
dollar. However, in order to enable overseas<br />
transactions to be resumed, it has been<br />
decided to continue to fix an exchange rate<br />
with the pound sterling on a daily basis.<br />
For purposes of the last 3 days trading the<br />
existing parity with sterling-that is,<br />
$ A2.1429 for œ 11 sterling-has been maintained.<br />
It is true that, as sterling has been<br />
traded at a rate about 2 per cent above<br />
parity with the United States dollar, this<br />
means that at the moment there is, in<br />
effect, a similar small appreciation of -the<br />
Australian dollar in relation to the United<br />
States dollar. However, the situation is<br />
being reviewed on a day-to-day basis and<br />
any short term change in the rate should<br />
not, of course, necessarily be taken as an<br />
indication as to the long term rate that will<br />
eventually be settled for the Australian<br />
dollar. </p>
<p>For the time being, and until further<br />
notice, banks have been advised that they<br />
may undertake foreign exchange transactions<br />
in respect of normal trade transactions,<br />
other current account payments contractually<br />
due, and the reasonable requirements<br />
of travellers. Rates of exchange for<br />
these transactions are quoted by the banks<br />
under arrangements with the Reserve Bank<br />
and are based on developments in the London<br />
and other main foreign exchange markets<br />
overseas. forward transactions and, of course, this<br />
limits the scope of banks to offer such<br />
cover to their customers. I think this is<br />
reasonable in view of the present unsettled<br />
circumstances on the foreign exchanges.<br />
We will be ready to adjust our position as<br />
required in accordance with the emerging<br />
situation. I present the following paper:<br />
International Currency-Ministerial Statement,<br />
26 August 1971.<br />
The Reserve Bank is not yet offering Motion ( by Mr Swartz) proposed:<br />
facilities to the banks to cover them for That the House take note of the paper.<br />
W. G. MURAY, Government Printer. Canberra </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
