<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6840</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE, WEDNESDAY 19 FEBRUARY 1986</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/02/1986</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006840.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
4J,, AUSTRALIA<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE WEDNESDAY 19 ' FEBRUARY 1986<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
PM: Ladies and Gentlemen obviously this will be a general press<br />
conference but I wanted to take the opportunity at the outset to<br />
have the presence of my friend and colleague, Susan Ryan, who is<br />
the Minister Assisting me on Womens' Affairs to make a couple of<br />
comments on what we regard today as an historic occasion with the<br />
introduction of the Affirmative Action Bill, which we regard as a<br />
further example of the Government's commitment to improving the<br />
status of women in this country. The Bill's a statement, by the<br />
Government, to the women of Australia that the issues relating to<br />
increasing womens' opportunities, their role in the labour force<br />
are regarded by us as serious matters, which deserve a planned<br />
approach to remedy any existing discrimination and to promote<br />
real equal employment opportunities in this country. The Bill<br />
also conveys to Australian employers the Government's view that<br />
they need to take womens' participation in the workforce<br />
seriously and not to do that in some merely vocal way, but to<br />
actually plan for its improvement. I don't go any further to the<br />
details of the Bill, you're aware of those, but it is, as far as<br />
we're concerned in Government, one of the most important pieces<br />
of legislation which we've introduced to this point. Susan would<br />
you like to add anything?<br />
RYAN: Well I would like to say that one of the most remarkable<br />
things about the progress of the legislation to date is that<br />
we've achieved a very high level of agreement from a range of<br />
powerful institutions within the community. The legislation's<br />
based on the report of the working party which had the<br />
participation of Business Council of Australia, the Confederation<br />
of Australian Industry, the ACTU, womens' organisations, three<br />
Ministers in the Hawke Government and the opposition. And I<br />
think legislation based on such broad agreement is remarkable in<br />
itself and I think a very encouraging sign about the seriousness<br />
with which our society now is dealing with improving the<br />
employment skills of women and the employment opportunities of<br />
women. JOURNALIST: Prime Minister why do you believe that the threat of<br />
public exposure for non-compliance with the provisions of<br />
Affirmative Action plan should be sufficient sanction for those<br />
people who don't want to comply?<br />
PM: Well I think the important thing is not why I believe it,<br />
rather why those that were involved in it believe it. As I made<br />
clear in my speech in the Parliament and as Susan's just </p>
<p>indicated, this legislation reflects now the outcome of a very<br />
long process of real consultation. That consultation preceeded<br />
the initiation of the pilot program and then an examination of<br />
the results of that 12 months of the program by the range of<br />
parties involved, the employers and the trade unions and the<br />
higher education institutions, as well as our own office. And it<br />
was out of their discussions that the shared belief emerged that<br />
this would be the most effective way of producing the sort of<br />
results that we want. You had to strike a balance between an<br />
approach which on the one hand could have been a very coercive,<br />
punitive sort of approach. And one, which on the other hand,<br />
would have met the desires of some, but wouldn't ensure that<br />
there be no sort of coercion or punitive element at all. Now we<br />
believe on the advice of those who have been involved and are<br />
going to be involved that this is the most effective way. And if<br />
those people have that view then I think that it would not be<br />
sensible of us as a Government to neglect that.<br />
JOURNALIST: Senator Ryan can I ask you if the universities and<br />
colleges have had sufficient warning of the proposal to gear them<br />
up for 1986 and if they've had sufficient resources?<br />
RYAN: Well they certainly should be well prepared because we<br />
made it clear when we set up the working party that higher<br />
education would be covered and indeed a very large number of<br />
institutions already employed equal employment officers. The<br />
institutions in New South Wales were in any event to have been<br />
required to develop plans under the New South Wales legislation.<br />
We'll now be co-ordinating that nationally. So certainly I think<br />
they are very well prepared and the question of resources is one<br />
they may wish to take up in the future, but I think that they are<br />
adequately resourced to undertake this.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister why do you think the ALP is unable to<br />
find room for any more than one women in the 27 member ministry?<br />
PM: Well as you know the ways of Caucus are mysterious. Lots of<br />
forces operating there and who am I to try and analyse weight<br />
factors that operate.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you think it's appropriate that the Government<br />
asks society to accept a greater role for women when they're<br />
unable to find more room in the Ministry?<br />
PM: Wait a minute, you've got to go one or two stages back.<br />
This Party can hold its head up very much higher than I believe<br />
any other political organisation in this country in terms of the<br />
way it is translated the rhetoric of equal opportunity into<br />
reality as far as participation in the processes of the Party's<br />
organisation are concerned. There is a very strong degree of<br />
involvement and representation by women in the various levels of<br />
the Party organisation which has been now reflected in a very<br />
considerable increase in the number of women in the Parliaments.<br />
And we have just recently, last week, experienced a highlight of<br />
that commitment by the election in this Parliament of Joan Child<br />
to the Speakership. And in the South Australian Parliament, Ann<br />
Levy, to the Presidency of the Legislative Council. So we've got<br />
nothing to apologise for, I think, in regard to the acceleration </p>
<p>of the involvement of women in the processes of our Party and in<br />
elected positions within the Party. I accept your point that a<br />
logical development of that very substantial progress will be<br />
more women in the Ministry.<br />
JOURNALIST: When do you think that will happen?<br />
PM: When the Caucus votes that way.<br />
JOURNALIST: Will you be urging you colleagues to support women<br />
for the Ministry?<br />
PM: Let me make the point that was made by me in the speech. We<br />
are not in this legislation legislating for quotas. The concept<br />
of Affirmative Action means the-removal of barriers and bringing<br />
to the attention of employers that their practices should not<br />
discriminate against women. But it is still then a question of<br />
decision on merit and I believe that the women in the Caucus<br />
would not want it any other way.<br />
JOURNALIST: Senator Ryan are you hapy being the only member, the<br />
only female member of the ministry?<br />
RYAN: Well I'm certainly happy to be there. It's better being<br />
there than not being there. But I also regard myself as the thin<br />
end of the wedge. There'll be more to follow.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister you've been promising since October<br />
to write to the States on regulations on child care facilities.<br />
Can you tell us what the hold up is? t&gt;<br />
PM: Well I'm, of course in these matters, advised by the office<br />
of the Status of Women and the discussions that have been going<br />
on in this matter presumably have not reached the stage where<br />
that is the next step that's required. I will, of course, write<br />
at the time when I'm advised that is the most appropriate step.<br />
The States have no doubt about our commitments and requirements<br />
in this area. Are there any more questions in regard to this<br />
matter. If not we can go on to more general matters.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke you said there's going to be a tough<br />
Budget. Can you give us any idea of the quantity of expenditure<br />
cuts that will be needed?<br />
PM: I could but I won't Greg and I'm not trying to be akward in<br />
answering in that way. But let me say this that is really an<br />
elaboration of what I said in the House. We will meet the<br />
Trilogy requirements and it is clear that with the commitment to<br />
tax cuts that will be honoured, and the requirements of the<br />
Trilogy, that the substantial saving exercise that we require.<br />
I'm not going to put the figure on it at this stage. Though I<br />
can say this, it's going to require a considerable amount of work<br />
by myself and my colleagues in the ERC and the Budget process.<br />
JOURNALIST: That's not going to please some of your ministers is<br />
it? PM: Well I think we really should get this matter cleared up. </p>
<p>I'm not entirely suprised by the question of the Minister's<br />
attitude in this matter. Now first of all be prepared to award<br />
the prize for the beat-up of the year. There are those who talk<br />
about the revolt remarkable exercise. my ministers aren't a<br />
revolting lot, I can assure you. And they have done, in the<br />
letter that they wrote to me, what I would expect them to do. I<br />
wrote to them and said now I want you to nominate your<br />
priorities. They've done that and they've done it in a fairly<br />
lengthy letter. Spelling out those priorities in the light of<br />
what's happened to this point. And may I say, in the letter,<br />
there's a clear acknowledgement that what we are able to do in<br />
this forthcoming Budget will have to be decided, in the terms<br />
that they use as I recall, the perspective fiscal environment. A<br />
perfectly reasonable letter and one which caused me no concern at<br />
all. And as I say, I must give ten out of ten for the beat-up<br />
prize for those who call it a revolt.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke why didn't you say that to Parliament<br />
yesterday when you were questioned on it?<br />
PM: Well I felt no necessity to say it yesterday. I made a<br />
clear point that I thought was required by the level of questions<br />
that was directed to me and went to the next point.<br />
JOURNALIST: Isn't that a fairly contemptuous attitude to the<br />
Parliament? PM: Contemptuous of the opposition?<br />
JOURNALIST: No of the Parliament.<br />
PM: No not contemptuous of the Parliament at all. I mean if I'm<br />
going to operate on the basis that a beat-up really creates of<br />
itself a fact then I suppose then I'd be going on at considerable<br />
length on various occasions. I operate on a basis of dealing<br />
with the facts. The facts are quite clear there was no revolt<br />
and nothing which remotely approached a revolt. I didn't have<br />
the feeling Laurie that out there in electorate-land that they'd<br />
fallen for that beat-up. I didn't have any sense of urgency<br />
about it.<br />
JOURNALIST: Were you disappointed at the contents, or some of<br />
the contents of the letter?<br />
PM: Oh yes of course. I'd prefer that that sort of thing not<br />
happen, yes.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime minister are you critical of Westpac's<br />
decision to lift its interest rates, the only bank to do so to<br />
date? PM: Let me answer that question in an indirect way, but it gets<br />
you there. I have over a considerable period of time, both in<br />
the Parliament and outside it, expressed my absolute confidence<br />
in the Treasurer, Paul Keating. I still have that absolute<br />
confidence.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke you said in Parliament today that next </p>
<p>year's Budget deficit will fall in proportion of GDP. Would you<br />
actually give a commitment that there'll be a cut in money terms?<br />
PM: I gave a considered deliberate answer.<br />
JOURNALIST: The Treasurer in his statement about the tax package<br />
last year said that tax cuts would be financed by the increase in<br />
the deficit which means that there would be a nominal increase in<br />
the deficit in nominal terms next year.<br />
PM: The Treasurer's made it quite clear that the requirements of<br />
the Trilogy will be met. It is possible that as well as meeting<br />
the requirements of the Trilogy that there be no increase in the<br />
deficit as a proportion of GDP, that there may be a reduction in<br />
the nominal amount as well. But neither I, nor the Treasurer at<br />
this stage of the Budget process are going beyond that statement.<br />
And it would be unrealistic to do so.<br />
JOURNALIST: . that could mean an increase in nominal terms.<br />
PM1: Well I don't expect it but if there were, now let me be<br />
quite clear. I don't expect it, but if there were it would not<br />
be inconsistent with the Trilogy. Now I hope that's clear and<br />
that you get both parts of what I said.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke in your review of spending can you give a<br />
guarantee that the promise to the States of a real increase in<br />
their tax sharing grants will not be disturbed?<br />
PM: I think that the whole range of our expenditures will be<br />
reviewed and within that review the position of all elements,<br />
including the States, will obviously be looked at. Now don't say<br />
Hawke says they're going to be slashed. I'm simply saying that<br />
all elements will be looked at.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you agree with Mr Kerin that the Government will<br />
have to look at cutting into some major programs in order to meet<br />
its commitments?<br />
PM: Look what we have done since we've been in Government is<br />
steadfastly and effectively each year gone about the process of<br />
Budget formation in a way calculated to produce the result that<br />
will satisfy our economic objectives. And we have on each<br />
occassion, both at the formal Budget time itself and as you know<br />
the other years in the earlier May Statements, gone about the<br />
expenditure restraint exercise in a way which is on some<br />
occasions gone into major areas. On other occasions into minor<br />
areas, or a combination and we've produced the result that's<br />
required on each occasion. Now we're entitled to say there's our<br />
track record. We will make the decisions which are necessary to<br />
produced the overall fiscal result that's required. We've done<br />
it three years, we'll do it again. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Prime minister, how do you respond to the<br />
opposition's point today that the ordinary Australian can no<br />
longer afford the high interest rates that your policies have I<br />
PM: I am touched to have the Leader of the Opposition<br />
talking about what the view and attitude of ordinary Australians<br />
is about interest rates because after all he is not entitled to<br />
come and speak with any authority. In the first place, he has no<br />
policy in this area of any substance. Apparently, as far as one<br />
can follow him he would be in favour, in the housing area, of<br />
having a ceiling on interest rates for housing when interest<br />
rates are rising. And when interest rates were falling, to<br />
remove it. He is regarded as a joke. And it has been quite<br />
clear that when he talks in this area the industry has repudiated<br />
him as having any capacity to talk with sense. His own<br />
colleague, Senator Chaney, has recently commented on this issue<br />
in the very specific context of the attitudes of the people. He<br />
said, that is Senator Chaney, " I have been round the electorate<br />
and they don't seem to have the same view about this as they didI<br />
before." He was complaining in a sense, we tried to beat this up<br />
as a stick with which to push the Burke Government out of office.<br />
It didn't work. What that means, Laurie, is this. And I have<br />
been saying it before and I have said it in the House. Let me<br />
say it again the Australian people are more intelligent and<br />
perspicacious on these issues than this bereft, motley collection<br />
of people who purport to pass for an Opposition. Because the<br />
people of Australia understand that interest rates are to be<br />
looked at not simplicita, but as part of a total economic<br />
strategy. No government wishes to have recourse to a tight<br />
monetary policy for the sake of slowing down activity or imposing<br />
difficulties for some. You are not masochists. What you are<br />
about is to have an overall economic strategy which is calculated<br />
to maintain economic growth, employment growth with sustainable<br />
levels of inflation and with containable balance of payments<br />
outcome. Now the people of Australia have seen the capacity of<br />
this Government to bring together a total, effective economic<br />
strategy. They recognise that within the circumstances that we<br />
have been confronted with last year, that the decision that we<br />
taken to have a tighter monetary policy was appropriate. And<br />
they have reflected their understanding of that, I would suggest,<br />
both in actual electoral situations and in the polls.<br />
JOURNALIST: Just to clarify that, Sir. Are you saying that this<br />
is not hurting you electorally?<br />
PM: I am not trying to be brash about it. It would be stupid to<br />
be brash. I am saying this that on the evidence of the<br />
elections of South Australia and Western Australia, and Scullin<br />
if you like, and on the assertion of Senator Chaney, that the<br />
people of Australia seem, and I congratulate them for it, to be<br />
making an overall judgement. They say if you are going to see<br />
how an economy is going you just don't look at one element. if<br />
there is one element of it which has some results which, for<br />
some, are not pleasing okay sure we note that. But is this a<br />
government which has shown its capacity to produce an overall<br />
economic strategy which produces the best results for the<br />
economy. They seem to be making that judgement. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Prime minister, do you see any circumstances under<br />
which the Government might intervene to change or to block the<br />
Bell Resources bid for BHP? I<br />
PM: I think you would appreciate that the general position of<br />
this Government is that it is appropriate that these sort of<br />
things should be worked out in the market place. We have been<br />
watching developments quite closely. And we will continue to<br />
monitor them. To this point, by defintion, we have not felt a<br />
compulsion to intervene. So I therefore say that we will<br />
continue to watch this. Should some circumstance arise where we<br />
felt the need to change the present stance, well we would<br />
consider it. But to this point, no, it is a matter for the<br />
market. JOURNALIST: Just on that question Mr Hawke, does the Government<br />
have a view on whether or not BHP should be broken up<br />
PM: My prima facie view would be against it breaking up.<br />
JOURNALIST: Would the Government therefore be prepared to take<br />
action to ensure that that was the case?<br />
PM: The correct answer to that, Paul, is that we haven't, as a<br />
Government, directed our mind to it. It is a hypothetical<br />
question, but I think I would answer it this way. Should a<br />
situation arise where there was some suggestion that action would<br />
be taken in that direction which, on our judgement, would be<br />
inimical to the best interests of Australia we would consider<br />
that. But it hasn't arisen at this stage.<br />
JOURNALIST: Why would you be worried about it being broken up,<br />
Mr Hawke?<br />
PM: You may notice that I used the word prima facie. Obviously,<br />
we are talking about a totally hypothetical situation Greg, but<br />
let me give you the flavour of what is in my mind. You will<br />
recall that when we came to government there was a very, very<br />
real possibility that BHP was going to make a commercial decision<br />
to abandon its steel making enterprise, that it was<br />
non-profitable and non-competitive, and that their resources tied<br />
up in that would be better used-in another way. Now I said then<br />
on behalf the opposition I wasn't long in that capacity but I<br />
said then and then I certainly said it when I became Prime<br />
Minister, that we would not tolerate that situation because the<br />
national interests of Australia were not compatible with not<br />
having a steel industry. Now, it is in that sense that I am<br />
saying should there be some suggestion that the resources tied up<br />
there would be more profitable to the acquirer in other ways. It<br />
is that sort of thing.<br />
JOURNALIST: Sir, could I ask if you are disturbed that for the<br />
second day in a row your Treasurer has allowed the Opposition to<br />
get under his skin in the Parliament?<br />
PM: Let me say this, it is a repetition of something I have said<br />
earlier, I have very, very great confidence in Paul Keating. </p>
<p>There are varying judgements about the outcome. I notice in<br />
reading reviews today that in some quarters he was awarded a KO0<br />
not a technical KO0, a KO0. So, in the judgement of many he did<br />
very well. I haven't heard the proceedings today but I have<br />
almost unlimited confidence in the capacities of the Treasurer to<br />
handle himself effectively. He has, let's put it, a variety of<br />
modes. And he is very effective in nearly all of them.<br />
JOURNALIST: Why did you qualify this and say almost?<br />
PM: There is only room for a few of us<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, do you really intend to legislate<br />
separately for the Bill of Rights to override state gerrymanders<br />
and if so when?<br />
PM: What we have said there is that if the Bill goes through you<br />
would expect to get, I would think fairly early, a report from<br />
the Commission on the question of how state electoral legislation<br />
met the requirements of the convention. And I can't therefore<br />
put an actually time specific point on it, but I would expect<br />
that within this year we should be in a position, if the Bill is<br />
passed and the Commission reports, we would be in a position<br />
within this year.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you believe the Queensland ALP would win an<br />
election if the present boundaries are overturned by<br />
PM: It is very difficult with the present boundaries and that is<br />
not just my assessment, but it is the assessment of the Liberal<br />
Party in Queensland that the electoral boundaries are totally<br />
unjust and make it virtually impossible for either the Liberal<br />
Party or the Labor Party to achieve the result to which you<br />
refer. Under fair boundaries, yes I think they could because I<br />
say this and say it very firmly, the Queensland Government is<br />
the worst State Government in Australia. It has far and away the<br />
worst economic performance. It is pitifully below the national<br />
average whether you look in terms of employment, unemployment,<br />
industrial disputation, bankruptcies, all these relevant<br />
criteria, Queensland under that Government is pitifully the worst<br />
performer in Australia. It is also a government which is<br />
increasingly racked by internal scandals and incompetencies.<br />
Under a fair electoral system Labor would win.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime minister, which Bill do you mean when say..<br />
PM: The Bill which Mr Bowen has put through the House of<br />
Representatives and which is being considered by the Senate.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you mean the Bill of Rights itself or the Human<br />
Rights? PM: I mean the Bill that is before the Senate now.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, does your Government support the Master<br />
Builders' Association in its campaign against the Builders<br />
Labourers' Federation? </p>
<p>PM: What we have done is in conjunction with the State<br />
Governments and in discussions with employers and the ACTU, tried<br />
to establish a code of conduct. And to the extent that the<br />
builders are acting in accordance with that code of conduct and<br />
that is not succumbing to the threats of the BLF, then they have<br />
the support of governments, Federal and State.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, have you had any representations from or<br />
talks with the Victorian Government about the oil price decision?<br />
PM: No, I haven't. But whether there has been some discussions<br />
with some of the Ministers I am not sure.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, reports today suggest that Mr Keating<br />
would the full flow-on effect should be passed on. Do you<br />
agree with that?<br />
PM: I talked about beat-ups before. If you are going to get me<br />
to make, or if you think you are going to get me pass an opinion<br />
on an alleged position of a minister in a newspaper report, well<br />
I congratulate you on your optimism. The decision of the<br />
Government on this issue oil pricing will be made next week<br />
and we will know then.<br />
JOURNALIST: Will we get a decision on Monday?<br />
PM: We might.<br />
JOURNALIST: We might?<br />
PM: It covers the possibilities, doesn't it?<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, when you said earlier that the whole<br />
range of expenditure would be looked at, does that include areas<br />
that have been looked at before but rejected such as tertiary<br />
education fees and family allowances?<br />
PM: You have got a general question and a specific. Answering<br />
your general question. Yes, the whole range will be looked at.<br />
I don't know whether you have an appreciation of just what is<br />
involved in this exercise. I wouldn't wish it upon anyone. It<br />
is a time-consuming, awful sort of process, but once you are<br />
committed to the position then it is appropriate in your economic<br />
strategy to reduce the demand on community resources through the<br />
public sector in ways which are consistent with the pursuit of<br />
your basic social objectives. Then you have got to look over the<br />
whole range and try and ensure that you can get a level of<br />
outlays consistent with the attainment of that objective. And so<br />
yes we will be looking at the whole range. And I guess some<br />
people will want to l. ook in areas which have been considered<br />
before. On the specific issue that you mentioned about tertiary<br />
fees, the Government has no intention of introducing tertiary<br />
fees. JOURNALIST: Have you made a decision on whether there is going<br />
to be a May statement?<br />
PM: No. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, on interest rates again. What is<br />
the Government's current thinking on the value of the home loan<br />
interest rates ceiling?<br />
PM: That position has been made quite clear on a number of<br />
occasions by myself and the Treasurer. I have got nothing to add<br />
to what I have said before about that.<br />
JOURNALIST: You are not at all moved by the banks' argument that<br />
finance will continue to dry up?<br />
PM: The banks have been putting that argument before when we<br />
stated our position.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, are you concerned that this..<br />
process which you have talked about will become destabilising?<br />
PM: Don't get carried away by the observations of others, those<br />
who are not involved in it. It is certainly not destabilising,<br />
hasn't been in our previous three years. We have produced the<br />
results. It won't. be destabilising in 1986. I respect very much<br />
the commitment and determination of ministers in particular<br />
portfolios to say well look I want to do as much as I can within<br />
this portfolio to advance the interests of those people that come<br />
within my portfolio. I mean, if they didn't have that commitment<br />
and that determination they shouldn't be in the job. Now<br />
having said that they have demonstrated in the previous three<br />
years their capacity to balance that commitment with an overall<br />
picture of the Government's economic strategy. They have been<br />
very good in that in the past three years, they will be again. I<br />
simply make the point that it is a tedious process. It is not<br />
great fun sitting in the Cabinet Room for hour after hour going<br />
through 27 portfolios and seeing what you can save here, what you<br />
can save there. If you wanted to think of a way of spending of a<br />
pleasant time, that would come at the bottom of the list. But we<br />
have shown our capacity to do it on three occasions without any..<br />
destabilising. And the same will happen again, the fourth time,<br />
in 1986.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
