<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7452</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF DOORETOP, MANLY OVAL, SYDNEY - 9 JANUARY 1989 E &amp;OE - PROOP ONLY</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/01/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007452.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF DOORSTOP, MANLY OVAL, SYDNEY 9 JANUARY 1989<br />
E A OH PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: Should Australians be saddened by the death of<br />
Emperor Hirohito?<br />
PM: I don't think it's a question of sadness but T think we<br />
should understand that while it's appropriate to remember the<br />
time of war between our two countries, it is more appropriate to<br />
remember now, 44 years after the end of the war, that Japan is<br />
our major trading partner and that much of the prosperity of this<br />
country depends upon that trading relationship and it's in the<br />
interests of this and future generations of Australians to build<br />
further upon that strong economic relationship.<br />
JOURNALIST: Why aren't you going to the funeral?<br />
PH: it's very interesting. We have the silly season of the<br />
media, there's no political stories, they have to make them up.<br />
There was never any intention of the Prime Minister going to the<br />
funeral. Never. so the media suggests that now I've made up my<br />
mind I'm not going, there's a story. so just understand, Billy<br />
season of the media that story, nothing more, nothing less.<br />
JOURNALIST: Why was there never an intention to go?<br />
PH: Because it's not appropriate. it's more appropriate that<br />
the level of Head of State, that your Head of State goes. The<br />
Emperor is not the Head of Government. I'm the uead of<br />
Government. The Governor-General, is the Head of State of here.<br />
So it was never on the cards in any shape or form. I repeat,<br />
silly season media beatup. I'm not unhappy about that but just<br />
understand that that's all it is and ever was.<br />
JOURNALIST: Are you concerned about somne of the comments that<br />
have been raised?<br />
PH: well, I don't think they've been helpful but those who've<br />
been associated with war time organisations may make comments<br />
like that. of course Sir William Keys would not make those sorts<br />
of comments. It's unfortunate the RSL doesn't have that Bort of<br />
leadership at this time. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, who will go over to Japan as the<br />
representative of Australia?<br />
PM; The Governor-General I imagine will go.<br />
JOURN4ALIST: Mr Hayden as well?<br />
PM: The funeral as i understand will be after he is<br />
Governor-General. if he is Governor-General when the funeral is<br />
on he will go. if it's before he is Governor-General and Sir<br />
Ninian is still Governor-General he will go. Let me repeat, this<br />
is a very uncomplicated position. I wish you wouldn't mak~ e<br />
something complicated which isn't complicated.<br />
ends<br />
0 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
