<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5551</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS AT CONFEDERATION OF SPORT MELBOURNE</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/03/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005551.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
4~ I~ A AS Dg-L; IVEPED<br />
PRIME MINISTER' WEDNESDAY, 25 MARCH, 1981<br />
ADDRESS AT CONFEDERATION OF SPORT<br />
MELBOURNE<br />
I would like to welcome you all here. Especially I would like<br />
to welcome His Royal Highness. We are always honoured when<br />
he visits Australia and it is a tribute to his significant<br />
contribution to the cause of sport that he is here on<br />
this occasion.<br />
I understand that Australia has some cause to be especially<br />
grateful on this occasion because as I am advised, a European<br />
country that I will not name and Australia both offered to<br />
host this inaugural meeting. Part of the business of seeing<br />
that Australia was successful in that particular competition<br />
was the willingness of his Royal Highness to travel to Austra]. ia<br />
if the meeting were to be held here. If he was going to trave~ l<br />
that distance to be here, how could anyone else refuse? So thtank<br />
you very much indeed, sir, for being here and helping to make<br />
sure that Australia and this city had the opportunity to host<br />
this particular occasion.<br />
I would. like to welcome, for my wife and myself and for the<br />
Commonwealth-Government, the delegates to Sport International 1981.<br />
More thJan 50 countries are represented here, representatives of<br />
a large number of international sporting bodies. I hope very<br />
much that your meeting will be productive, and that yourstay in<br />
Australia and in thft-s city will be a happy one, that you will not<br />
be wor'ked too hard during your days with us.<br />
Austraj. 4, and. I think especially Melbourne, are-delighted to<br />
be the venue for Sport International 1981.<br />
This event, as you would all know of course, goes back to<br />
discussions which began in 1974. At the Commonwealth Games in<br />
Christchurch, informal discussions between representatives from<br />
a number of countries gave rise to the idea that an international<br />
conference of national sports confederations should indeed<br />
be established. As. I understand, the purpose is to strengthen<br />
national sports confederations and to enable them to carry oul:<br />
their responsibilities to their many sports better and more<br />
effectively and independent of governments. In Australia there<br />
has never been any doubt th~ t our sporting bodies ' are independent<br />
of government. They have demonstrated that on many occasions,<br />
and long may it last. / 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
Four years after Christchurch, at Edmonton, there were further<br />
informal meetings convened by His Roya!' Highness, to consider'<br />
whether a world body along the lines of West European<br />
non-governmental sports organisations', as I am told, the NGO<br />
Club, was feasible and whether it was desirable. That led to<br />
a considerable degree of interest. That led to a meeting in,<br />
London in March in 1979 under his Royal Highness' chairmanship<br />
where representatives from 17 nations and several international<br />
sporting bodies met. A working committee was established.<br />
A draft constitution was-drawn. I do not know whether your actual<br />
constitution has any resemblance to the draft, but that is-the. way<br />
Of constitutions, they change as time goes on. Also, of course<br />
that working committee was to recommend aims and objectives.<br />
There was a further meeting in Amsterdam in the same year,<br />
and then an organising committee to establish this particular<br />
meeting. So there has been a long chain of events, a good deal<br />
of discussion and you have got to the launching point.<br />
This event is the culmination of a long process, but hopefully,<br />
this is only the end of the beginning. For it is the inaugural<br />
or the formation meeting of the International Assembly of<br />
National Sports Confederations. I think that there is great<br />
potential in this assembly.<br />
Sport is important to all of us. It is important to all nations.<br />
It is important in relationships between nations, and it is also<br />
important for sporting confederations and sporting bodies in<br />
particular countries to be able to conduct their own affairs with<br />
the maximum degree of freedom and conduct their own relationships<br />
with similar bodies in other countries. I hope very much that<br />
this assembly will advance that cause with strength.<br />
There is great importance and great value in sport, in the growth<br />
of sports and in greater participation in sport, not only at the<br />
highest level where nations compete with nations but to try and<br />
achieve the maximum participation of people in various sports.<br />
The fact that thisL-assembly represents, as* I am told, over 1004W<br />
sports:-instead of just a few is something of value. I hope it<br />
will add to international co-operation in sport.<br />
I would like to wish you all the best of good fortune for<br />
Sport International 1981, for this assembly, for its launching<br />
and for its success in future years. I thank you all very much<br />
for coming to Melbourne and I hope that you will return, and<br />
I am sure that the Premier, Mr. Hamrer, joins me very warmly<br />
in the welcome to this particular city.<br />
000--</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
