<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5021</transcript-id>
    <title>PJT FINDING ON SHELL AUSTRALIA APPLICATION FOR PRICE INCREASES</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/04/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005021.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
13<br />
APRILP 1979<br />
PJT FINDING ON SHELL AUSTRALIA APPLICATION FOR PRICE INCREASES<br />
I am concerned at the statement issued by Shell Australia to<br />
the effect that they are considering their position following<br />
the decision of the Prices Justification Tribunal to grant<br />
smaller price-increases than had been sought by the company.<br />
It is the public duty of companies to accept and abide by<br />
decisions of the Prices Justification Tribunal, which is the<br />
arbitral authority in these matters, even when companies<br />
privately disagree with its decisions.<br />
The Prices Justification Tribunal's role in determining prices<br />
is comparable to that of the Conciliation and Arbitration<br />
Commission in relation to wages. Companies quite rightly condemn<br />
unions for their failure to abide by the Commission's decisions<br />
when they do not receive the wage increases they seek. Such<br />
condemnation sounds hollow when companies behave in a similar<br />
fashion in respect to Prices Justification Tribunal findings.<br />
In this instance the Prices Justification Tribunal's inquiry had<br />
been thorough and wide-ranging. The Tribunal had reached its findings<br />
after carefully considering all the evidence submitted by Shell<br />
concerning its costs and profitability, and the submissions which<br />
the company made on the various issues raised at the inquiry. The<br />
Prices Justification Tribunal also considered evidence and<br />
submissions from other interested parties including State<br />
Governments, the oil industry, the transport industry, consumer<br />
groups, farmers and trade unions.<br />
The Government's fight against inflation needs the support and<br />
co-operation of all sections of the community.<br />
Accordingly, I expect Shell Australia and other oil companies<br />
to behave in a responsible fashion and to accept the decision of the<br />
Tribunal. The Government frequently calls on unions to abide by the umpire'is<br />
decision.-This is an occasion when we-call on. a company to do just tha<br />
0000000 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
