<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1533</transcript-id>
    <title>ASIAN TOUR 1967 - CAMBODIA - TOAST PROPOSED BY PRINCE NORODOM SIHANOUK AT GALA DINNER FOR THE PRIME MINISTER, MR HAROLD HOLT, AT PHNOM PENH - 29TH MARCH 1967</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/03/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001533.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
ASIAN TOUR 1967 CAMBODIA ARo,<br />
TOAST PROPOSED BY PRINCE NORODOM SIHANOUJK<br />
AT GALA DINNER FOR THE PRIME MINISTER,<br />
MR. HAROLD HOLT, AT PHNOM PENH. 29th March, 1967.<br />
It is with great pleasure that I welcome this evening the<br />
eminent Prime Minister of the Commonwealth of Australia, the Right<br />
Honourable Mr. Harold Holt and those distinguished personages who<br />
accompany him. May I assure them of the warmth of the welcome that<br />
awaits them, and express the hope that they, for their part, will enjoy<br />
their brief stay amongst us.<br />
I likewise assure you personally Mr. Prime Minister,<br />
of the great significance we Cambodians attach to this, the first occasion<br />
on which the Head of an Australian Government has paid us an offical<br />
visit, and of our appreciation of the opportunity thus afforded us of personal<br />
and friendly contacts between the members of our respective governments.<br />
I would likewise stress that your presence here this evening<br />
constitutes proof that different political options and social conceptions<br />
do not represent an insuperable barrier to the establishment of cordial<br />
relations between governments and peoples, nor do they preclude the<br />
possibility of co-operation to mutual advantage on mtters of common<br />
interest. Indeed, I would even make so bold as to claim that Khmer/<br />
Australian relations provide a world distracted by imperialist ambitions,<br />
and driven by national and economic rivalries with a shining example,<br />
not merely of peaceful but of fruitful and cordial co-existence. Moreover,<br />
the formula we have hit upon to produce such a state of affairs is a simple<br />
one, that of conforming in scrupulous fashion to the principle that all<br />
nations are equal, to that of give-and-take, coupled with a refusal to<br />
intervene in each other's internal affairs.<br />
Another factor which has contributed to the establishment<br />
of these cordial relations has been the provision of aid in various forms,<br />
and of a most practical sort provided unconditionally by your government<br />
including consignments of motorpumps for irrigation purposes, material<br />
for our railways, and equipment for our capital, and for the recently<br />
founded sea port which bears my name.<br />
We may be flattering ourselves unduly in regard to the<br />
assistance Australia has generously sent us in the light of a reward<br />
to the Khmer people for the untiring efforts they have been making<br />
ever since National Independence was recovered, to remedy Cambodia's<br />
formerly backward state and to equip it socially, economically and<br />
industrially with all the appurtenances of a modern nation.<br />
There are good m~ asons for assuming, however, that the<br />
rapid progress Cambodia has been making in every field has not<br />
attracted the attention it merits, and that the belief is still prevalent<br />
in the outside world that our country is a stagnant backwater where<br />
as one Australian newspaper expressed it " last year no industrial<br />
development of any sort has taken place". We have been devoting<br />
much time and energy to dissipating this mistake by providing foreign<br />
peoples with an opportunity to come to th~ eir own condusions in regard / 2. </p>
<p>-2<br />
zo the-progrmss-azhieved under the '" Sangkum" regime. in the course<br />
of the past-eleven years.<br />
One of the methods we adcpted was the creation cf a<br />
mobile exhibition of Cambodian achievements during the period in<br />
question, and of sending it abroad with a view to dissipating this<br />
mistken impression of our couitry. Visitors to this-exhibition<br />
in the m an y countries where it has opened its doors almost invariably<br />
exclaim " We had no idea Cambodia was so progressive, why it even<br />
boasts national industries and factories. This aspect of the progress<br />
Cambodia has made, Mr. Prime Minister, you will have an opportunity<br />
to verify in person.<br />
It is our sole ambition, however, as it is our passionate<br />
desire to be allowed to complete the task to which we have set our<br />
hand, free of threats to our national independence. For, were the<br />
Khmer people to be robbed of their national independence, they would<br />
be deprived of their present incentive to pursue their efforts, and would<br />
relapse into that state of apathy which prevailed at the time of the French<br />
protectorate, a moral condition which gave rise to the legend that the<br />
Khmers were an idle and obtuse race, lacking the mental capacity to<br />
acquire scientific or technical knowledge of any srt or description.<br />
If the erroneous nature of such an assumption has been<br />
demonstrated today, this should be ascribed to the impetus given by<br />
the recovery of national independence. But national independence<br />
perforce implies the absence of threats to territorial integrity. But<br />
certain great powers are presuming to call in question today the<br />
intangible nature of our present frontiers, obli vious of the fact that<br />
the " shoe is in fact on the other foot", as Cambodia possesses historic<br />
claims to territories at present being administered by neighbouring<br />
governments, We are however, a sensible, pragmatic people, who<br />
have no desire to stir up the embers oi pas-, quarrels or forgotten wars.<br />
All we ask is to be allowed to live in peace within our present frontiers.<br />
National independence likewise places us under an obligation<br />
to resist attempts from an y quarter to reduce the status of our country to<br />
that of a satellite. This obligation, reinforced by our firm conviction that<br />
it must be respected, disproved the " thesis" propunded by those who seek<br />
to disparage our motives to the effect that our neutral policy is biassed<br />
in favour of the" socialist camp" and implen-e nted in suchy fashion as to<br />
cause the maximum of embarrassment to the " free" world.<br />
But such an assumption is demolished by the very close and<br />
cordial nature of our relations with countries like Australia and France,<br />
the governments of which harbour no designs on the territories of their<br />
neighbours and cop~' 1uct their foreign policy in conformity with those<br />
principles of reciprocal respect and some best calculated not only to<br />
safeguard national interests, but to ensure the prosperity and happiness<br />
of the peoples confided to their charge.<br />
And it is with this assurance, and in this belief that I ask<br />
you, your E~ cellencies, ladies and gentlemen, to join me in this toast<br />
to the health of Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth Second, to the health<br />
of His Excellency Mr. Harold Holt, Madame Holt, and those Australian<br />
friends of curs present here this evening, to the prosperity of Australia,<br />
and to the happiness of its people ( di) to the friendship to bind our two<br />
countries and peoples together. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
