<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>598</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER RIGHT HON. R.G. MENZIES AT THE OPENING OF THE PHYTOTRON AT C.S.I.R.O., CANBERRA, ACT. ON 29TH AUGUST, 1962</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/08/1962</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000598.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE RIGHT HON R. G. MENZIES AT THE OPENING<br />
OF THE PHYTOTRON AT C. oS. IR0o CANBERRA, A. C. T.<br />
ON 229H AU 2T<br />
Sir, Your Excellencies, and Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
I have been very much struck today by the profound<br />
difference there is between politics and agricultural biology0<br />
You have just had it explained to you, those who are not<br />
already expert, that what is to be done in this place is to<br />
control the environment. In politics, it's the other way<br />
round, Thus today I've been down freezing at the airport<br />
saying goodbye to the King and Queen of Thailand, and acting,<br />
as nature has equipped me to do, us a windbreak for the Queen,<br />
with the wind blowing piactically at freezing point. And<br />
here I am this afternoon being gently cooked, feeling all the<br />
germs that I acquired in the wind this morning getting on<br />
nicely, being encouraged, being cultivated inside me.<br />
Now there is one other thing that I would like to<br />
tell you about the phytotron and I hope this won't go any<br />
further I beg of you to keep this dark. When C. S. I. R. O.<br />
first of all decided that a request ought to be made to the<br />
Government to find the money for a phytotron, the proposal<br />
fell into the hands of a relatively junior officer in my<br />
department who read it, and in all good faith, scribbled out<br />
a note saying, " This isronsense0 Oliphant already has a<br />
cyclotron, why do we have this overlapping and duplication?"<br />
Now that's not a it's a true story, but it. s a good story<br />
because it exhibits something that people don't always understand<br />
the astuteness of the civil service to avoid overlapping and<br />
waste. Thus " cocking a snoot" at Parkinson's Law with a<br />
vengeance. Well, Sir, you came along or somebody came along<br />
and explained to me what a phytotron was and I must confess<br />
that from that moment I found myself vastly interested in J. t.<br />
The idea of taking what has been in the past field work in<br />
remote places conducted under great difficulty and concentrating<br />
it in point of time. and space -that seemed to me, even to my<br />
ignorant lay mind, a dramatic thing, the value of which I<br />
thought quite obvious,<br />
It isn't always easy to resist the C, SI. R. O. though<br />
it thinks we resist it too much, Sir Frederick White referred<br />
to his great predecessor, lan Clunies Ross. I always thought<br />
of him not purely just as a scientist in himself, though he<br />
was, but as the greatest public relations man for science that<br />
this country has ever had.-a phenomenal genius for not sparing<br />
himself, for going out day after day, week after week, making<br />
other people understand the importance of the work that's being<br />
done in scientific research and, of course, in particular by<br />
C. S. I. ROo I suppose that if we were to ask ourselves what in<br />
the last twenty yearsup to fifty years, had been the great<br />
distinguishing feature of this century, apart from wars and<br />
political confusions, the answer would be the flowering of<br />
science and the growing application of science to technology,<br />
to the problems, the practical word-a-day problems, of the<br />
worldo And I7m perfectly certain that this is, in particular,<br />
true of agricultural scientific worko Each time we open a<br />
report by a statistician or by a demographer and we are told<br />
how rapidly the population of the world will double and how<br />
rapidly it will treble, we would need to be very insensitive<br />
to the problems of life if we weren't almost appalled by the<br />
idea that the same earth will have to sustain so many more<br />
thousands of millions of people, And. it will sustain them<br />
0 0 0 U 0 0/ 2 </p>
<p>only if, literally, the earth is encouraged to bring out its<br />
harivosto And in this field of scientific investigation, I<br />
think we see one of the great hopes of the future of mankind<br />
ne of the great hopes of fthture peace, oddly enough, because<br />
in a starving world there will always be war, And the great<br />
hope of peace with a growing population in the world is th't<br />
mon of devotion and women of devotionr. and distinction should<br />
give their talents to the kind of inv-estigation that will be<br />
conducted here. Now it isn't al. ways easy. is it, to make peoyle<br />
understand how important that is, fie're a bit given to taking<br />
things for granted. We ought to be able to bring up, not a<br />
few hundred people but a few scores of thousands of people<br />
to Kave a look at his and see wlhat is in the wind, see what<br />
is going on, see what the great objectives are, because then<br />
I think we would have a more understanding and encoaraging<br />
public. But there's another aspect of that which I want<br />
to mention to you0 We are in Australia I speak only for<br />
Australians here this afternoon we ar: e not a cynical race<br />
because cynicism is " well, whatts the use?", But we are a<br />
sceptical race, We need to have it proved " Show me, show<br />
me about this." I can remember and Ive said this before,<br />
I think in the presence of Dr. Lckson, I can remember a<br />
time when I was a small boy in the country, when the agricultural<br />
scientist put himself to tho trcuble of going up into<br />
the wheat country where I was born to try to explain to a<br />
collection of wheat farmers that a mysterious subjoet called<br />
superphosphate, if applied to that light sandy loam in that<br />
part of the country would bring about an enormous increase<br />
in productivity, ind you know, I could just almost hear<br />
wdoheast wit as cogsoti? n" g onS o ina ndth eso. r m" iOndh s well", O h, I Id odno'tn ' ktn okwno, w, t hew hoatld<br />
man didnyt use " Uh wcll you see, and in the end<br />
about three reasonably enlightened farmers decided that they<br />
would. give it a go,,<br />
I think from the long memory of it that they were<br />
told at that time in this particular soil that they ought<br />
to use a 1hundredweight of super to tbe acre And these three<br />
decided that they would try it out rather tentatively with<br />
half a hundredweight, And when they got ancther three bushels<br />
to the acre as ompared with their neighbours, then a few more<br />
people came to the conclusion th. lat it was prett1y good, You<br />
see, this is not a cynical attitude of mind but it's a<br />
sceptical attitude of mind and if I were asked to say, to<br />
name One defect in our pr'esent technological equipment in<br />
these areas, I would say it is that there i too great a gap<br />
in point of time and in point of space between the work done<br />
in a place like this and the work done on the farm and shoep<br />
station, In other words, we ale, so far in Australia, rather<br />
failing on the extension of the results of research to the<br />
man on the farm,<br />
This requires, of course, a great deal of co-operation<br />
between C! ommonwealth and Statos we hKave divided authorities<br />
on it but it also requires in the farmier himself a realization<br />
that he will not get the benefit of these investigotions until<br />
he is not only interested but enthusiastic and keen and<br />
demanding about getting it brought to him and his farm. And<br />
I know Sir. that you, because you! ve spoken many times to me<br />
about this, that you. woCuld regard it as a state almost of<br />
paradise, if the wol'k done, the magnificent work done by<br />
found its way out qaite quickly, quite effectively,<br />
C 0 0 JO a2/ 3 </p>
<p>3<br />
to the people who are engaged in production, because<br />
there is no doubt about it, all the old ideas have gone,<br />
Going back to that remote period wrnen I was a boy myself,<br />
Australia was a desert, it had a few sketchy bits of<br />
cultivable land around the margins, it had some areas<br />
where the rain fell agreeably, But oh, it could never<br />
sustain a population of more than ten millions. And<br />
then some bold fellow said, oh no, twenty, twenty some<br />
day, not this century, of course, but some time in the<br />
future twenty.<br />
Now we are casting loose from all those silly<br />
prejudiced ideaj and if we are now discovering that the<br />
same area of land, and of course it's been enormously<br />
extended, that the same area of land, with the benefits<br />
of scientific research brought to it, can produce twice<br />
as much, three times as much, four times as much as it<br />
did then we're ourselves making a contribution to the<br />
sus enance of an enormous, relatively enormous population<br />
in our own country and also making available for developing<br />
countries, which have much more acute problems of<br />
population and feeding, the results of the work that will<br />
be done here,<br />
So, Sir, I say that I'm grateful to you for<br />
allowing me to come along here and have the pleasure of<br />
saying a few very inadequate words on what I helieve<br />
to be one of the exciting occasions in applied science in<br />
the history of our country. Sir, I declare the phytotron,<br />
the controlled environment the CERES I'll call it I'm<br />
told now for short Vhatevcr you call it, I declare it<br />
open, Y~ Y_ </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
