<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9286</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P.J. KEATING, MP DOORSTOP, KAMORUNGA ENVIRONMENTAL PARK, CAIRNS, WEDNESDAY, 20 JULY 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/07/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009286.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL 20. Jul. 94 17: 51 No. 015 P. 01/ 08<br />
L PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING, MP<br />
DOORSTOP, KAMORUNGA ENVIRONMENTAL PARK, CAIRNS,<br />
WEDNESDAY, 20 JULY 1994<br />
E&amp; QE PROOF COPY<br />
J. Prime Minister can I ask you, first you were approached by the<br />
gentleman on the way in and he discussed Sky Rail with you, do you<br />
see that as a bit of a contradiction in terms to be planting trees on the<br />
one hand and, as they say, pulling them down on the other.<br />
PM; We are working on a bigger front than that. I mean, the declaration of<br />
the world heritage area was, I think, a huge leap forward for North<br />
Queensland and the Commonwealth, of course, committed, I was the<br />
Treasurer at the time, we committed the better part of $ 90 million to it<br />
and established adjustment schemes for those who were formerly<br />
employed there. And what I am doing today is announcing the further<br />
development of those adjustment schemes where we've taken forestry<br />
workers and put them into re-establishment of forests and<br />
rehabilitation of forests. So i think, you know, one has got to look at<br />
the big gestures because they are the ones that matter and as far as<br />
the specific projects go, I think Senator Faulkner is coming up anyway<br />
in a week or two's time and he can debate that then.<br />
J: Mr Keating, can you tell us why so long between official visits here to<br />
Cairns?<br />
PM: I have been here three times this year.<br />
J: But they were private visits though..<br />
PM: They are all the same when you drive through, whether it is public or<br />
private, they are all the same. I was here, I had a long inspection of<br />
thDe ~ ireo about a year ago and as a result of that the<br />
Commonwealth Government has now committed with Queensland<br />
million to buy back the hole in the heart on the other side of the<br />
Daintree river and to try and repair the damage done by the Bjelke </p>
<p>TEL 20. JuI. 94 17: 51 No. Ul1) r. uz/ uo<br />
2<br />
Petersen government in that disgraceful development on the other<br />
side of the river. So that came from my last unofficial visit. So I do<br />
things here officially and unofficially.<br />
J: ( John O'Farrell) Your concern about the development of Cairns the<br />
last time you were up here.<br />
PM: I haven't seen you for years, how are you going?<br />
JO'F: Long time.<br />
J: You thought he was dead didn't you?<br />
PM; No, he's too smart for that.<br />
JO'F: Since then there have been major developments either started or<br />
announced, is this getting worse. Is Cairns getting as bad as the Gold<br />
Coast, is that the way it's headed?<br />
PM: Well I don't think so. I think that I'm very encouraged by what I see as<br />
a renewed interest, you know, a more mature interest in the<br />
management of our heritage areas and the understanding that to<br />
preserve the heritage is not only intrinsically important, important in its<br />
own right, but because the region has such huge tourist potential that<br />
everything that then is done in the built environment as well as in the<br />
natural environment becomes important. There is a point of harmony<br />
between the two and I think people are getting to that and what we are<br />
seeing here today is a further example of that.<br />
J: What about change to the city itself though, I mean you had some<br />
harsh words about development in Cairns, that it was looking like<br />
another Gold Coast.<br />
PM: And I think people take some notice of those sorts of views and maybe<br />
change their attitudes a little. I'm optimistic that I think that Cairns can<br />
grow through another phase of economic growth. Just remember this,<br />
the Federal Government has got the economy growing at 5 per cent at<br />
the moment. The Australian economy is growing faster than any<br />
economy in the Western world. One per cent inflation, 5 per cent<br />
growth and 3 per cent employment growth. Now that sort of growth will<br />
bring its development pressures with it and, I think, you know, a<br />
municipal government has got to be alert to that and say right there is<br />
going to be another phase of development how do we handle it.<br />
J: Those factors for growth, do they include low interest rates and loans<br />
for houses?<br />
PM: Well they include the maintenance of low inflation principally, and -the<br />
fact that the country is now imeasurably more competitive. I mean,<br />
Australians have done a lot to produce their own cornucopia of growth </p>
<p>TEL:' 20. JU1. 94 1 K: t~ l NO. U IZ r -1I<br />
3<br />
and opportunity and one of the points I always make about my<br />
opponents, they are always trying to sort of cruel the pitch. They are<br />
now trying to say the recovery is too strong: " too good, too good, the<br />
recovery is too good. We might have to have higher interest rates in<br />
there shocking." What we have got to do is preserve the recovery and<br />
preserve low inflation and that is, I think, going to be important to all of<br />
us. And it is going to be no less important here in Cairns where I think<br />
there is tremendous potential. For a start, there is a shift of population<br />
to Queensland and beyond that, of course, the carriage of very large<br />
visiting communities of tourists. And we want to do that and do it well<br />
and still preserve the best of what we have.<br />
J: Ralph Willis said this morning that the sale of the FAC is very<br />
important to the success of the Budget, do you agree with that?<br />
PM: Well I got asked about that down in Townsville.<br />
J: Does it worry you, the way, that the Coalition is targeting the seat of<br />
Leichhardt the number of senators and opposition spokesmen they are<br />
sending up here?<br />
PMV: Well they can do their best, but basically it is the Commonwealth<br />
Labor Government that put international tourism on the map. I mean,<br />
the growth in the prosperity of Northem... Queensland was there<br />
because of the Commonwealth Labor Governmnt. iI It was there from<br />
the early 1 980s and it is now being helped by a sensible State Labor<br />
Government who we work together with very well, I mean, Mr Downer<br />
is out there in the Financial Review saying today: " I won't be giving<br />
detailed policies, they are saying we won't be giving detailed policies,",<br />
where a month ago he was saying the public are entitled to some<br />
detail about policies. They want to be in the debate, these characters,<br />
without any policy. And, at the same time, trying to claim from you that<br />
which a real government has put into place over ten years. That is,<br />
you know, this area has been completely changed for the better<br />
because of the policies of the national government.<br />
J: Rockhampton, Townsville and Cairns are all part of the itinerary, Prime<br />
Minister, everywhere that you have gone, protests, are you happy with<br />
the welcome you have received?<br />
PM: Oh, absolutely. It's an amazing reception. I had 1,100 kids turned up<br />
to have a general talk down at one of the principal schools on the<br />
itinerary and I really enjoyed that, I mean, I think particularly year 11<br />
and 12 students, they are as sharp as tacks, they are a tough<br />
audience. And I really enjoyed a chance to talk to them. I met another<br />
very large community group in Rockhampton, I got a wonderful<br />
reception. I had a tremendous civic reception last evening in<br />
Townsville and then a bumper party function in the evening and I have<br />
had the same sort of general goodwill here in Cairns. So I couldn't be<br />
happier. I mean, you will always get the odd person with a placard </p>
<p>20. Jul. 9 417: 51 No. 015b . ua/ uo<br />
TEL: 4<br />
about this or about that. You know, it will be Hinchenbrook(?) Island<br />
or it will be something else. But I mean, look at the big mass of<br />
people, how they respond and the answer is very well.<br />
J: Well the issues up here like this Sky Rail and the Hinchinbrook issue<br />
you just mentioned there, environment issues. How important is the<br />
environment generally going to be at the next election?<br />
PM: Well I think it is going to be important and I think the Labor Party is<br />
going to be the best at it. Because we are the only ones that care<br />
about it. I mean, here we are in the national Budget just a month or<br />
two ago, announcing the fact that we are going to buy back the land in<br />
the hole in the heart which was, I think, disgracefully developed and<br />
sold in the 1970s and 80s and these sort of, if you like, broad ticket<br />
issues in the environment are the ones that matter.<br />
ENDS </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
