<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8880</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP INTERVIEW WITH PAUL LYNEHAM, 7:30 REPORT, MELBOURNE, 9 JUNE 1993</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/06/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008880.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL: 10. Jun. 93 16: 15 No. 018 P. 01/ 08<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
INTERVIEW WITH PAUL LYNEHAM9 7.30 REPORT, MELBOURNE, 9 JUNE<br />
1993 E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
PL: Prime Minister, welcome again to the program.<br />
PM: Thanks Paul.<br />
PL When we get down to basics are we talking about a different attitude<br />
towards Aboriginal Australia between, say yourself, and Premiers<br />
Kennett and Court?<br />
PM: I think so, yes that's right, yes I do. I think there is not the willingness<br />
there ought to be to accept that the High Court has made a seminal<br />
decision and It's the Governments of the Commonwealth and the<br />
States to set up mechanisms to respond to the hearing and awarding of<br />
Native Title in accordance with the decision of the High Court.<br />
PL: Could it be that you are too far out in front of community opinion?<br />
PM: No, it is not a matter of community opinion, It Is a matter of the law. The<br />
High Court has said that there Is a Native Title In the common law and It<br />
has existed since settlement in 1788, not In a sense, we will use the<br />
word, discovered until June 1992, but existing from 1788. Now I would<br />
like to say for the purpose of your viewers who are not certain what the<br />
legal position Is, it doesn't mean that large parts of Australia, partlcuiariy<br />
of the buiit up areas of Australia, the urban areas of Australia will be<br />
subject to a native title ciaim. Where freehold title has been issued the<br />
native title has been held to have been extinguished, where a lease hold<br />
has been Issued, the native title In most cases, or in many cases has<br />
been extinguished.<br />
PLU So these enormnous claims we have seen in recent days, I mean the<br />
entire ACT for example, that's a nonsense?<br />
PM: A nonsense. It has got nothing to do with Mabo. </p>
<p>TEL: 10. Jun. 93 16: 15 No .018 P. 02/ 08<br />
2<br />
PLU Anid not very helpful to you I would have thought?<br />
PM: it's a tactic of some of the extreme elements of the Aboriginal<br />
community, it has got nothing to do with Mabo, has no chance of<br />
succeeding and as a sense.. this particular process.<br />
PU Now you began these talks here today with some Premiers wanting<br />
simply to, if you like, forget that Mabo had ever happened, extinguish<br />
native title across the whole of Australia<br />
PM: There was, if you like, an unwillingness on the part of some Premiers to<br />
accept that the High Court has made a seminal decision to be less then,<br />
if you like, accepting of the tact, or In fact to debate the High Court's<br />
right to mae~ a decision about native title. Well of course this may be<br />
Interesting for them, but of no Interest to me. The High Court has made<br />
this decision, native title does exist and It Is now up to the Governments<br />
to see that the methods are put in place to hear native title, to dispense<br />
native title and to validate all the leases which are put into question.<br />
PL: So, when the Western Australian Premier says that these key decisions<br />
In our national life should be made by elected leaders, you say well<br />
that's a nice Idea, but that's not the way It Is?<br />
PM: No, I said to him today, we have got a constitution which Is made up of<br />
an executive, a legislature, a judiciary and the judiciary, our High Court<br />
makes decisions about these sorts of matters and it has made a<br />
decision about native title. There is no appeal to that decision, there Is<br />
no privy council and nor should there be and therefore the law of that<br />
decision should be respected by all governments in Australia and his In<br />
particular whether he likes it or not.<br />
PIL: Last night, fairly late last night, you thought didn't you that you were<br />
about to come pretty close to getting some sort of agreement here?<br />
PM; I thought I was moving towards an agreement, yes.<br />
PL: What sort of agreement did you have hopes of at that stage?<br />
PM: One where the Commonwealth's said for its part it would validate all<br />
leases that were Issued since 1975.<br />
PL: The year of the Racial Discrimination Act?<br />
PM: The year the Racial Discrimination Act was Introduced and I made what<br />
I thought was a generous offer of the Commnwealth paying any<br />
compensation arising from eighteen years of the Issue of that lease. </p>
<p>TEL: 10. Jun. 93 16: 15 No. 018 P. 03/ 08<br />
3<br />
PL: So whatever leases the States had issued you would pick Up the tab?<br />
PM: We would pick up the tab which was an exceptionally I think generous<br />
offer from the Commonwealth.<br />
PU And what else was part of the plan?<br />
PM: In return they had to agree to the establishment of a set of tribunals<br />
under Commonwealth guidelines, but set up In the States to hear native<br />
title claims and award native title and to adopt some principles on the<br />
way through such as the protection of native tite and Its revival there<br />
after; after a particular purpose had ceased.<br />
PL: This system for hearing claims for native title, this could apply to future<br />
leases? 6<br />
PM: Future leases that is right.<br />
PUL What went wrung last night?<br />
PM: Premier Kennett unilaterally told the meeting about 10: 30 pm that he had<br />
had enough of this, he was going to legislate unilaterally, that he had<br />
advice that he could validate the leases by a decision of the Victorian<br />
Parliament and that he would then legislate to dispense native title In<br />
VIctorla and where that native title was Inconsistent with a commercial<br />
purpose, he would extinguish the title.<br />
PU: And where native title was found to be proved he would pay<br />
compensation?<br />
PM: He would pay compensation.<br />
PL: But he doesn't expect to have to pay very much at all does he?<br />
PM: No, because most of Victoria, the native title has been extinguished by<br />
freehold title over the last..<br />
PL: Being such a closely settled State.<br />
PM: Yes, over the last one hundred and fifty years, there Is very little<br />
unallenated crown land, other than state forest and national parks which<br />
Is not true of Western Australia, It is not true of Queensland, so in a<br />
sense his response was sort of a beggar my neighbor response, It<br />
wasn't going to cost him anything like as much to choose this path as It<br />
would have cost Queensland or Western Australia.<br />
PL: Can he legally do this? </p>
<p>TEL: 10. Jun. 93 16: 15 No. 018 P. 04/ 08<br />
4<br />
PM: He has been advised so though Commonwealth legal advisers would<br />
doubt this Is so and we have expressed those doubts In the document<br />
we published a week or so ago which says that legislation In the<br />
Commonwealth Parliament Is the only certain way of validating leases.<br />
Now, It may well be that the States can validate leases, If they can,<br />
good. They issued the leases, they Issued these grants of Interest in<br />
land, not just leases, but grants of Interest In land over the last eighteen<br />
year. They have been the land managers so If they can validate their<br />
own leases and pay the compensation well, that Is not a problem for me.<br />
I say good, If they can do that good.<br />
PL: How did you react to Premier Kenriett's sudden flourish?<br />
PM: I thought it was disruptive of the spirit of the discussion and again this ad<br />
hoc apprcdabt to things, it Is not the way a matter like this, a national<br />
matter should be dealt with. It ever there Is a decision handed down by<br />
our most supreme court, our High Court about the indigenous people of<br />
this country that requires a national response.<br />
PL: And you were prepared then though to make some compromises this<br />
morning weren't you?<br />
PM: I proposed again a change to our document to Indicate that It would be<br />
possible to agree to a package provided that the States understood that<br />
the High Court has made an historic decision, the decision being that a<br />
native title existed in common law, that It was not extinguished by the<br />
acquisition of sovereignty In 1788, that survived sovereignty in 1788 and<br />
that we had to establish the mechanism for tribunals to hear and<br />
dispense native title. Premiers Court and Kennett would have no bar of<br />
that and other Premiers who might have accepted that and some would<br />
have found there was no point In them accepting it.<br />
PU Premier Kennett says an agreement was possible here, but Paul Keating<br />
wanted to do too much, to go too far, you wanted to solve the entire<br />
Aboriginal question once and for all by linking everything on to the Mabo<br />
Issue.<br />
PM: I don't doubt for a moment that Premier Kennett sees attractions in that<br />
glib line, but that Is not true. He and Premier Court wouldn't embrace<br />
even the primary remedial policy changes to give effect to the core of<br />
the Mabo decision, not the add ons or the embroidery or anything on the<br />
edge of it, the core Issue.<br />
PL: We now have Victoria, New South Wales and I gather Queensiand at<br />
least planning their own legislation now to validate those leases between<br />
1975 and now. You can understand they have got to give certainty to<br />
business don't they? </p>
<p>TEL: .2Jun. 93 16: 15 No. 018 P. 05/ 08<br />
PM: Absolutely and it they can by the passage of legislation through their<br />
houses ot Pariamnent do that and pick up the compensation.<br />
PL That you would have otherwise been prepared to..<br />
PM: No, but you have got to understand that the cost of compensation to<br />
VIctoria will be minuscule compared to the cost of compensation to<br />
Western Australia or Queensland.<br />
PL So, we have been here now for the best part of two days, you have<br />
worked right through into the night, we have got effectively what<br />
nowhere?<br />
PM: Let me say this. We have as a Commonwealth government as a<br />
mlnstet-Fommittee of the Commonwealth been at work now for a<br />
couple Of months on this. We produced a highly Informative document<br />
which the States have had a copy of now for over a week, we refined<br />
that to 33 key proposals and then refined It down further to what we call<br />
the core issues yesterday and today. The States have had their own<br />
legal advice. The Council of Australian Governments Is an executive<br />
body, when a Premier comes to this body they are there to make<br />
decisions, not to have studies or to go back and consult but to make<br />
decisions.<br />
PU* They have Prime Minister, they have said no.<br />
PM: They have made a decision, they wouldn't make decisions to embrace<br />
the core proposals to deal with the High Court decision.<br />
PL: OK, so we have this executive body meeting, the big white chiefs of<br />
Australia in a pow wow, what message does this now send to Aboriginal<br />
Australians?<br />
PM: I think Premiers Court and Kennett have to got to explain to the<br />
Aboriginal community why native title as a concept so rankies of them,<br />
why they are not prepared to hear native title claims and have them<br />
dispensed and I think they have got to explain to the business<br />
community why they have refused a generous Commonwealth offer to<br />
validate the titles and pay the compensation.<br />
PL: And what message does it send to investors If you were sitting In Tokyo<br />
right now wondering whether to put $ 100 million Into a mine In Australia?<br />
PM: That Is a different issue. They can Issue from now on valid grants of<br />
Interest In land providing they follow two key points of procedural<br />
fairness and compensation, they can Issue from here on valid Interests<br />
of grants of land. But each interest in the land extinguishes the native<br />
TEL: </p>
<p>ILL 1O. Jun. 93 16: 15 No. 018 P. 06/ 08<br />
6<br />
title unless we provide for a revival of the title when the economic<br />
purpose Is finished.<br />
PL So I want to develop a midne. NOe then got to advertise, the State<br />
government has got to advertise the potential native title of it?<br />
PM: Yes, it has got to avertise. If there Is an area of land that the State<br />
wishes to develop It has to advise potential native title holders or the<br />
Aboriginal people of the region or maybe Land Councils that it seeks to<br />
exercise an Instrument over a grant or a grant of Interest In particular<br />
land.<br />
PLU How long will this hold me up for? How long does this hold up the<br />
proce-s?<br />
PM: I don't think It Is effectively a holdling up process at all because even if it<br />
takes a number of years for a native title claim to be heard and<br />
dispensed it doesn't stop the valid Issue of the lease or the Interest,<br />
PU: But I don't know as a business person what compensation I am up for<br />
down the track do I?<br />
PMIV: In the legislation that I was proposing at this meeting we would have<br />
guidelines for the compensation so a business would have an Idea of<br />
what the cost would be further down the track. The key point Is Paul<br />
that the States can now Issue a valid lease, a valid grant of interest in<br />
land.<br />
PRL: Have you perhaps pumped up average expectations too high. I mean<br />
there will be a lot of disappointment out there?<br />
PM: It Is not only me pumping it up. You have got to understand this. This Is<br />
something I have said to thorn on a number of occasions and I'll say to<br />
you that this decision was not a decision of the Commonwealth<br />
government, it was a decision of the High Court of Australia....<br />
PL: But you're linking It with reconciliation.<br />
PM: In a matter between Merlam people and the State of Queensland. The<br />
High Court held In favour of the Menamr people, and in doing so created<br />
a historic decision, it is that we are responding to. So, it Is not a matter<br />
of the Commonwealth government-building up expectations, It Is simply<br />
a matter of law which has to be dealt with.<br />
PL: And how will you go forth from here?<br />
PM: We will I think, as a result of the day, we'll consider our position and see<br />
where we think how best we should respond.<br />
I LL 10. JUh. 93 16' 15 .01 P 06/ 08 </p>
<p>U. 16: 5 No. 018 P. 07/ 08<br />
7<br />
PL There's talk of drafting legislation.<br />
PM: Well we'd be drafting legislation anyway, because we haven't had a<br />
frame work legislation within which these State tribunals could operate.<br />
So, we will go ahead and do that anyway. but again we will be<br />
considering our position. But can I also say that the meeting, the<br />
Council of Australian Governments, considered many other matters,<br />
reform in water, electricity, gas, micro-economic reform and other<br />
mnatters between us, and tha was quite a successful feature of the<br />
meeting. But the most Important one could niot be agreed upon. While it<br />
is the resolution of the Impact of the High Court decision In respect of<br />
native title.<br />
PL: You said s~ eral times that you thought that the Mabo decision was a<br />
great opportunity for Australa, are you still of that view?<br />
PM: Yes, because it Ist he classic evener up, It Isth e thing that gives to<br />
Aboriginal Australians an Interest In land which-has been theirs under<br />
the common law since settlement. It has a wholly different character to<br />
statutory land rights, land given by statute from a Parliament to an<br />
Aboriginal community. It has more Inherent dignity In the sense that it is<br />
available to a native type of hold, and as such It means that this<br />
possession which came with the settlement and the concept of terra<br />
nuilius, the land of no one, has been over turned by the High Court and<br />
Australians community can go forward together on the basis of the<br />
quality of access and availability to land.<br />
PLU Finally, comments by people like Tim Fischer, that this is the guilt<br />
Industry, that this was done by vastly distant past generations, not our<br />
generation, we shouldn't bear the cross.<br />
PM: Well that's wrong, that's a prejudicial view, and it is a wrong view, it has<br />
nothing to do with guilt, it Is a matter of law. In Captain Cook's<br />
Instructions he was told that In establishing a settlement In Australia that<br />
he should proceed with the consent of the native people. So, even back<br />
then the consent of the native people was an Issue. Of course In New<br />
Zealand there was the treaty of Waitangi, whereupon the Maori and the<br />
Crown came to a decision about the development of that country and<br />
their particular rights. This didn't happen In Australia, we had this<br />
concept of the land of no one which the High Court now overturned.<br />
PL: And you will be back with the Premiers again in the next couple of<br />
months, will you, to keep trying?<br />
PM: Well we have got a Premiers Conference, a fi-nancial Premiers<br />
conference meeting In July but at each meeting we are not prevented<br />
rm discussing any matter financial or otherwise. But they have got to </p>
<p>I~ iv 1U. jufn 5 10; 1D ra. Vio r. voivo<br />
show a willingness to accept the decision of the most supreme of our<br />
Courts, the High Court.<br />
PL Prime Minister, thak for your time.<br />
PM: Thank you.<br />
ENDS </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
