<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>16875</transcript-id>
    <title>Largest Australian free trade agreement to begin in 2010 Prime Minister Minister for Trade Media release 25 October 2009</title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/10/2009</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The largest Free Trade Agreement Australia has ever concluded will come into force on 1 January 2010, following discussion between ASEAN leaders today. </p>
<p>The Agreement establishing the ASEAN-Australia-New Zealand Free Trade Area (AANZFTA) spans 12 economies, with over 600 million people and a combined GDP of $3.1 trillion. </p>
<p>The Agreement will cover a massive 20% of Australia's two-way trade, worth $112 billion. </p>
<p>The deal will eliminate tariffs on 96 per cent of our current exports to ASEAN nations by 2020. </p>
<p>Currently, only 67 per cent of our exports to the region are tariff-free. </p>
<p>This will support Australian industry by promoting exports, and will play an important role in supporting Australian jobs. </p>
<p>This will be the most comprehensive Free Trade Agreement to enter into force for ASEAN, covering a range of areas including:</p>
<p>     * Goods</p>
<p>     * Services</p>
<p>     * Investment</p>
<p>     * Intellectual property</p>
<p>     * e-commerce</p>
<p>The nations covered by the AANZFTA are the 10 ASEAN Member States: Brunei Darussalam, Cambodia, Indonesia, Lao People's Democratic Republic, Malaysia, Burma, the Philippines, Singapore, Thailand, Viet Nam; and Australia and New Zealand. </p>
<p>When the global financial crisis began at the end of last year, one of the greatest threats to economic recovery was the potential for an outbreak of national protectionism. </p>
<p>The initial signing of the AANZFTA in February was an important sign of the determination of nations to work together to build economic recovery, and today's announcement cements that cooperation. </p>
<p>The entry into force of AANZFTA is also another important step towards greater cooperation and economic integration in the region.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
