<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9428</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP AAP CONFERENCE OF ASIAN, AUSTRALIAN AND PACIFIC MEDIA EXECUTIVES,REGENT HOTEL, SYDNEY - TUESDAY, 22 NOVEMBER 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/11/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009428.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
to reinvest<br />
and drug<br />
m" Feu nAdc. t and<br />
Fund. In<br />
ojects. In<br />
3672.000 ially sold<br />
1d but be<br />
icular use<br />
' Cigation the<br />
establish in the<br />
' ation md ) StS.<br />
he use to<br />
ttecting<br />
iSSETS PRIME MINISTER<br />
ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
AAP CONFERENCE OF ASIAN, AUSTRALIAN AND PACIFIC MEDIA<br />
EXECUTIVES, REGENT HOTEL, SYDNEY TUESDAY, 22 NOVEMBER 1994<br />
* CHECK AGAINST DEUVERY'<br />
I am very grateful for the Invitation to speak to such a distinguished audience as<br />
we have here today and I welcome all of you from overseas to Australia and to<br />
Sydney. It is somehow gratifying that within a week of the Bogor Declaration we have a<br />
conference of media executives drawn from the Asia-Pacific.<br />
Less than a decade ago, the Asia-Pacific was just a concept.<br />
Increasingly today It is a defining reality.<br />
With APEC all the more so, of course.<br />
Mind you, had they read some of the Australian media at the weekend, the<br />
uninitiated could be forgiven for thinking that the Asia-Pacific and APEC were still<br />
unproven concepts, or realities of no great consequence.<br />
Those of us with long experience know that this was the obligatory spray of<br />
scepticism to prevent ary hubris sprouting.<br />
The Australian media are conscientious in keeping us In our places and reminding<br />
us that good works are never an excuse to draw more than a breath of<br />
satisfaction. But in fact. like everyone else, they know that change j1 upon us.<br />
No one I suspect knows it better than the Australian media. 3,137 </p>
<p>And if it is a political leaders prime responsibility to anticipate and manage<br />
change, and confront the necessities change brings then I amr sure they aiso<br />
know that the political leaders al Bogor did this as It has rarely been done before.<br />
That was where the sense of euphoria came from: from doing something with<br />
some genuine vision about it.<br />
Not a mandatory genuflection or theatrical squint into the future, but an act which<br />
might actually mark this generation as one with sufficient wisdom, care arnd<br />
foresight to lay the basis of a better world for millions of people In the fUtue.<br />
And sufficient resolve.<br />
That it should have happened and that it should have been so rapidly taken for<br />
granted perhaps testifies to the transforming times in which we live.<br />
It seamns to me that these are times when the most pessimistic among us find ft<br />
difficult to escape the possibilities on offer.<br />
We might even call it an age of possibility.<br />
So much changed with the end of the Cold War.<br />
We watched, millions of us around the world, as its most powerful symbol the<br />
Berlin Wall was broken down.<br />
We all knew that we watching a long chapter in the history of the modern world<br />
come to an end.<br />
How we read its fail depended, I suppose, on our natural disposition.<br />
Pessimists will tend to see only t problems which flow from the collapse of an<br />
old order.<br />
Optimists will fail to see them.<br />
The near-sighted and the nostalgic will see a symbol of a century at it end;<br />
romantics and visionaries will see the start of a new one.<br />
My vote is with the pragmatists.<br />
Pragmnatists will see the possibilities.<br />
And seize them.<br />
3 43 8 </p>
<p>It is a great era for those with an eye for possibilities in trade and investment the<br />
envionment cultural development, information technology.<br />
Namie your Interest.<br />
We all know an era has ended.<br />
We all speak of a new " Post Cold War world".<br />
And In Bogor we took a practical step towards defining it.<br />
It Is a cliche to say that much remains to be done, and many hurdles will have to<br />
be jumped but it is just as true to say that an extraordinary amount w-as done<br />
and an extraordinary number of hurdles were jumped.<br />
We cid niot define the next century, but we gave ourselves a chance to shape it as<br />
it should be shaped, which Is to say in all our interests.<br />
In fact a clue to the shape of the new post Cold War world lay hidden In the drama<br />
of events leading up to the end of the Berlin Wail.<br />
While we watched the collapse of the Soviet Union on television and perhaps<br />
secretly wished that CNN had been there in 1917, teenage students in California<br />
were communicating by another means with teenage students in Moscow and St<br />
Petersburg.<br />
As tho Soviet Union disintegrated. and the legacy of older generations fell apart<br />
before our eyes on television, a new generation was talking to Americans on<br />
Internet unfiltered and unedited.<br />
It gives us a glimpse of what awaits us in the 21 st Century.<br />
And I think it gives us a hint of why we are more Inclined to think In terms of the<br />
possible why agreements like the APEC agreement can be credibly pursued.<br />
The barriers of distance and communication awe down and, In the end, It is not<br />
easy to say why others should not follow.<br />
We only need the courage to ask the question.<br />
In APEC we did ask t.<br />
And suddenly we are talking as a region in many forums, like this one. thinkm<br />
as a region. ' 143: .9 </p>
<p>That was the source of the little puff of euphoria.<br />
Thol feeling that what we had just done could be done again.<br />
We can break down language and cultural bamers and Increase the<br />
understanding and respect between us.<br />
And we can break down the barriers to trade and Investment<br />
We can prevent bottlenecks before they develop.<br />
We can find creative ways to deal with issues before they become problems.<br />
Global communications. for instance.<br />
it is difficult to overestimate the impact that global communications wiil have on the<br />
daily lives of all of us.<br />
And, for that matter, on the daily operations of the media.<br />
Interactive multimedia. In particular, now has the potential to become a new force<br />
In education, art, culture and the media.<br />
That Is why In the Australian Government's cultural policy, Creattve Nation, we<br />
took a number of major Initiatives to generate a vibrant multimedia Industry as part<br />
of our push into the information age.<br />
These specific Initiatives seek to build on our creative abilities: a substantial and<br />
innovative film and television Industry; our software skills and our entrepreneurial<br />
traditions. They also seek to utilise what is one of the more advanced telecommunications<br />
networks In the world as a platform upon which the multimedia Industry can be<br />
Most of you here will be aware that our two major telecommunications players,<br />
Teistra. and Optus. have plans to Install broadband cable to millions of Australian<br />
homes before the turn of the century.<br />
The plans involve some of Australias biggest and best known media corporations<br />
which should come as no surprise given the convergence taking place across<br />
media, information and telecommunications industries. </p>
<p>These developments have profound implications for media organisations right<br />
around the world and I am sure that all of you here are already grappling with the<br />
challenges they pose.<br />
I think It is worth making the observation that in all this, there is the real possibility<br />
that those large media organisations. which have traditionally relied on the<br />
broadcast nature of their medium, are going to come under Increasing pressure as<br />
the ' iemocraisatlon of our information-gathering via networks like the Internet<br />
takes effect.<br />
That Is not to say that the major media organisations won't remain global players.<br />
They will because some people will prefer to have their information handed to<br />
themn In an easily digestible form.<br />
In fact, there will be so much Information available that it may well be those who<br />
can h~ est package and tailor it to specific needs who will gain a large share of the<br />
globil information gain.<br />
But for those who actively search for Information arnd news. the means of<br />
communication available will enable them to sidesiep the hierarchical nature of<br />
broacast newis and entertainment.<br />
Via th~ eir PC they will be able to pick and choose publications and author at will.<br />
This wIll also lead to an explosion of communities of interest groups of people<br />
interested In a particular topic macroeconomics or microbiology. Chinese<br />
medicine or the music of Chile will have access to all relevant Infbrmation on the<br />
subject world wide and the ability to communicate with others expeut and<br />
Interes-ted worldwide.<br />
Recipients of information will have far greater choice In the information that they<br />
choose to receive, and this will have considerable effects on media orgariLsatlons<br />
whch are not used to the nature and level of their competition.<br />
As the technology becomes more sophisticated, anyone with a small camera and<br />
notebook computer will be able to show the whole world events taking place<br />
virtually anywhere on the globe.<br />
And, even if they clon't have a camera, they will still be able to descrbe events<br />
taking place as they occur.<br />
Broadcast will continue to exist, but it will be broadcast from the bottom up ralther<br />
than th, 3 top down. 3 4 ' 1 </p>
<p>6<br />
And anyone who wants to will be a journalist,<br />
As the technology becomes more Sophisticated more parts of the globe will open<br />
up.<br />
This will, of course. have profound effects on the extent to which individual<br />
governments can regulate the flow of Information both within and Into their nations.<br />
In some cases, It may well be near impossible.<br />
Governments can take steps to restrict the flow of Information and ideas: but they<br />
do so at the nisk of limiting access to the very communication technologies that, in<br />
the information era of the next century, will be so critical to national economic<br />
development. This Ison e of the key challenges facing governments inthe region, particularly<br />
if those~ governments which are less open than others.<br />
And in one sense, this is why last week's Bogor Declaration of APEC leaders was<br />
so profound.<br />
It committed the developed APEC countries to achieving free trade by the year<br />
2010 and the developing APEC countries by the year 2020.<br />
It was a recognition that In the coming century. economic advancement will be<br />
inextricably lInked to the openness of national economies.<br />
Those who embrace the world economy and the information revolution now driving<br />
it will prosper.<br />
Those who don't will pay a heavy price.<br />
I don't for one moment want to underestimate te task of translating the political<br />
commitment of Bogor into an economic reality.<br />
I don't underestimate the challenges we face.<br />
But Bcgor means we will face them.<br />
It means we " a faced the future.<br />
I The commitment we made Is an enormous step forward.<br />
For instance, it can hardly have escaped anyone's notice that the Bogor<br />
I Declaration involved both developing and developed counties.<br />
34 42 </p>
<p>It wasn't a case of developed countries trying to drag developing countries along to<br />
a taible they didn't want to sit at.<br />
To the contrary, the Bogor Declaration was very much the initiative of the<br />
President of one of the worids most Important developing countries.<br />
It is a great tribute to President Soeharto's leadership and standing in the region.<br />
it is also a measure of his vision and grasp of the possibilities on offer In the next<br />
century. The fact that Australia was able to play such an Important role in the whole AP EC<br />
process, by launching the initiative in 1989 and then by turning it Into a Heads of<br />
Government and leaders' meeting embracing a free trade agenda, shows just how<br />
much Australia has changed In recent years.<br />
While I am sure that many people In the region have a reasonable appreciation of<br />
the nature of contemporary Australia. there is no doubt that the vast majority are<br />
not so well informed.<br />
That Is something we want to rectify.<br />
I know, for example, tht it is still widely believed that the White Australia policy<br />
still operates.<br />
It was abolished more than twenty years ago.<br />
Australia is, after all, a country where one In five of our population was born<br />
overseas. And Hyt ou add to that number all the children of overseas-born parents you have<br />
44per cent or almost half, of our total population.<br />
While Australia Is neither a monocultural nor a monolithic society. and while<br />
Australian communities ame separated by vast disances; and vastly different<br />
regional and cultural affections, profound ties of fellow feeling unite us.<br />
These days we ae Increasingly united by the pride and the pleasure we take In<br />
the difference itself In multicultural Australia.<br />
Our respect and enthusiasm for cultural diversity has become a defining element<br />
of Australia's; national sentiment. 3 ' 14 3 </p>
<p>It was some indication of this fact when a recent poll revealed that a clear majority<br />
of Australians viewed the recent wave of Asian immigration as of significant benefit<br />
to Ajstralla.<br />
Whatever way you look at it, the contrast between the Australia of today and the<br />
Australia of thirty years or even twenty years ago could not be more marked.<br />
The economic changes have been as profound as the cultural ones.<br />
A decade of reform has given us one of the most open economies In the world.<br />
Some time ago now, we floated the dollar, deregulated our financial markets,<br />
knocked down the tariff wall and pushed ahead with a widespread program of<br />
industry and mlcroeconomic reform.<br />
That reform process has delivered substantial benefits.<br />
We are now growing at 4 to 5 per cent. The Economist believes that next year we<br />
will continua to grow faster than the other major industria. 1ised economies in the<br />
world. We also have increasing business Investment, a big rise in employment, an<br />
underlying inflation rate of two per cent and continued growth In exports.<br />
In fact, 60 per cent of all Australian exports are to t Asian region a share that<br />
has doubled In less than thirty years.<br />
Exports to the ASEAN countries, for example, are at least equal to those going to<br />
either the United States or Europe.<br />
Trhis major shift of national focus to t region has also seen the reach of the<br />
Australian media extend further Into the Asian region.<br />
Radio Australia, which has been bro dating to the region for many years, now<br />
has an estimated sixty mrillion listeners worldwide.<br />
More recently, we have seen the establishment of Australia Television<br />
International which now broadcasts to millions throughout the region.<br />
Its charter Is to build on Radio Austr-alias reputation as an authoritative,<br />
independent and Impartial provider of international news and information, and of<br />
high quality entertainment which Is sensible to the cultural mores of a highly<br />
diverse audience.<br />
3,' 144 </p>
<p>9<br />
Accompanying this whole push into Asia has been a large increase in the numbers<br />
of Australan journalists based In th~ e region.<br />
On% 3 problem with the coverage of Asia and the Pacific in the Australian media is<br />
that, In my view, there Is not enough of it<br />
But things are improving as the foreign pages of most of our newspapers show.<br />
All of us get deluged with Information about the US or Britain, but if greater<br />
regional coverage generates only a regional equivalent of an 0 J Simpson or<br />
House of Windsor media soap opera, we're better off without ft.<br />
But what we really need is better coverage: and that depends on first, ensuring we<br />
have a flow of information fro a wide variety of sources and second, that those<br />
sources are well-informed.<br />
This works both ways.<br />
Coverage of Australia in the Asian media also tends to be limited and to fall too<br />
easily Into caricatures of Australians preferring the beach to work.<br />
In this ignorance stakes, things are pretty well matched.<br />
Not surprisingly, the reportage of Australian journalists has sometimes created<br />
difficulties in our relations with some regional countries, particularly those where<br />
the views and policies of the Australian media are seen by some as<br />
interchangeable with the views and policies of the Australian Government<br />
Media freedom Is a fundamental and unalterable tenet of Australian democracy<br />
and Australian life.<br />
Here in Australia, from time to time, those on both sides of politics may wish it<br />
were a more positive and altoether less irksome and contrary beast, but these<br />
sensibilities only exist at the margins.<br />
At the centre, Australians hold the right to be objectively and critically informed<br />
about current political developments as inalienable.<br />
We do think, however, that when our media go to the region to the extent that<br />
thy are ' our media they should be responsible and sensitive to the specific<br />
circumstances of different nations.<br />
Objectivity and knowledge about a regional audience which constitutes a mosaic<br />
of different ethnic and linguistic groups Is essential if the Australian media are to<br />
gain widespread respect I44.14 </p>
<p>However, as we seek to understand our Asian neighbours we are equally Justified<br />
In expecting that they should do the same of us that the tolerance and<br />
understanding should be applied equally to Australia anid its media.<br />
At the same time, it Is important not to overtook the positive role that our media<br />
can play in building a sense of community among regional countries.<br />
With the advent of multimedia as a means by whch culture can be delivered, there<br />
Is a real risk that local culture will be swamped by Imported products.<br />
That Is even more likely to be the case where the Imported culture is of a higher<br />
technical quality: In education and information programTs, for Instance, our children<br />
are more likely to learn through a medium which Is more intuitive, and more fun to<br />
operate.<br />
That places a great responsibility on us to provide programs which take account of<br />
cultural diversity and sensibility.<br />
That was one very Important reason why we launched the multimedia initiatives<br />
we did to build within Australia a multmedia industry which will ensure thal we*<br />
continue to sustain and originate our own culture.<br />
Given Australia's strong links to many of the Asian countries In the region,<br />
Including the great link of migration, I think there is significant scope for Australia<br />
to develop content for the region, content which Is sensitive to local cultures and<br />
promotes them.<br />
While we should seek to use the new communications technologies as a vehicle to<br />
develop greater understanding and a greater regional Identity. we should also<br />
encourage the maintenance of distinctive and diverse cultural values.<br />
Australia Is perhaps better placed than most to do ifuls.<br />
In this. as in so much else, technological change will have greater Impact than<br />
government flat.<br />
In the end ' cultural sensitMWi if we mean by that a thoroujgh understanding of<br />
the cultural and political background within which events are taking place can<br />
only come from the media themselves from journalists, editors and managers<br />
who know what they are talking about and appreciate the complexity of the region.<br />
3,146 </p>
<p>Most Importantly, It will come from informed consumers whose knowledge of jhq<br />
countries they are reading about or heaing about Is deeper than what they pick up<br />
from a five paragraph news story about riots or political change or economic<br />
growth. That is why Austrailla has been putting such emphasis on Asia In our education<br />
system.<br />
We are developing a national Asian Languages Strategy designed to Increase the<br />
number of Asian language teachers and to develop teacher training courses as<br />
well as national student proficiency levels in languages such as Mandarn.<br />
Indonesian, Japanese and Korean.<br />
We are very conscious that we must continue to Increase our understanding of the<br />
countries In the region that we will become a more effective player and a more<br />
effective partner as we do so.<br />
Obviously, the Bogor Declaration has commnitted us all to this.<br />
It committed us all to a greater level of regional consciousness.<br />
It therefore committed us Irrevocably to paths of change.<br />
In this we feel confident that we can say we are at least as well advanced as<br />
anyone even, maybe, that we are more advanced than most.<br />
It is now more than a decade since we saw the need for major structural reform In<br />
Austraiia. In tha* time we have learned a lot about change both about implementing it and<br />
about managing It<br />
We learned that it Is a tOring process, but it is also an exhilarating one.<br />
And because it Is so rich In possibilities for all our countries and all our people,<br />
surely none is more exhilarating than the process which so rapidly took us to the<br />
declaration In Indonesia last week.<br />
Perhaps the most important element at work in Bogor and Seattle was the one too<br />
obvious to earn much reporting.<br />
It was that all the countries of the region, in all their diversity, were talking to each<br />
other, In a common forum, with a common interest.<br />
The ac: of communication was the important one. 34 4 7 </p>
<p>r1 12<br />
Ultimately it is from this that all those vast post-Cold War possibilities derive.<br />
We need to keep the communication going.<br />
We need to keep it expanding and deepening.<br />
That Is why you, the region's media, have such a crucial and creative role to play<br />
and why I am so gratified to see you here in Sydney.<br />
Thank you.<br />
3448 . iX </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
