<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2443</transcript-id>
    <title>ECONOMIC CONSULTATIONS - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR WILLIAM MCMAHON</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/07/1971</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002443.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRE&amp; u. PM6 No. 72/ 1971<br />
t CCNOMIC CGNSULTATIONS<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, Mr. William McMahon<br />
Over the last three days, the Government has had extremely<br />
useful and wide-ranging discussions with the ACTU and organisations<br />
representative of major sectors of industry and commerce.<br />
These discussions were much greater in scope, and more<br />
time was allotted than previously to enable the organisations to put<br />
their views to the Gover:! ment on the trends in the economy generally<br />
and on aspects of particular concern to them.<br />
Ministers w-3re given up-to-date and first-hand information<br />
and assessments of the problems concerning the rural industries,<br />
particularly wool. The manufacturing, commerce and mining represent atives.<br />
provided an appreciation of the prospects and problems affecting their<br />
industries. The Ministers also had the benefit of advice from the<br />
Manufacturing Industries Advisory Council and the Export Development<br />
Council which have a special advisory association with the Government.<br />
In the course of these discussions, representatives put forward<br />
a number of proposals, some of which will require careful consideration.<br />
The Government appreciates the preparatory work undertaken<br />
by the organisations in presenting well-documented submissions. These<br />
greatly facilitated the full and fruitful discussions which have now just<br />
ended. The organisations represented at the consultations are shown<br />
on the attached list.<br />
CANBERRA 9 July 1971 </p>
<p>NATIONAL ORGANISATIONS REPRESENTED AT<br />
ECoToC9f07BgCT!^ 3GTT<br />
Primar IndustryGroup<br />
Australian Farmers' Federation<br />
Australian Woolgrowers' and Graziers'<br />
Council<br />
Australian Wool and Meat<br />
Producers' Federation<br />
Australian Wheatgrowers' Federation Vice-President Mr. J. P. Cass, 0. B. E.<br />
President Mr. B. A. Wright, O. B. E.<br />
President Mr.<br />
President Mr. R. V.<br />
L. V. Sewell, O. B. E.<br />
Price, O. B. E.<br />
Manufacturing Industry Group<br />
Associated Chambers of Manufactures<br />
of Australia<br />
Master Builders' Federation of<br />
Australia<br />
Federal Chamber of Automotive<br />
Industries<br />
Commerce and MiingGroup<br />
Associated Chambers of Commerce<br />
of Australia<br />
Australian Bankers Association<br />
The Australian Council of Retailers<br />
Australian Mining Industry Council President Mr. H. N. Herford, E. D.<br />
President Mr. R. S. Prentice<br />
Vice-President Mr. N. W. Lawrance<br />
President Mr.<br />
Chairman Mr.<br />
President Mr.<br />
President Mr. N. M. Blyton, O. B. E.<br />
G. F. Bowen<br />
E. L. Byrne<br />
J. B. Massey-Greene<br />
Manufacturing Industries Advisory Council<br />
Sir Ronald Irish, F. C. A.<br />
Sir James Vernon, C. B. E.<br />
Mr. T. M. Ramsay<br />
Mr. F. W. Wiltshire<br />
Export Development Council<br />
Chairman Mr. D. H. Freeman<br />
Deputy Chairmen Mr. R. V. Sewell, O. B. E.<br />
E. P. McClintock<br />
Executive Members Mr. H. McE. Scambler<br />
Mr. N. G. Wilson<br />
Member Mr. 0. G. Meyer, E. D.<br />
Australian Council of Trade Unions<br />
Junior Vice President The Honourable R. B.<br />
Secretary Mr. H. J. Souter. Marsh, M. L. C.<br />
Chairman Members </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
