<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>15961</transcript-id>
    <title>Joint doorstop Interview with  the Acting PM, The Hon Julia Gillard, MP and  the Minister for Housing, The Hon Tanya Plibersek, MP  </title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/06/2008</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>JULIA GILLARD: Today I'm here with the Minister for Housing, Tanya Plibersek, to launch a technical paper about our Housing Affordability Fund. It's a paper for quick consultation.</p>
<p>The Housing Affordability Fund is all about assisting Australians with more affordable housing. We know that it's the great Australian dream to own your own home, and we know for many working Australians that dream seems a very long way away.</p>
<p>And we also know from the statistics that in terms of the generation of new homes for Australians, we are going to be running behind demand. That is going to make the dream of owning your own home a more difficult dream to realise.</p>
<p>One of the things that we promised Australians before the last election is that the government would act on housing affordability; we would have our actions led by a dedicated Minister for Housing, and Tanya is doing that work for the government; and we would also create a Housing Affordability Fund - a $512 million fund, the purpose of which would be to try and take the pressure off.</p>
<p>What this fund is for is to assist with developments. What we want to do is we want to make sure that planning happens more quickly, so holding costs can be reduced. We also want to make sure that there is potential from some assistance with infrastructure.</p>
<p>If through the Housing Affordability Fund we can address these issues, that means that developments can happen more quickly, and in a more affordable way, for working Australians. This is a partnership that is going to involve local governments. It's a partnership that I'll get Tanya to more fully describe.</p>
<p>The paper that we're releasing today is for short consultation. This fund is going to be open for business from mid-July, with a first $50 million allocation to try and make a difference on housing affordability. I'll hand over to Tanya at this point.</p>
<p>TANYA PLIBERSEK: Thank you. We're here today talking about our Housing Affordability Fund technical paper. The Housing Affordability Fund is one of the measures that were funded in the last federal budget. It's a $512 million fund over five years.</p>
<p>The money is to reduce the cost of new homes for purchase, either by speeding up development processes so that we reduce holding costs on these new homes, or by paying for small amounts of linking infrastructure.</p>
<p>If there's a little project that's holding up a much larger development, local government, State Government will be able to apply to this fund for a little bit of money to help with that.</p>
<p>The money will be distributed on a competitive basis, and this technical paper lays out exactly what it is that we're expecting of people; exactly what it is that we require of local governments, local government associations; State Governments, and others who will be applying for this funding.</p>
<p>It sets out how we will expect them to make their application, and how we'll expect them to respond to the government and report to the government on savings that have been passed on to home buyers at the end of the day. The critical thing to remember here is that we will determine applications on the basis of value for money, savings for new home buyers.</p>
<p>This technical paper, as I say, lays out how bodies will be able to; the information they need to make a successful application to the fund.</p>
<p>It tells how we will measure success. It asks a few questions of local governments and State Governments for their feedback. But it is very clear that at the end of the day what we're looking for is a reduced cost for new homes to purchase.</p>
<p>We have Chris Lamont with us today from the Housing Industry Association, and Chris is going to make a few comments from the housing industry's perspective.</p>
<p>CHRIS LAMONT: Thank you Minister. The HIA is delighted to support the Housing Affordability Fund. </p>
<p>This is a targeted and appropriate measure. As the Minister and the Acting Prime Minister stated, this is about reducing those costs that relate to holding costs; that red tape which is delaying construction, to make a practical difference to reduce the price, or the sticker price as HIA refers, of a new home.</p>
<p>This is a measure that is not without strings. It is an outcome-based policy, an outcome-based fund that designs to reduce the cost of a new home.</p>
<p>Housing affordability is now at a record low. The situation won't get any better unless we have funds like this, and measures such as these, to improve the situation. HIA is delighted to see that the Federal Government's re-entered the housing affordability space. This is the first measure of this kind for 11 and a half years.</p>
<p>Our urban centres have been the victims of an under-investment by the Federal Government, and previous Federal Governments, and this measure is specifically targeted to improve housing affordability on the ground to those that matter.</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
<p>JULIA GILLARD: Thank you. </p>
<p>Can I ask people at this stage if they've got questions on housing affordability and the Housing Affordability Fund to ask them now; and then I'll take the opportunity to make a statement about two other matters, and we'll move to general questioning, but, with Chris and Tanya, if people have questions about housing affordability then obviously we're all standing by ready to take them.</p>
<p>No - housing affordability questions? Okay. Alright. Well if I can move on to dealing with two other matters.</p>
<p>Firstly I'd like to make some comments about the matter involving the disruption of gas supplies in Western Australia.</p>
<p>People may be aware that there is a major disruption to gas supplies in Western Australia. As a result of an explosion, 30 per cent of gas supplies are no longer available.</p>
<p>That's got implications obviously for people who live in the west for household use. It's winter, and people want to be able to have ready access to gas.</p>
<p>It's also got an implication for businesses and for the people who work within them. Obviously many businesses are dependent on gas, either directly or through its energy generation capacity; and for those businesses they are now facing a tough time, which has implications for the people employed in them and whether or not there will be stand-downs.</p>
<p>This is obviously a major matter affecting Western Australia, and the West Australian economy.</p>
<p>It is not a matter that is going to be remedied overnight, in terms of the return of full supplies. This is a major disruption, and will take time to fix.</p>
<p>I yesterday spoke in my capacity as Acting Prime Minister to the Premier of Western Australia, Alan Carpenter, and we will continue to be talking to the Premier on ways in which the Federal Government can assist Western Australia to deal with this major disruption.</p>
<p>Alan Carpenter of course has taken a series of actions locally in Western Australia to try and ameliorate this problem, but it is a significant problem that is going to have ongoing economic and social consequences.</p>
<p>We are going to be working with the Western Australian Government on addressing those consequences. And I will be having further discussions with the Western Australian Premier on the matter.</p>
<p>On a further matter; the matter involving the Federal Member for Robertson, Ms Belinda Neal, can I say in relation to that, obviously this matter has achieved a great deal of media attention in recent days. I indicated yesterday, when asked by the media, that I was not happy with the situation that emerged over the weekend, and the matters associated with Ms Neal's visit to a restaurant in her local area.</p>
<p>This morning of course there are further revelations in the newspapers. I am also concerned about those revelations.</p>
<p>With both matters now having come to my attention, and particularly the new matter this morning contained in newspaper reports, I am concerned that this is indicative of a pattern of behaviour which obviously is not acceptable.</p>
<p>I have spoken this morning to the Prime Minister, who is as we all know, in Japan. The Prime Minister and I have discussed the matter. We will be making some further statements during the course of the day in relation to the matter.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister is very fully committed in Japan. He is, as we speak now, meeting with the Japanese Emperor, but we have discussed the matter, and a further statement about it will be available later on during the course of today.</p>
<p>QUESTION: Does that mean you're going to ask the Member to stand down?</p>
<p>JULIA GILLARD: That means we'll be making a further statement during the course of the day.</p>
<p>QUESTION: Does that mean that's one possibility, that you'll be discussing?</p>
<p>JULIA GILLARD: That means we'll be making a further statement during the course of the day.</p>
<p>QUESTION: Does it sound as though a position has become untenable?</p>
<p>JULIA GILLARD: The factors here are as follows; obviously I was concerned about the original matter, a second matter has come to public attention today. I believe that this is indicative of a pattern of behaviour. I've discussed the matter with the Prime Minister and we will be making a further statement later today.</p>
<p>QUESTION: What's the hold-up? Why a further statement later today, what are you waiting for?</p>
<p>JULIA GILLARD: The Prime Minister is in Japan. He has a fully committed program. He is currently meeting with the Japanese Emperor. Obviously our bi-lateral relationship with Japan is of critical importance to this country. The Prime Minister's focus is therefore on acquitting the program in Japan and meeting with the Japanese Emperor. Obviously we will be dealing with this matter during the course of the day.</p>
<p>QUESTION: The Dalai Lama's in Sydney today and I understand Chris Evans is meeting with him. Will you be meeting with the Dalai Lama and if not is that because you're trying to avoid him?</p>
<p>JULIA GILLARD: The Acting Prime Minister will meet with the Dalai Lama later this week. Chris Evans will be Acting Prime Minister later this week. That is because the Prime Minister will be in Japan. I will be in New Zealand, leading a high-level ministerial delegation to a forum with our New Zealand counterparts. Obviously there is no closer bilateral relationship, I suspect, on the planet, than the relationship between Australia and New Zealand. That is a forum that I will be attending with a number of my ministerial colleagues and which the government has made a commitment to attending. Chris Evans will be here as Acting Prime Minister and he will meet the Dalai Lama on behalf of the Australian Government.</p>
<p>QUESTION: Is Chris Evans up to the job of Acting Prime Minister, he's never done that before, has he?</p>
<p>JULIA GILLARD: Of course he is and he will be Acting Prime Minister for a period of about, I think, it's 26, 27 hours while I am in New Zealand.</p>
<p>QUESTION: There's reports today that Toyota was already going to be making its environmentally friendly car, I just wanted to know whether you think that's true and if it is, if it's a fair use of taxpayer's money to prop Toyota up?</p>
<p>JULIA GILLARD: Can I say, you're raising a matter very dear to my heart and about which I can speak at length. I live in Altona, I live within walking distance of the Toyota factory . Car manufacturing is important to this nation, it's important to jobs in this nation, it's important to innovation in this nation and making sure we've got an Australian made hybrid car is important to Australian consumers.</p>
<p>About a million cars will be bought by Australians this year, but only 5000 of them will be hybrids. Now that's not because Australians don't want to have cleaner, greener, vehicles, people do. But they want to see an Australian made cleaner, greener, vehicle.</p>
<p>The government believes that it was appropriate to work with Toyota through our green car fund to ensure that there would be an Australian made hybrid and to ensure that it was available for Australian consumers as quickly as possible. I am delighted by yesterday's announcement. I am delighted that Australians will be able to make the choice to buy an Australian made hybrid vehicle. And I'll be more than happy, should anybody want to come to Victoria and tour through Toyota with me, to show it to you.</p>
<p>QUESTION: Just on ABC Learning, as well, I understand that they've increased their fees 10 per cent, do you think they're taking advantage of the childcare rebate?</p>
<p>JULIA GILLARD: There are press reports today about the intention of ABC Learning in relation to its fees. Those reports aren't directly confirmed by ABC Learning. On the question of childcare fees, I have made it absolutely clear that the government will be assessing whether there is any evidence of unfair pricing practices. The government is determined to lessen the pressure on working families by childcare fees. That's why we've increased the childcare tax rebate from 30 per cent to 50 per cent. It's all about taking the pressure off and getting extra assistance into the purses and wallets of working Australians who need childcare and need it to go to work.</p>
<p>What we're also doing, and this is very important for our childcare industry and the shape of the childcare market, is that the government is committed to a number of supply-side measures. We've already got more than 1000 new childcare workers in training.</p>
<p>We have plans to increase the childcare workforce beyond that by making sure we pay the TAFE fees for people who want to study childcare and by having 1500 new early childhood educator places at Australian universities we're also committed to delivering 260 new childcare centres and I have certainly said that when selecting the providers in those centres, a track record of affordability in terms of the provision of care will be one thing that the Government will be looking to.</p>
<p>QUESTION: [Inaudible question]</p>
<p>JULIA GILLARD: Well, your question is premised on an assumption. So that's your assumption not mine. We'll deal with these matters in a statement later today. Obviously Ms Neal is a member of the Federal Parliamentary Labor Party caucus and consequently it is a matter that Kevin Rudd as Prime Minister and I as Deputy Prime Minister currently Acting Prime Minister we will deal with on behalf of Federal Labor.</p>
<p>QUESTION: On the issue of alcohol, The Public Health Association has called for an increase in excise for alcoholic drinks, not just alcopops is that something you'd consider?</p>
<p>JULIA GILLARD: The government was motivated here by a concern about binge drinking amongst Australian young people and I think that there is plenty of evidence that we should be concerned. Binge drinking, by young people is a health issue, it's something that would concern us in terms of creating a pattern of alcohol use and abuse that will stay with people for the rest of their lives. It's also an issue of profound concern in relation to street violence. I mean, no-one wants to see a young Australian go out for a night out, for a good time and come back injured and tragically.</p>
<p>We know there have been some young Australians who have died as a result of street violence associated with alcohol - ingesting alcohol and binge drinking. So in those circumstances the government was committed to doing what we thought would make a difference for binge drinking for young Australians. We therefore dealt with a tax measure in relation to alcopops. These alcopops were taxed less than drinks that are mixed themselves that people mix themselves, we obviously wanted to make sure that the tax treatment was equal, and we've done so.</p>
<p>Now I suspect there will be people who bring a variety of perspectives to this debate and we'll see that variety of perspectives on display. We've seen it already, we'll see it again in the next few weeks but the government believes this is a measure that could make a difference in relation to binge drinking we are motivated to do that, we want to do that, we want to make sure that we do something on binge drinking and something to protect young Australians.</p>
<p>QUESTION: Just quickly, on an idea that was voted on the 2020 summit about sending Australians to -overseas to study Asian languages, in particular, has there been any progress on that idea?</p>
<p>JULIA GILLARD: On Asian languages, certainly there was the idea at the 2020 Summit and like all ideas from the 2020 Summit we will be responding to those ideas by the end of the year as we have committed. We went to the last election, promising a new investment into the provision of Asian languages in schools.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister is someone who is very personally passionate about people being able to speak one of the languages of our region as he does, obviously, being a fluent Mandarin speaker. We are making sure that that six - more than $60 million investment is there to encourage the learning of Asian languages in school, that is being worked through between the Federal Government and State and Territory Governments, the independent and Catholic schools sector with the first delivery in relation to Asian languages in the next school year.</p>
<p>QUESTION: You may already have been asked this, but in Mr Rudd's absence who do you think he would like you to support tonight out of New South Wales and Queensland in the State of Origin?</p>
<p>JULIA GILLARD: Well, look. There isn't too many times where I seek to say something different from the Prime Minister but I've considered the matter. Obviously I was a little bit torn because I am a Melbourne Storm supporter and of course we've got a Melbourne Storm player in the Queensland team but I've wrestled with it and wrestled with it and I think the fairest possible thing is if the Prime Minister supports Queensland and I support New South Wales. Thank you very much.</p>
<p>QUESTION: [Indistinct], one more question on the Dalai Lama - sorry to ask it...</p>
<p>JULIA GILLARD: Okay, last one and we're going.</p>
<p>QUESTION: ...I believe [indistinct] still here on Sunday, are there any plans for Mr Rudd to see him there and if not why not?</p>
<p>JULIA GILLARD: The arrangements have been made for the Acting Prime Minister Chris Evans to meet with the Dalai Lama on Friday. Thanks very much.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
