<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9852</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP INTERVIEW WITH JOHN SHOVELAN, &quot;AM PROGRAM&quot;, ABC RADIO, 20 NOVEMBER 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/11/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009852.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
INTERVIEW WITH JOHN SHOVELAN, " AM PROGRAM", ABC RADIO,<br />
NOVEMBER 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
JS: Japan wants it to be flexible, Malaysia wants it to be voluntary, we<br />
want a firm commitment. There seems to be conflicting approaches to<br />
exactly where we are going.<br />
PM: Not after today there is not. There is a very comprehensive action<br />
agenda and the declaration which, of course, run to 30-odd pages<br />
were all agreed. So while it may be true, the question you put<br />
reflected the position as they came into this, coming out of it they have<br />
agreed on these very firm dates of free trade by 2010 for developed<br />
countries and 2020 for developing countries, and the means of getting<br />
there. It is an absolutely outstanding result.<br />
JS: Well there was some question whether there was going to be much in<br />
it for the Australian farmer. What is the result for them?<br />
PM: Well the answer is there is much in it for everybody. It will mean we<br />
will be able to see the Asia-Pacific continue growing at this rate<br />
because you see as these very large economies like China start to get<br />
a critical mass, the resourcing requirements in minerals, in energy, in<br />
food, are going to be larger than we have ever seen before. So unless<br />
we get the trade barriers down now, the impediments straightened out,<br />
we won't see the Asia-Pacific growth continuing the way it has been.<br />
But for it to continue at that pace and at the same time have Australia<br />
integrated into it, is the biggest change in Australia's trade position in<br />
our history.<br />
JS: Can't the sceptics, though, still justifiably argue that it is long on<br />
rhetoric and short on action because essentially nobody is really giving<br />
certainly in Australia's case, we are not actually doing that we<br />
haven't already announced?<br />
PM: That is not true at all. In fact what we have said in this statement is<br />
that the action will begin now. That what the declaration and the<br />
action agenda require is that Ministers will start to put together their </p>
<p>2<br />
well let me read from it, " Each APEC economy will begin to develop its<br />
action plan immediately after the Osaka Leaders Meeting." This is for<br />
each individual country's plan for next year in The Philippines.<br />
" Overall implementation of action plans will begin as of January 1997."<br />
You can't get it more specific than that and, of course, the<br />
down-payments: what we have done here today is put a very big<br />
down-payment on the Uruguay Round outcomes. So, as a group of<br />
countries, we are advancing as distinct from the Europeans and<br />
others we are advancing the whole of the Uruguay WTO Round. And<br />
countries here today like Indonesia, China, others, Japan put very<br />
large deregulatory trade liberalising packages down and so to has<br />
Australia.<br />
JS: Can I ask about a couple of the personalities of the meeting.? One<br />
that wasn't there, Bill Clinton, and Dr Mahathir. Is Dr Mahathir still<br />
recalcitrant about APEC?<br />
PM: Now look focus on the big issues. I mean you can't get an Australian<br />
journo off an old slogan. Here you are faced with one of the great<br />
post-war trade changes and you are asking me about something<br />
Dr Mahathir said two years ago. Dr Mahathir signed up today to this<br />
process and the atmosphere of trust and goodwill and general<br />
good-naturedness amongst the leaders is what is driving this process.<br />
The problem about trade and economic integration in the past is that<br />
the people involved have been Trade Ministers or officials and, try as<br />
they will, they can't get the authority that heads of government or<br />
leaders have. So to get the leadership at heads of government and<br />
heads of state level of the whole Pacific-Rim and get them together in<br />
a very friendly environment, driving a process of this quality, is what<br />
has made all the difference and it gives the authority to the Trade<br />
Ministers, it gives the authority to the bureaucracy, to the Trade and<br />
Foreign Affairs Departments and, as a consequence, the Asia-Pacific<br />
will lead the world in open markets and that is why already over half<br />
the world's production is in the Asia-Pacific. In ten years time it will be<br />
odd per cent of the world's production and when this is<br />
implemented by 2010 and 2020, 75 per cent of the world's production<br />
will be in our backyard.<br />
JS: Can I ask you about the industrial dispute at home just briefly. What is<br />
your reaction to Bob Hawke going back into the Industrial Court as<br />
ACTU advocate?<br />
PM: The important thing is the dispute itself, not who the ACTU advocate<br />
is. The important thing is that the Government has taken the dispute<br />
over. Last week the company went its own way as it has done now for<br />
a number of years to try, in a discriminatory way, to take unions out of<br />
their sites so that they can control the sites without any group<br />
representation by trade unions. The ACTU for its part, didn't confine<br />
the dispute to the CRA, it broadened it to a waterfront dispute which it<br />
should not have done. I thought we could have this resolved last week<br />
and the indications from the ACTU and the company was that it could </p>
<p>be resolved. When that didn't happen I had a number of conversations<br />
from Osaka with the Minister for Industrial Relations and he and I<br />
agreed that he should speak to the President of the Arbitration<br />
Commission, President O'Connor, to suggest or to have the President<br />
consider whether a compulsory conference was a reasonable thing to<br />
do given the national interest considerations here. On balance,<br />
Justice O'Connor decided that and she has called a compulsory<br />
conference, as you know, over the weekend and for Monday.<br />
As a result of the weekend's meeting, the waterfront dispute is off.<br />
There is now a dispute limited to CRA and in the Commission<br />
tomorrow the matter to be considered is the question of discrimination<br />
or non-discrimination around equal pay for equal work. Given the<br />
Commission's history and its remit I can hardly see what avenue there<br />
would be for the Commission to say that there would be -unequal pay<br />
for equal work.<br />
So, I don't think it matters very much who the representative of the<br />
ACTU is. Whether it is Bob Hawke or Bill Kelty or whoever. I think<br />
almost anyone can get this proposition over the line in the ambience of<br />
the Commission's Act.<br />
JS: John Howard says that it is very embarrassing for you that Bob Hawke<br />
had to be called in to settle a dispute or to try to settle a dispute that<br />
the Government has failed to settle.<br />
PM: He is not settling a dispute. The dispute was taken over by the<br />
Government. It is the Government's Act and the Government's<br />
processes which have got the dispute settled to this point. I mean, the<br />
waterfront dispute off and nobody has gone to the Commission, not<br />
Bob Hawke, not anybody. So, it is. quite wrong for Mr Howard to say<br />
that. I mean, it suits him to make this tawdry political point, but let the<br />
public judge his remarks. The thing is the Government is going to take<br />
no nonsense from CRA or the ACTU and it has evoked the proper<br />
processes and if-the ACTU feel more comfortable about having Bob<br />
Hawke represent them, that is fine. But the case in question now, the<br />
residual matter, about equal work for equal pay, I think, almost anyone<br />
can win that case because I doubt very much the Commission, having<br />
decided to call a compulsory conference can say other than that work<br />
of equal value should have equal pay.<br />
JS: Just a last question, do you have any sort of advice or wishes for Mr<br />
Hawke?<br />
PM: Not at all, but I mean Bob has been in the self laceration business in<br />
recent years and any balm the Government can spread on it, I'm sure<br />
will be appreciated by him and be well meant by us.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
