<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9179</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P J KEATING MP BUSINESS LUNCH, BANGKOK, 7 APRIL 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/04/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009179.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEAJING, MP<br />
B3USINECSS LUNCH, ] BANGKOK, 7 APRIL 1994<br />
It is a great pleasure to be here in Tkhaan, and in Bangkok, one of the great cities of<br />
the world and without doubt one of the citics of the future.<br />
B~ angkok is a very important city to Australia. Not just as the capital and port of a<br />
country which is an increasingly significant trading partner, but for many thousands of<br />
Australians the gateway to Thailand and its culture, and indeed to) a wider experience<br />
of Asia.<br />
Bangkok has therefore played an important role in the transformation of Australian<br />
thinking about Asia.<br />
I make these remarks at a business lunch because we recognise that to successfully do<br />
business in the region we need to raise our level of cultural understanding.<br />
Wc rcalise that economic integration with the countries of the regioin means getting to<br />
know those counties better.<br />
And if our knowledge is still far from complete, there is no doubt thatt a great change<br />
has occurred in the direction of our thinking and our perceptions.<br />
These days not only do we look to the region for trade and investment, we now look<br />
to it as we used to look almost exclusively to Euro-p-e -for culture, -fbr leisure, for<br />
diiehrencc. And as I said in a speech in Vientiane on Tuesday night, this new orientation towards<br />
Asia has brought with it the rather unexpected consequence of recasting our<br />
perception of ourselves.<br />
We learnt very quickly that to succeed in Asia we had to be iore competitive and, in<br />
becoming more comipetitive, we learnt that we can work more efficiently, develop our.<br />
skills and tcclinology, develop new p~ rodulcts and markets. </p>
<p>We knew we had to find our competitive advantages and build on them, and in doing<br />
that we learned that some of them alone and in combination were unique.<br />
Above all, we have learnt from our increasing engagement with Asia that we can<br />
succeed. My visit to Thailand, and earlier this week to Laos, confirms that fact.<br />
I am confident that Australia has much to offer and the ability to deliver it.<br />
I am also confident that our two countries have the capacity and the will to deepen and<br />
expand our relationship.<br />
Thailand and Australia have fundamental interests in common interests which are<br />
revealed to us by the transformation of our economics and the opportunities for trade<br />
and investment which have consequently opened up.<br />
Two-way trade between Thailand and Australia last year amounted to just over $ 2<br />
billion. Over the last five years it has grown at an average rate of 25 per cent.<br />
If we do no more than maintain our share of Thailand's imports, we should double our<br />
exports to Thailand by 2002: and it is a measure of the change in Australia's economy<br />
Sincluded in that would be $ 1 billion worth of elaboratcly transformed manufactures.<br />
And 1 believe that we can do better than maintain our share.<br />
The capacity is undoubtedly there.<br />
Thailand's economy is the second largest inASEAN and is likely to be the fastest<br />
growing ASEAN economy within the next few years.<br />
Thailand also has the strategic advantage of being located at the heart of continental<br />
South-East Asia, linking Indochina with the ASEAN countries.<br />
The Mekong River Friendship Bridge, which tomorrow I will formally hand over to<br />
His Majesty the King of Thailand and President of Laos, is a powerful symbol of<br />
Thailand's importance as a hub for the South-East Asian hinterland.<br />
It is also proof of Australia's capacity to join with Thailand in contributing to the subregion's<br />
development.<br />
I am in no doubt that Australia has much to offer Thailand as an economic partner in<br />
the long term.<br />
The Friendship Bridge is one good reason to believe this.<br />
I saw more evidence to support the view on my visit to Laos earlier this week, and I<br />
have seen it in other Asian countries I have visited recently. </p>
<p>I know I will see still more of it when I visit Vietnam on Sunday. Australian<br />
companies are playing a very substantial role in the economic development of Vietnam.<br />
Rut the basis of my belief in the future of our relationship with Thailand as with other<br />
countries in Asia is the change we have made to the Australian economy in recent<br />
years. We have undertaken significant economic, financial and industrial reforms which have<br />
made the economy much more open and much more competitive.<br />
We are now seeing the fruits of those reforms.<br />
Our exports have grown to 20 per cent of GDP.<br />
Our manufactured exports are now consistently stronger than rural exports and the<br />
fastest growing component of these are elaborately transformed manufactures.<br />
Our exports of services in 1992-93 are now at $ 15 billion.<br />
The Australian economy is growing at 4 per cent, faster than any in the OECD, and<br />
with low inflation.<br />
Australia is now more efficient, productive and competitive than ever before and<br />
more export-oriented.<br />
We can offer to our economic partners first class tcclhnology, expertise and skills.<br />
We can provide them to Thailand.<br />
We can help Thailand develop its infrastructure.<br />
An Australian company is building the tallest building in Bangkok.<br />
Australian companies are installing a centraliscd trafic control system and fibre<br />
optic telecommunications for the State Railway of Thailand.<br />
An Australian company, in conjunction with a Thai group, is building the Si-<br />
Chang deep sea port on the Eastern sea board of Thailand..<br />
Australia can also offer high class services, education and training to Thailand.<br />
We are presently pursuing a program of activities in higher education through a<br />
memorandum of agreement with your Ministry of University Affairs.<br />
We are providing computer assistance to Thailand's customs service.<br />
Australia is a world leader in environmental technology. </p>
<p>We have unmatched experience in shaping environmentally-friendly urban development<br />
and in Bangkok Australian planners and architects are heavily involved in designs for<br />
new urban development schemes.<br />
For all these examples of success, there remains a well of untapped potential.<br />
When it comes to trade, we are basically like-minded countries.<br />
We have shared a commitment to the Cairns Group and to APEC which promises to<br />
deliver real benefits to our business communities by stimulating and facilitating trade<br />
and investment flows in our region.<br />
The Uruguay Round outcome will improve the economic prospects of middle ranking<br />
economies like ours.<br />
But of course we cannot simply wait for the opportunities to present themselves.<br />
I have to say that I do not believe we have yet made the most of our relationship.<br />
Until now we have tended to take each other, I think, rather too much for granted.<br />
This may be because there have been few major problems in what is a relationship of<br />
many yoars standing.<br />
Whatever the reasons, 1 would like my visit to be the moment at which Australia and<br />
Thailand began to pay each other greater attention.<br />
For instance, the level of investment, while increasing, does not do justice to the<br />
relationship. We need to take steps to maximise the conditions in which investment<br />
can flourish.<br />
And we need to tackle the remaining barriers which inhibit the expansion of trade<br />
between us.<br />
I discussed some of these issues with Prime Minister Chuan this morning.<br />
At the governmcnt-to-government level, we are putting in place the framework for<br />
greater private sector cooperation and investment.<br />
Today Prime Minister Chuan and I reached agreement on the formation of a<br />
Ministerial Commission a regular ministerial forum in which to discuss ways of<br />
expanding trade and investment links.<br />
Prime Minister Chuan and I also agreed that the Australian Trade Minister, Senator<br />
McMullan, will lead a major business mission to Thailand later this year with the aim<br />
of identifying ways to expand our commercial links and develop cooperation between<br />
us in third markets.<br />
It is essential that through government contact we create an appropriate framework for<br />
expanding trade and cooperation. </p>
<p>But on this visit it is equally an objective of mine to highlight to the business<br />
communities of Australia and Thailand the great opportunities which now exist.<br />
Australian business has the chance to be a part of Thailand's economic success and the<br />
certainty of burgeoning development in coming years.<br />
And, equally, the major reforms of recent years have made Australia a very good place<br />
for Thai companies to do business.<br />
The Australian Government welcomes foreign investment. We actively encourage it<br />
with a business tax system which includes generous accelerated depreciation<br />
allowances and research and development concessions, and a 33 per cent company tax<br />
rate after which foreign investors get tax free dividends.<br />
Foreign companies in Australia also enjoy the benefits of a skilled workforce, cheap<br />
energy, highly developed infrastructure including sophisticated telecommunications,<br />
and a society and a political system as stable as any in the world.<br />
It is, as I said, a very good place to do business these days.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen, 1 will be very pleased with this visit if hereafter our two<br />
governments and our two business communities acknowledge what has been until now<br />
a somewhat unacknowledged fact I mean the profound convergence of our interests.<br />
In the past few years we have worked together for the liberalisation of world<br />
agriculture markets. We have worked together on APEC. On Cambodia. Our<br />
companies are working together.<br />
We have been building bridges together for some time now.<br />
1 hope that my visit to Thailand will help both our countries to recognise that we are<br />
standing on the threshold of a dynamic new phase in our relationship.<br />
After my discussions this morning with Prime Minister Chun and his senior colleagues<br />
I am confident that the Thai Government shares that view.<br />
It is reasonable to infer from your presence here that the Thai and Australian business<br />
communities have come to the same understanding.<br />
If the Australian and Thai governments do everything that is practicable to make the<br />
most of the future we share, it will still depend on your efforts to turn potential into<br />
reality. You are at the heart of our relationship.<br />
If there is to be a new era, you will number among the pioneers.<br />
I congratulate you for your enterprise and wish you well with all your endeavours. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
