<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9260</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP, INTERVIEW WITH KEITH CONLON, RADIO 5AN, ADELAIDE THURSDAY 23 JUNE, 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/06/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009260.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP,<br />
INTERVIEW WITH KEITH CONLON, RADIO 5AN, ADELAIDE<br />
THURSDAY 23 JUNE, 1994<br />
KC: Prime Minister, good morning.<br />
PM: How are you, good, Keith?<br />
KC: Pretty good. Why are you available to the media at such short notice<br />
today, Prime Minister, is it as some critics are already saying, that<br />
you're a bit rattled by Downer's popularity?<br />
PM: No, it's just that you characters put in requests and occasionally we<br />
take them up. And, we take them up when it suits us. And, I did a<br />
major television interview last night on Late/ mne and there's a bit of<br />
press around, today, about that, so I thought this wouldn't be a bad<br />
opportunity. But, of course, if you don't want me on, just let us know.<br />
KC: No, we're delighted that you are. We're hoping that as we're talking to<br />
Alexander Downer fairly regularly we were hoping we might talk to you<br />
more regularly.<br />
PM: Well, now is your chance.<br />
KC: Yes, indeed. One of the big issues that came up last night was<br />
Telecom and we've actually been sent a letter from the Oppositionthey<br />
naturally keep track of what you do during election campaigns-<br />
* and -init you-told Telecom workers, ' Telecom won't be sold under my<br />
government," and later you said, " We are committed to continued<br />
public ownership of Telecom and Australia Post. tHow does that sit<br />
with your comments last night that public or private ownership, it<br />
doesn't matter, it's not of its essence, public ownership is not<br />
especially important? </p>
<p>PM; Before that I said that we are keeping Telecom in public ownership.<br />
That is, because of the pivotal role telecommunications plays in the<br />
economy and society and the need to ensure that services are<br />
available to all of the community on a fair basis. Because, as you<br />
know there are enormous cross subsidies in Telecom. A lot of rural<br />
and provincial country users, and certain other services within cities,<br />
are effectively a set of cross subsidies. I think, keeping those services<br />
there and the sheer size of Telecom and the local loop, as it's called<br />
that is the telephone connections to the homes of this country it's<br />
very important, I think, to make sure that those services are not<br />
impeded. So, that's why the Government has always said that<br />
Telecom will remain in public ownership. But, the question then was<br />
put to me, " Well, in terms of tariff rates and competition and<br />
efficiencies, is, therefore, the public ownership thing critical?" I said<br />
no, providing there's a competitive model there and we have a<br />
competitive model now, with Optus, with Vodaphone and, of course, a<br />
lot of private resellers of Telecom services.<br />
KC: You did say last night, or you actually wanted Kerry O'Brien to qualify<br />
the question last night, Prime Minister, you were saying, " Are we<br />
talking every little bit of it?" Has that left room for the Left<br />
PM: You were viewing, were you Keith, you were viewing?<br />
KC: I was certainly watching. Does that leave room for the Left of your<br />
party to be continually concerned about what they would call<br />
privatisation by stealth?<br />
PM: No, because what we're saying is that the government's got no plans<br />
for the sale of any part of Telecom. None of that is on the government<br />
agenda. But, its precise structure will always be evolutionary, it's<br />
continuing to adapt and change. So, not every last morsel of it will<br />
always be critical to Telecom, the entity.<br />
KC: So are there some non core assets that could be sold sometime soon?<br />
PM: There are none that we are planning to sell but Telecom is making<br />
commercial arrangements every day of the week and in a year from<br />
now or two or three years from now you wouldn't know what there will<br />
be there.<br />
KG: In a wide ranging interview last night, Prime Minister, this alleged<br />
comment that is coming up in Bob Hawke's book came out this idea<br />
that you had referred in a private conversation with him, to Australia,<br />
as the ' arse end of the earth'. Did you say that?<br />
PM: I can't ever remember saying that to Mr Hawke but if it's a reference to<br />
a short hand way of saying that Australia is way out of the Northern<br />
Hemisphere markets and is a long way from everywhere, that we have </p>
<p>to be better than most, that we have to be competitive, that we have to<br />
actually go out and get business, that we have to actually be better at<br />
trade and promotion these are all points that I have made to the<br />
Labor cabinet over a decade.<br />
KG: Is it likely, though, to become one of those statements like the ' silly old<br />
bugger' phrase that Mr Hawke had to carry with him, an aside<br />
perhaps?<br />
PM: Mr Hawke said that in public, to an aging person in a shopping centre.<br />
I don't remember making this comment to Mr Hawke, at all.<br />
KC: Did it did it in any way, if you said something similar to this, did it in<br />
any way reflect upon your attitude towards Australia as it is today?<br />
PM: I notice Alexander Downe r running on about this today saying that, you<br />
know, he wouldn't talk about his country in this way. He wants his<br />
country to have the Head of State an English Monarch, not an<br />
Australian. I mean, here's the Leader of the National Party the other<br />
night singing the national anthem of another country, " God Save The<br />
Queen". I mean, you know, let.. I mean, I think this debate about our<br />
commitment to Australia is a pretty silly debate frankly. I mean, I've<br />
been a member of Parliament for 25 years, I've been a Minister for 11,<br />
I've been Prime Minister for 2 and a half years, to be having a debate<br />
about whether one's committed to Australia or not is pretty, pretty<br />
puerile, I think. I mean, I accept the fact that Mr Downer's committed to<br />
Australia, as I am, but he's not committed to the sort of policies I<br />
believe are in Australia's best interest.<br />
KG: But this business about who's Australian and who's not and what the<br />
attitude is seems to be a matter of continuing comment. I understand<br />
in the Senate this morning,_ Galreth Evans told the Senate at least your<br />
Government has a leader with an Australian family, so he's making it<br />
an issue.<br />
PM: Well, I didn't know he'd said that. That matter is simply a matter for<br />
Mrs Downer herself.<br />
KG: Is it though that kind of continuing personal sniping that you claim that<br />
you don't want to be part of now?<br />
PM: But I'm not part of it. I mean I've just given you my reply. I mean,<br />
that's a matter for Mrs Downer.<br />
KG: And Senator Evans, perhaps?<br />
PM: Well, Senator Evans can speak for himself. </p>
<p>KC: Prime Minister, the market is obviously an area of enormous<br />
importance. It was the substance of the talk last night with Kerry<br />
O'Brien. What about the allegation today that it is not a question of<br />
whether the settings are right within Australia, but perceptions in the<br />
overseas markets that there is loose fiscal policy here?<br />
PM: Well that, that Keith, that's a bit of nonsense. Here we are look I was,<br />
as you know, recently at the D-Day commemoration with most of the<br />
leaders of Western Europe. Not a person there, not a Prime Minister,<br />
not a President, had 5 per cent economic growth and 1 per cent<br />
inflation. Not one. Not one had anything like 3 and a 1/ 4 per cent<br />
employment growth. Now they're the settings that Australia has got<br />
and in our national accounts, that came out just 2 or 3 weeks ago, for<br />
the year to March we found that average weekly earnings growth was<br />
half a percentage point. I mean, the thing that normally drives inflation<br />
along in this country, I mean you've got to go back, I don't know,<br />
you've got to go back well before I was in public life to find wages so<br />
subdued and as you know, the Government has just made another<br />
arrangement to pay $ 8 a week this year coming, and the following<br />
year, which will hold that's for the bottom 25 30 per cent of the<br />
workforce which will hold inflation, again consistent with that low<br />
inflation outcome. So...<br />
KC: And those, those things are within the country Prime Minister, but this<br />
is the perception of a world market, a market which you wanted us to<br />
enter Alexander Downer's made the point this morning.<br />
PM: It's not the world markets doing this, it's the Australian bond market<br />
doing this. This is not, the international bond markets have not shifted<br />
to the degree to which the Australian Bond Market has shifted.<br />
KC: This morning one of the Australian dealers has fought back, Prime<br />
Minister, and said " Look, it is not the Australian dealers, it is not their<br />
fault, we are part of a global market".<br />
PM: Oh, they're part of a global market but in the end who holds the great<br />
stock of Australian Bonds? It's held in the domestic portfolios, of, you<br />
know, the AMP Society's number one fund, National Mutuals' funds. I<br />
mean, they're held by the big Super funds and private instituions and<br />
companies, that's who holds the bonds principally and the bond<br />
markets may here.<br />
KC: Prime Minister, we started out with the Leader of the Opposition this<br />
morning here on 5AN asking him to do a bit of self-assessment on his<br />
first month in, would you mind doing a quick swat analysis? What do<br />
you think Alexander Downer's strengths have been in the first month?<br />
PM: Well, I think he's made the mistake of thinking he can go back to<br />
Malcolm Fraser's policies, and Malcolm Fraser's approach to life. That </p>
<p>is, back to that blancmange policies of the Fraser years, where we<br />
missed a decade of opportunitiy to restructure ourself and then had to<br />
do it with a great urgency from the early 1980' s onwards. We should<br />
have actually been changing this country, making the linkages into<br />
Asia, opening up the tariff barriers, getting our business competitive,<br />
lifting product innovation, lifting exports of things other than primary<br />
products. We should have been doing that from the early 1970' s and<br />
we lost that time and it's one of the reasons why the liberal Party is as<br />
ideological as it has been in the last, say, half dozen, ten years is<br />
because what they perceive is the perceived failures of Malcolm<br />
Fraser's administration, yet Alexander Downer wants to emulate it with<br />
soft fluffy talk anywhere and certainly, no, no hardness for policy What<br />
he's saying is..<br />
KC: Is he a tougher political opponent, though Prime Minister?<br />
PM: Well, I don't, I haven't had time to work that out, I mean John, John<br />
Hewson never made anyhting very easy for me, but if you look at what<br />
I've seen so far from Alexander Downer was, is basically spoiling<br />
negativity. On the Land Fund, where he had an opportunity with<br />
Aboriginal Reconciliation in this country, to put the MABO mess of the<br />
Liberal Party behind him, he corrected Chris Gallus the first time she<br />
opened her mouth in respect of saying maybe we should consider our<br />
support for the land fund, when the Church..<br />
KC: Prime Minister,<br />
PK: when the Church..<br />
KC: Prime Minister, unfortunately the news is coming up and we, and the<br />
news waits for no one. I much appreciate your time being with us<br />
today.<br />
PK: OK, Thank you then.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
