<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9168</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP AND THE TREASURER THE HON R WILLIS MP PARLIAMETN HOUSE CANBERRA, FRIDAY 25 MARCH, 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/03/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009168.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL 2. a : 3N. 0 1' Q<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, M. P.<br />
THE TREASURER, THE HON. R WILLIS, M. P, PARLIAMENT HOUSE<br />
CANBERRA, FRIDAY 25 MARCH, 1994<br />
PM: Well, Mr Willis and I were going to give you a comment about the<br />
outcome of the Premiers' Conference and Loan Council meeting. I<br />
tfihiik we've seen move into place today a very substantial reform to<br />
Commonwealth-State financial relations. For the first time in at least<br />
11f years we are seei ng -a formula for the Commonwealth dealing with<br />
the States which provides a basis of certainty and growth to<br />
Commonwealth payments to the States. We've given the States today,<br />
for the three years, in real terms, that is, a payment covering inflation,<br />
the existing base of Commonwealth payments to the States plus<br />
inflation. And we've built into that population growth.<br />
So, it will be the existing base, plus inflation, plus population growth<br />
which Is really the most certain stream of payments the States have<br />
had and one which can now grow along with national population<br />
growth. Now, of course, in that there will always be the within-state<br />
distribution and shifts in population which the Grants Commission<br />
measures because, as you know, people leaving Victoria and going to<br />
Queensland, all those sorts of things will come up in what is called the<br />
relativities, every year. But, the pool of funds from the Commonwealth<br />
to the States will now have that betterment factor of real terms plus per<br />
capita or . population growth. Now, I think we've seen here a<br />
substantial reform and even though you won't get all the Premiers to<br />
say so I think they do, too. They certainly said that inside. And, it<br />
means, I think, that the cooperation we were able to get at the Council<br />
of Australian Governments in Hobart, we'll see again in the August<br />
meeting as we now will not be having a discussion about the pool<br />
next year or the year later, that being settled today. Now, I would just<br />
invite the Treasurer to add his remarks to mine.<br />
T: 1 think the Prime Minister has said it all. Essentia~ y, this is a very good<br />
deal for the States. They are no worse off this year than they would<br />
have been had the old formula applied. By 1996-97 they start to kick<br />
28. Mar 948: 23 No. 001 P. 01/ 05 </p>
<p>TEL 2<br />
some real goals with the application of the real terms per capita<br />
coming through and giving them substantial increases by that time.<br />
And, in the years to come, of course, should the agreement continue<br />
as we expect it would, then the States would be very much in front.<br />
Over the course of a decade they'd be something in the order of $ 6<br />
billion dollars better off as a result of this formula applying, assuming<br />
that Inflation remains steady for ten years; $ 6 billion dollars better off<br />
than they would have been with the old formula. So, for the States this<br />
is a very, very substantial gain and one which should enable them to<br />
considerably improve their services over the next decade or so,<br />
J. Prime Minister, if that's the case why haven't the States been happy as<br />
they've come out only one seems to have supported it?<br />
PM: Well, when we said, " If you want to leave it as the status quo, that is,<br />
as last year," not one of them wanted to leave behind a real terms<br />
guarantee and population growth. I mean, no one really was prepared<br />
to walk away with the status quo. And, I think that's the best test. The<br />
best test, really, is what they say around the table. And, what they<br />
said around the table is, look, this is the best thing to come our way,<br />
let's have it.<br />
J: How would you describe your relationship with the States after todays<br />
meeting?<br />
PM: Pretty good, really. Look, this is a federation, there is a huge pool of<br />
national funds here which Is essentially divvied up and distributed in<br />
one day. Now, the effect of G rants Commission reports, a change in<br />
an old Capital Works Program with a very istoric distribution going<br />
all those things -coming and going some States are better off and<br />
some worse off. So, getting an outcome where most agree is a very<br />
difficult thing to get. But, we got that.<br />
J: Is there any talk of improving the States shaky revenue base and if<br />
there wasn't do you think something should be done about it?<br />
PM: Well, I think they'll pick up the revenue growth that comes with the<br />
recovery, So, if they're getting not just real terms maintenance of<br />
Commonwealth funding, but with population'as well and on top of that<br />
they have the growth in their own revenues they're going to be in a<br />
pretty comfortable position.<br />
J: Premier Fahey told us that over the next three years Commonwealth<br />
revenue is expected to rise by $ 26 billion, how much of that will be<br />
given to the states now?<br />
PMV: Well, as the Treasurer said, a proportion of it will be given to them as a<br />
consequence of the formula. But, again, over the last three years<br />
we've added about $ 25 billion to our national debt through the deficits<br />
T2EL8: . Mar. 94 8: 23 NO. 001 P. 02/ 05 </p>
<p>TEL: 28. Mar. 94 8: 23 No. 001 P. 03/ 05<br />
3<br />
which the Commonwealth has to run in the national economy. And, so,<br />
now is the time for the nation to pay those deficits back. I know that<br />
some Premiers had this quaint line, ' they're not giving the money back<br />
to the people'. Well, the people are all the people and the nation, the<br />
people, must have a reduction in the budget deficit if we're to keep low<br />
interest rates, growth -and jobs.<br />
So, the Commonwealth provides a natural stabiliser for the economy.<br />
That is, it provides the cushioning whenever there is a recession and<br />
therefore it has got to have the financial capacity to take the debt out<br />
when the good times come back.<br />
Now, to say ' Look, sorry, the States get full payments in the bad times<br />
and they also take all the joy in the good times," even I don't think they<br />
expect us to accept that.<br />
J: Mr Kennett says the extra $ 20 million for Victoria is disgraceful<br />
considering the extra revenue you would get as the economy grows.<br />
PM: Victoria did very well out of this and they are all saying look, lets get<br />
population growth and the real terms guarantee that's the real<br />
reform, let's grab hold of it. Now, they haven't been offered that in the<br />
past and they did grab hold of it and I think Mr Kennett was chief<br />
among them.<br />
J: Are you saying you will continue real, per capita increases beyond<br />
1996-97?<br />
PM: I think that is our general intention.<br />
T: The agreement is only for three years, but we would expect that that<br />
agreement would roll on provided we had a co-operative relationship<br />
with the States over that time. Now, we expect to get that in relation to<br />
micro economic reform. We have made that clear as an element of the<br />
proposal for the next three years and should that be forthcoming as we<br />
expect that it will be, then we would be prepared to maintain real terms<br />
per capita. So, that would roll on and the States would be very, very<br />
substantial beneficiaries.<br />
PM; As I said this morning, there is a maturing here of this relationship in<br />
terms of the big micro reform agenda in COAG and in terms of funding<br />
under this fofi-Tila so -the States now know whait they will be getting<br />
every year in terms of the Financial Assistance Grants pool. There will<br />
still be internecine interstate arguments about who gets what and what<br />
population shifts there are and whether the Grants Commission got the<br />
formula right, but that won't be about the pool; that will only be about<br />
the distribution amongst themselves. </p>
<p>TEL 4<br />
J Would you prefer to see the maturity of the relationship reflected in the<br />
Premiers' public comments?<br />
PM: The more grist to the mill the better. I always think it is better for them<br />
to tell the public as It really is. And as it really is, is pretty good.<br />
J: What was the tone of the meeting compared to previous years. It<br />
seems to have been pretty quiet?<br />
PM: Compared with the 1960s... they were tough meetings. This was, what<br />
we would say, wearying, but not harrowing.<br />
J: Prime Minister, In terms of Cabinet reshuffles, have we seen the end<br />
now?<br />
PM;-I think you are seeing a new stock of competent Labor people coming<br />
to ministries. One, a former Premier. You are seeing a new important<br />
contributor to the Government-John Faulkner, go into the Cabinet. I<br />
think the Labor party is very lucky that it can see people like Neal<br />
Blewett and John Dawkins and John Kerin leave the Parliament and<br />
see the kind of people who have replaced them.<br />
J: But is this the end of the shuffle?<br />
PM: It depends whether somebody resigns for some reason but I don't<br />
expect there will be anyone from this point on resign and, I think,<br />
probably you've seen the last change. But it is a good change and it is<br />
a very good ministerial line up.<br />
J: Why take science from. Senator -Schacht?<br />
PM: Science goes into the Cabinet with Senator Cook and Senator Schacht<br />
then will keep responsibility, amongst other things, for small business<br />
and also for thie Co-operative Research Centres. So, he is going to<br />
maintain his link with that science faculty which we've built into the Cooperative<br />
Research Centres as well as being the Deputy Minister to<br />
Senator Cook who will have science in the Cabinet.<br />
J: Have you been concerned though about the problems that have been<br />
occurring in the science portfolio since Chris Schacht took it over?<br />
PM: I think the scientists are a pretty tough team to manage, really. I don't<br />
know that anyone can do it easily. Again, it is not a case of cheers and<br />
clapping from the side.<br />
J: Would you have preferred to have the free hand at this time that you<br />
had last time after the election rather than having to bow to some of<br />
the factional pressures? T2E8L:. Mar. 94 8: 23 No. 001 P. 04/ 0t </p>
<p>TEL: 28. Mar. 94 8: 23 No. 001 P. 05/ 05<br />
PM: There was no bowing here. Let me assure you, the three people whio<br />
were elected yesterday were elected unopposed and each of the three<br />
were three that I had suggested to people should be coming to the<br />
ministry. As it turned out, the Caucus agreed with me about that We<br />
will now have something like about seventeen ministers. Sixteen<br />
ministers wilt have changed since the last election. That is a<br />
tremendous change for this country. Energy is the life blood of politics.<br />
Energy and Ideas. To keep that energy coming through Is terribly<br />
important for the national government.<br />
J: Are you saying you didn't want Mr Elliott in your Cabinet?<br />
PM: No. It is not a matter of making judgements about Mr Elliott or any<br />
other single person. It Is just that in terms of seniority and<br />
contributions others have made, others had greater claims at this time.<br />
J: Did Mr Brereton ask you for a change in portfolio?<br />
PM: We are happy to provide you with some overview advice, but not open<br />
heart surgery.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
