<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>137</transcript-id>
    <title>PRESS CONFERENCE GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R.G. MENZIES ON FRIDAY, 13TH NOVEMBER, 1959 AT 11 A.M.</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/11/1959</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000137_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
A, PRESS CONFERENCE GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER,<br />
THE RT. HON. R. G. MENZIES ON FRIDAY, 13TH<br />
NOVEMBER, 1959 at 11 A. M.<br />
QUESTE ON: Can you tell us Sir, when* you expect the new Governor-<br />
General to reach Australia?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes, early in February. He would be here well<br />
ahead of the beginning of the 1960 Session so that he<br />
will be able to open it.<br />
QUESTION: Any date fixed for this, Sir? The opening.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Oh, no. But I mean normally one assumes that it<br />
will be some time in February, but it may be late in<br />
February.<br />
QUESTION: He's coming by ship, I suppose, Sir?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes, he is due to arrive here about the 1st or 2nd<br />
or 3rd of February.<br />
QUESTION: Is it the usual customary five-year term?<br />
PRIME MINISTERi No special arrangement.<br />
QUESTIONX You expect it to be about 5 years do you, Sir?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes. As you know, it is an appointment at will.<br />
But that is the sort of normal practice.<br />
QUESTION-. Sir, there has been a certain amount of criticism<br />
of the appointment, mainly by Mr. Calwell and..<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Has it been in your paper. How important that<br />
would be!<br />
QUESTION: Well, I was just wondering whether you would comment<br />
on that, Sir, on the criticism that the Governor-<br />
General is not an Australia, Sir,<br />
PRIME MINISTER: My views on that are perfectly well-known. Australians<br />
are not excluded, but they are not to have,<br />
say, the exclusive right to be considered. My idea is<br />
to get the best man.<br />
QUESTION: Was there any thought given to the possibility of<br />
getting someone from one of the other Dominions, Sir?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No. Well, when you say " was there any thought" I<br />
ran the whole world over in my own mind first, but I<br />
didn't bring into consideration any individual from<br />
another Dominion.<br />
QUESTION: Could you tell us, Sir, whether this was your<br />
nomination to the Queen or her suggestion?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: My nomination to the Queen. I think I ought to<br />
tell you the way we go about this thing. I don't<br />
take up the attitude that I nominate ' Jones' and that's<br />
the finish. What Itve done twice now is to have quite<br />
a long discussion with the Queen about the kind of<br />
person we want, and getting her views on people, and<br />
offering a few comments on any names that she might<br />
' throw into the ring'. And then in this case I said:<br />
" Well you're going off to Canada and there's not all<br />
that hurry; I will correspond with you when you get<br />
back from Canada". Then I wrote to Her Majesty and<br />
suggested two or three names that might be considered </p>
<p>by her but I put them in my own order for preference,<br />
but indicated, of course, that if she had any strong<br />
feelings about any one of them that, naturally, would<br />
influence my mind. My No. 1 was W. S. Morrison and she<br />
emphatically approved of it. I think I should add<br />
having regard to some talented pieces of lying that I<br />
have read in one newspaper that from first to last,<br />
neither directly or indirectly, have I made any proposal<br />
that a member of the Royal Family should be appointed<br />
to be Governor-General, nor has any such proposal been<br />
made to me. I hope that is sufficiently specific. If<br />
people will invent stories, I wish they would invent<br />
something more consistent with my attitude to these<br />
matters.<br />
QUESTE ON:<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
QUESTION: How long have you known the Viscount, Sir?<br />
Twentyfour years.<br />
Did you first meet him in the legal or the political<br />
world?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: In the political world. In 1935 I think he had<br />
just become Financial Secretary to the Treasury and I<br />
went down and stayed with him a few days at his house.<br />
He lived in what might be described as an old remnant<br />
of some early monastery or something of that kind one<br />
of those little old houses that you strike in the<br />
Cotswolds with a slippery elm stairway up which I had<br />
to go; you know, a rope on the side, and a bathroom in<br />
the attic. But at that time, of course, his boys were<br />
very young. But he and I have been very great friends<br />
ever since. That, of course, I hope won't be held<br />
against him.<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTEF<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTK<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTEF<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTEF<br />
COMMENT: PRIME MINISTEF<br />
QUESTION: He is a Scot of course?<br />
Yes. He was born in the Hebrides in the western<br />
islands. Do you happen to know if he is a Presbyterian, Sir?<br />
1: Oh, I'd lay odds that he is a Presbyterian, but I<br />
wouldn't know. He's got all the marks.<br />
Sir, would you know if Lady Dunrossil's father was<br />
a Doctor of Divinity?<br />
Yes, he was a Presbyterian Minister. Like Lady<br />
Slim's father. In fact Lady Slim and Allison Morrison<br />
know each other.<br />
There has been some criticism in London, Sir, that<br />
he retired from the Speakership because of ill-health,<br />
I think that that amounted to a slight deafness<br />
and oddly enough he felt that even a slight deafness<br />
wasn't very good in a Speaker, who ought to hear both<br />
sides. It is sometimes very useful not to hear, Sir.<br />
I think you will find that he is in very nimble<br />
orm. The snapshot I've seen makes hi~ m look rather like<br />
a Munroe Ferguson portrait. Would that be true, Sir?<br />
f </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER: Don't think so. There's a superb photograph in<br />
this morning's Sydney Morning Herald. That is absolutely<br />
" Shakes" Morrison to the life. You know that<br />
big full-on one. He is a tall slightly built man.<br />
QUESTION: Where does the " Shakes" come from, Sir?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well, his name is William Shepherd Morrison and a<br />
lot of people when I first knew him were firmly of the<br />
opinion that his second name was Shakespeare. I think<br />
a lot of people got that misapprehension. Probably in<br />
his student days he might have got it because he took<br />
a keen interest in poetry and he read a lot of Shakespeare<br />
and is fond of Shakespeare. He wrote one or two<br />
very good poems himself, I don't mind saying. But I<br />
think he was called " Shakes" only afte-1 he came round<br />
to live among the Sassenachs. I think he was always<br />
called when he was at the University.<br />
QUESTION: Did he have an opportunity of seeing much of Australia<br />
the last time he was out here; to know what the<br />
country would be like?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Oh, I don't know. They weren't here for more than<br />
a few days. He didn't have much opportunity. But he<br />
bas represented a rural electorate in the North Cotswolds<br />
and he was Minister for Agriculture for some time<br />
in the United Kingdom Government.<br />
QUESTON: Sir, I think you said much earlier that Australians<br />
were not excluded. Is t hat correct?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: That's right.<br />
QUESTION: You've no objection to Australians<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No, I haven't but it is very difficult to get a<br />
man from your own country in reality, unless you can<br />
get somebody who is not, politically, a contentious person.<br />
And most people who are best known in Australia<br />
have been through some political or controversial mill.<br />
You might very well have somebody who wasn't handicapped<br />
in that way, but who was a man of great eminence.<br />
I wouldn't exclude him. I think it is always useful<br />
for the man appointed to be known to the Queen because<br />
he is the Queen's personal representative. But I've<br />
advocated for many years the idea, for example, of<br />
having some Australian made Governor-General of Canada<br />
or South Africa or vice versa. I think these crossbearings<br />
are valuable. But there again, of course,<br />
it is not easy.<br />
QUESTION: Does that suggest, Sir, that the list you presented<br />
to the Queen could have included an Australian<br />
name?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No, it didn't. I did not find myself able to<br />
select a suitable name in Australia. You understand<br />
this was my No. 1 nomination. This notion that I've<br />
been toting the business around, of course, is most<br />
offensive because this is No. 1 nomination and warmly<br />
and promptly accepted at that point of time by the<br />
Queen. Up to that time we had, in effect, merely<br />
talked about the type of person or the qualifications,<br />
which is a good thing to do.<br />
QUESTION: He announced himself in London last nig7ht, Sir,<br />
that it wasn't until the 27th October that he was approached. </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER: That's quite right. I didn't sound him or anybody<br />
until I had the Queen's concurrence in my nomination.<br />
Then the next step is that I say: " I now ask permission<br />
to approach that man to find out whether he is agreeable".<br />
You don~ t go around saying: " if you were<br />
offered it -vuld you take it?" you know, That's no<br />
good.<br />
QUESTION: His retirement from the Speakership was not in any<br />
way related to the appointment?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No, As a matter of fact it was when I knew some<br />
little time back that he was giving up the Speakership<br />
that I brought him into the area of thought myself.<br />
QUESTION: Mr. Menzies, as I understand it then the machinery<br />
is that the Prime Minister approaches the nominee, not<br />
anyone from the Queen's..<br />
PRIME MINISTER: In this case, having got the Queen's approval, I<br />
then got Sir Eric Harrison to see Mr. Morrison with a<br />
specific message from me. He then considered the matter<br />
for a day or two, then Sir Eric Harrison told me<br />
that the answer was " Yes", then I communicated with the<br />
Queen saying that the nominee was agreeable and I<br />
therefore now formally nominated him and would be glad<br />
to know on what date the Queen would make the announcement<br />
what date and time so that it could be referred<br />
to concurrently at this end. Then, I finally got back<br />
word that Her Majesty would announce it at 12 o'clock<br />
noon yesterday.<br />
QUESTION: The other possible nominees, Sir, would not even<br />
know that they were considered?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No, never.<br />
QUESTION: One small point, Sir. The paper you referred to<br />
as not quite accurate. Could you tell us whether that<br />
was a Melbourne paper?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: It was a Sydney paper Sydney afternoon paper,<br />
You would have no doubt about that would you which<br />
one I mean?<br />
QUESTION: Sir? W~ hat's the fate of the Divorce Bill going to be,<br />
PRIME MINISTER: It's a non-party measure. Somebody was asking<br />
when I was in there last night whether that stood<br />
right. It does, Most of the argument seems to centre<br />
about this Separation clause.<br />
QUESTION: Are you going to speak on it, Sir?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I don't think so.<br />
QUESTION: Have you made up your mind on it, Sir?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I'll support the Bill.<br />
QUESTION: You stated, Sir, that the new Governor-General<br />
would open Parliament. That means there will be a prorogation<br />
of the Parliament?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: That's right.<br />
QUESTION: Sir re the Governor-General. Have you heard any<br />
word as Lo whether he will be bringing any personal<br />
staff out at all or will he </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTE]<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTE]<br />
QUJEST'ION: PRIME MINISTEi<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTEI<br />
qJESTION: PRIME MINISTEI<br />
QUESTION: Those matters are being discussed with him now.<br />
What progress has been made with your review of<br />
Parliamentary allowances and amenities, Sir?<br />
; Ahat review is that?<br />
I believe you said you were informing yourself<br />
about it.<br />
i: I said I was informing myself about it yes. But<br />
somebody appears to have got into his head that I have<br />
established a committee or something, but I haven't.<br />
There has always been an Amenities Committee.<br />
Have you informed yourself, Sir, to the extent<br />
that you are going to crack any heads?<br />
I: haven't yet informed myself I regret to tell you.<br />
I have been too busy on other matters.<br />
Which Ministers have the authority to direct the<br />
activities of the Security Service without reference<br />
to you, Sir?<br />
1: The Attorney-General's Department has it for administration<br />
purposes. I am responsible for policy and<br />
the Head of the Security Service communicates directly<br />
wfith me. Would Sir Garfield's direction to approach<br />
Professor Stout be an exercise of his administrative<br />
authority or a policy matter?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: 1. ell, he didn't direct Spry; he found out that<br />
Stout wranted to know and so apparently Sir Garfield<br />
conveyed that to Spry, no doubt with an indication that<br />
he thought it might be useful if Spry saw him and helped<br />
him. I don't ro-ard that as a normal practice. As I<br />
said in the Parliament, the normal practice on these<br />
matters is that the Security Srvic oepor'. s to me, or from<br />
time to time if I say I want the Attorney-General to<br />
see this, to the Attorney-General or from time to time<br />
to the Department of Scternal Affairs because these<br />
things havo a bearing, but the Security Service exists<br />
to inform us putting it in that way and does not in<br />
fact normally convey information to other people, It<br />
collects information. But I don't foel at all disturbed<br />
about the fact that he saw Stout because as a matter of<br />
fact it became quite clear that everything that he informed<br />
Stout about, had already been published in the<br />
Press. There was no secret cloak and dagger stuff<br />
about it.<br />
QUESTION: The end in effect of this project though, Sir,<br />
seems to have been to dissuade some non-communist<br />
people from attending this meeting and perhaps leaving<br />
the Communists to win the Congress by default. Do you<br />
think that was a desired end result?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well, you are now saying the " end re sultll of<br />
what? The end result of statements made by Mr. Casey<br />
and Sir Garfield Barwick and myself, not by the Security<br />
Service, but by us, may have had the effect of dissuading<br />
a lot of people to attend. I hopoit did. I consider<br />
it most desirable. I don't like to see decent citizens<br />
having their legs pulled. So there you are. I<br />
must be careful because I saw in one report that they<br />
ASre going to pass a vote of thanks commending me, and I </p>
<p>hope none of you will publish anything that will prevent<br />
that from coming about.<br />
QUESTION: QUESTION: PRIME MINISTEI<br />
QUESTION: i It might be just to test the feeling of the meetng.<br />
On the Security Service, Sir, you told Mr. Whtitlam<br />
in the House, 10 days or so ago, that you expected to<br />
reach some conclusions on the telephone matter before<br />
the end of the year. Has that been developed yet, Sir?<br />
well, no. W4e've been so heavily engaged in Cabinet<br />
on other matters. I've had some discussions with the<br />
Attorney-General but I haven't got it to the point of<br />
discussing it with the Cabinet yet.<br />
When do you expect the Defence Statement to be<br />
ready Sir?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I don't know. We've had two or three Cabinet<br />
Meetings on it. We're having another one next<br />
Wednesday. I am hopeful that all this will enable a<br />
Statement to be made in the following week, but as I<br />
said earlier to you chaps, I want this thing to be<br />
cleared up before I leave.<br />
QUESTION: Has any decision been made, yet, Sir, on National<br />
Service Trainihg?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No. No decisions have been made yet. We have<br />
arrived at a series of tentative views, but further paper,<br />
or papers, are being prepared which we are going<br />
to examine when we next moet on this matter next week<br />
and we will then, I hope, be in a position to arrive<br />
at a final conclusion.<br />
QUESTION: You mean, Sir, that you are hopeful of being in a<br />
position to make a statement to Parliament the following<br />
week.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well, yes. I don't know whether I will make the<br />
statement or whether the Minister for Defence will. I<br />
haven't worked that one out but I'm hoping a statement<br />
will be makeable if that's the right word by the<br />
following week.<br />
QUESTION: Sir, there soems to be a su:; gestion from the United<br />
Nations that there has beon a change in the Australian<br />
Policy towards South Africa's racial laws. Formerly,<br />
when the matter was brought up, we voted on it<br />
against the resolution. This year we are abstaining.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well the reason for that was explained yesterday<br />
in the House at Question Time by the Acting Ministur.<br />
WJe have consistently opposed the United Nations intervention<br />
on the ground that this is a matter of domestic<br />
jurisdi ction.<br />
QUESTION: Has that been a policy hitherto or<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Oh, no. That's boen our policy for ten years,<br />
that it is a matter of domestic jurisdiction just as we<br />
would resist United Nations intervention in some discussion<br />
that we were having with Papua, or with people in<br />
it. I say that's domestic jurisdiction. We've never<br />
felt called upon to sit in judgment on actual policies<br />
pursued by the South African Government because we've<br />
said that matter doesn't arise with us, 1TT say the<br />
matter is a matter of domestic jurisdiction under the </p>
<p>7.<br />
Charter and therefore it ought not to be dealt with.<br />
This year our people felt that this point of view of<br />
the Australian Government, though it is completely<br />
logical and prudent from our point of view, was becoming<br />
a little misunderstood and was being interpreted in<br />
some countries as an approval by Australia of the actual<br />
policies being pursued by the Government of<br />
South Africa, and in order that that should not any<br />
longer be an inference from our voting against it, it<br />
was decided that Australia would abstain, having explained<br />
first, once morc, its belief that this is a<br />
matter of domestic jurisdiction and not cognizable by<br />
the United NL. tions. That is the whole of the story.<br />
QUESTION: A cable from London yesterday, Mr. Menzies, stated<br />
that Dame Pattie would launch the liner " Canberra" on<br />
March 1st and I was wondering whether this had any<br />
bearings on your plans for that time next year?<br />
PRIME MINISTER! No. I'll be here on March 1st. She is going over<br />
by herself, quite privately.<br />
QUESTION: Could you tell us, Sir, what Sir Gilos Chippindall t<br />
salary will be as the new Chairman of T. A. A?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I don't know. I suppose the same as the last one.<br />
Better ask Shane Paltridge. I don't know. W4hat does<br />
the Chairman get?<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTEF<br />
QUESTION:. PRIME MINISTEI I think he probably got œ C2,000.<br />
' doll, whatever it is.<br />
That doesn't compromise his Public Service Pension<br />
I presume, Sir?<br />
You don't suppose I've beon thinking about that do<br />
you? lle only made the appointment yesterday afternoon.<br />
O0 MWri. t h Hutgheh DCaosmhp, liments of<br />
Press Secretary to the Prime Minister. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
