<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>40774</transcript-id>
    <title>Remarks at the bilateral meeting with His Excellency Benjamin Netanyahu, Prime Minister of the State of Israel</title>
    <prime-minister>Turnbull, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20150915 - 20180824</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/02/2017</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
  <strong>PRIME MINISTER:</strong><br />
  Prime Minister, Lucy and I were  delighted to welcome you and Sara to Australia. Not your first visit, your  second, but your first as Prime Minister of Israel and the first visit by a  Prime Minister of Israel in office. We are delighted to have you here. </p>
<p>
  We have a lot to discuss. Our two  nations have so much shared history. From the charge of the Light Brigade of  Beersheba, 100 years ago – </p>
<p>
  <strong>PRIME MINISTER OF THE STATE OF  ISRAEL:</strong><br />
  On the dot. </p>
<p>
  <strong>PRIME MINISTER:</strong><br />
  Yeah, on the dot, almost on the dot.  To the foundation in 1947, Australia’s support, leading support for the Partition  Resolution. </p>
<p>
  So it is a long history and we are  working together on so many areas. We have so much to discuss. Security,  naturally, but also the way in which your nation leads by example with  innovation. </p>
<p>
  Israel’s ability to create a 21st  century economy of technology and innovation is the envy of the world. We have  a lot to discuss. We share your passion for innovation. We talked about it back  in 2004, remember?   </p>
<p>
  <strong>PRIME MINISTER OF THE STATE OF  ISRAEL:</strong><br />
  Absolutely.</p>
<p>
  <strong>PRIME MINISTER:</strong><br />
  When neither of us were Prime  Minister. So it is good to be back together. </p>
<p>
  <strong>PRIME MINISTER OF THE STATE OF  ISRAEL:</strong><br />
  Well, it turned out to have been a  productive conversation.</p>
<p>
  [Laughter]</p>
<p>
  <strong>PRIME MINISTER:</strong><br />
  It was! Clearly we laid the  groundwork for great things to come. </p>
<p>
  So welcome. </p>
<p>
  <strong>PRIME MINISTER OF THE STATE OF  ISRAEL:</strong><br />
  Thank you. Prime Minister, thank you  for this truly extraordinary reception. I have to say that we feel we are in  the friendliest country possible. I think this visit, this historic visit,  first time that an Israeli Prime Minister officially comes to Australia, marks  100 years of friendship. </p>
<p>
  You’ve been there at every key  junction of our history. In 1917, the liberation of the land from the Ottoman  rule, and the incredibly gallant and valiant charge, the last successful  cavalry charge in history. </p>
<p>
  <strong>PRIME MINISTER:</strong><br />
  Yes, the Light Horse. </p>
<p>
  <strong>PRIME MINISTER OF THE STATE OF  ISRAEL</strong><br />
  I want you, when you visit Beersheba  this year, you’ll see what happened to this quaint desert hamlet that has now  become a metropolis, and the cyber capital of Israel and soon I think there  will be [inaudible]. </p>
<p>
  Couldn’t have done it without  Australia’s contribution. The same, of course, was the tremendous courage of  the Australian troops in World War Two preventing the invasion of the eastern  part of the Middle East by Romell’s forces. We wouldn’t be here without that as  well.</p>
<p>
  Your very bold leadership in the  Partition Resolution that recognized the establishment of the Jewish State and  the subsequent conflicts, including in the Gulf War when we were receiving  information from Australian satellites against incoming missiles. That saved a  lot of Israeli lives.</p>
<p>
  So we’ve had a tremendous  partnership. But we’re looking not merely at the past, we’re looking at the  future. Seizing the future with innovation and [inaudible] Israel we’d like to  be here. I hope that this visit enables us to bring our friendship to much  higher levels in trade and technology, in security, in intelligence, in  cyber-defence, in agriculture. All the areas that I look forward to discussing  with you.</p>
<p>
  Most especially I want to say this  year, in Jerusalem and Beersheba, we await you with open arms. You’ll be  received with equal friendship by the Government of Israel and by the people of  Israel. </p>
<p>
  Thank you. </p>
<p>
  <strong>[ENDS]</strong> </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
