<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1707</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER OF LAOS, HIS HIGHNESS PRINCE SOUVANNA PHOUMA, AT A GOVERNMENT LUNCHEON, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA - 2ND NOVEMBER 1967</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/11/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001707.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Speech by the Prime Minister of Laos,<br />
His Highness Prince Souvanna oua<br />
at a Government Luncheon,<br />
Parliament House, Canberra. 2nd November, 1967.<br />
Ladics, Gentlemen, Mr. Prime Minister, I am touched to speak today<br />
before this gathering of people from the Australian Parliament<br />
people who have such a deep knowledge of international politics.<br />
I am really touchod by the praise which has been<br />
made by the Prime Minister and the Leader of the Opposition,<br />
Mr. Whitlam. All my actions in the present and the-past have<br />
been uniquely aimed at letting my country survive in its<br />
independence and its neutrality. As I have said on several<br />
occasions Laos has been at war for more than 20 years. As I<br />
have said before for Laos a greatly under-populated country,<br />
this is a great thing. We are three million inside and there<br />
are more than 16 million outside.<br />
All that is in the past; the present means to us<br />
that we have to make available more than half of our annual<br />
budget for our defence. That's why we have more than a hundred<br />
thousand Laotians under arms. </p>
<p>2-<br />
in the recent history of our relationship, this<br />
is the first time that a Laotian Prime Linister has paid a<br />
visit to your country. I feel this honour very deeply,<br />
and so does our nation. Therefore, ladies and gentlemen,<br />
the warm regards I addresj you in the name of my people are<br />
full of Zrat: itde and friendship.<br />
How could it be else? The relationship between<br />
our jovernoents is excellent. You know our difficulties, and<br />
as friends you. help us to solve them, taking as friends your<br />
share of our troubles. In Laos, Australia is rightly ! aro-, m as<br />
a dynamic, prosperous country, in a stage of full economic<br />
development. Ye are also pleased to low that today she has<br />
the feeling of belonging to that great entity of South East<br />
Asia, where changes, nutations ana dangers retain har<br />
attention particularly. In these conditions, the understanding<br />
and collaboration between our t, o countries are natural..<br />
But, in all truth, I have to say that in our exchanges your<br />
share is by far the =: ore important and generous.<br />
Howevei, Ladies and Gentlemnen, Laos does not find<br />
the same understanding everywhere. i. ant to speak of our<br />
' forgotten war, and of its consequences. ! any think that the<br />
situation is not so drastic that we axaZg rate our troubles.<br />
In fact we are tho victims of a certain literary romanticism.<br />
The country .,! here it is good to live, one calls our old<br />
kingdom a country w here time flows slowly, in a quiet and<br />
musical nonchalance. Maybe Laos was so, in some periods of<br />
our history, when we were not under attack by our neighbours.<br />
But for at least twenty-two years, it has not been so at all. </p>
<p>-3<br />
L.~ iesa~ d(~ nt~ meL.) allo7w. ime to illutstrate<br />
this period by so-me Gest'Gimony, fLor hose so-.; eti,, raes personal<br />
nature I as~ c youi e::, calse rie. -' Tht thiis test') imony belongs<br />
in effect -to -th-e history of our country, and therefore -to<br />
the his-tory of 3out-. h ZJ7ast Asia wh. iJch is niow. at sta'Le.<br />
Let u~ s -o bach to 1:* 45 Joan ended th-e status<br />
of the French Protectora. te, r stablis.* ed in La,? os f-or more<br />
tbhan-half a ce-ntury. e suddenly -faced orryi-n-ch-v. age<br />
and a n-reat void. Ho-.-. evor. tie Liao -i-, triots seized th'e<br />
-to recover thin dependence omd to reunifyr<br />
their country. s you lrno%-, Laos w-as artificially divided<br />
into twjo 1r. nteone hand, in th not he Kin-dom<br />
of Luzang ifrabemi-and its f rovince, w:, hore -the Court edthe<br />
IRoyal ministries are located,, on the other the rest of t'he<br />
countnj w: as under the administration of th Frnc gvenos<br />
.3o that the tro united int'o the indepnendernce<br />
move.-aent. the Lao issara (% hi'_ ch 7ree . J S CCoiLsiC, , 71y<br />
c r oat ed a Go va e: t DTheU --imemibers 7were. including :_ yiself and<br />
o t h er L. ao ' Fationalirsts, Frrice 1Fhotsarath : wi eider1 brother,<br />
ovur leader, axid Frne2ouu-Panouvoag, 2.: Y yoLUIIger brother, at<br />
present loader of" the 17co Lao ' Aaksat, a F--arty* of coi-im,, uist<br />
persuasion. Ti~ vr the rench ca.,, e back in strenth! in 1' q46.<br />
and -ie q! e re obliged to take rocfa-e in Thailmid .:, here w: e<br />
continued our struagl-e with alas, alotno mleans. Our only<br />
streng; th asour hepe, adthe ipossilmility of a reasonable<br />
solution at Gf3 hiands of our 1 or: mor coloniz-ers.<br />
.3~ hnaogdid not vic-. i -the eveats thL'e seine w. a y<br />
w--e did. Hie w.-as veyinfluenced by hIis 7Vietm-ih fIriends.<br />
-: loly hie fell co-mpletely be-neath tercontrol. Kesar their<br />
idea of a erciless.) arm--ed srgl. In fact th-e dis s emsion<br />
beca such that our Governmi; ent, i. eary of the servitu de accepted<br />
by ' ioLlphan,: Javong-decided to eust hi-m in na, 1r349. I i~ s destn<br />
washenefoth eald ie beca-i. 2 a creature of the iorth<br />
Vietnariese. </p>
<p>-4<br />
During that troub) lcd yre-r, '. ie h-d been t old<br />
th' at the French C-eve: nmu'm-it th L-LI , ing of' L rolitical<br />
chem~ i,, e 1for the-. foricr Protoctorate. T7ferelace . Jas matrde to<br />
special atooy. okoiectyvhtaas envio~ gd our<br />
Govern:. 2ort eat rae to ? ais Ivas notified Uf tile<br />
Frcnch proposals, iich beccuime the sL'bject of the Fraanco-Lao<br />
Treaty, sirmedJYn. 1aris in J 194g T2e contents of th~ at<br />
ireaty,. ex-ramined by our ' Iovernr_ ent -, Then I returned to Dmn-ijkok,~<br />
so ems d honouarabl.. ard acceptable in the e.-is tine:: Circtis to. Lc s.<br />
Our objcectives being ach-ieved-', th1e LA1O0<br />
movemient had n-, o ft: hrreason to exist. it ;, i-ac dissolved.<br />
~ ot o f it-U-s iiemib e rs r ot urn -d t o Ljao s. -" or rersonaal Loa. ors<br />
IPri :-ce 1 1citsarath stayed in ' hailmid. As for y brother<br />
SouT)! m' 2~ rCL! VO., y-, a s' 12-Ve to his convictions and to th1e<br />
organisation to ;-. hicli ' fe had adhered, ho 2resur-. Ied th1e frh<br />
a-ainst ud his countr<br />
4oweiver, -the follo;., in. yar in 15, a new and<br />
impot~ t olitical fact a--c-ared. TPw-o Pr3iltisof the<br />
Lao _ Issara oeetincluclilng m.-, yself , erc .: icmbo_ 7rs ofL the<br />
Royal I! to v.; rans indetc ide-d thU.' at Seineral ele ctionis<br />
should taker-p~ lacc in 1 ) 51. .; ere loy ally aj?.-lyin-t1.. e<br />
~ Dri~ lccof ocr l 1' beral deimocrc. cy, , h.' ich ao~ sall oT -inions.<br />
21bo vote bein.-favourable t'Uo our -party, tha<br />
Lao Cao ( v : hich1, ei h " 1ro-res , arty) I 1ra a'e<br />
lead th',' e 2' sv rnfeoitr ' Jou---_' anoulvo1n:, ad hi-s f_-riends,<br />
helpned by th-1e Viet., ainh, the. y kept)' U _ fir-! tin-tIL :!, rench and<br />
the Lao. 7, ti~ h eao our coanti'ry7 s_, riously r<br />
three years. In 10/ 53, Lu=. 2 I'rabmir, th2 % oyal cnd r: eliriols<br />
capital 1. Ias iyn danger. Thalkhel: in the south, seized bthe<br />
Victmi-nh. In Prance. at the sa~ no timec the volitical<br />
conce-tio-n of thec ' Fren-ch Union vas u-ndor-loin-a notable ch-an-e.<br />
The independence of the Associated 2ts Jas conceived on<br />
anoth., er basis. Timus, in 19,, 53, byr thel F_ r L co-L:_ o TratyFnc </p>
<p>decided to Ziv Laos complete inadcende-nce. This Treaty<br />
is notable for neveDr havmnr:' ! been tif. ied by the Dronch<br />
~ ar i ament -cause of its conflict vt' the rech<br />
Constitutio-i. 1i~ ovaer, so far as La os is concerne.,. d, o-l1<br />
the special lincs w.. ith rcaac disx-peared. Trd jnce<br />
vias complete, as co-cmplete as tLhe lmost infraz igont of our<br />
natijonalistUs could hope.<br />
HTow.-ever, av, n~ ts icre oving--to a criLsis. In 19' 4,<br />
the battle of Dien Dien Tuended f in-ally-the7 1In1dochina war.<br />
In Gaiieva, the bellic~ ren tUhaec ,, utris colcerned in<br />
this -trage,--: dY iut in confere~ c,, nce. 0 Lao, L _ Yd I -ooint<br />
it OLIt 15o i. 1, icato its servi tade -to the Victr-ainh, wa<br />
represented by iTorth Tiotnam, which con: Lfirmed what . we had<br />
alw-ys miaintaincd th. at, ' theiit it'Us ]_ 4orth1-Vicetrna.-e se Callies.<br />
thec Pathot -ao) ': Tould be nothing.<br />
Y ow i e 1e re o n th t h res hol1d o f i. eac. -HOvqTevcr, I<br />
could only conceive of ne. ace in TLaos on tnc-, baskr of national<br />
r ec o nc ili a t ion-. i. should not r~ taea ci* vil -iiar, for<br />
the -profit only of ozi er* srac2. rds; t-' e Vuturc olicy<br />
of our yrourn:, naion the , ilea of i~ itaiysec;', od to i-e -the<br />
best formula. C'ontuitly 1 tri,-. ed to bring, y comp triots<br />
Go acce. ct -this conce:,-t, heor; ct -Ti. several. ob-tacles.<br />
1evrth-oless~ , Li 10,57 e sacc Oeded -L. a creatlia.', a"<br />
Govermient of 1hatienal Union whi~ ich could kceep on oylly<br />
with the greatest1 difficulty. " Pie~ Covorm. en of th1-e U'nitoed<br />
! Dta te ofL . iaerica not inclinod to Inavour the -mersence<br />
of the Pat! hoit TLao inside thie Toyal Govornmerit. Pressulro<br />
reached the mt where I hrad to-, re: eign in-, 13 158, leavinfg a<br />
OitLuation Ghat detcrior,-: tcd ra-pidly, as+ a; s easy to forecast.<br />
In the event, after U-_-cular failures, th-Ie -w-ay<br />
I had so: nhad t'o be roer7ui., Ed. ILjx-, poriJc-1co provos riore am. d.<br />
maore that. for such a .? ra--ilc ~ igio:~ lyinj: whera it does<br />
bocause of roo:--ra7, hy ornd the, history of its porle, -the only<br />
w. ay. is the ado tion of a v: lol icy of strict neutralityT an.' d<br />
non-coi tMont. </p>
<p>6<br />
lh-arefore, in 19360, after thec tragic events<br />
that you -my remlemfbei-, I ca. P back: int-'. o rzowcr. lThc followiinrg<br />
year, a secon. d Conference as _ 1ieol Jn Genoeva, for the<br />
i-robleo of Lao2 alone. ' Lourtecn nations voere prosen'G.<br />
Finally in juily, 1962 the jtatut of " ou'rality for the<br />
Kingclom~ was agreed ai uaned by the. thirteen othor<br />
nations narticipoatin in th1e or-, ferencc.<br />
-were fuallyN satisfiod -v.-ith the Geneva A1ccords.<br />
eh o.-hat the ni-Jht-mare of? int-ornal subve: rsion anLd<br />
forei arerssion -, ae over. &gt; ialas, ou~ r people iwere<br />
,-rievously deceived. The,. 2Xcccrds v. rc i,.: uediately d<br />
shianelossly violateod. The Lao Hasat ( the political par'ty<br />
cruslied by the 1' athet uao after -the for: aation of -the<br />
Govcrnma-ent o' ' Thtional Uniuin in 1957, valet of theo H,-. noi<br />
Gov-. rn.:_ Icnt.. co-ntinucd its sabot-aL-c. -0-11 war., instead of<br />
sto--iinvg, ngrey) aore intonse. Today five years after the<br />
signaturc of the Gencva 1* ccorie, wie canr cow-it about 40,000<br />
_: orth Victnaiic soldiors On ou~ r territory. : hyarc fi-b. tirtc.<br />
besd5e, 00 9tht paid, trainocd mid encailred<br />
byT, o rth Vietnan. The devolopm.. e-n-1 of ouU conryi arlyzed.<br />
Thousaands of" refuvsecs strea;-i into thei Govern.. vaintal zones.<br />
UuandrcOs ofC vill.-c-a aLdeo iiod. Onlyv half of tho soil is<br />
cult-ivatLLed. ' The IHo--Ch-Iin trail b-oo-rie a-n actcive<br />
tra:-sit routo for 1 ort. h Viotnau_-es: e forces.<br />
This Tadios end Gentuile. on, is the real 1v-icturo of<br />
ou~ r country. It be admiltted tGhat it does n.. ot c; 7actly<br />
corres-.. ond with~ tho 1cturc :) ain-God byv -writers of a quie-t<br />
care-free country, pjreooc e d b2 festv1l and asc h<br />
acountry of three uillion inh) itants wit C US~. aeu<br />
thiis is thie : sroatest tc': d of its history<br />
LU, thec most dcrsi. aspect ' tGo th a'uh-t<br />
this vueeloss, blood, , tragedyr could not occurre If o<br />
i dcoo ci c al z: e dy-P ~ a-UJ 0 o s1-dh -; io ' U 00: 10 2d d intorfered<br />
directly indire., ctly ini our in-Genal affa-irs. 73y vatriight,<br />
i. hat i:; eral, do thei--tsuaco t~ e iji to liberat-e Lis? </p>
<p>Truly,: n are still subject -to the reijn_ 7 of<br />
force ir: rela-tionshlirs bet. ico:. nat-Jos. So rmh~ ch tIh0.-Iworse<br />
for the ;' orak. The deception of the o-rv1l 1 nations is growillclay<br />
by day,. 7-or ou~ r rtbitternaess is do-nor people,<br />
wh-o onlyv dociro, -pace and tr -Cl~ ciil it-, -the-re-, p-Zct of<br />
theiir front-iers anI&amp; o-f their sovercignty.<br />
Laldies and. C, ci tle:; icn, I zA~ s orry -to lhave been.-<br />
so long. for theo ouw'Usi. de 1 willl ropoat outr<br />
plraint wI-ith, out end, for.; t'o pU it brely thi role<br />
Of _ 00aCC MI-d .72. r conIcerns1 US all.<br />
IPinally, 1 iould lito say agan hat otir<br />
pcorile are apy tGo be able to coun-t oan solid, scin~ cre<br />
frienidshipli. c. th of AiSJtr7,' liG. I-se. ct for liborty,<br />
respect for are, solidarity betvien peoples, th'I'eso arc the<br />
"' 11i ' i ieS '-ie0 lik in vo u, fLo r thy arc o inc er a, r ien.-dly jand </p>
<p>-8<br />
We count on you and your assistance to help us<br />
survive. You must remember that Laos is in the vanguard of<br />
the free world, de are neutrals; we ojant friendly relations<br />
with all countries in spite of their philosophies and political<br />
systems. ie have our old religion, our monarchy, our traditionsd<br />
' vie want friendly relations with the socialist countries and all<br />
other countries but we don't want communism in our home.<br />
We hope to see perpetual peace in this world, and<br />
friendly co-existence become a reality between all nations.<br />
We want to see all men brothers in spite of their differences<br />
of ideologies and cultures and everything else. This is our<br />
most hopeful wish, and in this spirit I'd ask you, gentlemen,<br />
to drink with me to the health of your Prime Minister, Mr. Holt. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
