<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>19059</transcript-id>
    <title>$47 Million CRC Funding Secures Future Bushfire And Hazard Research</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/02/2013</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Canberra</p>
<p>The Gillard Government will make a substantial investment to establish a new Bushfire and Natural Hazards Cooperative Research Centre (CRC) from 1 July 2013.</p>
<p>This will build on the work of the existing Bushfire CRC and expand research efforts into other natural hazards.</p>
<p>The Government will contribute up to $47 million over eight years to ensure that the valuable work done by the Bushfire CRC can continue while developing a complementary natural hazards research program into flood, earthquake, cyclone and tsunami events.</p>
<p>The Commonwealth contribution is contingent on the states and territories making similar commitments to this expanded research activity, at a level equivalent to state financial support for the existing Bushfire CRC.</p>
<p>State and territory governments have been closely involved in the existing Bushfire CRC and we expect that they will be prepared to make a substantial contribution to this important initiative.</p>
<p>Communities across Australia have been severely impacted by bushfires, floods and severe weather events again this summer.  This increased investment in research will improve approaches to mitigation, operational responses and community resilience to natural hazards.</p>
<p>The expanded focus of the new CRC appropriately reflects the impact of broader natural hazards on the Australian community.  The new CRC will conduct coordinated and interdisciplinary research, including work with communities, to improve disaster resilience and reduce the human, social, economic and environmental costs from bushfires and other natural hazards.</p>
<p>The Bushfire and Natural Hazards CRC will undertake vital research to support the development of cohesive, evidence-based policies, strategies and tools to build a disaster-resilient Australia.  The funding will enable the CRC to provide a long-term research base that directly supports our emergency services as they work to prevent, prepare for, respond to and recover from natural disasters.</p>
<p>The structure of the new CRC will be determined in consultation with key stakeholders and participants, including the Bushfire CRC, the Australasian Fire and Emergency Service Authorities Council and state and territory governments.</p>
<p>The Gillard Government will also establish a priority public good funding stream within the CRC program to deliver primary research outcomes with wider social and environmental benefits to Australia and the broader community.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
