<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>17011</transcript-id>
    <title>Prime Minister Member for Solomon Territory employers sign up to Kickstart apprenticeships 22 January 2010 </title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/01/2010</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Prime Minister, Kevin Rudd, with Member for Solomon, Damian Hale, today urged Northern Territory businesses to take advantage of the great new incentives to hire apprentices.</p>
<p>In just over six weeks since the start of the Australian Government's $100 million Apprentice Kickstart initiative, 27 young people are now working in traditional trades in the Northern Territory.</p>
<p>Around Australia more than 6,400 apprentices have been employed since Kickstart began.</p>
<p>Apprentice Kickstart is a practical measure to generate jobs for young people, tackling both youth unemployment and providing a down-payment on the vital skills Australia needs for the future.</p>
<p>Under Kickstart, the Rudd Government has more than tripled the commencement bonus for employers in the first year, from $1500 to $4850.</p>
<p>Employers receive $2350 when they employ a 15- to 19-year-old apprentice in an eligible trade and then receive a further $2500 after the apprentice completes nine months.</p>
<p>The Kickstart bonus is available to employers of apprentices in the fields that have been hardest hit by skills shortages - identified on the National Skills Needs List. These include butchers, bakers, bricklayers, carpenters, plumbers, electrical trades and hairdressing.</p>
<p>The bonus is available until 28 February 2010 and aims to sign up 21,000 young apprentices.</p>
<p>Member for Solomon, Damian Hale said as an Australian apprentice of the year he learnt the value of applying himself to a trade.</p>
<p>"The Northern Territory economy needs young people and employers to meet the demand for a more skilled workforce and this Rudd Government initiative will assist them to do this," Mr Hale said.</p>
<p>"The economic downturn particularly hurt apprenticeships, with commencements dropping by about 10,000 in the past year, and this financial incentive for employers will help develop a highly-skilled workforce and is a great foundation to support the recovery of the Australian economy."</p>
<p>The Australian Government today also invites the NT Government to submit proposals for a share of $20 million in funding to boost pre-apprenticeships.</p>
<p>Pre-apprenticeship training allows young people to gain a more realistic expectation of the work involved in their trade and to develop basic skills, which can reduce the period of time they will spend in their apprenticeship. This bonus will fast-forward hiring decisions - to bring apprentice numbers back up to the levels before the global recession.</p>
<p>Increased apprenticeship training is crucial to enhancing the productivity and innovation of Australian businesses.</p>
<p>Funding for Apprentice Kickstart comes from the Government's $650 million Jobs Fund and was negotiated with the support of the Australian Greens and Senator Stephen Fielding.</p>
<p>It brings to about $250 million the level of additional support the Rudd Government is providing to apprentices.</p>
<p>More information on Apprentice Kickstart is available at <a href="http://www.australianapprenticeships.gov.au">www.australianapprenticeships.gov.au</a></p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
