<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>16343</transcript-id>
    <title>Australian Government support for North West Queensland floods    </title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/01/2009</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Acting Prime Minister Julia Gillard today expressed the Government's concern about those affected by the floods in North West Queensland and confirmed that the Australian Government will provide support to Queensland to assist in the relief effort.</p>
<p>Through the Natural Disaster Relief and Recovery Assistance (NDRRA) program the Government is currently providing assistance to 12 disaster-declared Queensland local government areas following monsoonal flooding in the state's North West.</p>
<p>The damage to local roads and public infrastructure is estimated to be $21.5 million though this is likely to increase. </p>
<p>The Australian Government will provide partial reimbursement to the Queensland Government for its expenditure on a range of natural disaster relief and recovery measures, including personal hardship and distress assistance (such as emergency food, clothing and accommodation) for those affected by the recent storms in North West Queensland. </p>
<p>The Australian Government will also reimburse between 50 and 75 per cent of eligible state expenditure on a range of other measures including restoration or replacement of essential public assets such as roads and schools.</p>
<p>The Australian Government works closely with state governments in times of disasters to support the delivery of assistance to affected communities.</p>
<p>For further information on assistance available for personal hardship, contact the Queensland Department of Communities on 1800 173 349.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
