<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>20686</transcript-id>
    <title>Television Interview with Ray Martin A Current Affair, Nine Network </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/05/2003</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>The PM joins us live now from Canberra. Prime Minister, thank you for your time.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Hello, Ray.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>Was that a good call? Do you think it was your biggest political mistake in the last seven years?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, mistakes and regrets are always in hindsight and are in retrospect. At the time I, of course, knew nothing about the things that subsequently emerged. He was a very impressive, servant of the underprivileged, he had a very good reputation. I'd known him for a long time and there was no suggestion to me, amongst the people I spoke to - admittedly it was a limited group - of anything of this kind. And it still has to be said in his defence, and although he made a big mistake, as it ultimately emerged in his earlier job, he's a person who's devoted his life to helping the underprivileged of Australia...</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>Yep, no question.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>And I don't think that should ever be forgotten.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>No question.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>And I think there's a tendency for that to be forgotten.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>You said today that Dr Hollingworth was not vetted for the job, you just repeated that. Wasn't there even a security check? I mean, we get security checks for everything these days.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, Dr Hollingworth was a very well-known public figure and I'm quite certain that if there had have been a security problem in relation to him, that would have emerged immediately after the announcement and before his appointment. And the fact that it didn't, indicated that there wasn't a security issue.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>But the Governor General is privy to to very sensitive information, he's privy to briefing...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yeah, I know that.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>... government papers, he's chairman of the executive council.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>But you appoint... yes... but hang on - once he was appointed to the job, he went through security procedures, once he's appointed to the job, they...</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>Well, why wait Prime Minister?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, you don't have a security check run when you announce somebody's going to be a Cabinet Minister. If something emerges, then that person's got a problem.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>But if you go through...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>You check...</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>If you go through an airport these days, you've got to take your shoes off. Wouldn't you check the bloke who's going to be the boss of the Armed Forces?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, when the person has... I mean, he's got to go through all sorts of security checks if he travels commercially - so do I, Ray - if I travel commercial...</p>
<p> MARTIN:</p>
<p>No, I meant for the job, Prime Minister.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>...I don't do it very often, I insist on it. Well, I didn't go through a security check before I became a minister way back in the 1970s...</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>So you could be a Russian spy, could you?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>When I... well, I doubt it, I doubt it. I'll trust my luck on that.</p>
<p> MARTIN:</p>
<p>Okay.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>But when I became a minister and I had access to certain information, I had to go through certain security procedures.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>All right. Today in pleading for a fair go for Dr Hollingworth - which I agree with - you said attitudes towards child abuse have changed in the last ten years. I don't think they have.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, no, no. The attitudes to the child abuse has not changed.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>Right, what's changed?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It's always been, I think, the way in which people in authority respond to it. There was a culture, a wrong culture mind you, but there was nonetheless a culture in the past, where people were, for example in churches, moved around. And it's not only in churches where this occurred. I think it's important to keep that in mind.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>But it's always been repugnant.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>... child abuse.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>We haven't changed that [inaudible] repugnant.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>And it's always been... but I haven't said that it was at one stage non-repugnant. What I said was the way in which people handled it when they were in positions of authority has changed - that's the point I was making.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>You spoke to him for an hour...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>There's no suggestion...</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>No.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>There's no suggestion that I ever regarded child abuse...</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>And I'm not suggesting that at all.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, no, than anything other than absolutely repugnant. I...</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>Did he apologise to you personally today? Did he apologise personally? You chose him, he embarrassed you, obviously?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, Ray, it was a very personal discussion, I'd rather not go into the details of it. He is obviously dispirited by what has occurred; he obviously feels that it's all across; it's gone very bad; he accepts that he had to go. I think it's fair to say that he made a judgement that he couldn't continue to command the support of the Australian people in the role and that if he continued, then that would damage the office. I think he put the office ahead of himself.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>Right.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>But I... you know, it's happened and I think we know have to move on...</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>All right, let's talk...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think we have to move on...</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>Let's talk about that, Prime Minister. Here's your big chance - you can tell us here tonight, you've got a forum, there you go. Who's the replacement?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I haven't decided yet.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>Have you got a short list?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I really haven't. Well, I've thought of a number of people and I've had a preliminary discussion with some of my senior colleagues.</p>
<p> MARTIN:</p>
<p>After all these years, will a woman get an equal opportunity at last?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I'm not going to talk in gender. You always appoint a suitable person.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>How do you get along with Tim Fischer these days?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh, I get on very well with Tim, but I also get on very well with a lot of other people who I better not name because they will go on your list.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>All right. Now, just the last question, quickly - will it be a quick decision or will you wait till your next birthday before you make a decision.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh, it'd be fairly... my next birthday?</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>Yeah, because a lot's hinging on your next birthday.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, no. I hope to see the Bledisloe Cup that night, that's... an Australian victory's hinging. Now, it'll be fairly quick decision, it's not something that...</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>A matter of days?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>... Sir Guy Green will continue.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>Days or weeks, PM?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh, no days is... you're looking at a number of weeks but not too many.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>All right. We thank you. Thanks for your time, very much.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Thanks, Ray.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
