<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18948</transcript-id>
    <title>Agreement For Full Roll Out Of National Disability Insurance Scheme In NSW By July 2018</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/12/2012</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Canberra</p>
<p>The Australian and New South Wales governments have today reached an historic agreement that will allow for the full roll out of a National Disability Insurance Scheme (NDIS) in New South Wales by July 2018.</p>
<p>The agreement will provide care and support to around 140,000 NSW residents with significant disability, and provide coverage in the event of disability to around one third of the Australian population.</p>
<p>It will provide peace of mind to people with a disability, their families and carers, and to the Australians who will unexpectedly face misfortune in the future.</p>
<p>It will give people with disability choice and control over the care and support they receive, rather than exposing them to the cruel lottery that currently exists, where care depends on a range of unpredictable factors.</p>
<p>Under the agreement reached today:</p>
<p> * 	The Commonwealth will provide funding of $3.32 billion in 2018  -  51.4 per cent of the funding needed. This will cover the administration of the scheme and contribute to the cost of individual care and support packages and other supports for people with disability, their carers and their families.<br />
 * 	New South Wales will provide more than $3.13 billion in 2018  -  48.6 per cent of the funding needed. This will contribute to the cost of individual packages and other supports for people with disability, their carers and their families.<br />
 * 	The full scheme costs will be reviewed by the Productivity Commission in 2018-19 to inform COAG agreement on final scheme funding arrangements.</p>
<p>Today's agreement builds on the agreement to launch in the Hunter region of NSW from the middle of next-year. Other eligible New South Wales residents will start entering the scheme in 2016, and by July 2018, all eligible residents will be covered by the NDIS.</p>
<p>The implementation of the NDIS in NSW provides a framework for a national scheme to be rolled out in all states and territories.</p>
<p>An NDIS will also be launched in South Australia, Tasmania, the Barwon region of Victoria and the ACT and final bi-lateral agreements for these launches will be considered at tomorrow's COAG meeting.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
