<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8902</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATIG, MP OFFICIAL DINNER HOSTED BY PRESIDENT KIM YOUNG-SAM CHONG WA DAE (THE BLUE HOUSE), SEOUL, 21 JUNE 1993</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/06/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008902.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
S. j_<br />
TEL: 21. Jun. 93 18: 44 No. 025 P. 01/ 10<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER# THE HON P J KEATING, NP<br />
OFFICIAL DINNER HOSTED BY PRESIDENT KIM YOUNG-SAM<br />
CHONG WA DAE ( THE BLUE HOUSE), SEOUL, 21 JUNE 1993<br />
( EMBARGOED UNTIL 8.00 PM KOREAN TIME, 21 JUNE 1993)<br />
I appreciate very much the warm welcome I have received<br />
on this my first visit to the Republic of Korea.<br />
Ours is a friendship of long standing which spans the<br />
turbulent history of the Western Pacific in this century.<br />
Our first contacts date from the arrival here around the<br />
turn of the century of Australian missionaries.<br />
in 1950, Australia was one of the 16 countries which sent<br />
military forces under the United Nations flag to assist<br />
the Republic of Korea in its bitter struggle against<br />
aggression.<br />
About 17,000 Australian soldiers, sailors and airmen<br />
served in the United Nations forces. Australians will<br />
always be proud of the service they gave.<br />
The loss of life and devastation caused by the Korean War<br />
was horrendous, and it has demanded of the Korean people<br />
great qualities of faith and endurance, not just to<br />
withstand he haydship end suffering, but to overcome it<br />
and build this mo~ dern Korean society.<br />
Australians who know Korea well admire Koreans' courage<br />
and resilience.<br />
They respect not only your recent achievements: they<br />
respect also your long struggle earlier this century to<br />
achieve independence and to reassert the rich tradition<br />
of your national heritage and culture.<br />
As one of the world's ol~ dest democracies, Australians<br />
also applaud the great achievement of the Korean people<br />
in establishing democratic political institutions.<br />
We congratulate you, Mr President, on your decisive win<br />
in last December's presidential election.<br />
My own Governmuent was returned in the Australian election<br />
which was held in March. </p>
<p>TE: 21. Jun. 9 3 18: 44 No. 025 P. 02/ 10<br />
2<br />
So like you, I know something of the excitement and<br />
challenge of the electoral process.<br />
Your election as the first civilian President in 35 years<br />
is itself a great step forward in the maturing of the<br />
Korean political system.<br />
We admire the vigour with which your new Administration<br />
has set about the task of stimulating and revitalising<br />
the economy.<br />
We are no less impressed by your campaign to strengthen<br />
democratic institutions and create in Korea honest and<br />
open government.<br />
Mr President, what I have seen in Seoul today helps me to<br />
understand In new ways the pride of your people in their<br />
achievements in economic development and nationbuilding.<br />
Korea ' s record of economic growth and dynamism over the<br />
last four decades has been truly impressive.<br />
We value greatly the partnership that we have forged with<br />
you in the course of your extraordinary economic advance.<br />
In 19921 AuStralia-Korea two-way trade was worth over<br />
five billion Australian dollars.<br />
The size of Australia-Korea trade and the interdependence<br />
it generates between key industries on each side give our<br />
economic relationship a strategic character which commits<br />
us to an enduring, long-term partnership.<br />
We are a reliable source of high quality and<br />
competitively priced mineral and energy commodities for<br />
Korean industry, and this is a role we take very<br />
seriously., i<br />
As well as expanding established areas of commerce, we<br />
are interested in widening and diversifying the base of<br />
our economic and business relationship.<br />
We also would like to see expanding air links to Support<br />
the growth of tourism, education and business travel in<br />
both directions.<br />
Increasing numbers of visitors in both directions,<br />
establishment of parallel cultural foundations, and<br />
efforts to promote the study of the Korean language in<br />
Australia will increase awareness of each other's society<br />
and culture.<br />
And that can only deepen our friendship.<br />
TEL: </p>
<p>-Tf E C: 21 . Jun .93 * 18: 4 A No .025 P d3/ 1Oi<br />
3<br />
Mr President, our strong and successful bilateral<br />
relationship also provides Australia and Korea with an<br />
opportunity to work together in helping nurture a<br />
stronger sense of community among the countries of the<br />
Asia-Pacific region.<br />
Australia arnd Korea share a fundamental interest in the<br />
maintenance of an open and non-discriminatory<br />
multilateral trading system.<br />
We also share a vital interest in encouraging economic<br />
cooperation in the Asia-Pacific region, and in having the<br />
countries of North America and the Western Pacific remain<br />
together within the some vibrant trading community.<br />
In 1989, our countries played decisive roles in helping<br />
launch the Asia-Pacific Economic Cooperation or APEC<br />
process which is now showing such promise as a vehicle<br />
for promoting open economic regionalism in the Pacific<br />
area. I have been encouraged by the strong support given by the<br />
Korean Government to the proposal I made last year to<br />
establish a process of periodic meetings of APEC leaders.<br />
interest in this proposal is now gathering momentum.<br />
If realised, it will add status and authority to APEC and<br />
ensure that it becomes the pre-eminent vehicle for<br />
advancing economic cooperation and trade liberalisation<br />
in the Asia-Pacific region.<br />
The economic dynamism of the Republic of Korea and other<br />
East Asian countries provides a very positive outlook for<br />
our region.<br />
But to achieve this great promise it will be important<br />
that our efforts towards economic institution-building<br />
through APEC are complemented by appropriate attention to<br />
regional abcurittr.<br />
Australia recognises continuing uncertainty in the<br />
security situation on the Korean Peninsula.<br />
More widely in the region, a general trend towards a more<br />
favourable security outlook is tempered by increased<br />
fluidity in strategic affairs.<br />
Maintaining in good order the bilateral alliances that<br />
Australia, the Republic of Korea and Japan each have with<br />
the United States Is therefore very important.<br />
In addition, both our countries welcome the increasing<br />
support throughout the region for processes of security<br />
dialogue. </p>
<p>TEL: 21. Jun. 93 18: 44 No. 025 P. 04/ 10<br />
4<br />
Mr President, as I explained in our talks today,<br />
Australia is now embarked on a sustained effort to make<br />
our economy more competitive, more open and better placed<br />
to take full advantage of economic dynamism in East Asia.<br />
For Australia, the economic imperative of integrating<br />
more closely with Asia coincides well with the regional<br />
focus of our diplomatic and security policy.<br />
The Asia-Pacific region is where Australia must work out<br />
its destiny: the changes we have made and are continuing<br />
to make, to our economy and to our business and<br />
industrial culture, have been expressly geared to this.<br />
These efforts are now finding expression in an<br />
Increasingly confident and independent view of<br />
Australia's national Identity, and a broad debate about<br />
the institutional forms and symbols of our nationhood<br />
reflects this.<br />
As we strive to transform our economy and engage Asia<br />
more closely, we value all the more the relationship we<br />
enjoy with the Republic of Korea.<br />
Based on trust and friendship and a congruence of<br />
economic and regional interests, our relationship with<br />
you can only advance and prosper.<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen,<br />
I should be glad if you would join me in a reciprocal<br />
toast to the good health of President and Mrs Kim<br />
to the success and prosperity of the Republic<br />
of Korea, and<br />
to Australia-Korea friendship. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
