<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11150</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                   THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                   RADIO INTERVIEW WITH RAY HADLEY                 THE JOHN LAWS PROGRAMME, RADIO 2UE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/01/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE....................................................................................................</p>
<p>HADLEY:</p>
<p>We've got a very special and a surprise guest in the studio,</p>
<p> the Prime Minister, Mr John Howard, good morning to you.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Good morning, Ray, very nice to be here.</p>
<p>HADLEY:</p>
<p>It is a surprise. Thank you very much. I'm sorry I'm not</p>
<p> responding in coat and tie but I didn't know you were coming.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>You look terrific. I don't think your head's all that bad</p>
<p> either.</p>
<p>HADLEY:</p>
<p>Well, compared with some others it may not be. How was the break?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Terrific, the best holiday I've had in about 20 years and the</p>
<p> longest one. I played a lot of golf. It hasn't improved all that</p>
<p> much but it has improved a bit. I watched a lot of cricket, read a</p>
<p> lot of books including Tom Wolf's latest book, A Man In</p>
<p> Full', which was a great read, the whole 750 pages of it and</p>
<p> had a very good holiday. And I'm happy now to be back. There's</p>
<p> a lot to be done but I think it was good to get right away from it.</p>
<p> I think the Australian public likes a break from politics over Christmas</p>
<p> and the New Year and sport was on the front pages, not always in a</p>
<p> positive way but it was certainly on the front pages and I think that's</p>
<p> good and I think that's what Australians want.</p>
<p>HADLEY:</p>
<p>Does it sometimes get a bit frustrating when you're on holidays</p>
<p> and Tim Fischer's looking after the shop for you that maybe you</p>
<p> think, gee I'd like to have a crack at something about this but</p>
<p> you're...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, no, not this time. I have every confidence in Tim and I even got</p>
<p> to the stage where a couple of nights I didn't mind whether or</p>
<p> not I saw the news on television. I really switched right off and</p>
<p> I think that's good and I'm now back with a vengeance.</p>
<p>HADLEY:</p>
<p>We can see that. There's been some criticism, I think it's</p>
<p> ill-founded, this morning about this attack on the young people </p>
<p> and I say attack in the true sense of the word, attacking the problem,</p>
<p> not the people  literacy and numeracy. You've offered in</p>
<p> the past opportunities for these young people to go back and learn</p>
<p> a bit more. That hasn't come to fruition so now you're basically</p>
<p> saying you have to or we're going to take some money off you.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yeah, that's what we're saying. And it's a very, very</p>
<p> fair principle. We say to people who can't get a job, we're</p>
<p> prepared to provide you with a safety net, provide you with the unemployment</p>
<p> benefit. We're not prepared to allow people to...we don't</p>
<p> want to see people starve on the streets, that's not the Australian</p>
<p> way. But we're saying to people that if we give you help and</p>
<p> support you when you don't have a job, in return, if you're</p>
<p> able to do so, you should do something to help yourself. And clearly,</p>
<p> in the modern age, if you can't read or write properly it's</p>
<p> very hard, indeed, to hold down a job. It was always difficult but</p>
<p> it's even harder now because there are fewer manual jobs and</p>
<p> we are far more a knowledge based, communications based society. And</p>
<p> far more of the jobs require more communication and knowledge, therefore,</p>
<p> if you don't have those basic skills, you can't get to first</p>
<p> base. And what we're saying to people is, if that is your situation</p>
<p> then we're going to require you to do a remedial course as a</p>
<p> condition of getting the unemployment benefit. We're not saying</p>
<p> to you that you've got to pass that course with flying colours.</p>
<p> We're not saying to you that, yeah, you've got to be some</p>
<p> kind of literacy or numeracy genious. What we're saying is that</p>
<p> if you've got a clear problem and you've failed basic tests</p>
<p> then you've got to do a remedial course. Now, what's unfair</p>
<p> about that? I think it's elementary, absolutely elementary. It's</p>
<p> a question of we help you if you will help yourself, we will help</p>
<p> you if you give something back in return. I don't think that's</p>
<p> unfair.</p>
<p>HADLEY:</p>
<p>The critics say the problem extends back to the fact that many young</p>
<p> people come out of the education system not knowing how to read and</p>
<p> write.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>That could well...that is clearly the case. And in some instances</p>
<p> it's the fault of the system, in some instances it's not.</p>
<p> But it doesn't alter the fact that they come out in that condition</p>
<p> and that condition prevents them getting a job and society is saying</p>
<p> to them we want you to get a job, the first step to getting a job</p>
<p> is to get basic skills so we're going to require you to undertake</p>
<p> a course in return for the unemployment benefit. Irrespective of what</p>
<p> the cause is, addressing the problem is still the same. It's</p>
<p> still got to be dealt with. You've still got to try and give</p>
<p> to people who don't have basic skills a capacity to read and</p>
<p> write. Now, it is an appalling problem and I feel desperately sorry</p>
<p> for people who can't read and write properly and there are many</p>
<p> mature-age people, there are many people in their 40s, 50s, 60s and</p>
<p> 70s in our society that are in that situation. Now, with the older</p>
<p> age groups they went through a time when perhaps it wasn't quite</p>
<p> the inhibition that it is now. But whether it was or it wasn't</p>
<p> is, in a sense, beside the point. We're dealing with a current</p>
<p> day problem and that current day problem is quite real. And all we're</p>
<p> saying is, we'll help you if you help yourself.</p>
<p>HADLEY:</p>
<p>Just away from that. These secret Treasury documents we read about</p>
<p> today claim the GST won't create one job, in direct opposition</p>
<p> to what you were told.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, no, no, they don't say that. What they say is that they didn't</p>
<p> do a calculation of the job impact. They didn't model the employment</p>
<p> impact. They don't say they won't create jobs, they just</p>
<p> say that they didn't do any calculation on that. Now, that's</p>
<p> not contrary to anything that's been said. We never represented</p>
<p> it, they did. But Treasury did give evidence yesterday saying that</p>
<p> they thought the employment impact of the package would be positive</p>
<p> but they just didn't try and quantify.</p>
<p>HADLEY:</p>
<p>At the end of the sausage machine, which is this inquiry, I mean,</p>
<p> are you going to have any more luck with the Upper House in trying</p>
<p> to push it through?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, we'll find out. But I just go back once again to the basics</p>
<p>  we took this plan to the Australian people. They voted us back</p>
<p> despite all the opposition to which we were subjected and all the</p>
<p> criticism and all the fear campaigns and we won the election. And</p>
<p> what we're saying is, can we please now implement what the Australian</p>
<p> people voted for.</p>
<p>HADLEY:</p>
<p>I've been talking about this in New South Wales about the need</p>
<p> for a house of review, an upper house, and the amount of money that's</p>
<p> wasted on it. Do we need a house of review when you have the mandate</p>
<p> to govern? I mean, do we need someone looking over your shoulder?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, whether we do or we don't  and I still support having</p>
<p> a Senate, obviously  we've got it and it's part of</p>
<p> the Constitution. We can't abolish it, even if we wanted to and</p>
<p> we don't. Do we need it? I think you do need a second chamber</p>
<p> but I think you need a second chamber that respects the will of the</p>
<p> people. If the second chamber adopted the attitude that it will pass</p>
<p> anything that has been put at an election in a very clear and open</p>
<p> and comprehensive way and the public's voted for it  different</p>
<p> matter if we hadn't said anything about taxation reform at the</p>
<p> last election and we were now putting up, I think the Senate would</p>
<p> have a perfect right to blow the whistle and say, look, you fellows</p>
<p> didn't tell the public about this so we're not going to</p>
<p> support it - but we did tell the public about it. We laid it out painful,</p>
<p> complete detail and the public voted for us, we're entitled to</p>
<p> get it through.</p>
<p>HADLEY:</p>
<p>Well, most people thought you'd lose the election based on a</p>
<p> GST.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, they did, a lot of people did. I mean, an enormous number of</p>
<p> people said to me, you're mad, you're crazy, you shouldn't</p>
<p> be doing it, if you didn't mention the GST you'd cruise</p>
<p> back. Well, we did mention it because I believe in it and there's</p>
<p> no point in being in government unless you're willing to do things</p>
<p> that you believe in and which you regard as important to the future</p>
<p> of the country.</p>
<p>HADLEY:</p>
<p>The other issue that seems to be rather divisive is this republic</p>
<p> debate. And I keep getting open-line calls about it, as John does,</p>
<p> right throughout the year and I simply say to the people, look, there's</p>
<p> no point you and I discussing it here and me arguing with you about</p>
<p> what I think and what you think, some time later this year we'll</p>
<p> all make a decision.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>That's right. Well, that's my view. I mean, I don't</p>
<p> support a republic. I've said that and I said that in '96</p>
<p> and I said it in '98. A lot of people disagree with me, a lot</p>
<p> of people agree with me but I'm not going to try and force my</p>
<p> view down your throat or the throat of your listeners. I think the</p>
<p> present system is about the best you can devise. Other people have</p>
<p> different views. We are going to have a vote. I said we'd have</p>
<p> a convention and we had it. I said that I'd put to the Australian</p>
<p> people what came out of the convention and that is exactly what I'm</p>
<p> doing. I'm not trying to pull the wool over anybody's eyes</p>
<p> but I don't want to get heavily involved in the debate. If somebody</p>
<p> asks me my view, I will give it. The public know where I stand on</p>
<p> it. But I'm not trying to ram John Howard's view down anybody's</p>
<p> throat. I really don't want to get involved in a day-to-day basis.</p>
<p> I am allowing a free vote inside the Liberal Party. I've said</p>
<p> to my Liberal Party colleagues, you have different views  there's</p>
<p> nothing wrong with that on an issue like this. I think it's a</p>
<p> mark of maturity that a political party in government can allow a</p>
<p> free vote amongst its members. That's not a mark of weakness,</p>
<p> it's a mark of maturity. The debate will be conducted in a civilised</p>
<p> fashion and at the end of the day we'll all have a vote. And</p>
<p> if the vote is yes', well I will preside over the transition</p>
<p> to a republic. If the vote is no', well, it will be off</p>
<p> the agenda for a while. It will obviously, if people want it to, come</p>
<p> back in the future. It's a free country. What else can I do?</p>
<p> I mean, I said I'd have a convention and I had it. I said I'd</p>
<p> put what came out of the convention  and the clear majority</p>
<p> of people voted for the model that's being put at the end of</p>
<p> the year. They didn't vote for the direct election model. And</p>
<p> I'm putting it. Now, it will either win or lose. Now, if it loses</p>
<p> it could well be, some years into the future, the issue will come</p>
<p> back. I don't know.</p>
<p>HADLEY:</p>
<p>I'm glad you used the word maturity' because there</p>
<p> was a lot made when you were playing golf and reading books, about</p>
<p> a couple of your colleagues going at each other about this. I think</p>
<p> it's very healthy. [Inaudible]...basically the same views</p>
<p> about it.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, it's one of those...politics, modern politics is not</p>
<p> so straight-jacketed and blinkered and ideological that you can't</p>
<p> have a genuine difference of view on something like this within the</p>
<p> same party. Now, I would reckon, I mean they will never admit, but</p>
<p> I'd reckon that there are people in the Labor Party who don't</p>
<p> agree with the republic. But because the view in the Labor Party is</p>
<p> so overwhelmingly republican, they're sort of a bit scared, you</p>
<p> know they probably feel a bit intimidated. Now I don't want that</p>
<p> in the Liberal Party. There are people who I respect in the Liberal</p>
<p> Party who disagree with me on this. So what? Providing things be done</p>
<p> in civilised manner which it will be, and there are no personal changes</p>
<p> and people just put their point of view. I think the public appreciates</p>
<p> that. They see it as a breath of fresh air. They see it as a departure</p>
<p> from rigid party doctrine. I mean there's no way that I could....you</p>
<p> could ask some people in the Liberal Party who have strong views on</p>
<p> this to sort of toe the line with the majority view, or equally it</p>
<p> would be quite unreasonable to ask people who hold strong views in</p>
<p> favour of the status quo to toe some other line. They're going</p>
<p> to have a free vote but it's not the most important issue, it</p>
<p> really isn't. The great bulk of Australians do not talk about</p>
<p> this issue very much. I've had virtually nobody raise it with</p>
<p> me, they just don't.</p>
<p>HADLEY:</p>
<p>Away to some other issues that maybe are dear to my heart and are</p>
<p> dear to your heart as a sports loving Australian, the Olympic bidding</p>
<p> process. Without specific reference I guess to Sydney, but there's</p>
<p> been mail for years that this has been a tainted process and now we're</p>
<p> finding out it is. Four have resigned and probably more will go. Is</p>
<p> there something that people like you in authority can do to try and</p>
<p> [inaudible]?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Somebody in my position is....on the one hand, I respect the fact</p>
<p> that sports administrators have got a job to do and the worst thing</p>
<p> in the world is, for a sports administrator, to have his or her decisions</p>
<p> being double guessed by a Prime Minister or a senior politician who</p>
<p> happens to be interested in the sport. As everybody knows I'm</p>
<p> a great lover of cricket, I'm also a great lover of rugby league</p>
<p> and a whole lot of other things, sport. But if I was sort of giving</p>
<p> a running commentary every time that a decision was taken on something</p>
<p> or other it would be quite wrong and unfair. So I try not to do that.</p>
<p> But the Olympic bribery scandal is sort of something of a one-off.</p>
<p> The dimension of it is so huge. I think there is...in the minds</p>
<p> of some people, it comes as no great surprise. I don't think</p>
<p> there's any doubt about that. I think there is something of an</p>
<p> excessive imperial grandeur about some aspects of the international</p>
<p> Olympic movement and I think that's been brought down to earth.</p>
<p> And I think in the long run that will be a very healthy thing. I went</p>
<p> to an Australia Day ceremony in my own electorate in Ryde and the</p>
<p> ambassador was Shane Gould. And she made a lovely speech and she talked</p>
<p> about the aristocracy of international Olympic administration and</p>
<p> I thought she put it very nicely. And I thought to myself, it carries</p>
<p> so much more weight coming from an Olympic gold medallist. I mean</p>
<p> they're the people who should really be speaking for us on these</p>
<p> issues and they're the people who in the long run have a lot...as</p>
<p> much to loose as anybody else. But I have to say in defence of the</p>
<p> Sydney bid - and I was not involved in any way myself because I was</p>
<p> in Opposition, federally, when it was taking place, but I know a lot</p>
<p> of the people who were involved - I don't think on the evidence</p>
<p> available you could say in its purist sense there was any bribery</p>
<p> involved in what I've heard. I mean bribery is personal enrichment</p>
<p> isn't it, to change your mind. Now sure there was some extremely</p>
<p> zealous lobbying and perhaps that became excessive. But I hope it</p>
<p> doesn't take community and corporate support for the games. I</p>
<p> want to get behind it as Prime Minister. I want to work with the government</p>
<p> of New South Wales, of whichever political persuasion it will be after</p>
<p> the next election, to make them a success. And so far the evidence</p>
<p> is that the preparations for the games have been extremely good, very</p>
<p> good indeed and I congratulate those associated with them.</p>
<p>HADLEY:</p>
<p>Without wishing to embarrass you, you come into this radio station</p>
<p> regularly to talk to John Laws and Alan Jones and other people, I'm</p>
<p> in here doing sport, we pass each other in the corridor: What's</p>
<p> doing, Ray?', Prime Minister good morning, how are the</p>
<p> Dragons going?', - we have a yarn about different things, how's</p>
<p> the golf. And it's just a normal conversation with a bloke you'd</p>
<p> have at any stage. The fact that you're Prime Minister, a certain</p>
<p> amount of dignity goes with the position. But when Juan Antonio came</p>
<p> here, I'm informed I've got to call him Your Excellency</p>
<p> and there's a bit of bowing and there is that sense of theatre</p>
<p> and royalty attached to the IOC which it shouldn't be there.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well of course it shouldn't be and I think that's sort of</p>
<p> being cut down to size. Australians don't like that. Australians</p>
<p> are innately courteous people but they are innately unpretentious</p>
<p> people and I just think people should be treated courteously and respectfully</p>
<p> but you treat people on their merits. If you've got a job to</p>
<p> do, you do it. It's not been an easy time and I feel for all</p>
<p> of those thousands of people throughout Australia who devote their</p>
<p> weekends without any king of reward to keeping sport going. I mean</p>
<p> we've all sort of done it at various stages in our lives as parents</p>
<p> and you get in and become an official of the local cricket or soccer</p>
<p> club or something or other. I mean this is what really keeps sport</p>
<p> going in this country.</p>
<p>HADLEY:</p>
<p>The mums that wash the jumpers, the dads that mark the line.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Absolutely right. Absolutely. And that's what it's all about.</p>
<p> And they have a certain ethos and a certain spirit. Some of them get</p>
<p> very spirited. Overall it sort of keeps sport going in this country</p>
<p> and it's their sort of expectations about what's right and</p>
<p> what's wrong and the expectation of their kids about what's</p>
<p> right and what is wrong in sport that really matters most to me. Now</p>
<p> that applies whether it's the Olympic Games or whether it's</p>
<p> international cricket, or rugby league, or AFL, it doesn't really</p>
<p> matter.</p>
<p>HADLEY:</p>
<p>A couple of quick ones: should Mark Taylor go to the West Indies?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>That's a matter for him. He put the issue back into play. All</p>
<p> I can say is he has been a fabulous captain. He's a great choice</p>
<p> as Australian of the Year. And whatever decision he makes I think</p>
<p> all of Australia will accept. But he really has been a wonderful captain</p>
<p> and his shoes will be very difficult indeed to fill.</p>
<p>HADLEY:</p>
<p>As a rugby league supporter of the St George Club with one red and</p>
<p> one white eye, have you embraced yet the St George-Illawarra joint</p>
<p> venture?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh yes, yes. Even to the extent of having an across the party divide</p>
<p> discussion with Stephen Martin who's the Labor Member for Cunningham</p>
<p> and therefore an Illawarra man. It was inevitable that mergers of</p>
<p> that type would take. It seems to have gone ahead pretty well, and</p>
<p> I think there's been some give and take on both sides. Certainly</p>
<p> the St George identity is still very, very strongly maintained but</p>
<p> there's a proper respect for Illawarra. I hope that I can get</p>
<p> to one of their early games this year, I really do.</p>
<p>HADLEY:</p>
<p>Now on the final thing, much was made of your golf game during your</p>
<p> holiday. Judging by the pictures there's a lot of work to do.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yeah, there is a lot of work, Ray.</p>
<p>HADLEY:</p>
<p>But there's an open invitation for you to join the continuous</p>
<p> call team and Channel 9's Ray Warren. We think that you are an</p>
<p> able candidate for our group of golfers. Firstly you can accept sledging</p>
<p> having been in Parliament and Question Time for a long, long time</p>
<p> now. So no matter what [inaudible] on the back swing you'll still</p>
<p> complete the stroke or on the putting surface. And you are about our</p>
<p> standard which would suit you better because I know you don't</p>
<p> bet but you could make an exception for us and we could get some money</p>
<p> off you.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>You could. You probably would.</p>
<p>HADLEY:</p>
<p>Which would be something to brag about for a long, long time </p>
<p> the day we beat the Prime Minister.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
