<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2209</transcript-id>
    <title>CROWN OF THORNS STARFISH - MINISTERIAL STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR JOHN GORTON</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/04/1970</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002209.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
E M B A R G 0: Not for publication, broadcastigor telecasting<br />
before 9 p . Tuesdy 7 April 197<br />
FOR PRESS: P. M. No 48/ 1970<br />
CROWN OF THORNS STARFISH<br />
Ministerial Statement by the Frime Minister, Mr. John Gorton<br />
Honourable Members will be aware that the Commonwealth<br />
and Queensland have agreed to establish a joint Committee to investigate<br />
the problem of the Crown of Thorns starfish.<br />
The Committee will be supported on a $ 1 for $ 1 basis by<br />
each government. It will report to each government.<br />
On behalf of the Premier of Queensland and myself I am<br />
pleased to be able to announce to the House that the Committee will comprise<br />
the following experts:-<br />
COMMONWEALTH NOMINEES<br />
Professor R. J. Walsh, Professor of Human Genetics at the<br />
University of New South Wales ( Chairman).<br />
Professor W. G. H. Maxwell, Associate Professor of Geology<br />
at the University of Sydney.<br />
Mr. D. J. Tranter M. Sc. Senior Research Scientist, Divis ion<br />
of Fisheries and Oceanography, C. S. 1. R. 0.<br />
QUEENSLANDNOMINEES Dr. j. M. Harvey, Director-General of Primary Industries.<br />
Professor J. M. Thompson, Professor of Zoology at the<br />
Queensland University. Mr. C. L. Harris of the Department of Primary Industries.<br />
I have asked that the joint Committee meet as soon as is<br />
practicable in view of the urgency of the situation.<br />
CA NBERRA<br />
7 April 1970 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
