<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6540</transcript-id>
    <title>GOVERNMENT&#039;S REPONSE TO FINAL REPORT OF ROYAL COMMISSION INTO THE ACTIVITIES OF THE FEDERATED SHIP PAINTERS AND DOCKERS UNION</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/11/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006540.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
GOVERNMENT'S RESPONSE TO FINAL REPORT OF ROYAL<br />
COMMISSION INTO THE ACTIVITIES OF THE FEDERATED SHIP<br />
PAINTERS AND DOCKERS UJNION<br />
Release of Final Report<br />
The Government is releasing Volumes 1 to 5 of the<br />
Costigan Commission Final Report. This is in accordance<br />
with the strong recommendation of the Royal Commissioner<br />
( at paragraph 1.025 of Volume 1 of the Report). The<br />
Government is also releasing an appendix volume<br />
containing Appendices 1A, lB and IC, which list the<br />
public witnesses, their representatives and public<br />
exhibits. There are another six substantive volumes which<br />
Mr Costigan recommended, and the Government accepted,<br />
should remain confidential. Mr Costigan has said ( at<br />
paragraph 1.024 of Volume 1) that he made such<br />
recommendations in some cases because persons are on<br />
trial and in other cases because hig~ hly sensitive<br />
current investigations could be impeded, if not<br />
destroyed, by disclosure. ( In addition, some appendix<br />
volumes have not been published because of similar<br />
concerns, because of the need to protect the security of<br />
the systems passed to the NCA or because they contain<br />
material published elsewhere).<br />
Within three of the five -substantive volumes published,<br />
certain deletions have been made identified by blank<br />
spaces in certain parts of those volumes. As I had<br />
informed the Parliament would occur, these deletions<br />
were based on the advice of the Government's legal and<br />
law enforcement advisers. The Victorian Government and<br />
its advisers were also involved in this process and the<br />
deletions were brought to Mr Costigan's attention.<br />
Agreement was reached between the Commonwealth and<br />
Victorian Governments that certain limited deletions<br />
should be made. In Volume certain names of<br />
individuals and companies have been deleted on the </p>
<p>strong advice of the Commonwealth and Victorian<br />
Directors of Public Prosecutions in order to avoid<br />
prejudice to certain current and imminent prosecution<br />
proceedings. only 12 pages are affected pp 86-91,<br />
100-101, 104-106, 113. In Volume 3, certain material at<br />
pages 31-33 which might have identified 4n individual<br />
has been deleted on the strong advice of the Victorian<br />
Director of Public Prosecutions to avoid prejudice to a<br />
current prosecution. In Volume 5, certain material<br />
( pages 29-72) about the activities of a drug trafficker<br />
which, if revealed, might impede investigations has been<br />
deleted on the strong advice of the National Crime<br />
Authority. My assurance to the Parliament that the decisions on<br />
what would or would not be tabled or published would in<br />
no way be affected by political considerations has<br />
accordingly been completely honoured.<br />
Just three days after my Government received the Final<br />
Report, I made available a complete copy to the Leader<br />
of the Opposition ( with the exception of 3 appendices<br />
containing highly sensitive and technical material<br />
relating to the Commission's computer systE! m<br />
Mr Peacock is aware that only a very restricted number<br />
of copies of this sensitive material was presented to<br />
the Commonwealth by the Commission). Mr Peacock has<br />
assured me that the confidential material wrill be<br />
completely protected.<br />
The release of the final report of the Costigan<br />
Commission puts to rest the irrational claims and<br />
behaviour of the opposition on the crime issue.<br />
Firstly, it sinks without trace the charge made by the<br />
opposition Leader on 3 October 1984, that:<br />
11 We are going into an election campaign<br />
without Mr Hawke allowing the Australian people to<br />
know what is in the Costigan Report Australia<br />
is entitled to know the extent to which this<br />
sophisticated network of organised crime is taking<br />
over this country. And yet the Prime Minister is<br />
not going Co allow that to occur This man<br />
is trying to walk away from telling Australians<br />
just what the extent of the threat is."<br />
Secondly, it buries the claim that in any way this<br />
Government had something to fear from the Costigan<br />
Commission Report as I said on 20 September: </p>
<p>" The Government has no reason to believe that the<br />
Costigan Commission's investigations will reflect<br />
adversely on it."<br />
That judgment has been vindicated by both the Report and<br />
the Royal Commissioner himself.<br />
Finally, after muted threats to leak material properly<br />
deleted from the Report, as I have noted above, the<br />
Opposition Leader has conceded that the deletions are<br />
appropriate. Yet again the Opposition Leader has been revealed as one<br />
who is prepared to make the wildest allegations without<br />
any foundation in fact. This will further confirm the<br />
judgment of the Australian people as' to his unfitness<br />
for the office to which he aspires.<br />
Overview of Final Report<br />
Mr Costigan's Final Report, both in its published and<br />
unpublished volumes, represents his important overview<br />
of the state of organised crime in Australia. It<br />
confirms the picture sketched by Mr Costigan in his five<br />
interim reports, of widespread white-col. lar criminal<br />
activities involving tax offences, offenices against<br />
company law, drug importations and many oth ' ers, as well<br />
as substantial linkages to blue-collar criminal<br />
activity. It renders all the more important the Labor<br />
Government's unequivocal commitment to total support for<br />
a sustained fight without fear or favour against<br />
organised crime.<br />
The remarkable evolution of the Costigan Royal<br />
Commission, as it pursued the labyrinth of organised<br />
crime, began from the Painters and Dockers Union. In<br />
Volume 3 of his Final Report, Mr Costigan concludes that<br />
union employees have engaged in manifold criminal<br />
activities including tax fraud, social security fraud,<br />
ghosting, compensation fraud, theft on a grand scale,<br />
extortion, the importation of drugs, the shipment of<br />
armaments and all manner of violence.<br />
By the end of its evolution, the Costigan Commission had<br />
also made a significant contribution, so confirming the<br />
results of previous major inquiries of the past decade,<br />
to the exposure of the role of organised crime in drug<br />
trafficking. Thus certain of the unpublished<br />
confidential volumes relate to unfinished inquiries into<br />
drug-related matters. Mr Costigan also refers to having<br />
monitored, during the last two years, various drug<br />
offenders, and in the course of this action, having<br />
uncovered a range of further criminal activities.<br />
Arrests and prosecutions have resulted from information </p>
<p>obtained analysed and disseminated by his Commission;<br />
joint action by drug enforcement and taxation<br />
authorities has been encouraged. A number of unfinished<br />
drug-related investigations have been referred to the<br />
National'Crime Authority; these are now under active<br />
consideration.<br />
My decision to request the Royal Commissioner in April<br />
1983 to concentrate his further investigations on drug<br />
trafficking has been amply vindicated it is, as<br />
Mr Costigan puts it, a " particularly nauseating"' area of<br />
crime. Exposure of tax frauds and related tax evasion ~ Schemes<br />
has undoubtedly been a major achievement of the Costigan<br />
Commission, as witnessed by its disclosure of the bottom<br />
of the harbour schemes and the substantial number of<br />
consequential prosecutions by Special Prosecutor<br />
Redlich. At July 1983 tax assessments of $ 25m had<br />
issued as a direct result of the Commission's<br />
activities, a figure Mr Costigan believes has increased<br />
significantly during the last 15 months. Mr Costigan<br />
refers to Special Prosecutor Gyles' identification of<br />
6206 companies involved in bottom of the harbour schemes<br />
and revenue collection which has netted the Government<br />
$ 333m, with $ 257m remaining to be collected. The<br />
enduring impact of the Costigan Commission on<br />
investigation, prosecution and recovery acti6n in<br />
relation to tax fraud in Australia is thus indisputable.<br />
A reading of the Final Report discloses that the<br />
Costigan Royal Commission has consciously sought and<br />
developed a high degree of co-operation with law<br />
enforcement agencies throughout Australia. It<br />
deliberately focussed on major targets within its terms<br />
of reference and adopted a practice of referring lesser<br />
matters for example, social security and workers'<br />
compensation frauds to relevant agencies. Amendment<br />
to the Royal Commissions Act was sought and granted to<br />
enable dissemination ( otherwise than through formal<br />
reports) of information to law enforcement agencies; in<br />
addition to convictions ilready obtained, numerous<br />
investigations and prosecutions by agencies thro. ighout<br />
Australia are continuing as a result.<br />
Mr Costigan also adopted the practice of referring major<br />
matters to other bodies for the final investigative<br />
processes leading to arrest, charge and prosecutions.<br />
Creation of the Special Prosecutor's office was in<br />
recognition of, and assisted in, this practice; the<br />
creation by this Government of the office of Director of<br />
Public Prosecutions has enabled the effective<br />
continuation of the practice. </p>
<p>Acknowledgement of the Costigan Commission's unique<br />
development of investigative techniques in relation to<br />
organised crime is particularly warranted. The<br />
Commission has concentrated both on documentary evidence<br />
in seeking to follow the paper trail and upon the<br />
development of sophisticated computer information<br />
management systems; and has done so in two major areas:<br />
the accrual of criminal wealth, as traced through the<br />
financial system, and the manifestation of criminal<br />
organisation as demonstrated through the association of<br />
individuals. The capacity to do so was greatly enhanced<br />
by the more than doubling of the financial resources of<br />
the Commission under this Government, and the<br />
substantial increase in its staff. The bulk of the<br />
Commission's staff, skilled in these ' investigatory<br />
techniques and the technology upon which they vitally<br />
depend, has been transferred to the NCA, which now<br />
carries the baton of this Government's commitment to the<br />
fight against organised crime.<br />
Comments on National Crime Authority ( NCA)<br />
Not surprisingly, Mr Costigan's report includes many<br />
references to the National Crime Authority ( NCA).<br />
Chapter 9 of Volume 1 deals with the transfer from the<br />
Royal Commission to the NCA; in various sections,<br />
Mr Costigan points to what he considers to be<br />
inadequacies in the National Crime Authority'<br />
legislation; finally the NCA features in the<br />
recommendations: one change to the NCA plus a number of<br />
matters to be investigated further by the Authority.<br />
Thus, despite the opposition's criticisms of recent<br />
times, Mr Costigan has only made one explicit<br />
recommendation for change to the NCA legislation.<br />
Transition Mr Costigan devotes Chapter 9 of Volume 1 to the<br />
transition to the NCA. It is mainly an historical<br />
account, drawing heavily on correspondence between<br />
himself and the present and former Governments, much of<br />
which has already been tabled.<br />
Mr Costigan raises two specific concerns regarding the<br />
transition: the possible prejudice to future investigations by<br />
the publication of the summaries in the National<br />
Times a concern shared by the NCA and this<br />
Government; and<br />
. the lack of time to conduct briefings. </p>
<p>Much has already been said on this latter point. As<br />
noted in the report, Senior Counsel was able to give<br />
some briefings in the Commission's last days.<br />
Mr Costigan draws a parallel to the time taken by<br />
Special Prosecutor Redlich and Gyles and the Director of<br />
Public Prosecutions, Mr Temby, to fully understand the<br />
Commission's operatiohs. There is one great,<br />
overwhelming difference the NCA has absorbed almost<br />
all of the Commission's staff, fully versed in the<br />
Commission's operating techniques, computer system,<br />
extensive data base and outstanding investigations. It<br />
has thus assimilated the accumulated knowledge of the<br />
Costigan Royal Commission.<br />
Mr Costigan also refers to a " substantial", but<br />
inevitable, hiatus in continuing his operations. The<br />
Government does not accept that there has been a<br />
substantial delay. The Authority wasted no time in<br />
resolving on 18 July to investigate the Commission's<br />
outstanding investigations. Given the important<br />
objective of the Authority subsuming the Commission's<br />
staff, it was not able, of course, to become! fully<br />
operational until the Commission staff had completed<br />
their work on the final report. That has now happended<br />
and the Authority is up and running, with fully trained<br />
staff and an extensive computer system.<br />
Importantly, the report in no way criticises, the NCA for<br />
its part in the transition. Indeed, it notE-s that only<br />
one day after receiving the Commission's summaries of<br />
outstanding investigations, the Authority resolved to<br />
investigate these matters and requested access to all<br />
documents held by the Commission.<br />
Legislative Criticisms<br />
Mr Costigan's criticisms of the Authority's statutory<br />
framework fall into three main areas:<br />
the need for the Authority to seek specific<br />
references;<br />
* insufficient access to taxation records; and<br />
* inability of the NCA to expose an individual's<br />
involvement in criminal activities.<br />
Mr Costigan urges removal of the requirement in the NCA<br />
Act for references to be given by the Ministerial<br />
Committee to the Authority before the Authority can<br />
exercise coercive powers as to a specified subject<br />
matter of inquiry. He assumes that the references to be<br />
given by Governments to the Authority will go into such<br />
detail that, if they become public, reputations of </p>
<p>persons referred to will suffer.<br />
The security of such information is, of course, very<br />
important. The Government, however, is not convinced<br />
that appropriate procedures and safeguards oral<br />
briefings in the most sensitive of cases) cannot be set<br />
in place. In fact, I-have already written to the<br />
Special Minister of State, who is the Chairman of the<br />
Inter-Governmental Committee, requesting that he take up<br />
these matters with the NCA to ensure appropriate<br />
security and that briefing arrangements are put in<br />
place. In considering the form of the references to be given to<br />
the NCA there is not only the concern referred to by<br />
Mr Costigan that references might identify persons to<br />
the prejudice of their reputations, but the further<br />
concern lest references be expressed so broadly that<br />
they impose no effective limit on the area of a special<br />
enquiry by the Authority.<br />
However, in the drafting of the first references given<br />
by the Commonwealth Minister to the NCA on 19 October<br />
1984, deliberate care was taken to ensure that both<br />
concerns were met. Thus, the two referEnces did not<br />
identify individuals and, by referring in the references<br />
to additional information furnished to the Minister,<br />
reasonably clear limits were placed on the Authority's<br />
areas of inquiry.<br />
It must be emphasised that the Authority may undertake a<br />
general investigation within its very broad statutory<br />
charter without a reference, and it is only when it<br />
requires to exercise coercive powers that a reference is<br />
needed.<br />
For the Government to allow the Authority to exercise<br />
these special coercive powers otherwise than under a<br />
reference of a specified subject matter of inquiry would<br />
be an abdication of the Government's proper<br />
responsibility and the great majority of the community<br />
would, I am sure, be gr~ atly concerned if restraints on<br />
the exercise of the special powers were removed.<br />
Mr Costigan expresses disappointment that the NCA will<br />
not have the same access to taxation records as he has<br />
had. The NCA does, of course, have access to taxation<br />
information. In relation to tax-related investigations<br />
the Commissioner of Taxation may pass information direct<br />
to the NCA. In other cases, the Authority must first<br />
obtain a warrant from a Federal Court Judge. This is<br />
considered an appropriate balance between the need to<br />
protect individual privacy and to allow the NCA acess to<br />
relevant information. The Opposition did not oppose or </p>
<p>move to amend this when the legislation was debated.<br />
Mr Costigan considers it a weakness in the NCA's armoury<br />
that it does not have the power to hold public hearings<br />
and to report upon identities. He considers it a<br />
particular handicap in the fight against drug<br />
trafficking, and indeed to overcome this, proposes a<br />
Taxation Investigation Tribunal and a new Royal<br />
Commission to investigate a particular matter.<br />
The importance of public exposure as a deterrent is one<br />
of the central themes of the Commission's final report.<br />
Mr Costigan acknowledges, however, that this very<br />
fundamental issue was fully considered by the Senate<br />
Select Committee to which both Mr Costigan and his<br />
Senior Counsel gave evidence and indeed by the<br />
Government in developing the legislation. Public<br />
hearings and reports were, however, specifically<br />
rejected, primarily on the ground that a person's<br />
reputation should not, as a general rule, be prejudiced<br />
or put at risk unless and until he or she becomes<br />
subject to the ordinary process of the criminal or civil<br />
law. This is a quite legitimate difference of opinion<br />
about the best way to tackle organised crime.<br />
This raises important issues which ought to be re-stated<br />
here. There has been considerable debate as to what<br />
model the Government ought to adopt in establishing a<br />
permanent body to lead the fight against organised crime<br />
and to follow up the important start made by the<br />
Costigan Commission. As instanced earlier, views differ<br />
on almost all points.<br />
Mr Justice Stewart's comment on 26 September, however,<br />
is very pertinent. He said:<br />
function of a Royal Commission is completely<br />
different to the function of a National Crime Authority.<br />
The function of a Royal Commission is completely<br />
different to the function of a National Crime Authority.<br />
The function of a Royal Commission is to identify areas<br />
of crime, to point in the right direction. A Royal<br />
Commission is not a body that seeks to accumulate hard<br />
evidence and Mr Costigan has already indicated that he<br />
hasn't seen ihis task as that, he hasn't want~ ed to do<br />
it, he hasn't tried to do it But the function of<br />
the NCA accumulating hard evidence is quite a different<br />
function<br />
The Government and the members of the Authority are<br />
confident that the Crime Authority has the appropriate<br />
powers and resources to do the job. It has a mix of<br />
powers specifically designed for the task powers which<br />
in some areas go beyond those of a Royal Commission. it </p>
<p>has taken over almost all of the resources of the<br />
Costigan Royal Commission staff trained in the<br />
Commission's investigative techniques all of the<br />
information collected, and the Commissioner's computer<br />
system and extensive data base. Furthermore, all<br />
Australian Governments have advised of their support for<br />
and co-operation with-the NCA.<br />
The Government has also made it clear that should<br />
members of the Crime Authority form the view that they<br />
require an extension of their power, then it will*<br />
respond quickly and sympathetically to any such request.<br />
The Government is not alone in believing the Authority<br />
can meet the challenge ahead.<br />
Previous recommendations<br />
In Volume I of his Final Report, Commissioner Costigan<br />
lists recommendations contained in his Interim Reports<br />
3, 4 and 5. ( Interim Reports 3 and 4 were presented to<br />
the previous Government; Interim Report 5 was presented<br />
to the Labor Government in July 1983). Additionally,' Mr<br />
Costigan adverts to his understanding about what action<br />
the Government has or has not taken on them.<br />
Prior to the announcement of the election, decisions had<br />
been taken or action was in train, in respect of all of<br />
Mr Costigan ' s recommendations emanating from Interim<br />
Reports 3, 4 and<br />
Mr Costigan's recommendationq concerning amendments to<br />
the Income Tax Assessment Act, contained in his Tnteri"-<br />
Report 3, were incorporated in amendments to the Income<br />
Tax Assessment Act passed in 1982. Subsequently, this<br />
Government passed the NCA ( Consequential Amendment) Act<br />
1984 which enables Royal Commissions to pass taxation<br />
information they have received to the NCA.<br />
In respect of Mr Costigan's recommendations concerning<br />
the establishment of a Special Task Force to investigate<br />
and prosecute criminal afid civil cases contained in<br />
Interim Report 4, Special Prosecutors Redlich and Gyles<br />
were appointed. -Their work will now be carried on by<br />
the Director of Public Prosecutions Office created by<br />
this Government. </p>
<p>In respect of Mr Costigan's recommendation in Interim<br />
Report 5, that attention be paid to an appropriate<br />
degree of co-operation between the Office of the<br />
Director of Public Prosecutions and State prosecution<br />
agencies, Mr Temby has indicated that he is conscious of<br />
the need to bring about co-operation between his office<br />
and State authorities'and he is taking steps to that<br />
end. In respect of Mr Costigan's recommendations in Interim<br />
Report 5, concerning exchange controls, they were<br />
significantly affected by the Government's new foreign<br />
exchange arrangements, a point acknowledged by Mr<br />
Costigan in Volume I of his Final Report.'<br />
In respect of Mr Costigan's recommendations in Interim<br />
Report 5 concerning corporation controls, the Government<br />
has endorsed the Ministerial Council's decision of 16<br />
December 1983 to approve in principle the desirability<br />
of achieving a national information system on<br />
shareholdings. This should substantially meet the<br />
objectives of Mr Costigan's proposals.<br />
In respect of Mr Costigan's recommendations in Interim<br />
Report 5 concerning mining reserves, the Government has<br />
agreed that the Petroleum ( Submerged Lands) Act be<br />
amended to clarify and strengthen provisions relating to<br />
the approval and registration of agreements between<br />
parties holding or acquiring interests in petroleum<br />
titles. The recommendations on Mining and Petroleum<br />
have been brought to the attention of State and Northern<br />
Territory Ministers, and the Minister for Resources and<br />
Energy had been undertaking consultation with his State<br />
and Territory colleagues on proposed amendments to the<br />
Petroleum ( Submerged Lands) Act.<br />
In respect of Mr Costigan's remaining recommendations in<br />
Interim Reports 4 and 5, concerning amendments to<br />
Section 16 of the Income Tax Assessment Act, tax<br />
controls, banking controls, and overseas arrangements,<br />
extensive consultation has taken place on these farreaching<br />
recommendations. In each area, firm proposals<br />
had been prepared which can be considered after the<br />
election.<br />
Mr Costigan's Final Recommendations<br />
Mr Cost igan's principal recommendations are summarised<br />
in Chaper 10 of Volume 1 of his report.<br />
Mr Costigan makes a number of recommendations relating<br />
to the strengthening of existing legislation or new<br />
legislation for the fight against organised crime in<br />
Australia. Some of these also involve State </p>
<p>Governments, with whom the Federal Government will need<br />
to work closely in considering the recommendations.<br />
These include, for example, proposals for new agencies<br />
such as the Port Security Authority, Taxation<br />
Investigation Tribunal and Taxation Investigation<br />
Office. In its formal response to these recommendations, the<br />
Federal Government will also wish to have the detailed<br />
advice of the NCA, the Commonwealth DPP and the AFP,<br />
they now have independent statutory responsibility for<br />
the investigation and prosecution of offences against<br />
Commonwealth law. As the Government has consistently<br />
made clear, it will respond quickly and sympathetically<br />
if it should be evident that their existing powers are<br />
inhibiting these organisations in the f * ight against<br />
organised crime. Any formal changes to their existing<br />
powers would, of course, be a matter for decision after<br />
the caretaker period.<br />
Mr Costigan makes a number of recommendations regarding<br />
ongoing investigations and prosecutions. The full report<br />
is now in the hands of the NCA, the Commonwealth DPP and<br />
AFP and under their statutory powers they do not need<br />
any formal direction from the Federal Government to<br />
proceed with the gathering of admissible evidence or<br />
prosecutions if they judge such courses to be<br />
appropriate in the light of the report. However, should<br />
the Government receive any recommendations requiring<br />
immediate action from these bodies during the caretaker<br />
period, such action will be immediately taken by the<br />
Government. As to recommedations concerning the setting up of<br />
investigations outside the framework of the NCA the<br />
Commonwealth DPP, and the AFP, the Federal Government<br />
takes the view in principle that the NCA, the<br />
Commonwealth DPP and the AFP are the bodies to which the<br />
Federal Government, with the support of the States in<br />
the case of the NCA, has entrusted the leading role in<br />
the fight against organi -zed crime in Australia. it is<br />
not only logical but essential that the Government<br />
should give them ' full support in that fight. Formal<br />
decisions on these recommendations should, of course,<br />
properly wait until the end of the caretaker period.<br />
Ongoing Investigations/ Prosecutions<br />
Apart from ongoing investigations/ prosecutions referred<br />
to in the Final Report ( including the Confidential<br />
volumes), Mr Costigan's staff were also attending to a<br />
number of ongoing inquiries. The Commission also passed<br />
to the NCA a number of completed or wel. l advanced<br />
analyses of investigations into drug-relIated matters. </p>
<p>These current investigations and prosecutions are now<br />
the subject of action by the NCA, the Commonwealth and<br />
Victorian DPPs, and the AFP. Mr Costigan's<br />
investigations have therefore been continued in none<br />
have the trails gone cold.<br />
Moreover, the resources of the Costigan Royal Commission<br />
have now been transferred to the NCA: the Commission's<br />
computer database and system; the analyses prepared by<br />
the staff of the Commission: the material contained in<br />
reports of the Commission, including the full,<br />
unexpurgated final report; one of the Commission's<br />
junior counsel; most of the solicitors who have been<br />
engaged in conducting Mr Costigan's operations; and<br />
accountants, analysts, collators and other staff who<br />
have been involved in Mr Costigan ' s operations. There<br />
can be no doubt that, as Special Prosecutor Redlich said<br />
at page 48 of his recent report, " the Authority has the<br />
scope to maintain the initiatives developed by the<br />
Costigan Royal Commission"<br />
Mr Costigan has recommended that the activit~ ies and<br />
affairs of certain persons mentioned in the confidential<br />
volumes be closely monitored and investigated by all<br />
relevant law enforcement agencies including the NCA, the<br />
Australian Taxation Office, Australian Customs Service,<br />
corporate affairs offices, bankruptcy offices arid law<br />
enforcement agencies in the United States. It will fall<br />
to the incoming Government to address these matters and<br />
to give such further directions as may be considered<br />
necessary. Civil Liberties Issues<br />
Some of the material in the published Volume! s posed<br />
difficulties for the Government because of the<br />
Government's strong commitment to civil liberties. This<br />
material relates to the naming of certain individuals.<br />
Mr Costigan argues at some length that exposure of<br />
suspected criminal activities by public reports of Royal<br />
Commissions and like bodies before conviction of the<br />
persons concerned and, indeed, even in circumstances<br />
where conviction-is unlikely, is a proper and effective<br />
means of dealing with those activities. on this basis<br />
Mr Costigan has named a considerable number of persons<br />
as suspected of committing offences or being in some way<br />
involved in the commission of offences.<br />
The Government strongly believes that such a course is<br />
normally neither correct in principle nor effective in<br />
final result. It believes that persons should not be<br />
named in public reports as having committed, or as being<br />
suspected of having committed, offences unless duly </p>
<p>convicted in the courts of law. To do so would make a<br />
mockery of the rule of law, of the long-standing<br />
presumption of innocence before conviction and of<br />
protections that should be afforded by the law to every<br />
citizen. In the circumstances surrounding this Report, however,<br />
the Government believes it has no alternative to<br />
deciding that deletions should be confined to those made<br />
on narrow legal and law enforcement grounds which I have<br />
described. With considerable reluctance the Government<br />
has decided that no deletions should be made because of<br />
the civil liberties considerations mentioned above, many<br />
of which are almost certainly applicable. This decision<br />
has been taken for two primary reasons:<br />
given the nature and structure of Mr Costigan' s<br />
Report, it would not be practical to delete all<br />
references to persons named as being involved in the<br />
commission of offences to delete all such<br />
references would make the Report, to a large extent,<br />
meaningless; and<br />
there has been a high degree of public expectation in<br />
relation to this Report resulting from the breaches<br />
of confidentiality that have occurred by publication<br />
of material in the National Times, arnd the cheap and<br />
dishonest political posturing by the opposition that<br />
the Government had something to hide. The<br />
substantial deletion of names would therefore be<br />
likely to lead to community concern and<br />
misunderstanding.<br />
For the reasons stated the Government's profoundly<br />
regrets the course of action that has been necessary in<br />
this instance, and it is important to note that the<br />
National Crime Authority Act makes provision to ensure<br />
that this cannot happen in the case of the NCA. The<br />
Government does not believe that naming of persons in<br />
public reports is an effective or appropriate<br />
alternative to the processes and sanctions of the law of<br />
the land.<br />
Conclusions Finally I should like to extend, on behalf of all<br />
concerned Australians, our sincere appreciation for the<br />
application and dedication with which Mr Costigan and<br />
his staff have approached the important tasks they were<br />
given by successive Governments, tasks which expanded<br />
from limited objectives into the investigation and<br />
exposure of organised crime.<br />
There have, as Mr Costigan acknowledges, been frank and </p>
<p>robust differences of view, from time to time, between<br />
his Commission and both my Government and the former<br />
Government. As I have earlier noted these have been<br />
legitimate differences of opinion about the best way to<br />
tackle organised crime. But, as Mr Costigan records,<br />
there has never been any doubt that the Government was<br />
anxious to maintain the attack on organised crime.<br />
Under the auspices of the NCA and relevant agencies and<br />
with undoubted community support, the Government as<br />
Mr Costigan acknowledges will continue to take all<br />
action to stamp out organised crime.<br />
1 November 1984 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
