<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1579</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. HAROLD HOLT IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES 18TH MAY 1967 - &quot;VOYAGER&quot; ENQUIRY</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/05/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001579.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT.<br />
HON. HAROLD HOLT IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES<br />
18TH MAY, 1967 b<br />
a-2 2MAY 1967<br />
" VOYAGER" ENQUIRY RAf'<br />
I told the House last night at the conclusion of what I had to<br />
say on the " Voyager" matter that the Government would be taking the<br />
opportunity this morning to consult with members of the Government parties<br />
on the course that it could recommend to the Parliament, and I am now in a<br />
position to indicate the course that we believe should be followed.<br />
My colleagues and I have considered the various possibilities<br />
that are open to us. Vie have considered, among other questions, whether an<br />
inquiry should be conduct-ed by a select committee of this Parliament. I think<br />
most honourable gentlemen will have concluded that, having regard to the<br />
involvement of so many members in the debate and the quality and content of<br />
the debate., this would not be the most suitable tribunal to consider a matter<br />
of this sori. There is room for a vi ew that the matter, having been<br />
thoroughly debated here and all aspects that honourable members could see<br />
as being relevant having been canvassed, little useful purpose would be<br />
served by a committee of the Parliament conducting a further inquiry. The<br />
Government has considered that view, but it believes that, though the detail of<br />
these discussions has been well known to us and perhaps to those who have<br />
carefully read all that has appeared in the Press, there will be many members<br />
of the public who will be left with a feeling that more should be done to<br />
. s atisfy th ei r minds regarding the matters in dispute.<br />
So the Government has concluded that there should be a further<br />
inquiry and that it should be a judicial inquiry conducted probably by three<br />
judges. I have not yet the precise terms of reference which later we will be<br />
putting to the House, and I ask that I be not held strictly to what I now say as to<br />
the substance of matters which the Government thinks should be covered by such<br />
an inquiry. Clearly, it should be directed to the allegations made against<br />
Captain Stevens and the questions arising from them that is, whether he was<br />
incompetent to command the " Voyager", whether his command of that ship<br />
left him open to criticism, whether the allegations have sufficient substance<br />
for these matters to have been known or whether they should have been known<br />
to superior naval officers who would then have been in a position to deal<br />
appropriately with him, and whether they should have dealt with him according<br />
to the evidence in their possession. The question arises also as to whether<br />
any evidence was improperly withheld from the Royal Commission, and if so,<br />
whether that would have substantially affected his findings.<br />
I have not attempted to put what I have said in strict legal<br />
parlance. It is the substance of what we believe should be considered by<br />
such an inquiry. Our own view is that there is no need for a second " Voyager"<br />
inquiry in the full sense of the one that was conducted before. I believe that<br />
the public generally is satisfied that there was a competently conducted<br />
inquiry which has covered most of the matters in issue at that time. But<br />
this is a special area which has been the subject of debate in this Parliament,<br />
and the Government thinks that the issues and the allegations can be<br />
satisfactorily resolved only by an inquiry conducted on the lines that I have<br />
proposed. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
