<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9051</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON. P J KEATING MP BOEING FACTORY, SEATTLE USA, SUNDAY 21 NOVEMBER, 1993</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/11/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009051.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON. P J<br />
KEATING, M. P.,<br />
BOEING . FACTORY, SEATTLE, U. S. A.<br />
SUNDAY 21 NOVEMBER, 1993 . m<br />
4o. h;<br />
E OE PROOF COPY<br />
J: Prime Minister, why did you decide to come to the Boeing factory?<br />
PM: Well, we do a lot with them commercially. ASTA, which is the Ausmtlian<br />
Government's aerospace organisation, has just won the international supplier<br />
award for Boeing. We supply the rudder assemblies, for rudders for 737s and<br />
other elements for other aircraft So, in a very internaionally competitive<br />
environment like this, to end up as supplier of the year is one hell of a feather in<br />
Australia's cap. So, it was my pleasant duty to be associated with that award and<br />
to talk to Boeing about the future of ASTA in the event that we privatise it<br />
J: Is there much chance that we'd get more work for Australia from the Boeing<br />
factory?<br />
PM: Well, the good thing is we're getting the work now, not as part of the old offsets<br />
program that is, if we buy a Boeing aircraft it is mandatory that we make some<br />
of the bits we get it now, purely commercially. We're winning commercial<br />
contracts to supply major components to Boeing against the rest of the world. So,<br />
it's a really good basis for doing things.<br />
J: Prime Minister, Boeing has an interest in tendering for the refurbishment of the<br />
P3 Orions and also for the supply of the AWACs aircraft. Given that the defence<br />
budget took a big cut in August would you say that either of those two programs<br />
are threatenend and were you able to tell Boeing anything about that today?<br />
PM: We discussed both of those. There's another development of the AWACs<br />
program which Australia is going to wait for, we're not going to be picking at a </p>
<p>ftaditr, conventional technology. In other words, a 707 with a dish on the top.<br />
We're not buying any of those. I think we'll wait for the later development. But,<br />
on the P3, well, this is our maritim surveillance capability and Boeing is going to<br />
be part of a group tendering for the refurbishment program, but that program will<br />
go ahead.<br />
J: Can you guarantee the AWACs will go ahead, based on the 767 airframe?<br />
PM: No. And I don% think it ever will go on a 767 airframe. We'll go for... thars only<br />
for a very conventional technology which we are not interested in. We want to go<br />
to the next generation AWACs technology which doesn't require a very big<br />
aeroplane to carry it around.<br />
J: Did you discuss a VIP plane for yourself?<br />
PM: No. Like all good salesmen they said, " We've got everything on offer, including<br />
those," and I said, " Thank you, no, no, we're happy with one of your earlier<br />
models."<br />
J: In ters of Boeing's chances for the P3 Orion you say they're just one of the<br />
firms tendering offers there? And in terms of AWACs there doesn't seem to be<br />
any commitment for either of those programs on Australias part<br />
PM: Are you a Boeing rep' are you?<br />
1: No, no I'm from the local media in Seattle.<br />
PM: Well, I suppose that's one and the same around here, right?<br />
J: inaudible.. Australia's going to spend some money here.<br />
PM: Well, we're always spending money here. No, I think the P3 program will go<br />
ahead and Boeing will probably become part of the consortium for the<br />
redevelopment of our P3 capability. But on the AWACs, we're going for the next<br />
generation of technology which lets us out of these very big airframes.<br />
J: Do you say the 767, then, is not suitable, in terms<br />
PM: We won't need it. It will just go in a much smaller, fuel efficient aircraft.<br />
J: Prime Minister, Dr Mahathir says he is not sorry that he didn't come to Seattle.<br />
He says if you snub your nose at people they take more notice of you. Is he a lost<br />
cause for APEC? </p>
<p>PM: Look, I don't know and I don't care. I'm sick of asking questions about Dr<br />
Mahathir. Everyone bad a chance to come here if he didn't come, that's his<br />
business. The thing about it was, it was just a very historic meeting. Just<br />
remember this: we war sitting there with the leaders of half the world's<br />
production. China's sitting there even though it has great diplomatic problems<br />
wih the Unted Staes whmthe U. S. has putan embrgoon ms alearmt<br />
of China's activity; where President Soeharto, who reprzmt the non-alignd<br />
movement in Indonesia, was sitting there. I mean, it wus a most historic gathering<br />
and everyone who was there felt the sense of history of it But, I think the other<br />
great thing about it was, it was a meeting of leaders without officials. The leaders<br />
there were making their interventions and moaking their suggestions without notes<br />
from officials and without winiks and nods. And, it had a tremendous freshness<br />
and vitality about it. And, to put together an organisation like this. for the Asia.<br />
Pacific area, will enhance economic developments in the* Asha-Pacific very<br />
rapidly, I believe, compared to that which would otherwise happen. And, it will<br />
also just, naturally, produce a good strategic envirnment, a better strategic<br />
environment because these leaders know each other and are talking to one<br />
another.<br />
J: Is theme still time for Dr Mahathir to get on board?<br />
PM: Look, I couldn't.-please don't ask me any more questions about Dr Mahatbir. I<br />
couldn't care less, frankly, whether he comes or not.<br />
J: Will you still see him next year, Prime Minister?<br />
PM: Yes. I'll see him in his own right. Malaysia is a country which Australia has<br />
interests with and which is a neighbour and I'll see him on those terms. But,<br />
APEC is bigger than all of us; Australia. the and Malaysia and Dr Mahathir<br />
and any other recalcitrants. I mean, APEC is a very big development in world<br />
termis and, I think, ushers in a period of important cooperation very important<br />
cooperation in what is already the most integrated trading area of the world.<br />
What you saw yesterday was a very historic meeting and I think the sense of<br />
history was not lost on any one of us there.<br />
J: Do you want the same formuat for the next one?<br />
PM: I think the format's fine and I think the fact that the leaders agreed to have another<br />
one was very important and we'll have the samne sort of arrangement wHere the<br />
leaders will attend without officials and we'll have a genuine discussion. It was,<br />
one of the high points for me was, we were sitting there in this room just fifteen<br />
people with these huge economies, discussing these contemporary problems. The<br />
problems in developed economies of high productivity and higher output but with<br />
fewer people involved and, therefore, higher unemployment. What we do about<br />
that, how we get these developing economies able to cope with their savings </p>
<p>requirements and' nFrasruure needs... and to have leaders actually sitting there<br />
focussing on these particular issues and thinking inventively about poroblems is a<br />
pretry novel experience.<br />
J: Mr Kmazng, should the outlook for the economy change in any way because of<br />
the APEC conference?<br />
PM: No. I don't think the short term outlook changes, we're in a growth phase now. I<br />
don't think the short term outlook changes but the long term outlook certainly<br />
changes. I think that, you know, we were just talking to Boeing about simple<br />
things like standardisation of receiving capacities in airports, some<br />
comprehension about the development of generations of aircraft and how they<br />
will be accepted. And whether wide-bodied aircraft carrying many people comning<br />
to few national airports and using them as feeder airports will be the way things<br />
develop, or whether we should go to one step down in smaller generation widebodied<br />
aircraft which go to other ancillary ports. I mean, all, these things are very<br />
key questions in the development of transportation. And the APEC group can<br />
think about these things because the greatest growth in air travel is in the Asia.<br />
Pacific. The greatest growth in &amp; icraft sales is in the Asia-Pacific. The growth in<br />
air travel is in the Asia-Pacific. So, what we do with our airports will decide how<br />
the aircraft are buit to take these things. So, APEC's going to have avery big<br />
spin-off for Boeing, a very big spin-off for the aviation industry in general and the<br />
tourism industry.<br />
Ends. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
