<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5582</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS TO THE NATIONAL COUNCIL OF INDEPENDENT CONFERENCE ON SCHOOL GOVERNANCE</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/05/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005582.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
I<br />
EMBARGO: 8: 00 pm<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIAFRIDAY, 8 MAY, 19 81<br />
ADDRESS TO THE NATIONAL COUNCIL OF INDEPENDENT CONFERENCE<br />
ON SCHOOL GOVERNANCE<br />
I am very pleased to be with you tonight, and to have the<br />
opportunity to address a conference whose theme is the<br />
governance of schools.<br />
The matter of governance, in a general sense, is one in which<br />
I suppose I have some experience. I. can only hope that school<br />
governance is free of some of the problems that-atise in<br />
governing a country. I am, of course, " considerably less<br />
familiar with school governance although while I was Minister<br />
for Education, I developed an abiding interest in the role of<br />
Government in the educational process. And in this context<br />
I wish to make a few comments about the present and future<br />
role of this Government in education..<br />
Let me say at the outset that the Government views with very<br />
great satisfaction the present strength of independent schools<br />
in Australia and the strong support that independent schools.<br />
are receiving from the community.<br />
We have consistently maintained, from the very first, that<br />
choice in education is a fundamental element of a free society.<br />
It was an earlier Liberal Government which originally introduced<br />
the concept of State aid, a concept which. was decisively upheld<br />
from a constitutional point of view in the High Court's decision<br />
-earlier this year.<br />
The Government's objectives in education involve promoting freedom<br />
of choice and equality of opportunity in schooling, while<br />
aspiring to standards of excellence at all levels, and at the<br />
same time helping the disadvantaged in the community. Our wish<br />
is to see that access to choice in schooling is open to the<br />
widest possible cross-section of the community. To advance<br />
this objective, the Government must plainly make a financial<br />
contribution to independent schools as well as to Government<br />
schools and the level of contribution to independent schools<br />
must be considerable. / 2 </p>
<p>2-<br />
In the early 1970s, for reasons which I n~ eed not go into,<br />
a bleak future seemed to lie ahead for the'independent schools.<br />
Financial problems mounted, and solutions were hard to find.<br />
Between 1972 and 1977, the number of independent-schools in<br />
this country actually declined by 65.-and that is a lot of<br />
schools to close down. An increase in Commonwealth support was<br />
necessary in order to redress the balance which had almost<br />
been destroyed in earlier years.,<br />
The facts seem to show that our efforts have borne fruit, for<br />
in the two years after 1977, the number of independent schools""<br />
increased by 75-and over the last three years ( 1977 to 1980)<br />
enrolments in independent schools have risen by 37,000,<br />
comprising 20,000 at the primary level and 17,000 at the secondary.-<br />
Putting the secondary figures in a different way, the<br />
proportion of secondary students enrolled in independent schools<br />
has risen from 24.4% in 1977 to 26.4% in 1980, and projections<br />
for 1984 suggest that this proportion will increase by one or<br />
' two'frte percentage points.<br />
The implication of these figures is unmistakable a large<br />
number of Australian parents wish their children to be educated<br />
in-independent schools.<br />
If the position of independent schools was deteriorating in the<br />
early seventies, the reason was not that this type of education.<br />
was less attractive to Australi'ans -the reason. was rather that.<br />
the Government--of the day adopted-policies the effect of~ whichand<br />
possibly the intent of which was to weaken the independen. t<br />
school sector. We opposed this trend utterly. Our support for<br />
an independent sector is not support for an exclusive sector,<br />
but for a more widely accessible independent sector.<br />
The aim of our policies is to place more, not less, Australian<br />
parents in the position where they can choose which kind of school<br />
best suits their children. If the education offered by a<br />
particular school suits a particular child then we would<br />
increasingly want to see a system in which the parents of that<br />
child would be in a position to send their child to that school..<br />
That is what freedom of choice in education means.<br />
I cannot emphasise too strongly that we support the independent:<br />
sector not because it is exclusive, but in order to make it<br />
more accessible. More and more parents are becoming alive to the<br />
importance of education and more and more are feeling an obligation<br />
to seek out the kind of education which seems best suited to<br />
their children. It would be a tragedy if in this situation fewer.<br />
parents were able to make the choice they really wanted.<br />
While choice is a fundamental reason for the support we give to it,<br />
the independent school sector provides a range of further benefEits<br />
for the Australian educational system. If all schools were<br />
Government schools, there would be an inevitable shift towards<br />
a monopolistic and bureaucratic control of education and education<br />
is surely an area in which monopoly and excessive bureaucracy -can<br />
have only the most damaging consequences. ./ 3<br />
K </p>
<p>3<br />
Government funding itself, of course,<br />
must be careftlly watched on its impact on<br />
the independence of independent schools. It would plainly be<br />
self-defeating if the independent schools were to become wholly<br />
dependent upon Governments. While independent schools currently<br />
receive considerable Government support, the future of each<br />
particular school depends fundamentally on the quality and<br />
attractiveness of the education which it offers.<br />
Independent schools have no forced clientele. If enrolments fall<br />
off at an independent school no bureaucratic fiat to swell its<br />
numbers will come forward to save it. This surely is a<br />
desirable discipline as well as a challenge.<br />
Schools which depend upon voluntary enrolments have a strong<br />
incentive to adapt to the demands of changing conditions. And<br />
within the independent school sector t: ere-r a -degree-odf diversity<br />
which . must surely provide-asa-tiaptiorr. and change. right<br />
across the spectrum of schools.,: T is-Esi-nat-to~-s that<br />
experimentation is going on only with the independent school<br />
sector the Government sector has equally made a major contribution.<br />
But the kind of experimentation which can occur in an independent<br />
sector cannot be guaranteed under a centralised education system.<br />
There is a . fundamental reason why: this-is-so andTI will expand.<br />
upon it because it applies in many areas of life beyond education.<br />
The independent schools provide this diversity and experimentation<br />
because they are responsive to the values of different groups<br />
in Australian society they reflect the diversity of our society.<br />
They are responsive because ultimately the parents who send their<br />
children must themselves pay a substantial proportion of the costs<br />
so the schools must provide the education that a sufficient<br />
number of parents want, or else close down.<br />
Institutions which are closely identified with what people want<br />
will remain healthy and strong because " they are in a state of<br />
continuing renewal as people's wants change and develop. Placing<br />
control over the allocation of funds to institutions in the hands<br />
of those whom I will broadly call the " users" is the best possible<br />
guarantee of their continuing health and vitality. In few . areas<br />
of life is this more important than in education for the vitality<br />
and adaptiveness of our whole society is so much bound up with<br />
the appropriateness of our education to the needs of our children.<br />
Institutions which are less subject to the mechanism of<br />
" user-control" experience greater difficulty in adapting to<br />
changing needs.<br />
We are emphasising the " user pays" or " user controls" concept<br />
as part of our wider approach to encourage a dynamic adaptation<br />
throughout Australia to the needs of the 1980s and beyond. We have<br />
been doing that in our recent decisions to transfer a number of<br />
Government enterprises to the private sector and in our recent<br />
health decisions. / 4<br />
I C </p>
<p>4<br />
Total Government control over any institution can lead to<br />
rigidities, inefficiencies and a lack of responsiveness which we<br />
believe Australia can ill afford in the challenging period<br />
ahead of us. A strong independent school sector encourages<br />
the adaptive potential of our educational system. It is an<br />
important element in Australia's capacity to face the future<br />
with confidence. And it is to the need to adapt that I now turn.<br />
Your programme for this conference lists papers on the<br />
relationships between governing bodies and principals, bursars,<br />
parents, past pupils and so on. But I see no paper explicitly<br />
addressing the relationship between the governing bodies and th.<br />
needs of present pupils. In the rest of my remarks I would like<br />
to address the question: " What kind of education do we owe our<br />
children in the rest of the eighties, given the challenges that<br />
confront Australia?". What do schools and parents owe to the<br />
children who come within their care? What is the role of<br />
Government, and more particularly, what system of education should<br />
Governments encourage and provide for? All these questions have<br />
acquired particular urgency in recent years.<br />
I want to discuss them with particular reference to the need of<br />
our young people to find satisfying jobs in the years ahead.<br />
You all know that numbers of young people who should be able to<br />
work* productively are unable to find employment when they<br />
leave school. The fact that this situation exists gives the<br />
Government, as well as parents, schools and students great concern.<br />
It is a situation which neither society nor the Government is<br />
willing to accept.<br />
It is important not to get the problem out ofperspective, . for<br />
the great majority of school leavers either proceed to<br />
tertiary education or else find employment quickly and I am pleased<br />
to say that youth unemployment is now dropping quite fast as the<br />
economy gathers pace. Total teenage unemployment is now 13,400 below<br />
the level recorded in April, 1980 but it is still much too high.<br />
. There is a minority who have real difficulties and these<br />
difficulties cannot be overlooked. During 1980 about 20,000<br />
15-17. year old young people were unemployed for at least eight<br />
months. Through transitional programmes the Government is making a very<br />
considerable contribution designed to enable these young people<br />
to find jobs and be able to cope with them. And let me refer here<br />
to reports a few months ago that the Government was proposing to<br />
withdraw unemployment benefits from 16 and 17 year olds for<br />
never have I known a greater perversion of a public debate.<br />
Our proposal was first to get a situation in which there would be<br />
worthwhile courses, together with adequate secondary allowances<br />
for the disadvantaged and then, and only then, to consider merely<br />
consider whether the young people concerned should be left with<br />
the option of going on the dole and possibly thereby lose for<br />
years the chance of getting a job. How false an impression of<br />
that proposal was conveyed to the people of Australia.<br />
A( </p>
<p>5<br />
The situation that confronts young people is the product of<br />
a variety of factors. There is the economic situation, in other<br />
countries as well as our own, there i-s a higher participation<br />
rate in the work force, there are problems of wage relativities<br />
which have made it difficult for many young people without<br />
experience to appear attractive to employers.<br />
In addition to such factors, young people are perhaps more<br />
selective about the kind of employment they will undertake, and<br />
there is also the well-known Catch 22 problem that it is hard<br />
to get a job without experience, and impossible to get experience<br />
without a job.<br />
These factors all have a place in explaining the current problems<br />
with youth unemployment. But a further factor is that many of the<br />
the people concerned have inadequate skills and inadequate<br />
training. They have not received the kind of education which<br />
C they required.<br />
It is easy to over-simplify the problems that are opened up<br />
by this consideration. I think it is generally agreed -hat<br />
schools must be adapative to the. requirements, . the-in-teiests and<br />
theen thusiasm of pupils. Every teacher know-s-how.-vital! it is to<br />
capture the interests of students. The teacher believes<br />
almost as a matter of faith that there is in all young people<br />
_-' some latent curiosity, some enthusiasm no matter how much<br />
hidden to acquire knowledge. If only the teacher can strike<br />
S. the right note then there will be a. take-off-even with the<br />
f--least promising -students.<br />
A point which has received an entirely proper emphasis in recent<br />
times is that while many schools provide well for pupils who have<br />
an academic bent and who are suited to tertiary studies, they<br />
provide much less well for pupils of a more practical disposition.<br />
One of the most pressing responsibilities of secondary schools is<br />
to those students who wish to leave school early and start working.<br />
These are-the students whose needs are not being met wiose<br />
interests are not being captured, whose enthusiasmsare not being<br />
exploited, whose natural abilities are not being harnessed, whose<br />
self-confidence is not being built up. In earlier-times, it was<br />
often thought that these students were simply failures. But it<br />
is now increasingly accepted that it is the system that is failing<br />
not the students who do not get much out of it.<br />
Surely there must be a relevant and a useful education which will<br />
serve the needs and at the same time capture the interest of<br />
every child. If we do not find that education, then surely we<br />
have failed the child. And if a few students would leave school<br />
feeling they had gained little no matter what had been offered to<br />
them, feeling they were failures, then surely we can make sure<br />
that they are very few indeed. / 6 </p>
<p>6<br />
In the vast majority of cases, when children leave school with<br />
a sense of failure or frustration, the inescapable conclusion<br />
is that the school has failed them. It is obviously easier to<br />
say these things than to work out suitable curriculums or to<br />
finance them. There is a range of challenges that teachers,<br />
schools and perhaps even governing bodies must try to meet.<br />
It is not clear, for example, that the kind of knowledge and<br />
skills that students will be interested to acquire will<br />
necessarily satisfy the requirements of employers. Again, the<br />
skills and knowledge that are attractive to the employers of<br />
today may not enable the students concerned to adapt to the<br />
changes of tomorrow yet education should surely aim to teach<br />
young people how to make the kinds of adaptations that are likelyto<br />
be necessary during their lifetimes.<br />
Further, young people do not always like what they are best<br />
at which means that there may be a gap between capturing their<br />
interest and providing them with the skills which may best enable<br />
them to obtain satisfactory employment.<br />
Secondary schools also face the challenge of not knowing, at least<br />
in the early years, whether a student will want to go on to<br />
further education, or whether he will wish to leave -school as<br />
early as possible and start working. It. is easy-forthose of us<br />
outside the-educational system to underestimate-these challenges<br />
which are in many ways most acute during the earlier years of<br />
-secondary education. But unless they are confronted in the early<br />
years, the problems that are currently arising for 16, 17 and 18<br />
year olds will remain.<br />
The challenges--to schools, and-to everyone-concerned. about<br />
education, are obviously very great indeed, and the Australian<br />
community rightly believes that they have not yet been met<br />
satisfactorily. Is it too hard to develop courses which will tap the talents of more<br />
of our children, courses that will capture their interest and<br />
meet their practical needs? I do not believe that this is too hard<br />
or that our society or our school system lacks the capacity to<br />
meet the-challenges.<br />
The Government will co-operate both with the States and with<br />
schools to help meet them. A major responsibility of Government is<br />
to make sure that we have the system that is best calculated to<br />
provide our children all of them with the kind of education<br />
which we owe them. That is why we place so much emphasis on<br />
encouraging a healthy independent school sector.<br />
The matters that I have talked about tonight concern all schools, and<br />
in the independent school sector the solutions depend very much<br />
on an awareness of the needs and the opportunities on the part of<br />
school governors and staff. The academic achievements of the<br />
independent schools are well-known and respected. As the needs of<br />
pupils change I have not the slightest doubt that the independent<br />
schools can adapt in ways that parents and pupils would want.<br />
Independent schools or many of them have changed and adapted<br />
to a remarkable degree. The independent schools have over many<br />
centuriesmade an incalculable contribution to the civilisation of<br />
which we are the heirs. I have no doubt that provided their<br />
accessibility to as many parents as possible is maintained<br />
they will continue to do so.<br />
C </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
