<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3115</transcript-id>
    <title>APPOINTMENT OF DEPUTY HIGH COMMISSIONER, LONDON</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/12/1972</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003115.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
NQ DATE<br />
M/ 8 14 December 1972<br />
APPOINTMENT OF DEPUTY HIGH COMMISSIONER, LONDON<br />
The Minister for Foreign Affairs, Mr Whitlan, announced today the<br />
appointment as Deputy High Commissioner in London of Mr D. W. McNicol, C. B. E.<br />
Mr McNicol is currently Australian High Commissioner to Canada.<br />
Mr McNicol was born in Adelaide in 1913 and was educated at<br />
YKinrs College and the University of Adelaide. He served in the Royal<br />
Australian Air Force from 19J40 to 1943 and joined the Department of Foreign<br />
Af fairs in 1946.<br />
Mr McNicol is a senior and experienced officer of the Department<br />
of Foreign Affairs. After service in TGkyjo and Washington, he was, during<br />
the period 1953 to 1954, accredited as Australian Minister in Viet-Nam,<br />
Cambodia and Laos. Mr McNicol attended the Imperial Defence College in<br />
London in 1957 and was then appointed Australian Commissioner in<br />
Singapore, where he served from 1957 to 1960. After a period as<br />
Assistant Secretary of the Pacific and Americas Branch in the Department,<br />
he was appointed Australian High Commissioner to Pakistan towards the<br />
end of 1962, an appointment he held for three years. From the end of 1965<br />
until early 1968 he was Australian High Commissioner to New Zealand after<br />
which he served as Australian Ambassador to Thailand. Mr McNicol has<br />
served in his present position as High Commissioner to Canada since<br />
August 1969. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
As Deputy High Commissioner Mr McNicol will succeed Mr W. B. Pritchett,<br />
who has been Acting High Commissioner since the retirement of Sir Alexander<br />
Downer. The Prime Minister recently announced that the new High Commissioner<br />
will be Mr J. I. Armstrong.<br />
Mr McNicol is expected to take up his appointment in London in<br />
April 1973. He is married with one son. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
