<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4498</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF AN ADDRESS TO TEH AUSTRALIAN-AMERICAN ASSOCIATION, 23 SEPTEMBER 1977</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/09/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004498.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS SEPTEMBER 1977<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF AN<br />
ADDRESS TO. THE AUSTRALIAN-AMERICAN ASSOCIATION<br />
This association does serve a very real need to remind us all<br />
of the strength of, and association between, the United States<br />
and Australia.<br />
I do not think there is really any need in this company to dwell<br />
overlong on the importance of the relationship between America<br />
and Australia.<br />
The United States of course is important to every society but<br />
maybe a little more important to those societies which have<br />
basically the same philosophical perceptions, the same outlook<br />
on the forms of government, and of the nature of individuals<br />
and society.<br />
But America as the world's richest, most powerful and technologically<br />
most advanced society is obviously important to the whole world.<br />
Its actions in every field of activity economic, political,<br />
social and cultural have significant influence on all of us.<br />
But the Australian-American relationship does go well beyond that.<br />
Australia and the United States are both democracies sharing the<br />
highest regard for individual freedom, opportunity and achievement.<br />
We have a common heritage, a common frontier experience.<br />
Indeed, that common heritage, common frontier experience is<br />
sometimes closer than many of us might want to recognise.<br />
Because if the war of independence had not led to the United<br />
States ceasing to be a place that would receive enforced emigrants<br />
from the United Kingdom, then the development of Australia and<br />
Port Jackson would have been years later than in fact it was.<br />
So we have a common origin.<br />
We are both nations of immigrants. We are free peoples with<br />
common philosophical perspectives.<br />
We have co-operated in many regions, in the pursuit of common<br />
goals. We have co-operated because our own independent perception and<br />
assessment of our respective national interest have led us into<br />
genuine agreement on the most effective ways we can contribute to<br />
world peace, stability and economic processes. / For </p>
<p>For decades now the mantle of leading the democracies has fallen<br />
to the United States. During my recent visit to that country it<br />
was apparent that President Carter and his administration were<br />
responding with confidence and vigour to the challenges of<br />
America's role as leader of nations, and the seriousness of the<br />
challenges posed by such problems as the world's energy situation,<br />
nuclear non-proliferation, the economic position of the developing<br />
countries and restrictions on human rights.<br />
President Carter has shown a deep concern about these issues and<br />
also a confidence that solutions can be found. He has shown a<br />
willingness to resolve them, even a willingness to take risks to<br />
resolve them. I believe also that the United States has underlined<br />
strength and resolution in its Executive and its Congress. There<br />
is a very real importance of the perception other countries have<br />
of the United States.<br />
All of us recognise that countries of Australia's size c an do many<br />
things. But there are some things in this world that have to be<br />
. done but which at the same time only the world's greatest power<br />
can do. If the United States leaves them undone, they can-not<br />
be done by any other country.<br />
Sometimes in the past, democracies have been put on the defensive,<br />
not only in respect to material matters but in respect of ideas.<br />
I believe that democracies such as Australia and the United States<br />
should never have to be on'the defensive.<br />
No other system of government has offered so much to its own<br />
people in terms of spiritual and real advantage. There are<br />
times when democracies tend to forget that. There are<br />
times when democracies allow themselves to be put on the<br />
defensive when they should always be on the offensive for what<br />
they have achieved, for what they have done for their own people,<br />
and for what they have done to advance human dignity.<br />
We can, and should, be proud of our democratic values and<br />
institutions, of our record of protecting and enhancing the<br />
integrity of people.<br />
President Carter's vigour and confidence, his willingness to<br />
speak out-about the values of democracy, signals I believe an<br />
end' to defensiveness.<br />
A resurgence of faith in the democratic system and of the ability<br />
of free people to face up and surmount the challenges confronting<br />
them, but acting effectively to meet common problems, requires<br />
co-operation and consultation between democratic nations.<br />
President Carter has made it clear this is the touchstone of<br />
his approach. When I was in Washington recently, the President<br />
made it perfectly plain that he wanted to hear Australia's views<br />
on matters which we thought to be of major importance whether<br />
they affected our own immediate part of the world, or events<br />
which might be taking place further afield. / There </p>
<p>-3<br />
There has been close and warm correspondence and communication<br />
since that time, on a quite continuous basis. It is a communication<br />
that I value and the Australian Government values very<br />
greatly. Australia has an obligation to speak in the free<br />
councils of the world particularly on matters of international<br />
concern where Australia might have a particular expertise or a<br />
special understanding because of history, geography, or past<br />
experience. That is done, and will continue to be done.<br />
There is one area of practical co-operation and one of great<br />
importance for the future for Australia, America and the world<br />
and that is the future of energy policy.<br />
President Carter has taken the lead with his practical proposals<br />
for meeting the ever-increasing needs in an energy-scarce world:<br />
through energy conservation programmes and through broadening<br />
the energy base; to encouraging the use of nuclear energy while<br />
minimising the risks associated with it; and in particular taking<br />
steps to slow the entry to a plutonium fuelled economy.<br />
We recognise that, as a country richly endowed with energy<br />
resources, Australia has a special obligation to develop its<br />
resources wisely in the interests of global peace and global<br />
stability. It-is very often difficult for Australians to understand<br />
that other countries are often very short of natural<br />
resources. We have coal in great supply, iron ore and minerals,<br />
including uranium, and great supplies of natural gas. In a<br />
sense, Australia is indeed a lucky country.<br />
But we might well find it difficult to understand the problems<br />
and attitudes of countries whose major resources are the energy<br />
ancl the capacity of their own people.<br />
If a country of great natural resources such as Australia were<br />
to say ' O no, the rest of the world cannot share in the benefits<br />
of those resources we are going to lock them up in Australia<br />
and deny them to the world' then that would be taking a very<br />
serious course of action. It would be saying to other countries<br />
that we are prepared to deny you the energy-to keep your factories<br />
operating; we are prepared to deny to you the right to have your<br />
homes heated in winter, and to be able to put on the light after<br />
sunset. Nuclear energy is the only viable and practical option many<br />
countries have to close the gap in their increasing energy needs<br />
for factories, for jobs, for homes, to meet the diminishing supply<br />
and increasing cost of oil and natural gas. Uranium is clearly a<br />
key resource of which Australia has an abundance.<br />
And we have a responsibility to be a continuing and stable<br />
source of supply of energy and raw materials to other countries,<br />
and particularly to our major trading partners. In meeting<br />
those responsibilities, we need also to protect our economic<br />
and social environments.<br />
The use of nuclear technology however brings with it attendant<br />
risk, risks of which we are all aware. / We have </p>
<p>we have welcomed the fresh impetus President Carter has given to<br />
discussion of the question of nuclear non-proliferation, one of<br />
the most crucial problems in international affairs. The Fox<br />
Report basically said, and I think it is correct,. that-Australia's<br />
attitude to the export of u. ranium should be determined by the most<br />
efficient way in which Australia can argue against nuclear weapon<br />
proliferation. In this area there are two points. We can pretend that our uranium<br />
does not exist. We can pretend that Australia is somewhere on the<br />
moon, not in this world. We can pretend the world around us does<br />
not exist, and ignore the fact that people are going to use uranium<br />
for peaceful purposes and pretend that it was not going to affect us.<br />
If we did that, we would have no influence on the International<br />
Atomic Energy Agency, or on President Carter's evaluation and<br />
study of nuclear supplies, all of which are designed to try and<br />
make sure that nuclear fuel is used for peaceful purposes, and is<br />
used as safely as possible under the most strict and absolute<br />
safeguards. Do Australians really want the people of this country to turn their<br />
backs on this great issue? Or do they want a vigorous Australian<br />
Government to get out into the world and use its influence?<br />
Because our natural resources give us the possibility of doing<br />
just that for the peace and stability of the world.<br />
I really believe that pe ople in Australia could feel safer if<br />
they knew that an Australian Government with proper objectives<br />
in mind was out in the world forum arguing for proper purposes<br />
and for proper objectives. I do not know a single'Australian who<br />
opposes those particular objectives.<br />
The choi ce is clear. Australia will either turn its back on the<br />
great province of the world which might well'in history be the<br />
greatest-of-the last part of this century. Or Australia will<br />
take its place in the world and will use its influence for a<br />
better and safer world.<br />
Every Australian would have a right, and I believe would feel<br />
a capacity to sleep safer at night if they knew that an Australian<br />
Government with that in mind was taking its part in the world<br />
rath~ r than Pretending that the world does not exist.<br />
But President Carter's efforts to foster dialogue and discussion<br />
and international effort in these matters is to be applauded.<br />
Australia is proud to stand with the United States in the general<br />
objective of seeking a better and safer world.<br />
Australia may never be short of electrical energy because of<br />
massive coal reserves. One energy area which does pose problems<br />
for us is that of liquid fuel. And unless new discoveries are<br />
soon made, Australia will have to rely increasingly on costly<br />
imported crude oils. / By </p>
<p>By firm pricing policies through a wide range of incentives,<br />
the Government hopes to encourage conservation on the one hand<br />
but further exploration and development on the other. We can<br />
no longer afford the continued extravagance and wasteful<br />
consumption of this vital and scarce resource which has been<br />
caused in the past by exceptionally low prices for oil and<br />
oil-derived products.<br />
The Australian Government is also acutely aware of the need to<br />
develop and harness new technology to meet out energy requirements.<br />
Solar energy and coal research are areas that this Government<br />
will be pursuing. We are already involved in co-operative<br />
measures with Germany in relation to coal research. We are<br />
investigating the possibility of forming co-operative researches<br />
with the United Kingdom and with the United States and a special<br />
levy is being introduced to help pay for that research.<br />
In all of this, there is great scope and co-operation between<br />
Australia and the United States and in practical fields I think<br />
we will knit closer together as the years pass.<br />
This in part leads me to a question I would like to touch on<br />
briefly foreign investment. The Government's policy is clear.<br />
We welcome foreign investment. We recognise the contribution it<br />
can, has, does, and will continue to make, to the development<br />
of the Australian economy.<br />
We have established clear guidelines which give foreign investors<br />
fair treatment and Australian nationals fair treatment. In this<br />
area it is obviously a question of balancing interests. But<br />
those guidelines are also sufficiently flexible to allow<br />
important new ventures to proceed when there might not be<br />
Ade4uate Australian capital to meet the guidelines.<br />
There are two factors which have slowed the rate of foreign<br />
investment and development in Australia.<br />
one is the problem of inflation. The other is an industrial<br />
relations problem.<br />
In both areas, however, I think there has been a marked<br />
improvement, although not yet enough. In our economic policies<br />
there has been considerable success in reducing inflation. How<br />
many people remember that in the last half of 1974 inflation was<br />
running at a fraction under 20%, and when we came to office,<br />
was at 16% and 17%. As measured by the CPI in June this year,<br />
inflation was running at 10.4% -obviously with Medibank excluded.<br />
But you can take other indices when that particular aberration<br />
did not operate, because they recognised that health care was a<br />
reality, that in fact it had a cost, that it suddenly did not<br />
disappear because you paid for it in a different way. The<br />
implicit price deflator for gross domestic product which takes<br />
into account all expenditures, brought inflation downfror. 16%<br />
or 17% to 9.2% in the June quarter. / I have </p>
<p>I have a friendly objective with the United States, in that<br />
the Governor-of the United States Reserve Bank, Mr. Arthur<br />
Btirns, said that next time I have lunch with him out objective<br />
is to have the Australian inflation rate under that of the<br />
United States. Inflation has only to increase a . little bit<br />
more in the US, and ours to reduce a little bit more, as ours<br />
will, and I will be able to go to the United States and win<br />
that bet.<br />
In the other area of industrial disputes, there has also been<br />
a significant improvement, but again not enough. To give<br />
examples from figures and then I will say how the figures<br />
4 mislead in the'first six months of 1974, 2 .4 million man days<br />
were lost in industrial disputes. I do not need to emphasise<br />
that my administration was not in power in the first six months<br />
of 1974. In the first six months of this year, 718,000 days were<br />
lost a reduction of 83% from the position three years ago.<br />
But there is still considerable improvement needed. Some<br />
extreme union leaders have fewer and fewer people who go out<br />
on a strike, and cause this disruption and regular disruption;<br />
whereas before there might have been more people to cause that<br />
disruption. Therefore, while statistics indicate considerable<br />
improvement, the improvement is not as great as the figures allow.<br />
In the seamen's dispute which held up Norwich Park venture on<br />
behalf of Utah and the seamen' s dispute is running the risk<br />
of closing down the Utah operations because they are demanding<br />
certain conditions which are quite unreasonable in relation to<br />
the export of some commodities jobs are being lost.<br />
In the case of the builders labourers federation, thousands<br />
I of jobs throughout Australia are being piit at risk as a result<br />
of guerilla tactics. This must not be allowed to continue.<br />
Australia must not continue to be prejudiced as a result of<br />
the act-ions of minorities.<br />
lie have now established the Industrial Relations Bureau and the<br />
very able Director of that Bureau will be taking up office<br />
within a few days time. We have introduced secret p) ostal<br />
ballots for the election of officials of trade unions registered<br />
under Commonwealth legislation. It is likely that there will<br />
be amendments to that legislation because of activities of at<br />
least one union designed to upset the processes of the secret<br />
ballot. Srecondary boycotts have been brought within the ambit of<br />
rcst~ rictLed. trade practices legislation. That is a significant<br />
advance. Following our actions during the air traffic controllers<br />
ezis; pute and the postal employees dispute at Redfern, people can<br />
understand that the Government is not prepared to accept nonsense<br />
4 and allow the Australian people to be held to ransom.<br />
But much remains to be done. Tony Street has done a<br />
magnificent job in a very difficult area. Further legislation<br />
will be introduced in relation to industrial legislation within<br />
the next four or five weeks. / We would </p>
<p>-7-<br />
We would much prefer to be able to solve problems in this<br />
area by consultation, and it is worth noting that the first<br />
thing we tried to do was to establish a tripartite consultative<br />
process between Government, employees and employers. But<br />
Mr. Hawk said he would have none of it. It was only in May<br />
of this year that the union movement came to the view that<br />
that kind of consultation would be worth while and that it<br />
might have merit. It was not the Government that rejected<br />
the consultation from the beginning. We argued for it, and<br />
the proposal was rejected. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
