<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5399</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/07/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005399.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
JAUTRAIA~ EMBARGO: 5: 00 PM<br />
PRIME MINISTER A~. r<br />
FOR MEDIA SU11DAY, 20 JULY ' 1; 9W0<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
Federal Cabinet has been meeting in Canberra over the past<br />
week making decisions that will lead to the framing of this<br />
year's Budget.<br />
There is still much to be done, but-the Budget that the<br />
Treasurer will deliver in four weeks' time will consolidate<br />
and strengthen the progress that we have made over the<br />
past five years.<br />
That progress has resulted from consistent policies that<br />
have cast aside soft options and the so-called " easy solutions"<br />
Our policies have consistently maintained downward pressure<br />
on inflation, and have helped restore the profitability, the<br />
competitiveness and vitality of Australian industries.<br />
The Organisation for Economic Co-Operation and Development<br />
has recently drawn attention to the fact that Australia's<br />
growth prospects are twice as strong in 1980 as those for<br />
the O. E. C. D. area as a whole.<br />
What is particularly pleasing to the Government is that:<br />
Australia has been able to maintain and improve its level of<br />
economic activity at a time when there is a significant: downturn<br />
in a number of major overseas economies.<br />
This better growth rate reflects Australia' s sound economic<br />
management, improved competitiveness and abundant resources,<br />
including energy.<br />
This potential would not, of course, be realised were i~ t not<br />
for our tighter control over inflation.<br />
Australia' s inflation rate this year is forecast by the 0. E. C. D.<br />
to remain significantly below the average of the O. E. C. D. area.<br />
Current developments in the Australian economy support our<br />
faith in Australia's prospects.<br />
The basis for this encouraging outlook can be seen in a revitalised<br />
Australian capital market; in the high level of private capital<br />
inflow; in the progress of our industries such as the great<br />
rural industries which had earlier encountered severe setbacks.<br />
For the first half of the past financial year the main source<br />
of improving activity was exports. / 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
It is most pleasing that recent figures show that the sources<br />
of economic growth broadened in the second half of the<br />
financial year.<br />
Private consumption and private investment are showing<br />
indications of solid growth.<br />
The rise in investment, based on confidence in the future,<br />
is expanding Australia's capacity to generate prosperity and<br />
jobs in the years ahead.<br />
A number of important domestic surveys confirm the strength<br />
of Australia's prospects as forecast by the 0. E. C. D.<br />
The survey in May of investment prospects by the Department<br />
of Industry and Commerce shows that there is $ 29 billion of<br />
investment projects committed or in a final feasibility stage.<br />
This investment is beginning to be put in place.<br />
A survey taken during April and May by the Bureau of Statistics<br />
shows that expected investment expenditures for the current<br />
financial year are about 40% higher than the expectations at<br />
this time last year.<br />
Even allowing for inflation, this rise is dynamic.<br />
The Statistician's survey reflects the very large anticipated<br />
investment in resource-based projects but also shows the<br />
improvement taking place in a wide range of Australian industries.<br />
This investment demonstrates a confidence that Australian<br />
goods can be competitive both at home and abroad.<br />
In the competitive trading world in which we live the present<br />
encouraging outlook is due largely to the Government's<br />
economic policies.<br />
Sensible and firm economic management is a continuing requirement<br />
if we are to keep this momentum going.<br />
We have particular advantages in resources, in energy, and in<br />
our geographic position in the fast-growing Asia-Pacific region<br />
which gives us the potential to partially ride out the bleaker<br />
conditions in the world economy.<br />
More than 45% of our exports now go to Asian and Middle East<br />
countries which in general are likely to do relatively well<br />
in sustaining their growth rates in the years ahead.<br />
The world is becoming increasingly dependent on reliable<br />
energy supplies and in that we are better placed than most.<br />
I must emphasise, however, that these forecasts depend very<br />
much on the continuing success of our anti-inflationary strategy.<br />
Warning signs are already here.<br />
The rate of increase of wages has been accelerating in recent<br />
months placing upward pressure on the Australian inflation rate. </p>
<p>-3-<br />
Claims for increased benefits such as a 35-hour week are<br />
totally self-centred and irresponsible when the welfare of<br />
the whole Australian community depends on retaining our<br />
favourable position in the world; on keeping our recovery<br />
on the move.<br />
It is fair enough to ask what all this activity and development<br />
means to the average Australian; what all this developiment<br />
means to an Australian family wanting a decent education for<br />
its children and a-secure-future for them.<br />
The answer is straight-forward. A nation can* only consume<br />
what it produces. A nation cannot consume what it does<br />
not work for.<br />
If we want improved standards of living, if we want improved<br />
education, health and welfare programmes; all of these can only<br />
be provided from the wealth earned by the people of our nation.<br />
There is no particular value in development for its own sake.<br />
Its merit lies in the jobs that it provides for Australians;<br />
and in the opportunities that it makes available to<br />
individuals and to our community to share in a high standard<br />
of living as a result of sustained economic growth.<br />
To this end, the Government is committed to responsiblE!,<br />
disciplined economic management.<br />
Our track record matches that commitment.<br />
The Budget to be brought down next month will show all<br />
Australians and those looking to Australia of our resolve<br />
to build on the strong foundations established over the<br />
last five years. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
