<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9003</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ KEATING RELEASE OF INTERVIEW OF GOVERNMENT POLICY ADVICE MECHANISMS ON THE STATUS OF WOMEN</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/10/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009003.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL: 18. Oct. 93 10: 05 No. 003 P. 01/ 03<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE KCIN P J KEATING, MP<br />
RELEASE OF THE REVIEW OF GOVERNMENT POLICY ADVICE<br />
MECHANISMS ON THE STATUS OF WOMEN<br />
I am pleased to be here this morning at the rei~ ase of this review of the<br />
Government's policy advice mechanisms on the status of women.<br />
Today marks the opening of a new chapter in the formation of -public policy on<br />
the status of women in Australia.<br />
Ten years ago the Government embarked on an ambitious program to<br />
advance the status of women. The so-called ' radical' policies espoused by<br />
Labor then, such as sex discrimination and affirmative action laws, are now<br />
an accepted part of our culture.<br />
Since then, the Government has put forward policies to meet the needs and<br />
aspirations of women across the many spheres of their lives. We have made<br />
significant gains in areas such as employmeni, education, access to child<br />
-, care and income security for women caring for children.<br />
We have taken on the challenge of ending violence against women and<br />
children, acknowledging the enormity of the task.<br />
We know we have more to do In many areas, such as health, retirement<br />
income and equality of participation In public Ile, but In these areas Important<br />
advances have also been made.<br />
Policies of governments can promote lasting, structural and attitudinal<br />
change to promote equality for women,<br />
When we won the election in March this year, 1 thanked the women of<br />
Australia who voted for us believing In the policies of the Government.<br />
The Government is very proud of the role it has played in achieving advances<br />
for women over the last decade. But we neec to look forward, not backwards,<br />
if those achievements are to continue.<br />
That is what this review is about. </p>
<p>TEL 2<br />
It Is about ensuring that our policy advice mechanisms remain appropriate,<br />
effective and responsive to the changing needs and interests of women.<br />
The Off ice of the Status of Women, in my Depaiment, has played a key roie<br />
In achieving major advances for women since 1383.<br />
In its early days it was responsible for putting tcgether the Sex Discrimination<br />
and Affirmative Action Acts. But its recent work has been no less Important.<br />
Work to produce a National Strategy on Violenc~ e Against Women, the new<br />
National Agenda for Women and development of important new policies on<br />
child care announced earlier this year, are just some exampies.<br />
These are all policies that have a real impact oni women's lives.<br />
Getting the policies right for women has to be vur top priority.<br />
The Government needs a strong Office Of the Status of Women which can<br />
provide accurate, weii-researched and authoritative advice on how to move<br />
the agenda forward for Australian women.<br />
I fully endorse the review's recommendation that such policy advice should<br />
be the primary focus of the Off ice of the Status of Women. I also support<br />
giving priority to the three critical policy areas identified in the review:<br />
women's economic security; the participation of women in public life; and<br />
women and the law, with a particular emphasis on eliminating violence<br />
against women.<br />
But the Off ice of the Status of Women and the Government can't get it right<br />
without help from women and their organisaticns.<br />
When launched the new National Agenda for Women, in February this year,<br />
I said that a unique partnership between the women's movement and the<br />
Government has contributed greatly to our achievements over the past ten<br />
years. We want that partnership to continue.<br />
That doesn't mean everything has to stay the same. We need to find the<br />
most effective ways of working together towards our common goals.<br />
The review sets out an approach to consultaton which is designed to be<br />
effective and focussed and elicit the views of the diversity of Australian<br />
women. Consultation has to be purposeful, timely and focussed. It must give you the<br />
opportunity for real input, and provide us witt advice we can use to improve<br />
outcomes for women.<br />
Because we want to hear regularly from organisations representing women,<br />
we will hold Round Table Meetings with national women's Organisation$ twice<br />
each year. The Minister assisting me on the status of women, Senator<br />
Crowley, will host these meetings and invite other Ministers as appropriate.<br />
T1EL.: O ct. 93 10: 05 No. 003 P. 02/ 03 </p>
<p>TEL: 18. Oct. 93 10: 05 No. 003 P. 03/ 03<br />
3<br />
As with today, such meetings will Include repre~ entatives of the union<br />
movement, the business community, Aboriginals and Torres Strait Islanders<br />
and ethnic communities.<br />
We will also convene specific purpose advisory committees, as necessary, to<br />
assist us with discrete tasks. The first such committee will be the Australian<br />
Council for the Fourth World Conference on Women.<br />
Its role will be to act as a focal point for Australia's preparations for the United<br />
Nation's Fourth World Conference on Women, to be held in Beijing in 1995.<br />
Senator Crowley will be announcing details of tViat Committee very soon.<br />
We will also undertake regular research on the views and concerns of women<br />
in the community to ensure that we stay in touch and on track.<br />
In closing I would like to thank the Minister assisting me on the status of<br />
women, Senator Rosemary Crowley, for underlaking this important review<br />
and for her report. I would also thank you for the contributions and comments<br />
many of you made on aspects of the review.<br />
I have accepted and welcomed the review's re%. ommendations. I will leave it<br />
to my colleague, Senator Crowley, to detail the, recommendations and their'<br />
Implications for you. There is however, one rel-ommendlation that I would like<br />
to comment on.<br />
I take very seriously the first recommendation, that we should have a Minister<br />
Assisting representing women's interests in Cabinet.<br />
I do not intend to enter into speculation about how or when this will be<br />
achieved. However, I will give serious consideration to the Issue at the next<br />
_ appropriate opportunity.<br />
The report of this review outlines some exciting and challenging work for<br />
Senator Crowley and the Office of the Status ) f Women. I look forward to<br />
working with Senator Crowley and the Office of the Status of Women, and<br />
with you here today, to achieve further progress towards true equality for<br />
women. CANBERRA 18 October 1993 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
