<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>127</transcript-id>
    <title>PM 42/1959 - VISIT OF TUNKU ABDUL RAHMAN - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R G MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/10/1959</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000127.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
P. M. No. 42/ 1959<br />
VISIT OF TUNKU ABDUL RAHMAN<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON.<br />
MENZIES<br />
The Prime Minister today released details of the programme<br />
for the visit to Australia of the Prime Minister of the<br />
Federation of Malaya, Tunku Abdul Rahman.<br />
Mr. Menzies said he greatly looked forward to meeting<br />
Tunku Abdul Rahman especially since he would be visiting Malaya<br />
for the first time with Dame Pattie Menzies in December, when he<br />
would again meet the Malayan Prime Minister.<br />
Tunku Abdul Rahman will travel by Qantas from Kuala<br />
Lumpur to Sydney via Singapore, Djakarta, Perth and Melbourne.<br />
The Minister for the Interior and for Jorks, Mr. Gordon Freeth,<br />
will meet Tunku Abdul Rahman at Perth Airport on behalf of the<br />
Commonwealth Government. The High Commissioner for Malaya, Dato'<br />
Gunn Lay Teik, Australia's High Commissioner at Kuala Lumpur, Mr.<br />
T. K. Critchley and a representative of the 4estern Australian<br />
Government, will also be present at the Airport.<br />
Tunku Abdul Rahman will stay informally in Sydney at<br />
Kirribilli House on Saturday, 31st October, and will arrive in<br />
Canberra at 4.15 p. m. on Sunday 1st November where he will be<br />
met by the Prime Minister, Mr. A. G. Menzies, and will inspect a<br />
Guard of Honour provided by the Royal Australian Air Force. He<br />
will dine that evening at the Prime Minister's Lodge.<br />
On Monday morning the 2nd November, Tunku Abdul Rahman<br />
will attend the official Opening of the Commonwealth Parliamentary<br />
Association Conference by His Excellency the Governor-General,<br />
and in the afternoon will travel to Melbourne in the Commonwealth<br />
Government's V. I. P. aircraft Metropolitan<br />
Convair). In Melbourne he will attend the State Governor's late<br />
afternoon Reception and in the evening will attend " My Fair Lady"<br />
at Her Majesty's Theatre.<br />
On Tuesday, 3rd November, Tunku Abdul Rahman will attend<br />
the Melbourne Cup and will be a guest at the Governor-General's<br />
Buffet Luncheon at the Racecourse.<br />
On ednesday, the 4th November, he will trqvel to Portsea<br />
and visit the Officer Cadet School whore he will inspect a<br />
Guard of Honour and remain to lunch. In the evening he will attend<br />
a Dinner Party in his honour at Government House and afterwards<br />
attend the Naval Ball in the Governor of Victoria's party.<br />
Thursday, 5th November, will be spent informally in<br />
Melbourne taking in a sightseeing tour during the day. In the<br />
evening Tunku Abdul Rahman will give a Buffet Dinner to Malayan<br />
students. Tunku Abdul Rahman will visit the Snowy Mountains<br />
Scheme from Friday, the 6th, until Sunday, the 8th November.<br />
Tunku Abdul Rahman will re) turn to Canberra in the late<br />
afternoon of Sunday 8th November and for the following three days<br />
will stay at Government House as the guest of Their Excellencies<br />
the Governor-General and Lady Slim.<br />
On Monday, 9th November, he will have official discussions<br />
in Canberra and attend a Luncheon in his honour given by<br />
His Excellency the Governor-General at Government House. In the<br />
afternoon Tunku Abdul Rahman will officially open the Chancery of<br />
the High Commissioner for Malaya and later attend a Reception in<br />
L </p>
<p>his honour given by His Excellency Dato'' Gunn Lay Teik.<br />
On Tuesday, 10th November Tunku Abdul Rahman will<br />
give a National Press Conference and later lay a wreath on the<br />
commemorative stone at the Australian War Memorial. He will attend<br />
a Parliamentary Luncheon at Parliament House given by the<br />
Commonwealth Government. After the Parliamentary Luncheon Tunku<br />
Abdul Rahman will attend question time in the House of Representatives<br />
and in the Senate. He will be invited to take a seat on<br />
the floor of each House. In the evening he will attend a Dinner<br />
in his honour given by the High Commissioner for Malaya, Dato'<br />
Gunn Lay Teik. Guests will include the Prime Minister, Mr.<br />
Menzies, Leader of the Opposition, Dr. Evatt and some senior<br />
Ministers. On Wednesday, llth November Tunku Abdul Rahman will<br />
leave Canberra for Sydney where he will attend a State Luncheon<br />
given by the Government of New South T-* ales. In the late afternoon<br />
Tunku Abdul Rahman will attend the Sydney University and<br />
will receive the degree of Doctor of. Laws, after which he will<br />
attend the University's Annual Reception. That evening Tunku<br />
Abdul Rahman will tender a Buffet Dinner to Malayan students.<br />
He will spend the next throe days ( 12th to 14th November)<br />
informally in Sydney.<br />
Tunku Abdul Rahman will leave Sydney for Kuala Lumpur<br />
on Sunday, the 15th November.<br />
Tunku Abdul Rahman will be accompanied by his Minister<br />
of the Interior, Dato' Suleiman, and four officials.<br />
CANBERRA<br />
28th OCTOBAjR, 1959. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
