<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7286</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER &quot;CRY FREEDOM&quot; PREMIERE SYDNEY - 10 FEBRUARY 1988</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/02/1988</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007286.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIMESTRMINISTE<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
" CRY FREEDOM" PREMIERE<br />
SYDNEY 10 FEBRUARY 1988<br />
AS Australia celebrates its Bicentenary, " Cry Freedom" is a<br />
stark, powerful remi'nder that, in South Africa, a different<br />
kind of anniversary is in train: the fortieth anniversary of<br />
apartheid. In these forty years, many former colonies throughout<br />
Africa, the Caribbean and in our own Asia-Pacific region<br />
have achieved nationhood with majority rule and<br />
independence. The concept of racial equality has become<br />
accepted as a basic fact in the international community as a<br />
whole. But in South Africa those four decades of<br />
Nationalist Party rule have seen only the development of an<br />
anti-democratic state built on discrimination, injustice and<br />
brutality. Steve Biko's story as told by Sir Richard Attenborough in<br />
" Cry Freedom", forces us again to face the human tragedy of<br />
South Africa today. Steve Biko was obviously an exceptional<br />
individual in his courage and the force of his personality.<br />
But tragically, in confronting an intransigent and<br />
inexorable police state, Biko's was not an isolated fate. It<br />
is typical of the experience shared by so many blacks in<br />
South Africa from leaders such as Nelson Mandela to unknown<br />
numbers of people, including even children.<br />
The plight of children as victims of the apartheid system<br />
lends a special poignancy to this film and to this evening's<br />
Australian premiere.<br />
I am particularly pleased that the proceeds of tonight's<br />
showing will go to UNICEF which does so much for children<br />
all around the world, including the many in South Africa who<br />
continue to be the brutal victims of apartheid.<br />
" Cry Freedom" also highlights, in the story of Donald Woods,<br />
the troubles that await white South Africans who dare to<br />
support the cause of justice and freedom.<br />
For millions of South African blacks, life under the now<br />
seemingly permanent provisions of the State of Emergency<br />
remains appalling. 004335 </p>
<p>In the townships, poverty, ill-health, evictions and<br />
violence continue to prevail either unhindered or actively<br />
helped by the security forces.<br />
In Australia we see less of this South African oppression<br />
these days because of the new censorship regulations, the<br />
purpose of which is to keep South Africa's shame from the<br />
world. But trying to hide apartheid doesn't make it go away.<br />
That official silence gives us the responsibility to ensure<br />
that we do not become immune to the horrors of apartheid or<br />
allow other, more immediate, tragedies and troubles to<br />
dissipate our sense of outrage and our determination to<br />
achieve peaceful change.<br />
And the silence of censorship also makes it very important<br />
that " Cry Freedom" has been made. It is encouraging that<br />
this film will undoubtedly reach millions of ordinary people<br />
around the world. It frustrates the South African<br />
Government in its attempts to hide apartheid and keeps world<br />
attention focused on the enormity of the issue. It shows the<br />
tragic human reality behind the cold facts of the apartheid<br />
system and the methods used to enforce it.<br />
There is encouraging evidence that the international<br />
community remains determined to keep up the pressure for<br />
change on the minority government of South Africa.<br />
Within the Commonwealth, that concern has made Southern<br />
Africa the dominant political issue at the two most recent<br />
meetings of the Commonwealth Heads of Government in Nassau<br />
and Vancouver, and the subject of a special Commonwealth<br />
Summit in London in 1986.<br />
In 1985, in response to an Australian initiative, the<br />
Commonwealth established the Eminent Person's Group, whose<br />
aim was to provide a basis for negotiations between the<br />
South African Government and representative black groups.<br />
The EPG was co-chaired by Malcolm Fraser, and I take this<br />
opportunity once again to express my appreciation of his<br />
role both in Government and later with the EPG, in helping<br />
the international community to a proper understanding of the<br />
issues at stake in South Africa.<br />
As well as helping to set up the EPG, Australia has also<br />
participated very fully, both in the Commonwealth and<br />
independently, in the imposition of economic and other<br />
measures designed to put pressure on the South African<br />
Government to come to its senses before it is too late.<br />
South African whites are feeling increasingly under pressure<br />
from such measures and, as their own minister for Finance<br />
has acknowledged, the South African economy has been<br />
significantly affected. 0 043 3G </p>
<p>My Government has also been concerned to do what we can to<br />
help the victims of apartheid. Last month, we announced-an<br />
increase from $ 55 million to $ 100 million in our current<br />
three year aid program for Southern Africa.<br />
A few days ago, Mr Hayden attended a meeting of Commonwealth<br />
Foreign Ministers in Lusaka, the aim of which was to push<br />
forward the Commonwealth's goals in Southern Africa.<br />
I am pleased that an Australian proposal, which I had made<br />
at the Vancouver Commonwealth Conference, for a study of<br />
ways of limiting international financial links with the<br />
South African economy was enthusiastically endorsed by the<br />
Lusaka meeting.<br />
Western nations, which have ignored the case for economic<br />
sanctions, citing as their justification that sanctions<br />
would only hurt the black majority, would do well to<br />
consider the views of Steve Biko, as quoted in a recent<br />
newspaper interview by Donald Woods:<br />
" Steve Biko used to say you must always ask the victims<br />
what they want not the non-victims."<br />
Along with the overwhelming majority of representative South<br />
African black leaders, Steve Biko was strongly in favour of<br />
sanctions against South Africa.<br />
Australia of course has not been free of its own racial<br />
problems a fact which we acknowledge in particular during<br />
our Bicentennial as we review our history and look to the<br />
future. The question of black deaths in custody, which is<br />
an issue in " Cry Freedom", has been a subject of profound<br />
concern to my Government in recent months and the apparent<br />
scale of the problem has rightly caused anguish in our<br />
community. Our public response to this situation and the actions taken<br />
by the Commonwealth and State governments in Australia to<br />
tackle it reflect the world of difference that exists<br />
between the nature of the problem here and in South Africa<br />
and between the political systems in Australia and South<br />
Africa. We quickly mobilised Federal and State resources in the<br />
establishment of a Commonwealth/ State Royal Commission,<br />
headed by Commissioner Muirhead to enquire into these<br />
deaths. We have sought the fullest participation of<br />
Aboriginals in the Royal Commission processes. When, after<br />
the Royal Commission had been operating for some weeks, the<br />
number of deaths identified was found to be significantly<br />
larger than first thought, we took rapid steps to augment<br />
the Royal Commission, with the objective of seeing that<br />
answers are produced as quickly as possible. 004337 </p>
<p>4.<br />
This systematic, principled approach we have taken is aimed<br />
at unravelling the causes of the problem and identifying<br />
remedies. In South Africa, the authorities try to ijnore or<br />
to conceal the truth of violent and illegal acts carried out<br />
by the police and the security apparatus and to do nothing<br />
to deal with the fundamental evils of the apartheid system<br />
and the human tragedies that flow from it.<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
It is instructive to compare " Cry Freedom" with another of<br />
Sir Richard Attenborough's films, " Gandhi" a film which<br />
also deals with the great themes of racial equality and<br />
political freedom, and non-violent political protest.<br />
The oppression which Gandhi experienced in South Africa had<br />
a fundamental impact on his subsequent struggle in India and<br />
on the whole course of Indian history indeed, it is no<br />
exaggeration to say, world history. The oppression and<br />
death of Steve Biko, decades later, continue to have an<br />
impact on the fight for freedom in South Africa, the outcome<br />
of which is yet to be determined.<br />
But the outstanding difference between the two stories, and<br />
I believe it is a tragic one, is that, unlike Gandhi's<br />
cause, the cause in which Steve Biko risked and lost hislife<br />
remains unachieved. The forces which destroyed him still<br />
prevail. His people remain in thrall to them. Their<br />
struggle goes on.<br />
What we must realise is that time is running out. The<br />
wisdom, moderation and courage so fully possessed by Steve<br />
Biko is in limited supply. If the successors to Steve Biko<br />
fail to achieve the necessary reform, then they may be<br />
replaced by leaders with less wisdom, less moderation, less<br />
courage. The consequence for all South Africans, black and<br />
white, and for all of us who care about the future of South<br />
Africa, would be dire indeed.<br />
I believe we all owe Sir Richard Attenborough a great debt<br />
for lending the weight of his talent and prestige to telling<br />
the inspiring but tragic story of Steve Biko.<br />
" Cry Freedom" reminds us that the monstrous injustices of<br />
the apartheid system continue undiminished. The film<br />
enables us to feel directly the human dimensions of the<br />
tragedy of South Africa. I am sure that Sir Richard's film<br />
will play a major role in furthering public understanding of<br />
the great moral and political issues involved. 004,338 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
