<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>17995</transcript-id>
    <title>Government energy skills package - securing jobs for the future</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/07/2011</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
The Gillard Government will invest up to $32 million to help tradespeople and professionals learn vital green skills that will be in strong demand as Australia moves towards a clean energy future.</p>
<p>The Clean Energy Skills package will deliver integrated green skills training and clean energy knowledge, advice, products and services to transition Australia to a low carbon economy.</p>
<p>For the first time, the sustainability skills of professionals such as engineers and others with the technical ability to deliver energy efficiency solutions will be targeted as part of the Government's comprehensive Clean Energy Future plan.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Julia Gillard and Member for Wills, Kelvin Thomson today met apprentice plumbers in Melbourne who are being trained to work with the latest technologies to tackle climate change.</p>
<p>Touring the Plumbing Industry Climate Action Centre in Brunswick, the Prime Minister viewed innovative technologies which have been put to use in a 5 Star Green-rated home used to train apprentice plumbers.</p>
<p>The Centre is an excellent example of an industry-led training organisation that is providing vital green skills to our workforce.</p>
<p>Under the package, specialised energy efficiency skills sets will be developed in occupations such as building and construction, facilities management, engineering and financial management and auditing.</p>
<p>Teaching resources will be developed to support high quality delivery of these skills sets by VET practitioners.</p>
<p>There are four key components to the package:</p>
<p>路         A baseline map of existing sustainability knowledge and skill needs in key clean energy and energy efficiency products, services and advice will be developed</p>
<p>路         Specialised skills sets in energy efficiency will be developed for existing workers in building, planning and construction</p>
<p>路         Undergraduate engineering students will get the technical skills required to deliver and promote energy efficiency solutions in the workplace</p>
<p>路         Up to $10 million in funding based on co-investment with industry will be provided to undertake training that supports the use of low emissions technology or clean energy skills.</p>
<p>The Gillard Government is investing in energy efficiency, green innovation and skills and workforce development.</p>
<p>These policies, combined with a price on pollution, will ensure Australia's continued prosperity as we move towards a cleaner energy future.</p>
<p>The Plumbing Industry Climate Action Centre provides world class facilities for plumbers to learn the skills required to deliver clean energy services.</p>
<p>As we move to a greener economy, we will see increased demand for grey water recycling and water-wise plumbing and irrigation systems.</p>
<p>Water conservation and energy efficient plumbing, grey water recycling, natural waste water treatment and solar technologies are all on the curriculum for apprentices studying green plumbing courses at the Centre.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
