<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8582</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP PRESS CONFERENCE, CANBERRA 20 JULY 192</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/07/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008582.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
PRESS CONFERENCE, CANBERRA<br />
JULY 1992<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
PM: Earlier I published a document to you, a background<br />
statement, for the meeting on Youth Training and<br />
Employment, and a few of you expressed an interest<br />
in me making a few introductory remarks about it and<br />
taking some questions, so I am quite happy to do<br />
that. Perhaps I could begin with these few points. I<br />
think what the paper shows is that the problem with<br />
yo-uthunemployment has arisen from changes in the<br />
labour market over a very extended period of time,<br />
the 1_ i960s onwards, over the last thirty years<br />
economic, social and-technologi~ cal changes have<br />
fairly radically altered the types of -õ bs which<br />
young people are now competing for. On Wednesday<br />
the National Meetina on Youth Training ! ad<br />
Emplovment will bring together young people,<br />
employers, unions, community groups and the<br />
Government, and those at the meeting will benefit<br />
from the different perspective being put, and will<br />
tackle directly the two key issues. The two key<br />
issues are; the longer term issue of assisting young<br />
people to make the transition from school to work,<br />
and the immediate issue of how best to help the<br />
current group of young unemployed obtain employment.<br />
So the purpose of this statement is to set out a<br />
framework for-~ understanding and-tackling the issues<br />
surrounding the training and employment of young<br />
people, including of course, the problem of youth<br />
unemployment. The ideas contained in this paper will be discussed<br />
at Wednesday's meeting, as well of course the ideas<br />
and proposals of other proponents. Following the<br />
meeting on Wednesday the Government will carefully<br />
consider the views canvassed at the meeting, that's </p>
<p>in the period subsequent to the meeting, and I will<br />
announce specific measures in these areas in the<br />
following week.<br />
I think you will agree the Statement does contain a<br />
lot of interesting information and perceptions on<br />
the problems. It stands, might I say, an obvious<br />
and stark contrast with the efforts of the<br />
Opposition, who without serious thought have<br />
dismissed technological and compositional changes to<br />
the labour market for young people. They have now<br />
approached the training issue as an afterthought and<br />
piecemeal at that, and who crudely believe a massive<br />
slashing of yquy h_ wages will solve the problem.<br />
Well unlike the Opposition, the Government will be<br />
viewing the later teenage years as a period of<br />
vocational preparation and will be doing all that is<br />
sensible, all that can be done to put arrangements<br />
and resources in place, to allow that vocational<br />
preparation to be undertaken. There is a distinct<br />
and truly marked contrast between the way in which<br />
the Government is approaching the issue, both on a<br />
long run basis, in respect of the transition from<br />
school to work, and for those in the shorter run who<br />
are unemployed before that transition and pathways<br />
are established. That's what the paper is about,<br />
and of course as I say, it is in marked contrast to<br />
the Opposition who for training, their policies,<br />
their fightback proposals have virtually nothing for<br />
training and they have now tried to tack training on<br />
as an afterthought, when training is part of the<br />
essence of such a structural shift. So I am sure<br />
the paper will be interesting to you and if you<br />
would like to put questions to me I will try and<br />
deal with them.<br />
J: Prime Minister arguing that there is in fact no<br />
quick fix. In fact, it says by the year 2001 at<br />
least 95 per cent of nineteen year olds should have<br />
completed year 12 or postschool qualification,<br />
that's a long way off from solving today's problems,<br />
isn't it?<br />
PM: No, no. There are two problems here. The proportion<br />
of children completing year 12 now is over 70 per<br />
cent, that was only 30 odd per cent in 1983. So if<br />
we had of taken that approach in 1983 saying this is<br />
a long-term problem that is too hard there would<br />
. still -be 30 per cent-of kids only completing year<br />
12. Well there is now over 70 per cent of kids<br />
completing year 12. Getting up to the nineties is a<br />
very desirable thing to do. So that's the longer<br />
run transition, the school to work transition, the<br />
pathways, the things which are mentioned in the<br />
Carmichael Report. But there are those, as we say<br />
in the statement, who will have lived through their<br />
later teenage years before this transition is in </p>
<p>full swing and who are now currently unemployed, and<br />
we will be focussing on them as well.<br />
J: Prime Minister, will you have by Wednesday a form of<br />
agreement between the States and the Federal<br />
Governments on the TAFE, or the future, the shape of<br />
the TAFE system?<br />
PM: Well that remains to be seen. I have been working<br />
on this problem now for a couple of weeks, so has<br />
Kim Beazely, and we have had, I think, quite long<br />
and we hope fruitful negotiations with the States,<br />
and getting a break through here is a very tall<br />
order, this is a system which is essentially managed<br />
by the States, and most of the resourcing comes from<br />
the States. The fact is they can't keep the growth<br />
up to the system, and that's why we think there is a<br />
case for national leadership, national policy and<br />
national funding. But it has to be run<br />
cooperatively, obviously, because the Commonwealth<br />
has not been the TAFE manager, and it is trying to<br />
construct a new system which would be a very<br />
revolutionary change and of course an entirely<br />
important change in the history of our federal<br />
arrangements to be able to bring such a system<br />
together and make it work. Now, we are still<br />
working on it.<br />
J: The TAFE system hasn't been that efficient in the<br />
past, how is it going to be made more efficient by<br />
superimposing yet another level of bureaucracy on<br />
it?<br />
PM: Well I think that, when you say that it has not been<br />
efficient, the truth is it hasn't had the throughput<br />
which the nation needed of it. As we say in the<br />
paper we have had a 43 per cent increase in<br />
university graduations but in terms of TAFE exits<br />
there has been a decline. So it has not been<br />
keeping up. What we need is national training<br />
profiles, we need training profiles related to<br />
industry and we need volume, we need resources, and<br />
that can't be done without the Commonwealth, nor at<br />
this stage can that be done without the States.<br />
J: It is envisaged, I think, isn't it over time that an<br />
increasing amount of the money would come from<br />
Commonwealth sources? In that case does that imply<br />
increasingnational control?<br />
PM: Well the arrangement we are working on is about that<br />
control being somewhat more diffuse between the<br />
Commonwealth and the States, but national control we<br />
have as an objective, certainly. Not Commonwealth<br />
controlled. I don't know whether you meant<br />
Commonwealth or National. </p>
<p>management will always be the hallmark of the<br />
Government, and we've made that clear in recent<br />
times and will continue to make that clear.<br />
Q: Mr Keating out in the community there's a great deal<br />
of, there seems to be an increasing amount of<br />
scepticism about Government statements of various<br />
types and the community seems to think the<br />
Government is trying to be seen to be doing<br />
something but not having much effect. Are you<br />
worried that the Youth Statement could be seen that<br />
way as well?<br />
PM: You think that we want to be dealing in<br />
anti-intellectual policies, that is that we don't<br />
actually articulate policies and we don't try and<br />
solve things lest people think we're trying to do<br />
something. Well is that the state where our<br />
journalism is really, where our public comment is?<br />
Q: Mr Keating you've talked about two aspects of the<br />
problem in the paper, the long-term one and trying<br />
to get people into that frame of mind where they<br />
stay in education and training opportunities longer,<br />
it talks about the immediate short-term problems<br />
for kids who are caught in transition at the moment.<br />
In that context how important are the kind of youth<br />
corp land degradation projects?<br />
PM: You're now asking me to look at various proposals<br />
and responses. The paper is basically there<br />
to paint an overview of the whole problem. I mean<br />
this has been a problem which has developed over a<br />
long period of time and which will now only be<br />
solved by clear paths and policies designed to make<br />
that transition from school to work, and at the same<br />
time, for those as I say, whose latter teenage years<br />
have arrived now before that transition, the fine<br />
policies which get them back into a labour market.<br />
As we say there's some figures there about the<br />
generation about the current young unemployed people<br />
are actually in that unemployed pool, and the role<br />
of labour market programs. Obviously we want to try<br />
to get those people back into work, back into work<br />
experience, but it's the longer run transition of<br />
the great bulk of young people who are currently in<br />
school that we want to see go into the labour market<br />
with training, in properly formed paths, and if we<br />
can do that, and if part of that can be, a<br />
substantial change in the way in which the TAFE<br />
system functions and works in Australia it will be a<br />
milestone reform.<br />
Q: the immediate problem are you tempted then by<br />
suggestions of the kind from Peter Hollingworth<br />
about youth corp, job corp projects? </p>
<p>PM: Everyone attending the meeting including<br />
ArchbishopHollingworth will put those propositions<br />
and weilc onsl1Wi-fhose in the course of the week.<br />
Q: But they're out there now?<br />
PM: Well, wait for the response.<br />
0: Prime Minister are you keeping a very careful eye on<br />
the row between the Liberals and the Nationals of<br />
New South Wales?<br />
PM: Well I've been keeping an eye on it for weeks, I<br />
mean if you go to the country newspapers of the<br />
areas of Hume and the other surrounding Federal<br />
seats you'll find there's been a very bitter war<br />
being conducted by the Liberal and National Parties<br />
on each other, but the clear point in all this was<br />
that the New South Wales Liberal Party is not going<br />
to let its political imperative slip or be talked<br />
down, in the interests of the National Party, by the<br />
Federal Liberal leader. They say the Party's got<br />
prerogatives, our commitments are long term, that of<br />
the Party, and involving other long term people,<br />
people committed long term to the Party like Wal<br />
Fife, and they object to the fact that this sort of<br />
careerist approach, which Dr Hewson has to his<br />
political life is one that basically sells down the<br />
drain the Liberal Party, long term Liberal Party<br />
structural interests. So this is an argument of<br />
some proportions.<br />
Q: Sir how has that differed in keeping Leo Macleay in<br />
his job?<br />
PM: Sorry<br />
Q: How does that differ then from the careerist point<br />
of Leo Macleay?<br />
PM: A great deal. If I said to my Party that I wanted a<br />
change of policy and my Party said no, you would all<br />
write, Prime Minister no longer in charge, Party<br />
decides for him. Dr Hewson has said to his Party<br />
that these contest s ought to be decided to favour<br />
the National Party and his Party has said no. And<br />
as Mr Murray said yesterday anybody who can't make<br />
their Party deliver on such important fundamental<br />
things if they're that weak, said Mr Murray, they<br />
shouldn't be seeking to be the Prime Minister of the<br />
nation.<br />
Q: Liberals are too democratic are they?<br />
PM: I don't think democratic would be the word for it.<br />
The fact is the Liberal Party's got long term<br />
organisational interests, which Dr Hewson does not<br />
identify with, and they're reminding him of his </p>
<p>responsibilities, but reminding him in a very sharp<br />
way.<br />
Q: Can you guarantee young people that at the end of<br />
the day we won't simply have a much better trained,<br />
better educated group on unemployed?<br />
PM: Absolutely, look at the ' 80s experience, people who<br />
are training themselves were taken up in employment<br />
and if you look at the information contained in<br />
there about the responses by industry, lack of<br />
maturity, school levels too low, lack of relevant<br />
training, all those numbers, those very high 87%,<br />
83% indicate that the absence of training is a real<br />
impediment to getting a job. So, hankering for<br />
untrained work in a labour market which is<br />
technologically been subjected to great<br />
technological change is basically hankering back to<br />
the 1960s, in their past, the labour market of those<br />
days is a thing of the past.<br />
Q: But orders decide unemployment or decide employment<br />
levels<br />
PM: Yes, sure, orders of what products? What products?<br />
Services. All the sort of things we now have in the<br />
economy we didn't have in the 1960s.<br />
ENDS </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
