<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8624</transcript-id>
    <title>ENBARGOED AGAINST DELIVERY: APPROX. 6.30PM SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J. KEATING MP THE AGE OF ANGKOR, AUSTRALIAN NATIONAL GALLERY, 21 AUGUST 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/08/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008624.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
. J A R LI<br />
EMBARGOED AGAINST DELIVERY: APPROX. 6.3OPM<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
THE AGE OF ANGKOR, AUSTRALIAN NATIONAL GALLERY,<br />
21 AUGUST 1992<br />
The Honourable Lionel Bowen and Mrs Bowen, Mr Pich Kec,<br />
Ministerial Colleagues, Mr and Mrs Hoare, distinguished<br />
guests, ladies and gentlemen.<br />
I am honoured to be invited to open this exhibition.<br />
It is a very significant exhibition an historic one.<br />
I know what imagination, hard work and persistence have<br />
gone into it.<br />
And part of my duty this evening is to acknowledge the<br />
debt we owe to those who conceived the idea and worked<br />
intensively through the past year to make it a reality.<br />
In particular Mr PichKeo, the Director of the National.<br />
Museum in Phnom Penh.<br />
Mr Keo welcome to Australia; on behalf of the Government<br />
and everyone here, I thank you for your part in this.<br />
Your staff and many others in Cambodia also deserve our<br />
thanks. Mr Hun Sen, I know, gave the project his personal<br />
backing. I look forward to the opportunity to personally deliver<br />
our thanks when I visit Phnomn Penh next month. While I<br />
am there, I hope I will have a chance to visit the<br />
National Museum.<br />
I also want to congratulate Michael Brand,. the curator of<br />
Asian Art here at the Australian National Gallery, both<br />
for his vision and his stamina.<br />
I know that in such things as this there is a long way to<br />
travel between vision and realisation: I know also that<br />
it takes a lot of team work to get there. 1485 </p>
<p>So, for the sake of brevity, I congratulate the people on<br />
the team including the RAAF who took them to Phnom Penh<br />
along with the empty packing crates, and brought them<br />
back with the exhibition.<br />
I must also pay tribute, of course, to my colleague, the<br />
Minister for Foreign Affairs, Gareth Evans.<br />
Gareth's outstanding contribution to the implementation<br />
of a peace process in Cambodia is well known to everyone<br />
here. His support for this proposal is a measure of his<br />
admiration and affection for Cambodia and its people.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen,<br />
Cambodia, rightly I believe, sees the protection of its<br />
cultural heritage as a vital part of the current<br />
reconstruction. The culture of a people unites them. I always think of<br />
it as a great healer.<br />
And Cambodia has tragic wounds to heal.<br />
Just as a nation's cultural heritage unites its people,<br />
so can cultural exchanges such as this one bring people<br />
of different cultures together.<br />
It is because we want to expand our understanding of<br />
Cambodia and other countries in the region where we live<br />
that Australia seeks to develop cultural, as well as<br />
economic and political, relationships.<br />
Much has changed within a generation: among Australians<br />
today there is an awareness and appreciation of Asian<br />
cultures which was unimaginable twenty years ago.<br />
Travel, migration, trade and communications have played<br />
their parts in bringing us closer together.<br />
So will cultural exchanges and in this context the<br />
Australian National Gallery is to be congratulated for<br />
for its efforts to raise the profile of Asian art in<br />
Australia. There is still a long way to go, but the Australian<br />
Government and its agencies are actively pursuing<br />
programs aimed at heightening the level of mutual<br />
understanding through culture and art.<br />
This, then, is an exhibition of great consequence.<br />
Not only does it comprise magnificent and unique works of<br />
art, but it is the first time these works have left<br />
Cambodia.<br />
1486 </p>
<p>We are delighted that Australia should be the first<br />
country in the world to have that honour.<br />
Yet the significance of the exhibition goes well beyond<br />
that. It strengthens the bond between our two countries,<br />
our two peoples.<br />
Australians have been shocked and saddened by the<br />
terrible crimes and suffering inflicted on the Cambodian<br />
people. This exhibition might be taken as a symbol of our hope<br />
that Cambodians are at last succeeding in their struggle<br />
to regain the opportunity for better lives.<br />
As we admire these works, I think we should also pause<br />
for a moment to recall that the peace process on which<br />
these hopes depend still faces severe difficulties.<br />
Along with many others who are contributing to and<br />
supporting the United Nations presence in Cambodia, the<br />
Australian Government is committed to doing all it can to<br />
help the peace process succeed.<br />
In addition to our significant contribution of military<br />
and civilian personnel to the United Nations Transitional<br />
-Authority in Cambodia, this financial year Australia will<br />
provide approximately 15 million dollars in humanitarian<br />
assistance to Cambodia.<br />
We have much to gain from coming to understand the<br />
societies of Asia and we have much to give.<br />
This evening I am happy to annouce a small contribution<br />
we may be able to make towards the rehabilitation of<br />
cultural life in Cambodia.<br />
In an effort to help preserve the important symbol of<br />
Khmer culture and unity which these works of art<br />
represent, the Australian Government and the Australian<br />
National Gallery have agreed to contribute towards a<br />
public appeal to raise S700,000 for urgently needed<br />
repairs at the National Museum of Cambodia.<br />
To help launch the appeal, which will be run at the<br />
Gallery in the course of the exhibition, the Department<br />
of Administrative Services will provide S250,000 in<br />
technical assistance, the Department of Foreign Affairs<br />
and Trade will provide S50,000, and the Gallery will<br />
provide $ 25,000.<br />
Our aim is to raise the remaining S375,000 through a<br />
public appeal, with the Government matching public<br />
contributions on a two for one basis. 1487 </p>
<p>I understand that a promising start to the public appeal<br />
has already been made, with Qantas offering to pay the<br />
cost of flying 12 specialists involved in the Museum<br />
project return from Australia to Bangkok.<br />
In addition to this appeal, theAustralianInternational<br />
Development_ Assistance. Bureau has agreed to ' provide<br />
training and development for the staff of the Museum at a<br />
cost of $ 150,000 over two years.<br />
This training will concentrate on developing skills in<br />
the conservation and restoration of stone and bronze<br />
works, as well as photographic exhibits.<br />
Further assistance will also be possible within<br />
Australia's established sponsored training program for<br />
Cambodia which will allow Museum staff to study in<br />
Australia in conjunction with the Gallery.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen<br />
As I said, it is a privilege to be present at this<br />
opening as it is to see these works.<br />
I sincerely hope we are the first among a multitude.<br />
Once again, let me congratulate all those who have worked<br />
so hard to bring this great project to fruition.<br />
It represents, as I have said, a significant moment in<br />
our cultural history.<br />
I wish it every success.<br />
And I hope in years to come it will be seen to symbolise<br />
peace at last in Cambodia.<br />
Thank you.<br />
1488 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
