<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4757</transcript-id>
    <title>INTERVIEW - BTV 6 BALLARAT</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/07/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004757.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS OFFICE TRANSCRIPT<br />
19 JULY 1978<br />
INTERVIEW BTV 6 BALLARAT<br />
QUESTION: You've come to Ballarat within four weeks of the<br />
Budget bing brought down. How do you begin to draft a<br />
Budget with a $ 3,000 million deficit to cover from last<br />
year? PRIMrE MINISTER: Well, you have to look at all your expenditures,<br />
all the programs of Government. You've got to look at<br />
obligations, payments to the States, you make sure that you<br />
are responsible as you can be in whatever expenditures you<br />
have to undertake and you've got to make decisions overall<br />
which are responsible and in the best interests of Australia.<br />
We are quite determined in what we have been doing over recent<br />
weeks to make sure that taxpayer's dollars are well spent.<br />
We are well aware that whatever Government's spend they've<br />
got to take from people and we are also quite determined<br />
that in its final result, the Budget will be seen as being<br />
responsible, one that will continue to get inflation down,<br />
interest rates continuing to move down in a steady and<br />
sustained manner and that is going to, by that means, help<br />
Australia. QUESTION: You've already hinted that some indirect taxes<br />
will rise. What are some of these indirect taxes?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I don't think I did hint that indirect<br />
taxes would rise. I was asked once on another program about<br />
an inquiry Mr. Howard had initiated into broader-based<br />
indirect taxes. Now that inquiry will take several months,<br />
the Government will have to examine it, and Mr. Howard said<br />
at the time that the purpose of that inquiry was not to raise<br />
more money, but to put the Government in the better position<br />
to make sure that the money it did raise from people was<br />
equitably shared. I think it was against that context that<br />
I'd made remarks about indirect taxes.<br />
QUESTION: You've also described the Budget as being austere<br />
and tough it doesn't sound as if it is going to be one to<br />
gain your Government much popularity.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: It will be an austere budget and I think<br />
everyone understands that it will have to be. But I have<br />
sufficient faith in all the people of Australia to believe<br />
that they respect a responsible budget and I do not believe<br />
that they any longer respect politicians who merely promise<br />
to spend more of other people's money because when politicians<br />
make promises to spend and spend up big, they are not promising<br />
anyth~ ing of their own. They are promising something which they<br />
first have to take from people like you and people watching<br />
this program and indeed all the taxpayers of Australia and<br />
I believe that the overwhelmingly majority of Australians know<br />
that that kind of policy gets this country into a great deal<br />
of trouble and they don't want it any more. </p>
<p>-2<br />
QUESTION: Sir, you are not going to give much away about the<br />
Budget, so can we turn to...<br />
PRIME MINISTER: On August 15, Mr. Howard will give it all<br />
away he'll let it be know then.<br />
QUESTION: Fair enough. Returning to employment. Now you saw<br />
some of Ballarat's unemployed here today and figures released<br />
this morning show that our unemployment rate is 9 percent of<br />
the work force. What is your answer to these people say these<br />
people that demonstrated this morning?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: -There are a number of things that I would like<br />
to say about that. First, I understand that tho ' se who demonstrated<br />
this morning were not unemployed. They had shut down their<br />
factory for the day so they could come and demonstrate against me.<br />
I also understand that they've got work bans on the factory so<br />
that they won't work more than 35 hours a week and as a consequence<br />
the factory is having to turn away orders because orders that have<br />
to be filled within a certain time can't be filled under these<br />
bans. Now that is a classic example of union activity, which I<br />
wouldn't have thought the majority of the blokes support which...<br />
QUESTION: I think these people were under retrenchment notices.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well, some might have been, but the bans are<br />
sti-1lon the factory for the reasons that I have mentioned.<br />
Whether they are under retrenchment notices or not, I don't know,<br />
but that kind of action and the kind of action by the Builders<br />
Labourers in Melbourne, which has led to the cessation of work on<br />
a major building I think about $ 150 million worth has led to<br />
a great deal of employment just not being created. In Melbourne<br />
many major projects have just been abandoned and hundreds of<br />
jobs lost because of the tactics of a number of union leaders.<br />
Now that is obviously not the only problem but I make those points<br />
to indicate that in getting back to a proper employment base,<br />
everyone in this country has got a role; Governments have got<br />
a role, trade unions have got a role, and employers. Now, for<br />
our part, we've got to go on getting inflation down. We've got<br />
to make sure there is stability in this country. We've got to<br />
get access to the maximum extent in markets overseas. Employers<br />
have got to show inventiveness, initiative, and they've got to<br />
work well with their own people, their employees. But we need to<br />
understand that our interests in this area are interests as<br />
Australian which we share; they are not competing interests. The<br />
sort of action which seeks to drive up wages too high, the tourist<br />
industry in many areas has been destroyed by penalty rates now<br />
these are things that are only going to be solved if the trade<br />
unions, and the people in the industry, can get together and work<br />
out a way which allows an industry to operate profitably.<br />
QUESTION: There appears to be a vicious circle at the moment;<br />
employers are reluctant to take on more staff because of high<br />
costs. ./ 3 </p>
<p>-3<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I think that's true. You see in one two-year<br />
period wage rates, hourly wage rates, went up by over 50% and<br />
that was much higher than our competitors, much higher than<br />
people overseas. Inflation in Australia at the same time went<br />
up much more than that of many other countries. Now we've<br />
got inflation down, it has in fact fallen in this country<br />
faster than in any other OECD country over the last couple of<br />
years and we will keep on getting it down and I think we will<br />
have it below the average of a number of our major trading<br />
partners I think really our inflation rate is below the<br />
United States now and that will start to make Australian industry<br />
more competitive again. But these particular attempts are in<br />
part frustrated when unions go on wage claims outside the<br />
indexation process and they are also frustrated if the<br />
Arbitration Commission awards wage increases which are<br />
unreasonably high.<br />
QUESTION: Now, we've already discussed the National Budget,<br />
local Governments too are working on their documents and many<br />
Municipal Councils are claiming that the ten percent increase<br />
in the General Purposes Grant is less adequate than the 1.52%<br />
of the share of income tax. Can you explain this?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well, I think I can, yes. All Governments<br />
of Australia had got into a state of going on spending more<br />
year after year after year. Now the taxpayers of Australia,<br />
in the case of local government, ratepayers obviously can't<br />
afford to go on having their rates put up, especially in rural<br />
communities where many people were going through difficult<br />
times; drought, disastrously low beef prices, and other difficulties,<br />
and you know the idea that governments at any level whether<br />
it is Federal or Local or State can and should spend a larger<br />
share of Australia's resources year after year, is a view that<br />
I am quite certain the overwhelming majority of Australians reject<br />
and that applies to local government as much as it does to the<br />
Federal Government. We've sought to supplement the funds to local<br />
governments so they can make their own decisions.-We enormously<br />
increased grants to local government in the first year of about<br />
million to $ 8Qmillion to $ 140 million, that went to over<br />
$ 160 million last year and that will go to over $ 180 million<br />
this year. It is a 10% increase it is much more than enough<br />
to cope with inflation that is running at maybe 7% in that sort<br />
of order and therefore gives them greater real resources coming<br />
from the Commonwealth. Now, against that background, I believe<br />
there is no justification for local governments saying that the<br />
sum is inadequate and I hope also that their ratepayers and<br />
if I can speak as a ratepayer at a moment will be putting their<br />
view to the local government that rates also ought to be held<br />
and not increased. We do have a commitment to move from 1.52%<br />
of income tax collections to 2% but against the budgetary<br />
circumstances that we knew we were facing, we said we couldn't<br />
do it this year and that still means that the significant increase<br />
which I mentioned, does flow to local government. / 4 </p>
<p>-4<br />
QUESTION: One councillor in your own electorate said he<br />
believes they have been sold a pup because you haven't increased<br />
the share of income tax.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:-We said we would do it over the life of the<br />
Parliament and we will, but at the same time there are<br />
substantial increases from a bit over $ 160 million to around<br />
about $ 180 million and if that's a pup, it's a very expensive<br />
PUP. QUESTION: Can I ask you now for some comments on one or<br />
two rural matters. First, the issue of the export of live<br />
merino rams. Now the Graziers Association has asked your<br />
Government to back its decision to lift this ban despite union<br />
interference. Do you expect union interference?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I would hope that there won't be and that common<br />
sense will prevail. I'm sure the rams will be exported.<br />
QUESTION: On the matter of sheep and wool, can you update<br />
growers on what's happening to the submission made in 1974<br />
by the Wool Corporation on their marketing plan?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: The marketing plan was put forward, there were<br />
discussions with the industry that involved quite substantial<br />
changes from the present marketing, a further change towards, if<br />
you like centralised control and a year or so ago the Minister<br />
negotiated with the industry, the Marketing Corporation, to<br />
undertake an experiment to demonstrate whether they could by<br />
these means, handle wool more cheaply than is done through the<br />
sources presently used. But until we see the results of that<br />
the Government would be reluctant to take further steps. We<br />
need to understand in the wool industry, that we have a marketing<br />
operation that is working extraordinarily well. It has put<br />
a floor in the industry, that floor price has been steadily<br />
increased. It was increased two or three weeks ago for the opening<br />
of this season and at the same time the Corporation has been<br />
getting rid of surplus stocks. There is stability in the price,<br />
the price going to growers is a good price. The price of sheep<br />
is good and the system I was one of the early advocates for<br />
change and back as early as 1960 or ' 61 was advocating substantial<br />
changes to the system of marketing. But what we've got now<br />
is quite different from the free and open unregulated auction<br />
system of older days and its working very well to the advantage<br />
of growers and therefore when we take further changes, we want<br />
to be cautious and make sure they are going to be successful<br />
and that they don't in any sense jeopardise the gains and<br />
the advances that have been made and again I believe that<br />
would be a view that would be shared by a majority of<br />
woo lgrowers.<br />
QUESTION: A matter closer to your own heart, being a beef breeder,<br />
the U. S. A. recently expressed interest in a $ 90 million order<br />
of Australian beef. Are there any other orders of this magnitude<br />
in the pipeline? </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER: Well, this is a particularly large order.<br />
I believe that the beef industry has turned through the<br />
bottom. Now I had hoped this would have arisen earlier,<br />
a year ago it didn't but the United States had had<br />
very severe drought over about half of America and in our<br />
terms about 25 states would have been declared drought areas.<br />
As a result, their own cattle numnbers have come down about<br />
million over the last two to three years; they have been<br />
selling enormous numbers of additional surplus stock breeders<br />
for their manufacturing meat which was competing directly<br />
with our Northern Queensland/ Australian beef. Now, their<br />
droughts have broken, they are facing better seasons, as we<br />
are, they are going to want to build up their stock numbers<br />
again and over a period of years; and that means that there has<br />
been a substantial shortage of meat on the American market<br />
and that's the basic reason why they are importing more from<br />
us. While that additional quotas, imports, were to come into<br />
this United States by Christmas of this year, I don't believe<br />
we are in a short-term situation. They are going to need<br />
more meat, not just from now to Christmas, but I believe for<br />
years ahead and against the backgrou~ nd that our own beef<br />
numbers are down about 4 million, I really do believe that<br />
the beef industry has turned the corner; prices are now<br />
much better, I have no reason to believe that those better<br />
prices won't be sustained. At the same time, of course, we<br />
are going for increased access to markets in Japan and in<br />
Europe, and in Japan we are having some success, and we are<br />
getting access into other markets also. So, for the beef<br />
industry I think the future is bright and I think this is<br />
already reflected in the great farming and pastoral communities<br />
of Australia because there is an optimism in the air in rural<br />
Australia with forecasts of up to 40% increase in rural<br />
incomes this coming year now we haven't had forecasts of<br />
that kind for seven or eight years and that's not only good<br />
news for farmers and graziers, it's also good news for country<br />
towns that feel it very much when farmers themselves are in<br />
difficulty. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
