<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4008</transcript-id>
    <title>MAJOR CHANGES IN  MINISTERIAL AND DEPARTMENTAL RESPONSIBILITIES AND FUNCTIONS - 18 DECEMBER 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/12/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004008.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
MAJOR CHANGES IN MINISTERIAL AND DEPARTMENTAL<br />
RESPONSIBILITIES AND FUNCTIONS De( Si1<br />
The Prime Minister gave the following details about major<br />
changes to be made to the administrative structure:<br />
Administrative Services<br />
The Department of Administrative Services will include, in<br />
addition to the functions previously held by that Department, many<br />
of the functions carried out by the Departments of the Special<br />
Minister of State and of the Media, which are to be abolished.<br />
In addition, it will be responsible for the property and survey<br />
functions of the Department of Urban and Regional Development and<br />
the Overseas Property Bureau from the Department of Foreigii Affairs.<br />
The Department will work closely with the Department of Prime<br />
M~ sinister and Cabinet.<br />
Attorney-General<br />
This Department will now concentrate on more purely legal<br />
aspects of the Governments work. Regulatory activities are imore<br />
effectively situated in the Department of Business and Consumer<br />
Affairs. It is proposed that the Attorney-General should resume<br />
responsibility for the Australian Security Intelligence Organisation<br />
although the Director-General of Security would have responsibility<br />
to report directly to the Prime Minister.<br />
Business and Consumer Affairs<br />
This Department will assume responsibility for business practices,<br />
bankruptcy and insolvency, patents, trade marks and copyright<br />
froin the Attorney-General's Department, the customs and excise<br />
functions from the Department of Police and Customs, which is to<br />
be abolished, and consumer affairs from the Department of Science<br />
and Consumer Affairs. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
These functions will now be administered by a Department<br />
which is organised to have close contact with the community,<br />
consumers and business. The Department will have a strong<br />
practical orientation which will ensure that regulatory activities<br />
are carried out in the public interest. The Department will<br />
maintain close contact with other more specialised Departments.<br />
it is proposed that the Minister for Business and Consumer<br />
Affairs would be responsible for the-. Industries Assistance Commission,<br />
the Temporary Assistance Authority, the Prices Justification Tribun*<br />
and the Trade Practices Commission.<br />
Responsibility for the future Securities and Exchange legislate<br />
would be within this Ministry.<br />
Employment and Industrial Relations and Immigration and Ethnic Affairs.<br />
These proposed new Departments will result from the abol~ itioni<br />
of the Department of Labor and Immigration, and the separation of<br />
the employment and industrial relations functions from the immigration<br />
functions. The creation of a Department of Immigration and Ethnic<br />
Affairs indicates the importance placed by the Government on the<br />
immigration programme and its concern that issues affecting migrants<br />
and their families in Australia should receive close and sympatheti* e<br />
attent ion in line with the Government' s announced prograim-me. The<br />
creation of the Department will be the specific fulfilment of an<br />
election promise given by the Coalit ion* Parties.<br />
Environment, Housing and Community Development.<br />
The Departments of Urban and Regional Development, the. Environment<br />
and Tourism and Recreati-on are to be abolished as separate entities. </p>
<p>-3-<br />
The proposed new Department of Environment, Housing and<br />
Community Developmeht would be responsible for the majority of<br />
functions of all three Departments together with the housing<br />
function of the Department of Housing and Construction. This<br />
will be a large and important Department working closely with<br />
the States. In its operation it will express the Government's<br />
view that matters of local concern will be undertaken with<br />
maximum consultation and concern for local conditions.<br />
Responsibility for the National Capital Development Commission<br />
will transfer back to the Minister for the Capital Territory. The<br />
administration of the Housing Loans Insurance Corporation and the<br />
in surance provisions of the Defence Service Homes Act will<br />
be transferred from the Dept. -of . Repatriation and Compensation.<br />
The Australian Government works functions from the Department<br />
of Housing and Construction would be the: responisibili-ty of the<br />
proposed new Department of Construction.<br />
Health It is proposed that responsibility for Medibank be transferred<br />
from the Department of Social Security to the Department of Health...<br />
Industry and Commerce<br />
This proposed re-naming of the Department of Manufacturing<br />
Industry takes account of the Government's intention to widen<br />
its functions to include tertiary industry including the tourist<br />
industry, an increased concern with small business and a transfer<br />
to it of responsibility for shipbuilding from the Department of<br />
Transport. National Resources<br />
This proposed re-naming of the Department of Minerals and<br />
Energy indicates the broadening of the Department's functions to<br />
include the water resources functions of the Department of<br />
Environment and the Department of Northern Australia. </p>
<p>-4-<br />
Postal and Telecommunications<br />
This proposed re-nam-Ling of the Postmaster-General's Department<br />
takes account of the increase in the functions of the Department<br />
to include all electronic media matters which are the responsibility<br />
of the Department of the Media. The Minister for Post and<br />
Telecommunications would be responsible for the A. B. C. and A. B. C. B.<br />
Repatriation It is proposed -to transfer the compensation functions from the:<br />
Department of Repatriation and Compensation to the Department of<br />
Social Security and to transfer the Housing Insurance functions to<br />
the D epartment of Environment, Housing and community Development.<br />
Treasury It is proposed to transfer responsibility for the Australian<br />
Industry Development Corporation from the Minister . for Manufacturing<br />
Industry and the Australian Bureau of Statistics from the Special<br />
Minister of State to the Treasurer.<br />
Senior Appointments<br />
As a consequence of the abolition, creation and renaming of<br />
Departments, there will be a number of appointments to the<br />
position of Pernaneni Head. The list of Permanent Heads of<br />
Departments will be as follows: </p>
<p>The Secretary to the<br />
Department of Aboriginal<br />
Affairs The Secretary to the<br />
Department of<br />
Administrative Services<br />
The Secretary to the Attorney-<br />
General's Department<br />
The Comptroller-General of<br />
Customs ( Permanent Head<br />
of the Department of<br />
Business and Consumer<br />
Affairs) The Secretary to-the<br />
Department of the Capital<br />
Territory The Secretary to the<br />
Department of<br />
Construction and Director-<br />
General of Works<br />
The Secretary to the<br />
Department of Defence<br />
The Secretary to the<br />
Department of Education<br />
The Secretary to the<br />
Department of Environment-,<br />
Housing and Community<br />
Development The Secretary to the<br />
Department of Foreign<br />
Affairs The Director-General of<br />
Health The Secretary to the<br />
Department of<br />
Industry and Commerce<br />
The Secretary to the<br />
Department of National<br />
Resources MR. B. G. DEXTER,<br />
MR. P. J. LAWLER, O. B. E.<br />
MR. C. W. HARDERS, O. B. E.<br />
MR. A. T. CARMODY, C. B. E.<br />
MR. L. W. B. ENGLEDOW<br />
MR. A. S. REIHER<br />
SIR ARTHUR TANGE, C. B. E.<br />
MR. K. N-JONES, C. B. E.<br />
MR. R. B. LANSDOWN<br />
MR. A. P. RENOUF, O. B. E.<br />
DR. G. HOWELLS.<br />
MR. N. S. CURRIE, O. B. E.<br />
MR. J. SCULLY </p>
<p>The Secretary to the<br />
Department of the<br />
Northern Territory<br />
The Secretary to the<br />
Department of<br />
Overseas Trade<br />
The Secretary to the Postal<br />
and Telecommunications<br />
Department The Secretary to the<br />
Department of Primary<br />
Industry The Secretaryto the<br />
Department of the Prime<br />
Minister and Cabinet<br />
The Secretary to the<br />
Department of<br />
Repatriation and<br />
Chairman of the<br />
Repatriation Commission<br />
The Secretary to the<br />
Department of Science<br />
The Director-General of<br />
Social Services<br />
The Secretary to the<br />
Department of<br />
Transport The Secretary to the<br />
Department of'the<br />
Treasury MR. R. S. LIVINGSTON<br />
MR. D. H. McKAY, O. B. E.<br />
MP. F. J. GREEN<br />
MR. W. IVES<br />
MR-. J. L. MENADUE<br />
MR. R. KINGSLAND C. B. E, D. F. C. 0<br />
SIR HUGH ENNOR, C. B. E.<br />
MR. L. J. DANIELS, O. B. E. 0<br />
MR.* C. C. HALTON<br />
SIR FREDERICK WHEELER, C. B. E. 0<br />
Pending consideration of the filling of the Permanent Head<br />
positions in the Department of Employment and Industrial Relations,<br />
and Immigration and Ethnic Affairs, Mr. K. C. McKenzie, a Deputy<br />
Secretary in the present Department of Labor and Immigration, will<br />
act in both positions.<br />
Consideration is being given to the placement of other Permanent<br />
Heads of existing departments and these matters will be finalised<br />
as soon as possible. In accordance with the statement of 9 November<br />
1975, their rights will not be compromised. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
