<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>141</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT, HON. R.G MENZIES AT THE OFFCIAL OPEINING OF THE CUNNINGHAM LABORATORIES BRISBANE, MONDAY , 30TH NOVEMBER, 1959</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/11/1959</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000141_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE RT. HON. R. G.<br />
MENZIES AT THE OFFICIAL OPENING OF THE CUNNINGHAM<br />
LABORATORIES RISBANE,-MONDAY., 30TH NOVEMBER, 1291.<br />
Dr. White and Ladies and Gentlemen, I think I ought to<br />
follow my normal practice by naming them the Cunningham Laboratories<br />
and declaring them open before I get taken up with my own<br />
remarks and forget to do what I came here to do.<br />
I never think of the C. SQI. R. O. without thinking of<br />
two things quite detached, one from the other, though they may<br />
be. First of all I think of money, because under Dr. White's<br />
very distinguished predecessor, Sir Ian Clunies-Ross, one of the<br />
great men in the history of this country and, I regret to say, no<br />
less under him, every time I see somebody from the C. S. I. R. O.<br />
around, money crops up. W1ell, the subject of money crops up,<br />
and sometimes the money crops up too! Every time my colleague,<br />
Mr. Casey, comes in to see me with a particularly thoughtful air<br />
I don't fall into the error of thinking that he's worrying very<br />
much, that day, about Laos or Cambodia or one of these other<br />
trouble centres in the world; it is bound to end up by him saying<br />
to me: " You know, we're getting a very poor deal in C. S. I.<br />
And so millions are produced from time to time and we go<br />
through all the motions of pretending to be annoyed, but in<br />
reality I don't mind telling you we're very proud of the work of<br />
C. S. I. R. O. ( Applause)<br />
I don't know of any institution, if I may call it by<br />
that horrible name, which has done continuously such magnificent<br />
work, so much of it, perhaps, little recognised. It isn't only<br />
a Government enterprise this; it has, particularly in recent<br />
years, been able to attract from the great primary industries a<br />
considerable amount of support, as these great industries have<br />
more and more realised that research in their industry is the<br />
whole condition of future success, and both Dr. White and I have<br />
an ambition in common, and that is, that as years go by more and<br />
more will the great secondary industries of Australia realise<br />
the tremendous importance of this work, and themselves come to<br />
contribute more and more to its achievement.<br />
When Dr. W~ hite was speaking about Cunningham, the<br />
lawyer gone wrong the Botanist gone right, I thought to myself:<br />
' Well, there are two things, to people of my generation, that<br />
stick out very clearly in the memory'. The first is that when<br />
I was a student, Botany was regarded as a rather feminine<br />
attainment ( laughter). People who studied Botany were supposed<br />
to be those useful people who could walk around a suburban<br />
garden with you and dazzle you with science. Just as I was<br />
thinking to myself -my wife's good at this, I'm not -now: ' Is<br />
that a carnation or -what's the other thing I like -a<br />
geranium?' the hostess, or hier friend who was a student of Botany,<br />
would be attributing in a somewhat ill-pronounced Latin the most<br />
remarkable names to all these vegetables that one happened to be<br />
looking at. Botany I think I'm right Dr. W4hite in saying<br />
that 30 or 40 years ago this was regarded as a rather amiable<br />
sort of occupation, and in that period of time it has come to be<br />
one of the dominating things in the development of Australia.<br />
The second thing that one always recalls is that, 4o<br />
years ago, I'm going back I'll make it 50 years ago back to<br />
my own time, when I was a boy it was well understood that<br />
Australia had a fertile coastal belt and that inside that there<br />
was country that ranged from " Marginal" that horrible word<br />
to " Desert", the great dead heart of Australia, and there were<br />
vast tracts of land now completely fertile and productive<br />
which were regarded as unworthy of the attention of sensible<br />
human beings. There were vast areas of Queensland covered with<br />
prickly pear and not available for productive employment in the<br />
production and growth of stock. </p>
<p>e a 2.<br />
And then the scientists got to work and the great<br />
leader among the scientists has been, Sir, your wonderful Organisation.<br />
And they got to work and they said: " You know this<br />
can't be right" and thae result is, that today, by a variety of<br />
means running from the work of the metallurgists to the work of<br />
the entomologists and the botanists, there are millions of acres<br />
of land in Australia, fertile, productive, which were at that<br />
time regarded as, more or less, hopeless and useless. The last<br />
development, and we are associating ourselves with it today, has<br />
been to devote proper study to the improvement of pastures, the<br />
introduction of new g-rasses the discovery of leg-umes in the<br />
sub-tropical areas of Australia, because everybody who thinks<br />
about these problems except in terms of current œ Cs Ss and pence<br />
knows perfectly well, that much production in sub-tropical areas<br />
has been grievously handicapped in the past by an undue dependence<br />
on native grasses, by our relative failure so far, to<br />
discover the right kind of grasses, and above all, the right<br />
kind of legumnes if we are going to improve our production of<br />
cattle; not only of dairy herds, but of cattle in the vast and<br />
growing meat industry of Australia. And I like to look forward<br />
6n these matters. I like to feel, and I'm sure you do, Sir,<br />
that on top of all this work on the sub-tropical areas of Aus-*<br />
tralia will come concentrated work on the tropical areas of<br />
Australia. How much remains to be done in the north of Queensland,<br />
for example. If we could only encourage our scientific<br />
people in their patient work, because it is patient work, to<br />
discover these remarkable instruments for growth and development,<br />
I said then, Sir, tit's patient work'. I'm afraid,<br />
speaking on behalf of rmy own craft, the politicians, we are<br />
sometimes tempted to bel~ ieve that if we find a few million pounds<br />
today we will have thirty million pounds worth of results in 12<br />
months time. And it doesn't just happen in that way. It may be<br />
that in these very Labs, there will be work done under simulated<br />
conditions which will last, by trial and error and careful expe: 1&gt;.-<br />
rnent, for 10 or 15 yeas, and nobody may be able to say that any<br />
one of those years, to the political people ulho produce so much<br />
of the funds: " Yes we have a result, 9 and this is going to be<br />
worth so-and-so". Science just doesn't operate in that way. As<br />
citizens of this country it is our duty to find just as much as<br />
we can for the scientists to enable them to do their work, take<br />
every possible pains to see that-Je have earnest and skilful<br />
people engag': ed in the -work and then leave it to them, because<br />
the best re sults they will obtain will not be as a result of some<br />
happy fluke, as so many people choose to think, but the best<br />
results will come as a result of patient examination, patient<br />
testing, patient elimination of things that have proved not to<br />
be useful. Ofcourse, there will be happy flukes. 11ho am I to<br />
deny the existence in the world of happy flukes? I'm one myself<br />
But all scientific work doesn't involve the happy fluke. It<br />
involves enormous scholarship, and skill, and patien and support.<br />
I believe, you know, that out of the work that will be<br />
done here weO may very wroll hope some dqr to find the production<br />
let us take one case the production of cattle in these subtropical<br />
areas, multipled four or five times. And think of what<br />
that can mean to a State like Queensland, so rich in resources,<br />
so many of her resources so difficult to tap. And after all,<br />
what's -ood for Queensland is good for Australia, and what's<br />
good for Australia is good for the living standards of men and<br />
women all over the world.<br />
So, Sir, I'm most honoured and delighted to be here tht,<br />
aftornoon. I can see, sitting, around here today, people who have<br />
been closely associated with this remarkable work. I wish it<br />
well: it's a great honour to be asked even to speak for a few<br />
minutes on such an occasion, and feeling that way, I express my<br />
gratitude. I offer you and your colleagues the gratitude of the<br />
fgcooo ur ndgtoorwtynt, e na nandid t a novnIec eid le mcaloa rrpee, l aqntuhoeet. Lhaabvoinrga ~ orcyo notrpaerny, taon d pIas wt ilelx, p eIri etnhcien, k, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
