<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>866</transcript-id>
    <title>BROADCAST OVER NATIONAL STATIONS  - FINAL BROADCAST</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/11/1963</release-date>
    <release-type>Broadcast</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000866_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>63/ 143<br />FINAL BROADCAST: BROADCAST BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE RT.<br />HON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES, OVER NATIONAL<br />STATIONS AT 7.15 P. M. ON WEDNESDAY, 27th<br />NOVEMBER, 1963.<br />This campaign began with contests in the fields<br />of foreign affairs and defence, contests which continue in full<br />vigour and political significance. We then moved into domestic<br />problems particularly housing and education about which<br />I will say something. But, quite late in the campaign, Mr. Calwell has<br />produced a brand-new item of policy, of tremendous importance.<br />Labour, if elected, will abolish preferential voting for the<br />House of Representatives, a voting system which has operated<br />in Australia for 4+ 5 years, unchallenged by either Party, Its<br />whole purpose is to ensure that no man may be elected a Member<br />if most of his electors don't want him. Take a simple example:<br />Suppose there is a country seat which is being contested by<br />Labour, Liberal and Country Party candidates. Both Liberal and<br />Country Party candidates support the Government. The real<br />question is: " Which of the two Government parties should win<br />a clearly Government seat? Let the people decide,"<br />Now, under preferential voting, suppose the count<br />of first preferences showed Labour 18,000<br />Liberal 16,000<br />Country Party 11,000<br />The second preferences of the Country Party candidate, if they<br />went only 80 per cent. to the Liberal and 20 per cent. to Labour,<br />would produce a final count of<br />Liberal 24+, 800<br />Labour 20,200<br />This would be a proper result, since clearly most voters did not<br />want Labour. Mr. Calwell now promises to abolish this voting<br />system by reverting to " first past the post". This would mean<br />that Labour would win the seat with 18,000 votes out of 1+ 5100.<br />I hope you will clearly understand what Mr, Calwell<br />is after. He would destroy all minority parties, such as the<br />DLP and other groups, by making their votes virtually votes for<br />Labour. In short, if Labour wins this election, it will<br />" rig" the voting system so as to make Labour undefeatable for a<br />long time. There are curious aspects of this matter, It was<br />Mr. Calwell in the Chifley Government, who was the architect<br />of the new genate voting system proportional representation.<br />Up to that time, Senate voting was " first pest the post", which<br />left minorities in a State with no representation at all.</p>
<p>2-<br />Mr. Calwell proposes to keep the new Senate system, since in<br />every State it assures Tabour of some Senators. He is all for<br />proportional representation to keep control, or near-control, of<br />the Senate, and now all for " first past the post" for the House<br />of Representatives to keep control of that House,<br />But the matter does not end there. Labour wants<br />" first past the post" for the House of Representatives. But<br />it chooses its own candidates for Parliament by the preferential<br />voting systemi And how does it choose its Parliamentary leader and<br />the members of its Parliamentary Exeoutive? By exhaustive ballotnot<br />by " first past the post". Let's say that there are<br />Labour Senators and Members meeting to choose a leader. And<br />let's suppose that four offer themselves for election. On the<br />first vote, A gets 30 votes, B 25 votes, C 20 votes and D 5 votes.<br />So the chairman of the meeting strikes out D, and another vote is<br />taken, and so on until somebody has 41 votes, or an absolute<br />majority. As you will see, the purpose is the same as in<br />preferential voting. Yet, under the system Mr. Calwell now<br />advocates for the House of Representatives, A would instantly<br />win, with 30 votes out of 801<br />I urge you to beware of this recently-disclosed<br />Labour Policy. It is designed to destroy minorities and to<br />give Labour perpetual power. And who will exercise Lhis power?<br />Not the people you send to Parliament, but the outside Executive,<br />the 36 men who owe you no responsibility at all, but whose<br />decisions and orders a Calwell government would be bound implicitly<br />to obeyl Our housing and education programmes, to which I made<br />a brief reference earlier have been attracting great attention<br />among younger voters, This has been manifest in -each State and<br />at all my meetings, These voters acknowledge generously what<br />we have achieved in both fields; but they are looking forward to<br />marriage, to home building, to children and to the education of<br />' those children to be good citizens, good builders of a growing<br />nation. In effect, what they are saying to us is " What can you<br />do to help us to help ourselves and our children and the nation?"<br />Now, this is no selfish attitude. It is a constructive and<br />imaginative attitude. We have tried to meet it in our policy.<br />Thus our scheme for subsidising a saved deposit on a home at the<br />rate of V1 for œ 3 for married people in the " under 35 age group"<br />with a maximum subsidy ( that is, a gift not repayable) of œ E250,<br />will give great encouragement to those who ineed it at the right<br />time and in the right way. For most ambitious young miarried<br />couples want to have a hone of their own. This indeed is the<br />ideal of genuinely civilised democracy. The ownership of a home<br />is the kind of security which naturally attracts them because it<br />represents a measure of independence. I understand the Opposition<br />now questions the validity of our proposal. Mr. Calwell will be<br />surprised to see how valid it is.<br />Similarly, in our new education proposals, we have<br />been looking in a practical w33 to the future. The parents of<br />families want their children to have the best education they can<br />afford. They want this education to enable their child to advance<br />in life, in character, in skill and in reward. The best parents,<br />I have no doubt, want their children to be trained to be good<br />citizens and good contributors to the advancement of the nation.<br />e / 3</p>
<p>-3<br />Recognising this, We have put forward three<br />Completely new propositions.<br />The first concerns the encouraging of secondary<br />School students to put in some extra time on their secondary<br />studies SO that they may be better qualified thereafter, and<br />the encouraging of their parents to persuade themi to taeti<br />extra time. This is frequently a matter of great faily<br />difficulty. To facilitate extra training for bright boys and<br />girls at secondary schools we will award each year 10 000<br />scholarships, tenable for Lhe two later years at seconaary<br />schools; each scholarship will be worth up to œ-100 a year for<br />fees and books, and œ 100 a year for maintenance. Secondary<br />schools will include those which are public and those which are<br />independent. Second, the provision of 2 ,500 technici1 school<br />scholarships will be made on the samae terms and for similar<br />purposes. The demand in Australia for-technically skilled<br />people is growing, Indeed, the supply of competent technicians<br />very frequently deteroines the extent to which any enterprise<br />can employ unskilled labour. To assist in this field, we are<br />proposing to find each year a non-repayable grant of œ C5M. a<br />year to the States for the building and equipment of technical<br />school facilities, Third, it is essential that provision for science<br />teaching in the secondary schools should be modern and adequate<br />if we are to draw from -them into the universities and into<br />post-graduate and research work the scientists and technologists<br />we will increasingly need, We are therefore proposing to<br />distribute fœ 5M. a year among secondary schools, again without<br />discrimination, for the building and equipment of science<br />laboratories and, in this way, the encouragement of science<br />teaching. It has been clearly observed by large audiences of<br />younger electors whora I have addressed that these practical<br />proposals, well-considered, not extravagant but most valuable,<br />will open up new avenues in life for many thousands of younger<br />people who might otherwise fail to enter them.<br />Finally, I go back to wihere I began to foreign<br />affairs and defence to the vital matter of national security,<br />without which no domestic progress can be achieved. When you<br />recall how much the present Government has strengthened our<br />alliances on a basis of co-operation, diplomatically and<br />militarily for the common security against Communist aggression,<br />do you really feel tempted to entrust our relations with the<br />United Kingdom, the United States, and our other friends, to<br />the left-wingers and the compromisers who make up the great<br />majority of ILabourts non-elected Parliament? It is because<br />we think that such dangerous nonsense will never be entertained<br />by a majority of our Australian people that we ask you with<br />confidence for a sweeping victory on Saturday.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
