<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5847</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/06/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005847.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER~<br />
FOR MEDIA SUNDAY, 27 JUNE 1982<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
There were three main issues at the Premiers' Conference and<br />
at the Loan Council. First, giving the States responsibility<br />
for their own electricity borrowings and the greater Commonwealth<br />
authority in nationd 1 econcirnic mranagement and third, the funding level<br />
for the States following the Grants Commission report.<br />
The Commonwealth's package to the Loan Council produced some<br />
historic decisions, giving the States freedom to determine<br />
the size of thieir electricity borrowings and to set the<br />
interest rates on them, will make the states responsible for<br />
their own electricity programs, and that greater degree of<br />
responsibility will be welcomed by the community.<br />
The Premiers also agreed to provide much more information about<br />
their electricity authorities, to publish audits and tariff rates<br />
and so end any secret deals on special electricity tariffs.<br />
This information will open these authorities up to far more<br />
public scrutiny and help in making the States more responsible<br />
for their actions in a real sense.<br />
The Loan Council also determined that the Commonwealth have<br />
greater flexibility to use instruments which are vital in<br />
national economic management through a tender system for<br />
selling Commonwealth bonds as recommended by the Campbell<br />
Committee, and through delegated authority to set terms and<br />
conditions for the sale of Australian Savings Bonds. This will<br />
make money supply management simpler than it has been for the<br />
Commonwealth in the past. The Commonwealth will be able to<br />
take the decisions in its own right where before it has been<br />
necessary to consult in detail with six Premiers. No<br />
longer will we need agreement from the state Premiers to adjust<br />
rates, no longer will national economic objectives in this<br />
area be constrained by state political considerations.<br />
In relation t~ o the tax sharing grants all States have received<br />
significant real increases in their funds. on present estimates<br />
the overall increase on last year's base grant will be 17.1%<br />
and they coul~ d only have achieved more through higher taxation.<br />
This year's tax sharing arrangements, taking into account the<br />
million the Commonwealth put in last year-as a first step<br />
towards the new shares, means a 17.2% increase for New South<br />
Wales and a 1.6.8% increase for Victoria. Arnd if the Labor Premiers<br />
of those two states cannot manage their affairs on the basis of<br />
that sort of increase then they should let somebody else do the<br />
job for them. / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
Immediate adoption of the Grants Commission report would have<br />
meant an actual reduction in dollar * terms for two of the smaller<br />
states. No Au~ stralian would want to impose that kind of hardship<br />
on the smaller states; no Australian would regard that as a<br />
fair deal.<br />
The Grants Commission itself suggested phasing in the recommendat ions<br />
and the Commonwealth has guaranteed to the three smaller states<br />
who dtood to l. ose that they will receive some real increase<br />
in the tax sharing funds over the next three years. No one<br />
can suggest with any validity that it is discrimination against<br />
Victoria and New South Wales when they are getting 16.8% and<br />
17.2% respecth'vely compared to Western Australia and Tasmania,<br />
which will be getting a 12.2% increase under the Commonwealth's<br />
guarantee. But now, against the background of a 16.8% increase for Victoria,<br />
the Cain Labor Government is threatening to reduce hospital<br />
services for t: he people living in three specific Federal electorates<br />
including Wannon. Never before have the people of particular<br />
electorates been threatened in this way. Using constituents in<br />
this callous way is a new low in Australian politics, and the<br />
Cain Labor Government will surely pay the price of this<br />
explicit discrimination because ordinary Australians will not<br />
stand for this kind of tactic by Governments.<br />
The Cain Labor Government has made it perfectly plain that they<br />
picked out the people of the electorates of Wannon,* Corangamite<br />
and Gippsland because they are represented by three Federal<br />
Ministers. Before I conclude tonight, I would like to say something about<br />
the Brisbane Games and Mr Whitlam's trip to Africa. The<br />
Commonwealth Games are one of the world's great sporting events<br />
and all Australians were delighted when any shadow of a boycott<br />
was lifted last May by the Games Federation's agreement to<br />
full participation. Mr Whitlam may have subsequently denied<br />
any intention to advise an African boycott of the Games, but<br />
I would like to remind you all of the terms of the original<br />
press statement that was issued which also announced his<br />
participation. in the delegation. Part of that press statement<br />
said this: " To participate in games such as the Queensland<br />
Commonwealth Games with New Zealand participating,<br />
and further in a country such as Australia that<br />
deniEs the right of self determination of her<br />
indigenous population, is to waive that responsibility."<br />
That is quite plainly an indication that the delegation was<br />
going to urge African states not to participate and that was<br />
in the original press release on account of this particular<br />
delegation. But Mr Whitlim has also said on other occasions that he was " ve'ry<br />
much criticising Australia" and that he agreed that so far as hE! was<br />
concerned that the Africans " rersn a tool to bring about<br />
domestic change in Australia." So far from refusing to condemn </p>
<p>-3-<br />
a boycott he said he would " tell the Africans that it is<br />
up to them to decide how they can make their views on the<br />
treatment of Aborignes known." I think it is the first<br />
time that a former Australian Prime Minister has gone<br />
overseas so explicitly to criticise and seek to damage his<br />
own country. I leave it up to the people of Australia to<br />
judge what they think of Mr Whitlam and what Mr Whitlam is<br />
really about on this visit. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
