<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1339</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S VISIT TO US AND UK - EXCHANGE OF REMARKS BETWEEN PRESIDENT JOHNSON OF THE USE AND PRIME MINISTER HAROLD HOLT OF AUSTRALIA AT ARRIVAL CEREMONIES FOR THE PRIME MINISTER ON THE SOUTH LAWN OF THE WHITE HOUSE - 29TH JUNE 1966</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/06/1966</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001339_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRrLvIE MINISTER'S VISIT TO U. S ITD U. K.<br />
Exchange of' remarks between President Johnson of the<br />
U. S. and Prime Minister Harold Holt of' Australia at<br />
arrival ceremonies for the Prime Minister on the<br />
South Lawn of the * White House. 29th June. 1966.<br />
ADDRESS BY PRESIDENT JOHSNSON:<br />
Mr. Prime Minister and Mrs. Holt:<br />
. ie greet you this morning as friend and partner.<br />
It is a very genuine pleasure to welcoirie you and M. rs. Hclt,<br />
and the distinguished members of your party, to our country.<br />
j\: jy personal ties to your country are as deep as a man' s<br />
can be. During the war I found among you openhearted<br />
friendship when I was far from,, home. Now, once again, our two<br />
nations are fighting side by side in the defence of freedom.<br />
The first thing that I read every morning are the<br />
battle reports from Viet Nam. I want you to know that I follow<br />
the exploits of 4~, 500 Australians fighting there with the<br />
same interest and concern as those of our ow. n men. Mr. Prime<br />
Minister, I take great pride in their courage and their<br />
dedication. I derive great strength from the sacrifices they<br />
are making. You in Australia know that in Viet Nam we are meeting<br />
a challea. ge which just must be met. It imst be met because<br />
it is always dangerous to let aggression succeed. It must be<br />
met becauge our SEATO commitments require us to defend the<br />
people of South Viet Nam from external attack.<br />
It must be met because the security of Australia and the<br />
United Status of 1America is directly at stake in preserving<br />
the independence and the freedom of the nations of South East<br />
Asia. Jie also know that behind the struggle against<br />
aggression in Viet Nam a vital, free Asia is rapidly emerging.<br />
Shielded by the courage of the Vietnamese and their allies,<br />
many Asian countries are driving forward with real success in<br />
their economic and social development.<br />
Vte all know of the remnarkable growth of Australia and<br />
Japan in recent years. But last year the growth rate in South<br />
Korea was 8 per cent., in Taiwan it was 7 per cent., in<br />
Malaysia it was 512 per cent., in Thiland it was 6 per cent.<br />
Growth in Iran has been averaging better than 6 per cent a year. </p>
<p>Pakistan is rapidly recovering from the setback<br />
caused by the conflict last year.<br />
Last week I received word from India which moved<br />
me greatly. The monsoons have begun. It looks as though<br />
the rainfall this year will be ample and the harvt will be<br />
good. With adequate rainfall, the courageous measures of the<br />
Indian government, and the support of the world cormunity, I<br />
hope and I expect that India will surge forward in the year<br />
ahead. Indonesia is turning the corner into the most<br />
promising phase of its postwar history.<br />
M1eanwhile, there is rising in Asia a new spirit of<br />
regional association and regional self-confidencu. It was<br />
that spirit to which I responded and which I tried to encourage<br />
in the talk I gave in Baltimore in April, 1965.<br />
Now the dream of an Asian development bank is a reality,<br />
binding up the peoples from Teheran to Seoul in a great common<br />
enterprise. . ork goes forward to develop the M4ekong Valley,<br />
despite the conflict close by.<br />
I know that Australia has, for many years, assuned a<br />
majcr responsibility for the security and the development of<br />
its region, through the Colombo Plan, the ,1ekong Committee,<br />
SEATO, and bilateral contributions to developing regions of<br />
the area. Our ovn security is heightened because we are<br />
joined with you in hNZUS.<br />
vie feel a new sense of fellowship and conmon destiny<br />
emerging in Asia. followed with great interest the recent<br />
meeting in Seoul of the Asian and Pacific Council, in which<br />
your government participated.<br />
Nations that were long isolated from each other are<br />
now beginning to know each other and to find new cormon ground.<br />
Old antagonisms are giving way to a new awareness that there<br />
are great possibilities in working togethcr, great challenges<br />
to be met and great jobs to be done.<br />
Above all, Asia is proving once agai-that stability<br />
and power are not to be found in tyranny and aggressive wars<br />
against a neighbour.<br />
Stability and power come frca free men and free nations<br />
working together on behalf of the people. de both know that<br />
should we fail in Viet Nan these new possibilities in free Asia<br />
would be endangered or destroyed. </p>
<p>M1r. Prime Minister, as you co,. e this morning to this<br />
house on your long-awaited visit, I wish to tell you and,<br />
through you, to tell your wonderful people, that we shall not<br />
fail. W~ e shall persist. 14e shall succeed.<br />
The good, brave people of South Viet Namn shall be given<br />
their chance to forge their own destiny in peace.<br />
The free peoples of Asia shall be given their chance<br />
to shape the destiny of their own region.<br />
These are your goals in Asia, M'r. Prime Minister, and<br />
they are ' also the goals of the United States of America.<br />
delcome.<br />
llro President and Mlrs. Johnson..<br />
Thank you for your warm welcomne, Mr. President. You<br />
have said warin and generous things about Australia andits<br />
people. Wk-hat a memorable morning for the Australian people and<br />
f or an Australian Prime Minister. I thank you for the honour<br />
which, by this ceremonial, you have accorded to my country and<br />
you have accorded to me. vhat has been done will be appreciated<br />
deeply by my people as it is by myself as head of my government.<br />
4e meet, Mr. President, as heads of government while<br />
our two nations are again-comrades in arms. This is at least<br />
the fourth time in this century that Americans and Australians<br />
have combined together vvith other friendly forces to resist<br />
aggression. We fought alongside each other in two world wars, and<br />
then Australia was the first country, I believe, to announce<br />
itself beside you when America iiade the historic decision to<br />
bring its strength to the aid of South Korea.<br />
I say historic decision advisedly, because I believe<br />
that to have been, Mr. President, one of the turning points<br />
in human history. I believe at that critical point of time<br />
was decided the issue of whether we handed Asia over to<br />
penetrating, aggressive communism, or whether we kept intact<br />
a large part of Asia as member countries of the coimñ pany of<br />
free people throughout the world.<br />
Australia was with you when you decided on the<br />
decision, critical also to you and to us, in South Viet Nam,<br />
another battleground against communist aggression.<br />
You have spoken of the task force of Australians which<br />
is now assembled in Saigon. You will be aware, M~ r. President,<br />
that in other parts of South Last Asia Australia is making<br />
a military contribution, small by the standards of your own<br />
great country, but useful in the company in w.-hich we find<br />
ourselves there. </p>
<p>I know that this task force in South Viet Nam will<br />
acquit itself with disti-ction. The men that are serving<br />
there are men of quality. They are well trained. The<br />
first battalion was accorded the highest commendation by your<br />
own leaders and by the leaders of South Viet Nam. The task<br />
force which follows them will acquit them selves With no<br />
less courage and distinction.<br />
The outcome of this struggle is critical for the<br />
hopes that you and we share for a better and more secure way<br />
of life for the free people of Asia.<br />
You have spoken of the vital free Asia that is<br />
emerging. I can speak of this from some personal experience,<br />
because not merely do we have a view from dom under which is<br />
pelhaps a different perspective from that of others in<br />
different parts of the world, but it has been my own good<br />
fortune in recent times to have travelled over several of these<br />
coLntries of South East Asia.<br />
W, hat has occurred over recent years is a transformation.<br />
To go through Thailand, 1,1alaysia, and even South Viet Nam,<br />
itself, and see the massive support being rendered there, see<br />
the security, the progress which has beon found possible by<br />
these other countries where com,: unism has successfully been<br />
held in check to see these things is to give heartening<br />
encouragement to go on with the job of resisting aggression<br />
where we find it.<br />
But it does not take a war to bring Americans and<br />
Australians close together. vq'e like each other. Friendships<br />
form quickly between us. le have many mutually beneficial<br />
links., our trade with each other., the investment that you<br />
make with us with your capital. ge co-operate in many<br />
constructive international interests and oauses.<br />
You mentioned, 1ir. President, your time in Australia<br />
years ago. A new Australia has arisen since then. When<br />
can we ste you there again? And this time we hope with Mrs.<br />
Johnson, and perhaps the whole family.<br />
You will be encouraged to see the National growth in<br />
which many American skills and resources have assisted.<br />
lIr. President, we recognize all too clearly in my ovn<br />
country that on yoa, personally, falls the heavy and at times<br />
lonely responsibility of free world leadership on your country<br />
these burdens have been assumed in comparatively recent times<br />
in terms of modern history. But America has shouldered those<br />
burdens firmly, and you have inspired and encouraged us all by<br />
the strength of your own resolution. </p>
<p>You know that in Australia you have an understanding<br />
friend. I am here, Sir, not asking for anything an<br />
erperience which I am sure you value at times when it is not<br />
sofrequent as it might be.<br />
You have in us not merely an understanding friend, but<br />
one staunch in the belief of the need for our presence with<br />
you in Viet Nam. vie are not there because it is right to be<br />
there, and, like you, vie shalh stay there as long as seems<br />
necessary in order to achieve the purposes of the South<br />
Vietnamese government and the purposes that we join in<br />
formulating and progressing together.<br />
And so, sir, in the lonelier and perhaps even more<br />
disheartening moments which comre to any national leader, I hope<br />
there will be a corner of your mind and heart which takes cheer<br />
froii the fact that you have an adiiring friend, a staunch<br />
friend, that will be all the way with LBJ. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
