<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9359</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J.KEATING, MP ADDRESS AT &quot;TIMBAROO&quot;,DUARINGA,QUEENSLAND, THURSDAY, 15 SEPTEMBER 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/09/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009359.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
L L<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING, MP<br />
ADDRESS AT " TIMBAROO", DUARINGA. QUEENSLAND, THURSDAY,<br />
16 SEPTEMBER 1994<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
. John and Thelma, Ian ( McFarlane), Don ( McGauchle) President of the<br />
National Farmers Federation and my colleague the Premier, Wayne Goss,<br />
Marjorie H-enzell my federal parliamentary colleague, John Purcell from the<br />
Cattleman's' Union and distinguished representatives of rural organisations<br />
and ladies and gentlemen.<br />
Well, let me at first, on behalf of the Premier and myself, thank John and<br />
Thelma for this opportunity to see the drought as It affects them and for the<br />
reception they have given us, which Ian has said, is one given on behalf of<br />
the rural communities of this country and of Queensland. So, we thank you<br />
most sincerely for that, to be able to come here and see It.<br />
A century ago we had the worst drought end the worst of depression In<br />
Australia's history. And, It was also the century where the nation was born<br />
with the Federation of the Australian States and where much of the Australian<br />
legend was created. A large part of the Australian legend Is the legend of the<br />
bush and the fortunes of rural Australia and the bush have been very much<br />
tied up with the fortunes of the country. Each time we have faced adversity<br />
we have invaribly weathered It and over come It. We are now, I think,<br />
experiencing whether it is for the moment, this is for these last three or four<br />
years or whether it is actually a sea change in climate at least a substantial<br />
change in the weather patterns In this country. And, it means that large parts<br />
of our rural communities and our farm and grazing communities have been<br />
devastated by it. Their lives have been hurt. Their Incomes have been<br />
slashed. Our national Income has been reduced and now we are facing not<br />
simply'an economic matter In the bush, but a social matter where families<br />
have been under pressure, where children have been withdrawn from school,<br />
where genuine hardship and sustained hardship Is a part of daily life.<br />
During the election campaign or at the end of it in 1993 I said that we would<br />
never leave the unemployed behind. Well, let me also say In the same terms,<br />
. L D Ic k J UUQ r Ui </p>
<p>L L 1 o, qu uuU<br />
2<br />
we won't leave the country people of this nation behind the farmers and the<br />
graziers and their families who have been beset by this drought and have<br />
faced difficult conditions after a prolonged period of bad seasons. And, I<br />
think, that that can be said and should be said because the country<br />
notwithstanding this epoch is wealthy enough to say that we will help people<br />
through. That we won't forget them. That we will put Into place Some<br />
systematic support for them.<br />
I think, one of the real worries about this drought Is the Impact it Is having on<br />
the psychology of the bush, on the psychology of farming and on families and<br />
on family breakdown. I was telling Jan Darlington the other day a parish<br />
priest who used to give sermons where I went to mass as a boy, used to say<br />
when poverty flits In love flits out the door. It is very true, I think, that when<br />
families are put under financial pressure you see a lot of marital breakdown<br />
and a lot of stress and it Is particularly, I think, sad when you see It starting to<br />
Impact on children and on their education.<br />
So, there Is a real worry here, I think, about the vaibility of the farming family,<br />
the rural family and, of course, the people In the towns who live from this sort<br />
of generated wealth from the land. And, it is the holding of those family units<br />
together, I think, which becomes our principal concern and seeing people<br />
able to work through their financial problems and stay In the business of<br />
' farming and grazing when the drought breaks and to see them ease through<br />
It and back Into better times in the future is what we have to do.<br />
So, I have taken this opportunity to look at first hand, at the impact of the<br />
drought. I have been In drought affected areas before, but each area tends<br />
to be different, In this case it is so prolonged, it followed a period of high<br />
Interest rates ( inaudible) knocked cash flows around. So, each epoch is<br />
different. This one is different and I am pleased to have the opportunity to<br />
hear what farmers and graziers and farm and grazing organisations have to<br />
say about this and to try and take that In and to think about some way we can<br />
have some sort of tiered support. Be it In Income support or Interest<br />
subsidies to deal with debts taken on In carry through periods or the funding<br />
that is necessary to actually kick off after a drought, restocking and what<br />
have you. And, It is that, I think, that the Federal Government is now<br />
considering. We have already, under the RAS scheme, seen In a joint<br />
arrangement with the States funding for rural adjustment assistance needed<br />
to carry on finance. And, I think, already since 1992 the Commonwealth<br />
spent about $ 100 million there. The Premier was telling me yesterday, I<br />
think, In Queensland between the Commonwealth and the State<br />
Governments we spent about $ 130 million in Queensland for that period.<br />
So, It Is not as if there isn't funding going in. It is a matter of whether it Is<br />
targeted well enough, whether it's of the kind that is actually helping people<br />
out with income support, where their own financial capacity is simply run out<br />
with the prolongation of these conditions.<br />
So, this is, I think, a first rate opportunity for me to come. As I said I very<br />
much appreciated the hospitality which John and Thelma have given us this </p>
<p>LL~ 3<br />
morning and their friends who have come around and those of you who<br />
represent rural communities and the towns, the Mayor, I appreciate seeing<br />
him here and the businesses who rely upon the growth of incomes off the<br />
land. It gives us a chance to get a handle on ( inaudible) to see It at first<br />
hand and to listen to what people say. You have got to be a good listener In<br />
public life and let me assure you I am and to always listen to those ideas, the<br />
odd jewel that comes through, that you can build upon or marry up with<br />
something else, to end up with a better ( inaudible) policy.<br />
I think in this country, because drought has now become somewhat endemic<br />
to the country, that areas are drought declared for six months, out of it for a<br />
year, then back In for six months. We really need, I think, a long term policy<br />
in place. ( inaudible drought or a flood is ( inaudible) it is an easy<br />
enough thing to do. Taken by some to mean that one has a heart. Well..<br />
( Inaudible) I think It is better to have a head about it and a heart, that Is,<br />
put the two things together and perhaps a consistency in policies and a<br />
proper and appropriate funding.<br />
That Is what we will try and do, but thank you all very much indeed to give us<br />
a chance to try and to it better.<br />
ends -4 uuu r<br />
ILL </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
