<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6562</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS TO SPORTS FUNCTION, SYDNEY, 23 NOVEMBER 1984</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/11/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006562.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
ADDRESS TO SPORTS FUNCTION SYDNEY 23 NOVEMBER 1984<br />
LADIES AND GENTLEMEN,<br />
IT IS WITH SPECIAL PRIDE THAT I AM HERE TODAY WITH YOU<br />
TO CELEBRATE OUR ACHIEVEMENTS IN SPORT. I HAVE<br />
DELIBERATELY USED THE WORD " OUR" BECAUSE I SEE THE<br />
PROGRESS WE ARE MAKING IN SPORT AS VERY MUCH THE OUTCOME<br />
OF A PARTNERSHIP A PARTNERSHIP BETWEEN THE SPORTING<br />
COMMUNITY AND THE GOVERNMENT.<br />
WE ARE PRIVILEGED TO BE PLAYING OUR PART IN THAT<br />
PARTNERSHIP FOR THE BENEFIT OF ALL AUSTRALIANS WHETHER<br />
THEY BE THE " WEEKEND SPORTSPERSON" OR WHETHER THEY BE<br />
ONE OF OUR HIGH PERFORMANCE ATHLETES PURSUING EXCELLENCE<br />
IN THE SPORTING ARENAS OF THE WORLD.<br />
SPORT MAKES AN ENORMOUS CONTRIBUTION TO OUR SOCIETY.<br />
IT IS SUCH AN INTRICATE PART OF HOW WE, As AUSTRALIANS,<br />
EXPRESS OURSELVES AS A NATION THAT IT WOULD BE DERILICT<br />
OF ANY FEDERAL GOVERNMENT TO ABROGATE ITS RESPONSIBILITIES<br />
IN THIS AREA. e o / 2 a </p>
<p>I HAVE COME HERE TODAY TO ANNOUNCE SPECIFIC<br />
PROPOSALS WHICH I AM CONFIDENT WILL BE OF SIGNIFICANT<br />
BENEFIT TO OUR SPORTSMEN AND WOMEN IN THE YEARS AHEAD.<br />
I REFER SPECIFICALLY TO PROPOSALS TO ASSIST OUR ELITE<br />
SPORTSPEOPLE AND THEIR COACHES,<br />
BUT BEFORE I GIVE YOU THE DETAILS OF THESE<br />
INITIATIVES ALLOW ME TO TAKE A LITTLE OF YOUR TIME TO<br />
PAY SPECIAL TRIBUTE TO JOHN BROWN, MY MINISTER FOR SPORT,<br />
RECREATION AND TOURISM.<br />
OVER THE PAST 18 MONTHS JOHN HAS MADE GIANT STRIDES IN<br />
IDENTIFYING THE SPECIAL PROBLEMS CONFRONTING OUR<br />
SPORTSPEOPLE AND IN ESTABLISHING THE ENVIRONMENT IN<br />
WHICH THESE PROBLEMS CAN BE OVERCOME.<br />
Two MONTHS AGO JOHN AND I ANNOUNCED THE ESTABLISHMENT<br />
OF THE AUSTRALIAN SPORTS COMMISSION AN INITIATIVE<br />
WHICH I CAN NOW TELL YOU JOHN BROWN HAS BEEN WORKING ON<br />
FOR THE LAST TWO YEARS. THE SPORTS COMMISSION WILL<br />
PROVIDE THE GOVERNMENT WITH A DIRECT LINK WITH THE<br />
SPORTING COMMUNITY. IT HAS THE RESPONSIBILITY OF<br />
CO-ORDINATING OUR NATIONAL SPORTS EFFORT AND OF ADVISING<br />
THE GOVERNMENT ON THE BEST USE OF AVAILABLE RESOURCES. / 13 S </p>
<p>INCLUDED WITHIN ITS CHARTER, THE COMMISSION WILL SEEK<br />
TO MAXIMISE FUNDING FOR SPORT FROM THE PRIVATE SECTOR<br />
TO SUPPLEMENT FUNDS FROM THE FEDERAL BUDGET. IT WILL<br />
DO THIS THROUGH THE ESTABLISHMENT OF A SPORTS AID<br />
FOUNDATION WHICH WILL BE INCLUDED AS PART OF THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN SPORTS COMMISSION BILL TO BE INTRODUCED<br />
IN THE FIRST SESSION OF THE NEW PARLIAMENT NEXT YEAR.<br />
WE LOOK FORWARD TO A CONTINUING AND PROSPEROUS<br />
PARTNERSHIP WITH SPORT.<br />
NOW LET ME RETURN TO THE SPECIFIC INITIATIVES I<br />
WANT TO ANNOUNCE TODAY. INITIATIVES WHICH<br />
FOLLOW ON FROM MY ANNOUNCEMENT IN MY POLICY SPEECH<br />
LAST WEEK IN WHICH I PROMISED TO EXTEND TAX AVERAGING<br />
TO SPORTSMEN AND WOMEN WHOSE INCOME FLUCTUATES WIDELY<br />
WITHIN RELATIVELY SHORT CAREERS.<br />
OUR IMPORTANT OBJECTIVE AS A GOVERNMENT IS TO CREATE<br />
A HEALTHIER AND HAPPIER SOCIETY AND SPORT IS AN ACTIVITY<br />
WHICH WILL HELP US ACHIEVE THIS GREAT OBJECTIVE. IT IS<br />
ALSO OUR GOAL TO CREATE THE ENVIRONMENT IN WHICH THE<br />
TALENTS OF OUR PEOPLE CAN BE FULLY DEVELOPED FOR THE JOY<br />
AND FULFILMENT OF US ALL. a ./ 14@ </p>
<p>UNDER PRESENT TAX DEDUCTABILITY ARRANGEMENTS, SPORT<br />
IS DISCRIMINATED AGAINST COMPARED WITH OTHER AREAS<br />
OF LEISURE ACTIVITIES SUCH AS THE ARTS. AT PRESENT,<br />
MAJOR SPORTS SPONSORS CAN CLAIM ADVERTISING COSTS AS<br />
DEDUCTIBLE TAX CONCESSIONS WHEN THEY RELATE TO SPORTS<br />
PROMOTION BUT INDIVIDUALS WHO MAY WISH TO PROMOTE<br />
AUSTRALIAN SPORT AND SUCH INDIVIDUAL ENDEAVOURS AS<br />
AMERCIA'S CUP CHALLENGES AND OTHER MAJOR SPORTING<br />
EVENTS CAN CLAIM NO SUCH DEDUCTION.<br />
THE PROVISION OF TAX DEDUCTABILITY WOULD ALSO BE<br />
IMPORTANT FOR THE SUCCESS OF THE PROPOSED SPORTS AID<br />
FOUNDATION. IT IS IMPORTANT THAT SUFFICIENTLY ATTRACTIVE<br />
INCENTIVES ARE MADE AVAILABLE TO MAXIMISE DONATIONS FROM<br />
INDIVIDUALS AND CORPORATIONS ALL OF WHICH ARE VITAL<br />
PARTNERS WITH GOVERNMENT IN THE AUSTRALIAN SPORTING " TEAM".<br />
I UNDERTAKE THEREFORE TO GIVE FAVOURABLE CONSIDERATION<br />
NEXT YEAR TO SUCH A MOVE. / 5 S </p>
<p>I NOW TURN TO OUR NEW SPORTS TALENT PLAN. THIS PLAN<br />
WILL INVOLVE, THROUGH THE AID FOUNDATION WHEN ESTABLISHED,<br />
BOTH PRIVATE AND PUBLIC SECTORS IN ASSISTING OUR<br />
ATHLETES IN ALL SPORTS TO COMPETE AGAINST THEIR PEERS IN<br />
EUROPE, ASIA AND AMERICA.<br />
IT HAS APPALLED ME THAT OVER THE YEARS AUSTRALIA'S HIGH<br />
PERFORMANCE ATHLETES -AND COACHES HAVE BEEN TREATED SO<br />
SHABBILY BY COALITION GOVERNMENTS. SPORTSMEN AND WOMEN,<br />
THROUGH THEIR DEDICATION AND SHEER HARD WORK, HAVE BEEN<br />
GREAT AMBASSADORS FOR THIS COUNTRY AND HAVE BEEN GREAT<br />
MORALE BOOSTERS AT HOME. IT IS SIMPLY UNFAIR AND UNJUST<br />
FOR GOVERNMENTS TO UNDERESTIMATE AND HENCE UNDERVALUE<br />
THE ROLE PLAYED BY OUR SPORTING COMMUNITY IN THE PROJECTION<br />
OF OUR IMAGE AND PRESTIGE OVERSEAS AND IN THE FOCUS THEY<br />
PROVIDE FOR NATIONAL PRIDE AND NATIONAL ACHIEVEMENT-AT<br />
HOME. IT IS DISGRACEFUL THAT WE CAN BENEFIT SO GREATLY AS A<br />
NATION THROUGH THE EFFORTS OF OUR SPORTSPEOPLE AND YET<br />
TAKE NO ACTION TO ALLEVIATE SOME OF THE GREAT FINANCIAL<br />
HARDSHIPS SUFFERED BY THE SAME HEROES AND HEROINES.<br />
My GOVERNMENT WILL ADDRESS THIS PROBLEM THROUGH THE<br />
SPORTS TALENT PLAN TO BE ADMINISTERED BY THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
SPORTS COMMISSION. v s / 6 </p>
<p>FOR TOO LONG AUSTRALIAN SPORTSPEOPLE HAVE SUFFERED<br />
FROM LACK OF REGULAR INTERNATIONAL COMPETITION AND<br />
LACK OF FINANCIAL SUPPORT TO PURSUE THEIR SPORTING<br />
CAREERS. THEY HAVE ALSO SUFFERED FROM THE LACK OF<br />
QUALIFIED AND EXPERIENCED COACHES WHO ARE ABLE TO<br />
DEVOTE SUFFICIENT TIME TO THEIR ATHLETES. INADEQUATE<br />
FINANCIAL ASSISTANCE TO ATHLETES AND COACHES IS<br />
PROBABLY THE GREATEST SINGLE PROBLEM PRESENTLY<br />
CONFRONTING AUSTRALIAN SPORT. IT HAS LED TO THE<br />
DEPLORABLE SITUATION WHERE TOP CLASS ATHLETES HAVE<br />
BEEN FORCED ON THE DOLE IN ORDER TO EXIST WHILE THEY<br />
TRAIN TO REPRESENT THEIR COUNTRY AGAINST THE BEST IN<br />
THE WORLD.<br />
IT IS PATENTLY UNFAIR FOR US TO CELEBRATE THE VICTORIES<br />
AND PERFORMANCES OF OUR ATHLETES WHO DO SO WELL AT<br />
THE Los ANGELES OLYMPICS AND THEN IGNORE THEM UNTIL<br />
THE NEXT INTERNATIONAL COMPETITION. WE HAVE AN OBLIGATION<br />
TO ENSURE THAT EXCELLENCE IN ALL AREAS OF AUSTRALIAN<br />
LIFE IS ENCOURAGED AND THAT THE ENVIRONMENT IN WHICH<br />
EXCELLENCE CAN DEVELOP IS CREATED. IT IS THEREFORE<br />
PARAMOUNT THAT WE GIVE OUR ATHLETES THE OPPORTUNITY<br />
TO COMPETE ON AN EQUAL BASIS WITH THEIR INTERNATIONAL<br />
COUNTERPARTS. 17. </p>
<p>AUSTRALIA'S WORLD RANKED ATHLETES AND EMERGING<br />
TALENT HAVE RECEIVED SOME VALUABLE, ALBEIT, LIMITED<br />
ASSISTANCE UNDER THE PRESENT NATIONAL ATHLETE AWARD<br />
SCHEME ADMINISTERED BY THE AUSTRALIAN SPORTS COMMISSION,<br />
THE SCHEME HAS SERVED A USEFUL PURPOSE OVER THE YEARS<br />
BUT HAS BEEN UNABLE TO MEET OVERALL REQUIREMENTS IN<br />
SUCH A CRITICAL AREA OF SPORT,<br />
THE SPORTS TALENT PLAN WILL BUILD ON THIS EXISTING<br />
FRAMEWORK AND WILL EXPAND THE PROGRAM OF ASSISTANCE<br />
TO WORLD-RANKED ATHLETES, POTENTIAL SPORT STARS AND<br />
TOP RANKED COACHES,<br />
IN THE FIRST YEAR ( 1985/ 86) AN ESTIMATED 400 ATHLETES,<br />
INCLUDING INDIVIDUALS AND TEAMS, AND UP TO 20 COACHES<br />
WILL BE ASSISTED, GRANTS TO INDIVIDUAL ATHLETES AND<br />
TEAM MEMBERS WILL BE TO A MAXIMUM OF $ 10,000 EACH<br />
WHILE THOSE TO TOP COACHES WILL BE TO A MAXIMUM OF<br />
$ 20,000 IT IS ESTIMATED THAT THE FIRST YEAR COST<br />
OF THE PLAN WILL BE $ 3.5 MILLION.<br />
I ANTICIPATE THAT WHEN THE AUSTRALIAN SPORTS AID<br />
FOUNDATION IS PROPERLY FUNCTIONAL NEXT YEAR THAT THE<br />
PRIVATE SECTOR WILL BE ABLE TO SHARE INVOLVEMENT IN<br />
THIS PLAN WITH THE GOVERNMENT TO ASSIST AUSTRALIA'S<br />
ATHLETES AND COACHES TO SINGLE-MINDEDLY PURSUE THEIR<br />
SPORTING CAREERS, SECURE IN THE KNOWLEDGE THAT THEIR<br />
FAMILIES WILL NOT SUFFER FINANCIALLY, e e / 8e </p>
<p>8.<br />
THE LAST 18 MONTHS HAVE BEEN CHARACTERISED BY GREAT<br />
ADVANCEMENT IN SPORT BROUGHT ABOUT LARGELY THROUGH<br />
THE ENERGY AND ENTHUSIASM OF JOHN BROWN, BUT, LADIES<br />
AND GENTLEMEN, THE GREAT CHALLENGES ARE STILL AHEAD<br />
OF US AND I KNOW THAT THE COMBINED WILL AND COMMON<br />
SENSE OF BOTH GOVERNMENT AND THE COMMUNITY AT LARGE<br />
WILL ENSURE THAT THOSE CHALLENGES ARE MET, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
