<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>236</transcript-id>
    <title>WOOL MARKETING COMMITTEE OF ENQUIRY - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, RT. HON. R.G. MENZIES.</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/09/1960</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000236.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>WOOL MARKETING COMMITTEE OF ENQUIRY<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister? Rt. Hon. R. G. Menzies.<br />
Late last year L-announced that in view of the<br />
importance of the wool. industry the Government had agreed to the<br />
request of all the federal wool growing organisations that an-ejquiry<br />
be arranged into -Australian wool marketing methods.<br />
After mature consideration the Government has deqided<br />
to appoint an independent Committee of Enquiry comprising a Chairman<br />
aAn d two._ members. The Chairmanwill be Sir R. slyn Ph] i p Justice<br />
of the Supreme Court of Queensland and the members will be Mr. A, M. C.<br />
Buttfield, who recently retired from the position of General Manager<br />
of the Australian Mutual Provident Society, Sydney and Mr. D. H. Merry;<br />
B. Com., Chief Economist of the Australia and Now Zealand Bank,<br />
Melbourne. The organisations all requested that the Chairman<br />
should be a member of the Judiciary.<br />
The Government will be guided by the Committee itself<br />
as to whether it may perhaps be necessary or desirable at some stage<br />
to formally retain consultants to assist the Committee in the conduct<br />
of the enquiry. The terms of reference of the Committee of Enquipy will<br />
be to enquire into the present systems of marketing and<br />
of promoting the sale of the Australian wool clip and<br />
matters relating thereto, and to report upon the<br />
efficacy of these systems;<br />
to report upon the merits of any other systems or of<br />
modifications of the present systems which may be<br />
advocated to the committee of enquiry or which the<br />
committee itself considers would be of long-term<br />
benefit to the woolgrowing industry and in the best<br />
interests of the nation.<br />
The Government considers that the terms of reference<br />
of the Committee are sufficiently broad to provide for a full scale<br />
enquiry into the problems of disposing of the Australian wool clip<br />
to the best advantage. If it should transpire however that they<br />
do not fully cover all matters of importance the Government will be<br />
prepared to look at them again.<br />
It is expected that the Committee of Enquiry will have<br />
its first meeting early in February to consider the general arrangements<br />
for the conduot of the enquiry and the procedures to be adopted,<br />
including the taking of evidence.<br />
In view of the great national importance of this enquiry,<br />
having regard to the key role of wool in jur economy, I appeal to all<br />
organisations and others concerned with the outcomie of the enquiry to<br />
co-operate fully with the Comriittee in the complex and arduous task<br />
ahead of it. </p>
<p>[Exact date unconfirmed]   </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
