<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5404</transcript-id>
    <title>CONSTRUCTION OF NATURAL GAS PIPELINE FOR CANBERRA</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/07/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005404.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR D THURSDAY 2S Y 198<br />
or a little more than that, from about 1969. But now we. have<br />
mtahne y cidricfufmesrteanntc epsa rtisn owfh icthhe nactouurnatlr y. gas is extending out into -71<br />
areas as can economically carry the capital costs invol. ved. An<br />
CONSTRUCTION OF NATURAL GASq PIPELINE FOR CANVtE, RRA<br />
example of the challenge over recent years, in my own State<br />
thery arneg wayseom ething likwe ast t hmomieis otnh at are serviced by1910.<br />
natural gas. Oil heated conversions thfuel over the l asdt ecade<br />
or alittle more atbhoaunt t1h, a0t0,0 9f6ro9m. But now wehaweek.<br />
the ircumstances whine n natural gasf iirss t linked I understand it<br />
would be feeding a thousand homes and 100 buildings, but the<br />
potential is for about 30,000 hones or more. Therefore it was<br />
manyobvious to extend the pipeline to this city and to undertake a<br />
reticulation system for the people of Chave led to the circumstancerra.<br />
in which conversion to natural gas is promoted by economic factors-<br />
I am glad that Ithink wobuelden nodtohnaes very much in collabged tenor fifteen<br />
with private enterpribse come moretahnadt, asntG oav ernmenpt riwceth e of fuel.<br />
just decide risent o it as a Governen tI. t is something in whichmany<br />
areas as can erise ough to be sinificantly involved and I am<br />
glad to see that it is.<br />
At the of tVenichcalleSu mmit Meeting of the seven major economSitcte countries.<br />
feaw days ago, the decisions million homes thindicattheadt over the<br />
coural gas. Oil heated cmonajvoert hres ions inducstoriualn tries must break<br />
about 1,000 a week.<br />
the link that energy crises have fpiuriss t on growth anddeopmerstand it<br />
woudtinh e feedmianjdours trial counthroimdes and 100 buildings, but therica,<br />
and also of Japan. Indeed the decisions that they made have<br />
confirmed the wisdom and the strength of Australia's own energy<br />
poliies. ntialisI tw orth noting that all international organisations<br />
obvious teox tend thepr icing mechatnoi stmh iasip eline ancidty to undertake a<br />
achieving sensai ble use of end one vergy in parnodm oting greater<br />
with explorationa nd conversion that a as Government we did not<br />
just decide to do it as a Governient. It is something in which<br />
private enterprise ought to be significantly involved and I am<br />
glad<br />
At the Venice Summit Meeting of the seven major economic countries<br />
a few days ago, the decisions made there indicated that over the<br />
course of this decade the major industrial countries must break<br />
the link that energy crises have put on growth and developmentin<br />
the major industrial countries of Europe and North America,<br />
and also of Japan. indeed the decisions that they made have<br />
policies. It is worth noting that all international organisations<br />
have endorsed-the pricing mechanism as the major factor in<br />
achieving a sensible use of energy and in promoting greater<br />
exploration and conversion to other forms of fuel. v.<br />
o </p>
<p>2<br />
Under our oil parity pricing policy, which is one of the things<br />
that has led to the great promotion of natural gas in Australia,<br />
S oil exploration is now five times that which it was in 1975.<br />
In 1980, 50 to 60 on shore wells will be drilled. Five or six<br />
years ago about five on shore wells were drilled. Esso and BHP<br />
have committed themselves to $ 1.2 billion worth of additional<br />
exploration and development as a result of the policies. The<br />
North West Shelf is getting underway at a cost of many billions<br />
of dollars and the Rundle partners are moving forward in partnership<br />
with Esso, in the pilot stage, which itself will cost several<br />
hundred million dollars to test the production of fuel oils from<br />
shale. It is expected that that will be successful and oil from<br />
shale will start to fill in the very serious gap that will occur<br />
in Australia as production of Bass Strait runs do-. n severely<br />
towards the latter part of this. cade.<br />
Indeed, the shale oil deposits in Queensland are vast and future<br />
developments there, costing many billions of dollars, will lead to<br />
Australia having a continuing degree of independence and self<br />
sufficiency of a kind that we would not be able to have if we. had<br />
to purchase all our supplies from OPEC countries, or alternatively<br />
if we had pricing policies which did not encourage and make that<br />
kind of development viable. There are already over 3,500 kilometres<br />
of gas pipeline in Australia, including this pipeline to Canberra.<br />
there are over 2,000 new kilometres planned or approved. And<br />
after five years we believe that something approaching a million<br />
barrels of oil will be saved each year by the access of the<br />
citizens of Canberra and the industries of Canberra to natural gas..<br />
And this is the kind of saving that can come with. proper pricing<br />
policies and with a vigorous promotion of this particular form of<br />
energy. This site is going to the heart of the underground reticulation<br />
system. The Commonwealth is likely in this city to be a major<br />
consumer and this spot is also the centre of the Parliamentary<br />
triangle. I think it is, in a sense, a symbol of the importance of<br />
co-operation between government and the private sector, which is<br />
of course exemplified by the way this reticulation system is going<br />
to be put into being and gas piped to the homes of people right<br />
throughout this capital.<br />
I think it is a mark of the Government's confidence in the future<br />
growth and development of Canberra, but it is also a mark of the<br />
confidence in the kind of policies that we have pursued.<br />
I would like to say one further thing about world parity pricing<br />
policy for oil. I do not think it is a particularly popular policy.<br />
I don't like it when I get the bills from my own farm because they<br />
are much higher than they used to be. But the Government pursues.<br />
that policy not only because it believes it'to be right,<br />
but also because it knows the policy to be necessary for the<br />
well-being of Australia. We do not want the future to arrive and<br />
to have our children when they come to stand in our places in a<br />
few years time being beggars for fuel on the international markets,<br />
forced to pay the highest spot prices, whatever they might be.<br />
Under those circumstances they would have to go through a conversion<br />
period of getting-used to different energy circumstances as Bass<br />
Strait oil got used up, which would be much more difficult than<br />
anything that we have had to experience at the present time. * 1<br />
~ 1 </p>
<p>33<br />
It would not only be difficult for individuals, for farms and<br />
for industries, it would be difficult for the whole country.<br />
Our policies have been designed to maintain a real. sense of.<br />
security and independence in Australia in relation to fuel and<br />
energy reserves, to bring on alternative forms of energy as is<br />
happening with the increasing use of natural gas, as will happen<br />
with the development of the shale oil. reserves.<br />
This will . ean that Australia will have a continuing sense of<br />
self sufficiency, a continuing degree of self sufficiency which<br />
is important and a sense of independence of the kind that we now<br />
have. It would have been a very easy policy to say: " let's<br />
continue to use up our liquid fuel supplies cheaply it's<br />
available to us this generation today". But it would have been<br />
an enormously selfish policy and it would have been a policy thatignored<br />
the needs of our kids in 3 or 10 or 15 years time. I<br />
believe that it is the objective of all Australians to try and<br />
leave this country a better place than when they entered it and<br />
this is one of the policies which is very important in seeking<br />
to achieve that particular objective.<br />
We will be leaving the future more secure, more certain and much<br />
safer than it would otherwise be. That is why the world parity<br />
pricing policy is important and that is why the policy will be<br />
maintained. It is necessary for the future security of Australia<br />
in the broadest sense and it is necessary for the well-being of<br />
our own children. I think that that is an objective that all<br />
Australians would want to share in.<br />
I would like to congratulate all those that are involved in this<br />
project. I would like to congratulate the company that is<br />
involved in the reticulation system. I am sure the work will<br />
be done efficiently and well and as far as the Government is<br />
concerned the sooner it is completed the better. It is all very<br />
well laying foundation stones or turning sods, but I think when<br />
something is completed it is the better side, or the better end<br />
of the ceremony. So the day when gas can be turned on to the<br />
citizens of Canberra is really the end point that we are looking<br />
for as a result of what has begun today.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
