<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6970</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE IN SYDNEY - 2 JULY 1986</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/07/1986</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006970.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE IN SYDNEY 2 JULY 1986<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, would you like to see a national<br />
superannuation scheme?<br />
PM: Well, what I would like to see is this sort of situation<br />
emerge. First of all let's take the fact. The fact is that about<br />
of the Australian workforce currently enjoys superannuation.<br />
So it is an inevitable fact of life, whatever political<br />
persuasion or wherever you are, it is the fact of life that in<br />
the coming years it will be natural that the people who haven't<br />
got superannuation will aspire to get it. And that is a<br />
legitimate aspiration. So what I want to see happen is under the<br />
control and regulation of the Arbitration Com ' mission the gradual,<br />
and I emphasise the gradual, extension of that to the rest of the<br />
workforce. And it should be done in a way which matches the<br />
capacity of industry. There are some sections of industry which<br />
today would not have the capacity to extend that benefit. But<br />
over the next two or three years as productiv-ity increases that<br />
improvement in productivity I think should in part be applied to<br />
extending that benefit. And if at the end of that process of what<br />
I hope will be peaceable negotiation under the control of the<br />
Commission, if at the end of that process there is a very small<br />
proportion of the workforce not being covered then that would be<br />
appropriate at that point for the national government to have<br />
some sort of safety net which picks up the rest of the workforce.<br />
That is how I would like to see it happen and essentially after a<br />
few of these initial little bubbles get worked out I think that's<br />
what will happen.<br />
JOURNALIST: How do you think the Arbitration Commission can<br />
introduce a normal scheme with so many breakaways now occurring?<br />
PM: Your in the media and you know that prominence tends to be<br />
given to the most dramatic but we are here in a scientific<br />
institution and it is very important to try and get the<br />
statistics right. I mean you are seeing a couple of dramatic<br />
outbreaks at the moment but overwhelmingly, in statistical terms,<br />
overwhelmingly the process will be as I have said. The Commission<br />
I understand is going to be meeting under the Chairmanship of the<br />
President, Justice Maddern, on Monday and it is my hope and<br />
expectation that out of that meeting the sort of orderliness that<br />
I am talking about will brought into the process. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: And what have you got to say to the wharfies who are<br />
out on strike at the moment?<br />
PM: I hope that as I say that that will quickly come back into<br />
the orderly process following that meeting on Monday. That is<br />
my hope. Again it fascinates me that the headlines have been<br />
given to the fact that the wharfies are out now and there is a<br />
bit more strife, strife that I would rather not see. But to be<br />
fair again to the workforce, you have had in this last year and<br />
the last three years a dramatic diminution of industrial<br />
disputation. We now have the lowest level of industrial<br />
disputation for about 20 years. So let's give credit where it is<br />
due and where they deserve a little bit of a rap across the<br />
knuckles. If they do well let's give it but let's be fair about<br />
it.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, in the light of today's opinion poll in<br />
the Bulletin, perhaps you might be using<br />
PM: No. You just have a look at who is the preferred Prime<br />
Minister. I know who would want to do the swapping in the polls.<br />
That is said modestly.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you think employers will be willing to negotiate<br />
under a national scheme?<br />
PM: Well, I don't want to pre-empt the meeting, the very<br />
important meeting that Mr Justice Maddern will chair next week. I<br />
believe that out of that meeting their should come a willingness<br />
to negotiate. But I repeat it has got to be a staged process and<br />
where there is not the capacity then there shouldn't be a pushing<br />
for that in those areas where there isn't a capacity. It should<br />
be spread over a period of two or three years.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Ministe r, a question on politicians salaries.<br />
The Government hasn't accepted the full recommendation of the<br />
Remuneration Tribunal but accepted the 9.2% increase in<br />
allowances. Do you think that is economically responsible?<br />
PM: It certainly is. It is merely in line with what has happened<br />
in costs in those allowances. And it is minor compared to what<br />
the major recommendation of the Tribunal was. They wanted us to<br />
take an 11.7% increase in salaries and there is no doubt that<br />
historically that is justified. The private sector workforce, the<br />
public sector workforce, the people that Ministers and Members of<br />
Parliament are dealing with in the public service, they have had<br />
that 11.7%. members of Parliament haven't and I don't think that<br />
people should just jump on the bandwagon of saying that<br />
politicians salaries should be forever pushed down and down and<br />
that they shouldn't recognise that the community has a value in<br />
trying to attract people of calibre into the Parliament. And you<br />
won't do that if you continuously press down their remuneration.<br />
The anomaly is there, it is justifiable if you look at it of<br />
itself but it should rectified and the Tribunal has said that it<br />
should. However, having said that I said to the Cabinet that we<br />
are saying to the community that there must be restraint and I<br />
don't believe that I could expect the rest of the community to </p>
<p>3<br />
exercise restraint if I agree to that 11.7% increase beyond the<br />
national wage increase in salary. I said to the Cabinet that I<br />
think that shouldn't happen. To its credit the Cabinet agreed<br />
with me and so that will be the position. So we won't be taking<br />
that 11.7% that has been recommended and I hope that others in<br />
the community will, in those circumstances where they are not<br />
under the constraints of arbitration tribunals, people who are<br />
able to set their own salaries, will take a lead from what we are<br />
doing so that that restraint will be exercised. It goes back to<br />
the sort of thing I was saying before. All of us would like to<br />
grab what we can I suppose now and say well that's beaut, that<br />
will give us some satisfaction. It is much more intelligent to<br />
have a longer time scale in your thinking and there is no doubt<br />
that present restraint exercised will now will pay great<br />
dividends for us all in the years ahead.<br />
ENDS </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
