<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6736</transcript-id>
    <title>JOINT STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER AND THE MINISTER FOR PRIMARY INDUSTRY</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/09/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006736.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
F~ OR MEDIA 23 SEPTEMBER 1985<br />
JOINT STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER~ AND THE MINISTER FOR<br />
PRIMARY INDUSTRY<br />
The Federal Government has today approved a total 8sst3flcC<br />
package for the sugar industry including price support,<br />
adjustment assistance and research funding.<br />
On price support the Federal Government will guarantee a<br />
No 1 Pool price higher than that proposed by the Savage report.<br />
The Federal Governmrent's decision recognises the serious plight<br />
of the sugar industry and that government assistance<br />
including price support is necessary if this important<br />
Australian primary industry is to stand on its own feet and<br />
prosper again.<br />
The Cocrinonwealth's offer of assistance depends on two conditione<br />
being met.<br />
The f i7s t is that the Oueensland Government contributes funds<br />
for price support.<br />
Su~ gar is grown almost entirely in Queensland and the industry<br />
has been structured and regulated by Queensland State legislation<br />
for over sixty years.<br />
Tropical coastal Queensland is heavily dependent on sugar.<br />
The Federal Government therefore believes that the Queensland4<br />
Government has an obligation to contribute to price support<br />
assistance and is sure the sugar industry agrees.<br />
The second cond. ition is that the industry iself agrees to a<br />
significantly greater degree of deregulation than so far they<br />
have been prepared to accept.<br />
The Commonwealth is proposing a specific phased introduction of<br />
restructuring measures over the next three years.<br />
The Federal Government recognises that the industry needs time<br />
to adjust to the changes which are so essential for its longer<br />
term survival.<br />
Hr Kerin will meet his Queensland counterpart Mr Neil Turner, MLA<br />
on Wednesday, 25 September 1985, to dincuss the Savage report.<br />
7 r ' 1 -' 1<br />
J </p>
<p>Mr Kerin will then inform Mr Turner in more ' detail of the<br />
Commonwealth's position and seek agreement on specific aspects<br />
of the new arrangements, including the level of price support,<br />
the extent of the Queensland Government's contribution and<br />
the schedule for the phased industry deregulation.<br />
Hie will also discuss other matters raised in the Savage report,<br />
including adjustment assistance, research and industry<br />
organisation. The Government hopes that Mr Turner will finally be given a<br />
mandate from the Queensland Government to negotiate on these<br />
issues.<br />
The Federal Government has decided on its response and believes<br />
the sugar industry and the people of Queensland have the right<br />
to expect the Queensland Government not to delay any longer<br />
in negotiating on this crisis. VI </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
