<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8222</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT TO PARLIAMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER ON THE GULF CRISIS TUESDAY 4 DECEMBER 1990</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/12/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008222.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
STATEMENT TO PARLIAMENT BY THE PRIME MINI STER<br />
ON THE GULF CRISIS<br />
TUESDAY 4 DECEMBER 1990<br />
Mr Speaker,<br />
I wish to inform the House, and the people of Australia, of<br />
the Government:' s views on developments in the Gulf crisis,<br />
and of the Government's policies in response to those<br />
developments. Members will k~ now that on 29 November the Security Council<br />
of the United Nations passed an extremely grave Resolution.<br />
That Resolution is momentous, and in some respects it is<br />
quite unprecedented.<br />
Resolution 678I authorises member-states of the United<br />
Nations, from 15 January 1991, to use all necessary means to<br />
uphold and implement the Security Council's previous<br />
Resolutions on the Gulf crisis. Essentially, those previous<br />
Resolutions call on Iraq to withdraw unconditionally from<br />
Kuwait, and to release all hostages.<br />
The Resolution also requests all states to provide<br />
appropriate support for actions taken under the Resolution.<br />
The words ' all. necessary means' carry a clear meaning in<br />
this resolution: they encompass the use of armed force to<br />
compel compliaince with the Security Council's Resolutions.<br />
The UN has of ten authorised the deployment of military<br />
forces to prevent conflict; but only once before has it<br />
authorised the! use of armed force to compel compliance with<br />
its Resolutions. That was in Korea, forty years ago.<br />
Korea is in that respect a precedent for the action which<br />
the Security Council has now taken. But in other respects,<br />
and in very important respects, this Resolution is quite<br />
unprecedented. Never before has such a grave and momentous Resolution been<br />
so broadly supported. Honourable members will know that<br />
the Resolution was carried by a vote of twelve to two, with<br />
one abstention. They may not realise that the Resolution<br />
was actually E-nari by six members of the Council,<br />
including not just the United States and Britain, but also<br />
the Soviet Union, France, Canada and Romania.<br />
I t </p>
<p>The fact that both superpowers were prepared, with four<br />
other nations, to sponsor this Resolution shows in the most<br />
concrete terms that the nations of the world are<br />
overwhelmingly united in their condemnation of Iraq's<br />
aggression; and in their determination to do whatever it<br />
takes to use all necessary means to make sure Iraq's<br />
aggression is not allowed to stand.<br />
In a century marked by terrible wars, uneasy peace and<br />
international distrust, this sort of response to armed<br />
aggression has proved an elusive dream. Now it is a<br />
reality. Resolution 678 offers the best prospect of a just and<br />
peaceful resolution of the crisis. In passing Resolution<br />
678 the Security Council is not seeking war. On the<br />
contrary, the Resolution, while explicitly contemplating the<br />
use of force if necessary, is founded on the hope that a<br />
clear statement of that preparedness will in fact avoid war.<br />
As President Bush wrote to me in a letter over the weekend<br />
on his decision to seek high-level talks with the Iraqis,<br />
" I know of your hope which I share that military<br />
force be used only as a last resort".<br />
Resolution 678 is seeking to show Iraq's leaders, just as<br />
clearly as possible, that they must withdraw from Kuwait and<br />
release the hostages. The Security Council has given Iraq's<br />
leaders, in the words of the Resolution, ' one final<br />
opportunity, as a pause of goodwill, to do so.'<br />
This Resolution is a stark signal, but Iraq's leaders have<br />
shown that no softer signal will move them. They have<br />
ignored statements from around the world condemning their<br />
actions, and they have ignored the concrete expression of<br />
that condemnation in the mandatory and comprehensive<br />
economic sanctions imposed by the UN.<br />
Those sanctions have been very widely complied with, and<br />
effectively enforced. Many countries, like Australia, have<br />
paid heavily in lost earnings, and many, including<br />
Australia, have contributed to enforcing the sanctions.<br />
Nothing could be more effective than these sanctions in<br />
persuading Iraq to get out of Kuwait, except the threat of<br />
armed force.<br />
This Government has nev * er ru ' led qut the, possibility that<br />
armed force may need to be used as a last resort to resolve<br />
the gulf crisis.<br />
The question is, whether now is the right time to<br />
contemplate this further and graver step. Should the<br />
sanctions not be given longer to work? To answer that we<br />
have to clarify how the sanctions have been intended to<br />
work. Has their aim been to starve Iraqi people into<br />
submission, or has it been to show Iraqis leaders that the<br />
world would not accept their incorporation of Kuwait? </p>
<p>The answer is plain. The aim of the sanctions has been to<br />
prove to Iraq., both through the seriousness of the action<br />
itself, and through the great sacrifices which the sanctions<br />
have imposed already both on Iraq and on its former trading<br />
partners, that the world would not accept Iraq's invasion of<br />
Kuwait. Starving Iraq's people into submission was not the UIN's aim<br />
in imposing sanctions. That was implicit in the decision to<br />
allow exceptions in cases of humanitarian need. Nor do I<br />
believe that further economic hardship for Iraq's people is<br />
likely to change the minds of Iraq's leaders. Sanctions can<br />
be very powerful instruments of persuasion as they have<br />
been in South Africa but they cannot force the hand of a<br />
dictatorial leadership which is willing to ignore the<br />
interests of its people.<br />
I am myself surprised and deeply disappointed that Iraq's<br />
leadership should have proven itself so resistant to the<br />
message of sanctions; surprised because no rational reading<br />
of Iraq's self-interest by its leaders should have allowed<br />
them to ignore the message the sanctions sent.<br />
The sanctions have succeeded for over three months in<br />
virtually stopping all Iraq's trade with the rest of the<br />
world. And yet they have not succeeded in persuading Iraq's<br />
leaders to withdraw from Kuwait, nor to show the least sign<br />
of reconsidering their disastrous position.<br />
Meanwhile the economic impact of the Gulf crisis is causing<br />
damage to fragile developing-country economies around the<br />
world, and the difficulty and uncertainty of relying on<br />
sanctions alonre to resolve the crisis is becoming all too<br />
apparent. We believe that it is therefore timely to send an even<br />
clearer signal the clearest and strongest signal that can<br />
be sent that Iraq must leave Kuwait. We believe the<br />
Resolution must improve whatever prospects there are that<br />
Iraq will withdraw. We believe that this Resolution offers<br />
the best prospect that war can be avoided.<br />
Since Resolution 678 was passed, Iraq's apparent willingness<br />
to consider President Bush's offer of talks, to be held<br />
strictly within the framework of the UN Resolutions on the<br />
gulf crisis, shows that already Iraq may be re-assessing its<br />
position. in. the light of.. that. Resolution.<br />
But we recognise that the power of Resolution 678 depends on<br />
the acceptance by UN members that in the last resort it may<br />
be necessary -to compel Iraq to comply with the UN's<br />
Resolution by force of arms. Otherwise it is empty;<br />
something that Iraq can shrug of f; something that would fail<br />
to compel IraqI's leaders to address the terrible<br />
consequences of a refusal to withdraw; a missed opportunity<br />
to drive home the benefits for them and for their country of<br />
making a choice for peace. </p>
<p>The gravity of the situation makes it important to restate<br />
the reasons we believe that Iraq's actions must be reversed,<br />
even to the point of using armed force, and why we believe<br />
that important Australian interests are at stake.<br />
Iraq's seizure of Kuwait was an act of pure aggression,<br />
motivated solely by the desire of Jraq's leaders to increase<br />
their territory, their wealth and their power. I would ask<br />
anyone who is inclined to credit Saddam Hussein' s claims of<br />
a wider mission on behalf of the Arab people, to explain the<br />
incorporation of Kuwait as the nineteenth province of Iraq.<br />
I would ask them to explain the plundering of Kuwaiti<br />
property and the persecution of its residents.<br />
And I would ask them to explain away the testimony before<br />
the Security Council last week by people who have fled from<br />
Kuwait. Even allowing for the exaggeration common in such<br />
circumstances, this testimony was indeed shocking.<br />
As well, Australia has been deeply concerned by the<br />
consequences for the Middle East as a whole if Iraq's<br />
aggression was allowed to stand. Who could doubt that<br />
having swallowed Kuwait, a stronger Iraq would not then turn<br />
on its other neighbours? Who will explain how Iraq could<br />
then be prevented from establishing an hegemony over the<br />
entire region; an hegemony backed not only by chemical<br />
weapons, but sooner or later by nuclear weapons as well?<br />
And who could doubt the brutality of that hegemony?<br />
These are not scare-mongering speculations. They are<br />
serious assessments of the regional consequences of allowing<br />
Iraq's aggression to stand. And they carry with them the<br />
terrible question were we to turn a blind eye now, what<br />
still greater crisis, with what still greater stakes, would<br />
we have to act to resolve in the future, at what still<br />
greater cost?<br />
These are crucial issues. They relate to the fate of vast<br />
numbers of our fellow human beings. But these humanitarian<br />
concerns do not stand alone.-They stand alongside, and<br />
reinforce, important Australian interests which are deeply<br />
engaged in the Gulf.<br />
First, Australia has a direct and immediate interest in the<br />
peace and prosperity of the Middle East. It is an important<br />
market for our products and an important source of imports.<br />
Australia-needs the-Gulf'-s-. oil, -and -our -trading partners<br />
elsewhere in the world need the Gulf's oil. So stability in<br />
the Gulf is important to all Australians.<br />
But most important of all, standing higher than all the<br />
factors I have mentioned, Australia has an interest in the<br />
establishment and maintenance of an international order<br />
based on the Charter of the United Nations. This has been<br />
from the outset, and remains, the Government's guiding<br />
principle in this crisis. </p>
<p>Our highest priority is to uphold the principles of the<br />
United Nations: that international disputes must not be<br />
settled by force; that national borders must be respected;<br />
and that aggressors must not be permitted to prevail.<br />
Those principles were enshrined in the UN charter by the<br />
generation who saw the world slide into chaos in the 1930' s,<br />
and who strove in 1945 to build an. international order which<br />
would stop that happening again.<br />
With the end of the Cold War the need to rebuild that order<br />
is urgent. Iraq's invasion of Kuwait proves the urgency of<br />
that need, and provides the first test of our ability to<br />
meet it. With the momentous changes changes so much for<br />
the better in the world political scene over the past few<br />
years the world community has a tremendous opportunity to<br />
achieve a more secure and just ordering of international<br />
relations; to try again to give effect to the principles to<br />
which the founders of the UN aspired.<br />
The re-establiLshment of that order engages our direct<br />
interests as well as our sense of right and wrong. The<br />
security and prosperity of middle powers like Australia will<br />
in the years ahead depend directly on the strength of the<br />
UN's principles. And the strength of those principles in<br />
the years ahead depends absolutely on the support we give<br />
them today. To put it bluntly, if we or our neighbours were<br />
subject to aggression in the future, we would want, and we<br />
may need, the support of the UN. It is in our interests to<br />
support the UN today.<br />
That support must include our recognition that the UN should<br />
be willing to defend its principles with armed force if<br />
necessary. War is a terrible thing. Some people will find it<br />
paradoxical that the UN, as an organisation devoted to<br />
peace, should contemplate war. But that tragic paradox has<br />
to be accepted. It can be necessary to be prepared to<br />
fight, and in fact to fight, in order to secure peace in the<br />
future.<br />
That necessity was recognised by the United Nations at its<br />
outset, and is: inherent in its nature. No one knew the<br />
horrors of war better than the generation who built the UN.<br />
Dr Evatt, who as Australia's Foreign Minister played a<br />
leading role in establishing the UN, said in this House in<br />
1945 that if economic or-diplomatic sanctions<br />
" are deemed inappropriate to the situation or prove<br />
ineffective, the Security Council may take any military<br />
action necessary to suppress the aggressor."<br />
We would all fervently hope for a peaceful resolution. But<br />
if we rule out the use of force against a regime which has<br />
already used it, we have given up seeking a resolution at<br />
all. The international community would have simply<br />
acquiesced in Iraq's aggression. </p>
<p>For all these reasons, the Government unreservedly supports<br />
the United Nations Security Council Resolution 678.<br />
Our support for the Resolution imposes on us an obligation<br />
to respond to the request, in its third paragraph, for all<br />
Nations to provide appropriate support for actions taken<br />
under the Resolution. I emphasise. that the Resolution not<br />
only authorises all necessary means; it explicitly requests<br />
that member states provide support.<br />
Members will be aware that the Government has provided<br />
support for the sanctions imposed earlier by the Security<br />
Council by deploying a task force of three ships of the RAN<br />
two frigates and a supply ship to help enforce the<br />
embargo against Iraq. Our ships have been performing that<br />
task with great distinction, and have played a major role in<br />
the multinational effort. They have brought credit to<br />
themselves and to their country.<br />
The passage of Resolution 678 clearly requires us to<br />
consider whether we should extend the operational role of<br />
our task force to allow it to prepare for, and if necessary<br />
to participate in, operations envisaged by the Resolution.<br />
In the light of the direct Australian interests which are<br />
engaged in the crisis, and in the light of our support for<br />
the specific measures contained in the Resolution, this<br />
Government believes that Australia should take this course.<br />
I therefore inform the House that Australia is prepared to<br />
make our naval task force available to serve with allied<br />
forces in operations authorised by Resolution 678, should<br />
that become necessary.<br />
Accordingly, if conflict occurs of a kind which is<br />
contemplated and authorised by the Resolution, our ships<br />
would be available to participate in action with the allied<br />
fleet in the Gulf, where they would be in a position to make<br />
an important contribution to its air-defence capabilities.<br />
The Government will now authorise the ADF to deploy ships of<br />
our task force from the Gulf of Oman into the Persian Gulf<br />
to exercise and operate with allied naval forces in<br />
preparation for that role. The ADF will also now<br />
participate in allied military planning.<br />
These steps need to be taken now because they are essential<br />
to ensuring that our ships are fully prepared to operate as<br />
safely and effectively as possible should conflict erupt.<br />
They do not formally commit Australian forces to any action;<br />
ADF units will remain at all times under Australian national<br />
command. Our ships will operate principally with ships of the US,<br />
Britain and Canada, under US operational control. This is<br />
normal under such circumstances, and will contribute both to<br />
the effectiveness and to the safety of our ships and men. </p>
<p>Under these command arrangements, the roles and missions of<br />
our ships would be specified by the Chief of the Defence<br />
Force in conformity with Government decisions. The task<br />
force commander would be responsible for ensuring that<br />
specific tasks assigned to Australian ships conform to these<br />
specified roles and missions, and he would be required to<br />
refer any disagreements back to the CDF and the government<br />
for decision. In all circumstances Australia will retain<br />
priority over the assignment of our ships.<br />
As well as maintaining the task force of three ships, the<br />
Government wiJll send another two medical teams totalling<br />
some twenty people to join the two already serving on<br />
hospital ships in the Gulf.<br />
It is not proposed to make any other contribution of naval,<br />
air or ground forces.<br />
Australia's naval task force will be maintained at the<br />
present level of two combat ships and a supply ship. The<br />
frigates HMAS Darwin and HMAS Adelaide will leave the gulf<br />
region to return to Australia in the next day or two, after<br />
being replaced by the frigate HMAS Sydney and the destroyer<br />
HMAS Brisbane.<br />
This is a significant commitment which is proportionate to<br />
the interests we have at stake and to our national<br />
resources. It is also a practical commitment. Our ships<br />
are in the area, and they are trained and equipped for this<br />
task. We are confident that they will be properly prepared<br />
for the role they may have to play.<br />
Should conflict break out, naval forces in the Gulf could<br />
face a serious threat, particularly from Iraqi aircraft.<br />
The role of our ships will be to help defend against that<br />
threat. It will be a hazardous role. The decision I am<br />
announcing today is therefore a very serious one. I have<br />
consulted the Leader of the Opposition on it. In taking<br />
that decision I am fully conscious of the difficult task we<br />
are asking our navy to perform. We recognise the great<br />
contribution they are making to Australia, and to world<br />
peace. I know there will be some who will ask why we should<br />
contribute in -the Gulf when others do not. The essential<br />
answer is this that what others do or don't do does not<br />
obviate our responsibility to j udge-. or. ours ' elves what is<br />
right, and what is in our interests, and to act accordingly.<br />
We also need to recognise that not -only should we<br />
contribute, but unlike many others, we can contribute we<br />
have a relevant capability to contribute.<br />
I know there wiLll also be some who cavil at the leading role<br />
being played in the Gulf by the United States. They will<br />
suspect that other nations who participate will only be<br />
serving American interests. That view is profoundly<br />
mistaken. </p>
<p>The US is certainly playing a leading role, as we would<br />
expect from a nation as wealthy and powerful as the US.<br />
Indeed, we would be disappointed if the US did not play such<br />
a leading role. But the US role has been clearly at one in<br />
this case with the wider interests of the international<br />
community, as demonstrated by the support for Resolution 678<br />
in the Security Council.<br />
There are even those who have purported to base their<br />
assessment of the Gulf situation on the presumption of moral<br />
equivalence between the US and Iraqi positions. If such<br />
views were to be taken seriously, it would reflect very<br />
poorly on the standard of our public debate. Let there be<br />
no ambiguity here no mindless muddying of the waters. If<br />
it comes to conflict, the international community will not<br />
be the aggressor. The United States and. the other allies<br />
will not be the aggressor. The aggressor is the nation that<br />
took, occupied and annexed Kuwait in August.<br />
The Labor Party comes to this issue with a lot of history.<br />
For much of its one hundred years the ALP has struggled to<br />
ensure that Australia's armed forces are not used to fight<br />
other peoples' wars. In the 1930' s that led Labor to turn<br />
its back on aggression, as so many others did in so many<br />
parts of the world.<br />
But Labor learnt the lessons of that mistake, and did more<br />
than its share to correct it. Dr Evatt recognised not only<br />
that aggression must be resisted, wherever it occurs, and by<br />
armed force if need be. He also recognised that all nations<br />
must be prepared to contribute to that task. As he said in<br />
1945: " It must be made crystal clear that the nations seeking<br />
representation in the world organisation must be<br />
prepared to contribute their share of physical force to<br />
restrain the action of proved aggressors.<br />
Since its establishment, Labor has been committed to<br />
strengthening the UN as the arbiter of a better world order.<br />
That is still our goal, more so than ever, as the passing of<br />
the Cold War brings the goal closer to our grasp. And we<br />
recognise the obligations which those aspirations impose on<br />
us as a nation.<br />
Confident as I am of the importance of Australia's interests<br />
and the correctness of ou. r approach, cannot deny that the<br />
decisions we are taking are onerous indeed. Should it come<br />
to conflict, Australians may be involved in combat for the<br />
first time in nearly twenty years albeit in very different<br />
circumstances. This is a heavy responsibility, but I and my<br />
Government will not shirk the exercise of that<br />
responsibility. </p>
<p>Before closing, it is important to restate what I have<br />
stressed before. The Australian Government and people have<br />
no ill-will to the people of Iraq, and wish them no harm.<br />
For their sake as much as for the rest of the world I<br />
earnestly hope that peace will prevail. If Iraq has genuine<br />
grievances they can be heard in recognised international<br />
forums, but riot until Iraq has complied with the UN's<br />
resolutions. Let me turn lastly to the issue which has been most<br />
constantly in our thoughts throughout this crisis; the<br />
situation of Australians, and of other foreign nationals,<br />
held in Iraq and Kuwait against their will.<br />
We have all heard in the last twenty-four hours of<br />
suggestions including from Iraq's Ambassador in Australia<br />
that Australian hostages may soon be. released. Of course<br />
we hope that is true. We say to Iraq, as we have said<br />
continually over recent months let them all go.<br />
Like all Australians whatever we may think of Iraq's<br />
propaganda lcottery being played out in Baghdad I hope<br />
that as many of our people as possible may find their<br />
freedom through it. But I recognise, as most Australians<br />
do, that that lottery is entirely arbitrary. There is no<br />
way to guarantee the freedom of all our people, except<br />
perhaps by surrendering our policy and our national<br />
interests entirely to the hostage-taker. Most Australians<br />
understand that, including many of our people held in Iraq,<br />
as I know through correspondence with me. It does them<br />
great credit that they do understand that.<br />
The only way to ensure the release of all our hostages is to<br />
resolve the crisis. And the only way to resolve the crisis<br />
is to press Iraq to withdraw from Kuwait. That is what<br />
Resolution 678 is intended to achieve, and that is what our<br />
support for Resolution 678 is intended to achieve. We<br />
believe it is our best chance.<br />
We see in Resolution 678 our best chance to get all the<br />
hostages home, to get Iraq out of Kuwait, to bring stability<br />
to the Middle East, and to take a vital step towards<br />
establishing a new world order in which nations like<br />
Australia can live in peace. That is why we have supported<br />
it by word, and that is why we will support it by deed.<br />
We see in Resolution 678 the tragic necessity to confront<br />
aggression, if necessary with-. armed force.<br />
And we see in Resolution 678 the hope that, through<br />
international cooperation, would-be aggressors will in<br />
future be deterred before they begin. </p>
<p>Mr Speaker, I finish on a practical note. In the light of<br />
the situation in the Gulf, and particularly of the timetable<br />
implied by Resolution 678, I have decided that I should not<br />
at this time plan to be away from Australia in January 1991.<br />
I have therefore decided that I will at this point defer my<br />
plans to travel to Europe at that time as had been planned.<br />
One purpose of that visit had been. to allow me to pursue<br />
Australia's interests in the Uraguay Round, if the Round is<br />
not concluded this year. I will of course remain committed<br />
to, and active in, pursuing these interests, including by<br />
travelling for direct talks at a different time if that is<br />
required. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
