<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>40076</transcript-id>
    <title>Doorstop - G20 summit Turkey</title>
    <prime-minister>Turnbull, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20150915 - 20180824</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/11/2015</release-date>
    <release-type>Transcript</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong>We've just finished last night a very long discussion on terrorism, on security and the leaders of the G20 nations are utterly united in a commitment to defeat terrorism. We had a very good discussion about domestic policies, about international policies and there was again, very strong statements especially from the leaders of the big Muslim countries in the room. Indonesia - of course the largest, Turkey, Saudi Arabia, Malaysia and others repeating what they have been saying. Especially since the attack in Paris but for a very long time, that the claims by these terrorist groups, by Daesh or ISIL, to be speaking in the name of God, to be speaking in the name of Islam are absolutely blasphemous. They do not, these Islamic leaders repeat, they do not speak in the name of Islam. They defame Islam. They are an abomination to religion and they reject them utterly. The leadership they're showing is very important and is appreciated by everybody. All of the leaders in the room are all utterly of one mind. </p>
<p>The commitment of course to the G20 goes beyond national security in the physical sense. The commitment is to the strong economic growth. That was set at the Brisbane G20 last year and while there have been some headwinds in terms of slower growth forecasts, none the less the commitment remains. We have had very good discussions about infrastructure, particularly urban infrastructure, about the importance of free trade, the entering into by Australia and China of the Australia and China Trade Agreement for example has been widely welcomed. I've just come from a very good discussion about the CHaFTA and other important Australian China relations issues with President Xi. So this G20 I believe will be known for its commitment to defending national security, collective national security, standing up against terrorism, doing everything it can to ensure the claims of these terrorists are refuted at every level and at the same time promoting economic growth and jobs. Innovation too is a consistent theme. It's just as much a theme of President Xi's government in China as it is to Chancellor Merkel's government in Germany, David Cameron's government in the United Kingdom, President Obama's government in the States, as it is of our Government in Australia. Innovation, technology, taking an advanced, and innovative approach to economic development in this very rapidly changing environment is well understood by all of the leaders. Now, do you want me to say, I thought you were going to ask some questions?</p>
<p><strong>QUESTION:</strong> I thought we weren't allowed to?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER:</strong> No, no, go ahead…We continue to monitor carefully the Paris tragedy and as I've said before the people of France have our deepest sympathy and our most resolute solidarity and I've had the opportunity to convey that personally to the French Foreign Minister, Laurent Fabius, who is here at the G20. The President Hollande, is of course in Paris dealing with the consequences of this attack. I've spoken this morning as I have every day with our key security agency heads, with the head of ASIO, Duncan Lewis, the Commissioner of the Federal Police, Andrew Colvin and my ministerial colleagues.  The alert level in Australia remains as it was, at high from September last year. Our security agencies are the best in the world. We recognise that risks exist, that attacks are possible. Attacks in this environment are likely to happen in the future, but Australians can be assured that we have the best security agencies, they are monitoring the situation and seeking to protect Australians at home and so far as we can, abroad. So I have every confidence that our security environment, while challenged of course in this context of global terrorism is nonetheless being well managed by the most professional security agencies in the world.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST:</strong> Could you please share with us some of the comments that President Xi made in the conversation?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER:</strong> Well it was a private discussion obviously but can I say I think President Xi would be happy for me to say that the warmth between China and Australia is very strong. He still enjoys his celebrated visit to Australia, and especially to Tasmania which was the last Australian Sate he had yet to visit. The ChAFTA, the China Australia Free Trade Agreement of course, we are both seeking speedily to finalise all of the ratification process so it will come into force. So it was a very good meeting, a very frank meting and I've also had some less formal discussions with President Xi in the course of this G20. So, I feel the Australia China relationship, which is very strong, and of course has been built upon, by Prime Ministers and Foreign Ministers and Trade Ministers over many years will continue to strengthen under my time, during my time as Prime Minister.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST: </strong>Are you still confident the growth targets that were arranged last year in Brisbane will be met given the slowing of the global economy excreta.</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong>The growth targets as we know from the work of the IMF are if you like, facing headwinds. But, nonetheless there is a renewed commitment to drive grow economic growth and the key leavers in Australia, as indeed in every other country, are remain, ensuring economies are flexible and agile and not only is innovation is promoted but that it is enabled through micro economic reform. And that there is continuing substantial investment in infrastructure - and of course the global infrastructure hub which has been set up in Sydney is a key part of that.</p>
<p>As I discussed in Jakarta with President Widodo, whose commitment to increased investment and infrastructure in Indonesia is very understandable given his background as City Mayor, the key focus has got to be to ensure that key infrastructure projects are investable. It's one thing to talk about them, to have them sketched out on a map if you like, but the important thing is to bring them forward to effectively the bankable feasibility stage so they can attract investment. There's plenty of money in the world to invest in infrastructure, it's a question of making sure the projects are capable of receiving that investment and of course delivering the secure and long term returns that institutional investors need.</p>
<p align="center"><strong>Ends</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
