<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11172</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                   THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                   RADIO INTERVIEW WITH MATT PEACOCK,                 AM PROGRAMME, ABC                                                  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>31/05/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Subjects: Tax avoidance, Ralph Review, ANTS deal, Democrats, Sale</p>
<p> of Telstra</p>
<p>E&amp;OE............................................................................................</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, can you tell me a bit more about this crackdown on</p>
<p> contractors? People who've been avoiding tax by avoiding tax</p>
<p> by forming companies, that kind of thing, are going to pay 20%. What's</p>
<p> that about?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well what we've agreed to do is to refer to the Ralph Committee</p>
<p> the desire of the Democrats to have some action taken in relation</p>
<p> to unfair avoidance of tax through the use of certain company structures,</p>
<p> and also to examine the possibility of the introduction of a 20% company</p>
<p> tax. What we've agreed to do is to refer those proposals to the</p>
<p> Ralph review on business taxation.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>But it's on the never ever, it may not ever happen?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well no. We have.....</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>It'll be referred.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>May I finish? We have agreed to refer it to the Ralph Committee.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>And what happens then though? I mean there's no guarantee.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well the Ralph Committee will have a look at it and make a recommendation</p>
<p> to the Government.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>So there's still a bit of, what would you call it, fine</p>
<p> tuning' to this package that will be scrutinised by the</p>
<p> Democrats in the Senate?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Matt, I don't know what the purpose of that question is. Can</p>
<p> I answer it this way by saying that we have made an agreement with</p>
<p> the Australian Democrats, and that agreement is going to be honoured</p>
<p> in full.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>Senator Murray said at the weekend that they'll be watching every</p>
<p> paragraph basically through the Senate. You're not concerned</p>
<p> about any changes that may be necessary in the drafting of the regulations</p>
<p> et cetera?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>We are going to honour the agreement.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>Mr Costello did describe it as "nightmare on main street".</p>
<p> And is that problem of whether you're putting thermometers or</p>
<p> using your fingers or whatever with cooked chickens and uncooked chickens</p>
<p> one of the Democrats' making? Do you leave the responsibility</p>
<p> at their feet or do you share it?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Matt, everyone knows that we would have preferred an option that didn't</p>
<p> include the carving out of some food, but that was not possible of</p>
<p> achievement. Everyone knows that. And the condition of getting agreement</p>
<p> with the Democrats was to leave out food, basic food. Now everyone</p>
<p> knows that. There's no point in going over all of what happened</p>
<p> before we reached the agreement. That is a waste of time.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>But it is something that the Treasurer dinned into us over the months,</p>
<p> this....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well Matt, Matt look, you know the reality. The reality....I'm</p>
<p> sorry, the reality is that in order to get agreement we had to accept</p>
<p> the excision of food. Now that was the reality.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>But I accept that this isn't your responsibility, it's not</p>
<p> something that you've deliberately done of your own making. But</p>
<p> how much more unpopular do you think it's going to make the tax?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Matt, I think the outcome is very popular.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>It's not the feedback that comes from the shop owners is it?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I think the public is very pleased indeed, and I haven't</p>
<p> spoken to a businessman publicly or privately over the last week who</p>
<p> didn't want a settlement, even if the price of that settlement</p>
<p> and that understanding was a carve-out of food.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>Now both you and the Treasurer seemed delighted on Friday night when</p>
<p> the announcement was made. The Treasurer even went so far as to offer</p>
<p> to kiss Meg Lees over the deal. There is this concern though isn't</p>
<p> there that it may be the kiss of death. Rather than a paradigm shift</p>
<p> for the Democrats, it might be the recipe for a splintering of the</p>
<p> party.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Gee, you're negative.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>But it is, it is a question to be put is it not?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I don't think the Democrats are going to split. Anyway if you</p>
<p> want to talk about another political party, go and talk to that other</p>
<p> political party. I mean I'm not a commentator on the Australian</p>
<p> Democrats. It's presumptuous of me to make public comment on</p>
<p> the internal affairs of the Australian Democrats. I have found Meg</p>
<p> Lees and Andrew Murray good people to deal with. They're straight,</p>
<p> they're not playing games. They're interested in the national</p>
<p> interest unlike the Labor Party who've just huffed and puffed</p>
<p> and said no. In those circumstances it doesn't serve anybody's</p>
<p> purpose for me to give running commentaries on the Australian Democrats.</p>
<p> You go and talk to the Democrats about that.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>We hope to shortly Prime Minister. The green initiatives in the GST</p>
<p> tax package, you're quite proud of them? You think...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes I am. I feel very comfortable with those initiatives. They sit</p>
<p> very easily, and very comfortably with the initiative we took after</p>
<p> election in '96 to establish the natural heritage trust, the</p>
<p> largest ever capital injection into environmental care in Australia's</p>
<p> history. Those initiatives announced on Friday night are all of the</p>
<p> piece with the earlier one.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>Are they things you would have done anyway?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well it's very hard to know which and when, but whatever the</p>
<p> answer to that is they're being done and that's what matters.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>But I mean, it's again relevant, was it something that the Democrats</p>
<p> got?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well the Democrats felt very strongly about those issues. I don't</p>
<p> disguise that. I'm not pretending for a moment those proposals</p>
<p> were all sponsored by us. I'm not saying that for a moment. I</p>
<p> give the Democrats full credit for what they've done in that</p>
<p> area.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>Are you concerned at all to get back to the question of Democrats</p>
<p> signing off on this deal that any of the Ralph recommendations may</p>
<p> be held up by the Democrats, or do you think that will get a green</p>
<p> light?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well it's a separate issue. We have made an agreement with the</p>
<p> Democrats. Can I say it again very slowly, that agreement will be</p>
<p> honoured in full.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>But this separate issue is something that business is clearly concerned</p>
<p> about.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>What separate issue is that?</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>The result of the Ralph review</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes I know, but what I'm telling you is that that is unrelated</p>
<p> to the agreement I made on Friday night. The agreement made on Friday</p>
<p> night was in relation to matters that are not within the reach of</p>
<p> Ralph. We will, after we get the Friday night thing fixed, we will</p>
<p> then move onto the business review. We remain very committed to the</p>
<p> business review and like all of the other taxation changes, anything</p>
<p> that we settle on in relation to business tax has to be negotiated</p>
<p> through the Senate.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>And there are no strings like this question of the 20% for contractors</p>
<p> that are tied to Ralph?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>There are no strings. The one is not interdependent on the other,</p>
<p> but the referral of those issues which you asked me about is fair</p>
<p> dinkum. We're asking Ralph to have a look at them.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, the other issue of course, Senator Harradine suggested</p>
<p> that you might be able to rustle up a little more money for the Telstra</p>
<p> deal. Is there any chance of [inaudible]?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I haven't, for understandable reasons, been involved in</p>
<p> the all the detail of that because I've been fairly focused on</p>
<p> taxation. I understand there are ongoing discussions between Senator</p>
<p> Harradine and Senator Alston. Precisely where they are at the moment</p>
<p> I don't know, you better ask one of them.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>The Treasurer has flatly ruled it out it appears yesterday.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well look, I haven't followed the detail of that. You go and</p>
<p> talk to Senator Alston about that.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>Or the Treasurer.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>You go and talk to Senator Alston.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, thanks for joining us.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>You're welcome.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
