<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7815</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, TREASURY PLACE, MELBOURNE 17 NOVEMBER 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/11/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007815.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
i. r 9 1 1 9 vv z r r rN V I(_<br />
r-n. r: CV 0r'r'-C v, rD TCL. V1-vV-rVzrQ=;<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, TREASURY PLACE, MELBOURNE, 17<br />
NOVEMBER 1989<br />
G 0 -P. ROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, what's the latest on the pilots<br />
dispute? PM4: Latest on the pilots dispute? Well the situation is<br />
quite clear. The airlines are significantly rebuilding their<br />
capacity. We're taking the Air Force out in the middle of<br />
December. International airlines will be out by the<br />
beginining of January and airlines will be handling the<br />
Christmas traffic and next year we will have what I've been<br />
continuously promising, and that is a significantly more<br />
efficient airlinme industry.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, your reaction to the<br />
Pharmaceutical Benofits Remuneration Tribunal decision to<br />
bring on its hearing on the chemists. Ara you happy with<br />
that? PH: Yes, I Uielcome the decision of the Tribunal. We have<br />
consistently sought to got a resolution of this issue which<br />
meats the requirements, the legitimate requirements of the<br />
pharmacy profession, of the consumers and of the taxpayer.<br />
Those are our triple responsibilities. We were very close,<br />
as you know, earlier this year to getting agreement with the<br />
Guild, That slipped us by and so we had no alternative but<br />
to go the the Tribunal under the legislation. We accepted<br />
the umpire's decision. The elements of the pharmacy industry<br />
have expressed unhappiness about elements of the decision.<br />
about its data base, about its methodology atnd about its<br />
outcome. Now under the announcement of Mr Jrustice Riordan,<br />
heit. agread to open all these issues and he's saying to them,<br />
' well if you've got concL-rns, I will listen to them and<br />
listen to them in detail, whatever you've got to put.' lilt<br />
prepared to visit the States and visit centres in the States,<br />
in all States. We will co-operate with that and of course in<br />
regard to some of the decisions that we've made, post the </p>
<p>2.<br />
( P14 cont) decision, we'll continue that. For instance, the<br />
essential pharmacy allowance, we're prepared to continue<br />
that. As an indication of the total good faith of the<br />
Government you will recall that one of the things that I said<br />
in the package After the decision is that we would be.<br />
prepared to contemplate adding to the Tribunal a person with<br />
experience in the retail pharmacy industry. So I've<br />
authorised the Minister, in his response that he'll be<br />
releasing this afternoon to Mr Reardonts statement, an<br />
indication that we would be prepared to add such a person for<br />
this inquiry. So I trust that now any concerns that our<br />
friends in the pharmacy industry have got, that they will<br />
bring before the Tribunal take the opportunity to put every<br />
piece of information that they want to. we don't want any<br />
information witheld, we want a decision which is fair for<br />
everybody. JOURNALIST: Did you askc the Tribunal to sit early?<br />
PH4: No. This is an initiative of the Tribunal.<br />
JOURNALIST: What happens to the $ 60M pack&amp; qe now?<br />
PM: Well as Mr Staples will indicate in his statement which<br />
I've authorised, just how that will stand now. What we need<br />
to do with all that is something that we will need to discuss<br />
before the Tribunal when it meets. But I've said Just<br />
moment ago that the essential pharmacy allowance for<br />
instance, we think that should go ahead, that makes sense.<br />
I've also said in regard to representation on the Tribunal,<br />
if someone with experience in the retail pharmacy industry,<br />
I'm prepared to go ahead with that so that can be part of the<br />
now review. That would presumably give even more confidence<br />
to pharmacists that their concerns will have been fully<br />
understood and considered.<br />
JOURNALIsT: Willsyou expect the pharmacists to stop<br />
campaigning agains the Government now?<br />
PM: I think you'll see in Mr Justice Riordan's statement<br />
which I have only had the opportunity of reading briefly<br />
because Xc have been in EPAC all day, but he refers to the<br />
need of course if they are going to take this opportunity to<br />
do so in a situation where there is no duress.<br />
JOURNALIST: A Macquarie Bank report bas suggested the<br />
Government's policies, economic policies are short sighted,<br />
referring directly to monetary policy. Did that come out in<br />
the EPAC conference today. </p>
<p>r~~ fl. Irvo a Orr Iv VflrlO~ TCL. o-vr" Z -3-<br />
P: No, it certainly did not. I think if you were going to<br />
characterise the contributions at EPAC today of the<br />
discussions on the economy, I think there was general<br />
agreement as to the thrust of the Government's econonic<br />
pol icies.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, the Opposition says that it's<br />
preparing for an early election in the new year. What<br />
chances? PM: I think this opposition is becoming an increasing joke,<br />
isn't it. As a charitable man in politics, one of the most<br />
charitable In the hittory of this c ountry, I Would say, I<br />
would simply give this kind advice to the Opposition. Before<br />
they contemp late getting into an election they ought to<br />
conduct their first fight first, and their first light is to<br />
get their own act in order. You have a situation where<br />
people outside the Party, outside the Parliamentary Party,<br />
are to a very large extent setting their agenda<br />
JOURNA. LIST: You mean John Elliott?<br />
PH: You said that, I didn't. You also have a situation<br />
where there are the deepeat of divisions within the Liberal<br />
Party, within the National Party and importantly between the<br />
Liberal* s and the National Party. I would think that before<br />
they think about tackling a strong and unified Government the<br />
best thin? they could do would be to try and get their own<br />
acts together.<br />
JOURNALIST: Tony Eggleton says that he believes Labor, to<br />
use his word, is panicking over the impact -of the<br />
Opposition's family tax package and says again, to use his<br />
own words, he believes that you'll offer a sop to families.<br />
PM: Is that right? Well 10m very., very interested to hear<br />
the observations of Tony Eggleton. over recent years he<br />
hasn't got a very good track record. It's not going to be<br />
improved next time rounds<br />
JOURNALIST: Are you going to have anything more for families<br />
between now and say the middle of next year?<br />
PH: I would've thought that if I've got Something to<br />
announce before we go to the election I would pick a somewhat<br />
different localeand context and time and situation to<br />
announce that than in this environment.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
