<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9721</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP DINNER FOR PRESIDENT RAMOS OF THE PHILIPPINES PARLIAMENT HOUSE, TUESDAY 22 AUGUST 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/08/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009721.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL: 22. Rug. 95 18: 2U No . U22 t'. LJ.<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MIMiSTER, TilE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
DINNER FOR PRESIDENT RAMOS OF THE P11ILIPPINES<br />
PARLIAMENT HOUSE, TUESDAY 22 AUGUST 1995<br />
PLEASE CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
On behalf of the Government of Australia and all Australians, I warmly welcome<br />
President Ramnos, his wife and his party to Australia.<br />
Before you left Manila, Mr President, you said that you were embarking on a journey<br />
of friendship and opportunity.<br />
That is exactly how we see your visit, too.<br />
And although you are making your first visit here as President of the Philippines, you<br />
and your service to your country are widely known in Australia.<br />
People here along with much of the rest of the world were deeply moved in early<br />
1986 by the images we saw of the tense struggle taking place in Manila where the<br />
People's Power movement and Mrs AquinQ. stood their ground in support of<br />
democracy. You played a courageous and vital role in that struggle.<br />
In the following years, when the restoration of democracy was threatened time after<br />
time, we observed and deeply admired your loyalty in defending the rebirth of your<br />
country's democratic political institutions.<br />
And in your first three years as President, you have displayed the same tenacity and<br />
courage in implementing reform, in opening up the Philippines economy and allowing<br />
it to regenerate.<br />
The Philippines return to growth well over 5 per cent expected this year and the<br />
large amounts of foreign investment now flowing into your country, are reflections of<br />
your personal conumitment to responsible economic management and deregulation.<br />
In your efforts, you have been able to draw on a private sector with business and<br />
managerial skills that are highly regarded throughout the region. We particul1arly<br />
welcome the members of the business delegation you have brought with you.<br />
22. Rug. 95 18: 20 No. U22 </p>
<p>TEL: 22. Rug. 95 18: 20 No. 022 P. 02<br />
2<br />
Mr President, you made an important point in a speech last year, and you have since<br />
demonstrated its truth: the truth that political democracy, social discipline and<br />
sustained economic development are not incompatible.<br />
By your succcss at home in consolidating democracy and reforming the economy you<br />
have also given the Philippines a new standing in the regional and international<br />
community. It is very fitting that you and the Philippines will have the honour of<br />
hosting the summit meeting of APEC leaders in 1996.<br />
Mr President, you will find Australia much changed since your last visit in the late<br />
1970s.<br />
We, too, have opened up our economy. With the assistance of eight successive<br />
accords with the union movement we have ensured that the Australian business<br />
environment has become more competitive. Last year Australia had one of the fastest<br />
growing economies in the OECD and corporate profits were at historic highs.<br />
Moreover, that growth has come with low inflation and high job growth.<br />
Our utilities, telecommu ni cations industry, waterfront, civil aviation, and rail transport<br />
have undcrgone dramatic reform. We have introduced a national superannuation<br />
scheme to help lift our savings. Our education and training systems have received<br />
massive investments.<br />
But beyond these changes, Australia has been coming to terms with its history, with its<br />
region and with its own society.<br />
With native title legislation, a new epoch has begun for our indigenous peoples an<br />
historic wrong-has been righted, at least in legal terms, and we are determined to see<br />
that social justice follows.<br />
Our place in the Asia-Pacific region is no longer disputed. Geography and economic<br />
integration have driven this trend. But there is more to it than geography and<br />
commerce. Important changes are taking place in the way Australians think about themselves not<br />
leug because more than half the immidgrants joining Australia's multicultural society<br />
each year come from Asia.<br />
And Australians are now debating our future constitutional arrangements.<br />
The changes have been fundamental. But they have been achieved without rejecting<br />
our history.<br />
In all this, it seems to me, there are important parallels with the recent experience of<br />
the Philippines. Both of us have had to come to terms with our history and the<br />
necessities which global change is imposing on us. We understand that we have to<br />
make our own way in the world. We have thought hard about the sort of societies we<br />
wish to be, and what our role will be in the world of the 2 1st century. </p>
<p>TEL: 22. Rug.-95 18: 20 NO. 022 P. O'<br />
3<br />
And, not least, we have had to work hard to rework the images others hold of us.<br />
I amn sure that your visit will contribute to this process for both our countries, Mr<br />
President:* Australia and the Philippines have a good foundation on which to build.<br />
Mr President, you said you come here as a friend and the commemorations this year<br />
for the fiftieth anniversary of the end of the war remind us what close and longstanding<br />
friends we arc. The Philippine government'-in-exile of President Quezon was<br />
headquartered in Australia during the war. Earlier today we launched at the War<br />
Memorial a book on the Battle of Leyte Gulf. This was the largest engagement by<br />
Australian vessels during the war, and that victory began the liberation of the<br />
Philippines. Australia hits provided economic assistance to the Philippines for many years. We are<br />
a significant source of training for your defence force.<br />
Our trade is growing well. But there is no doubt that our economic ties ought to be<br />
more substantial than they are at present.<br />
I am confident that this will happen. The opportunities have never been greater as our<br />
two economies have opened up. A sign of what lies ahead can be seen in the MOUs<br />
and agreements we witnessed being signed this morning and in the number of very<br />
senior Australian businesspeople who are present at this dinner tonight.<br />
I amn very pleased to join you, Mr President, in urging our business leaders and<br />
investors to look at the new opportunities which are opening up for Australia and the<br />
Philippines to do business together.<br />
In all we do together bilaterally, we have the invaluable resource of the Filipino<br />
community in Australia, now numbering around 120,000. It has doubled in size at<br />
every census since 196 1.<br />
Let me assure you, Mr President, that Australia and its government value our citizens<br />
of Philippine origin, and we will care for them.<br />
Our bilateral links wil also be strengthened by regional developments, like APEC and<br />
the discussions we are having about closer links between the ASEAN Free Trade Area<br />
and the Australia-New Zealand Closer Economic Relations Agreement.<br />
Australia and the Philippines and you and 1, Mr President have been working very<br />
hard to set up in APEC a structure which will strengthen the region economically and<br />
increase its stability as it enters a period of historic economic and strategic change.<br />
This visit has a particular significace. Not only are you the first President of the<br />
Philippines to visit Australia, but you ame the first foreign Head of State I have ever<br />
welcomed here who has an Australian grandchid. </p>
<p>TEL: 22. Rug. 95 18: 20 No. 022 P. 04.,<br />
4<br />
That makes you doubly welcome as the leader of a great regional country with which<br />
we want to develop close relations.<br />
And evin more deeply as family. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
