<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11059</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                   THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                   PRESS CONFERENCE                 PRIME MINISTER&amp;#146;S COURTYARD, PARLIAMENT HOUSE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/02/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE....................................................................................................</p>
<p>Ladies and gentlemen, I'd like to canvass a number of issues</p>
<p> this morning. The first is, of course, the quite outrageous behaviour</p>
<p> of the Senate in potentially destroying 50,000 Australian jobs by</p>
<p> knocking back the Government's regulation on unfair dismissals.</p>
<p> This is a completely irresponsible piece of behaviour by the Labor</p>
<p> Party, the Democrats and others in the Senate. This has been part</p>
<p> of our policy for a long time. It was voted on at the last election.</p>
<p> We'll introduce the legislation again to the Senate, which is</p>
<p> now in the House and it will go to the Senate in a few weeks time.</p>
<p> And we'll give them another opportunity to vote for jobs and</p>
<p> not against jobs.</p>
<p>And I give fair notice to the Australian Labor Party and the Australian</p>
<p> Democrats that every month that employment figures come out in this</p>
<p> country the Australian public will be reminded that but for their</p>
<p> behaviour the employment figures would potentially be 40,000 to 50,000</p>
<p> better. And the Labor Party will have another opportunity to show</p>
<p> what it thinks about preserving jobs, particularly for young Australians,</p>
<p> when it's asked to vote on the legislation to entrench the youth</p>
<p> wage within Australian awards. According, not to the Government but</p>
<p> to people in the retail industry, that involves 230,000 jobs for young</p>
<p> Australians.</p>
<p>Jobs is of overwhelming concern to the Australian community. It's</p>
<p> an ongoing mainstream issue and here you have the alternative government</p>
<p> of this country and the Australian Democrats voting to destroy Australian</p>
<p> jobs. And they won't be allowed by the Government to forget their</p>
<p> behaviour and they won't be allowed to forget the contribution</p>
<p> that they have made to the destruction of job opportunities for people</p>
<p> in small business. The evidence is overwhelming. It is independent</p>
<p> of government assessment. And we will not tire in our efforts to further</p>
<p> relieve small business of the burden and the deterrent impact of the</p>
<p> threat of unfair dismissal actions.</p>
<p>The other issue that I would like to briefly comment upon relates</p>
<p> to the referendum in November of this year. The Joint Party Room,</p>
<p> last night, approved in principle the Government's proposals</p>
<p> in relation to the holding of a referendum on whether or not Australia</p>
<p> should become a republic. The Party Room approved the model that came</p>
<p> out of the Constitutional Convention last year. The Party Room also</p>
<p> approved, overwhelmingly, the proposal I put to it on behalf of the</p>
<p> Government that there should be another question put to the Australian</p>
<p> people. And that related to the adoption into the Constitution, or</p>
<p> the incorporation into the Constitution, of a preamble which would</p>
<p> canvass a number of matters including an acknowledgement of the prior</p>
<p> occupancy of the land mass of Australia by the Aboriginal people and</p>
<p> some of the other matters that I have mentioned in the course of the</p>
<p> past few days.</p>
<p>There was a very strong sense of support within the Party Room and</p>
<p> a sense of occasion, a feeling that this was a good time for something</p>
<p> to be incorporated into the Australian Constitution about the history</p>
<p> of this country and some of the undeniable truths.</p>
<p>What I intend to do over the next few weeks is to settle the precise</p>
<p> form of that preamble. I will, of course, reserve the right to consult</p>
<p> others on the preparation of that  not that I doubt my capacity</p>
<p> to pen the odd word but I will certainly not to be so presumptuous</p>
<p> as to pass up the opportunity of seeking the advice of other gifted</p>
<p> wordsmiths within the Australian community. And we'll then be</p>
<p> presenting the final polished form of it to the Party Room, along</p>
<p> with the bill that was outlined by Daryl Williams yesterday dealing</p>
<p> with the republican issue for a final tick from the Party Room. We</p>
<p> then, of course, will engage, in relation to the republican legislation,</p>
<p> a process of consultation with the Opposition and others in the community.</p>
<p> And I'll also seek the views of the Opposition on the preamble.</p>
<p>We do intend to go ahead with the preamble and there is a very strong</p>
<p> view in the Party Room that we should go ahead with it. I will be</p>
<p> campaigning actively for a yes' vote. There wouldn't,</p>
<p> I expect, be any Ministers who would be campaigning against the preamble</p>
<p> and, technically, it is a conscience vote because I gave an undertaking</p>
<p> at the Constitutional Convention that things relating to the republic</p>
<p> would be the subject of that. But I think it's fair of me to</p>
<p> say, and I think it's been pretty accurately reported in the</p>
<p> papers this morning, that you're really looking at a de facto</p>
<p> government position because there was really very little opposition</p>
<p> to the idea in the Party Room. And it is possible  I'm</p>
<p> not making this prediction  but it's possible there may</p>
<p> not be anybody who wants to vote against it when it comes before the</p>
<p> Parliament.</p>
<p>I should point out a couple of other things, that the republican legislation</p>
<p> is government policy, the republic is not government policy but the</p>
<p> holding of the referendum is government policy and, therefore, of</p>
<p> course, the legislation to put it before the people is government</p>
<p> legislation. But in order to allow for the official yes'</p>
<p> and no' cases it will be accepted and arranged and understood</p>
<p> that a number of government Members and Senators will vote against</p>
<p> the legislation in the Parliament, not because they're breaking</p>
<p> ranks with government policy to have the referendum but because that</p>
<p> is needed so that they can officially write the no' case.</p>
<p> And the identity of those people will be worked out in consultation</p>
<p> with the Deputy Prime Minister and myself. There are plenty of volunteers,</p>
<p> I can assure you, who want to vote no' because they're</p>
<p> not in favour of the republic. But I should point out, so as to forestall</p>
<p> any stories about people trying to stop the referendum being held,</p>
<p> that they won't be trying to stop the referendum being held,</p>
<p> it's just necessary, according to the law, if you're to</p>
<p> have an officially circulated no' case somebody must have</p>
<p> voted against it in the Parliament.</p>
<p>I also indicated yesterday that we would have some public funding</p>
<p> of television, radio, newspaper and other material during the intensive</p>
<p> stage of the campaign. Fifteen million dollars is being made available</p>
<p> - $7.5 million to the yes' case, $7.5 million to the no'</p>
<p> case. The respective cases for the expenditure of that, or the material</p>
<p> for the expenditure of that money, will be prepared by committees</p>
<p>  nine people on each side, including what I might loosely call</p>
<p> the usual suspects. There will be a majority of non-parliamentarians</p>
<p> on each committee. There will be no Ministers on either committee</p>
<p> and there'll be no frontbenchers from the Labor Party on either</p>
<p> committee. We're in the process of contacting the people that</p>
<p> we have in mind. It's fair to say that Mr Turnbull will be on</p>
<p> one of the committees and Mrs Jones will be on another. There will</p>
<p> be, if he accepts, one direct election republican on the no'</p>
<p> committee because that compromises part of the case against the republic.</p>
<p> And there will, on the yes' committee, be somebody who</p>
<p> advocated the McGarvie model at the Constitutional Convention but</p>
<p> decided in the end, when that dropped out on the exhaustive voting</p>
<p> principle, to support the Australian Republican Movement's model.</p>
<p> We are, as I say, contacting the people and they are government nominees,</p>
<p> they're not people who have been nominated by the ACM or the</p>
<p> Australian Republican Movement. And when that's been completed</p>
<p> I'll be pleased to announce the names. They were all members</p>
<p> of the Constitutional Convention. And there will be, I think, three</p>
<p> politicians on the yes' committee and two politicians on</p>
<p> the no' committee. I think that's the most sensible</p>
<p> way of handling that issue.</p>
<p>There will be liaison between those two groups and the committees</p>
<p> officially writing the yes' and no' booklets</p>
<p> to be circulated to the households. And the material that they prepare</p>
<p> will be submitted to the Government for audit through the normal processes</p>
<p> but the Government won't be expressing the view as to the political</p>
<p> or campaign impact of any of the material. That will be entirely a</p>
<p> matter for the committees to determine.</p>
<p>In addition to that, we'll also be at an official and neutral</p>
<p> level circulating some material of an educative nature some months</p>
<p> before the referendum campaign, perhaps by means of newspaper supplements</p>
<p> and the like to provide a bit more information on the working of the</p>
<p> Australian Constitution so that people have a better idea of the background</p>
<p> against which the referendum is going to take place.</p>
<p>I should emphasise that the preamble question, the separate preamble</p>
<p> question, will be a republic neutral question so that, naturally,</p>
<p> it will be open to any Australian who wishes to vote no'</p>
<p> to the republic, to vote yes' to the preamble. And I should</p>
<p> make that absolutely clear.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, how attracted are you to some of the other ideas that</p>
<p> were thrust up in the Party Room yesterday about the preamble specifically</p>
<p> acknowledging the contribution of migration and of cultural diversity</p>
<p> to the nation?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I said, Jim, that I'd consider a number of those and I don't</p>
<p> want to respond more than that at the moment because it's very</p>
<p> much in the works. And I'd like the opportunity, having heard</p>
<p> those suggestions, to reflect on how a number of things might be expressed</p>
<p> but I certainly listened to what people had to say and it was an extremely</p>
<p> valuable positive discussion, but I don't want to be anymore</p>
<p> specific than that at this stage.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Must under the law there be a no' case against the preamble,</p>
<p> and if so how do you get that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well no. I'm advised that under the law there doesn't have</p>
<p> to be a no' case. There's only a no' case</p>
<p> under the law if people, as I understand it, vote against the measure</p>
<p> in the Parliament.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>And if they do does there then have to be [inaudible]? Say if Mr Katter</p>
<p> voted.....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well look, I'm not going to answer a hypothetical question. You</p>
<p> asked me a question about the law and that's the law.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Your previous stance was that you weren't going to take an active</p>
<p> role on a day to day basis.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>In relation to the republic.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Now that you're going to take an active role in relation to the</p>
<p> preamble, does that suggest that you may take a more active role in</p>
<p> relation to the republic? And if not, isn't that tacit activity</p>
<p> anyway?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Sorry. What was that last bit?</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>If you take an active role on one part of the referendum....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yeah, but it's a completely separate question. Well, I'm</p>
<p> not going to spend every waking hour but, I mean, I want people to</p>
<p> understand that the preamble, when it is promulgated and put forward,</p>
<p> will have my total support as the head of the Government. And I tried</p>
<p> to explain as openly, as directly as I could earlier what I stance</p>
<p> is. I mean I'll be asking people to support that preamble. How</p>
<p> actively I do that, well I do have other responsibilities and I don't</p>
<p> want to spend the next nine months talking about these two issues</p>
<p> important though they are in the eyes of a lot of people. And I think</p>
<p> the preamble in particular is an important issue and obviously the</p>
<p> head of State issue is important too. I was making the point in the</p>
<p> context of the republican debate that I wasn't going to be talking</p>
<p> about the republic everyday, arguing the merits of the debate everyday.</p>
<p> But Tony, nobody should be in any doubt, I am not a republican and</p>
<p> the Australian people will be left in no doubt as to where I stand</p>
<p> on that issue. But I just don't intend to spend an enormous amount</p>
<p> of time on that, and nor indeed would I expect, particularly over</p>
<p> the next few months, my senior ministers to spend an enormous amount</p>
<p> of time on it. We do have important ongoing other responsibilities</p>
<p> to the Australian people and they would expect us to focus on those</p>
<p> issues not to the total exclusion of other issues but certainly to</p>
<p> the substantial exclusion of other issues.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>On the question of your legal advice regarding the preamble, is there</p>
<p> any threshold to the dissent in the Parliament that requires a no</p>
<p> case to be put? I mean does it only.....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I'd have to check that. The advice I got yesterday was that if,</p>
<p> from the Attorney General, the advice I had was that if nobody votes</p>
<p> against it there's no case circulated. Beyond that I don't</p>
<p> have advice.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, you say that on the preamble that you'd like</p>
<p> to take advice from other people about what it...the wording of</p>
<p> it but I do take it that at the end of the day you'd like the</p>
<p> preamble to have your seal, your stamp on it.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>At the end of the day it will be a preamble that I feel I can totally</p>
<p> support.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>With your words?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, Jim, nobody has total ownership of the words of the English</p>
<p> language. But I'm obviously not going to put something forward</p>
<p> that I don't like but I'm not so conceited as to believe</p>
<p> that if it was something like this I couldn't benefit from the</p>
<p> elegance of the pens of other Australians.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>That's outside the Government?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well yes, oh yes. Of course.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What sort of people?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I'll let you speculate about that.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Bob Ellis?</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>How about Mr Beazley who has asked to be consulted in advance?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well Mr Beazley, after the Government has decided what it would like</p>
<p> I will seek Mr Beazley's views.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Is this before you unveil it publicly as [inaudible]?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well the Government will decide what it wants first and then we will</p>
<p> seek Mr Beazley's views. Mr Beazley a few weeks ago was against</p>
<p> this. Mr Beazley has flipped and flopped on this issue from start</p>
<p> to finish. But look, I'm perfectly happy once we have worked</p>
<p> out what we would like, to seek Mr Beazley's views on it before</p>
<p> it is presented to the Parliament.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What sort of people are you inclined to go to for advice on this?</p>
<p> Academics, Lawyers, poets, writers.....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I'm not going to speculate about that. I'm simply making</p>
<p> it clear, Catherine, that I feel free to seek the advice of any Australian</p>
<p> on this.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, can we get your reaction to the Kurdish demonstrations</p>
<p> around the world and in Sydney?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well let me say a couple of things about those. First of all that</p>
<p> the actual handling of the demonstrations in Sydney is a police matter</p>
<p> and I don't make a habit of commenting on operational police</p>
<p> matters. I think it's best for those to be handled by the police.</p>
<p> There has been discussion between the New South Wales Police and Commonwealth</p>
<p> security authorities overnight and I was given a briefing on those</p>
<p> discussions this morning. Let me say this that it's always part</p>
<p> of the Australian tradition that people have a perfect right to lawfully</p>
<p> express their view about a political issue that occurred anywhere</p>
<p> in the world. And all Australians have that right. But it must be</p>
<p> done in accordance with the law and anything that involves a breach</p>
<p> of the law, anything that involves violence, anything that involves</p>
<p> endangering lives or property, is something that will be condemned</p>
<p> not only by the Government but also by all of the Australian people.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Are you confident that the Commonwealth security agencies such as</p>
<p> ASIO did an adequate job in informing the Greek Consulate that such</p>
<p> a threat was coming?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look I don't comment on those sorts of things and you know that</p>
<p> Paul.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Are you worried about some of Australia's tax positions forcing</p>
<p> Australian companies offshore?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think the proposals that we have in mind in relation to taxation</p>
<p> reform and the machinery we've set up, particularly the Ralph</p>
<p> review, will determine whether there are proper grounds for those</p>
<p> concerns.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[inaudible] capital gains tax?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I've already said that capital gains tax is part of the</p>
<p> Ralph review. We need to ensure that it's not working in the</p>
<p> negative way that some people claim in which I mentioned on the program</p>
<p> at the weekend. I think we ought to wait and see what Ralph has to</p>
<p> say about that. I don't know that there's anything useful</p>
<p> that I can add to what I've already said. It's part of the</p>
<p> review, it needs to be looked at, but we don't want a situation</p>
<p> arising where people are running around saying we don't need</p>
<p> a capital gains tax. I mean we do need a properly working, properly</p>
<p> set capital gains tax as part of the taxation system. But it must</p>
<p> work, as I said at the weekend, in a way that doesn't act as</p>
<p> a disincentive.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[inaudible] new furniture for your office?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well the other furniture had been there for 11 years and was frankly,</p>
<p> in the eyes of people, even those who have been reported in the press</p>
<p> as condemning the decision that I took and casting aspersions on the</p>
<p> quality of that decision, even in their eyes the furniture needed</p>
<p> extensive replacement, refurbishment, or whatever. Indeed I'm</p>
<p> advised that the alternative that was being advocated by those who've</p>
<p> condemned my decision would have involved a cost of $24,864, plus</p>
<p> of course......</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Where do those figures come from?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I beg your pardon?</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What's the basis of those figures?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I'm just telling you I'm advised by people who know</p>
<p> that that was the figure. And there's another figure $1500 for</p>
<p> consultancy. So not only was the alternative that I decided upon involving</p>
<p> Australian made material, it was also on those figures significantly</p>
<p> cheaper.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, Jocelyn Newman attacked the Anglican Churches today.</p>
<p> Is that anyway to treat a supporter of the GST?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I don't know that she's attacked the church. But can</p>
<p> I just say one thing about food and the GST, let me say something</p>
<p> catholic about what the Anglicans have said, and that is that I thought</p>
<p> at the end of last year, or before the election, his Grace, the Catholic</p>
<p> Archbishop of Melbourne, had something very sensible if I may say</p>
<p> so with respect and I do respect him, about taxation, he s</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
