<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7911</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH WARWICK BEUTLER, ABC AM PRE-RECORDED 18 FEBRUARY 1990 (TO AIR 19 FEBRUARY 1990)</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/02/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007911.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH WARWICK BEUTLER, ABC AM<br />
PRE-RECORDED 18 FEBRUARY 1990 ( TO AIR 19 FEBRUARY 1990)<br />
E OE PROOF ONLY<br />
THOMPSON: Mr Hawke spoke to Warwick Beutler at The Lodge<br />
in Canberra last night just a few days ahead of the<br />
announcement of the new wages-tax-superannuation deal<br />
with the ACTU. It's expected to deliver a substantial<br />
wage rise next financial year. Mr Hawke wouldn't reveal<br />
the details of the wage deal but he did discuss the<br />
principles on which it was based.<br />
PM: You've got to have decisions which produce the best<br />
outcome in aggregate terms. Quite clearly if you are not<br />
able to negotiate an arrangement with the trade union<br />
movement which gives you predictable outcomes and within<br />
reasonable bounds, then the alternative, and certainly<br />
the alternative which is contained in the Opposition's<br />
policy will be a massive wages breakout.<br />
BEUTLER: So it's the price we've got to pay for<br />
industrial harmony is it?<br />
PM: It's not a question of the price you have to pay.<br />
It's a question of making a choice as a society whether<br />
you want the chaos of the alternative prescription, and<br />
we don't have to be theoretical about it. They practised<br />
this at the beginning of the ' 80s wages explosion,<br />
collapse of the economy, worse recession in 50 years,<br />
double digit inflation, double digit employment never<br />
before been achieved. Now that's the alternative you've<br />
got. BEUTLER: Yes but the other alternative, the alternative<br />
under your Government, is to deliver big pay rises when<br />
the country has to pay for that in high inflation, high<br />
interest rates and we price ourselves out of<br />
international markets, don't we?<br />
PM: On the contrary. You conveniently ignore the facts.<br />
Let's take the last point first, pricing ourselves out of<br />
international markets. In the last two years a 14%<br />
increase in real terms in manufactured exports. Totally<br />
inconsistent with the proposition that you're putting.'<br />
If you price yourself out of international markets you<br />
can't have a 14% real increase in manufactured exports. </p>
<p>BEUTLER: But we still have the worst balance of payments<br />
crisis we've ever had in our history.<br />
PM: That is in fact not true. The current account<br />
deficit and your external position as a proportion of GDP<br />
was in fact worse just before we came to office than now.<br />
Now the fact is that what we<br />
BEUTLER: But you wouldn't say it was good now, would<br />
you? PM: No of course not. There's room for improvement.<br />
But you wouldn't say would you either Warwick that you've<br />
priced yourself out of business if in the seven years of<br />
government you've created 1.6 million new jobs, a rate of<br />
employment growth five times as fast as in the previous<br />
seven years and if you've had a rate of employment growth<br />
twice as fast as the rest of the world and if in that 1.6<br />
million new jobs that we've created, 92% of them have<br />
been in the private sector. How about taking account of<br />
that. BEUTLER: Yes, and we've got<br />
PM: Thank you.<br />
BEUTLER: and we've got high interest rates, very high<br />
interest rates.<br />
PM: Not as high we haven't reached the peak that we<br />
did under the conservatives.<br />
BEUTLER: We wouldn't want to would we?<br />
PM: No, we certainly wouldn't want to achieve any of the<br />
things that they did in their period and we haven't. Now<br />
let me make the point that as far as the high level of<br />
interest rates is concerned, I haven't tried to hide the<br />
fact that they've been high. But they've had to be high,<br />
as I've explained to the Australian people, because we<br />
had a situation, put simply, in the last full financial<br />
year you had an eight per cent increase in consumption, a<br />
four per cent increase in production, and that gap of<br />
four per cent was taken up by imports. You can't keep<br />
doing that. So with tight fiscal policy and tight wages<br />
policy you also had to have tight monetary policy. You<br />
see I'm not, as I've said, I'm not a masochist, I'm not a<br />
sadist. I don't want to hurt myself. I'd be out of my<br />
cotton picking mind to hurt myself and I'd be out of my<br />
cotton picking mind to hurt you and your listeners.<br />
Because you have votes and you're going to cast a vote.<br />
The reason why we had to have tight monetary policy was<br />
to ease demand. And to have it goes back to what<br />
you're talking about, our external position. If we<br />
hadn't been prepared to supress demand in the economy you<br />
would've had an infinitely worse external position, which<br />
is what you're talking about. </p>
<p>BEUTLER: You mention interest rates. Interest rates<br />
have begun to fall and housing interest rates can't be<br />
too far behind. But they can't fall far can they?<br />
PM: The extent of their fall is not something that I can<br />
predict. But what is the most important thing for your<br />
listeners I think is not in a sense what I'm saying but<br />
what the banking industry itself is saying. They are<br />
saying quite clearly and universally that interest rates<br />
are going to fall. They are already falling. The cash<br />
rates have fallen. They're down now, cash and bills are<br />
down very significantly. You've got the situation where<br />
they've reduced prime rates and they've indicated they're<br />
going to fall further and that mortgage rates are going<br />
to fall.<br />
BEUTLER: But they can't fall far can they?<br />
PM: They can fall considerably but I can't put a figure<br />
on it and I'm not going to because that would be quite<br />
irresponsible. But what we have done is to take the<br />
tough decisions and take a lot of flak for making the<br />
tough decisions and being prepared to make tough<br />
decisions. The other side have the rhetoric but we had<br />
the responsibility and the courage to take the tough<br />
decisions. And now what the financial community is<br />
saying, and saying unequivocably, is that those policies<br />
have worked, are working, and within that framework that<br />
rates can come down. Now the extent to which rates fall<br />
is, they're not capable of exact prediction. And I'm not<br />
going to say how much. All I can say is that I've done<br />
the tough work with Paul Keating and have copped the<br />
flak.<br />
BEUTLER: But give us a ball park figure.<br />
PM: No, I'm not going to give you a ball park figure. I<br />
know you'd like one Warwick. Wouldn't it be good for you<br />
to be able to say I got the Prime Minister to give a ball<br />
park figure. I'm not going to do it.<br />
BEUTLER: How much will wages grow next year?<br />
PM: Well that will be part of the statement that the<br />
Treasurer will be making on Wednesday. He'll give you a<br />
precise figure as to what the projected wages growth<br />
figure will be for ' 90-91.<br />
BEUTLER: Can voters be excused in this election for<br />
believing there's not much of a choice at all, for<br />
believing that you and Mr Peacock are a bit like Bib and<br />
Bub. You don't differ on foreign policy, you don't<br />
differ on defence, you don't differ on the need to help<br />
the family, to help middle Australia.<br />
PM: Just excuse my laughter. Let's take it bit by bit.<br />
' We don't differ on foreign policy.' Well let's just<br />
give you one smidgeon of difference. I'm being </p>
<p>sarcastic. Fundamental. I negotiated, initiated and<br />
brought to fruition the South Pacific Nuclear Free Zone<br />
Treaty to which we are a party. Mr Peacock would abandon<br />
that to allow the stationing of nuclear weapons in<br />
Australia. Do you think that's peripheral? Fundamental.<br />
I suggest<br />
BEUTLER: But the United States doesn't support that<br />
Treaty for example.<br />
PM: The United States is not running my policy. Nor<br />
would they, I think, hope to have their policy run by Mr<br />
Peacock or be running his. The question you asked was<br />
not about a difference between me and the United States.<br />
I think if you roll the tape you'll find, and it will<br />
show that you asked about the difference between Mr<br />
Peacock and me. Correct?<br />
BEUTLER: ( inaudible)<br />
PM: Yes, correct. That was a yes listeners. Yes he<br />
said. And in answer to the questions you put to me I'm<br />
saying on that fundamental question of whether you have<br />
nuclear weapons stationed in Australia or not, Mr Peacock<br />
would abolish our adherence to the Treaty that I<br />
negotiated which prevents that happening.<br />
BEUTLER: That's one minor element. But essentially<br />
PM: Your judgement ' minor', but I doubt Warwick whether<br />
your listeners would regard the question of whether<br />
you're in favour of the stationing of nuclear weapons in<br />
Australia or not as minor. You may regard it as minor.<br />
I don't.<br />
BEUTLER: Alright. The family.<br />
PM: The family. Yes, well, I was coming to the family.<br />
Now let's look at the family. Rhetoric is cheap and<br />
easy. But you know, if you have a concern for the family<br />
you' re not talking about something that lives up in<br />
Mohammed's coffin. They exist here in Australia. You<br />
know what affects the welfare of families? Let me tell<br />
you. Jobs, education and health.<br />
BEUTLER: And interest rates.<br />
PM: We'll come to interest rates. They had higher<br />
interest rates than we've ever reached. So dispose of<br />
that. Now, let's look at what they did in regard to the<br />
three things which are fundamental to the question of the<br />
welfare of families. Jobs last 12 months, another<br />
quarter of a million on the unemployment scrapheap. The<br />
worst record of employment and unemployment of any poswar<br />
government. They brought the worst recession in<br />
years. Threw mum and dad and the kids out of work.<br />
Health we came to office with two million Australians,<br />
you know, members of families. Not somewhere out there </p>
<p>in Mars. Two million members of Australian families<br />
uncovered for hospitals and doctors visits. If they got<br />
crook they had no cover. Now they were very concerned<br />
with families weren't they. Well my concern with<br />
families was translated by bringing in Medicare which<br />
meant that every Australian, every member of every<br />
Australian family covered. Not having to worry about<br />
being unable to pay the bill. Education let's just<br />
think about education and how they talk about their<br />
concern for families. Do you know what their magnificent<br />
achievement was? Seven years in office and they<br />
increased the participation rate by a miserable two<br />
percentage points, from 34% to 36% when they walked out<br />
of office. In other words one in three of Australian<br />
kids staying on in the education system. The basic<br />
building block of education. The basic determinant of<br />
the future welfare of the kids of Australian families. I<br />
said that was pathetic. And against their two percentage<br />
points increase from 34% to 36, I've lifted it from 36 to<br />
62 and next year it will be 65. In other words, not one<br />
out of three but now two out of three kids staying on in<br />
school. So you've got it. Jobs, health, education.<br />
They can have the rhetoric. Give me the facts.<br />
BEUTLER: Yes but you can constantly refer to the<br />
previous seven years of the Fraser government and it's<br />
natural that you should make that comparison. But a lot<br />
of Australians aren't interested in what happened then.<br />
They're interested in what's going to happen in the next<br />
seven years.<br />
PM: Exactly. And it's because they are promising<br />
exactly the same as the policies before that I go back to<br />
the past. Not simply to say there's their seven years<br />
and there's mine. But you look at the issues that we<br />
talked about jobs, the economy. What devastated the<br />
economy in the last years of their office? Very simple.<br />
They had no wages policy. They allowed wages to explode.<br />
The economy collapsed. They are promising a return to<br />
exactly the same thing. So what they produced before<br />
will produce the same or even worse this time. Health<br />
they are now promising a return of the same. To abolish<br />
Medicare. To go back to the situation where people will<br />
be uncovered. In regard to education, the same thing.<br />
You look at their education policies in regard to<br />
universities. They are saying we'll give a certain<br />
number of scholarships and then the rest will be fees.<br />
So the rich will get the places, the poor and the middle<br />
income people miss out. They are returning in other<br />
words to exactly the sort of policies which gave the<br />
disaster of the past.<br />
BEUTLER: Do you accept that 30% of the electorate, as<br />
much as 30% of the electorate is undecided?<br />
PM: I would doubt if it's as high as that. But I see<br />
some polls suggest it. But they will make up their mind.<br />
That suits me fine because I mean, if that figure's </p>
<p>right because what they're already seeing in the<br />
election, what they are already seeing is the total<br />
disarray of the Opposition. They are seeing the absolute<br />
unity of purpose and of policy of my people. And the big<br />
question, the big question is going to be in regard to<br />
all their rhetoric and their promises ' where's the money<br />
coming from?'<br />
BEUTLER: Is your Government tired?<br />
PM: Do I look tired?<br />
BEUTLER: I said is the Government tired?<br />
PM: No, well I'm a large part of the Government. I'm<br />
certainly not the Government exclusively. But I'm not<br />
tired. My Ministers are not tired.<br />
BEUTLER: Why is it necessary for you to spend $ 19<br />
million on advertising in this election?<br />
PM: It won't be $ 19 million on advertising. I think<br />
there was some reference that the total cost of the<br />
campaign might be of that order. But that's not just<br />
advertising. BEUTLER: But a fair amount of it will be advertising.<br />
PM: ( inaudible)<br />
BEUTLER: Why do you need to spend that much?<br />
PM: Well, the Opposition will have unlimited financial<br />
support. I think<br />
BEUTLER: You will too.<br />
PM: I wish you were right my friend, I wish you were<br />
right. Not unlimited I can assure you.<br />
BEUTLER: No, but you'll spend more than they will.<br />
PM: I don't know about that. We've got no reason at<br />
this stage to judge that that'll be true. They've<br />
already started. We haven't. I mean<br />
BEUTLER: But why is it necessary?<br />
PM: Would you suggest we don't need to spend any on<br />
advertising? You're saying it's a tight election and<br />
we've got to explain to the Australian people. I mean I<br />
think if we listen to the rest of, y'now, what's gone on<br />
before this you would concede that probably there's a lot<br />
of the Australian people don't yet fully understand and<br />
appreciate why there's been a need to do some of the<br />
things we've done, what are some of the achievements of<br />
the Goverment in a whole range of areas. I don't blame<br />
them for that. If there's been a problem in a full </p>
<p>comprehension, we have to accept some of the blame for<br />
that. Then if that's true then in the campaign we've got<br />
to make sure that people do understand what the<br />
alternative is. I mean I so deeply believe Warwick that<br />
this election is crucial for the future of this country.<br />
It really is going to determine in my judgement what sort<br />
of Australia we take into the 21st Century. If $ 19<br />
million is the figure that needs to be spent to make sure<br />
that the right decision is made well then so be it.<br />
BEUTLER: Andrew Peacock surprised you in 1984 didn't he?<br />
PM: No he didn't surpise me. No he didn't.<br />
BEUTLER: You didn't think he'd do as well as he did.<br />
PM: Well. Were you privy to the polling? I mean I know<br />
what the leads were of the Government and the Opposition<br />
at that time. And there is some suggestion that it was a<br />
massive gap, that we were streets ahead. We never were<br />
streets ahead?<br />
BEUTLER: What's the polling say this time?<br />
PM: That's for me to know and you to find out if you<br />
can. I don't like your chances.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
