<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8296</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/05/1991</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008296.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR MEDIA 7 MAY 1991<br />
1 will be visiting Europe from 5 to 17 June 1991. The visit:<br />
will include Geneva, Paris, London, Luxembourg, Bonn and<br />
Berlin. I will be having discussions with GATT Director-General<br />
Dunkel in Geneva; with Prime Minister Rocard and the French<br />
Trade Minister in Paris; with Prime Minister Major and other<br />
Ministers in London; with Prime Minister Santer of<br />
Luxembourg, and with the President of the European<br />
Commission, Mr Delors, in Luxembourg; and with President<br />
Weizsaecker, Chancellor Kohl and German Ministers in Bonn.<br />
While in London, I will attend the two-day meeting of the<br />
Commonwealth High Level Appraisal Group which will consider<br />
Commonwealth priorities for the 1990s and beyond.<br />
I will launch the Paris chapter of Australian Business In<br />
Europe, a new group which will bring together businessmen<br />
with a common interest in expanding Australia's trade and<br />
economic relattions. I will also be addressing the<br />
Federation of German Industries in Cologne.<br />
In Geneva, I will address the United Nations Conference on<br />
Disarmament. Australia is internationally respected in<br />
disarmament forums and has a contribution to make,<br />
especially in the area of chemical weapons.<br />
In Germany, 3: will visit both Bonn and Berlin, and the state<br />
of Brandenburg in the former East Germany.<br />
At a time when Europe is reassessing its role and priorities<br />
in the aftermath of the Gulf War and when a single European<br />
Community market is close to realisation, the visit will<br />
provide important opportunities for me to promote<br />
Australia's developing relations with the new Europe and to<br />
raise Austral. ia's concerns about the European Community's<br />
agricultural subsidies and our interest in a successful<br />
completion of the Uruguay Round. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
