<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7836</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER ANNUAL DINNER OF THE CONFEDERATION OF AUSTRALIAN INDUSTRY CANBERRA - 29 NOVEMBER 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/11/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007836.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELITVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
ANNUAL DINNER OF THE<br />
CONFEDERATION OF AUSTRALIAN INDUSTRY<br />
CANBERRA 29 NOVEMBER 1989<br />
Tonight's annual dinner of the CAI occurs at a truly<br />
significant time for the debate about the future of the<br />
Australian economy.<br />
It is a time requiring renewed efforts by the Government to<br />
explain to the community the necessity and effectiveness of<br />
the strategy we are following.<br />
And it is a time that is flushing out the opportunism of the<br />
Coalition parties who are making a bid for power that is<br />
fundamentally and, I believe, fatally flawed.<br />
It a significant time when some respected business and media<br />
commentators are preoccupied with doom-saying while many<br />
basic characteristics of the economy are fundamentally<br />
bright. So I welcome this opportunity to talk to you, and through<br />
you to ask the Australian business community about the sort<br />
of Australia in which it wants to operate.<br />
That is neither a frivolous question nor an academic one.<br />
It is a question you will have to contemplate seriously in<br />
the coming months.<br />
Because the answer the Australian community gives will<br />
profoundly affect the prospects for Australian business'and<br />
the Australian economy at large.<br />
There are two alternative Australias facing business: an<br />
Australia of confrontation, an Australia shaken by a wages<br />
explosion and industrial warfare, an Australia of recession<br />
and of introspection; or an Australia of co-operation and<br />
industrial order, of sensible wage determination, and of<br />
deliberate pursuit of a clear strategy of internationalising<br />
the economy. </p>
<p>Then, of course, there is also the fantasy world of<br />
Professor Hewson who talks in terms of no inflation, no rise<br />
in unemployment, minimal interest rates the world whose<br />
creation Ross Gittens says would win the Nobel Prize.<br />
I ask you to take a hard-nosed look at the two Australias<br />
that, realistically, are open to you.<br />
In doing so I make no apology for these direct<br />
politically-relevant comments.<br />
Indeed, in making these points, I am returning to the theme<br />
to which I have devoted considerable attention over the last<br />
few weeks in Parliament, press conferences and speeches<br />
namely, the vast chasm that separates this Government from<br />
the Opposition in every aspect of Government policy making.<br />
When I addressed the Evatt Foundation recently I focussed on<br />
the deep ideological divide between us and the conservatives<br />
on social justice; when I spoke to the National Farmers'<br />
Federation and when I launched the Garnaut report I<br />
addressed the profoundly different approaches we have<br />
brought to the task of micro-economic reform and its<br />
relationship to our future in the Asia-Pacific region.<br />
Today I want to address issues of macro-economic policy.<br />
Do you remember Hanrahan, the farmer in John O'Brien's poem<br />
whose incessant prediction was: " We'll all be rooned"?<br />
If it wasn't a drought Hanrahan was lamenting, it was a<br />
flood or the threat of bushfires the only thing certain<br />
was that one way or another " we'll all be rooned, before<br />
the year is out."<br />
Hanrahan could easily get a job today as an economic<br />
commentator with some of the newspapers or financial<br />
institutions or as an advisor to the Coalition.<br />
This week, for example, he would have been bemoaning the<br />
current dip in house prices just a few months after<br />
lamenting increases in house prices. We'll all be rooned if<br />
house prices rise; we'll all be rooned if they fall.<br />
Don't misinterpret me. I welcome the current debate about<br />
interest rates, foreign debt and the balance of payments.<br />
And I'll address each of these tonight.<br />
But what I find disappointing and, more than that, what I<br />
find damaging to the community and to the economy itself<br />
is the Hanrahan-style refusal to take a balanced or<br />
comprehensive view about the economy.<br />
Hanrahan reckons things are pretty crook in today's business<br />
world. </p>
<p>3.<br />
The profit share is 23 per cent higher than the average of<br />
the last 15 years and 50 per cent higher than it was when<br />
the Labor Government came to office.<br />
The company tax rate is down to 39 per cent.<br />
Real unit labour costs have fallen more than 11 per cent<br />
since 1983.<br />
Business investment is at its highest level in 40 years.<br />
Manufacturing investment has been growing at 13 per cent in<br />
real terms per annum over the last five years compared<br />
with a rate of minus 1.6 per cent over the previous five<br />
years. And Access Economics has documented $ 90 billion in new<br />
investment projects in the pipeline or at an advanced stage<br />
of planning.<br />
Now I'm not saying there are no problems. There are real<br />
problems and the Government is by no means complacent<br />
about them.<br />
The build-up of Australia's international debt is a real<br />
problem. The Government has never sought to deny that. But<br />
we do not accept the Hanrahans of the Macquarie Bank who<br />
predict a cataclysmic explosion in our overseas debt by the<br />
turn of the century. Nor for that matter does<br />
Sir Roderick Carnegie, orthe former Governor of the Reserve<br />
Bank, or EPAC whose conclusion earlier this year was that<br />
stabilisation of Australia's foreign debt at around the<br />
existing level could occur in the mid-1990s.<br />
Remember that our net external debt stood at 34% of GDP in<br />
September 1986, and it now stands at 31.9 per cent.<br />
In other words, substantial stabilisation of our<br />
indebtedness has already occurred.<br />
The modern day Hanrahans seem to think that all debt is bad.<br />
Some of those people are running our larger companies.<br />
Presumably debt was not a dirty word when their boards of<br />
directors considered the financing of their new investments.<br />
Yet when commenting on the national accumulation of all<br />
those investment decisions 89 per cent of Australia's debt<br />
is business related the verdict is, " we'll all be rooned".<br />
Of course the nation must service that net debt of which,<br />
as you know, the Commonwealth owes not a cent but most of<br />
that indebtedness would not have been incurred had<br />
businesses not had the expectation and the confidence it<br />
could be repaid with interest. </p>
<p>The Government could, of course, slash Australia's overseas<br />
debt and break the balance of payments problem by banning<br />
the importation of planes by Qantas and the domestic<br />
airlines. We could prohibit the importation of factory<br />
equipment, computers, construction materials which are<br />
being used to re-tool and reconstruct the Australian<br />
economy. But those policies, while reducing debt, would not<br />
be in the nation's economic interests.<br />
And I add this observation: our foreign debt would have<br />
been up to $ 42 billion, or nearly 40 per cent, lower if my<br />
Government had not freed up opportunities for Australian<br />
investment abroad. For that has been the growth in<br />
Australian equity investment overseas from $ 7 billion in<br />
1983 to $ 49 billion now. That investment will yield future<br />
income for Australia: it is already yielding $ 3 billion a<br />
year, more than double the inflow of only three years ago.<br />
Hanrahan would no doubt point out that Australian foreign<br />
investment abroad is smaller than foreign investment in<br />
Australia. But there has always been foreign investment in<br />
Australia; it has only been in recent years that such<br />
spectacular growth in Australian investment abroad has<br />
occurred. It is income-earning investment; investment that<br />
is integrating Australia into the global economy; investment<br />
which is generating markets, technology, ideas, skills.<br />
Obviously if national savings were higher Australia could<br />
finance this Australian overseas investment and reduce its<br />
dependence on foreign debt.<br />
For our part, the Government is making a substantial<br />
contribution to the national savings effort. Since coming<br />
to office we have, by turning around the Public Sector<br />
Borrowing Requirement by 8 per cent of GDP, increased public<br />
sector savings by around $ 30 billion per annum. This year<br />
is the fourth year of real reductions in Commonwealth<br />
outlays. As a proportion of GDP they will reach their<br />
lowest level since the mid-1970s: lower than in any of the<br />
seven years of the previous Government.<br />
This is the tightest fiscal policy Australia has ever seen.<br />
These figures provide a firm basis for the future. Indeed,<br />
by 1992-93, we expect Government outlays to be at their<br />
lowest level since the early 1960s.<br />
So on fiscal policy, the Government's record, our current<br />
performance, and our future determination are matters not of<br />
speculation or of rhetoric but of fact. </p>
<p>And so it is with the second instrument of macro-economic<br />
management: wages policy. You have heard me often enough<br />
speaking of the benefits to Australian workers and<br />
businesses of the Prices and Incomes Accord the creation<br />
of more than one and a half million new jobs, the 11 per<br />
cent reduction in real unit labour costs, the 60 per cent<br />
reduction in industrial disputation and, I repeat, a higher<br />
profit share and record investment.<br />
But let me cite fresh, independent evidence just released by<br />
Drs Chapman, Dowrick and Junakar in a paper presented to an<br />
economic policy conference at the Australian National<br />
University. Their study concludes that the Accord has<br />
contributed massively to job growth, to an associated fall<br />
in unemployment and to an increase in the profit share.<br />
This is the Accord that our political opponents have from<br />
day one written of f as a doomed experiment. Hanrahan has<br />
predicted its demise more often than I can recall. But it<br />
still survives and adapts providing now a comprehensive<br />
basis for the establishment of responsible wage outcomes in<br />
concert with improvements in the social wage.<br />
The current process of award restructuring presents an<br />
opportunity to tackle some of the barriers to improved<br />
industry efficiency and productivity.<br />
I stress the word ' opportunity'.<br />
Sustainable increases in productivity will not come from<br />
unilateral Government action. They depend upon business and<br />
employee willingness to change, and on an environment<br />
conducive to change.<br />
My Government is creating that environment. A clear<br />
strategy of internationalising the Australian economy has<br />
changed the economic debate in Australia.<br />
We have now widespread acceptance of the need for micro<br />
reform, particularly the idea of exposing Australians to<br />
competition, both domestic and overseas.<br />
This promotes change.<br />
And ~ it will encourage use of the opportunities available<br />
through the current wage fixing system for increased<br />
productivity. Such opportunities are not static.<br />
Broader mechanisms are in place to bring about a move away<br />
from occupational awards and fragmented, craft based unions<br />
to arrangements which better reflect the needs of industries<br />
and enterprises. </p>
<p>We are seeing union amalgamations, an acceptance of<br />
significantly fewer bargaining units on the factory floor<br />
indeed, the desirable goal is one such bargaining unit and<br />
widespread acknowledgement that craft-based awards need<br />
redrafting. And we will take these developments much further through the<br />
Accord and within nationally accepted wage fixing<br />
principles. But, and this is vital, at the same time as the objectives<br />
of increased flexibility and decentralisation are being<br />
achieved, we are maintaining an institutional structure that<br />
produces responsible aggregate wage outcomes.<br />
This is fundamental to assessing the desirable path for<br />
future change.<br />
So you should not simply listen to political promises about<br />
wage and productivity outcomes you must look carefully at<br />
the proposed policy actions.<br />
The increases in productivity flowing from award<br />
restructuring will in some cases be immediate, and in other<br />
cases take longer. But in all cases they are being achieved<br />
through sensible and constructive negotiations in which<br />
everyone can play a part.<br />
Look at the recent airline upheavals.<br />
As a result of the actions of the AFAP very large<br />
productivity increases will occur in the airline industry.<br />
But they have not been achieved in a way desired by my<br />
Government. There has been massive disruption and pain for tourism; an<br />
expensive program of training new pilots; and inevitably an<br />
aftertaste of bitterness.<br />
This is the espoused method of Coalition reform.<br />
But is the bull in the china shop approach the desirable<br />
method of achieving micro reform? It produces a lot of<br />
broken china.<br />
And would will the Coalition have the guts to follow it<br />
through? They would have given into the AFAP. What chance<br />
would they stand with the Waterside Workers?<br />
With continued responsible wage setting practices and with<br />
continued fiscal restraint, we will, in time, be able to<br />
ease the pressure on the third instrument of macro-economic<br />
policy monetary policy. </p>
<p>I know high interest rates give no pleasure to the business<br />
community. I certainly know home buyers hate high interest<br />
rates. And as a politician, I'm not thrilled about them<br />
either. But it would be economically irresponsible to bring down<br />
interest rates prematurely.<br />
I will not do that.<br />
The Government's three-pronged attack on the unsustainable<br />
growth in domestic demand accompanied by our continued<br />
program of micro-economic reform is beginning to show the<br />
desired results. Signs of a slowdown are becoming more<br />
widespread. But the Government will not ease monetary policy until it is<br />
confident that the slowdown in demand is broadly based.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen<br />
Contrast all this with the other world in which you as<br />
business men and women could live. That is the world<br />
offered by the conservatives. I don't have to traverse the<br />
full terrain with you, because most of you have been there<br />
before. Remember 1980, 1981, 19827 An 18 per cent wage<br />
explosion. Industrial chaos. Factories closing down.<br />
Double digit inflation. Double digit unemployment. The<br />
lowest profit share in more than 20 years. High marginal<br />
tax rates. Ninety day bank bills at 22 per cent.<br />
That's the other world. The conservatives are caught in a<br />
time warp: the Economic Action Plan promises to take you<br />
back in the time tunnel to 1982. It took business<br />
investment five years to recover from that battering. Their<br />
policies promise a new belting for business.<br />
No-one who cares about the future of the economy can take<br />
comfort from the fact that after seven years in Opposition,<br />
the would-be Government has produced only a woefully thin<br />
document, full of policy contradictions, a prescription that<br />
would take us back to the past.<br />
If we are to address our serious economic problems, we won't<br />
do it with a plan whose philosophy John Elliott describes as<br />
taking from the bludgers and giving to the workers.<br />
Lest I be accused of sounding like Hanrahan, I want to<br />
substantiate those claims with three facts.<br />
Fact One: the Economic Action Plan involves a very<br />
substantial relaxation of fiscal policy. By the Coalition's<br />
own stated figuring it involves no tightening. But there is<br />
an $ 800 million over-estimate of savings on unemployment<br />
benefit identified by the Department of Finance. Add to<br />
that the multi-billion dollar handback of capital gains tax<br />
revenue and you have a significantly relaxed fiscal policy. </p>
<p>I ask you, as representatives of the Australian business<br />
community, to consider the full economic ramifications of<br />
the Liberals' promise to abolish Labor's capital gains tax:<br />
S the consequent relaxation of fiscal policy must<br />
inevitably increase the pressure on interest rates;<br />
S there would be highly distorting behaviour in relation<br />
to asset disposals driven by a desire to minimise or<br />
avoid tax on capital gains;<br />
S a sell-off would occur on stock markets as shareholders<br />
sought to realise their capital gains before the<br />
following Federal election;<br />
S capital would be diverted once again away from<br />
economically productive, job creating investments and<br />
into schemes yielding tax-free capital gains.<br />
I put it to you in the strongest possible terms that<br />
Australia's economic difficulties will be worsened by<br />
abolishing Labor's capital gains tax returning us to the<br />
days when the fastest growing industry, indeed the only<br />
thriving industry, was tax avoidance.<br />
Fact Two: the conservatives' industrial relations policy<br />
would return Australian business to the industrial jungle.<br />
Their policy is no different from what it was in 1981 and<br />
1982. And if you need any evidence of that, just look at<br />
their explicit and still continuing support for the<br />
Australian Federation of Air Pilots.<br />
The strong are allowed to opt out and exercise their<br />
industrial muscle just as they did in 1981; just as the<br />
AFAP sought to do.<br />
It is a policy that the Opposition Leader has failed to<br />
articulate because he does not understand it. It is, in<br />
reality, a complete abrogation of responsibility in the<br />
critically important area of wage fixation.<br />
Fact three follows from the previous two.<br />
In the end the only weapon the conservatives really have to<br />
contain their wages explosion would be to depress the<br />
economy through high interest rates. It is a theory that<br />
was practised with disastrous results when they were last in<br />
office. While ninety day bank bills are currently around<br />
18 per cent, in April 1982, I repeat, they reached<br />
22 per cent.<br />
In the final analysis they would have no choice a looser<br />
fiscal policy and a wages break-out would leave them totally<br />
reliant on the swing instrument, interest rates, to bring<br />
the economy to heel at massive economic cost and social<br />
dislocation. </p>
<p>That is why I have made it quite clear that while interest<br />
rates are high now, they would certainly be very much higher<br />
under a hypothetical Peacock Government.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen<br />
Members of the CAI and all those concerned about the<br />
economic future of this country have a fundamental<br />
question to answer: what kind of Australia do they wish to<br />
live in and invest in?<br />
Would they rather it be an Australia whose immediate<br />
economic problems high interest rates, debt and current<br />
account imbalances reflect buoyant employment growth and<br />
record private investment.<br />
Or an Australia where the economic levers are pulled by<br />
would-be Nobel Prize winners trying to demonstrate the<br />
impossible notion that interest rates and inflation can<br />
be eliminated without job loss an experiment with<br />
architecture as much as with economics, because it<br />
would drive interest rates through the ceiling, the<br />
dollar through the floor and all our hopes of recovery<br />
out the window?<br />
Would they prefer 1989 where families that need second<br />
incomes can find an additional job?<br />
Or a return to 1982-83 where families found their sole<br />
breadwinners had lost their jobs because the dole queue<br />
was being used as an instrument of economic policy<br />
making?<br />
Would they rather live and invest in an Australia that has<br />
started down the road of economic reconstruction, shaking<br />
off the bad habits of protectionism and introspection, and<br />
building a thriving, diverse export culture?<br />
Or an Australia back in the hands of those whose<br />
slavish subservience to the agrarian socialists meant<br />
the taxpayers forked out subsidy after tariff after<br />
bounty for sectional interest groups?<br />
Would they rather have an Australia where wages are set in a<br />
predictable, stable fashion, where aggregate wage outcomes<br />
reflect national priorities of international competitiveness<br />
and domestic social justice?<br />
Or an Australia where the strong can extract massive<br />
wage increases and there is thought to be no need to<br />
control aggregate wage outcomes?<br />
Would they rather see an Australia where personal and<br />
corporate rates of taxation are set so as to create an<br />
efficient and fair system of taxation, that directs<br />
investment to productive job creating activity? </p>
<p>Or would they rather see public revenue undermined and<br />
public confidence eroded by the ingenuity of the sharp<br />
paper shufflers aided and abetted by the smart tax<br />
accountants and lawyers whose sole activity is to find<br />
and exploit loopholes?<br />
You should have no doubt about the kind of Australia that we<br />
are trying to build.<br />
Australia is in the middle of an historic transition from a<br />
narrow, inward-looking, uncompetitive economy to a broadly<br />
based, export-oriented economy that can proudly take its<br />
place in the world.<br />
The nation has its economic problems, but the Government's<br />
macro-and micro-economic reforms are delivering<br />
demonstrable improvement.<br />
There is no time for looking back to the easy comfort of<br />
mediocrity, relying on a good harvest or wool clip, or a<br />
mineral commodity boom then dragging ourselves through the<br />
next rural bust, blaming the rest of the world for not<br />
paying us a living.<br />
Now is a time of hope, not despair a time for keeping our<br />
eyes on the long-term goal of an internationally competitive<br />
economy. In a few short years we have travelled a very<br />
great distance along the national road of economic<br />
reconstruction. And through co-operation, consensus and a<br />
shared commitment to see the job through we will take into<br />
the 21st Century a re-invigorated, modern and cohesive<br />
nation, one truly able to stand up and make a full<br />
contribution to global prosperity.<br />
The Australian economy is fundamentally strong.<br />
We are experiencing an investment boom unparalleled in<br />
Australia in the period that records have been kept an<br />
investment boom spanning the entire economy and with<br />
enormous potential for new jobs and new exports.<br />
Employment growth is twice the rate of the Western world.<br />
Participation in employment is at record levels, as is<br />
participation in the education system.<br />
We have a stable yet flexible wages system that has survived<br />
the intense pressures placed on it by buoyant economic<br />
conditions one that through its inherent adaptability will<br />
be a key instrument for continued economic reform.<br />
The public sector is in long-term surplus and the<br />
Commonwealth is reducing the national debt.<br />
Today's national accounts support our Budget predictions<br />
that the current account deficit will improve significantly<br />
in the first half of next year. Demand growth is slowing<br />
and net exports are contributing once again to growth. </p>
<p>11.<br />
Our foreign debt must be brought down. There is clearly no<br />
room for complacency. But most certainly it is not a time<br />
for heeding the Hanrahans among us. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
