<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8889</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP MATTHEW TALBOT HOSTEL APPEAL SYDNEY - 11 JUNE 1993</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/06/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008889.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL i1Jun. 93 11: 29 No. UU4 V. Ulluz)<br />
rv A s;<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P 3 KEAITING MP<br />
MATTHEW TALBOT HOSTEL APPEAL<br />
SYDNEY 11 JUNE 1993<br />
Ladies and gentlemen<br />
It is a prl~. ylege to be invited here to launch an appeal<br />
by one of the great charitable organisations of<br />
Australia, for one of the great humane institutions of<br />
Sydney. The St Vincent de Paul has been around f or a very long<br />
time of course. It doesn't have as high 8 profile 8s some<br />
of the other charitable institutions, but it is<br />
unquestionably the biggest, it provides more help to more<br />
people than any other, and none is more efficient.<br />
Rather like John Menadue, it is modest and effective<br />
and like the airline he used to run, there's a bit of the<br />
spirit of Australia about it. That's certainly true of<br />
the Matthew Talbot.<br />
Because the Matthew Talbot has been around for a long<br />
time too. It's part of the Sydney legend. it was built<br />
during the Great Depression sixty years ago, when 8 third<br />
of Australia's workers were unemployed, and the idea that<br />
governments should provide a safety net for the victims<br />
of poverty was still pretty much just that an idea.<br />
These days It is much more of a reality. But in modern<br />
Australia where we have one of the better social welfare<br />
systems in the world, we continue to need organisations<br />
like the St Vincent de Paul Society and places like the<br />
Matthew Talbot Hostel for Homeless -Men.<br />
And while we would like to think that the day will come<br />
when we don't need these charities, life being what Is,<br />
and perfection being pretty well beyond us, the fact is<br />
we will always need them.<br />
And, in truth, when it comes to delivering the help that<br />
people need when they are on hard times, in many ways the<br />
charities do it better than the government and nobody<br />
does it better, of course, than the St Vincent do Paul<br />
Society. </p>
<p>T : PT . n. 9<br />
2<br />
The Matthew Talbot speaks for itself: every day and every<br />
night three hundred men sleep here, 2000 free meals are<br />
served, nursing and medical services are provided, and<br />
counselling along with acceptance, friendship, love and<br />
hope. The men here have come by different routes through<br />
family breakdowns, sickness, alcohol and drug dependence,<br />
unemployment but at Matthew Talbot they all get the<br />
same thing, which in a word is Cag Care and very often<br />
another chance.<br />
I know in her book about a family's experience of coping<br />
with schizophrenia, Anne Deveson pays special tribute to<br />
Matthew Talbot for the care and friendship given to her<br />
son, Jonathan.<br />
I am very nitdti aware that the demands on the society and<br />
on this hostel have been dramatically increased in the<br />
last couple of years as a result of the recession and now<br />
the intractably high levels of unemployment.<br />
I wish I could say that unemployment vias going to rapidly<br />
fall. But it is not going to and wishing will not make<br />
it go away.<br />
Just the same, there are things we can do and are doing<br />
to create jobs and train people, give the young work<br />
experience, and keep those who are older in touch with<br />
the labour market.<br />
We can do these things to give people a chance to reenter<br />
the workforce when the recovery gathers more pace<br />
and business looks for new people. And of course we will<br />
continue to fund the charities and our own welfare<br />
programs to help people through.<br />
There may be other things which can be done I am sure<br />
there are, and that's why we've established a high level<br />
committee to assess thoroughly our policies on<br />
unemployment and to come up with whatever solutions they<br />
can. Because of the long term personal and social damage it<br />
does, unemployment simply has to be our highest priority.<br />
I am well aware that while funding such places as this is<br />
essential, by far the best thing we can do is get our<br />
economy flourishing again and create jobs.<br />
And that, by the way is a message for the whole<br />
community. It's a message business might listen to. </p>
<p>TEL: 11 . Jun .93 11 : 29 No-. 064 P. 3/<br />
3<br />
If we are committed to the country and the people as well<br />
as to the company or corporation, maybe we could make<br />
some useful improvement by changing the set of our<br />
business minds and looking for ways to employ people<br />
rather than disemploy them. It is not really an<br />
altruistic suggestion to take on new blood now so that<br />
they will have skill and experience on their side when<br />
the economy begins to buzz again.<br />
I think these days, at every step in our economic life,<br />
the consequences for employment have to be considered.<br />
when companies make an investment decision, when they<br />
look at their operations, when banks decide whether or<br />
not to lend to companies wanting to begin or expand.<br />
We need business which is tough and competitive in a<br />
tough and competitive business culture. But that does<br />
not mean efther that business has no responsibility<br />
beyond the balance sheet, or that the operations of the<br />
human heart are inimical to success.<br />
And unions might be thinking along the same lines is<br />
their duty only to their members, or ts it also to the<br />
country and the people? And, therefore, is it really in<br />
their interests to deny work experience to young people,<br />
to close out the unemployed, to make them someone else's<br />
problem? That is something I believe we are learning in the<br />
nineties unemployment is never just someone else's<br />
problem. It's a problem for all of us.<br />
it's a national problem and the solution will have to be<br />
a national one. It will require a concerted effort.<br />
Rather like the effort which is made here.<br />
I don't make the comparison lightly this is a great<br />
cooperative enterprise between the Society and other<br />
groups, governments and individuals. The roots of it are<br />
in the vision, good will and compassion of the people of<br />
St Vincent de Paul and all the volunteers who work here.<br />
They are the roots and the government adds water and<br />
fertiliser. In this enterprise government plays a<br />
supporting role, rather than a leading one and it is all<br />
the more effective for that.<br />
We have provided $ 5.5 million towards these marvellous<br />
renovations but we did not provide the inspiration. The<br />
inspiration came from the people here. It was not the<br />
government which decided that the homeless men of Sydney<br />
deserved a re-built hostel, a safer, more efficient and<br />
friendly building, one so good that I'm told you could<br />
feel the lift in morale. It is rarely in the nature of<br />
governments to understand needs so well. </p>
<p>TEL: 11. Jun. 93 11: 29 No. 004 P. 04/ 05<br />
4<br />
Similarly, it was not the government which decided that<br />
this hostel for homeless men should not be a place for<br />
41warehousing" people, but one providing decent and<br />
dignified accommodation; that no one should be turned<br />
away; that the front entrance of the Matthew Talbot<br />
should cease to be a security gate and become a receptIon<br />
office those sorts of decisions can only be made by<br />
people who are passionate enough about their vocation to<br />
have a vision, and practised and knowledgeable enough to<br />
understand reality. I mean the sorts of people paid<br />
and unpaid who work here.<br />
Governments do not have the capacity to do these things<br />
so well. But they do have the capacity to recognise<br />
social need. They even have the ability to share the<br />
good will. And when they do that they spend their money<br />
wisely. So the Matthew Talbot does provide a model for the<br />
problems we now face it is proof, I think, that where<br />
the resolve exists, inspiration and cooperation will<br />
follow, and when we cooperate, when we work cohesively,<br />
when we think imaginatively, we can w6rk miracles like<br />
this. Old Matthew Talbot could not have imagined this piece.<br />
When it was founded sixty years ago no one could have<br />
imagined it. 5ut you will often find in the history of<br />
Australia when the collective will has existed the<br />
unimaginable has happened.<br />
And there is one more thing for us to learn from this<br />
place. It seems to me that the best measure the truest<br />
measure of our worth as a society and as a nation<br />
really is the degree to which we care for each other. I<br />
mean the fellow feeling among Australians and how much<br />
importance we attach to it.<br />
Not only Is that intangible thing a measure of a<br />
compassionate and just society, but of a strong societya<br />
society capable of solving its problems.<br />
We will. be stronger for Including everyone in the<br />
national equation, just as Matthew Talbot is stronger for<br />
turning no one away.<br />
And we will be better able to solve our problems if we<br />
face them unflinchingly, as Matthew Talbot does, and if<br />
we recognise that all of them economic, political and<br />
social are essentially h~ uman problems.<br />
And nothing speaks more eloquently of that than life at<br />
Matthew Talbot. All of us who might sometimes forget can<br />
come here and remember that when we get it wrong in those<br />
things we call the economy, or the family, or society, or<br />
the democracy, it falls out in the lives of ordinary<br />
people and the last place they fall is here. </p>
<p>TEL: 11. Jun. 93 11: 29 No. 004 P. 05/ 05<br />
4<br />
There is one more thing to learn from Matthew Talbot it<br />
is that problems can be solved. That despair can give<br />
way to hope. That ways can be found to re-build lives.<br />
And that we are all strengthened by our involvement in<br />
the process.<br />
Thank you for having me, and I mean alU of you the<br />
board, the staff, the volunteers and the men for the<br />
inspiration you give the rest of us.<br />
And for the rest of us it remains to give. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
