<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11485</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER            THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP            JOINT PRESS CONFERENCE WITH THE RT HON            HELEN CLARK            PRIME MINISTER OF NEW ZEALAND</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/03/2000</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE ..........................................................................................</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER HOWARD:</p>
<p> Well, ladies and gentlemen, I would like to welcome you</p>
<p> to this joint news conference. Can I say on behalf of the Australian Government</p>
<p> how delighted I am to have the new Prime Minister of New Zealand, Helen</p>
<p> Clark in Australia undertaking her first visit as Prime Minister of New</p>
<p> Zealand.</p>
<p>  It has been an opportunity for both of us to reaffirm the</p>
<p> importance the two governments attach to the relationship between our</p>
<p> two nations and our two societies. Australia and New Zealand have a long</p>
<p> history together and that history of course, and the momentum of the relationship</p>
<p> involved in that history of course, propels itself forward irrespective</p>
<p> of who is in power in either country. But it is also important in the</p>
<p> context of that that governments keep the relationship in good repair.</p>
<p> And just as I sought and obtained a very good basis of relationship in</p>
<p> working with the two former prime ministers of New Zealand with whom I</p>
<p> dealt, so it is with the new prime minister and I welcome her very warmly.</p>
<p> I thank her for the very direct and constructive nature of the discussions</p>
<p> that we've had today which have covered most areas of the bilateral</p>
<p> relationship.</p>
<p>  We'll be releasing a report to both of us from our</p>
<p> respective officials regarding progress made and rising out of the joint</p>
<p> prime ministerial taskforce established by Mrs Shipley and myself last</p>
<p> year. And I am also pleased to report that agreement's been reached,</p>
<p> an agreement relating to child support and that is to be signed shortly.</p>
<p>   We've also both accepted the recommendations of our</p>
<p> officials concerning the discussions on the social security arrangements</p>
<p> between the two countries and our discussions will be undertaken between</p>
<p> the respective ministers on both sides of the Tasman on that.</p>
<p>  I am also very happy to say that both of us will be in Gallipoli</p>
<p> on Anzac Day this year. And it is also expected, and I look forward to</p>
<p> the event that the New Zealand War Memorial in Australia will be unveiled</p>
<p> on the eve of Anzac Day in the year 2001, which of course is the Centenary</p>
<p> Year of Federation in Australia. And those two events are symbolic, but</p>
<p> nonetheless a very important symbol of our, a reminder of our shared history</p>
<p> and the determination in relation to those matters that the association</p>
<p> continue in a very open and very well developed way.</p>
<p>  But I really am very pleased to have had the discussions</p>
<p> and to take the opportunity so early in the term of the new New Zealand</p>
<p> Government to reaffirm the very strong commitment of the Australian Government</p>
<p> to the association.</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER CLARK:</p>
<p> Thank you. We have had a very warm welcome from John Howard.</p>
<p> This isn't the first time that we've met. I made the observation</p>
<p> to Mr Howard that when you're in opposition for nine years, a lot</p>
<p> of people treat you as though you're dead. That was not the case</p>
<p> with John Howard, I met him three times while I was Leader of the Opposition</p>
<p> in New Zealand and that's given a good basis for us to start our</p>
<p> work as prime ministers today.</p>
<p>  This is also probably the first of four times that we will</p>
<p> meet this year. Because there is not only Gallipoli coming up, which is</p>
<p> of great significance to both countries, but also the meetings of APEC</p>
<p> leaders in Brunei and then the Pacific Island Forum later in the year.</p>
<p> So there is going to be a lot of contact.</p>
<p>  We've had a good discussion that's ranged over</p>
<p> many issues that Mr Howard mentioned. I've briefed him on our current</p>
<p> defence planning intentions. We've talked about the terms of reference</p>
<p> for the review of issues arising out of Trans Tasman migration and the</p>
<p> social security issues there. We've had a brief discussion on matters</p>
<p> relating to civil aviation. Certainly the Anzac Memorial which we're</p>
<p> committed to following through on and we hope to be able to have a ceremony</p>
<p> around that in Canberra next year.</p>
<p>  So, over all, I think it's got off to a good start.</p>
<p> We're very pleased to see the child support payment arrangements</p>
<p> coming to finality. And hoping to be able to have the practical arrangements</p>
<p> underway around the middle of the year. In essence we want to run a no-surprises</p>
<p> policy with the Australian Government and I am sure that will be reciprocated.</p>
<p>  And on defence, can I say we support the ongoing very close</p>
<p> relationship the two countries have enjoyed for a century. Nothing has</p>
<p> changed about that. Whatever semantic arguments one might pick through</p>
<p> the media are we're committed to the high level of co-operation that</p>
<p> saw us work so well together in Timor and I am sure there will be other</p>
<p> opportunities for us to show in a practical way just how important that</p>
<p> is to us.</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p> Are you happy with the commitment from the New Zealand</p>
<p> ...[inaudible]...?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER HOWARD:</p>
<p> Well, the level of commitment of defence, for defence, is</p>
<p> a matter for the New Zealand Government. New Zealand is a sovereign, independent</p>
<p> country it makes its own decisions and we accept and respect those. Naturally</p>
<p> for a whole host of reasons we would like the strongest possible defence</p>
<p> commitment and provision from New Zealand. And like any other country</p>
<p> New Zealand recognises that there are strategic and operational consequences</p>
<p> attached to any particular decision on defence. I mean it is no secret</p>
<p> that Australia places a different and lower priority on the defence association</p>
<p> with the United States than New Zealand. Now that is a matter of open</p>
<p> record and understanding. That doesn't prevent of course the two</p>
<p> countries working together very closely as we did in Timor.</p>
<p>  I mean I've said on a number of occasions that the</p>
<p> most reassuring element in many respects of Australia's commitment</p>
<p> in East Timor was the ready and very strong support from New Zealand.</p>
<p> It was New Zealand's largest deployment overseas since World War</p>
<p> II, so, and Australia welcomed that. And the professional harmony between</p>
<p> the command and the men and women of the two forces was very much in evidence.</p>
<p> It was certainly related to me when I was in Timor and it has been relayed</p>
<p> since.</p>
<p>  But we have some different perspectives and we understand</p>
<p> the consequences of different provisions. I indicated to the Prime Minister</p>
<p> that it would be Australia's intention to increase defence expenditure</p>
<p> beginning from the year after next. The size, shape and disposition of</p>
<p> that increased expenditure is something that we're yet to determine.</p>
<p> We had a very lengthy discussion about defence matters in our National</p>
<p> Security Committee Cabinet on Monday along with our defence and strategic</p>
<p> advisers and it is an issue that is receiving quite a lot of attention</p>
<p> in Australia.</p>
<p>  But we have to be open and candid about these things. We</p>
<p> share a lot of, not only history, but we share a lot of interests in common.</p>
<p> But there are going to be points at which we put an emphasis differently</p>
<p> from New Zealand and New Zealand different from us. And it is far better</p>
<p> to recognise that from the very beginning and be candid about it and get</p>
<p> on with the association and I am encouraged by what the Prime Minister</p>
<p> has said both here and also earlier, and we understand each other perfectly</p>
<p> well.</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p> Prime Minister how will that expenditure be increased</p>
<p> and what particular areas would ...?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER HOWARD:</p>
<p> Well I've just said that we haven't decided</p>
<p> that. We have some ideas, but we've made it very clear that, I mean</p>
<p> I've said this before on a number of occasions, perhaps some haven't</p>
<p> heard it before but anyway I am saying it.</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p> And is that going to increase differences though between</p>
<p> Australia and New Zealand?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER HOWARD:</p>
<p> Well no I don't think. No, no look, I've just</p>
<p> said that we have a different, you know we have some differences of emphasis,</p>
<p> well on the American association obviously I mean that has a history to</p>
<p> it. And we respect the New Zealand position, we understand it. they respect</p>
<p> ours.</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p> Prime Minister Howard on the social security arrangements.</p>
<p> Did you have a concern basically that New Zealand was not contributing</p>
<p> enough?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER HOWARD:</p>
<p>All that happened today was that we agreed on the terms of reference</p>
<p> for a discussion. And there is a history to this like all of these things.</p>
<p> We're going to have a talk and we will see where we get.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What are your concerns?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER HOWARD:</p>
<p>I don't have any concerns beyond the desire to see the ministers</p>
<p> get together and see how they progress the discussion and the issue in</p>
<p> accordance with the terms of reference.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Does one of the terms of reference limiting trans-Tasman migration.[inaudible]...?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER HOWARD:</p>
<p>Look, we in Australia want an open welcoming association with our friends</p>
<p> in New Zealand. Obviously every country has a right to look to the net</p>
<p> sort of economic and other outcomes and New Zealand has views on that,</p>
<p> Australia has views on that, lets not get excited and create a difficulty</p>
<p> that doesn't exist, but we are going to look at..</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[inaudible] any consideration for limiting trans-Tasman...?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER HOWARD:</p>
<p>We would not want to behave in an arbitrary way in relation to that.</p>
<p> We like the current arrangement on a people to people basis. And its proper</p>
<p> and right and the expected thing in an association as old and as important</p>
<p> as our with New Zealand that there should be a freedom of movement that</p>
<p> perhaps doesn't exist between other societies, but there are economic</p>
<p> consequences of that. And we are going to examine it so I am not going</p>
<p> to get into the business of making any other declarations.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER CLARK:</p>
<p>Can I say we put a very high priority on the free labour market between</p>
<p> the two countries and I think that when you see the terms of reference,</p>
<p> you will see that they are very broad and enable us to look at a whole</p>
<p> range of issues and one of them I will put on the table is net economic</p>
<p> benefit because as I said several times in the last week, we know we are</p>
<p> losing a lot of our best and brightest to Australia, which is certainly</p>
<p> of considerable benefit in the growth and development of this country,</p>
<p> so we have to balance some of these things out. But there is no sense</p>
<p> of aggravation about this, simply a realisation that the way the social</p>
<p> security agreement worked in the past has probably run its course and</p>
<p> that lead the two governments to agree in the last couple of years that</p>
<p> they would move towards paying a flat global sum and get together to talk</p>
<p> about the longer term arrangements and that is exactly what we are doing.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard there are four hundred thousand New Zealanders living in this</p>
<p> country in the upper income stream. There's an argument in New Zealand</p>
<p> why should our Government pay your government anything given that they</p>
<p> are looking after themselves through the taxation system.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER HOWARD:</p>
<p>Well I'll leave it to the political figures in New Zealand to deal</p>
<p> with those arguments in New Zealand. Suffice it to say that we have terms</p>
<p> of reference that will enable all points of view to be considered, on</p>
<p> both sides of the Tasman. New Zealand economic arguments as well as Australian</p>
<p> economic arguments and I am quite certain that commonsense will prevail.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mrs Shipley...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER CLARK:</p>
<p>Excuse me?</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, with increased Australian Defence spending do you concede</p>
<p> that there will be a very large gap now between the capability even now</p>
<p> and in five to ten years time between New Zealand and in Australia and</p>
<p> given Professor Dibbs recent comments do you feel that New Zealand can</p>
<p> hold its own in the region and what would be the implications for the</p>
<p> New Zealand capability?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER CLARK:</p>
<p>I think New Zealand has to work out how it makes an effective contribution.</p>
<p> We also have to take in to account our capacity to pay. The defence planning</p>
<p> of the previous government last calculated its capital expenditure and</p>
<p> budgets on a US, New Zealand dollar rate of 69 cents. When I last looked</p>
<p> it was 48 and whether that has fallen again, given what I read about the</p>
<p> Australian dollar to which we so closely linked today, I don't know.</p>
<p> In essence we are trying to see that we have a coherent defence plan which</p>
<p> we can afford. There are only 3.8 million of us. We are used to having</p>
<p> a high degree of interoperability with Australia. Not just through the</p>
<p> bilateral relationship and exercises but also through very regular contact</p>
<p> in the five power defence agreement. We are going to keep our end up but</p>
<p> we will have to work out whether a small country can in the future try</p>
<p> to be quite as ambitious as we have been in the past on better exchange</p>
<p> rates and higher levels of prosperity.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What has been your response to Mr Howard's urging you to make the</p>
<p> maximum possible commitment to defence. Have you said anything to him</p>
<p> about not just maintaining defence spending but in future possibly increasing</p>
<p> it ...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER CLARK:</p>
<p>I wouldn't put words in Mr Howard's mouth as I think your question</p>
<p> did. We have a desire to work very closely on these issues. We will be</p>
<p> keeping each other informed about each other's defence reviews. New</p>
<p> Zealand wants to keep the high level of interoperability that it has had.</p>
<p> That means for us quite a lot more investment forthcoming in the New Zealand</p>
<p> army because we feel if there is one thing that has let us down a little</p>
<p> in our overseas deployments, whether we are talking Bosnia, Bouganville</p>
<p> or Timor, it is the antiquated nature of the New Zealand army's equipment</p>
<p> and that is right at the top of our priority list for significant expenditure.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What's the reason for your shift away from your predecessor's</p>
<p> commitment to being a single strategic entity [inaudible]?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER CLARK:</p>
<p>I have looked at quite a lot of the history of this in the last few days</p>
<p> and what I find is that that was a phrase that had some currency, although</p>
<p> heavily qualified, in the early 80's and then largely disappeared</p>
<p> from use, although it popped up in a communique between the New Zealand</p>
<p> and Australian defence ministers in 1998. Last year there was a very full</p>
<p> report from the Foreign Affairs and Defence Select committee of the New</p>
<p> Zealand parliament, which made the blunt statement that the two countries</p>
<p> were not a single strategic entity. For the reasons Mr Howard alluded</p>
<p> to, the Australians have a different relationship with the United States.</p>
<p> That leads them to project differently. Australians are a middle sized</p>
<p> power, we struggle to get into the small power category. Australia has</p>
<p> an Indian ocean border. We do not. We're more focused towards the</p>
<p> South Pacific than to the west of Australia, so all that will always make</p>
<p> for some distinction of view. But none of that detracts from the fact</p>
<p> that the two countries want to and always have worked very closely together</p>
<p> and will continue to do so.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do you believe that New Zealand Defence budget gives it any credible</p>
<p> defence capacity in South East Asia at all given for example the inability</p>
<p> to provide air support to your troops in New Zealand and secondly are</p>
<p> you giving an ironclad commitment that if you cancel the F-16s you will</p>
<p> spend that money on defence, that that won't lead to a saving in</p>
<p> the defence budget.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER CLARK:</p>
<p>We are not looking to cut the Defence budget. We are trying to stop it</p>
<p> spinning out of control, given the very sharp deterioration in the New</p>
<p> Zealand currency over the past couple of years. What we want is the defence</p>
<p> force that can make a credible contribution, we will want to make that</p>
<p> contribution. We have had considerable praise which is much appreciated</p>
<p> from Australia on the contribution in Timor. But in all honestly, we feel</p>
<p> it could have been better if our army had been better equipped. So that's</p>
<p> where we are looking to improve our performance.</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p> Do either of you believe in the notion of a common currency?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER HOWARD:</p>
<p> No but I'll answer that by saying that it's</p>
<p> not been undertaken in any of the discussions I've had with New Zealand</p>
<p> prime ministers. It didn't occur to me in the lead up to this discussion.</p>
<p> I don't think it is going to occur to me tomorrow or next year.</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p> Have you got any . . .</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER CLARK:</p>
<p> I feel the same.</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER HOWARD:</p>
<p> Okay, thanks a lot. Thank you.</p>
<p>  [ends]</p>
<p>  Report</p>
<p> to the Prime Minister on Australia-New Zealand Bilateral Economic Relations</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
