<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3008</transcript-id>
    <title>AUSTRALIAN COUNCIL FOR THE ARTS - GOVERNMENT GRANT FOR WORLD DESIGN CONGRESS, JAPAN</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/09/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003008.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
E1MBARGO: 10.00 P. M.<br />
_ AUSI RAI A A,<br />
PRIME MINISTER PRESS STATEMENT NO. 130<br />
14 September 1973<br />
AUSTRALIAN COUNCIL FOR THE ARTS GOVERNMZENT GRANT FOR WORLD<br />
DESIGNJ CONGRESS, JAPAN<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr. W-. hitlam, today announced an<br />
Australian Government grant of $ 25,000 to assist 45 designers,<br />
teachers and students from all Australian States to attend the<br />
Eighth World Design Congress to be held next month in Kyoto,<br />
Japan. The grant was recommended to the Prime Minister by the<br />
Visual Arts Board of the Australian Council for the Arts in<br />
consultation with the Industrial Design Council of Australia.<br />
The Congress has generated such wide interest among designers<br />
that a party of 64 Australians will now participate.<br />
Sponsored by the International Council of Societies<br />
of Industrial Design, the Congress is held every second year<br />
and is being held for the first time in the Asian/ Pacific area.<br />
Those travelling with the aid of the subsidy represent<br />
a diverse range of interests. The group includes practising<br />
designers and design teachers from many fields, architects, a<br />
ceramist, and students in mechanical engineeripng, sculpture<br />
and painting as well as industrial design.<br />
. The Visual Arts Board, in recommending the grant, said<br />
that Australia has so far lacked a tradition of good local design<br />
in its industrial products. Although there have been talented<br />
individuals, they have not had sufficient support by way of<br />
professional training and steady demand for their work.<br />
Australian manufacturers have always leaned heavily on foreign<br />
design for their products.<br />
The Board believes that Australians are now taking more pride<br />
in what we can produce, and our international markets are<br />
demanding a high standard of design. Both f" or our own sake<br />
and for the sake of our export trade, we need excellence of<br />
design to become the rule rather than the exception. </p>
<p>-3-<br />
In administering the $ 25,000 grant, the Industrial-<br />
Design Council has made a particular effort to encourage student<br />
participation in the congress, and students comprise about half<br />
the number of people who have received travel subsidies.<br />
Australian participation in this biennial design<br />
congress has previously been limited almost entirely to one<br />
or two official delegates. " This year, for the first time,<br />
this country will participate in strength, representing about<br />
per cent of the anticipated attendance of 600 overseas<br />
visitors from 35 countries. Some 1500 Japanese designers will<br />
bring the number attending the congress to around 2,000.<br />
The World Design Congress provides a unique opportunity<br />
for the kind of international contact, discussion and exchange<br />
of ideas which are so vital to the development of designers<br />
individually and to the development of attitudes which will lead<br />
to the design of products with qualities more closely related to<br />
the everyday needs of people.<br />
CANBERRA, A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
