<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5159</transcript-id>
    <title>DEFENCE FORCE ASSISTANCE TO NEW SOUTH WALES AND SOUTH ASUTRALIA IN COMBATTING PLAGUE LOCUSTS</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/10/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005159.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER.<br />
FOR MEDIA 4 OCTOBER 1979<br />
Defence Force Assistance to New South Wales and<br />
South Australia in combatting Plague Locusts<br />
The Prime Minister, the Rt. Hon. Malcolm Fraser, today<br />
announced that the Commonwealth would be providing Defence<br />
Force assistance to the New South Wales and South Australian<br />
Governments in combatting the current plague locust infestation<br />
in both States.<br />
Mr Fraser said that on the basis of expert advice, three<br />
helicopters and their crews would be made immediately available<br />
for search and destroy missions against the locusts in<br />
New South Wales.<br />
Mr Fraser also said that the South Australian Government would<br />
be assisted by the immediate provision of a communications<br />
system comprising two mobile base units each with ten<br />
back-pack radios, two teams each with ten land rovers, a<br />
communications helicopter and the necessary command and<br />
support systems.<br />
The Prime Minister said that the Commonwealth was most concerned<br />
over the magnitude of the current infestation. He also said that<br />
assistance was being provided at the direct request of the<br />
Premiers of both States and was in addition to the assistance<br />
being given by the Commonwealth through the control activities<br />
of the Australian Plague Locust Commission. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
