<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7111</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW OF PRIME MINISTER ON RAY MARTIN MID DAY SHOW - FRIDAY 13 FEBRUARY 1987</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/02/1987</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007111.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
E O-B-POOF ONLYTRAN<br />
kCITP1' O1_ iN1' I( V IEW1_ UF P. FME1 rT$~ ROJR'MATN<br />
DAY SHOW TUIDAY 13 FESL3R1Y 1987-<br />
RM: The Prime minister 1s with us today so please make<br />
him welcome. Mr Bob Hawke. Welcoine Mr Hawke arid thidnk<br />
you for your time.<br />
PM: Alwasxy a pleasurc to be with you.<br />
R~ M. I hope~ you a~ nd Mazel had nilirsta.-<br />
PM: A beaut Christdmas. thank you.<br />
RM: A couple of questions to start. A couple of tough<br />
ones. H-ow is your golf going? And we going to have an<br />
early election?<br />
PMV: They are both easy. 17 is What they have got me on<br />
ntow which is a bit tough I think;'<br />
RM: That.-you gLqf g~ jmv4,,. but arc we going to have an<br />
early election?<br />
F'M: No. I stick to what I s. aid deapite of all the<br />
temntapt ions they Are putt ing In front Qf me, The parliament<br />
will 80 its full terin and the election will be either the cnd<br />
of this year or early in 1988.<br />
RM: So no prospect if the Sxinate knocks the Aust c -a rd<br />
asecond time with in doublc dissoiluLcv. n<br />
PM: I just hope that thia Senate. won't do that. It is<br />
a v. simple thlng.. thc only people in Aust. who stand to benefit<br />
by a refusal by the Libs and the Democrats and the Nationalti<br />
to pass that legislation arc-2 set5 of people--Ta-x-Cheats<br />
on the one hand and the welfare bludgers on the otherL. They<br />
are the only people who stand to gain by that Legiblation being<br />
knocked back. I hope good SenISe Will jirevail.<br />
RM: If they dca knnrir hArk though...<br />
PM: I don't anawer htypothetical quc., tionr,. But my commitment<br />
really. . what I want to sec happcn is, to see this Parliameunt<br />
goit&amp;; rull Lein. I thinak most Australins would agree. with<br />
me that really our parliamentary terms are too short. 3 years </p>
<p>PM: just about the n5hort est in the world. And I think<br />
they would l ike to see longer aind mrce staible. That is what<br />
we arc t ryirig io du PuVIV idc a btatll t; vvt: 1 1111-It II CVl i<br />
all this flofl$ CflS to the others.<br />
ElM: Al right. Wha t abou t thisb nion benube. EvCunIybody else<br />
ha s had their . opinion. WhatL is* Joh up t o? What do you think<br />
he is tip to?<br />
PM: Well it maty conhC as no suprisc, but Joh does not confide<br />
in me so I have just go to specul&amp; te but sceriously, I<br />
think that-Joh ' allowed h-Imself to be._.. lkedmt U a posit iol<br />
by this group of v. wealth backers that he has. And Idntknock<br />
them because they-are wealthy but thats the group. of batckerb.<br />
Thttey tii-n--t--t--. joh--ouleJieepuLv tq their sort of position.<br />
And I think they persuaded him that they had financial resources<br />
_ t-o push him perhaps__ right to the Lodge. And lie hais Luiken that<br />
ba it and Tiilriottjh sp-hme-fI-to--ps-t--nwhxe__<br />
his own-crecdibility__ would b~ e absolutecly--zflch if he doe * sn t-<br />
-go -ahead now and come to tFdrIalien. utmy -judg-enien-t-<br />
! s that if he comes to the Fed. Parlilament hie couldn't evcn gct<br />
the leadership of the National Party, let alone anything else.<br />
RM: Are you still praying that hie will still come?<br />
PM: Yes, I would v. much like him in t. here. As I put it t o<br />
-you he would such at cohiesive force in conservative force in<br />
C Anbe r r a.<br />
RM: Let me play you what Joh said on Tuesday when I asked<br />
-him if he could beat-you ont hi -s __ own wtt-a-Joh Party. or. if i-t<br />
would have to be a coalition effort -both the Nationals arid-the<br />
Liberals. Here is what he said<br />
" Quite simply yes I can, he can, he con. With ihe Nutional P a rt y<br />
behind me and supported the policies 1 had we could do it ourselve<br />
without any problem at all. because the Austral [ an people are fed<br />
up to here, with everything that the Labor Party are doing. They<br />
are claimed to run a nation on a cracked foundation.... . you wouldn't<br />
build a house on a foundation that. they hiave got of 20 odd<br />
different UL-SUxLiSdtiUllb... the CoMnUuliuiSitS, the Socialists, the<br />
iriernational Socialists, the Majority Group, the Right Wingers,<br />
the Left, the old guiard, tle tlew gu&amp; ud you mention it the stack<br />
of them... How could you run a8government that way? I told then)<br />
that at the first Summit that Hawke had"<br />
RM: Quick rcaction?<br />
PM: Well if you want to talk about factions and grou~ ps -its<br />
the conservative poitics that you have to look at -you just<br />
can't keel) up with the numbers of groups there. I ans just going<br />
oni with the busli-ess which I know this audience and Australia<br />
wants me to do. It is to providc solid, cautious govcrnmcnt.<br />
That is what we arc doing and wc a rc doing it with a v. considerable<br />
degree of support<br />
RM: But Joh has proved in the past. Mr Hawke that it is foolish,<br />
dan~ el-oufs to dismiss him. </p>
<p>PM: There is one thing that you have got to remember Australia<br />
is niot Queensland when it comes to the fairness of electoral<br />
laws. Joh cannot get elected PM of Australia with 38% or-the vote<br />
or 40% of the vote.<br />
RM: But recent polls has shown that he has got more than that.<br />
The polls would indicate that there arc an awful lot of or-diriary<br />
Australians who a) respect him and b) like him.<br />
PM: I srn not here to k ' nock oh. it -s -not-pa -or my. Iii;<br />
hi storicHl ly in pol it ics tio get in to the person. It the pier-son<br />
says something that is wrong I will go as toughly a~ s L ca. BuLt<br />
I haven't got a record of1 attack on the PeUS0ri. 1 am not here<br />
to attack ] of;.<br />
_ PM: us mktepont that th-e-poAIls-don_' trslooW1. &amp; ffi overf-7i--<br />
whelmiiag support L or J oh. They simply don't . Yoiu just have<br />
a look at the polls.<br />
RM: 70 odd perccnt it was the other day?<br />
PM. You arc not serious about telephone polls, are we? I<br />
mean I would've thought that a hellava lot of people who rung<br />
in in support of J olf, I f they had any-sense-whould have been-Labor.<br />
supporters because they would really want to see'the push for<br />
Joh to CAnberra. I mean can you think of aniything better, from<br />
our point of view. thars him coinrg. Ian Sinclair. was horriftied.-<br />
He eeti his job on the line and John Howard Is a bit like<br />
that, so why wouldn't we want to see him there?<br />
RM: When is Andrew Peacock goin8 to maake hiS o1Ve Onf John<br />
Howard?<br />
P'M: Well ag~ ain, Andrew docbui't r-ing me up every day but Anidrew<br />
is poised to pounce. I think he conduced himself v. stupidly<br />
in the last fortnight and I say that to my friend Andrew. Things<br />
WCU-C going V. Well for you and you should've rshut up But he<br />
ha~ d to come out and say Sir Joh was the greatest thing since sliced<br />
Ure~ d Now a l ot of peopl e in the Li beral gun have had J oh ' s<br />
guni right at their head Joh was going to knock, them them and<br />
them off those people were Peacock supporters. Then Andrew comes<br />
out anrd siays Joh is the greatest thing ever. I think that some<br />
of those JIberol supporters of Andrew weren't terribly impressed.<br />
However, hie made a tactical blunder there anid he has a \ pt Of<br />
support in the Lib. Par-ty. Johun hats v. little. There Is not a<br />
marjority there who thinks tie can win and so Andrew Is just<br />
waiting. What will happen I just don't know. As I Say I am<br />
just getting on with the business of running government. Leave<br />
all that to them.<br />
RM: I had a telephone call1 a few minutes ago from hir H1oward...<br />
PM. You mean he had the temerity to ring you up anid ask you<br />
something? Shocking </p>
<p>RM: lie says he is looking forward to comning ort this show<br />
on Moniday atid tic noticed that you were on and he said there is<br />
a que5tion for you. This is MLr Iluward.. s question<br />
PM: He doesn't ask me mnany in Parliament so 1 might as well<br />
get one thi s way.<br />
RM: He says that he~ read in the papers this mornintg that YOU<br />
Are going to reshuffle your cabinet. He says " Given that Mr<br />
Keat ing is so unpopular around the country for not having put his<br />
tax returns ini anid other things, are you thinking of shifting Mr<br />
Keating cis Treasure, arnd 1.1 so plea# 3e don<br />
PM: Ah, he is di splaying sornefhting C~~ Th ~ cTa~<br />
a sense of humou r. Let me say__ 2_ thIngs john, I hope you are<br />
wa telli fig Firstly, don't get deluded about Mr Keating s<br />
urILpQpularity you John made a decisTon to fight the 8ak-s-r o<br />
by-election on " Give Keating a -Bea-ting 9-and in ' What were<br />
i-t-rp-it--e-wo-utsa---c~ f i-I r-tin -tey~ eLe~ ti Dn<br />
ht31j%' 2-party pr-cf'crr-ed -swing-agaIn-st--abor was-t-he-t-hi-rd<br />
t-ow-estswtng-i-n--a: -by -ci1 ect i-on -in-th-s -S1t--e--f-or'--y-ear.-S Zdon<br />
' t get carried -away wi th that. And secon~ dly-let ths<br />
-Paul Keating okay he has made some mistakes which as a man he<br />
has openly conceded to and expresued his regrets. Good on him.<br />
I don't, condone thc mistakes neither does he. Test him as<br />
a Treasurer. The best Treasurer irt tbe history of this country.<br />
iRM: Thank you for that. We-we will comte back with youLr<br />
que t l ons in a-one'. sinen t </p>
<p>MARTIN: It's now your chance to ask some questions. Let's start<br />
with the blokes down the front in the ties, the farmers.<br />
QUESTION: My question to the Prime Minister is last time I spoke<br />
with him in Moree he walked away from me, mainly because he<br />
didn't have time to answer the question. The question I pose to<br />
the Prime Minister today is when are we going to have interest<br />
rates reduced so everybody can have an even standard of living<br />
throughout Australia? And when canh-Australians expect -the<br />
Government taxes on all our fuels reduced by 50 per cent, so we<br />
all go away for the weekend and have a'good time?"<br />
PM: Well I wish economics were as easy as your questions imply.<br />
Letme . make the first point, there is no politician, in his right<br />
mind, who likes high interest rates. You don't have interest<br />
rates any higher than_ are necessary._ You'd be certifiable if youdid.<br />
The simple fact is -that if we precipitatively and too early<br />
reduced interest rates what would happen is that you'd loose the<br />
exchange rate, you'd absolutely loose the exchange rate, and then<br />
interest rates would spiral in a way over which you had no<br />
control. That's the first point. Interest rates will come down<br />
in this country as soon as we are responsibly able to bring them<br />
down. I want them down just as much as you do. It's not only<br />
farmers, everyone in this community wants them as low as<br />
possible. That's the first point. -The second one, about-the<br />
reduction of taxes, I'm not in the business of John Howard and<br />
Joh Bjelke-Petersen of making irresponsible promises about tax.<br />
John Howard and his mob were in government for seven and a half<br />
years and he walked out of office leaving-a top-marginal rate of<br />
cents in the dollar. In four years, by the middle of this<br />
year, four years from 1983, we will have reduced that top rate<br />
from 60 to 49. We will have brought in the fairest tax system<br />
that this country has seen. Ours is not rhetoric. We will get<br />
taxes down in a way which is responsible, and which is going to<br />
keep economic growth going, and keep inflation under control and<br />
not have it blowing through the roof in the way it was done<br />
before. Let's just look twice at what our opponents did in the<br />
area of tax. In 1977 we went to an election. Remember the<br />
fistful of dollars they gave you for the big tax cuts. The<br />
people trusted them, put them back in and within three months of<br />
them being elected they grabbed it all back. Then in 1982 what<br />
did they do then? They gave you tax cuts which blew the deficit<br />
out to $ 9.5 billion in 1983, which we had to deal with. You get<br />
tax cuts from us, you get real ones which you keep.<br />
QUESTION: I'm John Williams. Your government has. adopted a<br />
policy of high inflation rates to support a sinking Australian<br />
dollar and to slow the economy. If you look at the BAE<br />
statistics last year 1985/ 86 32 per cent of men on the land had a<br />
negative income. I've got it right there if you don't believe<br />
me. The fact is that interest rates are our biggest cost. We<br />
compete on world markets. We've got to clean up the rest for the<br />
grab of the world market. Yet our costs here at home in<br />
Australia, our interest rates, our fuel costs are-just leaving us<br />
uncompetitive. MARTIN:_ Haven't we just answered that question? </p>
<p>PM: I'm very glad in your question John you quoted the BAE,<br />
because that means you believe the BAE figures.<br />
QUESTION: I believe<br />
PM: You're quoting them, do you believe them or don't you?<br />
QUESTION: I believe the figures, the history figures, but not<br />
the ones they've forecast.<br />
S I see. I don't want to worry about forecasts, we'll<br />
their actuia statistics, so I'm glIad you rely on them. The BAE<br />
statistics show that under this government the increase in farm<br />
_ 0tcos shaveb een-mo-rethan-haLved-f-Lom-thterat-eu ndetr__ t hep. rev-_ Lo-us____-<br />
government. Now that is the BAE statistics, the source that you<br />
quote.. -W. ith-respect-to -qui-te1_ silly, I-don--t-w. ant. to-..<br />
be rude, but it is quite silly to say that we've deliberately.<br />
increased inflation to slow down the economy. What are the<br />
facts? When we came to office what was the rate of inflation?<br />
11.2 per cent, that was the rate of inflation that we inherited.<br />
By the beginning of 1985 we'd more than halved that. We'd got it<br />
down to 5 per cent. The increase that has taken place since then<br />
is absolutely the result of the turnaround in the terms of trade<br />
and the devaluation that has gone with it. But even with that<br />
the rate of inflation hasn't gone-back up to that Il-. 2-per cent<br />
of our predecessors. So your facts are wrong and your own source<br />
shows that we've more than halved the rate of farm costs. Those<br />
. are the facts. As to the future let me_ saythis, and even the<br />
National Farmers Federation, which give us a bit of a tickle up<br />
now and again, have been good enough to say no government could<br />
have done more than we have done in tackling what is your real<br />
problem. And that is the fact that you people, who are the most<br />
efficient farmers in the world, are being kicked to death by the<br />
corruption of international trade which is being practised by the<br />
Europeans and the Americans and the Japanese. That's what is<br />
kicking you to death. And no one could have done more than I and<br />
Kerin and Dawkins have done to try and start to get good sense<br />
into the international trading system. So we will continue what<br />
we've done, to halve the rate of increase in farm cost, that were<br />
inflicted upon you by people who kept the exchange rate too high.<br />
That was the National Party and the Libs, they kept the exchange<br />
rate too high. We've brought it down, so you've benefited from<br />
that and we'll continue to fight as hard as we can for you,<br />
whether it is in Brussels, Geneva, Washington to do the thing<br />
that is really going to do something to give you the returns that<br />
your efforts justify.<br />
MARTIN: Let's change it for a moment. Let's go with the two<br />
schoolgirls from Bankstown.<br />
QUESTION: Mr Hawke, my name is Julie Dean, I'm from Blacktown<br />
Girls High. Recently you spent a lot of money on the drug<br />
offensive, how effective do you think that was?<br />
PM: Well we haven't finished spending it. It is a program which<br />
was not just the Commonwealth Government, and I give tribute to<br />
all the State Premiers, including our political opponents. They<br />
came, at my request, to Canberra and it is a combined </p>
<p>Commonwealth and State drug offensive campaign. And the major<br />
emphasis that we're trying to give Julie, is in the education<br />
area. What I can say is that my own impression, and it is<br />
confirmed by what is being put to me by people who are constantly<br />
in the area, that with young people there has been, it seems, a<br />
significant decline in the tendency that there was on their part<br />
just to easily say yes to drugs. There is a greater tendency on<br />
young people now to say no. We can't justrely on that and say_-<br />
well it's worked. we're going to continue that education<br />
program. May I take this opportunity, if you don't mind, in<br />
terms of talking about education program, I want to give enormous<br />
credit to the Reverend Ted-Kn-of-f--of--th-e Wayside Chapel--and-is<br />
life education centres. I've just gone in and witnessed that and<br />
no-one__ is. s-doing-a-more. effec-tivej o b-ing elti. ngt oouryo-u ng<br />
-people and teaching them about the-deadly danger of-hard drugs.<br />
It's with programs like that, assisted byCommbnwealth and-state-lfunding,<br />
we'll keep up this fight.<br />
MARTIN: Mr Hawke, can I quickly ask you on that point of Ted<br />
Knoffs and what Julie's asked? I've found, in the Christmas<br />
break as well, ordinary Australians appear to me to be more<br />
concerned, with children of Julie's age, more concerned not<br />
whether they're going to get a job, not whether someone's going<br />
to drop the nuclear bomb, but whether or not they're going to get<br />
-hit by hard drugs. Do you read -that-as well?<br />
PM: In all the correspondence I've had and in all the research<br />
that we've done, certainly the question of hard drugs loomed as<br />
one right up there as one of the major problems. It would be<br />
absurd for us, as Australians, I'm not talking about a<br />
government, it would be absurd for us to say that we're going to<br />
eliminate the problem. And it would be absurd, given our<br />
enormous coastline, to say that we're ever going to be able to<br />
totally stop hard drugs getting into this country. We've<br />
increased resources, we'll increase penalties in the states and<br />
so on. The real thing is to stop the demand and that is why<br />
education is so important. I believe that with the sort of<br />
things that people like Ted Knoffs, in particular, are doing, and<br />
with our support, that gradually there is going to become an<br />
awareness amongst our young people that it is an insanity to<br />
endanger your life, or indeed to debilitate yourself to the point<br />
of uselessness by using hard drugs. We haven't won the fight<br />
yet, but I think the signs are there that as a community, I'm not<br />
talking about he government, together we're going to win it.<br />
QUESTION: My name is Karen. I'd like to talk about the student<br />
fees of $ 250. Can you tell me to what purpose are these fees.<br />
And do you see in future the fees will be increased to make<br />
higher education something just for the upper classes?<br />
PM: Let me make these points, a very important question.<br />
Firstly, they are not student fees. They are administration<br />
charges and they don't cover the whole of the administration<br />
charges. The calculation is that the full cost per annum of<br />
someone going through university is about $ 8,500. That's the<br />
cost, so it is not a fee. It just meets some of the<br />
administration-charges. Secondly, we-have,-in introducing that<br />
administration charge, provided that those who are in receipt of </p>
<p>TEAS, that is the most needy relatively, will not pay the charge.<br />
The talk about the question of ensuring that those who are most<br />
in need will be helped and not those who don't need it. The fact<br />
is that under the previous situation the wealthiest in the<br />
community were paying no contribution in any way to the cost of<br />
university education directly. Now the $ 250, structured as it<br />
is, to take it off those with-the lowest income is providing a<br />
Sway in which the more affluent are making some contribution. The<br />
final part of your question, o I see any way in which this will<br />
be increased? The only way in which you're going to get<br />
university fees, as the present political partiesare stating<br />
their position, is under the Liberals who are-s ayg -they will<br />
introduce university fees. If that were done in the way they'ddo<br />
it, without any way of looking after the needy, that would<br />
ensure that university-education did-become the-preser. ve.-of. the..<br />
most affluent..--Whatwe.' v_ e_ got_ to _ do-_ i. n._ thi. s country, and it's my_<br />
goal and always has been, to try and create a situation-where<br />
there is true equality of opportunity. It doesn't matter if a<br />
kid is Bob Hawke's kid, or a multi millionaire's kid, or a kid<br />
from the poorest circumstance, if that kid has got the intrinsic<br />
ability to go on and be trained in a tertiary institution, that<br />
training should be there. That's why we in government have<br />
provided an additional 37,000 places in the universities, to<br />
create more opportunities. We should put the issue of the<br />
-education of our kids-beyond-and-above-politics, because that is<br />
our greatest asset and that's what we're^ trying to do-.<br />
QUESTION: My name is Tim, may I call you Bob?<br />
PM: Yes Tim.<br />
QUESTION: The ludicrous work practices on the wharves are the<br />
thing that worries me. People are waiting to get their stuff and<br />
there's strikes and practices like if five guys are working<br />
together and one goes to the toilet the other four will stop<br />
until he comes back. Stuff like that. What do you think should<br />
be done? What are you doing about that sort of stuff?<br />
PM: Let me just make these points quickly. In terms of<br />
industrial stoppages, which are really the things that do cause<br />
the most problem, I'm proud of the fact that under my government<br />
the rate of industrial disputes in this country has been more<br />
than halved than what was the level in the seven and a half years<br />
of the Fraser government. We've more than halved the level of<br />
industrial disputes. But I'm not resting on that record. I've<br />
convened a meeting last year and I give credit to the employer<br />
organisations of this country and to the ACTU. They responded,<br />
they came to me. I said look, the sort of thing you're talking<br />
about, practices that grew up in easier days, some of them<br />
initiated by employers to get labour, others initiated by unions,<br />
I said we can't accept that those practices are any longer<br />
justified. Will you join with us in examining these and see if<br />
we can get rid of those that are not necessary. They said yes.<br />
So what is happening now is that at enterprise and industry<br />
levels discussions are going on between employers and trade<br />
unions to try and work out a way in which not only work<br />
practices, but some management practices which can't be<br />
justified, should be eliminated. Because what we've simply got<br />
I </p>
<p>to recognise in this country is that for 30 years or so after the<br />
war, due in large part to the efficiency of our farmers and then<br />
of our mineral operations, we just got enormously high incomes<br />
because people were paying the prices for those things. They're<br />
not now and they're not going to pay the same sort of prices. So<br />
if we're going to prosper as a country, if our kids are going to<br />
have the opportunity of enjoying improving living standards, then<br />
we've got to be competitive in a whole range of other areas. And<br />
we won't be competiftive if we have-restficti-ve work-pracfices-and---<br />
restrictive management practices.<br />
QUESTTONTM-.--M--H-awk-e I was just wondering, I was going to a<br />
rehabilitation centre for a car accident that I had and that<br />
_ cen-tre isbe-in-gclo. s-edd. o-wn Itlsone-o-f_-temna jQrrehabilitation<br />
centres in Sydney. That and its-sister.<br />
rehabilitation centrehave-been closed down and I was_ jus t<br />
wondering with tax cuts and that, can-we expect more-closures of<br />
centres such as this?<br />
PM: What has happened there is that there's a program being<br />
undertaken where we're rationalising the operations between<br />
states and the Commonwealth. It's not on our part a cutting down<br />
of rehabilitation services. We're handing more responsibility<br />
over to the states. There's not going to be a net reduction in<br />
the provision of rehabilitation services but a rationalisation ofactivities<br />
so that you don't get a duplication between the<br />
Commonwealth and the states. And you'll find as this is worked<br />
out, not only in this state and other states, there'll be no<br />
reduction in total in the services provided.<br />
QUESTION: I come from a small country town, population 500,<br />
called the greatest little town in the west. Mr Hawke, have you<br />
got a word of encouragement for country people? Our town is<br />
dying. We're losing our railway line. We're threatened with<br />
closure of our hospital. Small country towns and close-knit<br />
communities such as ours are dying.<br />
PM: Well one of the problems, I've alluded to it a bit in the<br />
answers in regard to what the farmers were saying about their<br />
situation, is that we've lost an enormous amount of income as a<br />
result of the fact that the world is paying very much less for<br />
the products that we produce. I don't want to bore you with<br />
statistics but the fact is in the last 18 month period we had $ 6<br />
billion wiped off our national income. That was because the rest<br />
of the world was paying less for our wheat, our dairy products,<br />
our meat and so on. They just paid less. There was $ 6 billion<br />
gone. Now if $ 6 billion is taken out of the economy that means<br />
there is less demand. The farmers haven't got the money to buy<br />
the machinery and buy other things that they were doing. So some<br />
of these things are going to happen unfortunately, until, as I<br />
said, we can get sense into the international.. trading. community.<br />
You've got the absurdity, this is why I went over to Davos to<br />
tell world leaders there, you've got the absurdity that the<br />
Europeans and the Americans are paying billions of dollars for<br />
uneconomic production. They're just building up these great<br />
surpluses, paying people to produce and then they dump them on<br />
the markets-where our people were previously competitively and<br />
efficiently selling. What we're trying to do is get sense back. </p>
<p>If we can start to do that and get a more prosperous and<br />
profitable rural community then the sorts of things that you're<br />
talking about won't happen to the extent that properly concerns<br />
you now.<br />
QUESTION: Mr Hawke, I'm just interested with the big takeovers<br />
that are going on, worldwide. Does that affect our balance of<br />
payments. Is it detrimental to the country, or is it any good to<br />
the country?<br />
PM: No. We're appearing in a studio that has been taken over by<br />
Mr Bond. The---f ftakeovers su n as det r imfenftal.<br />
The whole theory of competitive enterprise is that if a<br />
.&amp; parzticular. enterpriseis _ operating__ i. n_ a Ka_ ywhere others think<br />
they can do it better and operate it more efficiently, then<br />
that's-what hapi s. J -l'd-cif! tlNd-ve--i-i-b t--ioit ta~ eo. r<br />
such. We've watched the-situation.-If we thought there was<br />
going to be some competitive disadvantage created for this<br />
country then we'd have to consider taking action. But I think<br />
what Australians want to see, generally speaking, they want to<br />
see a free enterprise market where the initiative of individuals<br />
is available to be used. Where competition can take place and if<br />
someone can do something they think better than another, let them<br />
do it. We've examined the financial implications as to whether<br />
in terms of our external balances there is any adverse impact and<br />
all the best analysis that can be done by our treasury and<br />
independent officials suggest that there is no adverse impact<br />
upon our external position. I can assure the two things we're<br />
concerned about is trying to see this economy operate as<br />
efficiently as it can and to see that doesn't happen in a way<br />
which is going to impose external problems for us.<br />
MARTIN: We are out of time. In a word though Mr Hawke, is 1987<br />
going to be rougher and tougher? Are we going to have to tighten<br />
our belts more than last year?<br />
PM: 1987 is going to be a better year. It is certainly going to<br />
be a better year than 1986. We're not going to have $ 6 billion<br />
knocked off our income.<br />
MARTIN: Did you hear that sigh of relief then?<br />
PM: Well sure. I can understand it. If I were a farmer, I can<br />
understand their feelings completely.<br />
FARMER: ( inaudible)<br />
PM: You can say that but you're wrong.<br />
FARMER: Come to Moree again Mr Prime Minister.<br />
PM: Alright I'll come. The situation is what do you feel like<br />
if you go andsow your fields and you get a crop and you just have<br />
the prices going down.<br />
MARTIN: But it is more than farmers isn't it? It's ordinary<br />
people too. </p>
<p>PM: But it is farmers to a very large extent. Farmers and our<br />
mineral products. What people tend to say is the farmers are<br />
suffering poor bloody farmers, if you'll excuse the French.<br />
But when the farmers are suffering the whole Australia suffers.<br />
So what I'm saying is that on all the evidence 1987 will<br />
certainly be a better economic year than 1986. We're not going<br />
to have the same degree of problems, but we're still, as a<br />
community, going to have to adjust to the fact that we've had<br />
that loss of income and make the sort of tough-decisions that are<br />
necessary. We won't get out of problems by pie in the sky<br />
nonsenses about 25 per cent flat tax rates. It is nonsense and<br />
the people who are sayingt k-now-thEt-if's nonsense. 1-well--make<br />
the decisions that are right.<br />
ends I<br />
~ I </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
