<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>19120</transcript-id>
    <title>Transcript of Interview with Mark Simkin, ABC News</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/03/2013</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PM: When I've come in the past it might have been for one hour, one meeting, one engagement, a half day, a full day.</p>
<p>I've got the opportunity to spend a few days here, and so I'm doing that.</p>
<p>I've had some great experiences today.</p>
<p>I've certainly met some local disability services providers working with Australians with disabilities who are just doing the most magnificent job, and who are anxiously awaiting the start of the National Disability Insurance Scheme, which happens in just 17 weeks' time.</p>
<p>REPORTER: Well, traffic congestion was on your mind today. With already the State Government scoffed at your proposal, and you didn't put an actual specific dollar figure on the table.</p>
<p>Are you just picking a fight with Barry O'Farrell or playing catch-up politics, as Tony Abbott suggests?</p>
<p>PM: As a responsible Government, if we are going to put big money into a roads project, then we want it to be properly planned and we want it to do the things that need to be done. We have given $25 million to the O'Farrell Government for planning.</p>
<p>Now, until you see the full plan and really understand what is happening with this project, then it would be reckless to do a funding commitment.</p>
<p>Now, Mr Abbott may have taken a different approach and decided to commit $1.5 billion without knowing anything about the plan; I'm not going to do that.</p>
<p>I have got clear conditions for this project; what I'm prepared to fund. And that's because I want dollars well spent and a project that truly works for western Sydney.</p>
<p>REPORTER: In all cities, people worry about crime, congestion, cost of living. But the Federal Government can't solve those problems, can it?</p>
<p>PM: As I said yesterday, you can't do everything, you can't fix every pothole, you can't catch every crook were my exact words last night.</p>
<p>But you can make the big decisions now which build a future for our country, and you can help modern families with the stresses and strains they're under.</p>
<p>REPORTER: All your events in western Sydney so far have been very Labor friendly. Are you planning to engage with voters who may be less Labor friendly?</p>
<p>PM: I have done things today which really have given me a great sense of what's going on.</p>
<p>I met with representatives of all the local councils, for example, and they have got their shopping list of things that their communities are talking about and we had a good discussion.</p>
<p>And you always learn something, you always pick something up, and more than anything else, you always find something to admire.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
