<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3227</transcript-id>
    <title>ABC BROADCAST BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR EG WHITLAM QC MP, TO BE BROADCAST ON TUESDAY 30 APRIL 1974</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/04/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Broadcast</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003227.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO: 7.30 P. M.<br />
ii MI 7,<br />
A. B. C. BROADCAST BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. E. G. WHITLAM, QC, MP,<br />
TOBEBROADCASTONTUESDAY,_ 30_ APRIL_ 1974_____<br />
Last night, for the second time in 17 months, I put to you,<br />
the Australian people, the program of the Australian Labor Party.<br />
For the second time I delivered my policy speech in the civic<br />
centre of a suburb which symbolises so many of the problems<br />
which my party and my Government have been determined to solve.<br />
Australia regrettably abounds in areas like it, areas where the<br />
residents have had to suffer inadequate transport, overcrowded<br />
hospitals and inferior and uncoordinated community services.<br />
In 1972 the Australian people looked to us as the only political<br />
party in Australia which had considered and devised comprehensive<br />
programs to deal with those shortcomings.<br />
That was 17 months ago. Since then we have taken giant steps<br />
towards dealing with the problems of our nation. For the first<br />
time in a generation Australia has had a Government dedicated to<br />
equal opportunity for all its citizens. For the first time<br />
Australia has had a Government determined to promote Australian<br />
ownership and control of Australian industries and resources.<br />
For the first time Australia has had a Government determined to<br />
reduce inequalities between regions.<br />
Nowhere has this new and vital presence been more keenly<br />
felt than in our schools and other educational institutions.<br />
In our first Budget, we nearly doubled the amount of money for<br />
Government and non-Government schools tHiroiqhout Australia.<br />
We have abolished fees for tertiary~ education. We have approved<br />
a massive injection of finance for technical education. We have<br />
been the first national Government to provide significant funds<br />
for the care and education of pre-school children.<br />
We have not yet been given a fair chance to implement all<br />
of the program I put to you for the 1972 elections. A number of<br />
those programs \; ill grind to a halt and be abandoned if we are not<br />
given that chance. That is what the election on 18 May is all<br />
about: whether the programs, the new hope of 1972 should be<br />
fulfilled; whether the vigour and enthusiasm for change and<br />
improvement, released through your decision in 1972, should be<br />
replaced by the old lethagy.<br />
There is a striking similarity of background, not just of<br />
content, between the speech I delivered last night and that which<br />
I gave in 1972. Neither speech contained piecemeal or unconsidered<br />
policies. All of our policies have been researched, not just by<br />
politicians but by independent experts. All have been given the<br />
widest possible dissemination. That process has taken time, in<br />
some cases as much as 7 years. But it has twice enabled me to<br />
stand before you as the leader of the only party with a coherent<br />
and consistent plan for our development. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
What a contrast with our opponents. They forced a premature<br />
election and then discovered they had to make up some policies<br />
on which to fight it. Bit by bit, you have had to watch their<br />
ideas and whims dribble out of hastily convened and divided meetings<br />
held behind closed doors. Even then you have had to listen to<br />
their spokesmen tell you that they have not been able to cost these<br />
so-called policies.<br />
The same men who cannot put a price on their hasty and<br />
unconsidered plans expect you to believe them when they say<br />
they will cut taxes. It is all too similar to 1969 when they<br />
promised to cut your income tax but did not tell you that they<br />
proposed increased duties on petrol, cigarettes and wine, higher<br />
postal charges, and increased sales taxes.<br />
This is the choice you face on 18 May. It is a clear choice<br />
between our careful planning and thei. r patchwork of last-minute<br />
promises and gimmicks. It is a choice between the continuation<br />
of your new aspirations for Australia or a return to the stale<br />
ideas of yesterday. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
