<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>21234</transcript-id>
    <title>Address to the Australian Troops Baghdad, Iraq </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/04/2004</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
  Well thank you very much Commodore, Colonel, ladies and gentlemen. I';ve come to Iraq on Anzac Day very deliberately to express my personal thanks and admiration to the men and women of the Australian Defence Force for the work that they have done and they continue to do in very challenging circumstances. But it';s not only to them that I extend my thanks and the thanks of the Australian people. But also to many civilian people from Australia, starting of course, with the head of our representative office Neil Mules and all of the others who have worked as advisers to the Iraqi people, the treasury and other departmental officials, all of which have played a very major role. This is not only something that has a military dimension, importantly though that dimension is, and of ongoing significance. But rebuilding the country, advising on the infrastructure, helping to put in place a system of Government and a public service and a bureaucratic structure that will mean that there is enough sustenance for the political expression of democracy that we hope to emerge in this country is also very important.</p>
<p> So I want to say to the men and women who have done that work, to you Neil who will become our Ambassador after the 30th of June and to all of the others who have worked with you, I express my thanks.  These things only happen and work effectively if there is a proper communication between the civilian and the military side of the exercise and in the words that have been spoken about the role of the military, I would not want those on the civilian side to think that in anyway the contribution that they are making is not also very, very deeply valued.</p>
<p>I just say again to all of you, this is a challenging time. What you are doing is for the future of the Iraqi people. It';s a just cause. The nation is united in its prayers and hopes for your well being and your safety and your continued contribution to building a better future for the Iraqi people. And how better and how appropriate I guess it is to express that sentiment on behalf of the Australian people on Anzac Day.</p>
<p>Could I conclude this brief speech by saying that the Government has decided and I';m announcing in Canberra as well as here in Baghdad that we will be, having obtained the necessary approvals from those on high that we';ll be issuing special medals: both a medal for service in Afghanistan and also a medal for service in Iraq to Australian military personnel who qualify and the arrangements for that are going to be set in train. We came to the conclusion that it was appropriate to have a separate medal for each campaign and I think that is the right decision and I believe it will be a decision that is widely welcomed by the relevant defence personnel.</p>
<p>  To all of you again. Thank you. You are doing a great job for Australia and your country is very, very proud indeed of what you are doing.</p>
<p>Thank you.  </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
