<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7678</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF ARRIVAL STATEMENT, RAAF BSE FAIRBIRN, 12 JUNE 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/07/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007678.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF ARRIVAL STATEMENT, RAAF BASE FAIRBAIRN, 12<br />
JULY 1989<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you support the Treasurer's move to ban the<br />
officials from Treasury and the Reserve Bank from talking to<br />
Moody's? PM: I haven't had a chance to talk to him yet. I've been<br />
dealing with international matters. I'll no doubt hear from<br />
Paul about this. I'm sure he had very good reason for doing<br />
it.<br />
JOURNALIST: But you weren't aware of it before it happened?<br />
PM: Look you ought to know by now you've been watching me<br />
for six years I don't sit over every Minister in the<br />
discharge of his portfolio responsibilities, that's why<br />
we've got a good Government. I trust the Ministers, they do<br />
a first class job. I don't sit there watching every move<br />
they make, Why should I?<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, are you concerned that the latest<br />
Morgan Gallup poil shows your personal popularity has<br />
dropped 4% and Mr Peacock's has risen 4%?<br />
PM: I know whose rating I'd rather have, both in terms of<br />
popularity and in terms of preferred Prime Ministership.<br />
You didn't mention that, Why not? Leave him behind a<br />
country mile on that.<br />
JOURNALIST: Are you disturbed by the backbenchers'. meeting<br />
tomorrow to talk about mortgage relief?<br />
PM: I don't get disturbed by backbenchers' meeting. Why<br />
should I? I mean if your a Liberal Party leader or a<br />
National Party leader that's when you've got to be worried<br />
about your backbenchers' meeting. I don't have to worry<br />
about mine meeting.<br />
JOURNALIST: You support their meeting then?<br />
PM: Of course. It's a democratic country.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime minister, do you want the issue of southeast<br />
forests solved before your environment statement, even<br />
if that means confronting New South Wales? </p>
<p>-2-<br />
PM: talk with my two ministers about that. I've asked<br />
them to be looking at it over the last week or so. I'm not<br />
making any comment about that until I have a chance to talk<br />
to them.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister do you think the travel overseas<br />
in the last month and a half has had a -impact on the<br />
Government's standing with the electorate?<br />
PM: I don't know. It's impossible to tell. But the only<br />
important response to that question is that what I've been<br />
doing has been important for the present and future welfare<br />
of Australia. I mean just look at the issues. As far as<br />
the trip to Europe and North America was concerned, the<br />
centrally important issue on that of course was the<br />
international trading environment question. There's no<br />
doubt that on that issue I was able to advance our interests<br />
wherever I went. That's going to mean that not only for the<br />
present but more importantly for the future, better<br />
possibilities not merely for Australian farmers but for the<br />
whole Australian economy. It would have been a dereliction<br />
of duty on my part if I hadn't been there advancing<br />
Australia's cause on those issues. on this two days I've<br />
been away or three days there and back in the South<br />
Pacific Forum no-one is going to question surely the<br />
necessity of maintaining and improving relations with the<br />
countries of the South Pacific. All the things we discussed<br />
there were of intrinsic importance. Of course in regard to<br />
driftnet fishing we have now been able to initiate a move<br />
there which I believe, will lead to not merely a regional<br />
ban on driftnet fishing but I think that will be the lead to<br />
a more extensive and I hope global ban on fishnet fishing.<br />
Now that's something which is again important for Australia,<br />
important for the region and important for the world because<br />
if we don't move on this issue we will be sitting back idly<br />
and witnessing the obliteration of a fundamental resource.<br />
Now you only have to have that exposition from me to know<br />
that what I've been about is important. It would be a very<br />
churlish interpretation which put it in any other light?<br />
JOURNALIST: But while you've been away, for example John<br />
Button has been his characteristic self and being very<br />
honest in saying that in his own Party he's failed in his<br />
Ministry? PM: That is a total misrepresentation. You don't think<br />
that while I'm away I don't read the transcripts and find<br />
out what's happening. That's a total misinterpretation of<br />
what he said. He didn't say he'd been a failure.<br />
JOURNALIST: inaudible<br />
PM: No, no, no, no. Don't misinterpret what Button has<br />
said. He's referred to a disappointment in terms of the<br />
reaction of industry to some extent. But he hasn't said<br />
he's been a failure. </p>
<p>-3-<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, how worried are you by events in<br />
Papua New Guinea in the last week?<br />
PM: You can't help but be worried about events in Papua New<br />
Guinea. There've been another three civilians killed there<br />
and that is disturbing. I've had the opportunity on this<br />
visit of course of having fairly lengthy discussions with<br />
the Deputy Prime Minister of Papua New Guinea, as well as<br />
being kept informed by our own resources. One must be<br />
worried and one can only hope that with the action that the<br />
Government of Papua New Guinea is taking now under the<br />
Declaration of the State of Emergency that they will be able<br />
to bring that insurgency in Bougainville under control and<br />
get the mine open because you've got to realise that that<br />
mine provides the best part of 20% of the Government's<br />
revenue. They can't go on indefinetly suffering that<br />
haemorrhaging of revenue.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
