<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5181</transcript-id>
    <title>SUMMARY OF ABC&#039;S &#039;PM&#039;</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/10/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005181.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER FRIDAY,-19 OCTOBER ' 1979<br />
From the Press office<br />
SUMMARY OF ABC'S<br />
The Australia Council has announced a major inquiry into<br />
opera in Australia. It follows a series of upheavals in<br />
the Australian Opera with its latest General Manager,<br />
Mr. Peter Hemnmings, leaving the country last night having<br />
served only two years of a three year engagement.<br />
There is still confusion over reports earlier today that<br />
the Soviet President, Mr. Breshnev is critically ill or even<br />
dead. Breshnev has dominated Soviet politics. Krushov's<br />
demise and the West has been concerned for some time at what<br />
effect his death might have on Soviet foreign policy.<br />
Interview with Geoffrey Dukes, Research Fellow at ANU.<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr. Fraser, today foreshadowed that the<br />
Commonwealth Government would investigate ways of blocking<br />
State unions who applied for Federal awards as a counter<br />
against State de-registration. The Prime Minister was<br />
speaking at a brief press conference after a meeting in<br />
Canberra today of State Liberal leaders. Mr. Fraser also<br />
launched into a strong political attack on the Opposition.<br />
Excerpt from press conference ( transcript held in Press office).<br />
The biggest demonstration yet in Tasmania's history was held<br />
in Hobart today when 2,000 people gathered to protest against<br />
the Tasmanian Hydro-Electric Commission' s plans to flood the<br />
Franklin and Gordon Rivers in Tasmania's southeast. The<br />
protest was organised by the Tasmanian Wilderness Society.<br />
Interview with the Society's President, Bob Brown.<br />
A voluntary adoption agency in N. S. W. called Jigsaw, which<br />
claims to help adopted children locate their natural parents,<br />
has come under fire from the State Minister for Youth and<br />
Community Services, Mr. Jackson. Mr. Jackson said his<br />
Department had been flooded with complaints from people who have<br />
had contact with the organisation and that they had been<br />
subjected to harrasment and invasion of privacy.. President<br />
of jigsaw, Lorraine Carrol, interviewed. One man who has<br />
been associated with Jigsaw is Noel Turney, an announcer with<br />
a Sydney commercial television station who was with the<br />
organisation as its publicity officer and who left because he<br />
was disturbed by the organisation's activities: interviewed.<br />
There were reports today that the Church of England has been<br />
shocked by the recommendation of a church committee on<br />
homosexuality. The Committee has virtually sanctioned the<br />
homosexual relationship. Editor of The Church Scene in<br />
Melbourne, Gerard Davis, interviewed. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
