<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7654</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF DEPARTURE STATEMENTS BY PRIME MINISTERS HAWKE AND THATCHER, 10 DOWNING STREE, LONDON, 21 JUNE 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/06/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007654.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
IliQ/<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF DEPARTURE STATEMETS BY PRIM MINISTERS HAWKE<br />
AND THATCHER, 10 DOWNING STREET, WNDONO 21 JUNE 1989<br />
9 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
HAWKE: Mrs Thatcher has invited me to make the initial<br />
comments. The first thing I say is to express to Mrs<br />
Thatcher the appreciation of the Australian Government for<br />
the catalytic role which she's taken to put a new vigour<br />
into the Australian/ United Kingdom relationship. I think it<br />
commenced with a visit to Australia last year and upon her<br />
return she has ensured that the preparations for our visit<br />
have left nothing at all to be desired. We are now<br />
participating in an historic meeting by which I mean that<br />
never before has there been a delegation at a level of Prime<br />
Minister and so many Ministers, reciprocated on you side.<br />
That of course will be followed up tomorrow by the meeting<br />
of more than 300 high level businessmen from my country and<br />
from the United Kingdom. so we are engaged at this time in<br />
as I say an historic enterprise to increase the level of<br />
economic and trading relationship between our two countries<br />
but it would be a misapprehension if it were to be taken<br />
that it is merely bilateral matters with which we are<br />
concerend. As important as they are, the United Kingdom and<br />
Australia share common perceptions on matters of<br />
international and regional importance. I think it's, fair to<br />
say Margaret, that tragically at this time an issue which<br />
has taken up a fair bit of the discussion between yourself<br />
and myself and between our Ministers is what has been<br />
happening in China. We are at one in expressing a sense of<br />
almost immeasurable tragedy as to what has happened there<br />
and what has been further compounded by the most recent<br />
evidence now of the execution of the Chinese who were<br />
involved in the train incident in Shanghai. We both deplore<br />
the decision of the Chinese authorities in taking that sort<br />
of action which is out of all sort of relevance to what<br />
those people were involved in. * So we have talked about the<br />
issue of China. We've talked about regional issues. We've<br />
talked together about the challenges that confront us in a<br />
world now where Europe is moving closer tog ether after 1992,<br />
where in our part of the world the region is developing at<br />
an enormously rapid rate offering for us and British </p>
<p>( HAWKE cont): companies who come to operate out of<br />
Australia, enormous opportunities. We are also living in a<br />
time where the changes within the Soviet Union led by<br />
President Gorbachev are also presenting their own<br />
opportunities and challenges and I think that Mrs Thatcher<br />
and I share a fundamental perception about those<br />
developments. That is that we welcome them. We believe<br />
that is it appropriate that the West should, with caution,<br />
assist in those changes that are happening but, as I say,<br />
that that should be done with an appropriate sense of<br />
caution. so you can see that I think we have covered a wide<br />
range of subjects and our discussions will continue now over<br />
what I think will be a useful working lunch Margaret. But I<br />
conclude as I began by expressing my appreciation to you and<br />
your Government for the thought and the preparation that has<br />
gone into this meeting, which I believe can properly be<br />
described as historic.<br />
THATCHER: Just a few words because Mr Hawke has said almost<br />
everything that there is to say about this. We give him a<br />
very warm welcome to the United Kingdom. The invitation was<br />
extended when I was over there for the bicentennial last<br />
year, when I think we all realised that we were entering on<br />
a new era of contacts. We must have more consultation about<br />
global matters and much more consultation between Ministers<br />
so that we may work for better on things like defence<br />
matters, on things like trading matters, on things which<br />
affect the whole world. Australia's position is very<br />
prominent and the very thing about talking to her and her<br />
Ministers is that our approach is the same. It starts on<br />
human rights, the desire to extend those the world over and<br />
as we now have great problems to face in the Pacific and<br />
things happening which we never thought to see, it is very<br />
good that we and Australia should have the time to talk<br />
about those and other matters that Australia's very keen on,<br />
such as the environment. I may say it is very easy to talk<br />
with Australia, with all her Ministers, because of this<br />
similarity of approach which is not just a one off-zeeting,<br />
it is the beginning of a course of meetings which we'll<br />
pursue regularly. There is a special one tomorrow between<br />
trading ministers. While we have a conference at the Queen<br />
Elizabeth Conference Centre to enhance the trading contacts<br />
and to enhance investment both ways. We have long been high<br />
investors in the United States. The United States is also a<br />
very high investor in Britain, which we velcome. There has<br />
been a very, very successful start and I'm sure that that<br />
atmosophere will continue through the rest of the visit.<br />
Thank you.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime minister can I ask you what your reaction<br />
is to the first reported executions of people involved in<br />
the unrest in China? </p>
<p>THATCHER: Utterley appalled. Just exactly as Bob Hawke<br />
pointed out, the punishment is totally out of proportion to<br />
the crime and we are calling on them not to persecute those<br />
who are merely trying to have better arrangements for<br />
democracy. it just shows you that the depth of what has<br />
happened in China is something which we hoped would never<br />
happen and which we still can't quite believe has to the<br />
extent that they are repressing anyone who merely wants to<br />
enlarge human relations.<br />
JOURNALIST: Did you make any progress on reassurances you<br />
might offer the Hong Kong people?<br />
THATCHER: we obviously talked about the Hong Kong people<br />
because we both feel the same way and understand how they<br />
must be feeling. We cannot go any further than that at the<br />
moment. We also have a very avid difficulty in Hong Kong<br />
which we are working together on the Vietnamese boat people<br />
and Australia has been really very, very help about that.<br />
Australia has also had a considerable number of people from<br />
Hong Kong, particularly those involved in industry and<br />
taking up residence in Australia, which has been of great<br />
comfort to the Hong Xong people and I think also of big<br />
benefit to Australia.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke what about Hong Kong. What do you<br />
think should be done about desires to have the right to come<br />
out of the country if things get worse?<br />
HAWXE: Obviously as far as this is directly a matter for<br />
decision by the United Kingdom as to the request by those<br />
people to exercise what they may perceive as their right to<br />
come here, that is a matter for decision and judgement by<br />
M'rs Thatcher and her Government. All that we are concerned<br />
to say is these things. First, that we express our<br />
understanding of the pressures, the problems that confront<br />
the United Kingdom in a situation where they had properly<br />
thought that through detailed, unremitting negortiation with<br />
the Chinese authorities that a position of being reached in<br />
which you could have confidence for the future of the people<br />
of Hong Kong. Well that basis of confidence has gone after<br />
the 4th of June and what has transpired since then. Now<br />
live said to Margaret that we will do what ever we can in<br />
the approach together that we will adopt towards China to<br />
try and create the basic improvement that is necessary.<br />
That is to try and create a situation whereby the time we<br />
get up towards ' 97 there can be a much sounder ground for<br />
saying to the people of Hong Kong, have confidence in the<br />
future. That's what constructively must be the basic<br />
approach. But in the meantime we have indicated for<br />
instance in this financial year which is just concluding,<br />
we've doubled our intake of people from Hfong Kong. We will<br />
look sympathetically at any approach on this matter in terms </p>
<p>4.<br />
HAWKE ( cont): of that other aspect of the question that<br />
Margaret has referred to, that is the Vietnamese refugees.<br />
our assessment is identical. There shouldn't be any doubt<br />
about this because there are amongst our friends a<br />
reluctance to understand the realities. The realities are<br />
these, that the people that are flooding into Hong Kong now<br />
from Vietnam are not political refugees, they are economic<br />
refugees. And as that is the case, then a different<br />
approach is required and we are at one on that and I believe<br />
that as a result of the approach that we are adopting in<br />
consultation with others, and including what's happened in<br />
Geneva recently, we can have a more appropriate response to<br />
what is an unacceptable influx of these people into Hong<br />
Kong. JOURNALIST: I just wanted to ask Prime Minister, whether<br />
you've both thought about how you ought to be reacting to<br />
China now, given that the United States are taking some<br />
measures? THATCHER: we have in fact spent I think about an hour<br />
talking about that subject alone because it is so important<br />
and of course we also keep very closely in touch with the<br />
United States.<br />
HAWKE: May I just add to that. It's not as though it is<br />
just the United states that's taken decisions. The<br />
Government of Mrs Thatcher has already taken decisions in<br />
the area of supply of arms and so on, they've taken<br />
decisions, so have we. It's not a question of the United<br />
States being in front. If anything they are catching up<br />
with us.<br />
JOURNALIST: on the environment. Did you discuss<br />
Antarctica and what is your attitude now in light of the<br />
agreement between the French Government and the Australian<br />
Government to oppose mining there?<br />
THATCHER: We both have the same objective in Antarctica.<br />
it is a very important environmental area. There of<br />
different. France did of course build a very considerable<br />
air strip there compared to recently which is not<br />
necessarily the best thing to do.<br />
JOURNALIST: Can I take this opportunity about why you did<br />
so badly in the European elections?<br />
THATCHER: Because insuffienct. of our supporters came<br />
out. The time when we did best in the European elections<br />
was in 1979 when a far bigger proportion of those supporters<br />
cane out. just exactly what I said to you the day before it<br />
happened, it's an organisational election, it depends on<br />
which side can get most of their supporters out. That's an<br />
absol. utely correct judgement. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Did you get it wrong..<br />
THATCHER: The message we had was the bigger proportion of<br />
our people were intending to come out but it did not turn<br />
out to be the truth on a very hot, nice warm day.<br />
JOURNALIST: Did you yourself get it wrong over Europe, do<br />
you think?<br />
THATCHER: No, no. Not at all.<br />
HAWKE: You ought to try the Australian system Margaret. We<br />
make them vote, it's compulsory.<br />
ends TOTAL PAGE. 0096' TW* </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
