<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8323</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINSITER ADDRESS TO THE CATTLEMEN&#039;S UNION MT ISA - 26 AUGUST 1991</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/08/1991</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008323.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHECKC AGAINAT nELTVERY NMBARMOFn UNTIL flELYERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
ADDRESS TO THE CATTLDID(' S UNION<br />
NT ISA 26 AUGUST 1991<br />
Mr Chairman, I regard it as an honour to come here to Mt Isa<br />
to talk to the Cattlemen's Union today.<br />
Facing up to you blokes reminds me of the story of the cocky<br />
who bought a very expensive prize bull. A couple of days<br />
later the stock agent who sold him the animal drove past and<br />
saw that it was hard at work hooked up to the plough.<br />
Thinking this was a bit of a waste he asked the cocky why he<br />
was using an expensive asset in such a way. Surely it would<br />
have been better off doing what bulls do best.<br />
The cocky said, " I just want to show the beast that<br />
farming's not all romance.*<br />
Coming here I feel a bit like that bull.<br />
Mr Chairman,<br />
You have come from places all over Australia to attend this<br />
conference. Many of you, being cattlemen, have come from<br />
remote places in our vast Continent. But wherever you have<br />
come from, you will I know have been fascinated, as I have<br />
been, by the extraordinary events in the Soviet Union last<br />
week; so ominous and menacing at the start, but moving sCo<br />
swiftly to such a splendid resolution.<br />
As cattlemen you are all international traders, and you all<br />
know how interdependent the world has become. I am sure you<br />
understand that the events in Moscow last week will be<br />
important for all of us. In Parliament last week, I<br />
expressed our delight at the outcome, and our admiration for<br />
those who made it possible. Today I want to start by taking<br />
this first and very appropriate opportunity of a major<br />
speech to explain briefly to you, and through you to<br />
Australians everywhere, what I think is the broader<br />
significance of these events.<br />
Between Monday and Thursday last week, we witnessed one of<br />
the pivotal events of the century. I want to explain why,<br />
when I say that, I mean exactly what I say.<br />
9 </p>
<p>From where we now stand, only eight years from its end, we<br />
can see that the history of thiis century has been the<br />
history of the struggle by people all over the world to<br />
achieve or to defend political and economic liberty.<br />
These liberties are ideals which have been evolving in our<br />
civilisation for many centuries. But it has fallen to this<br />
century to try to build social, political and economic<br />
structures which would bring those ideals to life for all<br />
people, everywhere.<br />
In that long struggle, ideologies have carried the banners.<br />
This has been the century of ideologies. But where the<br />
ideologies have been strongest, it has been easiest to<br />
mistake the means for the endi; to betray the ideals to<br />
defend the ideology. So much of the history of our century<br />
has been the histor-y of such betrayals. Nowhere has that<br />
been more true than in the tragedy of the Bolshevik<br />
Revolution, which promised the Soviet people so much, and<br />
has given them so pitifully :: ittle.<br />
For them, and for all of us, the events of last week mark<br />
the decisive end of that tragedy. Last week the oldest and<br />
greatest of the Communist systems showed, at last and beyond<br />
any question, that it is weaker than the will of its own<br />
people in their striving for political and economic freedom.<br />
The ideal has defeated the ideology.<br />
It is obvious what this means to the Soviet people<br />
themselves. For them, the sczenes we saw on our screens last<br />
week are the most exciting and auspicious since Lenin<br />
arrived at the Finland station in October 1917. Now, as<br />
then, a coup has ended, and a revolution has begun.<br />
Today the people of the Soviet Union have the chance to<br />
define their nationality and rebuild their society anew. it<br />
will not be easy. But they have great material and<br />
9piritual resources. We wish them well, and we will help<br />
where we can.<br />
For other nations still held by tyranny, last week's scenes<br />
must mean hardly less than they do to the people of the<br />
Soviet Union. They are a bright beacon of hope.<br />
For the world as a whole, the events of last week show that<br />
the spirit of international cooperation which has grown in<br />
recent years is deeply rooted in the strongest soil. They<br />
challenge us to expand that cooperation.<br />
The world can stand united to0 confront aggression, as we did<br />
a year ago. And the world can speak with a single voice to<br />
support freedom and deter tyranny, as we did last week. So<br />
we must wonder why the world cannot learn to cooperate<br />
better to serve the important interests we share in other<br />
areas as well. I113 t </p>
<p>At the moment, no international issue is more pressing than<br />
the future of the Uruguay Round. Since 1986, when the<br />
Uruguay Round began, the world has changed so much because<br />
in so many areas we learned to apply the harsh lessons of<br />
the past to avoid the mistakes of the past. But in world<br />
trade we seem to be in danger of repeating the terriblo<br />
errors of the 1930s, which produced not just poverty but<br />
war. Time is running out for a successful conclusion to the<br />
Uruguay Round of the GATT. Nine months have now passed<br />
since the failure of the ministerial meeting in Brussels<br />
last December. Unless real progress is made by the end of<br />
this year or very early in 1992, the political momentum<br />
required to conclude the Round successfully could be<br />
dissipated. of course, there are many reasons to be worried<br />
on that score, but the most obvious is that once we get into<br />
1992, the United States will go increasingly into election<br />
mode. The importance of a successful outcome to the Round for the<br />
world economy and for Australia, including of course the<br />
beef industry, is as high as ever.<br />
We are absolutely committed to the need for a balanced<br />
outcome in the Uruguay Round. No one can afford a deail that<br />
perpetuates the gross waste of the world's scarce resources<br />
that presently occurs. The Common Agricultural Policy of<br />
the EC, the EEP policy instigated by the US to combat it,<br />
and on a lesser scale the import restrictions in Japan,<br />
Korea and other countries, all add up to an intolerable<br />
situation for Australian primary producers.<br />
It cannot, and will not, go on forever.<br />
Success in the Round will be of lasting benefit to your<br />
industry. If we can implement changes that see the lowering and<br />
eventual elimination of export subsidies, then, but only<br />
then, the Andriessen assurance that EC subsidised beef<br />
will not be dumped onto our North Asian markets would<br />
become redundant.<br />
The overwhelming responsibility for a successful conclusion<br />
to the Round rests with the Europeans. As I wrote to the<br />
leaders of the G7 meeting before the London summit last<br />
month, the key to the future of world trade is GATT; the key<br />
to GATT is the Uruguay Round; the key to the Uruguay Round<br />
is agriculture; and the key to agriculture is reform of the<br />
European Community's agricultural protection policies. The<br />
Europeans are principally responsible for the corruption of<br />
the international market in agricultural goods, which<br />
adversely affects this country and other free traders in the<br />
Cairns Group.<br />
' k) 32 </p>
<p>We welcome signs that the European Community is addressing<br />
serious reform of the Common Agricultural Policy. As for<br />
the Uruguay Round, we do not make unreasonable or inflexible<br />
demands that has not characterised the approach we have<br />
taken, either individually or in our role as leader of the<br />
Cairns Group but we do seek qp~ nifir and concrete<br />
commitments in each of the three areas of internal support,<br />
border protection and export subsidies.<br />
I have asked the Leader of the Opposition to join the<br />
Government in sending a bipartisan mission to Europe to<br />
press Australia's concerns about these issues. The mission<br />
will be led by the Minister for Trade and Overseas<br />
Development, Dr Blewett.<br />
Beyond that, it is essential that world leaders maintain a<br />
close personal interest: in the Uruguay Round, as it may well<br />
be that direct involvement by Heads of Government will<br />
become necessary to secure an outcome to the Round. if so,<br />
you may be assured tha': I will be at the forefront of those<br />
efforts. Under GATT, imperfect as it is at present, we have achieved<br />
important liberalisation in the Japanese and Korean beef<br />
markets. Korea has an obligation to remove, by July 1997 at<br />
the latest, import barriers introduced for balance of<br />
payments reasons. Japan has moved to a tariff-based import<br />
regime with tariff reductions from seventy per cent in April<br />
1992 to fifty per cent by April 1993.<br />
Japan and Korea currently account for about 37 per cent of<br />
Australia's total beef and veal exports. By 1995-96 these<br />
two markets are projected to account for as much as 47 per<br />
cent of our total exports.<br />
Australia continues to supply seventy per cent of Korean<br />
imports. In 1991, Korea is expected to import 100,000<br />
tonnes, well over the 62,000 tonnes minimum access level.<br />
The challenge is to ensure improved access for the period<br />
after 1992. The Australian industry will also need to adapt<br />
to be able to satisfy the changing pattern of demand as<br />
higher incomes lead to consumers preferring boneless cuts of<br />
grain-fed product. Without industry development to meet<br />
this demand change, the US will have an edge in the Korean<br />
market. Japan's movement to a tariff-based import system is expected<br />
to lead to a substantial improvement in demand for imported<br />
beef. Whilst the initial change will lead to some<br />
constraints as the market adjusts, the tariff reductions<br />
should boost demand. The forecast is that our sales could<br />
increase to 320,000 tonnes by 1996, or by over 65 per cent<br />
on this year's expected sales. </p>
<p>Mr Chairman, the US has been our largest export market since<br />
the mid-sixties. Sales are expected to remain firm. This<br />
year's projected sales of 370,000 tonnes is up on last year.<br />
There is the possibility that the US Meat Import Law trigger<br />
level will be exceeded, raising the prospect either of the<br />
US Administration negotiating Voluntary Restraint<br />
Arrangements ( VRAs) with suppliers, or a quota set at the<br />
trigger. That would mean a 10% reduction in our access.<br />
The next US quarterly consultations with supplying countries<br />
will be held this week, after which the position, and<br />
whether the trigger level will be reached, will be clearer.<br />
Officials mest with the Cattle Council last week, and there<br />
will be further consultations with the industry in the weeks<br />
ahead. In the long term, the challenge is to have trade restricting<br />
measures, such as the US Meat Import Law, removed.<br />
Mr Chairman,<br />
Today we do have a lot to thank the cattle industry for.<br />
Australia has prospered on the sheep's back, but today is<br />
increasingly riding on the back of the cattle industry,<br />
which now contributes 15% of the total gross value of farm<br />
production and is Australia's third-largest rural<br />
export-earner.<br />
In this period where the world trading environment is so<br />
distorted and where commodity prices, for the most part,<br />
have nose-dived, the beef cattle industry is doing fairly<br />
well. This is in no small measure due to the<br />
resourcefulness, creativity, energy and sheer hard work of<br />
those involved in the industry. The work done to adapt<br />
different breeds of cattle to Northern Australian conditions<br />
is but one outstanding example.<br />
Looking to the medium term, saleyard cattle prices are<br />
projected to increase until 1993-94, which reflects keen<br />
demand by existing producers and new entrants responding to<br />
the favourable medium-term export outlook.<br />
Cattle numbers are forecast to reach 28.5 million head by<br />
1995-96 and slaughterings projected to rise to 9.6 million<br />
per year.<br />
By 1995-96, production looks like being 19% above the<br />
1990-91 estimates.<br />
Because growth in production will be in excess of the growth<br />
in total demand, prices are projected to fall after 1993-94.<br />
The rate of increase in the retail price of beef is also<br />
projected to slow, which should increase retail demand.<br />
Total per person beef consumption is projected to increase<br />
to 42.5 kg by 1995-96.<br />
93 4 </p>
<p>* Beef production costs are projected to increase, which means<br />
we should plan for an increase in efficiency or face a<br />
decline in profitability in the mid-. 1990s.<br />
Mr Chairman,<br />
Some of you might recall the first time I addressed the<br />
Cattlemen's Union, which was in 1977 when I was President of<br />
the ACTU.<br />
What I talked about then was the need for us to work<br />
together so that we might achieve consensus for the<br />
betterment of your industry and all the people who work in<br />
it. As Prime Minister, I say the same thing today. We must work<br />
together. The economic future of this country depends on it.<br />
The Australian meat industry is characterised by a maze of<br />
complex awards and over-award agreements. Its workforce is<br />
made up largely of pieceworkers. ' Work is repetitive and<br />
conditions uncomfortable. Training is deficient, career<br />
paths and job security are, by the standards of many other<br />
Australian workers, deficient. So too are standards of<br />
workplace health and safety.<br />
Such an environment is a breeding ground for discontent and<br />
mistrust. If we are to overcome the legacy of generations of poor<br />
relations between employers and employees, and create an<br />
environment in which this industry can raise its<br />
productivity and efficiency, a major attitudinal change is<br />
required. As I said, we Government, unions and employers<br />
must strive to work together.. Employers and unions must<br />
change their traditional adversarial approach. They must<br />
address their combined prcoblems in the long-term interests<br />
of the industry. Such changes ' are already occurring in some<br />
areas but there is still a long way to go.<br />
To this end, we believe that t~ e establishment of a<br />
tripartite consultative committee Employers, Government,<br />
and unions at industry level would be a key factor in<br />
improving communication between unions and employers in the<br />
meat industry. The same kind of arrangement should also be<br />
set up at the plant level.. Consultative arrangements like<br />
this have been crucial in other industries, such as vehicle<br />
manufacturing and iron and steel production.<br />
Mr Chairman<br />
My Government has been an active participant in the pursuit<br />
of industrial relations reform in the meat industry.<br />
We have provided funding through the Workplace Reform<br />
Program to help the Meat and Allied Trades Federation of<br />
Australia and the relevant unions with award restructuring. .9; 1 </p>
<p>In Queensland, we have helped the drafting of a consolidated<br />
model award to apply to the export sector. The aim is to<br />
reduce substantially the number of job classificationsi in<br />
existing awards, create greater flexibility in working<br />
arrangements and skill utilisation, and to develop career<br />
paths. My Government is also awaiting the results of the Australian<br />
Industrial Relations Commission Inquiry into the Meat<br />
Industry, as it should provide a basis for further reform in<br />
the industry.<br />
Mr Chairman, I know that some of your members have been<br />
worried about foreign investment in your industry<br />
particularly as it relates to ConAgra.<br />
But Mr Chairman, your industry has since its inception<br />
depended on foreign investment to get where it is today.<br />
Imagine the industry's development without the significant<br />
capital injections that started it last century. Imagine it<br />
without the innovation of frozen meat transport, or more<br />
recently the development of grain feed-lot capacity.<br />
The concern about ConAgra is to my mind a misplaced concern.<br />
Your industry body, the Australian Meat and Livestock<br />
Industry Policy Council, has submitted foreign investment<br />
guidelines to the Government.<br />
While those guidelines are still under consideration,<br />
ConAgra's purchase of Elders meat division does fall within<br />
them. In the ConAgra case, we required that the shareholders<br />
agreement for the meat business provide for at least fifty<br />
per cent of directors to represent Australian interests and<br />
that ConAgra report back to the Foreign Investment Review<br />
Board on developments within the meat industry generally<br />
within twelve months.<br />
Mr Chairman<br />
I know that cost recovery for the Australian Quaranti. ne and<br />
Inspection Service ( AQIS) is also a major concern for you.<br />
The Government's decision to introduce full cost recovery<br />
for services provided by AQIS from 1 January 1991 was made<br />
as part of the micro-economic reform process. It ensures<br />
that all users of the inspection service pay for the<br />
services they require.<br />
We fully expected that the introduction of full cost<br />
recovery would lead to debate about the quality, type and<br />
cost of services provided by AQIS. Such debate is a natural<br />
and desirable consequence of this charging policy, as it is<br />
only with such debate that the most efficient services can<br />
be provided. </p>
<p>Those paying f or the ser-vice are fully entitled to pressure<br />
AQIS to ensure they get the most efficient and effective<br />
inspection service possible.<br />
It must be emphasised that Government-certified inspection<br />
is in some cases the only means of access to overseas<br />
markets and the only way of ensuring that information on<br />
product quality is available to assist the producer. It is,<br />
therefore, in the interests of both the industry and AQIS to<br />
ensure that cost-efficient services and effective product<br />
monitoring is carried out.<br />
Mr Chairman,<br />
Last week also saw my Government's ninth Budget. That<br />
Budget was the third instalment of policy decisions which<br />
have made i991 the year of the most substantial and farreaching<br />
economic reforins, not just in the life of this<br />
Government, but in the entire post-war era.<br />
That is a large but completely justifiable claim.<br />
The Budget must be seen in the context of the continuing and<br />
comprehensive process cf reform on which we have embarked.<br />
It must be assessed in the context of the landmark programs<br />
we have placed on the national agenda, including those<br />
already being implemented, such as the abolition of the<br />
two-airlines policy and telecommunications reform both, I<br />
might say, crucial to the future of Northern and outback<br />
Australia. In the quest for a sustainable and internationally<br />
competitive economy, in this year alone we have set in train<br />
through the March Statement the acceleration of<br />
unprecedented tariff reform: taxation reform, notably the<br />
simplification of depreciation provisions, and the widening<br />
of sales tax exemptions: and resource security.<br />
Again in 1991 alone, the commitments undertaken through the<br />
Special Premiers Conference process are fundamental to<br />
economic reform.<br />
The July Special Premiers Conference agreed to establish the<br />
National Rail Corporation, the National Road Transport<br />
Commission, and the Electricity Grid Management Council, and<br />
to business deregulation which will sweep away the stupidity<br />
of having six sets of regulations around our nation. These<br />
are all major reforms which are fundamental to building a<br />
competitive Australia.<br />
It is in this broader context of reform that the Budget must<br />
be viewed, and it is against that background that I want to<br />
emphasise some basic points about the Budget itself. () 3? 7 </p>
<p>9.<br />
First, and most importantly, the Budget will underpin<br />
economic recovery over the course of 1991-92. Unemployment<br />
will go higher in the short term something I regret deeply<br />
but sustainable job growth will resume in this financial<br />
year. For a Labor Government, high unemployment cuts to the quick.<br />
We could easily have attempted artificially to pump-prime<br />
the economy. But we resisted that, because it would have<br />
simply put us back on the path of the cyclical boom-and-bust<br />
periods which have for too long characterised the Australian<br />
economy. Any jobs created in the boom would have been more<br />
than of fset by the jobs lost in the subsequent bust.<br />
Second, while the Budget is the first in five years to<br />
provide for a deficit, all spending initiatives are fully<br />
offset by savings. We have protected the structural<br />
integrity of the Budget while at the same time taking<br />
initiatives, especially for families and disadvantaged<br />
groups. Third, the changes to Medicare are designed to further<br />
entrench~ a great reform into the Australian landscape. The<br />
problem of overservicing had to be addressed. We have done<br />
it in a way which preserves the fundamental characteristics<br />
of Medicare and in a fair way which protects those least<br />
able to afford it and those in greatest need.<br />
Finally, this is a Budget containing far-sighted reforms in<br />
the area of superannuation. Like Medicare, it would have<br />
been easier to duck the problem. Instead, we have tackled<br />
it head-on and, in doing so, have laid firm foundations for<br />
the retirement incomes of our rapidly ageing population into<br />
the twenty-first century.<br />
in the ninth Budget of my Government, we are still taking<br />
the tough decisions, we are still doing what is best for<br />
Australia's long-term interest. We have always drawn some<br />
flak for our tough decisions. But the Australian people<br />
have always recognised and rewarded my Government for<br />
displaying a commitment to the long term. I believe they<br />
will continue to do so.<br />
Mr Chairman<br />
My Government is acutely aware of the difficulties currently<br />
being experienced in rural Australia.<br />
938 </p>
<p>i't propose to reiterate Budget details which you<br />
3dy know, but I will mention one major reform which<br />
fits families in rural Australia those families which<br />
as we say, asset rich but cash por. The introduction<br />
n assets test on the family allowance, at a threshold of<br />
:, 000 net of debt and excluding the family home, has been<br />
) mpanied by hardship provisions to protect asset rich,<br />
poor families. For two years from 1 January 1992,<br />
. lies will continue to receive the Family Allowance<br />
3onent of the Family Payment regardless of the value of<br />
ir assets if current income is less than the basic rate<br />
Social Security benefit S13,078 plus S624 per child<br />
liquid personal assets are less than $ 10,000 in the case<br />
a couple.<br />
im the same date, families meeting the above tests and<br />
: h net business assets up to a value of $ 600,000 will<br />
; ome eligible to receive the equivalent of the present<br />
nily Allowance Supplement under the new combined Family<br />
Yment. Under the new arrangements, families could be<br />
igible for family assistance payments of up to about $ 50 a<br />
ek per child.<br />
have also put in place a strategy to facilitate rural and<br />
! gional development. To reduce gaps in rural and regional<br />
! rvices and to promote the diversification of rural and<br />
3gional economies, we have introduced new measures in the<br />
991-92 Budget with additional funding of $ 2.3M in 1991-92,<br />
nd S4.3M in both 1992-93 and 1993-94.<br />
ike the Budget as a whole, these treasures need to be seen<br />
gainst the background of Government action through the<br />
ear. In particular, the then Minister for Primary<br />
ndustries and Energy announced in April an increase in<br />
unding for the Rural Adjustment Scheme by Sl00M to S160M in<br />
991-92. This assistance is directed to those farmers most<br />
n need and gives the Commonwealth the capacity to support<br />
P to S1.4bn of rural debt in 1991-92.<br />
n addjition to these programs, the Government recognises the<br />
articular mix of difficulties facing the residents of<br />
orthern Australia. A Northern Australia Social Justice<br />
trategy is to be developed over the next year, in<br />
Onjunction with a Northern Australia Economic Strategy.<br />
r Chairman, in conclusion let me say that whenever I come<br />
Northern Australia, whether hece in Mt Isa or in Darwin,<br />
orth Queensland, or the Kimberleys I realise once again how<br />
he economic and social balance in Australia is changing.<br />
outherners, more and more are coming to see that where the<br />
wentieth century has been dominated by the south, the<br />
wenty-first will swing to the north.<br />
attlemen knew that a long time ago, and if there is one<br />
riticism that I might make, it that you have kept the<br />
ecret of Northern Australia to yourselves for too long. BONBON EN-</p>
<p>SThe fundamental changes my Government has made in the<br />
economy of Australia, whether in encouraging tourism in the<br />
North by abolishing the two-airline policy and protecting<br />
our wonderful environmental tourist attractions, or<br />
redirecting our trade efforts towards our Asian and Pacific<br />
markets, have changed, and benefited Northern Australia more<br />
in the last nine years than in the previous ninety.<br />
But whatever the future holds for Northern Australia one<br />
thing is for sure cattle and cattlemen will play an<br />
important part in it.<br />
Thank you.<br />
0910<br />
W </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
