<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10801</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER               THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                  PRESS CONFERENCE &amp;#150; PARLIAMENT HOUSE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/07/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE.................................................................................................</p>
<p>  Good afternoon ladies and gentlemen. The vote in the Senate this</p>
<p>   morning to approve the Government's Native Title Amendment</p>
<p>   Bill is a wonderful outcome for all Australians. I thank the</p>
<p>   Senate in particular. I thank Senator Brian Harradine for the role</p>
<p>   that he played in resolving this matter in a way that I believe</p>
<p>   over time will be widely applauded by the entire Australian community.</p>
<p>   I would especially want to thank my colleague, the Special Minister</p>
<p>   for State, Senator Nick Minchin, who has skillfully guided this</p>
<p>   legislation through both the partyroom, the Australian community,</p>
<p>   and most recently the Senate.</p>
<p>  This vote this morning brings to an end 18 months of at times frustration,</p>
<p>   intense delay, difficulty, complication, and in some sections of</p>
<p>   the community, a certain amount of acrimony. It resolves in a fashion</p>
<p>   that is, I believe, fair and equitable, one of the most difficult</p>
<p>   socio-legal issues that Australia has ever faced. It does preserve</p>
<p>   the principles of Native Title laid down in the Mabo case. It does</p>
<p>   give security and predictability to the farmers of Australia. It</p>
<p>   does protect the legitimate interests of the mining industry and</p>
<p>   all of that means to the export potential of our country, and it</p>
<p>   will at long last provide a workable mechanism for native title</p>
<p>   claims to be addressed and resolved.</p>
<p>  More importantly, I believe it will allow Australians to feel good</p>
<p>   about themselves in that the institutions of our society have, at</p>
<p>   long last, albeit through a very protracted process, been able to</p>
<p>   come up with a solution to an extremely difficult and challenging</p>
<p>   issue. No section of the Australian community has got everything</p>
<p>   it wanted out of native title. No section of the Australian community</p>
<p>   can run around and say we won and everybody else lost'</p>
<p>   and it was never my intention that that be the outcome. And that</p>
<p>   guided very much my handling of the matter from the time that the</p>
<p>   Wik decision was handed down by the High Court in December of 1996.</p>
<p>   It is a very good outcome indeed.</p>
<p>  It allows the Australian community to move onto other issues. It</p>
<p>   takes from the national political agenda something that was always</p>
<p>   in the eyes of some, divisive. I believe it is an issue that the</p>
<p>   Australian people would not have shirked from resolving if that</p>
<p>   had been necessary through the ballot box, in a restrained and tolerant</p>
<p>   fashion. But nonetheless it is overwhelmingly to be desired that</p>
<p>   the matter was resolved in the way in which it was.</p>
<p>  And I again thank Senator Brian Harradine for the contribution that</p>
<p>   he made and I also thank my colleague Senator Minchin and all the</p>
<p>   members of the Wik taskforce and my staff for the roles that they</p>
<p>   played in bringing about this marvellous outcome this morning.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Prime Minister you say that no section can say "we've</p>
<p>   won", yet isn't that exactly what is happening? Senator</p>
<p>   Harradine is saying he's not diminished Aboriginal rights and</p>
<p>   yet you've got Mr Fischer still pushing the "bucketloads</p>
<p>   of extinguishment" line. I mean, who's right in that sense?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  I don't think anybody can say they've totally won to the</p>
<p>   exclusion of others.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Mr Howard, you have said it is a wonderful outcome for all Australians.</p>
<p>   The Aboriginal people don't seem to think so.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, you've got to make your own judgments about these things.</p>
<p>   Perhaps some of their leadership was wrongly encouraged to believe</p>
<p>   by the Labor Party that they could achieve an outcome that was never</p>
<p>   realistic. The fact is that the principles of Native Title as laid</p>
<p>   down in Mabo are still there. It is still possible to use the right</p>
<p>   to negotiate' over vacant crown land. The principles of Wik</p>
<p>   have been respected. But they've been respected in a way that</p>
<p>   delivers greater clarity and greater predictability. Nobody can</p>
<p>   say that the fundamental rights of Native Title enunciated in Mabo</p>
<p>   and distilled in Wik have been taken away by this legislation. In</p>
<p>   the end, the judgement of whether something is fair to a particular</p>
<p>   group has got to be an objective judgement, and I believe that this</p>
<p>   legislation achieves the right balance within the Australian community.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Do you think that this legislation will survive a High Court challenge?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  As to its constitutionality, yes I am.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Why?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Because that is the weight of the opinion that we have received</p>
<p>   and that is the trend of court cases confirming that opinion.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  How do we assess the success of the legislation down the track?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  How do we assess the success of it down the track? Well, the way</p>
<p>   it works out obviously, and I believe it will be successful because</p>
<p>   this is the first time we've got a decent framework to allow</p>
<p>   native title claimants to go forward and be resolved but also to</p>
<p>   prevent vexatious claims. We've toughened the registration</p>
<p>   test because the old Keating registration test was too loose. We've</p>
<p>   provided some predictability in relation to farming and mining activity.</p>
<p>   We've provided a state based regime as an alternative to the</p>
<p>   right to negotiate and I believe that that lays down a guide path</p>
<p>   for the successful operation of the legislation. It was never going</p>
<p>   to be easy, but it was never realistic to leave the Keating act</p>
<p>   in place. The Keating act was flawed from the beginning and the</p>
<p>   Keating act was rendered irrelevant almost by the decision of the</p>
<p>   High Court in the Wik case because the Keating legislation had been</p>
<p>   premised on another outcome of the High Court in that particular</p>
<p>   case.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Mr Howard, before these final sets of negotiations with Brian Harradine,</p>
<p>   you and Senator Minchin and the National Party said the sunset clause</p>
<p>   was non-negotiable. What changed?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  We decided that in the end that was our contribution to achieving</p>
<p>   an honourable compromise.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Do you believe that this the circuit breaker that your Government</p>
<p>   desperately needs?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, Mr Smith, I never embrace expressions of desperation ever</p>
<p>    never ever, to borrow a phrase! Of course I don't. But</p>
<p>   this is a good development for Australia, and people want governments</p>
<p>   to be, not only to be seen to be, but to actually resolve difficult</p>
<p>   problems and I'm able to say to the Australian people that</p>
<p>   I have been able to solve the vexed problem of Native Title in a</p>
<p>   way that my predecessor could never have done, and I've been</p>
<p>   able to resolve it in a way that is fair and honourable to all sections</p>
<p>   of the Australian community.</p>
<p>  Look, not every farmer in Australia has got everything he wanted.</p>
<p>   Not every miner has got everything he wanted. Not every Aboriginal</p>
<p>   person has got everything he wanted, but it is fair and equitable</p>
<p>   and delivers security and predictability as much as any legislation</p>
<p>   in such a difficult vexed area could possibly have done. That is</p>
<p>   why I am very proud of what it has been possible to achieve.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Why is it fair and honourable Mr Howard to accommodate the retrospective</p>
<p>   change in the West Australian legislation which changes the entire</p>
<p>   extinguishment regime for West Australian pastoral leases?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, I don't share your interpretation of that but perhaps</p>
<p>   we can go into it in more detail in another circumstance.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Could you explain why you put the Telstra bill to the bottom of</p>
<p>   the Senate list and is this a deferral til the next sitting</p>
<p>   of the Parliament?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  To the next sitting of the Parliament? No no, the Telstra legislation</p>
<p>   will be debated and will be voted on in the Senate this sitting.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Previously you talked about Native Title as a land management issue</p>
<p>   and since the Queensland election you've talked about it as</p>
<p>   a potentially divisive issue. Has your thinking on the prospect</p>
<p>   of a Native Title election changed since Queensland?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, those statements are not necessarily mutually exclusive, Raphael,</p>
<p>   they're not. You can have a land management issue that is potentially</p>
<p>   divisive and you can have potential division over land management.</p>
<p>   I mean, it is a lot of things. It is, to many people, it is symbolic.</p>
<p>   To many people it has a cultural content. To many people it has</p>
<p>   a spiritual meaning. To other people it is a land management issue.</p>
<p>   Much of the argument about the detail of the legislation concerned</p>
<p>   land management issues, and much of the intense debate was about</p>
<p>   whether you had rights of this variety or that character. It was...I</p>
<p>   can assure you that the detailed discussions that I had with representatives</p>
<p>   of the Indigenous Working Group earlier on and with others surrounded</p>
<p>   the nitty gritty, the bread and butter of the legislation and certainly</p>
<p>   strayed only fleetingly into the more general areas.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  So you weren't more worried after Queensland?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  No.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  How confident are you that the States will pass the complementary</p>
<p>   legislation that's required, that all States and Territories</p>
<p>   will....</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, that is up to them. It will be desirable to have a degree</p>
<p>   of uniformity but that is up to them. I'm not going to sit</p>
<p>   in judgement on the States. We have done our job. It is now up to</p>
<p>   each State to assess its responsibilities and to make its judgments.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Labor has predicted bucket loads of litigation, will you fund and</p>
<p>   expedite a High Court challenge on the Constitutionality to clear</p>
<p>   up the matter as quickly possible.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, more in sorrow than in anger. Can I say that the Labor Party</p>
<p>   has throughout this whole thing played a negative, destructive,</p>
<p>   point scoring game and so have the Democrats and the Australian</p>
<p>   Greens and I don't think the Australian public gives them any</p>
<p>   marks for that at all. The Labor Party left us with this mess. It</p>
<p>   was the flawed Keating/Beazley act that we had to address and we've</p>
<p>   grappled with it, we've had no help from them - no help at</p>
<p>   all - and it's taken agreement with Senator Harradine to resolve</p>
<p>   the matter. I don't think they win any marks for this at all.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Prime Minister are you confident of being able to reach a compromise</p>
<p>   with the National Party or to get their support on the full sale</p>
<p>   of Telstra, given that sections continue to be in open rebellion</p>
<p>   against the privatisation?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  I think we should just allow events to unfold.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Will you allow announce anything before the vote?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Anything what?</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  On Telstra?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Oh, the situation regarding Telstra is that it has always been understood,</p>
<p>   and I made it clear at the National Convention, that if the legislation</p>
<p>   empowering the Government to sell the rest of Telstra were passed</p>
<p>   it would then be economically possible to make available a social</p>
<p>   bonus. Now, as to when you may announce details of that and in what</p>
<p>   form that announcement would take, although obviously, some of the</p>
<p>   social bonus if Telstra were to go through would be in the form</p>
<p>   of spending on communications infrastructure in regional areas of</p>
<p>   Australia and communications issues in regional areas of Australia.</p>
<p>   As to when, what form, how, etcetera, is a matter that is still</p>
<p>   under discussion but the Government remains committed to the legislation</p>
<p>   and the reason that we are committed to the legislation is that</p>
<p>   it is a very important part of our debt retirement strategy.</p>
<p>  I mean, this will bring enormous benefits to future generations</p>
<p>   of Australians to be able to enter the next century virtually free</p>
<p>   of Federal Government debt. We'll be down to 1.5 per cent of</p>
<p>   gross domestic product from a level of 20 per cent in the middle</p>
<p>   of the 1990s. Now that is a huge benefit to the Australian community.</p>
<p>   That's why we are committed to it and we believe that if it</p>
<p>   does go through it will be possible and economically quite responsible</p>
<p>   to use some of the proceeds to fund spending on socially desirable</p>
<p>   things. That's the social bonus, and part of that will obviously</p>
<p>   be spending on improving communications in regional and rural Australia</p>
<p>   because there are some services in that part of the country which</p>
<p>   are in need of more help and more spending and this is something</p>
<p>   that we have had in mind for some time.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Have you held or will you be holding discussions with Senators Colston</p>
<p>   and Harradine on this issue?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Look, I talk to a lot of Senators about a lot of things and I don't</p>
<p>   ever rule out discussions with Senators. They are always people</p>
<p>   that you should talk to.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Even those Senators whose vote you won't accept, namely Senator</p>
<p>   Colston?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, you understand the background of that George, and I have got</p>
<p>   nothing more to say to that. But I am obviously willing to talk</p>
<p>   to anybody.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  The Nationals also want you to wind back on certain areas of national</p>
<p>   competition policy. Can we expect any more exemptions?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, I think these are things that from time-to-time come up and</p>
<p>   we talk our way through them and I am not sort of giving a whole</p>
<p>   sort of running announcements on policies as we go through. Look,</p>
<p>   we worked our way through the Native Title Amendment Bill and we</p>
<p>   got a fantastic outcome and I didn't give a running commentary</p>
<p>   on those discussions. I mean what matters in these things, Craig,</p>
<p>   is the outcome, not the doorstops each morning. What really matters</p>
<p>   is where you end up and we have ended up with a terrific outcome</p>
<p>   on Native Title. We have solved the most difficult problem that</p>
<p>   I think any Government has faced for 10 years given the complexity</p>
<p>   of the social and economic and political issues bound up with it.</p>
<p>   So you keep your eye on the final outcome. The noise and static</p>
<p>   along the way is of no moment when measured against the outcome.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Mr Howard, the Nationals want to see the same level of service that</p>
<p>   the city gets in the bush, they are talking about high-speed digital</p>
<p>   data transmissions. Is that what your Government is aiming to deliver</p>
<p>   to the bush?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  A lot of people want to see the same level of services. The Liberal</p>
<p>   rural members want to see the same level of service. Rural people</p>
<p>   I talk to want to see the same level of service. Ann, there are</p>
<p>   a whole lot of things being discussed and as I've said I am</p>
<p>   not going to engage in that noise and static along the way. It's</p>
<p>   the outcome that is important and I obviously want to see communications</p>
<p>   justice for the bush. Communications justice for the bush will be</p>
<p>   more assuredly delivered if there is a sale of Telstra than if it's</p>
<p>   not....you know people should understand that if there were not</p>
<p>   a full privatisation of Telstra the money is simply not there to</p>
<p>   fund a lot of things that people want. I mean that should be understood.</p>
<p>   We don't have an inexhaustible supply of money. There are other</p>
<p>   things that have a call on the Government's resources and people</p>
<p>   should understand that one of the benefits of selling the remaining</p>
<p>   two-thirds of Telstra is that you have additional resources to spend</p>
<p>   on things that people want. If you don't sell it, then that</p>
<p>   capital is lying idle and tied up and unavailable for socially beneficial</p>
<p>   purposes.</p>
<p>  I mean there are two socially beneficial outcomes from the full</p>
<p>   privatisation of Telstra. You get this terrific debt retirement</p>
<p>   profile which gets us down to 1.5 per cent by the beginning of the</p>
<p>   century and you also have money to spend on socially desirable things.</p>
<p>   Now that is a win-win for all Australians. Not just for Australians</p>
<p>   in the bush but selling Telstra delivers win-win for all Australians</p>
<p>   and that's why I am committed to it. I think some of you are</p>
<p>   looking a little cold. Do you enjoy having press conferences here?</p>
<p>   You're all rugged up. This is the last one, I must go then.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Mr Howard, just to clarify, it sounds like the communications part</p>
<p>   of the package you'd expect to unveil in the couple of days....</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Look, I am not saying any more than I have said. Don't, don't</p>
<p>   sort of hypothesize. I have indicated to you that if we can get</p>
<p>   Senate approval to the sale of Telstra then we have money to spend</p>
<p>   on certain things that we wouldn't otherwise have and we also</p>
<p>   retire debt. I have indicated that one of the things that we would</p>
<p>   spend it on is obviously communications in regional Australia because</p>
<p>   that's something that is high on our list and it's been</p>
<p>   high on our list for months and months and months. But as to the</p>
<p>   details of where we will spend that money, in what way, in what</p>
<p>   amounts, and on what things I have got nothing further to say this</p>
<p>   afternoon.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  How confident are you with those two Independent Senators'</p>
<p>   votes?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well as...Raphael, discussions continue. That's what I said</p>
<p>   in the lead-up to the Native Title outcome and I am not going to</p>
<p>   change and people can have their doorstops, they can say whatever</p>
<p>   they like but I am simply saying discussions continue. It's</p>
<p>   what happens out of those discussions that matters and I'll</p>
<p>   be measured not by the doorstops and the static along the way but</p>
<p>   I'll be measured by the outcome and we got a fantastic outcome</p>
<p>   for Australia out of Native Title. And I naturally want a good outcome</p>
<p>   on Telstra but we are having discussions, I am not making any lavish</p>
<p>   promises or asserting any claims. I am trying to get the legislation</p>
<p>   through the Senate because it will be good for Australia if it gets</p>
<p>   through the Senate, and the bush will get communications benefits</p>
<p>   it hasn't got a hope on earth of getting because there won't</p>
<p>   be the same amount of resources available. So it's in the interests</p>
<p>   of rural Australians that we get that extra money so we can spend</p>
<p>   it on things that rural Australians need.</p>
<p>  Thank you.</p>
<p>   [ENDS]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
