<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9234</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ KEATING MP INTERNATIONAL DAY OF FAMILIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/05/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009234.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
INTERNATIONAL DAY OF FAMILIES<br />
( embargo 12.01 am 15 May, 1994)<br />
International Day of Families is a day to reflect on what families do for all of us, and<br />
on how we might strengthen family life.<br />
Most families go through difficulties at some time or another. Illness or injury, trouble<br />
in balancing work and family responsibilities, any number of unexpected events can put<br />
families under strain. These days there is no greater cause of pressure and hardship<br />
than unemployment.<br />
In a good society those in need of help receive it. They are not left to fend for<br />
themselves, but are supported by their communities and governments. Throughout<br />
this International Year of the Family, Australian communities should take up the<br />
challenge which unemployment presents to us all. Because it has the capacity to cause<br />
a breakdown in family life, the effects of unemployment go beyond the damage done to<br />
individuals it strikes at the basic unit of our society and squanders our greatest<br />
national resource.<br />
The Australian people rightly expect their Government to devise programs which meet<br />
the needs of families in difficulty. They also expect that these programs will be tailored<br />
to the different needs which exist among various sorts of families. They must be<br />
programs which recognise diversity and change. In Australia we have devised a<br />
system of family payments which is equal to the best in the world. Our Medicare, child<br />
care and aged care services provide real support; and in part they do it because they<br />
also provide real choice.<br />
My Government's White Paper on Employment and Growth will play a major role in<br />
relieving some of the pressures on our families by creating opportunities for jobs and<br />
training and reforming the Social Security system in ways which will greatly assist<br />
families to balance domestic and work responsibilities.<br />
The White Paper requires more than an effort from Government it requires a national<br />
response. All Australians must recognise the threat that unemployment poses to our<br />
society and rise to meet the challenge. There can be no greater incentive than the need<br />
to defend our families against the stress of unemployment. </p>
<p>In the International Year of the Family the Australian Government is anxious to find<br />
ways to make life easier and more secure for families. That is why the National<br />
Council for the International Year of the Family, chaired by Professor Bettina Cass, is<br />
holding consultations around the country, seeking the opinions of communities, groups<br />
and individuals and advising the Government of their views. On the basis of the<br />
Council's investigations, at the end of the year, we will release a blueprint for future<br />
policies called the Australian Government Agenda for Families.<br />
There is much to celebrate today about Australian families, and much to thank them<br />
for. There is also much to resolve to do to build a healthy environment and strong<br />
foundations for family life, and to assist those families in need.<br />
We should remember also that the greatest responsibility for the health of our family<br />
life rests with Australian families themselves. In the end, families must recognise their<br />
essential role in the support and nurturing of new generations of Australians, and their<br />
responsibility to deliver the things which our children need.<br />
It is in families that our essential values and traditions lie. It is through families that<br />
they are passed from one generation to another. The quality of our lives and the<br />
strength of our community and nation depend to a large extent on families.<br />
May 1994<br />
Canberra </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
