<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>21988</transcript-id>
    <title>New Light Aeronautics Industry Cluster At Illawarra Regional Airport  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/10/2005</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I am very pleased to open the new Light Aeronautics Industry Cluster at the Illawarra Regional Airport.</p>
<p>The opening of this magnificent new facility will provide significant social and economic benefits for the Illawarra Region.  This facility has turned a previously under-utilised asset into a hub for economic growth in the region.</p>
<p>Five hangars will provide the region's first aeronautics business park attracting light aeronautics businesses to the region and increasing employment opportunities.</p>
<p>This project is an excellent example of government and community partnerships acting together to deliver local solutions.</p>
<p>The Australian Government is very pleased to have supported this project with $300,000 in funding from the Regional Partnerships Programme.  Through this Programme, the Australian Government is providing significant support to regional communities who want to strengthen growth and opportunities within their region.</p>
<p>Projects funded under the Regional Partnerships Programme have resulted in increased employment and business prosperity for regional Australia.</p>
<p>I acknowledge the initiative of Shellharbour City Council in developing the Industry Cluster, and I congratulate everyone involved in its planning, design, construction and operation.</p>
<p>I am also pleased to announce today Regional Partnerships Programme funding of $250,000 to the Historical Aircraft Restoration Society for the relocation and expansion of their commercial aircraft restoration business to the Illawarra Regional Airport.</p>
<p>The project will involve the construction of educational facilities, a retail outlet and a library, as well as providing the public with the opportunity to see the aircraft restoration work in progress.</p>
<p>In addition to creating new jobs in the region this project will be a major drawcard for tourism.</p>
<p>I congratulate the Society and its extensive network of supporters for their dedication and commitment.  </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
