<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9534</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J.KEATING, MP FORESTS POLICY</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/03/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009534.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINYISTER 27/<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING, MP<br />
FORESTS POLICY<br />
Cabinet met today to discuss the Government's strategy for the protection of<br />
Australia's native forests and the long term future of our forest industries.<br />
The management of Australia's forests is primarily a State responsibility.<br />
However the community looks to the Commonwealth for leadership in the<br />
protection of what are national assets treasured by all Australians.<br />
Cabinet agreed to implement a number of important measures which will<br />
ensure Australia has a system of reserves comprehensively representing all<br />
forest types, and at the same time a diverse, internationally competitive wood<br />
products industry.<br />
As a first step, I am releasing today a discussion paper detailing the<br />
Commonwealth's position for a future forest reserve system. The aim of the<br />
paper is to stimulate public comment on appropriate criteria for establishing<br />
the reserves. During the six week consultation phase, the Commonwealth<br />
will also be working with State and Territory governments to develop<br />
nationally agreed criteria for application in the development of forest<br />
agreements for all regions.<br />
With the cooperation of the States, the Commonwealth will use these criteria<br />
to undertake a preliminary reserve analysis to set aside areas pending<br />
completion of regional forest agreements. This will enable applications for<br />
1996 woodchip export licenses to be assessed on a regional, rather than<br />
coupe-by-coupe basis. Our strategy will also make sure that the<br />
Government's policy of protecting high conservation value forests in<br />
perpetuity will not be compromised while regional forest agreements are<br />
being developed, and industry will enjoy more certainty about the availability<br />
of resources.<br />
These regional forest agreements will identify areas for incorporation in a<br />
national reserve system that adequately and comprehensively represents all<br />
forest types, and areas which may be harvested on a strict basis of ecological<br />
sustainability. </p>
<p>The Government takes the view that the best policy for Australia is one which<br />
at once protects forever our unique and irreplaceable native forests, and<br />
develops and maintains a profitable and ecologically sustainable forest<br />
products industry based on re-growth forests, plantations and other fibre<br />
sources. The two ambitions are compatible and mutually re-inforcing. An<br />
ecologically sustainable forest products industry is consistent with our<br />
environmental ambitions, including that of reducing the degree to which<br />
ecologically unsustainable industries develop in other countries. The<br />
development of a model industry in Australia can be a tangible expression of<br />
thinking globally and acting locally.<br />
As an integral part of the overall strategy I am releasing an industry<br />
discussion paper and consultations will be undertaken over the next<br />
weeks, prior to its finalisation in the middle of the year.<br />
Central to the Government's position for the future of the industry is the need<br />
to turn around Australia's $ 1.8 billion trade deficit in forest products by<br />
encouraging greater downstream processing, more intensive plantation<br />
production, and international best-practice forest management.<br />
Relevant Commonwealth departments will be taking this opportunity to bring<br />
together labour market programs and industry programs aimed at improving<br />
the competitiveness of the wood products industry.<br />
We have also agreed to recommend to the Minister for Resources that he ask<br />
export woodchip companies to refrain from sourcing woodchips from 264<br />
coupes that Cabinet believes might be required for a future reserve system,<br />
and that were originally proposed by States for logging in 1995.<br />
1 will be asking the States to fully protect all these coupes, including the nonnational<br />
estate coupes we have set aside, pending finalisation of the regional<br />
forest agreements.<br />
The Government recognises that requesting companies to stay out of areas<br />
proposed by States for logging in 1995 will have consequences for the<br />
livelihoods of some forest workers. The Government will provide income<br />
support under existing programs for those workers. For any self-employed<br />
workers the Government will consider the payment of transitional assistance.<br />
Local CES offices will be active in ensuring that workers are aware of<br />
programs they are eligible to join, and other forms of assistance that are<br />
immediately available to them.<br />
The Government has developed a tailored package of assistance available<br />
immediately for self-employed workers, employees and their families affected<br />
by structural adjustment to the industry. The Forest Industries Special<br />
Assistance Package will provide individuals with access to training and </p>
<p>employment programs under Working Nation. including the National Training<br />
Wage, JobStart and JobSkills and assist with relocation and travel costs.<br />
These programs will be individually designed to address the training and<br />
employment needs of people affected by the decision and will assist them to<br />
find alternative employment opportunities as quickly as possible.<br />
In partnership with State and local government, industry, unions and<br />
communities, a range of projects will be identified in regions to provide<br />
employment opportunities in areas such as plantation and farm forestry and<br />
value-added forestry related industries. These projects will be initially<br />
facilitated through the Working Nation initiatives.<br />
CANBERRA MARCH 1995 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
