<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2774</transcript-id>
    <title>APPOINTMENT OF SPECIAL TRADE REPRESENTATIVE, MR G WARWICK SMITH</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/01/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002774.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
J<br />
P~ ES3 STATMIENT ITO. 36<br />
16 January 1973<br />
IAPOINTL121T OJF SPECIAL TPADE 2E-i7ETATIVE, MR.<br />
G. TARTICK SMITH<br />
The Prime Minister and Minister for Foreign Affairs,<br />
Mr. Wvhitlam, today announced the appointment of a Special Trade<br />
Representative to represent Australian interests in the forthcoming<br />
multi-late ral rae negotiations under the General Agreement on<br />
Tariff and Trade ( GATT).<br />
" These negotiations" said Mr. , Thitlam " are regarded by<br />
the Government as having a significant bearing not only on Australia's<br />
trading patterns but on the expansion and liberalisation of world<br />
trade in agricultural and industrial products.<br />
" A prime objective of the negotiations is a programme<br />
aimed at improving the living standards of the people of the world,<br />
and about 100 countries are expected to participate,<br />
" Preliminary meetings will be held over the next few months<br />
and the multi-lateral negotiations are expected to continue at least<br />
through 1974". The Government had appointed as Special Trade Representative<br />
Mr. G. ' Tarwick Smith formerly Secretary of the Department of the<br />
Interior who has had extensive experience in international trade<br />
negotiations. In his previous capacities as Deputy Secretary of<br />
the Department of Trade and Industry and Special Commercial<br />
Adviser in London, Mr. Varwich Smith had been directly associated<br />
at senior level with the operations of the GLTT and the complexities<br />
of multi-lateral trade negotiations, He would be located in Canberra<br />
whilst the preparatory work for the negotiations was being carried<br />
out, and would be based in Geneva for the actual negotiations,<br />
" There is" said IMr. Whitlam " a clear need for an experienced<br />
negotiator to put the Australian viewpoint at the highest level, In<br />
previous multi-lateral negotiations a number of countries found an<br />
appointment at this level materially assisted their negotiating<br />
position, I would expect the Australian decision to be welcomed<br />
by other participating countries as an indication of the importance<br />
we attach to the negotiations".<br />
C ITB 1,. g. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
