<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5882</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH IN RESPONSE TO THE WELCOME BY THE PREMIER OF CHINA</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/08/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005882.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
( H1K :' STTF CDE L.~ VLERY<br />
. i~) AUS H~ l I<br />
FORMIA WEDNESDAY AUGLU lS 19 82<br />
SPECH IN RSPONSE<br />
TO THiE WELCOME BY<br />
THE P1REMIER OF CIIINA<br />
T am very pleased to be here in China again to have the opportunity<br />
to get to know many of you personally. I am looking forward with<br />
great interest to exchanging views with Chinese leaders on a number<br />
of issues of common concern, and thus helping to strengthen the<br />
productive relationship which has been built up between our<br />
countries. At the base of a close relationship lies mutual understanding not<br />
just between Governments, but between peoples. Since my last<br />
visit here relations between our peoples nave strenqthened and<br />
laid the foundations of diverse and widening contacts. The<br />
Australian Government has embarked on a policy to encourage an<br />
active interes; t and knowledge of China, and in pursuit of that<br />
policy we established the Australia/ China Council after my last<br />
visit here.<br />
Australians have a very keen interest in China and its culture,<br />
and that interest is reflected in the attention .: ich China<br />
receives in our newspapers, on our television and in our education.<br />
It is also reflected in the large number of Australian tourists<br />
who visit your country each year and return with an enthusiasm<br />
which cuarantees that China will continuo to attraC: t. large<br />
numbers of Australians. We now have a sister relationship between<br />
Chinese provinces and A't ralian sta es and or plo ne<br />
participated together Hi nuwcroun nportin" and Zs eAl -vecnts.<br />
These personal contauL s lb Iuw on " ur peopl. c i -nr c h to<br />
brine our two countries tnU: the.<br />
This spirit of ca-opp r' n is ! watnwnq a n: a U fNatur of the<br />
Asia/ Pacific region. In recnt years our n : is in qeneral<br />
benefiteA from a deir-o no it in 1 stibi i. ch hs led<br />
to a growth in eccnowiu prspnrity nnt fanmd ii '' hqr parts of<br />
the w. or Ld. ] t is not I w thAt Ihi n prospered'c<br />
and continued to pr-sper in spit, of the K sion. The<br />
average growth rates fur ASiN cunwi fr drin the<br />
1970' s ranged from 3.4% to 6M a yar. </p>
<p>I have just come from Malaysia and have been impressed by what<br />
I have heard about the efforts of the ASEAN partners to work<br />
together more closely. Their determined and successful efforts<br />
to develop their economies and to pursue political cohesion, have<br />
done much to keep South East Asia largely free from the troubles<br />
which have characterised so many other parts of the globe.<br />
It is in the interests of both our countries that ASEAN be<br />
encouraged and that its cohesion be strengthened, for it has<br />
done a great deal to build up the resilience of South East Asia<br />
and to help bring security to the region. Next week I shall be<br />
attending a meeting of South Pacific leaders who will be<br />
looking for ways of enhancing co-operation to augment regional<br />
security and to promote mutual prosperity. That is another<br />
example of constructive co-operation in the region, co-operation<br />
which will help our region prosper politically and economically<br />
in a difficult and complex world.<br />
The last six years have brought many changes to the w'. orld and to<br />
our countries. In recent years you have made great efforts to<br />
modernise China's economy and to develop your economic ties with<br />
the outside world. That has led to a great expansion in<br />
Australia's trade with China which has been to the benefit of both<br />
China and Australia, and which has sown the seeds of greater<br />
co-operation between our two economies.<br />
Today there are many challenges before us. The world economy is<br />
going through a period of recession which has lasted longer and<br />
become more serious than anyone anticipated. It has had a<br />
detrimental impact on the development of nearly all countries,<br />
including China and Australia. Australia has had comparatively<br />
high economic growth in recent years but as a substantial trading<br />
nation, dependent largely on exports for our economic growth, we<br />
cannot escape the effects of the world recession. The situation<br />
has been worsened as countries have tried to insulate themselves,<br />
by increasing protectionist devices and export subsidies. Such<br />
measures are depressing the volume of world trade and together<br />
with falling commodity prices contributed to a fall in the value<br />
of world trade last year for the first time in over 20 years.<br />
In the case of Australia our agricultural exports to Europe, which<br />
were so important to us, have been decimated over the last decade<br />
by protection more generally, about 50 per cent of our exports are<br />
now subject to non-tariff barr irs. The Auust r l j, 1n Government<br />
believes thit to bre k oul.. f the. e-conomii c s-: il. ui i;: n in which<br />
negative influences i'ur: int y f upor tCr ' Lh'<br />
international communiL t' ntri t. i tike iit t n't ion to<br />
revive trade and resto:-o! c-cnom c a rowth.<br />
2I </p>
<p>It is in thiis contoxt that t he Aust ralIian Government has put<br />
forward proposals a helIp r eclnera tr qrowtn in world trade.<br />
These proposals call for a freeze on increases in trade<br />
protection, a progressive reduct: ion in levels of protection,<br />
and the abol iti on within five years of export subsidies and<br />
incentives. These proposals have been well recel veQ by a number<br />
of countries, and they are to ba di scusseud la ter this year by the<br />
GATT. To be effect ive, those proposaliis would have to be adop: tod<br />
by nat ions acting in concert. They wouldi call for a real.<br />
commitment of will, as few if any coauntries would find it easy to<br />
adopt every part of them. But we bel ieve that if they could be<br />
acted upon they would help return us all to the high growth<br />
rates in world trade which we experienced in the 1950s and 1960s,<br />
and which contributed signif icantly to the g~ rowth of living<br />
standards through those years.<br />
The Australian trade proposal was put to the Versaill as Summit<br />
two months ago. I believe the Summit could have given a stronger<br />
lead to help revive world trado, not necessarily by adopting<br />
the Australian proposals, but by at least takiny some concrete<br />
action. In Australia, we have made significant reductions i<br />
our own levels of protection, hut any further unilateral.<br />
reductions at this time which weren' t recip; rocatedA, woul 2.<br />
cause serious economi c and social dicl oca Lion in A\ us trali. 1<br />
There is all the d ifferencec in the woul1d between coon tries<br />
acting in concert, providi31ng incentives f: or eacn to concentrate<br />
on the things t he: do best and councries acun r niIa teral 2 v<br />
in these matters, giv. inr a ~ dvan tages to o thers whi ch are not<br />
reciproca ted. To iqnore this fundamental distinct. ion, as s; ome<br />
of my; Australian critics do, is to misjudg~ e the attitude ana<br />
poli cies of the Australian Government very 5; era ovn ~ i ndeed.<br />
These remarks are not, or course, in ary way a comment ary on the<br />
trade rel. ationship between Australia and China. I make them<br />
because T want the Australian G; ove-rnmenit's trade policies to be<br />
clearly understood.<br />
Nonbodly bou ld forget that Lhe count ries na rdetst hit by the world<br />
recessi~ on and trade protectLion have been noe avel1opi nq countries.<br />
Those count r: s nave a patticular i ntp~ re~ t inr the succqss of<br />
cons trutiot1vc tradoi proposals. A joint UrCT'APM/ AR study in 1972<br />
estimated t hat tnhe qinn' in nxporr " orn to duvo"' lpinq countries<br />
of reinovinq all barr jet: t" th'i It r iallrof 4-avde would<br />
be, in 191 dollca rs ' a iilon P to nusV34 b~ ilin Without those<br />
obstacles to their traip, d Wpi up cwt ri es cn V he much<br />
more aide to stand wN their own fw-an'd would] rruire much less<br />
arid, Austrailia believesc itis impurnfative vhat yaos be fundl t~ o<br />
help developing countio s hno: out of tb cro r p over ty and<br />
deprivation. Both of~ 9" ri countr: i' havae vi ni ppourt for the<br />
launch ing of g lobial~ nia&gt; u: i inn cn n inI ci a li aconomic<br />
development issues and so'fo it is ii ( I a;" ninq that those<br />
negotiat ions have nnh pracniecdc't. Thp wil ms b1 e creat ed to<br />
bring all count rins wqath( r t" hep fin soulut ions to Pconnmic<br />
development prrblemsru. </p>
<p>4<br />
That same wi1L seems to ho lacking i tiO context of the Law of<br />
the Sea Convention. TIho , Au stralian Gorv,. nment shar7es China's<br />
view that the failure so tar to get global agreement on a draft<br />
Law of the Sea Convention is most regrettable. if there is no<br />
progress towards a solution to the prob] ems of world poverty,<br />
and something as fundamental as the Law of the Sea, then it<br />
will be all the more difficult to create a stable world for<br />
ourselves and our children.<br />
The goal of world stability has continued to elude us. Armed<br />
conflict and disputes continue to erupt, often with littl. e<br />
warning. Who-would have predicted war between Iran and Iraq,<br />
or conflict in the South Atlantic? There are also continuing<br />
crises in Central America, Southern Africa and South-Fast Asia.<br />
The Soviet Union has pl. aved a part in exacerbating this<br />
instability. Its objective is expansion of its influence<br />
and the subjugation of sovereign peoples, and we are at<br />
one with China in opposing Soviet hegemony. In all the<br />
years since 1945, the Soviet Union has been determined<br />
to spread its influence. It has invaded Hungary and<br />
Czechoslovakia. Its troons are still in Afghanistan in<br />
large numbers. It has engineered pressure on Poland. It<br />
has given and continues to give massive support to the<br />
Vietnamese in their invasion of Cambodia. It has used and<br />
is still using the Cubans and East Germans to interfere<br />
in Africa and Central America. And it has interfere'd<br />
directly in the Yemen and Ethopia. That is a shaneful record.<br />
I have long admired China's determination and strength in<br />
opposing the expansion of Soviet power anO I have also been<br />
encouraged by the resolve of the United States under President<br />
Reagan to deal with the Soviet Union from a position of strength.<br />
It is only by dealing with the Soviet Union ith strength that we<br />
can counter it and a strong America is a prerequisite for world<br />
peace. I believe a good relationship between China and the United States<br />
is very important in preserving world peace, just as is a united<br />
and powerful Western alliance. There are times when, in order<br />
to achieve the objectives of world peace and the prevention of<br />
nuclear war, we all have to exhibit a degree of tolerance and<br />
understanding so we can work together in a conmon cause. In the<br />
case of our region, relations between China and Japan, and between<br />
China and the United St. ates are of very cqreat impnrtance.<br />
If international a : s. m ; t: i lity r i it 0-<br />
essential that all nations n hh r. t. o in'. rnti nal law<br />
and conduct based on Lhe i., inci.: les of<br />
respect for terrmtor, i-qjrity, and th; riqht. . f ;: n: nkin </p>
<p>5<br />
Mr Premier, in an unstable and complex world both our countries<br />
have set an example of how, despite our different cultures,<br />
political systems and approaches, countries can recognise<br />
their common interests and build close and valuable relations<br />
based on mutual understanding, mutual trust and mutual respect.<br />
It is in recognition of what we have achieved in the last<br />
decade that I propose a toast to Chairman Hu Yao Bang, to Your<br />
Excellency Premier Zhao Ziyang, to all distinguished guests here<br />
tonight, and to the further development of the relationship<br />
between our peoples. c </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
