<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10915</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                RSL WAR VETERANS&amp;#146; PARK, FRANKSTON, VICTORIA</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/06/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE..........................................................................................................................</p>
<p>Thank you very much Mr Campbell, and my friend and colleague Bruce</p>
<p> Billson, and ladies and gentlemen.</p>
<p>It's part of the delight of being Prime Minister of Australia</p>
<p> that you get numerous opportunities to go around the country and to</p>
<p> meet in a very informal, social atmosphere, different sections of</p>
<p> the Australian community. And I'm especially delighted to be</p>
<p> at this Veterans' Village this morning and just to say very directly</p>
<p> to all of you that no country can ever do enough for the men and women</p>
<p> of this country who put their lives on the line to defend it during</p>
<p> wartime.</p>
<p>And my Government, in company with other governments, have tried over</p>
<p> the years to do the right thing by the returned service men and women</p>
<p> of Australia. We have recently made a number of announcements extending</p>
<p> the Gold Card, extending the Seniors' Card which will be of great</p>
<p> benefit to veterans and to their families. And whenever I can I take</p>
<p> the opportunity, on behalf of the rest of the Australian community,</p>
<p> to express the gratitude of our nation to those men and women who</p>
<p> did so much in most cases so many years ago.</p>
<p>Recently I led a pilgrimage of returned service men and their families</p>
<p> to the notorious Hellfire Pass in Thailand and I opened the Hellfire</p>
<p> Pass Museum on Anzac Day to honour the sacrifice of those Australians</p>
<p> who died in such terrible circumstances, and also to honour those</p>
<p> who survived. Many of them were accompanied by their children and</p>
<p> their grandchildren, and it was a very experience, indeed it was one</p>
<p> of the most meaningful experiences of my Prime Ministership. And the</p>
<p> way in which the different generations of Australians, who had bothered</p>
<p> under their own steam and at their own expense, to travel to that</p>
<p> remote part of Thailand to pay their respects to those brave Australians</p>
<p> who did so much to give us the freedom and the way of life that we</p>
<p> have.</p>
<p>Thank you very much for having me here. It is not an occasion for</p>
<p> long speeches. It is an opportunity for me to have a cup of tea, to</p>
<p> chat to you, to express my admiration for the contribution that you</p>
<p> made to the country, to assure you of the continued understanding</p>
<p> and support of people in Government for those people who have done</p>
<p> so much, to thank the staff, to compliment the RSL, which is a great</p>
<p> organisation, on the role that it plays in caring for veterans here</p>
<p> in Victoria, and all around Australia. It is an ongoing responsibility</p>
<p> and one that the Government respects and supports and will continue</p>
<p> to support in the years ahead.</p>
<p>And could I just put in a plug, not excessively but in a very general</p>
<p> personal sense for Bruce. He is a hard working fellow, he really does</p>
<p> doggedly pursue Ministers on behalf of the people of his electorate</p>
<p> and that is what a local member should do. He looks after all of them,</p>
<p> whether they like him, whether they vote for him, or they don't</p>
<p> vote, that his responsibility.</p>
<p>But, ladies and gentlemen, again my thanks and it is very nice of</p>
<p> you to have me amongst you and I hope to have the opportunity over</p>
<p> a cup of tea of talking to you.</p>
<p>Thanks a lot.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
