<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4979</transcript-id>
    <title>REPORT OF THE STUDY GROUP ON STRUCTURAL ADJUSTMENT</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/03/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004979.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
J1~ LL~ 6<br />
T~~ V2 NiNA=~ 6 I LARC1I 1979<br />
OF THE STUDY GROUP ONSTRUCTURAL ADJUSTMET<br />
The ;--cudy Group, cnaired by Sir John Crawford, was set up to<br />
ex--amine and ad the Government on the adjustment problems<br />
of Australian manufacturing industries. Other members of the<br />
Study roup were Sir Brian Inglis ( Chairman of the Government's<br />
Akustralian Manufacturing Council, and Managing Director of<br />
Ford Australia) Mr. R. J. L. ( President, Australian<br />
Council of Trade Unions) and Mr. N. S. Currie ( Secretary,<br />
Departcment of Tr,_ L, 3-r-and Cormerce)<br />
I would like to place on record -the Govrernment's thanks to<br />
the mnembers of the Study Group, and particularly, to the<br />
Che rme. n.<br />
Thel Studv Groupis report represents a further contribution made<br />
by Sir J2ohn iLn the,-course of a long and distinguished career.<br />
* In JL-s preface, tb-e Study Group expresses its concorn that<br />
" ei: pectations about its report have been raised too high in<br />
As ? eoort rmal. es clear, the challenges fEacing Austral. ian<br />
ma-. 7r in 4i n21stry are great and there are no easy solutions.<br />
The er are necssarily to be found in a wide complex of<br />
poli: masurs. he Report, as rertuested in the terms of<br />
a7ed iessed it-s ef t-o these me asures.<br />
In vie-, of: the Report, low..-er population growth rates.,<br />
zz; . zo qiic a c hangqe, irizcort ccmpetition, changing patterns<br />
nd waecst-oressur's arc-all. part of<br />
L" r: e i e r zc u Ir in g t hese ie s ures.<br />
4-onr o te s tat In the earl 1970s, wa gosepcal<br />
thoS focr women, increased sharply, partly a s the result of<br />
hne I n-r0, 1u c tiJo n of ecjual pa], In 1973-74 alone, irinimun Faw-ard<br />
wacc-s incro-2ased by for fer-alesv and 27% 0 for males."<br />
In ad-. di-tion the ' Report Underlines th'e -fact -that " Government<br />
ac~ nhs ttmscon tribu red to the adijustment pressures on<br />
i n d u St The 25% acosTebadtariff cut in 1973, a-mTreciations<br />
of the-exchange rate in 1972 ar., d 193, an a scaling clown of<br />
the exlcr-incentive scrt: re in 11974 are imcportant exampics of<br />
such -aotns. * 1 i 1!<br />
F-0_ . ESS </p>
<p>-2-<br />
" However, more irecent Government actions ' nave been directed<br />
towards r-eCducing inflation and reducing exteornal pressures on<br />
the n-ardas-Press(-a imrort-compa tinq indiustries through<br />
limitIng irprts by quotas and teirporary increases in tariffs."<br />
" 7Iu:~ n3of t1h. L , australia'., Dollar since 1974 have also<br />
as3: e th motcme~ gid. tries as welas the export<br />
s CThe ezort mposes a series of positive measures to respond<br />
to tha= *: ha'Lenqaes, and opportunities face d by Australian manuf actu ring<br />
in acu-: e s The Governmitent believes that the analysis and<br />
recnmedaions contained -in the ' Re-oort wl be an important<br />
contribution to its consid eration of long-term policies to<br />
ass:* 7t industry -to adjust to a changing environment and to<br />
sound nc-1strial growth in the future.<br />
The Re-o ort also iorovides a focus for all interested parties<br />
in the-ir evaluation of future prospects for Australian<br />
industry. The Report endorses and cons iderably elaborates<br />
the need identified in the V. 1hite Paper on manufacturing<br />
industry for Australian industry to become more competitive<br />
both able better to compete with imports and to enter export<br />
m a ts<br />
The manuffacturing sector must be exoort-oriented if it is to<br />
use fully our resources and skills. The Australian market is<br />
see:-, v the _ Report_ as being too limited -for any other policy.<br />
The s: tudy Gro~ up is " in favour of the Governiment following<br />
policies that setth right climate for investment and growth",<br />
an,_ it has proposed an extended range of-: incentives as the<br />
prinipalmeans of encouraging industry to become more<br />
comzetitive and export-oriented.<br />
It_, is way, the~ eort believes growth rates in the sector<br />
can raised an---employment better sustained and expanded.<br />
of -the areas covered by the Report are matters to which<br />
the: overnrrent is giving continued attention: export development;<br />
ins: Kalresaronand development; investment incentives;<br />
pr: L:. rvemntand ind-ustrial f-inancing.<br />
rnment has already introducedl taxation concessions to<br />
ti: i75e at-; mae. significant imc'rovernents to export<br />
: ncrc:-asc1 or~ r~ ir. Juilt-rial<br />
deve,: lopm,, ent and instituted other prociramrmes<br />
icc to ' m&gt; arove productivity in ind: ust-ry. In addition,<br />
oar~ ccuzr ewhasis has bee--n given to increasing our efforts<br />
to secu: re oetter access to overseas artsfor : 7Australian<br />
gooe. a matter heavily emphasised in thze Report.<br />
7 77_ 777:::= </p>
<p>-3-<br />
The Crau; focd Study Group believes that further improveaments<br />
could be ma'de in tnhe ranr.-e of Programmes and has put forward<br />
a l--e body of recommendat ions. It seas the -need -for a<br />
" oost'.' e" Strazz-q to deaal with = ICIUsr.~ etpcln wa<br />
i t r m s an Iitndu s ir ial1 ad-a. 3ta t io n Polic v;<br />
-emet -1 h stratezay outlineea a nd: cvooDd i h<br />
r adua a: _-ust7. ent dfownw.-ar-s i'n th-e hiuhier<br />
f ustralian i-rotect ion lovels; an overseas trade<br />
dein s ecr makets for Aas tralian manufacturing<br />
, axpor: . anp-ower policles t1o help the -work-force to adjust to<br />
mos : ighy ppo ' uiesca; nd special o~ olicies for the<br />
n. -iglyprota _ cted industries, aimed at. easing the process<br />
oz utmn for them. Each of the Study Group's reco, mendations<br />
wil1 : De given , very careful consideration. Jany of them have<br />
Lar-i --, icni~ impi<br />
In anumber of cases, the Study Group's analysis of particular<br />
issues will, as -i recognises, be complemented by related<br />
studi-* es cortanissioned by the Government, such as: the Committee<br />
of lncui ry into Education and Training; the Inquiry into the<br />
process of Technological Change in Australian Industry; and<br />
the inquiry into the Australian ' Financial system.<br />
The Report will be a very valuable input to the Government's<br />
decision-making process. It is very iruch concerned with what<br />
the authors believe to be necessary and practical programmes.<br />
It 1lassist the overnment to ensure t-hat future zool icy<br />
Jecirsions will cont-ribut-e to the maxi-xum possible exten to<br />
achieving the Covernment's overall economiic and industry policy<br />
ob _ Je C Z Ive s t noving the competitive position of Australian<br />
indu'*--tr' and, to a_-ssisting the transfer of: resources to those<br />
col-'-t itive, ex-or . t-orientI-ed industries, w.. hich in the years<br />
ahead, must nrovide the bascis for a successfEul industry policy<br />
and en manulac-_ uring to play a much stronger role in the<br />
economy as a wah o.<br />
Sign--: : cant progress has been made in bringing down inflation<br />
anc-im. proving coetitive position of local indlustries.<br />
An,-7'? eport re-nises that " man ufa cturing is in a better<br />
t:: nio than it has been for some time1' 2". There is<br />
n~ ow a; zenc th itralian industries are increasi-. gly being<br />
e: xploit t opprtunities overseas, and' that our<br />
omct'~-~ position has generatred significant<br />
r ne in-vestimant in local -idustry.<br />
~ se nt th-at these gains be sustained and new opportunities<br />
actealysough if the economic growth which would facilte<br />
strcua adjustme. nt is to be reali sed.<br />
In via-, of the importance and breadth of the matters raised in<br />
the Stuldy Group's report, it is being tab led now so that it<br />
can be widely and intensively discussed and the community's<br />
response regist-eredI by the Governm,, ent. A~ special Comittee<br />
of IMinisters has been set up to co-orr~ nate the Gov. ernment's<br />
assessment-or the re commeanda tions. ThsCmitewl echaired<br />
by the Miitrfor Industry and Co= merce. </p>
<p>O~ h~ r ebe -11ii b~ iistr fho r Primary Industry,<br />
Educa-tion, incj-: t riai Rela-tions, the Treasurer, Employment<br />
and Youtlh Pfa~, Irod uctivity, 73usino. ss and Consumer Affairs,<br />
and S-.-ecial ri Rocorecsentat-ons.<br />
0000<br />
O IW </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
