<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>16373</transcript-id>
    <title>Address at the PM&#039;s XI Reception Parliament House, Canberra   </title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/01/2009</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Can I acknowledge the President of ACT Cricket, also James Southerland, CEO Cricket Australia. Heather Ridell, Acting High Commissioner of New Zealand. Where are you Heather? You're lurking here somewhere I know. There you are. I see you.</p>
<p>I see lurking in the distance the Deputy Prime Minister of Australia and I'll come to her in a minute. Ambassadors, High Commissioners, those from the diplomatic core who love and to support this great game of cricket.</p>
<p>Chief of the Defence Force, Air Chief Marshall Angus Houston. Where are you Angus? What's this got to do with the defence of Australia more to the point? Absolutely nothing is the answer to that. Mind you if I was you I'd be going to the cricket too.</p>
<p>And Andrew Barr, Minister for Sport in the ACT and can I acknowledge also members of the 1948 Invincibles. Arthur Morris, Neil Harvey and Sam Loxton. Every time I meet these guys I still sort of draw a deep breath at the thought of here I am dealing with members of the Immortals and their great contact with that great side of that great year and it is an honour to have you among us.</p>
<p>ACT cricket officials, members of the New Zealand team, great to have you here. Members of the Prime Minister's XI, even better to have you here. Umpires who've already been given their instructions by me, to be fair, impartial and Australian. Sponsors one and all. And of course the two captains of the two sides.</p>
<p>And I begin by acknowledging the First Australians on whose land we meet and whose cultures we celebrate as the oldest continuing cultures in human history.</p>
<p>It gives me great pleasure to welcome the New Zealand Cricket Team, the Prime Minister's XI, Cricket Australia and the ACT Cricket Community to Canberra once again for the Prime Minister's XI match.</p>
<p>The PM's XI has become one of the most notable days on the Australian cricketing calendar, and it's wonderful to see New Zealand here to take on this challenge for</p>
<p>the fourth time.</p>
<p>The history of this match, first taking place in 1951, serves to reflect Australia's great love of cricket  -  and often that of the cricket tragic of the Australian Prime Minister of the day. And of course 51 takes us back to the great days of Sir Robert Menzies.</p>
<p>For our New Zealand friends less familiar with the history of Sir Robert Menzies who was a long-serving post-war Prime Minister. Ming as he was affectionately known in Australia's great habit was to organise every official visit to the United Kingdom to take in an entire Ashes series.</p>
<p>These days if we're abroad for more than two or three days, the questions are raised as to what you're doing there. Menzies could get away with two or three months and no one would ask why. As he just appeared not just at the test game, not just the test matches, not just at Lords, but at most of the country games as well. We pine for an earlier and more civilised age. Alas it has passed us by.</p>
<p>However, despite the prominent role that we've grown accustomed in recent days, which is fixture there was a time when the game wasn't played for twenty seasons through to the early 1980s. Of course the Arch Deakin of its resurrection was none other than Bob Hawke, cricketer extraordinaire.</p>
<p>We all know that great shot of Bob himself playing cricket. Bob fancied himself as a cricket played of renown and that great shot of him having his glasses removed by fast delivery by members of the press gallery, which reflects their general contempt for the Office of Prime Minister.</p>
<p>One of the stands at Manuka, where we will be playing tomorrow, is named after Bob. And this is very appropriate, as he played no small part in reviving this great tradition.</p>
<p>In Hawkey's first effort overseeing the team in early 1984, a young stocky Tasmanian from Launceston by the name of David Clarence Boon put his name in lights and earned himself a test spot after scoring a run-a-ball 134 in all against the fearsome West Indies attack of that day. And so Boonie's career began.</p>
<p>David Boon would go on to amass 21 test centuries and 7,400 runs for his country in over 100 appearances in the baggy green and is one of its most proud custodians and of course a high celebration of Australian fashion and culture as well. Where's Boonie? Is he here? That's good, I've insulted him in his absence.</p>
<p>It was also the last time that we would be blessed with opportunity to see the great D K Lillee in an Australian XI, who picked up 2/21 leading the attack in a typically effective and economical display.</p>
<p>Australia went on to win that day, a rare victory against ‘the Windies' who were at the time very much at the peak of their powers.</p>
<p>Bob Hawke's Midas touch as a cricket selector I'm sure will surprise few, as has been his way in most areas of his most extraordinary life.</p>
<p>Over the years this match has retained that reputation as a curtain raiser for future stars, and also a most appropriate opportunity to recognise some of Australian cricket's most revered champions.</p>
<p>This year we are privileged to have Justin Langer captain the Australian side, honouring his commitment and enormous contribution to the game. Good on you Justin.</p>
<p>Few Australian cricketers have worn the baggy green with such pride and distinction as Justin. His test debut was a baptism of fire against other, another fearsome West Indian attack in 1993.</p>
<p>Until his retirement in 2007, Justin got every last ounce out of himself, compiling one of the most impressive test records in the modern era.</p>
<p>He played an extraordinary 105 Tests for Australia  -  14 against New Zealand  -  and formed one half of Australia's greatest ever opening partnership with Matthew Hayden. Who came from Queensland. I just thought I'd mention that. So do I.</p>
<p>With 23 test centuries and over 7,600 test runs, Justin's application, passion and dedication to the cause will go down in cricketing folk lore.</p>
<p>It was very appropriate that Justin retired from international, retirement from the international cricketing circuit occurred after Australia regained the Ashes with a five nil whitewash against the old enemy. That's what we describe in politics as social justice. That is a five nil whitewash of the Poms. Is the British High Commissioner here? That's good.</p>
<p>With Justin Langer, it was the team that always came first.</p>
<p>We are honoured that he will once again represent Australia and for the second time in his career, captain the Prime Minister's XI.</p>
<p>It is also great for us to welcome Daniel Vettori and all the Black Caps to our nation's capital before they tour the country in the Chappell/Haddlee series.</p>
<p>Our two countries have met at Manuka Oval on four occasions, with New Zealand claiming victory on all occasions, with the exception of the one match that was abandoned. That's very disturbing when you think about it. Isn't it Justin? No pressure mate.</p>
<p>As is always the case in our traditional trans-Tasman rivalry, New Zealand will do everything they can to knock us off, and ensure a tough game of cricket.</p>
<p>While I have no doubt that the Black Caps will prove formidable opponents, it is my sincere hope that the Australian XI will prove too strong tomorrow and take out their first win against New Zealand, and the first win in my Prime Ministership. Otherwise I'm in deep trouble too.</p>
<p>Finally, I wish to offer my appreciation to Cricket Australia and the ACT Cricket Association for their ongoing support and commitment to the PM's XI.</p>
<p>With your partnership and great dedication, I am sure that we will be enjoying this day of cricket for many years to come.</p>
<p>My very best wishes to both teams for a competitive game of cricket.</p>
<p>I'd also as I said in my earlier remarks, draw attention to the presence of the Deputy Prime Minister. A few things have changed this week, I today was due to be in New Delhi because we had an official visit planned to India and the Prime Minister of India, Prime Minister Singh unfortunately became ill so that visit was cancelled, hence why I am able to be with you.</p>
<p>Now the person who was ready to stand into the breach is, was the Deputy Prime Minister and about to be Acting Prime Minister Julia Gillard. And the look of panic on Julia's face as I explained to her, her responsibilities including the toss, active involvement in team selection and batting order and bowling order and in fact general advice [inaudible] game, was a look I shall always treasure.</p>
<p>So Julia, good to have you with us. I'm sorry that I'm here talking your place.</p>
<p>Can I say to all of you, those of our friends who've come across the Tasman and the members of the PM's XI that this is a great game, it's a great tradition in Australia and I'm glad that you are part of this continuing chapter of the Australian cricketing story.</p>
<p>I was with your Prime Minister yesterday in Port Moresby, John Key. And for those of you who have not seen the New Zealand Prime Minister in recent times, he's broken his arm in three places and I just assure the New Zealand team I had nothing to do with it.</p>
<p>He said to me to pass on to you his best wishes for the game and they are best wishes [inaudible] I am sure you will honour the great name of New Zealand in your feats on the field tomorrow.</p>
<p>Everyone is here because they love the game of cricket. And this is something that unites not just Australia and New Zealand but I've got to say countries and peoples across the world. Transcends racial divides, it transcends cultural divides, it transcends language divides and it is just a great celebration of life in itself.</p>
<p>And this small part of it, this great game and institution in Canberra each year, the Prime Minister's XI, I believe is one part of a much grander tale and that is the grand story of cricket itself.</p>
<p>Ladies and gentlemen thank you for being with us, let's celebrate the game tomorrow.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
