<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1174</transcript-id>
    <title>PM 77/1965 - COMMONWEALTH SECRETARIAT - APPOINTMENTS AS DEPUTY SECRETARY GENERAL </title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/10/1965</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001174.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>FOR PRESS P. M. No. 77/ 1965<br /><br />The Prime Minister today welcomed the statement made in London on behalf of Commonwealth Governments, announcing  the appointments of Mr. Amishadai Larson Adu of Ghana and Mr. Tillak Eranga Gooneratne of Ceylon to positions of Deputy Secretary-General in the Commonwealth Secretariat.</p>
<p>The Commonwealth Secretariat was established at the meeting of Commonwealth Prime Ministers in London last June.</p>
<p>The appointment of Mr. Arnold Si; ith of Canadaas<br />Secretary-General of the Commonwealth Secretariat was then<br />announced and Mr. Smith has since taken up duty at Marlborough<br />House in London the headquarters of the Secretariat. It was<br />envisaged that Governments would make appointments to the two<br />positions of Deputy Secretary-General provided on the Secretariat.<br />The position to which Mr. Adu is appointed will have<br />general responsibility for international relations and administration.</p>
<p>Mr. Gooneratne will deal with economic matters.<br />Mr. Adu is a former Secretary to Cabinet in Ghana<br />and former Head of the Ghana Civil Service. He is currently<br />Regional Representative of the United Nations Technical Assistance<br />Board and Director of Special Fund Programmes for East Africa.<br />Mr. Gooneratne has served in a number of capacities<br />in Ceylon's Civil Service dealing mainly with economic affairs.<br />He is at present Deputy Secretary to the Treasury in Cuylcn.<br />Sir Robert Menzies said both Mr. Adu and Mr.<br />Gooneratne were known as experienced officers, well qualified<br />for the positions they would occupy in the Commonwealth Secretariat.<br />Both would have Australia's full support in their work.</p>
<p><br />CANBERRA,<br />13th October, 1965.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
