<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3859</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S WEEKLY BROADCAST - THE NEW TAX SYSTEM - SUNDAY 24 AUGUSG 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/08/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Broadcast</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003859.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER'S WEEKLY BROADCAST ,3<br />
THE NEW TAX SYSTEM<br />
SUNDAY 24 AUGUST 1975<br />
THE PART OF THE BUDGET THAT NATURALLY INTERESTS<br />
US MOST AS TAXPAYERS IS THAT DEALING WITH INCOME TAX<br />
REFORM, THERE WAS SO MUCH OF IMPORTANCE IN BILL HAYDEN'S<br />
BUDGET LAST TUESDAY NIGHT THAT THE FULL SIGNIFICANCE<br />
OF THE TAX REFORMS MAY EASILY HAVE ESCAPED YOU,<br />
IT'S WORTH REFLECTING FOR A MOMENT ON JUST WHAT THESE<br />
CHANGES MEAN, I HAVE NO HESITATION IN SAYING THAT BY<br />
MEANS OF-THIS BUDGET WE HAVE BROUGHT ABOUT THE MOST<br />
SWEEPING REFORM OF-THE TAX SYSTEM EVER MADE.<br />
I HAVE NO DOUBT THAT TAX REFORM COULD PROVE ONE OF<br />
ThE REALLY AACEHAIET-' YEMENTS OF THE LABOR GOVERNMENT<br />
IN THE LCO'G RUN, AND FROM THE POINT OF VIEW OF JUSTICE<br />
AND FAIRNESS FOR THOSE MOST IN NEEDS PERHAPS EVEN MORE<br />
IMPORTANT 7-. AN iEDIBANK, 1,12 I<br />
.1 </p>
<p>2,<br />
PRACTICALLY EVERY TAXPAYER IN AUSTRALIA WILL<br />
BENEFIT FROM THE NEW SYSTEM. FAMILIES AT THE LOWER END<br />
OF THE INCOME SCALE WILL HAVE MOST TO GAIN, BUT EVEN HIGHLY<br />
PAID PEOPLE WILL BENEFIT AS WELL, THOSE WHO WORK HARDER TO<br />
EARN HIGHER SALARIES OR EXTRA OVERTIME WON'T BE PENALISED FOR<br />
THEIR EFFORT, THE MAJORITY OF AUSTRALIANS WILL PAY LESS TAX;<br />
HALF A MILLION AUSTRALIANS WILL PAY NO INCOME TAX AT ALL.<br />
MANY PEOPLE WON'T HAVE TO BOTHER ABOUT FILLING IN TAX<br />
RETURNS, AND FOR EVERYONE ELSE THE TAX RETURN WILL BE MUCH<br />
SIMPLER AND EASIER TO FILL. IN. THE WHOLE PROCESS WILL BE<br />
FAIR AND JUST TO EVERYONE,<br />
IF ALL THIS SOUNDS TOO GOOD TO BE TRUE, LET<br />
ME EXPLAIN JUST HOW WE HAVE TACKLED THIS PROBLEM AND HOW<br />
WE ARE SOL', : T T HE BASIC TROUBLE WITH THE TAX SYSTEM<br />
IS THIS: 1~ HAS BEEN SEARED MORE OR LESS TO CONDITIONS<br />
APPLYING 3 CR MORE YEARS AGO, IN 1950, SAY, A MAN EARNING<br />
SIX THOUSAD CtLLARS A YEAR 3000 POUNDS WAS VERY HIGHLY<br />
PAID; HE ~ 1 THE TOP INCOME BRACKET, THE TAX HE PAID THEN<br />
WAS APPROPRIATE = CR A HIGH INCOME EARNER, BUT TODAY OF COURSE,<br />
6000 DOLLARS PUTS A NAN IN THE TOP INCOME BRACKET;<br />
YET THE ' AN C'N THAT :. CCME IS STILL BEING TAXED AS IF HE WERE<br />
WEALTHY, . T: E .1 COE TAX SCALES JUST HAVEN'T BEEN ADJUSTED TO<br />
TAKE ACCOUNT THE CHANGE IN MONEY VALUES AND OTHER CIRCUMSTANCES.<br />
PEOPLE ON L3 CR MEDIUM INCOMES WHO WORKED HARDER TO EARN MORE<br />
MONEY FOUND : ICST OF THE EXTRA MONEY GOING IN TAX. / 3 </p>
<p>IT WAS THE SAME WITH REGULAR WAGE INCREASES THROUGH<br />
AWARDS ON BASIC WAGE ADJUSTMENFS, MOST OF THEM<br />
WENT IN TAX. IN FACT, IN ROUND FIGURES, EVERY ONE<br />
PER CENT INCREASE IN EARNINGS LED TO A TWO PER CENT<br />
INCREASE IN TAX RECEIPTS FOR THE GOVERNMENT, THIS<br />
WAS CONVENIENT FOR THE GOVERNMENT BUT IT WAS PRETTY<br />
TOUGH ON THE TAXPAYER, EVEN GOVERNMENTS THAT HAD FAR<br />
LESS NEED OF PUBLIC REVENUE THAN WE DO WERE REMARKABLY<br />
RELUCTANT TO CHANGE. THE SYSTEM,<br />
THE OLD SYSTEM HAS BEEN DREADFULLY UNFAIR IN<br />
ANOTHER W4AY, IT RELIED ON AN UNJUST SYSTEM OF<br />
CONCESSIONAL DEDUCTIONS, -I WONDER HOW MANY OF YOU,<br />
WHEN YOU .' EE CLAIMING YOUR SO-CALLED TAX CONCESSIONS<br />
T-E VERY SJ-G6ES3TS O PATRONISING THE SYSTEM WAS<br />
STOPPED TO T--INK THAT PEOPLE BETTER OFF THAN YOU WERE<br />
GETTING MUC--IGHER CONCESSIONS FOR THE SAME EXPENSE.<br />
PUT IT THIS WE ALL HAVE TO SPEND MONEY ON EDUCATION<br />
EXPENSES, PL? E~ NUAT. I: AND OTHER THINGS; UNTIL<br />
. ED3ANK., WE -AD TO SPEND MONEY ON HEALTH INSURANCE.<br />
SCME OF US ST-' 30 DEPENDING ON WHAT STATE WE LIVE. IN,<br />
BUT DEDUCT:' S FC? T. HESE EXPENSES UNDER THE OLD SYSTEM<br />
, WERE WORTH MORE TO THE WEALTHY MAN THAN PEOPLE ON<br />
LOWER INCOES. 3 QUITE LITERALLY, THE WEALTHY MAN WAS<br />
PAYING LESS FC-THE THINGS WE ALL NEED, I OFTEN QUOTE<br />
THE COMPARISGO BETWEEN ME AND MY CAR DRIVER. I EARN<br />
PERHAPS FIVE TIMES AS MUCH AS MY DRIVER; WE BOTH NEED<br />
INSURANCE AND WE HAVE BOTH HAD TO PAY EDUCATION EXPENSES<br />
FOR OUR CHILDREN, WHY SHOULD I PAY, IN EFFECT, MUCH LESS<br />
FOR THESE THINGS THAN MY DRIVER? / 4 </p>
<p>THE WHOLE SYSTEM WAS GROSSLY UNFAIR, THE<br />
WEALTHIER A MAN BECAME THE MORE HE WAS SUBSIDISED<br />
BY POORER Y-t R TAXPAYERS. THE WEALTHIER A MAN<br />
BECAME. THE ; KQRE HE WAS ABLE) AND THE MORE HE WAS LIKELY,<br />
TO SPEND MONEY ON BIG INSURANCE POLICIES OR EXPENSIVE<br />
EDUCATION FOR HIS CHILDREN, THE LIBERALS ACTUALLY<br />
ENCOURAGED THIS SYSTEM, THEY MADE A VIRTUE OF<br />
INCREASING THE ALLOWABLE CONCESSIONS, KNOWING THAT<br />
THE PEOPLE TO BENEFIT WOULD BE THE RICH, AND THAT<br />
POORER PEOPLE WOULD BE SUBSIDISING THEM, MR FRASER STILL<br />
MOUTHS SLOGANS ABOUT FREEDOM TO SPEND OUR MONEY AS WE WISH,<br />
OF COURSE WE SHOULD BE FREE TO SPEND OUR MONEY AS WE<br />
WISH1 BUT WHAT REAL FREEDOM DOES A MAN HAVE TO SPEND HIS<br />
MONEY WHEN A LOT OF IT HAS TO GO IN HEALTH, SUPERANNUATION,<br />
HIGH TRANSPORT CHARGES AND EDUCATION EXPENSES<br />
BECAUSE THE PU3LIC SERVICES PROVIDED IN THESE AREAS ARE<br />
POOR OR HON-EXISTENT? THE OLD TAX SYSTEM WAS DEVELOPED<br />
AND EXPANDED UNDER LIBERAL-COUNTRY PARTY GOVERNMENTS<br />
THOSE WERE THE DAYS WHEN YEARS OF NEGLECT BY THESE<br />
GOVERNMENTS ENSURED THAT DECENT HEALTH CARE AND EDUCATION<br />
WENT ONLY TO THOSE WHO COULD AFFORD IT, </p>
<p>OUR SYSTEM WILL BE COMPLETELY DIFFERENT<br />
AND MUCH SIMPLER AND FAIRER, YOU WILL DEDUCT YOUR<br />
UNION DUES AND YOUR INTEREST CHARGES FOR HOME LOANS<br />
FROM YOUR TOTAL INCOME ( AND I REMIND YOU THAT THOSE<br />
HOME LOAN DEDUCTIONS ARE ANOTHER INNOVATION BY THE<br />
LABOR GOVERNMENT)., THEN YOU DEDUCT FROM THE TAX<br />
PAYABLE ON YOUR INCOME A FLAT AMOUNT A REBATE FOR<br />
DEPENDENTS, EDUCATION, INSURANCE AND SO ON,. THE CRUCIAL<br />
POINT IS THAT EVERYBODY'S ALLOWANCE FOR DEPENDENTS AND<br />
EXPENSES WILL HAVE EXACTLY THE SAME-VALUE. THE<br />
DEDUCTIONS FOR A WEALTHY MAN WILL BE WORTH EXACTLY<br />
0 THE SAME AS THE DEDUCTIONS FOR ANYONE ELSE, IN THE<br />
STUDIES EDRTOOK ON THE OLD TAX SYSTEM WE FOUND<br />
THAT . OS~ TAXAY"' ERS WITH DEPENDENTS CLAIMED AROUND<br />
) 150IN . E: LCTIONS, 80 WE HAVE ADOPTED THE SIMPLE<br />
TACTIC OF GI: ING EVERYONE A REBATE EQUIVALENT TO THAT<br />
AVERAGE DEDUCT: ON, THIS MEANS THAT ONLY THOSE PEOPLE<br />
' HO ARE GOING CLAIM DEDUCTIONS WORTH MORE THAN<br />
$ 13550 WILL BE *. SKED TO FILL IN THE DETAILS ON THEIR<br />
TSA X FORMS. </p>
<p>I<br />
FOR YEARS THE LIBERALS KEPT PROMISING* TO<br />
REFORM THE TAX SYSTEM BUT THEY NEVER DID ANYTHING ABOUT<br />
1T, SiR ROBER-r MENZIES PROMISLED IT IN 194,9 AND<br />
AGAIN IN 1958. THREE WEEKS AGO EVEN MIR FRASER WAS<br />
PROMISING SOME KIND OF REFORM. ALL THE LIBERALS<br />
DID WAS INCREASE ALLOWABLE DEDUCTIONS AND MAKE THE<br />
SYSTEM MORE UNFAIR, IT HAS TAKEN A LABOR GOVERNMENT<br />
TO GET THE SYSTEM CHANGED, IN ONE SWEEP, WE ARE<br />
PUTTING AN EXTRA $ 5 A WEEK AND iNORE IN THE PAY<br />
PACKETS OF AROUND THREE MILLlo . jAL ISTRALIANS ON AVERAGE<br />
INCOMES; WE ARE ELIMINATING TAX ALTOGETHER FOR HALF.<br />
A MILLION AUSTRALIANS ON THE LONEST INCOMES; VIE ARE<br />
GIVING TAX RELIEF TO 100,000 loilli-JOWS AND UNMARRI ED<br />
S LIP? -: iG ' CN, AND Wc: ARE EAS I NG THE<br />
p 7I N G ' TAX 7=_ S ON ililDDLE-INCOME: EARNERS WHICH HAVE<br />
DISCOURAGED ARNING MORE. ' 4E HAVE SIMPLIFIED<br />
THIE ' vIHOLE Clu',' 3ERSCME BUSINESS OF FLLING IN<br />
CO, 1.1 D C A TE_ Di S COUNT IT A GREAT ACHIEVEMENT THAT<br />
IN BRI," IGING JDC". 4-N B U D GET TO TACKLE INFLATION WE HAVE<br />
TO R 5: = 0 D-t 1-H E TA X SYSTEM SO RIADICALLY<br />
NANAGED ND<br />
CR EAT E TH E CC11ND T-ONS FOR A F1A1% IRER AND MORLE JUST SOCIETY. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
