<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3339</transcript-id>
    <title>REVISED AUSTRALIAN VISA POLICY</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/08/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003339.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
1) UAI A. I L<br />
-PRIME MINISTER PRESS STATEMENT NO. 292<br />
1 August 1974<br />
REVISED AUSTRALIAN VISA POLICY<br />
The Australian Government has informed the Governments<br />
of the United Kingdom, Ireland, Canada, New Zealand and Fiji<br />
that it has decided to require all persons entering Australia<br />
for settlement or temporary stay to obtain visas.<br />
This will remove a long-standing discriminatory practice<br />
from Australia's immigration policy. For over 70 years European<br />
British subjects ( now Commonwealth citizens) and Irish citizens<br />
have been able to enter Australia without visa formalities,<br />
whereas non-European Commonwealth citizens from the same countries<br />
have been required to undergo visa formalities.<br />
This preferential treatment afforded European over<br />
non-European Commonwealth citizens is wholly inconsistent with<br />
the Australian Government's non-discriminatory immigration policy.<br />
From 1 January 1975 therefore Commonwealth citizens of European<br />
descent and Irish citizens coming to Australia for any period,<br />
whether for a visit or settlement, will be required to obtain<br />
visas just as non-European people and European aliens do.<br />
As well as removing a discriminatory practice from<br />
Australia's immigration policy, the visa requirement will provide<br />
a distinct strengthening of Australia's control of travellers.<br />
At present those exempted represent a significant proportion of<br />
people entering each year and come here without any form of prior<br />
checking as to health or character. It will also provide a manpower<br />
planning control which has been absent in the past.<br />
The only continuing exception to the visa requirement<br />
will be travellers already covered by the reciprocal arrangemfents<br />
existing between the New Zealand and Australian Governments. As<br />
agreed between the two'Governments, there will be continuing<br />
consultation between officers to review the operation of these<br />
arrangements. CANBERRA. A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
