<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>174</transcript-id>
    <title>SOUTH AFRICA COMMON MARKET AND FREE TRADE AREA</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/04/1960</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000174_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
South Africa<br />
Common Market and Free Trade Area<br />
! oomera<br />
Commonwealth defence<br />
South Africa<br />
3lue S3treak<br />
David iheppard<br />
8outh Africa<br />
Apartheid<br />
Riussian Submarines to Indonesia<br />
i,' ew Guinea<br />
Visit to Continent Paris<br />
K,, orean situation<br />
Red China<br />
VJisit to Queen<br />
South *-frica<br />
Summit </p>
<p>-F ThRhE MIISTERWS PRFS AND COMM'TENCE<br />
LOJUX) I; N QAtI.-h -Z12 l v q<br />
T IIITERVT2M,<br />
I. T. V. ~ e~ tion: Do you feel that there is any influence the Cotmnorwalth<br />
Prime hiistero can bxing to bear on the situation ini South Africa?<br />
. Answer: Well.$ I don' t know but I think the tal. ks the Co~ aunwoalth<br />
Prime hinisters will have with each o4; her and the represent'Uativ: e of' the<br />
Prime Ministor of. South Africa car-not fall to do som-e good because they<br />
will increase our knowleodge. They may have an efei-on both sides.<br />
I don't maan by that that I think there ought t o be talks in the fuill<br />
Confurence. % q never have g-one in for that kind of thing in the past<br />
and frankly I hope we won't in fut-ureo because the iiicment you get to thait<br />
you got to the point whero you bave resolutions and votes, and we have<br />
n,-vor had tho~ tu,<br />
Ruest-Jon Do you feel that thure ave any steps * that the Commaonwealth<br />
countriens can take which might have s-orwe tfect on this th-reateoning trade<br />
vwr in Europe between the Cunmon Mar'ket a: id tLae Pree Txdde Area?<br />
Answer: This problem of tha Seiren. and the Oix is muoth too comnplicated<br />
to l. end itself to the half minule flashy genor: alisation and<br />
I'm not goi;. rg to make cne.<br />
41Ll right, we'll 5skip that one,<br />
Qz3qsti Australia has a big G-ak9 in th1e Woomera Rocket Range. What<br />
effect will the abandonment of the Blue Str oak have?<br />
kn-wer: Wel, wre have every reason to believe that there wrill be<br />
a considerable amourit of work for it t o do and for a con-23zvable time to<br />
come, lf in fact it turns c~ ut thai; the appara~ tus could be used for<br />
purposes of space research thare might be no redaoing off ect on operations<br />
of -Woomera at all. It mightA be some increasing resu. 3, But you don't<br />
want to exag,; e'oate our trouble in this matter if there ie tro'uble.<br />
Our contribution to Womera h-i be( en E-u% at:_ ntli but Cveat s<br />
contribution has been a bigao: one, you know, and any losses in-volved in<br />
the change of direction the losses will primarily ihil on thiLs country.<br />
aU Lcstro: Are you happy about Cornmonwea2th defenca as long as we don't<br />
have a long range missile of ou-own?<br />
Answer:* Well. you are now asking me a question again which coulIdn't<br />
possibly be answered in under half an hour, Have we half an hour?<br />
You had better just write me down as being not unhappy.<br />
auestion: Coul. d I put it in another way do you think the Commonwealth<br />
oughat to have a long range missile?<br />
Answer: Now you are asking me a question -that relates almost entirely<br />
to the Govewnment of this Country and I thin~ k I've heard in qr trave. o~<br />
that there is gcxdng to be a debate. I am not in it.<br />
Thank you very much indeed, </p>
<p>2.<br />
B. B. C.<br />
Questicn: Mvr. 1ienzies, you are on record as saying that you<br />
belleve the South Afr-Ican situation is a doulestic one and not one for<br />
discussion by the ' Urnited Nations, but ' how do you feel about its be-Ing<br />
discusoecl at the forx6hclomling Prime k-Ami. ster' s Conferonnc:?<br />
I would hope that it was not discussged. as a set itmi in<br />
a fornial session of the Conrferernce, because if that were to occur there<br />
woul~ d inevitably be somn divisions of opinion and thoe wculd become<br />
mault. 9ro of notorietLy, port-aps w~ tt. ars reso'ui, n~ ~ hv<br />
never had votes in the Prime Miniates' Cofrne W area a wvoilder'<br />
fuJ. body. We have no rules, no votes, plent-ty of discussion, cut of<br />
it all there emorges a comm~ on accepted view about 8cme -; hing or thore<br />
doesn'~ t. and if thore. is no co~ on accepted view on a particaular probl. em<br />
t hen nothing is said pulicly what~ ever. But at the samae time lEin suve<br />
that other Prime Ministers like 4yrse. f are look-ing forviard to<br />
writh the reprenontative of South lfrica in.. d to becovia bettbar nord<br />
as to what goes on, It is ver easy to talk about thoix policy, vc. , y<br />
easy to be rather ill-informed about it. I have novux pvofessed to<br />
und ; tand oth-D~ paople Is policies frightfully well. I have all the<br />
viox-la' trouble in understanding my ow n. .1 want to learn, I want to<br />
understand, and if in a private vray I disagree writh someothing then I am<br />
able to say it in a private wray.<br />
_ Zi: es4-ion: Don't you feel that open discu~ ssion of tho situation at<br />
the Conference might give soire encourag~ montb to the Inoe modera-te elements<br />
amongst the South African Governmnt supporters?<br />
Answer: Nothingr could persuade me this ought to be listed for<br />
discussion in forffl s,. ssion of this Primne I, 1i. iirtersj' Conference. I can<br />
see nothing but harm coruing from it.<br />
Q-uesion: Do you thlink if it wore listod for aiscuasion it could<br />
result in Suth Africa leaving the Coivannv-althi?<br />
Anower: That 1.9 of course a purely specdLative matter but there<br />
are some things whl-ich if they are allowed to haippon in the formal<br />
proceedings of the Prime hinisters' Conforenoe rroy -Iexmphasiso mty<br />
have a damaging effect on the whole s-; ruct ture.<br />
.&amp; eiio: One of the leading Nationa. 42' papers in South Aftri. a<br />
envisages a situation wiherevby Sou~ h Afica could become wh1at thoy call tho<br />
Polecat &amp; t the waKia. Wouild wie necessarily i-nt a PdLeoat ixi the Coimamonwealth<br />
house? Idon't think that is a questVion that I ought to be askedL<br />
to answer' because of course that assumes something about pdLecats, doesn't<br />
it? I1 have no c ament.<br />
_ Qae s t Icn: To change the subject, sir, how do you feel about the<br />
abandonment of the rocket Blue Streak?<br />
An Well., the a-: ime 11inister was good enough to send out to<br />
us the First Sea Lord so that ive might be put in possession of all<br />
technical and military considerations whiich had led them to their conclusions,<br />
We found nothing which we could object to in those conclusions,<br />
and that being so those conclusions ought to be put into effect.<br />
Thank you very muoh, 8sir. </p>
<p>3.<br />
THE PRESS<br />
,. estii, o n: Prime Minister, could you tell us what you think of<br />
David Sheppard's decision not to play against the South Africans?<br />
Answer: I regret it.<br />
Qlestion: Can you re-state for us Australia's attitude to the<br />
South African situation?<br />
Answer: The attitude of the Australian Government was stated by<br />
me on two occasions in the House of Representatives, and what I said<br />
amounts to this, We regard the problem of the racial policies existing<br />
in South Africa as matters of domestic jurisdiction. We regard them as<br />
not being within the jurisdiction of the United Nations by reason of the<br />
Domestic Jurisdiction Clause. We think also, apart altogether from the<br />
Charter of the United Nations, that it is a very sound rule of foreii<br />
policy not to seek to interfere in the domestic political problems of<br />
another country, That has been our attitude and that remains our<br />
attitude. As I have said, that doesn't at all exclude the possibility<br />
of private or semi-private discussions between the Prime Minister of<br />
South Africa or his representative and myself and hr. Nash and Mr. Macmillan<br />
and whoever else wants to have discussions. I want to have them,<br />
I am very anxious to know more than I know now. I seem to be in a bit<br />
of a minority. Most people seem to think they knov all about what goes<br />
on in South Africa. Not a dark shadow of doubt in their minds at all.<br />
But I don't belong to that happy band. I would like to have an oppartunity<br />
of discussing their policies but, as you know, not as a matter<br />
of formality. People ought to remember that there have been previous<br />
occasions when suggestions were made that a particular topic that involved<br />
a Cormonwealth country or countries ought -o be listed. Kashmir was<br />
one but it wasn't listed. That was a problem which was producing<br />
tension between two great members of the Commonwealth. It was never<br />
listc:. l It was discussed privately. And if a matter of that kind,<br />
with all its possibilities and involving as it did flatly different<br />
views on the part of two identified nations, if that were not to be listed,<br />
how does it come about that we list for discussion a matter which affects<br />
South Africans in South Africa but whiuh after all we think is their<br />
business. Question: I was just going to ask you, Ir, henzies, if you can say<br />
that you personally dislike Apartheid?<br />
Answer: I have made it clear in Parliament, and I am sorry that<br />
I have to make it clear here, when I speak publicly I speak as Prime<br />
Minister and on behalf of the C-overnment and therefore I don't permit<br />
myself the luxury of private views.<br />
Question: There was a statement made today, hr, Menzies, that Russia<br />
has supplied submarines to Indonesia with trained crews. Have you<br />
had any confirmation that this is true, and have you had any concern<br />
over it?<br />
Answar: I have had no canfirmation of that at all.<br />
But it is<br />
Oh well, if you had a brother, would he like cheese? That is too<br />
hypothetical far me.<br />
f </p>
<p>Question: ir. Menzies, a question on New Guinea. The Dutch are<br />
now talking in terms of offering self-determination to New Guinea in<br />
something like ten years. Does this speeding up of New Guinea's<br />
political development surprise you?<br />
Answer: I have no official confirmation of the proposition you<br />
have just referred to. I know that there has been an idea floating<br />
around. We think it is impossible to state a timetable on these<br />
matters. We think that the test ill be i. n the long run what stage<br />
of development have the people reached. That is the thing that determin<br />
the question of self-determination on their part. I don't think<br />
one ought to assume that the Dutch have really vitten down a specific<br />
timetable. I have read about it in the Press but that doesn't pr-ove<br />
much. It was announced in the House...<br />
Well, I wasn't there, I didn't hear it. Anyhow Mir. Hasluck is coming<br />
ovur here and no doubt he will have smne talks with them.<br />
Question: Have you any plans for going to The Hague on this visit?<br />
Answer: No,<br />
Question: What visits will you be making on the Continent, ir. enzios?<br />
Answer: I doubt whether I will make any. It looks as if Paris<br />
might be a bit crowded after we finish our Conference here. No, I have<br />
no plans for going to the Continent. I have just come from Geneva.<br />
Cuestion: Miay I take it from that, Mx. henzies, that you will not be<br />
going to Paris as certain suggestions have been made that you would go to<br />
Paris? Answer: Really' Well I didn't know about them. I haven't noticed<br />
any of the big shots making them.<br />
Question: ir. Menzies, hr. } acmillan has said that the winds of change<br />
are blowing through South Africa. How do you see the future in South<br />
Africa? Answer: I make no comment on that. I wvill be much better informed<br />
on that matter when I have had an opportunity of talks with the representative<br />
of South Africa at this Conference.<br />
Question: hr. Menzies, what do you feel about the Korean situation?<br />
inswer: I suppose it might be permitted for me to say that I am<br />
not surprised full stop. Whore's mny adviser on External Affairs? I think<br />
that's permissible, don't you, hiick?<br />
Question: iKr. 1henzies, what is your policy with regard to recognising<br />
Red China?<br />
Answer: We don't recognise Red China.<br />
Do you intend to in the near future?<br />
® 1 Question: </p>
<p>Answr: I know of no prospect of that policy being changed. It is<br />
elementary, of course. I can say that now but somebody else may have<br />
different views in future. But we hve nothing before us to suggest<br />
any change in the present policy,<br />
Qu9stion: Sir, is a visit to the Queen before the Wedding on the 6th<br />
listed in your programme?<br />
Answer: I don't know. I know that I am down to have an audience with<br />
her some day. I think it is quite early in the Conference, isn't it?<br />
But whether it is before or after the Wedding does that nmtter very much?<br />
Is that very important? What point are you going to make of it? It<br />
will have all the time and novelty to me whoAn you make it.<br />
Question: Returning to Africa, sir do you see the South . fx-ican<br />
situation causing a Commonwealth split? With the coloured nations being<br />
separated from the white?<br />
Answer: Look, I am not going to say any more on that subject because<br />
un t!. hing that anybcdy sayson that at this time is not very helpful to the<br />
Conmmnwealth. Lets get together, and let us have this great oppcrtunity<br />
for meeting each other, directly and personally.<br />
Question: Have you anything to say, sir, on the prospects of a Summit<br />
success?<br />
Answer: No, nothing to say on that.<br />
Question: Mr. Nash was quoted in Moscow ycsterday as saying that he was<br />
sure that 1Mr, KCrschev wanted peaceful co-existence and disarmament.<br />
Ansvwer: Well, if he turns out to be right, this Conference has a wonderful<br />
opportuiity of being productive.<br />
Question: Are you able to discuss any subjects which you yourself will<br />
raise at the Prime Ministers' Conference?<br />
Answe: No, I am not very talkative about these things before they<br />
happen. Well, we are trying hard.<br />
I know.<br />
Quest ion" How long are you here for?<br />
Answe: Three or four weeks, I think. I have to go and do a lecture<br />
at Cambridge.<br />
Question: On what?<br />
Answer: On the changing Commonwealth.<br />
Question: Will you fit in some cricket then?<br />
Answer: No. I would like to see them once but I don't know whether<br />
T will be able. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
