<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>20662</transcript-id>
    <title>Doorstop Interview - Blair House, Washington  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/02/2003</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, is the looming war on Iraq shaping your thinking re your possible retirement?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look there's only one thing on my mind at the moment, and please just understand that, and that is to do the right thing by Australia in this very difficult international situation. It's the only thing on my mind and I just don't intend to get diverted from that.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>You're pledging to see it through if there is military conflict. Do you anticipate a drawn out war or something that would be over relatively....?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I'm still hoping that we don't have military conflict and the best way to avoid military conflict is for the entire international community to send a single unambiguous message to Iraq. There's not a strong hope that Iraq will take notice of it but the likelihood of Iraq taking notice will be the greater if everybody is saying the same thing and that is why we very strongly support trying to get a second resolution.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What did you mean when you said you'd see it through?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I meant Laurie that any suggestion of walking away from my responsibilities during a time like this would be, you know, quite out of the question that's what I meant and that's what I said and that's what I repeat.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, you'll be around until Saddam is dealt with one way or another, is that what you're saying?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Jim I don't think it's appropriate to create an issue about my future in the context of this very difficult thing. What I've said is that we have a very difficult international situation and any suggestion while that is working its way through of my having thoughts on my mind about my future or doing anything about my future is absolutely out of the question.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, what will be your fundamental message to President Bush about conflict and the potential for war?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well my message to him will be that Australia would like every effort made to get a second resolution. We very strongly share the concern of the United States and the United Kingdom and other countries that the world does face the horrific possibility that chemical, biological and nuclear weapons in the hands of rogue states like Iraq and others joined with international terrorism would create a real nightmare and that is the twin evil of the modern world and it is something that has to be dealt with.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Does dealing with Saddam Hussein now involve regime change for Australia?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Our position on regime change is that if it happened as a consequence of any action that might be taken then so be it but our objective is disarmament and the reason why this issue is important to Australia is that I don't want Australia to live in a world where weapons of mass destruction in the hands of rogue states could marry international terrorism and you to have the most lethal of all cocktails.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Is the aim of disarmament regardless of a second resolution at the United Nations?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I think what we should state is the policy goal and that is disarmament. Everybody's in favour of that. Mr Crean back in Australia is as in favour of that as well as I am. We think it can best be achieved through mobilising the maximum number of countries in saying the same thing. The reason why I believe a second resolution would be a good thing is not as a matter of international law, it's not necessary as a matter of international law, but it would bring forth the greatest level of support and commitment and involvement.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do you believe that you and Australia can make a difference this week with these talks?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I think it's always a mistake to discount the capacity of this country as a very close ally of the United States and also of course a close ally of the United Kingdom, to have an influence on the way issues are handled. I mean we don't want to exaggerate it but equally we don't want to be shrinking violets about our capacity to have an influence and I think it's also important that I'm going to have the opportunity on this trip of going to Indonesia and talking to President Megawatti.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[inaudible] United States went on a higher level of alert on the basis of what was described as new intelligence. Have yet been briefed about that and does it have any implications that you can talk about in relation to the level of alert at home in Australia?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well we've been on a high alert since the 11th of September. I mean obviously the whole security situation has changed as a result of that. And then there was further concern after the tragedy in Bali, and there was that general alert that was referred to in November of last year. We haven't any cause to alter the current castings of alert if I can put it that way. We don't have any additional specific information suggesting that there is going to be any attack affecting directly Australian interests or Australians. But obviously we're living in a very difficult situation and I've said time without number over the last year or more that we're all vulnerable and nobody can assume they are immune from terrorist attacks.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, what do you want a second resolution to say?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I want at this stage I think I want one that gives full authority to enforce the conditions of resolution 1441. But that's stating it very generically at this stage and I think what we want is the whole world saying the same thing. I think there has been a very significant change in the opinion of a number of countries as a result both of Dr Blix's report and also the very polished and effective presentation of the Secretary of State. I think that was a very compelling presentation and my assessment is that it would have had quite an impact not only on other countries but also on opinion in Australia.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Is it your assessment that the United States is now coming around to the idea of a second resolution, that 1441 won't suffice?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well President Bush said he would support a second resolution. Obviously they're not going to support any second resolution but that's a matter for them. I mean from our point of view as I stated in my address to Parliament last week we want a second resolution because it will mobilise the maximum level of support and commitment in any military action if that becomes necessary. But can I just finish which I will with this question where I began - the prospects of a peaceful resolution don't look good at present but if there is to be a peaceful resolution it will in my view only occur if the whole world says the same thing to Iraq. The maximum pressure must be exerted on Iraq because that is the only language she's demonstrated in the past she understands and in those circumstances there's every reason to work very hard to get an unambiguous expression of opinion through the Security Council. Thank you.</p>
<p>[Ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
