<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7978</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/03/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007978.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>' I<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA 20 MARCH 1990<br />
LAUOAI afUN n LAW 4WUBHTDI CE SIT6TIVTYVR<br />
My Government's commitment to law reform, law enforcement<br />
and the effective administration of justice in borne out by<br />
our record, we have made major reforms in areas as diverso<br />
as corporate regulation, human rights and privacy, the<br />
attack on organised crime, family law and services and the<br />
infrastructure and operation of the Federal court system,<br />
LAbor's fourth ter initiatives will therefore build on thi<br />
substantial steps wn have already taken.<br />
rrimiAl Ammet TruIt F, nd<br />
I am pleased to announce today that, in its fourth term, the<br />
Government will establish a statutory Criminal Asset Trust<br />
Fund to turn the procead. of crime back againat the<br />
criminal. Labor's Proceeds of Crime Act of 1987 has denied criminals<br />
the benefit of 01 million so far recovered by the Crown, and<br />
an additional 01.7 million has been recovered under the drug<br />
trafficking provision of the Customs Act. A further<br />
030 million in currently frozen pending prosecution.<br />
The new Criminal Asset Trust Fund will establish a pool into<br />
which will be paid all those funds which are forfeited under<br />
the Proceeds of Crime Act or the drug trafficking provisions<br />
of the Customs Act.<br />
Forfeited property, vehicles and other assets will generally<br />
be oqld and the proceeds placed in the Trust Fund. In some<br />
case however, seized equipment may be of direct use to law<br />
enforcement agencies.<br />
The Government has decided that the monies held in the Trust<br />
Fund will be distributed fifty percent to law enforcement<br />
agencies and fifty percent to programs for the<br />
rehabilitation of drug users. Thus, the proceeds obtained<br />
by drug traffickers will be directly applied to programs to<br />
assist those who have suffered as a result of drug usage.<br />
1 1* </p>
<p>The urse of criminals' asset@ in this way will provide a<br />
direct and substantial ñ nra-Aa in funds available for law<br />
enforcement and drug rehabilitati~ on. The existence of the<br />
Trust Fund, an payments made out of it, will not af feot the<br />
regular funding, through the budget, of relevant bodies.<br />
Because it is not possible to predict with certainty the<br />
timing of completion of legal proceedings and the success of<br />
prosecution., precise sums available each year f or<br />
disbursement from the Trust Fund cannot be set in advance.<br />
It is expected, however, that they will average several<br />
million dollars per annum and an initial estimate has been<br />
made in the costing of this initiative of $ g million over<br />
3 years.<br />
Altarngt~ ya Dinputa Raun1ntnn<br />
In its fourth terma, the Government will also legislate to<br />
expand alternatives to court proceedings an a mean. of<br />
reaolving disputes.<br />
It is essential that the judicial system be as efficient as<br />
possible while maintaining the capacity properly to resolve<br />
disputes. The use of such processes as mediation and<br />
arbitration can help achieve this aim. The Government<br />
actively encourages commercial disputes to which it is a<br />
party being resolved In this way.<br />
Within the Family Court we have already encouraged<br />
resolution of disputes without reference of cases to judges.<br />
The use of counsellors and court staff to ansint parties to<br />
reach agreement has ensured that the vast majority 0f cases<br />
are resolved without the need for a formal hearing.<br />
Within the Federal Court initiatives have also been taken<br />
using pro-trial conferences to resolve commercial dispute.<br />
in a way which reduces the demand on court time and provides<br />
a faster result for the parties.<br />
For the most part, however, these* processes are informal.<br />
The fourth term legislation will provide a statutory<br />
framework within which the Federal and Family Courts can, by<br />
the use of court rules, establish dispute resolution<br />
processes. If alternatives such so mediation and<br />
arbilration are to be used the Court rules need to deal with<br />
such tssues ast<br />
time limits to lodge documents<br />
basic procedures<br />
privilege for persons taking part in the proceedings<br />
recognition and enforcement of orders<br />
fees and costs. </p>
<p>The courts will be given flexibility to design procedures to<br />
best meet the needs of particular jurisdictions and to<br />
encourage the portion to opt for these alternatives and to<br />
accept the result of the process.<br />
Parties who wish to have their dispute resolved by a audge<br />
will not, however, be prevented from doing no.<br />
01tbay Pf~ riIrJJJ<br />
My Government has put in place a new Commonwealth law to<br />
govern the whole of corporate Australia under one low and<br />
one administration, the Australian Securities Commission.<br />
The next Labor Government will press ahead with implementing<br />
a truly national system of corporate law.<br />
Other priorities for the next Government in the area of law<br />
and justice will flow from reviews underway into legal aid<br />
and the reamily Court.<br />
The National Legal Aid Advisory Committee will shortly be<br />
reporting to the Government on legal aid policis and<br />
services. This report, coupled with the continuing efforts<br />
of the Government to make sure that all Auatralians have<br />
fair and effective access to the legal system, will provide<br />
the blueprint for legal aid in the 1990a and beyond.<br />
A major review of the Family Court is being undertaken by<br />
the government to ensure that its structure is best suited<br />
to meeting the needs of the community and, in its fourth<br />
term, the Government will respond promptly to the<br />
reooimendtions of that review. This follows on the<br />
substaxitial reforms already made by the Government in the<br />
field of family law.<br />
16c </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
