<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10207</transcript-id>
    <title>EMBARGOED UNTIL 6.00AM, 1 JANUARY 1997 THE YEAR AHEAD</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>31/12/1996</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010207.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
p a<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
Embarzoed until 6. O0am. 1 January 1997<br />
THE YEAR AHEAD<br />
Australians have every reason to look forward to 1997 with hope and<br />
confidence.<br />
The ftundamentals of our economy are strong. Very low inflation, lower<br />
interest rates, more flexible labour market conditions and substantial<br />
progress in cutting the budget deficit, a bode well for strong business<br />
investment and greater consumer confidence.<br />
Relatively strong growth in the major economies of the world will be<br />
positive for the Australian economy in 1997.<br />
From today, new tax benefits worth $ 1 billion will be delivered to low and<br />
middle-income Australian families with children. These benefits Will<br />
enhance the child care choices of parents and give particular assistance to<br />
one income families thus addressig some of the current bias in the tax<br />
system against such families.<br />
Although much has been achieved in recent months the task of economic<br />
reform is far from finished.<br />
Supply side impediments to a more competitive economy, in areas such as<br />
the waterfront, must be addressed.<br />
More steps must be taken to lift the burden of red tape from small<br />
businesses which, now freed of the stultifying effects of the old unfair<br />
dismissal rules and antiquated industrial relations laws, still offer the best<br />
hope of progress on the jobs front.<br />
2732 </p>
<p>4 N<br />
ow that the saleoffo ne-thirdoffT estra has been authorised byP<br />
arliament, 1997 will see reality giventoo the Natural Heritage Trust ofA<br />
ustralia. From it willbeef unded the greatest ever capitali nvestment int<br />
the renewaloffA ustralia's environmental assets. T<br />
his will representannh istoric programme well intothe 2 1s t centuy ofr<br />
eclaiming Australia's environmentalh eritage for ftuture generations. T<br />
here aremaajo r challenges aheadonnt he native title front. Inn the wake oft<br />
he Wik decision, which altered oneofft he basic tenetsoffp revioust<br />
thinkingo nnative title, responses are required which deliver bothp<br />
redictability and justicetoo all concerned. T<br />
he responsibilityoffd elivering such a balanced and fair outcome does notr<br />
est with governments alone. A<br />
sA ustralians approach the New Year, weea re entitledtoo doo soow ith aq<br />
uietp ride thatweel iveinna nation whichissu nsurpassed whenittc omes tof<br />
freedom, stability and tolerance. W<br />
e still have many blemishes. Someoffo ur fellow Australians remainp<br />
rofoundly underprivileged livinginn orra ttheedgeoffp overty. Theyc<br />
continuetoo need our compassion and help. I<br />
fweec an keep that balance prideinn whatweeh avea chieved yetd<br />
eterminedtoo address our shortcomings, 1997 willbeea very good year forA<br />
ustralia. M<br />
y wife and childrenjoinmee inn wishing all Australiansa v ery happy NewY<br />
ear. 3<br />
31 December 19962 2733 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
