<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8652</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP UNITED STATES EXPORT ENHANCEMENT PROGRAM</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/09/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008652.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL I97/ 92<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP'<br />
UNITED STATES EXPORT ENHANCEMENT PROGRAM<br />
Set out below are the texts of an exchange of correspondence<br />
between President Bush and me on the recently announced<br />
expansion of the US Export Enhancement Program.<br />
Letter from President Bush dated 4 September 1992<br />
" I know that you are concerned about the new multi-country<br />
Export Enhancement Program ( EEP) initiative that I just<br />
announced. This initiative, however, does not represent a<br />
fundamental change in the program. We are Continuing to<br />
take into account Australia's interests as a nonsubsidizing<br />
exporter. The initiative was constructed as carefully as<br />
possible to allow room for Australian sales.<br />
" In announcing the multi-country package, I made a point of<br />
emphasizing that it was aimed at countries which subsidize<br />
wheat exports and not at those, such as Australia, which do<br />
not. believe that the EC must be challenged directly on<br />
this unfair trading practice. Our farmers are hurting, as I<br />
suspect yours are too. I agree with you that a successful<br />
conclusion of the Uruguay Round is of critical importance<br />
for advancing global trade liberalization. I remain firmly<br />
committed to reaching agreement on outstanding issues before<br />
the end of the year. my G-7 colleagues agreed on this in<br />
Munich, and I am working hard to ensure we deliver on this<br />
commiitment. " I value highly Australia's close cooperation on the GATT<br />
negotiations. I hope that we can continue to work together,<br />
notwithstanding any differences we may have on the EEP<br />
issue." Sep .92 14 oU4 Nu UUO I-U I 7VZ </p>
<p>TEL 2<br />
Mly response to President Bush dated 8 September 1992<br />
" Thank you for your personal message offering your<br />
perspective on your recent announcement on the Export<br />
Enhancement Program.<br />
" I appreciate your assurance that you remain firmly<br />
committed to reaching agreement on outstanding issues in the<br />
Uruguay Round negotiations before the end of the year. In<br />
this you can count on Australia's continuing close<br />
cooperation. " I was also glad to have your confirmation that you were<br />
continuing to take Australia's interests into account in<br />
constructing this latest EEP initiative.<br />
" Nonetheless, I have to say that the issue of export<br />
subsidies remains a major difference between Australia and<br />
the United States. It will continue to have a corrosive<br />
impact on public support in Australia for the relationship<br />
between our two countries. This is something which should<br />
be of concern to us both.<br />
" After due consideration the Australian Government has<br />
decided that the comprehensive nature of the<br />
Administration's announcement last week leaves us with no<br />
alternative but to take up the whole issue of agricultural<br />
export subsidies under the appropriate procedures of the<br />
GATT Council.<br />
" Given the prime responsibility the European Community bears<br />
for escalating the use of subsidies, my Government will<br />
subject their programs to the same GATT complaint<br />
procedures. " Let me assure you of my direct and personal support for<br />
your wish that our two countries continue to work closely<br />
together to finalise the Uruguay Round, which can alone<br />
provide a long-term and sustainable solution to the problem<br />
of agricultural subsidies. The stakes involved for all of<br />
us in avoiding a trade war are very high. As I explained to<br />
you here in Australia last January, I believe the United<br />
States has a vital leadership role to play in completing<br />
this important task.-<br />
CANBERRA 8 September 1992 3. ; ep., 32 14: U4 t. UZ/ Uz </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
