<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1774</transcript-id>
    <title>BACKGROUND BRIEFING GIVEN BY  THE PRIME MINISTER, MR JOHN GORTON, FOR THE HEADS OF SERVICE, PARLIAMENTAR  PRESS GALLERY, CANBERRA</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/02/1968</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001774.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
BACKGROUND BRIEFING GIVEN BY THE PRIME<br />
MINISTER, MR JOHN GORTON, FOR THE HEADS<br />
OF SERVICE, PARLIAMENTARY PRESS GALLERY,<br />
CANBERRA 2ND FEBRUARY, 1968<br />
PRIME MINISTER : I called this because I thought it might be of interest to you,<br />
n ot because I have anything specific to say, but rather there might be<br />
a number of questions in your own minds that you might wish to ask<br />
at this stage. So I thought this would be an opportunity for you to come<br />
here. More particularly did I think this because I will be going to<br />
Melbourne shortly to put in my nomination for Higgins and then coming<br />
back and then on Saturday I am going down to Sydney. On Monday I<br />
have got a lunch-time talk in Sydney in connection with the New South<br />
Wales elections, and after that, as far as you are concerned, I am going<br />
into smoke for about five or six days and as far as anybody else is<br />
concerned I hope. Anybody up here will know where to get on to me<br />
I mean, the Department of Defence, the Department of External Affairs<br />
if anything comes up they will know where to get on to me. I don't want<br />
the -press to get on to me. I want four or five days off after what has been<br />
rather a strenuous two and a half or three months, so I will be out of<br />
circulation and I thought, right, now is the best opportunity for you to<br />
ask any questions that might be in your minds.<br />
Q. This break is just a bit of a rest, is it? It's not<br />
PM: Yes it is a rest.<br />
Q. You are not going to cook up something big?<br />
PM: N0. Oh, no. There will be a certain amount of work to be<br />
0 done, a certain amount of thinking to be done. It really has been pretty<br />
strenuous. I had this Leader of the Senate business for a time, Harold<br />
disappearing and then the campaign, then various crises since. I just<br />
want to try to get four or five or six days before we really get stuck<br />
into it again.<br />
Q. PM: How many reports are you taking with you?<br />
Pleas e.. you don't know where I'm going, but if you find out<br />
don't reveal it' / 2 </p>
<p>Q. Prime Minister, will you release the correspondence to Sir<br />
Henry Bolte on the tax?<br />
PM: Yes, I will, but so far I haven't had Sir Henry Bolte's reply to<br />
our letter to him, and I would like to get his reply and release both<br />
together.<br />
Q. We understand you have to pay this tax?<br />
PM: I don't know whether we have to pay lis tax or not. This would<br />
be ultimately a matter for some other decision. But we are not<br />
collecting from our Commonwealth employees the tax which he has<br />
imposed on wages and salaries.<br />
Q. As the Member for Higgins, you are subject to this tax?<br />
PM: Oh, me personally? Yes, while this legislation is in force,<br />
it will probably cost me about $ 10 a rear or something like that.<br />
Do you intend to pay it?<br />
14: Yes, of course I do.<br />
Q. Willxj~ a compensatory deduction at the next Premiers'<br />
Conf erence?<br />
P0M: I think all I can tell you is this. We have expressed our opinion<br />
to Sir Henry Bolte on this general taxation that he has imposed. We, as<br />
a government, have no quarrel with a stamp tax, a turnover tax, a tax<br />
on receipts. We feel that a tax on wages and salaries, even though it<br />
would be a flat rate tax, in fact, in principle, is a tax on income, and<br />
we could not accept that as a principle. This does not necessarily mean<br />
any immediate action on our part, but it does mean that we are not going<br />
Ito cdilect it, and we regard it'. in principle as a tax On income and therefore<br />
a breach of the Uniform Taxation Agreement. Now, while I am waiting<br />
for a reply from the Premier of Victoria, we don't want to have any<br />
I confrontation on this sort of matter, any sort of violent quarrel There<br />
are a whole lot of things connected with it that will require discussion<br />
and ultimate resolution, but there is no violent hurry about the thing.<br />
Q. In your early observations, do you see this as a real threat to<br />
uniform taxation? Do you see a collapse? / 3 </p>
<p>PM:<br />
Q. Again, at the moment that would be my intention but again I want,<br />
as a matter of courtesy, to confer with Mr McEwen and Mr McMahon<br />
MR EGGLETON: so again, they could understand that without quoting you.<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
Q. When do you expect to get the " Voyager" report?<br />
PM: I've got it. I got it yesterday. I got a copy. The Governor-GeneraI.<br />
got a copy. I am told that it will be about a fortnight or possibly three weeks<br />
Well, let us put it this way. I don't regard this imposition of<br />
one cent on one dollar in itself as a threat to uniform tax ation After all,<br />
the Western Australian Government has been imposing something of the<br />
kind for some time. but if the principle were accepted and ultimately to be<br />
expanded so that it became ten cents or fifty cents or something like that,<br />
then that would then reach a stage where it would be a threat to uniform<br />
taxation. You haven't proposed anything in the nature of what might be<br />
cal-led reprisals, and are going to cut Sir Henry's ground from underneath<br />
him? No, I haven't. I have presented to Sir Henry our views on this<br />
matter. I am awaiting his and his Cabinet's reply to our views on this<br />
matter, and have been suggesting that we might all get together and have<br />
a talk about this matter before it blows up like a pyrotechnic or something.<br />
Does that mean the next Premiers' Conference?<br />
Well, it could be one before, it could be the next one. Other<br />
Premiers are interested in this too....<br />
It is not just a Liberal family matter.<br />
Oh, no.<br />
Have you fixed a date for the meeting of Parliament, Prime Minister?<br />
Of Parliament?<br />
Yes. This is not for attribution. For myself, I would like the Parliament<br />
to meet about the 12th March, but I would like, as a matter of courtesy,<br />
to talk to the Deputy Prime Minister and Deputy Leader of the Liberal Party<br />
which I have not yet done. I don't think we can meet before that, which<br />
gives us twelve days or so after the 26th February.<br />
Are we right in understanding that it is likely to be that date?<br />
Yes.<br />
PM:<br />
8Q.-PM: Q. PM:<br />
Q. PM:<br />
0. PIM: </p>
<p>PM ( Contd.) sufficient bulk printing for distribution it is then my intention to release it<br />
so that all concerned could study it before the Parliament, if there needed<br />
to be anything to be done in Parliament, rather than waiting met and<br />
tabling it, because it is a pretty bulky report. It is about that thick.<br />
If we waited until Parliament met and put it down on the table, people<br />
could, I think quite rightly, say, " We have hardly had time to study this<br />
before some debate or other comes on" so I would be intending to release<br />
it<br />
Q. Will Cabinet have to examine it first?<br />
PM!, No. Why?<br />
Q. I just wondered.<br />
Q. Will this be part of the work you will be studying during your<br />
period in smoke?<br />
04: Oh, I spent a long time last night reading it.<br />
Q. The broad findings, Sir?<br />
PM: The broad findings oh.. dear.... do you want this<br />
for publication?<br />
Q. Well even " understanding" as background, Sir.<br />
PM: Off the record background. I really think I had better not go<br />
further than that. I haven't spoken to the Governor-General who has<br />
got his report about-it, and the only other one it has come to is me.<br />
Other Members of my Government might want to have a look at it before<br />
I sort of did anything more than off -the--record background stuff. From the<br />
0 reading I was able to do yesterday afternoon<br />
Q. May I interrupt, Sir? There is a confusion between' 6ff the<br />
record" and " background" I think in your mind, Sir. Background'Is<br />
0something you can use without attribution. " Off the record" is<br />
something that we must not use.<br />
MR EGGLETON!' I think the PM means " off the record" in its purest sense.<br />
PM: I think I do on this one.<br />
Q. Can you assist us a bit more? Does it upset, say, the original<br />
finding. Something we can use for background just in a broad way. </p>
<p>MR EGGLETON: I think the PM has explained that he has to talk to his colleagues<br />
about this, and for them to read it in the papers....<br />
PM: That one we leave for the moment. But off the record what it says<br />
and I use my own words is this. Cabban didn't tell anything that was<br />
untrue in his own mind as being untrue but he dramatised a helluva of a lot.<br />
He saw himself as the centre of all sorts of things that came along. He<br />
exaggerated. When you sifted his evidenc out, it became quite clear that<br />
Stevens wasn't a drunkard, a chronic drunkard or subjected to alcohol or<br />
anything of that kind, and indeed, when they questcned Cabban about it, he, Cabban,<br />
agreed that there could be no allegations against Stevens' seamanship and there<br />
could be no allegations that Stevens was an alcoholic or a drunkard. But on at<br />
least two occasions in port during the 184 days' voyage, Stevens had been<br />
affected by alcohol, but he had probably been affected by alcohol because he<br />
had an ulcer, which with a small amount of alcohol was upset. The report<br />
recommended that before anybody with a record of having had an ulcer was<br />
appointed to command, they should have an extra specially severe medical<br />
check befor e they were appcfnted. I can't quite remember the terms, but it<br />
said the Naval Board obviously didn't know there was anything at all wrong<br />
with Stevens, couldn't have known a couple of the medical officers hadn't<br />
done their duty by filling in the appropriate forms when Stevens went to<br />
see them about having an ulcer. That's the guts of the report.<br />
Q: Sir, have you made any assessment yet of the current si tuation<br />
in Viet Nam? No because it is such a fluid situation. It is changing syjfapidly.<br />
WI have been speaking to the Minister for the Army this morning. You make<br />
an assessment of something which is in such a state of fluidity, it is daabtful<br />
whether-it is worth a very great deal. There has been some suggestion that<br />
W our own troops have been moved into a northern area of combat. Well this is<br />
not so. Our contribution was to the Third Corps area, and I can show you a<br />
map of what the Third Corps area is, if you are interested in seeing it. Now,<br />
this is the area in which our troops have always been intended to op erate,<br />
although when we have only had two battalions there instead of the three, we now<br />
have, the operation through other parts of that area have been very inhibited.<br />
Well we have got three battalions now and one of them is operating. I think it<br />
is about thirty miles away from the main base, that's all. It is not sort of<br />
way up on<br />
Q. Still in the area.? </p>
<p>PM: Yes, still in that area. We have had some casualties in the<br />
last couple of days but the next of kin have n ot yet been properly<br />
informed. We have had casualties heavier than we have in the past been<br />
having.<br />
Q. Is this off the record, Sir?<br />
PM: No, you can say this. We'll have the whole of the relatives of<br />
e verybody up there upset if we use the casualties one I think we<br />
must keep that off the record.<br />
Q. Can we understand that, without attribution?<br />
PM: No, I think we had better leave that off the record. But they are<br />
not operating more than thirty miles away, this battalion we have been<br />
speaking of. Again off the record, we have had six or seven killed in<br />
the last couple of days. But everybody with any relatives up there will<br />
be so upset in thinking it's theirs that we have got to let them be notified<br />
first.<br />
Q. Can you tell us, Sir, what progress has been made in surveying<br />
the general future of defence in South-East Asia.<br />
PM: Malays ia/ Singapore? Only, a's you already know, Paul Hasluck<br />
is leaving, lie is going to talk to Harry Lee, he is going to talk to the<br />
Tunku, to see what their views on this are. It's an exploratory r~ ji~ g<br />
more than anything else, to see what they see for the future, what they<br />
have in mind as to anything that might come out of a Five-Power pact<br />
meeting.. And then he will be talking to New Zealand, and he will, I am<br />
delighted to say, be speaking to the Indonesian Government as well during<br />
the course of this visit. It is essential that anything we do. if we<br />
do anything in the future is seen not as directed against any country<br />
in that area.<br />
Q. Will yMxx he be seeking to set a date or fix a time when a<br />
meeting might be held?<br />
PM: No, he won't. We will be leaving that to other people. But what<br />
he will be seeking to do is to find out..... he's going to Harry Lee,<br />
he's going to the Tunku and saying " You have been talking about Five-<br />
Power Pacts, you have been talking about what might happen when the<br />
British pull out, what do you have in mind, what do you see, what sort<br />
of contribr-utions do you imagine could come from other places </p>
<p>PM ( Contd.) for what purpose? If there are some Australian troops in a base which<br />
had been previously occupied both by British and Australian troops and<br />
logistic supply has been provided to that base, what do you see for the<br />
future of the logistic supply? Do you expect to take it over yourselves,<br />
Singapore/ Malaysia? Do you expect us to take it over? If so, why?<br />
just what, in detail, you see as the future in this area".<br />
Q. Coming back to Viet Nam. In view of these latest developments,<br />
is there any suggestion that Australia will increase its commitment?<br />
PM: Australia won't increase its commitment.<br />
Q. Have we been asked to?<br />
PM: No.<br />
Q. Is that a permanent statement, Sir? Or the position as it.<br />
As far as I am concerned it is.<br />
What about the visit to South-East Asia.<br />
PM: With the best of intentions, and really wanting to do it, I can't<br />
it coming up before the end of April ci May. If we meet on the 12th, if<br />
we meet having prorogued and having the Speech from the Throne, it<br />
looks to me as if the session would go on well into May, anyway. I<br />
suppose it might be posbeithr) eicfai uisg would'b'ebreak over Easter to rort<br />
off and have a quick run-round. I would prefer, if possible, to wait until<br />
the first Session is out of the way, and you can go at more leisure and<br />
spend more time and talk to more people without so much pressure.<br />
Any countries in mind? Any particular countries?<br />
Oh, clearly, the places I would want to go to would be Indonesia,<br />
Singapore, Malaya, Thailand, South Viet Nam, Japan, and if there were<br />
time.... now, I had better not say that in that way the United States.<br />
Are you including a trip to New Zealand, Sir?<br />
PM: I would hope it might well be fitted in. As you probably know,<br />
I think the first Prime Minister that I spoke to from any Commonvml th<br />
country, after I was appointed to this position, was the Prime Minister of<br />
New Zealand, and he extended an immediate invitation to go there as<br />
soon as it was possibly convenient for me to do so.<br />
Q. Have -you had formal invitations from W ther places?<br />
PM: Not as far as I know. Not formal. They have all sort of said...<br />
you know their Ambassadors and people.... have all sort of said " For </p>
<p>PM ( Contd.) invitations as yet. I would have thought you can correct me, you<br />
people who know more about this than I do that the normal way this was<br />
done was to have the External Affairs Department to say to their External<br />
Affairs Departments: " Our Prime Minister is interested in going around"<br />
and get a reaction from them.<br />
Q. Sir, you omitted Nationalist China from the list of countries<br />
you would like to visit. Was that accidental?<br />
PM: It was neither deliberat~ fior accidental. But they don't seem to<br />
me to be ( interjection:; Important?) I didn't say that.' They don't<br />
seem to me to be ones that are involved in this particular visit.<br />
Q. South Korea is involved in the Viet Nam dispute.... i( China?).<br />
PM: Yes, I know it is, but surely neither South Korea not\ Viet Nam,<br />
important as they may be, are so immediately we are not surely so<br />
immediately involved with problems there as we are with Singapore or<br />
Malaysia or Indonesia or Viet Nam or Thailand or the United States.<br />
Q. Sir, does this mean that if the fighting blew up in -Korea, there<br />
would be no question of sending an Australian troop commitment there?<br />
With what we have got in Viet Nam and in Malaysia?<br />
PM: This is what President Roosevelt used to call a terribly " iffy"<br />
question. We've got an ANZUS pact with the United States which says<br />
that if the forces of either country are attacked in specified areas, then<br />
the other country will act in accordance with its constitutiona. processes<br />
or words to that effect. ftikf If you want a personal opinion, I believe<br />
that with what we are doing in Viet Nam, if we retain our present le vel<br />
of forces in Singapore and the Malaysia area, that is abont all a country<br />
of our size could reasonably be expected to do. But this is all an answer<br />
* to a terribly " iffy" question; tethnhgs haven'tcome up<br />
yet. Fighting hasn't broken out. We haven't been asked. No-one has<br />
approached<br />
Q. We are usually available to go into a United Nations force, aren't<br />
we?<br />
PM: Yes, we usually are, but how much we could divert to a United<br />
Nations force now we've got an awful lot doing right here.<br />
MR EGGLETON: That last one. Was that for attribution?<br />
Q. Wjich one?<br />
MR EGGLETON: The last one on the use of forces. fma The " iffy" question and </p>
<p>PM: Well, I don't mind that " iffy" question one being<br />
used. Well, look, use it, but use it " not for attribution".<br />
MR EGGLETON: If I might say PM, if we want to get to Melbourne, I think perhaps<br />
just one more question....<br />
PM: Oh, we'll get there in time.<br />
Q. Have you given any more thought to your new Minis try?<br />
PM: Oh, forget that one.<br />
Q. Are you at all apprehensive about what is going on<br />
with the APWU as a result of their wage claim being knocked back by<br />
the Public Service Board. Have you given any thought to taking the<br />
Postal Unions out of the Public Service proper?<br />
PM: Well, the second part of your question has nothing<br />
really to do with the immediate problem because they are in now. They've<br />
made an approach to the Public Service Board and they have had a reply,<br />
and as you will have noticed, I have asked the Public Service Board to take<br />
all the steps it can. It is not completely in control because the Public<br />
Service Arbitrator is a quasi-judicial chap who makes his own mind up.<br />
But I have asked them to try and see as best they can that there is no delay<br />
in the hearing of an appeal from the Public Service Board, and I would hope<br />
that these processes of arbitration which, if I understand it correctly,<br />
could if the Arbitration Court itself agreed, finish up in the Arbitration<br />
Court, would not be delayed, so that the steps are open all the way through.<br />
Therefore I hope that these steps would be taken. Now you have gone on<br />
from that to ask a real policy 14uestion. All I will say in reply to that<br />
policy question, to use the words that you used to me has any thought been<br />
given to it? Some thought has been given to it, but that is not to be<br />
construed into any suggestion that something will be done or might be done<br />
or is likely to be done. It is just that the matter hasn't escaped attention.<br />
Q. Mr Prime Minister, are you about to have talks with people<br />
like the Commonwealth Police and Attorney-General's Department about this<br />
vexed question of personal security for yourself?<br />
PM: I have been told I ought to have t alks with somebody<br />
in the Prime Minister's Department on it. I don't mind a reasonable<br />
amount of personal security but I don't want guys following me around all<br />
the time.<br />
Q. You have been seen to have been giving them a bit </p>
<p>PM: Is that right? They have lost me a couple of times?<br />
Q. Sir, there has been talk of growing Australian interest<br />
in the Indian Ocean. Could we expect defence talks to take place with<br />
India, South Africa and other countries interested in this area?<br />
Q. I have heard no suggestion of that from the Defence<br />
Department nor have I thought about it myself.<br />
Thank Y'ou. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
