<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7367</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER PREMIER DOWDING&#039;S &#039;DECISION MAKERS LUNCHEON&#039; PERTH - 5 AUGUST 1988</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/08/1988</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007367.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
PREMIER DOWDING'S ' DECISION MAKERS LUNCHEON'<br />
PERTH 5 AUGUST 1988<br />
Peter Dowding,<br />
Ladies and gentlemen.<br />
In less than a month on 3 September the Australian<br />
people will be asked to make four changes to the<br />
Constitution.<br />
The four proposals are:<br />
to provide for four year maximum terms for bath Houses<br />
of the Commonwealth Parliament;<br />
to establish fair and democratic Parliamentary elections<br />
throughout Australia;<br />
to recognise local government as an integral part of the<br />
system of government in this country; and<br />
to extend rights already in the Constitution so that<br />
they effectively cover all Australians.<br />
These proposals cover four separate areas of our<br />
Constitution, but they share one key and overwhelming<br />
element: they are about benefiting people, rather than<br />
empowering governments.<br />
Constitutional reformers have not had a good track record in<br />
this country.<br />
In the 87 years of Federation, only 8 changes have been<br />
approved out of 38 proposals.<br />
This has taught this Government two very important lessons<br />
in proposing these referendums.<br />
One relates to perceptions of change; the other relates to<br />
the process of change.<br />
The fact that we inherited the Constitution from our<br />
colonial predecessors as the very basis of our Federal<br />
system created the perception that the Constitution is<br />
therefore immutable.<br />
860 </p>
<p>2.<br />
But that perception is misplaced. Australia is an<br />
infinitely more sophisticated and complex community in the<br />
1980s than it was in the 1890s.<br />
Increasingly, Australians are recognising that a document<br />
drawn up in the last century as a compromise between<br />
separate colonies cannot provide the best guidance for a<br />
fully integrated nation making its way in the world economy<br />
of today.<br />
Thomas Jefferson put it well when he said:<br />
" Some men look at constitutions with sanctimonious<br />
reverence, and deem them like the Ark of the Covenant,<br />
too sacred to be touched. They ascribe to the men of<br />
the preceding age a wisdom more than human, and suppose<br />
what they did to be beyond amendment We might as<br />
well require a man to wear the coat that fitted him as a<br />
boy, as civilised society to remain ever under the<br />
regime of their ancestors."<br />
These referendum ' s will help ensure that our political<br />
structures can wear a coat that fits them.<br />
Who could have*-predicted 90 years ago that the pace of<br />
decision-making needed to keep up with the international<br />
marketplace would become so hampered by the constant threat<br />
of an early election?<br />
who could have predicted the present demand for fair and<br />
democratic elections and the extent to which electoral<br />
systems in some States are now rorted when the very<br />
concept of universal suffrage was still a novelty in the<br />
late 19th century?<br />
Who could have envisaged Local Government having the<br />
responsibility and importance it now does, when 90 years ago<br />
its role was confined simply to the provision of roads and<br />
property services?<br />
And who could be satisfied today that such basic rights as<br />
the freedom to practise a religion, to be given a trial by<br />
jury and to receive fair compensation for property acquired<br />
by any Government do not extend to the States or<br />
Territories? These referendums propose simple and broadly acceptable<br />
reforms which will ensure the Constitution more closely<br />
reflects the principles by which we govern ourselves.<br />
Given all this, I am confident that Australians are now<br />
willing to consider and support change to a document which<br />
up till now has proven remarkably impervious to change.<br />
I referred earlier to a second lesson from the failure of<br />
previous referendums -a lesson about the process of change. 86.1 </p>
<p>3.<br />
It is the way in which these proposals have been drawn up Sn<br />
which also gives me confidence they will succeed at the Fd<br />
ballot box. Eaci<br />
In the past, referendum proposals all too often seemed to<br />
emerge from on high, as flats of Government, without prior The<br />
consultation with those who were being called upon to vote inslt<br />
on them. proc<br />
It was a process almost guaranteed to arouse the suspicions Foui<br />
of the political opponents of the Government of the day, as, cost<br />
well as of those cynics who automatically interpret any<br />
change as a plot to enhance the power of Canberra. Thai busi<br />
The result was that many well intentioned'and worthwhile betti<br />
proposals failed. They were seen as having been formulated<br />
by politicians for politicians. The-<br />
By contrast, our proposals have been developed by the people o<br />
for the people. But<br />
in 1985 we established the Constitutional Commission a tmootrf<br />
bipartisan community-based group to study what could be -b<br />
done to achieve essential constitutional reform. the<br />
caus<br />
The work of this Commission, chaired by the former elec<br />
Solicitor-General, Sir Maurice Byers, has been absolutely<br />
first class in the number of public hearings it held and The<br />
the number of submissions it received, and in the quality offi<br />
its committee work and above all the quality of its reports. If r<br />
By giving constitutional reform back to the people, we have of<br />
ensured that the issues being put on 3 September reflect prod<br />
their priorities, their concerns not Labor's agenda, not<br />
Canberra's agenda at the expense of the States, not the' No<br />
agenda of politicians of any stripe. tha<br />
If these four proposals succeed, the real winners will be equ a<br />
the people of Australia. if t~<br />
n eve<br />
The first question asks voters if they approve of four year todla<br />
maximum terms for both Houses of Parliament. most<br />
aittt eimsp tae dc, l astshiact tfhaec t paoif n ecporneocmeidce s chtahne geg, a inw. h ereG ovietr nimse nts vaontd<br />
seeking change need time to implement those decisions which,<br />
though they may cause political pain in the short-term, are No g<br />
essential and will deliver long-term benefits to the whole cont<br />
community. Aust unde<br />
Four year terms provide that tine. They will ensure shou<br />
governments can get on with the job of running the country. recc<br />
over the last few years, four-year terms have been adopted Yet<br />
by every State Parliament except Queensland. whe r<br />
That has happened because Governments frequently failed to Panl<br />
run their full term under the three year system.<br />
862 </p>
<p>4-4.<br />
Since the Second World War, Australians have had to vote in<br />
Federal elections, on average, every two years.<br />
Each election now costs the taxpayer some $ 50 million.<br />
The cost is to be measured also in terms of the economic<br />
instability and dislocation sparked by the ever-present<br />
prospect of an election.<br />
Four year maximum terms would mean fewer elections, less<br />
cost, and less uncertainty.<br />
That is why four year terms are strongly supported by<br />
business groups. They would mean more stable government and<br />
better decision-making.<br />
These changes will not alter the power or the independence<br />
of the Senate in any way.<br />
But four year terms for the Senate will make that Chamber<br />
more accountable. The Senate's powers to force a Government<br />
to the polls will remain untouched for better or for worse<br />
but it will itself have to account to the electorate at<br />
the same time. And. that will eliminate one of the chief<br />
causes of early elections namely, bringing the timing of<br />
elections for the two Chambers back into line.<br />
The second proposal, for fairer elections, complements the<br />
first proposal, for fewer elections.<br />
If representative Parliaments are to retain the confidence<br />
of their electors in other words, if democracy is to work<br />
properly the electoral rules must be fair.<br />
No voter can be allowed substantially more or less power<br />
than another. A democratic government must be based on<br />
equal representation of its citizens.<br />
If this sounds elementary text book material, it<br />
nevertheless does not reflect the situation in Australia<br />
today.<br />
most specifically, it does not reflect the situation for<br />
voters electing State Parliaments in Queensland, Tasmania<br />
and here in western Australia.<br />
No government more than mine has recognised the unique<br />
contribution to the nation's prosperity made by country<br />
Australia. But we do not need to have a gerrymander to<br />
understand and recognise that contribution indeed it<br />
should be considered an insult that the contribution is<br />
recognised in such a way.<br />
Yet where is the justice in the Queensland electoral system,<br />
where 25,000 country voters elect three members of the State<br />
Parliament while 25,000 metropolitan voters elect only one? 863 </p>
<p>The r<br />
the pray alon<br />
The infamy of the Queensland gerrymander is well known. Loa<br />
But the electoral systuenmf oirnt uWnesatteer~ n~ ~ A~ u~ s~ to~ rsLal ia hhna: sm the caiftbnitgoe<br />
Queensland's despite the improvements of last year's alovnag<br />
Electoral Reform Act. stat<br />
Each country elector in this state has, on average, almost The<br />
twice as much say as a metropolitan elector in deciding who dese<br />
will govern Western Australia and therefore ultimately. in<br />
deciding how it will be governed. And each country elector This<br />
has almost three times as much say in electing the<br />
Legislative Council -which has the power to deny the<br />
legislative program of the Government.<br />
The proposed amendments to ensure fair and democraticelections<br />
are simple.<br />
They will ensure that the number of voters in each<br />
electorate is within 10 per cent of the average number of<br />
voters in all electorates in each State, and they will All trial<br />
They will not impose Commonwealth laws on the States. whici<br />
Indeed, they do not give more power to any Government-<br />
Federal, State or Territory. The i<br />
and<br />
what they do is to guarantee the rights of the people by<br />
ensuring that their voices are heard equally on election Ladil<br />
day. It w(<br />
At the same time, they fill one of the most glaring gaps in high<br />
the Constitution: its failure., to guarantee the right to Cons'<br />
vote. guidi<br />
A vote for this question will ensure that all But<br />
Australians have the constitutionally-guaranteed right to to w<br />
vote, subject to existing legal disqualifications such as its<br />
mental incapacity or imprisonment. leas<br />
it is no disrespect to the statesmen who framed our On wi<br />
Constitution to assert that in 1988, it is surely time to de te<br />
enshrine the right to vote in the document that is the basis no ai<br />
of our democratic government. Id<br />
without it, our democratic heritage is sullied, and our leadi<br />
democratic reputation is tarnished. polio from<br />
If the third referendum succeeds, it will insert a new<br />
section into the Constitution which will at last provide I mu,<br />
constitutional recognition of the third tier of government, not i<br />
local government. The(<br />
The merits of this case do not need much elaboration by me prop(<br />
because they are fully and frequently outlined by local<br />
government organisations themselves.<br />
864 </p>
<p>6.<br />
There are more than 850 local councils around Australia. In<br />
the last financial year they spent more than $ 6.5 billion on<br />
providing the grass roots services that local government<br />
alone can provide.<br />
Local government exists and it should and will endure as<br />
a valid, democratTEcaicountable and respected tier of<br />
administration in Australia. This referendum will provide a<br />
long overdue and thoroughly legitimate recognition of its<br />
status in the Constitution.<br />
The fourth and final referendum is as simple and as<br />
deserving of support as the preceding three.<br />
This question asks voters to ensure the rights of:<br />
trial by jury for people facing * serious criminal<br />
charges; fair compensation for property taken by any government;<br />
and freedom of religion.<br />
All three of these ' rights already exist in the Constitution<br />
but they apply only to the Commonwealth, and in the cases of<br />
trial by jury and -freedom of religion there are loopholes<br />
which could allow those rights to be avoided.<br />
The amendments will apply these rights to all governments<br />
and will close those loopholes nothing more.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen,<br />
it would have been fine to be able to end this speech on the<br />
high note outlining the prospect of a refurbished<br />
Constitution providing more relevant and more effective<br />
guidance to government and justice in Australia.<br />
But the opposition, for its own unique reasons, has decided<br />
to withhold its support from these proposals a reversal of<br />
its support which it expressed at the last election for at<br />
least two of the issues.<br />
On what-can only be ch-ar-acterised as a platform of<br />
determined illogicality, the opposition now urges " no, no,<br />
no and no" to the four proposals.<br />
I do not now want to speculate about the failure of<br />
leadership in-the Liberal Party which allowed its standing<br />
policy to be overthrown in the party room under pressure<br />
from the National Party.<br />
I must however highlight, and in the starkest of terms, the<br />
motives behind that reversal.<br />
The Opposition now makes the extraordinary claim that these<br />
proposals are a grab for power by Canberra. 865 </p>
<p>7.<br />
But the truth is that opposition to the proposals means<br />
retaining the8 privileg-es--n -oers of politicians and<br />
entrenhing the inefficiencies of the present system.<br />
opposition to the four year term proposal means support for<br />
disrupting the nation with elections far more frequently<br />
than even our Constitutional founders would have expected or<br />
ever intended.<br />
opposition to the one vote-one value proposal means allowing<br />
politicians to retain the power to manipulate electoral<br />
boundaries. opposition to the local government proposal means turning a e<br />
blind eye to the existence of the third tier of governmentI<br />
and refusing the benefits of closer cooperation among Local,<br />
State and Federal Governments.<br />
opposition to the rights and freedoms proposal meansB<br />
allowing State politicians to retain the capacity to deny r<br />
people a number of essential rights. c<br />
g<br />
Ladies and gentlemen,<br />
The real question before us is this.: Who will decide and<br />
control the process of change? M CI<br />
We believe the answer must be " the people".<br />
These referendums have been carefully chosen to give the<br />
people of Australia the best possible opportunity to come<br />
back into the mainstream of the Constitution-making and<br />
Constitution-changing processes of this nation.<br />
It is those who oppose these referendums who should explain<br />
their refusal to tolerate this trend.<br />
Because there is a broader'issue at stake in this campaignthe<br />
issue of Australia's capacity to adapt flexibly and as a<br />
nation to changing world conditions and to equip itself to<br />
meet the challenges of the twenty first century.<br />
In the 1980s, Australia needed a more efficient and<br />
effective economy.<br />
In the 1980s, Australia needed a more efficient and<br />
effective industrial relations system and a more efficient<br />
and effective taxation system.<br />
in the 1980s, Australia needed more efficient, effective<br />
education and training systems and health and welfare<br />
services. Providing these better services and creating these more<br />
efficient systems has been the overarching task of the<br />
Government which I have the honor to lead.<br />
866 </p>
<p>8.<br />
But it has never been a case of change, just for the sake of<br />
change.<br />
What has always been at stake is the protection of living<br />
standards, the creation of jobs, and the building of a<br />
society based on fairness and justice.<br />
I am proud to stand here and state that my Government has<br />
made and is continuing to make significant progress towards<br />
each of these goals.<br />
And I am also proud to stand here and argue the case of<br />
constitutional reform.<br />
Because . just as Australia has needed to achieve vital<br />
reforms in other areas of our community life, so<br />
constitutional reform is an essential ingredient of our<br />
growth into the next century.<br />
In the 1980s and 1990s as we prepare for the 21st century<br />
Australia needs a more effective Constitution, a more<br />
modern Constitution, a fairer Constitution, a people's<br />
Constitution. 867 -I </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
