<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9804</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J.KEATING MP DOORSTOP, CITY HALL, BRISBANE, 20 OCTOBER 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/10/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009804.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
DOORSTOP, CITY HALL, BRISBANE. 20 OCTOBER 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
PM: I have a number of things to say to you and some information to release<br />
to you. You may now have a statement where I have said I am going to<br />
appoint Con Sciacca as Minister Assisting the Treasurer for<br />
superannuation matters. As you know Mr Sciacca was involved,<br />
through most of the year, as Minister for Veterans' Affairs, in the<br />
Australia Remembers commemorative arrangements and<br />
commemorative program, which by the way, reached its climax here in<br />
Brisbane and I think that we in the Government have been very proud<br />
of the commitment he has made to that. The fact that it has worked<br />
particularly well and that, I think, also the RSL and other groups<br />
Involved in the commemoration were very appreciative of his efforts.<br />
He has very clear personal skills to do an outstanding job consulting<br />
Australians and explaining to them policies, things which are of value to<br />
them and we think that superannuation is such a significant matter<br />
given the fact that this Government now over a period of a decade has<br />
got superannuation up to the point where soon, by 2002, every<br />
Australian will be putting away 15 per cent of his or her income for their<br />
retirement benefits. Many issues are involved here and I know the<br />
public want information about this Important and sea change to<br />
retirement income and national savings and while this area of<br />
responsibility, of course, is principally that of the Treasurer, he has<br />
indicated to me that he could do with more both administrative support<br />
and field support on this. So, Mr Selacca will be Minister Assisting the<br />
Treasurer on superannuation and will be working with Paul Elliott who<br />
has been Parliamentary Secretary involved with this and who, with the<br />
Treasurer, has done a very good job to date.<br />
That is one thing of, I think, importance to the country and also to<br />
Queensland because a Queensland Minister will be doing it and we<br />
now have a strong complement of Queensland Ministers in the Cabinet<br />
and this is, in a sense, a bit of a feather in Con's cap for a job well done<br />
this year and the appreciation of his colleagues. </p>
<p>A number of other things I would like to announce. I have got three<br />
statements. One which is to announce a major upgrade of the Bruce<br />
Highway which is a $ 150 million commitment to the highway and today<br />
we have committed $ 64 million towards that $ 150 million planned<br />
upgrade from Brisbane to Cooroy. Under plans approved by Cabinet<br />
today a 24 kilometre stretch of lhe highway between Brisbane and<br />
Cabooltuie will be widened to six lanes. Over the next three years $ 14<br />
million will be spent on this section, $ 9 million on the construction of an<br />
interchange at Buchannan Road serving Caboolture and Morayfield<br />
which will be opened to traffic by Christmas next year and $ 5 million on<br />
planning, project design, land acquisition, traffic management plans and<br />
an EIS and public consultation on the Brisbane to Caboolture<br />
upgrading. The project which will get under way before Christmas Is<br />
te first stage of a $ 100 million ten year upgrade of the highway.<br />
My colleague, Laurie Brereton, also announced that $ 15 million will be<br />
spent widening the dangerous stretch of the Bruce Highway between<br />
Yandina and Cooroy to four lanes. The full 18 kilometres will be<br />
completed by 1990 end will link up with the Yandina bypass now under<br />
construction. So, I think there are about 2000 construction jobs over<br />
four years involved here. This is a further important upgrading of the<br />
national highway system and particularly this section of the Bruce<br />
Highway Another announcement that I am able to make is that we will be<br />
spending an additional $ 20 million for capital developments for<br />
Queensland universities in 1998. Simon Crean has, I think, announced<br />
today that $ 15.5 million will be for three major capital developments at<br />
Loganlea, Gold Coast. Ipswich and Rockhampton in 1998. This on top<br />
of the $ 27.3 million allocated to Queensland institutions from the capital<br />
development pool in 1998/ 7. Queensland institutions will receive a<br />
further $ 4.5 million in 1998. Around $ 13.5 million will be directed<br />
towards a new campus development In Brisbane's western and<br />
souther growth corridors and the remaininlg $ 2 milliol will be allocated<br />
to Central Queeilland University for its Rockhampton campus. The<br />
1990 allocation represents the federal government's ongoing<br />
commitment to providing adequate facilities for Queensland's rapidly<br />
growing higher education student population. You might remember in<br />
an earlier announcement this year we added 4200 places to university<br />
places In this state; $ 6.5 million of these funds will go to the University<br />
of Queensland to enable construction of a new campus on the site of<br />
the old railway workshops in North Ipswich. This is estimated to serve<br />
a population of around 400.000 In Ipswich and the surrounding<br />
communities. The develuplent of the new campus will enable the<br />
University of Queensland to maintain its tradition of providing a diverse<br />
and high quality range of courses to Queensland and Brisbane<br />
students.<br />
An allocation of $ 7 million will go to Griffith University to enable<br />
expansion of Its existing Gold Coast campus as well as the<br />
development of a new campus at LoganLea In Brisbane's southern </p>
<p>growth corridor, This southern growth corridor has, of course, been an<br />
Important component of the growth along the east coast of Australia. It<br />
is one of the fastest growing areas in the country, if not the fastest and<br />
you know the natilal government has had an interest thoro in rail<br />
facilities, in transport and now in education. So, that funding will be<br />
made available there as well.<br />
I might also mention that my colleague the Minister for the Environment,<br />
John Faulkner, announced with the Government of Queensland today a<br />
$ 16 million package to protect the endangered Mahogany Glider and<br />
other unique flors and fauna along the Queensland coastline. It will<br />
involve a package of around 38.000 tiectares along the coast being<br />
voluntarily acquired. Il these areas most of the crucial glider habitat<br />
will be purchased and added to existing national parks between Tully<br />
and Ingham and voluntary conservation agreements will be introduced<br />
on the remaining crucial habitat areas. This package is, I think, an<br />
important landmark package that will ensure the continuing protection<br />
of four remaining significant Mahogany Glider colonies including the<br />
one associated with the Cooper wetlands adjoining Halifax Bay. The<br />
package will also ensure the continuing protection of other important<br />
tiora and fauna species unique to the regiuon such as the Southem<br />
Cassowary and the Proserpine Rock Wallaby.<br />
The Minister said they were looking at acquiring 16 free hold and free<br />
lease hold properties in the Tully/ lngham area and, I think, land holders<br />
in the area have been informed of the Governments intentions. I<br />
understand this has been very widely welcomed by industry and by the<br />
environment movement around the country.<br />
So, I'll leave my remarks at that and that Is. of cui se, additional to the<br />
remarks I made at lunch time.<br />
J: Prime Minister, Peter Costello denied that a Coalition government<br />
( inaudible)...<br />
PM: No, obviously this is the problem about secrecy in politics, of political<br />
parties not coming out and saying where they will stand. Obviously the<br />
source of that article in the BRW was someone who has been engaged<br />
with this process over a considerable period of time und this, of course,<br />
was for an announcement in September next year. Long after a<br />
national election had been held. As a consequence of such a change<br />
and remember it is not as If this has not been heard of before. This is<br />
very much in the conservative agenda and they have been at the<br />
Commonwealth, of course, they wasted their time with me proposing In<br />
my day as Treasurer that we should give them a commonwealth<br />
income tax and then let them set the rates. I mean, the glue that holds<br />
this federation together is the uniform taxing power of the<br />
Commonwealth. The day it is split up and given back to the states you<br />
will have six state economies and you will have the Australian nation<br />
substantially fractured. When one looks at any of the federations </p>
<p>around the world be it Germany or Canada it is very clear that the<br />
taxing power is central to their maintenance ea cohesive countries<br />
The Coalition's view has been always that If you have all the power<br />
vested in the national government the economic power particularly<br />
and the Labor Party gets hold of the government therefore the whole<br />
progressive agenda is advanced. Their question is, how do we hold<br />
the progressive agenda back? You hold it back by fracturing the power<br />
and giving it back to the States. All in the name of federalism as if<br />
when we federated a century ago it wasn't simply to create the nation<br />
which, of course, now it is. being used as a way of regressively going<br />
back to the needs of the States, what ever they might be.<br />
But, in this proposal where they would vary the marginal tax rate from<br />
the initial 16 per cent, as a consequence of that it would affect some<br />
States differently than other States and South Australia would need to<br />
increase the total marginal tax rate by 6 per cent. Tasmania by 9.5 per<br />
cent et cetera. So, again, this would have very different affects and, of<br />
course, those States which have stronger domestic, stronger if you like<br />
indigenous tax bases would be able to give more income tax relief by<br />
way of a different rate structure than others. So, the States that had a<br />
stronger domestic base would be able to provide a lower rate of income<br />
tax than other States. So, you would have wealthy people shifting their<br />
domiciles so they could pick up the lower tax rates et cetera. It would<br />
be the sort of mayhem you would see from it.<br />
I have said before and I said today earlier and I'll say it again and that is<br />
there can be no honesty and credibility in public life and in politics<br />
without policies. Mr Howard says they will dribble out, this is what he<br />
means by dribbling them out. But here you have got an important<br />
component of national economic policy, the prerogative of the<br />
Commonwealth to be able run fiscal policy in this country, which you<br />
know has been very important in these times when we have had<br />
problems with the current account imbalance and savings problems and<br />
terms of trade problems in the middle 1980s. It has been entirely<br />
central that the Commonwealth has this power. This is a power, of<br />
course, they would put asunder.<br />
J: As part of his denial today Mr Costello says a Coalition government<br />
wouldn't raise taxes and has called on you to give a signal.<br />
PM: He wouldn't be giving the denial unless someone wrote this In the<br />
BRW. You wouldn't be asking me any questions about this. In other<br />
words, he has kept you in the dark, happily, and then when we flushed<br />
him out he gives you a pap answer and you want me to respond to it<br />
seriously and I'm not going to. The only response I make is this, at<br />
least we can see what John Howard is up to. It is all the old agenda<br />
tax powers back to the States, hopping into working people, knocking<br />
Medicare off and getting a consumption tax up, the GST up but in the<br />
name of the States and the hands of the States. It is the same agenda<br />
and when the Liberal backbencher Kevin Andrews said this week and </p>
<p>was rebuked by Mr Howard for supporting a GST, lie probably didn't<br />
know that Mr Costello had a more surreptitious way of getting to it, that<br />
is to say to the States you have yuur own consumption taxes.<br />
J: Do you put any store to the criticism today of calling the major<br />
institutions...<br />
PM: I got asked that at lunch time, I can't make a senal of it<br />
J: Has Cabinet decided what to do with the computer bounty<br />
PM: No, it hasn't but It will probably do so later in the year.<br />
J: Later in the year, so ( inaudible)<br />
PM: We had a preliminary discussion about it, but no final decisions were<br />
made about it.<br />
J: So you need more Information from Peter Cook?<br />
PM; More information and more time.<br />
J: Prime Minister. France has apparently called on Britain and the US to<br />
sign the treaty banning nuclear testing in the South Pacific.<br />
PM: I often say to people that those who try to pretend that Britain Interests<br />
and ours are the same, particularly in respect to the republic, that<br />
Britain has her interests in Europe and we have ours in the Asia Pacific.<br />
It is very clear in respect of nuclear testing that Britain has been one of<br />
the very few countries which has said anything. In fact it said nothing<br />
which has been critical of France's decision to test weapons in the<br />
Pacific. I make no criticism of them in that respect, it is entirely Britain's<br />
right, but people in this country should notice that Britain's interest and<br />
our interest are completely different and that the Queen of Australia. as<br />
head of Australia and Queen of Great Britain is looking at the world<br />
through different prisms and that is why, of course, we need an<br />
Australian head of state in this country. We need our full sovereignty to<br />
be expressed so our views on Important issues such as these are not<br />
compromised whatsoever.<br />
J: Just back to computers again, do you think that despite your general<br />
predisposition to oppose tariff barriers, subsidies that there is a case<br />
for the computer industry...<br />
PM: There has never been a, if you like, any religion in all this for us. We<br />
have generally taken the view that Australia is advantaged by getting<br />
protection levels down and I thinK the proof of the pudding has been in<br />
the eating. Those who believed In high tariff poltections have been<br />
wrong and shown to be wrong, but we have got other programs and<br />
other supporting measures in ship building which has improved, I'm<br />
sure. ship building, computers in the partnership programs. We have </p>
<p>sought to encourage particular parts of industry to do innovative things,<br />
but in the context of generally declining overall protection.<br />
J: Well, this is an industry that does require considerable investment..<br />
PM: Yes, but again the bounty does apply generally and the things we tend<br />
to do best at are software writing, that sort of sharper end of the<br />
business and not particularly the hardware area, the screwdriver area,<br />
where this bounty has in the past generally been spread. Now, it may<br />
be this is the right way to support the industry.<br />
J: But something more focussed?<br />
PM: But something more focussed might be bettor too.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
