<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3093</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S PRESS CONFERENCE, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA, TUESDAY 4 DECEMBER 1973</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/12/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003093.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER'S PRESS CONFERENCE<br />
PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA<br />
TUESDAY 4 DECEMBER 1973<br />
QUESTION: Prime Minister, the Director of General Motors yesterday<br />
said that his company believed that Australian equity in General<br />
Motors Australia would reduce the quality of its product. Would you<br />
agree that this policy of not allowing Australian equity conflicts<br />
with the thrust of the Government's policy. Why have previous<br />
Governments refused General Motors Corporation of America permission<br />
to sell shares in Australia? Will you reverse this policy if equity<br />
in General Motors Australia is not forthcoming and do you agree<br />
that there should be only three car makers in Australia?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I'm not responsible for the policy of previous<br />
Governments. The Australian Government has asked the Tariff Board<br />
to report on the general overall position of the motor car industry.<br />
General Motors will be one of the companies, the present ones, giving<br />
evidence before the Tariff Board. I think one can well wait until<br />
the Tariff Board report comes to hand about all these features.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Ladies and gentlemen: There are a few things that<br />
perhaps I should say myself first.<br />
You will already have been told, I believe, that the<br />
Federal German Chancellor, Herr Willy Brandt, has accepted our<br />
invitation to visit Australia. The date of the visit will be decided<br />
next year. I have a press statement on this subject. This is the<br />
most significant visit from Europe since President Saragat visited<br />
us in September 1967. It is of very great gratification and<br />
significance to this country and our region.<br />
There were quite a number of decisions that the Cabinet<br />
made yesterday. We have decided to appoint a Committee of Inquiry on<br />
Retraining. The terms of reference will be into the role that<br />
training should play in an active manpower policy, the extent to which<br />
opportunities for training and retraining should be provided or<br />
improved, the broad methods of training and retraining that should<br />
be used, the methods of selecting respective trainees and of<br />
allocating trainees to prospective employers, the rationalisation<br />
of existing schemes of training and retraining and the level of<br />
allowances that should be paid to trainees, and the question of<br />
taxation in relation to such allowances. The Chairman of the committee<br />
will be Professor Donald Cochrane of Monash and the other members<br />
will be Mr Pat Clancy, Secretary of the Building Workers! Industrial<br />
Union, and Mr E. Donoghue, Proprietor of Donoghub Furniture Pty Ltd.<br />
Mr Jock Nelson has been appointed Administrator of the Northern<br />
Territory. Mr William Worth has been appointed as the Australian<br />
Commissioner-General for the International Exposition on the<br />
Environment which, as I told you a week ago, we have decided to<br />
participate in at Spokane in Washington State between May and<br />
October next year. Mr Worth has already been Deputy Commissioner-<br />
General at Expo ' 67 in Montreal and Expo ' 70 in Osaka. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
Then there are some decisions concerning tertiary education.<br />
We have approved the establishment of a university at Campbelltown<br />
and a university at Albury-Wodonga. The Minister for Education is<br />
arranging for the Universities Commission to undertake discussions<br />
with the appropriate authorities in New South Wales with a view to<br />
determining the way in which these universities might be constituted<br />
and with the Victorian authorities also as regarding Albury-Wodonga<br />
and developing proposals for special funds being made available during<br />
the remainder of this triennium should that prove necessary.<br />
The Government has decided to provide a new medical school<br />
at the University of Newcastle and another at the James Cook<br />
University of North Queensland and to expand a number of existing<br />
medical schools as recommended in the report of the Committee<br />
on Medical Schools. The position of a medical school at Wollongong<br />
University and at the A. N. U. in Canberra is still being discussed.<br />
The Government has decided to provide funds to support<br />
departments of or courses in community practice in medical schools<br />
of universities seeking to establish such programs in conjunction<br />
with community health centres supported or approved by the Interim<br />
Committee of the Hospitals and Health Services Commission. The funds<br />
for these departments or courses in community practice will be of<br />
the order of $ 35,000 in the first year of operation and $ 75,000 in<br />
the second and subsequent years and $ 50,000 to provide teaching<br />
accommodation in each community health centre where such a centre<br />
is to be used in conjunction with a medical school. Also on hospitals,<br />
we have included in the 1973/ 74 Civil Works program proposals for<br />
Concord Repatriation Hospital. We have also approved the construction<br />
of a new hospital at Tennant Creek at a preliminary estimated cost<br />
of million. Then there are some matters concerning Canberra. We have<br />
considered the joint planning study carried out by officers of the<br />
Australian and New South Wales Governments about the growth of<br />
Canberra and the lands adjacent to the present borders of the<br />
Aiustralian Capital Territory. The Government has authorised<br />
Miv Uren, the Minister for Urban and Regional Development and<br />
Mr Bryant, the Minister for the Capital Territory to enter into further<br />
discussions with the New South Wales Government. These discussions<br />
could explore the basis on which agreement may be reached on land<br />
acquisition and development for urban and associated purposes, for<br />
lanid acquisition for environmental protection purposes, including<br />
appropriate funding and cost recovery arrangements.<br />
The Government has decided to call tenders for the<br />
consjtruction of the Googong Dam to supply water for the Australian<br />
Capita. Territory and Queanbeyan. The Minister for Urban and Regional<br />
Development is to confer with the New South Wales Government about<br />
the pollution of all waters downstream from Captains Flat and is<br />
arranging a meeting with the New South Wales representative. </p>
<p>-3-<br />
Then about turtles. On 24 August I asked Senator Willesee,<br />
who was then the Special Minister of State, to arrange for expert<br />
studies into ecological and commercial aspects of the turtle farming<br />
projects being conducted in Northern Australia in Aboriginal and<br />
Torres Strait Island communities. Reports by Professors A. F. Carr<br />
and A. R. Main and Mr L. F. Smart have been presented and it is<br />
proposed to table them probably tomorrow, I thought they would be<br />
tabled today but we have been unable to get the reports to the<br />
Premiers of Queensland and Western Australia in time, so we expect<br />
they will be tabled tomorrow. I have, however, telegraphed our<br />
decision to the Premiers so I can now read it to you. As a matter<br />
of fact, a great number of the decisions I have been reading to you<br />
have concerned the States and I had to wait until we telegraphed<br />
those decisions to the Premiers who will have them by now. The<br />
Government has approved continuation of the turtle industry as a pilot<br />
experimental project in which research is emphasised. as recommended<br />
by Professors Carr and Main, to determine the feasibility of<br />
developing the industry on the lines described by Mr Smart.<br />
The Government has authorised the Attorney-. General,<br />
Senator Murphy, to introduce a Family Law Bill. As with the<br />
Matrimonial Causes Bill 1959, it has been decided that this bill will<br />
be dealt with as a Government measure for the procedural purpose only<br />
of bringing the measure to a vote. All Government members will be<br />
entitled to a free vote and to move such amendments as they see fit.<br />
The bill will deal not only with matters upon which the Australian<br />
Parliament has already made laws but it will also deal with matters<br />
which under the Constitution can be the subject of legislation passed<br />
by the Australian Parliament but which hitherto has been dealt with<br />
by State Parliaments. In particular deserted wives and children's<br />
legislation and married women's property legislation. The legislation,<br />
of course, will be sent to the Premiers as I have telegraphed them.<br />
Now, some matters of meat and drink. We have directed the<br />
Bureau of Agricultural Economics to investigate the costs involved<br />
in the marketing of cattle, sheep and pig meat with special reference<br />
to the composition of the margin between the prices paid to primary<br />
producers for animals slaughtered and the retail prices paid by<br />
consumers for their meat products. The wholesale prices of meat have<br />
been dropping but the retail prices don't(-seem to have been dropping<br />
proportionately, so the BAE is to inquire in~ to the situation.<br />
Then, brandy. I expect that this week we will be tabling<br />
-the Tariff Board report on brandy. The Minister for Primary Industry<br />
and the Minister for Secondary Industry will establish a body to<br />
report to them on means of absorbing grape surpluses arising before<br />
any longer term restructuring or adjustment programs can be implemented.<br />
We expect this body to submit its first report by the middle of<br />
February. The new harvest, of course, is due ifi March. The whole<br />
difficulty of the brandy industry is that we produce more grapes for<br />
this purpose than we can absorb in thE -rocessed form. </p>
<p>-4-<br />
Mr Hayden, the Minister for Social Security, will be giving<br />
you a statement about Social Services legislation. There is another<br />
item which I might mention. Pending legislation being introduced<br />
and passed the Government has approved pensions being paid as an<br />
act uf grace to people overseas who are in extreme hardship and who<br />
have lived 30 years in Australia and have left Australia after reaching<br />
age pension age or were within five years of reaching age pension<br />
age at the time of departure. These resident's requirements will be<br />
waived where permanent incapacity or widowhood occurred in Australia.<br />
Following on the decisions we announced a week ago concerning<br />
the mining licences and leases in the Northern Territory, the<br />
Government has decided to create a National Park in the Northern<br />
Territory to be called the Kakadu National Park. It will comprise<br />
1450 square miles; it is to be gazetted along the original boundaries<br />
suggested by the Planning Committee for it. The position of uranium<br />
mining interests inside the Park will be reviewed in the light of this<br />
decision. This represents a major breakthrough in conservation in<br />
Australia. The park is one of truly international significance. It<br />
will become one of the great National Parks of the world. The Government<br />
will also be considering making further additions to it. It is as an<br />
important part of the National Estate as the Great Barrier Reef and<br />
Ayers Rock; it contains a wide diversity of important parts of the<br />
National Estate including sites of great importance to the Aboriginal<br />
I-eople and some significant wetlands. Conservation interests regard<br />
Kakadu National Park as of importance at least equal to that of<br />
La1 e Pedder. In this case, only the Australian Government is involved.<br />
B3y acting irt this way the Australian Government is demonstrating to<br />
t~ e Australian people that within its own territories, within its own<br />
jurisdiction, it is taking its responsibilities in conservation<br />
sQriously. The Government agreed to amend the Navigation Act to require<br />
ships to lodge voyage plans and subsequent position reports.<br />
Are there any questions.<br />
QUESTION: This morning Senator Cavanagh announced tbat he decided<br />
tO dismiss Senator Georges from the Board of the main turtle compan~ y.<br />
14ere you consulted in..<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Senator Cavanagh is responsible here, he was asked a<br />
quiestion and he answered it. I was asked a question and I answered<br />
16 too. I have no further matters to say on this. It is the Minister's<br />
responsibility. QUESTION: I understand the Director of the Rhodesian Information<br />
Centie, Mr Bradley, expected to leave Australia around December 13.<br />
Does the Australian Government intend to allow a new director to<br />
enter Australia to replace him?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Allow me to consider the situation when I see the<br />
passport. Quite clearly, I would think, the Australian Government<br />
would do nothing to promote this illegal activity.<br />
QUESTION: Can I clear up one point on the turtles. Was it a Cabinet<br />
decision to reinstate Dr Bustard on the project? </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER: Dr Bustard has never been mentioned in Cabinet.<br />
QUESTION: Was it a Cabinet decision<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Now Senator Cavanagh has answered questions on this<br />
matter. He has answered all these questions.<br />
QUESTION: Was it his decision?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Of course, it is his responsibility and he is well<br />
able to fulfil it.<br />
QUESTION: When you spoke of the Northern Territory uranium leases, he<br />
mentioned a decision a week ago on mining leases in the Northern<br />
Territory. I may have forgotten it, but I don't remember any decision<br />
that you publicly made on it.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I thought that Dr Patterson had made an announcement<br />
later.<br />
QUESTION: No sir.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Oh well, I thank you for correcting me.<br />
QUESTION: Can I now ask....<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well, no leave I will not be making any<br />
statement on it.<br />
QUESTION: It has been reported that the South Australian Branch of<br />
the A. L. P. is doing nothing and the W. A. Branch is doing virtually<br />
nothing in support of the prices and incomes referendum, and if<br />
this is so, do you think they are acting contrary to the decision<br />
of the Federal Executive and do you think their reported lack of<br />
action would seriously jeopardise a successful YES vote on Saturday?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I only go on what is in the newspapers here. I am<br />
surprised if the reports are true because I believe they would be<br />
going against the letter and certainly the spirit of the Federal<br />
Executive decision on this matter. The Federal members in South<br />
Australia are, I know, taking steps themselves to see that the case<br />
for a YES vote in both the prices referendum and the incomes referendum<br />
is put properly to the people of South Australia. I, myself, have<br />
been in touch at first hand, as you know, in the last few days with<br />
both the Queensland Branch and the New South Wales Branch of the Labor<br />
Party and both are pursuing an active campaign in support of both<br />
the prices referendum and the incomes referendum. I haven't been<br />
in direct touch with the other branches for some time. I am visiting<br />
Perth next Friday.<br />
QUESTION: Would the Government suppor't an amendment moved by the<br />
Liberal Party in the Senate to the State Grants ( Schools) Bill which<br />
added $ 5 million to the Government's projected 694 million dollars<br />
cost in order to continue per capita grants to those schools which<br />
will lose out on the present needs policy which the Government is<br />
proposing? </p>
<p>-6-<br />
PRIME MINISTER: There has been no -amendment moved by any of the<br />
Opposition parties in the Senate to the State Grants ( Schools) Bill<br />
which was passed by the House of Representatives a week ago. The bill<br />
will come up for debate in the Senate I suspect this week. Obviously<br />
the Government will consider any amendment or amendments which any<br />
Opposition party or parties move in the Senate when it or they is<br />
or are moved. I only have to go on the newspapers as to who speaks<br />
on behalf of the opposition in these matters. I gather that there<br />
is some dispute as to whether Senator Rae is the Opposition spokesman<br />
on education or the Liberal Party spokesman on education and whether<br />
he is the spokesman in the whole Parliament or just in the Senate.<br />
I don't know whether Mr Malcolm Fraser is the spokesman for the<br />
Liberal Party in the whole Parliament or in the House of Representatives<br />
alone. He assumes many mantles and going by what you gentlemen<br />
report, his activities as self-appointed spokesman at least in<br />
education and labour and foreign policy has cuased some distress to<br />
his colleagues who have been nominated by the Leader of the Opposition<br />
or have nominated themselves to these respective posts. It is all too<br />
confusing. I have no doubt a personal explanation will be sought<br />
tomorrow.<br />
QUESTION: Do you personally support the Karmel Committee's<br />
recommendation that per capita grants to A, B and C category schools<br />
shoiuld be phased out over two years?<br />
PATME MINISTER: I support the Government's decision on this matter.<br />
Thc Karmel Committee unanimously recommended a program for upgrading<br />
Schools on the basis of needs by grants by the Australian Parliament<br />
for the scholastic years 1974 and 1975. It had this to say about<br />
Category A schools: " Category A schools' . or perhaps I suppose<br />
you will recall that the general objective of the Karmel Committee<br />
wa 5 to sac that all schools in Australia should, in six years, by<br />
1970, achieve a minimum standard of instruction and accommodation<br />
and equipment that is by 1979 and it set targets for that purpose<br />
fLor the Government schools and the non-government schools and it<br />
cat. Qqorized the non-government schools A to H. It had this to<br />
" Category A schools already use a volume of resources that well<br />
Qxceeds tL-he 1979 targets; and the Committee believes that Government<br />
assistance to these schools cannot be justified." I would agree as<br />
an individual with that finding and the Governmenit agrees with that<br />
f~ ndilc. The Committee proceeded: " However all schools are presently<br />
recevingc $ 62 per annum per primary pupil and $ 104 per annum per<br />
secondary pupil. The Committee feels that the sudden termination of<br />
financial aid on six months' notice could place some schools within<br />
c~ tegory A in temporary difficult-,". I interpose there because you<br />
w ilt remiember that tche report of the Committee was made at the end<br />
o~ f last-may. " Hfence the gradual phasing out of assistance over 1974<br />
and 1.975 is recoiainded, This implies that in 1976 schools whose<br />
resource falls in category A should receive no general recurrent<br />
assistance". Now the Government believes that in view of the findings<br />
of the 1Yarmel Commaittee the unanimous finding of the Karmel<br />
Cenw'iittee, this committee drawn from all types of schools in Australia<br />
that Government assistance to category A schools cannot be justified.<br />
Trhe Government believes that in view of that finding by the Committee,<br />
we-didn't believe that we could justify the additional expenditure<br />
involved in paying these category A schools these amounts during<br />
1974 and 1975. You will notice that this finding was made the<br />
sudden termination of financial aid on six months' notice is it<br />
was, in fact, a bit more than six montbs' notice. </p>
<p>COMMENT: Seven months.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes but the schools don't open until February do<br />
they? It would have been eight months'notice really wouldn't it?..<br />
" Could place some schools within category A in temporary difficulties.<br />
There has been quite a deal of reassessment by the Karmel Committee<br />
of the schools which it originally placed in category A. A great<br />
number of those schools have now been placed in lowerly categories<br />
and accordingly would continue under the Government's decision to<br />
receive the amounts that the Karmel Committee unanimously recommended.<br />
Now I would imagine that now there would be no schools which, in the<br />
Karmel Committee's view, would be in temporary difficulty if they<br />
did not receive those amounts in 1974 and 1975.<br />
QUESTION: Is your rejection of that recommendation quite irreversible?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I have already answered a question about this on<br />
the basis that there might be amendments moved in the Senate.<br />
QUESTION: Is it irreversible?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I said that we would consider any amendm ents moved<br />
in the Senate when they are moved.<br />
QUESTION: Your announcement of the appointment of an Administrator<br />
to the Northern Territory after such a long time without one where<br />
there was a fairly easy devolution of power to the Secretary of the<br />
Department of the Northern Territory which you created. In view of<br />
the fact that there is no longer a Northern Territory administration,<br />
what was the need to complicate the administration of the territory<br />
by appointing Mr Nelson to this largely redundant and archaic post<br />
up there?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: The position is not archaic or redundant until some<br />
of the Acts covering the Northern Territory are amended. The Government<br />
is committed to proposing some form augmented form of self-government<br />
for the Northern Territory before the end of 1974. You will remember<br />
that the Party discussed this at the Federal Conference in Surfers<br />
Paradise in July. I haven't got the platform with me but I am pretty<br />
sure I correctly state it that the Government is committed to<br />
introduce a form of augmented self-government in the Northern Territory<br />
by the end of 1974. Until the amendments have been made to the Act<br />
covering the Northern Territory there are still responsibilities falling<br />
to the Administrator. He is named in those Acts, and there can be<br />
something inappropriate or embarrassing in the Secretary of the<br />
Department of the Northern Territory purporting to disallow or suggest<br />
amendments to ordinances passed by the Legislative Council of the<br />
Northern Territory. Furthermore, it wouldn't bq proper to reserve all<br />
ordinances to the Governor-General. We could use that device, but it<br />
is more appropriate to have an Administrator performing the functions<br />
which the statutes still impose on a p :-son holding such a position.<br />
I would expect that Mr Nelson will hold the position until the end of<br />
next year.<br />
QUESTION: Does the Government intend to bring the States Grants<br />
( Schools) Bill to a vzt*-c in the Senate this session of Parliament?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes, certainly. </p>
<p>-8-<br />
QUESTION: If the Senate votes to defeat Clause 66 in the Bill, will<br />
the Government then reconsider the Bill in the House of<br />
Representatives during this session of Parliament?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I would expect the Government would not accept the<br />
continuation of the 1972 legislation. Clause 66 of the States Grants<br />
( Schools) Bill 1973 repeals the operation of the States Grants ( Schools)<br />
Bill 1972 in respect of the next four scholastic years 1974, 1975,<br />
1976 and 1977. In the House of Representatives you will remember<br />
that Mr Malcolm Fraser, the only Opposition member to speak on the<br />
clause, urged the defeat of that repealing clause in the Bill and all<br />
the members of the Opposition in the House of Representatives at<br />
the time voted to defeat to delete Clause 66. Obviously the<br />
effect would have been and Mr Fraser expressed the objective of<br />
retaining the 1972 legislation. Now the 1972 legislation proceeds on<br />
a completely different basis and philosphy to the 1973 legislation.<br />
The 1972 legislation made no provision for Government schools and it<br />
made the same provision per pupil of all non-government schools whether<br />
they were in category A, B, C, D, E, F, G. or H. The 1973 bill which<br />
the Government introduced and which the House of Representatives<br />
passed and which the Senate is to consider this week, makes provision<br />
for Government schools; it makes varied provision graduated provision<br />
for non-government schools according to their needs. The total<br />
provision in the 1973 Bill is three times that in the 1972 Bill.<br />
The Government quite clearly would not accept the continuation of the<br />
1972 Act. However, the Senate would have to agree to the repeal of<br />
tile 1972 Act. The Government would not accept the 1973 Bill without<br />
thQ repeal the deletion of the 1972 Act.<br />
QULESTION: There would be no point in taking it back to the Reps<br />
thiS session if the Senate did not agree to vote for Clause 66?<br />
F2i'E MINISTER: It would depend, of course, on the form in which the<br />
dealt with the Bill. It might move amendments or purport to.<br />
There is, of course, clearly the question whether the Senate could<br />
ca. a-ry an amendment which increased expenditure because expenditure<br />
cannot be above the amount which the Governor-General asks by his<br />
snessage to each House. The Senate might, however, make a request.<br />
NDcbviously, one waits to see what form any motion in the Senate takes,<br />
QUJESTION: If the Senate rejects Clause 66, that's it for this session<br />
' ariiament, is it?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well there again one has to wait to see if there are<br />
any other motions that the Senate carries in respect to the StateF<br />
GF6. nts ( Schools Bill 1973. But even if the only thing it does is to<br />
doiete Clause 66, i. e. continue the 1972 Act, even if that is all it<br />
dioes, it will have to come back to the House of * Representatives to<br />
see if the House accepted the Bill as so amended.<br />
QUESTION: This session or next session?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well it depends on what days we are sitting. I would<br />
expect the Senate would decide that matter this week, and in those<br />
circuinstances, the House of Representatives can consider it this<br />
week or next.<br />
QUESTION: If the Senate makes a request for an amendment will you<br />
consider that well let's put it this way: Before you consider it will<br />
they have to repeal Section 66 of the present Schools Bill? </p>
<p>A -9-<br />
PRIME MINISTER: It is not for me to suggest amendments or requests in<br />
the Senate. It is really up to the various personalities in the<br />
Liberal Party and each House and various opposition parties to sort<br />
this matter out for themselves. But it would be quite easy, I image,<br />
for the Senate to carry motions or requests quite irrespective of<br />
Clause 66. Clause 66, may I repeat, deletes or repeals last year's<br />
Act in its operation for the next four scholastic years.<br />
QUESTION: What I am asking is will you consider.... is it a proposition,<br />
a condition, to consider any request that they pass Section 66 for the<br />
repeal of the existing legislation. Is that a pre-condition before<br />
you will consider any request from the Senate?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I think I have made it quite clear on this. I don't<br />
believe the Government would accept the continuation of the per capita<br />
grants the same payment per pupil for the richest, best endowed,<br />
best staffed, best equipped, best housed schools in-Australia as for<br />
the poorest. I don't believe that we would accept such a proposition.<br />
I don't believe the Australian people would accept such a proposition.<br />
After all, the proposal that Australian Government assistance for<br />
non-government schools should be allocated on the basis of needs as<br />
examined and recommended by an expert body was put to the people at<br />
the House of Representatives elections in 1969 and again at the<br />
House of Representatives elections in 1972. There can not have been<br />
a more thoroughly discussed proposal by any Government.<br />
QUESTION: It was reported this week that an English predecessor<br />
of yours is now on a Government pension of $ 23 a week. Do you see any<br />
inconsistency in the policy of your Government in gradually<br />
alleviating the means test on pensions but now applying it to school<br />
students? PRIME MINISTER: There is this is one of the oldest furphies<br />
and cliches in controversy, the idea that there is now some parallel<br />
between the grants which the Australian Government makes to assist<br />
s.; iools and the payments it makes to retired people. Now there is no<br />
similarity between I mean you are a newcomer to these conferences<br />
but I don't think anybody has put this up at such a gathering for<br />
years there is no means test applied to the parents of school pupils;<br />
there is, in fact, an assessment of the school itself. What services,<br />
what facilities does the school provide, and that is capable of<br />
computation and a highly skilled committee has made a computation<br />
of this before the end of last May and nobody has cavilled at their<br />
computation. The people have done their suu.. s afresh, they have<br />
looked at it afresh. Now, you do mention the case of a former<br />
Prime Minister, who has sought and receiv-d. the * age pension. * He~ is<br />
perfectly entitled to do so and retired Prime Ministers in Britain<br />
and Canada have received age pensions for years.<br />
QUESTION: I don't quarrel with that case, but it just seems to me<br />
that there are two cases of means tes' Policy.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I still can't see the comparison.<br />
Laurie Oakes from the Sun, Prime Minister.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I have been waiting and this is the last.<br />
OAK( ES: I am not going to ask whether you have read any good books<br />
lately. Mr Hamer.... </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER: I have read books on excellent subjects.<br />
QUESTION: Mr Hamer said today that he would like a national conference<br />
on the energy crisis. Could we have your reaction to that suggestion?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: The matter is well in hand. I have mentioned this<br />
before and Mr Connor has answered questions on it already. My<br />
ministers and I have the whole question under constant surveillance<br />
and if there is any matter where the State Governments need to assist,<br />
and there might be such matters in the field of distribution, then<br />
we would very promptly do so. We would welcome their co-operation in<br />
any such matters. But the question of importation of oil and petrol<br />
is not a matter for State Governments it never has been it is<br />
a matter for the Australian Government and I would take the opportunity<br />
to repeat that Australia is more fortunately situated than most<br />
countries in respect to energy resources and also the importation of<br />
those resources where we are not self-sufficient.<br />
QUESTION: In the light of the reported threats against Mr Hawke and<br />
his family, has any Commonwealth authority been instructed to<br />
investigate and report the existence of Arab activeness in Australia<br />
and the degree of their activities?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: The usual procedures are in operation and have been<br />
both before and after the reports which you have quoted. Gentlemen,<br />
i don't encourage questions on these matters as you know. Every<br />
body in public life is aware of these matters and deprecates the<br />
dScussicn of them. My predecessors did, I shall. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
