<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8661</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P J KEATING MP ESD POLICIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/09/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008661.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
4.. 104192<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
ESD POLICIES<br />
The Prime Minister today chaired another roundtable<br />
meeting of major national interest groups to discuss the<br />
development of Ecologically Sustainable Development ( ESO)<br />
policies. The following is a precis of his opening remarks:<br />
The ESD process has been very worthwhile. It has brought<br />
together a wide range of Interests and groups, who have,<br />
through the nine working groups and the intersectoral<br />
reports, made a large number of recommendations which the<br />
Government must now address.<br />
The Government remains committed to the process and to<br />
the timetable I made clear at the ESD roundtable in<br />
March. Under that timetable, a national ESD strategy will<br />
be in place by the end of the year.<br />
Since the March roundtable, we have released a draft<br />
strategy and are now taking into account the submissions<br />
received regarding that strategy.<br />
In the Budget, we announced a range of ESD measures,<br />
including funding for climate change research, work on<br />
energy efficiency, tax deductions for environmental<br />
protection measures, and feral animal control.<br />
During the year, we have also taken other actions, such<br />
as the National Waste Minimisation and Recycling<br />
Strategy, coastal zone tasks; the landcare and<br />
environment action program, and the signing of the Rio<br />
Contrary to some rep6rts, the ESD process has not<br />
* stallIr, ' ayid -irr regard -to the -proc~ ess -and<br />
recommendations, the Government now plans to:<br />
Take into account submissions on the draft strategy<br />
and comments made at today's roundtable<br />
Continue negotiations and congultations, in<br />
particular with the States, to develop a national<br />
strategy and a firm set of policies and objectives.<br />
The Council of Australian Governments meeting later<br />
this year will discuss these issues. </p>
<p>2<br />
Pursue, through consultation, the positions of<br />
States on ESD working group recommendations and the<br />
recommendations of the intersectoral reports.<br />
Determine the apportionment of responsibilities and<br />
jurisdiction for policies on particular issues.<br />
Detail the extent to which recommendations are<br />
already being implemented or locked into place in<br />
existing policy of the Commonwealth or States.<br />
Make clear what policies and actions we will adopt<br />
in relation to areas where we have sole<br />
responsibility. Also make clear, through consultations, our<br />
objectives on issues the vast majority of issues<br />
which require discussion with States and local<br />
Government, because sole or primary responsibility<br />
for implementation of those policies does not lie<br />
with Commonwealth.<br />
Some of the most important issues not in order of<br />
priority emerging from the recommendations and on which<br />
we place a high priority are:<br />
Land and water management, including salinity and<br />
the Murray-Darlinjg__ basin.--<br />
Feral animals-and other pests.<br />
Remnant vegetation cover and soil degradation.<br />
Marine protection systems, and multiple use of<br />
coastal waters.<br />
Industrial waste production and disposal.<br />
Air and water quality.<br />
Urban infrastructure problems.<br />
The environment management industry.<br />
Energy production, conservation and management.<br />
They are just some of the issues on which we place a high<br />
priority. 1 can assure everyone involved in this process that we<br />
will keep at the forefront of our thinking the<br />
recommendations of the working groups and the<br />
intersectoral reports, and finalise our policies on ESD<br />
by the end of the year.<br />
CANJBERRA 17 September 1992 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
