<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2389</transcript-id>
    <title>THE MINISTRY - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR WILLIAM MCMAHON</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/03/1971</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002389.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO NOT FOR PUBLICATION OR BROADCAST BEFORE<br />
reoTMU KI7_ T{? I1fW To/ 7Ch-Fq71<br />
FOR PRESS: PM No. 35/ 1971<br />
THE MINISTRY<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, Mr. William McMahon<br />
His Excellency the Governor-General has authorised me to announce<br />
that there will be a swearing-in of certain Ministers into their new portfolios tomorrow<br />
( Monday, 22 March). As a consequence, the Cabinet and the Ministry will then comprise<br />
the following<br />
1. Prime Minister<br />
Deputy Prime Minister<br />
and Minister for Trade<br />
and Industry<br />
Minister for Defence<br />
Minister for Primary<br />
Industry<br />
MInister for Supply and<br />
Leader of the Government<br />
in the Senate<br />
Minister for National<br />
Development and Leader<br />
of the House<br />
Treasurer<br />
Attorney-General<br />
Minister for Education<br />
af'i! Science<br />
Postmaster-General and<br />
Vice-President of the<br />
Executive Council<br />
* 11. Minister for Foreign Affairs<br />
12. Minister for Shipping and<br />
Transport<br />
13. Mirister for Labour and<br />
National Service The Rt. Hon. William McMahon, M. P.<br />
The Hon. Q Anthony, M. P.<br />
The Rt. Hon. J. G. Gorton, M. P.<br />
The Hon. Itn Sinclair, M. P.<br />
Senator the Hon. Sir Kenneth Anderson<br />
The Hon. R. W. C. Swartz, M. P.<br />
The Hon. B. M. Snedden, Q. M. P.<br />
The Hon. N. H. Bowen, Q. M. P.<br />
The Hon. David Fairbairn, D. F. M. P.<br />
The Hon. Sir Alan Hulme, K. B. M. P.<br />
The Hon. L. H. E. Bury, M. P.<br />
The Hon. P. J. Nixon, M. P.<br />
The Hon. Phillip Lynch. M. P. / 2 </p>
<p>14. Minister for External Territories<br />
Minister for Immigration<br />
16. Minister for Social Services<br />
17. Minister for Works<br />
18. Minister for Civil Aviation<br />
19. Minister for Customs and Excise<br />
Minister for Air<br />
21. Minister for the Army<br />
22. Minister for Repatriation<br />
23. Minister for Health<br />
24. Minister for the Navy<br />
Minister for the Interior<br />
26. Minister for Housing The Hon. G. E. Barnes, M. P.<br />
The Hon. A. J. Forbes, M. C. I M. P.<br />
The Hon. W. C. Wentworth, M. P.<br />
Senator the Hon. R. C. Wright<br />
Senator the lion. Robert Cotton'<br />
The Hon. D. L. Chipp, M. P.<br />
Senator the Hon. Tom Drake-Brockman,<br />
D. F. C.<br />
The Hon. Andrew Peacock, M. P.<br />
The Hon. R. McN. Holten, DA. P.<br />
Senator L Greenwood, Q. C.<br />
Dr. M. G. MacKay, M. P.<br />
The Hon. Ralph J. Hunt, M. P.<br />
Mr. K. M. K. Cairns, P.<br />
I have proposed to His Excellency that Senator 1. J. Greenwood, Q. C.,<br />
Dr. M. G. Mackay, M. and Mr. K. M. K. Cairns, M. P. be sworn as Members<br />
of the Federal Executive Council.<br />
The first 13 Ministers named will comprise the Cabinet.<br />
I foreshadow that a proposal will be put before Parliament for the<br />
amendment of the Ministers of State Act 1952-1968 to provide for an increase in the<br />
number of Ministers from twenty-six to twenty-seven. Providing Parliament has<br />
passed, and assent has been given to, the necessary amendments, I shall<br />
recommend to His Excellency the appointment of an additional Minister who will<br />
administer the Department of the Vice-President of the Executive Council. In the<br />
meantime, the Postmaster-General will administer the Department.<br />
at 2 p. m. Monday's swearing will involve nine Ministers. It will take place<br />
I mention the following administrative arrangements<br />
Mr. Wentworth and Senator Wright will continue their functions<br />
in relation to Aboriginal Affairs and Tourist Activities respectively.<br />
Mr. Peacock will continue as Minister assisting the Prime Minister. / 3 </p>
<p>It is intended to appoint in due course certain Assistant Ministers<br />
or Parliamentary Under-Secretaries who would be sworn of the Executive Council<br />
and assigned to assist particular Ministers. At that stage the present " Minister<br />
assisting" arrangements will be reviewed. I am of the strong view that it is<br />
desirable to proceed on these lines, because of the growing complexity of government<br />
and the need for additional members of Parliament to gain experience both in the<br />
legislative and administrative fields.<br />
I mention also that the outgoing Minister for Labour and National<br />
Service, Mr. Snedden, now to be Treasurer, will, for the time being, have control<br />
of industrial relations policy.<br />
CANBERRA 21 March 1971 NOTE: This is embargoed until<br />
10.00 pm, Sunday 21 March 1971<br />
L </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
