<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8987</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J. KEATING MP INTERVIEW WITH MICHAEL BRISSENDEN, ABC &quot;PM&quot; 4 OCTOBER 1993</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/10/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008987.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL 4. Oct. 93 17: 372 No. 00? P. 01/ c<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
INTERVIEW WITH MICHAEL BRISSENDEN, ABC 4 OCTOBER 1993<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF ONLY<br />
MB: Prime Minister, welcome to ' PM'.<br />
PM: Michael.<br />
MB: It doesn't matter really what you think of Dr Hewson's actions, calling<br />
him an ' undemocratic vandal' is not going to help the Budget through<br />
the Senate is it'?<br />
PM: No, it is not a matter of name calling, it is making clear what is on here.<br />
It takes 38 votes to block Budget measures. Dr Hewson has 36 of the<br />
38 votes. He has been meeting with Independents in the Senate to<br />
add to his 36 and I am just making the point that does Dr Hewson now<br />
concede and accept that any future Liberal government has forfeited<br />
the right to make its Budget and enact economic policy?<br />
That is, do his actions now lead him to conclude that being the duly<br />
elected government with a majority in the House of Representatives<br />
gives you no further right than simply to be able to negotiate a majority<br />
in the Senate?<br />
MB: Well, is that a threat? If you were in that position, would you<br />
guarantee the government those economic policy rights?<br />
PM: I made it clear last year before the election campaign and during the<br />
election campaign that Labor, in opposition, would pass the money<br />
bills of the duly elected government if that were a conservative<br />
government, including the GST. Now, I did that for good and sound<br />
reasons of convention and princi ple.<br />
MB* But what are you saying here?<br />
PM: Dr Hewson it seems to me is now under a grave obligation to spell out<br />
just what his determination to do this to the Budget means for<br />
representative democracy in Australia. That is, are governments now </p>
<p>TEL: 4.0Oct.~ 17: 32, Io. 007 P. 02/ C<br />
2<br />
I mean he seeks to be Prime Minister, he is peeved about the last<br />
election result, but he wants to come back in two and a half years time<br />
and re-compete, to get a majority in the House of Representatives.<br />
What does he think that majority is going to mean to him if in fact he<br />
seeks to rewrite the rule book by saying, all you get is the keys to the<br />
kingdom, but not the kingdom you can't pass the money legislation<br />
unless you can garner the support of Independents because 1, John<br />
Hewson, am saying from here on out there are new rules in Australian<br />
politics and those rules are that the major parties have a right to block<br />
the money legislation, the financial legislation of a government in the<br />
Senate.<br />
MB: As you say in your statement, you ask if Dr Hewson does now concede<br />
and accept that any future Liberal government has forfeited the right to<br />
frame an exact Budget policy. Does that mean that gloves are off now,<br />
that you have changed your mind and that if you were in that position,<br />
you would do what John Hewson has done?<br />
PM: No, I am just saying there is a very fine line between an Opposition's<br />
right to make political capital, to make a political point and<br />
irresponsible, intolerable behaviour.<br />
MB: When does he cross that line?<br />
PM: That is I think, a matter for the coming week or weeks. The Bills are<br />
now in the Senate and Dr Hewson has got to make it clear that political<br />
capital is one thing, but actually turning the system on its head is<br />
another. Here we are in a position where the economy is now picking<br />
up we have seen motor vehicle registrations rise in August to be 16<br />
per cent above where they were a year ago; housing finance numbers<br />
are up 30 per cent on a year ago; you have got job skilled vacancies<br />
up 26 per cent; you have got vacancies overall up 50 per cent. The<br />
economy is now in recovery phase and what is hanging over it? The<br />
passage of the Budget and the stalling of legitimate revenue measures<br />
by the properly elected government and stall for what reason?<br />
Because John Hewson didn't like the outcome of the last election.<br />
MB: But isn't that precisely the point? With respect, there has been a fair<br />
amount of political posturing from all sides. The political realities at<br />
the moment would suggest that you have to make some compromises<br />
as well to get this Budget through.<br />
PM:. But look, the Government sat dlown and looked at a range of these<br />
measures it sat down with the Democrats. Now you saw what<br />
Senator Kernot said last week, she said Senate obstructionism has<br />
gone far enough. Remember the point I made a moment ago Michael.<br />
It takes 38 votes to block a Budget measure in the Senate, to block a<br />
Budget. John Hewson has got 36 of the 38 he Is the principal<br />
blocker, he only needs the top up of a couple of Independents to make<br />
it a reality. All the focus has been on the Independents, it has been on </p>
<p>TEL: 4 . Oct 9 1-7: 29 o.-007 P.-03z/ 0<br />
3<br />
the Democrats, on the Greens and on Senator Harradine. But the<br />
blocker votes, the 36 of the 38 are standing resolutely against the<br />
Budget at the behest of John Hewson.<br />
Now, Malcolm Fraser said last week the Senate is running the risk of<br />
making Australia ungovernable, to use his words. He said it is running<br />
the risk of turning the annual Budget process into a series of bargains<br />
and trade-offs similar to those which occurred in the United States. In<br />
other words, of all things, the cloud hanging over the economy's head<br />
in a recovery phase, when we are now finally getting on with it and the<br />
place is starting to grow, is the Budget. Can I say a Budget where the<br />
revenue to,. GDP is actually falling. That is, where the a tax share, the<br />
revenue share in GDP, it is actually going down.<br />
MB: But, you have been playing politics with it too? The political realities<br />
are still there.<br />
PM: Stop this playing politics business. The Government is not playing<br />
politics introducing a Budget.<br />
MB: Well why not drop..<br />
PMV: No, hang on. The Government is not playing politics introducing a<br />
Budget. A Budget which gives away the equivalent of $ 3 billion a year<br />
in tax cuts beginning from the middle of November and a Budget which<br />
has increases on the indirect side on the revenue which are less then<br />
the tax cuts. In other words, we are raising less than we are giving<br />
away and revenue to GDP is falling. What possible basis of objection<br />
could there be to a Budget where revenue and tax to GDP are falling,<br />
where the Government is about to give away tax cuts to middle income<br />
Australians and yet the Opposition says no, for reasons of political<br />
spite will stall all this, but what we'll do is we'll hide behind a couple of<br />
Independents and put the blame on them. As if they could think they<br />
could lie doggo with 36 votes when it only takes 38 to do the trick to<br />
stop a Budget, to stop the revenue changes of a Budget.<br />
MB. Do you concede that the political realities of the Senate mean that you<br />
will have to drop the linkage between the tax cuts and the revenue<br />
measures?<br />
PM; Look, the technical linkage means nothing.<br />
MB. It means nothing?<br />
PM: Nothing.<br />
MB: So you will drop it?<br />
PM: It means nothing. Let me just make this point clear as day to you.<br />
When the Budget bills come back into the House of Representatives, </p>
<p>TEL: 4. Oct. 93 117: 32 No. 00? P. 04/ 0<br />
4<br />
the Government cannot be providing tax cuts while the other revenue<br />
base of the Commonwealth is eroding. So in other words, it Is John<br />
Hewson and John Hewson only who will spike $ 8-i10 a week tax cuts<br />
for Australians from November. So all if you like, the kick along to the<br />
economy coming from the spending of tax payers and their families,<br />
the boost to retail sales, the boost to manufacturing and consumption<br />
that is, the next needed boost to gro * wth from public demand, coming<br />
from tax cuts John Hewson is spiking for no reasons other than<br />
political spite and petulance saying I didn't win, so if I didn't win I'll turn<br />
the system on its head.<br />
MB: If the linkage means nothing then why not drop it? In effect if you did,<br />
you would get the petrol tax rise through, you'd get the first round of<br />
the whole sale sales tax increases and you would end this uncertainty<br />
wouldn't you?<br />
PM: Look, let's forget about all the technical, tricky, rinky-dink things and<br />
the rinky-dink questions.<br />
MB: Well, those are the arguments that are being used though aren't they?<br />
PM: Look, there is a Budget presented by the Government a proper<br />
Budget. A Budget which gives a stimulus now and brings the Budget<br />
to 1 per cent of GDP and deficit by 1996. In the United States they are<br />
still cheering the passage of President Clinton's Budget which was<br />
carried by one vote by Vice-President Gore in the Senate. That brings<br />
the American deficit to 3 per cent of GOP by 1996. Ours will be only<br />
one third of that and yet despite its high mindedness in economic<br />
terms and its sense in economic and social terms, in the early round of<br />
tax cuts it is being spiked by a spiteful Opposition. No basis of<br />
economic objection whatsoever.<br />
MB: Well, you're not going to move. The situation Is still going to be here at<br />
the end of this week, and at the end of next week, the end of the<br />
month, isn't it?<br />
PM: That's the point. So far, Australia's not been Informed about the course<br />
of action Dr Hewson is taking. He's hiding behind a couple of<br />
independents in the Senate, needing 38 votes to block budget<br />
measures, and having 36 of the 38 himself, resolutely opposed to it.<br />
That's why he's been attacked by the president of the National<br />
Farmers' Federation, by Malcolm Fraser, by Senator Vanstone and<br />
people on his side of politics, because what he is doing is trampling on<br />
the basic principles of the operation of the democratic system of<br />
government in this country. And that is that parties in the upper house,<br />
the Senate, pass the money legislation of the Government. Now that's<br />
not to say that every budget has gone through untinkered with. I mean<br />
many of the ones I put through in the 80s were tinkered with here and<br />
there. Small measures, small twists in some of the measures. And<br />
some Opposition people are relying on those things and saying " oh, </p>
<p>TEL: 4 . Oct 9. 17 : 32 No.-007<br />
look what happened then" but no Opposition none ever, has ever<br />
refused the passage of major budget revenue measures. This is what<br />
John Hewson is doing in trying to re-write the rule book of Australian<br />
politics.<br />
MB: Well, Prime Minister, where does it leave us? We're still at a stand-off.<br />
They're not going to change. You're not going to compromise.<br />
PM: The point is the Opposition have got to think about their position. They<br />
have to say: " We are in a position now where were we to form a<br />
Government, if we do this and at some stage in the future we form a<br />
Government, we will have forfeited the right from that point forever and<br />
always to frame and enact budgetary and economic policy. Our right<br />
as a majority elected government will only be that which we can snaffle<br />
on the highways and byways of independents in the Senate." Now is<br />
that the kind of chaos, is that the kind of uncertainty Australians want?<br />
Or do they want to get on with it with a recovery which is now well<br />
and truly underway, as we see a return to growth and employment<br />
again. And there's only one person standing in the way of that, and<br />
that's JR Hewson.<br />
MB: So you in Opposition wouldn't guarantee the smooth passage of<br />
budget bills?<br />
PM; Look, leave me to one side. I've made my position clear. I believe a<br />
Labor Opposition should pass the money bills of an elected<br />
Conservative Government. That's what I believe. I said so, when it<br />
mattered in the key weeks of an election campaign, and before. But<br />
what Labor leader in the future would be able to say to his or her party<br />
:" Look, don't stand up the Liberal Party's budgetary measures.. the<br />
reply would be, well they stood ours up, they've turned budget making<br />
on its head." I mean this is what John Hewson's doing. I mean he's not<br />
been around this place long. But he's into the conventions with a pick<br />
axe. And he's got to understand what happens with the chaos and<br />
uncertainty which will arise from It.<br />
MB: If the stand-off continues the Greens have said they would be<br />
prepared to give you the trigger for a double dissolution. Would you<br />
take it?<br />
PM: I'm not talking about double dissolutions. This is not the refusal of<br />
Supply Bills. This is not 1975. This is not the refusal of the passage of<br />
the Government's spending. This is a change in the mix of the<br />
budgetary measures on the revenue side in the main. But what it<br />
certainly means is that tax cuts which are economically right, and<br />
socially useful will be put at risk by the behaviour of Dr Hewson and<br />
his colleagues in the Senate. But as I say, more importantly, what will<br />
be put at risk are the conventions which Malcolm Fraser wrote about<br />
eloquently last week, and other people on the conservative side of<br />
politics. </p>
<p>TEL: 4.0ct. 93 17: 32 No. 00? P. 06/ 0<br />
6<br />
MB:-We could remain in an ungovernable position though, couldn't we?<br />
PM: Let's assume that word has some credence. Who is responsible. Only<br />
one person, John Hewson.<br />
MB: The budget of course isn't the only problem that you are going to face<br />
with the Senate, is it? You are going to face this problem with Mabo,<br />
with with almost any contentious legislation.<br />
PM: I got* greater changes through in the 80s as Treasurer, In the tax<br />
system than I think most other persons in that job attempted. I<br />
compromised on many things: the capital gains tax, the fringe benefits<br />
tax. I kept the core principles and changed the detail around the<br />
edges. I mean, no one can assume that you can Pass anything you like<br />
through the Senate. No one's assuming that. And that's not<br />
reasonable and it's not sensible. But, the money bills, the financial<br />
legislation of a Government, they are the core things that give the<br />
country binding, cohesion and stability. They are the things that give<br />
certainty to our style of Government. And they are done by convention.<br />
They are not done by the ruthless use of numbers.,<br />
MB: And have you compromised as far as you are prepared to go then on<br />
those budget bills?<br />
PM: We've made it quite clear right the way through that where we think<br />
there is a reasonable case to shift some of these measures we will. I<br />
mean, we've done that in the past. But the idea that John Hewson says<br />
that the Government has no mandate for any tax rises when we are<br />
giving even greater tax cuts is of course just a bit of nonsense.<br />
MB: So you won't shift on the tax measures?<br />
PM;. Look. We are not shifting on the key principle, and that is the<br />
Opposition in the Senate has no right to block the revenue measures<br />
of the duly elected, properly elected Government in the House of<br />
Representatives.<br />
MB: Prime Minister, thanks very much.<br />
PM, Thank you Michael.<br />
ends. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
