<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>733</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: PM 36/1963 - COMMONWEALTH POSTGRADUATE SCHOLARSHIPS - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/05/1963</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000733.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS P. M. 36/ 63<br />
CCMI'. ON-AI TH PO STGRADUJATE SCHOLARSHIP S<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister,<br />
The Rt, Hon. Sir Robert Menzies.<br />
The Commonwealth in 1959 began a scheme of<br />
postgraduate awards designed to encourage the training of<br />
research workers in Australian universities. The scheme is<br />
administered by the Commonwealth Scholarships Board in<br />
co-operation with the universities. In each of the first<br />
three years 100 awards were available. In 1962 the<br />
Comonwealth Scholarships Board advised that the quality<br />
of applicants was such that an increase in the number was<br />
warranted. As a result 125 awards were made in 1962.<br />
Following a further review by the Commonwealth<br />
Scholarships Board, the Government has authorised the Board.<br />
to offer additional awards this year and in future years.<br />
It is expected that by 19,64 the quality of candidates will<br />
justify more than 200 awards yearly,<br />
The availability of so many qualified young graduates<br />
is an indication of th.-level of work of our Australian<br />
universities as well as of the quality of the students. The<br />
fact that universities are able to provide post-graduate<br />
training for those incixeasitig rnumbers of Commwonwealth<br />
Scholarship award holders, as well as for Australian and<br />
overseas students holding other awards, is evidence of the<br />
development in the past few years of advanced studies in<br />
this country,<br />
This is gratifying because it is from pcrsons under-taking<br />
this advanced training that we will recruit not only the<br />
future research workers of the Commonwealth, but also many<br />
members of the larger teaching staffs in our universities,<br />
technical colleges, teachers colleges and other institutions<br />
of higher education,<br />
The Government has also examined a report of the<br />
Scholarships Board on the operation of the Commonwealth<br />
Scholarship Scheme. Under this scheme, since 1961 some<br />
! 4,000 open entrance awards have been available annually and<br />
in addition the Board is authorised to offer later years<br />
awards to students who have successfully started university<br />
studies. The rising standard of applicants for Commonwealth<br />
scholarships was noted, as wel~ l as the success of the Scheme<br />
in encouraging able students to undertake university studies.<br />
No immediate changes in this Scheme ave proposed, but another<br />
review will be made later this year.<br />
CANBERRA<br />
May 8, 1963 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
