<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4009</transcript-id>
    <title>THE DEPARTMENTS OF INDUSTRY AND COMMERCE AND BUSINESS AND CONSUMER AFFAIRS</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/12/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004009.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
ALIA<br />
_ Y 4.<br />
^~ uSrRA3A.<br />
PRIME EINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS DECEMBER 19i 1975<br />
THE DEPARTMENTS OF INDUSTRY AND COMMERCE AND BUSINESS AND'CONSUMER<br />
AFFAIRS The division of responsibility between the new Departments of<br />
Industry and Commerce and of Business and Consumer Affairs is<br />
a logical development under the Government's proposals to<br />
streamline administration and eliminate duplication.<br />
The Department of Industry and Commerce is under a Minister<br />
who is a member of the Cabinet.<br />
It is. the principal contact point for industry, as well as being<br />
the policy making Department, drawing together matters relating to<br />
tertiary industry and manufacturing industry.<br />
The Department of Business and Consumer Affairs groups the<br />
regulatory bodies, which are removed from the purely legalistic<br />
Attorney Generals Department. The result will be to give them<br />
a more practical application while ensuring that the interests<br />
of consumers are taken into account adequately in any decisions<br />
which are made.<br />
The decision to place under one Ministry such agencies as t~ ie<br />
Industries Assistance Commission, the Temporary Assistance Authority,<br />
the Prices Justification Tribunal, and the Trade Practices Commission-is<br />
in accordance both with the recommendations of the Jackson<br />
Committee and with sound administrative practice. </p>
<p>it should lead to rationalisation', consistency and improved<br />
communication. Industry and commerce will be looking to the Department of<br />
Industry and Commerce as an ally in putting matters before<br />
the Industries Assistance Commission just as rural industry<br />
will be looking to the Department of Primary Industry..<br />
It is important therefore that the IAC should be in a<br />
neutral department where the interests of the community<br />
as a whole can be weighed.<br />
There is no question of limiting access by industry to the<br />
IAC, or of restricting references made to it.<br />
* Ministers a nd expert officers from other Departments will<br />
continue to play important roles in referring matters to the<br />
Commission and in dealing with its reports.<br />
I am sure that industry will notice an improvement in its<br />
relations with the IAC from these administrative arrangements. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
