<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9109</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF DOORSTOP INTERVIEW WITH THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON. P.J. KEATING, MP KIRRIBILLI HOUSE, SYDNEY, SUNDAY JANUARY 30 - WERRIWA BY-ELECTION</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/01/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009109.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF DOORSTOP INTERVIEW WITH THE PRIME MINISTER THE<br />
HON. P. J. EATING, NP<br />
KIRRIBILLI HOUSE, SYDNEY, SUNDAY JANUARY 30 W WERRIWA BYELECTION<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF ONLY<br />
PM: Do you want a comment on the by-election? It was a<br />
very standard by-election result, a sort of " as you<br />
were" result, a six per cent swing against the<br />
government is at the bottom range of par for the course<br />
for by-elections. A couple of years ago when we-had<br />
by-elections in Adelaide and Oxley when Mr Howard was<br />
leader of the Liberal Party the swings were double<br />
digit swings, 10 per cent, that sort of order. I think<br />
the difference between mue and Dr Howson on this byelection<br />
in Werriwa Is that him party will be very<br />
unhappy with result today and mine is very happy and 1<br />
congratulate Mark Latham on a campaign wall fought and<br />
I think as a result of this you will hear the knives<br />
sharpening in the Liberal Party, you will see a very<br />
desperate Dr Hewson jump out of the boxes at Question<br />
Time this week. Telecom would have had a great fillip<br />
this morning from the calls in the Parliamentary<br />
Liberal Party saying, well there it is, this fellow has<br />
not won one political contest since he's been Leader of<br />
the Opposition, not a general election and not even a<br />
decent swing in a by-election. So if you hear the<br />
clattering, you'll know what it is, it's the sharpeners<br />
at work.<br />
J: You mentioned mr Howard, does that mean you're pushing<br />
John Howard...<br />
PM: No, no. They're the only things to compare against,<br />
simply to compare against the by-elections which were<br />
on a couple of years ago in Oxley, in Brisbane where<br />
the swings were the order of 10 per cent. Six per cent<br />
against the Government is a standstill result in a byelection<br />
and if the Liberal Party is looking for any<br />
comfort, if Dr Hewson's looking for any endorsement<br />
from this he is really, I think, sadly mistaken. I'll </p>
<p>bet if there is any sort of frequency counter inside<br />
Telecom, or Optus indeed, today, you can bet the<br />
Liberal Party's frontbench has really sent it up on the<br />
scale this morning.<br />
J: When you say a standstill result, does that mean the<br />
Labor Party is content to stand still at the moment as<br />
far as the electorate is concerned?<br />
PM: It means the electorate is basically continuing to<br />
support the Government and the opportunity that any<br />
group of constituents have to express an opinion in a<br />
by-election, well they have to the order of six per<br />
cent. It's a good result for us. Thankyou very much.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
