<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>458</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: COMMON MARKET DISCUSSIONS - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER AND MINISTER FOR TRADE, MR. J. MCEWEN</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/02/1962</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000458.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS. No. 110<br />
COMMlVON MARKET DISCUSSIONS<br />
( Statement by the Deputy Prime Minister and Minister for Trade,<br />
Mr. J. MoEwen)<br />
The Minister for Trade, Mr. McEwen, today confirmed<br />
press reports that Australia was seeking the right to be present<br />
and to speak during the negotiations between Britain and the<br />
E. E. C. countries at times when matters affecting Australia's<br />
trade interests were under discussion.<br />
" This question," said Mr. McEwen, " is regarded as one<br />
of very great importance by the Australian Government. We<br />
discussed it with Mr. Duncan Sandys the Secretary of State for<br />
Commonwealth Relations, when he was in Australia last July.<br />
The communique which described the talks between Mr. Sandys and<br />
Australian Ministers made it plain that the Australian Government<br />
considered that Australia should be in a position to negotiate<br />
direct on Australia's behalf when details and arrangements<br />
affecting items of Australian trade were being discussed."<br />
The Australian Government, Mr. McEwen explained, felt<br />
that the case for Australia's export industries could not be<br />
put by anybody as well as by Australia. It was not enough to<br />
be consulted from a distance. Australian Ministers believed<br />
it essential that when the discussions in Brussels got on to<br />
wheat or dried fruits, or other commodities which Australia<br />
exported to Britain, then Australia should be inside the<br />
negotiating room, aware of what was going on and in a position<br />
to explain the nature of Australia's trade interests.<br />
Mr. McEwen said that the British Government had readily<br />
agreed that it would, at an appropriate time, raise the question<br />
with the Common Market countries of Australia's participation<br />
in the negotiations. " Of course," said Mr. McEwen, " Australia does not<br />
and cannot claim to take a full part in the negotiations which<br />
concern the conditions of Britain's possible entry into the<br />
Common Market. The sta; tus which Australia seeks, and which </p>
<p>-2-<br />
Britain supports, is one that would give Australian representatives<br />
an appropriate basis to speak on matters that<br />
bear directly on Australian trade interests that stand to<br />
be affected by the possible entry of Britain into the<br />
Common Market." Mr. McEwen said that the Governments of the Six<br />
had been made aware of the views of the Australian Government<br />
on this matter. They would know how strongly the Australian<br />
Government felt about it. They would, he hoped, see advantage.<br />
to themselves as well as to Australia and Britain in having<br />
Australian representatives present when the discussions<br />
concerned arrangements for products involved in Australia's<br />
trade with Britain.<br />
p " Last week," said Mr. McEwen, " Britain raised this<br />
matter of Australian participation at one of the regular<br />
meetings of the senior British and Common Market officials<br />
carrying on the negotiations. It was agreed at this meeting<br />
that the matter would be taken up at the next meeting,<br />
scheduled for February 22nd, of British and Common Market<br />
Ministers," " Australian producers and exporters,"' Mr. McEwen<br />
added, " can be essured that the Austra-, lian Government has<br />
spared no effort to secure the right to be present and to<br />
speak on appropriate occasions during the negotiations in<br />
Brussels. " The A'ustralian Government appreciates the support<br />
being given by Britain to Australia's desires in this matter<br />
but clearly it now rests with the Common Market countries to<br />
decide whether to accede to the reasonable request that has<br />
formally been put forw-rd by Britain on Australia's behalf."<br />
Canberra, 7th February, 1962. 14/ 62 T </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
