<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>196</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R G MENZIES, CH, QC, MP, AT THE BRIGHTON TOWN HALL ON WEDNESDAY, 13TH JULY 1960</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/07/1960</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000196_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTI. i, THE RT. HON.<br />
RTO. wGN]. MHEANLZL IEOSN, JEDNEJS4 3_ HJLYA T T_ H96E o BRIGHTON<br />
~ 3TH JLYl6<br />
Sir, Parliamentary colleagues and ladies and gentlemen:<br />
In speaking to you tonight I want to say something<br />
about affairs inside Australia. Although one or two sections<br />
of the newspapers don't appear to like it, I would also like to<br />
say something about affairs outside AustrCiia, because not for<br />
the first time in our history they are of vital literally<br />
vital importance to the people of this country. And a Prime<br />
Minister who is not prepared to say something about them, is<br />
not fit for his office.<br />
But, Sir, before I pass on to that I want to say<br />
something about affairs inside Australia. And in particular I<br />
would like to say something very brief supplementing wh-' my<br />
distinguished colleague Senator Gorton and the candidate aave<br />
said to you about the development in this country over the last<br />
ten years. I have yet to encounter anybody and I will warrant<br />
that none of you have encounte-' ed anybody who is prepared to<br />
say that the people of Australia, by and large, in material<br />
terms, are not better off today than we ever were in the history<br />
of Australia. I don't need to quote individual statistics.<br />
The fact is I just put this to all of you that if we could<br />
go-back.-to--thetime-hen--we were-children, go back to our<br />
parents and our grand-parents and ask them to imagine the state<br />
of life in whihc 95 j of us live today, they wouldn't have<br />
believed it possible. Have the people re-elected us because<br />
things have been going bad? Or haie they re-elected us because<br />
they felt, year by year, election period by election period,<br />
that things were going wiell. Now I don't need to repeat all<br />
these statistics. Statistics are frightfully interesting<br />
things. I much prefer to say to the human beings who are here,<br />
and who may be listening: you test it for yourself: l'k back<br />
over your own experience. What is it that a divided Labour<br />
Party with Leader quarrelling with Deputy Leader, with factions<br />
fighting around every corner, what is it that the Labour Party<br />
can give you which you haven't had from your own Government.<br />
That is a fair simple test and all I ask is that sensible<br />
people s :, uld think about it,<br />
Now I have taken some interest, casual interest, in<br />
trying to follow the to and fro of my opponents, particularly my<br />
good friend Arthur Calwell. ( Interjecticn: How can you, you're<br />
never in the country) Now, wait a moment, wait a moment son.<br />
( Interjection: You're never in the country) Oh, is that so?<br />
( Laughter) You know I always know when I am winning because<br />
when I am winning somebody tries to make incoherent noises so<br />
that I won't be heard. I want to tell you I am too long in the<br />
tooth for that. Sir, my good friend Arthur Calwell, the Leader of the<br />
Opposition, he leaps on to a band waggon have you noticed<br />
it? every morning. It's a different band waggon. If he<br />
reads a criticism in a newspaper which is not difficult<br />
then that is his policy for the day. ( Laughter) Or at any<br />
rate until the afte rnoon newspapers appear, when that is the<br />
policy for the evening. ( Laughter) And that is very amusing.<br />
I enjoy Arthur. I've enjoyed him for many years. I hope to<br />
enjoy him for many years to come. ( He enjoys you too!) : 1-<br />
couldntt enjoy anything more. But what is he going to do about<br />
all these things? Have you discovered how he proposes to<br />
improve the present state of Australia. I am not talking about<br />
funny little doctrinaire ideas about socialism and so on </p>
<p>they are all so stupid that most people in Australia reject<br />
them out of hand and most of the Labour men apologise for them.<br />
I wonder if you know that this Labour Party whihi<br />
moans and groans about Social Services and is prepared to offer<br />
everybody pie in the sky, I wonder if you know that in the last<br />
year in which they held undisputed power in the Federal<br />
Parliament, 1949, they spent in the last full financial year,<br />
1948-49, of what I will call for this purpose, the Calwell<br />
Government, the total payments of Social Services, a topic now<br />
dear to their hearts, was œ 80m. and that in our last completed<br />
year of office it was œ 300m. The œ 80m. boys come along and<br />
promise you everything. Je perform. We have never made a<br />
Social Services promise and don't put your hand up to your<br />
face, it doesn't improve you we have never made promis s<br />
that we have not performed. ( Interjection). Oh, yes. I know<br />
all about that. How many pounds a week do you earn, sir? He<br />
can't answer that, you see. The fact is that he is earning<br />
about four times as many pounds a week now as he could have<br />
earned in 1949. ( Interjection) ' Value back in the pound'<br />
Value in the standard of living in Australia, yes. And nobody<br />
could deny not even my vociferous friend that the standard<br />
of real living in Australia is at an all time high in the<br />
history of the country. Nobody could deny that our provision<br />
for the poor and the aged, the invalids, the pensioners, is at<br />
an all time record in the history of Australia. What I want to<br />
know is what, at this by-election, at which apparently the<br />
Labour Party has given up the ghost and is not appearing at all<br />
except to hand out cards on Polling Day, what are they telling<br />
you that they are going to do for Australia which we can't do<br />
and haven't done and are not doing? Now that is a very sensible<br />
fair question. And that, in reality, is the only question that<br />
you need to worry about, I venture to say, in this election.<br />
But Sir, my friend down here got in early about<br />
inflation and I assume that he is a Labour man. ( Interjection)<br />
Well I am assuming that, sir, your favour, ( Laughter) And<br />
assuming that he is a Labour man I an very interested in the<br />
question, because I noticed that the Leader of the Opposition<br />
has something to say about inflation. It is very interesting<br />
to me you know I am a sort of old hand now in the Federal<br />
Parliament. I have heard all these arguments tit-after time.<br />
I've heard these prophesies. And every tir. c I hoar orn from<br />
my friend, the Leader of the Opposition, I think of the<br />
expression? you remember, ' And if there be prophesies, they<br />
shall fail'? Because oe:. y prophesy he ever made has failed.<br />
I remember, and my friend Rossiter here, on the<br />
platform, will remember it: there was a by-election in Flinders<br />
and we lost it because the Leadeir of the Opposition, and in<br />
particular my distinguished and prophetic friend, Arthur<br />
Calwell, were going around saying, " In three months' time there<br />
will be mass unemployment. In three months' time youwill be<br />
ruined. Spend all your money. It won't be :. rorth saving."<br />
Dear me, it made my flesh creep even to read abcut it.<br />
( Interjections) And as a result of all this :-illy tattle, they<br />
won the Flinders by-election. EBt they didn't hold i; beyond<br />
the next General election because by that time people had<br />
discovered what arrant rubbish it was, ( Interjection) Not a<br />
change of heart, a change of knowledge They had discovered<br />
then, that although it may be the professional techniaue of an<br />
Opposition of this kind to cry Calamity, to prophesy gloom and<br />
disaster, the people who ought to be running the country are<br />
those who meet the facts and who deal with themn; who are<br />
optimists and who look forward to a general recovery of the<br />
country. And how right they were, in 1954. when that General<br />
election occurred, because from that time until this Australia<br />
has made unbroken progress. </p>
<p>But ohe one thing that my friend goes back to<br />
occasionally is inflation. Now I have many times said and done<br />
things about inflation and some of them very unpopular. But<br />
there was a time, only a few years ago, when my Labour opponents<br />
in Parliament used to describe talk of inflation as a mere<br />
bogey. " Nonsense!" they used to say: " All this talk about<br />
inflation is, I suppose, a capitalist trick to deceive the<br />
worker". I used to hear this kind of thing time after time in<br />
the Federal Parliament. What has the Labour Party offered to<br />
solve inflation. Because, after all, inflation if we may<br />
reduce it to its simplest terms is a state of affairs in<br />
w~ hich there is a greater demand than there is supply and therefore<br />
the cost of the thing you want goes up: whether it is the<br />
supply of money, or the supply of goods or the supply of<br />
services. This problem of inflation is a tremendously difficult<br />
one. Every country in the world has encountered it. Every<br />
country in the world has had to do something about it. We have<br />
been acting along the lines of a policy design to check inflation,<br />
to hold it within, bounds, and, ultimately, to arrest it.<br />
But what does the Labour Party propose about it?<br />
Now I gave myself tho trouble it was a pleasure as<br />
well as a trouble to write down on a piece of paper what I<br />
understood to be the Australian Labour Party's answer to<br />
inflation. I derived this entirely from reading in the Press<br />
what Mr. Calwoll has said and I have been reading, as far as I<br />
can, what his Deputy Leader has had to say and of course I<br />
have heard them in Parliament and I'm not unacquainted with<br />
their views and I see that the first thing that Mr. Calwell<br />
wants to do is to spend œ F60m. a year in the Northern Territory.<br />
Oh, yes œ C60m. a year in the Northern Territory. ( Interjection:<br />
A flea bite) A flea bite you say, Sir. I compliment<br />
you. Because the last year he was in office and had all the<br />
power in the world he spent alVn. And we now spend about œ a4.<br />
or œ l15m. Not too bad, when you consider everything. But he<br />
thought better of it and as he doesn't expect to win an<br />
election or to be made Prime Minister ho can afford to be a<br />
little easy, a little at large -it doesn't matter if the<br />
clothes ar~ e cut a bit too big -and therefore he says: œ C60m. on<br />
the Northern Territory. Well as an answer to inflation I don't<br />
quite follow it. ( Interjection: No you wouldn't) ( Laughter)<br />
No, of course I wouldn't. œ C60m. more money but how many more<br />
goods or services to buy. His Deputy Leader, stung to rivalry...<br />
yes, stun., to rivalry by his Leader, has undertaken<br />
to say that we ought to spend œ lOOm. a year on foreign aid.<br />
( Interjection) Of course you would. You are the kind of fellow<br />
that would make it œ 300m. like a Labour loader as long as<br />
you didn't have to find the money. ( Laughter) ( Interjections)<br />
Then, Sir, the next thing that I see they are going<br />
to do is to restore import restrictions. They must mean that<br />
because they complained violently when we took them off.<br />
Almost as violently as they complained, a few years ago, when<br />
we put them on. You know you can't be right, can you, on these<br />
matters. But he is going to restore import restrictions because<br />
there are too many goods available to be bought according to his<br />
view. He is going to increase Social Services? He would be<br />
hard put to it to beat our record. He is going to increase the<br />
cost of production. ( Interjection) Of course. " Hear, hear"<br />
says his devoted follower. ( Laughter) Increase the cost of<br />
production: that's a fine anti-inflationary measure. And<br />
above all things, Sir, to reach the height of the ridiculous, he<br />
has developed a tremendous hatred of overseas investment in<br />
Australia. pol i cy? This is the Labour Party's what anti-inflationary </p>
<p>Now just let me say something about the last one:<br />
the hatred of overseas investment in Australia usually associated<br />
with some extraordinarily profitable concern. ( Interjection:<br />
Don't you like people to be inconsistent?) I love it.<br />
( Interjection: I thought you did) It gives me such an<br />
advantage over thorn. ( Applause)<br />
Now, Sir, overseas investment. I just want to say<br />
this: that one of thO notable ovents in our period of office<br />
is that Australia, which was in no sense attractive to overseas<br />
investment when we came into office quite the contrary<br />
because of Bank nationalisation and all those eccentric affairs,<br />
has in these recent years, attracted from overseas and in<br />
spite of theories to the contrary * mostly from Great Britain,<br />
something like œ lO00m. a year of private capital investment. I<br />
am not talking about Government borrowing on Government account<br />
from the ! iorld Bank or wherever it may be, but private capital<br />
investment brought in here by private enterprise, producing<br />
enormous factories, enormous developments and employing scores<br />
of thousands of people. That has happened in the last ten<br />
years and increasingly during the last six years. Is that<br />
unimportant to us? I wonder whether we would have gone as far<br />
as we have or have had as much production as we have had,, or<br />
have had as much employment as we have had, if we hadn't<br />
received this proof of confidence from people outside, not only<br />
in the future of Australia but in the stability and honesty and<br />
reliability of its Government. ( Applause)<br />
I remember one election -not long ago speaking to<br />
a lot of employees in a vast works -not very far from here<br />
and my opponent of that time had only the previous day denounced<br />
overseas capital in A~ ustralia. I tell you I had groat fun<br />
saying to four or five thousand men: " Now of course you know<br />
that these works were established by American capital. Are you<br />
in favour of American capital? Are you hostile to the jobs that<br />
you are now occupying. This silly little Australian outlook<br />
the littlest Australian outlook: we're not to have people<br />
coming in from outside; we're not to have money coming in from<br />
outside. I tell you, ladies and gentlemen, if that doctrine<br />
prevails then Australia's progress will come to an end. Ten<br />
million people in a country of this si. in a Continent of<br />
this size, can't possibly themselves, out of their savings,<br />
produce all the capital that they need for the vast development<br />
that we must have in this country.<br />
And therofore I can only conclude that if we had a<br />
Labour Government they would say to these people: " You stay<br />
away; we don't want you". ( Interjections-Now look, if you<br />
want a little technical advice, the three of you have got most<br />
unmusical voices, you all shout at the same time and you drown<br />
each other. And the result is that all you are is a rather<br />
foolish noise off-stage, You take my tip as an old interjector:<br />
" Get the other fellows to shut-up; then speak very, very clearly<br />
and slowly." Everybody will hear you and so~ un-. oztunatsly,<br />
will I. ( Applause) Now, Sir, having said a few things about that matter<br />
might I just say something about another matter 1. which is<br />
primarily outside Australia, though it has groat concern for us.<br />
If thero is one thing that is pretty obvious in the<br />
world today we discussed it a great deal1 at the Prime<br />
Miites Conference in London it is that there is a stirring<br />
of the movements of self-government in Africa far more acute<br />
( Interjections) well if you like it, listen, ( Applause)<br />
there is a stirring of the movements of self-government in<br />
Africa, the whole of Africa Africa contains over 200 million<br />
people and this stirring is stronger, s-w-fter, than anybody<br />
ever thought of before. And the result is that we have all had </p>
<p>to think hard about what happens whten countries which have<br />
been colonies or territories want to govern themselves a very<br />
na ',. ral feeling, a feeling that grows stronger as more and more<br />
people in the community are educated and learn to think and<br />
learn to assume or assimilate the ideas of Government. And the<br />
result is that we have seen in the last few years and I've<br />
had great reason to understand about it because I have seen<br />
their leaders repeatedly we have seen the coming to life in<br />
Africa of a new Commonwealth member in the shape of Ghana up<br />
above the Gold Goast, Nigeria up above Lagos, Nigeria which is<br />
a bigger country than Ghana and which will become fully independent<br />
and fully a member of the Commonweal th inside the next<br />
month or two. We have right across Nyasaland and Rhodesia and<br />
Kenya great movements for self-government. And south of some<br />
of those on the western side you have the Congo which has now<br />
been given self-government and, unhappily, at the moment, does't<br />
know what to do about it; and is involved in riots and wars and<br />
feuds of the most formidable kind.<br />
Now, Sir, what to do about these events is a matter<br />
of tremendous concern. Because, ladies and gentlemen, the<br />
position is: it is easier for people to ask for and obtain<br />
political independence than it is for them to achieve economic<br />
independence. This is one of the great pro blerns. C ; on) Of<br />
course you don't agree but every one of the nine Prime Ministers<br />
at Downing Street agreed. And so therefore you must dissent<br />
from them. This is one of the great problems and I regard it<br />
as a great and grave problem. Because if countries become<br />
independent, politically, so that they govern themselves in a<br />
political sense, but they are economically dependent upon other<br />
people, then the Communist powers will se., an easy opportunity<br />
of coming in with help and thereby7 buying themselves into some<br />
measure of internal control. And, Sir, that is why the economic<br />
position of these countries is, in my Qpinion, a tremendous<br />
challenge to the free nations of the world. More and more and<br />
more, all the free nations of the world will have to realise in<br />
relation to these new countries that they are their brothers'<br />
keopers; that they must help; that they must do what they can<br />
to forward the economic development of these newly omerged<br />
self-governing communities. And, Sir, we had a great deal of<br />
discussion about that and a great number of studios are in hand<br />
on that point. Every seriously minded man who is concerned with<br />
world affairs recognises this problem and wishes that something<br />
may be done about it.<br />
But, Sir, there is another aspect of self-government<br />
which I venture to say is very considerably misunderstood.<br />
Indeed, some of the things I have said about it myself have<br />
been grossly misinterpreted.<br />
Last December I had occasion to take a short journey<br />
into Indonesia and a short journey into Malaya. Now here you<br />
have two countries, both of which have achieved self-govurnment<br />
quite recently: Indonesia in 1945; Malaya two or three years<br />
back. But the difference is this: that in the case of<br />
Indonesia the achievement of independent self-government was<br />
preceded by war, by conflict, by bloodshed, by hatred. And the<br />
result is that there are still echos of these things in<br />
Indonesia and Indonesia has yet to settle down into a stable<br />
Govornmon stablo economy, with no internal armed conflicts,<br />
But in the case-of Malaya: Malaya was a British colony<br />
administered originally from the United Kingdom, the one great<br />
colonial power in history which has understood the responsibility<br />
of having colonial territories.<br />
When Great Britain saw that the time was comaing when<br />
Malaya would wish to have self-government, when the Malayans<br />
would wish to govern themselves, did they do it in a spirit of<br />
reluctance or conflict? Not at all. They first of all., </p>
<p>conjointly with Australia and New Zealand, invested forces in<br />
Malaya in order to get rid of the Communist bandits, in order<br />
to give ti-e Government a chance to work and to survive. And<br />
they then, on a Constitution drafted by the representatives of<br />
half a dozen Commonwealth countries, and presided over by one<br />
Of the Lords of Appeal of Great Britainbg, av e complete selfgovernment<br />
to Malaya, under their very distinguished Prime<br />
Minister, the Thnku Abdul Rahman.<br />
And, Sir, in Malaya what did I find? Hatred? No.<br />
Friendliness? Yes in abundance. The old English and<br />
Scottish firms, Irish firms, carrying on their work ' as of old<br />
inKuala Lumpur and in Penang and so on. Up in the hills on<br />
some bydro-electric work where you would expect the Chief<br />
Engineer to be a Scot, he was one. This I think tras a superb<br />
example of how much better it is that Independence should be<br />
* achieved in friendship and with goodwill, than that it should<br />
be achieved by revolution and blood. ( Int. rjections: Wdhat<br />
about Sharpeville?) My dear sir I know nothing more than you do about<br />
Sharpoville. Now don? t get yourself misled by Sharpeville.<br />
There have been thousands killed in Africa, outside South<br />
Africa, for everyone who was killed in Sharpevillo. I regret<br />
to tell you that a groat deal of the independence that I have<br />
been talking about has been followed, if the circumstances were<br />
not right, by bloodshed; by the deaths of hundreds or thousands<br />
of people. 1. fhat I am saying is that our method, the British<br />
method, is the best. If there is to be Independencu, let us<br />
have it with friendliness. Lot us have it with , oodwill. Let<br />
us, above all things, precede it by training the colonial<br />
peoples in the art of self-government, in the art of administration.<br />
The great secret of India, for example, as a selfgoverning<br />
country today is the old Indian Civil Servant. The<br />
fact is the British trained po* ple, they brought up a great<br />
number of people, thousands of Indian people, and people from<br />
Pakistan as it is now called, and they were trained into the<br />
Civil Service, they were hiighly educated, they have become<br />
great experts I've known quite a few of them. And Sir<br />
without them, no self-government could have been instantly or<br />
very quickly, efficient. That is the whole technique of the<br />
British Colonial System and developing colonies into selfgoverning<br />
nations.-Now Sir, Ijust want to take that proposition and<br />
reduce it to a point ( Interjection) I know; I road somewhere<br />
today from some goat that people don't rant to know about<br />
affairs overseas. Eve-py thoughtful Australian does. ( Applause)<br />
Thoughtful Australians knew that these things are of supreme<br />
importance and as long as I think they are of supreme importance<br />
I shall so describe thema.<br />
I just want to bring out the point of what I hiave<br />
been saying because I am going to relate this to one of our own<br />
territories. I want to bring out the point. And the point is<br />
that provided you do your best to develop the people in the<br />
colony or territory, provided you do your best to give them<br />
education, health services, a knowledge of the instruments of<br />
governme-int and bring them to s point where they can first<br />
participate in goenetand then take it over if they are<br />
so disposed if you are pursuing that policy, as we were in<br />
Papua and Ne w Guinea, then if you get to a point whqre you<br />
think they may be you're not sure that they may be ready<br />
you think they may be that last point which may come in 1<br />
years' time, I don't know, whatever period you care to name<br />
then I say: " It is better to take some small risk of doing it<br />
a little too soon than to delay it to a point where the agitation<br />
for it breaks out into hatred and rebellion". ( Hear, hear)<br />
( Applause) </p>
<p>Now that is my view and I would have thought tb-ere<br />
was nothing very strange about it. ( Interjections) Nothing<br />
very strange about it. Do I gather you disagree with it?<br />
( What have you done for New Guinea?) Boc -usc if you d~ isagree<br />
with it you arc going to be in great trouble as a Labour man<br />
because Mr. Calwell thinks I am talking about it too soon and<br />
Mrt Whitlai-says it ought to be done now. ( Laughter) Al. I<br />
can do is toll you our view on the matter.<br />
I wouldn't be foolish enough to suggest that this is<br />
a matter that can be achieved in a few short years. Of course<br />
it can't. ( Interjections) As there has been a certain amount<br />
of reference made to what I said about this matter-or rather<br />
to what was alleged that I said I think I might quote you the<br />
verbatim report from the tape of what I said about this when I<br />
came back to Sydney a few weeks ago. ( Interjection: We got it<br />
in the Press) Oh no you didn't; that's why I am, quoting it to<br />
you. I said: '' Whereas at one time many of us might have thought<br />
that it was better to go slowly in granting Independence<br />
so that all of the conditions existed for a wise exercise<br />
of self-government, I think the prevailing school of<br />
thought today is that if in doubt, you should go sooner<br />
not later. -I belong to that school of thought now, though<br />
I didn't once. But I have seen enough in recent years to<br />
satisfy me that even though some Independences may have<br />
been premature, where they have been a little premature<br />
they have at least been achieved with goodwill. And when<br />
people have to wait too long for their Independence then<br />
they achieve itwith ill-will and that, perhaps, is the<br />
difference between British Colonial policy in this century<br />
and that of some other country."<br />
And then somebody said: " Would you apply that to New<br />
Guinea?" and I said this:<br />
" When you say ' apply that to New Guinea', yes. But that<br />
does not mean that I belong to this fancy school of<br />
thought that you write a timetable out and say that in<br />
ten years' time so and so, and in 20 years' time, so-andso.<br />
That is just silly" ( Interjection) Believe me my<br />
boy I've heard it said in other countries, very definitely-<br />
" But we are all doing a faithful job of work in Papua and<br />
New Guinea. Wie will go on doing it,"<br />
And then I went on to say " that we may get to a point<br />
or my successors may get to a point, where they say: " Well<br />
maybe if we allow then to determine their future now, it<br />
is a little premature: I would sooner take that risk at<br />
that time, than leave it too long'"<br />
Now Sir, and laidies and gentlemen, I think if I may<br />
say so that is good commonsense. That is all. Nothing very<br />
rovolulionary about that: it is good cormionsense. But,<br />
ladies and gentlemen, there is now being built up around this,<br />
some sort of idea that we ought to be out of New Guinea and<br />
Papua in a few years a few years. And the result is, if that<br />
view obtains currency, that the development of Now Guinea for<br />
self-government will be greatly postponed. Because what New<br />
Guinea and Papua need for their conomic developmeint for the<br />
development of their population, is a steady inflow of investment<br />
in those lands so that their rural-industries may be<br />
developed, their cattle industry developed: all these various<br />
things which mean a rising standard of living for the New<br />
Guinea people and for the Papuan people.<br />
All these things require confidence and investment<br />
and I do wish I could persuade people who are talking but </p>
<p>8.<br />
" Out in five years" to understand that if they are believed<br />
they will make it impossible to be out in many many mr years<br />
than that. Weo want to see a steady development as fast as<br />
possible, according to our resources. iind aftor all, we are<br />
spending a groat deal of money in New Guinea, or you are,<br />
through us. d1e want to see all these things go on. But above<br />
all things it , ould be idle to talk about giving self-government<br />
to the native inhabitants of Now Guinea and Papua unless<br />
you had developed their economy in their country so that they<br />
had industries, so that they had employmient, so that they had<br />
a standard of living of a kind that we would recognise based<br />
upon their owrn efforts in their own country.<br />
Now Sir I apologise for having discussed those<br />
miatters because, of course, apparently they have nothing to do<br />
with Balaclava. But they have a great deal to do with the<br />
future of this country: a hostile New Guinea would be deadly<br />
from Australia's point of view. A friendly Now Guinea is<br />
essential to Australia. And the right way to get it is to<br />
pursue in a porfectly normal sensible fashion, the development<br />
of this country and the developm-, ent of its people. Not being<br />
turned aside by chocr-chasers or by violent advocates on one<br />
side or the other, but going straight along the track and<br />
saying: " Our ultimate objective, as Australians, is that we<br />
shall bring these people to a point when they are fit to rule<br />
0 themselves and to determine their own future". When we have<br />
done that we will have discharged a gre2at trust for humanity and<br />
we will have brought great credit and, as I think, great<br />
security in the true sense, upon ourselves. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
