<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>269</transcript-id>
    <title>P.M NO. 2/1961 - CONTRIBUTION TO WORLD HEALTH ORGANISATION - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER AND MINISTER FOR EXTERNAL AFFAIRS, THE RT. HON. R.G MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/02/1961</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000269_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
P. M. No. 2/ 1961<br />
CONTRIBUTION-TO WORLD-HEALTH ORGANISATION<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister and Minister for External<br />
Affairs, the Rt. Hon. R. G. Menzies<br />
In 1955 the 4orld Health Organisation launched a<br />
world-wide campaign to eliminate malaria, a disease which<br />
threatens a third of the world's people. The campaign is<br />
being financed in large part by voluntary subscription to a<br />
Special Account for Malaria Eradication. In response to an<br />
urgent request from the Director-General of the World Health<br />
Organisation, the Australian Government has this year<br />
contributed œ C20,000 to the Fund.<br />
This year's contribution is larger than previous<br />
contributions, and is a token of Australiats support for the<br />
campaign and of the Government's appreciation of its<br />
objectives. The Australian mainland is virtually free from<br />
malaria, but in the Territory of Papua and New Guinea the<br />
eradication of malaria rjmains a major problem. In that<br />
Territory Australia has undertaken a fourteen year eradication<br />
programme, estimated to cost ovter two and three quarter million<br />
pounds. The success of that programme, on which last year<br />
the Administration of the Territory spent over f-200,000, will<br />
be of benefit not only to the Territory, but to the world-wide<br />
campaign which the World Health Organization is directing.<br />
CANBERRA, 7th February, 1961. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
