<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>15922</transcript-id>
    <title>Government to Tackle Congestion and Improve Liveability for Melbourne    </title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/05/2008</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Rudd Government will immediately provide $12 million towards a joint Commonwealth and Victorian Government $30 million study of projects that improve East West connections across Melbourne.</p>
<p>The study will assess the projects identified in the recent report, Investing in Transport: East West Link Needs Assessment, that proceed to the feasibility stage following the current consultation process.</p>
<p>These projects have the potential to keep Melbourne's mantle as one of the world's most liveable cities.</p>
<p>Rapid population growth and increasing travel in the city outstrip current and planned infrastructure capacity  -  increasing congestion and undermining Melbourne's liveability edge.</p>
<p>Patronage on Melbourne's trains increased by 23% over the past two years.</p>
<p>Without action, urban congestion is projected to cost families and businesses in Melbourne $6.1 billion a year by 2020, with many working parents spending more time in their cars and less time at home with their kids.</p>
<p>The Rudd Government will therefore examine these major nation-building projects that have the potential to transform the way Melbournians get around, tackle traffic congestion and reinforce Melbourne's world-renowned liveability.</p>
<p>Two innovative rail proposals include:</p>
<p>     * A new 17 kilometre Melbourne Metro rail tunnel linking Melbourne's booming western and south-eastern suburbs and providing a major increase in the capacity of the rail network</p>
<p>     * A new rail connection from Werribee to Sunshine (the Tarneit link) to significantly improve the frequency and reliability of services from Werribee, Geelong, Ballarat and Bendigo</p>
<p>These projects are estimated to cost between $7.5 billion and $8.5 billion.</p>
<p>A decision on which projects proceed to feasibility stage will be made by the Victorian Government following community consultation by the end of the year.</p>
<p>The Commonwealth Government will invest in feasible projects that meet strict criteria through the new $20 billion Building Australia Fund, outlined in last week's Budget.</p>
<p>The Building Australia Fund is designed to invest from next year in nation building projects that address infrastructure bottlenecks and ease traffic congestion in our cities and towns.</p>
<p>The Government believes it is time to invest in long-term nation-building, with a horizon that takes us beyond the incremental changes thrown up by political cycles.</p>
<p>The Investing in Transport: East West Link Needs Assessment study was prepared for the Victorian Government by Sir Rod Eddington, who is also Chair of the Commonwealth Government's Infrastructure Australia advisory council.</p>
<p>This study takes a 30-year perspective and concludes that doing nothing on urban congestion is not an option.</p>
<p>The Commonwealth Government's commitment to examine new nation building projects is on top of its substantial existing investment in Victorian transport infrastructure.</p>
<p>In 2008-09, the Commonwealth Government is investing almost $500 million in road and rail projects in Victoria, including:</p>
<p>     * $53 million for the Deer Park bypass and Leakes Road Interchange;</p>
<p>     * $24 million for the Geelong Ring Road; and</p>
<p>     * $26 million for the Dynon Port Rail Link.</p>
<p>The Government is also investing $51 million in 2008-09 to make an early start on delivering its election commitments, including:</p>
<p>     * $25 million to start the Westgate Bridge rehabilitation;</p>
<p>     * $6.5 million to start the 4A section of the Geelong Ring Road; and</p>
<p>     * $5 million to start the Western Highway duplication planning.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
