<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11406</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                 THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                 ADDRESS AT AUSTRALIAN INDUSTRY GROUP NATIONAL DINNER                 THE GREAT HALL, PARLIAMENT HOUSE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/03/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...................................................................................................</p>
<p>Well, thank you very much Mr Thomas, to your joint President, Mr Hale,</p>
<p> to my ministerial colleagues including in particular Senator Nick</p>
<p> Minchin the Minister who directly relates to your organisation, Peter</p>
<p> Reith, Robert Hill, Philip Ruddock, to Kim Beazley the Leader of the</p>
<p> Opposition, other distinguished guests, ladies and gentlemen.</p>
<p>I certainly do remember that occasion some seven and a half months</p>
<p> ago when I launched the AI Group at the National Press Club. And I</p>
<p> took the opportunity then of commending all of those who had played</p>
<p> such an important role in bringing your organisation together. And</p>
<p> I look back over that seven and a half months and I can record that</p>
<p> quite a bit has happened. We launched a tax policy a few days after</p>
<p> your group was launched. We then had a federal election during which</p>
<p> the principal issue of debate was the taxation plan detailed by the</p>
<p> Coalition. We enjoyed, those of us who were successful, the results</p>
<p> of the election and perhaps even more importantly than all of that</p>
<p> I think since the launch of your group and during the past seven and</p>
<p> a half months the true extent to which the Australian economy has</p>
<p> been able to stare down the worst economic recession the Asian-Pacific</p>
<p> region has experienced in decades has become apparent to all of us.</p>
<p>There was a time in the middle of last year when the majority view</p>
<p> amongst economic commentators was that some kind of quite significant</p>
<p> slow down was just around the corner. There was a widely held view,</p>
<p> I guess based on the experiences of past economic history in Australia,</p>
<p> that it just wasn't going to be possible for the Australian economy</p>
<p> to avoid the impact of the Asian downturn. But through the later months</p>
<p> of last year and certainly in the first three months or so of this</p>
<p> year that sentiment has turned around. And now it is no exaggeration,</p>
<p> it is no piece of empty triumphalism for somebody in my position or</p>
<p> any of my senior Ministers or people who talk about these things to</p>
<p> assert the obvious and that is that the Australian economy has performed</p>
<p> remarkably well, that we have enjoyed very high economic growth for</p>
<p> a sustained period. We have the lowest interest rates in 30 years,</p>
<p> we have a persistently lower inflation rate than we used to have.</p>
<p> In three years we have turned a deficit of $10.5 billion into a surplus.</p>
<p> We have presided over very significant levels of business investment</p>
<p> and very importantly we have been aided and you as exporters have</p>
<p> been aided by the very intelligent management of the Australian exchange</p>
<p> rate by the Reserve Bank of Australia. And all of these things have</p>
<p> come together to give to our economy a sense of strength, a sense</p>
<p> of resilience and a sense of optimism that not even the most enthusiastic</p>
<p> of us may have thought possible seven and a half months ago and indeed</p>
<p> 12 months ago.</p>
<p>So it is possible as I speak to you tonight on behalf of the Government</p>
<p> and congratulate you on the progress that has been made with your</p>
<p> new organisation over the last seven and a half months and particularly</p>
<p> to you Mr President to thank you for a thoughtful and constructive</p>
<p> speech which as this organisation and its predecessors has always</p>
<p> done, made a very good contribution to the ongoing economic debate</p>
<p> in our country. One of the many encouraging things about the taxation</p>
<p> debate which we have had in this country and we continue to have is</p>
<p> the way in which it has been possible to bring forth intelligent,</p>
<p> thoughtful debate about the long-term structure of our taxation system.</p>
<p>The core of our taxation reform is, of course, comprised in the legislation</p>
<p> that is now before the Australian Parliament. But the process of business</p>
<p> tax reform which we highlighted in the lead up to the election is</p>
<p> a very important, indeed crucial, element of the long-term challenge</p>
<p> of economic and taxation reform. And I think all of us are greatly</p>
<p> in debt to John Ralph for the way in which he has been prepared to</p>
<p> bring his great business and accounting skill and integrity to the</p>
<p> task of presiding over the taxation reform group.</p>
<p>Australia is indeed fortunate to have men and women out of the business</p>
<p> community like John Ralph who are willing to commit themselves to</p>
<p> such an important task. And I do warmly welcome the way in which your</p>
<p> group has responded tonight and has put forward its views and made</p>
<p> its constructive, intelligent, thoughtful contribution to the debate.</p>
<p> And knowing as I do the diversity of the companies that you represent</p>
<p> forming that consolidated view would not have been easy. And it is</p>
<p> an act of leadership and an act of courage on behalf of this organisation</p>
<p> to do precisely that.</p>
<p>But, ladies and gentlemen, although we gather at this dinner at a</p>
<p> time of tremendous optimism about the Australian economy, at a time</p>
<p> when because of rising real incomes, low interest rates and the lowest</p>
<p> unemployment level in eight or nine years the purchasing power and</p>
<p> the sense of optimism of the average Australian is at a very high</p>
<p> level and we are therefore entitled to feel a sense of satisfaction</p>
<p> and a sense of pleasure as Australians about that.</p>
<p>I don't speak to you in any sense of smugness or complacency</p>
<p> about that situation and mine is not a counsel of resting on our oars,</p>
<p> mine is not a counsel of saying the reform task is behind us. Indeed,</p>
<p> the reform task in the modern economy is never behind us. There is</p>
<p> no alternative in the modern globalised economy in which we all live</p>
<p> than to go on indefinitely with the process of economic reform. The</p>
<p> idea that any nation that wants to preserve a decent living standard</p>
<p> can opt out of reform, the idea that there is such an alternative</p>
<p> to ongoing economic reform is to completely misread the changes that</p>
<p> have occurred in world society over the last 20 years.</p>
<p>We are permanently part of a globalised economy. That will never change.</p>
<p> There is no going back to the creation of national fortresses where</p>
<p> barriers can be put up against the rest of the world. We may delay</p>
<p> and temper the impact of change but in the end it will envelop all</p>
<p> of us. And the intelligent response of national policy makers is to</p>
<p> take the opportunity to reform on an ongoing basis and I can't</p>
<p> think of a time in Australia's recent economic history that bodes</p>
<p> better for ongoing economic reform than in the early months of this</p>
<p> year. It is precisely because our economy is doing well, it is precisely</p>
<p> because we do have low interest rates and low inflation and a strong</p>
<p> budget position that we should embrace in a very enthusiastic manner</p>
<p> ongoing economic reform. And this is exactly the right time to be</p>
<p> reforming our taxation system.</p>
<p>I have been involved in the debate about taxation reform in this country</p>
<p> now for something like 20 years. In a former government I argued the</p>
<p> case for broad based indirect taxation. I remember giving my old political</p>
<p> adversary, Paul Keating, very strong support in the middle 1980s when</p>
<p> his Government advocated the introduction of a broad based consumption</p>
<p> tax. But in all of the occasions that it has been on the table before</p>
<p> I can't think of a time when it is more appropriate for taxation</p>
<p> reform to occur. We have low inflation, we have an opportunity to</p>
<p> grab by the scruff of the neck and consolidate even further the competitive</p>
<p> advantages that our strong economic position are providing us around</p>
<p> the world. And the boost to our exporters that a taxation reform package</p>
<p> would give. The way in which our farmers and our miners would be made</p>
<p> more competitive through the changes we have in mind in relation to</p>
<p> diesel fuel and the list goes on.</p>
<p>And on top of that, as we were reminded by Chris Richardson of Access</p>
<p> Economics only a few days ago that the planned personal income taxation</p>
<p> cuts which will provide an enormous additional boost to personal spending</p>
<p> power will, in fact, come in at the very time that some of the capital</p>
<p> spending in this country in areas like the Olympic Games and so forth</p>
<p> would be going off the boil. And Mr Richardson made the very interesting</p>
<p> observation that on past occasions when governments have delivered</p>
<p> personal income tax cuts they have often chosen the wrong time to</p>
<p> do it. And he said that on this occasion the personal income tax cuts</p>
<p> that are planned under the Government's taxation package are</p>
<p> coming in at precisely the right time.</p>
<p>Not surprisingly I argue very strongly to you as I will to any audience</p>
<p> anywhere in Australia the long-term economic benefit of the taxation</p>
<p> plan that we took to the Australian people last October. It is not</p>
<p> without importance in that debate that the detail of that plan was</p>
<p> quite unparalleled in Australian political history. No government</p>
<p> before ours had presented in such minute comprehensive detail a blueprint</p>
<p> for such major and fundamental economic change. And that is a consideration</p>
<p> that we believe should certainly not be lost on the Parliament as</p>
<p> it deliberates on that plan and makes a decision some time during</p>
<p> the next three months.</p>
<p>I have no doubt that the long-term cause of economic reform in this</p>
<p> country, I have no doubt that the long-term cause of making this nation</p>
<p> an even more competitive nation will be done a very grievous blow</p>
<p> if that plan is not implemented. And I would not want any of the people</p>
<p> who are here tonight to underestimate the determination of the Government</p>
<p> and my own personal determination to ensure that the verdict of the</p>
<p> Australian people last October on that issue is given full effect</p>
<p> to by the Parliament of this country.</p>
<p>Could I also say to you, ladies and gentlemen, that it is not only</p>
<p> in the area of taxation reform that I believe further reform and change</p>
<p> should take place. I welcome the remarks that have been made about</p>
<p> the Government's workplace reform agenda and I want to acknowledge</p>
<p> the contribution that Peter Reith, who is here tonight, has made to</p>
<p> the reform process in our Government. It hasn't always been easy</p>
<p> and there was a time almost a year ago in relation to the waterfront</p>
<p> reforms where there was no shortage of people who were ready to criticise</p>
<p> what the Government did in that area but time has vindicated those</p>
<p> decisions and the productivity improvements particularly on the Melbourne</p>
<p> waterfront have demonstrated the wisdom of the actions that were taken</p>
<p> by the Government.</p>
<p>But we have foreshadowed further reform in that area and one of the</p>
<p> principal reasons why further industrial relations reform is needed</p>
<p> is the contribution that it can and will make to providing further</p>
<p> flexibility in the Australian labour market. We are disappointed that</p>
<p> the Senate has chosen thus far to reject our attempts to entrench</p>
<p> youth wages within the Australian industrial relations system. We</p>
<p> are also disappointed thus far that those who had the numbers in the</p>
<p> Senate have rejected our attempts in relation to the unfair dismissal</p>
<p> laws. We will persevere with those measures again in the future because</p>
<p> we believe they and others are important to the long-term and sustained</p>
<p> attack on unemployment levels within the Australian community.</p>
<p>So, ladies and gentlemen, my message to you tonight is not a message</p>
<p> of smug complacency and satisfaction, it is not a message of saying</p>
<p> to you look what a terrific job has been done in relation to the Australian</p>
<p> economy. Quite naturally, I, as Prime Minister and my Ministers take</p>
<p> some pride in the Government's economic achievements. I take</p>
<p> some pride in the fact that we took the difficult budget decisions</p>
<p> three years ago which helped deliver us the economic security which</p>
<p> is now working to the benefit of all Australians. But this is not</p>
<p> an occasion for smugness and backslapping, it's not an occasion</p>
<p> to say what a great job we have done, it's an occasion to acknowledge</p>
<p> the real strength of the Australian economy. But above all, it is</p>
<p> an occasion to recognise the undeniable reality of modern economic</p>
<p> life.</p>
<p>There is no alternative to the reform process. Arguments about reform</p>
<p> fatigue are important in so far as they remind those in government</p>
<p> and indeed all of us involved in public life that the obligation to</p>
<p> reform carries with it an obligation to explain the benefits of reform</p>
<p> and the reasons for reform. And I have always believed that the Australian</p>
<p> people can be persuaded of the wisdom of economic reform if two conditions</p>
<p> are satisfied. The first of those conditions is that you must persuade</p>
<p> them that it is in the national interest. And the second of those</p>
<p> conditions is that you must persuade them that it is, generally speaking,</p>
<p> fair to all sections of the Australian community. And if those two</p>
<p> obligations are discharged then I believe the Australian people as</p>
<p> they have demonstrated in relation to all of the reforms that have</p>
<p> occurred over the last 20 years the Australian people will respond</p>
<p> to and they will support those reforms.</p>
<p>But there is no national interest to be achieved in anybody seriously</p>
<p> believing or anybody seriously arguing the proposition that in some</p>
<p> way the Australian people and the Australian economy can opt out of</p>
<p> the globalisation process, that we can turn our backs on the realities</p>
<p> of modern economic life. That option is no longer available. But in</p>
<p> asserting that reality I, of course, accept that the overwhelming</p>
<p> obligation on myself as Prime Minister and the members of my Government</p>
<p> to explain to the Australian people the ongoing benefits and the ongoing</p>
<p> advantages of economic reform. If we can seize the moment which our</p>
<p> remarkable economic strength gives us to press ahead with reform we</p>
<p> can give to future generations of Australians an even stronger economic</p>
<p> base on which they can prosper and build their lives and the lives</p>
<p> of their children.</p>
<p>Can I say to the members of the AI group which, of course, was formed</p>
<p> out of two other great industry organisations with whom I have had</p>
<p> a lot to do over the years. And as I have looked around the audience</p>
<p> tonight I recognise many familiar faces going back to some I met 25</p>
<p> years ago when I first entered Federal Parliament. I want to thank</p>
<p> your group, I want to thank its antecedents for the contribution that</p>
<p> they have made to the cause of industry in this country. I think your</p>
<p> President did us a service in reminding us of the ongoing fundamental</p>
<p> importance of manufacturing industry to the Australian economy. And</p>
<p> I admire the way in which Australian manufacturing has changed and</p>
<p> modernised particularly over the last 10 or 15 years. The way in which</p>
<p> it has picked up the challenge of successive governments in this country</p>
<p> to shift its emphasis to exports. The way in which it is in no sense</p>
<p> of shame or lack of pride in its past the way in which it has shared</p>
<p> its image of being entirely concerned with what was regarded as the</p>
<p> old traditional industries and the way in which it has embraced the</p>
<p> new technologies and the new export opportunities that go with those</p>
<p> new technologies.</p>
<p>I thank you very warmly for inviting me here this evening. I thank</p>
<p> you again Mr President for your constructive contribution to the taxation</p>
<p> debate and more particularly I thank the members of your group for</p>
<p> the tremendous contribution that you continue to make to the employment</p>
<p> of a million Australians or more and the building of the strength</p>
<p> of the Australian economy. Thank you very much.</p>
<p> [ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
