<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7870</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER CEDA ECONOMIC AND POLITICAL OVERVIEW ADELAIDE - 24 JANUARY 1990</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/01/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007870.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
CEDA ECONOMIC AND POLITICAL OVERVIEW<br />
ADELAIDE 24 JANUARY 1990<br />
I appreciate this opportunity, at the outset of the 1990s,<br />
to present my overview of the Australian political and<br />
economic scene.<br />
CEDA of course has for many years taken a close interest in<br />
both domestic and international policy. I recall with<br />
particular pleasure your conference in Sydney last May at<br />
which I launched the CEDA publication Towards Freer Trade<br />
Between Nations a book which made a significant<br />
contribution to the ' inderstanding of an issue vital to our<br />
national future.<br />
This is a timely gathering.<br />
Internationally, the past twelve months have seen profound<br />
and, in modern experience, unprecedented change<br />
spectacularly in Eastern Europe, and very encouragingly,<br />
too, in relations between the superpowers, but from<br />
Australia's vantage point even more powerfully felt in the<br />
continuing explosion of economic activity in our own region.<br />
Domestically, we witnessed the further steady emergence of<br />
an Australia that, though still grappling with shorter-term<br />
economic problems that are causing hardship, is becoming<br />
equipped as never before to tackle and conquer the<br />
challenges of the 1990s and the 21st Century.<br />
So against this background of change, the overview provided<br />
by a forum such as this is not merely useful but necessary.<br />
As we approach the next century I want to see the evolution<br />
of an Australia that is attuned to, and conscious of, these<br />
tremendous changes an Australia with several distinctive,<br />
deeply interrelated characteristics.<br />
Late last year, in a speech to the National Press Club, I<br />
outlined my ideas as to what these necessary characteristics<br />
of an emerging Australia must be. </p>
<p>I said, first, that I want to see us become a modern,<br />
growing Australian economy, shaken out of the old complacent<br />
dependence on commodity exports, re-equipped and<br />
restructured in its attitudes, institutions and technology<br />
to be fully competitive in the world.<br />
Second, I want an Australia self confidently and vigorously<br />
engaged with the world economy, and in particular enmeshed<br />
with the dynamism of Asia and the Pacific an outward<br />
looking country capable of contributing to and drawing<br />
enduring prosperity from the region a country which others<br />
wish to have as a partner because they see that we have got<br />
our own act together and are able to contribute.<br />
Third, I want an Australia committed to maintaining and<br />
enhancing the quality of life, not merely the quantity of<br />
our economic output. We must not be panicked into a strategy<br />
of industrialisation at any cost. We must enlarge our<br />
commitment to social justice; to the preservation of our<br />
natural environment; to the creation of a tolerant,<br />
multicultural, egalitarian society a society immensely<br />
vigorous because of its diversity yet uniquely harmonious<br />
because of the deep and genuine mutual respect each<br />
component group holds for all others.<br />
And fourth I want a self-reliant Australia, drawing strength<br />
from its traditional attachments to other countries but<br />
attuned to and pursuing in a hard headed way its own<br />
interests in a changing world; speaking with an independent<br />
voice; not merely fitting in with the world as we find it<br />
but helping shape it.<br />
When you look around Australia today you see abundant<br />
evidence that the attainment of these goals ambitious as<br />
they are is well within our grasp.<br />
After virtually three decades of conservative inertia,<br />
neglect and distorted priorities our vision is starting to<br />
be realised. Australians have turned the national tide,<br />
from ebb to flow.<br />
So, today, you see factories and offices infused with a<br />
greater capacity and a greater determination to modernise,<br />
to look outward, to compete. You appreciate what our<br />
creation of 1.6 million new jobs really means for<br />
Australians and for Australia.<br />
You see schools where the kids are staying on to Year 12.<br />
You see universities, technical colleges, research labs,<br />
where that most vital of resources, human knowledge, is<br />
being fostered and put to use.<br />
You see ethnic clubs, child care centres, environmental<br />
societies crucibles all of them for a big-hearted, decent,<br />
secure Australian community. </p>
<p>You see prosperity being shared, on the basis of fair and<br />
efficient systems of taxation and social justice. You see<br />
investment for productive purposes rather than the<br />
manipulation of the tax system to accrue untaxed capital<br />
gains; and you see unprecedented social assistance targeted<br />
to the people who need it, instead of the allocation of<br />
pensions to millionaires.<br />
You see Australia more actively and creatively involved in<br />
international affairs than ever, including the affairs of<br />
our region as witness for instance our initiatives on<br />
Cambodia and on new arrangements for Asia-Pacific Economic<br />
Co-operation.<br />
And let me say that as part of this transformation underway<br />
in Australia you see now a united Labor movement maturely<br />
and constructively responding to the challenges of our time.<br />
Now, none of this gives cause for complacency. This is not<br />
a time for deluding ourselves about the magnitude of either<br />
the challenges still ahead of us or the opportunities. It<br />
is certainly not a time for listening to those among us who<br />
are prepared to sacrifice our hard won gains on the altar of<br />
ideology, be it that of the New Right or, let me say, the<br />
Old Left.<br />
As I said at the National Press Club, I am perfectly open to<br />
debate about the pace of our progress towards these goals.<br />
But I shall fiercely resist those who would impede or<br />
jeopardise or reverse this progress.<br />
Nowhere is this more important than in the crucial area of<br />
industrial relations.<br />
I appreciate that your organisation is not involved in party<br />
politics but exists to conduct research and education on<br />
public affairs in a non-partisan, objective fashion.<br />
But I think you will understand that my responsibility is<br />
not merely for the analysis of good public policy but also<br />
for its implementation and, in a pre-election period, its<br />
advocacy against those who would reverse it.<br />
My concern is with the welfare of the Australian economy and<br />
people and it is with those interests that I want today to<br />
outline the dimensions, including the political dimensions,<br />
of this issue of industrial relations.<br />
As we enter the 1990s, industrial relations stands at the<br />
heart of the profound differences between the two main<br />
political parties.<br />
On this issue of whether the way forward lies with<br />
consensus or confrontation in the workplace the two<br />
parties have been divided for more than a decade more<br />
consistently, more sharply and more profoundly than on any<br />
other issue. </p>
<p>Evidence for how this critical question will be resolved in<br />
the 1990s is provided by the dramatic events of the 1980s.<br />
At the start of the decade, the Fraser Government was<br />
grandstanding over the impending resources boom, with its<br />
chimerical promise of massive investment and higher living<br />
standards which would give all Australians a bigger slice of<br />
a bigger cake.<br />
At the same time, that Government deliberately abandoned<br />
attempts to control aggregate wages outcomes.<br />
The combined effect of such measures would be obvious to any<br />
first year economics student. In effect the Government was<br />
saying that in an impending period of demand growth, those<br />
with power in the economy should exercise it in their own<br />
interests, and let prices be determined accordingly.<br />
That was certainly a message heard clearly by the metal<br />
trades and transport unionists who, responding to those<br />
signals being emitted by the Government, sparked the wages<br />
explosion of 1981/ 82.<br />
In that way, the simultaneous double digit inflation and<br />
unemployment that followed in 1983 an achievement<br />
unequalled by any other Government in the history of<br />
Federation was an achievement directly and explicitly the<br />
result of the irresponsible economic management of the<br />
Fraser Government.<br />
The nation's well-being as a whole was retarded and corroded<br />
by the selfish pursuit of short-term interests in the<br />
poisonous atmosphere of confrontation fostered by the<br />
Commonwealth. I have said this before on many occasions, but its truth has<br />
not been eroded by time or by repetition: effective<br />
industrial relations is the result of making workers<br />
understand that their legitimate aspirations for improved<br />
standards, and employers' equally legitimate aspirations for<br />
growth, are not likely to be achieved by confrontationist,<br />
tunnel visioned pursuit of their individual aspirations.<br />
The early 1980s proved that.<br />
Effective industrial relations requires both sides to<br />
understand that their legitimate aspirations can best be met<br />
by constructive co-operation.<br />
The rest of the 1980s proved that.<br />
Because under the Accord with the trade union movement, this<br />
Government has given life to that philosophy.<br />
The Accord has been the crucial instrument of economic and<br />
social policy under this Government. </p>
<p>The fact that under the Accord, the trade union movement has<br />
accepted smaller pay packets has led to two massively<br />
important and genuinely beneficial processes:<br />
first, it has allowed social wage increases such<br />
as the restoration of Medicare, the opening up of<br />
superannuation, the trebling of childcare places,<br />
increases in Family Allowances, and the<br />
inauguration of the Family Allowance Supplement;<br />
and second, real wage restraint has started a dynamic<br />
process in which the resultant record profits have<br />
led to record investment and sustained record<br />
employment growth. I repeat: record profits,<br />
record investment and record job growth.<br />
At the same time the consensus model of industrial relations<br />
is allowing the restructuring of craft based unions and<br />
union awards so as to lay the basis for greater flexibility<br />
in wages and working conditions across industries. And all<br />
this with a reduction of some 60 per cent in industrial<br />
disputes under this Government.<br />
Here then is the essence of the industrial relations lesson<br />
of the 1980s.<br />
At the start of the decade, a confrontationist, selfish<br />
approach led to recession. By the end of the decade, the<br />
co-operative approach had produced new jobs, a stronger<br />
safety net of social welfare, a fairer taxation system,<br />
steady economic growth, and a durable and genuine investment<br />
boom. Such achievements are not just helping Australians of today.<br />
Just as importantly, they are providing building blocks for<br />
the future critical elements in the achievement of those<br />
four goals I outlined earlier.<br />
Now all this would be the stuff of the history books if it<br />
were not that the industrial relations prejudices and<br />
self-delusions of the Coalition that were so decisively<br />
exploded by the trauma of the early 1980s were threatening<br />
to return, in new garb, in the 1990s.<br />
Industrial relations is still at the heart of the<br />
differences between the two parties. The Peacock<br />
conservatives have failed to learn the lesson so<br />
dramatically taught by their Fraser predecessors that<br />
lifting the lid off wages for a few will spell disaster for<br />
the nation as a whole.<br />
We saw this most clearly during the pilots' efforts,<br />
supported by the Coalition, to overthrow the centralised<br />
wage fixing system. </p>
<p>What the pilots sought to do extract a massive and<br />
unjustified wage increase, with all that this would mean for<br />
industry and economy wide employment and productivity levels<br />
would be replicated any number of times whenever a<br />
powerful union believed it could get away with it.<br />
Saying " let * em rip" to the powerful few would mean the<br />
weaker many are trampled in the rush.<br />
Is that the kind of Australia that the Opposition Leader<br />
wanted when he promised a fairer and more compassionate<br />
Australia? The fact is simple: do away with a mechanism to control<br />
aggregate wages outcomes and you will do away with effective<br />
management of the entire economy.<br />
Do away with consensus and you will remove from the hand of<br />
public policy the means to achieve<br />
national wage outcomes that will restore and<br />
improve our international competitiveness;<br />
the wage protection of employees whose bargaining<br />
position is weaker than a metal worker or a pilot;<br />
the capacity to bring to bear other elements of<br />
public policy such as taxation, superannuation,<br />
training, social welfare policies to the key<br />
task of wage fixing;<br />
the means to achieve productivity improvements<br />
through award restructuring and union<br />
amalgamation.<br />
Do away with consensus and you do away with the system that<br />
is delivering those record levels of profits, investment and<br />
jobs. But doing away with consensus is precisely what the<br />
Opposition proposes.<br />
A deeper difficulty lies in the process under which the<br />
Coalition's system would be established the transitional<br />
phase in any immediate post-Accord years and the effect of<br />
the Opposition's industrial relations policies on aggregate<br />
wage outcomes.<br />
It was when he was questioned about this that the Opposition<br />
Leader produced his now famous " who's to know" comment a<br />
shrug of the shoulders that conveyed so eloquently his lack<br />
of understanding on this key issue.<br />
Andrew Peacock may not understand the implications of his<br />
own policy. But Australians can be assured that the real<br />
architects of the policy those such as John Stone, John<br />
Elliott, Ian McLachlan understand clearly. </p>
<p>What they clearly foresee, because they have coldbloodedly<br />
planned it, is the chaos of industrial confrontation a<br />
bonfire which would consume in flames the progress we have<br />
achieved in the past seven and a half years.<br />
Australians are now by and large well informed about the<br />
nature of the national economic challenge; they have<br />
experienced, in their workplaces, their homes, their schools<br />
and communities, the impact of money wage restraint and<br />
social wage improvement; they understand the need for<br />
international competitiveness through micro-economic<br />
productivity improvements even if they skip the economic<br />
jargon.<br />
They are not going to be satisfied with strategies for the<br />
future that fail to address the fundamentals.<br />
So what we need to do is carefully to appraise the progress<br />
we have made; clear-sightedly to understand the reasons for<br />
that progress; and deliberately to chart a course for the<br />
future that will ensure continued progress.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen,<br />
Your invitation to address this seminar reminded me of an<br />
invitation to address another January conference seven years<br />
ago the 1983 Summer School of the Australian Institute of<br />
Political Science.<br />
The title of that conference is today an evocative relic of<br />
the era: " Industrial Confrontation Can we Survive It?"<br />
In my address, I summed up the essential malaise of the<br />
Fraser Government's period of office as being, " an<br />
increasing erosion of any sense of common national purpose".<br />
That same phrase could apply with equal relevance and<br />
accuracy to the conservative parties today.<br />
Because a determination to put the private interest of a few<br />
ahead of the public interest of the many is the touchstone<br />
of all they are offering for the 1990s.<br />
It is the philosophy underlining John Elliott's infamous<br />
statement that the Liberals would take from the ' bludgers'<br />
and give to the ' workers'.<br />
It is the key to their determination to undo the fair and<br />
efficient Capital Gains Tax in favour of the privileged<br />
minority. It is the basis for the callous determination to pull the<br />
carpet from under the sick, the elderly, the Aboriginal, the<br />
newly arrived migrant, as seen in the cuts outlined in the<br />
so-called Economic Action Plan. </p>
<p>It is the raison d'etre for their short-sighted stubbornness<br />
to develop policies for the genuine protection of the<br />
natural environment.<br />
But most critically, this absence of a sense of common<br />
national purpose is the essence of their proposals for<br />
industrial relations. Their proposals will see once again<br />
the triumph of sectoral interest over the public good the<br />
triumph of the strong over the weak the triumph of blind<br />
ideology over rational common sense.<br />
It would also, let me add, be a triumph of the John Stones<br />
and the other ideologues of the Coalition parties over<br />
Andrew Peacock who, though he nominally leads that<br />
Coalition, utterly lacks the weight to control it.<br />
Australians cannot afford and I believe, will not choose<br />
a Coalition that deliberately, consistently and blatantly<br />
seeks to put the interests of the few ahead of the interests<br />
of the nation as a whole.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen,<br />
My theme today has been change within Australia, and how it<br />
can be effectively managed by consultation.<br />
But I began by mentioning the spectacular transformation<br />
sweeping Eastern Europe.<br />
In closing I want to return to those historic developments,<br />
as they are relevant to that theme of the management of<br />
change. There is of course an intimate connection these days between<br />
the future character of Australia and of the world in which<br />
Australia must operate. Foreign and domestic policy are<br />
increasingly two sides of the same coin.<br />
The lesson of Eastern Europe is that a society that turns<br />
its face against change, and that tells its people that the<br />
received wisdom of 40 years ago remains relevant and valid<br />
today, will fail.<br />
Even the harshest surveillance and repression will in the<br />
end provide inadequate shields against a people determined<br />
to claim their birthrights of freedom and well-being.<br />
Australia of course will never experience the depths of<br />
official corruption and depravity represented so vividly by<br />
the fallen despots of Eastern Europe.<br />
But the lesson is valid nevertheless: societies that are<br />
successful and that best fulfil the aspirations of their<br />
people are societies capable of anticipating and responding<br />
to change, of taking advantage of opportunities as they<br />
arise and of eschewing the comfortable temptations of habit<br />
and entrenched interests. </p>
<p>On the threshold of the 1990s, Australia would do well to<br />
take that lesson to heart.<br />
I feel that I can stand before you and say with complete<br />
conviction, backed up by seven years of achievement in both<br />
domestic and foreign policy, that ours has been a Government<br />
attuned to change.<br />
We have shown the capacity to anticipate change and to<br />
devise effective strategies which are not merely reactive<br />
but look to the future and to shaping that future for the<br />
benefit of the Australian people.<br />
And therefore over-arching every particular proposition and<br />
message which I will be putting in coming months is the<br />
critical commitment that, while my Government is deeply<br />
proud of its record, we will never be a Government that<br />
shirks the challenge of capturing the benefits of further<br />
change for the Australian people.<br />
Let me say finally that I have deeply appreciated the<br />
positive response of so many in the business community to<br />
our consultative approach to governing for change. And over<br />
the whole of my period of leadership, no organisation has<br />
been more consistently co-operative in facilitating the<br />
process of consultation and exposition than CEDA. I thank<br />
you most sincerely for that. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
