<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2885</transcript-id>
    <title>AUSTRALIAN DELEGATION TO ECAFE</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/04/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002885.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
AF ARA<br />
-if A AF<br />
NQ DATE<br />
M/ 69 5 April 1973<br />
AUSTRALIAN DELECTATION TO ECAFE<br />
The Special Minister of State a. nd Minister assisting<br />
the Minister for Foreign Affairs, Senator Willesee, announced<br />
today that he would leave for Tokyo tomorrow ( 6 April) to lead<br />
Sthe Australian Delegation to the 29th Session of the Economic<br />
Commission for Asia and the Far East ( ECAFE),<br />
The 29th Session of ECAFE, from 11 23 April, will<br />
review the work of the Commission during the nast year and<br />
Sdecide on policy and programs of work for ECAE for the coming<br />
year.<br />
0 The Minister said that the Australian Delegation would<br />
seek to be as helpful as possible to ECAFE in its attempts to<br />
promote economic and social development in the ECAFE region.<br />
He expected to deliver Australia's principal statement<br />
in the general debate at the 29th Session on 13 April and to<br />
provide further details in that statement of the Government's<br />
approach to the work of ECAFE and to regional economic and<br />
social co-operation. ./ 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
Senator Willesee will return to Sydney on 16 April and<br />
proceed to Apia on 17 April to participate at the meeting of the<br />
South Pacific Forum, from 17 to 19 April.<br />
Senator Willesee will then proceed to Tonga on 21 April<br />
at the invitation of the Prime Minister of Tonga, H. R. H. Prince<br />
Tu'ipelehake. During his visit to Tonga he will discuss with<br />
the Tongan Government matters of mutual interest.<br />
The Minister announced that the Australian Delegation<br />
to the 29th Session of ECAFE will be: 0<br />
The Special Minister of State, Senator Willesee Leader<br />
The Honourable Gordon Freeth, Australian Ambassador to<br />
Japan<br />
Mr J. R. Kelso, Assistant Secretary, Department of<br />
Foreign Affairs<br />
Mr J. S. F. Bowan, First Secretary, Australian Embassy,<br />
Bangkok<br />
Mr J. A. Benson, First Secretary, Australian Embassy, Tokyo<br />
Mr B. L. Ryan, Trade Policy Officer, Department of Overseas<br />
Trade<br />
Mr N. Stuparich, Senior Finance Officer, The Treasury<br />
I<br />
Mr C. G. S. Willis, Second Secretary, Australian Embassy,<br />
Tokyo<br />
Mr J. A. Tilemann, Private Secretary to the Minister of State </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
