<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11504</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER            THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP            DOORSTOP INTERVIEW            RYDE CITY COUNCIL                    </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/01/2000</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Subjects: New rules for jobseekers; Olympics protest; National</p>
<p> Textiles; Australia Day date shift; call for apology to Aboriginals</p>
<p>E&amp;OE...................................................................................................</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[Inaudible]</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh, the toughening is not very great, it's only reasonable particularly</p>
<p> in the city areas where there are more jobs around to make certain that</p>
<p> people who are out of work are, all of them, making a reasonable effort</p>
<p> to find a job. It's a question of keeping a balance. Look, we are</p>
<p> seeing huge job growth in this country and if we can maintain a strong</p>
<p> rate of economic growth we can drive the jobless level down even more.</p>
<p> The good news in the Australian economy now is on the jobs front. The</p>
<p> first social responsibility of any government is to provide jobs for the</p>
<p> people. We are providing jobs for the people, we have provided over 500,000</p>
<p> jobs since my Government came to power and we are discharging our greatest</p>
<p> social obligation in providing people with jobs.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Is it a bit harsh for people who are [inaudible]...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh, I don't think there's anything harsh about these new requirements</p>
<p> at all. I think they are perfectly reasonable and they are just ensuring</p>
<p> that there's a balance.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Is this one way of reaching Mr Costello's forecast of unemployment...of</p>
<p> all Australians [inaudible].</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It's all about preserving a balance.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>How do you respond to accusations that it's a media stunt and it's</p>
<p> shifting the blame to the unemployed for unemployment?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, such a comment is a media stunt.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do you support Ian Causwell's comments...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Ian who?</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Ian Causwell.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Causwell. I don't know anybody by the name of Ian Causwell.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[Inaudible] unemployed in regional Australia needs to [inaudible]...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look, I haven't seen his remarks.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Larry Anthony says any job's worth having no matter how bad it is.</p>
<p> Do you agree with that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I didn't hear the exact remark and I have long since learnt</p>
<p> not to respond to people's interpretation of what others say. They</p>
<p> are sometimes wrong.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Well, what do you think of that concept? Do you think unemployed people</p>
<p> should...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think it's a beautiful afternoon.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, do you think Australians have reconciled themselves to</p>
<p> the fact that there is good and bad, as you were saying in your speech,</p>
<p> good and bad in our heritage...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh, I think most Australians are sensible and reasonable and decent and</p>
<p> they look back on our history and they see on balance it's a rich</p>
<p> history of huge achievement but like any other nation we have made mistakes.</p>
<p> Australians are very sensible, down to earth, decent people. They know</p>
<p> our history, they are proud of it, they're thrilled at what this</p>
<p> country has achieved but they also recognise we have made mistakes. All</p>
<p> of us make mistakes. But on balance this country has been hugely decent</p>
<p> and beneficial and is seen by the rest of the world as exactly that.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, I am wondering your response to comments today by our Australian</p>
<p> of the Year encouraging people to demonstrate at the Olympics [inaudible]</p>
<p> reconciliation.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I haven't heard that Sir Gustav Nossal has said that.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>He said this morning when [inaudible] would carry the Olympic Torch that</p>
<p> the aboriginal protest outside the Olympics would [inaudible] Federal</p>
<p> Government....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I didn't hear that and I don't support any protest at</p>
<p> the Olympics. But, you know, in a democratic society, anybody is entitled</p>
<p> to protest if they want to but I don't encourage it and I don't</p>
<p> think he would either.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do you think [inaudible]?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look, I didn't see his comments. Once again I don't accept</p>
<p> on face value other people's interpretations of those comments.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[Inaudible] on Australia Day do you have anything to say to the former</p>
<p> employees of National Textiles?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, we are naturally sorry that because of economic conditions in that</p>
<p> industry and it's an industry that has seen retrenchments and closures</p>
<p> for a long time. It's very difficult for an industry like textiles</p>
<p> for Australian companies to remain completely competitive with low wage</p>
<p> countries. I mean, that's just an economic reality and the only way</p>
<p> that you can do that is to have absurdly high tariffs. And we can't</p>
<p> have absurdly high tariffs in this country otherwise other people would</p>
<p> do that to us and we won't sell our goods to those countries. So</p>
<p> it's just not possible. So unfortunately some firms close. As far</p>
<p> as their benefits on retrenchment are concerned Mr Reith has already indicated</p>
<p> that he'll be taking a plan to the Cabinet. I will be supporting</p>
<p> Mr Reith when that plan goes to the Cabinet.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[Inaudible]</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I will support what Mr Reith is putting to the Cabinet.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Have you had an opportunity to discuss [inaudible]...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I haven't discussed the matter with anybody in the company.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, do you think today is the most appropriate day to continue</p>
<p> celebrating our national day?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh, absolutely. I think the 26th of January is in the words</p>
<p> of the eminent historian, Geoffrey Blainey, this morning, the 26th</p>
<p> of January is catching on. I have to say that in my lifetime it's</p>
<p> gone from being merely the anniversary day long weekend at the end of</p>
<p> the school holidays to being a day that people really look forward to</p>
<p> and a day that people really celebrate in quite an excited, varied way.</p>
<p> I think the constant call for it to be shifted is falling on increasingly</p>
<p> deaf ears. No day is perfect so what do you shift it to? If we shift it</p>
<p> to the 1st of January that doesn't mean a lot to a lot</p>
<p> of people. If you shift it to the 25th of April which is a</p>
<p> very sacred day in the Australian calendar you confuse two things, you</p>
<p> confuse sacrifice in war with a national day. Anzac Day is redeveloping</p>
<p> its momentum and it would be a pity to confuse the two concepts. So I</p>
<p> come back to being a very strong supporter of keeping it at the 26th</p>
<p> of January. And the important thing is that the people are voting with</p>
<p> their interest in favour of the 26th January...</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What about those Australians are who marking survival day today?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I respect that they have a different view but just as a lot of</p>
<p> people didn't vote for Advance Australia Fair as our national song</p>
<p> when it was adopted more than 20 years ago, but the majority of Australians</p>
<p> did, so it is with our anniversary, Australia Day. So it is with whatever</p>
<p> day you want to use. The great majority of Australians, I believe, support</p>
<p> the 26th of January and I think it ought to stay at that. But</p>
<p> you won't have 100 per cent of people supporting it. That's</p>
<p> impossible. Any more than you get 100 per cent of people adhering behind</p>
<p> any national observance or any national symbol. I respect the right of</p>
<p> some Australians to mark it as survival day, that is their right. But</p>
<p> I would say to them that I think the majority of their fellow Australians</p>
<p> want to leave it at the 26th of January. And they are demonstrating</p>
<p> their interest. You find all over the country now people are embracing</p>
<p> Australia Day. There's an excitement about it, there's an interest</p>
<p> in it. Not only in Sydney. This idea that it just belongs to the foundation</p>
<p> of a colony of New South Wales is absurd. It is now acquiring a national</p>
<p> resonance and affection that it hasn't had, that wasn't there</p>
<p> years ago. And as I say, in my lifetime it's been transformed.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Would today be an appropriate day for an apology to indigenous Australians?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>You know that I don't think a formal statement of that kind is appropriate</p>
<p> because I don't believe that current generations of Australians should</p>
<p> be seen as responsible for deeds over which they had no control and in</p>
<p> which they had no involvement.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
