<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2664</transcript-id>
    <title>2GS TALKBACK - BRIAN WHITE INTERVIEWS THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT HON WILLIAM MCMAHON CH MP FOR THE MACQUARIE NETWORK - 24 AUGUST 1972</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/08/1972</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002664.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TALKBACK<br />
BRIAN WMITE = INTE~ rrIEW1S THE. PIUI MINISTER, ' THE<br />
RT ON. _ WILLIAM. -MC. M4ON, CH, M4P, FOR THE<br />
M-ACQUAYE NETWORK 24 AUGUST 1972<br />
Well, now, one of the major subjects which is<br />
occunying Federal political attention at this.' moment<br />
is Ithis matter-of re-aluation-of the Australian dollar.<br />
In its annual report this week, the Reserve Bank camne.<br />
out quite definitely. it -would appear in support ofthe<br />
notion of revaluation. The report. does not specifically<br />
mention the word " revaluation"~ but nonethele!: s, the ,. hole<br />
tenor of the remarks.-iJt made on this-subDject seem to<br />
indicate that it war-.. in ' favour of it. Then we had onwhat<br />
night was it T'uesday night, the Leader of th-e<br />
O) pposition in an interview macte a statement to the effect<br />
that he ondorsed what the Bank,-had to say. Yesterday<br />
as sor'e nowspaper-report-ri today for example, the<br />
Adelaide Advertiser -renorted today that Mr Whitlam<br />
came undar sustaincd attack from Labor MPs yesterday<br />
for advocating revaluation of the-dollar. On This<br />
Day Tonight last night, the. Deputy Prime Mini, 7ter, 1" r<br />
Doug PAnthony came out flatly in op~ position to revaluation.<br />
In Parliament today, the Prime !-inister has-endorsed that<br />
stand. On the line from Canberra at this time, I have<br />
tho 1Prime MinIster, the Right Honourable William McMahon.<br />
Prime M4inister, can i ass you if there is any<br />
disagreement in Cabinet on whether or not there should be a<br />
revaluation?<br />
PM.-Not so far as I am awire. I di-d say in Parliament<br />
today that in the course of the last twoc days ycsterday and<br />
today, I had discussed this question both with the Deputy<br />
Prime Minister and the TreaSurer w: eo Js functionally responsible<br />
for those problouis. Thcere was no disagriement between us.<br />
0. WFere you aware that Mr :, anony planned to make his<br />
statement against revaluation last night?<br />
Q. You were not?<br />
PN1-INo. I don't think thpt mattered because I had<br />
discussed it w Ith him oarlier in the day.<br />
Q. The suggostion which arose last nig~ ht which has been<br />
taken up by some people is that Mr A1nthony simply took matters<br />
into his own hands. </p>
<p>-2<br />
PM: I don't think that is true because I : iscussed it<br />
with him earlier in the day. But I confirm that he didn't<br />
discuss with me beforehand the question o f going on<br />
television.<br />
Q. On a matter of this importance, perhaps, some<br />
people might think that would have been expected?<br />
PM: Oh, I don't think so because I had only on the<br />
previous Sunday gone on television myself and I had made<br />
the Government's position clear. in other words, as I<br />
listcned to what he said, I don't want to say he necessarily<br />
did this, but it did appear as though he had followed<br />
exactly the same lines as I had. So I couldn't object in<br />
a caso like that.<br />
Q. Can I ask you what factors would lead Cabinet to<br />
a new assessment of this matter?<br />
PM: If it were brought up by the Treasurer and I<br />
don't think it will be because I h-ave already mentioned<br />
it to the Treasurer -we could consider it again. But I<br />
gave four good reasons why we should remain w, hee we were,,<br />
and I stick to them.<br />
0. Would you like to go into those again?<br />
PM: Yes, I indicated that when we revalued on the<br />
last occasion, I had five important problems in mind. The<br />
first one I had to consider the interests of thcse primary<br />
producers who would have to meet comnetition from the<br />
producers of countries that devalued, and I didn't want to<br />
affect them more than they had been, The second point was<br />
that in the case of our mineral industrics, we were going<br />
through a particularly tough time, and who lost about<br />
$ 8 million ( Australian) for every cent we revalucd against the<br />
American dolhr and those who had their contracts made in<br />
US dollars would suffcr further losses, and I didn't think<br />
it was appropriate at that time. Then we had to think of<br />
the manufacturers Australian manufacturers who had to<br />
compete with the manufactured goods of the people from<br />
overseas and, for that matter, import-competing manufacturers.<br />
Then, most importantly, was the economic climate of<br />
confidence in Australia itself. i did not beliovc it would<br />
help our cause by revaluing upwards any further than we did.<br />
In other words, when unemployment is proving tough to handle,<br />
when confidence has to be restored then further revaluation<br />
would, in my opinion, havo done harm and I wasn't prepared<br />
to permit that to happon.<br />
Q. You think those factors still apply?<br />
PM: Yes. ./ 3 </p>
<p>-3<br />
Q. What about the economic climate? you think<br />
it is no different?<br />
PMI: It has moved a lot further, yes. it's a lot<br />
better. But I would like to sea it much better before TI<br />
would contemplate any change.<br />
Q. The Reserve D~ ank, while not spociF-ically<br />
using the word l" revaluati. oni, su) ggested it pir etty clearly<br />
in its report this week as a means of ccmbatina, inflation.<br />
You do not agree with thatT<br />
PM: ImpJlicitlvr thle Reservc-Ban'! said that it thought<br />
there should be further rev'aluaition, that is appreciation<br />
of the P.. 1. stralian currency. It looked at it from a purely<br />
monetary point of view, i, as the head o~ government, had<br />
to take a wiAdor vie,-, part ' icularly with relation to<br />
unem-ploymcnt and clonfidcnce and sus3taining Australian industry.<br />
Q. The Opposititon Leader, M4r Whitlam, has been accused<br />
in the House today of committina a nnlitical crime by suggesting<br />
that the dollar shnu.' i. be revalued. Do you go along with<br />
that?<br />
PM: I wudtusc those T. o rdo, no. But what I will<br />
say is that I thin, ihe ' Wa-S extremol&gt; foolish, and he made it<br />
-aooear that he has little no knowledge of economic or<br />
financial problems. 1 am amazed that lie e-von got involved<br />
in the problem becau~ e ilt becamye ovu3he did not know<br />
what he was talking about.<br />
Q. Mr Trritlam's attitude wvas that he w,, as endorsing<br />
Sirfllv what the Reszerve:. Bank said.<br />
PM. N-0, it is not. No it is not. He was endorsing that,<br />
but he went much further. Hie accepted personal responsibility<br />
for what he said. ; Lid for that -xitter, there was a second<br />
question in the D3ouse toda. y that confirmed that as the view<br />
of certainlv a la~ rqe section of the Lab: or Party.<br />
Q. There a feeling abroad that w-, hichever Party wins<br />
the ncxt olection,...... bo~ th the Government and the 0Opposition<br />
at the momcnt !, ould. l stand against revaluation, but come the<br />
election when it is ver there will be a revaluation.<br />
Dco you have anx, cormment on that?<br />
Ptl : oJ -lW e are putting , hv-o
f irst o.-f all, sc. far as I an conccrned and the Gcvernment<br />
is co-ncernead, wc: -arc not contemplating revaluation. We are<br />
not;-conteriolating changes in the value of the currency. It<br />
is obvious, too, that thcre iL, a T. 7ide differance of opinion<br />
wi1 thin the Lab'or Party itsclf. Ane'. th ose who ara exoressing<br />
o-pini( ns believe that thero shoul,' be a rcv., luation. I<br />
don't know which side would triui--th. .14 </p>
<p>A--<br />
Q. Do vou believi that tjie<br />
-Co~ nmlet-ely uitcd e n revaluaton.?<br />
PM: believe.-they fie Y-es.<br />
Q. All right; Sir. Tha. nk you for talking to me. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
