<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4748</transcript-id>
    <title>CLOSING OF JUBILEE APPEAL</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/07/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004748.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 4 JULY 1978<br />
CLOSING OF JUBILEE APPEAL<br />
Last year the Queen Elizabeth II Silver Jubilee Appeal for<br />
young Australians was launched to commemorate the Silver<br />
Jubilee of Her Majesty The Queen's accession to the throne.<br />
The patron of the Appeal was His Highness, The Prince of Wales,-<br />
and the Appeal was truly national in scope and character.*<br />
Each State and Territory was given its own target a total of<br />
$ 5,000,000, and 12 months in which to raise the funds.<br />
I am pleased to be able to tell you that every State and<br />
Territory exceeded its target.<br />
The Commonwealth and State Governments made major contributions,<br />
large contributions came from businesses and individuals all<br />
around Australia, and I am happy to be able to announce that<br />
the fund now stands at $ 5,400,000.<br />
This function marks the official closing of the Appeal, but the<br />
Trust's call for funds will in fact never close.<br />
I am sure that we shall be reminded before the evening is out<br />
that the Trust will always gratefully receive donations.<br />
But now that the first phase of the Appeal has ended, work<br />
can concentrate on the administration of the Trust and the<br />
award of grants. I<br />
We have already seen an example of the dedication and determination<br />
of the members of the Trust. Last November, when the Appeal still<br />
had six months to go, the first awards were announced. These<br />
were the Special Awards for 1977, which the Prince of Wales<br />
presented during his visit last year.<br />
The Special Awards give a good idea of the basis on which the<br />
awards will operate.<br />
The Awards were made to individuals or organizations in every<br />
State, the the Northern Territory and Norfolk Island.<br />
For example, in Western Australia 12 teenage Aboriginal girls<br />
were helped to undertake a leadership course; funds for a horse<br />
riding school were granted to the Riding for the Disabled<br />
Association of Victoria; the Queensland State Centre of the<br />
Surf Life Saving Association of Australia received an award to<br />
assist with the purchase of three inshore rescue boats. </p>
<p>The field is wide, and deliberately so.<br />
The Trust has been designed to be as flexible as possible.<br />
This will mean it will be able to assist in the widest<br />
possible variety of projects and causes involving young<br />
people. In making awards, the Trust aims to respond to community needs<br />
as they arise, and will take careful account of community views,<br />
especially those of young Australians.<br />
The Trust will play a real part in helping to mould a better<br />
society, a more tolerant and diverse society in Australia.<br />
It will enable many young Australians to develop new skills,<br />
to draw on their own creativity, to express themselves more<br />
fully. It will offer new hope and opportunity for young men and women<br />
who might not otherwise have the chance to develop their talents<br />
to full capacity.<br />
Above all, it will help our young nation realise our potential,<br />
our vast capacity which as yet has been barely tapped.<br />
I have no doubt that the trust will be a fitting tribute to<br />
the first 25 years reign of The Queen.<br />
I am sure Australians will long remember the many events which<br />
took place in the past year to mark her Silver Jubilee above<br />
all, of course, the visit in March last year of The Queen and<br />
The Duke of Edinburgh, and the visit in November of the patron<br />
of the Appeal, The Prince of Wales.<br />
Though the Silver Jubilee year is now past, important things<br />
that it stood for are still with us. Great changes in technology,<br />
lifestyles, and community values have taken place in<br />
the quarter century since The Queen acceded to the Throne.<br />
Yet the Crown, while adapting to and meeting these changes, has<br />
remained constant in the fundamental values we value and cherish.<br />
When The Queen turned 21, she solemnly pledged her life to the<br />
service of her people. At her Silver Jubilee celebrations in<br />
London last year, Her Majesty recalled that pledge and added:<br />
" I do not regret or retract one word of it".<br />
Her Majesty's 25 years of dedicated service, and the grace,<br />
dignity and human warmth with which she bears the burden of<br />
her high office, are an inspiration and an example to us all.<br />
We may hope that The Queen Elizabeth II Silver Jubilee Trust<br />
for Young Australians with its objective of helping young<br />
people to help themselves and through them the community<br />
will stand as an enduring tribute by Australians to Her Majesty<br />
for her first 25 years of service to us all.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
