<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9879</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP REGIONAL VICTORIA FEDERAL TOURISM FUNDING </title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/12/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009879.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
14 5/<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
REGIONAL VICTORIA FEDERAL TOURISM FUNDING<br />
Regional Victoria is to receive almost $ 500,000 in Federal funding to help it become<br />
more involved in the State's growing tourism industry.<br />
The funding will be provided under the four year, $ 23 million Regional Tourism<br />
Development Program ( RTDP) which aims to help spread the economic and social<br />
benefits of tourism beyond metropolitan Australia.<br />
Grants will go to six key tourism projects covering areas from Bendigo to the<br />
Dandenongs. The largest grant of $ 213,000 will go to the Bendigo Tourism Board, to relocate the<br />
visitors centre from Kangaroo Flat to the city's recently restored historic post office.<br />
This funding recognises Bendigo's importance to the State's tourism industry,<br />
particularly as the regional gateway to the goldfields of central Victoria.<br />
An additional $ 55,000 grant will enable a signage system to be developed throughout<br />
the goldfields to educate people about the region's grand history, including its fine<br />
buildings which are a legacy of the gold rush era.<br />
A new tourist information centre at Heathcote, to receive $ 100,000 in funding, will not<br />
only highlight that town's natural assets it will provide information on attractions<br />
throughout the broader region, including the ' Pink Cliffs' which developed their unique<br />
character as a result of past gold-mining activity.<br />
Other funding includes $ 71,500 to build a world-class walking track along the Great<br />
Ocean Road between Cape Otway and Princetown, $ 45,000 to develop a tourist drive<br />
with linked walking tracks from the Puffing Billy Steam Train in the Dandenong Ranges<br />
through the Casey Cardinia and Westernport regions, and $ 15,000 to develop a tourist<br />
trail along the rail line between Mirboo North and Boolarra.<br />
Regional Australia can offer both domestic and international tourists a wealth of<br />
experiences that they could not find in our major cities.<br />
Tourism is one of Victoria's growth industries, currently employing around 130,000<br />
people and pumping more than $ 7 billion annually into the State economy.<br />
BEN DIGO<br />
12 DECEMBER 1995 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
