<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10213</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON. JOHN HOWARD MP INTERVIEW WITH STEVE LIEBMANN-TODAY SHOW, CHANNEL NINE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/01/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010213.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
22 January 1997 TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE HON. JOHN HOWARD MP<br />
INTERVIEW WITH STEVE LIEBMANN-TODAY SHOW, CHANNEL NINE<br />
E O E<br />
LIEBMANN: Good morning to you. Happy new year.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Happy new year, Steve, it's great to be back.<br />
LIEBMANN: Now last night you had an informal meeting with the State leaders and Jeff Kennett was there.<br />
Did you talk about the fires? Did he want help?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Yes we did, we did and I just want to say along with all other Australians how distressed I am<br />
at the loss of life, the loss of livelihood and homes. It's always a terrifying thing to have your<br />
home burnt before your eyes, There are disaster relief arrangements in operation between the<br />
Commonwealth Government and the States and in circumstances like these they come into<br />
operation immediately and they are handled at the State level as far as the access and the<br />
distribution is concerned, and when the cost gets to a certain figure then the Commonwealth<br />
chips in to make a contribution. They are well established arrangements. Mr Kennett and I<br />
talked briefly about the crisis. I hope the rain this morning will give relief and I just want to<br />
again on behalf of the public, thank those magnificent volunteer and other fire fighters who<br />
always perform so splendidly and in great danger on an occasion like this. It's a very<br />
dangerous occupation as the terrible fires in Sydney demonstrated three years ago but it's one<br />
of those things that always grips the apprehension and the concern and the sympathy of the<br />
entire nation. </p>
<p>LIEBMANN: All right. So the mechanics are there if they need help? Everything is okay?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
The mechanics are there. There is a well established disaster relief mechanism and it has<br />
worked pretty well in the past and I will be watching it very closely to ensure that it works<br />
fairly and promptly in the case of the fires in Victoria.<br />
LIEBMANN: All right. You met informally with the state and territory leaders last night and you meet<br />
formally with them today. These talks today are being tagged by some as crisis talks. Are<br />
they? PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Crisis is too dramatic a word but we do have a serious problem. The Wik decision overturned<br />
one of the fu~ ndamental understandings of the Native Title legislation and that was that if a<br />
pastoral or other lease had been granted, then that extinguished native title. And that's not a<br />
mere opinion, that was actually written into the Native Title Act in the preamble. The<br />
preamble of the Act is a bit like that part of the marriage ceremony where you say, we've<br />
come here to get married. That's the preamble, the core of the ceremony is when you say, I<br />
do, and so the bit, that we have come here to get married, is the preamble, and that bit said<br />
that terra nullius, the notion that this land belonged to nobody before European settlement had<br />
been abolished by the High Court, and also that the High Court had found that the grant of a<br />
freehold interest in land or the grant of a leasehold interest in land had extinguished native<br />
title. Now that was the belief, the former Prime Minister said that was the situation.<br />
Pastoralists all around Australia were told that. We all operated on that basis and now the<br />
High Court has..<br />
LIEBMANN: Changed the rules.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
has changed the rules dramatically and has dramatically expanded the potential reach of<br />
native title. Now in a situation like that I can't sit around and do nothing. The States can't sit<br />
around and do nothing. I want to find a solution that is fair to everybody. I don't want to<br />
take native title away, the notion of native title away. I know how precious and important that<br />
is to the Aboriginal community. I am not going to get involved in some kind of exercise in<br />
picking on one or other section of the community. Equally, I can't have a situation where on<br />
my current advice pastoral leaseholders may not be able to build dams in certain parts of this<br />
country without getting the permission of people who may be native title holders over that<br />
land because of the co-existence finding under the Wik decision. </p>
<p>LIEBMANN: So what are you going to do?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, the first thing I am going to do is to talk to everybody who is involved.<br />
LIEBMANN: So a quick solution is out of the question?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well I would like to see, I mean, a ' quickie' solution is out of the question. A speedy,<br />
commonsense response is not out of the question. I think there is a difference. You talk to<br />
the Premiers. They all have a legitimate interest in this because they've got to manage the<br />
land. I then want to talk to the Aboriginal leaders. I have already through the Chairman of<br />
ATSIC sent a message to them that I want to meet a representative group of them as soon as<br />
possible. I want to hear everything they've got to say. I understand their feelings and that I<br />
also want to talk to the mining industry and the pastoral industry.<br />
LIEBMANN: Aboriginal leaders are saying this morning that, in fact they are demanding guarantees that<br />
native title on pastoral leases will not be altered nor will the Racial Discrimination Act, they're<br />
saying that's out of the question. Now is that the atmosphere in which you can come up with<br />
a compromise?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, people take strong positions which I understand at the beginning of these discussions. It<br />
is not going to be easy. One will require a certain Solomon-like capacity to try and get the<br />
right balance.<br />
LIEBMANN:<br />
Well playing Solomon, do you have a preferred option?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I have some, let's put it, fairly well developed ideas as to how the thing might be handled,<br />
but... LIEBMANN: Can you tell us what they are? </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:<br />
No, because part of the further development of those is to listen to what other people have got<br />
to say and I don't think the solution that we ultimately come up with is going to please<br />
everybody but we cannot leave it as it is. And I want the Australian public to understand that<br />
what has created the problem is that one of the basic underpinnings of the legislation has now<br />
been dragged away. And if it hadn't been dragged away, if the three rather than the four<br />
judges who were in the minority in the High Court decision, if their views had obtained then<br />
we would have had an entirely different situation. Now the High Court of Australia, you must<br />
understand, has the role in our system of declaring the law as it is now.<br />
LIEBMANN: Right. PRIME MINISTER:<br />
There is nothing sacrosanct about any decision on the High Court of Australia other than that<br />
it declares what the law is. And I respect the role of the High Court completely in declaring<br />
the current law, but the High Court and the rest of the community must expect that it's the<br />
role of the Parliament, if it chooses, to change that law if it thinks that law is not operating<br />
correctly. There's no law of Australia which is so sacrosanct that it can never be changed.<br />
The Keating Government changed the Racial Discrimination Act. The Keating Government<br />
actually rolled back the Racial Discrimination Act to validate leases it thought were invalid<br />
prior to the operation of the Native Title Act. So we mustn't get hung up on this idea that<br />
you can never ever, ever amend the Racial Discrimination Act or never ever overturn a High<br />
Court decision.<br />
LIEBMANN: Can we talk about matters economic...<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Sure. LIEBMANN: because you're already thinking of the next Budget. You come back to work and you find<br />
that two respected research organisations are claiming that your first Budget sliced up to<br />
a week from low income earners. Hit hardest, the people you were keen on helping is that<br />
what's happened?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
No. I've had a preliminary look at that survey. It's based on some pretty dodgy assumptions.<br />
It also completely ignores the impact of interest rate cuts and safety net wage increases on<br />
Australian households. I don't know how you can do a household survey of the last year<br />
without factoring interest rate cuts or the potential of the safety net wage increase which is </p>
<p>now before the Industrial Relations Commission. In addition, there are other aspects of the<br />
methodology that we don't think are accurate...<br />
LIEBMANN:<br />
Right. PRIME MINISTER:<br />
and Peter Costello will be saying something in more detail about it.<br />
LIEBMANN: How tough is the Budget going to be? I mean, we hear about further cuts up to $ 2 billion.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well I don't want to put any figure on it Steve. We won't be taking out the amount we did<br />
last time. I mean, we did a big fiscal correction. We obviously, to the extent that we have lost<br />
money in the process of getting legislation through the Senate, we'll be wanting to at least<br />
retrieve that. Look, we can't relax, but it won't be another 7 or 8 billion.<br />
LIEBMANN: Tax cuts are definite?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well they've started on the first of January.<br />
LIEBMANN: But there is a suggestion that in 1997 we might get the cuts but in a different form. It might<br />
be related to super and...<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Oh the Family Tax Initiative...<br />
LIEBMANN: Yeah. PRIME MINISTER:<br />
That remains, that remains untouched it will go on. I think you're talking about the so called<br />
matching contributions that were promised by the former government. We said that we would<br />
deliver it in the superannuation contribution or some other assistance to savings. That has to<br />
be considered in the context of the Budget. </p>
<p>LIEBMANN: When are you going to stop tampering with Super? When is Government going to leave<br />
Super alone, stop moving the goal posts and leave some certainty in the minds of people?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, we've only been there for less than a year and we inherited a system that had a lot of<br />
flaws. LIEBMANN: But you understand people, some people are being told get out of Super get into stocks.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Oh some people are. The contributions that are flowing into the funds don't indicate that it's<br />
on struggle street yet superannuation. I understand that. I'll try not to make too many<br />
changes to Super, but it is one of those animals that over the years all Governments have<br />
changed, I think probably too much. But we made one change really, and that was to make it<br />
a bit fairer by really reducing the scale of the generous tax concession for high income earners<br />
and it was one of the things that we've seen in the Budget as making the Budget fair because it<br />
hit the big end of town a bit.<br />
LIEBMANN: Tax reform?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, we won't be having a GST this session.<br />
LIEBMANN:<br />
No, you guaranteed that.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
But look, of course I don't rule out further tax reform. We're reforming the capital gains tax<br />
for small business from the first of July this year it will be possible up to the tune of<br />
million to sell a business and invest in another one without paying any capital gains tax. Now<br />
that will include a hell of a lot of small businesses. It effectively defers indefinitely capital<br />
gains tax liability for small businesses under $ 5 million and on my advice that's about 600 000<br />
to 700 000 out of the almost 900 000 or a million small businesses in Australia.<br />
LIEBMANN:<br />
Would you contemplate a tax summit? I mean, State leaders are now saying we've got to<br />
reform tax, it's become an embarrassment. </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:<br />
They are talking differently. I noticed this morning Mr Borbidge said he was totally against a<br />
GST. Mr Beazley says he's still against it.<br />
LIEBMANN: Are you?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Am I totally against it? Well, we've made a commitment we're not going to bring it in this<br />
term. LIEBMANN: But in a broader sense?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, Steve, I think I haven't been here 12 months yet, and what I'm going to take to the<br />
next election in this whole area is something that I'll decide closer to the election. I supported<br />
the proposals that were put forward in the 1993 election I'm on the record as having done<br />
that but the Australian public said no, and you've got to take notice of the public. One of the<br />
reasons people get cynical about politicians is that they think they know better than the public,<br />
and when you've exposed something to the public and the public has said no, you've got to<br />
take notice and that's why we made the commitment we did last time. But I think the debate<br />
that is going on at the moment about taxation is a good debate, but I don't think people<br />
should make the mistake of imagining that a dramatic change to the tax system is going to of<br />
itself transform the economy. People get this false idea that it is the economic elixir of<br />
Australia. Now, there are a lot of things that are needed to make a better economy including a<br />
better taxation system, but this idea that you can sheet home every economic shortfall to the<br />
taxation system is an easy way out and there's a danger in the present atmosphere that too<br />
many people will imagine that. And there's also a danger in the present atmosphere that<br />
people who are advocating things like GST forget that there is still a lot of entrenched<br />
opposition to it in the community.<br />
LIEBMANN:<br />
Nice to see you this morning and thank you for coming in.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
