<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3753</transcript-id>
    <title>THE PRIME MINISTER&#039;S SPEECH AT THE LAUNCHING OF &#039;THE AUSTRALIAN CONSTITUTION&#039; BY GEOFFREY SAWYER ON  MONDAY 26 MAY 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/05/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003753.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
THE PRIME MINISTER'S SPEECH AT THlE LAUNCHING OF<br />
' THE AUSTRA\ LIAN CONSTITUTION' BY GEOFFREY SAWYER<br />
ON MONDAY, 26TH MAY, 1975<br />
I suppose I have been brought in to launch this book to<br />
direct some attention to it and I'm very happy to fulfil<br />
that purpose. I'm certain that anybody looking at the<br />
book will find it interesting. It will be accessible to<br />
a degree that very few books can be accessible because it<br />
is being published by the Australian Government Publishing<br />
Service and it will be available at all its outlets. It will<br />
not only be accessible, it will be stimulating.<br />
Geoffrey Sawyer is one of the most scintillating of our<br />
academics. I w-. as first exposed to him getting on in the*<br />
middle ' 50' s, when I was sitting on the Constitution Review<br />
Committee of the Federal Parliament both Houses, both sides<br />
of each House. There were very many distinguished witnesses<br />
who gave their views and the one whose views I remember most<br />
dazzlingly, was Geoffrey Sawyer.<br />
There are a great number of academics these days who write<br />
for the newspapers and particularly for the Fairfax press.<br />
It's no compliment to say that Geoffrey Sawyer is the best.<br />
Some of the others are fallible in proportion to -their dogmatism.<br />
I've never known professors to be so unfailingly in error.<br />
But Geoffrey Sawyer is better than most. He is certainly as good<br />
as any. This is not patronising. One has to remember that<br />
judges don't agree and their word is final. How many unanimous<br />
decisions do you get from the High Court? In recent years we<br />
have learnt how the Privy Council, of course, wasn't unanimous<br />
always. A lot of things must have been decided by majority.<br />
So if judges can disagree, there is no shame i~ n academics also<br />
disagreeing and being wrong because the judge is only right if<br />
he is in the majority. For all that, this book will be accessible,<br />
it will be stimulating.<br />
The important thing is that we should encourage people to<br />
know the framework within which all the Australian Parliaments<br />
have to operate. We are one of -the very few federal systems<br />
in the world and we are the most litigious of them all. There<br />
is West Germany, United States, Canada and Australia. There<br />
are other federal systems, India, Mexico and Brazil and so on,<br />
but one never really finds there the constitutional contests<br />
in the courts such as you find in the three English speaking<br />
federations and you don't find them in West Germany either.<br />
I wish people would read the Constitution and see what it says.<br />
I've had some people in the States just blowing their heads,<br />
they are just beside themselves with outrage when anybody<br />
suggests that perhaps we should take some responsibility for<br />
seeing that there is a trafficable road between Sydney and<br />
Melbourne. That's always been in the Constitution trade<br />
and commerce between the States. True, at the time the thing<br />
was written there weren't motor-cars and people, of course, </p>
<p>wouldn't go the whole of that distance in a horse and dray,<br />
but there are roads now, and people do travel between Sydney<br />
and Melbourne, but they can't do it on the road provided.<br />
Nov, what is unreasonablie in using the trade and commerce<br />
among the States it's perfectly feasible, right from the<br />
beginning.<br />
Again, I wish -they'd read what is said about hospitals. It<br />
w,. as regarded as utterly outrageous, provocative arnd irresponsible<br />
for me to suggest that if in large centres of population, such<br />
as outer suburbs, which of course have larger popula-t-ions than<br />
any country towns, any provincial centres except Newcastle,<br />
-that if they haven't got hospitals provided by the States,<br />
then the Australian Government could provide the hospital.<br />
This was absolutely unheard of but since 1946 we have always<br />
been able to provide medical services.<br />
As it turned out, they disturbed themselves in the States<br />
and they have now laid a few foundation stones. But I just<br />
give you those practical examples. People do want to travel<br />
between Sydney and Melbourne by road, people do want to have<br />
hospitals near where they live, or are injured or are confined.<br />
If the roads or the hospitals are not adequate, there's nothing<br />
to say that the Federal Governizent shouldan't provide them.<br />
One of the things which distresses me, of course, is how<br />
negatively people regard these things. I don't mind the<br />
limitations in the Federal Constitution on federal action<br />
in terms o. f civil liberties or human rights, such as they<br />
are there. I thnk it is monstrous that the provision providing<br />
for jury trial has been by-passed by a shabby dodge but,<br />
nevertheless, it meant well jury trial for serious crimes.<br />
And again, acquisition of property on just terms. I don't cavil<br />
at those at all, but nobody ever seems to think why shouldn't<br />
the same things be applied to the States in the Constitution?<br />
We had a Constitutional convention about 18 months ago, and<br />
out of its deliberations people suggest that there should be<br />
acquisition on just terms provided in the territories. Of<br />
course there should be.. Nobody seemed to -think there should<br />
be in the States too. What's the use of having a safeguard<br />
like that which is applied only partially. It should be made<br />
universal. Defective as the safeguard! of jury Lrial is under<br />
federal criminal law, it should be tidied up but it should<br />
also apply no less to State criminal laws. I wish people<br />
would look at these things in a more basic way, in a less<br />
conservative, restrictive and negative way.<br />
Of course, the constitutional provisions are always taking on<br />
new aspects. It's happened only a year ago. For -the first<br />
time there was a double dissolution on several Bills. The<br />
previous double dissolution had been on a single Bill. We<br />
had them on six Bills. The currenit rate is over a dozen. </p>
<p>For the first time after a double dissolution, -the Bills<br />
had to be rejected a third time so there was a joint sitting,<br />
the first that ever had been. For the first timn, lasL May,<br />
there were some referendums on another Provision of the<br />
Constitution which said that if the Senate twice rejected<br />
referendums, then Bills, then they could be put to the peop.* Ie<br />
willy-nilly. The Senate can prevent a Bill being passed but<br />
i~ t cannot prevent a referendum being put. Of course, the<br />
Constitution is always taking new forms.<br />
I want to pay tribute to the High Court and the way it has<br />
developed it. It has done much more than the people ever<br />
have at referendums. I was referring to the Constitution<br />
Review Committee report in the late ' 501s. An am-tazing degree<br />
of unanimity was reached there. There were never any of<br />
our recommendations which were supported by fewer<br />
than 11 of the 12 members. Most of them were unanimous. It's<br />
only last year that it was found that there were objectionable<br />
features about some of them. But in the meantime, some of the<br />
provisions in our report have come about. We were much agitated<br />
about the limitations of -the National Parliament's power over<br />
civil aviation. Under the external affairs power, we now have<br />
it, coupled with the import power. No, the Federal Parliament<br />
doesn't need to amplify its civil aviation powers now it's got<br />
them. Again, we were concerned about television which, naturally,<br />
was not contemplated -in 1900 when the Constitution was drawn up.<br />
Nobody worries that we haven't in the Federal Parliament, now<br />
got jurisdiction over television. We were agitated about trade<br />
practices. In the light of the concrete pipes case, the<br />
corporation's power, we can effectivel~ y deal with trade practices.<br />
So, one way or another, things develop.<br />
I do urge that people should read the Constitution. A lot<br />
of people think that if something is not used, that -there's<br />
something improper about it. Take the Interstate Commission<br />
an emminently reasonable body. But because it hadn't been<br />
used for over half a century, people think that there must be<br />
something improper about bringing it to pass. In the United<br />
States, they would never think. of abandoning it. In West<br />
Germany and Canada, they now have similar bodies. And so one<br />
could go on. B~ ut I wish people would just be rational enough<br />
to look at the Constitution; not just look at it in a restrictive<br />
and negative, a cussed way, but to see what can be done if ii:<br />
i. s necessary or desirable or preferable to do something. There<br />
are very considerable shortcomings in it. A great amount can<br />
be done by cooperation between the Federal and State bodies,<br />
but at least one needs -to be clear where each of them stands<br />
under the Constitution.<br />
While I'm immensely flattered by what the Minister has said<br />
about me, I suppose in many ways, all I can claim is that I<br />
brought a lot of these m-atters to a head. I've made the<br />
Parliameznt face up to them. I've made the State Parliaments<br />
and Governments face up to them and I am trying to exercise<br />
them internationally as well. </p>
<p>One of the most fascinating things about this book of<br />
Geoffrey Sawyer's is that it makes the whole subject live<br />
in human and political terms. I naturally regard political<br />
terms as essentially human. That may have an elemet of<br />
rationalisation about it. But, the Constitution was, in<br />
terms of British colonies at the end of last century, a very<br />
bold initiative. Most of the other Federal Constitutions in<br />
the world have come about as a result of external pressures.<br />
That was the case in America, in Canada and West Germany.<br />
They have arisen from successful national liberation movements<br />
or unsuccessful wars and the newly emancipated colonists have<br />
resorted to federal systems or the banquished have resorted to<br />
federal systems or had them imposed upon them. We did it,<br />
largely, voluntarily. While I suppose you can say in retrospect,<br />
the horizons were those of colonial politicians at the time, yet<br />
nevertheless, there can be no doubt of the vigour of the debate<br />
which took place. Of course the book is well illustrated. The<br />
next edition ought to be still better illustrated, with some<br />
of these fascinating cartoons here. It's one form of art or<br />
controversy in which Australians have always been innovative<br />
and excellent. But between us, the Australian Government<br />
Publishing Service, Geoffrey Sawyer and the current Government,<br />
I suppose constitutional matters will continue to be exciting<br />
for quite some time. There can be no question that the public<br />
is more interested in politics than it has been for 40 or<br />
years. The 1920' s or 1.930 was the last time that there was<br />
the interest in politics in Australia that there is at the<br />
moment. If you are to understand Australian politics, you have to<br />
have some acquaintance with the Australian Constitution.<br />
With a scintillating author and a pretty good lawyer, we<br />
now have the material readily accessible and I'm certain<br />
people of all ages and all conditions, will be better and<br />
wiser through reading ' The Australian Constitution' written<br />
by Geoffrey Sawyer and published by the Australian Government<br />
Publishing Service. I'm very happy now to launch it. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
