<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1338</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S VISIT TO US AND UK - PRESS CONFERENCE GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR HAROLD HOLT ON ARRIVAL AT DULLES AIRPORT, WASHINGTON - 28TH JUNE 1966</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/06/1966</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001338.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
' PRI. IINTSThR'S VISIT TO U. S. AIM U. K.<br />
Press Conference given by the Primae Minister, Mvr. Harold I<br />
on arrival at Dulles Air: oort,, ashington.<br />
28th June, 1966.<br />
DM. HOLT: I am glad to be in WVashington, looking forward very much<br />
to my first meeting with President Johnson. I believe that<br />
he and I have this in cormmon,. that we prefer talking to<br />
people to talking to paper. And, although we have been in<br />
communication from the outset of my own Prime Mlinistership,<br />
I have been looking forward, and I gather that he has been<br />
looking forward,. to making personal contact.<br />
The visit, I think, is timely in that quite recently I<br />
have been Th-South Viet Nam myself and I have comie from the<br />
formal opening of the SEATO Conference where I have been<br />
able to talk to the Foreign Ministers of the countries<br />
directly involved in the area.<br />
And so, having talked with his own Secretary of State,<br />
I shall be able to pass on to the President the views of<br />
other ForeignlMinisters from South East Asia.<br />
61e, of Australia, have very good cause to be appreciative<br />
of what AmRerica has done in that part of the world. liie<br />
recall with gratitude the American action which saved our<br />
own country from invasion at the time of the second world<br />
war. And we have so many interests in cormmon which have<br />
brought us together again as comrades in arms in Viet Nam.<br />
vie believe that thanks to American resolution, communist<br />
aggression will be successfully resisted there. And it is<br />
from the more hopeful reports that have been brought to us<br />
by the delegates to the SEATO Conference and from the<br />
evidence we can give of the valuable gains made in other<br />
parts of South East Asia that I shall be able to strike a<br />
brighter note for the President than some of the reports<br />
I have been reading lately. ( Applause).<br />
Q. 11r. Prime Minister what is the most significant thing you<br />
expect to come out of the SEATO Conference?<br />
M. HOLT: '. ell, this brings together in the SEATO Conference not<br />
only the countries of the area but the major powers which<br />
have brought strength and given a basis of aid and security<br />
to those countries that are situated in the area. And<br />
coming out of the present conference will be, I think, a<br />
deeper understanding of each other' s viewpoints. They will<br />
be able to point not only to the gains which have been made<br />
over the last year, but some of the emerging problems,<br />
particularly the increasing pressure from communism in<br />
Thailand, the developments which will arise out of the<br />
abatement of confrontation by Indonesia. There will be<br />
plenty for them to talk about, but by their combination<br />
they are able to act with strength and in each country there<br />
is recognition now tM t victory is not to be gained by<br />
military maeans alQne, that we must combine also on constructive </p>
<p>positive Q.<br />
MR. HOLT:<br />
MR. HOLT: measures of economic co-operation if vwe are to persuade the<br />
peoples of the area that there is a better world order for<br />
them and that liberty can have a significance which they have<br />
never known before.<br />
Who else do you expect to see while you are here?<br />
In the United States I expect to see in addition to the<br />
President,. Mr. McNardara, PMr. George Ball, 11r. Averell<br />
Harriman and to have sae talk with my old friends from my<br />
days as the Finance Minister, 11r. Connor and Mr. Fowler. So<br />
it will be quite a comprehensive cover in Washington itself.<br />
I go then to New York where I am meeting another old friend<br />
in David Rockefeller., talking to the Australian-American<br />
Association on the day after your July fourth celebration. And<br />
Mayor Lindsay has been kind enough to extend me a dinner on<br />
Tuesday night before I take off for London.<br />
In London I shall be talking irith the Prime Minister,<br />
with the Chancellor of the Exchequer, with the 14inister for<br />
Commonwealth Relations and other senior members of the British<br />
Adminis tration.<br />
MLr. Prime 1, iinister you spoke of the brightening picture in<br />
that part of Asia. Do you think the prospects for peace have<br />
improved, and, if so, in what direction?<br />
46ell0 I think you have to direct that question to Hanoi<br />
rather than to the government I represent. We have welcomed<br />
the United States initiative in pursuing every conceivable<br />
avenue for a peace negotiation. So far every such attempt<br />
has been rebuffed from Hanoi. And this is true not only of<br />
efforts made by the United States but by other representatives<br />
of countries that, too, are seeking a peaceful end to the<br />
struggle there.<br />
The good-will towards negotiations is present with us all.<br />
But in order to negotiate there must be two parties to the<br />
discussion. And so far Hanoi has turned a deaf ear to every<br />
effort made in this direction.<br />
DIR. EGGLETON: Thank you gentlemen. I think that is about all we<br />
have tii.-e for today.<br />
Q. I wo id like to ask.. this brightening picture, does it also<br />
include the political situation in South Viet Nam?<br />
MR. HOLT: I understand that it does. ' ve had a talk with the<br />
Foreign Minister of South Viet Nam who fecls that there has<br />
been a signigicant strengthening of the governmIents position<br />
with the people. And he spoke optimistically himself, not<br />
merely of the military progress, but of the political<br />
stability which could be anticipated in the months ahead. I<br />
merely give you his judgment on that matter but it was the<br />
judgment of a very responsible-minded mar. whose faithful<br />
account of events in his own country I have learned to<br />
respect. 4ell, thank you all.<br />
The Press Thank you, sir. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
