<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3398</transcript-id>
    <title>1974 BUDGET - LIVERPOOL RAIL PROJECTS</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/09/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003398.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
STATEMENT FOR WERRIWA PRESS: AU) S 1! AlI A_<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
1974 BUDGET LIVERPOOL RAIL PROJECTS<br />
The Australian Government will providca two-thirds<br />
of the $ 21.5 million cost of constructing a new double<br />
track railway between East Hills and Glenfield. This<br />
will duplicate the existing Riverwood-East Hills section,<br />
and when completed, the new rail link will -provide greatly<br />
improved services to Sydney for travellers from the<br />
rapidly developing areas south of Liverpool.<br />
" This is an example of the greatly increased<br />
emphasis the Australian Government places on improving<br />
the long-neglected urban areas of Australia, such as<br />
Liverpool," the Prime Minister and Member for Werriwa,<br />
Mr. Gough Whitlam, said today. Ile was<br />
commenting on Budget allocations to urban public transport.<br />
He pointed out that express services from Campbelltown<br />
to Central using this route could save up to 17 minutes in<br />
travelling time. Other services would also benefit because<br />
delays on the Liverpool/ Central route would be avoided.<br />
In addition, the new line should help, to ease traffic<br />
congestion in the Liverpool area, since it would reduce<br />
pressure and dependence on road transport.<br />
Mr. Whitlam said that the new railway should be<br />
seen as part of the Australian Government's practical commitment<br />
to improving the quality of life in the cities.<br />
" Combined with our other urban initiatives, such as<br />
acquiring land for homes,. developing new growth centres like<br />
the Holsworthy/ Campbelltown/ Camden/ Appin area, and overcoming<br />
the backlog in sewerage programs, it represents a major<br />
breakthrough for our cities and the people who must live<br />
in them," Mr. Whitlam said.<br />
19 September 1974 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
