<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>710</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: PM 30/1963 - LABOR CONFERENCE DECISION - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/03/1963</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000710.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
63/ 029<br />
FOR PRESS:. LABOR CONFERENCE DECISION<br />
Statement by, te Priame Minister_ bt he RLl, Hon, Sir Robert Menzies<br />
The resolution carried by a very narrow majority<br />
in the Labor Party Conference deserves very close examination.<br />
It is, in fact, made up of the most dangerous ambiguities.<br />
Approval of the American radio-communications<br />
station in the North-West has been secured only by acceptance<br />
of conditions which threaten the establishment of the station<br />
by our friends and allies the United States of lAmerica.<br />
As has been repeatedly stated, the purpose of the station<br />
is to provide means of radio-communication with naval vessels<br />
in the Indian Ocean and in the North-' Wst Pacifico<br />
It must be clear to anybody that the existence<br />
of these facilities for the United States will become of<br />
crucial importance if they become involved in hostilities<br />
in this part of the world.<br />
What the outside Parliament of the Labor Party<br />
has now decided is that if such an event should occur, the<br />
Americans cannot use these facilities except with the concurrence<br />
of whatever Government ray then be in power in Australia.<br />
It will be clearly seen that this is a most dangerous and<br />
frustrating condition. Wh1at it moans is that if the United<br />
States whictl is, I repeat, our ally and a most powerful<br />
friend, becomes involved in hostilities with some common<br />
enemy, and the Australian Government is disposed to isolate<br />
itself under the clock of neutrality, a direct blow will be<br />
struck against the United States and against its effective<br />
conduct of naval warfare.<br />
I wonder if the Labor Party believes that we<br />
would establish at groat expense such facilities for ourselves<br />
in an allied country on the condition that they could be<br />
rendered useless by the decision of that country. In matters<br />
of life and death for Australia, surely we know who our<br />
friends are and what side we are on in relation to them,<br />
I can only hope that this miserable compromise will not<br />
inflict serious damage on the security of our own country.<br />
There are, of course, other aspects of this<br />
matter. The people of Australia have had a sharp reminder<br />
that an Australian Labor Government would not be responsible<br />
to the people or even to its own judgment, but that it would<br />
be bound hand and foot by the decisions of 36 people forming<br />
the A. L. P. Conference, not elected by the people of Australia<br />
and in no sense responsible to them<br />
I syr. pathiso with my friend, Mr. Calwell.<br />
For the leader of a Party and an aspiring Primo Minister of<br />
Australia to be compelled to hang around in hotel corridors<br />
until his masters inside have given him his instructions is<br />
a complete denial of leadership. 00..* 0 o. o/ 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
I notice that already Mr. Calwell is being<br />
consoled by the assertion that he has had a notable<br />
victory. He is expected to derive comfort from the<br />
fact that a fraction less than half of his governing<br />
body wanted to adopt a policy which would throw the<br />
United States and its communications station out of<br />
Australia and that an equally narrow majority has been<br />
persuaded to accept the station only on conditions which<br />
are both dangerous and contradictory.<br />
The people of Australia will not have failed<br />
to observe that the whole incident thro,., s light upon<br />
how Labor policy is created and upon the purely nominal<br />
and subservient role which a Labor leader is expected<br />
to play.<br />
CANBERRA, 21st March, 1963. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
