<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3070</transcript-id>
    <title>AUSTRALIAN PUBLIC ADMINISTRATION UNDER A LABOR GOVERNMENT</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/11/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003070.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
THE SIR ROBERT GARRAN MEMORIAL ORATION<br />
" AUSTRALIAN PUBLIC ADMINISTRATION UNDER A LABOR GOVERNMENT"<br />
BY<br />
THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. E. G. WHITLAM, M. P.,<br />
CANBERRA, 12 7.4OVEMIBER, 1973<br />
Let me say simply that it is a great honour to deliver the<br />
Garran Memorial Oration in 1973, 14 years after my father delivered<br />
the inaugural Oration. I know how deeply he felt honoured by the<br />
invitation to inaugurate the series of lectures to honour his great<br />
former chief. You will understand something of my feelings at this<br />
moment when I use my father's words of 14 years ago to introduce the<br />
1973 Oration. My father said this of Robert Garran:<br />
" It was an exhilarating experience, for to me he was always<br />
more than a high official, more than a skilled Parliamentary<br />
Draftsman, more than an erudite constitutional lawyer, more<br />
than a figure of social importance; to me, as to others,<br />
he was a person of remarkable distinction.<br />
" As a permanent head it was a real satisfaction and a pleasure<br />
to discuss a problem with him. In the less complex matters,<br />
so long as one was thoroughly prepared with the ascertainable<br />
facts, and was able to present them concisely and in their<br />
proper relation and proportion and indicate the contingencies<br />
and this was what he would expect his conclusion was<br />
unhesitating and decisive.<br />
" In the more complex matters, where principles were involved<br />
which required discussion, the discussion was free, subject only,<br />
of course, to the limits of relevance; there was, on his part,<br />
no restriction to orthodoxies or conventional thinking but a<br />
hospitality to all ideas that might have a bearing on the problem<br />
in hand, an enlightened weighing of pros and cons, and a firm<br />
choice of the course to be pursued."<br />
Those words well describe a great public servant, the<br />
ideal public servant. They certainly described Sir Robert Garran.<br />
It is more than perhaps filial loyalty which allows me to say that<br />
they came aptly from their author. It is not without significance<br />
in my own career, in my own attitude to the Public Service, to the<br />
role of the Public Service, the duties and responsibilities of the<br />
Public Service and to the role of Government, that I lived my boyhood<br />
here in Canberra as the son of a great public servant among whose<br />
colleagues were great public servants and that I am Autai'<br />
first Prime iMinister with that particular background.<br />
Sir Robert Garran's place in the annals of the Australian<br />
nation is as unique as it is distinguished. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
The first ten years of his public career coincided with<br />
and were inspired by Australia's march to nationhood, an event<br />
in which he played an important, if secondary, role at the time,<br />
as secretary to various committees promoting the federal movement.<br />
Garran' s energy and creative genius were immediately<br />
channelled into the establishment of the new nation. He was<br />
appointed Secretary to the Attorney-General's Department, in whi h<br />
office he served over a period of thirty-one years, and from 1910<br />
held also the office of Solicitor-General.<br />
A significant and lasting contribution by Sir Robert<br />
Garran is, of course, to be found in The Annotated Constitution<br />
of the Commonwealth of Australia, the authorship of which he shared<br />
with Sir John Quick.<br />
As one of his successors in the office of Solicitor-<br />
General, the late Sir Kenneth Bailey, has written:-<br />
" The work at once became a classic. Ever since, no careful<br />
opinion on an Australian Constitutional point has been<br />
written without seeing what " Quick and Garran" had to say<br />
about it." Any of us who have studied the law or been involved in<br />
public administration would, I think, agree with this view.<br />
Garran saw the adoption of the Constitution not as an<br />
end of a process, but as a beginning.<br />
If Garran took justifiable pride in the work of the<br />
Constitution, as the outcome of 10 years' work, and saw it as a<br />
suitable basis for a national government, he nevertheless recognised<br />
its inadequacies and saw that as time passed, as circumstances<br />
changed, so it would be necessary for the Constitution itself to be<br />
amended. In his posthumously published autobiography Sir Robert<br />
remarked " that hitherto amendment of the Constitution has been<br />
piecemeal and that something more systematic is now needed."<br />
I shall not tonight be dealing very much with the<br />
Constitution but I think it worth recalling the words of one who<br />
had so much to do with its framing and its interpretation. It<br />
is worth recalling that he had no illusions about the inadequacies<br />
of the admittedly very great work in which he participated.<br />
There has been a convention on the Constitution this year. There<br />
are to be re ferendums to amend the Constitution next month. Last<br />
week I introduced bills for three amendments and foreshadowed a<br />
bill for a fourth amendment which will be put to the people next<br />
year. I have to say, however, that given the experiences of the<br />
Convention in Sydney in August, given the political difficulties<br />
in attaining any amendment and the difficulties even of getting a<br />
referendum for an amendment put to the people, then I have to<br />
concede that the consummation of Sir Robert Garran's true, wise<br />
and absolutely accurate remarks will be reached only with the<br />
greatest difficulty. To balance that seeming pessimism, let me say<br />
that a determined Government, a Government clear on what it wants to<br />
do for Australia, can find means of living with the Constitution.<br />
The Constitution imposes great limitatio ns but the Constitution is<br />
not an alibi. </p>
<p>Garran joined the Public Service in its infancy, along with<br />
many other able men from all walks of life who were inspired by the<br />
creation of the new nation.<br />
He joined the service of Australia at a crucial time, for<br />
public servants, as for politicians, at a time when the demands on<br />
the creative capacities of all those engaged in nation-building<br />
were very great. There are demands, similar in magnitude, pressing on us<br />
today in the challenging environment of the Seventies.<br />
Tonight I wish to speak principally about the role of the<br />
Australian Public Service under a Labor administration, as that Labor<br />
administration responds to the immense challenge imposed upon it<br />
by the decision of the Australian people just under a year ago.<br />
It is not always realised that Australia itself was in a unique<br />
positio n in the English-speaking democracies. None of those other<br />
democracies Great Britain, the United States, New Zealand, Canadahad<br />
been for so long without a change of Government. In the United<br />
States one would have to go back to the Republican hegemony of 24<br />
years from the election of Lincoln to the election of Cleveland.<br />
In Britain itself, from which we take both our Parliamentary system<br />
and our civil service tradition, one has to go back to 1807<br />
to the Tories under Liverpool, Canning and Wellington, from 1807<br />
to 1832 to find a comparable period of unbroken rule by a single<br />
party. That so ancient a parallel has been equalled only in some<br />
of our Australian States may not be without its relevance.<br />
However that may be, it should be recognised that our situation<br />
when we came into government was unique in modern English-speaking<br />
democracies, unique in the Australian National Parliament, unique<br />
for an Australian National Government and unique for the Public<br />
Service responsible to that Parliament and that Government. Yet<br />
this change, unique in so many respects, coincided with and indeed<br />
was largely created by, a desire for clear and rapid change on the<br />
part of the Australian people. The demands upon Government,<br />
upon administration, are greater than they have been at any time in<br />
human history. All governments are expected to make changes and<br />
deliver benefits with a precision and promptitude never before<br />
expected or experienced in history. When a new government comes in<br />
after so long an absence, those demands, those pressures are<br />
accelerated and intensified.<br />
I have sometimes quoted the complaint of Garran' s<br />
co-worker and part-contemporary, Alfred Deakin, about " the<br />
impossibility of governing with a reporter at one's elbow".<br />
He had a lot to complain about at the same time he was complaining<br />
he was, even as Prime Minister of Australia, the anonymous regular<br />
correspondent and reporter for the London Morning Post. No television,<br />
no tapes. Politicians are not so blessed today.' There can be no<br />
doubt that in modern times the immediacy of the media itself is a<br />
strong force generating change and sometimes irresistible pressures<br />
for change by raising exceptionally high expectations about the<br />
potential and performance of administrations. </p>
<p>-4-<br />
For any Government to measure up to these expectations<br />
and to meet these pressures it was inevitable that there would be<br />
changes in the administrative structure.<br />
It is inevitable that political change will bring with<br />
it administrative change in terms of modern politics. This is<br />
not to say, at all, that our Public Service has to be politicallyorientated,<br />
or motivated. It does not.<br />
We as a Government were and are anxious to maintain the<br />
fundamental tradition of a non-political Public Service in the true<br />
sense. This is not to say that public servants will not be involved<br />
in matters relating to politics, rather that their involvement will<br />
be as loyal, as dedicated and as intense regardless of what<br />
Government is in power.<br />
Some doubtless were sceptical whether this tradition<br />
could be maintained. Could the administrative machine that had<br />
been controlled by our political opponents for 23 years respond<br />
to a significant political change to a Government charged with<br />
urgently needed reforms and impelled by a philosophy which involved<br />
a shift from long-established positions?<br />
No doubt the Public Service was equally anxious to see<br />
whether we would be able to adjust effectively to the business of<br />
government, how we would go about the task of governing.<br />
But the significant political change does involve a shift<br />
from long-established positions; it does require an administrative<br />
response of a different order. It is not a difference of a political<br />
order; the difference lies in the magnitude of the challenge.<br />
Under this Labor Administration, the outstanding need<br />
for change, restructuring and expansion arises from our particular<br />
view of the role of the national government. We assert that the<br />
national government has responsibility for a whole range of matters<br />
which under previous Governments were deemed either to be the<br />
responsibility of State Governments or the responsibility of no<br />
government at all. This basic approach of ours was, I believe,<br />
upheld by the people at the election. It is exactly one year ago<br />
tomorrow since I delivered the Policy Speech which outlined our<br />
program. In that speech I said:<br />
" Before this campaign is out, I shall have completed<br />
years as a member of Parliament. The basic foundations of<br />
this speech lie in my very first speeches in the -Parliament,<br />
because I have never wavered from my fundamental belief that<br />
until the national government became involved in great matters<br />
like schools and cities, this nation would never fulfil its<br />
real capabilities."<br />
And in the penultimate paragraph I said:<br />
" We shall need the help and seek the help of the best Australians.<br />
We shall rely of course on Australia's great Public Service, but<br />
we shall seek and welcome the advice and co-operation from beyond<br />
the confines of Canberra." </p>
<p>These sentences do I believe encapsulate the course<br />
that has been pursued by this Administration, in its program and<br />
in choosing the men and women to carry out this program.<br />
Administrative and Advisory Support for the Government<br />
In opening the first session of Parliament on 27 February<br />
the Governor-General said the Government saw the importance of<br />
certain principles upon which we should base our program for<br />
change. One of these principles was the need for Government to<br />
have available machinery and advice to plan for the inevitable and<br />
accelerating change now occurring in all modern communities.<br />
The tradition of democracies based on the British model<br />
is that elected governments have available to them a career<br />
Public Service which is politically neutral and designed to give<br />
administrative support and advice to whatever government may be<br />
in office. But in addition, it has been practice to rely along<br />
with the Service on other forms of support. One of the marks of<br />
our first twelve months is the extension and deepening of that<br />
kind of support to enable us to meet the challenges of office.<br />
In broad terms, the system of support which we have<br />
developed while in office is a blending of five elements<br />
The Public Service, impartial, responsible<br />
and professional<br />
Task forces and Committees of enquiries, with<br />
all or a large part of the membership consisting<br />
of outside experts, highly competent in their<br />
particular fields<br />
Commissions and other continuing authorities,<br />
drawing staff from inside and outside the<br />
Service investigating and managing new areas<br />
of Government initiatives<br />
A new form of long term priorities advise a<br />
" think-tank" which we have named the<br />
Priorities Review Staff<br />
Consultants and outside advisers for Ministers.<br />
The Public Service<br />
My Government took over a large and efficient Public<br />
Service which, since its foundation at the start of the century,<br />
has built up a reputation for efficiency and probity which<br />
places it in the front rank of the Civil Service Systems of<br />
western democratic countries. 6/ </p>
<p>-6-<br />
The Government was, however, elected to carry out its<br />
declared policies and it quickly set about the task. It was not<br />
until after the election that the leaders of the Labor<br />
Parliamentary Party the new Ministers were able to seek the<br />
help of the Public Service Board and others in the Public Service<br />
on how the Service should be restructured. Some difficulties were<br />
encountered, and to an extent these difficulties could be<br />
attributed to some lack of understanding on the part of the<br />
Government and the Public Service of each other's purposes and<br />
processes. In the interests of good Government, I have since<br />
announced that, as long as I am Prime Minister, there will be an<br />
opportunity for pre-election discussion on the structure and the<br />
working of Departments between Members of the Opposition and<br />
senior officials. Naturally, these discussions will not embrace<br />
matters of a party political nature. They will simply ensure<br />
that whenever there is another change of Government, the changeover<br />
as it affects the nation's administration, will take place<br />
as smoothly as possible.<br />
In retrospect, the quite massive changes which can be<br />
seen as reflections of the underlying new orientation of our<br />
policies were brought about with reasonable speed and remarkably<br />
little friction. The changes were by no means revolutionary; they left<br />
the system and the principles on which it is based intact, but<br />
they were substantial and are beginning to have their effects<br />
in achieving our purposes.<br />
All the important changes can be seen as reflections<br />
of the underlying new orientation of our policies. What we have<br />
done is to re-structure departments of state to accord more with<br />
the thrust of these policies. We have brought an emphasis in<br />
departmental strength to accord with the emphasis in the<br />
Government's administration. In so doing we have moved in the<br />
direction of organising departments on a functional basis, of<br />
distributing responsibility in groups which are as homogeneous<br />
as possible. This has led, in part, to the amalgamation of<br />
departments which is now in process.<br />
I am aware that amalgamation as a process can come under<br />
question. I am aware of the problems of size and in particular<br />
the problems of manageability for a single minister and a single<br />
head of department. I am aware of management problems, of staff<br />
morale problems, and public relations problems.<br />
But set against these problems and far outweighing them,<br />
are the advantages of unification. There are the economies<br />
resulting from the reduction of inter-departmental barriers<br />
e. g. the resolution within a single department of the differences<br />
that arise notoriously between separate and competing<br />
departments. There are internal economies economies of scale. .7/ </p>
<p>-7-<br />
But the primary factor as I see it, determining the size<br />
and manageability of large departments, is coherence of subject<br />
matter. It is this coherence that has prompted many of the<br />
structural changes that we have introduced.<br />
Take transport. For too long, we have seen responsibility<br />
f or transport divided between the Australian Government and the<br />
States, without effective co-ordination between the four main arms<br />
road, rail, air and sea. At the Australian level, we are now<br />
moving rapidly towards the amalgamation of the Departments of<br />
Civil Aviation and Transport.<br />
The desirability of amalgamating the Departments of<br />
Transport and Civil Aviation rests on the improvement which is<br />
to be expected in the development and co-ordination of general<br />
transportation policies, the more effective determination of<br />
expenditure priorities and resource allocation and on the greater<br />
ability to harmonise the totality of transport activities with<br />
the Government's other objectives in economic and social fields.<br />
A size problem may arise associated with air and sea navigation<br />
systems. To meet this eventuality we intend to establish<br />
operating agencies functioning separately from Departments.<br />
Take Defence. We are fully aware of the importance of<br />
a highly efficient and mobile defence force. But equally, we<br />
are aware that there is no immediately foreseeable threat to the<br />
security of this country. We are bringing together under the<br />
one administration what should after all be an integrated system<br />
of defence of our country and its interests, and in so doing, are<br />
following the example of other countries. So here again, the<br />
changes we have made in the administration have reflected basic<br />
policy objectives. We are in the process of planning the amalgamation of<br />
the Departments of Works and Housing. This amalgamation will<br />
give us another more co-ordinated way of achieving important<br />
policy objectives in housing and construction areas.<br />
We are considering abolition of the Department of<br />
Supply with transfer of its functions to Secondary Industry<br />
and other areas.<br />
Restructuring of the public service is also evident in<br />
the field of social welfare. Here we have attempted to move from<br />
the fragmented system of our predecessors to a broader concept of<br />
caring for the total needs of an individual. To this end, we<br />
have brought together in the remodelled Department of Social<br />
Security many functions previously handled in other Departments.<br />
And by stripping the Department of Health of a complicated system<br />
of national insurance and payment to individuals, we are allowing<br />
it to concentrate on the important problems of medicine and health,<br />
and on health care delivery. 8/ </p>
<p>7<br />
-8-<br />
In other areas the achievement of our objectives has<br />
called f or the establishment of new Departments. Each of these<br />
Departments is a viable unit, necessary for the attainment of<br />
the Government's policy aims and new initiatives.<br />
The greatest single area of new initiative is in the<br />
cities the places where most Australians live. The time has<br />
come for us to take fresh initiatives in making our cities<br />
places where people can achieve the fullest enjoyment and self<br />
fulfilment in living, as well as to work efficiently and without<br />
unnecessary inconvenience. For this purpose, we established the<br />
Department of Urban and Regional Development. This Department is<br />
at the centre of some of the most important of our policy<br />
initiatives. Here again, we have an example of a Department<br />
comprehending a wide but wholly coherent subject matter.<br />
In my Policy Speech last December, I foreshadowed the<br />
establishment of a separate Department of Aboriginal Affairs<br />
to have offices in each State to give the Australian Government<br />
a genuine presence in the States. The Department of Aboriginal<br />
Affairs is now a fact and is working to give effect to the will<br />
of the people as expressed overwhelmingly in the 1967 referendum.<br />
The Department of the Media will be able to work more<br />
closely with the radio and television industry and for instance<br />
have oversight of the legislation which regulates the industry.<br />
Let me describe what we have done in the words of the new head<br />
of the Department of the Media, himself a man brought from<br />
experience in the business and television world to head our new<br />
department. Mr. Oswin said<br />
" Coming to a decision to form a Department of the<br />
Media didn't mean starting everything from scratch.<br />
A lot of its components already existed and many<br />
of them were functioning efficiently and well, but<br />
they were all over the place responsible to<br />
departments with which they had little in common..."<br />
was a matter of bringing together under a<br />
common Ministry, Government services that were<br />
often misplaced and regrettably, even neglected."<br />
The Public Service has responded magnificently to the<br />
challenges we have set it. But it would simply have been unable<br />
to achieve all that we require in the time available. So, while<br />
retaining it as an expanding administrative centre for all our<br />
activities, we now have working with it in varying relationships,<br />
or independently, many new bodies to provide specialistic<br />
assistance to the Administration. 9/ </p>
<p>There is a further question beyond that of the limits<br />
on the professional public service to carry out all the tasks<br />
required, in the time required. It is in Australia' s interest<br />
and in the interest of the Public Service itself that there<br />
should be greater mobility between business and the universities<br />
and between the federal and state public services. For a job in<br />
the public administration to be done competently it is not always<br />
necessary that the appointment be for life or retirement on<br />
reaching a certain age. Clearly, many valuable men and women<br />
will be unwilling or unable to accept appointment on those terms.<br />
Sometimes a specific task involved is of limited duration. The<br />
task should not be left undone or the skills lost through<br />
inflexibility in the Public Service structure.<br />
Task Forces and Other Inquiries<br />
To help us to focus quickly on the many new areas of<br />
policy initiative, we have brought in academics and practical<br />
men from the private sector.<br />
First, there is the task force. In the main, the object<br />
of the task force is to produce in a short time a report by a<br />
person of stature in the community who is not part of the regular<br />
Public Service. We have provided him with assistance some from<br />
the. Public Service itself and some from our valued group of<br />
consultants and Ministerial advisers with the object of<br />
assembling material quickly and without the problems associated<br />
with departmental boundaries.<br />
The result has been a series of most helpful reports.<br />
The concept of the task force is in the main that the leader<br />
of it assumes responsibility for the report. The task force<br />
helps and advises him but doesn't blunt the acuteness of his<br />
own perceptions and the purport of his policy recommendations.<br />
Perhaps the best known of the task forces was that led by<br />
Dr. Coomnbs, in his investigation of the continuing expenditure<br />
policies of the previous Government with a view to finding room<br />
for our own higher priority programs. Another task force worked<br />
under Mr. Rattigan, Chairman of the Tariff Board and produced the<br />
report which led to the 25% cut in tariffs.<br />
I believe the task force technique to be a most effective<br />
way of producing a high quality report in a short time which<br />
combines the skills and insights of prominent citizens with the<br />
background and experience of the actual working of the Government<br />
machine which officials and ministerial advisers can contribute.<br />
Second, there is the committee of inquiry. In this area<br />
men and women from many walks of life have joined new commissions<br />
and committees; since we came into office, no less than 70 short<br />
term inquiries have been appointed. To mention a few, they range<br />
from inquiries into Aboriginal land rights, to an inquiry into<br />
the Burdekin, into the maritime industry, into the protection of<br />
privacy, into employment statistics, into FM radio, into<br />
rehabilitation and compensation, into legal aid, into nursing<br />
home fees and into the components of growth in urban centres. </p>
<p>The use of specialist commissions and committees of<br />
inquiry serves a number of valuable purposes. These include:<br />
immediate action on a wider range of issues than would otherwise<br />
be possible, many being issues where the electorate, having<br />
given us a mandate, is wanting quick results;<br />
availability of specialised skills and advice not always<br />
required on a bng-term basis;<br />
access to advice and information on developments and research<br />
in industry, academic institutions, the trade union movement<br />
and other community areas;<br />
fostering of co-operation with, and participation by the States,<br />
a matter of special importance in our Federal system of government;<br />
providing a key channel of communication between Parliament<br />
and the people.<br />
Some might argue that some of the matters dealt with<br />
initially in this way could properly have been dealt with by existing<br />
departments. However, such a course would have meant an unbearable<br />
strain on the Service because of the wide range of new matters,<br />
many of which the Service had not been asked to deal with before.<br />
The Service has been and is fully occupied responding<br />
to other initiatives of the Government, as well as ensuring the<br />
normal conduct of business.<br />
The response by talented people of wide experience outside<br />
the Public Service to join us in our endeavours has been quite remarkable.<br />
I mention just a few.<br />
Mr. Justice Woodhouse, of the New Zealand Supreme Court<br />
came to head the Inquiry into a National Scheme of Rehabilitation<br />
and Compensation, and his colleague Mr. Justice Meares from the<br />
Supreme Court of New South Wales.<br />
Mr. Justice Else-Mitchell, Professor Mathews and Mr.<br />
G. J. Dusseldorp on Land Tenure;<br />
Sir James Vernon and others on the Post Office Inquiry;<br />
Mr. Justice Hope and a number of others on the Committee<br />
of Inquiry into the National Estate;<br />
Dr. Scotton and Dr. J. Deeble on Health Insurance;<br />
Mr. McGarvie on Discrimination in Employment and<br />
Occupation together with a number of others including Mr.<br />
G. Polites from the Australian Council of Employers'<br />
Federation and Mr. J. Petrie from the A. C. T. U.<br />
I invite your attention to the range of the inquiries<br />
as well as to the names of those conducting them. </p>
<p>-11-<br />
With the active co-operation of State Governments, we<br />
have been able to secure the services of several State judges to<br />
chair some of these committees.<br />
In making appointments we have, we believe, succeeded<br />
in bringing together people with relevant expertise from all<br />
sections of the community.<br />
Committees of Inquiry have, of course, been used in the<br />
past. But the record shows that the system has not always been<br />
well used I need only mention the fate of the Report of the<br />
Committee of Economic Enquiry whose members were Sir John Crawford,<br />
Professor Peter Karmel, Mr. Kenneth Myer and the late Mr. D. G.<br />
Molesworth under the Chairmanship of Sir James Vernon or the McCarthy<br />
Committee on Dairying. Not the least regrettable feature of the<br />
treatment of the Vernon Committee report at the hands of the then<br />
Government was that it must necessarily have reduced the willingness<br />
of men and women of the highest qualifications, men and women with<br />
very great demands on their time and experience, to serve in a<br />
similar capacity. Whilst I am realistic enough to know that all<br />
recommendations of Committees of Inquiry cannot necessarily be<br />
adopted at least immediately our intention is a positive one.<br />
Most reports are published and acted upon, not shelved<br />
and forgotten. A real contribution is made to public<br />
administration and to the development of policies acceptable to<br />
the community. In this way we are restoring the use of inquiries to<br />
their proper role in Government.<br />
Commissions and Other Continuing Bodies<br />
The willing response of the Public Service and the<br />
efforts of task forces and other instruments of inquiry would not<br />
in themselves have been sufficient to achieve our purposes. So we<br />
have added greatly to the range of support which in greater or lesser<br />
degree has always been associated with government in the field<br />
of statutory commissions and other such authorities.<br />
Since we have taken office, we have made decisions to<br />
appoint no less than 25 continuing bodies to assist us in achieving<br />
our policies. Those already at work include such diverse bodies<br />
as the Cities Commission, the Child Care Standards Committee, the<br />
Commission on Consumer Standards, the National Pipeline Authority,<br />
and the National Commission on Social Welfare. Others are awaiting<br />
the passage of legislation to enable their establishment, for<br />
example, the Industries Assistance Commission and tne Petroleum and<br />
Minerals Authority. The Interim Committees for the Schools<br />
Commission and the Pre-School Commission have advanced their work<br />
quite splendidly, while awaiting their establishment as statutory<br />
bodies. These bodies will in part be supplied from the Public<br />
Service. But in part they will draw to them men and women of<br />
experience in their calling. They will be freer to operate than<br />
the Public Service itself, though necessarily functioning within<br />
the broad framework of government policy and administration. These<br />
are performing a task of administration, often in new and uncharted </p>
<p>-12-<br />
areas, which will have important and positive effects on many areas of<br />
life and activity in the community.<br />
The Priorities Review Staff<br />
One of the difficulties of government is to ensure<br />
continuing challenges to think and plan more than a few months ahead.<br />
There is a real danger that, unless there is a constant input to<br />
government on this side, the day to day pressures will lead to<br />
shorter and shorter term policies, to government that is reactive<br />
rather than inspirational in quality and therefore loses its sense<br />
of direction and purpose. We believe that the best way to maintain<br />
an effective input of longer term thinking is to establish special<br />
machinery for the purpose. It is true that particular Departments<br />
will think months and years ahead and indeed the Treasury for<br />
some time has been preparing three and five year estimates. But<br />
that is not enough.<br />
What we have done is to establish a new group within<br />
the Department of the Special Minister of State which we are<br />
calling the Priorities Review Staff. It consists of highly skilled<br />
specialists with high academic and professional qualifications.<br />
Its purpose is to review Government programs, not with<br />
the object of duplicating or censoring the work of specialist<br />
departments, but with the object of advising ministers on long-range<br />
priorities and planning. It is based on the well-established<br />
Priorities Review Committee headed by Lord Rothschild in Great Britain.<br />
This venture, I believe, marks a significant step<br />
forward in orderly national management and long-range planning. </p>
<p>-13-<br />
Ministerial Staff<br />
As the business of government grows faster and the<br />
range of political involvement of the people extends, Ministers<br />
must necessarily look to more help from their own immediate<br />
offices. It has been traditional to think of the Ministerial<br />
Private Secretary as an efficient and experienced officer of<br />
middle rank, capable of maintaining effective liaison with the<br />
Department and of seeing that the Minister is where he needs<br />
to be to keep his many commitments.<br />
But with the present need to develop and maintain<br />
new policy initiatives involving people outside the Department<br />
and the authorities associated with it, we have found a need<br />
to provide Ministers with greater help on the policy side.<br />
I have no hesitation in saying that the help Ministers have<br />
obtained from their offices has relieved Departments of<br />
involvement in party political matters and has given ministers<br />
support as they have forged ahead in their own particular fields.<br />
In machinery terms, we have improved the quality of the<br />
contribution made by Ministerial staff by increasing both the<br />
numbers and the salaries paid.<br />
Noalte e iiseilstaff have come from outside<br />
the Public Service. There is provision in each Minister's staff<br />
for a departmental liaison officer who remains on the departmental<br />
establishment and undertakes duties directly connected with the<br />
Department. This preserves an avenue for able young departmental<br />
officers to gain valuable experience in the operations of government.<br />
Ministers, of course, are free to choose their staff and many<br />
of them have made personal staff positions available to career<br />
public servants. I have, this year also arranged for substantial increases<br />
in both the numbers and levels of staff available to the<br />
Opposition parties. Again, in my view, this was a very necessary<br />
change. I might point out that the Ministerial personal staff<br />
from outside the professional Public Service have no security of<br />
tenure. They depend wholly on the whim or fate of the Minister.<br />
In no sense can they be said to have been obtruded into the<br />
structure of the Public Service. They are part of the Government<br />
in its political and personal sense and in that sense, they are<br />
responsible to the people, their paymasters and political masters<br />
in the same way as Ministers. </p>
<p>-14-<br />
I should further point out that this development<br />
in no way represents a departure from the principles of the<br />
Westminster system. Central to that system is the principle<br />
that Ministers as individuals and the Cabinet as a whole must<br />
exercise real control over the Public Service and accept full<br />
responsibility for policy. In Australia, the staff of Ministers<br />
has, for various reasons, remained far smaller and junior than<br />
in Britain or Canada. In Britain, the Minister is supported by<br />
Parliamentary Under-Secretaries and by Parliamentary Private<br />
Secretaries as well as a far larger staff. The function of the<br />
Parliamentary Under-Secretary is deemed unconstitutional in<br />
Australia. It is a perfectly objective statement to say that<br />
there have been notable cases in Australia in the past of a<br />
remarkable lack of ministerial control over departments and<br />
over policy. The lack of competent staff undoubtedly contributed<br />
to this. The Canadian model has been descrined as " politicallvorientated<br />
yet operationally sensitive" staff and a " non-parti'san,<br />
operationally-orientated yet politically sensitive" department.<br />
We have not of course adopted that model, but to the extent<br />
that the appointment of a competent personal staff assists<br />
ministers to exercise their proper constitutional authority<br />
we are enhancing the basic Westminster tradition.<br />
Implications for the Public Service<br />
All this means that government is on the move.<br />
I recognise that this imposes strains on the Public<br />
Service. Perhaps there are two particular problems which I<br />
might discuss in a little more detail in the remaining time<br />
available. These relate to the process I have described, by<br />
which many new people and authorities are being added to the<br />
familiar administrative scene; and the emphasis we are placing<br />
on open government. First, the influx of new people and new skills. During<br />
the war years, feeling were expressed which, although more intense,<br />
were much the same as those of which I am aware today. They<br />
relate to the fears which permanent public servants have because<br />
of the possibilities that their own career prospects will be<br />
diminished, or the standards of the Service lowered, as a result<br />
of the influx. It is true that the sweep and pace of the recent<br />
changes have hardly been equalled in peace time in Australian<br />
history. Though as I say this I should make the point I do not<br />
expect the growth of the Public Service in 1973-74 to be more than<br />
This is a figure which has been exceeded on several recent<br />
occasions. You will all be aware of the task force I set up under<br />
the leadership of Dr. Coombs which identified for the Government<br />
a number of areas of spending that could be reviewed. His report<br />
concluded: ' Existing government programs are taxing the resources<br />
of the Australian Public Service and it is clear that<br />
it will be subject to increasing pressure. Administrative<br />
and management skills are important and scarce resources.<br />
It is essential that the cost of existing and new expenditure<br />
programs in terms of these skills be taken into account in </p>
<p>Government decisions and that every effort should<br />
be made to use such skills to the best advantage...<br />
The Public Service Board as the primary authority on<br />
establishment matters must be given a sensible degree<br />
of control in seeking to establish a reasonably uniform<br />
classification structures and to avoid the competitive<br />
ways destructive to wage-justice and reasonable economy<br />
in Government. The fact that the Board should recognise<br />
special competitive elements in particular situations<br />
does not invalidate the need for such control. This<br />
control, with appropriate modifications to deal with<br />
special circumstances, is relevant also to the agencies<br />
outside the Public Service itself such as statutory<br />
corporations.' Some of the additional staff on the payroll of the<br />
Australian Government will merely be a transfer from other places<br />
where, in one way or another, the taxpayer is footing the Bill;<br />
for example Health Insurance now administered by more than<br />
100 private bureaucracies.<br />
The history of the war and immediate post war years<br />
may be of some encouragement, because there is general agreement<br />
that the Public Service today is as efficient as anywhere in<br />
the world, and probably more efficient than most.<br />
During the war years the size of the public service<br />
doubled and the number of departments grew from 13 to<br />
There was great pressure on the public service,<br />
which did not have many of the skills required.<br />
Various people were brought in from outside the<br />
public service, perhaps the most notable being the late Essington<br />
Lewis, then Chief General Manager of Broken Hill Propriety Limited,<br />
who became Director-General of Munitions, but there were others,<br />
including Lawrence Hartnett, another great industrialist.<br />
New people were brought into such areas as rationing,<br />
prices control, manpower control, credit control and censorship,<br />
which were established under National Security Regulations.<br />
Numerous Boards and Committees were set up also to<br />
facilitate communications between agencies, to carry out desired<br />
executive functions or to conduct investigations into specific<br />
topics. Many of the people brought into the public service<br />
in that period attained high office. To mention only some of<br />
the now retired Permanent Heads, there were Sir Kenneth Bailey,<br />
Sir Henry Bland, Sir Allan Brown, Sir John Crawford, Dr Coombs,<br />
Professor Fin Crisp, Mr Ted Hook and Sir Richard Randall.<br />
There are others among them who are still serving in high office,<br />
including a number as Permanent Heads.<br />
We seek more men of their calibre for the tasks of<br />
today, for we are engaged on a new operation mercifully in<br />
a period of peace. </p>
<p>-16-<br />
There is a new light on the hill, if I may recall<br />
a phrase of the late Ben Chifley, and we need all the skills<br />
we can command as we move towards it.<br />
With the introduction of new people and new skills,<br />
the existing Public Service is placed in a more competitive<br />
situation both in relation to competition for higher jobs and<br />
competition for influence in the policy making process.<br />
I see only advantage in increased advertising of<br />
senior Public Service positions as open to people outside the<br />
Service, and indeed I agree with the report of the Boyer Committee<br />
that the morale and self respect of the Public Service could<br />
only be enhanced i-f it felt it were standing on its own feet<br />
by force of merit rather than by restriction of competition.<br />
I am sure, from what I have seen of it, that it can so stand.<br />
We have not altered the traditional role of the<br />
Public Service in the policy making process, but by greatly<br />
increasing our sources of policy advice and by involving public<br />
servants in our task forces and commissions, we have provided<br />
for a meeting of minds, a re-stimulation which is coupled with<br />
a leadership from the political level. Where this has resulted<br />
in tension it has in the main been creative tension and that is<br />
our object. The Public Service has not only demonstrated in<br />
the last twelve months that it can work impartially for a<br />
new Government after 23 years with the old, it has for the<br />
most part shown the benefit of its inter-reaction with the<br />
Government's other advisers and an enthusiasm for working with<br />
others in pursuing the policies of an activist Government.<br />
Perhaps the change in Government had its greatest Public<br />
Service implication in relation to the Permanent Heads of<br />
Departments. Unlike all other public servants, Permanet Heads<br />
are appointed by the Government of the day. They have a<br />
continuing tenure but they also have close personal dealings<br />
with their Ministers.<br />
Before the election there was talk of wholesale sackings;<br />
some observers seemed to expect that we would change the Public<br />
Service by replacing its leaders. This did not happen and at<br />
no stage did we consider it desirable. On some occasions,<br />
associated not only with changes of Government but with, for<br />
example, reshuffling of portfolios in existing Governments, it<br />
is desirable that Permanent Heads be transferred to other<br />
Departments or other duties in the interests of good Government.<br />
Like previous Governments, we have made some changes at the top<br />
of the Service, but this has been done in a manner which does<br />
not damage the tradition of an impartial Public Service.<br />
We all tend to think of the Permanent Head as a policy<br />
adviser. Important and glamorous as this aspect of their work<br />
undoubtedly is, it should not be allowed to obscure the very<br />
real responsibility that Permanent heads carry as general managers<br />
of departments under their Ministers. </p>
<p>-17-<br />
Permanent Heads should be ever mindful of the<br />
need for ensuring that their departments are efficiently<br />
managed, of the need for cost-effectiveness, of their role<br />
in ensuring that staff savings are achieved where possible,<br />
and of the need for leadership of their departments in<br />
such matters as ensuring that personnel are developed to<br />
meet -emerging needs of public administration.<br />
Open Government Greater participation in the affairs of Government by<br />
concerned people in the community generally has been a theme<br />
in this lecture. We want to extend this sense of participation<br />
far beyond the use of particular individuals who have skills<br />
currently needed. We want the Australian people to know the<br />
facts, to know the needs, to know the choices before them.<br />
This is really at the heart of what has been called " open<br />
government". There come times and we recognise this when<br />
decisions must be taken, or are better or more quickly taken,<br />
if there is not at every stage a need for the decision makers<br />
to discuss publicly and explain publicly what they are doing.<br />
A balance has to be struck. I think we are striking that<br />
balance. I myself am reporting regularly to the press and<br />
telling them promptly of decisions that we are making.<br />
We are tabling reports in Parliament, not just the annual reports<br />
of statutory bodies but many papers providing useful general<br />
information where there is a public interest and where other<br />
interests are not compromised.<br />
Legislation foreshadowed in my policy speech as the<br />
Freedom of Information Act will be shortly before the Parliament.<br />
Meanwhile, much is already being done to provide greater information<br />
to the public, particularly by the release of various reports.<br />
At the same time, the Government is very aware of the need to<br />
ensure adequate privacy for the individual.<br />
A review is in train of the legislation to remove<br />
unreasonable restrictions on public servants which inhibit<br />
them from discussing in public matters of public and official<br />
interest. There will still be a proper observance of the<br />
conventions that public servants do not justify or propagandise<br />
policies. That is the job of Ministers. But within the<br />
proper conventions there can be a lot done to relieve public<br />
servants of unnecessary restriction.<br />
We will be bringing down archives legislation which<br />
will clarify the rules relating to access to official records<br />
and facilitate such access. It will also greatly improve the<br />
service that the public gets when they want to consult some<br />
of the more ancient records.<br />
Another aspect of the involvement of the community<br />
generally in government is the benefit which can flow in<br />
both directions from extended arrangements under which staff<br />
of the Public Service spend periods in industry, commerce,<br />
universities and the like and for people from those areas<br />
to spend periods attached to Public Service departments. </p>
<p>-18-<br />
I quote the Fulton Committee. It had this to Aay<br />
' Determined efforts are needed to bring about the temporary<br />
interchange of staff with private industry and commerce,<br />
nationalised industry and local government on a much<br />
larger scale than hitherto. War-time experience proves<br />
beyond doubt the value of such movement in promoting<br />
mutual knowledge and understanding.'<br />
At the same time, while I intend to see arrangements<br />
developed in this area, it is only proper to note also the<br />
warning given by the Fulton Committee that the exchanges should<br />
take place in a professional atmosphere, fostered by the<br />
fact that the majority of public servants expect to make a<br />
career of their period in the Service. They should not see<br />
themselves, or be seen, as in the prospective employment of<br />
business, or something of the necessary confidentiality and<br />
privacy which governments must preserve and protect will be lost.<br />
It is a truism that we live in a changing world.<br />
It is essential that the whole framework of public administration<br />
in Australia be geared to respond to new initiatives of government<br />
demanded by the electorate.<br />
An important factor in this will be the continual<br />
exchange of ideas and discussion of techniques between the<br />
sectors of the economy.<br />
The public sector, which has much to learn from the<br />
private sector, will facilitate this.<br />
But it needs the co-operation of the private sector,<br />
whose interests today demand a better knowledge of the working<br />
of government than ever before.<br />
It may be true that the people get the government<br />
they deserve. It is certainly true that governments get the<br />
Public Service they deserve. The measures, decisions and approaches<br />
I have outlined are designed to promote the efficiency, the<br />
excellence of public administration in Australia, now and for<br />
the future. I close as I began, with a quote from the inaugural<br />
Sir Robert Garran Oration:<br />
" The task before Australia is honourable, and its<br />
efficient discharge would make for a dynamic peace;<br />
to it all the resources, skills and energy that Australia<br />
can command deserve to be committed. The honourable task,<br />
however, could become majestic, and infinitely inspiring,<br />
and the peace could become creative, deep and rich,<br />
and enduring, if there be added what I have termed<br />
Excellence, Excellence in all its fullness."<br />
The pursuit of excellence is still an eminently proper<br />
and desirable goal for Australia, her people, her public<br />
Administration and I believe, her elected Government.<br />
-0-o-0-</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
