<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>719</transcript-id>
    <title>OPENING OF THE NEW SCIENCE BULIDING AT SYDNEY GRAMMER SCHOOL. SYDNEY N.S.W ON 9TH APRIL, 1963</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/04/1963</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000719_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
OMLUG OF TIM MKW SCZI WLIdDNG AT<br />
œ ZNEM SAMU 6CBOJ., SM IU9, JWo<br />
I dea't uind tUlag y" a I a aff" l th~ is aftsuin<br />
mea dwqd~ tkut att night I le1t<br />
MLU = nJ1 ( Apam) uAa to" I heam' to a~ x<br />
0001tlama Oay with a teash of greweaw4 hamout ; W6 lah<br />
SObe" s' I e n. iag ht say all present aut<br />
sueret* 7* 41 M pi or Iew a AnUwarLS ad" tatlp-but<br />
wwb It is from y~ rI ; vOinmt li to sp. Bit ta<br />
Gia4wt~ are, 4' atIsast. am is toot I-6wa lil .1&amp; I<br />
&amp; aV21i*' VGOr the m et or Whe looking a bit<br />
9 dI usaM be tf unius, sa the USA is<br />
um~ fficr thet iMI nm * w o at a" l ( Za61be0<br />
Ue lp bue" s on mm A s that<br />
Is a 410WAatafp. I abMyil0k0, * 0 60 M 4o0 O aMudem.<br />
Ifea " tu&amp; Yew"" that yea have mse ityou can see It*<br />
Aaotherp A aadvAMt to that Apsem this nost<br />
fas urs. eumset as oWith this mwl<br />
.7 hum baldeo<br />
63O . s 1 o ofth " Ltbass am<br />
seek tim 1 3as4 aem maidlp I W, bhaea9 W. Chales<br />
Meh used to be an eld1A of sims) a" We KAR<br />
andh SStw DOWNm do" thelkig thoe e<br />
the a ) aamnddaa ltem I t aid heaving<br />
rd= m Wift 1IMA to fotr1 4 los m<br />
VOOM het I aJan" bwh fat aseasiss &amp; An % h~ ea<br />
I Wii l do1 best to Omewoomm this bandIeap.<br />
at, 0 rosily this IS a ll enn Ww t. I Et<br />
eses~ as yew femastew k" t* Asta n " t<br />
4100 amar" tOf bmsa aic logth<br />
str~ ei~ t~ wswl a 9A to ' UM 4d. ou yamS &amp; U~<br />
WOn Tis. Is wow tMO I hes I boe as" A it And I<br />
st ll mok w but tb wre bum arA thatg. I thlxk,<br />
0Vetf0 thing fte ft* W anda May pad thing 1W<br />
New I gnat to Oabma to To* that W claim to<br />
allt ; 240". are = enerly dwh* Wbo I was a<br />
ho" I bad as inoasrdi 5 somery* I WOs the MMn<br />
of UbeloP t tlu'oso we ti. rte silyo ya"<br />
OXOpt I gse or mteUt. n woeasIi tsow U<br />
brand" IsOtfft I WOW<br />
I -' el to l.. A. VRth: d 1W ber9a as I o" said in the<br />
II-of Nr'. Robou, I a1b0My Ipt fiffy as a reMit.<br />
hil-half thesay * P0stie. fto TI rit WWWW" mt " a<br />
g0* 00** </p>
<p>. O2 g<br />
X7 04tMfie qualiletea Sluem thm . my Instinetiw<br />
bet not smltlmtud osimtifle Ideas haw beau roes MMM<br />
I m a Dt~ of 3sm b* lim It or not of<br />
US M21iOTsltY Of NOW 8outh Wales, and seeing a esupi.. of<br />
pmwftl di al aem uhe are frionis of min Inl 91" st<br />
row I wat t. tall the that I aln als 0; WA; of the JWMl<br />
Crlte Of Oi. 5a. and. Obst-tilms ( Iauitea)( A las)<br />
so you mee a soes M vat entiwly unqi1fin ( Letw<br />
for the tas t asft e* Woo 1 a tboh tWO Codly thin4 dli<br />
Is spsk.( wut., aplueI<br />
* At tt~ ng all that an aw side, the truth of the<br />
Satter is that w hewo heesm pertauAwly ija the last test<br />
twar ea iwe inlj GaseoM of the mlg )) aee or<br />
OcdenevIn aim In1 the whale emhot Of tile afftirs<br />
of the World* ft" i is to aly time. it O beai<br />
that Perhaps we are a little earrIed a*. y I! the ths42LI<br />
or iMelear PWIOSis tv the SPOGUaMlw &amp; dAolWSMsat WhIeb &amp; M,<br />
akIa place no doubt at this moment -iamu p * be" use<br />
gottisIst to b nds to the fat at inaty b<br />
it live* In soe le of some of these 1a<br />
laimfi ted eiaouui bvthe smientift vsft= dameinthis<br />
Oft"-the Woft of the xmio~ e1ogists, the antL -Utis<br />
thed ewebloglem 0t 1MLao dwnl oGmIl, n8o179I n gmtIs WIhn vtWhQea psmotdaAm<br />
i~ sty -all these thJing lFaw not 1 d . y<br />
to ' a wealth and khepeI ness but thhave, in Yu<br />
aeems w lated to a w arbte E= me of WORK liWe.<br />
iir i smetbingr that we a" e not to forgt In vie * ell -IN! t<br />
at the moment of awne tsh~ aehbl Man * tielating Ideas*<br />
I emse took the eppoctunitr of saylingt mo<br />
the univer Itles, at the tin, wham the first SpuLNwenku<br />
and ws to be soon 4r earnet obevr in th * t nkt It<br />
mes imith e while of a lot of the people is the worldA who<br />
waeloekiag at It and mrvoliag at It to remember that MAt<br />
for the vowk partimularly of the numedl selemntists in this<br />
emtury almiios of then woal4 not hae been there to see it,<br />
go, as always*, w wast pulise ftms men and ' ederstand vbat<br />
we are talkint about wbon w are talki of sosee not<br />
a avl ht In all its " seta*<br />
Xo%&amp; io In Australia have I thi nk, two tvs~ no s<br />
Isterests in na~ ssttere, In % 1W rzt Plaee thl o Is n<br />
the maders world, as a proomu of 4. volommat We* an a<br />
eawtazat presemon the mat lewi, a omnstaat inflationary<br />
rd tow em all the tWags that enter Into the est<br />
twLand theee of omsev avo or -v0m1s ifterest,<br />
ow Amovi. t tw man em the land9 to tb fb-Mreur' to tNo<br />
gpesew ad# of lqrnie., of tlvvnisa Interest to ME other<br />
people. No" e and in., q we ae coming to realse that the<br />
right angw to this is not a blind attempt to g!! h basek the<br />
tdqbut the right amewar is to Inorease our orf eiaW of<br />
prodetIoin al Its aspects aid that tho right myto 40 that<br />
Isr lrUZ r devoti" ov a&amp; nMosv soientifla stWW and<br />
to gtoaaPulAtiSSO to the problem In band.<br />
WQ~ W all gem love seem It In my ow liftI<br />
bov the pidelsof wimat Wa improvedo how MMW areas lawe<br />
oe AWr profitable mIUtVOUM that mW tiut to be arid.<br />
Mat an eoms 4evelpmit tber. has been Ina tbe wool iMnftW#<br />
in the sheep Industa7 Ir 0 blt tv eendo--i eeit<br />
ares oeinwrlug awry 6% qiUU% p'eat inlust" ellri" AM<br />
if you Wbaft far snougkL, It Is ver seldom just a happq aemlest#<br />
it is isany the " esuit 6f the earefAl weft of s&amp; me Scientist<br />
In tUs labmtoy a&amp; W of same applied sclentist In the Sn~ g~<br />
flelde 00** 000 </p>
<p>2brow. tbois I qeif an so aeloutist<br />
tholu I i~ f an beod Is the tweditIon of the ainmaties<br />
and hes that tradition will always wvive I si<br />
utterly euMVIWimott wo mt" Par A ia4M. S. Ing attotion<br />
to alientitie tsaa to senetiflo dia'sWWlWyt9 io<br />
aPPlise0tion If we are~ I be wn in the msrdk d time, if o<br />
00VU7IS to hae 30= 9 WAn 10020 a to bmkand<br />
anik Rpoepe fiem that p~ oloe l . abth WWseo the,<br />
fulles of taim am buildig will at sLap: yhdoIng<br />
somthiag that my smmday qua24 hin to told a paitimlr<br />
Job or to tamn a Par'ticular Inmo* m B3e wi la thets be eas<br />
of tbouands aking a osat1Wihtie to the uitXuS' adaommet<br />
of the tiyo A the 1 e-out of the country and the<br />
oMvaammest of the pseople and thed he Inins a-ut<br />
tban auq Individual a ta etma lfil* iv h<br />
first reeu Tbe sooem resoni is perhaps ist iaojated with<br />
It. We boe a soupIdly-p'eving Pepulatiem we hoea emn<br />
it 11 10i11100 A l In Axistalia, mimy aosniea<br />
I fit Immv vhs i6 uate of Ausi NOWk te<br />
are other 0amtrigss th V4t0% 1M into e8f2.0010110010<br />
asI~ 4 just 401ging late aust MsseiMAO spum. 0<br />
tiie a a fateulag may th esi ~ tatOf lf-. sen mt<br />
The pepsiai of ( biaa Itself will probably be a tamsd.<br />
plla at the ta of the ewtwu. The peu ofIna<br />
Ww illion. The popuafte of IA i Ipts VWY now<br />
to 100 ailitm We mvhw b4s, b.. ealagiaplay ~ e~<br />
of Million of people in the ; W no iai n La settlod,<br />
somm~: L~ o tv uag the amnities of life that we enjq,<br />
lapasIty ro at wating tbm useiag than tmatrglIac twvds<br />
them, 9 and owt owmW sa Ist it fM-lmdIas<br />
that : It vast piadne selatist not wItself butttete<br />
emutresLathe world baemess we bae a taUs m souutribation<br />
to make if this owvwtd La to deowlep ad mintain Its pride,<br />
SOWO its lsuuja-6m and to ha able to held up its beat IS the<br />
ftll proes of what we sell medaihs OListIon<br />
An sov flor the IM14oal# tt Whs, mtin, for<br />
other grast ations In the venld, the study of * clanoe, the<br />
attaining of the higbost possible standards, bovw beesm of<br />
vital lapoatmmee. One of the reasonsWw1 L Be sotly * adire the<br />
liciatiwe vook of the inbastril fnd end of those publiospirited<br />
. stoma ftsot its affairs, Is that when I was<br />
a seolb4 adeatiftle equipment was of a highly lUeantaN<br />
kind Tda it bosoms note and oompea s nt at Ganes<br />
as In a research univeity oart Il a univorsIty or the swml.<br />
Sstill eoaplx and expesive as eapareod to the<br />
iv apparsas of the pest. It Is mash mstly to<br />
establish a selam theamtp in a MIniwersi then it is to<br />
iestablish a arts tbeslty. ? u ta tooo people rLUn, with<br />
s~ difflty, I tako It* hat you am toek people [ atla witk<br />
the nialoolf of eqUIput. NYv xpewies. was aom beaks and<br />
a teache with a gimlet eje ( aUghte.) fTat was the equipmt<br />
that eold set you ping an the rood.*<br />
* la L os" a it is big nom that Is mw ovnded,<br />
This Involves baso~ oe eawi amd La the 1pm00140<br />
flelA, dealing as I do with Whe UNiVORsieS, ofrAstella I<br />
an ia* SraeSily . s Oaof this fact bollus the outay, ewe0<br />
WO 00 </p>
<p>S se the Vst Nwey Ropet we adod lw vas9 6m<br />
Itself 13Vthrb. yews* LAd this nsot ivtsl<br />
to%: e f equigAjmt. ! h MW mtli~<br />
this as a of pwsreeel experismee hs onm<br />
Its am emtuibatmsp amasiwv as tqare es.<br />
l1aSotoi J 4tet to seeiNg that oa jist ' mt an<br />
agmabg, Ith pOd Ught Sming tMMKOnl too<br />
va tholt yft hae. the UMesu of IthLLhhag<br />
timof the Stmwt œ guim pep up to the<br />
at vhiohk they to wis = Lppsty,<br />
fepeooins out of bosaie<br />
Swip dir that is all I west to Saq. I boe<br />
s too Issas hIs a Ofem thing abiautih offset<br />
I wll have to opt air xweem sf~ to GiplAmw It to as<br />
Smetis a swig" s thin shout L f'ot 40the optic<br />
jme, but it you Is*~ at a akleme, o a sth daft* as<br />
lesgs 1have beft1O~ higat yo$ y iito PLAout a<br />
ftv faoas and tht's hAwt has bow happening to mo* Iat<br />
Is perhaps * 7y I be" spdm teo lang.<br />
size at I wa't ObRth~ its msom hae<br />
ak my Post doinl of . mtisgtioua nde] awig this lmdlding<br />
OPS1 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
