<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3185</transcript-id>
    <title>NATIONAL BROADCAST</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/03/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Broadcast</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003185.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
R; SA 17 LiV~~ GC: 7.3' . M<br />
March 1974<br />
NATIONAL BROADCAST<br />
Good evening. I want to talk to you tonight about some basic issues<br />
of democracy, about your fundamental rights as citizens in a free<br />
society. At the Senate elections later this year the Government<br />
will be putting several referendums to the electors. By voting<br />
YES in those referendums you will be doing two things: you will<br />
be giving a new deal to local government, to the local councils<br />
that provide many of our essential services; and you will be CfaI<br />
Aeussttarballiisahnisn, g tfhoer tbhaes icf irdsetm octrimaet, i c anrdi ghftosr oafl l Autsitmer. a lians. All Z<br />
There is no principle more basic to democracy than<br />
that all people should be equal in their rights and freedomsI.<br />
We hear a great deal about gerrymianders in Australia, about<br />
politicians rigging the electoral system to suit their own 6--<br />
interests. And it's unfortunately true that there have been<br />
many examples of this practice in our history. Fo r decades<br />
* in every State there have been wrangling and debate on this<br />
Wquestion. And it's not just the Labor Party that complains;<br />
the electoral laws in Queensland where the Government is dominated<br />
by the Country Party are directed just as much against the Liberals<br />
as they are against Labor. In every State, one party or another<br />
is usually complaining about bias in the electoral system.<br />
The reason for all this wrangling the reason whyv.<br />
politicians can gerrymander electorates for their own purposes<br />
is that there is nothing in the Constitution to stop h.<br />
There is nothinq in the Constitution to guarantee<br />
Parliaments must be elected directly and democratically by the<br />
people. There is nothing to guarantee equal voting rights<br />
for all Australians. So the Government has decided, by means<br />
of these referendums, to allow the people to establish these ktt~ t<br />
rights once and for all. 4<br />
A-<br />
7 ljf. g </p>
<p>-2-<br />
t I~~ prseut.. J n in every mainland<br />
State Parliament, 1 Le : cL c~ -41i. par to gain<br />
a majority of seats even if, after the distribution of preferc-nc<br />
I it has gained much less than a majority of' votes. In every i-ousce<br />
there are cases where some clectoratces cont-ain more than twice as<br />
many pcople as other electorates. That's not democracy; its; nct.<br />
justice. FThere is one House of Parliament -the Legislative<br />
Council of New South Wales that is not elected by the people<br />
at all; its elected by the politicians, some of them about to<br />
retire. And country people suffer as well. as city people.<br />
In Western Australia there are more people in the Pilbara<br />
electorate than there are in any other electorate except one.<br />
In the same way, votes inMount Isa are worth less than votes<br />
Xn Brisbane. So it goes on. To use a good Australian phrase,<br />
the system is crook. It's time we did something about it.<br />
My Government tried to remedy this situation last<br />
year, when we introduced amendments to the electoral laws that<br />
would have made the size of electorates in the national<br />
Parliament pretty much the same; much closer to the ideal<br />
* of equality. The Senate twice rejected our legislation.<br />
SQ we have now resolved to let the people decide this q. uestion.<br />
If our referendums are carried it will mean that every Australian<br />
Parliament State or Federal will be * elected directly by the<br />
people, ahd that in each House-of Parliament any electorate will<br />
have, as nearly as practicable, the same number of people as any<br />
other electorate. We put this emphasis on people because registered<br />
voters are not the only individuals who matter in a democracy;<br />
they are not the only ones whose interests are represented ina<br />
* Parliament. Children have no vote, but children matter;<br />
unnaturalised migrants have no vote, but their interests matter;<br />
many Aborigines choose not to enrol, but their rights and<br />
welfare are important. We belie~ re that in a truly democratic<br />
system all people matter and all people must be treated as<br />
equal. That's the view taken by that great instrument of<br />
democracy the United States Supreme Court. For the past ten<br />
years, the court has ruled that any inequality in the population<br />
of electorates in the Congress-or in the State legislatures is<br />
unconstitutional. In Australia any elector will have tho right<br />
to approach the High Court for a decision on any of ti: c<br />
electoral matters. And let me remind you of this: this<br />
particular proposal will come into operation in July 1976. That<br />
Is, it will be the next House of Representatives and the next<br />
State Parliament which will in each case have to comply with<br />
this new safeguard. </p>
<p>I<br />
I -3-<br />
4v wp'+ to ensure tha-c. 17--ions for the House<br />
of Representatives and the Senate are neid at the same time-<br />
Ji not just when'it suits the Government to hold them toget'her,<br />
but always, In the eleven y'ears from 1961 to 1972 we had eighnt<br />
national elections. That's too many it's inconvenient for<br />
th1e people, it's bad for the working of Parliamenti and it's<br />
too costly. The simple proposition is that elections for t * he<br />
national Parliament should normally be held every three years<br />
aorfni dg hatnasyl waoSyres n aatufotorrh orwbihototy h tooHfoo ku seeiostf hfeitrco eg eHtotuhhserere;. e yenToharir ss wiawlgolon ' toi rt awfsifhleolcr tt entt ahekth* ee--tem<br />
office this year. this safeguard will come into operation<br />
at the House of Representatives elections after next.<br />
Furthermore, we are asking you to approve a proposal<br />
that will make it easier to amend the Constitution in ways that<br />
the majority of the electors approve.. Instead of requiring a<br />
majority of voters in four States to approve a change in the<br />
Constitution, it will be sufficient to have a majority , in<br />
three States provided there is a majority of all the<br />
Australian electors including Territory electors. I remind<br />
you that that change was recommended as far back as 1958 by the<br />
Constitutional Review Committee established by Sir Robert Menzies.<br />
The same committee endorsed the proposal for simultaneous<br />
elections of both Houses of Parliament. They are sensible'<br />
proposals. Let's do something about them.<br />
, Finally, we are asking you to give a new deal to19w<br />
local government. For generations now, local councils have<br />
sleawcekreadg et, h e defciennatn cicaolm murneistoyu rcheesa lttho psreorvviidcee s, b etctheirl d rocaadrse, cebnettr esi* T<br />
and facilities for sport and recreation. These services are<br />
best provided by local authorities, but the Constitution makes<br />
no mention of local government. By agreeing to our<br />
referendum, you will enable the national Government to borrow<br />
money for local. authorities if they wish and top up their<br />
revenuesif they wish. In this way the national Government will<br />
be able to have direct financial dealings with local government<br />
bodies in helping them to do the job for which they were elected.<br />
I know this adds up to a long list of proposals, but<br />
we would not be putting them to you unless we were convinced<br />
of their urgency and importance. Our opponents have not only<br />
resisted our reforms; they have done their best to preveait<br />
you, the people, from deciding these questions for yourselves.<br />
I ask you to keep in mind the basic principle enshrined in<br />
our proposals; their candid and honourable purpose. They go"<br />
beyond party politics to elementary rules of right and justice.<br />
We seek an end to all gerrymanders, by any party, by all<br />
politicians, for all time. I believe deeply, from life-long<br />
conviction, that these reforms will make Australia a more just'<br />
and dbmocratic nation a model of democracy in the eyes of our<br />
neighbours and the world. Goodnight. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
