<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11038</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                   THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                   TELEVISION INTERVIEW WITH KERRY O&amp;#146;BRIEN                 7:30 REPORT                                                  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/05/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Subjects: Senator Harradine's decision</p>
<p>E&amp;OE................................................................................................</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>John Howard, what happens now.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well we will amend the legislation in the Senate to give effect to</p>
<p> all of the increases in compensation and other changes that I outlined</p>
<p> to Senator Harradine yesterday. We will naturally do everything to</p>
<p> the legislation that I told him yesterday we were going to do. We'll</p>
<p> then put that legislation up and if it's rejected we'll</p>
<p> put it up again. And that's because the Government believes that</p>
<p> this country badly needs taxation reform. We told people all of the</p>
<p> details of our plan before the last election. It's not just a</p>
<p> GST. It includes massive cuts in fuel taxes, it includes a 30% top</p>
<p> marginal rate for 80% of Australian tax payers, it takes $4 billion</p>
<p> off our exporters, $10 billion off business costs, and it's</p>
<p> got $13 billion of personal tax cuts. It's a total revamp of</p>
<p> our system, and we need it. And I believe in it because it's</p>
<p> good for Australia, not because I'm on some ideological kick.</p>
<p> I've got plenty of other things I could be ideological about.</p>
<p> But I really believe that this country will be better and stronger</p>
<p> if we can have a changed tax system.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Was it clear from Senator Harradine's conversation with you today</p>
<p> that not only does he reject this latest package of yours, but that</p>
<p> he is now not open to any further offers, that his mind is made up</p>
<p> against the GST?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>That was the very clear impression that he gave to me today. I thought</p>
<p> until the last 24 hours that he may have thought that it was more</p>
<p> important to honour the mandate we received at the last election,</p>
<p> particularly as we made full disclosure before the election what we</p>
<p> were going to do, that that would, with a bit of extra compensation,</p>
<p> that that would outweigh his reservations about the character of our</p>
<p> taxation reform. But he decided no.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>So once you've put it a second time, if it's rejected a</p>
<p> second time, will you keep open the option of a double dissolution</p>
<p> election on your tax reforms?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well if a bill is rejected a second time after the lapse of three</p>
<p> months it's always open for a government to have a double dissolution.</p>
<p> You'll understand I'm not foreshadowing now when the next</p>
<p> election will be. I don't know when it will be and I would think....</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>But it's a live option?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well it's always a live option of you have a double dissolution</p>
<p> trigger, yes of course it is. But we don't need another election.</p>
<p> We just had one on the GST and I made full disclosure. I mean I looked</p>
<p> everybody in the eye and said this is what I'll do if I get elected.....</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>But then you've taken it back to a Senate that wasn't elected</p>
<p> at this election.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh yeah, but I mean I think that's fairly corny argument. Well</p>
<p> if that is the only objection then the Senate that was elected at</p>
<p> the last election ought to pass it the second time around.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Except that unfortunately for you the same who put you back into government</p>
<p> also put in a Senate that would appear to continue to be hostile to</p>
<p> the GST.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>But governments are formed in the Lower House and if we're to</p>
<p> have a political process that works then it's got to a possible</p>
<p> for a party that makes full disclosure to get its mandate implemented.</p>
<p> I mean it would be a different matter if I had simply said to the</p>
<p> Australian public if you reelect me I'll cut your personal tax</p>
<p> by 20% and I didn't say anything about the GST until after the</p>
<p> election which is what a certain Mr Keating did in 1993.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>It's hardly a screaming mandate if you scramble back by a few</p>
<p> thousand votes and less than 50% of the vote overall.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>There's an old political saying that if you get 50 plus 1 you</p>
<p> win by a landslide.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>You always seemed confident that you'd be able win Senator Harradine</p>
<p> in the end with what you called more than once, fine-tuning. You were</p>
<p> wrong it seems.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, I said I was hopeful, rather than confident. I always thought</p>
<p> it would be difficult but I was hopeful. And we certainly made a very</p>
<p> generous change to the compensation arrangements. The pensioners alone</p>
<p> will get almost $800 million more compensation; 5% instead of 4% increase</p>
<p> in the pension; and in future, if the plan goes through, the pension</p>
<p> will be always 26% of male average weekly earnings instead of 25%.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>And yet you never convinced Senator Harradine at any point that you</p>
<p> were able to guarantee that these compensations would last over time,</p>
<p> that they would not be eroded over time, whereas as he said in the</p>
<p> Senate today, the GST is there for good.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well no current Parliament can bind a future Parliament. By the same</p>
<p> token a future Labor government could increase wholesale sales tax.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>But you are binding a future government to the GST aren't you?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well a future government can repeal a GST.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Only with the support of the Premiers. I mean you......I'm</p>
<p> sorry, no, that was about increasing it.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yeah that's right. Now they can repeal it. I mean, you've</p>
<p> put a very interesting point, the Labor Party is against the GST yet</p>
<p> when asked Mr Beazley doesn't promise to repeal it if he inherits</p>
<p> it. I mean we are being utterly consistent. I have always believed</p>
<p> in tax reform. Mr Beazley knows that tax reform is needed. The three</p>
<p> Labor leaders I've opposed, Bob Hawke, Paul Keating, and Kim</p>
<p> Beazley, all at some stage have embraced a GST. Mr Beazley is engaging</p>
<p> in political opportunism by doing what he's doing now.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>But the person whose vote you really needed, and the person who appeared</p>
<p> to approach this with all sincerity and no kind of political opportunism</p>
<p> was Senator Harradine. Do you accept that he has been sincere in this?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well look, I don't make a judgment about Senator Harradine accept</p>
<p> things that he said to me. He's been honest with me. But it doesn't</p>
<p> alter the fact that..he's not accountable to me. He's accountable</p>
<p> to the Australian people. I mean the Australian people will make a</p>
<p> judgement about him. It's not for me to pass a judgement. I've</p>
<p> always found...</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>I think you've been respectful of him in the past.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yeah, I've always found him to be an honest person to deal with,</p>
<p> and I've always dealt honestly with him.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>He sat through four months of Senate hearings on the GST. He's</p>
<p> obviously agonised for months over this decision and he does appear</p>
<p> to be genuine in this. If you're right and he's wrong, having</p>
<p> listened to all he's listened to as an intelligent man how could</p>
<p> he get it so wrong?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I can't answer that Kerry. I can't answer that. In</p>
<p> the end in politics what you do is you put up a program, you seek</p>
<p> electoral support for it and then you hope you can implement it. Now</p>
<p> I did that. I mean nobody could say for a moment that I held anything</p>
<p> back. I mean we hear a lot of criticisms of politicians for being</p>
<p> deceitful and dishonest. On the issue of tax reform I was open, I</p>
<p> was patent, I was sincere, I was transparent. I told it warts and</p>
<p> all before the last election. Now if you can't in those circumstances</p>
<p> get your program implemented, we really are approaching political</p>
<p> gridlock in this country because under the present electoral system</p>
<p> no one side of politics can ever win control of the Senate. So the</p>
<p> only way you can ever hope in a decent sense to get your program implemented</p>
<p> is to spell it out in detail before an election and then say to the</p>
<p> Senate the people knew about it, they returned us and you ought to</p>
<p> pass it.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Senator Harradine made the point also today, and in this he seems</p>
<p> to agree with Labor, that if the system ain't broke why fix it.</p>
<p> And I suppose what he's pointing to, amongst other things, is</p>
<p> that you've brought in a surplus of $5.4 billion in your next</p>
<p> financial year. If you look at future years without the GST you could</p>
<p> be looking at a surplus of $20 billion three years from now. Now how</p>
<p> is that system broke if it can deliver you that kind of surplus?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well it's broke in a number of ways. It doesn't provide</p>
<p> enough funds for the States. One of the great advantages of the GST</p>
<p> is that it will underwrite the essential services of the States. A</p>
<p> tax system is not just about raising revenue. It's also about</p>
<p> making our exporters more competitive. We could be a wealthier more</p>
<p> competitive, more successful society if 80% of our taxpayers paid</p>
<p> only 30 cents in the dollar at the top. If we provide more incentive</p>
<p> we can have a more energetic, more forward-looking community. We are</p>
<p> a vast country. The price of haulage by fuel is still too great in</p>
<p> this country. All of those things can be attended to by taxation reform.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>But presumably if you've got a $20 billion surplus to play with</p>
<p> three years from now you can provide a greater largesse in a number</p>
<p> of those areas that you're talking about now.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well Kerry, you can't assume that you'll have all of those</p>
<p> surpluses forever, and after all we are accumulating surpluses now</p>
<p> to pay off the debts that Mr Beazley ran up when he was finance minister.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>But $20 billion would look after that.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well hang on, we inherited $90 billion, so we have a lot of debt still</p>
<p> to pay off. And what we would like to do with those surpluses Kerry</p>
<p> is not squander them, but to use them to repay debt.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>You've faced the prospect of this defeat for months now. What</p>
<p> is your alternative plan, your fallback plan if you go through the</p>
<p> process of the next three months of being rejected twice in the Senate?</p>
<p> What is your fallback plan for the tax reform that you say you're</p>
<p> going to remain committed to?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well Kerry, I think you should invite me back in 3 months time, and</p>
<p> I promise to appear if that eventuality occurs. I have known from</p>
<p> July 1997, when I resolved that this country needed taxation reform,</p>
<p> that I would have to go through this process. That I would have to</p>
<p> go to the public, telling them everything, laying it out in detail,</p>
<p> running the risk of a fear campaign, running the risk of losing the</p>
<p> election. Facing the inevitability of not controlling the Senate,</p>
<p> knowing that I would have to try and persuade Brian Harradine, and</p>
<p> Mal Colston to support us. I knew that. I've known that for two</p>
<p> years and in that sense I'm prepared for all eventualities. But</p>
<p> that is the only way that you can get tax reform. There is no other</p>
<p> way because that is our system. I mean Kim Beazley 14 years ago believed</p>
<p> in what I now believe in. He supported a broadbased indirect tax in</p>
<p> 1985. Bob Hawke did, Paul Keating did. We all know it's needed.</p>
<p> They're playing games. The country deserves better.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>John Howard, we're out of time. Thanks for talking with us.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Pleasure.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
