<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3369</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON. E.G. WHITLAM, Q.C., M.P., TO TEH ITALIAN COMMITTEE OF COORDINATION FOR THE LAUNCHING OF ITALIAN WEEK 1975 MELBOURNE, SATURDAY, 31 AUGUST 1974</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>31/08/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003369.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE PRIME INISTER,<br />
THE 0E. G. HITLA],<br />
TO THE ITALIANCOMIITTEE OF COORDINATION<br />
FOR THE LAUNCHING OF ITALIAN WEEK 1975<br />
' ELBOURNE, SATURDAY, 31 AUGUST 197'!.<br />
IT IS A RARE PLEASURE IN 1974 TO BE LAUNCHING ITALIAN<br />
WEEK 1975. I WISH WE COULD PLAN POLITICAL EVENTS WITH THE.<br />
SAME CERTAINTY. THIS IS THE FIRST IMPORTANT FUNCTION OF THE<br />
ITALIAN COMMUNITY I HAVE ATTENDED IN lIELBOURNE SINCE BECOMING<br />
PRIME MINISTER, IT WILL CERTAINLY NOT BE THE LAST.<br />
AUSTRALIANS NEED NO REMINDER OF THE CONTRIBUTION OF THE<br />
ITALIAN COMMUNITY TO OUR SOCIETY. ACKNOWLEDGE IT. WE ARE<br />
GRATEFUL FOR IT, IT IS IMPORTANT, HOWEVER, TO PROVIDE THE<br />
FULLEST OPPORTUNITY FOR CONTACTS BETWEEN OLD AUSTRALIANS AND<br />
THE ITALIAN COMMUNITY AND BETWEEN ITALY AND AUSTRALIA THEMSELVES<br />
IN THE FIELDS OF ART, CULTURE, EDUCATION AND COMMERCE. ITALIAN<br />
!' IEEK THEREFORE HAS A VALUABLE FUNCTION. THERE IS NO OTHER<br />
COMPARABLE NATIONAL CELEBRATION IN THIS COUNTRY. IT IS<br />
FITTING THAT WE SHOULD HONOUR THE LARGEST AND THE OLDEST OF THE<br />
EUROPEAN MIGRANT COMMUNITIES IN AUSTRALIA. ' ITH THE EXCEPTION<br />
OF THE BRITISH, NO MIGRANT IS MORE ACCEPTED, MORE RESPECTED OR<br />
MORE ADMIRED THAN THE ITALIAN. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
AUSTRALIA'S LINKS WITH ITALY GO BACK TO THE BEGINNINGS<br />
OF EUROPEAN CIVILIZATION ON THIS CONTINENT. THE FIRST ITALIANS<br />
TO SET FOOT ON AUSTRALIAN SOIL MAY WELL HAVE BEEN ANTONIO PONTO<br />
AND JAMES MARIO MlATRA, BOTH OF WHOM SAILED IN CAPTAIN COOK'S<br />
' ENDEAVOUR;". IN 1793 THE TUSCAN MlARQUIS ALESSANDRO M'ALASPINA<br />
LED AN EXPEDITION WHICH ENTERED BOTANY BAY, IN 1.352<br />
GIUSEPPE GARIBALDI, THE GREAT ITALIAN PATRIOT AND FIGHTER<br />
FOR THE UNIFICATION OF ITALY, IN COMMAND OF THE BRIG CARMEN'.<br />
WEIGHED ANCHOR OFF TASMANIA. HE LATER WROTE NOSTALGICALLY<br />
OF THE HAVEN OF PEACE AND BEAUTY HE FOUND THERE FAR FROM THE<br />
TURMOIL OF EUROPE,<br />
THE FIRST ITALIAN EMIGRANTS TO AUSTRALIA WERE ATTRACTED<br />
BY THE GOLD DISCOVERIES OF THE 1350s, THROUGHOUT THE 1050S<br />
AND 1360S A STEADY STREAM OF ITALIANS ARRIVED IN SOUTH EASTERN<br />
AUSTRALIA, AND IN 1370 THE ITALIAN CONSUL IN " IELBOURNE ESTIMATED<br />
THEIR NUMBER AT AROUND 1,0' 01. MOST WERE NORTHERN ITALIANS<br />
FROM SONDRIO AND NEARBY PROVINCES OF LOMBARDY; SOME WERE FROM<br />
PIEDMONT AND GENOA; A VERY FEW WERE FROM SOUTHERN ITALY AND<br />
SICILY. MOST OF THE LOMBARDS WENT TO THE GOLD FIELDS AND SOME<br />
K MADE THEIR FORTUNES IN WALHALLA AND HEPBURN. OTHERS LEFT THE<br />
DIGGINGS TO BECOME FARMERS, OTHERS MOSTLY FROM GENOA, * iAPLES<br />
AND SICILY, WORKED AS SAILORS AND STEVEDORES IN THE COASTAL<br />
SHIPPING TRADE, OR AS FISHERMEN. 914 / 3 </p>
<p>-3<br />
AMONG THE VERY EARLY ARRIVALS WERE THE CHALK-FIGURINE<br />
MAKERS FROM LUCCA AND THE VIGGIANESE STREET-MUSICIANS. THE<br />
HISTORIAN F, LANCASTER JONES HAS POINTED OUT THAT TODAY THERE ARE<br />
THREE GREAT CENTRES OF VIGGIANESE CULTURE VIGGIANO, IEW YORK<br />
AND fIELBOURNE. HE HAS WRITTEN: " INTERESTINGLY ENOUGHT IT WAS<br />
PROBABLY THESE MUSICIANS WHO PLAYED A PROGRAM OF ITALIAN MUSIC<br />
AT THE INAUGURATION OF MELBOURNE'S DANTE ALIGHIERI SOCIETY IN<br />
AUGUST 139E, A SHORT SEVEN YEARS AFTER THE FOUNDATION OF THE<br />
PARENT SOCIETY IN ITALY, FOR IELBOURNE WAS THEN THE CULTURAL<br />
CENTRE OF AUSTRALIA, AND ITALY THE CULTURAL CENTRE OF THE WORLD,<br />
BY THE TURN OF THE CENTURY THERE WERE 6,09 ITALIANS IN<br />
AUSTRALIA, BETWEEN THE CENSUSES OF 1921 AND 1933 THE NUMBER OF<br />
ITALIAN-BORN IN AUSTRALIA INCREASED THREE-FOLD TO MORE THAN<br />
2C, 000. SINCE 1945, AS A RESULT OF LARGE-SCALE ITALIAN<br />
IMMIGRATION, 165,000 ITALIANS HAVE BECOME AUSTRALIAN CITIZENS<br />
AND THERE ARE TODAY WELL OVER A QUARTER OF A MILLION<br />
ITALIAN--BORN PEOPLE IN AUSTRALIA.<br />
AUSTRALIAN CITIES ABOUND IN EVIDENCE OF ITALIAN WORK AND<br />
INFLUENCE. MUSIC WAS NURSED BY ITALIAN TEACHERS OF COMPOSITION,<br />
INSTRUMENTS AND BEL CANTO; PERFORMERS, SINGERS, MAESTRI. FOUNDERS<br />
OF SCHOOLS, AND OF CHAMBER AND SYMPHONIC ORCHESTRAS. ALBERTO<br />
ZELMAN FOUNDED THE VICTORIAN SYMPHONY ORCHESTRA, PIETRO CECCHI<br />
TAUGHT DAME NELLIE ! MELBA; VITELLI FOUNDED ALAN'S HOUSE OF ' IUSIC.<br />
COUNT CARANDINI MADE A FAMOUS PRIMADONNA OF HIS TASMANIAN--BORN WIFI<br />
MARY BURGESS, A RELATIVE OF SHELLEY. CLAUDIO ALCORSO, TILL RECENTI<br />
CHAIRMAN OF THE AUSTRALIAN OPERA COMPANY, AND NOW A MEMBER OF THE<br />
UNIVERSITIES COMMISSION, WAS KNIGHTED BY THE PRESIDENT OF THE<br />
ITALIAN REPUBLIC. ,/ 4 </p>
<p>4<br />
A LONG LINE OF ARTISTS EXTENDS FROM BRAMBILLA, A VERY<br />
EARLY SETTLER, TO ANTONIO DATTILO-RUBBO, WHO FOR MANY YEARS<br />
CONDUCTED ONE OF THE LEADING ART SCHOOLS IN SYDNEY AND WHO<br />
TAUGHT, INFLUENCED AND ENCOURAGED A GENERATION OF PAINTERS.<br />
MONTEFIERE WAS ONE OF THE FOUNDERS OF THE NEW SOUTH WALES ACADEMY<br />
OF ART IN 1371. WELL-KNOWN CONTEMPORARY ARTISTS INCLUDE<br />
ERNESTO MURGO, A VICTORIAN SCULPTOR WITH HIS OWN ART GALLERY,<br />
WHO LECTURES IN SCULPTURE AT THE MELBOURNE TECHNICAL COLLEGE.<br />
FRANCO BELGIORNO-NJETTIS, AN ENGINEER WHO CAME TO AUSTRALIA<br />
9 IN 1951, IS ALSO AN ARTIST AND SCULPTOR. THE TRANSFIELD<br />
ENGINEERING GROUP, OF WHICH HE IS ONE OF THE PRINCIPALS, IS<br />
O NOTED NOT ONLY FOR HEAVY STEEL CONSTRUCTION BUT FOR ITS PATRONAGE<br />
OF THE ARTS. THE TRANSFIELD PRIZE HAS BEEN FOR MANY YEARS ONE<br />
OF THE BEST-ENDOWED ART AWARDS IN AUSTRALIA. IN 1973 TRANSFIELD<br />
SURPASSED ITS PREVIOUS CONTRIBUTIONS WITH THE ORGANISATION OF THE<br />
FIRST SYDNEY BIENNALE, HELD IN THE OPERA HlOUSE.<br />
o CARLO CATANI CAME TO AUSTRALIA IN THE 1379s AND<br />
AS CHIEF ENGINEER FOR THE VICTORIAN PUBLIC WORKS DEPARTMENT, WAS<br />
O RESPONSIBLE FOR THE CREATION OF THE ALEXANDRA GARDENS AND ST.<br />
KILDA ROAD. THE CATANI TOWER OF ST. KILDA AND LAKE CATANI, ON<br />
MOUNT BUFFALO, WERE NAMED AFTER HIM. ETTORE CHECCHI, A<br />
CONTEMPORARY OF CATANI'S AND ALSO AN ENGINEER FOR THE VICTORIAN<br />
GOVERNMENT, IS NOTED FOR HIS EXPLORATION OF THE UPPER NIURRAY AS<br />
WELL AS FOR HIS CONTRIBUTIONS TO THE PLANNING OF THE IUME<br />
RESERVOIR. THERE HAVE BEEN FAMOUS PHYSICIANS AND SURGEONS LIKE<br />
FIASCHI; SCIENTISTS LIKE THE ASTRONOMER BARACCHI; GREAT FAMILIES<br />
SUCH AS THE CILENTOS. RAFFAELLE CARBONI, AN HISTORIAN AND EX-SCHO<br />
TEACHER, WENT DOWN IN HISTOPY AS ONE OF THE MINERS' LEADERS AT THE<br />
EUREKA STOCKADE IN 1854. </p>
<p>lORE RECENTLY, IN ADDITION TO THE SKILLS OF ITALIAN<br />
IMMIGRANTS, WE HAVE HAD THE EXAMPLE OF TWO GREAT ITALIAN<br />
ENTERPRISES WHOSE ACTIVITIES HAVE BEEN A MODEL AND IN MANY<br />
WAYS AN INSPIRATION FOR THE POLICIES OF THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
GOVERNMENT. I REFER TO ENTE NAZIONALE IDROCARBURI ( ElII) AND<br />
THE INSTITUTO PER PA RICOSTRUZIONE INDUSTRIALE ( IRI).<br />
WITH THEIR WORK AND ACHIEVEMENTS IN MIND WE HAVE SOUGHT TO<br />
EXTEND THE ACTIVITIES OF THE AUSTRALIAN INDUSTRY DEVELOPMENT<br />
CORPORATION AND ESTABLISHED THE PETROLEUM AND MINERALS AUTHORITY,<br />
ALL OF US KNOW WHAT ITALIAN MIGRANTS HAVE DONE FOR<br />
AUSTRALIA THE BENEFITS AND SKILLS, THE VITALITY AND ENERGY<br />
THEY HAVE BROUGHT TO OUR WAY OF LIFE. ONLY RECENTLY, HOWEVER,<br />
HAVE AUSTRALIANS FULLY ACCEPTED THEIR RESPONSIBILITIES TO<br />
MIGRANTS AND RECOGNISED A DEEP AND CONTINUING OBLIGATION TO<br />
THEM. RECENTLY THE GOVERNMENT DECIDED THAT THERE SHOULD NO<br />
LONGER BE A SEPARATE DEPARTMENT OF IMMIGRATION, FAR FROM<br />
DOWNGRADING THE VALUE WE PLACE ON MIGRANTS OR IMMIGRATION,<br />
THAT DECISION RECOGNISED THAT MIGRANTS MUST BE TREATED IN<br />
EVERY WAY AS FULL AND EQUAL CITIZENS. IT HAS BEEN TOO EASY<br />
IN THE PAST TO PUT MIGRANTS IN SEPARATE COMPARTMENTS, IN<br />
SPECIAL CATEGORIES, AND SHUFFLE OFF RESPONSIBILITY FOR THEM<br />
TO THE STATES OR TO OTHER DEPARTMENTS. [ NOW AT LAST WE HAVE<br />
ACKNOWLEDGED THAT MIGRANT CITIZENS ARE AUSTRALIANS IN EVERY WAY,<br />
AND THEIR RIGHTS AND PRIVILEGES, THEIR DUTIES, THEIR PROBLEMS<br />
AND THEIR NEEDS ARE NO DIFFERENT IN PRINCIPLE FROM THOSE OF<br />
ANYONE ELSE. </p>
<p>THIS DOES NOT MEAN THAT WE HAVE ABANDONED OUR CONCERN<br />
FOR MIGRANTS. IT DOES NOT MEAN THAT WE NO LONGER FEEL A SPECIAL<br />
OBLIGATION TO THEM. No GOVERNMENT HAS DONE MORE FOR THEIR<br />
HAPPINESS, THEIR SECURITY OR THEIR FUTURE THAN WE HAVE.<br />
UNDER THE OLD ARRANGEMENTS IT WAS IMPOSSIBLE FOR A<br />
RELATIVELY SMALL DEPARTMENT OF IMMIGRATION TO DEAL ADEQUATELY WITH<br />
SUCH DIVERSE MATTERS AS SETTLEMENT, WELFARE, EDUCATION, CITIZENSHIP<br />
AND POPULATION. THE DEPARTMENT SIMPLY DID NOT HAVE THE PHYSICAL<br />
OR FINANCIAL RESOURCES TO HANDLE THESE MATTERS. IT LACKED THE<br />
POWER TO PERFORM MANY OF THESE FUNCTIONS ADEQUATELY. SOCIAL<br />
SECURITY BENEFITS FOR MIGRANTS OR THE IN-SCHOOL EDUCATION OF<br />
MIGRANT CHILDREN WERE ESSENTIALLY FUNCTIONS OF OTHER DEPARTMENTS.<br />
REMEMBER THAT BEFORE LABOR CAME TO POWER THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
GOVERNMENT ADOPTED A VERY LIMITED ROLE IN SUCH AREAS AS EDUCATION<br />
AND URBAN AFFAIRS. IN THE FIELD OF SOCIAL SECURITY, ITS MAIN<br />
TASK WAS TO GIVE OUT PENSIONS AND OTHER WELFARE BENEFITS.<br />
IN ALL THESE AREAS THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT'S ROLE HAS NOW<br />
CHANGED RADICALLY. IN EDUCATION WE ARE SEEKING TO ELIMINATE<br />
AREAS OF DISADVANTAGE, . TO PROVIDE EQUAL OPPORTUNITIES FOR ALL<br />
AUSTRALIAN CHILDREN, NOT JUST TO HAND OUT ARBITRARY PER CAPITA<br />
PAYMENTS. IN SOCIAL SECURITY, THROUGH THE SOCIAL WVELFARE<br />
COMMISSION AND THE AUSTRALIAN ASSISTANCE P LAN, WE ARE TRYING TO<br />
ESTABLISH COMMUNITY WELFARE FACILITIES FOR ALL AUSTRALIANS. IN<br />
SHORT WE HAVE BECOME AN INITIATOR, AN ACTIVIST IN THESE FIELDS<br />
IN A WAY THAT NO PREVIOUS AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT HAD ATTEMPTED.<br />
s i i </p>
<p>5B<br />
IT IS ONLY LOGICAL THAT, IN LINE WITH THIS EXPANDED<br />
ROLE, MIGRANT AFFAIRS SHOULD COME WITHIN THE PURVIEW OF THE<br />
RELEVANT AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT DEPARTMENTS, IF THE DEPARTMENT<br />
OF EDUCATION IS TO TACKLE GENUINELY THE PROBLEMS OF THE<br />
DISADVANTAGED IN OUR SCHOOLS IT CANNOT IGNORE MIGRANT<br />
EDUCATION, IF THE DEPARTMENT OF SOCIAL SECURITY AND THE<br />
SOCIAL WELFARE COMMISSION ARE TO RESTRUCTURE OUR WELFARE<br />
SYSTEM EFFECTIVELY THEY CANNOT IGNORE THE WELFARE NEEDS OF<br />
MIGRANTS, THE SOONER WE SEE MIGRANT NEEDS AS PART OF THE<br />
OVERALL NEEDS OF THE WHOLE COMMUNITY, THE SOONER THOSE<br />
NEEDS WILL BE MET BY THE BODIES WITH THE APPROPRIATE STAFF,<br />
FACILITIES, FINANCES AND RESPONSIBILITIES,<br />
THE GOVERNMENT'S EMPHASIS IS NOT ON MERE NUMBERS OF<br />
MIGRANTS BUT ON THE WELFARE OF MIGRANTS. WE BELIEVE M'IGRANTS MUST<br />
HAVE THE SAME OPPORTUNITIES AS ALL OTHER AUSTRALIANS TO LEAD A<br />
FULL AND HAPPY LIFE AS FULL AND EQUAL CITIZENS, IN PARTICULAR<br />
WE BELIEVE THE EMPHASIS IN AN IMMIGRATION PROGRAM SHOULD BE<br />
ON THE REUNION OF FAMILIES, S/ </p>
<p>THE MOST DRAMATIC RESULT OF OUR POLICIES HAS<br />
BEEN TO CHECK THE FLOW OF' DISILLUSIONED AND DISAPPOINTED<br />
MIGRANTS LEAVING AUSTRALIA, PLACING FAMILY REUNION FOR MIGRANTS<br />
ABOVE MERE RECRUITING,, WE HAVE STOPPED THE MIGRANT DRIFT.<br />
THE NUMBER OF MIGRANTS WHO BECAME AUSTRALIAN CITIZENS IN 1973<br />
INCREASED By 485 PER CENT OVER 1972, p AND THE NUMBER RETURNING<br />
TO THEIR COUNTRIES OF ORIGIN DECLINED FOR THE FIRST TIME<br />
IN NINE YEARS. THESE FIGURES ARE DEEPLY GRATIFYING TO THE GOVERNMENT.<br />
THEY SHOW THAT WE ARE MAKING MIGRANTS HAPPIER AND MORE CONTENTED<br />
CITIZENS, WITH WIDER OPPORTUNITIES TO SHARE IN THE BENEFITS OF<br />
AUSTRALIAN SOCIETY. IN EFFECT, WE ARE SAYING IT IS NOT THE<br />
GOVERNMENT THAT SHOULD DECIDE WHO WILL COME To AUSTRALIA AS<br />
MIGRANTS, BUT MIGRANTS THEMSELVES. IA NEW CITIZEN WHO HAS SETTLED<br />
HAPPILY IN AUSTRALIA IS THE BEST PERSON TO RECOMMEND OTHERS TO<br />
JOIN HIM. VIE ARE BRINGING FAMILIES TOGETHER, AND WE ARE<br />
BUILDING UP OUR MIGRANT POPULATION ON THE ONLY PROPER BASIS<br />
A BASIS OF HUMANITY AND COMPASSION.<br />
THE AIM OF OUR'POLICIES IS TO PROMOTE THE SECURITY OF<br />
MIGRANTS AND'REMOVE THE CAUSES OF NEEDLESS FEAR, FOR EVERY NEW<br />
CITIZEN IN A NEW LAND THERE ARE NATURAL SOURCES OF ANXIETY.<br />
THERE ARE LANGUAGE PROBLEMS, PROBLEMS OF LONELINESS, HOMESICKNESS<br />
AND ISOLATION.. THERE ARE WORRIES ABOUT EMPLOYMENT AND HOUSING.<br />
THERE ARE UNFAMILIAR LAWS. THERE IS, PERHAPS, A FEAR OF<br />
DEPORTATION. THERE IS A FEAR THAT HE MAY NEVER BE ABLE TO RETURN<br />
TO THE LAND OF HIS BIRTH OR REJOIN HIS LOVED ONES IN OLD AGE.<br />
THERE IS A FEAR THAT, IF HE DOES LEAVE AuSTRALIA, HE WILL BE<br />
PENALISED FOR DOING SO THROUGH THE LOSS OF SOCIAL SERVICE ENTITLEMENT s. e t17 </p>
<p>-7<br />
THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT HAS WORKED VIGOROUSLY TO<br />
REMOVE THESE CAUSES OF FEAR. ', 1E HAVE M1ADE GREAT PROGRESS. ONE<br />
OF OUR GREAT REFORMS HAS BEEN TO INTRODUCE THE PRINCIPLE OF<br />
PORTABLE PENSION RIGHTS. UNDER LEGISLATION PASSED BY THE LABOR<br />
GOVERNMENT, PEOPLE IN AUSTRALIA RECEIVING AGE AND INVALID PENSIONS,<br />
INCLUDING WIVES'I OR WIDOWS I PENSIONS, ARE ABLE TO RECEIVE THOSE<br />
IN ANY COUNTRY WHERE THEY CHOOSE TO LIVE. THE NEW LEGISLATION<br />
IS BENEFITING AGED, INVALID AND WIDOWED MIGRANTS WHO WISH TO<br />
RETURN TO THEIR FORMER HOMELANDS. IT APPLIES EQUALLY TO ALL<br />
RECIPIENTS OF PENSIONS, INCLUDING THOSE BORN IN AUSTRALIA,<br />
WHO WISH TO LIVE ABROAD.<br />
IN MY POLICY SPEECH FOR THE LAST ELECTION I PROMISED<br />
ANOTHER VERY IMPORTANT REFORM FOR MIGRANTS. THE PRESENT<br />
INCOME TAX LAW ALLOWS CONCESSIONAL DEDUCTIONS FOR DEPENDANTS<br />
To AUSTRALIAN RESIDENT TAXPAYERS ONLY WHERE THE DEPENDANTS<br />
ARE THEMSELVES RE SIDENT IN AUSTRALIA, IN THE CASE OF A MIGRANT<br />
WHO COMES To AUSTRALIA INTENDING TO BRING HIS WIFE AND CHILDREN<br />
OUT TO THIS COUNTRY AS SOON AS HE HAS MADE A HOME FOR THEM, A<br />
PERIOD OF FIVE YEARS IS REGARDED AS A REASONABLE TIME FOR THE<br />
WIFE AND CHILDREN TO JO'IN THE MIGRANT IN AUSTRALIA. IF HE<br />
MAINTAINS THE FAMILY DURING THIS PERIOD INCOME TAX DEDUCTIONS FOR THE<br />
DEPENDANTS ARE ALLOWABLE TO HIM. </p>
<p>HOWEVER, MIGRANTS WHO ARE MAINTAINING DEPENDENT<br />
RELATIVES OVERSEAS WITH NO VIEW TO BRINGING THEM TO AUSTRALIA,<br />
OR WHO MAY BE PREVENTED FROM BRINGING THEM To AUSTRALIA BY<br />
RESTRICTIVE EMIGRATION POLICIES IN FORCE IN SOME COUNTRIES, ARE<br />
UNABLE TO QUALIFY FOR A TAX DEDUCTION FOR DEPENDANTS. THE<br />
GOVERNMENT WILL EXTEND THE PROVISIONS OF THE INCOME TAX LAWS<br />
GOVERNING DEPENDANTS'I DEDUCTIONS TO ENTITLE PEOPLE IN THESE<br />
SITUATIONS TO THE TAXATION ADVANTAGES AVAILABLE ALREADY TO<br />
ALL OF US MAINTAINING DEPENDENT RELATIVES WHO RESIDE IN<br />
AUSTRALIA. LABOR'S CONCERN. FOR MIGRANTS IS A CONTINUING CONCERN.<br />
IT FLOWS FROM OUR WHOLE SOCIAL PHILOSOPHY, IT IS NOT SOMETHING<br />
DISCOVERED ONLY AT ELECTION TIME.<br />
W'E HAVE STANDARDISED THE REQUIREMENTS FOR CITIZ7ENSHIP<br />
SO THAT EVERY MIGRANT SEEKING AUSTRALIAN CITIZENSHIP CAN DO SO<br />
IRRESPECTIVE OF NATIONAL ORIGINS AND UNDER CONDITIONS APPLYING<br />
EQUALLY TO ALL. THE PERIOD OF RESIDENCE IS NOW THREE YEARS<br />
FOR EVERYONE. WE HAVE AMENDED THE CRIMES ACT SO THAT IT IS NO LONGER<br />
POSSIBLE FOR AUSTRALIAN CITIZENS INCLUDING, OF COURSE,<br />
NATURALIZED MIGRANTS TO BE DEPORTED, TASK FORCES HAVE BEEN<br />
ESTABLISHED IN ALL STATE CAPITALS TO IDENTIFY THE MOST URGENT<br />
SETTLEMENT PROBLEMS CONFRONTING MIGRANTS. EACH IS CHAIRED BY A<br />
MEMBER OF PARLIAMENT AND INCLUDES PEOPLE IN DAY-TO-DAY CONTACT<br />
WITH MIGRANTS AND THEIR NEEDS, </p>
<p>9-<br />
THE GOVERNMENT HAS SET UP A COMMUNITY ' RELAT IONS<br />
COMMITTEE OF THE IMMIGRATION ADVISORY COUNCIL TO INQUIRE INTO<br />
DISCRIMINATION AGAINST MIGRANTS, EXPLOITATION OF MIGRANTS AND<br />
THEIR USE OF COMMUNITY SERVICES.<br />
AUSTRALIA'S FIRST TELEPHONE SERVICE IN 20 LANGUAGES<br />
HAS BEEN ESTABLISHED IN THE CAPITAL CITIES TO ANSWER EMERGENCY<br />
PLEAS FOR HELP FROM MIGRANTS.<br />
MiIGRANT EDUCATION CENTRES HAVE BEEN OPENED IN PERTH.,<br />
BRISBANE, MELBOURNEj SYDNEY AND ADELAIDE.<br />
BJY MEANS OF THE AUSTRALIAN ASSISTANCE PLAN, THE<br />
GOVERNMENT IS SEEKING TO INVOLVE LOCAL COMMUNITIES IN PLANNING<br />
THEIR WELFARE SERVICES. THE PLAN HAS SPECIAL SIGNIFICANCE FOR<br />
ITALIAN MIGRANTS BECAUSE IT PROVIDES THEM WITH AN OPPORTUNITY TO<br />
PARTICIPATE WITH OTHER AUSTRALIANS IN ESTABLISHING WELFARE<br />
PRIORITIES AND LOCAL COMMUNITY NEEDS. TO HELP EXPLAIN THE PLAN<br />
TO MIGRANTS, THE DEPARTMENT OF SOCIAL SECURITY IS PREPARING AN<br />
EXPLANATORY LEAFLET FO. R ITALIAN PEOPLE AND OTHER MIGRANT GROUPS.<br />
HERE IS ONE SMALL BENEFIT THAT I KNOW WILL PLEASE MANY<br />
OF YOU. YESTERDAY THE POSTMASTER-GENERAL ANNOUNCED THAT, FROM<br />
TOMORROW, THE MINIMUM CHARGE FOR A 3-MINUTE TELEPHONE CALL<br />
FROM AUSTRALIA TO ITALY WILL BE REDUCED FROM $ 1-~ TO $-D </p>
<p>6 p 10<br />
I BELIEVE AUSTRALIA'S PRESENT IMMIGRATION POLICIES<br />
ARE A RETURN TO THE HUMANITARIAN IDEALS THAT INSPIRED THE<br />
MIGRATION PROGRAM NEARLY 30 YEARS AGO, lE ARE DETERMINED THAT<br />
MEN AND WOMEN FROM OTHER NATIONS WHO HAVE SHOWN THEIR FAITH<br />
IN AUSTRALIA WILL HAVE THAT FAITH REWARDED AND RESTORED,<br />
MIGRANTS WILL BENEFIT AS MUCH AS OTHER AUSTRALIANS I REMIND<br />
YOU THAT MIGRANTS WILL BENEFIT LIKE EVERYONE ELSE FROM THE<br />
GOVERNMENT'S REFORMS IN HEALTHj HOUSINGi THE ENVIRONMENTj<br />
THE CITIES AND EDUCATION ESPECIALLY EDUCATION, IT WILL<br />
NO LONGER BE NECESSARY FOR SCHOOL PRINCIPALS TO RESIGN IN<br />
PROTEST BECAUSE OF THE POOR CONDITIONS FOR MIGRANT EDUCATION<br />
IN AUSTRALIAN SCHOOLS,<br />
I AM GRATEFUL FOR THE OUTSTANDING CONTRIBUTION<br />
MIGRANTS AND ESPECIALLY ITALIANS HAVE MADE TO AUSTRALIA'S<br />
PROGRESS, I LOOK TO THEM TO HELP US BUILD A GREATER AUSTRALIA<br />
FOR ALL OUR PEOPLE A MORE HUMANEj TOLERANT, JUST AND<br />
BOUNTIFUL SOCIETY, WE ARE DETERMINED THAT MIGRANTS WILL<br />
SHARE FULLY IN THE PRESENT PROSPERITY AND FUTURE PROMISE OF<br />
THE NATION THEY HAVE DONE SO MUCH TO DEVELOP AND ENRICH, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
