<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6427</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT, TODAY SHOW, 13 JULY 1984</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/07/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006427.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
47 i PAR UMLEN l. STER<br />
TRANSCRIPT TODAY SHOW 13 JULY 1984<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
LEIBMAN: Today sees the end of the 1984 Labor Party National<br />
Conference in Canberra and most observers agree that the<br />
Government has emerged with a range of moderate and flexible<br />
policies even though the Conference wasn't all smooth sailing<br />
uranium, East Timor, and to a lesser extent foreign banks<br />
provided the controversy and decisions on those issues didn't<br />
all go the Government's way, providing small embarrassments for<br />
Prime Minister Hawke. Nevertheless Mr Hawke has every reason<br />
to feel more than satisfied with the outcome of the Conference<br />
and I spoke with him last night and asked if he was satisfied<br />
that the Conference's decision on uranium reflected the community's<br />
view. Well it's not a question of thinking about it. Every poll<br />
that has been taken of the Australian community shows that they<br />
agree, if I can put it this way, with the position which I<br />
have been advocating now in Australia since the end of the<br />
1970' s. I've been steadfast in advocating this and every poll,<br />
including the latest which was taken on 29 May of this year by<br />
the Bulletin, showed these things. Firstly a clear majority<br />
of all Australian voters, secondly the majority of voters in<br />
all parties the majority of Labor voters, the majority of<br />
Democratic Party voters and the majority of Liberal/ National<br />
Party voters, and thirdly, as the issue was put as though women<br />
are different on this issue, a clear majority of women in favour.<br />
And that poll is confirmed by the most recent research that we've<br />
done within the Australian Labor Party.<br />
LEIBMAN: Why then limited mining and export of uranium.<br />
I mean, as Tony Gray has said, if it is good enough for<br />
South Australia and Northern Territory, why not elsewhere?<br />
But I quite frankly concede that you could point to<br />
limits of logic in this position. But you have to move in a<br />
way which takes account of the current realities. Let me make<br />
this point that it's my assessment that with Ranger operating<br />
which I remind you is the second largest uranium mine in the world<br />
that's operating now in the Northern Territory and with Roxby<br />
coming on stream which will be the largest mine in the world<br />
than Australia is going to be able in the foreseeable future<br />
with the resources it's got to meet the contract requirements<br />
that it's likely to come up for. Now the Party has made its<br />
decision in those circunstances and I believe the overwhelming<br />
majority of Australians think it's a sensible way of going about<br />
it now. </p>
<p>LEIBMAN; Prime Minister, one of the major factors at this<br />
Conference was the emergence as a voting block, if you like,<br />
of the Centre Left and at least one leading member of the Left<br />
wing has said that the Centre Left is really just ' a wing of<br />
the Right. Do you agree with that? Gerry Hand was the man<br />
who said it.<br />
Yes well I've never been one who believes that the<br />
application of tags as IVve put it, exhaust. your intellectual<br />
responsibility in analyzing political events. Some people<br />
. seem to think if you just say I'll put this tag<br />
on, that you've really said everything, and of course that is a<br />
nonsense and always has been a nonsense. I think the reality<br />
Steve, is essentially this, that the votes that we have won,.<br />
the Government has won, that have won support for the positions<br />
that I have espoused, I think those votes would have emerged<br />
at any rate. But I think to the credit of the Centre Left<br />
grouping., as they describe themselves, that they have been,<br />
able to impose a disciplineupon those votes. And so where<br />
there imight have been perhaps one or two who straggled over<br />
the other way I think the existence of the group has meant a<br />
more tightly disciplines vote and so we have tended to maximise<br />
or go close to maximrising, anyway, the votea5 for what I regard as<br />
the sensible positions, the ones which both reflect I think,<br />
fundamental Labor positions and the aspirations of the Australian<br />
people, so I think that's been the advantage of the disc iplining<br />
of those votes. </p>
<p>LEIBMAN: How do you think Bill Hayden has eme'ged from<br />
this Conference? I mean , ome sections of the media this<br />
morning were suggesting that he is now the Party's elder<br />
statesman. PM: I don't think elder statesman is the right word, but I think<br />
that Bill Hayden has emerged with considerabl&amp; credit in the<br />
period leading up to the Coference. Bill and I have had a number<br />
of conversations, and it really reflects what I said in answer to<br />
a previous question that we agree on issues. I;: think he's<br />
played an admirable role within his group, particularly if<br />
I may say so, on the uranium issue. Because within the Centre<br />
Left, there were a few, five, &amp; bout five, who were regarding<br />
themselves in a somewhat difficult position about<br />
voting for us on this matter. Now Bill and others within<br />
the Centre Left, in the meetings-that they held on this<br />
issue, held a very tough line, and a persuasive line.<br />
And that is to their credit.<br />
LEIBMAN: Mr Hawke, on the DAvid Combe decision, you said that<br />
you hope the affair is now a thing of the past. But do<br />
you really believe after what happened to Combe that he is<br />
willing to forgive and forget?<br />
PM: I can't put myself into David's mind. All I can say<br />
is this: that everyone who's been ulose to me from that day<br />
in April last year when I had this situation put before me,<br />
everyone knows that at no stage have I had any personal<br />
animus against David. How could I? He's been a friend<br />
of mine for very many years as I said to the Conference. I had<br />
saved him in 1976 at the time of the Iraqi affair and had<br />
incurred the wrath of people across the spectrum in the Labor<br />
Party. So how could I have any aniraus against him as a person?<br />
And at no point have I had that. I've noticed that he's said some<br />
very tough things about me but I can understand that he was<br />
hurt. His family was hurt, and its human nature in those<br />
circumstances that he's going to say some tough things. All<br />
I'm saying and putting the proposition that I believe its in<br />
the past, is to say that there is no blackball on him and<br />
what he feels towards me, how he feels, he can conduct himself,<br />
towards me is a matter for DAvid. I have no animus and the<br />
relationship is really a matter for him.<br />
LEIBMAN: Would you give him a job?<br />
PM: Well, what we've said is that there's no impediment,<br />
there's no blackball. He has talents, qualities to bring to<br />
bear and I would think that if he saw-fit to apply for some<br />
position that may arise, of some contract with the Government:<br />
that should arise, he'd obviously be in a very good position<br />
to get it. What's been clarified is that there is no impediment<br />
there and what's important in respect of his business is<br />
that the private sector should not see him as being less<br />
qualified to conduct his business than others because<br />
of anything that's happened. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
