<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9261</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ KEATING MP MEMBERSHIP OF THE CIVICS EXPERT GROUP</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/06/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009261.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER494<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
MEMBERSHIP OF THE CIVICS EXPERT GROUP<br />
The Government has finalised today the membership of the Civics Expert Group.<br />
I foreshadowed the creation of the Expert Group in my address to the New Educational<br />
Realities Conference on 15 June 1994. The Expert Group will provide the Government<br />
with a plan for a program of -public education. and information on. Australian government,<br />
citizenship and the constitution. The Group's terms of reference are attached.<br />
The Expert Group will be chaired by Professor Stuart Macintyre, the Ernest Scott<br />
Professor of History in the University of Melbourne and a Council Member of the<br />
Constitutional Centenary Foundation. Professor Macintyre has published numerous<br />
books on Australian history, most recently A History for a Nation.<br />
The other members of the Group will be Dr Kenneth Boston, Director-General of the New<br />
South Wales Department of School Education; and Ms Susan Pascoe, Co-ordinating<br />
Chairperson ( Policy) of the Catholic Education Office in Melbourne.<br />
Under the terms of reference the Expert Group will provide the Government with a<br />
strategic plan for a non-partisan program of public education and information on the<br />
Australian system of government, the Australian Constitution, Australian citizenship and<br />
other civics issues. In addition, the Expert Group is to monitor the implementation of the<br />
education program and contribute to its evaluation.<br />
The terms of reference will enable the Expert Group to consult widely, with education<br />
authorities, with political parties and with other expert and interested bodies of individuals<br />
in the field, such as the Constitutional Centenary Foundation.<br />
I have asked the Group to report by 30 November 1994.<br />
As a nation we do not seem to know enough about our system of government and our<br />
national achievements. As I said in my address on 15 June, the Government's education<br />
program will strengthen our democracy by enlivening our appreciation of it. It will inform<br />
all Australians of the privileges and responsibilities of Australian democracy and ensure<br />
that Australians have sufficient information about our system of Government to<br />
participate fully in decision-making processes.<br />
CANBERRA 23 June 1994 </p>
<p>ATTACHMENT A<br />
CIVICS EXPERT GROUP<br />
TERMS OF REFERENCE<br />
The function of the Civics Expert Group is to provide the Government with a<br />
strategic plan for a non-partisan program of public education and information on<br />
the Australian system of government, the Australian Constitution, Australian<br />
citizenship and other civics issues. In addition, the Expert Group is to monitor the<br />
implementation of the program and contribute to its evaluation.<br />
The Group will draw on an assessment of the current level of knowledge of<br />
governmental, constitutional, citizenship and civics matters in the community,<br />
based on research by an expert consultant working in consultation with the Group.<br />
The goal of the Government's public education program is to ensure that<br />
Australians have sufficient information about our system of Government to<br />
participate fully in decision-making processes. The public education program<br />
would therefore be expected to cover a broad range of topics which may include:<br />
the Australian Constitution, its history and development; how the federal<br />
government is structured and operates, including the role and working of the<br />
Parliament, the Judicature and the Executive, together with the Governor-General<br />
and the Monarch; Australia as a federation and the roles of the three tiers of<br />
government; the role and responsibilities of the citizen in government ( eg voting,<br />
jury duty); the principles of responsible parliamentary government; and the<br />
symbols and traditions of our government.<br />
The education program should address the needs of school students and others<br />
in the community. The strategic plan should be available to the Prime Minister by<br />
November 1994. The Government will arrange for its publication. The<br />
strategic plan should have regard to relevant initiatives undertaken by other<br />
organisations and should include recommendations concerning:<br />
initiatives to address deficiencies in the level of public understanding of<br />
governmental, constitutional, citizenship and civics matters;<br />
approaches to the development and testing of appropriate educational<br />
materials; and<br />
the timing, implementation and evaluation of the education program.<br />
In developing the strategic plan, the Expert Group should have regard to the<br />
following objectives for the education program: </p>
<p>to educate and inform the public about governmental, constitutional,<br />
citizenship and civics issues in Australia;<br />
to help Australians understand their rights and responsibilities as citizens and<br />
to promote good citizenship; and<br />
to enhance Australians' capacity to participate fully in decision-making<br />
processes affecting these issues.<br />
In developing the strategic plan the Group should ensure that recommended<br />
initiatives: have regard to rigorous quality standards and best practice in teaching and<br />
education; are planned to ensure that materials are available on an equitable basis;<br />
are non-partisan and likely to attract wide public acceptance;<br />
take account of the need for rigorous standards of accountability;<br />
use existing programs and delivery mechanisms where possible; and<br />
are planned to provide for appropriate evaluation to assess efficiency and<br />
effectiveness.<br />
The Expert Group should consult, to the extent practicable, with relevant<br />
organisations such as the Constitutional Centenary Foundation, with political<br />
parties and with Australia's government and non-government education sectors. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
