<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10303</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP ADDRESS TO LIBERAL PARTY DIVISION LUNCHEON BRIBANE CONVENTION CENTRE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/04/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010303.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Fax from15/ 04/ 97 17: 28 Pg: 1<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
April 1997 TRANSCRIPT OF TrM PRIE MINISTER<br />
THE RON JOHN HOWARD MP<br />
ADDRESS TO LIBERAL PARTY DIVISION LUNCHEON<br />
BRISBANE CONVENTION CENTRE<br />
Well, thanks Bob-It's great to be in Queensland. You shouldn't be so shy. But Bob, to<br />
you aad to your wifc and all the other members of the Queensland Division, can I say that<br />
I always do enjoy coming to Brisbane. I came to Brisbane frequently in the various other<br />
&amp; uses I've had in politics and I've enjoyed coming to Queensland and to Brisbane since<br />
becomeing Prime Minister. And today is the-fulfilment of yet another Coalition promise<br />
and that was to take the Cabinet of Australia away from Canberra Sydncy and<br />
Mclboune. And to take the Cabinet of Australia around Australia, and thereby to chive<br />
home the point that we were elected to govern for all of the Australian people and not just<br />
for the people who dwell in Canberra or Sydney or Melbourne. I can assure you that over<br />
the re= two years and beyond there will be regular Cabinet meetings in the mainland<br />
capitals of Australia and also regular Cabinet meetings in major provincial ccntres.<br />
We've already haed one or two provincial Cabinet meetings and there will be more to<br />
come over the cours of the next two years. And these exerises are not token exerrcises<br />
they arc a demonstration of the genuine commitment by the government to take the<br />
deliberations and the processes of government around the couutry. There is not the<br />
slightest doubt in my rnind that the more time we spend on the road, the more time we<br />
spend out of the Federal capital, the more timne we spend out of the two major<br />
metropolises of Australia, t greater will be our wuderstanding and the beter will be our<br />
knowledge of what the mainatreamn of the community really wants.<br />
Queensland of cour~ se was a marvelous Stae fbT us polirleally at the last election. The<br />
two party prefettd vote the Coalition received in March of Last yeAr in the State of<br />
Qeensland has not been beted inany State in a federul ceecion sin= e Federation. And<br />
I wan to thank my colleaguts from Queensland. Many of them arc heme today, and your<br />
efforts were not in " aim You have sent some very energtic, very artciodae, very<br />
vigorous and very plain speakng people from Qfeensand. Nothing shy about them in<br />
the party room I can assure you. They always tell you what you're not doing for<br />
Queenad. A eharactezistie to which I have becom accustomed over the years froln </p>
<p>Fax from 15/ 84/ 97 17: 28 Pg: 2<br />
people in the parliamentary parr and also in the oxganisation. But that is how it should<br />
be. Because Queensland is different, and Queensland bas particular characteristics.<br />
Queensland has a partirular con~ tribution to make to the future of our nation. And whilst<br />
and foremaost we are all united as Austrolians in the pursuit of common goals, as you<br />
go around our country you must accept and understand some of the regional variations<br />
and differencecs. And I understand the particular challenges, I know that the recestsion in<br />
some rects4 affectcd Queensland at a different time than it did the reat of Australia. I<br />
know the impact of the housing downturn on the Queensland economy of a few years<br />
ago. An I also know the importance of resolving the uncertainty surrounding Native<br />
Title, something to which I will come to in a moment.<br />
But! I thank your President for the comments that he made about some of the particular<br />
challenges facing the Government. It is true that small business in Australia has been.<br />
doing it very hard over the last few years. I am very conscious of that. Small business<br />
was badly mauled by the high interest rates of the recession. And small business paid<br />
very heavily far the stupid. intrusive industrial relations policies of the former<br />
government. And I'm delighted that we were able to get our industrial relations<br />
Legislation through. And in case somebody mnissed it, can. I remind you that in the small<br />
business package I announced a few weeks ago, we went even further than we had gone<br />
in the industrial relations bill in the area of unfair dismissals. And I said that the federal<br />
law would be amended so that any small business in Australia employing fewer than<br />
people, and under the existing law that is as far as we can go at the moment, would be<br />
free of any unfair dismissal restriction s of any kind in relation to any person employed for<br />
a lesser period than 12 months. In other words, any small firm under a federal award<br />
anywhere in Australia could take an employee on on 12 months probation, and if it<br />
doesn't work out that person, without any let ot hindrance could be let go. Now that<br />
particular reform, will be of enormous benefit to small business if it is extended not only<br />
to business operating under federal awards but also to businesses under State: awards.<br />
And I've already had a personal discussion with the Queensland Minister for Industrial<br />
Rebmtons, Santo Santoro, who is with us today and I know he shares my desire to extend<br />
that law to firms operating under Queensland law and I know that everybody in this room<br />
will encourage him to do so.<br />
I know tha there are some in the community who say that he should have gone further in<br />
some areas, and I know that there arm some in the community who have criticised the<br />
pace of reform. and change over the Lagt 12 months, arnd I want to say a few words about<br />
that. I've been in politics a very long time. I'm a realist. And I understand that the<br />
euphoria of a huge election victory has to be matched by performance. You can't live by<br />
rhetoric alone in politics, you've got to deliver. And I want to go back over the last 12<br />
months fbr a moment or two and remind you of what has been done in those ares where<br />
we've promised action. We did prondse ourselves and promise the Australian<br />
community that we would change our outdated industrial relatiorw legislation. Now we<br />
wcere't able to go quite as far as we wianted to go because we didn't have the numbers in<br />
the Senate. And it's an unfoitumate problem with our electoral system that because we<br />
have as a result of changes made in 1923, because we have a padamnr a Senote tam 2 </p>
<p>Fax from 15/ 04/ 97 17: 28 Pg: 3<br />
retires an even number of senators every three years, it's virtually mtathemnaficaly<br />
impoisible to get a majority in the Senac in a half Senate election. So we've had to rely<br />
on the support of minor parties and independents to get our legislation through. And as a<br />
result of the very skilful negotiations of Peter Reith we were able to get substantially all<br />
of our industrial relations legislation through. But it was six or nine months later thanz we<br />
would have liked and it is only now starting to come into operation. And it will be some<br />
time before the benefits of that arm really enjoyed and really understood and realised.<br />
And I ask people to accept and to understand that.<br />
We promised action in relation to small business and in trmsis of the actual commitments<br />
we made to small business it is fair to say that we have delivered beyond the<br />
comxniments we muade. I'm not saying that everybody is feeling the benefit. And I'm<br />
not saying that every small business in Australia has reason at the present time to think<br />
it's living in good conditions, because clearly it do=* nt. But lets take an area such as<br />
capital gains tax. We promised some rail over relief for capital gains. From the first of<br />
July any small business operator anywhere in Australia will be able to sell a small<br />
business and to invest the proceeds of that sale up to an amount of $ 5 Million in any<br />
busincss, not a business of a like kinid, in other words you can go from a newsagency into<br />
a computer software business, and you'll be able to invest up to $ 5 million without<br />
having any liability at all or capital gains tax Now that represents, ladies and gentlemen,<br />
that does represent us having taken that decision beyond what we promised at dhe time of<br />
the last election. We have also implemetnted most of the Bell Committee<br />
recommendations in relation to red tape. We have introduced remedial measures in<br />
relation to fringe benefits tax. If you have firinge benefits of less than $ 5,000 a year, then<br />
you are no longer required to keep records providing you keep paying the amount of<br />
fringe benefits tax levied on those finge benefits. We have also made some particular<br />
exemptions in relation to car parking and taxi travel. We have also simplified the<br />
procedures for small business dcaliag with governments. We implemented our<br />
commitruents irt relation to provisional tax relief. I mention these things ladies and<br />
gentlemr-n to remind you of what has been done, but also its a token of our continued<br />
determination to bring out and effect reforms that are important to small business.<br />
And we want to improve the climate for small busines for two reasons. Firs and<br />
foremost because it is the heart and soul of the Liberal ethic, indeed of the National Party<br />
ethic, to help and promote smoall business in the Australian community. SmaLl business is<br />
the engine room of economic growth. And as I travelled throughout China recently I was<br />
riot only reminded of the great opportunities that exist for large Australian companies in<br />
that huge nation, but I was also reminded of the opportunities for = mUl business. Azd the<br />
oppotnnities for niche exporters in Australia into the Asia-Pacific region are immne<br />
ond they are growing all t tizne. And the. communicatons revolution has empowered<br />
smallbusiness not only in Australia, but toughout the world, irna way that you wooldn't<br />
havw thought possible a few years ago. So we have a strong belie in the c= Wka<br />
imprtaceand role of small business iu our coimmity. We also have an unshakeable<br />
belief tha the only way in which we are going to achieve a lasting reduction in </p>
<p>Fax from 15/ 04/ 97 17: 28 Pg: 4<br />
unemployment, particularly amongst the young, is to get small business going far more<br />
actively and energetically thin it is at present.<br />
So I x-ould say ladies and gentlemen, yes I know that small business is stiU doing it<br />
tough. I know the burden small bu. siness carres. You will never hear pass my lips<br />
remarks such as " what = i you going on about? You've never had it so good". As was<br />
the siock response of my predecessor when small business men and women complained.<br />
I lmow you've had it Yough, I understand that. We have implemented our commitments.<br />
We continue to have our eyes fixed on fur-ther measures to help anid improve the climate<br />
for small business.<br />
And, Crs not only in thc economic area that we have delivered very strongly, we've also of<br />
course delivered very strongly in areas such as the environxnent. Fortunately we were<br />
able to scur the Senate's support for the one-third sale of Telsrra. I find it strange that<br />
peopic still criticise the fact that we worked with the independents to get the Teistra<br />
legislation through the Parliament. There was nothing dishonourable about that. We had<br />
actually told the Australian people before the election what we were doing in relation to<br />
Teistra. We had a mandate to sell one-third of Teistra. And we had a mandate to use a<br />
billon dollars of the proceeds of that sale to establish the Natural Heritage Trust And I<br />
find This suggestion in areas of the press and from our political opponents that in some<br />
way it was sort of wr-ong to actually deliver through the Parliament, with the support of<br />
tho numbers ia the Parliament what you actually promised the Australian people to do, a<br />
very curious piece of political analysis. And 1 Eun very proud of the fact tbat come the<br />
next clction I will be able to say on behalf of the Liberal and National Parties of<br />
Australia, that we have established the largest capital fund for investment in the<br />
environmental fututo of this country that any government has established since the end of<br />
World War 11. And I won't be reluctant to tell the Australian community at the time of<br />
the election that we established that fund for the benefit of the Australian envitrnent in<br />
the teeth of ferocious opposition from both the Australiani Labor P~ arty and the Australian<br />
Democrats. But it is true and it should never be forgott, that we did inherit a very large deficit, a<br />
very large budget deficit. On an underlying basis it was revealed a few months ago that<br />
the true deficit that we inherited was in the order of S10-l 11 billion.-Now people can say<br />
that incoming governments always say that they inherit deficits. Whether that is the case<br />
or noL, nothing can alter the fact that we did have that enormous fiscal challenge. And as<br />
a result of the decisions thad were takeen in the flrnt budget that Peter Costello brought<br />
down and delivered with such skil in Augus of last yeaw, we have broken the back of the<br />
fiscal challenge that we inherited in March of Last year. That doesn't mean that this<br />
yer'sudget is going tobe ey, oris going tobe slack. We stilhavea tough task<br />
ahead of But we broke the back of the fiscal challenge last year as a resul of the<br />
measu that we were able to take and as a direct consequence of that we created the<br />
climate for lower interst ratms </p>
<p>Fax from 15/ 64/ 97 17: 28 Pg:<br />
There have been imnprovements on the interest rate front. I know they haven't flowed<br />
through as well to the small business sector as they have in the housing sector and there's<br />
a very good reason for that. There's mome competition in the housing sector. And when<br />
the Wallis Committee report was released last week we made it very plain that we wanted<br />
more competition in the banking industry. And the thrust of that report is towards the<br />
thru~ st of the goverrnent policy is towards more compctition. And certainly both Peter<br />
andi I have rnedc it clear to the trading banks of Australia that we want to sce morc<br />
competition and a bente deal for the small businesses of Australia from the Australian<br />
banking system.<br />
I have said to many small business men and women, thae if you have the sort of<br />
conditions of competition in the small business lending area that organisations like<br />
Aussie Home Loans and RAM have provided for the banks in the housing area, you<br />
would have a cheaper flow of funds into the small business commaunity th= at the present<br />
trme. And I think it's very important that be said. So the fiscal challenge this year,<br />
although significant, will not be as great as it was last yewr. But providing a reduced<br />
budget deficit, continuing to provide fiscal consolidation, all of that buids international<br />
confidence in Australia. All of that builds the right climakte for lower inflation and lower<br />
interest rates. And ever one of you in business in this room know damn well that your<br />
best friends are really lower interest rates, stable economic conditions, and economic<br />
predictability. And the first responsibility of any government that really believes in the<br />
business community, really believes in the private sector, is to provide those conditions.<br />
In his remnarks thr. State President quite properly referred to the uncertainty over Native<br />
Title. Caa I say to you that that issue is of immense concern to me and to my<br />
Government. I have no problem with the coucept of Native Title. I had no particular<br />
problem with the decision of the High Court of Australia in the Mabo decision-I bad a<br />
lot of problems with the Native Title Act that was enacted by the Kceating Government<br />
with the support of the Australian Democrats and the Australian Greens.<br />
Arid for the sake of the record may I remind you that in 1993 the Liberal and National<br />
parties voted against the present Nrauive Title Act, so when quite correctly you rail against<br />
the failure of the Native Title Act to give certainty. when you throw up your hands in<br />
despair about the disgraceful saga of Century Zinc, which has taken an inordinaiely long<br />
time-, when many of you would have read with dismay the letter written by the former<br />
Governor General and a former leader of the Australian Labor Party Mr Hayden, to the<br />
Queensland Prcmier, you will wionder why it was tWa an Austwaian Parliament should<br />
ever have enacted such a confused law, I ask you to remember that th~ e wasn't one<br />
person in the Libera and National party who voted for the law in that form. Now, I want<br />
to make tha clear bcause occasionally in the heat of thes orts of debates it is forgotten,<br />
that the law in its present form, was something that we Mnherted anid it was acted in the<br />
face of our fierce criticism and opposition not to the principle of Native Title butt to the<br />
way in which the Keating Goverment implementd tha pmniple and the way in which<br />
the Keating Govenrnmnt gave to Native Title holders rights of veto which are not<br />
available to title holders of any other description under the land law of Australia. </p>
<p>Fax from 15/ 04/ 97 17: 28 Pg: 6<br />
That is why in the lead up to the lat election I said that we were going to make changes<br />
to the Notive Title Act. Now, I operated as most people in Australia did in the belief that<br />
the grat of a valid pastoral Icase would extinguish Native Title, because That was<br />
contained in the recitals to the Nattve Title Ac: t. It was contained in the former Prime<br />
Mini'sters second reading speech, it was acknowledged by leaders of the Aboriginal<br />
coinmuniry and it was acknowledged by leadens of other organisations, and I have to say<br />
iliaE it vas quite surprising to me that the High Court in the Wik Case found otherwvise.<br />
And on that point can I say very simply that there see= s to be a very confuised view in the<br />
Australian commuunity at the present time in the minds of some about the respectivc role<br />
of the judiciary and the role of the legislature and the executive. I am a staunch believer<br />
in the separation of powers. I believe in the rule of law, and as a citizen of Australia I am<br />
as subject to that rule of law as any other man or worman. 1 believe in judicial<br />
indiependence. I believe in the security of tenure of judges appointed to courts within<br />
Australia, and I accept that it is the role and the right of the judges of Australia to<br />
interpret the law of Australia as it presently stands. But I equally assert the undoubted,<br />
unqualified, unatrbiguous rights of the Parliaments of Australia to alter the law of<br />
Australia if they think that is in the national interest.<br />
I mention, that ladies and gentlemenc because of same strange interpretations that have<br />
been placed by sections of the media on the declaration made by the judges yesterday.<br />
There has never been anything wrong in any citizen of Australia inl disagreeing with or<br />
criticising a judgment of a court. That has happened for time immemorial, it has always<br />
happened under the anglo-Aiustralian legal system and it always ought to happen. But<br />
wbAt is wrong of course if far parliament or the executive to try and influence particular<br />
decisions or to unreasonably or improperly attack the integrity of judges or the<br />
applicarion of those judges to the task before them arnd there's certainly been no<br />
suggestion by my Government and there never will be that any such criticism is<br />
warranted. I respect the separation of powers but I will always assert the role and the<br />
right of both the executive and the legislature.<br />
But that my friends is a bit of a diversion, but a n~ ecesary one from what I was saying<br />
about Wik. I know it is a difficult issue and when the decision was brought down in<br />
December of this year, I studied it like everybody else and I convened a meeting of all the<br />
Premiers of Australia, including my friend arid colleague Rob Borbidge, the Premier of<br />
Queensland. and I said to the Preiierg that I had two goals that I would work towards<br />
achieving them I hoped by the common agreement of all parties anid those two goals<br />
ware to respec the concept of Native Title but to deliver to the pastoralists of Australia<br />
and the atining industry of Australia, a degre of predictability iod certinty to which I<br />
believe thy are entlid And they remain my goals and I am workting very hard to<br />
achieve them. My patience is not endless, it is nor inexhustble. I bowe spent a lot of<br />
time already in discussions with the various patties and I am talking to my Cabinet<br />
colleapme about the issu at tis very moment as we meet here in Queensland. I will go </p>
<p>Fax fromv 15/ 04/ 97 17: 28 Pg: 7<br />
on trying to find common ground if that is possible, but if at the enid of the day it is not<br />
possible, then we w. ill decide on a particular covaxse of action.<br />
Buat I want to make it very clear to the farmers of Austalia as f've said in the past, I won't<br />
let you down. I've made it very clear ini the past that I respect the contribution of the<br />
farners a-ad the pastoraists of ths country. I know the diffcult timnes that They have been<br />
through. I know the burden, they've had to catty, I know the contribution that they make<br />
to the grogt export earnings of this nation of ours and I can certainly assure them that I am<br />
not going to sell them short, I'm not going to sell them out, I'm not going to let them<br />
down. And I know that they and you would hope that if it is possible to find a common<br />
ground. if it is possible to find an accommodation of all parties behind a practical<br />
response to the this challenge, this unexpected challenge thrown up by a decision which I<br />
didn't expect anid I don't think anyone else expected then I think all of you would agree<br />
that it is my responsibility as Prime Minister, my responsibility in relation to all of the<br />
Australian people to go that extra yard in order to try and see if we can reach that<br />
commhlon grounld. I don't think it is going to be very easy. I have no false illusions but it<br />
is my responsibility to all of the Australian people to cndeavour to do that.<br />
Can I just say one other thing ladies and gentlemen, and that is that one of the many<br />
things tha I committed myself to when I became Prime Minister in March of last year<br />
was to remadn in touch with the Australian people, to not imnagine that I had been elected<br />
Prime Minister because of some sort of inspired belief on behalf of the mnajory of the<br />
Australian people that uniquely I had all of the answers and that nobody else had a<br />
legitimate alterative point of view. And what I've tried to do over the iast year is to<br />
remain in touch with the Australian people is to listen to them and in particular I've tred<br />
very hard to keep in touch with the business commnunity of Austraiai<br />
The Liberal Party is an independent party, the National Party is an independent party-<br />
Neither of the Coalition parties is owned by any section of the Australian community.<br />
The Labor Party is owned by the trade union movement and the politicaly correct<br />
chattering classes. I don't know who owns the Austaliian Democrats but I can assure you<br />
that we are not owned by anybody. We might have close links with the business<br />
community but from time to time we do things that some people in the business<br />
community don't like. I know that. I mean, I think there may be one or two people in<br />
this room who've been mildly critical of the decision we took in the budget last year<br />
about the superannuation surcharge. N'ow, I'm sorry about that but I think it is better for<br />
me o mention it and it is better for me to acknowledge the fact that I am aware: char you<br />
are unhappy about it and to epan briefly why we did it then to sort of pretend that I amn<br />
not aware that you arc aware that you arm unhappy with it, and that is why I've raised it.<br />
Now we brought dow a budget las yea that got nine-and-a-half out of ten in the<br />
Australian commuznity for fairnes anid balance ad one of the number of reasons why it<br />
got nine-and-a-half out of ten in the community for fairmes and balm=~ was that they<br />
thought we had invited all sections of the Australian commnunity to make a bit of a<br />
conribution to eclving the problem and I'd like you to see that particula decision in that </p>
<p>Fax from15/ 04/ 97 17: 28 Pg: 8<br />
context. I'd like you to see it as not a decision that we enjoyed taking but a decision we<br />
believ-. d ought to have been taken in the interests of balance and fairness, and I've had a<br />
lot of criticism of it and nonie of that criticism Wny~ e t indicated to me a superior way of<br />
irnplernenting the decision without having some deleterious impact an the revenue that is<br />
to be gathered from that particular decision.<br />
I wanted to mention that because I know there's been some criticism and because I<br />
waned you to 1now tha I'm a person who listens to and recives and is willing to<br />
respond to criticism and I wanted you to understand the context of fairness in which that<br />
particul1ar decision was taken in which I would like it to be judged. But I have<br />
enaeavourcd, and all of my colleagues have enideavoured to keep contiact -with the<br />
business community, rnot because of any sense of direct obligation but because our goals<br />
are essentially your goals, despite the fact that we are a free standing independent<br />
political movement reprumenting all Australians, we are at heat people who believe in the<br />
private enterprise system.<br />
We do believe in a smaller Governmtent sector, we believe in a strong Government sector,<br />
doing the things Governments ought to do like having a more efficient defence force and<br />
having a defence force that spends more money on training and weaponry and getting<br />
ready in case they arc needed than on bureaucrats in Canberra. We are a Goverrnent that<br />
believes strongly in small business, we are a Government that believes very strongly in<br />
private effort and of course very passionately in the rights of private property ownership<br />
for all Ausiralians irrespective of their position in life. So I have tried over the tast year<br />
to retain thud contact with the business community of AustzmIa and particularly of course<br />
with the business community here in Brisbane and I want to say thW the links through the<br />
Party organisation are very important. I think we have made a good start I think in<br />
many areas we have delivered beyond what we said. I know in some areas people might<br />
have wanted us to have gone further and a bit faster. Can I assure you that none of us has<br />
lost the zeal or the commitment or the enthusiasmn for further reformis. I thinok good<br />
Governent is about providing a sense of reassurance; a sanme of purpose. a sense of<br />
hope; from time to time providing a few surprises, surprises of the pleasant variety rather<br />
than the unpleasant variety and all the time remindig itself that its obligation is not to<br />
govern for the self interest of individual members of Parliament but to govern for the<br />
greater good for the Australian comnity.<br />
We had a slogan at the last electon called ' For all of Us' and I have endeavoured to<br />
govern for all of us. We are a group of men and women who worry very much about tU<br />
views of mainstrem Australia. We don't believ that Govarments' sbould ignore<br />
minorities but we strongly believe that Governments. shouldn't be driven by minorities<br />
and it has been very much our conc= r and our goal to govern fbi the minstreamn of te<br />
Australian cornmunity.<br />
I want to say thak you to 0l of you for the support that you have given to the Pmry<br />
particularly during its difficult yewr out of office both federally and Stae. The fiends<br />
you have when you ame out of office are the tru friencs. I want to dvink you fo~ r the </p>
<p>FaxF an15/ 04/ 97 17: 28 Pg: 9<br />
support that you've continued to give us, your support for bring here today and the role<br />
all of you played in the magnificent Coalition win in March of last year here in<br />
Queensland, and finally I want to say to you that I'll keep faith, I'll keep couch. I'll listen,<br />
I'll respond to criticism, I1T occasionally disagree with you as you will with me,. but you<br />
will always know tha fundamentally the goals and aspirations you have about your<br />
businesses and about your families and about the filare of your STat and the future of<br />
our nation are goals that we overwhelmingly share very much in common with you.<br />
Thank you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
