<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6237</transcript-id>
    <title>COUNTRY WATER SUPPLIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/10/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006237.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
R A N 9 N B : i6AR<br />
FOR MEDIA 10 ' October 1983<br />
COUNTRY WATP. SUPPLIES<br />
The Queensland Government is holding up urgently needed<br />
jobs improving water supplies in country towns.<br />
Federal Government funds are lying idle, while the StLre<br />
Government dithers on how it should be spent.<br />
The money is Queensland's shar-of a special allocation<br />
under the Community Employment Program designed to improve<br />
the quality and reliability of country water supplies.<br />
The money has been available for weeks, but the Queensland<br />
Government will not even beain to consider how it should<br />
be spent until almost a month after the State election.<br />
The availability of Commonwealth money for country town<br />
water supplies was first announced by the Treasurer in<br />
his 19 May Economic Statement. The Queensland Government<br />
has had plenty of tire to consider the matter.<br />
The Fea ral Government is. very concious<br />
of the inadequacies ot water supplies to some country<br />
towns in the Far North and North West of Queensland<br />
A number of councils have made applications for funding<br />
under the special water projects scheme to be funded<br />
under the Community Employment Progran.<br />
I am confident that there will be good news for somc<br />
of the local applicants, but until the State Government<br />
is prepared to honour its part of the bargain, these<br />
urgently needed projects cannot proceed.<br />
MT ISA<br />
October 1983<br />
I </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
