<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9137</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP SYLVIA SMITHS ELECTORATE OFFICE - LAUNCESTON, TASMANIA SATURDAY 26 FEBRUARY, 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/02/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009137.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF ADDRESS BY THE PRLIE MINISTER, THE HON P J<br />
KEATING, M. P.<br />
SYLVIA SMITH'S ELECTORATE OFFICE LAUNCESTON, TASMANIA<br />
SATURDAY 26 FEBRUARY, 1994<br />
It is a great pleasure to be here with Sylvia ( Smith) to open this, her electorate office,<br />
in the city of Launceston because it was on that night, just slightly less than a year ago,<br />
that we saw Tasmania lead the return of a Labor government. And, when I saw the<br />
numbers in the Tasmanian seats, given the fact that we had a substantial lead anyway, I<br />
knew then we were always going to be unbeatable. As it turned out, that's as it turned<br />
out to be. But, the truth is that we now want to earn that faith and trust which you put<br />
in Sylvia and the government, through the course of this parliament, to see again the<br />
great things that Labor can do for Australia, and to see return to the fold all of the<br />
Tasmanian seats at the next election.<br />
Tasmania, of course, is playing its part in the recovery which we are now seeing in the<br />
Australian economy. We are now growing faster than any other comparable economy<br />
and we'll be doing well growing around four percent into next year. And, I'm very<br />
pleased to see Tasmania taking a part in this, sharing in this, in fact in some places,<br />
leading it. And, today, just coming from Hobart, as I did, through Richmond and then<br />
Ross, up to Evandale, seeing the tourist industry of Tasmania obviously playing a role<br />
selling Tasmania's heritage as it does because the preservation of this wonderful city<br />
and the places I mentioned is, I think, second to none in Australia. But, what also<br />
pleased me this morning, I went through a fish export factory and, not so many months<br />
ago, one at Ulverstone exporting potato chips. And, when you look at the amount of<br />
industry and innovation which is taking place with Tasmanian companies picking up<br />
the competitiveness which this government has now induced in Australia... we're<br />
seeing Tasmania not just hanging behind the recovery but being ight in there with it.<br />
And that will mean, as we're already seeing, employment start to pick up and we're<br />
starting to see, I think, 145,000 job growth over the course of the last six months or<br />
so, so we're well on the way to the half million jobs in three years having kept the<br />
nearly two million of extra jobs which were created in the 1980s. So, we've had the<br />
recession, we're out of it, we're on our way again and weve kept the great social<br />
programs of the Labor party intact while we've been doing it. That is, Medicare and<br />
thie ed ucation ' sy stem -and support for aged people and for young people and for<br />
families we've been able to hold that together, now, as we contemplate the nineties.<br />
And the nineties hold such bounty for Australia, now, as a low inflation country locked<br />
into the. Asia-Pacific, -able to export our products and, in fhatjor the first time in our </p>
<p>history being closer to fast growing world markets where, for most of our history, we<br />
were a long way from the markets of Europe and North America. So, now we are<br />
part of the fastest growing part of the world and we're right in there with it.<br />
Now, of course, that couldn't be done, we couldn't realise the great ambitions we'ye<br />
had through the eighties in setting Australia up as a modem society and economy,<br />
without getting this period of office, this term of office, to give us a chance to ride the<br />
growth cycle through the 1990s. And, you've helped give us this term of office by<br />
sending Sylvia to Canberra as Member for Bass. Now, Sylvia said she is a woman of<br />
the people. She gets around and she knows the electorate and she knows the<br />
community. And this is what the Labor party always has, it has touch with the<br />
community because it is from the community. And, that is why it has taken a Labor<br />
government to give Australia a market economy, it's taken a Labor government to<br />
enlarge the country and give it a greater future, it's taken a Labor government to see<br />
the great opportunities in Asia and, at the same time, see our whole society grow<br />
along... so that this recovery is not just for stockbrokers or people at the top end of<br />
town, this recovery is a recovery for everybody and that includes the unemployed and<br />
the long term unemployed and all Australians who ought to be able to participate in it.<br />
Now, I said at the election, on election night, that we were not going to forget the<br />
unemployed. That we were going to reach out our arms and bring them up with us so<br />
we could go on to growth and prosperity in the 1990s. And, in this half year coming<br />
up towards this Budget, I'll be introducing a statement dealing with the problems of<br />
the long term unemployed and long term unemployment. And, let's, us, do something<br />
new in the world7-fist in the world, again to say that in our society, in our<br />
compassionate society, we will not leave three or four hundred thousand Australians<br />
long term unemployed. That the rest of us won't move on and forget them, that we'll<br />
go along as a society together. Because, only in that way will we keep this a nice<br />
country which has got good values where we care about one another and where we<br />
say, when we move along we all go along, not just those who are well off.<br />
So, these are the great things we're fighting for, these are the great things we've been<br />
elected for. And, we've now got a healthy, strong parliamentary majority and, for the<br />
first time in a long time, the state of Tasmania playing a real role through the Labor<br />
members in the Federal government of Australia. Now, it was 20 years ago when it<br />
was thus, last like this. But, now Tasmania has rejoined the fold and as a consequence<br />
Tasmania is getting the lift from the policies of the national government. And this has<br />
got to help in general prosperity, in employment in this beautiful state. So, ladies and<br />
gentlemen, Sylvia has already distinguished herself in the time she has been in the<br />
parliamentary Labor party, she is a person of the people, she has that common touch,<br />
she cares. And that input to the policies of the government, to the business of the<br />
caucus of the party, is what makes all the difference in whether you've got a real<br />
political party in office or just a business organisation which the Liberal Party is and<br />
always has been a sort of semi-business organisation. Not a feeling, growing,<br />
organic political organisation with touch to the community of this country.<br />
So, I had a lot of pride on election night, none more so than seeing Tasmania return a<br />
swag of Labor members. And, amongst them, Sylvia, whom I share this platform with<br />
today with very great pride. So, could I thank each and every one of you for coming </p>
<p>3<br />
along, for supporting her, for believing in her, for having faith in the government and<br />
faith in the great ideals of the Labor party. And let's hope, from the portals of this<br />
office, that the great humanitarian policies of the party and its great sense of<br />
enlargement can be accomplished here in Launceston. It gives me very great pleasure<br />
to declare Sylvia's electorate office open.<br />
Ends. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
