<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2026</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS:PRIME MINISTER&#039;S MESSAGES ON THE DEATH OF GERNERAL EISENHOWER</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/03/1969</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002026.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS PM. No. 33/ 1969<br />
PRIME MINISTER'S MESSAGLES ON THE DEATH OF<br />
GENERAL EISENHOWER,<br />
The Prime Minister, N'fr ( aorton, this morning sent<br />
the following messages-<br />
To Mrs Eisenhower " WE DEEPLY REGRET AND HAVE BEEN SADDENED<br />
BY THE NEWS OF YOUR HUSBAND'S DEATH. GENERAL<br />
EISENHOWER IN HIS LIFETIME RECEIVED THE RESPECT<br />
AND ADMIRATION OF ALL AUSTRALIANS, AS THE WAR-TIME<br />
LEADER OF OUR ALLIED FORCES AND, LATER, AS THE<br />
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES. HIS, GREAT<br />
ACHIEVEMENTS AND HIS DEDICATED SERVICE TO HIS<br />
COUNTRYMEN AND TO THE WORLD ARE MARKED IN OUR<br />
HISTORY AND WILL REMAIN LONG IN OUR MEMORY.<br />
ON BEHALF OF THE AUSTRALIAN * GOVERNMENT<br />
AND THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE, I EXTEND TO YOU AND<br />
YOUR FAMILY OUR DEEP SYMT\ PATHY.<br />
To President Nixon "? TODAY ALL AUSTRALiANS ARE SHARING WITH<br />
YOU AND WITH THE AMERICAN PEOPLE A DEEP SENSE OF<br />
GRIEF AT THE DEATH OF GENERAL EISENHOWER,<br />
WE MOURN HIM AS A LEADER OF MEN WHO<br />
SERVED HIS COUNTRY AS PRESIDENT WITH DEVOTION AND<br />
HONOUR. WE MOURN HIM AS A LEADER IN THE FIGHT FOR<br />
THE FREEDOM OF NATIONS. HE LED THE CRUSADE IN<br />
EUROPE AND BORE THE AWESOME BURDEN OF SUPREME<br />
COMMANDER IN WORLD WAR HI WITH COURAGE, SKILL AND<br />
THE HIGHEST QUALITIES OF LEADERSHIP. HE ACCOMPLISHED<br />
A GREAT VICTORY FOR THE FORCES OF ENLIGHTENMENT AND<br />
HUMAN DIGNITY IN THE WORLD.<br />
HE RESPONDED TO HIS COUNTRY'S SUMMONS TO<br />
THE HIGHEST OFFICE IN THE LAND WHE? 4 OTHER MEN MIGHT<br />
HAVE SAID ' I HAVE DONE ENOUGH'. AND AS PRESIDENT OF<br />
THE UNITED STATES, HE LED THE MOST POWERFUL OF THE<br />
FREE PEOPLES OF THE WORLD AT A CRUCIAL TIME IN WORLD<br />
HISTORY. AFTERWARDS HE CONTINUED TO DEVOTE HIS<br />
GREAT HUMAN RESOURCES TO THE ISSUES OF HIS TIME.<br />
AUSTRALIANS, AS DO PEOPLE THROUGHOUT THE<br />
WORLD, SALUTE HIS ACHIEVEMENTS AND MOURN HIS PASSING." i<br />
CANBERRA, March 1969 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
