<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1666</transcript-id>
    <title>HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES INCOME TAX (PARTNERSHIPS AND TRUSTS) BILL 1967 - NOTES FOR THE MINISTER&#039;S SECOND READING SPEECH</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/09/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001666.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
HOUSE OF -RE'LRESE-1ITAT IVES<br />
INCOL-2 TAX (] PRTMERSHIPS AND TRUSTS) BILL1 1967<br />
NOTES FOR THE MINISTER'S -SECO17D READING SPEECH.<br />
This Bill will declare the rates of income tax for the<br />
financial year 1967-68 on income of certain superannuation funds,<br />
trust estates and members of partnerships.<br />
These are special rates which have been declared in<br />
relation to the 1965-66 and 1966-67 financial years. Yo change is<br />
proposed for the current financial year. Honourable members will,<br />
no doubt, recall that the special rates are imposed for the purposes<br />
of legislation which, following the Government's consideration of the<br />
report of the Ligertwood Committee on Taxation, was enacted in 1964<br />
with a view to placing a curb~ on tax avoidance practices to which<br />
the Committee drew attention.<br />
A rate of 50 per cent is declared by the Bill for income<br />
of a trust estate, other than a deceased estate, to which no<br />
beneficiary is presently entitled and. which is not taxed as if it<br />
were the income of one individual.<br />
A rate of 50 per cent is also declared for the taxable<br />
income of a superannuation fund that is not exempt from tax. This<br />
rate does not, however, apply to the investment income of a fund that<br />
is subject to tax only because of the fund's failure to comply with<br />
the " 130/ 20" 1 rule concerning investments in public securities. The<br />
rates on this income are proposed by the Income Tax Bill 1967 and also<br />
remain unchanryed from th1ose that applied last year.<br />
As to income from a share in a partnership over which a<br />
person lacks, or is deemed to lack, real and effective control and<br />
disposal, the Bill will impose a rate of further tax sufficient to<br />
bring the aggregate rate on the income up) to 50 per cent. If a<br />
taxpayer's avera-, e personal rate of tax is 50 p~ er cent or more, no<br />
further tax is imposed under this Bill.<br />
I commend the Bill to the House. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
