<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>107</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, RT. HON. R G MENZIES, IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES, 24TH SEPTEMBER 1959</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/09/1959</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000107.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, RT. HON. fl. G. MENZIES,<br />
IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES, 24TH SEPT., 19 ' 9<br />
Mr Chairman I just want to intervene very briefly to<br />
say something on behalf of the Government in this matter. The<br />
honourable member for Scullin ( Mr. Peters) appears to be under<br />
the impression that the point that has just been under discussion<br />
has never been considered. I can assure him that he is<br />
wrong. Very many aspects of this law have engaged very close<br />
attention, But I think it is necessary to point out that when<br />
a Government produces a budget, it does not consider social services<br />
alone; it considers the whole range of financial and economic<br />
activities in the country, and it has to arrive at a<br />
balanced conclusion as to the terms of a budget which it thinks<br />
will be best for the country. In doing that, it cannot concentrate<br />
on one matter to the exclusion of others. It does something<br />
useful, as it hopes, in relation to each m--atter and on<br />
this occasion, we have done something useful as I believe, and<br />
as I think most people believe, in relation o the rate of pension.<br />
In previous years, we have made changes in the means<br />
test and we have dealt with other aspects of the social services<br />
law. I know, Sir nobody knows better that there are<br />
great differences dm..' pinion around the cham--ber on the matter<br />
of the m--eans test. The property means test has been very much<br />
discussed of late. The honourable member for Port Adelaide ( Mr.<br />
Thom.-pson) has given notice of an armendmaent in relation to it.<br />
Another amendm-ent is down in the name of the honourable memlber<br />
for Mackellar ( Mr. 1; entworth). I am very well aware of these<br />
differences of opinion. Somie of miy own friends have very<br />
strong views on them.<br />
Aill I want to say, Sir, is that we gave considerable<br />
thought to these matters as part of the general Budget preparation.<br />
The Budget has been presented; this is one of the<br />
Budget measures, and, naturally the Government stands by it. A<br />
vote against it is a vote against the existence of the Government.<br />
That is elementary in parliamentary practice.<br />
Mr Curtin: Look at the sour faces on Government supporters now.<br />
I thought that some of the new boys opposite might not<br />
know that. That, of course, is an elementary observation, Sir.<br />
I apologize for having felt obliged to state it. But I want to<br />
say this: Although the Government has not felt able to deal<br />
with the means test, or, in'particular, the property means test,<br />
in the Budget and in this measure, that does not mean that we<br />
regard the problem as closed or as finally disposed of. On the<br />
contrary, there are still many problems to be worked out, and<br />
this, no doubt, is one of the most contentious of them.<br />
I have, some timae since, agreed with m y colleagues in<br />
the Cabinet that it is not always satisfactory to deal with the<br />
intricacies of the social services structure at the time when<br />
you are considering the broad sweep of Budg et preparation, and<br />
I therefore propose to have this problem, and those problems allied<br />
to it, very carefully examined by the Government well before<br />
the preparation of the next Budg et. I say that because I<br />
know that the problem is difficult, and I believe that it requires<br />
concentrated attention and a Egood deal of close study.<br />
I want to muake it quite N~ lear, Sir, that when I say<br />
that, I am making no commitment. Ido not undertake to say<br />
what the result will be.<br />
Mr Reynolds: Two bob each way.<br />
Of course, if I undpp'. took to say what the result would<br />
be, it would be mere humabug to engage in the investigation; and<br />
I do not propose to engage in humbug at this late stage of my<br />
political life. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
