<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4691</transcript-id>
    <title>INTERVIEW WITH LAURIE WILSON, CHANNEL 7, 21 APRIL 1978</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/04/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004691.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS OFFICE TRANSCRIPT Embargo 6pm EST XS<br />
Interview with Laurie Wilson, Channel 7<br />
21 April 1978<br />
QUESTION: Prime Minister, the talks with Mr Ushibo. this<br />
morning were in fact unscheduled. That seems to indicate<br />
that they have some significance, the fact that they were<br />
called at the last minute.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well I think they're significant, beca use<br />
they flowed naturally out of the discussions that began<br />
yesterday with the Prime Minister. They're designed to<br />
probe in depth the trade negotiations taking course throughout<br />
this year. Australia I think has had a degree of<br />
scepticism about the total result, because on all previous<br />
occasions when there have been international trade negotiations,<br />
the major industrial countries have made arrangements to use<br />
tariffs on industr * ial goods, but then they have said " Oh well,<br />
agriculture was too hard, commodities are too hard, we won't<br />
do anything about that". And as a result, over the last<br />
decades there has been a general freeing of trade in industrial<br />
goods, but certainly no freeing of trade in agriculture. And<br />
the importance of that for many countries can be seen from<br />
the face that the negotiations on industrial goods will<br />
cover say 40% of Japan, North America and Europe's exports<br />
but only 5% of Australia' s exports. There have been many<br />
other countries in Australia's position, most of them<br />
developing countries.<br />
QUESTION: In terms of your talks with Mr Ushiba, just what<br />
are you after then?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well, what we really want is to make sur7e<br />
that in the international trade negotiations, a,-riculture<br />
is included as well as industrial g-oods. The United States<br />
says that agriculture -will be included, Japan says that<br />
agriculture will ~ e included, but it's not going to be any<br />
good waking't up at the end of the day and finding that<br />
agriculture is once again excluded as has occurred in the<br />
past. And there Is another reason why agriculture needs to<br />
be included, bocause the industrial side of these inte-rnational<br />
trade negotioitions are operating on something less than<br />
of world trade. You have to exclude traele inside the European<br />
community, because thot's already free. And if you exclude<br />
commodities and agriculture you find that the proposals on<br />
industrial trade, reductions in ' ariffs in that area, operate<br />
on less than 20% of wonrld trade, and I don't believe that<br />
anyone can really see that the proposals, which co uld involve<br />
about a half percent tariff reduction a year over 8 years,<br />
but not starting till 1980, are doing all that much to achieve<br />
an expansion of markets wh~ ich is necessary if wre tire to get<br />
t. reater ; roductive use of our resources, 6Lnd therefore a<br />
lessening of emplo,,. zent, not just in Australia~ but in all<br />
countries. QiUESTION: Is this the most significant aspect of the visit? ./ 2 </p>
<p>PRIME iIINISTER: I think it' a very significant aspect of what's<br />
happening throughout the course of this year, and I think it is an<br />
importqnt part of our discussions. We'll also be talking later<br />
today a. out the North/ South dialogue, and the need to make sure<br />
that the developing countries are not excluded from any benefits<br />
under the International trade negotiations. There must be movement<br />
in the Common Fund.<br />
QUESTION: Mr Ushiba is quoted as having said that the reason you<br />
were coming up here was because it was the normal sort of<br />
consultation which took place between the two countries prior to<br />
the major economic summit to be held later this year. You<br />
obviously see it as something different from that.<br />
PRIME MINISTER I had rather though that these talks were<br />
different from talks that have taken place between Japan and<br />
Australia in the past. They're not talks about bilateral<br />
issues, and that's been made plain and I think it's now accepted<br />
They are talks about what's happening in the intornational<br />
environment, and it's natural that we should want to talk to<br />
Japan about these matters because we're vastly affected as a<br />
significant trading nation, Japan as a significant trading<br />
nation. We're affected by Japan's access to markets overseas<br />
just as we're affected by our own access. Therefore I think<br />
it's natural to talk with Japan about these particular matters<br />
as we approach the more formal trade negotiations.<br />
QUIESTION: Are you yourself going to be going to Jamaica, and<br />
what is the significance of the jamaica conference following<br />
the talks in Japan?<br />
PIMI. MINISTER: Providing the Jamaica talks go ahead as we've<br />
been told and as scheduled, I i. 11 be attending, yes, because<br />
again I think this is maybe one of the very few forums, maybe<br />
the only forum in which a group cf developed and developing<br />
countries, Heads of Government, getting together in a completely<br />
unstructured way. There is the Commonwealth, of course, but<br />
I'm not taking that into accountat the moment. I believe that<br />
if we are to get the sort of results out of the more formal<br />
international negotiations taking place throughout this year<br />
there has got to be a new commitment, a new dedication on the<br />
part of nations, and my understanding is that the Jamaica<br />
meeting has been called largely because of the same kinds of<br />
concerns that Australia has expressed, and largely because<br />
Prime Minister Manley wants to re-energise the international<br />
trade negotiations so that hopefully they can really be successful. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
