<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8434</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP TOYOTA PLANT, ALTONA MELBOURNE, 4 MARCH 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/03/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008434.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
TOYOTA PLANT, ALTONA MELBOURNE, 4 MARCH 1992<br />
1<br />
Mr Toyoda, Premier Kirner, Mr Yamaguchi, Mr Johnston,<br />
distinguished guests, ladies and gentlemen.<br />
This is a great day for our motor vehicle industry. It is<br />
also a great day for Australian industry.<br />
The people gathered here are representative of the new<br />
direction in Australia progress in partnerships.<br />
Increasingly in Australia we are recognising that there<br />
is strength in partnerships between government and<br />
business, business and unions. Between Commonwealth and<br />
State governments.<br />
We are recognising how much there is to be gained from<br />
being a nation with unity of purpose.<br />
It is for the same reason that we seek partnerships with<br />
business in other countries, particularly in countries in<br />
our region.<br />
We seek them because we know that is where our future<br />
strength substantially lies in integration with global<br />
markets, and integration especially with Asia and the<br />
Pacific. Japan, of course, is one of our great partners and<br />
there is no better example of the partnership than that<br />
with Toyota.<br />
Toyota came to Australia thirty years ago. It was a very<br />
different place. We were more insular, dare I say more<br />
British, in those days?<br />
Certainly there was a great deal more apprehension about<br />
the region in which we lived, and a failure to comprehend<br />
the change that was about to occur there.<br />
Given the speed and the dimensions of that change, it's a<br />
failure we might be forgiven but when we failed in that<br />
we also failed to understand much of our future reality. </p>
<p>-2<br />
Last year Toyota sold more cars than anyone else in<br />
Australia. Today the one millionth Toyota will be driven off the<br />
assembly line.<br />
On a day like this there are a great many things which<br />
could be said in praise of the Toyota company.<br />
Not only in regard to its world leadership in the motor<br />
industry and the role of Dr Toyoda, but its faith in this<br />
country and its people.<br />
It is the commitment to quality which has made Toyota the<br />
number one car manufacturer in Australia in 1991.<br />
But, given Toyota's legendary determination to look to<br />
the future, it is more appropriate to talk about this new<br />
plant this: new investment in the Australian motor<br />
vehicle industry.<br />
Toyota's decision to build this new plant is a very<br />
welcome show of confidence.<br />
It is a major turning point in our manufacturing<br />
industry. It's no less significant for the car industry<br />
than the decision of General Motors to build Holdens in<br />
Australia in. the 1940s.<br />
For with this new plant Australia will enter world<br />
markets with a world product for the first time.<br />
It's worth remembering that this was the first country<br />
outside Japan in which Japanese companies established<br />
vehicle manufacturing facilities.<br />
It is pleasing to have Toyota say again loudly this is<br />
a good place to manufacture.<br />
We are delighted to have Toyota demonstrate that they<br />
share our belief in the industry's ability to be<br />
competitive in the world.<br />
It demonstrates that our intention to cut tariff rates to<br />
and end quotas has not only not meant the end of<br />
investment, but ' a renewal of it.<br />
Indeed, a new car industry is being built.<br />
Above all, this new plant is proof that Australia can do<br />
what it hiust do build an internationally competitive<br />
manufacturing industry.<br />
And to do that we must do a great deal more of what has<br />
been done here.<br />
The creative workplace agreement between Toyota and 6000<br />
employees reached here last December sets a new benchmark<br />
for industrial relations in this country. </p>
<p>-3<br />
All concerned will benefit and that means all<br />
Australians. It's the kind of workplace agreement which will<br />
increasingly characterise business in Australia.<br />
Mr Toyada, ladies and gentlemen, you may take this<br />
ceremony today as signalling the emergence of a much<br />
stronger Australia in the 1990s.<br />
Stronger through partnerships like this through<br />
creative workplace environments such as this one will be.<br />
Stronger through greater incentives for business to<br />
invest in worthwhile long term projects. With low<br />
interest rates, low inflation and low cost of labour<br />
giving us a cost of capital regime at least competitive<br />
with other countries.<br />
You will see us stronger through a vastly improved<br />
infrastructure. Through more efficient ports, new and<br />
better roads and, at last, a highly efficient,<br />
competitive rcail system. Through cheaper electricity<br />
under the National Grid Corporation.<br />
Above all you will see a stronger Australia emerging from<br />
a clearer sense of direction, a robust and mature<br />
national identity.<br />
I believe you will see that manifest in countless ways:<br />
from the new commitment, creativity and purpose of<br />
Australian workers to the willingness and determination<br />
of government to venture forth and strike new<br />
partnerships in the world and in our region.<br />
You are going to see in future an Australia of much more<br />
independent mind and of wholehearted belief in the<br />
future.<br />
We Australians may take great heart from this ceremony<br />
today. It is a landmark in our history a very<br />
significant step forward.<br />
In this context I want to take the opportunity to<br />
congratulate my colleague and friend, the Minister for<br />
Industry, technology and Commerce, Senator Button, who<br />
has done more for Australian industry than perhaps any<br />
other politician'this century and who will be regarded as<br />
one of this country's greatest reformers. This ceremony<br />
today might well'be seen as being in part a tribute to<br />
his efforts.<br />
It remains for me to congratulate the Toyota Company, the<br />
unions and workers, and everyone else associated with the<br />
project. I wish you all well with this great enterprise. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
