<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3100</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTERS PRESS CONFERENCE PARLIAMENT HOUSE CANBERRA TUESDAY 11 DECEMBER 1973</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/12/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003100_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER'S PRESS CONFERENCE<br />
PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA,<br />
TUESDAY 11 DECEMBER 1973<br />
PRIME MINISTER: There were a couple of appointments made in this<br />
last quarter of an hour by the Executive Council. Mr Jack Neary, MBE,<br />
is to be the Vice-Chairman of the Broadcasting Control Board.<br />
Mrs Anne Lowery a member of the Metric Conversion Board. There were<br />
several other decisions made by Cabinet-yesterday which individual<br />
ministers have already announced. There is one which falls to<br />
me, it concerns the GATT Anti-Dumiping Code. You will recall on the<br />
7th November, Australia announced its intention to accede to the<br />
GATT Anti-Dumping Code. New legislation is required to enable<br />
accession, and the Government called for a report from Sir John Crawford<br />
and Mr Rattigan on what proceduires should be established on the<br />
imposition of dumping duties in the light of the time limitations<br />
imposed by the Code. This report has been received and Cabinet<br />
has accepted its recommendation. The legislation will provide that<br />
the Minister for Customs and Excise may impose a dumping duty on any<br />
goods which he is satisfied are being dumped in Australia or are<br />
causing or threatening material injury to established domestic<br />
industry or are materially retarding the establishment of a domestic<br />
industry. If he requires independent advice, he may refer any such<br />
matter to the Industries Assistance Commission for inquiry and report.<br />
Provision will also be made for appeals to the Commission against<br />
the Minister's decision on a dumping complaint.<br />
Are there any questions?<br />
QUESTION: Could you give us the details of the deal that you propose<br />
to do on education the dcoal I understand was discussed by Caucus<br />
this morning?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: There was a meeting of Caucus this morning to discuss<br />
the general contingencies on the education legislation. Now I haven't<br />
got the full text, of course, of the resolution but in general it is<br />
in these terms: The Government wants the Schools Commissicn<br />
legislation to go through. It also insists on the general principle<br />
which was recommended by the Karmel Committee that there should be<br />
a reduction in 1974 on the amount which is to be paid per pupil to<br />
non-government schools in the highest categories and a further<br />
reduction in 1975. You mention a deal. I think there have been<br />
discussions between a Country Party former minister and also the<br />
Acting Minister for Eduction, and there may be further discussions.<br />
I also gather there might have been discussions between the Leader<br />
of the Country Party and the Leader of the Liberal Party. I forget<br />
which is now the blue-tailed fly or not. Was that an accurate<br />
report of the conversation?<br />
COMMENT: Yes.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: And you vouch for its accuracy?<br />
COMMENT: I vouch for its accuracy.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes, there seems to be no doubt as to the<br />
authenticity of the reaction that it suggests. I mentioned the<br />
recommendations of the Karmel Committee in this respect and perhaps<br />
I should remind you what it said. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
" The Committee believes that there are some non-government schools<br />
for which no case can be made on an overall relative needs basis<br />
for this type of Commonwealth support, i. e. equal per capita grants."<br />
That's on page 7. Now on page 71 of the report there are three passaq( es<br />
which I think I should read to you setting out its recoimnendations.<br />
" The Committee judged that uniform per capita grants would be an<br />
expensive way of bringing about acceptable standards in all schools<br />
and would unduly delay their attainment. The Committee believes<br />
that Government aid cannot be justified in maintaining or raising<br />
standards beyond those which publicly supported schools can hope to<br />
achieve by the end of the decade. Category A schools already use a<br />
volume of resources that well exceeds the 1979 target, and the<br />
committee believes that Government assistance to these schools cannot<br />
be justified." You will remember that the amendments or requests<br />
made by the Senate was that in 1974 and 1975 there should be a<br />
minimum per capita grant to all non-government schools of the amount<br />
which was paid in 1973 under the 1972 legislation $ 62 per primary<br />
pupil, $ 104 per secondary pupil. And against that for Category A<br />
schools, the Karmel Committee recommended $ 40 and $ 65 next year,<br />
and $ 35 the year after; Category B schools, $ 45 and $ 65 in<br />
each year; Category C schools, $ 60 and $ 90 in each of those years.<br />
Now the Government regards it as basic that there should be a reduction<br />
in 1974 and a further reduction in 1975 for those schools whose<br />
educational resources are and by 1979 at the end of the 6 year period,<br />
would still be above the resources available in Government schools<br />
and the rest the bulk of the non-government schools.<br />
QUESTION: The Government's legislation for the Schools Grants<br />
Bill cut out all grants to Category A schools as of the end of this<br />
year. Can I just clarify if tha Opposition agrees to pass the<br />
Schools Commissrion Bill uniended in the Senate, would the Government<br />
consider restoring the phising out of the grants to Category A schools<br />
under the Schoolt Gran~ s 14glflation?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes, it would consider that.<br />
QUESTION: I thought the Caucus had inade a prop~ osition?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No, I have given you the general principles. The<br />
Government wants the Schools Commission to be enacted. That has been<br />
nut to the people in 1969 and it has been put again in 1972. There<br />
Is no question that this is a principle to which we are committed,<br />
which the public exptects and the Commission is along the lines of<br />
the Education Commission set up by our predecessors, the Universities<br />
Commission and the Commission on Advanced Education. It seems<br />
reasonable to have one on schools again. I also stated the general<br />
at1-titude of the Government that for those schools whose educational<br />
resources are above, and by 1979 it will still be above, the resources<br />
in the Government and the bulk of the non-government schools, there<br />
should be a reduction in 1974 and a further reduction in 1975.<br />
QUESTION: How widespread do you believe the practices in industry<br />
of paying an extra week annual leave? </p>
<p>-3-<br />
PRIME MINISTER: In the metal industries it is now universal, and it<br />
has been applied in several of the State Public Services. If you<br />
want the details I can give them to you afterwards. I can't remember<br />
precisely which State Public Services apply an annual leave loading,<br />
some already do, and I can't remember precisely in which States<br />
Arbitration Tribunals have made such a provision for ev~ ryhno' ltheir<br />
awards. Queensland within the last mcoritAñ, i. kIt: u) accnsland<br />
Industrial Commission, it made provisions for an annual leave loading<br />
for everybody under State awards, and I * believe in the metal<br />
industries under Commonwealth awards there is provision for an annual<br />
leave loading. You are asking me that question because of the<br />
Government's decision relating to Australian Government employees.<br />
QUESTION: You don't feel that the Commonwealth is too early in<br />
setting a pace for this?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: In some respects such as the metal trades matters<br />
and this covers a great number of people say in the Department of<br />
supply facilitieswe are well behind. People in private employment<br />
are already getting it and people doing the same job in Australiani<br />
Government employment are not getting it.<br />
QUESTION: What sort of Budget will Le required for the Petroleum and<br />
Minerals Authority in order that it can do its job effectively?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Mr Connorin introducing the Bill for the Petroleum<br />
and Minerals Authority, said that at least 50 million dollars a year<br />
would be available to the authority to prospect for petroleum and<br />
minerals in Australia. That is the amount of money which has been<br />
paid by the Australian Government on behalf of the taxpayers for<br />
exploration of oil and minerals up to this stage. The manner in<br />
which the Australian Government subsidy will be paid for oil and<br />
mineral exploration will be changed from subsidising companies<br />
very largely overseas companies Australians who subqcribe often<br />
did so as a form of tax dodge. It will be changed from that method<br />
to expenditure by the Petroleum and Minerals Authority.<br />
QUESTION: After Saturday's referenda defeat, do you still intend -o<br />
go ahead with your four referendum proposals when the next Senat.:<br />
Election is held?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes. Three of those proposals, of courselwere put<br />
ijt the policy speech and are in the party platform. Another, the<br />
one concerning votes for referendums in the two territories and<br />
also requiring a majority not only over the whole of Australia but<br />
just in three States instead of the present four that flows from,<br />
I think, universal suggestions which have been made for many years<br />
past. Then there will be a fifth bill for a referendum put, I suspect,<br />
when we assemble next year. That is, the one which we are discussing<br />
with the States to make it easier for the Australian Parliament to<br />
refer matters which are in its exclusive jurisdiction to the State<br />
Parliaments as well, of course, as to make greater provision for the<br />
present section of the Constitution which says that the-State<br />
Parliaments can refer matters which are in their exclusive jurisdiction<br />
to the Australian Parliament.<br />
QUESTION: Will you agree to participate in a Conference with the<br />
States on prices and incomes as proposed by the Premiers of New South<br />
Wales and Victoria? </p>
<p>-4-<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I know nothing of this proposal except what I hear<br />
on the A. B. C. and, of course, I am inclined to believe it must be<br />
authentic for that reason, and also in the newspapers but I have<br />
received no communication from any of the Premiers on this subject.<br />
If it is a matter concerning prices and incomes they don't have to<br />
wait on any Australian Government initiative to get together. They<br />
have the power, still. They are able to meet whenever they wish<br />
to discuss it because there is very little that we can contribute to<br />
the exercise of any such power. We cando it for the Northern<br />
Territory and the Capital Territory but that's all.<br />
QUESTION: On that subject, have you heard at all from the South<br />
Australian Government in reference to its offer to give you power<br />
over prices and incomes on a trial basis?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: That offer has been repeated, I gather, but it<br />
has been open for quite some time. You will remember that at the<br />
Constitutional Convention in Sydney in the first week of September,<br />
I raised this * very matter and I said that we would be happy to have a<br />
reference by the States to the Australian Parliament of the power<br />
to pass laws with respect to prices, and I said if they preferred,<br />
then that could be done just, say, for a year or a period of years.<br />
I pointed out that any such reference, in order to be effective,<br />
would have to be made by at least the two larger States, New South<br />
Wal'es and Victoria, because they produce so many of the basic<br />
commodities which effect prices not only in their States but in<br />
the four 5-malier States which import tho~ se basic commodities from<br />
Sydney, Melbourne, Goolong, Rewccistle and Wollongong. There is no<br />
difficulty, of course, as I poitiled out at the time, it could have<br />
been done within a week of getting those references made by the<br />
New South Wales and Victorian Parliaments because the Government in<br />
each case has a majority ini the Legislative Council as well as in<br />
the Legislative Assembly. Now the three smaller States which have<br />
Labor Governments do not have a majority in the Legislative Council<br />
of those States. It may well be that a Bill referring prices pow; crs<br />
to the Australian Parliament would go through those Legislative<br />
Councils if the large States, New South Wales and Victoria, were under<br />
Liberal Governments, to refer those matters to the Australian Parliament.<br />
I don't know quite what the attitude of Queensland would be, because<br />
9ueensland's Premier is sui generis. He is not Labor, he is not<br />
Liberal, and I gather, again reading the papers, although I don't<br />
think the A. B. C. veiltures to say so, that he wouldn't attend any<br />
conference that was sought by Liberal Premiers.<br />
QUESTION: Just on the eduction grants matter again. What degreewhat<br />
rate of phasing out would be acceptable to Caucus in relation<br />
to Category A schools? Would the rate of phasing out that is<br />
recommended in the Karmel Report be acceptable to the Government?<br />
I-ave you received any offer of any form from the Liberal Party?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I have not spoken to any member of the Opposition<br />
Parties on this at all. Mr Bowen has spoken to one Country Party<br />
former minister, but that's all T know. I want to see'what the<br />
proposals were. There must be a reduction as I say in 1974 and a<br />
further one in 1975 for those schools which, as the Karmel Committee<br />
said, can't justify Government assistance at the present scale or<br />
at all in their view. </p>
<p>QUESTION: I understand you told the Caucus this morning that you<br />
had no intention of being a lame duck Prime Minister. You also spoke<br />
of the necessity of demonstrating that you had the respect of the<br />
people to preserve the international standing of the Government.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I wish I could say it as well as you can.<br />
QUESTION: Do you think the international standing of the Government is<br />
at risk at the moment, and could you tell us what you mean by you<br />
have no intention of being a lame duck Prime Minister?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: What I mean is this: I see no point in being in<br />
office if one can't achieve things. Obviously anybody in this job<br />
enjoys it but there is no point in just enjoying the prestige<br />
if one can't deliver the goods, and there can't be any subject on<br />
which the Government relied so much to become a Government as some<br />
of the matters which the Senate is delaying at the moment; such as<br />
schools and health and trade practices and overseas control.<br />
Australian control of our resources, equal opportunity for Australians,<br />
were quite basic to what we proposed for the people in 1969 and again<br />
in 1972, and it is, I believe, essential that we be able to carry out<br />
some of those things which we undertook to do.<br />
QUESTION: Have those referenda results harmed your electoral<br />
prospects at all?<br />
PRIME MNIdSTER: No, I don't think referendum results can be equated<br />
in any way with PlecLion results. There is, of course, one<br />
particular thing which W1ould distingjuish an election campaign,<br />
particularly for the House ofL" Representatives, where the results<br />
determine who is the Government, and that is we are positive<br />
or constructive in what we would put as we have been in what we<br />
have put. Pure negativism~ may be sufficed to beat a referendum. It<br />
won't, I believe, these days suffice to make an Opposition into a<br />
Government. QUESTION: I understand that there is a D Notice Committee mepf-1ng<br />
today. PRIME MINISTER: That is right.<br />
QUESTION: What is your personal opinion on D Notices? Do they<br />
need to be revised or are they alright. I gather you have carried<br />
on the same D Notice system as the previous administration?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: We are reviewing the system as you know, that's why<br />
y,-ur bosses are here in Canberra today talkinq well, when I say<br />
your bosses, I mean your editors. I don't say their bosses are<br />
here, but your editors are here and they are conferring with some<br />
of my colleagues and I am taking them to dinner tonight. We will<br />
have the long spoons. I dare say D Notices will be mentioned.<br />
The D Notice system operates through the media.<br />
QUESTION:. But with Government quidarice?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Co-operation. There is no law which governs the<br />
D Notice system and as some of you know quite well, you can defy<br />
the D Notice system. The only sanction, if you defy the D Notice<br />
system, would be that you wouldn't get information your newspapers, </p>
<p>-6-<br />
stations, wouldn't get information from the Government if you broke<br />
an arrangement which you made with the Government about the subjects<br />
concerned, but there is no criminal sanctions involved at all.<br />
There is no law broken, it is purely a matter of understanding or<br />
honour, if you like, between the medium and Government departments.<br />
QUESTION: But you lay down what is covered by a D Notice?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: It can only be done by agreement. The Government<br />
can' t say to any newspaper or station " you will not publish this".<br />
It can't, there is no law which enables it to say so. The only<br />
arrangement is a voluntary one between the medium and the department.<br />
QUESTION: You spoke a moment ago of your desire to keep achieving<br />
your policies. In view of the negative history of referendums,<br />
do you think you have really any chance of getting these next<br />
ones through at the Senate elections?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes. I believe that we have too easily accepted<br />
the fact that the people won't modernise the Australian Constitution.<br />
It is a grossly inadequate Constitution. But the best efforts<br />
of the Government and the editorial writers for those newspapers<br />
whose editorials are read, all went to no avail last Saturday. Every<br />
editorial on the subject in the Age and the Sydney Morning Herald<br />
and the Canberra Times and the Financial Review and the Murdoch<br />
papers were all in favour. They agreed with us for once, yet it<br />
wasn't sufficient. See, there was no referendum between 1951 when<br />
Mr Menzies lost his only ref eiendum and 1967 when Mr Holt won one<br />
and lost one. In the J. 940s there were several referendums put,<br />
Mr Curtin lost one in 1944, MZ Chif icy lost two and won one in 1946<br />
and he lost one in 1948 and then in 1937 Mr Lyons lost two. But I<br />
think the last one to be carried before that was in 1928. I think we<br />
ought to be more diligent and regular in enabling the people to<br />
modernise the Constitution. I think if you face up to the facts<br />
and do it regularly they are more likely to accept the procedure<br />
which the Constitution itself laid down. There is no other way<br />
you can alter the Constituion. Every Parliament in Australia,<br />
State and Australian Parliaments, could agree and you would still need<br />
a Bill to go through the Australian Parliament or at least twice<br />
go through the House of Representatives and the people to approve that<br />
bill at a referendum. That is the only way we can alter the<br />
arrangement.<br />
QUESTION: Can you tell us when the dispute between Mr Uren and the<br />
NCDC will be resolved and....<br />
PRIME MINISTER: May be today.<br />
QUESTION: You will recall that the McMahon Government set up an<br />
independent research group at the A. N. U. to study all aspects of<br />
Federal/ State financial relations. We have heard nothing about it<br />
since. Can I ask you whether your Government is still financing<br />
the project, have you received any progress reports on its work and<br />
will you act on any reccmivendations that come forward? </p>
<p>-7<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I stress that it is not just Commonwealth/ State<br />
financial relations. I was very insistent in questions at the time<br />
and it was accepted that it should also cover local government<br />
finances. In the last week I called for a report on this very matter.<br />
I have got it up on my table at the moment. There have been some<br />
articles written but not yet, I think, published in some learned<br />
journals. It is doing some work. I can't say at this stage one<br />
can see fruits of it, but I am pressing them to do something about it<br />
because the idea is a good one. We do need to have academics<br />
investigating constantly the question of Commonwealth and State and<br />
Civic finances and their interaction. Up until now the only time<br />
anything has ever been done is to get some Task Force to look into<br />
it such as the Coombs report into Commonwealth expenditure. I have,<br />
several times, advocated that the State Governments ought to have a<br />
similar Task Force or Task Forces looking into their expenditure. You<br />
always hear about the Australian Government's expenditure but in fact<br />
State Government expenditure rises almost as much, and in fact our<br />
expenditure has risen this year largely because of additional funds<br />
we have earmarked for expenditure by the States.<br />
QUESTION: policy says that in the public interest the<br />
Commonwealth should act positively in the Arbitration Commission<br />
to gjet an extra week's loading for workers at holiday time. I understand<br />
that yesterday in Cabinet you urged caution in proceeding with<br />
that through the Arbitration Court. When will the Commonwealth now<br />
enact that part of A. L. P. policy now that the Cabinet has decided to<br />
legislate to enact. that part about public servants getting the<br />
loading?<br />
PRIME MIFIS1' ER: We can't enact an~ ythingj. Wle haven't got the power<br />
aO~ Ir incomes except for our own employees or people in the territories,<br />
So we can't enact any such proV'ision. What can happen is that the<br />
Avaatralian Government or dtate Governments too for that. matter can<br />
appear they can intervene in proceedings before the Australian<br />
Can~ ciliation and Arbitration Cou'mii7sion where this matter or any<br />
athcr mratter are the subject a lot of c.-laims by registered<br />
organisations of employee-s. The fact that the Australian Government<br />
is hntroducing a hill for this wcmi-ld have an influence, I expect,<br />
an The Commission. Earlier at thi conference, I pointed out that<br />
the Commission had already accepted and provided for the principle<br />
ofan annual leave loading in the metal trades award. It is for,<br />
th~ is reason that people in that area who are Australian Government<br />
LompJoyees, had approacheO t. he Pulhie Snrvice Arbitrator. This will be<br />
in a bill which we will introdciue in the autumn session. I don't<br />
know at this stage whether the Opposition parties will oppose it or not.<br />
We believe that basic matters of Government policy such as this<br />
con~ cerning Australian Government employees should take the form of<br />
ie. jislation. As things stand at the moment Australian Government<br />
employees can apply to the Public Service Arbitrator for them. They<br />
have. Under our legislation, the people in the highest brackets will,<br />
in fact, get less than they are likely to get, ihan they are seeking,<br />
before the Arbitrator at present.<br />
QUESTION: Will you intervene in other cases and will you extend it<br />
to the other Commonwealth employees..<br />
rEIME MINISTER: I did overloo: ' ra Mr Barron has asked me. This<br />
was never discussed in Cabinet yesterday. There was no discussion<br />
on any matter pending before the Conciliation and Arbitration<br />
Commission. The discussion centered solely on the projected legislation. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
