<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3962</transcript-id>
    <title>THE DRIFT TO DISASTER</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/11/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Broadcast</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003962.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER' S WEEKLY BROADCAST<br />
THE DRIFT TO DISASTER<br />
Sunday 9 November 1975<br />
I want to suggest one very good way of<br />
describing the present behaviour of the Senate of<br />
putting that behaviour in perspective. It's a comparison<br />
that should appeal strongly to Opposition members themselves.<br />
The Liberals and the Country Party are fond of condemning<br />
Australian workers whenever they go on strike. They love<br />
to getup and fulminate about the evil of strikes. I wonder<br />
if it ever occurs to them that the Senate's present<br />
behaviour amounts to a strike. The Senate won't pass the<br />
Budget; they won't reject the Budget; they won't suggest<br />
any amendments to the Budget. They won't do anything<br />
about the Budget at all. They refuse even to consider it.<br />
In other words, the Opposition in the Senate are refusing<br />
to do their job. They have gone on strike.<br />
Now whenever workers go on strike for<br />
whatever reason the Opposition are always the first to<br />
condemn them for anti-social behaviour. But look at the<br />
anti-social consequences of the Senate's strike. Their<br />
strike is infinitely more disruptive and dangerous than<br />
anything contemplated by the unions. The Opposition in the<br />
Senate are holding the country to ransom. They aren't<br />
just disrupting a particular industry; they are threatening<br />
the whole nation with chaos. They are totally indifferent<br />
to the damage and hardship they are causing to the Australian<br />
people, to business, to industry, to the economy as a whole.<br />
The main thing that's different about the Senate's<br />
strike is that the Senators are getting paid for it.<br />
It can't be emphasised too often that although<br />
the Opposition Senators are refusing to pass the Budget<br />
they are also refusing to reject it. And we know why<br />
they won't reject it. They won't reject it because a<br />
minority of Opposition Senators have made it plain to<br />
Mr Fraser that they won't go along with rejection. So<br />
Mr Fraser has been forced to adopt these phony stalling<br />
tactics this repeated deferral of the Budget. And because<br />
of this he has been forced into a monstrous inconsistency<br />
a complete logical absurdity. The Opposition says it will<br />
pass the Budget but on certain conditions. Remember<br />
how they attacked and denounced the Budget when the<br />
Treasurer introduced it? Remember Mr Fraser's words when<br />
he announced his dangerous and irresponsible course?<br />
He said: " The Budget has been an admitted failure." Well. the<br />
Opposition now tell us that this same Budget will be passed<br />
by the Opposition provided I hold an election. Suddenly<br />
our Budget is good enough for the Liberals. It's not a<br />
failure after all! The Opposition knows very well the great<br />
benefits and advantages contained in the Budget the<br />
tax cuts, the tax reforms, the benefits for children, for the<br />
aged, for pensioners, for migrants. They don't dare reject </p>
<p>these benefits f or the Australian people. In fact<br />
only last week, the Senate passed our tax reform bills,<br />
but won't pass the Budget which will permit the<br />
expenditure of these taxes.<br />
It's frightening to contemplate the havoc and<br />
personal hardship, the business disruption, the uncertainty,<br />
the social and economic chaos which the Opposition is<br />
causing to the whole community. And make no mistake<br />
these effects are already being felt. They are happening<br />
now. They are already reflected in a downturn in consumer<br />
spending as the Christmas holiday approaches. For who can<br />
blame the Australian people especially public servants,<br />
who depend on the Government for their wages and salaries<br />
f or cutting back their personal spending when the outlook<br />
is so uncertain? Who can blame businesses for cutting<br />
staff when Government orders are in jeopardy? Even if<br />
the Senate called off its strike tomorrow, irreparable<br />
damage to the economy would already be done. In Parliament<br />
this week, the Treasurer, Bill Hayden, drew attention to<br />
the disastrous effects of the Senate's behaviour on rural local<br />
government, especially on local employment projects funded<br />
by the RED scheme. Bill Hayden made it clear that unemployment<br />
levels early next year are bound to be higher than anticipated<br />
because of the failure to pass the Budget. Inevitably there<br />
will be effects on other economic indicators. The whole<br />
difficult and delicate process of economic recovery is<br />
being wantonly jeopardised by the Opposition. It is<br />
heartbreaking to ministers like Bill Hayden and Jim<br />
McClelland it is heartbreaking to me and all my colleagues<br />
that the very real progress we've been making towards economic<br />
recovery is being set back by weeks, by months, perhaps<br />
even lon( 3er, by the irresponsible policies of the opposition.<br />
I can think ot nothing more likely to cause dismay to the<br />
business community than this needless prolongation of our<br />
economic difficulties., Everything that business and unions<br />
and the Government have been working for has been put at<br />
risk. In its efforts to overturn the elected Government,<br />
the Opposition is dragging this country to the very brink<br />
of catastrophe. There is no other way to describe what Mr<br />
Fraser and his cohorts are doing.<br />
As soon as the crisis began, the Government<br />
took stock of its responsibilities and immediately began<br />
looking at ways of avoiding unnecessary hardship to the<br />
public. We decided to do everything in our power to<br />
minimise disruption and suffering to innocent people<br />
especially to loyal public servants, who are carrying on their<br />
work out of a sense of duty to the Australian people.<br />
Quite plainly, it would have been a total abdication of<br />
the Government's responsibilities if we had sat idly by and<br />
done nothing in this emergency. Of course there are limits<br />
to what we can do. Without the Budget being passed, the<br />
normal conduct of Government services is impossible.<br />
Nevertheless, we expect, with the generous cooperation<br />
of the banks the private banks as well as the Commonwealth<br />
and State Government banks to make arrangements that<br />
will ensure as far as possible that public servants and<br />
contractors receive normal wages and payments for their work.<br />
/ 3 </p>
<p>I don't regard this as a solution to the crisis, Of<br />
course it is not. These will be temporary and in some<br />
ways awkward arrangements. They do not resolve the<br />
underlying problem. Yet Mr Fraser went into a lather<br />
of indignation the other day because the Government<br />
took steps to see that public servants and others<br />
are not made bankrupt or destitute by the Opposition's<br />
action. I make it clear that all these emergency<br />
arrangements will be legal and constitutional.<br />
It is the Opposition's behaviour that is defying the<br />
Constitution and subverting established parliamentary<br />
convention. It is the Opposition's behaviour that is<br />
bringing Australia to a standstill.<br />
There is and always has been one basic<br />
issue in this dispute: that the elected Government, the<br />
Government in the House of Representatives, has the right<br />
to govern for its normal three-year term. Three weeks<br />
ago Mr Fraser wanted the Government to resign immediately.<br />
Last week he maae another proposal. Now he's sayingthis<br />
was his incredible proposal last week that the<br />
Government can have another six months in office by grace<br />
and favour of the Opposition another six months in<br />
office providing we resign by the end of June.<br />
Mr Fraser and his supporters dressed up this<br />
preposterous suggestion by callirgit an " offer"; or a<br />
11compromise"~ or a " con-cession". It was nothing of the<br />
sort. Let's assume for the moment that the proposal was<br />
genuine. What are its practical implications? It can<br />
only mean this: Mr Fraser is now proposing, in the midst<br />
of the uncertainty and hardship he has already caused,<br />
that from this moment on, from now for the next six, seven<br />
or eight months, the nation should be involved in a<br />
continuing election campaign and should suffer all the<br />
paralysis of normal administration and the normal decisionmaking<br />
processes which inevitably comes from an election<br />
and its aftermath. I rejected this suggestion. I shall<br />
reject any other attempt to obscure or compromise the basic<br />
principle for which I am fighting the right of an elected<br />
Government to govern, the right of the House of Representatives,<br />
the people's House, to determine the Government of this<br />
country. I shall not yield on that principle. I shall<br />
not give up my fight to defend and preserve our democratic<br />
institutions. I know I can count on the support of the<br />
overwhelming majority of typical decent Australians. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
