<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3073</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON. E.G. WHITLAM, Q.C., M.P., FOR THE OPENING OF THE ADVANCED EDUCATION, HOBART, SUNDAY 18 NOVEMBER, 1973</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/11/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003073.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE HON. E. G. WHITLAM,<br />
FOR THE OPENING OF THE<br />
TASMANIAN COLLEGE OF ADVANCED EDUCATION1<br />
HOBART, SUNDAY 18 NOVEMBER, 1973<br />
I MUST CONFESS THAT IT IS A NOVEL EXPERIENCE FOR<br />
ME TO BE INVITED TO OPEN AN INSTITUTION THAT HAS BEEN IN<br />
EXISTENCE FOR FIVE YEARS. ICOMMEND YOUR PATIENCE AND<br />
FORESIGHT IN WAITING SO LONG FOR THIS OPPORTUNITY.<br />
NATURALLY I WAS DELIGHTED TO ACCEPT YOUR INVITATION<br />
BECAUSE I KNOW THAT THIS COLLEGE, FORMALLY ESTABLISHED<br />
IN 1968, IS AMONG THE MOST PROGRESSIVE AND COMPREHENSIVE<br />
INSTITUTIONS OF ITS KIND IN AUSTRALIA. THE ADVANCED<br />
EDUCATION ACT OF 1968, BY WHICH THE COLLEGE WAS ESTABLISHED1<br />
WAS AN IMPORTANT AND FAR-SIGHTED STATUTE. IT CREATED A<br />
COUNCIL OF ADVANCED EDUCATION IN TASMANIA WHICH ADMINISTERS<br />
NOT ONLY THIS COLLEGE BUT THE WHOLE FIELD OF ADVANCED<br />
EDUCATION IN THIS STATE. i e / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
THE AIMS AND OBJECTIVES OF THE COUNCIL, SET<br />
FORTH IN YOUR HANDBOOK, ARE CLEARLY ATTUNED TO SOCIAL<br />
AND ECONOMIC NEEDS AND THE ASPIRATIONS OF A GROWING<br />
AND DYNAMIC COMMUNITY, I CONGRATULATE ALL THOSE WHO<br />
HAVE WORKED TO ESTABLISH THIt COLLEGE AND LAID DOWN THE<br />
PRACTICAL AND ENLIGHTENED PRINCIPLES ON. WHICH IT IS<br />
CONDUCTED, I DON'T THINK THERE CAN BE ANY DOUBT OF THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT'S WHOLEHEARTED COMMITMENT TO EDUCATION,<br />
THE STRENGTH OF THAT COMMITMENT AND OUR READINESS TO<br />
DISCHARGE IT HAVE BEEN DEMONSTRATED OVER AND OVER AGAIN,<br />
WITHIN A FEW WEEKS OF TAKING OFFICE WE SET UP THE INTERIM<br />
COMMITTEE FOR THE AUSTRALIAN SCHOOLS COMMISSION; WITHIN A<br />
FEW MONTHS OF ITS APPOINTMENT THE COMMITTEE PRESENTED ITS<br />
HISTORIC REPORT; WITHIN THREE MONTHS OF RECEIVING THAT<br />
REPORT THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT, IN ' ITS FIRST BUDGET,<br />
PROVIDED AN ADDITIONAL SUM OF $ 404 MILLION FOR EDUCATION IN<br />
1973-74. THAT WAS AN INCREASE OF 92% ON LAST YEAR, THE<br />
GREATEST SINGLE UPGRADING OF EDUCATIONAL EXPENDITURES IN<br />
OUR HISTORY, THUS WE HAVE HONOURED THE PROMISE IN MY<br />
POLICY SPEECH A YEAR AGO THAT EDUCATION WOULD BE THE MOST<br />
RAPIDLY GROWING SECTOR OF PUBLIC SPENDING UNDER A LABOR<br />
GOVERNMENT, </p>
<p>-3-<br />
I HOPE I WILL NOT BE ACCUSED OF UNDUE COMPLACENCY OR<br />
SELF-SATISFACTION IF I SAY THIS: WHATEVER ELSE MY<br />
GOVERNMENT MAY ACHIEVE IN ITS TERM OF OFFICE, WE HAVE<br />
MANAGED IN LESS THAN A YEAR TO SET A NEW COURSE FOR<br />
EDUCATION IN THIS COUNTRY AND. NEW STANDARDS FOR OUR<br />
CHILDREN'S FUTURE. THAT COURSE WILL NEVER BE REVERSED,<br />
THOSE STANDARDS WILL NEVER BE DOWNGRADED,<br />
THE GREAT THRUST OF OUR REFORMS SO FARHAS BEEN IN<br />
SECONDARY EDUCATION NOT BECAUSE WE REGARD TERTIARY-EDUCATION<br />
AS ANY LESS IMPORTANT, BUT BECAUSE PRIMARY AND SECONDARY<br />
SCHOOLING HAVE BEEN THE AREAS OF GREATEST NEED, OF MOST<br />
PRESSING INADEQUACY AND IMPOVERISHMENT, So LET ME<br />
REASSURE YOU FIRST ON THIS POINT: TERTIARY EDUCATION, BOTH<br />
IN UNIVERSITIES AND INSTITUTIONS LIKE YOURS, RANKS AS HIGH<br />
IN OUR PLANS AND AMBITIONS AS EDUCATION OF ANY OTHER KIND,<br />
IT IS FUNDAMENTAL TO OUR PHILOSOPHY THAT THE WHOLE PROCESS<br />
OF EDUCATION SHOULD FORM AN UNBROKEN AND EVOLVING CONTINUUM<br />
OF INSTRUCTION AND CULTIVATION, IN WHICH ALL CHILDREN<br />
INDEED ALL PEOPLE HAVE A FULL AND EQUAL OPPORTUNITY TO<br />
PARTICIPATE AT EVERY STAGE,<br />
HAVING SAID THAT, LET ME MAKE ONE OTHER BROAD POINT<br />
ABOUT THIS PRINCIPLE OF EQUAL OPPORTUNITY, IT IS FUNDAMENTAL<br />
TO WHAT COLLEGES LIKE YOURS ARE ALL ABOUT, . WE BELIEVE IN WHAT<br />
OUR OPPONENTOSP POLLIINKKEEEN TTTSOO CCAALLLL I'FORRUEEREE DDOOMM OOFF CCHHOOIICCEEI', s ,/ 4 </p>
<p>-4-<br />
THAT FREEDOM, HOWEVER, MEANS SOMETHING QUITE DIFFERENT.<br />
FOR US FROM WHAT IT MEANS FOR THEM., FOR US, FOR THE<br />
AuSTRALIAN LABOR PARTY, FREEDOM OF CHOICE MEANS THE<br />
FREEDOM TO CHOOSE. BETWEEN METHODS AND CnIjiRSFS AND<br />
TYPES OF EDUCATION.: IT DOESNOT MEAN A CHOICE BETWEEN<br />
STANDARDS OR DEGREES OF EXCELLENCE BETWEEN A GOOD<br />
EDUCATION OR A BAD ONE, BETWEEN AN EXPENSIVE EDUCATION OR<br />
A POOR ONE. IT IS SOMETIMES SAID OF SOCIALISTS THAT WE<br />
WANT EVERYONE TO HAVE A UNIVERSITY EDUCATION. THAT WOULD<br />
BE AS SENSIBLE AS SUGGESTING THAT EVERY UNIVERSITY STUDENT<br />
SHOULDSTUDY ECONOMICS. THE WHOLE POINT-OF OUR APPROACH<br />
TO ADVANCED EDUCATION IS THAT A PLURALIST SOCIETY DEMANDS<br />
A PLURALIST CONCEPTION OF EDUCATION. IT DEMANDS DIVERSITY.<br />
YOU WILL REMEMBER THE INTELLECTUAL CONCE. IT PREVAILING<br />
IN VICTORIAN ENGLAND AND IT PERSISTED WITH SURPRISING<br />
RESILIENCE UNTIL QUITE RECENTLY THAT THERE WAS SOMETHING<br />
INHERENTLY SUPERIOR' IN AN EDUCATION IN THE HUMANE ARTS, IN<br />
THE CLASSICAL DISCIPLINES AS DISTINCT FROM THE. PHYSICAL<br />
SCIENCES. AGAIN, A FEW YEARS AGO, THERE WAS'A QUITE FATUOUS<br />
AND SNOBBISH ARGUMENT IN THIS COUNTRY ABOUT THE PROPRIETY OF<br />
COLLEGES OF ADVANCED EDUCATION AWARDING DEGREES. I HOPE WE<br />
HAVE; HEARD THE END OF SUCH ARGUMENTS. I HOPE IT WILL NEVER<br />
AGAIN BE SUGGESTED THAT ONE KIND OF SECONDARY SCHOOL IS<br />
SUPERIOR TO ANOTHER, OR THAT A UNIVERSITY EDUCATION IS MORE<br />
DESIRABLE THAN ONE PROVIDED BY A COLLEGE, THE" IMPORTANT<br />
REQUIREMENT IS THAT THE SAME STANDARDS OF EXCELLENCE, OF<br />
DEDICATION, OF MATERIAL ENDOWMENT, OF TEACHING SKILLS MUST<br />
APPLY IN WHATEVER INSTITUTION AN INDIVIDUAL CHOOSES. </p>
<p>I AM INDEBTED ONCE AGAIN TO PROFESSOR KARMELo<br />
THE CHAIRMAN OF THE AUSTRALIAN UNIVERSITIES COMMISSION<br />
WHOSE REPORT I HAVE MENTIONED THIS AFTERNOON, FOR A<br />
QUOTATION FROM HIS FRANK TATE MEMORIAL LECTURE DELIVERED<br />
LAST WEEK AT THE UNIVERSITY OF MELBOURNE, PROFESSOR KARMEL<br />
SAID THIS AND HE WAS SPEAKING OF THE COURSE THAT TERTIARY<br />
EDUCATION SHOULD TAKE<br />
" ONE WILL, GENERALLY SPEAKING, AIM TOWARDS<br />
RODUCING A CONTINUUM OF EDUCATION OPPORTUNI'TIES,<br />
IN DIVERSE INSTITUTIONS, OFFERING DIVERSE COURSES,<br />
USING DIVERSE MODES OF LEARNING; AND NO DOUBT<br />
WE WILL ATTACH DIVERSE' VALUES TO THEM...<br />
ACADEMIC EXCELLENCE ( WILL STILL) BE IMPORTANT<br />
FOR UNIVERSITIES AND FOR COLLEGES AND WILL SEPARATE<br />
THEM FROM OTHER INSTITUTIONS, BUT IT DOESN'T<br />
MEAN THAT THERE WON'T BE OTHER FORMS OF INSTITUTIONS<br />
THAT MIGHT EMPHASISE OTHER THINGS AND MIGHT REGARD<br />
UNIVERSITIES AS MORE BOUND UP WITH LIFE EXPERIENCES<br />
THAN WITH LEARNING IN THE TRADITIONAL SENSE.,"<br />
I HAVE NO DOUBT THAT COLLEGES OF ADVANCED EDUCATION HELP<br />
PROVIDE THIS ESSENTIAL ELEMENT OF DIVERSITY IN OUR EDUCATIONAL<br />
SYSTEM. BUT THEY DO MORE THAN THAT: THEY MAKE THE WHOLE<br />
PROCESS OF ACCESS TO TERTIARY EDUCATION MORE JUST AND EQUITABLE.<br />
IF WE LOOK BACK ON THE LONG YEARS OF RULE BY LIBERAL-COUNTRY<br />
PARTY GOVERNMENTS, NO ONE WILL DISPUTE THAT UNDER OUR<br />
PREDECESSORS MORE AND MORE YOUNG PEOPLE WERE ADMITTED TO<br />
UNIVERSITIES. </p>
<p>6-<br />
YET IT WAS ONLY IN THE EARLY DAYS OF WIDESPREAD COMMONWEALTH<br />
SCHOLARSHIPS THAT THIS GREATER ACCESS TO TERTIARY EDUCATION<br />
WAS BASED FAIRLY ON CONSIDERATIONS OF ACADEMIC MERIT ALONE,<br />
AS FEES ROSE AND THE SCHOLARSHIP SCHEME CONTRACTED, A<br />
UNIVERSITY EDUCATION DEPENDED MORE AND MORE ON THE ABILITY<br />
TO PAY FOR IT. ISUGGEST THERE IS A SIMPLE WAY TO TEST<br />
WHETHER GENUINE EQUALITY OF OPPORTUNITY. EXISTS, WE SHOULD<br />
LOOK TO SEE WHETHER THOSE GOING ON TO HIGHER EDUCATION ARE<br />
DRAWN FROM ALL GROUPS OF THE POPULATION IN THE SAME PROPORTION<br />
AS EACH GROUP IS REPRESENTED IN THE POPULATION.<br />
THE KARMEL REPORT HAS CLEARLY SHOWN THAT IN NO COUNTRY<br />
HAS THIS IN FACT HAPPENED. WE ARE NOT ALONE IN THE SOCIALLY<br />
DISCRIMINATING NATURE OF OUR EDUCATIONAL SYSTEM. MANY<br />
AUSTRALIAN STUDIES HAVE ILLUSTRATED THE GENERAL EXPERIENCE.<br />
A TYPICAL SURVEY OF STUDENTS ENTERING FOUR PROFESSIONAL<br />
FACULTIES IN six AUSTRALIAN UNIVERSITIES IN 1965 AND 1967<br />
SHOWED THAT NEARLY HALF THE STUDENTS ENTERING HIGHER EDUCATION<br />
WERE THE CHILDREN OF PROFESSIONAL AND MANAGERIAL FATHERS, WHO<br />
REPPFSENTEI 17.5% OF THE POPULATION IN THE AGE GROUP LIKELY TO<br />
BE FATHERS. INDUSTRIAL WORKERS REPRESENTED NEARLY 60% OF THE<br />
POPULATION, BUT THEIR CHILDREN ACCOUNTED FOR ONLY 22.6% OF<br />
STUDENTS ENTERING THE FOUR FACULTIES. A STUDY OF STUDENTS<br />
ENTERING SCIENCE COURSES AT UNIVERSITIES AND DIPLOMA COURSES<br />
IN APPLIED SCIENCES AT COLLEGES OF ADVANCED EDUCATION IN<br />
AUSTRALIA IN 1969 SHOWED THAT 64% HAD FATHERS IN4 PROFESSIONAL,<br />
MANAGERIAL OR FARM-OWNING OCCUPATIONS, ALTHOUGH THIS CATEGORY<br />
ACCOUNTED FOR 25% OF THE MALE POPULATION; 20.2% OF THE STUDENTS<br />
HAD FATHERS IN MANUAL OCCUPATIONS, ALTHOUGH SUCH WORKERS<br />
ACCOUNTED FOR 59% OF THE MALE POPULATION. o o m 1 </p>
<p>7<br />
PROFESSOR KARMEL' S COMMITTEE CONCLUDED: " AMONG TERTIARY<br />
STUDENTS OF ALL KINDS, THE CHILDREN OF MANUAL W4ORKERS<br />
ARE UNDER-REPRESENTED AND THOSE OF HIGHER STATUS FAMILIES<br />
OVER-REPRESENTED, TO THE EXTENT THAT HIGHER EDUCATION<br />
IS FINANCED FROM TAXES IT HAS, THUS A SOMEWHAT REGRESSIVE<br />
EFFECT, POORER PEOPLE CONTRIBUTING TO THE COST OF EDUCATION<br />
OF A GROUP IN WHICH THE CHILDREN OF RICHER PARENTS PREDOMINATE<br />
AND FROM WHICH RECIPIENTS CAN EXPECT TO DRAW HIGHER THAN<br />
AVERAGE INCOMES. IDON'T WANT IT TO BE THOUGHT FOR A MINUTE THAT WE<br />
SEE COLLEGES AS THE PRIME RECEPTACLES FOR POORER OR LESS<br />
AMBITIOUS STUDENTS, WHILE UNIVERSITIES CONTINUE TO CATER<br />
FOR THE WEL. L-TO-DO. OUR PURPOSE IS TO SEE THAT ALL<br />
INSTITUTIONS OF ADVANCED EDUCATION ARE OPEN TO THE WIDEST<br />
RANGE OF PEOPLE. TERTIARY EDUCATION, IN WHATEVER FORM,<br />
MUST BE AS ACCESSIBLE, AS INTEGRAL A. PART OF THE RANGE OF<br />
PUBLIC INSTRUCTION AS EDUCATION OF ANY OTHER KIND. THIS<br />
IS WHERE GOVERNMENTS IN THE PAST HAVE FAILED. No ONE WOULD<br />
DENY THAT THE UNIVERSITIES HAVE VASTLY IMPROVED IN QUALITY<br />
AND QUANTITY SINCE THE NATIONAL GOVERNMENT ACCEPTED<br />
RESPONSIBILITY FOR THEM. YET IN 1971 UNIVERSITIES REFUSED<br />
ADMISSION To 131 PER CENT OF THE QUALIFIED APPLICANTS IN<br />
NEW SOUTH WALES, 20 PER CENT OF THE APPLICANTS IN VICTORIA<br />
AND 11 PER CENT IN SOUTH AUSTRALIA, EIGHTY-SIX UNIVERSITY<br />
DEPARTMENTS WERE OBLIGED TO IMPOSE ENTRY QUOTAS. ONLY ONE<br />
STUDENT IN EVERY THREE AT UNIVERSITIES AND ONE STUDENT IN<br />
EVERY 10 AT COLLEGES OF ADVANCED EDUCATION HAS RECEIVED<br />
ASSISTANCE FROM THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT. i / 8 </p>
<p>-8-<br />
THE MAJORITY OF PLACES AT TERTIARY INSTITUTIONS HAVE BEEN<br />
OCCUPIED NOT BY THE STUDENTS BEST EQUIPPED TO TAKE ADVANTAGE<br />
OF THEM, BUT BY THOSE WHO CAN AFFORD THE FEES.<br />
As YOU KNOW, FROM NEXT JANUARY THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT<br />
WILL ASSUME FULL RESPONSIBILI* TY FOR THE FUNDING OF AUSTRALIAN<br />
UNIVERSITIES. I DO NOT NEED TO EMPHASISE THE IMPORTANCE OF<br />
THIS STEP FOR INSTITUTIONS SUCH AS THIS, OR IF I MAY SAY SO<br />
FOR THE FUTURE OF COMMONWEALTH-STATE FINANCIAL RELATIONSHIPS,<br />
OUR FIRST ACT WILL BE TO ABOLISH ALL. FEES. To DO SO WILL. COST<br />
US $ 33 MILLION FOR THE FIRST SIX MONTHS OF 1973-74 A SMALL<br />
PROPORTION OF THE INCOME UNIVERSITIES RECEIVE, BUT A LARGE<br />
PROPORTION OF THE INCOME OF STUDENTS AND THEIR FAMILIES.<br />
ACCESS TO UNIVERSITY EDUCATION WILL BE ON THE BASIS OF<br />
MERIT RATHER THAN MONEY.<br />
AT THE SAME TIME, MY COLLEAGUE THE MINISTER FOR<br />
EDUCATION, HAS ANNOUNCED A COMPREHENSIVE PROGRAM OF LIVING<br />
ALLOWANCES AND OTHER BENEFITS FOR STUDENTS ENROLLED IN<br />
APPROVED COURSES. THESE MEASURES WILL DO A GREAT DEAL MORE<br />
TO MAKE HIGHER EDUCATION GENUINELY FREE THAN SIMPLY REPLACE<br />
THE EXISTING COMPETITLYF_ SCHOLARSHIP SCHEMES. IN TASMANIA<br />
THIS YEAR LESS THAN 20% OF STUDENTS IN ADVANCED EDUCATION<br />
ARE RECEIVING ASSISTANCE UNDER PROGRAMS INITIATED BY TIHE<br />
PREVIOUS GOVERNMENT. NEXT YEAR, ALL AUSTRALIAN STUDENTS<br />
WILL BE ABLE TO APPLY FOR ASSISTANCE ON THE BASIS OF NEED. ,/ 9 </p>
<p>-9-<br />
LET ME MENTION SOME OF OUR OTHER MEASURES TO IMPROVE<br />
THE STANDARDS OF HIGHER EDUCATION OTHER THAN IN UNIVERSITIES,<br />
ONE OF OUR FIRST ACTS IN JANUARY THIS YEAR WAS TO SET UP<br />
A COMMITTEE ON TECHNICAL AND FURTHER EDUCATION, THAT COMMITTEE<br />
IS DUE TO REPORT IN THE FIRST HALF OF NEXT YEAR, I HOPE IT<br />
WILL BRING AS MUCH FRESH AIR TO THE STUDY OF ADVANCED EDUCATION<br />
AS THE SCHOOLS COMMITTEE HAS BROUGHT TO SECONDARY EDUCATION,<br />
IT WILL TAKE ACCOUNT OF OVERALL MANPOWER POLICY AND THE NEEDS<br />
OF INDUSTRY, GOVERNMENT AND COMMERCE, ANOTHER OF OUR EARLY<br />
INITIATIVES THIS YEAR WAS TO GRANT AN ADDITIONAL $ 5 MILLION<br />
FOR LIBRARY MATERIALS IN ALL COLLEGES OF ADVANCED EDUCATION<br />
DURING THE 1973-75 TRIENNIUM, TASMANIA'S SHARE OF THIS WILL<br />
BE $ 135,000, NEXT, WE HAVE APPOINTED A COMMITTEE OF THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
UNIVERSITIES COMMISSION TO ADVISE ON AN OPEN UNIVERSITY,<br />
ONCE AGAIN I ACKNOWLEDGE THE ASSISTANCE OF PROFESSOR KARMEL,<br />
WHO WILL BE THE CHAIRMAN OF THAT INQUIRY, WE HAVE ASKED THE<br />
COMMITTEE TO SEE HOW AUSTRALIA CAN BEST EXPAND THE OPPORTUNITIES<br />
FOR EXTRA-MURAL DEGREE COURSES OF UNIVERSITY STANDARD AND<br />
RAISE GENERAL EDUCATIONAL LEVELS IN THE COMMUNITY,<br />
FINALLY, WE HAVE DECIDED TO TACKLE THE REALITIES OF COST<br />
ESCALATION IN FINANCING TERTIARY EDUCATION, IN TAKING OVER THE<br />
FINANCIAL COMMITMENTS OF THE STATES, THE GOVERNMENT WILL, FROM<br />
THE BEGINNING OF NEXT YEAR, PROVIDE FOR ADJUSTMENTS TO APPROVED<br />
PROGRAMS OF EXPENDITURE, THIS WILL TAKE INTO ACCOUNT COST<br />
VARIATIONS IN BOTH CAPITAL AND RECURRENT EXPENDITURE WHICH WERE<br />
NOT ALLOWED WHEN THE PROGRAMS WERE ORIGINALLY ADOPTED, </p>
<p>10<br />
THIS WILL BE ESPECIALLY IMPORTANT IN TIMES OF RAPIDLY RISING<br />
COSTS. IMIGHT MENTION HERE THAT I AM AWARE OF YOUR OWN PRESENT<br />
DIFFICULTIES WITH RECURRENT FUNDS. MR. REECE WROTE TO ME A<br />
FEW DAYS AGO ABOUT THIS PROBLEM. kE HAS SENT A DETAILED<br />
STATEMENT TO THE COMMISSION ON ADVANCED EDUCATION TO SUPPORT<br />
HIS REQUEST FOR ADDITIONAL FUNDS. IASSURE YOU THAT MR. BEAZLEY<br />
WILL BE LOOKING CLOSELY AND SYMPATHETICALLY AT YOUR NEEDS.<br />
IBELIEVE I CAN CLAIM THAT WITHIN A YEAR OF TAKING OFFICE<br />
THE NEW AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT HAS TRANSFORMED THE PROSPECTS<br />
FOR EDUCATION IN THIS COUNTRY. ACROSS THE WHOLE FIELD OF<br />
LEARNING AND INSTRUCTION PRE-SCHOOLS, PRIMARY SCHOOLS,<br />
SECONDARY SCHOOLS, TECHNICAL AND FURTHER EDUCATION, UNIVERSITIES<br />
AND COLLEGES OF ADVANCED EDUCATION WE HAVE ACTED WITH SPEED<br />
AND DETERMINATION TO RAISE STANDARDS AND INCREASE OPPORTUNITIES.<br />
A LONG ERA OF NEGLECT AND IMPVERISHMENT IS AT AN END; BARRIERS<br />
OF PRIVILEGE AND INEQUALITY ARE BEING STEADILY REMOVED. YOU KNOW<br />
OF THE ATTEMPTS BY OUR OPPONENTS TO USE THEIR POWER IN THE SENATE<br />
TO FRUSTRATE AND DEL. AY THIS PROCESS. THEY HAVEN'T THE COURAGE<br />
TO BLOCK OUR REFORMS OUTRIGHT. THEY PREFER TO HINDER US BY<br />
NIT-PICKING AND STEALTH. ITELL YOU THEY WILL NOT SUCCEED.<br />
THEY WILL NOT SUCCEED BECAUSE THEY KNOW, AS WE KNOW, THAT THE NEW<br />
DEAL IN EDUCATION, THE NEW VISTA OF OPPORTUNITY WE ARE OFFERING<br />
To AUSTRALIAN CHILDREN TO ALL CHILDREN, WHATEVER THE BACKGROUNDS,<br />
THEIR INCOMES, THEIR ENVIRONMENT HAS THE WHOLEHEARTED SUPPORTAND<br />
ENDORSEMENT OF THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE. IAPPLAUD THE WORK OF<br />
THIS FINE COLLEGE AND OTHERS LIKE IT. YOU ARE AN ESSENTIAL PART<br />
OF OUR PLANS TO RAISE THE EDUCATIONAL HORIZONS OF THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
