<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1072</transcript-id>
    <title>EIGHTH MINING AND METALLURGICAL CONGRESS BANQUET HELD AT THE ROYALE SALLROOM, EXHIBITION BUILDING, MELBOURNE,  2ND  MARCH, 1965  SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/03/1965</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001072_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
6 5/ 0 39<br />
EIGHTH MINI14G A'IND METALLURGICAL CONGRESS BANQUET<br />
HELJD AT TIM,~ R~ OYAL2I~ BALLROOM, EXHIBITION iBUIi DING,<br />
MELBOURNE 2ND MARCH, 126~<br />
Sjeh h rm iitr h lit. Hon. proberMezs<br />
Sir, Your Excellencies, ladies and Gentlemen<br />
I think I ought to begin by making a rew, small,<br />
light-hearted protests. Our great host has complimented the<br />
Governor on having been Antarctica. I would go there tonight<br />
with the greatest pleasure in the world. ( Applause) 1Why he<br />
should be given marks for going there out of a sense of public<br />
duty while I lwould go there out of sheer necessity, I don't<br />
quite understand, ( Laughter) but between you and me, Sir, I<br />
would like to be there.<br />
There is one other little preliminary observation<br />
I would like to make. Your President made yesterday a somewhat<br />
ill-reported but remarkable Presidential address and, unlike<br />
many of you I have read it. ( Laughter) ( Applause). And I read<br />
it with loving care. And in the course of it he spoke about<br />
the constant need for research and developmeni.<br />
Now I agree with this I am a great believer in<br />
this, but while I still have it in mind, what I suggest to<br />
you scientific people who insist on innocent victims wearing<br />
this uniform ( Laughter applause) iLsthat you conduct a small<br />
research into delivering mankind from the constriction of stiff<br />
collars and stiff shirts. ( Applause) And if you want to give a<br />
small prize for the winner of this piece of research, I will<br />
willingly contribute œ-A100. ( Laughter)<br />
Now I've got that off my chest my wife had to get<br />
it on to my chest it is an awful business to be the wife of<br />
a bad-tempered husband who has to wear these stupid things, but<br />
it's almost as bad to have to wear them. However, you've<br />
registered the point haven't you, sir? Old Menzies promised<br />
: CLOO as a prize for ilhe iman who could discover how to get rid<br />
of them, and I hope all you gentlemen sitting there comfortably<br />
and sneakingly in your black ties ( Laughter) will support me.<br />
Now, Sir, when I found that I had been once more<br />
cast in the role of proposing the toast and I now do so but I<br />
will come back to it a little later to the Mining 2nd Metallurgical<br />
Industry of Australia and New Zealand, I said " Oh dear<br />
me, what have I let mayself in for?" And I was reminded that<br />
twelve years ago, in this very place, I had let myself in for it.<br />
Mind you, it was a better time of thle year, the temperature was<br />
milder it was then characteristic Melbourne weather, and I<br />
made a speech. W~ ell, as my speeches are not written, I demanded<br />
of my long-suffering staff that they should produce a copy of<br />
what I said twelve years ago on the remote chance that one of<br />
you old boys might remember what I then said, And they had no<br />
notes but they said, hhIt's published in a book" and so I looked<br />
up one of those expensive volumes that you sent me later on and<br />
there it was full of misprints ( Laughter) but still, I got a<br />
rough idea of what I had said on that occasion. And having<br />
amended the misprints I find and this is perhaps something that<br />
I want to repeat tonight that I had said this e / 2 </p>
<p>2-<br />
" The best thing that could happen to this<br />
world is that all the great specialists in<br />
specialised knowledge should work inside their<br />
specialty, should work and sweat so that humanity<br />
may know all that there is to be known in that<br />
field, but that they should live ( they the<br />
specialists who work in their specialty) they<br />
should live outside of it, that they should<br />
recognise that there is a life outside the work<br />
that i-re do day by day in the course of our own<br />
special a ctivities." ( Applause)<br />
Now, I venture to say that that was one of my<br />
better remarks, suitably edited after I read the book. You know,<br />
" he lives for hs work" is a good phrase, pointing to the<br />
contrast with the clock-watcher, but that we should live only<br />
in our specialties is, I rather thin%, one of the disasters of<br />
the century. I've been around a good deal for a long time and<br />
have had a good deal to do with our relations with other<br />
countries and the various crises of the world and more and more<br />
I find myself believing that one of our disasters is that the<br />
cleverer we become, the more scientific we become, on the whole<br />
the less civilised we've become.<br />
And the reason is perfectly clear. You may be,<br />
as our President is, a tremendous expert in a great dynamic<br />
field of knowledge. You may be, as so many of you are, great<br />
exflperts in these fields. And yet if, to you the only thing<br />
that matters is that your scientific and applied scientific<br />
skill should be of the highest order and what happens in the<br />
world doesn't matter, then the end will be trouble and disater.<br />
Give me somebody who works in his specialty and<br />
who manages to live outside of it you see the points I am<br />
making to you because while the world has an enormous demand<br />
for skill, for science, for expertise and this demand becomes<br />
more and more satisfied, the world has much greater demand for<br />
wisdom, for understanding, for a belief in other people as well<br />
as in ourselves, and therefore this is one of those cases, Mr.<br />
President, on which we have an opportunity of thinking about<br />
these things and indeed, Sir, I am not being very original<br />
because you, Mr, President, made a speech last night which on<br />
its merits should have been published verbatim in every newspaper<br />
in Australia ( applause) because it was informed, it was wise<br />
it was realistic and it was optimistic, Now mark those last<br />
two words realistic and optimistic,<br />
You know that meidncholy fellow you encounter<br />
in the club armchair whether it is in Kalgoorlie or in Melbourne<br />
you know who says, "' Jell, you know old man, Ilra a realist,"<br />
meaning that he's steeped in gloom ( Laughter). " I'm a realist"....<br />
well., now let's have reoalists by all means but let them be like<br />
your President, optimists, because that's the best kind of<br />
relaist, and let us remember in Australia in particular i dont<br />
profess to speak so much on behalf of New Zealand, although New<br />
Zealand is here and New Zealand is a great country and is in the<br />
fullest sense our blood brother ( Applause) but let us recall<br />
I won't be long let us recall what has happened as a result of<br />
the work of realists who face the facts but who are at the same<br />
time optimists who conquered the future. a so so s / 3 </p>
<p>-3<br />
Well$ I can remember when a serious time many<br />
of you may with a stroke of fortune when I came back into<br />
office at the end of 194+ 9. It was like the old scene in the<br />
" Tale of Two Cities" do you remember othen the slogan was<br />
" Recalled to Life" and Dr. Nanette came out of his cell and<br />
came back to London? I was " recalled to -life" if that is<br />
the right expression at the end of 194+ 9.<br />
All I viant to do is to remind you of the fact that<br />
at that time there was a fixed belief, based on that most<br />
pregnable of all foundations, the views of the experts, that<br />
our supplies of iron ore were very limited, tha t we must never<br />
allow one ounce to go out of the country. This was at the end<br />
of 191+ 9. As for oil and natural gas an expression which I<br />
must explain to some of our wives relates to something that<br />
comes out of the ground ( Laughter) as for oil and -natural<br />
gas, the whole of life was a big query, wasn't it? People who<br />
talked about looking for oil and who went on looking for oil<br />
were regarded as amiable lunatics, and today coal,*., coal,..<br />
When I came back into office, wie were importing coal importing<br />
coal and as the charter party rate at that time wias a little<br />
high, -, re paid if this is the right expression Sir we paid<br />
through the nose for the coal that we got, and today we're a<br />
large exporter of coal,<br />
Tin production was failing, and today it has all the<br />
signs of vivacity, Bauxite was imported and today, my distinguished<br />
friend on the right the President, has only two embarrassments<br />
about bauxite. Neither of them relates to the quantity of<br />
bauxite in Australia, One of them relates to how you get the<br />
cash in to develop the wretched stuff and the ot'ner is what you<br />
do with it when you have it. ( Laughter) But look, bauxite<br />
look at Lindsay Clark down there, he knows all about this but<br />
really it is hard to remember, isn't it, that in 194+ 9 bauxite<br />
was a somewhat rare imported commodity.<br />
Now there are dozens of other examples but I've<br />
mentioned these, Sir, in order to remind ourselves that this<br />
dramatic change has occurred in Australia not because of me;<br />
I don't claim to h, 1ve anything to do with it but it has<br />
occurred in Australia because there were optimists of energy,<br />
of drive and of confidence who translated all these things<br />
into achievement, Therefore ( applause) perhaps all I need<br />
to say is this. I was born there's no secret about my age at the<br />
end of 1891+, and before long whisked off into an old mining<br />
city I mentioned this twelve years ago but you've forgotten<br />
an old mining city called Ballarat, and to us in those days,<br />
to us small boys in those days, mining was a sort of memorial<br />
of the past. There were old poppet heads, there were old<br />
mullock heaps, and in an adventurous mood we would crawl along<br />
old drives and suddenly discover we were about to fall in and<br />
be lost forever and then realising our responsibility to<br />
history, we came back. ( Laughter) But there was Ballarat<br />
the old mining city the old gold mining city and so one became<br />
accustomed at tha,:; t time to say, " Yes, Australia " I'm speaking<br />
about Victoria nowr in particular, Henry. I won't make any<br />
reference to what happened in Sydney at a certain stage because<br />
this is indelicate, but in Victoria the pastoral age, the gold<br />
mining age, the agricultural age, the manufacturing age, all<br />
these have followed each other and each of them has brought 0mO@* 6O0 0/ </p>
<p>its own wave of population into Australia. But when the<br />
historian sets himself out to organise this thing in his own<br />
mind, I think that he will say that the age that intervened<br />
between your last conference and this one is the most dynamic<br />
and productive age in the history of our nation. At any rate,<br />
I believe so and therefore I say so.<br />
One other thing only, Sir, I w. ould like to say.<br />
This Conference is a conference which I think more than any<br />
other in Australia or in New Zealand is unique in its collation<br />
of practical kcno-. Iledge and its dissemination of practical<br />
knowledge. I had a look through the book of the wvords<br />
the programme and really, gentlemen, all I can say to you is<br />
that people who do as much work as you do every day on<br />
practical matters would never qualify for a convention in San<br />
Francisco. D. o you know what I mean?<br />
This is a remarkable event and a remarkable conference<br />
and I was delighted, Sir, when I heard or read in your speech<br />
( because I didn't hear it) your admirable point which we all<br />
need to remember that we mustntt go in too much for dividing<br />
things into the black and the white, we mustn't go in too much<br />
for the false dichotomy to which we are all rather prone, we<br />
mustn't say " Either you're for wool or you're for artificial<br />
fibres*" W~ e mustn't say, " Either youtre for coal or you're<br />
for oil or natural gas". What we have to understand more and<br />
more and this I thought, Sir, was the keynote of your speechis<br />
that in this modern world we are all whether we like it or<br />
not, interdependent interdependent internally, " Wooll<br />
artificial fibres, natural gas and oil coal Australia, the<br />
new world, the new nations we are interdependent and we will<br />
do very badly if in the course of our-work we don't recognise<br />
this fact and realise that what happens in the new ' vrorld in<br />
the new nations, politically immature, economically immature,<br />
will not only determine their future but may very ea-sily<br />
determine ours. And therefore, Sir, I want to say that it is a rare<br />
pleasure to me to be speaking for a little while at a conference<br />
which I believe is directing its mind to some of the greatest<br />
problems that we have not only here but all around the Commonwealth,<br />
and I would like to compliment them on having been given<br />
such magnificent leadership as you have already given them.<br />
( Applause) Therefore, Sir, to come back to the right form of<br />
the words, I propose, ladies and gentlemen, the health now<br />
lot's get this right of the mining and metallurgical<br />
remember the trouble I had about pronouncing thiat word the<br />
mining and metallurgical industry of Australia and New Zealand, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
