<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>15139</transcript-id>
    <title>Press Conference, Hobart</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/10/2007</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Ladies and gentlemen on behalf of the entire nation I want to say how saddened I am by the news of the death of an Australian solider in Afghanistan. We send our love and sympathy to his family. We know it is a time of great grief for them and we offer our prayers and our support to them and to the other loved ones of this soldier. It's a reminder to all of us that the men and women of the ADF who go overseas in our name put their lives on the line to preserve our way of life. </p>
<p>The operation in Afghanistan involves resisting brutal terrorism, it's a just cause and this soldier was part of an Australian contribution to that just cause. But that in no way lessens the loss and the bereavement and the grief that would be felt by his mates in his unit, other members of the Australian Army and the broader Australian Defence Force family. It's a close knit family, they look after their own, they care for their fellow soldiers and sailors and airmen and at a time like this the solidarity that they all feel towards each other will be very strong. </p>
<p>The Chief of the Defence Force has outlined the brief circumstances and I won't add to what he said. The family has requested that the details not be made known at this time and that wish must naturally be respected. Another soldier was seriously injured but the injuries were not life threatening and he is being well cared for. As to arrangements regarding the repatriation of the body and the like, that is being handled by the Defence Force and it will answer details concerning it. But can I simply say again this is a sad day for the Australian Army, it's a sad day for the Australian community. Somebody who loses his or her life on service for our country is owed a special respect and a special debt of gratitude that can never be fully repaid. Thank you.</p>
<p>[ends]   </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
