<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1673</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: STTE VISIT BY THE PRESIDENT OF ITALY TO AUSTRLIA : 25 SEPTEMBER - 1 OCTOBER 1967 - JOINT COMMUNIQUE</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/10/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001673.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS: STATE VISIT BY THE PRESIDENT OF ITA LY<br />
TO AUSTRALIA 25 SEPTEMBER 1 OCTOBER,<br />
1967<br />
JOINT COMMUNIQUE<br />
At the invitation of the Commonwealth of Australia, the President<br />
of the Republic of Italy, the Honourable -GiuseppeS aragat, accompanied by<br />
the Minister of Foreign ffairs, the Honourable Amintcre Fanfan., raid a<br />
State visit to Australia from 25 September until 1 October, 1967. staying in<br />
Canberra, Melbourne and Sydney.<br />
In Canberra, President Saragat was received by the Governor-<br />
General, Lord Casey, and had meetings with the Prime Minister, Mr Harold<br />
Holt, other members of the Australian Government, and the Leader of the<br />
Opposition, Mr Gough V,! hitlam.<br />
The Italian President was Guest of Honour at a dinner given by the<br />
Governor-General and at a State function at Parliament House, at which the<br />
President delivered an address. The President was host at a dinner at the<br />
Italian Embassy. In Melbourne and Sydney, the President attended functions given<br />
by the State Governors and was tendered Civic Receptions at the Town Halls<br />
of both cities. . i'hile in Melbourne, the President visited the Royal<br />
Agricultural Show. In both capitals, the President addressed large gatherings<br />
of t i Italian communities, bringing them the greetings of Italy.<br />
The Italian Foreign Minister, Mr Fanfani, had political talks<br />
with the Australian Minister for External Affairs, Mr Hasluck, and also had<br />
a meeting with senior members of the Australian Cabinet. Major international<br />
problems of the moment were reviewed in an atmosphere of frank cordiality.<br />
In the course of these conversations, the Italian and ustralian<br />
leaders reviewed problems concerning the role of the United Nations in the<br />
peaceful solution of international disputes in accordance with the Charter,<br />
co-operation in economic and social fields and assistance to developing<br />
countries. Emphasis was placed on the responsibility of the industrialized<br />
countries to assist developing countries and to encourage a more satisfactory<br />
balance in technological progress. Both parties reaffirmed their common<br />
aim to continue endeavours towards the progressive realization of disarmament<br />
and the non-proliferation of nuclear arms.<br />
Mr Fanfani outlined general aspects of action being taken by the<br />
Italian Government towards the maintenance of peace and security within the<br />
framework of its alliances and towards the realization of European unity.<br />
He also described Italian viewpoints on the process of European integration,<br />
together with the prospects of Britain's entering into the European Economic<br />
Community. Mr Hasluc, described the Australian Government's position in<br />
relation to South-East Asia and the Facific, and to the tensions existing in<br />
that area. Developments in Viet Nam were the subject of an exchange of<br />
views, particular attention being given to the present situation ' n South Viet<br />
Nam. The importance of early progress towards any possible negotiations<br />
for a just and peaceful solution was also considered. It was agreed that such<br />
a solution might be sought on the basis of the Geneva Agreements and with / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
the possible assistance, direct or indirect, of thb-United-Nations.<br />
Special consideration was g. ven-to-the question of Italian m. gration<br />
to Australia. The substantial contribution made by Italian migrants to the<br />
development of Australia's economy and population was highly appreci. ated<br />
by the Australian Government. Both countries indicated their desire that<br />
co-operation in this field between Italy and Australia should continue and<br />
develop still further . n the best possible conditions. Therefore the two<br />
Ministers of Foreign Affairs and the Australian Minister for Immigration<br />
signed an agreement on migration ai. d exchanged notes on an arrangemeqt<br />
for assisted migration. The agreement, which covers a wide field, provides<br />
a continuing basis for Italian migrants to participate in and to benefit<br />
substantially from A ustralia's future development.<br />
The imoortance of trade between the two countries was emphasised<br />
in the course of the talks. It was recognised that trade exchanges between<br />
the countries have been developing steadily and that there would be great<br />
value in encouraging further improz-nent of trade and economic relati ons.<br />
In this connection a Memorandum of Understanding, governing the health<br />
requirements for the ' mportation of Australian meat into Italy, was<br />
initialled. The possibility of co-operation in the industrial field was also<br />
raised. It was noted with satisfaction that there is a growing interest in<br />
Australia in the Italian language and culture, and both parties were n<br />
agreement on the value of increased collaboration in matters of science and<br />
culture. The proposal of the Australian Government to establish a<br />
Consulate-General in Milan was welcomed on the Italian part.<br />
The Italian and Australian Ministers agreed that the exchangeof<br />
views had offered an e,, xcellent occasion to consolidate the friendshi. p and<br />
co-operation exist-. ng between Australia and Italy, and it was felt that it<br />
would prove of mutual benefit to increase contact at all levels between the<br />
represenatives of the two countries.<br />
A formal invitation to visit Italy at a mutually convenient time<br />
was extended to the Frime Minister and the Minister for External Affairs,<br />
and was cordially accepted.<br />
FRIME MINISTER'S CFFICE.<br />
CANBERRA. 3C'th September, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
