<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7089</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE, KING DAVID HOTEL, JERUSALEM 28 JANUARY 1987</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/01/1987</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007089.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
) ZWAST LI( A<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE, KING DAVID HOTEL, JERUSALEM<br />
-2"--ANUAR-Y--l-93-7--<br />
E 0 E -PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: Why d: you support the concept of the Palestinian<br />
PM: I think it would repay you see exactly what I said before you frame the<br />
question. What I said is. that Australia sipport s the rights of the<br />
Palestinians to self-determination including should it be their choice<br />
to a state of their own and I alm said from discussions that I ha'ie had<br />
since I left Canberra those di Ecussions that I held in Jordan, it seemed to<br />
me that it was the view of.. tho se involved that the mo E likely outcome<br />
would be processes that could be put underway would be confederation with<br />
the state of Jordan. So the important point is the right of a people<br />
to self-determination. And I think one has got to include withini that<br />
right the concept of that possibility that I say on the best information.<br />
available to me that the exercie of that process, it seems to me, would be<br />
mo st likely to be a confederation with Jordan.<br />
JOURNALIST: What will you be taking back to Australia from this<br />
visit to Israel?<br />
PM: The visit to Israel of course will rmt e'something in inlation.<br />
It will be a part of a total itinerary. And m I make the point that the<br />
impressions I have from Israel will be part of a total mosaic of impressions,<br />
if you like. As far as I can isolate Israel it will be this that I<br />
am obviously impressed with the physical development that h-s<br />
taken nlace since I was last here in 1980. Also, there is the<br />
impression I have, hard to quantify, that there is a growing<br />
realisation that Israel is living in an environment markedly<br />
different than that which characterised my earlier visits<br />
beginning in 1971. There is an important point involved here.<br />
When I first came in 1971 and through the 1970s, Israel had<br />
the belief and on the evidence the justified belief that its<br />
neighbours sought its elimination. And that informed the<br />
thinking of Israel, it informed-its attitudes to how-it-should<br />
regard the occupied territories. It informed it attitude to what<br />
should be the position or status with its neighbouring states.<br />
In 1987 the situation has changed in that the world, as I said<br />
last night, has come to understand and accept, some albeit<br />
reluctantly, but nevertheless the world accepts now that Israel<br />
is not going to disappear. Israel is a continuing part of the<br />
Middle East scene. And therefore, the attitude of the 70s which<br />
were based upon having to belligerently fight against the position<br />
which said we are going to obliterate Israel. It is now different<br />
There is a greater obligation to investigate the processes of<br />
discussion with neighbouring states who do accept the right<br />
of Israel to exist. It is obviously difficult to quantify that<br />
sort of thing. But nevertheless that is the considerable impressi<br />
that I have and I think the obligation upon Israel and upon </p>
<p>PM cont: everyone is to build upon that changed tractual situation<br />
the acceptance of ISrael's right to exist behind secure and<br />
recognised boundaries. It is going to be complex, difficult and<br />
I think a prolonged process. But it must, I think, and is beginning<br />
to inform Israel in its attitude to its neighbours and it must<br />
also inform its attitudes towards the occupied territories.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke did you receive the impression in Jordan<br />
that King Hussein was interested in meeting<br />
PM: In the United States?<br />
-JOURNALIST: . Or anywhere? -7<br />
PM: No, I wasn'tgiventhe impression that King Hussein was_<br />
wishing to meet them in the United States or anywhere at this<br />
point in the immediate period that you referred to. But I had<br />
the overwhelming impression that King Hussein was unqualifiedly<br />
committed to pursuing the processes for a peaceful resolution<br />
of the Israeli/ Arab dispute. There is simply no question about<br />
the commitment of King Hussein to that goal, that objective, and<br />
it is therefore important that Israel and others seek. to build<br />
upon that fact. And if the building blocks, the initial building<br />
blocks, are created then it is inevitable that the sort of meeting<br />
that you refer to will take place.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, when you set out on this visit did you<br />
hope that Israel might demonstrate a more flexible attitude<br />
PM: I haven't finished my discussions in Israel yet. I have<br />
tDheipsu tye vePrniimneg Mtio nihsavtee r lSehnigmtohny Pdeirsecsu ssanido nsI wmieteht tahgea inF orweiitghn PMriinmies tMeirn isatnder<br />
Shamir tomorrow morning before I leave .~ rael. So I am not forming<br />
any final conclusions before I have completed those meetings.<br />
JOURNALIST: What role do you see for the PLO in the negotiations<br />
and secondly why has the Australian Government refused to<br />
allow PM: Let's pick up the last one first and could be easily disposed of.<br />
I had a brief discussion with the Foreign Minister about that question<br />
before I left and his views, subsequently explained in more detail,<br />
is that he has had very short notice from the United Nations about<br />
this meeting and it was his view, which I accepted, " that it was not<br />
appropriate this time that the meeting should. And he made the point<br />
-that no question of applications in regard to any individuals had been<br />
made in the circumstances of that brief period to which I refer. And<br />
so that issue was simply not on the agenda, it is not significant. </p>
<p>PM cont: Now let me go to the first part of your question which<br />
is very important. Your question for those who may not have heard<br />
it was if I get it correctly was " what role do I see for the PLO<br />
in the negotiation process". That is a very important question.<br />
Let me first of all put to you what the position of my Government<br />
has been. That is that we, as a Government, would not recognise<br />
the PLO in the formal sense of recognition while it continues not<br />
to recognise the right of Israel to exist that did not mean that<br />
there were not contacts between representatives of the Australian<br />
Government and PLO in various diplomatic positions and postings<br />
and functions around the world. And we said in that same context<br />
quiDieoVifoi isytfe -c~ apaci ty of the PLO to have a role in these<br />
processes would be the greater should it recognise the existence<br />
and--the right of Israel-to--exi-s-t------I-f--I may -take the---<br />
opportunity of that question which is I think is-a fundamental*<br />
question of developing this point which to some extent arose<br />
romthevery--use ful-discus sion s-I-had-this--morn-ing-wi th-a -numb-er<br />
of Palestinians. Those that I met were Mayor Freij of Bethlehem,<br />
Dr Ghazaleh from Gaza, Mr Kuttas from Jerusalem and Mr Nuseibeh<br />
also from Jerusalem. This question, of course, arose in those<br />
discussions. The point I made, which I think is of critical<br />
relevance, is this that the attitude of both sides, if you like<br />
Israel and the PLO, to inform out of the situations of the<br />
past by definition. But the realities in ' 87 are different but<br />
what we cannot seem to get is a statement from both sides which<br />
in words puts what I think they believe the facts to be. I believe<br />
that the PLO understand, not merely that Israel exists but. that<br />
it is going to continue to exist as an indecendent and viable<br />
state in this region. I believe it understands that but it hasn't<br />
in a formal sense said so. On the other side, I think that Israel<br />
knows that whether they like it or not in a broadly representative<br />
sense not merely of the PalestiniAns in the West Bank and the Gaza<br />
but g -iven the Palestinians' diaspora that there-is no-organisation<br />
more than the PLO which can speak for that. Palestinian diaspora.<br />
So the important thing seems to me to be to get the two sides to<br />
say what they in fact recognise. And it seems to me if that could<br />
be done then this large primary hurdle could be overcome, that is<br />
that there can't be discussions with the PLO, that they can't be<br />
part of the process. If the realities in the minds could be<br />
translated into the words then it seems to me the way is clear<br />
for the PLO to be part of the processes of the discussions.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke Palestinians although Australia<br />
might not be able to play a role in the macro sense there may<br />
be a role for you and if so how do you feel about it?<br />
_ PM: There was a view I think it. is.. f air to -say that-Australia--<br />
perhaps could play some role in the broader issue and as well in<br />
the particular issue to which you refer. And to what my response<br />
is as it has been from the beginning, we haven't come to be a<br />
broker, we haven't come to be a mediator and we don't put ourselves<br />
in that position now. Simply, that I have said that if there are<br />
things that we can do then we stand ready to do it.-Already to<br />
this point what I have attempted to do is to convey as strongly<br />
as I can to the Israeli leadership the firm impressions I have<br />
about the attitude of the King-and the leadership in Jordan. I have<br />
done that. I will, certainly in the discussions I am still to have / 4 I </p>
<p>PM cont: here in Israel put some of the things I have adumbrated<br />
here to you in this conference. I will do that in more detail.<br />
And when I come back from Switzerland to Egypt I will put the same<br />
sorts of things there and anything that comes out of my discussions<br />
with the Israeli leadership. I repeat I don't want to exaggerate<br />
what may be involved in that and what may come from it but it just<br />
seems to me that anyone who is in the position and we, for better<br />
or worse, are in the position, but anyone who is the position to<br />
convey information to try and clarify attitudes, tto open up<br />
possibilities should do that. That is what I will do.<br />
J0UhRN-A1-TST-Mr-Hawk, in--re-lation-to--the-prart~ icular-subtect<br />
Jordanians on exactly this matter that the Israelis will<br />
have to change some of their views have to change?__<br />
PM: I have already canvassed basically in the answer I gave before.<br />
Nery. y-briefly let me-emphasise the-points--The attitudeof-the<br />
Israelis as of today has necessarily been informed by the historical<br />
past. That historical past was to a large extent characterised by<br />
a non-acceptance of Israel's right to exist by the Arab states and<br />
by the PLO. As I have tried to say, I think the realities now are<br />
different. But whether it is reluctantly or not, nevertheless, there<br />
is an acceptance of Israel's right to exist. Israel needs, if you<br />
like, to be reassured but to accept that fact and from that new fact<br />
itself be prepared to accelerate the processes of discussion.<br />
JOURNALIST: any kind of expressed message from King Hussein<br />
to Mr Shamir confederation rather than federation.<br />
PM: In answer to the first question. I didn't bring a specific<br />
message in terms of the proposal. But what I was asked to bring and<br />
did bring was a clear enunciation of the Jordanian attitude and<br />
commitment. And that I have done; And secondly, no the concept<br />
of confederation in the sense that-you imention was not mentioned.<br />
It was not put. It was in terms of a federation of West Bank/ East<br />
Bank. JOURNALIST: PLO Israel has a right to exist<br />
( inaudible)<br />
PM: I can combine those two questions into one. They are really<br />
two parts of the one question. I don't say this with any intention<br />
of being rude. If you had the opportunity of listening to all I have<br />
said and read what I have said what I have put is that there can't<br />
be a legitimate expectation of Israel to proceed to any commitment<br />
of the sort that I have talked about with the PLO unless there is<br />
a clear recognition by the PLO of Israel's right to exist. That<br />
is the formulation that I have put. So your hypothetical quesdtionis<br />
not relevant to me because the position I have put is based upon<br />
the need for the PLO to recognise Israel's right to exist. And it<br />
is importantto understand the reciprocal of that. The reciprocal<br />
of that is that the PLO reoognises Israel's right to exist then it<br />
seems to me there is a corresponding obligation on Israel to treat<br />
with the PLO as part of the negotiating process.<br />
I' 4 </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, what approaches has the Israel Government<br />
made to you Soviet Jewry<br />
PM: Mr Shamir asked me to continue the efforts that I and my<br />
Government and Bill Hayden, my Foreign Minister, have made<br />
on behalf both on the requests of the Refusniks and also of the<br />
conditons for Soviet Jewry within the Soviet Union. And I, of<br />
course, said to him that I would do that. And I have just<br />
recently before coming to this conference had the very moving<br />
experience of meeting with representatives of the group who call<br />
themselves the Mothers of the Refuseniks who have given me the most<br />
_ moving,. and indee-d-tr-aqgi-cs. t. orie s-conc-erningthei irnext-o fkin-,<br />
their children, who want to leave the Soviet Union and come to<br />
join them here. And if one had needed, which in a sense I didn't,<br />
any added incentive then meet-ing these-women--would h-ave -provided-it--<br />
And I have also indicated to them that I would continue to press the<br />
case in general and in this case that I refer to their particular<br />
case.<br />
JOURNALIST: How do you see a situation where a representative<br />
of the Australian Government might meet with PLO officers to<br />
convey the views that you have in this news conference.<br />
PM: The position of the Government as publicly expressed and put<br />
by me and which I repeat is that we wouldn't be engaging in a process<br />
which involved formal recognition of the PLO unless and until there<br />
was that recognition by the PLO of Israel's right to exist. obviously,<br />
this is a matter that have talked about with the people I met this<br />
morning. It was the sort of thing that informed part of my discussions<br />
before I leave Israel, that is trying to get this reciprocal<br />
recognition, that is recognition by the PLO of Israel and its<br />
right to exist. And in a sense contemporaneously to that, an<br />
acceptance of the obligation on the part of Israel to deal with<br />
the PLO in the circumstances that-the PLO-recognise Israel. And of<br />
course, in that context it could be a si~ dation if the people wanted<br />
it could be appropriate in those circumstances for represenhiatives of<br />
the Australian Government to meet with the PLO.<br />
JOURNALIST: Did you read the recommendations of the Menzies<br />
Report and what is your attitude to its implementation.<br />
PM: I have had that question put to me before but I am quite happy<br />
to answer it again. Yes, I have-seen the recommendations-of the<br />
Menzies Report. But I make these points. I don't run a dictatorship<br />
in Australia. What the processes are there is that the Government,<br />
the Cabinet, will consider the Menzies Report and the light of<br />
consideration of the Cabinet the decision will be made as to how<br />
we will give effect to those recommendations. And that -process--wil-l--<br />
be undertaken quite quickly.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, how will you go about pressing the particular<br />
cases that were raised with you by the Mothers of the Refuseniks.<br />
PM: There will be two categories of approach. There was at least<br />
one of the circumstances that was raised which had a sense of absolute<br />
immediacy in that one of the women there has a mother who is dying of<br />
*-cancer in the Soviet Union and is seeking an entry visa -it-. is the<br />
/ 6 </p>
<p>PM cont: other way round to the Soviet Union to be able to see and<br />
be with her mother before she dies. Now obviously in that case I<br />
will try and accelerate an immediate representation of that case.<br />
In regard to the others, it will probably take a little bit more<br />
time as to how it is best to make that representation within the<br />
broader framework of our contacts with the Soviet Union.<br />
JOURNALIST: economic relations direct air links..<br />
PM: On the air links, the position is very simply this that this<br />
matter has been raised more recently in Australia. It was raised<br />
~ dii-ring the iEif6f lid Pi,&amp; Yd MH~ ifzog, and -pulEIff6Thim<br />
and I have said this again to Mr Shamiir and his Ministers yesterday<br />
-that in Australia we-have-an--arms-length -elIat ionsh ipbetween. Qan tas,<br />
our national airline,' and the Government. And I have indicated to<br />
Qantas that if the proposal was put to them that they should consider<br />
in the-normal terms--that the-question of--air -links -with--any--coun-t-ry--<br />
was considered. And that is what can happen. We have put no bar<br />
upon Qantas considering it in commercial terms. On the second questio<br />
of a free trade area. This was not raised in the discussions yesterda<br />
I see that it has received some currency in the press. But we were<br />
more practical in an immediate sense in our discussions yesterday<br />
what we agreed was that there could be to the mutual benefit of<br />
Israel and Australia greater cooperation in economic areas, and<br />
technology. And so we have set up a working party. We have agreed<br />
to the establishment of a working party between our two countries to<br />
examine the possibilities of further cooperation in the economic<br />
and the trading areas. As well, of course, you will recall that<br />
yesterday our Ambassador and the Minister here signed, in the<br />
presence of Mr Shamir and myself, a memorandum of understanding<br />
which provides for greater cooperation in the civil technological<br />
and science area, particularly for economic and social purposes.<br />
JOURNALIST:, Prime Minister, in your distussions this morning with<br />
the Palestinians oppressed what steps are there that your<br />
Government can take to address any human rights violations<br />
PM: On the first point, yes there were propositions put to me about<br />
oppression. Secondly, I said to them alright you give us the details<br />
of these things and we will be prepared to put those details to the<br />
Israeli authorities and we will be pleased to hear what they have<br />
to say about them.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you plan to fund any development projects in the<br />
West Bank and Gaza and secondly what is your view. on the<br />
PM: On the firstpoint... What. I said to the King-and the Prime_<br />
Minister of Jordan was thaat firstly I responded positively to their<br />
request that we should give moral and political support to the West<br />
Bank economic development. I gave that immediately because it is<br />
within my capacity as Prime Minister to make the decision on that<br />
in principle and to convey that to them. I did. They said that they<br />
would appreciate material support. on that point-I said to them that<br />
I would convey that request back to my Ministers and we will give<br />
consideration as to how we may be able to give some assistance to thai<br />
West Bank economic development plan. I think it would be appropriate / 7 </p>
<p>PM cont: to give some assistance. It will be a matter for discus<br />
with my Ministers. On the second.-question about the settlements,<br />
we have made our position clear on that and it follows that we<br />
wou~ d be opposed to new settlements.<br />
JOURNALIST: Lebanon ( inaudible question)-<br />
PM: Not only for that reason but it certainly gives added weight<br />
to our thinking.<br />
JOURNALIST: have you spoken to any of the Lebanon..<br />
I -haven--t--been-to South etalibon. If-f -eries one thing that<br />
is a totally open book here is my itinerary and I haven't been<br />
to south. Lebanon..__<br />
JOURNALIST: inaudible question<br />
PM: I don't. with respect, need any instruction on my moral<br />
or political obligations in regard to Lebanon. I have from before<br />
I was in government and certainly since I have been in government<br />
made the position of my Government crystal clear in regard to<br />
Lebanon. Let me repeat that position so there can be no doubt<br />
about it. Before putting the position it is based upon our oercepl<br />
that the position in Lebanon is one of total tragedy. It is argual<br />
the most tragic situation in the Middle East. And it is a tragedy<br />
beuazi. Se it is compounded by two features. First we have the<br />
interconfessional rivalries and bitterness and fighting and killint<br />
within Lebanon. You have that interconfessional tragedy. And<br />
superimposed, secondly, upon that interconfessional tragedy you<br />
have the intrusion of international forces and international rivali<br />
and that is truly gruesome mixture. And those who suffer and<br />
suffer in horrendous dimensions the casualties are enormousare<br />
the civilian population. So it is on that analysis-the<br />
position of the Australian Government-has been this that the,<br />
authority of the government ofl. Lebanon should be allowed to<br />
extend throughout its territory and that all foreign forces not<br />
in Lebanon at the express request of the government of Lebanon sho,<br />
be withdrawn. That is the objective and that is the policy of<br />
my Government.<br />
JOURNALIST: WThat sort of broad time frame you might have in mind<br />
proposal PLO and Israel do you think from the attitude<br />
or do you think it is the start of a very long process that<br />
you are talking about?<br />
PM: Mike, obviously what one would hope for and desire is that<br />
this sort of process could be very quick. I guess,-realistical. ly-,<br />
given the history of this matter that you can't put a short timetal<br />
on it. All I can say is that I think the facts are clear. There.<br />
many complexities about the Middle East situation. And I have beei<br />
associated with it, I have studied it closely now for getting on<br />
for 20 years, and there are many things that are complex. But the<br />
facts on this particular aspect are clear. And I repeat that I th<br />
that in fact the PLO recognise the state of Israel is here and is<br />
going to continue to be here. On the other hand, I think it is clthat<br />
the Israeli Government understands the fact that the-PLO is t.<br />
only broad organisation that can speak with some authority.<br />
h. </p>
<p>PM cont: Now the question is of trying, as I said, I don't want<br />
to go on again in detail, but the question is translating what<br />
I think are the facts into an expression of public acknowledgement<br />
of those facts. It shouldn't, one would believe, take long for that<br />
to be done. But I can't say whether it will.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you have any idea on how it might be done?<br />
PM: In this sort of area those sort of things can only emerge<br />
through discussions, negotiations, with people of good will and<br />
integrity trying to persuade people to that sort of position. And<br />
say. withiout overstating my role and Australia's role we would<br />
be trying to convey to those concerned that that is a sensible outcome.<br />
JOURNALIST: nadbequestion-<br />
PM: You don't need to wave your pen at me. I am quite capable of<br />
iinderstanding -any-point--th-at-you--are-try ing-ta -make -without<br />
I do happen to know a fair bit about the facts. I do happen to<br />
know about the provision in the covenant and I think it is a<br />
repulsive provision. And I am on record for some 16 years of<br />
saying that so I don't need to establish my credentials to you with<br />
or without pen waving here. I know it and I have said it publicly.<br />
What I am trying to say is that I believe the fact may be reluctantly<br />
arrived at but I believe the fact is that the PLO knows now, in 1987,<br />
that Israel is here, it is going to continue to exist. It is not<br />
going to disappear. And it has to conduct itself on the basis of<br />
that fact. What needs to be-done in the interests both of Israel<br />
and of the Palestinians is that-that understanding, however<br />
reluctantly arrived at, needs to be put publicly so that there<br />
is a clear statement from the PLO that that now in 1987 is their<br />
position.<br />
JOURNALIST: inaudible question<br />
PM: All I am saying is that I will try and convey that poositio-n,<br />
that understanding on my part of what seems to me to be a necessary<br />
and eminently sensible first step. There is the difference betzween<br />
being prepared to convey that and say it both publicly and privately<br />
and annointing oneself as a mediator. And I refuse to do the latter.<br />
I repeat that if, as a result in any way of the involvement that<br />
I have to this point, that those concerned would see that there<br />
is some further role then we would accept that responsibility.<br />
JOURNALIST: former Nazi war criminals..<br />
PM: I have already answered that question. It is a question of<br />
judgment as to whether-1 really answered itor not. . I__. willsim~ ly_<br />
say that the question I was asked before was-about the Menaies<br />
Report. So in case you don't understand that I have answered the<br />
question let me put to you again the facts so that you appreciate<br />
that I have answered. My Foreign Minister, Bill Hayden, was-given<br />
the list in the United States. He brought that back. We then<br />
immediately took action to appoint an investigator, Mr Andrew<br />
Menzies, as to the recommendations to the Government as to what<br />
we should do. We have received the report of Mr Menzies. I have<br />
said in answer to the-previous question that we-will as--a Government<br />
consider that report and make the decisions in the light of that </p>
<p>9.<br />
PM cont: report. I repeat I have answered the question.<br />
JOURNALIST: that Mr Sharpir is a flexible enough leader<br />
could talk to the PLO in the terms taht you are discussing<br />
today? PM: Good try, Greg, but you know that since I have been Prime<br />
Minister I have not in my own country and certainly not when<br />
I am a visitor to another country made observations about the<br />
leadership of that country. And I don't intend to depart from<br />
that practice. I am going to be having further discussions with<br />
~~~ Mtr~ o~ o~ rhaomwia vin Au wil e sa, wih<br />
Mr Peres today. And it is my hope that out of the discussions that<br />
-I have there wil be-the -i nd icat ions of_ t the-sor tpreparedness_<br />
proceed down the sorts of paths that I think are appropriate.<br />
and I will be putting that position both to Mr Peres and Mr Shamir.<br />
JOURNALIST: United States, West Germany and France, all of<br />
which have<br />
PM: Let me make these points. You put the United States and West<br />
Germany and France in the same category of relationship with<br />
Australia. I would like to think it was true. But on the part<br />
of France, at least, there doesn't seem to be the same warmth<br />
towards Australia as there is certainly form the United States.<br />
That may diminish in a week or so's time when we beat them in<br />
the yacht race or on the part of West Germany. It is a rather<br />
peripheral introduction to a reply.-Firstly, let me make-this<br />
point. The Government of Australia is totally opposed to the<br />
tactic and practice of terrorism. It cannot under any circumstances<br />
be a legitimate use of the pursuit of policy by any nation or any<br />
group, it must always be counterpr~ oductive. Now that should make<br />
it clear what I think about what happened. And I repeat, I -take<br />
this opportunity of repeating, our abhorrence at the tactics. Wle<br />
will continue, as a Government, to say that. I believe that<br />
clearly in this region the tactic of terror is a by-product of<br />
this overall dispute here and the Iran/ Iraq dispute. And so if<br />
in this region you are going to create the conditions for the<br />
removal of this tactic and practice of terror you have to attempt<br />
to solve the basic problem. And what I have been concerned about<br />
in my discussions in Jordan and here in Israel and I will be in<br />
Egypt is to try and talk about that basic Israeli/ Arab dispute.<br />
To try in whatever small way we may be able to to help the processes<br />
of resolving that dispute. If you can resolve that dispute you<br />
will have done the most effective and when I say. if you I am not<br />
saying me, I mean if you and everyone involved if that dispute<br />
can be resolved then you will have done-t-he best-thing you -canto<br />
remove the circumstances within $ zhich these things mill be<br />
done. And of course in all our discussions . about the Israeli/ Arab<br />
dispute we should not forget the great tragedy of the conflict<br />
between Iran and Iraq. It has been going for seven years a million<br />
dead, young children for what purpose, nothing. And again, there<br />
is an obligation upon all nations and people of good will to try and<br />
help those who are about trying to end that dispute. It is only when<br />
you remove the fundamental disputes as far as you can that you are<br />
going to have the best of bases for optimism about the end of<br />
terrorism. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: inaudible question on Lebanon<br />
PM: Just before you proceed I hope you will recall that that<br />
was not all I said. I said there were two factors involved. I<br />
said there was the interconfessional conflict. And I said there<br />
was the intrustion into the Lebanon of the international conflict.<br />
JOURNALIST: inaudible continuation of same question on Lebanon<br />
PM: I have heard you statement come question and I simply say this.<br />
If you are looking at the question of the interests of Israel you have<br />
g-t-f-t6I -th-ikEsiib ly--a-sk-yourseTf-the-question-are-the--interests<br />
of Israel going to be served indefinitely into the future by a situatiol<br />
which they are going to-have within their borders a population which<br />
if they continue to have it within their borders in its entirety<br />
is likely by the turn of the century or into the next century to<br />
have-the Jes----as minority-in--their-country,-Iwonder-and I_. say. -Idon't<br />
have to to you to establish my credentials as a friend of<br />
Israel. I think it is a legitimate question to ask and I know that<br />
very many of my Israeli friends are asking the question is it<br />
going to be in the interests of Israel to have a situation by the<br />
end of the century or into the beginning of the next to be a<br />
minority in their own land.<br />
ENDS W<br />
o<br />
A r </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
