<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9033</transcript-id>
    <title>DOORSTOP ONE AUSTRALIA LAUNCH, REGENT HOTEL, MELBOURNE</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/11/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009033.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON. P J KEATING, M. P,<br />DOORSTOP, ' ONE AUSTRALIA' LAUNCH, REGENT HOTEL, MELBOURNE,<br />WEDNESIDAY, 10 NOVEMBER, 1993</p>
<p><br />J: Inaudible,</p>
<p>PM: Well, Customs has been under review. We've got a systemic review going at the moment and it's been going for somne time.</p>
<p>J: Inaudible.</p>
<p><br />PM: Well, I think there'll be a more than adequate review undertaken.</p>
<p><br />J: What about Nick Greiner's comments on the leadership within the Liberal Party?</p>
<p><br />PM. I Well, that's for the Liberal Party. I think there's a great vacuum in<br />Australian public life with John Hewson. He's not providing the kind of<br />leadership which the Opposition needs. It's. incredible that after all this<br />time since the High Court handed down it's decision on Mabo that the<br />Opposition still don't have a policy. Can you believe that? John Hewson<br />doesn't have the courage to nominate a policy. And now, of course, he's<br />inviting Richard Court over to try and hold the Western Australian<br />parliamentary support under his leadership. Well, if you ever see me in<br />that state you can write me off. You can say, ' This guy is finished". If you<br />ever see me get to that you won't have to say anymore than say, " It's all<br />over".</p>
<p><br />J: Is Nick Greiner inaudible.</p>
<p><br />PM: I think just for some strength and leadership in the Liberal Party. Nothing<br />more and nothing less. I think as a former Liberal Premier he's entitled to<br />have a say about the state of the Party.<br />ends.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
