<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>12825</transcript-id>
    <title>NATIONAL SECURITY CAMPAIGN</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/12/2002</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
A public education campaign to provide the Australian people with information on national security will start on Sunday December 29.<br />
Australia has been at a heightened level of national security alert since September 11 2001.  This extended period of heightened alert for acts of terrorism is unprecedented in Australia';s history.  The Bali atrocity and the announcement of a credible threat alert on November 19 2002 have served to keep public attention focussed on national security issues.<br />
The level of public concern has increased following these events and is heightened over the holiday period. It is appropriate that the community be kept informed on security issues. This campaign gives Australians advice on the simple things they can do to help protect our way of life.   The campaign stresses that Australians should continue their normal way of life.  It aims to reassure the Australian community by putting the heightened level of alert, and the strength of our national security system, into perspective.<br />
It also gives people information on what they can do to help protect our way of life. It seeks a balance between encouraging people to be aware of their environment without increasing the level of anxiety in the community.<br />
The campaign includes television, radio and press advertising, including announcements in 28 languages. An upgraded Government national security website (<a href="http://www.nationalsecurity.gov.au">www.nationalsecurity.gov.au</a>) will be operational from the commencement of the campaign.<br />
A National Security Hotline (1800 123 400) has been established as a single point of contact for national security information.  It will be operational from Sunday.<br />
The Hotline is set up to receive information from members of community who wish to report any activity they feel may be relevant to national security and warrant further investigation. Information reported to the Hotline will be immediately relayed to the relevant police or security agency.<br />
A booklet with additional information will be distributed in coming weeks to every Australian household.<br />
The campaign will run for approximately three months.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
