<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8195</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF DOORSTOP, GARDEN ISLAND, SYDENY 12 NOVEMBER 1990</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/11/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008195.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF DOORSTOP, GARDEN ISLAND, SYDNEY,<br />
12 NOVEMBER JL990<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, are these ships entering a<br />
more dangerous situation than the previous two ships?<br />
PM: Well they get there at the beginning of December and<br />
it's difficult to say what the situation will be then.<br />
It's our hope that with the accumulating evidence and the<br />
determination of the rest of the world that the<br />
leadership ofE Iraq will come to the understanding which<br />
would be the intelligent decision that they must withdraw<br />
because the world is not going to accept their annexation<br />
of Kuwait. .1 hope that realisation will dawn.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you accept that war is now more of a<br />
possibility -than it was probability than it was<br />
before PM: Well I -think you would have to say that with the<br />
time that's passed and the refusal of the leadership of<br />
Iraq to withdraw that it does look somewhat grimmer than<br />
the situation before. One had hoped that the evidence<br />
that was available then would lead the leadership of Iraq<br />
to withdraw. That evidence of that being the sensible<br />
course has accumulated since then and yet we haven't had<br />
the withdrawal. But I still remain hopeful that there<br />
will be a peaceful resolution of this matter.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you expect a conflict before Christmas?<br />
PM: I'm not talking about expecting a conflict and I<br />
don't go to that.<br />
JOURNALIST: Are the sanctions working, Mr Hawke?<br />
PM: Well the sanctions are working in the sense that the<br />
economy of Iraq is running down very, very considerably.<br />
There is reduced food supplies there. So the impact is<br />
very, very considerable and the combination of the impact<br />
that there is already on Iraq, together with the evidence<br />
of the determination of the rest of the world not to<br />
allow the annexation of Kuwait to stand, as I say, should<br />
lead the leadership of Iraq to the conclusion that the<br />
only sensible decision in the interests of their own<br />
people is to withdraw. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Would you be prepared to reassure these<br />
sailors and their families that if there is an escalation<br />
they won't be left there alone?<br />
PM: The people on these ships and the ones that are<br />
there know the commitment of this Government to ensure<br />
that all decisions would be taken which were appropriate<br />
in the circumstances to ensure the maximum extent<br />
possible the effectiveness of our contribution and the<br />
safety of those involved.<br />
JOURNALIST: What are the families telling you?<br />
PM: Well it's very interesting. There's the natural<br />
human emotion of sadness at parting but overwhelmingly<br />
combined with that there is the expressed conviction that<br />
their boys have a job to do and that they're proud of<br />
them. JOURNALIST: Do you have any comments on David Lange's<br />
comment this morning in the Sydney Morning Herald?<br />
PM: Not at this stage. I will have later.<br />
JOURNALIST: Should Mr Uren be going to the Gulf?<br />
PM: That is a decision for Tom to make. Just let me<br />
make this point that the European Council of Ministers<br />
considering this matter recently have made a unanimous<br />
decision that it is not appropriate for official missions<br />
to go in regard to hostages and that has been accepted<br />
and adopted unanimously by our colleagues who are<br />
involved in this exercise. If private individuals go<br />
then they go not with the sanction, as it were, of<br />
governments but we understand their reasons for going and<br />
we accept their integrity and if they have some success<br />
then for those who are released, that's a great joy.<br />
Although for the great majority who are left behind it's<br />
a matter of mixed emotions I guess. But there is the<br />
very firm unanimous conviction that at the official level<br />
there cannot be comfort or stature given to Saddam<br />
Hussein by people going and meeting with him because this<br />
is a man who has broken all the rules of international<br />
law and behaviour in holding these people as hostages and<br />
they all should be released.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
