<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1700</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: PM 114/1967 - FUNERAL OF MR SHIGERU YOSHIDA - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR HAROLD HOLT</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/10/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001700.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FCR FRB-S: -NOI7V 1967<br />
LR A P. M. No. 114/ 13 7<br />
FUNERP L CF MR. SHIGERU YOSHIDA<br />
Statement by the l: ime Mnister, Mr. Harold 1-7ct<br />
The Honourable Gordon Freeth, Minister for Shiring and<br />
Transport, w'll represent the P ustral'an Government at the funeral of<br />
the late Mr. Shigeru Yoshida, former Prime Minister of Japan. The<br />
funeral w411 take place in Tokyo at 2. 00 p. m. on October 31st.<br />
VWth Mr. Yoshida's death, one of the greatest of postwar<br />
statesmen has passed from the scene. He dealt with the problems of<br />
restoring Japan to its place in the peaceful community of nations with<br />
great moral and political courage. He became Prime Minister in 1946<br />
and continued to hold this office until 1953. During that period he laid<br />
the foundations of Japan's postwar reconstruction and the firmness with<br />
which democracy is now rooted in Japan owes a great deal to his inspiration.<br />
For these achievements and for his personal qualities he earned the<br />
devotion of the Japanese people and the respect of the whole world.<br />
The Honourable Mr. Freeth has been a Member of the Parliament<br />
since 1c, 40 and a Member of the Australian Government since 1958. He<br />
has been Minister of the Interior and Minister for Works and, since<br />
December, 1963, Minister for Shipping and Transport. Mr. Freeth<br />
has represented Australia overseas as Leader of the Australian Delegation<br />
at a meeting of the Consultative Committee of the Colombo Plan, held in<br />
Djakarta in 1959, and was Leader of the Parliamentary Delegation to East<br />
Asia which visited Japan in 1965,.<br />
CANBERRA October, 1967. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
