<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>12255</transcript-id>
    <title>NEW YEAR MESSAGE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>31/12/2001</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
As we mark the coming of another year, first let us honour those firefighters, police, ambulance staff and other emergency workers who have protected so many Australians from disaster in recent days.<br />
Their work in fighting bushfires in New South Wales – so much of it voluntary – has inspired us all.<br />
They exemplify the core Australian spirit of mateship, of pulling together in times of common adversity.  We also pause to think of those Australians whose homes and other possessions have been destroyed by the fires.<br />
The American led campaign against terrorism will go on in 2002.  Australia must remain part of that fight.  The values and way of life attacked by the terrorists were as much ours as they were those of the United States.<br />
Our thoughts at new year, as at Christmas, will very much be with the men and women of the Australian Defence Force serving our nation';s interests aboard.<br />
Australia enters the new year with her economy stronger and better placed than most.<br />
Confidence, inevitably shaken by the tragic events of the 11th of September, has returned.  Inflation and interest rates are low, growth is strong and our trade accounts are healthy.  As in past years, a willingness to change and reform any current practices, which are impeding economic growth, will be needed in 2002.<br />
In social policy, 2002 will see the beginnings of implementing the McClure plan for welfare reform.  This will create new opportunities for people to achieve the transition from welfare to work.<br />
2002 will also see further progress with the Commonwealth';s long range plan to tackle – in co-operation with the states – the huge environmental problems of salinity and water quality.<br />
Australians have every reason to see 2002 as a year of hope and opportunity.  I wish all of my fellow Australians a happy and rewarding new year.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
