<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4135</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT ON THE WORLD SITUATION</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/06/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004135.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
A\-WC F76/ 103C<br />
1 JUNE 1976<br />
STATEMENT ON THE WORLD SITUATION<br />
Tonight I am going to talk about Australia's place in the world and about<br />
the inter-relationship of. domestic policy and foreign policy. The purpose<br />
of this statement is to outline some of the basic guidelines for the<br />
Government's approach in its dealings with other countries.<br />
The first requirement for an effective Australian role in the world is a<br />
realistic assessment of the state of the world in which Australia must act.<br />
That assessment must, as far as possible, be free of self-deception,<br />
self-delusion. We must be prepared to face the world as it is, and not<br />
as we would like it to be. Only in that way can we avoid becoming<br />
involved in the pursuit of policies whose assumptions are so remote from<br />
reality that their failure is inevitable. Only in that way can we hope to<br />
perceive accurately, possible problems for Australia and seek to overcome<br />
them. Only in that way can we effectively advance our objectives of peace<br />
and security.<br />
To point to possible problems and dangers is not to be gloomy or pessimistic.<br />
It is an essential step in the development of realistic and appropriate<br />
policies. It is an essential step in enabling us to Avoid problems and<br />
dangers which may arise.<br />
First of all, I will discuss the Government's general approach to Australia's<br />
foreign relations. Australia's basic interest is in survival as a free<br />
and democratic country, a country which can work effectively towards a world<br />
in which all people can live in self-respect. We want to help diminish the<br />
dangers of war and conflict, to help others as well as ourselves to<br />
live in peace and prosperity and to work towards an international<br />
environment which is favourable to these ends. There is a yearning in the<br />
world for peace and security. These must be the constant objectives of<br />
our policy. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
We will also seek to further our own deeply held values of democracy,<br />
freedom and respect for the individual at every opportunity. In our<br />
relations with other countries, the ideology of regimes is not irrelevant<br />
but it cannot be the guiding principle of our policy. While common values<br />
and attitudes may serve to make cooperation easier, their absence need not<br />
preclude such cooperation if there are parallel interests. Whatever the<br />
basis of a regime, whatever the organisation of its domestic government,<br />
the chief determinant of our relations will be that country's approach to<br />
foreign relations, how it meshes with ours, and of necessity the extent of<br />
the interests we share.<br />
We should strive to deal with other countries, and look to the development<br />
of cooperative relations with those countries with whom we have some common<br />
interests, regardless of ideology. A relationship founded in common interes<br />
is ultimately the only relationship that can be depended upon.<br />
In recent years, abroad as at home, lack of realism has inhibited Australia<br />
from the constructive role open to us. A government does a great disservice<br />
if it encourages acceptance by the people of an unrealistic view of the<br />
state of the world in which they live. At home, the costs of a lack of<br />
realism have become very apparent in the economic dislocation Australia has<br />
suffered. Abroadunrealistic notions that an age of peace'stability had<br />
arrived encouraged a neglect of power realities a neglect which did not<br />
serve our interests.<br />
It is time to move towards realism abroad, as we are at home. Australia in<br />
common with other medium and smaller countries is now facing a more<br />
difficult task in developing foreign policy in a deeply disturbing world<br />
environment. The evidence for concern is apparent to anyone who takes a<br />
realistic and dispassionate view of the world. The aspects of the<br />
international situation which give rise to concern are:-Firstly, the<br />
continued readiness of some states to pursue their interests by the use<br />
of force by the growing influence on the international scene of countries<br />
opposed to the freedom and respect for the individual person on which our<br />
own democratic system is based.<br />
Goodwill between nations would be enormously advanced if all nations could<br />
treat those within their boundaries equally and justly, and if nations<br />
could refrain from forcing their own form of government on others.<br />
But unfortunately, it would be unrealistic to expect that they will do so.<br />
Indeed, the practice of non-interference places a heavy responsibility on<br />
states. </p>
<p>-3-<br />
We have come far beyond the point where anyone can pretend that the<br />
denial of rights to minorities, or of basic rights to majorities, is not<br />
a matter of international concern. It is a tragedy, nevertheless, that<br />
great powers have sought to use problems arising from such situations<br />
not to achieve actively a just solution but to achieve the dominance of<br />
one ideology over another. A second aspect of the world situation giving<br />
rise to concern is the state of relations between the superpowers.<br />
Despite the hopes placed in detente, it has not st abilised relations<br />
between the great powers. Indeed a renewed arms race now looms as a real<br />
prospect. I shall comment on this matter further in a moment. Thirdly, there has<br />
been a spate of criticism, often ill-founded, of the United States which<br />
has reinforced domestic disputes within that country. Disagreement between<br />
Congress and Executive has impaired the capacity of America the only<br />
power which can provide a balance to the Soviet Union to act with full<br />
effect abroad.<br />
Let me not be misunderstood. This is not a plea for any power to be a<br />
policeman for the world, nor to do what small powers should do for<br />
themselves. A country without the fortitude to defend itself does not<br />
deserve help. But having said that I want to draw attention to the<br />
fact that there are many things which only the world's greatest free power<br />
can do. If she leaves them undone, they remain undone.<br />
Fourthly, the internal economic and political problems of many countries<br />
has led to uncertainty in their external relations. Fifthly, there is a<br />
serious problem of double standards in international life. Countries demand<br />
from others standards they do not observe themselves, while too often<br />
judgements are based not on the nature of an action but on the identity of<br />
the actor. Sixthly, problems of energy and raw material supplies have<br />
faced the international community with a novel set of problems which, if<br />
unwisely handled, could add a new set of disputes to the catalogue of<br />
dangers confronting mankind.<br />
Finally, the appalling widespread problems of poverty, hunger or disease.<br />
are not only an affront to human dignity, but constantly threaten discord<br />
and conflict between nations. By no measure can the developed nations of<br />
the world claim that they have acted with adequate foresight to redress the<br />
balance. </p>
<p>The developed countries have pursued a policy of tied loans and tied aidbut<br />
have completely failed to open their markets to the developing<br />
countries which will provide proper returns for their products to the<br />
developing countries. The developed countries are regrettably more<br />
interested in trade between themselves than they are in facilitating<br />
the progress of nations poorer than themselves. They can take no pride<br />
in their actions in this area.<br />
These factors show that a nation does not have to face a threat of imminent<br />
invasion before it has grounds for concern at the international<br />
situation. From our own point of view the primary concern is an internationa:<br />
environment which could progressively limit the capacities of Australia,<br />
her friends, and allies, to advance their interests and ideals: which<br />
reduces options: which almost imperceptibly weakens the capacity to<br />
pursue our interests. and advance the cause of human dignity#<br />
Whether or not such an unfavourable external situation occurs is ultimately<br />
of course, not in Australia's control. But it is not totally beyond the<br />
influence of our policies;<br />
A successful Australian external policy must be flexible, alert, undogmatic.<br />
We must recognise that Australia, a middle power, lives in a world where<br />
power in a broad sense remains the major factor in international politics.<br />
In international politics power indludes not only military strengths.<br />
Economic resources, industrial capacity, population, domestic stability<br />
and diplomacy all contribute to a nation's power and influence in the<br />
world. Australia lives in a world where predominant power is controlled by the<br />
United States and the Soviet Union. </p>
<p>It is a world whose relations also depend however, on the actions of<br />
other major powers China, Japan and the European powers and<br />
within particular regions also on the distribution of power between<br />
middle and small states.'<br />
The international diplomacy of the major powers with which Australia<br />
has to deal has to be understood principally as an effort by these<br />
powers to create a balance in the world favourable to their interests.<br />
It is in the pursuit of a more favourable balance that their policies<br />
impinge on middle powers, st~ ch as Australia, and on areas of immediate<br />
importance to Australia, such as South East Asia, the South Pacific<br />
area, and the Indian Ocean.<br />
We have certain advantages in achieving our international<br />
objectives. One lies in the common interest between us and others in the pursuit<br />
of similar goals. We have, for example, a common interest with the<br />
ASEAN countries that no one power should dominate the region again.<br />
It is not in China's interests that the Soviet Union should become<br />
dominate in the Indian Ocean.<br />
On the other hand, it is not, presumably, in the Soviet Union's<br />
interests that relations between China, Japan and the United States<br />
should be too close.<br />
In current international circumstances it is in the interests of many<br />
countries that South East Asia not become a region of increasing great<br />
power competition.<br />
Such a development would not merely be dangerous to our security.<br />
It would greatly restrict our freedom of action across the whole range<br />
of our foreign policy objectives.<br />
Another advantage we have in pursuing our objectives lies in the fact<br />
that% we have not only relaticn--s of convenience, common interests or<br />
even necessity with a great variety of nations. With some we also have<br />
co-.-non philosophical commitments, and friendships which we can and will<br />
strengthen. 4; </p>
<p>-6<br />
Our final advantage is in our people and our way of life. For all<br />
its faults, democracy is the best form of government yet devised,<br />
but its survival depends on the will and resolution of its leaders<br />
and peoples, and on a recognition that its values cannot be taken<br />
for granted.<br />
The guiding principle for Australia's role i~ n the world ought to be an<br />
active and enlightened realism. Although our capacities to advance<br />
our interests are limited we should be active and constructive in<br />
pursuit of a peaceful and favourable international environment.<br />
I turn now to consider relations between the superpowers and how<br />
these affect Australia's foreign policy.<br />
Detente It is clear, and it has been clear for a long time, that the U. S. A.<br />
and the U. S. S. R. have, as a major policy imperative the avoidance of<br />
nuclear war.<br />
Their principal common interest lies in limiting the possibilities of<br />
nuclear conflict and ending the wasteful arms race. This interest,<br />
shared by the rest of the international community, gave rise to the<br />
first S. A. L. T. talks and then to the enunciation of certain " basic<br />
principles of relations between the U. S. A. and the U. S. S. R."<br />
These principles were signed in Moscow by President Nixon and Leonid<br />
Breznev in 1972. They included the declarations:<br />
* That the different ideologies and social systems of the two<br />
powers would not prevent them developing proper relations.<br />
* That both countries attached major importance to preventing<br />
situ'ations capable of cau~ sing a dangerous exacerbation of their<br />
relations.<br />
* that efforts to obtain urn-flateral advantage at the expense of<br />
ofthe other were inconsistent with these objectives.<br />
* arnd that both powers would seek to promote condibons in which all<br />
countries would live in -aace and security and would not b e subject<br />
to outside interference in~ their internal affairs. ,7/ </p>
<p>Every country which desires peace must wish to see these principles<br />
observed. In an important sense, these principles, far wider than the mere<br />
containment of possible superpower conflict below the nuclear level,<br />
is what the world hoped Detente was all about. After all, earlier<br />
relations between the superpowers also involved a concern to avoid<br />
nuclear war, and Detente was heralded as a significant advance on<br />
this. As understood by people throughout the world, Detente meant not merely<br />
the search for security from nuclear war, but a genuine overall<br />
relaxation of political and military tensions.<br />
Unfortunately, the reality has not matched these aspirations.<br />
It is clear that maintenance of a stable relationship between the<br />
superpowers depends on realistic negotiation and crisis management.<br />
Negotiation is not a substitute for, it is an essential concomitant<br />
of, a stable military balance.<br />
Negotiations will not succeed unless they are accompanied by~ a clear<br />
determination to maintain a balance of forces, and are free from<br />
illusions about the effectiveness of unsupported goodwill.<br />
Our interests are in a lessening of tensions between the superpowers<br />
which only realistic negotiations make possible.<br />
I now turn to consider more closely the roles of the superpowers.<br />
The Soviet Union<br />
The Soviet Union has an immense responsibility before * mankind to<br />
use its power-and influence z. o strengthen the fabric of international<br />
peace and security. It has an historic opportunity to use its<br />
position to help build a stbeand humane international order and<br />
to end the arms build-up. It will be judged by the great majority<br />
of miankind against these stan~ dards. a4. 8/ </p>
<p>The Soviet Union is unquestionably committed to the avoidance of<br />
nuclear warfare. Reasonable people can however reasonably conclude<br />
that the Soviet Union still seeks to expand its influence throughout<br />
the world in order to achieve Soviet primacy. Its actions all too<br />
often appear inconsistent with the aim of reducing world tension.<br />
The U. S. S. R. Is actions during the 1973 Middle East war increased<br />
tensions to the point that the U. S. A. was led to put its armed forces<br />
on a world wide alert. The U. S. S. R. substantially assisted the<br />
North Vietnamese to take over South Vietnam. In Angola, the U. S. S. R.<br />
intervened by introducing 12,000 Cuban troops into the situation, and<br />
supplying them.<br />
In the last decade, the Soviet Union has expanded its armed forces<br />
by 1 million. The Soviet navy has grown substantially while the<br />
size of the United States' naval forces has declined.<br />
The Warsaw Pact countries have a major advantage in conventional<br />
forces over NATO. NATO has 70 divisions, the Warsaw Pact has 178<br />
divisions -' excluding the 43 Soviet divisions on the Sino-Soviet Border.<br />
This is a discrepancy of major proportions even when allowance is<br />
made for the difference in the sizes of the respective divisions.<br />
In addition, it would appear that the superior quality of NATO equipment<br />
which served to partially offset NATO's numerical inferiority has<br />
been eroded.<br />
The build up of the Warsaw Pact far exceeds the objective requirements<br />
of defending Eastern Europe.<br />
The Warsaw powers possess the conventional capacity to move into<br />
Western Europe with such rapidity and penetration that the use of even<br />
tactical nuclear weapons against them is now questioned.<br />
The U. S. S. R.' s nuclear armory has been elaborated to a point where<br />
there is considerable debate about the possibility of the Soviet<br />
Union gaining a strategic advantage. .9/ </p>
<p>-9-<br />
The Soviet Leaders now have a strategic and political reach a<br />
capacity to influence and even intervene well beyond the periphery<br />
of the established zones of Soviet security interest.<br />
The U. S. S. R. has demonstrated the will to exploit that capacity where<br />
the opportunity offers.<br />
Angola is not the only place affected by Soviet trained and sponsored<br />
movements. The Soviet Union is engaged in a major political offensive<br />
backed by the known presence of force, by training and by propaganda.<br />
The fabric of negotiations with the Soviet Union which we strongly<br />
support has unfortunately had limited success in winning restraint<br />
in this campaign.<br />
President Ford's abandonment of the term " Detente" clearly shows a<br />
recognition that the more extreme claims made for changes in the<br />
superpowers' relationship were quite unrealistic.<br />
Stability is disturbed and tension increased if the Soviet Union<br />
makes geo-political gains through its support of wars of national<br />
liberation, by the use of surrogates.<br />
The time has come to expect a sign from the U. S. S. R. that it understands<br />
this and that it is serious about reaching global accommodation with<br />
the West. A tangible signal is required from the U. S. S. R. in the<br />
form of a restraint in its military expansion. The pace is being set<br />
by the U. S. S. R. not by the U. S. </p>
<p>While the NATO powers' capability remains relatively static, whly<br />
is the Soviet arms build.-up proceeding apace? It is reasonable<br />
to ask: Why does the Soviet Union desire a military power far<br />
greater than any needed -to secure her own frontiers, or the expanded<br />
frontiers embraced by the Warsaw powers?<br />
It is for the Soviet Union to show that the conclusions so easily<br />
drawn from its actions are wrong that its basic purpose is<br />
world peace a world in which different nations can live and<br />
cooperate in harmony.<br />
That opportunity is open to the Soviet Union. It is up to the<br />
Soviet Union whether it pursues that path or whether it takes a<br />
different path which would lead to disturbing conclusions.<br />
The United States<br />
Along with many other countries concerned for their security and<br />
political independence, Australian security is greatly affected by<br />
the role of the United States.<br />
The world cannot afford any reduction of the credibility of the<br />
U. S. Foreign policy. In that way would lie huge risks. The dangers<br />
of miscalculation by other powers could become substantial, not only<br />
for the United States herself but for all those countries which look<br />
to a confident exercise of American policy in the cause of peace<br />
and stability.<br />
America is the only power that can balance the might of the<br />
Soviet Union. If America does not undertake that task it will not<br />
be done. If it is not done the whole basis of peace and stability<br />
is u. nsupported.<br />
Tte Vietnam war and Watergate undermined America's self-confidence<br />
and sense of purpose. Un~ fortunately, a contributory cause has<br />
also been undue world criticism of the United States opposition<br />
by people who ought to hav~ e been her friends and who ought<br />
to have understood Ameri~ a's objectives in the world. </p>
<p>Mutual recriminations about the causes and results of foreign<br />
events, differences between President and Congress on the conduct<br />
of American foreign policy area, are producing concern about America's<br />
capacity to act effectively around the world.<br />
This Government, while maintaining to the full its own independent<br />
national perspectives and sovereignty, will ensure that the ANZUS<br />
alliance with the U. S. and New Zealand does not fall into disrepair and<br />
disrepute.<br />
The interests of the United States and the interests of Australia<br />
are not necessarily identical. In our relations with the United<br />
States, as in our relations with other great powers, our first<br />
responsibility is to independently assess our own interests.<br />
The United States will unquestionably do the same.<br />
The fact remains that of all the gre at powers with active interests<br />
and capabilities in the areas of critical concern to Australia, the<br />
United States is the power with whom we have the closest links.<br />
Those links are based not merely on known common interests in, 9nd<br />
commitments to, a peaceful and stable world, but on common traditions<br />
of democratic institutions and values of respect for the individual.<br />
As long as Australia values freedom and respect for the individual,<br />
the United States is the power with which we can realistically<br />
establish close and warm friendship and with which we can most closely<br />
work to advance world peace and humane values we share.<br />
The U. S. can expect all p-roer cooperation from us in support of<br />
our comm= on objectives. </p>
<p>Although relations between the superpowers are a fundamental<br />
determinant of the world environment, Australia has the most vital<br />
in~ terest in the relations between countries in the areas of critical<br />
concern to us. We are and must be intimately involved in our own<br />
region I turn now to discuss relatisns between cour~ tries in the areas of<br />
critical concern to Australia.<br />
South East Asia<br />
The South East Asian region has been an area of close Australian<br />
concern and involvement for many years.<br />
Our interests are that the region should not become in the future<br />
an arena for great power conflict: That relations between States<br />
should be peaceful and cooperative: That political change in the<br />
area shou-ld not provide occasion for the assertion of a dominant<br />
role by any of the great powers: And that there should be opportunityI<br />
for commercial and cultural exchange between Australia and the<br />
countries of the area.<br />
Beyond these concrete interests, we would wish, within the limits<br />
of our possibilities, to help in the region's development needs<br />
and to be an understanding and dependable neighbour.<br />
Internally, most of -the countries of the region are vitally concerned<br />
with problems of economic development and social stability. Externally,'<br />
they are adjusting to the victories of communist movements in Vietnam,<br />
Laos and Cambodia and the changing roles of major powers with interests<br />
in t'n region. This change has inevitably brought a period of<br />
uncertainty and anxiety for countries in the area.<br />
W. e Share the concern of re= z: onal states at insurgency problems and<br />
at'-continued armed irS-= gencies encourage and supported from </p>
<p>-13-<br />
It would, in our opinion, be undesirable for mutually exclusive<br />
groupings to develop which could foster antagonism at the expense<br />
of economic and social development.<br />
We therefore, have an interest in establishing as broad relations<br />
as possible with countries in the region and this, of course,<br />
means that we stand ready to explore with the new governments<br />
in Indochina the development of relations Qf mutual benefit.<br />
It is critical for the peaceful development of the region that<br />
there should be mutual non-interference between the states and<br />
a commitment to the peaceful resolution of differences. Australia<br />
will seek to play a constructive role in the reduction of tensions<br />
and the resolution of disputes.<br />
Australia has long standing friendships with all Asean Governments.<br />
We welcome the activities of Asean as providing a constructive basis<br />
for regional relations.<br />
We want to identify and develop further areas of practical cooperation<br />
on shared political and strategic interests. We will seek to do so<br />
through our aid programmes, through involvement in regional efforts<br />
to advance economic and social development, and by the promotion<br />
of trade and other economic cooperation.<br />
Australia has a deep interest in maintaining sound and close<br />
relations with Indonesia. The broad relationship is of great<br />
importance to both countries. Relations are such that both countries<br />
can state their views plainly. Both countries have broad interests in<br />
the stability of the region and fundamental interests in avoiding<br />
great power conflict in the region. It is against that background<br />
that we have stated our views on Timor. We support a genuine act<br />
of self-determination in Timor. The very fact that we have stated<br />
our views on Timor plainly is a mark of the underlying strength of<br />
our relationship. Despite differences, a major concern of our policy<br />
will be to continue the friendship we both value. </p>
<p>-14-<br />
We would like to see the development of constructive relations<br />
between the region and countries beyond the region.<br />
The major powers will continue to be interested in South East Asia.<br />
The Australian Government will urge the major powers to restrain<br />
their competition in the region. Restraint will in any case be induced<br />
by the independent national interests of the countries of the region.<br />
Our own role is similarly influenced by what is acceptable to these<br />
Governments. Papua New Guinea<br />
The Government places very great value on Australia's relations with<br />
Papua-New Guinea. The warmth and respect between the two countries<br />
provides a strong foundation for our relationship.<br />
Papua New Guinea's needs will have the highest priority in our aid<br />
programmes. We have recently announced a five year aid programme which<br />
represents a substantial increase in Australian assistance. This<br />
programme has been warmly welcomed by the Prime Minister of Papua<br />
New Guinea.<br />
The Australian Government firmly supports the concept of a united<br />
Papua New Guinea. The unity of Papua New Guinea is of great importance<br />
to the stability of our part of the world.<br />
Japan Japan is of fundamental importance to Australia's long term political<br />
economic and security interests.<br />
Few countries match Japan's economic significance in the global<br />
system and with no country do we have closer economic links than with<br />
Japan. The Australia-Japan bilateral trade flow is the seventh largest<br />
in the world. </p>
<p>Japan's political and economic security is largely a function of her<br />
relations with the great -powers. The role which she defines for<br />
herself will be influenced by the condition of the great power balance,<br />
by her relations with China and the U. S. S. R.<br />
By the credibility of America's strategic role in the pacific, and<br />
by the qualities of her relations with countries like Australia.<br />
But Japan's role will also be defined by the reliability with which<br />
these relations guarantee her access to critical sources of supply<br />
of raw materials and mar1~ ets for her products.<br />
Australia and Japan therefore, share an interest in a-stable,<br />
great power balance in which no potentially hostile power dominates<br />
a region of critical concern to either of us.<br />
We share a respect for democratic institutions.<br />
We have mutual interests in establishing and maintaining reliable<br />
access to each other's markets.<br />
Since the agreement on commerce was signed in 1957 Japan has become<br />
Australia's largest trading partner. Australia is in turn, one of<br />
Japan's most important suppliers.<br />
The Australia-Japan ministerial committee ( AJMC) was established in<br />
1971 as a recognition of the importance of the economic ties between<br />
the two countries, and provides for wide-ranging discussion at the<br />
highest level on matters of mutual interest.<br />
In the light of change in the composition and structure of trade<br />
between the two countries, since the revision of the commerce<br />
agreement in 1963, at the October 1973 meeting of the Committee it was<br />
decided that the agreement should be reviewed taking account of the<br />
discussions on the basic treaty.<br />
As a result of Mr. Anthony' s visit to Japan, there is greater<br />
understanding of the importance of stability of trade both ways. </p>
<p>-16-<br />
Australia also understandis the importance placed by Japan on access<br />
to the markets of the United States and the European community.<br />
These concerns provide a sound basis for a frindly and expanding<br />
relationship between Australia and Japan.<br />
Early in the life of the new Government, the Prime Minister of Japan<br />
expressed to us the wish of the Japanese Government that a<br />
treaty of friendship and cooperation should~ be concluded in the near<br />
future. The Government welcomed this indication of interest<br />
and the negotiations delayed last year were continued.<br />
The negotiating officials some weeks ago agreed on a draft text of the<br />
treaty. It could be expected that the treaty will be signed by<br />
P. M. Miki and myself during my visit to Japan.<br />
The Government also places importance on broadening our relationship<br />
with Japan.<br />
Earlier in this Parliament the Government introduced the<br />
bill to establish the Australia-Japan foundation. The foundation<br />
will have the important role of promoting the study by the people<br />
of Australia and Japan of each other culture and institutions.<br />
Relations between Australia and Japan will be enhanced by the<br />
personal contacts and research which will come from the work of the<br />
foundation.<br />
Understanding between Australia and Japan can play a vital role in<br />
strengthening peace and security in the Asia-Pacific region. Australia<br />
will act consistently to deepen that understanding.<br />
China In moving towards a world in which peace is secure, a vital part must<br />
be played by the Peoples Republic of China. </p>
<p>-17-<br />
The development of China's foreign policy is difficult to foresee.<br />
In many respezt1-s, China remains a great unknown in international<br />
affairs. This is one reason why it is desirable for as many countries of the<br />
world as possible to develop close links with China.<br />
We look forward to a continuation of good working relations with<br />
the Chinese Government both now and in the future.<br />
A realistic view requires us to recognise that despite ideological<br />
differences, there are important areas where our ' interests overlap.<br />
In recent years, China's relations with the U. S. have improved due<br />
to certain mutual interests.<br />
China is clearly concerned at the Soviet role on her northern<br />
and southern frontiers.<br />
Australia and-China have a like interest in seeing that Soviet<br />
power in the Pacific and South East Asia is balanced by the power<br />
of other major states or by appropriate regional arrangements.<br />
We can therefore expect Chinese support for our own views on the<br />
need for an effective American presence in the Pacific and Indian<br />
Oceans. Such support has, in fact, been given. </p>
<p>-18-<br />
While I was in New Zealand, the Pacific Forum countries agreed to accept<br />
the movement of U. S. nuclear ships in the Pacific Ocean area. Such a<br />
decision, of course, reflected each country's independent assessment of<br />
its own interests. China has acknowledged that such an arrangement is in<br />
her interests also. In other areas too, China can make a positive<br />
contribution to peace and stability. We welcome the development of<br />
coaLnercial re2. ati . onship s between China and Japan and look forward to an<br />
expansion-of our own trading tiJes with both. China's attitudes and view<br />
of the world are often far removed from our own. Chinese judgements of<br />
the West, or its systems of representative government and the ideals of<br />
liberty and freedom of the individual seem to us mistaken.<br />
Moreover, China continues to give support to insurgencies in South East<br />
Asia. Australia does not support interference by great powers in the<br />
domestic affairs of smaller countries. We hope that China will give<br />
priority to the development of constructive relationships with a region<br />
which needs to be given every support for stable and effective government<br />
to develop and prosper.<br />
Nevertheless, constructive relations do not depend on agreement on all<br />
aspects of relations but on the development of those areas where there<br />
are common interests. My Government believes that interests of this kind<br />
provide a solid basis for working relations. We shall work to develop<br />
these, as well as improve our understanding of each other.<br />
INDIAN OCEAN<br />
The Indian Ocean is of considerable political and strategic importance<br />
to Australia. It is crossed by sea and air communication routes vital<br />
to Australia. Much of the vital flow of oil to our neighbours, friends,<br />
and trading partners passes through it. The entrance to the Persian<br />
Gulf has become a major focus of international attention.<br />
The objective of a neutral zone in the Indian Ocean, while admirable,<br />
has litl chance of success with the U. S. S. R. significantly increasing<br />
its =--a'nent presence in the vital North West sector of the Ocean.<br />
It is clearly contrary to Aus-ralia's interests for the balance in this<br />
area to move against our majcr ally, the U. S. A. </p>
<p>-19-<br />
It is also against our interests for both superpowers to embark on an<br />
unrestricted competition in the Indian ocean. We seek balance and restraint.<br />
We have supported the U. S. development of Logistic facilities at Diego-<br />
Garcia so that the balance necessary to stability in the area can be<br />
maintained. We also strongly support the recent appeal by the United<br />
States administration for restraint so that the balance can now be<br />
maintained at a relatively low level.<br />
This analysis cannot pretend to be a complete description of Australia's<br />
attitude to all parts of the world, but it would be unrealistic to make<br />
this speech and to refrain from mentioning two preas of great concern<br />
to us, and to the rest of the world the Middle East, and Africa.<br />
MIDDLE EAST<br />
In the Middle East the only future lies in negotiation -in a proper and<br />
broad recognition of the rights of all groups within that troubled aorea..<br />
Of an absolute recognition of the right of Israel to survive as a<br />
nation. And an equal recognition of the problems of the Palestinian refugees'<br />
There have been many wars in the Middle East, but no one has been the<br />
ultimate victor. There can be no ultimate victor. Compromise through<br />
negotiation is essential if there is to be any real settlement.<br />
AFRICA Even more than the Middle East, tensions and problems in Africa grow and<br />
become more difficult the longer they remain without solution. If<br />
movements towards majority rule in Rhodesia are not made within a<br />
reasonably short time-span, the result will be inevitable conflagration<br />
and lasting bitterness. There are a number 6f leaders in Africa who<br />
certainly do not support the white minority supremacy in Rhodesia but<br />
who have no wish for armed insurgency and no wish for ultimate conflict.<br />
They realise that such a solution to the problems of Rhodesia would lead<br />
to lasting bitterness, lasting divisions, and an increased possibility of<br />
domination of the continent of Africa by external powers. The national<br />
leaders of Africa have no wish t.-o see that happen.<br />
I have pre viously indicated in plain terms why we believe the policies<br />
facertheid will not work in telonger term. The greater the success </p>
<p>of the Bantustans, the greater will be their failure to achieve the<br />
objectives they were set up for. The more equal men become in economic<br />
and social matters, the less thcy will be prepared to accept denial of<br />
their basic political and humtan rights. However, we note with great<br />
hope the growing relationship between South Africa and some of the black<br />
nations of Africa. It offers the prospect of a broader and more sensible<br />
solution to Africa's problems.<br />
Within the framework of the Commionwealth of Nations we will seek to play<br />
what constructive role remains open to us and to the Commonwealth to help<br />
achieve a reasonable solution to these intract~ ble problems-.<br />
INTERNATIONAL COOPERATION<br />
In a world where increasingly complex problems transcend national<br />
boundaries, a commitment to multi-lateral cooperation; particularly in the<br />
field of economic and social development, is an indispensable part of<br />
Australian foreign policy.<br />
We support the United Nations, its Charter, and the work of the various<br />
specialised agencies. We have noted the degree to which the United<br />
Nations has come under attack. Its alleged failings have caused disillusion<br />
and even dismay. Despite the hopes held out for it, grievous problems<br />
between nations remain. It must indeed, be recognised that the United<br />
Nations is still an imperfect instrument for the solution of major problems.<br />
Some disquieting features have become apparent in its deliberations.<br />
These have included the use of confrontation tactics and the curtailment<br />
of the rights of participation of some member states.<br />
However, in our view, a number of the attacks on the U. N. have largely<br />
sprung from an unrealistic view of what the U. N. could hope to achieve.<br />
They also stem from a lack of understanding of the magnitude of the<br />
problems begetting the U. N. because of the sharp divisions throughout the<br />
world. The problems faced by the U. N. in no way diminishes the need for<br />
all nations to support the U. N. and make it a more effective instrument<br />
for peace.<br />
There are in fact many areas where the U. N. has achieved a great deal in<br />
imnproving conditions of life around the world. Australia will make every<br />
effort to help the organisation to expand its effectiveness. </p>
<p>I -21-<br />
We shall, be seeking opportunities to work cooperatively within the U. N.<br />
frainework as in other multi-lateral forums. These include the Commonwealth<br />
of Nations. We believe the Commnonwealth has continuing relevance as a<br />
distinctive indeed a unique framework bringing together something<br />
like a quarter of the world's population. As a means of fostering<br />
cooperation and consultation in many varied areas, it retains a lasting<br />
importance. ECONOMIC RELATIONS<br />
one of Australia's most prominent roles in the world is that of an<br />
important trading state. Indeed, with our annual trade worth some<br />
$ 17 billion, Australia ranks fifteenth in the world as a trading country.<br />
Despite an expanding export trade in manufactured products the bulk of our<br />
exports are raw materials and food stuffs. Australia is a resource-rich<br />
country in a resource-tight world. We have energy and raw material.<br />
resources of great importance to the world, and we are one of thefew<br />
food exporting countries.<br />
our position in world trade also implies duties and responsibilites.<br />
Countries which are rich in resources cannot neglect the needs and concerns<br />
of those countries whose principal resource is the energy and initiative<br />
of their people. This Government intends to have a reputation of<br />
responsibility and reliability in its international dealings. I believe<br />
other Governments overseas, whose economies depend on Australia for energy,<br />
raw materials, or foodstuffs, will welcome this.<br />
At the same time let me emphasise that the Government will ensure that our<br />
resource producers receive fair returns for their commodities.<br />
The Government will strive to widen and secure access to overseas markets<br />
for Australian producers. The Government is concerned, in particular, to<br />
improve access to the European community.<br />
The expanded European Community is the largest source of our imports and<br />
the second largest market for our exports after Japan. Raw or processed<br />
minerals, wool and other rural products account for 87% of our exports<br />
to the E. E. C. 13% are manufactured goods. Because the E. E. C. is the<br />
world's largest trading bloc, the trade policy decisions taken by the </p>
<p>-22-<br />
Commnunity are important to Australia, especially as they frequently<br />
affect not only the development of our direct trade but also<br />
our prospects in Third countries.<br />
The decisions of the Community, especially as they affect trade in primary<br />
products, are of course, also of great importance to the developing<br />
countries.<br />
As the second largest economic unit in the world, the Community-has a<br />
major role to play in world economic development. -We welcome the<br />
Community's prosperity and progress, which is also in our interests.<br />
The Government strongly hopes that it does not develop into a narrow<br />
and inward looking grouping but will come to play the role in the world<br />
which other countries expect of it. We welcome the constructive role<br />
Great Britain will play in the European Market, and the more outward-looking<br />
approach she has undertaken to encourage.<br />
There is a great need in general, for more practical recognition of the<br />
significance of international economic relations for the developing<br />
countries. More than any other single factor the developing countries<br />
need access-for their products to the markets of developed countries<br />
which we believe would come to be reflected in more appropriate terms<br />
of trade for their exports.<br />
International trading arrangements which provide relatively free trade<br />
for the industrial products of the developed countries while placing<br />
excessively high barriers before the products of the developing countries,<br />
offer little hope to the poorer countries in solving their great and<br />
grave pxroblems. One of the greatest contributions which could be made*<br />
by the industrial countries to the peace of the world would be<br />
international trading arrangements which provide greater opportunities<br />
for the primary products of the developing countries.<br />
We will cooperate closely with developing the Asia-Pacific region.<br />
But further afield, the Government is ready to concert its activities<br />
with other like-minded countries. In general, we must participate fully<br />
in the shaping of those world economic arrangements which will, in turn,<br />
help Ito determine our own econcmnic progress. In world financial and<br />
currency arrangements, in international raw materials, and energy bodies<br />
we must stand ready to play our part. The answer to these great world<br />
econcmic problems lies in international cooperation. ' Neither an abrasive </p>
<p>-23-<br />
., confrontation between competing nationalisms nor decisions by too narrow<br />
a club of decision-makers is likely to be helpful. Australia will<br />
meet the international responsibilities I have outlined.<br />
DOMESTIC CONDITIONS AND FOREIGN POLICY.<br />
Finally, I come to the crucial relationship between domestic and<br />
foreigj policies.<br />
Given the reality of the world situation it is critical that Australia,<br />
her friends and allies, must be able to bring their capacities<br />
to bear in the most effective way, if their position is not to<br />
be continually eroded in favour of regimes Inore effectively able to<br />
commit resources of all kinds.<br />
The international situation I have outlined clearly requires a<br />
carefully formulation approach to defence policy.<br />
The Government has asked for much more definitive work to be done<br />
in this area, so that defence planning can be based on the most<br />
realistic foundation.<br />
Our determination to act to improve our defence capabilities is<br />
evidenced by the program announced by the Defence Minister<br />
last week.<br />
International policy clearly requires a full appreciation by government<br />
of the economic and social characteristics of the international<br />
environment. The capacity of democratic countries to conduct effective foreign,<br />
defence, economic and social policies depends fundamentally on<br />
the understanding and backing of the people, on their will, and<br />
their commitment.<br />
One of the most critical conditions in securing developments in the<br />
world congenial both to our intersts and to our ideals, is that the<br />
democratic countries should retain their faith in systems of<br />
Government based on the freedom of, and concern for, individual<br />
people. </p>
<p>244<br />
Our capacity to act effectively in the world in the end depends<br />
on our sense of ourselves, on the strength of our commitment to<br />
ensuring that all Australians can live in freedom and dignity, and in<br />
our determin :_ on not to follow the paths of other states where<br />
belie--the capacity and right of people to seek their own goals<br />
is increasingly replaced by am enforced conformity to the wishes of those<br />
who control powerful bureaucracies.<br />
We believe that Australians will wish to take a realistic view of<br />
the world, and Australia's place in it. So long as our institutions<br />
foster a-resourceful and independent-minded people and a society based<br />
on self respect, Australia need not fear the future.<br />
It is here that the Government's domestic policies and long-term<br />
conception of Australia's role in the world are linked.<br />
Our ability to act with maximum effect to realise both our interests<br />
and our ideals in the world depends to a large extent on our<br />
capacity to work together at home.<br />
one of the great tests for the character and stamina of democracies<br />
is whether we can combine individual freedom with the capacity to<br />
acknowledge our responsibility to the common interest, whether we<br />
are prepared to sacrifice some of our apparent short-term interests<br />
to the long-term interests of the whole of the Australian people.<br />
If we cannot work together as a people except under threat of a<br />
clear and present milita : y danger to our national integrity, it is<br />
certai n that we will not be able to advance effectively pressing<br />
natic-nal interests in the world which faces us.<br />
There are common interests which unite all Australians.<br />
interests in a region and a world which is constructively meeting<br />
thie Dproblems which face Interests in an Australia which is<br />
: etitive in world mark= ets.<br />
Interests at home in securinz a return to soundly based growth in<br />
~. economy. Only out o_ such growth can higher real wages and </p>
<p>salaries and improved social welfare provision be paid, without<br />
inflation and unemployment..<br />
Without such growth we cannot meet as we might the requirements<br />
of security and aid.<br />
We will not achieve these objectives unless all sections of the<br />
Australian community are prepared to work together in the common<br />
interest.<br />
The question which faces Australia in common with other democracies<br />
is whether we are going to meet the challenge of cooperation and<br />
mutual restraint required from all the diverse groups in our society.<br />
In achieving success in our domestic policies, the Government hopes<br />
that Australia can be an example of the vital strength of the values<br />
of freedom and democracy which are still pursued and still far<br />
from reach in many parts of the world.<br />
The Government believes that the days of an elite forming foreign<br />
policy in isolation axe long since gone. They depended on a badly<br />
educated and apathetic public that could readily be manipulated.<br />
The people of the Western democracies are not passive, nor<br />
apathetic. The freedom and pluralism of democracies should not be<br />
regarded as a constraint on responsible foreign policy.<br />
On the contrary, free and open discussion, fairly conducted with<br />
respect for the views of others, will strengthen our foreign policy.<br />
A-foreign policy that ignores the realities of the international<br />
situation is irresponsible. A foreign policy which ignores the<br />
intelligence and goodwill of the people, that does not trust its<br />
people sufficiently to explain and seek support of its actions,<br />
cannot succeed. </p>
<p>26-<br />
The contemporary international situation is a test of the<br />
capabilities of democratic leaderships and democratic peoples.<br />
It is an environment with disturbing tendencies and shifts in<br />
balance. This diffuseness and complexity is the test. In finding our way in<br />
such a world, the democracies must not lose their sense of purpose.<br />
There must be no failure of will or resolution.<br />
The first step towards an adequate response must be a realistic<br />
assessment of the world and Australia's role in it. On the basis<br />
of such an assessment, we can work to advance our objectives of peace<br />
and humanity.<br />
The survival of democracy depends on a recognition that its values<br />
cannot be taken for granted.<br />
Let history not record that this was the age when the democracies<br />
abandoned their faith. 000... </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
