<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9621</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP INTERVIEW WITH PAUL LYNEHAM, SPECIAL EDITION 7.30 REPORT, ABC TV, 8 JUNE 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/06/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009621.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
VI(&gt; 1<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
INTERVIEW WITH PAUL LYNEHAM, SPECIAL EDITION 7.30 REPORT,<br />
ABC TV, 8 JUNE 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF ONLY<br />
PL: Prime Minister welcome.<br />
PM: Paul.<br />
PL: Now John Howard says that under your system we won't get what we<br />
the people want, we are going to get what you want in the end.<br />
PM: I think his colleague Jeff Kennett said it very eloquently today.<br />
He answered Mr Howard's point that what can be more democratic<br />
than a referendum where everybody has a say. I mean the<br />
Government and the Parliament could propose, or put a proposal to<br />
the community, that every person in the community has a say, has a<br />
vote, and they can reject it, or accept it.<br />
PL: But what happens between now and the referendum, we just all sort of<br />
mill around talking to each other do we?<br />
PM: No, we will do what we have intelligently done since this debate began.<br />
That is, we will consider the prospects of an Australian person<br />
becoming our head of state, consider what it means for Constitutional<br />
change, how it might be approached, how the change might be made,<br />
what it will mean to the country. Now that's happened already. We<br />
have seen a lot of debate, where now all of us, I think, are better in<br />
touch with the issues than we were then. We commissioned the<br />
Republic Advisory Committee Report, they consulted widely, that was<br />
reported, that debate has been had. Now I have, on behalf of the<br />
Government, put a set of proposals. This is promoting this debate<br />
between you and me tonight, Mr Howard etc and that will go on. </p>
<p>2<br />
PL: But the Civic Experts Group presented you with a report recently that<br />
said there is a great deal of ignorance in the community about the very<br />
basics of our political system, isn't there?<br />
PM: That is probably right. But you'll never have perfection about that. But<br />
that is not to say that we are then incapable of changing anything.<br />
Look at the changes Australia has made, both economically and<br />
socially, over the last 12 years they have been profound.<br />
PL: But how do we make sure that John Howard's fear that it is going to be<br />
divisive doesn't occur. I mean we wouldn't want to risk the<br />
PM: Well the thing is tonight, he squibbed the central question. There was<br />
only one question to answer and that was does he, forget the<br />
modalities, but does he believe an Australian should be our head of<br />
state. He wouldn't answer that question. He did everything to skate<br />
around that question, but he wouldn't come to the central question. In<br />
the final analysis he had to say " let's go to a peoples' convention" and<br />
then he had the temerity to say he would actually appoint half the<br />
people going to it. And so you would have a small cabal, half<br />
appointed by him, and in some way that supplants the rights of<br />
18 million people, a nation of 18 million, of the electorate of this<br />
country, the people of this country, to vote on a set of proposals in the<br />
most democratic of acts.<br />
PL: Nevertheless I think many Australians would have agreed with him<br />
when he said that it ought to be as non-political as possible this<br />
debate.<br />
PM: Oh well I mean that is like saying we want the air outside to be as full<br />
of oxygen as we would like it. I mean who is going to disagree with<br />
that? What I said last night was that, and today, if we can get<br />
agreement on the central point, that an Australian should be our head<br />
of state, the rest of it will fall into place. But that requires some<br />
leadership and he wouldn't provide it. You see in some respects I<br />
have got more respect for the Leader of the National Party who says<br />
he believes in the Constitutional Monarchy. He believes in the Queen<br />
remaining the head of state of this country. What Mr Howard<br />
wouldn't do anything. He is basically in favour of the Monarchy, but he<br />
wouldn't come and say so because he thinks it will offend too much<br />
Republican sentiment.<br />
PL: He says the system is working quite well and you have got to prove to<br />
him why it should be if it isn't broke, why fix it?<br />
PM: In other words, if I have to lead and if I lead sufficiently he may follow.<br />
Well, in that case, why does he want to supplant me as the leader. Let<br />
me get on and go on keep on doing it. </p>
<p>PL: Today in Parliament it looked like a real red-hot partisan issue, didn't it<br />
though? I mean your side yes. Their side raising all doubts and<br />
questions. I mean if this is the flavour we are going to have<br />
PM: No, it's like it has been for all the years I have been here, the Party of<br />
social attack. The Party of change, the Labor Party, keeps on<br />
advancing Australia, moving it forward and the lead weight is dragged<br />
along behind. Mr Howard always spotting the most conservative<br />
position he can adopt and you remember they said that, you know, we<br />
shouldn't have the Australia Act, appeals to the Privy Council should<br />
be maintained. All of that baggage has gone, we are the better for it.<br />
We will be the better for it for this change. I mean it is not just that<br />
those of us who want to see Australia's culture, identity perfectly<br />
reflected in this way should have to drag them along with us. But they<br />
should at least provide some leadership and say we believe. I mean<br />
here he was tonight talking about he said " I'm going to have a<br />
convention with 50 per cent appointed and I am going to put some<br />
people in there 18-25, young Australians". But he wouldn't let one of<br />
those young Australians become the President of the Commonwealth<br />
of Australia. He wants instead for Queen Elizabeth II of Great Britain<br />
to be our head of state and not one of those young Australians.<br />
PL: Well let's hear from some of these young Australians. While<br />
Mr Keating was delivering his speech to Parliament last night,<br />
Andrew Olle went to James Ruse High School in Sydney's North West<br />
to see what impact the Prime Minister had on the students and their<br />
parents.<br />
( panel discussion)<br />
PL: Well, pressured into it? Keating's personal baby?<br />
PM: That's called leadership. That's what leadership is about getting a<br />
country a choice, and that's what is involved here. The choice is to be<br />
exercised only by a majority of voters, in a majority of States, and a<br />
majority overall. I mean, the first person who spoke [ in the panel<br />
discussion] talked about " Keating's cronies". Well, the " cronies" are<br />
the Australian people they are the only people who can carry a<br />
Constitutional change. There's no way the Constitution can change,<br />
other than by a referendum provided for in the current Constitution.<br />
PL: There seemed to be a belief in that statement that you and your<br />
cronies would be choosing this head of state, as distinct from the idea<br />
that they wanted to choose this person themselves?<br />
PM: No. I thought more that the question was put " what difference does it<br />
make he and his cronies are choosing?" Well, for a start, the public<br />
alone choose this, in the most democratic of acts, across the country<br />
have a singular decision to make it, the point a referendum is put. </p>
<p>That referendum will be some years from now, so some of these<br />
concepts will be much better understood. But when it is put, then there<br />
will be a process whereby a head of state will be selected. That head<br />
of state it would be my wish that head of state is not a political<br />
person. But, if it is, by the way by popular election, it has to be a<br />
political person, because the candidate on the Labor side would be<br />
chosen by the National Conference, or the Executive of the Labor<br />
Party, and the same would go for the Coalition. Now, it is not<br />
necessarily to say that they would win, but both parties have<br />
demonstrated a capacity to out organise anyone else that has come<br />
along. So, if people want a non-partisan, if you like, non-political head<br />
of state of the kind of the last , say, numbers of Governors-General Sir<br />
Zelman Cowan, Sir Ninian Stephen then the proposal that I have put<br />
on behalf of the Government is the best way of getting that.<br />
PL: There does seem to be some discomfort about appearing to reject or<br />
deny the Queen, who, of course, has wide respect in the community?<br />
PM: That's true. But somebody said " the Queen is not seen by anybody as<br />
representing Australia" well, that is exactly right. That's part of the<br />
problem. When the Queen travels abroad, she travels as Queen of<br />
England, and the Monarch of Great Britain. She never travels as<br />
Queen of Australia, other than to Australia. So, if the Queen goes to<br />
Europe or North America, she doesn't go there as Queen of Australia,<br />
she goes as Queen of Great Britain. But if an Australian head of state<br />
were to go to Asia or to Europe the same as we have seen in<br />
Australia [ where] the Irish President, or the German President come<br />
here the whole embodiment of the country comes with them. And<br />
that's the point, we lose that opportunity. When Governments or Prime<br />
Ministers or Ministers travel abroad, they are there to represent<br />
Australia and do the business, but they are not there to embody the<br />
nation the way in which the head of state is able to do.<br />
PL: All right. Let's go back to school for a few minutes. According to the<br />
opinion polls, Australians overwhelmingly prefer to elect the proposed<br />
President directly. It's one issue on which nearly all politicians agree<br />
to disagree with their electors. The students of James Ruse High<br />
School and their parents are no different. As Andrew Olle found, they<br />
seem to be deeply suspicious of politicians.<br />
( panel discussion)<br />
PL: Well, what happens, if at the end of this whole process, you find the<br />
people still saying we want to make this a direct election?<br />
PM: Let's wait and see. The Government has put a proposal down and we<br />
have put it down for good reasons and that is that you can see by<br />
those comments Paul, people are saying they are suspicious of the<br />
policitical process. One person there insisting that politicians are not </p>
<p>to be trusted et cetera. But, there are in the Parliament roughly 200<br />
people representing the constituencies of this country. It is a very<br />
diffuse Parliament. Therefore it is a safe power. Diffuse power is safe<br />
power. That is why the representative nature of the House of<br />
Representatives and the proportional nature of the Senate, electing<br />
Senators for a state at large, gives the people of this country a system<br />
where no one is above it. The Prime Minister is not elected Prime<br />
Minister by the people, but appointed by the Parliament, by the<br />
Caucus. That is why the Government is saying don't elect a head of<br />
state, that is not the preferred model because to do it you lose that<br />
diffusion of power and you have one person only who becomes one<br />
person who becomes the embodiment of the nation and is potentially<br />
vested with substantial powers.<br />
PL: Far more political clout than the Prime Minister of the day?<br />
PM: Well, if you have an elected President and you were not to seriously<br />
delineate the powers, you would have a complete change of<br />
government. You would have a French presidential style system on<br />
your hands and the power would move from the Westminster style<br />
Cabinet and Prime Ministership and Parliament to that single person,<br />
because that person would be the only person in the system who is<br />
elected to it. I don't know whether it is generally understood. On<br />
election night 1993, I wasn't elected Prime Minister, I was elected<br />
Member for Blaxland. I was appointed Party leader at the subsequent<br />
meeting of the Parliamentary Party which had a majority in the House<br />
of Representatives and I was appointed Prime Minister by the<br />
Governor-General. I could be unappointed. Ministers could be<br />
unappointed. Opposition leaders could be unappointed. In other<br />
words, one has to be relevant and at the same time there is a test on<br />
you perpetually. But once one person and one person only is<br />
popularly elected across the nation for, say, a five year period, they<br />
are beyond the reach of the community and the power will gravitate<br />
from the representative system we now have to that person.<br />
PL: And you can only get rid of them by a vote of two-thirds of the joint<br />
sitting of Parliament.<br />
PM: Well, if they were elected you couldn't be rid of them other than<br />
through a process of impeachment. As President Nixon had to<br />
PL: Does this mean that we really ought to be writing down these powers,<br />
spelling them out and isn't it really a political problem rather than a<br />
legal one? If we sat down with goodwill couldn't Australians do this in<br />
a weekend?<br />
PM: No, I don't think so. Can we do it in a weekend? No. Could we do it?<br />
Possibly, but you then have to understand, Paul, that we are writing for<br />
the next 100 or 200 years, could you and I, in our crystal ball, see what </p>
<p>contingency may arise, that some person in the system should have<br />
power to address. I don't think it is necessarily a bad thing that that<br />
power exists.<br />
PL: But if they are not explicit, don't you become vulnerable to what<br />
Professor Donald Horne has called the ' Queen Mother of all scare<br />
campaigns'?<br />
PM: I don't think so, no, because that is why we have proposed, last night,<br />
that by providing some of these powers, not written, in other words,<br />
reserve powers to the head of state, but where the source of the power<br />
comes from the two Chambers of Parliament. No head of state can<br />
wander around saying ' I am here by virtue of being blessed by<br />
hereditary monarchy' or ' I am here, by the grace of God go It is only<br />
by the grace of the House of Representatives and the Senate and the<br />
House of Representatives and the Senate can unmake them. In other<br />
words, there is a limited basis and source for the power, but there is a<br />
substantial useful power there. But, if it is abused, they can be<br />
unmade.<br />
PL: And you can't be a candidate if you have been a politician within the<br />
previous five years. Does that really, do you think, rule out the<br />
prospects of President Keating?<br />
PM: Well, it certainly rules me out. I have always, in this, ruled myself out.<br />
This is not about me and it never will be. I would never ever contest<br />
such a post however it was available. But, the important thing is, I<br />
think, what we are seeking in the proposal that I have put on behalf of<br />
the Government is basically people who have served the community<br />
with distinction and who can enjoy the support of both major parties,<br />
but there is no doubt as one of the younger members of that audience<br />
made clear, if that person is elected you will have election campaigns<br />
for President, just like you have in the United States and it is pounds to<br />
peanuts that a politician will win. Whereas under the proposal that I<br />
have put on behalf of the Government it will be a Ninian Stephen or a<br />
Zelman Cowan or someone of that variety.<br />
PL: Prime Minister, thanks for your time.<br />
PM: Thank you, Paul.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
