<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9522</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P.J.KEATING MP INTERVIEW WITH KEITH CONLON, RADIO 5AN, ADELAIDE, 23 MARCH 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/03/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009522.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
INTERVIEW WITH KEITH CONLON, RADIO 5AN, ADELAIDE, 23 MARCH 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
KC: Prime Minister, good morning.<br />
PM: How are you Keith?<br />
KC: You might have been interested to see what the BBC thinks about<br />
Parliament this morning, have you read The Sydney Morning Herald<br />
yet?<br />
PM: Well, I heard a report about it, but I mean, talking about the cultural<br />
cringe, there is The Sydney Morning Herald proposing itself as a<br />
newspaper of substance running what some cub reporter puts on a<br />
BBC newsflash. Could you imagine The London Times running<br />
something that is on page three of The Sydney Morning Herald or The<br />
Adelaide Advertiser?<br />
KC: Well, they do say however it looks more like the Australian show<br />
Heartbreak High with school children bickering at the assembly rather<br />
than a parliament and they say that it is ' bull ring of bellowing<br />
vulgarians' in which the Prime Minister, you ' set a snide tone' and the<br />
Speaker is a ' Labor party poodle' with no moral authority. How do you<br />
respond to that?<br />
PM: What I say is let them look back over their history in the House of<br />
Commons where people who have come to fisticuffs, I mean we ought<br />
to be urging the time just to turn back over some of the speeches of<br />
Winston Churchill or some of the other greats of the House of<br />
Commons and just see how rough the debate was. When you look at<br />
some of the debates that have been there over free trade, over the role<br />
of the House of Lords in 1912, I mean it would make hair stand on end.<br />
KC: What about a leaf Prime Minister, from the Commons Book though in<br />
making the Speaker truly independent, resigning from the Party, going<br />
for a long term.<br />
PM: It doesn't work in our system. Our system, I think, works quite<br />
effectively and, I think, to have a robust parliamentary debate where </p>
<p>the issues of Australian public life are debated and where they are felt,<br />
heartfelt by those who represent positions is a good thing. For<br />
instance, let's take one of the current issues the Aboriginal Land<br />
Fund I mean, am I right to sit there and say ' oh well, if you want to<br />
destroy it in the Senate, that's all right, I'll take back a second hand<br />
bill, I won't say anything harsh', I mean, the fact that all title of the land<br />
was regarded as, put it this way, they were regarded as having no title<br />
to the land after European settlement and now we are giving them the<br />
chance under the Native Title legislation to establish that and where<br />
they can't, to buy it back. That is called progress. You get social<br />
change by victories, not by shilly-shallying compromises. The BBC<br />
would be better talking about British productivity, about how they are<br />
going to cope with the Deutschmark, about how they are going to join,<br />
if ever, the European Monetary Union and get their parliament onto<br />
some of the things like we get onto and that is the substances rather<br />
than the hub-bub of nonsense.<br />
KC: That gets us to matters economic. There is concern in the community,<br />
I know you are aware of it, some people believe perhaps that John<br />
Howard the five minutes of economic sunlight, others perhaps go for<br />
your line that the economy is slowing naturally. What is a rate of<br />
growth that is not too hot and is sustainable?<br />
PM: Let me deal with John Howard's line because it is basically just a bit of<br />
poll driven pap. They get told these things by their pollsters and they<br />
repeat it. They do what they call ' focus grouping' and someone says<br />
' oh, it doesn't seem right to me that we've had that much joy since you<br />
know so then it gets re-told back. The fact is Keith, we have had 36<br />
months of growth, we've had 12 quarters of growth. The Australian<br />
economy is growing now faster than any other OECD economy and as<br />
a test of its quality, I was with Chancellor Kohl in Germany a week ago,<br />
now you know there is this treaty called the Maastricht Treaty in<br />
Europe the tough conditions for joining the single currency with the<br />
Deutschmark that is called the convergence criteria. The only other<br />
two countries in the world who could meet that strict criteria at the<br />
moment and join is Luxemburg and Australia. Out of the 27 member<br />
states of the OECD the only two that meet the convergence criteria<br />
outside of Germany is Luxemburg and Australia. That is on<br />
productivity, on inflation, on government debt to GDP et cetera. On<br />
the sustainability in other words of your economy.<br />
KC: What does that translate to in terms of rate of growth?<br />
PM: What all that means is that the Australian economy, we have had the<br />
best run of statistics in the last year we've had in 30 years.<br />
KC: But aren't they too good?<br />
PM: Well, the economy has been growing at around six per cent which we<br />
think is too fast, but it has slowed back and we will soon see in the<br />
next quarterly accounts how much, but it has slowed back. It is still<br />
with low inflation and with massive employment growth. Last month we </p>
<p>had 91,000 job growth. If you go back to the election Keith, what the<br />
Government was asked to do was to re-start the economy and re-start<br />
employment and that is what we have done.<br />
KC: Frank Gelber from BIS Shrapnel was just talking to us a few minutes<br />
ago on the program before you came in saying he thinks that there will<br />
have to be more slowing of the economy, he is talking mortgage rates,<br />
home mortgage rates of 13 and 14 per cent next year.<br />
PM: Look, the fact that you mention his name and organisation is why he is<br />
on there saying that stuff. It is all a free plug for them.<br />
KC: So, they don't have credibility..<br />
PM: No, a lot of them don't no. There are ex-Treasury economists laying<br />
around, State and Commonwealth Treasury economists and other<br />
people laying around these institutions putting out blurb and they are<br />
all attempting to be noticed. The fact of the matter is that interest rates<br />
rose by two and a half per cent last year to slow the economy so that<br />
this was sustainable for people, so that they had not just three years of<br />
growth, but a decade of growth with low inflation and employment. Let<br />
me make this point, that in the period that this Government has been in<br />
office household disposable income has risen by 40 per cent in real<br />
terms, that's after you wash the inflation out 40 per cent real<br />
improvement in household incomes because more people in<br />
households are in work. Now, that is called income growth and social<br />
progress and you get it by consistency. I would much rather be<br />
managing a strong economy and making it sustainable than managing<br />
an economy in a recession.<br />
KC: So, when Senator Evans said this week that interest rates are not<br />
likely to rise in the foreseeable future, how long is that a month or<br />
two?<br />
PM: I think a good budget, and I am very confident the Government can put<br />
a good budget down, is going to make any move in interest rates far<br />
less likely.<br />
KC: You now don't think as the market seems to think there will be an<br />
interest rate rise in April or May?<br />
PM: I think markets are starting to say and make some of these noises<br />
because of movements in the international monetary system. You<br />
know, movements in the US dollar, movements in the Mexican<br />
currency, movements in Europe and they are looking at Australia and<br />
making some judgements about us. But, if the Government gets the<br />
budget right it will make any monetary movements far less likely.<br />
KC: Prime Minister, with the budget coming up I know that you are not<br />
going to get into what's on and what's not in detail, but there must be I<br />
suppose an annual dilemma here especially with an economy that is<br />
still maybe a bit too hot, you can slow the economy with interest rate </p>
<p>rises, you can wind back government spending or you can raise taxes<br />
or perhaps all three, which is fairest to most Australians?<br />
PM: Well, it is a matter of getting the balance right. Two years ago at the<br />
election my opponents were saying we were going to be in a double<br />
dip recession to John Hewson and a depression and John Howard<br />
endorsed his remarks. Now, if you say the economy is a bit too hot, if I<br />
had said at the election two years ago ' look, in two years time the<br />
economy is going to be very hot and strong and our real problem will<br />
be managing it' people would have said ' oh, tell us another one'. Now,<br />
that is the state of it. So, it is a matter of making certain that the<br />
budget, I mean what do we need? We have got strong investment and<br />
that strong investment soaking up our savings and more, it is flowing<br />
over into overseas savings. So, to stop that we have got to actually<br />
add to public savings and we do that by bringing the budget deficit<br />
back more quickly. That can be done by cuts in government spending<br />
or changes on the receipt side.<br />
KG: Both sides are you looking at?<br />
PM: Well, we will look at both sides, as we do on every budget.<br />
KG: Services taxes for instance as called for by the Metal Trades Industry<br />
Association?<br />
PM: That is another runner for the consumption tax.<br />
KG: But, it is a big area that isn't taxed isn't it? It is a huge part of our<br />
economy.<br />
PM: Then there is food not taxed and clothing not taxed, there is heaps of<br />
big areas that are not taxed.<br />
KG: So, services tax is not on?<br />
PM: I'm not saying, you said correctly at the start I'm not ruling things in<br />
and ruling things out because there is no point. Once I start on one<br />
you've got to continue to go through them and one can't put together a<br />
budget like that. But, the business organisations are very incredible<br />
when they want the incomes of the lowest income people in the<br />
country cut back, they want transfer payments cut back, but they don't<br />
want any business welfare cut back, they don't want any spending on<br />
business cut back and remember, I think Keith, you should recall that<br />
the government gave business about $ 3 billion a year of benefits in the<br />
year after the election, but none of that is to be cut back. So, you<br />
know, you say ' well ok, well you have put your views out and you have<br />
given us your little press statement, but thank you very much'.<br />
KG: Prime Minister, just one more area on the budget, something has got<br />
to give and you have told us you are looking at all sorts of options. Is<br />
there a way in which you can insulate those states, at least partly, that<br />
are not keeping up with the heat. South Australia, for instance, is </p>
<p>patchy in terms of its recovery compared with the east, so do we see at<br />
risk something like say the money for the Adelaide airport runway?<br />
PM: Keith, let me just say this Government's treatment, my treatment of<br />
South Australia, I don't think has even been slightly acknowledged at<br />
this point. Coming into the last election, I gave South Australia off the<br />
budget as direct real money, not loans, $ 640 million.<br />
KG: That was the State Bank bail out?<br />
PM: Yes, the largest payment by the Commonwealth Government in the<br />
history of our federation to any one State. Now, $ 640 million is an<br />
enormous amount of money to go into anywhere, but for it to go, not as<br />
a guarantee or as loans but just cold hard cash.<br />
KG: As you understand Prime Minister, that sort of helped us get out of the<br />
$ 3 billion well, so we had a fair way to get out, so we are still looking,<br />
the Adelaide airport money?<br />
PM: I know, but people say ' well, thank you for that', but a lot of don't even<br />
say thank you. I mean, the State Premier has never even<br />
acknowledged it. I mean, where would his budget be without it?<br />
Imagine the tax burden on South Australians without that $ 640 million.<br />
I mean it would be at least another $ 60 million a year in charges every<br />
year.<br />
KG: ( inaudible)..<br />
PM: Yes, well look, on the question about the airport, that is part of the<br />
scoping study we are doing at the moment. We are selling the airports<br />
which includes, of course, Sydney and Melbourne and Brisbane and<br />
we are currently looking at the future of Adelaide as part of the scoping<br />
and regulatory studies which are being undertaken preparatory to the<br />
divestment of those airports.<br />
KG: Can we look at the promise that came out of the ALP conference that<br />
there will be money attached to help with that divestment?<br />
PM: It really depends on how the whole scoping study goes.<br />
KG: So, it is not guaranteed that extra money, the money is perhaps not<br />
guaranteed in the short term?<br />
PM: It may well be that we do the things which the conference spoke about,<br />
but again it will be in the context of their sale. We are preparing this<br />
airport for ownership by another group or body and so whatever we do<br />
is in that context.<br />
KG: Mr Keating, another area that is of direct concern to South Australia,<br />
you will know that there is now bi-partisan support to stop any<br />
acceptance of the Industry Commission's wine tax recommendations,<br />
are you wanting to comment on that? </p>
<p>PM: Only that when I became Treasurer of this country the wine industry<br />
was a relatively small domestic industry. It is now a large international<br />
industry. So, I think, if you look at the wine industry under this<br />
Government in terms of that competitiveness, our support for it and the<br />
fact that we have now been able to open up market opportunities<br />
around the world and actually make very big indentations in some<br />
markets attests to, I think, the Government's regard for the industry.<br />
KC: Industry says however that if you don't provide the domestic basis then<br />
you kill the golden goose.<br />
PM: They have always been saying that and when wine was untaxed<br />
completely they said if you put any change to the tax treatment of wine<br />
that will be the end of the industry. It just stronger and stronger and<br />
stronger. That is not to say that we are about to accept the Industry<br />
Commission's view or<br />
KC: Prime Minister, the Hindmarsh Island bridge affair has been raised<br />
again. Mr Costello predicts a return of Mr McLachlan because he says<br />
the breach was a technical issue. What do you think?<br />
PM: Well, I think that is a disgraceful remark. What he did was intercept<br />
mail that was part of all of the legal documents in the Commonwealth's<br />
case for and on behalf of the Aboriginal people there. They<br />
intercepted them and copied the mail and sent it around and lan<br />
McLachlan was forced to resign because he mislead the House of<br />
Representatives suggesting that the Minister had copied it and sent it<br />
around. Now, only a couple of weeks later you have got Mr Costello in<br />
the most brazen outburst saying he thinks it is only a technical breach<br />
and lan McLachlan should return to the front bench. They have got no<br />
morals these people.<br />
KC: Prime Minister Paul Keating, thanks very much for your time.<br />
PM: Thanks very much.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
