<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6516</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT, PRESS CONFERENCE, ADELAIDE, 20 OCTOBER 1984</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/10/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006516.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PLEME MINUSTER<br />
TRANCPERSITS ~ rU MADELAIDE, 20 October 1984<br />
A 0 ERl~ PRFSS<br />
Well the campaign is into the very-interesting phase.<br />
We now have Mt Peacock and Mr Howard and Mr Sinclair as the<br />
* guardians of the family. They canit quite make up their mind<br />
who is the greatest moral custodian of all. I see that Mr Howard<br />
is attacking Mr Sinclair for his claims that Mr Sinclair is the<br />
greatest moral custodian in the country. Mr Howard says that<br />
he and Mr Peacock are equally great moral custodians. ' Well I think<br />
the people are going to make their judgements about that sort of<br />
nonsense. Again, I keep coming back to the point that our<br />
opponents insist on insulting the intelligence of the electoratte.<br />
They say that they are the protectors of the family.-. Who do t~ hey<br />
think suffered under the 7 years of Liberal and National Party<br />
Government. Did the increase of hundreds of thousands in<br />
unemployed, particularly amongst the young people. Did they come<br />
from outer Mars or did they not come from Australian families'?<br />
The Australian families suffered their greatest onslaught in -the<br />
post war history under the degenerate Government and economic<br />
mismanagement of Messrs Howard, Peacock and Sinclair. Whether~<br />
you look in the area of unemployment, of lost living standards<br />
opportunities, whether you look in the area of health -where when we<br />
came to office some two million people, niot living on Mars i-n some<br />
isolated communities, two million people in Australian families<br />
not covered in respect of health and medical insurance. The<br />
Australian family suffered its greatest onslaught in post-war<br />
history under-these people. And what we have done in Government<br />
is in each of these areas where the family's suffered we have<br />
turned Australia round. Australian families are now better<br />
off because unemployment h-as been reduced from 10.3% to 8.6%.<br />
Australian families are better off because of the change around<br />
from the growth of unemployment by a quarter of a million-in the<br />
last twelve months of our predecessors to the increase of 260,000<br />
jobs. under us Australian families are better off because we<br />
now have comprehensive and equitable cover for health and medical<br />
insurance. Australian families are better off now because we<br />
have'a housing industry which instead of operating at some<br />
of capacity has now brought the opportunity of homes to tens<br />
of thousands of Australian families that never had the opportunity<br />
of housing under the previous Government. That's in the private<br />
housing sector. Australian families are better off because we<br />
increased public funding for housing by 50% in our first Budget.<br />
Australian families are better off because we have reduced inflation<br />
from 11.2% to less than half of that. You'askc Australian families<br />
what hurts them. It's high and unctrolled inflation. Australian<br />
families are better off because we've reduced interest rates<br />
including mortgage interest rates. Now it doesn't matter what<br />
area you want to look at which directly-impinge upon Australi~ an<br />
V 4 </p>
<p>2.<br />
P. M. cont families. By any measure all Australian families<br />
are better off under this Goverinent since 5 March of 1983. So<br />
if Mr Peacock and Mr Sinclair and Mr Howard can take time off from<br />
fighting amongst themselves as to who is thc greater moral<br />
guardian, and they want to talk about families and things that<br />
impact upon families we'll do that every day up until the election.<br />
And of course as if that's not enough Australian families could<br />
look forward to a return to the economic mismanagement and<br />
disasters of those previous years if, and of course I talk<br />
hypothetically, these people were to come back.* Becuse you k: n-ow<br />
that I've talked about flat-e * arth economics. I told you about<br />
the blow-out of the deficit which was already indicated by the<br />
sorts of things that they were talking ah~ out before. But we<br />
pick up today's papers and what do we fin~ d the dam. The dam<br />
in Tasmania. We've fixed up the Vituation down there. We' 1ve<br />
healed the division, we've undertaken compensation to Tasmania.<br />
And Mr Peacock went down there and of course the great strategy<br />
that he had outlined seemed to come unstuck. Because he started<br />
off his conference and said well, the dam's been fixed<br />
Compensation's been paid. Then he got a short arm jab in the ribs<br />
fromr Mr Gray and so he changed tactics. Oh no, of course, if we<br />
wore to come back you could have your dam. Well it's a nice<br />
old pattern that's emerging. I negotiate with Mr Gray in good<br />
faith. He publicly announces that. I have met all my obligations<br />
and promises that I've made in respect of Tasmania. But now<br />
he's saying, no, we would undo it and go ahead with the dam under<br />
a Liberal/ National Party Government. And for good measure he's<br />
indicated that wouldn't give back the fir7st payments of compensation<br />
that I've made. Well how does anyone takeo any notice of a gaggle<br />
of incompetents like that. But that's not enough because he's<br />
going to pay for the dam. But Mr Sinclair has to try and make<br />
his mark too. So what's his contribution? He's going to have<br />
four nuclear submarines. Well what's he going to pay for<br />
four nuclear submarines. He's got about $ 7 billion additional<br />
blow-out in his deficit so far before they got going in their<br />
last couple of days of desperation. But now it's the dam. And<br />
now it's for nuclear submarines. At this rate by the time we've<br />
reached the end of the election campaign we'll have a deficit<br />
under these hypothetical people of about $ 20 billion. They are<br />
unstoppable. But it's going to be interesting isn't it to see<br />
in the days ahead with all these new promnises of outl'ays where<br />
they're going to cut existing programs. Are they going to cut<br />
other defence programs? Are they going to cut education? Are*<br />
they going to cut community employment programs? Where are they<br />
going to cut by these billions of dollars to make way for the<br />
dam in Tasmania and the four nuclear submarines.<br />
JOURNALIST: Your colleagues in Now South Wales seem concerncd<br />
about the capital gains tax issue. Do you share their concern<br />
that this could be a liability for the Labor Party?<br />
No, on the contrary. I repeat what I told you in the,<br />
last couple of days. I am happy abou t having tax and all its<br />
ramifications in the forefront of this election campaign. </p>
<p>P. M. cont... And if they try to walk away from it in the days<br />
and the weeks ahead, I will take them back to taxation. No, I'm<br />
not concerned about this at all.<br />
JOURNALIST: figure Prime Minister is that $ 20 billion deficit.<br />
Well that may be conservative because, I mean, just in one<br />
day we've had the dam and we've had four nuclear submarines. well<br />
at that rate, I mean $ 20 billion extra blow-out looks a bit<br />
conservative. I mean that's not bad for one day's effort is it?<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister on the submacrine question would a Labor<br />
Government ever equip its defence forces with nuclear submarines?<br />
No we've made it quite clear we see no reason for going<br />
C nvclear. And it's interesting to see today, in today's press, that<br />
the relevant spokesman for the armied forces has said that it is<br />
quite inappropriate and that the diesel powered submarines that<br />
we will be moving to under our existing plan are appropriate and<br />
adequate for Australian purposes.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke you campaign so far seems ratheir reactive.<br />
when is it going to become positive.<br />
Well you say it's reactive. But look at the things that we've<br />
been talking about. You see when you've provided good government,<br />
when you've turned the economy around, when you've got Australia<br />
together in a way it hasn't been before in recent memory, you.<br />
simply remind the people of what's going now as compared to what<br />
they had under the Liberals. And for reasons which I won't ever<br />
quite be able to understand my Liberal and National Party opponents<br />
seem committed and dedicated with each day in this early stages<br />
of the campaign of reminding the people of Australia that they<br />
want to take them back to the divisiveness and the incompetence<br />
of the past. I've told you about the fiscal irresponsibility-now,<br />
but we see, we are reminded that they are going to get rid of<br />
TAA1 they are going to get rid of Qantas, they are going to rid<br />
of the Commonwealth Bank that's going to be of interest to the<br />
millions of Australians who are involved in the Commonwealth Bank.<br />
They want to keep saying that they are going to take us back to the<br />
days of the past. Of course I'm going to react to that. Of course<br />
I'm going to tell the people of Australia, look what you're being<br />
promised, more of the same. Do you want that again?<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr H-awke are you confident -that you reassured some<br />
of your nervous N. S. W. colleagues about the capital gains tax.<br />
Oh, I believe so, yes...<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister to what degree are going to try to<br />
exploit division between the coalition parties. Is that going to<br />
be a theme? </p>
<p>4.<br />
Oh well, I'm going to try and stifle my grin and amusement<br />
as I watch from the sidelines as they sharpen their knives at<br />
one another. it's going to be interesting I think. I'd recommend<br />
to you who are following the campaign to look closely into Mr Shipton'!<br />
seat and Mr Macphee's seat because I would think that you'd find<br />
some beautiful lines down there. I think it's Babette Francis<br />
isn't it who thinks that Mr Shipton is a trendy I guess. He's too<br />
way out radical. I guess you'll find some marvellous lines in that<br />
electorate. You'll find some marvellous lines in the scat of<br />
Goldstein and Mr Macphee. They've started off we11l. and I won't<br />
be in there stirring. And I think they have enough ' animus against<br />
one another to make it very interesting already. It's early<br />
days yet and look how they're going. Z<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister did yoxi mean to say, did you mean<br />
to describe the previouis Government as degenerate.<br />
Yes, degenerate. I mean it really lost any they had<br />
started to decompose in terms of the their capacity to uinderstand<br />
basic economics or to display any competence whatsoever in<br />
economic management. I mean they are flat-earthers. But you<br />
would have thought wouldn't you after the debacle of reducing<br />
the Australian economy to its knees and having seen how we've turned<br />
it round into the fastest growing economy in the wor-ld that they<br />
would have had enough neus to say well, we were wrong and<br />
we should reform our thin king and regenerate our thinking.<br />
But they haven't. I mean really what they are about is worse than<br />
anything they did before. They are going to increase expenditures.<br />
The other one I forgot to mention I told you about the dam<br />
and I told you about the nuclear submarines but in their<br />
detailed defence exposition they were also talking about the<br />
Alice Springs to Darwin railway. So throw another $ 1 billion, they've<br />
just confirmed another $ 1 billion. This is the craziest set of<br />
propositions you've heard in your life. Just think about it<br />
nuclear submarines, the dam, the Alice Springs to Darwin railway.<br />
As I say, the weeks ahead are going to be fascinating. They are<br />
going to blow out expenditures like that. They are going to<br />
reduce taxes. So that's mean the deficit's going up and up<br />
like that. Unless one thing happens that for all these<br />
additional billions and billions and billions of dollars of<br />
new expenditure, they are going to cut at least that amount out<br />
of existing programs. -* So I hope that you'll be asking them day<br />
after day alright, you've told us all these billions of dollars<br />
of additional expenditure, you've told us you're also going to<br />
cut taxes please, please Mr Howard, please Mr Peacock, please<br />
Mr Sinclar, tell us where you're going to cut the billions of<br />
dollars on existing programs. Otherwise, if they can't do that, if<br />
they can't, well where's the money coming from. What are the new<br />
taxes. JOURNALIST: Prime Minister business deregulation. Could you<br />
be a bit more specific and outline what sort of deregulation you're<br />
talking about and particularly what camne uip at the'discussions at<br />
the Business Council. </p>
<p>Yes we had a very useful discussion. We had the<br />
representatives there of the Business Council of Australia, the<br />
confederation of Australian Industry, the Associated Chambers<br />
of Commerce of Australia, the National Farmers' Federation and<br />
the ACTU. And what I said to them is that I had the impression<br />
since being in Government that we did have a situation where after<br />
84 years there'd just been allowed to remain on the statute books<br />
an amount of legislation and regulation which may have been<br />
appropriate at the time, but wasn't now. And I said to them I<br />
know that you have this view, but it's obvious that, you, each<br />
of you will be better acquainted with theproblems ii ' your area.<br />
So I said to them well you go away, address yourself to this issue<br />
as you see the problems in your area, and-come back to us I<br />
nominated a senior public servant who would be co-ordinating<br />
our own work in this area and they-agreed that this would be the<br />
best way of doing it. That they should address themselves to it<br />
and we will then meet again after the election on the basis<br />
of the detailed work they'Id done. To the extent that they want to<br />
remain in consultation with our own people while they're doing that,<br />
then I've nominated the liaison point. And we'll meet after ': he<br />
election. We would then understand that in respect of the areas<br />
that may be of concern to business, they'd have detailed listings<br />
of regulations and laws which either demonstrably serve no us ful<br />
purpose now or needed some form of modification. Nbw-they agreed<br />
that that is the best way of going about it. We agree with that<br />
and I'm certain that on that basis, as we go through 1985, we'll<br />
be able to strip away a lot of this unnecessary regulation that<br />
exists. JOURNALIST: particularly that you would like to see.<br />
No, because it's just that one gets the impression, without<br />
going to details, that you hear a regulation mentioned or a ]. aw<br />
that's operative and you just wonder I can't help wondering<br />
whether that is in fact relevant and now serving a useful purpose.<br />
And you get the impression in talking with business people that that'Ec<br />
what they feel. But obviously they have a better idea from their<br />
day to day experiences as to what comes into that category.<br />
JOURNALIST: Ho0w specifically h-ave you allayed the concern of~<br />
Mr Keating and. other members of the N. S. W. ALP that capital gains<br />
could become a damaging political issue?<br />
Well, how specific? I mean I've just spoken with them<br />
and I think they share my view that the way in which the Liberals<br />
and the National Parties are going that they arc just with each<br />
passing day making themselves even more incredible in the area<br />
of tax than they were before the election campaign started. And<br />
we all take the view that with the release of the" policies" of the<br />
Liberal and National Parties on Monday we'll be stepping up the<br />
attack in the taxation area and not the Libs. </p>
<p>J'OURNALIST: Mr Hawke will you hold a tax summit next year?<br />
It's conceivable, yes. I've indicated that. It is con~ ceivable<br />
JOURNALIST: With the casino decision yesterday in the Northern<br />
Territory. Will that affect South Australia. One of the applicants..<br />
No, it won't affect South Australia, no. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
