<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8577</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ KEATING, MP 7.30 REPORT, 14 JULY 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/07/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008577.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
I.<br />
4 i<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
7.30 REPORT, 14 JULY 1992<br />
PL: You've said you're not going to panic about unemiployment, but many Australian<br />
families of course now are panicking, especially when they..<br />
PM: No, I said the Government's not going to panic about remedies, that is, being<br />
panicked into remedies which don't help that unemployment. That's what I said.<br />
Not that the Government isn't entirely and utterly concerned about enploVment<br />
and unemployment, but it's not going to be panicked as to remedies.<br />
PL: All right but when y ' ou're in the dark, when you're in that tunnel and say Dad's lost<br />
the job, or Mum's lost the job, or they've both lost the job, surely if the<br />
Prime Minister's even unable to say that we're passed the worst of it, surely that<br />
just makes panic more likely doesn't it?<br />
PM: Well we did see in last week's figures, notwithstanding the higher number of<br />
people looking for work which threw the rate up. In terms of unemployment, in<br />
terms of employment there was 28,000 jobs there for the month. That's the first<br />
very, reasonably strong sign we've seen that employment is starting to come<br />
through.<br />
PL: A lot more people came into the jqb Market, didn't they?<br />
PM: A lot more people came back looking for work.<br />
PL: And ended up with 11.1. I<br />
PM: That's what threw the rate up. That's right. If we'd had the same number of people<br />
looking for work as the previous month, the unemployment rate would have gone<br />
down.<br />
PL: Yeah, but..<br />
PM: Yeah but so what. </p>
<p>PL: There's still an enormous under-employment throughout the whole community.<br />
PM: Absolutely. The truth is, I think Paul, the~ p nvyis recovering. It's recovering<br />
but not as quickly as we believe, but still it's going to recover solidly. The<br />
problem for the unemployed..<br />
PL: When?<br />
PM: Well over the course of the next 12 months. We saw some quite strong retail<br />
figures this week, private consumption is picking up, we've seen housing starting<br />
to improve<br />
PL: But you've been saying this for the past 6 months haven't you, at the very least?<br />
PM: But the growth to date for three-quarters is 1.6 per cent. When we get the June<br />
quarter in, there's a reasonable prospect it'll be around 2 per cent for the year. So<br />
that's not a claim, that'll be a fact. Let me just say, and in the following year, that's<br />
from July 1, in the financial year we're in now, we expect it to be around the<br />
4 per cent area, in other words twice as fast again.<br />
PL: As distinct from the 4 3/ 4 in One . Nation.<br />
PM: That's right. A bit slower than then, but still reasonably strong. The problem with<br />
it is it's productivity laden. Or put another way, we're getting more output for<br />
fewer people employed. In the first instance there's more output for fewer people<br />
in employment. And it will take some time for those people in employment and<br />
the output to grow so that employers start to put on extra people.<br />
PL: Well that raises the question surely of what percentage of those jobs lost in recent<br />
years are now gone for good? And what percentage will be there in the future<br />
when the economy picks up?<br />
PM: Well I think it's largely a cyclical employment effect.<br />
PL: That's because of the recession?<br />
PM: I think so.<br />
PL: Not structural?<br />
PM: There's obviously some structural qualities to it. But again what you lose in one<br />
sense you pick up in another by the fact that the economy in the course of<br />
restructuring is now doing things it wasn't doing 7 or 8 years ago. </p>
<p>PL Such as?<br />
PM: For instance, manufactured exports, have gone up 300 per cent since 1983.<br />
PL: What of the argument, though, that to keep on cutting tariffs at a time of such high<br />
unemployment is really putting political ideology ahead of common sense?<br />
PM: It's a very phased and gradual reduction. It started in 1988 and it will end in 1997.<br />
And I think it would be to dupe people to give them to believe that any pause in<br />
the tariff changes would protect their job. It won't change the way in which<br />
investors or business look at the Australian economy, it won't change their long<br />
termn plans for the economy. All I think it will do will be basically to kid people<br />
along in their jobs.<br />
PL: It wouldn't save some jobs in the next few years?<br />
PM: I don't think so no. Because I think if anyone thinks that the tariff levels of a<br />
particular commodity are coming down they're coming down notwithstanding a<br />
pause, a phasing or what have you. I think that's there. The economies in a state<br />
of change, and it's a change which will produce stronger rates of employment in<br />
the ' 90s, but in a part of the world market where we can survive. You see, if we<br />
want to change Australia, that is recede into the old economy, to compete with the<br />
economies around us, you've got to take your wage rates back to the wage rates of<br />
Indonesia and Malaysia and these countries. That's $ 8 a week, A$ 1.30 a day.<br />
PL: Or we've got to get smarter?<br />
PM: We've got to move up the international division of labour. And you can only<br />
move up basically by new products, new processes and new skills.<br />
PL: There's also the idea around there, isn't there, of increasing the top marginal tax<br />
rate by a couple of cents to provide some money forob_ creation-schemes. What<br />
do you think of that idea?<br />
PM: Well it's promoted by people who understand the Government's natural concern<br />
about the deficit, and they're saving to us look for years you have been<br />
competent fiscal managers, you are worried about the deficit, we'd like vou to<br />
spend more money on labour market programs, would it help you if we said you<br />
should collect this on the receipt side and then spend it on the outlay side?<br />
PL: And what's the answer?<br />
PM: Well the answer is if y'ou want to give the economy a net stimulus. taking on the<br />
one hand and giving on the other, basically doesn't do that. </p>
<p>PL: But it might take from some of the so-called ' fatcats' and give to some of the kids.<br />
There's a certain sort of Robin Hood fairness about i?<br />
PM: But then as you call them, the ' fatcats', won't spend.<br />
PL: A couple of hundred bucks a year isn't much, is it?<br />
PM: No, but in terms of the net change of the economy from the budget. At any rate, a<br />
couple of percentage points onto the personal tax rate will only raise I think of the<br />
order of $ 3 350 million.<br />
PL: It would help.<br />
PM: It would help but it's not going to dramatically change the order of things. The<br />
Government can worry about fiscal policy, we have over the ' 80s, we're the only<br />
Government to ever produce strong surpluses. Those strong surpluses in the late<br />
are now, we're now enjoying at least the fact that we reduced commonwealth<br />
Government debt in the ' 80s so that now that the natural swing in the budget is into<br />
deficit, we can accommodate it more easily.<br />
PL: But you look like starting off in this budget with a deficit of $ 13.5 billion. That<br />
doesn't give you a lot of room to move, does it?<br />
PM: Well the starting point is not settled. Low inflation is a good thing, but the first<br />
impact of low inflation on the budget is to increase the deficit because if all<br />
payments to the Commonwealth are growing more slowly as inflation is growing<br />
more slowly, the receipts collapse<br />
PL: Your tax takes over.<br />
PM: That's right, therefore the deficit widens. So it's widening but in some cases<br />
wholly for good reasons.<br />
PL: Yes, but it does give you less room to move does it not?<br />
PM: Well I don't think it's going to seriously constrain the Government in focussing on<br />
the things I think it will need now to focus on in terms of directly supporting and<br />
helping those who are actually unemployed.<br />
PL: There's talk tonight of this billion dollar job creation scheme, presumably in the<br />
budget.<br />
PM: Yes well that's got no basis to it, that story. I saw that on the news, that's a total<br />
furphy. </p>
<p>PL: Well it is being put to you, isn't it, that you should run the deficit up to as high as<br />
$ 16 billion. Would that be imprudent?<br />
PM: Well I don't know who's putting that to you.<br />
PL: Well John Langnore says it.<br />
PM: Well there are always big budget deficit bangers all round the place here. I mean<br />
they were arguing that back in the early ' 80s, they're still arguing it. I mean there<br />
will always be same people..<br />
PL: You dismiss this?<br />
PM: Well I'm not picking numbers on the program this distance from the budget. I<br />
mean this Government will focus its effort on those people who deserve support<br />
and where we can materially help.<br />
PL: But will you be spending more to help them Mr Keating?<br />
PM: Yes, we will be spending more to focus assistance by way of direct assistance on<br />
labour market programs, as well as doing the things as we've been doing:<br />
lowering interest rates, again, watching the natural recovery come through, and<br />
with it hopefully some employment.<br />
PL: Thiere's also talk around at the moment of sort of work for the dole youth corps<br />
schemes _ Lan-dcpre, Working with local councils, that sort of stuff. What do you<br />
think of those ideas?<br />
PM: We're working through those. Some of those things have got something going for<br />
them. But we're looking at a menu of things in the labour-market area. But the<br />
one thing we won't be trying to do, we won't be employing the policies of the<br />
Opposition who's got a two pronged policy approach, and that is making prices<br />
dearer and wages lower. Prices dearer with the consumption tax, and wages lower<br />
by cutting youth and adult wages. We won't be having a bar of those sorts of<br />
things.<br />
PL: Do you think the se sort of youth corps schemes are worth trying if only to give<br />
kids a sense of purpose?<br />
PM: Oh I think so, I think it's very important particularly that young people have the<br />
opportunity of work experience, and where possible, training. And these will<br />
obviously be the issues we'll be focussing on it at the meeting next week cm -youth.<br />
train ing, youth wages etc. </p>
<p>64<br />
PL: How much do you worry about the personal damage this is doing to a generation<br />
of young Australians because we've got thousands of kids out there who don't<br />
believe this country gives a damn about them, haven't we?<br />
PM: Well I mean of course it worries me, it worries the Government, it always has. I<br />
mean, in the 1980s, we committed ourselves absolutely to employment, that's why<br />
the Australian labour market is 25 per cent larger in size than it was in 1983.<br />
There's 7.6 million people in work today, there were 6 million in 1983. We've<br />
always as a Government tried to focus that effort onto employment. But the<br />
economy is growing slowly. I mean, just in the Financial Review a day or two ago<br />
which I have here with me, it says European Community faces worsening slump in<br />
confidence. And they've got 1991 growth at 1.1 per cent, 1992 for Europe as a<br />
whole at 1.7, 1993 at 2.5. Now most of the developed world is growing very<br />
slowly. We're trying to beat the rap. We're trying to make the Australian<br />
economy grow at least at a pace which will pull employment up. So this problem<br />
is common to Western Europe, North America, Britain, and most economies like<br />
ours.<br />
PL: Meanwhile you're running out of political time and you face the prospect of going<br />
to the polls with unemployment at 10 per cent plus. How can you hope to win<br />
with that around your neck?<br />
PM: Well I think the issue has to be, people have got to say to themselves if the<br />
Australian economy has slowed in growth and is now starting to accelerate, but we<br />
have not yet got the employment effects, and we have a human problem of<br />
unemployment, who best to deal with those problems? Is it the Labor Party, which<br />
believes in picking people up, training them, giving them job opportunities, or<br />
supporting them, giving them at least the benefit of unemployment benefits, the<br />
benefit of Medicare, the benefit of these sorts of protections, or a Liberal Party<br />
which says we'll throw them out after 9 months, if you're sick you can insure<br />
yourself like the United States, if you don't carry your blue cross card in your<br />
pocket you don't get admitted to a hospital.<br />
PL: So you reckon y'ou're still in with a chance do you?<br />
PM: Well the economy's got problems particularly in the labour market and the Labor<br />
Party, the Labor Government is best suited to deal with it and its problems.<br />
PL: Prime Minister, we'll have to leave it there. Thanks for your time.<br />
ENDS </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
