<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6939</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER TO A PUBLIC MEETING AT CANOWINDRA NSW SATURDAY 31 MAY 1986</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>31/05/1986</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006939.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
TO A PUBLIC MEETING AT CANOWINDRA NSW<br />
SATURDAY 31 MAY 1986<br />
Mr Chairman, Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
Today I want to talk about the Labor Government and the<br />
bush. Farmers are businessmen and women, people who are prepared<br />
to take the risks. They are usually self-reliant. They are<br />
realists, people who do not usually make extreme demands. I<br />
do appreciate, however, that at times such as now many of<br />
you do feel some sense of being left to carry your many<br />
problems alone.<br />
This is a product-of isolation and of the sense of<br />
powerlessness to control such things as the weather, the<br />
middlemen, the markets, the unions and governments.<br />
I know many of you are feeling the pinch of higher interest<br />
rates, of farm cost pressures and of income shortfalls.<br />
Let me put it plainly that the problems facing Australia's<br />
rural sector are problems for all Australians.<br />
My Government understands that clearly, and accepts it<br />
absolutely. There have been demonstrations around Australia by which you<br />
have endeavoured to put your message to your fellow<br />
Australians. you have exercised your democratic rights as<br />
Australians. You have been right to do so.<br />
And it is a message which has always been fully understood<br />
by my Government. </p>
<p>The Australian farmer is no stranger to adversity. It has<br />
been, throughout our history, the very act of winning the<br />
struggle against adversity and the trials imposed by a tough<br />
land that has made the Australian farmer the most efficient<br />
in the world.<br />
And in this struggle, imposed this time not by the<br />
Australian environment but by the international economic<br />
situation the Australian farmer has this Government's full<br />
support.<br />
And I want to say this my Government backs the family<br />
farm. It is the family farm that is the backbone of the<br />
farm economy.<br />
We, as a Government are listening to careful and rationally<br />
thought out proposals from rural interests. We will always<br />
be receptive to proposals which recognise the reality of the<br />
situation, that have been subject to detailed analysis, and<br />
which have a clear-cut sense of purpose and direction.<br />
This is precisely the approach that John Kerin and the<br />
Government adopted in the recent Economic and Rural Policy<br />
Statement.<br />
That statement set out the Government's views on economic<br />
and rural policy in Australia. I thought it essential that<br />
the Government lay down such a statement so the community<br />
could know the Government's overall assessment of the very<br />
difficult rural situation.<br />
I believe it is important for all Australians to appreciate<br />
the dimensions of our rural problems and for people such as<br />
yourselves to recognise where progress can be made towards<br />
realistic solutions.<br />
Let us take a moment to look at the realities.<br />
It goes without saying that the economic well-being of<br />
Australia depends on all sections of the economy making<br />
their contribution. </p>
<p>F,<br />
Because Australia has long had a dominant and efficient<br />
rural sector its importance has often been taken for<br />
granted.<br />
The rural sector not only generates a high proportion of our<br />
export income but also generates employment both in<br />
supporting industries and throughout the service sector.<br />
Indeed agriculture is directly responsible for 7 per cent of<br />
the nation's employment. Taking into account those<br />
indirectly involved, this increases to as much as 20 per<br />
cent.<br />
While agriculture has declined in relative importance in the<br />
Australian economy since the 1950' s, it has in recent years<br />
maintained its share of GDP in a growing economy.<br />
In spite of the recent poor returns from world markets,<br />
rural products account for 37 per cent of our export income.<br />
The sector clearly has a vital role to play in our economic<br />
life.<br />
The problems of the rural sector are now among the most<br />
important on the Government's agenda.<br />
We are all aware of the sharp falls in international prices<br />
for our major rural commodities. Wheat prices have fallen<br />
by around 29 per cent since 1980/ 81; wool has fallen by 21<br />
per cent in the same period and, in the last two years, beef<br />
prices have dropped 24 per cent.<br />
This parlous state of international commodity markets<br />
markets heavily corrupted in recent years by the subsidy<br />
practices of some of the major producers is a cause of<br />
particular anxiety to all Australians.<br />
M </p>
<p>My Government's strength and this is where we are<br />
different to our opponents is to recognise the true nature<br />
of the rural sector's contribution and the true nature of<br />
the causes of the rural problem.<br />
The only policies that are going to work are the ones that<br />
are aimed at securing the long-term health of the sector and<br />
that are attuned to market realities.<br />
Individuals who are in need can be helped effectively only<br />
by measures that are properly targeted to those individuals<br />
not by broad brush handouts that were such a common<br />
feature of past so-called solutions to rural problems.<br />
Not all people who live in rural areas are dependent upon<br />
farming for their livelihood. But all people who live in<br />
rural areas do face the same problems in regard to access to<br />
a range of Government and other services that are taken for<br />
granted in the cities.<br />
It is for this reason that the Government has deliberately<br />
not confined its rural policies to farmers alone.<br />
I do not intend here today to present a whole series of<br />
facts and figures. But there are a few that I think bear<br />
repeating.<br />
The current rural difficulties to a large extent are the<br />
result of adverse world markets. This has meant that the<br />
farm sector has not been able to share fully in the growth<br />
of Australia's national income.<br />
Average export returns from our primary products have<br />
increased by only 5 per cent in the two years to 1985/ 86,<br />
despite a currency depreciation in order of 25 per cent.<br />
Unfortunately there is little prospect for any immediate<br />
improvement. Projections for 1986/ 87 suggest that there<br />
will be little improvement in world commodity prices.<br />
Negotiations for the elimination of subsidies will<br />
necessarily be drawn out. </p>
<p>It is simply not on to lay all of the blame, as many farm<br />
leaders and activists would like, on the Government's<br />
doorstep. Our overall economic policies cannot be blamed<br />
Australia's general economic performance has been<br />
impressive. our policy on tariffs cannot be blamed. The general<br />
direction of tariff assistance has been downwards. our<br />
broader industry policy has encouraged greater productivity,<br />
costs containment and reduced Government regulation wherever<br />
possible. At the same time, we have to reduce tariffs and<br />
other forms of assistance at rates which recognise the<br />
burden that such downward adjustment imposes on those<br />
investing and working in protected industries.<br />
Nor is the problem only one of high rural debt levels the<br />
use of debt finance is less in the rural sector overall than<br />
in other sectors.<br />
Nor is it high interest rates alone. Though, of course, I am<br />
aware that interest costs are by far your biggest immediate<br />
concern, the problem is that high interest rates have<br />
coincided with a period of low prices, exacerbated in some<br />
areas by a series of poor seasons.<br />
I know that here in the Canowindra area many of you have<br />
experienced only three good years in the past eight. I hope<br />
the recent rain makes it four out of nine.<br />
The question remains: what are we and that means not just<br />
the Government going to do about the obvious problems in<br />
the rural sector.<br />
The first step in coming to an answer is to appreciate that<br />
proposed solutions must be realistic.<br />
They must recognise the constraints that Governments face in<br />
terms of budgetary considerations, the impact on other<br />
sectors of the economy and whether they are in the long-term<br />
interest of the sector. </p>
<p>6.<br />
These are the essentials. Rural policy cannot be seen in<br />
isolation from the rest of the economy and society.<br />
Let me spell out what the Government's rural policy is<br />
about. It was set out in the Government's Economic and<br />
Rural Policy Statement of 15 April. In a nutshell it aims<br />
to do three things to strengthen the sector's long-term<br />
competitiveness, to assist those in most need, and to<br />
complement our general social and economic policy approach.<br />
These policies do, however, need to be set against the<br />
background of an understanding of the market environment in<br />
which the sector operates.<br />
Farming is a business activity and therefore should be<br />
treated like any other business activity. All markets<br />
involve risks and all market participants should know the<br />
risks.<br />
This does not mean that the Government is not prepared to<br />
give specific assistance to a single commodity industry when<br />
it is required. Recent assistance to the sugar industry is<br />
a case in point.<br />
Essentially, the Government's strategy is to deal with the<br />
rural sector's problems on five broad policy fronts. this<br />
strategy has been warmly welcomed in many quarters. let me<br />
quote the National Farmer's response to the April 15 package<br />
:" the most broad-ranging and thoughtful package of<br />
measures aimed at securing agriculture's future role in the<br />
economy amid tough world market conditions to be tabled by<br />
any Australian Government in years".<br />
First, we set the right general economic climate through our<br />
macro-economic policies.<br />
The benefits to Australia of our approach are there for all<br />
to see : our performance in respect of competitiveness,<br />
inflation, wages growth, output growth, employment and<br />
industrial disputation have each been vastly superior to the<br />
record of the previous Government. .77 P4.. </p>
<p>Just let me briefly give an indication of how the<br />
performance of this Government compares with that of our<br />
predecessors. I shall just quickly go through six<br />
indicators. Firstly, I refer to economic growth. in the<br />
Fraser years what was the annualised rate of economic<br />
growth? It was 2.6 per cent. What has it been under this<br />
Government? It has been 4.2 per cent. That is the<br />
comparison. I go to inflation. What was the average annual<br />
rate of inflation under the Fraser Government? It was 10.4<br />
per cent. What has it been under us? we have had an<br />
average of 6.5 per cent. What happened to profit share? It<br />
was 13.9 per cent. Under this Government it is 15.1 per'<br />
cent.<br />
What was the position in regard to employment under the<br />
previous Government compared with this Government? in the<br />
Fraser years, there was an average annualised rate of growth<br />
in employment of 0.8 per cent. Under this Government, the<br />
rate has been 3.5 per cent. The actual numbers of jobs<br />
created in the seven years under the Fraser Government was<br />
339,000. In three years under this Government 669,000 jobs<br />
have been created almost double the number of jobs in<br />
three years under this Government compared with the seven<br />
years of the previous Government.<br />
What was the legacy with regard to unemployment? It was<br />
10.2 per cent. Under this Government the rate is 7.9 per<br />
cent, despite a rise of 2 percentage points in the<br />
participation rate.<br />
Finally, with regard to industrial disputes, what was the<br />
record of the previous Government? The average number of<br />
days lost was 3.02 million days per annum. Under this<br />
Government to December 1985 1.4 million days were lost.<br />
This Government will not only compare itself and be<br />
compared favourably with other countries; most importantly,<br />
when it comes to a community judgement, it will compare the<br />
performance of my Government with that of our predecessors<br />
most favourably.<br />
while I do not share the alarmist views of those who claim<br />
that Australia is headed for recession, I cannot pretend<br />
that there are no problems in, the macro-economic area at<br />
Australia has to manage the transition from the phase of<br />
very rapid growth in the middle quarters of 1985 to a growth<br />
rate more in keeping with sustained non-inflationary growth<br />
and a realistic balance of payments.<br />
As the figures released with the National Accounts this<br />
Thursday show, the task of improving our balance of payments<br />
has been made very much harder by the decline in the prices<br />
received for our exports relative to what we pay for<br />
imports. </p>
<p>8.<br />
Just to illustrate the problem the decline in these relative<br />
returns over the 15 months to the March quarter is now<br />
adding about $ 6.5 billion to our anpual current account<br />
deficit. The Statistician has also estimated that the<br />
deterioration in the terms of trade has diminished gross<br />
domestic product at constant prices by the equivalent of 2.9<br />
percentage points over the year to the March quarter.<br />
Of utmost importance for Australia and, particularly the<br />
rural sector, is that we should ensure that we maintain the<br />
improvement in international competitiveness brought about<br />
by the currency depreciation. This becomes even more<br />
significant in the light of the figures which I just gave<br />
you. The Government recognises this and is accordingly retuning<br />
its policy settings to make the achievement of this<br />
objective mo're certain.<br />
That will require continuation of a firm approach to<br />
Government spending one which, while tough, will<br />
realistically recognise as much as possible the legitimate<br />
needs of particular groups for assistance.<br />
It will also require a continuation of realistic but firm<br />
wages restraint.<br />
of particular concern to farmers such as yourselves has been<br />
the level of interest rates over the past year or so. Let<br />
me first say that high interest rates are not unique to<br />
farmers but affect all people who have borrowed money.<br />
Interest rates rose late last year because of the unexpected<br />
strength in domestic demand and the need both to moderate<br />
the growth of demand and to provide some temporary support<br />
to the dollar at a time when markets were uncertain about<br />
its short-term prospects.<br />
If we had not accepted this market discipline we would have<br />
risked persistent unacceptably high inflation levels and<br />
entrenched balance of payment difficulties, with perhaps<br />
even higher interest rates.<br />
Interest rates generally have declined substantially since<br />
the end of 1985. The highest prime overdraft rate, for<br />
example, is now 3.25 per cent lower than four months ago..<br />
I acknowledge that, even so, interest rates remain higher<br />
than we and you would like. And it is for this reason that<br />
we have deliberately set about to rebalance economic policy<br />
to place even greater emphasis on budgetary restraint and<br />
continued moderation in wage claims.<br />
The Accord is producing the goods.<br />
Inflation has accelerated over the last year but<br />
overwhelmingly because of the effects of depreciation of the<br />
currency on the prices of imported goods. </p>
<p>The Accord will ensure that inflation declines sharply as<br />
these effects pass, and as the impact is felt of lover oil<br />
prices. The second element of the Government's approach is the<br />
adoption of industry policies aimed at developing a more<br />
vigorous and outward-looking industry structure.<br />
The Government accepts that the tariffs and quotas imposed<br />
by past Governments have resulted in higher farm costs and<br />
the exchange rate being at levels higher than they might<br />
otherwise have been.<br />
It is also necessary for the rural sector to acknowledge<br />
that the costs arising from protective assistance are not<br />
all attributable to protection of the manufacturing sector.<br />
The latest estimates from the IAC for 1983/ 84 show a range<br />
in effective assistance for the rural sector from minus 9<br />
per cent for the pig industry to 250 per cent for the egg<br />
industry. This Government is working toward long-term and sustainable<br />
reductions in protection. we have been doing this through<br />
sectoral plans for the steel industry, the car industry,<br />
textiles, clothing and footwear. And we have been<br />
converting tariffs to bounties where feasible.<br />
Secondary industry protection is not the cause of the<br />
farmers' current problems but our policies to reinvigorate<br />
secondary industry, including by programmed reductions in<br />
protection, will certainly contribute to the solution.<br />
The third key element of the Government's rural strategy<br />
comprises policies aimed specifically at reducing on-farm<br />
and off-farm costs and encouraging improvements in ruralsector<br />
efficiency.<br />
As I pointed out earlier, the Government is having<br />
considerable success in reigning in the growth in farm<br />
costs. The annual rate of increase in prices paid by<br />
farmers for their inputs reached 11 per cent in 1982/ 83.<br />
Under this Government's economic policies it fell to an<br />
estimate 8 per cent in 1985/ 86 and is forecast to fall to 3<br />
per cent in 1986/ 87. This in part reflecets-dereisions taken<br />
in last year's Budget and in the Rural Policy Statement<br />
which were aimed directly at reducing the costs of farm<br />
inputs. Fuel prices to primary producers have fallen significantly<br />
as a direct result of our decision in last year's Budget to<br />
fully rebate the excise for diesel used off-road by primary<br />
producers. we have maintained the full rebate even while<br />
fuel excises have been increased in recent months. Primary<br />
producers are the only users in receipt of this full rebate.<br />
This is in addition to the benefit to primary producers,<br />
like all users, from the recent petrol price reduction.<br />
These decisions are saving farmers around $ 300 million per<br />
year. 1-11 </p>
<p>The Government at present provides assistance to fertiliser<br />
consumption through subsidies costing some $ 55 million<br />
annually. We have also provided a $ 10 million subsidy so as<br />
to exempt farmers from the effects of anti-dumping action on<br />
certain fertiliser imports.<br />
Both these measures are currently the subject of review.<br />
The Government has decided that the overall cost of<br />
fertilisers to farmers will not increase as a result of any<br />
decisions which may flow from these reviews.<br />
The Government has also moved to minimise the impact of<br />
tariffs on farm Costs. Agricultural tractors have long been<br />
assisted by bounties at a cost of around $ 7 million a year<br />
in order to minimise the impact on users. In last year's<br />
Budget it was announced that the tariff on grain harvesters<br />
will be replaced with a bounty, reducing farm costs by some<br />
$ 14 million per year.<br />
The Government, in the Rural Policy Statement, took further<br />
action to reduce tariff-affected farm input costs.<br />
The tariffs on agricultural and horticultural machinery for<br />
soil preparation and cultivation will be replaced with a<br />
bounty providing equivalent assistance. This decision took<br />
effect on 15 April, and will cost an estimated $ 39 million<br />
in the first year.<br />
In last year's Budget Speech, the Treasurer also indicated<br />
that the Government was disposed to replace tariffs on<br />
agricultural chemicals with bounties when considering the<br />
IAC Report on the chemicals industry.<br />
A final decision will be made in the context of the IAC's<br />
final report. However, the Government is committed to<br />
reducing the price of these chemicals for farmers, either by<br />
bounties or the reduction of tariffs or a combination of the<br />
two. In the meantime, we have decided to remove immediately the 2<br />
per cent revenue duty where it now applies to agricultural<br />
chemicals, at a cost to revenue of $ 0.4 million in a full<br />
year. As well we have announced plans to establish a Royal<br />
Commission into the costs and efficiency of the national<br />
grain handling system. To proceed with this Commission will<br />
require strong support from the industry and State<br />
Governments. The fourth element is policies aimed at tackling directly<br />
adverse developments that affect the demand for specific<br />
rural commodities, both at the international and domestic<br />
level. My Government has been most active in expressing Australia's<br />
concerns on the international scene about the subsidisation<br />
practices of certain major agricultural producers. </p>
<p>11.<br />
We have had some successes in this regard. Last year we<br />
were able to negotiate the " Andriessen Agreement" with the<br />
European Communities which protects our major Asian beef<br />
markets from the intrusion of subsidised European beef.<br />
This year, the Government was also successful in securing a<br />
US Congressional decision to reduce the size of their export<br />
enhancement program. Important assurances were also<br />
provided to me by President Reagan on the operation of both<br />
that program and other aspects of the 1985 Farm Bill.<br />
Agricultural subsidisation practices featured prominently at<br />
the Tokyo Economic Summit, in part due to direct<br />
representations made by the Australian Government.<br />
John Kerin will be going to Europe and the USA next month to<br />
see what further progress can be made.<br />
Effective and innovative marketing is also essential to a<br />
more competitive and successful farm sector. Since becoming<br />
the Minister for Primary industry this is an area to which<br />
John Kerin has devoted a considerable amount of time and<br />
effort. For example, a comprehensive White Paper on Statutory<br />
Marketing Reform has been prepared and published by the<br />
Government. This has formed the basis of a program of<br />
reform of the statutory marketing arrangements. Marketing<br />
authorities are being given the necessary freedom from<br />
Government red tape, stronger commercial expertise at the<br />
Board level and more effective accountability to their<br />
industries.<br />
While it is difficult to estimate the gains from this reform<br />
it is interesting to note that an improvement of even one<br />
per cent in our rural export returns translates to a figure<br />
of some $ 100 million.<br />
In order to encourage a new approach in this area the<br />
Government has agreed to the establishment of a special fund<br />
of $ 25 million over five years in order to stimulate<br />
innovation in the marketing of agricultural products. This<br />
encompasses marketing systems, the differentiation of<br />
products, quality control and new product development. </p>
<p>Finally, the Government has developed policies that address<br />
tewelfare problems of the rural sector and<br />
non-metropolitan areas generally.<br />
This Government is vitally aware of the flow-on effects to<br />
country towns and remote settlements of the difficulties<br />
facing farmers. Moreover, it acknowledges that country<br />
people often have difficulty in gaining access to education,<br />
welfare and community services. Unemployment is also higher<br />
in rural Australia.<br />
In response to these problems the Government has announced a<br />
series of measures to aid rural and provincial Australia.<br />
A Rural and Provincial Affairs Unit has been established in<br />
the Department of Primary Industry.<br />
We are to establish a pilot Country Centres Project to<br />
enable investigation of the development potential of<br />
selected country towns. It will also help develop<br />
strategies to assist regions to adjust to change.<br />
A Rural Women's Access Program is to be established to<br />
improve the access of women to services and employment in<br />
rural areas. In this regard let me pay particular tribute<br />
to the constructive co-operation of the Country Womens'<br />
Association and their President Miss Dorothy Ross in<br />
developing policies and programs in this important area.<br />
we are also concerned at the low level of participation of<br />
country youth in senior secondary and tertiary education.<br />
Senator Ryan will shortly be bringing forward proposals to<br />
increase educational services and to improve retention rates<br />
in country areas.<br />
These measures will also assist in improving and maintaining<br />
the quality of life in the country. </p>
<p>13.<br />
Mr Chairman, ladies and gentlemen.<br />
The people of rural Australia have been going through a very<br />
difficult period.<br />
It brings me no joy to see you and your families facing such<br />
difficult circumstances. I nevertheless have great faith in<br />
your strength and determination to pull through these hard<br />
times. In exercising that strength and determination, let me assure<br />
you that you are not alone.<br />
I do not, nor I believe does anyone, have a panacea for all<br />
your problems. You and I both know this.<br />
We all know that the Government alone cannot solve your<br />
problems. But we also know that you alone cannot solve them.<br />
We must work together to get through these tough times and<br />
to lay down the foundations upon which the future prosperity<br />
of rural Australia will be built.<br />
My Government has an unequivocal commitment to work with you<br />
in this great task.<br />
There is a brighter future for rural Australia. We will win<br />
that brighter future only by facing today's problems<br />
together.<br />
We may have a long battle on our hands. But you have the<br />
courage to face that battle. So does my Government.<br />
Together we can build a better future for Australia's rural<br />
communities. I can assure you no Government in the history of Australia<br />
has fought alongside you with greater courage and<br />
determination than this one is doing, and will continue to<br />
do. I commend our approach to you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
