<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6196</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, AUSTRALIAN COUNCIL OF SOCIAL SERVICE CONGRESS, CANBERRA, 8 SEPTEMBER 1983</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/09/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006196.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
AGAINST Di 7<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
AUSTRALIAN COUNCIL OF SOCIAL SERVICE CONGRESS<br />
CANBERRA 8 SEPTEMBER 1983<br />
This Congress could hardly be more timely or i~ iore<br />
opportune, coming as it does so soon after the presentat ion<br />
of a Labor Government's first national Budget for eight<br />
years. The timeliness springs not only from the<br />
opportunity the Congress provides for all of us concerned<br />
with advancing the cause of social security and community<br />
welfare in this nation to review the work of the Government<br />
in this vital field during its first six months and it may<br />
seem longer to many, but it is only six months on Saturday<br />
since we were sworn in.<br />
But, the added timeliness of this Congress comes<br />
from the fact that, because of the work of the pa st six<br />
months, and not least the new directions foreshadowed in the<br />
Budget, the social welfare debate in this nation has taken<br />
on a relevance, a topicality and I hope, a maturity, that it<br />
has not had for at least seven years.<br />
The whole philosophy of the Australian Labor Party,<br />
and certainly the aim of this Labor Government, require that<br />
the approach to social welfare questions should be<br />
absolutely central to the entire debate about the course and<br />
shape of the future of this nation.<br />
For these issues go to the very heart of this<br />
nation's vision of itself and go to the very heart of our<br />
aspirations for a more just, a more equal and a more humane<br />
society. For if Australia is t'o have something special to<br />
say to the world if we are/ to stand among the nations of<br />
the world as having something relevant : and identifiably<br />
Australian to say and if we are to give worthwhile meaning<br />
to the Australian experiment and the Australian experience,<br />
then that special Australian contribution must turn on this<br />
central question of whether oi not we have Succeeded in<br />
securing, for all our people, fairer shares of the nation's<br />
wealth and a larger measure of genuine equality.<br />
At this stage it has to be acknowledged that no<br />
nation es basically rich as ours, which nonetheless has to<br />
confess the existence of at least one and a half million of<br />
its fellow citizens living in actual poverty, can claim<br />
success in achieving its-great goals of a more equal and<br />
humane society. It is t.-oth ese goals that the Government<br />
has tried in its first six months to address itself', even in<br />
the midst of economic difficulties and complexities not<br />
experienced in this country for more than 50 years. </p>
<p>We have not taken the view that reform of the<br />
social security system i3 something that must await national<br />
economic recovery. We have not tried to put these questions<br />
on the backburner Indeed, at a t-ime of deep ec -onomic difficulties<br />
such as vie inherited, the pursuit of greater equality takes<br />
on added dimensions. The whole task of economic recovery<br />
from the circumstances which we inherited cannot be achieved<br />
unless there is sharing of restraints and a sharing of<br />
inevitable burdens by those comparatively better able to<br />
bear them. And that is the approach we have asked the<br />
community to accept.<br />
It was the approach behind the National Economic<br />
Summit Conference. It was the approach of the nineteenth of<br />
May Statement. It was the approach of the Budget itself.<br />
We have not sought to use the economic crisis as an<br />
alibi against reform.<br />
On the contrary, we believe that the very<br />
seriousness of the general economic problems lends an added<br />
urgency to the need to tackle the reform of the social<br />
welfare system. Indeed, the inadequacies of the system are<br />
themselves part and parcel of the wider economic problem.<br />
The clearest specific example of this is of course<br />
the question of unemployment itself the most notorious<br />
ceuse of the new poverty in our midst. But even if one<br />
coulid ignore the human tragedy involved and no-one in this<br />
room ignores it the sheer economic cost of unemployment,<br />
and specifically the tremendous fiscal burden the provision<br />
of unemployment benefits pla~ es on the Budget is something<br />
which cannot be overlooked.<br />
So beyond our deep philosophical commitment there<br />
are pressing and profound reasons why reform of the social<br />
welfare system occupies a central position in our total<br />
approach to government and such a high priority in the<br />
application of that approach.<br />
I should take this opportunity to thank the Council<br />
for its participation and contribution to the work of the<br />
National Economic Summit in April.<br />
The views put by the President, Mr Bruce McKenzie,<br />
were significantly reflected in key sections of the Summit<br />
Communique. </p>
<p>In calling for all-round restraint, the Communique<br />
specifically stated:<br />
While the Summit recognises the difficulties for<br />
Australian society in meeting the increasing costs of<br />
social security, deprived groups must not be subject<br />
to the restraints mentioned above. It remains the<br />
overwhelming desire of th" nation to ensure that those<br />
in genuine need are adequately supported, whether they<br />
be the sick, the aged, the disabled, the unemployed or<br />
the impoverished. To this end, the Summit believes<br />
that a real improvement of their entitlements should<br />
be a major priority."<br />
I believe that my Government has honoured both the<br />
spirit and the letter of this important section of the<br />
Communique, as well as of the Communique as a whole.<br />
The Summit recognised that the reduction of<br />
unemployment remained the over-riding problem we face.<br />
When we took office there were more than 700,000<br />
people looking for work. That figure is more than double<br />
the number of people looking for work when the Fraser<br />
Government took office. An increase of 400,000 unemployed<br />
people was the legacy of seven years of fighting inflation<br />
first. It is only through a return to steady economic<br />
growth that long term jobs can be created, and that the<br />
living standards of all Australians can be raised. Our<br />
Budget has provided the framework for this economic growth.<br />
It has provided an adequate, but not excessive stimulus to<br />
economic activity. We have established policies designed to achieve<br />
growth, while reducing inflati'on. As the private sector<br />
recovers we are determined tb ensure that the public sector<br />
does not contribute to excessive pressure on interest rates.<br />
Higher inflation or interest rates would threaten the<br />
sustained economic recovery that is necessary if<br />
unemployment is to be reduced.<br />
In May we announced the introduction of the<br />
Community Employment Program, which will be used to create<br />
jobs that will benefit the community. This program wil~ l<br />
give priority to those CES registrants who have been<br />
unemployed for at least nine months, those who have never<br />
worked, and those most grossly disadvantaged in the labour<br />
market, such as Aborigines. Furthermore we will guarantee<br />
that women will be given-equal access to jobs created under<br />
the program. The Government has initially allocated $ 300<br />
million, which will be used to create 40,000 new jobs in<br />
1983/ 84. In a full year the program will create 70,000 </p>
<p>4.<br />
jobs. This is in addition to the $ 100 million allocated<br />
* under the Wage Pause Program, which is expected to create<br />
10,000 jobs. Altogether we will be spending $ 958 million on<br />
employment and training programs in 1983/ 84 an increase of<br />
per cent on 1982/ 83 expenditure. In total we expect<br />
employment to grow by about 90,000 over the course of<br />
1983/ 84. But as well as improving job prospects for the<br />
unemployed we have also taken the first steps towards<br />
significantly increasing the assistance available while<br />
people are unemployed. In particular:<br />
We have taken a major stop towards fulfilling our<br />
election commitment of bringing the single adult<br />
benefit rate into line with the pension. By May<br />
1984 the benefit rate will have increased by some<br />
22,1 in a little over a year. From now on it will<br />
be indexed. This is in stark contrast to the<br />
action of the previous Government, which removed<br />
indexation for this benefit, and reduced its real<br />
value. In addition we have doubled the amount of income<br />
the unemployed may receive withcut any loss of<br />
benefit. We will significantly assist those beneficiaries<br />
who have children, by our decision to increase<br />
additional benefits For children by 20.1, and we<br />
shall extend Mothers/ Guardians Allowances to single<br />
unemployment beneficiaries with children.<br />
Young unemployed people will get an additional<br />
$ 5.00 per week from November. Apart from the $ 4.00<br />
which the Fraser Golvernment. managed to find in<br />
its 1982 pre-election budget, this is the only<br />
increase that has occurred since 1975.<br />
Finally, in recognition of the difficulties facing<br />
those people living in remote areas, we will<br />
introduce a remote area allowance from May 1984<br />
which will benefit all, pensioners and beneficiaries<br />
in those areas whose incomes are too low to benefit<br />
from similar assistance provided through the tax<br />
system. This package of job creation and income security<br />
initiatives reflects the very high priority the Government<br />
has assigned to assisting the unemployed, despite the<br />
difficult budgetary circumstances we faced on coming to<br />
office.<br />
I </p>
<p>The second major priority in framing the welfare<br />
budget has been assistance for children of low income<br />
families. Because additional pension for children is not<br />
indexed, and was not regularly adjusted by the previous<br />
Government, it had fallen by some 35 per cent in real terins<br />
since 1975. Assistance for the children of pensioners will be<br />
increased by 20% 1 from November, which will go part of the<br />
way to meeting this shortfall.<br />
Assistance is also being increased for children of<br />
non-pensioners, by increasing the level of Family Income<br />
Supplement and relaxing its income test. This means, for<br />
example, that from March next year a family with 2 children<br />
on $ 11,000 per year will receive a supplement of almost $ 93<br />
per week, which is more than double the current rate.<br />
Thus our main priorities in the welfare area have<br />
been the unemployed and low income families with children,<br />
who have not benefited from indexed payments. Both these<br />
groups suffered in recent years through very significant<br />
decreases in the real level of assistance.<br />
The general pension rate, by contrast, is indexed<br />
in line with the CPI, which has meant that over the last 6<br />
months pensioners have received an income increase of nearly<br />
7A', while average weekly earnings have increased by only<br />
But the inequities and inadequacies of the system<br />
will not be removed simply by increases in the general<br />
pension rate. If no account is to be taken of need, then<br />
the inherent inequities will become entrenched and it will<br />
be impossible to increase the rate for those most in needthat<br />
is, for the vast majority of pensioners. In this<br />
regard it is important that the pensioners themselves<br />
understand the arithmetic of changes to retirement<br />
allowances that have been in~ tiated by the Government.<br />
Priorities demand that we begin our income security<br />
reforms by focussing on increased expenditure for the<br />
neediest. And that is what we have done.<br />
In the May Economic Statement we began to tackle<br />
inequities in the pension system with the revised income<br />
test arrangements for pensioners over 70. This was<br />
explicitly done to enable welfare expenditure to be directed<br />
to those individuals most in need. Its introduction only<br />
affects those with substantial private income married<br />
pensioners with private incomes below $ 500 per week are<br />
still eligible for a part pension. </p>
<p>In the Budget we have followed up this first<br />
initiative with a further reform to the pension system. I<br />
am talking about the intrcduction of the Assets Test. It is<br />
simply unfair that people with substantial assets are able<br />
to receive a full pension, while others miss out because<br />
they have a small income, even if they aen sest<br />
fall back on. Clearly this situation is completely out of<br />
line with the Government's objective of a just distribution<br />
of social welfare payments. It has allowed an increasing<br />
number of people to circumvent the income test through<br />
artificial avoidance schemes.<br />
The details of the assets test on pensions are<br />
being worked out, and we are consulting with ACOSS and other<br />
interested groups before taking final decisions on this<br />
matter. Nonetheless I should remove any misunderstanding<br />
about the impact of the new arrangements on pensioners with<br />
little means. The great majority of pnierwllnot be<br />
disadvantaged by the assets test. After taking account of<br />
the " free-area" for the pensicn, a single pensioner will be<br />
able to own non-exempt assets valued at up to $ 17,000 and<br />
still be entitled to a full pension, while a married<br />
pensioner couple will be able to receive the full pension<br />
with non-exempt assets up to $ 28,500. It should be<br />
emphasised that these figures do not include a pensioners<br />
home, car or personal effects.<br />
The Government has also acted to rectify the<br />
inequitable tax treatment of superannuation lump sums. Less<br />
than half the workforce is covered by superannuation<br />
schemes, and the considerable tax advantages enjoyed under<br />
the previous arrangements meant that burden of revenue<br />
collection was not being shared fairly. Recipients of lump<br />
sums-have also been advantaged vis-a-vis people who receiv~ e<br />
their superannuation in the form of a pension.<br />
Together with the asdets test, this will<br />
substantially reduce the double-dipping that has been<br />
occurring, whereby people largely escape tax on their lump<br />
sums and then qualify for Social Security pensions.<br />
Having said this, I would add that double-dipping<br />
is nut the only reason for the assets test and the new tax<br />
arrangements for lump sums. These measures are designed to<br />
remove fundamental inequities in both the tax and pension<br />
systems. And, of course, each of these specific decisions<br />
must be placed in their wider context of a complete and<br />
continuing program for reform.<br />
Removing the inequities of the social welfare<br />
system and removing the inequities in the tax system go hand<br />
in hand. They are both part of our total approach to making<br />
Australia a more just society. </p>
<p>And all Australians have to realise that unless our<br />
taxation reforms succeed, our efforts to reform the social<br />
welfare system and to enhance the benefits available to<br />
those most in need could eventually fail.<br />
If those whose need is least-., if those already in a<br />
highly privileged position, refuse to forego even the most<br />
marginal part of their privileges, then there can be no<br />
relief, no real improvement, for the overwhelming majority<br />
of those whose sole or main source of income is their social<br />
security entitlement. If we are to raise significantly the general level<br />
of benefits to all who need them, then we have to reduce the<br />
special and unnecessary privileges of some.<br />
That is a fact of life in these times of great<br />
economic difficulty. But it will remain a fact indeeJ,<br />
its force will increase as the number of Australians<br />
dependent on the pension grows as a proportion of those in<br />
the work-force. Let me be more specific about the demographic<br />
facts. Over the next ten years the number of working age<br />
Australians for each person over 65 will drop to about<br />
Looking further into the future, fifty years from now this<br />
number is expected to drop to about 3.<br />
So in the nineteenth May Statement and in the<br />
Budget itself we have set in train decisions whose real<br />
results will come not this financial year or even next, but<br />
will begin to bear fruit in the years ahead.<br />
It would be tragic if short-sighted consideraton of<br />
short-term political or personal advantage were allowed to<br />
retard the reform of the social welfare and taxation systems<br />
upon which we have embarked.<br />
This Government stands ready to consult with the<br />
community and representative groups to improve measures upon<br />
which a decision in principle has been taken, or to remove<br />
unforeseen anomalies that may be involved in those<br />
decisions. We have given abundant proof of that.<br />
But I make it quite clear that we cannot, as a<br />
responsible Government, submit to the piece-meal demolition<br />
of fundamental Budget proposals or to threats such as have<br />
been made by the Opposition in the Senate. If these threats<br />
are carried out, the whole strategy of the Budget would be<br />
undermined and the principles of justice and equity for<br />
which we stand would be liegated.<br />
We have taken difficult decisions, to re-order<br />
priorities and redistribute resources towards the<br />
disadvantaged. </p>
<p>Some of the things we wanted to do and to which we<br />
have a continuing commitment, have had to be delayed. There<br />
. are real constraints on the pace of change. Deficits, for<br />
example, have to be limited. But we shall continue the<br />
process of re-ordering priorities and improving equity, and<br />
in the future there will be further opportunities to<br />
redistribute more in favour of the disadvantaged.<br />
But that can happen only if the reform measures we<br />
have undertaken already are accepted, most immediately by<br />
the Senate, but ultimately by the people of Australia<br />
themselves as being necessary for the creation of a more<br />
just, more equal, more humane society.<br />
The current Labor Government believes that only a<br />
more just Australia, an Australia that is seen by most of<br />
its citizens as a fair society, will be able to sustain the<br />
changes that are necessary for a return to sustained growth<br />
and high levels of employment.<br />
I trust you can see that the Government has<br />
achieved a great deal in only six months in office. We are<br />
committed to further increases in assistance to the needy<br />
members of the community, and further reforms of the<br />
taxation system. Your theme for this conference justice<br />
and equity well express the goals for a revitalised and<br />
renewed Australia which my Government has set for itself. </p>
<p>-Y 4<br />
,,, AU6TK'ALA , L<br />
I<br />
PR E STE i<br />
r B 1 g!<br />
THE FOLLOWING ARE CHANGES MADE TO THE PRIME MINISTER'S<br />
SPEECH TO THE AUSTRALIAN . COUNCIL OF SOCIAL SERVICE CONGRESS,<br />
8 SEPTEMBER 1983.<br />
Page paragraph But the inequities and inadequacies of the system<br />
will not be removed simply by increases in the general<br />
pension rate. If no account is to be taken of need, then<br />
the inherent inequities will become entrenched and it will<br />
be impossible to increase the rate for those most in need<br />
that is, for the vast majority of pensioners. In this<br />
regard it is important that the pensioners themselves<br />
understand the arithmetic their own constituency. The<br />
country's capacity to provide decent levels of assistance to<br />
the majority, who in fact need such assistance from the<br />
community, requires that we do not dissipate those limited<br />
resources on those who do not requiile such assistance. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
