<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4802</transcript-id>
    <title>PRESS CONFERENCE AT BOULEVARD HOTEL, SYDNEY, COMMUNIQUE, 1 SEPTEMBER 1978</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/09/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004802.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS CONFERENCE AT BOULEVARD HOTEL, SYDNEY,: COMMUNIQUE<br />
1 September 1978<br />
Communique: ( Ke-c. 6,_<br />
LThe Liberal Party Parliamentary and Organisational leaders<br />
meeting in Sydney on 31st August and 1st September discussed<br />
the longer term objectives for Australia now that substantial<br />
progress has been mad e in breaking the back of inflation.<br />
It has been inflation that has been the biggest single factor<br />
preventing Australia's economic recovery.<br />
The leaders agreed that it would be dangerous to lower the<br />
anti-inflationary campaign, but that the time had come to<br />
identify more precisely the goals to which Australia should<br />
be moving.<br />
The meeting ranged over many of the important political and<br />
social issues facing Australia today and that challenge for<br />
the future. Topics discussed included our domestic economic<br />
recovery, strengthening the private sector, international trade,<br />
industrial relations, the increasing impact of the technological<br />
age, social welfare, fuel energy policy, Aboriginal Affairs,<br />
infrustructure financing, and national development.<br />
The meeting exchanged ideas on the Liberal approach to many<br />
of these issues at State and Federal level. The leaders spent<br />
some time examining the social and industrial impact of<br />
technological change and innovation. They agreed that this<br />
was an issue that required detailed attention from both<br />
Parliamentary Party and the Organisation. The leaders were<br />
optimistic about the contribution of technology. They were<br />
convinced that, in the longer term, it would create new-job<br />
opportunities in Austalia. At the same time, it would make<br />
Australia more competitive in domestic and in overseas markets.<br />
It would also strengthen the private sector.<br />
The total community needed to understand the challenges and<br />
the opportunities. There was a need for a better understanding<br />
of what is in the real interest of Australia's working men and<br />
women throughout the whole industrial area.<br />
The leaders were confident that Australia would cope with the<br />
computer age, and benefit substantially from it. Unfortunately,<br />
there were too many people with narrow vision those simply<br />
concerned with undermining the Federal Government's programme<br />
for recovery. The opponents of the Liberal Party were trying<br />
to destroy Australia's faith in the future.<br />
The leaders agreed that the Liberal Party needed to strengthen<br />
still further its partnership with the electorate so that the<br />
whole nation understood and backed the Liberal plans for<br />
Australia's development and its vision for a better way of<br />
life for all Australians. / 2 </p>
<p>The Prime Minister said that the Federal Government was looking<br />
forward to early decisions through the loan council in respect<br />
of infrastructure finance.<br />
The Liberal leaders endorsed the overall objectives of the<br />
recent Federal Budget as part of the strategy for reducing<br />
inflation and interest rates, and contributing to Australia's<br />
economic recovery. They were optimistic about the economic<br />
future based on today's policies. In particular, they noted<br />
the strengthening prospects for rural industry. The best<br />
prospects for 15 years. Further, there was every indication<br />
that Australia would increasingly become a major resource<br />
supplier--even more important than we now are--to the world.<br />
They recognised that there weresame immediate problems, not<br />
least the social difficulties associated with unemployment<br />
that needed careful and sympathetic monitoring and attention<br />
by Governments.<br />
All the leaders were united in the determination that Liberal<br />
policies designed for the long-term health of Australia should<br />
not be sacrificed to short-term political expediency. These<br />
responsible Liberal policies stood in marked contrast to the<br />
socialistic approaches being reconfirmed by the Australian<br />
Labor Party.<br />
The two-day exchange of views have made a significant<br />
contribution to the acknowledgment of objectives, and to<br />
closer co-operation of both the Organisation and Parliamentary<br />
levels of the Party. It has strengthened the Party's vision,<br />
strengthened its resolve, and underlined the essential unity<br />
of the Liberal Party.<br />
And Australia,. with Liberal policies, could move forward<br />
confidently into the 1980' s. 11~ 000---<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
That is the communique which we all put our names to this<br />
morning after two days of very useful and constructive<br />
discussions, and there are one or two aspects that I think<br />
I'd like to emphasise.<br />
one of the things which is now widely recognised by the States<br />
is the very real degree of co-operation between the Commonwealth<br />
and the States in a number of areas that are, in a sense, very<br />
important to government, very important to the well-being of<br />
people. But because of the wqy they have been handled they are<br />
not matters of major political contention.<br />
We know what has happened in the past overseas in submerged<br />
lands legislation, for example, and the arguments between<br />
governments, High Court decisions apparently taking power<br />
and influence away from States and areas that have traditionally<br />
been their concern. It has been left to this government to<br />
resolve that in co-operation with the states, by practical<br />
arrangements made by practical people in sorting out solutions / 3 </p>
<p>to the problems as a result of that High Court decision.<br />
Over two or three Premier's Conferences very great progress<br />
has been made. Agreement in principle has been reached,<br />
agreement in practical areas has been reached.<br />
In other areas also we have co-operated with the States in<br />
treaties powers, being prepared to have Federal causes in<br />
treaties, keeping the States in close consultation through<br />
the format of stages of treaties. These are new hallmarks<br />
in the development of Commonwealth and State co-operation,<br />
which augurs well the good government of this Commonwealth.<br />
There is one other innovatory area, which originally camne<br />
out of the advocacy of Sir Charles Court. That is infrastructure<br />
financing to enable State instrumentalities in certain<br />
circumstances to borrow overseas to assist in the forward<br />
development of major resource projects, energy projects,<br />
matters that are going to add to the commercial strength,<br />
to international paymen~ ts of Australia, and I think you<br />
know that the States have all put forward a number of<br />
projects that they hope will be financed under these<br />
arrangements. The total list costs $ 2,500,000,000 and<br />
the States all know that that total list can't be met but<br />
once, and officials have been having meetings since the<br />
last Premiers Conference, and there is to be a further<br />
meeting in about a week's time, and we're instructing<br />
our officials that flowing from that the matter will then<br />
come back to Ministers and Premiers and myself for decisions<br />
in relation to priorities in what might be done. In<br />
Western Australia for example there are projects in relation<br />
to the Dampier-Perth gas pipeline, the Pilbara power<br />
development, Worsely rail and water supply; the NSW power<br />
stations, port facilities for coal export; Victoria<br />
power generation project which is a very major project_.-a.<br />
world trade centre project; Queensland the Hay Point<br />
coal loaders and power development; South Australia<br />
Redcliffe Petro-Chemicals; Tasmania Hydro electric<br />
power generation projects and in Tasmania other water<br />
supply projects.<br />
I believe that if we can assume that Premiers and the States<br />
and the Commonwealth are going to come to agreement about<br />
infrastructure financing, raising funds overseas for this<br />
kind of infrastructure development, that that will be one<br />
of the things that will help to herald in an exciting new<br />
period of development for Australia--looking forward into<br />
the future. I'm quite certain that we are now setting the<br />
scene in Australia for an exciting decade of further<br />
development in the 1980' s and beyond. The determination<br />
and views of the Liberal Party", which Are firmly committed<br />
to achieving that kind of result, are going to be a great<br />
help to Australia. I'm certain that we have an exciting<br />
time ahead of us, with Australia running a good and wellbalanced<br />
economy, being well able to look after herself<br />
in the international economic community, but at the same<br />
time because our inflation rate is down, our economy is<br />
well run, we'll be able to take advantage of opportunities<br />
that become available in a larger share of world trade, / 4 </p>
<p>a larger share of resources for investment and development,<br />
our industries will become more competitive, have a larger<br />
share of our domestic market, and will at the same time<br />
become increasingly competitive and able to penetrate other<br />
markets overseas. Therefore, I look to the future with a<br />
very great degree of optimism, and I believe all Australians<br />
should share in that.<br />
Question: Prime Minister, you mentioned the States had put in requests<br />
for overseas borrowing totalling $ 2,500 million dollars.<br />
Can you see indications of wAat limits might be placed<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
That's over a period of years. Some of the projects are so<br />
large they are phased over many years. I don't want to<br />
pre-empt the report that is coming to us as a result of the<br />
joint work of Commonwealth and State officials. There will<br />
be advice on that. I just mentioned that to you to indicate<br />
the size and scope of the projects that, in a sense, are on<br />
the shopping list, and also the hope that it's not a<br />
hope, it will be a reality that in a very short space of<br />
time the Government should be in a position to make decisions<br />
about these matters.<br />
Question: Mr Fraser, you said that the Leaders were optimistic about<br />
the contribution of technology, and it was announced this<br />
morning from Canberra that a technology inquiry, an automation<br />
inquiry, would be held. Why didn't the Government announced<br />
that last Thursday when the Cabinet decision was made at the<br />
height of the Telecom dispute?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
You would have to ask the Ministers concerned about that.<br />
The Government makes decisions and it is generally left to<br />
the Ministers to make the announcement when they want to.<br />
Question: You don't think it would have helped the Telecom dispute and<br />
eased the tension somewhat?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
When you have a full understanding of the totality of the<br />
discussions that have gone on,., I don't really think so, no.<br />
We already had the Clarkson pr6posals before us. They were<br />
further developed by Commissioner Geudrin on Sunday, and<br />
the basis of the Clarkson six points were maintained in that<br />
discussion on Sunday. It was over a year earlier than that<br />
that members of that particular union had been given a ten </p>
<p>year guarantee against retrenchment as a result of technological change.<br />
I think I made the point yesterday that on advice available to me, it<br />
is expected that employment in the Telecom area will expand as a result<br />
of technical change and innovation, because while there can be some<br />
changes in employment, new technology will enable Telecom to offer more<br />
services, different services that businesses or people will want to buy<br />
and share in. Overall, therefore they would be doing more business and<br />
employ-ing more people. This is one of the things that will clearly come<br />
from new technology. Just as today we have things in our home that 30 years<br />
ago weren't dreamed of, so too in 30 years time I believe there will be<br />
other things in peoples' homes and part of their daily lives which today<br />
we don't think of. But that's part of the continuing change.<br />
our task is, through the Department of Productivity, through other<br />
programmes of Government, to try and make sure that we keep up that we ' re<br />
in the forefront. Our scientists have put us in the forefront of<br />
Interscan, which has been accepted worldwide as the best possible<br />
system for international aviation. Now the task is to make sure that<br />
Australian industry capitalises on the production potential of that,<br />
and that we haven't just invented something, put something together through<br />
the work of CSIRO and other scientists, which then is developed by the<br />
industry of other countries.<br />
The Government, as you know, is backing the Interscan project very substantially,<br />
and a very noted Australian Sir Ian MacLellan has become Chairman of<br />
the Guiding Light ( inaudible) of the Interscan project and development.<br />
That's one particular area, but we need to sort out those things which<br />
Australia can do, not well, but better than anyone else, and make sure<br />
that we go for our lives and are successful.<br />
QUESTION:<br />
When can we expect the decisions to start flow on the new borrowing arrangements<br />
for infrastructure?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I think we're very near those decisions, because there have been many<br />
meetings of officials, whose projects have been put forward, and the<br />
report that we are expecting after the next meeting is designed to put<br />
us in a position of making decisions. Then matters will flow from there.<br />
QUESTION: You mentioned the consultation with the Premiers. Are you suggesting<br />
another Premiers' Conference be put into view?<br />
PRIM] E MINISTER:<br />
I think that in relation to these things it is very likely that a<br />
discussion either Premiers Conference or Loan Council, because they'll<br />
be Loan Council procedures which enable the infrastructure borrowing<br />
to proceed but I think we've got to look at the officials' report<br />
to see to what degree they have got unanimity, how much of the decision<br />
making is left to members of the Loan Council. So, let's not pre-judge<br />
the report, but I will be very disappointed indeed if the report doesn't<br />
put governments in the position of making decisions pretty rapidly. A6 </p>
<p>QUESTION: Prime Minister, the thrust generally of this communique seems<br />
to me to be far more optimistic about the future in terms<br />
( remainder inaudible).<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
No, I don't think so. I think that if you note soem of the<br />
things that I have been saying, and other people have been<br />
saying We have spoken about the five percent inflation<br />
rate being a breakthrough, that the Budget is a watershed in<br />
terms of economic recovery and success that's not unnatural,<br />
it has been put together more. We've spent a day and a half<br />
talking about the future what we can jointly do to make<br />
these things a reality in even a shorter space of time and<br />
so in this document I think we have a consensus of views that have<br />
been emerging over recent weeks. You see a number of things<br />
have happened:<br />
We had the Budget, and that was well received in financial<br />
communities. Let me emphasise this was not just large<br />
investors, there are tens of thousands of small investors<br />
in Australia who have their savings out in that stock<br />
market. For years the market has been in a pretty<br />
desultory position with things just jogging along, but now,<br />
quite plainly, there is a degree of enthusiasm there.<br />
Then we had the Commonwealth Loan result, which was the<br />
best result in history, with I'm sorry for the technical<br />
jargon over 70% of the money subscribed by the non-bank<br />
public. For technical reasons, there there is no need for<br />
me to go into, the Reserve Bank always regards it as a much<br />
more successful loan if a high proportion of it is subscribed<br />
by the non-bank public, rather than being taken up by -Ehe<br />
Trading Bank. That again is a watershed.<br />
So a number of things have come together: a Treasury estimate<br />
of 5% inflation; the Budget itself, which has re-confirmed an<br />
anti-inflationary policy where, because of talk going on not<br />
from the Government, but I think from other circles there<br />
might have been sme doubt as to whether we would maintain<br />
the policy in the middle months of the Winter, but now those<br />
concerns are put aside; then the success of the loan. All<br />
these things come together, and when people start to come into<br />
my office and say " There * are not many countries overseas<br />
that we'd like to invest in." There is our own country of course..<br />
This was a member of a major United States corporation which<br />
is involved in Australia, and in a very responsible way and a<br />
way which is good for this countr~ y but he said " then there's<br />
Germany and Japan". I didn't say it, he said it. That really<br />
is putting Australia in respectable company, and that's something<br />
which I believe every Australian has every right to be proud of.<br />
We've got to make sure that we build on that and capitalise on<br />
it, because that's what's going to get this country moving again,<br />
/ 7 </p>
<p>re-establish confidence, not just in investors but in consumers<br />
and people out in country areas. Once that happens things will<br />
really start to hum.<br />
QUESTION: ( inaudible)<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
There was some discussion of the training. programmes--these are<br />
obviously monitored, changed, modified as necessary. I mentioned<br />
yesterday that we are spending very much more money on those<br />
training programmes this year than we were last year, and that<br />
about 110,000 people many of them young people are in<br />
training at any one time; that in the youth programmes over<br />
who are at on-the-job training keep the job at the end<br />
of the training programme. obviously it would be better if that<br />
was higher, but in terms of Australian and overseas<br />
experience the success rate is not too bad. We would have to<br />
be able to improve on that. I also mentioned, although it's<br />
too early to be categoric about, that the employment figures<br />
especially for the last month were marginally better than<br />
forecasts had indicated. It's too early to say whether that<br />
is going to indicate a trend or whether it's an aberration.<br />
Quite plainly, having Australian industry move forward thus<br />
establishing productive jobs for Australians in many different<br />
areas of activity, that's going to be the best thing to help<br />
the employment situation in this country. We have avoided a<br />
number of the mistakes that have been made by overseas countries,<br />
whereby subsidising labour directly in certain industries they<br />
locked labour, government and industry into uncompetitive<br />
enterprises. Training programmes, while helping a lot of<br />
people, have avoided that error and that's important tothe<br />
future well-being of this country. The Williams Inquiry<br />
into educational training Senator Carrick could have that<br />
in his hands. The decision which was announced today about<br />
Tony Street is also a further example of the Government's<br />
concern. We would hope that the Williams Inquiry would help<br />
us in devising future policies, determining what should be<br />
done, and making sure that the education system, for example,<br />
is well revised to meet the needs of Australia's young men<br />
and women through the rest of this century. So it's not just<br />
a question of standing off and watching with sympathy and<br />
concern, there is a good deal being done. There's much in<br />
train and the results of Inquiries which were established 18 months<br />
to two years ago in the Williams Inquiry. We how know when<br />
we are going to get the results * of it, and I hope that it will<br />
be the sort of inquiry that will., lead to action by State<br />
Governments and by Federal Government. So, it's not just an<br />
expression of concern there is a desire for action in these<br />
areas, as long as we do it in a way which enhances the well-being<br />
of people. / 8 </p>
<p>QUESTION: Prime Minister, was there any discussion about the possibility<br />
of a State election to be held in N'SW this year?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Oh, there was some discussion about the possibility of that,<br />
but not major discussion. The major discussion was about these<br />
particular issues I think there is-probably a general belief<br />
that there is going to be a State election. The Liberal Party<br />
will obviously fight back as hard as it knows how.<br />
QUESTION: Are they confident Prime Minister?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
The Liberal Party is always confident.<br />
QUESTION: The Liberal Party has always taken the attitude... ( inaudible).<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, I was holding a second press conference partly because<br />
I was asked to would I be available after the discussion<br />
this morning, and I said I would consider it. So I blame<br />
you for that, since I think you asked me the question, and<br />
I'm always willing to meet the press if they put the request<br />
in a nice way. Secondly, it was the nature of this discussion<br />
over the last two days. Very often the discussions, have been<br />
about internal organisational matters, which I don't think are<br />
of all that much concern and interest in the wider community.<br />
But over the last two days, contrary to what people might have<br />
thought, we have overwhelmingly spent the time discussing<br />
matters of intimate and great concern to all Australians, and<br />
having done that it becaupe very apparent that we should be talking<br />
about it. It hadn't originally been intended that there should<br />
be a communique. This communique was written as you know<br />
because we were waiting for it in the last stages of the conference,<br />
and it fully and adequately reflects I think what was discussed<br />
and said there. But it was one of the Liberal leaders not<br />
myself who suggested that there ought to be a formal communique<br />
because I think everyone felt that the discussion had been such<br />
a productive one and a useful one. 9 </p>
<p>QUESTION: Prime Minister, with the inflation rate down to 5% ( remainder<br />
question missed due to faulty tape)<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
( beginning of answer missed due to faulty tape)... There are not<br />
options in this. It is not one course or another. Because if<br />
you devote yourself only to unemployment and try to spend money<br />
to create jobs, you will end up with more unemployment. And that<br />
is what has happened in European country after European country,<br />
when they haven't given adequate attention to inflation. Now,<br />
getting inflation down, and getting interest rates down, will<br />
of itself proivde the circumstances in which private industry<br />
in Australia will be able to expand, will be able to invest<br />
and encouraged to invest, and investment will come into this<br />
country, and that will establish the preconditions which are<br />
necessary for getting down unemployment. Those countries that<br />
try to focus on unemployment and forget inflation have failed<br />
in both tasks, and failed dismally, to the immense cost of<br />
their own people. You can disguise it for a while, but you<br />
can't disguise it for too long. And the path we are taking<br />
is the path that will most quickly overcome the problem of<br />
unemployment. I'm not going to say that it's easy, or that<br />
we can get back to the 1950' s or early 60' s situation quickly,<br />
I know we ban't because circumstances have changed, and you<br />
can't play life over twice in the same way. But in terms of<br />
getting unemployment down I am absolutely certain that the<br />
policies we are pursuing are the ones that will achieve a<br />
desirable result that we all share, more quickly than any<br />
other path. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
