<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7214</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH PAUL LYNEHAM, IN KATHERINE, FOR 7.30 REPORT - 3 SEPTEMBER 1987</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/09/1987</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007214.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH PAUL LYNEHAM, IN KATHERINE, FOR<br />
7.30 REPORT 3 SEPTEMBER 1987<br />
E E 0 PROOF ONLY<br />
LYNEHAM: The Prime Minister's suggestion of a compact<br />
between white and black Australia came during an interview<br />
on Aboriginal community radio in Alice Springs and the<br />
timing of his public comments caught everyone, including<br />
Gerry Hand, the new Aboriginal Affairs Minister, by surprise<br />
not that Mr Hand was anything other than delighted.<br />
Indeed as the day wore on, taking the Hawke entourage north<br />
to Katherine and the Kalano Aboriginal Community, it was<br />
clear that the news of Bob Hawke's suggestion had spread<br />
quickly across the Territory and in many minds had already<br />
taken on the status of a firm commitment. But a commitment<br />
to what exactly? A cosy Claytons treaty aimed at a<br />
trouble-free Bicentenn'ary or a genuine bid to forge a new<br />
relationship between black and white? What's the essence of<br />
the Prime Minister's plan?<br />
PM: The essence is to try and establish in the minds of the<br />
Australian people that the time'. of European settlement<br />
important as it is and appropriate to be celebrated that<br />
200 years comes at the end of 40,000 years of Aboriginal<br />
history and culture and that if we are to properly celebrate<br />
in 1988 we must recognise, as non-Aborigines, the<br />
obligations and the commitments we have to them.<br />
LYNEHAM: would this involve a commitment on the part of the<br />
Government to help them more with things like health,<br />
education and housing?<br />
PM: What I've said is that in the period since we've been<br />
in office in real terms there's been an over 30% real<br />
increase in funding. So the commitment to more funding has<br />
been there. It's demonstrated. I don't have to say yes<br />
we'll do it. We've done that. I think we ought to<br />
continue, within the necessary economic constraints that are<br />
imposed upon government, to continue to do more. But I come<br />
back to the point I started with, Paul. If we think about<br />
this issue just in terms of money then we'll have missed a<br />
large part of the point. It's an attitudinal question. I<br />
think we've got to, as non-Aborigines, just understand, as<br />
I've tried to say from the time I've been in government,<br />
that this 1988, 200 years of European settlement, that that<br />
comes on top of a great history, a great culture, great </p>
<p>traditions of 40,000 years. The attitude has to be right.<br />
But we came here, we came into an existing civilisation if<br />
you like, an existing history and I want to get the<br />
attitudes right.<br />
LYNEHAM: Charles Perkins, Head of Aboriginal Affairs, says<br />
a compact, that sort of idea, is not good enough. He says<br />
we want a treaty that can be written into the Constitution<br />
for all time.<br />
PM: We're used to Charlie putting his points fairly<br />
directly and immediately. As I've said, I'm not trying to<br />
impose a particular view. I want to get the thinking<br />
started. LYNEHAM: But your th inking is, you said yesterday, a treaty<br />
doesn't appeal to you so much.<br />
PM: The main concern I have about it is that people think,<br />
they're insisting, it must be a treaty. They seem to have<br />
the view that the word itself is significant and I think if<br />
you get the attitudes right the words don't matter very much<br />
because you can say we've got a treaty. You can have a<br />
piece of paper and call it a treaty, you can have another<br />
and call it a compact but because one word has compact<br />
on top of it and one has treaty on the other is not going to<br />
mean something different. What it does mean<br />
LYNEHAM: In that case why not call it a treaty?<br />
PM: if you rouse undue expectations by a word, if people<br />
say that of itself is going to do something, I'm not sure<br />
that's wise. It's much more important that we get our sense<br />
of understanding right and then in that sense I'm not hung<br />
up about the word treaty, I'm not going to fight to the last<br />
ditch about that as such. I just have some sense that it's<br />
not the most appropriate word. But let's start thinking,<br />
and certainly I've had a discussion with Gerry Hand about<br />
this and I know he's starting to talk with others, let's<br />
talk about what's the best way of doing it. One suggestion<br />
for instance is that the concept could be embedded into<br />
legislation as part of the preamble to the legislation<br />
establishing the new Commission that we intend to establish.<br />
LYNEHAM: The Commission for Aboriginal Affairs next year?<br />
PM: It's suggested that that could be one way of getting it<br />
some legislative stature.<br />
LYNEHAM: Is that as good as it being in the Constitution?<br />
PM: A lot of things in the Constitution, just because they<br />
are there, don't mean a great deal. I think we're starting<br />
on completely the wrong approach. See what we're doing now,<br />
spending ten minutes talking about a word. It's just a<br />
wrong concept.<br />
LYNEHAM: Have you any thoughts about the idea of some sort<br />
of ceremony or special occasion along with this? </p>
<p>PM: I haven't addressed my mind to that, but provided that<br />
what came out of the processes of consultation could be seen<br />
to be acceptable broadly you're never going to have<br />
something acceptable to everyone then the concept of some<br />
ceremony could be appropriate.<br />
LYNEHAM: But you would see it, in the essence of it, a<br />
sense of white Australia making some recompense to black<br />
Australia? PM: Recompense in one sense, yes, but again don't let's<br />
just get the word of recompense, of payment. That is<br />
obviously a part. We've got to fund programs. But I keep<br />
coming back to the issue. If we just think of it in terms<br />
of money then we've avoided the essence of the problem. In<br />
that sense we've put, let's say that the budget is now $ 200<br />
million. You say, alright and you double it and make it<br />
$ 400 million and you've done your job. That's nonsense.<br />
I'm not saying that in the sense of avoiding the necessity<br />
for financial obligation. But in answer to the question you<br />
just asked, how do you change attitudes, it's not something<br />
you do overnight. But I think if you have Leaders of<br />
Government and I hope of Opposition, the political parties<br />
will accept the concept of obligation, accept the fact that<br />
as we go into 1988 we musn't think of it just as our 200<br />
years of European settlement but in some sense of continuum,<br />
of grasping something new and different into and onto a more<br />
ancient history and civilisation. If we understand the<br />
interraction of obligations then how long that takes, how<br />
you do it, I don't know, but I think it's important that we<br />
start it before we get into 1988.<br />
LYNEHAM: But what difference will the compact make to white<br />
Australia's big birthday party? Does Bob Hawke believe it<br />
will help us to celebrate with a clear conscience?<br />
PM: I think we won't celebrate 1988 properly, I don't think<br />
we'll celebrate properly if we either ignore the previous<br />
40,000 years or if we regard that pre-existing period as<br />
some sort of embarassment. We should recognise honestly<br />
that in our 200 years many injustices have been done to the<br />
Aboriginal people, many injustices, and that no-one is<br />
guiltless about that. It crosses Party lines, it crosses<br />
State lines, it crosses the lines of decades. We've all got<br />
an accumulated responsibility to what's happened and if you<br />
accept responsibility, whether it's in regard to Aborigines<br />
or any area where you've got the first step in being<br />
able to live properly is to recognise your responsibilities.<br />
You've then got a much more likely chance that you're going<br />
to do something about that responsibility and in a sense be<br />
at peace yourself. That's human nature isn't it.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
