<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>12010</transcript-id>
    <title>Interview with Jeremy Cordeaux, Radio 5DN</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/08/2001</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Subjects: illegal immigrants.</p>
<p>E&amp;OE................................</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>Prime Minister thank you so much for your time.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Good morning Jeremy.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>I know it must be probably one of the most difficult mornings of your Prime Ministership. Would you say that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Very difficult. Very difficult indeed.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>What's the latest you can tell us?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well the latest is that we are still in discussion with the Norwegian Government and the Indonesian Government. Our position remains that we do not have a legal obligation to take these people. We are ready to fly a helicopter to take doctors and other medical assistance out there and we remain ready to provide humanitarian assistance. That remains our position. But they do not have our, the ship does not have our permission to enter Australian waters.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>And he definitely needs that permission?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Of course, of course it needs our permission. Every country has the right to refuse entry to the vessel of another country of course. It's fundamental to a nation's sovereignty, a nation's control of its borders.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>Well the public opinion, the number of calls on our programme that I've taken over the last couple of days is absolutely unbelievable and except perhaps one or two, totally in support of your stance.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well that's encouraging but this is something that I've sought to do not on the basis of testing public opinion but on the basis of an instinctive feeling as well as an understanding of the law that Australia had to draw the line on this issue. It is not our legal responsibility. The people in question were picked up in the Indonesian search and rescue area, they were picked up by a vessel carrying a Norwegian flag and it is not our responsibility. They should in our view and on our advice be returned to Indonesia. That was their point of embarkation and according to our advice an Indonesia port was the nearest feasible port of disembarkation. Christmas Island does not have the capacity to take a large container vessel, there's no berth, it's just implausible for there to be any kind of civilised docking or landing there. So in those circumstances that is plainly unrealistic.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>Well it's not the Cuban Missile crisis, it is however I feel a defining moment in Australia's history as to what happens next. What do you think will happen next?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I obviously want the thing resolved in a sensible fashion. You will forgive me for not speculating , I don't think that is helpful. I am in discussion with the other countries and my ministers are. I don't really want to say any more at the moment.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>We have a report that the ship is on the move, have you heard that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I've heard a lot of reports, I don't at this stage want to answer any questions of that detail.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>Would you be reluctant and this is a fairly polarising and important issue in the minds of people, would you be reluctant to make this or would you be reluctant to see this made an election issue?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look I don't see this in the context of the election please. I'm doing what I think is right for Australia, I'm governing, I'm doing what is the best thing from the country's point of view and I'd be doing exactly the same thing irrespective of the timing of the election. It has nothing to do with the election and I don't seek to say anything else about that aspect of it.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>Okay. The discussions you've had this morning which has taken up all your time, can you tell me.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I've been in consultation with my colleagues and also I've had some communication with others. I don't really want to say anymore at this stage Jeremy please understand that I don't think it's appropriate just at the moment for me to say more than that.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>Now Prime Minister Joy Baluch who's the Mayor of Port Augusta has rung, would you take a call from her?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, I'm sorry I really have to now go back to another meeting, I'm not a in a position to do any talkback, I'm sorry.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>No I understand.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Please understand that this is a difficult morning and I would now really have to go back to a meeting, I am sorry I couldn't have a longer interview but I hope you will understand.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>I certainly understand.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>This is a morning that is quite difficult and quite important and if I could be forgiven and please apologise to the Mayor.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>And in the light of how difficult the morning is these few moments I'm very grateful for so thank you.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Thank you Jeremy.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
