<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9632</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP DOORSTOP AT INVERESK RAILYARD,LAUNCESTON, TASMANIA, 16 JUNE 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/06/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009632.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL I6 . Jun 2KSN. 1 Wu<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
DOORSTOP AT INVERESK RAILYARD, LAUNCESTON, TASMANIA, 16<br />
JUNE 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
PMV: I'll just take questions, I think that's the best way isn't it?<br />
J: Mr Keating, what's your reaction to the Democrat's decision that they<br />
are going to block the building industry sales tax from the Budget?<br />
PMV: I wasn't sure that they had made a decision about it. Well, it's a<br />
sensible extension of the base of the wholesale sales tax system, and<br />
it's a thing that Government's do, and the Government announced this<br />
In the Budget. And again, I think this is where the Senate needs to<br />
think about its position, and not overplay its hand to maintain its<br />
position as a House of review, but not to be there trying to knock out<br />
bits and pieces of the Government of the days Budget, which is not its<br />
function. The money function of the Commonwealth is with the House<br />
of Representatives and the Cabinet, and that's as it should be. That's<br />
the sensible measure, and I think that upon reflection, they will think<br />
it's sensible too.<br />
J: What impact will it have on the Budget if they go ahead with this?<br />
PMV: I'm not sure of the numbers we have there I think it's of the order of a<br />
couple of 100 million [ dollars], from memory. In year 1<br />
J: Will it affect your surplus?<br />
PMVI No. Well, it will affect it to some extent, but it won't affect the fact that<br />
there is a surplus, no,<br />
J: Can the Government afford to miss out on that revenue?<br />
PMV: The Government is there to support its Budget, and to get it through.<br />
J: If it's not passed by July 1, will you still collect the money? </p>
<p>I L L 6 .13 1,40F-u<br />
PM; Well, I just haven't had any briefing about it, and I am not anticipating<br />
the fact that at this stage, that the Democrats will vote against the<br />
measure in the Senate.<br />
J: They have said today they will.<br />
PM: They have said today they will?<br />
J: Yes.<br />
PM: Well, if they do, it would be a very inadvisable thing to do. I have<br />
made these points about the Senate before It's continually overplaying<br />
Its hand irresponsibly and unreasonably. This sort of measure<br />
is just a bit of sort of populism at the expense of the national<br />
management of the country, and populists won't be rewarded, I don't<br />
believe,<br />
J: How can the Government make up the revenue?<br />
PM: We'll see what the impact of it is how the Senate debate goes first,<br />
before we think about that.<br />
J: The French Ambassador held a press conference this morning and<br />
said that despite the delegation going, they won't change their minds<br />
is it a pointless exercise?<br />
PM: I don't think so. I think that there is a very clear point to it, that is, to<br />
express our anger at all of this, the fact that we and the other the<br />
nations of the Pacific feel it ( nuclear testing] is unnecessary, that it<br />
advances nobody's interests, and the best way of conveying that is<br />
directly. And, of course, the Foreign Minister will be with that<br />
delegation in Paris on Monday.<br />
J Is It an arrogant attitude they have, though?<br />
PM: I think so absolutely.<br />
J: Mr Keating, some Caucus members are reportedly preparing to put a<br />
motion on Tuesday that the Government' broaden its response to the<br />
French decision and to do things like recall the Australian Ambassador<br />
In Parls and expel the Ambassador from here...<br />
PM: I don't know that anyone is proposing measures such as that. We can<br />
see, and we have these sorts of debates.. . we had a debate about<br />
nuclear testing in the Pacific for many years in the Caucus. But I think<br />
that by and large, the Caucus will do that which is rational and<br />
sensible.<br />
J: What about the protest action last night that saw a truckload of manure<br />
dumped at the French Embassy? </p>
<p>T EL: 16 3uti. 9 5 2: 3 No.-0 13 P0 4,-0 T<br />
3<br />
PM: I mean, people do these things, and it's an indication, I think, of the<br />
objection that the people of this region of the world take to a decision<br />
which is made, and is not really fundamental to the security of the<br />
French nation, but something which is at the whim and caprice of<br />
French defence planners, which have obviously got the agreement of<br />
the French Government and President. And, you know, taking an<br />
objection there's going to be many more of them, I am sure, around<br />
the world, and you can see that with the reaction which President<br />
Chirac has had in the United States.<br />
J: You don't have a problem with that sort of protest?<br />
P M. I'm not here to endorse each particular action or not. Do I encourage<br />
people to be dropping loads of manure around? No, I don't. But, by<br />
the same token, I can understand where this feeling has come from.<br />
J: When will the delegation be going to Paris?<br />
PM: Monday.<br />
J: Will New Zealand be part of the delegation?<br />
PM: The delegation is not settled yet the composition.<br />
J: Would you like to see New Zealand be a part?<br />
PM: It's not settled I said that to you.<br />
J: The French Ambassador also this morning said that the French<br />
Polynesia, where they are testing, is part of France, so therefore they<br />
are doing it in their own backyard, and they have every right to do it?<br />
PM: Well, as they say tell it to the Marines. Tell that one to the Marines.<br />
J: Mr Howard has been critical of the Government's response he has<br />
accused Senator Evans of being an " old pussycat"?<br />
PM: Hasn't he become an old tart, John Howard, these days. Isn't he a<br />
dreadful old tart? I mean, two days ago he was saying that the<br />
Government's response is entirely appropriate, and after Mr Downer<br />
has emerged from the bathtub with his battleships, he is now saying<br />
that the Government needs to be tougher and stronger. This is<br />
somebody who believes that we should have the Queen of Great<br />
Britain as our Head of State who still believes in all those Colonial<br />
vestiges. Who is now telling us today that we should stand up to this<br />
power, France. This is someone who will be so obsequious in the<br />
presence of the French Minister, or a French President. I mean, he<br />
has been told this by his advertising agency. He's a shocking old tart.<br />
J: With the green issue being very important to the Bass electorate, so<br />
you think you have lost your seat already? </p>
<p>I1.6 L Jun z 5 2 : 33 N o.' 02! i3 P 0 51i 0<br />
4<br />
PM: Cut it out I have got such strength beside me here. No. I think -as<br />
always I mean, I was talking a moment ago about imagination, about<br />
support for regions who's supporting regions in this country? Who is<br />
supporting regional development? Who's rehabilitating the inner-cities<br />
of this country urban renewal? Only the Federal Labor Government.<br />
And also in the labour market programs support for those less<br />
advantaged. I made a point yesterday take the Commonwealth<br />
programs out of Tasmania, and Tasmanian employment has actually<br />
shrunk. So, on that basis, why would we believe that any of the seats<br />
that we hold are at risk? They're not, I'm sure.<br />
J: Would you say that this is a tough seat?<br />
PM: They are all tough, so what?<br />
J: Bass is only held by 42 or 43 votes it's quite likely to go the other<br />
way?<br />
PM: Well, after Sylvia's incumbency here, we will hold it by a bigger margin<br />
at the next election.<br />
J: How will your visit here today impact on the next allocation of Better<br />
Cities funding?<br />
PM; You get a minds eye picture of things when you move around<br />
Australia. I mean, I have been to most of the Better Cities programs<br />
seen them and then, I mean, as these things are actually discussed<br />
in the Cabinet room, as we talk about allocations, you see where the<br />
energy is, you know, where the imagination is, and you get a chance to<br />
make subsequent decisions. And often the things you think are going<br />
to be the goers are not, and the ones that may not, become the ones<br />
that work, for this reason. So, I think the job of Ministers and the Prime<br />
Minister particularly In these sort of things are to get around, see<br />
them, talk to people, get an idea of what is happening, and then you<br />
can make a better decision the next time around.<br />
J: But will there necessarily be any additional funding for this area?<br />
PM: Well, I have just announced some dollars today for Northern<br />
Tasmania, and you know, I think this will develop much the same way<br />
the others have. Look at Darling Harbour in Sydney the amount of<br />
private commitment to that now, is profound, but it wasn't true when it<br />
started. But then as it gets to critical mass, people fell that something<br />
is happening, and they are prepared to do more.<br />
J: Prime Minister, back to Paris who will the delegation be seeing?<br />
PM: That Is yet to be determined, but certainly the Foreign Minister<br />
certainly the Foreign Minister. Probably the Prime Minister.<br />
TEL </p>
<p>TEL: 16 Juri. 9 5 2 33 No 013 P. 1) 6,' 1-1-<br />
J: Carrying a message from you?<br />
PM:, No. It will be a message from the delegation, obviously.<br />
J: The international condemnation of the decision to resume the testing<br />
do you see it strengthening with that protest here at all?<br />
P M: You mean here in Australia?<br />
J: Yes.<br />
PM: I think so. I think that has happened already, and it is happening in<br />
these other countries, too.<br />
J, Just on a local issue, there is a billion dollar pulp mill proposal that the<br />
developers are saying won't go ahead until the Federal Government<br />
releases its pulp mill guidelines those were apparently going to be<br />
released when the Wesley Vale was up. They were going to be this<br />
month, but it has apparently been delayed what is happening with<br />
those?<br />
PM: They will be released I don't know exactly when they will be released,<br />
but they will be released because the Government does want to see<br />
the logical development of a forest products industry, and that means a<br />
concentration on regrowth and plantations, and to see the valueadding.<br />
I mean, our objection to woodchipplng Is that there is not the<br />
value adding, so the policy Is about value adding, and therefore we<br />
won't be value adding without these mills, and we won't have the milli<br />
without the guidelines. So the guidelines will be there.<br />
J: Given this proposal could be In doubt because the guidelines have<br />
been delayed, would you be moving on it?<br />
PM: Journalists say " the project's in doubt" you are not entitled to say<br />
things like that, because I am somebody who has heard all those sorts<br />
of claims over the years from journalists, and I know that they are<br />
empty.<br />
J: Do we know when these guidelines are going to be released?<br />
PM: We probably do, I I had any notice of the question. But I haven't, but<br />
let me say that I will take it on notice.<br />
ends. A </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
