<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18515</transcript-id>
    <title>&quot;We are serving our national interest in Afghanistan&quot;, Speech to the Australian Strategic Policy Institute and Boeing National Security Luncheon, Canberra</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/04/2012</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Some of you here will remember that the Council of the Australian Strategic Policy Institute met for the first time in late winter 2001  -  less than a fortnight before the September 11 attacks on the United States.</p>
<p>One thing that did not change after September 11 was Australia's need for the work of an Institute such as this.</p>
<p>Independent and non-partisan, of course.</p>
<p>But more: informed and informative.</p>
<p>Giving us the possibility, at least, of a public conversation which is more empirical than opinionated  -  and in strategic policy, this is what we must have.</p>
<p>Here, the facts are a matter of life and death.</p>
<p>This is why, on several occasions in the past two years, I have spoken directly to the Australian people about our mission in Afghanistan.</p>
<p>My annual statement to the Parliament has been an important formal mechanism to engage the nation as a whole.</p>
<p>So have the Defence Minister's regular statements to the House.</p>
<p>And sadly, the deaths of Australians serving in Afghanistan have also been occasions for me to express the nation's grief and to restate the nation's resolve.</p>
<p>To reassure Australians not only about what we are doing there and why  -  but for how long.</p>
<p>For two reasons, this is another important time for an extended statement on our commitment to Afghanistan.</p>
<p>First, ever since 1915, April in Australia has been memory's season.</p>
<p>It is our most solemn national promise that in the morning of the 25th of this month, we remember the service of Australians in all the wars of our history.</p>
<p>And that remembrance amply includes the men and women of the Australian Defence Force who  -  alongside their civilian counterparts  -  are serving us now, in Afghanistan and around the world.</p>
<p>They more than meet the grave demands the ANZAC tradition makes of them.</p>
<p>And I am sure that in the period leading up to ANZAC Day, there will be renewed discussion of the strategy and policies which see our Defence Force committed overseas. </p>
<p>So this is a symbolically significant period for Australians  -  and it is a strategically significant period.</p>
<p>In the next four weeks, the nations that make up the International Security Assistance Force in Afghanistan  -  ISAF  - will make critical decisions about the future of the mission.</p>
<p>On Thursday, the Foreign Minister Senator Carr and Defence Minister Smith will participate in ISAF Ministerial discussions in Brussels.</p>
<p>And on 21 May, I will attend the NATO/ISAF Leaders Summit in Chicago.</p>
<p>There, I will put Australia's view on the key questions before the international coalition.</p>
<p>I believe it is important I explain to Australians the decisions the Government is making and the position we will take to the table this month and next.</p>
<p>This audience is more than familiar with the origin of our commitment to Afghanistan.</p>
<p>You know that successive Australian Governments have seen our national interest in making sure that Afghanistan does not again become a safe haven for terrorists.</p>
<p>That the September 11 attacks  -  and most of the terrorist attacks since which have targeted Australian interests directly or in which Australians have been killed  -  had links to Afghanistan.</p>
<p>You know too, that successive Australian Governments have stood firmly by our alliance with the United States, invoked after September 11, against a shared threat.  </p>
<p>And you know that Australia's commitment  -  in our national interest, with our ally  -  is part of a strategy which enjoys wide international support.</p>
<p>In coalition with 49 international partners  -  under a United Nations mandate  -  at the invitation of and in co-operation with the Afghan government.</p>
<p>These facts of the origin of our commitment to Afghanistan are widely known and the fact that they have endured since 2001 is widely known too.</p>
<p>This consistency of purpose must not be mistaken for persistence in a strategy which is not working.</p>
<p>Quite the contrary. </p>
<p>In reality the current international strategy for Afghanistan has only taken shape since 2009.</p>
<p>Two and a half years ago, in December that year, President Obama announced a new international strategy.</p>
<p>Based on counter-insurgency.</p>
<p>Backed by a surge of 30 000 US troops and increased contributions from NATO/ISAF nations.</p>
<p>And designed to facilitate transition: to prepare the Government of Afghanistan to take responsibility for its own security.</p>
<p>It was the right approach.</p>
<p>To quote ISAF's military commander, General Allen:</p>
<p>Throughout history, insurgencies have seldom been defeated by foreign forces.  Instead, they have been ultimately beaten by indigenous forces.</p>
<p>So in the long run our goals can only be achieved and then secured by Afghan forces.  Transition, then, is the linchpin of our strategy, not merely the way out.</p>
<p>This is why eighteen months ago, at Lisbon in November 2010, Australia, our international partners and the Afghan government laid out a clear process and a clear timeframe for transition of full security responsibility to the Afghan National Security Forces.</p>
<p>And why we committed to supporting Afghanistan's security and stability over the longer term.</p>
<p>This should be clear.</p>
<p>The requirements of the new international strategy led to the adoption of the timeline.</p>
<p>Not the other way around.</p>
<p>While the challenges in Afghanistan are significant and there will inevitably be setbacks, the new international strategy has been accompanied by security gains over the past year and a half.</p>
<p>Bin Laden is dead.</p>
<p>Most of al Qaeda's senior leaders have been killed or captured.</p>
<p>We have pushed al Qaeda's remaining leaders to the Afghanistan-Pakistan border area.</p>
<p>Their freedom of movement, and capacity to plan and execute terrorist operations from Afghan soil, have been significantly degraded.</p>
<p>We continue to see steady gains in the fight against the Afghan insurgency.</p>
<p>In some areas these are fragile and are not beyond reverse.</p>
<p>But in each month since May 2011, there have been fewer attacks by insurgents than in the same month the previous year.</p>
<p>Afghan forces are now leading more than a quarter of special operations and just under half of conventional operations.</p>
<p>We are also seeing progress in Uruzgan province  -  the main focus of Australia's contribution. </p>
<p>The Afghan National Army's 4th Brigade is increasingly capable of planning and conducting operations on its own and the Afghan security presence across the province is expanding. </p>
<p>The Brigade is conducting combined operations with the Afghan National Police.  And it is leading on many operations, with our Mentoring Taskforce in a tactical support role. </p>
<p>For example, Commander 4th Brigade oversaw a two-week operation to clear a contested valley last month.</p>
<p>Led by the 6th Kandak, this operation demonstrated the 4th Brigade's ability to plan, execute and sustain an operation over an extended period.  It was marked as a keen success. </p>
<p>The Brigade was able to disrupt insurgent resupply, to manoeuvre through an insurgent stronghold without taking major casualties  -  and to make contact with the enemy in an area the insurgency previously considered to be a safe haven.</p>
<p>Although we still face a dangerous enemy, this is the kind of progress we see  -  in Uruzgan and across the country.</p>
<p>And this view is increasingly shared by our Afghan partners.</p>
<p>With all this in mind, Australia, the international community and Afghan authorities have now reached another point where key decisions need to be made.</p>
<p>This is the vital business of the Chicago summit in May.</p>
<p>To review our progress in transition  -  to map out how we intend to complete the handover of security responsibility to the Afghan Government.</p>
<p>To ensure sustainment  -  to build the international commitment necessary to fund, train and support the Afghan National Security Forces after transition is complete.</p>
<p>And to highlight our long-term support  -  to recommit to and define our continued contribution in the years after 2014.</p>
<p>In Afghanistan, transition is already happening. </p>
<p>Today, around half of the population lives in areas where the Afghan National Security Forces have begun taking lead security responsibility.</p>
<p>The next stage of transition  -  tranche three  -  will be announced soon.</p>
<p>And it's likely that by the middle of next year, mid-2013, the fifth and final tranche of districts and provinces will have commenced transition.</p>
<p>ISAF has made clear that this will not mean the end of combat, combat support or training.</p>
<p>But I'm now confident Chicago will recognise mid-2013 as a key milestone in the international strategy.</p>
<p>A crucial point: when the international forces will be able to move to a supporting role across all of Afghanistan.</p>
<p>I also expect President Karzai to make an announcement on transition in Uruzgan and other provinces in the coming months, including which areas of Uruzgan will begin the process first.</p>
<p>Once started, this should take twelve to eighteen months.</p>
<p>And when this is complete, Australia's commitment in Afghanistan will look very different to that we have today.</p>
<p>We will have completed our training and mentoring mission with the 4th Brigade.</p>
<p>We will no longer be conducting routine frontline operations with the Afghan National Security Forces.</p>
<p>The Australian-led Provincial Reconstruction Team will have completed its work</p>
<p>And the majority of our troops will have returned home.</p>
<p>When transition is complete, the international community will need to continue to support the Afghan National Security Forces. </p>
<p>This is what we mean by ensuring sustainment.</p>
<p>The ANSF  -  which includes the police, the Afghan National Army and Afghan Air Force  -  is building up to a surge force of some 352,000.  </p>
<p>We expect the final size of the ANSF to be smaller than this.  </p>
<p>Indeed, the Government of Afghanistan, in consultation with ISAF, has made some initial decisions about likely future size and force structure.</p>
<p>Importantly, the ISAF Summit will discuss a funding arrangement for the costs of ensuring sustainment.</p>
<p>To maintain full responsibility for security in Afghanistan after 2014, the Afghan National Security Forces will need the right support  -  including funding and training  -  from the international community.   </p>
<p>In Chicago, I will be arguing strongly for broad and substantial international support. </p>
<p>And I will go to Chicago prepared for Australia to pay our fair share.</p>
<p>Australia will also be prepared to provide niche training to the Afghan National Security Forces after 2014.</p>
<p>We are already involved in institutional training, through the Afghan National Army Artillery Training School. </p>
<p>In future, we will support the proposed UK-led Afghan National Army Officer Academy.</p>
<p>We will maintain a role providing training and support to policing in Afghanistan.</p>
<p>The AFP will progressively refocus its police development efforts from training in Southern Afghanistan to institutional capability development of the Afghan National Police in Kabul.</p>
<p>And, finally, as I have stated previously, we are prepared to consider a limited Special Forces contribution  -  in the right circumstances and under the right mandate.</p>
<p>There may be a continuing role to train the ANSF to conduct  -  and to work alongside them in carrying out  -  counter-terrorism operations in Afghanistan.</p>
<p>Australia has an enduring national interest in ensuring that Afghanistan does not again become a safe haven for terrorists.</p>
<p>Reviewing progress in transition  -  and ensuring sustainment  -  are vital work for Chicago.</p>
<p>Stating our commitment to Afghanistan's human and economic development is vital too.</p>
<p>Strengthening the capacity of the Afghan government, economy and institutions will be essential to ensuring that the gains made to date are not reversed. </p>
<p>Sustaining development and growing the economy will be enormous challenges in the years ahead.</p>
<p>The people of Afghanistan enjoy greater freedoms and a better quality of life now than in 2001. </p>
<p>In that time life expectancy has increased by five years to 48 today.</p>
<p>85 per cent have access to basic health care services, compared to 10 per cent under the Taliban.</p>
<p>Over 7 million children, including 2.5 million girls, are now enrolled in school.</p>
<p>But clearly, development and capacity-building programs will need to continue well beyond 2014.</p>
<p>Above all, Afghanistan must grow economically, including by developing its mineral resources.</p>
<p>Mining, education and agriculture will be crucial sectors  -  all areas in which Australia can offer some technical expertise.</p>
<p>Like many in Afghanistan, I believe that a successful democratic transition at the end of President Karzai's second term will be a critical point in the development of Afghanistan's democratic norms.</p>
<p>Previous elections in Afghanistan have been criticised and many in Afghanistan and the international community have urged electoral reform. </p>
<p>Electoral assistance will continue to be an important focus of the Australian aid program. </p>
<p>We will maintain our support to Afghanistan's Independent Electoral Commission. </p>
<p>During my visit to Afghanistan in October last year, President Karzai and I discussed formalising a comprehensive, long-term framework for the future of the Australia-Afghanistan partnership.</p>
<p>Indeed we hope to be in a position to sign the agreement when we meet at the Chicago summit in May.</p>
<p>This will set out Australia's enduring partnership with Afghanistan in development  -  along with security, trade and investment, as well as cultural and people-to-people links.</p>
<p>The Government of Japan will host an important ministerial conference in Tokyo in July.</p>
<p>At Tokyo, the focus will be on the coordination of international assistance through to 2014 and beyond  -  and on the Afghan Government's strategy for sustainable development.</p>
<p>At Chicago, it is vital that the nations of the Coalition restate our commitment to this cause.</p>
<p>I will use the opportunity that the Chicago summit creates to announce the details of increased Australian development assistance to Afghanistan through to 2015-16  -  and of our commitment to maintain that contribution in subsequent years.</p>
<p>At Chicago and at Tokyo, the international community will meet in a spirit of mutual commitment  -  so these are also opportunities for the Government of Afghanistan.</p>
<p>Opportunities to demonstrate its determination that our mutual gains over the last decade in democracy, development, tackling corruption and protecting human rights are maintained.</p>
<p>Australia and the international community also have a key role to play in supporting political reconciliation within Afghanistan.</p>
<p>Reconciliation is not a precondition for successful transition  -  our strategy is designed to ensure Afghanistan can wage counter-insurgency beyond 2014.</p>
<p>To be part of a settlement, those looking to reconcile need to lay down their weapons, renounce violence, cut links with al Qaeda and accept Afghanistan's democratic constitution.</p>
<p>And by taking the fight to the insurgents, and strengthening the Afghan forces in that fight, we help create the conditions for a successful Afghan-owned and led process.</p>
<p>It is clear talks are in their very early stages.  They are likely to be long and complex and will inevitably involve setbacks.</p>
<p>We will continue to support these efforts to pursue reconciliation.</p>
<p>We will also continue to work for a secure external environment for Afghanistan.</p>
<p>Australia welcomes regional initiatives  -  such as the Istanbul Process  -  which bring together Afghanistan's neighbours to identify ways to improve regional cooperation, including on economic linkages.</p>
<p>And Pakistan is critical to Afghanistan's stability.</p>
<p>We well know that Pakistan has been at the frontline of the threat of violent extremism in its region. </p>
<p>Terrorist groups have attacked its people and Government.</p>
<p>Pakistan has launched numerous operations against these groups including in areas near the border with Afghanistan.</p>
<p>And in this fight the people and the military of Pakistan have suffered losses in the thousands, indeed the tens of thousands, over the last decade. </p>
<p>Nevertheless, there is also no doubt that parts of Pakistan are being used by terrorist groups.</p>
<p>Particularly in the Afghanistan-Pakistan border areas.  </p>
<p>I am realistic about the threat that poses  -  realistic too about what can be done to limit that threat.</p>
<p>And our strategy, to build Afghanistan's own security forces, is founded in that realistic assessment of the country's future strategic environment.</p>
<p>The Government of Pakistan is in no doubt about Australia's determination  -  or our concerns.</p>
<p>We will work with Afghanistan  -  and with Pakistan  -  in those areas where our best judgement is that co-operation against terrorism which threatens both states is effective and real.</p>
<p>So for instance, there is scope to improve the tracking and control of items that assist terrorist groups in their attacks  -  as we see in the problem of Pakistani fertilisers being used to produce IEDs in Afghanistan.  </p>
<p>And we will do whatever else we judge best makes a difference in this difficult and sensitive task.</p>
<p>The people of Afghanistan face immense challenges for their national future.</p>
<p>Harsh natural terrain and turbulent history, tribal politics and the impact of thirty years of war, contemporary problems of corruption and narcotics.</p>
<p>National progress is the ultimate responsibility of the Afghan Government and people. </p>
<p>But the world can help  -  and Australia can do its part.</p>
<p>I welcome a genuine public debate on our commitment to Afghanistan.</p>
<p>I say this because I am confident that the Government's approach is one which is soundly in Australia's national interest.</p>
<p>As well, because our people are entitled to a genuine questioning of national policies in a matter so serious  -  and difficult  -  as this.</p>
<p>In 2011, eleven Australian soldiers were killed in action in Afghanistan and fifty were wounded.</p>
<p>Four died and ten were wounded as a result of attacks by rogue members of the Afghan National Army</p>
<p>Several other nations have also suffered such attacks. </p>
<p>These raised legitimate questions about the success of our mission to train the Afghan National Security Forces.</p>
<p>I also know that for many of our Defence Force families, the impact of these attacks was especially deep.</p>
<p>We are working with our Afghan partners to tighten vetting and screening and to implement a counter-infiltration plan.</p>
<p>I can assure Australians  -  through you  -  that we will do our very best to protect our soldiers from this threat.</p>
<p>Events of recent months have underscored the challenges for Australia and our ISAF and Afghan partners.</p>
<p>February's deeply unfortunate incident in which Islamic holy books were burned at Bagram Air Base caused offence to many in Afghanistan and around the world.</p>
<p>While in March, we were all appalled by the killing of Afghan civilians by a US soldier.  A shocking crime condemned by US and ISAF leaders alike  -  and by public demonstrations across Afghanistan.</p>
<p>These actions of an individual are no mark against the tens of thousands of courageous professionals deployed by Australia, the United States and other coalition countries.</p>
<p>Any more than attacks by rogue ANA members are a mark against the hundreds of thousands of patriotic Afghans training in uniform to build a capable national security force.</p>
<p>In March, an Australian Civilian Corps Adviser working with local communities on development activities in Uruzgan was injured in a suicide attack.</p>
<p>A reminder that our civilian staff in Afghanistan  -  our diplomats, aid workers, police and civilian corps workers  -  are also doing a magnificent job in dangerous circumstances.</p>
<p>And the weekend's renewed insurgent attacks in Kabul remind us that as the insurgency comes under greater sustained pressure in the field, the prospect of high-profile attacks aimed at disproportionate global public impact remains.</p>
<p>What remains too is the fact that these attacks were successfully countered by the Afghan National Security forces without substantial direct support from ISAF forces in Kabul.</p>
<p>An encouraging sign for the future of the counter-insurgency and for the success of transition to Afghan security lead.</p>
<p>And the shared endeavour between ISAF and Afghan forces across the country goes on.</p>
<p>None of this is easy.</p>
<p>There will be hard days ahead  -  there will be new days of grief. </p>
<p>We did not enter this conflict lightly and we do not persist in it without great care.</p>
<p>I know that the peoples of the world's democracies want to see their sons and daughters return from war. </p>
<p>This is as it should be.</p>
<p>I recognise that the global economic climate leads many, especially in Europe, to think of the pressing needs at home.</p>
<p>And I see that the people and leaders of Afghanistan rightly look forward to the day when they can truly lead in their own country. </p>
<p>These are considerations I weigh heavily, as do the leaders of all the ISAF nations.</p>
<p>They are why I argue strongly for the integrity of the transition strategy.</p>
<p>Because the international strategy for transition in Afghanistan is the responsible, orderly, sustainable approach to full and permanent Afghan responsibility for security.</p>
<p>The judgement of the Australian Government, which I will take with me to Chicago, is this.</p>
<p>We can proceed with the transition we agreed to in Lisbon: understanding that it is a difficult mission, but confident it is on track.</p>
<p>We will see our mission of training and transition through.</p>
<p>When transition in Uruzgan is complete, Australia's commitment in Afghanistan will look very different to that we have today.</p>
<p>We will have completed our training and mentoring mission.</p>
<p>We will no longer be conducting routine frontline operations.</p>
<p>The Provincial Reconstruction Team will have done its job.</p>
<p>The majority of our troops will have returned home.</p>
<p>And there will still be some work to do.</p>
<p>We will ensure sustainment of the Afghan National Security Forces after 2014.</p>
<p>And we will support the long-term development of the Afghan government, economy and institutions. </p>
<p>We will not abandon this mission for which so many have worked so hard  -  and for which some have lost so much.</p>
<p>So I can say today: to our people, whatever their view of the war.</p>
<p>To this audience, which consider these issues so carefully.</p>
<p>To the Australian civilians working in Afghanistan.</p>
<p>To our troops and their families.</p>
<p>This is a war with a purpose. This is a war with an end.</p>
<p>We have a strategy, a mission, and a timeframe for achieving it.</p>
<p>We are serving our national interest in Afghanistan.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
