<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4777</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S PRESS CONFERENCE FOLLOWING READING OF BUDGET SPEECH BY TREASURER 16 AUGUST</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/08/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004777.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS OFFICE TRANSCRIPT<br />
PRIME MINISTER'S<br />
PRESS CONFERENCE FOLLOWING READING OF BUDGET SPEECH BY TREASURER<br />
16 August<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
There are one or two important factors about the Budget which<br />
I'd like to remind you about first. The Treasury paper estimates<br />
that by next June or earlier inflation in Australia will be down<br />
to That's going to be below most of-our major trading<br />
partners. Japan and Germany might have a lower rate of inflation,<br />
but the United States, Canada, Britain, France and Italy are<br />
countries that will certainly, I would believe, have higher rates<br />
of inflation. That will mean that through the course of this<br />
year Australia will come to be performing better than the<br />
average of OECD countries, both in relation to inflation and<br />
in relation to output. That in itself will do much to encourage<br />
investment from Australians, it will do much to encourage<br />
investment from overseas. As a country that is very well<br />
endowed with natural resources, we are well placed to attract<br />
more than our fair share of investment from overseas, providing.<br />
we can offer a stable economy, political stability, and commonsense<br />
in our dealings with other nations. Under those circumstances<br />
I think Australia is much better placed to extend the difficulties<br />
of world trade whatever they might be than are many other nations.<br />
Our performance on inflation is now starting to assist our own<br />
exporters, assist our own industries in a very material way, and<br />
that's going to be reinforced. One of the threads, twin threads<br />
coming through the newspapers this-morning is that it is<br />
recognised that the Budget will bear down on inflation further<br />
a nd it is also I think recognised the Budget will make it possible<br />
to continue the steady but sustained movement downwards in<br />
interest rates. I have indicated before a 2% fall in interest<br />
rates to an average home buyer is worth something like<br />
a week. A move down in -interest rates helps all businesses,<br />
helps anyone who borrows money, helps home purchasers, helps<br />
exporters, helps farmers. If we are to get back to the kind<br />
of economy that is necessary, to the kind of economy which<br />
does offer jobs to all those that want to work, then getting<br />
inflation down and keeping it down, getting interest rates<br />
down and being able to keep them down I believe is of quite<br />
critical importance. The Government's Budget is certainly<br />
contributing to both these objectives in a very significant<br />
and major way. The overall impact of this particular Budget<br />
on the Consumer Price Index of the December quarter should<br />
be to make the Consumer Price Index movement about h% less<br />
than it would have otherwise been without the impact of the<br />
Budget, and that just goes to reinforce the overall thrust<br />
of the Budget that John Howard introduced last night.<br />
QUESTION: Prime Minister, when would you expect Building<br />
Societies and Banks to lower their interest rates?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I think that again you can't put a firm<br />
time scale on that. There has been a pause in the interest<br />
rate movement in the last few months. A pause in the first<br />
instance because of the run down period of April, May, June<br />
and then because of the blow-out of last year's deficit<br />
I think there was a further pause while people waited to </p>
<p>see what we were going to do in this Budget. Well now they<br />
know. There is a Government loan in place, open for subscription,<br />
and getting the results of that will also be very important<br />
of course in further development of these policies.<br />
QUESTION: Do you expect interest rates to come down within<br />
three months time?<br />
PRIM4E MINISTER: I would be expecting a movement down through<br />
the course of this year. Without putting a specific timetable<br />
on it, I would hope the movement can continue, because<br />
there has already been a significant movement in Government<br />
rates. I would hope that the move can continue sooner, rather<br />
than later. Much sooner rather than later. I'm not putting<br />
a figure on that, because all through we have emphasised a<br />
steady and sustained move down in interest rates. We don't<br />
want the kind of situation that developed in the United<br />
Kingdom, where interest rates came down very rapidly, and then<br />
in the April, May, June period of this year interest rates<br />
went up 3 again.<br />
QUESTION: Can we assume what's said on page 27 of the Budget,<br />
that the Federal Government will start to tax for public<br />
servants wages ( inaudible)<br />
PRIME MINISTER: You can assume from those sentences that<br />
if the wages bill rises unduly and significantly beyond our<br />
own expectations, we will then again look at the programmes<br />
of Government. We are seeking to emphasise the point that<br />
there is not a bottomless fount out of which wages can be<br />
paid irrespective of what people demand, irrespective of<br />
what the Arbitration Commission determines. Quite plainly<br />
private employers have had to alter the number of people<br />
on their own payroll as a result of wage decisions. One of<br />
the reasons for the shortfall in revenue was lower company<br />
taxes than had been anticipated I think because of less<br />
success in the wages front than we had anticipated. It has<br />
to be understood that the trade union movement as a whole<br />
has the choice before'. it. It can choose to press for ever<br />
higher wages for those in work at the expense of those out<br />
of work, or to show some greater degree of moderation to<br />
enable the circumstances to be developed in which more<br />
jobs can be available in Australia. I know that there are<br />
some people who get up and say they've been trying to grind<br />
down real wages, but on the figures that I have average<br />
weekly earnings increased last year marginally more than<br />
the Consumer Price Index. Now that doesn't sound like the<br />
erosion of anyone's living standards. It doesn't even<br />
sound like restraint.<br />
QUESTION: Un the rise ifithe price in petrol inaudible)<br />
PRIME MINISTER: If you look at that element by itself of<br />
course it does contribute to an increase in the Consumer / 3 </p>
<p>Price Index about or But you have also got to<br />
understand that that's not only a revenue raising measure.<br />
It is also designed to achieve the proper and best allocation<br />
of resources. Looking at the effect of the Budget on the<br />
Consumer Price Index you have got to have in mind the total<br />
impact in the Budget. The health financing changes, the<br />
reductions in sales tax on automobiles, have a very significant<br />
effect of reducing the CPI, and that movement more than outweighs<br />
the increases that would come from greater exercises<br />
in taxes of that kind or from the oil levy. So overall the<br />
impact of the Budget in the December quarter should be on<br />
our calculations, a favourable one by about 1%.<br />
QUESTION: Prime Minister, how dependent is the Budget, the<br />
success of the Budget, on the fact that the Arbitration<br />
Commission would toe the Government line, and also because<br />
of the increase in personal tax would you now expect trade<br />
unions to move outside indexation to try to compensate.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No I wouldn't. I wouldn't expect them to<br />
move outside, because if the Government has to pursue a<br />
certain matter as one of policy, it's quite wrong for one<br />
particular section of the community to try and insulate<br />
themselves from that policy by other countervailing actions.<br />
I would expect the Arbitration Commission to recognise that<br />
and to recognise that very plainly. Indeed in relation to<br />
the movement towards import parity price for oil which<br />
began a year ago, the Arbitration Commission has already<br />
recognised that, so I would expect them to continue with<br />
the decisions that they have already made, and I also<br />
believe that even if there are some trade union leaders who<br />
don't recognise it, the overwhelming majority of trade<br />
unionists know quite well that-wage increases that run too<br />
fast. take jobs away from other people, lead to inflation and<br />
don't do them any good at all. / 4 </p>
<p>QUESTION Apart from the CPI rationale, what reasons are behind the<br />
sales tax on motor cars. It obviously goes against the .( inaudible)?<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
Icbn't know that it does. It is an industry that has been in<br />
difficulty. Most of the industry sales tax are in the<br />
range, and cars have been for a long while at the higher end<br />
of the range. We thought it ought to be reduced. It is a<br />
very significant employment area the component industry<br />
is a very large one, and we believe that it would be sensible<br />
and rational if automobiles were brought down into the general<br />
industry range of 15<br />
QUESTION A follow-up on that. Was the CPI consida-ration a main reason<br />
for bearing the higher cost of this health insurance .( inaudible)?<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
No, the main reason is the greatly simplified universal health<br />
care that is now available.<br />
QUESTION But it is very expensive for the government?<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
Health care is expensive however it is paid for. It is much<br />
more simple. There was plainly a degree of complication in<br />
the operations as they were as they are now until the changes<br />
are introduced. I think it had been shown that that complication<br />
was undesirable. What we are doing, we are not altering the<br />
hospital side of things at all, we are offering a basic cover for<br />
all people, leaving it open for themselves to decide whether they<br />
want to insure for anything over and above that basic cover.<br />
So the individual choices are much more simple. The CPI element<br />
was one part of the total decision, but I don't think you can<br />
pick one part out and say it is more important than another<br />
QUESTION Inaudible overall revenue..?<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
No I don't think so because you have to look at other things.<br />
You had to look at the changes that were going to have to come<br />
in Medibank if it had not been altered increases in the levy,<br />
increases in the levy ceiling, matters of that kind.<br />
QUESTION Prime Minister, can I ask you how long you think the Federal Governmen' </p>
<p>will subsidise at a rate of 40% of scheduled fees?<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
I can't see any reason to change it. We have made that decision.<br />
QUESTION You think this will last for a number of year?<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
I think quite plainly we have got the continual battle to<br />
contain health costs. A number ofmatters that Ralph Hunt has<br />
introduced have been very successful in that. Negotiations<br />
going on with the States about hospital financing are designed<br />
to achieve a greater rationalisation of hospital costs, and<br />
a better use of hospital beds than has occurred up to the<br />
present time, because, as I am advised, some States are opening<br />
new hospitals when they only have a 60% use of existing<br />
facilities. That seems to be very-costly to the total community.<br />
I belive that any government would be foolish if it committed<br />
itself absolutely to a particular detail, knowing that the<br />
containment of hospital costs, medical costs, generally is one<br />
of the most serious problems that every government has had to<br />
face western-type governments-in recent years.<br />
QUJES TION<br />
Do you anticipate, Prime Minister, that this scheme as such will<br />
be maintained by the Government?<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
The scheme as such yes, because it is a great improvement and<br />
it is greatly simplified.<br />
QUESTION What will happen when bed charges rise and ( inaudible)?<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
I don't know. That depends upon detailed negotiations with the<br />
States about the restraint in hospital costs generally.<br />
I have got very little sympathy for a view that says let's<br />
not worry about being responsible in terms of hospital cost<br />
management, let's just put up bed charges regardless to cover<br />
the costs of our own inefficiency I don't think there shouldbe<br />
much sympathy with that sort of view anywhere. We will want to get<br />
to a situation in which there is glreater rationalisation<br />
and greater economy in hospital costs in the States. It is also<br />
worth noting that between the States there is a very great difference<br />
in hospital bed charges. I don't think anyone can draw a<br />
conclusion from that that in some States people are looked after<br />
much better than others. I think the additional costs come from<br />
./ 6 </p>
<p>different reasons.<br />
QUESTION<br />
Will the decisions on taxes backdated to July 1 the decision<br />
to only have one pension increase a year are you confident<br />
you have the full support of the Senators in those two areas.<br />
PRIE~ MINISTER<br />
Of course we have. You have got the circumstances in which the<br />
tax cuts that were introduced on February 1, together with<br />
half indexation, still leave a very substantial benefit to the<br />
taxpayers of Australia. I think you need to understand the<br />
reasons why it was necessary to have the temporary surcharge throughout<br />
this particular year. At this time last year tax undere: stimated the<br />
need for refunds by about $ 350m. In addition to that,<br />
non-PAYE tax was over estimated by about $ 400m. If we hadn't<br />
had those circumstances, which were estimates given to us,<br />
we would have had a different base, and I believe this temporary<br />
surcharge would not have been necessary. In addition to that<br />
and looking further into the future, the outlook for the rural<br />
area, rural incomes is much better, and I would think the<br />
outlook for company incomes is also much better. We should<br />
strengthen the revenue position next year arnd beyond.<br />
I would like to make one other point about the surcharge.<br />
Without tax indexation of course it would not have been necessary.<br />
We would have quite deliberately been able to keep the extra<br />
money comning through the inflationary process and maintaining<br />
tax'scales as they might have been. So this is an example of<br />
tax indexation forcing governments to do what we said would<br />
happen in the very outset -that if they felt it necessary to raise<br />
extra revenue, they would have to do it plainly and openly and<br />
not through the secret process of inflation. I think that<br />
is healthy and I think it is healthy that we have to justify it.<br />
QUESTION<br />
Mr Fraser, next year when you reach your projected 5% inflation rate..:<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
I would just like to interrupt at that point because people might<br />
have greater reliance on that figure if they know that that is<br />
the official Treasury forecast, in other words, it is not a<br />
political figure it comes from our official advisers who<br />
have some expertise in these matters. 7 </p>
<p>QUESTION Point taken, When it is reached next year will you then<br />
consider some stimulation for the economy to correct unemployment?<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
Obviously you judge the economy as it goes and from the outset<br />
we have had no reason to change the main thrust of our policies.<br />
One of the things that people forget, I think, is that one of<br />
the greatest stimulus that can come to this economy is through<br />
lower inflation itself and lower interest rates. Most people<br />
look upon stimulus as something that is Government induced by<br />
Government spending more money in this direction, a Government<br />
spending more money in another direction no recognising that<br />
in circumstances of high inflation and interest rates that are<br />
too high that kind of government stimulus just doesn't work and<br />
hasn't worked anywhere in any country that has tried it.<br />
Quite obviously the proper level of government expenditure needs<br />
considered judgement as each year passes. The point I want to<br />
emphasise is the stimulating effect of getting inflation down,<br />
leading to a return of full confidence and getting interest<br />
rates down, which also, of course, will do more to help all peoplewhether<br />
it is home buyers, pensioners, businesses, small businesses,<br />
large businesses, farmers, exporters it will do more, these<br />
two things, inflation and interest rates, will do more to help<br />
these people than any single act of government.<br />
QUESTION<br />
Prime Minister,, you have stressed that the inflation prediction<br />
comes from the Treasury is the Treasury responsible for<br />
miscalculating the Budget deficit by $ 1.2 billion last financial<br />
year, and if they were how do you as Prime Minister feel about<br />
this sort of expertise?<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
I believe the Treasury officials and Tax officials are highly<br />
skilled, highly dedicated and very capable. Also, I think we<br />
need to understand that over the past there have been swings<br />
and changes in the Australian economy that might have tested the<br />
models of the past. At the same time I would believe that the<br />
forecasts, and because of that experience last year, the forecasts<br />
for this year will, I believe, be more than cautious, done with.<br />
more than usual care. After what fell out last year I think that<br />
is only natural. They were obviously estimates that camne from our<br />
official advisers, but I don't say that as a point of criticism<br />
or as a point to detract from the responsibility of government<br />
in relation to it.<br />
QUESTION Isn't it fact that you are now forced into tax increases because<br />
of this miscalculation?<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
That may be, and I have indicated that but at the same time, I believe </p>
<p>Australia is as well advised in these particular matters as<br />
any particular country. I did draw attention to the fact that<br />
in recent years a number of countries, including Australia, have<br />
been through swings and changes which I think test the models<br />
of former times, and therefore sometimes make forecasting more<br />
difficulty than it might otherwise be. I then went onto make<br />
the point that because of the experience of last year I have<br />
got no doubt that the forecasts and estimates for this year<br />
are cautious and very very carefully made.<br />
QUESTION Do you see any contradiction in your advocacy internationally of<br />
freer world trade and the imposition last night of another<br />
12k7% customs duty on imported manufactured products?<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
Not at all because that is coming in an area where there is<br />
cuantitative restrictions of some kind. I think it needs to be<br />
uinderstood that our markets by comparison with the markets<br />
in most countries around the world are open and open in the extreme.<br />
In spite of some ill-advised comment from time to time to the<br />
contrary, I will continue to assert that. I have had correspondence<br />
from a particular textile firm that sought to export textiles<br />
to Iran and to the Philippines, and on trying to do so in both<br />
countries was told, no, this is a high labour intensive industrywe<br />
reserve it totally and absolutely for the local market, the<br />
local producers. There is a textile firm in Australia that is<br />
capable of competing in those markets, it is obviously doing a<br />
good job, it is obviously efficient, and it obviously ought to be<br />
given an opportunity to compete. I think that puts a different<br />
perspective on it, especially when we import more textiles,<br />
apparel and footwear, sensitive goods, from developing countries,<br />
and in particular from ASEAN countries, than any other developed<br />
country in the world we are now up to about $ 3 a head, while<br />
the United States and other countries are down around 50-60(, N<br />
a head, or even much less than that. I have made the comment<br />
before that if United States and Europe, and I think Japan also<br />
bought as much per capital from ASEAN of these sensitive goods<br />
as Australia does those countries would be selling an extra<br />
$ 1.2 billion worth of goods a year. Let me take another example<br />
of how our market is an open one: we allow overseas manufacturers<br />
to compete for about 20% of the Australian automobile market.<br />
If you go to Europe you don't hear very much about it they have<br />
negotiated voluntary restraint agreements with the major exporters<br />
to their market, which is basically Japan, and a voluntary restraint<br />
agreement is not particularly voluntary because it is always<br />
negotiated under the threat that there will be no access unless you<br />
come along and sign. In Britain it is restricted to 10-12%~<br />
of the market; in France to 3-4% w of the market; and Italy to<br />
of the market. Compare that access into those markets, allegedly<br />
free and open markets, with access to our market of<br />
It really is time that Australia stopped doing itself a disservice<br />
by continually trying to point out how protective we are by comparison<br />
with other countries, when in fact our markets are much more open than </p>
<p>those in most other countries.<br />
QUESTION You reaction to two things: Bill Hayden's claim statement,<br />
that we are heading for unemployment in excess of half a million;<br />
Bob Hawke's statement that this Budget will cost an<br />
Australian family an average of $ 7 each week.<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
How much more this Budget will cost Australian families in part<br />
will obviously depend on how much tobacco and how much alcohol<br />
Australian families consume. You have also got to understand that<br />
many Australian families will be relieved from paying the health<br />
levy, and that's a reduction in tax, and depending on what choices<br />
they make, I would believe the insurance they take out will<br />
cost less than the levy, or cost less than the full medical<br />
benefits insurance that they would now be pursuing. So there is<br />
a gain to Australian families there. In addition to that, an<br />
Australian family who happens to be bp. ying a new motor car, will<br />
save, depending on the price of the car, around about $ 500<br />
that is a saving for anyone who does buy and new tar and there<br />
is obviously a consequential saving on seoncd-hand cars, and<br />
further we want to note the tax advantage that came from<br />
half indexation on the 1 July. The extent to which this<br />
Budget does cost Australian families will depend, to a not<br />
insignificant extent, upon the decisions of the family concerned.<br />
QUESTION Unemployment claim by Mr Hayden half a million and more?<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
Last month the unemployment figures were I am not going to<br />
say they were optimistic, but they were better than had been<br />
expected, and whether that is a month which turns out to be an<br />
aberration or whether it is the beginning of a different trend<br />
or not, it is too early to say. One thing we do need to understand:<br />
the special training-programmes of the government are doing a<br />
very great deal to assist many young people, and over 100,000 are<br />
in training at the present time. These training programmes<br />
are going to be maintained, and additional funds are going to be<br />
made, very substantial additional funds, through the course of this<br />
year. Our concern with those who are unemployed is as real as<br />
compassionate, as any person's in the corrunity. The argument<br />
is about how you overcome the problem of unemployment.<br />
Our political opponents have always had the view that if<br />
governments spend more money no matter whether they get that<br />
money by taxes, or whether they just go to the printing press or<br />
buy another printing press because they run out of capacity to<br />
print they believe that that solves the problem of unemployment.<br />
They believe that governments spending more money solves the<br />
problem, whatever problem that might be in a community.<br />
I don't believe that, the government doesn't believe that. </p>
<p>I do believe that getting the underlying balances right in the<br />
Australian econbmy is the only thing that will lead to a<br />
better employment situation getting a proper relativity between<br />
wages and profits; getting inflation down and keeping down; and<br />
getting interest rates down. These are the things that will affect<br />
employment. In terms of this Budget nobody has denied that it will<br />
get inflation down further, nobody has suggested that it won't<br />
help in getting interest rates down. That being so, I suggest<br />
that it is the Budget that will do more for employment than any<br />
alternative that might be open to us.<br />
QUESTION Prime Minister, the official inflation forecasts, of what<br />
is the official unemployment forecast for next year?<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
I don't think it varies very much. The unemployrnent. situation is<br />
not good and we haven't tried to hide that. It will be significantly<br />
affected by what happens on the wages front, but one of the things<br />
which is holding unemployment high is quite clearly the ccntirjued<br />
rate . of ircrease in wages. I have already mode the point that<br />
average earrdimg-s increa! . cd more in the 12 months to June than the<br />
Consumer Price Index. That doesn't indicate any restraint on the<br />
wage front at all. indeed, the reverse.<br />
ENDS </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
