<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9521</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP INTERVIEW WITH FRAN KELLY, ABC RADIO&quot;AM&quot; PROGRAM 23 MARCH 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/03/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009521.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
, d~~ J y<br />
PRIME MINJISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
INTERVIEW WITH FRAN KELLY, ABC RADIO " AM" PROGRAM<br />
23 MARCH 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
EK: Prime Minister, isn't it fair to describe Ian McLachlan's resignation as<br />
being over a technical issue because he unwittingly misled the public<br />
over the secret Aboriginal women's documents?<br />
PM: Well, that's your question to get me started Fran, you couldn't possibly<br />
believe that. I mean the documents made up the Commonwealth's<br />
entire case file in litigation between the Minister for Aboriginal and<br />
Torres Strait Islander Affairs and the developers in this Hindmarsh<br />
Bridge case, and an appeal was lodged in the Federal Court in this<br />
matter last Friday that included the report on the secret Aboriginal<br />
women's evidence. Now, this box was marked confidential, it was then<br />
opened, the mail was pilfered and then in another envelope marked for<br />
women's eyes only, that was then opened and then another one,<br />
inside that was the envelope which had the women's secret advice and<br />
evidence. Now, this was then photocopied and sent to the developers,<br />
amongst others, and to newspapers.<br />
EK: But the secret women's documents weren't sent to the developers?<br />
PM: There were 800 documents 800.<br />
FK: Yes, but those ones, those particular ones, and that's the issue that Mr<br />
McLachlan resigned over isn't it?<br />
PM: Well, Mr McLachlan and Mr Howard should tell us who got the copies<br />
of the women's letters, who have received those, but the other thing is<br />
this...<br />
FK: Well, Mr McLachlan says no-one did, that only one photocopy was<br />
held in his office. </p>
<p>PM: He resigned for this reason. That he and John Howard, and John<br />
Howard admitted on a radio program in Sydney last week, that he was<br />
at the tactics committee. He and John Howard agreed on a series of<br />
questions they knew were misleading of the House of Representatives.<br />
And they then asked the Minister for Aboriginal Affairs, and charged in<br />
the question, that he had opened up the mail, he had done the<br />
photocopying and he had sent them around when they knew full well<br />
that it was themselves. So, not only is there the dishonour of breaking<br />
into this mail which was obviously not for them, but as well as that they<br />
then tried to frame a Minister, alleging of the Minister, that he, the<br />
Minister, was the photocopier and disseminated information when<br />
John Howard and Ian McLachlan knew it was them. Now, this is<br />
dishonour on very large scale and to have this sort of smarmy stuff<br />
from Costello, I mean, " he's a talent, and I think this will be seen as a<br />
technical issue", I mean these people have got the political morals of<br />
alley cats.<br />
EK: But, Mr Keating, no matter where you see the dishonour, isn't the truth<br />
that, or isn't it reality that Mr McLachlan in fact resigned because he<br />
said he misled the Australian public over the markings on that<br />
envelope containing the secret women's documents? That's the issue.<br />
PM: He misled the House of Representatives. This stuff about misleading<br />
the Australian people, he misled the House of Representatives, and he<br />
can't come back as a Shadow Minister and John Howard was party<br />
look, he resigned because he misled the House of Representatives.<br />
John Howard sat beside him knowing that the question he was asking,<br />
the question that misled the House, was one he approved of. They<br />
both misled the House and that's why we ask for Howard's resignation.<br />
And here they are a week later, I mean they have got nobody on their<br />
front bench, you see the whole Opposition is a shell down there, in<br />
Canberra. There's nobody there.<br />
FK: Yes, but why shouldn't he be able to come back at some point though,<br />
I mean...<br />
PM: Come off it Fran.<br />
FK: Ministers do this all the time. Senator Graham Richardson was<br />
brought back into your Cabinet after he had to step aside over the<br />
Marshall Islands affair.<br />
PM: You know what they said, these people, I mean the gall of them. They<br />
said they had a duty as an MP, Mr McLachlan said to his constituents,<br />
to developers in the Hindmarsh Bridge affair. But was it no less of a<br />
duty to his Aboriginal constituents in the same constituency? I mean<br />
then they said they had an obligation to pass the information over to<br />
these developers. John Howard and Ian McLachlan are not solicitors<br />
for the developers, they had no legal obligation no obligation at all. </p>
<p>And when asked on a Sydney radio, Mr Howard was enjoined by the<br />
questioner to say, " well I wouldn't do that if I came across legal<br />
documents that were on the other side of the case to me, I would send<br />
them back". And Howard said, " would you?". It was John Laws in fact.<br />
He said " yes I would". I mean, there's no morality here. But you<br />
understand, Fran, their front bench has nobody on it. They are now<br />
trying to get McLachlan back because, look, they appointed the other<br />
day Kemp to the environment portfolio who now says we shouldn't be<br />
using international treaties to protect the environment. They are now<br />
down to backbench Senators.<br />
FK: Yes, but Prime Minister, you have to concede that Governments do<br />
bring back Ministers who have slipped aside for some reason or other<br />
and you have done it yourself?<br />
PM: Yes, Graham Richardson came back after being out the better part of a<br />
year after a general election. Not the better part-of a week after one of<br />
the most dishonourable episodes.<br />
FK: Yes, but Mr Costello was talking about if the Coalition won<br />
Government.<br />
PM: They're talking about trying to bring him back beforehand they're just<br />
softening the ground. Ian McLachlan had to resign because he was<br />
caught red-handed trying to fit a Minister up for something that he,<br />
McLachlan, had done and the great injustice in this is that Howard was<br />
in it right up to his ears, admitted that he was at the tactics committee<br />
meeting, knew the question that McLachlan was going to ask, was just<br />
as culpable of misleading the House of Representatives as McLachlan<br />
was, but you see you couldn't get him to resign he just sat there and<br />
sat it out. He thought he would wear the rest of you out and that he<br />
could burn you off. And now they are so brazen that he thought he<br />
could burn the press gallery off and the media and public opinion off,<br />
and now within a week, they are so brazen, within a week, Costello is<br />
saying we ought to have him back.<br />
FK: Mr Keating, if I could turn briefly to the economy. The Australian<br />
newspaper reports today that your own internal polling is showing the<br />
next election could hinge on keeping interest rates down. Can you say<br />
now that you can manage the economy without the need for further<br />
rate rises?<br />
PM: You have not got to be a polling whiz, have you, to know that people<br />
don't like interest rate increases. I mean you don't have to be an<br />
insider to work that out. Well, the Government is in the course now of<br />
producing the Budget, and the Budget will be a Budget which will be<br />
appropriate for the economic circumstances of the moment, and for the<br />
medium term. We have got a medium term paucity in savings we<br />
want to address that in the medium term. I think the economy has </p>
<p>slowed and is slowing and I am waiting to see by how much when we<br />
get the next national accounts data. But in the meantime, the<br />
Government's going to do a first-rate job on the Budget because I think<br />
that's the important imperative now.<br />
FK: Well, are the clear signals coming from you now that the budget deficit<br />
will be cut by tough spending cuts rather than tax increases?<br />
PM: Well, the clear signal coming from me, don't put words in my mouth<br />
Fran.<br />
FK: Well, coming from you and your senior Ministers...<br />
PM: I know you are bright-eyed and bushy-tailed at this hour of the<br />
morning, but look, what we are saying is the clear message coming<br />
from me is the Budget will be right.<br />
FK: But, will the Budget be right through tough spending cuts rather than<br />
more tax increases?<br />
PM: Well, you just wait and see.<br />
EK: Is there room given the strong employment growth to cut spending<br />
from some of the money put aside for Working Nation?<br />
PM: Well, I think it is worth just recording, I mean people go on about the<br />
Budget and the economy, I mean, the Australian economy is the<br />
strongest in the OECD area. We have had strong growth with low<br />
( inflation) and we have had 590,000 job growth since the election. I<br />
mean, essentially the Government was re-elected to get growth started<br />
and employment started. We have had 3 and 3/ 4 per cent<br />
employment growth. And that is one of the reasons why household<br />
disposable income these strong levels of employment of this<br />
Government why the disposable income of Australian households<br />
have risen by 40 per cent since the Government came to office, which<br />
is a huge number.<br />
FK: Does that strong employment growth then translate though into you<br />
having some room in the money you had set aside for Working Nation<br />
to now put into bringing back the deficit?<br />
PM: Well, you are asking me about whether there is any spending room to<br />
reduce outlays under Working Nation, well, I'm not sure. I mean,<br />
analysis of all this in the ERC round will reveal this. The key point is,<br />
Mr Howard is running around saying we have had five minutes of<br />
economic sunshine. We have had 36 months of growth, 36 months of<br />
growth, go and tell the 593,000 people who have got their jobs that it<br />
was only five minutes of sunshine and go and remind them that the<br />
economy has seen one of the strongest investment phases in recent </p>
<p>years which is setting us up for more goods and services into the<br />
future.<br />
FK: Yes, but the question for the voters, I suppose, is can you tell them<br />
now that you can get the Budget so right that there's unlikely there will<br />
be a need for further interest rate rises?<br />
PM: Well, I won't have to tell them. That will be all apparent to them by the<br />
election, won't it? I mean, they are mature, they are conscientious,<br />
they will make their own judgements about all that. They will see, I<br />
believe, that the Australian economy will continue to grow and prosper<br />
and it will do so with low inflation and with all of the attendant changes<br />
of recent years in productivity and the rest. That's the key here.<br />
FK: And further rate rises though?<br />
PM: Well, look, these sort of questions about, you know, are you ruling in<br />
or are you ruling out interest rate rises. I mean, you have seen the<br />
change in the world monetary system over the last three weeks. I<br />
mean, no Government can say, well, there will never be another<br />
increase in interest rates, or that it is unnecessary. But, I am just<br />
saying that the Budget will be a key factor in that and we will be getting<br />
that right.<br />
EK: Mr Keating, thank you.<br />
PM: Thank you. Fran, before you leave now I know Mr Fahey's coming<br />
on, and he has been caught out with these non-existent costings of<br />
New South Wales Labor promises in New South Wales just ask him<br />
how does he defend that porky, that enormous porky?<br />
FK: We'll put that question to Mr Fahey. Thank you, Prime Minister.<br />
PM: It's an enormous porky. Thank you.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
