<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3951</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S INTERVIEW WITH STUDENTS IN ALICE SPRINGS ON RADIO STATION 8HA - 1 NOVEMBER 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/11/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003951.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER' S INTERVIEW WITH STUDENTS IN ALICE SPRINGS<br />
ON RADIO STATION 8HA 1 November 1975<br />
I gather the local commercial station has made available<br />
some period every week for the students of the High School<br />
to express these views and to interview visitors like<br />
myself. This is a very fine contribution-by the radio<br />
station itself; it's also a very proper opportunity given<br />
to the students. Many people will get the taste for the<br />
media; many people who go to High School here will now<br />
want to become radio announcers and producers and the<br />
radio station has given them the opportunity, and this is<br />
the time of life, of course, when you're bursting with<br />
ideas and when you respond most quickly to opportunity,<br />
I'm sure that the pupils of the High School will take<br />
advantage of this opportunity and the wider community<br />
will follow their contributions with much interest.<br />
Q: What effect do you feel, what effect do you think this<br />
type of program will have on, say, the staff, the students<br />
and the community as a whole?<br />
Well let me mention the effect on the people interested<br />
in the school itself. I think it's coming to be realised<br />
more and more that a school': concerns not only the staff,<br />
not only the pupils, but also the parents and the wider<br />
community. School-' takes up 12 years of every young persons'<br />
life; he spends more hours at school than he does at hcne or<br />
in any other activity. Accordingly,. it's very important indeed,<br />
that the whole community should realise what goes on at<br />
school. The school is part of life people are staying<br />
at school much longer and so I think as far as the school<br />
is concerned everybody will understand what goes on there<br />
and will be able to contribute to what goes on there much<br />
better than before.<br />
The other thing is that through radio, people who don't have<br />
children at school, people maybe who didn't go to school very<br />
long themselves, people who didn't go to school in Australia,<br />
will get a much better idea of what the rising generation<br />
is interested in doing, what it's succeeding in doing. I'm<br />
sure this will be very valuable for everyone, and it!'. s best<br />
done through radio. I believe that the community in general<br />
is coming to realise that radio is something that people<br />
can enjoy in greater variety and in more circumstances than<br />
any other medium. If you want to read a newspaper, you have<br />
to go out and get it, or you have to have it delivered to you,<br />
and if you' re in a place like Alice Springs many of the newspapers<br />
that you would want to read are delivered, are bought, hours or<br />
days after they are available in the place where they are<br />
produced. Again, television is extraordinarily expensive.<br />
It costs an immense amu-ount to build or to staff or to run a<br />
television station; also if you're to pick up television<br />
programs you have to have some expensive equipment and you can<br />
only operate it in certain circumstances. A radio, on the<br />
other hand, can pick up what is being broadcast instantly<br />
from any part of the world, and you can pick it up wherever<br />
you are, at any time of the day or night, any part of the<br />
country at work or at play, on the beach, out fishing, riding, </p>
<p>whatever it is. you can listen to radio. Radio is-with<br />
you the whole time; you've got the instant choice; you<br />
can pick from programs from all around the world, wherever<br />
you are, whatever you're doing, straight away, without<br />
expense, without delay.<br />
Q: Getting off the subject of the medium of radio and<br />
television, what do you think of the Northern Territoryin<br />
particular the people. Do you think they're different<br />
from any other, other different Australians?<br />
The people of the Territory comprise both the Australians<br />
who've been here longest, tens of thousands of years,<br />
and also the Australians who've been in this region for<br />
the shortest time. The Territory would have people<br />
living here for a shorter time than most parts of<br />
Australia. Most of the people who live and work in the<br />
Territory were not born or educated in the Territory.<br />
Accordingly there is immense mobility in-. the Territory<br />
population. Furthermore, there are things which have.-<br />
to be done in the Territory which can be done to the<br />
advantage of the whole of Australia and which should be<br />
done now. Some of Australia's most valuable resources,<br />
particularly mineral resources, are available in the<br />
Territory. Hitherto, Australians haven't processed<br />
these resources sufficiently themselves. In fact, in<br />
respect of most of the mineral wealth of the Northern<br />
Territory, it was not known to exist as recently as<br />
years ago. So, there was a great lot to be done here,<br />
and Territorians are different from other Australians<br />
because they've been here, except for the Aborigines,<br />
a shorter time than any other people as regards the<br />
Aborigines~ longer than any other people.-Furthermore,<br />
they're in that part of Australia where the resources<br />
are most plentifuil and least used.<br />
Q: Teenagers in Alice Springs say that there's not much to do, you<br />
know, no social life. Do you believe this, in your short<br />
visit here?<br />
I wouldn't care to express a view. This is something<br />
which teenagers express in most parts of the world, including<br />
most parts of Australia. But, there are a great number of<br />
things which teenagers can do here, more excitingly, than<br />
they can do in other parts of Australia. Teenagers very<br />
often say that the community isn't looking after them,<br />
but the things that are worth doing are usually the things<br />
you pioneer and create yourself. And there are an immense<br />
number of things that can be pioneered and created in this<br />
Territory a great number of Australians who are holed up<br />
in the big cities would find this an exceptionally exciting<br />
life.<br />
Q: Do you believe that teenagers are influenced politically by<br />
their parents ' beliefs?<br />
I think they probably are. I think that most people vote<br />
the way their parents voted; nevertheless, the younger<br />
you are the more likely you are to make up your own mind. </p>
<p>3.<br />
It's when you're young that you're likely to be most<br />
critical. It's when you're young that your ideas'<br />
are most likely to be changed or to be formed.<br />
And so whil~ e most teenagers would vote as their parents<br />
did, or maybe their teachers, yet they're more likely<br />
to made up their own minds than older people are -the<br />
older you are ) the more set you become in your ways.<br />
The teenagers are really, and the people in their twenties,<br />
are the people who are most variable and mobile in their<br />
political allegiances. That's largely, I suppose,<br />
because they see more critically what's wrong with our<br />
society, but they also still have the hope that things<br />
can be changed.<br />
Q: Do you think the High School should help teenagers to<br />
understand politics by having a particular subject in<br />
the curriculum to help with politics?<br />
I think -they should. I know this is a very controversial<br />
subject; a very great number of people say that politics<br />
should never be discussed at school. They say that<br />
the students will be too much influenced by the views of<br />
their teachers. This is mainly a view expressed by<br />
conservative people people who want the world to stay as<br />
it is; people who don't want theories, or practices or<br />
habits, to be analysed; they don't want things to be<br />
examined or criticised or reassessed. Now it is absurd that<br />
people going to school shouldn't have a full discussion<br />
on things that are going to be immensely important to them,<br />
particularly during the ten years after they leave school,<br />
when they will be completing their training for life, when<br />
they'll very often be marrying and getting into their life<br />
style these are the formative years; they ought to discuss<br />
these things at school, quite clearly. And moreover, every<br />
high school now has scores of men and women who are able to<br />
vote; it's absurd that they can't discuss these things at<br />
school.<br />
Q: Thank you very much Mr Whitlam for your time.<br />
Well I wish you well in your project. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
