<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9559</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP DOORSTOP, MELBOURNE, 27 APRIL 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/04/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009559.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
JA2W<br />
PRIME MINISTERA<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
DOORSTOP, MELBOURNE, 27 APRIL 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
J: How did the meeting go?<br />
PM: It was very good I think. We've will run one of the most successful<br />
income policies In the world. The Accord is now 12 years old when<br />
we first started, people didn't think it would become 12 months old.<br />
Now, it's 12 years old and we are now looking at this Budget and the<br />
economy for the balance of the nineties, and this is the time to have<br />
another discussion about the next variation on the Accord's model.<br />
J; What issues did you speak about?<br />
PM: The general ones obviously, the Budget specific ones about wages<br />
the wage system about inflation we have h: cd very good<br />
underlying inflation numbers today -we are very happy about that.<br />
And going back where we were with Accord Mark VII recording the<br />
progress we have made. We were seeking then half a million jobs<br />
over three years we have got the half a million jobs In two years<br />
we got to the target In two-thirds of the time. And so we went... . we<br />
reconnoitred back over the Accord Mark ViIl looked at the success<br />
we have had with it, what things we need to do differently.<br />
J: Was there any understanding on the issues discussed?<br />
PM: We had a good general natter, and we are going to probably meet<br />
again and say more to one another.<br />
J: Will there be a superannuation tax cut this year?<br />
PM: I'm not here to discuss the Budget, and we didn't go to that sort of<br />
detail at the meeting.<br />
J: How happy are you with that inflation rate? </p>
<p>PM: Well, the underlying rate actually came down, so it's a very good<br />
result it vvy: 1.9% thP underlying rate and It's the underlying rate<br />
that matters. The headline bounces around, depending on wh1ats in<br />
ft in any particular month, but the underlying rate even though the<br />
headline rate went up because It has now got mortgage interest<br />
payments and other payments heavily weighted in the basket of the<br />
index, the underlying rate, with those one-off's taken out of it. gives<br />
you the steady view of inflation. And the steady view on inflation is<br />
very steady, as those National Accounts in December showed. You<br />
see the non-farm product deflator in the National Accounts was 0.9%<br />
for the year. Can you believe that? The National Accounts in<br />
December have the broadest measure of inflation under 1% the<br />
private consumption deflator in the National Accounts puts Inflation<br />
at And so that's why, in calculating the underlying rate at<br />
1.9% that is, dis-aggregating the CP'I to look at the underlying rate<br />
is confirming those very good numbers we saw about two weeks ago<br />
in the December Quarter Accounts.<br />
J: Do you have any concern that the Unions can push a wage claim on<br />
the strength of the headline rate?<br />
PM: We have, I think, so much... the wage policy of the Government is<br />
working now very, very well indeed. That is, the Enterprise<br />
Bar-gaining is working well there have been some terrific bargains<br />
struck. There was one in the metals this week it might have been<br />
yesterday a terrific bargain, and this is the sort of wage system we<br />
could have only dreamed about a few years ago. Thank you.<br />
ends. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
