<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5437</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/09/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005437.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
RAI k4. LtA<br />
PURME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA SUNDAY 14 SEPTEMBER 1980<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
Last Thursday I announced in the Parliament that there will be<br />
a general election on October 18. The result of this election<br />
will shape Australia's future for many years to come. That is<br />
why, in a difficult and demanding world, the decision to be made<br />
by voting Australians is a critical one.<br />
It is a decision to select a Party for Government which is<br />
capable of successfully meeting the challenges faced by Australia<br />
in the decade ahead. our record over the last five years and<br />
our policies for the future entitle us as a Government, and as a<br />
nation, to great confidence.<br />
For five years ago we inherited an economy which threatened<br />
Australia's future security. Yet today Australia's economy is<br />
the envy of much of the industrialised world. Inflation, while<br />
still too high, is lower than the average of major industrialised<br />
countries; and much lower than the level of inflation in America<br />
and Britain. And the claim of any Party to Government in the<br />
must be based, above all else, on its capac~ ity to contain<br />
inflation and secure sustainable economic growth. Because<br />
everything we want as a people and as a nation depends upon that.<br />
This we have done; this, the Labor Party failed to achieve in<br />
the 70s and, on the eve of this election, they still have no<br />
anti-inflation strategy. It is because of the success of our<br />
anti-inflation strategy that business confidence in high and<br />
overseas investment is being attracted to Australia. As a<br />
result, in mining and manufacturing alone, $ 29 million of<br />
investment is either under way or about to go. One needs only<br />
to remember the investment collapse that occurred under Labor<br />
in the 70s, to realise the extent of our investment~ achievements<br />
in the last five years.<br />
Our rural industries are looking good again; and rural exports<br />
last year were the highest for a decade. Of course, the<br />
Government is aware that significant parts of Australia are now<br />
in the grip of severe drought conditions. It is because of<br />
these unpredictable seasonable variations, faced by Australian<br />
farmers, that the Government has consistently provided incentives<br />
and support for rural industries including comprehensive drought<br />
relief programmes. And these will continue.<br />
This is not the time for a Party in Government which is<br />
unsympathetic and hostile to rural interests. The most pleasing<br />
barometer of Australia's improved economic health has been the<br />
remarkable growth in employment over the last year. </p>
<p>While unemployment is still too high, in the 12 months to July<br />
this year, employment in Australia rose by 212,000, the highest<br />
annual increase for 10 years. And a recent survey by the<br />
Bureau of Statistics shows that expected investment for the<br />
year ahead is 40 per cent higher than expectations which existed<br />
at this time last year. It is our ability to sustain these<br />
expectations on which we base our claim to Government in the<br />
For it is only through the creation of national wealth that any<br />
community or government can meet its responsibilities and provide<br />
for those in need. Because of our success in strengthening the<br />
economy over the last five years, and in spite of much needed<br />
restraint in many areas of Government expenditure, we have been<br />
able to maintain our pioneering commitment to those in our<br />
community who, through no fault of their own, need our assistance.<br />
$ 600 million has been spent on man power and training programmes<br />
for the unemployed. 570,000 Australians have been assisted by<br />
these programmes in the last four years. Over 230,000 will be<br />
assisted this year. We have built 500 new self-contained hostels<br />
and nursing homes for the aged and this programme is to continue.<br />
And our assistance to families, the handicapped, migrants and<br />
Aboriginals has provided new and imaginative benefits.<br />
The Government's energy policies, in particular our oil parity<br />
pricing policy, are making sure that Australia will maintain its<br />
energy independence in the future. Expenditure on exploration<br />
and development is five times what it was in 1975. During this<br />
year, 50-60 on-shore wells are likely to be drilled compared with<br />
6 in 1975. And in the last four years, one bill. ion barrels of<br />
petroleum liquids have been added to Australia's economically<br />
recoverable reserves. Momentum such as this, which has been<br />
generated in so many areas of national activity, must be maintained.<br />
Yet our Opposition, the Labor Party, because of its policy and<br />
platform commitments to date threatens our hard won achievements;<br />
and challenges the very foundations that have so painstakingly<br />
been established. At a time when international, academic and<br />
business commentators point to the absolute priority that must be<br />
given to containing inflation, the Labor Party have announced<br />
massive spending programmes which would dramatically increase the<br />
national debt, fuel inflation, promote unemployment and threaten<br />
the national confidence and capacity that have been so successfully<br />
generated in the last five years.<br />
In only six areas, Labor have announced policies to spend more<br />
than $ 2,500 million of taxpayers' money of your money. And,<br />
almost unbelievably, there are more than 250 other programmes to<br />
which the Labor Party is committed, and which have not yet been<br />
costed. What Labor never understand is that governments have no<br />
resources of their own. When the Labor Party promises massive<br />
spending programmes, they are effectively promising to take money<br />
from you your neighbour and from all Australian taxpayers. They<br />
are promising something of yours. It needs to be understood that<br />
what governments spend cannot be spent by Australian families. </p>
<p>The productivity, the production of this country is limited.<br />
It is finite. In any one year if government consumes more,<br />
families must consumeless. That is why, quite deliberately<br />
of course, Labor avoids costing these programmes. Indeed<br />
Mr. Hayden is on record as saying, " we have to present our<br />
policies in an attractice and digestible form now this<br />
requires us to be selective." This simply means that Mr. Hayden<br />
will hide some of his commitments from the n3tion, in the weeks<br />
ahead, because he knows they would mean a colossal drain on<br />
taxpayers' money.<br />
They would plant inflation, once again, deep in the national<br />
soil. These consequences must be resisted and rejected.<br />
Economic responsibility will continue to be the watch-word of<br />
my Government in the 80s. Because it is on that economic<br />
responsibility that your standards of living can, and will, rise.<br />
We will continue to restrain Government expenditure. And by the<br />
containment of inflation we will continue to encourage the<br />
development of all Australia's natural resources; including the<br />
great and proven creative resources of the Australian people.<br />
We will continue, as in the past, to work with all Australians,<br />
to see that we secure the bright prospects that now lie before us.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
