<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4987</transcript-id>
    <title>MEDIA SUMMARY</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/03/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004987.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRI I: STR13 " ARC 1979 1,,<br />
From Alister Drysdale MED IA SULMARY<br />
Abortion The Aus-ralian says you assured clerymen yvesterday that<br />
you would vote in favour of a proposal co stop the<br />
financing of abortion. ( Page 2).<br />
Sydney Morning Herald says you had promised your support for<br />
the mo-ion calling on the Government to pay abortion benefits<br />
only when the life of the mother is at stake, ( Page 3),<br />
while the Age says you had indicated you would support<br />
Mr. Lusher's motion but may not be strongly opposed to<br />
possible amendments.<br />
Election Funding<br />
Sydney Morning Herald: Hamer and Corcoran support N. S. W. moves<br />
towards public funding of election campaigns. Hamer says<br />
one way the scheme would be achieved was by allocation to<br />
the party's from State consolidated revenue. Yet the Age<br />
says the State Government ruled out public funding of<br />
Dolitical parties in Victorian election ca. npains.<br />
Hamer is quoced as saying the present-syste-of party<br />
funded campaigns was " perfectly legiimae".<br />
In Sydney Morning Herald Eggleton quoted as saying Federal<br />
Liberal Party would continue to review its overseas<br />
experience. Queensland ALP<br />
', ewsoapers report that the threat of Federal intervention<br />
in Queensland has been averted. The Administrative Committee<br />
under which Mr. Hayden can appoint a proxy when he cannot<br />
attend party meetings.<br />
The Australian says Hayden and Queensland ironed out their<br />
differences formally and Senator George Georges was apparently<br />
left cut in the cold.<br />
Greek deportation<br />
Hamer . as told the Age and the Sun that he asked you to<br />
sto_ d. ee portation of a Greek couple living in Melbourne.<br />
This ;-ry leads theSun and makes Page 4 of the Age.<br />
I have already had the Melbourne Herald asking about the situation<br />
this morning. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
