<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>965</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: P.M. NO. 56/1964 - AUSTRALIAN FORESTRY COUNCIL - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/07/1964</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000965_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS P. M. No. 56/ 1964<br />
AUSTRALIAN FORESTRY COUNCIL<br />
Statement by the Prime Ministerg the Rt. Hon. Sir Robert Menzies<br />
The Prime Minister, the Rt. Hon. Sir Robert Menzies,<br />
announced today that agreement has been reached between all<br />
Australian Governments to set up an Australian Forestry Council<br />
as a national advisory body on forestry matters.<br />
The Council will provide the means for the mutual<br />
exchange of information and views between the State and Commonwealth<br />
Governments. It will co-ordinate research into problems<br />
affecting the establishment, development, management and fire<br />
protection of all forests and the utilisation of forest<br />
products, and thus help to ensure the maintenance and improvement<br />
of the quality of forests and forest products. It will assist<br />
in co-ordinating the work of State and Commonwealth Governments<br />
and also private enterprise in the development of Australian<br />
forestry. Sir Robert said that many of our forest areas fulfil<br />
an important function in that they protect the catchment areas<br />
of many of our major rivers and water storages. Moreover, the<br />
Australian forestry industry is an important one in the Australian<br />
economy; the annual factory-door value of sawn timber, plywood<br />
and veneers, fibre and particle boards, pulp and paper<br />
manuf'actured from Australian forests is about œ C220M.<br />
The Council will enable Australia to make the<br />
best possible use of resources in men, technical knowledge,<br />
available land and money and to co-ordinate activities in the<br />
field of forestry practice and forestry research.<br />
The Council will coim. prise the Minister for National<br />
Development as Chairman, the Minister for Territories and the<br />
Minister in charge of forests from each State. Provision has<br />
been made for Ministers responsible for closely related<br />
activities to be co-opted when problems of particular concern<br />
to them are under discussion. The Council will be assisted by<br />
a Standing Committee of Commonwealth and State officers.<br />
CANBERRA, 23rd July, 1964. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
