<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5797</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/04/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005797.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
. jjAUSTAL A<br />
FOR MEDIA APRIL 18 1982<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
One of our important responsibilities is to present a balanced,<br />
realistic view of where our economy stands, and of the prospects<br />
which lie ahead. People have a right to expect that the various<br />
elements bearing on Australia's economic position will be<br />
explained in a rational way, so that the whole picture emerges<br />
and can be understood. Balance, stability they are the keys<br />
to keeping Australia's economy on course, not only in the<br />
public presentation of the position but also in the substance<br />
of responsible economic management.<br />
Australia does not function in isolation. When the economies<br />
of the major industrialised nations strike trouble, then that<br />
is reflected in Australia. We are affected by the slackening<br />
demand for our products in those countries. We are affected<br />
by the levels of interest rates in Europe and America. The unhappy<br />
truth is thai: the economy of several of these major countries<br />
is not growing. Not only that, but in some instances, they are<br />
actually producing less.<br />
There are many economic indicators, but I think the plight<br />
of the United States' motor car industry illustrates the<br />
position quite dramatically. Four years ago, the United States<br />
produced 15 million vehicles. Last year, they produced half that<br />
seven and a half million. Imagine the impact of that change<br />
on jobs, peop:. le's spending, the suppliers of metals, and so on.<br />
In the face of a world economic downturn, Australia has done<br />
comparatively well. Our economy has grown faster than the<br />
average rate of other major industrialised countries in<br />
recent years.. Business investment growth in Australia was<br />
at its highest for 30. years in the last financial year.<br />
After-tax real incomes have been rising in Australia and<br />
more jobs have been created. In the three years to last<br />
February, almiost 380,000 new jobs were created in Australia.<br />
We know that we can succeed in Australia against world trends.<br />
We cannot avo~ id being influenced by those trends, but there<br />
is much we can do ourselves to meet the challenge of keeping<br />
Australia's economy on course in the face of difficult international<br />
conditions. For the Government's part, it is committed to<br />
providing stable, reliable government, the kind of government<br />
that inspires confidence among business people, large and small,<br />
in Australia and overseas. That is fundamental. / 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
At the same time, the Government must be sufficiently flexible<br />
to respond to changing economic circumstances internationally<br />
and at home. As a nation, it is vitally important that we<br />
recognise ourselves as an integral part of the world market<br />
place in which we must compete to sell our wares. We must be<br />
reliable suppliers of quality goods at the right price. At a<br />
time when the market for so many goods is very tight indeed,<br />
we are jeopardising our competitiveness. Put bluntly, this<br />
is a time for containing costs. This is not a time for<br />
shortening working hours. Nor is it a time for substantial<br />
wage increases when in some other countries people are actually<br />
accepting reduced wages in order to preserve jobs. This is<br />
not a time for talking the economy up or talking it down.<br />
This is a time for sound economic management, for stability<br />
and reliability.<br />
It is a time to recognise our achievements in the face of<br />
a world downturn and to accept the challenge of keeping<br />
Australia competitive in the difficult period ahead. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
