<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4074</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORAL TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/02/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004074.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Broadcast: 3HA Sunday 29 February<br />
3YB Thursday 4 March<br />
AAL<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 29 FEBRUARY 1976<br />
ELECTORAL TALK<br />
I want to talk to you tonight about the mandate you have given<br />
my Government.<br />
I want to spell out our commitment to every Australian.<br />
Our mandate is clear. We not only have to resolve the present<br />
economic crisis but we have to use this nation's unrivalled<br />
resources to rebuild a country which will be an example to other<br />
nations.<br />
First, we have to reduce inflation, reduce unemployment and<br />
stimulate community confidence. We have t * o aim for stable<br />
prices, more jobs, more rewarding jobs, higher real incomes and<br />
better living standards.<br />
However for us to succeed where Labor dramatically failed there must<br />
be a much more realistic view of what Government can and cannot<br />
do. Governments cannot presume to live peoples' lives; they cannot<br />
set personal achievement goals for individuals; they cannot take<br />
important decisions in peoples' lives.<br />
But Governments can and should create atmospheres where people<br />
have the confidence to plan ahead to achieve worthwhile goals<br />
and where the Government has adequate resources to generously<br />
assist the needy.<br />
Over the past three years this confidence in Government has been<br />
eroded. Ordinary Australians have been forced to finance a whole<br />
host of costly programmes through personal taxe -that flourished<br />
in the wake of the great inflationary tide.<br />
And let's not fool ourselves. The people who have paid for these<br />
massive and costly programmes that were in no way related to<br />
Government revenue are those whose income and savings have been<br />
eroded by inflation.<br />
The Henderson Report on poverty said:<br />
Inflation favours the active and powerful. The position of the<br />
poor deteriorates. The wealthy can protect their savings it<br />
is the small saver with savings bank deposits who suffer. / 2 </p>
<p>Many of the Labor Gov(-rnments programmes were introduced in the<br />
guise of assisting the disadvantaged. The fact that many of these<br />
programmes were financed out of inflacion makes mockery of these<br />
pretentions. Let's look at our mandate to the hundreds of thousands of unemployed<br />
Australians. We are committed to erasing this blight -the worst unemployment<br />
level in this country since the Great Depression.<br />
Three out of every four Australians rely on private business for<br />
their jobs. Therefore we must strive to create a climate where<br />
businessmen are again prepared to invest in plant, and machinery<br />
and people.<br />
You are aware that the Government has taken a number of initiatives<br />
in this area. And only this week in Parliament the Treasurer<br />
( Mr Lynch) announced further investment measures that will particularly<br />
h'elp the small businessmanA and farmer back on his feet.<br />
I talked earlier ojf this nation's unrivalled resources. Of course<br />
they are great but they are not unlimited.<br />
We therefore must choose which of the thinqs we do now, and which<br />
we postpone.<br />
These choices are not just choices about different areas of Government<br />
spending. They are choices between Government spending and private<br />
enterprise spending.<br />
The more Governments-spend on goods and services, the less real<br />
value the wage earner will receive in his pay packet. The more<br />
politic~ ians decide how to spend your savings, the less control<br />
you have over your own incomes, It's as simple as that.<br />
So a responsible Government which values the freedoms of Australians<br />
yet is mindful of the needs of the underprivileged must be<br />
prepared not to earmark too much of people's pay packets for<br />
Government programmes.<br />
Accordingly, as resources arp limited the choice between Government<br />
and private spending should be explicit. That is one of the<br />
reasons that tax indexation is a major part of the Government's<br />
plan to protect the value of people's savings and earnings.<br />
We strongly believe that by being responsible in our claims on<br />
people's incomes, so Australians will be responsible in their<br />
wage demands.<br />
Australians do not want Governments to run their lives. They<br />
want responsible Government, ethical Government, honest Government<br />
and fair Government.<br />
Our mandate then is to restore Australian Government to a role<br />
consistent with freedom and true democracy.<br />
000000000 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
