<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1288</transcript-id>
    <title>INTER-PARLIAMENTARY UNION - SPEECH OF WELCOME BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. HAROLD HOLT AT PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA. 12TH APRIL 1966.</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/04/1966</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001288.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
IPTR-PPLIK 1 TRYU1ION<br />
SPELCH OF ' JELCOIE, BY THE P-RIME I1INISTER. MR. HAROLD HOLT<br />
AT PAFIJIMENT HOUSE, CA1U1BERRA 12TH APRIL. 1%<br />
Mr. Chairman, Mr. President, Distinguished Delegates, Ladies and<br />
Gentlemen: Thank you for that very encouraging reception.<br />
It is a much more enthusiastic one than I usually receive in this<br />
Chamber. Indeed, as I look around the Chamber, I was a little<br />
discomfited at the outset to see how crowdod the Opposition benches<br />
had become, but as my gaze wanders further afield, I see that quite<br />
notable members of the Opposition are scattered on the Government<br />
side, so that itself is an encouraging sign.<br />
I am very happy to be able to add the w-arm welcome<br />
of the Australian Government and the Australian people to the<br />
meeting of the I. P. U. here in Canberra. ' 4c feel that not only is<br />
this most timely and opportune, having regard to circumstances<br />
unfolding around us in this area of the world. But that it is an<br />
honour to Australia which vie value, I assure you.<br />
You were speaking, M11r. 4) eaker of the symbolism of<br />
the Chair, and could I just round off your story because there is<br />
one chapter which I think would be of interest to our fellow<br />
Parliamentarians. As Er. Speaker, our Chairman has told you, our<br />
Chair, a replica of that in the House of Commons, was presented<br />
to us by the Commonwealth Parliamentary Association Branch there.<br />
In the period of the blitz, the House of Commons was bombed, and<br />
the Speaker's Chair was destroyed, so we were able to build a<br />
replica of our Chair and send that back to the House of Commons,<br />
and so the Parliamentary tradition, despite wars and threats to<br />
peace, can continue through the centuries if men and women of good<br />
will only have the determination to sec that this is so. And I<br />
believe that there is some happy symbolism in that for us.<br />
I hope you will find in the warmth, the sunshine<br />
and the tranquillity of the Canberra scene also a suitable setting<br />
for this gathering and that there in that warmth and tranquillity<br />
there will be a symbolic atmosphere created for your discussions<br />
in the days that lie ahead.<br />
I said that we Vlere gratified that you had chosen<br />
Australia. This is, I believe, the niost representative gathering<br />
of Parliamentarians ever to have been held in this country.<br />
There have been conferences here of various kinds in the past,<br />
some largely attended by 1dembers of Parliament and our Commonwealth<br />
Parliamentary Association has met here more than once, but I<br />
question whether we have had so representative a gathering from<br />
all parts of the world, all the continents, and from so many<br />
differing conditions and habits of life as we find represented<br />
in this gathering. Surely it is a hopeful sign for the future of<br />
mankind that men and women from the Parliaments of the iworld<br />
can meet togother in friendship ; u-ith a detormiration to find a<br />
better-ae understanding of ea. ch other, to become better informed<br />
0 090 .12 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
about the countries of the world and to take advantage of the<br />
conference meetings to learn something in more detail of the host<br />
country itself. And this is an aspect, of course, which is<br />
particularly prized by us.<br />
We in Australia want to be better known and better<br />
understood because it is through that better knowledge and<br />
understanding that friendship ripens and the causes of animosity<br />
or dissension tend to disappear. And here in this area of the<br />
world, I believe it is the first time that you have met for your<br />
Spring meetings which, as Mr. Speaker pointed out comes in the<br />
Australian Autumn, but the first time that you have met outside<br />
Europe. The first time, therefore, that you will have met in this<br />
Southern Hemisphere. And we believe that here are to be found<br />
and by " here" I mean in the total area of Asia some of the most<br />
compelling and difficult problems that the world has to face at<br />
the present time, and I shall say a word or two on that in a moment.<br />
But another reason why I welcome your presence here<br />
is that we become so conscious that we are living in turbulent,<br />
troubled, restless and rapidly-changing world, and I think we<br />
become over-conscious of that fact because it is thrust upon us<br />
every day by our newspapers, by the modern media of communication,<br />
the radio and the television. Bad news travels fast and good<br />
news tends to be no news so far as the journals of public dissemination<br />
are concerned. The sensational, the challenging and the<br />
troublous, these are the things that hit the headlines, and I<br />
believe it necessary for people in public office, for their<br />
national Parliaments, to get a more realistic and balanced<br />
perspective from time to time of what is oing on, certainly in<br />
their own country, and so far as the rest of the world is concerned,<br />
what is going on in the rest of the world. If you have a daily<br />
diet of trouble and strife, then you begin to think that this is<br />
the sort of world we live in, but of course it always has been<br />
a troubled and difficult world.<br />
Ours happens to be the generation which is told of<br />
these troublous occurrences within minutos virtually of their<br />
happening in almost any part of the world, and each day as we<br />
listen to the latest bulletin of news, we are made conscious of<br />
these things. And then, of course, we can't always rely, as<br />
faithfully as we would wish to do, upon the information which<br />
reaches us. In a world which is highly competitive as to its<br />
political systems and its ideologies, there tends to be in the<br />
propaganda directed from one country to another again a distortion<br />
of fact which makes honest and objective assessment the more<br />
difficult for us. And so hbo valuable it is to have people<br />
coming together in a spirit jf friendship, informed minds capable<br />
of assessing an argument or a situation, and in this way adding<br />
to the sum of human understanding and human knowledge about one<br />
another, and as you go back to your Parliaments, capable of<br />
faithfully and objectively reporting what it is that you have been<br />
able to learn. And so there should be a good dividend for a world<br />
that is striving for peace and social justice from the meeting of<br />
so many representative minds in the di scussions of this week. / 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
I thought Mr. Chairman, that it miht be useful<br />
if for a few minutes I tried to sketch in something of the country<br />
in which you find yourselves not to act as a sort of travel<br />
agent or a tourist organisation but because certain things have<br />
been attempted here which may be helpful to others, just as we in<br />
turn are helped by what is achieved in other parts of the world.<br />
No country has a monopoly of achievement or expertise. Science,<br />
fortunately, is more international than politics and so we can all<br />
profit from the achievements of each other.<br />
This is a country in which we have had to call very<br />
heavily upon science and upon skill. Most of you, unfortunately,<br />
will see comparatively little of it. As you probably know, it is<br />
the oldest continent geologically; the largest island approximately<br />
the size of the United States in area if you exclude Alaska<br />
from the United States, but we don't enjoy the same favourable<br />
terrestrial conditions throughout the whole of the continent that<br />
the United States would. There is a coastal fringe which is<br />
reasonably well watered, but ours is largely an arid continent<br />
and we have to struggle over much of our areas with a harsh,<br />
unyielding soil which calls for the skills we can bring, the<br />
application of science, the addition of fertilisers, trace elements<br />
in deficient soils and the development of legumes that can flourish<br />
where otherwise the lack of water would destroy any herbage at all.<br />
This is the sort of problem which challenges our attention, and: so<br />
water conservation, irrigation schemes, the supplementing of the<br />
soil, these are some of the tasks to which a country which has been<br />
one of the great suppliers to the rest of the world of foodstuffs<br />
and rural production must turn if our production is to continue to<br />
increase. But we have found also that it is necessary for us<br />
also to accumulate the resources out of which development can<br />
oroceed and so we have become one of the highest savers per capita<br />
in the world. Just on 27 per cent. of our gross national prodpct<br />
represents savings and our expenditure on capital equipment is<br />
exceeded, I believe, in per capita terms by only one country in the<br />
world and that is Japan. But fortunately, in addition to our own<br />
savings resources, we have been able to create a climate favourable<br />
to. enterprise and to capital and Australia has attracted investments,<br />
risk capital, from many parts of the world and this has brought<br />
with it new skills, new techniques, new industries, and as a result,<br />
a country which before the Second World ' Jar was thought of largely<br />
as a country of rural production its wool, its wheat, its meat,<br />
butter and sugar known around the markets of the world has so<br />
diversified and developed its secondary industries that to no doubt<br />
the surprise of many of you, we have fortunately now in secondary<br />
industry about the same section of our population that you would<br />
find in the United States of America. In percentage terms to<br />
population and work force, it is approximately the same as in the<br />
United States. Now the most recent development which makes for a<br />
more significant and important Australia in the eyes of the rest<br />
of the world has been a series of quite fabulous mineral discoveries.<br />
It is only a few years ago that we maintained as a Government, a<br />
prohibition on the export of iron ore because we couldn't see<br />
reserves that seemed to be more than was needed for our own<br />
Australian steel industry. Then came the discovery litarally of / 4 </p>
<p>-4-<br />
mountains of high-grade iron ore and in WIestern Aistralia, one<br />
of the States of the Commonwealth, there it has been assessed<br />
that some 15,000 million tons of high grade iron ore, of a<br />
percentage of 65; any of you who are knowledgeable of these<br />
things will pick up the percentage and its significance but all<br />
I am told is that it is very good iron ore, and already firm<br />
contracts have been arranged between Australia and Japan for the<br />
supply of this iron ore, I think I am right in saying to a total<br />
value of2,360 million, and we have been told that there will be<br />
other markets, even markets in Europe for this iron ore despite<br />
the problem of distance because of its quality.<br />
Then bauxite, a basic material for aluminium, has<br />
been found in what may prove to be the largest bauxite deposits<br />
anywhere in the world. But when ou add to this Pandora's box<br />
of mineral treasures the copper, he lead, the zinc, new<br />
discoveries of nickel and manganese, you will, I think, gain some<br />
concept of the basis for our confidence that not only will the<br />
country continue to grow in strength and prosperity but that in<br />
the years ahead our export income from mineral production will<br />
probably match and exceed that which we derive from our largest<br />
export item, that aell-known commodity, Australian wool.<br />
Now, I have mentioned these things because they<br />
have been achieved in a comparatively young country, ( our first<br />
settlement was in 1788) and with a comparatively small population<br />
of people making the most effective use that we could of our<br />
work force and applying as effectively as we could thC mod6rn<br />
aids which mechanical equipment, electronic and other engineering<br />
development can produce for us. And so wc have been able to<br />
sustain a high rate of growth, a high rate of population growth<br />
by the standards of Europe, although, of course, not by the<br />
standards of Asia or South America. But for any of our United<br />
States or British friends who are here today, it may interest them<br />
to know that if their population rate were to be geared to the<br />
sme rate of increase as that of Australia, in the United States<br />
you would need to build annually more than half a million<br />
additional homes above that which is now proceeding and in the<br />
United Kingdom about 170,000 homes. So you will see that when<br />
you add to the problem of the home construction the need for<br />
schools and hospitals and modern amenities that go wiith an<br />
increasing population, then you have an indication of the total<br />
problems that we face in this country. I could qrhaps sum it<br />
up by saying that our broad objectives are those development,<br />
of what are still relatively undeveloped national resources, to<br />
build population for these purposes, to give full employment to<br />
our people, not only because this is a cardinal aspect of national<br />
policy for any well-managed country these days but because a<br />
country of loss than 12 million people must make the most<br />
effective employment of its labour force of w'hich it is capable.<br />
Then, because we are a country of small population<br />
in a troubled and restless are-of the wrorld, we must apply<br />
rather more of our substance to the build-up of our defence<br />
capacity, more than we wJould crish but certainly no more than the<br />
hazards that we feel , e must face in the years ahead would require<br />
of us. And so with development, defenco, risin72 standards for our<br />
people and a rising programme of intornztional aid, we are trying<br />
to behave responsibly and as a good neighbour in this area of the<br />
world. </p>
<p>I am able to tell you that Australia has not shirked<br />
its responsibilities in the field of international aid and that<br />
we rank per capita fourth in all the countries of the world in<br />
relation to the aid distributed through a variety of channels<br />
and organisations. Now that, Mr. Chairman, gives a very sketchy outline<br />
of what is occurring in this country. It may interest you to<br />
know further that our system is one based principally on free<br />
enterprise but one job in every four in Australia is provided by<br />
the Government through one of its many utilities or through one<br />
of the many Government services. So in a sense we have a mixed<br />
system with the Government attending to the sort of public utilities<br />
which don't normally call for a competitive system. Where<br />
competition is desirable, we try to arrange matters so that there<br />
will be competitors in the private field, ensuring an effective<br />
and satisfactory service for the public.<br />
You will have noticed those of you who have had any<br />
time in the country that we don't go in so very much for<br />
apartment dwelling in the way that you find this in Europe and<br />
in parts of Asia, and indeed in most countries of the world.<br />
The general run of Australian likes to live in his own home with<br />
his own car and a small garden to look after, able to get away<br />
to one of the pleasant places that can be visited in what is for<br />
most of Australia, a temperate and very agreeable climate.<br />
And we are glad to be able to report to you that as you fly over<br />
the cities and see the tens of thousands, hundreds of thousands<br />
of homes that you will see underneath you from the aircraft in<br />
Sydney, Melbourne or one of the other capitals of the States of<br />
the Commonwealth, the homes will be occupied by homo-owners.<br />
Seventysix per cent. of the houses occupied in Australia are<br />
occupied by people who either own that home or are in process<br />
of acquiring it.<br />
Now I have said sorething on the economic side, and<br />
turning perhaps to something more agrecable, a lighter feature of<br />
our national life, we enjoy in this continent a remarkable range<br />
and variety of experience. I mentioned that it is a country in<br />
which much of it lies behind a coastal fringe and most of it is<br />
very arid indeed. But it is a country of contrasts and paradoxes<br />
in that in the North of Queensland, quite recently I was met by<br />
a body of people who at a time when I had taken deputations in<br />
the South of Australia wanting financial relief against some<br />
drought which was occurring in their part of the world, in the<br />
North of Queensland, I had a deputation of people wanting<br />
financial assistance because they had had so much rain that they<br />
couldn't plant their sugar crop. So we have a country, as<br />
described in one of our documentary films recently ' e run from<br />
the tropics to the snows". In the north of Australia you have the<br />
sort of rain forest which is typical of tropical countries, and<br />
rain forest so thick and lush that it is attractive to botanists<br />
from all parts of the world. Then by contrast, you come down<br />
hero to the Australian Alps and we can show you more snow than<br />
is to be found in Switzerland. So you have a country in which<br />
tropical production and temperate production can be achieved<br />
making the nation very largely self-sufficient in the production<br />
of items of this character. / 6<br />
L 5 </p>
<p>6<br />
As to production, we have been able to make a gesture<br />
quits recently which I hope the developing countries will find<br />
helpful. We have provided a preference for the entry of their<br />
oroduction into Australia and this was examined closely recently<br />
by the GATT and the GATT approved of this arrangement and we are<br />
hopeful that what we have provided in that direction will spread<br />
by way of example to other countries.<br />
Now I don't want to dwell too long, Mr. Chairman, on<br />
Australia, but it is not an easy country to discover in a matter<br />
of days. Some of you may have already come in contact with our<br />
decimal currency. It is only about two months February 14th<br />
since we made the changeover from pounds, shillings and pence<br />
to a decimal system of dollars and cents. Those of you who have<br />
acquired a range of the coins will find that on the side of the<br />
coin opposite the effigy of Her Majesty The Queen will be reproduced<br />
an Australian animal, and each of these animals is unique to this<br />
country and will not be found anywhere else in the world;<br />
geologically the oldest country with some of the strangest and<br />
weirdest of animals. In fact so weird that somebody has written<br />
a book about us calling us " They're a ' Jeird Mob". You may find<br />
that so in your experience of us as the week prococds.<br />
But here is an exciting country, and having at a period<br />
of great change in the circumstances of the nations of Asia,<br />
a role , we believe, to play of increasing importance in the years<br />
ahead, a role as a bridge of understanding between the countries<br />
of the West and the countries of Asia, a role as a groat supplier<br />
of foodstuffs, of raw materials, of minerals to the growing<br />
industrialisation of Asia. Here we arc situated with a handful<br />
of people in an area of the world in which there are 650 million<br />
Chinese more than 400 million Indians, some 110million Indonesians,<br />
' 100 million. Pakistanis, Itink it is-altogether some 1,500 million<br />
people in Asia .: ith a birthrate which should, if it maintans its<br />
present trend, see a doubling of that population, if this is humanly<br />
practicable and possible, ( this, anyhow, is the way the curve is<br />
proceeding) by the end of this centur e. ll, quite obviously,<br />
if this hungry world, and so much of Asia is a hungry area of the<br />
world, is to be fed and supplied, growing industrialisation calling<br />
for the raw materials and the more sophisticated equipment of<br />
a developing economy, then quite obviously Australia has a part<br />
to play in that developing process.<br />
But there is . the darker side totho problem of Asia,<br />
and here perhaps are to be faced some of the greatest hazards<br />
which mankind has to meet in the years loading to the end of this<br />
century, and it will be the firm intention of this friendly<br />
country to do what it can to make an effective contribution towards<br />
the attainment of peace and justice, social justice, justice as<br />
between countries in our own area of the world and indeed throughout<br />
the world as a whole. To some of us when we look at the problems<br />
which confront us in government, the picture looks so dark at times<br />
as almost to encourage despair, but we must recognise that despite<br />
all these problems and difficulties, however painfully slow the<br />
process may appear to be, there is developing a more sensitive<br />
conscience around the countries of the world in relation to those<br />
less favoured, there is a growing acceptance of responsibility to<br />
do something about those things. In my own public life, I have<br />
participated in discussions in such bodies as the International Bank,<br />
/ 7 </p>
<p>-7<br />
the International Development Association, the International<br />
Monetary Fund. We have contributed to the recent discussions<br />
of UNOTAD the United Nations Conference on Trade and Development.<br />
There is the United Nations show, SUNFED, which also is doing<br />
good work in its own direction. And out of these processes, some<br />
dividends occur from time to time. join together on an Indus<br />
waters scheme or we are able to help on some constructive project<br />
of one kind or another. e in Australia have a tremendous<br />
responsibility in relation to Papua and New Guinea, trying to leai.<br />
there virtually a Stone Age people to a viable independence within<br />
the earliest practicable period of time consistent with their own<br />
wishes, and if any of you have the opportunity to travel through<br />
that part of the world before you return home, I think you will<br />
find it a splendid examiple of what enlightened government is able<br />
to achieve with the co-operation of a people seeking better<br />
standards of literacy and of health and of economidc independence.<br />
These are some of the victories of peace which perhaps<br />
are even more glorious than those of war.<br />
tr. Chairman, I have no wish to detain you from tour<br />
important discussions. It has been said by some wise man that<br />
it is better to travel hopefully than to arrive, but as in most<br />
statements of this kind which are superficially attractive, there<br />
are of course the exceptions. I hope that your visit to Australia<br />
proves one of theim. I have no doubt you travelled hopefully,<br />
looking to the experience of discovery of a new continent and<br />
perhaps for many of you a new and somewhat strange people. You<br />
will find us a very friendly people and wie would have no better<br />
Uish than you would enjoy your stay with us and find it of<br />
increasing and helpful interest to you and that from the discussions<br />
of the I. P. U. hero in Canberra will be a contribution to the better<br />
understanding among peoples whaich will be the best foundation<br />
of the peace and social justice to which vie all aspire.<br />
I hope that you enjoy your stay vi th us and that you<br />
return feeling that Australia is a continent which must be revisited<br />
not once but many time s. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
