<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5544</transcript-id>
    <title>BUSINESSMEN&#039;S BREAKFAST, BRISBANE, ADDRESS AS DELIVERED</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/03/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005544.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS OFFICE TRAN4SCRIPT WEDNESDAY MARCH 18 1931<br />
BUSINESSMEN'S BREAKFAST, BRISBANE, ADDRESS AS DELIVERED.<br />
on a regular basis, but that will probably be. once a<br />
year for Federal Cabinet meetings in Brisbane. I certainly<br />
find them valuable... inaudible.., and meet in a more informal1<br />
way than is generally the case if we are coming to Queensland<br />
for a particular function, and then going out again.<br />
I welcome very much the opportunities that have been<br />
available. I said yesterday at this kind of function, two, three<br />
or four years ago, it would have been a necessity to argue<br />
our economic policy quite hard and to try and demonstrate<br />
the factsaid figures that the policy was working, that it<br />
was right, there was no alternative policy, and that we just<br />
had to persist with it. But, I don't believe there is a need in Australia<br />
and certainly in Queensland for remarks of that kind at the<br />
present tlimle because this State is moving forward very<br />
strongly indeed. Investment is going ahead rapidly and<br />
employment in Queensland grew by nearly 5% over the last<br />
12 months.<br />
I haven't taken out comparisons with earlier years, but<br />
I think: it riust be the best growth in employment for many,<br />
many vei3 nd -it iJS much better than many countries overseas.<br />
This -esult c_ policies. None of it has happened<br />
by az~.:. It has a-t times, been a hard grind in . inaudible..<br />
back :. u. Ier anai getting inflation down and helping<br />
to he circ-um:-stance for Australian industries<br />
and en: r': r_-ses to again be competitive. Butthat has been<br />
done.' It is not only in the resources area. There is the optimism<br />
and the enthusiasm and activity in Queensland or in Australia.<br />
The manufacturing industry, as many of you here would know,<br />
have been doing md-ch bet-ter and have been getting out into<br />
export markets in a way which four or five years ago they<br />
would have believed to be quite impossible. We see the results<br />
of that, of the cost of an export incentives scheme which<br />
has probably cost them four times more than the partners(?)<br />
estimated when it was first introduced. That is because of thd<br />
success and growth of exports.<br />
The priorities we have as a government -our tactics obviously<br />
change from time to time as circumstances change and the settings<br />
of policy obviously have to change but the strategy doesn't.<br />
alter. It is just as important as it ever was, to keep bearing<br />
down on inflation as a prerequisite for profitable enterpriset<br />
and for growing employment. We intend to do that.<br />
That obviously has consequences for expenditure. It has<br />
consequences for monetary policy, and for total levels of<br />
government activity. There has been a good deal of discussion<br />
about tax over recent days or weeks or months depending<br />
on . whateve perspective you want to look at it I suppose.<br />
I ' don't think it has been adequately understood that over / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
the last five years, while the Commonwealth expenditures<br />
have grown by about 1% a year in real terms, State expenditures<br />
and local government expenditures have grown very much more than<br />
that. I don't know how many people are aware that States<br />
and local government end up by spending over 50% of all<br />
the dollars collected by Australians in tax. State levels<br />
of government spend more than does the Commonwealth.<br />
If there is to be expenditure restraint of a kind that<br />
will make reductions in income tax of a reasonable and useful<br />
kind and I don't want to be dramatic about that reasonabl,.<br />
and useful kind possible, expenditure restraint will have to<br />
be exercised by State governments as well as by the Commonwealth<br />
government. I always believe that the best measure of restraint in a<br />
government is what it does with its own employees. Over the<br />
last five years, our employees have been reduced by about<br />
10,000, while State employees, not just Queensland but<br />
all States, have increased by the best part of 100,000.<br />
That doesn't seem to me to be the hallmark of the government<br />
activity that is particularly restrained in its expendithre.<br />
If you look at the levels of expenditure in the States,<br />
compared with 10 years ago, and if you projected forward<br />
the same reai level of expenditure as States had been<br />
involved in years ago, you would find that in this State<br />
and at t-e level of expenditure today, instead<br />
of a .: irler leve1 you would find that the citizens of<br />
Queens hod txes reduced by $ 900 million a year.<br />
Now, be a substantial sum. : t has nothing to do<br />
with oo. ro nwCeoalmrhm onwealth taxes. It indicates<br />
the e::: znrto which gcovernment has grown, and the extent<br />
to wh.-. n es have grown over and above the real levels<br />
that e a decade ago.<br />
Queensland is not by itself in that. I think the equivalent<br />
-figure for New South Wales is $ 1,700 million, for Victoria<br />
$ 1,500 million. In-the first five years of the decade, under<br />
our predecessors the Commonwealth was a pretty fierce sinner<br />
in the area as well. Over the last five years we have done a<br />
good deal to seek to redress that, as the employment figures<br />
indicate. But the point that I do want to emphasise, is that if there<br />
are to be tax cuts which I know, as I have said before,<br />
the good Premier wants, there also has to be expenditure<br />
restraint. I am not quite sure that any of the States want<br />
to hear that side of the story because at every Premiers<br />
conference that has ever existed, on every item that has<br />
ever been raised, Premiers have asked for more money. If<br />
we said yes to all the requests of all the Premiers there<br />
would be no point in employers paying their wages to employees,<br />
they could post them straight to the Federal tax man, because<br />
even then it would not be enough to meet the requests and<br />
aspirations of the States in terms of expenditure. / 3 </p>
<p>3<br />
It might seem odd that that is so, but that is just the way<br />
it is operated. One of the greatest disappointments for me<br />
over the years at Premiers conferences is that in. terms of<br />
expenditure restraint, in terms of putting some kind of limit<br />
on what the markets can bear for loah cuts, it always has to<br />
be the Commonwealth, and generally it ends up by being some<br />
kind of unilateral decision as to the maximum that can be<br />
taken from the tax payers of Australia or the maximum that<br />
we take out of the markets, because obviously, if we press_<br />
too hard, it does have an impact on interest rates, and'<br />
it absorbs funds and resouces that would otherwise go to<br />
the private sector.<br />
Now, in circumstances in which the private part of this<br />
economy is growing much more strongly than before, if<br />
we are to avoid the inflationary pressures and a resurgence of<br />
those pressures, it's perhaps more important for governments<br />
to be restrainted in their expenditure because otherwise<br />
there will be greater competition for resources that<br />
are inevitably finite. That competition would put up<br />
the price of money and re-establish inflationary pressures<br />
of a kind that we wouldn't want. That is only to say that<br />
restraint in government expenditure this year is just<br />
as important as it was five years ago, and on some counts,<br />
more important than it was then.<br />
That iS : Z4-the Premiers conference in April is going to be<br />
all ab: u: the lev of funds that are going to be made<br />
availah-&gt; the States from the Commonwealth. It has<br />
nothiu. c -io with the split up of funds between the States.<br />
In 197-e Premiers all agreed that the distribution of<br />
funds th1e States was something that ought to be<br />
examined. : ne formula between them was set in 1959 and this<br />
is so. e-2=. the Commonwealth can be pretty relaxed about<br />
because indoesn't affect our budgets as it was set in<br />
1959, but it is still heavily influenced by the end of<br />
State taxation and the introduction of uniform taxation<br />
going as far back as 1942, by the distribution in those<br />
days. I--<br />
Obviously circumstances have changed. All the Premiers<br />
recognise that they have, that there ought to be a look<br />
at the relativities between the States to see whether the<br />
break up of funds that are available to the Commonwealth<br />
is just and fair equitable in the interests of all Australia.<br />
That is what the Grants Commission is all about. I don't<br />
know what they are g6ing to report. I don't know what<br />
evidence the States are putting in front of the Grants<br />
Commission. I hope that the various things the Premier has been<br />
saying about resources over the last couple of days<br />
has been said to the Grants Commission because that is where<br />
they ought to have been said. If he hasn't even at this late<br />
stage I would urge him to.<br />
But we need that Grants Commission report and then hopefully<br />
we can look at the in the clear and careful manner to see what<br />
changes if any ought to be made in the distribution of the<br />
quantum which the Commonwealth is prepared to make available. / 4 </p>
<p>4<br />
That repor-t won't be available, as I understand it, until<br />
June. There hasn't been an interim report as was reported<br />
a couple of days ago, certainly not one that I have seen<br />
and not one the Treasurer has seen. It will be available<br />
in June so it can't be part of the discussions that are taking<br />
place in April which will be relevant to the total<br />
sum that we are prepared to provide, and that obviously<br />
will have a. very high relevance to our capacity to make<br />
adjustments to income tax.<br />
I think you probably understand now why we didn't move<br />
to much greater indirect taxation. It could have been<br />
done, but if you were going to reduce the tax scales by<br />
say seven points each, each scale, to make the standard<br />
rate 25 cents and take 7 cents off the two higher rates,<br />
that would cost $ 3.5 to $ 4 billion. To collect that money<br />
by indirect taxation would add on direct and indirect<br />
affects and much more depending upon the reactions of<br />
the Arbitration Commission in relation to wages. It would<br />
add 6% to 7% to inflation. We know what that would do<br />
to businesses, exports, overseas investment it seemedN<br />
to us that it would put the progress of Australia back<br />
a considerable distance and in the circumttances that<br />
were stili far more inflationary than we want, and more<br />
inflationary than you would want, that we shouldn't have<br />
taken that step.<br />
That t c2s force us back, with adjustments I have<br />
ever i income tax, to expenditure restraint.<br />
There 7 believe-pienty of room for that.<br />
There -oncerns i the community at the present time. We are<br />
y concerned in relation to the 35 hour week<br />
and -i : d2rl Govrnrr. ent has made decisions to make<br />
sure n -hwe ider Australian community will fully understand<br />
the coEst:.-of a 35 hour week, or fully understand that<br />
trade unions that press for a 35 hour week are in fact<br />
. pressing for higher unemployment, reduced sales of Australian<br />
made goods, and reduced activity in this country.<br />
We will obviously be lending continuing and full support<br />
to the industry associations, through Arbitration Commission<br />
cases, and we will alsobe undertaking a public campaign on<br />
our own account to make sure that the costs of a 35 hour<br />
week are fully understood by the wider Australian conmmunity.<br />
I believe that it is tragic that sections: of the trade union<br />
movement and the ACTU in its official policies so avidly<br />
press for policies whose only practical result can be much<br />
higher unemployment than would otherwise be the case.<br />
It is especially so against the circumstance in which<br />
last year average wages went up between 13% and 14%, nearly<br />
five points higher than inflation over the same period.<br />
That again indicates that there is need for greater efforts<br />
by all of us, I think, on that account, because with the<br />
enormous prospects open to us, unreasonable union activity<br />
lack of control over wages and wage adjustments I think<br />
they are the only two things that run any possibility of<br />
marring the prospects ahead of us. There is no doubt that<br />
union activity could destroy Australia's future. I don't believe </p>
<p>5<br />
it will happen because I have much greater confidence in the<br />
general common sense of the average Australian and the average<br />
Australian trade unionist. It is common-sense that a number<br />
of union leaders give their constituents little credit for.<br />
I don't believe the activities of the ACTU as we have seen<br />
over the last month win any support amongst the rank and file<br />
of unionists, or amongst the generality of the Australian<br />
public. It is going to be up to governments, State and Federal,<br />
and all those with a real interest and concern about what s<br />
happening to their own enterprise to make sure that in terms<br />
of industrial relations, wage changes, reductions in working<br />
hours, the great future which is within the grasp of all<br />
Australians isn't signficantly damaged. That will take<br />
considerable effort.<br />
But that aside, the prospects ahead of us, and the prospects<br />
for this State, are good indeed.<br />
I would like to thank you for coming here this morning.<br />
I would be happy now to react to whatever you might want?<br />
to say or to any questions you might like to put. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
