<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3011</transcript-id>
    <title>PARRAMATTA BY-ELECTION - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR EG WHITLAM QC MP, PARRAMATTA TOWN HALL, FRIDAY 14 SEPTEMBER 1973</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/09/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003011.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
( N<br />
EMBARGO: 8.15 P. M,<br />
PARRA14ATTA BY-ELECTION<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. E. G. WHITLAM, M. P.,<br />
PARRAMATTA TOWN HALL,<br />
FRIDAY, 14 SEPTEMBER 1973<br />
A fortnight ago, I launched Labor's campaign for Parramatta.<br />
Tonight, I launch another campaign not a campaign on behalf of the<br />
Australian Labor Party, but a campaign on behalf of the Australian<br />
people. And this campaign is not a test for the Australian Labor<br />
Party but a test for the Australian people themselves. And it is<br />
a test for great, important, and vocal sections of the Australian<br />
community. The Australian Government shall, before Christmas,<br />
submit to you, the people, a referendum to give the national<br />
government power over prices. The Australian Government is<br />
determined to combat inflation. We shall all have the opportunity<br />
within the next few days, within the next few weeks, within the<br />
next few months, to see whether that determination is shared by<br />
the individuals and groups who have been so vocal on this matter so<br />
recently. In particular you will all be able to judge within the<br />
next few days, how sincere the Liberal Party, the Country Party,<br />
and the five Senators currently engaged in courtship with the<br />
Country Party, are about the fight against inflation. The acid<br />
test will come next week. We-have heard the Leader of the<br />
opposition demanding a prices and incomes freeze. The National<br />
Government a Whitlam Government, any more than a McMahon<br />
Government, even with so brilliant a Treasurer as Mr. Snedden<br />
has not the power to freeze prices or incomes. The Liberals<br />
know this; the writers of editorials know this; the people of<br />
Australia know this. We propose to ask the people to change it.<br />
to give us at least the power which governments in any comparable<br />
country, whatever their systems, unitary or federal, already have.<br />
We'shall be seeking that power; but before we can do so, we have<br />
to get the Parliament to authorise us to refer the matter to the<br />
people. And whether that reference is made now lies fairly and<br />
squarely with our opponents. We await their declaration of intent.<br />
There are other people involved in this matter, other<br />
people responsible for the course that the Government has felt<br />
impelled to take. I refer to the Premiers in the three eastern<br />
States the anti-Labor Premiers. The basic reason why the<br />
Government has felt obliged to take this course is because of<br />
the refusal of these Premiers either to use their powers the<br />
undoubted powers of these States or to refer their powers to the<br />
National Government. These Premiers blather and bleat about<br />
inflation; yet they would not budge an inch towards helping the<br />
National Government do its job. I acknowlege, rather, I proclaim,<br />
the fundamental responsibility of the National Government for the<br />
economic management and the well-being of this nation. I do not<br />
slide away from that at all. But the Premiers in the anti--. Tabor<br />
States have refused point blank to give us the constitutional and<br />
legal power to do our job. It is because of that refusal that<br />
we now propose to go direct to the people of Australia. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
At Ermington, a fortnight ago, I undertook to ask the<br />
Premiers of New South Wales and Victoria to refer this power.<br />
I put the proposition to them on the opening day of the<br />
Constitutional Convention, last Monday. I said:<br />
" The Australian Paradox is that the National Government<br />
is in a stronger position vis a vis the States in<br />
financial matters than the national governments in any<br />
other federal system; but it is in a weaker position in<br />
economic powers than national governments in any other<br />
federal system. There is the matter of prices, for<br />
example. The Nixon Administration had the power to<br />
introduce price freezes. The Australian Government has<br />
not the McMahon Government no more than the Whitlam<br />
Government. There may be arguments about the economic<br />
effectiveness of such freezes, but there can be no question<br />
that if they are to be in any way effective whatsoever, they<br />
must be immediate and unchallenged in their application.<br />
I do not assert and I do not concede that the Australian<br />
Parliament could not enforce an effective prices policy<br />
by legislating under the corporations power. I do,<br />
however, assert, and I have to concede, that such<br />
legislation would be challenged in the High Court and its<br />
application would be stalled for many, many months in the<br />
process. The crucial element of immediacy would be lost.<br />
Unquestionably, the Australian Parliament should have<br />
legislative power over prices, whatever the Government in<br />
office. The Parliament can try to obtain the power by<br />
referendum but that would take some months the number of<br />
months depending upon whether the Bill was passed or rejected<br />
by the Senate. Alternatively, the Parliament can obtain<br />
the power by reference, by some or all State Parliaments,<br />
That is something which could be done in a matter of weeks.<br />
The reference of power could be permanent or temporary.<br />
If, however, the Governments in the two great States of<br />
New South Wales and Victoria, Governments which currently<br />
have a majority in both Houses of their Parliaments, decline<br />
to introduce a Bill, then the reference would be ineffective.<br />
I venture to say that without New South Wales and Victoria,<br />
it would be a largely futile exercise, ' While, with those<br />
two States alone referring, it could be made effective<br />
throughout Australia. If the Premiers of New-South Wales<br />
and Victoria were to offer such a reference, then this<br />
Convention would be indeed a landmark in Australian economic,<br />
political and constitutional history."<br />
But those ? remiers have refused to refer this power to the<br />
national government.<br />
The National Government of Australia should have<br />
reasonable constitutional powers to manage the nation's economy.<br />
We have not got it; we now seek it. The States the anti-<br />
Labor States will not do their job; we now have to ask you<br />
to equip us to do the job. </p>
<p>-3-<br />
I recognise, and everybody recognises, that the kind<br />
of inflation we are now experiencing is not only a matter of<br />
prices. There is the matter of incomes and that means your<br />
income, your salary, your wage. The fact is, of course, that<br />
Australia has a highly complex and highly regulated system of<br />
wage fixation. The system is in fact one-sided; wages are<br />
fixed, prices are not. But I can say this, speaking not only<br />
as the Prime Minister of Australia, speaking not only as the<br />
Leader of the Federal Parliamentary Party, speaking not only<br />
as the Leader of the Australian Labor Party, but as the Leader<br />
of the Australian Labor movement if the people of Australia<br />
give us power to control prices and if our efforts to contain<br />
inflation within reasonable limits then fail, we shall receive<br />
the full co-operation of the trade union movement in restraining<br />
wages incomes. But what the trade union movement will first ask<br />
is that the national government and the whole public shall<br />
together show that they are dinkum on this matter of curbing<br />
inflation. If we show we are dinkum, the trade union movement<br />
stands ready to show restraint in the interest of the whole<br />
people, of whom its members and dependants form the great bulk.<br />
I still appeal to every section of the community to<br />
get this whole matter in perspective. The national government<br />
needs reasonable powers to manage the economy. Inflation is<br />
undoubtedly a major problem, the besetting problem of current<br />
economic management. But is it not the be-all and end-all of<br />
our national problems. And indeed it is as much a inter-national<br />
problem as it is a national one. But I long ago determined that<br />
the Labor Government which I head would not be reduced to a<br />
nullity by any unreal pre-occupation. It would be monstrous<br />
if a Labor Government, coming into power after 23 years were to<br />
attempt nothing more than curbing some of the gross economic<br />
defects created by our predecessors. When the Government framed<br />
its Budget, it had to look at the whole range of problems created<br />
by our predecessors, the whole backlog of 23 years of conservative<br />
rule. Growing inflation was only one of these problems. It is<br />
true that the Treasurer could have brought down a traditional<br />
Budget designed to contain economic growth. It is true, for<br />
instance, that we could have renegged on our program.<br />
But what would that have meant?<br />
What is the big new factor in the spending of this<br />
Government? It is on education. I could have starved the<br />
schools; I could thereby have received plaudits for a " responsible"<br />
Budget; and I should have penalised every Australian child, now at*<br />
school or about to enter school not just for this year but for<br />
the rest of his life. I would not have a bar of it. </p>
<p>-4-<br />
I for one am not prepared to say that an Australian<br />
child who happens to be in school in 1973 must pay the penalty<br />
for 23 years of Liberal mismanagement or pay the penalty for a<br />
passing economic problem, no matter how difficult and complex<br />
and intransigent that economic problem may be. I am not prepared<br />
to say that Government spending designed to reduce costs or to<br />
promote production in years and decades to come must be<br />
indefinitely postponed, just in order to save money in 1973.<br />
One of the principal reasons why our costs are rising is because<br />
spending in the public sector was postponed or entirely refused<br />
for so long. Why are land costs soaring? Because of the refusal of<br />
past governments to involve themselves in public ownership of<br />
land. Why are transport costs soaring? Because of the refusal<br />
of previous governments to spend money on the upgrading of the<br />
public transport system, and particularly by the refusal of the<br />
national government to involve itself in urban transport systems.<br />
Why are our cities so expensive to the individual and the<br />
family?. Because of the failure of past national governments of<br />
Australia to involve themselves in the business of cities as much<br />
as the governments of all comparable countries have done for long<br />
past.* Why is health so expensive and why are our hospitals<br />
so inadequate? Because the previous government encouraged these<br />
fly-blown private bureacracies and high-flown pretensions of<br />
doctors. I suggest we did not even have a choice about whether<br />
or not we would act on these matters of schools and cities and<br />
hospitals. It was to act on these matters that the people elected<br />
us last December. And we were not prepared to sacrifice yet<br />
another generation of children and pensioners, the handicapped,<br />
the old, the sick, the aboricines and the city dwellers of this<br />
country. We have begun to do the job for which the people of<br />
Australia elected us. We shall before Christmas be asking you to<br />
give us another weapon so that we can continue to do that job.<br />
The times are not so urgent but we are no less sincere when we<br />
again say " Give us the tools and we will finish the job". </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
