<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>16857</transcript-id>
    <title>Transcript of Joint Press Conference Prime Minister, Anthony Albanese, Premier Mike Rann and Patrick Conlan Adelaide</title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/10/2009</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p><strong>PM: </strong>Great to be back in Adelaide and talking about this city and this State's need for infrastructure and our partnership between the Australian Government and the South Australian Government on building South Australian infrastructure.</p>
<p>Two reasons. One is, this is a platform for long-term economic growth. Secondly, it creates jobs in the here and now. That's what we're on about as an Australian Government, that's what the South Australian Government's on about as well.</p>
<p>Where the rubber literally hits the road today is of course, in this great project here, this South Road Superway which we're unveiling today. This is a big investment - a big investment - half a billion dollars from the Australian Government, some $400 million from the State Government and the economic benefit in terms of long-term transport infrastructure within Adelaide and the South Australian economy is large.</p>
<p>This investment will assist, of course, also in improving safety for up to 45,000 vehicles that use this section of the road each day. It's also about the efficiency of the Port, it's also about the separation of freight traffic from other forms of road traffic, it's also about how you therefore boost productivity growth for the long term.</p>
<p>Two big drivers of productivity growth of the Australian economy in the long term, one is infrastructure, road infrastructure, rail, port infrastructure, as well as our investments in high-speed broadband. And secondly, the investment in skills. This Government, this Australian Government, is active in both nation-wide, the education revolution and the infrastructure revolution, and on both these fronts we are proud to be partners with the South Australian Government in a close, cooperative partnership of building this State's future.</p>
<p>The last thing I'd say is about the immediate impact on jobs. This project is expected to support some 2,750 jobs. That is really important. We are not out of this global economic crisis. If you look at the international economic data, it is still patchy, very patchy. Therefore, the importance of building the infrastructure for tomorrow while supporting the jobs for today, is so much about what this Australian Government and the South Australian Government is on about.</p>
<p>We're proud to be supporting this project. We're proud to be investing half a billion dollars worth of Australian Government finance into this project and also to support this 2,750 jobs that will come off the construction and furthermore, to support also this critical piece of South Australia's long-term infrastructure needs. Mike.</p>
<p><strong>PREMIER RANN:</strong> Thank you very much, Prime Minister. Well, we're just delighted to be here, once again celebrating a partnership for South Australia's future. Just think about what's happened over the past 18 months. We've had a commitment from the Prime Minister to work with us to build a desalination plant, now under construction, that guarantees Adelaide's water security for the future, guarantees up to 50 per cent of Adelaide's water supply.</p>
<p>We had the announcement of the stimulus package money which was again, a joint investment in public transport, in the electrification of our north-south train system, and also an extension by the Commonwealth to take it further south to Seaford. The commitment to (inaudible) the work that we're jointly doing down at Techport on Defence. We're putting in $400 million, and what the Prime Minister has done is guaranteed that the next submarine project, worth over $30 billion, will be built in Adelaide.</p>
<p>So this is really about rolling out the biggest infrastructure partnership since Federation. And in South Australia, you know, even before this announcement was made, six times more investment on infrastructure than seven years ago, and in transport, about a seven times - not six percent a year, just exceeding inflation. This is a 600 per cent increase infrastructure spend in this State.</p>
<p>And what we're doing today, you've seen the Northern Expressway, you've seen the Port Adelaide Expressway, this about linking it up because it's all about removing road blocks. It's about making sure that traffic flows quicker. It's about underpinning what we're doing at the Port in Defence, but also, of course, about the mining boom. It's about making sure that we free up traffic, invest in infrastructure for the future, but create, of course, in this one, 2,750 jobs.</p>
<p>Prime Minister, and also Minister Albanese, Patrick Conlon, there could not be a better working relationship that we have together on infrastructure, and this another celebration of that.</p>
<p><strong>PM:</strong> Do our transport ministers wish to add? No corrections necessary? (inaudible) OK, over to you, folks.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST: </strong>Yes, Premier, just a quick question - can we afford this?</p>
<p><strong>PREMIER RANN:</strong> Absolutely. It's $500 million from the Commonwealth. This is already factored into our forward estimates. It's already been through the Budget processes. It's in the Budget for, under our Auslink future strategy, so what we're doing is rolling out infrastructure for the future, creating jobs now, linking it up and keeping our AAA credit rating. So, we can afford it. It was in the Budget.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST:</strong> (inaudible)</p>
<p><strong>PREMIER RANN:</strong> This was in the Budget, in our last Budget. It was already announced in the last Budget about forward expenditure on road infrastructure and so what we said was that even though we were rolling out the biggest infrastructure project in the State's history, projects, that there were some things that we couldn't do, and part of that was the prison complex.</p>
<p><strong>PM:</strong> I might ask Minister Albanese to add.</p>
<p><strong>MINISTER ALBANESE:</strong> I think the real question with infrastructure is, can we afford not to do it? It's important to recognise that this is an investment, not just an expenditure. It's an investment that will lead to future productivity growth, particularly because this is connected with the Port, because South Australia have developed a coherent transport plan that involves road, rail and port infrastructure.</p>
<p>That's why the Commonwealth has budgeted for, as part of the nation-building program, some $2.5 billion contribution from the Commonwealth to the Government of South Australia in partnership, to invest in infrastructure that will lead to better economic growth in the future.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST</strong>: (inaudible)</p>
<p><strong>MINISTER CONLON:</strong> You have to understand what the process has been. We started out on our own, looking at intersection by intersection, cutting our cloth according to what we could afford.</p>
<p>The big change came when the election of the Federal Government, the commitment of a major funding partner. The first thing that we did with that, and the Commonwealth commitment $70 million to a planning study, because when you can do it in a big way, rather than in a small way, you can take a different approach.</p>
<p>Now, in that planning study one of the things that we found, and of course we saw very good growth in the economy and very good growth forecasts in the South Australian economy, one of the things we found was that this section of road was going to see something like a tripling of freight movement over the next 20 years and it's all about wealth creation.</p>
<p>I mean, we're an exporting State. When you move freight, you make money. You move it more efficiently, you make money, so the study identified that. There is money remaining that will be addressed towards Darlington in the next few years and we're looking for, we're now studying the solutions that we'll use in the very difficult residential area of South Road, but this is the biggest commitment to that north-south corridor there's ever been in this State.</p>
<p>And, you know, people say 'can we afford $800 million?' What we're talking about is the biggest movers of freight in the State up there in the North. Now, you move that freight, you make money. The more freight we move, the more efficiently we move it, the more money this State makes, and you know, as Minister Albanese said, we can't afford not to do it.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST:</strong> (inaudible)</p>
<p><strong>MINISTER CONLON:</strong> Well, I think we've been talking about planning this for some time, but you've got to understand that planning road works isn't the sexiest thing in the world, so when you talk about it people don't necessarily listen, and big projects are sexy, but -</p>
<p><strong>MINISTER ALBANESE:</strong> I disagree with that.</p>
<p><strong>MINISTER CONLON: </strong>I've often fallen victim to (inaudible) myself. But we've been talking about planning the whole north-south corridor, we've announced the $70 million from the Commonwealth, and if you look at - sorry, I'll take this back a step. One of the things we've managed to do with the Commonwealth is we've committed ourselves to saying 'look, we're not going to bring you a project that doesn't have a really good cost-benefit analysis.'</p>
<p>That was our approach in Infrastructure Australia, it's our approach here. When you've got $70 million for study you can do very, very good work, and the cost-benefit analysis on these projects is very good.</p>
<p>You've got to remember, this connects up with the Northern Expressway which is under construction, going very well at present, Port River Expressway, the two new bridges over the Port to the Port that we deepened to panamax, to place panamax-sized vessels, so this make absolute sense when you look at a cost-benefit analysis of it.</p>
<p>Now, we have been talking about it. I'm just not sure that everyone gets terribly excited about freight roads.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST</strong>: Is this part of your Infrastructure Australia (inaudible)?</p>
<p><strong>MINISTER CONLON:</strong> No, this is not Infrastructure Australia money. There is, the Federal Minister can tell you, the child of Auslink. There used to be the Auslink program for funding roads. This comes from that type of commitment, although I don't know what it's called these days. I should do.</p>
<p><strong>MINISTER ALBANESE</strong>: This funding from the Commonwealth comes from the Nation Building program. The total expenditure on that is $36 billion. We have a memorandum of understanding with the South Australian Government of some $2.5 billion. And what that is, that goes out to 2013/14.</p>
<p>So what we've been able to do through Infrastructure Australia, have certainly assisted in the analysis of these projects. Jim Hallion of course, the Director-General is a member of the Infrastructure Australia advisory council. South Australia has been particularly good at having plans that lead to integrated transport as part of an integrated infrastructure strategy for Adelaide and for the state of South Australia, which is why the partnership has worked so well.</p>
<p>So it all fits together in terms of the Northern Expressway, and the investment that's going there. I was with the Premier, opening a bridge about a month ago. And we're continually- that's actually running ahead of schedule.</p>
<p>So it's all there over a period of time. The Commonwealth was able to bring forward, in our first budget, the first Rudd Budget, brought forward some expenditure in terms of our commitments to South Australia. That's what enabled us to, for example, put in place the $70 million for planning for this project, came from the Commonwealth. And then it's $430 million each from the Commonwealth and the State.</p>
<p>But it's getting that planning right which - I disagree with Patrick - I think it's very sexy, the planning for roads such as this. But it's getting that right as a precondition for making sure that every cent of taxpayer's dollars is a dollar well spent.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST: </strong>Prime Minister - on another topic- what's your response to the very personal and very emotional plea from these Tamils aboard that boat in Indonesian waters at the moment? They're pleading with you to let them (inaudible)</p>
<p><strong>PM: </strong>Firstly, I've not seen the immediate reports of that. Secondly, can I say what I have said all week - this Government makes no apology for a hard line approach to people smuggling and border security.</p>
<p>Secondly, what we have said consistently is that in processing any individual, if we have found- if we find that a person is not a legitimate asylum seeker, we send them home. We have already done that in the case of some people that have been sent back to Sri Lanka already. We will continue to do that in the future.</p>
<p>The other point, I would say is this. This challenge, arising from Sri Lanka and the civil war which unfolded in Sri Lanka over the last 12 months - which has been violent and bloody - is causing an outflow of people from Sri Lanka right across the world. Talk to the Europeans about this, you talk to South East Asians about this, you talk to other folk about this. This is a problem for everybody. Therefore, that's why we're dealing so closely with our friends in Indonesia on these challenges. And we will continue to do so without apology.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST:</strong> Are you planning an official deal with Indonesia to stop the flow of boats coming to Australia?</p>
<p><strong>PM:</strong> You know I speak with the Indonesian President a lot, President Yudhoyono. And I have, since I've become Prime Minister of Australia, regularly spoken to him in the flesh, on the telephone, about the challenges of terrorism, the challenges of regional security, and the challenges of people smuggling. We have a very close, collaborative relationship with our friends in Indonesia. And I thank them for their cooperation, and we will continue to work closely with them in the future.</p>
<p>It's a challenge for them. It's a challenge for Malaysia. It's a challenge for Australia. It's a challenge for our entire region. What is good is, the fact that our Governments and our security forces, our Police officers, our armed forces, our intelligence officers are working so closely together. It's a challenge for everybody. We believe, unapologetically, in a tough, hardline approach to border security. But we'll always treat people fairly.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST:</strong> Is sending the demountable homes from Alice Springs (inaudible)</p>
<p><strong>PM: </strong>Well first of all, on the detail of that, I can't comment. I've not seen that report. Secondly, we have always said that our approach to people smuggling, to illegal immigration, to asylum seekers, will be tough, hardline, but humane. Therefore, if you look at the facilities which are available on Christmas Island, we make no apology whatsoever for mandatory detention. We said we would maintain that, prior to the last election, and we have done so.</p>
<p>That's why we undertake our processing on Christmas Island as well. And the Immigration Minister for some time, has been quite plain about the fact that he would adjust the capacity of Christmas Island depending on future needs. And again putting all that into context, let's remember, we've had boats arriving in this country ever year for the last 20 years. That's the point.</p>
<p>Secondly, in the period of the Howard Government, to repeat what I said yesterday when I was at Murray Bridge. In the period of the Howard Government, some nearly 250 boats arrived, with nearly 15,000 people. And some 90 per cent of those put on Temporary Protection Visas ended up staying in Australia. In the period that I've been Prime Minister, we've had 30 odd boats arrive so far, with about 1700 people.</p>
<p>It's a challenge for the previous Government. It's a challenge for this Government. Our approach and policy is absolutely clear-cut. Hardline approach, but humane approach, to dealing with the challenge of asylum seekers. What is the Liberal's policy? They don't have one. Very easy to criticise and carp from the side. And the reason they criticise and carp from the side is that they are split right down the middle. Ask them today, what's their policy? They have no answer.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST:</strong> Prime Minister, there are reports of another six boats on their way to Australia. What are you going to do about those, and can you confirm those reports?</p>
<p><strong>PM: </strong>Well look, on the question of movements in and around the archipelago, and in and around South East Asia at any given time, that will vary. And we are not in the business of providing you know, spot reports on what the intelligence may say on one day or another.</p>
<p>This has been a challenge each day, every day, 365 days a year. And in the whole period that I've been in office, and I presume for my predecessors as well, as reflected in those previous numbers. Secondly, we will continue to deploy a hardline policy on people smugglers. Remember also, our efforts on people smugglers have already resulted in 44 prosecutions. Our actions in Indonesia have already resulted in 51, sorry, 81 interruptions or disruptions. We'll continue to work in that direction.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST:</strong> Prime Minister Gordon Brown has committed 500 more troops to (inaudible)</p>
<p><strong>PM:</strong> First of all, I have not had a discussion with Prime Minister Brown on that. Secondly, nor have I been briefed by the CDF in terms of the particular characteristics of the British deployment. Thirdly, what I'd say to you is that the Australian deployment was increased by 40 per cent, only some months ago, not long following the election of President Obama.</p>
<p>Our mission in Oruzgan Province is clear-cut. That is, our mission statement is to train the Afghan National Army and Afghan security forces to take control of the security of that province. We're in the business of raising an Afghan National Army brigade. We are training Afghan Police. And we are also engaged in capacity building with the Oruzgan Provincial Authority. Once that mission is completed, and we hand over our responsibility to that Provincial Authority, then of course Australia's mission will be concluded and our troops would come home. But as I say, our increase occurred some time ago.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST:</strong> Do you feel pressured or obliged at all by that move by the British Prime Minister?</p>
<p><strong>PM:</strong> None whatsoever. As I said, we made our position quite clear some months ago, in terms of the appropriate force for Australia, in order to achieve the mission which I have defined for Australia. If I could simply say this, the mission statement in the past for Afghanistan for Australia was somewhat unclear. I have defined in absolute clarity what we are seeking to do in Afghanistan.</p>
<p>The three functions I referred to before. That's where our effort is directed. That's the mission we are seeking to conclude in Oruzgan Province. I could say also, that this is a difficult and bloody operating environment. I have spoken to our troops on the ground there on several occasions, and I continue to be fearful for their safety and their security in the future. This is a very dangerous place to be.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST:</strong> Prime Minister, can I get you to clarify in relation to our current stances to people smugglers and the flow of boats coming to Australia. Are you satisfied with our current level of strategy or do you think we need something more official with Indonesia? (inaudible)</p>
<p><strong>PM: </strong>Can I just say, in terms of our cooperative relationships with Indonesia - and they go back in part to arrangements which were put in place by the previous Government, I see no point about trying to gild the lily in any negative way on that, but we have built on those significantly - these arrangements are working really well. And I would commend our friends and partners in Indonesia for the solid work they have done.</p>
<p>Secondly, we will continue as two Governments to work closely into the future, as the challenges of the future unfold. This is, if you were to roll back the clock several years, and ask where the push factors were coming from around the world, they weren't coming from Sri Lanka. They were coming from political instability in Iraq and Afghanistan at that stage had actually stabilised.</p>
<p>Since then we have had, in 2008 we've had, according to a report of the UN Secretary-General, one of the most violent years in Afghanistan that there's been since 2001. So Afghanistan is now a push factor. We've had a civil war in Sri Lanka. That's now a push factor. It affects all countries.</p>
<p>So therefore, frankly, the challenges are constantly changing. The pattern of operations by people smugglers are constantly changing. And therefore the tactics that we'll deploy with our friends and partners across the region will be calibrated accordingly. But the strategic-level cooperation between ourselves, the Indonesians and Malaysians is working well, and I commend those Governments for their cooperative efforts with us.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
