<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11320</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER          THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP          ADDRESS AT THE CENTENARY OF BOER WAR          CELEBRATIONS, PARLIAMENT HOUSE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/10/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE..................</p>
<p>  Well thank you very much Rear Admiral Griffiths, to Bruce Scott, the Minister</p>
<p>   for Veterans' Affairs, to Senator Schacht, the Shadow Minister for Veterans'</p>
<p>   Affairs, my other Parliamentary colleagues, ladies and gentlemen. This is</p>
<p>   another event which commemorates the long and rich military tradition and</p>
<p>   history of our country. It was in fact in the Boer War of 1899 to 1902 that</p>
<p>   for the first time Australians fought in the uniform of the forces of the</p>
<p>   Commonwealth of Australia. Because as you know they went, the first contingent</p>
<p>   as the contingent of the colonies as they then were, and returned in 1902</p>
<p>   to the federated Commonwealth of Australia. So today is a very special commemoration</p>
<p>   in that context.</p>
<p>  The Boer war was also the first military operation in which the nurses,</p>
<p>   the service nurses of Australia to whom an impressive memorial was dedicated</p>
<p>   here in Canberra only a week ago, were to serve with such distinction. And</p>
<p>   the nurses of Australia in the subsequent conflicts in which Australian</p>
<p>   forces were involved, played a magnificent part in helping and caring for,</p>
<p>   and nurturing, and sharing the risks of danger and death of our forces.</p>
<p>  16,000 young Australians served in the Boer War. It was a war that was to</p>
<p>   cost the lives of 600 of our countrymen, and remains on my understanding</p>
<p>   the third most costly military involvement in terms of loss of life of any</p>
<p>   operation in which Australian forces have been involved.</p>
<p>  This special commemoration, this colourful commemoration brings together</p>
<p>   the largest assembly of light horsemen in Australia since the 1940s. Certainly</p>
<p>   the largest gathering ever seen in Canberra. And I am, I know every Australian</p>
<p>   here is greatly indebted to those people who have come from the United Kingdom,</p>
<p>   from South Africa, from Canada, and from New Zealand to share this very</p>
<p>   special celebration. May I say to you Bruce that your Cabinet colleagues</p>
<p>   are very impressed at your own contribution. As of course fits the Federal</p>
<p>   Member for a great rural area such as Maranoa where a capacity to do what</p>
<p>   you have done is an absolute necessity, but I congratulate you nonetheless</p>
<p>   for it.</p>
<p>  But most importantly today we are here to commemorate an early sacrifice</p>
<p>   in the early days and early months of the Australian nation. A sacrifice</p>
<p>   of men and women who came and responded to a call to arms, to pursue what</p>
<p>   was properly seen then as being in the Australian national interest. Their</p>
<p>   deeds belong along side the deeds of others who fought for Australian and</p>
<p>   in Australia's interests in so many conflicts, and most particularly in</p>
<p>   World War I and World War II. And of course it is impossible for any Australian</p>
<p>   to attend any commemoration of this kind without thinking immediately of</p>
<p>   those young men and women of Australia who are in East Timor at present</p>
<p>   doing their duty by this country, and doing their duty by the things that</p>
<p>   we believe in, the values we hold and the values that we share in common</p>
<p>   with so many other freedom loving nations around the world.</p>
<p>  The bush tradition of Australia of course led to the formation of the Light</p>
<p>   Horse, and its contribution in the Boer War, and subsequently its contribution</p>
<p>   particularly in the Middle East in World War, belongs to the legend and</p>
<p>   the folklore and the great achievements and the great history of the Australian</p>
<p>   armed forces. In recent times there has been a regeneration of interest</p>
<p>   in the role and the contribution of the Light Horse to the Australian military</p>
<p>   tradition. And so it ought to be because it belongs very much to the heart</p>
<p>   and soul of the Australian bush which is so very much part and parcel of</p>
<p>   the kind of Australian nation in which all of us believe, and the kind of</p>
<p>   Australian nation that we have come to love.</p>
<p>  As we approach the centenary of the federation of Australia there is I am</p>
<p>   sure right across our nation a growing interest in, and an affection for</p>
<p>   and a desire to learn more about the great historical events that shaped</p>
<p>   our country which surrounded the formation of the Commonwealth of Australia.</p>
<p>   The readiness of Australians to go overseas in defence of an ideal, in defence</p>
<p>   of the Australian national interest has always been there. The willingness</p>
<p>   of Australians to involve themselves in a war between Great Britain and</p>
<p>   the Boer Republics of South Africa was an early indication of the desire</p>
<p>   of Australians to see themselves as playing a role not just in Australia</p>
<p>   but around the world and was of course part and parcel of a strong imperial</p>
<p>   sentiment that existed at that time all around Australia. We remember the</p>
<p>   contribution of those men. We honour their sense of service, their sense</p>
<p>   of sacrifice, and their willingness to respond to a call to arms and a call</p>
<p>   to duty.</p>
<p>  Importantly today we welcome the fact that the country in which they fought</p>
<p>   so long ago is now a more open democratic society, embracing the principles</p>
<p>   of freedom and equality and decent treatment of its citizens irrespective</p>
<p>   of their race or their colour or their creed. And indeed the leadership</p>
<p>   shown by men like Nelson Mandela in the modern South Africa is an inspiration</p>
<p>   to people all around the world who love and care about freedom and the dignity</p>
<p>   of men and women.</p>
<p>  Can I congratulate those who have been responsible for organising this commemorative</p>
<p>   event. Can I thank particularly those who've come from all around Australia,</p>
<p>   all ages, all parts of our country, and from around the world, to play a</p>
<p>   part in a very special celebration which honours the contribution of men</p>
<p>   and women so long ago. A century ago today commemorates the outbreak of</p>
<p>   the Boer War. Can I thank all of them for making a contribution because</p>
<p>   it reminds all of us as Australians of our rich history, our varied history</p>
<p>   and the willingness so long ago and in so many circumstances over the century</p>
<p>   that has gone by since of Australians to respond to the call to do their</p>
<p>   duty and to fight for what they saw and continue to see as the national</p>
<p>   interest of our country. Thank you.</p>
<p>  [ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
