<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5135</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/09/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005135.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
J\, AUSTR A IA w<br />
F17 MEDIA 2 SEPTEMBER 1979<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
We are all concerned about unemployment. We are concerned<br />
about men and women, particularly young men and women, who<br />
can't find jobs.<br />
Unemployment is not just a list of monthly figures from the<br />
Bureau of Statistics. It is a very real and personal problem.<br />
As the national Government, we have a clear obligation to do<br />
what we can to overcome that problem. How should we tackle<br />
it? What is the best course?<br />
In constant examination of unemployment, without exception<br />
and without equivocation, the Government comes back time<br />
an'" again to the only real solution, and that is the only<br />
way to create new and permanent and satisfying jobs: the<br />
p r cmo~ ion of sound economic growth.<br />
It is in business and manufacturing and in farming that the<br />
wealth of our country is at work. It is here, and only here,<br />
that lasting and produl-tive new jobs are created.<br />
Over the last year private employment has started to grow<br />
again. In the twelve months to May, civilian employment<br />
has increased by more than 60,000, private employment increased.<br />
by more than 50,000. In addition to sound economic growth<br />
we recognise that there are many people in the Australian<br />
community who need special help in their search for jobs.<br />
By the end of this financial year, more than half a million<br />
Australians, many of them young men and women, will have been<br />
assist'-ed into rewarding jobs through our various tra-ining<br />
programmes. These program-Les are under constant examination<br />
so they can be improved where necessary to help those most<br />
in need of them.<br />
The Labor Party professes concern for the unemployed. Perhaps<br />
they are concerned, but the brutal reality is that in the long<br />
run their alternate policies would do more to add to unemployment<br />
than to reduce it.<br />
Let's look at how false and shallow Labor's. policy really is.<br />
Labor has put forward a scheme to employ 50,000 peopl~ e. They<br />
claim it would cost between $ 85 and $ 100 million a year. / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
For some that may seem an attractive idea on the surface.<br />
The reality is that the cost of employing one person, and<br />
that includes wages, workers compensation, material and<br />
equipment, higher costs, transport and accommodation as<br />
well as expenses associated with the supervision and<br />
administration of the scheme would be just over $ 12,000<br />
a year. That is $ 240 a week subsidy by the taxpayers of<br />
Australia for each person under Labor's make-work scheme.<br />
Acco'rdingly, the total cost of employing Labor's 50,000<br />
people would be nearer $ 600 million a year. That is your<br />
tax, put into the kind of make-work scheme abandoned by<br />
the Leader of the opposition when he was Treasurer in the<br />
Labor Government of 1975, yet he would do it all again.<br />
He would ask tChe taxpayer for a massive subsidy to p--op<br />
up a form of his abandoned, artificial scheme to emp-oy<br />
Australians. So that is $ 600 million a year to crea :. e<br />
50,000 Government jobs.<br />
In addition to that, the Labor Party has said that would<br />
subsidise all net additions to employment by giving employers<br />
the equivalent of unemployment benefits for any net dditions<br />
to the workforce. That would be a very expensive policy<br />
indeed. The only way such a scheme could be worked would<br />
be on a company or a firm basis. Even while employrru., nt is<br />
relatively static, there are many firms which are doing better<br />
and expanding their workforces, because those firms are doing<br />
better, because they are selling more. This particular<br />
scheme would involve an additional Government hand-out of<br />
several hundreds of millions of dollars, and much of it would<br />
be subsidising employment, additional employment, that would<br />
take place anyway, merely because particular firms are doing<br />
better. Some would make the point " Well, at least it is reducing<br />
unemployment and finding work for those who want it". But<br />
my answer is plain, and I think it is a fair one..<br />
I talked a little earlier about creating the right conditions<br />
for economic growth. That is not just creating conditions<br />
for profits and expansion. It creates conditions for real<br />
and lasting jobs. Let me illustrate the point.<br />
Over the next few years in Western Australia, because of<br />
investment in the oil and aluminium industry, some 35,000 new<br />
jobs will be generated. They will be lasting jobs, they.<br />
will be secure and rewarding. At the same time in New South<br />
Wales and Victoria, because of expansion in the aluminium<br />
industry alone, some 20,000 new jobs will be created, That<br />
is. a total of 55,000 new permanent, productive and secure<br />
jobs in private industry. They won't be a burden on the<br />
taxpayer. They'll come out of industry that has the confidence<br />
to expand and develop because it knows that the Government<br />
is committed to responsible economic management. Surely there<br />
could be no starker contrast than that approach and Labor's<br />
hand-out mentality. / 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
of course it is not just in oil and aluminium that new jobs<br />
are being created. it is happening in industry aiter industry.<br />
M4r Hayden's economic policies would retrun Australia to the<br />
big deficit, galloping inflation days of Mr Whitlam. The extra<br />
money Mr Hayden wants to spend on unemployment programmes,<br />
make-work government jobs and other spending programmaes, would<br />
so expand the deficit that many people would cease to have<br />
confidence in the strength of the Australian economy. Under<br />
those circumstances we would not get a growth in jobs in the<br />
private sect%-or. Indeed, private sector jobs could well'fall<br />
as tL. hey did when Labor was in office once before. who will<br />
ever forget that in one year of Labor, unemployment rose by<br />
almost 200,000.<br />
Labor policies totally ignore inflation. Mr Hayden -Thould<br />
ask industry what they think of a policy that ignoreI ~ in<br />
He should think back to a time when inflation almost wrecked<br />
Australian industry, as it struggled to survive and omp%= te for<br />
markets here and abroad when Labor's policies pushed inflation<br />
much above the inflation figures of many other developed<br />
countries in North America and in Europe.<br />
Now, even if there are some additional inflationary pressures<br />
within Australia, our inflation is much below that of many<br />
countries in Europe. In Britain it is about 15 or 16 per cent,<br />
and in America it is now about 14 per cent on an annual basis.<br />
At around nine per cent ours is much lower. We intend to keep<br />
it that way, so Australian firms and industries can become<br />
more codipetive, sell more and get more jobs.<br />
Put bluntly, the Labor Party refuses to come to grips with<br />
* the simple fact that jobs come from industry that is confident<br />
and expanding. That will only happen if industry is competitive<br />
and is given incentive to invest and take risks. That is what<br />
my Government has aimed at over the last three and a half years.<br />
We don't think profit is a dirty word. It is from profits that<br />
expansion takes place, and with expansion new jobs are created.<br />
Our incentives to promote exports and development, and above<br />
all our determination to keep up the fight against inflation,<br />
will do more to provide jobs for Australians , who want to work. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
