<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3248</transcript-id>
    <title>ABORIGINAL LAND RIGHTS COMMISSION - SECOND REPORT</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/05/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003248.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER PRESS STATEMENT<br />
7 May 1974<br />
Aboriginal Land Rights Commission Second Report<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr Whitlam, announced today that<br />
the Government had accepted in principle the recommendations<br />
contained in the Second Report of the Aboriginal Land Rights<br />
Commission. The Report had been received by the Government following<br />
its presentation to the Governor-General last Friday, 3 May, and<br />
was now being released in accordance with the undertaking given by<br />
the Prime Minister in his Policy Speech.<br />
Following its re-election, the Government will arrange<br />
discussions with Aboriginal Councils and communities in the Northern<br />
Territory, with a view to early legislation.<br />
Mr Whitlam paid tribute to the Commissioner, Mr Justice<br />
A. E. Woodward, for the way in which he had conducted the Inquiry.<br />
The Commissioner had enabled Aborigines to participate with an<br />
effectiveness wholly new in Australian history. At the same time<br />
widely ranging evidence was received on the issues affecting his<br />
terms of reference. Mr Whitlam said that the Government strongly endorsed the<br />
Judge's view that " tan imposed solution to the problem of recognising<br />
traditional Aboriginal land rights is unlikely to be a good or<br />
lasting solution", and would adopt the suggestion that the proposals<br />
be taken as a basis for negotiation between the Aboriginal Representative<br />
Councils and communities and the Government,<br />
Mr Whitlam said the Government believed that the Report<br />
provided a well balanced consideration of the claims and needs of<br />
Aboriginal Australians in the Northern Territory while ensuring<br />
respect for rights granted under previous Governments. Its<br />
recommendations offer a-framework under which the legitimate claims<br />
of Aborigines can be met'-and their deep affiliation with the<br />
land acknowledged. It would therefore provide a basis for the<br />
development of the Northern Territory which Australians can in<br />
good conscience accept and defend,<br />
The Government welcomed especially the Report's<br />
recommendations relating to mining. They clearly justify the<br />
Government's concern to enable Aborigines to protect their way<br />
of life from the destructive effect of mining development.<br />
In particular it endorses the Government's decision on<br />
Queensland Mines proposals to mine uranium at N~ aalk<br />
The Prime Minister said that the electorate was entitled to<br />
know what attitude the Opposition would take to the recommendations<br />
of the Report. He had made arrangements for copies of the Report<br />
to be passed to Leaders of the Opposition Parties in the Parliament,<br />
tb the Premiers and to Corporations referred to in the recommendations. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
