<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>22746</transcript-id>
    <title>Historic agreement reached with independent schools</title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130627 - 20130907</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/07/2013</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Prime Minister, Minister for Education</p>
<p>Today the Australian Government and Independent Schools Council of Australia (ISCA) reached an historic agreement that will deliver real benefits to 562,000 students in independent schools across Australia.</p>
<p>The agreement will see more than $1 billion additional funding flow to Australian independent schools over the next six years – if every state and territory signs up.</p>
<p>The Better Schools Plan is a plan to give every student in every Australian school the opportunity to reach their full potential and compete with the rest of the world.</p>
<p>The Australian Government respects every parent’s right to choose where they send their kids to school.</p>
<p>Over a long period of time, the Australian Government has supported the growth of the Independent school sector and values the role it plays in educating young Australians.</p>
<p>Today’s historic agreement will ensure every Australian kid, irrespective of where they live, which school they attend or their family background, will get the best start in life.</p>
<p>This is not just an investment in schools, this is a down payment on the long-term strength of the Australian economy, and will underwrite higher productivity for decades to come.</p>
<p>The Australian Government has set an ambitious target for Australia to be in the top five in the world in reading, maths and science by 2025 and this can only be achieved by working together with our independent schools.</p>
<p>The Better Schools Plan delivers reform in the areas we know drive better student outcomes including quality teaching, quality learning, empowered school leadership, more individual attention for students, and transparency and accountability.</p>
<p>The Australian Government and the Independent Schools Council of Australia have worked cooperatively, respectfully and intensively to ensure this is a good deal for independent schools.</p>
<p>As a result of the agreements reached with New South Wales, South Australia, the Australian Capital Territory and Tasmania, 45 per cent of independent schools will also see additional state government funding.</p>
<p>It is now time for Victoria, Queensland, Western Australia and the Northern Territory to join with other states, the ACT and the Independent sector in embracing the Better Schools Plan.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
