<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6649</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE, 18 JUNE 1985</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/06/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006649.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
JjAUSTALA fr<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
E. O. E. -PROOF ONLY<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE 18 JUNE 1985<br />
PM: Well good afternoon. Over to you.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, are you disappointed by the way in<br />
which the big business and industry groups have reacted to<br />
the idea of a voluntary code of conduct to Australian firms<br />
in South Africa?<br />
PM: I'm disappointed at the initial reaction. We will have<br />
fuirther discussions with them and I believe that out of those<br />
discussions we should be able to achieve a basis of operation<br />
that will be acceptable. But when you commence anything new<br />
like this there is always going to be some reaction. I am<br />
not surprised.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, you said a week or so ago that the tax<br />
package was open to negotiation and possible changes. Do these<br />
possible changes include the level of the consumption tax and<br />
the question of exemptions?<br />
PM: Well, when you have a summit and you'say you are going to<br />
invite the community through its representative organisations<br />
to raise issues in the White Paper, then you do that without<br />
reservation. I would simply say this taking your two<br />
points in order. As to the level of the proposed broad based<br />
consumption tax, it has appeared to us that it needs to be of<br />
that order in conjunction with the other elements of the package,<br />
if you are going to be able to give the significant cuts in<br />
direct personal tax which we believe are necessary to achieve<br />
more realistic levels of contribution from peoples' wages and<br />
salaries to tax. On the question of exemptions, all the<br />
evidence that we have been given from overseas which deals<br />
with o~ u own consideration of the issues suggests the<br />
inappropriateness of exemptions. It is not firstly, the most<br />
efficient way of dealing with the quite legitimate problem<br />
which is in the minds of people when they raise it. That is,<br />
if you talk about food in particular, it goes without saying,<br />
and was recognised from the beginning that of itself, tax on<br />
food is regressive. But if you eliminated food from the broad<br />
based consumption tax at the level which has ' been spoken of, it<br />
would cost you $ 1.6 billion. Now, that would mean that higher<br />
income groups in the community would escape contribution,<br />
including that significant proportion in that region who virtually<br />
pay no tax at all now. So it wouldn't be the most effective way<br />
/ 2 </p>
<p>of dealing with the problem of the impost of the tax on low<br />
income people. You address that problem, we believe, more<br />
effectively in the way that we have talked about that is<br />
the combination of the tax cuts and the provisions for more<br />
than compensation through the social security welfare system.<br />
And of course, there are the other category of problems that<br />
are involved as well. Once you start making exemptions, then<br />
that immediately imposes significantly greater difficulties<br />
for the tax collectors. That is at the level of the retail<br />
shops and so on you have got to have a more complicated system<br />
of cash registers and so on. And secondly, you start down the<br />
track inevitably that has plagued this country in the existing<br />
area of tax on goods in the wholesale tax area where you have a<br />
totally incongruous, inequitable, logically unjustifiable<br />
mish mash of exemptions and inclusions at different level of<br />
tax at the V7 the 20% and 32 And the next point follows.<br />
That once you start to allow one area of exemptions, then of<br />
course you get pressure groups saying, well, you have exempted<br />
that item. There is a very strong case for exempting this item.<br />
And governments then are down the slippery path which has resulted<br />
as I have described in the totally unrealistic existing system<br />
of tax upon goods in the wholesale tax regimen.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, there has already been widespread reaction<br />
to the Government's preferred position on taxation reform,<br />
notably from the business community and the ACTU. In the light<br />
of that, are you satisfied with the level of debate so far.<br />
And more particularly, are you still confident you are going to<br />
be able to sell this package' to the community?<br />
PM: Well thanks for that question. I think it is an embracing<br />
one and very relevant. Firstly, am I satisfied with the level<br />
of debate. Yes. I think that by and large it has been a<br />
sensible debate. Inevitably, as one would expect when you are<br />
talking about tax, there has been the expression of particular<br />
interest group points of view. Naturally, people tend to be<br />
somewhat selfish and self-centred when they are considering tax<br />
reform. I am neither surprised nor disappointed about that. it<br />
is precisely what we expected. But importantly, I believe that<br />
the debate has not damaged the essential structure of the package.<br />
There is nothing emerged which has been put up as an alternative<br />
which would meet all the objectives of the Government's<br />
preferred package. I am indebted to the way in which the media<br />
generally has faciliated the discussion. And T believe that in<br />
the period which still remains between now and the summit that<br />
you will have a situation that the community will therefore be<br />
well served at the summit by the discussion that will have taken<br />
place till that point. I believe there will be a clearer<br />
appreciation of the essential objectives of the Government's<br />
approach. I think there will be a clearer understanding of the<br />
way in which the compensatory mechanisms are calculated to<br />
deal with, and I believe more than deal withf-the problems that<br />
would otherwise be there. To the second part of your question,<br />
do you think we can sell it. Well, I hope so and I believe so<br />
because the one thing, if you like, that remains untouched in </p>
<p>any way at this stage, is the conviction, I believe, of the<br />
overwhelming majority of the community that the existing<br />
system is finished. It is unfair. It is inefficient. And<br />
it is totally complex. And increasingly it is operating in<br />
a way which is becoming more evident, I believe, to the<br />
Australian community whereby more and more of our fellow<br />
Australians in the high levels of income are avoiding virtually<br />
any payment of tax at all. And that must mean, I believe,<br />
that a decreasing number of Australians and that will mean<br />
the ordinary wage and salary earners will have a greater<br />
burden imposed upon them if no change is made. Now, I think<br />
that understanding is increasing. And I therefore am optimistic<br />
that in the period between now and the Summit, at the Summit,<br />
and the period after the Summit, we will be able to persuade<br />
the Australian people that the preferred approach suggested by<br />
the Government is the best way to go.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, given that exemptions are virtually<br />
out, is there any sympathy for making some change to Option C<br />
so that lower income earners will receive a greater net benefit<br />
than Mr Keating has outlined?<br />
PM: Well, this is one of the areas that is open to discussion.<br />
and you will note from your reading of the White Paper, the<br />
indications of a disposition on the part of the Government to<br />
consider further ways in which some small groups who may not be<br />
encompassed by the compensation packages may be able to be<br />
covered. And how some already covered, may be able to be better<br />
covered. We have not said that what is set out in the White<br />
Paper represents the last word in terms of compensation. And<br />
certainly I can say this on behalf of the Government. If out<br />
of the process of discussion between now and the Summit and at<br />
the Summit itself, there emerge viable effective, equitable ways<br />
of making the compensation packages more effective, then the<br />
Government will be very very well disposed towards embracing<br />
them. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke~ are you concerned at all about the<br />
inflationary pressures building up in the economy,<br />
particularly the projected revision for next financial<br />
year of the inflation rate of seven per cent, and in<br />
the light of this 1 given that there are pros and cons<br />
both ways on this, will the Government be tempted at all<br />
to consider some sort of reduction in the 12.5% rate<br />
mentioned in option C in order to minimise these inflationary<br />
dangers. PM: There are two points to make about that. Firstly,<br />
of course, we have from the very first day in Government<br />
indicated that the control of inflation has been one of<br />
the primary objectives of Government economic policy<br />
making. We have translated that concern into effective<br />
action, and we have, as you know, more than halved the<br />
inflation rate that we inherited. So yes we are always<br />
concerned about inflation because inflation is damaging<br />
in terms of your competitive economic position internationally,<br />
And it is disruptive in terms of equity in the community<br />
because those on the lowest levels of income, whether it<br />
be as wage and salary earners, or as beneficiaries through<br />
the social welfare system, always have most to fear from<br />
inflation. And to the extent therefore that there are<br />
signs of some upward movement inflation, yes we are<br />
concerned and our economic policy making will be directed<br />
towards containing those elements and pressures within our<br />
economy which could, if not properly regulated, add further<br />
to those pressures. Now coming to the second point. You<br />
asked whether as a result'of those signs of potential<br />
inflationary pressures, would there be an argument considered<br />
by the Government to think about a lesser level of a broad<br />
based consumption tax than the 12.5%. I believe not.<br />
Because what you must understand is that the level of<br />
the proposed broad based consumption tax has been reached<br />
in very large measure, in terms of trying to maximise the<br />
degree of relief that Government will be able to make<br />
available to wage and salary earners with regard to the<br />
direct tax that they pay. In other words if it were a<br />
lesser level of broad based consumption tax, say 10% or<br />
something less, then Government would have a lesser amount<br />
of revenue to make available for the purposes of reducing<br />
direct tax. -Now this, I believ'e is relevant to the question<br />
you asked because wage and salary earners are not simply<br />
going to leave themselves unprotected against an increasing<br />
erosion of their earned income by deprivations of tax.<br />
It is the case, as you know, that now that 46% rate impinges<br />
around the 19,000 level,, and in the absence of change it<br />
would be biting in before the end of this Parliament at<br />
about 17,000. Now if people are paying more of their earned<br />
income in tax, then I believe that in the absence of<br />
significant reform they would be attempting to protect<br />
their disposable, real disposable, income position by<br />
more pressures for increases in money wages. And so if<br />
you're going to get the full anal'ysis, and proper appreciation<br />
of the relationship between proposed tax changes and inflation<br />
it's no good simply saying a 12.5% broad based consumption<br />
tax has a 6.5% CPI effect. A one-off effect that would wash<br />
out within a year. If you're going to do the analysis </p>
<p>.3properly you have to say well, is it not likely that if<br />
you don't do something significant to reduce the direct<br />
tax rates will there not be wage pushes to try and maintain<br />
or improve the real disposible income position. So its<br />
our assessment, taking all those factors into account,<br />
* 1 that we believe, we've pitched the proposal at the right<br />
level.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister one of the arguments of the<br />
business community is tha . t you could fund a reduction<br />
in the rate of the broad based consumption tax, through<br />
further cuts in government spending, still get the same<br />
level of income tax cuts but reduce the CPI level.<br />
PM: I'm glad you raised that. Arnithere are a number of<br />
things that need to be said about this. Firstly, no<br />
Government has done more than this to impose effectively,<br />
constraints, restraints upon the levels of government<br />
expenditure through the life a Parliament. The trilogy<br />
is a self-imposed constraint. And by now in the life of this<br />
second Parliament, we have strongly evidenced our<br />
commitment to making the trilogy effective, and ensuring<br />
that the levels of Government expenditure will be constrained<br />
within the growth of the economy. Now, we are therefore<br />
able to base the business community, and the community as<br />
a whole, and say in regard to that area of concern, that<br />
is the levels, of Government expenditures, that independently<br />
of what we're doing about tax reform, we have addressed<br />
that issue and addressed it more effectively than any other<br />
Government in the history of this country. That's the first<br />
point to make. Secondly,, I would say this in regard to<br />
the question of the reduction of the levels of Government<br />
expenditure. We've made it quite clear from the outset<br />
of this tax reform debate, and the processes of achieving<br />
tax reform*, that it is not appropriate within those forums<br />
to muddy the waters of tax reform by talking about the levels<br />
of government expenditures. We are open in the processes<br />
leading up to the Budget, and at all times, to representations<br />
from the business community, or elsewhere, as to how we<br />
should be addressing that issue. As I've said, in my first<br />
point, we've done more about it than anyone else, but we're<br />
still open to any submission that the business community,<br />
or others, wartto make to us. -To be precise, in budgetary<br />
terms, we have indicated that we will, in preparing the<br />
Budget for 85/ 86, reduce the deficit further, and you know<br />
we're talking in the order of 6 billion dollars. And I<br />
believe that that's the sort of figure which the business<br />
community believes is appropriate at any rate. The final<br />
point that I would make is this. That in all the talk<br />
about what should be done about the level of Government<br />
expenditures, and having said as I have what we have done,<br />
and more effectively than has ever been done before, I still<br />
want to make this point. That you won't find a very<br />
big file on the Treasurer's desk, or on mine, of detailed<br />
b submissions from the business,-community or elsewhere, as<br />
to precisely how existing levels of expenditure should<br />
be cut beyond what we've done. I mean when you look at the </p>
<p>expenditure patterns of this Government, and indeed the<br />
Commonwealth Government generally, you will find that there<br />
are very large hunks taken up by areas which people really<br />
don't want to do anything about. Defence, payments to the<br />
States, social welfare, housing, education, you add all<br />
those up and you're talking about a very-large proportion<br />
of government revenues. Now if the business community<br />
wants to, for instance, talk about the areas of government<br />
expenditures which are of assistance to the business<br />
community, well they should be cut back. Well that is<br />
certainly virginal territory for them, its open to them.<br />
And in the other areas that I've talked about, Defence,<br />
social welfare, payments to the States. In the area of<br />
payments to the States we ' ye exercised more rigour<br />
effectively there than has been done before. So I repeat,<br />
finally, as a Government we are open to submissions and<br />
expositions about what shouldbtaone in the level of government<br />
expenditures.. But I believe that when you get past the rhetoric,<br />
and get down to the detail that there is not a great deal of<br />
room for massive cuts in that area. But I believe, finally,<br />
that the two areas should not be confused. Because at any<br />
level of government expenditures there are the most<br />
appropriate, most equitable, most simple ways of gathering<br />
the revenue which is necessary to finance those levels o;<br />
expenditure, and we should address ourselves to those issues. </p>
<p>7.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, the Treasurer, Mr Keating has made it clear<br />
over the last week or so that if the Consumption Tax proposal<br />
doesn't get up that* he doesn't see much point in sticking around<br />
in politics. I wonder whether you think this sort of attitude<br />
assists the passage of Option C at all? Did Mr Keating indicate<br />
to you earlier on this particular attitude he's got? And what's<br />
your view of the Treasurer making this sort of threat to the<br />
Cabinet before some final decision is taken?<br />
PM: I think these things have been like Mark Twain's death<br />
grossly exaggerated. The situation is this quite clearly. The<br />
Treasurer has a audable and I believe understandable enthusiasm<br />
for achieving significant tax reform. This is not some personal<br />
Keating mission. It is consistent with the approach that he and I<br />
have adopted since we've come to government, that if you're going<br />
to put Australia into the best possible position for the rest of<br />
this century to properly develop its resources to take advantage<br />
of its position in the most dynamic region of the world, then<br />
fundamental structural reforms have to be undertaken. Our record<br />
already in this area, in the economic area, is quite outstanding<br />
and I don't think I need to repeat it in detail, as you know<br />
what's been done in the area. Financial deregulation, the<br />
bringing in of foreign banks, reform in the area of foreign<br />
investment, the floating of the dollar, the relationships between<br />
the Commonwealth and the States truly historic achievements in a<br />
very short time. Now tax reform by any definition must assume a<br />
significant place in structural reform of the Australian economy.<br />
Paul is unswervingly committed to achieving significant tax<br />
reform, and in that he has my support. He is an enthusiastic<br />
operator as well as being a very effective operator. I don't<br />
think it does justice to him for it to be said now that he's the<br />
little boy with the cricket bat who'll take it home, if he can't<br />
get it his way. He is working extraordinarly hard, toughly to<br />
achieve what he believes, and I believe, is-necessary to get the<br />
best possible basis for Australia to go ahead to achieve the sorts<br />
of growth -* the realisation of our capacities that's within the<br />
potental of this country. He will do his hardest, work his<br />
hardest to achieve that result and I believe it will be<br />
successful. And I think it does him very considerably less than<br />
justice to say that if he doesn't to hypothesise to say well<br />
if he doesn't get exactly what he's been talking about then he'll<br />
go home. I don't believe he would.<br />
JOURNALIST: That's based on his own words Prime Minister I think<br />
the question is whether you approve of those tactics he is using?<br />
PM: Well, I'm simply saying I know Paul Keating better than<br />
iinyone in this room. And I have nothing to add to or qualify the<br />
previous answer that I ~ gave.' I don't have to make my judgements<br />
about Paul Keating upon what in certain circumstances he may have<br />
said or be believed to have said to certain people. I know him<br />
better than anyone in this room. My judgement is based upon that<br />
knowledge of him. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, are you concerned that the consumption tax<br />
will hit rural people, if we go outside the capital cities, harder<br />
than city people because of the higher prices there. And what<br />
can be done about this?<br />
PM: Well let me say two things about that. Firstly I think it's<br />
evident from the time since we've been in government that we have<br />
a very clear realisation of the importance of the rural community<br />
to the Australian economy as a whole. I can't repeat too often,<br />
because it's still to easily forgotten, in all the talk about our<br />
mineral exports and so on, that 40% of Australia's export income<br />
is derived from the rural sector and therefore, quite apart from<br />
anything else it would be economically nonsensical deliberately to<br />
pursue policies which would be against the interests of the rural<br />
community, in terms of their capacity to produce. So we've never<br />
been about that and we are not about it now. We don't believe<br />
that the overall tax package will be of the kind that will have<br />
that sort of impact, that it will work against the effectiveness<br />
of rural production. As I've said in direct discussions with the<br />
National Farmers' Federation, we want to do what we can to help<br />
them in ways which are relevant to their position. And don't<br />
believe that you can use the tax system as a whole, when you're<br />
looking at the tax system for the whole of the country that you<br />
can use that as a way of specifically differentiating in favour of<br />
the rural community. But I can say this, that as we go up to the<br />
Budget I'll be looking at other elements of the rural cost<br />
structure to see what sort of things may be able further to be<br />
done to improve the position of the rural community in that way.<br />
JOURNALIST: It has not only b ' een said that the Treasurer has<br />
threatened take his bat home.' It's also been said that he has<br />
threatened to hit people with it. In the Cabinet discussions on<br />
this matter, did he threaten to call a special caucus meeting to<br />
have a new ministry elected if he didn't ge. t his own way?<br />
PM: I think you ought to know by now Laurie, and I give you<br />
out of 10 for trying, but I don't talk about what goes on in<br />
Cabinet Meetings.<br />
JOURNALIST: Is that how you want to see your Government<br />
portrayed, Prime Minister?<br />
' PM: Well I can'-t really help how people's imagination runs riot<br />
aotwhat happens in the Cabinet meetings. I don't run that sort<br />
of government. I'm simply not myself going to add to speculations<br />
about what goes on in Cabinet meetings by myself saying what does<br />
or does not occur.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister ' Would you close down Australia's Trade<br />
Commission in South Africa before going campaigning for trade<br />
sanctions in international forums.<br />
PM: What we do about our office there is a matter which will be<br />
considered within the totality of our approach-on this issue. No<br />
decision has been made. We will continue to conduct discussions<br />
with other countries within the Commonwealth, CHOGM, and within<br />
the United Nations. What we do ourselves will be consistent with<br />
the approach that we adopt in those forums. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke is it correct that the Foreign<br />
Minister has told you that he is very worried about the<br />
macro-ecornmi; cproblems associated with the broadly<br />
based consumption tax, and you believe that you and<br />
the Treasurer can get final Cabinet endorsement for a<br />
broadly based consumption tax if Mr Hayden does not come<br />
onto the cart.<br />
PM: Well again, similar to the answer I gave to<br />
Laurie Oakes earlier, I'm not about detailing conversations<br />
that I have with Bill or with other Ministers. Having<br />
said that I think its fair enough to say this, without<br />
going into details, that in discussions that I've had<br />
with Bill, he's not taken any final position on this<br />
matter. He has raised prima facie questions, on economic<br />
grounds, and on political grounds. But the end of our<br />
discussion, which was a relatively brief discussion, he<br />
made the point that because of the fact that he'd been<br />
away, he hadn't had at that stage the opportunity of reading<br />
in detail the White Paper and the associated work that<br />
had been done around it. He was going to do that, and<br />
that when he'd done it he and I and Paul would sit down<br />
and have a very serious discussion about this. I certainly<br />
welcome it because from the very first day of Government<br />
Bill Hayden has been a very strong supporter of the basic<br />
economic thrusts that have been pursued by Paul and myself<br />
and that have been endorsed by the Cabinet. And having<br />
said that I, of course, am not going to the hypothetical<br />
question of what may or may not happen in the Cabinet<br />
following the Summit. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Prime Minister how concerned are you that<br />
the Labor Party isn't doing so well inthe polls at<br />
the moment, and how much of that is responsible<br />
is due to the uncertainty generated by the tax debate.<br />
PM Oh I don't know there'll be another poll tomorrow<br />
I guess. I don't know exactly what it will show. I would<br />
think that we're not in bad shape. I think there is<br />
emerging a very clear understanding of the steadfastness<br />
of this Government to pursue meaningful economic reform.<br />
The evidence of the success of the policies that we've<br />
been pursuing is more and more on the board. We now have<br />
the fact of 375,000 new jobs having been created. The<br />
evidence that's coming from industry of significantly higher<br />
levels of real investment, than was talked about at the time<br />
of the last budget. Confidence in the consumer area. So<br />
if you take the essentials of economic policy I think each<br />
passing week clearer evidence of the success of what we've<br />
done, and of the commitment of what we're about. Against<br />
that is the increasing uncertainty and chaos displayed by<br />
the Opposition. They are at odds within the Liberal Party,<br />
they're certainly at odds between the Liberal Party and the<br />
National Party. And I think that the confidence and the<br />
success and purposefulness of the Government will become<br />
increasingly evident, in contrast to those of us in the<br />
political community on the other side of the fence from the<br />
Government. Now, let me make the final point in regard to<br />
the last part of your question. Its inevitable that at<br />
this time overall political judgements about the Government<br />
will be mixed up with people's assessment, at this stage<br />
of the proposed tax reforms. And I think for some time<br />
it will not be possible to disintegrate assessments about<br />
tax reform from their overall political judgement. And in<br />
the sense that that is true, let me say this, because I'm<br />
confident that as the debate goes on there will'be an<br />
increasing realisation of the, as I say, the good intent,<br />
the integrity, and the purposefulness of what we're about<br />
in the tax area, that the general political judgements<br />
about the Government will correspondingly improve.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke will you take one last question<br />
on the consumption tax?<br />
PM: Well I will be in trouble with my highly paid<br />
press officers if they having said that was the last one<br />
I now transfer their responsibility to you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
