<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>22090</transcript-id>
    <title>2005 Christmas Message  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/12/2005</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Embargoed until 12:01am, 24 December 2005</p>
<p>2005 CHRISTMAS MESSAGE</p>
<p>  2005 has seen the good heart of Australia very much on display. Our generous, overwhelming response to the tragic tsunami, the great work of our Defence medical teams in Aceh and more recently the wonderful work of our Army medical teams in Kashmir, helping the victims of the Pakistani earthquake, have demonstrated that this is a generous, outward looking nation willing to share the good fortune that life has given us with those who are less fortunate.</p>
<p> 2005 has been a year of great achievement and progress for our country. But we should remember there are still many within our midst who haven't enjoyed life to the full. We must continue to do what we can to help them and at Christmas we think of the wonderful work of organisations, such as the Salvation Army, the Wesley Mission and the Society of St Vincent de Paul who reach out to give assistance to those in great need.</p>
<p> Christmas of course celebrates the birth of Jesus Christ, a man whose life and example has given us a value system which remains the greatest force for good in our community. Christmas is a time for families to get together, to see old friends, to think of the good times and the good fortune life has given us. And in properly celebrating Christmas and enjoying that good fortune we should spare a thought for the lonely in our community, without family and without friends, for whom Christmas can be a particularly hard time.</p>
<p> At Christmas I know many of you will think of the families of the men and women of the Australian Defence Forces who are serving the interests of our nation abroad, and who can't celebrate Christmas with their families like the rest of us.</p>
<p> Janette joins me in wishing all of you a peaceful and happy Christmas. Enjoy it and I look forward to a strong and prosperous New Year for all of us in 2006.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
