<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>16118</transcript-id>
    <title>Joint Media Release with  the Minister for Housing, Tanya Plibersek, Housing Affordability Fund Guidelines Released  </title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/09/2008</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>From today Local, State, and Territory Governments and private companies can apply for grants from the Rudd Government's Housing Affordability Fund to help reduce the cost of building new homes.</p>
<p>Housing Minister Tanya Plibersek joined Mr Rudd today at a new housing development in Franklin, where they released the application guidelines for the Government's new Housing Affordability Fund.</p>
<p>The Housing Affordability Fund is a Rudd Government initiative that invests $512 million over five years to target the planning and infrastructure costs that are incurred when building new housing developments.</p>
<p>Tens of thousands of new home buyers are set to directly benefit from the Fund, with savings coming from grants of up to $10 000 per home, reduced holding costs, and contributions from other levels of government.</p>
<p>Mr Rudd said the fund aimed to encourage the building of much-needed housing developments for Australians.</p>
<p>“We know that Australia is facing a significant housing shortage problem  -  that is why we are taking action,” Mr Rudd said.</p>
<p>“We need to keep up with the housing demands of a growing population and help to reduce the costs of owning a home.</p>
<p>“These grants will be targeted towards areas with high demand for new, entry-level housing.</p>
<p>“Applicants will have to be able to demonstrate that their cost savings are passed on to new home buyers.”</p>
<p>Ms Plibersek said the Fund was an important new initiative that would specifically focus on reducing the holding costs that our planning system imposes on developers.</p>
<p>“These are costs that are in turn built into the price that home buyers pay for their new home,” Ms Plibersek said.</p>
<p>“Governments at all levels owe it to home buyers to have planning processes that do not add unnecessary costs to housing development.</p>
<p>“The Fund will also address some of the other upfront costs faced by developers that are ultimately passed on to home buyers  -  like infrastructure charges for the installation of sewerage, roads, cycle-ways and parks.”</p>
<p>State, Territory and local governments and private companies are all eligible to apply for grants.</p>
<p>The Rudd Government also wants to improve the efficiency of the planning and development paper trail  -  to drag it into the 21st century by making it quicker, more accessible and more user-friendly.</p>
<p>That is why the Government has allocated $30 million from the Housing Affordability Fund to fast track the national roll-out of an electronic development assessment (eDA) system to make use of 21st century technology to replace a 19th century paper-based system.</p>
<p>The Housing Affordability Fund is a critical part of the Australian Government's housing strategy. The 2008-09 Budget included $2.2 billion in new housing affordability investments:</p>
<p>     * A $623 million National Rental Affordability Scheme to encourage the building of up to 50,000 new rental properties.</p>
<p>     * A $150 million Place to Call Home initiative to build hundreds of new homes for the homeless across Australia.</p>
<p>     * A $1.2 billion investment in First Home Saver Accounts to help first home buyers save for a deposit.</p>
<p>For further information on the Housing Affordability Fund and the application guidelines please visit:  <a href="http://www.fahcsia.gov.au/internet/facsinternet.nsf/housing/haf.htm">www.fahcsia.gov.au/internet/facsinternet.nsf/housing/haf.htm</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
