<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>20816</transcript-id>
    <title>2003 Awards for Excellence in Community Business Partnerships  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/07/2003</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I am pleased to announce that nominations are now open for the 2003 Prime Minister';s Awards for Excellence in Community Business Partnerships.</p>
<p>These awards recognise successful partnerships of business and community organisations who work in a spirit of social coalition to tackle problems of disadvantage and to build stronger local communities.</p>
<p>These partnerships draw upon the unique skills of business and community groups and involve the sharing of ability, expertise, time and resources.  In addition to relieving disadvantage they can also benefit the partners by boosting customer loyalty, staff morale and community goodwill.</p>
<p>Since 1999, The Prime Minister';s Awards for Excellence in Community Business Partnerships have recognised the outstanding achievements of such partnerships.  Many hundreds of partnerships have been nominated during that time and past national winners have come from across Australia and from metropolitan and regional areas.</p>
<p> Separate Awards may be made to small, medium and large businesses operating in each state or territory.  Multi-state Awards may also be made to partnerships operating in more than one state. From these state and territory winners nine National Finalists will be identified from which the best partnership in each business category will be honoured with a National Award.</p>
<p>  In addition to these Awards, three Special Awards will be presented to:    the business that, through its partnership, has had the greatest positive impact on its community;    the media organisation that has most consistently and positively reported on community business partnerships and corporate social responsibility; and    an outstanding partnership that has been operating for more than five years.</p>
<p>Winners will receive their Awards at a special gala ceremony and dinner in Sydney.  Each winning partnership will also receive $10, 000 for the partnership';s community programme or project.</p>
<p> Nomination forms and further information are available at:  <a href="http://www.partnerships.gov.au">www.partnerships.gov.au</a> or Freecall 1800 102 014</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
