<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8665</transcript-id>
    <title>SEC DISCRIMINATION AND AFFIRMATIVE ACTION</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/09/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008665.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
The Government's Response to the Lavarch Report<br />
Statement by<br />
The Prime Minister<br />
The Honourable P. J. Keating. MP<br />
19 September 1992 </p>
<p>Sex Discrimination and Affirmative Action<br />
Sex Discrimination and<br />
Affirmative Action<br />
The Government's Response<br />
to Recommendations<br />
of the Lavarch Report<br />
Introduction<br />
The Government's commitment to eliminating discrimination<br />
against women is reflected in the Sex Discrimination Act 1984<br />
' and the Affirmative Action ( Equal Opportunity for Women) Act<br />
1986. The Sex Discrimination Act is the legal framework for<br />
the Government's policies and programs for the elimination of<br />
discrimination on the ground of sex, marital status or pregnancy.<br />
It is based on the United Nations Convention on the Elimination<br />
of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women, which Australia<br />
ratified in 1983.<br />
The operation of the Act is based on the resolution of<br />
individual and group complaints through conciliation by the Sex<br />
Discrimination Commissioner. The great majority of complaints<br />
are about discrimination at work, but there are also a large<br />
number of complaints about sexual harassment.<br />
The Act has been both a symbolic and a practical source of<br />
support for women in their struggle for equality, especially in the<br />
workplace. Several amendments to improve its operation and </p>
<p>Sex Discrimination and Affirmative Action<br />
widen its scope, including the replacement of the blanket exemptions<br />
for insurance and superannuation with more limited<br />
exemptions, have already been made.<br />
The Act now has wide acceptance, even among many who<br />
opposed it in 1984. Moreover, there is now a more general<br />
understanding of the institutional and social factors which have<br />
worked against equality for women. It is timely to review several<br />
aspects of the operation of the Act, and this has been done in<br />
part by the House of Representatives Standing Committee on<br />
Legal and Constitutional Affairs ( the Lavarch Committee) in the<br />
context of its Inquiry into Equal Opportunity arnd Equal Status for<br />
Women in Australia. Other aspects of the Act h'ave been examined<br />
by the Sex Discrimination Commissioner in her Review of<br />
Exemptions, tabled in Parliament on 10 September 1992.<br />
The aim of the Affirmative Action Act is to remove<br />
discrimination against women in employment, with the emphasis<br />
on positive programs to improve the position of women workers.<br />
The legislation has been gradually phased in to cover all higher<br />
education institutions and private sector organisations with 100<br />
or more employees. Employers are required to report each year<br />
to the Affirmative Action Agency on the progress of their affirmative<br />
action programs. Those who do not comply face being<br />
named in Parliament. There has been a very high level of compliance<br />
with the Act.<br />
In May 1991 the Minister for Industrial Relations announced<br />
a review of the Act, with the aim of introducing<br />
amendments to legislation in this Parliamentary sitting. The<br />
Effectiveness Review of the Act conducted by the Agency's<br />
Director revealed strong support for the legislation and this was<br />
also reflected in the Lavarch Report, which makes a number of<br />
recommendations to improve the Act.<br />
The Government intends to pass further amendments in<br />
the Budget sittings of Parliament to extend the scope and im-Sex Discrimination and Affirmative Action<br />
prove the operation of these Acts. These, and the other measures<br />
discussed here, are the Government's response to those<br />
recommendations of the Lavarch Committee which deal with the<br />
Sex Discrimination Act and the Affirmative Action Act. A number<br />
of the recommendations do not require legislation. In regard to<br />
the Sex Discrimination Act, some present complex or very sensitive<br />
legal or social issues, and require full examination before<br />
decisions can be reached on implementation. In these cases,<br />
however, the Government has set out the process, including the<br />
timing, it will use to arrive at a response.<br />
The recommendations are reproduced for reference. </p>
<p>Sex Discrimination and Affirmallive Action Sex DIscrlmlnation ond Affirmative Action<br />
Extension of the<br />
Sex Discrimination Act<br />
to Industrial Awards<br />
Recommendation 74<br />
The Committee recommends that the<br />
Pay Equity Unit in the Department of<br />
Industrial Relations undertake investigations<br />
into the impact on women of<br />
removing the current exemption at<br />
In particular they should<br />
monitor the extent to which discriminatory<br />
clauses are being removed as<br />
part of the structural efficiency negotiations<br />
and decisions.<br />
The Government will introduce legislation in this session of<br />
Parliament to extend the Sex Discrimination Act to cover federal<br />
industrial awards, and variations to federal awards, made after<br />
the date of the legislation.<br />
At present, the Sex Discrimination Act does not apply to an<br />
act done by a person in direct compliance with an industrial<br />
award. Further, the Australian Industrial Relations Commission is<br />
not bound by the Sex Discrimination Act, although it is required<br />
to take account of the principles embodied in the Act.<br />
When the Act was passed in 1984 there were many discriminatory<br />
provisions in awards and anomalies in the rates paid<br />
for work traditionally done by women. Since then, employers,<br />
unions, industrial tribunals and governments have worked to-</p>
<p>Sex Discrimination and Affirmative Action<br />
wards eliminating discrimination, and most of the overt discrimination<br />
has been removed. Under the Structural Efficiency Principle<br />
established by the Australian Industrial Relations Commission<br />
in 1988, minimum wage rates have been reviewed on the basis<br />
of work value, and this minimum rates adjustment process has<br />
resulted in re-evaluation of many women's jobs. The Government's<br />
intention in extending the Sex Discrimination Act to<br />
awards is to guard against the introduction of discrimination in<br />
new awards, especially in the changed climate of dlecentralised<br />
bargaining arrangements. This is consistent with the Government's<br />
commitment to protecting the interests of low paid and<br />
vulnerable workers.<br />
The mechanism proposed will enable indiviiduals to complain<br />
to the Sex Discrimination Commissioner about federal<br />
awards. The Sex Discrimination Commissioner, if she is satisfied<br />
that the complaint is not frivolous, will refer it to the Australian<br />
Industrial Relations Commission. if it finds that the award is<br />
discriminatory, the Commission will be required to vary the<br />
award unless there are compelling public interest reasons not to<br />
do so. The Sex Discrimination Commissioner will have a right to<br />
appear before the Industrial Relations Commission in relation to<br />
matters she has referred. The exemption in the Sex Discrimination<br />
Act will be modified to take account of the extension of<br />
the Act. Workers with-<br />
Family Responsibilities<br />
Recommendation 62<br />
The Committee recommends that ILO<br />
156 be attached to the SDA as a<br />
schedule and further that the powers<br />
of the Commissioner be expanded to<br />
include responsibilities in association<br />
with ILO 156. Sex Discrimination and Affirmative Action<br />
Recommendation 63<br />
The Committee recommends that<br />
the SDA be amended to include as<br />
a prohibited ground for discrimination,<br />
family, parental and carer<br />
responsibilities.<br />
Australia's ratification of the International Labour Organisation's<br />
Convention No. 1 56 on Workers with Family Responsibilities in<br />
1991 commits the Government to work towards enabling workers<br />
with family responsibilities to be employed without discrimination<br />
and, as far as possible, without conflict with their family<br />
responsibilities. The Government is in the process of amending the Sex<br />
Discrimination Act to prohibit dismissal on the grounds of family<br />
responsibilities. The other recommendations are being addressed<br />
in the context of the Government's plan for implementation of<br />
ILO 1 56. Further consultation and investigations will be undertaken<br />
as to whether family responsibilities will be incorporated<br />
fully as a prohibited ground of discrimination, including consideration<br />
of the definition of ' family'. Several States have already<br />
incorporated family responsibilities in their anti-discrimi nation<br />
legislation. The Attorney-General's Department has been given<br />
resources in this Budget to complete this examination.<br />
Sexual Harassment<br />
Recommendation The Committee recommends that<br />
Division 3 of the Sex Discrimination Act be<br />
amended to:<br />
remove the need for a complainant<br />
to demonstrate<br />
disadvantage by repealing<br />
Sections 28( 3) and 29( 2) and<br />
replacing them with a<br />
definition of sexual harassment<br />
similar to that in Section 58 of<br />
the ACT Discrimination Act 1991 </p>
<p>Sex Discrimination and Aff irmative Action<br />
amend Section 29( 1) to inlude<br />
harassment of staff by students<br />
as an offence; and<br />
make unlawful sexual harass<br />
ment in the provision of goods<br />
and services and accommodation.<br />
The Government will introduce legislation in this session of<br />
Parliament to strengthen the sexual harassment provisions of the<br />
Sex Discrimination Act.<br />
Since the Act was passed, the level of ge) beral understanding<br />
of the harmful effects of sexual harassment has increased<br />
and sexual harassment is no longer regarded as a trivial matter. It<br />
need no longer be linked to an individual suffering some detriment<br />
in employment or education to be unacceptable.<br />
A new definition will be used in the Act so that a complainant<br />
need no longer demonstrate disadvantage; it will be<br />
sufficient that she or he was offended, humiliated or intimidated<br />
by the behaviour in question and that it was reasonable to feel<br />
that way. It brings the prohibition closer to the now common<br />
understanding of the term.<br />
The operation of the sexual harassment provisions will be<br />
extended to the provision of goods and services, and to other<br />
areas where discrimination is unlawful under the Act, including<br />
contract, commission and partnership relationships, bodies<br />
deciding employment qualifications, unions, employment agencies,<br />
clubs, land agents, and the administration of Commonwealth<br />
laws and programs. Sexual harassment of students by<br />
adult students and staff by adult students in educational institutions<br />
will be made unlawful. Sex Discrimination and Affirmative Action<br />
Victimisation<br />
Recommendation<br />
The Committee recommends that<br />
Section 94 of the Sex Discrimination<br />
Act be amended so as to allow complaints<br />
of victimisation to be considered<br />
either through a court of law or<br />
a process of conciliation.<br />
The Government intends to amend the Act in this session of<br />
Parliament to allow complaints of victimisation to be dealt with<br />
by the Sex Discrimination Commissioner by conciliation. Section<br />
94 of the Sex Discrimination Act provides that victimisation of a<br />
complainant is a criminal offence and, as such, can only be<br />
prosecuted in a court. The Government is concerned that such a<br />
procedure, which may be expensive and daunting, could discourage<br />
people from complaining of victimisation. The amendment<br />
will not remove the right to court proceedings.<br />
Group Complaints<br />
Recommendation 66<br />
the Attorney-General's<br />
Department examine<br />
of the SDA in the light of the<br />
recent Federal Courts Amend<br />
ment Act 1991 to ascertain<br />
whether amendment is needed<br />
to provide for a less cumber<br />
some procedure for initiating a<br />
group complaint and to clarify<br />
the right to damages by way of<br />
representative action. </p>
<p>Sex Discrimination and Affirmative Action<br />
The Government intends to amend the Act in this session of<br />
Parliament to bring the provisions for representative complaints<br />
into line with the model used in the Federal Court.<br />
The Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission has<br />
power to inquire into representative complaints. However, the<br />
Commission must first determine whether the complaint meets<br />
seven criteria for a representative complaint. The cumbersome<br />
nature of these provisions means that they have been rarely<br />
used. Under the new procedure a person may bring proceedings<br />
on behalf of a group of seven or more persons Where the claims<br />
of those persons arise from similar or related events and a common<br />
question of law or fact arises with respect to all of their<br />
claims. The consent of a person to be a group member is not<br />
required and a member of the class does not have to take a<br />
positive step to be included in the proceedings, although he or<br />
she has the right to opt out within a period specified by the<br />
Court. Making Determinations<br />
More Easily Enforceable<br />
Recommendation 67<br />
The Committee recommends that<br />
HREOC determinations be registrable<br />
in the Federal Court and that in the<br />
absence of an appeal they automatically<br />
become an enforceable order of<br />
the Court.<br />
In this session of Parliament the Government will amend legislation<br />
to simplify the procedure for enforcing determinations of<br />
the Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission.<br />
Determinations under the Sex Discrimination Act will be Sex Discrimination and Affirmative Action<br />
registrable in the Federal Court when they are made. A respondent<br />
will be allowed a period to challenge the determination in<br />
the Federal Court. If a challenge is brought, the matter will be<br />
heard again by the Court. If there is no challenge, the determination<br />
becomes enforceable as if it were an order of the Court.<br />
This will increase the effectiveness of the Human Rights<br />
and Equal Opportunity Commission's decisions, which at present<br />
are not binding. To enforce its decisions it currently must have<br />
recourse to the Federal Court, which has to go through for itself<br />
the process of establishing that unlawful conduct has occurred.<br />
Operation of the<br />
Human Rights and<br />
Equal Opportunity<br />
Commission<br />
Recommendation<br />
The Committee recommends that<br />
Trade Union and employer organisations<br />
in conjunction with HREOC run<br />
ongoing campaigns amongst men to<br />
raise awareness of the effects of sexual<br />
harassment<br />
The Government supports this recommendation. At present a<br />
Commission training package and video entitled Eliminating<br />
Sexual Harassment in the Workplace A Guide for Managers is<br />
nearing completion. Aimed at private sector middle management,<br />
it has been developed in conjunction with unions and<br />
employer groups and should be available for purchase by the<br />
end of the year. It could be used to supplement a campaign<br />
targeting men. </p>
<p>Sex Discrimination and Affirmative Action<br />
Recommendation 59<br />
The Committee recommends that<br />
without breaching the rights of privacy<br />
of parties to a complaint, HREOC<br />
publish more comprehensive statistics<br />
on the nature of concluded complaints,<br />
including those:<br />
which did not proceed to<br />
conciliation; those resolved through<br />
conciliation; and<br />
those requiring formal<br />
determination by the<br />
Commission or the Court<br />
The Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission has<br />
developed a comprehensive database on complaints and matters<br />
proceeding to formal inquiry. It has sought legal advice on the<br />
boundaries and requirements of confidentiality, and could make<br />
the statistics described here available subject to that advice. In<br />
addition, the Sex Discrimination Commissioner intends to produce<br />
a quarterly information sheet on developments in sex<br />
discrimination issues, with particular focus on legal decisions and<br />
conciliated complaints. Recommendation 66<br />
The Committee recommends that:<br />
the Sex Discrimination<br />
Commissioner seek, through<br />
arrangements with the ACTU.<br />
to ensure that the union<br />
movement is familiar with the<br />
complaint handling processes<br />
of the SDA and of the potential<br />
for union involvement in<br />
complaints under the SDA.<br />
The Sex Discrimination Commissioner is developing a range of<br />
strategies including meetings, seminars and workshops targeted<br />
at unions, in order to inform them and their members about<br />
rights and procedures under the Sex Discrimination Act. The<br />
project is planned to cover two years. Sex Discrimination and Affirmative Action<br />
Recommendation 68<br />
The Committee recommends that:<br />
the Sex Discrimination<br />
Commissioner be provided with<br />
adequate resources to ensure<br />
that the Commission's proactive<br />
functions specified in Section<br />
48( l) of the Act can be more<br />
effectively carried out;<br />
the Human Rights and Equal<br />
Opportunity Commission<br />
determine separate budget<br />
allocations for each of its areas<br />
of responsibility in order that<br />
the Sex Discrimination<br />
Commissioner have access to a<br />
clearly designated budget.<br />
The Commission, an independent statutory body, has indicated<br />
support for these recommendations. The Sex Discrimination<br />
Commissioner has a separate allocation within the Human Rights<br />
and Equal Opportunity Commission's budget, but further discussion<br />
will continue within the Commission on distribution of<br />
resources. Areas Where Further Work<br />
Will be Done on<br />
Strengthening the Act<br />
Recommendation The Committee recommends that:<br />
a general provision stating that<br />
discrimination on the basis of<br />
sex, marital status, potential<br />
pregnancy and family<br />
responsibilities is unlawful<br />
should be included in the SDA. </p>
<p>Sex Discrimination and Affirmative Action<br />
This recommendation will be considered over the next six<br />
months. The Government understands the recommendation to<br />
mean the addition of potential pregnancy and family responsibilities<br />
as prohibited grounds of discrimination. It needs to be<br />
considered in conjunction with Recommendations 61, 62 and<br />
63, which also deal with potential pregnancy and family responsibilities.<br />
The issue of adding family responsibilities to the Act is<br />
currently under consideration ( see Recommendation 63). Adding<br />
potential pregnancy explicitly might strengthen the Act, particularly<br />
in regard to occupational health and safety issues. It is<br />
discussed further under Recommendation 61. Consultations with<br />
the States, and with business and employer groups, will be<br />
necessary before any action is taken.<br />
a provision allowing for ' equal<br />
protection before the law',<br />
similar to the provision in the<br />
Racial Discrimination Act, be<br />
adopted in the SDA.<br />
The Government will investigate this recommendation further<br />
over the next six months. If. as a result of the investigation, it<br />
appears that the new provision would strengthen the Act, it will<br />
be implemented. The proposal for equal protection before the<br />
law, in conjunction with extension of the Act to cover new<br />
' prohibited grounds', could involve a detailed process of searching<br />
for inconsistent legislation. It could cause difficulties with<br />
State legislation and will be discussed with the States.<br />
Recommendation 61<br />
The Committee recommends Section<br />
7 of the SDA be amended by:<br />
the inclusion of ' potential<br />
pregnancy' as a ground of<br />
prohibited discrimination.<br />
the repeal of 701)( b). Sex Discrimination and Affirmative Action<br />
The Government will investigate these recommendations further<br />
over the next six months. If, as a result of the investigation, it<br />
appears that the amendments would strengthen the Act, they<br />
will be implemented.<br />
It is not entirely clear where there could be discrimination<br />
on the grounds of potential pregnancy which would not be<br />
caught by the definition of sex discrimination already in the Act.<br />
However, it could strengthen the Act, in particular with regard to<br />
occupational health and safety issues. Consultation with States<br />
and business and employer groups would be necessary.<br />
Section 701)( b) provides a defence of reasonableness for<br />
discrimination on the grounds of pregnancy. Even if it were<br />
repealed, temporary exemptions could continue to be made<br />
under Section 44, similar to those which have been made in the<br />
past for the lead industry.<br />
Recommendation 64<br />
The Committee recommends that the<br />
dlef inition of ' marital status' in Section<br />
6 be extended to include discrimination<br />
on the basis of the identity of the<br />
spouse of the person lodging the<br />
complaint.<br />
The Government will implement this recommendation, and is<br />
examining the best means to do so. It may be necessary to allow<br />
for exceptions to the new provision, for example if an employer<br />
wished not to employ someone whose spouse worked for a rival<br />
firm. This might be dealt with by a ' reasonableness' criterion, but<br />
further consideration and consultation are warranted.<br />
Recommendation 72<br />
The Committee recommends that the<br />
Attorney-General's Department, in<br />
consultation with HREOC. determine<br />
if an amendment is necessary to </p>
<p>Sex Discrimination and Affirmative Action<br />
Section 33 so that it ensures that<br />
measures to promote equal opportunity<br />
for women or to meet their<br />
special needs are not unlawful.<br />
The Government will investigate this recommendation fully over<br />
the next six months. If, as a result of the investigation, it appears<br />
that a new provision would strengthen the Act, the Act will be<br />
amended. The Lavarch Report refers to evidence of a very strongly<br />
expressed view in the community that the section of the Act<br />
which allows for measures to promote equality' needs to be<br />
reinforced. This concern has been expressed in the context of<br />
extending the Act to cover federal industrial awards, a small<br />
number of which contain provisions which discriminate in favour<br />
of women. The Government recognises that recent cases have<br />
caused concern. It has been argued that these cases have demonstrated<br />
that the clause is adequate, but many women's organisations<br />
would disagree with this view. On the other hand,<br />
drafting a more satisfactory clause may be extremely difficult,<br />
and there is a danger that a change would obviate the usefulness<br />
of previous cases as precedents. Further consideration is<br />
warranted. Indirect Discrimination<br />
Recommendation 70<br />
The Committee recommends that:<br />
sub-sections 6( 2) and 7( 2)<br />
paragraph be deleted.<br />
a new sub-section be added to<br />
Sections 5, 6 and 7 in the<br />
following terms:<br />
it shall be a defence for a discriminator<br />
to show that the imposition of the Sex Discrimination and Affirmative Action<br />
condition or requirement was reasonable<br />
in order to pursue the least<br />
discriminatory option available to the<br />
discriminator in the circumstances of<br />
the case.<br />
The Government accepts the principle behind this recommendation,<br />
but implementation warrants further consideration of legal<br />
precedent and consultations with the States and Territories and<br />
business and employer groups. This will be done over the next six<br />
months. These provisions deal w ith the test for indirect discrimination.<br />
If the recommendation were implemented, it might be<br />
necessary to amend the test in paragraph to refer not only to<br />
the least discriminatory option but also to allow for a test of<br />
economic viability. Legal Aid-<br />
Recommendation 69<br />
The Committee recommends that the<br />
Attorney-General investigate the criteria<br />
applied by the Legal Aid Commission<br />
in deciding aid applications<br />
for assistance in sex discrimination<br />
cases with a view to ensuring that<br />
complainants and respondents are<br />
assisted in appropriate cases.<br />
Legal Aid is provided through State agencies, and the criteria are<br />
decided at State level. Over the next six months the Government<br />
will consider the issues, in the light of the scarce resources<br />
available. </p>
<p>Discrimination a~ ndc A~ ffiraaiienAatodteA firmative Action)<br />
The Defence Force<br />
Recommendation 71<br />
The Committee recommends that<br />
Section 43 be amended to include a<br />
specified time period not exceeding<br />
two years to allow the removal of<br />
prohibitive and discriminatory provisions<br />
from Defence Force legislative<br />
requirements and administrative<br />
procedures.<br />
The Minister for Defence Science and Personnel will re-examine<br />
the exclusion of women from combat duties and the legislative<br />
basis of that exclusion after the Chief of the Defence Force<br />
presents the results of a comprehensive review of the employment<br />
of women in combat and combat-related duties later this<br />
year. Women are at present excluded from serving in combat<br />
positions. The Sex Discrimination Act also allows their exclusion<br />
from combat-related duties although the latter exclusion has not<br />
been applied since May 1990 when the Chiefs of Staff recommended<br />
against its continued application and the Minister for<br />
Defence announced a new policy based on this advice.<br />
A progress review of the policy of employing women in<br />
combat-related positions was considered by the Chiefs of Staff<br />
Committee in June 1991. The Chiefs of Staff found that the<br />
implementation of the new policy was progressing well and<br />
without any major impediment. A further review of policies<br />
relating to the employment of women in combat and combatrelated<br />
positions, prompted by the Lavarch Report, is being<br />
conducted with a report to be submitted by the Chief of the<br />
Defence Force by 30 October 1992. Religious Schools<br />
Recommendation 73<br />
The Committee recommends that<br />
Section 38 of the Sex Discrimination<br />
Act be amended to add the requirement<br />
of ' reasonableness'.<br />
The Government will consult widely on this issue, and on the full<br />
implications for religious schools of adding any reasonableness<br />
criterion to the Act. It recognises the need to balance people's<br />
right to equal treatment with the right to freedom of religious<br />
practice. It will reconsider its response to the recommendation in<br />
twelve months' time.<br />
Implementation of the recommendation to add a criterion<br />
. of reasonableness to the exemption of employment by educational<br />
institutions established for religious purposes would mean<br />
that a religious body could be called on to show that discrimination<br />
in employment of staff was reasonable having regard to the<br />
objectives of the organisation. The Lavarch Report expresses the<br />
view that it is unacceptable to have a double standard between<br />
men and women employed in schools established for religious<br />
purposes.<br />
Sex Discrimination and Aftirmative Action </p>
<p>Sex Discrimination and Affirmative ActionSex Discrimination and Affirmative Action<br />
Quality of Programs<br />
Recommendation 76<br />
The Committee recommends that:<br />
the Affirmative Action Agency<br />
be resourced to undertake<br />
qualitative assessments of<br />
reports received.<br />
The Government supports this recommendation. In the 1992-93<br />
Budget the Government has provided an additional $ 0.4m in<br />
1992 ( and $ 0.25m in 1993-94) to the Affirmative Action Agency<br />
for a new program of measures to encourage quality affirmative<br />
action outcomes.<br />
Submissions and consultations of the Effectiveness Review<br />
of the Affirmative Action Act revealed wide ranging and strong<br />
support for maintaining the existing general structure of the<br />
legislation. There was concern, however, about the uneven<br />
quality of employers' affirmative action programs and strong<br />
support for focussing on improving quality in the next phase of<br />
the legislation. The new measures will include development of performance<br />
standards based on best practice benchmarks; and cooperative<br />
research projects and training initiatives with employer<br />
bodies and unions. Evaluation of reports and feedback to employers<br />
will be integral to these measures.<br />
the Agency encourages<br />
companies to focus more<br />
carefully on identifying and<br />
addressing the particular needs<br />
of groups of women with<br />
special needs in the workforce. </p>
<p>Sex Discrimination and Affirmative Action<br />
The issue of how to encourage employers to focus on the<br />
needs of particular groups of women workers was considered as<br />
part of the Effectiveness Review of the Act. The Government<br />
accepts the Director's conclusion that the most fruitful approach<br />
would be for the Agency to develop models of good practice cooperatively<br />
with interested companies ( including for example,<br />
language and literacy training for women, and workplace design<br />
facilitating employment of women with disabilities), rather than<br />
provide legislative coverage by category for women with multiple<br />
disadvantage. This will be taken up by the Agency in the next<br />
stage of the legislation. Recommendation 77<br />
The Committee recommends that:<br />
those organisations consistently<br />
recording good progress should<br />
have the obligation of report<br />
ing reduced accordingly,<br />
reducing the workload of the<br />
organisation itself and the<br />
Affirmative Action Agency; and<br />
The Government will implement this recommendation which was<br />
also raised in the Effectiveness Review, by introducing legislation<br />
in this session of Parliament to give the Director the power to<br />
vary reporting requirements.<br />
This amendment will enable the Director to alter the report<br />
, format to permit, for example, detailed reporting in one year and<br />
progress and exceptions reporting the next. It would also allow<br />
the development of a scheme for exempting exceptional performers<br />
from reporting requirements for a number of years,<br />
similar to the ' exceptional trainer' status under the Training<br />
Guarantee ( Administration) Act 1990. Sex Discrimination and Affirmative Action<br />
the Affirmative Action Agency<br />
to be charged with responsibil<br />
ity to distribute reports to<br />
relevant interest groups,<br />
principally trade unions.<br />
Submissions, consultations and research for the Effectiveness<br />
Review suggest that the requirements of the Act for employers<br />
to consult with trade unions and with employees about their<br />
affirmative action programs are not well met. The Government<br />
has decided that a tripartite advisory committee will be established<br />
to address this issue as well as how to improve the quality<br />
of affirmative action reports. A priority for the committee would<br />
be to develop general principles for compliance with the eight<br />
steps of an affirmative action program and codes to interpret<br />
them. Early emphasis will be given to steps Three and Four on<br />
consultation. Effective consultation by employers with their<br />
employees and with unions would include providing them with<br />
copies of their affirmative action reports.<br />
Employers' affirmative action reports are available to any<br />
individual or organisation upon request to the Agency. To improve<br />
availability, from 1992-93 a full set of the most recent<br />
reports will be made available on microfiche in each capital city.<br />
Coverae<br />
Recommendation 77<br />
The Committee recommends that:<br />
a further expansion of the<br />
number of companies which<br />
come under the Affirmative<br />
Action Act to include those<br />
employing 40 people and in the<br />
long-term, all employees; </p>
<p>Sex Discrimination and Affirmative Action<br />
the resources of the<br />
Affirmative Action Agency<br />
would need to be increased<br />
commensurate with the<br />
increased work load;<br />
In the Effectiveness Review of the Act, the Director estimated<br />
that reducing the threshold to 50 would double the number of<br />
reports to be handled by the Agency yet increase coverage by<br />
only 8 per cent of private sector employees. Accordingly the<br />
Government has decided that the objectives of the Act would be<br />
better advanced through focusing on the quality of employers'<br />
programs rather than reducing the threshold.<br />
The Government intends, however, to legislate in this<br />
session of Parliament to extend the Act to ensure the coverage<br />
of elected union officials as employees and of trainees employed<br />
through Group Training Schemes.<br />
The Effectiveness Review highlighted * considerable community<br />
concern about discrimination against women in smaller<br />
companies. This issue is to be kept under review by the Agency.<br />
As part of its program of new measures arising from the Effectiveness<br />
Review, the Agency will also develop a strategy for<br />
raising awareness of issues surrounding discrimination against<br />
women in smaller companies. This could include cooperative<br />
training with employer organisations and unions, preparation of<br />
appropriate policies and guidelines, and pilot programs in industries<br />
reporting particular difficulties.<br />
Recommendation 78<br />
The Committee recommends that: Sex Discrimination and Affirmative Action<br />
The Government intends to legislate in this session of Parliament<br />
to extend the operation of the Act to voluntary bodies employing<br />
one hundred or more employees. This will bring an estimated<br />
60,000 additional paid employees under the Act when the<br />
amendment comes into operation and will mainly affect the<br />
largest charities, independent schools and the Catholic school<br />
system. Statutory Authorities<br />
Recommendation 78<br />
The Committee recommends that:<br />
evaluative analysis be under<br />
taken by DIR to ensure that<br />
statutory authorities are<br />
adopting effective<br />
affirmative action programs;<br />
and<br />
The Government supports this recommendation. The Department<br />
of Industrial Relations, in administering the Government's<br />
industrial relations co-ordination arrangements, will analyse the<br />
extent to which statutory authorities are adopting effective<br />
affirmative action and equal employment opportunity programs.<br />
and report to the Minister for Industrial Relations. The evaluative<br />
criteria developed by the Agency will form the basis of the<br />
assessments. The Minister for industrial Relations will negotiate with his<br />
counterparts in State and Territory Governments to ensure<br />
coverage of all government employees by EEO provisions.<br />
work needs to be undertaken<br />
by DIR in consultation with AAA<br />
to establish how employers in<br />
the voluntary sector can be<br />
encouraged to adopt affirmative<br />
action programs. </p>
<p>Sex Discrimination and Affirmative ActionSex Discrimination and Affirmative Action<br />
Contract Compliance<br />
Recommendation 79<br />
The Committee recommends that:<br />
the Commonwealth Government<br />
introduce contract<br />
compliance for all Commonwealth<br />
contracts so that all<br />
corporations/ organisations<br />
tendering for government<br />
contracts should be required to<br />
supply evidence that they<br />
practice equal employment<br />
opportunity; and ance for purchasing that occurs through the Department of<br />
Administrative Services.<br />
The Minister for Industrial Relations will raise with his State<br />
and Territory counterparts the importance of the adoption of<br />
similar contract compliance policies by State and Territory governments.<br />
The Victorian Government has put contract compliance<br />
in place and the policy is operating effectively with minimal<br />
administrative costs.<br />
as part of greater Commonwealth<br />
State co-operation in<br />
equal opportunity matters, the<br />
State and Territory Governments<br />
explore options such as<br />
contract compliance to enhance<br />
the effectiveness of sex<br />
discrimination legislation.<br />
The Government accepts this recommendation, which is also a<br />
recommendation in the Effectiveness Review, as a means of<br />
signalling the Government's support for affirmative action<br />
through an additional incentive to employers to comply with the<br />
Act. Those employers who fail to comply with the requirements<br />
of the Act will not be eligible for consideration for government<br />
contracts for goods and services and specified industry assistance.<br />
This will encompass purchasing by all government departments.<br />
Operational details of the policy are currently being<br />
developed and the implementation date and operational policy<br />
will be announced at a later date. The Minister for Administrative<br />
Services has already announced the adoption of contract compli-</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
