<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>12784</transcript-id>
    <title>JOINT STATEMENT WITH PRIME MINISTER KOIZUMI AUSTRALIA - JAPAN CREATIVE PARTNERSHIP</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/01/2002</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Recognising the great benefits and merits of the long-standing close ties and cooperation between Australia and Japan, based on their shared values of democracy, freedom, the rule of law and market-based economies, Prime Minister John Howard and Prime Minister Junichiro Koizumi today committed themselves to a dynamic and forward-looking relationship, in order to take maximum advantage of the tremendous opportunities and challenges of the new international environment in the early 21st Century.<br />
Global<br />
2.</p>
<p>Both Prime Ministers recognised the importance of international solidarity in the fight against terrorism and acknowledged the value of each other';s contribution to this effort.  In this context, the Prime Ministers also reaffirmed their commitment to support Afghanistan.<br />
3.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Howard reaffirmed Australia';s continued strong support for Japan';s permanent membership of the United Nations Security Council.<br />
4.</p>
<p>The Prime Ministers expressed their determination to promote further liberalisation of global trade and investment, and recognised the crucial importance of the successful conclusion of a new round of trade negotiations in the WTO.<br />
5.</p>
<p>The Prime Ministers reaffirmed their determination to address the major environmental issue of climate change, taking into account both economic and environmental effects.  Japan was in the process of ratifying the Kyoto Protocol.  Australia would continue to work to meet its Kyoto target.  The Prime Ministers emphasised their desire to work together to build a global climate change regime that included all countries.<br />
6.</p>
<p>Sharing the objective of sustainable development, the Prime Ministers stated their intention that the two countries continue to work together for the success of the Johannesburg Summit.<br />
Regional<br />
7.</p>
<p>Both Prime Ministers welcomed the peaceful conclusion of the recent presidential election in East Timor.  In particular, the Australian Prime Minister welcomed Japan';s valuable contribution to the UN peacekeeping forces.  The Prime Ministers reaffirmed their commitment to work together to help East Timor in its transition to independence and beyond, including by ensuring the continued success of the UN peacekeeping operation there.<br />
 8.</p>
<p>Drawing on their strong record of cooperation in APEC, the East Asian financial crisis, the ASEAN Regional Forum, peacekeeping in Cambodia and now in East Timor, both leaders affirmed their renewed commitment to work together to meet regional challenges.<br />
9.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Howard welcomed Prime Minister Koizumi';s vision of a “community that acts together and advances together”, as expressed by him in Singapore on 14 January 2002.  Prime Minister Koizumi reiterated his expectation that Australia would be a core member of this community, and emphasised the contribution that Australia could make in this regard.  The Prime Ministers stated that consideration should be given to regional diversity and the specific needs of other countries in the region.  Furthermore, the two Prime Ministers highly valued the contribution made to regional cooperation by the existing frameworks.<br />
10.</p>
<p>The Prime Ministers emphasised the importance of working together to combat effectively transnational problems such as people smuggling and money laundering.  In this regard, Prime Minister Koizumi congratulated Australia on successfully co-hosting with Indonesia the Regional Ministerial Conference on People Smuggling convened in Bali in February this year.<br />
11.</p>
<p>Noting both nations'; respective core alliances with the United States, they gave their strong support to United States'; engagement and presence in the Asia-Pacific region, which underpinned regional stability.  They reaffirmed their intention to work together to preserve the security environment in the region.<br />
Bilateral<br />
12.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Howard reaffirmed his strong support for Prime Minister Koizumi';s structural reform efforts, and noted the benefits for Australia and the world of a strong Japanese economy.  Prime Minister Koizumi said that Australia';s strong economic growth highlighted the benefits of structural reform.<br />
13.</p>
<p>The Prime Ministers noted the exciting prospects for increased cooperation across the entire relationship, as evidenced by the range of recommendations which emerged from the ‘Australia – Japan Conference for the 21st Century';, held in Sydney in April 2001.<br />
14.</p>
<p>The Prime Ministers reaffirmed their commitment to work to strengthen further the bilateral economic relationship to reflect the dynamic structural changes now occurring in the two economies, including in response to regional economic developments and globalisation.  The Prime Ministers welcomed the recent submission of proposals and suggestions from the two private sectors on ways to strengthen trade and economic linkages between the two countries.  The Prime Ministers agreed that the two Governments would launch high-level consultations to explore all options for deeper economic linkages between Australia and Japan.<br />
15.</p>
<p>The Prime Ministers welcomed the expanding dialogue and cooperation between the two nations on security and defence issues, underpinned by their close strategic interests.<br />
 ANNEX<br />
In line with the Joint Press Statement by Prime Minister Howard and Prime Minister Koizumi, the Governments of Australia and Japan will take the following specific actions to advance the Australia – Japan Creative Partnership.<br />
Global<br />
1.</p>
<p>Terrorism High-level consultations on counter-terrorism.<br />
2.</p>
<p>Energy Enhanced cooperation in the field of energy bilaterally and in multilateral organisations and fora such as the International Energy Agency (IEA) and APEC.<br />
3.</p>
<p>Environment Meeting between Australian and Japanese Environment Ministers in the near future to discuss climate change, including the Kyoto Protocol, and other international environmental issues of common concern, and to explore practical collaboration between the two countries on measures to address climate change.<br />
4.</p>
<p>United Nations   Increased cooperation with a particular focus on maintaining appropriate UN engagement in the legitimate needs of the Asia Pacific region.   Closer cooperation in peacekeeping in the region.  Continued collaboration on implementation of the Brahimi recommendations and the need for Security Council and other reforms.<br />
Regional<br />
1.</p>
<p>Transnational Crimes </p>
<p>(a)</p>
<p>People Smuggling Joint efforts to follow up the outcomes of the Regional Ministerial Conference held in Bali last February, including the possibility of joint cooperation on projects requested by countries in the region. </p>
<p>(b)</p>
<p>Money laundering Closer cooperation in the Asia-Pacific Group on Money Laundering (APG) and Financial Action Task Force (FATF).<br />
2.</p>
<p>APEC Closer cooperation on advancing the APEC agenda, including promoting the WTO agenda, intellectual property rights enforcement, strengthening economic legal infrastructure and competition policy, enhancing the mobility of business people and furthering e-commerce, especially in the field of electronic customs and paperless trading.<br />
3.</p>
<p>Development Cooperation   Closer cooperation on improving development capacity within the region. Increased consultation and coordination of development assistance in the South Pacific, including on assistance to improve capacity building in response to regional needs.<br />
Bilateral<br />
1.</p>
<p>Political Dialogue Continued annual Prime Ministerial meetings and regular Ministerial meetings.<br />
2.</p>
<p>Economic Consultations High-level economic consultations at the deputy minister level and working groups at the director level in order to discuss global, regional and bilateral economic issues.<br />
3.</p>
<p>Defence and Security   Visit to Australia by the Japanese State Minister for Defense Affairs at the earliest opportunity.   Continued annual discussions aimed at advancing cooperation and understanding of each other';s approaches to security and defence issues. Convening of bilateral 1.5 track security talks between academics and officials in their private capacity, to be held later in the year.<br />
4.</p>
<p>Education   Endorsement of the Australia – Japan Higher Education Forum in Tokyo this month. Exploration of ways to enhance the teaching of the Japanese language in Australia, noting the idea of Japan';s JET programme.<br />
5.</p>
<p>Science and Technology </p>
<p>(a)</p>
<p>Expanded dialogue in science and technology for closer research, cooperation and collaboration through government-initiated symposia. </p>
<p>(b)</p>
<p>BiotechnologySupport for the Fifth Australia – Japan Symposium on Drug Design and Development in Nara, Japan, where Australian and Japanese biotechnology companies will meet and explore mutual interests. </p>
<p>(c)</p>
<p>SpaceExpanded cooperation between Australia and Japan on space matters, including the scheduled launch by the National Space Development Agency of Japan (NASDA) of Australia';s Federation Satellite in 2002.<br />
6.</p>
<p>Sister cities A national level event to be organised by relevant authorities to commemorate the 40th anniversary of the first sister-city relationship between Australia and Japan.<br />
7.</p>
<p>Australia – Japan Conference for 21st Century Appropriate follow up to the ‘Australia – Japan Conference';, held in Sydney in April 2001. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
