<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7733</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF JOINT NEWS CONFERENCE WITH NT CHIEF MINISTER, MARSHALL PERSON, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, 7 SEPTEMBER 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/09/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007733.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
T89/ 150A<br />
S<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF JOINT NEWS CONFERENCE WITH NT CHIEF MINISTER,<br />
MARSHALL PERRON, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, 7 SEPTEMBER 1989<br />
E 0 E -PROOF ONLY<br />
PM: Ladies and Gentlemen, could I just go to the<br />
arrangements, the first part of this Press Conference of<br />
course will be about the Historic Agreement that Marshall<br />
Perron and I have reached in respect of our both Governments<br />
on this fundamental important issue and we will make each of<br />
us a brief statement about that and when we have done that<br />
we would sign the Agreement, the Memorandum between us and<br />
after we have done that we would each be available for any<br />
questions that you would want to address to us and then once<br />
this issue is completed in terms of questions, Mr Perron<br />
would withdraw and I would be available for questions from<br />
you on any other subject. Those terms then could I just<br />
briefly say that both Mr Perron and I regard today as an<br />
historic day not just for our Governments, but much more<br />
importantly than that for the Aboriginal people of the<br />
Northern Territory. Before I make a brief comment about<br />
what it is that we have agreed on, may I pay an unqualified<br />
tribute to the Chief Minister of the Northern Territory. We<br />
have been engaged in an exercise, which by its nature, you<br />
would appreciate is full of complexities in regard to which<br />
there are accumulated aspirations, prejudices if you like,<br />
which make negotiations between the tw o Governments<br />
inevitably difficult. And in these negotiations I have<br />
found, from the Chief minister, a spirit of give and take,<br />
compromise, a willingness to listen constructively to points<br />
of view, and I hope that from our side we have been able to<br />
reciprocate because if there hadn't been that spirit between<br />
us then this historic agreement would not have been able to<br />
have been reached. And I would also in paying tribute to<br />
the Chief Minister take this opportunity of paying a very<br />
significant tribute to my Minister, Gerry Hand, for whom<br />
this also represents the culmination of great commitment and<br />
a very great deal of hard work. The Agreement that we are<br />
about to sign, has come as result of long hours of<br />
discussions and negotiations over the last two days, and<br />
essentially, as you will appreciate from having read the<br />
material, it is a memorandum of agreement concerning the<br />
provision of Aboriginal living areas in the Northern<br />
Territory. In regard to the stock routes and reserves, that<br />
title will be provided under Commonwealth legislation, in<br />
respect of excisions in pastoral areas that will be provided<br />
by legislation of the Northern Territory. We of course<br />
realise-that the provision of title is not the end of the<br />
story but it is a necessary and has always been a necessary </p>
<p>-2-<br />
precondition of addressing the tragic conditions of so many<br />
of our Aboriginal fellow citizens in the Northern Territory.<br />
And just as we are committed now to accelerating the<br />
processes which will provide title so we have a joint<br />
commitment to ensure that we do as much then as we can.<br />
Title having been provided to rectify the conditions under<br />
which so many of our Aboriginal fellow citizens live. It is<br />
our intention to move ahead quickly in the legislative<br />
process, with October being the schedule for both Marshall<br />
Perron and ourselves here in Canberra, but beyond that<br />
commitment to acceleration in the legislative area we are<br />
both committed to moving in co-operatively in the<br />
administrative area to give effect to the agreement that we<br />
have reached.<br />
PERRON: I would just like to say that I feel honoured, I<br />
guess, that I have managed to complete a task that was<br />
commenced by, and handled by, three of my predecessors who<br />
were unfortunately over those years, unable to reach the<br />
stage of agreement that we have today. It is a matter of<br />
enourmous complexity. We are talking about the subject of<br />
settling the aspirations of some Aboriginal people for land<br />
which is currently owned by Australians under normal title.<br />
And that together with the history of aboriginal affairs<br />
generally in the Northern Territory, having regard that it<br />
is different from the rest of Australia, the advent of the<br />
Land Rights Act in 1976 has provided us special problems and<br />
challenges over the last decade plus, and no doubt has<br />
contributed to a degree to the difficulty in parties<br />
reaching resolution on this matter previously. It is<br />
unfortunate that it has taken both our Governments as long<br />
as this, however, the important thing is that the Agreement<br />
is about to be signed. It is an agre~ ment that I believe<br />
both Governments believe is fair and just, although like all<br />
agreements obviously neither of us con~ sider it the ideal, or<br />
what we would have liked to have achieved right from the<br />
start. The important thing is that those who we both most<br />
want to help, the Aboriginals, are going to benefit from<br />
this process, and they will benefit from it quickly. And I<br />
am very pleased to have been able to complete what I see as<br />
a four year negotiation period. I'd like to pay tribute to<br />
the officers both of the Commonwealth and of my own<br />
Government who have spent something like about 20 hours<br />
straight in concluding this matter and we can now get on<br />
with the job of actually meeting the aspirations of many<br />
Aborigines in the Northern Territory.<br />
( Agreement Signed)<br />
PM: We are open to questions on this subject.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Perron, stock routes separated from<br />
the pastoral holdings that surrounded them?<br />
PERRON: Yes. </p>
<p>-3-<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister and Mr Perron, how sure are you<br />
respectively that the Land Councils in the Northern<br />
Territory and the Cattlemens' Association will accept this<br />
package. PM: Well let me pick up a point that the Chief Minister<br />
made. It is accurate as he put it to say that this<br />
Memorandum of Agreement that we have just signed, not only<br />
not be regarded as an ideal solution from the point of view<br />
of the respective governments, but it is the case, and it<br />
would certainly not represent the ideal solution from the<br />
point of view of the Land Councils or certainly the<br />
Cattlemens' Association. But as well as agreeing as we have<br />
to this document, the second agreement we have is that we<br />
will use our respective influences with the Land Councils<br />
and with the Cattlemens' Association to explain what is<br />
being done and the overall benefits that are involved, and I<br />
think that commitment that we have each made and of course<br />
with Gerry Hand on our side being so importantly involved in<br />
his relationships with the Land Councils, we believe that we<br />
will be able to make everyone with a direct interest<br />
understand that this is the best possible solution. Just a<br />
minute Mr Perron may want to say something.<br />
PERRON: No, No, I think you have summed it up very well<br />
Prime Minister.<br />
JOURNLALIST: Can you describe the conditions that the<br />
Aborigines are living under at the moment and how this<br />
agreement will help them?<br />
PM: Yes, its been recognised by everyone concerned that in<br />
respect of many of these conditions,-which are appalling,<br />
there is no argument, there has never'been any argument<br />
between the Chief Minister and myself-about that fact, and<br />
they are circumstances which have brought no credit to<br />
Australia. They have been projected, not only within this<br />
country, but internationally, but it has been recognised by<br />
us all that you have to settle the question of title. The<br />
title has to be given before the combination of<br />
responsibility between the Territory Government and<br />
ourselves, we can then make the provision to rectify those<br />
appalling conditions. And we have a commitment to do that.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, will there be a need for the<br />
Commonwealth to legislate to concrete in the Northern<br />
Territory side of this deal?<br />
PM: No the only, where our legislation involves in regard<br />
to the proclamation, section 50, we had addressed this<br />
question of whether there may be some idea of entrenchment<br />
from the Commonwealth point of view in our legislation, what<br />
is the requirement on the part of the Northern Territory to<br />
give effect to the excisions decision. But we have through<br />
the exchange of the letters which will be associated with<br />
this and the dual signing of this Memorandum, we now have a </p>
<p>-4-<br />
situation where, from our point of view, we believe that the<br />
commitment of the Northern Territory is fully entrenched, if<br />
you like it that way, and we have never had any doubt about<br />
the integrity of Marshall Perron, or his Government about<br />
adhering to an agreement that we would reach. There was<br />
some concern, on the part of some representing the<br />
Aboriginal people, that okay that's okay but * what about the<br />
future. Now what we have done in this way by entrenching<br />
the arrangement between us in a memorandum of Agreement, the<br />
exchange of letters to be associated with that, we believe<br />
that that concern is appropriately addressed.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Perron, two questions. What is the, or is<br />
there any difference between the security of title granted<br />
under the NT legislation in this package and the<br />
Commonwealth? And the second one is, do you think that the<br />
relationship that you and Mr Hawke may have developed over<br />
the past months in negotiating this issue might see an end<br />
to the race politics, if you like, that has been a feature<br />
of the Northern Territory for so many years?<br />
PERRON: In answer to your first question there will be two<br />
forms of title. They will be quite distinct. Those areas<br />
that are scheduled by the Commonwealth, as a schedule to the<br />
Land Rights Act will be inalienably freehold. They will be<br />
restricted to some areas on stock reserves only. The titles<br />
issued by the Territory Government will be a modified form<br />
of Territory freehold with special protections in that title<br />
to provide comfort to Aboriginals in this situation. And we<br />
will be legislating specifically for that in the October<br />
sittings. Answer to your second question, I guess time will<br />
tell whether the rapport which the Prime minister and I have<br />
built up over this matter lessens the-publicness, I guess,<br />
of aboriginal issues between the Territory and the<br />
Commonwealth in the future. Aboriginal issues in the<br />
Territory have always been sensitive. I think they have<br />
often been totally misrepresented in the national press. I<br />
think the Territory's performance in aboriginal affairs is<br />
one that we can be very proud of, yet is poorly understood<br />
by southern journalists. I would advocate to you all that<br />
the Territory's performance in regard to the recognition of<br />
tribal customs in territory law. Our recognition of<br />
Aboriginal participation in national parks across the<br />
Northern Territory. Our health programs. We have<br />
initiatives in education, which are unique in this country,<br />
designed specifically to assist Aborigines record their<br />
culture, and be taught their culture. And electoral reform<br />
is another example. We're the first in the country, I think<br />
possibly still the only, to introduce mobile polling booths<br />
and compulsory voting. Voluntary enrolment, compulsory<br />
voting for Aborigines. Photographs on ballot papers and so<br />
on. Small matters you may think, but collectively we have<br />
the best record in this country, by far, of the social<br />
advancement of Aboriginals. And much of the national<br />
~ impression of us as a bunch of red necks is lack of, is<br />
ignorance on behalf of other Australians. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Mr Perron, how many Aboriginal people do you<br />
expect to benefit from excisions and do you expect that most<br />
claims will be settled by consensus or do you think they<br />
will mostly be dealt with by the Tribunal and the Northern<br />
Territory Supreme Court?<br />
PERRON: I would expect by far the vast majority to be<br />
settled by agreement prior to getting near a tribunal<br />
process. As for the actual numbers, that is very difficult<br />
to predict but it will be certainly, certainly a couple of<br />
thousand. It may be many more. But it is difficult to<br />
predict exactly how many people will eventually meet the<br />
eligibility criteria through the entire process.<br />
JOURNALIST: Can I just clarify the mining issue. Does this<br />
mean that Aborigines will be able to reject mining on the<br />
land that they have titles to?<br />
PERRON: Let me explain it this way. We have undertaken to<br />
provide a mining reserve around portions of land which is<br />
granted as a result of an excision application in order that<br />
the actual residential component of that land is not<br />
disturbed, in exactly the same way as we provide a mining<br />
reserve around all towns in the Northern Territory in order<br />
that you don't find a drilling rig in your backyard one day.<br />
And with the negotiation with each individual excision<br />
applicant we can vary the size of those boundaries to<br />
prohibit mining exploration on their land. Bear in mind<br />
that by and large these parcels of land will be fairly small<br />
and also bear in mind that many Aborigines in the Northern<br />
Territory today are quite happy, indeed anxious, to have<br />
mining activity on their land.<br />
JOURNALIST: How many years will it bKe before we start to<br />
see the fruits of this before the conditions of Aborigines<br />
are actually improved?<br />
PERRON: Well the conditions for Aborigines are improving<br />
all the time. The amount of money that flows into<br />
Aboriginal essential services and housing via the<br />
Commonwealth and with funds from the Territory Government as<br />
well is enormous. I think we calculate we have spent some<br />
$ 4 billion in the last ten years as a Territory Government<br />
alone. That's excluding direct specific purpose funding by<br />
the Commonwealth itself. And its an ongoing process. It<br />
was only, I think, the last six months that we agreed with<br />
the Commonwealth for an additional $ 30 million program to<br />
upgrade Aboriginal housing in towns throughout the<br />
Territory. And these are the sorts of initiatives that are<br />
taken basically every year or two. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: These 2,000 Aborigines living in appalling<br />
poverty at the moment, now how long will it be before they<br />
get a better deal?<br />
PERRON:. Well, I can't give you an answer to that.<br />
Excisions I would expect land titles will begin to flow<br />
within a matter of months, bearing in mind that the entire<br />
process doesn't start until October when all the legislation<br />
is in place. Titles will flow in a matter of months. Now<br />
the speed at which roads on to that land, water can be<br />
found, houses built is going to be dependent on the supply<br />
of money and it's going to be very expensive.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime minister, there are still appalling<br />
conditions in western Australia because of similar problems<br />
with title there. Would you hope that this agreement will<br />
provide some sort of precedent for the western Australian<br />
Government? PM: Well, I think it's fair to say of the minister who, as<br />
you will recall I gave the appropriate tribute to a moment<br />
ago, has not been exclusively concerned during his Ministry<br />
with the Northern Territory and there will be on-going<br />
consultations with the other areas of Australia where work<br />
needs to be done. I think we can say this, that we would<br />
hope that what has been done here in regard to the Northern<br />
Territory will stand as an example of what can be done by<br />
appropriate cooperation. So, in that sense, while it won't<br />
directly mean anything outside of the Northern Territory, I<br />
hope it will act as an inspiration, not only to those that<br />
are directly involved, but I hope really that this will be<br />
important for the people of Australia as a whole, that it<br />
will represent a recognition by two Gg9vernments of different<br />
political persuasions of the necessity to act<br />
constructively in the committed way to address these issues.<br />
So, in that sense, I do hope and expect it will have a<br />
significance beyond just the Northern Territory.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime minister, have you got any idea of how<br />
much land has now been opened up, in this way, throughout<br />
the country in the same way<br />
PM: It's a matter of detail which Mr Hand would be perhaps<br />
better able to answer, or in respect of the Northern<br />
Territory, Mr Perron. I don't pretend to have those details<br />
but Gerry<br />
PERRON: I think the question related to land elsewhere,<br />
outside the Territory-<br />
PM: But you also include the Territory in your thinking, do<br />
you? JOURNALIST: I asked about<br />
PM: Yet. Not just the Territory. </p>
<p>-7-<br />
JOURNALIST: Queensland New South Wales.<br />
HAND: this only effects<br />
PM: I know it does, but he's extended beyond there so, I<br />
mean, the answer to your question I don't think either the<br />
Minister or the Chief Minister could give you a precise<br />
answer in regard to the Northern Territory, in particular,<br />
or Australia as a whole.<br />
JOURNAL-IST: But you're basically now inviting Aboriginals<br />
to make-<br />
PM: I beg your pardon?<br />
JOURNALIST: You are now inviting Aboriginal groups to make<br />
these claims in all States?<br />
PM: a question of, as a result of what we're doing,<br />
inviting Aboriginals to make these claims in all States.<br />
Let me say in regard to the Northern Territory, it's not a<br />
question of invitation, the claims have been there. They<br />
don't need an invitation as a result of Marshall Perron<br />
coming down here and talking to Bob Hawke. The claims have<br />
been there and they're a fact of political life for some<br />
period of time. So the concept we're now inviting them to<br />
make claims, with respect, as is often the case with you,<br />
portrays an ignorance of the facts. The facts are there and<br />
solid. The claims exist. What we've been dealing with is a<br />
method of having a process of dealing with claims that<br />
exist. So, it's not a question of invitation there or<br />
anywhere else.<br />
JOURNALIST: Could you elaborate on why it's taken so long<br />
to resolve these negotiations and, in-particular, why the<br />
proposal for voluntary agreements on living areas didn't<br />
succeed and your concerns about eligibility criteria for<br />
applications for living areas?<br />
PERRON: Well, you've asked a question which would really<br />
probably require, in fact, the 20 odd hours of negotiations<br />
it's taken to resolve in the final form, to answer. Your<br />
first question was why has it taken so long. The matters<br />
are enormously complex. They're also enormously politically<br />
sensitive and they have a very long history to them as well<br />
of things that were said and done and undertaken years ago<br />
by various parties. As a result of those things that have<br />
. been said and done and not done, other parties have locked<br />
themselves into various positions. we've made no secret of<br />
the fact that we have long believed that, had the<br />
Commonwealth commenced the admendments to Section 50 of the<br />
Land Rights Act in mid, I think, ' 87 when they were passed,<br />
then we wouldn't, this matter wouldn't have taken so long.<br />
However, I'm sure the Commonwealth have another view of that<br />
. and other parties felt that had Section 50 been commenced<br />
then something else would have come off the rails. So, I </p>
<p>-8-<br />
don't claim responsibility for all that period because<br />
unfortunately I wasn't in charge of negotiations, or perhaps<br />
fortunately, I don't know. But for whatever reasons, it's<br />
been very long and slow in coming. I regret that, the<br />
Commonwealth certainly does and so do the Aboriginals. So<br />
the important thing is we're here today, having reached an<br />
agreement, and we're going to proceed as fast as we can.<br />
Now your question of eligibility. Obviously eligibility was<br />
one of the crucial matters to be determined finally between<br />
the respective parties. It was important, I believe, to<br />
indicate that we weren't talking about a process of land<br />
claims under traditional attachment, a la the Aboriginal<br />
Land Rights Act because that's not what we're talking about<br />
and you won't find that embodied in the document that we've<br />
both signed. But we are however, providing for a system of<br />
claims to land by persons of particular eligibility and<br />
there are particular requirements about what can be claimed<br />
and there's criteria on that end of the scale as well. So<br />
these matters are all very important and had to be picked<br />
over piece by piece. They have been and we've resolved them<br />
all. JOURNALIST: you said before that there's one aspect<br />
less than ideal. Which specifically are those matters?<br />
PERRON: Well, I'm obviously not going to run through what<br />
the Commonwealth decided to let slide and what the Territory<br />
Government decided to let slide, but clearly if you've had a<br />
disagreement for at least four years and, in fact, the<br />
disagreements go back, if I recall, possibly even pre the<br />
Labor Government, Federal Government, then obviously to<br />
reach an agreement in the end, someone's got to give. What<br />
I'm saying is that it wasn't one side-who gave in this<br />
exercise, it was both sides. Had both sides not given,<br />
well, we'd be sitting back perhaps for another four years<br />
throwing stones at each other.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, Mr Perron the need for<br />
additional funding to flow through to the Northern Territory<br />
once excisions are settled, will the Commonwealth be<br />
injecting more funds in the Northern Territory for basic<br />
services like housing<br />
PM: Let me say this. As far as we're concerned and Mr<br />
Perron, of course, he should and would speak for himself,<br />
but as far as we're concerned this is as I've put. The<br />
precondition for addressing the conditions that we've<br />
referred to under which these people live. As far as we're<br />
concerned now having resolved that precondition of title,<br />
then it will be the attitude of my Government that we should<br />
give very special attention to taking advantage of the fact<br />
that we've cleared that hurdle and address as effectively as<br />
we can the provision of facilities. Now in all these<br />
things, this is a matter of coordination between our two<br />
Governments. I gather from the discussions that we've had<br />
that Mr-Perron would share that view, but he obviously can<br />
speak for himself. </p>
<p>-9-<br />
PERRON: Well like most, just to say briefly not to hold<br />
people up on this issue, but most of Governments' problems,<br />
I guess, in meeting the aspirations of constituents can be<br />
boiled back to money problems. There never seems to be<br />
enough of it, of course, for any of us for any of the<br />
purposes we're here for. There are very substantial sums<br />
that flow into the provision of services and housing to<br />
Aborigines in the Territory and no doubt across the country.<br />
However, if we are going to fairly quickly escalate the<br />
amount of land which requires housing and services, well<br />
then it is going to require some more funds. I'm not using<br />
this public forum to put the on the Prime minister. It<br />
will be dealt with through the budgetary process of course<br />
and the Commonwealth will make its decisions at the time.<br />
But I guess I need to point out that most of the Territory<br />
Government's funds flow from the Commonwealth, as you're<br />
probably aware, and it's not simply a matter of us saying<br />
' well we'll find another $ 5 or $ 10 or $ 20 million per annum<br />
or $ 50 million per annum from Territory sources'. We don't<br />
have the powers of the States, we don't have the tax raising<br />
abilities of the States because of our limited powers and so<br />
we rightly turn to the Commonwealth<br />
PM: I'm sure that I'll be hearing from Mr Hand on this<br />
issue. JOURNALIST: The agreement, as it relates to stock routes,<br />
the Commonwealth's been worried about Aborigines who had<br />
claims on stock routes and wouldn't be eligible for<br />
excisions once the stock routes weren't claimable any more.<br />
Are all of those groups covered by this?<br />
PM: In regard to the stock routes which has been agreed<br />
between us will be a matter handled tinder the Commonwealth<br />
legislation. we have agreed that there will be full<br />
consultation between the Commonwealth and the Northern<br />
Territory to deal with the There's a mass of<br />
applications there as you know. I mean, I was just amazed<br />
when I saw the map and extent of them, the spread of them.<br />
Now, on dealing with all those which are now established,<br />
then there's going to be a consideration under the terms of<br />
our discussion of what are appropriate. There are some that<br />
will, may have lapsed because of the range of circumstances,<br />
but we will consult with the Northern Territory and then<br />
once those decisions are made in regard to those claims,<br />
then the essence of the agreement is the proclamation of<br />
so that that means that that is the end of the issue.<br />
JOURNALIST: Chief minister, how long has it been since<br />
these stock routes were in fact used as stock routes? The<br />
nineteenth century, 50 years?<br />
PERRON: I think some of them have been used more recently<br />
in short segments, but it's true that the great cattle<br />
drives -of the last century, which was the reason they were<br />
originally put in for, there haven't been many of those<br />
since the one we ran for the Bicentennial of course. </p>
<p>But the facts are that they are not part of a pastoral<br />
lease, they're an area excised from the pastoral lease at<br />
the time the pastoral lease is granted. They are Crown land<br />
and the history of the matter of stock routes arose because<br />
the challenge to the High Court that they were not<br />
claimable, should not be claimable under the Land Rights<br />
Act, ruled that they were claimable and that that presented<br />
special difficulties for everybody because in some cases<br />
they divide pastoral properties in three, in many cases in<br />
two. However, they were claimable under the Land Rights Act<br />
and the Land Councils claimed them, as was their right.<br />
What we have here now is a negotiated settlement for a<br />
portion of stock routes not to have to go through the land<br />
claim process to be directly scheduled to the Land Rights<br />
Act. Following a period of consultation with the Territory,<br />
an examination of the applicants and their meeting a certain<br />
criteria and that will be balanced. Land that is scheduled<br />
on stock routes will be balanced with excisions on<br />
neighbouring pastoral leases. So, it's not a matter of<br />
everybody sort of doubling up, as it were. In some cases<br />
Aboriginal claimants may well prefer a piece of land off a<br />
stock route for various reasons and they may drop a claim on<br />
a stock route, obviously they don't get both. That's our<br />
agreement between us, is designed to look at stock routes<br />
and excisions on pastoral leases virtually concurrently.<br />
PM: That's right.<br />
JOURNALIST: From any decade these stock routes have been,<br />
have functioned as parts of the, as a part of the pastoral<br />
leases that surround them?<br />
PERRON: Yes.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, if I could just raise another issue?<br />
PM: Is it about this subject?<br />
JOURNALIST: No, it's about<br />
PM: No, you can't. Didn't you hear what I said at the<br />
beggining? when this is concluded, then it will be open.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Perron said earlier that the significance of<br />
this deal is that it's taking title away from generally<br />
white pastoralists and granting it to Aboriginal people.<br />
The question to you, Prime minister, is given that you've<br />
pulled something as tricky as that off, is there any chance<br />
of you dusting off the treaty proposal?<br />
PM: Well, I don't accept the language that you use about<br />
dusting off the treaty proposal. The position there is that<br />
the minister is in the process, and has been for some time,<br />
of conducting discussions and trying to get a mechanism for<br />
ascertaining the views of the Aboriginal people. He's also<br />
looking-at the issue of how we may also try and get ideas<br />
from the non-Aboriginal community. </p>
<p>-11-<br />
Now, I have reports from the Minister on occasion he<br />
says ' well, there is where we are and where we're going' and<br />
I expect that that process is going to continue. It has<br />
not, at any point, been put in a pigeon-hole or a back-box<br />
at all. We have the two questions there are a whole<br />
number of other issues which have had to involve, including<br />
this The predominant attention of the Minister, and of<br />
course, the whole process of moving to set up the ATSIC<br />
structure, now that hasn't meant that the other's been<br />
forgotten but there is a limit to the amount of time that<br />
you've-been able to give to this. But it is still very much<br />
on the table and it's my hope that the processes will evolve<br />
in a way which will enable the minister to come to me and<br />
say ' well here is the concept from the Aboriginal people as<br />
to what they would wish to see' and contemporanously, I<br />
hope, we'll be able to have the idea discussed in the<br />
non-Aboriginal community and then the issue can be dealt<br />
with. By definition, as I've said always, this is not<br />
something which will lend itself to an imposed arbitrary<br />
sort of process. The essence is that we get an<br />
understanding on both sides of what it should be about.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, at Burunga you indicated that<br />
you'd like to get the treaty in place by the end of the life<br />
of the current Parliament. Is that still your aim?<br />
PM: Well, that was my aspiration. I would have to say the<br />
processes, it would appear, are going to take longer than<br />
that. I would liked to have got it by the end of this<br />
Parliament. Realistically now I'd say that that is not<br />
possible, but there has been no lessening in my commitment<br />
or that of my Minister on this issue. Now, I don't want to<br />
be difficult about cutting off questions on this issue, but<br />
I imagine that there are other issuei you want to talk about<br />
and I do have to get in the Parliament, so<br />
0 JOURNALIST: One more question<br />
PM: No, you've had three and they were pretty poor at any<br />
rate. Yes?<br />
JOURNALIST: in relation to Yambah station<br />
PERRON: Yes.<br />
JOURNALIST: The people that are sitting outside the Supreme<br />
Court in Darwin today. Would you they'd rather be<br />
sitting on their own land. How does this help them and what<br />
would you say to them today?<br />
PERRON: I believe what we've done in the last 24 hours will<br />
help them. Yambah is a particuarly complex case, even<br />
within complex cases. That's acknowledged by all parties,<br />
Land Councils, Aboriginal Affairs, Departments, Commonwealth<br />
Offices and Territory Offices. It's going to require some<br />
special attention by a number of senior people, possibly </p>
<p>-12-<br />
including myself and the Federal Minister for Aboriginal<br />
Affairs, to try and carefully resolve. I can't go into much<br />
more detail than that, but I think that the agreements that<br />
we've reached to date providing for a special form of<br />
Territory title, providing for scheduling of land to stock<br />
routes because there are stock routes running through<br />
Yambah. In fact, some of the Aborigines are camped on<br />
stock routes as well as those who are camped on the station<br />
itself and so I think that the, a resolution to that problem<br />
is in sight, but it may take a little while yet and a lot of<br />
talking and, hopefully, goodwill.<br />
ends<br />
0 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
