<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5492</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER INTERVIEWED BY JIM BONNER ON ABC&#039;S &#039;AM&#039;</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/12/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005492.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS OFFICE TRANSCRIPT WEDNESDAY, 3 DECEMBER, 1980<br />
PRIME MINISTER INTERVIEWED BY JIM BONNER ON ABC'S " AM"<br />
Steve Cosser<br />
In Federal Parliament yesterday, the Leader of the Oppositi on<br />
called on the Prime minister to review the classification of<br />
secret documents in light of Monday's ruling in the High Court<br />
against the Federal Government's injunction which sought to<br />
prevent the publication of the book " Documents on Australian<br />
Defence and Foreign Policy, 1968-75". The Prime Minister was<br />
urged to prevent current guidelines being used as a device<br />
to stop discussion and criticism of Government policy. However,<br />
in this exclusive interview with Jim Bonner, Mr. Fraser<br />
defended the Government's action.<br />
Prime Minister<br />
We weren't trying to protect any secrets that might have been<br />
made, or any arrangements that have been developed over the<br />
last five years, because they were mostly documents of the<br />
Labor years. And so we were acting out of a basis of principle.<br />
Quite obviously any Government needs to be examining what it<br />
is doing, needs to be making sure that various security<br />
classifications are used with discretion. I would hope that<br />
that is a continuing process. But there is a great deal of<br />
material.-advice on sensitive matters from Departments to<br />
Ministers, especially of Foreign Affairs and Defence, or the<br />
Prime Minister which must be handled with discretion;<br />
involving security material, conduct of relationships between<br />
different countries. It is just not good enough to think that<br />
these things can be published without doing harm to relations<br />
between countries.<br />
Bonner-But some of those documents in that particular book go back<br />
to 1968 when there would have been a Liberal/ National Country<br />
Party Government in power.<br />
Prime Minister<br />
A few of them do. They were not documents of this particular<br />
Government. The main documents, the ones that had most interest,<br />
would have been the more recent ones which were prepared and<br />
developed in the 1972 to 1975 years. There is almost a view<br />
that some people seem to have that there is not only a right but<br />
almost a moral obligation to publish everything that people<br />
can lay their hands on about the activities and about the affairs<br />
of Government. I will be amongst the first to concede that full<br />
public disclosure of what Governments are doing, to the maximum<br />
extent, is a good thing. But when you come into this area of<br />
foreign affairs and defence, where relationships between other<br />
people as individuals, as Ministers, as Heads' of Government<br />
where just the relationship between countries is involved you<br />
cannot have the sort of communication you need if you are going to do<br />
it through the front pages of the newspapers. ./ 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
Bonner But it does seem that apart from the instances that you have<br />
given that the bureacracy, the public service, is holding<br />
information that doesn't come into those categories. It has<br />
been classified ' secret' unnecessarily. Do you agree witIh that?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
You have got to look at the circumstances at the time. when<br />
the documents were devised. I do not particularly want to<br />
criticise the classifications that were put on the documents in<br />
those Labor years. The classifications were there. They were<br />
dealing with sensitive matters involving relationships between<br />
Governments. I was a little bit concerned to hear on " AM" a<br />
suggestion that certain things would not be published and this<br />
came from a former senior public servant he indicated that<br />
the previous Government had made a decision that certain things<br />
would not be published merely because they would be some<br />
advantage to the then Opposition. Well, that is not a principle<br />
that I have ever stated. That is not the basis on which matters<br />
ought to be published or ought not to be published.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
