<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7475</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER LUNCHEON OF KOREAN BUSINESS ASSOCIATIONS &quot;REGIONAL CO-OPERATION: CHALLENGES FOR KOREA AND AUSTRALIA&quot; KOREA - 31 JANUARY 1989+</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>31/01/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007475.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
LUNCHEON OF KOREAN BUSINESS ASSOCIATIONS<br />
" REGIONAL CO-OPERATION:<br />
CHALLENGES FOR KOREA AND AUSTRALIA"<br />
KOREA 31 JANUARY 1989<br />
Australia and Korea lie near the northern and southern<br />
extremities of the most dynamically growing region in the<br />
world: the Asia Pacific region.<br />
This regIon generates more than one third of the world's<br />
trade, and is likely in the next decade to create more than<br />
half the world's economic output.<br />
This extraordinary growth gives nations such as ours<br />
tremendous opportunities and new responsibilities.<br />
Whether we can fulfill the predictions of those who see us<br />
entering a ' Pacific Century', with all that would mean for<br />
rising living standards for our people, is in our own hands.<br />
But these opportunities cannot fully be exploited unless we<br />
are prepared, as individual nations and as a region, to do<br />
the hard work that will be involved.<br />
Today I want to discuss one focus for that work: how we as a<br />
region can better cooperate so that our future, individually<br />
and regionally, is a secure and prosperous one.<br />
First I want to pay tribute to your own spectacular<br />
achievements in Korea.<br />
When I came here last in 1984, I commented on the rapid<br />
economic progress you were making.<br />
Today, five years later, I find that not only have you<br />
managed to maintain the pace oE economic progress, you have<br />
also undertaken very welcome political reforms.<br />
This combination of economic dynamism and emergent democratic<br />
processes so vividly and magnificently encapsulated in the<br />
Seoul. Olylmpics last yeat is justifiably pushing the<br />
Republic of Korea into a more prominent place on the world<br />
stage. </p>
<p>Indeed it is no wonder that Korea will, before the turn of<br />
the century, join the ranks of the developed nations a<br />
transition that will bring new responsibilities as part of<br />
your integration into the global political and economic<br />
system.<br />
As part of all this, Australia and Korea have built a very<br />
successful bilateral trade relationship.<br />
We are each among the eight most important trading partners<br />
of the other.<br />
Two way trade in 1987/ 88 was valued at almost $ A3 billion.<br />
over the last five years the trend rate of growth of<br />
Australia's exports to the ROK has been over 16 per cent per<br />
annum, while for imports it has been over 29 per cent per<br />
annum. This is spectacular growth.<br />
S There are excellent prospects for further expansion. Last<br />
year my Government released a Korean Trade and Commercial<br />
Development Program as a means to develop further Australia's<br />
relationship with the Republic of Korea.<br />
In addition I am pleased that we have an in-principle<br />
agreement to negotiate a protocol to the Australia-Korea<br />
Bilateral Trade Agreement which was originally signed in<br />
1965. 1 look forward to its early finalisation because it<br />
will help both our countries identity and promote areas which<br />
will expand our bilateral trade and commercial interests.<br />
Australia enjoys excellent relations with Korea, the<br />
countries of North East Asia and the Asia Pacific region as a<br />
whole. About two-thirds of Australia's exports and imports<br />
are directed to or sourced from our regional neighbours.<br />
About half of the total foreign investment in Australia has<br />
come from the Asia-Pacific region and almost three--fifths of<br />
~ Australia's total investment overseas is located within the<br />
Wregion. So we are keenly aware that the economic growth and<br />
structural change taking place in North East Asia, in<br />
particular, will have vital implications for us as well as<br />
our region and the wider international economy.<br />
With this in mind we have asked Dr Ross Garnaut, our former<br />
Ambassador to China, to review the Australian response to<br />
these changes. Dr Garnaut is one of our most distinguished<br />
economists and a person closely associated with public<br />
policy. His study will analyse and report on North East Asian changes<br />
over recent years and prospectively through to the end of<br />
this century and beyond. It will identify areas where our<br />
country can co-operate with you and other regional countries<br />
for mutual economic, political and wider benefits. </p>
<p>Dr Garnaut will be coming to Seoul in April arid proposes to<br />
discuss these : issues with Government and business leaders. I<br />
hope that these discussions, and the subsequent report, will<br />
be of value to Korean decision makers as it obviously will be<br />
to those in Australia.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen,<br />
If one had to isolate the single key factor underpinning the<br />
growth of all the dynamically performing nations of the<br />
region, it would surely be their capacity to take advantage<br />
of a relatively open and non-discriminatory international<br />
trading system.<br />
The multilateral system of gi6bal trade, under the auspices<br />
of the GATT, has provided more than four decades of growth<br />
for the world's economies.<br />
O North Asian economies, as major exporters, are enjoying<br />
growth rates much greater than the OECD average.<br />
Given this centrality of trade to our region, we have cause<br />
for concern about our economic future.<br />
Serious cracks are appearing in the international trading<br />
system which have major implications for the future health of<br />
both our region and the world economy.<br />
First, you will all be aware of the bilateral trade pressures<br />
associated with the significant trade imbalances between a<br />
number of regional countries and the United States.<br />
Second, there is a trend towards the formation of bilateral<br />
or regional trading arrangements which run the risk of<br />
undermnining a truly multilateral trading system.<br />
Third, there are fundamental tensions within the GATT<br />
framnework of multilateral trade, of which the recent Montreal<br />
deadlock is but the latest manifestation.<br />
Each of these problems has prompted calls for some sort of<br />
regional action.<br />
But they are not the only driving forces behind calls for<br />
closer regional ties.<br />
It has long been recognised especially as the region's<br />
economic importance continues to grow that the countries in<br />
the region are essentially interdependent; our economic<br />
futures are interlinked.<br />
That realisation led in 1980 to the creation of the Pacific<br />
Economic Co-operation Conference PECC of which Australia<br />
was a co-founder and of which we remain a consistent<br />
supporter. </p>
<p>PECC's work has illuminated large areas of common interests<br />
within the region.<br />
But its informality, which has helped to broaden its<br />
membership, has also made it difficult for it to address<br />
policy issues which are properly the responsibility of<br />
Governments. We have heard more recent proposals for new and closer<br />
regional consultations from both sides of the Pacific.<br />
Former Japanese Prime Minister Nakasone has put forward a<br />
suggestion for a Pacific Forum for Economic and Cultural<br />
Co-operation.<br />
Former US Secretary of State, George Shultz, canvassed the<br />
need for a Pacific intergovernmental forum to encourage<br />
Sco-operation in specific sectors.<br />
More recently, US Senator Bill Bradley has proposed a Pacific<br />
coalition on trade and economic development designed to<br />
reinforce the Uruguay Round and remove barriers to economic<br />
growth in the region.<br />
There have also been calls for various kinds of free trade<br />
areas in the Pacific, including one between the US and Japan.<br />
These different proposals have in common the perception that,<br />
as a region, we do have interests that can be advanced<br />
through greater consultation and co-operation.<br />
I believe the time has come for us substantially to increase<br />
our efforts towards building regional co-operation and<br />
seriously to investigate what areas it might focus on and<br />
what forms it might take.<br />
SThat is why Australia has recently launched a substantial and<br />
concerted diplomatic effort.<br />
We have asked our missions in the region to gauge opinion<br />
within the region about how best to push forward our regional<br />
co-operation.<br />
Senior Australian Ministers held constructive talks on this<br />
issue with the Japanese leadership earlier this week.<br />
We want to assess what the region's attitudes are towards the<br />
possibility of creating a more formal intergovernmental<br />
vehicle of regional co-operation.<br />
A meeting of ministers from throughout the region would be a<br />
useful forum to investigate the question. </p>
<p>What we are seeking to develop is a capacity for analysis and<br />
consultation on economic and social issues, not as an<br />
academic exercise but to help inform policy development by<br />
our respective governments.<br />
I see merit in the model provided, in a different context, by<br />
the OECD.<br />
I discussed these issues yesterday with President Roh, who is<br />
of course the leader of a major regional economy one of t he<br />
economies whose involvement would be vital to the success of<br />
any new regional institution.<br />
I regard it as a significant step forward that President Roh<br />
gave his support to the proposals and expressed his<br />
enthusiasm for pursuing them throlugh further regional<br />
consultation.<br />
OLet me spell out three areas in which I believe the<br />
Asia-Pacific region could profit from closer co-operation<br />
through such an institution.<br />
First, effective regional co-operation can greatly improve<br />
the chances of success of the Uruguay Round and could thereby<br />
give a vital boost to the liberalisation and therefore the<br />
preservation of the GATT-based trading system.<br />
The GATT system now faces its most crucial test. The<br />
Montreal impasse, essentially due to lack of progress on<br />
trade liberalisation in agriculture, must be overcome. If<br />
the Uruguay round fails, the underlying tensions which will<br />
have caused this failure will corrode the essence of the GATT<br />
system.<br />
We must work together to save the GATT system. The region's<br />
role will be critical given its strong growth, reliance on<br />
trade and growing world importance and responsibility.<br />
In 1983, in recognition of the importance of the<br />
liberalisation of multilateral trade, I proposed a process of<br />
regional consultations on these issues.<br />
The most recent meeting was held in Wellington last year,<br />
just prior to the Montreal Mid-term review. It was<br />
successful in providing a better understanding of the<br />
interests and concerns of regional countries in the<br />
multilateral negotiations.<br />
I am pleased that Korea has been participating in that<br />
process and look forward to further regional consultations<br />
this year.<br />
NN0N0N931 </p>
<p>At the same time, regional co-operation could lead to a<br />
better understanding of, and a close monitoring of, the<br />
impact of international economic developments, including the<br />
1992 integration of Europe and the recent US/ Canada Free<br />
Trade Agreement.<br />
Australia and Japan are currently undertaking a study of the<br />
potential regional impact of these new blocs. Because this<br />
study will, I believe, be of relevance and importance beyond<br />
our two countries, Prime Minister Takeshita and I will be<br />
discussing how best to familiarise other countries with its<br />
findings.<br />
Second, we must be prepared openly to discuss obstacles to<br />
trade within our region.<br />
From Australia's point of view, the success of the newly<br />
industrialising economies is an enormous opportunity, for us<br />
and for the whole region.<br />
Others see this very success as a threat, and it has led to<br />
frictions in trade relations within the region and beyond.<br />
There is undoubtedly room for dialogue and cooperation on<br />
this issue.<br />
Australia's view is that the essence of a properly<br />
functioning trading system is, of course, that countries<br />
should seek multilateral trade balance, not bilateral balance<br />
with all countries.<br />
Equally, we believe the newly industrialising countries have<br />
a responsibility to liberalise further their own markets to<br />
reflect their phenomenal growth in trade and investment.<br />
And where such liberalisation occurs, it must not be used to<br />
Slacate trade frictions being encountered with certain<br />
countries. This is anathema to the principles of free trade,<br />
and only invites counter-retaliation by those third countries<br />
whose interests are damaged.<br />
As a region we must investigate the scope for further<br />
dismantling of barriers to trade within the region,<br />
consistent with the GATT framework.<br />
It is a noteworthy source of opportunity that each of us has<br />
tended to impose the greatest barriers to trade in areas in<br />
which regional partners are most competitive.<br />
Some progress has been made in this area. In Korea, for<br />
example, we recognise and appreciate reforms which have<br />
lowered tariffs, liberalised imports and reduced restrictions<br />
on foreign traders. </p>
<p>We give the Korean Government high credit for this and look<br />
forward to further dismantling of barriers to trade and<br />
investment, including in agriculture in which the problems of<br />
trade barriers are greatest.<br />
The recommendations of your recent Presidential Commission on<br />
Economic Restructuring, if implemented, would be a worthw~ hile<br />
move towards a more open Korean market.<br />
in Australia, we have implemented a range of reforms to<br />
liberalise our economy. We are intent on continuing this<br />
process and the reforms to date are already providing new<br />
opportunities for countries such as Korea.<br />
We have floated the Australian dollar, deregulated our<br />
financial markets, liberalised our foreign investment policy,<br />
cut the rate of company taxation, reduced by a third the<br />
level of tariff protection afforded to Australian<br />
manufacturing industry, and made our primary industries more<br />
responsive to changes in the international market place.<br />
The third area in which we could benefit from regional<br />
cooperation is through identifying the broad economic<br />
interests we have in common. We should try to investigate<br />
whether through co-ordinated Policy making we might better<br />
capitalise on the extraordinary complementarity of the<br />
economies in the region.<br />
Australia's Industry Minister, Senator Button, has, for<br />
example, just this week cited the enormous benefits we can<br />
reap from harnessing our diverse science and technology<br />
research efforts.<br />
Surely this is an area in which we should assess our<br />
capabilities to see where we can boost each other's efforts<br />
in this crucial field.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen,<br />
I have already referred to the regional trading consultations<br />
I initiated in 1983, and to the valuable work of PECC.<br />
Bilateral exchanges such as my visit to Korea and that of<br />
President Roh to Australia last year form valuable avenues of<br />
co-operation. Studies such as Dr Garnaut's inquiry into<br />
North East Asia, and the joint Japanese Australian inquiry<br />
into the impact of the trading blocs will provide valuable<br />
information with which to guide our future decisions.<br />
But Ii believe we should be striving for a more effective<br />
means of analysis of and consultation on the central issue we<br />
face as a region.<br />
Before I leave this topic, I must stress that my support for<br />
a more formal vehicle for regional co-operation must not be<br />
interpreted as suggesting by code words the creation of a<br />
Pacific trading bloc. </p>
<p>Australia's support for non-discriminatory multilateral<br />
trading solutions in the GATT framework is clear,<br />
long-standing and unambiguous.<br />
I have made it clear that a major priority of any regional<br />
effort would be the strengthening of the GATT system.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen,<br />
Australia attaches particular significance to our<br />
relationship with Korea. We would like to work with you, not<br />
just in developing our bilateral ties, but also in developing<br />
our mutual interests and opportunities in third countries.<br />
The Asia Pacific region is at a pivotal point in history.<br />
And the region is located at a pivotal point in the global<br />
economy.<br />
We have much to offer each other. We have substantial shared<br />
political and economic interests, and a powerful<br />
complementarity in our economic skills, resources, and<br />
business, cultural, and political links.<br />
Co-operation offers the region the opportunity to influence<br />
the course of multilateral trade liberalisation, avoid<br />
alternative approaches which would undermine this objective<br />
and enable us to enter the next century with confidence that<br />
our potential will be fulfilled.<br />
I I </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
