<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6799</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, CEDA SILVER JUBILEE COMMEMORATIVE DINNER, &#039;AUSTRALIA&#039;S POLICIES FOR CONTINUING ECONOMIC GROWTH&#039;, SYDNEY, 4 DECEMBER 1985</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/12/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006799.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
CEDA SILVER JUBLILEE COMMEMORATIVE DINNER<br />
" AUSTRALIA'S POLICIES FOR CONTINUING ECONOMIC GROWTH"<br />
SYDNEY 4 DECEMBER 1985<br />
TONIGHT WE CELEBRATE 25 YEARS OF SUSTAINED ACHIEVEMENT BY<br />
THE COMMITTEE FOR THE ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT OF AUSTRALIA.<br />
DURING THESE TWENTY FIVE YEARS CEDA HAS CONTRIBUTED<br />
SIGNIFICANTLY AND CONSTRUCTIVELY TO THE PUBLIC DEBATE OF<br />
ECONOMIC POLICY IN THIS COUNTRY.<br />
IF HE WERE ALIVE TODAY, I HAVE NO DOUBT THAT SIR DOUGLAS<br />
COPLAND, A DISTINGUISHED AUSTRALIAN ECONOMIST AND FOUNDER OF<br />
CEDA, WOULD TAKE GREAT PRIDE IN THE SERVICE WHICH CEDA HAS<br />
DONE FOR THIS COUNTRY.<br />
SIR DOUGLAS, WITH WHOM I HAD THE HONOUR OF WORKING IN MY<br />
CAPACITY AS ACTU ADVOCATE IN THE EARLY 1960' S, ARGUED<br />
FORCEFULLY IN FAVOUR OF THE INVOLVEMENT OF THE COMMUNITY IN<br />
THE FORMATION OF PUBLIC POLICY A SENTIMENT WHICH, AS YOU<br />
KNOW, I STRONGLY SHARE.<br />
IN MANY RESPECTS CEDA'S TWENTY-FIVE YEARS HAVE SEEN QUITE<br />
MARKED CHANGES IN AUSTRALIA'S ECONOMIC AND SOCIAL<br />
ENVIRONMENT. IN 1960, FOR EXAMPLE, THE COMMUNICATIONS REVOLUTION HAD NOT<br />
BEGUN FUNDAMENTALLY TO CHANGE OUR SOCIETY. THE TELEVISION<br />
INDUSTRY IN AUSTRALIA WAS IN ITS INFANCY AND COMPUTERS<br />
FILLED ROOMS, NOT BRIEFCASES.<br />
THE POST-WAR BABY BOOMERS ( WHICH MOST OF US HERE EITHER<br />
CONTRIBUTED TO OR ARE A PRODUCT OF) WERE JUST STARTING TO<br />
ENTER HIGH SCHOOLS. THEIR IMPACT ON THE WORKFORCE, FASHION<br />
AND SOCIAL MORES WAS STILL SOME YEARS HENCE.<br />
MOREOVER, RELATIVELY FEW WOMEN COUNTED THEMSELVES IN THE<br />
FULL-TIME PAID WORKFORCE.<br />
IN THE WORLD OF FINANCE, THE FORCES IMPINGING UPON THE<br />
INTERNATIONAL FINANCIAL SYSTEM WERE SUFFICIENTLY TRANQUIL<br />
THAT EXCHANGE RATES WERE FIXED; AND THE DOMESTIC FINANCIAL<br />
SYSTEM WAS DOMINATED BY BANKS AND FIXED INTEREST RATES. </p>
<p>AND EVEN AFTER POST-WAR RECONSTRUCTION AND THE ATTEMPTED<br />
MODERNISATION OF AUSTRALIAN INDUSTRY, BEHIND A VERITABLE<br />
WALL OF PROTECTION AGRICULTURAL PRODUCTS STILL ACCOUNTED<br />
FOR THE LARGEST SHARE OF OUR EXPORTS. THE MINING INDUSTRY<br />
WAS YET TO EXPERIENCE THE RAPID EXPANSION THAT OCCURRED<br />
LATER IN THE DECADE.<br />
OVER THE LATTER PART OF THE FIFTIES THE GEOGRAPHICAL PATTERN<br />
OF OUR TRADE HAD BEGUN TO SWING AWAY FROM EUROPE TOWARDS<br />
JAPAN AND SOUTH AND SOUTH-EAST ASIA BUT MOST OF THAT<br />
REORIENTATION WAS STILL TO COME.<br />
FINALLY, THROUGH THE COURSE OF THE 19601S AND 1970' S<br />
AGRICULTURAL AND TECHNOLOGICAL REVOLUTIONS SPREAD STEAD ' ILY<br />
BEYOND THE SHORES OF THE INDUSTRIALISED COUNTRIES. AS A<br />
RESULT, AS TIME PASSED, MORE AND MORE OF OUR NEAR-NEIGHBOURS<br />
BEGAN TO COMPETE EFFECTIVELY WITH US IN OUR TRADITIONAL<br />
MARKETS. IN MANY RESPECTS THESE DEVELOPMENTS VERY MUCH PROVIDE THE<br />
BACKDROP TO THE CHALLENGES WHICH NOW FACE'AUSTRALIA. THESE<br />
INCLUDE THE CHALLENGE TO CREATE LONG-TERM AND PRODUCTIVE<br />
JOBS, NOT ONLY TO EMPLOY THE EXPANDING WORKFORCE, BUT ALSO<br />
TO REDUCE PROGRESSIVELY THE LEVEL OF UNEMPLOYMENT WHICH WE<br />
INHERITED; THE CHALLENGE TO KEEP OUR INDUSTRIAL STRUCTURE<br />
RELEVANT TO THE NEEDS OF WORLD TRADE AND STEADY GROWTH; AND<br />
THE CHALLENGE TO ADJUST TO THE VOLATILITY OF MOVEMENTS IN<br />
INTEREST RATES AND THE EXCHANGE RATE UNDER A FLOATING DOLLAR<br />
AND FINANCIAL DEREGULATION.<br />
THESE FUNDAMENTAL CHALLENGES PROVIDE'THE PRIMARY FOCUS OF<br />
THE GOVERNMENT'S ECONOMIC STRATEGY.<br />
IT IS IMPORTANT, IN MY VIEW, FOR US AS A COMMUNITY TO ACCEPT<br />
THAT THE PACE OF AUSTRALIA'S ECONOMIC GROWTH AT LEAST<br />
UNTIL VERY RECENTLY HAS BEEN POOR BY W0I9LD STANDARDS; AND<br />
CERTAINLY POOR COMPARED WITH OUR POTENTIAL. IN PARTICULAR<br />
THE SEVENTIES BECAME THE ERA OF STAGFLATION AND RISING<br />
UNEMPLOYMENT. WE CAN LOOK BACK AND SEE MISSED OPPORTUNITIES. WE CAN ALSO<br />
SEE A PERIOD IN WHICH THE FOUNDATIONS FOR SUSTAINED GROWTH<br />
WERE WEAKENED IN SOME IMPORTANT RESPECTS.<br />
THE LABOR GOVERNMENT CAME TO OFFICE IN 1983 WITH A<br />
COMMITMENT To INAUGURATE A NEW ERA OF RECONCILIATION IN AND<br />
RECONSTRUCTION OF THE AUSTRALIAN ECONOMY.<br />
WE MOVED QUICKLY AND PURPOSEFULLY TO INITIATE ECONOMIC<br />
RECOVERY AND TO SHORE UP THE FOUNDATIONS OF OUR ECONOMIC<br />
PERFORMANCE SO THAT OUR IMPROVED ECONOMIC GROWTH COULD BE<br />
PRESERVED. I WISH, TONIGHT, TO LOOK BRIEFLY AT SOME OF THESE<br />
FOUNDATIONS AND ASSESS WHERE WE STAND.<br />
LET ME START WITH PEOPLE. </p>
<p>3.<br />
IN A VERY FUNDAMENTAL SENSE, AUSTRALIA'S FUTURE RESTS WITH<br />
OUR PEOPLE, ESPECIALLY OUR YOUNG PEOPLE. YET, IN THE PAST,<br />
DESPITE DEVOTING MASSIVE PUBLIC RESOURCES TO THE FUNDING OF<br />
EDUCATION, TOO LITTLE HAD BEEN ACHIEVED TO DEVELOP MOST<br />
EFFECTIVELY THE POTENTIAL OF THE YOUNG.<br />
COMPARED TO COUNTRIES LIKE THE USA, WEST GERMANY AND JAPAN,<br />
FAR TOO FEW OF OUR YOUNG PEOPLE FINISH EVEN SECONDARY<br />
EDUCATION, AND FEWER STILL PROGRESS TO THE TERTIARY LEVEL.<br />
THE PRESENT GOVERNMENT HAS BEGUN TO ADDRESS THIS CHALLENGE.<br />
WE HAVE MADE A SUBSTANTIAL FINANCIAL COMMITMENT THAT WILL<br />
PRO VIDE AN ASSURED FINANCIAL BASIS FOR THE GROWTH OF OUR<br />
GOVERNMENT AND NON-GOVERNMENT SCHOOLS FOR THE REMAINDER OF<br />
THE DECADE. BUT WE ARE EQUALLY CONCERNED ABOUT IMPROVING<br />
THE QUALITY OF OUR EDUCATION.<br />
DRAWING ON THE RECOMMENDATIONS OF THE KARMEL REPORT WE ARE<br />
AT PRESENT SEEKING THE COOPERATION OF THE STATES TO UPGRADE<br />
THE QUALITY OF EDUCATION OFFERED BY AUSTRALIAN SCHOOLS.<br />
OUR AIM IS THAT RESOURCES SHOULD BE DIRECTED IN SUCH A WAY<br />
AS TO ENSURE THAT SCHOOLS OFFER COURSES WHICH PROVIDE THE<br />
SKILLS NEEDED BY A MODERN DYNAMIC AND FLEXIBLE WORKFORCE.<br />
WE HAVE A SERIES OF PHASED IMPROVEMENTS IN STUDENT<br />
ALLOWANCES IN TRAIN WHICH, OVER TIME, WILL HELP TO REMOVE<br />
ANY EXISTING FINANCIAL INDUCEMENT TO OPT OUT OF EDUCATION<br />
AND INTO AN INITIATIVE-DESTROYING EXISTENCE ON UNEMPLOYMENT<br />
BENEFIT. IN ADDITION WE HAVE INITIATED A PROGRAM OF STRUCTURED<br />
ON-AND-OFF-THE-JOB TRAINING, TARGETTED ESPECIALLY ON YOUNG<br />
PEOPLE WHO LEAVE EDUCATION BEFORE COMPLETING SECONDARY<br />
SCHOOL. THIS IS A RADICAL NEW CHOICE FOR'YOUNG PEOPLE. IT<br />
REPRESENTS A NEW APPROACH TO YOUTH TRAINING WHICH, IN TIME,<br />
WILL PROVIDE SIGNIFICANT OPPORTUNITIES TO IMPROVE THE<br />
LONGER-TERM JOB PROSPECTS OF THE YOUNG UNEMPLOYED.<br />
FURTHERMORE, THE GOVERNMENT WILL BE PROVIDING 85,000<br />
ADDITIONAL TAFE PLACES OVER THE CURRENT TRIENNIUM TO MEET<br />
THE GROWING NEEDS OF STUDENTS.<br />
OF COURSE IT IS ONE THING TO HAVE WELL TRAINED PEOPLE, IT IS<br />
ANOTHER TO USE THEM MOST EFFECTIVELY.<br />
ESSENTIALLY THAT TASK IS ONE FOR MANAGEMENT TO PROVIDE<br />
PROPER CAPITAL TO WORK WITH; TO DEVELOP INITIATIVE AND<br />
FLAIR; AND TO RECOGNISE AND FOSTER TALENT.<br />
BUT GOVERNMENT ALSO HAS A ROLE TO ENSURE THAT THE WORKFORCE<br />
IS MOBILE ENOUGH TO BE ABLE TO SHIFT BETWEEN EMPLOYERS,<br />
INDUSTRIES OR OCCUPATIONS AS THE NEED ARISES.<br />
THE NEED TO DEVELOP A MORE MOBILE WORKFORCE IS A MAJOR<br />
RATIONALE FOR THE EMPHASIS WHICH THE GOVERNMENT HAS PLACED<br />
ON IMPROVING VOCATIONAL PREPARATION IN SCHOOLS AND ON OUR </p>
<p>TRAINEESHIP INITIATIVE FOR YOUNG SCHOOL LEAVERS. BUT THIS<br />
IS COMPLEMENTED BY AN. ADDITIONAL EMPHASIS ON PROGRAMS TO<br />
RETRAIN WORKERS WHO HAVE BEEN OUT OF WORK FOR EXTENDED<br />
PERIODS. IN THE LAST BUDGET WE ANNOUNCED THE INTRODUCTION FROM THE<br />
BEGINNING OF 1986 OF A NEW INTEGRATED WAGE SUBSIDY PROGRAM.<br />
THIS NEW PROGRAM WILL CONSOLIDATE AND RATIONALISE LABOUR<br />
MARKET PROGRAMS THAT SEEK TO MAINTAIN AND IMPROVE OUR SKILLS<br />
BASE. ENHANCED LABOUR-MARKET MOBILITY IS ALSO ONE OF THE POORLY<br />
UNDERSTOOD BENEFITS OF OUR APPROACH TO OCCUPATIONAL<br />
SUPERANNUATION. THE GOVERNMENT'S AGREEMENT WITH THE ACTU TO PROGRESS THE<br />
SPREAD OF OCCUPATIONAL SUPERANNUATION TO THAT HALF OF THE<br />
WORKFORCE NOT NOW COVERED AND IN PARTICULAR To IMPROVE THE<br />
PORTABILITY OF SUPERANNUATION BENEFITS WILL HELP TO REMOVE<br />
ONE OF THE POTENTIAL BARRIERS TO MOVEMENT BETWEEN JOBS OF<br />
MANY EXPERIENCED WORKERS. PREVIOUSLY SOM4E WORKERS COULD<br />
HAVE BEEN DISCOURAGED FROM CHANGING JOBS BECAUSE OF THE LOSS<br />
OF RETIREMENT BENEFITS WHICH WOULD HAVE RESULTED.<br />
LET ME COMMENT BRIEFLY ON SOME ASPECTS OF THE GOVERNMENT'S<br />
APPROACH TO SUPERANNUATION AND ITS LINK WITH THE ACTU'S<br />
PRODUCTIVITY BASED WAGES CLAIM.<br />
FIRST, THE GOVERNMENT'S AGREEMENT WITH THE ACTU CANNOT AND<br />
DOES NOT USURP THE PREROGATIVE OF THE CONCILIATION AND<br />
ARBITRATION COMMISSION TO DETERMINE, IN THE LAST ANALYSIS,<br />
THE SIZE, TIMING AND NATURE OF ANY DIRECT SHARING BY LABOUR<br />
IN IMPROVED PRODUCTIVITY.<br />
RATHER THE GOVERNMENT SUPPORTS THE LEGITIMACY OF THE ACTU'S<br />
CLAIM TO SHARE IN THE BENEFITS FLOWING FROM THE IMPROVED<br />
PRODUCTIVITY IN THE ECONOMY, AND FOR THIS TO BE AVAILABLE IN<br />
THE FORM OF SUPERANNUATION. BUT, HAVING SAID THAT, OUR<br />
SUPPORT IS ALSO FOR A PAYMENT PACKAGE WHICH RECOGNISES THE<br />
OVERRIDING NEEDS OF GENERAL ECONOMIC POLICY FOR MODERATION<br />
IN WAGE INCREASES AND INFLATION.<br />
SECOND, THERE IS NO SENSE IN WHICH THE CONDITIONS ATTACHING<br />
TO OCCUPATIONAL SUPERANNUATION WILL BE FOISTED UPON THE<br />
BUSINESS SECTOR WITHOUT ADEQUATE CONSULTATION.<br />
DRAFT GUIDELINES TO ENSURE THAT SUPERANNUATION IS GENUINE<br />
AND NOT SIMPLY DEFERRED PAY ARE BEING PREPARED AND WILL BE<br />
RELEASED SHORTLY BY THE GOVERNMENT. BUT THEY WILL NOT BE<br />
FINALISED UNTIL THE GOVERNMENT HAS HAD THE OPPORTUNITY TO<br />
LISTEN TO THE VIEWS OF THE BUSINESS SECTOR AND OTHERS IN THE<br />
COMMUNITY. THE TREASURER WILL BE MEETING WITH BUSINESS<br />
REPRESENTATIVES ON THIS SUBJECT NEXT WEEK.<br />
FINALLY, LET ME REITERATE THAT THE GOVERNMENT'S POSITION ON<br />
INDUSTRIAL DISPUTATION IN SUPPORT OF SUPERANNUATION CLAIMS<br />
IS THAT SUCH INDUSTRIAL ACTION IS UNNECESSARY IN TERMS OF<br />
OUR AGREEMENT WITH THE ACTU, AND AS I ANNOUNCED TO THE CAI </p>
<p>LAST WEEK WE WILL NOT SUPPORT IT.<br />
IF I MAY RETURN TO MY MAIN THEME, ANY BUSINESS KNOWS THAT IT<br />
MUST OFFER RELEVANT PRODUCTS IF IT IS TO SURVIVE AND TO<br />
EXPAND. THE AUSTRALIAN ECONOMY IS NO DIFFERENT.<br />
AS I SAID EARLIER IN MY ADDRESS THE PRODUCT MIX OF OUR<br />
EXPORTS HAS CHANGED SIGNIFICANTLY OVER THE PAST TWENTY FIVE<br />
YEARS. THE SHARE OF AGRICULTURAL PRODUCTS IN TOTAL EXPORTS<br />
IS NOW ABOUT HALF THE EARLY 19601S, WITH VIRTUALLY ALL OF<br />
THE DIFFERENCE TAKEN UP IN HIGHER EXPORTS OF MINERALS AND<br />
METALS. THE SO-CALLED RESOURCES BOOM OF THE EARLY 1980' S ADDED<br />
SUBSTANTIALLY TO OUR EXPORT CAPACITY, AND THE MINING SECTOR<br />
HAS CONTRIBUTED IMPORTANTLY TO THE 10 PER CENT GROWTH IN THE<br />
VOLUME OF EXPORTS OVER THE YEAR TO THE SEPTEMBER QUARTER.<br />
BUT IN MANY WAYS THE GROWTH SPURT ASSOCIATED WITH THE<br />
RESOURCES BOOM SIMPLY POSTPONED THE FUNDAMENTAL ADJUSTMENTS<br />
REQUIRED IN AUSTRALIA'S TRADING STRATEGY,<br />
FOR MUCH OF THE POST-WAR PERIOD AUSTRALIA HAS RECEIVED POOR<br />
RETURNS ON ITS EXPORTS.<br />
SO POOR, INDEED, THAT THE VOLUME OF EXPORTS WHICH WE NEED TO<br />
SELL IN ORDER TO BUY A QUANTITY OF IMPORTS HAS RISEN SLOWLY<br />
BUT STEADILY THROUGH TIME.<br />
THIS HAS BEEN A MAJOR FACTOR IN PUTTING PERIODIC UPWARD<br />
PRESSURE ON OUR CURRENT ACCOUNT DEFICIT OR, AT TIMES,<br />
DOWNWARD PRESSURE ON OUR EXCHANGE RATE.<br />
MOST RECENTLY THAT-GENERAL TREND HAS BEEN EXACERBATED BY THE<br />
CONJUNCTION OF A NUMBER OF INFLUENCES ON WORLD MARKETS.<br />
MODERN PRODUCTION PROCESSES ARE NOW FAR MORE ECONOMICAL IN<br />
THEIR USE OF SOME OF OUR MAJOR EXPORTS, AND CLOSELY RELATED<br />
PRODUCTS SUCH AS OIL. THE NATURE OF GOODS DEMANDED IN OUR<br />
TRADITIONAL MARKETS IS ALSO CHANGING WITH THE WEALTHIER<br />
COUNTRIES PREFERRING A RICHER DIET OF SERVICES AND HIGH-TECH<br />
PRODUCTS THAN WAS PREVIOUSLY THE CASE. WE HAVE ALSO<br />
SUFFERED FROM REDUCED ACCESS TO SOME MARKETS, ESPECIALLY FOR<br />
AGRICULTURAL PRODUCTS. IN ADDITION OTHER COUNTRIES,<br />
INCLUDING SOME HEAVILY IN DEBT, HAVE ALSO EXPANDED THE<br />
VOLUME WHICH THEY SUPPLY TO THE MARKET, WHICH HAS FURTHER<br />
DEPRESSED PRICES.<br />
AS A RESULT THE DIVIDEND FROM THE SO-CALLED RESOURCES BOOM<br />
FOR AUSTRALIA'S CURRENT ACCOUNT WAS VERY MUCH LESS, AT THE<br />
EXCHANGE RATE RULING IN 1984-85, THAN HAD BEEN EXPECTED.<br />
WHILE OUR PRICES IN WORLD TRADE SEEM LIKELY TO REMAIN<br />
DEPRESSED FOR A TIME, WE CANNOT COUNT ON A NEW RESOURCES<br />
BOOM TO ADD NEW LIFE TO OUR EXPORTS. BECAUSE WE ARE AMONG<br />
THE MOST EFFICIENT SUPPLIERS IN THE WORLD OF OUR TRADITIONAL<br />
EXPORTS AGRICULTURAL COMMODITIES, MINERALS AND METALS<br />
THESE WILL REMAIN THE MAINSTAY OF OUR EXPORT EFFORT. BUT, </p>
<p>FOR THE LATE 1980' S AND INTO THE 1990' S WE WILL NEED TO DO<br />
MORE THAN IN THE PAST. IN OTHER AREAS PARTICULARLY IN THE<br />
AREAS OF A SUBSTANTIALLY TRANSFORMED MANUFACTURING SECTOR<br />
AND THE SERVICES SECTOR.<br />
THE SPREAD OF ADVANCED TECHNOLOGY TO OUR NEAR NEIGHBOURS HAS<br />
ADDED A NEW DIMENSION TO THIS ADJUSTMENT PROCESS. IT WILL<br />
BE NECESSARY TO CHOOSE OUR AREAS OF SPECIALISATION CAREFULLY<br />
AND, AS A NATION, TO TARGET OUR EFFORT WHERE AUSTRALIAN<br />
PRODUCERS CAN CARVE OUT A NICHE IN THE WORLD# S M4ARKET FOR<br />
NEW OR BETTER PRODUCTS AND SERVICES.<br />
THAT IS A LARGE TASK. BUT NOT ONE, I BELIEVE, WHICH IS<br />
BEYOND US._-<br />
FOR A START THE DEPRECIATION OF THE $ A OVER THE PAST YEAR<br />
HAS IMPROVED THE COMPETITIVENESS OF AUSTRALIAN INDUSTRY BY<br />
ABOUT 20 PER CENT.<br />
AUSTRALIAN FIRMS SHOULD NOW FIND IT VERY MUCH EASIER TO<br />
COMPETE ON PRICE AGAINST IMPORTS OR AGAINST FOREIGN<br />
SUPPLIERS ON EXPORT MARKETS.<br />
THIS IS THE MAJOR REASON WHY THE GOVERNMENT EXPECTS THE<br />
CURRENT ACCOUNT DEFICIT TO IMPROVE OVER THE COURSE OF<br />
1985-86 AND 1986-87.<br />
IT IS SIMPLY INCONCEIVABLE THAT EXISTING PROFITABLE<br />
AUSTRALIAN CONCERNS WOULD NOT BE ABLE TO TAKE ADVANTAGE OF<br />
SO LARGE A SHIFT IN PRICES IN THEIR FAVOUR TO SELL AT THE<br />
EXPENSE OF FOREIGN SUPPLIERS.<br />
BUT THERE IS MORE TO THE GOVERNMENT'S CONFIDENCE THAN THAT<br />
FACTOR ALONE.<br />
OUR WHOLE APPROACH TO ECONOMIC POLICY IS DESIGNED TO CREATE<br />
THE RIGHT ENVIRONMENT FOR BUSINESSES TO DIVERSIFY INTO NEW<br />
AREAS AND EXPAND EXISTING PROFITABLE LINES.<br />
MONETARY POLICY, FISCAL POLICY AND THE ACCORD ARE ABOUT<br />
CREATING CERTAINTY FOR BUSINESS: CERTAINTY THAT GROWTH WILL<br />
BE M4AINTAINED WITHOUT AVOIDABLE INFLATION OR BALANCE OF<br />
PAYMENTS CRISES; CERTAINTY THAT BUSINESS PROFITABILITY,<br />
HAVING NOW BEEN SO CONVINCINGLY* RESTORED TO THE LEVELS OF<br />
TO 20 YEARS AGO, WILL NOT BE PLUNDERED BY AN UNTHINKING<br />
RESORT TO MASSIVE INDUSTRIAL DISLOCATION OR AN UNREASONABLE<br />
ACCELERATION OF WAGE CLAIMS; CERTAINTY THAT THE SIZE OF THE<br />
PUBLIC SECTOR WILL BE RESTRAINED AS PRIVATE ACTIVITY<br />
EXPANDS; CERTAINTY THAT WE AS A LABOR GOVERNMENT HAVE SOUGHT<br />
AND ACHIEVED A MUTUAL UNDERSTANDING AMONGST ALL THE MAJOR<br />
ECONOMIC INTEREST GROUPS ABOUT THE TASK AHEAD, AN ENDURING<br />
UNDERSTANDING BUILT ON CONSULTATION AND CONSENSUS.<br />
THAT COOPERATIVE APPROACH EXTENDS ALSO TO INDUSTRY POLICY.<br />
IT HAS PERMITTED AN UNPRECEDENTED SET OF AGREEMENTS TO BE<br />
CONCLUDED IN THE STEEL INDUSTRY. ALTHOUGH THERE WERE SOME<br />
WHO SAID THAT IT COULD NEVER BE DONE, THESE AGREEMENTS<br />
INCLUDED MEASURES TO RAISE PRODUCTIVITY AND HAVE BEEN A </p>
<p>MAJOR FACTOR IN THE CURRENT ABILITY OF OUR MAJOR STEEL<br />
PRODUCER TO RESPOND TO MARKET OPPORTUNITIES AND CAPTURE<br />
SALES WHICH IN OTHER PERIODS WOULD HAVE GONE BEGGING.<br />
THE MOTOR VEHICLE PLAN IS ANOTHER EXAMPLE OF OUR POSITIVE<br />
APPROACH TO INDUSTRY POLICY.<br />
FURTHER, THE GOVERNMENT HAS TAKEN A NUMBER OF INITIAL STEPS<br />
TO REDUCE THE REGULATORY BURDEN ON INDUSTRY, AND WILL<br />
CONTINUE TO LOOK AT FURTHER POSSIBLE STEPS. IN THIS REGARD I<br />
HAVE RECENTLY ANNOUNCED A NUMBER OF INITIATIVES IN THE AREAS<br />
OF FOREIGN INVESTMENT POLICY AND EXPORT CONTROLS, AND LAID<br />
OUT AN AGENDA FOR FURTHER REFORM.<br />
I EXPECT THAT THE GOVERNMENT WILL BE RELEASING IN THE NEW<br />
YEAR A DRAFT SET OF GUIDELINES TO GOVERN THE OPERATIONS OF<br />
COMMONWEALTH STATUTORY AUTHORITIES. THESE GUIDELINES WILL<br />
BE INTENDED TO PROMOTE THE MORE EFFICIENT AND MORE EFFECTIVE<br />
PROVISION OF SERVICES BY THE PUBLIC SECTOR.<br />
THE REASON FOR OUR INTEREST IN THIS MATTER IS THAT THE<br />
SECTORS OF THE ECONOMY ARE INTERCONNECTED AND MUTUALLY<br />
DEPENDENT. JUST LIKE ANY FOOD PREPARATION, ECONOMIC RESULTS CAN ONLY BE<br />
AS GOOD AS THE RAW MATERIALS THAT GO INTO PRODUCING THEM AND<br />
THE SKILL WITH WHICH THESE ARE COMBINED.<br />
AN INEFFICIENT PUBLIC SECTOR CAN UNQUESTIONABLY DRAG ON THE<br />
GROWTH PERFORMANCE OF THE ECONOMY MORE BROADLY.<br />
SO, WHILE WE RECOGNISE THAT CERTAIN GOODS AND SERVICES ARE<br />
MOST EXPEDITIOUSLY PROVIDED IN THE PUBLIC SECTOR, WE ALSO<br />
RECOGNISE THE NEED TO ENSURE THAT GOODS AND SERVICES ARE<br />
DELIVERED EFFICIENTLY.<br />
IN THE SAME WAY, AS A COMMUNITY WE SHOULD CONTINUE TO LOOK<br />
AT WAYS TO IMPROVE THE EFFICIENCY OF OUR PRIVATE SECTOR.<br />
FOR GENERATIONS, IN THE DISCUSSION OF INDUSTRY POLICY AND<br />
APPROPRIATE INDUSTRIAL STRUCTURES IN THIS COUNTRY,<br />
PARTICULARLY IN THE CONTEXT OF NEEDING TO CONTAIN THE GROWTH<br />
OF OUR CURRENT ACCOUNT DEFICIT, THE REGULATORS INSTINCTIVELY<br />
TURNED TO THE GREAT BOOK OF PROTECTION.<br />
COMPETITION TOO STIFF FROM ABROAD? SLAP ON A TARRIFF.<br />
STILL NOT GOOD ENOUGH TO MEET THEIR PRICE? GO FOR A QUOTA<br />
OR TARIFF QUOTA.<br />
NOT ANY LONGER.<br />
WE MUST RECOGNISE THAT CONSUMERS PAY A HIGH PRICE<br />
EQUIVALENT IN THE CASE OF MANUFACTURING, IN 1982-83, TO A<br />
TAX OF $ 11.2 BILLION ACCORDING TO THE IAC FOR THE<br />
PRIVILEGE OF BUYING AUSTRALIAN WHEN FOREIGNERS CAN PRODUCE<br />
SIGNIFICANTLY MORE CHEAPLY.<br />
DOWNSTREAM USERS OF HIGHLY PROTECTED PRODUCTS BEAR THE<br />
ADDITIONAL COSTS OF RAW MATERIALS, WHICH REDUCES THEIR </p>
<p>ABILITY TO COMPETE IN WORLD MARKETS. AS A GENERAL<br />
PRINCIPLE, THE PREFERENCE OF THIS GOVERNMENT IS TO REDUCE<br />
PROTECTION, OVER TIME, AT A PACE DESIGNED TO MINIMIZE<br />
ECONOMIC AND SOCIAL DISRUPTION, STARTING WITH THE MOST<br />
HIGHLY PROTECTED. INDEED WE ARE PROGRESSIVELY IMPLEMENTING<br />
POSITIVE EXPORT-ORIENTED INDUSTRY POLICIES.<br />
ONE OF THE MORE INTERESTING FINDINGS OF SOME WORK PREPARED<br />
BY THE OFFICE OF EPAC HAS BEEN THE TENDENCY OVER TIME FOR<br />
INVESTMENT TO BE CONCENTRATED RELATIVELY MORE HEAVILY IN<br />
LESS PROTECTED SECTORS OF THE AUSTRALIAN ECONOMY.<br />
SUCH AN INVESTMENT ORIENTATION IS TO BE ENCOURAGED.<br />
ONE NOTAB3LE CHARACTERISTIC OF ANY DEPRECIATION OF THE $ A IS<br />
THAT IT IS NON-DISCRIMINATORY ALL PRODUCERS BECOME MORE<br />
COMPETITIVE WITH IMPORTS, IRRESPECTIVE OF THE LEVEL OF<br />
PROTECTION ALREADY ENJOYED.<br />
THE NEED TO PURSUE POLICIES WHICH PRESERVE THIS BENEFIT TO<br />
DOMESTIC SUPPLIERS GENERALLY IS ONE OF THE MAJOR DRIVING<br />
FORCES BEHIND OUR GENERAL MACRO-ECONOMIC STRATEGY.<br />
BUT THE MORE INVESTMENT IS ATTRACTED TO HIGHLY PROTECTED<br />
AREAS THE HARDER BECOMES THE TASK IF, SUBSEQUENTLY, IT IS<br />
DECIDED TO SEEK TO DIVERT RESOURCES TO MORE OUTWARD-ORIENTED<br />
INDUSTRIES BY REDUCING DOMESTIC PROTECTION IN SOME CASES.<br />
LADIES AND GENTLEMEN, THERE ARE THREE OTHER FACTORS BEARING<br />
ON OUR ECONOMIC PERFORMANCE WHICH I WOULD LIKE TO DISCUSS<br />
BRIEFLY PROCESSES, MARKETING AND FINANCE.<br />
BY " PROCESSES", OF COURSE, I-MEAN TECHNOLOGY. AND THERE IS<br />
A WHOLE RANGE TO CHOOSE FROM HI TECH, NEW TECH AND MORE<br />
EFFICIENT OLD TECH ALMOST MORE " TECHS-, INDEED, THAN THE<br />
NSW EDUCATION SYSTEM USED TO HAVE.<br />
BUT, WHATEVER IT IS. CALLED, THE MEANING IS CLEAR: NEW<br />
PRODUCTS; NEW WAYS OF TRANSFORMING RAW MATERIALS OR<br />
PROVIDING SERVICES; OR THE MORE RAPID SPREAD OF EXISTING<br />
KNOW HOW SO AS TO CAPTURE NEW MARKETS, TO PRODUCE THINGS<br />
MORE CHEAPLY OR, TO USE A CLICHE, TO " BUILD THE BETTER MOUSE<br />
TRAP". AUSTRALIA HAS SOME IMPORTANT ADVANTAGES IN RESEARCH AND<br />
DEVELOPMENT ACTIVITY. THE EDUCATION SYSTEM PRODUCES CAPABLE<br />
RESEARCH WORKERS. THE COST OF R D IN AUSTRALIA IS NOT<br />
HIGH. IT IS PERHAPS SURPRISING, THEREFORE, THAT WHILE GOVERNMENT<br />
FUNDING IS COMMENSURATE WITH OTHER DEVELOPED COUNTRIES,<br />
INDUSTRY FUNDING AND PERFORMANCE OF R D IS SMALL.<br />
BUT THE GOVERNMENT RECOGNISES THE MAGNITUDE OF THE TASK OF<br />
IMPROVING THIS EQUATION.<br />
FOR FIVE YEARS FROM I JULY THIS YEAR WE WILL PROVIDE A TAX<br />
DEDUCTION FOR 150 PER CENT OF EXPENDITURE ON APPLIED </p>
<p>9.<br />
RESEARCH WITHIN AUSTRALIA. AND WE ARE DETERMINED TO IMPROVE<br />
THE COORDINATION OF EFFORT BETWEEN THE PRIVATE SECTOR AND<br />
PUBLIC BODIES SUCH AS CSIRO AND THE UNIVERSITIES.<br />
AS REGARDS MARKETING, AUSTRALIA'S OFFICIAL MARKETING EFFORT<br />
OVERSEAS HAS BEEN RADICALLY OVERHAULED IN RECENT TIMES. WE<br />
ARE IN THE PROCESS OF ESTABLISHING THE AUSTRALIAN TRADE<br />
COMMISSION A ONE-STOP SHOP FOR ADVICE AND OTHER GOVERNMENT<br />
SERVICES TO EXPORTERS.<br />
FURTHER WE HAVE AN ACTIVE TRADE POLICY SEEKING BOTH<br />
LIBERALISATION OF THE GLOBAL TRADING ENVIRONMENT IN AREAS OF<br />
INTEREST TO AUSTRALIA, AND INCREASED EMPHASIS IN RESPECT ON<br />
BILATERAL TRADING OPPORTUNITIES. THESE INCLUDE,<br />
PARTICULARLY, OPPORTUNITIES TO DEVELOP SPECIAL RELATIONSHIPS<br />
WITH MAJOR COUNTRIES IN OUR OWN REGION.<br />
FINALLY, IN RESPECT OF MY LAST POINT, FINANCE, THERE SHOULD<br />
BE NO NEED FOR ME TO REMIND THIS AUDIENCE OF THE<br />
TRANSFORMATION WHICH THE FINANCIAL SECTOR HAS ALREADY<br />
UNDERGONE, THE FULL RAMIFICATIONS OF WHICH WILL BE YEARS IN<br />
COMING.<br />
AUSTRALIA NEEDS AN EFFICIENT FINANCIAL SECTOR CAPABLE OF<br />
ENSUING THAT ADEQUATE RESOURCES ARE AVAILABLE AS CHEAPLY AS<br />
POSSIBLE TO THE EFFICIENT ENTERPRISES OF TOMORROW. OUR<br />
POLICIES TO PROMOTE COMPETITION IN BANKING AND MORE<br />
GENERALLY HAVE PRECISELY THAT END IN VIEW.<br />
LADIES AND GENTLEMEN, AS I SAID EARLIER, THE TWENTY THREE<br />
YEARS TO 1983 FOR ALL THEIR ACKNOWLEDGED ACHIEVEMENTS<br />
HAVE BEEN SOMETHING OF A DISAPPOINTMENT.<br />
WE NOW HAVE THE POLICIES IN PLACE TO ENSURE THAT AUSTRALIA'S<br />
PERFORMANCE IN THE NEXT TWENTY FIVE YEARS WILL BE FAR<br />
BETTER. HAPPILY, LONGEVITY RUNS IN MY FAMILY.. UNLIKE MY FATHER, I<br />
DO NOT EXPECT TO SEE A SECOND HALLEYS COMMET. BUT I DO LOOK<br />
FORWARD TO AN INVITATION TO ADDRESS YOU, THOUGH POSSIBLY NOT<br />
AS PRIME MINISTER, AT YOUR GOLDEN JUBILEE TO REPORT ON HOW<br />
WELL THE FOUNDATIONS FOR GROWTH WERE LAID IN THE TERM OF<br />
THIS GOVERNMENT. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
