<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8762</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP DINNER FOR KEIDANREN MISSION PARLIAMENT HOUSE CANBERRA, WEDNESDAY, 9 DECEMBER 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/12/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008762.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
DINNER FOR KEIDANREN MISSION<br />
PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA,<br />
WEDNESDAY, 9 DECEMBER 1992<br />
Mr Itoh, Ambassador Hasegawa, distinguished guests,<br />
ladies and gentlemen.<br />
I am delighted to welcome Keidanren's Economic Exchange<br />
Promotion Mission to Australia.<br />
The Australian Government and business sector value<br />
highly the close relations we have enjoyed with Keidanren<br />
over many years.<br />
We recognise Keidanren's pre-eminent position among<br />
Japan's national business organisations.<br />
We admire the broad and long-term view your organisation<br />
takes of your country' s economic circumstances.<br />
Both with regard to an unending process of economic<br />
restructuring within Japan, and the evolving challenges<br />
you face in the international economic environment.<br />
During my visit to Japan last September, I had an<br />
opportunity for private discussions with your Honorary<br />
Chairman, M4r Eishiro Saitoh, and other senior business<br />
leaders.<br />
Mr Saitoh's personal experience of the Australia-Japan<br />
economic relationship spans more than four decades, and<br />
he brings a great deal of understanding and authority to<br />
our joint interests.<br />
He spoke warmly about the contribution that Australia's<br />
reliable supply of raw materials and energy has made to<br />
industrialisation in Japan.<br />
For our side too, trade with Japan has been a crucial<br />
component in Australia's economic advancement.<br />
Our two countries enjoy a truly mature and diversified<br />
economic partnership.<br />
4752 </p>
<p>The bilateral trade relationship, now worth almost<br />
billion US dollars a year, is one of the principal<br />
sinews of economic interdependence in the Western<br />
Pacific. But there can be no room for complacency about past<br />
achievements at a time when the Australian and Japanese<br />
economies face severe challenges both at home and abroad.<br />
Your mission to Australia is well timed.<br />
You have the opportunity to observe the effects of<br />
historic changes in both the economic performance and<br />
attitudes of Australians.<br />
During the 1980s, we embarked on an irreversible process<br />
to open our markets to the world, and to make our economy<br />
more internationally competitive.<br />
We now export approximately 23 per cent of total output<br />
compared with 14 per cent in 1983.<br />
Our rate of taxation to GDP is now one of the lowest<br />
among OECD countries, virtually the same as Japan's.<br />
We have transformed ourselves from a high inflation<br />
nation to a very low inflation nation.<br />
We have increased our competitiveness by well over one<br />
tenth.<br />
We have replaced industrial disputation with a<br />
cooperative system which has delivered the lowest level<br />
of strikes for 30 years.<br />
We are moving away from the centralised fixing of wages.<br />
We have decided to make most wage settlements by<br />
negotiation, and at the enter~ rise level.<br />
We expect more than half the workforce to be covered by<br />
enterprise bargains by the middle of next year.<br />
During your visit, you have no doubt seen something of<br />
the current political controversy about labour relations<br />
in the State of Victoria.<br />
The difference between the Australian Government and our<br />
political opponents is that our side puts emphasis on<br />
encouraging change and improved productivity through<br />
consultation and respect for basic labour conditions<br />
rather than by adopting a confrontationist approach.<br />
Recession and restructuring have caused unacceptably high<br />
levels of unemployment. 4 7773 </p>
<p>This year, we have invested a great deal in measures to<br />
alleviate the social and human consequences of<br />
unemployment. The Australian economy is now growing at an annual rate<br />
of about two per ceint in real terms.<br />
This is among the fastest rates in the OECD but not yet<br />
sufficient to bring unemployment down.<br />
Those of you who knew Australia before will have seen<br />
that attitudes have also changed markedly.<br />
Despite setbacks and hardship, there is awareness in<br />
Australia as never before that our standard of living<br />
depends totally on how well we make our own way in the<br />
world. As you have learned in Japan, change induces more change.<br />
Australians now have a new sense of national identity.<br />
The challenges which face us are inspiring a new sense of<br />
national purpose.<br />
The recession has set us back, but the Australian people,<br />
I believe, recognise the worth of what they achieved in<br />
the past few years, and are not willing to give these<br />
things up. I<br />
We have laid the basis for economic transformation.<br />
We know the direction we have to go and I am confident<br />
that the Australian people are determined on going that<br />
way. We have a more confident view of our role in the<br />
Asia-Pacific region.<br />
We have a sharper awareness of the opportunities for us<br />
to engage more closely with economic dynamism in East<br />
Asia. Australians are now committing much greater resources to<br />
education and training.<br />
This is so we can better meet the demands of a modern,<br />
internationally oriented economy.<br />
We reco~ gnise that Australia's human capital provides a<br />
comparative advantage in economic relations with the<br />
rapidly developing economies to our North.<br />
Earlier this week the State Premiers and I agreed to<br />
develop a comprehensive strategy to promote the study of<br />
Asian languages and cultures in Australian schools.<br />
Already around 100,000 young Australians study Japanese.<br />
4754 </p>
<p>AS Australia fully comes to terms with the potential of<br />
our economic relations with the wider East Asian region,<br />
the importance of relations with Japan is unlikely to<br />
diminish. Japan still accounts for 28 per cent of Australian<br />
exports, compared with 57 per cent for all East Asia.<br />
Mr Itoh and colleagues, I trust that your mission will<br />
return to Japan impressed with the vitality of the<br />
bilateral relationship with Australia and the scope for<br />
two-way expansion of trade and investment.<br />
From the Australian Government's perspective, the<br />
relationship with Japan is a corner-stone in the<br />
development of our broader policy towards the Asia-<br />
Pacific region.<br />
Both our countries have a fundamental interest in the<br />
maintenance of an open, non-discrimatory, multilateral<br />
trading system and in the promotion of open regionalism<br />
in the Asia-Pacific area.<br />
A recent article by a senior Japanese official in a<br />
journal published by the Japanese Foreign Ministry<br />
attracted close attention here.<br />
The author identified Australia as having the attributes<br />
to be a key partner of Japan in promoting a desirable<br />
form of economic integration in the Asia-Pacific region.<br />
I should say for Australia's part that we are always<br />
ready to work closely with the Japanese Government and<br />
private sector to strengthen cooperation at both the<br />
bilateral and regional levels.<br />
Senior officials of the two Governments will be<br />
discussing just these sorts of issues early in the new<br />
year as a follow-up to my visit to Tokyo.<br />
In responding to an increasingly fluid world trade<br />
system, Australia has a core interest in maintaining the<br />
most favourable possible environment for our bilateral<br />
trade relationships with Japan and the other economies of<br />
East Asia.<br />
As I said in Japan in September, Australia will not be a<br />
party to any trade arrangement which is directed against<br />
Japan. But in all of this our aim should be to avoid an inwardlooking<br />
relationship and work together to encourage the<br />
most open possible processes of economic integration in<br />
the Asia-Pacific region. 4755 </p>
<p>The Asia-Pacific Economic Cooperation or APEC process is<br />
a particularly valuable mechanism in this regard, because<br />
it embraces the key economic linkages between the<br />
countries of the Western Pacific and North America.<br />
The interests of both Australia and Japan are best served<br />
by ensuring that the Western Pacific and North America<br />
remain part of the same thriving trading community.<br />
Mr Itoh and colleagues, let me again welcome you to<br />
Australia. And let me say on behalf of all the Australians here this<br />
evening that we hope that your visit to Australia is both<br />
professionally satisfying and personally enjoyable.<br />
Thank you.<br />
4756 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
