<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4693</transcript-id>
    <title>INTERVIEW WITH LAURIE WILSON, CHANNEL 7, 22 APRIL 1978</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/04/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004693.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
F1{ LS~ UF'FI(' F. TRANSCLRIP1 ./ 2<br />
Interview with Laurie Wilson, Channel 7<br />
22 April 1978<br />
QUESTION: P. M. What sort of positive things do you point to<br />
as having come out of these two days here. There has been a<br />
bit of a feeling that maybe-. it really hasn't achieved that<br />
much. PRIME MINISTER: I think the discussions have been very useful.<br />
because it's the first-time Japan and Australia have sat down<br />
together to talk about the broader based economic and trade<br />
issues. It's natural that we should talk to Japan about these<br />
matters because we're both very much affected by the world<br />
economy, very much affected by changes in trade. We also have<br />
very substantial economic and trade links of our own. I believe<br />
there is a significant degree of a common view between Japan<br />
and Australia about the problems that we all face at the present<br />
time, and about the need to make the trade negotiations taking<br />
place through this year as successful as possible, about the<br />
need to make sure that agriculture is included, and also about<br />
the need to make progress in the dialogue between developing and<br />
developed countries not just progress, but positive results.<br />
QUESTION: If we look to an area like more particularly the<br />
EEC, there have been some pretty harsh words exchanged between<br />
yourself and some members of the EEC over the past few weeks.<br />
Is it possible that Japan can be of assistance in smoothing<br />
the way, so to speak?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well I don't think that's the role, and that<br />
aspect didn't come up. I would hope that in some matters,<br />
such as codes for export subsidies, there can be very close<br />
co-operation between Japan and Australia, and Australia will<br />
be tabling a code for export subsidies in the MTN discussions.<br />
The bilateral matters between the EEC and Australia we need<br />
to battle on in our own way in relation to those matters.<br />
Those words that we used, we used very deliberately, advisedly<br />
and with forethought, because only relatively shortly before<br />
that we found representatives of one Community country in MTN<br />
discussions saying if Australia doesn't do this, we will<br />
break off the bilateral discussions, and Vic. Garland got<br />
something of the same flavour in Europe, and after the best<br />
part of a year in getting to the situation where constructive<br />
and meaningful bilateral discussions could take place, we felt<br />
that that was going a little too far, and something needed<br />
doing about it.<br />
QUESTION: Looking at the sorts of things that you'vye been<br />
saying over the past few weeks, particularly overthe past<br />
few days, there now seems almost a sense of urgency about<br />
your feelings about what needs to be done internationally,<br />
particularly in respect to trade. Can we expect to see over<br />
the next say six months or so you playing a much more active<br />
role internationally? </p>
<p>2.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well I think there is a sense of urgency<br />
because there are major trade negotiations going on through<br />
the course of this year, and if the w,. rong decisions are<br />
made the dangers are a reversion to the protectionism of the<br />
1030' s. Therefore it is very important to try and get to.<br />
a situation where constructive, useful and sensible decisions<br />
are made to try and widen the bases of world trade and to<br />
try and achieve an expansion of marketLs. It is very<br />
important to make sure that the devl oping countries are<br />
involved in that. Let me give you one example.......( tape<br />
turned) a matter of a week or a matter of a month. And I<br />
don't think anyone really suggests that that kind of<br />
improvement in tariff structure is going to have a substantially<br />
great effect on trade. Bringing that to attention just<br />
emphasises the importance of other aspects of MTN discussions<br />
and negotiations, and emphasises the importance of making sure<br />
that agriculture stays a realistic partC of the negotiations,<br />
and doesn't get pushed aside, as it has on other occasions.<br />
If the wrong decisions are made through the course of this<br />
year we face the prospects of protectionism of a kind that<br />
the world hasn't seen for many years, and I think that would<br />
be most unfortunate for all of us, and therefore the decisions<br />
taken this year could set the pattern for many years, and<br />
therefore it's important to try and set the right pattern.<br />
QUESTION: Finally Prime Minister, You have said that in the<br />
past Australia has perhaps been a little reticent in its<br />
attitude towards bring some influence to bear on world attitudes.<br />
Are you hoping in fact that we are going to be able to have more<br />
influence in the next twelve months?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well I think that we've always expressed our<br />
views constructively in international forums where Australia<br />
is represented as a responsible member of the international<br />
community. But any Australian governznent has a very particular<br />
responsibility to all the Australian people, and it's not good<br />
enough to say that merely that other nations are larger, more<br />
powerful and that therefore they discuss these things amongst<br />
themselves, and that Australia can happily leave it to other<br />
people. We do have a responsibility to our own people, and<br />
countries with whom we have close relationships, Japan, the<br />
United States when the Vice-President visits Australia in<br />
a few days time. There is a responsibility to speak about<br />
these issues as we see them, and I believe that Australia<br />
has a constructive role to play, and I believe that should<br />
apply to any nation, no matter what it's size. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
