<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>949</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS:  WHITE HOUSE LUNCHEON TEXT OF SPEECHES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/06/1964</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000949.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS WHITE HOUSE LUNCHEON 64/ 0 7<br />
TEXT OF SPEECHES<br />
Following are the texts of speeches by Presicent Johnson<br />
and the Prime Minister, Sir Robert Menzies, at lunch on<br />
24th June at the !" hite House, Washington.<br />
PRLSIDIENT JOHNSON<br />
" Mr, Prime Minister, Mr. Chief Justice, My Friends<br />
This is a delightful and very happy and heartwarming occasion<br />
for me today.<br />
It is one to which I have looked forward with great<br />
anticipation. We here in Wasington know our guest as a good and great<br />
friend of America<br />
I hope that Sir Robert and all of his countrynaen know<br />
equally well that the President is both an old and good friend<br />
of Australia : ind a very great admirer of the Australian peoplea<br />
As many of my personal friends and associates have heard<br />
me say through the years, I lost at least a part of my heart<br />
to the Australian people a long time ago.<br />
I v'ill never forget their warmth when I wac statiuned.<br />
there in the early and anxious days of the war in the Pacif: c,)<br />
and just to illustrate why our guest of honor has been Prime<br />
Minister for 17 years and why he has beon an astute and expert<br />
parliamentarian for more than 35 ye: ars, before we came<br />
downstairs I was telling him of the graciousnesj of a great<br />
lady whose name I could not remember, but with a very slight<br />
description of her qualities and her assistance to me during<br />
the early dnys of the war, the Prime Minister, without any<br />
difficulty, called her name and located her and brought<br />
back to my memory many other gorid things obout her.<br />
I long for the day to come, and hope it can come between<br />
now and November, when I will have my constituency as well In<br />
hand and know them as well as he doe-,<br />
Some of you may be familiar with the accounts of one<br />
apisode that occurred when the plane in which I was riding as<br />
a member of the Navy was forced to land away from our Base.<br />
Several writers later filed stories that my contacts with<br />
Australians in the area indicated that I might have had a<br />
promising political future down under.<br />
I can only say that in considering his extraordinary<br />
success for many years, the Prime Minister obviously has much<br />
to teach the elective officials in America, and I am so proud<br />
that I have been privileged to sit and visit with him and to<br />
learn from him.<br />
We are grateful, Sir, that you honor us with this visit<br />
this year, We remember with particular favor your visit to our<br />
country last year when you sat here at this chair by the side<br />
of our beloved President John Kennedy.<br />
At that time you made a statement which I think expresses<br />
so well the feeling between our lands.<br />
Then you said, " We work for the same kind of free world." / 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
In the geography of frecdom, all areas and all corners and<br />
all regions of the free world are important, and they are all<br />
vital. For us here in the United States it has been a source of<br />
great strength to know that there stands a nation so dedicatei<br />
to freedom's defense as Australia.<br />
I don't know when a news announcement has given our<br />
country more comfort or been received with greater satisfaction<br />
than the announcement made las week by your Minister c'l<br />
External Affairs concerning the additional contribution that<br />
the people of Australia were ready and anxious to make to<br />
contribute men and materials and equipment along the side of<br />
our men who are now fighting for freedom in South Vietnami,<br />
So we are proud and we are very grateful, Mr. Prime Minister,<br />
to have you stand by our si. e.<br />
We are glad to have you stand with us as members of ANZUS.<br />
V o are happy to work with you in the United Nations.<br />
We are assured to know that you are with us wherever<br />
freedom is in danger.<br />
Australia and the United States do really, truly, as<br />
you say, woirk for the same kind of free world.<br />
I am sure that brief as your visit now must be, this<br />
frienly meeting with you, will help us to work together in<br />
even closer understanding,.<br />
I am grateful that you have come here.<br />
Out di3cussions have been fruitful,<br />
Our understanding has been improved,<br />
My desire to return your visit has increased, if that is<br />
possible, So to my good friends who have assembled here v. ith us<br />
today in this house, I should like to ask you to join with me<br />
in a toast to Sir 1obert M-enzies, The Prnie Minister of<br />
Australia, and to the enduring bonds of friendship and freedom<br />
between our lands.<br />
Mr. Prime Minister."<br />
SIR ROBERT MENZIES<br />
Mr. President, Chief Justice, and Gentlemen I have<br />
been reminded by you, Sir, that last year I spoke in this room,<br />
I think, in the presence of and as the guest of that great man,<br />
the late President Kennedy, and I should not wish to begin<br />
even the briefest of speeches without paying a tribute of<br />
respect and affection to his memory.<br />
But, Sir, the world goes on, and you now have the<br />
responsibilities of this enormous office.<br />
I think perhaps the one thing that prevents a man occupying<br />
one of the very greatest offices in the world from becoming<br />
subject to delusions about himself is that he is usually so<br />
conscious of the task and of the responsibility that he has no<br />
time left for showing off.<br />
This is so true. 000 / 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
You have this enormous responsibility, and you would be<br />
perhaps surprised to know how many people, so many thousands<br />
of miles away from you, and whether they would be on your<br />
side or another in your own country, they pray for you and<br />
wish you well in the discharge of this immense human<br />
responsibility, And so, Sir, I am greatly honoured to be here as your<br />
guest. There is another thing about it.<br />
I am here as Prime Minister of Australia, a British<br />
country. I myself am British, and some people might say<br />
insistently so, but here we are in one place, at the one time,<br />
When I saw you last time here, Sir, and you were<br />
Vice-President, I was beginning to turn over in my mind . vhether<br />
I shouldn't have a premature election, and I de. ided that<br />
I should, Most people were confident that I would be beaten, but<br />
I wono Now T don't know whether there is a moral in this,<br />
Mr. President, but everybody I have spoken to so far in the<br />
United States is confident that you will win.<br />
I hope this is not a bac omen.<br />
Now, Sir, I don't want to detain this distinguished<br />
audience, but I think that it would be appropriat-, if you<br />
don't mind, for me to say something about the position of<br />
your great country in the world, and particularly in the<br />
free worl, and in particular with us in Australia.<br />
It is one of the issues of history, something that I<br />
have referred to before today, that nations which have immense<br />
power, and, therefore, acciumulate immense responsibilities,<br />
are seldom terribly popular.<br />
Great Britain, you know, was the Great Power in the<br />
world in the 19th Century, and enjoyed a supply of epithets<br />
of an abusive kind in Europe which has perhaps never been<br />
equalled since,<br />
Great Power doesn't give you great friendship.<br />
Indeed, great gifts to other nations don't buy<br />
friendship. Gratitude is a scarce commodity, and yet all great<br />
nations, and none more so than yours, perhsps none so much<br />
so as yours, have been conscious of responsibility and have<br />
done things materially and spiritually for other countries<br />
in the world, and very frequently have received small thanks<br />
for it. That doesn't matter.<br />
What matters is that these things are cone,<br />
What matters is that people are given an opportunity<br />
of standing on their own feet, of developing their own<br />
national and individual characteristics.<br />
This I am sure in the long run is a good thing for the<br />
world. </p>
<p>But mhen it comes to a country like Australia, well,<br />
we are a small country,<br />
I preside over a country which is about twice as large<br />
in point of population, and perhaps ten times as large in<br />
point of physical resources as the country which was presiled<br />
over by Thomas Jefferson,<br />
It is worth recalling becaus we go on as yor went on,<br />
and we may some day in the wisdom of providence and by some<br />
strength in our right hands ani courage in our own hearts<br />
and minds be one of the great and powerful countries in the<br />
world,. But that is a long way off.<br />
What is present with us J. s that vwe have a relationship<br />
with the United States which is not the rslationship between<br />
a benefactor and a pensioner.<br />
It is, I am happy to say, a proud relationship 06tween<br />
friends, one immensely powerful and the other, ourselves,<br />
much less powerful?<br />
Why are we friends<br />
People will say to me in a skeptial sort of mood,<br />
" Yqs, o c-ours,, you keep in with tle United Statos be-ause<br />
you want i. hem to defen. you."<br />
This is said as if we regardel the problem of our defence<br />
as something for somebody else to attend to, and for us to<br />
neglect or ignore.<br />
Don't you believe it for one momenta<br />
Vde shall defend ourselves in Australia, whe . ever the<br />
circumstances, to the very last gasp that we have, but we will<br />
defeni ourselves with all the greater succoss if we know that<br />
we have great friends like yourselves who will be defending<br />
us or helping to defen?.-us not because there is some statutory<br />
obligation, or not just because of some treaty between us,<br />
but because we both heppen to believe in exactly the sane things,<br />
the same attitudes of mind, the same patterns of behaviour,<br />
the same great attributes of character and quality.<br />
These things we have in common,<br />
It is because vwe have them in common that we will defend<br />
them in common.<br />
Sir, there may be people around the world, I dare say<br />
there are, who fall into the deplorable habit of thinking<br />
that the United States should be regarded as a sort of<br />
Gendarme to keep the peace of the world, and true it is that<br />
you have accepted enormous responsibilities, but ion't you<br />
think for one moment that in my country when we consider<br />
problems of international peace and war we say " Lea-e it to<br />
the United States".<br />
We may be small, but we are friends, and it is a good<br />
thing to have friends, great or small.<br />
It is a good thing, above all other matters, to have<br />
friends who are not going to resort to questioning when the<br />
day of trial comes, but who will be there, and there for all<br />
purposes of the survival of those things that you stand for and<br />
that we stand for. </p>
<p>I am always completely at home in this place, in this<br />
city, always capable of having an argument with an American.<br />
Not with the President.<br />
I wouldn't dare to do that.<br />
And not with the Chief Justice, althouoh I would enjoy it.<br />
But with Dean Rusk, vwho I want to tell you at once,<br />
I don't care what side you are on in politics, but Dean Rusk<br />
is personr. gratissima with us in Australia.<br />
But still capable of having an argument, of course.<br />
It will be a poor day, won't it, when we can't<br />
It would be a very poor day when little iustralia won' t<br />
be able to summon up its traditional impudence by looking<br />
at the big United States and saying, " What do you mean, you<br />
big stiff This, of course, will happen.<br />
You wouldn't belie-7e it, but there are people in my own<br />
country who have been heard to make rude remarks about me,<br />
and I don't mind that a scrap as long as they are in the<br />
minority. But, Sir, I have enjoyed meeting you today.<br />
I had met you before, but in a highly formal sense.<br />
I am very glad to kn-w that from now on we will be able<br />
to communicate with each other in terms of personal<br />
friendship. I do hope you will be able to come to Australia, and I<br />
believe that you want to come to Australia,<br />
But whether you succeed in the near future or, as one<br />
might say, in my time, or not, the fact remains that in'-<br />
Australia you have friends, little friends, friends you may<br />
chide, friends you may encourage, friends to whom you can hold<br />
out all of the usual appurtenances of friendship which run from<br />
chastisement to approval, but still friends, because I want to<br />
make it clear to you that however small it is, the thing that<br />
we do, we will always be foun, to do it because we know that<br />
everything that matters for us, and everything that matters<br />
for you, is at common risk in this strange world, and must,<br />
therefore, be defended explained and defended in common,<br />
Sir, I thank you very much, indeed, for your great<br />
courtesy. I regret very much to find that your congress is under no<br />
better discipline than my House of Parliament, and some of the<br />
ones who were here whom I was hoping to persuade about<br />
something or other have gone off, not to persuade or to be<br />
persuaded but to vote.<br />
So thank you very much. OO---<br />
ISSUED BY The Press Secretary<br />
to the Prime Minister. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
