<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6458</transcript-id>
    <title>Appointment of Mr. Bernard Vincent McKay as Secretary, Department of Health</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/09/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006458.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>3 September 1984</p>
<p>The Secretary, Department of Health, Mr. L. J. Willett, is to take up appointment for a period as Director of the Merit  Protection and Review Agency.</p>
<p>As a consequence, the Government-will be recommending to the Governor-General in Council the appointment of Mr. Bernard Vincent McKay as Secretary, Department of Health, as from September 10. Mr. McKay is currently Secretary of the New South Wales Health Department. He was a former Chairman of the South Australian Health Commission, and previously held.positions in the Commonwealth Department of Health.</p>
<p>Mr. Willett's appointment as Director of the Merit Protection and Review Agency is an interim appointment to assist with the establishment of the Agency. It is the Government's intention. to recommend Mr. Willett's appointment to statutory positions on the Health Insurance Commission and the Commonwealth Serum Laboratories Commission.</p>
<p><strong>MR B. V. McKAY CURRICULUM VITAE</strong></p>
<p><strong>Full Name:</strong><br />Bernard Vincent McKay</p>
<p><strong>Date and Place of Birth: </strong><br />26 January 1940 Numurkah, Victoria</p>
<p><strong>Previous career details:</strong><br />* Since December 1982, Secretary and Permanent Head of . the NSW Department of Health<br />* 1980-82 -Chairman and Chief Executive Officer of the South Australian Health Commission.<br />* 1974-80 Regional Director, North Coast Region, New South Wales Health Commission<br />* 1972-74 Assistant Director, Planning and Executive Services, ACT Health Services, Commonwealth Department of Health<br />* 1971-72 Director Administration, Northern Territory Health Services, Commonwealth Department of Health</p>
<p><strong>Membership of Relevant Bodies: </strong><br />Executive Member of ithe Standing Committee of Health Ministers and the Australian Health Council.<br />Member of the National Health and Medical Research Council.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
