<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18074</transcript-id>
    <title>Remembering Vietnam Veterans 45 years on</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/08/2011</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Prime Minister Julia Gillard and Minister for Veterans' Affairs Warren Snowdon today said the 45th anniversary of the Battle of Long Tan was an opportunity to reflect on the service of the men and women who served during the Vietnam War.</p>
<p>Some 60,000 Australians including ground troops, air force and navy personnel served in Vietnam for over a decade from 1962.</p>
<p>As a result of this war, 521 Australians died paying the ultimate sacrifice for their country.</p>
<p>Ceremonies held around Australia today will honour the service and sacrifice of these brave men and women.</p>
<p>Vietnam Veterans' Day is commemorated each year on the anniversary of the Battle of Long Tan, one of the most significant Australian actions of the Vietnam War.</p>
<p>On 18 August 1966, 18 service personnel were killed and 24 were wounded at Long Tan when Delta company of the 6th Battalion, Royal Australian Regiment, engaged a much larger force of North Vietnamese army regulars.</p>
<p>The Battle of Long Tan demonstrated the courage, determination and teamwork of our Australian soldiers in the face of overwhelming adversity.</p>
<p>A unit citation of gallantry was awarded by the Governor-General to the Delta Company 6RAR at a ceremony at Enoggera today.</p>
<p>The Vietnam War caused the greatest social and political unrest in Australia since the First World War and for many veterans, the treatment they received on their return to Australia left enduring scars.</p>
<p>For the 47,000 surviving veterans, time has not always healed the physical and psychological scars, which have often been shared by loving family members.</p>
<p>Today, we recognise and honour these fine Australians and their families.  </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
