<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9853</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP THE FOURTH FRENCH NUCLEAR TEST </title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/11/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009853.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINJISTER 136/ 95<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
THE FOURTH FRENCH NUCLEAR TEST<br />
I strongly condemn the latest French nuclear test at Mururoa Atoll.<br />
I am appalled that the French Government continues to show disregard for the<br />
feelings of the people of the South Pacific. It has further isolated itself from<br />
international thinking on nuclear i ssues and significantly devalued its international<br />
credentials.<br />
Australia warmly welcomed the recent United Nations General Assembly resolution<br />
calling for an immediate end to nuclear testing. It is clear the international<br />
community shares Australia's conviction that continued nuclear testing is not<br />
consistent with changed global strategic circumstances and changing world opinion.<br />
The Government fully supports the recent Commonwealth statement on disarmament<br />
in which the overwhelming majority of leaders condemned continued nuclear testing<br />
and all leaders emphasised the importance of the determined pursuit of the<br />
elimination of nuclear weapons. This confirmed to me the breadth and depth of<br />
opposition to continued nuclear testing.<br />
Continued testing raises the level of scepticism amongst non-nuclear weapon states<br />
about the sincerity of some nuclear powers to pursue nuclear disarmament and<br />
therefore advances the prospect that some non-nuclear weapon nations will pursue<br />
their own nuclear weapons programs. The French Government must realise that by<br />
sending the wrong signals about its nuclear intentions it is in fact undermining its<br />
long term security, not strengthening it. Security in the next century will not be found<br />
in the possession of nuclear weapons.<br />
The Government calls on France to abandon immediately its testing program and to<br />
desist from actions which undermine progress towards a Comprehensive Test Ban<br />
Treaty and measures to prevent the proliferation of nuclear weapons.<br />
I will shortly be making a statement on the next steps Australia will be taking to<br />
pursue the goal of a world free of nuclear weapons which I set out in my<br />
United Nations Day speech on 24 October 1995.<br />
CANBERRA 22 November 1995 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
