<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3934</transcript-id>
    <title>THE ADMINISTRATIVE CONSEQUENCES OF THE FAILURE OF SUPPLY</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/10/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003934_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
.4 1 ? RESS STATE: MENT-NO. 50E. 1 C<br />
914 C r 197-/ 5<br />
7neGcvrnrentis J aa1l1l . i _ ts p: F'rto s ee-that-<br />
DCL~. 3Jli1s are passe: d. In the event,<br />
ovr,' thea Oc'-ciz. on in t'l Senat-e remains<br />
-Lca-a,-d r nst h7e 1D avet-iL o f s Zlar1iae Sis su SDe n C . d<br />
will. ncve-' rt. h-l. csS, T<br />
to assent'-al oo:~ cieisv sarsv : e ffec-Lively<br />
as Dosbe It iS hSe in te re st s o al 1 PO S. Oo. c FL lj-S the<br />
1-: 1 nt s objec t ve an d cl1ear d Uty-to M i n S e a ny<br />
d i I-c rt i o n o F 1 t~ t ehi~ h To cnr, COJrwe<br />
would exci llls-nloe~, t r .1o we7--jjave to 3-oak, J'or<br />
tne provi.,-sion o-so mayvital servi es, t~ o con aniie a T<br />
cmplovim-ernt and to Vork1ormJ. iv<br />
I " Ile guarnc aa ia~ ee -tha t th -orn ior t'ñ s<br />
salary and sg oriiet ari-sing . rrom thi'atL erloyimr1nt-wil<br />
event-Utalv bea t At t1h-= s; inxe time the Go-vernm-e nt knowsFthatla<br />
ari cutOn th-"-e CIC0o'J: tWA. and qrocd sen: o-L all1<br />
orri-* cerS, on the loy-altv t-hc-y give to whatever Govc,-, rnmerit is<br />
in powear., and on th * aanthey apply t o ' th eJ-r t. as, s.<br />
The Govern-ment will not, however, act other than strictlyv<br />
~ naccord1arnCe with 2law ' n a-;-terripting to preserve, aciministrabive<br />
s e ac. . s a nd maP ~ a n Eg e an sai--l a r y p aym1e n tS.<br />
The Goverrument h-as revieojed the f inancial position ofL<br />
all Dea-rtmrents and authl-ori-ties and-; steps have beenaen to<br />
ensure that w-. acre and salary payme-nts will be maintained th11iroucilh<br />
th uply period, that is until. the Cend: of Nov embl'er.<br />
T3, e Govornment has directed that all spendi ng on non-essential-s<br />
is to ~ ecLt to the bon--and that funds bie conserved as -much DS,<br />
possible. It is likl-ely that. in addition to -vages arld salaries<br />
Most ot;-e-r essential paymrents can a lso be wholly7 main t a~ in ntilI<br />
orfl oY em: r<br />
If IChe Opo)-7ositi*' on in the Senate continues to deny Supply,<br />
n-owever, Government employees may face som-e proa. nrsis<br />
, n that event I would ask them to accept some personal but<br />
_ e-moorarv sacrifices i n the interest of tewelfPare ol hi<br />
' o ustr-alians. T can assure thee1-that the0 2-o-verrnn-ent iS<br />
loo-: inc an-d wi2ccntinue to look at every possi blFe w% 17ay oT.<br />
sa ~ c the icu1tie-s and inconv. oni once whilichnu face its<br />
/ 2 </p>
<p>2.<br />
cm-,) lovees and that t[-he Governnlen 4. c V. cveloping schemes<br />
which wil co-, l with the. exis--a and which are<br />
imed at all-viating, as much as thsieb -problms<br />
which micht con-front e! mplovees afterT. the<br />
Cn of] N Ibar. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
