<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>23051</transcript-id>
    <title>A spirit distilled in the heat of battle</title>
    <prime-minister>Abbott, Tony</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130918 - 20150915</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/10/2013</release-date>
    <release-type></release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>When nature is at its worst, Australia tends to be at its best. This week, thousands of volunteers have worked around the clock to tame New South Wales' most difficult bush fires in years.</p>
<p>All Australians grieve for what hundreds of people around New South Wales have lost this week.</p>
<p>If you have been affected by the fires, assistance is available through the Australian Government Disaster Recovery Payment.  This payment provides $1,000 per eligible adult and $400 per eligible child to assist those whose homes have been lost or seriously damaged.</p>
<p>Information about assistance is available on the Australian Government Disaster Assist website at <a href="http://www.disasterassist.gov.au">www.disasterassist.gov.au</a> or on 180 22 66.</p>
<p>If you live in a bushfire prone area, I hope that you might develop your own bushfire survival plan if you have not already done so.  If you haven’t prepared one, there’s a plan available at <a href="http://www.rfs.nsw.gov.au">www.rfs.nsw.gov.au</a> which has been put together by experts.  Remember that leaving early is always the safest option.  Fires are fast and changes in weather make them unpredictable.</p>
<p>Thirteen years as a volunteer fire fighter has taught me to respect the force and ferocity of bushfire. Fire can travel much faster and further than you can imagine.  No house, property or animals are worth putting yourself or your family in harm’s way when you are thoroughly prepared.  If in doubt, leave!</p>
<p>To the Rural Fire Services’ 70,000 volunteers, I wish you strength and stamina because the full force of summer is yet to arrive.</p>
<p>The 2,000 brigades of the RFS prepare throughout the year for any eventuality.</p>
<p>My own brigade at Davidson is typical of the volunteer brigades across the country.  When we put on the  yellow uniform we aren’t mechanics, accountants, public servants or indeed, Members of Parliament, we are a team dedicated to fighting a fire and looking out for each other.</p>
<p>The word ‘heroic’ is often used in association with fire fighters. I have never met a volunteer fire fighter who thinks in those terms.  We are simply men and women trained to do a job.  On our truck, everyone has each others' back.</p>
<p>I do want to pay tribute to the support teams that back up our fire fighting units. Every RFS unit is backed  by a team of radio operators, cooks and logistics staff who quickly materialise to support an instant army of fire fighters.</p>
<p>Community groups like Red Cross, Salvos, Lions and Rotary and so many others also lend a hand and provide ongoing assistance to communities as well as to the emergency services volunteers.</p>
<p>I particularly want to thank the employers across Australia who support our fire fighters and SES workers.  It’s not easy to lose your staff to the emergency services with almost no notice and inevitably without complaint.  You too help our community.</p>
<p>There could be a long and difficult fire season ahead.  The citizens of a "sunburnt country" will rise to this challenge, as we always do.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
