<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>16443</transcript-id>
    <title>Extra Support for Young Jobseekers    </title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/03/2009</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Thousands of young Australians will get training and support to develop the basic skills they need to get and keep a job under new Australian Government funding announced today. </p>
<p>From 1 July 2009, an additional 3,650 pre-vocational training and support places will be made available for vulnerable young jobseekers through the Australian Apprenticeships Access Program. </p>
<p>The Rudd Government will invest $30.2 million to expand the Australian Apprenticeship Access Program, which provides at-risk jobseekers with the support they need to pursue an apprenticeship or training and then move into skilled employment.</p>
<p>This measure will provide assistance of around $6 million for an estimated 730 young Queenslanders.</p>
<p>The Australian Apprenticeships Access Program gives job seekers who experience barriers to skilled employment nationally recognised pre-vocational training, support and assistance. The program is provided at no cost to participants.</p>
<p>The new places will support 19-24 year old jobseekers who are most likely to be affected by the impact of the economic downturn on the labour market and also those made redundant.</p>
<p>Eligible young jobseekers will receive tailored support to move into an Australian Apprenticeship or further training and ultimately into skilled employment as the economy recovers.</p>
<p>These new places will see participants receive:</p>
<p>     * a minimum of 150 hours of pre-vocational training to improve their basic skills in areas like literacy and numeracy; </p>
<p>     * up to 13 weeks job search support; and </p>
<p>     * post-placement support in an apprenticeship, further training or employment.</p>
<p>This measure builds on recently announced measures to secure Australian Apprenticeships and assist retrenched workers, including: </p>
<p>     * $145 million to assist apprentices and trainees who have lost their job to complete their training with another employer or a group training organisation </p>
<p>     * $9.7 million to assist apprentices and trainees to continue their training through a registered training organisation. </p>
<p>     * preference to be given to businesses which demonstrate a commitment to retain and employ new trainees and apprentices when new Australian Government funded infrastructure projects go to tender. </p>
<p>     * $298 million to be invested in employment services to ensure workers made redundant receive personalised assistance and advice to help them find work as soon as possible.</p>
<p>The Government has acted decisively to support economic activity through its $10.4 billion Economic Security Strategy, and the $42 billion Nation Building and Jobs Plan. </p>
<p>This action has been specifically designed to support demand for labour in the economy. </p>
<p>For those people who through no fault of their own are unable to gain or retain work during the economic slowdown, the Government is investing in a range of measures to help people improve their skills.</p>
<p>These investments will increase the ability of people who are now out of work to gain better and higher paying jobs in the future. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
