<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10357</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP GENERAL MEETING OF NSW STATE COUNCIL</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/05/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010357.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Fax from 3 Iit 321UrL a reJ<br />
, MAY 26 ' 97 10: 42 P. 3<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
24 May 1997 ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE HON JOHN HOWARD NIP<br />
ENE* RtL-* NEETING-OF'NSW STATE-COUNCILI<br />
It is as always a great delight for me to be with you this morning to say a few words<br />
about the Federal political scene and to share wvith you a very important theme as we<br />
approach the half way point of our first term in Government, And that is the theme of<br />
keeping faith. And this morning I want to develop with you the way ii which the<br />
Coalition Government has kept faith with the people who voted for it, how we have<br />
kept faith with the interests of the Australian community and how we have kept faith<br />
with the long term goals that we, as the Liberal Party, have.<br />
When we were elected in March of last year it was rightly said that there were many<br />
people who voted for us on that occasion who had never previously done so. And that<br />
one of our prime responsibilities was to keep faith with those people commonly<br />
called, often called, the battlers of Australia.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen, one of the biggest problems that we inherited when we became<br />
the Government of Australia in March of last year was, of course, the appalling state of<br />
the budget deficit. I said then, and this is true, that there were sonic features of the<br />
Australian economy that wvere good, that there were some that were bad and there<br />
were some that were very bad. And one of them that wvas very bad was the fact that<br />
we inherited a budget deficit of $ 10.5 billion. In the last financial year that the<br />
KeatinglBeazley government was in power the national debt of Australia that's the<br />
total of all the debts run up by governments in the past had risen to almost twenty per<br />
cent of the total wealth generated on an annual basis by the entire Australian<br />
community. And I am very proud to say that at the end of our first term in<br />
Government, we will have turned that $ 10.5 billion deficit into a surplus of $ 1.6 billion.<br />
Ane Afl 4 0 r3 fl.. 4 </p>
<p>Fax from 3 It 26/ 05/ 97 10: 53 Pg: 2<br />
MAPY 26 ' 97 10: 42 P. 4<br />
Now it's not the most exciting thing in the world to talk about, it's not the only thing<br />
in the world to talk about, but it's pretty fuandamental because if you are going broke, if<br />
you are not paying your way, if you are borrowing on the backs of your children's<br />
future, which is what previous governments had done, then you don't have many<br />
options and you don't have much of a capacity to do anything else. But in the coming<br />
financial year. 1997/ 98, my Government will repay $ 5.3 billion of Paul Keating's debts<br />
and I am very proud indeed to be able to say that.<br />
I'm very proud to-be able-to say that we-won't be-going into the financial markets in<br />
1997/ 98 to borrowv anything because there will be no borrowing requirement by the<br />
Commonwealth. And what, of course, that means is that we are laying the foundation<br />
for a stronger and more prosperous and a faster growing future for all of the Australian<br />
c o mmun ity.<br />
So the first news, and the really good news about the Budget brought down two weeks<br />
ago, is -thatit-has kept faith-with our ffundamental responsibility to-repair the budget, to<br />
repair the national accounts of Australia and to make certain that once again this<br />
country is able to pay its wvay, and Ae make no apology at all for having given it such<br />
an enormous priority. But it's not just something that makes you feel good but it's<br />
something that delivers hard and credible and strong gains and strong rewards and<br />
strong benefits. There can be no doubt at a in my mind and there can be no doubt at<br />
all in the minds of any fair observer but if it hadn't been for the deficit cutting policies<br />
of my Government, we would have not have seen a two per cent reduction in interest<br />
rates since we came to power in March of last year.<br />
Those who created the problem, that's Mr Beazley and Mr Evans, can crow all they<br />
like about how it would have happened anyway, and it's all the result of something<br />
else. The brutal reality is that because we are not borrowing and in fact in paying debt,<br />
there's greater room for the Reserve Bank to do what it did yesterday. And once<br />
again we are keeping faith with the battlers. Delivering interest rate cuts which on an<br />
average housing loan have been worth $ 225 a month, that's over $ 50 a week let me<br />
repeat over $ 50 a week added to your disposable income, after tax, to the average<br />
wage and salary earner. I can't think of a greater delivery on the commitment we<br />
made to the battlers of Australia in March of last year than to be able to deliver that<br />
kind of reward for their support, for their wage restraint, and for the fiscal policies of<br />
the Howard Government.<br />
So ladies and gentleman there is a great message in yesterday's interest rate reduction.<br />
And that message is that there are rewards for wage restraint. It's much better for a<br />
wage and salary earner in Australia to show wage restraint and get an interest rate cut<br />
on a housing loan, than it is to lack wage moderation and to have the high wages<br />
consurned by the progressive taxation system and higher interest rates. </p>
<p>Fax from 3 11 26/ 05/ 97 18: 53 Pg: 3<br />
MA~ Y 26 ' 97 10: 43P.<br />
The strongest possible message that should go to the wage and salary earners of<br />
Australia is that if you continue to show wage restraint you'll get fuirther interest rate<br />
relief. That's the message that ought to go to the wage and salary earners of Australia.<br />
Good on you for showing wage restraint. Good on you for being part of a combined<br />
effort to tackle the economic problems of Australia. And there is a reward at the end<br />
of the road and that reward is lower interest rates. And it is worth far more than a<br />
wage increase, far more every time. And I think that is a reality that has dawned on a<br />
large number of people in Australia. It is perhaps the reality that terrifies our political<br />
opponents but it gives happiness and satisfaction to the battlers of Austraia and to<br />
middle Australia, because they deserve rewards. I mean let us -not forget that we -still<br />
have very high real interest rates in this country. They may have come down, but when<br />
you've got an inflation rate of two per cent they ought to come down and there ought<br />
to be a reward. And that is what I think the wage and salary earners of Australia have<br />
received over the last fourteen months, and that is why they know that we have kept<br />
We weren't elected to government to ignore the mainstream of the Australian<br />
community and we have kept faith with that mainstream. And the budget that Peter<br />
Costello delivered the week before last did the job on deficit reduction. It also, or the<br />
first time since Federation, delivered something that, year after year, people have asked<br />
me: " Why can't we have in Australia and that is an across-the-board tax incentive for<br />
savings?" I have lost count of the number of meetings I've been to, I've lost count of<br />
the number of resolutions that have been passed by Liberal Party gatherings calling for<br />
a savings break. Those innumerable occasions when I've sort of been pinned against<br />
the wall by an irate branch member who said: " Why is it that we are taxed twice on<br />
savings, why is it that we pay income tax on our income and then we put what's left<br />
over into some investment and wve're taxed on the return for that investment. Why is<br />
it?" Well it's a good question. I was never able to answer it. But I always said, well<br />
you know, good idea, good point, take it on board. And all the other sort of excuses<br />
you're left with when you don't have an answer. You've all heard it, probably every<br />
one otf you has had the conversation with me. I feel like it after twenty two years.<br />
But at long last we're able to do something about it. And quite unapologetically it is<br />
non means tested. Cheryl Kernot wants to put a means test at $ 35,000 on it. And<br />
extraordinarily enough I am getting criticised for breaking a promise because the<br />
savings initiative we brought in in the budget is more generous than what we promised<br />
during the election campaign. Now this is the new ALP and from some sections of<br />
the Australian media definition of a broken promise. If you deliver more than you<br />
promise you have broken your promise.<br />
So in other words, ladies and gentleman, be on notice from now on, if wve do in any<br />
area more than what we said we were going to do, you can bet your bottom dollar that<br />
sonme of those smart alecs will be on our backs, saying-, " Oh there they go again,<br />
dishonouring their promises." </p>
<p>Fax from 3 11 26/ 05/ 97 16: 53 Pg: 4<br />
MAY 26 ' 97 10: 44 P. 6<br />
I'm proud of the fact that I over delivered on my savings tax promise. I'm proud of<br />
the fact that I've over delivered on the capital gains tax concession for small business.<br />
And that's another group in the community with whom we have well and truly kept<br />
faith, and that is the small business community. I said during the election campaign<br />
that providing incentives to small business so that they could generate more jobs was<br />
one of the great goals of a Coalition government. And we've kept faith with all of the<br />
promises we made. We delivered the relief in relation to provisional tax.<br />
From tile first of July this year, every small business operator in Australia will be able<br />
to. sell. his-or-her business and -thirty-per cent, let me say, of new small businesses<br />
being established in Australia now are owvned and operated by women. And I say that<br />
very advisedly because it's one of the great growth areas of the Australian economy<br />
where the influence of the women in our community is being~ increasingly felt. And<br />
from the first of July this year, any person who sells a small business, whether it's<br />
operatedthrougha-compay, a-partnership-or a-tru-st or whatever, will bec able-to invest<br />
the proceeds of the sale of that business into any other kind of business. It do esn't<br />
have to be the same, or anything like it. You can go from being a bookmaker to a<br />
software operator, whatever you like. Doesn't matter what the combination is. You<br />
can invest up to $ Sniillioii out of the proceeds of the sale of that business without being<br />
liable for a cent of capital gains tax. Now that represents an over-delivery of a promise<br />
and it represents a massiv'e new incentive for people to put their money into small<br />
business. We've also changed the industrial relations Jaws to help small business. We made<br />
major changes to Laurie Brereton's unfair dismissal law. And we had those changes<br />
contained in the industrial relations amendments. And then six weeks ago when I<br />
announced my small business response to the Bell Report, we went a step further in<br />
relation to unfair dismissal. We said that any firm in Australia that employed fewer<br />
than fifteen people would be completely exempt completely and utterly exempt from<br />
any kind of unfair dismissal law in relation to a person who had been employed for less<br />
than one year.<br />
Those of you in the audience who run small businesses will know that if you could feel<br />
that you can put somnebody on for a trial for up to a year, and if it didn't work out you<br />
could let them know without ending up in the industrial relations commission, at the<br />
end of a fairly modest claim like $ 15,000 or $ 20,000, modest it may be for the claimant<br />
but crippling for you if you're starting a new business then you might be inclined to<br />
take the person on. And that was our thinking it's a pretty reasonable proposition<br />
and we brought down a regulation to give effect to it but predictably perhaps the<br />
Labor Party and the Australian Democrats and Senator Harradine have said they're<br />
going to vote to disallow it. They're going to vote to stop us giving small business in<br />
Australia a greater incentive to take on people, particularly young people. Because thle<br />
truth is that we will only substantially reduce unemployment in this country if we can<br />
get the small firms that employ three or four people to employing four or five or six<br />
that's how you're going to reduce unemployment in Australia. You won't reduce<br />
unemployment by looking to the big companies. They're all down-sizing. You'll<br />
reduce unemployment in this country by taking the shackles off small business, and one<br />
of the ways you take shackles off smiall business is to take away the intirniidatorv effect<br />
of unfair dismissal laws. </p>
<p>Fax from 3 11 26/ 85/ 97 16: 53 Pg:<br />
MAY 26 ' 97 10: 44 P. 7<br />
It is as plain as the proverbial nose on one's face, yet sure enough echoing the<br />
instructions of the trade union movement of Australia who told the Labor Patty they<br />
couldn't support it. Two weeks the federal Parliamentary Caucus said it was going to<br />
vote to disallow the regulations. And the Trade Union movement of Australia, what a<br />
sorry group. I mean, if you think of the last 14 months, what's the most vivid memory<br />
of the Trade Union movement of Australia trying the bash down the door of<br />
Parliament House on the evening of the Feder-al Budget after having heard an<br />
inflammatory speech from the President of the ACTU and the Secretary of the ACTU.<br />
And -who -was-oDn the plat-form with them butnone other then the Leader of the Federal<br />
Opposition. The fact of the matter is that they contribute nothing to the public debate about<br />
employment. They contribute nothing to the public debate about Australia's economic<br />
-future.. The Trade-Union -movement-in. Australia at the present time is locked into-n<br />
introspective, backward looking attitude towards protecting what they have rather than<br />
trying to build and grow the strength of the Australian economy, and their attitude to<br />
unfair dismissal laws is evidence of that, </p>
<p>Fax from 3 11 26/ 05/ 97 10: 53 Pg: 6<br />
MAY 26 ' 97 10: 45 P. 8<br />
Ladies and gentlemen wve have kept faith. We've kept faith with our families of<br />
Australia. We introduced on time. without deduction, in fulll the $ 1 billion family tax<br />
initiative from the first of January with greater equity to families with young children,<br />
particularly those living on one income.<br />
On 1 July this year we will again keep faith with the families of Australia by delivering<br />
in fll, on time, without deduction the $ 600 million tax incentive scheme encouraging<br />
people to maintain or take out private health insurance.<br />
And.. what-a shame is that-our predecessors, what a crying -shame it is that our<br />
predecessors hadn't acted in this area years ago. If something~ like this had been<br />
introduced in the early 1990s we wvould nowv have 40 per cent of the Australian<br />
population with private health insurance, instead of 34 per cent and they were told in<br />
the early 1990s by the ANIA, they were told by the then Minister, they were told by<br />
everybody-who-hac4any. understading of what private, health. insurance wa-al. about<br />
that unless you provided an incentive, unless you put a floor under the fall in private<br />
health' insurance, it would gather momentum and run the risk of becoming a selffulfilling<br />
prophecy. And now you have the deplorable situation wvhere even sections of<br />
the current leadership of the AMA are denigrating private health insurance.<br />
We have inherited a very parlous situation in this area. I believe that the private health<br />
initiatives that come into operation on the first of July will staunch the deterioration in<br />
this area. They will put a line under the fall and over time they will lead to more<br />
people taking out private health insurance. But we are certainly late in the game<br />
because of the inactivity, the indolence, the ideological hostility to private health<br />
insurance of the former federal Labor Government.<br />
But we will keep faith in that area. We will also keep faith with the retired people....<br />
We promised that we would put them on the same footing as pensioners in relation to<br />
the tax free rebate and by the end of our term, first term in government, that will have<br />
occurred. . And the savings initiatives will be of enormous benefit to self funded retirees arnd let<br />
me say to them that it wvill be of enormous benefit if it is non-means tested.<br />
And attempts to means test it, particularly of the type proposed by Cheryl Kernot,<br />
show a complete misunderstanding, a complete misunderstanding of the situation and<br />
the needs of self-funded retired people in Australia and they completely ignore the facts<br />
that although interest rate reductions are of great benefit to small business, to home<br />
buyers, to battlers who have young families to bring up, they're not all enjoyed for selffunded<br />
retirees.<br />
I know that. My Government knows that. My colleagues know that. And that is wvhy<br />
we have a non-means tested savings rebate. That is why we have a tax incentive for<br />
private health insurance. That is why we brought in a tax rebate for self funded<br />
retirees and that is why we will always follow policies that keep faith with self-fuinded<br />
retirees. </p>
<p>Fax from 311t 26/ 05/ 97 18: 53 Pg: 7<br />
-MA4Y 26 ' 97 10: 45 P. 9<br />
But just remember who doesn't know that. Just remember that Cheryl Kernot and<br />
Kim Beazley want to means test it. Just remember that they are opposed to the health<br />
insurance rebate, Just remember that when they were in Government for 13 years they<br />
hit the self fUnded retirees in the eye by treating them in a very discriminating fashion.<br />
Once again, my friends, this is an area where we have kept faith with the people who<br />
supported us and kept faith with the Australian community.<br />
It remains the fact, ladies and gentlemen, that unemployment in Australia is still<br />
unacceptably high. As always. unemployment is the. last of the indicators to come -Sood<br />
ater a deep recession. We have made major changes to the industrial relations systemn<br />
which over time because of their greater flexibility, their greater focus on wvorkplace<br />
agreements, their rejection of the compulsory role of trade unions, will produce freer,<br />
more flexible workplaces and ' will add to job creation.<br />
It is also true, ladies and gentlemen, that you cannot hope for a sustained fall in<br />
unemployment until we have a sustained and higher level of economic growth.<br />
The great problem that this country has had year after year is that it has never been<br />
able to run the economy at a high level of economic growth for a long period of time<br />
without something going wrong and the shutters had to be brought down to stop the<br />
current account blowing out or inflation going through the roof.<br />
And we have had these major breaks on the rate of economic growth. We've had<br />
these road humps along the path to sustained economic growth and we are starting to<br />
see daylight on that front.<br />
We are now in an era of very lowv inflation. We now have interest rates that are at pre-<br />
Whitlam levels. We haven't had housing interest rates where they are at the present<br />
time since the late 1 960s and it is an extraordinary achievement and it has a long term<br />
significance if we can maintain it for the strength and stability of middle Australia. It is<br />
v'ery important to their psychology. It is very important to the outlook for average<br />
AustralIan families.<br />
We have begun to tackle the structural impediments to Australian labour markets and<br />
we have gone a long way down that path although there is further distance to be<br />
travelled. We have fundamentally tackled the problem of the structural budget deficit. We are<br />
not just relying on asset sales for a transient improvement in the Budget deficit. We<br />
have made long term improvements to the budget deficit,<br />
And by the turn of the century spending levels, as a proportion of national wealth<br />
generated each year in this country, % ill be at the sort of levels they were in the early<br />
1970s. And to go further than that will, of course, be to threaten the fundamentals of<br />
the social security safety net which we will not do or to threaten such fundamental<br />
areas as a necessary level of defence expenditure. </p>
<p>Fax froim 3 11 26/ 05/ 97 10: 53 Pg: 8<br />
MAY 26 ' 97 10: 46<br />
And on that point, ladies and gentlemen, and on the question of keeping faith, let me<br />
say another thing of which I am particularly proud, is that my Government has kept<br />
Cith with its commitment to maintain the level of defence expenditure.<br />
I know it is fashionable in some corners to say you don't need any defence<br />
commitment now that the Cold War is over. I know it is fashionable in some circles to<br />
say that there is a never ending, bottomless pit called the peace dividend and you can<br />
keep on cutting and cutting and cutting defence expenditure.<br />
Well, -that -is. a very misguided notion. I mean, our-levels of-defence expenditure now<br />
are at historically low levels and it would be nothing short of a repudiation of our<br />
responsibilities as a Government to cut them even fuarther. And that is why we have<br />
quarantined them from expenditure reductions. At the same time we are going to<br />
achieve a major shift in the emphasis of defence expenditure away from what I might<br />
loosely.-call offialdem towa~ s-those men -and women. in the firont-ine<br />
So, ladies and gentlemen we have kept faith on all fronts. We have kept faith with our<br />
responsibility to repair tile economy of Australia. We have kept faith with small<br />
business. We have kept faith with families. We have kept faith with self fuinded<br />
retirees and very importantly we have kept faith with the battlers of Australia who<br />
deserted the Australian Labor Party in droves in Mlarch of last year and the latest and<br />
most dramatic piece of evidence was the interest Tate reduction that occurred<br />
yesterday. And let me say in relation to that that the major banks of Australia carry a very heavy<br />
responsibility in the interest of their customers and the interest of Australian<br />
community to pass on in full and without reduction and without the delay the fall<br />
measure of the official interest rate reduction.<br />
Let me make it clear, ladies and gentlemen, I am no bank-basher, I never have been, I<br />
understand the role of banks in the Australian financial system. I inaugurated a<br />
landmark inquiry that led to the deregulation of the Australian financial system. I<br />
supported the introduction of foreign banks into Australia. I continue to support tile<br />
further deregulation of the banking system but it's pretty hard to believe that we have a<br />
highly competitive banking system at the present time, when there can be delays of the<br />
kind that we are apparently about to witness in the passing on of reductions in official<br />
interest rates and those who argue that there are adequate levels of competition at the<br />
present time might have a bit of explaining to do if that apparent tardiness in passing<br />
on those increases actually occurs.<br />
So, let me say again that it is in the national interest that those reductions be passed on<br />
quickly and in full. The battlers of Australian who have waited a long time for their<br />
reward and they are entitled to have it on time without delay and without reduction.<br />
Finally, ladies and gentlemen, can I say something, you'd be disappointed if I didn't.<br />
Can I say something about our political opponents .( interjection). . no, I'm a<br />
charitable man. </p>
<p>Faxf1r1o2' 6~/ 05/ 97 10: 53 Pg: 9<br />
MAY 26 ' 97 10: 46 P. 11<br />
Can I say something about this marveilous thing called privatisation. I had a talk to<br />
Peter Collins about this yesterday. Very interesting thing privatisation. That was the<br />
thing that way back in the mid 1 980s I started advocating when I was first Leader of<br />
the Opposition and the Labor Party said: oh dreadlial.<br />
With their hand on their heart they said we would never privatise Qantas. We would<br />
never privatise it was then Trans Australian Airlines. But, of course, the<br />
Commonwealth Bank. I mean, the sweetest fruit of all of the tree of Barcaldine the<br />
Commonwealth Bank. How could you ever privatise the Commonwealth Bank? Sure<br />
enough that!' s what they said when we. were advocating it. Then they win. an election<br />
in 1987 and Bob Hawke says: oh well, we'd better have another look at it.<br />
So they did. They had another look at it. And then they started to privatise Qantas and<br />
Trans Australia Airlines and then you camne to the 1990 election and we had a policy of<br />
-privatising. the. CommnmwealiBank, and Paul -Keating-said oh, . nov-he said, what's<br />
this, he said I'll write to them all, So he wrote to every single member of the<br />
Commonwealth Bank Employees Association saying that it was a solemn commitment,<br />
a solemn commitment this one, a solemn commitment of the Australian Labor Party<br />
that it would never sell shares in the Commonwealth Bank. They even put out a<br />
prospectus after they decided to sell half of it, saying they didn't sell the other half<br />
I mean, if the provisions of the Companies Act was applied Ralph Willis would have<br />
been in the slammer as a result of that.<br />
But no, they ended up and of course the crowning glory of it all was that Beazley had<br />
to come running to us before the 1993 Budget to guarantee our support in the Senate<br />
if they went ahead wvith the sale of it.<br />
I mean, we were consistent, we were policy consistent. We have always argued that<br />
Governments have no business running commercial undertakings. And we have been<br />
arguing it for years, we have been arguing it without alteration. But, of course, I<br />
thought the hypocrisy had sort of scaled Himalayan heights in relation to the sale of the<br />
Commonwealth Bank but then of course we come to Telstra.<br />
We comle to dear Teistra. At the last election we said we would sell one third of it and<br />
I said then and Mr Egan and Mr Carr here in New South Wales have delivered proof<br />
positive of what I've said wvas right. But the real difference on privatisation between<br />
myself and the Labor Party at the last election wvas that if they won the election they<br />
were going to sell the lot having promised not to sell any of it, but if we won the<br />
election we would sell a third, precisely what we said before the election we were<br />
going to sell. And what Carr and Egan are proposing to do here in New South Wales,<br />
which is, of course, a direct steal of the policies of the Coalition here in New South<br />
Wales. But I have always said, and I said it again to Peter Collins yesterday, in politics<br />
as in life, imitation Is the sincerest form of flattery.<br />
They've decided to do something that federally they did when they were in<br />
Government yet hypocritically they promised not to do when they were in Opposition. </p>
<p>Fax from 3 11 26/ 05/ 97 10: 53 Pg:<br />
MAY 26 ' 97 10: 47 P. 12<br />
Time and time again the Labor Party has gone to the Australian people, be it here in<br />
New South Wales, be it federally, be it anywhere in Australia and have said: We will<br />
never sell any of the jewels in Labor crown. We will never sell any of these great<br />
Australian assets, that Ben Chifley and Eddie Ward would roll in their graves if they<br />
thought any of these assets were being sold and yet when they get into office they<br />
relentlessly say: We need the money, so let's sell, sell the assets.<br />
It is a bankrupt, hopeless, hypocritical policy. They believe in nothing, they stand for<br />
nothing. And they demonstrate by that kind of blanket searing hypocrisy why they are<br />
no-longer-the. government of Australia-and why-they are held in such low-esteem as the<br />
Government of this State.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen, Michael said at the beginning that the last three months marked<br />
the end of the honeymoon. Well, let me say I've always thought that the basis of a<br />
long-and stable and. happy marriage is a.. very long and. happy. honeymoon.-.......<br />
We had a very long and happy honeymoon as a Government and I can'tellyou we are<br />
going to have a very long and stable marriage with the Australian people.<br />
Thank you </p>
<p>Fax f'raom 3 It2/ 5/ 71: 5 g1<br />
MAY 26 ' 97 10: 47 P. 13<br />
Q A Session:<br />
Question: Prime Minister wvould you consider provided funds from the<br />
Commonwealth Government for the screening of prostate cancer which is prevalent in<br />
men, particularly over 50 years. This disease is more common in men than breast<br />
cancer in women and if left undetected can result in death. I understand that this<br />
screening is supported by the.. Association in New South Wales.<br />
Prime Minister: I was briefly associated with the launch of a video on prostate<br />
-cancer. put-tege# 4ieriby the. Department of Veterans Affairs and-I do think it is an.-illness<br />
which should be talked about with the same degree openness and the same<br />
acknowledgment of the threat that it poses to the health of men and breast cancer and<br />
other forms of cancer it talks about in relation to the health of women.<br />
1 wiR -consider what-yotu ve-put4o me-and-willtalk , to-Mike Wooldt-idge a-beut--it*<br />
Question: Prime Minister thank you very much, it was an inspiring speech. I have a<br />
question. Is it possible for you to take out time on television and make that sort of<br />
speech to the Australian people who regrettably, every time I see you on television<br />
You're being asked some ridiculous question about something of really no great<br />
interest to people other than journos. If you could really take time out to make that<br />
sort of speech to the Australian people ( inaudible) I don't believe they do.<br />
Prime Minister: .( Inaudible)..<br />
Question: I am speaking to you this morning as a six generation citizen of the city of<br />
Newcastle, I am pleased to hear your affirmation of faith of battlers.<br />
This week there couldn't have been a more miserable Or embattled city in the whole of<br />
Australia from what we felt in Newcastle. BEI has confirmed that it will withdraw<br />
from Newcastle and we are in a situation where we wvill be losing very shortly 2,500<br />
jobs from the current skilled workforce. The question is, Prime Minister. we are<br />
looking at a situation where the best remedy of loss of workforce would be with<br />
( inaudible) steel... Can You give us a pledge of your assistance to the steel workers in<br />
Newcastle today?<br />
Prime Minister; Well, can I just say a couple of things in relation to the BHP I<br />
have said that we will match the offer made by the New South Wales Government of<br />
assistance. We think that the way it was proposed was kneejerk, fairly superficial.<br />
We think that there are better ways of spending the resources. We'll also look to<br />
BHP for a great contribution than was involved in the New South Wales proposal.<br />
We think that B HP should match the contributions to the Governments and we will<br />
certainly work to that end. I don't ( inaudible) deliberately, but I think it's a fact of life.<br />
Next Thursday, at their request, I will meet a delegation of steel workers. They're not<br />
being filtered through the ACTU, they're coming to see me direct. And, a number of<br />
my Ministers have been to Newcastle already and I intend to also go to Newcastle<br />
sometime within the next few weeks. I haven't picked a particular day. There's no<br />
point in going there just for show, I want to talk to the steelworkers, I want to talk to<br />
26/ 05/ 97 10: 53 Pg: 11 </p>
<p>Fax from 3 11 26/ 65/ 97 10: 53 Pg: 12<br />
MAY 26 ' 97 10: 48 P. 14<br />
the Civic leaders, I want to talk to the Chamber of Commerce and the elected<br />
representatives of both political persuasions.<br />
Of course, we have a Newcastle-based ( inaudible) Bob Hawke, this idea that<br />
Newcastle/ Hunter is a Labor area, is quite wrong, it is not. It's a mixed political area<br />
and we should try to tackle this in a non-political fashion.<br />
Simon Crean, I trust, believes that ( inaudible)<br />
It won.' t-be quite as devastating now-as it would -have been ten or fifteen. years ago,<br />
because there has been a diversification. But Newcastle is a symbol of industrial<br />
Australia. I understand that. And I understand the psychological impact of it. am not<br />
unfamiliar with Newcastle. I have, through my wife, I have family connections with<br />
the area ( inaudible)<br />
( inaudible) can I just make one thing perfectly clear, it wouldn't have been any<br />
different. If the Labor Party had won the last Federal election, BlIP would still be<br />
closing down. Can I make that very clear they're now running around saying that if<br />
we'd been in power it would have been different ( inaudible). I mean while they were<br />
in power, BHP's payroll went from 56,000 to 24,000. ( inaudible)<br />
But I am very sympathetic with the area. I know the psychological impact of what has<br />
happened. We will match the New South Wales Government's offer. We will<br />
encourage the company to match the contributions of the two governments and we will<br />
see that what resources we put into it are all wisely spent. I've sent a number of<br />
Ministers there already. I'll be going there again sometime in the next few weeks and<br />
I'll be seeing ( inaudible) next Thursday unhindered by the ACTU.<br />
Question: Is the next Budget likely to be showing more of these incentives ( inaudible)<br />
and are tax cuts likely. ( inaudible). Also, just another question, ( inaudible)..<br />
Prime Minister-( inaudible) well, I don't know that I want to speculate about next<br />
year's Budget. But as I often say when I'm being interviewed, if I can get a wvord ill<br />
with some of themn. I often say ( inaudible) always expect a few surprises. and I think<br />
one of the things that people should understand is that we are about sensible reform<br />
and sensible change, there's been a bit of debate about taxation over the last week, and<br />
can I just repeat that if you're thinking about taxation reform in this country you've<br />
got to ask yourself three questions. The first question is will it help create more jobs?<br />
And the second question is will it make Australia more competitive, and the third<br />
question is will it lift the living standards of the Australian people? So they're the three<br />
benchmarks against which we will assess any changes we make in relation to the<br />
taxation system. And the reason why we brought in the savings initiative is that I'm a<br />
great believer in incentives. You can change ( inaudible) if you give people the right<br />
incentive. And in giving people the incentive to save is a great gift. And what we've<br />
done is tackled the savings problem on two fronts. By reducing the deficit we're<br />
tackling public savings, and by giving people tax incentives we're encouraging private<br />
savings. When the two things wvork together they complement each other and that<br />
really is what a good sa~ rings policy is all about. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
