<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5122</transcript-id>
    <title>RHODESIAN CONSTITUTIONAL CONFERENCE</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/08/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005122.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
) S T KA L I<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA 15 AUGUST, 1979<br />
RHODESIAN CONSTITUTIONAL CONFERENCE<br />
The Prime Minister, Malcolm Fraser, has welcomed the early<br />
initiative of the British Government in calling a Constitutional<br />
Conference on Rhodesia to begin on 10 September. It is a most<br />
encouraging development in the long history of confl. ict which<br />
has brought suffering and distress to a large part of Africa,<br />
which with peace could have a promising future. Peace and<br />
prosperity can'only flow from co-operation among all groups of<br />
Rhodesians on the basis of genuine majority rule. Human dignity<br />
demands a constitutional settlement based on the framework agreed<br />
at the Cormmonwealth Conference in Lusaka.<br />
Australia has been particularly concerned to see that provisions<br />
for constitutional amendment should be consistent with the general<br />
objective of providing for effective majority rule and that<br />
similar considerations should be incorporated in arrangements<br />
for administration of the Defence Forces, Public Service and the<br />
Police. The Prime Minister expressed the strong hope that the leaders of<br />
the Patriotic Front and the Salisbury Government would participate<br />
in the forthcoming discussions in the same spirit of practical<br />
good sense which the Front Line States and Britain had brought to<br />
the Lusaka conference, making it one of the most successful in the<br />
history of the Commonwealth.<br />
We cannot ignore the difficulties which are bound to arise along<br />
the way but an important requirement now is to ensure that the<br />
process of discussion gets under way as early as possible and that<br />
the momentum developed at Lusaka is maintained.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
