<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1822</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE RT HON. J. G GORTON, M.P. ON REPORT OF ROYAL COMMISSIONERS ON STATEMENT BY LIEUTENANT - COMMANDER CABBAN</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/04/1968</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001822.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA<br />
SPEECH BY<br />
The Rt Hon. J. G. GORTON, M. P.<br />
ON<br />
REPORT OF ROYAL COMMISSIONERS ON<br />
STATEMENT BY LIEUTENANT-COMMANDER<br />
CABBAN<br />
[ Fromn the Parliamentary Debates," 2 April 1968]<br />
Mr GORTON ( Higgins-Prime Minister)<br />
[ 8.50-Mr Speaker, we have heard tonight<br />
from the Leader of the Opposition ( Mr<br />
Whitlam) an exposition which appears to<br />
attack and to seek to attack not only the<br />
Naval Board, the Government and myself<br />
but also and in particular the findings of<br />
the Royal Commissioners who were set up<br />
to conduct an examination and who, being,<br />
I imagine the honourable member would<br />
agree, completely impartial, should not be<br />
subjected to this kind of attack and to this<br />
kind of denigration for the findings they<br />
made on the evidence presented to them<br />
over such a period of time. But of course<br />
the attack was not confined to the Commissioners<br />
and their findings. it was also -xtended<br />
in a way in which no politician<br />
ought to extend an attack in this place to<br />
a public servant to the extent of describing<br />
the Secretary of the Department of the<br />
Navy as ' this creature'. This is a shameful<br />
way for the Leader of the Opposition to<br />
carry on. If there is to be some opposition<br />
to a course that is taken by a senior public<br />
servant, if there is to be some claim that<br />
that course was wrong, let it at least be<br />
made in a reasonable way and let it not<br />
be attached to this kind of childish denigration<br />
of a man who cannot support himself<br />
in this place.<br />
14964168 It has been pointed out to me by a member<br />
of the Opposition that I have 18<br />
minutes left; but there are a number of<br />
other honourable members on this side who<br />
have a lot more than 18 minutes left and<br />
who will be well able to defend themselves<br />
against the improper attacks made upon<br />
them. Let me just indicate to the House the<br />
approach that the Government makes on<br />
this matter. A second Royal Commission<br />
was set -up as a result of allegations mnade<br />
; by Lietitenant-' Commander Cabban, who<br />
brought into question the drinking habits<br />
and the seamanship of the late Captain<br />
Stevens. Because the allegations in the<br />
statement were so serious and because if<br />
they had been proved to be accurate they<br />
could have had such a serious effect, it was<br />
decided that the question would be reopened<br />
and that there would be a second<br />
Royal Commission. Mr Speaker, the Royal<br />
Commissioners, who I know are not exempt<br />
from attack by the Leader of the Opposition<br />
but whom most people would regard<br />
as being completely impartial, have stated<br />
that any reasonable man reading the<br />
Cabban statement as it was made some 6<br />
months after the completion of the first<br />
Royal Commission could not fail to reach a<br />
conclusion that Captain Stevens was a<br />
chronic drunkard, that he spent his time </p>
<p>in port drinking until he became ill, recovering<br />
from that and then embarking<br />
upon another drinking bout and that his<br />
qualifications as to seamanship were such<br />
that he should not have been in charge of<br />
one of Her Majesty's vessels. This was what<br />
the Commissioners said a reasonable man<br />
reading the Cabban statement would conclude,<br />
and this was what the Commissioners<br />
specifically and completely rejected as being<br />
a true history of the facts.<br />
We in this House should now take this<br />
opportunity to point out that the Commissioners<br />
reached this conclusion after<br />
examining all the relevant evidence and<br />
they expressed their findings in these words:<br />
This is not merely a cale where allegations of<br />
frequent drunkenness are not proved. Not only<br />
is there no evidence to support frequent drunkenness,<br />
but the evidence positively establishes that<br />
this was not the fact.<br />
If it is true, as the Commissioners claim<br />
it was true, that this officer of the Royal<br />
Australian Navy, who perished in the performance<br />
of his duty, has been held up<br />
whether with malice or not, and the Commissioners<br />
claim no malice, before the<br />
public as somebody who was in such a<br />
state of drunkenness, it is essential to establish<br />
here that the Commissioners have completely<br />
refuted in the words I have just<br />
stated any accuracy in this accusation.<br />
Indeed, I can go further and state, as I<br />
believe I should state, that Lieutenant-<br />
Commander Cabban himself in his evidence<br />
before the Commissioners disclaimed any<br />
attempt to have drawn from his evidence<br />
a conclusion that the late Captain Stevens<br />
was in fact so affected by drink. It is essential<br />
that this should now be stated in this<br />
House. Similarly it is necessary to state that on<br />
the question of the competence as a seaman<br />
of the late Captain Stevens the Commissioners<br />
found that he was not in any way<br />
incompetent as a seaman to command one<br />
of Her Majesty's ships and indeed again<br />
Lieutenant-Commander Cabban in his<br />
statements and evidence before the Commission<br />
disclaimed any intention in what<br />
was in his statement to suggest that the late<br />
Captain Stevens was in any way lacking as<br />
a seaman. These two points should be made<br />
clear, because : this officer has been subjected<br />
to these accusations and these accusations<br />
have been found by a judicial commision to be not founded in fact. I wish to make<br />
that point in justice to an officer who is<br />
no longer with us.<br />
Now I move on -to some of the strange<br />
and inaccurate statements made by the<br />
Leader of the Opposition in his address to<br />
us tonight. One of the first and most inaccurate<br />
statements, if there is a degree of<br />
inaccuracy in these matters, was that the<br />
Commission found that from January 1963<br />
to February 1964 Captain Stevens was unfit<br />
to retain his command. This is what the<br />
Leader of the Opposition told us 10 minutes<br />
ago. Yet when we read the report of the<br />
Commissioners, from which I presume the<br />
Leader of the Opposition was pretending<br />
to quote, we find that they say:<br />
We must answer this question as from 31st<br />
December 1963.<br />
They did not say as from 1st January but<br />
as from a year later. Here we have been<br />
told that the Commissioners have found<br />
something -to be true that the Commissioners<br />
did not find to be true. What sort of<br />
creditability can we give to this kind of<br />
accusation? Mr Donald Cameron-None.<br />
Mr GORTON-I agree. I thank the<br />
honourable member for the answer. I prefer<br />
to rely on the findings of the Royal Commissioners.<br />
Then we have the Leader of<br />
the Opposition suggesting to this House that<br />
the Naval Board did know of the allegations<br />
against Captain Stevens. Yet the findings<br />
of the Royal Commissioners are perfectly<br />
clear on this point. They are:<br />
We find-<br />
' We' are the Royal Commissionersthat<br />
the Naval Board did not know of the allegations<br />
and there was nothing that came<br />
to their knowledge which ought to have put them<br />
on inquiry.<br />
This is a different presentation from the<br />
one we have received tonight from the<br />
Leader of the Opposition. Again, one must<br />
make one's own judgment on the relative<br />
credibility of the Leader of the Opposition<br />
and of the Royal Commissioners sitting in<br />
impartial findings on these facts. We are<br />
told, and it is true, that officers such as<br />
McNeill and Tiller did not complete the<br />
forms which naval regulations required<br />
them to complete. This is admitted. Both<br />
these officers were out of the Navy by the<br />
time the inquiry was set in train. But all<br />
that this proves is that the regulations laid </p>
<p>down by the Navy will, if they are followed<br />
by the officers in it, bring to the attention<br />
of the Board facts which the Board ought<br />
to know. There is no military, Air Force,<br />
Naval Board or other administrative<br />
authority which can do more than lay down<br />
regulations which, if they are carried out,<br />
will fulfil the requirements sought to be<br />
attained by that administrative authority.<br />
I think one of the most serious derogations<br />
of the Leader of the Opposition was<br />
his attempt to suggest that the Attorney-<br />
General ( Mr Bowen), the Treasurer ( Mr<br />
McMahon) and the honourable member for<br />
Higinbotham ( Mr Chipp), the former<br />
Minister for the Navy, have in some way<br />
misled this House during the last debate<br />
upon this matter. It is claimed by the<br />
Leader of the Opposition that there was<br />
corroboration at the time of the statements<br />
made by Lieutenant-Commander Cabban<br />
and that these Ministers knew of that<br />
corroboration and that in saying there<br />
was not such corroboration Ministers<br />
deliberately misled this House. I do not<br />
believe there is any scintilla-I use that<br />
word advisedly-of evidence to support this<br />
statement. Let us look at what in fact was<br />
said by Lieutenant-Commander Caibban and<br />
what in fact was said by the relevant<br />
Ministers in this place and what was said<br />
by those officers whom Lieutenant-Commander<br />
Cabban said would corroborate him.<br />
In his statement Lieutenant-Commander<br />
Cabban said:<br />
During the period in the Far East the situation<br />
became more than trying, it was quite desperate,<br />
as he drank for very long periods in harbour<br />
until he became violently ill and then would<br />
spend days in bed being treated by the doctor<br />
and his steward until he was fit to again start<br />
drinking. Lieutenant-Commander Griffith, the officer<br />
who Cabban said would corroborate him,<br />
stated: I had never seen Captain Stevens under the<br />
influence of drink.<br />
Mr Kevin Cairns-A bit different.<br />
Mr GORTON-Well, it is not corroboration,<br />
although at the mess dinner to which<br />
Cabban refers in his statement, Captain<br />
Stevens obviously did not look well.<br />
Lieutenant-Commander Griffith said:<br />
The general remarks made on or after the<br />
dinner was that the Captain had drunk too much<br />
but when Captain Stevens left the mess he was not held up. I do not remember any signs of<br />
slurred speech or of actions to indicate drunkenness<br />
such as mentioned by Mr Cabban.<br />
Can the Leader of the Opposition truly<br />
claim that this statement by Lieutenant-<br />
Commander Giffith is corroboration of the<br />
statement by Lieutenant-Commander<br />
Cabban? Later Lieutenant-Commander<br />
Griffith-this is the officer who was supposed<br />
to corroborate Cabban, whom the<br />
Leader of the Opposition said did corroborate<br />
Cabban, whom the Leader of the<br />
Opposition said the Minister knew corroborated<br />
Cabban, and in respect of whom the<br />
Leader of the Opposition therefore said, the<br />
Minister misled the House-said:<br />
My understanding is that Captain Stevens had<br />
the reputation of being a heavy rather than a<br />
moderate drinker. I know of no occasion on which<br />
I have seen him intoxicated.<br />
Is that corroboration of a charge<br />
of drunkenness? Lieutenant-Commander<br />
Griffith went on to say:<br />
Subject to the qualification on the night of the<br />
mess dinner, the Captain was obviously unwell but<br />
whether this was due to alcohol I cannot say. I<br />
have never seen Captain Stevens drink at sea and<br />
although I have been in his cabin I have never<br />
seen him drink there other than the ordinary issue<br />
of lime powder and water.<br />
Is this corroboration of a statement which<br />
the Royal Commissioners claimed would, to<br />
any reasonable man, indicate that the late<br />
Captain Stevens was a drunkard? What is<br />
this claim of corroboration tied to?<br />
Let me move to the question of seamanship.<br />
In the statement made by Lieutenant-<br />
Commander Cabban a number of incidents<br />
are mentioned. There is the alleged collision<br />
between two destroyers. This was the time<br />
when one destroyer was berthing alongside<br />
another destroyer which was static, not<br />
moving. There was the incident when a towline<br />
parted. There was the incident mentioned<br />
when a ship drove in-I think that<br />
was the term-between two other ships.<br />
These incidents took place. Lieutenant-<br />
Commander Cabban in his evidence before<br />
the Commission said that he did not advance<br />
these incidents as indications of bad seamanship<br />
at all or of bad ship handling at all.<br />
This was not in his mind and he did not<br />
advance them in that way. But nevertheless<br />
the Commission found that a reasonable man<br />
reading the documents would have thought<br />
they did tend to indicate some lack of seamanship<br />
or some lack of ship handling, and </p>
<p>they did take place. But on all the evidence,<br />
including the evidence of Lieutenant-<br />
Commander Cabban himself, they were not<br />
either evidence of bad seamanship or<br />
advanced as evidence of bad seamanship.<br />
According to his evidence they were merely<br />
advanced as an indication of the temperament<br />
of Captain Stevens.<br />
It is no corroboration of an incident to<br />
say that that incident took place. If I were<br />
to say here tonight-and of course I would<br />
not-that yesterday I saw the Leader of the<br />
Opposition walk through the door of his<br />
office and he had had so much to drink that<br />
he tripped on the carpet and fell flat on the<br />
floor, and if later someone were to say, ' Yes,<br />
he was walking through the door of his office<br />
and he did trip on the carpet and fall over,<br />
but I know he had nothing to drink the<br />
whole day; he tripped because the carpet<br />
was loose', then this second statement would<br />
not be a corroboration of the first. It would<br />
be quite different in content and in the<br />
implications to be drawn from it. Yet, it is<br />
that kind of suggestion which the Leader of<br />
the Opposition claims to be a corroboration.<br />
It is just not a corroboration at all. These<br />
matters will be developed by the Ministers<br />
who have been attacked. They cannot be<br />
developed by the Royal Commissioners who<br />
have been attacked, but they will be attacked<br />
by those who can speak for themselves in<br />
this House.<br />
Let me refer to the questions which the<br />
Leader of the Opposition asked in his statement<br />
and to the answers which he has<br />
given. The Leader of the Opposition asked:<br />
Was Captain Stevens unfit to retain command<br />
of ' Voyager'? The Commission said<br />
he was. The Commission said he was as<br />
from December 1963, not as from the date<br />
which the Leader of the Opposition<br />
advanced in this chamber as the time from<br />
which he was unfit to retain command. The<br />
Leader of the Opposition also asked: Did<br />
the Naval Board know of his unfitness? The<br />
Leader of the Opposition answered his own<br />
question by saying: ' We know at least that<br />
the Chief Medical Officer of the Navy was<br />
aware of it.' Mr Speaker, what a misleading<br />
statement that is. What an inaccurate<br />
statement that is. Let us look at the Leader<br />
of the Opposition's statement that the chief<br />
medical officer of the Navy was aware of<br />
Captain Stevens's unfitness to retain command<br />
of ' Voyager'. tExtension of time granted.] I thank the House for its courtesy<br />
in granting me an extension of time. I shall<br />
endeavour not to extend my time too far.<br />
The basis of this claim by the Leader of<br />
the Opposition that the chief medical officer<br />
of the Navy was aware of Captain Stevens's<br />
unfitness to retain command of ' Voyager'<br />
is that the chief medical officer of the Navy<br />
knew that on one occasion Captain Stevens<br />
had had a duodenal ulcer, and that he knew<br />
that Captain Stevens was taking care of that<br />
ulcer and was drinking milk when he went<br />
out to see the chief medical officer in his<br />
own home. In other words, Mr Speaker, all<br />
that that means is that the chief medical<br />
officer of the Navy knew that there had<br />
been a medical history, knew that there had<br />
been treatment for an ulcer, knew that the<br />
condition had healed, and knew that the<br />
officer was taking care of that condition.<br />
This is now advanced in this House and is<br />
twisted round to a suggestion that, because<br />
of that, the chief medical officer knew that<br />
some years later the late Captain Stevens<br />
was unfit to retain command of ' Voyager'.<br />
What credibility can we give to arguments<br />
of this kind?<br />
Then the Leader of the Opposition asks:<br />
Should the Naval Board have known? He<br />
answers his question-and he answers all<br />
his questions, naturally, in a way that suits<br />
himself, as I suppose we all do with our own<br />
questions-in this way: In the light of<br />
Stevens's known past history and his conduct<br />
while in command of ' Voyager', it is plain<br />
that there was a gross malfunctioning of<br />
the system of check and control of naval<br />
commanders. So the Leader of the Opposition<br />
has decided that the royal commissioners<br />
were wrong in their findings, because<br />
what they found was that the Naval Board<br />
did not know; that there was nothing<br />
which came to its knowledge which should<br />
have put it on inquiry; that the two naval<br />
medical officers referred to in the report<br />
had in fact not filled in the forms which<br />
the regulations required them to fill in; and<br />
therefore there could have been no possibility<br />
of the Board, or responsible members<br />
of it, knowing.<br />
' Did responsible officers of the Navy<br />
know of the condition which made him<br />
unfit to retain command?', asks the Leader<br />
of the Opposition. And he answers: There<br />
is evidence that many more officers beyond<br />
those criticised * n . the report were in fact </p>
<p>aware of it. Aware of what, Mr Speaker?<br />
aware of the fact that he had a duodenal<br />
ulcer? Of course there were a number of<br />
officers aware of that. There were alsoand<br />
the Leader of the Opposition did not<br />
care to tell us . this-a number of other naval<br />
officers, members of the Royal Navy as well<br />
as members of the Royal Australian Navy,<br />
commanding and responsible for Captain<br />
Stevens and other captains in charge of<br />
ships, who were so satisfied with the way<br />
in which he performed his duties as commanding<br />
officer of ' Voyager' that they<br />
reported on him as having properly and<br />
thoroughly carried out his duties in command.<br />
Those were not just officers of the<br />
Royal Australian Navy, but also officers ol<br />
the Royal Navy. Then we are asked by the<br />
Leader of the Opposition: Did corroboration<br />
exist for all or any of his statements at the<br />
time of . the parliamentary debate last May?<br />
That is a reference to Cabban's statements.<br />
What corroboration was available, if any,<br />
Mr Speaker? I suggest that there was none.<br />
Oh, yes, there was corroboration by incidents<br />
occurring when ships went close to<br />
each other and when tow lines parted. But,<br />
as I pointed out, this was not corroboration<br />
of the underlying suggestion that this was<br />
due to bad seamanship. Oh, yes, there was<br />
corroboration that on 3 days, as the royal<br />
commission found, out of the 180-odd days<br />
of the cruise Captain Stevens was affected<br />
by alcohol-slightly on one occasion, more<br />
than slightly on another. Is that corroboration,<br />
Mr Speaker? Would this House think<br />
that that was corroboration of the kind of<br />
impression that one would gain from a first<br />
reading of the statements that the late<br />
Captain Stevens was drunk all the time in<br />
port, that he spent his time drinking, then<br />
getting better so . that he could drink again?<br />
Could that be called corroboration? For it<br />
was not called corroboration by the royal<br />
commissioners. Then we are asked: If there was corroboration,<br />
was it known to the Navy Department?<br />
It was, the Leader of the Opposition<br />
tells us, because the Department had obtained<br />
it. What the Department obtained.<br />
Mr Speaker, was statements by Lieutenant-<br />
Commander Griffith refuting completely the<br />
claims made by Lieutenant-Commander<br />
Cabban. What the Department obtained<br />
which did to some extent support the claims<br />
made by Lieutenant-Commander Cabban<br />
was a statement made by the medical officer<br />
14964/ 68-2 who had since left the Navy--Surgeon-<br />
Lieutenant Tiller. The Leader of the<br />
Opposition has attempted to make great<br />
play with the suggestion that because<br />
Surgeon-Lieutenant Tiller had made a statement<br />
which tended to corroborate-as it<br />
did-some of the statements by Lieutenant-<br />
Commander Cabban, therefore Ministers in<br />
this House were wrong because they suppressed<br />
this statement, because they did not<br />
let it come to the light of the day. What is<br />
the truth of this, Mr Speaker? The truth<br />
of this is that Surgeon-Lieutenant Tiller<br />
made a statement long before there was<br />
any question of a royal commission being<br />
appointed and long before there was any<br />
chance of his ever being held in the witness<br />
box to sustain the evidence and the truth<br />
of whatever he might put in the statement<br />
that he then made. Subsequently, this<br />
question of the royal commission arose, and<br />
there also arose the question of sustaining<br />
the truth and accuracy of the statement<br />
previously made. And in those ciroumstances,<br />
Surgeon-Lieutenant Tiller-not the<br />
Government-said that he did not wish his<br />
statement to be used; it was a statement<br />
which was his personal property, and he<br />
did not want it to be used. The royal commissioners,<br />
in their judgment and in their<br />
findings, found that this was a perfectly<br />
reasonable attitude for Tiller to take and<br />
that it was a perfectly reasonable attitude<br />
for Mr Landau, the Secretary of the Department<br />
of the Navy, who was referred to by<br />
the Leader of the Opposition as ' this<br />
creature', to respect the privacy of what<br />
was in effect a private communication and<br />
to get another statement, which was subsequently<br />
made.<br />
Mr Speaker, I do not wish to trespass too<br />
long on the courtesy that the House has<br />
done me in extending my time. I shall complete<br />
what I have to say in these words: The<br />
second royal commission was set up by the<br />
Government as a result of statements made<br />
by Lieutenant-Commander Cabban. Those<br />
statements, on the royal commissioners' own<br />
findings, were found to be untrue, though<br />
not untrue as a result of malice. On the<br />
findings of the royal commission, the implications<br />
inherent in what the Leader of the<br />
Opposition has said this evening about the<br />
drinking habits of the late Captain Stevens<br />
were fully rejected by the royal commissioners.<br />
In their view, on the evidence </p>
<p>of Cabban himself, the allegations as to bad<br />
seamanship were fully rejected. In the view<br />
of the royal commissioners, examining the<br />
matter as a whole, the previous findings of<br />
the first royal commission in relation to<br />
Captain Robertson were rejected. And the<br />
Government has already taken action to do<br />
what was considered to be the just thing<br />
in that case.<br />
Mr Bryant-It would never have happened<br />
without Cabban.<br />
Mr GORTON-I would not contest that.<br />
Mr Bryant-Then why do you not say so?<br />
Mr GORTON-I am saying so, am I not?<br />
How can I do more than say that I would<br />
not contest that?<br />
Dr J. F. Cairns-Give credit where credit<br />
is due. Mr SPEAKER-Order! The honourable<br />
member for Yarra will cease interjecting. Dr J. F. Cairns-The Prime Minister<br />
needs a lot of help, Mr Speaker.<br />
Mr GORTON-If I needed a lot of help<br />
I would not get it from the honourable<br />
member for Yarra, Mr Speaker, and I certainly<br />
would not seek it.<br />
Mr SPEAKER-Order! I have already<br />
asked the honourable member for Yarra to<br />
cease interjecting. If he continues in this<br />
vein I will have to deal with him.<br />
Mr GORTON-It is quite evident that<br />
the findings regarding the causes of the<br />
collision would not have been made if there<br />
had not been a second Royal Commission.<br />
I would imagine that this was evident to<br />
a 2-year old child. There would not have<br />
been a second Royal Commission if it had<br />
not been for what were found to be misleading<br />
accusations by Lieutenant-Commander<br />
Cabban. This, again, I think would<br />
be evident to the honourable member for<br />
Yarra.<br />
BY AUTHORITY: A. J. ARTHUR, COMMONWEALTH GOVERNMENT PRINTER, CANBERRA, A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
