<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9396</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P J KEATING PRIME MINISTERS XI</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/10/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009396.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
PRIME MINISTER'S Xl<br />
This years Prime Ministers XI team, to play England at Manuka<br />
9 November, has been chosen. The team is:<br />
Allan Border ( Captain)<br />
Mark Atkinson<br />
Greg Blewett<br />
Michael Di Venuto<br />
Shane George<br />
Brad Hodge<br />
Brendon Julian<br />
Shane Lee<br />
Darren Lehmann<br />
Martin Love<br />
Greg Rowell<br />
Mark Higgs ( 1 2th man) Oval on Wednesday<br />
Queensland Tasmania South Australia<br />
Tasmania South Australia<br />
Victoria Westemn Australia<br />
New South Wales<br />
South Australia<br />
New South Wales<br />
Queensland ACT<br />
This year, the Prime Ministers XI match provides us all with three great opportunities.<br />
First, to honour one of the game's all-time great players Allan Border.<br />
I am truly delighted that Allan has agreed to captain the side. This will be the tenth time he has<br />
done so, and I am sure his special retumn to the international cricket scene will prove to be a<br />
momentous occasion. I heartily agree with the comment by PM's Xl co-selector Laurie Sawle that<br />
" there will never be another Allan Border'.<br />
Second, the game will give us a chance to see no less than ten PM's XI players who have been<br />
associated with the AIS Commonwealth Bank Cricket Academy, six of them graduates of this<br />
very successful institution.<br />
It will also be an important opportunity for the young PM's Xl players to gain match practice<br />
against the English side, and to press for selection in either of the two Australian one-day sides<br />
and the Test team.<br />
Third, it will provide a chance to witness yet another great clash in the long-running rivalry<br />
between Australia and England.<br />
I am sure the match will be entertaining, and, with Allan Border captaining a fine Australian side<br />
against the English, an historic occasion.<br />
The day before the game, I will be launching, for the Australian Cricket Board, the Intemnational<br />
Cricket Season, featuring four teams: Australia, England, Zimbabwe and Australia A.<br />
CANBERRA October 1994 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
