<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>15133</transcript-id>
    <title>Address at the Cochlear Implant Centre Gladesville, Sydney</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/04/2007</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...</p>
<p>  Listen to this Speech (MP3 -   0.00Mb - secs)</p>
<p>Thank you very much Mr Calvert, Professor Gibson, to Lady Mary Fairfax and the other very generous benefactors over the years.  I am very, very pleased indeed to be here.  I, like everybody else was very touched by the two stories that we've heard this morning and as somebody who as you know has over the years has had a lot of hearing problems himself and had a number of operations but fortunately my hearing deficiency was one that could be attended to with conventional hearing aids.  I can only begin to imagine the sense of despair of a parent.  </p>
<p>I've had a talk to Soraya and her mum and dad and she's a very alert girl, she responds, she's no different to my eyes and hears than any other little girl who's just turned one.  But the story was moving, the story was inspirational and there's no better way I guess of saying a big thank you to the Centre but also honouring the contribution of two very energetic Australians who in their different ways have brought this about. </p>
<p>I've had the privilege </p>
<p>over the years of meeting both of them.  I knew Paul Trainer very well, he used to live in Hunters Hill and he used to turn up on occasions at various functions I went to and we became quite good friends and I was aware not only of his great skill as a businessman but his personal dedication to cochlear implants and as Prime Minister over the last 10 years and previously I've certainly met Professor Clark who is one of those quite unforgettable people.  Somebody who embodies the capacity of Australia in medical research to always punch above her weight and that is what this country has done.  I think it's also an occasion to remark that the system of screening for deafness in newborn children in New South Wales is the best in the country.  It is followed by more or less by two other states and one the things that I'm encouraging Tony Abbott to do and I will do my bit as well, is to encourage the other states of Australia to embrace the approach that's been operating here in New South Wales. I am independently very much aware of how effective it is and I've had some representations from Bruce Shepherd and from many other people to do what I can to make sure that it spreads around world, spreads around Australia and indeed around the world.   This isn't an occasion to sort of reel off figures about the Federal Government's contribution to the hearing services and also to the CRCs rather it's an occasion for me to remark that we normally do things best in this country in areas such as health, in remedial responses to particular ailments people have, we normally do them best where there is cooperation between the Federal Government, the State Government.   People who are affected either as parents and of course this morning as well as meeting Soraya, I also had the opportunity of meeting a gentleman who believed that he could... he had his Cochlear implant at the age of 70 and he was intending amongst other things to return to RSL meetings and he told me how he was standing for Vice President and I wished him luck in the election and I think with his enthusiasm and energy, he will be very successful.  But it's wonderful to understand that an invention such as this can help people at both ends of life's spectrum and we've had of course from Professor Brand-Miller we've had a story of somebody and I thank her very much for remaining in the workforce and the contribution she has thereby made.</p>
<p>But it's a wonderful reminder of the capacity of medical science not only to save lives but also to enrich them despite a natural defect at every point.  At zero, at 45 and at 70 and that is not a bad capacity, it's not a bad thing. </p>
<p>So, thank you very much for asking me to come here.  It's wonderful to see, the old Gladesville Hospital being put to such tremendous use, it's a rambling adequate facility, now very beautifully refurbished and that of course is and this is my final expression of thanks, that of course very much due also to the wonderful generosity of philanthropic Australians and many of them are here today, Mary in particular, but many others I see, some quite familiar faces that I find I see at lots of gatherings around Sydney where the hand is in the private pocket in order to help a good cause.  It is an occasion as well as honouring our scientists and rejoicing in the miracle of hearing being given to people, it's also an occasion to thank those who can afford to help but do help.  They are a special group and they deserve our gratitude and our thanks and in that spirit I have very great pleasure in declaring the refurbished Sydney Cochlear Centre open, or re-established and long may it be the joy of which Mrs Wyndham spoke.</p>
<p>[ends]  </p>
<p>  Listen to this Speech (MP3 -   0.00Mb - secs)</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
