<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3160</transcript-id>
    <title>EARTHMOVING, CONSTRUCTION AND MATERIALS HANDLING EQUIPMENT ETC.</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/02/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003160.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
JAUSTRALIA g-<br />
PRIME MINISTER PRESS STATEMENT NO. 188<br />
18 February 1974<br />
EARTHMOVING, CONSTRUCTION AND MATERIALS HANDLING EQUIPMENT ETC.<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr Whitlam, today announced the Government's<br />
decision on the Tariff Board's report on Earthmoving, Construction<br />
and Materials Handling Equipment, Etc. The Prime Minister stated that<br />
the Government had accepted the Board's recommendations, with some<br />
minor rate adjustments arising from international commitments.<br />
The report covered a wide range of earthmoving, construction<br />
and materials handling equipment including attachments and parts.<br />
The Government's decison to implement the Board's recommendations<br />
will mean that for the more important products the following rates<br />
of duty will apply: for loaders and backhoes 40%; for cranes<br />
to 35% ( the lower rate applying to cranes with a working. weight in<br />
excess of 50 tonnes); engine propelled forklift trucks 30% ( with<br />
the existing alternative specific rate being phased out in two stages<br />
over five years); for road rollers and road making machinery<br />
hoists, pulley tackle and other lifting devices 30% to 40%; conveyors<br />
but reducing to 20% and 30% over 3 years; lifts and escalators<br />
Although the Tariff Boards report was signed after the<br />
Government's announcement on the 25% tariff cut the existing duties<br />
referred to in the report are those applying before the reduction.<br />
Consequently, although the Board's recommended rates are in some<br />
cases lower than the rates applying before the 25% tariff cuts when<br />
compared with the rates actually operating since the tariff cuts, the<br />
rates on some products will now have been increased.<br />
Furthermore, importers may also encounter increased duties in<br />
certain circumstances, for example, higher duties could result from<br />
the abolition of the tariff preferences which British goods have<br />
enjoyed. In some cases Britain is the main source of competition to<br />
the local industry.<br />
Mr Whitlam said that details of the Customs tariff changes<br />
arising from the Government's decision will be announced when<br />
administrative arrangements to implement them have been finalised.<br />
CANBERRA. A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
