<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3891</transcript-id>
    <title>OFFICIAL CAR TRANSPORT</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/09/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003891.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
) 4WUtRLIA PRESS STATEMENT NO. 562<br />
19 September 1975<br />
OFFICIAL CAR TRANSPORT<br />
The Prime Minister has announced that as part of<br />
its deliberations on the Budget and in keeping with its<br />
desire to cut costs wherever practical, the Government<br />
has decided to restrict the use of official bar transport.<br />
A number of measures have already been taken and<br />
further measures are in hand to achieve this objective.<br />
Rules governing the use of official transport<br />
were last reviewed by the Rt. Hon. J. McEwen as Acting<br />
Prime Minister in April 1966.<br />
New rules designed to curtail the use of cars have<br />
been approved and will apply to all Australian Government<br />
employees and to members of the Armed Forces.<br />
The Australian Government transport authorities will<br />
maintain only skeleton staff on weekends and public holidays.<br />
Weekday services will also be closely examinedtto see whether<br />
further cost savings can be achieve whilst maintaining a<br />
reasonable level of service.<br />
Ways and means of rationalising official transport<br />
to and from Canberra Airport and of extending the existing<br />
inter-departmental passenger bus service between major<br />
work locations in Canberra are under consideration.<br />
Departments and other Australian Government<br />
instrumentalities are to be requested to review urgently<br />
all cars owned or on hire, in conjunction with the appropriate<br />
Australian Government transport authority, to ensure that<br />
their use is economic.<br />
Whilst it is not possible to estimate precisely the<br />
full effect of these measures, it is considered that they<br />
will involve substantial savings in official transport costs.<br />
CANBERRA, A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
