<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>21366</transcript-id>
    <title>Committed to Small Business  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/07/2004</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>A thriving small business sector is a tremendous asset to Australia.  Small businesses make a major contribution to our economy and to community life in general - especially in regional areas.  It is a dynamic and expanding generator of jobs.</p>
<p>  I am very pleased therefore to launch, this evening, an important small business statement Committed to Small Business.</p>
<p>This statement outlines the additional steps the Government is taking to improve the climate for small businesses in Australia by reducing the paperwork burden and improving the regulatory environment.</p>
<p>In particular, it includes a significant reduction in businesses' superannuation compliance burden by removing the need for employers to report contributions to employees under the Superannuation Guarantee arrangements.</p>
<p>The Government is also extending information services, enhancing the effectiveness of the Trade Practices Act for small businesses and committing to further reform of the workplace relations system.</p>
<p>Tonight I will also be announcing the creation of a new Deputy Chairman position within the Australian Competition and Consumer Commission.</p>
<p>  While consultation with the states and territories will be required, it is intended that Mr John Martin, the longest serving ACCC commissioner and the commissioner with small business responsibilities, will be promoted to this position.</p>
<p>The measures contained in the statement bring together a range of recent and new initiatives and give further expression to the Government's commitment to small business.</p>
<p>Committed to Small Business is available as a fully browsable online version on the Department of the Prime Minister  and Cabinet website - Committed to Small Business (HTML)<br />
  Further information on Committed to Small Business and links to related media releases are available on the Industry, Tourism and Resources website.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
