<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10969</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                ADDRESS TO THE 127TH STATE COUNCIL OF THE VICTORIAN DIVISION OF THE                 LIBERAL PARTY                HAWTHORN CAMPUS, UNIVERSITY OF MELBOURNE                HAWTHORN, VICTORIA</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/04/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...............................................................................................................................</p>
<p>Well, thank you very much Peter for those very warm words of welcome;</p>
<p> to Joy Howley; to Tony Staley; to Peter Poggioli; to Phil Gude, the</p>
<p> Deputy Leader of the State Parliamentary Liberal Party, Alan Stockdale,</p>
<p> the Treasurer of Victoria, to my other Ministerial and Parliamentary</p>
<p> colleagues, both State and Federal, and most importantly the men and</p>
<p> women of the Liberal Party of Victoria.</p>
<p>It is a great pleasure for me to back addressing once again the State</p>
<p> Council gathering of the strongest division of the Liberal Party of</p>
<p> Australia. A Division, that over the years through good times and</p>
<p> bad for the Federal Parliamentary Party, in Government and in Opposition,</p>
<p> has always delivered a magnificent electoral dividend to us in Canberra.</p>
<p>I want in my remarks this morning to express again my gratitude to</p>
<p> the Victorian Division for the tremendous understanding, and support,</p>
<p> and loyalty, and vigorous advocacy which all of you have delivered</p>
<p> to us over the last two years. It has been a two year period of tremendous</p>
<p> achievement. And as we turn our gaze towards the inevitability of</p>
<p> a Federal election some time in the next twelve months and if I were</p>
<p> some of the newspaper commentators I wouldn't get too excited</p>
<p> about particular dates. Can I say to all of you that the next twelve</p>
<p> months is not a time to be reticent, it is not a time to be shy, it</p>
<p> is not a time to be unforthcoming about what the Government that I</p>
<p> have the privilege to lead has achieved.</p>
<p>In many respects the Coalition Government elected in March of 1996</p>
<p> has been the greatest reform government Australia has had since the</p>
<p> end of World War II. In all the areas you look at you have seen sweeping,</p>
<p> indeed, fundamental reform. No Government and no Treasurer has achieved</p>
<p> what my Government, and Peter Costello has achieved, over the last</p>
<p> two years in turning around the disastrous fiscal inheritance that</p>
<p> was left to us. A $10.5 billion deficit concealed - but so obvious</p>
<p> and there for the asking. But the day after the election when I met</p>
<p> the outgoing head of the Prime Minister's Department and his</p>
<p> two colleagues in my then Opposition Leader's office in Sydney,</p>
<p> still recovering as I was from the euphoria of the night before, but</p>
<p> able to read, just, because I had been to Church. I was able to read</p>
<p> those dreadful figures. They handed me the book. It was all there</p>
<p> and, of course, it had been there for weeks but somebody hadn't</p>
<p> bothered to ask. And that is the measure of the difficulty that we</p>
<p> faced. We did inherit a deficit of $10.5 billion. And in just two</p>
<p> years we have turned that by dint of an extraordinary effort of fiscal</p>
<p> discipline to which all of my colleagues have contributed. We have</p>
<p> turned that around and I am immensely proud of that reform. And it</p>
<p> is a reform that is widely recognised throughout the economic world.</p>
<p> It is a reform that is helped to fire-proof the Australian economy</p>
<p> against the worst of the Asian ravages. It means that as we talk to</p>
<p> the leaders of Indonesia, the leaders of China and Singapore we are</p>
<p> able to talk from a position of strength. And along with Japan, Australia</p>
<p> is the only nation that has been strong enough to participate in the</p>
<p> three IMF bailouts, respectively of Korea, Thailand and Indonesia.</p>
<p> And all of those bailouts have involved an investment in the future</p>
<p> of Australian jobs and Australian industry and that is why we have</p>
<p> done it. But you only do that from a position of strength. If Mr Beazley</p>
<p> and Mr Keating had been returned at the last election Australia would</p>
<p> not have been able to help Indonesia and Thailand and Korea in their</p>
<p> hour of need. We would not have been able to be the good regional</p>
<p> mate that we have been to those countries.</p>
<p>But as Peter said, we have delivered the lowest interest rates that</p>
<p> this country has seen for thirty years, or more. The reductions in</p>
<p> housing interest rates, worth on average about $250 to $300 a month,</p>
<p> or put another way - the equivalent for the average wage and salary</p>
<p> earner in Australia of an increase of $100 a week in that person's</p>
<p> income. That is the measure. And none of you should ever forget in</p>
<p> the months ahead that in 1990 the overdraft rate for small business</p>
<p> was driven to 20.5 per cent under Mr Keating's Treasurership.</p>
<p> And in the last week we have had two of the major banks in Australia</p>
<p> announce dramatically lower interest rates for small and large businesses.</p>
<p> And that we will have a base rate for small business in the order</p>
<p> of 7.25 per cent from Westpac and about the same from the Commonwealth</p>
<p> Bank. And I expect it will only be a matter of time before the other</p>
<p> banks and financial institutions respond. None of that would have</p>
<p> been possible if we hadn't cut the budget deficit. None of that</p>
<p> would have been possible if we hadn't embarked upon a process</p>
<p> of fiscal consolidation.</p>
<p>But it doesn't end there. We have reformed the industrial relations</p>
<p> system and we have reformed it in a climate of industrial peace and</p>
<p> industrial tranquility, the like of which we have not seen at any</p>
<p> time since the end of World War II. Indeed, in 1997, the number of</p>
<p> industrial disputes in Australia hit the lowest level it had been</p>
<p> for</p>
<p>85 years. In other words, we had to go back to the years of World</p>
<p> War I to find a period of industrial peace, the equal of what we experienced</p>
<p> in 1997. So much for all the prophecies of blood in the streets and</p>
<p> industrial strife - all the warnings that were made in those speeches</p>
<p> by Mr Kelty and others on the eve of the 1996 election. Because what</p>
<p> the Australian people have said and what the Australian workers have</p>
<p> said is that they welcome the opportunities and the choice involved</p>
<p> in the new industrial relations era that we have introduced.</p>
<p>And, of course, under Peter Costello's Treasurership, we have</p>
<p> also embarked upon some very fundamental changes and reforms to the</p>
<p> Australian financial system. We have, in the Australian financial</p>
<p> system now, one of the most competitive in the world. And increasingly</p>
<p> Australia is seen as a haven for investment in this part of the world.</p>
<p> We have a stable political system. We have stable economic conditions.</p>
<p> The lowest rate of inflation in the OECD area. We have a stable legal</p>
<p> system. We speak the international language, the English language.</p>
<p> And we are seen as having a stable banking system with an open competitive</p>
<p> financial approach. In other words, you have a coming together of</p>
<p> all of the influences that make Australia the most attractive place</p>
<p> in the world in which to invest. And I believe that we are set fair</p>
<p> to realise one of our other great goals in the next century. And that</p>
<p> is to see Australia become, after Tokyo, the second great financial</p>
<p> centre of the Asian Pacific region. And to join New York and London,</p>
<p> along with Tokyo, as the four great financial centres of the world.</p>
<p>And, of course, the reform agenda doesn't end there either. We</p>
<p> have, by our commitment, to allow the men and women of Australia to</p>
<p> buy the remaining two-thirds of Telstra. We have given ourselves the</p>
<p> capacity, in that one single decision, to reduce, by 40 per cent,</p>
<p> the total Federal Government debt of this country. In other words,</p>
<p> 40 per cent of the almost $100 billion of Federal Government debt</p>
<p> that we inherited from Mr Beazley and Mr Keating in March of 1996.</p>
<p>We've also seen significant strides on the employment front.</p>
<p> We have seen, over the last six months, the generation of about 140,000</p>
<p> new jobs. We have seen significant reforms to small business. We have</p>
<p> seen the introduction of the work-for-the-dole principles. The principle</p>
<p> of mutual obligation. The principle that Mr Beazley chokes on. The</p>
<p> principle that no Labor government could ever embrace because the</p>
<p> trade union movement would deny them the capacity to deliver it in</p>
<p> government.</p>
<p>And so, my friends, the list of reforms has been quite fundamental.</p>
<p> On the 1st of May we will introduce a fully competitive system of</p>
<p> labour market tendering. The Jobs Network, it represents, for the</p>
<p> first time anywhere in the world, a far more private sector approach</p>
<p> to the process of job placement. Wherever you go, in all the fields</p>
<p> of our responsibility and our endeavour, this has been a great reforming</p>
<p> government.</p>
<p>And, of course, we have ahead of us that great unfinished piece of</p>
<p> economic reform business in Australia, and that is to reform Australia's</p>
<p> increasingly outmoded and ramshackled taxation system. We've</p>
<p> said, consistently, that we will lay before the Australian people,</p>
<p> before the next election, a plan to be implemented after the election</p>
<p> that will restore fairness and equity to the Australian taxation system.</p>
<p> A plan that will be bad news for the cheats, but good news for the</p>
<p> honest workers of Australia. It'll be good news for the exporters</p>
<p> of Australia. It'll be good news for the small business men and</p>
<p> women of Australia. And, above all else, it will be good news for</p>
<p> the future economic competitiveness of our nation.</p>
<p>What is the response of the Labor Party to that? The response of the</p>
<p> Labor Party to that is to pretend that the present system is adequate</p>
<p> - the system that they made worse and worse over a 13 year period.</p>
<p> And they demonstrate, by their response to our approach, they demonstrate</p>
<p> their fundamental indifference to serious reform and they demonstrate</p>
<p> their fundamental and continuing unfitness for office.</p>
<p>Ladies and gentlemen, there is one other great issue that is with</p>
<p> us at the present time. And that, of course, is to reform the Australian</p>
<p> waterfront. It is part, almost of the legend of industrial relations</p>
<p> and life in Australia, that our waterfront is inefficient. There's</p>
<p> that wonderful story about the lady of Charleville, when she was told</p>
<p> that a cyclone was coming by her grand-daughter and she said: don't</p>
<p> worry, darling, the wharfies won't land it. And, of course, it's</p>
<p> not a joke, only in the most peripheral of senses. It has long been</p>
<p> the grim reality of many of the exporters of Australia, particularly</p>
<p> our farmers who've worked hard in difficult seasons against great</p>
<p> odds only to see market opportunities squandered because of the inefficiency</p>
<p> of our waterfront. By any measure, we have a highly inefficient waterfront.</p>
<p>Bob Hawke promised and delivered many meetings when he was Prime Minister.</p>
<p> And that is the response of Mr Beazley He said: oh, there's no</p>
<p> problem with the waterfront, all you've got to do is have a meeting</p>
<p> or, if necessary, two or three or four or five meetings and at the</p>
<p> end of the day you can negotiate an arrangement with the Maritime</p>
<p> Union of Australia. Well, they tried that. The Labor Party tried that.</p>
<p> And there was about $450 million spent, under the former government,</p>
<p> as a result of all of those meetings. And we got absolutely no lasting</p>
<p> dividend in terms of improved productivity.</p>
<p>Our waterfront is still woefully inefficient by world standards. It</p>
<p> is miles behind the wharves of our competitor nations in the Asian</p>
<p> Pacific region. The reforms that were undertaken in New Zealand a</p>
<p> few years ago have literally left us for dead. We have tried negotiating.</p>
<p> We have always been willing to embrace sensible reform. But in the</p>
<p> past, the law has stood in the way. But now you have a government</p>
<p> that has had the courage to change the law.</p>
<p>When we changed the Industrial Relations Act, we broke the</p>
<p> monopoly on the recruitment and the supply of labour on the Australian</p>
<p> waterfront by the Maritime Union. And it has now been possible, through</p>
<p> the courage of Patricks - and I say that deliberately and unashamedly</p>
<p> - and the courage of the National Farmers' Federation. Those</p>
<p> two organisations have taken advantage of the law that we are proud</p>
<p> to say that we changed. And what we are now seeing is the first real</p>
<p> attempt for 50 years to deliver a more competitive waterfront. And</p>
<p> this is a defining moment in Australia's industrial relations</p>
<p> history. It is a defining moment in a very, very long saga, a disgraceful</p>
<p> saga, of low productivity and anti-competitive behaviour. And it's</p>
<p> an opportunity that has to be embraced, an opportunity grasped by</p>
<p> the Australian community.</p>
<p>And I want to say, on behalf of the Government, that we will support</p>
<p> any attempts, provided they are within the laws of Australia, to make</p>
<p> Australian wharves more competitive and more productive. And we will</p>
<p> support any, legitimately, within the laws of Australia, who commit</p>
<p> themselves to achieve those very important national interest goals.</p>
<p>And, of course, we're not dealing here with the battlers of the</p>
<p> trade union movement. We're not dealing here with underpaid people.</p>
<p> We're dealing here with people whose incomes are in the order</p>
<p> of $70,000 to $80,000 a year on average. We are dealing here with</p>
<p> people who've made an art form out of the rorting that goes on,</p>
<p> on the Australian waterfront. And we are dealing with a union that</p>
<p> believes that, above all unions, it has a right to privileged treatment,</p>
<p> that has a monopoly on privileged treatment and to hell with the consequences</p>
<p> to Australia and to the rest of the trade union movement. And one</p>
<p> of the things that I find quite intriguing about the behaviour of</p>
<p> the MUA over the past few days is the way in which the ACTU is edging</p>
<p> itself away and saying: well, no, we really want this strike limited,</p>
<p> we don't really want it to spread.</p>
<p>Well, can I just say again to all of you, ladies and gentlemen, this</p>
<p> is a defining moment in our industrial relations experience. It is</p>
<p> a very important issue and it is very important to the national interest</p>
<p> of Australia that there be the right conclusion.</p>
<p>My friends, can I say something of the contribution, as I would very</p>
<p> much like to do, of my Victorian colleagues to the successful working</p>
<p> of my Coalition Government. I'm very proud of the fact, of course,</p>
<p> that there are five Victorians in the Cabinet. And one of the most</p>
<p> interesting things I find to do is to make a few comparisons. I think</p>
<p> of the Minister and, if I can remember the Shadow Minister, I contrast</p>
<p> the performance of the Minister versus the Shadow Minister.</p>
<p>Now, I start with Peter Costello. Now, he's done pretty well.</p>
<p> He's done very well. And you know who his Shadow is - you must.</p>
<p> You're not depriving Gareth of attention, are you? The only thing</p>
<p> I'd say about that comparison is simply this, while Peter Costello's</p>
<p> been cutting your interest rates, Gareth Evans has been trawling through</p>
<p> the gutter of Australian politics.</p>
<p>Now, this is one that you really won't get, even in jest. Who</p>
<p> really knows the Shadow Minister for Industrial Relations? But, of</p>
<p> course, it gets even better. I don't think there's any -</p>
<p> Laurie? No, no. He's the Shadow Minister for Foreign Affairs.</p>
<p> Laurie was the Minister for Industrial Relations, now it's Bob</p>
<p> McMullan, in case anybody hadn't noticed - Bob McMullan - m-c-m-u-l-l-e-n,</p>
<p> I think. But if you think, you know, there's a bit of obscurity</p>
<p> there, I don't think any of you could name - and Richard, you're</p>
<p> not allowed to take part in this - the Shadow Minister for Communications.</p>
<p> He's an obscure...</p>
<p>INTERJECTION:</p>
<p>Richard doesn't know either, Prime Minister. Richard, doesn't</p>
<p> know either.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER CONTINUES:</p>
<p>And then, of course, we have the comparison of the Health Minister,</p>
<p> Michael. And can I say, very, very seriously and very, very sincerely</p>
<p> what an outstanding job, in a very, very difficult portfolio, Michael</p>
<p> Wooldridge has done. He's an extremely valued member of my Ministerial</p>
<p> team. His opponent is that man - the little boy lost, we call him</p>
<p> - home alone from Dobell, Michael Lee.</p>
<p>And then, of course, we come to David Kemp's adversary. I'm</p>
<p> reminded of that old biblical injunction:- would that my enemy would</p>
<p> write a book. And, of course, David's adversary is Mark Latham.</p>
<p> And he's read his bible and he's written a book. The only</p>
<p> thing Mark Latham hasn't done, of course, is to say anything</p>
<p> relevant about education. And I can remember when he was appointed</p>
<p> as the Shadow Minister for Education, Mr Beazley ran around saying:</p>
<p> look, watch out Liberals, you'll be sorry you ever heard of Mark</p>
<p> Latham. I think Kim Beazley would be sorry that he'd ever heard</p>
<p> of Mark Latham. It's a great book. It actually contains some</p>
<p> thinking. And for the first time in two years you've seen somebody</p>
<p> in the Labor Party say something relevant about the future. And we're</p>
<p> very happy to remind the Australian people of this because Mark Latham</p>
<p> supports fundamental reform of Australia's taxation system. He</p>
<p> supports a broad-based, indirect tax. He supports the principle of</p>
<p> mutual obligation in welfare. He supports a progressive industry policy.</p>
<p> In other words, he supports all of the things that Kim Beazley, Simon</p>
<p> Crean and Gareth Evans totally oppose. He's a great Shadow Minister.</p>
<p>Ladies and gentlemen, could I finally say something, recognising that,</p>
<p> inevitably, in a federation, there will be some differences of emphasis</p>
<p> from time to time on the respective responsibilities of the Federal</p>
<p> and State governments. Can I something about the issue of the respective</p>
<p> health care responsibilities of the State and the Federal Government.</p>
<p> As governments we all have our responsibilities. And I think there</p>
<p> is a united view, certainly between myself and the Premier of Victoria</p>
<p> and all the other Premiers and Chief Ministers of Australia, that</p>
<p> we should deliver, to the Australian people, the best aged care and</p>
<p> the best health care system that we can.</p>
<p>We have our direct responsibilities. We have them for aged care and</p>
<p> we have them for private health insurance. And we also share responsibilities</p>
<p> through the Medicare agreement for the funding of public hospitals</p>
<p> by the State governments. And I know there have been some public disagreements</p>
<p> between the Federal and State governments. And I do want to say very</p>
<p> factually and calmly, on behalf of the Federal Government, that we</p>
<p> believe that the offer that we have made to the States is a fair and</p>
<p> reasonable one.</p>
<p>I understand the concern of States. Equally, I ask you to understand</p>
<p> the facts. I ask you to remember that the agreement that we propose,</p>
<p> commencing on the 1st of July this year, for a five year period, will</p>
<p> involve an increase of three per cent each, so that there'll</p>
<p> be accumulative real increase of 15 per cent over the five-year period.</p>
<p> And this is in a climate of zero inflation. I ask you to bear in mind</p>
<p> that in our general tax payments going to the States, for all purposes,</p>
<p> there will be an increase of almost five per cent, in real terms,</p>
<p> in a climate of zero inflation. I think it is a matter, undisputed,</p>
<p> on the public record that between 1993 and 1998, the Commonwealth</p>
<p> spent over $3.25 billion more on hospitals than if the 1992 levels</p>
<p> had continued. And the States only spent $355 million more than if</p>
<p> the 1992 funding levels had gone on. And that in the first and second</p>
<p> years of that five year period, State spending actually declined by</p>
<p> $500 million in 93-94 and $331 million in the following</p>
<p> year. And that according to my advice, Victoria, South Australia,</p>
<p> Western Australia, Tasmania and the Northern Territory, on adjusted</p>
<p> 1992 dollar levels, is spending less now than was the case in those</p>
<p> years.</p>
<p>Now, I don't mention these figures other than to put, plainly</p>
<p> and unemotionally, on the public record what is our position. Because</p>
<p> the offer that we have made does represent real growth over that five-year</p>
<p> period. And it is a fair and defensible and reasonable offer. We have</p>
<p> responsibilities in the health and aged care area that go beyond our</p>
<p> responsibilities with the States in relation to public hospitals.</p>
<p>I announced last Thursday a very important expansion of the Commonwealth's</p>
<p> investment in the aged care area, built around the belief that the</p>
<p> greatest thing that we can do for the aged in Australia is to give</p>
<p> them the choice, for as long as possible, to remain within the secure</p>
<p> environment of their own homes. And the whole purpose of the policy</p>
<p> I announced on Thursday was to do that. And it was also a policy that</p>
<p> broke new ground at a Federal level in the area of providing assistance</p>
<p> and comfort for carers within our community. And I have to say, in</p>
<p> all the years that I've been in Parliament, the most moving stories</p>
<p> that I have had from constituents have been stories about the difficulty,</p>
<p> often of very elderly people caring for adult children with profound</p>
<p> disabilities and impairments. And nobody could be less than totally</p>
<p> moved and touched by those stories. They are the great unsung heroes</p>
<p> and heroines of any compassionate and decent society. And what they</p>
<p> have a right to expect from the Government and what they have a right</p>
<p> to expect from the entire community is a recognition, is a firm recognition</p>
<p> of the tremendous role that they play and also some improvement in</p>
<p> the material support that they receive.</p>
<p>And I'm very happy that, from the 1st of July this year, there'll</p>
<p> be a significant increase in the domiciliary care benefit. And also</p>
<p> that we are going to expand the respite facilities. And we're</p>
<p> also, over the next 12 or fifteen months, we're going to expand</p>
<p> the eligibility criteria for that care benefit and we're going</p>
<p> to combine it with the Disabled Childrens Benefit into a new carers</p>
<p> allowance which will have expanded criteria. So that a larger number</p>
<p> of people, I estimate up to 14,000 or 15,000 additional people, will</p>
<p> be able to qualify. This is an area of very great need. It is an area</p>
<p> of direct Federal Government responsibility. And it is an area in</p>
<p> which we are injecting more resources and more support.</p>
<p>I always regret, as I know my State colleagues do, any disagreements</p>
<p> on issues that are important to our joint endeavours. But it is the</p>
<p> responsibility of both levels of government, when those disagreements</p>
<p> occur it is the responsibility of both levels of government to put</p>
<p> their cases with care and with prudence, not emotionally, understated</p>
<p> it necessary, but nonetheless firmly, politely and factually. And</p>
<p> I have to say, on behalf of my Government, in that firm, polite, factual</p>
<p> fashion, that the offer that we have made does represent a generous</p>
<p> increase on the last five years. It does represent three per cent,</p>
<p> real, each year for five years. It does build upon an almost five</p>
<p> per cent real increase in the general tax money going to the States</p>
<p> in a climate of zero inflation. And it does have to be used against</p>
<p> the background of the individual spending decisions on hospitals that</p>
<p> have been made by all the State Governments over the past few years.</p>
<p> Now, I do have available as a result of work done by my staff, I do</p>
<p> have available, and with Michael Wooldridge's office, some material</p>
<p> explaining these things in more detail for any of you who would be</p>
<p> interested to have it.</p>
<p>Ladies and gentlemen, I know that in the course of Government it is</p>
<p> inevitable that there will be some disagreements and I think it is</p>
<p> important that the facts be examined in a very unemotional, and if</p>
<p> necessary, understated fashion.</p>
<p>Can I finally say, ladies and gentlemen, that in a sense returning</p>
<p> to what I said at the beginning of my address, and that is that we</p>
<p> have achieved an enormous amount over the last two years. And we've</p>
<p> achieved it because there has been tremendous co-operation between</p>
<p> all of the members of the Federal Parliamentary Party. And I want</p>
<p> to express to all of my Victorian colleagues, to all of you without</p>
<p> exception, my personal gratitude for the support and loyalty and understanding</p>
<p> that you have given over the last two years. There have been occasions</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
