<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>17472</transcript-id>
    <title>Transcript of joint press conference with the President of the United States of America, Yokohama, Japan</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/11/2010</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Yokohama, Japan </p>
<p>PRESIDENT OBAMA: The United States does not have a closer or better ally than Australia. We are grateful for all the work that we do together. I expressed my personal thanks to the people of Australia through the Prime Minister for the enormous sacrifices that are being made in Afghanistan by Australian troops.</p>
<p>We, I think, are going to be discussing these issues further when we see each other at the Lisbon Summit, but obviously all of us here have an interest in bringing about a good outcome in that region that ensures our safety and security over the long term.</p>
<p>On the economic front, I have reiterated to the Prime Minister how important the Asia Pacific region is to our economy and to world economic growth. Australia is a central player in that economy, so we are going to continue to explore ways that we can work together to expand trade, expand investment, ensure that everybody is playing by the rules of the road in the region and co-operating effectively. The Trans-Pacific Partnership is a good example of the kind of collaboration between our two countries and I think we can expand opportunities for all people.</p>
<p>So I am just grateful to have this opportunity to speak with the Prime Minister, I have extended an invitation to her to visits the United States sometime early next year and we'll find a date and hopefully we can build on some of the discussions we've already had to further enhance our bilateral co-operation.</p>
<p>So Prime Minister, thank you and to your entire delegation for the good work that you've done and I look forward to seeing you in Washington.</p>
<p>PM: Thank you. If I could say to President Obama, we've had the opportunity to be at the G20 over the last few days and had the opportunity to have a few brief discussions there and we will see each other in Lisbon next weekend.</p>
<p>Our two countries are great mates, to use our terminology and as great mates we are continuing to work together in our region and beyond. We have had the opportunity to talk about Afghanistan and I do take this opportunity to pass on the condolences of the Australian people for the losses that you have suffered there. But we are working together there and will have time next weekend at Lisbon to talk about the transition strategy.</p>
<p>We have also had the opportunity to reflect on the discussions we had at AUSMIN about the American force posture review and the work that we are doing on new challenges like cyber security. And we've had the opportunity to talk about our engagement in the region there, the US engagement is strengthening through forums like the East Asia Summit and we are on the same page on trade, so we very much look forward to the discussions of the Trans-Pacific Partnership during the course of the APEC meetings.</p>
<p>So a very good opportunity to have a good discussion about the areas where our two countries are collaborating now and will in the future. Thank you.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
