<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9537</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP INTERVIEW WITH DAMIEN MURPHY, 2WEB, BOURKE 5 APRIL 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/04/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009537.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
I, j<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
INTERVIEW WITH DAMIEN MURPHY, 2WEB, BOURKE<br />
APRIL 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
DM: Mr Keating, good morning and welcome to Bourke.<br />
PM: Good on you, Damien. Nice to be here great to be here in the name<br />
of Fred Hollows.<br />
DM: Ever been to Bourke before?<br />
PM: No. I have been, of course, all over being a New South Welshman -I<br />
have been all over NSW, but I have always wanted to come to Bourke.<br />
DM: A number of people have said over the last couple of days that really<br />
with Fred Hollows the recognition hasn't come until his death it has<br />
really sort of been since Fred Hollows died that, you know, all the<br />
news about the good work that he did has come about. Now, you<br />
actually met Fred Hollows what are your memories of the late<br />
Professor?<br />
PM: I don't think Fred was after recognition he was after results. And I<br />
think that's why people admired him, and what I remember of him was<br />
a very no-nonsense, straight to the point fellow who was a member of<br />
the community. Though he was a professional, he dedicated himself<br />
to people and he was a no-nonsense, down to earth, straight down to<br />
the job sort of person.<br />
DM: You have come a long way you have come up from Canberra last<br />
night why have you made the effort to be here today for the launch of<br />
the Fred Hollows race?<br />
PM: I think that it is important that people who do good things like Fred<br />
did, and where it is now being continued by the Hollows Foundation<br />
with Gabi and Mike Lynskey and others that this sort of community </p>
<p>2<br />
activity should be celebrated and supported, because it is going on not<br />
simply in Australia with disadvantaged communities like the<br />
Aboriginal community but it is going on now in Nepal and Eritrea and<br />
Vietnam and all these other places where hundreds and thousands of<br />
people are going to be given back their sight. It is also a model for the<br />
way we can approach the problem of health well, certainly health<br />
problems of disadvantaged people direct, on the ground,<br />
compassionate, practical. So these are the reasons we are here to<br />
remember Fred and to support the Foundation.<br />
DM: Professor Hollows was heavily involved in health care for indigenous<br />
Australians, as you just mentioned, and made it his priority to care for<br />
those free of charge who could afford nothing else are these the sorts<br />
of values that are maintained by the Federal Government today?<br />
PM: That's why we say the values one of the primary things that drives<br />
Government policies is inclusion. That everybody... this is where<br />
Medicare comes from you get medical support regardless of income,<br />
and regardless of your circumstances but we want to make sure that<br />
this universality of care and compassion goes to the most<br />
disadvantaged. So that's why we are interested in the Aboriginal<br />
community, that's why we are interested in the long-term unemployed,<br />
it's why we try and say that this country the policies are there for<br />
everybody. It is one nation, and it is inclusive. And I think Fred made<br />
that very obvious he was doing he could have been a professional in<br />
a ritzy house with a Mercedes under instead of that he was out<br />
in the scrub looking after disadvantaged people. I think that same<br />
spirit should pervade Government policy, and I can say that with this<br />
Government, it does.<br />
DM: Fred is buried at Bourke, of course that was his request it's a harsh<br />
environment out here we have had the drought for the last 18 months<br />
or so, and we did get some rain back in January. However, that rain<br />
hasn't continued the drought is still a bit of a problem up here any<br />
chance of a review of financial assistance policies for farmers?<br />
PM: Let me tell you the Mayor said the moon looked pretty good last night,<br />
and he thinks that the rain is coming there was half an inch overnight,<br />
so was it half an inch, Wally? (" further out") Further out. Well<br />
anyway I'm banking on him I think he is the best weather man I know<br />
around here. And it's rain, of course, that matters in the farm analysis,<br />
but what we have sought to do is to extend the Commonwealth's social<br />
security system to farmers who have been severely affected by<br />
drought, by removing the on-farm assets tests. Now, what that means<br />
is that we discount the value of the assets to give people income<br />
support. And I think we have now got about 10,000 families farm<br />
families getting income support, where they weren't before. Because<br />
the argument used to be you have got all these assets, but as we<br />
know, those assets can't be eaten, and you can't dispose of them, so<br />
then we have got of course the structural adjustment assistance </p>
<p>through RAS the Rural Adjustment Scheme. And we have been<br />
continuing to improve that over time. At any rate, I am going to meet<br />
some of the people here today who have been affected by drought<br />
just have a discussion with them.<br />
DM: Just yesterday, newly elected State Premier Bob Carr announced that<br />
he would be touring the State tomorrow and Friday if he determines<br />
that there is more assistance required, will you be heeding that?<br />
PM: We have a set of what we call national disaster relief arrangements,<br />
and we have got an even more sophisticated set of arrangements now<br />
with the drought because there has been this sort of impact on the<br />
seasons that seems to have changed, and we have had more drought<br />
than perhaps we have seen in a long time, and policy has adjusted<br />
accordingly. So we have got a regime running with the States<br />
particularly Queensland and NSW. But NSW was dragging the chain<br />
on drought payments, and I hope Bob Carr does put the right amount<br />
of time and attention to it.<br />
DM: Liberal Senator from Western Australia, Noel Crichton-Browne, with<br />
the domestic violence restraint order there should he stay, or should<br />
he go?<br />
PM: That's something for himself and the Liberal Party.<br />
OMV: If there was somebody in the Labor Party who was involved in the<br />
same sort of scandal if you like, what would you be suggesting they<br />
do?<br />
PM: These are basically personal matters, and they are for Parties to make<br />
decisions about who they have representing them. I don't want to be<br />
judgmental about Mr Crichton-Browne and the Liberal Party he has<br />
got his own family and his own party to think about, and I'm afraid it is<br />
a matter for them.<br />
DMV: Top story of the day this morning is the super-league what do you<br />
think about that?<br />
PM: I think it has added a lot of spice to football, obviously. It's the biggest<br />
news since World Series Cricket.<br />
DM: Do you think there is any role for the Government in the super-league?<br />
PM: A good role as a spectator, I can tell you that.<br />
DM: Any deeper role than that Government intervention?<br />
PM: I don't think so. </p>
<p>DM: Okay. You wouldn't be worried then if the Rugby League split and<br />
there were two competitions running concurrently?<br />
PM: As long as league fans think there is a live, energetic competition out<br />
there... when Rugby League moved to other States there was bound to<br />
be some sort of change in the League, I think. But anyway, that is for<br />
them to manage.<br />
DM: You're a Canterbury supporter how would you feel if the team is<br />
knocked out of the League next Tuesday?<br />
PM: It depends whether the Sydney clubs which are now getting where<br />
you can run a competition with the Bronco's and the Raiders with the<br />
Sydney clubs the way they were I think probably what has happened<br />
might have been inevitable, maybe it happened a bit faster with a<br />
couple of big cheque books around.<br />
DM: Prime Minister, super league or no super league, thanks very much for<br />
your time today, and I hope you have a great day in Bourke.<br />
PM: Good on you thanks Damien, good to be here.<br />
ends. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
