<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>40665</transcript-id>
    <title>Prime Minister Unveils Australia&#039;s DCNS HQ in Adelaide</title>
    <prime-minister>Turnbull, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20150915 - 20180824</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/12/2016</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The DCNS Australian headquarters, dedicated to the $50 billion Future Submarine Program, has been officially unveiled in Adelaide today, marking a significant milestone.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister the Hon. Malcolm Turnbull MP, and Minister for Defence Industry, the Hon Christopher Pyne MP, congratulated Chief Executive Officer DCNS, Mr Herve Guillou, and Chief Executive Officer DCNS Australia, Mr Sean Costello, at the Future Submarine facility.</p>
<p>“I welcome the infrastructure investment from DCNS as Australia’s international partner for this historic Future Submarine Program,” Prime Minister Turnbull said.                </p>
<p>“This space will be more than just an office; it will be an innovative hub delivering cutting edge administration and support services focussed on delivering regionally superior submarines and creating and sustaining jobs across Australia for decades to come.”</p>
<p>Minister Pyne said that today's DCNS site unveiling in Adelaide was a significant milestone that highlights a timely start of design and robust planning for each phase of the Future Submarine Program that will allow benefits to start flowing to the Australian economy.</p>
<p>“DCNS understands the importance of Australian industry involvement in the Future Submarine Program to ensure the on time delivery of a regionally superior sovereign submarine capability for Australia.</p>
<p>“The Turnbull Government is committed to maximising Australian Defence industry involvement in this continuous naval shipbuilding strategy – an approach that will ensure thousands of permanent jobs are created, and supported.</p>
<p>“DCNS has already held the first of many industry engagement sessions, which shows that industry is working with the Turnbull Government to deliver on our commitment to regenerate the Navy in a way not seen since the Second World War,” Minister Pyne said.</p>

]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
