<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3551</transcript-id>
    <title>INTERNATIONAL WOMEN&#039;S YEAR</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/12/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003551.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
457<br />
AUS l RIA. A IA PRP'SS STATEMENT NO. 417<br />
17 Mecember 1974<br />
INTERNATIONAL WOMEN' S YEAR<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr Whitlam, announced today the<br />
recipients of the first set of grants to be made for special<br />
activities during International Women's Year, 1075.<br />
He stated that he had approved the grants on the<br />
advice of the Australian National Advisory Committee for<br />
International Women's Year. This w,. iuld be the first of a<br />
series of grants to be made for the Year .: ind ref-! ected the<br />
areas of special priority determined by the Committee and set<br />
out in the paper for discussion tabled in both es of<br />
Parliament on 4 December 1974. De: ni. cd arrangements are<br />
subject to negotiation with the individuals ao groups<br />
concerned.<br />
General Community Attitudes<br />
Australian Council of Churches Status of Women Commission<br />
The Australian Council of Churches in June 1973 established<br />
a Commission on the Status of Women to investigate the status<br />
and role of women in the church and society, to remove discrimination<br />
on the grounds of sex and to stimulate tilr. full participation of<br />
women in the church and society. During 1975, the Commission<br />
will hold a national conference, a regional conference involving<br />
women from Papua New Guinea, Pacific Islands, New Zealand and<br />
Australia . and a seminar for clergy; will undertake a study of<br />
the history of women in the church! and will produce various<br />
publications and visual displays.<br />
Gwen Wesson La Trobe University ( Victoria)<br />
Ms Wesson has collected the writings ( poems, essays, short<br />
stories) of suburban housewives, to be published in a book as<br />
unedited expressions of women in the process of resocialisation<br />
as they move from the domination housewifery.<br />
Australia ' 75 ( Canberra)<br />
This festival, to be held in Canberra in March, will feature<br />
a Baroque to Rock Concert, featuring woeien arliists; the reading<br />
of songs and poetry by Dorothy Hewett; and a stage portrayal of<br />
pioneer women in Australia by Nita Pannell. ./ 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
National Council of Women of Tasmania<br />
The Council will hold a one-day seminar in May 1975 to<br />
focus attention on the importance of women in all walks of<br />
life taking an active part in the processes of government<br />
at all levels, to encourage the increased participation of<br />
women in government.<br />
Health and Welfare<br />
Fitzroy Accommodation Service ( Victoria)<br />
The Fitzroy Accommodation Service will receive an interim<br />
grant to enable it to continue to assist homeless women and<br />
men find suitable accommodation until the Department of<br />
Housing and Construction is in a position to fund it. The<br />
majority of such demands for assistance are made by women.<br />
Committee for the Liverpool Women's Health and Resources<br />
Centre Interim funding is to be provided to enable the establishment<br />
of a multi-purpose women's centre consi'sting of a refuge shelter<br />
for women in urgent and desparate need, and a meicrial/ recreational/<br />
educational centre with child mindi~ g facilities.<br />
Western Australian Institute of Technology<br />
A grant has been approved to enable women with low incomes<br />
to attend a one-day seminar on " Women frori Minority Groups"<br />
which will involve women from various minorities ( aboriginal,<br />
ethnic, single mothers, physically and emotionally handicapped,<br />
etc.) Education Footscray Institute of Technology ( Victoria)<br />
The Institute will prepare leaflets to attract women to<br />
engineering, against obvious Australian prejudi. ce to the<br />
contrary, and will offer an orientation course to women who<br />
have felt that their knowledge of technological terminology<br />
has been inadequate compared to that of men. It is hoped<br />
that their action will attract some women to enter the profession<br />
of engineering who would otherwise have gone to a profession<br />
of their second preference.<br />
Work Anne Conlon and Edna Ryan<br />
Ms Conlon and Ms Ryan have written a book, The Gentle<br />
Invaders Australian Women at Work 1788-. 974, on women's<br />
participation in the labour force rince Australia was founded.<br />
It describes the arbitration system and gives the background<br />
to wage fixation in Australia with particular refercnce to<br />
women. </p>
<p>-3-<br />
Creativity Joan Long<br />
A grant will assist in the production of a feature fil. m<br />
based on the book Caddie, an autobiography set in 1.925-32<br />
about a woman on her wn, her struggle to support herself<br />
and her children, of the attitudes of the society and of<br />
her efforts to adjust and survive.<br />
Women's Theatre Group ( Victoria)<br />
This group of women uses theatre to show the oppression<br />
of women in society, to challenge sex roles, and to create<br />
new styles and new images for women. Their 1975 program will<br />
include community per: ormances, performances in schools and<br />
places of work, and a country tour.<br />
The Prime Minister also announced that the Australian<br />
National Advisory Committee, which is composed of individuals<br />
chosen from the community and do not represent nry organisation,<br />
state or sectional group, recoanised the great value and need<br />
to actively involvewomen's groLps in International Women's<br />
Year. Accordingly in view of the long association of the<br />
United Nations Association of Australia in United Natio'ns<br />
Years he intended to make grants to the forum of women's groups<br />
at both national and state level constituted by the United<br />
Nations Association of Australia the United : ations Association<br />
of Australia Committees for International Wonten's Year. These<br />
grants would enable the Committees to meet throughout the Year<br />
and engage in specified activities. It was expected that the<br />
Committees would carry out these activities within the context<br />
of the objectives formulated by the National Advisory Committee.<br />
The Prime Minister also announced that Australia had<br />
contributed $ US40,000 towards the United Nations Voluntary Fund<br />
for International Women's Year. This will ena''. e the United<br />
Nations to carry out its own activities duri!, i the year whichinclude<br />
a world conference on the theme-of Equality, Development<br />
and Peace to be held in Mexico in June 1975, an inter-regional<br />
conference on The Communication of Attitudes: Women, The Arts<br />
and The Media to be held in Australia in 1975,<br />
and the publication of a wide range of malrerial relating to the<br />
Year. CANBERRA, A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
