<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5346</transcript-id>
    <title>THE CONVENTION FOR THE CONSERVATION OF ANTARCTIC MARINE LIVING RESOURCES</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/05/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005346.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
THE CONVENTION FOR THE CONSERVATION OF<br />
ANTARCTIC MARINE LIVING RESOURCES<br />
The Commonwealth Government has decided to propose Hobart as<br />
the site for the headquarters of an international Conservation<br />
Commission to be established under the proposed Convention on<br />
the Conservation of Antarctic Marine Living Resources.<br />
This proposal has been under discussion for some time with the<br />
Premier of Tasmania and has been pursued informally during<br />
earlier international meetings developing the Convention.<br />
Delegates from 15 countries are meeting in Canberra from today<br />
until 20 May 1980 to draw up the text of the Convention, which<br />
has been under negotiation in international forums for over<br />
two years.<br />
Australia's decision to propose Hobart as the headquarters of<br />
theConservation Commission reflects the Commonwealth's<br />
determination to promote Tasmania'* s pre-eminence in fields of<br />
study and research relating to Antarctic and marine matters.<br />
There have been several other important Commonwealth initiatives<br />
to assist Tasmania in this respect, including establishment of<br />
the Australian Maritime College in Launceston, transfer to<br />
Hobart of the Antarctic Division of the Department of Science<br />
and the Environment, and most recently, the Government's decision<br />
to establish a Marine Science Centre in Hobart including the<br />
transfer of the CSIRO Division of Fisheries and Oceanography.<br />
The Commonwealth's recent initiatives in this respect, including<br />
the proposal for Hobart as the site for the international<br />
Conservation Commission, reflect the positive response taken by<br />
the Commonwealth to the report of Sir Bede Callaghan on his<br />
examination of the structure of industry and the employment<br />
situation in Tasmania.<br />
The meeting of delegates in Canberra to discuss the draft<br />
Convention on Antarctic Marine Living Resources is the culmination<br />
of a long negotiating process which commenced with an earlier<br />
Canberra meeting in March 1978 to prepare the basic negotiating<br />
text. ./ 2 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
