<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10243</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER AND THE PRIME MINISTER OF NEW ZEALAND DOORSTOP INTERVIEW REDWOOD GROVE - ROTORUA</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/02/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010243.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Fax from 4?<br />
____ PRIME MINISTER<br />
16 February 1997 TRANSCRIPT OF M$ PRIME MiNISTER<br />
AND THE PRIME MINISTER OF NEW ZEALAND<br />
DOORSTOP INTERVIEW<br />
REDWOOD GROVE ROTORUA<br />
BOLGER: Can I just say thank you for comning. Prime Minister Howard and myself of course have<br />
had an iniformal chat that has continued since we met at Ohakea yesterday morning and,<br />
as anticipated, there are certainly no big issues between us. We've got a number of<br />
issues that we have a common interest in and we will continue to discuss those over the<br />
next 24 hours or so, but it's been a very, very pleasant opportunity to talk to John about<br />
the issues that arc important to Australia, about the issues that are of importance to both<br />
our countries, and for me to perhaps explain how we are bringing together the new<br />
Coalition Government and aWl of that. So, good chat.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister Howard, what sort of issues, have you so far talked about?<br />
HOWA) RD-:<br />
Oh, just about everything,<br />
BOLGER: Yes. HOWARD;<br />
We had four-and-a-half hours of very friendly, very informal, very informative<br />
discussions. One of the good things about our association at a personal level is the<br />
Faoxm1 6/ 82/ 97 11: 17 Pg: 1 </p>
<p>Fax fromU-16/ 62/ 97 11: 1 7 Pg: 2<br />
capacity to razWg over the whole gamut of domestic and foreign affirs issues. Jim<br />
Bolger, of course, was the first oversas leader to speak to me after the electon. We've<br />
seen each other on three Occasions since we've spoken regularly on the telephone.<br />
Through that association, there's the basis of strengthening in evezy way the already very<br />
close association between our two countries. I certainly find the opportunityto compare<br />
notes on domestic political issues and also to look at our joint efforts within the region.<br />
In most area we have a very common view, although on some occasions inevitably<br />
there's a different emphasis here and there because of the different interests of our<br />
countries, but I thought last night was about as good as it ever gets, as far as the<br />
informality and the friendly exchange of excpernmnce that you can get between two<br />
policitical leaders. Of course, im and I share, through our respective parties the<br />
Nationals in New Zealand and the Liberals in Australia many common values and<br />
common philosophies, and we also ecvhanged a few notes on the vagaries of Coalitions,<br />
which is something that I'm a veteran of.-Coalition Governments.<br />
BOLGER: That's right, yes. More experienced than us.<br />
JOUR1NALIST: Did you discuss the Australian experience of gun control, in light of recent tragic<br />
circumstances here?<br />
HOWARD: We touched vety briefly on that last night. I imagine that will come up. That, of course,<br />
is I'm only too happy to talk about the expeionces that we had but, as in all things,<br />
that's a matter for the New Zealand Government. But if I can be of any help in that area<br />
and if any of my experience of last year and the experience of the Australian people<br />
following Port Arthur is of any help in current circumstances in New Zealand, well, I<br />
would only be too happy to help.<br />
JOURNALIST: Are you concerned at New Zealand.' s defence spending, how it's sort of dwindled over<br />
the past eight years?<br />
HOWARD: Oh look. I baven't come here to son of give lectures to people. We have our attitudes<br />
and I'll be saying something in the more formal setting of the discussions tomorrow in<br />
the address that I'm giving, but we will be talking about that in the discussions, along<br />
with a lot of other things, but I'm not a I don't come here as ' lecturer Howard', I come<br />
here as ' allied friend Howard',<br />
JOURNALIST: M&amp; Bolger, would you like to follow Australia's lead on gun control? </p>
<p>Fax from 16/ 02/ 97 11: 17 Pg: 3<br />
BOLGER3. Well, at the tune of the tragedy last week, of COUrse we already had in train a review of<br />
our gun laws. So, no doubt, whatever lessons may be learned from that tragedy,<br />
whatever might emerge in terms of the discussions that follow and the inevitable trial,<br />
will no doubt be taken into account In New Zealand, but you may be aware that we<br />
changed and tightened our gun control after the Aromoana tragedy of 1990. So, we had<br />
moved quite substantially to control the use of multi-weapoN, multi-fidnzg bullets, multifiring<br />
guns, the old AK 47 lookalikes and all of those. So that's already very tight in<br />
New Zealand. But if there's anything we can learn from Australia, if there's anything we<br />
cam lean from the report that's being conducted now by a former High Court Judge,<br />
well, we will certainly do so.<br />
JOURNALIST: MW Howard, have you discussed whether is there something Australia can learn ftrm<br />
New Zealand in that area and just one quick one on after the talk the other day, there<br />
was concen from some of the parties that your hope of doing it by Easter could be<br />
ambitious. Are you flexible on that?<br />
HOWARD: Well, I don't want to talk about domestic issues specificay here. Look, on the question<br />
of shared experiences with native title issues, we in fatct did spend a lot of time talking<br />
about that last night. in fact, it occupied as much, if not more, time than any other<br />
subject. The experience of New Zealand and Australia is different. The legal basis of<br />
the relationship between the indigenous people of Now Zealand and the indigenous<br />
people of Australia has been quite different. I thought we had a very for me, that was a<br />
very valuable discussion, I suppose in all of these things you can learn things from each<br />
other's VEperience. We are endeavouring in Australia, of course, to see if there is the<br />
basis of an agreed outcome and that's the purpose of-<br />
BOLGER: All of us are ultimately controlled by the.. .( inaudible)...<br />
HOWARD; Having initiating discussions. I don't want to get into any discssion at this stage about<br />
the relevance of dates. We still have a long way to go, and rm under no illusions about<br />
how difficult it is. But the New Zealand experience has been very different, and because<br />
of that different legal starting point, and, Of course the relative size of the indigenous<br />
population has also been a major facor as well.<br />
BOLGIER: Can I just say on tha. I think we had, as Primne Mnister Howard said, an excellent<br />
discussion on what is one of the most complex issues for both our countries, and that is<br />
how we deal with the indigenous people's rights and aspirations, and the range of that<br />
discussion, I thought, was tremendous. </p>
<p>Fax-from HOWARD:<br />
It was excellent.<br />
BOLGER: In terms of just looking at it ina a totally non-partisan, non-doctriniaire way and saying,<br />
look, there are issues. We were talking about our New Zealand experience, John<br />
Howard is talking about the Auistralian experience as it's emerging now, the involvement<br />
of the courts in both countries and setting some parameters and some guidelines for<br />
goveilazents. It is a complex issue, dare I say it, and we in New Zealand know that and<br />
you in Australia know that.<br />
JOURNAIZT:, Gentlemen, did you discuss your difing views on a Republic?<br />
BOLGER: No. we didn't, but we did discuss the fact that Australa of course is going to have the<br />
Convention that John Howard promised beforehand, and that we, of course, are in the<br />
process of a constitutional change of same enormous significance here, with the move to<br />
proportional elections and now the first elected Coalition Government for 60 years, so<br />
we certainly had general discussions on political structures, and they were interesting. I<br />
have to say I find that whole constitutional debate an interesting development in both<br />
countries, and I'd have to saylI don't think we've heard the last of it here, arnd I surmise<br />
not in Australia.<br />
JOURNALIST: What about on the Social Welfare front? Are you looking at legislation to make<br />
BOLGMR Didn't get onto that, Duncan.<br />
JOURNALIST: A two year stand down period? You haven't talked about that?<br />
BOLGER:<br />
No, we didn't.<br />
HOWARD: Oh, we didn't dicuss that last night. Farxom 16/ 02/ 97 11: 17 Pg: 4 </p>
<p>fax trom 16/ 02/ 97 11: 17 Pg:<br />
a r BOLGER: No, no.<br />
JOURNALIST: It's not on the agenda?<br />
HOWARD: Well, anything's on the agenda that either Minister it's the sort of relationship that if<br />
there's anything on Jim's mind that he wants to raise, he wilL If there's anything on my<br />
mind that I want to raise, I will, but that specifically was not discussed last night,<br />
BOLGER: No, I think you've got enough now for today. Look, you've done extraordinarily well.<br />
HOWARD: That's right.<br />
BOLGER: You've got far more than I thought, and I feel like a walk. Thanks a lot. TOTAL </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
