<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9746</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J.KEATING MP DOORSTOP, BEAUFORT HOTEL, DARWIN, 6 SEPTEMBER 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/09/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009746.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
C)<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
DOORSTOP, BEAUFORT HOTEL, DARWIN, 6 SEPTEMBER 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
J: How do you feel about the bomb going off, are you going to take any<br />
action?<br />
PM: I condemn what the French have done in the strongest possible terms.<br />
It is an act of stupidity. It is not something they need to do. Australia<br />
has now arraigned the strongest set of sanctions we have ever<br />
arraigned against any other democracy in our history. We have<br />
suspended defence contracts. We have withdrawn the Ambassador.<br />
We have taken this issue up at the United Nations. We have made an<br />
impact in France and in Europe and, I think, this is reacting now<br />
against the Government of France in France. So, these things, I think,<br />
show the strength of our feeling here and the fact that the risk is the<br />
proliferation risk. It isn't that the French don't have weapons that are<br />
of high military grade. The risk for all of us is the proliferation of<br />
nuclear weapons and that is what the French are devaluing.<br />
J: Are you aware the New Zealanders have withdrawn their Ambassador<br />
this morning?<br />
PM: We withdrew our Ambassador a month ago to register our protest.<br />
But, we now want an Ambassador to make that contact to express our<br />
disaffection and also to be there when Minister Bilney leads the<br />
delegation there. Now is the time we want contact, basically, to hop<br />
into the French.<br />
J: How do you feel all this time, all this effort, to no avail?<br />
PM: France is an independent country and they can make the decisions,<br />
but they are now wearing the admonition of people around the world<br />
including Australia.<br />
J: What sort of a response can you outline now, what can you do now,<br />
what is the next step? </p>
<p>2<br />
PM: We are continuing to proselytise on the issue. As you know I have<br />
had a substantial amount of press in France. The Foreign Minister<br />
has had. Mr Bilney is going with a delegation. We have already had<br />
oie led by Gareth Evans and this is putting pressure on the French<br />
and President Chirac has given some indication now to reduce the<br />
number of tests. Well, we want it reduced to zero.<br />
J: So, his offer last night isn't good enough as far as you are concerned?<br />
PM: They should abandon the tests. They should abandon the tests and<br />
get on with the real problem, that is, how they contain the nuclear<br />
threat in the non-nuclear nations.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
