<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9604</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING AND COMMUNICATION LINK</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/05/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009604.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
48/ 95<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING AND COMMUNICATION LINK<br />
At our meeting today MITI Minister Hashimoto and I agreed that Australia and<br />
Japan will establish a high performance computing electronic data connection<br />
between the two countries. The initial capacity of the link will be l92KBit per<br />
second.<br />
This initiative will provide a foundation for the development of broadband<br />
communications between Australia and Japan.<br />
The network connection will allow close collaboration between Australia and<br />
Japan in new generation high performance computers. A working group of<br />
officials from both countries will be examining the further enhancement of the<br />
communications link to at least 2MBit.<br />
That capacity would support software research and development in<br />
broadband and multi-media technologies and real-time simulation associated<br />
with industrial design of new components. This agreement will help ensure<br />
that Australia and Japan remain at the forefront of information technology<br />
developments. We hope this bilateral connection will eventually become a building block for<br />
a more extensive high-speed data network linking other countries in the<br />
region. Eventual applications for the enhanced research collaboration which such<br />
links can support include advanced climate modelling ( including prediction of<br />
weather and global climate change) computational ocean science,<br />
superconductivity and linked testbeds for research into advanced multi-media<br />
applications such as simultaneous virtual reality modelling of 3-0 spaces.<br />
International communications links, such as this, are an integral element in<br />
the development of the Australian Government's national strategy on<br />
information and communications services and technology.<br />
The initiative builds on existing cooperation between Australia and Japan in<br />
high performance computing and communications.<br />
TOKYO 27 May 1995 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
