<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2564</transcript-id>
    <title>VISIT TO SOUTH-EAST ASIA</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/04/1972</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002564.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EL3.. ARGO -OfZ--F LdtLE" E BEFORE. 11 Pm 1 9/ 4/ 1 972<br />
PRIME MINISTER'\ 89~~<br />
FOR PRESS PM. No. 37/ 1972<br />
VISIT TO SOUTH-EAST ASIA<br />
It was announced today that the Prime Minister,<br />
the Rt. Hon. William cMahon, CHi, MP, would make official visits<br />
to a number of South-East Asian countries in June.<br />
? r McMahon will visit Indonesia from 5 to 8 June,<br />
Singapore from 9 tZo 11 June and Malaysia from 11 to 14 June.<br />
The visits reflect the Australian Government's<br />
long-standing interest in the region and the importance of its<br />
friendship with the governments concerned.<br />
The Prime Minister's visits take place at a time<br />
of rapid and far-reaching changes in the international scene which<br />
affect the whole South-East Asian area. The Prime Minister will<br />
take advantage of his visits to discuss with the leaders of the<br />
friendly countries of Indonesia, Singapore and Malaysia a wide<br />
range of international issues which have a bearing on the region.<br />
Australia shares with her three neighbours similar<br />
views on the independence, progress and stability of the region<br />
and on the importance of regional co-operation and national<br />
resilience. The Prime Minister's visits therefore come at a<br />
particularly appropriate time.<br />
Australia's association with Indonesia dates back<br />
to the first days of Indonesia's independence. Particularly close<br />
relations have been developed in recent years, extending over<br />
many fields of co-operative endeavour.<br />
The strength and cordiality of these relations was<br />
demonstrated during the successful visit recently made by President<br />
and Madame Soeharto to Australia. At that time President<br />
Soeharto issued an invitation to the Prime Minister to visit<br />
Indonesia and it is in response to this invitation that the Prime<br />
Minister's visit will be taking place. / 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
It is expected that many of the initiatives for<br />
deepening Indonesian/ Australian relations which were discussed<br />
during President Soeharto's visit will be taken forward by the<br />
Prime Minister while he is in Djakarta. The Prime Minister<br />
lookcs forward to renewing his close personal relationship with<br />
President Soeharto.<br />
The Prime Minister welcomes the opportunity to visit<br />
Singapore, a friendly Commonwealth partner with whom Australia<br />
shares many interests bilateral, regional and international.<br />
He last visited Singapore in 1971, and it will be a great<br />
rleasure to him to renew the friendshins then established. He<br />
looks forward to fruitful discussions on a wide range of questions<br />
of mutual concern to Autralia and Singapore.<br />
Australian relations with Malaysia, anothar Commonwealth<br />
partner, have been characterised since their inception by frequent<br />
consultations at the highest level. The Prime Minister sees his<br />
visit as part of this continuing process. He believes that<br />
such consultations will contribute to further improvement in<br />
the already close ties which exist between Australia and Malaysia<br />
in so many fields.<br />
When details of the programme in the respective<br />
countries have been determined they will be announced.<br />
CANBERRA, 19 April, 1972 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
