<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2926</transcript-id>
    <title>THE PRIME MINISTER&#039;S PRESS CONFERENCE AT PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA, TUESDAY 15 MAY 1973</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/05/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002926.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
THE PRIME MINISTER'S PRESS CONFERENCE<br />
AT PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA<br />
TUESDAY, 15 MAY 1973<br />
PRIME MINISTER: ( Answer to a commnent). There is no<br />
Government which has made so many announcements in the<br />
Parliament. Not only what it was doing in the Parliament but<br />
what it was doing in collaboration with the States or with<br />
other countries. As you know we table promptly the minutes<br />
of all Commonwealth/ State conferences and so on. The last such<br />
one was with the Premiers last Thursday, and I thought I would<br />
bring together what's happened since then.<br />
The following day the Secretary to the Australian Treasury<br />
met with the Under-Treasurers from each of the States and they<br />
recommended as follows: there should be a main committee of<br />
Commonwealth/ State Treasury officials at Secretary/ Under-Secretary<br />
level. Secondly there should be four Commonwealth/ State working<br />
groups. one on prices justification which the Australian Treasury<br />
would convene, another on restrictive trade practices which the<br />
Australian Attorney-General's Department would convene, a third<br />
on land prices which the Departments of Urban and Regional<br />
Development and Housing would convene, and the fourth on building<br />
costs which the same Departments would convene. Then there's a<br />
fifth working group on consumer protection under the control<br />
of the Minister for Science, Mr Morrison, as you heard the<br />
Premiers and me agree on Thursday afternoon. The working groups<br />
are to be convened as soon as possible this week. The main<br />
committee is to meet in Melbourne on Saturday 26 May.<br />
Because the Cabinet met yesterday you've already been given<br />
information of the decisions that were made then.<br />
Are there any questions?<br />
Q: Sir, on this question of Cabinet decisions, you explained<br />
to the House this morning that you found it difficult to follow<br />
the line that you'd put while in Opposition about Cabinet<br />
decisions Government decisions being made to the House before<br />
they were made public. I was wondering, in view of what's<br />
happened over the last few days, could you explain to us why,<br />
if the Cabinet sits on Sunday you are unable to announce to the<br />
House any decisions that Cabinet has made before you hold this<br />
Press Conference? If the Cabinet sits on Tuesday morning and<br />
the House sits at 2 o'clock on Tuesday you are unable to announce<br />
to the House any Cabinet decisions before you hold this Press<br />
Conference on Friday. Would it not be easier for both the Houses<br />
of Parliament and certainly for us if the basis of these decisions<br />
were announced perhaps after Question Time two hours before you<br />
hold this Press Conference?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: PTRIhMeErMIeN'IsT ERb: e en one Cabinet meeting on Sunday. </p>
<p>The decisions were given to the Press that afternoon.<br />
There's been some on Monday, the latest yesterday, and the<br />
decisions were given to the Press that afternoon. I suppose<br />
it would be possible to announce the decisions of Cabinet on<br />
a Tuesday morning after Question Time on Tuesday afternoon.<br />
This would have to be done in the form of ministerial<br />
statements I suppose. But nevertheless there is no regular<br />
procedure for that to be done. I suppose one could always<br />
promote a question on the subject and give the information<br />
that way. But I thought there'd been no demur by any of the<br />
Press or any of the public to our announcing Cabinet decisions<br />
on the day they were made. Also announcing Caucus decisions<br />
on the day they are made. That was always what we did in<br />
Opposition. I would expect that you would expect and that<br />
everyone in Australia would expect we would do the same now<br />
that we are in Government.<br />
Q: Prime Minister, following a statement made by Mr Snedden<br />
today, that he is quite happy to have a double dissolution<br />
over the issue of amendments to the Arbitration Act, and similar<br />
statements made by the D. L. P. and the Country Party can you say<br />
today whether you're quite happy to have a double dissolution<br />
on those amendments and if such an event will occur?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I don't know what the Senate's conduct will<br />
be in regard to any of the Government's Bills. I doubt if<br />
many of the Senators have made up their minds yet either.<br />
The fact is that there will have to be an election for half<br />
the Senate at some time between the first Saturday next July<br />
and the last Saturday in June next year. The whole question<br />
is whether, if the Senate makes the Government's business<br />
unworkable, there should be an election for the whole of the<br />
Senate and for the House of Representatives some time in that<br />
period. It would be many months before there can be such an<br />
election for the two Houses. As you know, there has to be<br />
the rejection by the Senate of a Bill from the House of<br />
Representatives or the undue delay of the Bill or the unacceptable<br />
amendment of the Bill. Then, after a lapse of three months,<br />
the same fate must befall the same Bill again. Quite obviously<br />
this would take some months. If the Senate takes the same<br />
attitude towards two of the Bills which have gone through the<br />
House of Representatives the Electoral Bill and the Arbitration<br />
Bill then that would be the first rejection of Bills of<br />
substance, and then those Bills, if they're put up again in<br />
three months time and rejected again, there would be the basis<br />
for a double dissolution, then, as you know if, after an<br />
election, there is a majority for the Government in the House<br />
of Representatives but not for the Senate there can be a joint<br />
sitting of the two Houses and they debate and decide the Bills<br />
which were the cause of the double dissolution. Now there are<br />
other Bills, of course, of substance such as the Sea and<br />
Submerged Lands Bill or the Pipeline Authority Bill or the<br />
Prices Justification Bill. I don't know what the attitude of<br />
the Opposition Parties will be to such Bills as that.<br />
Q: Prime Minister, do you consider that the Government Party<br />
acted correctly in the Senate last Thursday in calling off for<br />
pairs in the Thursday evening debate? </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER: This matter has been raised at Question Time<br />
in both Houses. I will say nothing about it now.<br />
Q: Why not?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Because one of the protagonists is out of<br />
the country.<br />
Q: Prime Minister, you've received a reply from the Government<br />
of Yugoslavia. Would you say if you are satisfied with that<br />
reply and if not why not?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I can say this: the Yugoslavian Ambassador<br />
handed over a note last Saturday in reply to the Australian<br />
note which was passed to the Yugoslavian Government on the 14th<br />
of last month. The Yugoslavian note doesn't provide all the<br />
information we were seeking. It reiterated however a willingness<br />
to provide details of the trials of the three Australians<br />
executed following their participation in an illegal incursion<br />
into Bosnia as well as further information about this incursion.<br />
Our Ambassador in Belgrade is pursuing this matter with the<br />
Yugoslavian authorities. He is also discussing the cases of<br />
other Australians about whom we have had representations or<br />
reports that they have been detained. Although the Yugoslavian<br />
Government insists that under the terms of The Hague Convention<br />
it is not obliged to give Australian Government access to dual<br />
nationals arrested and detained in Yugoslavia. The Australian<br />
Government believed that we had a right to this access on<br />
humanitarian grounds. I think I mentioned to you a week ago<br />
that I am referring to the Joint Select Committee on Foreign<br />
Affairs and Defence this question of dual nationality which<br />
affects scores of thousands of migrants, not only from<br />
Yugoslavia, but from many other countries, I suppose most of the<br />
countries which have the Roman Law the Napoleonic Code.<br />
Q: Sir, could you tell us whether you oppose or favour the<br />
construction of the proposed tower on Black Mountain and whether<br />
the Government is likely to make a decision on it soon?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I think the Government will decide this next<br />
week, at last, I think.<br />
Q: Sir, the Treasury said in its paper on the economy last<br />
July that demand pressures of any sort must be removed before<br />
anti-inflationary measures can be successful. The Treasury<br />
now says there's a state of clearly excessive demand in the<br />
housing sector. Do you expect that the Commonwealth/ State<br />
talks can achieve much in reducing housing costs while the<br />
Federal Government allows a state of excessive demand to exist?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: The Australian Government has no legislation<br />
no statutory authority at this stage to quell the excessive<br />
flow of funds into the housing sector. I think in the last year<br />
the amount of money made available to purchase or build houses<br />
has been 80 per cent greater than the amount available in the<br />
previous year. I don't doubt that the Australian Parliament<br />
can pass laws concerning financial corporations other than banks.<br />
It hasn't done so up till now. The great increase in funds<br />
has not come from banks over which the Australian Government<br />
already has statutory authority. The State Governments could </p>
<p>introduce in their Parliaments legislation to regulate the<br />
flow of funds from financial institutions other than banks.<br />
The Australian Parliament has already covered the banking<br />
field. Until it covers other fields, the States could certainly<br />
cover them. The answer is I think that any of the Parliaments<br />
in Australia could pass laws regulating the flow of funds<br />
into housing which has been responsible for the excessive<br />
pressure in housing in the last three or so quarters.<br />
Q: Prime Minister, you mentioned that the Yugoslav Government<br />
hadn't given you all the information that you'd asked for in<br />
your note. I wonder if you could tell us what information they<br />
failed to supply?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I listed before Easter twelve names about<br />
whom we were seeking information. On the same day it transpired that<br />
one of them had been found and a couple of days later that<br />
another one had been found. We have no further information<br />
about the other ten, and that's the information which is being<br />
sought. There is a question on notice in the House of<br />
Representatives in fact about one of the three who were executed<br />
and about whom information was given by the Yugoslavian Government<br />
newsagency in the middle of last month, but we have no further<br />
information about that man yet.<br />
Q: Prime Minister, Dr Cairns had talks today in Peking with<br />
the so-called Prime Minister Prince Sihanouk's Government in<br />
exile. Can you say if those were official talks and if they<br />
had your blessing, and what was the nature of them and can you<br />
say what is the official status of Prince Sihanouk with the<br />
Australian Government?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Prince Sihanouk has no official status with<br />
the Australian Government. He does usually reside in Peking<br />
and it is quite often that visitors to Peking encounter His<br />
Royal Highness.<br />
Q: Prime Minister, Mr Hawke has announced today that the<br />
A. C. T. U. Executive has decided to go ahead with its total ban<br />
on French shipping, communications and manufactured goods from<br />
midnight tomorrow. He has announced the ban will stay in force<br />
until the French testing program is abandoned. He has also<br />
announced that the A. C. T. U. Executive will call on the Federal<br />
Government for maximum diplomatic and economic sanctions.<br />
Can you tell us firstly do you think this ban will achieve<br />
anything or will it hamper our Court case and secondly what is<br />
your attitude from a call from the A. C. T. U. for maximum<br />
diplomatic and economic sanctions?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: The maximum diplomatic action has been in<br />
train for some months. If a ban on communications extends to<br />
mail and postal and telegraphic services it will harm Australia's<br />
case before the International Court of Justice. You've just<br />
mentioned the word ' communications' I trust that postal and<br />
telegraphic communications are not covered by any such ban.<br />
Perhaps I should read you the telegram that I sent to all<br />
members of the A. C. T. U. Executive yesterday. It explains the<br />
overall position: </p>
<p>" Australia has claimed in the proceedings which have<br />
been brought against France in the International Court of<br />
Justice that the conducting by France of atmospheric nuclear<br />
tests in the Pacific is contrary to international law.<br />
Especially as a country that has invoked international law<br />
against France, Australia must at all times in her relations<br />
with France act in accordance with international law.<br />
" This does not mean that there is no scope at all<br />
for union action against French nuclear tests. But when both<br />
Australia and France are parties to particular international agreements<br />
we must avoid placing France in a position to bring<br />
proceedings before an international tribunal against Australia<br />
alleging breach of an obligation that Australia has accepted<br />
in relation to France. We must also avoid the possibility<br />
that France, in the current proceedings in the could<br />
allege that we are acting in contravention of international<br />
law in other respects and are therefore not appearing before<br />
the Court with clean hands.<br />
" I am especially concerned about the following<br />
conventions: 1. Vienna Convention on Diplomatic Relations<br />
2. Vienna Convention on Consular Relations<br />
3. Universal Postal Convention 1964.<br />
" Both Australia and France are parties to and are<br />
bound by these conventions.<br />
" We must under the Vienna Conventions avoid doing<br />
anything which would prevent or hinder the proper normal<br />
functioning of the French Embassy or the French Consulates in<br />
the States. This would include the protection of personnel and<br />
property as well as the facilitation of official communications.<br />
" The Universal Postal Convention imposes on Australia<br />
an obligation to forward mails passed to it by the French<br />
postal authorities. " As I have said, these are the international conventions<br />
that concern us most. I urge you most strongly to assist in<br />
ensuring that no action is taken which would involve Australia<br />
being in breach of her obligations under international law.<br />
( Signed) E. G. WHITLAM<br />
Q: Sir, has the Vatican refused to accept the nominated<br />
Australian Ambassador and what reason does the Vatican give<br />
and what will you do now as Prime Minister about this?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: You would not expect me to make any comments<br />
on such matters even if they're true.<br />
Q: Prime Minister, has Cabinet considered the Wheat<br />
Stabilisation Bill and if it has are you in favour ( inaudible)? </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER: Yes, we've considered it and we have a<br />
recommendation on this matter for the Party tomorrow.<br />
Q: Sir, do you believe that the Labor Premiers of<br />
Western Australia, South Australia and Tasmania are in breach<br />
of either Labor policy or the spirit of Labor policy in joining<br />
their Liberal colleagues in appealing to the Privy Council<br />
against your new Territorial and Sea Bill Seas and Submerged<br />
Lands Bill?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes. Both.<br />
Q: You believe they are in breach of both?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes.<br />
Q: Do you intend to raise this in the Councils of the A. L. P.<br />
such as the Federal Conference?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No.<br />
Q: Have you pointed it out to them, Sir?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: They know it. They were at the Launceston<br />
Conference which resolved that the Commonwealth should legislate<br />
for regulation and exploitation of the Continental Shelf and<br />
offshore resources. An amendment was moved that the Commonwealth<br />
and the States should legislate. . The words and the States the<br />
amendment to that effect was defeated so there's no question what<br />
the Party has said about this matter. As you know the Seas and<br />
Submerged Lands Bill and the Seas and Submerged Lands Royalty<br />
on Minerals Bill which Mr Connor introduced last week incorporate<br />
the Territorial Sea and Continental Shelf Bill which Mr Swartz<br />
introduced on behalf of Mr McMahon when he was Foreign Minister<br />
under Mr Gorton in April 1970 and the companion Minerals Bill<br />
which was promised at the same time. You'll also remember<br />
that in the speech the Governor-General made opening the last<br />
Parliament reference was made to both these Bills. The<br />
Governor-General in opening this Parliament repeated the same<br />
words so this is legislation which has been before the Parliament,<br />
which has been supported by the Liberal/ Country Party Government<br />
over three years ago and now by my Government. It is a subject<br />
matter which was considered less than two years ago by the<br />
Federal Conference of the Australian Labor Party. There is no<br />
question as to the attitude of the Labor Party on this matter.<br />
Whatever the attitude of the Labor Premiers may be the fact is<br />
that the Country Party Premier of Queensland and the Liberal<br />
Premier of New South Wales would challenge the legislation anyhow.<br />
Q: Sir, following from that, what is your reaction to the<br />
Premiers' decision to try to stop your moves to abolish the<br />
States' appeals to the Privy Council and your reaction to the<br />
Queensland Premier's so-called secession statement, as the time<br />
could be fast approaching when the links between the<br />
Commonwealth and the States would have to be reviewed? </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER: I always knew there were terrific<br />
similiarities between Mr Bjelke-Petersen and Mr Ian Smith.<br />
I think Mr Smith would represent about one-twentieth of the<br />
population of his State. Mr Bjelke-Petersen at least represents<br />
one-fifth of the population of his. This idea of secession,<br />
I must confess, staggered me. I hadn't heard of the idea since<br />
the early 1930' s. It was suggested in Western Australia in the<br />
1930' s the early 1930' s and Mr Bjelke-Petersen with his<br />
fine sense of history is reviving the idea. I've no doubt what<br />
the people of Queensland would say if they had a referendum on<br />
the question because in a referendum every vote would be of<br />
equal value and I've no doubt that the great majority of the<br />
people of Queensland want to remain part of Australia.<br />
You asked me about the Privy Council: the whole situation<br />
is of course that Australia is one of the very, very few<br />
countries in the world which allows legal disputes between its<br />
citizens to be determined in the courts of another country.<br />
The Privy Council sits in England. It's composed of judges<br />
who are appointed by the British Government. Its judgments take<br />
the form of advice to the Queen of England not the Queen of<br />
Australia. The Australian States are still British colonies in<br />
this respect. Appeals can go from their Supreme Courts either<br />
directly or via the High Court to the Privy Council and this<br />
means that you can have three forms of appeal. You can appeal<br />
from a single judge of the Supreme Court judge and jury<br />
to the Full Court or the Court of Appeal of the State. You can<br />
then appeal to the High Court. You can then appeal to the<br />
Privy Council. This is the most ample, dilatory, extravagant<br />
form of appeal in the world. The Australian Labor Party has<br />
said for decades that appeals to the Privy Council should be<br />
abolished. Now what we are doing is under the Statute of<br />
Westminster passing a Bill in this Parliament requesting and<br />
consenting to a Bill in the British Parliament abolishing<br />
those appeals. It's the British Parliament which provides<br />
this method of appeal and the Australian Parliament is being<br />
asked to request and consent to the British Parliament giving<br />
up this form of appeal. This is something which the Australian<br />
National Government is entitled to bring up in the Australian<br />
National Parliament and to forward to the British Government<br />
so that it can bring in companion legislation in the British<br />
Parliament.<br />
Q: Sir, what action do you propose to take if the unions do<br />
go ahead with the ban on French mail?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I won't assume that the relevant unions will<br />
harm our country's interest.<br />
Q: Prime Minister, regarding this Commonwealth/ State<br />
Committee all the Liberal Premiers accepted the idea of<br />
the Committee on the basis that one of the facets of the<br />
economy we have would be wages and income, and I notice that<br />
the five sub-committees don't mention either wages or income.<br />
Are we to take that the main Committee will be looking at this? </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER: The four Sub-committees and the Consumer<br />
Protection Committee that's the five Committees all told<br />
are, you'll notice, dealing with the five matters where I<br />
suggested State action could be taken. These were the<br />
suggestions I made. They were accepted by the Premiers on<br />
Thursday and the following day the Australian Treasury and<br />
State Under-Secretaries all agreed to set up committees on<br />
those subjects, so that's why there's no specific reference<br />
to prices or incomes. As I said at the Conference, we are<br />
anxious to do what is possible and to do it promptly and all<br />
these matters are things which it is possible for the Governments<br />
of Australia with their different political complexions to agree<br />
to undertake and I'm very pleased that they acted as promptly as<br />
they could on it. The biggest increase in prices is in the price<br />
of land and this is something akn~ at which the Australian<br />
Parliament can do nothing except in-the Federal territories.<br />
It is something about which all the States can act without<br />
any limitation whatever. Section 92 doesn't impede State<br />
legislation in this respect because you can't take a block of<br />
land across a State border. Now all the States can do something<br />
about the price of land. The Commonwealth can do nothing.<br />
We are in fact inviting the States to co-operate with us in<br />
acquiring tracts of rural land which are due for conversion<br />
to residential land to acquire them and to develop them.<br />
We've already got the agreement of the New South Wales and<br />
Victorian Governments to do this in the designated area around<br />
Albury-Wodonga. Western Australia agreed to do this last Friday.<br />
Mr Tonkin and Mr Uren announced it then. The other States have<br />
not yet agreed to do it but that is the most that the Australian<br />
Government can do. It can help. It can provide the finance<br />
for the State Governments to acquire land on just terms and to<br />
develop it at cost but there is no way of land price fixation<br />
or freezing which is available to the Australian Government<br />
within the borders of the States. That's the serious thing<br />
that has to be done and it's the thing which now is being<br />
tackled I trust. But prices have gone up for land by a greater<br />
percentage than wages or interest rates or services have gone up.<br />
Q: . Mr Whitlam, will the Premiers get their way and will<br />
wages and prices be considered by the major Committee?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: They may be. But as you know there's very<br />
little chance of getting price control introduced by the<br />
New South Wales Government or getting it through the Victorian<br />
Legislative Council. Income freezes similarly can't be brought<br />
about because as regards wages and salaries as determined by<br />
arbitration or by a Wages Board, if the States try to do that<br />
then they produce a flight to the Federal jurisdiction, and<br />
the Commonwealth Conciliation and Arbitration Commission can<br />
make awards in those matters over which the Australian<br />
Parliament can exercise no jurisdiction and of course the<br />
State Parliaments can't either. So it's being quite unrealistic<br />
to suggest that you can get a freeze on wages and salaries<br />
although there is a form of justification through arbitration<br />
There. It would be very difficult also to persuade the State<br />
Parliaments Federal Parliament couldn't do it to freeze<br />
charges for services or incomes from investments and in the<br />
material areas the principal areas of Sydney and Melbourne<br />
the big manufacturing centres there is no chance of getting<br />
prices legislation through the State Parliaments. </p>
<p>Q: Mr Whitlam, are you prepared to hold a referendum to get<br />
the price control power through the Commonwealth?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: See how we go with these things first.<br />
You wouldn't hold a referendum by itself. You might hold it in<br />
connection with a Senate election or a double dissolution,<br />
but price control in that sense, even if one got the power in<br />
this Parliament, would take a long time to set up the machinery.<br />
Q: Sir, your northern friend, Mr Bjelke-Petersen, this<br />
afternoon at his own press conference declared that you were<br />
about to withdraw all Australian postage stamps with the Queen's<br />
head PRIME MINISTER: I didn't have the advantage of hearing<br />
Mr Bjelke-Petersen's press conference. I don't really see why<br />
you should publicise his press conference at mine. There is<br />
no proposal to take the Queen's photo off any of the Australian<br />
postage stamps. I notice that our republican predecessors<br />
put a great number of past Prime Ministers and artists and<br />
explorers on the postage stamps. Next century mine may be in<br />
some commemorative issue but no Labor Government has taken<br />
Her Majesty's photographs off the stamps.<br />
Q: Sir, you've spoken today about main with France. You've<br />
made a more or less kind reference to Mr Smith. I had a cable<br />
today from Johannesburg saying that there have been a lot of<br />
complaints in Salisbury that mail from Australia has been<br />
tampered and interfered with. As you know there is an<br />
injunction at present before the High Court, but pending that,<br />
can you say that you would frown upon any interference, no<br />
matter which way that decision goes, with private mail between<br />
two countries whether we recognise them or not?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: The position of Rhodesia is covered by<br />
Security Council resolutions. I can't remember what they say<br />
about mail, but communications of other sorts such as airlines<br />
are certainly covered by Security Council resolutions. The<br />
present Australian Government will loyally support those<br />
resolutions. There are no Security Council or General Assembly<br />
or related bodies which have passed resolutions limiting mail or<br />
telegraphic services with France. There can be no question<br />
of the Australian Government's obligations to protect French<br />
missions and to provide postal facilities for France.<br />
The other matter that you mention about the proceedings in the<br />
High Court that concerns the extent to which the Australian<br />
Post Office must provide services for the so-called Rhodesia<br />
Information Office at Crows Nest near Sydney. You'll understand<br />
I can't comment on that because it's before the Court.<br />
Q: Private mail wouldn't be in that category surely between<br />
Rhodesia and France?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I didn't know that mail was not being<br />
delivered from or to Rhodesia, but I don't know what our<br />
obligations are under this. There can be no question of our<br />
obligations in regard to France. Our obligations in regard<br />
to Rhodesia are set out in the Security Council resolutions.<br />
I forget the details on that point.<br />
Q: Sir, on the question of appeals to the Privy Council </p>
<p>one of the main complaints of the States is that you didn't<br />
consult them first. Can you say why you didn't do so?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: The proper means of communication with<br />
Britain is through the Australian Government. It's a method<br />
which the Statute of Westminster envisages. Now if one were<br />
to ask the States one would get different answers and surely<br />
we aren't to contemplate the absurd situation where there can<br />
be appeals to the Privy Council from the Supreme Courts of some<br />
States and not from the Supreme Courts of other States. It is<br />
a humiliating and archaic process. It is insulting to our Judges<br />
that we still allow the States to be regarded as British colonies<br />
in respect of their Courts. The State Supreme Courts are well<br />
able to cope with all matters at that level of appeal and the<br />
High Court of Australia is as distinguished a Court as there is<br />
in the English-speaking world.<br />
Q: Prime Minister, my question is about a number of points<br />
you made about inflation here today. Fortunately you had the<br />
Conference open last Thursday and I'm left with the impression<br />
especially after speaking to your officials that wages and<br />
incomes would be studied by the Committees. Do you think<br />
Mr Hamer might have left with the same impression or do you<br />
think that your eloquence persuaded him that it is unrealistic<br />
to pursue this?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes.<br />
Q: Secondly, on the question of housing, Sir, you said that<br />
the Australian Government has no legislative authority to<br />
quell excessive flow of funds into the housing sector beyond<br />
the banking powers...?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I did say legislative and then I saind<br />
statutory. I meant there is no Act of this Parliament dealing<br />
with that at this stage but I think I also said I trust there<br />
was the power to pass such acts but we haven't done them<br />
hitherto. Q: The works and housing program, Sir the housing agreement<br />
is due for negotiation and this is one of the areas where you<br />
intend to lift public spending. Am I right?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Not necessarily. The inflationary aspects<br />
in housing the pressure on goods and services in housing has<br />
come from the increased funds being made available not under<br />
the Housing Agreement but principally by the Permanent<br />
Building Societies or by some of the Terminating Building<br />
Societies or to a certain extent by the Savings Banks themselves,<br />
but the public funds for building under the Housing Agreement<br />
Housing Commissions and the War Service Homes have not been<br />
responsible for any increased demand on housing. I would guess<br />
that the number of houses being built by Housing Commissions<br />
in the last twelve months is considerably fewer than the number<br />
built in the preceeding twelve months. Now our whole effort<br />
in regard to public housing Housing Commission houses will<br />
be to see that they are made available principally to those who<br />
need them most, and I forget the exact figures there is a<br />
very rapidly increasing waiting list for Housing Commission </p>
<p>houses in Sydney and Melbourne in particular and, unless<br />
money is made available under much more direct conditions<br />
for those who need the housing most then there is no prospect<br />
of these families getting housing for a long time and there<br />
are tests in some of the States they vary in intensity between<br />
the States but there are tests in some of the States on<br />
economic and accommodation grounds. We want to see that those<br />
who need the accommodation most are first served.<br />
Q: I just wanted to clear that point, Sir, because housing<br />
demands... ( inaudible) between public and private.<br />
It's just an aggregate figure. What you're saying is that<br />
this Government has no intention of doing what the previous<br />
Government did when excessive housing occurred. They would<br />
cut back on their own housing program...?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No.<br />
Q: Do you intend to keep that...?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: It is most unlikely that we would reduce<br />
the number of Housing Commission houses or War Service Homes.<br />
Q: and the particular influence you see where pressure<br />
could be brought to bear is the Permanent and Terminating<br />
Building Society people?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes. That is where the distortion has occurred<br />
in the last twelve months or a little less than that. I certainly<br />
don't subscribe to the idea that if more money is coming from<br />
private financial institutions for housing that you then cut<br />
back on Housing Commission houses. That just puts the people<br />
that can get housing from no other source further back.<br />
That is not responsibility of Government. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
