<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11362</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                 THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                 COMMUNITY AND CIVIC RECEPTION SPEECH                 HANNAN&amp;#146;S NORTH KALGOORLIE HISTORIC TOURIST MINE                 KALGOORLIE, WESTERN AUSTRALIA                                             SUBJECTS: Gold mining industry,                 Kalgoorlie community, East Timor meeting spirit of volunteerism, Native                 Title, Barry Haase</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/04/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE.......................................................................................</p>
<p>Can I say to you, Mayor, to Barry Haase to Ron Manners to other distinguished</p>
<p> guests, ladies and gentlemen. It is a great delight to be in Kalgoorlie</p>
<p> for the first time as Prime Minister. Kalgoorlie has a special place</p>
<p> in, not only in Western Australian history, but a special place in</p>
<p> Australian history. It's a very distinctive part of our country.</p>
<p> It boasts a number of things. Kalgoorlie of course is the largest</p>
<p> electorate in the world I think and I often entertain my European</p>
<p> visitors in particular when we start comparing political notes and</p>
<p> I point out that we have an electorate in Australia that is larger</p>
<p> than about two-thirds of the European Union put together.</p>
<p>This of course is the second time that I visited the electorate of</p>
<p> Kalgoorlie in the space of a month because I went to Exmouth only</p>
<p> a short while ago with Barry to see for myself first hand and with</p>
<p> the Premier of Western Australia, Richard Court, to announce some</p>
<p> special assistance to the people of Exmouth who suffered so severely</p>
<p> as a result of the cyclone.</p>
<p>It is not the first time that I've been to this city but it is</p>
<p> certainly the first time as Prime Minister and I want to thank Barry</p>
<p> very warmly for the invitation. It's an opportunity for me to</p>
<p> do what I like to do when Parliament is not sitting and that is as</p>
<p> frequently as possible get away from the larger urban concentrations</p>
<p> of Australia which are, of course, an important part of our national</p>
<p> community, to get around the country to understand first hand through</p>
<p> discussion and listening to people how different life is, how important</p>
<p> life is to the national good in the regional areas of Australia. And</p>
<p> to say to you that I do understand as Prime Minister that there are</p>
<p> special challenges and special difficulties. That I do appreciate</p>
<p> the contribution that the mining industry in particular makes to the</p>
<p> wealth of Australia and to the living standard of Australia.</p>
<p>Only a month or so ago, I opened the Olympic Dam Site in South Australia</p>
<p> which is part of the great Roxby Downs Project. And that project is</p>
<p> making a huge contribution potentially to Australia's export</p>
<p> income. The gold mining industry is the second biggest export earner</p>
<p> amongst the mining industries of Australia and Kalgoorlie is the greatest</p>
<p> gold mining producing area in Australia. And it is a city which is</p>
<p> rich in the history of this country, it is rich in the history of</p>
<p> Western Australia and played, as you all know, a major and decisive</p>
<p> role and part in the decision of Western Australia to join the Federation</p>
<p> in the name of Paddy Hannon is synonymous with the development of</p>
<p> the mining industry and of gold mining in Australia. It incidentally</p>
<p> as I remarked to one of my staff coming here this morning, I think</p>
<p> it's the only federal electorate in Australia whose Member was</p>
<p> once expelled from Federal Parliament for entirely, I think in historical</p>
<p> perspective, inappropriate reasons, for something that would certainly</p>
<p> not happen today.</p>
<p>But most importantly this community is an example of how people work</p>
<p> together and cooperate together in the regional areas of Australia.</p>
<p> And as I moved around here this morning I met people from the local</p>
<p> home nursing organisations, I met the Anglican Priest, I met the Pastors</p>
<p> of other Churches, I've met people involved in Centrelink, I've</p>
<p> met people involved in the Lyons clubs, people involved in all the</p>
<p> different organisations that make a community work. Australians are</p>
<p> very good at working together. And as we approach, in two years time,</p>
<p> the Centenary of the Federation of Australia, we are becoming a lot</p>
<p> more conscious as a nation of what we all have in common and how much</p>
<p> we have achieved over the last one hundred years. And I am particularly</p>
<p> pleased to acknowledge the presence of people from the Indigenous</p>
<p> community of Kalgoorlie and the recognition that all of us as Australians</p>
<p> working together have a common interest and a common investment in</p>
<p> a harmonious and cooperative and caring future together as Australians</p>
<p> as we go into the next century.</p>
<p>Australia has achieved an enormous amount. And it is a huge country,</p>
<p> it varies enormously and I never tire of the opportunity of moving</p>
<p> around our country and meeting people in different circumstances.</p>
<p> And the richest thing about being an Australian is the immense diversity</p>
<p> of this country yet the common humanity of the people of this country.</p>
<p> Although we live in different circumstances, and this community is</p>
<p> a long way away from the settled suburbs of Sydney and Melbourne and</p>
<p> very different from the tropical areas of Far North Queensland and</p>
<p> very different again from some of the mountain areas of the Snowy</p>
<p> Mountains of New South Wales and yet the sense of community and the</p>
<p> sense of cooperation and the national spirit is as deep and strong</p>
<p> in all of those areas as it is in the next. And, although we live</p>
<p> in different areas and we face different challenges, we have so many</p>
<p> things in common particularly the common values we all have as Australians.</p>
<p>I'm very conscious, as Prime Minister of our country, of the</p>
<p> role not only of Australia in a domestic sense but also the role of</p>
<p> Australia in the world community. And like any other nation we have</p>
<p> opportunities and responsibilities. I'm very proud of the fact</p>
<p> that Australia's economic strengths at the present time has enabled</p>
<p> it to stare down the worst of the Asian economic downturn. But in</p>
<p> saying that I'm conscious that not everybody in Australia is</p>
<p> enjoying the benefits and the bounty that come out that come out of</p>
<p> that economic success. And it's the responsibility of the community</p>
<p> to remember at a time of relative national prosperity, that there</p>
<p> remain people within our community who continue to need our help.</p>
<p> But we shouldn't lose sight of what Australia has achieved. We</p>
<p> are performing better than most, we are seen in our region in particular</p>
<p> as being economically very strong and one of the advantages of that</p>
<p> is that we are listened to more carefully and more respectfully. We</p>
<p> speak from a greater position of strength because of our economic</p>
<p> achievements than would otherwise be the case.</p>
<p>I will, next week, meet the Indonesian President, Dr Habibie, to talk</p>
<p> about the concerns I have about what is happening in East Timor. I</p>
<p> will do so as the Leader of a country which has developed a friendly</p>
<p> relationship with Indonesia, not an uncritical friendship. No true</p>
<p> friendship is always uncritical. A true friendship in a personal level</p>
<p> as well as at a national level, is a friendship that is based upon</p>
<p> long and shared common experiences but is also a friendship that enables</p>
<p> you to speak with candour and openness when the circumstances require.</p>
<p> All Australians are concerned about what is happening in East Timor,</p>
<p> all want a just and peaceful solution. We must all remember, of course,</p>
<p> that it is part of Indonesia. And ultimately a proper resolution,</p>
<p> a positive resolution of what is occurring there can only happen through</p>
<p> the involvement, the consent and the support and the active participation</p>
<p> of the Indonesian Government and the armed forces of that country.</p>
<p> But our relationship with Indonesia is important to us. It's</p>
<p> a nation of more than 200 million people, it's our nearest neighbour</p>
<p> and it's within close flying distance, particularly of Western</p>
<p> Australia. But I will go to those talks as the Leader of a country</p>
<p> which has been a good friend but not an uncritical friend and a country</p>
<p> whilst understanding the political and cultural differences of our</p>
<p> neighbour is also a country that is concerned about human rights,</p>
<p> is concerned about justice and is concerned to ensure the fair treatment</p>
<p> and decent future for the people of East Timor.</p>
<p>But, ladies and gentlemen, it's always a special privilege for</p>
<p> a Prime Minister to come to regional Australia, to talk to people,</p>
<p> to listen to them, I hope in a small way to encourage them and, most</p>
<p> importantly, as Barry has done on behalf of the broader community</p>
<p> to express my thanks and my respect for all of those people who work</p>
<p> in such a tireless, unselfish and open hearted way to help those who</p>
<p> need assistance and to make our community work more effectively.</p>
<p>There are many things that make up the matrix of Australian values</p>
<p> and one of those things is our great spirit of volunteerism. And you</p>
<p> find volunteerism and a willingness to help each other, some even</p>
<p> call it mateship, in rural and regional Australia to an even more</p>
<p> pronounced and marked degree than you'd find in other parts of</p>
<p> Australia. And the willingness of everybody to dig in and help and</p>
<p> work together, particularly in adversity, is an instinctive Australian</p>
<p> characteristic. And we really do do it better than any other country</p>
<p> in the world, and it's one of those precious Australian assets</p>
<p> that we must always hang onto and we must always work very hard to</p>
<p> preserve.</p>
<p>Now, as you are aware, the Federal Government out of the Federation</p>
<p> Fund, which is a one billion dollar fund designed to support projects</p>
<p> that will in part honour one hundred years of the Australian nation</p>
<p> and also contribute valuably to the infrastructure of this country,</p>
<p> out of that we have contributed the sum of some five million dollars</p>
<p> for the marvellous enterprise for which Mr Manners is principally</p>
<p> responsible. And the Hall of Fame that will quite rightly and properly</p>
<p> honour the contribution of the mining industry of Australia to this</p>
<p> nation. The mining industry is an integral part of the Australian</p>
<p> economy. The contribution of the mining industry to the wealth of</p>
<p> this country is incalculable. And it will always be part of the policies</p>
<p> of my government and the policies of Coalition Governments generally</p>
<p> at a State and Federal level, to support and to help and to promote</p>
<p> and to defend the mining industry of this country. And that applies</p>
<p> in relation to a whole range of things, many of which have been under</p>
<p> debate recently and continue to be under debate, matters relating</p>
<p> to Native Title and a resolution of that issue is important to the</p>
<p> people of this district because while ever there is uncertainty surrounding</p>
<p> investment there will be less investment. As surely as night follows</p>
<p> day if you have uncertainty about an industry you will get less investment.</p>
<p> And the sooner that that is resolved the better it will be for the</p>
<p> people of Western Australia, for the people of this district and for</p>
<p> the people of the Australian community generally. And it's been</p>
<p> the desire of my Government, and I believe that last year we worked</p>
<p> out an honourable compromise which was fair to the mining industry,</p>
<p> fair to the farmers, fair to the Indigenous people and fair to the</p>
<p> generality of the Australian community. And the translation of that</p>
<p> outcome here in Western Australia is being held up at the moment.</p>
<p> And because it's being held up the mining industry is suffering</p>
<p> and the community is suffering. It ought to be fixed and it ought</p>
<p> to be fixed quickly. Because while it remains held up all of those</p>
<p> groups, the Indigenous groups, the mining industry and the farming</p>
<p> interests of this country which is so very important and the general</p>
<p> community are suffering.</p>
<p>But, ladies and gentlemen, can I say to Barry, who's been in</p>
<p> a short period of six months an extremely energetic representative</p>
<p> of this vast community and this vast and vast electorate of Kalgoorlie</p>
<p> and he is working very hard in Canberra for you. He's certainly</p>
<p> persistent and that's what you want and that's what a community</p>
<p> like this is entitled to have, you're entitled to have somebody</p>
<p> who will speak up for the particular problems and challenges of a</p>
<p> community such as this. I thank Barry very warmly for having me here</p>
<p> today, it's a delight to be amongst you, I wish you well and</p>
<p> to all of you thank you most warmly for the contribution that you</p>
<p> are making to this magnificent community.</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
