<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1903</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS:  P.M NO. 72/1968  CONTROL OF ILLEGAL FISHING</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/07/1968</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001903.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS: ~ iL1 6<br />
LrB RP No. 72/ 1968_<br />
CONTROL OF ILLEGAL F ISH ING,<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr. John Gorton, this evening replied to<br />
the telegram he had received from the Premier of Queensland, Mr. Pizzey,<br />
in regard to contravention of fisheries laws.<br />
Here is the text of the Prime Minister's telegram to Mr.<br />
Pizzey: " In reply to your telegram received this morning, the<br />
Commonwealth has had under examination ways in which illegal<br />
fishing operations might be controlled and Australia'o marine<br />
resources protected. Recently extra patrol boats have become<br />
available to the R. A. N. and these will alk~ w the coverage and<br />
frequency of sea patrols to be considerably increased within<br />
Australia's 12-mile exclusive fishing zone. The R. A. A. F.<br />
also will participate regularly in patrolling activities<br />
particularly Gver northern fishing grounds. It is anticipated<br />
that amendments to Commonwealth legislation will shortly be<br />
proposed in order to give the necessary legal powers to control<br />
the taking of all sedentary species, including clams, from the<br />
Continental Shelf, including the Reef. As to the incident reported<br />
in your telegram, this has been brought to the attention of the<br />
Chinese Embassy who have been made aware that further such<br />
acts w*., uld render the vessels concerned liable to arrest and<br />
legal prcceedings. The Embassy said that the Chinese Goveknrnent<br />
fully appreciated the need to avoid breaches of the Australian<br />
Fisheries Act. The Embassy would do everything possible to<br />
ensure that Chinese vessels respected the 12-mile limit and<br />
the Chinese Government was being informed immediately about<br />
the recent incidents. The help received from the Queensland<br />
authorities in repcrting the activities of foreign fishing vessels<br />
is much appreciated and it is hoped that the present valuable<br />
co-operation between Commonwealth and State in this field will<br />
crkacinue. I am writing to you separately on this matter.<br />
CANBERRA 23 July 1968 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
