<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3893</transcript-id>
    <title>INTERVIEW WITH THE PRIME MINISTER ON HSV7&#039;S &#039;THIS WEEK&#039; PROGRAM - REPLAY SUNDAY 21 SEPTEMBER 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/09/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003893.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
a EMBARGO: AS DELIVERED ON<br />
' THIS WEEK'<br />
21 SEPTEMBER 1975<br />
INTERVIEW WITH THE PRIME MINISTER ON HSV7' s<br />
" THIS WEEK" PROGRAM. RE-PLAY SUNDAY<br />
21 SEPTEMBER 1975<br />
QUESTION: A lot of speculation about whether there's going to<br />
be an election before the Labor Government ends its term in<br />
1977. If an election is held bef9re May next year, what would<br />
your reaction be to that? Would you welcome it?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I think there ought to be an election for the<br />
House of Representatives at the end of the proper term, that is~,<br />
in the middle of 1977. There must be an election for half the<br />
Senate befo3 e the middle of next year.<br />
QUESTION: Would you welcome an election if the opposition saw<br />
fit to refuse Supply? How do you think the Labor Government would<br />
go in that case?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: We2? l, obviously the polls show that we would be<br />
in great difficulty. But it has to be remembered that this would<br />
only come about,. an election for the House of Representatives, if<br />
the Opposition were again to do what it threatened to do in April<br />
last year, '-that ispto reject funds to carry on the business of<br />
of Government. If that was the issue I believe there would be<br />
an immense increase in support for the Labor Party as there was<br />
in May last year. Furthermore, if the Opposition objected to the<br />
Budget, refused to pass the Budgetjthe election would be on the<br />
propriet~ y . the merits of our-Budget. And accordingly, the<br />
Opposition would have to give up mere negative criticism. It<br />
would have to propose a Budget of its own. And I'm certain that<br />
in any contest between our Budget, which is there , and any<br />
Budget which they then produced, we would win.<br />
QUESTION: ' Prime Minister, you seem to be taking a softer lineif<br />
I may say so. You were quoted the other day as saying,<br />
" If Mr Fraser refused to pass, approves the Budget in the Senate,,<br />
then you would tough it out."<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I don't think I ever used the word'tough it out'.<br />
What I did say was this, -That there is no law on this subject,<br />
there is no rule on this subject, there is no precedent on this<br />
subject and since there had never been any discussions on the<br />
possibility of the Australian Senate rejecting a Budget from the<br />
House of Representatives there wasn't even a convention. A<br />
great number of people assume that if the Senate were to reject<br />
a Budget or to refuse Supply then the Prime Minister would have<br />
to advise the Governor General to dissolve the House of Represent-<br />
* atives. There is no such law, rule, precedent, or in fact,<br />
convention. QUESTION: And if Mr Fraser does decide to reject the Budget in </p>
<p>the Senate., then you would not advise the Governor-General, you<br />
would tough it out.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: That's one of the options. I'm not using the<br />
words'tough it out'. That's your words. But I want to point<br />
out that the holding of a House of Representatives election under<br />
the Constitution is decided by the Governor-General-in-Council,<br />
those are the words of the Constitution. That means the Governor<br />
General can only dissolve the House of Representatives if he is<br />
advised to do so'by his Government. The Government is composed<br />
of that party which has a majority in the House of Representatives<br />
My Party has that majority.<br />
QUESTION: It is the apparent indecision of Mr Fraser to make up<br />
his mind one way or the other, which is causing all the speculation<br />
at the moment and an editorial says, " that Mr Fraser should<br />
come out once and for all and say is he going to accept the<br />
Budget or not". Do you agree with that?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Oh yes. I think that is very clearly the case.<br />
I-to<br />
Mr Fraser hides behind the formula 1 Well I'm not promoting<br />
speculation on this; I've never said, as Bill Snedden was always<br />
saying, that, ' we will refuse Supply in the Senate-. But of course<br />
he is well aware that everybodyp including Mr Anthony his<br />
Opposition colleague, Mr Lynch his Deputy and a very great<br />
number of other people are saying things like that. They always<br />
say, " But, of coursd, this is finally a decision for Mr Fraser<br />
himself". Now if Mr Fraser wants to kill this speculation heq<br />
only has to say~~ no, there will be no rejection of the Budget.<br />
That is, he knows the speculation is going on, he refuses to<br />
do anything to kill it. He's apparently thinking that this must<br />
be to his advantage to appear to be driven to this course which<br />
he's always said up till now, when he's been cornered, would<br />
be an improper course.<br />
QUESTION: Do you think he's lost his opportunity for forcing<br />
an election?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well, I don't know whether I'd put it in exactly<br />
those terms. As I say., there is no certainty that there would<br />
be an election if the Senate were to reject the Budget. But<br />
I think Mr* Fraser must now be'oning to realise that he'll have<br />
to'put up or shut up'. If there is an election on the Budget<br />
then there has to be an alternative Budget. He has to say in<br />
any election what expenditures he would increase or reduce;<br />
what taxes he would increase or reduce. And he's never been<br />
specific. QUESTION: Do you think it's his inability to come up with agood<br />
alternative Budget that's holding him back?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I think that he's being very coy about it.<br />
He's enjoying the speculation ' and in a negative wqay he's encouraging<br />
the speculation. I think it may be that., cynically, he believes<br />
that all such speculation undermines confidence in the business<br />
community. And it impedes the processes the Budget. People"<br />
feel uncertain. / 3 </p>
<p>QUESTION: This might be hypothetical, it's looking a long<br />
way into the future, but say the Labor Government does survive<br />
till 1977?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes.<br />
QUESTION: Can you say now what you think your chances would<br />
be ' in 1977 of being returned?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Oh~ well,, obviously we think-and Mr Fraser, those<br />
around him and behind him, must also think. that with the passage<br />
of time our chances improve. This was a very good Budget, it is<br />
bound to bring about an improvement in Australia's economy.<br />
QUESTION: There's no doubt in your mind that you'd win in 1977?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Oh yes, that would be my expectation. Admittedly<br />
the polls show thatwef1do very badly at the moment. I believe<br />
that in an election campaign where people were voting for real,<br />
where they 4eren't just making criticisms of the Government<br />
and where they had to choose whether they wanted the present<br />
Government and the present Budget or an alternative hypothetical<br />
and, obviously in many cases, unpalatable Budget, they'd choose<br />
the one that there is there now.<br />
QUESTION: There is ~ a lot of popularity obviously to be gained<br />
from the business co'mmunity as a whole and a poll conducted by<br />
the Age newspaper in Melbourne a short time-ago, showed that<br />
something like 90% of the chief executives of a cross section<br />
of Australia's biggest companies believe that the Government<br />
must' change if business conditions are to improve. So obviously<br />
business confidence is still down despite all..( interjection)<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I think a poll conducted among business leaders<br />
at any time,.. this year, five years ago, five years to come... would<br />
tend to favour the Liberals. But you noticed that poll, although<br />
it wasn't in the Age heading, was that 60% of those people said<br />
that the Budget, Bill Hayden's Budget, was a responsible one.<br />
So when it comes to the.. ( interjection)<br />
QUESTION:. But they still predict a gloomy future., these same<br />
business people. What do you say to them about the future?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: That things will steadily, but not quickly,<br />
improve. So what I think we've got to realise is that every<br />
country, like Australia~ is having bad economic conditions<br />
every countryplike Australia, has far too high unemployment and<br />
far too high inflation.<br />
QUESTION: Isn't that just too easy~ to pass it off on to what's<br />
happening in the rest of the world when we perhaps could be finding<br />
some solution. to the problems, here?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well~ none of-us have been able to find a solution.<br />
I mean none of the other countries have been able to find a quick<br />
or an easy solution. If there was one it's certain that such<br />
a solution would have been tried, because there is a difference<br />
of political philosophy in all those countries, North America and<br />
Europe and Japan, Australia, New Zealand. And there's no easy<br />
solution. </p>
<p>QUESTION: Slowing down inflationdo you agree ) would be the<br />
key to electoral success at the next election?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I think this is the biggest component in<br />
electoral success. Yes.<br />
QUESTION: And if you've admitted that you can't do that, that<br />
Australial can't find the answer, how does that leave you when<br />
the next election comes up?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I think you will find that inflation is steadily<br />
declining. It won't decline rapidly. But our inflation is<br />
not very much out of gear with the inflation in comparable<br />
countries. We all have much worse inflation than any of us<br />
would have thought possible or tolerable back in the ' 60' s<br />
all of us.<br />
QUESTION: Can we just come down to the'State of the Nation'.<br />
And I'd like to quote Mrs Margaret Thatcher, of all people.<br />
She said thi other day that " the persistent( interjection, P. M.<br />
" You don't hear much of her now, No but she<br />
has just been to America and there she said, " the persistent<br />
expansion of the role of the State and the relentless pursuit<br />
of.-equality has caused and is causing damage to our economy in.<br />
a number of ways". Now isn't this exactly the situation that<br />
we've got in Australia at the moment?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: It's one of the criticisms which is made of us.<br />
But we make no apologies for wanting to give everybody equal<br />
opportunities. It's true enough that if you have the traditional<br />
inequalities which there have been in Australia, then Governments<br />
don't have to spend so much. If you accept inequalities then<br />
obviously Governments can save money. But we don't accept<br />
inequalities ybu must give people more access to good schools,<br />
hospitals, transport etc.<br />
QUESTION: Yes, but many of the valuable social reforms that<br />
your Government has introduced are being grossly misused by<br />
bludgers, . let's face it; what comment do you have about these<br />
bludgers? PRIME MINISTER: There are some-bludgers. Obviously private<br />
bodies like St. Vincent De Paul, Red Cross, Salvation Army,<br />
will tell you that there is an irreducible minimum of bludgers.<br />
And I suppose this is the experience of all Government welfare<br />
agencies too. It becomes finally a choice between employing<br />
a very great number of public servants to weed all the bludgers Outor<br />
accepting the universal experience of private as well as<br />
Government welfare agencies that there are a number of immoral<br />
types who pole on charitable people and on taxpayers.<br />
QUESTION: The public is saying though that there are so many<br />
of these bludgers around and the'ym paying their taxes to keep<br />
them having a pleasant time. Do you see... </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER: Well, it would cost an immense amount, let's<br />
face it to expand the public service to detect or punish all<br />
the bludgers there are. Mind you I do think this can be<br />
exaggerated. Clearly there are some people in the hinterland<br />
of Cairns or on the Gold Coast who are bludging but I don't<br />
believe that most people willingly or knowingly bludge on the<br />
community. but I d6n't'believe that most peoplo are like that<br />
QUESTION. Would you agree that there are people who have taKen<br />
advantage of the iTEAT scheme, there are people who have taken<br />
advantage of the RED scheme, there are people who have taken<br />
advantage of various schemes that you have introduced, Medibank<br />
is the latest one I see that it...<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well, I'm not sure about the Medibank thing<br />
but there again in the NEAT scheme and the RED scheme overwhelmingly<br />
there has been merit and virtue in them. There's been a very<br />
great number of individuals and families who've benefited and<br />
communities. The RED scheme is supported by a great number of<br />
people, such as the N. S. W. and Victorian Governments, who are<br />
challenging. itinthd High Court. You've got the extraordinary<br />
position, they're challenging our right to have the RED scheme<br />
but at the same time they want in -to be expanded.<br />
QUESTION: The Victorians are challenging your right to administer<br />
money. They say they can administer the money better and this is<br />
one of the big thinigs in Victoria, I think that has Mr Hamer upset.<br />
He says. under section No. 96 that the Commonwealth is going<br />
too far under these tied grants ; you're trying to insist that<br />
you tell the States how to spend the money. Why can't the States<br />
decide for themselves?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I think Mr Hamer's objection and the objection<br />
of a very great number of other State parliamentarians is to the<br />
fact that my Government has had direct relationships with local<br />
Government bodies in Australia.. The State Governments want to<br />
centralise relations with the local government bodies in the<br />
State capitals, and they don't like direct...<br />
QUESTION: Mr Hamer accuses you of centralisation and you are<br />
accusing him of centralisation.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well the States are much more centralised in<br />
their administration than my Government or any previous<br />
federal Government. That's a fact.<br />
QUESTION: But isn't it true that one of the things that has<br />
cost the country a fortune is the establishment of a new army<br />
of public servants in Canberra to administer State functions.<br />
And we already have those public servants here in the State.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well, if you look at the figures the increase<br />
in the numbers of public servahts in the time I've been Prime<br />
Minister has been much smalle: federally than in the State<br />
administrations or in local government. -The federal public<br />
service has expanded much less than any of the State<br />
public services or than local government employment. That's<br />
the figures, there's no question of that. / 6 </p>
<p>QUESTION: What gives you the impression that Mr Bjelke-Petersen<br />
is a'Bible bashing bastard'?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well I used that in the context of saying that<br />
he'd acted in his unprincipled immoral-way in stacking the<br />
Senate and I said it was all the more nausaating since he was<br />
a Bible bashing bastard. That is, I didn't use it in isolation,<br />
I wanted to highlight the fact that he is a hypocrite. Which,<br />
of course, he is.<br />
QUESTION: Bible bashing hardly seems a term that one would expect<br />
a Prime Minister to use though in referring to a State Premier<br />
bastard eitherI suppose.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I would have thought that any of us would use<br />
those words about a blatant hypocriteas Mr Bjelke-Petersen is.<br />
Nobody will support, I don't think anybody would come on your<br />
program and support what Mr Bjelke-Petersen did. Now they<br />
mightn't use the words that I used when some of your people<br />
asked me foi an opinion on the kerbside andso on. But they<br />
would all agree that it was nauseating hypocricy.<br />
QUESTION: It was on the kerb; was it just a slip? Did you<br />
regret the statement?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Oh, it was a bit strong I suppose but he is a<br />
hypocriteand I'm entitled to say it.<br />
QUESTION: Do you regret it now, saying that?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I suppose it'd be better if I hadn't because<br />
it distracts attention from the rest of what I said.<br />
QUESTION: In relation to Senator Field and the bluff and<br />
counter bluff about elections and also the Senator Gair aff ir<br />
and Mr Bunton: What's happening to the ethic of Parliament. Is<br />
good Government in jeopardy because of the politickingf<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes obviously. The things that Mr Bjelke-Petersen<br />
has now done and which Mr Lewis did earlier are quite<br />
unconscionable. That is, they're gone against the principles<br />
which had been followed by every State parliament under governments<br />
of both sides of politics without deviation throughout the 1950' s<br />
and the 1960' s. Until this year there had been a quarter of a<br />
century of obedience toacceptance of~ the convention, that<br />
if a Senator's position became vacant he'd be replaced by a<br />
Senator of the same Party.<br />
QUESTION: But how is it affecting good government? What<br />
effect is it having in the running of the country?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well, the whole of the political basis of<br />
Government in Britain and accordingly in Australia, which has<br />
adopted British practices, depends overwhelmingly on conventions.<br />
In Britain totally on conventions. In Australia on conventions<br />
except where the Constitution makes some specific provision.<br />
And you know, there's no provision in the Constitution for<br />
things which we all accep such as, Cabinet Government and<br />
so on / 7 </p>
<p>QUESTION: Can we talk about Mr Hawke for a moment? He says<br />
that the Labor Party is facing its gravest, crisis and you<br />
bear him out on that. Has the ACTU contributed to this crisis<br />
by its failure to control union wage demands?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:. Well the ACTU, one has to realise is a body<br />
to which well over a hundred separate unions belong. And those<br />
unions all have a separate legal identity when it comes to<br />
proceedings before arbitration tribunals. So it's quite wrong<br />
to suggest that the ACTU, whoever is the President of it, can<br />
have a monolithic-attitude to every possible subject and you<br />
can't expect it.<br />
QUESTION: But surely the ACTU has a duty to control union wage<br />
demands?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No I don't think you should -it's always<br />
assumed that, employee organisations are there to discipline<br />
their members. Well we don't seem to accept the same thing<br />
when it comes to employers, -disciplining their associates<br />
when it com~ s to when it comes to pricing of goods and services.<br />
There's always a balance in these things. Clearly the amount<br />
of wage increases last financial year was excessive and it<br />
could not be allowed to continue that was quite obvious.<br />
You can't just blame the ACTU only., because under the laws as<br />
they are-and the States have resisted the Arbitration Commission's<br />
pleas.. six or more Years ago to coordinate and standardise their<br />
laws-under these State laws, Every union is a separate legal<br />
body and you can have the same union which is a separate legal<br />
identity in the four States which have compulsory Arbitration<br />
as well as federally. And it makes an extraordinarily difficult<br />
situation in which to deal with wages or conditions of any sort.<br />
QUESTION: Well at this week's Congress the ACTU has accepted<br />
the principle of wage indexation, they've also lef t themselves<br />
a loophole for collective bargaining. But the ACTU has also<br />
urged the Government to adopt tax indexation and your Treasurer<br />
has successfully avoided this; why?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: ' Well, I don't think you'. re correctly putting what<br />
the Treasurer has said. Bill Hayden has brought in the most<br />
sweeping tax reform, income tax reform, that's ever been brought<br />
in the federal parliament.<br />
QUESTION: In place of iridexation?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No, as a matter of fact, it's better than<br />
indexation. What Bill Hayden has done in this year's Budget<br />
will produce a much better deal for income tax payers than<br />
would have been produced by applying indexation to the present<br />
tax scales. My Government has reduced income tax on three<br />
occasions and the percentage of income that people have to pay<br />
in income tax is lower now than it was. And what we've done<br />
makes it lower still. </p>
<p>QUESTION: Prime Minister could just comment quickly on the<br />
fact that the Opposition parties have apparently accepted XV<br />
the proposition that if returned to power some personal<br />
~ income taxation powers may be handed back to the States. r<br />
" Wh-at do-y-ou think this would do to the Australian economy?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: It just wouldn't work. The simple fact is that<br />
there are some States which would be able to get as much income<br />
as they get now, through arrangements with the Federal Governmenteven<br />
if they were to raise income tax themselves -that applies<br />
to Victoria certainly and New South Wales is 50<br />
But the other 4 states, if they were to raise income tax<br />
themselves would have to levy the tax at a much higher rate<br />
than it is at present levied. This is because the taxability<br />
of the 4. smaller. States is much less than the taxability of<br />
Victoria and New South Wales. Now I thought we all accepted<br />
that the Sta * tes which are richer, longer settled, more<br />
industrialised, like Victoria and New South Wales should help<br />
to pay for services provided by the other States. That's<br />
what uniforrr taxation does. But it's inevitable that you have<br />
uniform taxation and that should be raised by the Federal<br />
Government alone, in Australia. And a lot of Liberals accept<br />
that situation.<br />
QUESTION! But a lot of Liberals don't accept the way that<br />
your Government makes the grants to the States and then wants<br />
to control the way those grants are spent.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well that's not completely true. The States<br />
this. year will be receiving 34%, I think it is, more money<br />
from the Federal Government than they received last year. And<br />
they can spend that as they see fit.<br />
QUESTION:' But-the conditions have changed.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No, No, this is as,' they see fit.<br />
QUESTION: Our education Minister, Mr Thompson, is very upset<br />
because against the recommendations of the Schools Commission,<br />
which suggested that there should be a triennial payout in<br />
education_, Mr Hayden is now giving grants on a six-monthly<br />
basis. PRIME MINISTER: No, No, that's not true. Every educational<br />
grant by the Federal Government to the State Governments is<br />
indexed. That is, if there is inflation the value of the grant<br />
is adjusted to maintain its value. We are committed to the<br />
triennial business; we haven't been able to bring in as many<br />
new programs as we were hoping this financial year. But we<br />
are committed to the triennial concept and what the States get<br />
this year will in every respect be of the same value as or<br />
greater value than they got last year for education. Now you<br />
mention Mr Thompson, but Mr Beazley has exposed,.. in the Parliament,<br />
I need'-t repeat it,.. the Vict~ orian Government's failure<br />
to maintain it's share of educational expenditure. A lot of<br />
the State Governments are saying that, where as in schools and<br />
in hospitals and public transport, my Government has stepped in<br />
to raise the standards, because the States were obviously allowing<br />
them to decline, that for some reason we should then 19 </p>
<p>do the lot. Now we don't believe that we should run the<br />
schools or the hospitals or the public transport, but we<br />
do believe that each of those should be improved. We are<br />
helping to improve them but we do say the States at least<br />
should maintain the commitment that they had always had.<br />
Wd don't mind topping them up, but we don't think that<br />
when we come in they should then be able to. relax and diminish<br />
their contributions.<br />
QUESTION: What is Australia's current position in regard to<br />
Portuguese Timor? Are we merely following Indonesia ' s<br />
wishes in our behaviour towards this part of our hear North,<br />
or what is our policyexactly now?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well, we say it i's a Portuguese colony and<br />
the Portuguese Government ought to accept responsibility instead<br />
of just clearing out and dropping their bundle. Secondly,...<br />
QUESTION: What happens if they do clear out?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well then we're saying-and we've provided<br />
a very great afnount of transport and communications to help.<br />
that the contending forces in Timor should get together and<br />
settle their differences.<br />
QUESTION: Would we , be prepared to recognise a Fretelin-controlled<br />
East Timor?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Fretelin hasn't got to its. present position<br />
as any result of self-determination. They got the Portuguese<br />
Army's weapons, and they then tried to clean up their opponents.<br />
That's not an act of self-determination.<br />
QUESTION: ' If they did take control, and in<br />
fact were-running the country, would we recognise them?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well, are they in control? Our position is<br />
quite clear., that there are three contending parties, they've<br />
all emerged in less than 2 years. They ought to get together.<br />
We have supported all along the idea of self-determination,<br />
that Portuguese ought to help in that process and the Timorese<br />
parties ought to get together and help it.<br />
QUESTION: But currently we support the pro-Indonesian party,<br />
Do we?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No, we don't support any of the parties. there.<br />
We never have and I don't think that has been alleged. We don't<br />
support any of the parties. We think that the parties ought<br />
to get together. That's why we spent a lot of time, a fair<br />
amount of money, a lot of effort, Air Force and communications<br />
equipment to help the Portuguese envoy get the parties together.<br />
QUESTION: Mr Whitlam a lot of people have asked me to ask you<br />
this one. Why does Australia want to take over the Cocoa Island~<br />
why can't you leave those people alone? </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER: Well we took them over from Britain. We took<br />
the islands over from Britain in the 1950' s and they are living<br />
in conditions which the rest of the world will not accept.<br />
QUESTION: Some parts of the world envy their conditions.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well, maybe they do, but these people haven't<br />
got any choice. That is~ they're all employed by the one man,<br />
who.--pays them in tokens and they can cash those tokens only in<br />
his stores. Now it might look idyllic from our distance but<br />
it's a very paternal attitude for us to say that that's good<br />
enough for them. Nobody else in the world would accept it.<br />
And Cocos is important to us; if we are to retain jurisdictionwhich<br />
we-sou'ght 20 years ago, and, this is a territory a fair<br />
distance from us,.. then obviously we have to see t hat I<br />
acceptable standards apply; they're entitled to education,<br />
they're entitled to proper employment conditions and they<br />
haven't been getting them.<br />
QUESTION: hey won't inherit inflation?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I don't know how you inflate tokens at the<br />
Clunies-Ross store. He prints them, he cashes them~ he sells<br />
things for them, you've got no option. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
