<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>644</transcript-id>
    <title>FIFTIETH ANNIVERSARY CELEBRATIONS OF THE SMALL ARMS FACTORY, LITHGOW, NSW ON 5TH NOVEMBER 1962 - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R G MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/11/1962</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000644_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FIFTIETH ANNIVERSARY CELEBRATIONS<br />
OF THE SMALL APMS FACTORY, LITHGOW,<br />
N. S. 1' 1ø ON 5TH NOVEMBER, 1962<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister, the Rt. Hon, R. G. Menzies<br />
Sir, Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
I was just making a little precautionary investigation,<br />
and do you know, improbable as it may seem there<br />
are cigars in it, ( Laughter) As a matter of fact, I don't<br />
quite know what I am supposed to do this afternoon. I<br />
haven't been given adequate instructions. Usually when I<br />
attend something of this kind, I have to declare something<br />
open. I won't get out of the habit and, therefore, I begin<br />
by saying that I declare the Small Arms Factory to have been<br />
well and truly opened fifty years ago. ( Laughter) ( Applause)<br />
I suppose that on a day like this, a beautiful<br />
day in a beautiful setting, one gets the best possible<br />
impression of the place and the work and the people and I<br />
would like to say a few words to you about each of those<br />
matters whilst I have the floor,<br />
First of all, the place, I suppose that the<br />
people who live in Lithgow tend to take it fcr gr:: nted.<br />
I don't know. Lithgow has a remarkable hibtor* r. a history<br />
which in itself embodies the development of Austva-Lia from<br />
one stage of activity to ano. e right dowth.. its<br />
time. it was here in Lithgo½ I think I am rA-, u in saying<br />
that the first iron and steel industry was est""". ished,<br />
always to be associated with the great Lithgow name of Hoskins.<br />
And I sometimes wonder whether it was the fact that this<br />
existed and that there was coal here that induced the Government<br />
of the day, fifty years ago, to establish this factory,<br />
in its initial form, in this place. But the fact is that<br />
ever since then, this factory, through all sorts of<br />
vicissitudes it has had its ups and downs in the course<br />
of its time has become increasingly famous for the quality<br />
of its work. Today when I was walking around, I couldn't help<br />
rubbing shoulders occasionally with a number of men prominent<br />
in engineering and other activities in Australia, all of them<br />
feeling pretty amiable, all of them quite prepared to have a<br />
friendly word with me thatts not always the case ( Laughter)<br />
but all of them taking the opportunity of commenting on the<br />
excellence of' the work that is done here. I think myself,<br />
Mr. Minister, that this not unassociated with the history<br />
of Lithgow or the spirit and character of its people. This<br />
town has tradition, this town has made a great contribution<br />
in its own way, much bigger than its population, to Australian<br />
life and Australian development, and they would be very poor<br />
people of Lithgow who didn't feel a pride in the fact that<br />
here is a place, known all over Australia, a place that has<br />
been able to contribute to activities and skills all over<br />
Australia. Now, I think that is a matter for great pride,<br />
a matter for great celebration.<br />
There are people, of course, in the world a great<br />
number of them to be found in Australia who are ' knockers."<br />
Wherever you go, you meet a " knocker". Nothing is any good.<br />
Nothing is ever as good now as it used to be. They talk<br />
about the " good old days". If they had to live in the good / 2 </p>
<p>old days, some of these " knockers", they woL,. dnrt talk about<br />
them So rmuch. But they " knock" Other countries can do<br />
better than we can at this or that, " Oh yes, this is all<br />
right for an Australian enterprisc." Such people make me<br />
tired. They have never done anything to forward. Australia.<br />
The people who keep this country moving are not the " knockers",<br />
but the doers, the people who get on with it the people who,<br />
themselves, establish the standards and maintain them and<br />
improve them, Anybody who went around here today, even in<br />
an ignorant state of mind, couldn't cme out of it without<br />
being proud of the demonstrated Australian capacity for<br />
precision work of the highest possible kind. Nothing<br />
slovenly, nothing second-rate you couldn't produce the<br />
end result from this factory if anything in the end result<br />
was second-rate. Everything in its own way has to achieve<br />
pcrfection, so that in the end, the instrument is, in itself,<br />
a perfect and accurate instrument. I think that we ought to<br />
provide for some system of government grant to elect a dozen<br />
prominent " knockers'" every week and make them come up here and<br />
walk around. ( Applause)<br />
Now, Sir, I have said a little about the place, not<br />
enough; a little about the work, not enovgh; but you all<br />
know about the place and you know about the work. I just want<br />
to say a little about the people because, here again, there<br />
is a considerable amount of mis-understanding in the world.<br />
There are too many people in the world who try to create<br />
differences when none exist, who try to pretend that everybody<br />
lives at all times in a state of discontent, I don't believe<br />
that's true0 I think, and I have noticed it, going around<br />
here today, that th. s is a place in which the morale is high<br />
and the work is good, because the spirits of the people who<br />
are working here are goodo ( Applause) This strikes me as<br />
outstandingly a happy place and it is in happy places that<br />
the best work is done, Not in grumbling places, not in places<br />
in which people live with a chronic sense of injustice, but<br />
in a well-run, well-organised, well-managed place of this<br />
kind and with people of the kind I am addressing this afternoon,<br />
there is happiness. Therefore, we are celebrating the fiftieth anniversary<br />
of a works whica began in a very small way and I gather,<br />
looking around, in a very noisy way, fifty years ago. Today,<br />
it is the last word in modernity, increasingly employs a great<br />
number of pcople, makes its contribution to Australian history<br />
and to the future security of Australia and does it all in<br />
a community and a setting where cheerfulness is the keynote.<br />
So it is a very good thing for a travelling<br />
politician like myself to get away from the cut and thrust<br />
of Canberra you may have heard of Canberra ( Laughter)<br />
sometimes you Day have listened in to the exquisitely courteous<br />
exchanges ( Laughter) that we engage in at Canberra. It's<br />
a good thing to get away from that for a few minutes or for<br />
half a day and come up here and see ycu all and be delighted<br />
to be with you.<br />
Now, before I sit down, I will just make one more<br />
comment. How is it that if I were here to make a political<br />
speech, I wouldn't see any of you chaps at all ( Laughter)<br />
( Applause). Well I understand that but, anyhow, you get the<br />
point. I am happy to tell you that political speech or no<br />
political speech, I will be delighted to have this, made on<br />
the premises, as a souvenir of this event and each time I look<br />
at it and open it or have it ratted by one of my friends who<br />
wants a cigar ( Laughter), I will look back to this day and<br />
remember how many beautiful, magnificent electors there were,<br />
to whom I couldn't address a solitary word on the policy of<br />
the Government, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
