<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9725</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP DOORSTOP, NATIONAL ART GALLERY OF AUSTRALIA, CANBERRA 22 AUGUST 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/08/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009725.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
DOORSTOP, NATIONAL ART GALLERY OF AUSTRALIA, CANBERRA<br />
22 AUGUST 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
J: Any comment on the appointment of Sir William Deane?<br />
PM: Well, I think he brings, amongst a few people, almost unparalleled<br />
vista of the Constitution, he's made clear the symbiotic relationship<br />
between the public in our democracy, and the Constitution. He has<br />
been a very progressive Judge on matters which have been of quite<br />
substantial moment to Australia. He is amongst a few one can't say<br />
uniquely, but near uniquely fitted to the task of Governor-General,<br />
which I think he will execute with great dignity and commitment.<br />
J: ( inaudible)...<br />
PM: He has already played a substantial part, of course, in the Native<br />
Title judgement, and I think he is exercised by the notion that the law<br />
is a living thing, and that these were social questions that needed to<br />
be addressed by the law he did then, and I am sure when he says<br />
that, he will take that opportunity, because I think coming to terms on<br />
a sort of deep basis of reconciliation with our indigenes has been<br />
something obviously on his mind for most of his legal and judicial life.<br />
J: How long can Carmen Lawrence continue to enjoy your support.<br />
PM: Well, she has enjoyed it to this point.<br />
ends. cm, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
