<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8205</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER LAUNCH OF ALAN OXLEY THE CHALLENGE OF FREE TRADE SYDNEY - 19 NOVEMBER 1990</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/11/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008205.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
CHECZ AGAINRT nRELIVERy RMAR= ORf 1MT11L DELIVERY<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister<br />
Launch of Alan Oxley's ' The Challenge of Free Trade'<br />
Sydney 19 November 1990<br />
Alan Oxley has wihitten an extraordinary book.<br />
The GATT the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade is<br />
not exactly the world's most easily understood or most<br />
transparently lucid of organisations. Not for nothing has<br />
it earned the nickname " The General Agreement to Talk and<br />
Talk". As for the Uruguay Round, it has too often, especially in<br />
its early years, run the risk of being mistaken for a kind<br />
of Latin American dance.<br />
If ever there was a topic that needed a knowledgeable and<br />
readable author to explain its fundamental importance to<br />
international affairs, then GATT is that topic.<br />
And Alan Oxley is precisely that author. As Australia's<br />
Ambassador to GATT from 1985 to 1989, he has spent more than<br />
his fair * share of hours engaged in the hard, long-drawn-out<br />
grind of international trade negotiation.<br />
But instead of writing some dry-as-dust analysis, Alan's<br />
book is fast-paced, engaging and even especially when you<br />
get to Appendices Three and Four funny.<br />
His subtle insight into how the crisis in the current round<br />
of trade talks unfolded, his explanation of the profound<br />
significance of this crisis, and his plea for a successful<br />
outcome, are masterly elements of this book.<br />
" The Challenge of Free Trade" will be rewarding reading for<br />
the specialist, for the businessman and woman, and for the<br />
general reader alike, and I hope it will reach the wide<br />
audience it deserves.<br />
This is also a very timely book, and I know I will be<br />
excused if I spend a few minutes outlining Australia's views<br />
about tbo. current impasse in international trade.<br />
GATT emerged from the political and economic rubble of World<br />
War Two.<br />
3360 A<br />
* 4ATVW </p>
<p>2.<br />
With a certain degree of idealism it sought to establish an<br />
international order in which free trade between nations<br />
could flourish unimpeded by the senseless and vicious<br />
bouts of protectionism that had so damaged the pre-war<br />
global economy.<br />
The fundamental principles of GATT are that open markets are<br />
the most efficient, and that measures which impede trade<br />
should have the least distorting effect on markets and<br />
should be gradually reduced.<br />
GATT has, by and large, been a resounding success. It<br />
created a free trade umbrella beneath which the world has<br />
enjoyed a dramatic and continued growth in prosperity since<br />
the Second World War.<br />
But as the GATT approached its fortieth anniversary, in the<br />
mid-1980s, it was well and truly into a mid-life crisis.<br />
Resurgent protectionism in a number of the more prosperous<br />
countries was threatening to overturn the multilateral<br />
system of trade rules the very system which had helped<br />
make them prosperous in the first place.<br />
So in 1986, at a meeting in Uruguay, the GATT members<br />
decided to embark on a c~ ritical four-year round of.<br />
negotiations to liberaliLse world trade and to revitalise the<br />
GATT rules.<br />
That Uruguay meeting wal3 an auspicious one. There were more<br />
participating countries than ever before, including<br />
developing countries; and there was a broader agenda than<br />
ever before including the issues of trade in services and,<br />
of special importance to Australia, trade in agriculture.<br />
Because we believed it imperative to realise this first-ever<br />
opportunity to establish a firm and sound basis for trade in<br />
agriculture, Australia took the initiative to bring together<br />
a number of other like-minded agricultural nations in the<br />
Cairns Group.<br />
This Group represents 25 per cent of world trade in<br />
agriculture, and we have been relentless in applying<br />
pressure on those agricultural producers whose protectionist<br />
measures are distorting our markets and seeking to negate<br />
our efficiency.<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen,<br />
GATT is now approaching the final few days of that four-year<br />
negotiating period of the Uruguay Round.<br />
And despite its auspicious start, it is no overstatement now<br />
to say that the Uruguay Round is in a state of crisis.<br />
The cause of that crisis is that the European Community,<br />
stubbornly and short-sightedly, has refused to negotiate in<br />
any genuine way on agric~ ulture. 3i 3~ 6 1 </p>
<p>3.<br />
If the Europeans do not shift their position on agriculture<br />
if they do not show they are prepared to reduce the<br />
massive distortions to the world economy caused by their<br />
agricultural protectionism then the Uruguay Round as a<br />
whole will fail.<br />
I don't make that statement as a threat. I make it as a<br />
statement of plain fact.<br />
Agriculture has become the key to the success or failure of<br />
the Round.<br />
The Cairns Group the United States have made it clear<br />
that the Europeans must agree to substantial and progressive<br />
cuts in support and protection for agriculture, with<br />
specific commitments on each of the three key types of<br />
support.<br />
But it was only earlier this month, with merely a few weeks<br />
to go before the end of the Round, that the Europeans<br />
finally made an offer on agriculture and it was an offer<br />
that fell far short of what we have been seeking. It<br />
contains no prospect that the Europeans will significantly<br />
cut their subsidies of agricultural exports, nor that they<br />
will open their markets to imports.<br />
And since they tabled that offer, it has become plain that<br />
the European Governments have given their representatives no<br />
significant scope to negotiate.<br />
In other words, with time running out, we are deadlocked.<br />
Let me make quite clear to you what I believe is at stake.<br />
Success in the Uruguay Round will offer the opportunity to<br />
borrow from Alan Oxley's crisp summary<br />
to increase global growth;<br />
to break the developing-country debt cycle:<br />
to increase global food production;<br />
to underpin economic and political renewal in<br />
Eastern Europe; and<br />
to apply the dynamism of the information age to<br />
-expand global trade.<br />
Failure in the Round will not only mean we have missed the<br />
opportunity. 44to reap those benefits, it will also see the<br />
start of a slide into the economic and political dangers of<br />
renewed protectionism.<br />
As I said at the outset, GATT was established explicitly to<br />
prevent a recurtence of the economic mismanagement of the<br />
1930a that helped bring about the Second World War.<br />
336~ 2 </p>
<p>4.<br />
The Europeans of today seem to have forgotten what the<br />
founders of GATT knew, from their own terrible experience of<br />
the 1930s: that protectionism is not just an economic<br />
disease but a potential source of political friction and<br />
conflict. r"<br />
That is why the weakening of GATT, brought about by a<br />
failure of the Uruguay Round, would not only pose a grave<br />
threat to the world's prosperity but would also be a<br />
tragically regressive step at the very time when we should<br />
be trying to make permanent the truly positive trends that<br />
are emerging in the world.<br />
Surely, the lesson of the 1930s is a lesson too costly to<br />
repeat. With that much at stake, you can well understand why it has<br />
been my Government's high priority to ensure a successful<br />
outome to the Round.<br />
Even with the prospects of success as dim as they now are,<br />
we must not simply lie down and die. We have to fight this<br />
out to the end.<br />
That is why I spoke to President Bush last Friday. And it<br />
is why I have written today to the leaders of the European<br />
Community Chancellor Kohl, Prime Ministers Rocard,<br />
Andreotti, and Thatcher, EC President Delora, and the<br />
leaders of the other Community members urging them all to<br />
exercise real political leadership in the interests of the<br />
international system.<br />
In these letters I expressed my deep concern over the future<br />
of the Round In the light of the totally unsatisfactory<br />
nature of the European offer on agriculture.<br />
That offer was too restrictive on access by other nations to<br />
the European market, and failed to reduce the export<br />
subsidies which are the most trade-distorting of all<br />
policies. They are also the most damaging to efficient agricultural<br />
producers and I said in my letters that the rural<br />
economies of Australia and of many of our Cairns Group<br />
colleagues are being devastated by export subsidies.<br />
Of course it is relativ'ely easy to spell out the damage<br />
protectionism is causing countries such as Australia.<br />
It is more difficult, but equally important, for the<br />
European leaders to understand that their own people are<br />
being hurt.<br />
I said in my letters that I understood the internal<br />
pressures that made it difficult to cut support for<br />
agricultural producers. 33 a </p>
<p>But underlying this must be the recognition of the fact that<br />
morq open markets will mean much cheaper food costs for<br />
European consumers; while the elimination of subsidies will<br />
liberate taxpayers of the massive burden they bear in<br />
supporting inefficient farmers.<br />
In other words, the ordinary man and woman in Europe will<br />
enjoy the benefits of a more efficient economy in which the<br />
resources of the community are directed towards productive<br />
investment not poured into the bottomless pit of farm<br />
supports. And consider . the context in which this situation has arisen.<br />
The European Community is poised on the verge of an historic<br />
breakthrough the creation of a single market in 1992 which<br />
will, if it is an open market, dramatically improve the<br />
living standards of Europeans and generally provide a boost<br />
to world economic prosperity.<br />
It is a triumph of mature and far-sighted political<br />
leadership; a demonstration that the Europeans can overcome<br />
the obstacles that stand in the way of an even more<br />
prosperous and more productive life.<br />
At the sane time, Western Europe is facing up to the<br />
challenges of closer economic integration with Eastern<br />
Europe, now being freed from the shackles of central<br />
planning. What a tragedy it would be what an absurdity it would bel<br />
if at the time of these historic developments<br />
developments which demonstrate the unqualified merits of<br />
competitive open markets the Europeans were to deny those<br />
merits, and undermine their bright prospects, by a failure<br />
of will in agriculture.<br />
What are we to make of a Europe which in respect of the 1992<br />
Single Market is capable of vision and wisdom, and which in<br />
respect of agricultural protection is capable-of selfishness<br />
and short-sightedness? At the very least, the claims of<br />
Europe to a position of respect and influence in the<br />
international community will be significantly diminished if<br />
it caves in to the pressures of its farm lobby.<br />
My appeal is not for favours to Australia or charity to the<br />
Cairns Group. it is an appeal to the European Community's<br />
own long-range self-interest. The-subsidisation of<br />
inefficiency cannot serve that self-interest; nor can the<br />
imperiling of a negotiation which in so many other sectors<br />
of fers:. Burope great benefits and opportunities.<br />
All this underlies my plea to the European leaders to exert<br />
political muscle in the final days leading up to the<br />
ministerial meeting in Brussels in early December.<br />
3364, 77, a-</p>
<p>6.<br />
I know from my conversation with President Bush that he and<br />
Secretary of State Baker will be urging the Europeans to<br />
adopt a more reasonable stance and I unreservedly welcome<br />
the pressure that the US has exerted and continues to exert<br />
in these vital talks.<br />
To be sure, we have no fondness for American export<br />
subsidies, and I have never neglected to criticise them<br />
publicly or privately. But the difference is that in the<br />
Uruguay Round, the United States is willing to cut, and cut<br />
substantially, if others will do likewise. The onus<br />
therefore lies squarely with the European Community.<br />
I stress that it is still the very earnest wish of the<br />
Australian Governmrent to see the Brussels meeting yield a<br />
successful outcome.<br />
However, I have ma~ de it clear that should it fail, then I<br />
would see merit in bringing Heads of Government together in<br />
a subsequent meeting not to settle fine points of detail<br />
but to give the process new impetus and firm direction from<br />
the top.<br />
We simply must do whatever we can to ensure a successful<br />
outcome of the Uruguay Round. We cannot afford to fail.<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
Throughout the entire Uruguay Round, Australia has<br />
diligently and ardently pursued what we consider to be our<br />
essential interests ensuring our farmers get fair access<br />
to the world's markets, and generally protecting the global<br />
system of unimpeded trade.<br />
It was very much iLn pursuit of these interests that we<br />
established the Ca~ irns Group so that nations with similar<br />
interests can spea~ k with a collectively louder and more<br />
influential voice.<br />
The Cairns Group activity in the Uruguay Round is but one<br />
example of Australia's increasingly productive emphasis on<br />
multilateral diplomacy.<br />
Be it in international trade talks, or' in global or regional<br />
efforts to ban chemical weapons, or the campaign to ban<br />
mining in Antarctica, or the initiative to find a peaceful<br />
solution in Cambodia, or the Asia Pacific Economic<br />
Cooperation initiative, or indeed the task of building a<br />
stable post-Cold ' Wiar world order in the United Nations,<br />
Australia is prepared to do the hard work of multilateral<br />
diplomacy. We stand to gain and the world community stands to gain.<br />
I want to take this opportunity to say a few words about the<br />
men and women who are at the coal-face of this work -people<br />
like Alan Oxley. 3365 </p>
<p>7.<br />
Multilateral diplomacy demands patience, commitment and an<br />
unshakeable perception of the long-term goals. It may not<br />
be particularly glamorous work but it is essential and it is<br />
an increasingly important part of what diplomacy is all<br />
about. Australia is particularly well served by its overseas<br />
zepresentatives and I want to take this opportunity to<br />
record the Government's appreciation of their work. In<br />
particular I want to say to those engaged in the<br />
multilateral efforts I have outlined, how much the<br />
Government respects the contribution they are making to<br />
aidvancing our national interests.<br />
3: had the opportunity to see Alan Oxley's work at close<br />
quarters when I visited Geneva in October 1987 to deliver a<br />
Cairns Group address to GATT. As he records in this book,<br />
t~ he preparation of that speech couldn't be finalised untiliahall<br />
we say quite late in the piece and required a degree<br />
of international coordination of Cairns Group members. That<br />
the speech went smoothly was of course a tribute to Alan's<br />
e~ fforts, and I express my thanks to him for that.<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen,<br />
, rhis is as I said at the outset an extraordinary book.<br />
In addition to all the other reasons I have outlined, it is<br />
extraordinary because it tells a story as intricate and as<br />
dramatic as any detective thriller.<br />
It is about nothing less than how the world managed to get<br />
itself to the edge of a precipice.<br />
And unfortunately for the world, this real-life thriller<br />
doesn't yet have a last chapter.<br />
We don't know if the world crawls back from the abyss or<br />
whether it plunges down to the depths.<br />
It is my very sincere and profound hope that commionsenseand<br />
a greater degree of political leadership by the European<br />
Community will ensure that there is a satisfactory ending<br />
to this tale. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
