<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1597</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: P.M. NO. 57/1967 - STATEMENT BY THE ACTING PRIME MINISTER MR. JOHN MCEWEN</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/06/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001597.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
-8JUNj<br />
QS8RAVO<br />
FOR PRESS I21.10 . 57/ 1967<br />
" Tl T-IY7, IVT 3Y T ' E ACTII7PRIM!. E MiIT<br />
B. JOHF1 M~ cE<br />
The Actin-, Prime Minister, Vr. MlcEwen, said that he<br />
had called a Cabinel meeting in vie,;. ' of. developments in the M, 1iddle<br />
East, which Aus-traliai, in common .7ith all other* likeminded cm) ntries,<br />
viewed with deep -ind -r,' iiin-, concern.<br />
he1* d r. 1-cI'., en said thaIt, in vie, of the developinx tensions,<br />
he -adthought it essential that Cbinet M'inisters shouil not only<br />
oe kept informed of all that wa. s know,, n of the situa-) tion bUt shoulda<br />
ha-. ve -in opportunity to consult.<br />
Mr. Mvc.' wen said th-at he h . d ueen keeping in close touch<br />
with the Prime Minister, w-ho h; a's himself had thje idvanta'e of<br />
discussin.-) this with President Johnson -ind Secretary of tate Rusk.<br />
Mr. Holt also hid anu e-arly opportunity of communicattion with Mr.<br />
Harold ' Jilson, the 3ritish rime Mlinister.<br />
Mr. McEwen saiid th-It he was sure it would be expected<br />
of the Austr-ili-: n -Thvernment thA it should join wi th others in<br />
evHery ittempt to qvoid tensions in t'he Middle Eist developing into<br />
conflict ue t . ieen the arties confrontin::, each other ther i.<br />
Mr. IvcE . en said tha-t I reait principles a-ffecting the<br />
freedom of passcie over mercantile saa laines were -A issue aind<br />
this was of crit'ical import-ince to Ire A intern.-tional traing<br />
nations. A".. so involved wa--s the right of independent member states<br />
of the United . latons to a-secure, O peacfl ex; 3ene<br />
Hle sfaid th.-t, on the question of the olockg-de of the JTulf<br />
of Agaua, a'Ith-oritaitive st. Aements by the Minister for External<br />
Affarlls Ave falrea. dy oeen made renresentinZ the view stron fly held<br />
by the AIustraIli,-n JTovernment thit thle Stra-iits of Tir. In musl oe<br />
re'-rded : in internationail waterwty through w., hich vessels of all<br />
ntAions haive a right of pa'-ssagie.<br />
21 CD JUTh', E 1967. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
