<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4800</transcript-id>
    <title>RETIREMENT OF CHAIRMAN OF PUBLIC SERVICE BOARD</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/08/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004800.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
_ 4&gt; JS~ U ALIA<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 30 AUGUST 1978<br />
Retirement of Chairman of Public Service Board<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr Fraser, announced today that the<br />
Chairman of the Public Service Board, Mr K. C. O. Shann, CBE,<br />
had decided to retire from public office for personal and<br />
family reasons.<br />
Mr Shann, who is aged 60, was appointed as Chairman of the<br />
Board in March 1977, following a distinguished diplomatic<br />
career which included postings as Australian Ambassador in<br />
Japan, Indonesia and the Philippines, and other postings in<br />
London and New York. From 1970 to 1974 he was a Deputy<br />
Secretary in the Department of Foreign Affairs in Canberra.<br />
In paying tribute to Mr Shann, Mr Fraser said " Mick Shann<br />
has had a most illustrious career as public administrator<br />
and senior diplomat. While I am personally sorry that the<br />
Government is losing his services, I wish him well in<br />
retirement."<br />
Mr Fraser said that Mr Shann had taken over as Chairman of<br />
the Public Service Board in a challenging time for the<br />
Public Service. He had made a significant contributuion<br />
towards the modernisation and greater efficiency of the<br />
Service. During his period as Chairman, Mr Shann has been<br />
closely involved with implementation of the report of the<br />
Royal Commission on Australian Government Administration,<br />
and the development of the program of staff interchanges<br />
between the Australian Public Service and other areas of<br />
employment, including private industry.<br />
Mr Shann is proceeding on leave from 1 September prior to<br />
retirement. Mr Fraser said that he expected that Cabinet<br />
would consider the question of his replacement shortly.<br />
Mr J. C. Taylor, a Commissioner of the Board, would act as<br />
Chairman from 1 September while Mr Shann is on leave. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
