<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6914</transcript-id>
    <title>AUSTRALIA-CHINA TENNIS TOURNAMENT ANNOUNCEMENT BY PRIME MINISTER, 19 MAY 1986</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/05/1986</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006914.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
AUSTRALIA-CHINA TENNIS TOURNAMENT<br />
ANNOUNCEMENT BY PRIME MINISTER<br />
IN THE PRESENCE OF MY FRIEND AND VERY FORMIDABLE OPPONENT<br />
ON THE TENNIS COURT, VICE PREMIER WAN Li, I AM HAPPY TO<br />
ANNOUNCE THAT IN PRINCIPLE AGREEMENT HAS BEEN REACHED TO<br />
ESTABLISH A TENNIS TOURNAMENT BETWEEN AUSTRALIA AND CHINA.<br />
TENNIS IS AN INCREASINGLY POPULAR SPORT IN CHINA AND I KNOW<br />
THA fHE RECENT VISIT OF PAT CASH GENERATED GREAT INTEREST.<br />
THIS IS A SPORT IN WHICH AUSTRALIA HAS A LONG TRADITION.<br />
THE CONCEPT IS TO CREATE AN ANNUAL TENNIS CHALLENGE WHICH<br />
WILL ALTERNATE BETWEEN VENUES IN AUSTRALIA AND CHINA. IT<br />
WILL INVOLVE FOUR MEN AND FOUR WOMEN PLAYERS IN A DAVIS CUP<br />
CHALLENGE FORMAT SINGLES, REVERSE SINGLES AND DOUBLES.<br />
FHE AUSTRALIAN TEAM IS EXPECTED TO CONSIST OF YOUNG<br />
PROFESSIONALS OF HIGH CALIBRE AND I UNDERSTAND THAT PAT CASH<br />
HAS EXPRESSED KEEN PERSONAL INTEREST TO PLAY IN THE FIRST<br />
CHALLENGE ROUND.<br />
THE ORGANISER-S IN AUSTRALIA ARE WORKING ON THE BASIS THAT<br />
THE FIRST ROUND COULD BE HELD IN MELBOURNE IN EARLY DECEMBER<br />
1986, PREFERABLY ON GRASS COURTS. THIS WOULD GIVE THE<br />
CHINESE PLAYERS EXPERIENCE OF GRASS COURT TENNIS. </p>
<p>S A 2.<br />
WE HOPE IT WILL BE POSSIBLE TO ARRANGE FOR AUSTRALIAN PLAYERS<br />
TO PARTICIPATE IN COACHING OF YOUNGER CHINESE PLAYERS WHEN<br />
THE CHALLENGE TAKES PLACE IN CHINA,<br />
I LOOK FORWARD TO SOME OF OUR FINE YOUNG PLAYERS PARTICIPATING<br />
IN THIS COMPETITION. THE OPPORTUNITY TO PLAY AGAINST<br />
COUNTERPARTS IN CHINA WILL NOT ONLY BE GOOD FOR TENNIS IN<br />
BOTH COUNTRIES BUT WILL MARK A NEW STEP IN THE GROWING<br />
PEOPLE-TO-PEOPLE RELATIONS BETWEEN AUSTRALIA AND CHINA,<br />
PLANNING FOR THE EVENT IS WELL IN TRAIN AND AN ANNOUNCEMENT<br />
REGARDING SPONSORSHIP IS EXPECTED TO BE MADE LATER THIS YEAR, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
