<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8557</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ KEATING MP, AUSTRALIAN BOOK PUBLISHERS AWARDS, SYDNEY 26 JUNE</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/06/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008557.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
AUSTRALIAN BOOK PUBLISHERS AWARDS, SYDNEY 26 JUNE<br />
Ladies and gentlemen.<br />
It's a pleasure to be here tonight on one of the big<br />
occasions in the Australian literary year.<br />
And to be here with an Englishman of such courage and<br />
grace that he is prepared to share the stage with a<br />
notorious Pombasher.<br />
I assure you, John, that I am not.<br />
It is only my enemies who say that I am my enemies, the<br />
British tabloids, and a certain type of intractable<br />
colonial which I'm sure you'd never come across in the<br />
Australian publishing industry.<br />
I'm pleased to be here because I want to congratulate the<br />
industry for holding this first international book fair<br />
in Australia.<br />
It's a very welcome development.<br />
Similar events are held around the world; in fact the<br />
international reputation of some cities is to a<br />
significant degree built on book fairs.<br />
There are book fairs in Frankfurt and Bologna. A US book<br />
fair, and Pacifica in Canada.<br />
They are held in Asian countries.<br />
Until now they not have been held here.<br />
Yet, per capita, Australians read as many if not more<br />
books than any of these places. They buy at least as<br />
many. They depend on books as much. </p>
<p>We are an important market for English language<br />
publishing and, increasingly, for books in other<br />
languages and in translation and it's a vigorous<br />
competitive market.<br />
We gholid celebrate books and their authors.<br />
And their publishers.<br />
And we should do what we can to focus the attention of<br />
Australians on an industry which is a vital supplier of<br />
their cultural needs.<br />
If the word cultural is off-putting, let's say education,<br />
information, communication, entertainment, ideas,<br />
politics, history, stories the skeleton, heart and mind<br />
of a community if you like.<br />
And an essential underpinning and partner of film and<br />
television and many other industries.<br />
And still probably the best measure of who we are, what<br />
we are about, and how well we are doing on the scale of<br />
civilisation. There we have a few reasons why I am pleased to be<br />
associated with the Australian Book Fair and with these<br />
awards. There is another one books offer us a window on to the<br />
world. Just as they do much to define us to ourselves, they can<br />
define us to the rest of the world.<br />
And quite frankly, I think we could do with a bit of redefining.<br />
Visitors like John Mortimer could be forgiven for<br />
wondering why we are so pre-occupied with questions of<br />
identity.<br />
Not only visitors my political opponents describe it as<br />
a distraction, or an obsession, depending on their mood.<br />
But it seems to me a fundamental concern.<br />
In the 1990s we need to be confident in ways that we have<br />
never been, independent in ways that we've never been.<br />
Why? Because all the old supports that gave us both<br />
confidence and a vicarious identity have been pulled<br />
away. The old imperial supports contrived to make the matter of<br />
our independence a secondary concern: for long periods of<br />
our history political expediency made it an illegitimate<br />
concern. </p>
<p>The same reflex governs the conservative knee Jerk today.<br />
As my opponents are inclined to believe only certified<br />
historians, or RSL Presidents, on such matters, let me<br />
quote one W. J. Hudson, the pre-eminent historian of<br />
Australian foreign policy.<br />
In an article published this year he writes:<br />
When independence from Britain came piecemeal in the<br />
twentieth century diplomatic independence 1923,<br />
executive independence in 1926 and legislative<br />
independence in 1931 it came unsought by<br />
Australia. The independence campaign was waged by<br />
Canada, South Africa and the Irish Free State, and<br />
Australia unsuccessfully opposed them. Australia<br />
became independent not by her choice, not when she<br />
wanted it, not as a result of her own efforts and<br />
not because Australians sought freedom to fulfil<br />
their own alternative visions. From the Australian<br />
point of view, Britain abdicated and Australia was<br />
thrust into an independence which she did not want<br />
and which, lest a potential aggressor might think he<br />
had only Australia to face and not the might of the<br />
British empire, she pretended had not happened.<br />
Some Australians some influential Australians still<br />
pretend. Some symbolic vestiges and some attitudes<br />
suggest that thenat~ ion is still pretending.<br />
I don't think that we can pretend anymore in any form.<br />
We will go into the world independent or we will not<br />
succeed, we will go by our own efforts because there is<br />
no one else to help us, we will fulfil our own visions<br />
because no one is going to lend us theirs.<br />
We have always been ambivalent about who we are. Robert<br />
Menzies of course resolved the dilemma by saying wie we<br />
like a child that is we were not so much two people at<br />
once as one caught between childhood and adulthood.<br />
He imagined us in our relationship wi:: thBri4, tain as being<br />
like a youth returning to its mother, the old family as<br />
if back from a spell at Timbertop, or jackerooing.<br />
Hudson uses a similar metaphor but puts a different spin<br />
on it.<br />
When Britain formalised her withdrawal into Europe, he<br />
says, Australians " felt bereft and betrayed".<br />
Australia was like an adult son having affairs<br />
( economically with Japan and militarily with the<br />
United States) but still living at home and, worse<br />
than kicking him out of the old home, mother was<br />
moving house and not taking him with her. </p>
<p>In the 1990s without the slightest disrespect to a<br />
country for which I have the greatest admiration, and to<br />
whose language and institutions I am a very grateful<br />
heir, I want to see us leave home.<br />
Of course, we do not remain there in any substantial<br />
material way but we are there emblematically and to a<br />
degree psychologically, and it would be much better for<br />
us in the real world that we now inhabit if we removed<br />
the emblems and excised the doubts.<br />
We need very badly that spirit of independence and faith<br />
in ourselves which will enable us to shape a role for<br />
ourselves in the region and the world.<br />
I mean a faith that is deeper than the mix of chauvinism<br />
and expediency which has tended to shape our political<br />
culture: and a degree of confidence which will allow an<br />
image of us to form that is both more helpful and much<br />
closer to the truth than the lingering stero-types of<br />
gormless men, and shrimps and barbecues.<br />
In this connection I might tell you that yesterday I<br />
presented Australia's Second Report to the Chair of the<br />
UN Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination Against<br />
Women. The Chair, Mrs Mervat Tallawy, pointed out that, in<br />
legislation to protect and improve the status of women,<br />
Australia was a model for the rest of the-wo'rld,-<br />
surpassed by none, and equalled perhaps only by the<br />
Scandinavian countries.<br />
Nowhere in the image we present to the rest of the world<br />
nor, I suspect, in our self-image is there a<br />
reflection of that fact.<br />
It would do us good if Australians did know that, and if<br />
the rest of the world knew it.<br />
It would do us good psychologically.<br />
And because we have learned things in getting there and<br />
so have skills and experience which other countries need<br />
it would do us good materially.<br />
I think our ignorance of these things comes from that<br />
same abdication of responsibility for our own destiny,<br />
and our own history.<br />
Let me quote another historian, Professor Stuart<br />
Maclntyre of Melbourne University, who said recently: </p>
<p>Australian history lacks a civic dimension that<br />
would record how it established its forms of selfgovernment<br />
and the values for which the polity<br />
stands. Just as a survey revealed that more<br />
Australian schoolchildren knew of the Constitution<br />
of the United States of America than the<br />
constitution of their own country, so Washington and<br />
Martin Luther King are more celebrated figures than<br />
Wentworth and Catherine Helen Spence. Our interest<br />
in the past is an interest in family history but not<br />
civic history.<br />
How else could we consider removing Caroline Chisholm<br />
from our currency the most signif1fit woman of our<br />
colonial history, and one engaged in the most significant<br />
phenomenon of aiL our history immigration.<br />
The fact is that for a very long while the focus of our<br />
historical interest was not our own history.<br />
In the age of multicultural Australia we have not by any<br />
means entirely replaced the old sentiments with<br />
unequivocally Australian ones.<br />
Indeed, in a sense, multiculturalism combined with the<br />
lingering Britishness of the place to circumvent the<br />
emergence of a singularly Australian identity to replace<br />
the old imperial one.<br />
As Professor Maclntrye says, " at the very moment when<br />
Australia asserted a more forward-looking and pluralist<br />
identity, the public culture lapsed into inarticulacy."<br />
Again, it seems to me, the questions of identity, image<br />
and our place in the world are linked.<br />
We have very rapidly transformed ourselves from a<br />
notoriously xenophobic and insular society to one which<br />
has the beginnings of a reputation for its remarkably<br />
successful multicultural experiment.<br />
But that success does not form a significant part of our<br />
image abroad, and we do not take much pride in it here.<br />
Nor do we take sufficient advantage of the skills,<br />
experience and cultural insight which our multicultural<br />
population offers us in international business.<br />
The Japanese will tell us that their success is built on<br />
their uniquely monocultural society.<br />
The fact that we can't do that should not concern us<br />
the United States achieved phenomenal success from a<br />
multitude of cultures.<br />
I believe we can too. </p>
<p>But I think we have to make clear that our belief in<br />
liberty, tolerance, equity and the encouragement of<br />
ethnic diversity in no way compromises our expectation<br />
that the first loyalty of all who make their home here<br />
will be to Australia.<br />
In the 1990s I think we should make it clear.<br />
As a simple step in that direction, I believe the Oath of<br />
Allegiance sworn by new citizens at naturalisation<br />
ceremonies should proclaim unequivocally their loyalty to<br />
Australia and the things we believe Australia stands for<br />
including liberty, tolerance, social justice those<br />
very beliefs which underpin multiculturalism.<br />
As Professor Maclntrye says, there is at present " no<br />
doctrine of citizenship.. The new citizen swears an oath<br />
to abide by the laws of her or his new state, but these<br />
laws are not spelt out, nor is there any elaboration of<br />
their guiding principles or the ethos they encompass."<br />
My own feeling is that the truth about us is more<br />
profound than we are accustomed to admit.<br />
We are still very often described as a place which is<br />
" 1new" or " young". But Australia is n= young.<br />
The truth about the continent is that it is the oldest in<br />
the world and the continent shapes our culture.<br />
The truth about the Australians who were here before 1788<br />
is that they lived in the oldest continuous civilisation<br />
in the world and they have shaped our culture.<br />
The truth about the people who have come here since is<br />
that they brought cultures as old as Europe's, Asia's,<br />
the Middle East's.<br />
The truth about Australian democracy is that there are<br />
few older.<br />
The truth about the first few years of our nationhood-is<br />
that we were in the vanguard of social and democratic<br />
progress. Just as it is true that we are once more.<br />
We are a mature social democracy in need of more<br />
direction and cohesion than we have so far had, and more<br />
confidence than we have presently but mature and robust<br />
nonetheless. A mature social democracy, ladies and gentlemen, with a<br />
remarkably active publishing industry and literary<br />
culture. </p>
<p>7<br />
A mature social democracy in which the people read books.<br />
And involve themselves in the arts to an extent at least<br />
equivalent to other cultures. And seek to make civilised<br />
lives. And think and invent.<br />
And they write books they win Nobel, Booker, Pulitzer<br />
and other international prizes.<br />
They win Au tralfan prizes. Many Australian prizes.<br />
I wonder if any other country has more literary prizes.<br />
Increasingly they have an international profile in the UK<br />
and the USA.<br />
I hope that increasingly they will be read in Asia that<br />
this book fair will mark a turning point in the<br />
internationalisation of our cultural industries, and that<br />
the book world will do all it can to develop export<br />
markets in our region.<br />
I cannot stress too much how important that task is.<br />
That answer to our biggest contemporary problem<br />
unemployment the answers about our economic future, are<br />
bound to our success in Asia.<br />
And our success there, like our success at home, is bound<br />
I believe to many of the issues I have talked about<br />
tonight. Books already play a vital role in carrying the message<br />
of who we are: the message that this is a culture of<br />
imagination and sophistication.<br />
It is also a culture like the nation itself of vast<br />
unrealised potential.<br />
No industry will play a more significant role in<br />
realising it than the publishing industry.<br />
None will do more to shape and project our identity.<br />
I hope that tonight I have made reasonably clear why I<br />
think this task is so very important.<br />
So I congratulate the industry for this week's great<br />
convention. I also congratulate all those who have been short-listed<br />
for these awards and, of course, all those who have<br />
won.<br />
And I thank you very much for giving me the opportunity<br />
to speak.<br />
a I </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
