<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6797</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH &#039;MOLLY&#039; MELDRUM, COUNTDOWN, BROADCAST 1 DECEMBER 1985</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/12/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006797.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
lA U STALIA(~<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
Transcript of interview with " Molly" Meidrum Countdown<br />
broadcast 1/ 12/ 85<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke it was almost a year ago that we launched<br />
International Youth Year and you said then that the Government<br />
would concentrate on youth throughout 85. You also said that, in<br />
the Address to the Nation earlier this year. The promises have<br />
now come with Priority One. Can you explain first of all what<br />
Priority One really is all about, how it came about?<br />
PM: It's about young people. And it came out of our acceptance<br />
of our responsibility towards the young people of Australia, and<br />
particularly in International Youth Year. We didn't want to just<br />
do something in 85, have a splash and forget it. Priority one is<br />
calculated to address the problems of young people in 85, 86 and<br />
beyond because they are the greatest asset of this country. So<br />
we are talking about education, employment and training. Other<br />
things as well but esentially those things so that we're going to<br />
be able as a country Molly, to get our resources properly<br />
organised in a way which is going to help the young people of<br />
this country.<br />
JOURNALIST: You've often referred to the problems you're aware<br />
are facing you. You're now giving them a chance and this is the<br />
Priority one pamphlet where you in fact pick this up in cinemas<br />
at the CES and just different places. And make sure you pick up<br />
one of these. You're giving the chance now for the Government<br />
and personally yourself, for the next week or so, for the youth<br />
to air their views, grievances and for what?<br />
PM: Well that's right because we accept a responsibility as the<br />
Government Molly, to work out these programs in a way which we<br />
think are going to help to meet the problems of young people.<br />
But . it's always been my view, because I'm closely associated with<br />
young people, that they don't want to have things just shoved<br />
down their neck. We oldies working out what their problems are<br />
and telling them how they should be solved, so we've accepted<br />
our responsibility of getting the thing going, but the purpose of<br />
the phone-in and my talkback appearances is for me to listen,<br />
basically to listen to young people. There'll be many, many<br />
phone calls not just the ones I've got to take personally.<br />
They'll be computerised and so as well as me getting directly<br />
from the calls I take the views of young people, we'll also have<br />
a profile then built up out of the computerised bank of phone<br />
calls and the expression of views, so that we'll be able to make<br />
a judgment about two things: one, what. are the young people<br />
themselves saying about their problems. What sorts of things<br />
that ought to be done. And secondly, therefore, are there some<br />
modifications in the approach that we're adopting to take account<br />
of the views of the young. </p>
<p>I. 2/<br />
JOURNALIST: Well obviously there's many. You see them all the.<br />
time, you've touched on unemployed and many issues of<br />
unemployment that have by-products. You're making yourself<br />
available on radio stations right around the country Adelaide<br />
SAFM, Perth 6PM, Brisbane FMlO4, Wollongong 200, Newcastle 2NX,<br />
Sydney 2MMM and Melbourne EFM and Hobart 7H0, within that time of<br />
being able to talk to them what, obviously you're leaving<br />
yourself quite open in the sense that you get a multitude of<br />
calls, I mean cranks and whatever, how will that bank of<br />
information be sorted out and get back to the Government?<br />
PM: It's a highly computerised -operation. It's mind-boggling<br />
the capacity that's now available with this new technology. It<br />
will mean that all the material that comes from those tens of<br />
thousands of calls that we expect to get will be computerised<br />
into topics so that we will be able to see, as I say have a<br />
profile of the thoughts of the young people of Australia. And<br />
then we will, as a government, study those views as I say make<br />
sure that we're on the right sort of track. If there are some<br />
variations in what we're doing, which seems sensible as a result<br />
of that, then we're prepared to adapt. What I want for the young<br />
people of Australia to understand is that we're concerned about<br />
helping them. We're not doing that from the point of view of<br />
saying look we know what your problems are, we know what the<br />
answers are. You better than anybody than anyone know what your<br />
own problems, your own concerns, your own aspirations are, how<br />
can we adapt and adjust and work together.<br />
JOURNALIST: Right well as I say we've now launched Priority one<br />
it's something that's not just going to be over now to Christmas.<br />
It's going to be a continuing thing, as you said, that can go for<br />
the next two or three years until something perhaps is sorted<br />
out. I might also add Sydney are very lucky in the essence that<br />
they have this great concert coming up and that's on 8 December,<br />
Sunday at the Domain. In fact you'll be attending that as well,<br />
to open that particular concert. Thanks very much. I think it<br />
does give a lot of hope. As I say please pick up one of these<br />
pamphlets when you see them at the CES offices or at cinemas and<br />
it gives you all the information that needs to be told and gives<br />
you I think a lot of heart, once they read this. The last thing<br />
you've given me some good news and I'd like you to say it because<br />
it's just blown me out when you told me before.<br />
PM: Well it's relevant to what we've been talking about, that is<br />
the inspiration, the views, the attitudes, the thoughts of the<br />
young people. I think one of the outstanding events of this year<br />
has been Bob Geldof's inspiration to the world and your very<br />
important part in it here in 0z for Africa. And Bob came to see<br />
me here in this office just a few weeks ago and he said to me<br />
directly the sorts of things he hoped we might be able to do.<br />
And one suggestion he made was could we help with aircraft for<br />
the distribution of famine relief in Africa. So I thought about<br />
it, so what I've decided is we'll make two hercules aircraft<br />
available. They'll need to be refitted, put into operational<br />
form and we'll fly them to Africa. That will cost about $ 1.7<br />
million. I've got that underway now and those two aircraft will<br />
be in Africa and operational by February of next year. And we're<br />
pleased that we've been able, in that way'to respond to the<br />
magnificent initiative of Geldof internationally and you and the<br />
young people of Australia.<br />
JOURNALIST: Well I think that's the greatest news I've heard. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
