<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6954</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW ON ABC 7.30 REPORT - 11 JUNE 1986</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/06/1986</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006954.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW ON ABC 7.30 REPORT 11 JUNE 1986<br />
GOWARD: Mr Hawke, thank you very much for joining us this<br />
evening. PM: My pleasure Pru.<br />
GOWARD: How quickly do you believe your policy outline tonight<br />
will start correcting our balance of payment difficulties and<br />
heading us away from bananahood.<br />
PM: I think that in many respects it can start immediately if<br />
the Australian people, as I believe they will, respond with the<br />
changes of attitudes that you rightly referred to Pru, then that<br />
starts to have its impact. As to when you see it in the<br />
statistics, of course, that is further down the track. But what I<br />
am trying to say is we have got both an immediate problem and, in<br />
what I am saying about wages and so on that is addressed to those<br />
immediate problems, we have got the longer term problem and<br />
challenge which we can meet of realising that we have got to<br />
broaden our export base. Now as I said..<br />
GOWARD: Have we got time?<br />
PM: We have got as much time in a sense as we give ourselves. If<br />
we accept the challenge immediately and the world sees that we<br />
are accepting the challenge then the reactions will be right.<br />
GOWARD: Would you say that your speech will be welcomed by<br />
international finance markets?<br />
PM: I don't know, but let me say this Pru, I think what I have<br />
done is to make it clear that we'll do everything within our<br />
direct power to create the best macro-economic environment. We<br />
want a lower wages outcome. We are, as Governments, going to<br />
exercise very severe budgetary restraint. So I think if they look<br />
dispassionately at what I have said they will say yes, well, this<br />
Government, and I think the people of Australia, are dinkum in<br />
the right areas.<br />
GOWARD: Is your speech weighted against wage earners, salary<br />
earners, and perhaps a little bit too, employers?<br />
PM: No, it is not weighted against them. I mean the fact is that<br />
wage and salary earners constitute b far the greatest proportion </p>
<p>of our national income and our national expenditure therefore you<br />
have got to talk about them. But if we are going to get the<br />
co-operation of the wage and salary earners business has a<br />
corresponding responsibility. In three areas particularly, i.,<br />
their pricing policy, their own remuneration policies, and<br />
in investment policies.<br />
GOWARD: Well, your speech tonight had Simon Crean reacting<br />
already, and we will come to him in a moment, that the unions had<br />
already done their bit in terms of wage restraint. Do you believe<br />
they can be made to accept any more?<br />
PM: Well let me go to the first point. The trade unions have<br />
exercised considerable restraint. The outcome in 1985 in wages<br />
was 6% against 5.5% of the OECD our major trading partners.<br />
That was good. Certainly if you hadn't had a centralised wage<br />
fixing system with which they co-operated the wages outcome would<br />
have been much more. Now as to the future part of your question<br />
Pru, the actual decisions as to what the wage outcome should be<br />
must be made under our system by the Arbitration Commission. I<br />
believe the trade union movement will co-operate with the<br />
decisions of the Commission.<br />
GOWARD: Would you be prepared to forgo the Accord if they<br />
weren't prepared to co-operate?<br />
PM: I don't want to forgo the Accord. As Prime Minister I have a<br />
responsibility in this country to make the decisions which are<br />
necessary. As we see it, looking at the economic situation, we<br />
need a further discount in the next case. That's what we will be<br />
putting to the Commission.<br />
GOWARD: You don't want to forgo the Accord?<br />
PM: No I don't want to forgo the Accord.<br />
GOWARD: You seem to be suggesting in the national interest you<br />
would accept that you might have to.<br />
PM: No, I don't think it will happen because I do believe Pru,<br />
that the trade unions will say well, we want to see what the<br />
outcome of this wages case is. And I think they will abide by<br />
that decision and then face up to the realities whatever they are<br />
when we come to the next case which will be the end of this year.<br />
But there should be no further decision before the 1st of January<br />
1987. </p>
<p>GOWARD: Now back to you Mr Hawke, I suppose you heard all of<br />
that. Are you encouraged by Simon Crean?<br />
PM: Well I think that Simon has said the Accord is still alive.<br />
He recognises the right under the Accord of the Government to put<br />
its position. We'll be putting that position. I think that the<br />
rank and file of the trade union movement are going to give<br />
support to responsible leadership because it is my firm belief<br />
that the ordinary rank and file trade unionist, that's the<br />
ordinary Australia, knows that we have a challenge and will want<br />
to respond to it.<br />
GOWARD: I also asked Mr Crean about the dole, the young people,<br />
and making people work for it. He, like a lot of us, is a little<br />
bit puzzled by what you mean. Would you like to expand on it.<br />
Does it mean having to work for the dole.<br />
PM: What it means is this, I have had the opportunity Pru, of<br />
talking intimately with large numbers of young people in<br />
Australia now. I did that during the Priority One campaign.<br />
Almost universally the young people told me that they wanted to<br />
do something for the benefit. I'm terribly encouraged by that.<br />
Correspondingly, I think, the community wants to see something<br />
done. So what we're going to be about, this is not trying to<br />
impose something upon a reluctant unemployed constituency, what<br />
it is is co-operating with a constituency that wants to do<br />
something. In talking with the voluntary organisations, the<br />
State and local governments and the trade unions, I'm sure we're<br />
going to be able to create a situation of a fairly large number<br />
of worthwhile community activities which will involve the<br />
opportunity for young people to do something for the community<br />
for the benefit they get.<br />
GOWARD: And if they choose not to do they lose the dole?<br />
PM: Well that situation doesn't arise. At this stage, and later<br />
on, if you had a position where the community saw that you had<br />
large numbers of people who just didn't want to do anything, then<br />
I think the community would want to address that, but that's<br />
entirely hypothetical. We've got to understand those unemployed<br />
people the overwhelming majority, there are some you might call<br />
bludgers, but the overwhelming majority of those kids and the<br />
unemployed out there want to do something. We want to help them.<br />
GOWARD: Mr white, just finally, referred to some disappointment<br />
with your package. He felt that we were a bit soft on work<br />
practices in Australia?<br />
PM: well he referred to soft on the productivity case. Bob I<br />
hope you're still watching. Remember I said a prolongation of<br />
this over two years, now if as a community, including you in the<br />
business community you've got a great responsibility don't put<br />
it all on the trade union movement management in this country<br />
has got to get off its butt in a lot of areas and invest and use<br />
its entrepreneurial spirit as so many of you are doing. The rest </p>
<p>4<br />
of you have got to do it too. Now if together, over those two<br />
years, we lift our productivity performance we'll be able to<br />
absorb this productivity superannuation decision, which I hope<br />
will come within the context of a significant improvement in our<br />
own productivity performance.<br />
GOWARD: Mr Hawke, thank you very much for your time.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
