<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2084</transcript-id>
    <title>PRESS STATEMENT: MOTOR VEHICLE AIR POLLUTION</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/07/1969</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002084.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS STATEMENT MOTOR VEHIICLE AIR POLLUTION JOJU<br />
( Statement by Ministers)<br />
State and Commonwealth Transport Ministers meeting in<br />
Port Moresby as the Australian Transport Advisory Council today<br />
( July 10) discussed the establishment of' standards to control<br />
motor vehicle exhaust pollution in Australia,<br />
The Council directed its Standing Committee of Advisers<br />
to discuss with the automotive and petroleum industries the<br />
introduction of' U. S. standards on exhaust emissions. The<br />
Committee hopes to arrange a meeting with industry early in<br />
September. It will report back as a matter of urgency to ATAC at<br />
its next meeting in about six months.<br />
The report will cover:<br />
* Recommended uniform exhaust control standards;<br />
* Approved devices to be fitted to motor vehicles<br />
to reduce exhaust emissions;<br />
oRecommended date of application of the standards.<br />
Ministers studied a comprehensive dossier covering<br />
air pollution from all modes of transport prepared by South<br />
Australian officials at the request of Council.<br />
The Queensland Minister, Mr W. Knox, suggested maximum<br />
permissible levels for chemical emissions from motor vehicle<br />
exhausts which his Government is considering implementing.<br />
Ministers were anxious to obtain the best achievable<br />
emission control standards so as to effectively combat the<br />
public health problem of air pollution. </p>
<p>2.<br />
It is estimated that the various transport modes<br />
mainly the motor vehicle can under certain circumstances and<br />
in some Australian cities contribute about 64 per cent of<br />
atmospheric pollution in Australia.<br />
The Standing Committee of Advisers would also discuss<br />
with the petroleum industry developments in reducing the<br />
contaminants in motor fuels,<br />
Following a previous decision of ATAC, all States have<br />
taken action to require manufacturers to fit devices to new<br />
motor vehicles designed to prevent the discharge of crankcase<br />
gases into the atmosphere.<br />
PORT MORESBY, ToP. N. G.<br />
CANBERRA, A. C. T. 10 JULY 1970 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
