<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>321</transcript-id>
    <title>CITIZENS&#039; LUNCHEON, ASHFIELD TOWN HALL - 15TH MAY 1961 - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R G MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/05/1961</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000321_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CITIZENS' LUNCHEONS ASTH'IELD TOWN HALL<br />
MAY, 1.961<br />
Speech byv the Prime Minister, the Rt. Hon. R. G. Menz--LSir<br />
and gentlemen: I have been suffering this morning from a sort of-I<br />
think I am right when I describe it as a sort of undulant fever.<br />
Is that right? When the temperature goes up; and then goes<br />
down? Because my good friend and colleague, Fred Osborne,<br />
originally inveigled me into this matter, and that depressed me.<br />
Then he said to me, " Of course you understand that they are not<br />
all political fans of yours who will be there". I said, " Oh,<br />
no, I know that", So he said, " Make a non-political speech".<br />
And I said, " Do you mean by that, Fred, a non-Party speech?" He<br />
said, " That's right". So that depressed me still further.<br />
But then, by a singular stroke of genius on the part<br />
of somebody, just as I was to come in here, I saw Tommy Androws,<br />
Look at him! Tommy Androws! And as I am the greatest living<br />
hopelessly incompetent cr~ icket lover in this country, I greeted<br />
him like a man and a brother. And that cheered me up. Tommy<br />
I must say that if I manage to say something worth listening t<br />
today, you may take the credit.<br />
I thought perhaps I might say something to you in a<br />
genuinely non-Party way, about the business of Government,<br />
because you are, for the most part, business men. I am<br />
perfectly certain that in your more inaccurate moments you<br />
criticise the Governme-int, and criticise politicians, and say<br />
it's a great pity more businessmen are not in politics and<br />
course I agree with that. The trouble is they won't come. An.<br />
you say there ought to be more business in Governm,, ent, and, I<br />
think that highly original phrase goes on, less Government in<br />
business. Well I an familiar with all those things. Man and<br />
boy now I've been in Parliarment of one kind or another for 33<br />
years. The Mayor and I are contemporaries, I think he said.<br />
Thirtythree years! He's a bit inclined to complain because he's<br />
been an Alderman, treated rather badly, and he thinks that I am<br />
a silver-tail because Itve been for l years or so, in total, a<br />
Prime Minister. But 33 years, man and boy, we've been engaged<br />
in it. I know most of the noises people make about us, and<br />
about the business of Governrment.<br />
I just want to say this to you: The business of<br />
Government is not only the greatest business in the country, but<br />
it is, I think, the most difficult business in the country. It<br />
is extraordinarily difficult. I amn able to make a complarison,<br />
because, believe it or not, it is now 21 years since I was<br />
first sworn in as a Prime Minister. In these days I well<br />
remember the kind of problem that fell on to the table. The<br />
nizmber of problems has quadrupled in that time. I well remember<br />
thie amount of paper one had to read, the number of actual<br />
decisions that had to be taken. Today all those things have<br />
quadrupled. Wge have all around the world, diplomatic posts.<br />
We have to instruct Zhem and be instructed by them. I suppose<br />
it is pretty safe to say that I would read 100 to 150 cables in<br />
the course of one day and a great number of them pretty longwinded<br />
because, thanks to the pe~ rson who invented stenography,<br />
people dictate cables now. If they had to write them by hand<br />
they would be much shorter and Much more readable. You have<br />
masses of things ee-r-ing up fronm the various departments; you<br />
have ministers to interview; you have to give a nudge at the<br />
appropriate time in the direction of a particular decision on a </p>
<p>particular matter. And above all things you must keep<br />
yourself informed, because it is a changing world, and it is a<br />
world that can't be coped with even from here in Australia<br />
without irmmense study and concentration. I would have hopelessly<br />
collapsed under this job if I hadn't earlier in life<br />
acquired the habit of concentrated work, and close stu of<br />
particular problems. Therefore I assure you that this .5 a<br />
very difficult business.<br />
It is frequently a very technical business. There<br />
are all sorts of things that one has to consider. You can't<br />
deal with the economic policy of a country without having<br />
acquired laboriously over years, a knowledge of economic matters<br />
a knowledge of financial matters. There is a mass of<br />
technique that underlies the easy and platitudinous<br />
observations that you expect politicians to make to you.<br />
Of course all this demonstrates that it is a<br />
business that can't be learned over night. Now I wish I could<br />
persuade everybody that that was true. The older I got, the<br />
more experience I have, the more I know, because I must know by<br />
this time a great deal about these things, the less dogiatic do<br />
I become, the less certain am I that my voice is the last voice<br />
of authority. But you produce to me some fellow who is in the<br />
way of airing his mind on these matters and who knows nothing<br />
about it at all, he knows all the answers. You can read him<br />
frequently, day by day. The less you know, the more certain you<br />
are that you are right.<br />
Now there is another aspect of the matter that I wan<br />
to say something to you about. I wonder to how many of us th<br />
business of politics is an emotional business. There are a 1<br />
of people who write and speak, who convert everything into tc:<br />
of emotion. If I am discussing somewhere in Parliament the<br />
question of the level of social services, for example, there i.<br />
bound to be some hearty emotionalist who will say, " How would<br />
you like to live on a week?" And of course I wouldn't.<br />
That seems to me to have nothing whatever to do with the case.<br />
This is an eimotional argument. It is easy to whip up emotions.<br />
I toll you that on any great problem that arises, whether it is<br />
the position of South Africa or whether it is the position of<br />
some social service or whether it is something else entirely<br />
unrelated to both, the easiest thing in the world, and the<br />
quickest thing, is to be emotional. I don't think that I am a<br />
stranger to emotion because I have a great number. But it is a<br />
very great mistake to think that because a man has a cool head<br />
he's cold-blooded. The two things are entirely different. I<br />
hate cold-blooded people. But I like to hqve people around me<br />
who have cool heads. Because cool heads and good judgment are<br />
needed in the management of your public affairs, more than<br />
perhaps anything else. So I say to you, distrust the easy<br />
rather cheap emotional reaction. We all have it. It isn't to<br />
be supposed that we are not human beings. Of course we all<br />
have it. But when you have responsibility you must exorcise a<br />
cool balanced jud: ement, because that is, after all, what you<br />
owe to the people of your country.<br />
Now, Sir, may I turn from that to say somethin%, about<br />
our attitudes to Government? These are perhaps a few cautionary<br />
observations which a Prime Minister of any political party could<br />
make to you, if he had had a lot of experience in these things.<br />
First of all Australia has now, as a result of great<br />
efforts by Australians in two wars, and as a result of a growing<br />
enlightenment in our own country about the rist of the world,<br />
become internationally significant. I suppose that it's very<br />
sel~ om that a few weeks may go by without I nyself being in </p>
<p>communica. tion in a direct sense with the Governr. ent of the<br />
United States or the Goverm. ont of New Zealand, or the Government<br />
of the United Kingdom. Fortunately I know all these men<br />
now extremely well and we exchange our ideas with considerable<br />
point and with complete frankness. I like to believe, :. nd I<br />
think I am right in believing that Australia has a sir ficance<br />
in the world of affairs rather more than the population of our<br />
country would warrant. We are regarded, increasingly, as a<br />
notable country, as a happy country as a country with an<br />
immense future, and as a country made up of people who have<br />
good common sense . and courage. These are good things to have<br />
thought about our country around the world.<br />
The result of all this is that from time to time an<br />
Australian Government through its Prime Minister, or through<br />
somebody, will offer an opinion on what goes on in the world.<br />
It may be necessary to offer a public opinion on some problem in<br />
some other country. I have done it myself a few times. And<br />
the moment a Prime Minister does it he will be told " You mustn't<br />
say that there's some other country that won't agree with you.<br />
Now you mustn't do that you'll be misunderstood, here or here<br />
or here". Gentlemen, this is an absurdity. Never offer an<br />
opinion unless it is well considered; never offer an opinion<br />
gratuitously, as if you wanted to blow your bags out and tell<br />
the world how clever you are. But when you find yourself<br />
called upon to offer a view on behalf of Australia, don't fall<br />
into a state of terror because somebody, or some other country,<br />
disagrees with it. If you didn't believe in your own view it<br />
would be idle to state it. If you do believe in it, it's<br />
pathetic to run away from it because somebody else, somewhere<br />
else, doesn't accept it. That's the thing, that's one of thr<br />
elements of maturity in our country which I believe we have K:<br />
hang on to. You know there are a lot of people around the world<br />
who talk about the ' colonial powers' and the ' colonial<br />
attitude' of mind. There may be a few people left in Australia<br />
who still think that the great problems of the world can be<br />
safely left to other people. It's not true. Of course we must<br />
have groeat friends; and occasionally we must subordinate our<br />
views to the views of our great friends if we are to ensure the<br />
security of our own country. But these things are well<br />
understood by statesmen. The real point is that we are an<br />
adult country, far more adult, far wiser in judgment, though I<br />
say it myself, than some countries with many times our<br />
population. And we must have in relation to these matters, a<br />
decent pride for this is a remarkably great country.<br />
I an not one of those people who believes that we<br />
ought to go on as if we had a hundred million peopla as if wea<br />
were a second United States of America, but I do want to<br />
emphasise to you that we are so addicted, still, to the o.<br />
knocking our own country and our own people that we occasionally<br />
forget that this is, man for r. man, a great country, with a great<br />
place in the world, and a great future.<br />
Now, Sir, having said that may I refer to another<br />
aspect of our relations to Government? Every now and<br />
somebody comes to see me under the simple illusion that in ry<br />
official capacity of course, control unlimited supplies of<br />
something fascinating about money, particularly if you haven:<br />
got it. And people come along, " Well now this is a thing, all<br />
we need is œ 0,000, all wo need is half a million, all we need<br />
is I've had all the vriants of this even in the last<br />
few weeks. And they say, " Now the Cormmonwealth can provide all<br />
this money. What about it?" If you show some reluctance, it<br />
you are a little coy about ante-ing up œ Xmr, the assumption is </p>
<p>that you are an insensitive character, you are a cold-blooded<br />
fellow, you don't understand the real needs of the case,<br />
because if you did, of course, you would just find the money,<br />
It would oms out of some magnificent cornucopia, just flowing<br />
out. Thoerfore I want to renind you, if you need to be<br />
reminded gentlenen, that Governments are not proprietors of<br />
money. Al the money I have wouldn't solve the problem of the<br />
smallest municipality in the bush. Governments are not the<br />
proprietors of money; they are the trustees for the money<br />
that ordinary citizens earn and pay to them. That's their<br />
position. Easy enough for a Government to say, handsomely,<br />
" Right œ 50m; that's no trouble". But the people will find<br />
the This is the basic element of Government that<br />
Governments don't have any money of their own. They borrow<br />
money from the people, or they tax money from the people; and<br />
whatever money they get in these various ways they are able to<br />
spend according to their jadgment. We must never forget that.<br />
ll the money that a Government has to deal with is money that<br />
has been worked for and earned by private citizens and<br />
transferred by them to the Government in order to give effect to<br />
the Government's policy.<br />
Therefore, if, as private citizens and we all are<br />
we want more from Governments than we get today then there must<br />
be more of us at work, we must perhaps work a little more<br />
successfuly we must certainly produce considerably more. The<br />
greatest illusion in the wjrld is to think that the standard of<br />
living is a monetary standard whereas in fact the standard of<br />
living is what a man has by way : f a house, by way of shelt('-,<br />
by way of food, by way of the amenities of life. These are cK!.<br />
material things I'm now talking about the material standards<br />
of life. And they all have to be produced by somebody.<br />
I say to you, therefore, that in addition to having<br />
some pride in our own country, we must not place upon Governnents<br />
demands which jointly we are not prepared to place on<br />
ourselves. Because you are the Government. If you add up all<br />
the people in Australia who work and produce and pay, they are<br />
the Government, they are the creators of the available<br />
resources of the nation. I don't need to tell you that if a<br />
Government pretends to pay us as individuals more, and carries<br />
out the pretence of inflating the currency it's just giving with<br />
one hand and taking away with the other.<br />
And yet, Sir, the odd thing about political life and<br />
I say this quite dogmatically is that though inflation is<br />
unpopular with many people, not by any means with all people<br />
for there are some who have a vested interest in inflation,<br />
measures against inflation are always even more unpopular..<br />
Because you can't restrain inflation, you can't push down<br />
inflation without imposing some immediate disability on -ohn<br />
Brown, or Ton Smith I hope neither of then is here which hc<br />
will resent and say " Why deal with me, why am I the follow to<br />
be affected?" You can't have any policy, no Government can have<br />
any policy, which is designed to produce some stability I. the<br />
currency a firm foundation for future expansion unlc:<br />
time to tine it takes measures calculated to produce ti; ar<br />
result. Now, Sir, the next point that I want to mention is<br />
this. We talk a good deal about democracy and I'm a groat<br />
believer in democracy. Democracy is the only system of<br />
Government so far in the world that has operated with over..<br />
shadow of social justice. Pople can be very superior about . to<br />
They may say how ridiculous that every man's vote should be oi </p>
<p>the same value when men are so infinitely varied. True enough,<br />
perhaps. But I want to see a better system. The world hasn't<br />
yet produced it.<br />
The truth is that the great glory of democracy is<br />
that it does pay attention to the individual person. The<br />
authoritarian systems that exist in other countries tend to<br />
reduce the individual to a mere cipher to a more calculating<br />
medium in a blue book, or a statisticai record. But in<br />
democracy it is the man and the woman who count. The business<br />
of Goverrnent is to promote them, to enlarge their opportunities,<br />
to broaden their borizons, to develop their personalities.<br />
But when we have said that, I believe we must<br />
remember that the point of democracy is not just that everybody<br />
has a vote that's the mechanics of democracy, that's not the<br />
essence of democracy. The essence of democracy is that every<br />
individual, and he may express it through the vote from time to<br />
time, has his own responsibilities, and because he has his own<br />
responsibilities he has his own unalterable rights. This could<br />
not be said about any other system of Government in the world.<br />
If, occasionally, I think that I detect in our own<br />
democracy a weakness it is simply that I think that occasionally<br />
do you agree? we think too much of our rights, and too<br />
little of our responsibilities. Because if we think of our<br />
rights only, of our demands only, of our claims on Government<br />
only, then we will transfer the responsibility for meeting those<br />
claims to a smaller and smaller body of men; until ultimately,<br />
we'll find that we have brought about a system of oligarchy or<br />
bureaucracy, or even of autocracy, because the responsibilit7<br />
has been piled on to other people while we ourselves assert ou. r<br />
rights. Now, Sir, finally I would like to say this to you. I<br />
have just said something about responsibilities. We don't have<br />
responsibilities only to ourselves, or to our own country.<br />
Here's something quite remarkable that is going on in the world.<br />
We are, in a broad sense, aware of it; we have, in a true<br />
sense done something about it as a nation. But in 1950, which<br />
is not long ago, there were 2,500 million people in the world<br />
2,500 millions. In 1975, in the absence of unprecedented<br />
pestilence or ruinous war , or some disaster on which we can't<br />
predicate any views of ours, in 1975 other things being equal,<br />
there will be not 2,500 millions, there will be 3,800 millions<br />
1,300 million more people at the end of a period of 25 years,<br />
And by 2,000, again predicating the same conditions, it is<br />
estimated that there will be 6,000 million people in the world.<br />
Now here are we, in 1961, half way through that first span so<br />
let us assume that we have perhaps a little over 3,000 million<br />
people in the world today. Double that in the year 2 000;<br />
double that in the lifetime of many, any hundreds of thousands<br />
of -people now living in Australia.<br />
This is a colossal problem. It is not only a problem<br />
for the people who live in the large countries in the world,<br />
it is a problem for us. Do we, in Australia, contemplating that<br />
by 2000 we might have what? 20 or 25 million peoplet I don't<br />
know remain indifferent to the fact that in Continental China<br />
alone thore will be 1 000 millions at t; he same time? What are<br />
they . oing to live on; What's going t) become of wor. 1M food<br />
production? To feed 3,000 millions more people is a to.-k, a<br />
challenge, a challenge to education, to our Ionorosity of<br />
outlook, to our technical skill, our willingness to cont. i~ bute<br />
so that land now not fertile will produce food for this coming<br />
hungry world. This is a tremendous problem. We do sormethtng<br />
about it through the Colombo Plan. We have a very creditable </p>
<p>4 1-6.<br />
record in technical aid to new countries, under-developed<br />
countries in the training, of their students in ;. ustralia. But<br />
we can't afford to sit back on it, we can't afford to say " How<br />
kind we are, how cltcver we ar". we, as a highly intelligent<br />
and highly qualified cormaunity because we are in world terms<br />
have a responsibility far beyond our numbers on this matter.<br />
If the world as a whole doesn't do something increasingly about<br />
this tremendous, this overshadowing problem1 then I believe<br />
that we can look forward, or our sons can," l all the most<br />
terrible results of a hungry population pressing upon inadequate<br />
resources, with all the threat that it contains of starvation<br />
and pestilence and war as the last desperate expedient.<br />
Thereforo, Sir, I like to foel that when we bask a<br />
little in the satisfaction that we occasionally have in our own<br />
system of Government in our own happinoss, in our own relative<br />
prosperity, though iz may vary a little, a high relative<br />
prosperity, we should recognise that as a rowing nation we have<br />
a significance and a responsibility in the world, and not only<br />
to ourselves. I think that one of the unfortunate things is that all<br />
too few p~ eople study history they think it's a rather<br />
academic matter. History academic? The world would save itself<br />
from an abundance of errors if it knew something about human<br />
history. And we ourselves night g et a more proper understanding<br />
of our opportunities in this world if we recalled a little<br />
history. Because don't let it be forgiotten that in the spacious<br />
days of groat Elizabeth, the first Elizabeth, the days of<br />
Shakespeare and Marlowe and Beaumont and Fletcher, running on<br />
into the time of Francis Bacon, the days of Raleigh and Drake,<br />
the great blossoming period in 13aglish history, a period which<br />
made this little island in the North Sea one of the groat<br />
factors in the world, and in civilisation, at that time the<br />
population of England was probably no more than todayts<br />
population of New S_, uth Wa. les. We forget these things. It<br />
isn't just numbers. It's quality. Give me 10 million people of<br />
quality and they will influence the current of human events, and<br />
human dLestiny, more than 50 million people of poor quality.<br />
This is our ; reat opportunity. Vnd we seize it if<br />
we just take a little time off, occasionally, as I've tried to<br />
take with you today, to consider what our relation is to<br />
Government, not in an or., anised Party sense, but as citizens,<br />
what is our relationship to Government in our own country;<br />
what is our relationship to each other in our own country; and<br />
finally, what is the rolationship of all of us to a world which<br />
will unquestionably bring its prob~ lems to us in due course,<br />
unless we can have made our own contributions to the solving of<br />
those problems, to the well-being of mankind, 6,000 millions of<br />
them, and therefore to the peace of the world. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
