<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7251</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA THE HON. R.J.L. HAWKE, AC, MP THE 1987 SINGAPORE LECTURE &quot; THE CHALLENGE OF CHANCE IN THE ASIA-PACIFIC REGION&quot; SINGAPORE- 27 NOVEMBER 1987</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/11/1987</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007251.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA<br />
THE HON. R. J. L. HAWKE, AC, MP<br />
THE 1987 SINGAPORE LECTURE<br />
* THE CHALLENGE OF CHANGE IN THE ASIA-PACIFIC REGIONE<br />
SINGAPORE 27 NOVEMBER 1987<br />
Mr Prime Minister<br />
Mr Rajaratnam<br />
Professor K. S. Sandhu, Executive Director<br />
of the Institute for South East Asian Studies<br />
I was honored when my friend Mr Rajaratnam extended to me an<br />
invitation to deliver the 1987 Singapore Lecture.<br />
Since its inception in 1980 the Singapore Lecture has been<br />
delivered by a number of distinguished speakers.<br />
This is the first time however that you have invited a<br />
serving head of government to address you, and the first<br />
time you have invited a speaker from within the immediate<br />
Western Pacific region.<br />
That I believe imposes on me a responsibility which I am<br />
happy to accept to outline to you my-own perspective,<br />
based on my involvement in public affairs in Australia, on<br />
the ways in which we as a region might master the principal<br />
challenge facing us.<br />
That challenge is the challenge of change and there can be<br />
few more appropriate venues than Singapore to discuss it.<br />
It is the challenge to anticipate change and to channel it<br />
for constructive ends or, if events are unanticipated, to<br />
have the perspicacity and flexibility to adapt quickly.<br />
It is the challenge to leaders and opinion makers to inform<br />
and guide those affected by change so that the pace and<br />
benefits of change are not impeded by fear or ignorance.<br />
It is the challenge to individuals and societies to be open<br />
to change and to question whether precepts and practices<br />
inherited from the past are still appropriate for today.<br />
In many ways Singapore is a model of the region's increasing<br />
importance in the world economy and a paragon of flexibility<br />
in the face of changing circumstances. CC) 2) </p>
<p>2.<br />
Your economic performance makes you one of the success<br />
stories of our times a story based on hard work and a<br />
capacity to grasp opportunities as they present themselves.<br />
only two years ago, Singapore's long burst of growth came to<br />
an end as the economy slumped into recession. But it is to<br />
the lasting credit of all Singaporeans that you were able to<br />
make the necessary sacrifices and adjustments to your<br />
economy. As a result, the nation is back on the growth path<br />
with the economy predicted to expand by 8 per cent this<br />
year. Although this evening I want to suggest ways in which we can<br />
understand and master change, I say at the outset that, in<br />
the light of that recovery, the people of Singapore, and<br />
their Prime Minister Lee Kuan Yew, need no advice from me<br />
about bouncing back from unexpected adversity.<br />
In talking of the region this evening, I am defining it to<br />
encompass the two superpowers, the United States and the<br />
Soviet Union; the world's most populous country, China; the<br />
economic power-house of Japan; the dynamic so-called NICS;<br />
the countries of ASEAN; the island states of the South<br />
Pacific; Australia and New Zealand; and the other nations of<br />
East and South East Asia.<br />
This region contains the greater part of the world's<br />
population and produces the greater part of the world's GNP.<br />
Its economic growth has been such that in recent years it<br />
has been exporting and importing more across the Pacific<br />
than the older economies trade across the Atlantic. Yet it<br />
still includes societies which have failed to take advantage<br />
of the region's overall prosperity and whose people as a<br />
consequence still live in poverty and hunger.<br />
The region embraces many of the religions and cultural<br />
traditions of the world. If one includes India, it holds<br />
the world's seven largest armies. It encompasses the<br />
principal exponents of free market capitalism and the<br />
principal interpreters of Marxism-Leninism.<br />
The sheer dynamism of the Western Pacific region has led<br />
many commentators to predict the next century will be the<br />
' Pacific Century'.<br />
But before we start counting the rewards that will flow to<br />
us in the Pacific Century, our task must be to ensure that<br />
the prediction actually comes true. V<br />
The fact that things have gone so well for us in the recent<br />
past does not mean they will continue to go well.<br />
We cannot assume, as I think too many observers do, that<br />
because the Japan of the 1950' s and 1960' s is today's<br />
South Korea then, tomorrow, the baton will automatically<br />
pass to other countries here in South East Asia. ' 3 U L ' 3 </p>
<p>3.<br />
And to assume continued political stability and harmony is a<br />
reassuring assumption, and certainly a polite one, but it is<br />
not necessarily one that will stand us in good stead.<br />
I do not want to be misunderstood. The Asia-Pacific region<br />
holds the potential to fulfil its greatest expectations.<br />
But those expectations will only be fulfilled as-the result<br />
of hard work and a clear understanding-of our challenges and<br />
our problems, as well as our potential.<br />
The point must be to identify the pragmatic assumptions on<br />
which our planning should be based and to do so before<br />
problems loom so large they cannot be handled excep-t by<br />
wrenching dislocation.,<br />
The key assumption I believe should be the constructive<br />
power of enlightened self-interest.<br />
What this means is recognising as an enduring fact of human<br />
nature that each of us wishes to advance our own standard<br />
and quality of life and that of those who depend on us.<br />
This does not, I stress, mean responding to the selfish<br />
demands of individual groups. Quite the contrary it means<br />
seeking ways in which individual wishes for self-advancement<br />
can be better advanced through mutual cooperation.<br />
To draw an example from the domestic economy one which has<br />
been repeatedly validated throughout my years as both a<br />
trade union leader and a politician this means overcoming<br />
the traditional antagonisms and rivalries between employer<br />
and employee and winning their cooperation so as to enhance<br />
the interests of both groups through an expansion in the<br />
size of the whole economy.<br />
Achieving this goal requires active involvement in the<br />
decision-making process on the part of those who will be<br />
affected by the decision and of particular importance in<br />
this time of rapid change it requires the sharing of<br />
information relevant to those decisions.<br />
The challenge is always to create a secure and confident<br />
environment within which we can each rely upon, and build<br />
our strategies around, the continuation of cooperative<br />
responses of others.<br />
These prescriptions are valid beyond the Western democratic<br />
tradition of Australia in which I have operated.' I do not<br />
seek to underestimate the differences which exist among the<br />
systems of different nations. But I am convinced that<br />
whatever our system, the bottom line is that successful<br />
change ultimately requires the informed cooperation of those<br />
who will ultimately be charged with implementing it and<br />
those who will be affected by it. </p>
<p>That cooperation is most easily won if the reasons for<br />
change and its costs and benefits are understood and<br />
accepted by the whole community which underlines the need<br />
for a leadership capable of winning that community<br />
understanding and acceptance.<br />
For economic change unaccompanied by the necessary changes<br />
in social attitudes can only be stalled and frustrated, and<br />
the scale of the consequent losses can be enormous.<br />
If fear or ignorance prevail over enlightened self-interest,<br />
the costs can be measured in lower living standards and<br />
poorer life chances, not only for those individuals affected<br />
but for the whole community.<br />
It took the cataclysm of World War II to expose the assumed<br />
verities of the thirties, based as they were on narrow<br />
conceptions of national self-interest, and to fashion the<br />
consensus which led to Bretton Woods, the GATT and the<br />
trade-based growth era of the sixties and pre-oil-shock<br />
seventies. In that case the cost of ignorance and fear was a lost<br />
decade of growth in the thirties and the disaster of World<br />
War II.<br />
The lesson is that we can choose to live dogmatically<br />
entrenched in our old attitudes towards each other or we<br />
can choose to seek areas of cooperation and routes to an era<br />
of growth which is all the more beneficial because it is<br />
mutual. Ladies and gentlemen,<br />
To help us find this path to growth and so ensure that the<br />
Asia Pacific region does in fact fulfil its potential I want<br />
to turn to the trends which I believe will endure as<br />
important influences on us and on our region over the next<br />
quarter century or so.<br />
In embarking on this course, I am fully aware of the dangers<br />
awaiting those who seek to predict the future.<br />
As George Orwell pointed out, it requires a constant<br />
struggle even to see what is in front of one's own nose.<br />
Had an Australian Prime Minister been asked a quarter of a<br />
century ago, in 1962, to foreshadow how the Asia-Pacific<br />
region of today would appear, he could scar!' ely have<br />
imagined what was in store.<br />
He would have been addressing you, not a week or so before a<br />
Summit, but a month or so after the Cuban Missile Crisis.<br />
In 1962 the region was characterised by uncertain economic<br />
growth in nations still heavily reliant on the production<br />
and export of agricultural commodities. 8 r" </p>
<p>In 1962, the gigantic bulk of China lay locked to the rest<br />
of the world, poised on the verge of the turmoil and<br />
economic regression of the Cultural Revolution. who could<br />
have predicted either the extent of that turmoil or China's<br />
subsequent determination to achieve effective and rational<br />
modernisation and openness to the rest of the world?<br />
In 1962, many Western observers still operated on the<br />
assumption of a monolithic Sino-Soviet bloc several years<br />
after those countries had in fact entered a deep and<br />
enduring schism.<br />
And could an Australian observer in 1962 have predicted that<br />
Singapore would today be the independent, vigorous,<br />
resilient city state that it now is?<br />
Australian perceptions of Singapore in 1962 were indeed<br />
varied. I was interested to read one admittedly extreme<br />
view, put at the recent " Pacific 2000: Global Challenge"<br />
Conference held in Singapore. Professor Gregory Clark, who<br />
is now Professor of Economics at Sophia University in Tokyo,<br />
dlaimed that as a young Australian diplomat in Canberra in<br />
1959 he found parts of the Australian government deeply<br />
concerned over a vigorous, intelligent, progressive Chinese<br />
politician in Singapore, whose possible electoral victory<br />
was seen as likely to result in the communisation of<br />
Singapore. Of course that politician won his victory. His<br />
name was Lee Kuan Yew.<br />
I do not mean to be disparaging in recounting that story.<br />
After all, in Australia in 1962, there was a certain trade<br />
union official who, it is said, had attracted the unwanted<br />
and unnecessary attention of Australia's security people for<br />
his political work. And his name was Bob Hawke.<br />
So with all the necessary caveats about the difficulties of<br />
the task of prediction, let me now to use Orwell's phrase<br />
again struggle to see what is in front of our noses today.<br />
I have frequently said that the single most enduringly<br />
important event of our time is the emergence of China from<br />
its period of isolation.<br />
Viewed from any angle political, strategic, commercial,<br />
cultural this is a truly momentous transition.<br />
The recent 13th Congress of the Chinese Communist Party has<br />
done a remarkable thing: it has heralded a smooth... transition<br />
of power to a younger generation of leaders while*<br />
entrenching Deng Xiaoping's policies of modernisation.<br />
These policies of modernisation are perhaps the clearest<br />
example in action of what I have referred to as enlightened<br />
self-interest. I ii </p>
<p>The Chinese leadership is acting the better to fulfil the<br />
basic aspirations of the Chinese people for an improved<br />
quality of life. The nation is putting behind itself the<br />
days when mindless ideology was rampant an era which led<br />
more to deprivation and national scarring than to progress.<br />
I do not suggest that China is now about to abandon the<br />
political principles it holds and I certainly do not<br />
underestimate the differences between contemporary Chinese<br />
society and societies like Australia.<br />
My point is that China's commitment to modernisation springs<br />
out of its realisation of the legitimate ' material needs of<br />
its people. The implications of that realisation are<br />
immense, not only for the Chinese people themselves but for<br />
those of us outside China who seek to involve our economies<br />
more closely with the Chinese economy.<br />
From Australia's point of view, the prospects of greater<br />
enmeshment of our respective economies through, for example,<br />
joint ventures in mining and manufacturing projects in China<br />
and in Australia, offer both sides enormous mutual benefit.<br />
Only this month, and despite the initial doubts of a number<br />
of sceptics, Chinese and Australian enterprises concluded an<br />
agreement which I had been convinced would bring real<br />
benefits to both China and Australia. It is the first major<br />
overseas mining investment by the People's Republic a<br />
project to develop the iron-ore resources of Mount Channar<br />
in Western Australia for the Chinese iron and steel<br />
industry. The difference between China and Vietnam in this regard is<br />
stark. More than a decade after achieving unity through the<br />
Vietnam war, that nation is still isolated, committed to<br />
economic principles which derive more from abstract ideology<br />
than from realism, and is consequently failing to take<br />
advantage of the enormous opportunities which the region<br />
presents to it. Vietnam is indeed an island of stagnation<br />
in a sea of development.<br />
I have been convinced for many years and with great<br />
confidence since my discussion in Canberra in early 1983<br />
with the then Premier and now General Secretary Zhao Ziyang<br />
that fundamental and long-lasting change is underway in<br />
China. More recently, and I am sure partly as atconsequence, there<br />
have been more and more signs that the Soviet Union has<br />
embarked on long-lasting and far-reaching change.<br />
If China has embarked on its modernisation program<br />
substantially in reaction to the turmoil and disorder of the<br />
Cultural Revolution, the USSR has done so in response to a<br />
crisis of stagnation.<br />
In the past quarter of a century, particularly in the years<br />
of the Brezhnev era, Soviet leaders opted for old thinking<br />
and old methods in the management of their economy. </p>
<p>But our world is one where, thanks to the information and<br />
communications revolution, comparative economic performance<br />
can be judged continuously, widely and relatively easily.<br />
The failure of the USSR's performance to measure up to what<br />
the rest of the world, and, importantly, what the Soviet<br />
people, could have expected of it, has been starkly<br />
revealed. It was very clear by the mid 1980s that a new style of<br />
leadership was long overdue.<br />
Before I became Prime Minister, I made four visits to the<br />
Soviet Union in the 1970s in my capacity as President of the<br />
Australian Council of Trade Unions. I had become deeply<br />
concerned about the plight of Soviet Jews unable to gain the<br />
permission of the authorities to emigrate. The difficulties<br />
and intransigence I encountered in that task gave me no<br />
illusions about the nature of Soviet society but they also<br />
give me hope for the current phase of reforms proposed by<br />
General Secretary Gorbachev.<br />
As-you know, I will be making an official visit to Leningrad<br />
and Moscow immediately after my stay here in Singapore. I<br />
have not yet had the opportunity to meet Mr Gorbachev but I<br />
look forward to discussing these reforms with him.<br />
Leadership can be judged, in part at any rate, from a<br />
willingness to acknowledge the existence and scale of<br />
problems. By that measure, Mr Gorbachev and his colleagues<br />
are providing real leadership. At the same time as they are<br />
employing disciplinarian methods to tackle corruption,<br />
drunkenness and sloppy work habits, they are discussing with<br />
an unprecedented degree of frankness where things are wrong<br />
and what needs to be changed.<br />
Mr Gorbachev has said that the country has entered a<br />
" 1pre-crisis situation" calling for measures " amounting to a<br />
revolution" as he put it " a revolution without shots".<br />
I do not seek to equate the situations in the Soviet Union<br />
and China. But it is worth noting that both countries, in<br />
their efforts to lift economic performance, are clearly<br />
reducing the emphasis on central planning, and are making<br />
greater acknowledgement of the-merits of the market, of<br />
incentive and of competition.<br />
I am not suggesting that either country is embracing<br />
capitalism. They are certainly not embracing Western<br />
democratic ideas. But they are devolving responsibility in<br />
economic management from the centre and that will certainly<br />
raise expectations and generate political and social<br />
pressures. The Chinese leadership has made a number of adjustments in<br />
dealing with these problems while maintaining the firm<br />
direction of modernisation. The capacity of the USSR, a<br />
huge, complex, multi-national society with a sizeable and<br />
sophisicated intelligentsia, to make similar adjustments is<br />
still to be tested. j~~ L I </p>
<p>The key long-term question for the rest of us will be the<br />
impact which these major internal changes have in the<br />
international arena. That they have already begun to have<br />
an impact is abundantly clear.<br />
As for China, for well over a decade now, it has developed<br />
important and constructive relationships with many countries<br />
in our region, including Australia.<br />
As for the Soviet Union, we are seeing a more imaginative<br />
and subtle Soviet diplomacy in the world and particularly in<br />
our own region. We not only have the evidence of Mr<br />
Gorbachev's speech in Vladivostok. I was very struck by the<br />
detailed attention he gave to our part of the world in his<br />
book, Perestroika, New Thinking For Our Country and Our<br />
World, excerpts of which were published recentlyy1 n the<br />
Australian press.<br />
We must watch very carefully to see how this approach is<br />
developed. For my part, I would welcome a constructive<br />
involvement by the USSR in political and economic<br />
developments in the Asia-Pacific region. we seek mutually<br />
beneficial cooperation with the Soviet Union in a sincere<br />
and open-minded way. But we will be observing Soviet action<br />
in, for example, Indochina and Afghanistan as indicators of<br />
good faith.<br />
Mr Gorbachev's period in power has certainly seen a welcome<br />
reduction in tension with the United States. I think it is<br />
fair to assume that there is a large measure of economic<br />
self-interest in the Soviet pursuit of arms control<br />
agreements. Massive military expenditures have clearly had<br />
their impact on the failure of the Soviet economic<br />
performance to measure up internationally.<br />
I welcome the INF Agreement as an intrinsically important<br />
step, not least for its Asian dimension in that Soviet<br />
missiles will be removed from our region. I congratulate<br />
the United States and the Soviet Union on achieving it. I<br />
hope it leads on to major reductions in strategic weapons.<br />
Beyond that, I want to see continuing dialogue and<br />
cooperation between Washington and Moscow at the forthcoming<br />
Summit and into the future.<br />
Let us not forget the fact that our region saw the<br />
super-power confrontations in Korea and Indo-China. A<br />
resurgence of damaging super-power rivalry in this part of<br />
the world would pose a threat to the stability which has<br />
underpinned the region's economic growth ancd increased<br />
prosperity. I firmly believe that the importance of the changes underway<br />
in China and the USSR cannot be over-estimated. Those in<br />
China have proved positive. The more rational and creative<br />
path suggested in the USSR holds out positive prospects. I<br />
feel privileged to be leader of my country at this<br />
fascinating juncture for our region and the world. J) U*. </p>
<p>9.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen,<br />
' perestroika' means ' restructuring' and ' glasnost' means<br />
' openness'.<br />
At their face value, these are concepts which are not only<br />
familiar to western economies but which have indeed been<br />
critical to our economic success.<br />
So surely it is a paradox that at a time when both Communist<br />
giants, for different reasons and in different ways, are<br />
giving some recognition to the Western concepts of<br />
competition and open markets, the leading Western economies<br />
are making disturbing moves in the opposite direction.<br />
If those moves are not reversed in particular if the trend<br />
towards protectionism is not halted we face, to put it<br />
bluntly, the prospect of jeopardising the prosperity and<br />
stability of those countries fortunate enough to have it,<br />
and the hopes of those that do not.<br />
Anybody who has heard me address international forums in the<br />
United States and Europe recently not to mention within<br />
Australia will know that I have not wasted an opportunity<br />
to argue the merits of free trade.<br />
It is a message which needs to be trumpeted loud, clear and<br />
often and I shall continue to do so at every appropriate<br />
opportunity. But it is a pleasant change to address an audience like this<br />
in the knowledge that you appreciate, probably as keenly as<br />
any group in the world, the advantages which flow from free<br />
trade. The growth of Singapore and of the ASEAN countries<br />
in general has been heavily reliant on access to a liberal<br />
trading system.<br />
The United States has become a particular focus of the<br />
present world debate about protectionism, and for two<br />
reasons. one is the gross distortion of agricultural<br />
markets stemming from the actions of Europe and Japan,<br />
against which the US has reacted through its own subsidies,<br />
and against which some Americans are contemplating an even<br />
more drastic response; the second relates to the apparent<br />
inflexibility of US fiscal policy.<br />
As we know all too well, fiscal inaction in the face of the<br />
massive current account imbalances between the United<br />
States, Japan and West Germany was the underlying cause of<br />
the October stock markets crash and the associated<br />
realignment of the major currencies.<br />
US post war economic history has, until recently, been that<br />
of a lender. That fact, combined with the relative size of<br />
the US economy, had given it a degree of immunity from<br />
international financial developments which few other<br />
countries could expect. </p>
<p>The emergence of the US as the world's largest borrower has<br />
been a more recent event. But it would have happened much<br />
earlier except that US trade deficits since the early<br />
seventies had been mostly offset by interest earned on<br />
investments.<br />
So even if the US were to begin to run a trade surplus<br />
tomorrow, it would take many years before it could expect to<br />
regain its net lender status.<br />
This presents a major challenge for economic leadership in<br />
the US: to recognise in a way which has not been required<br />
previously both the interdependence of global economic<br />
policies, and the increased dependence of the US economy on<br />
the favourable judgements of foreign investors.<br />
It is heartening to see that the US Administration has<br />
negotiated a new fiscal package. President Reagan has<br />
described it as " a beginning" in winding back their fiscal<br />
deficit. Clearly much more work remains. The Reagan<br />
Administration is also to be praised for its efforts to<br />
resist the rising protectionist tide.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen,<br />
It must be remembered that this is not a task solely for the<br />
United States. Western Europe and Japan also have crucial<br />
reform roles to play.<br />
Indeed, the rapid escalation of the Japanese trade surplus<br />
over recent years, the corresponding emergence of Japan as<br />
the world's largest lender each year and the growing<br />
internationalisation of the yen will continue to test the<br />
leadership qualities of Japan for some time to come.<br />
Japan's economy is likely to experience continuing pressure<br />
to open its markets further and restructure its industrial<br />
base, certainly for as long as world trading balances remain<br />
at their current unsustainable levels.<br />
The change required in the economic structure of Japan over<br />
the longer term, especially a greater reliance on imported<br />
foodstuffs, is likely to raise quite fundamental political<br />
and social sensitivities.<br />
The question is frequently asked whether Japan should adopt<br />
a more active international political role, one more<br />
commensurate with its position in the worll economy. To ask<br />
this is, I believe, to ask the wrong question.<br />
The fact is that Japan's economic power will inevitably<br />
translate into a higher international profile.<br />
Such major economic interests carry the need to protect them<br />
through activity in the international political sphere.<br />
This is a natural link. j 
</p><p>The relevant question to ask is therefore what the nature of<br />
an increased Japanese political role will be. It would be a<br />
mistake if we think that Japan will, in taking on a<br />
h" ewei" g htbee netdh e rUonlei, t eda utSotmataetsi, c aloltyh erd o Wwehsatte rnw e awlalnite s, AwShEeAtNh, er<br />
Australia or whoever. Like every other country Japan will<br />
pursue its own interests which at times will coincide with<br />
those of others but at other times may not.<br />
That Japan has been moving to a more active foreign policy<br />
is evident in a number of areas. Japan has sought to<br />
contribute to a solution to the war in the Persian Gulf. It<br />
has signalled an intention to take a closer interest in the<br />
South Pacific. The Nakasone initiative to contribute to<br />
regional development through re-cycling part of the Japanese<br />
surplus is another manifestation of a foreign policy<br />
interest in the stability of the region which goes beyond<br />
the mere pursuit of commercial interests here.<br />
we all know that Japanese defence is an issue which arouses<br />
debate and emotions. Given its interests, Japan will want<br />
to ensure that its defence is secured. over time it will no<br />
doubt do more for itself. I would say the important thing<br />
is that it do so in the context of a tight integration with<br />
the Western alliance and in the context of collective<br />
perceptions about what serves the security interests of this<br />
region.<br />
For all these reasons, we must develop a greater habit of<br />
consulting with and talking to Japan about international<br />
political and security issues, not merely economic ones. We<br />
have consciously sought to do this in Australia's<br />
relationship with Japan over recent years.<br />
Most pressingly however the crucial test of Japan's<br />
leadership will not come in some new political arena but in<br />
its performance on the crucial issue of economic adjustment<br />
an issue whose resolution will directly affect the claim<br />
of Japan, and the rest of us, to continued prosperity.<br />
The Maekawa report provides clear guidelines for Japanese<br />
economic reform which would yield great benefits to the<br />
Japanese people themselves and to the rest of the world.<br />
These guidelines involve a reduced Japanese reliance on<br />
exports and a greater willingness to open its domestic<br />
markets to imports.<br />
If Japan were able by such means to exercise the same kind<br />
of beneficial world leadership as the United States provided<br />
in the 1950s, through open trading policies, then we would<br />
all welcome that kind of leadership without reservation.<br />
Let me also stress how crucial it is that the United States<br />
and Japan are able to manage their relationship effectively.<br />
It is a relationship which has the greatest significance for<br />
the security and economic prosperity of others of us in the<br />
region. </p>
<p>Ladies and gentlemen,<br />
If I have concentrated so far on the major political and<br />
economic powers of the region, I most certainly do not want<br />
to leave the impression that the medium and small nations<br />
can avoid the challenge of change or have no role in<br />
mastering it.<br />
The various organisations of regional co-operation which<br />
exist bear witness to the way in which the smaller nations<br />
can strive to advance their collective goals and to exert<br />
their collective influence on the political and economic<br />
giants.<br />
ASEAN is entering its third decade as one of the most<br />
successful regional organisations in the world; the South<br />
Pacific Forum is also emerging as a valuable voice having<br />
among other achievements conceived and implemented the South<br />
Pacific Nuclear Free Zone Treaty; the Cairns Group of Fair<br />
Trading nations, which includes six countries from our<br />
region, is playing a pivotal role in the multilateral<br />
negotiations on the liberalisation of trade in agriculture.<br />
Such co-operation is likely to become more important to<br />
achieving our shared aspirations as our region faces the<br />
legacy and in some cases the continuing experience of<br />
colonialism.<br />
As the situation in New Caledonia bears witness, France has<br />
not yet found the way towards a constructive durable role in<br />
the South Pacific.<br />
In many nations which achieved independence in the 1970s, a<br />
new generation of leaders is emerging to face the issues not<br />
of immediate post-colonialism but of established membership.<br />
of the world community.<br />
In many of the South Pacific nations, the issues now are<br />
ones of complex economic management, sophisticated foreign<br />
policy choices, profound social questions.<br />
In the former Australian territory of Papua New Guinea, the<br />
second decade of independence is bringing new solutions to<br />
the management of our relationship.<br />
And in Fiji of course a military dictatorship has snuffed<br />
out a democratically elected Government.<br />
If these issues are to be resolved, close " and patient<br />
cooperation and mutual goodwill will be required of us all.<br />
In the context of regional co-operation, it is my hope that<br />
all nations will support the efforts of the Aquino<br />
Government as it negotiates the adjustment process following<br />
the overthrow of the Marcos dictatorship. The bloodless<br />
political transition from oppression to People's Power has<br />
earned the continuing respect, and warrants the continuing<br />
support, of all who are committed to decency in government. I) 2 2~ </p>
<p>13.<br />
Indeed, if we are committed to achieving the goal of the<br />
Pacific Century, we cannot ignore the fact that despite our<br />
region's optimism and its overall prosperity, some countries<br />
are burdened by crippling debt levels and appear to be doing<br />
little more than treading water. In some countries indeed,<br />
people are still not being fed, clothed or sheltered<br />
adequately. Paradoxically, other nations face dramatic social and<br />
political problems which result directly from their<br />
increasing economic prosperity.<br />
Tens of millions of would-be entrants to the workforce have<br />
left their close-knit rural communities to seek a better<br />
life in the cities. This is true throughout our region from<br />
Shanghai to Jakarta. The population of those two cities<br />
alone are estimated to total some 42 million people by the<br />
end of this century.<br />
And in South Korea, for example, there is a clear connection<br />
between the country's outstanding economic achievements and<br />
the unfulfilled aspirations for greater political<br />
expression. Ladies and gentlemen<br />
I have so far traversed just about the whole region. I have<br />
left to last a discussion of Australia's role in the region<br />
and Australia's capacity to cope with change.<br />
I could not stand here, of course, and describe the<br />
challenge of political leadership and economic adjustment in<br />
our region unless I were willing to meet that challenge in<br />
Australia. I think there have been times in the past when Prime<br />
Minister Lee, believing that Australians had protectionism<br />
in their blood, wondered whether we were beyond redemption.<br />
At the time of the ASEAN's consolidation and development and<br />
of the growth of the NICs a sceptical eye was cast on<br />
Australia. But I can say with confidence that the era of<br />
Australian complacency of postponing the task of<br />
adjustment is now behind us.<br />
Australia's economic history is replete with examples of a<br />
promising economic upturn cut short by an inflationary<br />
spiral. In the old days Australians habitually found it hacd to<br />
reconcile their differences about how best to share the<br />
fruits of growth. Excessive industrial disputation was one<br />
result. Wage-push inflation was another. Poor economic<br />
performance was yet another.<br />
But as I said at the outset, the constructive role of<br />
enlightened self-interest has a central role to play in<br />
securing sustained economic growth. </p>
<p>In the Australian environment, that required each party to<br />
understand the role of income restraint and the need to<br />
encourage investment and job creation through mutually<br />
supportive economic policies.<br />
That is the approach which I have attempted to bring to my<br />
stewardship as Prime minister of Australia.<br />
It was the approach which underlay my calling of the<br />
historic National Economic Summit Conference immediately on<br />
coming to office in 1983 an approach which promoted a<br />
shared understanding between competing groups and which<br />
healed the divisions and discords which had marred much of<br />
the seventies and the early eighties.<br />
Few would deny that the approach has worked well. The<br />
pay-off has been an absence of wage push inflation, a more<br />
than halving of industrial disputation, a consistent decline<br />
in the real costs of employing labour, sustained economic<br />
growth, a growth in jobs at twice the rate of the industrial<br />
world, greater confidence in the stability of the Australian<br />
economy and an improved climate for investment.<br />
The Australian union movement now well appreciates the<br />
importance to our future growth prospects of progressively<br />
higher productivity.<br />
That awareness lies behind the current willingness of<br />
organised labour to cooperate with management to reform work<br />
and management practices, to restructure Australia's economy<br />
to make it more outward looking and more internationally<br />
competitive, and to cooperate more closely with potential<br />
new foreign investors in Australia.<br />
A complementary change in attitudes has taken place<br />
regarding protectionisin.<br />
Business groups in particular have come to recognise the<br />
benefits to themselves and to Australia of an open trading<br />
system. They acknowledge the role of reduced protectionism<br />
in improving their ability to export and to meet competition<br />
from imports.<br />
one manifestation of this has been a general community<br />
acceptance of the need to reduce gradually the protection<br />
afforded to some of our least efficient industries in the<br />
context of industry specific plans.<br />
By the end of the current plan for the textile6, clothing<br />
and footwear industries, for example, Australia will be the<br />
only country in the developed world not relying on<br />
quantitative restrictions on TCF imports.<br />
Another manifestation has been the recent call by business<br />
groups in Australia and New Zealand to go beyond the<br />
existing framework of the Closer Economic Relations<br />
agreement between our two countries. </p>
<p>Yet another manifestation is our role in the Cairns Group,<br />
fighting for an end to the madness afflicting agricultural<br />
trade, and our firm and clear offer to the contracting<br />
parties of the GATT to reduce our border protection,<br />
including non-tariff protection, in a multilateral context.<br />
Australia in short has recognised that its future is one of<br />
a trading nation which must diversify its export base.<br />
We are no longer passively responding to developments<br />
elsewhere. we have become a force for change in our region.'<br />
Ladies and gentlemen<br />
Let me close by drawing together the strands of the argument<br />
I have put tonight.<br />
First, change is a constant of our region and our<br />
newspapers, textbooks and government reports are<br />
littered with assessments which failed adequately to<br />
understand the essential dynamics of change.<br />
Second, we can nevertheless identify today some of the<br />
facts of our regional life which will undoubtedly assume<br />
greater importance to us all up to the early decades of<br />
the next century. I have discussed the essential ones<br />
this evening: the emergence and modernisation of China;<br />
the current reforms in the Soviet Union; and the need<br />
for sustained action by the major economies of the West<br />
to solve their current account deficits and to resist<br />
protectionism. Third, beneath this level of the major political and<br />
economic powers all of us have a duty to undertake<br />
appropriate domestic reform which will contribute not<br />
only to our own efficiency but to increase trade among<br />
US. Fourth, these economic reforms are encouraged and<br />
advanced where they are accompanied by changes in social<br />
attitudes and practices. This means in effect that<br />
efforts to increase the material well being of the<br />
community which is after all the desired end point of<br />
such reforms will be enhanced where separate interest<br />
groups in the community are prepared to abandon<br />
traditional antagonisms and work together for thQ. mutual<br />
benefit of all.<br />
Fifth, it is the task of community and political leaders<br />
to recognise ways in which the interests of the<br />
community can best be advanced and it is their task as<br />
well to ensure that all those who will be affected by a<br />
decision appreciate and understand the reasons for it. </p>
<p>Sixth, and finally, any democracy whose institutions are<br />
created for the purpose of public involvement in public<br />
affairs should regard this task as possible and<br />
certainly desirable. But it is an essential task for<br />
all societies, whatever their political system, to win<br />
the understanding and acceptance of the whole community<br />
in the making of the necessary changes. Without that<br />
involvement, the needed economic changes cannot be made.<br />
For it is ultimately the people those in the<br />
factories, on the farms, in the classrooms, in the<br />
offices who will determine whether those economic<br />
reforms succeed or fail.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen,<br />
I do not advance these thoughts with any pretence that they<br />
provide comprehensive prescriptions to the broad field of<br />
issues I have addressed this evening. I do believe however<br />
that they are the kinds of general guidelines which are<br />
relevant to the tasks of policy makers in our region<br />
. including in Australia and Singapore.<br />
When confronting change, many of us can readily and clearly<br />
articulate the problems resulting from a change to the<br />
status quo.<br />
What I find most distressing is that there is a relative<br />
poverty in the intellectual effort devoted to the task of<br />
addressing the problems indeed the disasters which can<br />
result from avoiding or ignoring change.<br />
It is only by a preparedness to meet the challenge of change<br />
head on that we can overcome that challenge rather than be<br />
overcome by it. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
