<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3674</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER TO LAUNCH THE INDO-CHINE/VIETNAM APPEAL</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/04/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003674.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER PRESS STATEMENT NO0. 479<br />
3 April 1975<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER TO LAUNCH THE<br />
INDO-CHINA/ VIETNAM APPEAL<br />
I know that I speak for all Australians in expressing<br />
my deep concern at the current-plight of refugees in<br />
Indo-China. Today, the Disaster Emergency Committee of the Australian<br />
Council for Overseas Aid opens the national Indo-China<br />
Vietnam Appeal so that Australians will have an opportunity<br />
to contribute personally to the organisations which are<br />
helping suffering people in these areas.<br />
As a Government we have acted promptly to assist the<br />
plight of these homeless refugees. Already this financial<br />
year we have given $ 2.4 million to international agencies<br />
which are working on both sides of present lines of military<br />
control and we have reaffirmed our commitment to contribute<br />
generously to the future reconstruction of post-war<br />
Indo-China. We are conscious of the depth of feeling on this<br />
humanitarian issue among the Australian people and their<br />
desire to help personally. I therefore warmly commend this<br />
national appeal to the Australian people and have pleasure<br />
in launching it with a donation from the Government of<br />
$ 50,000. I know that individual Australians will express<br />
their personal concern by responding quickly and generously<br />
to this-appeal.<br />
The Australian Council for Overseas Aid coordinates the<br />
work of the 32 voluntary aid agencies in Australia, including<br />
such organisation as the Australian Red Cross, Australian<br />
Council of Churches, Australian Catholic Relief, Freedom from<br />
Hunger Campaign, Austcare, Community Aid Abroad, and other<br />
major organisations in this area.<br />
The Australian people have the assurance from past work<br />
by the. Disaster Emergency Committee that the money given will<br />
be sent quickly and spent wisely by reputable organisations.<br />
TOWNSVILLE, QLD. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
