<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2989</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER AND MINISTER FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRS, THE HON EG WHITLAM QC MP, ON HIS NORTH AMERICAN VISIT, IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES, WEDNESDAY 22 AUGUST 1973</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/08/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002989.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
DEATMN OF<br />
MNO DATE<br />
N122 22 August 1973<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINIST7R AND MINISTER FOR<br />
FOREIGN AFFAIRS, THE HON. E. G. WHITLAM, ON<br />
HIS NORTH AMERICAN VISIT, IN TI-fl HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES,<br />
W~ EDNSPAY, 22 AUGULST, 1 973. </p>
<p>NORTH AMERICAN VISIT<br />
I would like to take leave of the House to report briefly<br />
to the Parliament and, through the Parliament to the Australian<br />
neoole, on my recent overseas visit to Mexico the first by an<br />
Australian Prime Minister to the United States and to represent<br />
Australia at the Commonwealth Heads of Government Meeting in Ottawa.<br />
I believe the visit was timely and useful to Australia<br />
both in establishing new and significant contacts overseas at the<br />
Head of Government level and in developing the more diversified<br />
and indenoendent foreign policy for Australia to which the<br />
Government is committed.<br />
In combining a visit to Mexico and a visit to Washington<br />
with the Commonwealth Heads of Government Meeting in Ottawa I was<br />
able to restore a more appropriate balance to our anproach to<br />
Central and North America. Washington is not the sole capital in<br />
that vast hemisphere.<br />
MEXTI CO In Mexico which is a leader of opinion in Central and<br />
South America my delegation and I received an enthusiastic and<br />
warm reception, especially from President Echeverria and Foreign<br />
Minister Rabasa. I believe the visit has opened a window onto<br />
Central and South America; that in future we shall have more<br />
frequent and meaningful contacts with Mexico and, indeed, with<br />
other Latin American countries. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
I found considerable common ground between our two<br />
countries as middle powers on opposite sides of the Pacific.<br />
Like Australia, Mexico has had problems of overdependence on<br />
foreign countries and inadequate returns from the exploitation<br />
of its natural resources. The Mexican Government is also strongly<br />
opposed to the poisoning of the Pacific environment by nuclear<br />
weanons testing and has taken the lead in ensuring that there will<br />
be no such tests in Latin America.<br />
I found that we were in general agreement also on that<br />
complex subject, the Law of the Sea, and our respective representatives<br />
w ill be co-operating closely in future to ensure that coastal states<br />
receive a fair share of the wealth of the oceans and of the sea bed.<br />
I believe that the Mexicans are well disposed to Australia<br />
and our oresent policies and that they are eager to see the<br />
relationship between our two countries further enhanced.<br />
President Echeverria accented my invitation to him to<br />
visit Australia, probably some time next year. In the meantime<br />
we are oleased to welcome a group of Mexican Members of Parliament<br />
and probably, next month, the Minister for Agriculture, Mr Manuel<br />
Aguirre. It is the firm intention of the Government that the<br />
increasing momentum of our relations with Mexico in particular and<br />
Latin America in general shall not be lost. I left President<br />
Echeverria in no doubt that we looked forward to having him here,<br />
not only because of the great n~ erson. il charm of which he and a* -/ 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
Senora Echeverria disnose, but also because such a visit will nut<br />
the seal, as it were, on the Government's policy of fostering<br />
closer links with our neighbours across the Pacific.<br />
I shall not take up the time of the House with further<br />
details of my visit to Mexico as I propose to table the Joint<br />
Communiqu. issued after my visit.<br />
THE UNITED STATES<br />
In Was'hington I had substantive and straightforward<br />
discussions with President Nixon, Vice-President Agnew, Secretary<br />
of State Rogers, Dr Kissinger and numbers of other prominent<br />
Americans, including members of the Congress and the Senate<br />
Committee on Foreign Affairs. All showed very considerable<br />
interest in recent develonments in Australia.<br />
My discussions in Washington covered the situation in<br />
the Asian and Pacific region, including relationships between the<br />
Great Powers, our relations with the United States, ANZUS, SEATO,<br />
the situation in indo-China, nuclear testing, Korea, regional<br />
co-operation in Asia, the special importance of Japan and<br />
Indonesia to us, and other matters of mutual interest.<br />
I told United States leaders that we continue to give<br />
strong support to ANZU9 which we see as embodying some of the most<br />
imnortant nermanent and natural elements in the relationship between<br />
the three Pacific nartners. On the American side also, the value<br />
of ANZUS is not questioned. / 4 </p>
<p>I also told the Secretary of State that ANZUS alone of<br />
ou Treaties in this area seemed entirely satisfactory and that<br />
any Australian Government would strongly support it.<br />
I explained our reservations about SEATO and found that<br />
many of them were shared by the United States. I made it clear<br />
that some aspects of the Manila Treaty as distinct from the<br />
Organisation itself, were of continuing value, especially to<br />
TPailand, and that Australia did. not intend to withdraw from SE'! ATO.<br />
I can assure the House that, following my talks in<br />
Washington, I believe those basic matters on which we agree are<br />
much more numerous, imnortant and lasting than those few issues<br />
on which our views might differ. That is certainly the view of<br />
the American Administration,<br />
I believe, in fact, that the Australian-American<br />
relationship will be seen to rest now on firmer foundations<br />
than it did in the past, We have brought it to a new maturity.<br />
I believe too that the American Administration now fully<br />
accepts that Australia is not a small and relatively insignificant<br />
country as it was once called there but a middle power of growing<br />
influence in the South East Asian and South Pacific regrions,<br />
I believe that America respects and welcomes the less<br />
compliant and more independent, though equally friendly annroach,<br />
which the Australian Government now adopts towards the United States.<br />
a0 </p>
<p>In the United States I also paid a brief visit to New<br />
York where I visited the United Nations headquarters and addressed<br />
a very well attended gathering of the Australian-American Association.<br />
The texts of this speech and my address to the National<br />
Press Club in Washington are of course available io any Member<br />
who might wish to have them,<br />
THJE COMM~ ONWEAL~ TH<br />
I turn now to the meeting of twenty-three Commonwealth<br />
Heads of Government and representatives of the other nine<br />
Commonwealth Heads of Government which took place in Ottawa from<br />
2 to 10 August. This was, in the opinion of the more experienced Heads<br />
of Government present, the most successful Commonwealth Meeting yet<br />
held at this level. It was successful because participants<br />
focussed their attention on the main practical issues in international<br />
affairs facing us today. The Conference was attended for the most<br />
part by men with modern ideas. They represented every geographic<br />
region. Above all it was a meeting of equals sharing a common<br />
concern for co-operative effort and frank consultation.<br />
The scope and achievements of the Conference are outlined<br />
in its final Communique which I also table for the House's<br />
information, The document largely speaks for itself. / 16 </p>
<p>-6-<br />
The Meeting was remarkable, not as some have suggested<br />
for differences of opinion, but for the wide identity of interest<br />
in the aDproach of so many members to the realities of contemporary<br />
international life. We started with the basic proposition that we<br />
of the Commonwealth are now all medium or smaller powers and that<br />
we all experienced in some way or other a vulnerability to changes<br />
brought about by the nature of the relationships between the major<br />
powers. From this position we developed an appreciation of the<br />
opportunities for members of the Commonwealth and the benefits<br />
to be realized through closer Commonwealth consultation and<br />
co-operation. In this respect my pre-election statement of faith<br />
in the Commonwealth and its importance for Australia has been<br />
vindicated. I would like to place on record the value of the wideranging<br />
discussions to all present and to draw attention to the<br />
practical and functional co-operation at the Conference.<br />
Moreover, I believe I established or consolidated a<br />
number of very useful personal contacts with a number of Heads of<br />
Governments especially from the Caribbean countries, Africa, and<br />
countries like Bangladesh, Sir Lanka, Malaysia, Mauritius and, of<br />
course, Canada itself. These contacts demonstrate that the<br />
Commonwealth is, as I believed even before I went to Ottawa, a<br />
valuable forum through which Australia can develop its more<br />
diversified approach to our foreign affairs. / 7 </p>
<p>The need to codify acceptable behaviour by multinational<br />
corporations has been widely recognised and is the subject of detailed<br />
study by the United Nations, Problems created by a " brain drain" in<br />
develooing countries have been the subject of international<br />
negotiation and study for a number of years. Similarly our concern<br />
with the threat from atmospheric nuclear tests is shared universally<br />
even if it is not transmitted in every case into effective action.<br />
In this resoect i regret that a very small minority of Members could<br />
not sumoort the original declaration submitted by the Prime Minister<br />
of New Zealand, to which we lent our sunport, in the context of<br />
our present efforts to orevent further such tests.<br />
In Ottawa I was able to indicate to Commonwealth leaders<br />
that Australia will give more active support to Commonwealth<br />
co-onerative ventures, We already are a contributor to its major<br />
channel for multilateral assistance, the Commonwealth Fund for<br />
Technical Co-operation and to the Commonwealth Foundation. I<br />
announced in Ottawa that Australia will also sunport the new<br />
Commonwealth Youth Program to the extent of 860,000 per annum for<br />
the next three years and that we will Darticinate in the further<br />
study of Droposals for a Commonwealth Development and Export Bank<br />
and an institute for the auplied study of government.<br />
I believe the contacts I made in Ottawa will lead to<br />
the develonment of more meaningful relationshios with a number<br />
of countries in the Caribbean and around the Indian and Pacific<br />
Oceans, and in Africa, / 8 </p>
<p>AUSTRALIAN REPRESENTATION<br />
I should report to the House that one consequence of my<br />
visit to Mexico, Washington and Ottawa will be the widening of<br />
Australian representation in the Caribbean and in South America.<br />
Following the discussions which I had, I Dropose to take<br />
steps to accredit the Australian High Commissioner in Canada to<br />
the five Caribbean Commonwealth countries, Jamaica, Trinidad and<br />
Tobago, Barbados, Guyana and the Bahamas, pending the establishment<br />
of a separate High Commission in the Caribbean, the head of which<br />
will then be accredited to all five countries. At the same time<br />
I have under active review the Cuban request to establish a Trade<br />
or Consular Office in Australia. I am also consulting Guatemala<br />
and Panama with a view to accrediting non-resident Ambassadors<br />
to these countries. I seek leave of the House to table the Communique issued<br />
at the conclusion of my visit to Mexico and the Joint Communique<br />
adopted in Ottawa by the Meeting of the Commonwealth Heads of<br />
Governments. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
