<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6304</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER: REMARKS TO JAPAN-AUSTRALIA SOCIETY, 1 FEBRUARY, REMARKS TO JAPAN, AUSTRALIAN SOCIETY, 1 FEBRUARY</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/02/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006304.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
x<br />
1, ALSTHlA&amp; lA~<br />
PRIME MINOSTER<br />
PRIME MINISTER: REMARKS TO JAPAN-AUSTRALIA SOCIETY: 1 FEBRUARY<br />
REMARKS TO JAPAN AUSTRALIAN SOCIETY: 1 FEBRUARY ( UNDERLINED)<br />
AMBASSADOR SAITO<br />
MEMBERS OF THE JAPAN-AUSTRALIA SOCIETY<br />
DISTINGUISHED GUESTS<br />
THANK YOU VERY MUCH FOR THE WARM WELCOME YOU HAVE GIVEN ME THIS<br />
EVENING. I REGRET THAT OTHER COMMITMENTS MrrEAN THAT I CAN ONLY<br />
SPEND A SHORT TIME WITH YOU.<br />
A FEW BRIEF WGRDS ARE, HOWEVER, IN ORDER.<br />
AS YOU ALL KNOW JAPAN HAS FOR MANY YEARS BEEN AUSTRALIA'S MOST<br />
IMPORTANT TRADING PARTNER. AM SURE THAT IT WILL REMAIN SO.<br />
HOWEVER, THE NATURE OF TRADE BETWEEN OUR TWO COUNTRIES IS CHANGING.<br />
THIS IS ONLY NATURAL AS THE TWO PARTIES ADJUST TO EVOLVING ECONOMIC<br />
CIRCUMSTANCES. DESPITE THESE DIFFERENT CIRCUMSTANCES, HOWEVER, I<br />
WOULD EXPECT JAPAN TO REMAIN A SUBSTANTIAL MARKET FOR AUSTRALIAN<br />
RAW MATERIALS AND AGRICULTURAL PRODUCTS. THESE ITEMS WILL CLEARLY<br />
REMAIN VERY IMPORTANT TO JAPAN.<br />
AS BEFITS A TRADING PARTNER OF MANY YEARS STANDING, AUSTRALIA IS<br />
DETERMINED TO BE A RELIABLE AND COMPETITIVE SUPPLIER. W4E ASK IN<br />
RETURN THAT AUSTRALIA BE TREATED NO LESS FAVOURABLY THAN OTHER<br />
SUPPLIERS AND TH4AT AUSTRALIAN INTERESTS BE TAKEN FULLY INTO ACCOUNT<br />
BY JAPAN IN ITS APPROACH TO THE RESOLUTION OF BILATERAL TRADE PROBLEMS<br />
WITH OTHER COUNTRIES.<br />
AUSTRALIA NEVERTHELESS RECOGNISES THAT IT MUST GIVE CLOSER ATTENTION<br />
TO THE POTENTIAL OF OTHER MARKETS IN JAPAN. JAPANESE MARKETS FOR<br />
MANUFACTURES, PROCESSED FOODSTUFFS AND SERVICES N4EED TO BE EXA11INED<br />
CLOSELY IF AUSTRALIA IS TO ARREST THE FALL IT HAS EXPERIENCED IN<br />
RECENT YEARS IN ITS SHARE OF TOTAL JAPANESE IMPORTS. WITH THIS IN<br />
MIND WE ARE DEVELOPING A JAPAN MARKET STRATEGY THAT WILL INVOLVE<br />
THE APPOINTMENT OF TWO SENIOR JAPANESE CONSULTING FIRMS TO RESEARCH<br />
NEW MARKETS FOR AUSTRALIA. THE OPPORTUNITIES IDENTIFIED WILL BE<br />
BROUGHT TO THE ATTENTION OF AUSTRALIAN FIRMS LIKELY TO BE ABLE<br />
SUCCESSFULLY TO SUPPLY SUCH MARKETS. WITH THE ASS; ISTANCE OF THE<br />
JAPANESE GOVERNMENT, AUSTRALIA ALSO HOPES TO SE ABLE TO PARTICIPATE<br />
FULLY IN JAPAN'S PROGRAM OF IMPORT LIBERALISATION.<br />
THE CHALLENGE POSED BY ECONOMIC CHANGE IS FORMIDABLE. IT WILL REQUIRE<br />
CONTINUING CONSULTATION AND DISCUSSION TO ENSURE THAT EACH<br />
SIDE FULLY UNDERSTANDS THE NEEDS OF TH4E OTHER. IT IS ONE OF<br />
THlE PRIN4CIPAL OBJECTIVES OF MY VISIT TO JAPAN TO ENSURE TH4AT THE<br />
MUTUAL UNDERSTANDING AN4D TRUST ESSENTIAL FOR HARMONIOUS PARTNERSHIP<br />
IS DEVELOPED AND MAINTAINED. MY DISCUSSIONS WITH PRIME MINISTER<br />
NAKAS0O4E THIS MORNING HAVE ASSURED ME THAT JAPAN SHARES TH! TS PERCEPTION. </p>
<p>2.<br />
THE ECONOMIC RELATIONSHIP BETWEEN JAPAN AND AUSTRALIA IS NOT OF<br />
COURSE CONFINED TO TRADE. MY GOVERNMENT WELCOMES THE GROWING<br />
JAPANESE INTEREST IN INVESTMENT IN AUSTRALIA. THE PROSPECTS FOR<br />
CO-OPERATION IN SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY ARE ENCOUJRAGING. THE POTENTIAL<br />
FOR DEVELOPING TOURISM IS ALSO ' CONSIDERABLE. I SEE PROSPECTS IN<br />
TH4ESE AREAS AS GOOD REASONS FOR CONFIDENCE IN THE CONTINUED GROWTH<br />
AND DIVERSITY IN THE ECONOMIC RELATIONSHIP.<br />
BUT IN THE END IT IS PEOPLE THAT MATTER. THE VERY SUCCESS OF THE<br />
JAPANESE ECONOMY IN A COUNTRY WHERE BASIC PHYSICAL RESOURCES ARE<br />
LIMITED IS EVIDENCE OF THAT.<br />
AND SO IT IS THAT AN ESSENTIAL ELEMENT IN THE BROADENING OF CO-OPERATION<br />
BETWEEN JAPAN AND AUSTRALIA HAS BEEN THE CONTINUING COMMITMENT<br />
OF INDIVIDUALS AND PRIVATE-LEVEL ORGANISATIONS TO THE FOSTERING OF<br />
MUTUAL UNDERSTANDING AND GOODWILL. I CAN ASSURE YOU THAT THE ROLE<br />
YOUR OWN SOCIETY HAS PLAYED OVER THE YEARS IN PROMOTING FRIENDSHIP<br />
AND EXCHANGES BETWEEN AUSTRALIANS AND JAPANESE IS GREATLY APPRECIATED<br />
IN AUSTRALIA. THE PRESENCE HERE OF SO MANY DISTINGUISHED PEOPLE IS<br />
A MOST ENCOURAGING INDICATION THAT T1HERE IS IN JAPAN A CONTINUING<br />
HIGH LEVEL OF INTEREST IN AUSTRALIA AND AUSTRALIANS. AS WELL AS<br />
EXCELLENT HOSPITALITY, YOU HAVE GIVEN ME A FURTHER REASON FOR<br />
CONFIDENCE IN THE FUTURE VITALITY OF OUR RELATIONSHIP.<br />
I WISH YOUR SOCIETY EVERY SUCCESS IN ITS FUTURE WORK. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
