<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7600</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF OPENING REMARKS TO THE PREMIER&#039;S CONFERENCE, CANBERRA, 18 MAY 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/05/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007600.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
RIW/ 1<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF OPENING REMARKS TO THE PREMIER'S CONFERENCE,<br />
CANBERRA, 18 MAY 1989<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
PM: Premiers and Chief Ministers, I extend a welcome to all<br />
of you, a very warm welcome. There's some special features<br />
about this meeting. Of course it's the first to be held<br />
here in the new Parliament House. It's also the first<br />
meeting to be attended by a representative from the new<br />
Government of the Australian Capital Territory. So we<br />
extend an especially warm welcome to you, Rosemary. Of<br />
course there's another aspect to that particularly warm<br />
welcome, not only because you're the first representative of<br />
the Australian Capital Territory Government, but Rosemary<br />
becomes the first woman in a State or Territory to sit at<br />
the Premier's Conference table. That's a particular first.<br />
Also welcome Marshall Perron, attending for the first time<br />
-as Chief minister of the Northern Territory, and welcome to<br />
you Marshall. David Parker attending as Deputy Premier and<br />
Treasurer of Western Australia.<br />
Now as you will see this year the agenda has been restricted<br />
to five items only so that we can focus on and in fact<br />
progress a limited number of important issues which affect<br />
all States. That I think is an improvement from the<br />
previous situation where we've deluded ourselves by having<br />
the long agenda items that we're going to deal with and of<br />
course we never do.<br />
0 The key issue on this occasion colleagues, is the<br />
achievement of responsible fiscal outcome. We're meeting at<br />
a time when I think you appreciate some very difficult<br />
economic decisions must be taken so that we can ensure that<br />
the hard won gains of recent years -particularly the<br />
achievement of 1.4 million new jobs -that those<br />
achievements can be maintained.<br />
Now put simply the problem that we have at the present time<br />
the context within which we meet is the problem of<br />
excessive growth. The level of domestic demand has been<br />
running at a point which is not capable of being satisfied<br />
by domestic supplies and that's meant that almost half the<br />
growth in demand in 1988 was satisfied by imports. And<br />
that's generating in the simplest of terms an unsustainable<br />
outcome for the Balance of Payments. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
We might like to try and ignore that, avoid it, say it's not<br />
happening, but we can't do that. Those are the facts and so<br />
we've got to all play our part in achieving a momentum<br />
towards a position where can have a level of activity which<br />
is sustainable and that's going to require adjustment. As<br />
far as Governments are concerned which we represent here<br />
the Governments of Australia that requires a moderation in<br />
Government demand. It's as simple as that.<br />
Now I'm not trying to pretend in saying that colleagues,<br />
that Governments have not already been making contributions<br />
towards that adjustment. I know that looking around the<br />
table you've had to make all of you have had to make<br />
some difficult political decisions in order to live within<br />
the reduced funding and the reduced borrowing capacity which<br />
has been agreed as a result of earlier Premier's<br />
S Conferences, we know that. I must say that having said to<br />
you that I recognise that you've had to make some tough<br />
decisions as a result of the previous Conferences, that I'm<br />
somewhat bemused and not a little annoyed by some who seek<br />
to convince the public and the media that there have been no<br />
hard economic or political decisions required of the<br />
Commonwealth in recent years, now that's a nonsense.<br />
The Commonwealth Budget surplus of $ 5.5B this year which<br />
is the second year in a row it didn't come out of thin air.<br />
Put very simply since the collapse in our terms of trade in<br />
1985 the Commonwealth and I want to emphasise this the<br />
Commonwealth is spending around $ 10B less on its own purpose<br />
programs. That's excluding payments to the States. We're<br />
spending since 1985 some $ 10B a year less on our own purpose<br />
programs. So let's not have any nonsense that the<br />
requirements are being placed simply upon other Governments.<br />
That's what we've done ourselves $ 10B less each year.<br />
While the Commonwealth has as you very much appreciate also<br />
cut payments to the States. The fact is that the strength<br />
of State revenue has allowed you to increase your<br />
Governments' own purpose spending by about 6% since 1984-85<br />
when as I say during that period our own purpose payments<br />
have declined. If the States own purpose general Government<br />
sector had matched Commonwealth outlays restrained over the<br />
that period, that fact is that States borrowings would be<br />
this year about $ 3B lower than in fact they are. On our<br />
current estimates that would be sufficient to wipe out the<br />
States nett borrowing requirement and to put the public<br />
sector as a whole in a position to repay substantial<br />
outstanding debt. </p>
<p>-3-<br />
In talking about our position it also ought to be understood<br />
colleagues that the improvement in the Commonwealth budget<br />
to which I've referred can't be attributed as some people<br />
sometimes try to do, can't be attributed to the so-called<br />
soft option of increasing revenue, because the fact is that<br />
the Commonwealth revenue of the share of GDP has remained<br />
virtually stable for the past five years. In other words<br />
our deficit reduction is not attributable to fiscal drag.<br />
Indeed the tax cuts of the first of July more than<br />
compensate for that.<br />
The other point that I want to make is to say to you that<br />
you are going to be significant beneficiaries of the April<br />
Statement, of the $ 5.5 billion tax-wage package that was<br />
brought down then because as you know the purpose of that<br />
package was not simply to do what needed to be done in terms<br />
of assistance to Australian families but also it was part of<br />
a wage trade-off whereby as a result of that $ 5.5 billion<br />
package the pressures for higher wage increases were<br />
reduced. And so we were able to look at a 6.5% wages<br />
outcome for 1989-90 which is significantly less than it<br />
would otherwise have been if we hadn't had that package.<br />
And to give an idea of what that means to you the fact is<br />
that every one per cent in wage restraint achieved through<br />
our economic policies saves your governments well over $ 200<br />
million each year. The simple fact is that if wage growth<br />
had repeated the experience of the last boom at the<br />
beginning of the ' 80s then the States would have been the<br />
sufferers. So we need also to restrain our overall call on debt. The<br />
Commonwealth has cut its call and as you know is repaying<br />
debt. The States in aggregate are continuing to acrue debt<br />
at broadly unchanged levels and that needs to be changed so<br />
that the private sector has the resources it needs for<br />
export expansion and import replacement.<br />
We don't in any sense seek to deny to you colleagues that<br />
the restraint that we are talking about is going to cause<br />
difficulties. So I know you want to tell us about those<br />
difficulties and I have no doubt that you will. We know<br />
that there'll be problems. I simply want to say to you what<br />
is unavoidably, unarguably true, and that is that if we<br />
don't take these difficult decisions now as governments with<br />
a combined sense of responsibility for the future of this<br />
country then the long term difficulties and penalties will<br />
be considerably greater and will be more enduring. So we're<br />
not in a situation of easy choice.<br />
So in summary colleagues before asking Paul to go into more<br />
detail into the economic context I simply want to say this<br />
to you, that we are meeting at a time when restraint by<br />
governments is absolutely necessary. We are in the<br />
document we've put in to you, making it clear that we want<br />
you to join with us in exercising very considerable </p>
<p>-4-<br />
( PM cont) restraint and that restraint is absolutely<br />
necessary if we're going to discharge our responsibilities<br />
to the people of this country and we believe that the<br />
strategy, the overall strategy of which this is part is the<br />
only strategy which is capable of addressing these<br />
fundamental external problems that we have of moderating the<br />
level of demand in Australia in a way which is going to<br />
enable us to meet those external problems. We trust that<br />
you'll understand that and be prepared constructively to<br />
play your part in the strategy which is necessary to deal<br />
with these challenges.<br />
Having said that I'll now ask the Treasurer to speak in some<br />
greater detail about the economic outlook to set the<br />
environment within which we will consider the items on the<br />
agenda of our meeting today Paul.<br />
ends<br />
0 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
