<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>21444</transcript-id>
    <title>Australia to Fund Transport Reform in the Pacific  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/08/2004</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
I am delighted to announce Australia will establish a $2 million fund to assist transport reform in the Pacific.</p>
<p>Leaders at this week's Pacific Islands Forum have supported a number of Australian recommendations drawn from the Pacific Regional Transport Study, which I initiated at last year's Forum.  In particular, they have endorsed the Apia Declaration of Principles on Regional Transport Services.</p>
<p>In their current state, many regional transport services are economically unsustainable and place an excessive burden on the economies of Forum island countries.</p>
<p>The recommendations propose practical measures to improve the economic efficiency and sustainability of the region's aviation and shipping sectors, including through the pooling of scarce regional resources.</p>
<p> The fund will give Forum island countries access to specialist economic, financial and legal expertise to help them make key policy decisions in the transport sector.</p>
<p>The maintenance of regular, reliable and competitive transport services is crucial to the economies of Forum island countries.  Recent changes in the transport sector, including the entry of low-cost competitors and new international safety and security requirements, will have significant implications for Pacific services.</p>
<p>Good governance, including sound processes for appointing boards, disclosure of financial statements, awarding of contracts and infrastructure decisions, will be essential to meet these challenges successfully.</p>
<p>Australia will continue to work closely with Forum island countries and the Forum secretariat on this important issue.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
