<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1458</transcript-id>
    <title>PM 126/1966 - PRIME MINISTER&#039;S CHRISTMAS MESSAGE TO AUSTRALIAN FORCES</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/12/1966</release-date>
    <release-type>Message</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001458.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>FOR PRESS P. M. No. 126/1966</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER'S CHRISTMAS MESSAGE TO AUSTRALIAN FORCES</p>
<p>The Prime Minister, Mr. Holt has sent the following message to Australian servicemen and women at home and overseas: " To all Australian servicemen and women I convey, as Prime Minister, the thanks and appreciation of the Australian people, and their warmest good wishes for your well-being and happiness<br />through the time of Christmas and throughout the coming year.<br />Australia is grateful to you for the personal contribution you are<br />making to the security of the nation. Behind the shield of protection<br />which members of our fighting services and our allies provide, this nation<br />is able to advance steadily in strength and prosperity.<br />" Some of you are actively engaged in operations of war.<br />We have followed with pride the story of your exploits, a story brightened<br />by the gallantry and devotion to duty you have demonstrated. Those of<br />you who are absent from Australia, whether on military operations, on<br />other active duty or joining in the tasks that enable us to honour our<br />international obligations, all have a special place in our regard. This<br />is true at all times, but you are much in our thoughts at that time of<br />year when most of your fellow -Australians can happily enjoy the love<br />and companionship of their families. We hope this deprivation will be<br />softened in some degree for you by the knowledge that you have our<br />heartfelt gratitude. " May the coming year bring a just, honourable and enduring<br />peace enabling many of you to be united with your families again in<br />1967." 1 HAROLD HOLT,</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER.<br />Canberra, 23rd December, 1966.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
