<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10177</transcript-id>
    <title>CHIEF SCIENTIST</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/11/1996</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010177.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Kertaken.<br />
The<br />
/ relopment. It<br />
' vided in a<br />
ch as<br />
as indirect<br />
roach to a<br />
issues already<br />
I Ito nto Taxation<br />
ap issues<br />
ns; and<br />
! levant<br />
) oth access<br />
analysis<br />
ccount. ) ehalf of<br />
) enable<br />
) ther<br />
i willibe PRIME MINISTER<br />
CHIEF SCIENTIST<br />
I am very pleased to announce that Dr John Stocker, former Chief Executive of<br />
CSIRLO, has been appointed the new Chief Scientist and Chairman of the Australian<br />
Science, Technology and Engineering Council ( ATSEC).<br />
Science and technology underpin much of Australia's economic and social<br />
development and it is essential that our considerable national investment in new<br />
knowledge is based on sound and well-considered advice.<br />
The position of Chief Scientist, or its equivalent, is one which the governments of<br />
many advanced. nations have found useful in dealing with the complexities of modern<br />
science and technology.<br />
Dr Stocker will provide advice on issues to which science and technology are relevant.<br />
he will assist the Government in ensuring that public investment in science and<br />
technology is directed in accordance with national priorities.<br />
By combining the positions of Chief Scientist and ASTEC Chairman, the Government<br />
will strengthen its sources of policy advice and ensure that the work of ASTEC<br />
continues to be directed to issues of the highest national importance.<br />
Dr Stocker will play an important role in bringing issues to the Prime Minister's<br />
Science and Engineering Council ( PMSEC). The Council provides a forum for the<br />
Prime Minister and other senior Ministers to discuss issues of national importance with<br />
key figures in science and technology, business and the general community.<br />
The Government thanks the former Chi ef Scientist, Professor Michael Pitman, for his<br />
services over the past four years. Since the election, Professor Pitman's advice has<br />
been particularly helpfil to the Minister for Science and Technology. Professor Pitman<br />
also served the previous government with distinction.<br />
22 November 1996 2223 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
