<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3586</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA AT A LUNCHEON GIVEN IN HIS HONOUR BY THE PRESIDENT OF YUGOSLAVIA IN BELGRADE ON 10 JANUARY 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/01/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003586.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Speech by the Prime Minister of Australia at a luncheon given<br />
in his honour by the President of Yugoslavia in Belgrade on<br />
lOJanuary 1975<br />
It is, indeed, a very great honor for us to have<br />
been received here by you, to have talked with<br />
you at such length and to have been shown<br />
such hospitality and kindness. Our countries<br />
have ties between them which reach back<br />
across two full generations. We began our cooperation<br />
back at the start of the World War I,<br />
and this co-operation was continued later during<br />
the course of World War II when Yugoslavia<br />
represented the only country in the whole of<br />
Europe which rebelled and fought against the<br />
occupiers. You, Mr President, belong to a group of older<br />
statesmen, distinguished men, who in their day<br />
rebelled with determination and who, in the<br />
end, won freedom for their people. This obligation<br />
you took on has been understood by you<br />
not just as an obligation to your people, but as<br />
one to the whole of mankind because you are<br />
among those who have demonstrated by your<br />
example and your acts, and, in the end, proved,<br />
the way in which freedom can be preserved and<br />
must be defended.<br />
Mr President, you have mentioned the hundreds<br />
of thousands of Yugoslavs who today live<br />
in Australia and you have also made note of certain<br />
problems which, from time to time, have<br />
come up in Australia itself and been the cause of<br />
difficulties in relations between Yugoslavia and<br />
Australia. These difficulties were created by just<br />
one, very small, group of people who betrayed<br />
their country during its most difficult moments,<br />
and then came to make difficulties in the country<br />
where they had chosen to make their homes.<br />
However, I want to assure you that the majority<br />
of Yugoslavs living in Australia today are very<br />
solid citizens. They are proud of their earlier<br />
homeland and they are loyal to their present<br />
country. Of course, the largest group of people<br />
in Australia's present-day population are of British<br />
descent. Next are those of Italian descent,<br />
and then, just behind, the Yugoslavs.<br />
Because increasingly intensive relations and<br />
co-operation exist between our two countries and because hundreds of thousands of your<br />
people already live in Australia, I am convinced-<br />
entirely sure-that all this must lead to<br />
better understanding and the development of<br />
better relations between our two countries.<br />
Yugoslavia is a highly diversified country.<br />
Different parts of your country were at different<br />
times under the occupation of different powers<br />
and countries. You have had different internal<br />
administrations within the framework of the<br />
country itself, and quite a few differences, likewise,<br />
in cultures. However, I must state that<br />
among the Yugoslavs living in Australia today a<br />
pride and satisfaction is to be noted at belonging<br />
to one unified Yugoslav community which was<br />
achieved thanks to your leadership. </p>
<p>comes from Yugoslavia, by realising that the activity<br />
of those people who had done much harm<br />
here must be thwarted, at least in your country<br />
in order to provide peace for those who went to<br />
work there honestly as citizens of Australia.<br />
You have helped greatly to improve the situation<br />
in this respect. It goes without saying, Mr<br />
Prime Minister, that all those who emigrated<br />
soon after the war are not negative, many<br />
people wish to forget the past and to work<br />
peacefully in your country. We have no objection<br />
to such people. Today, too, some of our<br />
people leave for your country. We put no obstacles<br />
in anybody's way, each may go where<br />
he wishes. These are Yugoslav citizens, honest<br />
people, and I am convinced that they, in your<br />
country too, will be equally good citizens, who<br />
will work in the interest of their new homeland<br />
-Australia. Many of them will return. You said,<br />
a while ago. that some of these people have vacation<br />
homes, small villas, on the Dalmatian<br />
Coast, and I think this is very nice. Such people<br />
are a bridge of friendship between our two<br />
countries. I would like to take this opportunity to express<br />
my satisfaction with the fact, also, that on many<br />
international questions we hold identical views.<br />
Our co-operation at the United Nations is very<br />
good. I think that many more possibilities exist,<br />
too, in other areas such as, let us say, the economic,<br />
to expand our co-operation. We import<br />
many raw materials from you, and Yugoslavia,<br />
for its part, has many things that it can export to<br />
your country. It would be a good thing for us to<br />
export more, too, because the economies of our<br />
two countries are complemetary and possibilities<br />
really do exist for us to expand this cooperation.<br />
Your visit to Yugoslavia, unfortunately, is very<br />
short. Furthermore, the weather at present here<br />
is not pleasant. Therefore, we hope that you will<br />
come to Yugoslavia when it is more at its best,<br />
warmer weather, and when you will be able to<br />
see more, including the beauties of our Adriatic.<br />
It is our hope, also, that as many as possible of<br />
your citizens will come to Yugoslavia.<br />
Yugoslavia today is a tourist country, very attractive<br />
to many, and so it will be a pleasure for<br />
us to have as many guests as possible from<br />
friendly Australia. In ending, I would like, Dear<br />
Friend, to emphasise once again how happy we are to have you with us today. I, myself, have<br />
wanted to meet you, to see you, because I had<br />
heard a great deal of the best about you, and I<br />
know that you are a friend of our country, as are<br />
your wife and associates. May I express the<br />
hope, Dear Friend, and Mrs Whitlam, that you<br />
will take the very best impressions with you<br />
when you leave our country. Australia is known<br />
in Yugoslavia as a friendly and progressive<br />
country whose aspiration it is to build as good<br />
and happy a life as possible where many people<br />
from Yugoslavia are working and making their<br />
contribution. </p>
<p>Speech by President Tito of Yugoslavia at a luncheon in honour of<br />
the Prime Minister of Australia in Belgrade on 10 January 1975<br />
I would like to express the great pleasure, of my<br />
wife, Jovanka, of myself and of all of us, to have<br />
you all here as our guests today. You have come<br />
from a far-away country geographically but one<br />
close-by in terms of aspirations and outlook on<br />
the world, in terms of efforts for the best possible<br />
relations throughout the entire world, in<br />
terms of eliminating, as soon as possible, the<br />
various negative features which even today are<br />
still burdening our world.<br />
Many of our countrymen live in your country...<br />
some arrived before the last war, and<br />
others immediately after that war, but these are<br />
two categories of people who differ in many ways. Those who originally left Yugoslavia to go<br />
to your country did so because of economic<br />
need, because they lived in great poverty. But<br />
among those who went immediately after the<br />
last war, there were those who were traitors,<br />
who had collaborated with the occupiers and<br />
committed terrible crimes-crimes you and<br />
your people did not know about. Naturally these<br />
two categories of our people who found a home<br />
in your friendly country had to come into conflict<br />
and to hate each other, to a situation which was<br />
not in the interest of our two countries. I know<br />
that you, personally, Mr Prime Minister, and<br />
your Government, have done a great favour to<br />
us by realising that it is not all the same who<br />
The Prime Minister in talks in Belgrade with the Prime Minister of Yugoslavia. Mr Bijedic </p>
<p>national community. We have failed to grasp<br />
opportunities to set the world on the path to<br />
peace: We have failed to eliminate the threat of<br />
war: we have failed to regulate the development<br />
and proliferation of the instruments of war. The<br />
threat posed by the production and proliferation<br />
of nuclear weapons is the most awesome ever<br />
posed to the future of mankind. The development<br />
of measures to eliminate the threat of<br />
nuclear war is therefore the most pressing issue<br />
which confronts us.<br />
The issues which symbolise the change in Australian<br />
foreign policy under my Governmentand<br />
the increasing similarity of approach between<br />
Australia and Yugoslavia-are<br />
colonialism and racism. It is my conviction that<br />
the most significant historical trend since the<br />
Second World War has been the struggle to end<br />
imperialism, colonialism and racial discrimination.<br />
One of my first actions after coming to<br />
power was to instruct our representatives at the<br />
United Nations to add Australia's voice to the<br />
international condemnation of colonialism and<br />
racism. We have supported all actions in the<br />
United Nations against the illegal racist regime<br />
in Rhodesia and against the infamous policy of<br />
apartheid. Recently Australia voted in the<br />
Security Council for the expulsion of South<br />
Africa from the United Nations for its twentyeight-<br />
year-long flouting of the most basic principles<br />
of the Charter: we have joined the United<br />
Nations Council on Namibia: reactivated our<br />
membership of the United Nations Committee<br />
of Twenty-four: and are providing assistance to<br />
subject peoples in their fight for liberation.<br />
In pursuing more independent policies, my<br />
Government has sought to identify the common<br />
interests which Australia shares with a broad<br />
range of countries. Australia straddles many of<br />
the categories which are often used to distinguish<br />
countries-namely, the developed<br />
from the developing, the rich from the poor, the<br />
second from the third world, the producers from<br />
the consumers, the aligned from the nonaligned.<br />
Ours is a developed country, yet the<br />
foundations of much of our prosperity on primary<br />
production and the export of minerals has<br />
made us conscious of the problems faced by<br />
both producers and consumers. As a<br />
predominantly European community in the<br />
Asian and Pacific region, we are conscious of<br />
the pressing requirements of our neighbours. As a comparatively rich country, we accept the<br />
responsibility of extending asistance to the<br />
developing countries. Bound by treaty to the<br />
United States, we nonetheless respect and seek<br />
to understand further the views of those<br />
countries which have chosen to espouse nonalignment.<br />
The bilateral relations between Australia and<br />
Yugoslavia are strong and cordial. My visit will<br />
help to strengthen them. Many migrants of<br />
Yugoslav origin live in Australia. Their skills and<br />
initiative have contributed to Australia's<br />
progress and form an enduring bond between<br />
our nations. I believe, Mr Prime Minister, that<br />
after your visit to Australia you were satisfied<br />
that my Government is determined to do all in<br />
its power to prevent and punish criminal acts of<br />
terrorism directed against Yugoslavia by a small<br />
minority of malcontents and undesirables. You<br />
may be assured that we will hold firmly to our<br />
commitment. Trade between our countries is growing and<br />
there is every sign that it will grow further. It is<br />
my hope that we shall soon enter into long-term<br />
agreements for increased trade. I hope to see a<br />
greatly increased flow of private business,<br />
officials and experts between our two countries.<br />
Recent negotiations leading to the conclusion of<br />
a bilateral civil aviation agreement covering<br />
flights of your national airline to Australia and<br />
ours to Belgrade is a positive contribution to this<br />
goal. Negotiations for the conclusion of a<br />
Cultural Agreement are well advanced.<br />
The relationship between Australia and<br />
Yugoslavia is based on an affinity of views on<br />
the fundamentals of the international order. An<br />
interdependent world demands co-operation<br />
rather than confrontation: and no state, however<br />
great, should threaten the independence of<br />
another state, however small. These shared beliefs,<br />
and the opportunities and demands presented<br />
by a troubled world, form the basis of a<br />
friendship that will be healthy and beneficial for<br />
our two countries, and a constructive contribution<br />
to the wider needs of peace and understanding<br />
in the world. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
