<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10773</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP DOORSTOP INTERVIEW OLD PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/02/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Very nostalgic to be back.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What did you think of Costello's speech today?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I didn't hear it but I knew what he was going to say.</p>
<p>   I've known his views on this for some time.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What did you think of his model?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, what did we both think of Mr McGarvie's model? I made</p>
<p>   my views clear on this to McGarvie's model yesterday. I said</p>
<p>   that it was the least worst of the alternative options to the present</p>
<p>   system. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>If it became the basis for the referendum question, would you as</p>
<p>   Prime Minister support it?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I don't deal in hypotheticals. I think if you read my speech</p>
<p>   yesterday, which was a very carefully put together statement of</p>
<p>   my strongly held beliefs, you have a full comprehensive statement</p>
<p>   of where I stand on this issue. Unlike my opponent, Mr Beazley,</p>
<p>   I haven't waved around in the shifting constitutional breezes</p>
<p>   like some kind of confused weather vane. I've had a very strong</p>
<p>   and consistent and resolute view on this issue. I believe in the</p>
<p>   quality of our present system. I believe of the alternatives, none</p>
<p>   of which I support against the present system, of course, but of</p>
<p>   those, the McGarvie model is preferable to the other two.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, would you bind the Government or the Cabinet to</p>
<p>   a yes or no case in a referendum?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look, I have made it very clear that we have a free or open vote.</p>
<p>   I made that clear yesterday. We're not like the Labor Party</p>
<p>   on these sorts of issues. It's free or open vote. I made that</p>
<p>   clear yesterday.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>So in a referendum you might be going one direction and Mr Costello</p>
<p>   another.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It is a free vote. I'm not conceding anything in relation</p>
<p>   to individuals. I'm just making the point that it's a</p>
<p>   free vote.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Does it make it difficult, though, for you to go to a referendum</p>
<p>   [inaudible]?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>When you have a free vote - we've had free votes before, you</p>
<p>   may not have been around as long as other people - we've had</p>
<p>   free votes on quite a number of issues and these are the sorts of</p>
<p>   issues where one ought to have free votes.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Have other senior Ministers told you they favour a republic?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>When you have a free vote people can say what they want.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Beazley has called for you to go a few steps further like Mr</p>
<p>   Costello...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Why won't I do it, I mean, I thought your problem was that</p>
<p>   I was poll driven. Now you want me to be poll driven. You characters</p>
<p>   have got to make up your mind. I have a very, very simple view on</p>
<p>   this and that is that you say what you believe. You don't bend</p>
<p>   in the breeze, according to the latest opinion poll, like Mr Beazley</p>
<p>   has. Now, Mr Beazley looked at the opinion polls and said: Gee,</p>
<p>   there's 78 per cent in favour of a directly elected President.</p>
<p>   I'd like to have a slice of that action. I really would'</p>
<p>   So what do we do. We change. We go down to Hobart. We say: Well,</p>
<p>   I sort of probably am in favour of two-thirds of it. Gee, if that's</p>
<p>   not going to get up, I'll go right over to a directly elected</p>
<p>   President.'</p>
<p>I mean, I've had a consistent view. I don't care who</p>
<p>   knows it. The Australian people respect people who stand by what</p>
<p>   they believe in. And the most important thing that I ought to say</p>
<p>   is that I guarantee the Australian people a referendum. </p>
<p>I saw a curious article in the papers this morning saying that</p>
<p>   it was odd for a person who opposed a change to support a referendum.</p>
<p>   What I'm doing is supporting democracy and I'm supporting</p>
<p>   democracy very strongly. And everybody wants a vote on this issue.</p>
<p>   The monarchists want a vote, the republicans want a vote and I'm</p>
<p>   going to give them a vote. And as far as I'm concerned that</p>
<p>   is what the Australian people want and from me they are guaranteed</p>
<p>   to get it. And what's more, they will always get from me an</p>
<p>   honest statement of my position on this issue, unlike the weather</p>
<p>   vane in Western Australia who leads the Labor Party at the present</p>
<p>   time.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What chance would any republic question have of getting up if the</p>
<p>   Prime Minister of the day...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look, I am not going to start dealing - I'm not going to give</p>
<p>   you a political science lecture on the steps of Old Parliament House.</p>
<p>   We are dealing with a very interesting convention. I think it's</p>
<p>   going very well. It's a very good exercise in shared participation</p>
<p>   in the democratic process of this country. And there's a spirit</p>
<p>   of cooperation and common purpose working for the good of Australia</p>
<p>   abroad and I think that's terrific. I think it's a great</p>
<p>   idea this convention.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>You said it it's to happen it should be a unifying event for</p>
<p>   Australia.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think it's been very unifying over the past few weeks.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Could it happen with you are opposing it?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>You really are remarkable, Michael. You're quite remarkable.</p>
<p>   I meant not taking notice of the polls, but when you don't</p>
<p>   agree with me not taking any notice of the polls I've then</p>
<p>   got to take notice of them.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>If you agree there is disquiet in the Monarchy?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look, I made my speech on the substance of the issue. Don't</p>
<p>   ask me that in a doorstop.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>If there is quite a serious split at the end of the 10 days or</p>
<p>   approaching the end of the 10 days, would you intervene to try and</p>
<p>   get some consensus?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Malcolm, I'm not going to telegraph my punches. I put my position</p>
<p>   down yesterday on the substance. It couldn't have been clearer.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>But is that a function of your leadership role?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I think I've displayed leadership on this issue. I haven't</p>
<p>   bobbed around in the ocean like that weather vane of Western Australia.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, can you understand Mr Costello's view?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes, he explained it to me in English.</p>
<p>Yes, he explained it to me in English.</p>
<p>[Ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
