<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2534</transcript-id>
    <title>&#039;THIS DAY TONIGHT&#039; - INTERVIEW GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT HON WILLIAM MCMAHON CH MP ON ABC NATIONAL TELEVISION - 14 FEBRUARY 1972 - INTERVIEWER: RICHARD CARLETON</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/02/1972</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002534.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
" THIS DAY TONIGHT"<br />
INTERVIEW GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT HON.<br />
WILLIAM McMAHON, CH, MP ON ABC NATIONAL TELEVISION 14 FEBRUARY 1972<br />
Interviewer : Richard Carleton<br />
Q. Mr McMahon, the Premiers' Conferenc&amp; today-. one<br />
cannot help but feel is something of a char-ade. It has all-:<br />
happened before. The Premiers come to Canberra on Sunday<br />
night, breathing fire and brim stone. They come and meet<br />
you in the cordiality of the Cabinet Room and it's all over.<br />
The Commonwealth makes a concession. There is no long-term<br />
solution that has come out of any of these Premiers'<br />
Conferences. Is there one in the future?<br />
PM: I don't think there is. And certainly there<br />
couldn't be one under present circumstances when wages are<br />
rising so rapidly and the'States are unable to tax to the<br />
extent necessary to recoup the moneys. In other words<br />
Q. Would the....<br />
PM: Look, please don't interrupt when I am trying<br />
to give an answer to what is a tremendously important<br />
natimhal problem. This is important. In cases like this,<br />
it is not a charade. In fact, I have done my best to<br />
ensure that they are listened to with attention, we take<br />
notice of what they have said and we adapt our policies as<br />
far as we practicalaly can and as far as we think it is wise<br />
to'meet their wishes.<br />
Q. But you called it a pilgrimage yourself, this<br />
evening.<br />
PM: I did call it a pilgrimage but that does not<br />
necessarily mean to say it is a charade. There is a totally<br />
different meaning of the two words. What I do believe is<br />
that they played a contribution, a marked contribution towards<br />
an understanding of the problem and towards the solution<br />
of it. Far from being a charade, it was a valuable exercise<br />
and one that will be of benefit for the nation.<br />
Q. They will be back in June and apparently the<br />
same thing will be played out again. They will be back in<br />
February next year. There is no solution to the States' </p>
<p>long-term problems of finance.<br />
PM: PM: Q. PM: There is no solution to this if present<br />
conditions continue.. But what I have done in order<br />
that we can get the most detailed and careful analysis<br />
of this, I have asked the Australian National University<br />
to establish a small school of the top-thinking economist<br />
we have got in the country and I hope two of. the most<br />
important and capable civil servants we have had<br />
Sir John Crawford and the former Secretary to the<br />
Treasury, Sir Richard Randall. A school will be<br />
established so that we will know the facts associated<br />
with CommonwealthStt rltin and see if they can<br />
come up with a better answer.<br />
Mr McMahon, forgive me, but the problem has<br />
been with Australia virtually since the lastwar when<br />
the States gave up their income taxing power8. Now in<br />
1972, you are proposing an investigation which will<br />
produce a possible solution in years to come. In the<br />
next three or four years<br />
I don't think so at all, with great respect<br />
to you. These men know the dangers and the difficulties<br />
and they have been specifically charged with the objective<br />
of getting an answ6r as soon as they can, and as and when<br />
they are able to give us solutiorsor recommendations, they<br />
will do it. You are not seeing this in twelve months'<br />
time, or anything, though?<br />
I don't know how long it will take, but so<br />
long as we get an answer and I must impress this upon<br />
you that while wages go up the way they are, between<br />
11 and 13 per cent per annum, or averaqe earnings go up<br />
at that rate, it is not going to be an easy solution, and<br />
the solution has not been found in any other country of<br />
the world. </p>
<p>Well, I will come to wages in just one<br />
moment, but can I raise a point that you made in your<br />
opening address to the Premiers today where you spoke<br />
of " excessively gloomy views being put about" and this<br />
giving rise to lack of confidence in the community.<br />
Would you name for me the people you claim are putting<br />
about " excessively gloomy views"?<br />
PM: Q. PM: Q. No, of course I won't but it is commonly<br />
practised and why should I enter into an argument with<br />
a particular individual. In fact I don't like speaking<br />
about individuals. There is too much discussion about<br />
them already. I believe in policies. I believe in saying<br />
" Here is a problem. This is the way we are going to solve<br />
it" but I do have-to stress that people don't quit4<br />
understand, for example, the problem of unemployment;<br />
because I pointed out if you look at it in what is<br />
called and now I am using academic language<br />
" seasonally adjusted figures for unemployment", you<br />
will find that the figures are not far different from<br />
the long-term average, and our figures are better than<br />
any other country in the world. These are points that<br />
have to be made. The talk of seasonal arguments and the<br />
like has gone on for some time<br />
But what you have got to do about them,<br />
you've got to understand them. And I would like even,<br />
to try and give you, if I Could, an explanation of why<br />
the seasonal figures are the ones that you lookza+, But<br />
go on, you ask me further questions now.<br />
Well, Sir, I won't go into the seasonal<br />
points because I don't want to bring up the matters you<br />
brought up in the House yourself last year not<br />
looking at the seasonal figures but rather at the<br />
absolute figures. </p>
<p>4.<br />
PM: Well I said that one was the one that was<br />
emotive in quality and that created the greatest public<br />
interest and could be used for political purposes.<br />
But if you want to look at it for economic and national<br />
purposes, the figures that you should look at are the<br />
seasonally adjusted figures.<br />
Q. Well, now just to go back to the excessively<br />
gloomy views, one of the problems that you ' have said<br />
you are facing yourself is that these views are being<br />
put about, So I don't understand why you won't name the<br />
persons who are responsible for it.<br />
PM: Because it is not my practice to be naming<br />
persons. I believe in fighting the issues, as I said<br />
before, and every time you get a Prime Minister naming<br />
people, irritating them, then it has a counter-reaction 0<br />
and the ones that suffer are people like myself,-and you<br />
get into a kind of a bra~ 4l that does nobody any good.<br />
We are here to solve national problems and that is what<br />
we will do.<br />
Q. Let's come now to the spiral<br />
of which you spoke a moment ago. The argument of the<br />
ACTU through Mr Hawke is that the Unions cannot be<br />
expected to hold back on their wage demands whilst the<br />
Federal Government makes no constructive policy towards<br />
price control.<br />
PM: The problem here is to understand causes<br />
and effects, and Mr Hawke knows the answer just as well<br />
as I do. And the cause of our problems today is that<br />
average earnings are rising so substantially between<br />
11 and 13 per cent. Now the simple fact is that if wages<br />
rise, earnings rise greater than productivity increases<br />
which are about 2 per cent, you must get-built into that<br />
a cost inflationay factor of the difference between the<br />
two. It is inevitable that it will happen. So if Mr<br />
Hawke cares to get on the platform or on television and<br />
talk about the realities of life, he will be driven to<br />
the con~ lusion that the primary cause is wages and this is<br />
one that we have to find the answer to, if possible, through<br />
the Arbitration system. </p>
<p>Q. Implicit in Mr Hawke's argument seems to be<br />
PM: I did ask you a few minutes ago if you would<br />
let me finish...<br />
Q. Sorry, I thought you had finished.<br />
PM No, I hadn't quite finished. . But what I<br />
wanted to end, therefore, is this question of prices.<br />
Naturally enough, we are giving a great deal of<br />
consideration to this problem of prices, but it is not<br />
a problem that you want to go creating the impression<br />
" Well we are having conferences about it to see what we<br />
can do" because if you did, then I think you would find<br />
quite a number of people in the community would be<br />
bumping up their prices in anticipation of what-is likely<br />
to happen in the days to come. But nonetheless we don't<br />
within the Cabinet, of course we discuss the whole of the<br />
national economy and every single aspect of it and we will<br />
continue to do so.<br />
Q. Sir,' the Government's last Budget, the Budget<br />
you supervised as Prime Minister was styled as an<br />
" anti-inflationary" Budget.<br />
PM: Who styled it that?<br />
Q. Well, it has been styled that way not only<br />
by the commentators, of course, but by your own Ministers,<br />
and by your own Treasurer.<br />
PM: Well let me correct you, please, because<br />
Mr Snedden is my Treasurer, and I, too, have said it<br />
was a Budget that was designed for several purposes,<br />
not one. The first one was that w( should ens ure growth<br />
and that we should keep unemployment down. They are<br />
two objectives. The second of them is enormously<br />
important to me personally, and I have wanted to keep<br />
unemployment to a low rate ever since I have been in<br />
the Government, over 21 years. And the third, the major </p>
<p>problem we face today, a long-term problem, is how do<br />
we handle the problem of wage increases and, consequently,<br />
of inflation. So when you say it was singularly or<br />
solely an anti-inflationary policy, that isn't accurate.<br />
There were three objectives in our policy.<br />
well insofar as inflation has continued since the<br />
Budget for the seven months since the Budget, plus the<br />
concessions you made today to boost employment, do you<br />
then acknowledge that the strategy, the third point of the<br />
strategy of the Budget to control inflation has failed?<br />
No, I don't because again I think you must<br />
try and understand the difference between the powers that<br />
we can exercise and what we try to do. Now there are<br />
two different types of inflation one is what you call<br />
demand inflation*-and that is the old classical fotm of<br />
inflation too much demand chasing too few goods.<br />
There is a second kind that is quite new to us, and that<br />
is the rapid increase in wages that has been occurring<br />
in recent months Which you are hoping to control?<br />
Which we hope to slow down and finally control.<br />
But we in the Commonwealth have very little powers because<br />
other than in our Territories, the ACT and the Northern<br />
Territory, we have no power whatsoever to control.<br />
other than through the Arbitration system.<br />
If the problem is really serious, Sir, why<br />
don't you seek those powers?<br />
Go to a referendum?<br />
Yes. Yes, we could probably do that-but that is a<br />
process that would take about nine months at least to<br />
become effective. It is seven months since the last Budget and<br />
in that time you haven't been able to control inflation.<br />
No, but we did feel frankly, when I want<br />
away, up to Queensland at the end of December, I was fairly<br />
certain we had got it where we had seen the glimmerings of<br />
PM: Q. PM. Q.<br />
PM: Q. PM:<br />
Q. PM: </p>
<p>7.<br />
a prospect of bringing it under control because the<br />
Arbitration Commission in what is called the Carpenters'<br />
Case had acted with sweet reason and had shown that<br />
wage increases were beyond the capacity of the community<br />
to sustain or to pay. To my horror, we then found that the<br />
Electricity Commission of Victoria went and gave a 9 per cent<br />
increase beyong our capacity to control. And. then the<br />
Municipal Officers got an increase. And-. then the claim<br />
was made by the Electricity Commission for an extra week's<br />
leave. Now all these things have happened since December,<br />
at a time, as I have said, and subsequent to the time when<br />
I felt that at long last we had got this problem under<br />
control.<br />
Q. Well if that glimmer, Sir, just to conclude<br />
with on this point, if that glimmer of hope that you<br />
have is dimmed for the rest of this year, could you<br />
now give a pointer that'you might .466k powers for the<br />
Commonwealth to control wage increage?<br />
PM: Well what we are trying to do first of all<br />
is to look at the problem of containment, or isolation-<br />
I used the word today of isolating these three cases<br />
to Victoria. If we can do that, and we will try to the<br />
maximum of our capacity, then we can see another glimmer<br />
of light in the difficulties in front of us. But now I<br />
must confess I will be looking at this question of<br />
greater Constitutional powers for the Commonwealth.<br />
, In my view, the one area where, if we are to exercisip<br />
ouerall economic management, the one area where &amp; should<br />
try and get greater powers is to see what we can do in<br />
terms of this control of the wage structure. But we<br />
couldn't do it directly and we would never want to do<br />
it directly. We would want to do L~ t through the<br />
Arbitration Commission.<br />
Q. Mr McMahon, thank you for speaking on<br />
" This Day Tonight". </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
