<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3903</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER ON HSV7&#039;S THIS WEEK PROGRAM, SUNDAY 28 SEPTEMBER 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/09/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003903.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER ON HSV7' S THIS WEEK PROGRAM<br />
SUNDAY 28 SEPTEMBER 1975<br />
You will have noticed that in Melbourne this week-<br />
Wednesday, Thursday and Friday there was a second meeting of<br />
the Australian Constitutional Convention. The first meeting<br />
took place in Sydney in September 1973. That meeting, the<br />
Convention set up, unanimously, committees and working parties<br />
to prepare for the next meeting. And then over the last three<br />
months all the Premiers in Australia and I have co-operated<br />
in arrangements for this meeting of the Convention in<br />
Melbourne. We all drew up an agenda which we thought we<br />
should make in order to make more modern and effective<br />
arrangements between us for the government of Australia.<br />
These arrangements were in fact supported by the Federal<br />
Opposition. A month ago Mr Fraser, the Leader of the<br />
Opposition, spoke in the House of Representatives in<br />
these terms: " It's our hope that this Convention will be<br />
Affika useful forum in which Federal and State<br />
0 representatives may constructively consider<br />
Constitutional reform in a way which will<br />
advance the good government of Australia.<br />
The Co~ istitutional Con-vention will provide<br />
a place where constructive efforts may be made<br />
to work out constitutional reform. The<br />
Opposition is glad that the Constitutional<br />
Convention will be reconvened in Melbourne<br />
in September."<br />
Now those were fine words. I agreed with all ofU<br />
0 them. And yet what happened? When we camne along to<br />
Melbourne last Wednesday, all the Liberal leaders were<br />
absent. The agenda had been announced three weeks before<br />
by the Deputy Premier of Victoria, Mr Thompson, and he<br />
expressed the hope which we all share, that this will<br />
O be a fruitful meeting of the Convention.<br />
But the very next day,' after Mr Thompson spoke,<br />
Mr Bjelke-Petersen, the Premier of Queensland, said that<br />
Queensland wouldn't be sendling a delegation. Then the next<br />
day the Premier of Western Australia, Sir Charles Court,<br />
said that Western Australia wouldn't be sending a delegation.<br />
And then Mr Lewis did the same for New South Wales and last<br />
of all Mr Hamer for Victoria. And then bringing up the<br />
rear, Mr Fraser let it be known that he wouldn't. So all<br />
the noble words, all the work of two years went to nothing.<br />
Nevertheless there was a full delegation from South Australia,<br />
a full delegation from Tasmania, a full delegation from<br />
local government throughout Australia, a full delegation<br />
from the Northern Territory and from the Australian Capital<br />
Territory and of course, the Australian Government. </p>
<p>2.<br />
Now the idea didn't come from the Australian<br />
Government; it came from the Victorian Parliament in 1972.<br />
It wasn't a Labor gathering; a majority of the people who<br />
should have-been there and a majority of the people who were,<br />
in fact, there, didn't belong to the Labor Party. But<br />
nevertheless we went through the agenda, we agreed on<br />
proposals for the Federal Government to-put to the people<br />
to reform the Constitution. We agreed on proposals for<br />
the State Governments to refer matters to the Federal<br />
Parliament under the Constitution.<br />
Over the road on the opening day the Liberal<br />
leaders throughout Australia met and issued a statement on<br />
Federalism. It's amazing theydidn't choose to turn up and<br />
debate it and discuss it with us. But the significant thing<br />
about it was and this is the real reason why they boycotted<br />
the Convention on the agenda was provision for local<br />
0, government. Because, obviously, if you're looking at<br />
constitutional arrangements in Australia today, you ought to<br />
make it possible for the Federal Government to have<br />
financial relations; to borrow money, to make assistance<br />
o available to local governments as well as to the State<br />
governments, and that's what we decided at the Convention.<br />
And this is the key to the Liberal objection, because the<br />
Liberal Governments, starting with the Victorian State<br />
Government, have~ been opposing Federal financial assistance<br />
for local government. They've challenged this in the High<br />
Court and programs, for instance, for child care, preschools,<br />
projects for aged, homeless, handicapped and aboriginal peo~ ple,<br />
isolated children, health centres, legal aid offices, nursing<br />
homes and home nursing, meals on wheels, flying doctor services,<br />
blood transfusion serVices, all these are under challenge in<br />
the High Court, by State Liberal Governments. The Liberalo<br />
0 if they got the chance would cut off assistance for local<br />
government and for community providence.<br />
That's why they boycotted the Constitutional<br />
0 Convention this week in Melbourne.<br />
NOW </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
