<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9927</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON PJ KEATING MP WILL MR HOWARD AND HIS SENIOR SHADOW MINISTERS DEBATE THEIR LABOR COUNTERPARTS?</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/01/1996</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009927.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL: 28. Jan. 96 10: 43 No. 004 P. 01'.<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON PJ KEATING MP<br />
WILL MR HOWARD AND HIS SENIOR SHADOW MINISTERS DEBATE<br />
THEIR LABOR COUNTERPARTS?<br />
Yesterday, I challenged Mr Howard to two head-to-head debates, and to<br />
other debates which will give electors a chance to judge in more detail both<br />
the policy differences and the leadership differences between Labor and the<br />
Coalition. Mr Howard agreed to the head-to-head debates, but he appeared to baulk at<br />
the idea of debates which would pit himself and the Coalition's three most<br />
senior shadow ministers against their counterparts in the Government<br />
namely, himself, Mr Fischer, Mr Costello and Mr Downer against myself, Mr<br />
Beazley, Mr Willis and Senator Evans.<br />
There can be no good reason to refuse these debates. Yesterday,<br />
Mr Howard suggested debates between junior ministers instead If this is<br />
really what he Is offering it is a lame excuse for not exposing to public<br />
scrutiny the people who would be most powerful in a Howard government.<br />
I renew the challenge to Mr Howard:<br />
Will the man who would be Prime Minister, and the man who would be<br />
Deputy Prime Minister, and the man who would be Treasurer, and the<br />
man who would be Minister for Foreign Affairs in a Coalition, publicly<br />
debate the future of Australia with the people who presently fill these<br />
roles in the Labor Government?<br />
CANBERRA 28 January 1996 9/ 96 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
