<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8280</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINSITER LAUNCH OF THE ENERGY GUIDE SUDNEY - 12 APRIL 1991</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/04/1991</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008280.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Z,<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
rHEIC AGAINST DMLIVER EMBARCOEn UNTIL nDFLIVPRY<br />
SPEECH DY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
LAUNCH OF THE ENERGY GUIDE<br />
SYDNEY 12 APRIL 1991<br />
The issue of weather and climate change has been around for<br />
quite some time.<br />
Last century the editorial writer of an American newspaper<br />
commented that " everybody talks about the weather but nobody<br />
does anything about it".<br />
You can't say that: anymore. The activities of humanity have<br />
started to exert et profound and an unhealthy influence on<br />
the earth and its atmosphere, resulting in the emergence of<br />
" The Greenhouse Effect" as a global environmental problen.<br />
In the spirit of the newspaper editorialist, we must do<br />
something about this accelerated global warming and its<br />
potentially drastic effects, and we must do it now.<br />
The need for energy conservation and efficiency is<br />
paramount. Last year, my Government adopted an interim plannin target<br />
of stabilising emissions of greenhouse gases by thw year<br />
2000, and reducing them by the year 2005 to 20% below their<br />
1988 levels.<br />
Of course, we had already adopted a policy of phasing out<br />
CFCs and halons ( ozone depleting gases and also greenhouse<br />
gases) by 1997, three years ahead of the scheduled proposed<br />
by the Montreal Protocol.<br />
These sorts of measures are a matter of great pride for me<br />
personally and for this Government.<br />
much of the focus about our environmental achievements over<br />
the years has been on domestic issues. But Australia has<br />
also been steadily building up a record of strength on<br />
international environmental issues which is second to none.<br />
Truly global issues such as the Greenhouse Effect, depletion<br />
of the ozone layer and ecologically sustainable development<br />
are assuming increasing importance world-wide. G~ -1: 1 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
