<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5940</transcript-id>
    <title>WORLD FOOD DAY</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/10/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005940.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
L 1&amp; A) -9<br />
EMBARC-O: MIAJOR hVENIING NEWS<br />
~ J4BULLETINS ON 16.10.82<br />
-Z-&gt; V<br />
FOR MEDIA SATURDAY, OCTOBER 16 1982<br />
WORLD FOOD DAY<br />
Today is World Food Day, and I want to take this opportunity<br />
to talk to you about the problems of hunger and poverty,<br />
about what the world is doing to try to solve those prohlems,<br />
and about how Australia is contributing,.<br />
We sometimes become preoccupied by what we see as significant<br />
problems here in Australia, and there is no doubt that many<br />
of these problems are real. But it doesn't hurt to remem,, ber<br />
that there are vast numbers of people in the wvorld ! aho are<br />
much worse off than we are. . In a relatively affluent country like<br />
Australia, it is easy to forget that about 1,000 million<br />
people in the world have an income of no more than $ 200<br />
a year.<br />
That means they have less than 55 a day to spend on food,<br />
clothing, housing, transport and all the other services that<br />
most Australians take for granted. Those people live in<br />
inadequate housing, without proper water supplies, roads,<br />
electricity, medical services or education. What is worse,<br />
many of them do not even have enough to eat. They can't<br />
go down to a corner shop and buy a loaf of bread w~. hen<br />
they are hungry: if there was a corner store, in all<br />
likelihood its shelves would be empty.<br />
What is particularly tragic is that the world grows enough<br />
food to feed everyone, yet the problems of hunger and poverty<br />
are getting worse, not better. At the international level,<br />
various things have been done to try to overcome these<br />
appalling problems.-<br />
Attempts have been made to try to arrange for a better<br />
distribution of food throughout the world, to provide<br />
better access to world markets for the products of developing<br />
countries, to provide better financial arrangements for<br />
those countries and to help them with their energy, problems.<br />
But these initiatives have so far had only limited results.<br />
There is still1 a great deal to be done. Wle have been<br />
particularly disappointed that attempts to launch major<br />
negotiations on the problems of developing countries have<br />
so far been unsuccessful. Efforts must continue, because<br />
the need for international solutions to those problems is<br />
urgent. / 2 </p>
<p>I am sure most Australians would agree that poverty and hunger<br />
are among the greatest problems which humanity faces, and<br />
as one of the world's major trading nations as one of the<br />
largest food exporting nations Australia is in a position<br />
to help significantly. Indeed, we have already done a number<br />
of important things. We played a. nmajor role at, the Commonwealth<br />
Heads of Government Meeting in Melbourne last year which did<br />
so much to get the international com: munity to think more about<br />
how to tackle these problems, and we are continuing to play<br />
an active role in international fornums to try to get all<br />
countries to recognise that poverty and hunger are calamities<br />
for mankind, and that solutions must be found.<br />
This year the Australian Government will spend nearly $ 740 million<br />
on aid to the world's developing countries.. We are also<br />
providing technical assistance and advisers to help those<br />
countries to develop their own agricultural resources, and<br />
to help them build roads and dams and other essential<br />
services. The new Australian Centre for International<br />
Agricultural Research will ensure that Australia's agricultural<br />
research skills are used as effectively as possible to<br />
help developing countries increase their own food production.<br />
Trade is one of the major engines of economic development,<br />
and significant barriers to trade are one of the factors<br />
holding back the development of many of the poorer countries<br />
of the world. There is an urgent need for all countries,<br />
acting together, to reduce obstacles to trade, and developing<br />
countries would be major beneficiaries if agreement to do<br />
so could be reached.<br />
Australia was one of the first countries to give special<br />
preferences to a range of imports from less developed<br />
countries. We have initiated studies of the particular trade<br />
problems that developing countries face, and we have put<br />
proposals to international meetings on world economic and<br />
trade problems which, if adopted, would help developing<br />
countries significantly.<br />
But there is still a need for more energy for a much<br />
greater commitment by all countries acting together to<br />
tackle the trade problems faced by the developing nations.<br />
Greater access to world markets is by far the best way<br />
to enable developing countries to stand on their own feet,<br />
and to become less dependent on official aid, and to be<br />
able to do something about the standard of life for their own<br />
people.<br />
The greatest single problem faced by many developing countries<br />
remains that of food security. There is an urgent need to<br />
increase food production in a large number of countries, and<br />
an equally urgent need to ensure that those countries<br />
consistently have sufficient supplies of food at reasonable<br />
prices. </p>
<p>Australia has done a great deal to help to solve this<br />
problem. This year. we will provide about 450,000 tonnes<br />
of grain for food for needy countries, and we have called<br />
on other countries to increase their food aid. In addition,<br />
we are helping developing countries to increase the productivity<br />
of their own farms so that they are able more easily to<br />
feed themselves. Internationally, work has been done on<br />
securing awheat price stabilisation agreement and to<br />
encourage the building up of food stocks so that reserve<br />
supplies will be available in times of particular need.<br />
But progress has been slow, and in many countries despite<br />
what has been done the problem of food security is greater<br />
today than it was 20 years ago.<br />
The problems of hunger and poverty are significant and<br />
tragic indeed. If the international community cannot agree<br />
on action to be taken together, then mankind will not only<br />
carry a heavy responsibility for failing to solve these<br />
serious human problems, its failure also will. contribute<br />
to international instability and make thewr] c1 a riore<br />
difficult place than it already is.<br />
Australians are increasingly becoming aware of this, and<br />
th6 Government will continue to use every avenue open to<br />
it! to play its part in overcoming world-wide poverty and<br />
hunger. World Food Day is an occasion when all of us should reflect<br />
on these problems, on what they mean to thle people who face<br />
them and on what more we can do to help solve them. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
