<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7498</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF DOORSTOP, FORESTRY OVAL, CANBERRA, 19 FEBRUARY 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/02/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007498.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF DOORSTOP, FORESTRY OVAL, CANBERRA, 19 FEBRUARY<br />
1989 E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: What tactics will you be employing today<br />
against PM: Well I hope they will be winning tactics. No, we are<br />
just going to have a good time and see if we can get the<br />
right result, but you people in the Press have a much larger<br />
pool upon which to call than I do from my office so we've<br />
really got our backs to the wall.<br />
JOURNALIST: That sounds like an excuse.<br />
PM: No it's an explanation.<br />
JOURNALIST: On the economy Mr Hawke, is that on the rail~ s?<br />
PM: On the rails? Well I don't know what you mean by on<br />
the rails.<br />
JOURNALIST: Some commentators are suggesting that the<br />
economy, we should be looking at a mini budget or to<br />
rethink the economy?<br />
PM: Yes, well we've been in office for six years now and.<br />
different sorts of economic circumstances people have been<br />
telling us what to do. I mean characteristic of this period<br />
is that we've known what to do. We've done what has been<br />
necessary to deal with the problems without blowing the<br />
economy apart and that's what we are doing now. As I've<br />
just said on another program, no politician in his right<br />
mind would want to have tight monetary policy for a moment<br />
longer than is necessary. No one gets any joy out of higher<br />
interest rates, but the fact is that we have an economy<br />
which is booming. Just some sort of indication of that is<br />
that if you look at new factory approvals, in the first six<br />
months of this year 51 percent up on the same period last<br />
year. New hotel approvals 57 percent up. Investment higher<br />
the proportion of growth domestic product than it has been<br />
for 35 years. So we've just got to pull things back because<br />
we can't sustain a level of imports associated with that<br />
level of activity and so we are bringing things back. Now<br />
that means higher interest rates. We will bring inflation </p>
<p>-2-<br />
( PM cont): back and we'll do all these things without what<br />
our conservative opponents did when they were faced with<br />
these circumstances destroying the economy. We've got<br />
employment growing very very strongly. 300,000 new jobs in<br />
the last 12 months, growing in employment terms more than<br />
twice as fast as the rest of the world. Now those are the<br />
sorts of things that we can do but it means a bit of<br />
toughness in the monetary policy area. Now there's no need<br />
for panic and we don't panic but we won't get complacent.<br />
JOUNALIST: Can we afford the ACTU's wage tax claim?<br />
PM: You can't afford not to have a combined tax/ wage<br />
movement. There must be wage increases and there must be<br />
tax cuts and we<br />
JOURNALIST: The full amount though that the ACTU want?<br />
PM: Well, it's a question of timing. I haven't committed<br />
myself to precise amounts, but the concept is right. We<br />
will discuss it with the ACTU as we will with employers,<br />
just what the right rate of application of these things is.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
