<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7523</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW/BLACKBACK WITH DOUG AITON, RADIO 3LO, 10 MARCH 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/03/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007523.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
A WU7<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW/ TALKBACK WITH DOUG AITON, RADIO<br />
MARCH 1989<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
AITON: Prime minister, welcome to<br />
PM: Thank you very much. It's a pleasure to be with you.<br />
AITON: It's very good to see how healthy you're looking. I<br />
mean we were talking earlier about how Malcolm Fraser aged<br />
in office over the years. You've done the reverse really.<br />
PM-Thanks. Well I must say Doug, I've never felt better<br />
than I do now and I've got a lot things to thank for that.<br />
More than anything I've got Hazel to thank for it. She<br />
watches my diet and I eat very sensibly. As I've mentioned<br />
I do have a capacity, I don't get a hell of a lot of sleep<br />
always but when the head hits the pillow I go to sleep. But<br />
I think more importantly than anything whether you're Prime<br />
Minister or whatever you're doing it's what you put into<br />
your body, really that determines what you're going to be<br />
like.<br />
AITON: Well you've changed two things of course over the<br />
last few years. You gave up the booze, as we all know so<br />
well, and I saw a photo of you about ten years ago and you<br />
really have slimmed down as a result of no beer intake I<br />
would say. would that be right?<br />
PM: Yes although even when I was drinking a lot of beer I<br />
was lucky I inherited from my dad, I'm a pretty lean sort of<br />
frame, but as I say, even when I was drinking a lot of beer<br />
it wasn't but I'm just very much leaner and stronger<br />
now. AITON: It does show up when you look at photos of ten years<br />
ago. And then you went on the, I think, the Pritikin Diet.<br />
PM: Yes well Hazel I mean to say what's so marvellous<br />
about the way she does she was convinced about it herself<br />
and she was on it for some time and you know husbands tend<br />
to be a bit sceptical about wives saying " well why<br />
she didn't preach it at me but I watched and I thought<br />
that's pretty sensible. So I just found it very, very much<br />
an improvement. In the job I've got Doug, it's impossible<br />
to stay on it 100 percent when you're travelling and so on<br />
but when I'm in Canberra I'm basically on it completely and<br />
I try to eat as sensibly as I can when I'm moving around. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
AITON: Actually that would be very difficult at all the<br />
functions wouldn't it?<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
AITON: Do you ever miss the conviviality of booze?<br />
PM: No I don't. In the early days I mean I gave up in<br />
May of 1980 so it's getting on for 9 years now and in the<br />
early days it's true to say yes you missed it. But people<br />
accept I mean there's no question they accept that I'm a<br />
non-drinker and so they relax with me and the only thing<br />
about it is get out of it early, you don't finish up so<br />
silly in the morning, so ill-equipped to take the day.<br />
AITON: Six years now, last Sunday I think was the sixth<br />
anniversary of your coming into office as Prime minister.<br />
You don't feel tired?<br />
PM: No I don't. I mean it's silly to say that there aren't<br />
days when you're not tired. Of course there are. But in<br />
terms of the excitement about the job and the enthusiasm,<br />
if anything it's stronger than it was then.<br />
AITON: Well apart from going into current issues such as<br />
economic setbacks here, there and everywhere and things that<br />
happen from day to day, are you happy with the progress the<br />
Hawke administration has made in 6 years?<br />
PM: Yes I am. I wouldn't be honest if I said that we've<br />
done everything perfectly. we haven't. Obviously there are<br />
some things we could've done better and that's true of any<br />
human being or any collection of human beings. But I think<br />
Doug, the thing that I am happiest about is this. That I<br />
look back at the Australia that we inherited in Government<br />
in ' 83 and I think all your listeners who remember back then<br />
will remember what a divided, divisive sort of country it<br />
was then when you had Australians set against Australian and<br />
the trade unions against employers, city and against<br />
country. It was just confrontationalism. Now what I asked<br />
of the Australian people was isn't there a better way?<br />
Can't we sort of work together better? Not that we have to<br />
agree with everyone, with each other on everything. But<br />
let's recognise that there's so much talent in the business<br />
community, so much talent in the trade unions, so much<br />
talent in representative organisations, representing farmers<br />
and women and so on, can't we just try and tap into one<br />
another's experience and expertise and work better together.<br />
Looking back now over the 6 years that's what thrills me<br />
most about the 6 years. we do work together better now.<br />
AITON: Yes you had that summit when you first came into<br />
office, that everyone and most of all the media were so<br />
sceptical about? </p>
<p>PM1: Yes they were.<br />
AITON: And understandably, I mean I remember thinking<br />
myself that what a grandstanding piece of nothing that's<br />
going to be. But it actually worked.<br />
PM: Of course it worked. It worked because Australians are<br />
essentially decent people. I mean we were a paradoxical<br />
people. We liked in a sense knocking one another in a<br />
sense we almost liked knocking success in some senses in<br />
whatever field, but in the end basically Australians are<br />
fair-goers. They believe in the concept of a fair go and I<br />
think they understand and they understood then that we<br />
were in a mess in ' 83. We had the worst recession we'd had<br />
in and I'm not going to be parading to you or to your<br />
S listeners Doug, a whole series of statistics. The facts<br />
were however that in ' 83 we had the worst recession we'd<br />
ever had. You know the highest level of unemployment, the<br />
highest level of inflation together ever. And it wasn't<br />
good enough. We were just much better than that and, if I<br />
had to be asked what's my feeling now, it's one of gratitude<br />
to the Australian people that and this is not just words<br />
I mean a real gratitude that they did respond to my<br />
suggestion that if we did work together the better we could<br />
do things. There are a whole lot of statistics but just two<br />
that seem to me to prove what I'm saying. The job creation<br />
Doug, the last statistics came out just yesterday and we've<br />
now to it<br />
AITON: Buried in the paper too I noticed.<br />
PM: Yes, buried in the paper because it wasn't bad news.<br />
AITON: That's right.<br />
0 PM: We've now created over one milion three hundred<br />
thousand new jobs. Just the measure of that is that that's<br />
four times faster a rate of job creation than under our<br />
predecessors, under Howard and Fraser. It's more than twice<br />
as fast as the rest of the world. Now that couldn't have<br />
happened just because we had good policies, we have. But it<br />
couldn't have happened without the cooperation of the people<br />
in business and in the trade unions. Now we look at the<br />
industrial disputes 59% less now than in the previous<br />
period. So those are the sorts of indications of what I'm<br />
talking about how good the Australian people have been.<br />
AITON: Well what have you been you said there have been<br />
some minor disappointments, I think you said. Can you name<br />
any? PM: Yes. I guess that one area that disappoints me is that<br />
we weren't successful perhaps we could've handled it<br />
better I don't know but we weren't successful in getting </p>
<p>-4-<br />
( PM cont): Constitutional change. I think it's just a<br />
tragedy that we couldn't have got those things through<br />
because they were all manifestly in the interests of the<br />
Australian people. That's a disappointment.<br />
AITON: But that wasn't really anything to do with your own<br />
administration was it?<br />
PM: No, athough you've got to ask youself Doug, looking<br />
back could you have done it better.<br />
AITON: Cou ld you have sold it better?<br />
PM: Could you have handled it better? I suppose we didn't<br />
do well in the result. Perhaps we could've handled it<br />
S better. AITON: I think it's fair enough for me to say that you're a<br />
bloke who likes to be liked.<br />
PM: Sure I do, yes. But I qualify that? I mean obviously<br />
I like to be liked. I mean I've got it might be silly<br />
language but I've just got a love relationship with the<br />
Australian people, I lust am besotted with this country, I<br />
just love it, the Australians in it. I just like it when we<br />
respond to one another, which I think we do. But the<br />
qualification I wanted to make is that I hope that if you<br />
look back over the 6 years, that there's plenty of evidence<br />
that if I think that what's required is something that will<br />
be unpopular, I'm still prepared to do it.<br />
AITON: Yes, maybe, I'm sure that's so. But I've noticed<br />
over the years even before you were Prime Minister that you<br />
seem to me to want to be liked to the extent that you get<br />
upset when people don't understand what a good bloke you are<br />
and what good intentions you have when people criticise you.<br />
PM: what upsets me is not that people get annoyed about<br />
something, what upsets me is that a part of the Australian<br />
media, and I'm not a media knocker, but there is a tendency<br />
in the Australian media to be negative and that involves<br />
often either deliberate or careless misrepresentation and<br />
you know that's what upsets me. Obviously just about any<br />
decision that a Prime Minister or a Government makes, there<br />
will be another alternative point of view and I never, never<br />
get upset about argument and disputation. It's deliberate<br />
or near deliberate misrepresentation of what you're about<br />
and of your motives which upsets me.<br />
AITON: I know something else that really gets you angry<br />
too. And that is when journalists question you about things<br />
that you have carefully worked out, maybe complicated<br />
economic matters to do with your Government or your<br />
Treasurer or what have you, and journalists question you in<br />
a confrontational manner and they haven't done their<br />
homework. </p>
<p>PM: -Well that's right. I mean that is annoying because<br />
after all journalists are in a sense opinion formers, they<br />
are people who provide a basis of judgement for the<br />
Australian people. It just seems to me there is an enormous<br />
obligation upon those people to do their homework and so<br />
often they don't. But let me make it clear. I mean I'm not<br />
making a blanket condemnation but there are so many very,<br />
very good people in the media, very many.<br />
AITON: Yes and there are some very bad ones too.<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
AITON: Journalism can be very sloppy and it can be very<br />
good. I'd like your opinion as to whether the performance<br />
of the media in 1989 is better or worse than it was say<br />
during your ACTU days?<br />
PM: It's a very hard comparison to make Doug, because in<br />
those days one had a close and more direct relationship with<br />
a smaller band of people and therefore the opportunity for<br />
them and in a sense for you to share knowledge so that they<br />
really understood things, was greater and you can't do that<br />
in this broader sphere. But generally speaking is it better<br />
now than before? I don't know. There are some very, very<br />
good people and there are some bad ones. But this year<br />
we've had the most amazing example of irresponsible, sloppy,<br />
almost criminally neglectful journalism in that story about<br />
Hawke talking down the dollar. They ran that story. This<br />
is the Fairfax group. Ran the story that Hawke talks down<br />
the dollar says it ought to be 78 cents. I didn't even<br />
the day before I hadn't addressed the issue. But on the<br />
basis of them running that story, you know, the dollar went<br />
down. And it was wrong and they didn't have the decency<br />
and the honesty the next day to come out and say " we got it<br />
wrong". I think obviously we can all make mistakes, but if<br />
newspapers in an organisation like that, you know, one at<br />
the centre of financial journalism, they make that blue,<br />
well why don't they just say so?<br />
AITON: There's not much to be lost?<br />
PM: I think people<br />
AITON: inaudible<br />
PM: When I make mistakes, and I make them, I just think not<br />
only is it right to say that you've got it wrong, and if<br />
you just look at it, in terms of self interest, people are<br />
going to respect you more if you concede it.<br />
AITON: The media is more opinionated than it used to be,<br />
even in straight reporting. Say in the Age or the Sydney<br />
Morning Herald will be full of comment from those people who<br />
the organisations concerned allow to do that. </p>
<p>-6-<br />
PM: Yes, there is an enormous amount of editorialising in<br />
journalism and in one sense, you know, it's very difficult<br />
to say that journalists shouldn't express an opinion in a<br />
sense. Why shouldn't they? But it just seems to me Doug<br />
that there's a corresponding responsibility. If you are in<br />
the media and you're going to offer an opinion, a judgement,<br />
then the more you're prepared to do that the greater is the<br />
obligation to be fully informed. I think there's a bit of<br />
an imbalance at times with some journalists, but I want to<br />
get back to the point, I'm not into media knocking. By and<br />
large in this country we've got a media which tries to do<br />
its job. I think too often as you have said, they try to<br />
make themselves the centre of the story particularly in<br />
television to say ' look this is what I think' and bang,<br />
bang, bang and have a confrontation. But generally speaking<br />
we've got a media and thank God it's free.<br />
AITON: You said before that you hope that you've brought<br />
Australia together to an extent and that there are good<br />
people in business which used to be the traditional enemy of<br />
Labor of course. Along with that, with what you've tried to<br />
achieve there, have come the criticisms that you've taken<br />
the Labor Party across to the Right. How do you feel about<br />
that criticism?<br />
PM: Well, it's not correct. I mean, even before I went<br />
into Parliament I've said that I've always regarded the<br />
exercise of political analysis as rather sterile when it<br />
thinks it's done something by simply putting a tag on it<br />
saying ' that's Right, that's Left'. It's just so stupid<br />
because an intelligent person is going to be on some issues<br />
classified as Left, on some issues classified as Right. I<br />
mean, there is no intellectually respectable position which<br />
flows from being just Right or just Left or just Centre<br />
that's in my judgement anyway. Now, what I've tried to do<br />
is to say, what are the sorts of things that we've got to do<br />
as a community which are capable of getting basic community<br />
support. It's not absolute consensus, you know, a good<br />
working sort of position of consensus. That often means<br />
that you've got to do some things which are not exactly in<br />
some ideal world what you might say is right, but good<br />
Government is about leadership but not being that far away<br />
from your community that you're not going to be able to make<br />
things work. So people who conduct their analysis in terms<br />
of the ivory tower, the academic study or the boardroom or<br />
something like that and say ' this is what's the correct<br />
thing to do' OK it might be a nice academic exercise but<br />
that's not what Government's about.<br />
AITON: Have you changed your mind about anything<br />
significant during the time that you've been Prime Minister?<br />
PM: Yes, I guess I have. Let me think what those things<br />
are. </p>
<p>AITON: Possibly the sort of question you need to have in<br />
advance? PM: Oh no. As you know, I never like questions in advance.<br />
AITON: Yes I do know that.<br />
PM: If I've changed my mind, it's in terms of becoming just<br />
much more convinced about some things and I've become even<br />
more passionate about some things. The thing that I've<br />
become even more convinced of and more passionate about in<br />
terms of the future of this country, Doug, is the<br />
fundamental importance that all Australians understand that<br />
our future, particularly the future of our kids, depends<br />
upon us understanding that we are part of this region. The<br />
dynamic growth region of the world is going to be in Asia,<br />
particularly North Asia. I've always had the view that we<br />
should have a close relationship but the more I've been in<br />
Government, the more I've understood what's happening in the<br />
world, the more worried I get about some elements in<br />
Australia which try to fan some sort of anti-Asian feeling<br />
because the certainty is that our kids out there now are<br />
going to be disadvantaged if we don't do everything we can<br />
to become part of the dynanism of this region. You can't<br />
have it both ways, you can't say ' look we want to sell all<br />
our stuff to you, but we think you're second rate human<br />
beings'. It doesn't work. I mean it's morally wrong but<br />
it's also intrinsically insane.<br />
AITON: What do you think of Malcolm Fraser in 1989?<br />
PM: Well I think this about Malcolm Fraser. That's why in<br />
fact I'm actively trying to get him the job of Secretary<br />
General of the Commonwealth of Nations. I think that<br />
Malcolm Fraser has shown, while he was in office, I never<br />
questioned him on this and certainly since he's been out of<br />
office, a commitment to the concept of racial equality and<br />
has worked diligently and very effectively to advance that<br />
cause. I think he is worthy of being Secretary General to<br />
the Commonwealth because I think, more than anyone that I<br />
can think of, he would advance the cause of racial<br />
integration in that tragic area of Southern Africa. I would<br />
still have disagreements of course with him in areas of<br />
domestic policy, quite fundamental ones. I still think ' he<br />
can be, in some senses, a prickly sort of fellow, but I<br />
believe he's the best man for that job. I'm working hard to<br />
try and get him the job.<br />
AITON: Did you always think about him the way you do now?<br />
PM: I always respected and it wasn't just a privately<br />
held view I've publicly said that he has an impeccable<br />
record on the question of race and colour. Absolutely<br />
impeccable. I disagreed fundamentally with the way he was </p>
<p>-8-<br />
( PM cont): trying to govern Australia internally. I think<br />
there was far too much confrontationism there and a lack of<br />
trust in the Australian people.<br />
AITON: We'll go to listeners' calls in a moment. The<br />
switchboard's filling up on 678 9044. What about Gough<br />
Whitlam? Have you got any thoughts about him?<br />
PM: Yes, Gough and I have always had a good relationship.<br />
That hasn't meant that we haven't had our arguments and<br />
disagreements. But Gough did some great things both for the<br />
Labor Party and for this country. The thing he did for the<br />
Labor Party was modernise its platform, get it up towards<br />
current realities and future challenges and its organisation<br />
improved enormously. Of course, in the area of Government,<br />
the most important thing he did, the single most important<br />
thing he did, was with China the establishment of a<br />
relationship with China.<br />
AITON: Who should the Liberals put up as leader if they're<br />
going to knock you off?<br />
PM: Well, I hope this doesn't sound complacent, but there's<br />
no-one there that really has the qualities of leadership.<br />
The important thing is they know that themselves. They are<br />
totally dissatisfied with the incumbent and he would have<br />
been out by now, but there's no-one they've got to turn to.<br />
AITON: Not Fred Chaney? I know he's in the Senate of<br />
course. PM: No I think Fred's passed his zenith. I've said in<br />
conversations with him, I've meant it sincerly, I think<br />
they've been criminally neglectful over the years in their<br />
preselection methods. I mean they've put very ordinary<br />
calibre people in their safe seats. I mean they should have<br />
got better people in and I wish they had.<br />
AITON: Do you?<br />
PM: Honestly I do because I think Governments are better<br />
with better Oppositions. I honestly believe that.<br />
AITON: And what do you want to be remembered for? I won't<br />
ask you how long you are going to stay in office because I<br />
know you've been evading the question for a long time, but<br />
as Prime Minister yourself I mean, but what would you like<br />
to be remembered for?<br />
PM: I'm going back to what I said before. If I can be<br />
remembered for being a bloke who had a capacity to get on<br />
the wavelength of ordinary Australians and persuade them<br />
that there was a better way of conducting their affairs than<br />
one of antagonism and confrontationalism and of trying to<br />
work together more, then that's the main thing I'd like to<br />
be remembered for. </p>
<p>-9-<br />
AITON: Mr Hawke, I've heard, just today there's been some,<br />
within the ALP, there's been some factional rumblings in<br />
Canberra, that's the only way I can put it and I can't put<br />
my finger on it, I don't know what's going on. Is this any<br />
indication that we might be gearing up for an election this<br />
year? PM: No, that's to do with the State Parliament<br />
preselection in New South Wales. There was some shenanigans<br />
going on which didn't reflect much credit on people involved<br />
and it was before the National Executive this morning which<br />
I was present for an hour or so before I came down to<br />
Melbourne. I think that will be sorted out.<br />
S AITON: Do you want to say anything about the forthcoming<br />
election? PM: No, the election is a long way away.<br />
AITON: This year?<br />
PM: In no sense necessarily. As I've said, it's the latter<br />
part of this year at the earliest, you know, it could be<br />
well into next year.<br />
0 </p>
<p>AITON: Ok, let's go to some calls. Roger, good afternoon.<br />
CALLER: Good afternoon. Mr Hawke, having just left the<br />
Australian defence forces I would like to know from you,<br />
given that we've got a pretty high turnover rate in the<br />
defence forces about 30% over the last three years when<br />
are you going to face up to the fact that the defence<br />
force's pay is pretty low and do something about upgrading<br />
it? PM: Let me say this, that what we did was to establish an<br />
independent tribunal to consider the levels of remuneration<br />
and that's something -that had been asked for by the defence<br />
force. We've done it and we abide by the tribunal. One of<br />
the problems~ of course that we've got, and let me make it<br />
quite clear I'm not trying to avoid the fact that there are<br />
high separation rates which create some problems, but I can<br />
assure you that I keep in touch not only with the minister<br />
for Defence but with Defence chiefs. They assure us,<br />
certainly with one area of exception that I'll come to in a<br />
moment, that the issue is manageable. But one of the<br />
problems we've got just flows from what I was saying to Doug<br />
before. We have lifted the level of economic activity and<br />
created so many jobs in this country that the people of<br />
quality and we've got as you know, because you've been in<br />
it we've got so many people of quality in our armed<br />
forces that they are able to get very very much more<br />
attractive positions often outside the forces than in it.<br />
Of course, as I think you would know, the area where our<br />
greatest problem has been, and it's not unique to Australia,<br />
is with our pilots.<br />
CALLER: But the pilots aren't everything Mr Hawke.<br />
PM: No, I accept that and I would've thought you would've<br />
understood from what I'm saying that I wasn't saying it's<br />
just pilots. People who are in the armed forces get well<br />
trained within the armed forces and there are so many areas<br />
where the training, whether it be in technical terms or<br />
professional terms, the quality of training provided in the<br />
Australian armed forces is very very high by world<br />
standards. In the event people in the armed forces get very<br />
well qualified and in an expanding economy which is growing<br />
twice as fast in terms of employment as the rest of the<br />
world there are so many attractive alternatives. Now you<br />
can't pitch the rates of pay and the conditions in the armed<br />
forces at the level of the competition outside. Just take<br />
the area of pilots. If we paid pilots what they're being<br />
offered by Qantas and these other shows you would just blow<br />
the defence budget out of the water. we wouldn't be able to<br />
do what we are doing and having a massive re-equipment of<br />
our defence forces.<br />
CALLER: I agree Mr Hawke but the majority of the people i n<br />
the defence forces aren't pilots, they're all corporals and<br />
sergeants and a corporal's base rate of pay is $ 18,054. Now<br />
that by your own figures is $ 7000 below the average income. </p>
<p>PM: I've got to go back to what I said before, that we<br />
established an independent tribunal at which you're able to<br />
go in and argue your case and we accept the findings of that<br />
independent tribunal. If you say that the findings of the<br />
tribunal are wrong well it's like saying that we don't<br />
accept the umpire's decision.<br />
AITON: We'll have to move on I think. John, hi.<br />
CALLER: Mr Hawke, in the Hawke Government at the moment, in<br />
the Parliament, there are quite a number of your ministry<br />
and members of Parliament who hold dual nationality, which<br />
is firstly against the Constitutional right, first of all<br />
that is an illegal thing for them to have that under the<br />
Constitution.. Secondly, and more importantly, you keep<br />
preaching the fact of citizenship being important. I<br />
would've thought that a Prime Minsiter of our country would<br />
regard it not only as illegal but as immoral for some of<br />
them to have these dual nationalities, particularly one who<br />
is very prominent who has accepted an Israeli citizenship as<br />
well. But apart from that, when are you going to speak out<br />
PM: Just so that we're not being eliptical, who is this<br />
prominent one who has accepted Israeli nationality?<br />
CALLER: Well, one of them is the Prime Minister of<br />
Au st ral1i a.<br />
PM: Look John, just let me get it straight. I love<br />
talkback radio but I was saying to Doug that one of the<br />
things and I hope you won't be too offended you get<br />
ratbags on it and you come straight into that category.<br />
You're wrong, I haven't got Israeli citizenship, so don't<br />
take up the valuable time of Doug, myself and the listeners<br />
by coming on and telling lies.<br />
AITON: We'll go on to the next questioner. Hello Ian.<br />
CALLER: G'day Doug and g'day Mr Hawke.<br />
œ. FLL~ Idon't think either of us are ratbags Mr Hawke. I'd<br />
like firstly to congratulate you on the first six years. I<br />
think that you and the Labor Party have got nine to go to<br />
make something substantial of the country. my work is in,<br />
and the concern that I have which is some degree of a<br />
qualification I guess, is in the fields of employment, and<br />
particularly people in poverty or in disadvantage. I'd like<br />
to put to you a proposal that we as a nation need to take on<br />
a full employment objective. I know employment is<br />
decreasing and that substantial jobs have been created, but<br />
as an objective, the concept of full employment, something<br />
that we seem to have in the back of our minds as an ideal,<br />
but it's on the backburner. Just a suggestion with regard<br />
to the J curve and import substitution, those sorts of </p>
<p>C~ Ue( cont): issues, it seems to me that there's<br />
possibilities for national incentives towards employment<br />
generation programs and opportunities in those areas that we<br />
seem to be missing out on but we've got a terrific<br />
opportunity to aim for over the next ten years.<br />
PM: Let me say this to you that we haven't put the concept<br />
of full employment on the backburner. Could I just point<br />
this out to you, we've got the unemployment rate down now to<br />
6.7% from the double digit figure that we inherited. You<br />
would've heard I think Ian what I said earlier that we have<br />
created jobs now four times faster than under the previous<br />
people and importantly in the current situation we're<br />
creating jobs in our period of six yeazs more than twice as<br />
fast as the OECD average. So<br />
CALLER: That's the important figure isn't it? The OECD<br />
one's important isn't it? The 1.3 million figure does take<br />
into account things like CEP programs that were<br />
non-repetitive<br />
PM: This is now jobs that have been created and may I say<br />
that 85% of those jobs have been created in the private<br />
sector. That doesn't mean we sit back and say well done<br />
good and faithful servant, you haven't got anything more to<br />
do. But I just ask you to understand this statistic.<br />
That's also been achieved where we now have the highest<br />
participation rate for more than 20 years. If we had the<br />
same participation rate, that is people who could<br />
potentially be in the workforce actually saying we want to<br />
work, if we had the same participation rate as when we came<br />
into office the unemployment rate would be just about 3%,<br />
just over In other words that's so close to full<br />
employment that it doesn't matter, we are going to do more<br />
in the areas of trying to get our companies in this country<br />
to undertake more research and development work so that<br />
they'll open up more opportunities. There's still more to<br />
be done Ian but I think we're very very much closer towards<br />
the concept than this country has been for very many years.<br />
0 AITON: We'll move on. Hello John.<br />
CALLER: I'd like to speak to Robert Hawke please.<br />
PM: Yes John.<br />
CALLER: Robert. I live down in your old down in<br />
Sandringham way mate. I've followed your career with great<br />
interest, I've been a trade unionist since I was<br />
PM: Which union are you in mate?<br />
CALLER: The Eletrical Trade Union.<br />
PM: ETU, yes. </p>
<p>CALLER: I've followed your career with great interest and<br />
I've been a Labor voter ever since I started to vote. I was<br />
in the army for five years and I have a family of two<br />
daughters and a wife who have been staunch Labor voters,<br />
having been educated by myself.<br />
PM: What's the question John?<br />
CALLER: The question is what's the strength of the<br />
tertiary fees? I'm so boiled up about these tertiary fees.<br />
I have a daughter going to Melbourne University and she's<br />
going to be saddled with a bloody great debt when she<br />
finishes. I'm a pensioner and God knows how she's going to<br />
pay for it..<br />
PM: Well the answer to that John is quite straight forward.<br />
They are not tertiary fees, they are a requirement that not<br />
when she graduates, not while she's doing her degree, but at<br />
a point when she reaches a reasonably high level of earnings<br />
that there will be a repayment of what constitutes about a<br />
fifth of the cost of the education. See, what we had was a<br />
position where still in this country there is a if you<br />
like in the ratio of people who go to the university against<br />
the population proper. In other words there are many many<br />
more people who go to university from the very high income<br />
sections of the community out of proportion to what they<br />
represent in the community as a whole. which means that<br />
generally speaking it's the ordinary lower to middle income<br />
people who've been paying proportionately much more for the<br />
education of the well-off. That simply just isn't fair. So<br />
what we're saying is not that we're going to impose burdens<br />
upon lower income people or lower income kids, we've done<br />
more to increase the Austudy payments and so on than has<br />
ever been done before. We're saying you don't have to pay<br />
while you're there, you don't have to pay when you graduate,<br />
but when you have reached a relatively high level of<br />
earnings afterwards then you will pay a very small<br />
proportion of that so that you'll pay then when you can<br />
afford it approximately a fifth of the cost of the<br />
education. The point is John, there is no such thing as<br />
free education. It's a myth, the phrase is a nonsense.<br />
CALLER: I understand that.<br />
PM: And John, it's a question of who is going to pay for<br />
the education.<br />
CALLER: Could I say this. I think you blokes have jumped on<br />
the wrong tram. I think what you should have done is hit<br />
the people that drop out of university. You've got people<br />
who go to university who go for one year just for fun and<br />
they get all that for free, they drop out. Now they're the<br />
people you should be whacking. You should say ok, you pay<br />
for I've been in that category of supporting university<br />
students all my life because I've paid tax and I've got one<br />
daughter who goes to university. I've been working since I<br />
was 14 and I'm 68 years old. </p>
<p>A<br />
PM: But John, you know what the situation is if you look at<br />
Australia as a whole. What was happening was that the Johns<br />
of this world like yourself and others, the majority of whom<br />
didn't have kids going to university, were through paying<br />
your tax, you were paying to put the kids and the wives of<br />
millionaires through university.<br />
CALLER: I know that.<br />
PM: And that's crazy.<br />
CALLER: I know that.<br />
AITON: But your daughter will be paying later on, it won't<br />
be hitting you at all.<br />
CALLER: She's terribly concerned.<br />
PM: But John, she's not paying until such time as she is<br />
earning a level of income whereby she will be able to pay,<br />
not for the whole of her education, but for about a fifth of<br />
it, but not until she reaches a level of income where she<br />
can afford to do it.<br />
AITON: We'll have to move on. I must say, I don't know if<br />
you sold that one wrongly or the publicity was bad or<br />
something, but so many people don't seem to understand that<br />
one. You only pay later on at such time as you are earning<br />
a decent salary.<br />
PM: That's right. Exactly right.<br />
AITON: But people don't seem to absolutely grasp that<br />
point. PM: Let me say this, that from the feedback I'm getting and<br />
I've talked to a lot of students myself, they do. most of<br />
them are understanding. But it is true that some people<br />
don't want to understand it.<br />
AITON: Hello Bill.<br />
CALLER: Hell Doug. I have a question here for Bob.<br />
PM: Yes Bill.<br />
CALLER: Let's lead into it first. Look, I'm a veteran<br />
pensioner Bob and I took strong exception when I was means<br />
tested I might say, but never mind. In early 1940s when I<br />
was serving overseas I think the Labor Government here, sort<br />
of following on from New Zealand I believe, brought in the<br />
Social Security Act which guaranteed every citizen a<br />
sufficient and indexed retirement pension plus full medical<br />
care and all that sort of thing. For that we had to pay in<br />
one and six in the pound in those days. That worked out at<br />
17.5% of total income and went on for the whole of my<br />
years of working life. I paid in 17.5% of my total income, </p>
<p>PM ( cont): the same as everybody is today, and now I find<br />
that because of this Medicare scheme I have to join private<br />
schemes if I really don't want to join long queues, and have<br />
to pay for it. I'm means tested when I believe that every<br />
citizen who paid in, and that is every working citizen, was<br />
entitled to a pension without means testing. Damn it all,<br />
we paid in 17.5%, now what's gone wrong?<br />
PM: Nothing's gone wrong. Let's make it quite clear that<br />
this is one issue on which there is unanimity between the<br />
opposition and Government. That is that you can't just be<br />
paying benefits to everyone in the community irrespective of<br />
income and assets. I simply want to say to you that you<br />
have a situation in this community where, particularly with<br />
increased ageing of the community Bill, that we've got to<br />
make sure that the limited resources of the community go to<br />
those who relatively need it Most. This is one point for<br />
instance where John Elliott and I are absolutely at one. He<br />
said he regards it as an obscenity, this is John that<br />
his parents should be receiving benefits from because<br />
they simply don't need it.<br />
AITON: John Elliott or John<br />
PM: John Elliott. I'm making the point that in a<br />
community, if you don't want high taxes, if you want taxes<br />
coming down and we of course have brought them down<br />
significantly and very soon we'll bring them down further,<br />
you've got to then say does it make sense to pay pensions to<br />
millionaires? The answer is it doesn't.<br />
CALLER: Haven't they paid in their 17.5% the same as I<br />
have? In this way aren't they entitled to the same service<br />
as I'm entitled to?<br />
PM: No, this is where I differ with you, and as I say, John<br />
Elliott agrees with me and so does the Liberal Party.<br />
CALLER: They may agree but they've paid in just the same<br />
PM: And they've had a greater capacity. Do you want your<br />
taxes to be higher or lower? If you want your taxes to come<br />
down then we can't be paying out your taxes to people who<br />
don't need the assistance of the community.<br />
AITON: How would you feel about John Elliott being your<br />
opponent in the House? election?<br />
PM: I'd be quite happy to have John as my partner. It'd be<br />
a pretty lively contest I think.<br />
AITON: It would, but do you think he might get closer to<br />
knocking you off than anyone else we've seen in the Liberal<br />
Party? PM: I doubt it but I'd like to try it. </p>
<p>AITON: Hello, you're calling from Tasmania?<br />
CALLER: Hello Mr Hawke.<br />
PM: -How are you?<br />
CALLER: Fine thanks.<br />
PM: We've got to think about Tasmania next week with that<br />
mill. CALLER: That's what I wanted to speak to you about. I live<br />
on the north west coast and I would really like to appeal to<br />
you on behalf of the majority of the Tasmanian people to<br />
take the objective, logical, long term view of this mill and<br />
prevent it going ahead and polluting the Bass Strait, the<br />
fisheries, the farmlands, affecting our children<br />
detrimentally. I've got a child who goes to school very<br />
close to Wesley Vale. The children themselves are<br />
concerned, in fact my nine year old daughter wanted to ring<br />
you, she wanted to speak to you but they said there wouldn't<br />
be time for children to ask questions<br />
PM: She could've spoken.<br />
CALLER: But I'm really appealing on behalf of her and all<br />
of her friends.<br />
PM: Could I just say a couple of things just quickly about<br />
it. I think you'd agree that on our record in six years<br />
we've got a pretty good environmental record, and<br />
particularly in the area of Tasmania.<br />
CALLER: That's right, that's why I appeal to you.<br />
PM: I think you can take it for granted that we will be<br />
looking at this extremely closely. Let me put it to you,<br />
there are two sets of arguments. one is that with<br />
Australia's external account problems that we need to<br />
substitute imports and provide our own stuff and also<br />
export. CALLER: I realise that. It's very important but surely,<br />
surely PM: Let me finish. There's that argument but I recognise<br />
there is the environmental argument that you're putting. I<br />
have instructed my Ministers that they are to come to<br />
Cabinet with as full a submission as they can, including<br />
from the CSIRO and any relevant sources all the information<br />
that is relevant to those concerns that you've got the<br />
pollutant effect in the atmosphere and the ocean. So you<br />
can be sure that all those issues will be before us and if<br />
the evidence is that that sort of environmental impact is of<br />
unacceptable levels then we will not accept it on its<br />
present proposals. The venturers would have to come up with<br />
something better if on what they're proposing now it's<br />
environmentally unacceptable. So there's no easy ride on<br />
this one. </p>
<p>AITON: Sorry, I cut you off without meaning to, I thought<br />
we were going to the next questioner. How do you like it<br />
when the media refers to you as the silver bodgie?<br />
PM: I don't mind. At least I've got my hair.<br />
AITON: I think you're going to keep it forever too. Hello<br />
Gwen. CALLER: Hello.<br />
PM: Hi Gwen.<br />
CALLER: Hello Mr Hawke. Now we're 70 year old pensioners<br />
with our own homes, we've always been in the low income<br />
bracket but we own our own home. We manage quite well on<br />
the pension thank you very much and we've never been better<br />
off in our lives. But I resent some of these greypower<br />
leaders who live on Sydney harbour with Swiss bank accounts<br />
or a few other rollover schemes and they whinge all the<br />
ruddy time. God, they talk about the Pommy whingers, I<br />
think Australians are getting just as bad. Who pays for the<br />
pension? We know very well that the people who are paying<br />
for us are young people with mortgages, with kids to educate<br />
and I really think that we're better off than they are.<br />
PM: Well Gwen, I must say how grateful I am to hear what<br />
you've got to say. There are amongst some people who are<br />
now recently trying to set themselves up as spokespersons<br />
for the elderly some reasonably unsavoury characters as you<br />
would've seen. I must say that just this week I've had<br />
meetings with the representatives of the Pensioners<br />
Federation and they are very concerned. They have been<br />
representing your interests now for very very many years,<br />
they are decent people who've got a long continuous history<br />
of concern and involvement in the issues concerning the old.<br />
They are very worried about these Johnny-come-latelys<br />
CALLER: That's right, and they give us a bad reputation.<br />
We're not whingers and we are happy with the pension.<br />
PM: I'm glad you are but we still think that there's some<br />
more things that can be done and we're in the process of<br />
consultations with your legitimate representatives and I can<br />
assure you<br />
CALLER: I hope you take notice of them and not these bloody<br />
money hungry so and sos.<br />
PM: Thanks Gwen.<br />
CALLER: Anyway, I wouldn't have your job for double your<br />
salary. I think you're doing a damn good job.<br />
PM: Thanks Gwen. </p>
<p>AITON: I wouldn't either as a matter of fact. You're<br />
turning 60 this year too. How do you feel about that Prime<br />
Minister? PM: I think it's inevitable and I must say I feel, as I<br />
said before, I feel fitter and happier than I think I ever<br />
have.<br />
AITON: You've never been very age conscious really have<br />
you? PM: No, never. People who worry about their age, it seems<br />
very silly to me. There are certain things in life that you<br />
can do nothing about and I don't know if this sounds too<br />
philosophical but I've always thought it's an enormously<br />
stupid waste of one's time to worry about things about which<br />
you can do nothing. You should conserve your energies and<br />
worry about those things about which you can do<br />
something.<br />
AITON: I think I fall into the stupid category. Hello<br />
Megan. CALLER: Hello. Hi Mr Hawke. I'd like to it's a beef<br />
really. I really wanted to say that the way that you speak<br />
to each other as normal human beings I find quite offensive.<br />
manner in which Parliamentarians address each other,<br />
sometimes in Parliament and on radio. It may be games of<br />
power between you but as a member of the public trying to<br />
understand the issues, I often have to turn off the radio<br />
rather than to listen to the condescending manner in which<br />
you converse with each other. Do you think this behaviour<br />
can be addressed?<br />
PM: Megan I think it's a fair point you make. Let me say<br />
in fairness, not just to myself, that doesn't matter so<br />
much, but to the generality of people in politics, and I'm<br />
talking about both sides, not only mine. I think you're a<br />
little bit too sweeping in your condemnation but I do accept<br />
that at times our behaviour in the Parliament leaves a lot<br />
to be desired. I don't retract from that and I as well as<br />
others have been guilty of behaviour which is less than<br />
perfect. So I accept that, I don't argue it. So that's a<br />
sincere statement I'm making and if you heard in the earlier<br />
part of the program, I think one of the problems it<br />
doesn't excuse some of the things we do and say at times<br />
but I think one of the problems is the sort of<br />
confrontationalist atmosphere that i' s created by the media<br />
to some extent and we respond to it. We ought to do better<br />
and I hope we will.<br />
CALLER: It's just communication really.<br />
PM: Sure, sure. </p>
<p>AITON: I think we'll have time for only one more call. By<br />
the way, do you ever find any time as Prime Minister to be a<br />
grandfather? PM.: Now you'll really get me going. I'm just about to get<br />
my sixth grandchild it might be an Easter baby. This is<br />
the great joy of my life. I'm lucky in having two of my<br />
grandsons who live very close to me in Canberra and I see<br />
them very very regularly and they are beautiful kids. my<br />
daughter in Sydney has got my one granddaughter who is the<br />
most beautiful little girl in Australia as I suppose all<br />
grandparents say. She's got me wrapped round her little<br />
finger and she's about to get a baby brother or baby sister.<br />
They are really just the joy of my life.<br />
AITON: Noel, you're the lucky last.<br />
CALLER: Thanks Doug. Good afternoon Prime Minister. It's<br />
good to have access to you through Doug's program.<br />
PM: Thank you.<br />
CALLER: My concern is about naturalisation and I would love<br />
to see the two million or so non-Australian residents in<br />
Australia become naturalised.<br />
PM: It's only one million Noel.<br />
CALLER: One million, ok, sorry about that. I'd love to<br />
see them all become Australian citi-. ens because I'm a loyal<br />
Australian myself. I'm just concerned Prime minister about<br />
the way you're going about it. squirm when I see these<br />
adds that say all you have to do is swear. Now apart from<br />
your own personal record in that field I really feel that<br />
really trivialise the whole issue. almost a bargain<br />
sort of approach. I'm concerned Prime minister, what about<br />
belief in Australia, what about pride in Australia?<br />
PM: Those are the things I've tried to stress. I take your<br />
point Noel that you might think that that's a cheap way.<br />
All I can say is that those sort of making the decisions in<br />
the communication areas seem to think it was a way of<br />
striking a chord. I take your point that there might be<br />
some who are offended by it but certainly please accept my<br />
word it wasn't in any sense intended to be offensive. But I<br />
think if you read Noel all the things that I've said,<br />
particularly during the Bicentennial year, I said the one<br />
thing that makes an Australian is not your colour, your<br />
creed, your country of origin. There is one thing and one<br />
thing alone, and that is commitment to Australia. I think<br />
you and I are at one on that and I think you may be<br />
interested to know that as a result of the campaign we're<br />
undertaking there's been a massive increase in the<br />
applications for citizenship and I hope that we will make a<br />
significant inroad to this million. </p>
<p>CALLER: I'm a counsellor, I attend many nationalisation<br />
ceremonies, but I really feel that a lot of people that I<br />
have spoken to are really off by this whole approach of<br />
all you have to do is swear, whole triviality of the<br />
issue. Prime Minister, I would like to ask if you would ask<br />
your people to look at that and see what the effect is and<br />
see whether perhaps<br />
PM: Ok, we'll have a look at that Noel. Thank you.<br />
AITON: Thanks Noel. And I think that's about as far as we<br />
can go. Thank you very much indeed Prime Minister for<br />
coming in today. I know it's not often that you can find<br />
the time to go on radio programs these days.<br />
PM: It's been my pleasure and can I say thank you to you<br />
Doug and to your listeners because I must say it's been a<br />
very very positive, constructive sort of hour and I've<br />
appreciated it very much.<br />
AITON: Thanks again.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
