<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2651</transcript-id>
    <title>OIL INDSUTRY DISPUTE - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT HON WILLIAM MCMAHON CH MP</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/07/1972</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002651.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS: PM. No 72/ 1972.<br />
OIL INDUSTPY DISPUTE<br />
Statement by the Prie M: i ster, the Rt.<br />
Hon. William CniMP<br />
Following discussions yesterday with senior Ministers in<br />
Sydney about Ehe oil industry dispute, I announced that the<br />
Minister for Labor and National Service, Mr. Lynch, the Minister<br />
for Shipping and Transport ( Mr. Nixon), and the Attorney General,<br />
Senator Greenwood would have inmediate discussions with oil<br />
industry employers and the ACTU.<br />
The Ministers met last evening with senior representatives of<br />
the oil industry and this morning with ACTU officials, Mr. Hawke,<br />
Mr. Petrie and Mr. Souter.<br />
The purpose of these discussions was to enable the Ministers<br />
to obtain a first-hand appreciation from the employers and from<br />
the ACTU of the strike situation, possible developments and their<br />
consequences. The Ministers have now reported the substance of<br />
these discussions to Cabinet so that steps might be taken as<br />
appropriate. The ACTU representatives informed the Ministers that they were<br />
not prepared to say whether the ACTU wanted or could get the<br />
w striking union members back to work, except under conditions which<br />
could be seen as inconsistent with the decision of Mr. Justice<br />
Moore. The strikers are to hold meetings in the four States<br />
directly affected, Victoria, South Australia and Queensland<br />
tomorrow morning ( Friday). This gives them the opportunity and the<br />
responsibility for deciding to return to work immediately under<br />
the terms of the recent decision of Mr. Justice Moore of the<br />
Conciliation and Arbitration Commission. The Government wants a<br />
full resumption of work and the lifting of any bans or restrictions<br />
on the work to be performed.<br />
The termination of this strike would make possible an early<br />
resumption of proceedings by the Conciliation and Arbitration<br />
Commission for hearing and determining the unions' claims in full.<br />
The employers have consistently maintained their willingness to<br />
proceed without delay to arbitration provided that normal work<br />
is resumed. </p>
<p>The Government for its cart is firmly convinced that when<br />
matters in disnute between emnlovers and unions cannot be resolved<br />
by negotiation or conciliation, there can be no alternative but to<br />
proceed with arbitration. That is precisely the situation which<br />
has been reached in this particular dispute.<br />
It is in the interests of all sections of the community that<br />
our system of arbitration be maintained and that any efforts to<br />
undermine it must be resisted.<br />
The situation is becoming increasingly critical. The oil<br />
companies have no,. put forward reasonable proposals for an<br />
emergency plan that would minimise inconvenience to the public.<br />
Unlike the plan proposed by Mr. Hawke the companies' plan<br />
would not discriminate between companies but would involve the<br />
participation of all of them.<br />
The ACTU officers have been prepared to recommend that some<br />
men return to work. It is a tecL of their authority and concern<br />
for the public interest whether they now recommend that all men go<br />
back to-ork. This is the only sure way in which the unnecessary<br />
hardship and suffering by countless members of the community as<br />
well as the threat to their welfare by the needless. disruption of<br />
industrial and commercial activity can be avoided.<br />
I emphasise the ACTU carries a heavy obligation for the<br />
continuation of the strike.<br />
427 Julv, i? 7?. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
