<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11337</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                 THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                ADDRESS AT MT SCOPUS COLLEGE FOUNDATION                 GALA JUBILEE                 HER MAJESTY&amp;#146;S THEATRE, MELBOURNE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/03/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE..........................................................................................</p>
<p>Thank you very much Solomon, to your wife Rosie, to Mr and Mrs Lanzer,</p>
<p> Mr and Mrs Baker, the School Principal Mr Ruben and his wife and the</p>
<p> many other guests and friends of the Mt Scopus College.</p>
<p>It is an honour for me to share this very important celebration. 50</p>
<p> years of achievement of any organisation is always a milestone and</p>
<p> something to be grateful for. But the 50 years that your community</p>
<p> has traversed has been no ordinary 50 year period. IT is difficult</p>
<p> for somebody in my position to fully conceive of the hurdles and the</p>
<p> obstacles that the very small Jewish community of Melbourne must have</p>
<p> faced 50 years ago in embarking on this endeavour. With many of its</p>
<p> members having passed through the unbelievable experience of the earlier</p>
<p> years of that decade.</p>
<p>And yet 50 years later this school and this community can boast many</p>
<p> things. It can boast the largest Jewish day school not only in Australia</p>
<p> but I understand in the Southern Hemisphere. It can boast of outstanding</p>
<p> scholastic achievement which is seen as one of the consistently best</p>
<p> three performers of Melbourne schools in VCE examinations. But most</p>
<p> importantly it can boast of having made a wonderful, cultural and</p>
<p> spiritual contribution to the life of the Jewish community here in</p>
<p> Melbourne and throughout Australia.</p>
<p>We celebrate together tonight a number of things. First and foremost,</p>
<p> can I say that we celebrate a very important belief of the entire</p>
<p> Australian community. It's a very important personal belief of</p>
<p> my own and it's a very important belief of the party and the</p>
<p> Government that I lead. And that belief is in the absolute right of</p>
<p> every Australian parent to determine the character and the value system</p>
<p> of the education that their children receive. And that right of parental</p>
<p> choice lies at the heart of good education policy. It's a policy</p>
<p> that recognises the need for choice and variety within the education</p>
<p> system. We need a strong government education system. As someone myself</p>
<p> who is a proud and unapologetic product of the government school system</p>
<p> in New South Wales, as someone who chose both government and independent</p>
<p> schools for the education of my own children, as someone who has argued</p>
<p> consistently all of his political life for the maximum degree of freedom</p>
<p> of choice, I think it is important on an occasion such as this to</p>
<p> emphasise the centrality of that principle of freedom of choice. And,</p>
<p> of course, exercising that choice is particularly important for a</p>
<p> community such as your own. You are able through the tremendous support</p>
<p> that you give to schools like Mt Scopus, along with government assistance,</p>
<p> you are able to preserve in a special and a very effective way your</p>
<p> own distinctive culture and your own beliefs. But you do it as an</p>
<p> integral part of the Australian community. You are practising the</p>
<p> preservation of what is dear and special to you but you are doing</p>
<p> it in a way which continues to contribute to and enrich the overall</p>
<p> character of Australian life.</p>
<p>Australia is the beneficiary of a plural system of education. Just</p>
<p> as I don't believe in monopolies in commerce I don't believe</p>
<p> in monopolies in education. I don't believe that the State has</p>
<p> a right to monopolise the provision of education. I believe that certain</p>
<p> educational standards laid down and required of all schools are reasonable.</p>
<p> But beyond that the value system, the spiritual beliefs, the cultural</p>
<p> heritage that is taught within those schools is ultimately available</p>
<p> to those Australian parents who seek to exercise a choice in the education</p>
<p> of their children. And this school has done it in a most remarkable</p>
<p> way. And it is an enormous tribute to the Jewish community of Melbourne,</p>
<p> it's a remarkable tribute to the strength and the resilience</p>
<p> and the sense of family that has been a hallmark of the Jewish community</p>
<p> in Australia. And as Solomon said, I have been an unashamed and unapologetic</p>
<p> friend of Israel and of the Jewish community in Australia all of my</p>
<p> public life and my affection for the Jewish people and my association</p>
<p> with them long pre-dated my entry into politics.</p>
<p>And what has been achieved by Australian Jews in all walks of life</p>
<p> is truly remarkable. They have preserved their distinctive Jewish</p>
<p> characteristics and beliefs but they have done so as true and straight</p>
<p> and stalwart Australians and the loyalty and the commitment of the</p>
<p> Jewish community to the overall national interest of the Australian</p>
<p> community has been quite remarkable. I am, therefore, particularly</p>
<p> pleased to be here tonight.</p>
<p>I want to honour the tremendous commitment of Solomon Lew and his</p>
<p> wife Rosie to this cause of this school. I want to honour all of you</p>
<p> for the fact that you have been prepared to support something that</p>
<p> adds enormous value to the life of a nation. Any school that teaches</p>
<p> the values of the spirit, as well as sheer academic achievement, any</p>
<p> school that seeks to combine the values of the spirit, education,</p>
<p> sporting and other endeavours is adding enormous value to the Australian</p>
<p> community.</p>
<p>We have many gifts in this country, but we are a nation ultimately</p>
<p> that will continue to survive and continue to do well if we use and</p>
<p> nurture our intellectual capital to the maximum possible extent. We</p>
<p> are only 18.5 million people and we inhabit a vast continent and increasingly</p>
<p> as the years go by and we move into the 21st century we will have</p>
<p> rely more and more on the use and the effective application of our</p>
<p> intellectual capital. And in so many fields of human endeavour that</p>
<p> intellectual capital is quite remarkable. And the community of Mount</p>
<p> Scopus by dint of what it stands for and by dint of the men and women</p>
<p> that have graduated from the college is playing a very significant</p>
<p> role in it.</p>
<p>Ladies and gentlemen I salute your achievement. I salute the contribution</p>
<p> of the Jewish community of Melbourne to the life, not only of the</p>
<p> Australian Jewish community, but the life of the broader Australian</p>
<p> community. I recognise and continue to uphold the importance of the</p>
<p> links that exist between Australia and the state of Israel. It is</p>
<p> an old friendship, nurtured in more difficult times but preserved</p>
<p> through the years in the face of changing political fashion and changing</p>
<p> political attitudes. There is great affection in Australia for what</p>
<p> Israel has achieved. There is great admiration for the triumphs of</p>
<p> over great adversity and great difficulty and great hostility by such</p>
<p> a small country. There is a recognition of the tremendous generosity</p>
<p> of the people of Israel over the years to so many immigrants from</p>
<p> all around the world.</p>
<p>I, as Prime Minister, am immensely proud of the tolerance and the</p>
<p> diversity of the Australian community. We have welcomed people from</p>
<p> more than 150 nations. It is a remarkable achievement. It is a tribute</p>
<p> to the decency and the honourability of the average Australian and</p>
<p> we have done it in a very remarkable and a very harmonious fashion.</p>
<p> And it's an opportunity such as this, people coming together</p>
<p> as part of a vibrant community here in the city of Melbourne to celebrate</p>
<p> the joy of living in Australia in 1999 and the expectation of continuing</p>
<p> to enjoy the benefits of our nation and our society as we move into</p>
<p> the 21st century.</p>
<p>I congratulate the Mount Scopus community. I thank it for the contribution</p>
<p> that it is making to the education of the young men and women of the</p>
<p> Jewish community here in Melbourne and I especially honour the personal</p>
<p> contributions of so many people here tonight who have made that dream,</p>
<p> of which Rosie spoke earlier, come to fruition and to be made possible.</p>
<p>Thank you very much indeed for having me as your guest tonight.</p>
<p> [ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
