<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1708</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE RT. HON. HAROLD HOLT, CH, MP, IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES - 2ND NOVEMBER 1967 - FUTURE PROGRAMME OF BEEF ROAD DEVELOPMENT IN THE NORTH</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/11/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001708.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
' k VER'. S<br />
CL<br />
( y lJNOyi% 7<br />
STATEiIENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE RT. HON. HAROLD HOLT, M. P.,<br />
IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES<br />
2nd NOVEMBER, 1967<br />
FUTURE PROGRAMME OF BZF ROAD DEVELOPMENT IN THE NORTH<br />
I am pleased to announce to Honourable Members that the<br />
Premiers of Queensland, Western Australia and South Australia<br />
have accepted a Commonwealth offer to provide, over the seven<br />
year period from 1st July 1967, non-repayable grants totalling<br />
350 million for the further development of beef roads in<br />
Northern Austrelia.<br />
Of the total amount, $ 39.5 million will be made available<br />
to the State of Queensland, ' 9.5 million to the State of<br />
Western Australia and l million to the State of South Australia.<br />
The programme to be undertaken in Queensland will provide<br />
for the construction of selected roads in the Channel Country<br />
and the Gilbert, Burdekin, Fitzroy, MIitchell, Cape York and<br />
Gulf Regions. In Western Australia the programme will cover<br />
selected road works in the Kimberley Region and in South<br />
Australia permanent work on the Biidsville Track. The overall<br />
programme in each State will be capable of some variation if this<br />
is desirable. Each State will be the constructing authority for<br />
its roads and will be solely responsible for necessary maintenance.<br />
Honourable Members will recall that the Commonwealth,<br />
in collaboration with the appropriate State Governments, has<br />
been continuously associated with beef road development in the<br />
North since 1961. The Commonwealth has spent ? 10.4 million<br />
since 1961 on its own initial beef roads programme in the<br />
Northern Territory, linked with the developments in the States,<br />
and has begun work on a further programme estimated to cost<br />
$ 14.3 million. As well, the Commonwealth has provided by<br />
way of grants and loans to the States, ' 28.9 million, in a<br />
programme which has triggered-off an expansion of private<br />
investment in the beef industry. This in turn will result<br />
in greater beef production, in increased prosperity in the<br />
North and in greater export earnings for Australia as a<br />
whole. The further programme I now announce is evidence of<br />
the Commonwealth's desire to foster the further development<br />
of the beef industry and the North generally, I am confident<br />
that the next seven years will see tremendous benefits from<br />
this programme, not only to the North, but to the Nation as<br />
a whole. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
