<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8967</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ KEATING MP, UNITED NATIONS CENTRE, NEW YORK, USA 15 SEPTEMBER 1993</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/09/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008967.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL: 16-. Sep. 9,3 9: 15 No. 007 P. 08/ 0<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH THE PRIME MINISTER, THE IfON. P. 3.<br />
KEATING, UNITED NATIONS CENTRI!, NEW YORK, U. S. A.<br />
SEPTEMBJER, 1993<br />
J: Prime Minister, did the U. N. ask for any more Australian contribution to<br />
peacekeeping efforts?<br />
PM: No, I had the chance of a good discussion with the S ecretary-General about the<br />
United Nations, about its rote in the world today and its future. I reassured him of<br />
Australia's commitment to the United Nations, as a foundation member, which has<br />
always paid its dues on time and which has committc4 itself to the serious work of'<br />
the including peace keeping. The Secretary-General told me that there is<br />
great difficulty in managing the organisation with many countries not paying their<br />
funding to the organisation on time which, he says, constrains its capacity to<br />
play the role it can play in the world.<br />
I've assured him that we will continue to be the stolid supporters of the<br />
organisation which we are and that his agenda for peace initiative which he<br />
unveiled some time ago that Australia is responding to that seriously with a<br />
major work. And that in all the other activities that the United Nations undertakes<br />
we'll continue to play the role we've played. In the czurse of his discussions with<br />
me he indicated that the U. N's role goes, of course, beyond peace keeping to other<br />
agendas; like the agenda for women and other humanitarian and social programs.<br />
And I indicated to him that Australia was intent upon holding an international<br />
conference on multiculturalismi next year and he indicated, very generously,<br />
support for that proposal. So, we shall probably end up, I think, next year holding<br />
a conference on multiculturalisin an international confcrence, with the support<br />
of the United Nations and its Secret ary-General.<br />
T. How extensively did you preview the Evans proposals?<br />
PM: Not extensively but he said he was grateful that Australia had responded and was<br />
participating in the dcbatc about the organisation's future. And that was the kind<br />
of debate that he wanted stimulated and he was pleased that we were responding in<br />
the serious way that we were.<br />
J Did you express any reservations about some of the, apparently, appalling things<br />
the U. N. has been up to in Somalia? </p>
<p>TEL<br />
PM: No, only to say that I thought that if the U. N's prestige matters that like any other<br />
organisation it has got to build a constituency for itself within the populations and<br />
the communities of member states. That whatever it does it should try and pick its<br />
mark so that what it does it does well. So " that with its prestige high, its charter<br />
can then be more effective.<br />
J: So, are you concerned about some of the things going on in Somalia?<br />
PM: Well, in some respects, in some particular things, yes. But, I didn't go to the<br />
particular in this discussion.<br />
J: Do you think Australia is doing enough, sufficiently, in the peace keeping area?<br />
PM: Well, we've I think, at the moment got about 600 people in Cambodia. We're in the<br />
Middle East and the Sahara and I think probably we've got upwards of 700 people<br />
around the world in peace keeping. I think the Secretary-General thinks we're<br />
pulling our weight which I am sure we are. And, in Australia's terms, we can only<br />
support this organisation institutionally, support the requests when we think we<br />
can meet them and play our role and pay our dues on time.<br />
J: Did you discuss East Timor with the Secret ary-General, Sir?<br />
PM: No.<br />
J: Could you comment on the latest U. S. moves to put pressure on the Government<br />
of Indonesia?<br />
PM: No. I didn't discuss it with him.<br />
J: But could you comment?<br />
PM: No, I'm not here to discuss that.<br />
J1: Mr Keating you haven't thought about taking a peace keeping force with you to<br />
confront the tabloids in London, have you?<br />
PM: Not I thought you'd do that.<br />
Ends. T1E6L:. Sep. 93 9: 15 No. 00? P. 09/ 09 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
