<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1544</transcript-id>
    <title>HONG KONG -  PRESS CONFERENCE GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. HAROLD HOLT  3RD APRIL, 1967</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/04/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001544.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
ASIAN TOUR 1967 41~<br />
HONG KONG 10AR16<br />
PRESS CONFERENCE GIVEN BY TIM~ PRIMAE MINISPER9 QSIRAOV<br />
MR. HAROLD HOLT 3RD APRIL,,_ 1967.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I think most of you are aware of the reasons<br />
particula reasons anyhow why I am making this journey. It will<br />
include, apart from this visit in transit to Hong Kong, the visits<br />
I have already made to Laos and to Cambodia and from there we<br />
proceed to Taiwan and South Korea.<br />
Australia over recent years has become increasingly<br />
involved in the affairs of this region of the world in a commercial<br />
and trading sense particularly since the dramatic growth of our<br />
trade with Japan. As striking evidence of that, vie have now become<br />
the second or third largest customer for the export of Japanese<br />
goods and Japan has now outstripped the United Kingdom as the<br />
largest purchaser in value of Australian exports. But it is in<br />
the military and diplomatic fields that we are also finding ourselves<br />
increasingly involved in the affairs of the region and so, since<br />
becoming Prime Minister, I have tried to develop a closer and better<br />
knowledge of the countries, the leaders and the peoples within the<br />
area and to manifest Australia's growing interest by my own presence<br />
and that of members of my official party,<br />
Last year, I went to the centres where Australia had its<br />
own forces operating, whether in South Vietnam in direct military<br />
operations or in other places such as Malaysia, where we have<br />
people on station in the strategic reserve, or in Borneo where,<br />
at that time, they were serving in aid of Malaysian forces in<br />
coping with the Indonesian Confrontation Policy. This year I<br />
have sought to round off that sariee of visits by including the<br />
countries which I have not previously visited in this area, and<br />
once I ha, v e completed this tour, I think, with the exception of<br />
Mainland China, I will just about have covered the field. But<br />
there is no specific political purpose, I mean I am not here to<br />
negotiate treaties or enter into any special agreements<br />
with any of the countries concerned, as you will gather from the<br />
composition of the two countries pursuing official policies of<br />
neutrality, and South Korea which has joined with us in forming<br />
part of the friendly forces engaged ini support of the South<br />
Viotnamese, and Taiwan with which Australia has had a long<br />
friendship and a growing trade connection.<br />
So it is, as you will gather, not a simple uncomplicated<br />
pattern of visits, but the prime purpose is to get to know the<br />
countries better, make Australian policies better known to them.<br />
An,* there is, I think, an indirect consequence which is of<br />
considerable value to us. Thanks to the assistance we received<br />
from people like yourselves, the countries and peoples and their<br />
problems are made increasingly known to my fellow countrymen in<br />
Australia as a result of these visits.<br />
Now, perhaps having said that I could try to cope with<br />
any questions you may have.<br />
Q. Mr. Holt, would you say it is safe to say, that<br />
Australia is becoming now, more and more Asia conscious and<br />
possibly might even want to get into Asia in a way of speaking?<br />
P. M. Wiell, vie are in Asia in a very practical and realistic<br />
fashion. We are not only in Asia geographically and a certain part<br />
of South East Asia, but the ullustration I have given of the growth<br />
of Asia, the involvement of military forces, the increasing<br />
participation of Australians in the various instrumentalities such<br />
as ASPAC, the Asian Development Bank, SEATO, and ANZUS treaty<br />
arrangements these are an i'llustration of active Australian<br />
particiaation in the affairs of Asia. So it is not so much a case<br />
/ 2. </p>
<p>-2<br />
of becomiing involved in the work for the first time there has<br />
been an increase in the degree of participation. This doesn't<br />
imply that vwe have diminishied our interest in other areas of the<br />
world. Later in the year I shall be making visits to Canada for<br />
the Australian participation in Expo 67 and in the course of that<br />
will be making a visit to Washington and also to London<br />
Waahington and London still being, of course, the principal centres<br />
of diplomatic interest for my country.<br />
Q. You put a great deal of stress on trade but a number of<br />
people in other Asian countries are somewhat disturbed by what is<br />
referred to generally as the White Australia policy I refer to<br />
immigration.<br />
P. M. Well in my experience, that conccrn is manifested more<br />
by representatives of the press than by representatives of the<br />
government concerned. I find on behalf of the governments<br />
concerned, an intelligent appreciation of Australia's attitude and<br />
the basis for its policy. I think too, there is an inadequate<br />
realisation of the liberalisation of the policy which has occurred<br />
over recent years. Just to illustrate that, there are some thirty<br />
thousand people who have come into Australia in the years since the<br />
war and -\: lould not have been eligible to enter Australia under the<br />
rules and arrangements which applied prior to that time. There<br />
are at this time some twelve thousand students from countries of<br />
Asia in Australian universities and colleges. Same six thousand<br />
Asian citizens over recent years have become fully naturalised<br />
Australian subjects. Any Asian who marries in Australia several<br />
do they enter Australia with full rights as residents, their<br />
children are full citizens of Australi. So there refmains a<br />
degree of misconception about the policy and its operation. And<br />
the liberalised arrangements make provision also for people to<br />
be admitted ,. ho can make a contribution to Australia's growth<br />
development I think that when one considers the numbers involved<br />
and the manner in which citizens of Asia are currently received in<br />
Australia, it will be seen there has been a considerable liberalisation.<br />
It was said not long ago in my presence, and I think it<br />
is a fact, that there is no country in the world in w--hich a citizen<br />
of Asia or a citizen of a country in Africa would find themselves<br />
better or more comfortably treated as they would in Australia,<br />
outside of their own country. This would be their experience and<br />
this is echoed by the students and others who come to the country.<br />
We find that on their return they are the best ambassadors we can<br />
hope for in building better relations with my country.<br />
Q. Prime Minister Holt, during your talks with Prince<br />
Sihanouk did he give you the impression that Cambodia might be<br />
willing to re-establish diplomatic relations with the U. S.?<br />
P. M. Well, my talks with Prince Sihanouk were private and<br />
confidential talks. It is not part of my purpose to narrate<br />
publicly what passed between us. If he wishes to make any<br />
comment about the talks, that of course, is within his province<br />
to do so, but I regard the discussion as a confidential one and<br />
I wouldn't feel free to narrate.<br />
Q. W~ ell, did you get the impreosion that Cambodia might<br />
now be willing to resume contact a~ ith the U. S.?<br />
P. M. Well, I don't think this is other than trying to present<br />
the question in a slightly different form, as you have done.<br />
Prince Sihanouk has made it publicly clear that his country pursues<br />
a policy of neutrality and non alignment. I believe he wishes to<br />
proceed on a basis of friendship and peace with other countries of<br />
the world, but I don't want to put into hiis mouth, words which he<br />
is quite capable of expressing himself. e s/ 3 </p>
<p>-3<br />
Q. Acting in the interests of the United States, which you<br />
did in Cambodia, were any messages exchanged throui'i the Australian<br />
Embassy or throughi yourself?<br />
PM. If you mean, did I purport or attempt to convey messages<br />
from any other government, the answer is a simple no, and I don't<br />
want to go any further than that in any reference to what passed<br />
between Prince Sihanouk and myself. We had a most valuable and<br />
interesting talk together running over an hour and three quarters.<br />
I am quite certain that he w4ouldn't have talked as freely as he<br />
did unless he felt confident in what passed between us. He<br />
expreased a basis of respect of mutual confidence and that is the<br />
basis on which I wish to treat it.<br />
Q. Mr. Holt you canft consider giving us detailed information<br />
about your talks in Cambodia. What about the other countries you<br />
did visit, did any really significant, really important points<br />
emerge7<br />
P. M. Well, I don't want to imply that nothing really important<br />
emerged in Cambodap. It was a most important visit, a very valuable<br />
one. I came away myself with a much clearer appreciation, I believe,<br />
of the basis of policy in Cambodia. I hadn't realised previously<br />
the intense feeling in -the country for the retention of the Khmner<br />
tradition, the separate identity of Cambodia related to a historic<br />
past goin,~ back over many centuries, and it became more readily<br />
understandable to me why Cambodia had been following the particular<br />
line it has in its foreign policies over recent years.<br />
The only other country so far that I have visited has<br />
been Laos, and -there we had a special interest based on the strategic<br />
importance of the country in relation to the security of South East<br />
Asia generally. The fact that Australia has been a contributor of<br />
aid in useful diroctions there, has been a good basis of friendship<br />
between our two countries and I was glad to build on this by the<br />
personal contacts I made with the King and Prime Minister and other<br />
leaders of the country. The impression gained there encouraged me<br />
to say something on this aspect of propa, anda, which we have to face<br />
so frequently from communist sources, that the programmes of aid<br />
and processes of aid are those producing a brand of neo-colonialism.<br />
And I attempted to deal with that directly by referring to the<br />
situation of Laos as illustrating the importance and the values of<br />
these programmes of aid. Here is a country which is able to preserve<br />
its identity, is able to improve its material circumstances, is able<br />
to make itself more secure in a military sense because friends with<br />
goodwill and of no ulterior purpose have made resources available<br />
to them, and given them support.<br />
Here is a country which haj had to face the ravages of<br />
man and the ravages of nature under conditions of great difficulty<br />
for many years. And without this kind of aid, then the oldest<br />
colonialism of all, the enslavement to the age-old enemnies of<br />
mankind of ill health, pover ty, illiteracy, lack of securitsy<br />
in onets national affairs these things would be perpetuated,<br />
I believe, as a result of the kind of aid that countries of<br />
goodwill are giving to Laos, vie will help to overcome what<br />
otherwise would be an enslavement to the past and a chaining<br />
to these backward destructive processes.<br />
Q. Mr. Holt, speaking of Cambodia there waa a story<br />
in the press to the effect that Prince Siliianouk had more or less<br />
admitted to you the fact that North Vietnam was flying troops and<br />
materials to South Vietnam through the country of Cambodia and<br />
that he, or his government, would make efforts to cease tjaat.<br />
Is that so?<br />
P. M. I can see that you won't take no for an answer, because<br />
I have already said I have no intention of publicly indicating<br />
what passed privately between us. 0 0/ 40 </p>
<p>4<br />
Q. How would you account for that story getting out then?<br />
P. M. I would have to be accountable for every story which<br />
appears in the press relating either to myself, my-discussions<br />
or those of other people. I learned with some amusement shortly<br />
after leaving Australia that I was limping my way through my<br />
Asian tour as a result of some injuries I sustained in the water<br />
in Australia. I had a couple of abrasions but I thought I was<br />
getting along without noticeable defects in my pedestrian,<br />
Q. Excuse me Mr. Halt, would you be interested in the<br />
possibility of increased armed commitment in Vietnam and<br />
particularly after Air Marshal Ky's visit to your country?<br />
P. M. We have already indicated publicly the extent of our<br />
military participation and we have no plans to increase that at<br />
the present time.<br />
Q. Don't you find it rather embarrassing, Mr. Holt, that<br />
while Australia is committed in Vietnam, her racial partner<br />
Britain is not committed. Whereas Britain seeks American support<br />
in Europe. Is it not embarrassing? ( The main portion of the<br />
text of this question was unintelligible due to badly spoken<br />
English).<br />
P. M. No, I don't find it embarrassing. Australia is an<br />
independent country capable of adopting independent attitudes<br />
in its foreign policies as of course is the United Kingdom and<br />
Canada, India and other members of the Commonealth of Nations.<br />
Australia, in pursuit of its own interests and in support of<br />
principles which it has supported by military participation in<br />
two world wars, in Korea, in Malaysia in resisting Indonesian<br />
Confrontation, has come with other fitiendly forces in support<br />
of the South Koreans ( Vietnamese?) in resisting what we believe<br />
to be a communist inspired agreesion in that country. Our<br />
reasons, I think, have been made clear enouGh for the<br />
participation. The Australian electorate wihere this was foughtas<br />
an outstanding issue of the last eledtioa campaign<br />
overwhelmingly endorsed the Government's policy in this direction,<br />
and the visiting Prime Minister Ky highlighted not only issues<br />
but the fact of Australian support for South Vietnam.<br />
Yes, but it is said that Britain is interested in<br />
retaining American support in Europe so is Australia interested<br />
in retaining American presence in Asia, this is in direct result<br />
of her maintaining her military presence in Asia. Do you<br />
subscribe to this view?<br />
P. M. Well, I find it rather an involved question. I have<br />
tried to indicate why it is that Australia is participating.<br />
I repeat, we are quite capable of making up our owin minds as<br />
to what we should do on these issues, and each country of course<br />
consults its own interests. But in Australia's case, our own<br />
interests also include our presence in what we hope would be a<br />
more peaceful and more secure world. We have not waited for<br />
these threats to come to our shore in the past, if we felt the<br />
peace of -the world w.. as threatened. We fought in two world wars,<br />
as you mentioned, many thousands of miles away from our own shores.<br />
Much of the fighting in which we have participated since has been<br />
conducted a long Way from Australia.<br />
Q. Mr. Prime Minister, are you encouraged by the free<br />
world's military position in Vietnam' 4<br />
P. M. I think it has greatly improved, yes, even since I was<br />
in Saigon myself. At that time I came back and expressed my<br />
confidence that the Viet Cong and the North Vietnamese could<br />
not win the military confliat there. Events which have occurred<br />
since then, I think, have produced a considerable improvement in<br />
the position of the South Vietnamese and those supporting them.<br />
ot. / 5 </p>
<p>Q. By this do you imply Mr. Premier, that you expect a<br />
political solution or a military solution. The Viet Cong won't<br />
win militarily, that means they won't be defeated militarily.<br />
P. M. I have always felt that for a satisfactory solution<br />
which had any prospect of enduring, there had to be a political<br />
solution, I predicted when I came back from Saigon about a year<br />
ago, that as the Viet Cong were forced either into a retreat or<br />
were defeated in the military sense, they would tend to concentrate<br />
more on guerrilla activities and put pressure perhaps on other<br />
countries outside of South Vietnam itself. And I based that<br />
judgement on what has occurred in Malaysia where, for ma~ ny years,<br />
a comparatively few guerrillas wiere able to occupy the attention<br />
of very much larger forces at very great expense. So that to<br />
achieve a military victory or a series of victories against massed<br />
and organised military forces of Viet Cong and North Vietnamese<br />
would not produce the abiding solution unless as a result of this,<br />
or accompanying it, there were a political solution also.<br />
Q. ( Indistinct, but concerning peace talks for Vietnam)<br />
P. M. It is true that attempts have proved abortive but that<br />
doesn't mean that the attempts should be abandoned. Australia<br />
has supported thle attempts made to find a solution which would<br />
produce a just and enduring peace. In my own experience, which<br />
is not only in the external field, but as a former Minister for<br />
Labour dealing with communist led unions, I found that, although<br />
you seem to be up against a brick wall in negotiation and it<br />
becomes an impasse, once the communists themselves come to the<br />
conclusion that it is no longer profitable to pursue their tactics,<br />
you can get a quite dramatic switch you know, without regard to<br />
consistency or logic or anything that has been said previously as<br />
to where they.-stood. And contemporary history is studded with<br />
instances of this kind, from the Berlin crisis onwards.<br />
Q. ( Indistinct but -to the effect,: Do you expect a shift<br />
in American policy as a result of the Presidential Elections or a<br />
dramatic change in the military climate?)<br />
P. M. I don't see that the American elections should affect<br />
the basic situation because, after all, there have been three<br />
American Presidents in succession and coming from different sides<br />
of the political spectrum in the United States who have all<br />
consistently supported American involvement in support of the<br />
South Vietnamese. I would think that any American Presidential<br />
Candidate who stood on a platform of abandoning the South<br />
Vietnamese or retreating from the conflict before a just peace<br />
had been discovered would poll very poorly in the United States.<br />
Q. Mr. Holt, do you think we might bring Hanoi closer<br />
to the conference table a little quicker if the air war against<br />
North Vietnam was escalated.<br />
P. M. I am not offering a military judgement on these matters.<br />
We have supported the tactics pursued by those who are more expert<br />
in the military field and I don't wiant to offer a technical comment<br />
on a technical point of aspect.<br />
Your External Affairs Minister made the point here last<br />
week that the bombing of North Vietnam was a question of military<br />
necessity. Do you imply now that military pressure would mean a<br />
military solution ( rest of questio,:, indistinct).<br />
P. M. I think a military solution is much more likely to lead<br />
to a political solution than the absence of military pressure.<br />
This could drag on indefinitely unless the other side were to<br />
Comes to the conclusion that the game wasn't worth the candle. / 6. </p>
<p>-6<br />
Q. Thailand announced recently that they were going to take<br />
a more active part in the war. To what-degree has this move been<br />
prompted or even pressed by the allies.<br />
P. M. Again, the Thai people are quite capable of making up<br />
their own minds as to the course they should follow. Itve had<br />
some interesting~ discussions myself in Thailand and at the Manila<br />
Conference and in Australia, where we had a visit from the Prime<br />
Minister of Thailand, his Foreig.-n Minister and one or two of his<br />
other colleagues last year, and Pote Sarasin, and I am well aware<br />
from these discussions that Thailand is very conscious of' the<br />
threat of communist expansion it has to cope with itself, with<br />
communist guerrilla activity within its own borders, and it believes<br />
the policies being followed by those supporting South Vietnam are<br />
policies more likely to produce peace and stability, economic<br />
development in South East Asia, than surrender to the pressure of<br />
the communists.<br />
Q. How do you expect SEATO to function when it has fallen<br />
flat on its nose thanks to its ( word indistinct) How do you account<br />
for this?<br />
P. M. I find there is still considerable value in SEATO and<br />
discussions together with those -who participate in SEATO have<br />
produced valuable exchanges of views and can lead to co-operative<br />
action in various directions. I don't think that it should be<br />
assumed there is no continuing virtue in SEATO. That is certainly<br />
not the view of my Government nor would it be the view of either<br />
the American or British Governments.<br />
Qb When do you expect the next escalation in the Vietnam<br />
War will be? I wouldn't like to offer an opinion on this. These are<br />
matters largely of military judgement. We respect the judgement<br />
of our military advisers. Theirs is th responsibility of securing<br />
the necessary degree of military victory to produce the result.<br />
Q. Do you think it could be the bombing of power plants in<br />
( word indistinct Haiphong?).<br />
P. M. No, I don't propose to speculate on that. These are<br />
matters, of course, which are discussed between governments<br />
and I have no desire to conjecture publicly.<br />
Q. There have been repeated calls that the bombing should<br />
be stopped and even this would be a stimulant to peace. Do I take<br />
it Sir, the bombing would produce this stimulant?<br />
P. M. We have had no encouragement frora past experience when<br />
there has been a cessation in thie bombing. The other side have<br />
employed these respites to build up their own supplies, accelerate<br />
the movement of troops and President Johnson has made it abundantly<br />
clear that the bombing would be stoppedL if Ithere was a sign of<br />
genuine willingness on the part of the other side to abandon their<br />
aggression, to cease infiltration, to cease the movement of supplies.<br />
But so far there has been no encouraging signs that this would occur.<br />
Q. How about your trip to Taiwan? Is this the first time<br />
you have been there?<br />
P. M. The only other visit to Taiwan was purely incidental,<br />
almost repeated on this occasion by bad weather. I was en route<br />
to Tokyo and scheduled to land here iii Hong Kong but bad weather<br />
caused us to be diverted and I didn't leave the airport, so I can<br />
hardly say it was a visit to Taiwan. For all substantial purposes<br />
this will be my first visit to Taiwan. 0 </p>
<p>7-<br />
What will be your talks with Gover'nment officials?<br />
Will they be more on trade or more politioal2<br />
P. M. The princoipal purpose from my point of view, as I said$<br />
earL. 4r, is to inform my own mind, to get to kniow the leaders of<br />
these countries that I am visiting personally, to concentrate a<br />
certain degree of' attention by my own countrymen on these conries<br />
and their problems. This is a consequence of the visits, but there<br />
is no special purpose, no concealed purpose as far as I am concerned.<br />
Q. What are your vieww on U Thant's proposal on unilateral<br />
cease fire in Vietnam?<br />
P. M. I thought I had already indicated that we fcmxd no<br />
encowmgement from our past experience to adopt such a course, in<br />
the absence of an expressed willingness on the part of the other<br />
side to reciprocate.<br />
Q. Is Australia " All the way with IL. B. J."?<br />
I would just like to comment on that, because it suited<br />
my political opponents to give a -twist to that statement which of<br />
course w~ as never intended. We have been consistently with America<br />
in relation to South Vietnam. On other matters Australia has its<br />
own independent mind, and follows its own mind. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
