<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>482</transcript-id>
    <title>OPENING RSL VILLAGE, CHELTENHAM, 2ND MARCH 1962 - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R G MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/03/1962</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000482.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
OPENING R. S VIL: LAGER , CHELTENHAMi<br />
: D MARCH 1. 62<br />
S. eech by the Prime Minvster the nt. Hon R. Gr, Men i3.<br />
Sir George, and ladies and gentlemen,<br />
I think I ought to begin by telling you that my<br />
appearance here today, and that of my :. ife, are the result of a<br />
long negotiation. Most of last year we were trying to fi:-. d a date,<br />
When we found one that suited George Holland it turned out it<br />
didn't suit me5 and when we found one that suited me it turned out<br />
that it didn't suit somebody else. Je got to a point, finally,<br />
wrhere we both began to wonder whether, if the event came off at the<br />
beginning of March 1962, I would be here in my official capacity<br />
at all. ( Laughter3 But with his usual magnanimity Sir George took<br />
a chance and I did too. Anyhow on a photo finish here we are<br />
and very pleased I am to be able to be here,<br />
Sir George's referring in generous terms to the Aged<br />
Persons' Homes Act is a very interesting conjunction of the planets<br />
I may tell you today, because this particular scheme originated in<br />
one of those rather abrupt remarks that one's wife makes<br />
occasionally at breakfast time. My wife put her finger on this<br />
years ago and said, " This is the great problem and why don't you do<br />
something about it, the problem of providing proper living<br />
accommodation, not in barracks, or institutions, but in an<br />
ordinary human way for people who are up in years?" I was stunned<br />
by this, but my rmind, for once, was quite active, and cut came the<br />
scheme as we now know, it, which of course, has since been<br />
improved. I'm interested to tell you that in her favour because,<br />
without any fall realisaticn of it, when the date for today's<br />
function was fixed Iforgot, you see, that it's her birthday today.'<br />
Now, Sir George, there are two or three reasons I won't<br />
be long why I'm delightedo to be here and one of them, if I may<br />
start off with yourself, is because you are presiding here today,<br />
and have had a great deal to do with this achievement. You know,<br />
contrary to the public impression ladies and gentlemen, it isn't<br />
all beer and skittles being a Prime Minister. I know there are<br />
plenty of applicants for the job at any given moment, but it's<br />
really not all that fun, you see. I've been a Prime Minister,<br />
now, as anybody can tell you, for too long, for about 12 years<br />
and a bit, on my recent term. During the great bulk of that, for<br />
the first 10 or 11 years of that, the Federal President of the<br />
League was George Holland. That means in the course of events<br />
that he and I, over a long period of time, have seen a lot of each<br />
other. It's been a very, very happy association not because I<br />
found it easy to say " No" to him, I occasionally said but<br />
quite frequently, as he'll agree, he got away with a certain amount<br />
of loot rightly or wrongly, and we've had a very, very happy<br />
personal association. Now no Govrnment in Australia will be as effective in<br />
its work as anybody would expect unless it has representing great<br />
groups in the nation competent and responsible people. A Federal<br />
Government charged with responsibilities for repatriation, i. ith<br />
responsibilities in relation to a mass of things affecting exservicemen<br />
and ex-service women, wiould find it difficult to<br />
discharge these responsibilities on a merely departmental basis.<br />
So much depends on the quality of the service organisations and the<br />
responsibility or irresponsibility with which they put forward<br />
their case. I went to say about the League that in my<br />
protracted experience as a Primo Minister and as a Minister, I<br />
know of no organisation which has so firmly and agreeably asserted<br />
what it believes to be the rights of its members and has so<br />
scrupulously refrained from being a mere pressure group. </p>
<p>2.<br />
This is a wonderful record. Of course, although I pay tribute to<br />
many many scores and hundreds and thousands of people for it, I<br />
would like to say that the people who are at the top themselves<br />
can do much to make or mar the relations between the League and<br />
the Government. That is my second reason for being delighted to<br />
be here. The third reason is that I am really delighted, time<br />
after time, with what is being done in this field not in<br />
creating gloomy institutions, not in giving people an idea that<br />
they are put away into a corner and as long as they can eat they<br />
are all right. The whole basis of this Village, the whole basis<br />
of so many of these Homes that have been referred to is that they<br />
reconcile a sort of community life of an agreeable kind extremely<br />
agreeable here with the Bowling Green, with individual life, with<br />
a capacity for being private, with a capacity for being at home<br />
and visiting your friends, and being visited by your friends,<br />
but never just a number in an institution: hiuman beings with<br />
every right in the world as all of us hope to have a home of their<br />
own as they go along past the active working years of their lives.<br />
This has created something that is completely new.<br />
I remember never tired of saying this I remember<br />
when I was a boy in Ballarat I lived with an old Scots grandmother<br />
in a little cottage opposite the Benevolent Asylum which we<br />
youngsters knew, irreverently, as " tae Benev". From the Benevolent<br />
Asylum there came out a trickle of old men, diefly, with corduroy<br />
trousers on, looking a little bit dejected, the whole thing rather<br />
sad., rather pitiful, because in those days people didn't<br />
understand that you don't cease to be a human being when you reach<br />
a certain number of years of life, On the contrary, you become<br />
more and more a human being, and you have your own requirements and<br />
interests, and you want tu live your orwn life.<br />
What has been going on in Australia I shall always be<br />
proud of having had anything to do with and I have had a<br />
little to do with it, I'll never cease to be proud of the fact<br />
that w-. e have taken all of that atmosphere a! ray and we have now got<br />
to a point : 0rhero, as this village demonstrates, fellow citizens,<br />
ourselves, those who are here, meet on normal human terms, and are<br />
able to live happily and enjoy the company of each other and the<br />
company of their friends, not fooling that they are a drug on the<br />
market, but feeling proudly independent individuals, It's very<br />
interesting to me. I've been to a few such places well, fairly<br />
recentlyo At the last one I looked at I met a man Id known many<br />
years before in Mildura. I didn't know that he was living in this<br />
particular place, He was always a cheerful chao, and he was still<br />
a cheerful chap: life and soul of the party, all his friends,<br />
comfortable home, comfortable circumstances. This to me was such<br />
a tremendous improvement on the old idea in which a man could grow<br />
old and unfortunate and just sort of disappear from sight,<br />
So we have 6ot rid of all the elements of condescension<br />
and of charity. We've substituted for these a feeling of goodwill<br />
and of individual responsibility, and of friendship, and of<br />
perpetuating a home atmosphere, and a home life. No Govcrnment<br />
can create those things it can help to bring them about, But<br />
they can be created in physical, terms only by -the enthusiastic<br />
people of the kind who thought of this Village and who hLave<br />
brought it to construction and to completion. I am greatly<br />
indebted to them, as you are. I hope that for i: any, many<br />
generationia to come this will be a centre of a happy life for, in<br />
the long run, hundreds, and perhaps thousands, of men and women.<br />
Sir I have a very great sense of privilege in<br />
declaring the Village open. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
