<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6613</transcript-id>
    <title>SPECIAL PREMIERS&#039; CONFERENCE ON DRUGS, CANBERRA, 2 APRIL 1985, COMMUNIQUE</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/04/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Communique</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006613.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
T 8* 1: UC. S, H.; 18-3-92 10: 33 DRUGS OF DEPENDENCE-# 062715300; g 2<br />
A1 b tLI<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA SPECIAL PREMIERS' COSFERENCE ON DRUGS<br />
CANBERRA 2 APRIL 1985<br />
COMMUNIQUE<br />
The Commonwealth, State and Territory Heads of<br />
Government met in Canberra today in a special Premiers'<br />
Con ferenceand, pledgd-their governments to do everything<br />
possible top combat the growing problems of drug abuse<br />
arnd addiction in Australia. They agreed to mount a<br />
National Campaign Against Drug Abuse in which all<br />
Governments will co-operate and which will also seek the<br />
full involvement and support of the community as a<br />
whol1e.<br />
The Campaign will place a major emphasis on reducing the<br />
demand for drugs through education, treatment and<br />
rehabilitation programs, particularly for young people<br />
and particularly relating to hard drugs.<br />
The Conference noted that the cost to the Australian<br />
community of drug abuse is high whether measured In<br />
terms of death and illness, wasted human potential,<br />
violent and property crime, loss of production or social<br />
misery. It was recognised that drug abuse is a complex<br />
probl * em and that there are no simple or quick solutions.<br />
The Conference agreed that a sustained effort would be<br />
required over a period of years.<br />
The Conference emphasised that governments have a<br />
special responsibility to address problems associated<br />
with those drugs the use of which is illegal in our<br />
society. It was agreed that the Campaign will focus<br />
particularly on illegal drugs. At the same time it was<br />
recognised that there are also widespread health and<br />
social problems arising from the abuse of licit drugs<br />
and that the Campaign will need to encompass these as<br />
well.<br />
The Conference agreed that it was essential that<br />
government efforts to combat drug trafficking and to<br />
prevent supplies of hard drugs coming into the country </p>
<p>SENT BY: D. C. S. H.<br />
be intensified. Particular attention will be paid to<br />
those who control, direct and finance such activities.<br />
The Conference recognised, however, that the drug<br />
problem will not be effectively tackled unless there is<br />
success in reducing the demand for drugs. Every effort<br />
will be made to convince young people of the dangers of<br />
involvement with drugs. Greater assistance and support<br />
will be provided for parents, educators, community<br />
groups and others who work with and counsel young<br />
people. It was also agreed that both the quality and<br />
the quantity of treatment and rehabilitation programs<br />
for those already suffering from drug addiction should<br />
be improved.<br />
Special attention will be given to the needs of<br />
particular sectors of the community. The so called hard<br />
drugs pose a threat to young people generally: but for<br />
other. groups, such as aborigines, abuse of licit drugs,<br />
or substances, may be more significant problems.<br />
The Conference acknowledged that women's pattern of drug<br />
use differs from men's and presents problems which may<br />
require different approaches. There are particular<br />
problems which need to be addressed in the case of<br />
. heroin addicted women who may be forced into<br />
prostitution or, in the case of pregnant addicts, whose<br />
lives and those of their babies may be endangered. The<br />
Conference also noted the greater reliance of women on<br />
minor tranquillisers and agreed that measures were<br />
needed to dissuade doctors and patients from resort to<br />
these drugs of addiction.<br />
The Commonwealth Government will contribute to the<br />
Campaign by the funding of national projects and by<br />
making additional funds available to the States. The<br />
States and the Northern Territory will continue and<br />
expand existing programs, provide matching funds and<br />
administer a major part of Commonwealth funding.<br />
The Commonwealth Government has committed itself to a<br />
long-term program of assistance. For the next three<br />
years it has agreed to provide up to an additional<br />
million a year for the education, treatment,<br />
rehabilitation and research aspects of the campaign. It<br />
will also be spending substantially increased amounts on<br />
strengthening law enforcement. Of the $ 20m, which will<br />
be indexed, $ 8 million will be allocated for national<br />
projects which will be fully funded by the Commonwealth.<br />
The remaining $ 12 million will be available to the<br />
States and Territories to match increased expenditure<br />
undertaken by them.<br />
SEBNYT3CD -., 9 2 H .1810-: 33 DRUGS OF DEPENDENCE-# 0662771553000;;;; 3 </p>
<p>S~ NT ~ yO. 3C-9.2 10: 34 DRUGS OF DEPENDENCE-* 67130;<br />
3<br />
The Campaign will be co-ordinated and oversighted by the<br />
ministerial Council on Drug Strategy which wiii report<br />
to the Premilers' Conference. The Council will have the<br />
authority to deal with all matters related to drugs of<br />
dependence. The Conference agreed on the introduction of a number of<br />
specific initiatives.<br />
Euaion Progr am s<br />
The Conference agreed that, in consultation with the<br />
States The National Drug Education Program will be<br />
upgraded; New drug education materials are to be developed,<br />
to assist those who educate, counsel or work with<br />
young people and others at risk; materials will be<br />
made available for use in schools;<br />
Use will be made of media campaigns, in conjunction<br />
with other drug education initiatives, to inform<br />
and educate the community about drug problems# and<br />
to provide positive directions to assist the<br />
community in preventing and overcoming such<br />
problems. Training programs on drug abuse matters for both<br />
lay and professional workers in education, health<br />
and welfare areas will be improved;<br />
24 hour telephone information services on drugs,<br />
staffed by trained counsellors, is recommended in<br />
those States and Terrritories where they do not<br />
already exist.<br />
Treatment and Rehabilitation<br />
The Conference agreed that existing methadone<br />
maintance programs should be expanded and new ones<br />
established; the existing guidelines for the use of<br />
methadone will be reviewed. The Conference was<br />
opposed to the provision of heroin as a treatment<br />
for drug addiction.<br />
it was also agreed that a range of special<br />
treatment and rehabilitation services for drug<br />
abusers be established in teaching hospitals and<br />
other major hospitals.<br />
Treatment and rehabilitation services are to be<br />
made available to drug dependent prisoners.<br />
, SENT D. C. S. H. 062715300; 4 4 </p>
<p>S; E18N-T 3H-. 9 2 10: 34 DRUGS OF DEPENDENCE-# 6750;<br />
4<br />
Regular evaluation of programs by community<br />
agencies will be a condition of continued<br />
government funding of services.<br />
Research and Information<br />
The Conference endorsed the establishment of<br />
National and State drug data collection systems.<br />
It was agreed that there is a need for more<br />
ressearch into the prevention and treatment of drug<br />
abuse; it has been agreed in principle that one or<br />
more centres of excellence will be established; the'<br />
States have been invited to bring forward<br />
proposals.<br />
Legislation It was agreed in principle that there should be<br />
uniformity of approach among jurisdictions on<br />
legislation governing'drugs of dependence,' and<br />
broad consistency on key issues such as<br />
classification of drugs and thrust of offences and<br />
penalties. The Conference noted that the<br />
Commonwealth is developing a model legislation<br />
packa . ge covering the regulation of the manufacture,<br />
distribution and medical use of drugs of<br />
dependence; diversion for treatment; and penal<br />
provisions. The package will be developed in<br />
consultation with the States.<br />
The Conference agreed in principle that legislation<br />
be introduced to enable the forfeiture and<br />
confiscation of assets of convicted drug dealers.<br />
This matter is to be discussed further by the<br />
Standing Committee of Attorneys-General.<br />
The Conference agreed that there should be a review<br />
of the controls on the use of barbiturates and it<br />
was agreed that this matter be examined urgently.<br />
Existing controls on cannabis are to be maintained.<br />
Law Enforcement<br />
The Conference endorsed the importance of achieving full<br />
co-operation between law enforcement authorities both<br />
within jurisdictions and between jurisdictions. The<br />
Conference called on all relevant authorities to ensure<br />
that they work together in a co-operative way.<br />
The Conference noted the actions being taken by the<br />
Commonwealth and the States to strengthen their<br />
capabilities to deal with drug trafficking. The<br />
Commonwealth will over the next three years be spending<br />
$ 7 million on computer capacity and $ 10 million on<br />
additional manpower for the'Australian Federal Police.<br />
SENT P: 0. C. S. H. 062715300; 4 </p>
<p>062715300;# 6<br />
SEN BYD. HC. S;, 1 8-3-92 ; 10: 35 DRUGS OF DEPENDENCE-4<br />
It will provide additional resources of the order of<br />
million over the next two years to enhance the<br />
capacity of the Australian Bureau of Criminal<br />
Intelligence to provide drugs intelligence to all<br />
participating law enforcement agencies.<br />
The Commonwealth will also provide substantial resources<br />
equipment and staff costing $ 5.5 million over 2<br />
years to strengthen the capacity of the Australian<br />
Customs Service to interdict drugs entering Australia.<br />
Fixed barrier operations will be buttressed with<br />
additional surveillance, enhanced communication and xray<br />
machines. There will also be a revised Customs<br />
strategy for the North.<br />
The Conference noted that the Australian Police<br />
Ministers' Council and the Australian Transport Advisory<br />
Council would be considering measures to upgrade<br />
waterfront security, including a recommendation for a<br />
) new National Port Security Authority.<br />
The Conference also noted the recently introduced<br />
arrangements for coastal surveillance,. including the<br />
Coaslal Protection Unit within the Australian Federal<br />
Police. The importance of ensuring adequate<br />
surveillance of the Australian coastline was recognised.<br />
Australia's strong commitment to international efforts<br />
to combat drug trafficking will continue. opportunities<br />
for increased co-operation with other countries on<br />
narcotics matters will be actively pursued.<br />
The Conference agreed that telephone interception powers<br />
can be a valuable aid in investigation of drug<br />
trafficking. The Commonwealth will extend such powers<br />
in relation to drug trafficking to the States, subject<br />
to stringent controls being exercised over their use.<br />
The controls will include a requirement for judicial<br />
) warrants<br />
The Commonwealth will create a new offence of sending<br />
illicit drugs through the mail. The AFP will have<br />
powers to examine suspected mail.<br />
The Commonwealth has decided in principle to amend the<br />
Customs Act to clarify powers to detain and search<br />
persons concealing drugs internally to bring themi Into<br />
Australia; the emphasis will be on detention with<br />
medical search as a last resort. </p>
<p>-SENT 6Y: D C. S. H. ; 18-3-92 1 0* 35 ; DRUGS OF DEPENDENCE-062715300;; 7<br />
6<br />
WHO Recommendations<br />
The Conference agreed to refer to the Health Ministers'<br />
Conference, for consideration without specific<br />
endorsement# strategies on alcohol and tobacco as<br />
recommended by the World Health Organisation.<br />
Drugs and Driving<br />
The Conference agreed that States should give<br />
consideration to the introduction of zero or equivalent<br />
blood alcohol levels for novice drivers, stringent<br />
application of penalties, and more severe penalties for<br />
persistent drink driving offenders.<br />
StrateqX Document<br />
The Conference agreed that a document settifl4 out the<br />
aims and strategy of the National Campaign Against Drug<br />
Abuse should be prepared by the Commonwealth, in<br />
consultation with the States, for release as soon as<br />
possible. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
