<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>798</transcript-id>
    <title>OPENING OF THE HOWARD FLOREY LABORATORIES UNIVERSITY OF MELBOURNE, 30 AUGUST 1963 - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/08/1963</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000798_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
OPENING OF THE HO; ARD FLOREY LABORATORIES<br />
UNIVERSITY OF MELBOURNE<br />
AUGUST, 1963<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister the Rt. Hon. Sir Robert Menzies<br />
Mr. Deputy Chancellor, Mr. Minister, Mr. Vice-Chancellor,<br />
Sir Howard and Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
I want to confess to you that I meet an initial<br />
difficulty. I came out here innocently, thinking that I wap<br />
going to open this building. I see from the print that I am<br />
to dedicate it. Now this you may say is rather out of a<br />
politician's jurisdiction, although I do remember that on one<br />
occasion in suitable circumstances I was introduced to an<br />
audience as the Right Reverend R. Menzies. ( Laughter) Sir,<br />
in that capacity I dedicate this building ( Laughter). In my<br />
other capacity, I open it. But whichever way it goes doesn't<br />
matter very much because the hero of the day is Sir Howard<br />
Florey himself. This is one of those occasions when we get together<br />
and can say quite truthfully, " Let us now praise famous men"<br />
because here is a famous man. I suppose he little thought when<br />
he was a mere stripling in 1921 that in the course of time he<br />
would be a Nobel Prizewinner and President of the Royal Society,<br />
two of many things in his life that have been referred to today.<br />
And I feel rather uncommonly conscious of the privilege you<br />
give me by allowing me to speak anything here today at all,<br />
I look around here here they are, Fellows of the Royal Society,<br />
distinguished physicians, distinguished surgeons, distinguished<br />
chairmen of broadcasting conmissions ( Laughter) ot hoc genus<br />
omni and what is worse, I must have made about five or six<br />
speeches at university events in the last six months and the<br />
first time, I did rather well, It was all fresh, but the second<br />
time I saw the same people ( Laughter) and again and again and<br />
again I looked down and I saw I won't name them but you know<br />
them. ( Laughter) The same eminent audience. All I hope is that<br />
the next time I make a speech on some occasion, some Providence<br />
will intervene and I will be able to begin by saying, " All,<br />
all are gone, the old familiar faces." ( Laughter)<br />
Sir, you did well, if I may say so, to pay tribute<br />
to the remarkable facts financially associated with this establishment<br />
because they are remarkable. Australia has an<br />
honourable record in the field of private contribution to<br />
universities, but on this occasion, this little group of people<br />
of whom two distinguished citizens have been named7 got together,<br />
found a great deal of money and then having established their<br />
bona fides much more satisfactorily than most people who come<br />
to me and ask for money ( Laughter), they arrived, Dr. Denton<br />
with them ( Applause) and I found myself so enthusiastic about<br />
the work that he was doing and the work that would b\ odone in<br />
this laboratory that I avoided the steely eye of Sir Leslie<br />
Martin ( Laughter), had a talk to the Treasurer instead, and we<br />
found œ 100,000 not just tucked into the triennial payment<br />
but an extra. Very useful extra, ( Applause) I mention that to<br />
you in strict confidence ( Laughter) here this afternoon because<br />
I wouldn't like other representatives of other universities to<br />
think that this constitutes a precedent. ( Laughter) And then<br />
the Rockefeller Foundation and the result is that this<br />
represents, in a sense, a tribute to the scientific work, the<br />
remarkable and brilliant scientific work that has been done and<br />
S000000/ 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
a tribute to this great man, Sir Howard Florey which represents<br />
a combination of private interest and contribution and Government<br />
interest and contribution which I think might well set a pattern<br />
in Australia Now Sir, I am not going to detain you very long<br />
because, like you, I'want to hear from the fountainhead, I want<br />
to hear Sir Howard, You all know about him. You all know of<br />
the nature of the work that he has done modestly, rather selfeffacingly<br />
actively, with tremendous imagination, with a willingness<br />
at all times to take up the most challenging problems and<br />
tackle them and try to solve them, and in the result, there will<br />
be many people who go down into history as having been responsible<br />
for great wars or matters of that kind, there will be some<br />
villains go down in history, there will be some wise men go<br />
down in history, but the people who read about the history will<br />
if they have occasion to remember it realise as to a considerable<br />
proportion of them that they wouldn't bo alive to road the<br />
history if it hadnt been for the work that has been done of the<br />
kind that Sir Howard Florey has done in this world. ( Applause)<br />
So that his work and the work of others like him has been<br />
powerful, constructive work for humanity, and this engages the<br />
attention and gratitude of all of us.<br />
There is just one other thing that I would like to<br />
say, I was recently in America, reminding myself for the<br />
purpose of another speech, of the American Declaration of<br />
Independence, with its fine resounding statement that all men<br />
are born equal and thats true, In a human sense that's true.<br />
In terms of civic rights and human and divine responsibility,<br />
men are born equal, but it is a matter for gratitude that in<br />
terms of talent they are not born equal because what has<br />
contributed to the progress of the world, the progress of<br />
humanity, more than anything else perhaps, is that you get<br />
these peaks in the graph of ability, you get these distinguished<br />
p. ople who not only do remarkable things themselves but who<br />
gather around them other people who are all the better because<br />
they worked with a great man. And the result is that thr'. ljgh<br />
the very inequality of talent that exists in human beings, the<br />
ordinary human being like most of us is able to go along better,<br />
happier, with a better future and a better understanding.<br />
I always feel interested when I encounter some<br />
distinguished physicist for example who will say to me before<br />
our conversation ends, " You know I did some work with<br />
Rutherford." This is a wonderful thingo I don't go as far as<br />
Carlylo, you know, about great men being the stuff of history,<br />
but I go to this extent that I believe that the influence of<br />
a remarkable person, of genius of application, of tremendous<br />
drive of force of mind, is not confined to what he does<br />
himself in hiscwn righto It extends to the way that he perhaps<br />
stimulates an entire generation of people in the work that<br />
they do in his branch of knlowledge. Really, of course in<br />
Australia we are occasionally a bit odd aren't we, to be quite<br />
frank about it. We occasionally think in Victoria that a man<br />
from South Australia can't be quite as good, ( Laughter) though<br />
the people : from Adelaide have for years and years been conscious<br />
of their superiority in all moral qualities to the rest of us.<br />
( Laughter) This is well understood.<br />
But apart from that, we are a little bit inclined,<br />
aren't we, to think that everything unknown is to be taken as<br />
magnificent. Grant people in any branch of life are people / 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
who live at a distance, about whom we read in the newispapers<br />
or in the cables. We are not always prepared to recognise,<br />
in their own lifetime, these great men that we have produced,<br />
and today is a very happy proof that here, at any rate, you<br />
don't suffer from that complaint because here we have a man<br />
famous all over the world, so moaest that he has been having<br />
a most ungovernable fit of misery for the last half hour<br />
( Laughter) listening to his praises, But he is entitled<br />
to praise. He is entitled to gratitude because in due course<br />
of time when, as we believe optimistically, things get sorted<br />
out and fall into their proper perspective and proportions, the<br />
name of Howard Florey will be regarded as one of tne absolutely<br />
outstanding names in Australian history.<br />
I am delighted beyond words that this building<br />
which 1 am now authorised by the Deputy Ghancellor to call<br />
a laboratory I have never been too sure how you pronounce<br />
that word rat I am delighted beyond words that this<br />
laboratory should be set up here for all to see to carry out<br />
work of great distinction and utility in his name in my own<br />
university. This is something that gives me especial pleasure<br />
and therefore adds to my satisfaction in dedicating and/ or<br />
opening this building. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
