<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4826</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/09/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004826.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIMESHMIN ISTE<br />
FOR PRESS 17 SEPTEMBER, 1978<br />
ELE CTORATE TALK<br />
The decision of the Conciliation and Arbitration Commission<br />
to replace quarterly national wage increases with six-monthly<br />
hearings is heartening news for Australia.<br />
I believe the decision which comes at a time when<br />
Australia' s rate of inflation is heading towards the five<br />
percent mark--will certainly add to confidence and<br />
economic stability. Less frequent hearings give us greater<br />
opportunity to moderate wage increases. Another piece in<br />
the econom,-ic Jig-saw is falling back into place. It is<br />
good news for business, for manufacturers, for exporters,<br />
for farmers and for Australia's great rural industries.<br />
Moderation in wage increases is critical in the fight against<br />
inflation. It is critical in the restoration of the<br />
profitability of business and industry. But on top of that,<br />
it is fundamental to any g-overnment's attempts to create<br />
new job opportunities and to reduce unemployment.<br />
This decision should mean that companies will be able to<br />
budget ahead with greater confidence in the stability of<br />
business conditions and in the reliability of their forecasts.<br />
Wages are a key and central factor in the control of<br />
inflation. We have only to look back to 1974 and 1975 when<br />
wages went up by 50 percent. In that period, inflation<br />
rocketed and unemployment grew with it. Excessive wage<br />
increases, excessive inflation, cost jobs that's the<br />
experience in Australia and around the world.<br />
Just recently the world's largest trade group, G. A. T. T.<br />
said in its annual report on international trade:<br />
" The inescapable conclusion is that the industrial countries<br />
can only move towards increased growth and employment,<br />
sustainable payments processes and more stable exchange<br />
rates, by reducing their inflation to levels of the<br />
" Inflation does not reduce unemployment, on the contrary, it<br />
is one of the main causes". Clearly, Australia's strong<br />
stand in its fight against inflation is the only responsible<br />
course if we are to bring unemployment down. / 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
Although the Government would have much preferred and<br />
argued for annual wage hearings, the unanimous decisior.<br />
of the Commission is encouraging. I hope that all<br />
governments, employers, and unions will meet the decision<br />
with full and sincere support.<br />
If we continue to restore the economy back to health and<br />
put the jig-saw pieces back in place Australia can<br />
expect an improvement in growth, welfare and job opportunities.<br />
Overseas and local investors can see this happening and<br />
are demonstrating their confidence in Australia. I have no<br />
doubt that this confidence will continue and that after<br />
many years of fighting our way out of near economic chaos,<br />
Australians will see a return to real and sustainable<br />
prosperity. The Australian economy has been given greater breathing space.<br />
We accept and welcome the decision of the Conciliation and<br />
Arbitration Comnmiss ion.<br />
However, all Australians have a part to play in our return<br />
to full economic health. The Government certainly has a role.<br />
We have demonstrated through our determination to press on<br />
with the fight against inflation that we are prepared to<br />
accept our responsibilities. We have been unswerving in our<br />
commitment to get the economy right.<br />
The Arbitration Commission, too, has a key role. Its decision<br />
to replace quarterly hearings with six-monthly hearings<br />
is perhaps the best indication that it accepts its<br />
important role.<br />
We have stressed that employees and employers both have their<br />
part to play.' Employers have a clear responsibility not to<br />
seek unreasonable price increases for their products and<br />
services. Employees have a responsibility not to push<br />
outside the Arbitration Commission for higher wage increases.<br />
Labor Treasurer Frank Crean once said: " One man's wage increase<br />
is another man's job". That remains true today. The more<br />
wages can be restrained, the greater the opportunity<br />
Australian industry will have to find a larger domestic market<br />
and compete more successfully on world markets. That can only<br />
lead to greater job opportunities.<br />
The Government is giving industry this opportunity to develop.<br />
Inflation is falling, interest rates are falling, imbalances<br />
in the economy are being put right, and business investment<br />
is rising. But the recovery process would be quicker if wage<br />
increases were more restrained.<br />
The Government is not in the business of hitting the pockets<br />
of the working men and women of Australia. The figures show that<br />
over the last few years average weekly earnings increased at<br />
a greater rate than inflation as measured by the<br />
Consumer Price Index. I believe the overwhelming majority of<br />
Australians know the damage caused by excessive wage increases.<br />
They sill remember what happened to jobs when wages soared<br />
in 1974 and 1975. 3 </p>
<p>3<br />
The trade union movement know that by pursuing higher and<br />
higher wages they are putting their workers' jobs in<br />
jeopardy. There is an opportunity for us all to work together with<br />
a sense of national purpose to help this great country<br />
move forward into the exciting decade that lies ahead.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
