<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9451</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP MR MCLACHLAN AND ELDERS IXL</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/12/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009451.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER 110/ 94<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
MR MCLACHLAN AND ELDERS IXL<br />
The dschslon of the Victorian Supreme Court to grant the Bank of New Zealand leave to<br />
Issue claims against fo-mer Elders-AXL board members, Including Liberal frontbencher [ an<br />
McLachlan, casts a cloud over Mr McLachlan's Shadow Ministry role as a former direct&amp;-<br />
of thtiicompany.<br />
Mr McLachlan likes to portray himself on television and In the print media-as someone<br />
who resigned from the board, after ten years, because the situation had become<br />
overheated. But as yesterdays decision confirms, he was a director years earlier when<br />
Elders bought 20 per cant of BHP as part of that company's attempt to block the late<br />
Robert Holmes a Courts takeover bid.<br />
As the public now knows, the tactic apparently was that Elders would hold about 20 per<br />
cent of [ 3HP, denying Mr Holmes a Court any chance of compulsory acquisition above<br />
ninety per cent of the stock, and in return OHl-would protect the Elders Board by holding a<br />
large block of Elders stock stock later sold by BHP to Harlin Pty Ltd.<br />
Mr McLichlan might tell the public what contribution he made and how he voted on the<br />
board on these matters whether he supported the move to buy stock in BHP, and if so,<br />
why? Given his frontbench position in the Federal Opposition, he should tell the public if he had<br />
any role in the Hawkins transactions, or if he had any knowledge of those transactions.<br />
The Lealder of the Opposition should insist on knowing the full details of the McLachlan<br />
involvemnent on the board of Elders IXL as it relates to these transactions.<br />
As a board member of a major public company, his contribution on the board of Elders<br />
affected many thousands of public shareholders.<br />
If Mr McLachlan is not forthcoming about his role he should be stood down from the<br />
Opposiiion frontbench until these matters are heard and until evidence of the discharge of<br />
his fiduciary responsibilities confirms that he acted with propriety.<br />
CANBERRA 13 DEC: EMBER, 1994 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
