<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>23811</transcript-id>
    <title>ICAO preliminary report into the downing of MH17</title>
    <prime-minister>Abbott, Tony</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130918 - 20150915</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/09/2014</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Government welcomes the findings of the International Civil Aviation Organisation’s (ICAO) preliminary report on the cause of the MH17 crash.</p>
<p>It is the first official account of the downing of MH17.</p>
<p>The ICAO’s preliminary findings make clear that the tragic downing of MH17 was not due to aircraft malfunction or pilot error.</p>
<p>Instead it was penetrated by a large number of high energy objects from outside the aircraft, leading to an in-flight break up.</p>
<p>The findings are consistent with the Government’s statement that MH17 was shot down by a large surface-to-air missile.</p>
<p>The report draws on data from the black box, satellite imagery and photos from the crash site. Its findings are based on an objective analysis of available evidence.</p>
<p>It does not attribute blame or liability for the incident – this is the role of the multinational criminal investigation led by the Dutch Public Prosecution Service, which is currently underway.</p>
<p>The final ICAO report will likely be released in the second quarter of 2015.</p>
<p>A copy of the interim report has been made available to the families of the victims.</p>
<p>The international community must remain focused on finding, prosecuting and punishing the perpetrators of this cowardly attack.</p>
<p>We owe this to the innocent victims of the MH17 downing and their families.</p>
<p>We are grateful for the Dutch Government’s efforts to coordinate the repatriation and identification of the victims of MH17, as well as its strong leadership of the ICAO and criminal investigations.</p>
<p>9 September 2014</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
