<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8173</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH PAOLO TOTARO, AMANDA BUCKLEY AND GEORGE NEGUS, FACE THE PRESS, SBS TV 25 OCTOBER 1990</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/10/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008173.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME.. MIISE<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH PAOLO TOTARO, AMANDA BUCKLEY<br />
AND GEORGE NEGUS, FACE THE PRESS, SBS TV<br />
OCTOBER 1990<br />
E OE PROOF ONLY<br />
TOTARO: Mr Hawke, what's your dream for SBS in the year<br />
2000?<br />
PM: I hope that it will be stronger, even more widely<br />
watched than it is now. But I won't be relying on my hopes.<br />
I will be delivering on the commitment I made when I<br />
outlined the multicultural program agenda for Australia that<br />
I would be introducing legislation to guarantee in a<br />
statutory form, its independent existence as an independent<br />
corporation. That will be introduced next year, that<br />
legislation, after further discussions with SBS itself and<br />
with the Federation of Ethnic Communities.<br />
TOTARO: Should SBS have additional sources of funding to<br />
the Government?<br />
PM: That's a question which is, as you know, not entirely<br />
hypothetical because you do now. You are able to have<br />
sponsorship and indeed you helped to give the great<br />
telecasting of the World Cup with some assistance by way of<br />
sponsorship. This is a vexed question. The important thing<br />
is that we wrill ensure that you have substantial funding<br />
from the Government. You know I gave the three year<br />
guarantee, real terms guarantee in ' 88 and which means you<br />
get $ 60 million this year from the Federal Government. So<br />
we're not going to let SBS wither because of an absence of<br />
Government financing. The question of advertising is<br />
something which has got to be discussed with the SBS and<br />
with the ethnic communities.<br />
TOTARO: And to you personally, what ways of receiving<br />
additional funds for SBS would be acceptable?<br />
PM: There are really these sources. You've got Government<br />
funding which you'll continue to get, you've got sponsorship<br />
and there's advertising. Now we've got to make sure that<br />
this thing is not imposed from Canberra. That there is<br />
appropriate discussion with you in SBS and with the ethnic<br />
communities so that what emerges is something which is ( a)<br />
understood; acceptable; and effective.<br />
BUCKLEY: Moving on to political matters, Mr Hawke. Next<br />
week you are going up to the Premiers' Conference in </p>
<p>Brisbane and this is, you've said, one of the most important<br />
things you'll ever do as Prime Minister, trying to change<br />
Commonwealth.-State relations. What actual concrete<br />
proposals do you expect to get out of it and, I mean, the<br />
Opposition is saying it's just a gabfest.<br />
PM: Some of the Opposition is. They really have been<br />
repudiated and properly repudiated by other sections of the<br />
political parties opposed to us. Let me pay tribute to Nick<br />
Greiner, the Liberal Premier of New South Wales. Of course<br />
I have some differences with Nick in politics but I pay<br />
tribute to the seriousness with which he is approaching this<br />
together with his Labor Premier colleagues. This attempt to<br />
play petty politics by some sections of the Federal<br />
Opposition is anathema to him, I know, as it is to me. We<br />
are about a serious piece of work here. Now as to the part<br />
of your question as to what we hope to achieve. These<br />
things: first of all it will not all be done in one special<br />
Premiers' conference. This will be the first of a series of<br />
special premiers' conferences. There will be some specific<br />
decisions made. For instance, I hope to be able to get<br />
signed a heads of agreement in regard to a national rail<br />
freight corporation. That's just an example. But<br />
essentially w~ hat we'll be doing, I think, is to say well<br />
here are the areas in which we need now to cooperate,<br />
perceive how we can avoid, for instance, unnecessary<br />
duplication of services, unnecessary duplication of<br />
regulation. We'll establish now ongoing processes so that<br />
we won't wait for some uncertain time in the future where<br />
the whole thing will be done. Ongoing decisions.<br />
NEGUS: Are we talking here in the long run, Mr Hawke, about<br />
less government because it's been almost a conventional<br />
thing to be said around the place that this country is<br />
grossly over-governed, too many governments.<br />
PM: I mean particularly for your viewers who come from<br />
other countries. They must be staggered by the level of<br />
government. We've got 17 million people in Australia and<br />
we've got one House of Parliament virtually for every<br />
million of our people. We've got two federal houses of<br />
parliament. We've got six states which is 11 state<br />
legislatures because it hasn't got an upper house in<br />
Queensland. So there's 11 plus two there's 13; the ACT<br />
14; and 15 when you come to the Northern Territory. That's<br />
just about one House of Parliament for every million of<br />
people. TOTARO: Talking again about<br />
PM: That's crazy. So the point is that we've got to get<br />
more efficient government. We want to say now look if the<br />
Federal Government's doing it and the State Government's<br />
doing it and Local Government's doing it, is there a way in<br />
which we carL rationalise that so there's not overlap?<br />
That's what it's about.<br />
NEGUS: We're not talking about doing away with any of the<br />
tiers though are we? </p>
<p>PM: No. I said back in 1979 in the Boyer Lectures that I<br />
don't think -there'd be anyone in Australia who would<br />
disagree with me. If you were making a decision now as to<br />
what form of government you would have for Australia going<br />
into the 21st century you wouldn't have what you've got.<br />
There's no way. But it's there so the challenge to<br />
intelligent leaders is to say alright how do we make the<br />
existing system work more efficiently. That's what this<br />
Special Premiers' Conference is about.<br />
BUCKLEY: John Hewson says that the way he would do it would<br />
be to abolish Commonwealth departments. Now is it your plan<br />
to make the National Capital more central or to hand back<br />
more powers to the States?<br />
PM: John Hewson frankly doesn't know what he's talking<br />
about. He is an embarrassment to the Liberal Party and to<br />
his state colleagues. He simply doesn't know what he's<br />
talking about. This nonsense that we've had that you'd<br />
abolish the Department of Social Security. I mean it is<br />
laughable. It's repudiated by all the welfare organisations<br />
in Australia. It's repudiated-by anyone who knows something<br />
about the real social needs of Australian people. Of<br />
course, Dr Hewson, the multi-millionaire, doesn't understand<br />
the Coming to the specifics of your question<br />
BUCKLEY: Mr Hawke<br />
PM: There are some areas, Amanda, in which I believe it<br />
would make sense for the Commonwealth to say I think<br />
probably in that area the States and or Local Government can<br />
do that better. Certainly parts of program delivery. There<br />
are other areas of human affairs in Australia where it would<br />
probably make sense for the Commonwealth to do it. So it<br />
won't be a one way traffic. I think there will be some<br />
session of obligations from the Commonwealth to the States<br />
in some areas. There could be a session from the States to<br />
the Commonwealth. There should only be one criterion. Not<br />
what I want or what a State premier wants, but we should all<br />
be saying what is it that's best for the Australian citizen.<br />
NEGUS: Is that the way you'd like to go out, on that sort<br />
of note? Bob Hawke, the man who put his stamp on a new form<br />
of government in this country because<br />
PM: I don't look for monuments. I hope that I'll be<br />
remembered for a number of good things. That's for history<br />
to decide. But I have a long established concern about how<br />
we govern ourselves. I've addressed it not only in the<br />
Boyer Lectures. I've addressed it at a number of academic<br />
dissertations and speeches. Because the real thing is this.<br />
We have got, I think, the greatest country in the world.<br />
One of our greatnesses, as I say to your viewers, is the<br />
fact that we'lre made up of people from so many different<br />
countries 140 different nations. We've got natural<br />
resources. We've got the paradox of a heterogeneous<br />
population coming from 140 different nations but homogeneous<br />
in our commitment to the democratic parliamentary processes. </p>
<p>Now the great challenge to us is that we should use our<br />
resources in the most efficient way. We shouldn't denigrate<br />
ourselves and dissipate our capacities by a duplication and<br />
a lack of integration between those governing processes. If<br />
I can do something to make that better, well I'll be very<br />
pleased. TOTARO: This is of course what multiculture would mean to<br />
you. PM: Multiculturalism means many things to me, but it means<br />
these things. It means releasing or having the capacity to<br />
release all the talents of the individual, irrespective of<br />
their race, colour or creed, background, origin. It means<br />
social justice and it means economic efficiency. So what<br />
I'm talking about here in this Special Premiers' Conference<br />
is relevant to multiculturalism, yes.<br />
TOTARO: So you'll go beyond the simple question of You<br />
see multiculturalism as real cultural pluralism and of<br />
cultures. Is that<br />
PM: What to me politics is about is very very simple. You<br />
don't need, as I said once recently, you don't need great<br />
volumes by political scientists. Politics is about the<br />
creation of human happiness. Maximising the opportunity for<br />
happiness. Maximising the opportunities for individuals to<br />
release and use all the talents within each individual. And<br />
multiculturalism is an aspect of that. We have great<br />
opportunities for strengthening and enriching Australia<br />
because we have people coming from 140 different places, so<br />
we have to be intelligent as a community and say what are<br />
the ways in which we maximise the opportunities for every<br />
individual irrespective of their background to achieve<br />
happiness. That's what multiculturalism is about.<br />
TOTARO: Is there still bipartisanship in multiculturalism?<br />
PM: Well le~ t me say this. There have been times when our<br />
political opponents I think have been, when you get into an<br />
election situation, a little bit opportunistic about this<br />
and have attacked multiculturalism and have been a bit dicey<br />
on the question of immigration. I pay tribute to the basic<br />
thrust of ou~ r political opponents basically, although they<br />
succumb a bit to temptation when they think it might help<br />
them. Basically I think they do have a commitment to our<br />
multicultural Australia.<br />
BUCKLEY: OnL your own population and immigration policy, do<br />
you expect by the end of this term of Parliament to have a<br />
population target, keeping in mind environmental concerns as<br />
well as the Liberals' worries about immigration<br />
PM: There's; no in November of this year we're going to be<br />
having this Outlook conference and that will come out of the<br />
work of the Bureau of Immigration Research which I have<br />
established recently. Now I hope that, if I may talk to<br />
your viewers; is that you will see this conference that we're<br />
setting up is not just something which is going to be for </p>
<p>politicians and officials but I hope that people generally<br />
will take an interest in this. If they've got thoughts,<br />
let's have them, get their views to us. Now that will help<br />
us as a Government have a better idea about levels. But I<br />
don't think it makes sense to say that you're just going to<br />
have a level come what may. To have a cohesive society<br />
you've got to have a community which accepts, broadly<br />
speaking, the level of immigration that you're pursuing.<br />
And it won't necessarily be the case that you can say now<br />
what is the level which will satisfy that criteria perhaps<br />
in two years time. Having said all that, by inclination I<br />
tend to be a higher immigration level rather than a lower<br />
one. We're a country of only 17 million people in a world<br />
of five and a half billion and I think that it's in the<br />
interests of this generation and future generations of<br />
Australians that we build that population up as much as we<br />
can. TOTARO: You seem interested your own grandchildren.<br />
PM: Yes. ' Yes I do.<br />
NEGUS: Mr Hawke, I don't think anybody would argue at the<br />
sort of aspirations that you're expressing for the country.<br />
It would be a pretty nasty cynic who'd do that. But at the<br />
moment we're! looking at those things in the context of a<br />
pretty awful. economic climate. I mean you're talking now<br />
about us being possibly in technical recession. What does<br />
that mean? Does that mean that people are technically<br />
having a hard time, technically out of work?<br />
PM: No, no, no. Don't be the cynic yourself.<br />
NEGUS: I'm not.<br />
PM: Well<br />
NEGUS: ( inaudible)<br />
PM: It means, very simply, that economists define a<br />
recession as two successive quarters of negative economic<br />
growth. And as yet we're not in that point. That's all<br />
I've been saying. I haven't done anything That's<br />
what the economists' definition of a recession is. We're<br />
not yet at that point. But I've said quite clearly, as<br />
you've heard me say to the Parliament Amanda, I don't deny<br />
that there Eire economic problems out there for a lot of<br />
people. The simple point is this, and I'm not going to push<br />
statistics at your viewers, but there's one overridingly<br />
simple statistic. Last year we had an eight per cent growth<br />
in expenditure and a four per cent growth in our production.<br />
We financed that four per cent gap by just calling on the<br />
savings of overseas people. You can't go on doing that. if<br />
we hadn't brought down the level of activity and the level<br />
of imports, if we hadn't done that ourselves, with the pain<br />
that's been involved, the world would have imposed a much<br />
harsher, more draconian remedy upon us. </p>
<p>BUCKLEY: I think Mr Hawke that you get your message across<br />
pretty well. I think, as you've said yourself many times<br />
you've educated the community on economic matters and they<br />
do understand<br />
PM: It's a two-way process.<br />
BUCKLEY: A two-way process. But I think there are mixed<br />
messages coming from the Government about the future. I<br />
know you're always more optimistic in many of the things you<br />
say and yet Paul Keating often talks about the Argentinian<br />
road, as many economists do. What exact message are you<br />
trying to tell us about what will occur<br />
PM: Let me say two things. To be fair to Paul, Paul is not<br />
and hasn't been preaching the message of doom. He has the<br />
optimism that I have. But he has seen it as his<br />
responsibility as Treasurer to warn about the dangers that<br />
if we are not prepared to exercise the discipline that we<br />
have, then we could be as a country in a much worse<br />
situation, in his Argentinian reference. Now that's what<br />
the responsibility of government is about. Let me say to<br />
your viewers, the beaut thing as a politician would be to<br />
just do nice: things, say oh yes, well yes we'll have<br />
interest rates not at 18% or more that they got up to, we'll<br />
have them at: 10 or five. That will make you all feel nice<br />
about it. But what would've happened if we'd done that is<br />
the place wo'uld have exploded. We just would've gone like<br />
that, sucking in imports and the world would've suddenly<br />
said bang, that's the end to you. They would've wiped us<br />
out. Now what the message therefore is, in answer to your<br />
question Amanda, the message is simple. We've got enormous<br />
natural capacities and opportunities. Not only because of<br />
our people and our resources but of our geographical<br />
proximity tco the fastest growing region in the world. But<br />
it's a hard, tough, competitive world and we've got to<br />
conduct ourselves in a way which enables us to compete in<br />
that world. So we can't consume essentially, whether it's<br />
in terms of private consumer goods or investment goods, we<br />
can't consume more than we produce.<br />
NEGUS: The horrible fact of life though for you politically<br />
is that whether people believe what you're saying about the<br />
economy or riot the polls are looking pretty dreadful<br />
wiped you off the map if you went to the polls this week.<br />
PM: You go back and look up your files, and Amanda knows<br />
this. You l. ook at your files<br />
BUCKLEY: Fourteen points though. Fourteen points.<br />
PM: Well you go back to your polis and look what they were<br />
saying to us; before the 1987 you look at the beginning of<br />
1987.<br />
NEGUS: They've never been this low before.<br />
PM: Ok, we haven't had a Victorian situation before. Have<br />
we? Now, if I'd listened to all the panic merchants back </p>
<p>there in ' 87 and before the ' 90 election I would have gone<br />
and shot myself or something like that. But I didn't. You<br />
know, I said well<br />
NEGUS: ( inaudible)<br />
PM: No, I'll leave that to you George. But I've said all<br />
along that I have confidence in the intelligence of the<br />
Australian e: lectorate. You've heard me say it. When<br />
everyone was down most of my colleagues said we had no<br />
chance of winning last time. A lot of them thought it in<br />
' 87. But I have a faith in the Australian people. If I go<br />
to them and say look, we're not perfect, of course we've<br />
made mistakes. You can't be in government for seven and a<br />
half years and not make mistakes. But we haven't been<br />
mistaken in 1L) our trust in the Australian people; 2) the<br />
capacity of -them to respond. And remember this when you<br />
talk about the gloom, just remember this statistic. We have<br />
created, in our period of government, 1.6 million new jobs,<br />
of them : in the private sector. And remember this, that<br />
rate of job creation is five times faster than in the seven<br />
years of the conservative government and it's twice as fast<br />
as the rest of the world. So we have done things in terms<br />
of the most important requirement of the Australian<br />
population. That is job creation. We've done more than has<br />
been done before. We're doing much better than the rest of<br />
the world. We'll continue to do it.<br />
NEGUS: So why are the polls so bad for you then if that's<br />
the case?<br />
PM: The polls are bad for these reasons. People don't like<br />
being hurt, as we've had to hurt them over recent times with<br />
high interest rates. They don't like it. They don't say oh<br />
beauty Bob, beauty or you up. And secondly, we've had<br />
the disaster of Victoria. Victoria is a very very big hunk<br />
of Australia.<br />
BUCKLEY: We're becoming two nations here in Australia<br />
aren't we?<br />
PM: No, no, we're not becoming two nations. But it is the<br />
case that a federal government will be hurt if you're seen<br />
as one of your big state components as having gone bad.<br />
Similarly, because we're not travelling terribly well at the<br />
moment some of our state colleagues will be hurt. That's<br />
the nature of things. But how many times have you heard me<br />
say Amanda, you've got to get your time scales right. When<br />
I see the journalists saying gone, gone,<br />
NEGUS: You can definitely turn it round?<br />
BUCKLEY: You've been pretty tough on John Hewson<br />
TOTARO: Just want to change that for a moment.<br />
PM: Yes sure. </p>
<p>TOTARO: Immigration. Is the Government a little bit out of<br />
step with public feelings about immigration numbers?<br />
PM: Well, I don't know. I mean there is some part of<br />
public feeling which says it should be higher, there's some<br />
which says we shouldn't have any. But you know in the end<br />
what leadership is about? It's about leading. You don't<br />
get elected to0 go like that and say what's the opinion,<br />
like that. Leadership is about leading.<br />
TOTARO: When you have the growing level of unemployment,<br />
people say why should we bring migrants in.<br />
PM: Then we wouldn't have 17 million people that we've got<br />
now if governments had just responded to that view.<br />
Whenever there was any sort of recession<br />
NEGUS: ( inaudible)<br />
PM: and this country now would've denied itself millions<br />
of great citizens.<br />
TOTARO: What's in your view<br />
PM: You've ( jot to get your time scales right. If you say,<br />
look things are a bit tough now so we'll cut off the<br />
immigration t: ap, then that's not something you'd just do<br />
then. That's a loss forever.<br />
TOTARO: When your grandchildren are grown up, what do you<br />
think should be the level of population they should have?<br />
PM: It's impossible to say.<br />
TOTARO: Should be 25 million, 30 million?<br />
PM: It's impossible to say now. But I answered the<br />
question before by saying I am a higher immigration man<br />
rather than a lower immigration man. But, I repeat, the<br />
real criterion has got to be, well there are two<br />
essentially, and they are related. It's got to be<br />
economically responsible. I mean you've got to say now I<br />
believe that with that level of immigration we're going to<br />
be able to essentially integrate them into our economic<br />
growth and our employment growth and secondly, while I say<br />
you don't go like that and say well what are people wanting,<br />
in a broad sense however you've got to be able to persuade<br />
the Australian population that the sort of immigration<br />
program you're having is one which they understand and<br />
accept. Not to which there will not be some objection. But<br />
basically the Australian people have got to be going along<br />
with what you're doing. I think essentially on immigration<br />
and multiculturalism they are.<br />
NEGUS: Mr Hawke, you've said to Amanda and others that,<br />
you've made it very plain lately, that you intend hanging<br />
around for a while longer, at least until the next election.<br />
Why? </p>
<p>PM: Because I'm a good Prime Minister.<br />
NEGUS: Or because you think the alternatives couldn't win?<br />
PM: Well I don't know whether they could or they couldn't.<br />
All I know is that I've been Prime Minister for seven and a<br />
half years and I'm a much better Prime Minister now than I<br />
was. I've never felt fitter physically and mentally. I<br />
still believe I've got a significant contribution to make to<br />
this country as Prime Minister.<br />
NEGUS: But do you think that you could win more easily than<br />
Paul Keating or Kim Beazley?<br />
PM: Well at the moment the polls would when they you look<br />
at alternatives, who do they prefer? Well that is the case.<br />
But that's maybe good for your ego in one sense but it's<br />
also in a sense unfair to others. I'm there, I've had the<br />
opportunities. So people can maybe tend to identify with<br />
you a bit. But even when they don't agree with you on<br />
everything, they say well you know, we know Hawkey and they<br />
tend to say yes we prefer him. But I don't think that's the<br />
point. I mean I'm a very healthy 60 George, and 60 is not<br />
very old.<br />
NEGUS: But it might be the point for the Party. Without<br />
you, no longer Government.<br />
PM: You knoiw, the Party will make up its mind. All I can<br />
say, as far as the Party is concerned, they are 100% behind<br />
me. TOTARO: I must interrupt because this after all is the<br />
tenth birthday of SBS. Our viewers often cannot see SBS<br />
simply because it doesn't reach them, or because it is<br />
What's the Government going to do?<br />
PM: Well you know what we've done. We've<br />
TOTARO: But what are you going to do?<br />
PM: Well we'Ive made provision for the extension of<br />
services. We've made money available for the extension of<br />
the services and as it's possible through time to extend it,<br />
we will.<br />
TOTARO: Do you think that Channel 10 could be handed over<br />
to PM: Now don't jump too many hurdles in advance. I think<br />
your viewers know that Bob Hawke's very firmly established<br />
his commitment to SBS. We'll do what we can to see<br />
TOTARO: Do you believe that the new 1991 Aussat satellite<br />
could be used by SBS to increase its coverage?<br />
PM: It's conceivable, but let me say this. In conjunction<br />
with my excellent Minister for Communications, Kim Beazley, </p>
<p>we will see that we do all we can to create the environment<br />
within which SBS can prosper.<br />
TOTARO: You can't give us any more assurance?<br />
PM: I don't regard programs like this, as enjoyable and as<br />
important as they are, as the places in which you make<br />
policy announcements.<br />
BUCKLEY: We'll give you an opportunity to speak on another<br />
matter in that case. You had a pretty spectacular flare-up<br />
with Archbishop Hollingworth last week. What are your<br />
relations with him and why do you let him get under your<br />
skin? Why do you let these people get under your skin?<br />
PM: He doesn't get under my skin. I don't care whether<br />
it's Amanda Buckley, Archbishop Hollingworth, George Negus.<br />
If people say something which I think is not right, then I<br />
will say so. It's no reflection upon Peter Hollingworth as<br />
an individual, none.<br />
NEGUS: ( inaudible)<br />
PM: I respect him in may ways. He's been a man who's<br />
dedicated his life to the things in which he believes. In<br />
the Brotherhood of St Laurence he's done some very important<br />
things. But where I think Peter, or George or anyone says<br />
something publicly which I think isn't right, then I'll say<br />
so. But that doesn't affect my judgement about them. May I<br />
say in regard to Peter Hollingworth that fortunately he<br />
tends to have reciprocated to myself.<br />
NEGUS: Sure, but you said he was talking nonsense and all<br />
he was really saying was that people were hurting which is a<br />
fact. PM: Well why don't you get your facts straight? It's not<br />
what he said, that I objected to What he said that I<br />
objected to., and as a professional journalist there is an<br />
obligation upon you to get your facts right, and you've got<br />
them wrong. What he said, and what I objected to was that I<br />
and the Government had used the single instrument of<br />
monetary policy. He was wrong and I objected to that.<br />
Because we'd had the tightest fiscal policy in history and<br />
the tightest wages policy. That's what I referred to as the<br />
unholy trinity of fiscal policy, wages policy and monetary<br />
policy. The Archbishop was wrong in saying we'd only used<br />
the one and I objected to that.<br />
TOTARO: We have only a very short time.<br />
PM: Ok, don't let these people overrule you. You assert<br />
your authority mate.<br />
TOTARO: Yes, yes, absolutely.<br />
PM: Good on you mate. </p>
<p>4-.9 11<br />
TOTARO: I copy you. On the 10th birthday of SBS, what's<br />
the Australia you'd like to bequeath to your children? In<br />
which way is Australia different from what your father left<br />
you? PM: I want it to be a more tolerant society. I can<br />
remember the first year I went to university was 1947. An<br />
exciting period to be a young university student. What<br />
caused me to join the Labor Party then was the great<br />
immigration -program that they'd introduced which was<br />
bringing hundreds of thousands of people to this country.<br />
TOTARO: After the White Australia Policy?<br />
PM: Yes. Yours truly was the one who with others worked to<br />
see that that was abolished. I saw then and I was hurt by<br />
the prejudice that my fellow Australians Then it was<br />
the dagos and the wops which was the language. Yes, that's<br />
the language that was used by my fellow Australians against<br />
you people who've come to help us be such a much better<br />
country than we were. I dedicated myself from that time to<br />
try and make Australia a more tolerant society. Because if<br />
there is one obscenity that I can't stand it is the<br />
obscenity which says that one human being, one child is less<br />
worthy than another because it has a different coloured<br />
skin, or different shaped eyes or a different accent. So<br />
what I want to see in this country as compared to those<br />
earlier days is a more tolerant society, one which<br />
understands the great truth of this planet, that all people,<br />
all people, irrespective of the colour of their skin, shape<br />
of their eyes, their religion, all people are intrinsically<br />
equal in terms not of their endowments -some people will be<br />
born with more intelligence than others -but they are all<br />
equal in terms of their right to have their talents<br />
developed and their opportunities for a free and independent<br />
life. And if Australia accepts that more readily at the end<br />
of my time than it did before, then I'll be happy.<br />
TOTARO: And you think that SBS has helped to create this<br />
new climate?<br />
PM: There's no doubt that SBS has helped. That's why I'm a<br />
great supporter of SBS.<br />
TOTARO: Thank you very much Mr Hawke. I'm afraid we have<br />
to leave it here. Thank you very much for coming, and best<br />
wishes. PM: Thank you very much.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
