<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1300</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S TOUR OF SOUTH-EAST ASIA - PRESS CONFERENCE GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. HAROLD HOLT, AT SAIGON. - 26TH APRIL, 1966</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/04/1966</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001300_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER'S TOUR OF S( UTH-EAST ASIA 4 r C)<br />
PRESS CONFERENCE GIVEN BY THE PRIIE MINISTER,<br />
iR. HAROLD HOLT, AT SAIGON. 26th April, 1966.<br />
Thank you Mr. Linh for your introduction and good<br />
morning to you ladies and gentlemen.<br />
As Mr. Linh has explained to you, I have a prepared<br />
statement. I thought having regard to the need for translation,<br />
in respect of some of the members of the press, it might be<br />
desirable t0 have a statement preparea which coulu be translated<br />
before-hand and so it gives an outline of what I wish to say.<br />
But you can supplement this to a certain extent by<br />
questions you may wish to ask.<br />
You will appreciate, of course, that I am an official<br />
guest and the head of the Government in my own country and that<br />
does place some limitations upon the range of comments that one<br />
woula otherwise, perhaps, be able to make in a visit of this sort,<br />
but I think we shall be able to cover the ground adequately enough<br />
together. This morning sees the conclusion of my official visit<br />
to Viet Nam. Later today I visit Ubon in Northern Thailand where<br />
an Australian Air Force Squadron is stationed.<br />
From there I go to Bangkok, and subsequently to<br />
various centres where Australian F'orces are serving in Malaysia<br />
and Singapore. I have felt it important to go to all these centres<br />
because there is an impression in some countries and even among<br />
some people in our own country, that because Viet Nam is so very<br />
much in the news that we are not doing very much anywhere else.<br />
Jell, in point of fact, we have a military obligation<br />
and have undertaken military assistance in other centres and I<br />
shall be visiting these before I return to Australia.<br />
I am deeply appreciative of the welcome which has<br />
been given to me in Viet Nam anu of the many evidences of<br />
friend-ship ana warm feeling for Australia which I have<br />
experienced. I have haa inforim. tive ana useful exchanges of views<br />
with the Chairman of the National Leadership Committee, with the<br />
Prime inister and with other Vietnamese le. aauers, as well as with<br />
Australian, United States ana other officials.<br />
These contacts, together with the observations I have<br />
been able to make in visits to military anac other estabñ ishments,<br />
have given me a closer insight into the situation in Viet Nam and<br />
into current problems.<br />
MiIy conclusions and assessments have strongly confirmed<br />
the earlier judgments on which we have based our policies. </p>
<p>It was not necessary for me to come to Viet Nam to come<br />
to a firm conclusion as to the course of action Australia should<br />
pursue. we have aecidcd that course some considerable time ago<br />
but it has certainly strengtheneu an, confirmea the assessments<br />
which we haa earlier maqe in deciding those policies.<br />
As Prime Minister of Australia I was able in person to<br />
convey to the Vietnamese Government the admiration and support of<br />
the Government and people of Australia for the South Vietnamese<br />
people in their struggle to preserve their national independence.<br />
Our support for the Republic of Viet Nam has included<br />
moral support, International Political and Diplomatic support, as<br />
well as Military and Economic assistance.<br />
Jo have a great interest in the effort of Viet Nam to<br />
achieve internal stability.<br />
At the same time, we comprehend that this is no easy<br />
task, and the Government and people of Viet Nam may be assured of<br />
our understanding and awareness of the difficulties they face.<br />
This country has for years been under Communist attack<br />
systematically designed to destroy the growth of its institutions<br />
and its structure of administration.<br />
The Republic of Viet Nam also has faced great problems<br />
after the end of dolonialism in bringing about national stability<br />
and cohesion. But the will to resist Communist aggression and to<br />
prevent Communist domination is common to all the different<br />
elements other than the Viet Cong anu its so-called liberation<br />
front. This has been a constant factor throughout a period<br />
of political change.<br />
I have discussed the m. ilitary situation with the most<br />
senior military and diplomatic figures in the Government, the<br />
United States representation and that of Australia.<br />
All have confidently expressed the view that the<br />
iilitary threat can be successfully dealt with.<br />
There are political difficulties which all recognise.<br />
The task of the United States ana Australia and of<br />
other allied countries is to help resist the aggression and ensure<br />
the security of the country while it establishes the basis for an<br />
enduring stability. The aspirations of the Vietnamese people are the same<br />
as those of many other newly independent countries of South and<br />
South-East Asia, namely the right to the full and free exercise<br />
of sovereignty and national inaependence.<br />
Each has the right to the forms of Government and<br />
society of its chcice and to develop its own approach to the<br />
problems of aconomic and social development. </p>
<p>In resolutely waging its own struggle for freedom,<br />
South Viet Nam is making a major contribution to the security of<br />
the whole region. The problems of security and development are, of<br />
course, interdependent. Efforts to provide and preserve security by dilitary<br />
means need to be complemented by measures designed to raise<br />
standards of living.<br />
It was with particular interest, therefore, that I<br />
have learnea about the Vietnamese Government's revolutionary<br />
development programme. I knew, of course, of it in general before I came<br />
here but this visit has enabled me to learn about it in much more<br />
detail. The programme is designed to counter the Communist<br />
threat to the villagers by providing protection and in various<br />
useful ways building a better life for the people in rural areas.<br />
Yesterday morning I visited the Revolutionary<br />
Development Cadre Training Centre at Vung Tau where teams are<br />
being given comprehensive training for these tasks.<br />
I was most impressed by the dedication of the<br />
instructing staff and the thoroughness and realism of their<br />
training programme. Of special interest for me, of course, have been the<br />
visits to Australian military and civilian personnel serving in<br />
Viet Nam and the discussions I've had with them have been full of<br />
interest and valuable information.<br />
Our present force is small but it is a highly trained<br />
and effective force, which includes a body of instructors working<br />
directly with the Vietnamese Armed Forces imparting their<br />
knowledge ana skills to improve the performance of thousands of<br />
others. ie are now in the course of trebling the size of the<br />
present Australian effort to 0., 500 men.<br />
This will be a self-containca task force with two<br />
battalions, a special reconnaissance squadron, its own air<br />
transport support, artillery and so on.<br />
In addition, the auvisory training programie will<br />
continue. I have been greatly encouraged by what I hive seen of<br />
the work and the morale of the Australian Forces.<br />
Wherever I have gone I hnve been given glowing accounts<br />
of their standard of performance.<br />
They clearly have a well developed sense of purpose<br />
and a proper pride in their achievement.<br />
They well understand the need for what they are<br />
doing. </p>
<p>In their military operations they have added to the<br />
security of the local villages and they themselves have had the<br />
satisfaction of seeing the villagers react favourably to the<br />
greater protection they have brought.<br />
They have participated gladly in work of civic action<br />
through giving medical and dental services, help with sanitation,<br />
school construction, and the teaching of English.<br />
The careful searches conducted by the battalion have<br />
led to the recovery of supplies of rice sufficient to feed many<br />
thousands of Viet Cong over a considerable period.<br />
In addition, they have helped save rice harvests for<br />
the villages and have denied then to the Viet Cong.<br />
They also fully realise the nature of the struggle and<br />
that the contributions they can make to security, welfare and<br />
social progress must suppleilent operations of a purely military<br />
kind. I visited several hospitals and, of course, took<br />
particular interest in the admirable work of our own Australian<br />
surgical team at the Bien Hoa Provincial Hospital.<br />
I believe much more needs to be done through<br />
international effort in the medical field.<br />
I have been deeply impressed by the high morale and<br />
devotion to auty shown by all these Australians in the difficult<br />
and often arduous conditions in which they are fighting and<br />
working. I would sum up comment on my visit by saying that it<br />
has been of absorbing interest, it will be of endu ing benefit in<br />
my discussions with my Cabinet colleagues ana for assessment of<br />
any future developments, and I shall take away with me an abiding<br />
impression of the resolution, the detennination and devotion to<br />
the cause of freedon of the people of South Viet Nan themselves.<br />
No cox. ment on the current situation coulu ignore the<br />
tremendous part being played by the United States of America, its<br />
forces and its material contribution.<br />
This, I believe, is an historic struggle which is<br />
proceeding in South Viet Nan today.<br />
It could very well mark a turning point in history and<br />
if we can succeed not rimrely in gaining the military success but<br />
in establishing a better world order, or its foundation, or its<br />
example, in tnis area of the world, then I believe that those<br />
friendly forces and in particular the United States of America<br />
whose contribution is so vast, will have made a notable contribution<br />
to mankind's unending search for freedom and a better world order. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
