<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5112</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS TO THE WESTERN AUSTRALIAN STATE CONFERENCE OF THE LIBERAL PARTY</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/07/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005112.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
4/ 16'&amp; 1V<br />
FOR MEDIA SUNDAY 22 JULY 1979<br />
ADDRESS TO THE WESTERN AUSTRALIAN<br />
STATE CONFERENCE OF THE LIBERAL PARTY<br />
This St~ ate Council, which from all reports is midway through<br />
being a most successful one, follows what I believe was a<br />
highly successful Federal Council meeting in Perth. That is<br />
a tribute to the strength of Western Australian Liberalism.<br />
It is a tribute to your State Cabinet, to your organisation.<br />
It is a tribute to Sir Charles and the leadership that he<br />
has given not only this State but Liberalism throughout<br />
the Commronwealtk-h.<br />
I know quite well the enormous contribution that Western<br />
Austra. bia has made to the Federal Governmrent over a long period.<br />
I've only got one disappointment with that. You have a rather<br />
miserable record of holding only nine of the ten seats in the<br />
House of Representatives. I think it is quite unforgivable<br />
to allow the Labor Party to have even that one. So that<br />
ought to be the objective of the next election.<br />
But making this State's economy go ahead has been a major part<br />
of the work of the State Government. W,-here we can, the<br />
Commnonwealth has sought to co-operate in that. With the<br />
Noxfth West Shelf for example, we have a number of special<br />
arrangements agreed between the State and the Commonwealth<br />
to enable that to move ahead. The last reports I have had in<br />
relation to the feasibility study are encouraging. I would<br />
hope very much that major projects are sucessfully launched.<br />
Those few thousand million dollars of major development work<br />
either going ahead, or in the final feasibility stages of this<br />
State that can only happen with Liberal policies, as I believe,<br />
co-operation between the State and the Commonwealth.<br />
I would thank your State President, Noel Crichton-Browne, for<br />
four years as President. The Constitution doesn't allow him<br />
to be President again.<br />
But Noel has done an enormous amount of work for the Liberal<br />
Party, in this State I know, and also in the Federal sphere<br />
through general elections; on the Federal Committees, on the<br />
Federal Executive. He has spent a very great amount of time and<br />
effort. That is what is needed. It's not'just sitting here<br />
being the State Presiden't. It ne~ eds energy, initiative, the<br />
capacity to get out and maake sure that our organisation is<br />
as strong an organisation that it can possibly be. I believe<br />
Noel * Crichton-. Browne has served Western. Australia, and the<br />
Federal Liberal Party, well. </p>
<p>-2<br />
There is one thing which Liberal Party Councils, whether they<br />
are State or Federal, just can't match. We can't match the<br />
Labor Party, the socialists -solidarity spectacular that it<br />
always seems to have when they get together.<br />
I want to say one or two things ab'out the Labor Party<br />
Conference we need tc look at the policies and make<br />
sure that everyone understands the policies that have been<br />
adopted over this last weekend, in the Labor Party, and which<br />
commit them, and commit them all.<br />
Mr. Hayden said he wanted to leave the Whitlam years behind him.<br />
But he was proud to be part of them. He w-. as in fact Mr. Whitlam's<br />
economic architect for a large part of those years. He still<br />
carries responsibility. He obviously doesn't want to leave<br />
those years as far behind as he says because the policies they<br />
have endorsed and adopted are substantially the same as the<br />
policies that were applied during those times.<br />
If w. e can remember 1972 Whitlam and Labor before the election<br />
were hailed as moderate and reasonable by the media. But as<br />
soon the polls were declared at the end of 1972 moderation was<br />
left behind and we had the three most terrible years that<br />
Australia has ever seen. The destructiveness of Labor showed.<br />
Over the last weekend we have had<br />
Mr. Hayden offering Mr. Whitlam's failings, but maybe without<br />
Mr. VWhitlam's flamboyancy and sense of theatre.<br />
But the objective to destroy the States is totally unchanged.<br />
Sure, they said ' w'e will keep the Senate', but let's make sure<br />
it is a Senate with no powers; no power to do the things that<br />
sometimes that Senate has to do to protect the smaller States<br />
and sometimes had to do to protect the whole of Australia.<br />
So that is Whitlam all over again.<br />
Then what about a simple majority to alter the Constitution.<br />
No question of having a majority in a majority of States. That<br />
is the wise men of the East, I suppose, telling. Western Australia<br />
what to do. It is not something that you would willingly accept<br />
and not something that you ought to accept. But that is Whitlam<br />
all over again.<br />
Again, they said they would assert total Commonwealth power over<br />
mining offshore. Painstakingly, Sir Charles and myself, his<br />
Government and mine, have come to an agreement about offshore<br />
matters. Special arrangements also to meet the particular<br />
needs of this State in relation to the joint authority. All that<br />
is going to be torn up, thrown away, because Federal Labor would<br />
want to do it all from Canberra*. They specifically said, " we<br />
will move the Federal departments out into the States so that<br />
we can better control what the States would do". Now, surely, that<br />
is Whitlam all over again.<br />
For the economy; interventionist in the extreme. Direct<br />
planning of allocation of resources by Government, not by private<br />
enterprise. Nationalisation where it is necessary. Joint<br />
public and private ownership to be promoted. Extension of public<br />
enterprise to national investment fund which our tax dollars would<br />
go to to mfake the losses for socialist bureaucratic failures.<br />
An Australian Hydrocarbon Corporation to do what private enterprise<br />
again ought to do. That a~ ain is Wh-itlam all over again. </p>
<p>-3<br />
High taxes they certainly promise. You know Mr. Whitlam<br />
promised to pay this was one promise he certainly kept<br />
to promise to pay for a large measure of his proposals through<br />
higher inflation and therefore higher taxation as a result of<br />
inflation. Well he kepL that and we had the greatest inflation<br />
in Australia's history.<br />
He also proposed a capital gains tax and then found it too<br />
difficult to implement. But Mr. Hayden is going to do that<br />
all over again. On top it, he would have a wealth tax, so<br />
I suppose it is Whitlam over again but slightly worse.<br />
In addition, a resources rents tax designed presumably to stop<br />
the great development projects in the State, in Queensland, in<br />
other parts of Australia, as they effectively stopped them in<br />
three years of Government. But then again, they will intervene<br />
to take action to prevent the continuance of trans-national<br />
corporations that are against the public interest. What a<br />
wonderful way to say we want overseas investment in this country;<br />
to'have a sword hanging over the head of every trans-national<br />
or multinational company say we are going to prevent the<br />
activities of the ones we don't like. But which ones don't they<br />
like? Are they going to get up and say what projects they<br />
want to stop. Are they going to get up and say whether they<br />
are goin9 to expropriate the ones they don't like? Instead they<br />
just create a policy which is going to cause doubt and dismay<br />
if there ever was a Labor administration which there isn't<br />
going to be amongst all those whom we want to have invest<br />
in this country with confidence and vigour.<br />
They said staff ceilings would come off. We have nearly 60,000<br />
less public servants than we would have had under their policies<br />
and programmes. That is not a bad effort.<br />
They also want to politicize the public service. We passed a<br />
law to stop future Prime Minister of any power moving his own<br />
private and chosen people in a political sense, into the<br />
public service, because we believe in the apolitical nature of<br />
that service. Three private secretaries of Mr. Whitlam became<br />
permanent heads. We thought that ought to stop. We passed a law<br />
to stop it. Labor said they will remove that law if they ever<br />
get the chance.<br />
But what did they do about the mainstream of economic problems.<br />
They sold out to the Left. They ignored inflation as though it<br />
doesnt-L-exist. No recognition of a wages problem, that it adds to<br />
inflation. No real recognition that too much Government expenditure<br />
adds to inflation. Even Mr. Wran called the policy a hotch-potch<br />
and Mr. Hawke sdid it was a gutless sell-out to the Left. If<br />
Mr. Hawke, whose much of his ACTU and semi-Dolitical life is<br />
dependent upon the votes from the left, is accusing Mr. Hayden of<br />
a gutless sell-cut to the Left I can't see any reason why on that<br />
occasion we shouldn't believe Mr. Hawke. / 4 </p>
<p>-4<br />
We've got to give it to Mr. Hayden. He does some things just<br />
like Mr. Whitlam; he fights with Mr. Hawke.<br />
But in industrial relations, where Australia is today facing<br />
a challenge in the Str~ tes and in the Commonwealth, which this<br />
State and the Commonwealth is seeking to match and to meet<br />
with all the vigour and power at our command, they say " we will<br />
place the unions above the law. We will place any activity<br />
undertaken in the name of unionism beyond the reach of any law"<br />
Labor and their words will ensure the right to strike immune<br />
from any pains or penalities; recognise the right of trade<br />
unions to regulate their own affairs free from Government or<br />
judicial interference, even though some of them have an annual<br />
income of nearly $ 10 million a year and exert more power in<br />
this community than any corporation, Australian or multinational.<br />
They will free trade unions from the Trade Practices Act which<br />
has been useful on many occasions; repeal all penalties for<br />
strikes against arbitral decisions a decision of Labor<br />
aimed at the heart of arbitration, aimed at the heart of the<br />
industrial processes of this country. They will repeal the<br />
disciplinary legislation that we have introduced. Repeal the<br />
legislation that ended the TLelecom dispute. Labor has sided<br />
with industrial anarchy against the people of Australia. They<br />
will plainly repeal any lawa which gives any Government power<br />
which is so patently and clearly needed under current circumstances.<br />
They would repeal the lot and leave Government and the people<br />
of Australia naked and defenceless.<br />
Not only that, they are going to have a special body to spy<br />
on multinational companies. Then they are going to give the<br />
information they get from those multinational companies<br />
t'-o the domestic trade unions and to international trade unions.<br />
Just as though their other policies weren't going to do enough<br />
to stop investment and development in this country, they would<br />
have a special spy service against multinational companies to<br />
make damn sure that there wasn't going to be any more investment.<br />
The accumulation of Labor's policies would stop Australia dead in its<br />
tracks, just as effectively as it did in the past. It is our task<br />
mnake sure that all Australians understand that.<br />
Let me now g -t on with the real business of where Australia<br />
stands today and what we ourselves, in co-operation with the<br />
States, intend and seek to do about it.<br />
Australia is now more competitive than it has been for many many<br />
years.-Our industries are selling again better in Australian<br />
markets and also in overseas markets. That started from the<br />
devaluatk-ion of two to three years ago and the management of the<br />
exchange rate and the economy since then, which has rebuilt the<br />
competitive base of Australian manufacturing industry and<br />
helped Australian farming industries. As a result, our balance<br />
of payments is stronger than it has been. Where is all that<br />
speculation about a weak Australian dollar today? It doesn't<br />
exist because of the effectiveness of our policies. </p>
<p>Since February, private capital inflow has been over<br />
$ 1,000 million. That is a better result than for many many<br />
years. In the eight months to February, export prices rose at twice<br />
the pace of import prices, greatly assisting Australian exporters.<br />
in this last year non-farm gross domestic product I hope<br />
you can put up with one or two figures increased by three and<br />
a half percent in real terms. In the nine months to March<br />
company profitability r * ose over 20 percent. In the year to March<br />
investment expenditure rose 25 percent in mining uD 45 percent.<br />
What happened under Labor? Real investment for those industries<br />
on many estimates fell by an average of eight percent a year.<br />
There Ihas been great progress in this State with major projects<br />
cornritted or in the final feasibility stage, upwards of<br />
$ 2,000 million and in other States in Queensland, in great<br />
resource projects there are equivalent figures indicating<br />
the progress that is and can be made.<br />
our rural industries are looking to the 1980s with a deg ree<br />
of conf'idence for the first time in many years. We know what<br />
has happened to beef prices. This was needed because farmers wiere<br />
in a very difficult position. Last year's wheat crop was an<br />
all-time record. There are continuing high export prices and<br />
a larger area has again been planted this year throughout<br />
Australia. The prospects are good. In wool, production is<br />
rising, not greatly, but usefully. The average price for wool<br />
is very sound. The reserve price has been increased by 20 cents.<br />
Remember Labor, just when confidence was needed -they reduced<br />
the reserve price by 50 cents in one year. The forecastsfor<br />
1979-2,0 for the wool industry are again sound. Reserves at the<br />
moment are lower than they have been for many, many years. That<br />
industry will be able to build on the future with confidence.<br />
But rural recovery is no accident. The industry has been assisted<br />
by policies to control the internal economy and to get better<br />
access to markets. We had a situation where other governments<br />
had argued and spoken for thirty years about getting reductions<br />
in the American wool tariff. It is this Government that has<br />
achieved a 60 percent reduction in that American wool tariff.<br />
Our beef industry will have better and more secure access to<br />
Japan, to the United States and even some access to Europe as<br />
a result of the trade policies that we have pursued.<br />
Then the Primary Industry Bank which has already re-financed<br />
$ 100 million of debt, income equalisation deposits, the new<br />
Wheat Stabilisation Scheme, the support for the Wool Corporation<br />
and tax averaging are all specific policies designed to rebuild<br />
the strength of Australia's rural industries.<br />
Of course, the fundamentals of economic control getting inflation<br />
down, getting expendituro down great progress has been<br />
made in both of those areas. ./ 6 </p>
<p>-6<br />
There have been unexpected events Iran and what happened as a result<br />
of Iran and the upset of world oil supplies. We wanted beef prices<br />
to be increased but the increase was larger t!-L-an we expected and had<br />
greater inflationary consequence than we expected. The wheat<br />
harvest was an all-time record) as you know. It is good for<br />
wheat farmers and good for the balance of payments, but not good<br />
for inflation. For these reasons there were upward pressures<br />
on inflation which we had to respo-nd to, as we did in the<br />
mini-budget. But if we hadn't, people could have charged us<br />
and said " what has happened to your anti-inflationary policy,<br />
aren't you going to keep the country on track in relation to that".<br />
The change was necessary; necessary more so than desirable.<br />
Industrial disputes: I have indicated what Labor wouldn't do.<br />
Let me say what we are doing and will do. If strikes continue<br />
as they have over the last two to three months, they will assuredly<br />
destroy Australia and the possibilities and prospects of this<br />
nation in the 1980s.' The strikes are selfish; seeking confrontation,<br />
not with Government , but with the people of Australia. So many<br />
union leaders seem not to want consultation. Where the<br />
Commironw.. ealth has clear power it will act. It has clearest power<br />
in relation to our own employees. So we have proclaimed an Act<br />
that has been on the books for some time, really, in a sense2<br />
waiting for the opportunity nr the necessity, if that should be<br />
forced upon us. The proclamation was enough to end the<br />
Telecom dispute.<br />
The Postal Commission already has well * over 2,000 people stood<br />
down. If they are not back at work by M". onday with the bans<br />
lifted from the Redfern Sydney Mail Exchange, then further measures<br />
will be taken and we know precisely what we are going to do.<br />
The Postal Commx-ission has already indicated that no matter what, back<br />
to work or not, they are going to move to dismantle Redfcrn.<br />
It is a large operation that can't be done overnight, but they<br />
have set the task and that is irrevocable.<br />
The special Act we proclaimed is a reasonable one. It enables<br />
. us to suspend, stand down, or ultimately to dismiss employees<br />
who are seeking to disrupt activity in Australia. There is no<br />
way we are going to accept the circumstances where people go along<br />
and say amn going to do 70 pearcent of my work, and I don'It like!<br />
the other 30 percent or I am not going to do the other<br />
percent because I don't like a Government policy. Of course,<br />
you the employer, being the taxpayer, and the Government, are going<br />
to pay me my full wage as though I am doing my whole job".<br />
Doing part of your work, striking for the other part, and expecting<br />
to be paid in full that is the position we were faced with<br />
no private employer would put up with it for two minutes. This<br />
Commonwealth Government is not going to put up with it. Any<br />
public servantswho expect that they can behave in this way can<br />
now axpect to be stood down forthwith as the minijmun consequence<br />
of that kind of action. </p>
<p>7<br />
The Australian Council of Trade Union's actions and attitudes<br />
have been inflammatory in this situation. Tony Street called<br />
a meeting and said: " We are not asking you to take sides<br />
in any dispute, but we do ask you to support arbitration to<br />
support reason to get your affiliates to stop these bans and<br />
limitations which are damaging Australia". And what did<br />
Mr. Hawke do? He just thubed his nose at that very reasonable<br />
request and then said " Well, that is all your problem. We<br />
are not going to do that" and attacked the Government on its<br />
economic policies. So they didn't exert their influence<br />
when they could and should have. Now they call for rolling strikes<br />
by Australian Government employees against our legislation.<br />
That won't change us in our attitude in relation to that<br />
legisliation, which is now a part of the industrial relations<br />
inventory. Where it needs to be used to supplement other<br />
powers in relation to Commonwealth employeesL and employees of<br />
Commonwealth statutory bodies, it will be so used. If the<br />
unions want to give support to rollinq strikes, I suppose there<br />
are some other things that we could also do. We know that eiey<br />
would be.<br />
Last night I had what I believed was a very useful discussion<br />
with your Premier) Sir Charles Court, before coming down here this<br />
morning. There is obviously a very serious situation in the<br />
Pilbara which the State Government has been battling with for<br />
some time. But $ 80 million in export funds, I am tcd has<br />
already been lost since May. We can't allow that to continue. rhe<br />
, tate and Commonwealth jointly can't allow that to continue. The<br />
Ccr-onwealth is prepared to co-operate in any way we can with the<br />
State Government, with Sir Charles Court and his Government, to<br />
make sure that where joint powers are needed if they are<br />
needed those powers are available to<br />
get this State back to industrial sanity.<br />
For example, if the unions operating in the Pilbara happen<br />
to be de-registered under State law and they are under State<br />
awards at the moment there is a fear that they might obtain<br />
a benefit of a Commonwealth award. I don't believe for one<br />
moment that the Arbitration Commission would give the benefit<br />
of a Commonwealth award to unions that were de-registered as<br />
the result of the industrial action that has taken place. But<br />
if there is a need to change our law to strengthen that, to make<br />
sure that it could not happen, then so b6 it. The law will<br />
be changed to make sure that it doesn't happen.<br />
But one of the things we discussed last night was whether it Tmight not be<br />
best that the unions that now operate and have a coyerage of the<br />
Pilbara were in fact de-registered, Then we might use our powers<br />
jointly to see that one union was established for the Pilbara--for<br />
the iron ore industry which would then have an in. terest in<br />
the well-being octne Piinara, in the well-being of the iron<br />
ore industry~ instead of these other unions that are sometimes<br />
Australia-wide in their coverage caring nothing about the well-being<br />
of. any particular industry or of Australia caring only about<br />
the pressure points of power; being able to disrupt and destroy<br />
where the opportunity offers itself. / 8 </p>
<p>8<br />
If those unions, the AMSWU and others, were de-registered<br />
from the Pilbara and denied any possibility of ever getting back<br />
into that arena, it might cause a little fuss for a while, but<br />
if that is the fuss Western Australia wants the Commonwealth<br />
will stand with Western Australia. Let's have it out and let's get<br />
it over with.<br />
I would like to say something for a moment about Australia and<br />
where we stand in the world, because we have every reason to<br />
be proud of the achievements of this nation. If we get this<br />
industrial disruption oehind us sensibly then we can look forward<br />
with overwhelming confidence to the 1980s and the years ahead.<br />
In many overseas countries the increased inflationary pressures<br />
are worse than they are in this country--the United States,<br />
six months to hay, already 12 percent; the United Kingdom,<br />
13 percent on the admission of their own Government going to<br />
16 or 17 percent; Canada, 10 percent and risi. nq; Italy, 15 percent.<br />
Australia at the moment is around 8 percent, but faces increased<br />
Al, and new inflationary pressures2as we know, which we are determined<br />
to combat and ve. have already taken some measures in relation to<br />
that. In growth rates, the OECD has forecast 4 percent for Australia<br />
in 1979. That is not as good as we would like, but it is<br />
well above the OECD average; the United States, 2 3/ 4 percent;<br />
Britain) 1 1/ 4 percent; and Canada leqs than us again.<br />
Productivity improvement: Australia with 3 1/ 2 percent on the same<br />
forecast is well above the OECD average which is 1 3/ 4 percent;<br />
the United Stateswit ro productivity growth through 1979;<br />
the United Kingdom, 1/ 4 percent3and Canada 1/ 4. Now it is no<br />
wonder that the world is in trading difficulties. We have had<br />
high inflation for nearly seyen or eight years or more. In<br />
the twenty years to 1973-we had an eighnt percent growth in<br />
world trade each year. Since then there has been a 4 percent<br />
growth in world trade, largely because of high inflation and low<br />
growth in the economies of a number of major countries.<br />
What does that mean for Australia? It does mean that with<br />
inflation remaining too high we can't look to the world to pick<br />
us out of problems and difficulties. There won't be<br />
adequate growth in world trade and markets to achieve that.<br />
That means we've got to look to ourselves. We can--and we<br />
shouldn't be deterred by that or frightened by that) because<br />
it is within our power. Ifwe keep our inflation below that of our<br />
maior trading partners, our industries will sell more here and<br />
more in other markets overseas. If we keep our industries<br />
more competitive we will do better no matter what is happening<br />
in the wider worid. With economic stability as an encouragement<br />
for investment, with greater political stability than in many<br />
other resource nations, then again there is a greater<br />
incentive for investment in this country than in many others.<br />
Because we have coal and gas, iron ore and bauxite and other<br />
minerals that the world needs, with these things we h~ ve a<br />
capacity to attract investment to Australia and get more than<br />
our normal share of world trade. It is within our power with the<br />
right policies to achieve that. ./ 9 </p>
<p>9.-<br />
For all these reasons Australia has many advantages. We have<br />
taken tough decisions. We are not going to go the way of<br />
some other countries. We have the right, the responsible,<br />
policies and we can do better and look after this nation even<br />
if the world trading scene gets tougher and more difficult<br />
than it has been.<br />
The one blotch, the one difficulty, is industrial relations.<br />
The time has come to make sure that we do something about that.<br />
With Liberal philosophies, with our approach, with co-operation<br />
between State and Commonwealth, there is nothing that this<br />
State of Western Australia--there is nothing that Australia<br />
herself--cannot achieve. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
