<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1573</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: PM 52/1967 - ALP TACTICS ON POSTAL CHARGES - COMMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR HAROLD HOLT</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/05/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001573.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
r W. 67/ 10 2<br />
FOR PRESS: P. M. No. 52/ 1967<br />
A. L. P. TACTICS ON POSTAL CHARGES_<br />
Comment by the Prime Minister, Mr. Harold Holt<br />
Increased charges by Governments are never popular, and<br />
it is not surprising that the Labor Party should attempt to turn the<br />
announced increases in postal and telephone rates to its political advantage.<br />
But the decision to use its numbers in the Senate to defeat the Government<br />
on a substantial financial matter reveals the depth of political opportunism to<br />
which the Labor Party, under its new leadership, will allow itself to sink.<br />
It is one of the most firmly established principles of British<br />
Parliamentary democracy that a House of review should not reject the<br />
financial decisions of the popular House. The terms of the Commonwealth<br />
Constitution reflect this principle.<br />
It has long been a cherished principle of Labor policy that the<br />
Senate should not frustrate the financial policies of a Government possessing<br />
majority support in the House of Representatives. This was consistently<br />
adhered to by the former Leader of the ALP, Mr. Calwell; it has been<br />
repeatedly emphasised by Labor's Shadow Treasurer, Mr. Crean, and given<br />
clear expression by Mr. Whitlam himself. He is on public record as having<br />
stated Labor's belief that Senate powers on financial matters diould be only<br />
those of consultation. He made this statement at a time when he was acting<br />
Leader of the Labor Party. Labor's attitude on this matter is carried to the<br />
point of maintaining as a plank of policy in its platform, the abolition of the<br />
Senate. There will be many staunch Labor supporters disgusted by this<br />
cynical abandonment of a long-held princtp1e and this blatant exercise of<br />
political opportunism in the teeth of so many firm and clear public declarations<br />
of the past. If this is the new look in Labor leadership, then it is revealed<br />
as having no basis of consistency or principle nor any respect for historical<br />
democratic tradition and practice.<br />
CANBERRA, May, 1967. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
