<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5611</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S REMARKS AFTER ARRIVAL CEREMONY AT THE WHITE HOUSE, WASHINGTON</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/06/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005611.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS OFFICE TRANSCRIPT TEDY 0JN, 18<br />
PRIME MINISTER' S* REMARKS AFTER ARRIVAL CEREMONY AT THE<br />
WHITE LOUSE, WASHINGTON<br />
The discussions that we have had this morning, I regard as<br />
being particularly useful and constructive. Quite clearly,<br />
from the policies that have been implemented in the<br />
United States under the President's charge, you would expect that<br />
Australia would be in a fair measure of agreement on a number<br />
of those policies. on the economic policies and the strengthening<br />
of the dollar, and the strengthening economy of this country, we<br />
would like to say all strength to your arm, Mr. President,<br />
because an economically strong United States is important for<br />
the entire free world; the policies in relation to East/ West,<br />
again, a strong United States is important not only to the<br />
Ameri. can people but to the Australian -people and to free people<br />
everywhere. So again, Mr. President, all strength to your arm.<br />
We discussed, as you have indicated, a wide range of issues.<br />
I was particularly delighted, Mr. President, with your willingn2ess<br />
to see what can be done to remove the rough edges at the<br />
extra-terroritial reach of United States law. We have agreed<br />
that, as and when it will be convenient for both our<br />
Attorneys-General, for them to consult to see how this might<br />
best be achieved. Thank you very much for directing that that<br />
review take place.<br />
We have discussed at length major North/ South issues, the<br />
economic relationships between wealthy countries such as the<br />
United States and Australia, and many others, and developing<br />
countries or the least developed countries in this world.<br />
I hope I am not putting words into your mouth, Mr. President,<br />
in saying that. I believe that we both recognise that it is<br />
important for the peace and stability of the world that we<br />
try and make progress in these major issues, that we try and<br />
see that more and more peoples of the world have opportunities<br />
to live a decent life in dignity and self-esteem. You have<br />
told me of some of the things that you have in mind to help<br />
achieve that particular objective.<br />
We are meeting again this evening, Mr. President. I will<br />
be looking forward to discussions with your Secretary of State<br />
and Secretary of Defence and other members of your administration.<br />
Again, may I say how much my wife and I and the entire Australian<br />
party are delighted to be here. May I say how delighted we are<br />
to see what is happening in the United States right at this time.<br />
000---TUESDAY, 30 JUNE, 1981 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
