<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7989</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, RADIO, 2UE, SYDNEY 22 MARCH 1990</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/03/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007989.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, RADIO 2UE, SYDNEY,<br />
22 MARCH 1990<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, when will Greg Norman start<br />
commencing TV commercials?<br />
PM: I don't know what the time will be, it will fit in<br />
with his schedule. I think he would do it as soon as his<br />
schedule allowed. All he's concentrating on at the<br />
moment, of course, is preparing for the Masters and I've<br />
wished him the best of luck in that. So it will be a<br />
question of when it can be worked out with the Australian<br />
Tourist Commission. But I'm thrilled, as I'm sure all<br />
Australians will be, that this outstanding world figure,<br />
this Australian, has been prepared to make his services<br />
available free, as Paul Hogan did before him. It's a<br />
magnificent gesture which is very much appreciated.<br />
JOURNALIST: Who approached who?<br />
PM: Well,-John Brown and I had been talking about it and<br />
John talked with Greg and I mentioned it to Greg and,<br />
John Brown has to get credit for this, in really getting<br />
it through and I'm very fortunate of course that I'm a<br />
close personal friend of Greg's and he really wants to do<br />
it to help his country.<br />
JOURNALIST: Indicative of the sort of bunker the tourism<br />
industry's in then?<br />
PM: Not some bunker. I mean, you know what the growth<br />
figures have been. Before we came in less than nine<br />
hundred thousand visitors from overseas, now almost two<br />
and a half million. An enormous increase in investment,<br />
three hundred thousand increase in employment in the<br />
irrfdustry and already the signs being that the downturn<br />
. after. 9B8and-the-problems--ith. the.-airline industry are<br />
already being overcome and people are starting to come<br />
back because we're already getting the impact of some of<br />
the advertising that we've done as part of the special<br />
package. But with Greg Norman in the action, it will<br />
have an enormous impact I think.<br />
JOURNALIST: Will that be more successful than the Paul<br />
Hogan ads, given his international reputation? </p>
<p>PM: Who can tell whether they'll be more successful than<br />
Paul Hogan? What you'd have to say is this, that at the<br />
beginning of his advertisements he will be a better known<br />
international figure than Paul Hogan was when he started<br />
doing his ads. But we owe a great debt to Hogan, I mean<br />
let's don't forget the great job that Hogan did. I'm<br />
certainly grateful for what he did for his country and I<br />
think Greg Norman will do an enormous job.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, earlier on it looked like attacks<br />
on Mr Elliott would be part of the election campaign, now<br />
that seems to have disappeared and today you said he was<br />
respected. Why the turnaround on John Elliott?<br />
PM: No turnaround at all. I'm saying that in regard to<br />
the Multi Function Polis, a disgraceful episode brought<br />
into the election by Mr Peacock, you had the situation<br />
where I said a wide range of people who were respected in<br />
the business community, I included Mr Elliott in that,<br />
he's respected in the business community, no-one argues<br />
that he's not respected in the business community, here<br />
he was supporting it. Now I have my arguments with Mr<br />
Elliott in regard to Liberal Party policies. Let me<br />
remind you that in May of last year after the coup, when<br />
Andrew Peacock knocked off John Howard, Mr Elliott went<br />
out of his way to say that he had discussed with Mr<br />
Peacock, in his capacity as Shadow Treasurer, the<br />
economic policies of the Liberal Party, that he had been<br />
involved in them. So I noticed that Mr Peacock said the<br />
other day that he didn't tell Mr Elliott what to put in<br />
his jam and he didn't have Mr Elliott telling him what to<br />
put in his-policies. Well that's not what Mr Elliott<br />
said in May he said he'd discussed those policies with<br />
Mr Peacock.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, the Coalition is a taking great<br />
deal, or taking some comfort, from the latest Morgan<br />
Gallop figures. Are they right to do so?<br />
PM: I find it rather amusing that they should take<br />
comfort from figures which has us winning. If they take<br />
comfort from a poll which has us winning, that's<br />
interesting, an interesting comment upon them. The fact<br />
is that if you take all the polls and I want to be very<br />
careful in what I say if you take all the polls, it has<br />
Labor winning, but I'm not drawing any solace from that.<br />
I-ve taken the view from the beginning of the campaign<br />
that . I! ve.. got.. to-fight.-hard,-. that-it's a tight election<br />
and I've got to fight right up till tomorrow night. I'd<br />
rather have the polls the way they are now, than have<br />
them showing a Coalition victory. But I think that I've<br />
done what the people want, I've talked about our policies<br />
for the future, I've exposed inadequacies of the other<br />
side and I've faced up to the questions that need to be<br />
asked and answered. I think, as you get to the end of<br />
the campaign Peter, it's an amazing paradox. You have<br />
the Liberal strategy which started off saying that there<br />
are questions to be answered, and if there's one thing </p>
<p>3.<br />
that's characterised this election campaign, it's been<br />
the refusal of Mr Peacock to face up to questioning and<br />
provide any answers.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, you said today that the Liberals<br />
couldn't achieve sustained falls in interest rates. Are<br />
you conceding that after the election, if they did get<br />
in, they could get interest rates down?<br />
PM: No, I can't say what would happen, what the reaction<br />
of the banking industry would be, because I know what it<br />
is to us. Because they've said so. You don't need me to<br />
quote again from the Reuters screen and the various<br />
spokesmen for the banking industry which have said that<br />
if Labor is returned, interest rates will fall. And<br />
they've said it because they know what our policies are<br />
and what it's producing. Now what their judgement would<br />
be about the Liberals, I can't say. I know that looking<br />
any way into the future they would have to be terribly<br />
disturbed because the two elements which can sustain a<br />
fall in interest rates are lacking in the Liberals'<br />
policy. That is, an acceptable wages outcome is not<br />
there, there would be a wages explosion and, in terms of<br />
fiscal responsibility, the surplus that we've built up<br />
the first government ever to do it would be dissipated<br />
under the Liberals because they've got a six to seven<br />
billion dollar unfunded set of bribes. Now, what<br />
judgement the banking industry would make about that I<br />
simply don't know.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, are you annoyed that your<br />
relationship with Sir Peter Abeles has been raised in the<br />
way that it has in the media this morning?<br />
PM: No. Look, I've had this been thrown at me over a<br />
number of years and the facts are simple. I've stood up<br />
in the Parliament, when I was in Opposition and since<br />
I've been in Government, where people have sought to<br />
denigrate me because of my friendship with Sir Peter<br />
Abeles. I've stood up and defended the man and defended<br />
my friendship. I happen to be a person to whom<br />
friendship is important. I don't dispense my friendship<br />
lightly. My friendship with Sir Peter Abeles goes back<br />
to 1970. He has never, in my period as President of the<br />
ACTU or Prime Minister, asked me for a favour. He<br />
wouldn't abuse my friendship by so doing. And as I<br />
pointed out on the John Laws program, if there's one<br />
. person. who. has._ acted against , the-interests of Sir Peter<br />
Abeles, it's Bob Hawke. Because under the Opposition in<br />
government, they created and kept going that cosy<br />
two-airline agreement which was a licence to print money<br />
for the Ansett organisation. It's Bob Hawke and his<br />
Government who's brought that to an end.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
