<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10</transcript-id>
    <title>DIGEST OF DECISIONS AND ANNOUNCEMENTS AND IMPORTANT SPEECHES BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE RIGHT HON. J.B CHIFLEY - NO. 131</title>
    <prime-minister>Chifley, Ben</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19450713 - 19491219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/10/1947</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000010_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
COMMONWEALTH GOVERNMENT.<br />
DIGEST OF DECISIONS<br />
AND ANNOUNCEMENTS<br />
IMPORTANT SPEECHES<br />
BY<br />
THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
( THE RIGHT HON. j. B. CHIFLEY).<br />
No. 131.<br />
PERIOD -9TH OCTOBER, 1947, to 5TH NOVEMBER, 1947.<br />
* h Aumwdty:<br />
L F. JoamN. Cammnwealth Governm Printw. Canbom.<br />
( Printed in Austmlia.)<br />
L_ _ Y I<br />
L~<br />
lU~ I -rs -uy--ur </p>
<p>L INCOME TAX.<br />
UNIFORM TAXATION-REIMBURSEMENT TO STATES,<br />
BILL INTRODUCED.<br />
In Parliamnt. v-Qn 9th October, 1947, the Prima Minister ( Mr.<br />
Chifley) introduced the States Grants ( Tax Reimbursement) Bill. Mr.<br />
Chifley said-<br />
The object of this bill is to provide for the payment of an additional<br />
tax reimbursement grant to the States under the uniform tax plan.<br />
Under the 1946 act, a revised basis of tax reimbursement grants came<br />
into operation as from 1st July, 1946. Main provisions of that act<br />
were-Aggregate grant in 1946-47 and 1947-48 to be œ 40,000,000, distributed among<br />
the States in Accordance with the first sche~ dule of the act.<br />
-In 1948-49 and subsequent years, the aggregate grant to be increased in<br />
accordance with the formula, which takes account of the variations in the States,<br />
jpopulations, and one half of the percentage increase, if any, in the level of<br />
average wages per person employed, over the level in 19441-47.<br />
In 1948-49 and subsequent years, the distribution of the aggregate grant<br />
aniong the States to be varied to an increasing degree in accordance with the<br />
adjusted populations of the States.<br />
The gralit to each State in any year to be not less than that received in<br />
1946-47.<br />
" At the conference of Commonwealth and State Ministers in<br />
August, 1947, the Premiers maintained that the aggregate grant of<br />
œ 4,000,000 would be insufficient to enable them to balance their budgets<br />
in 1947-48. It is clear that there has been a deterioration of State<br />
finances. Mainly because of the success of the Commonwealth Government's<br />
low interest rate policy, State debt charges-which constitute a<br />
major item of State expenditures-have in the aggregate not increased<br />
over the 1938-39 level. In the field of administration and social services,<br />
however, State expenditures are showing an unusually rapid increase,<br />
partly because of the impact of rising costs and prices.<br />
o " The Commonwealth Government does not desire to upset the basis<br />
ofreimbursement provided for in the 1946 act, which, in the absence of<br />
a major change in the relations between the Commonwealth and any<br />
State or States having an effect on the finances ot a -State or -States, was<br />
to operate for at least seven years. On this basis, the State governments<br />
are, in effect, guaranteed the reimbursement provided for in the act,<br />
irrespective of fluctuations in the financial position of the * Commonwealth.<br />
Accordingly, the Government proposes that the States Grants<br />
( Tax Reimbursement) Act 1946 shall continue in operation, with the<br />
addition of a section to provide for-<br />
The payment of an additional grant of œ 5,000,000 to the States in 1947-48.<br />
The payment of an additional grant in subsequent years to cover any del<br />
ciency that may occur between the aggregate grant as determined under the<br />
present provisions of the act and 45,000), 000.<br />
" It is also proposed that in each instance the additional grant is to<br />
be distributed among the States in the same proportions as the aggregate<br />
grant of œ 40,000,000 is distributed at present [ The bill was passed.<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 129, page 41.) </p>
<p>ROYAL AUSTRALIAN NAVY.<br />
NAVAL BOARD-FOURTH MEMBER.<br />
On 9th October, 1947, the Minister for the Navy ( Mr. Riordan)<br />
announced that Captain E. W. Anstice had been appointed Fourth<br />
Naval Member of the Naval Board.<br />
COMMONWEALTH LITERARY FUND.<br />
DECISIONS.<br />
On 9th October, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-.<br />
The Commonwealth Literary Fund Committee to-day awarded<br />
fellowships for 1948 to K. ( Seaforth) MacKenzie, J. K. Ewers, and<br />
Miss Jean Campbell. A Commonwealth Literary Fund pension was<br />
awarded to J. W. Gordon Jim Grahame")"<br />
BARLEY.<br />
STABILIZATION PLAN-CONTINUANCE.<br />
On 9th October, 1947, the Minister for Agriculture ( Mr. Pollard)<br />
announced that the Commonwealth Government would extend barley<br />
marketing regulations to enable the incoming crop to be marketed by<br />
the Australian Barley Board as in previous seasons, on a Commonwealth<br />
basis, with a guaranteed minimum price. Urgent requests had been<br />
made by the Victorian and South Australian Governments and growers'<br />
organizations that that would be done.<br />
On 30th Octobcr, 1947, Mr. Pollard announced that the Australian<br />
Barley Board would handle and market oats of all grades under voluntary<br />
pool with a minimum guarantee from the Government, and<br />
would be the sole exporter of oats. The arrangement would apply in<br />
all States, but growers would be free to sell on the open market. The<br />
Government guarantee of 3s. 3d. a bushel on rails at growers' sidings,<br />
plus an extra 3d. a bushel to off-set higher cost of bags, would be payable,<br />
but growers would not be permitted to rail oats until advised by the<br />
board. ( For earlier references, please see No. 117, page 44.)<br />
No. 8 POOL-FOURTH ADVANCE.<br />
On 28th October, 1947, Mr. Pollard announced that a fourth advance<br />
of 9d. a bushel for malting grades and 3d. a bushel for feed grades had<br />
been approved on 1946-47 crop barley in No. 8 pool. The advance<br />
brought payments to growers to 7s. 3d. a bushel less freight for 2-row<br />
malting barley, and 3s. 8d. less freight for 6-row feed grade.<br />
REMEMBRANCE SUNDAY.<br />
On 9th October, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
In accordance with the approval given by the King in respect of<br />
the observance this year of Remembrance Sunday in Britain, the Commonwealth<br />
Government proposes that the usual arrangements be made </p>
<p>in Australia for the commemoration of Remembrance Day on 9th<br />
November, 1947, as a Day of Remembrance for those who gave their<br />
lives both in World War I. and World War II.<br />
WHEAT POOLS PAYMENTS.<br />
No. 11 POOLr-FIRST ADVANCE.<br />
On 10th October, 1947, the Minister for Agriculture ( Mr. Pollard)<br />
announced that the first advance to growers for No. 11 wheat pool would<br />
be 4s. 6d. a bushel net for bulk wheat and 5s. a bushel net for bagged<br />
wheat-the highest first advance for any pool.<br />
No. 10 POOL-THIRD ADVANCE.<br />
On 30th October, 1947, Mr. Pollard announced that a third advance<br />
of Is. a bushel had been approved for No. 10 pool. The advance would<br />
bring the amounts to 6s. 7d. for bulk and 6s. 10d. for bagged. less freight.<br />
PRIMARY INDUSTRIES.<br />
DAIRY INDUSTRY-ADVISORY COMMITTEE, REPORT.<br />
On 13th October, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) announced<br />
that the Joint Dairy Industry Advisory Committee which had made a<br />
survey of farm costs of production of butter, cheese and processed milk<br />
products had, in advance of its final report, submitted recommendations<br />
to the Government. It had been decided that the overall -basic return to<br />
the farmer at the factory door would be 2s. per lb. commercial butter<br />
basis-an increase of 41d. per lb. on the present recognized cost of production<br />
of Is. 7Id. per lb. to the dairy farmer and, in accordance with<br />
the Government's understanding with the industry, would be retrospective<br />
to 1st April, 1947.<br />
The Government had decided to guarantee a price to the industry<br />
on total production of the products mentioned for five years from 1st<br />
April, 1947. The basic return to the farmer of 2s. per lb. commercial<br />
butter would be subject to variation up or down in accordance with<br />
demonstrated movements in cost factors. There would be a review of<br />
cost factors between 1s, April and 15th June in each year during the<br />
five years, following which any necessary adjustmnents of the basic price<br />
now determined would be made as from 1st July of the year under<br />
reniew. As a result of the Government's decision, increases in the retail<br />
prices of butter, cheese and associated milk products would be necessary<br />
and while the existing subsidy payments of about œ 4,500,000 a year<br />
would be continued, it had yet to determine the extent to which the whole<br />
or part of the increased prices would be passed on to the consumer. It<br />
was estimated that from 1st April, 1947, until such time as it was<br />
possible to adjust retail prices to the consuming public the Commonwealth<br />
Government would pay a further subsidy of about œ E2,000,000. </p>
<p>The Government had approved an annual grant of an amount not<br />
exceeding œ 250,000 for five years commencing 1st January, 1948, to<br />
promote improved farm practices in the dairy industry. Plans would<br />
be drawn up by the Minister for Agriculture ( Mr. Pollard) in consultation<br />
with representatives of the industry and State Ministers of<br />
Agriculture. ( For earlier references, please see No. 115, page 33; No. 122, page 18.)<br />
DAIRY INDUSTRY-CONTROL, BOARD CHAIRMAN.<br />
On 4th November, 1947, Mr. Pollard announced that the president<br />
of the Australian Dairy Farmers' Federation ( Mr. G. C. Howey) had<br />
been appointed chairman of the Australian Dairy Produce Board,<br />
re-constituted under recent legislation.<br />
( For earlier reference, please see No. 130, page 3.)<br />
EXPORTS TO BRITAIN-UNITED KINGDOM MISSION.<br />
On 17th October, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
The Australian Government considers it desirable that Britain<br />
should send a small expert mission to Australia to continue exploratory<br />
discussions commenced at London between representatives of the two<br />
Governments, regarding the production of larger quantities of food in<br />
Australia, so that greater supplies will be available for export to the<br />
British people.<br />
This view is being conveyed to the British Government through the<br />
Australian High Commissioner at London ( Mr. Beasley). He will<br />
express the opinion, already known to : be acceptable to the British<br />
Government, that such a mission will become familiar with technical and<br />
other problems associated with particular primary industries, and secure<br />
a clearer appreciation of action already being taken to stimulate<br />
production. The Australian Government will co-operate enthusiastically in a<br />
project to further increase output of those foods desired by Britain<br />
which can be produced on a commercial scale here, and or which markets<br />
for a reasonable term ahead are assured. This will necessarily include<br />
extensions of existing long-term contracts, and the negotiation of others<br />
-exemplified in preliminary discussions on wheat with Lord Addison<br />
when he was in Australia.<br />
Australia has already been able to increase direct exports to Britain<br />
since the war ended, and to provide food for British Empire countries<br />
in the Pacific and elsewhere. The latter has, no doubt, relieved pressure<br />
on Britain's other supply sources. Australia's efforts will be continued<br />
and, no doubt, can be augmented with direct aid from Britain. Meii<br />
and machines are among urgent requirements to stimulate production<br />
The proposed mission of experts to Australia will have an opportunity<br />
for discussion with Australian agricultural experts, and when<br />
proposals are matured it can be anticipated that their guidance will be<br />
a major contribution in developments </p>
<p>7<br />
EXPORT. S TO BRITAIN-BUTTER.<br />
On 5th November, 1947, Mr. Pollard said that total exports of<br />
butter during 1946-47 were 133,642,282 lb. of which 116,640,028 lb.<br />
went to Britain. Excepting for a small quantity, Australian butter was<br />
shipped either to or at the direction of the British Ministry of Food and<br />
in accordance with International Emergency Food Council allocations.<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 115, page 32.)<br />
RURAL PRODUCTION.<br />
On 19th Oct6ber, 1947, Mr. Pollard said-<br />
Gross value of rural production in Australia for 1947-48 has been<br />
estimated at œ 447,000,000 compared with the estimated value of<br />
œ 379,000,000 for 1946-47 and the average annual value for the five<br />
pre-war years ended 1938-39 of œ 211,000,000. The current year's<br />
estimate is about 18 per cent. higher than 1946-47, and considerably<br />
more than double the pre-war figure.<br />
Of the estimated total, agricultural industries are expected to<br />
contribute œ 192,000,000, pastoral industries œ 168,000,000 and dairy<br />
and farmyard industries œ 87,000,000, of which dairy and pig products<br />
represent œ 60,000,000. The estimated figures for 1946-47 are<br />
œ 139,000,000, œ 159,000,000 and œ 81,000,000 respectively.<br />
Expressed in terms of percentages, compared with the average<br />
figures for the pre-war five year period ended 1938-39, increases in the<br />
estimated value of rural production for the current period are-<br />
Wheat.-More than 300 per cent. increase in value and about 29 per cent<br />
incrpase in volume.<br />
Wool.-About 90 per cent. increase inlva lue, but about 8 per cent. decrease in<br />
volume. Meats ( except pig-meats).-About 133 per cent. increase in value; 9 per cent.<br />
increase in number of sheep and lambs slaughtered, but 4 per cent. fewer beef<br />
cattle and calves.<br />
Dairy Products ( including pig-meats).-About 112 per cent. in value, but<br />
per cent. decrease in total milk produced and 16 per cent. decrease in the<br />
number of pigs slaughtered.<br />
" Wool, estimated to return œ 96,000,000, and wheat, at œ 93,000,000,<br />
are expected to contribute 42 per cent. of the estimated gross return"<br />
SUGAR-AGREEMENT, BILL INTRODUCED.<br />
In Parliament.-On 23rd October, the Minister for Customs<br />
( Senator Courtice) introduced the Sugar Agreement Bill. Senator<br />
Courtice said-<br />
This bill is intended to approve the supplementary sugar agreement<br />
made on 17th October, 1947, between the Commonwealth Government<br />
and the Queensland Government. Under that agreement the<br />
governments agreed to amend the present sugar agrement to provide for<br />
an increase of œ 4 2s. 8d. a ton in the wholesale price of refined sugar of<br />
la grade, and for the prices of sugar of other grades at present fixed by </p>
<p>the Sugar Agreement Act, to be increased comnmensurately. Comparison<br />
of the new maximum prices with the present ones is supplied in the<br />
following table Present Price. New Price.<br />
Per ton. Per ton.<br />
E s. d. F d.<br />
Refined sugar of I A grade 33 41 0 37 6 8<br />
Refinied sugar of 1XD grade 32 10 9 36 11 9<br />
Mill white and first quality mill sugar of not less than 98<br />
net titre--<br />
Price to mnanufacturers 29 8 0 32 10 6<br />
Prico to other purchasers 30 0 0 33 3 9<br />
" The effect of the increase of œ 4 2s. Sd. a ton in the wholesale price<br />
will be to raise the retail price of refined sugar by Ad. per lb. The new<br />
retail price in capitdl cities will be 4jd.<br />
When the present agreement was signed in October, 1945, the Australian<br />
Government gave an assurance to the sugar industry that, if<br />
during the currency of the agreement, cost levels increased substantially,<br />
it would be prepared to consider instituting an inquiry into the position<br />
of the industry. The Government has become increasingly aware of the<br />
difficulties which the industry had to face during the war years and since,<br />
and it is now convinced that the urgency of the industry's need for<br />
assistance is such that immediate action must be taken to provide a<br />
stimulus to the industry [ The bill was passed.<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 112, page 30; No. 129, page 24.)<br />
EDUCATION.<br />
UNESCO-AUSTRALIAN DELEGATION 1947.<br />
On 14th October, 1947, the Minister for Post-war Reconstruction<br />
( Mr. Dedman) announced that an Australian delegation would attend<br />
the second session of the Unesco conference at Mexico City in November,<br />
1947. The delegation comprised-<br />
Dr. E. R. Walker. leader, the Ausistant Director of the Commnonwealth Office<br />
of Education ( Mr. WV. J. Weeden), the Secretary of the New South Wales<br />
Public Library ( Mr. J. W. Metcalfe), the Lecturer in Arts at Sydney Technical<br />
College ( Mr. F. Medworth), and a nomninee ( if the Australian Teachers<br />
Federation. 
127, page 32.)<br />
BANKING CONTROL.<br />
LEGISLATION-NATIONALIZATION, BILL INTRODUCED.<br />
In Parliament.-On 15th October, 1947, the Prime ' Minister ( Mr.*<br />
Chifley) introduced the Banking Bill 1947. Mr. Chifley said-<br />
" eThe purpose of this bill is to empower the Commonwealth Bank to<br />
take over the banking business at present conducted in Australia by<br />
private banks. ' State banks and savings banks will not be affected. </p>
<p>9<br />
It will be the responsibility of the Commnonwea lth Bank under this<br />
legislation-To provide, in accordance with the conditions of normal banking business,<br />
adequate banking facilities for any State or person requiring them;<br />
To conduct its business without discrimination.<br />
To observe, except as otherwise required by law, the practices and usages<br />
customary among bankers and, in particular, to maintain strict secrecy within<br />
the law as to the affairs and dealings of its customers.<br />
The bill also envisages the development, under public ownership,<br />
of a comprehensive banking service that will strengthen and assist the<br />
growth of the Australian economy and provide facilities adequate to its<br />
rapidly expanding and changing needs.<br />
" I hardly need argue the importance of money and credit in a<br />
modern economic system. As the means by which resources are brought<br />
together in production, goods are bought and sold, and prices, wages,<br />
contracts and debts are determined, it plays a part as vital to the<br />
economic body as the blood-stream to the human body. No single factorcan<br />
do more to influence the welfare and progress of a community thanthe<br />
management of the volume and flow of money. Mismanagement of<br />
money, on the other hand, has contributed to the greatest economicdisasters<br />
of modern times-booms and slumps, mass unemployment,<br />
waste of resources, industrial unrest and social misery. Because these<br />
facts are recognized, there is very wide agreement to-day as to the<br />
puirposes which a monetary and banking system should serve in a modern<br />
economy. In that connexion I quote the views expressed in 1937 in the<br />
Report of the Royal Comm ission on Monetary and Banking Systems in<br />
Australia-The general objective of an economic system for Australia should be to<br />
achieve the best use of our productive resources, both present and future. This<br />
mneans. the fullest possible employment of people and resources under conditions<br />
that will provide the highest standard of living. It means, too, the reduction of<br />
the monetary and banking system is an integral fluctuation in general economic<br />
activity. Since part of the economic system, its objective will be to assist with<br />
all the means at its disposal in achieving these ends. ( Para. 616.)<br />
Those views as to the place and functions of money and banking in<br />
Australia were subscribed to by all members of the commission, even<br />
though there was some difference of opinion as to ways of achieving<br />
them. The Labour party has maintained for many years that, since the<br />
influence of money is so great, the entire monetary and banking system<br />
should be controlled by public authorities responsible through the Government<br />
and Parliament to the nation. On this principle the Labour<br />
party has held further that since private banks are conducted primarily<br />
for profit and therefore follow policies which in important respects run<br />
counter to the public interest, their business should be transferred to<br />
public ownership. For this view the strongest reasons can be stated.<br />
In the absence of control, private banks can expand or contract the<br />
volume of their lending and so vary within wide limits the supply of<br />
money available to the public. They can also determine when arid<br />
where they will lend and on what terms; and in these operations they </p>
<p>are guided primarily by the interests of those who own and control<br />
them. Whatever regard they may claim to pay to the wider concerns<br />
of the nation, their policies are dictated in the last resort by the desire<br />
to make profits and to secure the value of their own assets. Experienet'<br />
of the past has been that private banks increased their lending in good<br />
times and contracted it in bad times, lent always where the profits<br />
seemed largest and most assured, and charged the highest rates they<br />
could obtain for their loans and general services.<br />
" Since trading banks have handled practically all commercial<br />
lending within Australia, their influence on the state of business has<br />
been enormous-indeed dominating. Moreover, the number of banks<br />
has been progressively reduced through amalgamations, of which twelve<br />
have been carried through since 1917. Two more were announced this<br />
year and had they been completed the number of major private trading<br />
banks in Australia would have been reduced to seven. By this means<br />
the great power of private banking in Australia has become concentrated<br />
in the hands of boards of directors comprising a relatively few men<br />
who are responsible for the exercise of their powers not to the nation<br />
but only to a limited number of people, some here nd some abroad, who<br />
have invested money in bank shares.<br />
Time and again the policies of the private banks have run counter<br />
to national needs for steady growth and high levels of employment. To<br />
go some years back it is correct to say that the banks fed the boom and<br />
promoted unsound development in the ' twenties. When the depression<br />
came the banks as a whole restricted new lending and. called in advances.<br />
Between December, 1929, and March, 1932, their advances fell by<br />
approximately œ 45,000,000. The effect of this was to accentuate the<br />
contraction of business and the unemployment of those years. They<br />
helped but little in recovery during the ' thirties, waiting rather for<br />
improvement to come from other sources instead of taking the initiative<br />
and helping to promote recovery. They followed these courses because<br />
it seemed best and safest from the standpoint of their own interests.<br />
" Labour policy on banking has envisaged that, together with the<br />
elimination of private banking, the Commonwealth Bank would be<br />
strengthened to give it adequate control of monetary and credit conditions<br />
within Australia and its services would be extended to meet the<br />
needs of all sections of the people. The Labour party has in particuluar<br />
advocated the reduction of interet rates which, in the absence of control,<br />
were maintained at excessively high levels.<br />
" The Commonwealth Bank was established in 1911 by the Labour<br />
Government as a national bank, intended primarily to compete with the<br />
private banks on their own ground and break the monopoly they held<br />
over the business of banking in Australia. Despite bitter opposition<br />
from private interests and many prophecies of failure, the Commonwealth<br />
Bank rendered great service to the nation and grew rapidly<br />
during World War I. and the succeeding years. In 1924, however, the<br />
Bruce-Page Government reconstituted the bank and placed it under a </p>
<p>board comprised predominantly of representatives of private industry<br />
and commerce. This board was mainly interested in turning the Commonwealth<br />
Bank into a bankers' bank and its policy was to forbid the<br />
bank from competing actively with the private banks for general banking<br />
business, thus restricting its expansion and defeating the key<br />
purpose for which the bank had been established. That fact was clearly<br />
demons: rated in evidence before the banking commission. The late<br />
Sir Ernest Riddle, who was then Governor of the bank, stated that even<br />
if the bank had funds available over and above those deposited with it<br />
by the trading banks it would not use those funds for advances to people<br />
who wanted to transfer their accounts from trading banks to the Commonwealth<br />
Bank. That kind of situation prevailed until the Labour<br />
Government took office in 1941. Moreover, the Commonwealth Bank<br />
Board, as constituted by the Bruce-Page Government, aligned itself with<br />
the private banks during the crisis of the early ' thirties in attempting<br />
to force on the Government a policy of monetary deflation and curtailment<br />
of wages and social service payments. That policy was stated in<br />
the following extract from a letter addressed by the chairman of the<br />
Bank Board ( Sir Robert Gibson) to the then Treasurer ( Mr. Theodore)<br />
on 12th February, 1931, which read-<br />
Subject to adequate and equitable reductions in all wages, salaries, and<br />
allowances, pensions, social benefits of all kinds, interest and other factors which<br />
affect the cost of living. the Commonwealth Bank Board will actively co-operate<br />
with the trading banks and the governments of Australia in sustaining industry<br />
and restoring employment.<br />
Thus during a critical time in Australia's history the bank was<br />
used by reactionary interests for a purpose directly opposed to the<br />
welfare of the Australian people and in opposition to the will of the<br />
Government of the day.<br />
In spite of conservative management under a board for many years,<br />
the Commonwealth Bank, including the Commonwealth Savings Bank,<br />
has made remarkable headway. At 30th June, 1947, it had 377 branches<br />
spread throughout Australia, as well as branches in Papua, New Guinea<br />
and in London. Total employees exceeded 9,000 and total assets, apart<br />
from those held in respect of deposits of the private banks, were almost<br />
œ 900,000,000. It has nearly 4,000,000 accounts and is unique among<br />
the banks of the world in that it provides comprehensive banking facilities<br />
for business and personal needs through its General Bank, Savings<br />
Bank, Mortgage Bank, Rural Credits, Industrial Finance and Housing<br />
Departments. In both wars the bank made advances against primary<br />
commodities to enable producers to be paid promptly despite serious<br />
delays in sea-borne trade. These advances exceeded œ 350,000,000 during<br />
the six years of the last war. In another field the bank has administered<br />
controls over banking, interest rates, the note issue, foreign exchange<br />
and gold and has developed the full functions of a central bank. In all,<br />
the record of the Commonwealth Bank stands as a great justification of<br />
publicly-owned banking and demonstrates beyond question that a public<br />
banking institution is capable of being highly efficient, progressive and </p>
<p>adaptable. In another respect also the bank has largely fulfilled the<br />
intentions of its founders that it should be a bank for the people.<br />
Together with its associated institution, the Commonwealth Savings<br />
Bank, it has become pre-eminently the bank for the average man and<br />
woman. To-day it has a far greater number of depositors than the<br />
whole of the private banks taken together. At April, 1947, the number<br />
of deposit accounts with the Commonwealth Bank and Commonwealth<br />
Savings Bank was about 3,800,000, whereas the number of deposit<br />
accounts with the trading banks was approximately 1,250,000.<br />
" Assisted by the existence of the Commonwealth Bank, the Labour<br />
Government has been able to make notable progress in carrying out its<br />
policy of lower interest rates. After World War I. the interest rate on<br />
government loans reached as high as 64 per cent. At the outbreak of<br />
World War II., the rate for long-term government loans was almost<br />
4 per cent. It is now 34 per cent. The treasury-bill rate is now 1 per<br />
cent., as compared with a rate of 6 per cent. in 1930. The maximum<br />
overdraft rate has been restricted to 44 per cent., as compared with rates<br />
of 6 per cent. and higher some years ago. Substantial reductions have<br />
also been made in the rates at which semi-governmental bodies are able<br />
to borrow, and in many other rates.<br />
The experience of the war years emphasized the vital importance<br />
of public control of the banking system. Through governmental expenditure<br />
for war purposes, the liquid resources of the trading banksand<br />
hence their capacity to expand credit-increased rapidly. To<br />
prevent ' secondary inflation arising from such as expansion of credit.<br />
even the then Treasurer ( Mr. Fadden) felt that some action was<br />
necessary, and, in 1941, he obtained an undertaking from the private<br />
banks that they would inform the Commonwealth Bank of the amount<br />
of surplus investible funds they held from time to time and would<br />
deposit with the Commonwealth Bank such amounts as were determined<br />
by that hank. On assuming office in November, 1941, the Labour Government<br />
carefully examined the arrangements made by the previous<br />
Government and decided that it was necessary to introduce National<br />
Security ( War-time Banking Control) Regulations. These regulations<br />
greatly strengthened and increased in scope the arrangements agreed to<br />
by the previous Government. They also ensured that the private banks<br />
would not make unreasonable profits out of the war and implemented<br />
certain recommendations of the Banking Commission.<br />
" In the light of experience gained in the administration of these<br />
regulations, the Government decided, in 1945, that the main principles<br />
on which they were based should be embodied in substantive legislation.<br />
At the same time the Government decided to reconstitute the Commonwalth<br />
Bank and to assume greater powers over banking policy. The<br />
main objects of the system of control provided by this legislation were-<br />
To strengthen the central banking functions of the Commonwealth Bank,<br />
especially by providing for the co-ordination of banking policy under the direc-<br />
ø tion of the Commonwealth Bank; control through the special account system </p>
<p>of the volume of credit in circulation: control of bank interest rates and bank<br />
advance policy; and the mobilization and control of the foreign exchange and<br />
gold resources of the Australian economy.<br />
To ensure that the financial policy of the Commonwealth Bank would be in<br />
harmony with the general economic and financial policy of the Government and<br />
in the interests of the people of Australia.<br />
To reserve to publicly-owned and controlled banks the banking business of<br />
governments and governmental authorities.<br />
To safeguard the depositors of the banks against loss of their deposits.<br />
The Bank Board was abolished and management of the bank was<br />
entrusted to the Governor, assisted by an advisory council.<br />
This legislation was very strongly opposed by the trading banks,<br />
by some sections of the business community and by the Opposition<br />
parties. It was said that the legislation would hand over the banking<br />
system to political control, that it was nationalization on the cheap<br />
and that it would open the way to the general socialization of industry<br />
by indirect means. In his second-reading speech on the legislation, the<br />
Leader of the Opposition ( Mr. Menzies) made a pledge that, if he and<br />
his colleagues were returned to office, they would restore the former<br />
method of control of the Commonwealth Bank by a board and would<br />
hold themselves obliged instantly to review the working of the<br />
legislation. In spite of the sectional clamour against the legislation<br />
and the prediction of dire consequences to follow from it, the Government<br />
was returned to office at the general election last year. It may,<br />
therefore, be said that a majority of the electors have endorsed the<br />
Government's 1945 banking legislation and have approved the purpose<br />
for which it was enacted, namely, to give the Government full and<br />
effective control over monetary and banking policy in Australia. That<br />
object was made clear to Parliament and to the country.<br />
The Banking Act of 1945 was framed on the best constitutional<br />
advice and the Government felt confident that it would withstahd any<br />
legal challenge that might be directed against it. For example, it<br />
seemed quite clear that Parliament had made a law with respect to<br />
banking, and had thus acted within the scope of the powers conferred<br />
by section 51 ( xiii.) of the Constitution, when it enacted section 48 of<br />
the Banking Act. This section prohibited trading banks, other than<br />
State banks from carrying out banking business for a State or any<br />
authority of a State, including a local governing authority. The provision<br />
was regarded by the Government as an important part of the<br />
legislation. It embodied the principle that the banking business of all<br />
public bodies should be reserved to publicly-owned and controlled banks.<br />
Further, in most other countries it has long been accepted that all<br />
government banking business should be conducted through the central<br />
bank so as to give the central bank added strength to control the supply<br />
of credit and to enable it to take action in time to offset any disturbance<br />
to credit conditions resulting from government operations. In the<br />
aggregate the banking business of State governments and State<br />
authorities is large and so are some of their individual transactions. </p>
<p>They have an important bearing on current financial conditions. It was<br />
the Government's view that the powers of the central bank should be<br />
strengthened by making it as far as practicable the banker for public<br />
authorities. When challenged in the High Court, however, section 48<br />
was held to be invalid on the grounds that so long as private banks<br />
existed States and State authorities could not be denied the use of their<br />
facilities. The decision showed that full public control of banking as<br />
sought under the 1945 legislation could not be secured without pubiic<br />
ownership of banking.<br />
" The decision forced the Government to re-examine all the circumstances,<br />
constitutional and otherwise, surrounding the legislation of<br />
1945. In particular, the Government has had to reconsider the constitutional<br />
basis of sections 18 to 22 of the Banking Act which required the<br />
private banks to make deposits in special accounts with the Commonwealth<br />
Bank and also the attitude of the private banks towards those<br />
sections. The special accounts are the crux of the control of credit given<br />
to the Commonwealth Bank by the Banking Act of 1945. The necessities<br />
of war-time finance greatly increased the base of liquid reserves<br />
on which trading banks normally build a superstructure of secondary<br />
credit. To prevent secondary inflation with rising prices it was necessary<br />
to imobilize some parts of the banks' deposits in special accounts<br />
with the Commonwealth Bank from which the banks were not allowed to<br />
withdraw any amounts, except with the consent of the Conimmonwealth<br />
Bank. If the amounts in these special accounts were freely available<br />
to the trading banks, they could, by increasing their advances, build up<br />
a secondary credit expansion of formidable dimensions. Added to the<br />
spending power already available to the public, this might easily<br />
produce a dangerous inflationary situation. It would be disastrous,<br />
from the point of view of the people of Australia and the prospects of<br />
economic stability, if sections 18 to 22 of the Banking Act were held to<br />
be invalid and the consequent loss of control over the banking system<br />
led to an inflation of credit, with all the loss and disorder which inflation<br />
entails. These sections necessarily severely limit the freedom of action<br />
of the trading banks. This was their intention. The Government was<br />
determined that the control of the Commonwealth Bank in this field<br />
should be absolute and beyond dispute.<br />
While the precise form of special accounts provided for in the<br />
Banking Act of 1945 was peculiar to Australia, the essential feature of<br />
the control of credit by this means are to be found in operation in<br />
Britain, Canada and a number of other countries. The same conditions<br />
which made a control of this kind essential in Australia have forced<br />
governments elsewhere to adopt similar measures. They are to-day an<br />
accepted part of central bank technique in many parts of the world.<br />
The private banks in Australia have always bitterly resented any<br />
attempt to place restrictions on their power to create or restrict credit.<br />
When the 1945 Banking Bill was before the House they fought these<br />
provisions with all the means, at their disposal. Towards the end of </p>
<p>1945, when the bill had become law, they were required to transfer their<br />
war-time special deposits to the special accoun's established under the<br />
new legislation and to make their first monthly lodgment to these<br />
accounts. The private banks, obviously acting in concert and on legal<br />
ndvice, made it clear a' that time that, while they were submitting to<br />
the legislation for the time being, they were reserving the right to<br />
rhalleng, it at a suitable opportunity. The following reservation was<br />
made by one of the Iank-. in a let'er to the Commonwealth Bank:-<br />
We are most anxiions. to co-operate with your Bank to ensure the continuance<br />
of our present harmonious relations, but you will appreciate that our duty to our<br />
shareholders compels us to have regard to our legal position; therefore, we feel<br />
it necessary to advise yon, with all due respect, that acquiescence or compliance<br />
on this Banik's part with any request or directions from you is not to be taken<br />
to import nny contract with your Bank in the terms of the Act.<br />
Statements to a similar effect were made in letters sent by six of<br />
the other banks. These reservations were brought to the notice of the<br />
Commonwealth Government at the time for legal consideration. This<br />
indication of the attitude of the private banks assumed greater significance<br />
when the special account system was challenged in the statement<br />
of claim made by Melbourne City Council in connexion with the section<br />
48 case-even though eventually the challenge to sections 18 to 22 of the<br />
Banking Act was not pressed. It assumed still greater significance<br />
when the High Court decision on section 48 made it clear that, although<br />
the Commonwealth Parliament had by the Constitution been given<br />
power to legislate on banking, nevertheless a law which was clearly a<br />
law with respect to banking could be held invalid on other constitutional<br />
considerations. The position which confronted the Government was<br />
that while doubts had arisen as to the constitutional validity of its banking<br />
legislation, there was evidence that the private banks were maintaining<br />
their hostility towards this legislation and were biding their time<br />
against a suitable opportunity to challenge it in the hope of throwing<br />
off the restraints they so strongly disliked.<br />
With economic difficulties increasing overseas the Government<br />
must be in a position to act with certainty and effectiveness to ensure<br />
fulfilment of its policy of full employment and the maintenance of economic<br />
and financial stability. During the war and since its conclusion<br />
the Australian economy has been kept more stable than the economy of<br />
any other country in the world. It must be remembered that an important<br />
part of the machinery for maintaining that stability has been the<br />
control over the banking system exercised under the 1945 banking<br />
legislation and that an essential part of that legislation is the special<br />
account procedure. The difficulties of the transition from war to peace<br />
are far from over. In fact, in some directions they are increasing.<br />
The rapid exhaustion of the United States loan to Britain has confronted<br />
the sterling area-and many other countries as well-with serious<br />
balance of payments problems and this is only one aspect of a general<br />
situation which is highly unstable. </p>
<p>" To deal with the economic and financial problems both of the<br />
transition period and of the following years, the Government must have<br />
the necessary powers over banking and monetary policy. Fluctuations<br />
in business activity and employment are not solely due to monetary<br />
causes, but they are certainly greatly influenced by financial policy.<br />
The Government would not be justified in gambling on the outcome of<br />
possible threats to the 1945 legislation. The structure of banking based<br />
on the legislation of 1945 went part of the way towards the objectives<br />
which the Labour party has long advocated in regard to banking. At<br />
the same time it offered to the private banks the opportunity to cooperate<br />
within a national system of banking, subject to overall control<br />
by the Commonwealth Bank, as they had, in fact, done during the war<br />
period. That position was never accepted without reservation by the<br />
private banks and now that the legal foundations of the system have<br />
been challenged the Government has decided to proceed with its longstanding<br />
policy of full public ownership.<br />
The bill which is before the House gives effect to the Government's<br />
decision. Before the Attorney-General ( Dr. Evatt) left Australia, he<br />
gave close attention to the legal and constitutional aspects of the bill,<br />
and laid down the main lines on which the preparation of the measure<br />
has proceeded. I would emphasize that under this measure there will be no interruption<br />
or disturbance of the usual banking facilities available to the<br />
Australian community. The bill provides that the private banks shall<br />
maintain their services until they are taken over by the Commonwealth<br />
Bank. As the banks are taken over, either through the acquisition of<br />
their shares or of their assets, they will be kept in operation as going<br />
concerns. Customers will not notice any difference after the control<br />
of the bank with which they have been dealing has passed to the Commonwealth<br />
Bank. They will be able to continue their banking business<br />
without change or interruption.<br />
" The bill imposes on the Commonwealth Bank an obligation to<br />
conduct its banking transactions in accordance with the practices and<br />
usages customary among bankers particularly in regard to the nondisclosure<br />
of information concerning the affairs of its customers. The<br />
confidential nature of the relationship between banker and customer is<br />
well established in law; and, subject to certain exceptions sanctioned<br />
or required by law, bankers are under an obligation of secrecy with<br />
respect to their customers' affairs. The bill specifically provides that<br />
this position will be preserved.<br />
" Differences between the constitutions of the various private banks<br />
and the fact that some are incorporated in Australia and some overseas<br />
make it desirable to provide alternative ways in which the Commonwealth<br />
Bank may acquire their business. Accordingly the bill provides<br />
for two main processes of acquisition-<br />
Voluntary or compulsory acquisition of the Australian business and<br />
assets of the private banks, or<br />
Compulsory acquisition of shares. </p>
<p>" The first could be applied to all banks, whether incorporated in<br />
Australia or overseas, and in the case of banks incorporated in. Australia,<br />
any part of their overseas assets may also be acquired compulsorily.<br />
Under the alternative procees, the shares of a private hank<br />
may be conmpulsorily acquired if the Treasurer is satisfied that the<br />
majority of its shares are registered in Australia. This process would<br />
be applied only to banks9 incorporated in Australia, and would be the<br />
initial step towards an eventual transfer of their business to the Commonwealth<br />
Bank. As a preliminary step to tb' acquisition of the<br />
business of a ) rivate bank, provision is m-ade for the Treasurer, by due<br />
notice, to invite the private bank to make an agreement with the Cornrnonweal'h<br />
Bank for the transfer of its business on a specified date,<br />
which must be not more than two months later than the date on which<br />
the notice is given. If an agreement for the transfer of the business of<br />
a private bank, which is willing to negotiate, is not completed by the<br />
specified date, the Treasurer may -extend the currency of the notice<br />
until agreement is reached. Agreement must, however, be reached-if<br />
there is to be agreement at all-before the notice expires. Once the notice<br />
expires, the assets of the bank concerned forthwith becomes vested in,<br />
and its liabilities are assumed by, the Commonwealth Bank. There is<br />
nothing in the bill to prevent the Commonwealth Bank from reaching<br />
an agreement with a private bank for the acquisition of its business<br />
before any notice is issued at all; but all agreements, whether made<br />
before or after notice is given, will be subject to the approval of the<br />
Treasurer. The bill also includes a provision whereby the Treasurer<br />
may, after the business of a private bank is acquired by the Commonwealth<br />
Bank, require that private bank to cease carrying on further<br />
banking business in Au-tralia.<br />
" If a private bank enters into a voluntary agreement for the<br />
acquisition of its business by the Commonwealth Bank, it will be<br />
entitled to receive an exemption from taxation on the amount paid to it<br />
in pursuance of the agreement. It is further provided in the bill that<br />
shareholders of the bank will be exempt from taxation on any dividend<br />
or distribution which directly results from the payment received from<br />
the Commonwealth Bank under the agreement. These concessions will<br />
not apply in the case of a compulsory acquisition. The exemptions<br />
referred to will not relieve the private bank from liability for any tax<br />
payable by the bank in respect of profits derived in the normal course<br />
of its business but upon which the ordinary tax liability has not been<br />
met. The bank and its shareholders will still be liable to taxation in<br />
relation to profits earned after the year of income ended 30' h June, 1947,<br />
or any accounting period substituted therefore, and before the date of<br />
transfer, or in relation to any interest which may become payable under<br />
the agreement. If shares are acquired by voluntary purchase, the price paid by<br />
the Commonwealth Bank must not be less than the market value in<br />
Australia of those shares at 15th August, 1947. These prices have been </p>
<p>carefully ascertained and are specified. The provision iinade for the<br />
compulsory acquisition of shares will apply only to the share.-of private<br />
banks incorporated in Australia, which are the institutions referred to<br />
in Part I. of the First Schedule to the bill. Where the majority in<br />
number of the shares of any of these banks are situated in Australia,<br />
the bill provides that the Treasurer may, by notice published in the<br />
Gazette, declare that the shares in the bank concerned shall be vested<br />
in the Commonwealth Bank on a date specified by the Treasurer; and<br />
on that date the Commonwealth Bank will, by force of the legislation,<br />
become the holder (, othfe shares and a: m ember of the bank in question.<br />
" It is provided that the directors of an Australian private bank,<br />
the shares of which have Leen compulsorily acquired by the Commonwealth<br />
Bank, will cease to hold office on the date on which the compulsory<br />
acquisition becomes effective. The Governor of th
Bank will, with the approval of the Treasurer, thereupon appoint<br />
directors, including a chairman of directors. The directors appointed<br />
by the Governor of the Commonwealth Bank will have full power to<br />
manage the bank in question, to dispose of its business in Australia<br />
to the Commonwealth Bank and to dispose also of the bank's business<br />
outside Australia: but any arrangement for disposal may only be concluded<br />
if approved by the Treasurer after he has received a reccommendation<br />
from the Governor of the Commonwealth Bank.<br />
For all property or shares of the banks, conmpulsorily acqtuiredl. fair<br />
and reasonable compensation will be payable. The compensation<br />
payable may be determined by agreement, approved by the Treasurcr<br />
or, failing agreement, the amount payable will be determined by th: e<br />
court of claims to be established under the proposed legislation. The<br />
bill sets out the procedure to be followed in reaching agreement or,<br />
alternatively, in referring claims to the court for determination. The<br />
bill provides for the establishment of a Federal Court of Claims consisting<br />
of a Chief Judge and such other judges as are appointed. The<br />
court may, if it thinks fit, appoint two assessors to assist it. The court<br />
will have jurisdiction to hear and determine claims for compensation<br />
arising under this bill. Regulations may be made under other acts<br />
also to confer jurisdiction on the court to determine claims arising out<br />
of the operation of those acts. The jurisdiction of the court in respect<br />
of compensation under this hill must be exercised by not. less than<br />
three judges. Jurisdiction may, however, be exercised by less than<br />
three judges by agreement between the parties concerned. A determination<br />
of the court will be final and conclusive and not subject to appeal<br />
to the High Court.<br />
" The bill makes provision for the protection of officers of private<br />
banks in respect of continuance of employment, salaries and conditions<br />
of service. The bill provides that when the Commonwicalth Bank </p>
<p>proceeds by way of acquisition of the shares of a private bank, the<br />
salary and general conditions of service of officers of the private bank<br />
will not be disturbed, and will be secured to them. Similarly, when<br />
the Commonwealth Bank takes over the assets of a private bank,<br />
including the assets of a bank whose shares have previously been<br />
acquired, each officer of the private bank who was employed in the<br />
service of that bank in Australia will be entitled to be employed by<br />
the Commonwealth Bank at the salary and on the general conditions of<br />
service applicable to his existing employment. The Commonwealth<br />
Bank will be obliged to appoint each such officer, being a . British<br />
subject, to an appropriate position in the Commonwealth Bank Service.<br />
This will be done as soon as practicable after employment commences<br />
with" the Commonwealth Bank. Special provision also is made to enable<br />
that service to absorb all officers stationed ou'side Australia whose duties<br />
are connected with the Australian business. It will be seen that during<br />
the period necessarily elapsing between the date of acquisition of a<br />
private bank, either by way of shares or assets of the private bank, and<br />
the date when an officer of that bank is appointed to an appropriate<br />
position in the Commonwealth Bank Service, he is fully safeguarded.<br />
He will continue to be employed with salary, pension benefits, and sick<br />
and long service leave at least as favorable as when in the employ of<br />
the private bank. When later appointed to the Commonwealth Bank<br />
Service, he will enjoy all the rights and privileges of an officer of that<br />
service, with protection in respect of existing salary, pension benefits,<br />
and sick and long service leave. Service in the private bank, continuous<br />
with service with the Commonwealth Bank, will count as service with<br />
the Commonwealth Bank for purposes of promotion, leave and pensions.<br />
To establish an officer's present entitlement to pension benefits and<br />
sick and long service leave, the bill provides for the appointment of a<br />
committee in respect of each private bank affected, consisting of a judge<br />
( or a person qualified to be a judge), an officer of the Commonwealth<br />
Bank, and a representative of the bank officers concerned, to ascertain<br />
the benefits which are, or woul'd have been granted in accordance with<br />
the practice of the private bank concerned, or of the superannuation<br />
fund of that bank. The findings of this committee will then become a<br />
legally enforceable right in respect of the future employment of these<br />
nfficers even though they may not have at present any such legal protection.<br />
The industrial awards now governing the employment of persons<br />
in private banks will continue in force until appointment to the Commonwealth<br />
Bank Service is made. Further, during this period, officers<br />
will continue to have the right to apply to the appropriate tribunal for<br />
variations of these awards. On appointment to the Commonwealth<br />
Bank they will have the same rights in respect of industrial matters as<br />
. lr, now enjoyed by officers of the Commonwealth Bank.<br />
The Commonwealth Bank is recognized as a good employer. On<br />
ihe whole the general conditions of employment in its service are at<br />
least as good as, if not better than, those generally provided by the </p>
<p>private banks. Its employees are given special legal protection as to<br />
promotion, dismissal and disciplinary action. Under Part XIII. of<br />
the Commonwealth Bank Act promotion and disciplinary appeal boards<br />
have been constituted. Those boards, which are under an independent<br />
chairman and include representatives of employees, are empowered to<br />
give final decisions on appeals relating, respectively, to the promotion<br />
and to the punishment, dismissal or reduction in status of officers.<br />
Such rights of appeal . are not at present enjoyed by employees of the<br />
private banks. The changed conditions of the expanded Commonwealth<br />
Bank will, of courst, render it necessary to examine the provisions of<br />
the Commonwealth Bank Act relating to the Commonwealth Bank<br />
Service, and any amendments considered desirable to -meet the position<br />
will be brought forward at an early date.<br />
" With regard to former officers of the private banks who have<br />
retired on pensions from the private banks' services, their position, as<br />
well as that of dependants of deceased officers, is also fully safeguarded.<br />
The Commonwealth Bank will assume responsibility for the payment<br />
of pensions in accordance with existing rights, which will be converted<br />
into legally enforceable claims. As the Commonwealth Bank is required<br />
to assume liability for pensions, both in respect of retired officers and<br />
officers now serving, it is necessary that an appropriate amount of the<br />
superannuation funds established in association with the private banks<br />
to meet these obligations should be transferred to the Commonwealth<br />
Bank. The bill contains the necessary provisions to give effect to this<br />
requirement. " There will be no necessity for a parliamentary appropriation to<br />
provide for compcnsation. In acquiring the business of the private<br />
banks the Commonwealth Bank will also assume the liabilities of these<br />
institutions. The amount of compensation payable will necessarily<br />
have regard to this factor and it will be well within the capacity of the<br />
Commonwealth Bank to meet the payment from its own resources. The<br />
Commonwealth Bank will make payment in cash or government bhond<br />
as desired. " As I have said before, the Government believes that a publicly<br />
owned and controlled banking system, in which final responsibility for<br />
policy is in the hands of a government directly responsible to the<br />
electors, conforms much more closely to the luirements of a democratic<br />
community than the system advocated in 1945 by Mr. Menzieis,<br />
who, with his party, is pledged to restore control of banking and<br />
monetary policy to a body having no responsibility to the electors.<br />
In most advanced countries there has been during recent years a<br />
strong trend towards public ownership of key public utilities. This<br />
trend has not been confined to governments, representing particular<br />
political parties. Such projects have been brought forward both in<br />
Australia and elsewhere not only by Labour governments but also by </p>
<p>non-Labour ' go vernments who recognized that in the circumstances of<br />
the case the balance of advantages from the community standpoint lies<br />
in national rather than private ownership and control. But if any<br />
service fits the description of a key public utility it is banking. As I<br />
have said earlier, no element in the working of our economy has a<br />
greater influence for good or ev-il upon economic and social welfare<br />
than the management of money and credit.<br />
" The Government is convinced that under public ownership the<br />
banking system will have immense opportunities for serving Australia.<br />
It will have the backing of the entire credit resources of the nation. It<br />
will be free from the cramping limitations of sectional private ownership<br />
which bid the private banks to serve this interest but not that<br />
interest, and to judge all business from the narrow standpoint of maximu-<br />
m profits for the smallest outlay. It will be able to take longer-term<br />
views of projects requiring finance and, since the whole Australian<br />
economy will be its field, it will have the widest scope for initiative<br />
and for the spread of its investments.<br />
" Essentially tile task of the new organization will be to provide<br />
a financial mechanism appropriate to the needs of our rapidly growing<br />
economy. Australia is destined to see great developments in the coming<br />
years and this process, which is already under way, must be promoted<br />
by every every means possible. There will be a great increase in our<br />
population. Industries will expand in all fields and we must extend our<br />
markets abroad. The basic services of transport and communications,<br />
water supply, power, housing, health and education must be enlarged to<br />
meet the needs of a larger economy working at higher levels of technique<br />
and productivity. The stress everywhere will be upon new forms of<br />
enterpris e, new methodi of production, and new uses for the resourceis<br />
of this country. Finance must co-operate and take the initiative in<br />
this progress. As new types of industry are developed, new types of<br />
finance will be required and the banking system s-hould anticipate these<br />
needs and be in the field with the right kind of facilities to assist and<br />
encourage such development.<br />
Moreover, there can be no doubt that a bank should be more than<br />
a mere money lender. A banking system created to serve the welfare of<br />
the community can aid industry by the quality of its advice and the<br />
incidental services it renders as well as by the financial accommodation<br />
it provides. Hence the Government sets particular store on the developmnent<br />
of these ancillary services, It has in view the building up of a<br />
highly qualified staff that will enable the Commonwealth Bank to give<br />
skilled advice as part of its banking service. Secondary industries, for<br />
exa'mpkc, will be able to turn to the bank for the assistance of prodnction<br />
engineers and cost accountants to help them with their problems.<br />
Primary industries will have the aid of agricultural experts. I contemplate,<br />
too, that the Bank would establish, at least in the capital cities,<br />
departments of advice which would help individuals with their daily<br />
financial problems. Whiether any charge would have to be made by the </p>
<p>bank would naturally depend on the circumstances of each case but<br />
as far as possible these facilities would be provided freely as part of a<br />
Ftrengthened banking service.<br />
" But if the financial system is to meet these requirements it tmust<br />
be comprehensive, strong and flexible. It must be alive to the requirements<br />
of the times and be capable of seeing ahead. It must have one<br />
goal for its policies and one standard for its work-the service of the<br />
nation in all its interests, great or small. The Government believes that<br />
only under a national system of banking can this ideal be approached.<br />
Only under such a system will finance be a real servant of industry and<br />
not its master.<br />
" Fears are being spread by opponents of this measure that the<br />
people will lose an advantage by reason of having only one bank to<br />
deal with instead of a choice between several banks. This brings up the<br />
question of competition between the private banks-how far it exists<br />
and what it has been worth to the community and to customers of the<br />
banks. The Banking Commission went into this question of competition<br />
at great length. It found that the private banks did not compete in any<br />
serious way as regards interest rates and other charges but sought rather<br />
to attract customers by offering various other inducements. In general,<br />
they behaved in the manner of semi-monopolistic institutions which<br />
stood in fear of ruining their own market. There was certainly nothinglike<br />
the all-out rivalry to give the public the widest and cheapest services<br />
which we are asked to suppose exists between them. Amalgamations on<br />
the other hand have reduced the number of banks, so accentuating the<br />
monopolistic character of those that remain. There are to-day really no<br />
more than eight trading banks doing a nation-wide business where<br />
years ago there were twenty, -and we have no reason to suppose that this<br />
process would not go further if private banking continued. The average<br />
man, I suggest, will find it hard to believe that fewer banks mean greater<br />
competition. We recall how the former Commonwealth Bank Board, which<br />
considered itself to be conducting a bankers' bank, prevented the Commonwealth<br />
Bank from competing with the private institutions. We<br />
have the admissions of private bankers that competition between themselves<br />
is of a limited kind. We have seen the number of banks dwindling<br />
over the pears, each amalgamation removing one or more possible<br />
competitors from the ring. It is a fair conclusion, I think, that from<br />
the standpoint of benefit to the community, banking competition has<br />
meant little for some time past and would probably have meant less as<br />
time went on. On the other hand, I may point out that the Commonwealth<br />
Bank is charged under the legislation to be strictly impartial as<br />
between customers and to avoid all discrimination. A system of appeal<br />
will be provided so that a person who considers he has not had reasonable<br />
treatment from a local manager will be a'ble to refer his case to<br />
regional authority for reconsideration. Special arrangements will be </p>
<p>: made to ensure that this re-con. sileration is given without delay. In<br />
view of these considerations, therefore, it appears to me that the advantages<br />
of having a choice between several private banks as compared with<br />
. a single national bank are largely illusory.<br />
The proposal to take over the banks is being condemned in some<br />
quarters in recklessly extravagant terms; all kinds of hidden purposes<br />
are being wrongly ascribed to it from the same sources. The simple<br />
truth is this-the reasons and motives for this measure and the uses to<br />
which it can and will be applied are no more and no less than I have<br />
stated. The opponents of banking change seems always to have fought<br />
against new developments while belatedly approving such changes as<br />
have been made and which they had originally opposed. In 1937 they<br />
criticized the Banking Commission Report and defended the old<br />
syst-em. In 1945 they nailed their colours to the Banking Report and<br />
resisted implacably the legislation of that year. Now they seem disposed<br />
to make the 1945 legislation their rallying cry whilst preparing<br />
themselves once again to die in the last ditch against a new, logical<br />
and necessary developmen'. Their predictions of calamity will prove<br />
just as groundless as those they have expressed so many times before.<br />
There has been no political interference in banking under the 1945<br />
legislation and there will be none under the new system. In not one<br />
instance since that legislation was passed has the Government intervened<br />
in the administration of the Commonwealth Bank. Within the<br />
framework of the broad economic and financial policy laid down by<br />
the Government the bank has carried on its work successfully and harmnoniously.<br />
On broad policy issues it has in turn advised the Government<br />
and been advised by the Government. Conflict has not arisen at<br />
any stage. It is timely to record that under section 9 of the Commonwealth<br />
Bank Act 1945 the Government cannot interfere in the internal<br />
transactions of the bank. Its power is limited to the laying down where<br />
necessary of the broad lines of monetary and banking policy. Business<br />
people and private citizens will have all the safeguards as to the conduct<br />
of their banking business which can be given by law and by the<br />
long and honorable administrative tradition of the Commonwealth<br />
Bank. On acquisition of a bank, shareholders are assured of just compensation,<br />
bank employees are protected, depositors are guaranteed and<br />
business will be carried on without interruption.<br />
Full public ownership of the banks will ensure control of banking<br />
in the public interest. It will enable effective steps to be taken against<br />
the dangers of secondary inflation. It will assist us to stave off depres-<br />
. sion and to avoid a repetition of the miseries of 1930. Beyond this, it<br />
will o0 : nu a lung-locked doorway to the development of a monetary and<br />
banking system truly adequate to our national requirements and wholly<br />
devoted to the service of Australia [ The bill was passed. </p>
<p>NORTHERN TERRITORY.<br />
CIVIL ADMINISTRATION-LEGISLATIVE COUNCIL<br />
ELECTIONS.<br />
On 15th October, 1947, the Minister for the Interior ( Mr. Johnson)<br />
announced that elections for the Northern Territory Legislative<br />
Council would be held on 13th December, 1947.<br />
( For earlier reference, please see No. 126, page 33.)<br />
COMMUNIST PARTY.<br />
PRIME MINISTER'S STATEMENT.<br />
In Parliament.-On 15th October, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr..<br />
Chifley) said:-<br />
" I understand that members of the Opposition last week pressed<br />
for an inquiry into Communist activities in Australia. It is true that<br />
similar proposals have been made before. The fact is that the Commonwealth<br />
Investigation Service keeps under close observation all who<br />
might be guilty of subversive activity. They include not only Communists<br />
but also other persons whose activities might be detrimental<br />
to the interests of this country. Nothing has been disclosed to date<br />
that would warrant the appointment of a royal commission or any<br />
other body to make a special inquiry. Should such an occasion arise as<br />
the results of reports received regarding any section of the community<br />
or any individual, the necessary action will he taken."<br />
BRITAIN.<br />
PRINCESS ELIZABETH-WEDDING PRESENT.<br />
On 16th October, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said:--<br />
" The gift from the Commonwealth Government to Princess<br />
Elizabeth on the occasion of her marriage to Lieutenant Philip.<br />
Mountbatten, will be in the form of silver plate, comprising a<br />
pair of comports and a pair of salvers. The salvers will be hand-chased<br />
with pierced border of wattle design, on three hand-pierced feet. The.<br />
Commonwealth Coat of Arms will be inlaid in gold on the comports<br />
and inscribed on the salvers. The gift will be despatched by air to.<br />
the Minister for External Affairs ( Dr. Evatt) at London for presentation<br />
to Her Royal Highness."<br />
FINANCIAL POLICY-DOLLAR IMPORTS, ESSENTIAL<br />
GOODS.<br />
On 30th October, 1947, the Minister for Customs ( Senator<br />
Courtice) said that import licences for goods of dollar area origin would<br />
be confirmed only if the goods were in transit on 21st October, 1947,<br />
or if they were covered by an irrevocable credit or if they were determined<br />
by his department to be essential to the Australian economy. </p>
<p>Goods which the department considered had a high degree of essentiality<br />
and in respect of which outstanding import licences would be confirmed<br />
were-Cotton yarn, rayoi yarn, sewing threads, tyre cord, tyre cord fabric, elastic<br />
piece goods for the nanufacture of corsetry, rubber thread, uncovered, for use in<br />
the manufacture of elastics, paper pulp send waste paper for use in the manufacture<br />
of paper, writing and printing paper, costing 15 cents or less per lb.<br />
in respect of which evidence was available that shipment ex mill would<br />
be effected on or before 30th November, 1947, timber ior construction work and<br />
boxmaking, ball and roller bearings, high silicon steel sheets provided evidence<br />
was available that shipment ex mill would be effected on or before 31st March,<br />
1948, hand or tenon carpenters' saws, wood bits, carpenters' chisels, felts and<br />
wire for paper-making machines, card wire for use in the textile industry, wood<br />
turpentine, pine oil, caustic soda, soda ash, chemical re-agents for flotation<br />
processes in gold-mining, carbon black, chemicals, rubber accelerators and antioxidants,<br />
for use in the processing of rubber. chemicals for use in the tanning<br />
of leather, asbestos fibre , um or wood resins, solvents for use in the manufacture<br />
of paints, enamels and lacquers ( but not including toilet preparations), motor<br />
vehicle chassis provide evidence was available that shipment ex factory would<br />
be effected by 31st December, 1947, replacemeit parts for motor vehicles, food<br />
processing equipment, marine engines, mining machinery for gold or coal-mining,<br />
oil boring plant, tractors, wheel and crawler types,. provided evidence was available<br />
that shipment ex factory would be effected on or before 31st December, 1947,<br />
. and replacement parts, electric motors and replacement parts.<br />
( For earlier references, please gee No. 129, page 27; No. 130, page 9.)<br />
PRICES.<br />
GOODS " DECLARED "-HAY, CHAFF, REVOCATION.<br />
On 17th October, 1947, the Minister for Customs ( Senator<br />
Courtice) said that hay and chaff had been removed from price control.<br />
INDUSTRIAL.<br />
ARBITRATION SYSTEM-CONCILIATION<br />
COMMISSIONERS.<br />
On 20th October, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
" Cabinet decided to-day to appoint the president of the New South<br />
Wales branch of the Australian Railways Union ( Mr. L. P. Austin),<br />
the general secretary of the Australian Federal Union of Locomotive<br />
Enginemen ( Mr. J. M. Galvin), and the New South Wales Minister for<br />
Labour and Industry ( Mr. Hamilton Knight) as conciliation commissioners<br />
under the Commonwealth Conciliation and Arbitration Act."<br />
( For earlier reference, please see No. 129, page 6.)<br />
[ Messrs. R. H. Beers. N. Roberts and W. Wallwork, who were appointed<br />
on 15th August. 1947, resigned.]<br />
UNEMPLOYMENT-FIGURES.<br />
-On 29th October, 1947, the Minister for Labour ( Mr. Holloway)<br />
said that the demand for labour in Australia continued to rise and the<br />
level of unemployment to fall. At September, 1947, the number of<br />
recipients of unemployment benefit had fallen to the new record low<br />
level of 3,465 ( 3,335 males and 130 females). Unfilled vacancies held<br />
by the Commonwealth Employment Service numbered 80,500 ( 47,300<br />
: males and 33,200 females), over 4,000 greater than at August, 1947. </p>
<p>During September, 1947, the Commonwealthl Employment Service.<br />
had referred 20,500 males and 7,300 females to employers. In addition,.<br />
advice and information on employment and other problems had been<br />
given to 26,800 males and 5,600 females.<br />
HEALTH.<br />
DIRECTOR-GENERAL--APPOINTMENT.<br />
On 20th October, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
Cabinet to-day decided to appoint Dr. A. J. Metcalfe as Commonwealth<br />
Director-General of Health."<br />
CIVIL AVIATION.<br />
INTERNAL ROUTES-AUSTRALIAN NATIONAL AIRLINES,<br />
ACT, AMENDMENT.<br />
On 20th October, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
Cabinet decided to-day that legislation . be prepared for submission:<br />
to the Federal Parliamentary Labour party to amend the Australian<br />
National Airlines Act to permit Trans-Australia Airlines to engage in<br />
intra-state operations in Queensland in addition to intra-state operations<br />
which a'e incidental to interstate and territorial services. At the.<br />
conference of Commonwealth and State Ministers in August, 1947, the<br />
Premier of Queensland ( Mr. Hanlon) intimated that his Government<br />
was in favour of the Commonwealth airlines operating air services in-<br />
Queensland." ( For earlier references, please see No. 105, page 38; No. 129, page 19.)<br />
AUSTRALIAN WAR MEMORIAL.<br />
NATIONAL WAR MEMORIALS-TOBRUK.<br />
On 20th October, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Ohifley) said-<br />
" In September, 1947, Cabinet considered a recommendation fromu<br />
the Australian Battlefields Memorial Committee that an Australian delegation<br />
proceed to the Middle East to unveil a memorial in Tobruk war<br />
cemetery. Cabinet decided that the committee's recommendations be referred<br />
back for further consideration.<br />
Cabinet decided to-day that the Australian delegation should comprise<br />
a member selected by the Commonwealth Government and a<br />
representative of each of the Australian Battlefields Memorial Committee,<br />
Returned Sailors, , Soldiers and Airmen's Imperial League of.<br />
Australia, and the Rats of Tobruk Association. If possible, the Government's<br />
representative will be Lieutenant-General Sir Leslie<br />
Morshead, who commanded the Australian forces during the seige of<br />
Tobruk. All members of the delegation will be returned servicemen<br />
and, at the conclusion of the ceremony at Tobruk, the delegation will<br />
proceed to Gallipoli on a tour of Australian war memorials and war<br />
graves-the first official visit since 1924." </p>
<p>27<br />
EXTERNAL COMMUN ICATIONS.<br />
TELE-COMMUNIOATIONS--INTERNA TIONAL RADIO<br />
BOARD.<br />
On 20th October, 1947, the Postmaster-General ( Senator Cameron)<br />
: announced that, as a result of decisions reached by international tele-<br />
* communications conferences recently held at Atlantic City, an<br />
international board would be established ' at Geneva to deal with the<br />
-orderly registration of radio frequencies throughout -the world to meet<br />
radio communication requirements generally. The International Frequency<br />
Registration Board would be a highly specialized body responsible<br />
for the study of the purposes and technical characteristics of each<br />
; radio-frequency assignment necessary for application in the radiocommunication<br />
sphere, with a view to ensuring formal international<br />
, recognition thereof. The board would render advice to 80 member<br />
countries of the International Tele-communications Union to secure the<br />
-operation of the maximum practicable number of radio channels in<br />
those portions of the spectrum where international interference might<br />
occur. The board would consist of eleven members including Australia.<br />
The Chief Research Engineer of the Postmaster-General's Depa-rtment<br />
( Mr. S. H. Witt) would be Australia's representative on the board<br />
mentioned. ,( For earlier references, please see No. 116, page 17; No. 123, page 3.)<br />
DEFENCE.<br />
SCIENCE CONFERENCE, 1947.<br />
' On 20th October, 1947, the Minister for Defence Dedman)<br />
announced that Australia would be represented at a meeting at London<br />
in November, 1947, of British and Dominion representatives on defence<br />
science by the chairman of -the New Weapons and Equipment Development<br />
Committee ( Major-General L. E. Beavis), the Controller-General<br />
of Munitions Supply, Department of Munitions ( Mr. N. K. S.<br />
Brodribb), Brigadier H. S. Nurse and the Professor of Physics at<br />
Melbourne University ( Professor L. F. Martin).<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 114, page 7.)<br />
PARLIAMENT.<br />
MEMBERS' ALLOWANCES-PARTY LEADERS, BILL<br />
INTRODUCED.<br />
In Parliamnent.-On 21st October, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr.<br />
Chifley) introduced the Parliamentary Allowances Bill ( No. Mr.<br />
Chifley) said-<br />
" Parliamentary Allowances Act makes provision for the payment<br />
' of annual allowances to the Leaders of the Opposition in both Houses<br />
-of the Parliament as some recompense for the onerous nature of their<br />
duties. When the act was under consideration in this House in June,<br />
1947, I gave an undertaking that T would consider the submission to </p>
<p>Parliament during this sessional period of a bill to provide for the , payment,<br />
as from 1st July, 1947, of an annual allowance to the Leader of<br />
the Australian Country party for the same purpose. This bill is in<br />
consequence of that promise." [ The bill was passed.<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 126, page 7; No. 127, page 34.)<br />
SERVICE PAY RATES.<br />
REPATRIATION-PATRIOTIC FUNDS.<br />
In Parliament.-On 21st October, 1947, the Minister for Repatriation<br />
( Mr. Barnard) introduced the Australian Soldiers' Repatriation<br />
Bill. Mr. Barnard said-<br />
The bill is to bring provisions for control of patriotic funds under<br />
the Australian Soldiers' Repatriation Act. The existing . provisions are<br />
National . Security ( Patriotic Funds) Regulations under the Defence-<br />
( Transitional Provisions) Act. The main activities of the funds are<br />
diminishing, and many have already been wound up, but others are<br />
continuing their ordinary operations, and will eventually go through<br />
the winding-up stage. Altogether, it is probable that, in some -form or<br />
another, activities will continue for some time yet. It is therefore<br />
desirable that the provisions be removed from the Defence ( Transitional<br />
Provisions) Act. They are administered by the Minister for<br />
Repatriation and the Repatriation Commission, and the logical place<br />
for them is in the repatriation legislation. The bill inserts a section<br />
in the Repatriation Act to enable the Governor-General to make the<br />
necessary regulations under that act. National Security ( Patriotic<br />
Funds) Regulations will be repealed, and the new regulations in the<br />
Australian Soldiers' Repatriation Regulations will . be generally on the<br />
same lines as those under which control has * been exercised up till now."<br />
[ The bill was passed.<br />
HOUSING.<br />
WAR SERVICE HOMES-PRIORITY.<br />
On 22nd October, 1947, the Minister -for Works and Housing ( Mr.<br />
Lemmon) said that following the recent amendment to the War Service<br />
Homes Act to enable a building programme to be undertaken it had<br />
been necessary to meet changed circumstances resulting from greatly<br />
increased demand for materials. The new procedure provided for the<br />
determination of priority for building war service homes on the basis<br />
of need. Applicants who had been requested by the War Service<br />
Homes Commission to pay preliminary fees or arrange for the preparation<br />
of plans and specifications by a private architect under the<br />
previous priority system would be finalized under that system, but the<br />
priority of all other applications would be decided in accordance with'<br />
the new policy of determining priority on a needs basis.<br />
( For earlier references, plea ; e see No. 128, page 33.) </p>
<p>RECONSTRUCT ION.<br />
TRADE AND EMPLOYMENT-HAVANA CONFERENCE.<br />
On 28th October, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
" Cabinet to-day approved acceptance of the invitation to the<br />
World Trade Conference which opens at Havana on 21st November,<br />
1947. The Leader of the Australian delegation will be the Minister for<br />
Post-war Reconstruction ( Mr. Dedman) and the delegation will comprise<br />
the Director-General of Post-war Reconstruction ( Dr. H. C.<br />
Coombs), the Secretary of the Department of Commerce and Agriculture<br />
( Mr. E. McCarthy), the Assistant Comptroller-General of Customs<br />
( Mr. C. E. Morton), the Commercial Counsellor, Australian Embassy,<br />
Washington ( Mr. J. U. Garside), Messrs. J. G. Phillips of the Commonwealth<br />
Bank's London office ( representing the Treasury), G. A.<br />
Rattigan ( Department of Trade and Customs), C. L. Hewitt ( Departinent<br />
of Post-war Reconstruction) and G. W. Smith ( Department of<br />
Commerce and Agriculture).<br />
" The work of the conference will be concerned mainly with the<br />
consideration of a draft charter for an International Trade Organization.<br />
This draft charter has been drawn up by a preparatory Committee<br />
of eighteen countries, including Australia, which was set up by<br />
the Economic and Social Council for the purpose early in 1946. The<br />
preparatory committee has had two sessions-at London towards the<br />
end of 1946 and more recently at Geneva. A special drafting cominittee<br />
examined the text evolved at London before the full committee<br />
reconsidered it at Geneva. The draft charter will now come before the<br />
representatives of other countries which were not represented earlier.<br />
If the work of the world conference is successful and sufficient<br />
governments adopt the draft charter, the establishment of an International<br />
Trade Organization, guided : by the principles of the charter,<br />
should follow in due course."<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 122, page 30; No. 124, page 5; No. 125,<br />
page 9; No. 126, page 21; No. 127, page 3; No. 129, page<br />
TRADE AND EMPLOYMENT-PREPARATORY COMMITTEE,<br />
MINISTER'S STATEMENT.<br />
In Parliament.-On 29th October, 1947, the Minister for Post-war<br />
Reconstruction ( Mr. Dedman) said-<br />
" 1 make a brief statement in relation to tariff negotiations at<br />
Geneva in which an Australian delegation has been engaged for some<br />
time. Since April, 1947, the delegation has been conducting negotiations<br />
with the re. presentatives of seventeen other countries for the<br />
readjustment of tariffs and preferences on a mutually advantageous<br />
basis. These negotiations have reached finality and the results are<br />
being incorporated in a draft general agreement on tariff and trade </p>
<p>which is to be laid before the governments concerned for their consideration.<br />
The large number of countries concerned involves certain practical<br />
difficulties which have to be overcome. In the first place, it is<br />
virtually impossible to keep proposed tariff changes completely confidential<br />
for an indefinite period. Publication of the results in one<br />
country before release in another could be very embarrassing.<br />
Moreover, if the published rates differed from those at present<br />
in force complications would arise because of the desire of<br />
traders to wait for lower rates of duty. Further, the several<br />
countries concerned have a variety of procedures for putting trade agreements<br />
into force. To overcome those difficulties, a method has been<br />
devised to provide for the simultaneous publication of the draft general<br />
agreement on tariffs -and trade, and for the provisional application<br />
of that agreement by the governments concerned. The countries concerned<br />
may, instead of adopting the agreement outright, agree to apply.<br />
provisionally, its provisions, including the tariff schedules. Their legislatures<br />
will then -be able to examine the agreement and decide whether<br />
or not it should be adopted.<br />
Provided the requisite number of governments concur and notify<br />
the Secretary-General of the United Nations by 15th November, 1947,<br />
that they are prepared to adopt, provisionally, the draft agreement, the<br />
text will -be published on 18th November, 1947.<br />
The Australian Government believes that the proposed agreement<br />
will prove advantageous to Australia. Accordingly, it has decided to<br />
accept and . apply, provisionally, the draft general agreement on tariffs<br />
and trade. The following procedure will be followed: On 30th October,<br />
1947, the final act of the Geneva conference will be signed for the purpose<br />
of authenticating the text of the draft general agreement. On or<br />
before 15th November, 1947, the Government will inform the Secretary-<br />
General of the United Nations that it is prepared to accept and apply,<br />
provisionally, the general agreement on tariffs and trade. On 18th<br />
November, 1947, if the requisite number of governments have decided<br />
to accept the general agreement on tariffs and trade provisionally, the<br />
agreement will be published simultaneously in the countries concerned.<br />
On that date, the Australia -Government will lay the agreement on the<br />
table of the House, and introduce the necessary tariff motion. The new<br />
rates will become operative provisionally from that date.<br />
Later, after conclusion of the Havana conference and within six<br />
months of the tabling of the draft agreement, the Government will<br />
decide whether Parliament is to be asked to confirm the agreement and.<br />
if it so decides, will seek Parliament's approval for this course.<br />
A statement on all phases of the Geneva conference will be made to<br />
the House later in this session. For reasons I have outlined, it is not<br />
possible, before the date agreed on for publication, to give any details<br />
of the concessions made. However, I can assure the House that the<br />
Government is convinced that the draft agreement will create new<br />
export opportunities of great value to Australia. Throughout the </p>
<p>negotiations the Government has maintained the closest collaboration<br />
with other members of the British Conunonwealth. The agreement<br />
takes full account of the legitimate interests of both . primary and<br />
secondary industries in this country; and, in relation to imperial preferences,<br />
the agreement conforms to the policy enunciated ' by the Government<br />
from time to time in this House.<br />
Beyond these assurances, it would be improper for me to go at this<br />
stage. Further, speculation is likely to be misleading and embarrassing<br />
to all governments concerned. The Government, therefore, invites the<br />
co-operation of the House and of the press until publication becomes<br />
possible.' FOURTH SECURITY LOAN.<br />
PRIME ~ VINISTER'S OPENING BROADCAST.<br />
On 28th October, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) broadcast<br />
over the national network. Mr. Chifley said-<br />
Good evening ladies and gentlemen,<br />
The Fourth Security Loan of œ 80,000,000 will be opened on 29th<br />
October, 1947. The people of Australia are asked to subscribe<br />
œ 48,000,000 for the programme of Commonwealth and State works<br />
approved by the seven governments and for the rehabilitation of<br />
former mem. bers of the fighting forces.<br />
In addition, holders of securities in loans floated in the early years<br />
of the war to a total of œ 32,000,000 are asked to convert their holdings<br />
into new bonds in the Fourth Security Loan. Therefore, the loan which<br />
will be opened to-morrow is for a total of œ 80,000,000 and, in the name<br />
of the Commonwealth and State Governments of Australia, I ask that<br />
it be over-subscribed.<br />
The two financial operations involved in this loan-namely, the<br />
subscription of new money and the conversion of old bonds-are a<br />
vital part of the over-all economic policy being followed by the Australian<br />
Government.<br />
" That policy has been followed with the dual purpose of maintaining<br />
the economic balance in this country and of ensuring that Australia,<br />
as a member of the British Commonwealth of Nations, can fully<br />
play her part for the welfare of all member nations and of Britain in<br />
particular. The Australian Government's economic policy during the war<br />
years and in post-war years that have followed have been amazingly<br />
successful. To-day, the Australian œ 1 purchases more for the Australian<br />
citizen in Australia than the American dollar does for Americans<br />
or the œ 1 sterling does for the people in the United Kingdom.<br />
Further, Australia is one of four nations in the world whose price rise<br />
has ' been the lowest. </p>
<p>Those two facts demonstrate very clearly that the Commonwealth<br />
Government's economic policy has resulted in the maximum welfare for<br />
Australian men and women as individuals and for Australia as a<br />
nation. You, the people of Australia, are asked to ensure the smooth<br />
continuance of that policy by an over-subscription for the Fourth<br />
Security Loan.-By so doing, you will make a contribution not only to<br />
your own security but will maintain Australia's economic strength so<br />
that she can continue to be a strong right arm for Britain in her<br />
struggle. As you know, the Australian Government has laid down a . policy<br />
of the . fullest possible assistance to the United Kingdom on the following<br />
lines:-Export of the greatest volume of foodstuffs.<br />
A gift of œ 23,000,000.<br />
Export of current Australian gold production so that Britain<br />
can use it to buy dollars.<br />
Severe restrictions on Australian use of dollars.<br />
The success of the Fourth Security Loan is essential so that the<br />
policy I have outlined to you may , be maintained. I ask you to oversubscribe<br />
the amount asked for in new money-œ 48; 000,000-and to<br />
convert fully the œ 32,000,000 of securities from earlier loans. The<br />
loan will open to-morrow and I am fully confident that you will play<br />
your part as Australians."<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 130, page 27.)<br />
NATIONAL MAPPING COUNCIL.<br />
COMM YWEALTH SURVEY COMMITTEE.<br />
On 28th OctoL:. r, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
In 1935, Cabinet appointed the Commonwealth Survey Committee<br />
comprising the Surveyor-General, chairman, and representatives<br />
of the three defence services to bring about co-ordination of survey work<br />
in Australia. In 1940, a representative of the Department of Civil<br />
Aviation was appointed and in 1944 a representative of the Department<br />
of Post-war Reconstruction was co-opted. In 1945, Commonwealth and<br />
State Governments -agreed to the formation of a National Mapping<br />
Council to ensure the co-ordination of mapping activities.<br />
Cabinet decided to-day to re-constitute the committee to provide<br />
for the Commonwealth Surveyor-General, who is also Director of the<br />
National Mapping Council, as chairman, and a representative of each<br />
of the Council for Scientific and Industrial Research, the three service<br />
departments, the departments of Civil Aviation, Post-war Reconstruction<br />
and Supply and Shipping. The committee's function will be to<br />
recommend, through the Minister for the Interior, such action as is<br />
needed to co-ordinate the activities and requirements of Commonwealth<br />
Departments in respect of mapping and ground and air surveys."<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 94, page 36; No. 97, page </p>
<p>TRADING WITH ENEMY.<br />
GERMANY-RESUMPTION.<br />
On 28th October, 1947, the Minister for Customs ( Senator Courtice)<br />
announced that the control authorities of the combined British-United<br />
States zone in Germany were now permitting the entrance of limited<br />
numbers of Australian businessmen to buy Oerman goods. Buyers<br />
would be admitted into the zone for periods not normally exceeding<br />
fourteen days. Because of the small quota allotted to Australia, sponsorship<br />
would be accorded only to those businessmen who desired to<br />
purchase goods considered essential in the national interest. Selection<br />
for sponsorship would take into account the range and quantity of goods<br />
available for export from Germany and the limitations on imports imposed<br />
by the Australian import licensing system.<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 175, page 27.)<br />
MOTOR CAR PRODUCTION.<br />
CAR -CHASSIS IMPORTS.<br />
On 30th October, 1947, the Minister for Customs ( Senator Courtice)<br />
s~ aid that on 2nd September, 1947, it was -announced that imports for<br />
North American motor vehicle chassis for 1948 would be reduced by<br />
per cent, as against the quantities authorized for importation during<br />
1947 and that the allocation of the cut to the various makes and models<br />
of chassis would he considered by an inter-departmental committee on<br />
which the trade would be represented. In the light of the subsequent<br />
deterioration in the dollar situation, the Government had reconsidered<br />
the matter to effect further economies. It had been decided that the<br />
maximum amount be allotted for the importation of motor vehicle<br />
chassis from the United States and Canada during 1948 was<br />
œ A. 8,000,000. It has been decided to abandon the former system of<br />
allocating quotas on a quantitative -basis and to fix a total c. i. f. and e.<br />
ceiling value for each make and model of chassis. It would be necessary<br />
to impose the condition that the value of the chassis to'be imported<br />
during the first half of 1948 be not more than half the approved quota<br />
value. ( For earlier -references, please see No. 125, page 29; No. 128, page 33.)<br />
WAR H ISTORY.<br />
WAR INDUSTRIES.<br />
On 4th November, 1947, the Minister for the Interior ( Mr.<br />
Johnson) announced that Dr. D. P. Mellor, of Sydney University, had<br />
been chosen to write the volume of the Australian official war history<br />
dealing with war industries and the application of scientific research<br />
to war-time needs. Re succeeded Dr. A. S. Fitzpatrick who was unable<br />
to continue the work.<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 108, page 34.)<br />
7081.-2 </p>
<p>JAPAN.<br />
WAR CRIMINALS-SIR WILLIAM WEBB'S RETURN.<br />
On 4th November, 1947, the Prime Minister. ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
" At my request, the Australian Government's representative on the<br />
International Military Tribunal at Tokio ( Sir William Webb) has<br />
arranged to return to Australia alriost imnmediately. This ivill enable<br />
him to take his seat on the High Court Bench for the forthcoming<br />
Sydney sittings. Sir William will return to Tokio, if necessary, ( luring<br />
the summer vacation to complete his work as president of the tribunal.<br />
" A seventh justiceship was restored to the High Court in April,<br />
1946. When Sir Willi-am was appointed in May, 1946, it was anticipated<br />
that his work at Tokio would last only a few months longer. The<br />
trials have been unexpectedly long and Sir William ha~ s so far been<br />
unable to assume his judicial duties here."<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 110, page 41.)<br />
TRANSITION.<br />
CONTROLS-FURTHER BILL INTRODUCED.<br />
it. Parliament On 5th November, 1947, the Minister fox Post-war<br />
Reconstruction ( Mr. Dedman) introduced the Defence ( Transitional<br />
Provisions) Bill. Mr. Dedman said-<br />
The purpose of this ' bill is to continue the operation for a further<br />
period of twelve months of certain National Security Regulations, the<br />
operation of which has already been prolonged by the Defence ( Transitional<br />
Provisions) Act 1946 until the end of December, 1947. When<br />
the Attorney-General ( Dr. Evatt) introduced the bill for that act he<br />
dealt fully with the constitutional -basis for the bill. At that time, I<br />
think that we all believed that by December, 1947, we should be able<br />
to dispense with many of the regulations then in operation. However,<br />
events have proved otherwise. Tihe principal reason is, that western<br />
Europe has not succeeded in regaining a state of economic health. In<br />
November, 1946, it appeared that the economic recovery of Europe<br />
would not be unduly delayed, but since then Europe has experienced an<br />
exceptionally severe winter, followed by a drought. During 1946, the<br />
fact that the balance had been upset between the productive power and<br />
resources of the western hemisphere, on the one hand, and those of the<br />
rest of the world on the other, was obscured by the vast quantities of<br />
goods poured into Europe by Unrra and other organizations. The disastrous<br />
effects of winter and drought were followed by the dollar crisis.<br />
Those events have had repercussions extending far beyond Europe;<br />
indeed they threaten the foundations of world economy. In his speech in<br />
1946, Dr. Evatt emphasized the need for the retention of measures designed<br />
to check inflation and maintain stability. The Oovernment at<br />
that time indicated its view that the operation of regulations covering<br />
price control, rent control, capital issues, and land sales, would need to<br />
be continued beyond December, 1947. The -bill makes provision for the<br />
continuation of those regulations for a further twelve months. </p>
<p>No one would argue that price control has not been highly successful<br />
in helping to keep the economy of Australia steady. A comparison<br />
of the figures of the cost of living in Australia to-day with those for<br />
the period following World War and those of countries which have<br />
abandoned price control, prove the wisdom of the Government's action<br />
in continuing the operation of war-time price control regulations in the<br />
post-war period. To-day, Australia is one of the countries which shows<br />
the lowest increase of prices, and a comparison of living costs with<br />
those of other nations where prices control has lapsed, or has never<br />
been enforced, proves how well we have controlled the post-war boom.<br />
The United Nations' monthly ' bulletin of statistics for September, 1947,<br />
shows that Australia is only one in a list of 35 countries in which the<br />
rise of wholesale prices since 1937 has been less than 50 per cent. The<br />
same authority gives the following percentage increases of retail prices<br />
from 1939, to June, 1947:-Australia 28; South Africa 39; Canada<br />
32; United Kingdom 29; United . States of America 57; Argentine<br />
Sweden 52; Switzerland 56; Spain 109; Ireland 70; Turkey 245;<br />
Poland 15,010; and China 2,087,900. The indications are that during<br />
1948, the Australian price level will be subjected to pressure, as it was<br />
in 1947. By V. P. Day, export prices had increased by 78 per cent.<br />
over pre-war prices, and by 183 per cent. by June, 1947. Import<br />
prices rose by 99 and 147 per cent., respectively. There is no sign of<br />
the increase of overseas prices steadying as yet, and there is no doubt<br />
that a serious post-war boom is taking place in the international field.<br />
Under these conditions it would not be wise to remove the existing<br />
control over prices.<br />
An attempt to control prices generally without controlling the land<br />
values would because of the present state of demand, permit serious distortions<br />
of the whole cost-price structure. Excessive land values would<br />
greatly inflate the cost of home-building and would make the administration<br />
of rent control extremely difficult, if not impossible. The effect<br />
on rural industries must also be particularly serious. When producers<br />
are receiving high returns for their products, speculation becomes rampant<br />
and land changes hands at boom prices financed by mortgage loans.<br />
Then, when export prices decline, many producers find themselves ' burdened<br />
with debt and high costs. A long and painful re-adjustment becomes<br />
inescapable; and the result is a general state of depression<br />
throughout the rural industries. To prevent a repetition of such experiences,<br />
and to prevent execessive land values from unduly inflating costs<br />
generally, it is proposed to continue the control of land values for a<br />
further twelve months under this bill.<br />
" Speculative investments are not confined to land. At present there<br />
is a large supply of capital awaiting investment, but it is impossible<br />
for all of it to be employed without making inordinate demands on the<br />
available resources of material and man-power. It is clearly desirable<br />
that resources should be concentrated on essential production and not be<br />
diverted to speculative or unnecessary enterprises. It is, therefore, proposed<br />
to continue the Capital Issues Regulations.<br />
7081.-3 </p>
<p>Rent control is a special aspect of economic controls, and its continuance<br />
is rendered necessary by the present shortage of accommodation<br />
of all kinds. It ensures a measure of stability where stability is<br />
most needed. Its removal, and the removal of control over evictions<br />
under present conditions, would result in inflation of rents, wholesale<br />
evictions, exploitation and much misery.<br />
" I mention briefly some marketing regulations which it is proposed<br />
should be continued. The regulations under this group include those<br />
relating to the control of barley, apples and pears, hides and leather,<br />
potatoes, rabbit skins, as well as the acquisition of wheat and the<br />
stabilization of the wheat industry. The reasons for continuing these<br />
regulations are simply that the conditions which necessitated their<br />
introduction are still with us, and the Commonwealth must keep the<br />
faith with the primary producers. The detailed considerations differ<br />
somewhat, depending on the commodity. In respect of the Australian<br />
Barley Board, it was expected that legislation would be enacted by the<br />
South Australian and Victorian Governments to carry on after the<br />
end of 1947 the authority originally established by the Commonwealth,<br />
but the sudden dissolution of the Victorian Parliament has delayed the<br />
necessary legislation in that State, and the Commonwealth is accordingly<br />
obliged to continue the regulations so that there will be no disorder<br />
in the handling of the forthcoming crop. Refrigerated shipping<br />
space for the apple and pear crops of Tasmania and Western Australia<br />
is still inadequate, and hence the continuance of assistance is necessary<br />
to protect the growers in those States. As regards potatoes, the Commonwealth<br />
has let contracts to growers for the 1947-48 crop, and the<br />
regulations are intended to control marketing until the crop<br />
is sold. It is hoped that by the end of 1948 the organizations of the<br />
States will be ready to take over potato marketing. Wheat regulations<br />
are intended to cover the marketing of the 1947-48 crop. It has not<br />
been practicable to reach agreement on a permanent marketing scheme<br />
for the industry, but a further conference with the States will be held<br />
shortly. Meanwhile the Commonwealth is continuing the Australian<br />
Wheat Board in accordance with the desires of the growers and all<br />
State Governments. In fact, no other organization could satisfactorily<br />
market the crop. Controls over hides, leather and rabbit skins are<br />
necessary mainly for price stabilization purposes, as the world prices<br />
of these commodities greatly exceed the domestic prices. A limited<br />
section of the food control regulations is preserved so that the distribution<br />
of certain fats and oils can be equitably arranged, and also that<br />
essential service supplies may be obtained.<br />
There is a group of regulations which affect servicemen still serving<br />
in the occupation forces in Japan. It is obviously necessary to<br />
keep in force the Military Forces, Naval Forces and Women's Service<br />
Regulations. There are still a few internees and prisoners of war in<br />
Australia, and although very few are affected by them the provisions<br />
by which their detention is regulated must remain in force. </p>
<p>37<br />
" Parliament has considered several bills dealing with industrial<br />
conditions-notably the Commonwealth Conciliation and Arbitration<br />
Act, the Stevedoring Act and the Coal Act. These enactments go back<br />
some distance in bringing back to a peace-time footing the framework<br />
within which industrial conditions are settled. There are still, however,<br />
fields to which attention has not been given, particularly the maritime<br />
industry and the craft unionists employed in the coal industry. Pending<br />
some further clarification in these fields, the existing regulations<br />
must be preserved for a time.<br />
Superphosphate regulations have been discontinued and the operation<br />
of the Agricultural Aids Regulations restricted to a single item of<br />
nicotine sulphate. The prospect of a record harvest has aggravated the<br />
demand for both cornsacks and galvanized iron, and control over these<br />
commodities must be continued for some time longer. While Britain's<br />
position is so critical it is unthinkable for Australia to remove all<br />
restrictions on commodities which are needed so badly there, and<br />
accordingly ration schemes are being continued, particularly in relation<br />
to meat and butter.<br />
" About one do. en sets of regulations will be continued. They are<br />
those under which war materials are being disposed of, war damage<br />
claims settled, compensation with regard to requisitioned cargoes<br />
assessed, property of enemy nationals administered, and the hundred<br />
and one other things necessary to unwind the war effort. A good many<br />
of the provisions of this sort cannot be dispensed with until the Treaty<br />
of Peace is signed with Japan.<br />
In 1946, a few amendments were made in permanent legislation.<br />
This bill gives permanent expression in appropriate acts to some provisions<br />
hitherto contained in National Security Regulations. The Acts<br />
Interpretation Act is amended in two respects. One provision is made<br />
to cover the case where the functions of one department are transferred<br />
to another department. Reference to the former department or its<br />
Minister will be read in an agreement as referring to the latter department<br />
or its Minister. Secondly, there is a provision relating to delegation<br />
of powers or functions. This provision permits the exercise of<br />
powers or functions by a delegate in circumstances in which the exercise<br />
of the power or function is dependent on the opinion, belief or state<br />
of mind of the person exercising the power. An amendment made in<br />
1946 to the Land Tax Assessment Act is continued for a further year.<br />
This amendment continued for land tax purposes pegging of land values<br />
which, up to that time had been pegged at 1939 values by regulation<br />
under the National Security Act. The assessment of land tax on land<br />
owned as at 30th June, 1948, will be based on the 1939 value.<br />
" Action is being taken to amend the Defence Act by exempting from<br />
jury service members of the Citizen Forces engaged on war service.<br />
Probably the most important of these changes in permanent legislation<br />
is the clause which repeals the National Registration Act. The Government<br />
regards the National Registration Act as a type of legislation </p>
<p>which is undesirable during peace-time. It is the policy of the Government<br />
to embody in permanent legislation at the earliest possible date<br />
provisions now contained in National Security Regulations and which<br />
it is desirable shall have permanent effect as part of the law of the<br />
Commonwealth. This bill is one of a group of about half a dozen bills<br />
which deal with matters previously covered ' by National Security Regu-'<br />
lations. Already the Dairy Produce Export Control'bill has been introduced<br />
and one of the effects of its pas-sage would be that the Dairy<br />
Produce Acquisition Regulations will be permitted to lapse at the end<br />
of the year. The Australian Soldiers Repatriation Bill contains a provision<br />
permitting regulations to be made about patriotic funds, and<br />
accordingly the Patriotic Funds Regulations will not be ' Continued next<br />
year. Other legislation involving amendments to other acts is in train,<br />
and will be introduced as early as possible. When thes3e bills are intro<br />
duced, opportunity will be taken to place in permanent form some of<br />
the provisions now carried on temporarily." [ Teblwapsed<br />
( For earlier reference, please see N-o. 122, page<br />
By Authority: L. F. JOHNSTONq, Commonwealth Government Printer, Canberra. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
