<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11308</transcript-id>
    <title>US RESTRICTIONS ON AUSTRALIAN LAMB EXPORTS</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/07/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
   The Australian Government is appalled at the decision by the US Administration</p>
<p> to introduce restrictions on Australian lamb exports to the United</p>
<p> States.</p>
<p>I will convey Australia's deep concern about the decision when I see</p>
<p> President Clinton next Monday.</p>
<p>The Government will take steps to assist the Australian lamb industry</p>
<p> cope with any damage caused by the US decision. The Government will</p>
<p> pay for up to two years the equivalent of half the transaction levy</p>
<p> applying to the sale of all lambs in Australia. We will enter into</p>
<p> immediate discussions with appropriate representatives of the industry</p>
<p> to implement this decision.</p>
<p>The Government will also canvass with lamb processors ways of ensuring</p>
<p> that they are not unfairly disadvantaged by the US action.</p>
<p>There is no rational foundation for the American decision. The restrictions</p>
<p> will provide no help to US producers of lamb. The decision will make</p>
<p> high quality lamb more expensive for US consumers.</p>
<p>There is no justice in the decision. Australian lamb producers have</p>
<p> created a market for lamb in the United States, a market which simply</p>
<p> did not exist before and a market that US producers had been unable</p>
<p> to create for themselves.</p>
<p>Australian lamb producers have developed this market without any support</p>
<p> or subsidy from the Australian government. Their only mistake is to</p>
<p> have developed a new market, produce high quality product, and sell</p>
<p> it at a competitive price.</p>
<p>They are being punished simply for succeeding.</p>
<p>The decision is hypocritical. The US has argued long and loudly that</p>
<p> it favours free trade and the opening up in particular of agricultural</p>
<p> markets. It has taken a decision which strikes at the credibility</p>
<p> of its rhetoric.</p>
<p>Even worse, the decision will damage the prospects of an early and</p>
<p> successful WTO trade round. This is a protectionist decision which</p>
<p> sends precisely the wrong signal in the lead up to the Seattle Ministerial</p>
<p> meeting in November.</p>
<p>The decision is all the more disappointing because Australia is a</p>
<p> close ally and friend.</p>
<p>The Australian government is extremely sympathetic to those lamb exporters</p>
<p> who will be affected. They have been most unjustly treated, and the</p>
<p> government shares their sentiments about the US decision.</p>
<p>In addition to the steps mentioned above, the Australian government</p>
<p> will pursue the case vigorously within the WTO. It will initiate a</p>
<p> formal request for consultations as soon as possible with the US government</p>
<p> under article 12.3 of the WTO Safeguards Agreement. If these consultations</p>
<p> do not produce satisfactory results, Australia will take action under</p>
<p> WTO disputes settlement procedures.</p>
<p>Tokyo</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
