<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6530</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MELBOURNE CHAMBER OF COMMERCE, MELBOURNE, 29 OCTOBER 1984</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/10/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006530.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
EMBARGOED UNTIL .1.30 P. M. CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINIS-TER<br />
MELBOURNE CHAMBER OF COMMERCE<br />
MELBOURNE 29 OCTOBER 1984<br />
I very much appreciate this opportunity to address you<br />
today.<br />
Some of you may be aware that your invitation to me was<br />
made some time ago and that I was unable to accept at<br />
the time.<br />
The delay has meant that I am able to report further<br />
evidence of strengthened economic performance. With the<br />
passing of time, the strength and extent of economic<br />
recovery is becoming increasingly apparent. At the same<br />
time, there is increasing evidence of decisive progress<br />
in the decade-long fight against: inflation.<br />
Today I want to talk to you about a number of aspects of<br />
the economic recovery which are vitally important to the<br />
well-being of all Australians.<br />
I want to talk to you about our general strategy for<br />
sustained, strong non-inflationary growth.<br />
I want to talk to you about employment.<br />
I want to talk to y~ u about industrial disputes.<br />
I want to talk to you about how we havet been keeping<br />
wages growth within the capacity of the economy, and<br />
about the other side of this coin, real. unit labour<br />
costs to business and the profits sharc of total<br />
incomes. I want to talk to you about inflation and interest<br />
rates. I want to talk to you about housing. </p>
<p>I want to talk to you about the tax cuts which come into<br />
effect this week, and about broader taxation reform.<br />
I want to talk to you about all these things that are<br />
absolutely vital to all Australians.<br />
You don't hear much about most of these issues from the<br />
other side of politics these days.<br />
When did you last hear Mr Peacock and Mr Howard talk<br />
about growth, and inflation, and interest rates, and<br />
housing, and employment and unemployment, and the<br />
profits share of total incomes?<br />
Obviously they are not very comfortable on these<br />
subjects.<br />
But they know quite a lot about them.<br />
After all, Mr Howard was Treasurer and Mr Peacock was<br />
Minister for Industrial Relations at the onset of the<br />
great wages explosion of 1980 and 1981, which destroyed<br />
the profitability of Australian business and set the<br />
scene for the subsequent recession.<br />
Mr Howard knows quite a lot about inflation. He could<br />
be considered something of an expert, since he created<br />
inflation rates that were well into double digits and<br />
twice the world average.<br />
Mr Howard should know a good deal about unemployment.<br />
He was Treasurer when a quarter of a million<br />
Australian's jobs disappeared in the year before my<br />
Government took ofof ice.<br />
Mr Howard was Treasurer when interest rates rose to<br />
record highs and housing activity slumped to record lows<br />
a couple of years ago.<br />
Mr Peacock, Mr Howard and Mr Sinclair hold all sorts of<br />
records for indust ' rial confrontation, wages explosions,<br />
high inflation and-interest rates, housing slumps and<br />
growth in unemployment, not to mention the $ 9.6 billion<br />
budget deficit that they tried to hide from the<br />
Australian people.<br />
But don't be fooled.<br />
Just because they won't talk about the special expertise<br />
they accumulated in seven years in government, it<br />
doesn't mean that they would not apply their expertise<br />
if, by some accident, they were ever to form a,<br />
government again. </p>
<p>A Peacock-Howard-Sinclair government would give us the<br />
stagnation, the inflation and the recession all over<br />
again.<br />
They would wheel out the same old failed policies.<br />
Only a bit messier, a bit more damaging, because, after<br />
all, those that are left in their ranks are really the<br />
second eleven of the last conservative government. I do<br />
not intend to be deterred by their silence from<br />
addressing the issues that matt~ er most to all<br />
Australians. I want to tell you what the Labor Government has<br />
achieved on the issues that most affect the standards of<br />
life of all Australians.-<br />
This Government is proud of its record on these matters.<br />
This Government, and I as Prime Minister, can look the<br />
Australian people in the eye and say that we have<br />
delivered the economic recovery that we promised.<br />
And because from the beginning of our period in<br />
Government we have been preparing and building not for<br />
one or two years of economic recovery, but for a long<br />
era of strong non-inflationary growth, we face the<br />
future with anticipation, pride and confidence.<br />
When the Labor Government took office early last year,<br />
the economy was in deep recession, and Australia's<br />
political and economic life was characterised by<br />
destructive confrontation. The policies of the outgoing<br />
Government offered no way forward.<br />
Economic growth was negative, the unemployment rate had<br />
ri~ en to levels not seen since the 1930' s Depression and<br />
our inflation rate was around twice that of our trading<br />
partners.<br />
That was only twenty months ago.<br />
The transformation in the economy's fortunes since that<br />
time can only be described as dramatic. The progress so<br />
far has created real opportunities for the first time<br />
for a decade, to entrench sustained strong<br />
non-inflationary growth in Australian economic life.<br />
As I promised the Australian people in February 1983,<br />
immediately after taking office the Gove-rnment convened<br />
the National Economic Summit Conference an event<br />
unique in Australia's history. That initiative made<br />
manifest the Government's commitment to a new approach<br />
to economic policy. </p>
<p>I do not think it is possible to overstate the<br />
importance of the spirit of co-operation engendered by<br />
the Summit and the crucial contribution that it has made<br />
towards achieving sustainable economic recovery. In<br />
particular: The process begun by the Summit and carried forward<br />
through EPAC has seen an unprecedented degree of<br />
information sharing and exchanging of ideas about<br />
feasible solutions to the twin evils of unemployment<br />
and inflation;<br />
This process has been the concrete expresssion of the<br />
Government's commitment to consultation and<br />
consensus; and<br />
It has helped to forge a new spirit of common purpose<br />
and a conviction that together we can overcome<br />
our difficulties.<br />
The linchpin of the Government's macroeconomic strategy<br />
has been the Prices and Incomes Policy based squarely on<br />
the Accord with the ACTU. That policy has been<br />
ouLstandinjgly successful in constraining wage and price<br />
C) C S I,<br />
has been alnost in iversal compoLiance . eith the ag. j<br />
fixing pr ilncai! e'; Iard dovqn by thie -rbi tration<br />
Commission, reflecting in no small measure the restraint<br />
and cominmItnent of virtually all of the trade union<br />
movement to the centralised wage fixation system.<br />
A further measure of the success of the Accord is the<br />
shiarp reduction in industrial disputation. The nuinbc! r<br />
oF . j-rking days lost, in the last year is the lowest<br />
since 1969. And the mechanisms of the Accord can be<br />
expected to be instrumental in holding award wages<br />
growth below 3 per cent through the current financial<br />
year. Measured against AustraLia's history, and by any<br />
standards, this is an extraordinary oitcome in the<br />
second year of strong economic recovery.<br />
The change since early 1983 in Australian industrial<br />
disputation, in wage outcomes, in the profit share of<br />
total income and in the prospects for all of these<br />
is nothing short of phenomenal. It is being recognised<br />
well beyond our shores. Already it is being reflected<br />
in strong r d. mr-and for our mnineral exports. It is a<br />
major cause of our greatly improved performance in all<br />
spheres of national life. It is the single greatest<br />
difference between life and policy under my Government,<br />
and life and policy tinder the Liberal National Parties.<br />
0<br />
^ yy V t.
</p><p>With the Labor Government, Australia has left behind the<br />
debilitating confrontation and division of the past.<br />
The gains, measured in terms of productivity and<br />
competitiveness, are for everyone to share.<br />
Wage moderation within the Prices and Incomes Accord has<br />
allowed us to use fiscal policy to stimulate economic<br />
recovery. We have done this by increasing resources to<br />
housing and other activities central to economic<br />
recovery while cutting unnecessary expenditure,<br />
cutting taxes and re-ordering budgetary priorities.<br />
Our Budgets have given special a: teni: ion to alleviating<br />
the hardship and the distress of the unemployed and the<br />
disadvantaged.<br />
We provided substantial fundinrg foEr : he Community<br />
Employment Program and for the Community Youth Support<br />
Scheme to assist the unemployed. Medicare now provides<br />
basic medical care for all Australians. There have also<br />
been substantial increases in real pensions, benefits<br />
and services to the most needy groups in our society,<br />
including pensioners with children, pensioner renters,<br />
the single unemployed, and the Aboriginal community.<br />
Our efforts to improve the living standards of these<br />
groups stand in stark contrast to the real decline in<br />
funding which occurred in the previous seven y. ears.<br />
At the same time, we have made a major investmeit<br />
thcrogh our fiscal policy to strenjthening ' and<br />
supporting our Prices and Incomes Policy. Chief amoij<br />
such elements has been the tax cut in the 1984-85 Budget<br />
and improvements in the social wage. That has been a<br />
major investment in the sustainabili-y of economic<br />
recovery.<br />
The setting of our fiscal and moneta: y policies has been<br />
and will continue to be an important factor in ensuring<br />
that the recovery continues to broaden and strengthen.<br />
In particular, restraint in the growth of public sector<br />
borrowing will be essential to limit pressures in<br />
financial markets as the private sector recovery<br />
broadens and increases momentum.<br />
In the last Budget we achieved a substantial reduction<br />
in the deficit.<br />
In conjunction with the restraint which States, at the<br />
Loan Council earlier this year, agreed to exercise under<br />
the new system of global borrowirg limits for public<br />
authorities, this means that the public sector borrowing<br />
requirement as a proportion of GDP is falling<br />
substantially in 1984/ 85. Further reductions ' will be<br />
achieved in later years. 0<br />
A t^ ' V 2^ ^ Y r ic T ;/ cl 1 </p>
<p>The Incomes Policy and the fiscal stance have been<br />
supported by an appropriately firm monetary policy which<br />
has, nonetheless, permitted significant declines in<br />
interest rates, in line with reduced inflationary<br />
expectat ionts.<br />
1983/ 84 was the first time in years that any Government<br />
achieved its monetary projection.<br />
And we have alopted] a conditional monetary projection<br />
for 1984/ 85 that will continue to provide for strong<br />
economnic gjrowth while accommodating no mo(-re than the<br />
minimal cost and price increases that mnight flow from<br />
the effect ive oaeration of Llie Pr ices and Incomes<br />
Z'c co rd.<br />
zks the Summit !-ore witness, an-imp. ortinlL element of Lhe<br />
Gove rnment ' s cvera 11 pol icy approach has been the<br />
consultative me chanisins iniclubding the Cormail Advisory<br />
Clouncils frcom, EPAC through to indutstry sp) eci fic-<br />
IrinCis j1e( s1 .1 -3W ide c -I' I g informal C 0 1t -1C L-<br />
0on: 13 t. 1It i o n las -b-, 3n a t-vo 4ay proces: s-. Th rotigh i i-h<br />
? o 21et 11 -3 bnne i1t. i rr on a ' ide r a of ' i ew<br />
Equally, it fos-, ters greater colimuni): y understanding and<br />
3co t an vL vflent esi'C<br />
The correctness of our general economic strategy hias<br />
t'x-en coriE i rn-ed I-lihe : l-rl.: sw~ 22 nnic reCo(.. e ry<br />
ini economnic i nd i: a tors across t: he oa id.<br />
Ec: onr. m! ic on tu ' hiisa ecjjer-jd ama I y, ithi CDP<br />
growing 10 per cerit through the course of 1983/ 84, the<br />
fastest annui~ al result sin3,? National \ u,, counts h~ tve been<br />
kept in a comparable formn, and Lhe st. fongest perforfnancle<br />
in that ye-: ir o iaiy advani ed country.<br />
Par-t of this grovith is attributable to the breakingj of<br />
the drought and the consequent bounce--back of the rural<br />
sector. In addition, world economic activity began to<br />
pick up in 1983-84, particularly in the United States.<br />
But those factors do not fully explain the rapid growthi<br />
in non-farmi prodiict, which rost. by 3.3 per cent over<br />
1983-84; nor do they explain the strong underlying<br />
growth now runningj through the economy; nor the<br />
substantial progress which has been made towards<br />
achieving sustained growth.<br />
They do not explain the pace oif the expansion in housing<br />
activity, and they do not explain. the lift in business<br />
investment which the latest National Account Estimates<br />
and investment Surveys reveal. 3. </p>
<p>The reasons for these are to be found in economic<br />
policies which have cut inflation, restored<br />
profi tabil i ty, re] ced uncer ta inr ty, boos ted con f idence<br />
and cut interest rates.<br />
Inflation hais been drainatically redi.: cd in the last<br />
six month the underlying rate of inflation has been only<br />
half of . hat it was in the six ' nonths prior I: o on being<br />
elected. Thle annual rate now of 6.1 per cent is the<br />
lowe; t inFlat ion ate for , nore than a decade. Eqlally<br />
important, however, is that ii-lationary expectations<br />
have been subs tafiiilly red? i c d. In Lhis, the<br />
circuit-breaker wage inflation provided through the<br />
A\ ccorcd arln tlhe .1dicace ef Efcr: . on : th-CPI has been<br />
crucially imnportant.<br />
As a rsu t1, n( wj4 ect rio : 1ovement in award v j3es<br />
until April 1935. These lower inflationary expectations<br />
have enabled our fiscal stimulus to increase real<br />
activity rather than prices.<br />
The re has been a real i: nmpro: vemnt in employment as well<br />
as inl output. Over 260,000 new. jobs were created from<br />
the Summit in . Aril 1983 to Septernber this year, and the<br />
Government is well on its way to achieving the target of<br />
500,000 new jobs in thre.? years.<br />
The unemployment rate has fallen to 8.8 per cent, down<br />
from 10.2 per cent in April 1933.<br />
Importantly for business, and for new job prospects,<br />
real init labour costs have fallen dramatically and are<br />
now at the levels of the late 1960' s and early 1970' s.<br />
I wouldi add that the imnasire oE labour costs to whichi<br />
am Creerrring is based on the :. ational Accoun; ts Estimate<br />
of w-iges, sal i and sup~ p) lenents. It ther efore<br />
includes an estimate of most on-costs.<br />
Reflecting the restrained growth of unit costs, the<br />
profit share has risen to its highest level in the last<br />
years. That summary measure also based on the<br />
National Accounts is being confirmed almost daily by<br />
profit reports of individual companies.<br />
Interest rates have fallen across the board, from<br />
housing loan rates which are down by up to 1 per cent;<br />
through larger falls in yields on official securities;<br />
to a drop of up to 2 3/ 4 per cent in the prime overdraft<br />
rate. C)<br />
rr r-r Inr;-~ tn~~ I r </p>
<p>The Government's economic policies, together with the<br />
success of the First Home Owners Scheme, have led to a<br />
dramatic recovery in the housing sector. Commencements<br />
in 1983/ 84 were 30 per cent above the 1982/ 83 level, and<br />
in the first half of 1984 ran well ahead of our<br />
announced target of an annual rate of 130 to 135<br />
thousand.<br />
The latest forecasts predict even higher commencements<br />
in 1984/ 85. Indeed the industry is expected to be<br />
performing at close to its capacity. The lift in this<br />
sector not only directly provides jobs and alleviates<br />
the housing needs of many, but also contributes to<br />
strengthened demand for a wide range of goods as<br />
, hoise.} hoid:.] s e.-s'tablish the, 1selves.<br />
With that record already behind us, it is not surprising<br />
that confidence in the community is at a high level.<br />
Consumer surveys continue to show optimism at record<br />
high levels, while surveys of business indicate that<br />
trading conditions and profitability have improved in<br />
recent j-iarters al: n firm e xpectatioris j[ further<br />
improvements over coming months.<br />
The survey results have been borne out by a turnaround<br />
in business investment, which increased in the March and<br />
June quarters aEtr 8 successive quarterly declines.<br />
Business itself expects further growth in investment<br />
throgh 1984/ 85, an expectation thai has been assisted<br />
by our specific actions in the Budget to encourage such<br />
investment. These include the introduction of company<br />
group taxation; lifting the depreciation rate for<br />
commercial buildings from 2 1/ 2 per cent per annum to<br />
4 per cent per annum; and an extension by one year of<br />
the time for the eligibility of plant ordered before<br />
I July 1985 under the terms of the investment allowance.<br />
While workinj towards these clear achievements in<br />
reducing inflation, expanding employment and providing<br />
the basis for a sustainable recovery, the Government has<br />
from the very beginning given high priority to issues<br />
relevant to raising Australia's long term growth<br />
performance.<br />
One area of concern is the burden that excessive and<br />
often irrelevant and obstructive laws and regulations<br />
imposes on the economy and on the operations of<br />
businesses. We see the removal of unnecessary<br />
regulation as contributing significantly to improved<br />
economic growth performance. The Australian Chamber of<br />
Commerce is one of several national busin'ess<br />
organisations which have pledged ' their assistance to the<br />
Government in its efforts to remove unnecessary<br />
regulation. </p>
<p>I believe that this Government is the first to have<br />
begun tackling daregulation in an effective manner.<br />
The major financial deregulation we have been<br />
implementing over the past year is benefitting the many<br />
users of F inanc ial services and the whole community<br />
through the contribution of financial reforms to overall<br />
growth. The Steel Indiustry Plan and the approach to the Motor<br />
Vehicles announced by John Button earlier this year<br />
provid a realistic basis for improving the performance<br />
and efficiency of Australian industry in these areas.<br />
Th'" y are an ntejral part of oir stra'g/ for ensirinj<br />
us tai; ned, long-term economic growth.<br />
Lookrig i: i: e f , it re, there is ev ry reason to expectL<br />
that strong economic growth will continue.<br />
T; i-B'a jet o L'ce as ts i nd i caL on tinued s trong j row-th in<br />
activity at around 4 to 5 per cent, further gains in<br />
. e: nployrment of over 2 per cent through 1984/ 85, an-i lower<br />
underlying rates of inflation.<br />
There has been nothing since the 3, ud: et to cause us to<br />
revise that broad assessment in any way downwards.<br />
Rather t" he opposite indeed, revisec. forecasts of th: e<br />
farm sector by the Bureau of Agricultural Economics<br />
suggest an upwards revision to farm GDP: and private<br />
investment and consumption both appear to be performing<br />
as well as or better than anticipated in the Budget.<br />
In the three months to August retail sales rose by 1.7<br />
per cent compared with the previous three months and it<br />
seems likely that private consumption spending will show<br />
strong growth in the September quarter.<br />
I know that some concern has been expressed that the<br />
timing of the election may prejudice the growth of<br />
retail sales. You should remember that some. powerful<br />
countervailing pressures will be operating. From next<br />
week, tax cuts will be increasing everyone's take home<br />
pay. For the great majority the increase will be $ 7.60<br />
per week. Increases in pensions and benefits will also<br />
mean higher disposable incomes.<br />
Single rates of pension and benefits will increase by<br />
$ 2.50 a week, which represents an increase in real terms<br />
beyond that required for indexation. The rate of rent<br />
assistance will rise by $ 5.00 a week, or" 50 per cent,<br />
while supplements for children will increase by $ 2.00 a<br />
week, bringing the total increase in child supplements<br />
since we came into office to 40 per cent. n<br />
. r14 .1 1 1. 41 I I r r r. n' I I I </p>
<p>This is happening at a time of year when spending always<br />
tends to be high and when, furthermore, consumer<br />
confidence is at record levels. Retail sales should<br />
reflect the combined benefit of. all these factors.<br />
To maintain the recovery and to establish sustained noninflationary<br />
growth, we must address a range of<br />
difficult issues.<br />
We will continue to reduce the budget deficit as private<br />
investment expands strongly as it will do next year,<br />
and beyond, in the course of economic recovery.<br />
In this area, our record as responsibl fiscal managers<br />
stands for all to see.<br />
We delivered a final 1983/ 34 i3udgjet deficit of iinder $ 8<br />
billion, substantially lower than the inherited<br />
prospective iit ro'i ef $ 9.5 bi'. lion, and the 1983/ 84<br />
Budget estimate -of $ 3.4 billion.<br />
In the 1984/ 35 3udet reduc. id d! f icii: by a<br />
further $ 1200 million, as compared with 1983/ 84.<br />
Let: there be no doubt, under my Government the deficit<br />
will be reduced further next year.<br />
We belie. the only long-term way to : reduce deficits i:<br />
through jrowvth in the economy, coupled with firm control<br />
over Governne'-it spending.<br />
We do not believe that there is any scope for reducing<br />
the budget deficit by increased taxation.<br />
I give you, the categorical assurance : hat there will be<br />
no overall increase in the tax burden, next year or<br />
through our next term in office.<br />
But while avoiding any increase in the overall level of<br />
taxation, we will not let down the Australian people,<br />
who believe that the whole taxation system is in need of<br />
a thorough overhaul.<br />
We all know that the burden of taxation at the moment is<br />
distributed unfairly.<br />
And we all know that there are features of the<br />
Australian taxation system that: inhibit production,<br />
investment and employment.<br />
What is needed is not a quick political fix, but a<br />
careful review in full consultation with the Australian<br />
community. C) </p>
<p>My Government is proud of the economic' recovery of these<br />
past twenty months.<br />
But we recognise that these are only the beginnings of<br />
our struggle to achieve the great ambitions we share for<br />
Australia. Australia needs and deserves not one or two years, but a<br />
generation near the top of the world league table of<br />
economic growth.<br />
Australia needs and deserves not unly higher employment<br />
and lower unemployment, but a return to full employment.<br />
Australia needs and deserv(.' 3 not a peCr'iod of lower<br />
inflation, but permanently low inflation.<br />
Australia n: eeds and deserves a Government that is<br />
conscientious in allocating part of the fruits of<br />
national economic growth to genuinely needy Australians.<br />
These are the great ambitions we all share for<br />
Australia. And now, after a decade of despair, Australians<br />
justifiably are daring to hope that they can realise<br />
there great anbitions.<br />
The Australian Government is working to realise these<br />
hopes and ambitions.<br />
I look forward to your continued support in this great<br />
venture for Australia. A* k*<br />
I ~ 1<br />
1<br />
: 1 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
