<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9263</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J. KEATING MP SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING COUNCIL</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/06/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009263.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL: 24. Jun. 94 14: 34 No. 017 P. 01/ 02<br />
PRIME MINISTER 52/ 94<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING COUNCIL<br />
Together with several of my Ministerial colleagues, I met a number of leading<br />
scientists, engineers and business people at today's meeting of my Science<br />
and Engineering Council.<br />
The Council discussed some areas of technicaf and economic development<br />
critical to the future prosperity of Australia, many of which were addressed in<br />
Working Nation.<br />
Working Nation is about looking to the future, making decisions today which<br />
will give us an innovative and competitive future using and developing our<br />
skills and our science and technology base.<br />
An important feature of our future will be the so-called ' information. super<br />
highways', which will transform all our lives over the coming years. We<br />
discussed these today at my Science and Engineering Council.<br />
My Government has a keen interest in seeing Australia reap maximum<br />
benefits from the development of the information super highway.<br />
We established the Broadband Services Expert Group last year to advise it<br />
on the technical, economic and commercial preconditions for the widespread<br />
delivery of broadband services in Australia.<br />
The Group reported to Council today on its progress, and expects to release<br />
an interim report around the end of July 1994, and a final report by the end of<br />
1994.<br />
My Government also commissioned a report from the Australian Science and<br />
Technology Council on research data networks, an information highway<br />
already up and running. This report was discussed today by the Science and<br />
Engineering Council before being presented to Government in August.<br />
The Australian Academic Research Network allows our scientists and<br />
engineers to Interact with one another and with their counterparts around the<br />
world. It provides access to data banks, sophisticated opportunities for<br />
Information exchange with other users, and the ability to shrink global<br />
distances that we expect from the super highway. </p>
<p>, n 1.~ LL: n. 941 4: 34 NO. 017 P. 02/ 02<br />
2<br />
The Australian Vice Chancellors Committee has developed this network,<br />
drawing on significant government assistance, and we now have a network<br />
that is second only to the US.<br />
Discussion at the meeting of my Science and Engineering Council today also<br />
focussed on strategic directions for the Government's policies for science and<br />
technology, and on identifying the key strategic issues needing to be<br />
addressed. In creating an innovative future, I believe that we will need a cultural change<br />
in our perceptions of science, technology and innovation, building an<br />
appreciation in our society of their importance in maintaining our quality of<br />
life. We will also need to recognise the vital role of demand for science and<br />
technology in stimulating industry to innovate and to improve its innovative<br />
capacity to compete globally.<br />
At today's meeting, members discussed a new study that the Australian<br />
Science and Technology Council is proposing to undertake, of matching<br />
science and technology to future social and economic changes in Australia<br />
over the next fifteen years.<br />
I consider this is an important study which should provide insights for policy<br />
development, as well as stimulate awareness of science and technology<br />
more generally.<br />
I was also impressed by a presentation to Council today from leading<br />
business people and scientists, about the opportunities that Asian food<br />
markets provide for Australia's agri-food industry.<br />
It confirmed the directions we are taking in responding to the Hilmer Report,.<br />
and the initiatives announced in Working Nation.<br />
Australian agri-food companies, with their high quality, low cost products and<br />
high skills bases, are already increasing our presence in Asian food markets.<br />
In the past 2 years, exports of highly processed food have increased by<br />
$ 900 million or 39%,<br />
It is this type of success that my Government is laying the foundations for<br />
through the initiatives of Working Nation.<br />
Also, through expert studies such as those I heard about today at the Science<br />
and Engineering Council, we will be able to take a long term view, putting in<br />
pl ace the policies and programs that will secure an innovative and<br />
competitive future for all Australians.<br />
CANBERRA 24 June 1994 TEL L'-4 . JU </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
