<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6369</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, HOUSING INDUSTRY CONVENTION, ADELAIDE, 14 APRIL 1984</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/04/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006369.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHEC AGANSTDEULNITERIYLE MlB-A RAG. OME. D<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
HOUSING INDUSTRY CONVENTION ADELAIDE 14 APRIL 1984<br />
Thank you for inviting me to address you today, and thank<br />
you particularly for the welcome conveyed just now by your<br />
National President.<br />
It is a pleasure to address the Housing Industry Association<br />
at its Nineteenth National Convention. We hayve seen much of<br />
each other in the past year, a year which has been a very<br />
exciting one for the Government and for the housing<br />
industry.<br />
Although, as Mr Graham points out, we have not always agreed<br />
with each other on every issue, I can say that we have come<br />
to respect deeply the expertise and experience of the<br />
Housing Industry Association's executive and are very<br />
grateful for their important contribution to the development<br />
of the Government housing policies over the past year.<br />
Mr Graham has just mentioned that we have always been<br />
available to speak with the Housing Industry Association in<br />
the past. Let me assure you that the Government will always<br />
be available for consultation in the future too.<br />
We have been in Government now for just over a year. It is<br />
timely to stand back and recognise just what has been<br />
achieved. In particular, given the high priority the<br />
Government places upon housing, and given the parlous state<br />
of the industry when we were elected, the Government is<br />
particularly proud of what has been achieved in the housing<br />
a r ea.<br />
The high priority the Labor Government has placed upon<br />
housing has reflected our strong philosophic commitment to<br />
the right of all Australians to decent, affordable<br />
accommodation. Stability in both the home building industry<br />
and in the supply of reasonably priced housing finance are<br />
key aims of our policy approach.<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY </p>
<p>The Government believes its obligations to Australian<br />
families extend beyond providing a favourable environment in<br />
which most are able to arrange their own accommodation.<br />
There are significant groups in the community who are at a<br />
disadvantage when it comes to buying their own homes, or<br />
even affording market prices for rented accommodation.<br />
For example, young couples are usually among the lowest<br />
income earners and least wealthy in the community and face<br />
an enormous hurdle in'buying their first home.<br />
Owning a home is usually so important to promoting attitudes<br />
of confidence in the future, enabling young couples to<br />
establish their positions in the community and plan their<br />
families. Successive Australian Governments have recognised<br />
an obligation to assist this group, and have implemented<br />
various schemes to assist first home buyers over the years.<br />
Further, the Government believes it has an obligation to<br />
assist other disadvantaged groups in the community such as<br />
the unemployed, the elderly, the sick, deserted wives,<br />
supporting mothers with their accommodation needs.<br />
Accordingly for many years, Commonwealth and State<br />
Governments have co-operated in an endeavour to assist these<br />
groups through the Commonwealth State Housing Agreement..<br />
This Government looks forward to the day when all<br />
Australians, no matter what their circumstances, are<br />
decently housed. Homelessness, fear of eviction and<br />
inadequate housing have no place in our vision of<br />
Australia's future.<br />
The Government has worked determinedly to promote its<br />
housing objectives in the past year. But no Government ever<br />
achieves anything on its own. It is always dependent upon<br />
the co-operation and goodwill of many others in the<br />
community. One~ of the best examples of how the consultative process has<br />
shaped our policies is the development of the First Home<br />
Owners Scheme. Mr Graham has just recalled how this was the<br />
outcome of a meeting between the Government and the Housing<br />
Industry Association at the National Economic Summit<br />
Conference in April last year. And everyone acknowledges<br />
the important contribution this Scheme has made to the<br />
recovery now underway in the private home building industry<br />
and to the turnaround in the economy more generally.<br />
That such a successful scheme was the outcome of the Summit<br />
Conference is, of course, testament to the value of that<br />
experiment in the formulation of important national policies<br />
and priorities.<br />
On present estimates some $ 147 million will be allocated to<br />
the new scheme this financial year, assisting some 70,000<br />
first home buyers. </p>
<p>3.<br />
The First Home Owners Scheme has been an important plank in<br />
the Government's overall effort to get things moving in the<br />
Housing Industry.<br />
You will recall that * after consultation with the industry,<br />
my Minister for Housing and Construction, Chris Hurford,<br />
announced in April 1983 that the Government had set itself<br />
as an objective that it should secure a massive increase in<br />
the number of housing commencements from the trough level of<br />
105,000 in 1982-83 to an annual rate of 130,000 to 135,000<br />
by the second half of 1983-84.<br />
This objective represented a statement of the Government's<br />
confidence in, and commitment to, the home building<br />
industry. It is an important benchmark against which we<br />
were prepared to judge the success of our policies. And, I<br />
am glad to say, the indications are that our objective will<br />
easily be achieved.<br />
Further, the Government has moved to give effect to its<br />
commitment to assisting needy groups within the community to<br />
obtain decent accommodation in the 1983-84 Budget. We<br />
provided a massive 50 per cent increase in funding under the<br />
Commonwealth State Housing Agreement. This arrangement is<br />
presently under review, and we have every intention of<br />
preserving its integrity as an effective instrument of a<br />
truly needs-based housing policy which is attuned to the<br />
requirements of Australia today.<br />
More generally, the Government has recognised the importance<br />
of sound and stable macro-economic policies in promoting a<br />
healthy and vigorous housing industry. The private sector<br />
accounts for by far the lion's share of housing activity in<br />
this country. This sector, quite properly, looks to the<br />
Government to conduct its macro economic policies in such a<br />
way as to engender confidence in the future prospects of the<br />
industry. Theze are two macro-economic forces which will particularly<br />
impact adversely on activity in the housing industry: a high<br />
and variable rate of inflation, and a level of public demand<br />
for real resources so high that it constrains private<br />
ac t iv ity<br />
The last thing this Government wants is to allow either of<br />
these forces to damage either the housing recovery or the<br />
economy more generally. The centrepiece of our<br />
macro-economic policies the Prices and Incomes Accord is<br />
specifically designed to keep inflation in check by seeking<br />
agreement from trade unions to contain wage demands to no<br />
more than past price increases. A matching commitment to<br />
restrain non-wage incomes was given by key employers and<br />
professional groups at the time of the Economic Summit and<br />
in subsequent correspondence. </p>
<p>Progress on the inflation front has been remarkably swift,<br />
and the rate of inflation is now significantly lower than<br />
when we took office a year ago. We would like to see it<br />
lower still. Indeed, the CPI is likely to have recorded<br />
hardly any movement at all in the March quarter, which<br />
given indexation bodes well for our prospects of retaining<br />
those hard-won gains against inflation.<br />
On the issue~ of public sector competition for real<br />
resources, I note Mr Graham's call for more expenditure<br />
restraint by the Commonwealth and a lower budget deficit in<br />
1984-85. The massive budget deficit this financial year was<br />
part of our inheritance when we took office.<br />
The Treasurer Paul Keating and I have repeatedly<br />
committed the Government to exercising expenditure restraint<br />
and reducing the budget deficit in 1984-85. You can again<br />
be assured that we are making every effort to find ways of<br />
achieving sensible reductions in Commonwealth expenditures<br />
and reducing the deficit in the next budget.<br />
I say sensible reductions because there is hardly any point<br />
in cutting expenditure back so far that domestic demand is<br />
contracted so sharply that unemployment begins to rise<br />
again. However, it must be recognised that it is not only<br />
the Commonwealth which draws resources away from the private<br />
sector. Particularly with building resources, it is the State sector<br />
too that must exercise restraint in 1984-85. We will be<br />
emphasising this point to our State Government colleagues in<br />
the upcoming Premiers' Conference Loan Council round.<br />
High rates of inflation and high levels of public sector<br />
spending can both produce upward pressures on interest<br />
rates, which also harm the housing industry, particularly<br />
because they adveresly affect both the cost and the<br />
availability of home finance. Needless to say, the success<br />
of t~ he Government's housing policies requires an adequate<br />
and stable flow of finance to the specialist home loan<br />
institutions savings banks and permanent building<br />
s oc ie t ies<br />
1983-84 has been an easy year for home finance with<br />
finance usually readily available and at lower interest<br />
rates than a year or so ago. However, this may not always<br />
be the case, especially as the economic recovery begins to<br />
be reflected in other industries.<br />
Last year, the Government commissioned the Martin Group to<br />
report on the Australian financial system. The terms of<br />
reference of that inquiry included the Government's<br />
commitment to ensuring adequate finance for housing. The<br />
savings banks are central to that and, as you know, it was<br />
announced last Tuesday that the Government would phase out<br />
remaining size and maturity controls on savings banks'<br />
deposits. This is a first step, if a small one. </p>
<p>Other issues raised by the Martin Group including that of<br />
the deregulation of home loan interest rates are of great<br />
importance and decisions on them will not be rushed. The<br />
Government is hoping to have further public debate on the<br />
issues involved and in the true spirit of consultation<br />
which is our hallmark we would welcome your views.<br />
So much for policy issues. Let me now turn to the " good<br />
news" of what has been happening recently. It is no<br />
exaggeration to say that there has been a spectacular<br />
recovery in the housing industry.<br />
This recovery is confirmed by every recent economic<br />
indicator on housing: these include the December quarter<br />
national accounts estimates on capital expenditure on<br />
dwellings, monthly figures on home finance approvals, data<br />
on building approvals granted by local government, estimates<br />
on dwelling commencements; the list goes on.<br />
Some selected examples of what the figures are showing: the<br />
latest national accounts show a seasonally-adjusted real<br />
increase in investment in dwellings of 7 per cent in the<br />
December quarter 1983, following a 7 per cent increase in<br />
the September quarter. What a contrast to twelve months ago<br />
the bottom of the recession when investment in dwellings<br />
had fallen some 36 per cent below its previous peak level in<br />
December 1981.<br />
The same trend is also apparent in the home loan figures<br />
for example, savings banks provided finance for nearly 11<br />
per cent more dwellings in the December quarter 1983, which<br />
was itself up some 10 per cent on the June quarter. Again,<br />
these trends are in sharp contrast to the home lending<br />
figures a year ago.<br />
Further, the figures indicate that the recovery is spread<br />
right across Australia, and is strongest in States where the<br />
recession hit hardest.<br />
They also suggest that the recovery has been particularly<br />
marked since the introduction of the First Home Owners<br />
Scheme last October.<br />
What about the future? A fortnight ago, a report released<br />
by the Indicative Planning Council on the housing industry<br />
forecast some 135,000 dwelling commencements in 1983-84<br />
the same figure just mentioned by Mr Graham.<br />
This represents no less than 29 per cent growth over the<br />
level of 1982-83. Since this full-year figure represents<br />
fairly steep growth through the year, there can be no doubt<br />
that the annual rate in the second half year will easily<br />
exceed our target range of 130,000 to 135,000 commencements. </p>
<p>The Government's earlier confidence that the housing<br />
industry would pull off such a dramatic recovery will, in<br />
the event, be amply justified.<br />
We cannot, and should not expect a repeat performance of<br />
these growth rates next year. The housing industry in<br />
1983-84 has done a magnificent job some might have said<br />
earlier an impossible job. But the circumstances of the<br />
recovery have been very favourable: housing finance has been<br />
readily available, resources were left considerably<br />
under-utilised after the recent recession, the First Home<br />
Owners Scheme gave a strong one-off fillip to demand last<br />
year The task before us now is to sustain what has already been<br />
achieved, to prevent the " bubble from bursting". On this<br />
matter, the IPC's forecasts give us all reason for<br />
encouragement they indicate dwelling commencements<br />
reaching a " plateau" of some 145,000 in 1984-85.<br />
But we cannot take this for granted. If we are to sustain<br />
next year what we have all worked so hard to acheive this<br />
year, we must continue what we began last year.<br />
There must be an ongoing process of consultation and<br />
discussion between all parties involved in the housing<br />
industry. Only if we continue to work together can we<br />
expect to consolidate these achievements.<br />
Judging by the relationship we have already established<br />
together, and by Mr Graham's very positive remarks in his<br />
opening address, I am personally very confident of a bright<br />
outlook for the housing industry in 1984-85.<br />
Before moving on to open this convention formally I should<br />
say a few words about the vexed question of the operation of<br />
the prescribed payments system or " withholding tax" as it<br />
is more commonly known.<br />
We know the industry has problems with this tax and has made<br />
several representations to the Government expressing its<br />
concerns. It is not the style of this Government to ignore<br />
genuine and constructive criticisms of any of its policies.<br />
On the matter of this tax, we have already moderated its<br />
impact by relaxing the exemption conditions following<br />
representations from the industry. This has resulted in the<br />
issue of some 29,000 exemptions and 99,000 variations by 3<br />
March this year.<br />
As a result, the tax has not produced the revenue originally<br />
expected. However, we recognise that the industry still has<br />
considerable difficulty with the tax and, as Mr Graham has<br />
already mentioned, the Government will be conducting a<br />
review of the system. Naturally, we will be keen for close<br />
consultation with the industry during the conduct of the<br />
re v iew </p>
<p>7.<br />
Mr President, just before I officially open your Convention,<br />
I have another pleasant task to perform. Peers in the<br />
industry consider that you have done an excellent job as<br />
President of the Association and that you have tendered<br />
distinguished service to the industry at large. They have<br />
elected you to the office of life Member and it gives me a<br />
great deal of pleasure, John, to be able to present you with<br />
your Life Membership Certificate. Congratulations!<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen, I know that whatever task the<br />
Association takes on, it does so with vigour, determination<br />
and considerable professionalism. I have the first copy of<br />
your new National Journal " Housing Australia" and I'm sure<br />
it will be still going strong many years from now. It is my<br />
pleasure to launch the Journal.<br />
I have also had an opportunity to look through your<br />
conference propgram. I was delighted to see that my old<br />
friend and son of South Australia Darcy Hoysted will be<br />
giving the luncheon address on Monday. Darcy has given me<br />
good advice and help regarding renovations to. my home in<br />
Melbourne and I hope to be able to call on him when<br />
renovations are undertaken at The Lodge.<br />
In the meantime I have much pleasure in declaring this<br />
Convention open. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
