<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2231</transcript-id>
    <title>OFFSHORE MINERALS LEGISLATION - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR JOHN GORTON</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/05/1970</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002231.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS P. M. No 58/ 1970<br />
( FFSHORE MINERALS LEGISLATION Y<br />
StateMent bytePrm inister, Mr. John Gorton<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr. Gorton, announced today that the<br />
Mmister for National Development as President of the Australian Minerals<br />
Council had invited the State Ministers for Mines to attend a meeting of the<br />
Council which would be held in Adelaide on Tuesday 9th June.<br />
Early next week and well prior to the meeting of 9th June, the<br />
Commonwealth would send to the States the draft Offshore M1ining Bill together<br />
with the Heads of Agreement suggested by the Commonwealth to be the basis<br />
of arrangements between the Commonwealth and the States for the administration<br />
of the legislation. The Offshore Mining Bill would not be introduced into the Commonwealth<br />
Parliament until after the discussions with the States in the Australian Minerals<br />
Council. In the meantime the debate on the Territorial Sea and Continental<br />
Shelf Bill which was introduced in the Federal Parliament on 16 April, would be<br />
held over until after the meeting.<br />
Mr. Gorton said that the Commonwealth Government remained<br />
firmly of the view that it was highly desirable in Australia's national and<br />
international interests to have the legal position as, to the respective jurisdiction<br />
of the Commonwealth and the States in offshore areas resolved as soon as<br />
possible. As had been indicated by the Minister ffor National Development in<br />
his second reading speech on the Territorial Sea and Continental Shelf Bill on<br />
16th April 1970, this would be a matter for decision by the courts.<br />
Mr. Gorton added that as an earnest of the Commonwealth's desire<br />
to see this matter settled, the Commonwealth Government had decided that it<br />
would meet the legal costs of the States in conducting their case. Although<br />
the Commonwealth wished to see the issues determined by the High Court, this<br />
in no way detracted from the Commonwealth's wish to work in close co-operation<br />
with the States in the effective and eff ic ient administration of Australia's off shore<br />
areas. With this in mind the Minister for National Development at the meeting<br />
of the Australian Minerals Council on 9th June would be seeking to establish<br />
a sound working relationship between the State Governments and the<br />
Commonwealth Government.<br />
CANBERRA May 1970 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
