<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7590</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT OF THE PARLIAMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER OF SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY 8 MAY 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/05/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007590.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
STATEMENT TO THE PARLIAMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
ON SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY<br />
8 MAY 1989<br />
As never before, scientific and technological developments<br />
are altering the lives of every person, changing the face of<br />
nations, cultures and the international economy, and even<br />
throwing into question the very environment in which we<br />
live.<br />
Medical discoveries are offering relief for the sick and<br />
injured, helping childless couples to have children, opening<br />
broader horizons for the elderly. Researchers are providing<br />
new drugs and new surgical techniques and are even probing<br />
the nature of life itself.<br />
New manufacturing techniques are revolutionising the way we<br />
work, the way we travel, what we eat, how we live.<br />
Computers store and manipulate information in quantities and<br />
with a speed that would have been inconceivable a few<br />
decades ago.<br />
Rapid communications are delivering instant news throughout<br />
an apparently shrunken world, criss-crossed with optical<br />
fibre networks and surrounded by satellites.<br />
Concepts of warfare today are largely unrecognisable to<br />
those who fought in the Second World War.<br />
Even the most basic cycle of our climate, the purity of the<br />
air we breathe, the very borders between sea and land, seem<br />
affected by technology. Problems such as the Greenhouse<br />
Effect and the depletion of the ozone layer are real issues<br />
today that even in the last decade would have seemed<br />
incredible outside the pages of science fiction.<br />
one possible response to this vast process of change is<br />
despair the feeling that attempting to control the<br />
seemingly remote forces of unleashed innovation is futile.<br />
Honourable members who are in contact with their<br />
constituents will know that many people, especially many<br />
younger Australians, do indeed border on despair when they<br />
contemplate the dangers of nuclear war and the despoliation<br />
of the environment.<br />
A more realistic reAWpe -is-t o attempt to understand the<br />
nature of these cha nges and to harness the best endeavours<br />
of all people to ensure that the forces of science and<br />
technology yield a better future for mankind.<br />
The march of technological change where it seems possible<br />
that it might only lead to a polluted, clamorous, dangerous<br />
and uncertain world must be made to serve our needs and to<br />
create a world in which our children and grandchildren can<br />
live at ease. </p>
<p>Indeed, if Australians of the next century are to inhabit a<br />
prosperous nation and a clean and safe world, we today must<br />
grasp the challenge of gaining control of the processes of<br />
scientific and technological innovation and ensure that we<br />
receive benefit, not disadvantage, from change.<br />
This is a challenge that confronts all Australians.<br />
Australians of course are used to enjoying a quality of life<br />
equal or superior to that anywhere in the world.<br />
But just as we accept that our predecessors had to work hard<br />
to build this society, so we must recognise that retaining<br />
such advantages, so as to pass them on to our children, will<br />
require hard work and constant effort.<br />
Since this Government came to office in 1983, we have been<br />
single minded in our determination to ensure that such an<br />
effort is made.<br />
A crucial foundation for the pursuit of our wider goals is<br />
our adoption of the most wide ranging and comprehensive<br />
program of structural adjustment in Australia's history.<br />
We have taken the decisions tough ones, many of them to<br />
create a more internationally competitive economy and to<br />
remove the impediments which prevent industries and<br />
individuals from making their fullest contribution to<br />
national prosperity.<br />
In this endeavour, science and technology continue to have<br />
an essential role to play.<br />
They can open the way for Australia's manufacturing and<br />
service industries to be more competitive, and for the men<br />
and women who make up the Australian workforce to be more<br />
productive. Our agricultural and mining industries, our medical<br />
researchers, our astronomers, our communications specialists<br />
are already showing the way, not just with new techniques<br />
and new products that can be sold abroad, but with new<br />
knowledge, on which no price tag can be placed.<br />
This Government is determined that Australia will not fall<br />
behind. We are committed to maintaining and enhancing the<br />
proven excellence of our researchers, allowing them to<br />
further the horizons of basic research and to contribute<br />
through their creativity and innovation to Australia's<br />
goals. Mr Acting Speaker,<br />
Since coming to office my Government has pursued a<br />
consistent science and technology strategy. </p>
<p>This strategy recognises that crucial elements of research<br />
must be supported by public funds. It adopts as two<br />
important objectives the pursuit of excellence and the<br />
closer co-operation between researchers and users of that<br />
research. It recognises that science and technology depend<br />
on the creativity of individuals. And finally, it seeks to<br />
integrate science and technology into the broader community.<br />
In pursuit of that strategy, research into science and<br />
technology in Australia is supported by public funds<br />
totalling about $ 1.9 billion annually, through direct<br />
funding, through institutions of higher education and<br />
through tax concessions.<br />
We have introduced new research and development promotion<br />
and incentive schemes, and reorganised our research<br />
organisations. There has been a massive expansion of higher education<br />
places and a dramatically lifted school retention rate.<br />
The best Australian research can now receive increased<br />
support, as researchers must now win a proportion of their<br />
funding by competing with others against a variety of<br />
standards, some involving peer review and others commercial<br />
criteria. Since 1982-83, Government support for research through<br />
grants, higher education and Government agencies has risen<br />
by 12 per cent in real terms. Support for industry research<br />
and development has trebled.<br />
Public funding of research and development in Australia is<br />
at about the middle order of OECD nations. But private<br />
sector support has been near the bottom of the ladder. When<br />
this Government came to office, 80 per cent of the nation's<br />
research activities were publicly funded, with private<br />
industry providing the remaining 20 per cent. By 1986-87,<br />
within a substantial increase in total R and D expenditure,<br />
industry had increased its share in the nation's research<br />
effort to 35 per cent.<br />
This is a welcome trend. But with this Statement today, the<br />
Government is saying that it recognises that more needs to<br />
be done.<br />
More needs to be done both to enhance our efforts in the<br />
quest for knowledge, as well as to ensure that a sufficient<br />
research effort is directed to areas of crucial application<br />
for Australia. Ok6iA--<br />
The details of the Government's initiatives will be<br />
announced directly by the Minister for Science, Customs and<br />
Small Business, Barry Jones. </p>
<p>Let me take this opportunity first to pay tribute to this<br />
Minister's determined and far-sighted advocacy of these<br />
issues. He is a minister who makes an invaluable<br />
contribution to the Government's consideration of science<br />
issues and one in whom the science community can place its<br />
trust and confidence.<br />
The first element of the Government's statement that I wish<br />
to announce today is that I will be appointing Mr Jones as<br />
Minister Assisting the Prime Minister-for Science and<br />
Technology. In this role Mr Jones, who will retain his existing<br />
portfolio duties, will exercise on my behalf the day to day<br />
responsibility for the development and co-ordination of<br />
science policy across the Government.<br />
I also announce the establishment of a new consultative body<br />
which will bring together at the highest level all those who<br />
have a role to play in setting the nation's priorities in<br />
science and technology.<br />
This new body will be known as the Prime Minister's Science<br />
Council. I will chair it and Mr Jones will be its Deputy<br />
Chairman. Its membership will consist of Government<br />
ministers, representatives of the science community and<br />
leaders of Australian industry.<br />
The first meeting of the Council is to be held in October.<br />
At the top of its agenda will be a consideration of the<br />
status of science in Australia covering both the state of<br />
research in Australia and the nature and effectiveness of<br />
linkages between research and industry. The October meeting<br />
will also consider the Greenhouse Effect, to the research on<br />
which the Government has recently provided $ 7.8 million.<br />
I want my Council to bring a new focus and prominence to<br />
discussions on Australia's national priorities in scientific<br />
research and a new capacity to make sure that our aims in<br />
basic and applied science are properly set and implemented.<br />
To assist in this, I am appointing Professor Ralph Slatyer<br />
as Chief Scientist. He will assist me and Mr Jones on<br />
science and technology policy, chair the Science and<br />
Technology Co-ordinating Committee and serve on and be the<br />
Executive officer of my new Council.<br />
Professor Slatyer is a scientist of national and<br />
international distinction, both in research and in the<br />
-development of scier'~ ndd t~ chnology policy. He has served<br />
as Chairman of the World Heritage Committee, President of<br />
the International Scientific Committee on Problems of the<br />
Environment and most recently as chairman of the Australian<br />
Science and Technology Council.<br />
The Australian Science and Technology Council which has been<br />
providing analysis of developments in Australian science and<br />
technology throughout the term of my Government will<br />
continue to provide this valuable service. </p>
<p>Indeed, I expect ASTEC to make a substantial contribution to<br />
the success of the new arrangements I have just announced<br />
and to enjoy an enhanced role as a result of them.<br />
Mr Acting Speaker,<br />
This statement is based on extensive consultation with the<br />
science and technology community, and on detailed reviews<br />
both of specific problems and of the broader needs and<br />
concerns of scientists.<br />
It brings together, as the Government promised it would, all<br />
the strands of the Government's support of science and<br />
technology research throughout a number of portfolios.<br />
This statement does not represent a conclusion to the debate<br />
about science and technology in Australia, nor a reaction to<br />
it. It represents a contribution, and I believe a very<br />
significant one, to a continuing process of policy<br />
development. It provides for the expenditure of an additional $ 390<br />
million over the next five years in order to boost<br />
Australia's science and technology performance. Taken with<br />
the anticipated revenue foregone due to the extension of tax<br />
concessions, this represents a $ 1 billion package of support<br />
for science and technology in Australia.<br />
This statement represents our recognition that the pace of<br />
change in this country cannot be relaxed. We cannot rest on<br />
our laurels. The world will not let us do so.<br />
Mr Acting Speaker,<br />
No Australian wants * to leave it up to the rest of the world<br />
to make the decisions that are so important to shaping our<br />
future.<br />
With this Statement, we are showing our determination that<br />
Australia will be a full participant in the exciting and<br />
vital processes of scientific discovery, innovation and<br />
adaptation. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
