<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>16228</transcript-id>
    <title>Joint Media Release with Minister for  Innovation, Industry, Science and Research,  Kim Carr  A New Car Plan for a Greener Future  </title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/11/2008</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Prime Minister Kevin Rudd today announced a $6.2 billion plan to make the automotive industry more economically and environmentally sustainable by 2020.</p>
<p>The Green Car Plan will feature an expanded $1.3 billion Green Car Innovation Fund which will provide Australian car companies with the opportunity to receive Government funding to design and sell environmentally friendly cars.</p>
<p>The Innovation Fund will see the Australian Government match industry investment in green cars on a $1 dollar to $3 dollar basis over a ten year period from 2009.</p>
<p>This is another chapter in the Rudd Government's green investment strategy to transform Australia's economy into a low-carbon emission, internationally-competitive economy of the future.</p>
<p>This is decisive and strong action to protect the Australian economy during the global financial crisis.</p>
<p>The 13-year New Car Plan for a Greener Future is about manufacturing competitive, low-emission, fuel-efficient vehicles in Australia. It will create well-paid, highly-skilled green jobs for the future.</p>
<p>The plan is expected to generate $16 billion in investment in the Australian automotive industry over the life of the plan.</p>
<p>Further the overall Green Car Plan will provide:</p>
<p>     * A better-targeted, greener, $3.4 billion assistance program, the Automotive Transformation Scheme (ATS), running from 2011 to 2020;</p>
<p>     * Changes to the Automotive Competitiveness and Investment Scheme in 2010, consistent with the Bracks review proposals, to smooth the transition to the ATS ($79.6 million);</p>
<p>     * $116.3 million to promote structural adjustment through consolidation in the components sector and to facilitate labour market adjustment;</p>
<p>     * $20 million from 2009 - 10 to help suppliers improve their capabilities and their integration in complex national and global supply chains;</p>
<p>     * $6.3 million from 2009 - 10 for an enhanced market access program;</p>
<p>     * A new Automotive Industry Innovation Council, bringing key decision makers together to drive innovation and reform; and</p>
<p>     * A $10.5 million expansion of the LPG vehicle scheme, to start immediately, that doubles payments to purchasers of new vehicles using LPG technology.</p>
<p>The plan implements the recommendations of the Review of the automotive industry, including a reformed Automotive Transformation Scheme, an expanded Green Car Innovation Fund, and measures to promote industry competitiveness.</p>
<p>Automotive tariffs will be cut to 5 per cent, giving Australia the third-lowest tariff regime among economies with a well-developed automotive industry.</p>
<p>Australia will continue to pursue a free trade agenda because the future of the industry lies in innovation and global integration, not industry protection with old fashioned quotas and tariffs.</p>
<p>The $7.7 billion automotive industry is critical to Australia's economic future because it employs over 60 000 Australians, and is critical to national R&amp;D and exports.</p>
<p>Automotive manufacturing sits at the core the nation's manufacturing effort, because building a modern car involves almost every advanced technology we use, from microchips to light metals.</p>
<p>Only 15 or so countries in the world can design, engineer and build a car from scratch and we are determined to maintain that capacity.</p>
<p>The plan has a high level of support at the beginning to accelerate reform and renewal, eventually tapering down to zero.</p>
<p>The plan works in four key areas. It will:</p>
<p>     * Attract new investment in long-term, sustainable vehicle production;</p>
<p>     * Green the industry  -  improving fuel efficiency and reducing carbon emissions;</p>
<p>     * Strengthen the local supply chain and boost skills; and</p>
<p>     * Link to international supply chains and improve market access for Australian manufacturers.</p>
<p>A New Car Plan for a Greener Future provides the investment certainty the industry needs as it adjusts to significant new challenges.</p>
<p>The plan demonstrates the government's commitment to modern manufacturing and to providing high-skill, high-wage jobs for Australians.</p>
<p>For more information on A New Car Plan for a Greener Future, including the full government response to the Review of Australia's Automotive Industry, visit <a href="http://www.innovation.gov.au/automotivereview">www.innovation.gov.au/automotivereview</a></p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
