<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11075</transcript-id>
    <title>19 November 1999                     TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER          THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP          RADIO INTERVIEW WITH NEIL MITCHELL, 3AW                              </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/11/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Subjects: executive salaries; sub-contractors; Illegal immigrants; Alan</p>
<p>   Jones and John Laws; East Timor; Jeff Kennett; Andrew Peacock; media laws;</p>
<p>   Pura Milk Cup; Hey Hey It's Saturday.</p>
<p>E&amp;OE..........</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>  The Prime Minister, Mr John Howard. Good morning.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Hello Neil. Good to be with you.</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>  Thank you for your time.</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>  Mr Howard. Are things getting a bit out of whack in Australia? We've got</p>
<p>   Bureau of Statistics figures showing profits have gone up 17.3% in the year</p>
<p>   to September. Wages have gone up 1.8% which means they're going backwards.</p>
<p>   But that has to cause demands from the union, it has to cause division.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>You've got to remember that one of the reasons why employment has risen</p>
<p>   and unemployment has fallen is that firms are more profitable and some of</p>
<p>   that profit share is going into higher employment levels. So it's not immediately</p>
<p>   quite as you put it. If you're asking me whether at a time of general economic</p>
<p>   prosperity, examples in the corporate sector of excessive levels of remuneration</p>
<p>   for example cause some resentment in the workforce, well the answer is yes.</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>  Well look at Coles-Myer's Dennis Eck. Four million dollar salary, $8 million</p>
<p>   share bonus.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I'm not going to personalise it because I don't believe that the Government</p>
<p>   should ever entertain the idea of interfering in remuneration levels of</p>
<p>   corporate executives, and I recognise that there are competitive forces</p>
<p>   involved. But what I would say to corporate Australia is that you've got</p>
<p>   to exercise a degree of restraint and self-surveillance. You've got to understand</p>
<p>   that at a time of generic economic plenty, if it looks as though one part</p>
<p>   of the community is over indulging itself or helping itself too readily</p>
<p>   that will cause resentment. Just as people in public life are required to</p>
<p>   exercise reasonable restraint, so it is people in corporate life have got</p>
<p>   to do so.</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>  Well they're failing to at the moment.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well some do. I mean let's keep a sense of proportion, and I'm the last</p>
<p>   person to condemn the need to remunerate the chief executives of Australian</p>
<p>   companies at appropriate levels, at levels that are sufficient to attract</p>
<p>   the right people. But in all of these things there is a sense of proportion</p>
<p>   and a sense of balance and we've all got to understand. I've certainly recognised</p>
<p>   it, and my colleagues I know recognise it. But although we are as a nation</p>
<p>   very strong economically at the moment, there are areas that are missing</p>
<p>   out and at a time of general economic plenty, if you're missing out you</p>
<p>   feel it all the more keenly. You feel as though it's passing you by, that</p>
<p>   other people are getting it and you're not. And I do understand that and</p>
<p>   it's therefore very important in all of our actions of the Government, and</p>
<p>   it's also important that corporate Australia in all of its actions as corporate</p>
<p>   Australia understand that there are gaps between the not so well off and</p>
<p>   the well off in the community. And we as a people that have always prided</p>
<p>   ourselves on being very egalitarian and having the largest middle class</p>
<p>   in the world. That used to be one of our proudest boasts. We've got to make</p>
<p>   sure we retain as much of that as we possibly can.</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>  So you do agree that some of these salary packages are just over the top?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think the perception of some of them is over the top. Absolutely.</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>  Bank bosses in particular are cleaning up, Coles-Myer.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I mean look, I don't want to get, because I don't think it's fair of me</p>
<p>   to start singling out individuals. I'm not going to do that. I'm making</p>
<p>   a general observation. It is not reading well in the general community.</p>
<p>   Now, I mean quite properly business has a go at the Government when.and</p>
<p>   individuals in the Government when they think we're doing the wrong thing,</p>
<p>   or not doing the right thing, I mean in different economic areas I just</p>
<p>   make the observation that there is a responsibility on corporate Australia</p>
<p>   to recognise that just as in politics perceptions..just as in politics so</p>
<p>   it is in business that perception is important as well as the reality of</p>
<p>   the situation and it is not necessarily a good thing, it's certainly not</p>
<p>   a good thing at a time when the whole country is so strong economically</p>
<p>   but there are others who are.some who are missing out quite badly the perception</p>
<p>   is that some are getting more than a fair crack of the whip.</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Okay. We're getting some calls about this immediately, but I'd like some</p>
<p>   other questions too. But Cameron, go ahead please Cameron.</p>
<p>  CALLER:</p>
<p>Yeah Mr Prime Minister, I was interested in you saying that you wouldn't</p>
<p>   interfere in executive wages but then again you'll go and you'll interfere</p>
<p>   with workers' wages.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No I don't interfere with workers wages.</p>
<p>  CALLER:</p>
<p>  I think the Government does by pressuring, and bring the point to the..</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well we go to the..I'm sorry, with respect Cameron, Cameron?</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>  Yep that's right.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  What we do is we go to the commission and put our case, this is for essentially</p>
<p>   the minimum wage case, but our philosophy more generally in relation to</p>
<p>   wage levels in the community is that you have a guaranteed standard and</p>
<p>   then what you get over and above that is a matter of negotiation between</p>
<p>   you and your employer, or between your union and the employer. Now that's</p>
<p>   our general philosophy. We don't seek to put a limit on that. We leave that</p>
<p>   to the individual bosses or employers and employees. Now my point is that</p>
<p>   you can't as a Government start controlling wages. That's crazy. It won't</p>
<p>   work and it's anti free enterprise. But you can exercise a degree of self</p>
<p>   restraint and be sensitive to the fact that when the whole nation is doing</p>
<p>   well the people who are missing out, and there are a lot who are missing</p>
<p>   out and I know that and in understand that, they're going to feel it all</p>
<p>   the more keenly if they think some are getting more than a fair share.</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Well is it fair to say that what you're saying to some of corporate Australia</p>
<p>   is exercise restraint?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Yes absolutely.</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>  Okay. Mary go ahead please.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes Mary.</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>  Yes hello. I'd like to complain to you about the wages that have been [inaudible]</p>
<p>   here. That's okay if they get a lot of money if the service is okay. Now</p>
<p>   you walk into a bank, it's absolutely atrocious. You walk into Coles-Myer,</p>
<p>   I mean they are the worst offenders in the world. Their shop [inaudible]</p>
<p>   looks like a shambles. It's actually impossible to get some service in there.</p>
<p>   So it's okay if they actually make the money as long as they provide a service</p>
<p>   [inaudible].</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>I guess it's the customer's decision in the end whether you walk in...</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yeah look, I'm not..I mean you've named two companies. Can I say I'm not</p>
<p>   criticising those companies' quality of service. I mean I'm not a customer</p>
<p>   of the Commonwealth Bank. I bank with another bank. My impression is that</p>
<p>   Coles-Myer run a very good operation and their staff are very friendly.</p>
<p>   That's the experience I've had. But look, I'm not getting into individual</p>
<p>   companies. I'm making a general point.</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>  We have got a pretty big gap there though don't we? Even accepting your</p>
<p>   point about reinvestment. With 17.3% increase in wages..in profits, 17.3</p>
<p>   profits, 1.8% increase in wages. It's a big gap.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I understand that but you've got to understand that all of these figures</p>
<p>   are aggregate figures and we have had a huge improvement in employment.</p>
<p>   But the other thing you've got to remember Neil is that the thing that matters</p>
<p>   and that is the take home pay has gone up a lot in real terms because on</p>
<p>   top of everything else, also there's been a very significant reduction in</p>
<p>   interest rates. Even though they've just gone up by a tick recently the</p>
<p>   average mortgage is $300 a month cheaper now than it was four years ago</p>
<p>   and that means a lot for the average family.</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>  A bit more pressure on rates from the United States this week too.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yeah well the United States is the United States and Australia is Australia.</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>  Okay. But it leads me to another area if we may just quickly, I talked to</p>
<p>   the Treasurer about this earlier in the week. Tax changes for sub-contractors.</p>
<p>   It's looking to me like an administrative nightmare. It's full of anomalies,</p>
<p>   almost like another assets test. Are you wedded to this system?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well it was recommended by Ralph. The short answer is we think it's a good</p>
<p>   reform, we think it's fair because what it will do is prevent people who</p>
<p>   are carrying on a particular activity in reality as an employee turning</p>
<p>   themselves into a company purely for the purpose of reducing their tax liability.</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>That's fair enough but it seems it's going to catch a lot of genuine sub-contractors</p>
<p>   in there as well.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well I'm not sure that that is right. I mean there are certain criteria</p>
<p>   that are going to be applied. I mean for example in the building industry</p>
<p>   contractors are not in any way going to be denied legitimate deductions.</p>
<p>   It's not going to alter their status in an industrial relations sense.</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>  I mean it's not hard for, in the building industry, even a barrister, to</p>
<p>   find themselves working for one employer for a year. Even though they're</p>
<p>   still a sub-contractor, they get the big job and they spend a year getting</p>
<p>   their income from one source. Now under the 80% rule they're now taxed as</p>
<p>   PAYE taxpayers.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well barristers are now aren't they?</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>  No no, they're business.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  No no barristers...</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>  They're the equivalent of sub-contractors.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well no. Well no, I mean the last barrister I spoke to sort of paid tax</p>
<p>   as an individual. He's not incorporated.</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>  Okay. Well we'll take them out of it. I talked to Mr Costello, he seemed</p>
<p>   to think some of them were. But take them out of it. What about the building</p>
<p>   worker who is a sub-contractor. Sets himself up as a subbie, gets the big</p>
<p>   job on Crown Casino with Lloyd, when he was there, and he works there for</p>
<p>   two years. He's getting all his money from one source but he's still a subbie</p>
<p>   and he'll go back to several employers. Why should he pay a different tax</p>
<p>   rate?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well it's a question of.take somebody who is, and I've even been told the</p>
<p>   example of people who are, so the tax people told us, some tram drivers</p>
<p>   have turned themselves into companies.</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Sure that's silly. [inaudible].</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well okay, if you acknowledge, see you're acknowledging the point and that</p>
<p>   is if the thing you are doing is properly in the nature of a employer-employee</p>
<p>   relationship then the tax liability ought to attach accordingly.</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>  Sure but you're throwing out a net that's going to catch.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well I'm not sure that when these rules are settled down, I mean we've got</p>
<p>   another, there are quite a period of time before these things come into</p>
<p>   operation, I'm certain any anomalies of that type can be ironed out.</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Hello Trevor, go ahead please.</p>
<p>  CALLER:</p>
<p>  Hello, how are we?</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>  Well you're alright Trevor. Go head.</p>
<p>  CALLER:</p>
<p>Yeah good. Mr Howard, a question regarding sub-contractors. I'm a sub-contractor.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>What in?</p>
<p>  CALLER:</p>
<p>In the ground maintenance area. I sub-contract to a reasonably big company</p>
<p>   and probably 80% of my income comes from the one company, although I do</p>
<p>   have my own, what would you call, suburban..</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>And do you control the hours of work and where you perform that work?</p>
<p>  CALLER:</p>
<p>  Well I control the hours of work but I work at various sights for this company.</p>
<p>   Like as an example I look after QANTAS out at the airport here.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  And do you provide much infrastructure? Is all the infrastructure provided</p>
<p>   by you or by the, well the organisation that you do close to 80% of your</p>
<p>   work for?</p>
<p>  CALLER:</p>
<p>  I supply the labor and all the equipment.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  You supply the labor and all of the equipment, yes.</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>  So is he a sub-contractor or does he pay as PAYE taxpayer?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well there are a number of other principles and I think it sounds to me</p>
<p>   as though he could, depending on, I mean there are a number of criteria</p>
<p>   laid out and we have to, I'd have to know all the circumstances [inaudible]</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>What are the other criteria?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well the level of control over hours of work and where it's performed, whether</p>
<p>   the same services are contracted to the public at large. Do you do that?</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>  How can they be if you're doing all your work for one person for a particular</p>
<p>   period?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Yes but I mean is it in the nature of the activity that you could do that</p>
<p>   kind of work for somebody else.</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>  Well you could advertise for it but be unavailable to do it because you're</p>
<p>   tied up with employee.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well yes but the point is that you may by dint of the particular work that</p>
<p>   you do, it may be only work that you'd be able to perform. Not because of</p>
<p>   time constraints but because of the character of it you could only perform</p>
<p>   it for one company or one organisation which of course means that you are</p>
<p>   more in the nature of the employee of that company than you are a sub-contractor</p>
<p>   at large.</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>But you might be an employee for a year because you get the big job. I mean</p>
<p>   you might be one company you're working for for a year, the next year you've</p>
<p>   got 12. So you're going from one to the other where as you're essentially</p>
<p>   the same businessman.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes but Neil, I understand that in some cases that can happen but can you</p>
<p>   also understand, and those who are being critical of this proposal, that</p>
<p>   there are a growing number of examples of where straight employer-employee</p>
<p>   relationships are being converted into independent contractual relationships.</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>But the tax office looked at it for four years and came up with next to</p>
<p>   nothing. Look I guess we better not [inaudible] but I know there's a lot</p>
<p>   of concern about it. I just think it could lead to enormous problems for</p>
<p>   sub-contractors.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I think if we have got an obligation to the generality of taxpayers</p>
<p>   who can't do things to reduce their tax liabilities we've got an obligation</p>
<p>   to them to make sure that there is equity, but to do it in a way that doesn't</p>
<p>   interfere with legitimate arrangements when no tax avoidance is involved.</p>
<p>   I think the rules that we're working out will achieve that goal.</p>
<p>  [Commercial break]</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>  The Prime Minister is in our Sydney Studio. Mr Howard, the Sydney broadcaster,</p>
<p>   Alan Jones, seems to have a number of contracts which make John Laws look</p>
<p>   almost virginal. What's your reaction to them?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, I stated a view when this thing first broke and it was not specific</p>
<p>   to either Mr Laws or Mr Jones or indeed anybody else and that is that if</p>
<p>   you hear the view of somebody on radio or television for that matter you</p>
<p>   assume that that is that person's view uninfluenced by any commercial arrangement.</p>
<p>   Now, that, my attitude, is if the cap fits, wear it irrespective of the</p>
<p>   individual. I have been asked before I think by you or perhaps by you and</p>
<p>   others, would I comment on the evidence that so far has been given before</p>
<p>   the broadcasting inquiry. The answer is, I am not going to comment on the</p>
<p>   specific evidence while that inquiry is still going on. I don't think that</p>
<p>   is appropriate. I shouldn't as Prime Minister set myself up as a judge in</p>
<p>   a particular proceeding but the principle.when this first broke I was asked</p>
<p>   this question - I think I was in New York at the time -.</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>  Well, we've seen the criticism then of John.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  But I was asked the question. I mean, you say it was seen. I mean, I was</p>
<p>   asked a question can I just make it perfectly clear, the principle I then</p>
<p>   stated and I restate now is not I don't think to apply that specifically</p>
<p>   to one individual, I'd apply it to anybody.</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>  Okay. Are you disappointed by what you are reading?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, I said at the time that I'd be very disappointed if that were the</p>
<p>   reality and it would apply to anybody.</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>  Could this jeopardise any of the appointments Mr Jones holds? I think he</p>
<p>   has got at least one Government position hasn't he?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, you are inviting me to do what I said I wasn't going to do and that</p>
<p>   is effectively comment and I don't think I should.</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>  Okay. Now, the illegal boat people, do you agree this is costing hundreds</p>
<p>   of millions of dollars?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  It is. It has become quite expensive.</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>  How many have been sent back immediately do you know?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, I haven't got the figure off hand but the turn around has been very</p>
<p>   quick but it is not an easy situation. And one of the reasons why we are</p>
<p>   so attractive is that there's a view around the world that we are an easy</p>
<p>   touch and we have been trying as a Government to tighten the laws for, I</p>
<p>   think, up to a couple of years now. It looks as though the Labor Party is</p>
<p>   finally going to cooperate and help us put some legislation through but</p>
<p>   this should have happened some time ago.</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>  What's wrong with the principle, which is as a lot of people put of course,</p>
<p>   is that when people arrived illegally they have no right, just put them</p>
<p>   on a boat or plane immediately and send them back.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, sometimes there is nowhere to send them back to straight away. We</p>
<p>   try as far as humanly possible to do that but if they were put to sea in</p>
<p>   unseaworthy craft and they drowned I don't think that would be seen as right</p>
<p>   or humane or decent.</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>  Well, what about hiring a jet? Put them on a Qantas jumbo and send them</p>
<p>   back.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, you have got to negotiate the return of the people because that jumbo</p>
<p>   jet might be refused landing rights.</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>  Yeah. The Uniting Church has said today that the automatic detention policy</p>
<p>   is racist. What's your reaction to that?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, that is wrong. I mean, that is a very uninformed, unreasonable remark.</p>
<p>   I think it is for a country like Australia that's opened its heart and its</p>
<p>   shores to genuine refugees for decades that is a very unfair and inaccurate</p>
<p>   remark and it contributes nothing to an intelligent debate of what is a</p>
<p>   very difficult issue. I mean, we took more Indo-Chinese refugees on a per</p>
<p>   capita basis in the 1970s than any country on earth.</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>  Would you be willing to legislate to remove the rights of these people when</p>
<p>   they arrive?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, what we are trying to do is to tighten the law. I mean, we have tried</p>
<p>   to tighten the law as much as we can and so far we are being obstructed</p>
<p>   in the Senate. Now, I hope that is now changing but I think we would have</p>
<p>   presented a firmer face to would be boat people earlier if we'd been able</p>
<p>   to tighten the law earlier. And we'd have been able to do that if we'd have</p>
<p>   got cooperation from the Labor Party in the Senate.</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>  Still Foreign Affairs reports today that some of our relationships with</p>
<p>   Japan were a bit strained that you badgered them over East Timor.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, I heard that report. I did urge the Japanese Government to make a</p>
<p>   contribution to the East Timorese fund. Bear in mind this is the fund that</p>
<p>   made it possible for poorer Asian countries and others who couldn't afford</p>
<p>   it to contribute peacekeepers. Now, I would have thought everybody would</p>
<p>   agree it was a good thing that you had a variety of countries contributing.</p>
<p>   I mean, many of the countries in the ASEAN area said, yes, we'd like to</p>
<p>   be in it but we can't afford it.</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>  Did you get a reaction from Japan or were they.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  They were very helpful.</p>
<p>  MITCHELL:</p>
<p>  ..resentment, do you think?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, I didn't find any</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
