<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>22001</transcript-id>
    <title>Government Provides Further Support for Education Initiatives in Cape York  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/10/2005</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>   Education is one of the key platforms that will help people in the Cape York region to move away from welfare dependency and promote economic development.  With a sound education comes many opportunities to build a real future.  While visiting Hope Vale today, I was delighted to enhance the Australian Government's contribution to education and youth support activities in the area.</p>
<p>I signed a Shared Responsibility Agreement with the Aboriginal community.  This Agreement, which is also a partnership with the Queensland Government, is an excellent example of what can be achieved if communities and governments work together.  Each of the parties to the Agreement is providing $75,000 to refurbish the local community hall and provide structured activities for youth in the community.  It is a further practical demonstration of the positive outcomes that can be achieved through a shared commitment.</p>
<p>I was also pleased to announce the extension of two Government education initiatives.</p>
<p>  The Government will provide a further $200,000 to extend the current Transitions Support Unit pilot, which is funded through Western Cape College with support from both the Australian and Queensland Governments.  The Unit provides support officers to Cape York students who leave their home community to continue secondary education.  The additional funding will extend the pilot by six months to the end of June 2006 and will allow greater certainty for planning for the future and the opportunity to evaluate the programme, which will help decide its longer term future.</p>
<p>The Government will also provide further support to the Whole of School Intervention Programme in Hope Vale.  The additional funding of $45,000 will allow for a Community School Participation Officer to conduct a series of workshops for parents of students from Kindergarten to Year Seven to help them address the barriers to education and improve their children's educational outcomes.  </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
