<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>390</transcript-id>
    <title>PM 54/1961 - MR E C A BROWN - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R G MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/11/1961</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000390_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
MR. E. C. A. BR W, 1<br />
Statement by the Prime 1inister. the 1t. Hon. RG. Menzies<br />
On 27th September, 1961 the Director-General of Posts<br />
and Telegraphs, in pursuance of Section 56 of the Public Sorvice<br />
Act, charged Ed-rard Charles Alfred Brown, Director of Posts and<br />
Telegraphs in Queensland with the following offences:<br />
That between 28th July and 31st July, 1.961 Mr. Brown<br />
was guilty of improper conduct in using for other than<br />
official purposes a motor car belonging to the Postmaster-<br />
General's Department.<br />
That between 6th August and 8th August, 1961 Mr. Brown<br />
was guilty of improper conduct in that he sought th. e<br />
assistance of Colin Douglas Manley, Chief Investigation<br />
Officer of the Postmaster-General's Department in Queensland<br />
in fabricating reasons to justify the use by him between<br />
28th July and 31st July of the motor car and<br />
That betwieen bOh August and lth September, 1961 he<br />
was guilty of improper conduct in that having been asked for<br />
an explanation of the use by him between 28th July and 31st<br />
July of a motor car belonging to the Postmaster-General's<br />
Department he made false and misleading statements.<br />
On 27th September the Director-General of Posts and<br />
Telegraphs suspended Mr. Brown and notified the Public Service<br />
Board of the charges and suspension.<br />
Mr. Brown in writing admitted the truth of the charges,<br />
and subsequently was given the opportunity of placing before the<br />
Public Service Board matters . hich he considered to be relevant<br />
to the recommendation the Board was required, under the Public<br />
Service Act, to make to the Governor-General. A similar<br />
opportunity was given to the Director-General of Posts and<br />
Telegraphs who had, on llth October, forwarded a written<br />
submission on the matter to the Public Service Board.<br />
Until the time when the charges were laid Mr. Brown<br />
haad a satisfactory record of service with the Commonwealth.<br />
The Public Service Board, having completed elaborate<br />
inquiries into all matters concerning the charges, has found that<br />
Mr. Broain abused the authority vested in him as Director of Posts<br />
and Telegraphs, Queensland, and has betrayed the trust and<br />
confidence which a Permanent Head must place in a senior officer.<br />
The Board noted that these are serious breaches of the<br />
standard of conduct expected of a senior officer and on 26th<br />
October recommended to the Governor-General that he be:<br />
removed from the office of Director of Posts and<br />
Telegraphs, Second Division, Queensland in uhich<br />
position he received a salary of f3,650 per amum<br />
reduced to an office of Engineer, Class 4, salary<br />
scale œ 2,748 œ 2,878 per annum, Third Division,<br />
Engineering Division, Central Office, Postmaster-<br />
Generalts Department, Melbourne<br />
paid salary at the rate of C2,878 per annum ( subject<br />
to the variations in salary prescribed by reulation<br />
106A of the Public Service regulations)<br />
An Order in these terms was made by the Governor-<br />
General in Council today and the decisions will take effect from<br />
today. CANBERRA2nd November, 1961. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
