<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9868</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P J KEATING MP LUNCH FOR THE PM&#039;S XI V THE WEST INDIES, MANUKA OVAL, CANBERRA, 5 DECEMBER 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/12/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009868.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
ILL 5 . eD ec .9,22:: 366 NN. 0. 0055 PP0-0110/ 07<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
LUNCH FOR THE PM'S XI v THE WEST INDIES, MANUKA OVAL,<br />
CANBERRA, 5 DECEMBER 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
Thanks very much indeed John ( Gallop). Can I just recognise Richie<br />
Richardson and Michael Bevan, Denis Rogers, Wesley Hall, Andy Roberts,<br />
Steve Bernard and ladies and gentlemen.<br />
What a pity we are at this point in the day. I thought we would be going well<br />
because my experience with these matches has been that we have mostly<br />
had good weather. It is a pretty safe time of the year in Australia, but with the<br />
weather patterns the way they are, nothing is safe any more it seems. At any<br />
rate, the clouds have lifted somewhat and I am hoping against hope that we<br />
might get five hours or something like that in. In which case, we would not<br />
have seen the day go to waste.<br />
I know this is an important day for the ACT Cricket Association because it is<br />
one of its fund raising days amongst other things, but I know it wants to keep<br />
up this tradition of the Prime Minister's Xl and so do I. Particularly for our<br />
colleagues from the West Indies and this being their first match of the tour,<br />
they pay us a great honour indeed in being part of the Prime Minister's Xl and<br />
coming last evening and today to play our side and in doing that, of course,<br />
they have done it quite a few times over the years. I was just looking through<br />
the book " The Prime Minister's Xl" by Don Selth there on the table, we have<br />
seen a number of them here in the past. Wes Hall, I think, back in the 1960s<br />
and Richie, of course, was here in 1992. So, they are no strangers to this<br />
place and we have kept the tradition going. Being the first fixture of the tour<br />
for them, I hope that they can limber up in a sense this afternoon.<br />
I would like to underline how important the West Indies are in the world of<br />
Australian cricket of world cricket and, of course, a measure of their<br />
greatness is the fact that only after two decades did Australia manage to win<br />
back the Frank Worrell Shield. There is a great sense of euphoria here and,<br />
I think, that they have set the standard in cricket by which other countries<br />
judge themselves. That is, the measure of someones euphoria is really </p>
<p>TEL 2<br />
whether they can climb over th-e top of-you. When they know how hard that is<br />
to do, they rate themselves by comparing themselves with you.<br />
Australian cricket, of course, has been riding high over recent times.<br />
Perhaps not yesterday, but mostly and our team has been performing very<br />
well under Mark Taylor and we have got many and very talented cricketers<br />
knocking on the door of the Test team. But we have got a long way to go<br />
before we achieve that special status which the West Indies have had in<br />
dominating international cricket so totally and for so long.<br />
It has always been a great wonder to me that from the Caribbean, those<br />
relatively small states and populations like Barbados with a population<br />
roughly the size of Canberra or Antigua with a population roughly akin to<br />
some of our provincial centres, yet it produces this huge number of<br />
international ranked people and it really is quite exceptional. We were just<br />
talking about my home town of Bankstown, how many cricketers we have<br />
produced from there and how many swimmers and the rest, well, there is<br />
Bankstown and the rest of Australia and I suppose there is Barbados and<br />
Antigua and what have you. I know what it is like to produce all these stars..<br />
Though we are very proud of our cricketing stars from that part of the world,<br />
we have never turned out the number of fast bowlers that you have and your<br />
success in the 1970s, 1 980s and 1 990s was founded on that magnificent fast<br />
bowling. We have got Curtley Ambrose and Courtney Walsh here today, of<br />
course, to show us some of their form if we get an opportunity.<br />
It Is a great pleasure for me to be here as Prime Minister with Wes Hall and<br />
Andy Roberts in our company as Team Manager and Coach. Of course, they<br />
were household names in Australia and great draw cards and they kept that<br />
contact with cricket and, of course, the other thing I have in common with<br />
Wes is he is a pollie, a politician. So, he knows about all of the other<br />
undercurrents going on out there too. We were just talking a bit earlier about<br />
how politicians immediately pick up the pulse of a crowd or a circumstance or<br />
a place and no doubt, this has put him in good stead with instinct it has put<br />
him in good stead in cricket and in public life. At any rate, it is great to have<br />
them both here with us and again we appreciate very much their commitment.<br />
Could I express my appreciation particularly to the Australian Cricket Board<br />
and to the ACT Cricket Association in organising what has obviously been a<br />
well organised event, other than the weather. If my predecessor was still<br />
here, he would have been a better chance on that too and a couple before<br />
that could But, I am only an ordinary politician and so I can only say thank<br />
you for the organisation that you have obviously displayed here and just in<br />
the year since the renovations and the extra facilities out the front, of course,<br />
are going to make it a much better place to organise cricket into the future.<br />
I would like to thank the players, Richie Richardson and his side and Michael<br />
Bevan and our side with many substantial young people coming through<br />
cricket and the great opportunity for them to be up against such a quality side<br />
and I thank them both. Of course, this stand has been called after the great<br />
Don Bradman and 1, as a former finance minister and Treasurer of this<br />
TEL D. ec 236 ' 40. u05 P -U2C/ K-</p>
<p>3<br />
country, you get a bit of a penchant for statistics, but whenever the statistics<br />
are brought out about Bradman, he distinguishes himself so obviously in<br />
Cricket world history. It was nice we had a $ 5 commemorative coin in his<br />
name punched and we were able to use it today. The Mint is still hanging on<br />
to it though and they won't let them have it. They are very thingy about the<br />
currency here. They make their money under a thing called seigniorage this<br />
is a little trick they have about what it costs to produce the money and the<br />
difference in its face value. So, given the fact that it never costs that much to<br />
produce these coins, they could give a few away. But, I don't think we are<br />
going to get hold of the Don Bradman coin today. We did ask Don to come<br />
over on this occasion, given that the coin was struck in his honour. We all<br />
take opportunities to remember his great life as a cricketer and his great life<br />
as a world sportsman and as an Australian sportsman, but he wasn't able to<br />
come for reasons, family reasons and others. It would have been nice to<br />
have had him, but we understand.<br />
So, can I just conclude by thanking you all the Australian Cricket Board and<br />
the ACT Cricket Association particularly. I thank you for keeping up the<br />
tradition of the PM's XI. I am glad also my parliamentary colleagues could be<br />
with us, from the Opposition and also mine in the Government and we can<br />
all of us Rwf e get some opportunity here, keep increasing the record book<br />
that we have on the table and keep alive this very important tradition. I'd like<br />
to propose a toast to our West Indies guests, if someone could pass over my<br />
drink. To just say thank you and wish you all the best on this tour.<br />
ends i cL t, Liec z ' Do NO uu U. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
