<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8798</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP, PRESS CONFERENCE, PERTH, 27 JANUARY 1993</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/01/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008798.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
27. Jan. 93 17: 50 No. 039 P. 01/ 06<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
lRANS( CMRJ-FPTO ' LlE PRIVE M[ NL1TER, THE HON P J KEATING MP,<br />
PRESS CONFERENCE, PXRTH, 27 JANUARY 1993<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
3: 1 ow important is the ouzome of this election to the-in of when you call the<br />
fcdcral clcotion?<br />
I'M: It's decidedly unimportant, because the Commonweah Government will decide<br />
the election itself<br />
1: 1 heard that Mr Dawkins was going to release today revised Budget forecasts. Is<br />
chat oil?<br />
PM: Not that I know of, no.<br />
J: line Minister, whats your reaction to John flcwsons comments In Adelaide<br />
on ABC radio this mornfn the fact that tax has which surfaced i the political<br />
debate because you haven't got any policies to counterfight them?<br />
PM: Tax surfaced in Lhu dcbawc bc4ause aournalist totany unconnected with the<br />
Ouvvnunen, wrote a profl about John Hcwson' career, and has obviously<br />
meticulously gone through his past. Thar's why ifs arisen. Notblng to do with<br />
the Govcrnnment whatsoever.<br />
J. And you've got no qulnu about somebody looking at your pigger?<br />
PM: fve had Liberal Senators, at Dr I lewson's bchsi, looking at me, asfitg<br />
qucstions two or three dmcs a day for 8 months. I didn't hear any indignation<br />
from any of you about that process. The key point here I4 Dr -ewson has<br />
made taxation the cenual feature of his campaign. He's saying that we have to<br />
change the ta mix from income to expenditure. You all know that low paid<br />
people, or unemployed people, or midle income people spend all of their<br />
Inconic. So whuller you Lax thr income or expenditur ifs one in the same,<br />
it's all spont. He says that's the way wo ought to raise the taxation we'll tax<br />
virtually all of your income. But if the claims in the book am coC; he's also<br />
TEL </p>
<p>27. Jan. 93 17: 50 No. 039 P. 02/ 06<br />
2<br />
saying. opT! d~ n well tax you absolutcly when you spend, on cvuy<br />
service you consume, evely good you buy, we2 lax you but on your income<br />
tax, if you'rwe ld-Mave then we Otk W OK to txi-ntdmi So irs Dr<br />
11awson's philosophy about taraion which Is impormn here. I Ufb whAfs<br />
revealing about a this Is not whedtwhe claimed this or deducted that, but his<br />
philosophy. He's saying tax i the leadng Issue of a nationl election from the<br />
coaliton's side of politics. lie's sayin that all goods and Al services in the<br />
community should be taxed absouioly at die poWit of purhase or talc. But fbr<br />
income tax he seems to be sayn he thinks dct'ius for ax tnimbniadon am<br />
OK. It's the philosophy that mullen here.<br />
3: But you can we that he was quite within die law to do what he hadon. If the<br />
philosophy was so wrong why don't you change the laws to make what he did<br />
ileal?<br />
PM: I didn' write this stuiTZ rm not privy to his income or his returns. He can rebut<br />
this if he wishes, ho has'l to date. Therefore these were matters at the time for<br />
the Commissioner of Taxaion. The point Is the point in principle.<br />
Ie. id he woms ketut to dobate you on yowr taxation arranccnta, w ould you<br />
oblige him?<br />
PM: There's no debate, rm a PAYE tax payer. m the most simple case around<br />
Let me just make this clear to youIf you want comparability, I bou&amp; M a house<br />
within one month of Dr Hewson buying his house. On my house al the<br />
deductions are carried by me, As Im an. yours ar. That M, If you We in a<br />
house as a domestic resldence, dw costs art not deductible. To paint the<br />
picture, or to aiake an anfangcmcnt where one nuns a private deduction Into a<br />
business expense, this Is the point her, is an arrangoment which minjirdaus tax,<br />
In the comparable situation, 1\ v still got the house, I'm still ranying the interest<br />
Costs on the mortgage, theyve never been doducte4<br />
3; And for the record, your taxation rate is?<br />
PM; rin a PAYE tax payer, it's as simple as dat<br />
J: And thaf a at what rate?<br />
PM; Pick up the scales and have a look.<br />
3; Do you know the rare that you're paying as a PAE?<br />
PM; LAA mc make ibkj clear to you there is no deduction I make that tries to turn a<br />
privae expcmv, inu ~ a busines" expense that's the key poinL<br />
J. ' then what rate<br />
FM: Don't put words in my tate, I'm te1Iina you<br />
TEL: </p>
<p>TEL: 27. Jan. 93 17: 50 No. 039 P. 03/ 06<br />
3<br />
I: tm asking the question<br />
PM: You've asked, so rm ivins you the answer. The answer is I do not seek tO turn<br />
private expens into business epenses to masquerade privat expenses as<br />
business cxptnrsas rm quite met al of you would be happy to tun your<br />
mortgage costs into deductibic crxPancs.<br />
1: Did Dr Iewson break thclaw?<br />
PM: Thai's a mailer for hini, the Tax Commissioner, ct cetcra. rm just making the<br />
point, as a matter of philosophy Dr Hewson says that taxation is the issue that<br />
malturs in hs counity. He want to ux exendcitu absolutely at the point of<br />
salt of goods or sorvlczs, but he's saYing in relation to income tax that he thinks<br />
the lelity, tphe lophy of taxniiaionis OK. Thars thekey poiL<br />
Can Ijust also say that we habtie fuldnibiiitioiis by Mr Downer ovrnigt<br />
For 8 month, 8 months mind you therea a few Canberra jounal&amp; ta here,<br />
the know this to be Uue fbr 9 months qutions have been asked wktout<br />
foundation. Questions with no foundation and proved to have no foundation,<br />
questions were asked of me for 8 months. A lot of it was printed in de<br />
newspapers. Someone unconnected with tho Govenument writes a book about<br />
Dr Howson, his taxation becomes a public issue, and eftWr&amp; away he's &amp; ayflg<br />
this is dirty pool, the ( overnnemn is up to dirty pooi. What about the<br />
nconsistency of 9 months of this as Dr -ewon's beheat I think you should ask<br />
Dr HewsoIn what was the point of his tactic7, did he think It was tight?, wa<br />
Senator Baum, aing on his xpress inalnios? and, does he now regret this<br />
1. Jb it the case that Dr Hewson is paying 15 per cent tax and you'rc paying 48 per<br />
cent?<br />
PM; I donit know what he's paying.<br />
3: Are you paying the top margnal rate of tax?<br />
PM: For a start I get rebates like you do, I get a rebate for dependent spouse and<br />
children, But I'm not turning private expenses into business xpem= e. Do you<br />
understand? ~ mars the key point rm not about " yingto tn a private<br />
expenso, like the cost of my mortgag, into a business expense.<br />
JAr eyou giving Dr IIcwson back what you<br />
PM. No, this Isue arose not by us but by a bo*, Mikrhistiwr,-WaUkpc has made<br />
this point But Dr Tiewson has taxation as the primmay issue tn a national<br />
election whorc he says, Australia has been ineficient and lazy and they've got to<br />
do moro, and they think they should be taxed at the point of sale of their goods<br />
or thvir servicos, but to take the view that income taxation should be available<br />
for ininimisation duough devises. In other words, if you're a wage or satiny<br />
varnar you pay absolutely, but if you're well-advised you can minkmise your tm </p>
<p>T2E7L: . Jan. 93 17: 50 No. 039 P. 04/ 06<br />
4<br />
Tisx Lq a question of philosophy. IV,, Dr Hcwsofl Who's runn* n On taxation not<br />
the Government.<br />
J; You're apparently feluotant to nam<br />
PM4: YouNVe had enough, ato tr any more qumstiw?<br />
J: I wAsjult goigto ak y01r atin&amp; uanyu telus what your uaadw ra<br />
is?<br />
pM. i r'd have to average If's inmateial what miy rate is. IIIl tell yoU this I have no<br />
ClaRM tha turns a private expense into a busines expense,<br />
3: DO YOU think tats morally wrong.<br />
PM* Pardon? Do you think, morally, rnii isation could be aeon as a ( inaudible)? Is tha<br />
what you bdlicvc?<br />
PM: Nc ncvcr Sought to do it, I bought a houst the same tinw as Dr J1owson, I<br />
didWnI Uip it into a company.<br />
J: Why not?<br />
PM; Isecause I don't thinik such a private oxpense ought to masquerade, as a busines<br />
expoense. That' why.<br />
J; Do you thinkpay as you carntax payrv) amben, paying for corpor<br />
Austraia?<br />
PM: Before I becamnc Treasurer, the tax system was subject to MAssiVo<br />
haemclTh&amp;&amp; zg through tax avoidance and evasion as well as minitnistn and<br />
most of thr. minimisation and &amp; vidance scheMV3 had a captal gain underneth<br />
thmm I introduced the = aaMon of capitains in this coUnbry. I inb* odtAcd the<br />
taxation of bingo benefits into tis country, As a resut, peopl now pay their<br />
fair share of tax, which was nover the case When Dr Hewsont was advisig Mdr<br />
Howard. lIn those days the taxation syste was in a state of accelerated<br />
hamorrhaso.<br />
3: Ame you prepared to hav; your taxes debate in Parliament along side Dr<br />
I lowfions?<br />
PM: Listcn, minec havc bcen debated for B nmths. You might have not noticed, or<br />
uhuscn not to notic, they were debated for s montis.<br />
I. Prinir Minister, rcgleas of the detailg of who started it, do you tink t<br />
clectoriaic of AUstralA is lnitetC4 t you and Dr Hewson's pemonal ian<br />
matters? TEL </p>
<p>TEL: 27. Jan. 93 17: 50 No. 039 P. 05/ 06<br />
PM-No, I don't think thay amc, but I th" n they ame MeY intereted iA the philooph<br />
of taxaio which D~ r Hewson is p~ omting 28 the fhzt issue in owr dational<br />
Politics. He's gaithat ansres and goods hould be t" cat IS parcent<br />
all oxpendtwoe. You know that for Wage and saay earners that MGMn 100 per<br />
Cent of their Income, because their income And . xpendinire Is the sante, they<br />
don't save. They don't have enough money to savC 90it mCAns that their<br />
incom~ e and expcnditur is one and tho samne, and he says therefore we'l tax<br />
thoue. But one oan dnw the obvious point that in teMM Of In1COMe tax, AS<br />
distinrct from consumption or expendIture tP.. .11rT T iniflim . f VA,' f. w. Al-<br />
J; Mr XeAtin.<br />
PM: Comc on, you've had mnorc than your rAir So.<br />
l: D~ o you expect tho Parliament will have the oppoiwiiy to debate ti inanor<br />
Weore shc ce dn<br />
PM: Yes, it will havo the opportunity to debate ThotPuziament Is schedulad to<br />
contC back in the third week of Februaty, it it not? In that p~ uiod all thinp wig<br />
be dcbWAtd<br />
3: Scheduled to come back before ihz elcuion?<br />
PM: At thi stagc if~ s cosing back, absolutely.<br />
3: M Keating, apart from your pononal tax and your busbin hterrsts., have you<br />
nerver souht u) mi'nimie your tax in your business interests?<br />
IPM: No, this was another fiaphy yesterday. The, thing about the Liberals, heme they<br />
were saying~ of me, Senator flaumne was askin these questions beeaus ft Was<br />
the ro~ t thing to do to elicit information on the need to know basis, but when<br />
thc Goverment says what about your position Dr Hewson? Shocking, this is a<br />
b wat p, ih gte o itical OK fortelbesto do itfor 8months, noM<br />
OK for the L~ bor Pailyto doIt for 8minutes. lhbarthie point<br />
3: What about the advantage to you tha tho perception may arise that it Is a<br />
Cuuaudible)?<br />
PM: ThAt'. for you to report and nuke clear, that the issuc of substance is his wish to<br />
tax the Australian clvctorate wit a conpsulon tax against what is apparently<br />
his record in relation to income tax. As far as, this Lady here asked me about<br />
my Affairs, yevivrday's statement woe a total flirphy, Thome is a thin in the tax<br />
provision callvd ' 1rouping. Companies today no lunge need to rn their<br />
mtaiing and tir production witbin the one company. You can have a<br />
prodution copanuy and a rtail compaty and the merge together in the end.<br />
1' otake the profita of one and saytat in smeway itsnot hMnWit s taxp aKd<br />
to i~ iorc the costs of the other is of course a total joke. </p>
<p>TEL: 27. Jan. 93 17: 50 No. 039 P. 06/ OE<br />
6<br />
J: Do you onaidor your txhtion affai are prdvatt 4min?<br />
PM: I tonoidvr dLcrn to be totally in order. Mine wore ai&amp; diid by a public auditor<br />
and placod of the public record of the ASC. So you can go down there and<br />
punch a screen and go and road about thom Go and ask Dr llewson will he<br />
make his available,<br />
J: Mr Koating, you've called It a lrphy, but to the public at large who may not be<br />
intimate with the laws of taxacol do you ( inaudible) of what the Opposidon Is<br />
saying?<br />
PM: No, why would they? Thtrets not any basis in this whatsoever in this, nothing.<br />
Apparently a number of people today on radio have made that point quite clear.<br />
The Vrouping provisios mean, in the old days people used to have a company<br />
that had income and run all the costs against it een if the companies had<br />
diferent functions. After &amp; ouplng proisions were Invroduced, you could then<br />
havvi a company which was a reta company and a company which was a<br />
prodation compuy, 100 per cent owned within the group. You can't look at<br />
the prolits of one and not include the costa of the other. lb1ats what they tied<br />
to do lat night knowing that moat of you wouldn't be on to it to ty to save him<br />
some ombarrasanint.<br />
J; John lewson wants changes to the debating situation, he doesn't want a panel<br />
ofjoumnaista he just wans a moderator. What's your reaction to that?<br />
PM: Wc'U negotiate a sot of anrangoments, rm not sure cxaiutly what weve asked for,<br />
I thitk a panel Is probably bcst.<br />
Why did you change your mind about a wonsunption tax?<br />
PM. rm not h10V to giva you an cuonornic history lesson. OK<br />
cnd </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
