<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10741</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP RADIO INTERVIEW WITH MIKE GIBSON RADIO 2GB, SYDNEY</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/02/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>Prime Minister good morning. Good to talk to you, so many things</p>
<p>   to talk about on a morning when you are all over the front pages,</p>
<p>   Mr Howard. First, the Government's hopes for an early double</p>
<p>   dissolution are in jeopardy, says The Australian, how much</p>
<p>   more pressure can you put on the Senate to deal with Wik?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I want the Wik thing out of the way. Most Australians want it out</p>
<p>   of the way. We don't want a double dissolution on Wik. We just</p>
<p>   want the Senate to do its job and pass the legislation. We have</p>
<p>   already made enormous concessions, we have been compromising all</p>
<p>   through the piece, we have finally reached a point where we won't</p>
<p>   and can't compromise any further because what we have got is</p>
<p>   a fair balance. And I just ask the Senate again, I ask the Labor</p>
<p>   Party, Senator Harradine, The Greens and The Democrats, let us pass</p>
<p>   this legislation, let us put this native title debate behind us</p>
<p>   and get on with our future. And for every week or month that this</p>
<p>   is further delayed then the Australian people are further being</p>
<p>   denied an opportunity for their elected leaders to focus on mainstream</p>
<p>   issues that are really of direct concern to them.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>If there was one thing you could do with Senator Harradine what</p>
<p>   would it be?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I would just hope that I could persuade him that in the national</p>
<p>   interest this debate should be ended and the matter should be put</p>
<p>   behind us.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>Should it not be, the 4th of July an important day in the United</p>
<p>   States, perhaps an important day this year for Australians?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well the only person who is talking about an election on the 4th</p>
<p>   of July is the National Secretary of the Labor Party. I have not</p>
<p>   talked about an election on the 4th of July. My preference is for</p>
<p>   the Parliament to go its full term and the only circumstance in</p>
<p>   which the Parliament wouldn't go essentially its full term</p>
<p>   would be if the Senate obstructs necessary legislation. And the</p>
<p>   only way I can get that legislation through is to have a double</p>
<p>   dissolution and then present it at a joint sitting following that</p>
<p>   double dissolution election.</p>
<p>You see, we have to amend the Native Title Act that Mr Keating</p>
<p>   left us in 1996 because it is not working. And investment is being</p>
<p>   held up and jobs are being destroyed all over Australia as a result.</p>
<p>   And unless we get these amendments through, mining investment is</p>
<p>   going to be withheld, there is going to be confusion and animosity</p>
<p>   in rural Australia. And what we want to do is fix all of that up.</p>
<p>   And we have been trying for a year to get it fixed. We have got</p>
<p>   a Bill which is a fair balance, which respects the rights of Aboriginal</p>
<p>   people as well as farmers and miners. Now we want to get that through</p>
<p>   and the people who are holding that up are the Labor Party principally,</p>
<p>   but aided and abetted by Senator Harradine and The Democrats and</p>
<p>   The Greens. And I just say again to the Senate: the Australian people</p>
<p>   are fed up with this debate, they are sick of it, they are tired</p>
<p>   of it, they want it behind them, they want to get back to things</p>
<p>   that are of direct, immediate, mainstream concern to them.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>The May budget, talking about direct, mainstream concern. We are</p>
<p>   maybe looking down the gun-barrel of an election, that being the</p>
<p>   case, one would suggest, perhaps this will be a fairly soft budget.</p>
<p>   Will anybody get hurt?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well we have taken a number of tough decisions, we inherited a</p>
<p>   deficit of $10.5 billion from Mr Beazley as Finance Minister and</p>
<p>   Deputy Prime Minister to Mr Keating. And I hope that in the May</p>
<p>   budget we will be able to announce a surplus. Now what that surplus</p>
<p>   means, of course, is that in two years we have turned the nation's</p>
<p>   finances around. We have also kept our promises to reduce family</p>
<p>   taxation, to introduce health insurance incentives and, remarkably,</p>
<p>   we have seen a reduction in housing interest rates over the last</p>
<p>   two years. They are now at their lowest level for 30 years.</p>
<p>And the value of those reductions is the same as if the people</p>
<p>   receiving them had got a wage rise of between $90 and $100 a week.</p>
<p>   I mean, that is a very, very big injection of cash into the pockets</p>
<p>   of average Australians because the fall in mortgage interest rates</p>
<p>   under my Government has been $256 a month on an average mortgage</p>
<p>   and that is the equivalent of a $90 to $100 a week wage increase</p>
<p>   for every person paying off an average mortgage. Now that is a direct</p>
<p>   result of our financial management.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>When you talk about the drop in interest rates, that is one of</p>
<p>   the reasons the ANZ organisation gives today for the shedding of</p>
<p>   1700 jobs, despite the fact that last year the ANZ made a billion</p>
<p>   dollar profit, as we know. Are we putting profits before people</p>
<p>   in this country Prime Minister, and as Prime Minister how does that</p>
<p>   make you feel?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I don't like to ever hear of job losses of that magnitude.</p>
<p>   The other side of the story, of course is, that over the last 4</p>
<p>   months 145,000 jobs have been created in Australia. So you have</p>
<p>   always got to look at the overall picture and remember that as jobs</p>
<p>   are lost in one part of the economy they can be generated in another.</p>
<p>   But it has to be said that Australian banks by world standards are</p>
<p>   very profitable and all institutions, large ones in particular,</p>
<p>   have social obligations, equally of course they have obligations</p>
<p>   to their shareholders. If you look at the overall employment scene</p>
<p>   in Australia and you don't just focus on one or two companies</p>
<p>   that have been in the news, you do see a picture of the last three</p>
<p>   or four months that the job market has strengthened - 145,000 new</p>
<p>   jobs created in the space of the last three to four months. Now</p>
<p>   that is the good news on the job front.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>Now, our troops in the Gulf, are we totally in America's hands?</p>
<p>   If Saddam Hussein opens these doors that he promises to, will you</p>
<p>   call our boys home or do we have to wait until the President of</p>
<p>   the United States says so?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>We are totally in our hands. I mean, we decide, and we alone decide</p>
<p>   whether we have an involvement and when that involvement ends. I</p>
<p>   said two night ago, in fact in a advance of the comments made by</p>
<p>   the President or anybody else, that I didn't believe until</p>
<p>   Saddam Hussein's word had been tested by an inspection, it</p>
<p>   would be a good idea for any of the troops, Australian or otherwise,</p>
<p>   to be withdrawn. Now, I don't think it would be.</p>
<p>It is one thing for somebody like Saddam Hussein to sign a bit</p>
<p>   of paper saying: I will allow people in. Until those people have</p>
<p>   been allowed in and they report back that there are no weapons of</p>
<p>   mass destruction, or alternatively those weapons have been effectively</p>
<p>   destroyed, I won't be satisfied that what he has said in this</p>
<p>   agreement can in fact be delivered. Now he has broken his word in</p>
<p>   the past, he is a brutal dictator and nobody should pretend, for</p>
<p>   a moment, that he signed this document because he has had a sudden</p>
<p>   change of heart. He has signed this document because of the presence</p>
<p>   of American, British, Australian and other forces in the Gulf.</p>
<p>It has been the presence of those forces and the potential use</p>
<p>   of those forces which has led to Saddam Hussein doing what he has</p>
<p>   done, not a change of heart, not some burst of compassion on his</p>
<p>   part and we should all understand that.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>At 9:22 am, my guest is John Howard. The Health Fund for private</p>
<p>   health systems, fewer than one third of Australians now belong to</p>
<p>   a fund, the public system is starting to buckle under the pressure,</p>
<p>   what are you going to do to get Australians back in the fund?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, we have done a lot already and if we hadn't injected</p>
<p>   tax incentives into the system, that figure you quote, would have</p>
<p>   been much lower, much, much lower. It is a great pity that five</p>
<p>   or six years ago, when Graham Richardson was the Labor Health Minister,</p>
<p>   that his advice to provide tax incentives for private health insurance</p>
<p>   hadn't been taken by, his then government colleagues, Mr Keating</p>
<p>   and Mr Beazley, because if we had stabilised the level at 38 or</p>
<p>   39 per cent, then we would now be in a stronger position. </p>
<p>And what I have said is that we need private health insurance and</p>
<p>   of course the product needs to be affordable and there needs to</p>
<p>   be a range of choices available to participants in the funds. We</p>
<p>   have got to remember that, for all the faults in the Australian</p>
<p>   health system, it is better and more economical and more accessible</p>
<p>   than just about any health system in the world. </p>
<p>We are pretty good at knocking it, no matter who is in office,</p>
<p>   but when you compare it with the American system, which is vastly</p>
<p>   too expensive for average people, you compare it with the British</p>
<p>   system, which doesn't deliver the same standard of health care</p>
<p>   for the average person, you compare it with the health systems around</p>
<p>   the world, it is still by world standards, a very good system. </p>
<p>Now that is not to say that there aren't shortages, there</p>
<p>   aren't weaknesses and there aren't deficiencies but we</p>
<p>   have to keep a sense of proportion and a sense of balance. And we</p>
<p>   run the risk in this country of, just by relentless political rhetoric</p>
<p>   on both sides, running down what is still by world standards a very</p>
<p>   good health system.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>You're in the gun this morning over what is described as your</p>
<p>   grand plan to buy back the foreshores of Sydney Harbour, to convert</p>
<p>   those old Defence sites into parklands for the people of Sydney.</p>
<p>   Your colleagues, the Nationals, say you are wasting money that could</p>
<p>   be better used on urgently needed rural projects. Will you stick</p>
<p>   by your plans to give us back our foreshores?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, we haven't made any final decision on this but it is</p>
<p>   obviously under consideration and I would be amazed, absolutely</p>
<p>   amazed, if we do end up giving harbour foreshore land to all of</p>
<p>   the people of Australia, and particularly the people of Sydney,</p>
<p>   I would be amazed if anybody would be critical of it. Now if the</p>
<p>   Defence Department does move out of certain installations it now</p>
<p>   occupies, and it has to buy alternative installations, well there</p>
<p>   is obviously a cost involved in that. And the idea that that can</p>
<p>   just be met by the budget and there doesn't have to be any</p>
<p>   kind of offset inside the Government in that, is ridiculous.</p>
<p>Now, I think the criticism that's being made, and I notice</p>
<p>   most of it is coming from the NSW Premier, is just a diversion from</p>
<p>   some of his own difficulties. The people I talk to, right across</p>
<p>   the political spectrum in Sydney, are saying that the idea of having</p>
<p>   the foreshore given back to the people, the people of Sydney, the</p>
<p>   people of Australia, is a terrific idea. And most sensible people</p>
<p>   understand that, if involved in that you have to have the Defence</p>
<p>   Department buy some land or spend money on remediation of the existing</p>
<p>   foreshores to make them more attractive for the public to use, they</p>
<p>   will understand that that money has to be spent. Apparently everybody,</p>
<p>   except Mr Carr, who thinks that it grows on trees.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>Aren't they...you are under criticism this morning from Mr</p>
<p>   Armstrong as well, who says that he figures you could be spending</p>
<p>   your money more wisely and fairly, out in the bush?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I noticed Mr Collins is not saying that, in fact Mr Collins</p>
<p>   is very keen on the land being given back to the people of Sydney.</p>
<p>   I understand why a representative of rural Australia would put that</p>
<p>   point of view but the people of Sydney are part of the Australian</p>
<p>   population. We have put enormous resources into rural areas and</p>
<p>   I would point out to any rural critics that the overwhelming bulk</p>
<p>   of the money coming out of the Natural Heritage Trust, that's</p>
<p>   the $1 billion fund that was made available out of the sale of one</p>
<p>   third of Telstra, the overwhelming bulk of that money is going into</p>
<p>   rural Australia.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>You talk about....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>...because that is where all the environmental difficulties are.</p>
<p>   So I don't think rural Australia is being short changed, on</p>
<p>   the contrary, in relation to capital spending by this Government,</p>
<p>   it has been very generously treated.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>You talk about Mr Carr, I mean you are not only the Prime Minister,</p>
<p>   you are pretty keen, old political observer, what hope do you give</p>
<p>   Bob Carr and his Government at being re-elected?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think they are struggling badly. I think people elected them</p>
<p>   by accident. I don't think the NSW.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>Would you describe John Fahey as an accident?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, I said they elected Carr by an accident. I think, no, I certainly</p>
<p>   don't, John Fahey is an extremely effective member of my team.</p>
<p>   He's doing an outstanding job as a Finance Minister - very,</p>
<p>   very good job. And he's been responsible for the very successful</p>
<p>   privatisations, amongst other things.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>What was the accident that led to...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think it was just one of those situations where there was no</p>
<p>   overwhelming feeling for change and, as a result, people have been</p>
<p>   very sceptical of the performance of the Carr Government. And I</p>
<p>   think their continued backflips give the impression of a government</p>
<p>   not only incompetent, but in crisis. But I will leave the running</p>
<p>   on that to my State colleagues. I'm naturally more concerned</p>
<p>   about good government for all of the people of Australia.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>The biggest event in Sydney this week, Prime Minister, the biggest</p>
<p>   event of the year, in fact, in terms of numbers and those who take</p>
<p>   part, the annual Gay and Lesbian Mardi Gras parade. You mentioned</p>
<p>   Peter Collins, you mentioned Bob Carr, the Leader of the Opposition,</p>
<p>   Kim Beazley - they all support it. Why do you steadfastly refuse</p>
<p>   to put your name to Gay and Lesbian Mardi Gras?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, for a couple of reasons. I think it's always wrong to</p>
<p>   assume that everything that somebody tolerates and understands,</p>
<p>   that they automatically endorse. There's no obligation on a</p>
<p>   political leader to positively endorse everything. I have a completely</p>
<p>   tolerant view towards homosexuality. But there are practises and</p>
<p>   people who are ridiculed in that parade for whom I have considerable</p>
<p>   respect. I mean, over the years Catholic nuns have been ridiculed</p>
<p>   in that parade. Over the years political colleagues of mine have</p>
<p>   been ridiculed in that parade. Why should I positively endorse something</p>
<p>   that includes ridicule of people in the community for whom I have</p>
<p>   immense respect.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>So this is very much a personal decision.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, all these things are personal.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>I think with many of them it's perhaps political. Not in your</p>
<p>   case. I think some of these other...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I suppose the political thing for me to do would be to send a message.</p>
<p>   But I just take the view that if an activity ridicules a group in</p>
<p>   the community for whom you have regard and respect, it's a</p>
<p>   bit odd then to turn around and send a message. Now, I'm not</p>
<p>   criticising people who are homosexual. I have an utterly tolerant,</p>
<p>   inclusive attitude. And I, for example, voted in the Parliament</p>
<p>   a couple of years ago to support legislation completely decriminalising</p>
<p>   homosexual conduct in Tasmania because I thought that kind of legislation</p>
<p>   was absolutely anachronistic in our society. But that doesn't</p>
<p>   mean to say that I'm under an obligation to positively embrace</p>
<p>   a particular event which includes condemnation and ridicule of people</p>
<p>   for whom I have a high regard and including, on occasions in the</p>
<p>   past, party and political colleagues of mine. I don't mind</p>
<p>   taking that attitude. I've been asked this before. And I know</p>
<p>   I'm probably one out on this amongst most political leaders</p>
<p>   in Australia and many community figures, but that's my decision</p>
<p>   and I feel quite comfortable about it.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>You have been our Prime Minister for the best part of a couple</p>
<p>   of years now and I must say in recent months you really look like</p>
<p>   you're enjoying the job. What was the toughest thing, after</p>
<p>   all those years of waiting, what was the toughest thing for you,</p>
<p>   John Howard, when you first became Prime Minister?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think just adjusting to the fact that every day you had enormous</p>
<p>   responsibility. I don't think I've felt a decision more</p>
<p>   keenly than the decision to commit our forces to the Gulf recently.</p>
<p>   Because I felt, as I talked to those men before they went off, you</p>
<p>   might have been involved in a decision that could put their lives...I</p>
<p>   knew I'd been involved in a decision that could have put their</p>
<p>   lives at risk and may yet do so. I hope it doesn't. And although</p>
<p>   the case for sending them was overwhelming - and I've had good</p>
<p>   support from the community including, may I say, from the Leader</p>
<p>   of the Opposition, and I appreciate that because it's always</p>
<p>   good to send Australian troops overseas, if they are to go overseas,</p>
<p>   with bipartisan support - despite that, I nonetheless felt that</p>
<p>   decision very keenly because it was very emotional and directly</p>
<p>   went to the very essence and being of those people and their lives.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>Before you go, your former colleague, John Hewson, is widely believed</p>
<p>   to have lost an election because he failed to communicate the GST.</p>
<p>   And you talk about the mainstream issues and I agree with you, I</p>
<p>   think there are many more issues more important than Wik and the</p>
<p>   republic. I think the GST is number one at the moment in most taxpayers'</p>
<p>   minds. Are you confident we all understand it this time around,</p>
<p>   and for those who aren't too certain, what percentage of tax</p>
<p>   will you be placing on goods and what sort of income tax breaks</p>
<p>   will you be offering in return?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>The next interview, Michael, I'll tell you that. I can't</p>
<p>   give you the rates. We haven't decided yet. But what I can</p>
<p>   tell you is that this is not a policy to introduce a GST. It's</p>
<p>   a policy to change the whole system including, in particular, to</p>
<p>   reduce personal income tax on middle income earners...</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>And put tax on goods which is a GST, but it's not a term,</p>
<p>   I guess, that the Liberal Party likes to use.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, whatever you call it. A broad-based, indirect tax, if it</p>
<p>   were introduced, would have the advantage of being much fairer.</p>
<p>   I mean, what is fair about everybody having to pay 22 per cent for</p>
<p>   the family car, but if you're one out of about 50 Australians</p>
<p>   who can afford to do so and buy a Lear Jet, you don't pay any</p>
<p>   sales tax on that. The existing system is riddled with those sorts</p>
<p>   of inconsistencies. And we had a report in the paper this morning</p>
<p>   from the Tax Office which said that it costs about $10.5 billion</p>
<p>   for the Australian community to just comply with the existing taxation</p>
<p>   system. That's about the most powerful endorsement I've</p>
<p>   seen in weeks of the need for root-and-branch reform of our tax</p>
<p>   system. Everybody who's studied it knows it needs reform. The</p>
<p>   Labor Party knows it. They're trying to block it. But deep</p>
<p>   down in their hearts they know we can't go on forever with</p>
<p>   the present taxation system. And I hope that as the weeks and months</p>
<p>   go by and the full details are revealed to the Australian public</p>
<p>   that the average man and woman in the street will see the value</p>
<p>   of a fairer and better tax system to take us into the 21st century.</p>
<p>   And we are very committed to selling it and I believe we will, very</p>
<p>   successfully.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>Will it be the average man and woman in the street who can look</p>
<p>   at the major benefits from your scheme?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes. I won't bring it in otherwise. I mean, there'll</p>
<p>   be some people who will suffer from the new system. People who are</p>
<p>   rorting the existing system will suffer. But we will bring in a</p>
<p>   system that is fairer, a system that will help Australian exporters</p>
<p>   for example, and a system that will provide people with more incentive</p>
<p>   and, therefore, greater levels of investment and more jobs. </p>
<p>I mean, you have to remember that when the Labor Party was in power</p>
<p>   it tried this in the middle 1980s. I mean, it squibbed it in the</p>
<p>   end because the unions didn't want it. But Paul Keating and</p>
<p>   Kim Beazley and Gareth Evans, in the mid 1980s, were the three strongest</p>
<p>   advocates, the three strongest advocates within the Government,</p>
<p>   along with Bob Hawke, the then Prime Minister, of reforming our</p>
<p>   taxation system. Now it suits them because they think they can win</p>
<p>   a few votes by running a fear campaign to oppose it. Now, let them</p>
<p>   do that. </p>
<p>I don't think the Australian people, in the end, if we explain</p>
<p>   it well, and we will, are going to fall for that. But that's</p>
<p>   a matter for them. I am the Prime Minister not just to enjoy myself</p>
<p>   in the job, I'm the Prime Minister to improve Australia. And</p>
<p>   one way of improving Australia is to give the country a better and</p>
<p>   fairer tax system and I'm determined to do it. And if the people,</p>
<p>   at the end of the day, don't accept it, well, that's their</p>
<p>   judgement and that is their right and I'll take that with the</p>
<p>   very best of grace. But I think that deep down the Australian people</p>
<p>   know the system needs improving. And if we give them a decent argument</p>
<p>   and a fair system, they'll go for it.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>All right. Well it's a gorgeous day here in Sydney. I'm</p>
<p>   sure those gardeners are enjoying themselves out on your lawns this</p>
<p>   morning over there in Kirribilli. And I trust that you'll have</p>
<p>   a busy and fruitful day down there in Canberra.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Okay.</p>
<p>G  </p>
<p>Okay.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Good on you, Mike.</p>
<p>[Ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
