<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4565</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS AT HOBART CAMPAIGN LUNCHEON, 28 NOVEMBER 1977</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/11/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004565.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
L' i 7L<br />
FOR PRESS 28 NOVEMBER 1977<br />
ADDRESS AT HOBART CAM. PAIGN LUN'. CHEON<br />
In this election, the questions which face the people of<br />
Tasmania and all Australians, are as clear as they<br />
were in 1975. In 1975 Australians faced up to the question of<br />
whether they wanted our country to lift itself out of the<br />
suffocating morass Labor had created.<br />
Australia and Tasmania first of all answered yes,<br />
with the most resounding vote in our history.<br />
Since then, the Australian people and government have been<br />
working together to bring our country -to the threshold of<br />
a new era of growth and prosperity.<br />
Now in this election, Tasmania will play a key role in deciding<br />
whether Australia will move forward, or whether we return<br />
to the excesses and extremes under Labor that almost wrecked<br />
our great country. of this result in Tasmania as throughout<br />
Australia I have no doubt. Just as in 1975 Tasmanians will<br />
resoundly return the Liberal government. For we can justly<br />
claim that we have done more for Australia, more for Tasmania,<br />
than any government before us.-This government has always<br />
kept the interests of Tasmania firmly in mind.<br />
Investment in Tasmania has been particularly helped, by our<br />
freight equalisation scheme which has removed Tasmania's freight<br />
disadvantage. That scheme, and our investment allowance,<br />
is responsible for such development as the new multi-million<br />
dollar APPM project at Burnie. It is development such as<br />
this which creates real new jobs for Tasmanians, jobs which<br />
they can keep.<br />
As a result of the Callaghan Report which we commissioned,<br />
the government is examining ways to boost further development<br />
of industry in this State. Investigations are already underway<br />
to see how we can further assist the forestry, fishing and<br />
tourist industries; how we might expand<br />
public service activities in this State; how we can<br />
best aiLect decentralisation funds to Tasmania; and the<br />
feasibility of launchinga pilot industrial estate in<br />
Launceston. The Hobart area has benefitted from Commonwealth funding of<br />
the first Hobart bridge I say " first" because this governmen-t<br />
is committed to the construction of a second bridge for Hobart. </p>
<p>I was surprised to see thta. t M~ r Neilsen had momentarily<br />
forgotten this the other day, surprised because last year he and<br />
I issued a joint press release confirming the decision that<br />
a second bridge be built. Pre'liminary studies for the second<br />
bridge are underway and I expect to receive the report in about<br />
six months.<br />
I want to pay special tribute at this point to the<br />
Tasmanian Liberal team in both houses. In my view they are<br />
the best team that Tasmania has ever had in the Federal<br />
Parliament. Kevin Newman has done a magnificent job in a<br />
difficult portfolio and he never lets his Ministerial rank stand<br />
in the way of sticking up for the interests of the State he<br />
represents. Bruce Goodluck has been a tireless fighter for<br />
lone fathers and the second Hobart bridge and he has been<br />
successful on'both. Max Burr has keenly advocated the interests<br />
of Tasmanian rural industry particularly the application<br />
of the investment allowance to primary producers. Ray Groom<br />
has fought for the -co ' ntinued existence of the Mount Lyeli<br />
Mine and Queenstown which is so dependent on the mine, and<br />
with his help, the Commonwealth has acted to keep the mine<br />
working. Michael Hodgman has pressed the cause of the<br />
underprivileged. It was largely through his efforts that the<br />
Commonwealth decided to assist most generously the overnight<br />
shelter for derelicts and alcoholics run by the Society of<br />
St. Vincent de Paul. And of course, as I think would be well<br />
known here, Michael Hodgman has taken a leading role in<br />
getting the Antartic Division transferred to his hometown<br />
Kingston. This project will have a major impact on the area<br />
creating 300 jobs durinq construction( which is scheduled<br />
to commence in 197S) and up to 200 jobs once it is opened and<br />
operating. The last two years have not been easy ones we have not taken<br />
soft options. We have not avoided the hard decisions.<br />
We have not fallen into the trap of seeking a cheap popularity<br />
that would undermine our country's future.<br />
We have faced the reality that if there is to be employment for<br />
those that want to work, Australia had to be restored to<br />
economic health. our policies are succeeding because we have<br />
restrained government spending, we have been able to reduce<br />
inflation.-inflation is down to 9 percent and fallinr this<br />
will help jobs. We have moderated wage increases.<br />
We have been able to make major tax reforms because of our<br />
restraint of government spending. $ 3.3 million will be saved<br />
in personal tax from our first two budgets. Business has saved<br />
a further $ 1000 million. They are a fundamental part of<br />
our strategy for wage restarint and economic recovery.<br />
We have ended Labor's tax rip off, cut taxes so that individuals,<br />
and businesses, could take decisions to invest, spend and save.<br />
Our tax reforms have greatly reduced the pressure for illusory<br />
wac--, increases which put more and more people out of work.<br />
our policies and our incentives to invest have given business<br />
the confidence to invest in Australia six billion dollars of<br />
investment is underway or ready to go. </p>
<p>These projects will bring work to Australia.<br />
It is through our policies of growth and development that we will.<br />
overcome the unemployment problei imposed on Australia.<br />
Labor increased unemployment by 157 percent almost<br />
200,000 people in one year. Labor did not just increase<br />
unemployment. It was not just that new entrantsto the workforce<br />
coulu not find jobs. The total number of people in work adtuallv<br />
fell.<br />
We have reversed this trend. In fact, over the two years<br />
to August 1977 total employment rose by 180,000. One<br />
vital reason for this is that we are propared to give<br />
Australian industry the protection itneeds. Labor slashed<br />
tariffs across the board even though they knew that this would<br />
throw tens of thousands out of work.<br />
Mr Whitlam and Senator Wriedt have made it clear Labor would do<br />
the same again. The vital protection we have given the<br />
Tasmanian textiles industry would be thrown into jeopardy<br />
if Labor were let loose on the economy again. We have<br />
passed laws to ensure that the Industries Assistance Commission<br />
fully takes into account the employment consequences of its<br />
recommendations. And we have taken decisions to protect<br />
the textiles,<br />
clothing and footwear industries for three years.<br />
All our economic policies are aimed at promoting greater growth<br />
and development and thus more jobs. </p>
<p>We are spending more than $ 100 million on training<br />
and job assistance schemes which help youngj people in<br />
particular learn new skills. Already well over 120,000 people<br />
have been or are being helped by hour schemes and we are<br />
constantly improving them. Because of our job assistance<br />
strategy and the growth and development our policies have<br />
made possible, unemployment will fall from February and<br />
keep failling.<br />
The major forecasts that the government has before it show that wit<br />
the continuation of the government's policies, work<br />
opportunities will expand. The first February tax cuts just two<br />
months away will increase the household income and spenaing<br />
power, injecting an extra $ 26.7 million a week into the economy.<br />
Because this injection takes place at a time when the<br />
inflationary fires are being put out the tax cut will have a<br />
positive impact on jobs. It will lift consumer spending,<br />
and because inflation is lower Australian manufacturers will be<br />
in a much better position to compete with imports in meeting<br />
the rising demand. our factories will get larger orders,<br />
and start working at higher levels of capacity.<br />
As that dei?-. vlopment gets under way, there will be a demand for<br />
more eraployees. Investment expenditure will continue to qrow<br />
in response to this more optimistic outlook.<br />
The February tax cuts are an integral part of the Government's<br />
plan for continued steady economic recovery. The reform not<br />
only greatly simplifies the tax rate scale,. it does not<br />
only assist 225,000 low income earners including<br />
tens of thousands of pensioners by relieving them of tax;<br />
it not only provides a new incentive for work, by putting<br />
percent of taxpayers on the same marginal tax rate, and<br />
allowing them to increase their earnings up to $ 16,000 a year<br />
before moving beyond this standard rate; it also provides<br />
for a responsible stimulus to the economy which will add to<br />
spending and activity, leading to higher employment.<br />
Unfortunately there has been no instant solution to the problems<br />
we inherited. There has just been the hard and undramatic grindi<br />
of developing and maintaining policies for restoring the<br />
economy and reducing inflation and unemployment.<br />
These policies are working. They form a consistent and coherent<br />
strategy which has brought us to the point of economic take-off.<br />
The Labor Party by contrast has no coherent economic strategy.<br />
Thatis the unequivocal conclusion to be drawn from ten days<br />
of conflict and contradiction between Labor's various<br />
economic spokesmen. Barely a day passes without some backdown<br />
anolocrv or hasty retreat. Consider their policy on taxes.<br />
Labor has said that, to pay for abolishing payroll tax, they will<br />
greatly increase personal income tax the major tax cuts<br />
to commence on first February are to be abandoned. Labor has<br />
spent over a week avoiding telling Australians what is now </p>
<p>obvious that they will not. only abolish the February 1 tax<br />
cuts they will abolish tax indexaLion too. They have<br />
tried to avoid telling the Australian people that to finance<br />
the abolition of payroll tax the average wage earner<br />
would be taxed an extra six dollars a week. Last Sunday<br />
week, Mr Whitlam said tax indexation would be postponed.<br />
Without hours, he s-iid he had " expressed himself wrongly."<br />
By Monday Mr Whitlam was saying Labor would bring in full<br />
tax indexation by July and Mr Willis was saying the same<br />
By Wednesday morning Mr Hayden was saying Labor could not commit<br />
itself beyond half tax indexation and Mr Hurford said<br />
he could not say what the Party's policy was, as he had not<br />
read about it in the papers.<br />
By Wednesday evening, Mr Hayden and Mr Hurford were disowning<br />
even half indexation. All this left the hapless Mr Whitlam<br />
somewhat in the lurch. He said yesterday he agreed with what<br />
Mr Hurford had said, apparently by that he meant the last<br />
thing Mr Hurford said whatever that was.<br />
Exactly the same confusion and deception has occurred over<br />
Labor's wages policy. Mr Whitlam said Labor would support full<br />
wage indexation. Mr Hayden however said Labor wanted only<br />
partial indexation. Then on Friday the ALP President, Mr<br />
Hawke, made it clear it did not matter a fig what Mr Whitlam<br />
and Mr Hayden thought the unions would not accept anything<br />
less than full wage indexation, regardless of the consequences.<br />
Amidst this conflict and confusion in the Labor Party, yesterday<br />
Mr Whitlam announced a sudden conversion to wage moderation.<br />
He sai he-supporte.-full wage indexation up to the level of<br />
average weekly earnings. When it is<br />
recalled how many speeches and statements Mr Whitlam has<br />
devoted to attacking this government's wages policy, the<br />
magnitude of Mr Whitlam's reversal can be seen.<br />
He has not only abandoned Labor's sacred platform. He has<br />
also admitted in effect that every statement hearnd his<br />
colleagues have made in Parliament over the two years attacking<br />
our wages policy have been cynical political propaganda.<br />
We've seen in the past how ephemeral Mr Whitlam's conv-sions<br />
to -conomic responsibility has been. Buthe has outdone<br />
himself with the current twists and turns<br />
the contradictions, the reversals in Labor's policy. A policy<br />
in which change is only a news flash away. The people of<br />
Australia must be rapidly coming to the conclusion that<br />
Mr Whitlan's latest " definitive commitment" is worth the<br />
price of yesterday's newspaper.<br />
Labor's-confusion on tax and wage indexation indicates how little<br />
they have thought through any of their economic policies.<br />
This is clear when their various unemployment schemes are<br />
examined in any detail. The scheme to abolish payroll t--<br />
will be a handy boost to company prof its that is, for those largE<br />
companies that currently pay State payroll tax. </p>
<p>Utah would be a windfall of $ 2 million.<br />
C RA $ 10 million<br />
BHP $ 33 million<br />
MIM 4.5 million<br />
CSR 8 million<br />
Bank NSW $ 11 million<br />
Ford 7 million<br />
ACI $ 11 million<br />
Dunlop $ 11-13 million<br />
General Motors $ 10 million<br />
A survey last week of large employers showed that not one<br />
could forecast any increase in their own employment levels<br />
if relieved of payroll tax. The Premier of South Australia,<br />
Mr Dunstan, has made it clear that a payroll remission scheme<br />
does not work he has tried it in South Australia with no result.<br />
Labor's alternative solution to unemployment is to spend up big.<br />
$ 800 million in the first six months, and if all their promises<br />
are to be believed, thousands of millions of dollars after that.<br />
Some of the initial $ 8.00 million will be spent on items that<br />
will produce no jobs at all, even in the short term. Mr Whitlam.<br />
includes money for the Julius Dam in Queensland, a dam that has<br />
already been built. He.-includes more funds for the Dartmouth<br />
Dam, even though the funds will not alter existing work<br />
schedules one iota. This spend-up would be quite counterproductive;<br />
it would expand the deficit and inevitably promote<br />
the biggest unemployment-creator in which country inflation.<br />
I can do no better in pointing out the obvious defects in Labor's<br />
scheme than to quote a former Treasurer who said:<br />
" While the level of unemployment is much higher than would<br />
be wished; the fact is that any efforts to accelerate the<br />
reflation of the economy in our urgent response to<br />
the unemployment figures., would have most undesirable<br />
effects. It would be self-defeating."<br />
Those sound words were spoken in October 1975. The<br />
Treasurer was Mr Hayden. How quickly responsible economics can<br />
hp~ fr)-rrcn-. f-. pn in thp T, ahn'r ' Part-w. How long it seems to be<br />
taking the Labor Party to adopt responsible policies which are in<br />
the interests of Tasmanians and all Australians.<br />
In just two years we h-ave gone a long way to restoring hope,<br />
confidence and spirit to our people. For total success, we<br />
need one more ingredient and that is certainty. We have<br />
to be certain that our countr economic management is in the<br />
hands of a government that will pursue sound policies. </p>
<p>4 .7.<br />
The alternative that Mr Whitlam offers is government by<br />
wrangle -a hop scotch governennt. That kind of government<br />
has been tried. It did not work. It will still not work.<br />
Australia needs policies whichwill reduce inflation, not increas<br />
it. Australia needs fair but firm policies for trade unions<br />
not placing Mr Gallagher hbove the law.<br />
Australia needs programmes and policies that it can afford.<br />
Not lavish and ill conceived crash schemes. Australia needs<br />
lower not higher taxes. That is the only way to get unemployment<br />
down, and keep it down.<br />
With your help in Tasmania, my Government will get on with the joh </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
