<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1787</transcript-id>
    <title>THE MINISTRY - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER. MR. JOHN GORTON</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/02/1968</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001787.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO FOR PRESS NOT FOR RELEASE BY ANY MEDIA UNTIL<br />
6.00 MONDAY, 26 FEBRUARY 1968<br />
P. M. No. 25/ 1968<br />
THE MINISTRY<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, Mr. John Gorton<br />
A new Ministry will be sworn at noon on Wednesday<br />
next, 28 February. With the authority of His Excellency the<br />
Governor-General, I release the following details of the new<br />
Cabinet and Ministry.<br />
1. PRIME MINISTER The Hon. J. G. Gorton<br />
2. DEPUTY PRIME MINISTER ANiD MINISTER FOR TRADE AND INDUSTRY<br />
The Rt. Hon. J. McEwen<br />
3. TREASURER The Rt. Hon. William McMahon<br />
4. MINISTER FOR EXTERNAL AFFAIRS The Rt. Hon. Paul Hasluck<br />
MINISTER FOR DEFENCE The Hon. Allen Fairhall<br />
6. MINISTER FOR PRIMARY INDUSTRY The Hon. J. D. Anthony<br />
7. POSTMASTER-GENERAL AND VICE-PRESIDENT OF THE EXECUTIVE<br />
COUNCIL The Hon. A. S. Hulme<br />
8. MINISTER FOR NATIONAL DEVELOPMENT The Hon. David<br />
Fairbairn, D. F. C.<br />
9. MINISTER FOR LABOUR AND NATIONAL SERVICE The Hon. L. H. E.<br />
Bury<br />
MINISTER FOR SHIPPING AND TRANSPORT AND ASSISTING THE<br />
MINISTER FOR TRADE AND INDUSTRY The Hon.<br />
Ian Sinclair<br />
11. MINISTER FOR SUPPLY AND LEADER OF THE GOVERNMENT IN THE<br />
SENATE Senator the Hon. Ken Anderson<br />
12. MINISTER FOR EDUCATION AND SCIENCE The Hon. Malcolm Fraser </p>
<p>-2-<br />
13. MINISTER FOR AIR AND ASSISTING THE TREASURER The Hon.<br />
Gordon Freeth<br />
14. MINISTER FOR EXTERNAL TERRITORIES The Hon. C. E. Barnes<br />
MINISTER FOR CIVIL AVIATION The Hon. R. W. C. Swartz,<br />
E. D.<br />
16 MINISTER FOR IMMIGRATION AND LEADER OF THE HOUSE The Hon.<br />
B. M. Snedden, Q. C.<br />
17. MINISTER FOR HEALTH The Hon. A. J. Forbes, M. C.<br />
18. MINISTER FOR REPATRIATION Senator the Hon. G. Colin<br />
McKe liar<br />
19. MINISTER FOR HOUSING Senator the Hon. Dame Annabelle<br />
Rankin, D. B. E.<br />
ATTORNEY-GENERAL The Hon. N. H. Bowen, Q. C.<br />
21. MINISTER FOR THE NAVY The Hon. C. R. Kelly<br />
22. MINISTER FOR THE INTERIOR The Hon. P. J. Nixon<br />
23. MINISTER FOR THE ARMY The Hon. Lynch<br />
24. MINISTER FOR CUSTOMS AND EXCISE Senator the Hon.<br />
Malcolm Scott<br />
259 MINISTER FOR SOCIAL SERVICES AND MINISTER IN CHARGE OF<br />
ABORIGINAL AFFAIRS The Hon. W. C. Wentworth<br />
26. MINISTER FOR WORKS AND UNDER THE MINISTER FOR TRADE AND<br />
INDUSTRY MINISTER IN CHARGE OF TOURIST ACTIVITIES<br />
Senator the Hon. R. C. Wright<br />
The first twelve Ministers named will comprise the<br />
Cabinet. I have proposed to His Excellency t~ hat Mr. Lynch,<br />
Senator Scott, Mr. Wentworth and Senator Wright be sworn as Members<br />
of the Federal Executive Council. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
