<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8596</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP BUILDING BETTER CITIES PROGRAM</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/07/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008596.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
ThN~<br />
I<br />
Cl.<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
BUILDING BETTER CITIES PROGRAM<br />
The Prime Minister today announced that the Commonwealth would support $ 10 million<br />
of Commonwealth funding to speed up the revitalisation of the South Townsville area.<br />
The funding would be made available under the Commonwealt' Builin BetrCte<br />
Program. In announcing support for the project, he congratulated the Townsville City Council and<br />
the Queensland Government on the considerable work carried out to ensure the success of<br />
the submission.<br />
Under the " One Nation" statement, the Commonwealth is already providing $ 20 million<br />
towards the upgrading of the Port of Townsville.<br />
" The South Townsville proposal demonstrates many of the principles of the Building<br />
Better Cities Program," the Prime Minister said.<br />
" The area is already well serviced and is capable of a twofold increase in population with<br />
only modest upgrading of roads, water supply and drainage infrastructure. And this can<br />
be achieved without destroying the area's historic character."<br />
" The completed scheme would also add to the already considerable tourist attraction of<br />
this region."<br />
" This is a much more efficient and environmentally sustainable way of managing the<br />
growth of our cities rather than encouraging expensive, car dependent sprawl.<br />
" Also one of the keynotes of micro-economic reform in Australia is to use more<br />
effectively the enormous capital investment Australia has made in established urban<br />
infrastructure. South Townsville project can be a significant demonstration project in the<br />
way to revitalise inner area land in Australia's regional cities," the Prime Minister said. </p>
<p>Under the proposals, industrial activities which are incompatible with residential land uses<br />
in South Townsville would be encouraged to relocate to more suitable sites in the city.<br />
Residential and freight traffic will be separated as far as possible and landscaped buffers<br />
will be constructed between residential areas and the rail and road freight routes which, at<br />
present, cause noise nuisance. A number of housing projects are planned to demonstrate<br />
how increased densities and greater housing choice can be achieved whilst reinforcing the<br />
distinctive and historic character of the suburb.<br />
The Prime Minister also emphasised that the Building Better Cities Program was about<br />
demonstrating better ways of co-ordinating the various agencies involved in town<br />
planning and the provision of infrastructure.<br />
" Townsville has the opportunity to provide leadership to many other regional centres on<br />
the issue of integrated planning," he said.<br />
" The co-ordination of planning for the residential areas with that of the adjacent Port area<br />
is also important because the rapid development of the Port is a key to the industrial<br />
development of Townsville. I'm looking forward to the Council's and State Government's<br />
proposals as to how integration will be achieved especially on freight routes and the<br />
location of bulk storage areas."<br />
Once planning for South Townsville is properly integrated with the planning for the<br />
adjacent port area and the railway yards then this important addition to the Queensland<br />
program will be signed, sealed and delivered.<br />
TOWNSVILLE JULY 28,1992 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
