<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>41312</transcript-id>
    <title>Bilateral meeting with His Excellency Li Keqiang, Premier of the People’s Republic of China</title>
    <prime-minister>Turnbull, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20150915 - 20180824</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/11/2017</release-date>
    <release-type>Transcript</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p><strong>THE HON. MALCOLM TURNBULL MP, PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>Thank you very much Premier.</p>
<p>Yes, I remember very fondly your visit to Australia with your wife in March.</p>
<p>I enjoyed welcoming you to Australia. You were very warmly welcomed by everybody, especially at our football match we went to together.</p>
<p>I know, as you know, Australia is the most successful multicultural society in the world, with Chinese the second most spoken language in Australia and we have nearly 6 per cent of Australians.</p>
<p><strong>HIS EXCELLENCY Li Keqiang, Premier of the People’s Republic of China:</strong></p>
<p>[Inaudible]</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>That shows you are a natural diplomat!</p>
<p>[Laughter]</p>
<p>As I was saying, Chinese is the second most spoken language in Australia, we have just under 6 per cent of our community are of Chinese origins.</p>
<p>I believe Australia is a great example of how people from every corner of the world, different faiths, different backgrounds, if they show mutual respect to each other, can live together in harmony.</p>
<p>I believe our relationship gets stronger and stronger.</p>
<p>We had a very good discussion yesterday about the challenge we face from the DPRK.</p>
<p>I look forward to discussing the other security issues that will be the focus of the East Asia Summit here today.</p>
<p>So it’s great to see you again and we’ve always had very frank and warm discussions.</p>
<p><strong>[ENDS]</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
