<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9174</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON PJ KEATING MP LAOS STATE DINNER 5 APRIL 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/04/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009174.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING, MP<br />
LAOS STATE DINNER, 5 APRIL 1994<br />
( CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY; EMBARGO 9PM AEST)<br />
Thank you very much for your warm welcome.<br />
I am pleased to have the opportunity to return the visit<br />
of Prime Minister Khamtay to Australia last Decemubervery<br />
pf~ eased to visit Vientiane and Laos.<br />
In the last two years, as Prime-Minister, I have been to<br />
many of the countries of the region. I have to say that,<br />
apart from the quite phenomenal energy and growth to be<br />
seen, nothing is quite so striking as the difference<br />
between them.<br />
Every country I have visited is a reminder of the fallacy<br />
which still prevails among many people in the Western<br />
nations, that Asia is essentially monolithic that the<br />
countries of Asia are fundamentally alike.<br />
Laos is another reminder of the untruth of that.<br />
Not only is Laos a country with a unique history and<br />
cultural heritage, within your borders live, I<br />
understand, people from about 70 different ethnic<br />
backgrounds. While I suspect that it is not widely known in the rest<br />
of the world, including in Asia, the modern Australian<br />
population is also a heterogeneous one deriving from<br />
some 150 national backgrounds, including the nations of<br />
As ia.<br />
Despite this, I think it is safe to say that in Asia many<br />
people think of Australia as a purely Europeanessentially<br />
British country, with a purely European and<br />
essentially British view of the world.<br />
In fact, like Laos, these days our view of the world is<br />
distinctly our own.<br />
Like Laos, Australia has embarked on a new future. Like<br />
Laos, we seek it primarily in new and deeper<br />
relationships with the countries of Asia and the Pacific. </p>
<p>2<br />
And because we have undertaken some fundamental reforms<br />
to open up our economy, we are succeeding.<br />
Today the Asia Pacific is where we do most of our trade;<br />
it is where we invest; it is where we work to develop the<br />
necessary stucues for trade and investment, increase<br />
mutual understanding and strengthen the security of the<br />
region. We have long recognised the fact of our proximity to<br />
Asia. We have long seen the necessity to engage with the<br />
rg-ibn.<br />
Our forty year old relationship with Laos is evidence of<br />
thi s.<br />
But we have never engaged as we engage now. Our<br />
relationships with the countries of the region have never<br />
been so rewarding or so complete. We have never been so<br />
positive about our relationship with the region, nor so<br />
confident about the creative role we can play.<br />
To do this we have had to open up both our economy and<br />
our minds.<br />
We have recognised the rewards to be gained from<br />
engagement with the most dynamic economies in the world;<br />
and the benefits which flow from our participation in the<br />
economic development of countries like Laos.<br />
These are great rewards.<br />
But Australia has also recognised that, whether it is in<br />
our relationships with the developed or the developing<br />
countries of the region, there is an added dimension to<br />
the return on our investments.<br />
There is a'sense in which contemporary Australia is<br />
discovering itself through its increased involvement in<br />
As ia.<br />
We have discovered, among other things, that we can<br />
compete with the Asian economies.<br />
In learning to compete we have discovered new capacities<br />
to work more efficiently and more cooperatively, to use<br />
and develop our skills and technology, to develop<br />
products and markets for them, to understand and do<br />
business with countries very different from our own.<br />
Countries like Laos.<br />
We have also discovered that we can play a creative role<br />
in the great issues confronting the region. We learned<br />
that through the success of initiatives to bring peace to<br />
Cambodia.-</p>
<p>We learned it through our initiatives with " APEC the<br />
forum which promises to contribute so much to -trade and<br />
investment in the Asia Pacific.<br />
And we have discovered that, far from representing a<br />
threat to our culture and institutions, our engagement is<br />
increasing our confidence and re-shaping and renewing our<br />
sense of national identity.<br />
For similar reasons I believe Laos should feel confident<br />
that its culture and traditions will readily survive the<br />
new openness the Laotian government is encouraging.<br />
Your government's far-sighted reforms will enable Laos to<br />
deepen its relations with other countries in the region.<br />
Reforms such as the new liberal forei-gn investment laws<br />
are attracting investment and expertiise essential for<br />
economic development.<br />
Australian companies are keen to take advantage of them.<br />
It is an example of the way in which, with the easing of<br />
longstanding political antipathies, we are discovering<br />
that we have many complementary interests.<br />
Australian companies can offer expertise in transport,<br />
building and construction, communications and energy<br />
emerging from the experience of developing a vast and<br />
immensely varied continent.<br />
It is a matter of great pride and satisfaction to my<br />
government and to the Australian people that we have put<br />
these skills to use in the construction of the Friendship<br />
Bridge. It is our great hope and belief that it will play an<br />
important part in making the future for the people of<br />
Laos more secure and more prosperous.<br />
Australia hopes that theFr. Lendsbhip_. Bari4ge will be an<br />
enduring symbol of our relationship with the region of<br />
the expertise we can bring and the good will we bring<br />
with it.<br />
It is also a matter of pride that, like the Friendship<br />
Bridge, the new border control facilities, which it will<br />
be my privilege to open tomorrow, were funded by<br />
Australian development assistance and engineered by<br />
Australian companies.<br />
Australia is now the third-largest foreign investor in<br />
Laos.<br />
An Australian company, T-ran~ s-4eld, is developing the Nam<br />
Thewn 2 hydro-electric project the largest single<br />
enterprise investment ever undertaken in your country. </p>
<p>NormandyPoseidon, an Australian mining company, has<br />
formed a joinfV venture to explore for minerals and<br />
develop a 5,000 square kilometre area north-east of<br />
Vientiane. During my stay I will have the pleasure of witnessing<br />
with Prime Minister Khamtay the signing of a Memorandum<br />
of Agreement between the government of Laos and the<br />
Hydro-Electric Corporation of Tasmania to develop two<br />
major projects in Southern Laos.<br />
Prime Minister Khamtay and I will also witness the<br />
signature of an investment promotion and protection<br />
agreement setting up a framework for commercial relations<br />
between us.<br />
I also take this opportunity to say that the Australian<br />
government is aware of the acute rice shortage Laos is<br />
presently suffering and I am able to announce this<br />
evening that Australia will contribute $ 1 million in<br />
emergency relief funds through the World Food Program to<br />
help meet this need.<br />
Tonight I am pleased to announce the first Australian<br />
multi-year commitment to Laos $ 47.5 million over the<br />
four years to 1997.<br />
This will allow pressing needs in a number of development<br />
sectors in Laos to be addressed.<br />
These include the construction of a number of<br />
bridges on Route 13 and further road works in<br />
association with the Friendship Bridge.<br />
An innovative program of English language<br />
instruction to be screened on Australian Television<br />
International supported by audio visual and print<br />
materials. A childrens health initiative including an increased<br />
effort to eradicate polio and control malaria in the<br />
region.<br />
We are friends of 40 years standing. Yet only now are we<br />
discovering the potential of our friendship.<br />
While very different countries we are rapidly learning to<br />
recognise similarities in outlook and interest we had<br />
never seen before.<br />
A common interest in trade and investment, in regional<br />
security and prosperity; a common interest in protecting<br />
our culture and identity while underpinning our future<br />
prosperity. If Australia and Laos continue to look for the common<br />
ground between us, while remaining open to the region and<br />
the world, I have no doubt that our friendship and our<br />
two countries will grow and prosper. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
