<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6139</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE HON RJ HAWKE AT THE EAST-WEST CENTER - HONOLULU, SUNDAY 19 JUNE 1983</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/06/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006139.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
o1<br />
SPEECH BY THE HON. R. J. HAWKE<br />
AT THE EAST-WEST CENTER HONOLULU<br />
SUNDAY, 19 JUNE 1983<br />
IT GIVES ME GREAT PLEASURE TO BE HERE WITH YOU<br />
IN HAWAII AND IN PARTICULAR TO BE ABLE TO ATTEND THIS<br />
DINNER OF THE INTERNATIONAL BOARD OF GOVERNORS. I AM<br />
MOST GRATEFUL TO THE CHAIRMAN OF THE BOARD OF GOVERNORS,<br />
MR, CHAR, AND THE PRESIDENT OF THE CENTER, DR. L, FOR<br />
THEIR THOUGHTFULNESS IN HAVING ORGANISED THIS MOST USEFUL<br />
OCCASION TO LET ME MEET AND TALK WITH YOU.<br />
I SHOULD ALSO LIKE TO SAY HOW VERY PLEASED I AM THAT<br />
RATU SIR KAMISESE MARA, THE PRIME MINISTER OF FIJI AND A MEMBER<br />
OF THE BOARD OF GOVERNORS, IS ABLE TO BE HERE AS ONE OF<br />
THE HOSTS THIS EVENING.<br />
AUSTRALIA AND FIJI SHARE A CLOSE PARTNERSHIP IN THE<br />
SOUTH PACIFIC REGION AND IT IS OPPORTUNE THAT WE SHOULD SEE<br />
EACH OTHER TONIGHT SINCE I SHALL BE PRIVILEGED TO HOST THE<br />
SOUTH PACIFIC FORUM LATER THIS YEAR IN CANBERRA.<br />
I SHOULD FIRST LIKE TO TAKE THIS OPPORTUNITY TO<br />
EXPRESS THE NEW AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT'S UNCHANGED AND FIRM<br />
SUPPORT FOR THE EAST-WEST CENTER. WE SUPPORT WHOLEHEARTEDLY<br />
THE PRINCIPLE ON WHICH THE EAST-WEST CENTER WAS FOUNDED.<br />
THAT IS, TO PROMOTE BETTER RELATIONS AND UNDERSTANDING AMONG<br />
THE PEOPLES AND NATIONS OF ASIA, THE PACIFIC AND THE UNITED<br />
STATES, </p>
<p>THE CENTER HAS BEEN IN THE VANGUARD OF OPINIONFORMING<br />
IN THE UNITED STATES ABOUT THE ASIAN-PACIFIC<br />
REGAION. WE IN AUSTRALIA EQUALLY BELIEVE IN THE<br />
IMPORTANCE OF THE FUTURE OF THE PACIFIC BASIN AS ONE OF<br />
THE MOST DYNAMIC REGIONS OF THE GLOBEAND THE IMPORTANCE<br />
TO AUSTRALIA OF HER PLACE IN THAT REGION. THE<br />
PARTNERSHIP AND CO-OPERATION OF THE COUNTRIES OF<br />
THIS REGION WILL BE A VITAL FORCE DETERMINING THE<br />
FUTURE OF WORLD AFFAIRS.<br />
THE EAST-WEST CENTER HAS A REAL ROLE TO<br />
PLAY IN THIS UNFOLDING STORY, AND WE IN AUSTRALIA<br />
LOOK TO THE CENTER TO CONTINUE TO FOCUS THE ATTENTION<br />
OF DECISION MAKERS IN AMERICA ON OUR PART OF THE<br />
WORLD. ONE SIGNIFICANT ASPECT OF THE EAST-WEST<br />
CENTER'S WORK TO WHICH I WOULD LIKE TO DRAW ATTENTION<br />
IS ITS CO-OPERATIVE NATURE. THE EAST-WEST CENTER'S<br />
PROGRAMS ARE NOT A ONE-WAY FLOW OF IDEAS, EXPERTISE<br />
OR FINANCE FROM ONE COUNTRY TO ANOTHER. RATHER, THE<br />
CENTER PURSUES A CO-OPERATIVE APPROACH, THROUGH THE<br />
TECHNIQUE OF JOINT PARTICIPATION IN ITS RESEARCH TEAMS<br />
BY EXPERTS FROM BOTH THE DEVELOPED AND THE DEVELOPING<br />
COUNTRIES IN THE ASIAN/ PACIFIC REGION. SPECIALISTS<br />
FROM ALL COUNTRIES ARE THUS ABLE TO WORK TOGETHER AS<br />
PARTNERS. ./ 3<br />
L </p>
<p>3.<br />
AUSTRALIA HAS BEEN PLEASED TO BE ABLE TO HELP<br />
THIS ASPECT OF THE CENTER'S WORK BY FUNDING THIRDCOUNTRY<br />
SCHOLARSHIPS UNDER WHICH STUDENTS FROM COUNTRIES<br />
IN THE REGION OTHER THAN AUSTRALIA ITSELF ARE ABLE TO<br />
PARTICIPATE IN EAST-WEST CENTER PROGRAMS8<br />
I WOULD LIKE TO TAKE A FEW MOMENTS TO SINGLE<br />
OUT THE EXCELLENT WORK BEING DONE UNDER THE PACIFIC<br />
ISLANDS DEVELOPMENT PROGRAM, A RECENT INNOVATION IN THE<br />
EAST-WEST CENTER'S SCHEDULE OF OPERATIONS, IT WAS<br />
DUE IN GOOD MEASURE TO A PERSONAL INITIATIVE BY RATU<br />
SIR KAMISESE MARA THAT THISPROGRAM WAS COMMENCED<br />
THREE YEARS AGO,<br />
THE PACIFIC ISLANDS PROGRAM RESPONDED TO A FEELING<br />
BY LEADERS OF PACIFIC ISLAND COUNTRIES AND TERRITORIES<br />
THAT THEY WISHED TO SET THEIR OWN PRIORITIES FOR DEVELOPMENT<br />
STUDIES AND TRAINING, THE PACIFIC ISLANDS DEVELOPMENT<br />
PROGRAM IS UNIQUE IN THAT ITS STANDING COMMITTEE, COMPOSED<br />
OF THE CHIEF EXECUTIVES OF GOVERNMENTS OF A NUMBER OF<br />
PACIFIC ISLAND COUNTRIES, MEETS TWICE YEARLY TO OFFER<br />
POLICY GUIDANCE ON THE RUNNING OF THE PROGRAM, </p>
<p>4,<br />
THIS TYPE OF INTIMATE INTEREST AND<br />
INVOLVEMENT IN THE PROGRAM ON THE PART OF THE<br />
MOST SENIOR POLITICAL LEADERS OF THE REGION IS<br />
IN ITSELF AN EXTREMELY VALUABLE RESOURCE AND ONE<br />
WHICH I AM SURE THE EAST-WEST CENTRE FULLY<br />
APPRECIATES, IT GIVES ME GREAT PLEASURE TO STATE<br />
THAT THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT SUPPORTS THE PACIFIC<br />
ISLANDS DEVELOPMENT PROGRAM, BOTH IN SPIRIT AND BY<br />
PROVIDING FINANCIAL CONTRIBUTIONS,<br />
I AM NOW OF COURSE NEARING THE END OF MY<br />
FIRST OFFICIAL OVERSEAS MISSION AS PRIME MINISTER<br />
OF AUSTRALIA A JOURNEY WHICH HAS TAKEN US TO<br />
PORT MORESBY, JAKARTA, LONDON, PARIS, GENEVA,<br />
WASHINGTON, NEW YORK AND TORONTO,<br />
You WILL, I TRUST, NOT FIND IT INAPPROPRIATE<br />
THAT I SHOULD REFER BRIEFLY TO THE GENERAL PURPOSES<br />
OF MY MISSION AND THE EXTENT TO WHICH THOSE PURPOSES<br />
HAVE BEEN FULFILLED FOR THE ADVANCEMENT OF AUSTRALIA'S<br />
NATIONAL INTERESTS, IT IS THE MORE APPROPRIATE FOR<br />
ME TO DO THAT HERE, IN AS MUCH AS, EVEN IN PLACES<br />
AS DISTANT AS PARIS AND GENEVA, I TOOK THE OPPORTUNITY<br />
TO PLACE IN THE FOREFRONT OF MY PRIVATE DISCUSSIONS AND<br />
PUBLIC STATEMENTS, CONCERNS AND INTERESTS POLITICAL<br />
AND ECONOMIC OF PROFOUND IMPORTANCE TO OUR REGION AND<br />
OUR PEOPLES,<br />
i I </p>
<p>AT ALL TIMES, BUT ESPECIALLY IN THE UNITED STATES, I<br />
SOUGHT TO EMPHASISE AUSTRALIA'S PLACE AS A PARTNER AND<br />
NEIGHBOUR IN THE FUTURE AND DESTINY OF THIS GREAT<br />
PACIFIC REGION. ALL SUCH MISSSIONS BY HEADS OF GOVERNMENT DO,<br />
OF COURSE, HAVE AS A PRIMARY OBJECTIVE THE ESTABLISHMENT<br />
OF PERSONAL CONTACT, AND HOPEFULLY, RAPPORT AND<br />
UNDERSTANDING WITH OTHER LEADERS.<br />
OBVIOUSLY, THIS HAS PARTICULAR RELEVANCE<br />
FOR THE HEAD OF A NEW ADMINISTRATION SUCH AS MINE. BUT<br />
AUSTRALIA'S RELATIONSHIPS WITH ALL THE COUNTRIES I<br />
VISITED, BUT ESPECIALLY WITH PAPUA NEW GUINEA,<br />
INDONESIA AND THE UNITED STATES, ARE FAR DEEPER<br />
AND ENDURING THAN GOVERNMENT-TO-GOVERNMENT RELATIONS,<br />
OR AS BETWEEN ADMINISTRATION AND ADMINISTRATION,<br />
FOR EXAMPLE, THE PARTNERSHIP BETWEEN THE<br />
UNITED STATES AND AUSTRALIA, FORMALISED BY THE ANZUS<br />
TREATY, WHICH INCLUDES NEW ZEALAND, TRANSCENDS THE<br />
LIFE OR DURATION OF ANY AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT OR<br />
ANY AMERICAN ADMINISTRATION. 6 </p>
<p>69<br />
ITS FUNDAMENTAL IMEANING, PURPOSE AND PURPORT<br />
IS NOT SUBJECT TO PASSIN4G -CHANGES IN PARTISAN FORTUNES,<br />
BECAUSE IT HAS NEVER BEEN BASED ON SUCH CONSIDERATIONS IN<br />
AUSTRALIA OR AMERICA*<br />
NEVERTHELESS, PERSONAL CONTACT IS ALWAYS MUTUALLY<br />
BENEFICIAL AND SO MUCH THE BETTER, IF THAT CONTACT RESULTS IN<br />
A CLEARER APPRECIATION ON BOTH SIDES OF THE POINTS OF VIEW$<br />
POINTS OF DIFFERENCE, AND THE LARGER AREAS OF COMMON PURPOSE.<br />
AND JUST AS, IN THE APPROACH my GOVERNMENT IS<br />
ATTEMPTING TO BRING TO THE PROBLEMS OF ECONOMIC MANAGEMENT,<br />
THE PROCESS OF KNOWLEDGE-ACQUIRING AND KNOWLEDGE-SHARING<br />
PLAYS A KEY PART, SO, ON THE WIDER STAGE, THE FIRST-HAND<br />
EXCHANGE OF VIEWS AND INFORMATION BETWEEN HEADS OF GOVERNMENT.-<br />
AND A WIDE RANGE OF MINISTERS AND SENIOR OFFICIALS,<br />
IS CLEARLY VALUABLE$ SECOND, MY PURPOSE WAS TO ESTABLISH THE<br />
UNDERLYING CONTINUITY IN THE MAJOR DIRECTIONS OF AUSTRALIA'S<br />
INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS UNDER AUSTRALIA'S NEW GOVERNMENT.<br />
AND, WHEN I SAY " CONTINUITY", I DO NOT MEAN ONLY OR<br />
EVEN MAINLY THAT BETWEEN MY GOVERNMENT AND ITS IMMEDIATE<br />
PREDECESSOR. IN A NUMBER OF QUITE FUNDAMENTAL AREAS, THIS<br />
ESSENTIAL CONTINUITY, WHATEVER DIFFERENCES MAY HAVE ARISEN<br />
OVER THE YEARS, ON SPECIFIC ISSUES SOME OF THEM OF GREAT<br />
MOMENT AT HOME AND ABROAD THIS ESSENTIAL CONTINUITY, I SAY,<br />
REACHES BACK YEARS AND DECADES# a .1 7 </p>
<p>7.<br />
FOR EXAMPLE, THE BI-PARTISANSHIP WHICH EXISTS<br />
ON AUSTRALIA'S EXCEPTIONAL OBLIGATIONS TOWARDS<br />
AN INDEPENDENT PAPUA NEW GUINEA, EXTENDS BACK<br />
MORE THAN A DECADE TO THE FOUNDATIONAL WORK OF<br />
THE WHITLAM LABOR GOVERNMENT. THE RECOGNITION<br />
OF THE FUNDAMENTAL AND OVER-RIDING IMPORTANCE OF<br />
CONSTRUCTIVE RELATIONS WITH THE NEIGHBOURING<br />
GIANT INDONESIA GOES BACK TO THE DAYS WHEN, IN THE<br />
LATE FORTIES, THE CHIFLEY LABOR GOVERNMENT WAS<br />
INDONESIA'S FIRST SIGNIFICANT SUPPORTER OF HER<br />
INDEPENDENCE. AND, OF COURSE, THE AMERICAN-AUSTRALIAN<br />
PARTNERSHIP ITSELF WAS FORGED FORTY YEARS AGO BY<br />
THE CURTIN LABOR GOVERNMENT, AND SUCCESSIVE<br />
AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENTS, LABOR AND LIBERAL ALIKE,<br />
HAVE RE-AFFIRMED ITS PRIMACY WITH EQUAL FIRMNESS,<br />
THIS IS A RECORD OF CONTINUITY, CONSISTENCY<br />
AND NATIONAL CONSENSUS ON FUNDAMENTALS WHICH FEW NATIONS CAN EXCEL<br />
AND, THROUGHOUT THIS MISSION, I HAVE TRIED TO GIVE<br />
EXPRESSION TO THE CLEAR AND OVERWHELMING WISH OF<br />
THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE THAT WE SHOULD CONTINUE ON<br />
THIS BROAD PATH. </p>
<p>4' t 8.<br />
THIRD, I HAVE TAKEN THE OPPORTUNITY TO PUT<br />
AUSTRALIA'S VIEW ON A NUMBER OF SPECIFIC MATTERS<br />
OF CONSIDERABLE IMPORTANCE, BOTH PRIVATELY AND<br />
PUBLICLY, THESE INCLUDE NOT ONLY ISSUES SUCH AS<br />
EAST TIMOR, CAMBODIA, AID TO INDO-CHINA, FRENCH<br />
NUCLEAR TESTING IN THE PACIFIC, THE ANZUS<br />
RELATIONSHIP AND THE JOINT AUSTRALIAN U. S.<br />
INSTALLATIONS, BUT MORE GENERAL MATTERS SUCH AS<br />
DEVELOPMENTS IN OUR REGION, ARMS CONTROL AND<br />
INTERNATIONAL ECONOMIC ISSUES.<br />
EQUALLY, I HAVE BEEN ABLE TO HEAR THE VIEWS<br />
OF OTHER COUNTRIES ON THESE ISSUES AND THOSE OF<br />
PARTICULAR CONCERN TO THEM.<br />
I HAVE BEEN ABLE TO LISTEN TO WHAT SENIOR<br />
ADMINISTRATION OFFICIALS IN THE UNITED STATES<br />
AND LEADING FIGURES IN THE BUSINESS AND FINANCIAL<br />
COMMUNITY IN NEW YORK HAVE TO SAY ABOUT THE<br />
RECOVERY OF THE US ECONOMY AND THE EXTENT TO WHICH<br />
IT CAN BE SUSTAINED, AND THE BROADER VIEWS ON THE<br />
OUTLOOK FOR THE GLOBAL ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENTS FOR THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN ECONOMY, INCLUDING THE FRAMING OF THE<br />
1983-84 BUDGET, </p>
<p>AND I HAVE PUT OUR VIEWS ON THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
ECONOMY, INCLUDING POLICY ON FOREIGN INVESTMENT,<br />
TO KEY FIGURES IN THE BUSINESS AND FINANCIAL<br />
COMMUNITIES IN NEW YORK AND PARIS, SO AS TO<br />
ENSURE ON THEIR PART THE MAINTENANCE OF CONFIDENCE<br />
IN OUR ECONOMY WHEN THEY COME TO CONSIDER INVESTMENT<br />
DECISIONS. 11ITHIN THIS BROAD FRAMEWORK I MIGHT<br />
MENTION SOME DETAILS OF THE WORK OF THE PAST FORTNIGHT.<br />
WE REACHED AN AGREEMENT WITH PRIME MINISTER<br />
SOMARE REGARDING FUTURE AID TO PAPUA NEW GUINEAAN<br />
IMPORTANT AGREEMENT FOR THAT COUNTRY'IS ECONOMYC<br />
AND SOCIAL STABILITY.<br />
IN JAKARTA I CONVEYED TO THE INDONESIAN<br />
AUTHORITIES AT THE HIGHEST LEVELS OUR CONCERN THAT AN<br />
ACT OF SELF-DETERMINATION HAD NOT TAKEN PLACE IN<br />
EAST TIMOR; THE IMPORTANCE THAT WE ATTACHED TO PROGRESS<br />
ON FAMILY REUNIONS AND THE ESTABLISHMENT OF AN AUSTRALIAN<br />
ASSOCIATED PRESS OFFICE; THE SIGNIFICANCE OF THE VISIT<br />
To EAST TIMOR NEXT MONTH OF AN AUSTRALIAN PARLIAMENTARY<br />
DELEGATION TO OUR DECISION ON A VOTE IN THE UNITED<br />
NATIONS ON THE INCORPORATION OF EAST TIMOR. 66/ 10 </p>
<p>1O.<br />
SINCE I LEFT JAKARTA I HAVE RECEIVED FROM OUR<br />
EMBASSY THERE SOME POSITIVE INDICATIONS OF PROGRESS IN THESE<br />
AREAS ON THE PART OF THE INDONESIAN AUTHORITIES$ AT THE<br />
SAME TIME I STRESSED TO THE INDONESIAN AUTHORITIES THE IMPORTANCE<br />
WE ATTACH TO HAVING CONSTRUCTIVE RELATIONS WITH INDONESIA,<br />
BOTH BECAUSE OF ITS GEOGRAPHICAL PROXIMITY AND ITS ROLE<br />
IN THE REGION. IN LONDON, I HAD USEFUL TALKS WITH THE<br />
SECRETARY-GENERAL OF THE COMMONWEALTH SECRETARIAT#<br />
MR RAMPHAL, ABOUT THE FUTURE OF CHOGRM,<br />
THEN IN PARIS I CONVEYED TO THE FRENCH AUTHORITIES<br />
AT THE HIGHEST LEVELS OUR TOTAL OPPOSITION To FRENCH NUCLEAR<br />
TESTING IN THE SOUTH PACIFIC, AND REACHED AN UNDERSTANDING<br />
THAT THERE WOULD NOT BE FURTHER SHIPMENTS OF URANIUM FROM<br />
AUSTRALIA UNTIL AT LEAST OCTOBER 1984 SO AS TO PROVIDE A<br />
" tWINDOW FOR FURTHER DISCUSSIONS ON THIS ISSUE.<br />
ITOOK THE OPPORTUNITY DURING THIS JOURNEY TO<br />
EXPRESS AUSTRALIA'S SUPPORT FOR THE PROPOSAL FOR A<br />
SOUTH PACIFIC NUCLEAR FREE ZONE, AND I BELIEVE THAT THE<br />
RAISING OF THIS MATTER WILL ASSIST THE DISCUSSION ON THE PROPOSAL<br />
WHICH I ANTICIPATE WILL TAKE PLACE AT THE SOUTH PACIFIC FORUM<br />
IN AUGUST.<br />
I I I I </p>
<p>11.<br />
IN BOTH INDONESIA AND FRANCE, AS WELL AS THE<br />
UNITED STATES, I WAS ENCOURAGED BY THE INTEREST SHOWN AND<br />
SUPPORT EXPRESSED FOR WHAT WE ARE ATTEMPTING TO DO IN<br />
REGARD TO CAMBODIA. IN THE UNITED STATES I HAD PRELIMINARY DISCUSSIONS<br />
WITH THE UNITED STATES OFFICIALS ON A NUMBER OF DEFENCE-RELATED<br />
ISSUES, INCLUDING THE ANZUS REVIEW AND GREATER INVOLVEMENT<br />
IN DECISIONS RELATING TO JOINT INSTALLATIONS, AS WELL AS<br />
SCOPE FOR IMPROVED AUSTRALIAN ACCESS TO OFFSET AND TRANSFER<br />
OF TECHNOLOGY. I FOUND MUCH INTEREST AND SUPPORT FOR THE APPROACH<br />
THAT OUR GOVERNMENT IS TAKING IN OUR EFFORTS TO RESOLVE THE<br />
PROBLEMS OF AUSTRALIAN ECONOMY.<br />
IN TURN, I BELIEVE THAT THE PROJECTIONS AND INSIGHTS<br />
I HAVE RECEIVED ABOUT DEVELOPMENTS IN THE WORLD AND AMERICAN<br />
ECONOMIES, WILL ENABLE US TO IMPROVE OUR APPROACH TO THE<br />
SOLUTION OF OUR ECONOMIC PROBLEMS,<br />
As I SAID EARLIER, I TOOK EVERY APPROPRIATE OPPORTUNITY<br />
TO SPEAK PUBLICLY AND PRIVATELY ON MATTERS OF INTEREST AND<br />
CONCERN TO AUSTRALIA AS PART OF THE PACIFIC REGION, AND<br />
THEREFORE OF INTEREST AND CONCERN TO ALL OTHER NATION-MEMBERS<br />
OF THIS REGION. / 12 </p>
<p>-12-<br />
E sPE C IA LL Y IN WA SHINGO AND NEW YORK,<br />
ISTRESSED THE IMPORTANCE TO THE ECONOMIES OF THE NATIONS<br />
OF THE SOUTH PACIFIC OF A LIBERAL INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND<br />
PAYMENTS REGIME AND THE IMPORTANCE OF MAINTAINING<br />
REALISTIC LEVELS OF CONCESSIONAL AID TO THE DEVELOPING<br />
COUNTRIES OF THE REGION AND THE WORLD.<br />
IN MAKING THESE POINTS, AND ON THE OTHER ISSUES<br />
IRAISED OF CONCERN TO OUR REGION, IMUST EMPHASISE THAT<br />
IDID NOT PRESUME TO ACT IN ANY WAY AS SPOKESMAN FOR<br />
THE REGION, OR ON BEHALF OF ANY NATION EXCEPT AUSTRALIA.<br />
THAT IS NOT MY ROLE AND IT IS NOT AUSTRALIA'S VISION OF<br />
ITS OWN ROLE. WE ARE NOT IN THE BUSINESS OF ANY PRETENSIONS<br />
ABOUT LEADERSHIP IN THE REGION. WE ARE ABOUT GENUINE<br />
PARTNERSHIP ON THE BASIS OF EQUALITY.<br />
BUT, IF AS A GOOD NEIGHBOUR AND EQUAL PARTNER<br />
IN THE PACIFIC, MY WORK ON BEHALF OF AUSTRALIA SHOULD PROVE<br />
TO BE OF VALUE FOR OUR FRIENDS, NEIGHBOURS AND PARTNERS,<br />
ISHOULD RETURN HOME WELL CONTENT.<br />
i I </p>
<p>FINALLY, MR, CHAIRMAN, I COULD NOT CONCLUDE<br />
WITHOUT EXPRESSING THE APPRECIATION OF THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
GOVERNMENT TO THE GOVERNMENT OF THE UNITED STATES OF<br />
AMERICA WHICH IS, OF COURSE, THE PRINCIPAL SOURCE<br />
OF FUNDING FOR THE EAST-WEST CENTRE, IN THE PAST<br />
THE UNITED STATES GOVERNMENT HAS PAID AROUND<br />
PER CENT OF THE CENTRE'S EXPENDITURE AND I BELIEVE<br />
THIS IS AN INDICATION OF THE IMPORTANCE WHICH THIS<br />
AND PREVIOUS ADMINISTRATIONS, AND MEMBERS<br />
OF CONGRESS, HAVE ATTACHED TO THE CENTRE AS A MOST<br />
USEFUL WINDOW FOR AMERICA ON THE ASIAN/ PACIFIC WORLD',<br />
MY OWN GOVERNMENT'S PRIORITIES LIE BOTH IN<br />
MAINTAINING AUSTRALIA'S FUNDAMENTAL LINK ACROSS THE<br />
PACIFIC OCEAN WITH THE UNITED STATES AND IN<br />
STRENGTHENING OUR ROLE AS A PARTNER AND PARTICIPANT<br />
IN THE ASIAN/ PACIFIC REGION,<br />
BUT, AS I HAVE SAID, THESE MAJOR OBJECTIVES<br />
REPRESENT THE CLEAR DESIRES AND DETERMINATION OF THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE A COURSE NOW PURSUED CONTINUOUSLY<br />
AND CONSISTENTLY FOR FORTY YEARS, </p>
<p>-14-<br />
AUSTRALIA'S FUTURE LIES WITH THE COUNTRIES OF ASIA<br />
AND THE PACIFIC. IT IS A MATTER OF SATISFACTION TO US<br />
THAT THAT THE UNITED STATES IS COMMITTED TO MAINTAINING<br />
A HIGH LEVEL OF CONSTRUCTIVE INVOLVEMENT WITH THE<br />
ASIAN/ PACIFIC REGION AND IT IS IN THIS CONTEXT THAT WE<br />
BELIEVE THE EAST-WEST CENTRE HAS A SIGNIFICANT ROLE TO PLAY<br />
AS A FOCUS FOR CONTACT AND FRIENDSHIP AMONG PEOPLES<br />
THROUGHOUT THE PACIFIC BASIN.<br />
THERE IS, OF COURSE. ONE SIMPLE WORD WHICH<br />
EXPRESSES OUR ULTIMATE GOAL FOR THE NATIONS AND PEOPLES OF<br />
THIS REGION AND BEYOND. IT IS THE NAME OF THE OCEAN<br />
ITSELF THE PACIFIC. WE WILL BE SERVING OUR PEOPLE WELL IF<br />
THROUGH THE WORK OF THIS CENTRE, THROUGH THE BUILDING OF<br />
CO-OPERATION AMONG OUR GOVERNMENTS AND NATIONS, THROUGH LONG<br />
AND CLOSE ASSOCIATIONS LIKE ANZUS, THROUGH ORGANISATIONS<br />
LIKE THE SOUTH PACIFIC FORUM, AND EVEN PERHAPS, IN SOME<br />
SLIGHT MEASURE, THROUGH THE RESULTS OF MY OWN MISSION,<br />
AS THEY MAY EMERGE IN THE MONTHS AND YEARS TO COME WE WILL BE<br />
SERVING OUR PEOPLE WELL INDEED, IF WE CAN CONTRIBUTE TO MAKING<br />
THAT NOBLE NAME OF THE WORLD'S LARGEST OCEAN A REALITY, SO<br />
THAT THIS PACIFIC OCEAN STANDS FOR A PACIFIC WORLD<br />
A REGION AT PEACE, A WORLD AT PEACE. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
