<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3665</transcript-id>
    <title>AUSTRALIA POLICE</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/03/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003665.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
p A75 % 7/ A&amp;<br />
PRESS STATEM * ENT NO. 476<br />
27 March 1975*<br />
AUSTRALIA POLICE<br />
The Prime Minister announced today the first<br />
steps in the formatLion of a service to be known as the Australia<br />
Police. lHe notified the appointment of Mr Kep Enderby,<br />
as Minister of a new Department of Police ' and Customs.<br />
The new Department would be formed out of the Department of<br />
Customs and Excise, the Commonwealth Police and the Police Forces<br />
of the Australian Capital Territory and the Northern Territory.<br />
The Permanent Head of the new Department is Mr A. T. Carmody<br />
formerly head of the Department of Customs and Excise.<br />
Mvr Enderby will also retain his portfolio of<br />
Attorney-General. The amalgamation of federal law enforcement<br />
agencies is one of the objectives of the Government which<br />
Mr Whitlam announced in his policy speech in November 1972.<br />
This action has been taken after wide ranging<br />
discussions with those concerned. It represents a major step<br />
in integration of the law enforcement agencies; it will achieve<br />
more efficient operations generally and in particular it will<br />
enable a concerted effort to be made against white collar or<br />
corporate crime. At the same time the creation of the integrated<br />
Police service wil~ l provide the Australian Government with the<br />
opportunity to build into the new system proper and betteF<br />
safeguards for the rights of the individual. , k<br />
In its operations the Australia Police will have<br />
regard for the Government's policy to place emphasis on the<br />
prevention of crime and the protection of the rights of citizens.<br />
The Australia Police will operate initially<br />
under existing legislation but the drafting of an Australia<br />
Police Bill will begin immediately. This will provide for a<br />
common framework for the operation of ' all the components of<br />
the Australia Police, for specialised training and for the<br />
appointment of an independent tribunal to investigate complaints<br />
against the police. / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
The Bill will also lay down guidelines to<br />
members of the service to preserve and reinforce civil rights<br />
and liberties. It will provide that there will be no<br />
discrimination against any sector of the community and will<br />
facilitate public scrutiny of police operations. The Bill<br />
will reflect the Government's policy to develop a well trained<br />
and educated police service equal to any national police force<br />
in the world. The new Police Service will have increased<br />
capacity to deal with areas of federal law under new legislation<br />
being developed by the Government. It will involve an increase<br />
in responsibility for Commissioners of Police in the A. C. T.<br />
and Northern Territory. More effective liaison arrangements<br />
will also be developed between the Department of Police and<br />
Customs and the law enforcement sections of other Departments.<br />
CANBERRA. A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
