<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11340</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                 THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                 CEREMONIAL SITTING OF THE SUPREME COURT                 175TH ANNIVERSARY &amp;#150; NEW SOUTH WALES</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/05/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...................................................................................................</p>
<p>Chief Justice, Chief Justice of Australia, your Excellencies, your</p>
<p> Honours, Premier,</p>
<p>Mr Whitlam.</p>
<p>I have the honour and privilege today to participate in this ceremony</p>
<p> on behalf of the solicitors of New South Wales and to offer my congratulations</p>
<p> on behalf of the Law Society of New South Wales to this Court on obtaining</p>
<p> its 175th anniversary.</p>
<p>It is, of course, a time when I believe despite our reluctance as</p>
<p> Australians over the years to think over much about our history and,</p>
<p> as Mr Whitlam said, we have tended in the past to think of history</p>
<p> as belonging to other countries. I do believe that as we approach</p>
<p> the Centenary of the Federation of the Australian nation and as Australians</p>
<p> begin to ponder the fact that within a very short period of time there</p>
<p> will be no Australians left alive who were personally associated with</p>
<p> many of the seminal events which have given shape to the modern nation.</p>
<p> We are as Australians becoming increasingly interested in and preoccupied</p>
<p> with our history. We are finding new meaning to many of the institutions</p>
<p> that have been important to our society over the years. And no collective</p>
<p> view, no institution has been more important to the development of</p>
<p> the modern Australian society than, of course, the rule of law.</p>
<p>We have many debates in our community about the desirability of writing</p>
<p> a bill of rights into our Constitution. There is an ongoing debate</p>
<p> acquired on most occasions as to whether the best protection of liberty</p>
<p> is a robust common law or perhaps something that is more firmly rooted</p>
<p> in statute. And it is not my role today to prolong or to add further</p>
<p> dimension to that debate except to express the view that in all the</p>
<p> time I have been in public life I have held very strongly to the conviction</p>
<p> that there are three great bulwarks to a democratic society in its</p>
<p> best sense. You need a vigorous and robust parliamentary system, you</p>
<p> need a free press and you need an incorruptible judiciary. And the</p>
<p> courts of this nation of which the Supreme Court of New South Wales</p>
<p> is in many ways the exemplar, the courts of this nation through the</p>
<p> years have demonstrated constant integrity, a constant discipline</p>
<p> and constant incorruptibility. The willingness of courts to impose</p>
<p> upon themselves and particularly this court those disciplines, to</p>
<p> impose those disciplines on its members has been a constant reassurance</p>
<p> to successive generations of Australians.</p>
<p>Of course the court has changed. Of course the profession of which</p>
<p> I had the honour of practicing until I entered Federal Parliament</p>
<p> has changed. I am reminded of the more obvious changes, the far larger</p>
<p> number of women. When I did my first year at the Sydney University</p>
<p> Law School in 1957 something in the order of 12 or 15 in my year were</p>
<p> women. When my daughter commenced that same year 35 years later 52</p>
<p> per cent of her first year were women. The technological changes that</p>
<p> have overtaken the practice of solicitors in the last quarter of a</p>
<p> century would leave a person who had been out of practice for 25 years</p>
<p> which is my situation returning to that practice in many respects</p>
<p> bewildered. It would have changed in so many ways yet there is a continuity</p>
<p> and that continuity is that the practices of a solicitor is the practice</p>
<p> of public service. A solicitor has an obligation to serve clients,</p>
<p> a solicitor has an obligation to honour the traditions of the profession,</p>
<p> a solicitor has an obligation to honour the principles and the service</p>
<p> of the law. The law is a valuable bulwark against tyranny and a slide</p>
<p> into authoritarianism. As we have seen only too sadly in one or two</p>
<p> places recently the first signs of a drift to authoritarianism is</p>
<p> an apparent encroachment by the executive upon the absolute independence</p>
<p> and the absolute integrity of the courts of a nation.</p>
<p>Your Honour, it is a privilege to extend on behalf of the solicitors</p>
<p> of this State the members of the Law Society of New South Wales, our</p>
<p> sincere congratulations on the 175th anniversary of this</p>
<p> very distinguished court, this great bulwark of freedom in Australia.</p>
<p> Thank you.</p>
<p> [ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
