<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2162</transcript-id>
    <title>DRILLING ON THE BARRIER REEF</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/01/1970</release-date>
    <release-type>Correspondence</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002162.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS P. M. No 8/ 1970<br />
DRILLING ON THE BARRIER REEF<br />
This evening the Prime Minister, Mr John Gorton, sent the<br />
following reply to a telegram received from Ampol Exploration Ltd<br />
" THANK YOU FOR YOUR TELEGRAM OF 13 JANUARY RE DRILLING FOR<br />
OIL ON BARRIER REEF. I HOPE YOU WILL BE ABLE TO PERSUADE JAPEX<br />
TO AGREE WITH YOUR DECISION AND CONGRATULATE YOU ON YOUR<br />
INITIATIVE. IT IS MY HOPE THAT OTHER COMPANIES WHICH HOLD<br />
PROSPECTING LEASES WILL FOLLOW YOUR LEAD PENDING A COMPLETE<br />
INVESTIGATION AND REPORT. IN MY VIEW THE SLIGHTEST DANGER Is<br />
TOO MUCH DANGER.<br />
AS YOU KNOW THE COMMONWEALTH GOVERNMENT WAS BOUND<br />
TO CONFIRM THE OIL LEASES ISSUED BY THE STATE ON AND NEAR<br />
THE REEF AND IS VIRTUALLY UNABLE TO PREVENT DRILLING ON<br />
THESE LEASES IF THE STATE AGREES TO DRILLING. HOWEVER I<br />
AM PREPARED TO ASK C. S. ILR . 0. TO CHOOSE EXPERTS EITHER FROM<br />
WITHIN THAT ORGANISATION, OR OUTSIDE IT, EITHER FROM<br />
AUSTRALIA OR FROM OVERSEAS, TO INVESTIGATE AND REPORT<br />
PUBLICLY ON THE MATTER. SUCH EXPERTS WOULD BE THE<br />
COMMONWEALTH REPRESENTATIVES ON A JOINT COMMONWEALTH/<br />
STATE INVESTIGATION SHOULD THE STATE GOVERNMENT AGREE TO<br />
SUCH A JOINT BODY. I HAVE SO INFORMED THE QUEENSLAND<br />
PREMIER. YOUR OFFER OF 5, 000 IS APPRECIATED BUT I BELIEVE YOU<br />
WOULD AGREE THAT IT MIGHT BE BETTER IF AN INVESTIGATION WAS<br />
IN NO WAY FINANCED BY AN ORGANISATION CONNECTED WITH OIL.<br />
I DO NOT BELIEVE AN INVESTIGATION INTO THE POSSIBLE DANGERS<br />
OF DRILLINGON THE BARRIER REEF SHOULD BE MIXED UP WITH AN<br />
INVESTIGATION OF THE CROWN OF THORNS STARFISH. THIS PROBLEM<br />
HAS BEEN INVESTIGATED BY SCIENTISTS FROM THE QUEENSLAND<br />
UNIVERSITY AND THE QUEENSLAND DEPARTMENT OF PRIMARY<br />
INDUSIRI ES WHO INVESTIGATED THE PROBLEM AT GUAM IN CONJUNCTION<br />
WITH SCIENTISTS FROM USA. A FURTHER MEETING WAS HELD IN<br />
BRISBANE IN AUGUST LAST BETWEEN OFFICERS OF C. S. 1. R 0. AND THE<br />
COMMONWEALTH DEPARTMENT OF PRIMARY INDUSTRY AND<br />
QUEENSLAND REPRESENTATIVES.<br />
THE ACADEMY OF SCIENCE HAS ALSO FORMED A COMMITTEE<br />
TO REPORT TO ITS COUNCIL ON THE PROBLEM. SO INVESTIGATION OF<br />
THIS PROBLEM IN THE HOPE OF DISCOVERING EFFECTIVE CONTROL<br />
ME4SURES IS PROCEEDING."<br />
CANBERRA January 1970 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
