<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1678</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH AT OPENING OF CUSTOMS HOUSE, MELBOURNE</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/10/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001678_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>OPENING OF CUSTOMS HOUSE. 131, A<br />MELBOURNE 6th October, 1967<br />Speech by the Prime Minister, Mr. Harold Holt<br />Mr. Minister, Ministerial colleagues, representative of<br />the Opposition, representative of the State Premier and of the<br />Lord Mayor, other distinguished gentlemen all of whom I am glad to<br />see here with us today.<br />Indeed, as I look around I see not only many of my<br />Parliamentary colleagues and some of the former administrators<br />of this significant Department of State, but a good many of the<br />larger customers of the organisation perhaps customer is hardly<br />the word. Contributor would ' be more practical in our expression<br />of it, but in a sense of course we are all contributors through<br />the Commonwealth to this valuable, revenue collecting Department.<br />I am glad to say that its revenues are collected ratter less<br />painfully, at least to the victim, than some other form of action<br />that we have had to devise, and it has been the more popular on<br />that a'ccount. It is for me a pleasure to open a Commonwealth building which<br />is by the testimony of our own vision at the same time functional,<br />decorative and aesthetically satisfying, and which will itself<br />be an addition to the grace and dignity of this fine city of<br />Melbourne. I have opened quite a number of different buildings<br />since I took office but it so happens that this is the first<br />administrative building I have opened in the capacity of Prime<br />Minister. Most of the other Commonw~ ealth buildings have been<br />associated with an outreach of Commonwealth activity of one<br />kind or another the Murray I ' Cower Project, the Space Station<br />at Honeysuckle Creek, our Army Barracks at Townsville and the<br />Communications Centre at the North. West Cape.<br />I mention these by item because it helps to illustrate the<br />ramifications of Commonwealth administration in thes3 modern times.<br />But the Customs administration is of ancient lineage and provided<br />one of the earliest revenue levies in Australia long before there<br />was such an item as income tax.<br />The Victorian Customs came into existence in 1836 and the<br />record shows that tobacco and spirits were at that time running<br />rather contrary to the form one would have expected in these<br />matters. They were being smuggled into New South Wales and not from<br />that area and into Van Diemen's Land, also via the Port Phillip<br />district. An Officer of Customs was appointed at an annual<br />salary of œ 200 and a Tide Waiter at œ, 100. I saw this reference<br />in the notes supplied to me I though t there was a misprint for a<br />" tired waiter", but he would get just about that much in tips<br />in a reasonable quarter these times. In their first quarter of<br />operation they collected œ, 329. Two years later ther collections<br />were œ 12,000 a quarter, so -they must have been covering their<br />expenses and salaries at that point of time.<br />Today Customs and Excise revenues are running about ~ OM<br />a quarter so at least this is one direction in which the Government<br />has shown no lack of progress, ge.-ntlemen. I sometimes ponder<br />what would hap;,-en to our revenues for Commonwealth purposes, and<br />that includes of course State purposes, if people stopped drinking<br />spirituous liquor and gave up the smoking of cigarettes. 2/.</p>
<p>Rhatever the moralities of the matter mi;:' ht beg it is the<br />sort of prospect which haunts a Commonwealth Treasurer. There is<br />no sign however of any diminition in our expenditures in these<br />directions and so we can rate the Customs and Excise administration<br />as one of the largest revenue gatherers for the Commonwealth. I<br />think you get in, Senator, about 24% through this organisation of<br />the total revenue of the Commonwealth.<br />This is the 4th Customs House which has been established in<br />Melbourne in 1837 it was a weatherboard cabin; in 1839 the first<br />Customs House which could be fairly described as such was constructed,<br />and in 1876 the old Customs House opp-site, a very graceful,<br />historic and dignified building was established. While over the<br />years age may have withered them, Customs have not staled in the<br />variety of their exactions.<br />And so we come to the present building of which I have<br />spoken in such appreciative terms, and I ask you Senator to accept<br />and to convey to all associated with this, to you Mr. Carmody, the<br />congratulations of the Government for a fine building which is a<br />welcome addition to the Commonwealth range.<br />It's widely recognised throughout the community that the<br />Customs Department is a unit which operates in a very efficient<br />way. ie often read of spectacular finds by Custons officers I<br />think most members of the public get the message that there is an<br />efficient body of investigators at work. I'm told, although I<br />don't have time normally to enjoy these amenities myself, that<br />the television serial " Contrabandits" has given us some insight<br />into the exciting ways of Customs investigators, and I am<br />advised Mr. Carmody that you carry yourself a badge of this<br />particular organisation.<br />What is not so often recognised is that as well as<br />safeguarding the revenue, the Customs Department plays a large<br />part in the welfare of the community. And I am not thinking here<br />so much of that area of its activities which results in the<br />exclusion of certain forms of literature from the geneyal<br />consumption I think there we have a part to play with the States<br />as well but it does play a major part in preventing the entry<br />of noxious plants and animal products into Australia. We have<br />been fortunat ly spared the degradation of some of' the exotic<br />diseases and some of the weeds which would otherwise hamper<br />agriculture in this country. The entry of some of these could<br />prejudice the wellbeing of our primary industries or thce health<br />of our citizens.<br />Another important aspect somewhat in this field of the<br />Department's work is in prOventing the illegal introduction of<br />narcotic drugs. Here is one Department where LSD really means<br />hard cash, but not loosely in the sky with the diamonds I<br />think the popular song is running at the present time. It came<br />to my ears that in their desire to avoid making any souvenir<br />presentation to me which would involve the expenditure of<br />Commonwealth funds, the Minister and his Department had in mind<br />to present me with a confiscated opiuci pipe. Well, I felt that in<br />the current circumstances this micht be misunderstood. It wJould<br />certainly have leant itself to the cartoonist, I have no doubt, but<br />it might have been taken as some encouragement on my part in this<br />unfortunate direction.<br />But we do read much in the papers these days of the sad and<br />harmful effects of these drugs, and the Department makes an<br />important contribution in ensuring that these and other<br />potentially harmful drugs are kept in the hands of responsible<br />people.</p>
<p>3.<br />Despite all these activities the cost of collecting Customs<br />and Excise I've already mentione' that this amounts to 24 of<br />the Commonwealth's total revenue is surprisingly small. Over<br />the past 5 years, at least, the total cost of operating the<br />Department of Customs and Excise is well under 2% of total<br />Customs and Excise collections9 and this is a tribute to the<br />efficiency of the Departmcnt.<br />I can personally testify to that efficiency from an experience<br />of my own just on nearly 30 years ago when I was for six weeks<br />Acting Minister for Customs. When Robert Menzies, es he then was,<br />told me I was to take on t1ais task while he was looking around<br />for a permanent Minister, I must confess that my heart sank. I<br />had seen all these schedules and all this esoteric language<br />associated with the Customs administration, and I wondered how I<br />could handle this Depa: tment without exposing my ignorance in the<br />Parliament to my discredit. But I then found and I'm sure this<br />would have been the experience of those of my colleagues on this<br />platform who had their own period of administration of the<br />Department that this, as one of the oldest Commonwealth<br />Departments, had built up a body of experience and know,. lede in<br />relation to almost every conceivable situation which could occur to<br />harass the Ninister-in-Charge. They were able to give sound,<br />detailed advice which made the task of administration relatively<br />easy. I'm not implying, Senator, nor to you my colleague, the Leader<br />of the Government in the Senate who occupied this post for more<br />than 7 years, that you have had a cushy time, because when things<br />are slack here, there's always a certain amount of activity in the<br />Senate to keep you occupied if all else fails! But certainly one<br />can look to a most efficient body of men and women in this<br />Department to ease the task of the 1' inister. I think it is also<br />a tribute to the co-operation which the community gives, even if<br />sometimes a little reluctantly, to those who have laid upon them<br />the duty of collecting the nation's tax revenue from this<br />particular area.<br />It may interest some of you to know that taking all<br />Commonwealth tax revenues together, less than is spent on their<br />collection, which the businessmen in the audience, I am sure, would<br />regard as a remarkably low figure. Although the community generally<br />co-operates very well in the broad with our tax collectors this has<br />not always been the case as my researches into the records for<br />this occasion have led me to discover. The report of the Border<br />Tariff Abolition League of 1866 a Lea-ue formed to fight against<br />the Customs duties imposed on goods moving between New South Wales<br />and the rest of Australia contained this passage " Families<br />have been searched, children detained an. interrogated upon family<br />affairs; the vehicles and goods seized and then restored again.<br />It's no wonder that a spirit of resistance has sprung up amongst<br />the people of Moama and your Committee regrets to find that<br />children are being trained to tell falsehoods when questioned by<br />Customs officers".<br />~ ell those were the bad old days we have improved on that<br />since. But as the flow of goods and people into and out of<br />Australia increases, so does the work of the Customs Depaitment.<br />It is a product of this increased flow that has led to the<br />construction of this large and modern building. In it, as the<br />Minister has told you, all the administration of Customs in<br />Victoria will be housed the first time that this has been<br />possible for many years.<br />I mention one particular matter because we are becoming 4/.</p>
<p>increasingly tourist-minded these days I am speaking not so much<br />of our own journeys abroad but in relation to the potentialities<br />of revenue and stimulus to the economy from a growing tourist<br />industry. e have set up, recently a Tourist Commission, and we<br />look to increasingly successful promotion of our attractive<br />capacity abroad. But one of the problems of travellers is, as we<br />have discovered in our own journeying, the Customs officer. We<br />believe that our own Department is not only efficient in this<br />direction but has taken a realistic view of the needs of<br />travellers, particularly those who come to us from other countries.<br />And one way in which the Department has contributed to our welcome<br />to tourists has been to abolish declaration forms and by doing so,<br />we have in this arm of Government supported the efforts of those<br />who are concerned in encouraging tourists to visit us.<br />I am glad to be able to report another measure which I do<br />not think the Minister has yet given publicity so I have that<br />pleasure here today. It concerns passengers and crews of overseas<br />vessels travelling around the Australian coast. I am happy to<br />announce, and I assure Senator Cohen it has no connection with<br />impending events in relation to the Senate, that from 1st January<br />next there will be no Customs duties or sales taxes levied on<br />goods consumed between Australian ports. Miost of you have been on<br />board a vessel at some time or another and you know what a shock<br />to the system it is when you strike the Australian coast and find<br />that the prices of the commodities consumed on board these ships<br />receive the full weight of sales tax and excise levies. And this<br />step has been taken as a contribution to the attraction S'rttind4Ss<br />to Australia, by making their movement to this country the more<br />convenient and agreeable. It is also a recognition of the large<br />distances covered by overseas vessels as they move from one<br />Australian port to the other, and I am sure it will be welcomed<br />by all travellers.<br />Before I declare this building open, and unveil the<br />commemorative plaque, let me recall again a piece of history. In<br />1876 the old Customs house was completed. And the Melbourne<br />" Argus" of the day reported on this event as follows<br />" The people of Melbourne have for some months past become so<br />accustomed to the sight of unfinished public buildings, that when<br />one is at last completed it is looked upon almost as a new erection.<br />Those who were unaccustomed to the dark and winding labyrinths to<br />be found in the interior of the building frequently lost an hour<br />in wandering . bout the cold and dreary passages before they found<br />the room they had been searching. This has all changed now, and<br />where there were formerly cold damp passages and rooms of<br />uninviting interior there are now to be found bright and warmlooking<br />corridors end cosy rooms in which business can be<br />transacted with both pleasure and comfort".<br />I am sure you will agree that that kind of description can<br />very aptly be applied to the fin,. building in which we find<br />ourselves at this time. There have been no unreasonable delays<br />in the construction of this building, and this has been due to the<br />effective planning and provision of the Department of , orks and the<br />efficient operation of the builders. I am sure that with its<br />modern style, its air-conditionin throughout and attention<br />to the needs of efficiency in the circumstances of today, this<br />building will represent an advance just as great over the old<br />house as was that house in its turn over the first permanent<br />Customs house.<br />It is with great pleasure I now formally declare this<br />building open and unveil the plaque.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
