<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7242</transcript-id>
    <title>AUSTRALIAN EXPORT AWARDS SYDNEY - 14 NOVEMBER 1987</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/11/1987</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007242.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
AUSTRALIAN EXPORT AWARDS<br />
SYDNEY 14 NOVEMBER 1987<br />
Over the past four and a half years, one of the most<br />
important tasks for Government Ministers has been talking:<br />
talking about the serious challenge facing the Australian<br />
economy and talking about the concerted community effort<br />
required to confront that challenge.<br />
I make no apology for my and my Ministers' frequent<br />
speeches, press conferences, Parliamentary statements,<br />
doorstops and other comments about these great issues.-<br />
Clearly, community awareness of the dimensions of our<br />
difficulties is increasing. And that means the essential<br />
tasks of rebuilding the economy, and of reshaping attitudes<br />
towards greater competitiveness and productivity, are well<br />
underway. Export awards such as these have played an important part in<br />
this process. I congratulate the organisers of this award<br />
on twenty five years, valuable support of the Australian<br />
export drive.<br />
But obviously, only an optimist could believe the job is<br />
done. The current account deficit is still unsustainably high<br />
and our overseas debt continues to mount. We remain<br />
heavily' dependent for our export income on unprocessed<br />
raw materials for others to turn into useful products,<br />
and a few very simply transformed manufactures. V<br />
The balance of payments constraint dominates our<br />
economic choices and our exposure to the vagaries of<br />
international capital markets was all too clearly<br />
illustrated by the recent crash.<br />
There are however many rays of light. Tonight is an<br />
occasion to celebrate some of them.<br />
This occasion belongs not to Government, nor to Austrade,<br />
nor to the CAI, although we might all justly claim some<br />
reflected glory. -U<br />
' 34 </p>
<p>The night properly belongs to the 244 companies who applied<br />
for this year's awards and who have taken the initiative to<br />
compete in the international marketplace and whose goods and<br />
services are in some degree bringing home the bacon.<br />
we are going to hear tonight mostly of the award winners and<br />
the larger group of finalists from whom those winners were<br />
selected, but we should not forget that every applicant had<br />
a success to point to and a story to tell of opportunities<br />
taken and adversity overcome.<br />
The other day, Bill Ferris of Austrade referred to<br />
successful exporters as " national heroes". That status is<br />
frequently accorded, and rightly so, to our sportsmen and<br />
women who make it in international competition. The praise<br />
we give the Borders, the Fenechs and the Gardners is well<br />
merited. But how much more important to the future of<br />
Australia are the efforts of the national heroes whom we are<br />
congratulating tonight.<br />
Now, I don't pretend that these export heroes are acting out<br />
of some altruistic patriotism. The profits awaiting the<br />
successful exporter overseas are too great for that. For<br />
instance, the companies which applied for these awards have<br />
consistently over the past five years netted more than twice<br />
as much profit on each dollar of export sales as they did on<br />
domestic sales.<br />
The companies that applied are not, obviously, a random<br />
sample of Australian industry.<br />
For that reason it may be interesting to give you some of<br />
the statistics which emerge from the data submitted by the<br />
companies which applied for these awards.<br />
They provide a thumbnail sketch of what an Australian<br />
company needs to do to make inroads into the export market.<br />
First, practically all of them have deliberately chosen a<br />
strategy of exports. They are motivated to export, they<br />
have worked hard at it and, as a group, they attribute their<br />
success in exports primarily to the drive and persistence of<br />
particular executives or other employees.<br />
Successful export, it appears, is very much about people<br />
people who have the capacity to plan, the entrepreneurial<br />
skills and the drive to put those plans into practice, and<br />
the willingness to go to potential markets, find out what is<br />
needed in those. markets and come home and do it.<br />
It is therefore most appropriate that tonight, for the first<br />
time, there will be an award made for individual achievement<br />
in export. Successful exporting is a team sport, but every<br />
team has its stars and there is nothing like an emphasis<br />
on the all important human factor to bring home to everyone<br />
that their personal efforts do count, however humble or<br />
exalted their position in the hierarchy-. 0U( 0 </p>
<p>3<br />
Let me list a few more of the statistics about this group of<br />
companies. Innovation is alive and well:<br />
100 of them began export in 1983 or later.<br />
99 of them described their export activities over<br />
the past five years as being primarily the sale of<br />
new products to new markets.<br />
* Small enterpreneurs have a big role to play in exports<br />
Exactly one half of the applicants employed fifty tin)<br />
or fewer people. In the short term most of ' our<br />
exports will be generated by large corporations<br />
from our traditional export industries. But if we<br />
are to break away from heavy dependency on<br />
commodity exports it will be substantially through<br />
the entrepreneurial and innovative skills fostered<br />
in smaller enterprises.<br />
* Language skills must be more widely acquired:<br />
only 87 companies employed people fluent in at<br />
least one of Japanese, Chinese, Arabic or French.<br />
on the whole, we are fortunate that so many<br />
foreigners do us the courtesy of speaking to us in<br />
our own language.<br />
New Zealand and the Pacific, South East Asia, West<br />
Europe and North America are the most important markets,<br />
in terms of sales value, for most Australian exporters.<br />
However it seems there are few climes so exotic<br />
that some Australian goods and services are not<br />
available.<br />
Now, however, let me make some invidious comparisons between<br />
the 38 companies which made the finals of these awards and<br />
the larger group of applicants. This is not comparing<br />
success with failure; to pick up the Ferris metaphor again,<br />
it is comparing super-heroes with heroes.<br />
The finalists were more export dependent than the others:<br />
over 45 per cent of their sales went to export and 94 per<br />
cent of their net profit derived from those sales; the<br />
comparable figures for the non-finalists were 12 per cent of<br />
sales to export and 28 of their net profit.<br />
The finalists, on average, made over 15 personal visits to<br />
their overseas clients in 1986-87, compared with 9 by the<br />
others. A greater proportion of the finalists employed people who<br />
were fluent in one or more of Japanese, Chinese, Arabic or<br />
French. 0 01253 6 </p>
<p>Ladies and gentlemen,<br />
Max Weber gave us the maxim " politics is the art of the<br />
possible". He also gave us " Government is slow boring<br />
through hard boards".<br />
I hope that is not a description of the Ministerial talking<br />
which I mentioned at the outset.<br />
Its relevance is instead that it expresses well the hard<br />
work and patience required by the Government, by export<br />
companies, by trade unions and by the whole nation if we are<br />
to diversify and increase our exports to the degree<br />
required.<br />
That I am afraid is a long term task. We cannot expect<br />
immediate results.<br />
We can and should however congratulate those companies<br />
including tonight's finalists and award winners which have<br />
begun to take seriously the task of exporting. For that is<br />
the task on which our long-term prosperity as a nation so<br />
clearly depends. 0 4? 5z 3 -11 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
