<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5902</transcript-id>
    <title>Coalition Silver Anniversary Dinner, Brisbane</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/09/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005902.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>3 September 1982 </p>
<p>It is a wonderful evening and thank you for asking somebody  from south of the border to share a part of it with you.  It is a great occasion and 25 years in coalition is something  to remember. The people who have to run coalitions get good  of experience in making it work and making it work smoothly  and it is up to both sides to make that possible. But those  who have to run coalitions get a lot of advice sometimes from  people who have never run a coalition in their lives and if the  advice is good that is fair enough, but if the advice is bad  you have to reject it and sometimes people don't like having  their advice rejected, but they haven't had the experience  and they don't know what has to be done. For my part let me  say that I am the luckiest Prime Minister that ever was with  Doug Anthony as my lieutenant. We watch and learn from what  happens from north of the border but it is important for the  good Government of Queensland and the good Government of the  Commonwealth because without a coalition in Queensland the  socialists would be in town and without a coalition. in Canberra  the socialists would be in power and I do not think any of us  intend to let that happen.</p>
<p>I want apologise for Tamie, she wanted to be here very much  tonight but we still have one school-aged kid and there are  family obligations so she had to go back early this morning.  We have had a day or two at Burketown, and if I had known  you needed something to eat tonight I could easily have got  up a little earlier and caught more fish, I thought I only  had to feed myself for breakfast. They had a dinner with perhaps  a few more people than are here tonight, but they were not all  Queenslanders, they had come from Murray Bridge from Victoria,  they had come from New South Wales and -elsewhere. They had  a few speeches and somebody got up to make a speech and I do  not know why but he went back to 1941 and the Brisbane Line.  He said he did not like the business about giving away Australia  north of the Brisbane Line, he thought that what they ought to  plan to do is exactly what the Premier has been doing the last  few years give away the country to the south.</p>
<p>The Premier rang me up two or three weeks ago at the early  stages before the strike really became serious and he said:  " Malcolm, if I go into bat on this 38-hours, you are not going  to offer them all 36-hours or something like that are you?"  I said: " no Joh, don't worry about that." He said: " we have  knocked off compulsory unions for public servants", I said: " good",  he said: " well what are you going to do?" I said: " well, we never  had it". Then he said: " well, we are not going to collect union dues anymore, will you follow us in that?", I said: " we  stopped collecting union dues four years ago, I am glad you  are with us." He said: " Malcolm, you might think you are  ahead, but you wait a couple of days.” We all know what happened.</p>
<p>This Coalition won in 1957 with the biggest swing against  any government that has ever happened in the history of  Australia and that says something about the Labor Party that  was in before and the point has been made that the Labor  Party hasn't changed that much. They get a bit more extreme,  they go a bit further to the left and they certainly would destroy  what has been built up if they had an opportunity to do so.  A great deal has been achieved in Queensland but I do not  take a great deal of pleasure from the fact that while 98% of it  is entirely due to Queensland and Queensland policies there is  a growing proportion of it that is going to be entirely the  responsibility of New South Wales and Victoria and the policies  that the socialists in those two places are pursuing. You were  nearly getting about $ 1 billion a week out of Mr Cain with his  probate duty that he was going to put back on, and there are people caning  here all the timre because the y do not like the sortsi of policies  that are being pursued in those two states. That of course makes  it so much easier but nevertheless, what has been done has been  remarkable.</p>
<p>We do need to take note of the fact that the new Victorian Government is the most ideological committed government in the whole  history of Australia. He might go about it a bit more skilfully  as Mr Whitlam did, not making quite as much noise in the  way he sought to undermine our arrangements with the United  States and our defence treaties, the way Mr Cain is seeking to  apply the ideology of the socialist left in my own state is  something which gives us all a good deal of concern. There are  things that happen in the Labor Party which we often don’t bother  to point out. In their recent conferences they committed  themselves clearly and firmly to turning Australia into a  republic and in their last conference they committed themselves  to tearing up the Australian Flag and tearing up the Australian  constitution. Why shouldn't we point these things out more often  than we do?</p>
<p>There are some odd things about the Labor Party also, there has  been a lot written about Mr Costigan over the last few days.  People seem to have forgotten that Mr Costigan was originally  appointed to inquire into a union, the Painters and Dockers  Union, and I thought I might just read out a few things about  this Union because it has some peculiar characteristics and  relationships. In Victoria the Union is under the control  of hardened criminals the Royal Commissioner says. There has been  some 15 murders that took place between 1970 and 1979.. The two  worst years were 1971 where three murders took place, and 1979  when four took place. Federal Secretary Gordon told the Sweeney  Royal Commission: " we catch and kill our own". That apparently  is exactlywhat the union does. Their answer to any interference  into their activities is not to use the processes of the law  but rather, threats, violence and intimidation. In this way the  Royal Commissioner says: " the painters and dockers have assumed  for themselves a position outside the law and have maintained  that " position by violence</p>
<p>If there was anyone or any organisation associated with the  National Party or the Liberal Party that had that record I  haven't the slightest doubt that we would be moving to  disaffiliate them, get rid of them, kick them out so fast it  would be nobody's business. But what does Senator Georges do?  He just says they are misunderstood. In Victoria of course, and  in other states they are affiliated with the Labor Party, they  send their representatives along to the policy making body  of the Party and they are some of the people who control the  Labor politicians. It is going to be interesting to see if  Mr Hayden or Mr Cain or any of the others try and clean up  their own business.</p>
<p>Victoria is also becoming a refuge for tired, worn out Labor  politicians. Joh, you seemed to indicate a bit of sympathy  for Mr Casey up here, I hope you don't get too sympathetic  for him. Mr Cain has given Mr Dunstan a job, I am told he is  going to give Mr Grassby a job, if you want to get rid of  S Mr Casey he would probably give him a job too, and-when  Mr Wran is kicked out of New South Wales I suppose he will  give him a job and there is no way that New South Welshmen  would buy him again, after the way he has wrecked the state.</p>
<p>We are going to try and get rid of Mr Cain in Victoria in the  next election but our own Opposition there has to work vigorously  and hard. There is one fallacy that Parties sometimes have. If  you have been in for a'long time, give the poor Opposition  a go for three years and brighten ourselves up. We have learnt  before that three years can be a long time and an enormous  amount of damage can be done and that has been demonstrated  again in Victoria. If you are having any doubts about the directions  you are pursuing just visit Sydney or Melbourne a little more often  and that is going to be just as good as visiting overseas and  then you will know that Queensland is the best place in the world.  The sense of direction that everyone seems to have in this state  Sis refreshing and whether it is Burketown, Brisbane or Townsville,  the sense of direction and purpose, the sense of believing in  free enterprise, because it is a way of life, is something that is  good to see.</p>
<p>Joh and Llew I would like to congratulate you both on the first  years. There is another 25 year dinner in Lismore in a  few weeks time. I do not know if any of you have been invited  to that, but if you haven't been invited, it is Doug Anthony's  years in Parliament and he has asked me to go along,. so I ask  all of you to come along as well.</p>
<p>Thank you for asking me to be a part of this evening. It is a  memorable time in the history of Queensland and the history of a  great State. The achievements that you have worked hard for over  the years r1OW are evident, it can be seen on all sides, and the  State is going from strength to strength. On this occasion I  am am prepared to say that it is totally the result of State  policies, when we get around to a federal election, I will be  claiming some part of that responsibility from our own policies.  At the moment it is all yours, and thank you for allowing me to  be a part of it.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
