<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8498</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON. P.J. KEATING MP DECLARATION OF INTERESTS</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/04/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008498.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON. P. J. KEATING, MP<br />
DECLARATION OF INTERESTS<br />
FollowIng the Opposi~ tion's preoccupation with declaration -s<br />
of interest I have today asked the Government Leader in the<br />
Senate to seek leave to reintroduce a resolution providing<br />
for the registration and declaration of Senators' interests.<br />
In doing so, I challenge the Leader of the Opposition to<br />
instruct his party in the Senate to support the passage of<br />
the resolution.<br />
The Government has sought to have the resolution passed on<br />
three previous occasions in 1983, 1986 and 1987. on each<br />
occasion this reform was blocked by the Coalition.<br />
If Dr Hewson fails to instruct his party to accept the<br />
resolution in the Senate it will prove his protestations<br />
about propriety in public office to be without substance.<br />
my advice is that the earliest opportunity for the<br />
Government to reintroduce the resolution would be Monday,<br />
May 4.<br />
I attach a copy of the resolution as put in 1987.<br />
CANBERRA April 30, 1992 ntj, j-L 1 : 44 uico r U I I </p>
<p>SENATE JOIRA ~ 7Mrh18<br />
No: 169 Page: 1680<br />
REGISTRATION AND DECLARATION OF SENATORS' INTERESTSPROPOSED<br />
RESOLUTION<br />
The Manager of Government Business<br />
( Senator Evans) at the request of the Leader<br />
of the Government ( Senator Buttoni) and<br />
pursuant to notlce, * moved-<br />
That the -Senate adopt the following<br />
resolution relating to the registration and<br />
declaration of Senators' interests, such<br />
resolution to continue in force unless amended<br />
or repealed by the -Senate in this or a<br />
subsequent Parliament:<br />
1 Declaration of Senators' interests<br />
That, within 28 days of making and<br />
subscribing an ' oath or affirmation as a<br />
Senator, each Senator shall provide to the<br />
Registrar of Senators' Interests a statement ofthe<br />
Senator's registrable interests; and<br />
the registrable interests of. which the<br />
Senator is aware of the Senators' spouse,-<br />
and ( ii) of. any children* who are wholly or<br />
Mainly dependent On the Senator for support,<br />
in accordance with the resolution adopted by<br />
the Senate and in a form'determined by the<br />
Committee of Senators' Interests from time to<br />
time, and shall also notify any alteration of*<br />
those interests to the Registrar within 28 days<br />
of that alteration occurring.<br />
Any Senator whoknowingly<br />
fails to provide a statement of<br />
registrable interests to the Registrar of<br />
Senators' Interests by the due date;<br />
knowingly fails to notify any alteration of<br />
those Interests to the Registrar of Senators'<br />
Interests within 28 days of the change<br />
occurring; or<br />
knowingly provides false or misleading<br />
information to the Registrar of Senators'<br />
Interests, shall be guilty of a serious contempt of the<br />
Senate and shall be dealt with by the Senate<br />
accordingly. 2 Registrable interests<br />
That the statement of a Senators registrable<br />
interests to be provided by a Senator shall<br />
include the registrable interests of which the<br />
Senator is aware of the Senator's spouse;<br />
and of any children who are wholly or<br />
mainly dependent on the Senator for support,<br />
and shall cover the following matters:<br />
shareholdings in public and private<br />
companies ( including holding companies)<br />
indicating the name of the company or com panies; m t an no i e<br />
c( ii) family and business tut n oie<br />
* cnPartiesin which a beneficial interest is held,<br />
indicating the name of-the trust, the nature of<br />
its operation and beneficial interest, and<br />
in which the Senator, the Senator's<br />
spouse, or A child who is wholly or mainly<br />
dependent on the Senator for support, is -a<br />
trustee ( but not including a trustee of an<br />
estate where no beneficial interest is held by<br />
the Sen~ ator, the Senator's spouse or<br />
dependent children), indicating the name of<br />
the trust, the nature of its operation and the<br />
beneficiary of the trust;<br />
( iii) real estate, including the location ( suburb<br />
or area only) and the purpose for which it is<br />
owned; ( iv) registered directorships of companies;<br />
partnershiips, indicating the nature of the<br />
interests and the activities of the partnership,,<br />
( vi) liabilities, indicating the nature of the<br />
liability and the creditor concerned,<br />
( vii) the nature of any bonds, debentures and<br />
like investments;<br />
( viii) saving or investment accounts,<br />
indicating their nature and the name of the<br />
bank or other institutions concerned;<br />
( ix) the nature of any other assets ( excluding*<br />
household and personal effects) each valued at<br />
over $ 5,000;<br />
Wx the nature of any other substantial<br />
sources of incomie;<br />
( xi) gifts valued at more than $ 250 received<br />
fromn official sources, . or at more than $ 100<br />
where received from other than official<br />
. sources, provided that a gift received thy a<br />
Senator, the Senator's'spouse or dependent<br />
children,-from family members or personal<br />
friends in a purely personal capacity need not<br />
be registered unless the Senator judges that<br />
an appearance of conflict of interest may be<br />
seen to exist;<br />
( xii) any sponsored travel or hospitality<br />
received; ( xiii) membership of any Organisation; and<br />
( xiv) any other interests where a conflict of<br />
interest with a Senator's public duties could<br />
foreseeably arise or be seen to arise.<br />
3 Register and Registrar of Senators' Interests<br />
Thatat the commencement of each Parliament,<br />
and at other times as necessary, the President<br />
17 March 1987 </p>
<p>17 March 1987<br />
shall appoint ' an officer of the Department of<br />
the Senate as the Registrar of Senatori'<br />
Interests and that -offcer shall also be<br />
Secretary of the Committee of Senators'<br />
Interests; Pb) the Registrar of Senators' Interests sha<br />
in accordance with procedures determined by<br />
the Committee of Senators' Interests,<br />
maintain ak Register of Senators' Interests in a<br />
form to be determined by that Committee<br />
from time to time;<br />
. as soon as possible after ' the<br />
commencement of each Parliament, the<br />
Chairman of the Committee of Senators'<br />
Interests shall table in the Sonate a copy of<br />
the completed Register of Senators' Interests<br />
and shall also table from time to time as<br />
required any notification by a Senator of<br />
alteration of those interests; and<br />
the Register of Senators iterests shall be<br />
available for inspection by any person under<br />
conditions to be laid down by the Committee<br />
of Stenatoru Interests from time to timne.<br />
4 Declaration of interest in debate and other<br />
proceedings That, notwithstanding the lodgment by a<br />
Senator of a statement of the Senatorts<br />
registrable interests and the registrable<br />
interests of which the Senator is aware of<br />
the Senator's spouse; and of any children<br />
who are wholly or mainly dependent on . the<br />
Senator for support, and the incorpor-ation of<br />
that statement in a Register of Senators'<br />
Interests, a Senator shall declare any relevant<br />
interestat the beginning of his or her speech if the<br />
Senator should participate in debate in the<br />
Senate, Committee of the whole Senate, or ' a<br />
Committee of the Senate ( or of the Stnate and<br />
the House), and*<br />
00i as soon as practicable after a Division is<br />
called for in the Senate, Committee of the<br />
whole Senate, or a Committee of the Senate<br />
( or of the Senate and the House) if the<br />
Senator proposes to vote in that Division, and<br />
the declaration shall be recorded and indexed<br />
in the Journals of the Senate or inutes of<br />
Pro~ eedings ( as applicable) and in any<br />
Hansard report of those proceedings or that<br />
Division: Provided that it shall not be necessary for a<br />
Senator to declare an interest when directing<br />
a question seeking information in accrdance<br />
with Standing Order 98 or 98A.<br />
Debate ensued.<br />
Senator Mackin, by leave, moved-That the<br />
Senate resolve itself into Committee of the<br />
Whole for the consideration of the motion.<br />
question put and passed.<br />
The Senate, ' accordingly, resolved itself Into Committee for the consideration of. the<br />
motion. In the Committee<br />
Motion, by leave, taken as a whole and<br />
debated. Senator Vigor ' moved an amendment, viz:*<br />
Leave out all words after " Parliament" ( first<br />
occurring), insert:<br />
() That a Senator, before speaking in any<br />
debate in the Senate or Committee -of the.<br />
Whole or participating in any, proceedings of a<br />
Committee appointed by the Senate or by both<br />
Houses of the Parliament, and before voting<br />
in. any Division in the Senate, Committee of<br />
the Whole or such a Committee, declare any<br />
interest of the Senator, or of any person<br />
associated with the Senator, of which the<br />
Senator is aware, which may be relevant to<br />
that debate or Division or those proceedings.<br />
That a declaration under paragraph ( 1 be<br />
made orally to the Senate, Committee of the<br />
Whole or such Committee, or by writing<br />
delivered to the Clerk of the Senate, where the<br />
declaration relates to the Senate or a<br />
Committee or the Whole, or to the secretary of<br />
the Committee, where it relates to such a<br />
committee, and reported to the Senate,<br />
Committee of the Whale or Committee.'<br />
That a declaration under paragraph. be<br />
recorded in the Journals of the Senate and<br />
Hansard where the declaration is made in the<br />
Senate or Committee of the Whole, and in<br />
Minutes * of Proceedings where the declaration<br />
is made in a committee.<br />
That,* fo r the purposes of paragraph<br />
an interest of a Senator shall be taken to be<br />
relevant to a debate or Division or to<br />
proceedings if the interest is such that the<br />
interest may influence the conduct of the<br />
Senator in the debate, Division or proceedings..<br />
That, for the purposes of paragraph a<br />
person shall be taken to be associated with a<br />
Senator if an association between the person<br />
and the Senator is such that the Senator may<br />
have regard to an interest of that person in<br />
determining the Senator's conduct as a<br />
Senator. That the Senate will regard as guilty of a<br />
serious contempt any Senator who knowingly<br />
fails to comply with this resolution.".<br />
And it being 10.30 The Chairman of<br />
Committees ( Senator Hamer), under Sessional<br />
Order, put the Question-That he do leave the<br />
Chair and report to the enate.<br />
Question put and passed.<br />
ILL.<br />
SENATE JOURNALS n P I 1 11 U </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
