<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7353</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/07/1988</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007353.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
. AU ST R ALIA.<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA 11 JULY 1988<br />
on the advice of the Australian Science and Technology Council<br />
( ASTEC) I am today announcing the amalgamation of ASTEC with its<br />
standing committee, the Technological Change Committee ( TCC).<br />
This integration will ensure that not only the benefits of new<br />
technology, but also its effects on those immediately concerned<br />
and on the wider Australian community, will be fundamental<br />
elements for consideration by ASTEC in all aspects of its work<br />
program. Established at the Government's request in 1980, the TCC has been<br />
responsible for maintaining a continuing review of processes and<br />
trends in technological change and evaluating and reporting on<br />
their social and economic effects. While located with ASTEC it<br />
has operated with its own secretariat and work program.<br />
In recent years there has been growing recognition of the need to<br />
achieve a balance between the advice provided by ASTEC, which has<br />
generally promoted the use of new technology where it can be<br />
shown to offer economic advantages, and that of the TCC, which<br />
has been more concerned with the social consequences of<br />
technological change. It is important that a balance in these<br />
perspectives be reflected when views and recommendations are<br />
presented to the Government. The Council and TCC members have<br />
agreed that this can best be done by combining the functions and<br />
responsibilities of the two bodies. An added benefit of such a<br />
move will be a streamlining of procedures for the preparation and<br />
approval of reports.<br />
In future people with credentials in technology assessment,<br />
either those who have served on the TCC or others who have gained<br />
such experience elsewhere will be appointed to the Council.<br />
ASTEC membership will encompass the expertise required to ensure<br />
full consideration of the societal impacts of new technologies in<br />
all its undertakings.<br />
292 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
