<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7633</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER MEMORIAL CEREMONY FOR THOSE KILLED IN CHINA CANBERRA - 9 JUNE 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/06/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007633.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
CHECKAGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
MEMORIAL CEREMONY FOR THOSE KILLED IN CHINA<br />
CANBERRA 9 JUNE 1989<br />
ror more than a month now, the eyes of the world have been<br />
on China.<br />
S We witnessed a massive rallying of people in Beijing and<br />
Shanghai and heard the powerful expression of their will in<br />
the cause of democratic reform.<br />
We were inspired by the idealism and courage of youth the<br />
~ ea ceful determination of students to create a better<br />
uture, and the support that rallied around their cause from<br />
throughout Chinese society.<br />
our sp irits were buoyed by the optimism of their vision and,<br />
no matter how far we were from the events in Tian'anmen<br />
Square, our hearts were with them.<br />
Then last weekend, our optimism was shattered as we watched<br />
in horror the unyielding forces of repression brutally<br />
killing the vision of youth.<br />
U narmed young men and women were sprayed with bullets and<br />
crushed by tanks. Innocent people were shot and beaten in<br />
the streets and in their homes.<br />
incredibly despite the horror and the risks, we have<br />
witnessed acts of indescribable bravery on our television<br />
screens: A lone man standing in front of a row of tanks, the<br />
strength of his will stalling the might of armour as it<br />
rolled down a Beijing street.<br />
Young people co nfronting lines of armed troops, not in<br />
anger, but in disbelief that an army could unleash force<br />
on its own people with such cruelty.<br />
Thousands have been killed and injured, victims of a<br />
leadership that seems determined to hang on to the reins of<br />
power at any cost -at awful human cost. </p>
<p>a~ n r r czi c Vuri r4 X TCL-V 1 00Z -TVZ: VZ V 1VV~ O 1D91O NQ. VoD r. Vz<br />
2.<br />
We meet here to mourn this tragedy and to share the grief of<br />
those who have lost members of their families, their loved<br />
ones and their friends, and to express our profound symathy<br />
to the Chinese-Australian community that has expressed ts<br />
outrage at the massacre in Beijing.<br />
We meet here to show our support for the Chinese people and<br />
to reaffirm our commitment to the ideals of democracy and<br />
freedom of expression that they have so eloquently espoused.<br />
And we meet here reflecting on the very future of China,<br />
which in recent years had built up so much goodwill in the<br />
international community of nations, which had already come<br />
to play such a welcome and constructive role in our region,<br />
and which promised to do so much more.<br />
It is my sincere hope and, indeed, my resolute conviction,<br />
that the values and aspirations of those who have been so<br />
brutally repressed over the past week will eventually<br />
triumph, that the death and suffering will not have been in<br />
vain$ that the path of reform and mode rnisation will be<br />
renewed.<br />
We all pray that moderation will eventually prevail, so that<br />
a new and better China can rise from this carnage, a China<br />
that befits the courage and determination of its people.<br />
I call on the Chinese Government to withdraw its troops from<br />
deployment against unarmed civilians, and to respect the<br />
will of its people.<br />
To crush the spirit and body of youth is to crush the very<br />
future of China itself.<br />
0 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
