<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9923</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP ELECTION, MARCH 2</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/01/1996</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009923.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
30/ 01 12: 11 PRIME MINISTER<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MVP<br />
ELECTION, MARCH 2<br />
Today I called upon the Governor-General and recommended that the House<br />
of Representatives be dissolved, with a view to holding an Election for the<br />
House and half the Senate on March 2, and he has accepted my<br />
recommendation. The proper thing has been done: the Parliament has run its full term and the<br />
Australian people will make their decision in full knowledge of the<br />
Govemnment' 4 record and the directions we have set for the country. They<br />
will know exactly where we stand and where we intend to go.<br />
This will be an Election about leadership. We seek a further mandate for the<br />
Government that has given Australia an increasingly creative role in the<br />
world; that has created an outward looking, diverse, competitive and<br />
successful trading economy; and provided strong economic growth and<br />
record growth in employment.<br />
It will be an Election about both domestic an d foreign policies, because the<br />
two cannot be separated.-<br />
At stake is Australia's continuing emergence as a successful partner and<br />
player in Asia and the Pacific. Therefore, the continued growth of the<br />
Australian economy, the prosperity of Australian society, and the jobs and<br />
opportunities of Australians in the next century are at stake.<br />
Three years ago we said we would re-start economic growth and<br />
employment. ' And we have. Australia has recorded an unprecedented 17<br />
quarters of continuous growth and 720,000 new jobs have been created.<br />
This will be an Election to decide whether the authors of these policies will<br />
continue to guide Australia's progress.<br />
For all the success of the last three years, much remains to be done if we are<br />
to continue to reduce unemployment and the Government will be seeking a<br />
mandate to continue the policies and programs which are working for us now.<br />
30Vi08 196 162 : 12 73 2923 PM PRESS OFFICEZ~ 001 </p>
<p>30/ 01 ' 96 12: 12 ' 061 6 273 2923 P RS FIEI 0<br />
2<br />
The future of Australia's universal health care will be at stake in this Election.<br />
So will the Accord and our flexible and fair industrial relations system which is<br />
delivering high labour productivity, low inflation and the lowest incidence of<br />
strikes in 55 years.<br />
The Election will also determine the prospects for our having an Australian as<br />
our head of state Australians will have to decide between a Labor<br />
government which will guarantee they have a vote on this issue, and a<br />
Coalition which is divided on it and led by a man who is passionately opposed<br />
to an Australian republic.<br />
Also at stake will be the environment. The Coalition's appalling record gives<br />
every reason to believe that Labor's massive investment in repairing and<br />
conserving our environment is at risk.<br />
These and many other differences add up to a profound philosophical gulf<br />
between the Government and the Coalition about what kind of society<br />
Australia should be, and what kind of nation we can be.<br />
Whatever the present tactics of the Coalition, the fact remains that most of Mr<br />
Howard's front bench were, just three years ago, avid supporters of the most<br />
radically right wing program ever put to an Australian electorate and none<br />
was more avid than Mr Howard.<br />
Australian voters have a right to know in detail the choice they face the<br />
policies and the people responsible for them.<br />
I am therefore asking Mr Howard to engage in 2 head to head public debates<br />
with me on ABC Television. In addition I will be asking the Coalition to join in<br />
further public debates on more specific policy issues. I am seeking debates<br />
between me and my three most senior ministers the Deputy Prime Minister<br />
Mr Beazley, the Treasurer Mr Willis and the Foreign Minister Senator Evans<br />
and Mr Howard and those who would fill these portfolios in a Coalition<br />
government, namely Mr Fischer, Mr Costello and Mr Downer.<br />
Labors platform will be constructed on a proven record of achievement. We<br />
have detailed policies to address the continuing needs of Australia an<br />
Australians. We have a strong team of leaders. And we have above all a<br />
desire to continue the remarkable progress and stability which is Australia's<br />
story as we approach the 21 st century.<br />
CANBERRA<br />
27 January 1996 -a<br />
PX PRESS OFFICEZ002 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
