<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4713</transcript-id>
    <title>AIMM CONFERENCE, CANBERRA</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/05/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004713.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
ble / 0<br />
jU SRA LIA&amp;<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 16 MAY 1978<br />
A. I. M. M. CONFERENCE, CANBERRA<br />
I was delighted to be invited to be patron of this joint<br />
conference, but the challenging task you have set yourselves,<br />
and your speakers' depth of expertise, deny anyone, even the<br />
patron, the opportunity to be patronising.<br />
Australia's history has been inextricably linked with the<br />
fortunes of our great mining industry. That link will remain.<br />
Just as the gold rushes of the last century, and the discoveries<br />
at Kalgoorlie arnd Broken Hill changed the lives oE generations,<br />
so the more recent development activity in iron ore, bauxite,<br />
nickel, coal and uranium are having a significant impact on the<br />
lives of Australians today.<br />
The minerals industry has contributed to Australia's jobs and<br />
prosperity. Mining is not free of problems, but so long as<br />
safeguards are strong and appropriate the net benefits the mining<br />
industry brings Australia will continue to be enormous.<br />
We rely on our mining industry to find, prove, develop and<br />
sell our minerals profitably, and my Government is committed<br />
to maintaining a healthy mining industry.<br />
In the past year there have been positive signs of a resurgence<br />
in exploration and development. The North-West Shelf ventures<br />
are spending $ 50 million on a feasibility study to work out the<br />
extent of future investment in that project; exploration expenditure<br />
for minerals other than petroleum increased by 34% in 1976-77<br />
to $ 134 million; petroleum exploration increased dramatically last<br />
year almost doubling to $ 94 million this year it is projected<br />
to reach $ 125 million.<br />
Much of this new exploration is occurring in Western Australia,<br />
a State lucky enough to have a rare diamond amongst its mineral.<br />
wealth. It's called Charlie Court, it's the only one of its<br />
type in the world, and that's our good fortune.<br />
Other major developments, such as the proposal to establish a<br />
large-scale aluminium smelter at Gladstone, have been announced.<br />
To a significant degree, these developments have been a produce<br />
of Government policies. We have created a healthier environment<br />
for investment in the mining industry. An environment in which,<br />
./ 2 </p>
<p>investors both here and overseas will find it profitable to<br />
invest in Australia.<br />
We have rich and abundant mineral resources. Their development<br />
depends on stability of costs and investment conditions in<br />
Australia and the availability of profitable markets overseas.<br />
The Government can influence costs and therefore the investment<br />
arithmetic by taking effective action to control inflation so<br />
that business can plan with confidence.<br />
We have succeeded and we shall keep going. We have improved<br />
the climate of industrial relations another element of<br />
uncertainty in investment plans.<br />
We believe economic growth is best fostered by private enterprise<br />
and we have acted to curb the massive increases in public spending<br />
which occurred between 1973-1975. A stable policy environment,<br />
so necessary to encourage investment, has been re-instated.<br />
our policies have met with considerable success.. In the past<br />
two years inflation has been halved. The O. E. C. D. acknowledged<br />
this achievement in its latest review. Even blind Freddy and<br />
his dog must now concede this to be true.<br />
The Consumer Price Index increased by only 1.3% in the March<br />
quarter the smallest March quarter increase since 1972.<br />
This compares favourably with the U. S. Wholesale Price Index,<br />
which increased 1.3% last month alone.<br />
our anti-inflation policy has enabled official and private<br />
sector interest rates to move down, with every prospect of<br />
falling further as inflation falls. Lower inflation strengthens<br />
our currency and international competitive position.-both of<br />
vital concern to the overseas investor. Recent figures showing<br />
strong private capital inflow $ 676 million in the last two<br />
months are in line with these developments.<br />
We welcome foreign investment in Australia. The Foreign<br />
Investment Guidelines are administered with flexibility. Each<br />
proposal is considered on its merits. The guidelines are<br />
being monitored. They were revised in April 1976, and certain<br />
aspects of the guidelines, as well as the Reserve Bank's<br />
administrative controls, are again being reviewed to see if thley<br />
in any way unreasonably impede investment.<br />
our aim is to preserve, wherever possible, 50% Australian<br />
equity in mining projects. But I want to make the point clear<br />
if it is demonstrated that this objective cannot be reasonably<br />
achieved, projects will not be held up.<br />
The mining industry has benefitted from a wide range of tax<br />
and duty concessions. Investment allowances, which allow for a<br />
fast tax write-off of capital spending ara available; exploration<br />
incentives in the mining industry have been restored, depreciation<br />
allowances have been extended; and the coal export levy introduced<br />
by the previous government is being phased out. / 3 </p>
<p>A realistic energy pricing policy has been introduced. This<br />
will allow petroleum products to be sold at world parity prices.<br />
Federal and State administrative and licensing arrangements have<br />
been clarified, and relevant Federal and State Ministers now<br />
meet regularly at the Australian Minerals and Energy Council.<br />
The Government has also simplified procedures applying to<br />
mineral export controls. our anti-inflation policies and<br />
incentives for minerals exploration and development are proving<br />
effective. They will continue.<br />
Although I know that not all the mining industry's problems<br />
have been solved, I am confident that Australia is in the<br />
forefront of those few countries in the world where overseas<br />
businessmen can invest their capital and use their technology<br />
and management skills, with profit and confidence.<br />
We are particularly keen to see greater processing of Australian<br />
raw materials in Australia. For example, while Australia is<br />
the major alumina exporter we produce only 2% of the world's<br />
aluminium. The announcement of the new Gladstone development is accordingly<br />
most welcome.<br />
There are sound economic reasons why more energy-intensive<br />
mineral processing should be carried out in Australia, close<br />
to ample sources of relatively cheap energy.<br />
I should say that we are at present consulting with the States<br />
on the steps that we can take to influence the amount of raw<br />
materials processing conducted in Australia.<br />
Australia's ability to supply increasing quantities of energy<br />
and of other vital minerals will bring added rposperity both to<br />
Australia and to our trading partners. But for this promise<br />
of prosperity to be fully realised, there is a need for growth<br />
in the world economy and an expansion in world markets.<br />
Government leaders everywhere are currently concerned about<br />
the slow rate of world economic expansion. It has been<br />
estimated that 5% annual growth rate in total world output<br />
is needed if unemployment is to fall internationally.<br />
Although there has been a tentative recovery in the economies<br />
of the major western countries, world growth has certainly not<br />
reached this rate, and will in all probability fall short of<br />
it in 1978.<br />
Expansion-in world trade last year was also sluggish, and on<br />
present indications the same will be true this year. The world<br />
is suffering from under-utilization of its resources. Factories,<br />
farms and mines working at less than capacity, and of course the<br />
greatest waste of resources of all, the unemployment of so many<br />
of our young.<br />
What is required is a revitalization of world trade an<br />
expansion of world markets. </p>
<p>Recent international discussions have focussed on this central<br />
and all important issue. World leaders are united in the belief<br />
that combined action must be taken to make sure that the world<br />
moves to the kind of growth rates we have previously enjoyed.<br />
What is needed is a greater commitment, a greater determination<br />
to find solutions of lasting benefit to all sections of the<br />
world trading community.<br />
Certain actions are needed if we are to start on this path.<br />
We must continue to reduce inflation inflation is still too<br />
high. We have seen that Go~ vernments can, by determined and<br />
responsible economic policies, reduce inflation substantially<br />
and put their domestic economy on a sound basis.<br />
In many cases, certain fundamental imbalances have been allowed<br />
to arise. In Australia's case amongst others, a surge in wage<br />
rates has far outstripped general inflation and gains in<br />
productivity. By correcting these imbalances each country can<br />
participate effectively in strong and lasting world recovery,,<br />
and indeed contribute to it by pursuing moderate expansionary<br />
policies. This year Australia has been able to introduce significant cuts<br />
in personal income tax without precipitating renewed inflation.<br />
In addition, barriers to trade expansion need to be reduced in<br />
a co-ordinated and equitable manner.<br />
The current multi-lateral trade negotiations have the potential<br />
to increase significantly world trade. These negotiations will<br />
soon be drawing to a close. The decisions which are taken will<br />
set the pattern of international trade relations for years to come.<br />
It is vital to the whole trading world that the result is a<br />
comprehensive and significant reduction in trade barriers.<br />
Regrettably, so far the discussions have not greatly . progressed.<br />
It is not yet clear that agricultural products and other<br />
commodities will be included in the final agreement. Some of the<br />
major industrialised countries are proposing a 40 percent cut<br />
in tariffs on manufactured products, and some claim that this would<br />
constitute'a significant breakthrough.<br />
But when this seemingly attractive proposal is examined, it quickly<br />
becomes evident that by itself it would provide only a very limited<br />
basis for expanding world trade. With average tariffs on manufactured<br />
goods being about 10 percent, the cuts would average as little as<br />
one half of one percent per year, for 8 years starting in 1980<br />
hardly the spark to ignite the engines of world trade expansion.<br />
What is more, the proposed cuts do not affect trade within' the<br />
EEC or trade in non-manufactured goods. They would cover less<br />
than one-fifth of total world trade, and they could be quickly<br />
cancelled out by even minor movements in currency exchange ratE! s. </p>
<p>I imagine the proposed cuts may have some value to the major<br />
developed countries up to 40 percent of exports from Japan, the<br />
EEC and the United States would be covered. But they would cover<br />
not more than five percent of Australia's exports, and no more<br />
than five percent of the exports of many developing countries.<br />
For MTN to be a success, the inclusion of agricultural products and<br />
other commodities is vital. Such wide-ranging trade liberalisation<br />
negotiations as the MTN may not occur again-this century.<br />
The opportunity must be taken and taken now to reduce the protectionisr<br />
which obstructs world trade. The MTN could lead to a new international<br />
compact of historic significance if meaningful reductions in barriers<br />
can be achieved for manutactured and for agricultural products.<br />
It is not enough merely to avoid an increase in protectionism.<br />
Avoiding a negative outcome is not a sign of success.<br />
It may appear to have some limited benefits for the developed world,<br />
it would do nothing for the third world. The interests of the developed<br />
countries would once again have been promoted while the developing<br />
nations interests as commodity producers would have been virtually<br />
ignored. This result would have serious long-term economic implications<br />
for all nations developed and developing alike.<br />
The Second World War was followed by 25 years of economic growth<br />
unparalleled in the world's history. If we, in 1978, stand back<br />
and look again at the dynamics of world growth we can as'k what<br />
will provide the impetus for a renewed expansion in world trade.<br />
We cannot look with certainty to consumer demand in developed<br />
countries providing a sufficient drive to generate the expansion<br />
we need. Any meaningful response'to the problem of<br />
depressed global demand must involve the developing countries<br />
and expand their access to the developed world's markets.<br />
This would help the developing nations to meet more<br />
effectively the basic human needs of their people. Increased<br />
demand from the developing countries would provide additional<br />
growth in the world economy and the expansion in world markets which<br />
is so urgently -required. This would help get our economies operating<br />
to capacity, and provide jobs for our unemployed.<br />
The developing countries view the world trading system as<br />
inherently biased against them. Relying heavily on commodity trade,<br />
they have been severely hurt by falling commodity prices,<br />
adverse movements in exhcange rates, and in some circumstances,<br />
difficulties in obtaining access to markets in the developed<br />
countries. In 1975, the latest year for which figures are available, the<br />
terms of trade for the non-petroleumi exporting developing<br />
were worse than at any time in the preceding 15 years. / 6 </p>
<p>6.<br />
Between 1973 and 1976, official aid doubled. It would in fact<br />
have had to increase fourfold that's an additional $ 22 billion<br />
just to compensate for the deterioration in the non-oil developing<br />
nations balance of payments.-a deterioration largely caused<br />
by a worsening in their terms of trade.<br />
In the light of this, it is not surprising that the<br />
developing countries want to stabilise world commodity prices,<br />
through the introduction of a Common Fund for commodity trade.<br />
There are signs that at last all countries are moving away from<br />
inflexible positions on this issue and genuinely want-a conclusion<br />
beneficial to all. Australia is convinced that a Common Fund<br />
can be established, which will help commodity producers avoid<br />
disastrous cyclical price drops, and will help consumers by<br />
avoiding inflationary cyclical price rises.<br />
This belief was reinforced at the Commonwealth Ministeral Meeting<br />
last month in London which broadly endorsed Australia's position<br />
on the Fund. Much of the economic progress since the Second<br />
World War has come from international specialisation<br />
made possible by the great expansion of world trade.<br />
1978 is a crucial year. It is of paramount importance that every<br />
effort be made to get a sustained expansion of world trade. It is<br />
in the interests of both developed and developing nations.<br />
Australia is committed to playing its part in achieving a<br />
strong and lasting expansion in the world economy.<br />
I am confident that the Australian Mining Industry will participate<br />
in this recovery. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
