<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8911</transcript-id>
    <title>PERFORMANCE AND ACCOUNTABILITY IN THE PUBLIC SERVICE</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/07/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008911.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PERFORMANCE AND ACCOUNTABILITY<br />
INnfHE<br />
PUBLIC SERVICE<br />
A statement by the<br />
Prime Minister<br />
The Hon P J Keating, MP<br />
I July 1993<br />
Parliament House<br />
Canberra<br />
A statement made upon the publication of the following papers of the<br />
Management Advisory Board and Its<br />
Management Improvement Advisory Committee<br />
The Australian Public Service Reformed<br />
An Evaluation of a Decade of Management Reform<br />
Building a Better Public Service<br />
Accountability in the Commonwealth Public Secicw~ </p>
<p>THE AUSTRAIMAN PUBLIC SERVICE is one of the great Institutions of our national<br />
life. Its establishment was one of the key acts of Federation. It, along with the nation, is<br />
approaching Its centenary.<br />
The performance of the Public Service and its values are basic to our national well being.<br />
The quality of our system of governance depends heavily upon the Integrity,<br />
professionalism and dedication of the Public Service.<br />
As an Institution, the Service has served us well through difficult times. Two world wars,<br />
the Great Depression and the challenging period of post-war reconstruction.<br />
But the Public Service cannot rest on Its traditions, however Illustrious they may be. The<br />
service has to maintain its relevance and keep ahead of the game.<br />
It can't be expected to do that entirely of its own volition. There has to be effective<br />
political leadership.<br />
As I said In the 1991 Inaugural Chris Higgins Memorial Lecture ( and there was a<br />
professional public servant for you):<br />
only politicians can make major changes to the way a country conducts Its budinesChnge<br />
cannot come fom the bureaucraq n matter how well motivated, or gifted, becuse the<br />
bureaucracy baa mo autodrty to rak priortes or make deddion... Jn the eud, polltidm have to<br />
have the foresight to n the need for change and the courage and sruzgth to carur it throagh.<br />
In fact In 1983 there was a huge reform task to be undertaken. The Publc Service, while<br />
managed and staffed by people of real ability, Integrity and motivation had not been<br />
allowed to move with the times. Rather than liberate the Service to allow its talents and<br />
energies to flourish, our predecessors had preferred Public Service bashing, crude staff<br />
ceilings and belligerent industrial relations.<br />
Central to our reforms of the Public Service was the desire to ensure the government of<br />
the country belonged to the elected poiltclam. We stated at the outset that a key<br />
objective was to make the Public Service more responsive to the government of the day;<br />
more responsive In the sense that it would be better able to recognise and achieve the<br />
Government's overall policy objectives.<br />
We wanted a Public Service that could take us Into the 21st century. A Service that<br />
would meet our aspirations for a modern, competitive, caring and confident Australia.<br />
The reform task has required a massive effort from the Public Service. It has risen to<br />
that challenge well.<br />
Let us take this opportunity to mark bow much we have achieved over the last decade.<br />
What our predecessors had allowed to become a stultifying bureaucracy, obsessed by<br />
process for its own sake, and which all too often had Its own agenda which failed to<br />
comprehend the objectives of the elected Government, is now a far more professional<br />
body. Without doubt the Public Service is more responsive to the general policy direction of the<br />
Government. PERFORMANCEANDACCOUATABLhTY JNTRE PUBLIC SERICE PAGE 1 </p>
<p>We are a reforming Government. We need a reform-oriented Public Service.<br />
We have already achieved a significant cultural change and that Is continuing.<br />
Public servants do now focus on results, on outcomes, on performance.<br />
And contrary to some misinformed commentary, that has not been at the expense of the<br />
traditional public service virtues of honesty, probity, Integrity and fair dealing.<br />
Ethics and equity continue to take their place alongside economy, efficiency, and<br />
effectiveness. Indeed, the greater emphasis on accountability and openness In decision maldng that we<br />
have seen since 1983 has been a powerful contributor to honest and fair administration,<br />
and has reinforced a more deliberate focus on equity.<br />
Nor has the Public Service been politicised.<br />
Quite the contrary. The dearer arrangements that we now have for ministerial staff and<br />
the Important Independent role played by the Public Service Commissioner In SES<br />
staffing decisions have bolstered the merit principle.<br />
We're not interested in a politicised Public Service. But that doesn't mean public<br />
servants have to be political neuters.<br />
We want men and women who have their own Ideas, who are ready to take the Initiative<br />
combined with a high degree of political sensitivity.<br />
That Is all part of a professional Public Service.<br />
A Public Service able to give strong advice.<br />
Able to test Ideas and come up with better one.<br />
Able to articulate objections and point to the pitfalls.<br />
Able to temper misguided enthusiasm.<br />
But with the sensitivity to know when not to press further.<br />
A Service which can recognise when the arguments have been understood, and avoids<br />
unproductive debate continuing to the point of nagging.<br />
A Service which Is then able to get on and implement a Minister's decision with whole<br />
hearted commitment.<br />
Again as I said in the Chris Higins' lecture:<br />
the Govusent has valued official advice and made tet hws titloms that provide It are<br />
strong and effective.<br />
Ahb Government has always believed I a career public service, capable of giving Independent<br />
advk the Government has not sought to shldd Itself from critical advice by appointing " frilendly<br />
voice" to key poeion.<br />
When we turn to performance I say don't be fooled that there was a golden age of public<br />
administration when everything was done perfectly.<br />
PAGE 2 PERFORMANCEANDACCOUIVfABJ7IT7IN JTHEPUBLICSERVICE </p>
<p>Remember the Review of Commonwealth Administration set up In response to what<br />
Malcolm Fraser referred to as ' breakdowns and administrative failures'?<br />
Remember the ' roc In the stew' meat substitution rackets?<br />
Remember Costigan, the painters and dockers, and the escort services being run out of<br />
the Perth Deputy Crown Solicitor's Office?<br />
And those of you In the Public Service remember what It was like.<br />
Trying to manage without the necessary authority.<br />
The levers that mattered outside your control.<br />
The dead hands of the central agencies.<br />
Departments had to argue with clerks In the Public Service Board and the Department of<br />
Finance on matters of detail that should have been left to management discretion and<br />
which bore little If any relationship to the Government's priorities.<br />
It was this failure to match authority with responsibility which Indeed meant that no-one<br />
could be held to be properly accountable. It was always possible to blame someone else;<br />
departments blamed Finance or the Board and vice versa whenever administrative<br />
failures occurred.<br />
Most Importantly the abdication of responsibility by the successive conservative<br />
Governments in favour of the Commonwealth Club mandarins did our country great<br />
harm. So much opportunity was lost.<br />
Often our political debate focuses on the sins of commission. The Opposition gets Itself<br />
excited about technical mistakes In tender documents.<br />
But what about the sins of omission?<br />
What did the do-not coalition governments give us?<br />
Let us take transport and communications for example.<br />
For all I know we may have had some perfectly drafted rules and regulations.<br />
But In a country so large and so dependent on Its transport and communications systems<br />
we ended up with the most ramshackle transport system In the whole OECD.<br />
Perhaps they did the job well. But It was the wrong job.<br />
The opportunities lost in industry policy over th ose decades were staggering.<br />
Tariff walls beautifly built Detailed and extensive industry regulation was faultlessly<br />
drafted. But who was concerned with whether It was the right poicy or not. It was the<br />
lazy days of the fites and sixties In the lucky country. Nobody was looking where we<br />
were going. No vision, no political thought and no leadership.<br />
PERFORM4NCEANDACCOUNFABILFTIN THE PUBLIC SERVIE PAGE 3 </p>
<p>We have been paying dearly for that political vacuum. We have had to labour hard to<br />
establish national Industry policies, to restructure the economy and to create the<br />
infrastructure Australia needs.<br />
In those days creativity, Imagination and the generation of Ideas were not called for and<br />
so they were not provided. The harnesses which had linked the Public Service to the<br />
driving needs of the Government and the community during the war and the period of<br />
post-war reconstruction worked loose. Uke all bureaucracies left to their own devices,<br />
it grew and focused its energies on itself.<br />
I don't propose to traverse the many changes we have made over the decade. They are<br />
comprehensively described In the evaluation.<br />
You are familiar with the 1984 reforms. You will recall the small change at that time<br />
which marked the direction of all the changes, the amendment of section 25 of the Public<br />
Service Act We added three simple words to the description of the responsibilities of<br />
heads of departments: " under the Minister". Three simple words which said it all. And<br />
we stopped using the description " Permanent Head".<br />
You are aware of the extensive changes we have made to the budget processes that enable<br />
Ministers to decide the priorities to be allocated to the Government's programs.<br />
You are aware of the 1987 machinery of government changes which were directed to<br />
strengthening Cabinet and ministerial control.<br />
At the same time we abolished the Public Service Board. Its time had truly come and<br />
gone. Quite deliberately, to Increase the responsibility and authority of managers in<br />
departments, we have steered away from a single strong management authority at the<br />
centre.<br />
And you are familiar with the more recent reforms: the award restructuring,<br />
commercialsation, even privatisation, where It's appropriate, and most recently<br />
enterprise bargaining.<br />
The evaluation of the reforms has been an ambitious undertaking. Vic Rogers and the<br />
other members of his task force are to be congratulated. Michael Keating tells me that<br />
he is unaware of any other country that has attempted such a comprehensive survey of<br />
management change.<br />
The evaluation has concluded that:<br />
the management reforms have been well directed;<br />
they have been well accepted and their benefits have substantially<br />
outweighed their costs, and<br />
agencies need to take more active steps to fully integrate the reforms into<br />
the culture of the Service and make them work more effectively.<br />
I am very glad that the task force has come to this conclusion because I, for one, have no<br />
intention of going back to 1982.<br />
And so to the future.<br />
PAGE 4 PERFORMANCE ANDACCOUNTABILITYN TIE PUBLIC SERVICE </p>
<p>T'he Management Advisory Board, itself a product of the 1987 reforms, has prepared the<br />
paper Buikding a Better Public Service. It Is an Important document that I commend for<br />
dose attention by all those with an Interest In understanding what the Public Service is<br />
about. It Is not a detailed blueprint for further reform. Rather, It suggests a strategic approach<br />
focusing on: making performance count,<br />
better leadership, and<br />
a strengthening of the culture of continuous Improvement.<br />
As the paper says, the drive for the reform of the Public Service must be viewed In the<br />
broader context of the changes affecting the whole of Australian society:<br />
the internationalisation of the economy and the release of competitive<br />
forces the Increased demand for Improved services, while maintaining<br />
expenditure restraint, thus requiring continuing Improvement in value for<br />
money and better educated staff wanting to be more closely Involved In decision<br />
makin affecting them.<br />
But the paper warns against complacency and argues that the task of continuing reform<br />
Is as urgent now as it ever was.<br />
And we cannot stand still.<br />
Thnere must be a stronger focus on clients and the quality of services.<br />
Leadership Is crucial. I have already discussed political leadership but more has to be<br />
done to cultivate leadership within the Public Service, especially at Secretary and SES<br />
levels, to achieve the high quality services, representing the best value for money, to<br />
which the Australian people are entitled.<br />
The Public Service has to sharpen Its focus on performance stili further. To Improve<br />
performance It Is essential that people should be told where they stand.<br />
Praise where praise is due.<br />
Fair, frank and firm feedback when they need to lift their game.<br />
The private sector and other public services have developed performance appraisal<br />
schemes. In the past the Australian Public Service has not been good at this. Too much<br />
use has been made of the too hard basket when It comes to appraisal. As a result there<br />
has been Inadequate communication between supervisors and staff.<br />
So to reinforce effective appraisal we are now introducing performance pay. It huas come<br />
In for the Senior Officers, the middle managers, and from today It comes In for the SE&amp;.<br />
We must be prepared to work at It and If necessary develop and refine the arrangements<br />
to ensure performance payIs an effective spur to good performance. It needs tobe given<br />
time to settle In and be properly evaluated.<br />
PERFORMANCEANDACCOUNTABIUrIYI THE PUBIC SERVICE PAGES </p>
<p>Of course there will be teething problems and we have to find the right balance of public<br />
accountability sought by Parliament and the confidentiality needed if the schemes are to<br />
work effectively.<br />
Again that calls for leadership by Secretaries and all the SES.<br />
As In private sector employment, enterprise bargaining will place the emphasis on<br />
generating reform at the local level.<br />
Increasingly It will be for public service managers at the local level to Improve the way<br />
work Is carried out. They are the ones, together with their staff, who are best placed to<br />
generate the Ideas on how to get that extra value for money and how to further Improve<br />
the quality of the service they and their teams provide.<br />
Those are the questions we must afi ask, a/ the time. We live in a competitive world. In<br />
building a better Public Service the focus is on continuing mprovement.<br />
We are getting this country moving again and the Public Service is playing its central role<br />
In that.<br />
Drawing on the Chris Higgins lecture again, I said then:<br />
rI I will be mm as the time that Amtralla finally stood up and took dock of Itsef and Its<br />
proble&amp; It wil be se am the tiue whem dhage and innovation became the dock in trade of the<br />
political proe.<br />
We Invest In peltical leadership and Ministers are In the driving seat. We have the<br />
talent In the Cabinet, and have maintained the supply of new talent to stay there.<br />
It's an impressive achievement.<br />
And It's also an achievement for the Public Service.<br />
Although the reforms have been driven by Ministers, as the decade has passed there has<br />
been an Increasing enthusiasm for reform. Many of the ideas for reform have been<br />
generated by public servants attuned to the Government's wishes. People such as<br />
Michael Keating who have done so much to push the reforms along can be proud of what<br />
they have achieved.<br />
Ideas have been acted upon and decisions have been Implemented.<br />
That Is how It should be.<br />
I turn now to the subject of the third paper accountability.<br />
This paper should be required reading for public servants at all levels, and for all<br />
Members and Senators especially Opposition Senators.<br />
The paper was first published as an exposure draft in August, 1991 It created a degree<br />
of fuss.<br />
PAGE 6 PERFORMANCEAND ACCOUNTABlJ7TIN T PUBUCSAMfCE </p>
<p>It has been the subject of a large number of seminars and workshops, both public and<br />
within the Public Service since then. It has been redrafted in the light of the comments<br />
received. I expect it will still create some lively discussion.<br />
But its publication is very timely. As the recent session of Parliament shows, there is a<br />
lot of muddled thinking about the relationships between the Public Service, the<br />
Government and the Parliament.<br />
Parliamentary accountability is a serious matter. Many of the public service reforms I<br />
have been describing have been directed to Improving the capacity of Parliament to<br />
scrutinise government.<br />
Recent commentary, however, has suggested ministerial responsibility no longer operates<br />
in Australia and that there are gaps in our system of accountability. Those parrot cries<br />
are devoid of any meaningul content.<br />
Statements are made that we have redefined the concept of ministerial responsibility.<br />
Watered it down. Changed the rules.<br />
This is not so. I remind you of what my predecessor said about ministerial responsibility<br />
in his 1988 Garran Oration:<br />
The true measure of ministerial accountability, here and in Britain, has never been the tally of<br />
ministerial resignations. Evem In the sower and simpler formative period of our system of<br />
Government, the strict theory that Ministers were fully accountable bor every act or omission of<br />
their departmental officer was, Amply far fetched.<br />
He went on to say:<br />
-ministers mt, of course, continue to be answerable to the Parllament and to take any necessary<br />
corrective actio. But the truth i there b no requirement for them to resign except where a<br />
signifcant act or omission was theirs, or was taken at their personal direction, or was a matter<br />
about which they obviously should have known, and done something.<br />
At that time the Government was criticised for changing the rules and departing from<br />
Westminster tradition. Again the commentators got it wrong. Back in January 1983<br />
the report of the Review of Commonwealth Administration for Mr Fraser disposed of the<br />
myth that In the United Kingdom ministers automatically, regularly or often resigned<br />
where there were acts of maladministration by their departments.<br />
Instead the Review concluded that there " has never really been [ such] a convention in the<br />
UK. Indeed, we have not been able to identify ( In well over a 100 years) a single case that<br />
can properly and confidently be claimed as a resignation for that reason."<br />
And 12 years before my predecessor's comments, the Coombs Royal Commission on<br />
Australian Government Administration, put it this way:<br />
there s little evidence that a minister's responsibility now seen as requiring him to bear the<br />
blame for all the faults and shortcomings of his public service subordinates regardless of his own<br />
Involvement, or to tender his resignation in every case where fult is found. The evidence tends to<br />
suggest rather that while obliged to answer to it when Parliament so demands, and to nldicate<br />
PERFORMANCEANDACCOUNTABIITYIN THE PUBLIC SERVICE PAGE 7 </p>
<p>corrective action if that called for, they themselve are not held culpable and ai consequence<br />
bound to resign or suffer dismmial unless the action whch stads condemned was theis, or<br />
takes on their direction, or was action with which they ought obvously to have been concerned.<br />
And so let us be a bit grown-up about this. On both sides of politics the question of<br />
ministerial resignation will be a matter of hard-nosed Judgement by the Prime Minister<br />
taking into account whether or not the Minister was directly involved, and if not, whether<br />
the Minister should have been Involved.<br />
As Sir Geoffrey Yeend, a former head of my Department, recently made cear in a letter<br />
to The Canberra Times the problem the Journalists have, not to mention the Opposition, Is<br />
confusing responsibility with resignation.<br />
Accountability and ministerial responsibility are not to be measured In scalps taken.<br />
Ministers are answerable to Parliament.<br />
And as Sir Geoffrey made dear in his letter, it cannot be assumed that if there is no<br />
resignation there is no cost. Sanctions are altogether a more subtle business than many<br />
critics apparently understand.<br />
I accept that there are grey areas. The question whether a Minister knew about some<br />
matter can be simply determined. Whether he or she should have known leaves room for<br />
genuine differences of opinion.<br />
What is certain Is that once the problem has come to the Minister's attention he or she<br />
has a clear continuing responsibility to fix t up.<br />
If the thinking on ministerial responsibility has been muddled, It s yet more so when It<br />
comes to the accountability of public servants and their proper relationship with the<br />
Parliament. Public servants are the employees of the Government, not the Parliament. A large<br />
measure of their direct accountability should therefore be seen In the context of the<br />
normal employment obligations that any employee has to his or her employer.<br />
The exposure draft of the MAB accountability paper was, however, criticised because it<br />
appeared to limit accountability to this direct relationshlp.<br />
As the new MAB document makes dear, Secretaries and departmental staff are<br />
accountable to the Parliament through their Ministers according to long established<br />
convention. The document, however, recognises the indisputable fact that the complexity<br />
and sheer scale of administrative tasks means that Ministers cannot be directly<br />
responsible for all the actions of their departments. This is explitly recognised in the<br />
many legislative provisions for extensive delegation to officials. Accordingly the MAB<br />
document recognises that the traditional hierarchical accountability relationships have<br />
been complemented by public servants' duty to explain or Justify their actions directly to<br />
parliamentary committees where the minister neither knew nor should have been<br />
expected to know about a matter.<br />
Furthermore, the Parliament has recognised that it itself is no better placed than the<br />
Minister to keep track of all the administrative decisions. Accordingly various external<br />
4<br />
PAGE PERFORMANCEANDACCOUNTABILITY IN TE PUBLIC SERVICE </p>
<p>review bodies such as tribunals, the Auditor-General and the Ombudsman have been<br />
established to supplement the traditional accountability processes.<br />
When we consider public servants' accountability, especially when it comes to the<br />
question of sanctions, we have to be clear about the respective responsibilities of the<br />
Government and Public Service managers.<br />
With the exception of the Government's statutory responsibilities in relation to<br />
departmental Secretaries, staffing decisions, including any questions of rewards or<br />
sanctions, are matters for Secretaries of Departments and in some instances the<br />
independent Public Service Commissioner. That is how it should be and I am sure no<br />
one would wish to see the Government Intervening more directly. It would be a slippery<br />
slope to politicisation.<br />
And what are the appropriate sanctions?<br />
Such matters will always Involve careful judgement. It's a weighing up of the<br />
significance of the problems and their nature, of peoples' competence, their overall<br />
contribution and their capacity to fix the problems.<br />
This weighing up of achievement is Important for wider reasons.<br />
We have put a lot of effort in the last ten years into trying to turn the public service<br />
culture around to Instil In public servants an understanding that performance and<br />
achievement are Important.<br />
We must reinforce the understanding that avoidance of mistakes is not the only<br />
imperative or touchstone of public service performance. We must not return to the riskaverse<br />
culture of the past.<br />
The cock-ups, the sins of commission, can be damaging, but typically their consequences<br />
are far less damaging than those sins of omission I referred to earlier.<br />
Unless we are prepared, as a government, to play by these new rules to assess people by<br />
their overall performance we can hardly be surprised if public servants seek to avoid<br />
risk at all costs.<br />
As part of the further developments in public service management reform there will be a<br />
sharper focus on effective performance appraisal, and related rewards and sanctions.<br />
In introducing this tougher environment, we should not lose sight of the Importance of<br />
professional pride for public servants, especially at senior levels. Respect among<br />
colleagues, satisfaction In the achievement of a difMcult task well done, are valued. It is<br />
relevant when discussing sanctions.<br />
The public exposure of shortcomings leads to professional embarrassment. Often this<br />
will be sufficient sanction.<br />
Performance and accountability often arise in the context of parliamentary committees.<br />
It is, I suggest, time for us to engage in some mature reflection on the question of scrutiny<br />
by parliamentary committees. PERFORMANCE ANDACCOUNTABIITY IN THE PUBLIC SERVICE PAGE 9 </p>
<p>Our committee system is potentially a very good system, capable of making a worthwhile<br />
contribution to the quality of govertnent.<br />
it Is so Important that It should not be prostituted.<br />
May I therefore makm some suggestions to the Opposition leadership? I hope there is an<br />
understanding among that leadership of the danger of debasing the committee system.<br />
We should take a long-term view of the value of parliamentary committees. We should<br />
expect and encourage public servants to play their full part in providing Information to<br />
parliamentary committees.<br />
But If some Senators In particular adopted a less adversarial approach they might<br />
achieve far more effective parliamentary scrutiny. As the Government has improved the<br />
quality of the Information being provided to the Parliament, and with the Increasing<br />
expectation that public servanats will explain the background to government policies and<br />
account for actions for which they are responsible, there Is a corresponding obligation on<br />
committee members to be professional In their role; for example, to have read the<br />
papers, to avoid aimless fishing expeditions, to have thought out their lines of Inquiry, and<br />
so On.<br />
There Is an Increasing demand for the tabling of documents In Parliament and Its<br />
committees There Is of course a case for the Parliament to have access to some<br />
documents. Often the Government wants debate to be Informed by having key<br />
documents on the record. Often It would help If the Opposition read them.<br />
But there needs to be a shared recognition of the limits and costs Involved.<br />
Consultation between the Opposition and Ministers and senior officials will help to<br />
enable the legitimate demands of parliamentary scrutiny to be met without wasting<br />
everybody's time and taxpayers' dollars Ministers will be cautious In their undertakings<br />
to produce documents and the Government will not accede to requests that are merely<br />
fishing expeditions.<br />
I do not wish my remarks to be taken as dismissve of the proper role of Parliament.<br />
Far from It.<br />
We are Interested to ensure that parliament Is a relevant and modern Institution. And I<br />
hope the Opposition will join us In that.<br />
T7he people of Australia look to their leaders and their representatives to address the<br />
challenges we face together as a nation.<br />
They want good government.<br />
T7hey want the Government they have chosen to be able to get on and do the things that<br />
need to be done.<br />
T7hey want Informed and constructive parliamentary debate about the Issues that matter.<br />
PAGE 10 PERFORMANCEANDACCOINTABILTIN THE PUBIC SERVICE </p>
<p>Dealing with unemployment<br />
0 Achieving sustainable economic growth<br />
Building up our manufacturing base and Increasing our exports<br />
0 Securing our place In the Asia-Pacific Region<br />
Working towards reconciliation with the nation's Indigenous people<br />
0 Protecting the less well-off, the sick and the aged<br />
Preparing our children for the lives ahead of them<br />
0 Looking after our matchless environment<br />
Fostering our cultural life<br />
Continuing the enrichment of our national life that we have gained from<br />
the successMi Integration of our diverse ethnic backgrounds<br />
Developing our sense of ourselves as a mature, confident and completely<br />
Independent nation with constitutional arrangements appropriate to the<br />
21st century.<br />
These are the Issues which the Australian people have entrusted to their representatives<br />
and the Government.<br />
For the Government's part we shall be energetic in pursuing the community's goals.<br />
I believe the Parliament has a corresponding duty to make Its contribution to the debate<br />
of these big issues.<br />
But all too often what passes for political debate Is the pursuit of scnd order Issues.<br />
The Public Service has a key role to play as we approach the new century. Historically,,<br />
the Public Service has been especially Important at key times In our national<br />
development. T1he push in the 1990s towards federation Is a good example. It took political leadership<br />
and community initiative and popular support to achieve the goal of nationhood.<br />
But a lot of the business of making It ali happen would have fallen to the officials and In<br />
the Commonwealth's first public servant, Sir Robert Garran, there was an excellent<br />
example of professional dedication, and above all, creativity,, In giving form and<br />
substance to the aspirations of the early federal governments.<br />
Similarly,, in those difficult times Immediately after the Second World War, Australia<br />
was blessed with a generation of gifted, capable and Imaginative senior officials.<br />
Contemplating the kind of country that we want Australia to be In 2001 and 2010 and on<br />
Into the century Iam struck by the parallelswith the values that we want to see In the<br />
Public Service and also by the crucial Importance of the Public Service In enabling the<br />
country to achieve that future.<br />
We want the country to be vital and energetic with a strong sense of individual fr-eedom.<br />
In the Public Service we are striving towards a new cuiture of continuing Improvement In<br />
performance. There wil be less emphasis on central direction and more on the freedom<br />
of local management and staff and unions to decide how things will be done.<br />
PERFORMANCE AND ACCOUNTABHMJYIN THE PUBLIC SERVICE PAGE 11 </p>
<p>We want a fair country with equality of opportunity for all groups within It. In the<br />
Public Service, social Justice, access to government programs and equity In all decision<br />
making will continue to be a central consideration.<br />
We want an honest and law-abiding country. In the Public Service we can be satisfied<br />
with nothing less than the highest ethical standards. The Integity and probity of public<br />
office holders ( and I Include politicians) Is the foundation upon which proper standards of<br />
conduct In all walks of life are built.<br />
Corruption in government and public administration rapidly permeates the community.<br />
There Is a heavy responsibility on the most senior levels of the Service because so much is<br />
learnt by example, good and bad. I am a strong supporter of the moves within the<br />
Service to re-emphasise the traditional Importance of public service ethics.<br />
Let me make It quite clear that It has never been any part of the Government's public<br />
service management reforms that the traditional Public Service values should be<br />
diminished. In focusing on performance and achieving results It has been right for us to<br />
examine process. Process which serves no useful purpose should be scrapped and that<br />
has been a significant ob~ ject of the reforms. But that does not detract from the<br />
Importance of adhering to the due process that remains, especially when It is part of the<br />
law. We need our public servants to be achievers We want results. They should be energetic,<br />
responsive, creative and Imaginative.<br />
But the responsibilities entrusted to the Government by the Australian people are<br />
precious. So the energy, the enthusiasm, the creativity and Imagination have to be<br />
carefuly balanced with some prudence, attention to detafl, sound judgement, healthy<br />
scepticism and the guts to stond against the flow.<br />
I acknowledge that we do ask a great deal of the Public Service.<br />
Addressing the Press Club after his Royal Commisson reported, Nugget Coombs<br />
observed that It was, after all, the men and women of the Public Service that could make<br />
politicians' dreams come true.<br />
As a community we should be thankful for It.<br />
PAGED1 PERFORRL4NCEANDACCOUNwTABIHflYIN THE PUBLIC SKRVIC </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
