<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3645</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON EG WHITLAM QC MP, AUSTRALIAN LABOR PARTY ZONE 1 CONFERENCE, LANE COVE TOWN HALL, SUNDAY 9 MARCH 1975 - THE POLITICS OF MEDIBANK</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/03/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003645.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON. E. G. WHITLAM, Q. C., M. P. o<br />
AUSTRALIAN LABOR PARTY ZONE 1 CONFERENCE<br />
LANE COVE TOWN HALL, SUNDAY 9 MARCH 1975<br />
THE POLITICS OF MEDIBANK<br />
THE OPPOSITION'S THREAT TO MEDIBANK SYMBOLIZES AND<br />
ENCAPSULES THEIR WHOLE DESTRUCTIVE AND NEGATIVE APPROACH TO<br />
NATIONAL ISSUES TODAY.<br />
1; IT PERFECTLY ILLUSTRATES THEIR CONTEMPT OF THE WILL<br />
OF THE PEOPLE AND THEIR REFUSAL TO ACCEPT THE PEOPLE S<br />
VERDICT. LABOR'S HEALTH INSURANCE PROPOSALS WERE<br />
FIRST PUT BEFORE THE ELECTORATE IN DETAIL AT THE<br />
ELECTIONS OF 1969 ELECTIONS IN WHICH THE LABOR PARTY<br />
GAINED 17 SEATS. THEY WERE AGAIN CENTRAL TO OUR<br />
POLICIES ON WHICH WE WON THE 1972 ELECTIONS. THEY<br />
WERE SPELT OUT AGAIN IN 1974. INDEED, THE HEALTH<br />
INSURANCE COMMISSION ACT WAS ONE OF THE. SIX BILLS<br />
REJECTED TN THE SENATE ON WHICH THE LABOR GOVERNMENT<br />
WAS GRANTED A DOUBLE DISSOLUTION AFTER THE SENATE'S<br />
REFUSAL OF SUPPLY. As THE MELBOURNEAGE SAID YESTERDAY:<br />
" THE BROAD HEALTH INSURANCE PROGRAMME IS ALREADY LAW,<br />
IT HAS BEEN APPROVED BY PARLIAMENT. IT HAS TWICE<br />
BEEN THE ? RINC! PAL PLANK IN A WINNING ELECTION POLICY,<br />
IF EVER THE WHITLAM GOVERNMENT HAD THE RIGHT TO CLAIM<br />
A MANDATE FOR ANYTHING IT IS FOR THE HEALTH SCHEME," </p>
<p>-2-<br />
2. THE OPPOSITION'S ATTITUDE IS A CLASSIC EXAMPLE OF THE<br />
USE OF THE SENATE TO FRUSTRATE NOT JUST THE ELECTED GOVERNMENT<br />
BUT THE CLEAR DECISION OF THE PEOPLE. THE HEALTH INSURANCE<br />
COMMISSION IS NOW ESTABLISHED BY THE LAW OF THE LAND AS ARESULT<br />
OF THE JOINT SITTING LAST AUGUST. WHEN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES<br />
AND THE SENATE TOGETHER PASSED THE BILL INTO LAW THE OPPOSITION<br />
THEN USED ITS NUMBERS IN THE SENATE TO PREVENT PASSAGE OF THE<br />
HEALTH INSURANCE LEVYASSESSMENT BILLS TO FUND MEDIBANKS<br />
IS<br />
3. I/ AN ILLUSTRATION OF THE WAY IN WHICH THE OPPOSITION NOW-.<br />
OPPOSES MEASURES WHICH THEY THEMSELVES PROPOSED OR INITIATED IN<br />
GOVERNMENT. SINCE THE JOINT SITTING THE OPPOSITION IN THE<br />
SENATE HAS TWICE EXCLUDED FROM A NATIONAL HEALTH BILL PROVISIONS<br />
WHICH WERE-RECOMMENDED SIX YEARS AGO BY THE NIMMO COMMITTEE AND<br />
WHICH FIVE YEARS AGO LAST WEEK DR FORBES WHEN MINISTER FOR<br />
HEALTH SAID THAT THE GORTON GOVERNMENT WOULD ADOPT.<br />
4I, MR. SNEDDEN'S WRITHINGS AND WRIGGLINGS IN HIS EFFORTS fO<br />
RECONCILE HIS STATEMENTS WITH MR ANTHONY'S IS A CARICATURE OF<br />
LEADERSHIP. THE COUNTRY PARTY TAIL IS WAGGING THE LIBERAL.<br />
WOOF WOOF. MR ANTHONY OPPOSES MEDIBANK ONLY BECAUSE HE IS<br />
DESPERATE THAT AN ELECTION BE HELD BEFORE THE NEXT RE-DISTRIBUTION<br />
CAN GUARANTEE AUSTRALIANS EQUAL ELECTORATES AS PROVIDED BY THE LAW<br />
OF THE LAND ANOTHER PROPOSITION ENDORSED BY THE PEOPLE LAST MAY<br />
AND APPROVED AT THE JOINT SITTING IN AUGUST. IT IS QUITE<br />
IMMATERIAL TO HIM THAT HIS LIBERAL ALLIES SUFFER AS MUCH FROM<br />
THE PRESENT APPORTIONMENT AS THE-LABOR PARTY.<br />
( MITCHELL, LIB, 29.98 ABOVE THE QUOTA; ROBERTSON, LAB, 25.29<br />
ABOVE THE QUOTA; CALARE, 16,82 BELOW THE QUOTA;<br />
HUME, 20.73 BELOW THE QUOTA; GWYDIR, 16.96 BELOW<br />
THE QUOTA.) I 3/ I </p>
<p>AND IT IS SYMPTOMATIC OF THE PRESENT STATE OF THE LIBERAL PARTY<br />
THAT IT WILL MEEKLY ACCEPT THIS DICTATION AND THIS INJUSTICE,<br />
THE ATTITUDE OF THE NON-LABOR STATES ILLUSTRATES THE<br />
PHONINESS OF THEIR " STATES' RIGHTS" SLOGANEERING WHEN IT COMES<br />
TO A MATTER OF THE PEOPLEIS RIGHTS. IN N. SW, DAILY CHARGES FOR<br />
PUBLIC WARD BEDS WERE LIFTED TO $ 30, EXACTLY DOUBLE THE CHARGE<br />
IN JULY 1972, NSW, STANDS TO LOSE $ 30 MILLION IN 1975/ 76 IF<br />
IT REFUSES TO OPERATE MEDIBANK,<br />
6. THE WHOLE BUSINESS IS DESIGNED TO DRAG OUT THE DEBATE, TO<br />
OBSCURE THE BASIC ISSUE SO THAT PEOPLE WILLEBECOME THOROUGHLY<br />
CONFUSED AND THOROUGHLY DISILLUSIONED. THE FACT IS THAT HOWEVER<br />
HEALTH INSURANCE IS FINANCED, HOWEVER MEDIBANK' IS FUNDED,<br />
MEDICAL AND HOSPITAL TREATMENT WILL NOT COST A CENT MORE. WE<br />
HAVE TO FACE THE FACT THAT AN INCREASING PERCENTAGE OF THE<br />
i ATIONAL INCOME WILL'BE APPLIED TO HEALTH. IT IS IRRELEVANT<br />
WHETHER THIS IS CHANNELLED THROUGH THE PRIVATE HEALTH FUNDS OR<br />
THROUGH MEDIBANK HOWEVER FUNDED. THE ONLY SIGNIFICANT RESULT<br />
IN OVERALL COST IS THAT MEDIBANK WILL BE LESS EXPENSIVE TO<br />
ADMINISTER THAN HEALTH INSURANCE ADMINISTERED BY MORE THAN 100<br />
PRIVATE BUREAUCRACIES PRESENTLY OPERATING IN AUSTRALIA.<br />
7. AS FAR AS THE GOVERNMENT IS CONCERNED MEDIBANK IS THE LAW<br />
OF THE LAND. WE WILL APPLY THAT LAW AND WE'WILL COMPLY WITH IT,<br />
, m D </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
