<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6487</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH MICHAEL SCHILDBERGER, 3LO, 28 SEPTEMBER 1984</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/09/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006487.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
K"<br />
J<br />
Jb AU' 3TAL! A<br />
P R DMi E: VIPUM S<br />
E. O. E. PROOF ONLY<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH MICHAEL SCHILDBERGER, 3L0, 28/ 9/ 84<br />
MS determine who gets your vote in. a few weeks. Thats<br />
what the Labor Party is now doCiding although we can be pretty<br />
sure va know what issues it will Jxa camnpaigning on and they'll be:<br />
different from those already selected by the Liberals. The Labor<br />
Party, will no doubt, want to bring our thinking right back to tho<br />
successes of the economy since it has been in office. Then of<br />
course, no political party can be; sure, at the start of a campaign,<br />
just which way it is likely to go: There can always be an upset to<br />
the beat laid plans ri(.-yit at the last moment. However confident,<br />
with good reason, the Labor Party'might. be at the moment, it can<br />
never be certain until the votes are cunted. So, no election<br />
campaign is tak-en lightly and I presuvme, rob Hawke wldagree.<br />
On the line from Canberra, Good morP~ ing, Prime Minister.<br />
Good mtorning Mike.<br />
I-S Never sure until the votop are countod, or are you super<br />
confident that you can't lose whateve r happens<br />
P. 1-1. No, it would ba silly to go into an election like that.<br />
LIS ,.~ Wall novy I e-j aceonting your odds oil bet that you'll be<br />
6 at : e<br />
announcing an election i; hortly', so in that contex-t what arc you<br />
hoping thñ issues will~ be?<br />
P. M Wll 1, in a cense don't riirnd what the issue is, bccause<br />
th'Lt government can han~ 2. e any is-mue that arices. But, I believe,<br />
that the issue trill be, as it noxmi'ally is, the question of the<br />
govc. rnments compoterce in handlIng the ba. sic eCOfloiniC affairc ol'<br />
the nation.* I think that the pcoi~ le of Au-tralia will rc~ mrr1exnbsrand<br />
re hembr starkly the inheritr~ co of M~ arch of ' 83. of k irilliort<br />
riseo in unemployr., nt in th. p.: 7evious 12 montho. High inflation,<br />
rucord high interect r ). tces TI-1y III see the reversal of thalk<br />
to a position whZre Paistralja unftcr my govornment had the facrto-st<br />
grc-yicieconoiay i,, n th. voz-l. IWi h ) g ill-ion new jobs, inflc.' ktion<br />
hlvizV6* A, inte%-est rc-toecs~ T~ hoo: p ar--thC thingso that affeci<br />
R* Zo 0 </p>
<p>cont 2<br />
ordinary people. There , Js a grea~ t tendency Michael, for people in<br />
press galleries and radio colluferratora to get their issues and say<br />
this is the one which we are fa&amp; inated in writing about. You have<br />
got to remember that Australia its made up of ordinary people out<br />
there whose everyday lives are dominated by economic questions,<br />
what is happening in the job znarkot. is it more likely that they<br />
can get work, that their kids canl get work? Is the rate of price<br />
Increase being reduced? W~ hat's happening to interest rates?<br />
These are the things that affect rdinary people.<br />
HS Um w i1l if the economy does become ' the issue, which presumably<br />
it should, with what confidence wX. l1 you be able. to promise that tile<br />
* next three years will be as good ' as the last 1.8 months?<br />
can promise with confidence, that the economy will keep<br />
growing significantly. The budget is based upon, again, very high<br />
growth, in 1984-85 and that will be achieved. What we will be<br />
able to point to of courso. is that: thes-e thingjs, in part are happening<br />
becaus-e of certain fundam~ ental cha~ nges that are being made in the<br />
way the economy is run. ror instce h rcsad nosacr<br />
means that we are not having the rm. ad wages explosion which has<br />
ruined previous recoveries. if you rerrove a bnsic cloxacnt<br />
of economic instability then you have got reason for ascuming<br />
that you are going to be able to c ontinue with a significant growth<br />
inlto thlfucure.<br />
1MS *. Well on the prices income6 accord buasiness eziployers arc<br />
warning that while it has reduced: indusi. rial disputati. on it hasn't<br />
been in the best longer term interest of the economy.<br />
P. N2. Vlell some are, but overx. halmingly the business comxpuqS ty<br />
nupports the accord. So if you iqant to say, oomeone caid that, V16-1<br />
okay, you arc entitled to say it. But %% hat I z= Saying is that<br />
* the ovoerwhelmiing portion of the business comm~ unity supports it.<br />
They'd b3 out of their minds if they didn't, because, under tha<br />
a ccord you had the restoration of ! business profitability to -the<br />
highost levels for more than a deo : iade. That's wThy they support. it.<br />
Do you fear though that teewill b0-more wage demands n eXt<br />
year? For cxainplc, the ACTU has n,! 1ready foreshado-, ied productivity<br />
claims &amp; t the beginning of next yoar.<br />
more </p>
<p>cont 3<br />
P. M. Thats the concept of a productivity case within the<br />
accord and within the guidelines laid down by the comzmission, But,.<br />
the ACTU has said and the governmient has said that tie will be<br />
approaching that on the basis of looking at the. economic capacity<br />
tit the time and in the forseeable future. The AC'rU has conmmitted<br />
that its not itself making a responsible claim and the government<br />
certainly won't be supporting them. The concept of a productivity<br />
case is part of the accord and it'is within the guid~ ines the<br />
commission itself the arbitration commission itself said that<br />
it expected such a case. But, th4t is-not a carte blanche for<br />
increases that are beyond economic capacity.<br />
MiS What do you say to the employers who will say that the<br />
employment situation is certainly ~ irproving but it is happening in<br />
the public sector, and you* Nwon't lie able to keep that up.<br />
P. M. Its wrong, its not just happening in the public sector<br />
as I presume you know. Its happening in the pr: i vate sector as well,<br />
and increasingly will happen in the private sector; as the fruits<br />
of investment in the private sector are implem.' ented, ire brou ;-t<br />
to Lear, Because what you are ae eing now-. is a turn-around end<br />
this is fundamental. You'd had de~ clines in private investment<br />
in the last few years. Now that's turned around you are going to have<br />
S) ignificant improvements in investment in the private Gector. That<br />
means moro employment.<br />
UF-Do you fezar, Prime Mi. nister, that some of the cingle iosu.-s<br />
m ight ov,_&gt;:_ ta1% e the campaigns? Say: assets tet say tiz-i-a<br />
No, I do not. Obviourly there is a legitzAitc interest in<br />
the qii-stion of assets test. There ought to be bacause w., hat is<br />
be-ing donc is what is being reconumindnhA by people acrors the political<br />
epectrum. Ile are making a change there, a--nd obviously in w.-ahing<br />
changes which have been ind-Icated' as necossary, com~ e people are<br />
intererstcd and concerned, worried.. Now, the simfle facts are, that<br />
only about 2t of those currently getting pension: 3 will bo in any<br />
w-ay cnffected. It means Chat the capacity of all govern~ ments into<br />
tha future, to look zfter the grea'* t majority who arne in neod %-ill<br />
La enhanced. I am cort-dn that, t~ e majo. rity of people will ac cPp t<br />
moreC </p>
<p>cont 4<br />
that it's silly for the gommunity to be unnecessarily paying<br />
pensions to people who are niillio~ iaires in assets terms. That'<br />
is an absurdity. Mr Peacock, in bppositi0fl has said it was an<br />
absurdity, Mr Howard and don't let this be forgotten, the current<br />
deputy leader of the Liberal Party, shadow treasurer, supports<br />
the assets test concept. if he Bsipports it then he would have to<br />
say, as he does support it, it is: unquestionable that he supports<br />
it-He would have to say; well if you are going to have an assets<br />
test how do you implement it? Int any implementation of an assets<br />
test with which Mr Howard agrees, then there-, has got to bn a way<br />
of doing it. N~ ow, let him. tell is how to implement the aosets<br />
test, with which he agrees, in some other way. So you have got<br />
Peacock, Howard, you've got Senatbr Chaney* when he was the shadow<br />
spokesperson in this area, suppor~. ing i. You've got Mr John<br />
Elliot of the Liberal Party in Victoria, supporting it. You'ye<br />
got Mr Do -rner an endorsed Liberal* party candidate, speech writer<br />
for 1Mr Peacock when* he was pocmnfor-the Australian Chzmbar<br />
of Coimnerce concratulaiting the gov,.' : nment. X see,. when I have<br />
pointed that out, Michael, he's cqinie cut and said,, Oh yes, but<br />
you have got to realise that whonjI spoke ' for the Chanber of C~ ec<br />
I didn't necesparily mean what IE Lid. Well beauty 17: 0,1<br />
be asking Mr Pea:, cock, we'll be a,,, ing RVr Downer whenever he opcn~ s<br />
his ri-outh does he really believe t or is he saying it becausec he<br />
thI ks that is the right thigeosy<br />
I-I. S But nevertc; s Andrcu Peacock has said that if the Liberals<br />
won, that they would reve2rse it<br />
Wel Isimtply don't b Dl~ eve that, becnuse but lcok it's<br />
hypothtic&amp;!, they are not: going to win.. But just putting<br />
Into a hypothetical Lituation, I di: Lmply don't believe that, b,_ cause<br />
IMr Peacock believes, lie has3 mada a ! cleaxt exposition wben he iiaG able<br />
to state. the position a-lie really, saw-X it, that was when hoc vas o1..<br />
the back bnnch in goveravannt, he &amp; 1tat. 1. in the parliani~ nt eand at tho<br />
Mational Press Club, that he belioved in means tested social soccrity<br />
payziant3. There wasn't any cqWivc; cation about it. r-r Peacock state~ d<br />
hiPea! cochc bclief that 110 bolieyved in weans testod social uwafcarcp<br />
a yT,-vn ts. So that's, rUr Pc-acock. L-r h1ox-ard I. believer. in it, the<br />
shadow troasurer, he bnlieves in i t. Senator Chaney, who wa thn<br />
ahadow spokesperson, he bctiovc s i it. Youv'e got senior figures<br />
More-</p>
<p>2in the liberal party and liberal drganisation they believe in it.<br />
NOw, I siimply do not believe and tsuggest that no-one in the coun~ try<br />
would believe that if this Labor Government did the hard work of<br />
introducing something in which all those other people on the other<br />
side had expressed their belief that they would refuse-it. There<br />
is as much credibility in that ar.$ ertion by M4r Peacock, Michael<br />
as there was in their 1977 pre-election and post election oituation.<br />
in 1977 these Liberals who ask to'be believed now went into the<br />
election with, you remember the ftst Lull of dollars, the tax Cuts?<br />
As soon as they came back they ripped those tax cuts back, They<br />
took them away. Now that's how w.% ich-you can believe in imr Peacock<br />
and the Liberals. They give tax cuts before the election and'take<br />
them back afterwards. They say n6w, before an election, thoy<br />
don't believe in assets tests. If through some mischance<br />
w( e re talking hypothosis of couro6, but if they were in govornment.<br />
the imeun thing would happen they w" ould say, oh. well, yes, wie<br />
that before-hand but I'm s. orry, v90 wouldn't do it now.<br />
I-IS Prime 16 nister, the other. thing that is going to be-caid<br />
against you though in that contex~ t is that you ha; d a brohen promicregarding<br />
uranium.<br />
P. 11. ho is going to say that? If anyone is going to cay<br />
that about me, they redlly don't ). now-me. I've uiade it quiteo cleer,<br />
right through, what my positi4on iu on. uranium. The dcsoiof th2io<br />
governrme nt taken in rergard to uranium wias totally consi,. tcn,. t-ith<br />
the existinlg uraniumt 0I don't-kno-: j what you are tall:'. ng Lbout,<br />
The po.. 00.<br />
1S Well do you think those xwho are now oppo. sinc-you on thio,<br />
Laz b. or party ps-orplo are opposing you saying that it is a brol: znr<br />
prolnulr. Did they misunderstand ~ ou?<br />
I know thc'y ara saying that. but they aro virong. I<br />
raeari, you a517 those same people, kihat did they say infter the 1982<br />
* conference of the labor party you look at tho televicion rceds<br />
of those pe-ople. When the uranivza policy of 1902 was carriod, they<br />
. wcre saying, these same peoplc , they were saying it uas a out.<br />
Its a pro-iiranium policy. it as under that policy tliLt u<br />
actecl, So ho-c-can it b-faid thcjC wel have broken a poic, You<br />
* really must do a bctter exercise in lc-jic than that. You ccan e<br />
have these people saying after ' 8.2 thzat theJt'! a pro turan Ux1 POliCY<br />
Moroe.. </p>
<p>cont o. 9.. 6<br />
and then saying that whoA' we act u. nder it we" ve broken it.<br />
M. S. What you are saying now of course will upset many of your<br />
party members. Won't it? Now obviously what you are saying is<br />
going to hurt particularly the'left wing.<br />
Pm oh , the left wing had,&amp; position, they fought it and<br />
they lost. They accept the decision of the government.<br />
M. S. But are-they accepting it?<br />
P. m. well you will see that t hose people will be working for<br />
the party. Working for its support, working for its return. In<br />
all parties, not just in the Labor party, yodi'have differences of<br />
views. if you'd like to analysce the--Liberal party and the National<br />
Party aboult their views on partichiar views. Try them on South<br />
Africa, for instance, within the; party, they have very# very<br />
different and violently held difLferences of opinion. I wish you<br />
know that you would under'otand that ir. a democracy, democracy ops:-ates<br />
in a way that you don't have programmcwd individuals believing I n<br />
exactly the same thing. Now that1 s true, of thle Labor Party, Nyou<br />
have different elementr, within it'. Jvs; t as you have the ecreie<br />
right and the exl. treme le,-t in the Conservative Party.<br />
M. S ,... Loolk I understand tl.: at well, buL in your party of cource<br />
youi arc having ths problems right now again witCh preselectLions and<br />
* good old fashioned faction fightinPg.<br />
P. H I toll you whe-t, wzt won~ t liave ttw. o Labor party People<br />
standing against one another and 8f fe ring thmevsto the V no 1le<br />
of 2~~ afain this ceIon4<br />
I-10' rx you sure?<br />
P. 1.1. The Cons-ervat. ve partiep will: the miost bitter fight in<br />
tis clect4. on will be between tlLO'JlibCoral party and the IUatiohI<br />
party in 3 cornered contest. Tharcos i-. here the bitterness and<br />
oppositicin will be.<br />
H4You're about to go to a National R): ecutive INeeting now<br />
* and the qucL~ tion for re-affiliat-1onr of' thosc four . right win-g uniono<br />
is goi. 1g to co-me iup. is that going to be of concern, to try ' and<br />
~ olv that one? Oh I always takze nnttcrs thlat come-i bo fo.% e the FEl'(-at:. cnal<br />
77-ccutivo scriously. I alw. ys try' and 5olve them. </p>
<p>cont 7<br />
14.. Do you think this one will be solved before the<br />
election or after?<br />
P. 149 B.. Iefore<br />
M. S today?<br />
P. M Of course we'll. solve i. t today.<br />
M. S Well there h~ as been the' suggestion that it might be<br />
deferred. P. M Wlell, a lot of people have ! 3uggested a lot of thing.<br />
* Do you want me to operate on the kDasis of accepting every suggestion<br />
that io made in the media?<br />
M. S. Its not the suggestion Of the media. It might be the auggestn<br />
of certain members of your party.:<br />
P. M O course it has bcen a , ugqestion. I don't thinhk that<br />
that will hFappen.<br />
II. S. * coo 3 in out?<br />
P. Vel. l I'm not going any, further, thi[ s is a mattor for<br />
discussion in the executive I've jutezpreseO" my view that X<br />
th)-nk that it wiill be resolved.. ow I'm not going to say anything<br />
more about that before the mcetin j0<br />
I42. S. Rlight. N~ ow I kiiow that you* don't rcgard popularity poll1s as<br />
boing Jinportant except for the oce-asional onl. 1 are you taking any<br />
interest in those that show And2r&amp;, Peacock as polling quite badly<br />
the m~ oment?<br />
PJIA. Voll I dont rezO. ly want, to talk~ about thc loadcr of the<br />
Opoitioflp but I must sciy that I' thin% that hti~ s hcappeningtho<br />
reflects the good rscn. c of the Aueralai. cto--atc,,<br />
II. S. Do you think he has gzaihod some in the last veek thoiugh,<br />
since the last wi.-tpaken sinco he hats marjaq-. d to maecl;-iraa<br />
an issuc.<br />
PJ1 I'nM not speculc. 1-ing oin2 vhzte pni I'~ m ccatznt with<br />
thc polls, and I have been for co,., ae timoe and if there i. s only one<br />
there ivhic1h deals directly with be-tweon the leader of the<br />
opposition a-nd myself zand that cji-w over, well ovc 70 au nac<br />
to about 15% for him to whYo rl ople kilho w,. uld Pre-Cer 1c,;( ec-r<br />
this count -y and T think khat tat cays it all.<br />
M. IS. Do you extpect a dirty c~ i-i-Eign? Will you he trying to get<br />
your-revenge on Andrei., PeFacock? </p>
<p>cont 8<br />
P. M. No, you can expect a dirty campaign from them biecaure<br />
that after all is the way they ha~, e been doing it. In NSW and<br />
Federally, because they cannot and will not talk about the economny.<br />
We sit there week after week, in tLhe 110use waiting for questions<br />
about the economy. They are not torthcoming because they know the<br />
truth, that they cann't do anything there which will advantage them.<br />
So they have descended not merely into the gutter but into the<br />
sewer,. ih note sus<br />
They find that you are mo4vulnerable o te sus<br />
P. M. Pardon?<br />
M. S. Thy might believe Chat : you.. are more vulnerable on other<br />
issues. P. M. On the contrary they knowl that there. is absolutely no<br />
mileage in talking about the econo y so they mnanufacture inones of<br />
the sewer type. If they wcant. to d o that l. et them do it. 1' T~ a vin'<br />
be getting dow-n into the sewer viti thci-,.<br />
M. S. Will crime an iss. ue?<br />
Well, If it is, it is go;. ng to bea very dangerou!; for the<br />
L. ibrals b % cause I will remind you hicha -el Chtji for 30 out of t7, Clast<br />
35 years at the Federal levcl. the Concset-, atives have beeon<br />
iipower in thi~ s country, I would'remind you that it w&amp; 3 in D2cora,'-.. c<br />
11901 tlh -t comissiore~ r Costigan zz* id that the twir avoidanco imelu-1ta'y<br />
which was-mined up with organicsed cr:. rae, that flourichcd in<br />
* he rzaid in D ce-mber' 01 particularl in the last 5 years. ThLat ic<br />
. twQ176 and 01 5o if thzy want to talk about Cr: ille they 0-ro<br />
* one-s who've had the mE-tnaioir-mt of his country, the orgaliisalticn<br />
of this country for the overwhemi. prope.. rtion of thio ti7, if<br />
thay wiant to talk abouit it and xiha-they have done or what hase'nt'<br />
h: on donec so be it. Ile will take t ,. emi h-ad on if theiy want to<br />
talk zaboutl that.<br />
N. S. Just one final question.: 0oh.. two quicko-saos.<br />
t. I. thae moions= of a prime ministnr be an clection iss-ua?<br />
11L. 112 I-' don't know. But-again' if anyone iwant. s; to Mak-Oe an se<br />
of, that, 1that's up to them. I'll df* a 1lh it.<br />
VXo, u~ ld you be disa-%) Jnted tf 1thatL wasj an cloction irt-3Lo?<br />
P. N Looh, I don't exoxoss di . Apoj. n~ tnent or no-about whiat<br />
pzoi want to make iF : uos Thi-g-5vernnhont rnd iyself are oc~~ l<br />
hanppy to dcal with all issuc.-, that Qre raised. I an, not one iiho<br />
iL-t 0 </p>
<p>cont 9<br />
walks away from any issue. Whaf. ver issue is raised, I will deal.<br />
a' with it.<br />
14. S But you are trying to ' make the economy the issue.<br />
P. M. I'm trying to make it. : 1 tried to explain to you before<br />
that I believed that the overwhelining majority of people as distinct<br />
from radio commentators like, Michael Schild-berger, and people<br />
in the press galleries who want t6 run particular issues and I<br />
don't criticise you for it. If you think running with an<br />
issue that's good. That's what dQemocracy is about. I'm simply<br />
saying that its a good idea for people in the gallery and people in<br />
the area of co entziry to just remamber at times that w~ e are talk: 1ng<br />
about the lives of ordinary, every'day Austral~ ian. They are<br />
concerned about their children's iducation, they are concerned abo~ ut<br />
their employment opportunities, they are concerned about what is~<br />
happaning to inflation, they are concerned ahout what is haippeanincl<br />
tg intorp. 1-t rrjtes, concerned as to whc Lhr tI~ jeo~ i<br />
o declining, these are the things which concern ordinary~ poople.<br />
Comranatr wilinr ht basic ftct at their peril.<br />
I. I. S. Lnot qiuestion then. You hadn't actulilly chosen the<br />
electi on date last time we,-% pohe. Ilavo you now in your own i. nd<br />
chot~ cn the date?<br />
PQ. 1 Ito not absolutcly final!-sed in my mind. I adhere to t-lat<br />
I Gaid, I will be.-malzing a s; tatoiient about it in the, relatively near<br />
fur~ tu9. r et at ctaement ill, a; distinct fromaltoef<br />
predccz.: sin the past be mu h arlierthnhectati ote<br />
elcAtion and will. not bz, pdayiicg arounrl with pnople's feelingo on<br />
t-hi, 3 matter; au our predeccessorfi have, and most imiportantly,<br />
uhin we have that e eton there will ba-a referendum with it<br />
a oiiaultanceous ciection o that; i-jQ government in the future ccan<br />
do the Cons erva ti ve pred-ecessor!. hLave dclurie of imposing unnecessary<br />
clections on the poople of Auutralia.<br />
IMIS~ U-Jil that be an election, issuc though, the choosi-ng of<br />
v. colul dn' t he-ve thought ! 3o, I % wo.: uldt hink -; hat pzopln<br />
' ncrc~ c2nd that they.(,-want 31ess clection.-and under wha . t we'llA boC<br />
Coi. ng thcrc-J' 1 J.) 3 one less" olnctc. n. Iist-cad of having tho.<br />
cone; titiut onaly noceossary I-,: lf senMate clection in the early pzare<br />
Of rert year and then the house ofreprcsontat-ver, election not lon </p>
<p>cont after. We'll have them together and save the people of Australia<br />
an election and that's what they ijant.<br />
W. S And you think you ha~ ie solved that well enough by al~ ouncing<br />
. it. in advance? -jell I just knoii th,. t people don't want. any more<br />
elections than are necessary. Ana this way they'll be saving<br />
themselves an election.<br />
M. S. Prime IKinister thank you for talld1ng with me this<br />
morning. I ' m sure we'll talk agbain before the election..<br />
P. 1-Thank you ~ Iichae1. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
