<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1910</transcript-id>
    <title>COMMONWEALTH DROUGHT RELIEF ASSISTANCE IN  1968 - 69   STATEMENT IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESEN - TATIVES BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. J.G. GORTON, M.P ON 20TH AUGUST, 1968</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/08/1968</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001910.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
COMMONWEALTH DROUGHT RELIEF ASSISTANCE IN<br />
1968-69<br />
STATEMENTJ IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES<br />
BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE<br />
RT. HON. J. G. GORTON, M. P. ON<br />
AUGUST, 1968<br />
After consultation with New South Wales, Victoria,<br />
Queensland and South Australia, my Government has decided that, subject<br />
to certain limitations, drought relief assistance will continue to be provided<br />
to those States in 1968-69. Although the drought which has been affecting<br />
most of the eastern half of the Australian continent now appears to be<br />
virtually over, we accept that the need for drought relief measures has not<br />
ceased with the advent of rains and that some further Commonwealth<br />
assistance in respect of State relief measures will be necessary in 1968-69.<br />
The Commonwealth will continue to reimburse the<br />
States in 1968-69 for their drought relief expenditures arising from<br />
Loans made during the whole of 1968-69 to drought-affected<br />
farmers who establish a need for " carry-on" loan<br />
assistance prior to the end of September, 1968 or for<br />
loan assistance for restocking prior to the end of<br />
December;<br />
Freight concessions extended to drought-affected farmers<br />
prior to the end of December on the trrnsport of stock<br />
back from agistment or for re-stocking purposes;<br />
Expenditure actually incurred on other measures, including<br />
expenditure by local authorities from grants for the<br />
maintenance of employment in rural areas, pri or to the<br />
end of September.<br />
I emphasise that it is not the Commonwealth's intention<br />
that the various State relief measures should necessarily cease on the dates<br />
on which Commonwealth assistance to the States will cease. The Commonwealth's<br />
approach is that, if a State feels that it is necessary to continue<br />
a particular measure after the " cut-off'' date for Commonwealth assistance,<br />
it would be reasonable for the State itself to meet the limited expenditure<br />
likely to be involved. In this regard, I point out that contrary to the normal<br />
arrangements in relation to natural disaster relief assistance, the Commonwealth<br />
has been meeting virtually the whole cost of State expenditures on<br />
drought relief measures. The arrangements have undoubtedly been the most<br />
generous ever devised to meet such a situation and, in the three years to the<br />
end of 1967-68, they have resulted in reimbursements of State relief<br />
expenditur~ s amoucuing to nearly $ 60 million. For 1968-69, it is estimated<br />
that, on the basis of the arrangements outlined, State expenditures eligible<br />
for reimbursement will amount to a further $ 19 million made up as follows: /' 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
New South Wales 6. 0 million<br />
Victoria $ 11.0 million<br />
Queensland 0.9 million<br />
South Australia 4 million<br />
$ 19. 3 million<br />
These payments include reimbursements in respect of commitments<br />
entered into during 1967-68.<br />
I have made it clear to the four States concerned that the<br />
Commonwealth will be prepared to consider new arrangements if<br />
drought conditions happen to re-emerge on a large scale. However,<br />
I am hopeful that present expectations for a generally favourable rural<br />
season in 1968-69 will be fulfilled and that, in consequence, there will<br />
be a substantial increase in rural output and incomes of farmers. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
