<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8455</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP AUSTRALIAN FINANCIAL REVIEW LUNCH, HILTON HOTEL SYDNEY, 12 MARCH 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/03/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008455.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING, MP,<br />
AUSTRALIAN FINANCIAL REVIEW LUNCH, HILTON HOTEL,<br />
SYDNEY, 12 MARCH 1992<br />
A little over two weeks ago I announced in the Parliament a<br />
plan designed to bring us out of recession, and also to set<br />
us up as a stronger and more prosperous society for the<br />
decade ahead. We called it the " One Nation" plan to<br />
emphasise the idea that it is not only about jobs and living<br />
standards. It will create 800,000 new jobs over four years.<br />
It will raise living standards. It will strengthen our<br />
economy for the long haul. But it is also about educating<br />
and training our kids, and about the kind of country we want<br />
them to grow up in. Its about linking the country together,<br />
and linking people in the workplace together. Australia<br />
works best when we work together when employees are<br />
involved as well' as employers, when those who have lost out<br />
are brought back in, when we take care of our future<br />
generations as well as our own. That is what One Nation is<br />
all about cooperating at home to compete abroad.<br />
Today I want to ' share with you some of the thinking behind<br />
the One Nation plan. By and large the plan has been well<br />
received but in the question period that follows I'd be<br />
delighted to respond to any concerns you have about the<br />
plan, and the direction it charts out for Australia.<br />
It is a forward-looking plan, but it is mindful of our<br />
experience of the eighties. In the distress of recession it<br />
would be easy to panic and forget just how far we have<br />
already come on the path to reshaping Australia and how<br />
much we would have to lose in turning back. We are going<br />
into the nineties with inflation lower than it has been for<br />
thirty years, and with every possibility of keeping it low.<br />
Because we have cooperated in setting wages and we have<br />
allowed the dollar to find its own level, we are going into<br />
the nineties: 17 per cent more competitive internationally<br />
than we were a decade ago. We have succeeded in increasing<br />
our exports, so that today we export twice as much as we did<br />
a decade ago, and at the same time we have succeeded in </p>
<p>diversifying them through tourism and manufactures. We have<br />
increased the profit share, and over the eighties we so<br />
greatly cut taxes and government spending that our outlays<br />
today are three per cent less as a proportion of GDP than<br />
they were in the last recession. Even when the deficit<br />
reaches it maximum next financial year, it will still be<br />
less than half the size of the deficit we inherited in<br />
1983/ 84, both compared to GDP. Above all, we have cut<br />
import protection and opened all our markets to foreign<br />
competition, so the successes we have are real successes,<br />
hard fought and hard won against the best the world can<br />
offer not the phoney successes of the fifties and sixties<br />
when we built an industrial museum and called it<br />
" development".<br />
From our successes in the eighties manufacturers have<br />
learned they can put their products onto world markets and<br />
win. Employers, employees and unions have learned that they<br />
can work together to change tired old rules which hold back<br />
change and diminish the value of work. They have learned<br />
that, working together, they can transform the workplace in<br />
ways that increase pay, profits and the enjoyment of work.<br />
We have all learned that tourism is winner for Australia<br />
so much so that it is now our largest and fastest growing<br />
industry. We have learned that we can reform big government<br />
businesses, making them charge properly for their services,<br />
run themselves efficiently, and pay a profit back to us. We<br />
have learned that we can control government spending, we can<br />
cut taxes, and we can eliminate deficits in our federal<br />
budget.<br />
We came a long way in the eighties, but there is no doubt<br />
the recession has set us back. We have lost a tenth of the<br />
economic expansion of the eighties. We have lost an eighth<br />
of the new jobs we created in the eighties. We have lost a<br />
fifth of the gains in average incomes we made in the<br />
eighties. The worst thing, however, is that in recession we<br />
lost some of the confidence we gained in the eighties some<br />
of our sense of direction.<br />
One Nation is designed to get us back on course.<br />
Work on the One ' Nation statement began the day after I<br />
became Prime Minister. Right from the beginning we wanted<br />
to link two purposes in the plan. We wanted to bring<br />
forward the recovery, create jobs and encourage confidence<br />
but we wanted to do it in a way which also strengthened us<br />
for the long haul which set us up as a more competitive<br />
economy in the nineties. We wanted things that created jobs<br />
now and also helped us later. This basically meant<br />
increasing public investment now while private investment </p>
<p>was weak, so we could generate growth while building<br />
something worthwhile. Right from the beginning we thought<br />
that our public investment should help goods transport,<br />
which is directly linked with the productivity and<br />
competitiveness of our economy. Many of our consultations<br />
encouraged us to think that was the right way to go. We<br />
also knew that for the long haul we should be doing<br />
everything we could to encourage business investment. We<br />
have brought from the eighties low inflation, an increased<br />
profit share, a sharply reduced cost of capital, and a<br />
cooperative industrial relations system. The one thing more<br />
we felt we needed to strengthen investment was a business<br />
tax regime which overall would compare favourably with those<br />
of other advanced industrial countries. Again, our<br />
consultations in the community demonstrated strong support<br />
for investment incentives.<br />
Of course our plan had to be made in some kind of financial<br />
framework. The last thing we wanted to see was all the hard<br />
won fiscal cains of the eighties, all the hundreds of hours<br />
of weary work in budget committees, blown with an<br />
irresponsible spending spree. We had brought federal<br />
spending under control, and we didn't intend to let it go<br />
again. If we were to spend more now, we should wind it back<br />
as the recovery proceeded. So we imposed three rules which<br />
are embedded inthe projections of One Nation. We required<br />
outlays to fall as a percentage of GDP over the next four<br />
years. We required the deficit to fall in each year of the<br />
planning period, from its peak next financial year to<br />
surplus by .995/ 96. And since a surplus can be easily<br />
achieved by letting revenues rise as inflation increases<br />
personal income taxes, we decided to commit ourselves to<br />
returning fiscal drag as income tax cuts beginning in<br />
1994/ 95. A surplus built on what would effectively be a tax<br />
increase was unacceptable to us, and I think would be<br />
unacceptable toyou.<br />
These three rules defined the amount of room we had to<br />
stimulate recovery over the next few years, and the size of<br />
the persona. income tax cuts required in the last two years<br />
of our four year program.<br />
I can tell you now that there were many moments in the<br />
period from Christmas last year to February 26 this year<br />
when I wondered whether we could meet our deadlines. We were<br />
preparingat: least the equivalent of a budget, starting from<br />
scratch. Throughout the whole process the Commonwealth Public<br />
Service, and most particularly my own Department of Prime<br />
Minister and Cabinet, the Treasury, and the Department of<br />
Finance, performed a spectacular job helping us get out<br />
right on schedule, a 200 page document detailing over </p>
<p>programs and containing projections for the economy over the<br />
next four years.<br />
We began implementing it on the night of the statement by<br />
cutting sales taxes on cars by one quarter. We will<br />
continue in three weeks with a $ 317 million fillip to<br />
consumer confidence, delivered as a one off payment to<br />
families with children. At the same time we are beginning<br />
work on a massive program of public investment which will<br />
cost $ 2.3 billion this year and next, and which will see the<br />
creation of a national rail freight highway from Brisbane to<br />
Perth, the creation of two new national highways, better<br />
ports, better air terminals, and better training centres.<br />
That is part of our public investment program but the<br />
private investment part of the plan is just as important.<br />
We are bringcring in a new competitive depreciation regime<br />
which halves the write off time for longer lived assets. We<br />
are increasing the depreciation rate on industrial and<br />
tourism buildings. We will allow private companies to issue<br />
tax advantaged bonds to finance land transport and<br />
electricity generating projects. We will offer a ten per<br />
cent development allowance to encourage major projects.<br />
A just completed EPAC study confirms that our changes have<br />
made Australia a world leader in business tax reform.<br />
We will increase both public and private investment, and at<br />
the same time create a more competitive economy. We are<br />
dropping the separation between domestic and international<br />
airlines to create more competition and we want to bring<br />
New Zealand in to a single aviation market with us. We will<br />
help the states create a national electricity grid which<br />
serves all of eastern Australia and separates electricity<br />
production from electricity distribution and sales.<br />
Australia's success depends on the quality of workforce and<br />
the cooperativeness of its workplaces, and we will improve<br />
both. We will expand and transform the TAFE into a high<br />
status vocational education and training system, immediately<br />
increase the places for trainees and apprenticeships, and<br />
substantially expand programs to help the long term<br />
unemployed regain their skills and return to work.<br />
We will encourage and entrench a national shift to workplace<br />
bargaining as the major focus of industrial relations over<br />
the next decade. It is from workplace changes that most of<br />
our productivity increases will come, and most of the wage<br />
increases which sustain a higher living standard in the<br />
nineties. </p>
<p>Finally, we built our whole structure on the objective of<br />
keeping low inflation. To that end we sought and obtained a<br />
commitment from the ACTU that wage claims would be<br />
consistent with keeping inflation no higher than the level<br />
of our major trading partners. I have to say in all due<br />
modesty it was not a hard commitment to get, because<br />
Australia's -contemporary trade union movement is as strong<br />
on the goal of keeping low inflation as any section of the<br />
community. The income tax cuts in two years time are designed to<br />
promote both our inflation goal and our productivity goal.<br />
They are focussed on reducing the middle marginal rate to<br />
per cent, underpinning the Accord at the same time as they<br />
increase the incentives to work and save.<br />
Turning the -plan into reality is the top priority of the<br />
government. Cars are cheaper already, and I saw in Financial<br />
Review yesterday a report that sales are expected to pick<br />
up. Two days after the statement was delivered, I went to<br />
Melbourne where the ACTU executive unanimously committed<br />
the trade union movement to the principle of wage outcomes<br />
which allow us to keep inflation to a level no higher than<br />
the level of our trading partners. And as I mentioned,<br />
early next month qualifying families with children will get<br />
one-off payment to help them meet their needs, and kick<br />
the economy along a little at the same time.<br />
Meanwhile, we are moving rapidly on our public investment<br />
program. My colleague Bob Brown, the Minister for Land<br />
Transport, has already approved " black spot" road<br />
improvement projects in the Paramatta area of Sydney, where<br />
the need for better roads is great, and unemployment is<br />
high. South Australia has now sent in a proposed black<br />
spots program, and the programs for NSW and Victoria will be<br />
along in a week or so. Discussions with the states on the<br />
national roads strategy, funded from the One Nation program,<br />
are scheduled to commence today.<br />
The National Rail Corporation is now convening working<br />
groups to develop programs for improvements to the<br />
Sydney/ Brisbiane corridor, the Sydney/ Melbourne Corridor, the<br />
Melbourne/ Adelaide corridor, and the Perth/ Adelaide corridor.<br />
Throughout the system, skills assessment groups are setting<br />
out to collect the information required for a greenfields<br />
industrial agreement, which we have made a condition for the<br />
project to go: ahead.<br />
My colleague Kim Beazley, the Minister for Employment.,<br />
Education and Training, has begun discussions with his state<br />
counterparts on our TAFE program and the Treasurer, John </p>
<p>Dawkins, is pressing ahead to introduce legislation to give<br />
effect to our business tax changes in this session of<br />
Parliament. So that is the essence of One Nation plan for Australia. It<br />
builds on our strengths of low inflation, the Accord,<br />
stronger and more varied exports, fiscal reform, improved<br />
competitiveness, and a better balance between profits and<br />
wages. It builds on them by increasing public investment in<br />
services directly related to economic growth, and by<br />
increasing the incentives for private investment. Far from<br />
being an old style Keynesian program to boost consumption<br />
spending, the direct effects of the program will<br />
predominantly be on investment. It's a supply side program.<br />
Certainly we are doing something substantial to help<br />
consumer demand over the next few months, but over the next<br />
two financial years three quarters of the One Nation<br />
spending will be on public investment programs and private<br />
investment incentives. And most of that additional spending<br />
will be finished by 1994/ 95, when we begin to return fiscal<br />
drag to taxpayers at the same time as we sharply restrain<br />
outlays and bring the budget back to surplus. Our goal is<br />
to enhance our capacity to produce for home and abroad, not<br />
just our capacity to consume. </p>
<p>TRANSCRIPT OF~ THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP,<br />
FINANCIAL REVIEW LUNCHEON, QUESTIONS AND ANSWERS, SYDNEY,<br />
12 MARCH 1992<br />
E OE PROOF COPY<br />
Q: role of Australia in the Asia-Pacific?<br />
A: I think our future is in the Asia-Pacific state.<br />
Already 70 odd per cent of our export goes to the APEC<br />
area and about 67-68 per cent from memory, of our<br />
imports come from there. We are all really largely<br />
integrated with the region, but, of course, more will<br />
happen. It's the fastest growing part of the world and<br />
we are now well set up to participate in that growth.<br />
Whereas because of our reliance upon border protection,<br />
tariffs, quotas, and the fact that we had a largely<br />
uncompetitive financial system back in the ' 50s and<br />
the trades in goods and services passed Australia<br />
by. Now we have removed exchange controls, broken the<br />
tariff wall down and now where national savings will be<br />
funding productive things. Our exports this Year, for<br />
the first time in our history, our manufacturing<br />
exports are, larger than our rural exports. We're now<br />
set up with a low inflation rate and with flexibility<br />
now coming into the labour market on an enterprise<br />
basis, we're really set up to participate in this<br />
growth which formerly we were not. So, we've got to<br />
the point for our exports again in the Asia-Pacific<br />
area, the gr~ eat bulk of our imports come from there,<br />
obvious: ly we are now better positioned to take our part<br />
of that trade and to share in that growth than we ever<br />
were. That's why I think it is important that we continue to<br />
improve our competitiveness, and we break down all<br />
these areas of inefficiency. These are the first order<br />
issues. The first order issue are continuing the<br />
change : Ln the micro-economy that we formerly were doing;<br />
and successfully in the macro-economy, that is ports,<br />
wharves, railways, airlines, power generation,<br />
training, enterprise bargaining these are the things,<br />
not whether we tax our Kelloggs or our income. It is<br />
an tenth order issue. The first order issues are </p>
<p>those, and if we concentrate on the first order issue<br />
that One Nation concentrates on improving the capacity<br />
of containers through our ports and onto our rail<br />
system, on our roads, training our kids and<br />
underwriting a tax break to capital, to investment.<br />
These are the things which will set us up more<br />
adequately to participate in that growth which is where<br />
our future must be.<br />
But again we have got to be confident about our future,<br />
confident about Australia and look as though we are<br />
confident. I think that is terribly important to the<br />
chemistry of the region, that at least they think we<br />
know who we are and what we are and what we're after.<br />
Q: Mr Keating, my question is about inflation. One Nation<br />
predicts inflation at 3.75 per. Will this blow out due<br />
to enterprise bargaining in wages and higher growth<br />
rates than predicted?<br />
A: No, because it is no accident now that for 9 successive<br />
years we brought wages, the average weekly earnings<br />
forecast, which was put together by the Government with<br />
the ACTU under the Accord, we brought it in under<br />
target. We brought it in because of that<br />
understanding. I said in my speech that the ACTU as a<br />
constituency was at least as interested in lower<br />
inflation as any constituency in the country. The<br />
truth is it has been much more interested in low<br />
inflation than any constituency in the country.<br />
Because interest is between it being prepared to<br />
cut demands back where most other sectors haven't. And<br />
it is because it understands how pernicious inflation<br />
is to the low paid, to the retired, to people trying to<br />
buy a house and carry large price increases in<br />
properties, but most importantly retarding investment<br />
and with it employment. It's been about knocking<br />
inflation down and the fact that on the large booms as<br />
we've seen in the post-war years, 1988-89, when<br />
employers were offering wage increases of 12-15 per<br />
cent. But the year AWE number came out at 6 1/ 4 shows<br />
just how entirely committed in the face of that<br />
enormous demand for labour the ACTU has been.<br />
I<br />
Now we are not focussing on average weekly earnings.<br />
Because we have got inflation down, the thing to do now<br />
is keep it down and we are now focussing on major<br />
trading partner average inflation and imputing in that<br />
a wage number which is consistent with that, that is to<br />
which the ACTU is committed. But if you take the view<br />
that we can't open the labour market up, that we've got<br />
to remain with the Arbitration Commission for all<br />
adjustments in relation to the economy, then I think<br />
what you'll end up with is a colony of losers-out on<br />
The economy just won't be as competitive as it<br />
ought to be, it won't be as clever in managing itself<br />
and remember this, we are not the New Zealand Labor<br />
Party, there is no blunder and stumble here into </p>
<p>deregulation. We've actually broken the craft system<br />
up. The craft system of industrial organisation meant<br />
that if someone on the metals construction award on a<br />
Sydney building site paid an increase, that went<br />
through the whole of the metal industry in Australia.<br />
That's now been broken into much more discrete<br />
elements, and by going at it on an enterprise basis if<br />
a union wanted to claim and use its industrial muscle<br />
to claim an increase which destroys the business, it<br />
takes responsibility for it. Where formerly this was<br />
happening with the Arbitration Commission, who had no<br />
great relationship with either the business or the<br />
union. Now a union can sit down with the company and get it<br />
managed better. And you've got the metals industry for<br />
its unions groups talking about advanced manufacturing<br />
technology. They now go and say what's your long-term<br />
corporate plan, what's your long-term investment plan,<br />
and how can we help the business grow. That's the sort<br />
of mindset of maturity, not the confrontation. The New<br />
Zealand trade union movement never spoke to the Labor<br />
Government in all the years it was in office, and the<br />
Government didn't speak to it, there was no accord.<br />
They had a sort of cold turkey system that Dr Hewson<br />
will give you, you go and have a punch up over wages<br />
and the national interest invariably loses out. That's<br />
why whe~ n David Lange or Roger Douglas come here to<br />
listen Politely but take no notice of them at all. I<br />
mean good intentions, but good intentions were never<br />
enough.<br />
Q: Why are you waiting to give tax cuts for two years.<br />
Are you holding a carrot for the election?<br />
A: To not do it would definitely see the tax burden<br />
That is, even with low inflation, the effect of low<br />
inflation on the tax which will see the real tax<br />
burden ' And this Government has been pursuing a<br />
policy of handing back fiscal drag from the system and<br />
more. So the reason we are not doing it this year is<br />
because we think fiscal policy can't afford it and at<br />
this point the build up is simply not there to return<br />
but over the next couple of years there will be a build<br />
up in the revenue, particularly as growth picks up and<br />
as more time goes by, with inflation even at low<br />
levels, to have an impact on the tax scales.<br />
And by that stage, as the, if you like the hump of the<br />
deficit starts to decline as the economy comes back, as<br />
revenues pick up and unemployment benefits and the<br />
other things start to diminish and the deficit starts<br />
to come back towards surplus, that's the point then<br />
that we can make these tax cuts. All of Labor's tax<br />
cuts, every single one there's been many of them<br />
since 1983 have all been honoured, every one of them<br />
has been honoured. It won't be a repeat of the John<br />
Howard, John Hewson and Malcom Fraser show in 1977, </p>
<p>remember that campaign they had, ring up and find out<br />
how much your tax cuts were. Well 3 months later they<br />
took it back, they legislated them away. There won't<br />
be any of that. And they'l11 be there as they've always1<br />
been. I think they will create a very good climate in<br />
the labour market. People will think they are getting<br />
a fair go out of the tax system by creating employment<br />
and it will provide a certain per cent rate of tax for<br />
people between $ 20,000 and $ 40,000. People on medium<br />
incomes where the incentive is to work and do more at<br />
per cent rather than 38 in the dollar. But I hasten<br />
to add 30 per cent, the same as Dr Hewson's but without<br />
a consumption tax, without 15 per cent.<br />
That's -the point and I don't know how you are going<br />
with your businesses at the moment but what's going to<br />
happen -to you is that in the nostalgia area as you give<br />
your Sundays away filling in, as you'll be a tax<br />
collection point on the GST, you'll give your Sundays<br />
to remitting money to the tax office, you will be<br />
nostalgic you will be nostalgic for a Labor<br />
Government if it were to ever come to pass<br />
Q: Will an international increase in interest rates affect<br />
One Nation forecasts?<br />
A: We've based it on what we think is a, in part, the<br />
trading environment over the forecast period. And the<br />
trading environment we are tied up to mostly is the<br />
Asia-Pacific environment which I think is growing at<br />
per cent in forecast to 92-3 and 4.5 the following<br />
year. I don't see that sort of change, I don't see now<br />
the prospect of that changing with some shift in<br />
interest rates. It needs to be borne in mind that<br />
we've still got a tighter monetary regime applied now<br />
than ever applied from the 82-3 recession. In 1982-3<br />
interest rates came down by about 12 per cent and<br />
same in this recession. By then we had inflation<br />
running at 10 and now we've got inflation statistically<br />
running at 1.5 or a trend to 3. So there is a 7<br />
percentage points difference with inflation and yet the<br />
fall in rates has been the same, ie therefore this<br />
regime haas been as it remains, much tighter than 1982-<br />
83.<br />
Q: current account deficit/ foreign debt?<br />
A: It says in the text that systems stabilisation, the<br />
Treasury says that. This has been consistent with a<br />
slight drift up in the ratio of net external debt to<br />
GDP. And the ratio of debt to equity financing have a<br />
return -towards levels which existed prior to the<br />
excessive leveraging of the late 1980s. Net external<br />
debt to GDP ratio could stabilise or decline slowly.<br />
In other words we shouldn't take as the comparable<br />
period, the high leveraging phase of the ' 80s, but<br />
something more sensible when that balance between debt<br />
and equity is more of a guide to how the economy will </p>
<p>be in the ' 90s. So any 2-3 percentage points the<br />
current account forecasts, will forecast by other<br />
people looking at the performance of the ' 80s. Now<br />
that has changed markedly, I can't remember the numbers<br />
exactly but I think we went from about 90 per cent debt<br />
in 89-90 to 90 per cent equity in 1990-91. One has to<br />
assume, I think, more sensible behaviour in financing<br />
levels assume that this is consistent with the<br />
stabilisation of debt and GDP or a slow decline.<br />
Q: In regard to the Monarchy and your comments about<br />
Australia, if Australia becomes a republic what form<br />
will it take, will Bill Hayden be president for<br />
example?<br />
A: Well just remember what I said. The remark which was<br />
objected to by our conservative friends, forelock<br />
tugging mates, was that I said in the presence of the<br />
Queen, I was congratulating her on her 40 years as the<br />
Monarch and to make the point that in the 40 so much<br />
had changed. In 40 years, I said to her, Britain had<br />
joined the European Community and Australia's largely<br />
devoted itself to the Asia-Pacific, we were necessarily<br />
more independent of Britain than Europe, but that she<br />
was part of that change. She was part of that<br />
independence by taking the royal style and title of<br />
Queen of Australia in 1973 a thoroughly unexceptional<br />
remark. But our friends in the Opposition had to jump<br />
all over it. Dr Hewson said I didn't have enough<br />
respect for the Queen of Britain outrage, he'd like<br />
to slip right back to the torpor of the 1950s. As I<br />
said he would be our first candidate for an exhibit in<br />
the constitutional museum down there at the old<br />
Parliament House. Like I said in Parliament, we are<br />
going to put him in there with the Morphy Richards<br />
toaster and the qualcast mower and all the other bits<br />
and pieces that we all remember affectionately and<br />
well. That's what I was saying. I was just saying that<br />
Australia isn't necessarily more independent and needs<br />
to be clear about itself, needs to be confident about<br />
itself. It's very bad for these people who wish to<br />
lead us in ' the ' 90s, but who harp back and want to be<br />
part of the ' 50s. What I'm saying is they are not the<br />
people to lead us. The people to lead us are people<br />
confident about Australia, confident Australians,<br />
people that know that we are good enough to make our<br />
way in the world and know that we are entitled to and<br />
have indeed an identity of their own. If one of our<br />
national leaders in the 1990s thinks that we shouldn't<br />
have an identity of our own but we should in some way<br />
not even be referring to changes in constitutional<br />
arrangements with Great Britain, then I say well thank<br />
you but we don't need you.<br />
That was one of my remarks, I was not talking about a<br />
republic or what sort of republic we ought to have or </p>
<p>what constitutional arrangements should be. That's<br />
something for the public debate to comprehend as time<br />
goes by.<br />
Q: When can we expect announcements on the simplification<br />
of superannuation and the clarification of pension<br />
rules?<br />
A: Well when the Government has adequately considered the<br />
area. It's a complex area and when you take any system<br />
like superannuation, which is again, part of the torpor<br />
of the ' 50s and ' 60s, it was a gift from Mr Howard and<br />
Mr Hewson when we had only a very small proportion of<br />
workforce accessing the superannuation concession. And<br />
when we've opened it up more generally the workforce<br />
and then more sensibly taxed superannuation earnings,<br />
to do that and not disrupt the expectations of<br />
Australians who are near retirement, at retirement,<br />
some proximity of retirement, has meant that<br />
necessarily we've had grand provisions what have<br />
you, to protect them. This is a matter of<br />
inconvenience I know to the industry, but there is more<br />
than industry inconvenienced in all this. There is<br />
reasonable expectation by those who believe they've<br />
grown up in the system which gave them certain<br />
entitlements. And it's not easy therefore to change<br />
superannuation, arrangements for tax computation<br />
without having due regard for those things.<br />
We've tried to do that. We've tried to make the system<br />
more simple but at the same time make it fair. There<br />
is probably areas where simplification can occur but<br />
they have to be proposals which we can adopt<br />
confidently and that will take examination and<br />
we've done more than any government in history.<br />
Q: Can you explain what assistance there is to small and<br />
medium business in the One Nation Statement and what<br />
does it do for women?<br />
A: I'll deal with the second part of the question first.<br />
The thing that I've had most in mind for women in this<br />
country since I've been a Minister was jobs,<br />
participation, choice, opportunity and of those<br />
million jobs we created between 1983 and 1992, 60 per<br />
cent of those went to women. In terms of my own direct<br />
responsibility beyond employment, a number of<br />
significant things which the Government did for women<br />
in the ' 80s and that is opening up child care<br />
opportunities for women to go to work if they choose,<br />
which didn't exist formerly. The child support agency<br />
where women are supported by their husbands or former<br />
husbands, as the case may be, in support of their<br />
children, in supplementary payments for low paid women,<br />
in medicare which is an obvious support for women<br />
because women mostly have the burden of worrying about<br />
children and regardless of their circumstances are<br />
covered for health protection. I mean it is just one </p>
<p>thing after the other, equal opportunity legislation,<br />
affirmative action legislation and we're continuing<br />
that tradition and of course access to superannuation.<br />
Before we came along there was no preserved benefits<br />
and women who entered the workforce, left the workforce<br />
to have children and came back and had no preservation<br />
of benefits. They were effectively chopped out of<br />
superannuation.<br />
These are quite milestone reforms. I notice the<br />
Opposition talking about pay rates for women, Dr Hewson<br />
said he will oppose national wage cases. A lot of<br />
women are in the low paid sector of the economy<br />
process workers, shop assistants who rely upon national<br />
wage adjustments for maintenance of their incomes which<br />
they say they are opposed to. So, as usual, it will be<br />
Labor who provides, again, for Australian women.<br />
c ( 2&gt; t' 3 N3 U dW<br />
I I </p>
<p>In relation to small business, waive got a number of<br />
changes in there which I think are important. The<br />
firist thing is growth. That's the most important<br />
thing small business lives of f the growth in the<br />
economy. And we've got growth through the year<br />
forecast at 4 3/ 4 per cent. The secon~ d thing is,<br />
there has been claims by the small business<br />
community about the mobility of capital between<br />
businesses. We've now decreased sharply,<br />
dramatically, the concession for good will, the<br />
taxation of good will under the capital gains tax,<br />
exempting up to 50 per cent of the value of good<br />
will up to the value of a business of $ 2 million,<br />
which should help, at least some people rolling from<br />
one business to another. We've also changed the<br />
rate at which smaller business meets the<br />
sueanuto guarrantee levy. We've also changed<br />
the timing of the taxation payments for small<br />
busiLness. So, there Is a fair bit there for small<br />
business. Let me say that I am not advocating any<br />
enviLronmental vandalism or scorching the earth, but<br />
what absolutely escapes me this time is that we<br />
desparately need to create jobs, we desparately need<br />
to create foreign revenue, but we persist with the<br />
poliLcy which allows some projects which have got<br />
potential to create lots of jobs and earn lots of<br />
money for this country to just sit on the back<br />
shelves. And it looks to me as if you are just<br />
pandering to a small political minority group as we<br />
persist with the uranium policy, which makes this<br />
country a laughing stock, where we are allowed to<br />
mine this mine but not allowed to take uranium from<br />
that: mine. I don't understand why we do that, why<br />
we don't use all of our resources and why we don't<br />
stand up to this vocal minority and get on with it.<br />
PM: I don't think that a vocal minority is holding major<br />
projects back. The only uranium mine which has ever<br />
been an issue in Australia is Pan-Continental In the<br />
East Alligator River's flood plain. And, for<br />
exactly the same reason that the former Coalition<br />
Government did not agree to this development is the<br />
same reason why this Government concerned with the<br />
prospects of mining uranium, building a retaining<br />
dam In the middle of a flood plain. And it's a real<br />
livel issue, in terms of the environment. But that<br />
is niot a new issue, it's not something that has<br />
risen in the last few years, it's something which<br />
has been there in the last 15 to 20 years. Now,<br />
Roxby Downs is larger than three or four<br />
conventional mines put together. So there's no<br />
prohibition to the actual export of uranium, it's<br />
only about the development problems of particular<br />
mining sites. And the only one that I know that is<br />
a problem is basically Jabaluka and Pan-Continental.<br />
And that's because of the flood plain problems, it's </p>
<p>right in the middle of the flood plain. If you had<br />
seert the escarpment and the flood plain, you know<br />
what: the problem was. The latest, largest project<br />
to tie, if you like begun, in terms of quantification<br />
and preserves is the-monster out in Western<br />
Australia in the Pilbara And whij--there were some<br />
objections to that this last week, it is now<br />
proceeding. And one of the reasons we put this<br />
per cent development allowance in is to say to<br />
people who are running companies, that are not<br />
certa~ in about their timing or whether they should<br />
enter the market and are Bitting on the Bide lines<br />
waiting and looking at particular commodities and<br />
market opportunities, and then sort of blaming the<br />
Government, to say look there is a 10 per cent<br />
investment allowance in there, so if you<br />
procrastinate now you have got to really want to<br />
procrastinate, because if you do you will lose the<br />
per cent. In other words, it is a carrot sitting<br />
out there, and if they don't take it they will lose<br />
it. It is time limited. So if you are here now,<br />
getting up and saying we are being held back, you<br />
know either they really are, because if they're not<br />
they are simply going to do their company a<br />
disservice by losing a very important component in<br />
their cash flows in their early years. So that's<br />
why it's there. It's basically there to support the<br />
ones who have got bigger projects together which are<br />
which go through all these various states and<br />
what have you, and get environmental assessments and<br />
the rest. It's to support them and to at the same<br />
time encourage them. Now, in the one Nation<br />
Statement we have announced a one enviornmental<br />
process, intergovernmental agreement, environmental<br />
assessment which will now take place between the<br />
Commonwealth and the States in one process, which Is<br />
a very great change. And also, the coordination and<br />
acceleration of projects which will now be conducted<br />
under the agis of the Prime Minister's Department,<br />
supported by my Parliamentary colleague,<br />
Laurie Brereton, to try to hurry and bring the<br />
projects through these approval processes. So don't<br />
believe that minorities are holding up major<br />
projects. The one major project that has been a<br />
problem ' for years is basically the pulp mill in<br />
Tasmania.. Now, the pulp mill in Tasmania was not<br />
held up because of wood or forest resource issues.<br />
It was held up because the company said they could<br />
meet the organo-chloride emmission targets of the<br />
Government, but they wouldn't be required to meet<br />
them. And that's why it didn't proceed three or<br />
four years ago. And part of that was because of<br />
Naranda,, the Canadian company, who wouldn't be<br />
required to do things in Australia who might then be<br />
required to be done in Canada. So, just a Little<br />
bit of guile helps here, sorting out what is true,<br />
what is ' fact and what is fiction. There's no doubt<br />
there is environmental differences in this country </p>
<p>a legitimate one, but again I believe they can be<br />
balanced of f in a sensible balance for development<br />
in Australia, and that there shouldn't be a<br />
preoccupation or a view that major projects can't<br />
start in this country. I just don't think that<br />
that's true.<br />
0: Actually, Mr Hunter is being a little coy since he<br />
has two questions and I'll save him the trouble by<br />
asking it. Is the Prime Mininister of Australia<br />
being trounced in cricket, yachting and boxing.<br />
Does this reflect on the new leadership as the<br />
previous incumbent has had no such problem?<br />
PM; I'll let that go to the keeper. We might have<br />
spurred the English team on, I'll take some<br />
responsiblity there.<br />
Q: Prime Minister, you've already referred to the<br />
avia-tion' policy in the One Nation Statement. Can I<br />
take it a little further and ask your predictions<br />
for the likely outcome of the 1992 round of the CER, 1<br />
and secondly if you could give us guidance on your<br />
thoughts for the longer term direction for both<br />
countries under a CER-type agreement.<br />
PM: Well I think it is important that Australia and New<br />
Zealand are more integrated as economies, and<br />
particularly in things like aviation where there's a<br />
group of people who are closer to Sydney then indeed<br />
to Perth is, and where it makes sense to run an<br />
airline system in Australasia. And a lot of the CER<br />
arrangements be concessioned by Australia to Now<br />
Zealand, letting a country with a smaller market<br />
access to a larger market. And that mostly costs<br />
us. I've never minded the cost because I think it<br />
matters politically and strategically in the long<br />
run -to keep New Zealand as a country which is<br />
economically strong and able to have access to<br />
larger markets. But I think it is important to get<br />
the airline agreement into piece and we've got some,<br />
now absurd, blanket claims like Air New Zealand who<br />
want 50 per cent of the on-carriage rights Out of<br />
Australia to Air New Zealand, which is of course<br />
absolute nonsense, absolute nonsense. I don't mind<br />
helping the New Zealand aviation industry, but i-f<br />
they think help means scraping more of our plate<br />
onto theirs in absurd arrangements, then they are<br />
cracking jokes. So, we'll be in a good negotiation,<br />
a meaningful, sensible one, but we're not about to<br />
be pillaged in the interests of bon honmie and the<br />
fellowship of man in the South Pacific.<br />
0: Primea Minister, just on one aspect of your One<br />
Nation Statement, do you think that the electricity<br />
grid will overcome State rivalries that currently<br />
exist, and are you hopeful that there will be more<br />
competition in the industry.? </p>
<p>PM: Are you from the industry?<br />
Q: Yes.<br />
PM: well, one of the problems is, one of the great<br />
comparative advantages Australia has is that it can<br />
produce cheap electrical energy. We have a<br />
colosseum all the way down the East Coast of<br />
Australia and therefore it is one of our<br />
comparatives strengths. It is nevertheless true<br />
that we are not able to fund cheaper power in the<br />
important industries who rely on it because of the<br />
control of the State Electricity Commission in<br />
particular states. The sensible thing is to set up<br />
an interstate grid company which is owned by the<br />
Commonwealth of the States which will be the<br />
distributer of power and the electricity commission<br />
will be the generators of power and that they will<br />
then tender a price to supply power to the grid, or<br />
that if a company wishes to use power, in the use of~<br />
that power, they can get a tender from Miraring or<br />
Loyang or somewhere else and then that power station<br />
funds the grid and we can get competitive power<br />
price3s to businesses around the country. That's the<br />
point of the grid corporation and which I think will<br />
be a very healthy thing for business and<br />
competitiveness and for consumers in the Eastern<br />
Coast of Australia, Queensland, New South Wales,<br />
Victoria and South Australia. Now the opportunities<br />
which I think will manifest there and it is<br />
important to bring them home and that is another<br />
important change. But can I just say, these are all<br />
the changes which Australia really does need. I<br />
mean, putting a national grid corporation together,<br />
or building a railway highway from Brisbane to<br />
Perth, or tying the ports to that railway highway,<br />
or extending the road highway system, are all things<br />
that can only be done really by Governments. And<br />
they can't be done by taking money away from Budget<br />
in these respects, which is what the Opposition<br />
wishes to do. It is not going to happen by simply<br />
taxing your Weet-Six or your clothes or your shoes.<br />
I meein it will not matter if you tax your clothes,<br />
your shoes or your Weet-Bix, it will have no impact<br />
on the curves and gradience of the Sydney-Melbourne<br />
railwray lines, or the ridsheights, or whether one<br />
has t~ o follow a route from the Port of Melbourne<br />
or the East Swanson dock to the railway yards.<br />
Whether a truck can only take one container not two<br />
because it cannot go onto the railway line, because<br />
it isn'tr mean these are all physical<br />
practical things that need to be done to make the<br />
country efficient where it matters most. Moving<br />
goods and around and being able to trade. Dr Hewson<br />
calls that irresponsible. He calls that spending<br />
irresponsible, he knows that no private company is<br />
ever going to Invest In the railway system in terms </p>
<p>of the permanent wave, he knows that. He knows that<br />
without Government action we will not get a better<br />
electricity distribution system. He knows without<br />
Government spending we will not invest in our<br />
children in technical and further education, and we<br />
can't have now as Labor has, 7 out of 10 children<br />
completing secondary school, but not enought uptake<br />
in-the TAFE system, to take them up and train them.<br />
But we can't have a clever country without a trained<br />
worklforce in this area. He knows all these things,<br />
and yet we are given only the ideology of the GST as<br />
the solution to Australia's problems. In other<br />
words, we are supposed to say, well look, we've now<br />
reformed the macro-economy largely, we are now<br />
producing competitively, we've now got our inflation<br />
rate down, now is the time to crack all these other<br />
areas, ports, wharfs, rail, road, training. All of<br />
these things. But we will not do that, what we will<br />
do is we will go and tax expenditure but not income<br />
and that will solve the whole problems. That will<br />
solve the whole thing. But of course it is<br />
nonsense. It is a tenth order matter, and<br />
regardless of what everybody things about t: axing<br />
expenditure, nobody is going to accept that: someone<br />
on $ 20,000 who spends all of their income, that is<br />
in material whether you tax their income or<br />
expenditure because it is one of the same, they<br />
spend the lot and mostly more, they do save, whereas<br />
some~ thing on $ 150 or $ 200,00 who is spending half<br />
their income and saving the rest, not only is not<br />
taxed fully on that income, but as well as that,<br />
receives a very big tax break. Nobody is going to<br />
wear that, nobody is going to wear that. And so not<br />
onlyr is it going to be, is it a focus on things<br />
which ate not material to improving Australia's<br />
competitiveness, but it will actually be divisive.<br />
And as we add 4 percentage or 5 percentage points to<br />
the price system, and inflation rate doubles, more<br />
than doubles and goes back towards double digits<br />
agaaln, Dr Holwson will require the workforce<br />
undorcompensated to take a real reduction in income<br />
by a discount to wages which will preserve the low<br />
infl~ ation rate, which of course they won't, they<br />
will. just go and recover it in the market. And<br />
there wil be a lot of buzz in the news then<br />
about inflation. A lot of buzz about inflation<br />
rising.-And what will he do then to repair it, lift<br />
the interest and slow the economy down, so you will<br />
end up with structural high level and structural<br />
unemployment, lower levels of economic activity and<br />
that is supposed to be a solution. The fact is you<br />
can't run Australia without an agreed basis of<br />
income determination. Whether you call it Accord,<br />
or conVeWTsation with the Government and the unions,<br />
or aL partnership with business, a partnership with<br />
the unions, you can't run this country without some<br />
agreed basis of income determination. And to throw<br />
a sort of hand grenade at the system with the </p>
<p>doubling of the inflation rate throught GST when we<br />
have the unions now prepared to make our enterprise<br />
efficient, committed to low inflation, wanting to<br />
train our children and prepared to come to into,<br />
agree with enterprise agreements on things like<br />
rail. ways, ports, power generation and the rest, and<br />
say oh no, we don't need that, we can have the<br />
luxury of not worrying about those things which have<br />
bedeviled us for half a century and will go for Dr<br />
Hewson's GST. And then when the system is inflamed,<br />
with higher inflation and lower growth, and the<br />
whole micro-economic change stalls, people might<br />
then say, well that was a mistake. It is a mistake<br />
becaiuse, it is a mistake for this reason, Dr Hewson<br />
had exactly the same opportunity as I had when I<br />
became Prime minister, and that was to sit back and<br />
say well, what needs to happen to Australia next,<br />
what: is the logical thing to be doing now? He sat<br />
back and said, not what should happen for Australia,<br />
or what is logical, he said, how can I be different?<br />
What can I do that marks me out to be different?<br />
And he said, I got it, it's a consumption tax. So<br />
then he has put this consumption tax and wrapped<br />
around it other policies on the basis that its<br />
canioflauged and hidden and disguised for all to say,<br />
oh that's clever Dr Hewson, that is terrific,<br />
terrific little result. He is going to double the<br />
inflation rate, blow the wage system out of the<br />
water, derail micro-economic reform, just what we<br />
need, just what we need. But he had such a dream<br />
ride for 3 or 4 months, that he actually believes<br />
that the policy brought down actually has some<br />
quality to it. I hope that I have punctured that<br />
dream.<br />
ENDS </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
