<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8469</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J. KEATING MP VISIT TO INDONSEIA AND PAPUA NEW GUINEA</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/03/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008469.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER 29/ 92<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. 3. KEATING MP<br />
VISIT TO INDONES2: A AND PAPUA NEW GUINEA<br />
At the invitation of the Governments of Indonesia and Papua<br />
New Guinea, I shall be visiting Indonesia from 21 to 24<br />
April, and Papua New Guinea from 24 to 26 April.<br />
My visit to Indonesia, the first by an Australian Prime<br />
Minister since 19383, will provide an opportunity to discuss<br />
with President Soeharto and his senior Ministers the scope<br />
for establishing a firm basis for the long-term development<br />
of Australia-Indonesia relations both in the bilateral<br />
domain and as partners in the Asia-Pacific region.<br />
Australia and Indonesia have in common major political,<br />
economic and strategic interests. In 1990-91 Australian<br />
exports to Indonesia were worth $ 1.4 billion, making<br />
Indonesia our ninth largest export market and the second<br />
largest in ASEAN. Indonesia is a key member of the Asia<br />
Pacific Economic Cooperation ( APEC) process, which Australia<br />
helped establish.<br />
I am also pleased to have an early opportunity to visit<br />
Papua New Guinea, a country with which Australia has a longstanding<br />
and close relationship, and to meet Prime Minister<br />
Namaliu and members of his cabinet.<br />
In Port Moresby, I shall take part in a special program on<br />
Anzac Day to commemorate the 50th anniversary of the Papua<br />
New Guinea campaign of World War II. That campaign, an<br />
important part of the Pacific War, holds great significance<br />
for all Australians.<br />
Media arrangements will be advised separately in the near<br />
future.<br />
CANBERRA 18 March 1992 I1 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
