<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1109</transcript-id>
    <title>FAREWELL DINNER FOR THE GOVERNOR-GENERAL, LORD DE L&#039;ISLE, HELD AT PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA - 4TH MAY 1965</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/05/1965</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001109.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
141UiL iij AT PAkiitU" 4 JJij<br />
Sir and Ladies and ( C. ntlemeti s<br />
I mabout to essay a task proposinZ your health,<br />
Sir, Nov I don't think you were around the precincts this afternoon<br />
but if YOU had WOODS YOU might haVe gathered that there wre som<br />
differenoes between ^ rthur Qklvell and ayseif. ~ iV the effluxion<br />
of tim and the athusiasm of the axment w are mw an the one<br />
avetengtho Isn't that right, Arthur? C ~ ughtr) ivrything I<br />
says he will ape. with, will add to and wiil adorn*<br />
M~ w my task tonight is to Propose the toast of Ris<br />
xcellency the Governor-General who Is, unhappIll, aiwut to leave<br />
us. He has n ' t cme to the 00001u51l = m~ L ta) leave us beoOMus<br />
, Aen Hear bMjesty The % usen was awd enough to approve of his<br />
aipointmnt he made It quitie CNrthat there was sm limit to<br />
thie mea; Uhe Ins served out his tiMme istt hat the right<br />
expression, air? ( LAi4ghtew) withk IMens success.<br />
The 0overnr-4eewrej has beean, in on with quito<br />
a number of his Predeoessors in facts I suppose, with all, though<br />
there were some I didn't know a robust occupant of this post,<br />
I mean bF that that he has never been unwiling; z to contribute a<br />
fev views; he has always spoian the mind of a Udghl--tnlentoad and<br />
very brae man. I have had no trouble with bin, if I wa~ say so.<br />
( Laughter) Hie knos this bmmuse one of his great eeoszs<br />
then 31r Vdi1em alia's vwas a little given to expreesting hiss mind<br />
in certain areas with vigour and ocasionally I had to go out to<br />
tarrali-1a stand ouate his stukg having made an appointment,<br />
stand to attention, may to my self, R1oi, Menuies don't ran sway<br />
from Itt, ( Laugter) a" then soIn and make my " to thes Governor,-<br />
Cerrlt and then he would says " My dear Vallov, do, sit dova,"<br />
very disaril s you mee.<br />
The h would says Odhat do you want to ame no<br />
about?" and I, once or twice itsmyed the task of saling to<br />
hmt awoufyo kniow you sailt so-and-soSi. u in the Northern<br />
, errito2' y.' It's a funny things Isn't ft, tMu it In onl~ y in the<br />
, vorthewn Territory in Jid -* rms here tonight? ( Laughter) It's<br />
onl~ y in the Northern T3eritory that people succumb to the temptation<br />
to s~ things. Ju4 L vould breuthe three times invzurds you know,<br />
,. nd say think perhaps, 31w, that wasn't entirely well advised. 8<br />
hen I had'done taiis I was in a swaet beoase I was frightened<br />
of his. ( 1AUghter) I conede that point.<br />
11. would smile and say, 08it dovwn* and ' There to~ y<br />
be a great deal In whamt jr. u say. 4ell that was wietiing and<br />
then realising I was on the point or collapses be did what the<br />
. Prsent Qovernor-Ceooral ocoasioral4 does~ or roguirly does and<br />
said to me1 You like a drink?" and If unj ari ever ne" Ad<br />
one, I irasothe man*. 40119 1 haven't had to hiove that kind of expori enoe<br />
4th you, JAr becuue from first to last, ever since the dav that<br />
IOU we" e appo~ ntod, I have boon veri, very happy to kno you, and<br />
all of us hmbeen~ lapy to know you as a man of imnense Charect<br />
and If you will allw~ me to say so distngaisbed ability and<br />
aieat eourage andi truditiona Thts, I thiinks hans bomin a very go </p>
<p>r a 2.<br />
thing for us and I am quite certain, Sir, that you yourself feel<br />
that it has been a good thing for you because you have been all<br />
round Australia, you have seen people at all angles, you have been<br />
into all the corners of Australia and you have made your voice<br />
clear in almost every corner of Australia and always to the<br />
immense satisfaction of the people of Australia.<br />
Therefore the first thing I want to say to you<br />
is that I am proposing the toast of a very distinguished and very<br />
gallant man of whom all of us know a great deal. I have been in<br />
a state of a little difficulty, Sir, about the next thing I want<br />
to say but I think on the whole you would like me to refer to<br />
it. When you, Sir, came here, you brought with you a<br />
wife who had the most enormous tradition of courage and the most<br />
enormous individual courage. She was a very great lady and I shall<br />
always recall the courage with which she bore herself at a time<br />
when ordinary mortals might have been depressed and sorry for<br />
herself. Do you mind Sir, if I refer to her because, really,<br />
her period out here with you, her bravery in the face of difficul-<br />
O ties moved everybody in Australia. I say that without the<br />
slightest hesitation. And of course her death was an irreparable<br />
loss to you. Now I don't like to have to speak about these matters<br />
because they are really rather emotional but I thought about this<br />
and I thought, " No this Governor-General oan't leave Australia<br />
S without knowing tha he leaves behind him not only memories of<br />
himself but memories of her" and therefore I take the liberty on<br />
behalf of all of you of referring to that very great lady.<br />
And then when she left, His Excellency was, I<br />
think, singularly fortunate to have had in succession two daughters<br />
very young not to be expected to face up to the formalities and<br />
responsibilities of Vice-Regal existence and each of them in<br />
her turn Kate and Anne, did a marvellous job, and everybody<br />
here ton ght would want me to say how marvellous that job was,<br />
how well they did. And of course although they were daughters<br />
and if I may say so, daughters have something rather special ( a<br />
number of you will understand this perfectly), they have something<br />
rather special, young Philip, the owner of the traditional name,<br />
young Philip Sidney has been here from time to time, quite a long<br />
time, one way or another, and I would like to say to him, Sir,<br />
through you, how much we have enjoyed having Philip here and how<br />
convineed I am that he will some day be a Member of the Federal<br />
Parliament, and I am keeping my fingers crossed in ease he gets<br />
muddled up with Arthur Calwell ( Laughter).<br />
The other thing Sir, I would like to say is this.<br />
It is sometimes forgotten the dovernor-General of Australia is<br />
not only etpected to be a man of distinction, as he is, but he<br />
is also to be recognised as the personal representative of The<br />
Queen. Now this is a very significant statement the personal<br />
representative of The Queen. In other words, the perfect<br />
Governor-General is one who knows The Queen and whom The Queen<br />
knows, who represents The Queen because The Queen would wish him<br />
to represent her. This is, I think, tremendously important at<br />
the outset. And when the end of the term of office comes, then<br />
it is equally important to remember the reciprocal aspect of this<br />
matter that the overnor-General who has represented The Queen,<br />
who is known to The Queeh, goes back home and finds himself<br />
representing not The Queen but Australia representing us,<br />
speaking for us, understanding us, and that is why it is such a<br />
lovely conjunction of the planets to have a Governor-General who / 3 </p>
<p>ma. rprsent The Qmmse because The ( Qan knav hin, mepects<br />
hs who has been 1er personal pWrsentativ. and who an his return,<br />
wundwruerstand mw, speak for uus, ii the rather tattered sentence,<br />
an Australian Ababssadr, osarxwyxt h hi. both ways an lanense<br />
aummt of reprseanttimal authoritty and if I may say so to YOU,<br />
ir, a very pat ofe espet, and what in evon mor importaft<br />
thma rospeot, affcttone Now, iAdicated toyou at the beginiing that<br />
Atbr Ca3vell and I having oasposed our differenes over the<br />
dinjor adjomRment, leoaUed that this is. a bi-partisan ocassion,<br />
and, Arthur, I knav that with your usual facility and talent,<br />
you Vill support me before I propose the toast. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
