<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5014</transcript-id>
    <title>COMMENTS TO PRESS IN ALICE SPRINGS</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/04/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005014.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS OFFICE TRANSCRIPT 6ARL17<br />
COMMENTS TO PRESS IN ALICE SPRINGS<br />
This is a strike that very directly involves State legislation<br />
and it is a strike, or a dispute therefore, between the<br />
truckies and in varying degrees different State Governments.<br />
It is a dispute in particular between the truckies that<br />
industry and New South Wales and as much as anything I think<br />
because of the immediate and knee-jerk reaction that Mr. Wran<br />
had in rushing legislation through the State Parliament when<br />
the normal thing in a beginning of a dispute is to see if you<br />
can talk to the people involved. The legislation has been passed.<br />
I don't know if it has been proclaimed but my understanding is<br />
that Mr. Wran has no intention of using it. The States have<br />
been trying to unload the dispute onto the Commonwealth, but it<br />
is not a Commonwealth dispute, it is a State dispute and involves<br />
State legislation and a State road tax. One Premier has put<br />
to me the view that the Commonwealth petrol tax should be<br />
increased for everyone so that the States could be recouped<br />
whatever they would lose for taking the road tax off the truckies.<br />
Well that is just not on and let me state that in complete, firm<br />
and absolute terms that it is just not on, it is not going to<br />
happen. We are not going to put taxes up on everyone to enable<br />
the States to take a tax off one particular group of road users.<br />
it would be inequitable and unfair and in any case, the States<br />
in recent times have had a good deal more funds available to<br />
them. All the States, over recent years, have decided to reduce<br />
many different taxes of different kinds. This has been their<br />
priority not to reduce or to get rid of this particular tax.<br />
Now having said that, let me also let me condemn in the strongest<br />
terms the action of the interstate truck drivers. What they are<br />
seeking to do by industrial muscle is wrong. It is destructive.<br />
It is harming people just as much as the TWU dispute was a few<br />
days ago, which was denying milk and food and bread to hospitals<br />
and families in the capital cities. The truckies, no matter what<br />
the merits of their claim and I say this in relation to all<br />
disputes where industrial muscle is used ought to get back to<br />
their jobs, get around the negotiating tables with the States and<br />
seek a proper resolution of the matter through consultation; if<br />
necessary, getting the States and themselves jointly to agree to<br />
an arbitrator. But that is their business the State's business<br />
and theirs. If they could jointly agree to somebody arbitrating<br />
the dispute, well then let that happen and let that be determined.<br />
That wuould be for them to decide jointly with the States. But<br />
the action of disruption is wrong and on behalf of the Commonwealth<br />
I certainly condemn it, in just as strong terms we condemn the<br />
action of the more traditional trade unions that cause a great<br />
deal of inconvenience and difficulty. I would like to reinforce<br />
one other point. we've said some reasonably firm things in recent<br />
days my colleague Mr. Street has about industrial disruption<br />
and at no point are we seeking to deny the right of people, or of trade<br />
unions to have thei~ r cases heard before the Arbitration tribunals.<br />
./ 2<br />
6 APRIL 1979 </p>
<p>-2<br />
What we are saying that we are going to take much firmer action<br />
than we have in the past against people who don't allow those<br />
tribunals to work in the normal, unfettered manner, who, almost<br />
before they make their case before the Tribunal decide to introduce<br />
work bans and limitations, go-slow, all the rest, with consequential<br />
harm for large sections of the Australian community.<br />
There has,' over many years, been a tradition of accepting arbitration<br />
of accepting the umpire' s verdict. Now if that system, which<br />
has worked fairly and reasonably, is to operate successfully, it<br />
ought to work without undue pressure from any of the participants<br />
before it. A week ago it was the Transport workers' Union. We<br />
said what we had to say about that. The moves for deregistration of<br />
that union were proceeding when they called the strike and their<br />
bans off. This case is not within the Federal jurisdiction,<br />
it is a matter for the States, but the same principles apply in<br />
this disruption which is doing significant harm, especially to<br />
people in the city of Sydney and get to talking about it with the<br />
States and see if the problems can't be resolved.<br />
Let me also say that I had some discussions with the Solicitor-<br />
General this morning to see if a certain view that I had had<br />
validity. But legal opinions always need to be verified<br />
and checked, but it was his view that it is within the capacity of<br />
the States to come to agreement amongst themselves on . uniform<br />
legislation or licensing charge for this particular industry.<br />
The funds would have to be related to road use and to road damage,<br />
as the present road maintenance charge now is. But the road<br />
maintenance charge is difficult to collect, as we know, and it can<br />
be avoided. That worries people. A uniform registration or<br />
licensing fee related to road use agreed upon by the States is<br />
probably capable of implementation by the States, but they would<br />
have to agree. This particular problem of road tax and the<br />
attitude of the truckies has been known to the States for years<br />
and they haven't been willing to get together and to seek, jointly,<br />
a resolution of it. The only way they want it resolved is for<br />
the Commonwealth to put up a tax so they could take a tax off<br />
We don't believe that that is a fair or a reasonable proposition.<br />
They have a capacity to act themselves. They've shown that they've<br />
had more funds by the fact that they have reduced many taxes over<br />
recent years. If it has been within their-priorities -they could -have<br />
reduced this tax if they wanted to. But I am not suggesting that.<br />
I am suggesting that there are other alternatives which would be<br />
much simpler to administer. / 3 </p>
<p>-3<br />
OFF THE RECORD<br />
It is my understanding that the truckies have significant other<br />
complaints as well, but they really seem to have been focussed<br />
on the road tax the road maintenance tax. They complain about<br />
the competition they get from State railways, the competition<br />
they get from some of the big transport firms. They complain<br />
also about not being able to get adequate or realistic freight<br />
rates from the people who do give them work. I think that in<br />
part is one of the results of the sort of competition within the<br />
industry. We know it is very easy to get finance; easy sometimes<br />
to get hold of a rig and if people get into difficulties they<br />
get a bit inclined to cut the rates to get work just to keep<br />
going. I can understand all the difficulties that that involves.<br />
But it does mean that the problems of the industry, I think, are<br />
many-sided. I think thiat matters are focussing on the road tax which<br />
is in fact just one element of an industry which has many more<br />
problems that that particular State charge. But again, they<br />
are problems that, if they are prepared to sit down with State<br />
Governments that has the regulatory capacity and all the rest for<br />
these things, could have been tackled long before this.<br />
ON THE RECORD<br />
Question Have you made a formal suggestion to the States that they should<br />
adopt that course of yours...<br />
Prime Minister<br />
I have spoken to one Premier about it and if, during the course<br />
of the day, I am speaking to others, I will put it to them.<br />
Question Would the Government be prepared to use its powers to unclog the<br />
roads if this thing isn't resolved within the next few days?<br />
Prime Minister:-<br />
The States are always telling us they have sovereign powers. This<br />
is a dispute that is within their province. I think it is<br />
certainly exacerbated in N. S. W. where it is worst, by Mr. Wran's<br />
legislation knee-jerk reaction to a certain situation and I would<br />
have believed that instead of trying to rush that legislation<br />
through Parliament, the matter had been handled calmly from that<br />
point, that it could well have been possible to get the trucks<br />
as they drdw up along the main highways-' and let people police<br />
drivers drive them off down some side road. But it wasn't handled<br />
that way and Mr. Wran will have to try and untangle that part of<br />
the mess for himself.<br />
Question You said in regard to the Government's -your Government's own<br />
position that the Government was prepared to take much firmer<br />
action against unions which take disruptive action to settle<br />
disputes. Can you say what that much firmer action... ./ 4 </p>
<p>-4<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Yes I can. It will be an amplification and repetition of<br />
what Mr. Street said last week. I think you will know that over<br />
a long period, when there are bans or work limitations in place<br />
there has been a tendency to go to the Arbitration Commission and<br />
the arbitral tribunals, to talk about it before any kind of action<br />
is taken as a consequence of the industrial bans. Now so far<br />
as Government employment is concerned, and statutory organisations<br />
all of whom have been contacted or are in the process of being<br />
contacted when there are bans or limitations of any kind<br />
imposed to reinforce a claim before one of the arbitral tribunals<br />
the policy of stand-downs, suspensions, no-work, no-pay will be<br />
applied forthwith from the outset.. It is fair enough to tell<br />
people that so they won't be caught unawares as a result of<br />
the change in policy. That is applying on the Postal Commis iion<br />
over recent days, as you know. That particularly of course applies<br />
in the Commonwealth's area of employment. Where suspension or<br />
stand-down clauses are not in an award when this kind of industrial<br />
action occurs and then action will be taken to get them into. the<br />
awards as soon as we can through the Tribunals. For unions with<br />
a long record of industrial di-* spute such as the Transport Workers<br />
Union we will be much more ready to go down the path of<br />
deregistration. Mr. Street has said if that c-ase is once lodged<br />
in the Federal Court it will be pursued to the end. Work in<br />
getting that case ready has not ceased. It is being continued.<br />
A final judgement as to whether or not that procedure will be<br />
taken when the material is fully ready to the satisfaction of<br />
the Crown Solicitor. The work in getting the case prepared for<br />
the Federal Court is quite substantial. A good deal of evidence<br />
has to be collected in a formal way. As we know, that dispute<br />
at the moment the Transport Workers' Union appears to be off.<br />
In addition to this, as has been shown in the paint<br />
dispute involving the motor industry, we have indicated that<br />
we are prepared to reinforce the capacity of private industry to<br />
argue by indicating that a PJT inquiry would be held on the<br />
company's or industry's pricing policies if they themselves<br />
unreasonably concede claims outside the Arbitration Commission<br />
guidelines. As further reinforcement of that, so that other<br />
industries do not have to penalised as a result, we will consider<br />
giving permission to import under by-law conditions so that<br />
essential supplies for other industries won't run short; the<br />
paint industry is a classic example of that. There we have told<br />
either the paint manufacturers or the motor firms themselves that<br />
if they wish to import they may. I think priority ought to be<br />
giLven to the paint manufacturers who would otherwise tend to<br />
lose business. But if they were unwilling to import, we would allow<br />
the motor firms to do so, if they wanted to. The principles involved<br />
in that will also be applied as appropriate in other areas.<br />
This indicates a significant firming of our immediate reaction to<br />
disputes involving cases that ought to be before the wage tribunals.<br />
Let me again emphasise, it is not saying that people cannot go<br />
to arbitration. It is not saying that people cannot have their<br />
cases heard. It is saying that we will do everything we possibly<br />
can to see that those cases are heard before the Arbitration<br />
tribunals, free of industrial pressure. If there is industrial<br />
pressure which involves dislocation to other people in the community,<br />
there will be consequences for the people who apply it. </p>
<p>Question I think you mentioned earlier that you had put a viewpoint about<br />
solving the truckies dispute to the Solicitor-General. Can you<br />
outline that viewpoint.<br />
Prime Minister<br />
I indicated what that was. I was saying that the advice I was<br />
given had reinforced a view that I had had that if the States<br />
agree they can establish a system of uniform licensing or<br />
registration charge, so long as it is related to road use and<br />
that that would be in conformity with High Court decisions under<br />
Section 92 of the Constitution. But if the States are not prepared to<br />
agree it will be very difficult because a State that doesn't act<br />
would leave it wide open. An agreement with five States wouldn't<br />
work. It would have to be an agreement with all States.<br />
Question Would the Federal Government be prepared to pick up the tab if<br />
all States abolished road tax?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
No. I have said we are not. No, because the States have made<br />
their own priorities, own decisions about their priorities for<br />
reducing taxes and this has not been one of them. Go through<br />
every State Budget for the last three years. There have been<br />
tax reductions in them or promised and therefore it has not<br />
been in the States priorities. If they want it in their priorities<br />
they can have it.<br />
What I am also saying is that on the advice that I had confirmed<br />
it was a verbal advice and obviously not formal in that sense<br />
from the Solicitor General that there are simple alternatives<br />
if only the States will get together and work out a scheme which<br />
would enable them to collect a licensing charge or a registration<br />
charge uniformly.<br />
Question: Would you be optimistic that such a move like that could actually<br />
come about.<br />
Prime Minister-<br />
Well, why shouldn't the States agree? -They say this is a problem.<br />
If it is a problem, let them act on it.<br />
Question: Do you believe that that would solve the dispute? / 6 </p>
<p>6<br />
Prime Minister<br />
No I'd also said that I think what is going to solve this<br />
dispute is people getting together and working out some approach<br />
to the future and consultations between the transport operators<br />
and the States. That will have to take place. But I have also<br />
said that I think the problems of this industry are much deeper<br />
than that road maintenance charge not being able to charge<br />
high enough freights because of the intense competition; maybe<br />
being able to buy rigs too easily; maybe also unfair competition<br />
through some of the rail systems.<br />
Question: What's the actual problem if five States agreed and the sixth<br />
didn't? Why would not...<br />
Prime Minister<br />
I think they would all register or license themselves in the<br />
sixth State. You've got to have them all agreed so there isn't,<br />
in a sense, a tax haven which enables them to get out.<br />
Question Could I clarify the Government's position on the TWU. Are you<br />
saying, sir, that if there is any further industrial action by<br />
the TWU,' the Government has the papers prepared and will proceed<br />
forthwith with deregistration proceedings?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
The papers are not fully prepared at the moment. The latest<br />
advice I had was that their preparation should be finished early<br />
this coming week. What we've said to this point is that we will<br />
make a decision when those papers are prepared as to whether they<br />
ought to be lodged with the Federal Court or not. Quite clearly<br />
that depzends upon the industrial circumstances in relation to<br />
that Union at the time when those papers are available to us.<br />
Question: But you will hang on to them in case the unions go on strike<br />
in a week's time?<br />
Prime Minister-<br />
We've also made the decision that in relation to that Union, that<br />
the documents will be kept up-dated and the reasons for that are<br />
plain because that Union has been involved in very severe<br />
industrial disputation and inconvenience to many different sections<br />
of the Australia community over a long and prolonged period of time.<br />
Question The truckies have said they would like to talk to you or Mr. Nixon.<br />
Would you be prepared to agree to that?<br />
Prime Minister-<br />
This is a dispute I did see a deputation from the truckies some </p>
<p>7<br />
Prime Minister ( continued)<br />
months ago. This is a dispute ( inaudible) at the present time.<br />
That's where the immediate situation has to be solved.<br />
Against the background of everything I have said to you, I think<br />
we need to understand that the Commonwealth is very firm here<br />
no matter what the merits of the case, it is not going to<br />
be negotiated under threat. We have no intention of doing so.<br />
I don't want State Governments to be in a position of conceding<br />
under threat to a particular section of the community<br />
I am saying there are problems in the industry<br />
but they basically stem from State legislation of one kind or<br />
another. It has been within the capacity of States, over a period<br />
of years, to do something about it and modify it. It has been<br />
within their capacity over recent times to modify the actual<br />
charges if it had been one of their State priorities, but it has<br />
not been one of their State priorities. Now that the States are<br />
in a degree of difficulty in relation to it, they tend to come to<br />
us and say ' please get us out of our problems'. It's a far cry,<br />
isn't it, from the bold days when States say they are sovereign.<br />
If they are sovereign, let them demonstrate that they have a<br />
capacity to solve one of their own problems.<br />
Question In relation to Ayers Rock, sir?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
I don't think there is anything I can say about that. I will<br />
be talking to the Chief Minister shortly and later I will let you know.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
