<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6269</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE, ORIENTAL HOTEL, BANGKOK, AFTER MEETING WITH THAI PRIME MINISTER AND FOREIGN MINISTER, 21 NOVEMBER 1983</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/11/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006269.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
ATA LI 1<br />
PRIME MINOSTER<br />
E. 0. E. Proof Only<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE, ORIENTAL HOTEL, BANGKOK,<br />
AFTER MEETING WITH THAI PRIME MINISTER AND FOREIGN MINISTER,<br />
.21 NOVEMBER 1983<br />
PM: Well Bill and I have had extremely useful and constructive<br />
morning with the Prime Minister and the Foreign<br />
Minister together and then lunch with the Foreign Minister.<br />
We could not,' I believe, be more satisfied than we are with<br />
the talks that have taken place. May I just go through<br />
generally the country that we've covered and then if you'd<br />
like to ask us any questions.<br />
I repeated the Australian Government's condemnation of the<br />
invasion by Vietnam of Cambodia and the continued occupation of<br />
that country. What I emphasised is repeated because what Bill<br />
Hayden and I will have to say here, of course we've said before.<br />
I added again in the same sense that there should be a phased<br />
withdrawal leading to total withdrawal of the Vietnamese<br />
troops from Cambodia and that there should be an act of<br />
self-determination for the Cambodian people and that conditions<br />
should be established which would permit the return of displaced<br />
Cambodians to their country and for normnal relations to be<br />
resumed between Vietnam, China, the ASEAN countries and the<br />
international community at large.<br />
I indicated that Australia attached importance to ending<br />
Vietnam's present political and economic isolation and growing<br />
reliance on the Soviet Union which was entrenching the great<br />
power rivalry in the region.<br />
I indicated that Australia intended offering disaster relief<br />
assistance to Vietnam, but that we had taken no decision in<br />
practical terms to resume development assistance to Vietnam.<br />
I pointed out that while Australian aid was continuing to be<br />
directed to displaced Cambodians in the Thai/ Cambodia border<br />
area, I indicated that we continued to consider that meeting<br />
the humanitarian aid needs of the internees and others inside<br />
Cambodia was necessary.<br />
We emphasised as strongly as we Could the great concern of<br />
Australia at any nossible return of p: ower of the regime as<br />
brutal as the Khmer Rouge. 12. </p>
<p>As the Prime Minister of Thailand, General Prem, and I<br />
agreed, our discussions had been very useful in clarifying<br />
misunderstandings which had recently arisen. We both agreed<br />
that the Cambodian situation carried disturbing implications<br />
for peaceful relations among all the countries of the SE ASian<br />
region. On the main issues of principle that is the withdrawal of<br />
Vietnamese troops and the need for acts of self-determination<br />
by the Cambodian people there was fundamental agreement<br />
between Australia and the Thai position.<br />
General Prem and myself, while noting that there was some<br />
room for difference of emphasis and approach in the manner in<br />
which each of our countries sought to give effect to the agreed<br />
principles, we each accepted that our countries each of themwas<br />
directing its efforts towards objectives shared by the<br />
other and we agreed that Australia ' n and Thailand intended to<br />
work in the closest contact, with communication on these<br />
matters of mutual interest in the future.<br />
Now, that covers the central features of our discussion i n<br />
regard to the Cambodian/ ASEAN position. We, of course, have<br />
quite detailed discussions on a number of bilateral issues<br />
concerning Australia and Thailand and I would indicate that<br />
just following the luncheon Bill Hayden and Foreign Minister<br />
Siddhi have just co-signed the geiieral co-financing agreement<br />
covering Thailand and World Bank Australia development<br />
co-operation which I think is a fairly clear indication of<br />
the position that has been reached as a result of our<br />
discussions today.<br />
JOURNALIST: Was there any discussions about talks at the<br />
officials level between Australia and the ASEAN nations and<br />
did we get any indication that these might be re-commenced<br />
after the suspension?<br />
PM: Well, of course, we are talking with one leader of ASEAN<br />
who will ( inaudible) in January and, as I said before,<br />
I haven't felt'that there will not be a resumption of the<br />
dialogue between ASEAN and Australia and I am confident that<br />
that will take place.<br />
JOURNALIST: Did we get any positive sign or negative sign<br />
today, one way or the other? I<br />
PM: It's not for Bill or I to ask of Thailand or for Thailand<br />
to be able to act on behalf of the rest of the ASEAN cou-ntries.<br />
That is not the way it operates. We have conveyed our position<br />
to Thailand. They understand it and they will be having<br />
their discussions. I think I can say on behalf of Bill and<br />
myself that we feel relaxed about what the outcome will be.<br />
/ 3 </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Sir, the matter was not discussed at all?<br />
PM: It's not appropriate. We didn't come here to plead with<br />
Thailand to act as an emissary for us. It's not their<br />
function and it's not our intention. We came here as<br />
previously scheduled and obviously took the opportunity of<br />
clarifying our position on these matters. Now, that's<br />
been done. in my judgement no need for any concern<br />
about the futdre course of relations between Australia and<br />
ASEAN. JOURNALIST: Could I just clarify the situation on aid to<br />
Vietnam we have already been giving some disaster relief<br />
have we or not, or is that a new position.<br />
PM: There has been some relief in the past, but what we're<br />
faced with now is Bill might be able to give more detail<br />
on this, but I understand that in this year there has been<br />
a concentrated impact of disaster in the area and through<br />
the United Nations agency there has been a request to<br />
member nations for assistance and we will, as we have<br />
indicated, respond to that.<br />
JOURNALIST: Would that be the first aid we have put into<br />
Vietnam at all?<br />
HAYDEN: It's the first we've put into Vietnam, but I'm not<br />
real sure. I think disaster aid probably went in before.<br />
However we discussed with the ASEAN countries before we made<br />
this announcement today and there was no opposition to the<br />
proposition not necessarily that that would stop us, but<br />
there is none. It's million and it covers a substantial<br />
quantity of rice I think over a thousand tons of rice.<br />
Richard Brinowski is our man in Hanoi. Do you recall<br />
what the dimensions of the disaster are the number of lives<br />
lost I think about 300 was it.<br />
BRINOWSKI: Loss of lives is nearly 500, plus a lot more<br />
missing. That's the figure that has been confirmed from<br />
various sources.<br />
HAYDEN: Other figures that you got from that. They may be<br />
interested.<br />
BRINOWSKI: Many thousands of homes have been destroyed . The<br />
main damage is in the central provinces schools, fishing<br />
boats. It's very extensive.<br />
JOURNALIST: Are the ASEAN nations themselves putting in any<br />
aid? HAYDEN: Wouldn't know.<br />
JOURNALIST: When was this discussed with the ASEAN nations?<br />
HAYDEN: Two or three weeks ago we started discussing it. / 4 </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Did they put any qualification on Australia<br />
putting any aid in at all?<br />
PM: On disaster aid, no. They've always said that disaster<br />
ai1d that is in the wake of a natural disaster, was<br />
something that they could never quibble about.<br />
JOURNALIST: After we enunciated our position on general<br />
aid to Vietnaru development aid was that taken up at all<br />
by the Thai leaders?<br />
PM: We expressed our position again which was not something<br />
w; hich we just said here. Both of us had made that position<br />
clear before. That was understood by the Thai leaders.<br />
There was nothing which was new about that. It was an<br />
affirmation of what we had said. They were interested and<br />
I think pleased to hear the exposition from us.<br />
JOURNALIST: Does this disaster aid go to you said it came<br />
as a response to a request from the UN agency?<br />
HAYDEN: Disaster relief organisation.<br />
JOURNALIST: It's not bilateral?<br />
HAYDEN: That's four times I've said that.<br />
JOURNALIST: Did the Malaysian proposal come up at all over<br />
lunch. PM: No.<br />
JOURNALIST: Has it been discussed at all?<br />
PM: No, you haven't had anything?<br />
HAYDEN: No.<br />
JOURNALIST: On another note, Prime Minister, I was wondering<br />
if you could tell me your reaction to a story that's<br />
floating out of Delhi today that Sonny Ramphal steps down,<br />
Malcolm Fraser will step in.<br />
PM: Well, I found myself a little surprised. I would have<br />
thought if there was any substance in it we may have heard<br />
something before this.<br />
JOURNALIST: I understand that Alan Griffith, Labor Member<br />
in Victoria is writing to both yourself and the Foreign Minister<br />
about this matter saying that it shouldn't<br />
PM: Well, we'll be waiting with baited breath for the letter.<br />
JOURNALIST: If it became a serious proposition would you<br />
support Mr. Fraser in seeking selection for the Secretary-<br />
Generalship? PM: ( inaudible) this chase of hypotheses is no wonder<br />
you're all looking so fi t, o0U' rc' alIways chasini-hypotheses. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: It was one of our esteemed colleagues, Mr. Lombard.<br />
PM: Oh.<br />
JOURNALIST: Was there any discussion at all with the Thais<br />
about what Mr. Dhanabalan has been saying or any discussion<br />
about the Singaporean view expressed over the last couple of<br />
weeks? PM: We didn't need to go to individuals. We explained our<br />
position in general terms. We, of course, recognised that<br />
there had been some problems created by statements of recent<br />
times, but the way to deal with that is not to go in an<br />
ad sense but to deal with the issues and that is what we<br />
did. JOURNALIST: Was there any discussion about possible Australian<br />
involvement in Kampuchea with the event of a Vietnamese<br />
withdrawal? PM: No, I've answered that question. That didn't the matter<br />
wasn't raised by the Thai leaders and obviously there wasn't<br />
any point in us going to it. The thing is to talk about<br />
the present situation and try and get to an improvement from<br />
where we are. If that has some possible substance in it, it<br />
will emerge at the appropriate time.<br />
JOURNALIST: Didn't the Malaysian Foreign Minister and Prime<br />
Minister put this in terms of the present situation in terms<br />
of one way that the Vietnamese might be induced to look at<br />
withdrawal terms?<br />
PM: reports that we saw in the paper, but what I've been<br />
trying to say to you for some time, the right way to conduct<br />
your affairs in regard to some domestic political situation<br />
or international, you don't hear something said by someone<br />
that is maybe down the track and then go down there after<br />
that. If you want to guarantee inefficiency in conducting<br />
your affairs, that is it. You deal with. the position as it is<br />
and if that develops into something that has been hypothecated<br />
and becomes relevant, then you address yourself to it.<br />
Otherwise it's a guarantee of inefficiency and potential<br />
insanity.<br />
JOURNALIST: When we enunciated our position, did we<br />
specifically indicate our reservations about the coalition<br />
because of the participation and the prominent military role<br />
in it of the Khmer Rough<br />
PM: Yes, we said here what we have said both of us in<br />
Australia that we praise the integrity and the commitment<br />
of Son Sann and Prince Sihanouk and their forces and reiterated<br />
our for Po1 Pot the coalition and in that respect 1<br />
don't think there is any significant divergence betwen ourselves<br />
and the Thais. / 6 </p>
<p>6.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr. Ghazali said in his interview with Michael<br />
Richardson that ASEAN Foreign Ministers in January<br />
would be looking at a series of options regarding the<br />
withdrawal of Vietnam from Kampuchea. Did the Thais give<br />
you any indication of the sorts of options that the ASEAN<br />
Foreign Ministers would be looking at?<br />
PM: No, they have a working party looking at these sorts<br />
of things. We have no indication of what specifics they<br />
may be coming up with. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
