<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7471</transcript-id>
    <title>PARTIAL TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE, SHERATON HOTEL, DARWIN 29 JANUARY 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/01/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007471.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
) 4USTA L A(<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE, SHERATON HOTEL, DARWIN<br />
29 JANUARY 1989<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST; t~ o you believe that President Mitterand GoQ<br />
defence contract do you believe that that should have been<br />
kept to the level of economics and business rather than politics?<br />
PM: Well we can't change the course of history, can we. I<br />
think if you look at the sorts of events, political influence<br />
is often brought to bear. I know that since I've been<br />
Prime Minister I've always been prepared to use my influence<br />
on behalf of Australian contacts where we are satisfied,<br />
and we always are, about the quality of the Australian<br />
tenders. Where an Australian tender for an overseas<br />
contract looks as though he should get it, then they'll<br />
have my support. We're not unique in that respect. In<br />
fact, without going into the details, not long after I'd<br />
been Prime Minister, in a country in our region it got<br />
down to the French and the Australians and I happened<br />
to be visiting the country and I put in a plug for Australia.<br />
The French were there just about signing a contract and<br />
we were able to a very substantial contract for Australia.<br />
And may I say the Australian contractor did the job extremely<br />
well and the nation very pleased they did what they<br />
did. Now that's the way of life. So I'll be in there<br />
fighting for the Australians when I'm in India, and they<br />
deserve to win.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, what will be the highlight<br />
of your trip to South Korea?<br />
PM: I think it's really a consolidation of the visit<br />
of President Roh last year and what impressed me was then<br />
the quite dramatic new approach of the new President in<br />
terms both with the relationship of the Republic of Korea<br />
with the North. and with the rest of the world. I want<br />
to follow up on my discussions with him the implications<br />
of that both for Korea itself and for the region. I think<br />
it's one of the more significant things that's been happening<br />
in recent times in our region. So I think the discussions<br />
on that issue will probably be as important as anything<br />
else. Of course we agreed during his visit to Australia<br />
last year to accelerate the processes of cooperation between<br />
our two countries in a number of areas beyond purely the<br />
trading and economic relationship and we will be reviewing<br />
just how well the mechanisms are going for establishing </p>
<p>those things upon which we agreed, for instance in the<br />
area of the Cultural Commission for accelerating exchange<br />
there across a whole range of areas of activities and<br />
in the establishment of the Business Forum. We agreed<br />
then that we'd meet as soon as possible this year to make<br />
clear to bodies and individuals in our two countries the<br />
extent of our commitment to these processes. The Korean<br />
economy is growing strongly, our trade is increasing,<br />
I want to ensure that Australia gets the benefit as rapidly<br />
as possible of that growth, and in turn that we can make<br />
some contribution to the development of Korea.<br />
JOURNALIST: Is Australia's trade performance with the<br />
four countries you're visiting as good as it ought to<br />
be given the levels of growth they are experiencing?<br />
PM: Well it's improving and the reason for the visit<br />
is to try and increase the rate of Australian involvement.<br />
I am never satisfied with where you are, I always think<br />
you can do better. It's these sorts of areas where I<br />
think that personal relationships are oportant and I do<br />
have the good fortune of alrea dy good relations with the<br />
President of Korea and the Prime Minister of India. This<br />
will be the first meeting for me with the new Prime Minister<br />
of Thailand and of course with Pakistan. So I hope that<br />
out of these personal contacts~ with the renewal in the<br />
former two countries that I mentioned and the opening<br />
up of personal relations in Thailand and Pakistan, that<br />
we will be able, as I say, to get the greatest benefit<br />
of the fact of that economic growth because they do have<br />
rates of growth which speaking of them generally are<br />
more than twice the rate of the OECD average for instance.<br />
So it is essential for Australia where you' re in a region<br />
of rapid growth as I've said so often) ck'cd you've heard<br />
me say it -we want to be in there and get as much benefit<br />
from it and make as much contribution to it as we can.<br />
JOURNALIST: What are the sorts of products<br />
PM: It comes really into two categories. There is our<br />
traditional export base and we are competitive producers<br />
and exporters of raw materials. We have iron ore, coal<br />
as well as in the aluminum area, and our agricultural<br />
products. Now those basic and traditional quantities<br />
are available from Australia in terms of reliable supply<br />
and competitive prices. We are the best suppliers in<br />
the world in those areas. So I want to stress that to<br />
our friends where we go. But, the second area where I<br />
will be particularly stressing the relevance and the competitive<br />
nature of Australia is in the areas of telecommunications.<br />
the telecommunications industry, the construction of<br />
stations in the power generation industry, like we have btiit </p>
<p>now coal-fired power stations in a way which gives us<br />
some expertise which is second to none in the world.<br />
On a whole range of infrastructure developments, roads,<br />
ports, those sorts of things, Australia is becoming an<br />
increasingly capable, sophisticated, competitive supplier<br />
of the infrastructure, developing infrastructure needs<br />
of these countries.<br />
JOURNALIST: Are we having the Thais are making on<br />
cracking down on the drug problem out in the triangle<br />
PM: We have close cooperation with them. As you know<br />
we have people working in cooperation with them. This<br />
is one of the areas I'll be discussing with our friends<br />
Sin Thailand to review the cooperative program that we<br />
work on together and of course if they have any suggestions<br />
to make to me as to how there may be areas for improvement,<br />
then I'll certainly be receptive to that.<br />
JOURNALIST: On a domestic level I understand Justice<br />
Muirhead delivered the first four case reports to the<br />
Government last Wednesday. Do you see any reason why<br />
those reports can't be released immediately?<br />
PM: I need to discuss that with the Minister. I mean,<br />
I just don't make a unilateral decision on that. I haven't<br />
had an opportunity of talking with Mr Hand yet.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you agree with Justice Muirhead that they<br />
should be released individually case by case as they're<br />
finished? PM: I haven't specifically discussed that with Mr Hand.<br />
My view would be that if the Minister was of that view<br />
then I'd be satisfied with that. But these are matters<br />
for the Minister concerned to have an involvement in.<br />
I don't impose my generally speaking at any rate I<br />
don't impose my will on Ministers. There's some times<br />
perhaps where that is necessary. But you know that that's<br />
the way I run the Government. Mr Hand is the Minister<br />
there. If he had a contrary view to that of the Royal<br />
Commissioner I'd want to hear it. But if he didn't I'd<br />
certainly say yes.<br />
JOURNALIST: So we could expect them to be out before<br />
the West Australian election?<br />
PM: Could be. I don't know. You really need to talk<br />
to Mr Hand about that. I'm leaving today and Mr Bowen<br />
will be acting Prime Minister in my absence. Mr Hand<br />
will have a view about it.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you have any progress on the proposed<br />
Aboriginal treaty?<br />
PM: I'll say this. In the sense that we still have commitment<br />
to the concept and just last Sunday week I had<br />
I I </p>
<p>further discussions in Melbourne with M~ r Hand about it.<br />
There are two sides to it as you'll appreciate. There<br />
is the continuing process of consultation within the Aboriginal<br />
community in this country and that is a long detailed<br />
process. We are not going to rush that. We want to get<br />
the full sense of appreciation from the Aboriginal people<br />
as to what the issues are in their mind to be dealt with t<br />
such a treaty, a compact. We are also addressing the<br />
point of how within the non-Aboriginal community there<br />
should be developed so that the people of Australia<br />
as a whole are going to have the opportunity of being<br />
informed about the issues, the concepts. This is particularly<br />
important in view of the fact that the Opposition has<br />
chosen so maliciously and dishonestly to misrepresent<br />
what is involved in this concept. So I've made it clear<br />
th at it would be impossible to achieve this position<br />
in the life of this Parliament. But I've always had the<br />
view that if that were not possible, if the processes<br />
that I'm talking about had not been satisfactorily completed,<br />
then there wasn't going to be any artificial date in my<br />
mind that it had to be done in the life of this Parliament.<br />
What's important is that at the end of the processes within<br />
the Aboriginal community and in the non-Aboriginal community<br />
that there is understanding and acceptance of the concept<br />
because there is no doubt in my mind that this and future<br />
generations of Australians are going to be better off.<br />
They're going to be better able to live in good conscience<br />
if we've done this thing. It's got such historical<br />
importance. It's not something that should be rushed<br />
with an artificial date.<br />
JOURNALIST: media should get off Pat Cash's back?<br />
PM: I hink that it is not really appropriate for me<br />
toMe: Itin who should get off Pat Cash's back but I<br />
think he has a few people on his back.<br />
JOURNALIST: What is your decision on Australia's involvement<br />
in the international peacekeeping force in Cambodia if<br />
that situation should arise?<br />
PM: We have made it quite clear over a number of years<br />
that Australia is prepared to play its part in finding<br />
a peaceful resolution to that continual tragedy in Cambodia.<br />
And if in the now much more encouraging scene that we<br />
see there where I think we have more grounds for optimism<br />
than we have had at any stage, it would be suggested<br />
that there would be some international force to supervise<br />
the situation following the withdrawal of the Vietnamese<br />
forces both in security terms and in intermediate<br />
sense, and perhaps in election supervision. If it were<br />
suggested that Australia could play a role in that, of<br />
course consistent with our whole in this matter, we<br />
would be prepared favourably to consider that. </p>
<p>PM: ( cont) But we are not there in this or any other<br />
area in the world trying to impose Australia but we do<br />
have legitimate interests, historical concerns, and we<br />
will be prepared to play a part in getting, finally, a<br />
resolution of what has been such a long continual tragedy<br />
for the people of Cambodia.<br />
ends<br />
0 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
