<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7068</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/12/1986</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007068.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER j<br />
FOR MEDIA 23 DECEMBER 1986<br />
The Commonwealth Government has recently held discussions<br />
with the South Australian Government and the Australian<br />
Cricket Board on a proposal to associate cricket with the<br />
Australian Institute of Sport, through the establishment of<br />
an AIS cricket academy in Adelaide.<br />
I am pleased to announce today that the Government will<br />
provide $ 300,000 in a full financial year to bring the<br />
arrangements with the South Australian Government, the ACB<br />
and the AIS to fruition. Providing all the necessary<br />
planning can be done by those bodies, I would expect these<br />
funds to be available in 1987-88.<br />
It is very appropriate that the AIS cricket academy should<br />
be established in South Australia, home of Sir Donald<br />
Bradman, our greatest cricketer, and of many other great<br />
Australian players. The Adelaide complex will provide the<br />
environment and facilities necessary to nurture and develop<br />
our outstanding young cricketing talent of the future.<br />
The Government's contribution to the project will complement<br />
the existing range of measures we provide to assist cricket.<br />
In the current financial year, an allocation of $ 140,000 was<br />
provided to the Australian Cricket Board by the Australian<br />
Sports Commission for coaching, international competition<br />
for juniors, administration, and development projects,<br />
especially Kanga cricket.<br />
I </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
