<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>500</transcript-id>
    <title>P.M.NO 36/1962  PRIME MINISTER CONFENCE STATEMENTS BY THE PRIME MINISTER THR RT. HON. A.G MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/04/1962</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000500.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
P* fm. ITe0 3, ' 10 2<br />
PRI I MINIS3::. E' CO. Tl., E-JN CE<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, the t. Hon. Menzie.<br />
The Prime Minister of the United Kingdom, after<br />
consulting all Commonwealth Prime Ministers, has convened a<br />
meeting of Commonwealth Prime Ministers in London on<br />
September to give further consideration to proposals which are<br />
expected by that time to have been formulated concerning<br />
Britain's application to join the Common Market.<br />
This is clearly not an ideal date from the point of view<br />
of Australia as the Budget Session will be in progress. But since<br />
it suited a majority we felt that we could not maintain an<br />
objection. I have no doubt that adequate Parliamentary<br />
arrangements can be made for our effective representation. I<br />
will discuss this with Mr. McEwen who has just completed a series<br />
of important discussions in Britain and Europe and will, on his<br />
return be reporting to the Gov-rnment on them.<br />
The essential thing about the Prime Ministers'<br />
Conference on the Common lMiarket is that it should not occur after<br />
minds have been made up but should present the Prime Ministers<br />
with an effective opportunity of influencing the ultimate<br />
decision. We have, of course, been most accive in this matter and<br />
will continue to be so in the period between now and September.<br />
From the time the British entry into the Common Market was first<br />
mooted, we have been seized with the need to secure an effective<br />
voice for Australia in all the discussions involving our vital<br />
trade interests. A special Committee of Cabinet has had<br />
developments constantly under review and we have made rereatod<br />
roprosentations to Britain and to the Six so that they might be<br />
fully cognisant of the nature and extent of Australian interests,<br />
and of our proposals for protecting those interests. At the<br />
outset we asked Britain to seek rith the Six an opportunity for<br />
us to state our case directly when matters of concern to us are<br />
involved. Since the initial discussions were opened with Mr.<br />
Duncan Sandys about a year ago this has been a main objective.<br />
, Je have pursued it in our discussions with British Ministers,<br />
through our Ambassadors in the countries concerned, in meetings<br />
beteon officials, and in a whole series of formal exchanges<br />
between Australia and the Governments of the Six and Britain.<br />
Those efforts have been reinforced by the approaches which Mr.<br />
McEwen has made during his rucent round of mootings in Europe.<br />
One result of these continuous efforts, but l no means<br />
the only one, is that an opportunity is to be afforded to<br />
Australia on 26th April to present her case to the body of<br />
senior officials of the Common Market countries and Britain in<br />
Brussel. s the Deputies which has the responsibility, under<br />
the Ministers, for detailed negotiations. As has boon announced,<br />
the Australian case, covering all points of trade interest to us,<br />
will be presented to this mooting by the Permanent Head of the<br />
Commonwealth Department of Tradj, Dr. J. A. , Josterman. Dr.<br />
. Jstorman will have available for consultation in London prior<br />
to the Brussels moeting, advisers from a wide range of<br />
Australian industries whose interests are most directly affect. d.<br />
The work done at this mooting will be vigorously followed up. </p>
<p>We are well aware of the difficulties in the way, of<br />
securing safeguards for Australian trade int,. rests which we<br />
would regard as acceptabloBut at least we can hope that, as<br />
a result of the efforts we have made, Australia's particular<br />
problems are now btter understood and the roat and grave<br />
importance of these matters to Australia better appreciated, by<br />
Britain and the Six. 1. e shall continue to press our claims, and<br />
to make our views known with the utmrost energy. But it must be<br />
roem. er. d that no conclusions on the terms and conditions of<br />
British entry to the Common Market can be arrived at without the<br />
agreement of the Six nations. Our task is th3erefore both heavy<br />
and challenging, and will continue to require constant Australian<br />
advocacy. CAN3ELRA, 19th April, 1962. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
