<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1086</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE RT. HON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES, K.T., C.H., Q.C., M.P., ON CONSTITUTIONAL REVIEW - FROM THE &quot;PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES&#039;&#039; 1ST APRIL 1965</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/04/1965</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001086.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA<br />
SPEECH BY<br />
The Rt. Hon. SIR ROBERT MENZIES,<br />
M. P.,<br />
ON<br />
CONSTITUTIONAL REVIEW<br />
[ From the " Parliamentary Debates," 1st April 19651<br />
Sir ROBERT MIENZIES ( Kooyong-<br />
Prime Minister) [ 11.41].-I hope that I will<br />
not disappoint either the Leader of the<br />
Opposition ( Mr. Caiwell) or anybody else<br />
in this House when I say that I have no<br />
intention whatever of making a party debating<br />
speech. The Leader of the Opposition<br />
did not do so either. I have no desire to do<br />
it because I agree that the issues of constitutional<br />
change ought not as a rule-and<br />
there may be some exceptions to this-to be<br />
settled or thought of in purely party<br />
terms. Indeed, I am able to say that I find<br />
myself in agreement with much of what the<br />
honorable gentleman has said. I think he is<br />
a little optimistic, if I may put it to him,<br />
when he asks that all sections of the report<br />
be placed before the people at a referendum<br />
without further delay, because he will agree<br />
with me that experience indicates that if that<br />
were to be done the whole lot would be<br />
lost. A great mass of proposals for constitutional<br />
change cannot be put before the<br />
people with any real expectation of getting<br />
them through. It has been tried and it has<br />
failed. The whole problem of constitutional<br />
change in our country is bedevilled by the<br />
fact that the disposition of the people is to<br />
say: " When in doubt, vote The<br />
change suggested needs to be crystal clear.<br />
It needs to be one which does not lend<br />
itself to misinterpretation or to absurd fears<br />
3900/ 65. which are occasionally promoted. These requirements<br />
are not easy to attain, but simplicity<br />
on a matter which really engages the<br />
public attention and to which the people<br />
will direct their minds thoughtfully is<br />
essential. I do not propose to cover the whole field<br />
that the honorable gentleman has dealt with,<br />
and for one very good reason-I am not<br />
here to indulge in the luxury of offering a<br />
lot of personal views on a variety of matters.<br />
The Government has, in fact, under its<br />
immediate consideration two aspects of the<br />
reforms which have been indicated, and I<br />
think I can say something about those, but<br />
in relation to others I am not in a position<br />
at present to make any definitive statements<br />
of policy on behalf of the Government.<br />
When I can, of course I will, because I do<br />
not at all underestimate the importance of<br />
these matters. One of them, the question of<br />
the division of the Commonwealth into<br />
electorates, on which the report has made<br />
proposals which are supported by the<br />
honorable gentleman, will no doubt be the<br />
subject of discussion when we introduce<br />
electoral legislation, because some of the<br />
points he has made, particularly about<br />
differen-tials, will very legitimately then be<br />
open for discussion. I do not want to anticipate<br />
that, but I do want to say something<br />
which I do not think is at all controversial </p>
<p>about two of these matters. I will start with<br />
the last one mentioned by the honorable<br />
member. With the proposition that section<br />
127 should be repealed we entirely agree.<br />
When any referendum is instituted that most<br />
certainly must be one of the questions. It is<br />
completely out of harmony with experience<br />
and modern thinking and, indeed, with a<br />
great deal of our own legislation in this<br />
Parliament relating to Aborigines. The retention<br />
of the old fashioned provision in<br />
section 127 is quite out of harmony with<br />
the elevation of the Aborigines into the<br />
ranks of citizenship. But it has been customary,<br />
and the wish has been made clear<br />
in a number of petitions, to associate with<br />
the repeal of section 127 the removal of<br />
what has been called the " discriminatory<br />
provisions" of section 51. On that I would,<br />
with great respect, challenge the assumption<br />
that is made. May I read the provision to<br />
the House in order to refresh its memory.<br />
Section 51 states-<br />
The Parliament shall, subject to this Constitution,<br />
have power to make laws for the peace, order, and<br />
good government of the Commonwealth with<br />
respect to:-<br />
( xxvi.) The people of any race, other than the<br />
aboriginal race in any State, for<br />
, whom it is deemed necessary to make<br />
special laws:<br />
It has been suggested that that provision discriminates<br />
against the Aborigines of Australia.<br />
I would have thought that the<br />
contrary was the fact. Parliament has been<br />
given power to make discriminatory laws in<br />
relation to the people of any race-special<br />
laws which would relate to them and not to<br />
other people; laws which would treat them<br />
as people who stood outside the normal<br />
grasp of the law, enjoying its benefits and<br />
sustaining its burdens in common with all<br />
other citizens. I would have thought that<br />
the perfect state of affairs in Australia would<br />
be that any Aboriginal citizen felt that he<br />
did' stand equal with every other citizen before<br />
the law, enjoyed its benefits and took<br />
his own part on a proper basis in sustaining<br />
its burdens. I have no doubt whatever that<br />
this provision in the Constitution was<br />
designed having regard to conditions that<br />
existed at that time and the possibility of<br />
having to make a special law dealing with,<br />
for example, kanaka labourers-perhaps a<br />
special law to deport them from the country<br />
or to confine them to some particular area.<br />
There was a good deal of discussion about this at the time this provision was framed.<br />
Therefore the framers of the Constitution<br />
inserted this provision, but they left out the<br />
Aboriginal race because they did not want<br />
to discriminate against the people of the<br />
aboriginal race. All we have to do now is to<br />
cross out this reference " other than the<br />
aboriginal race" and we confer on this<br />
Parliament a power to make a special law<br />
which relates to the Aborigines and to no<br />
other people.<br />
Mr. Reynolds.-But-<br />
Sir ROBERT MENZIES.-If you do not<br />
mind I want to pursue this. I do not think<br />
it is at all out of place. There is a second<br />
point about it, and this does concern me.<br />
If the Commonwealth, as one of its heads<br />
of power under section 51, has the right to<br />
pass special laws with respect to the<br />
Aboriginal race, I wonder what limitations<br />
will be on that separate head of power.<br />
Would this enable the Parliament to set up<br />
a separate body of industrial laws relating<br />
to Aborigines or some other kind of lawhealth<br />
laws, quarantine laws or laws under<br />
any of the other powers of the Parliament?<br />
It may well be true that it could because,<br />
make no mistake about it, this would be a<br />
head of power standing not inferior to any<br />
other power contained in section 51. That<br />
is a matter that requires a great deal of<br />
thought. I do not want honorable members<br />
to think that I have arrived at some positive<br />
conclusion about it. I am raising it<br />
here in order to indicate that it wants a<br />
good deal of thought and that we would<br />
want to give it a great deal more investigation<br />
than we have before we favoured<br />
changing the provision in section 51. But<br />
we would be very happy to see the end of<br />
qection 127.<br />
The other matter about which I wanted<br />
to say something concerns section 24. The<br />
Leader of the Opposition has said most of<br />
it, and, if I may say so, very well and<br />
clearly. I do not want to subtract from what<br />
he : has said. I just want to add a little to it.<br />
Section 24 of the Constitution is a puzzler.<br />
It reads-<br />
The House of Representatives shall be composed<br />
of members directly chosen by the people of the<br />
Commonwealth, and the number of such members<br />
shall be, as nearly as practicable, twice the number<br />
of senators.<br />
I confess that I do not ' know what " as<br />
' nearly as practicable" means. If it means<br />
mathematically practicable, then we must </p>
<p>have 120 members and that is the end of it.<br />
We have never had exactly -twice as many<br />
members as senators that I can -recall in the<br />
history of the Parliament, but we have been,<br />
in a sense near enough. Today we are a<br />
couple over that provision, with two other<br />
members full of hopes. I do not think anybody<br />
seriously t'hinks, that there could -be<br />
an effective challenge at law to the existing<br />
numbers. Nor, indeed, would I think that<br />
if we went to 123, 124 or 125 members<br />
we would necessarily violate the provision,<br />
because what is practicable involves consideration<br />
of hard -facts other than mathematical<br />
considerations. Still, it would bea<br />
bold man who would think that we could<br />
make any sizeable addition to the numbers<br />
of the House without incurring the risk<br />
of running foul of section 24. The moment<br />
somebody indicates that somebody is thinking<br />
about increasing the number of members<br />
of the House we will get the orthodox<br />
complaint in some quarters that there are<br />
already too -many members of Parliament.<br />
This is the cheapest cry in the world, but<br />
it is always produced. A good deal of<br />
unthinking criticism is put forward when<br />
any suggestion is made that the number of<br />
members -be increased. I have read some of<br />
it in the last few days. It is quite unthinking.<br />
It therefore becomes necessary that I<br />
should say what the Leader of the Opposition<br />
' has already said. There is one single<br />
fact that cannot be ignored if section 24<br />
and the little collection of sections stand as<br />
they are. Unless you are to have a perpetually<br />
deadlocked Senate, you cannot<br />
increase the numbers in the Senate except<br />
by 24. If you increase the total number of<br />
senators by 12 it will mean that at each<br />
election 6 senators are elected for each<br />
State. The result will be 3 elected on each<br />
side. There is the very definition of a perpetual<br />
deadlock. So if you are to have a<br />
Senate that is workable-an unworkable<br />
Senate would be a menace-you must<br />
increase the number of senators so that at<br />
each election each State will elect 7 senators.<br />
You will then have 4 on one side and<br />
3 on the other. This means increasing the<br />
size of the Senate ' by 24. That would mean<br />
increasing the size of the House -by 48<br />
members. Mr. Uren.-Too many. Sir ROBERT MENZIES.-If they all<br />
were like my friend I would be quite happy,<br />
' but nobody in this place at this time thinks<br />
it is necessary to increase the size of this<br />
House -by 48 -members. We may think it<br />
desirable to increase it by 10, 12 or 15 but<br />
not ' by 48. Such a proposition would not<br />
enter anybody's mind. Yet we are presented<br />
with a choice in which we will make either<br />
no increase in -the numbers, an increase so<br />
nominal that it does not violate section 24,<br />
or a vast increase ' by increasing the size of<br />
the Senate ' by 24.<br />
Mr. Duthie.-Why not wipe out 24?<br />
Sir ROBERT MENZIES.-If my friend<br />
from Tasmania wants to have an argument<br />
about that, all I can say is that he ought<br />
first to take it on with Senator Wright. The<br />
point I am making is obvious enough to all<br />
honorable members, though I think it has<br />
been overlooked by some of the incipient<br />
critics. The point is that this House has a<br />
choice. It can either for all practical purposes<br />
keep its numbers static or find itself<br />
increasing the size of the Senate, under the<br />
existing law, so as to be able to increase<br />
the size of this House. In my view, it would<br />
then be compelled to increase the Senate<br />
by 24-nothing else would work-and be<br />
required to increase the size of this House<br />
by 48 or 46, whatever the figure may be.<br />
It cuts both ways. If the numbers are to be<br />
as nearly as practicable twice the number<br />
of the senators, the position would be that<br />
the number in this House would need to be<br />
as nearly as practicable 168. Nobody proposes<br />
that; nobody would think of it at<br />
this time.<br />
I have said all this to show to the House<br />
that we adhere to the principle that is<br />
involved in that part of the report that says<br />
that the nexus ought to be broken. If it is<br />
not broken, there is no flexible future for<br />
this House. I have been reminded of my<br />
long experience in these fields. It is indeed<br />
long. I have been through a few referendum<br />
campaigns and I have come to respect the<br />
genius of the people for voting No. If we<br />
go to the people with a proposal to amend<br />
the Constitution to break the nexus between<br />
the two Houses, the first question that will<br />
be asked by those opposed to it-there will<br />
be quite a lot of people opposed to it, particularly<br />
in some States-will be: "' You want<br />
this so that you can increase the size of the<br />
Parliament. By how much do you want to </p>
<p>increase the size of the House of Representatives?<br />
That raises problems that do<br />
seriously require a great deal of thought.<br />
We would need to consider how these matters<br />
are to be presented and the extent to<br />
which we can go into details. We must be<br />
as forthcoming on those matters as we can.<br />
If we are not, we will be told that we are<br />
hiding something and the result will be<br />
disastrous from the point of view of ever<br />
increasing the size of this House. I am not<br />
at this stage proposing positively to give a<br />
programme for the Government on these<br />
matters. We must consider the various<br />
aspects. They are associated in the public<br />
mind with other matters concerning electoral<br />
laws and the spread of boundaries, which, as everybody knows, are matters of acute<br />
difference of opinion. As I have said, we<br />
will by suitable legislation give the House<br />
the opportunity for a debate and, therefore,<br />
decision on these matters.<br />
When I rose this morning all I hoped to<br />
do was to raise one of two of the matters<br />
that I do think are worth considering and<br />
which have been exercising our m-inds quite<br />
a lot. I wished to emphasise-it is very<br />
desirable to emphasise this on constitutional<br />
matters-that I really believe there is a very<br />
substantial body of opinion in common in<br />
this House. The qualifications that I have<br />
put have not been so much qualifications<br />
of principle as of application in the matters<br />
I have dealt with.<br />
BY AUTHOuRr: J. ARTHAM, COMMONWEALTH! GOVERNMENT PRINTER, CANBERRA. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
