<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8957</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ KEATING, MP NEW NATIONAL PRESIDENT OF THE RSL</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/09/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008957.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING, MP<br />
NEW NATIONAL PRESIDENT OF THE RSL<br />
I was pleased to be able to meet today with the new National President of the<br />
Returned Services League, Major General W. B. ( Digger) James.<br />
I congratulated General James on his election to the position on 1 September, and<br />
welcomed such an early opportunity to meet him in his new role.<br />
The RSL is an important community voice in Australia, especially on matters such as<br />
veterans' affairs and the conditions of service of serving Defence personnel.<br />
I look forward to developing a good and constructive relationship between my<br />
Government and the RSL, while acknowledging that we will continue to have our<br />
differences ovcr somc issues.<br />
In our mccting today, I assured General James that the Labor Government is<br />
committed to ensuring that veterans and their dependants are compensated<br />
appropriately for war service.<br />
My colleague the Minister for Veterans' Affairs, Senator Faulkncr, has appointed an<br />
independent committee to undertake a thorough review of the veterans' compensation<br />
program and to report to him in March next year to enable its recommendations to be<br />
considered in the 1994-95 Budget context.<br />
CANBERRA 8 SEPTEMBER, 1993 99/ 93<br />
8. Sep. 93 13: 15 No. 005 P. 01/ 01 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
