<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8029</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, SYDNEY TOWN HALL 10 JUNE 1990</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/06/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008029.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, SYDNEY TOWN HALL<br />
JUNE 1990<br />
E OE PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, on the question of the Chinese<br />
students, there's some doubt about whether the full 20,000<br />
will be able to stay and what status they will have.<br />
PM: Well let me say this. I have been amazed, if I can put<br />
it that way, by the media in this last week. I see that I<br />
have changed my mind, retreated. There's been no change in<br />
my position, no retreat. There seems to be a complete<br />
incapacity to understand the very simple propositions which<br />
I put and some distinctions which I made. Now let me make<br />
it clear. What I said was something that should not have<br />
surprised anyone because I'd been saying it for 12 months.<br />
And that is that in regard to those people that had come<br />
here pre-Tienanmen that there were special circumstances<br />
that applied to them and there would be a special category.<br />
The details of that of course I had in some sense talked<br />
about with Mr Hand before I made any public comment. He is<br />
preparing a submission for Cabinet on the basis of the<br />
discussions that we had, and the details of how we'll work<br />
out that special category will be considered and determined<br />
by Cabinet. But there will be, as there must be, and as<br />
I've made quite clear over a period of 12 months, special<br />
consideration as to how you deal with the problems of those<br />
people. For those who came after that I've made it clear,<br />
as will be the case, that the presumption will be that those<br />
people will return to China. Now I noticed that in the<br />
process some people seemed to have had a difficulty in<br />
making the distinction between that and what I had to say in<br />
regard to what in shorthand terms are called the Cambodian<br />
boat people. Now obviously I understood, and do understand,<br />
involved in what I said, that for those who get here,<br />
those who've arrived, there are legal processes to which<br />
they are entitled. And to be technical about it that's the<br />
DORS, the Determination of Refugee Status, DORS. And people<br />
get here whom are able to use those processes to determine<br />
by definition whether they have refugee status in the terms<br />
under our legislation, and internationally recognised, which<br />
would enable them to qualify for residency here under the<br />
refugee category. What I was trying to make quite clear and<br />
which I repeat again is that as far as I and the Government<br />
are concerned there needn't be some expectation that there<br />
is simply a great open door here for any people who want to<br />
come. People are saying oh but look at the difficulties<br />
they encounter in getting here. Sure, but where do we draw </p>
<p>the line? Say two hundred people have Come, they've<br />
encountered some difficulties. Alright, they get here.<br />
what if it's two hundred thousand, two million? It's got<br />
nothing to do with whether they are Cambodians, whether they<br />
are Irish, Greek, Italian. The fact is that I am making it<br />
quite clear as far as this Government is concerned that we<br />
as a sovereign country will determine our immigration policy<br />
and its content, its size. And let no-one think that we're<br />
just going to stand idly by and allow others by their<br />
autonomous action which reflect some perhaps unhappiness<br />
with the circumstances in which they find themselves in<br />
their own country, that those people are going to determine<br />
our immigration policy. That's not going to happen. Now<br />
those things I made quite clear in my comments last week.<br />
There was no equivocation about them. They were<br />
intellectually integrated, politically integrated and<br />
intellectually and politically proper. if people haven't<br />
been able to understand it don't accuse me of some changing.<br />
There has been no change. What I say now is precisely what<br />
I've said before.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, why did you bypass Cabinet when you<br />
were making that decision?<br />
PM: It's not a question of bypassing cabinet. As I've just<br />
indicated, I had detailed discussions with the Minister<br />
before I made the observation that I did. I've been Prime<br />
minister for seven years. On many occasions where there is<br />
a matter of public concern and interest 1I with the<br />
responsibility I have as Prime Minister, have made it clear<br />
what T believe the Government's position would be. And I am<br />
quite certain that the Government's position will be as I<br />
have indicated. Now as to certain details, particularly as<br />
to the details of how we work out the special category for<br />
those Chinese that were here prior to Tienanmen, then those<br />
will be a matter of detailed discussion and determination by<br />
Cabinet. JOURNALIST: Mr Wellington Lee and some other people in the<br />
Asian community have said that some of the students, the<br />
Chinese students, don't deserve to stay here.<br />
PM: Yes, well Mr Wellington Lee over the years has made<br />
observations which don't always emanate from his concern<br />
with matters of immigration as such. I mean he has his<br />
political sympathies and positions and if he sees an<br />
opportunity to attack the Government he's been prepared to<br />
do it over the years. And that's good on you Wellington<br />
that's part of this democracy and I welcome that. But I<br />
don't take any particular notice of Wellington Lee. I<br />
understand what the realities are. And they are, they've<br />
not only been recognised in this country, but it defies<br />
description that anyone should suggest that in regard to<br />
people who were here before Tienanmen that you don't have to<br />
have some special considerations as to how you deal with<br />
that. We will, and as I say the details will be worked out<br />
in discussion with my Cabinet colleagues. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Will you take into consideration their skill<br />
level, their educational level?<br />
PM: As I say, the details of how these things are taken<br />
into account are properly for decision. The important thing<br />
that I've done is to make clear that this country will<br />
compassionately and properly understand that there are<br />
special considerations that have to be given to that group<br />
of people.<br />
JOURNALIST: You must have been disappointed though that<br />
your decision sort of seemed to unveil a bitter new<br />
dimension to the Asian immigration debate.<br />
PM: Well I don't think it did. it's very interesting.<br />
What it did unveil was a lack of capacity on the part of<br />
many people writing in the media to understand fairly simple<br />
facts. But I'm used to that after seven years. I don't get<br />
terribly worried about that. one has an educational role in<br />
these matters. I think that in regard to the issue itself<br />
that it would be fair to say that people did, generally<br />
speaking, including those who I think misunderstood what I<br />
was saying, certainly none of the people who've written in<br />
the media I think, nor Australians generally, have taken the<br />
view that we shouldn't have a compassionate attitude on<br />
these matters. I haven't felt that that view has come<br />
through strongly.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, what do think of Mr Loosley's<br />
plan to change preselection rules in the State?<br />
PM: I think that is a matter predominantly for discussion<br />
here within the State branch of NSW.<br />
JOURNALIST: Ira it a good idea? Bob Hogg is proposing a<br />
similar change nationally.<br />
PM: I think it's a good idea that these matters should be<br />
discussed within the Party.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, you mentioned the Budget in your<br />
speech and there has been a figure floating around that<br />
you're going to make cuts of $ 1.6 billion to the<br />
Commonwealth Budget in the forthcoming Budget. Is that<br />
figure right?<br />
PMt That's a good try Amanda. A very very good try. You<br />
know that in this funny period that we're getting into now<br />
in the pre-Budget that there are all sorts of figures and<br />
ideas floating around. Now that's good, it's part of the<br />
process of public debate and democracy. But these things<br />
will be determined in the now awful period that's coming up<br />
of weeks and weeks in that Expenditure Review Committee.<br />
All I will say is this, that there will be decisions which<br />
will involve reductions in Commonwealth expenditure.<br />
Because that is necessary if we're going to meet the task<br />
that we have. And that is to ensure in the interests of<br />
this country that in the period ahead there be a position </p>
<p>where production is greater than demand. Because that is<br />
necessary to attack the twin problems of our external<br />
account and of inflationary pressures. So we'll play our<br />
part in Commonwealth fiscal policy and of course if we also<br />
want the States to be involved in some expenditure restraint<br />
we'll have to show sorne ourselves.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Greiner said that on the area of<br />
microeconomic reform his government has done more than most<br />
and he's asking for some tax rebate powers.<br />
PM: Yes well if you read all that Mr Greiner has said over<br />
the months and the years it makes very interesting reading.<br />
He's the one who said at times, perhaps most vociferously,<br />
that there's a need for restraint by the States. Then when<br />
you look at what's happened in NSW the performance doesn't<br />
quite match the rhetoric. But I'm not here to engage in a<br />
slanging match with Mr Greiner, as attractive as that may<br />
appear to be. I mean I hope that Nick Greiner and all the<br />
state Premiers, irrespective of their political persuasion,<br />
are going to accept that we all, all of us, have a<br />
responsibility to match as politicians, and as decisionmakers,<br />
the economic challenges confronting this country.<br />
That involves some hard decisions on the part of all of us.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, in terms of the public debate<br />
process of democracy, is it a wise move to throw a<br />
television news crew out of the Conference?<br />
PM: That's a matter for the decision of the conference.<br />
All I can say is that every other television station seemed<br />
to think it was appropriate to meet the requirements of the<br />
conference. That's their business.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, Mr Howe seems to be<br />
foreshadowing changes, possible changes to Medicare. How<br />
far can those changes go?<br />
PM: I don't put specific limits on that. I have a position<br />
where in Brian Howe I have a Minister of outstanding<br />
competence, great track record in the broad area of social<br />
issues. His reforms as Minister for Social Security were<br />
historic. He blended thid great capacity for compassion and<br />
targetting for eliminating unnecessary expenditure but while<br />
ensuring that those in need were better looked after. A<br />
great record there and he seems to be bringing precisely<br />
those characteristics and qualities to the discharge of his<br />
new Ministry. I am quite confident, knowing Brian as I do,<br />
that he will be having a quite wide-ranging examination of<br />
this area and be bringing to Cabinet proposals, which I<br />
don't know the detail of yet as I'm talking, but which will<br />
be characterised by those considerations. That is to<br />
eliminate waste if that can possibly be done to make for<br />
better targetting but to ensure that those who need<br />
protection get it.<br />
JOURNALIST: Are we talking about modifying or rebuilding<br />
Medicare? </p>
<p>PM: I'm not making any positions about it because I want to<br />
have further discussions with the Minister and we'll want to<br />
see what his proposals are. But it will ensure that<br />
whatever is done you can rest assured that the<br />
characteristics of Medicare will stay. And that is that for<br />
the people of Australia they will have universality and they<br />
will have equity.<br />
JOURNALIST: Is Mr Cameron as bad a pollster as Mr Loosley<br />
seems to think he is?<br />
PM: Now this is almost sub judice.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
