<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5668</transcript-id>
    <title>NEW RIVER MURRAY WATERS AGREEMENT</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/10/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005668.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
I' 16 October 1.9817n<br />
,~ NEW 1RIVriR MURRAY WATE~ RS AGREEE4T<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr. Malcolm Fraser, said today in Melbourne<br />
that he wias pleased that a new River Murray Waters Agreemnt<br />
has been settled..<br />
fi " The new~ River Murray Waters Agreement would be-44e-keynotv f<br />
the Commonwealth's involvement with Victoria, New South ' Wales<br />
and South Australia it) dealing with salinity problems. in.ñ he..<br />
Murray Valley", the Prime Minister said.<br />
The Prime Minister was speaking after a meeting at which be ant<br />
th Minuister for National Development and Eniergy, Senator J. L.<br />
Carrick, had met with State Premiers of.-. New U1th at<br />
Victoria and South Austr~ alia and their Water Resources<br />
* Ministers to discuss River Murray wattors.<br />
K'The new Agreement would place new responisibilities-on---the--+% i.---<br />
A Murray ConMission. In particular, the Commission would. formulate<br />
water quality objectives arnd standards for any part of the<br />
r-Riv-er-Murfay.' It would also make assessme'nts of the<br />
implications of new developments which could have a significant<br />
iVui4U-on -wetter quality in the River and make representations<br />
. p on any proposals which might adversely af fect water quality.<br />
The new Agre-ement would allow the further development of<br />
strategies to reduce salinity and other water quality problems<br />
in the River to manageab e. proportion6.<br />
IThe Prime Minister said that now that Peads of Government had<br />
reache4-a&amp; geement-ort th~ iferrs of the now Agreement the<br />
principles would be applied immediately on an interim basis<br />
pending the complet4o~ n-f-ñ ei31ativc-proceEsses. This meant<br />
that to all intents and purposes the River Murray CoMmission<br />
Fwould be authorised to assume its new responsibilities<br />
Mr. Fr aer said thnt there were already signs that recent<br />
initiatives by the four governments are gradually becoming effec<br />
tive. lr7ru~ iementF, will be accelerated by the new Agreement.<br />
I i l </p>
<p>Iater quality beyo dtihgl e River Mwuj.): ay Cruisooverthe<br />
reccIlt severe J: okkqht iwlicatect that sa). inity lc-ve]. s tlf-re<br />
lower than iji pi~ eviom; conmpayirbth-dj: y period13s. It appe~ ar's that<br />
tis comparatil/ e inprovcemnt j-s due~ to the-inIjtial opperatIons,<br />
of Dartmnouth Damr and tho effectivenems of aly.' ay com~ pleted N<br />
salinity conrl. ioh The heavy ): in since the be~ gillningi<br />
of June are having~ a ve) y be. f icial f lushing ef fect onthe<br />
river system finc adeqjuate water supplies of. good qual) ity<br />
should~ be ali. labl next seat-on,<br />
Fraser said that the Commiuniwalth and States' concern f or<br />
the economlo~ awl. envi)., ovnmntal health of, the Rive)* Murray has<br />
been backed tip -by strcng acinover : irecent Y~<br />
aboiut $ 35 million w~ is pr: ovided~ c foy: the cons-. truc:. on of.<br />
Darti~ o~ ith Dapi-and over $ 26 mill. ion in 10oa11 fundt; was<br />
Provided to the sStt-c0 se to Im1p them r," ee. t thteir<br />
respective sba-, Cs of the C05L of the project.<br />
the fv wth amis 11o1w abot two,~ thirds full by<br />
almost dloubling' thc rshae stor. 3, je, kk10k~ the<br />
colty. o 3-. of thte-4iiver Muric~ y Comzd-Ission, itL % will ell'hle<br />
th -1 NX;~ isIoI$ 11 to PUr-ISue a n~ brof river mallaeient<br />
objecti. v s not pireviously possllhle, inolvding (. iluU. on1<br />
Of I'i'. Er-aiiy<br />
in addcition, arisinq~ fvovi the 3.979 Kcaursefl. Report on<br />
Murray \' 44ey Salinit. y and EDrainajre3, about $ 36 rt3. ilion<br />
has bee n spent, o amjor ni salinity control projCt<br />
in t KAuriay ' Vali,: y sinc., e July 1.978 the Corp-ionwea). th<br />
has pro'. ided roillim an~ there are mratchingj<br />
contx . ihut. ons by th tt,~<br />
V: t ~ e c~' L ec~.' nc~~~ din tho 1979 M-amunsl. P-epo~<br />
i~ s thqh k9ho prior. tDy arje vjrci co irp). i ted or Q~ Ie<br />
ar~ dailtiu~ n~ ). cotro prOjctSin &amp; C-corda nce witjI<br />
A -Pr Qi 3. i~ sidcsi. ifieA b th S Li in conjtticULion oi. tI<br />
the River Murray Commission.-</p>
<p>The Prirte hfiristex said that all Gover: nments had agreed that<br />
improved irE igqAti~ on practi.; wereO~ a fundaien ta] olement in<br />
reduoin~ j sali). ty problem~ s in the Murray Rivei' Vaclley and iL<br />
w,, as esseritizi). that rapid p): ogress was ri,, ade'in thi)' s regard.<br />
AMinisters had zxgreed-t-here-fore that. offiocials shol). d review th e<br />
ex
V* eduoe salinity and the possible need for additional. incent'ives<br />
to hasten to adoptionr-of new pr. actices.<br />
In this context, the Prime Minister: ) efr. red tUr-th-p-new Ita;
co4) cess ions wh ieli-te4opicne) hhad introduced ill April<br />
and December 198() to encouryage irrigator: s to improve their<br />
i).' rtqation pricrticePs and salinlity control. Thiese concessions<br />
allowed the full write-off of c p,[. endjiture; 3Sn the, sam~ e year a 8<br />
the expond," iture occurred, ' rihii: g* e: neirou concession was al. ready<br />
h ill place and. % Wts erj. cou .9n toys to.-5rrove their.-<br />
practices andI to Combat salinit.<br />
The Prime Minister said that before any fuivthe deisions are<br />
considered onl a major follow-up to the cui-rent iirtplementatikon<br />
œ of the Maunsoll plan of action, some titie is needced to assess<br />
the effcti" eness of the hiqjh pri~ jority procijcts ) 1ow0 underyway,<br />
the ful~ l intc9L'at3. on of the Dartmouth Dam -into the oper: ations<br />
of the Ri~ ver Murray ComIi~ oP, improv. ed i) rrijgat-on practice's<br />
and the flew watey. qUality respo: n,-bi. xties1 of the Rliver 1Mrray<br />
Co() rm iss9i on . Iten these as; sessments bccoame possible, the<br />
Conirnonicalth will give careful consideration to proposals for<br />
further sa). ivity Control projects in the MurrE~ ay Valley.<br />
The Prime Minister said that. to hasten this pr. oceSs of assessmvicnt<br />
the JRiv., Murray Corrrnissio-n is ~ n~ gvg os3tnsto,<br />
elp a ma~ hc~ tiaYcpi~ r nocel hic Wil nable thu<br />
C~;~ t3s~ 1cnto si~ lth . e opcra-tiol ol ths whol. Ri. vcr 1Iiirra<br />
sys tern in terrms, not only
1lso Nwziter cTl Ih-yIi s T1ic3100 3.1 e nabl. e-the C :%, moriwea Ith<br />
ani State cnve :, ients. to c* al~. nc all. avais) lable options for new </p>
<p>,1 4,<br />
initiatives in managing t rivcr, haviiig regard to both water<br />
cluatity and cluaJity.<br />
WJhije the Comnmonvicalthi is making a significant cortribution te?<br />
conmbatting balinity in the River Muri-ay, it js made an equaly." y<br />
important contribution to helpinq Souith Australia improve the<br />
quality of river water skipplies for urban pu: qoses. By the qndof<br />
thi. s financial year, over million wI. ll have been pro-.,<br />
vicled towards the cozt; of a filtratioon scheiii for Adelaide<br />
reduce turbidity in water supplies an, at the Same time,<br />
irrprove both the taste aiid odour of trecated water for. Oomesl: j. c<br />
pur-poses.<br />
" The Riverv Murray Watiers Agreent his worked to the advantage<br />
of all three States over the paast 60 year.' s or so, and its<br />
Yrevision to met today's reqLrircements is a milestoe in<br />
co-operative rnagement of the PIver's water and in impro'dniig<br />
watur quality in the River the Prim-Minister coicluded.<br />
I _ I I<br />
F. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
