<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6155</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/07/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006155.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
-j AUb It Al IA., LL<br />
PRIRM! MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA 13 July 1983<br />
The Prime Minister today announced the appointment of members<br />
of the new Economic Planninq Advisory Council.<br />
EPAC has been set up to continue the process of consultation<br />
and information exchange started at the National Economic<br />
Summit Conference.<br />
Through EPAC, the Government will have available to it, on a<br />
continuing basis, independent advice from State Governments,<br />
the business sector, unions and community groups on the broad<br />
conduct of economic policy, particularly in a medium and<br />
longer term context.<br />
The first meeting of the Council will be held in Canberra on<br />
July 1983.<br />
This will enable the Government to consult the Council and<br />
have the benefit of its views during the course of the<br />
Budget's formulation.<br />
EPAC's views will supplement the already extensive consultation<br />
which the Government has engaged in about the conduct of policy<br />
both during the Summit and subsequently.<br />
The Council will have 17 members, including three Federal<br />
Government Ministers arid three State Government representativcs.<br />
The States will be represented on the inaugural Council by the<br />
Premiers of New South Wales, South Australia and Tasmania.<br />
The Federal Government will be represented by myself, the<br />
Treasurer and the Minister for Employment and Industrial<br />
Relations. Under the Act establishing EPAC, the State Government members<br />
are to hold office for a period of up to two years.<br />
The Government's intention is that one of the three State<br />
seats will rotate between NSW and Victoria while the other<br />
two seats will be shared among the remaining States and the<br />
Northern Territory so that, over time, each of-those five will<br />
get equal representation. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
The non-Government members were selected after consultation<br />
with relevant industry and community orgjanisations. These<br />
members, who have a four year term, are:-<br />
Mr A. W. Coates<br />
General 11Llanacjer and Director, AMklP Society<br />
Mr B. N. Kelman<br />
Director and General Manager, CSR Ltd<br />
Mr D. N. Hughes<br />
Chief Executive Cadbury Schweppes Australia Ltd and<br />
President, Confederation of Australian Industry<br />
Mr F. M. Davidson<br />
President, National Farmers' Federation<br />
Mr C. O. Dolan<br />
President, ACTU<br />
-Mr. W. J. Kelty<br />
Secretary, ACTU<br />
Mr C. H. Fitzgibbon<br />
Senior Vice-President, ACTU<br />
Ms J. Marsh<br />
ACTU Advocate<br />
Ms L. F. Cutts<br />
Director, Australian Council of Local Government<br />
Associations<br />
Mr C. K. Menzies<br />
Secretary-General ACOSS<br />
Dr J. B. Braithwaite<br />
Director, Australian Federation of Consumer Organisations<br />
In addition to drawing on its own resources, the Council will<br />
consult widely with Federal and State bodies and with<br />
commercial, industrial, consumer, welfare and other<br />
organ isations.<br />
It will also have power to engage consultants and to form<br />
committees and working parties to investigate matters on its<br />
behalf. The membership of such working parties will not be restricted<br />
to Council members and I expect the Council to seek the<br />
assistance and involvement of others whenever this is appropriate. </p>
<p>-3-<br />
The Government appreciates community interest in EPAC's<br />
future work and the contribution which will be made by<br />
the members of the inaug~ ural Council.<br />
The Council will play a significant role in national<br />
economic policy formulation. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
