<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3167</transcript-id>
    <title>THE ACTING PRIME MINISTER&#039;S PRESS CONFERENCE AT PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA TUESDAY, 20 FEBRUARY 1973</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/02/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003167.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
r33<br />
THE ACTING PRIME MINISTER'S PRESS CONFERENCE<br />
AT PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA<br />
TUESDAY, 20 FEBRUARY 1973<br />
ACTING PRIME MINISTER:. Today the Cabinet considered a number of<br />
submissions and the first one was on recreation leave and maternity<br />
leave. The Cabinet gave further consideration today to papers<br />
prepared for us which raised issues requiring clarification before<br />
our earlier decisions on an additional week's recreation leave for<br />
Commonwealth staff and maternity leave for them can be implemented.<br />
On recreation leave the principle is that the additional week's leave<br />
is to be restricted basically to members of a union whether registered<br />
or otherwise, that is recognised by the Australian Council of Trade<br />
Unions. As previously announced, provision will be made for<br />
consciencious objectors who will be expected to pay an amount<br />
equivalent to union membership fees to consolidated revenue with<br />
the Industrial Registrar determining when an individual may make<br />
such a payment. There are some complex legal issues requiring<br />
resolution for aspects of the principle of four weks annual leave<br />
are decided and the Cabinet has referred them to the Welfare<br />
Committee for study and report. A similar situation applies to<br />
maternity leave where a particular question raised was how the rules<br />
for servants of the Australian Government are to be brouqht into<br />
conformity with the relevant I. L. O. convention. The issues relating<br />
to maternity leave have also been referred to the Welfare Committee<br />
for examination and report to Cabinet.<br />
Probably one of the most important decisions that was made<br />
today was the decision to give effect to the recommendations of the<br />
Woodward Committee. You remember that this Committee was set up to<br />
examine pay, conditions and allowances for serving members of the<br />
Armed Forces. It sought the development of a cogent remuneration<br />
policy to meet the needs of modern-day defence forces within the<br />
framework of widely accepted wage fixing principles and community<br />
wage standards; secondly, the total abandonment of the present<br />
incomprehensible system and the introduction of a completely new<br />
and simplified pay structure which will clearly show its real<br />
meaning and value. 3. The adoption of the concept of commitment<br />
to service to life and financial recognition of the obligjations<br />
accepted by members resulting from commitment through the provision<br />
of a continuing allowance of $ 750 a year together with a series of<br />
additional allowances to meet particular circumstances which arise<br />
from time to time ( for example) separation of a member from his<br />
family. Comparisons between rates of pay before and after the<br />
Woodward Report cannot readily be made. The position of each<br />
individual member will be different depending on whether he is<br />
married or single; and because of the abolition of tax-exempt<br />
elements in pay his income tax commitments. I must stress that<br />
the new structure of service pay is a complete replacement of and<br />
entirely different from the old structure. I draw your close<br />
attention to the Report from which the difficulty of making ready,<br />
accurate comparisons will be clear. However, except for some junior<br />
officers who will now pay more for their rations and quarters,<br />
noone will suffer a decrease in pay. Most in fact will enjoy<br />
an increase. The figure of $ 73 million appearing in the final<br />
report and which will now be available to you and which was the cost<br />
Of the recommendation as submitted by the Woodward Committee is flow </p>
<p>2.<br />
reduced to $ 63 million following the abolition of national service.<br />
I will also be in touch with Mr Justice Woodward shortly about the<br />
offer made by the Committee in its final report to meet again if<br />
necessary to clarify or elaborate on any issue from the<br />
recommendations it has made. I have the question of permanent<br />
services pay fixing machinery currently under consideration.<br />
one of the recommendations of the Committee was that there should<br />
be a permanent committee established to conduct frequent enquiries<br />
into service pay allowa nces and conditions. I am now examining the<br />
terms under which that committee will be appointed and who should<br />
head it. Now what I've given you is only a brief outline of the<br />
Woodward Committee Report, the changes that have been made in<br />
relation to pay and allowances for serving members of the forces,<br />
the fact that for example taxation laws will now apply to members<br />
of the forces in a way that they were not previously applied. But<br />
there is a full press statement available on this matter and it<br />
will be made available to you immediately following this conference.<br />
Secondly of course the Woodward Committee's Report is also<br />
available. Now the * De fence forces re-engagement bonus. You will remember<br />
this is the $ 1,00O whichw as one of the policy matters that we<br />
* put to the people of Australia in the elections in 1972. There has<br />
been some comment in relation to this matter that it would not be<br />
the full $ 1,000, that if tax was considered, then something less<br />
than $ 1,000 would be available to an ex-serviceman who re-engaged.<br />
Cabinet considered this matter today and affirmed that the reengagement<br />
bonus of $ 1,000 to be paid to eligible members of the<br />
Defence forces will be exempt from tax. Appropriate amendments of<br />
the Income Tax Assessment Act will be prepared.<br />
I come next to the Tariff Boar Report on cathode ray tube<br />
display terminals. Cabinet today considered a Tariff Board Report<br />
on cathode ray tube display terminals. The particular units under<br />
reference comprise a cathode ray tube ( of the T. V. screen type),<br />
various specially designed electronic circuits and a device for<br />
connecting its terminals to other parts of a data processing or<br />
communications system. They are used for airline reservations,<br />
I. off-track betting, education and defence communications.<br />
The reference to the Board arose from representations by a Canberrabased<br />
firm Information Electronics and AWA now also manufacture<br />
these terminals. Subsequent to the Board reporting on these units<br />
the Government forwarded to it a reference on the electronics<br />
industry generally. Bearing in mind the Board's own approach that<br />
its examination of relevant issues can be more thorough in broader<br />
industry reviews than in inquiries covering only one or two outputs<br />
of an industry's total product range, the Government has decided<br />
to defer a decision on the Board's present recommendation pending<br />
its report on the industry generally. The Board is to be asked to<br />
consider any changed circumstances with regard to the local<br />
production of the units in its report on the relevant sections<br />
of the electronics industry. It is understood that the Board has<br />
this well in hand. In the meantime the present rates of duty<br />
general rate 32.5 per cent will remain in force, and because the<br />
Board noted in some cases that export prices were less than current<br />
domestic values the question of dumping will now be investigated<br />
by the Department of Customs and Excise. The Government is aware<br />
that the continuation of the existing level of protection could<br />
attract prospective new manufacturers. The Government would like<br />
it to be clearly understood, however, that it does not wish<br />
fragmentation to be caused in the electronics industry by reason </p>
<p>of the continuation of the present protection ' and it will not<br />
hesitate to take action which may prove necessary to prevent<br />
fragmentation and excess capacity.<br />
The Na{ tional Pipeline System. The Cabinet approved the creation<br />
of a national p ipeline authority by legislation in the forthc oming<br />
session. The authority will have the carriage of the planning and<br />
construction of a national pipeline system and its subsequent<br />
operation and maintenance. On this matter Mr Connor of course will<br />
have further details.<br />
On T. A. A. The Cabinet decided that it would move a step<br />
further towards implementing its t. w-ailn plg as set out in<br />
the Platform. Again, I suggest that on this question Mr Jones would<br />
be able to elaborate.<br />
Trespass on Commonwealth Lands. Cabinet decided to the repeal<br />
of sanctions 8A, 8B and 8C of the A. C. T. Tres pas ' s on Commonwealth-<br />
Lands Ordinance was approved. You remember that these sanctions were<br />
introduced by the previous Government in the last session of the<br />
Parliament. Cabinet also authorised the preparation of amendments<br />
to the Ordinance to ensure adequate protection of Commonwealth land<br />
in the A. C. T. while properly safeguarding the rights of citizens.<br />
Cabinet determined and approved the guarantee for loan from Asian<br />
Development 13ank to Papua New Guinea. It approved the preparation<br />
of authorising legislation to provide the necessary assurances to<br />
the Asian Development Bank for the borrowing of $ 9.8 million U. S.<br />
dollars by Papua New Guinea for the upgrading, realignment and<br />
sealing of about 75 miles of the Highlands highway between Lae and<br />
Waterais and the upgrading and new construction of about 62 miles<br />
of the Hiritano Highway between Port Moresby and Bereina. The<br />
legislation will be ready for introduction during the autumn sittings.<br />
Further guarantee for overseas borrowing by Papu a New Guinea.<br />
The Cabinet authorised the introduction of appropriate legisliation<br />
to provide for a contractual guarantee by the Australian Government<br />
of an overseas borrowing in the 1973 financial year by Papua New<br />
Guinea in foreign currencies not exceeding the equivalent of<br />
$ US 20 million.<br />
The Broadcasting and Television Act. Action against breaches.<br />
The Cabinet has authorised the Minister for the media to issue a<br />
notice of suspension to any television or radio ITJ-cecee company<br />
which may display in the future a blatant disregard of the standards<br />
laid down by the Broadcasting Control Board on advertising content<br />
and programs. Again this is a matter which the Minister for the Media<br />
may wish to remark on and you'll be able to get the full information<br />
from Senator McClelland.<br />
The Home Brewing of Beer. Cabinet decided to introduce<br />
legislation to amend the Excise Act to allow the brewing of beer<br />
by individuals for their own consumption. Senator Murphy has the<br />
full details. Wh~ a Delivery Quotas and First Advance. Cabinet today gave<br />
consideration to the question of wheat quotas for the 1973 pool<br />
and the level of the first advance in relation to that pool.<br />
Certain decisions were taken, but as you would know, wheat quotas<br />
is a matter involving the States. The next step therefore is for the<br />
decision to be conveyed to the States and discussed with them. My<br />
colleague, the Minister for Primary Industry, will be taking this<br />
up and I'm sure he will release details as soon as he is able to do<br />
SO. </p>
<p>4.<br />
Gentlemen, that completes the business the Cabinet<br />
Submissions, and the business of the Cabinet.<br />
Q: Mr Barnard, could you give us some indication of the number of<br />
troops that are going to be kept in Sinapore when the battalion and<br />
the artillery battery come home at the end--o-this year or early<br />
next year?<br />
Acting No, at this stage I cannot give you any indication.<br />
The matter is quite clearly under consideration. The Prime Minister<br />
has made a statement on this matter and I would not want to enlarge<br />
Upon it except to say this, since I have no doubt that it will be<br />
raised with me and I'm now referring to the question of the Signal<br />
Section. As soon as I became informed on this matter I immediately<br />
issued instructions that alternative arrangements were to be made<br />
for facilities to be provided for the Signal Section back in<br />
Australia. That information and that request that decision was<br />
conveyed to my Department and they are acting on it. There are some-<br />
I suppose if one dealt with a breakdown of the forces in Singaporethere<br />
are some forces probably that would be required but I would<br />
not be able to give you at this stage precisely any accurate figures<br />
in relation to the number who would be expected to remain for this<br />
purpose. It has been suggested that 500 to 600 might be kept there.<br />
Would this be an accurate estimation do you think?<br />
Acting The matter is still under consideration.<br />
If the Federal Conference of the Labor Party decides that all<br />
troops come home will the Government bring them home?<br />
Acting . If the Federal Conference of the Party makes a<br />
decision then I think as it was suggested quite recently that the<br />
Prime minister would accede to a decision, a decision of a properly<br />
constituted conference.<br />
Sir, you said you'd given instructions for the Signals Unit<br />
to come back. It was suggested last week by a senior source I<br />
understand that this wouldn't be until 1975. Do you think that<br />
it will now be advanced? And secondly can you tell us on the record<br />
what the function of the Signals Unit in Singapore is?<br />
Acting No, I cannot. That's the answer to your second part.<br />
But in relation to the first part, then I can assure you that<br />
whatever instructions and whatever decision I make in relation to<br />
bringing the Signals Unit back to Australia will be made on the<br />
basi~ s that it should be done Wi thout any delay. Let me amplify that:<br />
you cannot bring back a Signals Unit without certain facilities<br />
being available for them.<br />
Sir, that doesn't quite clarify the point. Will it be before<br />
1975? Acting I'm not able to answer that question at this stage.<br />
Sir, can we get some idea of your hopes on what you know...<br />
Acting In view of what has been said and what I have said<br />
that I would want to ensure that there is no undue delay.<br />
Q: Mr Barnard, you make the point that when you were told of </p>
<p>this existence of the Unit in Singapore you decided it should be<br />
brought back to Australia. When were-you told?<br />
Acting At the same time as the Prime Minister.<br />
Was there any discussion or decision in Cabinet about making<br />
greater use of the Commonwealth Savings Bank loans for housing to<br />
promote competition among the other banks?<br />
Acting No.<br />
Q. Mr Barnard, did Dr Cairns raise the question of revaluation<br />
and the way the decision was reached?<br />
Acting No, he did not. I put it to the Cabinet that any<br />
economic decisions should quite properly be left until the Prime<br />
Minister returned to Australia and that was accepted without question<br />
by the Cabinet.<br />
Sir, have officials of the Department of Defence or the Army<br />
advised the Queensland Premier that Australia should retain control<br />
of the islands it presently holds in the Torres Strait for strategic<br />
reasons? Were these discussions with Defe3&amp; se -officiawlhsic h<br />
Mr Bjelke-Petersen is alleged to have said took place did they take<br />
place with your knowledge were they official or unofficial?<br />
Acting I have no knowledge of the matter at all.' There has<br />
been some discussion as you know by correspondence between the<br />
Premier of Queensland and the Prime Minister.<br />
But you are unaware that Defence Department officials have<br />
spoken to the Queensland Premier?<br />
( 0 OAfc tiingt . I cannot confirm or deny it. I have no knowledge<br />
Mr Barnard, as Shadow Defence Minister you toured Pine Gap.<br />
As Defence Minister yesterday you toured Pine Gap. Can you tell us<br />
whether you were shown-things yesterday that you weren't shown in<br />
Opposition and can you give us 8ome indication of whether you plan<br />
to allow Opposition M. P. s and other M. P. s in Australia greater<br />
access than you had to these bases?<br />
Acting Yesterday and Sunday I visited Woomera and Alice<br />
Springs. I had been to these centres before but -yowui ll remember<br />
that I indicated when I was asked a question on this I think at<br />
the first Press Conference that the Prime Minister held what<br />
I would be doing about the bases in Australia. So I visited the<br />
joint Defence establishment at these centres Sunday and yesterday.<br />
I did that because I wanted to be in a position as I indicated<br />
during that first Press. Conference that I believed I had a<br />
responsibility to make a statement to the national Parliament<br />
and in doing so to inform the people of Australia. What I have said<br />
in the past in relation to these matters and any criticism I've made<br />
in relation to the Parliament itself was that there was never an<br />
opportunity for an informed discussion. The purpose of my visit to<br />
these areas was to bring myself up to date on these matters to enable<br />
me to be able to present a statement to the Federal Parliament as<br />
soon as possible. That statement will be considered by the Cabinet<br />
by the Parliamentary Labor Party and by the Government and it will<br />
be delivered in the Parliament.<br />
Could I press you on the first point. Were you shown things as<br />
Minister that you weren't allowed to see before you were Minister? </p>
<p>Acting The only thing that I can say all I would say<br />
in answer to that question is that when I visited ' the establishment*<br />
as the Deputy Leader of the Opposition I was shown the utmost courtesy<br />
and my visit on this occasion was no different.<br />
Sir, do you propose giving the Parliament the opportunity<br />
for informed discussion on these installations?<br />
Acting If I make a statement to the Parliament as I will be<br />
then naturally that statement will be open to debate.<br />
Sir, would the Government consider allox-inq the Press to<br />
inspect the installations at Pine Gap member-s of the Press?<br />
Acting I think that on these questions you should wait until<br />
I have made the statements to Parliament. You'll be able to question<br />
me further on them. Naturally one of the matters that I am looking<br />
at if I have been critical in the past would be the rights of<br />
members of Parliament and others.<br />
You'll be giving a detailed briefing to Parliament about<br />
Pine Gap and Woomera. Can you give me some general indication now<br />
as to what the bases are all about?<br />
Acting I do not believe, as I have said before, that I<br />
ought to make statements on these matters until I have the<br />
opportunity to inform the Parliament. I have been critical myself<br />
in the Federal Parliament on other occasions about statements on<br />
important matters being issued outside the Parliament. I think<br />
the nation has a right to be informed and it should be informed<br />
through the Parliament and I will do that.<br />
On a general note, have you learnt anything or were you shown<br />
anything that could make anyone believe that Pine Gap or Woomera<br />
might possibly be a nuclear target?<br />
Acting I'm sure that when I make my statement to Parliament<br />
you will have the answer to that question.<br />
Q. Mr Barnard, back to the Si-p~ Signals Unit why was it<br />
apparently suggested last week that the reason for us keeping<br />
Australian logistic troops in Singapore was to screen the Signals<br />
Unit there when it was only two or three years ago that the main<br />
Australian Army force moved from Terandah to Singapore and up to<br />
that stage no screen was apparently thought necessary?<br />
Acting I said a few moments ago that one could give a<br />
breakdown I haven't the figures before me of troops who would be<br />
stationed in Singapore of the men who are stationed now in<br />
Singapore, but who certainly would have no relationship to the Unit<br />
that you've just mentioned.<br />
Sir, you've said that you can't give us any details of<br />
Pine Gap and the other bases at the moment because you want to save<br />
thaEt or Parliament. But you've announced a number of major<br />
decisions today Mr Whitlam has done so every Tuesday when he has<br />
been in Canberra. Presumably you've got good reason for regarding<br />
the Pine Gap business as something special. Could you tell us why<br />
that must wait for Parliament when other major decisions can be<br />
announced outside Parliament?<br />
Acting Because the decisions that I have outlined today are<br />
Cabinet decisions. They have been approved by Cabinet. The one that </p>
<p>7.<br />
you've raised has not been considered by Cabinet. It will be<br />
considered by Cabinet.<br />
Will you have to get any clearance from America before you<br />
make your statement about Pine Gap?<br />
Acting This is not a matter for the United States<br />
Government. This is a matter for the Australian Government, and<br />
it will determine the issue since it's a joint Defence installation<br />
I would regard it as a matter of courtesy that the statement, once<br />
it is cleared by the Government, should be available to them.<br />
Sir, do you intend to get in touch with them before you draft<br />
the statement or in view of what you<br />
Acting No, I will not be getting in touch with them.<br />
Mr Barnard, will the agreement with the American Government<br />
in relation to American bases in Australia will the agreements be<br />
tabled in Parliament to allow any form of debate?<br />
Acting the agreements?<br />
The agreements setting up the bases. Would they be tabled<br />
as well?<br />
Acting Again I'll be referring to those matters in the<br />
statement. Mr Barnard, Mr Connor last week spoke to the Japanese<br />
Government and has suggested that mineral contracts should be<br />
re-negotiated in the wake of the currency decision last week.<br />
Was there any discussion of this in Cabinet?<br />
Acting No.<br />
Sir, even if no discussion came up in Cabinet today on the<br />
matter of Commonwealth Bank interest rates, was a decision made on<br />
this last week or has any concrete plan on lowering interest rates<br />
before Cabinet at the moment?<br />
Acting No.<br />
Sir, again on the r-e-engqagement bonus, you've cleared up the<br />
tax side of it. I don't know whether you are issuing a special<br />
statement on this, but it's not quite clear who decides who's<br />
eligible how many you envisage would be eligible in any one year,<br />
or this year, and what the cost would be?<br />
Acting I will be able to get these figures. of course the<br />
re-engagement bonus has been paid already to some members of the<br />
forces. I haven't got the figures in front of me nor could I recall<br />
them immediately but, no doubt this information will be required by<br />
the Parliament and it is available. 4<br />
Mr Barnard, was the subject of the Public Service Board's<br />
circular sent last week to Departments dealing with the fourth week<br />
annual leave for public servants discussed by the Cabinet in the<br />
course of discussion on the subject of maternity leave. Was there<br />
any criticism of the Public Service Board's circular in Cabinet?<br />
Acting I'm sorry. I didn't get the last part of your<br />
question... </p>
<p>8.<br />
Did Cabinet or any members of Cabinet criticise the Public<br />
Service Board's circular sent to the Departments last week dealing<br />
with the fourth week annual leave?<br />
Acting Cabinet had a submission before it in relation to<br />
the four weeks annual leave auestion. It dealt with that and<br />
nothing else on this subject.<br />
Sir, in relation * to the controversy over the Singapore<br />
Signals Unit, Mr Hartley last week made a statement in which he said<br />
that this showed there was a problem in relationships between the<br />
Government and the Public Service. I've no doubt that you've seen<br />
this statement since it was in most newspapers and it applied to<br />
your Department. Would you like to agree with Mr Hartl. ey?<br />
Is there a problem in dealing with the Public Service? Is there a<br />
problem in them trying to run politicians?<br />
Acting The answer is no.<br />
Could you elaborate obviously this impression is abroad.<br />
Could you tell us why<br />
Acting I can see no conflict of opinion in this. It's<br />
merely an interpretation of the Government's decision and I think<br />
it's reasonable that there may be a request for an interpretation.<br />
The Government determined its attitude in relation to that to<br />
the query that was raised in this way.<br />
Was it on your instructions that a desk in your office was<br />
allegedly cleared out by a Defence liaison officer or was it on<br />
the Department's instructions?<br />
Acting A desk in my office?<br />
Yes, Sir,<br />
Acting Well it certainly was not on my instructions and<br />
I'm not aware of it.<br />
Q. Was it searched?<br />
Acting I'm not aware of it, but what I can do, I can<br />
assure you, is find out.<br />
Q. Sixr, are you satisfied that the bases at Pine Gap are forming<br />
p~ roper and correct function in relation to Australia's defence?<br />
Acting P. M.: AAcgtiagi nP, M .: t his I will be stating in my statement. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
