<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7703</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH LIZ HAYES, TODAY PROGRAM, NORTHERN TERRITORY, 9 AUGUST 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/08/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007703.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
IAn<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH LIZ HAYES, TODAY PROGAMb,<br />
NORTHERN TERRITORY, 9 AUGUST 1989<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
HAYES: It seems, I don't wish to be cynical, but maybe<br />
these exercises have a touch of the Andrew Peacocks the<br />
war you have when you're not having a war. Do we really<br />
need it?<br />
PM: Do we need the exercise?<br />
HAYES: Yes.<br />
PM: Well, the army and the Government wouldn't be engaged<br />
in an exercise like this which involves so much money unless<br />
it was regarded as necessary. We can't assume that we're<br />
always going to live in a benign atmosphere and if we're<br />
going to have the troops, the airforce, our naval people in<br />
a state where they can discharge their ultimate<br />
responsibility to this country, its defence, then they have<br />
to have the opportunity of training in circumstances which<br />
will best equip them to do that and that's precisely what<br />
this is about.<br />
HAYES: Well, I understand that we can't assume a great<br />
deal, but we do seem to be assuming just who the enemy might<br />
be and we're suggesting that the enemy will only come<br />
through the Top End. I mean, are you prepared to pinpoint<br />
who we're going to be concerned about?<br />
PM: No. I'm not saying who we're going to be concerned<br />
about, but I don't think there's very much chance of an<br />
attack from the Antarctic, particularly after we make it an<br />
international wilderness park and as a matter of logic it<br />
must come from the northern area. That's part of the effect<br />
I'm sorry.<br />
HAYES: I understand.<br />
PM: I'm sorry Liz, just wait a minute, I can't hear you<br />
while that's going over. Better now. Obviously if there is<br />
going to be any danger for Australia it must come from our<br />
northern approaches. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
HAYES: One of the things we do seem to be doing is showing<br />
any potential enemy what we are about. We have observers<br />
from other countries here looking at exactly how we're going<br />
about defending ourselves if the event should ever occur.<br />
PM4: Yes, well it's an eminently sensible thing to do isn't<br />
it? Do you think that we spend all this money on defence,<br />
we have these extremely capable officers and ranks, do you<br />
think we have all those things, that they'd make a mistake<br />
of having someone here that they think is going to be<br />
adverse to our best interests?<br />
HAYES: No<br />
PM: In television we make the assumption that you act in<br />
terms of what you regard as your best interests. You ought<br />
to make the same assumption about the defence forces.<br />
HAYES: Well moving on to the frigate contract, if I can,<br />
and what is our position now that the frigate contract<br />
doesn't necessarily seem as though it's going to go ahead<br />
with New Zealand?<br />
PM4: We don't know what the New Zealand position will be.<br />
We are still hoping that they will accept the responsibility<br />
which is involved, in our judgement, in being part of that<br />
deal. We've been proceeding on that basis. The fact that<br />
there's been a change of Prime Minister doesn't, in my<br />
judgement, necessarily mean that the chances of them<br />
accepting the deal have been diminished. I believe that Mr<br />
Palmer thinks that it is appropriate that New Zealand should<br />
be part of the deal and I hope that will be the decision<br />
because, as I pointed out to his predecessor and as I<br />
pointed out to him yesterday in a brief conversation I had<br />
when he rang me, that it would have unhelpful effects upon<br />
the Australia/ New Zealand relationship if that were not to<br />
be the case.<br />
HAYES: But there is debate continuing and if New Zealand<br />
should decide not to go ahead, do we still go ahead?<br />
PM: Of course we go ahead, there's never been any question<br />
of that.<br />
HAYES: We can afford to go ahead?<br />
PM: How many times do I have to say it, Liz, we're going<br />
ahead. it's a decision that has to be made and it will<br />
be made. It's just much better, not merely in economic<br />
terms, but it's much better in terms of the relationship and<br />
co-operative relationship between our two countries that<br />
they should be part of it. They can't have a position, and<br />
let's be quite frank about it, they can't have a position<br />
where they want to be part of a co-operative defence<br />
relationship between Australia and New Zealand but </p>
<p>essentially do it on the cheap. If they're going to be part<br />
of a co-operative defence relationship which we've sought to<br />
enhance in the circumstances of their withdrawal from ANZUS,<br />
then there are benefits for that in it and there are also<br />
obligations in our judgement.<br />
HAYES: If I could change subjects just slightly and that is<br />
to the rebel rugby union team which may be going off to<br />
South Africa and it would appear as though some Australians<br />
may participate in that, I mean, can you understand that<br />
players may still wonder why they're being asked not to play<br />
when Governments still do trade with South Africa?<br />
PM: The Government doesn't do trade with South Africa. we<br />
have imposed very considerable sanctions on South Africa and<br />
we're doing all that we can, not only in regard to Australia<br />
but to other countries to bring about that position. I'm<br />
not trying to condemn an individual simply because he thinks<br />
that he wants to do something that will gratify himself, I'm<br />
simply saying that like individuals, have to do certain<br />
things which have a broader perspective than just a<br />
perception of their immediate self interests. What is<br />
happening is that, as far as the rest of the world is<br />
concerned and as far as South Africa is concerned, coming an<br />
increasing realisation that they can't continue the<br />
abhorrent regime which denies the eqality of human beings in<br />
terms of opportunity, that that must come to an end and that<br />
these people are not being asked just to advance the<br />
interests of sports, that they're being asked by South<br />
Africa to help to advance their own image and increase their<br />
own acceptability. I ask individuals to understand that, in<br />
a sense, they have responsibilities beyond themselves and I<br />
hope they will do that.<br />
HAYES: Well, we'll leave you on that note, Mr Hawke. We do<br />
thank you for joining us and we hope you enjoy Exercise<br />
Kangaroo.<br />
PM: It's been a pleasure. may I take this opportunity of<br />
saying how all Australians ought to be tremendously proud of<br />
their armed services. I've had the opportunity of seeing<br />
here not only their efficiency, but their commitment and<br />
their pride and I hope that's something that's shared by all<br />
Australians. HAYES: I can say, Mr Hawke, we've also noticed this at<br />
first hand ourselves. Thank you very much.<br />
PM: Thank you very much indeed.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
