<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5311</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/03/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005311.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGOED 6.00 PM PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA SUNDAY 30 MARC ) 4<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
It is now three months since the Russian army rolled into<br />
Afghanistan. That cold-blooded and brutal invasion drew universal condemnation.<br />
Russia had stepped out from behind its iron curtain for the<br />
first time to use its forces against a sovereign non-aligned<br />
Third World country.<br />
Today, the Soviet troops are still there.<br />
The murder 6f Afghans continues.<br />
Tragically, there is not a single sign that the Soviet leadership<br />
has paid any heed to the world's revulsion of its actions.<br />
On the contrary, there are still upwards of 90,000 Soviet troops<br />
in Afghanistan and some 30,000 to 40,000 more massed on the<br />
Soviet-Afghanistan border.<br />
If anything, the Soviets are increasing their military occupation<br />
of Afghanistan.<br />
In the past few weeks, Soviet forces have been heavily involved<br />
in suppressing resistance in the Kunar Valley near the Pakistan<br />
border. My information is that this action has been particularly ruthless<br />
and brutal. All but a handful of the valley's population of<br />
160,000 has been forced to flee.<br />
This once fertile food bowl has been defoliated its people<br />
have fled: those who remain are reported to be suffering<br />
injuries consistent with the use of napalm or phospherous weapons.<br />
What has the Soviet occupation meant to the people of Afghanistan?<br />
For the Afghan people, the large scale repression, terrorism,<br />
murder and torture have now become their way of life and the<br />
tyranny of violence has been imposed upon them.<br />
There are already 600,000 refugees in the United Nations-controlled<br />
camps in Pakistan and elsewhere. .2<br />
.4113f?, 1312Y ' Rg-</p>
<p>I am advised this figure is expected to reach one million,<br />
comparable to the exodus of Kampuchean refugees that so touched<br />
the world.<br />
In one prison in Kabul, the commandant boasts that his aim is<br />
t o reduce Afghanistan's population to around one million to<br />
achieve a " communist" society.<br />
Purges of intellectual and religious leaders are continually<br />
taking place.<br />
There are reports of Soviet-supervised torture dating from 1 978<br />
-that include drownings in latrine pits, mass drowning, and<br />
the night-time burying alive of village male populations.<br />
Ther aefrhrrpts in the central Afghan region of<br />
submission by starvation of village political and religious<br />
' Leaders. Eone incident on the outskirts of Kabul 150 people were burnt<br />
alive, and a further 150 buried alive.<br />
rhese reports have been documented by an observer from the Parisbased<br />
International Human Rights Federation a responsible<br />
organisation. which operates independently of any government and<br />
is recognised by the Council of Europe.<br />
on top of these atrocities come the reports in the world free<br />
press of: the murder, on April 20, 1979, in, the village of<br />
Kerala, of the entire male population of 1,200<br />
men and boys over 7 years old;<br />
the use of helicopter gun ships to put down peaceful<br />
protest rallies in Kabul with reported casualties of-<br />
800-1000 dead and 2,000 wounded.<br />
That's the story of Afghanistan today.<br />
Can that leave any doubt in anyone's mind as to why the w~ orld is<br />
so repulsed.<br />
Yet there is a tendency to regard that continued occupation of<br />
Afghanistan by the Soviet forces as a fact of life and to<br />
let it slip from the day-to-~ day consciousness.<br />
Perhaps that is why there are some among us who now ask us to<br />
re-think our decision on the Olympic boycott.<br />
As I have said all along, the issue before us is not the Olympic<br />
Games the issue is, and always will be, the Soviet suppression<br />
of the Afghan people.<br />
Are these horrific accounts of human tragedy and suffering not<br />
the real answer to those who doubt the wisdom of our course? 3 </p>
<p>Let me remind you again of how the Russians view the Olympic<br />
Games. They claim it is as " universal recognition of the<br />
historical importance and correctness of the course of our<br />
country's foreign policy".<br />
When you think about this whole question, ask yourself:<br />
" Do you want the Australian flag raised in Moscow?"<br />
" Do you want our national anthem played in Moscow?"<br />
Should Australia pay homage to tryranny?<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
