<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6751</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER TO THE TENTH CONFERENCE OF ASIAN AND PACIFIC LABOUR MINISTERS MELBOURNE, 1 OCTOBER 1985</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/10/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006751.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIM4E MINISTER TO THE<br />
TENTH CONFERENCE OF ASIAN AND PACIFIC LABOUR MINISTERS<br />
MELBOURNE, 1 OCTOBER 1985<br />
DELEGATES BOTH PERSONALLY, AND ON BEHALF OF THE GOVERNMENT AND THE<br />
PEOPLE OF AUSTRALIA I WELCOME ALL PARTICIPANTS TO THIS,<br />
THE 10th BIENNIAL CONFERENCE OF ASIAN AND PACIFIC LABOUR<br />
MINISTERS. I WOULD LIKE TO INCLUDE A PERSONAL WELCOME<br />
TO MY LONGSTAN4DING FRIEND AND COLLEAGUE THE DIRECTORGENERAL<br />
OF THE INTERNATIONAL LABOUR ORGANISATION,<br />
FRA14CIS BLANCHARD, AND TO THANK HIM FOR HIS ATTEN4DANCE<br />
AND ADDRESS TO THIS CONFERENCE.<br />
IT IS FITTING TO PAY TRIBUTE TO THE WORK OF THE ILO,<br />
WHICH HAS OBSERVER STATUS AT THIS CONFERENCE. AS MANY<br />
OF YOU ARE AWARE, THE PRIMARY TASK OF THE ILO IS TO SET<br />
TINTER1NATIONAL LABOUR STANDARDS OF UNIVERSAL CHARACTER,<br />
AND TO PROMOTE SOCIAL JUSTICE AND BETTER WORKIN G<br />
CONDITIONS FOR ALL WORKERS. TO THIS END, THE ILO NOT<br />
ONLY ADOPTS CONVENTIONS AND RECOMMENDATIONS, BUT<br />
ACTIVELY ASSISTS COUNTRIES TO FORMULATE AND IMPLEMENT<br />
NATIONAL LABOUR POLICIES IN THE LIGHT OF THOSE<br />
CONVENTIONS AND RECOMMENDATIONS.<br />
I AM PROUD OF THE LONG HISTORY OF THIS COUNTRY'S CLOSE<br />
LINKS WITH THE ILO. AS MR BLANCHARD HAS NOTED AUSTRALIA<br />
WAS ONE OF THE ILO'S FOUNDING MEMBER COUNTRIES IN 1919.<br />
IN ADDITION, AUSTR'. LIA IS CURRENTLY A MEMBER OF THE<br />
ILO'S GOVERNING BODY.<br />
PERSONALLY, I HAVE LONG BEEN COMMITTED TO THE TRIPARTITE<br />
APPROACH WHICH IS AN ESSENTIAL ASPECT OF THE I. L. O.<br />
SUCH AN APPROACH IS CENTRAL TO THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
GOVERNMENT'S CONSIDERATION OF PROBLEMS AND ISSUES. AND<br />
THIS APPROACH ONE OF TRIPARTISM IS PROVING<br />
REMARKABLY SUCCESSFUL. </p>
<p>THE RECENT OECD) EMPLOYMENT OUTLOOK FOR SEPTEM4BER 1985<br />
CONFIRMS THE SOUNDNESS OF MY GOVERNMENT'S PRICES AND<br />
INCOMES ACCORD AND OUR GENERAL ECONOMIC POLICIES. THE<br />
REPORT'S PROJECTIONS SHOW AUSTRALIA'S LABOUR MiARKET WILL<br />
BE THE MOST BUOYANT IN THE OECD IN 1985 AND 1986. AFTER<br />
SOME SEVEN YEARS OF VIRTUALLY STAGNANT JOB GROWTH PRIOR<br />
TO 1983, THIS IS A TREMENDOUS TURNAROUND. EMPLOYMENT<br />
GROWTH IN AUSTRALIA IS FORECAST, BY THE OECD, TO RISE BY<br />
2 3/ 4 PER CENT IN 1985 AND 2 PER CENT IN 1986. THIS<br />
COMPARES WITH JOB GROWTH IN THE OECD AS A WHOLE OF 1 1/ 4.<br />
PER CENT IN 1985 AND 1 PER CENT IN 1986.<br />
AUSTRALIA IS CLEARLY OUTSTRIPPING EMPLOYMENT GROWTH IN<br />
OTHER COUNTRIES, AND WE ARE DOING IT UNDER POLICIES<br />
BASED ON4 THE PRICES AND INCOMES ACCORD AN ACCORD WHICH<br />
REPRESENTS OUR C pNSENSUS APPROACH TO GOVERNMENT.<br />
I AM AWARE THAT THE PRINCIPAL ITEMS ON THE CAPLM<br />
AGENDA ARE THE IMPACT OF NATIONAL LABOUR POLICIES ON<br />
YOUNG PEOPLE IN THE REGION AND TECHNICAL CO-OPERATION IN<br />
THE LABOUR FIELD.<br />
IN THIS ADDRESS I SHOULD LIKE, AMONGST OTHER THINGS, TO<br />
HIGHLIGHT THE CONSTRUCTIVE ROLE OF THE ILO IN FOCUSSING<br />
ATTENTION ON YOUNG PEOPLE.<br />
THE 1983 INTERNATIONAL LABOUR CONFERENCE ADOPTED A<br />
RESOLUTION ON YOUNG PEOPLE REQUESTING THE ILO TO<br />
UNDERTAKE A SURVEY ON YOUNG PEOPLE AND WORK AS PART OF<br />
INTERNATIONAL YOUTH YEAR IYY. THE 72ND INTERNATIONAL<br />
LABOUR CONFERENCE IN 1986 WILL INCLUDE A GENERAL<br />
DISCUSSION ON YOUNG PEOPLE. SUCH ACTIVITIES WILL<br />
PROVIDE MANY OPPORTUNITIES FOR MEMBER COUNTRIES TO<br />
DISCUSS A VAST RANGE OF POLICY OPTIONS AND TO EXCHANGE<br />
INFORMATION.<br />
THE UNITED NATIONS ALSO IS TO BE COMMENDED FOR<br />
RECOGNISING THE IMPORTANCE OF YOUNG PEOPLE IN DECLARING<br />
1985 INTERNATIONAL YOUTH YEAR. HOWEVER, WE ALL<br />
RECOGNISE THAT WHILE INTERNATIONAL YOUTH YEAR IS A<br />
USEFUL AND A NECESSARY MEANS OF DRAWING ATTENTION TO THE<br />
NEEDS, ASPIRATIONS AND CONTRIBUTIONS OF YOUNG PEOPLE,<br />
WHAT IS NEEDED ABOVE ALL ELSE ARE SUSTAINABLE LONG-TERll<br />
ACTIVITIES AND POLICIES, RATHER THAN JUST ONE YEAR OF<br />
CONCENTRATED EFFORT.<br />
YOUNG PEOPLE ARE AM4ONG OUR GREATEST RESOURCES. THEY<br />
MAKE AN IMPORTANT CONTRIBUTION TO OUR NATIONS'<br />
WELL-BEING WHETHER THAT BE THROUGH THEIR STUDIES,<br />
THEIR LEISURE AND SPORTING PURSUITS, THEIR PART IN<br />
FAMILY LIFE, OR AS MEMBERS OF OUR RESPECTIVE LABOUR<br />
FORCES. COLLECTIVELY THEY ARE OUR NATIONS' FUTURE.<br />
COUNTRIES WITHIN OUR REGION HAVE EXPERIENCED A<br />
SIGNIFICANT' GROWTH IN POPULATION WHICH HAS LED TO LARGE<br />
NUMBERS OF Y( OUNG PEOPLE COMING ONTO THF LABOUR MARKET. </p>
<p>IN ADDITION, RAPID TECHNOLOGICAL CHANGE, SLOW ECONOMI1C<br />
GROWH RATES AND DECLINING AGRICULTURAL OPPORTUNITIES<br />
ARE LEADING TO ACCELERATED URBANISATION AND TO HIGH<br />
LEVELS OF UNEMPLOYMENT, BORNE DISPROPORTIONATELY BY<br />
YOUNG PEOPLE.<br />
THUS, THERE IS KEEN INTEREST IN THE ASIA/ PACIFIC REGION,<br />
SUPPORTING AS IT DOES APPROXIMATELY HALF OF THE WORLD'S<br />
POPULATION, FOR A CONFERENCE WHICH DEALS WITH THE IMPACT<br />
OF LABOUR M4ARKET POLICIES ON YOUNG PEOPLE.<br />
MANY OP' OUR YOUNG PEOPLE ARE INADEQUATELY PREPARED FOR<br />
ENTRY INTO WORKING LIFE. UNFORTUNATELY TOO 14ANY OF OUR<br />
YOUNG PEOPLE LACK THE NECESSARY BASIC SKILLS TO<br />
CONTRIBUTE IMMEDIATELY TO THE LABOUR MARKET.<br />
TOO MIANY OF OUJR YOUNG PEOPLE DO NOT HAVE AN ADEQUATE<br />
KNOWLEDGE OF * OCCUPATIONS, THE ORGANISATION OF WORK, HOW<br />
TO FIND A JOB, HOW TO PRESENT THEM4SELVES TO EMPLOYERS.<br />
AND TOO MANY YOUNG PEOPLE ARE ILL-EQUIPPED TO SURVIVE<br />
WITHOUT THE SUPPORT OF FAMILY AND CLOSE FRIENDS.<br />
IN THE DECADE TO 1983, UNEMPLOYMENT IN AUSTRALIA ROSE TO<br />
LEVELS UNPARALLELED SINCE THE 1930S. THE IMPACT ON<br />
YOUNG PEOPLE-OF DEPRESSED CONDITIONS IN THE LABOUR<br />
MARKET AND THE ECONOMY IN THIS PERIOD WAS PARTICULARLY<br />
SEVERE. THE UNEMPLOYMENT RATE HAS NOW IMPOVED<br />
CONSIDERABLY, THOUGH REGRETABLY SOME 216,300 YOUNG<br />
PEOPLE OR 14.4% OF THE LABOUR FORCE WERE STILL RECORDED<br />
AS UNEMPLOYED AND SEEKING FULL-TIME WORK IN JULY 1985.<br />
THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT HAS IN T-HE PAST TWO AND A HALF<br />
YEARS INITIATED A RANGE OF INQUIRIES WHICH HAVE PROVIDED<br />
THE BASIS FOR A CONSTRUCTIVE RESPONSE TO THE PROBLEMS<br />
FACILG YOUNG AUSTRALIANS.<br />
IN PkRTICULAR, WE HAVE THIS YEAR, ANNOUNCED A STRATEGYPRIORITY<br />
ONE FOR YOUNG AUSTRALIANS WHICH WILL BRING<br />
INTO HARMONY A NUMBER OF POLICIES AND PROGRAMS AIMED AT<br />
NOT ONLY REDUCING STILL FURTHER THE NUMBER OF YOUNG<br />
PEOPLE WHO EXPERIENCE UNEMPLOYMENT BUT ALSO IMPROVING<br />
THE NGE OF ALTERNATIVES ONCE THEY HAVE REACHED POSTCOMPUkLSORY<br />
SCHOOLING AGE.<br />
THER-T NRE FOUR PRINCIPAL PARTS OF MY GOVERNMENT'S<br />
STRA:-EGY FOR YOUNG PEOPLE.<br />
FIRST, WE ARE MAKING IT POSSIBLE, FOR THOSE WHO WISH TO<br />
DO SO, TO CONTINUE THEIR EDUCATION AND TRAINING BEYOND<br />
POST -COMPULSORY YEARS. WE ARE OFFERING MORE PLACES IN<br />
TERTIARY INSTITUTIONS, AND REMOVING THE DISPARITY<br />
BETWEEN EDUCATION ALLOWANCES AND UNEMPLOYMENT BENEFITS. </p>
<p>SECOND, WE ARE INTRODUCING ( AND THIS WILL DOUBTLESS BE<br />
OF MOST INTEREST TO YOUR HERE TODAY) A NEW COMBINATION<br />
OF TRAINING AND WORK, CALLED TRAINEESHIPS.<br />
WITH TRAINEESHIPS, OUR GOAL IS TO GREATLY IMPROVE THE<br />
VOCATIONAL TRAINING OF THOSE NUMEROUS YOUNG PEOPLE WHO<br />
DO NOT ASPIRE TO HIGHER EDUCATION AND WHO FIND<br />
DIFFICULTIES ENTERING THE LABOUR MARKET BECAUSE OF THEIR<br />
LACK OF SKILLS AND EXPERIENCE.<br />
TRAINEESHIPS WILL LAST FOR A YEAR, WILL PROVIDE<br />
EMPLOYMENT,' A WAGE, AND TRAINING BOTH ON-AND-OFF-THEJOB.<br />
WE WANT 1OO10O YOUNG PEOPLE TO BENEFIT FROM<br />
TRAINEESHIPS IN THE FIRST YEAR OF OPERATION AND FOR THAT<br />
NUMBER TO INCREASE To 75,000 IN 1988.<br />
. ATHE<br />
GOVERNMENT'S STRATEGY ALSO INCLUDES A<br />
RATIONALISATION OF THE VARIOUS INCOM4E SUPPORT SCHEMES<br />
THAT WE ARE ABLE TO OFFER DISADVAN4TAGED YOUNG PEOPLE.<br />
THE! MAIN SCHEMES WILL BECOME AGE-RELATED, AND INDEXED TO<br />
ENSURE THEY KEEP THEIR REAL VALUE.<br />
THE FOURTH PART OF OUR STRATEGY RECOGNISES THAT YOUNG<br />
PEOPLE NEED OTHER SUPPORT PROVISIONS BEYOND THOSE THAT I<br />
HAVE ALREADY MENTIONED, PARTICULARLY IF THEY ARE TO MAKE<br />
A SUCCESSFUL TRAN4SITION TO ADULTHOOD.<br />
THESE OTHER ARRANGEMENTS RELATE TO SUPPORT IN SUCH AREAS<br />
AS ACCOMMODATION, TRAINING IN FUNDAMENTAL LIVING SKILLS,<br />
HEALTH, AND DRUG EDUCATION.<br />
ALTHOUGH THE REDUCTION OF YOUTH WAGES HAS BEEN ADVOCATED<br />
BY SOME AS AN ANSWER TO YOUTH UNEMPLOYMENT, THE<br />
GOVERNMENT REJECTS THIS SIMPLISTIC VIEW AND ACCEPTS THE<br />
NEED FOR A CONSTRUCTIVE, MULTI-PRONGED AND POSITIVE<br />
APPROACH WHICH RAISES THE PRODUCTIVITY OF OUR YOUNG<br />
PEOPLE. SUCH AN APPROACH WILL ENHANCE THEIR EMPLOYM4ENT<br />
PROSPECTS AND INCREASE THEIR FLEXIBILITY IN THE LABOUR<br />
FORCE. THE SOLUTIONS TO HIGH YOUTH UNEM4PLOY14ENT ARE NOT SIMPLE,<br />
OR CHEAP, OR EASY, OR SWIFT AND THEY NEED THE FULL<br />
COOPERATION OF ALL SECTIO&gt;: S OF THE COMMUNITY.<br />
CO-OPERATION BETWEEN ALL SECTIONS IS THE VERY BASIS OF<br />
OUR POLICIES. INDEED Trii ;\' INTH CONFERENCE OF ASIAN AND<br />
PACIFIC LABOUR MINISTERS CONCLUDED THAT PROBLEMS FACING<br />
PARTICULAR COUNTRIES IN REGION COULD NOT BE OVERCOME<br />
THROUGH LONE EFFORTS,. BUT REQUIRED THE CLOSE COOPERATION<br />
AND EFFORT OF ALL COUNTRIES ACTING TOGETHER.<br />
A FURTHER ASPECT OF THIS CO-OPERATIVE PROCESS, ON WHICH<br />
THE 9TH CAPLM CONFERENCE PLACED GREAT STRESS, IS THE<br />
NEED FOR PROMOTION OF TECHNICAL CO-OPERATION IN<br />
EMPLOYMENT AND LABOUR FORCE DEVELOPMENT. SUCH PROMOTION<br />
PRESENTS AN EFFECTIVE WAY OF ASSISTING COUNTRIES IN<br />
THEIR SOCIAL AND ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT AND IN THE<br />
IMPROVEMENT OF WORKING CONDITIONS. </p>
<p>IN THE GOVERNMENT'S VIEW, AUSTRALIA HAS AN IMPORTANT<br />
ROLE TO PLAY IN THIS ARENA, PARTICULARLY AS WE ARE PART<br />
OF THE MOST ECONOMICALLY DYNAMIC REGION IN THE WORLD.<br />
IN THIS CONTEXT, IT IS IMPORTANT TO NOTE THAT<br />
CONSTRUCTIVE STEPS ARE BEING TAKEN TO BRIDGE GAPS<br />
REM4AINING IN RELATIONSHIPS BETWEEN AUSTRALIA AND ITS<br />
PACIFIC AND ASIAN NEIGHBOURS.<br />
AT THE RECENT SOUTH PACIFIC FORUM, UNDER THE AUSPICES OF<br />
THE SOUTH PACiFIC REGIONAL TRADE AND ECONOMIC<br />
COOPERATION AGREEMENT ( SPARTECA), I ANNOUNCED THAT AS<br />
FROM THE BEGINNING OF 1987, ALL GOODS FROM THE FORUM<br />
ISLAND COUNTRIES AND PAPUA NEW GUINEA WILL ENTER<br />
AUSTRALIA ON A DUTY FREE UNRESTRICTED BASIS EXCEPT FOR<br />
THOSE COVERED BY AUSTRALIAN SECTORAL POLICIES. SUCH<br />
LIBERALISED MARKET ACCESS SHOULD REMOVE MANY<br />
DI FFI CULT IES.' THESE COUNTRIES MAY HAVE ENCOUNTERED<br />
EXPORTING TO'AUSTRALIA, AS WELL AS INCREASING EMPLOYMENT<br />
OPPORTUNITIES IN THOSE COUNTRIES.<br />
AT THE FORUM BOTH AUSTRALIA AND NEW ZEALAND ALSO OFFERED<br />
TO ENTER INTO DISCUSSIONS WITH THE SOUTH PACIFIC ISLAND<br />
COUNTRIES ABOUT WHETHER THERE WOULD BE ADVANTAGE TO THEM<br />
IN ENTERING A BROADENED AUSTRALIA/ NEW ZEALAND CLOSER<br />
ECONOMIC RELATIONS AGREEMENT. THIS OFFER.-WHICH<br />
CARRIES IMPORTANT IMPLICATIONS FOR LONG-TERM TRADE<br />
RELATIONS WITHIN THE REGION-WAS INTRODUCED BY THE FORUM<br />
AND WILL BE FURTHER CONSIDERED AT NEXT YEAR'S MEETING OF<br />
THE REGIONAL TRADE COMMITTEE.<br />
WE HAVE ALSO ESTABLISHED A SOUTH PACIFIC REGIONAL TEAM4<br />
TO PROVIDE SPECIALISED ADVICE TO THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
DEVELOPMENT ASSISTANCE BUREAU ON THE PARTICULAR<br />
DEVELOPMENT NEEDS AND CONCERNS OF SMALL ISLAND<br />
COUNTRIES. AMONG THE RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED IN RESPECT OF TECHNICAL<br />
CO-OPERATION AT CAPLM 9 WERE THE NEED FOR PARTICULAR<br />
ATTENTION TO BE PAID TO OCCUPATIONAL HEALTH AND SAFETY<br />
AND THE AGREEMENT TO PROM OTE THE ESTABLISHMENT OR<br />
IMPROVEMENT OF RESEARCH INSTITUTES AND REHABILITATION<br />
FACILITIES. AUSTRALIA COMMENDS THESE FIELDS OF ENDEAVOUR TO CAPLM<br />
FOR CONSIDERATION IN THE CONTEXT OF INTERNATIONAL COOPERATION.<br />
I WOULD LIKE TO POINT OUT THAT WHILE TECHNICAL COOPERATION<br />
IS A STANDING AGENDA ITEM AT CAPLM, THE<br />
MATCHING OF RHETORIC WITH ACTIONS CAN BE DIFFICULT TO<br />
ACHIEVE. THIS DIFFICULTY ARISES IN PART BECAUSE LABOUR AFFAIRS<br />
ARE NOT ALWAYS GIVEN HIGH PRIORITY BY AID CO-ORDINATING<br />
BODIES IN DEVELOPING COUNTRIES. IT IS ALSO OFTEN<br />
DIFFICULT FOR MULTILATERAL PROGRAMS TO FOCUS ADEQUATELY </p>
<p>ON THE NEEDS OF INDIVIDUAL COUNTRIES AND APPROPRIATE<br />
MEANS OF SATISFYING THOSE NEEDS, ESPECIALLY AS<br />
MULTILATERAL AGENCIES TYPICALLY ARE FINANCIALLY<br />
CONSTRAINED.<br />
WE THEREFORE WELCOME THE PROPOSALS FOR GREATER EMPHASIS<br />
ON REGIONAL CO-OPERATION AND COLLECTiVE SELF RELIANCE<br />
THROUGH SCHEMES SUCH AS THE ASIAN AND PACIFIC SKILLS<br />
DEVELOPING PROGRAM.<br />
SUCH PROPOSALS ARE A POSITIVE STEP IN THE DIRECTION OF<br />
ENCOURAGING GREATER SELF SUFFICIENCY WHILST AT THE SAME<br />
TIME INVOLVING MORE INTERACTION AM4ONG INDIVIDUAL<br />
COUNTRIES OF,, THE REGION. I WISH DELEGATES EVERY SUCCESS<br />
IN ACHIEVING-THESE DESIRABLE AIMS.<br />
AT THE INTERNATIONAL LEVEL, THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT<br />
RECOGNISEq TiIE IMPORTANCE OF THE TECHNICAL CO-OPERATION<br />
ACTIVITIES 0F THE ILO WHICH SUPPORT DEVELOPING COUNTRIES<br />
IN FORM4ULATING EFFECTIVE LABOUR POLICIES.<br />
MY GOVERNMENT RECOGNISES THAT HUMAN RESOURCES<br />
DEVELOPMENT TO WHICH TECHNICAL CO-OPERATION CAN MAKE A<br />
SIGNIFICANT CONTRIBUTION IS AN IMPORTANT AREA WHICH<br />
PLACES STRONG PRESSURES ON LABOUR ADMINISTRATIONS. AS A<br />
MEMBER OF THE ILO AND ITS GOVERNING BODY, MY COUNTRY IS<br />
CONCERNED THAT THE LIM'ITED RESOURCES AVAILABLE FOR<br />
TECHNICAL CO-OPERATION SHOULD BE DIRECTED TO AREAS OF<br />
GREATEST NEED AND BELIEVES THAT GREATER EMPHASIS SHOULD<br />
BE PLACED ON MEASURES DESIGNED TO IMPROVE THE QUALITY,<br />
EFFECTIVENESS AND EVALUATION OF PROGRAMS.<br />
AGAINST THAT BACKGROUND, AUSTRALIA IS PLEASED TO INFORM<br />
THE MEETING THAT IT RATIFIED ILO CONVEN4TIONS NO 142 ON<br />
HUMAN RESOURCES DEVELOPM4ENT AND NO 150 ON LABOUR<br />
ADMINISTRATION ON 10 SEPTEMBER 1985.<br />
THROUGH ITS AID PROGRAMS, AUSTRALIA PROVIDES A<br />
SIGNIFICANT CONTRIBUTION TO THE DEVELOPMENT OF HUMAN<br />
RESOURCES IN OTHER COUNTRIES OF THE REGION.<br />
SPECIFICALLY, WE SPENT OVER $ 137 MILLION DOLLARS IN<br />
1984-85 ON TRAINING PROGRAMS. IN ADDITION WE CONTINUED<br />
TO SUPPORT LABOR RELATED PROJECTS SUCH AS THE TECHNICAL<br />
EDUCATION PROJECT FOR INDONESIA.<br />
DELEGATES, I HAVE SPOKEN OF THE PRO13LEMS OF YOUTH<br />
UNEMPLOYMENT IN OUR REGION AND MY GOVERNMENT'S PRIORITY<br />
ONE STRATEGY. IN THIS TIME OF DOUBT AND UNCERTAINTY IN<br />
WHICH WE LIVE, MANY OF OUR YOUNG MAY COME TO REJECT THE<br />
VALUES OF THE COMMUNITY IF THE COMMUNITY IN TURN DOES<br />
NOT ACCEPT ITS OBLIGATIONS TO THEM. WE NEED TO KNOW AND<br />
TO RESPOND TO THE CONCERNS OF THE YOUNG. MY<br />
GOVERNMENT'S APPROACH DRAWING ON THE PRINCIPLES OF<br />
TRIPARTISM WHICH ARE FUNDAMENTAL TO THE WORK OF THE<br />
I. L. O. IS AIMED AT MEETING THE CONCERNS AND NEEDS OF<br />
OUR YOUNG. I COMMEND THIS APPROACH ANDI OUR POLICIES TO<br />
THE CONFERENCE. </p>
<p>IN CLOSING I WOULD EMPHASISE THE APPROPRIATENESS OF<br />
THIS, INTERNATIONAL YOUTH YEAR, FOR CONSIDERATION OF THE<br />
THEMES OF THIS CONFERENCE OF YOUTH AND TECHNICAL COOPERATION.<br />
THESE ARE FUNDAMENTAL ISSUES THAT, ADDRESSED<br />
IN A CO-OPERATIVE SPIRIT, OFFER THE POSSIBILITY OF<br />
ASSISTING ALL PEOPLE OF THE WORLD PARTICULARLY THE<br />
YOUNG, TO ACHIEVE THEIR FULL POTENTIAL AND THAT OF THEIR<br />
NATIONS. THANK YOU. S. r<br />
C~ i~ ~ l~ rerDI-~ D-L ~ PI)~ YMI i~ r-I </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
