<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4586</transcript-id>
    <title>MR WHITLAM SEEKS TO MAKE CHEAP POLITICAL POINT - SCORING FROM THE PLIGHT OF AUSTRALIA&#039;S UNEMPLOYED.</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/12/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004586.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOP PRESS 6 DCX;? 1 O77<br />
Mr W~ i~ tlam seeks to make cheap political point -scoring<br />
from the plight of Australia's unemployed.<br />
His last-ditch panic camnpaign to frighten the electorate about<br />
this issue will backfire.<br />
It will backfire because it will remind Australians that Mr<br />
Whitlam's party increased unemployment by 192,000 in one year.<br />
Mr Whitlam had no responsible answers to the problem when in<br />
Government and, presents no credible solutions in opposition.<br />
He insults the intelligence of Australians by offering the<br />
same recipe that caused that massive unemployment.<br />
He thinks that his speechwriter's adjectives, flowing phrases and<br />
ringing declarations will convince people that he and his party<br />
can fix it overnight.<br />
lie forgets that Australians understand very clearly that his policies<br />
led to unprecedented unemployment, in manufacturing industry,<br />
-textiles, and clothing industry, in big business and small business<br />
in every State of Australia.<br />
In M-ay 1974, there were 1,357,400 people employed in manufacturing.<br />
Just one year later that num~ ber had dropped to 1,250,100<br />
that is a decrease of 107,300 people.<br />
As Prime Minister, Mr Whitlam used unemployment as a deliberate<br />
and calculated act of Government policy.<br />
Ignoring the warnings contained in an TAC report that Mr Whitlam<br />
kept secret, hie wiped out tens of thousands of jobs with the stroke<br />
of a pen.<br />
Hlow did he explain away this extraordinary decision? In his<br />
1974 policy speech he said " Administrativ\, ely we cut tariffs by<br />
percent to reduce the price of imports without damaginq<br />
Australian industries".<br />
But it was left to Mr Uren to let the cat out of the unemrployment<br />
bag. Just two weeks ago he admitted that Mr Whitlam made the<br />
percent tariff cut to correct an over-employment situation!<br />
That was some correction. In 1974 unemployment increased by<br />
a massive 192,000. r </p>
<p>But Mr Whitlam is: unrepentant. lie would do it all again.<br />
Just last Wednesday morning he flatly refused to guarantee protection<br />
for 120,000 workers in the clothing, textile and footwear<br />
industries. He would forget them all over again.<br />
What do the people in those industries think about Mr Whitlamis<br />
concern for the unemployed?<br />
iWhy is it that he is so reluctant to protect Australian industry,<br />
and Australian working men and women.<br />
Why does he refuse to face up to the fact that Australian<br />
industry needs protection because of our high wage structure<br />
and our small home market?<br />
Our consistent economic strategy is getting Australia back to work,<br />
and from February there will be a sustained and long term<br />
reduction in unemployment in Australia.<br />
We are reducing inflation, reducing interest rates, protecting<br />
industry, cutting taxes and encouraging investment and development.<br />
All this means jobs permanent jobs for Australians who want to work.<br />
These are jobs for people not Mr Whitlam's " administrative"<br />
tariff cuts which meant workers struck out by a<br />
Prime Minister's pen.<br />
-Mr WVhitlam's political epitaph is being written this week<br />
" the unemployment expert". </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
