<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10179</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP DOORSTOP UPON ARRIVAL FROM APEC - FAIRBAIRN</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/11/1996</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010179.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Fax from 26 November 1996 TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE HON JOHN HOWARI? MP<br />
DOORSTOP UPON ARRIVAL FROM A EC FAIRBAIRN<br />
E&amp; OE<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister are you buoyed by Dr Mahathir's comments that Pauline Hanson is a<br />
person of no consequence?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, I didn't know he'd said that but you know my views on that general subject. I<br />
had a very successful meeting. I very much welcome the discussions I had with Dr<br />
Mahathir, with the President of China and many other regional leaders. It was a good<br />
meeting from Australia's point of view because the process of trade liberalisation<br />
which will, if implemented by everybody, generate thousapds of jobs for Australians<br />
will go on.<br />
JOURNALIST: Are you disappointed Dr Mahathir made those comments when he didn't actually raise<br />
the issue with you in his talks?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Look, I'm simply not going to comment on that. You know my view on those things<br />
generally and I'm just simply not going to respond to that.<br />
JOURNALIST: So what's the big boost from the APEC meeting for Australia? 26/ 11/ 96 20: 01 Pg: I </p>
<p>Yak rroii 26/ 11/ 96 20: 01 Pg: 2<br />
PRIME MMNSTER;<br />
Well, the good news out of the meeting is that the process of trade liberalisation<br />
involving everyone, I mean that's important, goes on. And there are thousands ofjobs<br />
in this exercise for Australians, That's why we are in it. We are not in it because of<br />
commitment to some nebulous economic theory. We are in it because this is the<br />
fastest growing economnic region of the world and if the goals can be worked towards<br />
and achieved then there will be tens of thousands of more jobs created not only in<br />
Australia but throughout the region and that's very good news for the poorer countries<br />
of the region, all of which have very young populations, very high levels of<br />
unemployment and the need to lift their economies. And what encouraged me greatly<br />
was the commnitment of the United States and Japan, the two most powerful economies<br />
not only in the region but in the world, to the process, and it is something that<br />
Australia should be very much part of arnd something which it will be part of under this<br />
Government as it was under the former Government.<br />
JOURNALIST: Your trip to Beijing next year, will that fu~ rther cement your relations with China?<br />
PRIME MSTER:<br />
We have good relations with China. There were some misunderstandings. They in my<br />
view have been substantially cleared away. The Chinese President at the end of our<br />
discussion in English said to me " face to face it is much better we clear up things",<br />
and I don't approach China in any courting sense, but just in a sense of having a<br />
sensible mutually beneficial relationship with the most populist country in the world<br />
and a country incidentally that invests more in Australia than any other country other<br />
than Hong Kong, of course in a few months time Hong Kong will be part of China.<br />
JOURNALIST: Pauline Hanson has raised concerns about some aspects of the action plan relating to<br />
foreign investment in real estate. She says Australians are in danger of becoming<br />
tenants in their own country. Is that a valid concern?<br />
PRUME NMNISTER:<br />
No, see you later. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
