<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5780</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S SPEECH TO THE INSTITUTE OF DIRECTORS IN AUSTRALIA, WENTWORTH HOTEL, MELBOURNE</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/03/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005780.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
: e~ UTALIA<br />
FOR MEDIA TUESDAY, 23 MARCH 1982<br />
PRIME MINISTER'S SPEECH TO THE INSTITUTE OF<br />
DIRECTORS IN AUSTRALIA, WENTWORTH HOTEL, MELBOUR~ NE<br />
It is a great pleasure to have this opportunity to address such<br />
a wide audience, including representatives of overseas<br />
governments, international business concerns and public and<br />
private sector organisations in Australia. I trust your<br />
deliberations have been productive. For all of us, business<br />
as well as governments, unions as well as management, have a<br />
profound responsibility to face up to the realities of our time<br />
and the challenges that they create.<br />
I want to talk tonight about the response that is needed from<br />
govexrrmient to meet the challenges that Australia faces at the<br />
present time, about how our policies are already tailored to<br />
anticipate -the issues of the 1980s, and to lay the<br />
foundations for continuing growth and prosperity. The challenges<br />
themselves are not hard to discern. We are faced by uncertainty<br />
in the world economic outlook, by high interest rates world-wide,<br />
by wage and price pressures, strikes and industrial<br />
disputes, arnd some unreal expectations, by a host of threats<br />
to our international competitiveness, our balance of payments,<br />
our growth and our employment prospects.<br />
It is little wonder that recent surveys reveal pessimistic<br />
business expectations, little wonder that excessive wage settlements<br />
and rising industrial disputation, including the potentially<br />
horrifying effects, both for the economy and for families, of<br />
the present situation in NSW, should give the confidence of<br />
the business sector a heavy knock. The ultimate challenge<br />
arising out. of all this is to keep growth going in Australia<br />
while the world economy remains depressed, to secure the<br />
confidence and investment on which growth depends, to make sure<br />
we will be ready to take full advantage of world recovery<br />
when it eventually comes.<br />
T. hese are the great objectives which the Government is dedicated<br />
to achieve in the interests of all Australians. The<br />
Government has already shown that with the right policies and<br />
the right attitudes, Australia can succeed, even against world<br />
trends. For Australia has had economic growth at twice the<br />
average rate of other major industrialised countries in recent:<br />
years. Australia had its highest rate of increase in business </p>
<p>-2<br />
investment for three decades in the last financial year; Australia<br />
has had substantial growth in employment and in after tax real<br />
incomes over several years, and all of this at a time when<br />
most of the m~ ajor industrialised countries, in Europe and North<br />
America have been struggling to maintain any growth at all.<br />
The question now is what Australia's response should be when<br />
growth rates in Europe and North America have declined yet<br />
further as they enter the 19801s, when their unemployment<br />
rates are high and rising, and when interest rates have climbed<br />
to historicaily high levels. I have no doubt that the broad<br />
thrust of our established policy approaches provides the right<br />
response. Indeed, events have already shown that these<br />
approaches work; but we must also be flexible and imaginative<br />
in our approach.<br />
If inflationary pressures, and the problems of high interest<br />
rates are to be overcome, it is essential that we continue<br />
to restrain government spending. If the private sector is<br />
to remain the driving force in economic growth and prosperity,<br />
it must be allowed the resources to do so.<br />
We have already had success in reducing the share of GDP taken<br />
by government from over 30% in 1975-76 to less than 28%<br />
today, and we shall continue to stand by this approaach.<br />
But to continaue this progress will not be easy. Over 62% of<br />
the expenditure that now occurs is committed to the needy<br />
and the elderly, to the states, and to defence, all of which<br />
are areas of the highest priority.<br />
The unavoidable costs of government are high indeed. on top<br />
of this, many people want government to spend more, often<br />
without recognising the basic fact which<br />
we all know -too well, that higher government spending must<br />
inevitably mean rising taxes. The consequences of a big<br />
spending approach would be totally disastrous for Australia.<br />
A spendthrift government in Australia would rapidly be<br />
caught up in a spiral of higher taxes, and rising deficits,<br />
which would ' have an intolerable impact on Australia's families,<br />
especially thirough increasing pressures on interest rates,<br />
and there is little doubt that a high spending approach<br />
could threaten the very fabric of our society.<br />
The effects of budget deficit financing on interest rates<br />
in particular is clearly illustrated by the experience of<br />
governments overseas, which, unable to bring their budget<br />
deficits under control in the short-run, have had to adopt<br />
tighter monetary policies, and have thereby contributed to the<br />
pressures on interest rates that are now being felt world-wide.<br />
Despite our expenditure restraint, our determination to move<br />
away from deficit financing has committed us to a harder task<br />
than we would have liked in terms of achieving tax cuts. / 3 </p>
<p>-3<br />
The Government's tax reforms have been wide-ranging:<br />
we have reformed the tax scales, almost doubled the dependent<br />
spouse rebate, abolished death rebate, abolished death duties,<br />
allowed for deductibility of superannuation contributions<br />
up to $ 1,200 per annum for self employed persons and others<br />
not covered by employer sponsored schemes, improved income tax<br />
averaging for primary producers provided a tax rebate for<br />
health insurance and most recently a tax rebate for certain home<br />
loan interest payments;' and even apart from the reform of the<br />
tax scales, the annual cost to revenue of these initiatives<br />
amounts tC) a sum in thie region~ of million; we have been mo; re<br />
active than any previous ' Australian government in efforts<br />
to bind thie weeping sore of tax avoidance; we have attempted<br />
to broaden the base of the tax structure and to move away from<br />
a narrow reliance on direct personal taxation; and we have<br />
set our face against the taxation of the capital base<br />
so necessary to growth.<br />
We remain firmly committed to seeking to reduce the overall<br />
burden of taxation, and the burden of direct taxation in<br />
particular, but it would be irresponsible to do so ' unless<br />
economic conditions are right. The reduction we have achieved<br />
in the budget deficit from-almost 5% GDP in 1975/ 76 to less than<br />
1% this year, which last financ-ial year led to the first<br />
budget domestic surplus in seven years, has also made a<br />
significant contribution to our objective of restraining<br />
the growthi of money supply.<br />
The Government is concerned to achieve an adequate growth<br />
in the supply of money to allow expansion of activity<br />
in the economy, and to relieve pressure on domestic interest<br />
rates to the greatest extent possible. But at the same time,<br />
growth of the money supply must not be such as to accommodate<br />
an inflationary scramble after goods and services which<br />
are not available, or an inflationary weakening of the balance<br />
of payments, or an inflationary wages scramble. Indeed, in<br />
relation to the wages pressures that are now being felt in<br />
the Australian economy and which threaten our international<br />
comoetitiveness, it is the Commonwealth's ability to influence<br />
the economic environment within which wages are negotiated<br />
that represents its main weapon. The Government is committed<br />
to monetary and fiscal policies which prevent unbridled<br />
wages growth and the inevitable consequential increases<br />
in unemployment and inflation. Monetary policy will continue<br />
to be sufficiently tight that firms cannot be assured of<br />
financing an unrieasonably rising wage bill.<br />
If we were to let the money supply blow out, we might be<br />
applauded by some in the very short term we might even<br />
buy some short term reductions in unemployment. But let<br />
there be no mistake about it, only very short term benefits<br />
can be bought in this way. People would quickly realise<br />
that the benefits of such an approach are not soundly based,<br />
not sustainable, and the long run costs in-terms of inflation,<br />
in terms of loss of jobs, and in terms of loss of growth<br />
would be immense.<br />
The importance of the right settings in our monetary and<br />
fiscal policies in meeting the challenqjes that we face<br />
at this time cannot be overstated. </p>
<p>-4<br />
But it is not only through our macro-economic policies that the<br />
challenges of the eighties are to be met. The profitabilityand<br />
the competitiveness of Australian industry are central<br />
to our aim of maintaining growth through difficult times.<br />
The Government has consistently pursued policies to improve<br />
industry profitability and to encourage the development<br />
of internationally competitive Australian industries,<br />
and that thrust will be maintained.<br />
The initiative we have taken to encourage industrial development,<br />
to stimulate exports, and to stimulate investment by mreans of investment<br />
allowances and iThproved depreciation schedules, have been of major<br />
assistance to industry. We have been well aware that in the<br />
long-run, the interests of the Australian community would be<br />
served best. by policies which promote more outward-looking,<br />
internationally competitive manufacturing industries,<br />
but the Government also knows well that movement in this<br />
direction must be within the capacity of industry and the<br />
economy to accommodate change.<br />
The Government has aimed to achieve a balanced approach<br />
which can be seen in the fact that over 20 product groupings<br />
are subject to gradual, predictable phasing down of tariff,<br />
quota or bounty assistance as a result of decisions taken in the<br />
last three years. In addition, the motor vehicles industry,<br />
and the textiles, clothing and footwear industries should<br />
experience significant restructuring in the direction of<br />
greater competitiveness as a result of new assistance packages.<br />
Indeed, in some parts of the textiles, clothing and footwear<br />
industries, significant re-investment is now taking place.<br />
Some manufacturers are looking to secure overseas markets<br />
for their products, and it is our hope and intention that<br />
a similar path may be followed in the motor velhicles industry.<br />
The Governiment will soon be considering a number of major<br />
reports from the Industries Assistance Commission, and I want<br />
to make it plain that in dealing with these reports the Government<br />
will be taking into account the probleris that all industries<br />
face in dif'ficult world conditions, as well as the need to<br />
continue to promote a competitive industry structure, and<br />
we will be aiming to provide a stable and secure policy<br />
foundation on which industry will be able to plan for years<br />
ahead. A further : issue of profound concern to us all is the sort of<br />
irresponsible militant behaviour by unionists that has been<br />
experienced in Australia, particularly since the middle of<br />
last year. Australia desparately needs a more responsible<br />
atmosphere in industrial relations, a better balance between<br />
the effective powers of employees and employers in the context<br />
of industrial negotiations. All Australians lose from strikes,<br />
especially Australia's families and people wanting jobs.<br />
Strikes al: 3o reduce the competitiveness of Australian<br />
products, and bring into question Australia's reliability<br />
as a supplier. </p>
<p>A dramatic and profoundly worrying example is provided by<br />
powerzoning in New South Wales,-which is of course not just a<br />
questi on of the present *. trikes, but of inadequate maintenance and<br />
mishandled industrial relations over time.* The potential effects<br />
of even onE!-day-a-week zoning are immense. For example, if<br />
power zonin~ g meant that 500,000 employees in New South Wales<br />
each lost one day's work a week, and if each of those<br />
employees was on an average weekly earnings, there would<br />
be a loss of after tax'disposable income by families-in<br />
New South Wales of some $ 22 million each week, a loss<br />
of final output by firms in New South Wales of some<br />
million each week, a loss of P. A. Y. E. income tax<br />
receipts collected from New South Wales by the Commonwealth<br />
Government of some $ 10 million each week, and untold<br />
further repercussions in the form of reduced sales,<br />
reduced profits, increased prices and reduced employmentas<br />
these effects flowed-on throughout the economy.<br />
The impact of all this on the Australian economy and<br />
especially the suffering caused to the families of the<br />
people directly affected is incalculable, yet in essence,<br />
they represent only an extreme of the sort of damag~ e that<br />
industrial disruption has been imposing on the economy<br />
month after month in recent times, as many of you well<br />
know. The Government has been active in bringing improvements<br />
to Australia's industrial relations system throughout the<br />
last six years, and it is important to remember that bad as<br />
last year may have been, the number of working days lost<br />
did not approach the record 6.4 million days lost in 1974.<br />
The Government is now bringing forward additional<br />
initiatives to address the present situation. We have<br />
already discussed them with employers and unions. Under<br />
these proposals, employers will be granted the direct right<br />
to stand down employees who cannot be usefully employed<br />
because of industrial action by other employees. This<br />
will help protect employers from being doubly penalised by the<br />
actions of a handful of employees, and will bring more<br />
clearly to the attention of employees the full costs of<br />
industrial action.<br />
The Government gave itself the equivalent power a few years<br />
ago, and hLas used it on occasions to good effect.<br />
Only last week over 2,000 teachers were stood down in the<br />
A. C. T. . ThEy lost several days pay; if they did not go back to<br />
work we were quite prepared to consider dismissing them, and indeed there<br />
had already been preliminary discussions on this course of action. A further<br />
proposal involves amending the Conciliation and Arbitration Act to encourage the<br />
formation of industry based unions. Australia has long<br />
needed a more rational union structure, one that is more<br />
relevant to0 the nature of industry and commerce in Australia<br />
today, and our legislation will assist that process.<br />
The Government is also moving to promote voluntary unionism,<br />
in protection of the rights of employees. we are also seeking<br />
better co-operation with the States in handling<br />
demarcation disputes, and problems on the waterfront, and<br />
we hope to be able to advance a number of issues at the<br />
next Premiers' Conference. / 6 </p>
<p>6<br />
All these . pproaches should help in improving the industrial<br />
relations climate, but I want to emphasise that governments<br />
cannot conduct industrial relations on behalf of employees<br />
or firms. There is no substitute in industrial relations<br />
for on-going efforts in the workplace by the parties<br />
directly involved.<br />
A willingness on the part of top management to become<br />
involved is fundamental to successful industrial relations,<br />
and in the current economic environment, it is vital<br />
that priority should be given to these concerns.<br />
I have spoken tonight about how government policy in a<br />
number of key areas expenditure restraint, taxation,<br />
money supply, industry assistance and industrial relations<br />
is adapted to the facts of our present situation. I have<br />
referred to these policies because they are so fundamental<br />
but we are also pursuing policies in related areas which<br />
are equally relevant to the present needs of the Australian<br />
people. For example, we have training and transition schemes<br />
in place to give young people the kind of skills which will<br />
be increasingly needed in the years ahead. We are developing<br />
our defence forces in a way which is designed to meet<br />
Australia's needs at a time of considerable world uncertainty.<br />
And we have developed a new housing package which, I believe,<br />
addresses the key problems which have grown up in this<br />
area of concern to so many Australians.<br />
In terms of its practicality, its comprehensiveness, and<br />
its capacity to give help where help is needed this package<br />
is unrivalled in protecting the Australian ideal of home<br />
ownership. In the present world environment, Australia is<br />
obviously going to be facing some difficulties, but<br />
our achievements in the past provide the guarantee that<br />
we can face the future with confidence of success.<br />
We can be grateful for the underlying strength of Australia's<br />
economy, and provided we don't throw away the gains that have<br />
been made, provided we continue to anticipate and respond<br />
to new developments as they arise, we can keep building<br />
Australia up, and thus achieve the prosperity and the way<br />
of life which we seek for ourselves and our children. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
