<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3450</transcript-id>
    <title>AUSTRALIAN PUBLIC SERVICE - 12 NOVEMBER 1974</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/11/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003450.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER PRESS STATEMENT NO: 3-j( r<br />
12 November 1974<br />
AUSTRALIAN PUBLIC SERVICE<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr Whitlam, M. P.,<br />
said in his statement on the economy in Parliament this<br />
evening that he would issue a statement on the question<br />
of staff numbers in the Australian Public Service. In his<br />
statement in Parliament, Mr Whitlam said that:<br />
" Our program of Government expenditure has<br />
been Achieved without excessive increases in the number of<br />
public servants. The staff ceiling control on the Australian-<br />
Public Service will be retained in a modified form. This<br />
will be the subject of a separate statement."<br />
The separate statement is as follows:<br />
" The staff ceiling control on the Australian<br />
Public Slervice which was announced in my statement to the<br />
Premiers4 Conference on 7 June will be retained, so that the<br />
healthy influence on departmental efficiency of the<br />
disciplii~ s of internal priority review and staff redeployment<br />
will be maintained. The Government proposes, however, an<br />
extension of the trainee intake to the Public Service by up<br />
to 450 so that additional appropriate opportunities are<br />
made available for vocational training, and an additional<br />
intake of 1,000 youth and school leaver recruits to basegrade<br />
office categories so as to maintain an intake more<br />
consistent with recent years. These special intakes will<br />
lift the staff growth ceiling of the Public Service above<br />
the previously announced figure."<br />
CANBERRA. A. C. T.. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
