<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>246</transcript-id>
    <title>STATES GRANTS ( UNIVERSITIES BILL) 1960</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/11/1960</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000246_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SECOND READING SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER ( MR. MENZIES)<br />
HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES<br />
STATES GRANTS ( UNIVERSITIES BILL), I960<br />
I. INTRODUCTORY<br />
In April 1958, I had the privilege of presenting to the House<br />
a Bill to give effect to the proposals of the Committee on Australian<br />
Universities, which met in 1957 with Sir Keith Murray as Chairman.<br />
This Bill sought Parliamentary approval for the proposals of the Murray<br />
Committee for the triennium 1958/ 60.<br />
Once again it is my pleasant lot to introduce a Bill on universities,<br />
this time to give effect to the proposals of the Australian<br />
Universities Commission for the coming triennium, 1961/ 63.<br />
The Commission is the permanent successor to the Murray Committee.<br />
Honourable Members will recall that the Murray Committee recommended that the<br />
Commonwealth Government should have available to it continuous advice on<br />
the financial requirements of the universities if the universities are to<br />
develop rationally and coherently, and urged the appointment of a<br />
permanent Commission for this purpose. Parliament agreed to the<br />
establishment of the Universities Commission in 1959. The Commission<br />
consists of persons of eminence in university and business circles, and<br />
since its establishment last year it has exhaustively studied the problems<br />
of our universities and has brought forward recommendations on a wide range<br />
of matters. It has done this after taking into consideration all possible<br />
courses of action and after the fullest consultation with Commonwealth and<br />
State authorities and with all universities. The first report of the<br />
Commission, which presents the recommendations and the comments of the<br />
Commission upon present and future university problems, was tabled in<br />
the House on Thursday </p>
<p>0 2.<br />
It is relevant in considering the report and the Bill to recall<br />
the functions of the Commission as defined in the Universities Commission<br />
Act of 1959. Under Clause 13 the Commission is to furnish information<br />
and advice on grants by the Commonwealth of financial assistance to<br />
universities established by the Commonwealth, and of financial assistance<br />
to the States in relation to universities, together with information and<br />
advice that is relevant to the need for financial assistance, the conditions<br />
upon which any financial assistance should be granted, and the amount<br />
and the allocation of financial assistance.<br />
These functions are important, providdng as they do for a financial<br />
future for our universities that has a great measure of stability. However,<br />
the next section, Section 14, of the Act places an obligation upon the<br />
Commission that is to my mind of even greater importance. The section<br />
states: The Commission shall perform its functions with a view to<br />
promoting the balanced development of universities so that<br />
their resources can be used to the greatest possible<br />
advantage of Australia.<br />
( ii) For the purpose of the performance of its functions, the<br />
Commission shall consult with universities and with the States<br />
upon the matter on which it is empowered to furnish<br />
information and advice.<br />
The Commission has, therefore, addressed itself in its report<br />
not only to the financial problems involved but also to the present state<br />
and the future role to be played by the institutions of this country<br />
providing services at the tertiary level of our educational system.<br />
II. SOME MAJOR POINTS IN THE COMMISSION'S REPORT<br />
Honourable Members have had the opportunity of studying the<br />
Commission's report. Of the many important questions raised, there are<br />
five which would seem to lay claim to special comment.<br />
First, there is the influence of demographic factors.<br />
Chapter 2 of the Commission's report presents estimates<br />
of the likely increase in student enrolments at universities.<br />
In 1958 some 42,000 students were enrolled<br />
at universities, and universities now predict that by 1966 </p>
<p>0 3.<br />
the number will have risen to 95,000. These figures are<br />
considerably in excess of the estimates made by the Murray<br />
Committee on the evidence then available to it. If this<br />
estimate is realised, the ratio of students enrolled at<br />
universities to the total population will be approaching<br />
one in a hundred. This, of course, has enormous consequences<br />
in terms of the pressure on facilities, demands for staff<br />
and the need for more universities and university-type<br />
institutions.<br />
As a result of these demographic changes leading to a great<br />
bulge in the relevant age groups, there is obviously a quite explosive<br />
development taking place in universities. The achievement in<br />
recent years has been a very remarkable one, but the Commission<br />
has had to report that the changing age structure of our<br />
population and other factors have meant that, in spite of the<br />
greatly increased governmental assistance since the recommendations<br />
of the Murray Committee were accepted, many of our university facilities<br />
are still below a satisfactory standard.<br />
After a review of the Commonwealth Scholarship Scheme, the<br />
Commission supports the need for an increase in the number of<br />
scholarships from 3,000 to 4,000 a year.<br />
( ii) Pressure on Staff and Facilities. Chapter 111 of the report<br />
deals with. staff. * In spite of very considerabie staff'tecruitment<br />
in recent years, the number of students in relation to the number<br />
of staff is increasing and the position in Australia compares<br />
unfavourably with that in the United Kingdom. The Commission<br />
estimates that by 1966 the number of staff will need to be more<br />
than doubled to keep pace with the increased number of students.<br />
As to facilities, the Commission in Chapter 6 points out that if<br />
the enrolment demand is to be met in terms of the existing<br />
university pattern the Australian community must create in every<br />
two years the equivalent of at least one new university of 8,000<br />
students.<br />
The Commission has pointed out that there will not only be this<br />
tremendously increased demand for suitable academic staff but that<br />
we will have to rely largely upon our own resources to meet this<br />
demand. </p>
<p>It will become increasingly difficult to tap resources in<br />
overseas countries, since they themselves will be under pressure<br />
for reasons very much the same as those affecting the Australian<br />
situation. The Commission suggests some of the questions which<br />
must be considered and says " The issues raised in these questions<br />
are of great concern to Australian universities, faced as they are<br />
with staffing problems not likely to be solved unless far-reaching<br />
changes in the form of university education and teaching methods<br />
can be achieved."<br />
( iii) I turn now to the financial recommendations contained in the report,<br />
and to which the Bill before the House gives effect. The Commission<br />
recommends that a total of œ 103m should be made available to State<br />
universities in the coming three years. This compares with a total<br />
expenditure of some œ 55m in the last three years. The Commission<br />
is satisfied that financial provision of this order is necessary<br />
for the balanced development of Australian universities in this period.<br />
The Commission's report indicates that the sharp increase in expenditure<br />
required over the coming triennium is the result of several factors,<br />
notably the large increase in the number of students. The report<br />
also shows that a great deal of the increased expenditure is due<br />
to the establishment of Monash University, the extension of the<br />
universities in New South Wales and the establishment of colleges<br />
at Wollongong and Townsville. By contrast the Universities<br />
Commission proposes that the development of the well-established<br />
universities should be limited in order to keep their size within<br />
reasonable bounds and suggests for them a programme which is in<br />
effect a normal projection on previous expenditure. Taking into<br />
account the increased student population and the need for providing<br />
new facilities, it is clear, therefore, that the large upsurge in<br />
suggested expenditure is due principally to new university development<br />
of a kind which has been foreseen and recognised as inevitable<br />
for some time.<br />
( iv) The Basis of the Proposed Financial Arrangements:<br />
The Commission's proposals rest on the principle that the existing<br />
ratio of approximately œ 1.85 ( State) to œ 1 ( Commonwealth) for<br />
recurrent expenditure should be maintained and that the basis of<br />
œ 1 for œ 1 on capital expenditure should be applied uniformly as<br />
between States and as between universities. However, having in<br />
mind its obligations for influencing the balanced development of<br />
Australian universities, the Commission has examined separately the </p>
<p>factors which are determining the growth of each university.<br />
The University of New South Wales, the University of Queensland<br />
and the University of Western Australia are expected to<br />
experience a more rapid growth of student population than other<br />
universities. The Commission's proposals are therefore adjusted<br />
to meet the individual needs of universities in the light of the<br />
pressures upon each of them.<br />
Another consideration in the Commission's assessment of the future<br />
situation is its belief that any university should not exceed<br />
a certain size if it is to function effectively.<br />
The Commission has drawn particular attention to its proposals<br />
to bring the treatment of the University of New South Wales and<br />
the University of New England into line with that accorded to<br />
other universities. The ways in which its proposals differ from<br />
the pattern of previous arrangements are described in the report.<br />
The Commission also refers at various places in its report to the<br />
desirability of a greater flexibility than has previously applied<br />
in the distribution of Commonwealth financial assistance for capital<br />
projects, including expenditure on capital equipment and on<br />
residential colleges and halls of residence. I shall refer in<br />
particular to some of these matters later on when I turn to an<br />
examination of the Bill in more detail.<br />
The Problems of Universities and the Pattern of Development<br />
of Tertiary Education:<br />
The University Commission has shown at various places in its<br />
report a full awareness of the problems of university development.<br />
In dealing with staff recruitment in Chapter 3, the Commission<br />
has expressed itself as doubtful that any answer could be found<br />
in traditional terms, and in Chapter 6 it ranges over a number of<br />
possible changes that need to be considered by Governments and<br />
universities. The Commission proposes to make a special<br />
examination in the period immediately ahead into these matters<br />
and has suggested that it may seek to establish an advisory<br />
committee to assist it in its enquiries. </p>
<p>6.<br />
111. IMPLICATIONS OF THE UNIVERSITIES COMMISSION'S<br />
PROPOSALS FOR GOVERNMENT. S AND UNIVERSITIES<br />
COMMONWEALTH GOVERNMENT<br />
The. Commonwealth Government has examined the report and is<br />
prepared to accept its recommendationts in general. The Bill now before<br />
the House indicates its acceptance of the many financial recommendations<br />
for State Universities.<br />
This is not to say that the Commonwealth accepts every statement<br />
in the report, some of which will no doubt also be discussed inside and<br />
outside this Parliament. But by and large the Government feels that the<br />
Commission's analysis of the situation and its proposals are receiving<br />
a large degree of acceptance in Commonwealth and State Government circles,<br />
among the universities and by the community in general. The Bill for<br />
increased expenditure is, of course, a very large one, and meeting it,<br />
having in mind also what lies ahead after this triennium, raises many<br />
problems in our minds.<br />
After carefully studying the report of the Commission, the<br />
Government has taken the viewwhich it believes the Commission holds also,<br />
that unless there is early and substantial modification of the university<br />
pattern, away from the traditional 19th century model on which it is now<br />
based, it may not be practicable for Australian Governments to meet all<br />
the needs for university education in Australia, and at the same time to<br />
achieve the best use of resources in the national interest. We think,<br />
therefore, that the development of alternative kinds of tertiary education<br />
is likely to be of the greatest importance. In view, also, of the<br />
difficulties which may be encountered in finding sufficient staff for<br />
tertiary educational needs and for developing the facilities in time. the<br />
situation may well call for extensive re-organisation within the universities.<br />
The Commission' s report has referred to some of the possible<br />
ways of doing this. As the Commission points out, other countries are<br />
facing similar problems and are finding that new and unusual methods for<br />
solving them are becoming necessary. In the period ahead thought may well<br />
have to be given to re-arrangement of the university working year, re-arrangements<br />
to produce a greater use of existing facilities within the university, to<br />
standards of teaching staff and the most effective employment of our<br />
university teaching resources. Building programmes of universities will<br />
need to be kept under very close scrutiny in order to ensure that they<br />
are sufficiently restrained as to economy and directly related to need.<br />
The Government therefore welcomes the proposal of the Commission </p>
<p>to undertake an early examination of these matters and has informed the<br />
Commission that it regards this examination as a task of the most vital<br />
importance during the next 12 to 18 months. . To assist the Commission<br />
directly in its task the Government has agreed with the suggestion of the<br />
Commission that it might establish an advisory committee. No doubt the<br />
Commission will pursue its investigation in close co-operation with Governmental<br />
authorities both State and Commonwealth and with universities, and<br />
I have informed the States that the Commission will be looking to them for<br />
co-operation and assistance.<br />
STATES I have sent copies * of the report to the Premiers, and informed<br />
them of the Commonwealth views on it.<br />
Of course we fully recognise and respect the prime responsibility<br />
which the States have for determining the rate of development of their<br />
universities. As we see the role of the Universities Commission, it.~ is a<br />
so urce of advice and of advice only to Commonwealth and State Governments<br />
and to universities. Its authority lies not in coercion but in persuasion.<br />
Under the Commission's proposals it is the States who determine what the<br />
level of expenditure should be on both capital and recurrent sides. On<br />
the capital side the basis proposed is a œ 1l for and on the recurrent<br />
side it is perhaps worth noting that the proposed first level grants are no<br />
greater than the level of actual expenditure upon recurrent needs in 1960<br />
and the States should hot therefore encounter any difficulty in attracting<br />
the maximum first level Commonwealth grant, as they will get it by merely<br />
continuing to support universities as they did in 1960.<br />
It is of course quite open to the States and the universities<br />
to hold opinions differing from those of the Universities Commission on the<br />
rate of development which is desirable and practicable.<br />
( iii ) UNIVERSITIES The achievement in university development, especially since the<br />
acceptance of the recommendations of the Murray Committee has been<br />
spectacular, but the problems which lie ahead are obviously even greater.<br />
We feel that they cannot simply be solved by providing money and that univer-'<br />
sities must critically examine their procedures and problems in order<br />
to ensure that the funds which are provided are used as effectively and<br />
as economically as possible. Quite apart fz'om the question of developing<br />
alternative institutions there are many matters which lie within the province<br />
of universities. I have already mentioned a number of these building<br />
programmes, recruitment of staff and possible forms of internal re-organisation.<br />
We recognise the great problems which universities face in coping with the<br />
large increase in student numbers. Nevertheless universities must cotitinue </p>
<p>I to set as their aims the improvement in teaching and student achievement;<br />
better training for research workers, significant research contributions<br />
in widening fields of study, and intellectual leadership in the community.<br />
( iv) THE COMMUNITY AS A WHOLE<br />
The Commission's report points out that the Australian community<br />
has always regarded higher education as a right open to all young people of<br />
ability, rather than as a privilege of wealth or class. In this connection,<br />
the Commission raises a very real problem Ahether the community of itself<br />
realises the magnitude of its educational responsibilities if this aspiration<br />
is to be achieved. It is a regrettable feature of the present times that universities<br />
like many other institutions must depend most heavily upon the Governments<br />
for their finances. This, no doubt, is an inevitable trend arising to a great<br />
extent from the very high costs of tertiary education to-day. Nevertheless,<br />
private benefactions will, I hope, always be a feature of our universities, and<br />
in recent years there have been some notable contributions in this direction:-<br />
more is needed. IV. OTHER MATTERS<br />
In accepting-the recommendations of the Commission-in general the<br />
Government has agreed to proposals which do not need to be embodied in the<br />
Bill now before the House. These include the recommendation of the<br />
Commiission on Commonwealth scholarships.<br />
In the case of the Australian National University the financial<br />
responsibility. of course, rests entirely upon the Commonwealth. The rate of<br />
development of the Australian National University must be related in some<br />
degree to the development of Canberra. The Government has accepted in<br />
principle the recommendations of the Commission as to the but the<br />
proposals will need to be the subject of further careful investigation, especially<br />
on timing, before they are put into effect. Meanwhile, it is proposed to<br />
take immediate action to begin the construction of the Chemistry School<br />
building for the School of General Studies at the A. N. U. </p>
<p>9.<br />
MAIN PROVISIONS OF THE BILL<br />
In the main, the Bill before the House establishes Commonwealth-<br />
State financial machinery whereby the recommendations of the Commission<br />
may be put into effect. The Bill contains a number of features not<br />
present in its predecessor, the 1958 Act. There is, for instance, no<br />
provision in this Bill for emergency grants, since those in effect have<br />
been absorbed into the general grants for recurrent expenditure which the<br />
Bill makes provision for in a number of schedules.<br />
The Bill adds a new concept to the existing definition of university<br />
purposes. In order that the Commission may be able to provide for the<br />
staff at a new university, such as Monash, the Bill makes possible payment<br />
of recurrent grants to a university which may of necessity appoint its<br />
staff for planning purposes, but which is not in effect offering a teaching<br />
or research service.<br />
The Bill goes on to establish machinery provisions and at<br />
Section 6 gives the basis on which the salary element in recurrent grants<br />
has been calculated for the purposes of Commonwealth financial assistance.<br />
It states that the schedules have been based on a basic professorial salary<br />
at the rate of œ 4,000 per annum, which was the salary applying in a majority<br />
of Australian universities on the date the Commission reported. The Bill<br />
goes on to provide that the Minister may by an instrument under his hand<br />
approve an increased rate of professorial salary for the purpose of Commonwealth<br />
assistance. A copy of any such instrument will be sent to the<br />
Premier of each State affected by the instrument and will be laid before<br />
this House. The Bill provides that if a University pays basic professorial<br />
salaries in excess of this level the Commonwealth shall not be responsible<br />
for the increased costs involved. I must stress at this point that the<br />
Commonwealth has neither the desire nor an intention to fix professorial<br />
salaries. Any State Government is completely free to support whatever<br />
salaries it deems appropriate in the Universities of that State.<br />
As far as grants for the purposes of capital works within the<br />
universities are concerned, the Bill in general carries on the arrangements<br />
which have proved so successful in the last triennium. There is, however,<br />
f </p>
<p>a departure in Section 8 of the Bill, which puts into effect the recommendations<br />
of the Universities Commission as they relate to special grants for<br />
equipment. In summary form the Commonwealth will make available œ 250,000<br />
on a pound for pound basis with the States for the purchase of special<br />
equipment, and is prepared to see this sum disbursed in the proportions given<br />
in the Third Schedule to the Act. Under this Bill the Commonwealth will<br />
make available a further œ 250,000 on a pound for pound basis which will be<br />
disbursed on the advice of the Commission and therefore not necessarily<br />
in the same proportions as the first œ 250,000. The purpose is to allow<br />
flexibility so that the Commission may, with the co-operation of the States,<br />
assist with the purchase of special equipment for research and other<br />
purposes. The Bill provides grants to affiliated residential colleges under<br />
two headings. It incorporates a formula which will enable assistance to<br />
be given to residential colleges for recurrent expenditure, including tutorial<br />
assistance, in accordance with the number of students receiving services<br />
such as these from the college. It also provides that buildings for residential<br />
college purposes may be assisted on a pound for pound basis. It is the<br />
hope of the Commission and the hope of the Government that these forms of<br />
assistance will give the present residential colleges and those to come a<br />
greater opportunity for giving a service to the students within the universities.<br />
Assistance is also proposed in the Bill for halls of residence<br />
administered by the universities. VI. CONCLUSIONS<br />
The Bill before the House carries on and develops the work which<br />
the 1958 Act initiated. It is based on the firm belief that the development<br />
of our intellectual power and knowledge is vital to our future. We are a<br />
small nation of ten million people and we cannot escape meeting the rest of<br />
the world in competition. I am not willing to sit back and see Australia<br />
lag behind by omission. We must match the world in scholarship, in<br />
technology and trade. Our efforts are not without great merit. If it were<br />
not for the financial backing which we and the States have provided there<br />
would not be a Monash University or a University of New South Wales, and<br />
other university institutions would be in a deplorable condition. The<br />
programme is a large one. The expenditure involved is largely inescapable.<br />
However, it is not merely money involved but a question of national responsibility.<br />
Because of this the whole situation calls for continuing and<br />
special examination by all Governments and all universities and by the<br />
community in general.<br />
Canberra, 22nd November, 1960. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
