<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4707</transcript-id>
    <title>SYDNEY CITY COMMISSION - OPENING OF SWANTON LODGE, 12 MAY 1978</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/05/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004707.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
pEMBARGO: UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRE3SS 12 MAY 1978<br />
SYDNEY CITY MISSI-ON OPENING OF SlWAN\ TO. N LODGE<br />
Everyone involved in making this op ening possible must feel a<br />
real sense of pride. You have taken and translated into<br />
practice one of the great values on which all Australians are<br />
united the concern for the disadvantaged and the helpless;<br />
the belief that people are entitled to a fair go, and help when<br />
they are in trouble.<br />
This belief is one of the key values that brings our society<br />
together, giving it unity amidst its diversity. But like so<br />
many other shared values, concern for the disadvantaged and<br />
the helpless is too often only an abstract ideal, something we<br />
believe in but don't act upon.<br />
In politics, there is a rather similar problem. Although<br />
politicians basically understand that the things that unite<br />
the overwhelming majority of Australians are more important<br />
than their differences, rather than unity politicians too often<br />
emphasize division conflict rather than consensus.<br />
In the area of social concern, also,, all too often the tendency<br />
is to acknowledge that a problem exists, deplore it and say<br />
something should be done about it by someone else!<br />
Bridging the distance between the ideals we all share and our<br />
actions in everyday life is one of the major challenges confronting<br />
our society; confronting every one of us. The men and women who<br />
have worked to make Swanton Lodge a reality have ' confronted this<br />
challenge. They have bridged the gap between ideal and action<br />
by displaying a true sense of mission.<br />
For more than 115 years, the Sydney City M1, ission has dedicated<br />
itself to the homeless, the helpless.<br />
Although the Mission is now a vast organization, with a budget<br />
of $ 2.5 million, it is able to offer a network of ' services<br />
throughout the city, simply because Australian men and women are<br />
prepared to commit themselves to other people. 2 I </p>
<p>-2-<br />
Voluntary agencies such as this Mission are providing services<br />
in a way no government can hope to match. They are better<br />
equipped to face and meet directly the very special needs of<br />
the disadvantaged in our complex industrial society in ways<br />
which help people to become independent, and enhances their<br />
dignity and self-esteem.<br />
Looking at the problem in simple, practical terms, voluntary<br />
agencies can supply what money cannot human compassion,<br />
support and understanding. This voluntary work has the<br />
enormous strength that it is undertaken out of a deep personal<br />
commitmcnt to a cause, work whose only reward is the knowvledge<br />
of having helped those less fortunate in the community.<br />
Clearly the care, the time, energy and experience the Sydney<br />
City Mission contributes to human need cannot be matched by<br />
government and bureaucracy. That is one reason why my Government<br />
places such emphasis on the cooperative work of voluntary groups.<br />
We believe the interaction by individuals, groups and governments<br />
at all levels is utterly necessary for any social welfare<br />
policy to effectively meet the needs of people.<br />
Of course, the Government is aware of the financial burden carried<br />
by voluntary relief group agencies such as the Sydney City Mission.<br />
We are also aware of our own responsibilities. The Commonwealth<br />
Government has contributed over $ 800,000 to the capital cost of<br />
the Swanton Lodge. We will continue to support this project<br />
by providing substantial subsidies for meal, accommodation and<br />
salary costs.<br />
We share with the Sydney City Mission a real concern for those<br />
people who have become the casualties of our society, the drug<br />
dependent, the alcoholics and the homeless, who will be<br />
sheltered and helped in this centre.<br />
Swanton Lodge offers new hope for these people. It offers an<br />
alternative " home" to the dilapidated buildings, to the parks<br />
and streets of Sydney, and to the cells of its jails.<br />
Above all, this Lodge and this day stand as a moniment to the<br />
common humanity of all men and women and the commitment to<br />
overcoming the problems raised by poverty, alcohol, drugs<br />
or loneliness.<br />
Without such an organisation, there would be little hope for<br />
so many people, people so much in need of the community's<br />
compassion, yet perhaps least able to arouse it.<br />
I understand that 105 homeless, alcoholic and drug dependent<br />
men and women will be provided with accommodation and services<br />
in Swanton Lodge which also includes a detoxification unit,<br />
a medical centre and a sheltered workshop. 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
I would like to congratulate further the mission on its<br />
courage and enterprise in presenting " Operation Understanding-<br />
The Awakening of a Social Conscience" during the past week.<br />
The Sydney City Mission has filled a need in this city ever<br />
since its foundation by Benjamin Short. Today that need is<br />
stronger than ever. The problems of society are more complex,<br />
they demand new solutions.<br />
This great Mission continues to respond in its helping and<br />
healing with courage, care and dedication. It is facing up to<br />
these new challenges with a rare blend of sensitivity, compassion<br />
and innovation.<br />
am privileged to be with you today and am honoured to declare<br />
Swanton officially open. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
