<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6112</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON. R.J. HAWKE AC, MP TO THE AUSTRALIAN MINING INDUSTRY COUNCIL DINNER CANBERRA 12 MAY 1983</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/05/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006112.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
I AM DELIGHTED TO HAVE THIS OPPORTUNITY TO ADDRESS<br />
SO DISTINGUISHED AND REPRESENTATIVE A GROUP FROM THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN MINING INDUSTRY EARLY IN THE LIFE OF MY GOVERNMENT.<br />
SOME OF YOU MADE IMPORTANT CONTRIBUTIONS AT THE NATIONAL<br />
ECONOMIC SUJVIT AND FOR THAT, ONCE AGAIN, ALLOW ME TO<br />
THANK YOU ON BEHALF OF THE GOVERNMENT AND PEOPLE OF<br />
AUSTRALIA, OTHERS HAVE MADE REPRESENTATIONS ON<br />
POLICY ISSUES THROUGH MY MINISTERS. AND WHILE THIS<br />
DINNER ITSELF IS AN ANNUAL AND RELATIVELY FORMAL AFFAIR,<br />
LET ME SAY THAT OCCASIONS LIKE THIS CAN BE USED TO FURTHER<br />
THE PROCESS OF COMMUNICATION, CO-OPERATION AND INFORMATIONSHARING<br />
WHICH IS BASIC TO THE APPROACH OF MY GOVERNMENT<br />
TO THE GREAT TASK ENTRUSTED TO US BY THE PEOPLE OF<br />
AUSTRALIA, THE MINING INDUSTRY HAS BEEN IMPORTANT TO<br />
AUSTRALIAN PROGRESS AND PROSPERITY VIRTUALLY FROM THE VERY<br />
BEGINNINGS OF SETTLEMENT. INDEED, OUR FIRST COMMERCIAL<br />
EXPORT WAS NOT WOOL BUT COAL TO INDIA IN 1801.<br />
AND OF COURSE, TODAYj MINING IS CRITICALLY IMPORTANT,<br />
I CANNOT IMAGINE AUSTRALIA FINDING ITS WAY OUT OF THE<br />
ECONOMIC CRISIS WITHOUT A PROSPEROUS'AND EXPANDING MINING<br />
INDUSTRY. SIMILARLY, AS WAS MADE CLEAR BY MINING INDUSTRY<br />
REPRESENTATIVES AT THE SUMMIT, THE PROFITABILITY OF THE<br />
MINING INDUSTRY DEPENDS CRITICALLY ON THE ECONOMIC HEALTH OF THE<br />
WHOLE AUSTRALIAN COMMUNITY<br />
B Y T E P R J.. 11 S-1 E ON HA KE AC MP<br />
TO THE AUSTRALIAN fNi[ NI NG INDUSTRY COUCIL DINNER<br />
CA,, BERRA<br />
12 MAY 1983 </p>
<p>AND THOSE RENiARKS SERVE TO INTRODUCE THE THEME<br />
I W'ANT TO STRESS TONIGHT -THE INTERDEPENDENCE OF OUR<br />
SOCIETY AND OUR ECONOiMY -AN INTERDEPENDENCE WHICH IS BOTH<br />
NATION4AL AND INTERNATIONAL,<br />
THIS INTERDEPENDENCE WITH THE WIDER NATIONAL ECONOMY<br />
AND SOCIETY IS A UNIVERSAL FEATURE OF MODERN ECONOMIC LIFE.<br />
INTERDEPENDENCE IS ALSO AN IMPORTANT FEATURE OF<br />
INTERNATIONAL ECONOMIC LIFE AS YOU HAVE BEEN DISCUSSING<br />
TODAY, AND OF COURSE, A CENTRAL THEME OF THE SUMMIT WAS<br />
THE INTERDEPENDENCE OF ALL SECTIONS OF OUR COMMUNITY,<br />
IT WAS THE UNANIMOUS WELL, ALMOST UNANIMOUS RECOGNITION<br />
OF THAT INDEPENDENCE WHICH LAY AT THE ROOT OF THE SUCCESS<br />
OF THE SUMMIT. AND ITS CONTINUING RECOGNITION, AS A<br />
PERMANENT FEATURE OF OUR NATIONAL APPROACH, WILL BE<br />
ESSENTIAL IF THE WORK OF THE CONFERENCE IS TO BEAR ITS<br />
FULL FRUIT, THERE CAN BE NO DOUBT THAT THE INTERNATIONAL ECONOMIC<br />
ENVIRONMENT HAS BEEN GENERALLY UNFAVOURABLE FOR DOMESTIC<br />
ECONOMIC GROWTH FOR MUCH OF THE PAST DECADE. YET THE<br />
REALITY IS THAT OUR DOMESTIC PERFORMANCE HAS BEEN WORSE<br />
THAN THAT OF OTHER DEVELOPED ECONOMIES, AND THEREFORE WORSE<br />
THAN AUSTRALIANS MIGHT REASONABLY HAVE EXPECTED, EVEN IN<br />
CONDITIONS OF ADVERSE INTERNATIONAL CONDITIONS. IN THE YEAR<br />
OR SO BEFORE my GOVERNMENT TOOK OFFICE, AUSTRALIAN INFLATION<br />
HAD BEEN TWICE THE OECD AVERAGE, OUR CURRENT ACCOUNT DEFICIT<br />
WAS LARGER AS A PROPORTION OF GDP THAN ANY OTHER'OECD COUNTRY,<br />
AND OUR PERFORMANCE ON GROWTH IN OUTPUT AND EMPLOYMENT WAS<br />
AMONGST THE WORST OF DEYELOPED' COUNTRIES. </p>
<p>f's' GOVERNMENT IS SEEKING TO BRIDGE THE ENORMOUS GAP<br />
BE TW( E EN AUSTRALIAN ECONOMIC OPPORTUNITIES AND PERFORiMANCE<br />
THROUGH RECOGNITION OF THE IMPORTANCE OF INTERDEPENDENCE<br />
IN ECONOMIC LIFE, MIANY OF OUR FAILURES AS A NATION HAVE<br />
RESULTED FROM ARTIFICIAL DIVISIONS IN OUR SOCIETY,<br />
WE HAVE FAILED TO GRASP OPPORTUNITIES TO IMPROVE THE<br />
ECONOMIC CONDITION OF AUSTRALIA AS A WHOLE BECAUSE ON<br />
OCCAS4ONS. J THERE HAS BEEN A SHORTSIGHTED INSISTENCE THAT<br />
SHORT-TERM SECTIONAL INTERESTS SHOULD COME FIRST.<br />
CLEARLY, OUR FAILURES IN RECENT YEARS HAVE NO SINGLE OR<br />
SIMPLE CAUSE; AND IT IS FUTILE FOR ONE SECTION TO SEEK<br />
TO CAST ALL THE BLAME ON SOME OTHER SECTION.<br />
BUT I DO BELIEVE IT IS BEYOND DISPUTE THAT MANY OF<br />
OUR CURRENT PROBLEMS ARISE FROM THIS BASIC FAILURE TO GRASP<br />
FULLY THE BASIC INTERDEPENDENCE OF ALL SECTIONS UPON THE<br />
OTHERS. THIS MAY SEEM TOO SIMPLE A POINT TO HOLD THE KEY TO<br />
RESTORATION OF OUR NATIONAL FORTUNES. BUT SIMPLE THOUGH<br />
IT IS, IT HAS BEEN TOO LITTLE UNDERSTOOD, AND INSUFFICIENTLY<br />
ACTED UPON. </p>
<p>I.<br />
AN* D AN IMPORTANT PART OF THE CONCEPT OF THE SUbMMIT<br />
AND ITS ACTUAL W-, ORK WAS TO PROMOTE A WIDER AN4D BETTER<br />
UNDERSTANDING OF THAT FUNDAMENTAL FACT.<br />
HISTORICALLY, ECONOMIC GROWTH AND PROSPERITY HAVE<br />
BEEN ASSOCIATED WITH A HIGH DEGREE OF SOCIAL COHESION,<br />
A HIGH DEGREE OF AGREEMENT WITHIN AUSTRALIAN SOCIETY<br />
ABOUT NATIONAL GOALS. ABROAD, THE SOCIETIES WHICH HAVE<br />
PERFORMED BEST IN PRESENT CONDITIONS HAVE BEEN CHARACTERISED<br />
BY A HIGH DEGREE OF INTERNAL AGREEMENT ON CRITICAL<br />
NATIONAL GOALS.<br />
ITHINK IT IS CLEAR, FROM ALL OUR EXPERIENCE,<br />
THAT AUSTRALIA AS A WHOLE WILL BE LESS SUCCESSFUL, AND MOST<br />
IF NOT ALL OF ITS PARTS WILL BE DISADVANTAGED, IF<br />
INDIVIDUALS AND SECTIONAL INTERESTS ARE UNABLE TO ACT<br />
OUT OF MOTIVES BEYOND THEIR OWN IMMEDIATE PECUNIARY ADVANTAGE.<br />
MINING INDUSTRY LEADERS AT THE SUMMIT WERE<br />
PARTICULARLY CONCERNED TO MAINTAIN AUSTRALIAN COMPETITIVENESS<br />
THROUGH CONTROL OF WAGE COSTS, BUDGET POLICY AND<br />
INTEREST RATES AND TAXATION ON MINING. THESE AREAS<br />
PROVIDE AS GOOD EXAMPLES AS ANY OF THE POINTS I HAVE BEEN<br />
SEEKING TO MAKE. v </p>
<p>ON WAGE COSTS, THERE IS SOME SUPERFICIAL ATTRACTION<br />
IN DEMUANDING THAT EMPLOYED WAGE-EARNERS ACCEPT RESTRAINT,,<br />
WITHOUT HEED OF THE CONTEXT OF THE RESTRAINT. CERTAINLY<br />
OUR ECONOMIC MODELS WILL GENERATE BETTER EMPLOYMENT<br />
GROWTH IN TIMES OF UNEMPLOYMENT IF WE PLUG IN ZERO WAGE<br />
GROW,, TH OVER LONG PERIODS OF TIME. BUT THIS IS AN UNREAL<br />
EXERCISE, UNLESS WE ANALYSE CAREFULLY THE CONDITIONS THAT<br />
ARE NECESSARY TO THIS OR OTHER OUTCOMES THAT ARE FAVOURABLE<br />
TO STRONG EMPLOYMENT GROWTH. WE KNOW THAT IN THIS FREE SOCIETY<br />
WITH ITS MIXED ECONOMY, SOME ORGANISED WORKERS ARE ABLE TO<br />
WIN FOR THEMSELVES SUBSTANTIAL WAGE INCREASES EVEN IN<br />
ADVERSE ECONOMIC CONDITIONS. WE ALSO KNOW THAT THE TRADITIONS<br />
OF THIS ECONOMY GENERATE EXTREMELY STRONG TENDENCIES TO EXTEND<br />
WAGE INCREASES IN SOME INDUSTRIES ACROSS THE WHOLE ECONOMY.<br />
THUS THE RESORT TO DECENTRALISED WAGE-SETTING TWO YEARS AGO<br />
LED TO THE LARGEST WAGE INCREASES SINCE THE EARLY 1970s,<br />
AND WAS ONE OF THE CAUSES OF THE LOSS OF COMPETITIVENESS<br />
AND THE INCREASE IN UNEMPLOYMENT WHICH WE MUST NOW REMEDY,<br />
WE SHOULD TAKE THIS AS A WARNING AGAINST ANY IDEA OF<br />
ANY QUICK FIX" I ON WAGES POLICY OUR REALISTIC HOPE IS THAT<br />
WE CAN BUILD BROAD COMMUNITY AGREEMENT AROUND A PROGRAM OF<br />
MODERATE GROWTH IN WAGES AND OTHER INCOMES. WE ARE AIMING<br />
FOR RATES OF WAGE GROWTH THAT ARE LOW ENOUGH TO SUPPORT A<br />
LONG PERIOD OF EMPLOYMENT AND OUTPUT GROWTH, BUT NOT SO LOW<br />
AS TO BE IMPRACTICABLE. v / 6 </p>
<p>r<br />
WE HAVE AlIMED TO STAY WITHIN THE BOUNDS OF WHAT<br />
WILL HAVE WIDESPREAD SUPPORT WITHIN THE COMNMUNITY,<br />
THIS SUPPORT WILL ONLY BE FORTHCOMING, HOWEVER, IF OUR<br />
OTHER POLICIES, FOR EXAMPLE ON TAXES AND SUBSIDIES AND<br />
POLICIES WITH RESPECT TO NON-WAGE INCOMES, ARE SEEN AS<br />
BEING FAIR BY THOSE WHOM WE ARE ASKING TO EXERCISE RESTRAINT.<br />
THE SAME EXERCISE OF RESTRAINT BY POWERFUL GROUPS<br />
IN THE NATIONAL INTEREST IS NECESSARY FOR SUCCESSFUL BUDGET<br />
MANAGEMENT. OUR GOVERNMENT HAS INHERITED A DISASTROUS<br />
BUDGETARY SITUATION WHICH, IF NOT CORRECTED, WOULD PLACE<br />
INTOLERABLE PRESSURES ON FINANCIAL MARKETS AND KILL RECOVERY<br />
AS SOON AS PRIVATE INVESTMENT LIFTED ITS HEAD. THE WHOLE<br />
AUSTRALIAN COMMUNITY HAS A POWERFUL INTEREST TO SEE THAT<br />
THIS SITUATION IS CORRECTED. BUT THE CORRECTION WILL REQUIRE<br />
A LARGE NUMBER OF ACTS OF RESTRAINT, ACROSS THE-BOARD.<br />
My GOVERNMENT IS DETERMINED TO CORRECT THE STRUCTURAL<br />
WEAKNESS IN AUSTRALIAN BUDGETS, WE WOULD B3E GREATLY ASSISTED<br />
IF EACH SECTION OF THE COMMUNITY WHICH IS BEING ASKED TO BEAR<br />
PART OF THE NECESSARY FISCAL RESTRAINT, IS WILLING TO COUNT<br />
THE WIDE GAINS ON INTEREST RATES AND ECONOMIC STABILITY,<br />
AGAINST THE IMMEDIATE COSTS. As IN WAGES POLICY, WE ARE<br />
AIMING FOR A SET OF CHANGES IN FISCAL POLICY WHICH, TAKEN<br />
AS A WHOLE, ARE ACCEPTED AS BEING FAIR BY THE ENTIRE<br />
AUSTRALIAN COMMUNITY. i / 7 </p>
<p>-7-<br />
THE THIRD AREA OF DOMESTIC POLICY WHICH IWOULD<br />
LIKE TO USE AS AN EXAMPLE OF INTERDEPENDENCE BETWEEN<br />
DOMESTIC INTEREST GROUPS IS MINING TAXATION POLICY,<br />
SENATOR W'ALSH HAS OUTLINED THE GOVERNMENT' S PRIORITIES IN<br />
THIS AREA. 1E SEE CONSIDERABLE ADVANTAGES IN REPLACING<br />
THE CRUDE OIL LEVY BY A RESOURCE RENT TAX BY 1984-85.<br />
W4E ALSO SEE ADVANTAGES IN REPLACING THE EXISTING SYSTEM.<br />
OF DISTORTING ROYALTIES) EXPORT TAXES AND OTHER SPECIAL<br />
CHARGES ON OTHER MINING BY A RESOURCE RENT TAX, ESPECIALLY<br />
FOR COAL, WE BELIEVE THAT SUCH A SHI FT WOULD BE GREATLY<br />
BENEFICIAL TO THE AUSTRALIAN COMMUNITY AS A WHOLE, AND TO<br />
AUSTRALIANS INVOLVED IN THE COAL INDUSTRY AS A WHOLE.<br />
BUT THESE CHANGES WOULD BE POSSIBLE ONLY IF INDIVIDUAL GROUPS<br />
WERE ABLE TO RECOGNISE SUCH OVERALL BENEFITS AS WELL AS<br />
NARROW SECTIONAL BENEFITS,<br />
THE CURRENT RECESSION H-AS H-GHLIGHTED THE DAMAGE<br />
THAT DISTORTING TAXES IN THE COAL INDUSTRY HAVE DONE TO THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN ECONOMY. -OVER THE PROSPEROUS YEARS, SPECIFIC<br />
AND AD VA. LOREM ROYALTIES, EXPORT TAXES AND SUPER-ECONOMIC<br />
RAIL CHARGES WERE GRADUALLY RAISED BY THE COMMONWEALTH<br />
AND THE RELEVANT STATES UNTIL THEY REPRESENTED A HIGH<br />
PROPORTION OF THE VALUE OF PRODUCTION. IN THE GOOD TIMES,<br />
THE TOTAL OF THESE CHARGES LEFT THE LOWEST-COST MINES<br />
HIGHLY PROFITABLE, AND MODERATE-COST MINES IN A<br />
COMFORTABLE POSITION. THEY PROBABLY DETERRED THE s a/ 8 </p>
<p>DEVELOPCMENT OF SOMiE HI OH--COST 1 I1NES EVEN THEN, T HEY<br />
ALSO DETERRED EXPANSION AT MANY ESTABLISHED MINES.<br />
BUT THE BUOYANT MARKET CONDITIONS DISTRACTED ATTENTION<br />
FROMl SOME OF THE UNDERLYING DIFFICULTIES.<br />
THE CONTRACTION OF OUR TRADITIONAL NORTHEAST ASIAN<br />
MARKETS AND THE REDUCTIONS IN PRICE OVER THE PAST YEAR HAVE<br />
MADE THE DISTORTIONS AND COSTS OF OUR COAL MINING ROYALTIES<br />
MUCH MORE OBVIOUS. HIGH-COST MINES HAVE BEEN PUSHED TO THE<br />
EDGE OF CLOSURE. SOME LOW-COST. MINES STILL EARN GOOD RETURNS, 0<br />
BUT ARE RESTRAINED IN THEIR EXPANSION. THE WHOLE INDUSTRY<br />
IS CONFINED TO TRADITIONAL MARKETS IN OUR REGION, AND KEPT<br />
OUT OF LARGE, DISTANT MARKETS, IN EUROPE AND ELSEWHERE, BY<br />
THE COMBINATION OF SEA TRANSPORT COSTS WHICH ARE BEYOND OUR<br />
CONTROL, AND COST-INCREASING LEVIES OF VARIOUS KINDS THAT<br />
ARE WELL WITHIN OUR CONTROL,<br />
THERE IS NO DOUBT THAT OUR COAL MINING INDUSTRY<br />
COULD EXPAND WELL BEYOND ITS PRESENT LIMITS IF ROYALTIES<br />
WERE APPLIED ONLY IN FORMS THAT DID NOT INCREASE THE COST OF<br />
LESS PROFITABLE MINING OPERATIONS# THIS WOULD BE TO THE<br />
ADVANTAGE OF EMPLOYMENT, PROFITS AND GOVERNMENT REVENUE.<br />
THE COMMONWEALTH'S INTEREST IN REPLACING THE CURRENT<br />
DISTORTING SYSTEM OF CHARGES WITH A SINGLE TAX OR CHARGE<br />
BASED ON PROFITABILITY IS NOT TO INCREASE ITS OWN REVENUE.<br />
I SHOULD ADD THAT IN THE CURRENT BUDGETARY SITUATION WE ARE<br />
IN NO POSITION TO REDUCE OUR REVENUES. OUR INTEREST IS TO<br />
ENSURE THAT THE MINING INDUSTRY IS ABLE TO EXPAND<br />
EFFICIENTLY TO THE LIMITS OF ITS ECONOMIC POTENTIAL, of 19/ </p>
<p>-3-<br />
W DO NOT DELUDE OURSELVES THAT IT WILL BE EASY TO<br />
GET STATE GOVERNMENTS OF DIFFERENT POLITICAL PERSUASION,<br />
MINING COMPANIES WITH WIDELY DIFFERING INTERESTS, AND THE<br />
COMMONWEALTH TO AGREE ON AN IMPROVED SYSTEM OF MINING<br />
CHARGES. BUT THE STARTING POINT HERE, AS IN OTHER AREAS<br />
W'HERE MAJOR REFORM IS NECESSARY TO LIFT AUSTRALIAN ECONOMIC<br />
PERFORMANCE, IS THE RECOGNITION OF THE INTERDEPENDENCE OF<br />
THE INTERESTS OF DIFFERENT GROUPS IN AUSTRALIAN SOCIETY.<br />
HERE, AS ELSEWHERE, WE MUST FIND SOLUTIONS THAT MAXIMISE THE<br />
JOINT WELFARE. WE WILL FAIL IN THIS IF INDIVIDUAL<br />
GOVERNMENTS, OR INDIVIDUAL MINING COMPANIES, OR AUSTRALIAN<br />
MINING COMPANIES AS A GROUP, OR MINING UNIONS, SEEK TO<br />
MAXIMISE THEIR OWN SECTIONAL GAINS.<br />
I INVITE YOU TO JOIN US IN SEEKING A MORE EFFICIENT<br />
SYSTEM OF COAL MINING ROYALTIES, THAT PRESERVES THE<br />
LEGITIMATE INTERESTS OF MINE WORKERS IN MAXIMUM LEVELS OF<br />
MINING ACTIVITIES, THE LEGITIMATE-. INTERESTS OF THE-CITIZENS<br />
OF AUSTRALIA AND OF ITS STATES IN RECEIVING A FAIR PRICE FOR<br />
MINERAL DEPOSITS EXPLOITED BY PRIVATE FIRMS, AND THE<br />
LEGITIMATE INTERESTS OF THE MINING INDUSTRIES IN FAIR<br />
REWARDS FOR CAPITAL, RISKS AND SKILL, TOGETHER WITH<br />
INCENTIVES FOR HIGH PERFORMANCE. </p>
<p>I HAVE DRAWN MY EXAMPLES MAINLY FROM AUSTRALIAN<br />
DOMESTIC ECONOMIC MANAGEMENT AND PERFORMANCE, SINCE THESE<br />
HAVE BEEN MY OWN MAIN CONCERNS OVER THE PAST TWO MONTHS.<br />
BUT MANY OF THE SAME ISSUES, INVOLVING INTERDEPENDENCE<br />
OF DIFFERENT INTERESTS AND GROUPS, ARISE IN THE INTERNATIONAL<br />
SPHERE, THESE HAVE BEEN THE MAIN SUBJECT OF YOUR OWN<br />
DELIBERATIONS TODAY,<br />
THE NEW AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT HAS NOT YET SETTLED<br />
ITS POSITION ON A NUMBER OF THESE ISSUESi SO THAT YOUR<br />
CONCLUSIONS WILL BE HELPFUL TO US. BUT I WOULD LIKE TO<br />
INDICATE SOME OF THE GENERAL PRINCIPLES THAT WILL GUIDE US<br />
IN FORMULATING POLICY. FIRST, WE MUST LOOK FOR GENUINELY<br />
CO-OPERATIVE SOLUTIONS, THE INTERNATIONAL ECONOMY CAN<br />
FUNCTION EFFECTIVELY ONLY IF INDIVIDUAL NATIONS AND GROUPS<br />
OF NATIONS CONSTRAIN THE PURSUIT OF THEIR INDIVIDUAL INTERESTS<br />
IN THE WIDER INTERNATIONAL INTEREST. IF EACH COUNTRY<br />
THINKS ONLY OF ITS OWN NARROW INTERESTS, WE WILL ALL BE THE<br />
POORER, WHETHER WE ARE TALKING OF PROTECTION, THE LAW OF THE<br />
SEA, OR ANY OTHER OF THE GREAT INTERNATIONAL ECONOMIC ISSUES<br />
OF THE TIME, SECOND, IT MUST BE BUILT AROUND EFFICIENT<br />
SOLUTIONS TO INTERNATIONAL PROBLEMS. CO-OPERATION WILL<br />
BREAK DOWN IN DISSENSION UNLESS THE OBJECT OF CO-OPERATION IS<br />
EFFICIENT IN THE SENSE THAT IT IS CAPABLE OF INCREASING<br />
INTERNATIONAL WELFARE. THIRD, IT WILL NOT PREVAIL UNLESS<br />
IT PROVIDES FOR A DISTRIBUTION OF THE BENEFITS OF CO-OPERATION<br />
THAT IS WIDELY RECOGNISED AS BEING FAIR. WITHIN THE VALUE<br />
SYSTEMS THAT SUSTAIN MOST HUMAN SOCIETIESi THIS REQUIRES<br />
RELATIVELY GREATER CONCERN FOR THE SHARES OF THE POOR AND THE<br />
WEAK, </p>
<p>11-<br />
IN NATIONAL AND INTERNATIONAL ECONOMIC LIFE,<br />
I HOPE THAT THE AUSTRALIAN MINING INDUSTRY WILL JOIN<br />
MY GOVERNMENT IN SEEKING CO-OPERATIVE SOLUTIONS TO OUR<br />
PROBLEMS, TO THE ADVANTAGE OF ALL AUSTRALIANS, AND OF A<br />
WIDER INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY. AND, I REPEAT, THE KEY<br />
TO THE CO-OPERATION WE SEEK FROM ALL SECTIONS OF THE<br />
COMMUNITY IS A GREATER AND DEEPER RECOGNITION BY ALL OF HOW MUCH:<br />
WE DO REALLY DEPEND UPON EACH OTHER, IN THE TASK OF BUILDING<br />
A BETTER FUTURE FOR ALL, IN THIS GREAT NATION OF OURS<br />
THIS NATION SO RICH IN RESOURCES TO WHICH THE MINING INDUSTRY<br />
MAKES SUCH A VITAL CONTRIBUTION, BUT, ABOVE ALL, RICH IN<br />
THE MOST VITAL RESOURCE OF ALL THE SKILLS, ABILITIES<br />
AND QUALITIES OF OUR PEOPLE,<br />
FINALLY, I AM SURE, MR CHAIRMAN, YOU WILL WISH ME<br />
TO EXTEND OUR CONGRATULATIONS TO YOUR SUCCESSOR, MR LOTON.<br />
BRIAN'S PERSONAL CONTRIBUTION TO-THE WORK AND SUCCESS OF THE<br />
SUMMIT WAS INVALUABLE,-I THANK HIM FOR IT. I LOOK FORWARD<br />
TO CONTINUED CO-OPERATION WITH HIM AS PRESIDENT, AND WITH<br />
THE MINING INDUSTRY COUNCIL AS A WHOLE, FOR THE ADVANCEMENT,<br />
NOT ONLY OF AUSTRALIA', S GREAT MINING INDUSTRY, BUT FOR<br />
THE ADVANCEMENT OF AUSTRALIA ITSELF. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
