<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7621</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF DOORSTOP, MARIST COLLEGE, ASHGROVE, BRISBANE 4 JUNT 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/06/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007621.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
C2<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF DOORSTOP, MARIST COLLEGE, ASHGROVE, BRISBANE<br />
4 JUNE 1989<br />
E &amp; O0E-PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, is the Government looking<br />
at privatising Qantas as soon as possible?<br />
PM: Well you heard Mr Willis. It's not a question of<br />
looking at it as soon as possible. There are processes<br />
under way, as Mr Willis said, in the Party and I thought<br />
he put the position very fairly and straight.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you have a problem with Party policy?<br />
PM: That' s a silly question, if I may say so.<br />
JOURNALIST: What's your reaction to the news from Iran,<br />
Sir? PM: Well, I trust that the death of the Ayatollah will<br />
not be followed by a period of turbulence. I hope the<br />
processes of transition are peaceful and that we will<br />
see a situation which Iran will be able, more than it<br />
has been in the past, to be able to take its place fully<br />
in the community of nations. There have been difficulties<br />
in the past and a message will be sent from us by the<br />
Governor General, as is appropriate from Head of State,<br />
to Iran expressing our condolences in the situation,<br />
but we look to the future now and we hope that that future<br />
situation, after a non violent transition, that there<br />
be the opportunity, I repeat, for a greater degree of<br />
positive involvement by Iran in the community of nations.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
