<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4602</transcript-id>
    <title>THE NEW MINISTRY, 19 DECEMBER 1977</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/12/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004602.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
~ g2<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 19 DECEMBER 1977<br />
THE NEW MINISTRY<br />
The new Ministry will be sworn at Government House<br />
tomorrow morning. His Excellency the Governor-General has<br />
authorised me to announce details of the new Cabinet and<br />
Ministry. The Ministers of State Act limits the total<br />
number of Ministers to 27. Two Ministers in the present<br />
Ministry, the Deputy Prime Minister and the Treasurer,<br />
each have responsibility for two major Departments. I<br />
propose to put to Parliament when it meets an amendment of<br />
that Act to permit the appointment of one additional<br />
Minister. If this is approved the full list and portfolios<br />
of Ministers will be as follows: </p>
<p>2.<br />
MINISTRY LIST<br />
1. Prime Minister<br />
2. Deputy Prime Minister and Minister<br />
for Trade and Resources<br />
Minister for<br />
Minister for<br />
Minister for<br />
Minister for<br />
Rel1at ions<br />
Minister for<br />
Treasurer<br />
Minister for<br />
Minister for<br />
Minister for<br />
Minister for<br />
Minister for<br />
Minister for<br />
Minister for<br />
Minister for<br />
Affairs<br />
Minister for<br />
Minister for<br />
Minister for<br />
Minister for<br />
Minister for Industry and Commerce<br />
Primary Industry<br />
Administrative Services<br />
Employment and Industrial<br />
Transport Education Foreign Affairs<br />
Defence Social Security<br />
Finance Aboriginal Affairs<br />
Health Immigration and Ethnic<br />
the Northern Territory<br />
Construction<br />
National Development<br />
Science<br />
Post and Telecommunications<br />
22. Attorney-General<br />
23. Minister for Productivity<br />
24. Minister for Business'and Consumer<br />
Affairs<br />
Minister for Special Trade<br />
Representations<br />
26. Minister for Home Affairs and Minister<br />
for the Capital Territory<br />
27. Minister for Environment, Housing and<br />
Community Development<br />
28. Minister for Veterans' Affairs<br />
3. 4. 6. 7. 8. 9. 11. 12. 13.<br />
14. 16.<br />
17. 18.<br />
19. 21. Senator the Hon. G. Sheil<br />
The Rt. Hon. Malcolm Fraser, C. H.,<br />
M. P.<br />
The Rt. Hon. J. D. Anthony, M. P.<br />
The Rt. Hon. Phillip Lynch, M. P.<br />
The Rt. Hon. Ian Sinclair, M. P.<br />
Senator the Rt. Hon. R. G. Withers<br />
The Hon. A. A. Street, M. P.<br />
The Hon. P. J. Nixon, M. P.<br />
The Hon. John Howard, M. P.<br />
Senator the Hon. J. L. Carrick<br />
The Hon. Andrew Peacock, M. P.<br />
The Hon. D. J. Killen, M. P.<br />
Senator the Hon. Margaret<br />
Guil1foyle<br />
The Hon. Eric Robinson, M. P.<br />
The Hon. Ian Viner, M. P.<br />
The Hon. Ralph J. Hunt, M. P,.<br />
The Hon. M. J. R. MacKellar, M. P.<br />
The Hon. Evan Adermann, M. P.<br />
The Hon. John McLeay, M. P.<br />
The Hon. Kevin Newman, M. P.<br />
Senator the Hon. J. J. Webster<br />
The Hon. A. A. Staley, M. P.<br />
Senator the Hon. Peter Durack<br />
The Hon. Ian Macphee, M. P.<br />
The Hon. Wal Fife, M. P.<br />
The Hon. R. V. Garland, M. P.<br />
The Hon. R. J. Ellicott, M. P<br />
The Hon. R. J. Groom, M. P. </p>
<p>The first 14 Ministers will comprise the Cabinet.<br />
Pending amendment of the Ministers of State Act,<br />
Mr Garland will be sworn as Minister for Veterans' Affairs<br />
as well as Minister for Special Trade Representations.<br />
Senator Sheil will be sworn as an Executive Councillor<br />
tomorrow and will be sworn as Minister for Veterans' Affairs<br />
as soon as the Act is amended.<br />
The appointment of Ministers to assist the<br />
Prime Minister or Ministers in major portfolios has worked<br />
very well and I propose to continue along these lines.<br />
The following Ministers will be appointed also as Ministers<br />
Assisting: Minister Assisting the Prime Minister<br />
( including Public Service Matters)<br />
Minister Assisting the Prime Minister<br />
in Federal Affairs<br />
Minister Assisting the Minister for<br />
Trade and Resources<br />
Minister Assisting the Minister for<br />
Defence<br />
Minister Assisting the Minister for<br />
Employment and Industrial Relations<br />
Minister Assisting the Minister for<br />
Primary Industry Mr Viner<br />
Senator Carrick<br />
Mr Garland<br />
Mr McLeay<br />
Mr Groom<br />
Mr Adermann<br />
The Minister for Primary Industry will be Leader<br />
of the House. Senator Withers will be Vice-President of the<br />
Executive Council and Leader of the Government in the Senate.<br />
I have known for some time that Senator Cotton,<br />
the Minister for Industry and Commerce, has been </p>
<p>interested in serving his country in a different capacity.<br />
He does not wish to join the new Ministry and we will be sorry<br />
to lose his wide knowledge of industry and business, in Cabinet<br />
and in Government. I have asked him to be Consul-General in<br />
New York for a two-year period and in that capacity to develop<br />
further the strong Australian contacts with United States<br />
business interests. He will report to me on a wide range of<br />
matters affecting our Australian interests. It is planned<br />
that he will take up his new responsibilities towards the<br />
middle of next year.<br />
Mr Lynch will be sworn as Minister for Industry<br />
and Commerce. He has asked to be moved from the arduous<br />
position as Treasurer and to take this leading role in the<br />
important development of industry policy. The Government<br />
recognises the pressing need to co-ordinate its industry policy,<br />
embracing the areas controlled by the Ministers for BACA and<br />
Productivity. I have asked Mr Lynch to undertake an overriding<br />
responsibility in this area. He will co-ordinate particularly<br />
policy developments within the three Departments concerned.<br />
It will be seen from the list of portfolios that<br />
I am proposing to make changes in the structure of the Ministry.<br />
The Deputy Prime Ministership itself is becoming a heavier burden<br />
and the Deputy Prime Minister, Mr Anthony, is carrying a heavier<br />
load of Cabinet work. Mr Anthony has indicated that he feels </p>
<p>the time has come for him to hold only one portfolio instead<br />
of the two Overseas Trade and National Resources at present.<br />
Mr Anthony accordingly will be appointed as Minister for Trade<br />
and Resources, the opportunity being taken to draw together<br />
in the one Department those elements particularly relevant to<br />
our international trade in commodities. The Department of Trade<br />
and Resources will be responsible for the existing functions of<br />
the Department of Overseas Trade, and for the commercial<br />
development and marketing of minerals including uranium and<br />
hydro-carbon fuels.<br />
The remaining functions of the Department of<br />
National Resources and in particular national energy planning<br />
and research and minerals exploration and resource assessment,<br />
will be continued in a newly named Department of National<br />
Development. This Department will also be responsible for the<br />
Government's decentralisation policies.<br />
For some time now the Treasury and the Department<br />
of Finance have been separate Departments operating under the<br />
one Minister, the Treasurer. There is a heavy burden in this<br />
area to be borne at the ministerial level, both in the Parliament<br />
and in responsibility for economic affairs. The time has come,<br />
I believe, for two Ministers to be appointed a Treasurer and<br />
a Minister for Finance and this is now proposed.<br />
Some functions of the Department of the Prime<br />
Minister and Cabinet will be shifted to a new Department of </p>
<p>Home Affairs, in particular the arts and women's affairs;<br />
and from the Department of Administrative Services various<br />
cultural bodies, national archives, and external territories<br />
will also be transferred. Looking ahead I would expect the<br />
Department of Home Affairs in due course to absorb any residual<br />
functions of the Department of the Northern Territory and the<br />
Department of the Capital Territory after the Northern Territory<br />
and Capital Territory respectively achieve the additional<br />
measures of self-government that are presently planned.<br />
In the changes that are to be made I am proposing<br />
a new initiative in respect of policies and programs in the<br />
health and welfare field. Various administrative arrangements<br />
have been examined, including by the Royal Commission on<br />
Australian Government Administration, to achieve maximum<br />
co-ordination. A Secretariat will be established within the<br />
Department of Social Security responsible for the development<br />
of plans and policies and review of existing policies and programs<br />
in the broad field of health and welfare. The Secretariat will<br />
be headed by a senior Second Division officer and will comprise<br />
mainly expert officials seconded from Departments. It will work<br />
to a committee of Permanent Heads and a Standing Committee of<br />
Cabinet, while coming under the immediate supervision of the<br />
Head of the Department of Social Security.<br />
There will be other administrative changes which<br />
will streamline and improve government operations. A new </p>
<p>Background Notes<br />
CHANGES IN MINISTERIAL AN~ D DEPARTMENTAL<br />
RESPONSIBILITIES AND FUNCTIONS<br />
The following details of changes to be made to<br />
administrative arrangements supplement the statement by<br />
the Prime Minister issued on 19 December 1977.<br />
NEW AND RETITLED DEPARTMENTS<br />
A Department of Home Affairs is to be established,<br />
and the existing Departments of National Resources and<br />
Overseas Trade will be replaced by new Departments of National<br />
Development and of Trade and Resources. The number of<br />
departments will increase from 28 to 29.<br />
As mentioned earlier, it has been decided that the<br />
Minister for Special Trade Negotiations will in future be<br />
known as the Minister for Special Trade Representations.<br />
The Department of the Special Trade Negotiator will be renamed<br />
the Department of the Special Trade Representative.<br />
Home Affairs This Department-.* will~ assume responsibility for<br />
administration of the Territory of Cocos ( Keeling) Islands,<br />
the Territory of Christmas Island, Norfolk Island and the<br />
Coral Sea Islands Territory ( from the Department of Administrative<br />
Services), national archives and national museums ( also from the<br />
Department of Administrative Services), and women's affairs and<br />
support for the arts and letters ( from the Department of the<br />
Prime Minister and Cabinet). </p>
<p>2.<br />
Associated bodies for which the Minister for Home<br />
Affairs w'ill be responsible include the Australian War Memorial,<br />
the National Library of Australia, the Australia Council, the<br />
Australian National Gallery, the Australian Film Commission<br />
and the Film and Television School. In addition the permanent<br />
women's advisory body referred to in the policy speech of<br />
21 November will, when established, report to the Minister for<br />
Home Affairs. It is the Government's intention that, in the long<br />
term, residual functions of the Departments of the Northern<br />
Territory and the Capital Territory will be transferred to the<br />
Department of Home Affairs. With this in mind, administration<br />
of the Departmeaits of Home Affairs and the Capital Territory<br />
will, as already indicated, be the responsibility of one<br />
Minister. National Development The functions of this Department reflect the<br />
Government's intention that resources be devoted as a matter<br />
of' priority to the development of a national energy plan.<br />
in addition to the fundamental tasks of geodesy, mapping and<br />
mineral and energy resource assessment, performed by the<br />
Division of National Mapping and the Bureau of Mineral Resources,<br />
Geology and Geophysics, the Department will have responsibility<br />
for energy planning and research, exploration policy, water<br />
resources and electricity, and matters relating to the<br />
processing and distribution of oil and gas. </p>
<p>3.<br />
The Minister for National Development will be<br />
responsible for all bodies which currently report to the Minister<br />
for National Resources, with the exception of the Joint Coal<br />
Board and the National Coal Research Advisory Committee.<br />
Ministerial responsibility for these bodies will be transferred<br />
to the Minister for Trade and Resources. Nuclear commercial<br />
functions of the Australian Atomic Energy Commission will also<br />
become the responsibility of the Minister for Trade and Resources,<br />
all other aspects being allocated to the Minister for National<br />
Development. It has also been decided that responsibility for urban<br />
and regional planning and development, including decentralisation<br />
and growth centres, should be transferred to the new Department, of<br />
National Development from the Department of Environment, Housing<br />
and Community Development. Responsibility for the Albury-Wodonga<br />
Development Corporation, the Ministerial Council on the Development<br />
of Albury-! Wodonga and the Decentralisation Advisory Board will be<br />
transferred to the Minister for National Development from the<br />
Minister for Environment, Housing and Community Development.<br />
Trade and -Resources<br />
This Department will assume responsibility for all.<br />
functions of the existing Department of Overseas Trade, together<br />
with those functions of the existing Department of National<br />
Resources which relate to the mining, production and marketing<br />
of minerals ( including uranium and hydrocarbon fuels), and<br />
economic matters affecting the mining industry. 4 </p>
<p>4.<br />
.4 4.<br />
OTHER CHANGES IN FUNCTIONS AN) RESPONSIBILITIES<br />
Employment and Industrial Relations.<br />
It has been decided that responsibility for the<br />
National Training Council should be transferred from the<br />
Minister for Productivity to the Minister for Employment and<br />
Industrial Relations, and that training policy should be<br />
transferred from the Department of Productivity to the Department<br />
of Employment and Industrial Relations.<br />
Foreign Affairs Responsibility for the Australia-Japan Foundation<br />
will be transferred from the Prime Minister to the-Minister<br />
for Foreign Affairs.<br />
Immigration and Ethnic Affairs<br />
It has been decided to transfer to the Department ol<br />
Immigration and Ethnic Affairs responsibility for post-arrival<br />
migrant welfare ( from Department of Social Security) and<br />
migrant adult education ( from Department of Education).<br />
Prime Minister and Cabinet<br />
Responsibility for Royal Commissions ( other than<br />
servicing aspects) will be transferred from the Department of<br />
Administrative Services to the Department of the Prime Minister<br />
and Cabinet.<br />
Science Responsibility for servicing the Australian Science<br />
and Technology Council will be transferred from the Department </p>
<p>o, Primo Minister and Cabinet to the Department of Science.<br />
Ministerial responsibility for ASTEC will be assumed by the<br />
Minister for Science.<br />
Social Security The Department of Social Security is to assume<br />
responsibility for the development of plans and policies,<br />
and the review of existing policies and programs, in the broad<br />
field of health and welfare. To carry out this important<br />
responsibility, a special Secretariat will be formed within<br />
the Department; the Secretariat, to be headed by a senior<br />
officer, will be small and will consist mainly of expert<br />
officials seconded from departments.<br />
Treasury The Australian Industry Development Corporation<br />
will be transferred from the Finance Ministry to the Treasury<br />
Ministry. December 1977 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
