<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4752</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/07/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004752.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO UNTIL DELIVERY % AUSTLA<br />
FOR PRESS 9 JULY 1978<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
The Goverz7_. e; C has begun the formal process of taking decisions<br />
that will 1-ad to the framing of the Federal Budget.<br />
This year, the Budget takes on a particular significance.<br />
It is one of the most crucial years Australia has faced. It<br />
comes when our own economic recovery is gathering pace and when<br />
other nations are again starting to see Australia as a secure<br />
and stable co-ntry.<br />
Australia must again become a favoured nation for investment.<br />
We must gather and hold a competitive edge with other nations<br />
also competi__--!: for investment funds and for markets.<br />
Decisions we Make at home also come at a critical time on the<br />
international trade and economic front. This is a year when<br />
trade decisions made around the world will affect Australia<br />
and employmentI opportunities for Australians for years to<br />
come. In fact;-, some of these decisions will be made over the<br />
next few weeks by world leaders at the Bonn Summit and the MTN.<br />
The point I make is that this is a year when Australia has to<br />
do its utmost to put its own house in order. For those reasons,<br />
the decisions made in this Budget will follow the most rigorous<br />
and detailed examination of the Government's own housekeeping.<br />
Every area ofE Government spending will come under the microscope.<br />
Spending priorities will be rigidly set. The dollars we collect<br />
from taxpayers will be used wisely and with thrift. We are<br />
determined to count the cost of every spending decision we make<br />
on behalf of the Australian taxpayer.<br />
For too many years in Australia, governments have been less than<br />
responsible, less than caring, with taxpayers money. Governments<br />
seem to have accepted without question that spending must<br />
increase year after year as a matter of course almost as a<br />
divine right.<br />
Those days have been finished since -my Government.<br />
While this Gov--ernment controls taxpayers dollars, we will not be<br />
seduced into automatic willy-nilly annual increases in spending.<br />
Massive irres-ionsibility in Government spending combined with<br />
irresponsibility in wages policy that were the hallmark of the<br />
Labor years, was utterly counter-productive. Our country found,<br />
to our cost6-, that throwing money at problems simple added to<br />
those problems. ./ 2 </p>
<p>Although the Federal Government carries the responsibility for<br />
the Federal Budget, the States too have a real part to play in<br />
exercising discipline and restraint.<br />
Tt is worth noting t~ hat%. spending by the States and their semigovern~<br />
ent and local authorities accounts for more than half<br />
of Australia's tota_ public spending.<br />
In the last two r~ nilyears ( 197 6-77 and 1977-78), the States<br />
have received fcreasing proportion of total grants and<br />
advances. s h increase has come in the form of untied<br />
general grants, e is wide scope for the States to set their<br />
own priorites-.<br />
Expenditure przposals will be examined on their merit alone.<br />
The Government will not be lethargic in providing funds to<br />
meet real needs. We will not be backward in recognising our<br />
responsibilitLies to people, groups and communities not able<br />
to help therselves.<br />
: n fact the rse it true. We will continue to provide creative<br />
support and ==_, grams that advance our national cause and enhance<br />
-he well-beinz and dignity of Australian men and women. We will<br />
continue to stow that we govern for all Australians.<br />
But as the Na-zional Government, we cannot afford to apply anything<br />
less than the strictest discipline to our actions.<br />
I believe the Premiers well understand the special role they can<br />
play in maintaining restraint and thereby contributing to national<br />
goals. I believe they well understand that for Australia today<br />
there is a need for continuing economic responsibility by those<br />
who spend public funds.<br />
IThe Government is committed to responsible, disciplined, economic<br />
management. We have demonstrated that we will not yield to pressure<br />
to do otherwise.<br />
The Budget delivered by the Treasurer on 15 August will consolidate<br />
and strengthen the gains already made. It will show all Australians,<br />
and those looking to Australia, of our complete determination to<br />
build on the strong foundations set over the last 2 years.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
