<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>170</transcript-id>
    <title>DOBELL&#039;S PORTRAIT</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/04/1960</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000170.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Douell's Portrait<br />
Graduated and Capital inms Tax<br />
Taxation<br />
new shiip for Tasrman ran<br />
: Joomera Rocket Range<br />
Chambers of Commerce Guarantee<br />
Scheme<br />
hir. Hasluck and London visit<br />
External Affairs Piortfolio<br />
London Conference<br />
So~ uth frica at length<br />
K~ onopolies etc.<br />
Proposed Daom on M~ urray </p>
<p>PRESS CONFERENCE GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE<br />
RT. HON. R. G. MENZIES ON SATUiDAY 9TH APRIL, 1960<br />
AT 11 A. M.<br />
PRIME MINISTE<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTE<br />
QUESTION: R: Well what can I tell you?<br />
There's a message published in New York this morning<br />
Sir, saying that Time Magazine propose to send Dobell's<br />
portrait of you on a tour of Australia and then to offer<br />
it to you. It's at present on display in the Qantas<br />
Office in New York. Our people are wondering whether<br />
you've heard from them and whether you will accept it.<br />
R: I've heard nothing about it. I read it in the Age<br />
this morning. I've no comment to make on it.<br />
Mr. Calwell last night, Sir, proposed capital . r<br />
tax and graduated tax on Company profits, mainly for tih<br />
undoing I think of General Motors Holdens, as a deflationary<br />
measure, or anti-inflationary measure for the next<br />
budget. Are you likely to consider either?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I don't know ihat we'll consider for the next Bud?. o<br />
It's a little premat'ire. But you've heard this story<br />
about a graduated company tax many times. I seem to remember<br />
it was tried by Mr. Curtin and later on by Mr.<br />
Chifley, and abandoned. Of course, this is all part and<br />
parcel of Mr. Calvell's obsession with the idea that thic<br />
is a profit inflation. That argument has been answered<br />
pretty completely in the House.<br />
', UESTION: Sir, can we take it from : ihat you've said that<br />
there will be no reLgaoe T company tax and no . o<br />
PRIME MINISTER: You can't take me as saying anything whatever abor<br />
the next Budget. I don't know anything about it yet.<br />
That answer doesn't have any implications eithe-, ( Lter)<br />
QUESTION: Mr. Calwell also mentioned that you'll have to increase<br />
taxation to reach a non-deficit Budget. Is that<br />
fair assessment?<br />
PRIME MINISTER. What does Mr. Calwell know about it?<br />
QUESTION: ( Interjection)<br />
Oh, now come on, I'm not arguing about the Budget. Th-;<br />
is April and not even April the 1st.<br />
There are some fleeting rumours around that some<br />
action may be taken jointly by the Governments of Austr,.<br />
lia and New Zealand to provide a new ship to maintain<br />
Australasian Shipping Service on the Tasman. Mini<br />
tells me that he hasn't heard officially of it but sug<br />
ted that if anything had cropped up you may have been c..<br />
cussing it with Mr. Nash.<br />
PRIME MINISTEi;: Joderful. This, I think, involves a question fo--<br />
some replacement for the Honowai doesn't it? al1iel l,<br />
can tell you about it is that Mr. Nash, when I as spci<br />
ing to him on the telephone in Sydney a couple of days r<br />
told me that among othe: things he would like to discuss<br />
,, ith me in London was this question of the shipping link.<br />
And I've said I'd be glad to do that and I've now asked<br />
the Shipping Department to give me . ihatever background<br />
information they have on it so that I'll be qualified to<br />
talk about it. But that's all I can say about it, that's<br />
all I know about it.<br />
QUESTION: During the week, Mr. Menzies, there were reports </p>
<p>published from London, first appearing in tl. e London Daily<br />
Express, that Britain was considering abandoning the . Joomera<br />
Rocket Range and jiving away the Blue Streak and other<br />
missile experiments there.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I hope I'll be relieved from the responsibility of<br />
commenting on Mr. Chapman Pincher's rumours and speculative<br />
stories because one becomes accustomed to them.<br />
QUESTION: Sir, the Chambers of Commerce in their final session<br />
yesterday, agreed to try and sponsor a guarantee scheme<br />
for Commonwealth countries to guarantee investment 3i sks<br />
in some of the lesser developed areas and they propose<br />
that this should be part<br />
PRI1iE MINISTER: Don't tell me; I haven't read it. I'm certainly<br />
not going to comment on it, whatever it is. They didn't<br />
deliver the paper at ray house this morning before I left.<br />
Sir Garfield Barwick will be acting Minister for<br />
Eternal Affairs while I'm away. I notice that there has<br />
been some speculation about " Why Mr. Hasluck?". Well the<br />
answer, of course, might by " Why not?" Mr. Hasluck I'm<br />
taking with me for very good reasons. He's been deeply<br />
immersed in his territorial problems for years now without<br />
any intermission and I think that this will be very helpful<br />
to him to get a sort of distant perspective on these<br />
things'; to come with me to have discussions with the<br />
Colonial Administration in London; to go over to The<br />
Hague and have talks with the Dutch; to have discussic'-<br />
in New York with members of the Trusteeship Council -io<br />
Trusteeship Organisation; putting our point of view<br />
explaining our policies that are being pursued, I thin..<br />
it's very valuable. It has no significance beyond that,<br />
QUES'ION: Might he be useful to you on the question of rac'.-<br />
problems, integration, if those matters are discussed?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: If those matters are discussed, yes. Oh, he'll be<br />
extremely useful to me because he's very experienced and<br />
intelligent.<br />
QUESTION: -y s te-t the Trusteeship Council<br />
formally, Sir?<br />
PRIME MINISTER. Oh, I couldn't tell you that. I don't even know<br />
whether it could be meeting. Their Headquarters are in<br />
New York and that's all I had in mind.<br />
QUESTION: Does your statement, Mr. Menzies, suggest that yo"-<br />
will retain the External Affairs portfolio indcfini-<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I think the last time I was asked about that I s.-<br />
that that would depend entirely on how I found I was<br />
ing out with it.<br />
QUESTION: Have you found out yet Sir?<br />
PRIME MINISTER. Well, I'm so far not very embarrassed by it. No<br />
I've got Senator Gorton doing a lot of work.<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTE Is he doing any policy stuff, Sir, or is that a?.<br />
I; ' ell, not major policy stuff, i mean questions<br />
well they're not really policy stuff I suppose but<br />
questions of approval under the Colombo Plan, they involve,<br />
I suppose elements of policy well he deals with<br />
those. There's a good deal of routine, or semi-routine<br />
administration ihich takes up time. The things he attends<br />
to are broadly those things which are not top policy or </p>
<p>matters which involve some major decision. In which case<br />
he refers them to me and, if necessary, discusses them with<br />
me. So far it's working all right but nobody can pierce<br />
the mists of the future.<br />
QUEJTION: Will Mr. Hasluck present to the Dutch Goverrmient in<br />
his discussions any specific plans for the future of New<br />
Guinea?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Oh, now look, he's not going to Holland to present<br />
plans. Really why always force the cards in this way. He<br />
happens to be the Minister for Territories, Austr; lian-<br />
New Guinea, Papua. The Dutch happen to be the proprietors<br />
of Jest New Guinea so of course he'll call on the Dutch.<br />
Je hatve administrative contacts with them therefore he'll<br />
be very interested to talk to their people. Their man<br />
came out here and talked with us,<br />
QUESTION: His visit will be the equivalent, in fact, of the<br />
visit<br />
PRIME MINISTER: That's right; but we didn't discuss plans with<br />
their Minister , rho came out hero, nor will Hasluck have<br />
any proposals to put before them. There's always an assumption<br />
you know, about these internationsl thjngs ti:.;<br />
you go along with a plan and if it's got four paragraph_<br />
in it, it's a four-point plan. That's a good head. line<br />
you see. But you never go with a plan. You g o h-c'<br />
talk about things. You go to let the wind blow the ccversation<br />
around the room. You just take it as it goe:<br />
Something may emerge from it. You dont go in with a<br />
statement of claim.<br />
QUESTION: Can you give us any thoughts on the general Londo.-,<br />
Conference, Sir?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Oh, I think it's going to be very inter. sing because<br />
it's just, as you know, just before the Suit and<br />
I've no doubt Mr. MacmiJlan will look for lr. d to discussing<br />
with the other Prime Ministers the problems that ri..<br />
arise at the Summit; one of the major things of which,<br />
no doubt, will be the disarmament problem, which has run<br />
into some difficulties in Geneva and which I think, rays-N<br />
will probably need some direction from the Sur7mmit if it*:<br />
to be brought to finality, But I anticipate that he'll b,<br />
very frank about what he has in his own mind in discuss'-<br />
that problem with us. I suppose it will be too irmuchi to<br />
expect that he'll get eight or nine views all of which<br />
coincide. But he'll get some considerable bcnefit, no<br />
doubt, in having ideas thrown around at the table,' That<br />
Irather think is going to be the major object of the e: r<br />
cise. ' To may also have some talks about the future of<br />
Cyprus as to which there is still some uncertain,-Ly, T.<br />
will be a proposal from Ghana that, on becoming a Repub"' i-<br />
Ghana should remain in the Commonwealth, But we've no<br />
agenda. ie never do, Ihat happens, in fact rt a Pri-co<br />
Ministers' Conference is that, for example, a Foreign<br />
Secretary, whoever he may be, will, at a certain stage,<br />
give a conspectus of the foreign situation and c" urrent*<br />
problems, and then we discuss them exchanging ideas,<br />
getting further information where necessary. At anotchosession<br />
the Chancellor of the Exchequer will come along<br />
and he'll open , n economic session and discuss his own<br />
budgetary policy, the position of the Sterling area and<br />
what goes on in relation to conzertibility. Another, tie<br />
the President of the Board of Trade may be invited to cc-e<br />
and discuss the European common market,<br />
QUESTION: Do you think there'll be any serious discussion on<br />
that? The Chambers of Commerce are very concerned about<br />
the developments, </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER: I don't know how serious a discussion there'll be.<br />
But that there ,/ ill be some discussion is quite certain<br />
because we're interested and Canada is interested. ' Jhether<br />
those discussions will occur in the full meeting of<br />
Prime Ministers, or whether they will be talked out by two<br />
or three of us with the Board of Trade, for example, I<br />
don't know at this stage. iie don't have an Agenda paper.<br />
QUESTTIONDo you think it's on the broader racial question<br />
rather than South Africa-that there will be a possibility<br />
of that being discussed.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well, I don't know. I've ndt heard it proposed. The<br />
rule that has been applied in the past and by nobody more<br />
zealously than one or two of the Asian members of the<br />
Commonwealth is that we don't discuss matters at issue between<br />
two members of the Commonwealth. In other words we<br />
are not a board of adjudication. And that means for<br />
example this problem: these arguments that go on about<br />
South Africa. They will almost certainly not be discussed<br />
in the Conference but that there will be discussions in<br />
private in an informal way, I've no doubt. I, for example,<br />
would hope to have a talk wlith Dr. Verwoord before the Co;-<br />
-foernce begins. I'd like to add to my own knowledge of,<br />
not only the events, but the policies that lie behind ther<br />
That's quite inevitable and I'm looking for-ward to that,<br />
It will be very interesting. I gather that my colleague<br />
the Tunku Abdul Rahnan is going to raise this matter, biu'<br />
not, I think, in what I'll call full session of the Conference.<br />
Because that's ainst ourpractico, and, indeed,<br />
it's very undesirable because if you got to that point<br />
you can have somebody wanting to move a resolution or something<br />
of that kind.<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTI<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTE<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTE<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTE<br />
QUESTION: Is that rule always observed Mr. Menzies?<br />
R: Always, in my experience. And again in gy expericna<br />
and I am the oldest inhabitant, no motions are ever tabled<br />
and no votes are ever taken, though some of the suggestions<br />
I've read are a little bit revolutionary. No votes.<br />
As a matter of fact when re produce t'iat superb collection<br />
ofclichos known as the communique, at the end of the Conference,<br />
it is a collection of cliches only because every<br />
thing in it has to be agreed to by everybody at the table)<br />
Is it a fact, Sir, that each Session is put aside<br />
and re-arran ed at the next Session?<br />
R~ i'Jell if you said that, you'd have some prime facie<br />
evidence to support it. That's the position. You've been<br />
discussing some matter, it's very interesting, it's worth-.<br />
ihile referring to it and one Prime Min ster says I<br />
object to any reference being made to that subject" and<br />
that's out. ThataLy t'k sa bit. " biants mag-l<br />
Have you had any recent news of developments on<br />
South Africa Sir, Llart from what you said?<br />
R: I know that what I've said about this matter not<br />
being a matter of debate in the full Prime Ministers' Conference,<br />
coincides with Mr. Macmillan's view and I've no<br />
doubt that on examination it will be the generally accepted<br />
view. I know for example that Mr. Nehru will agree<br />
that this kind of problem is not a matter for full session,<br />
Can you tell us, Sir, what the Commonwealth is giving<br />
Princess Margaret as a Jodding Gift?<br />
R: No I can't.<br />
Reverting to that again, Sir, has our High Commissicn-</p>
<p>er in South Africa given a second report on this or in any<br />
way dealt with the circum-ntances of Sharpeville?<br />
PRIME MINISTE: Oh he's written one or tio quite lengthy letters on,<br />
this matter but I don't think there's anything very fresh<br />
in them. That's all I'll say about that.<br />
QUESTION: Do you think these discussions in London will ease<br />
the situatioh at all, Mr. Monzics?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: JWll, I don't know. I, for one, always hope so. At<br />
any rate any talks which, again I repeat, will be private<br />
and informal, must do good because they must produce explanations<br />
of policy, for example, which will be vcluable.<br />
You see there are two aspects in C matter of this kind,<br />
One is these terrible incidents which shock everybody. Yon<br />
may assume that these are the direct consequence of a<br />
policy or you may think that they are not, but that they<br />
are sort of inadvertent by-products of some policy. Well,<br />
we'll know more about that when we read the results of<br />
the judicial investigations that are in hand in South<br />
Africa. Idon't know whether my colleagues in London who<br />
desire to talk about this matte want to " out the<br />
incidents, or want to talk about the policy. I!' m myseY<br />
vastly interested to understand the policy while alway<br />
remembering that it's South Africa's policy, not min'e.<br />
is their business, not mine.<br />
QUESTION: Sir, if the South African Prime iiniste:. tokos<br />
viewpoint it might not be discussed at all?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I've no reason to suppose that he won't discuss it,<br />
with me, for exampleo I think he will. I'm sure that<br />
will be willing to discuss it with people, bu' net in the<br />
Conference Room with the threat that some people have<br />
hinted at, of emotion. I wouldn't expect that he woulV.<br />
that. But I've not the slightest doubt that matt<br />
will be freely discussed.<br />
QUESTION: Is there any fear that the colour question :-ay di-.<br />
vide the members at the Commonwealth Cofo---e.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Oh, I won't say anything about that, : T've got<br />
along pretty well so far. No reason . rwhy we shouldn't.<br />
There are just two crmments thatl'd like to make<br />
which are worth having in mind, I think. Those who tal. 7<br />
about expelling South Africa from the Commonwealth, if<br />
such a procedure is available, I think overlook the fact<br />
that there may be a great number of people in South Af: i<br />
including a considerable number of Africans, who want t?<br />
be in the British Commonwealth, who don't want to be tL:' o.<br />
out ofthe British Commonwealth.<br />
QUESTION: You mean the Dutch people?<br />
PRIME MINISTER No. I mean Africans the coloured people.; the<br />
Bantu. They call them Africans. ell, how does anybody<br />
here know? There might be millions of them who would not<br />
w. ant to be out of the Commonwealth, who feel that in a<br />
membership of the Comnonwealth they have sorn ' ection<br />
for their future, You don't know. I don't know. Unde<br />
those circumstances to say to South Africa: " You're ou<br />
the Commonwealth" may be to punish the wrong people, Now<br />
that's point No. 1.<br />
Point No 2. I'm glad to see that this nonsense<br />
about a trade boycott is beginning to fade out ofthe<br />
picture because never was anything sillier suggested.<br />
What's the object of a boycott? I suppose it is to punis.'<br />
the Government, the present Government of South Africa. o: </p>
<p>6.<br />
to affect its policies. Suppose if Australia imposed a<br />
boycott. It's worth remembering that perhaps the largest<br />
single item of import we have from South Africa is fish<br />
and thu great bulk of the people engaged in that industry<br />
in South Africa are coloured people. So in order to show<br />
our sympathy with them we put them out of a job. A boycot<br />
always was a blunt instrument, but if you apply it to the<br />
trade bet roon South Africa and Australia its stupidity and<br />
injustice become perfectly clear. Anyhow, I don't think<br />
anybody in Australia seriously suggests it.<br />
QUESTION: On a more local subject Sir, have you any hint of a<br />
kind of programme in mind on monopolies and other legislative<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No. I haven't. The Attorney is at work on that<br />
matter. As you know it's a complex . thing. ', ell he's<br />
bound to hold it until I get back because this is going tc<br />
require a great deal of examination. I would hope in the<br />
Budget Session.<br />
QJESTION: WJould a referendum be involved in this?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: A Referendum?<br />
QGETION: Mm. Like more Commonwealth power to deal with<br />
PRIME MINISTEIR: Oh, I Look we haven't yet czc, . c ony decision<br />
about this famous report on the amcndment of the Constit'c.<br />
tion.<br />
QUESTION: It would be an interesting paper if you took the<br />
whole lot of them wouldn't it, Sir?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes.<br />
QUELTi-ON: Do you have any particular monopolies or restrictive<br />
practices in mind<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Now, look, I'm saying no more about it.<br />
QUESTION: Sir, Sir Thomas Playford has suggested that it<br />
would be a fair thing if the Commonwealth and the State<br />
South Australia pay half each of the cost of his ooc.<br />
dam on the Murray. Have you any reaction to that?<br />
PRIME MINISTER. No comment.<br />
PRESS AN: It's quite surprising that he wants to pay half,<br />
isn't it? ( Laughter)<br />
fith the compliments of:<br />
Mr. Hugh Dash,<br />
Press Secretary to the Prime Minister. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
