<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8443</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP DOORSTOP ADELAIDE, MARCH 6 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/03/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008443.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
DOORSTOP ADELAIDE, MARCH 6 1992<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
J: Sir, if I may ask a question of a cricket nature, Ian<br />
Botham has come out today and said that your comments<br />
last week spurred him and England on to greater things.<br />
You have taken the wrap for the recession over the past<br />
months, will you now take it for the cricket?<br />
PM: Oh well, we, have got four games to go, I think, let's<br />
wait and see what happens.<br />
J: Well, Australians can stand perhaps a recession, but<br />
they really, can't stand losing the cricket.<br />
PM: Well in that case tell that to our crew.<br />
J: What about Mr Botham, what about his comments?<br />
PM: Well if it spurred him on to greater heights, it's good<br />
for spo: ct, good for cricket.<br />
J: Mr Keating, were you further annunciating your<br />
republicanism remarks within that speech?<br />
PM: Well I ' have never made republican remarks so-called, I<br />
was just talking about Australia's independence and its<br />
cultural identity, and the fact that Australians should<br />
be whole-hearted Australians, and not half-hearted<br />
Australians.<br />
J: Have they been that in the past, under the previous<br />
Prime Minister perhaps?<br />
PM: Certainly under conservative Prime Ministers, and I<br />
think that this is all part of Australia's continuing<br />
transition. </p>
<p>2<br />
J: But there is'a difference in your sort of<br />
Australianess, and Bob Hawke's sort of Australianess,<br />
isn't there?<br />
PM: Well I don't know, that is for you to make a judgement<br />
about. ' rhe ABC keeps a sharp eye on all these things,<br />
I know.<br />
J: Is Dr Hewson off the pace of the republican debate,<br />
Prime Minister?<br />
PM: Well, the republican debate is very hard to pin down<br />
isn't it, don't you think so?<br />
J: How long do you think it will be before it will happen?<br />
PM: I don't know, but I think we will probably see that<br />
happen in Australia, but I am not sure when.<br />
J: Will you be maintaining the pressure on the general<br />
debate Prime Minister?<br />
PM: Well I am not putting any pressure on the debate, I<br />
just sort of made a few simple points about Australia's<br />
independence from Europe, the fact that we are now a<br />
country trading our way in the Asia Pacific, and Dr<br />
Hewson had pains to point out. I didn't have enough<br />
respect. And I said well maybe not for you, but for<br />
Australia I have.<br />
J: Do you like the flag Prime Minister, or would you like<br />
to see it changed?<br />
PM: Well I do think it is a curiosity to have the Union<br />
Jack in the corner, I mean it is a bit of a corner.<br />
J: Should : Lt be in the middle?<br />
PM: Well the question is, should it be there at all?<br />
J: Do you -think we should take it off?<br />
PM: Well that's again another debate. It is no doubt, I ami<br />
sure, that plenty of people in our neighborhood wonder<br />
about us, whether we are as we describe ourselves as<br />
being, a nation, while there is so much ambiguity about<br />
our flag.<br />
J: How are we all together different? You are quoted in<br />
the Guardian this week as saying Australians are all<br />
together different. How are we all together different?<br />
PM: Well we are all together different in knowing, I think,<br />
what we feel about the place, and different certainly<br />
to Europe.<br />
J: But how, does an Australian be more Australian? What<br />
are you. saying about that? </p>
<p>PM: Well for a start, not tugging the forelock to the<br />
British establishment, that's a place for starters.<br />
The Liberal Party are yet to learn about this, well<br />
most of them. I<br />
J: What's the essence of being Australian today?<br />
PM: Being proud of the country, proud of our achievements,<br />
wanting to see it be independent and successful, and<br />
identifying with its independence and success, and not<br />
hankering for something else.<br />
J: What is going to be done about the Aboriginal questions<br />
you mentioned in your speech?<br />
PM: Well the Government is going to be attending to that in<br />
the Aboriginal Deaths and Custody recommendation to the<br />
Royal Commission, and which is one of the longest<br />
running Royal Commission, probably ever. It is a very<br />
serious set of recommendations which we are going to<br />
respond to seriously.<br />
J: Have you given some assurance to the, Premier of Western<br />
Australia, Carmel Lawrence, that you will be looking at<br />
perhaps modifying the fringe benefits tax in the<br />
Budget? L<br />
PM: No, I don't know why have you<br />
J: There has been a report today along those lines.<br />
PM: Well no I haven't.<br />
J: What's your reaction to certain businessmen asking for<br />
a lower dollar thinking that will fix their ills?<br />
PM: Well you know, the Australian Foreign Exchange Market<br />
is very deep, we turn over $ 40 billion a day, and if<br />
they wish to make plaintive pleas about the rate, they<br />
should make it loud and with feeling to the market, and<br />
maybe someone will listen and take notice.<br />
J: Mr Keating, what are your views on Bill Hayden being<br />
Australia's first President?<br />
PM: Well you should ask him that, I am not sure he has<br />
volunteered for that role yet.<br />
J: Mr keating, on a lighter note, Domingo is in town at<br />
the moment and he wants to catch up with you, will you<br />
have time?<br />
PM: Well I am around but the thing is, I have got things to<br />
do too.<br />
ENDS </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
