<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5592</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS TO THE REGIONAL DAILIES CONFERENCE (TOWNSVILLE)</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/05/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005592.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Jj, A A&gt; U$$&gt; RR
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA WEDNESDAY, MAY 20 1981<br />
ADDRESS TO THE REGIONAL DAILIES CONFERENCE<br />
( TOWNSVILLE)<br />
I am delighted to be with you this evening. It is reassuring<br />
to know that regional newspapers are flourishing, and encouraging<br />
that your member newspapers have increased their ovetall<br />
circulation by 22 per cent between 1970 and 1980.<br />
There is no substitute for the local paper in reporting the<br />
affairs of municipal and shire governments, or for<br />
repchring local events, which often affect people very directly<br />
indeed.<br />
_ As__ a_ farmer and Member for a country electorate, I have<br />
always appreciated the value of regional newspapers. The Hamilton<br />
Spectator has never been the last newspaper I select from the<br />
bundle which arrives at Nareen. Often enough, it is the first.<br />
Too often the trend these days is towards centralisation rather<br />
than diversification. It is easy to forget that nearly one<br />
third of the Australian people live in widely scattered and<br />
smaller communities, and the metropolitan dailies cannot<br />
respond to the legitimate needs of those outside our largest<br />
cities. Regional dailies are ideally placed to bring to their<br />
areas the latest national and international news, and at the<br />
same time, to promote local pride and community spirit. It is<br />
through the fostering of such an identity that a community's<br />
political institutions tend to-function more democratically.<br />
There can be no substitute for an informed and interested<br />
community. The Regional Dailies should be among the beneficiaries<br />
of the new stage of growth and development which Australia<br />
isnowentering. We are seeing a strengthening around Australia<br />
of a number of regions in response.. to Australian and world:<br />
demand for energy and resources. / 2 </p>
<p>2-<br />
Several major projects underway in various regions of Que'iisland<br />
provide outstanding examples: the open-cut mine at German Creek<br />
$ 400 million; the Collinsville/ Newlands coal project and<br />
associated rail and port facilities $ 460 million; the....<br />
Mount Isa lead, zinc and silver mine at Hilton i00 million;<br />
the Gladstone aluminium smelter $ 600 million; and the<br />
proposed refinery expansion $ 300 million. And the same<br />
story is being repeated throughout Australia.<br />
This development is the clear result of the efforts made<br />
since 1975 to restore health and vigour to private enterprise<br />
in Australia. We are now seeing the results of policies which<br />
have been guided by the philosophy that the most important thing<br />
that government can do is to create the conditions in which<br />
individuals and business can save, plan ahea." and be rewarded<br />
for their efforts.<br />
We have totally rejected the view that all wisdom resides in<br />
government. The future of Australia is, in our view, best<br />
secured when private enterprise has the resources to undertake<br />
commercially viable developments, and government must make<br />
room for this to happen.<br />
We have tried to make sure that the scarce finance which private<br />
en&amp; Jprise needs to expand is not directed into unproductive<br />
and non-commercial directions. This has involved the most<br />
rigorousrestraint on government spending, and a strategy<br />
designed to reduce the government bureaucracy and cut out<br />
unnecessary regulation. This approach is sometimes referred to<br />
as a ' smaller goternment' approach.<br />
In many ways, this term is apt. After the growth of the<br />
number of Commonwealth Government employees by 52,000 in<br />
the 1972-75 period, we have cut back the number of Commonwealth<br />
public servants under staff ceilings by 10,000 since 1975<br />
and as a result of the recommendations of the Committee of<br />
Review chaired by Sir Phillip Lynch, the number is expected<br />
to be further reduced by around 16,000 to 17,000 over the next<br />
two years.<br />
In relation to spending, again we have actually reduced the<br />
share of the nation's resources spent each year through the<br />
Commonwealth budget. Under the previous government, the Commonwealth<br />
budget increased its claims on Australian resources from<br />
23.8% to 30.1% We have cut this proportion back to 27.9%.<br />
Continued expenditure restraint, and economic growth will<br />
enable us to cut this back still further.<br />
We are also cutting back substantially on unnecessary<br />
regulation, and important decisions have been made heke in<br />
banking and finance, the airlines and through the abolition<br />
of the Prices Justification Tribunal. These decisions mean<br />
more streamlined government, a government better fitted to help<br />
Australia take advantage of the opportunities of the eighties<br />
and beyond. By becoming less intrusive and demanding, government<br />
is again playing a more constructive role in helping<br />
Australia. </p>
<p>3<br />
The benfits are already evident in higher economic growth,, more<br />
jobs, lower inflation, higher real incomes, and a consequent<br />
ability to do more to help those in our community who really<br />
need help. Cutting back on government spending also holds out<br />
the prospect of genuine tax relief. Expenditure restrrint and<br />
economic growth is, in fact, the only responsible way to<br />
reduce the tax burden.<br />
I want to dwell on this point, for the philosophy of this<br />
government has benefited the Australian taxpayer more than<br />
people say. We have made several major adjustments to tax<br />
thresholds through indexation. Apd the tax cut which will<br />
take effect from 1 July will put $ 500 million into taxpayers<br />
pockets. This decision represents only the latest of a large<br />
number of tax initiatives undertaken by the GQvernment. We<br />
have simplified the tax scale so that there -re now only three<br />
marginal steps instead of seven, and the marginal tax rate<br />
for the taxpayer on average weekly earnings has come down from<br />
44% in 1974/ 75 to 32% today. We have raised the threshold below<br />
which no tax is paid from $ 2,518 to $ 4,041 since 1975/ 76,-<br />
and half indexation next year will increase it further. We have<br />
doubled the rebate for spouses, and increased the sole parent<br />
rebate-nearly three-fold. -Gift and estate duties-have been<br />
abolished. Sales tax on motor vehicles has been reduced.<br />
Investment allowances have been introduced, and retention<br />
alto ances for private companies have been increased.<br />
In the three budgets under the previous government, the tax<br />
receipts of the Commonwealth Government grew by -ver<br />
per annum in real terms. We were resolved to stop this<br />
rate of g-rowth. Ad. thus far, in the five budgets since<br />
1975, we have cut it back to 3% per annum in real terms.<br />
Wecould have cut-it further-back had-it not been-for<br />
high priority we-have given to reducing the deficit to make<br />
room for private sector activity. Responsible deficits have to<br />
be funded and our aim has been to reduce year by year this<br />
burden of government borrowing on capital markets.<br />
We have done this for obvious reasons. Making room for private<br />
sector growth has been an absolutely central element in our<br />
plan to bring unemployment down by promoting economic growth.<br />
While bearing down on tax levels to the maximum extent that<br />
responsible public financing permitted, we have seen it as<br />
quite central that the growth and employment generated by<br />
private enterprise should once more be made possible.<br />
In our budgetting this year, the objective of making room for<br />
private sector growth will remain central. Indeed, it might be.<br />
seen as even more important this yeir because of the very success<br />
of our policies in stimulating private sector. growth. We want<br />
this growth to strengthen. This means increased vigilance to<br />
make sure that the claims of governments on financial resources<br />
through borrowing programmes are kept within reasonsable bounds. / 4 </p>
<p>This is a matter that the Treasurer and I will be discussing.<br />
with the Premiers in June. It bears particularly on the.<br />
infrastructure programmes the Commonwealth and the State t_<br />
have developed since 1978. The main projects to have received<br />
approval under the programme in its early years have ihcluded<br />
new electricity generation capacity necessary for the continued<br />
development of Australian industry, new efficiene port, facilities<br />
for loading coal for export markets, and other projects, supporting<br />
resource, development.<br />
On current estimates without allowing for inflation<br />
all projects currently approved under the programme would<br />
require over $ 4,000 million to be sought from the capital<br />
market before the end of the decade. In addition to approved<br />
projects there are also a number of new proposals. Some of these<br />
are substantial. They are mainly for accelerated increases in--<br />
electricity supply capacity, and would requir. an additional<br />
$ 4.6 billion borrowing under the: infrastructure programme.<br />
The Commonwealth supported the creation of this programme<br />
as making an important contribution to the revival<br />
of economic activity in Australia, and as making an important<br />
contribution to the promotion of resource development, particularly<br />
in decentralised areas.<br />
Indeed, the Commonwealth itself sought and received approval for<br />
: twanismall projects requiring borrowings of $ 132 million. But the<br />
pace of private enterprise has responded exceptionally strongly<br />
to government policies, and there is now a real danger that<br />
the demand for funds by governments for their projects may<br />
squeeze out private enterprise. There is no doubt that<br />
if all the States-. requests were met in full the implications for<br />
interest rates, capital markets, and private enterprise<br />
would be serious indeed.<br />
I am sure the States themselves are conscious that there must<br />
be an upper limit to public borrowings. The Commonwealth has<br />
asked the State Premiers to co-operate in examining these programmes<br />
to enable pressure to be taken off the capital market. We are<br />
all concerned with the possible consequences for housing<br />
and small business.<br />
I am confident that Australia is now embarking on a magnificent<br />
new stage of growth and development. And the regional dailies<br />
will be there to report it-with increasing circulations I have<br />
-no doubt.-And with increasing use of the latest technology.<br />
It is most appropriate that this forty-fifth annual conference<br />
is being held in Townsville for, speaking of the long association<br />
of the dailies with their regions, it would be difficult to find<br />
amore determined advocate than the. Townsville Daily Bulletin<br />
3n this its-centenary year the Bulletin is continuing-its policy<br />
of strong-minded independence and community concern which has<br />
characterised its association with North Queensland. Its resolute<br />
support for the development of the North has struck a respondent<br />
chord with all North Queenslanders and with many Australians.<br />
4 </p>
<p>p I believe the challenges facing the newspaper industry" iji<br />
the 1980s are immense. However, I am equally confident-,-<br />
that the Regional Dailies have both the capacity and willingness<br />
to respond to those challenges.<br />
I extend my best wishes for the future of the Regional' Dailies<br />
of Australia and for the Townsville Daily Bulletin in its<br />
centenary year. 0-</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
