<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>19249</transcript-id>
    <title>DisabilityCare Australia To Be Rolled Out In SA</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/04/2013</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Canberra</p>
<p>The Gillard Government and South Australian Government have reached a significant agreement today that will allow for the full roll out of DisabilityCare Australia, the National Disability Insurance Scheme, in South Australia by July 2018.</p>
<p>The agreement will provide around 33,000 South Australian residents with significant or profound disability choice and control over the care and support they receive.</p>
<p>DisabilityCare Australia will also give all South Australians the peace of mind that if they have or acquire a disability or have a child with disability that leaves them needing daily care and support, that they will get the support they need when they need it.</p>
<p>Under the agreement reached today:</p>
<p> * 	By 2018-19, the South Australian Government will provide $723 million to cover all people in South Australia. This contribution was determined using the benchmark set by New South Wales in the agreement reached with the Commonwealth in December 2012.  This will contribute to the cost of care and support for people with disability.</p>
<p> * 	By 2018-19, the Commonwealth Government will contribute around $760 million to the scheme for South Australians. This will be around 51 per cent of scheme costs. In addition, the Commonwealth will cover the full cost of people who turn 65 and choose to remain in the scheme.</p>
<p>Today's agreement builds on the agreement to launch in South Australia from July 2013 focusing on children aged birth to 5 years with significant and permanent disability.</p>
<p>By 2014 the age limit will be extended to 13 years and in the third year of launch all children up to 14 years.</p>
<p>We will progressively roll out DisabilityCare Australia in South Australia so that by July 2018, all eligible residents will be covered.</p>
<p>DisabilityCare Australia in South Australia will offer people with disability the care and support they need over their lifetimes.</p>
<p>DisabilityCare Australia will also end the cruel lottery that currently exists where the care and support they receive depends on where they live or how they acquired their disability.</p>
<p>The Gillard Government will continue to work closely with remaining state and territory governments to reach agreement on the national roll out of DisabilityCare Australia, so that all Australians can rest assured that if they have or acquire a disability they will have their needs met in a way that supports them to live with choice and dignity.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
