<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8685</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ KEATING MP DOORSTOP, ACOSS CONGRESS, CANBERRA, 1 OCTOBER 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/10/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008685.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL AF<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THlE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ KEATING MP<br />
DOORSTOP, ACOSS CONGRESS, CANBERRA, I OCTOBER 1992<br />
E OE PROOF COPY<br />
J: Prime Minister, what have you been advised of the implications of<br />
yesterday's High Court decision?<br />
PM: I want to talk about a fcw other things and that is the Reserve Bank, Mr<br />
Fraser said today in the contcxt of Dr Hewson saying that he would delete<br />
the object of full employment from the Reserve Banks charter. IHe says hell<br />
do this after it's been therc for nearly hai-fa century, when it's been part of<br />
the Australian consensus that price stability, that's low inflation or inflation<br />
control coupled with employment were the joint and dual objectives of the<br />
Central Banik and all conservative and Labor Governmcnts of the last half<br />
century. He wants to take it out, yet he has the hide to talk about<br />
unemployment and as the Governor of the Reserve Bank said so eloquently<br />
today, anyone who has opposed interest rate reductions and an expanded<br />
fiscal policy has no right to talk about unemployment. I say that applies to<br />
Dr Hewson and Mr Reith, both of whom have opposed interest rate.<br />
reductions, both who now oppose trenchantly an expansion of fiscal policy,<br />
yet they claim the right to talk about unemployment, yet they wish to<br />
remnove employment as an objective from the Reserve Banks policy.<br />
J: Prime Minister, is the Reserve sufficiently concerned about employment in<br />
the last couple of years, pushing up monetary policy? TE. LO: ct. 92 16: 08 No. 013 P. 01/ 04 </p>
<p>TEL 2<br />
PM: We had three times the rate of employment growth of the western<br />
economies throughout the ' 80s and that is just proof positive of the general<br />
balance in objectives, but again you can't go spending twice what you<br />
produce and that had to be reined in, but the general commitment to<br />
employment has been made so clearly by Mr Fraser speaking on behalf of<br />
the Bank Board now on a number of occasions.<br />
J: So what would be the implications of the..<br />
PM: The implications are that a Liberal Government would ask the Bank to push<br />
inflation below two per cent to zcro, by lifting interest rates and paying no<br />
regard for the employment consequences what so ever. In fact they would<br />
bc plcased probably, in their model to havc some unemployment around<br />
because this would simply reduce pressure on wages and inflation. Can I<br />
say the other thing is the question of the Catholic Social Welfare<br />
Commission, they went to sec Dr Hewson and Mr Reith yesterday, they<br />
were emptied out. They were told, barely politely that thcre would be no<br />
change to their policy and Dr Hewson would right over the heads of the<br />
Bishops to the Catholic community, not changing his policy, insisting that<br />
he should -tax food and saying that he knows best, what's goad for them,<br />
he'll tell them, Dr H-ewson will tell the whole Catholic community, the<br />
whole community of Australia what's good for them and we'll have Mr<br />
Reith doing a Goebel] like impersonation half making the argument that rich<br />
people have got bigger bellies, that rich people actually eat more and<br />
therefore it's goad for them that they tax food because it's fairer to the poor.<br />
This is the sort of callous rubbish you're getting from these ideologues, so<br />
when the Catholic Welfare Commission representing the Bishops of<br />
Australia stand up and say this is unfair and inequitable to Australians to tax<br />
food the ideologues push them to one side and say don't worry we'll right for<br />
the community over your heads and tell the community what's good for<br />
them. Dr Hewson knows what's good for everybody, a tax on everyone's<br />
food is good for them he says.<br />
J: Is the Reserve Bank charter much comfort to the unemployed at the<br />
moment?<br />
PM: It's been of enormous comfort to the unemployed right through the last forty<br />
or fifty years, most particularly in the last decade and we've now had<br />
thirteen one percentage point interest rate reductions, we've got bill rates<br />
around the six odd per cent mark in Australia, under six in fact, in Britain<br />
they're nearly twice that level. We've seen in Britain a celebration of a one<br />
percentage point reduction in interest ratcs, we've had thirteen one<br />
. Oct .92 16 : 08 No 011 3 P. 02/ 0. </p>
<p>TEL 3<br />
percentage point reductions from the Government and the Reserve Bank<br />
and this is because the Government and the Reserve is committed to the<br />
dual objectives of inflation control with growth in employment,<br />
employment remains, and has remained a key objective and that's why<br />
today, notwithstanding the unemployment wc have we've still got 26 per<br />
cent more people in work than we had in 1982, that is the labour market is<br />
now 7.6 million in size instead of 6 million as it was in 1982.<br />
J: Mr Keating, let's talk about ACOSS, they said to you today that your tax<br />
cuts should be reconsidered because of unemployment, are you just going to<br />
push them to one side?<br />
PM: Thcy've also said to mc a moment ago how regressive and unfair Dr<br />
Hewson's policy is, that the tax cuts are not funded, Dr Hcwson's tax cuts<br />
will only be funded by cuts iniGovernmcnt spending and that is what they<br />
are afraid of; taking 12-13 billion of unfunded money, of tax cuts out of<br />
the social welfare system as we now have today, out of the social welfare<br />
system.<br />
J: ( inaudible)<br />
PM: They believc that you can increase the real incidence of tax, they are a<br />
welfare organisation, they believe tax should rise to pay for more welfare. I<br />
don't believe the real incidence of tax should rise and the Government by it's<br />
tax cuts will not do that. But we're not putting a 15 per cent GST on<br />
people's food and clothing as Dr Hewson is that's the dirence. * We're<br />
reducing, maintaining the real incidence of tax, not letting it rise and I don't<br />
think it's fair that it should rise. Can I make another point about petrol.<br />
Yesterday we had Dr Hewson the bowscr boy, out there pumpinig petrol.<br />
What he didn't tell people is that their registration fees will double or treble,<br />
that they might save it on the tank, but they'll pay it on the front window<br />
when they slap the next rego sticker on there, where they pay twice as<br />
much. He did n't tell every truck driver who pulls up you notice there were<br />
not trucks there that there would be a $ 17,000 registration fee on trucks,<br />
so when he's at Mount Panarama watching the cars go round, the<br />
registration stickers will be flicking through his mind as the millions roll up,<br />
the billions roll up to pay for this squalid sleight of hand in reducing petrol<br />
prices. Again everything he does is basically about helping people who<br />
have got wealth.<br />
1: Mr Keating, do you welcome the High Court's decision yesterday that<br />
effectively guarantees the right.. TEL.: O ct. 92 16: 08 No. 013 P. 03/ 04 </p>
<p>TEL: 4<br />
PM: It is a decision they took and announced a couple of weeks ago and I haven't<br />
been through the fine print of the argument.<br />
Do you think this is going to make politicians fair targets of any sort of<br />
attack or criticism?<br />
PM: We've had free advertisements now since time immemorial. So what?<br />
J: Mr Kcating, you said recently that it's unlikely there will be an election this<br />
year<br />
PM: No more talking about that.<br />
ENDS 1.0ct. 92 16: 08 No. 013 P. 04/ 04 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
