<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>12</transcript-id>
    <title>DIGEST OF DECISIONS AND ANNOUNCEMENTS AND IMPORTANT SPEECHES BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE RIGHT HON. J. B. CHIFLEY - NO.133</title>
    <prime-minister>Chifley, Ben</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19450713 - 19491219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/12/1947</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000012_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
COMMONWEALTH GOVERNMENI<br />
DIGEST OF DECISIONS<br />
AND ANNOUNCEMENTS<br />
IMPORTANT SPEECHES<br />
THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
( THE RIGHT HON. J. B. CHIFLEY).<br />
No. 133.<br />
PERIOD 11THt DECEMBER. 1947, TO 4m FERRUARY, 1948.<br />
Wr Ailibhtht<br />
L F. loumm. Commowealth Gornmmt Printar. Cazbom<br />
( Priatd in Amtralia.)<br />
I -9 </p>
<p>ANTAROT ICA.<br />
EXPEDITION-PROGRESS.<br />
On 11th December, 1947, the Minister for External Affairs ( Dr.<br />
Evatt) announced that the Wyatt Earp, mother ship of the Australian<br />
National Antarctic Research Expedition, would leave on 13th December,<br />
1947, for a summer reconnaissance along the Australian sector of<br />
the Antarctic Continent.<br />
On 15th December, 1947, Dr. Evatt announced that the advance<br />
unit of the Australian National Antarctic Research Expedition reached<br />
Hleard Island on l1th December, 1947, and had established a food<br />
-depot. On 2nd January, 1948, Dr. Evatt announced that the Wyatt Easy<br />
had been recalled to Melbourne by the. naval authorities. The vessel<br />
had developed a leak in the hull which made it necessary for her to be<br />
overhauled in dry dock.<br />
On 25th January, 1948, Dr. Evatt said that he had conferred with<br />
the Leader of the Australian Antarctic, Expedition ( Group-Captain<br />
S. A. Campbell) who had reported to him the recommendations of the<br />
Planning Committee which had -met on 23rd January, 1948. He had<br />
approved variations in the programme of the expedition for the<br />
remainder of the summer as proposed by the committee. The committee<br />
had considered a report by the Department of the Navy regarding the<br />
condition of the Wyatt Earp which had been in dock undergoing repairs<br />
following her recall from Antarctic waters. Naval authorities were<br />
satisfied that the Wyatt Earp was fully capable of carrying out her<br />
duties. The Wyatt Earp would, subject to comprehensive trials being<br />
successfully completed, leave Melbourne about 6th February, 1948, to<br />
carry out reconnaissance in the eastern sector -of the Australian<br />
Antarctic territory. If practicable, the old magnetic station at Commonwealth<br />
Bay would he re-occupied, or magnetic observations would<br />
be taken in some other suitable region. On the return journey, the<br />
Wyatt Earjs would visit the IBalleny Islands and make a survey.<br />
The Naval landing craft LST3501 had received damage to her<br />
plates at Heard Island. She would go into dry dock and would leave<br />
for Macquarie Island during the last week in February to land a party<br />
, of fourteen scientists to stay there during winter.<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 126, page 5; No. 129, page 37.)<br />
AUSTRALIAN MILITARY FORCES.<br />
AWARDS FOR GALLANTRY.<br />
On 11th December, 1947, the Governor-General announced the award<br />
of the George Cross to Captain L. C. Matthews. </p>
<p>MILITARY BOARD-APiPOINTMENT.<br />
On 4th February, 1948, the Minister for the Army ( Mr. Chambers)<br />
announced the appointment of Major-General G. F. Wootten as a member<br />
of the Military Board, as an officer of the Citizen Military Forces.<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 108, page 17; No. 110, page 8.)<br />
FIGHTING FORCES.<br />
RECONSTRUCTION TRAINING SCHEME-FIGURES.<br />
On 11th December, 1947, the Minister for Labour ( Mr. Holloway)<br />
said that the present position of the Commonwealth Reconstruction<br />
Training Scheme for post-discharged ex-service personnel was-<br />
Total number accepted for training to 31st October, 1947-Full-timne training<br />
68,313, part-time and by correspondence 138,273, total 206,588.<br />
Total number commenced courses as at 31st October, 1947-Full-time training<br />
48,846, part-time training 125,227, total 174,073.<br />
Total number completed and at work at 31st October, 1947-33,205.<br />
The difference between the 174,073 and the 33,205 ( with the exclusion<br />
of those who changed their minds or left their State or country)<br />
were going through their courses.<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 127, g~ age 29; No. 128, page<br />
. PETROL SUPPLIES.<br />
RATIONING SYSTEM-REDUCTION, DECEMBER, 1947.<br />
On 11th D~ ecember, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
" It -is imperative that the cut of 10 per cent. in petrol, effective<br />
from 1st January, 1948, should be very real and reflect itself immiediately<br />
in the monthly consumption of -petrol through Australia. The<br />
Government realizes that there may be some very exceptional cases<br />
where special licenees will need to be grantcd to compensate for a portion<br />
of the cut. However, such licences will be granted only in the most<br />
exceptional circumstances and there will be no possibility of granting<br />
special licences to class 2 ( private motorists) and classes 3-7, including<br />
business cars and business-pleasure groups.<br />
The Government is doing its utmost under very difficult circumstances.<br />
Its objeetive is to spread the sacrifice over the whole community.<br />
The Government asks consumers to play their part and<br />
rigidly confine their purchases to the reduced licence gallonage under<br />
the new scale."<br />
On 12th December, 1947, Mr. Chifley said-<br />
A satisfactory arrangement has -been concluded with the oil industry<br />
for the checking of resellers' petrol coupons at the oil companies'<br />
main terminals and branch offices. This work will be carried out under<br />
the supervision of the Liquid Fuel Control Board inspectors. As a </p>
<p>result of this arrangement, the coupon system will be brought under<br />
complete control and coupons surrendered by resellers on receipt of<br />
deliveries into their tanks will be checked and verified within a few<br />
days after the date of each sale. Advices are being issued by the companies<br />
to the resellers of the new arrangements, which become effective<br />
immediately. It will be necessary for resellers to return their coupons in<br />
bundles of uniform quantity ( say 100 gallons) and each denomination<br />
will need to be kept separately. Liquid Fuel Boards are being instructed<br />
to take immediate action direct with resellers in the event of any inaccuracies<br />
being detected. The reselling of petrol will, like other<br />
rationing, be under an imprest system and any deficiencies will be<br />
deducted from the immediately following delivery into resellers' tanks<br />
OIL-SYNTHETIC PRODUCTION.<br />
On 12th January, 1948, Mr. Chifley said-<br />
In May, 1947, following consideration of the matter by the Minister<br />
for Supply ( Senator Ashley), the Minister for Post-war Reconstruction<br />
( Mr. Dedman) and myself, an inter-departmental committee<br />
was appointed to report to Cabinet on the general problems of fuel<br />
research in Australia.<br />
Cabinet to-day considered the committee's report which stated<br />
that, at this stage, it was unable to recommend any concrete proposals<br />
for the production of synthetic fuels. It considered it was impossible to<br />
decide what experiments should be undertaken. until extensive investigations<br />
had taken place both in Australia and overseas.<br />
Cabinet adopted the following recommendations-in regard to the<br />
administrative organization considered desirable to enable the formulation<br />
and development of future fuel policy-<br />
The Department of Supply to be given the initial administrati. e responsibility<br />
for the formulation, for the consideration of Cabinet, of Commonwealth<br />
policy in regard to fuel development; and the administration of such fuel<br />
development or production projects as the Commonwealth may control, either<br />
alone or in collaboration with other Commonwealth Departments or with one<br />
or more States.<br />
The responsible department to take such action as may be consid. red necessary<br />
to have the question of whether or not the production of synthetic fuels<br />
should be undertaken in Australia examined so that advice may be , ive. to<br />
Cabinet on the policy it should follow.<br />
It is proposed that the Department of Supply will work in close<br />
association with a section of the Council for Scientific and Industrial<br />
Research being established to engage in scientific research into fuel<br />
problems. A small mission, comprising two officers selected by arrangement<br />
with the Department of ' Supply and the Council for Scientific<br />
and Industrial Research, will be sent abroad in the near future to carry<br />
out investigations on the basis of which it will be possible to formulate<br />
sound recommendations as to future fuel policy." </p>
<p>BRITAIN.<br />
FINANCIAL POLICY-DOLLAR IMPORTS.<br />
On 14th December, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
" The Minister for External Affairs ( Dr. Evatt), the Minister for<br />
Supply (. Senator Ashley), the Minister for Health ( Senator McKenna),<br />
the Minister for Commerce ( Mr. Pollard), the Minister for Customs<br />
( Senator Courtice) and myself conferred to-night on the basis to be<br />
adopted for the issue of new import licences for dollar goods to he<br />
imported before 30th June, 1948.<br />
For the past two months there has been virtually a suspension of<br />
the issue of import licences for dollar goods. Following consideration of<br />
a report by the special inter-departmental committee, it has now been<br />
decided to resume the issue of licences. A maximum ceiling figure of<br />
very limited extent has been established for the value of new\ licences<br />
for goods to be imported from the dollar area before 30th June, 1948.<br />
This figure has been allocated over the various classes of goods and the<br />
Minister for Customs will issue licences only in accordance with the<br />
allocation. It must be emphasized that dollar licences to be issued for<br />
importation before 30th June, 1948, will be confined to goods of the very<br />
highest essentiality and the quantities of even these goods will necessarily<br />
be severely limited<br />
On 9th January, 1948, Mr. Chifley said-<br />
Much as the Australian Government regrets liavinz to impose<br />
restrictions on dollar imports, this action has been necessary if Australia<br />
is to assist Britain in its present economic difficulti: es. Any failure by<br />
Britain to meet the position that confronts it would have very disturbing<br />
economic results for Australia and the other Dominions. Therefore,<br />
in our own material interests-apart from sentiment and kinship<br />
-Australia must do everything she can to assist the Mother Country<br />
On 22nd January, 1948, the Minister for Customs ( Senator<br />
Courticc) said that licensing of goods originating in the dollar area for<br />
importation on or before 30th June, 1948, was being confined to indispensable<br />
goods to ensure that the limited amount of dollars allocated<br />
by the Government for new licences was not exceeded. Licensing of<br />
goods to be imported from dollar countries during 1948-49 would be<br />
oporated on a budget quota system related to imports during 1946-47.<br />
Each importer should, before 13th February, 1948, furnish to State<br />
Collectors of Customs statements, supported by a statutory declaration,<br />
showing-TIlportations of dol! ar area origin during the period of eighteen months<br />
Irultd 31st December, 1947, according to the individual specifications; and<br />
!' Piltienlars of the quantities and value outstandin as at Ist . lunaIry,<br />
19! k. on all valid licences issued for goods of dollar area origin including tho'e<br />
,,' olds in respect of which statements of importations are not required.<br />
Licences would not be issued to those importers who failed to furnish<br />
the required statements of imports and outstanding licences.<br />
fFor earlier reference please see Nos. 130, page 10; 131, page 24; 132, page 34. J </p>
<p>FINANCIAL POLICY-DOLLAR IMPORTS, PRIME<br />
MINISTER'S BROADCAST.<br />
On 26th January, 1948, Mr. Chifley broadcast over the National<br />
network. Mr. Chidley said-<br />
" Recently, as you know, the Government has imposed further<br />
restrictions on dollar imports and, in one way or another, these restrictions<br />
will affect most of you. You have, therefore, a right to be satisfied<br />
that they are unavoidable and that they serve a real purpose. My desire<br />
is to explain the position to you as simply as I possibly can.<br />
In Australia we require dollars to pay for American and Canadian<br />
good( s-uch as newsprint, cotton textiles, tobacco, motor chassis, and<br />
various kinds of machinery. There are also items such a freight, film<br />
royalties and a certain amount of interest on Australian Government<br />
loans in New York. We earn some of these dollars by selling to the<br />
United States and Canada commodities such as wool, rabbit-skins,<br />
canned fruits and so on. But in most years we do not earn as many<br />
dollars as we spend. For example, during the last trade year, 1946-47,<br />
we received round about 190,000,000 dollars and spent about<br />
290.000,000 dollars, so that there was a gap of about 100,000,000 dollars.<br />
Even before the war we earned less dollars than we spent. Then,<br />
however, Britain was able to provide us with sufficient dollars to make<br />
up the difference. Shel sold us these dollars for sterling-English<br />
pounds, that i. Therefore, so long as we could earn enough sterling,<br />
we were able to obtain the extra dollars we required. That position has<br />
greatly changed. Britain is not able to earn sufficient dollars to buy the<br />
things she wants herself. She has, therefore, to restrict the importation<br />
of goods from dollar sources and that imposes severe hardships on<br />
her people. It follows that Britain is not able to sell us all the dollars<br />
we require. . She is still selling us some of her dollars, but every additional<br />
demand we make on her means that she has to deny her people<br />
things that they need. It is true that Britain still has some reserves<br />
but they are being rapidly used up. After the war she borrowed about<br />
five billion dollars from the United States and Canada. But practically<br />
all that lhas now been spent.<br />
This situation has come about mainly in two ways. On the one<br />
hand, Britain needs goods from the United States and Canada to a far<br />
greater value than the goods she can sell there. Her industries need a<br />
great deal of re-equipping, after being damaged by bombs and worn<br />
generally during the war. Her export trade fell away by two-t ' rds<br />
largely because so much of her industry was diverted to war product on.<br />
She lost a great part of her shipping and sold most of her overs as<br />
investments to pay for war supplies. By great efforts and much se'fdenial<br />
on the part of her people, her exports have been increased, b,: t<br />
not far enough to pay for the goods she needs. Most of those exports<br />
go to countries which pay in currencies that cannot be changed into<br />
dollars. </p>
<p>On the other hand, many other countries look to Britain to provide<br />
them with dollars. All those countries devastated by the war need great<br />
quantities of plant and materials to re-build their industries. Some<br />
still more urgently need foodstuffs and the other necessaries of life,<br />
because their people are barely keeping ahead of starvation. These<br />
countries are all seeking supplies from the United States, but none of<br />
them has enough dollars to pay for the American goods they want nor<br />
enough goods of their own to export in return for American goods.<br />
For a time after the war the gap was partly bridged by loans from<br />
the United States and Canada and relief contributions such as Unrra.<br />
These resources could not have been more than a stop-gap and they have<br />
now come pretty well to an end.<br />
" A number of countries have balances of English money to their<br />
credit at London and nearly all countries acquire a certain amount of<br />
English money in the course of their trade. To get American supplies,<br />
these countries seek to change some of their sterling resources into<br />
dollars. Thus, over and above providing dollars for her own needs,<br />
Britain has to try to provide dollars for a large part of the trading<br />
work, including ourselves. Britain could meet this dollar deficiency<br />
only by borrowing or by drawing on her gold reserves. Actually she has<br />
done both.<br />
" As I have mentioned, the United States and Canada made loans<br />
to Britain totalling about five billion dollars. These loans were intended<br />
to fill the gap between dollar earnings and dollar expenditure until<br />
Britain could get on her feet.<br />
But whereas the United States loan of 3,750,000,000 dollars was<br />
expected to last two or three years, most of it was actually spent in<br />
about one year. During the same period, Britain was also drawing<br />
heavily against the Canadian loan. One reason for this rapid using-up<br />
of dollars was that American prices rose steeply, making the materials<br />
bought by Britain very much dearer. Another reason was the bad<br />
setback to British industry through the severe winter of 1946, which<br />
checked export production. Then, as the United States loan began to<br />
run out, a number of countries sought to convert large amounts of<br />
English money into dollars within a short period and this increased<br />
greatly the rate of drawings against what remained of the loans.<br />
Britain, therefore, has had to face the necessity of drawing on her gold<br />
reserves, which, by pre-war standards, are already very low. How low<br />
they are we have lately been told by the British Chancellor of the<br />
Exchequer ( Sir Stafford Cripps). He said in a statement to the House<br />
of Commons on the 19th December that, at the end of 1947, Britain's<br />
overseas reserves were expected to be about œ 500,000,000 sterling. He<br />
has since told us that the rate of drain on these resources is still proceeding<br />
at the rate of œ 11,000,000 sterling a week. Clearly this could<br />
not go on for too long. </p>
<p>" I needl only add that even the œ 500,000,000 mentioned by the<br />
Chancellor cannot be regarded as wholly available for spending because<br />
sonme part of it would havc to he held as a bedrock ro'serv-e against<br />
eincrg-enccs and to provide a mninimum wvorking fund for trade purposes.<br />
Clearly this very small mrargin of reserves must he very carefully<br />
husbanded. If the bedrock limit were reached, all the countries<br />
which now obtain dollars through Britain would have to live within<br />
their day-to-day earnings of dollars and this would cause acute difficulties<br />
for the individual countries-for ourselves perhaps as much as<br />
.1115oyn e.<br />
" As I have said, we have to call on Britain in most years for<br />
dollars to balance our accounts with the United States and Canada. The<br />
amount varies from year to year and depends largely on how much we<br />
sell to the United States and Canada. Wool is the main item at present.<br />
We , sold a lot of wool to America last year at high prices. This year<br />
weO will sell rather less, and although wool prices has risen, our total<br />
dollar earnings will be somewhat less than last year.<br />
If wool prices fall, our total dollar earnings might be a good deal<br />
less and wve would either has to ask the British Government for large<br />
amounts of dollars or else cut dollar imports very drastically indeed.<br />
" Since much that we buy from the United States is essential to the<br />
rining of our economny and to our future development we naturally<br />
do not wanit to cut dollar imports too far. And yet, as things stand, We<br />
cannot expect to draw more than a minimium * amount from the shrinking<br />
dollar reserves available to Britain. That, briefly, is the crux of<br />
our present position.<br />
" Britain has taken the main burden of the dollar shortage so far.<br />
They have cut their dollar imports very rigorously, even going' to the<br />
length of reducing their food rations still further. But the other<br />
sterling area countries-ourselves among them-must share this burden<br />
with them. This is not a mere matter of sentiment, but one of sheer, hard<br />
ncecessity. We simply could not afford to see Britain's dollar reserves run<br />
out. Therefore we must do onr very utmost in a practical way, on the<br />
one hand, to earn more dollars and, on the other hand, to save more<br />
dollars. Even with the cuts imposed, and even though we are selling'<br />
our current gold production abroad, we will not earn nearly as many<br />
dollars as we spend this year. There will still be an appreciable gap<br />
for which we must draw on Britain's dollar reserves. But we hope<br />
gradually to reduce that gap as the months go by.<br />
The action taken has inevitably caused a good deal of inconvenience<br />
and some dislocation to trade and industry. The Government<br />
regrets this but there was no way to avoid it. Even now it is estimated<br />
that dollar imports for 1947-48 will reach a total of œ A901000,000 a<br />
against œ A63,000,000 for 1946-47. </p>
<p>Since the basic problem behind the dollar shortage is that of<br />
reviving the war damaged economies of the world, we cannot expect any<br />
spectacular improvement within the near future. Those countries have<br />
made some progress since the war ended but it has been relatively slow.<br />
Their problems cannot be solved merely by outside help. The main<br />
effort must come from themselves.<br />
" Nevertheless, outside help is necessary and that is the reason for<br />
further United States help under what is known as the Marshall Plan.<br />
This is a proposal which aims to provide these crippled countries with<br />
the materials they require to step up their production, the idea being<br />
that if they can once get into their stride again they will be able to<br />
keep moving. If the plan is approved by Congress and is put into<br />
operation, Britain should benefit, both directly and indirectly. lcecovery<br />
in Europe would mean that supplies of goods which she now has to buy<br />
with dollars would become available to her from European countries.<br />
Sir Stafford Cripps has said that Britain could look forvward to<br />
some benefit of this kind in the latter half of 1948 if the AMarshall<br />
Plan had by then come into operation. But that is some way ahead<br />
yet and, in the meantime, the dollar problem! u for Britain, and for us too,<br />
is a pretty difficult job of making ends meet.<br />
" We can play our part in two main ways. One is to go carefully<br />
with all forms of dollar expenditure. This particularly is a matter in<br />
which business firms and individual citizens call do a good deal to help.<br />
The other is to produce and export all we can, not only of goods which<br />
can be sold for dollars but of goods which sterling area countries would<br />
otherwise have to buy for dollars. The Government is going very<br />
closely into the question of increasing exports along these lines and it<br />
may be possible to do a good deal, particularly if we have further good<br />
seasons. It is, of course, more satisfactory. to earn more dollars by<br />
increasing exports than to save them by reducing imlports-although<br />
as matters stand we must do our utmost at both. In expanding exports,<br />
however, we have to keep in mind the essential needs of our own plcoplC.<br />
Since world conditions underlying the dollar shortage will take.<br />
time to remedy, it would be wrong for me to hold out the prospect that<br />
import restrictions will soon be lifted or eased. We cannot ignore the<br />
possibility that some of these restrictions may have to be tightened<br />
further. That will not be done, however, unless it is absolutely<br />
inevitable. We have very great interests at stake in this matter because our<br />
overseas trade depends fundamentally on world economic conditions<br />
and above all on the strength and welfare of Britain which, these days,<br />
is hard-pressed to maintain the standards of living of her people. We<br />
all want to help her to win through. As a major exporting country we<br />
can do much by increasing the quantity of foodstuffs and other materials<br />
we send abroad. We can also help by economizing in the use of scarce<br />
dollar commodities. I put it to you that there is a job in this for every<br />
one in Australia </p>
<p>FINANCIAL POLICY-STERLING, DEVALUATION.<br />
On 24th January, 194S, Mr. Chifley said-<br />
If the International Monetary Fund agrees to devaluation of<br />
the French franc, the method of devaluation is important to Australia,<br />
as a problem cilhi arise regarding relationship of our currency with<br />
sterling. If the de\ valuation is carried out in certain ways, it could<br />
result in a weakening of sterling, and if that resulted in a depreciation<br />
of British currency, a problem affecting Australia could arise.<br />
There have been no consultations with the Australian Government<br />
as to devaluation of the irane, but there must be consultations with the<br />
International Monetary Fund if devaluation is more than 10 per cent.<br />
The move will have no effect on United States aid to Britain. It is a<br />
purely French problem.<br />
The real danger i~ the establishment of a double franc'-similar<br />
to the ' double ire in Italy-which means that some proceeds of<br />
FreniOi exports, would go to the French Treasury, while some would be<br />
free for exporters. This would result in a ' cross rate' of the franc<br />
against the dollar and the pound sterling. This could result in some<br />
weakening of sterling, and depreciation of sterling would set for us<br />
the problem of whether we would depreciate our currency in line with<br />
sterling. There can be no answe. r until these circumstances eventuate,<br />
bht that is the problem which might arise<br />
On 29th January, 1948, Mr. Chifley said-<br />
No consideration has been give. n to altering the Australian excli1ngp<br />
rate while sterling remains at its present value. Only in the<br />
event of a depreciation of sterling would the matter be considered.<br />
Tlhre have been no consultations with the British Treasury on the exchange<br />
rate.<br />
The Australian Government shares with the British Chancellor<br />
of the Exchequer ( Sir Stafford Cripps) his fears as to the dangers<br />
which may arise in regard to the French open market for gold and<br />
certain foreign currencies, unless strictly administered<br />
THE GOVERNMENT.<br />
ACTING MINISTERS.<br />
On 14th December, 1.947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
The Attorney-General and Minister for External Affairs ( Dr.<br />
Evatt) will be Acting Prime Minister; the Minister for Health ( Senator<br />
McKenna) will be Acting Treasurer; and the Minister for Air ( Mr.<br />
Drakeford) will be Acting Minister for Defence during my visit to<br />
New Zealand<br />
" r ir! C'li1tl e v \ w s ili:-nt in N' Zc( alhlind from 15th December, 1947, to 1st </p>
<p>MEAT.<br />
LONG-TERM CONTRACTS WITH BRITAIN-EXTENSION.<br />
On 15th December, 1947, the Minister for Commerce ( Mr. Pollard)<br />
announced that the Government had completed negotiations for an<br />
extension for two years of the long-term contract with the British<br />
Government for the purchase of Australian meat. The original contract<br />
was for four years ending 30th . September, 1948. Prices which<br />
operated during the period October, 1946, to September, 1947, would<br />
continue to operate for the October, 1947-September, 1948, period but<br />
provision has been made in the new agreement for pig meat prices to be<br />
subject to annual price review.<br />
JFor earlier reference please see Nos. 109, page 8; 116, page 32.]<br />
COMMONWEALTH BANK.<br />
POLICY-ADVANCES.<br />
On 18th December, 1947, the Acting Prime Minister ( Dr. Evatt)<br />
said-The instruction recently issued by the Commonwealth Bank to<br />
trading banks with regard to advance policy is similar to instructions<br />
issued by the Commonwealth Bank from time to time on the same subject<br />
since the early years of the war. During the past two and a half<br />
years the trading banks have increased from œ 200,000,000 to<br />
œ 320,000,000. The increase has been particularly rapid during 1947.<br />
Since December, 1946, trading bank advances have increased by<br />
œ 65,000,000. The Commonwealth Bank has facilitated this expansion<br />
by appropriate central bank action. The Government has endorsed<br />
the policy because it considered that the banks should be allowed to<br />
finance the re-conversion of industries from a war footing to peace-time<br />
production, to expand productive capacity for essential purposes and to<br />
assist the re-stocking of farm and station properties.<br />
" Recently a large amount of free money has been available in<br />
the open market for investment, largely because of the exceptional prices<br />
for export commodities and because of the influx of overseas capital.<br />
The existence of this free money was shown by the fact that the Fourth<br />
Security Loan was over-subscribed by œ 13,000,000. The Commonwealth<br />
Bank therefore considers that while funds are so readily available in the<br />
market for investment purposes, it is unnecessary and inadvisable that<br />
bank advances should continue to increase as rapidly as in recent months.<br />
In present circumstances, the Commonwealth Bank considers that<br />
capital expansion should be financed by new issues and not by bank<br />
overdrafts. Accordingly, in its revised instructions to the banks it has<br />
called for a somewhat stricter application of the principles which have<br />
formed the basis of its earlier instructions </p>
<p>WHEAT.<br />
SALE TO BRITAIN.<br />
On 18th December. 1947, the Minister for Commerce ( Mr. Pollard)'<br />
announced that the Government had completed negotiations with the<br />
British Governmuent in regard to the supply of wheat and flour from the<br />
1947-4S wheat crop. The Government had accepted the offer of the<br />
British Government for the purchase of 30,000,000 bushels of wheat<br />
at the overall price of A. 17s. a bushel, f. o. b. Australian ports. Thequantity<br />
represented shipments destined for British requirements and<br />
in addition the needs of colonial and other areas for whose wheat<br />
supplies Britain was responsible. The latter shipments would comprise'<br />
mostly flour. Because of the magnitude of the deal and the fact that<br />
the British Ministry of Food would provide shipping to lift all the<br />
wheat and flour over a period of thirteen months, the Government was<br />
justified in accepting the maximum offer which the British Government<br />
was prepared to make. The Government felt that a contract for sucha<br />
huge quantity should not be made on a quarterly price basis, particularly<br />
in view of market fluctuations which could occur over a period<br />
of twelve months.<br />
A clause in the contract provided for an additional allocation of<br />
5,000,000 bushels in the event that receivals by the board from the.<br />
1947-43 harvest reached 210,000,000 bushels of f. a. q. wheat. The price<br />
would be subject to review in the event of the participants to thecontract<br />
becoming parties to an international wheat agreement if and<br />
when made. Under those circumstances, the price of wheat remaining<br />
unshipped at the date the international wheat agreement came into force,<br />
would be adjusted to conform to the price operating under the international<br />
agreement. SALE TO INDIA.<br />
On 18th December, 1947, Mr. Pollard announced the conclusion of<br />
negotiations with representatives of the Indian Food Mission for the<br />
purchase of wheat on behalf of the Indian Government. The Government<br />
would sell to India from the 1947-48 wheat crop 25,000,000 bushels<br />
of wheat, including the flour equivalent of 2,500,000 bushels. The price<br />
would be on the basis of Ai8s. 6d. a bushel, f. o. b. Australian ports, with<br />
delivery spread over twelve months.<br />
A clause in the contract provided for an additional allocation of*<br />
5,000,000 bushels in the event that receivals by the board from the<br />
1947-43 harvest reached 210,000,000 bushels of f. a. q. wheat. The<br />
price would be subject to review in the event of the participants to the<br />
contract becoming parties to an international wheat agreement if and<br />
when made. Under those circumstances, the price of wheat remaining<br />
unshipped at the date the international wheat agreement came into.<br />
force would be adjusted to conform to the price operating under theinternational<br />
agreement. </p>
<p>INDIA.<br />
AUSTRALIAN SCIENTIFIC MISSION TO INDIA.<br />
On 21st December, 1947, the Acting Prime Minister ( Dr. Evatt)<br />
said-" A mission of Australian scientifists will shortly visit India. During<br />
the Empire Scientific Conference at London in 1946, many contacts<br />
were made between Indian and Australian scientists and, as a result,<br />
the Government of India has invited the Australian Government to send<br />
a goodwill mission to India to visit the main centres of University and<br />
Government research in that Dominion and to report on scientific<br />
development generally. Many problems encountered by Indian scientists<br />
are similar to those Australians have experienced, and it is believed<br />
that the exchange of views and closer contacts between Indians and<br />
Australians resulting from a visit should prove of mutual benefit to<br />
both countries.<br />
" The Professor of Electrical Engineering at Sydney University<br />
( Sir John Madsen) will lead the delegation, and other members will<br />
be the Professor of Physics at Adelaide University, the Director of the<br />
Waite Agricultural Research Institute ( Professor J. A. Prescott), and<br />
Mr. R. G. Thomas, of the Council for Scientific and Industrial Research<br />
Division of Industrial Chemistry. The Assistant Secretary of the<br />
Council for Scientific and Industrial Research ( Mr. G. Gresford) will<br />
act as secretary of the delegation<br />
MOVEMENTS OF SHIPS.<br />
. STEVEDORING COMMISSION-ACT PROCLAIMED.<br />
On 22nd December, 1947, the Attorney-General ( Dr. Evatt)<br />
announced that the Stevedoring Industry Act would commence on that<br />
day. [ For earlier reference, please see No. 124, page 36.]<br />
STEVEDORING COMMISSION-APPOINTMENTS.<br />
On 22nd December, 1947, Dr. Evatt announced that members of the<br />
Stevedoring Industry Commission would be-<br />
Mr. Justice Kirby, chairman, Mr. J. M. Hewitt, deputy-chairman, Messrs.<br />
G. G. Sutcliffe ( Department of Shipping), J. P. Williams ( overseas shipowners),<br />
A. J. Bampton ( Australian Shipowners), J. Healy and E. C. Roach ( Waterside<br />
Workers' Federation). INDUSTRIAL.<br />
ARBITRATION ACT-CONCILIATION COMMISSIONER.<br />
On 22nd December, 1947, the Attorney-General ( Dr. Evatt)<br />
announced that Mr. J. M. Hewitt had been appointed a Commonwealth<br />
Conciliation Commissioner.<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 129, page 6; No. 131, page </p>
<p>BASIC WAGE-FIXATION SYSTEM, PROPOSED<br />
COMMITTEE.<br />
On 9th January, 1948, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
The President ( Mr. P. J. Clarey, and the secretary<br />
A. E. Monk) of the Australasian Council of Trades Unions to-day<br />
discussed with me the matter of the establishment of a committee to<br />
inquire into the computation and adjustments affecting the basic wage.<br />
They intimated that they proposed to discuss the matter with their<br />
full executive next week.<br />
" I gave Messrs. Clarey and Monk an outline of the economic<br />
position generally and the question of increased production was<br />
discussed. Messrs. Clarey and Monk promised their fullest co-operation."<br />
PRIMARY INDUSTRIES.<br />
POULTRY FARMING-AUSTRALIAN EGG BOARD,<br />
APPOINTMENTS.<br />
On 30th December, 1947, the Minister for Agriculture ( Mr. Pollard)<br />
announced the appointment of the following persons as members of the<br />
Australian Egg Board for three years from 1st January, 1948-<br />
COMMONWEALThn GOVENMENT.-Mr. H. Souter.<br />
COMMERCIAL ExPr'unmc.-Messrs. R. C. Blake and A. A. Osborn.<br />
PRODUCERS.-Mlessrs. E. C. Mitford ( New South Wales) R. E. Huggins ( Victoria),<br />
R. E. Slaughter ( Queensland), C. R. Cowell ( South Australia), W. L.<br />
Hoops ( Western Australia) and T. M. Young ( Tasmania).<br />
( For earlier reference, please see No. 115, page 22.)<br />
EXPORTS TO BRITAIN-GIFTS.<br />
On 13th January, 1948, the Postmaster-General ( Senator Cameron)<br />
said that food parcels despatched by post to Britain in 1947 constituted<br />
a record. The total was 3,355,933 parcels and the weight 31,874.871<br />
lb. Previous figures were-Parcels. weight.<br />
1945 1,313,236 6,885,713<br />
1946 2,869,589 2&amp;, 309.305<br />
EXPORTS-NEW RECORD.<br />
On 28th January, 1948, Mr. Pollard said-<br />
" Australia's exports for the year ending 30th June, 1948, are<br />
expected to total œ 390,000,000, compared with œ 308,000,000 for 194647<br />
-an increase of 27 per cent. and an increase of 182 per cent. on the<br />
average figures for the five pre-war years ended 1938-39. Details are--<br />
WHEAT.-Estimated value of wheat and flour exports is œ 90,000,000, compared<br />
with œ 28,900,000 for 1946-47 and an average of œ 19,900,000 for the five<br />
p re-war years. Total volume of exports in terms of wheat may be less than<br />
10,000,000 bushels, compared with an average of 107,500,000 bushels in the five<br />
years ended 1938-39. The great increase in estimated value is due to the<br />
average export price being nearly five times pre-war level. </p>
<p>WooL.-Exports are expected to be worth œ 133,000,000, compared with<br />
œ 126,800,000 in 1946-47, in which year considerable shipments were made from<br />
stocks accumulated during the war. The estimated 35d. a lb. greasy basis<br />
compares with the 1946-47 return of 23d. a lb. and for the five pre-war years<br />
of 131d. a lb.<br />
BUTTER.-With a probable value of œ 16,700,000. shipments, which should<br />
reach a total of 70,000 tons, should be worth about 60 per cent. more than in<br />
either the previous period or the five pre-war years. when they were valued at<br />
about œ 10,400,000. If shipments did reach 70,000 tons in 1947-48 they would<br />
be about 26,000 less than the pre-war average but more than 10,000 tons above<br />
the 1946-47 total. An important factor in the decline in butter exports since<br />
pre-war is the diversion of more milk to whole milk consumption and production<br />
of processed milk.<br />
FROZEN MEATs.-Total exports are expected to increase from a verage of<br />
œ 9,100,000 in the five years ended 1938-39 and œ 10,500,000 in 1946-47 to<br />
œ 13,500,000 in the current period. Beef and veal shipments, estimated to total<br />
90,000 tons, will be nearly 10,000 tons more than in the previous period, but<br />
about 17 per cent. lower than before the war, when they averaged 106,000<br />
tons. Mutton and lamb. estimated at 70,000 tons, will he about 15 per cent.<br />
below the pre-war average of nearly 86.000 tons. The increased value of meat<br />
exports is due to an increase of about 90 per cent. in export prices.<br />
CHEESE.-Average shipments in the five pre-war years were 9,540 tons,<br />
worth œ 63 16s. a ton. For the current period, cheese exports are expected to<br />
reach 24,000 tons. at an estimated average price of œ 120 2s. a ton, the estimated<br />
total value for the season being nearly œ 2,900,000.<br />
EGGS.-For tile five pre-war years. shipments of eggs in shell averaged<br />
15,400,000 dozen valued at 13.52d. a dozen and eggs not in shell averaged 505,000<br />
lb. worth 7.9d. a lb. Estimated shipments to Britain for the current season are<br />
21,000,000 dozen eggs in shell at 2s. Id. a dozen, 20,000,000 lb. egg pulp at<br />
Is. 61d. a lb., and 2,000.000 11. egg pulp at 4s. lljd. a lb. New Zealand is<br />
expected to take 3,500.000 lb. egg pulp at ls. 7d. a lb. Total value of egg<br />
exports is estimated at almost œ 4,800.000.<br />
DRIED FRUITs.-Because of bad seasonal conditions, dried vine fruits' exports<br />
are expected to be below pre-war average in volume but higher in value.<br />
Current period's shipments are estimated at 45.000 tons worth œ 2,800,000, compared<br />
to pre-war average of 58,245 tons worth œ 2,200,000.<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 115, page 22.)<br />
WAR WITH JAPAN.<br />
BRITISH COMMONWEALTH OCCUPATION FORCEADMINISTRATION.<br />
On 31st December, 1947, the acting Minister for Defence ( Mr.<br />
Drakeford) said that the British Commonwealth Governments whose<br />
troops were taking part in the occupation in Japan recently reviewed<br />
the system for the control and administration of the British Commonwealth<br />
Occupation Force. They had decided to modify the organization<br />
for combined control by the governments concerned.<br />
It had been agreed, subject to the continued retention by the participating<br />
governments of sovereign control of their own policy and full<br />
consultation when their interests were affected, that responsibility for<br />
the control and administration of the force would be assigned to the Australian<br />
Government to be exercised through the Department of Defence<br />
in relation to joint-service matters and through the Departments of the<br />
Navy, the Army and Air in regard to matters within their respective<br />
spheres. </p>
<p>The new system would be introduced in January, 1948. The Joint<br />
Chiefs of Staff Committee in Australia, which had planned for and<br />
controlled the force on behalf of the British Commonwealth Governments,<br />
would be dissolved when the new system was introdn~ Ai.<br />
Service representatives of other participating British Commonwealth<br />
Governments would continue to be associated with the Australian<br />
machinery for consultation and advice in connexion with their respective<br />
countries' interests.<br />
BRITISH COMMONWEALTH OCCUPATION FORCECOMMANDER-<br />
IN-CHIEF.<br />
On 8th January, 1948, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
Approval has been given for the Commander-in-Chief of the<br />
British Commonwealth Occupation Force in Japan ( Lieutenant-<br />
General H. C. H. Robertson) to be absent from his command during<br />
January and February, 194S. Lieutenant-General Robertson will<br />
return to Australia for duty and leave and will visit New Zealand to<br />
discuss with the New Zealand Government matters affecting the disposition<br />
of its troops in Japan.<br />
" During Lieutenant-General Robertson's absence from Japan, the<br />
Air Officer Commanding the British Commonwealth Air Forces ( Air<br />
vice-Marshal C. A. Bouchier) will act as Commander-in-chief of the<br />
British Commonwealth Occupation Force."<br />
ROYAL AUSTRALIAN AIR FORCE.<br />
AWARDS FOR GALLANTRY.<br />
On 2nd January, 1948, the Governor-General announced the following<br />
awards:-<br />
Air Force Cross.-Flying Officers C. W. Stark, J. G. Cornish, D. R.<br />
Hebbard, A. J. Somerville, A. Starkey, G. Tuck.<br />
EXTERNAL COMMUNICATIONS.<br />
TELE-COMMUNICATIONS-COUNCIL.<br />
On 7th January, 1948, the Postmaster-General ( Senator Cameron)<br />
announced that the Deputy Director of Posts and Telegraphs ( Mr.<br />
F. R. Bradley), had been appointed Australian Representative on the<br />
Commonwealth Communications Council at London.<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 124, page 28.)<br />
TARIFF.<br />
EXPORTS PROHIBITED.<br />
On 8th January, 1948, the Minister for Customs ( Senator Courtice)<br />
announced that the export of maize and maize products, motor vehicles,<br />
partly or wholly assembled, and spare parts and accessories, and duplieating<br />
and blotting paper had been prohibited.<br />
730.-2 </p>
<p>PRICES.<br />
&amp; OODS " DECLARED "-BIRD SEED, REVOCATION.<br />
On 9th January, 1948, the Minister for Customs ( Senator Courtice)<br />
announced that ' bird seed had been removed from price control.<br />
AMERICA.<br />
VISIT OF ROYAL AUSTRALIAN NAVAL OFFICERS TO<br />
PEARL HARBOUR.<br />
On 9th January, 1948, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
Six Royal Australian Naval officers will fly to Pearl Harbour to<br />
join U. S. S. Valley Forge and take passage in her from Pear] Harbour<br />
to Sydney. The Valley Forge is the flagship of the American Task<br />
Force due to arrive in Sydney on 30th January, 1948. This is in continuation<br />
of the very close liaison wvhich existed between the Royal<br />
Australian Navy and the United States. Navy during World War II.<br />
" The officers, the senior of whom is Captain W. H. Harrington,<br />
will be able to observe the American Task Force during its operations<br />
at sea on passage. The kind invitation extended by the Commanderin-<br />
Chief of the United States Pacific Fleet will do much to further the<br />
close and cordial relations existing between the Royal Australian Navy<br />
and the United States Navy."<br />
COMMONWEALTH OFFICES.<br />
MELBOURNE.<br />
On 12th January, 1948, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
" Cabinet to-day authorized the Minister for the Interior ( M1r.<br />
Johnson) to proceed with the acquisition of land of an area of about<br />
94 acres, bounded by fSpring, Victoria, Latrobe, Exhibition and Lonsdale-<br />
streets, Melbourne, for Commonwealth office -purposes. The land<br />
is occupied by buildings, factories and residences, generally old and of<br />
poor class. Development of the site for Commonwealth purposes will<br />
be undertaken in stages. It is not intended to disturb owners or<br />
occupiers for some time as it is not likely that the first stage of the<br />
new office ' building will be commenced for about two years. Since June,<br />
1946, the ' Commonwealth has acquired properties, such as the Oddfellows<br />
Building, Reliance House, Chancery House and Henty House,<br />
and it is intended to dispose of these and concentrate activities in the<br />
new offices when erected." HEALTH.<br />
ACOUSTIC LABORATORY.<br />
On 12th January, 1948, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
In 1946, Cabinet approved of the Department of Health taking<br />
over the acoustic laboratory at Sydney from the National Health and<br />
Medical Research Council. At the request of the Department of </p>
<p>Repatriation, the activities of the laboratory have included the servicing<br />
and maintenance of hearing-aid equipment for ex-servicemen.<br />
Branch laboratories at Perth and Melbourne have been established.<br />
Cabinet decided to-day to establish the acoustir laboratory service<br />
to handle work for the Department of Repatriation at Sydney, Melbourne,<br />
Brisbane, Adelaide and Perth."<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 115, page 34.)<br />
MINING.<br />
MICA INDUSTRY.<br />
On 12th January, 1948, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
Cabinet decided to-day that Commonwealth control of the mica<br />
industry be continued for a further period of one year from 1st<br />
January, 1948. The matter will be further reviewed before the expiration<br />
of that period. Twenty portable air compressors will be obtained<br />
from the Commonwealth Government from stocks at present availa-<br />
ble in Australia for outright sale or hire purchase to mica-miners.<br />
Mica is a strategic mineral of first-class importance and development<br />
of the industry is essential in Australia both for national development<br />
and defence."<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 11, page 14; 118, page 25; 126, page 42.)<br />
URANIUM.<br />
On 12th January, 1948, Mr. Chifley said-<br />
Under the Atomic Energy ( Control of Minerals) Act, the Commonwealth<br />
Government took power in 1946 to control production and<br />
distribution of uranium, thorium, plutonium, or any of their respective<br />
compounds or other substances which may be used for the -production<br />
of atomic energy.<br />
Following discussions in 1947 with the State Departments of<br />
Mines, a programme of investigation of resources of radio-active<br />
minerals has been carried out in Australia. The more important<br />
localities of investigation are the beach sands of the east coast of Australia<br />
( thorium), the Mount Fainter and Radium Hill areas of South<br />
Australia ( uranium), and the Port Hedland area of Western Australia<br />
( uranium and thorium).<br />
Cabinet decided to-day that the following rewards be approved in<br />
connexion with the discovery of uranium ore.-<br />
A reward of œ 1,000 for the discovery of any new deposit of uranium ore<br />
which, in the opinion of the Minister, is of economic significance. A new deposit<br />
to be defined as a deposit more than 15 miles from any known occurrence.<br />
A reward of a further œ 2,000 for discoveries which, in the opinion of the<br />
Minister, are capable -of producing 25 tons of uranium oxide, and a pro rata<br />
payment for any additional quantities in excess of 25 tons of uranium oxide.<br />
730-3 </p>
<p>" 1The Minister will reserve the right to make payments of amounts<br />
to be determined by him to discoverers of new deposits which, although<br />
themselves not capable of yielding any substantial quantity of uraniumn<br />
oxide, may lead to the discovery of other deposits of importance."<br />
( rar earlier references, please see No. 112, page 48.)<br />
LEAD-CONTROL.<br />
On 12th January, 1948, Mr. Chifley said-<br />
The supply position of lead is very difficult in Britain and lead<br />
exported by Australia takes the place of that which would have to be<br />
procured by Britain from Canada and Mexico, involving the expenditure<br />
of dollars. The matter was dealt with by Cabinet in July, 1947y;<br />
but the Minister for ' Supply ( Senator Ashley) informed Cabinet to-day<br />
that there was evidence of dealers continuing to hold scrap lead.<br />
Cabinet decided that a further census of scrap lead be taken and<br />
dealers be required to, furnish details of their holdings at quarterly<br />
intervals thereafter. Export licences will be granted in respect of<br />
per cent. of declared holdings provided that holders furnish satisfactory<br />
evidence that the balance, including 50 per cent, of antimonial lead,<br />
has been sold for consumption in Australia. It is estimated that<br />
accumulated stocks of scrap lead in Australia amount to about 8,000<br />
tons, which could be turned to considerable advantage in the present<br />
dollar crisis." MIGRATION.<br />
GOVERNMENT POLICY-TRANSPORT BY AIR.<br />
On 12th January, 1948, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
Cabinet to-day approved of the Minister for Immigration ( Mr.<br />
Calwell) approaching the British Government to ascertain its views<br />
regarding the transport of British migrants to Australia by air. After<br />
full investigation the matter will be again submitted to Cabinet for<br />
final consideration SHIP BUILDING.<br />
PROGRAMME-FURTHER REVISION.<br />
On 12th January, 1948, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
Cabinet approved to-day of the construction of four additional<br />
class motor vessels to be propelled by the Doxford type diesel<br />
engine-making a total of twelve of this class of vessel ( six diesel and<br />
six steam) in the Australian shipbuilding programme. Cabinet also<br />
approved of the construction of four C class vessels, two of which<br />
will be propelled by double-compound reciprocating marine engines and<br />
two by N-E type marine engines </p>
<p>CIVIL DEFENCE.<br />
BOMBING-COMMITTEE APPOINTED.<br />
On 12th January, 1948, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
In October 1947, confidential documents were received by the<br />
Minister for Works ( Mr. Lemmon) from the British Ministry of Works<br />
giving an analysis of damage caused by bombs, including the flying<br />
bomb and rocket projectiles, and of the effect of atomic bombs.<br />
Cabinet decided to-day that a Cabinet sub-committee comprising<br />
the Minister for Defence ( Mr. Dedman), the Postmaster-General<br />
( Senator Cameron), the Minister for the Interior ( Mr. Johnson), the<br />
Minister for Works ( Mr. Lemmon) and. myself be appointed to arrange<br />
for a group of senior officers with specialized knowledge to be appointed<br />
from appropriate departments to advise the Cabinet sub-committee".<br />
ROYAL AUSTRALIAN NAVY.<br />
FIRST NAVAL MEMBER.<br />
On 12th January, 1948, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
" In August, 1944, War Cabinet decided that, on the completion of<br />
the term of appointment of Admiral -Sir Louis Hamilton as First Naval<br />
Member, an officer of the Royal Australia * n Navy should be appointed as<br />
First Naval Member and Chief of the Naval Staff.<br />
Cabinet decided to-day that Rear-Admiral J. A. Collins be<br />
appointed as First Naval Member and Chief of the Naval Staff. Rear-<br />
Admiral Collins has just completed an Imperial Defence College course<br />
in Britain ( ror earlier references, please see No. 99, page<br />
SOUTH-EAST ASIA.<br />
SCHOLARSHIPS.<br />
On 12th January, 1948, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
Cabinet decided to-night that provision be made for the establishment<br />
of three Australian scholarships for students from South-east<br />
Asian countries. The scholarships will be founded by the Commonwealth<br />
Government at Australian universities; the approximate annual<br />
cost being estimated at œ 5,000. It was considered that the provisions of<br />
opportunities in Australia for the students concerned would give further<br />
practical evidence of the goodwill of the Australian people towards the<br />
peoples of the countries concerned, such as India, Pakistan, Burma,<br />
Malaya, Ceylon, -Siam, Philippines and Indonesia. Arrangements for<br />
the selection of scholars and their welfare in Australia will be worked<br />
out by the Department of External Affairs and Post-war Reconstruction<br />
in co-operation with consular or diplomatic representatives </p>
<p>RECONSTRUCTION.<br />
BRETTON WOODS AGREEMENT-INTERNATIONAL<br />
MONETARY FUND AND BANK DIRECTOR.<br />
On 13th January, 1948, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
" Australia is eligible to participate in an election for the fourteenth<br />
Director of the International Monetary Fund and International Bank<br />
respectively. It is proposed to nominate the Secretary to the Treasury<br />
( Mr. S. G. McFarlane) for the executive directorship of both organizations.<br />
It is intended that the Commonwealth Statistician ( Dr. R.<br />
Wilson) will be the alternate director should Mr. McFarlane be elected.<br />
The tenure of office will be until September, 1948<br />
( Mr. McFarlane was later elected unopposed.)<br />
GOVERNMENT'S PLANS-SECONDARY INDUSTRY,<br />
DIVISION OF INDUSTRIAL DEVELOPMENT.<br />
On 21st January, 1948, Mr. Chifley said-<br />
" The Chairman of the Secondary Industries Commission ( Mr.<br />
J. K. Jensen) has discussed with me the position of manufacturing<br />
industries in Australia, having particular regard to their greatly<br />
increased importance relative to the Australian economy as a whole and<br />
to the fact that the condition of full employment now being experienced<br />
will tend to reduce the tempo at which sound expansion of manufacture<br />
can take place in the near future. We have also discussed the danger<br />
inherent in the present situation that some ventures may be started<br />
which are likely to be short-lived.<br />
The Australian manufacturing industry to-day gives employment<br />
to nearly 30 per cent. of the Australian labour force. Its growth,<br />
through the diversification of production, material assets and employment<br />
opportunities, has given added strength and resiliency to the<br />
whole economy.<br />
" In framing financial and general economic policy, governments<br />
and public authorities generally must ensure that the manufacturing<br />
industries continue to be given, within the limits of our resources, every<br />
opportunity to flourish and to develop, so that in turn they may continue<br />
to make their maximum contribution to the national policy of full<br />
employment. To this end, Mr. Jensen has represented to me that as<br />
much information as possible should be collated and made public regarding<br />
the structure and operation of manufacturing industry. Such<br />
information should be of use to management and entrepreneurs who<br />
are directly responsible for the operation of established ventures and<br />
the launching of new ones.<br />
The statistical information currently available aims only at giving<br />
a broad picture of the structure of industry. While it presents invaluable<br />
information, it is evident that additional data are desirable in<br />
, order to appreciate the position at any particular time of any one industry.<br />
For the guidance both of public authorities and of private interest, </p>
<p>therefore, we must aimu where possible to improve the information-which<br />
can be made available, whether it be from current statistics or from the<br />
results of special surveys. Sometimes such additional information is<br />
of a kind that cannot be reduced to statistical presentation. The sort<br />
of information which I have in mind includes particulars about existing<br />
and projected productive capacity; the demand for products; the age<br />
and relative efficiency of machinery and plants.<br />
As a result of the willing co-operation of industrialists with which<br />
it has been associated, the Division of Industrial Development has<br />
accumulated much information about manufacturing in Australia.<br />
I have arranged that this division, drawing on its own resources and<br />
the resources of other government departments associated in this field,<br />
should prepare for public information periodical reviews, bringing<br />
together all the relevant information that can be obtained about as<br />
many manufacturing industries as possible.<br />
In preparing these reviews no attempt will be made by the division<br />
to ask manufacturers to give any additional information regarding<br />
their operations unless the manufacturers themselves find it expedient<br />
to do so FIFTH SECURITY LOAN.<br />
TERMS ANNOUNCED.<br />
On 13th January, 1948, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
The long-term interest rate on bonds and inscribed stock issued for<br />
the next loan to be raised by the Commonwealth Government will be<br />
maintained at œ 3 2s. 6d. per cent. The same rate applied to the<br />
successful Third and Fourth Security Loans floated in 1947. The<br />
securities to be issued will be for a period of approximately twelve<br />
years. Once again there will be no short-term securities."<br />
On 4th February, 1948, Mr. Chifley said-<br />
The next Commonwealth cash loan will open on 14th April, 194S.<br />
The amount to be sought for repatriation, rehabilitation and public<br />
works of the Commonwealth and States will be œ 35,000,000. The loan<br />
will be raised under the title of Fifth Security Loan.<br />
The loan campaign will close on 5th May, 1948, but the Treasurer<br />
reserves the right to close the loan at any earlier time if he should<br />
consider that course desirable."<br />
WHEAT STABILIZATION PLAN SCHEME.<br />
POST-WAR-CONTINUANCE, MI-NISTER'S<br />
ANNOUNCEMENT.<br />
On 15th January, 1948, the Minister for Commerce and Agriculture<br />
( Mr. Pollard) announced that from 19th January, 1948, and to<br />
the conclusion of the marketing of the 1951-52 wheat crop a price of<br />
6s. 3d. a bushel bulk f. o. r. ports would apply for all wheat sold by the </p>
<p>Australian Wheat Board for human consumption and stock feed within<br />
Australia. The Commonwealth Government would guarantee a price of<br />
6s. 3d. a bushel bulk f. o. r. ports for all wheat sold by the Australian<br />
Wheat Board for consumption within Australia and for all wheat<br />
exported. The guaranteed price would be dependent on the States<br />
passing legislation identical with that required as complementary to<br />
the Wheat Stabilization Act of 1946 except in respect to the essential<br />
price alteration necessary to that Act to guarantee 6s. 3d. a bushel bulk<br />
f. o. r. ports. State complementary legislation would have to operate for<br />
the 1948-49 crop.<br />
In the event of the Cost of Inquiry Committee recommending an<br />
index accepted as practicable by the Commonwealth Government, consideration<br />
would be given to varying the price up or down according to<br />
the index variation.<br />
The operation of the plan would continue with the following alterations-<br />
the contribution of 50 per cent. would start under the new plan<br />
at 6s. 3d. a bushel bulk instead of 5s. 3d. a bushel bagged. The ceiling<br />
at which contributions stopped would be 10s. 7d. a bushel bulk instead<br />
of 9s. 6d. a bushel bagged.<br />
Stabilization contributions already collected on the 1945-46 crop<br />
would be distributed to growers not later than December, 1948, in proportion<br />
to their deliveries to the board -but no further distributious<br />
from the fund would be made except as Cabinet approved in the light of<br />
the position at the time. After disbursal of the 1945-46 contributions,<br />
œ 20,000,000 would be regarded as a reasonable minimum for the fund.<br />
The scheme would be reviewed -before the end of the 1951-52 season.<br />
The decisions followed the presentation on 18th December, 1947, of<br />
an interim report by the Cost of Inquiry Committee. The committee<br />
found a cost figure of 6s. a bushel at sidings. Conversion of that price<br />
to a bulk f. o. r. basis indicated a price of 6s. 8d. a bushel. Having<br />
regard to the long-range security provided and the profitable return to<br />
a reasonably efficient producer, the Government adopted 6s. 3d. a bushcl<br />
bulk f. o. r. ports as a fair proposition to all concerned including consumers<br />
and stock feeders. The price represented an increase of about<br />
is. 4d. a ' bushel bulk f. o. r. ports for home consumption purposes and<br />
Is. 3d. a bushel in the overall guaranteed price. With a refund to<br />
growers of about is. 1.5d. the 1945-46 fund contribution for that year's<br />
crop would return them 7s. 4.5d. a bushel bulk ( less freight). It was estimated<br />
that final returns for the 1946-47 crop would amount to 7s. 9d.<br />
a bushel bulk ( less freight).<br />
The crop now being harvested would give a price return substan-.<br />
tially in excess of the 1945-46 and 1946-47 crops. The plan in its<br />
revised form, if accepted by the States and growers, would give effective<br />
security for four crops after the one now being harvested. In the<br />
absence of Commonwealth marketing powers, complementary legislation<br />
by the States was essential.<br />
( ror earlier references please see Nas. 116, page 30; 123, page 28; 128, page </p>
<p>DEPARTMENT OF INFORMATION.<br />
DIRECT OR-GENERAL.<br />
On 15th January, 1948, the Minister for Information ( Mr.<br />
, Calwell) announced that the Director-General of Information ( Mr.<br />
E. G. Bonney) had resigned and would take over the Directorship of<br />
the Australian News and Information Bureau at New York. The<br />
Chief Publicity Officer of the Department ( Mr. K. Murphy) would be<br />
Acting Director-General of Information.<br />
CONVERSION LOAN.<br />
LONDON OPERATION, JANUARY, 1948.<br />
On 22nd January, 1948, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
" A conversion loan is being floated at London to convert a New<br />
South Wales loan of œ 17,870,000, bearing interest at 51 per cent. per<br />
annum, over which an option of conversion is held by the Government.<br />
The terms of the new loan are: Issue price 984, interest rate 3<br />
per cent, per annum, maturity date 1st May, 1965, with the option to the<br />
Government of prior redemption on or after 1st May, 1963.<br />
Conversion offer will be made to all existing holders of the old<br />
loan but issue of new stock will be limited to œ 12,870,000, as œ 5,000,000<br />
of old stock is being redeemed. The new loan will result in a substantial<br />
saving of interest to the New South Wales Government."<br />
BURMA.<br />
BURMESE DELEGATION.<br />
On 27th January, 1948, the Minister for External Affairs ( Dr.<br />
Evatt) said that a delegation of Burmese Government officials would<br />
arrive in Australia on 28th January, 1948. The delegation comprised<br />
the Chairman of the Burmese Public Service Commission ( Thakin Lun<br />
Baw), Boh Toon Lin and Lee Boon Thi. They would have consultations<br />
with the Commonwealth Public Service Board on public service<br />
organization and administration. NATIONAL GALLERY.<br />
On 4th February, 1948, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
" Mr. G. W. Booth, of Melbourne, has presented to the Commonwealth<br />
Government, for inclusion in the National Collection of Art<br />
Treasuires, a very fine painting by the late Tom Roberts."<br />
FOURTH SECURITY LOAN.<br />
OVER-SUBSCRIPTION.<br />
Cash subscriptions to the Fourth Security Loan of œ 48,000,000<br />
totalled œ 61,155,000 and œ 17,392,000 of the œ 32,000,000 conversion<br />
loan were converted.<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 130, page 37.)<br />
By Authority: L. F. JOH1NSTON. Comimon~ wealth Governm~ ent Printer, Canbenra. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
