<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6609</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER ST JEROME&#039;S SCHOOL - SYDNEY - 10 MARCH 1985</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/03/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006609.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGOED AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
AT 3.3OPM SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
ST JEROME'S SCHOOL SYDNEY 10 MARCH 1985<br />
Distinguished Guests, Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
It gives me much pleasure to be here today to open these<br />
major extensions and renovations at St Jerome's Primary<br />
School. As your local Member, John Mountford, has told me, today<br />
marks an important stage in the history of the school<br />
for its students, its dedicated staff, and the parent~ s<br />
and community it has served over the last 53 years.<br />
The opening today recogniises the place St Jerome's has<br />
won for itself in Punchbowl. It reflects your<br />
community's concern for the kind of schooling seen as<br />
vital to prepare your children for a changing world, and<br />
the energy and enthusiasm put into that vision.<br />
St Jerome's School embodies that vision. You have every<br />
reason to be proud of your students and the contribution<br />
they have made to national and local life.<br />
One of them is John Mountford who has represented Banks<br />
in the Federal Parliament since 1980, following his<br />
earlier distinguished service as an Alderman and Mayor<br />
of Canterbury. Another link was Eris O'Brien who was<br />
associated with the school's estalishment in 1952, and<br />
went on to become Archbishop of Canberra and Goulburn.<br />
As I look around the school today, I can see what an<br />
excellent job of construction and renovation has bee-I<br />
done on the school premises. Clearly, you are trying,<br />
successfully, to provide the kind of environment and<br />
facilities needed for both students and staff to achieve<br />
their best results.<br />
Construction is for the future, and the future requires<br />
confidence, not least confidence in the future place of<br />
a school such as St Jerome' s in the development of<br />
Australia's education system.<br />
As you know, over recent years there has been a great<br />
deal of debate over the future of that system, and in<br />
particular the future of Commonwealth assistance for<br />
non-government schools. Much of that debate stemmed<br />
from parent's concern over the way their children should<br />
be educated and the kind of values they wish to see </p>
<p>associated with that education. The policy my.<br />
Government announced last year recognised these<br />
concerns. It acknowledges the existence of a dual education system<br />
in Australia. It recognises too that education is a<br />
partnership between the school community and the State<br />
and Commonwealth Governments.<br />
On the Commonwealth side, that policy is intended to<br />
ensure, among other things, that Australia has a<br />
national education system which can cater for the<br />
diversity of our society diversity of abilities,<br />
aspirations and needs. Non-government schools have a<br />
secure place in that system.<br />
Our policy is intended too, to ensure that assistance<br />
should be on the basis of need. You will agree I am<br />
( 1 sure that in the interests both of equity, and of making<br />
the best use of the education dollar, that the neediest<br />
schools should receive the greatest assistance.<br />
The new funding basis which is taking effect in 1985<br />
will have the effect of reducing over time the resource<br />
gaps between different schools. Schools that are<br />
relatively disadvantged will receive very considerable<br />
increases in resources over the next 8 years, based on a<br />
new assessment of needs and tied to a common measure of<br />
resources across both government and non-government<br />
schools. For non-government schools that are in level<br />
12, the neediest category, these increases in per pupil<br />
grants will range up to 45 per cent by 1992, over and<br />
above the rate of inflation.<br />
We have managed to set this policy in place despite the<br />
very stringent overall budgeting constraints on the<br />
Commonwealth Government.<br />
C St Jerome's will benefit very materially from this<br />
policy. In 1984 Commonwealth grants to the school to assist with<br />
operating costs were close to $ 394,000. In 1985, I<br />
understand St Jerome's will be classified as a Category<br />
under the new scheme. By 1992, the school's<br />
grants will have increased by 41 per cent over and above<br />
increases necessary to account for inflation.<br />
The Commonwealth also recognises that some schools have<br />
very special needs to meet. I understand, for example,<br />
that here at St Jerome's Primary School you have<br />
students from some 13 different countries. This variety<br />
makes for a lively mix of different cultures and<br />
viewpoints, and offers the opportunity to enrich the<br />
education of all children at St Jerome's. It also<br />
presents a challenge to teachers, in ensuring that all<br />
students can receive the grounding in common experiences<br />
and learning skills necessary for them to succeed as<br />
Australians later in life. </p>
<p>3..<br />
The buildings being opened today are the result of a<br />
major co-operative effort. They will provide much<br />
needed new and upgraded facilties, including extra<br />
classrooms, a canteen, and ESL and kindergarten areas.<br />
I am pleased to note that the Commonwealth has been able<br />
to contribute over $ 450,000 towards the overall cost.<br />
The contribution made by the school itself, by parents<br />
and friends to the project, emphasises your own<br />
commitment to the future of St Jerome's and to the<br />
quality of education it provides.<br />
My concern with education, and that of the Federal<br />
Government, goes beyond the question of financial<br />
resources, to the quality and relevance of the education<br />
being offered in our schools. This emphasis is central<br />
to the investigation being carried out by the<br />
Commonwealth's Quality of Education Review Committee, a<br />
group of eminent educationalists chaired by Professor<br />
Karmel. This Committee's task is to develop strategies<br />
designed to ensure that extra funds taxpayers funds<br />
being invested in schools are used more effectively, to<br />
produce better educational standards among our students<br />
both primary and secondary.<br />
One Area the Committee has been looking at is how to<br />
ensure that the increasing number of students staying on<br />
to upper secondary level have the kind of skills needed<br />
for them to take up employment or higher education<br />
opportunities in the modern Australian economy.<br />
We place the highest priority on tackling these<br />
problems, especially in this year, International Youth<br />
Year. All this begins here, at primary school. Primary<br />
schools have an essential part to play in ensuring that<br />
all their students leave Year 6 with acceptable levels<br />
of basic skills, in literacy, numeracy, and<br />
communications. Satisfactory levels of attainment in<br />
these skills are vital they provide the foundations<br />
for all further study.<br />
The Catholic.-Church's appreciation of these realities,<br />
is-well known. I have welcomed the Catholic<br />
authorities' co-operation with the Government and their<br />
contribution to the development of a fair and effective<br />
education policy. I look forward to continuing<br />
constultations with your Church leaders on the issues<br />
involved. It gives me now great pleasure to declare these new<br />
facilities open. I wish all those associated with St<br />
Jerome's well for the future. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
