<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>22336</transcript-id>
    <title>Lockhart Review  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/06/2006</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Australian Government has considered the recommendations of the Lockhart Review. This is a difficult and complex issue on which many different views are held.</p>
<p>After careful reflection, the Government is not disposed to make any changes to the existing national legislative framework for research involving human embryos, agreed in 2002.</p>
<p>  Recognising, however, the range of issues and views, there will be a detailed discussion on this issue within the Government parties when Parliament resumes for the Spring sitting.</p>
<p>Maintenance of the current position would still allow the continued use of excess embryos, created originally for Assisted Reproductive Technology (ART) purposes, under licence for research.</p>
<p>  In forming its views, the Government considered the current state of science and was of the opinion that these arrangements continue to strike the right balance between ethics and morality, and scientific opportunity at this point in time.</p>
<p>The Lockhart Review also recommended some administrative improvements that will help reduce red tape in the licensing process and provide further support to the regulatory scheme by enhancing the National Health and Medical Research Council guidelines.  Taking into account experience since the enactment of the legislation in 2002, the Government is supportive of these recommendations.</p>
<p> The Government also supports further exploring the establishment of a national register of donated excess embryos created originally for ART purposes and a national stem cell bank.</p>
<p>  This infrastructure would offer a way of assisting research by making donated excess embryos and stem cell lines more widely available to the research community.</p>
<p>I intend writing to state and territory leaders explaining the government's position. I would be happy to discuss this at the next COAG meeting.  </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
