<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>24151</transcript-id>
    <title>The Honourable Tom Uren AC</title>
    <prime-minister>Abbott, Tony</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130918 - 20150915</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/01/2015</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Australia mourns the passing of The Honourable Tom Uren AC.</p>
<p>He was a prisoner of war, a parliamentarian, a minister, a deputy leader of his party and served our country throughout his adult life.</p>
<p>He was an aspiring boxer and outstanding athlete who joined the army at the age of 20 and deployed to Timor.</p>
<p>He spent his 21st birthday – and the following three – as a prisoner of war.</p>
<p>He suffered the brutality of the Burma-Thai Railway and he witnessed from afar the atomic bomb on Nagasaki.</p>
<p>Despite these experiences, he rejected hatred.</p>
<p>Tom Uren devoted his life to serving what he called ‘the human family’.</p>
<p>He taught a generation of Australians to forgive and to forge new friendships with our former enemy.</p>
<p>In 1958, he entered the Federal Parliament as the Member for Reid and represented the electorate for 31 years.</p>
<p>He became Minister for Urban and Regional Development in the Whitlam Government, and pioneered the protection of Australia’s historic and natural heritage.</p>
<p>He also served as a minister in the first two Hawke Governments.</p>
<p>When Mr Uren retired from Parliament in 1990, he was the Father of the House.</p>
<p>He remained an active conservationist after leaving parliament and was a strong supporter of the Sydney Harbour Federation Trust established by the Howard Government.</p>
<p>I have instructed that flags fly at half-mast on the day of Mr Uren’s State Memorial Service.</p>
<p>On behalf of all Australians, I extend to Mr Uren’s widow, Christine, and to his family the condolences of the Government and the Australian people.</p>
<p>26 January 2015</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
