<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4605</transcript-id>
    <title>EMERGENCY ACCOMMODATION FOR VICTIMS OF THE BLUE MOUNTAINS FIRES, 16 JANUARY 1978</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/01/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004605.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
F 78/ 1<br />
PRIME MRAINISTE<br />
FOR PRESS 16 JANUARY 1978<br />
EMERGENCY ACCOMMODATION FOR VICTIMS OF BLUE MOUNTAINS FIRES<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr. Malcolm Fraser, announced today that<br />
caravans which had been used as emergency housing in Darwin<br />
after Cyclone Tracy are to be made available to residents of<br />
the Blue Mountains.<br />
Many residents wish to re-establish themselves on their land<br />
while their houses are rebuilt. The vans will provide emergency<br />
housing during this period.<br />
Agreement to provide the vans follows a request from the State<br />
after-an appeal for-the loan-of caravans by the Mayor of the<br />
Blue Mountains City Council, Alderman Leslie.<br />
Arrangements have been made for the caravans to be freighted<br />
from Darwin to the Blue Mountains City Council. The caravans<br />
are being made available by the Commonwealth free of cost to<br />
the Council and the State Government.<br />
" I am particularly pleased that these caravans which proved so<br />
useful in Darwin can now be utilised to assist the people in<br />
Lawson and other mountain towns" Mr. Fraser said.<br />
This arrangement, which falls outside the normal natural<br />
disaster assistance scheme, again demonstrates the<br />
Commonwealth's willingness to act speedily and sympathetically<br />
when the need arises to help disaster victims. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
