<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5855</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/07/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005855.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO: 5: 00PM<br />
PRIME MINISTER.,<br />
FOR MEDIA SUNDAY JULY 11 1982<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
The Cain Labor Government's new probate tax is punitive and<br />
discriminatory. It is not just a tax, it is a confiscatory<br />
z-ppropriation. Thirty nine cents in the dollar is a punitive<br />
rate by any measure, and the rate is the same whether you are<br />
at the bottom or at the top.<br />
It is not a tax on the rich. The limit of $ 200,000 is not<br />
high. Many ordinary people with a house and a superannuation<br />
policy will be caught. People with a house and a small business<br />
are almost certain to fall outside the limit. Without doubt,<br />
probate will damage Victoria's economy enormously.<br />
If this new tax becomes law, it will cause an exodud from<br />
Victoria, as retired people go off in even greater numbers<br />
to Queensland. House and land values in Victoria will go down.<br />
People will see the assets they have built up for themselves<br />
and their families decline in value.<br />
I-ronically, it is the ordinary. home-owners and home-buyers<br />
in suburban Melbourne who will be amongst the'. hardest hit.<br />
The value of their homes will fall. Worse still, Mr Cain's<br />
new tax will-stop people investing in Victoria. Who will start<br />
a business in Victoria if they cannot leave it to their children<br />
without probate? Mr Cain's probate discriminates-against the<br />
family business, and takes away the incentive to work hard<br />
the very.. thing which has helped build Australi4 up.<br />
No-one outside this State will want to invest in Victoria,<br />
because every single dollar of assets which non-residents<br />
hold in Victoria can be liable to probate at the full rate<br />
of thirty-nine cei-ts in the dollar. o<br />
Labor has claimed that probate will only hit a small percentage<br />
of estates, but that. claim seems largely guesswork,. and when<br />
you take.-account of the exemptions that are in the Bill, especially<br />
the exemption for spouses, it is certain that a far higher<br />
percentage of families will be hit.<br />
I am certain Mr Cain kn6ws that exempting farmers from probate<br />
will lie divisive. It will lead to great resentment against the<br />
farming community amongst those who are not exempt. Labor has<br />
never understood, or sympathised, with our farming communities,<br />
so Mr Cain would not care about arousing. hostility towards ; the<br />
man on the land. There is only one way to prevent this to<br />
withdraw probate duty altogetlier. I am sure farmers were exempted<br />
because Mr Cain knows their returns are too low for them to put<br />
aside money for probate. But by taxing others in this divisive </p>
<p>-2-<br />
* way, especially email businesses# he has shownl a blatant<br />
disregard for them and for the community as a whole*<br />
It is natural for people toiwant to build up assets and-leave<br />
what they have accumulated to their families and children.<br />
Mr Cain's tax is socialism at its worst. Dogma has gone to<br />
his head. What can he be thinking of by exempting estates<br />
left children to their parents and grandparents?<br />
The natural thing is for parents to leave property todabno<br />
thcehil drn. hisis what Mr Cain should exempt abno<br />
this unnatural tax.<br />
Victoria will be the only State with probate if M4r Cain goes<br />
ahead. Why does Mr Cain want probate when even Mr Wran has<br />
ab-ish-~ -iEt-I probate is* i mposed on ' Vict~ oriansD New South<br />
Wales and Queensland will be the beneficiaries as people leave<br />
the State of Victoria and take their asset!; with them.<br />
Probate was always one of the most hated and vicious forms<br />
of tax, a~ nd Mr Cain's -proposal, with its hiLgh rate and its<br />
selective exemptions, is a particularly vicious form of probate.<br />
Taxes on the living are high enough without; taxing the dead. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
