<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9365</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J.KEATING, MP DROUGHT ASSISTANCE</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/09/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009365.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING, MP A t/<br />
DROUGHT ASSISTANCE<br />
With my colleagues, the Minister for Primary Industry, Bob Collins, and the<br />
Minister for Social Security, Peter Baldwin, I am pleased to announce the<br />
Federal Government's measures to help rural communities through the crippling<br />
drought in Queensland and New South Wales. The measures are designed to<br />
provide rapid relief to families and communities experiencing " exceptional<br />
circumstances" in the worst drought areas.<br />
Following a submission from Senator Collins and Mr Baldwin, Federal Cabinet<br />
endorsed the measures this morning. They will be implemented immediately.<br />
In some areas this is the worst drought on record. Farmers and their families,<br />
farm businesses and rural communities are suffering extreme hardship. Without<br />
immediate assistance, the hard work and personal investment of many<br />
thousands of Australians , might well be wasted.<br />
We cannot leave these people behind. The measures we announce today are<br />
designed to ensure that they will not be. They create a safety net to provide for<br />
their immediate needs and create the circumstances in which they will be well<br />
placed to recover when rain eventually comes.<br />
If only for the sake of fairness, we must take these measures. But it is also in<br />
the interests of the national economy to take them. It is in the interests of the<br />
long term sustainability of our rural industries. It is in the interests of the<br />
environment. It is in the interests of all Australians to take them.<br />
Today, in responding to the human and social consequences of the drought, we<br />
are also conscious as are the farmers' organisations and the farmers<br />
themselves that we must address the long term needs of the drought affected<br />
areas. For this reason we have taken care to ensure that the measures are<br />
consistent with the objectives of the National Drought Policy and the Rural<br />
Adjustment Scheme. </p>
<p>L 2<br />
The package has been costed at $ 164 million over 2 years. This amount will be<br />
exceeded if additional " exceptional circumstances" declarations are made, or if<br />
the drought persists well into next year.<br />
In addition, we will provide a generous tax incentive for farm storage and water<br />
facilities to encourage farmers to better prepare for drought.<br />
The key elements of the package are:<br />
a Drought Relief Scheme to address the immediate cash flow needs of<br />
the worst affected families;<br />
further measures under the Rural Adjustment Scheme to assist farm<br />
businesses;<br />
further resources for financial and social counselling.<br />
Other longer term measures will be dealt with in a later submission to Cabinet<br />
consistent with the Government's systemic approach to drought policy and may<br />
include further initiatives in the areas of taxation, income equalisation deposits,<br />
landcare, and climate research.<br />
In coming weeks, I will also meet with the major banks and pastoral houses to<br />
discuss the important role they have in helping rural businesses and<br />
communities now and in the period of recovery.<br />
The Government will continue its consultations with the States at a special<br />
meeting the Commonwealth has convened later this week of the Agriculture and<br />
Resource Management Council of Australia and New Zealand.<br />
CANBERRA<br />
21 September 1994 </p>
<p>SUMMARY OF MEASURES<br />
Drourtht Relief Payment<br />
The Drought Relief Payment ( DRP) will provide farm families with sufficient cash for<br />
basic necessities and services. Payments under DRP will be available to farm families<br />
in areas assessed to be in exceptional drought and will be subject to the income and<br />
off-farm assets tests that apply to the Job Search Allowance ( JSA). Farm assets will<br />
not be subject to assessment for DRP eligibility. Payments under the DRP will be<br />
available from mid-October retrospective to the start of the month and will continue<br />
until six months after Exceptional Circumstances conditions are terminated. Farm<br />
families eligible for DRP will also be eligible for Family Payments and Healthcare card<br />
benefits. The accompanying table provides a summary of entitlements.<br />
Austudy The existing Austudy farm assets test will be removed for all families in exceptional<br />
drought areas. The current Austudy income test, which is more generous than that for<br />
JSA, and off-farm assets test will apply.<br />
Farm Business Support<br />
An additional $ 74.25 million for the Rural Adjustment Scheme ( RAS) over 1994-95<br />
and 1995-96 will be available to assist farm businesses during drought exceptional<br />
circumstances and the recovery period. Normal RAS support has been supplemented<br />
by $ 8.25 million, while support under exceptional circumstances has been increased by<br />
$ 66.0 million over the next two years.<br />
In a significant improvement to RAS, we will ensure sufficient resources for all farm<br />
enterprises eligible for exceptional circumstance RAS to be fully funded. In the past,<br />
limited resources have meant many farmers have not been able to access their full<br />
interest subsidy requirements. The changes mean that for exceptional circumstances,<br />
RAS will be demand driven.<br />
The package also includes measures to help farms recover from drought. There will be<br />
a six month period after the termination of the exceptional circumstances declaration in<br />
which applications can be made. In addition, through a supplementation to normal<br />
RAS, eligible farms will be able to apply for some further assistance for an additional<br />
twelve months.<br />
Farmers have not been able to access the exceptional circumstance provisions of RAS<br />
without first selling all off-farm assets. This has created difficulties where farmers have<br />
taken steps to provide for their retirement. In recognition of this, investment in bona<br />
fide insurance and superannuation funds have been excluded from the assets test for<br />
the exceptional circumstances support while an assets test of $ 163,500 will apply for<br />
other off-farm assets.<br />
Finally, the maximum individual annual assistance limit on RAS interest payments has<br />
been lifted from $ 50,000 to $ 100,000, while the cumulative limit over five years on<br />
assistance has been lifted from $ 100,000 to $ 300,000. </p>
<p>These improvements to RAS will require matching funding by the States.<br />
Counselling and Support Services<br />
Further resources are being provided for rural financial and social counselling in areas<br />
affected by exceptional drought to assist farmers and their families manage the financial<br />
distress and social trauma dimensions of the drought. Provision has been made to<br />
increase the total number of Commonwealth funded rural financial and business<br />
counsellors to 140, and give farmers and their families access to additional personal<br />
counselling. The Rural Counselling Service is also to get access to further<br />
administrative assistance to accommodate the higher workload. The State<br />
Governments will be asked to help ensure that adequate social counselling is provided<br />
in drought affected areas.<br />
Drou2ht Preparedness<br />
The Government will also provide incentives for farms and rural communities to better<br />
protect the agricultural resource base during drought and encourage improved land<br />
management. The Government will consider providing a generous investment<br />
allowance for farm storage and water facilities. In addition, we will consider faster<br />
depreciation on storage facilities. In developing these measures, we will take into<br />
account the need to ensure that any such investments take full account of their<br />
environmental impact. The Treasurer, the Minister for Primary Industries and Energy<br />
and the Minister for the Environment, Sport and Territories will work with peak farm<br />
groups over the next few months to develop such a scheme.<br />
The Government will also examine the possibility of providing further funding through<br />
its labour market programs to address land degradation and environmental protection<br />
in drought prone areas. </p>
<p>DROUGHT RELIEF PACKAGE<br />
PROGRAM FUNDING DETAELSM1<br />
1994-95<br />
Farm Family Welfare<br />
Drought Relief Payments<br />
Austudy exemption<br />
Family payments<br />
Health Care Card<br />
RAS authority administration<br />
Total 43.45 3.69<br />
4.36 0.25 0.24 1995-96<br />
19.31 2.77 1.93<br />
0.11 0.10<br />
51.99 24.22<br />
Farm Business Support( 2<br />
Normal RAS<br />
Drought Exceptional Circumstances<br />
Total<br />
Drought Counselling<br />
Matching " Farmhand"( 3<br />
TOTAL 3.00<br />
25.00 5.25<br />
41.00<br />
28.00 46.25<br />
1.4572.40<br />
10.00<br />
91.447 72.87<br />
Excludes the Governent's further consideration of investment and depreciation allowances<br />
relating to fodder and water storage<br />
Excludes matching contributions from the States for the Rural Adjustment Scheme.<br />
Anticipated Government contribution </p>
<p>MAXIMUM DROUGHT RELIEF PAYMENTS per week)<br />
Single<br />
Couple Couple Couple Couple Couple Couple<br />
Couple Couple Couple Couple person 1 child under 13<br />
1 child aged 13-15<br />
1 AUSTUDY 16-17 yo at home<br />
1 AUSTUDY 16-17 yo<br />
1 AUSTUDY over 18 at home<br />
1 AUSTUDY over 18 away<br />
2 children under 13<br />
1 child under 13 1 child 13-15<br />
2 children 13-15 $ 148-65<br />
$ 268-20<br />
$ 310-95<br />
$ 324-15<br />
$ 334-35<br />
$ 377-40<br />
$ 347-75<br />
$ 388-95<br />
$ 353-70<br />
$ 366-90<br />
$ 380-10<br />
MADE UP OF<br />
Couple Rate $ 268-20<br />
Basic Family Payment,-$ 10-65 per child for first three children;<br />
$ 14-20 for each subsequent child<br />
Additional Family Payment $ 32-10 per child aged under 13<br />
$ 45-30 per child aged 13-15<br />
TJDY (-JSA) $ 66-15 tor each 16-17 year oi" -alt hoe--<br />
$ 109-20 for each 16-17 year old away from home<br />
$ 79-55 for each 18+ at home<br />
$ 120-75 for each 18+ away from home. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
