<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>957</transcript-id>
    <title>UNIVERSITY OF BIRMINGHAM  - DEGREE  CONREGATIONS 1944 , CEREMENY IN GREAT HALL -  11.0 A.M SATURDAY 11TH JULY</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/07/1964</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000957.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
UNITVMSITT OF 3h! RIINHAM<br />
DEGRE CONUGAYIO1 19W<br />
Ceremony In Great Hall-<br />
11.0 am. 3aturdaY. 11th July<br />
THE RT. RON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES -Prim Minister of Australia<br />
Hats are curious things -hae you noticed thatt The<br />
higher orders, like myself, we war these; and then I -m<br />
supposed to keep It en, but I wn't. I noticed this owrning<br />
that on a slightly lewer level they wear mortar-bierds ad<br />
this permits an imfimite variety of app arm" but I want to<br />
award a special prime to the m Who, I tboxgbtv were bis<br />
mortar-board with the post bravura tes right bookew a well<br />
thatched head. I refers you willI all uaderstai, to Mr.<br />
Jonathan George Hodgkins,<br />
Now, Sir, I don't want to detain this congregation but<br />
there are pertaps one or two things I would like to say. OVA<br />
of~ them is about the Public Orator. Boing public, but no<br />
orator, myself, I have a great Interest in Publie Orators..<br />
Very frequently they address the Chancellor in Latin, a language<br />
now not as commonly understood as it should beg but even then<br />
If you still retain a smattering of Latin, Sir, yeu are up<br />
0 against the great problem of hew It is te be premeunod: old,<br />
new. or what I call ' Law Courts Latia'. -A very great problem.<br />
At another great seat-. of learning 1* this country I as presented<br />
by'a Public Orator, who produced his Latta with the stiotest<br />
adherence to the new proieatms Xnms of Y" ot cients<br />
understand this), and the Chanoeller was Lord Ealifax, who plied<br />
much to my relief In the old prenuneiation, ad I thought I was<br />
doing very well when I roughly, roughly, understood both of them.<br />
I found out afterwards, looking around all the assenbled 4int<br />
that It turned out I was the only ome who did, and that Is very<br />
encouraging. In the University of Western Axstralia * the other'<br />
iday I was given a degree, 9one of these unearnd dogrees4 I have<br />
one or two of sy own that I lae sweated. for and A t'ePblic<br />
Orator. did most of -it. In Englsh and then a -few phrasses* In Latin.<br />
Now I must tell you, If you don't know, that mWn years ago in my<br />
country I had a 1little disputo with the waterside workoe about<br />
the shipping of vig iretm they emteed so ** Pig Ireneva I<br />
title that I have wars with singular distinotion for a longs long<br />
time, end the Public Oratokr at the Vniversity of Western Australia,<br />
Sir, he presentedom einally inthe Latin bit: ' 8sub nemime<br />
poemsi ferrimo'. </p>
<p>Sir, having disposed of these irr~ lvaines, I would lk*<br />
to say something, If I night on this very happy oecailon, about<br />
you.* I ease from a far but I do It camn fkab ' a very<br />
far spot In your mind. We hive bas. over many yeafts great<br />
friends, and 1, over many years, have been your preat. aairor.<br />
I think that this country has been fortunate ' in having In Its<br />
service a aman of sush learming, high Intelligence, great<br />
courage In prosperity and afversity, as the present Lord Avon,<br />
whom I know bettor as Anthony Meg ad this University, If I<br />
may war so, io greatly hemiured to have him Is the ohair.<br />
You know, Sir, polities of whieb I M a species of<br />
practitioner myself polities io regarded by all aes-politieal<br />
people an etraordinarily easy., and by all newpaper<br />
Icommentators as almost fantastically simple. Quite easy.<br />
Polities, of course; statesmanship In the conduct of the affairs<br />
of nations; is the most testing of all occupatins It sowetime<br />
attracts the attentio* of people * t coarse 1i6re and low<br />
quality. Ivory sow and thoen It attrats te attention of a man<br />
of fine fibre and great quality. I don't Ilke anticipating what<br />
that mythical being, the historian, will say; you knew, this Is<br />
one of the clches of life isn't It 40the historian will sayg,<br />
the belief being, Mrw. Chancellor, that histerima got It right.<br />
Well perhaps they do oceasiemally. But still, In the long<br />
a runthere Is a judgment of history and I ventur, to say with<br />
W some dogma that history wilf roeer4f when It somes to be settlei<br />
ad balanced, If -It ever 4068, that your Chancellor was the<br />
gratest Foreign Minister that this country has had In thi<br />
century, and a Prim Miniaster of such courage and Imagination'<br />
that, looking back an Itp and we had a few troubled tises<br />
together, I marvel at his fortitude.'<br />
This is a groat-story. af-g roat life,,. and when I received<br />
a letter asking me to come here to be honouared by a -degreeg and<br />
I found that the Chanellorwas thisfriend of em, what<br />
normally would have been a peat pleasure beoao a singular<br />
pleasure, a tremndous occasion for rejoicing io ' my heart, and<br />
pride In my mind, and that is my first reason feWt appreciating<br />
this honour. </p>
<p>Ihae a ade~ d reason, ' ast which I wtil bi. quits, brief.<br />
I t sum out that I have tad good deal 6a do Oith the moders.'<br />
developent of. Universities in Anstralia, aNo. I 1*~ It turns<br />
out,. because although I an a Uniersity am myself sd have<br />
always had, I hope, ioe undoretandiug of what Univereitses<br />
man and how mushi the wend ne043 thou, It 614 tuan' iut thatk<br />
after the wa there was a tremeadous upsurge In the umer of<br />
students who wanted to * one Into the Austr~ lian Universities.<br />
Now the Australian Universities are primarily the bulsino of<br />
the State Goverinomte, the Stato'Fanlset, In Autralia;<br />
the Commnwalth bad sever entered Into that field; but the<br />
whole problem seened to me to be so troesedous ad so growing<br />
that I did secure the services of Sir Keith Murray to come out<br />
and head a Comittee, and whea he made his rdport, and I read<br />
the figures, I concealed the report from the ' Treasury. I<br />
don't encourage deceit as a general role, but on this occ1ao<br />
I practised a 1ittl. 14 I didn't conceal it from the. altogether,<br />
but~ I just let them have It * t the las possible moment, and<br />
then I bad a Cabinet Meeting and I eiraulated the report Mons<br />
the Cabinet Ministers only the night befft the ' Cabinet Meeting,<br />
so I was the only ose really who know wat was in the report,<br />
and by nightfall we bad adopted every re~ onedatlon In the<br />
0report. Anybody who is coatemplating. pellitio as a career<br />
could do no -better than study that ozmple -of political technique.<br />
And'since then we have establid a Usiversity Commssion mad<br />
the " nount that is called for year by year, or every triennim,<br />
grows in the most fabulous fahibon, buj this I believe, has<br />
* opened up a new chaptoet In the history of the Universities*<br />
and In, this generation, In this omtury, everybody met realiso,<br />
that the greatest need of the world, and the greatest need of<br />
your country, and the greatest nemed of my souatip, is net am<br />
happy stroke on a financial inveptiment, but a lnreasing<br />
producton of educated men and wonen throu* b -or Uiveritse.,<br />
Ibis is -tho potential wealthl or the country ad, without i,<br />
* we will dwindle,, peak and pine.<br />
It Is a very exelig thing to me $ Irv to go to0 eenforriSg<br />
of degroes 11it this, becomee I leek around'and I see literally<br />
in front of se the additional assets thkat the nation % as secun"&amp;,<br />
and t hope every graduate will tbink of it, not in a priggIsh way<br />
but with an understanding of poew $ no that is'. </p>
<p>But' there Is one great* problem that conifronts the<br />
Universities In my country and that so doubt cozfronts the<br />
Universities here. it is this. It io always possible,<br />
given enough authority, or Impuence, or Ingenuity, to getmoney<br />
out of the Treasury., It!@ a fact It's always possible.<br />
But you can' t get. Uaiveroity. professors and lecturer, and staffs<br />
in nome shop or free any Govewmnt 4eparmt Thousinds and<br />
thousands of undergraduates are added to -the normal rate of~<br />
Increase in my country every year, and my complete problen all<br />
the time is where are we going to provide the academic staffs<br />
that are needed to mantain this standard. Tbat Is -a Much<br />
bigger problem than bricks aad mortar$ A mobh bigper preblem<br />
than money, because of-all things that W, mus" t 84014' -it is a<br />
debasement of the currency. . W. i co't hov# a Greshmans Law<br />
applying to aeaidenio standards., of bad money drivimng out good.<br />
we can't have this. We post son't. afford it.<br />
I have a fixe4 belief that every 7earls.# oup of g ra4jates<br />
ought to be, on the whole, rather better than their predecessors;<br />
better trained amd, of @ ou" rso, In the world of. Soiesnoeamplexities<br />
grow so-uch that you must be Immeasurably letter equipped a<br />
scientists than your fathers were. ftt must keep the standards<br />
up, end I hope that the staMisrds will be Ike" ae, that many<br />
people who are now going to the Unmvrsitles and who bay* great<br />
talent and have achieved high acidenic statuq, that som of then<br />
will think of working In the Univofttiei,.. of teaching I. n schools,<br />
of helping to produce a new generation. We can't all go off<br />
after the best paid job, there must be constantly, year Sy Year,<br />
a number of people who'have a feeling of dedication . to this<br />
matter and who say, I an determined th~ t the standards of my<br />
L'niverity will ris not fall, eivery year. That's the greatest<br />
problem that confronts the Univrsties, in my opinion, But<br />
every tim, Sir, I feel pessimistic abopt it*, and' I go to an<br />
In'vesttture and I see the neow graduates, I-become an optimist.' </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
