<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1654</transcript-id>
    <title>PM 90/1967 - Visit of President of Italy</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/09/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001654_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>FOR PRESS: PM. No. 90/ 1967</p>
<p>Statement by the Prime Minister, Mr Harold Holt</p>
<p>Following my recent announcement that the President of the Republic of Italy, Signor Giuseppe Saragat, accompanied by the Foreign Minister, the Honourable Amintore Fanfani, will make a State Visit to Australia this month, a programme of functions has been arranged in the centres he will visit.</p>
<p>The President is due to arrive at Fairbairn RAAF base, Canberra on the afternoon of 25th September. He will visit Melbourne from 27th to 29th September, and Sydney from 29th September to 1st October. He will leave for overseas on 1st October.</p>
<p>Although the visit will necessarily be restricted to only six days, every effort has been made by Commonwealth and State authorities to ensure that the President has an informative and pleasant stay in Australia.</p>
<p>In Canberra there will be governmental talks with the Foreign Minister, Signor Fanfani.</p>
<p>A summary of the President's Canberra programme is as follows:</p>
<p><strong>25 September</strong></p>
<p>Afternoon :</p>
<ul><li>President Saragat and party arrive at RAAF Fairbairn at approximately 3. 10pm to a ceremonial welcome. After being greeted by the Governor-General, Lord Casey and the Prime Minister, the President leaves for the Hotel Canberra ( where he will stay.)</li>
<li>Receives a formal call from the Prime Minister.</li>
<li>The President leaves for Government House where he will be the guest of the Governor-General and The Lady Casey at dinner.</li>
</ul><p><strong>26th September</strong></p>
<p>Morning:</p>
<ul><li>The President lays a wreath at the Australian War Memorial, receives Heads of Diplomatic Missions at Government House.</li>
</ul><p>Afternoon :</p>
<ul><li>Attends luncheon given by the Government of Australia. At this function, the President will make a major speech in reply to addresses of welcome from Government and Opposition Leaders.</li>
<li>The President makes a sight-seeing tour of Canberra.</li>
</ul><p>Evening :</p>
<ul><li>The President receives the Leader of the Opposition, Mr E. G. Whittlam.</li>
<li>Dinner given by the President of Italy at the residence of the Ambassador.</li>
</ul><p><strong>27th September </strong></p>
<p>Morning:</p>
<ul><li>The Fresident is farewelled at RAAF Fairbairn by the Governor-General, Lord Casey and the Frime Minister, and leaves for Melbourne.</li>
</ul><p>CANBERRA,<br />3rd September. 1967</p>
<p>NOTE: The programmes for Melbourne and Sydney will be released by the Premier's Departments in Victoria and New South Wales.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
