<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5666</transcript-id>
    <title>CONDOLENCE MOTION FOR PRESIDENT ANWAR SADAT</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/10/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005666.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER.<br />
FOR MEDIA TUESDAY, 13 OCTOBER, 1981<br />
CONDOLENCE MOTION FOR PRESIDENT ANWAR SADAT<br />
Mr. Speaker,<br />
I move " that this House records its sincere regret at the<br />
death on 6 October 1981 of President Mohamed Anwar El Sadat<br />
and expresses to the people of the Arab Republic of Egypt<br />
profound regret and tenders its deep sympathy to his widow<br />
and family in their bereavement".<br />
I advise the House that the Commonwealth Heads of Government in<br />
Melbourne jointly extended their deep sympathy to Madam Sadat,<br />
and to the Government and people of Egypt, and expressed<br />
their horror at the act of outrage which took his life.<br />
The Governor-General has also expressed his deep sadness and<br />
distress over the manner and the fact of President Sadat's death.<br />
The Deputy Prime Minister represented Australia at the funeral.<br />
Anwar Sadat was one of the architects of the movement which<br />
shaped modern Egypt, bringing it to the present level of social<br />
and economic development.<br />
on becoming President of Egypt in 1970 he led his country both<br />
as an outstanding patriot-nd-, a a-man of vision in relations<br />
between nations. It reflected hi-s-great personal courage and<br />
initiative, that he worked so hard to lay the groundwork for a<br />
comprehensive peace settlement in the Middle East.<br />
To embark on this process involved an acceptance of substantial<br />
risks, both domestic and international. His capacity to devote<br />
his energies singlemindedly while bringing his nation with him<br />
was itself a tribute to his greatness.<br />
In 1977, after 30 years of continual warfare in the Middle East,<br />
President Sadat made his historic and courageous visit to Jerusalem<br />
to address the Knesset, and thus opened the path to negotiation<br />
in the quest for peace. And theKf: 1979, the Egypti'an/ Israeli<br />
peace treaty was signed. I said at the time that the world<br />
hoped that work on a comprehensive Middle East settlement would<br />
proceed in the aftermath of that treaty.<br />
President Sadat sought peace to resolve the problems built up,<br />
through mistrust and fear.. He was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize<br />
in 1978, jointly with the Prime Minister of Israel. / 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
While the peace with Israel, and the stability which has<br />
ensued, is perhaps President Sadat's greatest monument, his<br />
other achievements are not less significant. He realised<br />
that the basic security of Egypt and the Middle East lay in<br />
distancing the region from wider global power struggles, and<br />
to this end he sought to diminish the impact of the Soviet Union<br />
by restricting its influence within Egypt and the area as a whole.<br />
His pursuit of constructive and realistic domestic and foreign<br />
policies brought both to himself and Egypt a reputation for<br />
moderation, balance and constraint in the non-aligned movement.<br />
His death is a great loss for Egypt, the Middle East and<br />
the world, not least because of the senseless and brutal violence<br />
which brought it about. To have lost a world leader of<br />
President Sadat's stature is tragic.<br />
Not everyone, as we know, agreed with what President Sadat<br />
was doing, although everyone must surely respect him for his<br />
courage and his objectives of peace and stability and certainly<br />
no benefits will follow from what has taken place.<br />
We can only hope and trust that President Sadat's achievements<br />
will be sustained and that his vision of a lasting and<br />
comprehensive peace settlement can be realised as a fitting<br />
tribute and memorial to him. We all mourn his death.<br />
000---7-L<br />
L </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
