<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2330</transcript-id>
    <title>VISIT OF POPE PAUL VI - FAREWELL AT SYDNEY AIRPORT - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR JOHN GORTON</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/12/1970</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002330.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
VISIT OF POPE PAUL VI<br />
FAR EWELL AT SYDi" L-Y A IRPORT<br />
peech by the Prime Minister, Mr. John Gorton<br />
Your Holiness, Your Excellencies, Mr. Premier, Ladies and<br />
Gentlemen No words of mine are necessary, Sir to let you<br />
know how welcome you have been, for the warmth and sincerity<br />
of the crowds that have flocked to see you have made that manlifest.<br />
This, the first visit by a Pontiff, is something we<br />
shall long remember. It has been specially significant to our<br />
Roman Catholic community, but it has had a wider significance<br />
and one that touches all of us.<br />
Your visit, Sir, has come at a time when there is<br />
a growing spirit of unity among Christian peoples, arid your<br />
1flessage of peace and goodwill, based on fundamental Chris" tian<br />
principles, has universal appeal.<br />
We admire the way in which you have managed<br />
to cope with the many demands and the constant demands upon<br />
your time and energy while you have been here.<br />
You have met many Australians, people-from<br />
various walks of life the old, the young, the native-born, the<br />
migrants but all Australians. And in addition, through radio<br />
and television, the message which you brought has been transferred<br />
to the remotest parts of this great continent.<br />
Now you are to continue your journey, and as you travel<br />
on, I hope you will have with you in your heart warm and happy<br />
memories of our nation.<br />
We are glad you came. We wish you Godspeedl and<br />
a safe journey home. And we thankc you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
