<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7296</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER LAUNCH OF THE NATIONAL AGENDA FOR WOMEN BONDI JUNCTION - 29 FEBRUARY 1988</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/02/1988</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007296.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTEAk<br />
LAUNCH OF THE NATIONAL AGENDA FOR WOMEN<br />
BONDI JUNCTION 29 FEBRUARY 1988<br />
Premier Barrie Unsworth,<br />
Ministerial colleague Margaret Reynolds,<br />
Parliamentary colleagues Jeanette McHugh and Pat Giles,<br />
Edith Hall, Convenor of the National Women's<br />
Consultative Council<br />
Ladies and gentlemen.<br />
Three years ago, an extraordinary gathering took place in<br />
Nairobi, in Kenya, which brought to a climax an<br />
extraordinary decade in the development of new policies and<br />
new hopes for the women of the world.<br />
The conference in Nairobi was convened to review the many<br />
achievements of the United Nations' Decade for Women, and to<br />
work out how to keep the momentum going.<br />
Australia was represented at Nairobi and our delegation<br />
endorsed the conf~ rence's conclusions. Those conclusions in<br />
effect threw down the challenge to the governments of the<br />
world to abolish, by the year 2000, all obstacles to the<br />
full and equal participation of women in all spheres of<br />
society.<br />
Today, three years later, we are gathered to show that, in<br />
Australia, t'hat challenge is being met.<br />
Those obstaZ~ les are falling.<br />
Full and equal participation by women is certainly not yet<br />
attained. But it is -on the way.<br />
And this document that I have the honour to launch today<br />
the National Agenda for Women is<br />
a demonstration of what we have achieved;<br />
a proof that we are on the right track; and<br />
a guarantee that we will achieve our goal. 004664 </p>
<p>In 1985, in a statement to Parliament, I announced the way<br />
in which the Government, in attempting to meet the challenge<br />
of Nairobi, would continue to raise the status of Australian<br />
women. The best resource at hand for advice on this matter the<br />
most accurate source of information about the needs and<br />
priorities of women is of course the women of Australia<br />
themselves. So in our search to create a National Agenda for Women we<br />
embarked in 1986 on a massive process of consultation with<br />
some 25,000 women throughout the nation.<br />
This led in 1987 to the report Setting the Agenda, and in<br />
turn that has led to this report on the N&amp; tional Agenda.<br />
This National Agenda goes further than an previous<br />
statement by any Australian community group, political<br />
party, or Government.<br />
It is the most comprehensive series of commitments to women<br />
and of strategies on women's issues ever produced by an<br />
Australian Government.<br />
It sets a new high water mark for our thinking, and our<br />
planning, as a nation, about how we can realistically<br />
advance the interests of women.<br />
The catch-cry of the National Agenda is " A Say, A Choice and<br />
A Fair Go"<br />
A Say which is about involving women in the planning<br />
and implementation of policies which will affect them;<br />
A Choice which is about ensuring women in fact have<br />
real options to enlarge their lives through full and<br />
equal access to education, employment, training;<br />
and A Fair Go which underlines the need for full and<br />
equal access to all the opportunities which our society<br />
offers<br />
This formulation provides the structure of the Report<br />
supplemented, as it should be, by sections on Australia's<br />
international links on the advancement ot the status of<br />
women links which hark back to the initial impetus given<br />
this process by the Nairobi conference.<br />
The Report spells out in detail the initiatives my<br />
Government has already taken to advance these goals of A<br />
Say, A Choice, and A Fair Go.<br />
It sets out the way in which we will make further progress<br />
or these g6als as we approach the year 2000. 004665 </p>
<p>And it has an action plan for more immediate work over the<br />
next five years, which will be monitored and modified as we<br />
move towards the long-term objectives for the twenty-first<br />
century. We recognise of course that mwany women choose to seek<br />
fulfillment within the home. That is their right and it is<br />
to be respected<br />
our achievements already on behalf of all women those<br />
within the home and those in the paid workforce are not<br />
insignificant. Indeed in five years we make the proud and<br />
the entirely accurate claim that we have done more than any<br />
preceding Government to advance the interests of Australian<br />
women.<br />
We have passed the Sex Discrimination Act in fulfilment of<br />
our commitments following ratification of the United Nations<br />
Convention on the Elimination of all Forms of Discrimination<br />
Against women. This Act prohibits discrimination on the<br />
grounds of sex, marital status or pregnancy in employment,<br />
education and other areas.<br />
We have passed the Affirmative Action Act which requires<br />
companies and higher education institutions to develop<br />
strategies to give women equal employment and promotion<br />
opportunities. These are landmark legislative acts and I want to pay<br />
tribute in passing to the work of the former Minister for<br />
the Status of Women,* Senator Susan Ryan, for the diligence<br />
and vision she displayed in creating them.<br />
We have elevated the office of the Status of Women in my<br />
Department of the Prime minister and Cabinet, so it can<br />
provide input at-the highest level of government.<br />
we have established the National women's Consultative<br />
Council to make sure Australian women do indeed have A Say.<br />
I pay tribute to Edith Hall, the Convenor of the Council for<br />
her consistent and effective hard work ove~ r the last four<br />
years.<br />
We have created more childcare places than any previous<br />
Commonwealth government, allowing thousands of women to<br />
enter or re-enter the workforce with the knowledge that<br />
their children are being adequately cared for.<br />
we are funding women's refuges, we are undertaking a<br />
campaign to eliminate domestic violence, we have established<br />
a Child Support Agency to help ensure single parents<br />
usually single mothers receive the help they deserve from<br />
the non-custodial parent.<br />
We have taken a number of other initiatives in the areas of<br />
education,-trainiing, health, and others which are itemised<br />
in the report. 004666' </p>
<p>And let's not lose sight of the fact that in addition to all<br />
these programs specifically directed at women, my Government<br />
has ensured through its overall policies, that Australian<br />
women are not left out in the cold.<br />
For instance, we have created, in our nearly five years in<br />
office, one million new jobs in the Australian economy and<br />
women have taken their fair share of them.<br />
we have lifted the number of school children staying on to<br />
complete their secondary schooling from about one-third in<br />
1983 to over one-half and many of these students are<br />
girls.<br />
We have revolutionised assistance to less-well-off families<br />
by introducing the Family Assistance Package late last year<br />
which is to direct new, tax-free, cash assistance to those<br />
families typically to mothers. May I take this<br />
opportunity to seek your assistance in ensuiring that this<br />
payment indeed reaches those for whom it is intended.<br />
Not as many people as we know are eligible for this payment<br />
have applied for it and I trust you will pass the word on to<br />
friends or work colleagues who you think may be eligible.<br />
So reviewing our progress, we can take satisfaction with<br />
what we have done. But on the other hand we cannot promise<br />
that remaining discrimination against women will vanish<br />
overnight. What we can offer is our commitment to work over the long<br />
haul for economic security and independence and equality of<br />
opportunity in all spheres of activity.<br />
Today I am pleased to announce another step forward, of<br />
special importamce to the many women who, during the<br />
consultations leading up to the National Agenda, told us of<br />
their concerns about income security.<br />
In the past, very few women have had access to<br />
superannuation schemes. Yet women retire earlier than men,<br />
are more likely to live longer, and often spend part of<br />
their retirement-years living alone.<br />
As part of'f. a five year plan under the National Agenda, we<br />
intend to ensure that women in the fulltime permanent<br />
workforce have equal access to superannuation schemes.<br />
Up till now super schemes have been totally exempted from<br />
the provisions of the Sex Discrimination Act.<br />
Cabinet has decided to eliminate the general exemption which<br />
will have the effect of removing many of the discriminatory<br />
aspects of these schemes.<br />
The removal of this general exemption will pave the way for<br />
the overall elimination of discrimination against women in<br />
superannuation. 004667 1: </p>
<p>Ladies and gentlemen<br />
Awareness of the legitimate needs of women is well<br />
established in the Australian community an achievement due<br />
in no small part to the growin,, g numbers of women's groups<br />
working across a range of issues.<br />
It is due also to the steadily growing number of women who<br />
have won election to office at the local, State and Federal<br />
level including, as this gathering makes very clear, in<br />
this part of Sydney.<br />
The growing awareness of the needs of women has also been<br />
due to the steady progress made at the State level.<br />
I want today to make special mention of the important and<br />
innovative policies in this regard of the New South Wales<br />
government. Barrie Unsworth recently announced the establishment of the<br />
NSW Women's Employment Company to boost business<br />
opportunities for women.<br />
The NSW Government has enacted significant legislation to<br />
improve protection for the victims of dom~ stic violence a<br />
complementary measure to the Commonwealth's recently<br />
announced research and education program to combat domestic<br />
violence. And just one year ago, to mark International Women's Day,<br />
Barrie Unsworth launched a policy statement which covered<br />
100 specific women's policy issues including housing,<br />
health, employment and education.<br />
Problems that remaain at the State and the Federal levelscannot<br />
be solved overnight. Progress will require of all of<br />
us patience, hard work and commitment.<br />
But the National Agenda shows us the way forward and gives<br />
us confidence that solutions will be foun6i.<br />
4 . V, 004668 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
