<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5204</transcript-id>
    <title>SUMMARY OF ABC&#039;S &#039;AM&#039;</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/11/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005204.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER TUESDAY, 20 NOVEMBER 1979<br />
From the Press Office<br />
SUMMARY OF ABC'S<br />
Today, on the second anniversary of his peace trip to Jerusalem,<br />
Egypt's President Sadat formally laid claim to Mt. Sinai.<br />
The problems of refugees in East Timor and South East Asia.<br />
have'been gaining increased attention in the United States. it<br />
has resulted in a special Congressional hearing on East Timor<br />
being called for next month. Freelance journalist, Jeremy Mark,<br />
has made a special study of the refugee crisis: interviewed.<br />
Said there is a growing interest in Washington-these days in<br />
East Timor, particularly in the last two weeks and with<br />
considerable press interest in the subject.<br />
Timor: Ken Pottinger reports from Lisbon that a new organisation<br />
has been formed to fight for the independence of the former<br />
Portugese territory of East Timor. At a press conference announcing<br />
the start of a campaign for independence for the Pacific Ocean<br />
territory, a former resident of Timor said the movement had<br />
no political ideology and welcomed support from all willing to<br />
fight for independence. The movement's first objective is to get<br />
the Portugese Government and-the U. N. behind a campaign to oust<br />
the Indonesians who formally annexed Timor in July 1976. The<br />
group wants the Portugese. Government to take over administrative<br />
responsibility for. Timor in the interim period before full<br />
independence was granted. The movement seeks to retain independent<br />
Timor's links with Portugal in a country run by a Christian<br />
government with freedom of worship and political association.<br />
Three Americans from among the 80 hostages at the U. S. Embassy<br />
in Tehran have been-freed by their Muslim captives and are now<br />
in hospital in West Germany. 10 others later told foreign<br />
reporters that they too would be released later tonight.<br />
In Washington, the suggestion of placing the other American<br />
diplomatic hostages on trial has created a sense of outrage.<br />
Report from Peter Barnett in Washington.<br />
Union officials and industry leaders rubbed shoulders last night<br />
with a common purpose; to farewell the strong-man of N. S. W.<br />
Labor politics, John Ducker, at a $ 25 a head dinner. Report<br />
from Graham Ramsey.<br />
The former South Australian Premier, Don Dunstan, has dismissed<br />
allegations about him cont-ained in a new book called " It's<br />
Grossly Improper" as a distorted fantasy. It is claimed that<br />
Mr. Dunstan gave special favours to Mr. John Ceruto because of<br />
their close friendship. Ceruto maintains the allegations<br />
are correct and adds that he may back them up. Report from<br />
Peter Rapp in Adelaide. Interview with Don Dunstan.<br />
The nation's share markets have experienced their sharpest<br />
fall since June 1974, as interest rates rise overseas and-gloom<br />
settles over the international econom-ic world. Interview with<br />
Allan Wood, Chief Economic of the Syn tec group of management<br />
consultants. </p>
<p>2-<br />
The man that most of Britain is waiting to hear from is the<br />
self-confessed Russian spy and former member of the Royal<br />
household, Professor Anthony Blunt. According to his<br />
solicitor, Blunt will give a press conference shortly and<br />
the whole affair will be debated in the House of Commons<br />
tomorrow. Report from Richard Palfreyman in London.<br />
As mentioned earlier, ten hostages-at the U. S. Embassy in<br />
Tehran were allowed to hold a press conference earlier this<br />
morning, in which they told journalists that they expected to<br />
be released later tonight. Warwick Adderly contacted the<br />
Embassy: interview with one of the students.<br />
A new book comes out today concerning the ABC's multilingual<br />
access station in Melbourne, 3ZZ, which was closed amid great<br />
controversy in June 1977 when the Federal Government felt it<br />
was having a dangerously divisive effect on the ethnic community.<br />
The book, " Radio Power", was written by a former staff member<br />
of 3ZZ, Joan Dougdale: Interviewed.( Transcript attached).<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
