<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9165</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATIN, MP THE ECONOMIST ROUNDTABLE, HYATT HOTEL, CANBERR THURSDAY 24 MARCH,1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/03/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009165.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON.<br />
P J KEATING, M. P.<br />
THE ECONOMIST ROUNDTABLE, HYATT HOTEL, CANBERRA<br />
THURSDAY 24 MARCH, 1994<br />
PM: Well, I'm going to missGraham as a colleague and as a friend, particularly as a<br />
fiend. We've been friends now for nearly a couple of decades. And, as a<br />
colleague he was somebody who believes that good policy is good politics. He<br />
was part of the shift in the culture not just of the Labor Party but of the<br />
country, the Government the shift that Australia should have had twenty or<br />
thirty years earlier. He held major portfolios with distinction, he ran major<br />
agendas. He was not only effective in developing policy, effective in the<br />
Cabinet room as well, in their carriage, but he was effective in going out and<br />
selling them. He was effective in communicating policies. So, he is going to<br />
be missed but as he has just, himself, eloquently said, we've got a store of new<br />
ministers and members truly regenerating the Labor government. And, it's<br />
never been our business to run our assets into the ground, we don't expect<br />
people to retire exhausted.<br />
So, I wish him well in his life in the future and Cheryl, his wife and his family.<br />
All families pay a price in public life, Graham's has paid a big price over a very<br />
long period of time not just in elective office but before in the machine of the<br />
party. And he can pride himself on being one of the generation that didn't shirk<br />
the challenge, that didn't throw the pass like twenty odd years of Coalition<br />
ministers did. He can leave public life with his head high, as somebody who<br />
saw a challenge and did his best to meet it.<br />
J: When did Senator Richardson tell you that he was leaving?<br />
PM: About a week ago, a bit over a week ago.<br />
J: Did you make any money fromfthe piggery?<br />
PM: I made a decision to divest myself of that. I was not going to have my partners<br />
in that pilloried by cowards under privilege twenty two months is long<br />
enough.<br />
Ends. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
