<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7212</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW, CENTRAL AUSTRALIAN ABORIGINAL MEDIA ASSCOCIATION, ALICE SPRINGS. WEDNESDAY 2 SEPTEMBER 1987</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/09/1987</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007212.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
a 4<br />
JAU8? RAUA7-<br />
PRIME MINISTER l(<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW. CENTRAL AUSTRALIAN ABORIGINAL<br />
MEDIA ASSOCIATION, ALICE SPRINGS, WEDNESDAY 2 SEPTEM'BER<br />
1987<br />
E &amp; O0E -PROOF ONLY<br />
FM: as the Aboriginal people come to understand that<br />
we are increasingly accepting their observations And~ 4h&amp;+ 4<br />
Aboriginal people in turn will recognise and accept that<br />
so that together we can move faster in the task that we<br />
have of rectifying many of the injustices that have accummulated<br />
owprt thn nearly 200 years of European settlement in this<br />
country. JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke~. next year does mark the 200th<br />
anniversary of the arrival of the British in Australia<br />
and many Aboriginal people around Australia are concerned<br />
that in 1988 there is some recognition of Aboriginal<br />
people have suffered over the last 200 years.<br />
PM: I have made it quite clear since I Jecame Prime Minister<br />
I think you will notice whenever I speaX~ the bicentennial I talk<br />
about it being a celebration of 200 years of European settlement<br />
because we must all remember that whiltu it is appropriate th3t<br />
we remember that period that we have goL Lo the most flecting<br />
stage of the history of this country goes back 40,000 yedavN ui<br />
more. And I very much want to see a situation before 1987 finishes<br />
whereby there can be a clear understanding by all of . us that<br />
that is the nap And I would like to see 1988 prece ded by<br />
some sort of unde~ rstanding--compact, if you like. I don't want<br />
to get caught up in particular words but a compact of understanding<br />
between the whole Australian community which recognises that<br />
1988 is the celebration of 200 years of European settlement.<br />
And to recognise that in that 200 years very many injustices<br />
have been suffered by the Aboriginal people; to recoqnise, I<br />
hope, that since 1967 when the referendum was passed and<br />
power given to the federal government, that there has been a<br />
significant acceleration in that period of act= directed towards<br />
meeting some of the problems of the Aborigina. And certainly<br />
I would hope that recognition has been further accelerated<br />
in the last years. But that compact, or statement of<br />
understanding, should recognise that there Is an obligation and<br />
commitment on the part of the whole Australian community to move<br />
further in the areas of education, health. employment, training<br />
so that there can be confidence in the Aboriginal community,<br />
as we go into 1988, that the proper celebrations that there should<br />
be of the bicentenary in the sense that I have described it,<br />
is something with which they can identify. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: But can you see your Cabinet M'inisters making<br />
a treaty Aboriginal people by the end of ' 88.<br />
PM: I have discussed with Cerry Rand) and I think we must address<br />
the question of stating the relationship and the obligations<br />
that are involved in that relationship. Whether it is called<br />
a btrehe~ ua tgy', n I woamr dso pen-am tinrdeeadt y, a bao uct oItm. p aI cdto. n'Tt hthiimnko twne tshioguld<br />
is that there be a clear statement of understanding by the total<br />
Australian comm~ unity of the obligations that the community has<br />
to rectify some of the injustices that have occurred during the<br />
our 200 year3-statement of understanding, of obligation,<br />
and of commitment, those are the important things. So whether<br />
you call it a treaty or a compact, I don't think matters very<br />
much and I am not hung up about the words, it is the substance<br />
that I think is important.<br />
JOURNALIST: inaudible question<br />
PM: Yes, and I have already made sure that is done as far as i<br />
in our powers. The negotiations that will be continued by Gerry<br />
wHainldl cwointhti ntuhee Stot atbees maandde qTueirtrei tocrleieasr aasn d haopupre nceodm mbietmfoernet tthoe thPaatrliament<br />
rose in the middle of this year. You know that the changes that<br />
were made in regard to mining and aboriginal rights in the Northern<br />
Territory recognised the unequivocal right of the Aboriginal<br />
bDeAcpaIpupse f-on f hatvhiee ira pveerocae ptti otnh o of thes taiymapso rtthainacte thof~ siwtceassa, L cd thLeuy may<br />
simply don't want to negotiate about that. And that is written<br />
into the legislation.<br />
JOURNALIST: Tha Federal Government has reelly is your Goverrnent<br />
going to extend..<br />
P1M: I would regard that as appropriate in the circumstances<br />
where there was a clear aboriginal community interest and involvement<br />
and I think we have shown the commitment.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, just going back if there is to be<br />
a treaty aboriginal culture, history and rights?<br />
PM: Let me taka the first point. You are absolutely right that<br />
there has to be an increased understanding on the part of non-<br />
Aboriginal Australians about the history of this continent.<br />
And the history of that 200 years that we will be celebrating<br />
next year as beA a super-imposition upon the 40,000 years or<br />
more of previous hi story. jnd I think that the more that Australians<br />
see the 200 years that ha s -assed as at% important part of that<br />
longer period, then there will be a growing sense of realisation<br />
of the importance of that culture and history and of our. 2] aigation<br />
to ensure that the Aboriginal inheritance of that 40,000y,, R; ve<br />
their interests, grievances, and concerns properly recognised.<br />
I don't think there is one particular way in which this educative<br />
process can proceed. I think we all ought to acceptlin the process<br />
of trying to get some statement this year before 1968 starts,<br />
of the nature of the obligation. Then, if we can get that general<br />
statement, then the process of education should permeate all<br />
the things that we do. There is no one particular way that I<br />
thials. we ahouvl sloole oi4 begause if you. do that it seems artificial. </p>
<p>PM cant: I think the important thing is, and we have an obligation,<br />
I have an obligation 4s Prime Minister, I have certainly tried<br />
well before the end of this year to get a clear statement made<br />
of how we should be thinking of 1988. And within that clear<br />
statement to try and get into the minds of all Australians the<br />
importance of seeing this 200 years against the background of<br />
the 40,000 years that have gone before. If we can get that sort<br />
of fundamental understanding then I think the educative process<br />
that you need will flow to lust about that we do.<br />
JOURNALIST: Can you tell us land rights. It is very difficult<br />
to get land rights. How Is the Government going to handle<br />
the Burke Government in Western Australia and get land rights<br />
in that State?<br />
PM: Let me make this preliminary observation. We have taken'<br />
the view that what is fundamentally important if we are going<br />
to make negotiations and meaningful decisions about land rights S10' 1*<br />
is that we have as much support as we can from the people in<br />
government of the states because the worst thing that could happen,<br />
I think, In this area, would be if there was an attempt Just<br />
quickly and unilaterally to impose something from the centre.<br />
And that there was within the states concern, who afterall do<br />
the responsibility of administering activities which are<br />
Important to the Aboriginal people. If there was a sort of backlash,<br />
lack of involvement, that could be counterproductive. So what<br />
we have tried to do ince we have been government, the previous<br />
Minister and canbIe pursued by Gerry Hand, the current Minister,<br />
is to negotiate~ with the states In a way which will hopefully<br />
get their co-operation and involvement. You mentioned Western<br />
Australia. Let me point out that already we have negotiated<br />
relatively early in the life of our Government, an agreement<br />
with thq Burke Government in regard to leases in the Kimberleys. IiIf4a<br />
kW LPr w _' dcu in $ 6 million to fac~ ilitate the purchase by<br />
the Government in Western Australia and on the condition that<br />
there would be a significant proportion of those cattle leases<br />
in the Kimberleys that would-be made available to the Aboriginal<br />
coimmunities in that area. In this sort of way we are trying<br />
to negotiate, not only with the Government in Western Australia.<br />
but with the other states, in., way which, in the end, will produce<br />
a situation, as far as q~~ C~~~~ there will be agreement<br />
from the states calling for a broad model that we think is<br />
appropriate. And I don't think it is very helpful at this stage<br />
while Gerry is going to be involved in negotiations of saying<br />
now if that doesn't work this is what we will impose-It i in 4) cfnwc<br />
Aboriginal people, as much as anyone, to try and continue the Fmvcess<br />
cfco-operation. For instance here in the Territory. Gerry<br />
will on the 4th September, Gerry Is going to be sitting down qeff<br />
and negotiating with the Northern Territory Cki~~~~ k&amp; L~ Ai<br />
to try and bring about a situation there where it is by agreement<br />
we will be able to get the sort of outcome that is desirable.<br />
So we have got provisions in the legislation that we passed earlier<br />
this year but which we haven't proclaimed. We could Just legislate<br />
but it seems to us much better for Gerry to sit down and negotiate.<br />
And if we can got aqreement on these issues then that over the<br />
longer term) is going to be much more beneficial for te Aboriginal<br />
people as well as for the non-Aboriginal communIty. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: What about land rights throughout Australia. There<br />
was the referendum in 1976 that changed the constitution so that fhit,<br />
Commonwealth could make laws for Aboriginals all over Australia.<br />
When do you see this power being exercised to make a national<br />
land rights bill Northern Territory land rights.<br />
P11: In fact the referendum was passed in 1967 not 1976 so in<br />
one sense you might think that makes it work because if it is<br />
yeari ago now that that referend~ i~ m was passed and it is worth<br />
noting that it was passed by an overwhelming majority. At that<br />
stage'the Australian people made a clear judgement that they<br />
wanted the national government to have responsibilities in<br />
an important area of Australian affairs. In a sense I have answered<br />
this question in some of the observations I made earlier. And<br />
that is that we, when we came to office in 1983, developed broad<br />
principles in regard to aboriginal land rights and then decided<br />
that what we would want to do would be to negotiate with each<br />
of the states. And I think you will appreciate the conditions,<br />
the areas involved, differ from state to state. And that, by<br />
definition, is a pretty slow and painful process. I think progress<br />
has been made and I know that it is going to be one of<br />
Gerry Hand's prime areas of interest and activity now that he<br />
is the Minister to pursue those negotiations with the various<br />
states. I repeat what I said earlier that ideally you would<br />
like to be able to negotiate this 4N6b1in a co-operative way because<br />
in the end it seems to me that the interests of the Aboriginal<br />
people are going to be best served if what comes out of those<br />
negotiations is something which is as a result of co-operation<br />
and agreement rather than something which has been imposed.<br />
And let me make this point I am optimistic that these processes<br />
of negotiation with the various states will be productive. I<br />
really am optimistic about that. But I do say this if at the<br />
end those processes of negotiation can't, in a particular state,<br />
produce an acceptable outcome then the Governrent will have to<br />
face the issue of exercising its legislative powers which were<br />
given to us by the Austra lian people 20 years ago. But I repeat<br />
we will be sending our best to try and get that result by 4he<br />
processes of CC-O" peiW<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, I have Aboriginal people in<br />
Central Australia and on behalf of CAAMA I would like<br />
to thank you for your time on CAAMA radio and hope that the rest<br />
of your stay here..<br />
PM: Thank you very much. Could I just say how to be here<br />
at CAAMA. I have only been here, obviously, for a very short<br />
time but I am impressed by and by the enthusiasm of Freida<br />
and all the people involved. And I certainly wish you all the<br />
best in your endeavours.<br />
ENDS </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
