<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8606</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PAUL KEATING MP, DOORSTOP, BERNIE, 5 AUGUST 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/08/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008606.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL 5. Aug .92 1<br />
-4 PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIM k; MINISTER, THE HON PAUL KEATIN~ G MP,<br />
DOORSTOP, BERNIE, 5 AUGUST 1992<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
3: For a town that has been so knocked about, how did you find thc wood in there<br />
today?<br />
PM: I thought it was profoundly good and optimistic, and amnongst each other kindly,<br />
and willing to be part of the changes which will have to take place here to keep<br />
this town in the pulp and paper Industry.<br />
J: What's your response to their suggestion to set up a task force?<br />
PM: Well, we'll cxamine that. I think the main thing is to guarantee that these plants<br />
here are viable, and that means the company and thc employees being involved.<br />
Onc thing is clcar that towns which have had adversity do stick together, and this<br />
Is true as I said, whether It be Bernie In Tasmania, or Newcastle In New South<br />
Wales, or Gcclon~ in Victoria, one does find that -spirit of cooperation which is<br />
encouraging.<br />
3: You've been fairly scathing of APPM since you've hit Bernie. They'vc suggested<br />
they are willing to negotiate with unions..<br />
PM: No, not scathing, It's good if they are, but on their announcement they should be<br />
talk ing to peoplc rather than announcing it. That's the way to get things donc.<br />
3: Is there a chance of slow down or a drop in tariffs, which the unions 11aVe<br />
requested?<br />
PM: The problcms of this mill is not to do with tariffs, it's to do with lack of investment<br />
ovcr a quarter of a century, and not keeping up with the thing in competitiveness<br />
termns. It's a slow phasc down In tariffs, thcre's hardly any daiagc to date from<br />
tariffs, It's a slow phase down over the next 6 or 7 years. But already, in the last 3<br />
months, the exchange rate has fallen by morc than the tariff change. So, it's not<br />
7: 49 No. O3O ? ffj </p>
<p>TEL: 5. Fug. 92 17: 49 No. 030 P. 02/ C<br />
2<br />
tariffs it's management and it's having a willingness on the part of the company<br />
to make the plant tick, and on the part of the employcs in making the town and<br />
the business tick.<br />
1: Prime Minister, in there you spoke about mateship. In that regard, can I just ask<br />
you about the OST. If in Victoria it's not proven that the ads bite, where does that<br />
leave your Govrment when you go to the polls?<br />
PM: Look, State election campaigns come and go. They have even done so in the past<br />
through major federal issues. I think people separate the issues out.<br />
J: Today a survey of Chief Executive Officers has shown that about 54 per cent could<br />
support a fomi of consumption tax.<br />
PM: Well, so what, so what. It will blow the inflation rate to pieces, it will add 6-7<br />
perceulage points to the price system, it will take bill rates from now under 6 per<br />
cent to around 14 per cent, it will break two decades of effort of lowered inflation<br />
rate. Look, Dr Hewson has got one policy he wants to lift prices through a<br />
consumption tax and cut wages. It's a pretty heartless policy, and worse than that<br />
it's a dumb policy. It will do nothing for Australia and nothig for Australia's<br />
Industrial dcvelopnent.<br />
J. says that the Federal Government has asked the State Government not to<br />
campaign against the OST.<br />
PM: It's no good trying to ask me questions about the Statc election, forgct about it.<br />
I: Mr Keating, what was that last meeting about in there?<br />
PM: They were just discussing the industry and the town, and factors in<br />
competitiveness.<br />
J: They are fairly keen on regional security.<br />
PM: Well I think anyone in the industry here is, and it's a pity the Liberal Party voted<br />
against the legislation in the Senate. We had the Bill there and they voted it down.<br />
J: What did they seek specifically at the meeting?<br />
PM: Nothing in particular, not one thing in particular.<br />
Thc survey of Chief Executive Officcrs also showed that they were willing to<br />
Invcst money, but that Investment Is not going Into jobs but capital equipment. Is<br />
that really one of the major problems? </p>
<p>TEL: 5. Aug. 92 17: 49 No .030 P. 03,<br />
3<br />
PM: No. no, look, it was the same In the 1980s. Whercvcr you see growth in the<br />
economy, you see employment. They go together like Bib and Bub. if g2owth<br />
goes up, employment locs up. So anything they do to get growth up will get<br />
employment up. Now at the momecnt we're going to have a bit of a lag there<br />
becausc we'll have more output from fewer people in the first instance, but as<br />
activity picks up so too will employment. But It always takes a while to catch up.<br />
But It will be there, as the economy starts growing as it's now doing, as I believe it<br />
will in the course of this year, employment will come up with it.<br />
J: Would you like to say anything about the death of Sir Robert Muldoon?<br />
PM: I put a statement out. alrcady saying that he was obviously a leadcr of significancc<br />
of the people of New Zealand and for the conservative party in New Zealand, and<br />
he has made a substantial contribution to Nzw Zealand over a period of time, and I<br />
expressed sympathy to his family, and to his party.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
