<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9058</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON. PJ KEATING, MP. ALP NATIONAL EXECUTIVE MEETING, CANBERRA 26 NOVEMBER, 1993</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/11/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009058.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON.<br />
P J KEATING, M. P.<br />
ALP NATIONAL EXECUTI VE MEETING, CANBERRA<br />
26 NOVEMBER, 1993<br />
J So, how do you respond to Conrad Black, Primc Minister?<br />
PM: Well, I responded very well to the last sentence of his piece where he said, " It<br />
will be the Prime Minister's accusers who will end up in trouble here." That's<br />
what he said. See, the clear point in all of this.... there are only two simple<br />
points in this: the first, that the Government has limited Mr Black's ownership<br />
of John Fairfax and Sons to 25 percent, and it did so fouir onths after these<br />
conversations. The other key point is that Mr Black has said that Dr Hewson<br />
promised him unlimited stock in John Fairfax and Sons, that he would remove<br />
restraints on ownership. So, therefore, it is the Government which has said<br />
percent and no further-, it is the Opposition who said, " You can have it. A<br />
foreigner can take control of our major broadsheet newspapers." It's therefore<br />
Dr Ilewson who has the explaining to do and that's why he's now backsliding<br />
on the Senate committee.<br />
J: But how do you explain the discrepancy between your version of the<br />
conversation and Mr Black's?<br />
PM: Well, I explain it by the statement. The Cabinet considered the Treasurer's<br />
submission for 25 percent and put out a statement in April saying the Cabinet<br />
considered the foreign investment questions of ownership of mass circulation<br />
newspapers and decided that the maximum should be 25. percent.<br />
J: Was there any discussion at all of 35 percent?<br />
PM-Yes. From Mr Black.<br />
J: In Cabinet?<br />
PM: No, no. Not in Cabinet, no, no. Mr Black comes into Australia about every<br />
four months, seeks to see me and, I'm sure, the Leader of the Opposition and </p>
<p>others and it's about, basically, getting his stock up. Now, John Hewson<br />
offered him 100 percent. In fact, I attended a lunch of Fairfax executives<br />
where Mr Mulholland was the host and where there was Mike Steketee,<br />
Ross Gittens and others before Christmas. And I told that lunch that Mr<br />
Black had told me that John Hewson would let him go to 100 percent.<br />
Now, if John Hew son doesn't appear before a Senate Comnittee, if Senator<br />
Alston can't persuade Senator Kernot to remove the referen-ce to him, Dr<br />
J-ewson, in the terms of reference, the likelihood is that Dr Hewson won't<br />
appear. And if he doesn't appear it will be because he would fear needing to<br />
perjure himself before the committee where Mr Black has said he's quite happy<br />
to appear.<br />
J: Why do you think Mr Black is claiming that you offered to consider<br />
percent, then?<br />
PM: Well, I don't know and people have fuizzy recollections of these conversations.<br />
I mean, I'e been Prime Minister for nearly two years and Treasurer for nine.-<br />
I've collected conversations with media proprietors like other people collect<br />
stamps. I remember them very well. And I know exactly what I say and<br />
what I said I'd consider we did consider, and the Government considered it<br />
with complete probity at Cabinet level, on a submission by the Treasurer, made<br />
a decision and announced it.<br />
J: Prime Minister, yesterday you were able to use Mr Black's words to<br />
devastating effect against Dr Hewson. Doesn't today's development make Mr<br />
Black, at best, an unreliable witness?<br />
PM: No, no. He said, let me read the part from his book. Mr Black said, " Te<br />
Leader of the Opposition had already promised that if he was elected that he<br />
would remove restraints on our ownership." See, when Dr Hewson says to<br />
you. " We didn't nominate any particular level," he must think you are complete<br />
fools. By not nominating a level he has told Mr Black there is no level. In<br />
other words it's an unconditional decision to let Mr Black go to whatever<br />
control he wishes of John Fairfax and Sons. Now, the Government's position is<br />
on the record and clear. . So there can be no debate about this. We're at<br />
percent, Dr Hewson's up to 100 percent with no specific limit. He said he was<br />
quite relaxed remember Mr Black said, " In agreed phraseology," he and Dr<br />
Hewson agreed what they'd say a fter the meeting and the term was ' quite<br />
relaxed' the Leader of the Opposition was quite relaxed.<br />
You sec, the context you've got to see all of this in is before the last election<br />
where the Leader or the Opposition arrogantly believed he was already Prime<br />
Minister and he's sitting in court receiving foreign visitors, including Mr<br />
Black and swanning around the business community just seeing who he<br />
would entertain or who would entertain him. And Mr Black has said, " Look,<br />
we want control of John Fairfax and Sons and we want you to comply in that,"<br />
and he has said, " Look, I'm very relaxed about that. There's no upper limit as<br />
far as rm concerned." Now, when Mr Black saw me he said, " Dr Hewson's </p>
<p>offiered us virtually unlimited control of the stock," and 1 said, " What, up to<br />
100 percent?" He said, ' Well, up to 100 percent but I don't need 100 percent.<br />
Just over 50 percent will be enough for me, to get control. Now, what about<br />
the Governmnent?" And I said, " Well, just hang on, just step back here. The<br />
Government's got national interest questions and we've always taken the view<br />
that these papers should be controlled by Australians. Now, I accept the fact<br />
that you've got difficulties running the papers at 14.9 percent and well consider<br />
a request for 25 percent." I mean, the Government's position has been<br />
conducted with complete probity whereas Dr Hewson has basically, has just<br />
obviously said, to a foreigner, " L~ ook, you can have control of the Age and the<br />
Sydney Morning Herald and I'm very relaxed about it."<br />
J: So, you're asking people to believe what Conrad Black says about Dr Hewson<br />
but not believe what he says about you?<br />
PM-: No, but I ask you to believe what he also says about me. He says the Prime<br />
Minister's accusers will find, in the end, they are the ones in difficulty.<br />
1: Have Mr Black's comments been unhelpful? is comments published this<br />
morning?<br />
PM. I'm sure they're not unhelpfual to you.<br />
Ends. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
