<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6151</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/07/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006151.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR MEDIA July 4 1983<br />
A Special Task Force on the Status of Women will be established<br />
by the Federal Government.<br />
The Task Force will consist of nine Permanent Heads and the<br />
Chairman of the Public Service Board.<br />
It will involve the Government's most senior advisers and<br />
administrators in consideration of women's interests in the<br />
development and implementation of programs and policies.<br />
Cabinet will receive an annual report from the Task Force on<br />
progress and future priorities.<br />
The members of the Task Force will be the Permanent Heads of<br />
the Departments of Prime Minister and Cabinet ( Chair) Finance,<br />
Attorney-General's, Foreign Affairs, Employment and industrial<br />
Relations, industry and Commerce, Education and Youth Aff1airs,<br />
Social Security, Immigration and Ethnic Affairs and the<br />
Chairman of the Public Service Board.<br />
The establishment of the Task Force was one of the conzit-Lments<br />
made during the election campaign in the ALP's policy on women.<br />
In another move to implement the ALP's policy on women, the<br />
Government has given the office of the Status of Women an<br />
expanded role and extra resources.<br />
The Office will monitor the impact of all Government policies<br />
and activities on women.<br />
It will also co-ordinate the development of specific pol4ies<br />
to raise the status of women.<br />
In accordance with the Government's undertakings these will<br />
include: a range of economic, employment and social policy<br />
proposals of importance to women,<br />
new and improved mechanisms for community consultations~<br />
with women,<br />
a national Women's Emergency program,<br />
an affirmative action program for public and nrivate<br />
employment, sex discrimination legislation, and<br />
ratification of the United Nations Convention on the<br />
Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Wi </p>
<p>2.<br />
The Government has also decided to seek more representation<br />
of women on Government boards, authorities and instrumentalities.<br />
Recent appointments, for example the ABC board, have reflected<br />
the Government's commitment in this area.<br />
1 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
