<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>903</transcript-id>
    <title>NENETEENTH STUDENT SESSION AT THE ADMINISTRATIVE STAFF COLLEGE, MT ELIZA, VICTORIA, 8TH MARCH 1964 - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/03/1964</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000903_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
NINETEENTH STUDENT SESSION AT THE ADMINISTRATIVE<br />
STAFF COLLEGE, MT. EL! ZA VICTORIA<br />
8TH MARCH, 196+<br />
Speech by the Prime Miriter,_ the Rt. Hon. Sir Robert Menzies<br />
Mr. Chairman and Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
The other day, having let myself in for this, I was<br />
interviewed by Charles Booth and Ragnar Garrett and I said to them,<br />
" What do you want me to talk about, because everybody knowsthat<br />
businessmen know all about politics and that politicians know nothing<br />
about business. It seems to me to be an unfair distribution of<br />
virtue, but everybody understands that this is the case."<br />
" But," I said, " there is one thing that I must say<br />
that most businessmen, and, I am almost prepared to think, most<br />
politicians, know nothing about and that is the true problems of<br />
running a federal system of government."<br />
I thought I would like to talk to you a little about<br />
it because, make no mistake, however effective you become in<br />
business administration, you will constantly be barking your shin<br />
against problems of government what government ought to do this<br />
what government has the power over this matter; and what government<br />
has the power over another. This is a problem that bedevils<br />
the scene in Australia. it is very little studied. I wonder how<br />
many people who are here tonight have read the Commonwealth<br />
Constitution in the last ten years? Not too many. Not too many.<br />
I think they do a little more reading of the Constitution in the<br />
United States of America. I am not sure" I think they like to<br />
re-read the Declaration of Independence because there is a fine<br />
bravura quality about it somewhat detached from life but very<br />
exciting. In Great Britain they know nothing about Constitutions;<br />
they have none. They are in a magnificent position. " The<br />
Constitution of England as the great French wit said, " Elle<br />
n'existe point". And it's true. Parliament has all power and<br />
may exercise it. The United States of America has a Federal Constitution<br />
of an orthodox kind. So have we, not inconsiderably modelled on<br />
the American one. Canada has one of a rather different kind but<br />
still it is a Federal system. South Africa has provinces as well<br />
as a inion, but it is not a federation of a country in which no<br />
problems of power in relation to the national government or the<br />
parliament can arise.<br />
Well, the world goes on. In Great Britain and<br />
I've told them this I am not talking hkhind their backs; I made<br />
a powerful speech to them on this across the table at the last<br />
Prime Ministers' Conference. I told them: " I think you gentlemen<br />
have had an immense experience in writing federal constitutions<br />
you know nothing about trying to make one work." And that's true,<br />
because in my own time, as in my current term as Prime Minister,<br />
Itve seen a Federation established in the West Indies and I've seen<br />
it broken up. I've seen a Federation established, the Federation<br />
of Rhodesia and Nyasaland and a few months ago it was broken up.<br />
It resolved into its constituent parts. And it is only a few months<br />
ago, relatively, that we were all meeting about and discussing the<br />
Common Market the European Commrion Market and I was being told<br />
by very distinguished English statesmen: " Of course, wo don't<br />
want to go into a European Federation; what we are contemplating<br />
is a kind of confederation" you see. I said to them, " Yes I<br />
know the meaning of the woras, but do you realise their implications?"<br />
I will say a little nore about that in a momentø So you / 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
see, here we are in Australia with a fcdara2. system a federal<br />
system in wh~ ich power is divided and divided according to a very<br />
precise specification in Section 51 of the Constitution, all the<br />
powers specified going to the Parliament of the Commonwealth, all<br />
ti-xe ones not mentioned remaining with the States, the sovereignty<br />
of Government belonging to the people of Australia and being<br />
exercised as to part, and as to the more important part, of<br />
reality by the Commonwealth Parliament and Government and as to<br />
the residue by the State Parliaments and State Governments.<br />
Now that is a very simple definition of our system<br />
of federation. You will be surprised to know how little<br />
understood it is. It is certainly not understood at all by the<br />
people who were talking rather glibly about a European federation.<br />
As I say, I will come back to that because it is, I think,<br />
interesting. But let us stay on the home ground for a while.<br />
Here we are, we have powers specifically given to<br />
the Commonwealth, enumerated, set out, you may read them all in<br />
Section 51 of the Constitut4on, and the ones that are not there<br />
belong to the States, Indeed, most of those that are there can<br />
be exercised by the States unless the Commonwealth exercises thorn,<br />
because few powers are exclusive to the Commonwealth like customs,<br />
bounties, excise, defence ( for all practical purposas); these<br />
are powers given to the Commonwea2 th exclusively, but all the<br />
other powers or most of the other powers are concurrent powers.<br />
We have a power of taxation. Well, so have the States not at<br />
the moment exercised, but not for constitutional reasons. There<br />
aro a lot of concurrent powers, but the Constitution itsclf<br />
solved that problem by providing that where the Commonwdealth<br />
exorcised a power and made a law in a particular field which was<br />
a valid lathen any State low whiich was inconsistent went by<br />
the board. In other words, it established the paramouLntey of<br />
Commonwealth law on items within Section 51 of the Constitution.<br />
Now, I mention this to you because IL think it ought<br />
to be compulsory reading for all people who aspire to debate<br />
these matters to read Section 51 with some care to see what<br />
powers are given to the Parliament of the nation. If you were<br />
in my place, you would go around Australia, you would receive<br />
representations, deputations of all kinds from people wrho say,<br />
" You know, we are coming to you with thiis, because this is a<br />
matter of great national importance. If it is a matter of<br />
national importance then of course,' 1 the Commonwealth ought to<br />
do something about It," 1 Lnd I say, " Wll, I ama sorry. Our<br />
Constitution doosntt soy that the Commonwealth Parliam. ent is to<br />
have power to pass laws about all matters of national -importance.<br />
It has power to make laws about thtirtyeight specified matters<br />
and no others." They say, " Oh, well, that is a legal quibble."<br />
Now, let's beware of this. This idea that you just make a good<br />
goneralised statement that " this is of great national importance<br />
and therefore you follows in the Commonwealth ought to be doing<br />
something about it", is not only stupid but disastrous. You<br />
know, Itve been in smaall shires in Australia, small towns in<br />
Australia and have had the local worthies say to me, " Look, we<br />
must have a better water supply in this town. It is going to<br />
cost œ C150,000, It's of immense national importance. It will<br />
improve Lthe health of this district and therefore make a contribution<br />
to the health of humian beings in this nation and therefore<br />
to our capacity to defend it in the event of war." Now this is<br />
superb, isntt it? ( Laughter) This is superb, this is the way to<br />
eliminate the Constitution and with it, eliminate all troubles.<br />
Of course, life is not like that, nor is the Constitution.<br />
Now, this is worth thinking about. There is an<br />
awful lot of nonsense talked about the Federal system of v e / 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
Government and a good deal talked in our country. Federalism,<br />
as a great writer once said, is legalism and we can't get away<br />
from it. If you are going to divide by a Constitution the powers<br />
of the national Parliament and the powers of State Parliaments,<br />
then it is quite clear that there must be somebody who will decide<br />
whether the boundaries have been overstepped. If you left it to<br />
the Commonwealth Parliament to say, " Well, in our opinion, our<br />
powers extend to passing this law," then we would have complete<br />
unification in Australia in a generation. Therefore there has<br />
to be an umpire and the umpire is the High Court, just as in the<br />
United States, the umpire is the Supreme Court of the United States.<br />
Its function, or one of its functions, and its most important<br />
function, is to pass on the validity of laws made by the Commonwealth<br />
or made by States in order that these constitutional<br />
boundaries shall not be overlapped. Now this is, I thinkr<br />
inevitable. It gives rise to all sorts of bitter arguments<br />
along lines like this: " What are these people doing? They<br />
are trying to control the progress of events." They're not.<br />
They are just trying to do their duty, just trying to exercise<br />
the judgment that they are bound to exercise as to the validity<br />
of some law made by some Parliament in Australia.<br />
Now, our great-grandfathers or our grandfathers 7as<br />
the case may be, who wrote the Constitution originally, did a<br />
remarkable piece of work. At this point I want to warn you<br />
against another fallacy. Every now and then, I am told by<br />
somebody probably somebody engaged in State politics, and I<br />
was once myself " You know, you are only here, you'ro only in<br />
existence, you the Commonwealth, because we, the States, created<br />
you. We made a bargain with each other and we conceded certain<br />
powers to you and kept the rest to ourselves. You beware."<br />
Well, that is, of course, unhappily untrue. The Constitution of<br />
Australia wasn't made by any of the six Colonial Parliaments at<br />
all. It was the product of a series of popular conventions which<br />
contained in some instances very well known members of State<br />
Parliaments but contained a groat number more people who were,<br />
fortunately for us, well furnished with learning and scholarship<br />
on constitutional matters and they had a great deal of moeeting<br />
and convention; they had two or three referenda in the nineties,<br />
and finally, the people of Australia voted for what some of the<br />
people of Australia not any Colonial Parliament had decided<br />
was a good thing. WIhon the people had voted for it off went<br />
the leaders of the Convention to London to present the new draft<br />
Constitution to the Government of the United Kingdom which then<br />
annexed the Constitution as a schedule to an Act of the Imperial<br />
Parliament, as it then was, and it became law. It became law in<br />
the short run because it was an Act of the Parliament of Great<br />
Britain. It became law, of course in substance, because it was<br />
the act of the people of Australia. It is well to have this in<br />
mind: The sovereignty was in the people; the sovereignty wasn't<br />
in six Colonial Parliamonts, although each of then was a completely<br />
self-governing colony, like the Colony of Victoria,<br />
Now I mention these facts to you because there is<br />
a fallacy which is constantly being promulgated here that you<br />
will come up against time after time and that is that Australia<br />
consists of six sovereign States. I hear this constantly every<br />
time there is a Premiers' Conference. It will be one of the<br />
red-letter days in my life if each Premier doesn't at some stage<br />
utter this piece of nonsense: " Of course, you must remember, we<br />
are a sovereign Stato," So there are six sovereign States;<br />
I don't know where the Conr,-onwenlth cones in because if we have<br />
six sovereign States what sovereignty is loft for the nation.<br />
It's absurd. The sovereignty inures in the nation in the people,<br />
Some of the sovereign powers are exercised by the Coimlonwealth<br />
Parliament and Government; some of the sovereign powers are<br />
0 0 a a 0/ 4 </p>
<p>exercised by the State Parliaments and Governments. Don't let<br />
any of us be under any misapprehension about that matter. There<br />
is a division of sovereign powers and each of us exercises his<br />
bit of sovereignty within the limits of the Constitution of the<br />
nation. I don't know how long it is since you gave yourself<br />
the pleasure of reading about the events that led up to the<br />
American Civil War, but they are very well worthwhile recalling<br />
in this field. When I was a boy, I thought the Civil War was<br />
about " Uncle Tom's Cabin" you know, that sort of thing......<br />
and the good man and the bad man and some little wretch being<br />
taken over the ice on the river, You know, it was a terrific<br />
affair, " Uncle Tom's Cabin", and peGple were brought up to<br />
believe that this was the whole outfit about which the American<br />
Civil War was fought. It wasn't. The Southern States in the<br />
United States took a very strong view that they weren't going<br />
to be dominated by what they regarded as the hard-faced<br />
professionals from the North and therefore they tended to be,<br />
in a very acute sense, " states righters", as we would say, and<br />
they would keep on saying, " But we are sovereign States." The<br />
very phrases were used.<br />
And they had the view that if they didn't like what<br />
the North was doing it might be on Negro emancipation it<br />
might be on anything, and they didn't like it then all they<br />
had to do was to secede because, being sovereign, they could<br />
exercise their own sovereignty by departing from the Union.<br />
You see? This was a very widely-held doctrine0 This was the<br />
doctrine about which Lincoln conducted his famous debates and<br />
which he challenged and ultimately defeated. Are we all<br />
sovereign? May we secede? And the answer to that was: No.<br />
Your sovereignty is now merged in the sovereignty of the<br />
Federation. You are not able to secede. You can't restore your<br />
own sovereignty by your own act. This Federation is a compact<br />
which binds everybody, and therefore this is an indissoluble<br />
Federation. In our turn, we said so. You may see it in the<br />
preamble to the Commonwealth Constitution " one indissoluble<br />
Federation". But in America, it hadn't been so stated; but<br />
essentially, of course, if the Federation were to mean anything,<br />
to have any existence and any future in the world and any<br />
service to the people, it had to be indissoluble and that was<br />
what the Civil War was about basically, that was what it was<br />
about. A very great Englishman named Bryce who wrote what<br />
is still the classical book on American Federation he wrote<br />
it back in the nineties, quite true, but he wrote it with full<br />
knowledge of all the events leading up to the Civil War<br />
pointed out that what the Civil War really achieved was to<br />
settle this argument once and for all and to establish quite<br />
plainly that the sovereignty was the sovereignty of the nati. on<br />
and that no State was sovereign in the sense that it could<br />
conduct its own affairs to the point at which it seceded.<br />
The State of Western Australia in a rather frolicsome<br />
moment what, how many years ago? had a Secession Movement.<br />
Well, it was good clean fun and, you know. it did no harm.<br />
They carried a referendum to secede from the Commonwealth and<br />
then the next time there was an amendment out to increase the<br />
powers of the Commonwealth Parliament, my good friends in<br />
Western Australia and I admire them for it voted for it,<br />
( Laughter) This is very satisfactory: Well, we would like to<br />
be out, but if we can't be out, we would like you boys to have<br />
0 0 </p>
<p>more power. The secessionists carried their case to the House<br />
of Lords. Well, it was quite hopcless, I was in London at that<br />
tine and, really there was nothing to argue about. It had long<br />
since been established that there is no sovereignty in that sense<br />
in some part of a federation nor is there any right to secede<br />
from the total body. And its important to remember that.<br />
I recalled it, to my own satisfaction at any rate<br />
when I was in London last year or was it the year before? Ilve<br />
forgotten now discussing the Common Market..... Now, of<br />
course, the Common Market argument ran high and hot and had a<br />
variety of aspects. I don't want to talk to you about the<br />
economic aspects of it because they have been canvassed to and<br />
fro all round the world. But one of the things that became<br />
involved in this was that I think at least five of the Continental<br />
countries were looking forward to having a European Federation.<br />
Le Grande Charles doesn't believe in it. ( Laughter) He said with<br />
great vigour that this was to be an association of people, an<br />
association of States, but it was not to be a federation. And<br />
he was right from my point of view, as a matter of intellectual<br />
reasoning, to deliver his veto.<br />
I've not the slightest doubt that he was right, and<br />
I tried to make this understood in London. I said, " You keep<br />
on telling me that you don't want to be in a federation but you<br />
want to be in a confederation in other words, you want a fairly<br />
loose association of States but you want to have a few things<br />
established at the centre about which you agree a common code<br />
on so-and-so, certain tariff rules which apply to everybody, a<br />
very considerable bureaucracy in the middle which deals with a<br />
mass of economic and sometimes legal and sometimes financial<br />
matters this is what you want, and you think that that means<br />
that no problem of a federation arises, but I am bound to tell<br />
you this, or remind you of this, that there is no example in<br />
history, in modern history of a confederation which didn't either<br />
break up into its constituent parts or become a federation, with<br />
the consequent loss of sovereignty in the constituent members<br />
I don't want to be too technical about it but this was vastly<br />
important. The same Bryce pointed this out in words that are<br />
quite modern, sixty or seventy years ago, that in a federation<br />
itself there are two impulses going on we see them in Australia.<br />
We've all seen them. Whether consciously or unconsciously, we<br />
all know a great deal about them. There is the centrifugal<br />
force tending to drive them apart I haven't seen that operate<br />
so much in Australia and the centripetal force that brings<br />
more and more centralisation of authority and centralisation of<br />
power, so that unless we all watch it, some day it will produce<br />
complete unification. And there is no escape from this. No<br />
confederation, no association of states in the history of the<br />
world ever stood still. It will become closer or it will become<br />
more remoteo We've seen it become more remote in the West Indies<br />
very quickly so that there is no federation there at all today.<br />
We've seen this separatist idea, the centrifugal force, operate<br />
so swiftly in the case of the African countries that Nyasaland is<br />
now an independent country Northern Rhodesia, Southern Rhodesia<br />
still have some vastly complex problems to deal with.<br />
And in the case of Europe, this must have been the<br />
same thing. This puzzles me. I couldn't make them appreciate the<br />
fact that once they cor. mitted themselves to something that was<br />
organic, something that was structural in their relations with<br />
European countries, however valuable a lot of arrangements of a </p>
<p>6-<br />
practical kind, a pragmnatic apprcach might be, that the moment<br />
they went in for anything structural, they would find that they<br />
were well on the move to having a Europe. an Federation,<br />
Now, it may be a very good thing to have a European<br />
Federation. I don't sit in judgment on that matter. This is<br />
not my immediate business. All I want to say is that if there<br />
is a European Federation, Great Britain won't be a sovereign<br />
State any more than Victoria is in Australia for the reasons that<br />
I have given you. It will be a constituent member of a highly<br />
legal structure in which there is a division of sovereignty<br />
according to the rules set out in the agreement and therefore<br />
it would be, I thought, rather hard to have Great Britain as a<br />
non-sovereign state but as a member of the European Federation,<br />
coming along to have conferences with soy, Ghana, as a fully<br />
self-governing state, Similarly with Pakistan, India, Australia,<br />
New Zealand Canada and Great Britain the only non-sovereign<br />
body. It didn't appeal to me very much.<br />
And of course the answer always was: But of course,<br />
that's the last thing we want and that's the last thing we are<br />
after. To which the reply had to be: But how do you know whoere<br />
you can stop the process, because if you establish what De Gaulle<br />
calls the " association of nations", " the society of nations", it<br />
will either become closer and begin to look awfully like a<br />
federation or it will grow more remote and Europe will go back<br />
into the old whirlpool of historical hostility. And do you<br />
know let justice be done the great De Gaulle...., it is always<br />
possible and in fact sometimes agreeable to disagree with him about<br />
tkiis or that arnd he is not one of the great constitutional<br />
scholars of Lhe world, but he is a very great man and he has<br />
seen with completely clear instinct that if he wants France to<br />
be a great powerful independent nation, restoring its glories in<br />
the Western world he can't allow it to become a mere province in<br />
a larger organisazion, He is quite happy about having Italy and<br />
the Benelux countries coming along and playing along, getting<br />
together for economic purposes, financial purposes but for'<br />
political purposes, for anything tb~ at will impair the sovereignty<br />
of France no. In other words: I think he is one of the<br />
statesmen in Europe who has understood that the federal idea<br />
produces problems which can't be solved by a few casual remarks<br />
in an armchair, which have to be studied, which have to be<br />
experienced so that you not only know them in theory as I have<br />
had to know them as a lawyer, but as I have had to know them by<br />
touch, in having to deal with the particular problems that emerge.<br />
You know, on the whole, I think that Australia has<br />
managed its federal system pretty well. I think there is a good<br />
deal of nonsense talked of a " states rights" kind. I have said<br />
something about that -that it iJs " flim flam" and by the way.<br />
But on the whole we happen to have managed the business in<br />
Australia by doing one or two sensible things, one of them quite<br />
illicit. Shall I tell you about the illicit one first? Yes,<br />
I knew that would have an instant appeal to you, you captains<br />
of industry, ( Laughter)<br />
Now here is a great continent in which all the highest<br />
concentration of development is down here in Victoria or over there<br />
in New South Wales or now, to an increasing extent, in the south<br />
of South Australia yet also in which up North, where you have<br />
so many growing things, are the large beginnings of what will be<br />
an immensely larger mineral industry in all its forms. Northern<br />
development is more than a political cliche; it is something<br />
that represents one of the great problems in Australia. How can<br />
the people who live, and live well and prosperously in one<br />
relatively small section of Australia do something to increase a<br />
a v o 9 */ 7 </p>
<p>7-<br />
development elsewhere? Now, you, m-, ay say to me7 " Well1 obviously<br />
something ought ' G to be don( 3, somctinrg ought to be done to give<br />
an incentive ( thatl tho nodorn. word) t11o people to go and<br />
adventure their capit~ al in the north and go into those remote<br />
places and look for minerals a nd search for oil and do all these<br />
things, that are wonderful things for this country,," And of'<br />
course the incentive obviously is to make some discrimination in<br />
their income tax.<br />
People say to me-. " Why? Why don't you relieve of'<br />
all tax people who are earning their income beyond a certain<br />
parallel in the country?" And I say, " A jolly good idea, but<br />
grandfather didn't think so." Because grandfather put into the<br />
Constitution a provision that no law may be made by the Commonwealth<br />
of taxation or briefly, of money, which discriminates<br />
between one State and another or between one part of' a State and<br />
another. You can imagine the old gentlemen doing it, canv't you?<br />
They sit down there. They've got six reluctant colonies who<br />
think that on the whole 1. t wouldn't be a bad idea to have<br />
Federation. Not flogged into it by a war, as the United States<br />
was by the War of' Independence but a conscious effort of reason<br />
and persuasion. But, at the same time, they wore all colonies.<br />
Down in Victoria, of coursa, we are the broadestminded<br />
of people, and I am perfectly certain of their saying,<br />
" Well, of course, we are going to get mixed up with those scomps<br />
across the Murray; we must be very careful; we must preserve<br />
ourselves as far as we can. And you get some of these rather odd<br />
provisions, in the Constitution about uniformity, It's uniformity<br />
mad. We are uniformity mad in Australia. Unless somebody gets<br />
exactly the same deal as somebody who lives 2,000 miles away, there<br />
is something wrong, This is awful nonsense.<br />
This is a country which can be developed only by<br />
encouraging the unorthodox, by encouraging non-conformity, by<br />
encouraging inequality I don't mean to the point of injustice<br />
for that is a different matter. But why should everything have<br />
to be ironed out in this fashion. But they did it, and therefore<br />
we cannot, by a taxation law, provide a rate of tax in Queensland,<br />
in the Commonwealth which is not to apply equally all over<br />
Australia. And in legal truth I don't want this to be used<br />
agdnst me if it comes before the High Court as it will no doubtwe<br />
can't apply a rate of taxation north of lownsville which is<br />
smaller than the rate of taxation south of Townsville, all other<br />
things being equal, because of this wonderful anti-discrimination<br />
provision in the Constitution. So all I can say is, that it was<br />
done by the Commonwealth Zone A, Zone B and there are many<br />
happy or unhappy taxpayers in the north of Western Australia, in<br />
the Northern Territory in the north of Queensland who secure an<br />
advantage from this,, Ll I want to say is, I think it is quite<br />
illegal. We have rested on the very com., fortable proposition -that<br />
nobody outside of an asylum is likely to challenge it,, ( Laughter)<br />
But now, that is just a single example of what I am<br />
really getting at over this matter9 in that I believe that a<br />
national Government could do far more for the development of<br />
these parts of Australia, crying aloudfbi' development, if it had<br />
eqbcate powers of discrimination and were not bound by these rather<br />
antiquated ideas that you must have uniformity and that means that<br />
whatever the law is9 it has to be the same at Weipa as it would<br />
be at Mount Gambier, This is very foolish, looking at it with the eye of<br />
history and certainly foolish if one tries to look at it with<br />
anything like the eye of statesmanship, But I mention it to you </p>
<p>8<br />
because a lot of people will say to you Why don't they do<br />
so-and-. so7 Wñ y-donyt : Loy dc sometiliirg aboit -it? ' Jall, if they<br />
had had to sit down as frequently as I 11ave had to do and say,<br />
" By Jove, I would like to do so-ar d-so,, I think this is a splendid<br />
idea. How can we work this one out so as to dodge the Constitution?"<br />
This is a health-~ giving exercise0 I don~ t have any objection to<br />
it, I think it is a highly moral. undertaking, not irmoral, After<br />
all, mest people I think dodge as much income tax as they can and<br />
as long as it is within the law it is right, but it is a great<br />
pity. I think that rmore and more, as we go on, we will be<br />
thinking about our constitutional powers -not in relation to a<br />
lot of these matters that get discussed on political platforms,<br />
most of which I can assure you are completely trivial from the<br />
constitutional point of view and trying to make a Federal system<br />
with its written Constitution flexible enough to serve the<br />
interests of a country that is growing at almost an explosive rate.<br />
This is the great problem of federal governrment. I've had a long<br />
experience of it. Ilve seen it from both sides, In a manner of<br />
speaking, I suppose I have got sorme expert knowledge on this<br />
matter and I still find it one of the most teasing things in the<br />
world, I will just add one thing because time goes on,<br />
I have to be in Sydney tomorrow. We have a meoting next week of.<br />
the Loan Council. The Loan Council consists of the State Treasurers<br />
who are usually the State Premiers and the Commonwealth Treasurer<br />
who is the Chairman, and I attend and by an act of grace on the<br />
part of the others who attend, I am allowed to speak when I vwant<br />
to. That is the Loan Council. The Loan Council. was set up under<br />
the Financial Agreement and the Financial Agreement was authorised<br />
by one of the -few ameondments ever made to the Commonwealth<br />
Constitution. The Loan Council was established to do one thing,<br />
one thing only, There had been great confusion up to that time<br />
New South Wales was borrowing at 5J per cent, and some ether'<br />
State wanted to borrow at per cent. Well, there was a great<br />
deal of conflict and competition in the markets and then if one<br />
State looked as if it might default, this affected the credit of<br />
the other States who wanted to raise money on the market. This<br />
became a terrible problem, particularly as we had one or two rather<br />
adventurous State Premiers in those days. And so the Financial<br />
Agreement was made and the Loan Council established,, And the<br />
function of the Lean Council is to decide how much mioney can be<br />
borrowed for a public works programme, how much money can be<br />
borrowed at reasonable rates and conditions. That's all,<br />
In the old days when the Lean Council decided that,<br />
the meeting adjourned with suitable compliments. When I was first<br />
a member of the Commonwealth Goverrnment, I was Attorney General,<br />
I used to attend the Loan Council meetings I don't knew in what<br />
capacity. Still there it was, and in looking back on it now, it<br />
is hilariously funny. This is back in 1935-6-7-8, you know,-not<br />
all that long ago, The Commonwealth Bank used to underwrite the<br />
loan programme, And the Commonwealth would get from the States<br />
what their estimates were and their loan works programme. As a<br />
rule, it was about œ 19M, or 20M1. for the whole lot and,<br />
metaphorically though not actually, the Commonwealth Bank sat with<br />
a Governor who was in the corner of the room and the Premiers<br />
would have a magnificent debate and beat it up by half a million,<br />
It might be œ_ 19 then it must be Z20M and then somebody got a<br />
run on and thought it ought to be œ C22M because his State wanted<br />
miore and then the Prime Minister, Mr, Lyons, would say, " Well01,<br />
letts adjourn for half an hour" and you would go around the corner,<br />
so to speak, and have a word Lind come back and say, " lNo, the 0 0. 6./ 9 </p>
<p>-9-<br />
banks will underwrite œ 20CMo" And œ 20CM. it was. And everybody<br />
went away, Th. e money was in his pocket because it was underwritten<br />
by the central banks.,<br />
Well, of course, today we talk in programmnos at<br />
Loan Council meetings of about œ 300M. and they are always too<br />
snall, so I gather. But we don't sit down now and say how much<br />
money can be borrowed on reasonable rates and conditions because<br />
until the last two years that would have meant that we would have<br />
decided that the limit was œ 60M, or œ 70M. because that was about<br />
what the market would yield over a period of years œ 80M. perhaps,<br />
sometimes a œ 100M. with a bit of luck, and we developed a new<br />
techniqueo We, the Commonwealth want now to satisfy ourselves<br />
that in physical terms the performance of the loan works programme<br />
is a feasible one and if that cones out at œ 300M. and if our<br />
estimate of what the loan market will produce is œ 150M., then<br />
we have got into the habit of saying, " Well, we think you need<br />
this programme, we think that these works must be done for the<br />
purposes of economic development and we will therefore raise what<br />
we can on the market and we will supplement the market return out<br />
of the Commonwealth Budget. We will advance the money to you to<br />
make up the short fallo" This honourable occupation, painful<br />
occupation, ran us up over a period of about ten years to<br />
something over œ 600 or œ 700M, and it is one of the beauties of a<br />
federal system that having done this, having either stepped up<br />
the taxation or jacked up the taxation in order to provide these<br />
vast sums of money, I was always able to attend something or other<br />
and hear my State colleagues denouncing the Commonwealth for its<br />
miserable attitude towards taxation and demanding that it be<br />
reduced, ( Laughter) I don't know whether that's a warning to<br />
business managers in esse or a warning to politicians in posse<br />
( Laughter) but it applies equally to both. These are complex<br />
matters. I think that it is remarkable how far accommodation<br />
has been worked out so that the strict letter of the Constitution<br />
hasn't prevented certain really material economic development.<br />
That's one of them. The Loan Council business has been made to<br />
work for the good of Australia though it is quite different from<br />
the one which was established by constitutional authority. It<br />
is not illegal but it is a voluntary affair, and it works, and it<br />
works to the good of the people of Australia.<br />
But don't let it be thought and don't let it be<br />
said that every problem which crops up in Australia is one which,<br />
because of its importance to somebody is one that belongs to the<br />
Federal Government or Parliament because I am a very great<br />
believer in the Federal system. I believe in the division of<br />
power. Butyoucan't really be an understanding, intelligent, devoted<br />
federalist unless you know what the federal system is, unless: you<br />
know that there is a division of power, that there are some things<br />
that a government may do one government and some things that<br />
it can't. And I think that if we increasingly clarify our minds<br />
on that, we will have less confusion, get rid of a lot of avoidable<br />
bad temper and irritation and sometimes hatred by realising that<br />
we are all the servants of the one sovereignty and of the one<br />
people, that each of us has his allotted task to do and ought to<br />
do it within the rules laid down for playing of the game,<br />
Now, Sir, I have spoken too long, I am going to leave<br />
after a little while and go to bed and make a powerful speech, I<br />
hope, to the graziers in Sydney tomorrow. Therefore, I will shut<br />
up and sit down, but if anybody has a simple question that he thinks<br />
I can answer I will be glad to have a shot at it. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
