<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>19395</transcript-id>
    <title>Australia To Engage Civil Society As G20 President In 2014</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/06/2013</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Perth</p>
<p>The Australian Government is very pleased to announce that the Reverend Tim Costello AO will chair the Australian Civil Society 20 (C20) Steering Group.</p>
<p>The Australian Government is strongly committed to ensuring that G20 deliberations in Australia next year are fully informed by the expertise and knowledge of civil society.</p>
<p>The benefits of economic growth must reach everyone, especially the most disadvantaged in our community. We must build a strong global economy that leaves nobody behind, and places jobs and growth at its core. </p>
<p>The Australian C20 will help the G20 to do this by gathering the views of civil society from across the globe and convening a C20 summit to develop recommendations for G20 leaders' consideration.</p>
<p>The Group will also include 13 Australians who are leaders in their field:</p>
<p>·         Mr Joseph Assaf AM  -  Ethnic Business Awards</p>
<p>·         Ms Jody Broun  -  National Congress of Australia's First Peoples</p>
<p>·         Reverend Tara Curlewis  -  National Council of Churches in Australia</p>
<p>·         Dr Cassandra Goldie  -  Australian Council of Social Service</p>
<p>·         Ms Julie McKay  -  UN Women Australia</p>
<p>·         Professor Rob Moodie  -  Melbourne School of Population and Global Health</p>
<p>·         Mr Dermot O'Gorman  -  World Wide Fund for Nature Australia</p>
<p>·         Mr Marc Purcell  -  Australian Council for International Development</p>
<p>·         Mr Bill Scales AO  -  Swinburne University of Technology</p>
<p>·         Ms Sally Sinclair  -  National Employment Services Association</p>
<p>·         Judge Rauf Soulio  -  Australian Multicultural Council</p>
<p>·         Dr Helen Szoke  -  Oxfam Australia</p>
<p>·         Mr Greg Thompson  -  Transparency International Australia</p>
<p>This year, Rev Costello and the C20 Steering Group will be engaging with Australian civil society, working closely with their counterparts in the C20 during Russia's presidency, and developing a process that will facilitate effective and productive engagement between civil society and G20 leaders in 2014. </p>
<p>The C20 must be civil society-owned and civil society-led.  While the Government will work closely with the C20 Steering Group on matters of process, the C20's input to G20 deliberations will be independent.</p>
<p>The C20 is one of a number of groups that will ensure that business, labour, civil society, youth and think tanks can contribute effectively to Australia's G20 presidency.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
