<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11490</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER            THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP            DOORSTOP INTERVIEW, FAIRBAIRN AIRPORT                     Subject: Labor&amp;#146;s tax position.</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/02/2000</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...............................................................................................</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Beazley says his tax policy is all aimed at alleviating the tax burden</p>
<p> on Australian families.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>That's why he won't rule out lifting income tax on Australian</p>
<p> families. And this morning we have this new report that the Labor Party</p>
<p> is looking at axing the health insurance rebate. Well I call on Mr Beazley</p>
<p> to guarantee that any government he leads would keep that rebate. Axing</p>
<p> the rebate would be a savage tax increase for 32% of the Australian population.</p>
<p> Many people who have private health insurance are elderly Australians,</p>
<p> self-funded retirees, people who regard private health insurance as a</p>
<p> very valuable safety net.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>And what does this whole tax debate say about Mr Beazley's leadership?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I think he's been very weak. He was bullied by the States into</p>
<p> giving an undertaking about the roll-back. He now faces the dilemma that</p>
<p> he can't get out of, that you can't be all things to all men.</p>
<p> You can't say you're going to roll-back the GST, tell the States</p>
<p> they won't be worse off, keep a budget surplus, and not lift income</p>
<p> tax. Now it's just impossible. And if Mr Beazley had been stronger</p>
<p> he would have resisted the bullying attempts of the State Labor leaders.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>No ticker?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>See you later.</p>
<p>[Ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
