<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3982</transcript-id>
    <title>MR WHITLAM&#039;S ADDRESS</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/11/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003982.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MI[ NI[ STER ,75A1/ l7l<br />
PRMIMEI NISTER 20th NOVEMBER 1975<br />
MR WHITLAM'S ADDRESS<br />
MR WHITLAM HAS AGAIN TRIED TO SUGGEST THAT AUSTRALIA'S<br />
PROBLEMS ARE CAUSED BY EVENTS THAT HAVE OCCURRED<br />
OVERSEAS. HE IGNORES THE REPORT OF HIS OWN TREASURY AND WHICH WAS<br />
ATTACHED TO MR HAYDEN'S BUDGET SPEECHAN AUGUST.<br />
THIS REPORT INDICATED THAT. AUSTRALIA'S ECONOMIC. PROBLEMS<br />
WERE BASICALLY CAUSED IN AUSTRALIA BY HIS GOVERNMEBT.<br />
MR WHITLAM IGNORES ALSO THE REPORT OF THE INTERNATIONAL<br />
MONETARY FUND AND THE ORGANISATION FOR ECONOMIC.<br />
CO-OPERATION-AND DEVELOPMENT WHICH AGREED THAT OUR<br />
ECONOMIC PROBLEMS WERE MADE IN AUSTRALIA.<br />
MR WHITLAM IGNORES. THE FACT THAT INFLATION AROUND THE WORLD<br />
WAS CAUSED BY A THREE HUNDRED PER CENT. INCREASE* IN THE<br />
PRICE OF OIL WHICH AUSTRALIA DID NOT SUFFER BECAUSE OF THE<br />
EXPLORATION. POLICIES PURSUED UNDER A LIBERAL/ NATIONAL COUNTRY<br />
PARTY GOVERNMENT. </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTERa<br />
MR WHITLAM IGNORES THE FACT THAT DURING THE FIRST 72 YEARS<br />
OF FEDERAL GOVERNMENT NATIONAL EXPENDITURE REACHED ONLY<br />
THE ANNUAL FIGURE OF TEN THOUSAND MILLION DOLLARS, BUT<br />
THAT DURING THE THREE YEARS OF HIS ADMINISTRATION IT<br />
MORE THAN DOUBLED TO TWENTY-TWO THOUSAND. MILLION DOLLARS.<br />
THESE FIGURES ARE ALMOST BEYOND THE COMPREHENRION OF<br />
SORDINARY PEOPLE.<br />
BUT THIS INCREASE IN EXPENDITURE IS WHAT HAS . CAUSE<br />
AUSTRALIA'S PROBLEMS OF INFLATION AND UNEMPLOYMENT,<br />
IT IS BECAUSE OF THIS INCREASE THAT SCHOOL LEAVERS THIS YEAR<br />
WILL NOT BE ABLE TO FIND JOBS AND THAT PEOPLE GRADUATING<br />
FROM UNIVERSITIES AND COLLEGES WILL NOT BE ABLE TO USE THEIR<br />
SKILLS. MR WHITLAM HAS ATTRIBUTED AUSTRALIA'S ECONOMIC FAILURES<br />
TO HIS FIRST TREASURER MR CREAN, TO TREASURY ADVICE,<br />
TO RISING WAGES, AND TO DR CAIRNS HIS SECOND TREASURER.<br />
MR WHITLAM IS CONSISTENT IN TRYING TO PRETEND THAT HE IS<br />
INNOCENT OF THE SINS OF HIS GOVERNMENT AND CONSISTENT IN<br />
ALWAYS TRYING TO LAY THE BLAME ON SOMBODY ELSE.<br />
HOW COULD ANYONE BELIEVE MR WHITLAM'S CLAIM TONIGHT THAT<br />
UNEMPLOYMENT WILL GO TO ONE MILLION UNDER OUR GOVERNMENT 0* 0 I<br />
3<br />
SI J<br />
ij, i' f,:<br />
. I it" r. l.<br />
-2 ; iL<br />
-v_ </p>
<p>A PRIME MINISTER<br />
UNDER LIBERAL-NATIONAL COUNTRY PARTY GOVERNMENT, AUSTRALIA<br />
ENJOYED THE HIGHEST EMPLOYMENT AND THE LOWEST INFLATION IN<br />
OUR HISTORY.<br />
MR WHITLAM WAS PRIME MINISTER WHEN UNEMPLOYMENT<br />
HIGHEST LEVEL SINCE THE GREAT DEPRESSION. HE<br />
MINISTER WHEN INFLATION ROSE TO RECORD LEVELS.<br />
RESPONSIBLE. REACHED ITS<br />
WAS PRIME<br />
HE IS </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
