<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11160</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                   THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                   RADIO INTERVIEW                 FRAN KELLY - RADIO NATIONAL, ABC</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/06/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE....................................................</p>
<p>KELLY:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, Pauline Hanson has again accused Aboriginal Australians</p>
<p> of getting preferential treatment in Government funding. She says</p>
<p> she'll campaign against the existence of native title and she has</p>
<p> warned that Aboriginal Australians and the United Nations are plotting</p>
<p> to establish taxpayer funded Aboriginal states. Are these sentiments</p>
<p> racist?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I've read the speech she made last night and I've got to say</p>
<p> it is not only an inaccurate, dishonest speech, but it verges on the</p>
<p> deranged in various places. I said all along that whenever she says</p>
<p> something that is wrong or against the interests of Australia I will</p>
<p> attack it. And in a sense she has done the political debate in Australia</p>
<p> a great service by delivering the speech because she has actually</p>
<p> put down in black and white, in writing, her views, rather than relying</p>
<p> on a series of one-liners and nudges and winks and inferences and</p>
<p> general attitudes. And what she says about this United Nations declaration</p>
<p> is wrong on four counts. Firstly, it's a draft declaration, is therefore</p>
<p> not legally binding. It's not a treaty. Secondly, the Australian Government</p>
<p> has not conspired as she suggests to keep it secret from the Australian</p>
<p> public. If she had bothered to turn up to Parliament more frequently</p>
<p> than she does, she would have known that one of the first things my</p>
<p> Government did was to introduce an open, accountable treaty making</p>
<p> process. We require treaties to be tabled in Parliament. We require</p>
<p> a far more open process. We have, as a Government, significant reservations</p>
<p> about this draft declaration. We have not approved it. We are not</p>
<p> in the business of trying to tear the heart out of the Australian</p>
<p> nation. It is not....to be involving the United Nations discussion</p>
<p> is not a treacherous sell-out of the Australian people. Now, you ask</p>
<p> me is it racist. The strict definition of a racist is somebody who</p>
<p> believes that his or her race is superior to other races. Now, what</p>
<p> she is doing, of course, is, I think, on this particular issue and</p>
<p> what she said in this speech is appealing to irresponsible racist</p>
<p> sentiment in the Australian community. It is a very irresponsible</p>
<p> speech and the more it is analysed the more reason there will be for</p>
<p> people not supporting her.</p>
<p>KELLY:</p>
<p>So she is racist in this context?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I've said, I mean, she is fanning racist sentiment. Now, let's</p>
<p> not sort of, I mean, you and I had a discussion about the definition</p>
<p> of a racist before we came on air and I think we agree that a racist,</p>
<p> strictly speaking, is somebody who believes one race is superior to</p>
<p> another. But by using this sort of language she is, I believe, appealing</p>
<p> to racist sentiment. And can I also take the opportunity of saying</p>
<p> that I saw an observation by Richard Court in the paper this morning</p>
<p> that one of the problems is that there's been a vacuum left by the</p>
<p> failure of the Senate to pass the Native Title Amendment Act. If our</p>
<p> Native Title Bill had been passed by the Democrats and the minority</p>
<p> parties and the Labor Party in the Senate, this native title issue</p>
<p> would now be off the national agenda. And it wouldn't be possible</p>
<p> for people like Mrs Hanson to run around Australia saying that native</p>
<p> title is going to lead to taxpayer funded Aboriginal states within</p>
<p> Australia. Now I mean that is just plain hysterical nonsense.</p>
<p>KELLY:</p>
<p>Okay, if it's hysterical nonsense, if it's a deranged account and</p>
<p> if she is fanning racist sentiment, will you now declare that the</p>
<p> Federal Liberal Party will not give her any preferential treatment</p>
<p> when it comes to preferences?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look Fran, I have said on that issue that that will be dealt with</p>
<p> in the normal processes of the Party and I am not going to say any</p>
<p> more. I would remind you, however, that at the last election the Labor</p>
<p> Party, in my seat of Bennelong and in Mr Beazley's seat of Brand,</p>
<p> gave Australians Against Further Immigration, who have now in Victoria</p>
<p> merged with One Nation to form a single party, gave preferences to</p>
<p> that party ahead of the Liberal Party. What the Labor Party has done</p>
<p> in relation to the preference issue is to adopt a stunt and to elevate</p>
<p> it into a huge national issue. Now, parties from time immemorial,</p>
<p> major parties, have allocated preferences towards the end of their</p>
<p> ticket in a fairly hit-or-miss fashion. You know that and so does</p>
<p> Mr Beazley.</p>
<p>KELLY:</p>
<p>Isn't it a bit different here because what we see is One Nation with</p>
<p> a big block of votes, for instance, in this Queensland election?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Fran, I will deal with the, if I may, we're in the middle of this</p>
<p> Queensland election. I will deal with the Federal electoral implications</p>
<p> of preference allocation at the right time.</p>
<p>KELLY:</p>
<p>But at the moment in the middle of the Queensland election you are</p>
<p> not uncomfortable with the fact that some One Nation candidates may</p>
<p> be elected with the help of Liberal and National Party preferences?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I don't believe that will happen. I am certainly not uncomfortable</p>
<p> with the stance that the Queensland Coalition has taken in the Queensland</p>
<p> election campaign. Their enemy is the Labor Party and I take the opportunity</p>
<p> of saying to a lot of decent people who might be thinking of voting</p>
<p> for One Nation because they may feel economically insecure. If you</p>
<p> go ahead and do so you would be voting for a party whose leader has</p>
<p> a very, very flimsy grasp on reality in relation to certain issues,</p>
<p> is prepared to deliberately misrepresent the position of my Government.</p>
<p> When she talks about native title she has missed the large number</p>
<p> of Parliamentary debates on native title and if our position on native</p>
<p> title which was a moderate, middle-of-the-road position. We are prepared</p>
<p> to give certainty to Australian farmers and pastoralists and indeed,</p>
<p> if our position on native title had been adopted months ago by the</p>
<p> Senate this would no longer be a major issue in Australian politics</p>
<p> and the people who have got to carry the major responsibility for</p>
<p> it still being on the agenda are the Australian Labor Party, the Australian</p>
<p> Democrats and others in the Senate who have voted our compromise bill</p>
<p> down, I mean, what they have done is to create the opportunity for</p>
<p> the sort of speech that was made last night to be made.</p>
<p>KELLY:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, just before we move off this issue, yesterday you welcomed</p>
<p> ex-ABC broadcaster Rod Henshaw as the new Liberal Candidate for the</p>
<p> Federal Seat of Dickson. Last night Pauline Hanson said that Rod Henshaw</p>
<p> compered the launch of One Nation in Ipswich and shared a lot of her</p>
<p> views. Are people who share her views welcome candidates for the Liberal</p>
<p> Party?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I understand that Rod Henshaw at the time was a paid broadcaster MC.</p>
<p>KELLY:</p>
<p>Does that make it all right?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Hang on, let me finish. He's also, as I understand, compered four</p>
<p> occasions or award nights for Wayne Goss. He's done some work for</p>
<p> Kim Beazley. He told my office that her observation about his sharing</p>
<p> her views on a lot of issues was rubbish but if you want to know Rod</p>
<p> Henshaw's views, I am quite happy, as a former ABC broadcaster he</p>
<p> would be delighted to be interviewed by you.</p>
<p>KELLY:</p>
<p>If I could just move onto tax now, Prime Minister. On the one hand</p>
<p> your promise to never, ever introduce a GST had a shelf life of three</p>
<p> years, or one term of Parliament. Why should voters think that your</p>
<p> latest promise, that the rate of a GST will not rise, should have</p>
<p> a life any longer than that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well Fran, I am putting my position in front of the Australian people</p>
<p> before an election. There can be no more open, transparent way to</p>
<p> conduct public affairs in this country, to say, this is our policy,</p>
<p> if you like it vote for it, if you don't, vote against it. There is</p>
<p> all the world of difference between that and what the Labor Party</p>
<p> did in 1993 when they promised not to introduce a GST before the election,</p>
<p> and after the election they introduced their own version of a GST.</p>
<p> I mean, are you seriously saying that somebody can never change their</p>
<p> mind?</p>
<p>KELLY:</p>
<p>No, what I am saying is I understand that.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I am glad you acknowledge that people are entitled to change their</p>
<p> mind.</p>
<p>KELLY:</p>
<p>But won't voters then also be led to think now that you might change</p>
<p> your mind about the rate of a GST?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No they won't, because they will know that if I do have a change of</p>
<p> mind about anything, and I certainly, I am obviously referring to</p>
<p> the promises I made before 1996, I will put that change to the public</p>
<p> but my position simply is this, Fran, that we are going to the next</p>
<p> election with a detailed tax reform policy and that detailed tax reform</p>
<p> policy will be out in the open. If people like it, they can vote for</p>
<p> it. If they don't they can vote against it.</p>
<p>KELLY:</p>
<p>When will it be out in the open? You have promised on several occasions</p>
<p> that the tax package will be released well before the next election.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Fran, that, with respect, is just a wasted question. You know I am</p>
<p> not in a position to say when it is going to be announced.</p>
<p>KELLY:</p>
<p>But it will be well before the next election?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It will be announced in plenty of time for people to digest it before</p>
<p> they vote.</p>
<p>KELLY:</p>
<p>If an election was going to be held in August...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Fran, don't waste my time asking those sort of hypothetical questions.</p>
<p>KELLY:</p>
<p>The latest Newspoll out today has support for a GST fading. Does that</p>
<p> concern you?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No it doesn't. I haven't seen the detail of that poll but I imagine</p>
<p> the question was just a straight question - are you in favour of a</p>
<p> GST or not? Now if it is, then I am not surprised that people say</p>
<p> no to that. I mean, I am not in favour of a GST on top of the present</p>
<p> tax structure and we won't introduce it. I would only be in favour</p>
<p> of a broad based, indirect tax if it involved the abolition of the</p>
<p> wholesale sales tax, at least, and significant cuts in personal income</p>
<p> tax. It has never been and it never will be our policy to put a GST</p>
<p> on top of the existing tax structure.</p>
<p>KELLY:</p>
<p>You have said in Parliament that the Australian people will either</p>
<p> believe you or they will believe Labor. In a sense, do both sides</p>
<p> have a bit of a credibility problem coming into this and is that really</p>
<p> the whole, part of the contributing factor to the rise in One Nation</p>
<p> stocks, the credibility problems, the baggage that both major parties</p>
<p> carry?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I think One Nation supporters are made up of three distinct</p>
<p> groups. I think there are a group of people in the community who are</p>
<p> racially motivated on some issues. That's one distinct group. I think</p>
<p> she got a few voters out of my strong stance on guns and I am not</p>
<p> going to compromise that stance, not under any circumstances and I</p>
<p> make that very plain to her and to her supporters on that issue. The</p>
<p> third group is a much larger one, are really just ordinary decent</p>
<p> Australians who are attracted by one line solutions. They feel economically</p>
<p> insecure. They think she has got the answers because she is different.</p>
<p>KELLY:</p>
<p>And they don't believe the promises of the major parties?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think it's more that they are, they have been knocked around by</p>
<p> life. They predominantly live in regional Australia. They feel economically</p>
<p> insecure and there are no easy solutions to many of these problems</p>
<p> and she comes along and says, look it's all the fault of the foreigners</p>
<p> and it's all the fault of the Aborigines and it's all the fault of</p>
<p> somebody else. And they say, maybe that's right, we'll give her a</p>
<p> go. Now the advantage in one sense of what she did last night in making</p>
<p> a detailed speech was to expose her flimsy knowledge, to expose just</p>
<p> how erratic is the line of argument that she's using on some issues</p>
<p> and I think in that sense it's a warning to people who are contemplating</p>
<p> voting for her that she has absolutely no solutions and I particularly</p>
<p> in the context of the Queensland election, would say to those Coalition</p>
<p> people who may be thinking of voting for her, it is a wasted vote.</p>
<p> She has no answers. She has an insecure grasp of reality, in fact,</p>
<p> and you ought to support the Borbidge Government which is really the</p>
<p> only conservative alternative on offer. I mean, it's a Beattie Government</p>
<p> or a Borbidge Government and if you are a conservative voter in Queensland</p>
<p> and you want a conservative Government, you ought to vote for Borbidge.</p>
<p>KELLY:</p>
<p>Prime Minister; thank you.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
<p>ENDS</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
