<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4160</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER ECONOMIC ORGANISATIONS (KEIDANREN) - 17 JUNE 1976</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/06/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004160.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
ECONOMIC ORGANISATIONS ( KEIDANEN) T 17 JUNE 1976.<br />
Thank you for your kind comments and words of welcome. It<br />
gives me great pleasure to be in Japan. I am especially pleased<br />
to have the opportunity to address this distinguished group of<br />
industrial and business leaders.<br />
Yours is the principal responsibility for the continuing<br />
development of the Japanese economy, which has such great<br />
significance for Australia and for much of the world.<br />
Both of our countries have had to cope over the last couple of<br />
years with the disturbing combination of recession and inflation.<br />
The Governments of both Australia and Japan have had to find<br />
new solutions to these problems.<br />
Fortunately, there are signs of economic recovery in your country<br />
and ours. There are still many problems to overcome but with<br />
patience and care we can look forward to better times.<br />
our main objective in Australia has been to restrain public spending<br />
in order to transfer resources to individuals and to companies.<br />
Through these means the private sector is acquiring the resources<br />
and the room to expand so that economic growth can once more take<br />
place. I am pleased to say that the Australian economy is now recovering.<br />
The economic recovery in Japan is also of great importance to us,<br />
as our recovery is to Japan.<br />
It is too often forgotten that the chance of improvement on the<br />
economic wellbeing of the people of the developing nations depends<br />
on the health and strength of the economies of the developed<br />
nations. We have seen the effects in the developing countries<br />
over the last couple of years of a decline in world economic<br />
activity and a slackening in demand for their products. Until<br />
we see an improvement in world trade there is little hope for those<br />
countries of any significant improvement.<br />
The new Treaty of Friendship and Co-operation emphasises,<br />
in Article IV, that " the continuous expansion of international<br />
trade on an open, multi-lateral and non discriminatory basis is of<br />
fundamental importance for the sound development of the world<br />
economy." .2/ </p>
<p>-2-<br />
The development of trade between Japan and Australia as you would<br />
know best has been remarkable.<br />
Nineteen years ago our two countries signed the Commerce Agreement.<br />
Since then trade between us has increased fifteenfold. It is now<br />
the seventh largest trade flow in the world.<br />
Japan has now become Australia's major trading partner. In<br />
1974/ 75 you toc30% of our exports and provided 20% of our<br />
imports. The reason for this is plain. Our trade is complementary. Australia<br />
has become a major source of raw materials and foodstuffs for Japan.<br />
In return Japan is a significant source of manufactured goods for<br />
Australia. Growing interdependence between our two countries has been an<br />
inevitable effect of the complementary nature of our trade. Some<br />
people suggest that such interdependence breeds risk and<br />
vulnerability. I cannot share that concern.<br />
Our interdependence reflects the national advantages which Japan<br />
and Australia possess. The nature and degree of our interdependence<br />
may change, but it will continue to provide a basis for a secure<br />
and stable relationship.<br />
We must continue to seek out and explore opportunities for economic<br />
cooperation to ensure that our trade is placed on the soundest<br />
possible footing.<br />
It is important that we each strive to develop the greatest possible<br />
degree of predictability and stability. This is the way to an<br />
enduring confidence between us.<br />
I strongly believe that both countries will benefit from the fullest<br />
possible consultation on supply and market prospects and on the<br />
development of domestic policies affecting trade and investment<br />
between the two countries.<br />
Present arrangements for discussions between Australian and Japanese<br />
Ministers and officials offer a useful and effective means of raising<br />
many of these issues in a cooperative atmosphere. These arrangements<br />
should be developed as the need arises.<br />
Perhaps the most important link which has emerged between our two<br />
countries over the last decade has been our increasing interdependence<br />
in respect of raw materials. Recognition of this factor prompted my<br />
Government to ask Mr. Anthony, Deputy Prime Minister and Minister for<br />
National Resources and Overseas Trade, to come to Japan early this<br />
year. He came on the first overseas visit by a minister of my<br />
Government. 3/ </p>
<p>-3-<br />
Australian exports of minerals to Japan are of fundamental<br />
importance to both countries. Australia has no other markets<br />
of such size and with such potential for growth. Japan has<br />
no other supplier with such a wealth of resources and the<br />
potential for security of supply.<br />
All the factors are present for the further development of an<br />
economic relationship which should confer enormous benefits on<br />
both countries.<br />
Since we came into office we have taken action to give confidence<br />
in Australia as a long term source of supply.<br />
Japan has emphasised the need for a secure and increasing supply<br />
of steel-making raw materials. The last couple of years have<br />
been difficult around the world. Predictably this has had its<br />
effect on the Japanese steel industry. It is now clear, however,<br />
that recovery is underway.<br />
The information supplied by Japan suggests that many new projects<br />
must come on stream within a fairly short time.<br />
Given the lead-time and the huge amounts of money involved<br />
for projects of the magnitude envisaged decisions must be made<br />
now to ensure that these raw materials will be available when<br />
required. We recognise that fact.<br />
In the case of coal, representatives from the Japanese steel<br />
industry and the Japanese Government indicated their concern that<br />
new projects should be developed in Australia. Between them these<br />
probjects will make available in excess of an additional 13 million<br />
tonnes of high quality coking coal per annum.<br />
My Government had urgent discussions with the companies concerned<br />
to remove impediments in the way of the development.<br />
In the case of iron ore, various Australian companies are promoting<br />
with Japanese mills a new generation of iron ore projects based<br />
on the vast, rich reserves of the Pilbara in Western Australia.<br />
These potential projects include completely new mining operations,<br />
and incremental expansions of existing mines.<br />
For some time now the Australian companies have met Japanese mills'<br />
request for bulk samples and detailed feasibility studies. They<br />
are now awaiting the mills' decisions on export contracts.<br />
I would explain that my Government is not setting any priorities<br />
as between individual projects, recognising that this is properly<br />
a matter for commercial negotiation.<br />
Japan will never find a more stable, convenient and efficient iron<br />
ore supplier than Australia.<br />
Australia first commenced exporting iron ore a little over a decade<br />
ago. In this time, Australian iron ore producers have supplied<br />
Japanese steel mills with 400 million tonnes of iron ore a virtual<br />
mountain of iron ore a mountain worth more than $ 3000 million<br />
Australian dollars. 4/ </p>
<p>-4-<br />
Further development of this mutually beneficial trade, depends<br />
on the new iron ore developments being brought into production.<br />
I look forward to Japanese mills reaching decisions soon on new<br />
export contracts for these projects. The urgent attention the<br />
Australian Government gave to these projects demonstrates, in<br />
a way that words never can, Australia's attitude to Japan. It should<br />
reassure your country of the reliability of Australia as a stable,<br />
continuing long term source of supply of raw materials.<br />
I have emphasized our trade in minerals because it is so important.<br />
But Australia is also a major exporter of agricultural projects to<br />
Japan and other countries. Access to international markets for our<br />
beef, wheat, dairy projects, wool and sugar and stable marketing<br />
arrangements for these products are of great importance to<br />
Australia. The development of our minerals industry has been based on the<br />
security of long term contracts.<br />
We would like to see the development with Japan of similar<br />
arrangements or at least minimum access assurances for our<br />
agricultural products.<br />
I am pleased in this respect that the market for Australian beef<br />
in Japan has started to grow and that your Government has decided<br />
to announce six monthly quotas. This will introduce a degree of<br />
predictability into the market.<br />
It is important that industries that have been developed or<br />
expanded to meet your requirements are assured of a stable market<br />
at fair and reasonable prices. The stronger the assurances that can<br />
be given the more confidently can businessmen undertake the necessary<br />
investments.<br />
One matter which I know has been a source of concern for Japan is<br />
the question of the Australian Government's export control ! powers.<br />
I wish to put any of your concerns on this matter to rest by defining<br />
first the role of business and then the role of Government in this<br />
matter. Let me make it clear that my Government looks to the<br />
private sector to negotiate and carry out export contracts in<br />
respect of minerals.<br />
We are fully committed to the private enterprise system. This<br />
confidence is based on our belief that the private sector is<br />
fully aware of the need to maintain and develop our trade.<br />
We believe that the private companies carrying our commercial<br />
negotiations are the best qualified to make judgements about what<br />
things are reasonable or not reasonable in mineral negotiations.<br />
Commercially acceptable agreements and reasonable market prices<br />
satisfactory to both buyer and seller are more likely to result<br />
from free and open negotiations by companies than general<br />
intervention by a Government that thinks it knows best. This<br />
is particularly so where differences between buyers and sellers<br />
a're on fine points which only exports can properly resolve. </p>
<p>if commercial negotiations produce a commercial result, related to<br />
world market prices, there is no role for Government. Only if the<br />
prices do not reflect world market prices if Australia's national<br />
interest is being adversely affected has the Government a proper<br />
case for intervention.<br />
I believe that in the short time my Government has been in office,<br />
we have provided evidence of our intention.<br />
Recent negotiations on iron ore and soft coking coal prices between<br />
Australian producers and the Japanese mills were settled on a<br />
commercial basis without the need for Government intervention.<br />
Given goodwill on both sides, there is no reason why this cannot<br />
be the pattern for the future.<br />
As well as the large and growing trade relationship between our<br />
countries, Japan is increasingly important as a potential source<br />
of investment capital.<br />
Traditional sources of overseas investment in Australia have been the<br />
United States and the United Kingdom. Japanese investment has<br />
represented only about 10% of total overseas investment over the<br />
last ten years.<br />
With the progressive relaxation of the Japanese Government's control<br />
over capital outflow, I expect that Japanese investors will play an<br />
increasingly important role in Australia's development.<br />
We welcome Japanese investment. Japanese investment is as welcome<br />
as the investment of any other country.<br />
My Government regards foreign investment as being of major importance<br />
to Australia's development. It brings with it job opportunities,<br />
new technological, managerial and workforce skills, increased<br />
export incomes, a broader and stronger industrial base.<br />
0 my Government's positive policy towards foreign investment has<br />
been thoroughly spelled out. Its major objectives are to encourage<br />
foreign investment and to ensure that the benefits of this investment<br />
are fairly shared between the foreign investor and the Australian<br />
community. To this end we screen certain categories of new<br />
investment to determine whether such investment would be contrary<br />
to the national interest.<br />
We would like to have Japanese capital in partnership-with<br />
Australian capital. One way to ensure that projects will be<br />
developed to meet Japanese needs is through joint ventures with<br />
Australian enterprise. Developments in Australia are also a way<br />
of securing access to Australian Markets, as Toyota and Nissan have<br />
discovered. In the case of mineral development and other natural resource<br />
projects, we have laid down guidelines on acceptable levels of<br />
Australian equity participation. 50% Australian equity is<br />
generally required. 75% in the particular instance of uranium. 6/ </p>
<p>These guidelines have been laid down because projects in these<br />
key areas involve the development and exploitation of the natural<br />
resources wealth of the Australian continent and off-shore areas.<br />
The Government believes that Australians should have the maximum<br />
opportunity to participate in the ownership and control of<br />
these projects. The Government recognises that Australian<br />
equity capital may not always be available on reasonable terms<br />
and conditions for some projects.<br />
Where adequate Australian equity participation is not available<br />
a project may still be permitted to proceed where it would not<br />
be against the national interest for it to do so. In such<br />
circumstances we will, as appropriate, seek satisfactory<br />
arrangements for increasing Australian equity within an agreed<br />
period. Australia's approach to foreign investment is not inflexible<br />
or rigid.<br />
If any potential investor is uncertain about whether a project<br />
satisfied the guidelines my advice is that the proposal be<br />
submitted to the Foreign Investment Review Board. The Board will<br />
be very happy to advise him and the Government will give a decision<br />
on any subsequent formal application as soon as possible.<br />
Concern has been expressed in Japan about Australia's participation<br />
in the bauxite, copper and iron ore producer organisations.<br />
I would like to dispel any grounds upon which these feelings might<br />
be based. As a participant in these organisations Australia has made<br />
it clear that its commitment is to producer/ consumer cooperation.<br />
Australia will not be a party to any action aimed at holding<br />
consumer countries to ransom. Producers of raw materials are entitled<br />
to receive fair prices for their exports. Consuming countries are<br />
equally entitled to reasonable supplies of raw materials at fair<br />
prices. The cooperation made possible throu~ h these producer bodies should<br />
assist to fulfill both our countries interests through the orderly<br />
development of production and trade.<br />
Both of our economies have undergone rapid change in recent years.<br />
I would not expect the dynamism of development to slacken though<br />
its form may differ.<br />
Herein lies an opportunity for both our countries; Japan's interest<br />
for example, in deploying a greater share of its-investment towards<br />
high technology industries can be complemented closely with,<br />
Australia's aim to upgrade the processing of our raw material<br />
production. .7/ </p>
<p>-7-<br />
Yesterday, I had the great pleasure of signing with your<br />
Prime Minister the Basic Treaty of Friendship and Co-operation.<br />
That Treaty is a symbol of the relationship which has developed<br />
between our two countries.<br />
But it is much more than that. It is also the symbol of what lies<br />
before us, of the wider relationship which will develop in the<br />
political and cultural areas as well as in the economic field which<br />
has so far been paramount.<br />
Our relationship will not be without its difficulties. These are<br />
only natural. But our relationship is a mature one. We can talk<br />
and resolve differences. The important thing will be not to lose<br />
sight of our long term objectives.<br />
All of us here today will have an important role to play in this<br />
new and exciting development. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
