<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7109</transcript-id>
    <title>ANNOUNCEMENT OF YOUNG AUSTRALIANS TO CREW BICENTENNIAL SCHOONER THE LODGE - 12 FEBRUARY 1987</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/02/1987</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007109.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
-EMBARGO-ED-U NL-I-L-L~-I-V-ERY C. H-ECK--AG; A-I-NS-T--D-E-L-I-VERYANNOUNCEMENT<br />
OF YOUNG AUSTRALIANS TO CREW<br />
B1CENTENNIAL SCHOONER--<br />
THE LODGE _ 12_ FEBRUARYU-987<br />
SIR JOHN LEAHY, DISTINGUISHED GUESTS, LADIES AND GENTLEMEN.<br />
I AM DELIGHTED TO WELCOME YOU TO THE LODGE ON THIS VERY<br />
SPECIAL OCCASION TO MARK THE SELECTION OF THE TWELVE YOUNG<br />
AUSTRALIANS WHO WILL HELP CREW THE UNITED KINGDOM'S<br />
BICENTENNIAL GIFT SCHOONER " YOUNG ENDEAVOUR" FROM BRITAIN TO<br />
AUSTRALIA. SIR JOHN, MAY I BEGIN BY THANKING THE BRITISH GOVERNMENT AND<br />
PEOPLE ON BEHALF OF MY GOVERNMENT -AND THE PEOPLE OF<br />
-AUSTRALIA FOR THIS MAGNIFICENT--AND-GENEROUS-G-IFT;<br />
THIS SPLENDID SAILING SHIP BEING BUILT IN THE UNITED KINGDOM<br />
WILL ARRIVE IN AUSTRALIA IN TIME FOR OUR BICENTENARY IN<br />
JANUARY 1988. ON BOARD WILL BE THE TWELVE AUSTRALIANS WHOM<br />
I AM ABOUT TO INTRODUCE, AND TWELVE YOUNG BRITONS WHOSE<br />
NAMES ARE ALSO BEING ANNOUNCED TODAY.<br />
THIS CREW OF TWENTY FOUR YOUNG PEOPLE Wr1tL BE GUIDED BY FOUR<br />
OFFICERS OF THE ROYAL AUSTRALIAN NAVY AND FOUR OFFICERS TO<br />
BE PROVIDED BY THE UNITED KINGDOM. THE ROYAL AUSTRALIAN<br />
NAVY REPRESENTATIVES LEFT LAST MONTH FOR THE UNITED KINGDOM<br />
TO COMMENCE TRAINING WITH THEIR BRITISH COUNTERPARTS SO<br />
UNFORTUNATELY THEY CANNOT BE WITH US TODAY.<br />
ON ARRIVAL IN AUSTRALIA, THE " YOUNG ENDEAVOUR" WILL TAKE<br />
PART IN ANOTHER MAJOR EVENT OF 1988 THE TALL SHIPS RACE<br />
FROM HOBART TO SYDNEY AND THE PARADE OF SAIL, INVOLVING THE<br />
TALL SHIPS, ON SYDNEY HARBOUR ON AUSTRALIA DAY 1988. IT<br />
WILL THEN BE OFFICIALLY HANDED OVER TO AUSTRALIA. THE ROYAL<br />
AUSTRALIAN NAVY HAS AGREED TO TAKE ON THE TASK OF<br />
M4AINTAINING AND OPERATING THE " YOUNG ENDEAVOUR" AS A-SAIL<br />
TRAINING VESSEL FOR THE YOUNG PEOPLE OF AUSTRALIA.<br />
THE SCHOONER'S NAME, " YOUNG ENDEAVOUR", IS HIGHLY<br />
APPROPRIATE A NAME WHICH RECALLS CAPTAIN COOK'S SHIP " THE<br />
ENDEAVOUR" BUT WHICH ALSO EMPHASISES THAT THIS VESSEL IS<br />
ESPECIALLY A GIFT TO BENEFIT OUR YOUTH. </p>
<p>2<br />
IN A DEEPER SENSE, THE NAME IS A REMINDER OF OUR HISTORIC<br />
LINKS WITH BRITAIN, AND OF OUR COMMON HERITAGE. THE GIFT IS<br />
YET ANOTHER STRIKING PROOF OF THE ENDURING AND CLOSE<br />
RELATIONSHIP BETWEEN BRITAIN AND AUSTRALIA.<br />
THE OPPORTUNITY TO PARTICIPATE IN THIS ADVENTURE CAPTURED<br />
THE IMAGINATION OF YOUNG AUSTRALIA. AROUND 7000 YOUNG<br />
PEOPLE, BETWEEN THE AGES OF 18-AND 25, RESPONDED IN THE<br />
AFFIRMATIVE TO THE QUESTION " ARE YOU ONE IN A MILLION?"<br />
T-HAT-MAGN-IF-I-CEN-T-RES-P-ONSE-SHOWED--THA-T-HE--SP-I. RE--OF<br />
ADVENTURE STILL LIVES IN OUR YOUTH. BUT IT ALSO POSED A<br />
DAUNTING TASK OF SELECTING THE FINAL CREW. THAT TASK FELL<br />
TO-THE'SELECTION-COMMITTEE--ESTABL-rSHED-BY-THE-AUSTRALI-AN--<br />
BICENTENNIAL AUTHORITY. I WANT TO THANK COMMANDER PARKER<br />
AND HIS. COMMITTEE-FOR--THE. TIME AND. EFFORT THEY DONATED TO<br />
THEIR TASK. I ALSO WANT TO THANK THE VARIOUS SUB-COMMITTEES<br />
IN EACH STATE AND TERRITORY WHO UNDERTOOK THE PRELIMINARY<br />
SELECTION. AROUND 200 OF THE ORIGINAL 7000 APPLICANTS WERE CHOSEN TO<br />
ATTEND TWO-DAY WORKSHOPS AT WHICH THEY WERE PUT THROUGH<br />
TESTS TO DETERMINE THEIR PHYSICAL AND MENTAL PROWESS AND<br />
THEIR ABILITY TO GET ON WITH OTHERS -UNDER TOUGH CONDITIONS.<br />
TO THOSE THOUSANDS OF FINE YOUNG AUSTRALIANS WHO HAVE NOT<br />
BEEN SELECTED, I OFFER THIS CONSOLATION: THE SELECTION<br />
COMMITTEE TELLS ME-THAT THE--QUALI-TY-OF THE-APPLICATIONS-WAS<br />
OUTSTANDING A GREAT INDICATOR OF THE QUALITIES OF OUR<br />
YOUTH AND A SOURCE OF CONFIDENCE IN THE FUTURE OF OUR<br />
COUNTRY. IT FOLLOWS THAT THE CREW THAT HAS BEEN CHOSEN IS OF A VERY<br />
HIGH CALIBRE INDEED.<br />
IT NOW GIVES ME GREAT PLEASURE TO ANNOUNCE THE NAMES OF<br />
THOSE TWELVE CREW MEMBERS AND THE FOUR RESERVES, WHO<br />
REPRESENT ALL AUSTRALIA'S STATES AND TERRITORIES:<br />
[ PRESENT A MEMENTO TO EACH CREW MEMBER AND RESERVES]<br />
[ MEMENTOS ARE NAMED AND WILL BE HANDED TO YOU]<br />
MAY I OFFER MY CONGRATULATIONS TO YOU ALL.<br />
I WANT ALSO TO EXTEND MY THANKS AND APPRECIATION TO THE<br />
CORPORATE SPONSORS COOPERS AND LYBRAND, W. D. SCOTT AND<br />
ANSETT FOR THE ASSISTANCE THEY PROVIDED IN SELECTING THE<br />
CREW. THIS IS A GOOD EXAMPLE OF-THE CORPORATE SECTOR<br />
JOINING WITH GOVERNMENT TO MAKE A SUCCESS OF OUR<br />
BICENTENNIAL CELEBRATIONS. THE ABA HAS PREPARED SPONSORSHIP<br />
PLAQUES FOR THE COMPANIES IN RECOGNITION OF THIS ASSISTANCE<br />
AND I AM PLEASED TO BE ABLE TO PRESENT THEM TODAY.<br />
[ PRESENT PLAQUES TO REPRESENTATIVE OF:<br />
COOPERS AND LYBRAND,-<br />
W. D. SCOTT AND<br />
ANSETT] </p>
<p>WHILE ON THE SUBJECT OF CORPORATE SPONSORSHIP I WOULD<br />
MENTION THAT PRESENT HERE TODAY ARE REPRESENTATIVES OF<br />
BRITISH AND AUSTRALIAN COMPANIES WHO WILL ASSIST WITH<br />
MEETING THE EXPENSES OF THE AUSTRALIAN CREW MEMBERS WHILE ON<br />
THEIR JOURNEY TO AND FROM BRITAIN.<br />
FINALLY I WISH TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE WORK DONE BY JIM KIRK AND<br />
HIS TEAM AT THE ABA. GIVEN THE TASK-OF SELECTING THE YOUNG<br />
AUSTRALIAN CREW THEY CARRIED IT OUT WITH ENTHUSIASM, FLAIR<br />
AND-EFFICIENCY.<br />
IN OUR TWO HUNDRED YEARS OF HISTORY AUSTRALIANS HAVE<br />
DISTINGUISHED THEMSELVES IN MANY FIELDS OF ENDEAVOUR. IN<br />
PART ICU-LAR, _ AS-A NATION, WE_ HAVE -A GREAT TRADITION OF<br />
EXPLORATION ANDADVENTURE BOTH. AT SEA AND ON LAND.<br />
THE CREW OF THE " YOUNG ENDEAVOUR" WILL CONTINUE IN THAT<br />
TRADITION. ALL OF YOU WHO WILL PARTICIPATE IN THE ARDUOUS TASK OF<br />
SAILING THIS SCHOONER ARE ABOUT TO MAKE A UNIQUE<br />
CONTRIBUTION TO THE SUCCESS OF OUR BICENTENARY. WHAT'S<br />
MORE, YOU WILL BE CALLED UPON TO DEMONSTRATE SOME SPECIAL<br />
QUALITIES: ENDURANCE--IN -THE FACE OF HARDSHIP, COURAGE IN<br />
THE FACE OF DANGER, ENTHUSIASM IN THE-FACE OF CHALLENGE, AND<br />
THAT CO-OPERATIVE SPIRIT WHICH HAS ALWAYS BEEN THE HALLMARK<br />
OF OUR PEOPLE.<br />
YOU HAVE MY BEST WISHES FOR SUCCESS IN THIS MEMORABLE<br />
UNDERTAKING. ALL OF US WILL TAKE PRIDE IN YOUR ACHIEVEMENT,<br />
AS A FITTING TRIBUTE TO THE BICENTENARY AND THE YOUTH OF<br />
THIS COUNTRY. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
