<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4600</transcript-id>
    <title>BUNDABERG IRRIGATION PROJECT - GRANT TO QUEENSLAND, 19 DECEMBER 1977</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/12/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004600.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
JAUSTRAI<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 19 DECEMER 1977<br />
BUNDABERG IRRIGATION PROJECT GRANT TO QUEENSLAND<br />
The Prime Minister announced today that the Commonwealth Government<br />
is to make an additional grant of $ 1.5 million available this<br />
financial year to the Queensland Government towards the Bundaberg<br />
Irrigation Project. The grant is to enable completion of the<br />
Gin Gin Channel from the Monduran Dam to the Burnett River near<br />
Maryborough. The Prime Minister had announced the Government's intention to<br />
provide this grant prior to last Saturday's election.<br />
The Prime Minister said that the offer would be in the form of a<br />
further non-repayable grant to Queensland on the basis of a dollar<br />
for dollar matching contribution by the State Government.<br />
Mr Fraser said that legislation would be introduced as soon as possible<br />
into the new Parliament to give effect to the Government's decision.<br />
He added that the Commonwealth has decided to provide this further<br />
assistance to Queensland because of the extremely dry conditions<br />
in the region and the need for the earliest possible availability<br />
of Monduran-Dam water for the irrigation of sugar cane crops.<br />
Since 1970, the Commonwealth Government has provided $ 17.2 million<br />
towards the Bundaberg Irrigation Project including the<br />
Monduran Dam, the main pumping station and initial work on the<br />
Gin Gin Channel. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
