<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1254</transcript-id>
    <title>TEXT OF PRIME MINISTER&#039;S &quot;MEET THE PRESS&quot; TV INTERVIEW</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/02/1966</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001254_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
I EMBARGO<br />
NOT FOR RELEASE BY ANY MEDIA UNTIL 10.50 PM<br />
SUNDAY 20 FEBRUARY. 1966<br />
TEXT OF PRIME MINISTER'S " MEET THE PRESS" TV INTERVIEW<br />
SUNDAY, 20TH FEBRUARY, 1966<br />
Following is the full text of the interview given by<br />
the Prime Minister, Mr. Harold Holt, in the " MEET THE PRESS"<br />
programme telecast by BTQ Channel 7 in Brisane tonight.<br />
The Prime Minister recorded the programme while in<br />
Brisbane last week.<br />
Introduction by the Chairman, Mr. Reg. Leonard<br />
Way back in the 1950' s when Mr. Lyons was Prime<br />
Minister of this country, the reporters in the<br />
Parliamentary Press Gallery at Canberra ard I<br />
happened to be one zf them were writing rather<br />
glowing phrases about an athletic young lawyer who<br />
had entered the House in 1955 as Member for the<br />
Melbourne metropolitan seat of Fawkner in succession<br />
to a blind barrister named Maxwell. Well, looking<br />
tack, I suppose in retrospect some of those phrases<br />
look a bit corny now references to the baby of the<br />
House and so on but there was a prediction made frr<br />
a shining political future for this young man and<br />
that certainly was right on the beam, because today<br />
he is this nation's leader, and I am sure that all<br />
you people after such a long association will<br />
appreciate my pride when I Tintroduce to you the Prime<br />
Minister of Australia, Mr. Harold Holt.<br />
MR. HOLT Thank you, Reg. Good evening to you all.<br />
MR. LEONARD Your Panel tonight: Alan Underwood, Elgin Reid<br />
and Lionel IHogg.<br />
And even with the Prime Minister, you know, there<br />
must be a message or two from th; se who pay the bills, and<br />
here they<br />
MR. LEONARD Well Sir it's been a lng climb to the top.<br />
This is the first time that we have had the honour of<br />
a Prime Minister in our studio and with that we are very<br />
pleased. Now, will you submit to this grilling of ours? ./ 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
MR. HOLT Certainly Reg. It is not the first time you have<br />
taken me apart and I on't imagine it will be the last.<br />
Chairman: Thank you. Well, now, Mr. Underwood,<br />
Q. _ dIr. Prime Minister, when you announced postponement<br />
of the Referendum a day or two ago, I think you said that<br />
Cabinet felt there should be a thorough review of current<br />
policies. Now, can we take this to signify that you meant<br />
changes, modifications or even departures from Menzies<br />
Government policies.<br />
MR. HOLT: Not necessarily at all, but each government has a<br />
character about it which is very much influenced by the person<br />
and policies and thinking of the Head of the Government, and<br />
here after a long administration of 16 uninterrupted years,<br />
we felt it appropriate or at least I did when I began my<br />
own Government, to take a look at some of the things we had<br />
been doing. I would think that i. the main they would be fully<br />
confirmed, but we live in a changing world. Australia itself<br />
has been striving vigorously forward, and we are looking now to<br />
a future which, as Denis Healey, the Minister for Defence from<br />
Great Britain when he was out here was . aying, took him in his<br />
thinking to the 1970' s even to the 1990' s. Now, a review of<br />
policy looking forward doesn't necessarily connote dissatisfaction<br />
with what was done. Indeed, I was part of what was done<br />
and very proud of it, but I am sure the Australian people would<br />
want us to take a fresh look at some of the basic policies we<br />
have been pursuing to see whether they adequately meet the<br />
situation we see ahead of us or whether there should be some<br />
modification. I wasn't implying anything more than that.<br />
Q. Mr. Prime Minister, are you satisfied that you and Mr.<br />
McEwen will be able to reach the same satisfactory relationships<br />
that marked the Menzies/ Fadden and the Menzies/ McEwen Government?<br />
MR. HOLT I am completely confident on that point. What seems to<br />
be overlooked by some is that Jack McE., en and I have been close<br />
colleagues now for thirty years, for more than two-thirds of that<br />
time in office together. Even in Opposition, we sat on the<br />
Opposition Executive together. We are good warm personal friends<br />
and I am glad to say that the new administration has opened in<br />
terms of complete cordiality and full co-cperation.<br />
Q. Mr. Prime Minister, the latest ALP upheaval. Do you<br />
really think this stems from State Aid . r do you think it is<br />
a revolt by the Parliamentary Party against the dictation of<br />
the Federal Executive?<br />
MR. HOLT: I think it is a product of the disintegration and decay<br />
that has been going on now for many years inside the Labor<br />
Party. Here is a party, once a very great party, which had<br />
conviction and cause over years, which followed the gaining of<br />
many of its more important goals. I think that spirit has<br />
gone from it. It was a socialist party and, nominally, still<br />
professes to be a socialist party but 1+ s own members realise<br />
that the Australian community of today doesn't want a socialist<br />
programme in that doctrinaire sense, and yet there it is. They<br />
haven't found something which they can substitute which would<br />
meet the needs of the modern Australia, and sa lacking a cause,<br />
lacking conviction, then their attention, I think tends to be<br />
turned more to personalities and to organisational problems.<br />
Q. Would this be the split again the DLP split, do you<br />
think? With the same source? </p>
<p>-3-<br />
MR. HOLT: Well, there you did have this major split. Certainly<br />
there were important policy elements but the division is more<br />
likely to occur because there is nothing to which any of them<br />
can point as firm Labor policy which they in their Caucus have<br />
evolved. Indeed, their rules don't enable them to do that<br />
unless they have gained the approval of the group to which<br />
Mr. Whitlam made this ra~ her unkind reference of the " witless<br />
12". We at least were rather mere polite when we talked about<br />
the " faceless 36".<br />
Q. Do you subscri. be to the theory, politics apart, that it would<br />
be a better thing if the quarrel were patched up and you had a<br />
stronger Opposition on the basis that government is better<br />
when opposition is strong?<br />
MR. HOLT: I think the Parliament functions better when there is<br />
a strong Opposition, but in my experience when the Opposition<br />
is weak, there tends to be rather more internal opposition<br />
developing inside the Government's own ranks. We found, for<br />
example, when we only had a majority of one, there was closer<br />
cohesion and unity of action on the part of our own Government<br />
parties than has been the case since we had a majority of more<br />
than 20, and at a time when the Opposition was weak. I don't<br />
think a government can ever relax and feel things are so good<br />
or so comfortable that it doesn't have to worry about the<br />
future.<br />
Q. You don't really think that where you have a large, thumping<br />
majority that the Heads of the Government tend rather to neglect<br />
the insignificant members who are supporting them?<br />
MR. HOLT Well, that's not the way it works out in my experience,<br />
because the insignificant members that you speak of have<br />
significant votes on issues which arise inside the party room,<br />
and in my experience Ministers, however highly placed,<br />
( and this went for tAe former Prime Minister, ir Robert<br />
Menzies) are very sensitive to the feelings of their backbench<br />
supporters. No, I don't think you need worry on that<br />
score, but I do aree that it is not a healthy t1' ng for a<br />
Parliament to lackan effective Oppisition. But this is up<br />
to the Labor Party to produce it. We will naturally try to<br />
win as many seats as we can.<br />
Q. You are not actually plugging, Sir, for a one majority again<br />
in the next election, are you?<br />
R. HOLT: Certainly not! I would hope to improve on the twenty-add<br />
that we have at the present time.<br />
Q. What significanue do you see Sir, in the ALP's having<br />
elected five Left Wing members to its Foreign Affairs Committee?<br />
MR. HOLT: This is the Federal Executive?<br />
Q. Yes.<br />
MR. HOLT: Well, I think the significance of this is where the<br />
source of power currently lies inside the Australian Labor Party.<br />
The Labor Party has been the voice of the trade union movement<br />
in Australia and for some years now, the more significant of<br />
the unions nr several of them have been under strong Left<br />
Wing leadership. Now this has made its impact on the thinking<br />
of he Caucus and quite obviously it is reflected in the<br />
Federal Executive. / 4 </p>
<p>-4-<br />
Q. What do you think, Sir, of this State Aid plan for education<br />
that Mr. Calwell has put out 10/-for<br />
MR. HOLT: This dollar-a-week plan? -ell, obviously it was a<br />
hasty product designed to offset the argument in the other<br />
direction, and it doesn't require very much analysis to show<br />
how unsatisfactory it could be in practice. Certainly, those<br />
who received an extra dollar a week would be glad to have it.<br />
People are always glad to have some extra money. But what<br />
about the parents whose children are under the school age and<br />
who are no included in this benefit but who have to pay<br />
increased taxation in order to finance the 80 million dollars<br />
which Mr. Calwell estimates the new proposal to cost.<br />
Q. Would yuu say it is a child endowment policy rather thai<br />
an education policy?<br />
MR. HOLT: Well, it is not even a general child endowment policy.<br />
This is the Point I've just been trying to make. It would apply<br />
to some children but not to many others who, for the parents<br />
concerned, represent a family burden.<br />
Q. Do you think there could be any guarantee that the dollar<br />
would be devoted to education and not to other purposes?<br />
MR. HOLT: I don't think there would. I think ours is a much<br />
more practicable approach, but as I said earlier, this has<br />
all the atmosphere and mark about it of improvisation to meet<br />
a political situation.<br />
Q. Mr. Prime Minister we notice that housing construction is<br />
down, car sales have been down and the effects of the drought<br />
are still with us. Could you give us, please, your oomment on<br />
the state of the economy?<br />
MR. HOLT: Well, Mr. Underwood you have picked on some of the<br />
weak spots. There are, fortunately, a good many strong spots<br />
and you may have noticed that Professor Horrie Brown, who<br />
Mr. Calwell said had helped him with his last Budget Speech,<br />
recently went on record as saying that the economy was currently<br />
in excellent shape. The soft spots that have been referred to<br />
have been receiving consideration frnm us but it is about this<br />
time of the year that Cabinet makes a thorough review of the<br />
economy, and we shall be doing this before Parliament meets.<br />
I prefer to reserve any more specific comment until we have<br />
done that. We do intend, of course, to maintain a full<br />
employment situation and a buoyant economy throughout the year.<br />
Q. Just to clear up one point on this Cabinet review Sir.<br />
Would that by any chance point to a supplementary budget?<br />
MR. HOLT: In practice this doesn't occur unless the drift in the<br />
economic si uation has reached a degree that seems to call for<br />
some abnormal action. It has occurred in the past, but I<br />
don't see anything in the current situation which could call<br />
for mere than marginal treatment.<br />
Q. For some months now Mr. Holt, economists have been warning<br />
of the drifting payments position with our import and export<br />
balance. Are you worried about this at all, unduly? </p>
<p>MR. HOLT: Well, Australia always has to be concerned to some<br />
degree about its balance of payments situation. We are<br />
affected by fluctuating climatic conditions. We are<br />
affected by fluctuations in the prices we get for our export<br />
products, and we im prt heavily * or the requirements of an<br />
affluent society and for a growing economy, but there is<br />
nothing, in the current situation which us cause for, ives<br />
alarm. Indeed, over recent weeks as I. ve seen the figures,<br />
the balance has tended to rise rather than fall. This is<br />
largely because there is a tendency now f~ r imports to steady<br />
down and there is a very strong and 2ustained inflow of<br />
capital.<br />
Q. There is no chance now 6f another squeeze, another tight<br />
sqaeeze like the last one, coming up?<br />
12. HOLT: Well, that should not be necessary.<br />
Q. I don't want to embarrass you by asking you for exact<br />
figures this is a snap question but our overseas reserves<br />
are healthy at the moment, are they?<br />
MR. HOLT: Yes, very healthy in historical terms. I mean there are<br />
not all that many years when Australia could p int to external<br />
reserves as high as they are now plus the fact that we have<br />
drawing rights which constitute our second line of reserves<br />
with te International Monetary Fund, and these have recently<br />
been increased as a result of us taking up the opportunity<br />
available to us in expanded reserve availability which the Fund<br />
had decided upon.<br />
Q. Sir, this would mean that neither the level of our<br />
reserves or the trend nf our balance now would be likely to<br />
cause your Government to have to take any emergency action.<br />
MR. HOLT: No, but what we have been doing for some time is trying<br />
to bring the economy into a better state of balance. I thifik<br />
that's been effectively achieved.<br />
Mr. Chairman: Well, now, could we change the sub ject, perhaps. There<br />
is a lot of territory to cover. Ihat about our commitments in<br />
the near North?<br />
Q. Mr. Prime Minister, what is your short answer to the<br />
eo~ le who tell you that we ought not to be fighting in Viet<br />
am.<br />
M2. HOLT: Well, I don't encounter very many of them, I am glad to<br />
say. I think most Australians recognise that what is happening<br />
in South Viet Nam constitutes a great struggle involving<br />
eventually the security of this country, that here we are<br />
meeting one of the critical challenges in the history of<br />
mankind, and that is the way we see it, and this is why we<br />
are there in Viet Nam, helping to strengthen by our presence,<br />
not necessarily by the size o our forces, the United States<br />
which has undertaken tremendous burdens on behalf of the free<br />
world in this context.<br />
Overseas, Mr. Holt, a lot of eople apparently see this<br />
as a national war of liberation in ie Nam in whic Australia<br />
and America are interfering. </p>
<p>-6<br />
MR. HOILT: liell some people see it th-, t way. There are some<br />
people in kustralia who see it that way, but I have studiied this<br />
as closely as I can. I have been present at discussions<br />
between men of the highest authority in these matters from<br />
the United States and from our own Departments of advice<br />
Service Departments, External fffairs, and I have studied a<br />
good deal of the evidence which come2 to us, and there can<br />
be no doubt that this goes far beyond the sort of civil war<br />
that Mr. Calwell has been talking about. There is clear<br />
evidence not only of infiltration, of subversion from the<br />
North, of the supply of equipment from the North but nowt, of<br />
course, military forces as wiell, m-d behind it, the guiding<br />
hand of the Chinese communists with their goal of world<br />
domination.<br />
Q. There have been constant rumours of more troops,<br />
Australian troops, being sent to Viet Nam. Is this correct?<br />
MR. HOLT: Well, these are rumours, and I am not able or prepared<br />
to comment on those matters. Normally, when the Govecrment<br />
has any announcement to make of this sort, it involves<br />
simultaneous announcements with other governments, or some<br />
notification of other governments. I couldn't make a comment<br />
on that.<br />
Q. Should Australians accept the probability Sir, that we<br />
will be maintaining troops in Viet Nam -for probably some years?<br />
Or do you have a hope of an earlier peace?<br />
MR. HOILT: Well, nobody can say with ayauthorityr hcw long this<br />
struggle will be drawn out, or whether negotiations are in<br />
the picture. Certainly the United States has been maintaining<br />
thoe stactve eace of fensive that any country could i l<br />
sincerity, be maing, but it took us a long, time in Maiaaa<br />
it then was to tidy up communist guerrilla activity in That<br />
country and a much less complicated task than the one which<br />
is faced. in South Viet Nam. On the other hand, of course,<br />
the forces which have been supplied are very considerable<br />
indeed, and the pressures and sensitivities arouind the world<br />
are very much greater th ~ n was the case in the Malaysian<br />
situation. 71e can only hope while at the same time making it<br />
firmly clear that we are not departing from the safeguarding<br />
of what seemed to us to be essential conditions, essential<br />
principles as we see them from Australia.<br />
Q. Excuse my asking this, Sir, but it relates to your<br />
previous answer that simultaneous announcements are made about<br />
such matters as sending more troops. I am oing to ask this<br />
because I think a lot of viewers out there will be asking it.<br />
Doesn't that at once indicate that more troops are to be sent<br />
because you would not be making simultaneous announcements<br />
if nothing was...<br />
MR. HOLT: I say this is the practi. e, and therefore you don't<br />
answer a question of that sort just off the cuff at even the<br />
most respectable of television sessions.<br />
Q. I gather that you are not going to answer.<br />
Q. Mr. Holt, I have two very short questions about the<br />
first battalion in Viet Nam. When will it be relieved,<br />
and ( b Do you intend to strike a special medal for the troops<br />
for Viet Nam service? </p>
<p>-7-<br />
MR. HOLT: I c-n't give ynu a precise date en the first question,<br />
but I can say it is the intention that there should, in<br />
respect of the troops who go there from time to time, be a<br />
programme of relief and the Service people wild have this<br />
matter well in hand. As to a special medal again I am not<br />
able to give a decisinn, out I can say that this matter has<br />
been engaging my attention that there is a document which<br />
has recently become available from the various Departments and<br />
Services involved and now available for the Cabinet, which<br />
will be discussing it, I hope in the next fortnight.<br />
Q. Can I just get in this questien? You have said, Sir<br />
that this is a battle against communism and its encroachment.<br />
Could I ask a question that has been puzzling us a littl3<br />
while what happened to the Government's promised I don't<br />
know whether it was promised, but indicated White Paper on<br />
communism in Australia?<br />
MR. HOLT: Well. again, we have had a look at this one on more than<br />
one occasion, but we haven't as yet decided to release such a<br />
White Paper. I am not going to canvass nc'w the arguments<br />
which run pro and con bn this matter or the difficulties<br />
which arise in relation to it. It would take more time than<br />
we have available here. All I can tell you is that it has<br />
engaged the attention of Cabinet more than once over recent<br />
years.<br />
Q. It indicates that, at any rate, it is prepared<br />
MR. HOLT: Not in any final form. There have been earlier draftings<br />
of the sort of thing that could be released if the Government<br />
decided that this should be done.<br />
Q. Mr. Prime Minister, you have had, very recently, talks<br />
with the British Defence 1Minister, Mr. Healey. Are we right<br />
in gathering that you feel reassured that British Defence<br />
Forces will be staying in the Indian Ocean and South East<br />
Asian area longer, perhaps, than you had first thought, and<br />
that we can expect UK defence co-operation?<br />
MR. HOLT: We were able to impress, I am sure, Mr. Healey with the<br />
importance that Australia, New Zealand, and, I would think,<br />
the United States, attaches to a British presence in that<br />
area, and the assurance which apparently Mr. Healey gave the<br />
Premier of Singapore recently would be in confirmat ion vf<br />
what I am now putting. And therefore we can expect the United<br />
Kingdom to hola on f~ r a considerable period cf time in<br />
Singapore. But discussing the matter quite realistically<br />
and remember, our talks with Mr. Healey were looking many<br />
years ahead, I repeat, he got as far as the 90' s of this<br />
century, and that is, although a long way away, still not too<br />
far away for us to be thinking and planning for contingencies<br />
which could arise, and we felt it would be useful if our<br />
Service people could talk over together ways in vhich if we<br />
were, for example, establishing some service establishment<br />
here, either Army, Navy or Air Fyrce, that we might have in<br />
mind that a situation could arise in which British servicemen<br />
would be wanting to make some use of that facility also.<br />
But there is no commitment, and no firm decision zf detail<br />
6n this matter.<br />
Q. Does this mean Mr. Holt, that if these forces you talk<br />
about do come here when and if Sinapore is given away by<br />
Britain, that you will give bases to Britain in Australia? </p>
<p>-8-<br />
MR. HOLT: There has been no decision on this point, but it is<br />
clearly in our interests, and we would hope in the common<br />
interests, for the closest collaboration and Service cooperation<br />
between ourselves and the United Kingdom and New<br />
Zealand, and we would hope that, so far as the area generally<br />
is concerned, this could extend to the United States of<br />
America. They have, together, an interest with us in the<br />
stability and economic progress of this region.<br />
Q. ~ ould yau agree, Mr. Holt, that it is to America, and<br />
not so much To Britain these days that Australia has to look<br />
primarily for defence aid?<br />
MR. HOLT: We have our arrangements under ANZUS and SEATO with<br />
the United States. Of course the United Kinordom io a party<br />
to SEATO, and this assurance we've had from the United<br />
Kimgdom about their continued presence East of Suez in<br />
substantial force is an indication that they will be playing<br />
a part in the security of the area. I don'l think I would<br />
want to be distinuishing publicly as between one or the<br />
other; in some situations we will be involved with the United<br />
Kingdom to a greater extent than, say, we would be with the<br />
United States. This is what is happening in respect of<br />
Indonesian confrontation. On the other hand, in Viet Nam,<br />
there we are involved with the Unite4 States.<br />
Q. It would be realistic, Sir, would it net, to imagine<br />
that in the event of a crisis for Australia Britain couldn't<br />
provide massive help on the lines that the United States<br />
might be able to?<br />
MR. HOLT: Well I don't think we are expectin-Great Britain to<br />
fight our tattles for us. On the other hand, Australia, at<br />
this stage of its development, can't meet every challenge which<br />
could conceivably be directed against it entirely of its own<br />
strength. That is why we have these alliances, but I wouldn't<br />
like to pursue against suppositions or contingencies too much<br />
public discussion on a matter of this sort. I thin we have<br />
robably covered it about as widely as I feel I wish to at<br />
his point. Mr. Prime Minister, the Defence programme is expanding,<br />
and this money has to come from somewhere. Does this mean<br />
that eventually there will be new taxes? You must raise<br />
this money somehow.<br />
0. HOLT: This of course depends on the degree of growth.<br />
Certainly fhe possibility is there of some increase because<br />
of the growth in the Defence programme. On the other hand,<br />
we have an expanding economy, returning increased revenue to<br />
the Government, year by year. It becomes a matter of<br />
judgment as to where any increase which comes to us from the<br />
r owth in our national product and the taxable income derived<br />
rom that, , ihere this should be directed, and this is one cf<br />
the teasing aspects of government, this problem cf balance cr<br />
the distribution cf resources.<br />
Q. This revolution in Indonesia, Mr. Holt, do you think<br />
that this has given Australia the chance to improve relationships<br />
with Indonesia and vice versa? </p>
<p>-9-<br />
MU. HOLT: Australia wants ta be a friend of Indonesia. We've<br />
demonstrated that many times, not merely because they are<br />
our nei hbours immediately to our North 100 million of<br />
them ut because it is our general disposition as a people<br />
to want to be friends with the countries that lie to the<br />
north of this country indeed, friends around the world.<br />
But at this stage, I think it is rather too early to say what<br />
the prospects are of an improved relationship. I may say<br />
that I had a very cordial message from the President of<br />
fndonesia, Dr. Sukarno, when I became Prime Minister, and<br />
also on Australia Day: a message also from Dr. Subandrio.<br />
And I did have the pleasure of meeting General ñ, asution when<br />
he was out here and was very much impressed bi him. I would<br />
hope that he has a growing influence in the affairs of that<br />
country, and that this could be a contribution to better<br />
relations betwnen us.<br />
Mr. Holt, just how seriously do you regard Indonesia's<br />
confrontation with Malaysia at the moment?<br />
MR. HOLT: Well it is a serious matter for us and for the British.<br />
Apart from anything else, it ties upa considerable body of<br />
servicemen from our respective countries and is very costly<br />
on that account if on no other, but it creates tensions for<br />
us all; it is disruptive in respect of Singapore and<br />
Malaysia. V ' e would certainly look to see an endto it,<br />
hopefully, but there is nothing in sight which would encourage<br />
us tt be lieve that this was going to happen.<br />
Have there been any indications of Indonesian trespassing<br />
in Australian New Guineai<br />
MR. HOLT: None that has come to my noti~ ce.<br />
Do you think that Indonesia will allow West Irian to<br />
make up its own mind eventually? Will the go to the people<br />
there at all, or do you think They will just take over?<br />
MR. HOLT: Oh, I wouldn't wish to comment on that one at this stage.<br />
I think we are getting into the realm of possibilities. There<br />
is nothing specific on this before us at the present time.<br />
Q. Then perhaps the Asian nation which we would have reason<br />
to fear most, if we have to fear a nation, that would be, of<br />
course, China.<br />
MR. HOLT: Well, China has made known its intention to go to world<br />
domination with its philosophy, if it can achieve that goal,<br />
and the Chinese are a patient people, but they have shown a<br />
firmness and a resolution on this matter quite unwaveringly<br />
since they took office. Now, we have learnt to our cost in<br />
the past that it is dangerous to igmore what dictators say<br />
about their intentizns. This was so of Hitler, this was so<br />
o Mussolini this was so in the case of the Japanese general<br />
who stated te Japanese intentions. And the Chinese gave<br />
set out their gols clearly enough, I think, for us to know<br />
where they inteni to go.<br />
Q. Well, gentlemen, would you care to change the subject<br />
now </p>
<p>10<br />
Q. Mr. Prime Minister, you were Minister for Immigration<br />
at one period. ihat is your viewpoint to-day on immigration?<br />
Do you think our present immigratinn policies are liberal<br />
enough?<br />
MR. HOLT: You are speaking of the restricted aspect of immigration?<br />
Q. Yes.<br />
MR. HOLT: Each country, of course reserves to itself these days,<br />
the right to the content of its population, and all countries,<br />
in our neighbourhood anyhow, maintain quite restriotive<br />
immigration policies, but in Australia, we have maintained<br />
the policy, over recent years anyhow, with what I described<br />
when I was Minister myself, humanity and good sense. Now<br />
there have been changes in the scene around us which, while<br />
not going to some fundamental change in our own policy, might<br />
indicate to rs that we should be reviewing the conditions<br />
which operate in respect of certain classes of migrant or<br />
settler in this country. For example, we do currently have<br />
a difference in the period required for naturalisation between<br />
the European settler and the non-European. Now this is a<br />
matter which, I think should be looked at. There may be<br />
powerful reasons why the distinction was observed at the time<br />
the rule came into effect, but it's one of the matters I am<br />
having currently Qxamined.<br />
Q. Just to make it clear Sir, you were in this referring<br />
we are talking about Asians, no doubt.<br />
MR. HOLT: That is so.<br />
Q. Would your review include the possibility of allowing<br />
Asian students to remain in Australia?<br />
MR. HOLT: I don't think we would be doing any service to the country<br />
from which they came if we were to do this. I know that our<br />
own students at the universities form strong friendships with<br />
many of the Asian students who go through the universities,<br />
but they have come to Australia with the primary object on the<br />
part of the country whence they came bf strengthening the<br />
economy and administration of that country, and if Australia<br />
was to reap by some change in its present rules, the cream of<br />
those who pass through the university here from Asia, I don't<br />
think we would be very popular with Asian governments.<br />
Q. Would it encompass such matters as that which many<br />
people thought was inhumane the deportation of a little girl<br />
named Nancy Prasad? Cases like that I mean. I don t know<br />
the background of the case, and I make no special pleadings<br />
in it.<br />
MR. HOLT: Well, I was long enough in the Department of Immigration<br />
to kncw that it is unwise to condemn a decision on what can<br />
be stated publicly. There are frequently personal, private<br />
family reasons which have a bearing on these matters, and<br />
I am not familiar with all the details in the Prasad case,<br />
but I do have the confidence in the warm humanity which the<br />
Immigration Department displayed over the years since the<br />
war while this programme has been in effect, so that I am not<br />
prepared to prejudge the matter without a full awareness of<br />
all the circumstances. </p>
<p>' ii<br />
Q. Mr. Holt, can we infer from all of this that there is<br />
certainly not going to be any wholesale rescinding of the<br />
White Australia policy?<br />
MR. HOLT: Well, we don't have a White Australia policy. You<br />
mean restrictive immigration policy.<br />
Q. That's the public service term for it, perhaps, but<br />
perhaps you will allow us to use our term.<br />
Q. I think we shouild get away from it as much as possible.<br />
Chairman: In any case, the question is clear.<br />
MR. HOLT: Yes, the question is clear. The current policy is<br />
supported by the great majority of the Australian people,<br />
but there is scope at times for liberalisation of conditions.<br />
This was done by us in the case of marriages to Japanese<br />
wives. This has been done in a number of-other instances,<br />
and we shall have coming to Australia as our trade builds up<br />
with the countries of Asia an increasing number of technicians,<br />
executives; the will want to bring families with them.<br />
Some of them will find themselves settled here for a number<br />
of 4ears. The point I am making about review is that we<br />
donyt necessarily go to the fundamentals of the policy when<br />
we make such a review; but there may be aspects of it that<br />
we should -e looking at in the light of what we see, the<br />
circumstances with which we are likely to be confronted in,<br />
say, the next decade.<br />
With great respect, Sir, don't you think that the<br />
majority of Australians are taking a mere liberal approach<br />
an immigration now than they were say ten or fifteen years<br />
ag?<br />
MR. HOLT: I think they are.<br />
Q. Mr. Holt, we have had an encouraging preliminary report<br />
from Sir William Hudson on the Northern Development. I t ink<br />
he dealt with irrigation. Can you tell us, please, if we<br />
can expect, Sir, any new kind of breakthrough in northern<br />
development?<br />
MR. HOLT: I think a very great deal is going on in the way of<br />
northern development. ' dhat is overlooked is the commercial<br />
activity, the industrial activity of the private operators.<br />
I heard a fi ure mentioned I think I am right in quoting<br />
this one aT $ 800 million of development expenditure<br />
currently going on north of the Tropic of Capricorn. Now<br />
don't hold me to that, because I haven't got this precisely<br />
in mind, but there is, if you take the programme as a whole,<br />
the private programmes and the Government programme...<br />
Q. Including the West<br />
MR. HOLT: a great dell of activity going on at the present<br />
time. Yes, but Queensland is also saring this and<br />
certainly the Northern Territory.<br />
Q. Talking of the North, this week in Dawson. What<br />
makes you think the Country Party can hold this against the<br />
very strong ALP onslaught? </p>
<p>12<br />
MR. HOLT: Well, first of all, the ALP itself is not very strong<br />
at the moment, and I am sure that this is % ell recognised in<br />
Dawson, jadging by some of the comment I heard while I was<br />
up there. But as to the confidence we have in our capaoity<br />
to hold the seat, our own candidate is a practical man, an<br />
enterprising younger member of a sugar-producing fami lya nd<br />
sugar is a vital commodity in the Dawson electorate. Hte has<br />
been overseas as a member of the Young Farmer group, he has<br />
shown an intelligent and modern approach to the pro lems of<br />
the area the farmin roblems, agricultural problems, and<br />
I think Ae will spea he language of Dawson much more<br />
realistically over the years ahead than a man who is<br />
crusading very commendably for one particular line of activity<br />
but hasn't so far taken a battleground other than that of<br />
northern development; and a representative of Dawson will<br />
have to involve himself in a great many more iesues than this.<br />
And of course, I would believe that the electors of Dawson<br />
would like to feel they had a voice in the Party Room of the<br />
Government.<br />
Chairman: I ask you that because we did have Dr. Patterson here<br />
a couple bf weeks ago, and we did nit have Mr. Fordyce, so<br />
I thiink now we have presented both sides.<br />
Q. A bit further north than Dawson, Mr. Prime Minister<br />
New Guinea. In your reviews of policies, are you having<br />
a look at the likely time it will take for New Guinea to<br />
reach a stage where it will be independent, whether you will<br />
have to change policies in New Guinea to any extent?<br />
MR. HOLT: No, we have got a very active programme of development<br />
g~ ing forward with our assistance in Nw Guinea. This is<br />
not only in the economic sense, but in the sense of governmental<br />
administration, constitutional development; we have<br />
been making reviews from time to time of the pace of constitutional<br />
development with the idea of leading or guiding the<br />
people in New Guinea to a point of viable indeendence. The<br />
interesting thing is to see how they caution themselves<br />
against too rapid a pace. They want this to be done in a<br />
way which will leave them sufficiently strong when they assume<br />
independence to be able to stand on their own feet, and to<br />
be able to conduct their own affairs in a proper fashion.<br />
Q. Do you favour a recent suggestion Mr, Holt, that the<br />
New Guinea people be given an opportunity of a referendum<br />
to cast their own vote as to whether they would like to<br />
become in fact a seventh State of Australia?<br />
MR. HOLT: Surely this is a very involved matter which would require<br />
far more than a casual comment from me at this point. I am<br />
not sufficiently well-informed on it to make the comment.<br />
Chairman: Look, with time running out, you know that before the<br />
end of this year, Mr. Holt has to take on a job he has never<br />
had to do before. He has to lead a government in an election.<br />
Would anybody like to touch on that facet?<br />
Q. Yes. Mr. Holt, in the next, in the coming election,<br />
would you rather do battle with Mr. Calwell than with Mr.<br />
Whitlam? </p>
<p>A t 15<br />
MR. HOLT: After all I have been involved in many elections since<br />
I came in in 195. Indeed, I cut my campaigning teeth in<br />
1954 against Mr. Scullin. So I am not<br />
Q. Obviously you weren't leading the Government then. It<br />
makes it a much more difficult task.<br />
MR. HOLT: No, but I have been in a senior role in Government for<br />
many years now, and there have been times in particular<br />
campaigns when I have been leading the campaign ef the Government<br />
in a particular State. I am not troubled by the prospect<br />
of going into a vigorous electinn campaign, and, Tfrankly,<br />
I think we will win handsomely regardless ef what emerges<br />
from the present disarray of te Labor Party.<br />
Q. Do you think the will vote for the Government and not<br />
worry about the Opposition?<br />
MR. HOLT: I don't think the Oppesition can produce even if it<br />
could find the complete answer in terms of leader, I don't<br />
think it can produce in that time the policies needed for the<br />
Australia of to-day. They w6uld have to scrap so much of<br />
their existing policy structure in order to achieve that result,<br />
and I don't think they will achieve it in the time.<br />
Chairman: Well, we will regard that as the first shot in the next<br />
election campaign, . and our forty-five minutes is up, and I have,<br />
to my great regret to close down, but I am coming back again<br />
to the Prime Minister after this message<br />
Well, Prime Minister, I didn't think that so much ground would<br />
be covered in the forty-five minutes that we had at our disposal,<br />
but it has been covered and a great deal of useful information<br />
given. I am quite sure that our viewers recognise that there<br />
were some curly questions to which you had to play a straight<br />
bat, and as a former inquisitor at Canberra, I can certainly<br />
appreciate it. All that remains for me now is to say thank<br />
you very much. We are greatly privileged that you have come<br />
o Queensland for your first full-scale interview of this kind.<br />
We do hope that we will see you again. Good night, Sir.<br />
MR. HOLT: Thank you Mr. Leonard. Thank you to you all. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
