<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3045</transcript-id>
    <title>D.A.C. REVIEW OF AUSTRALIAN AID</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/10/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003045.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
AAFFAIRS NQ DATE<br />
M4/ 150 24 October 1973<br />
D. A. C. REVIEW OF AUSTRALIAN AID<br />
The following is text of a communique released at<br />
the conclusion of DAC Review of Australia on 23 October 1973:-<br />
The Development Assistance Committee ( DAC) of the<br />
OECD held its annual review of the assistance efforts and<br />
a p) olicies of Australia on 23 October 1973, under the Chairmanship<br />
V of Ambassador Edwin Martin.<br />
The Australian delegation was headed by Mr Max<br />
Loveday, First Assistant Secretary, Development Divisi-on,<br />
Department of Foreign Affairs. The examining countries<br />
were Denmark and Japan.<br />
The Committee noted with satisfaction that net official<br />
development assistance ( ODA) disbursements ( US Dollars 272<br />
million in 1972) had risen as a proportion of Gross National<br />
Product from 0.53 per cent in 1971 to 0.61 per cent in 1972.<br />
Australia ranks fourth among DAC member countries in that<br />
respect. The Committee welcomed the announcement that the<br />
Australian Government would be working towards an official<br />
aid target of 0.7 per cent of GNP by the end of the decade.<br />
It expressed the hope that Australia's contributions to<br />
multilateral organisations would sub, c~ tialy increase in the<br />
future. Owing to a decline in private flows, total net<br />
official and private flows to the developing countries decreased<br />
to Dollars 422 million and represented 0.95 per cent of GNP<br />
in 19,72,. after having reached the one per cent target for<br />
the two preceding years. 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
In 1972, Australia extended all of its ODA in the forms<br />
of grants and was therefore in full compliance with the DAC<br />
reconmmendations on financial terms. There were no changes<br />
in Australia's procurement policies or practices in 1972,<br />
but Australia, at the DAC High Level Mleeting held o-i 18 and<br />
19 October, agreed to extend its official financial development<br />
assistance contributions pledged henceforth to multilateral<br />
institutions on an untied basis.<br />
The major part of Australia's ODA continued to be<br />
extended to Papua TNewG, u, i nea. The Committee took note of<br />
Australia's intention to maintain a substantial volume of<br />
assistance to Papua New Guinea following its accession to<br />
full internal self-government on 1 December 1973. At the<br />
samae time the Committee emphasised that it was desirable that<br />
other DAC members as well as international institutions<br />
supplement Austrlia's efforts in favour of Papua New Guinea<br />
with a view to speeding up its orderly economic and'social<br />
development. Interest was shown by the Committee in the decision<br />
to establish an Australian Development Assistance Agency.<br />
i;<br />
As from 1 December 1973, this agency, whichwill be<br />
responsible to the Minister of Foreign Affairs, will be<br />
entrusted with the administration of all Australia's<br />
bilateral aid and its participation in all programns of<br />
multilateral aid to developing countries.<br />
The Committee expressed satisfaction at the growing<br />
emphasis Australia intends to place on social factors and in"<br />
particular on measures designed to alleviate unemployment<br />
in the developing countries. It welcomed Australia's<br />
decision to contribute to multilateral programs dealing with<br />
population problems. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
