<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>208</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R.G. MENZIES, IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTITIVES ON 8TH SEPTEMBER 1960</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/09/1960</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000208.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
I 41* SPEECH 3Y THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT.<br />
HON. R. G. MENZIES, IN THE HOUSE OF<br />
REPRESENTATIVES ON 8TH SEPTEM3ER, 1960<br />
Sir, I do not propose to take very long over this<br />
matter because my colleague, the Minister for Territories ( Mr.<br />
Hasluck) has made, I think, a very comprehensive statement,<br />
with every word of uhich I agree. It might be quite adequate<br />
for me to say that I have heard the Ministerts statement that<br />
I have nothing to add to it, that I agree with it, and sit<br />
down.<br />
Mr. Pollard Why not do that?<br />
MR. MENZIES I will do the next best thing: I will stand.<br />
One aspect of this matter which was referred to by<br />
the Deputy Leader of the Opposition ( Mr. Uhitlam) deserves a<br />
little mention. The activities of the 7Tniversity Staffs<br />
Association and certain comments that have been published rather<br />
suggest that academic freedom is involved in the exclusion of<br />
this man from the Territory of Papua and New Guinea. I want<br />
to refer to that because it exhibits a complete misconception<br />
of this problem. Academic freedom yes. The Australian National<br />
University enjoys it in the fullest possible measure; We do not<br />
appoint people to the staff of that university. The university<br />
authorities do so according to their own untraimmellod judgment.<br />
I Ta not asked, as the relevant Minister, to approve of any<br />
appointment made by the Australian National University authorities.<br />
N Curtin It t8 just as well!<br />
M. MENZIES: Indeed it is just as well, because perhaps a few<br />
of the appointments that have boon made would not have received<br />
my approval. But I believe in academic freedom, and therefore<br />
I have maintained the view that when the university is appointing<br />
people professors, lecturers, readers or whatever they may<br />
be, it is the university's oinm business. But academic freedom<br />
does not carry with it the right to enjoy immunity from the<br />
immigration restrictions of the Territory which apply to other<br />
eople. Although academic people occasionally confuse the<br />
ssue, it is quite clear that you do not rise above the law<br />
simply because you attain academic freedom, and whether a man is<br />
free acad-mic or not, when he desires to enter this Territory<br />
he must secure a permit to do so. I eaphasize that point.<br />
Mr. Cairns No one put that proposition.<br />
MR. MENZIES: On the contrary, it was put in the letter written<br />
by the Staffs Association to the Minister. It was put as a<br />
matter of academic freedom.<br />
Mrb Whitlam I did not quote it.<br />
MRa MENZIES I know you did not. but it has boon quoted, no<br />
doubt. I am referring to the way ii % i it put by the_<br />
University Staffs Association. The speech of the honorableao " y<br />
member for Werriwa ( Mr. Whitlan), conta~ neo ht was<br />
a glancing reference to that topic.<br />
Mr Whitlam I was coning to it, in order to endorse it.<br />
M MENZIES I an glad to hear that, because now I have come<br />
to it in order to un-endorsc it. The first law of physics, of<br />
course, is that action and reaction are equal and opposite.<br />
The only other cosment I wish to make is this: the<br />
honorable member for Verriwa has given us a great number of<br />
testimonials. I do not know what those testimonials have to do </p>
<p>A 0<br />
I 0 I </p>
<p>2.<br />
with the case. Honorable nembers opposite can produce a<br />
string of testimonials to say that this can is very able, as<br />
he undoubtedly must be, or that he is distinguished in his<br />
profession, as I willingly concede, or that the persons who<br />
gave the testimonials like him, but what have testimonials to<br />
do with the point at issue? To send newspaper representatives<br />
prowling around irrelevant departnonts in Great Britain, asking<br />
spokesmen whoever those n: ysterious persons nay be whether<br />
they have certain things in nind, is to prepare the . akings of<br />
a ludicrous case. The essence of this natter is not what<br />
somebody else thinks about this nan or what his technical<br />
qualifications are; it is whether the Administrator was wrong<br />
in refusing hin a permit, on the information that the<br />
Administrator had before him.<br />
Mr. Barnard What is the information he had before him?<br />
MR. MENZIES To find that out, of course, is one of the<br />
objects of the exorcise. All we have to do is to publish the<br />
information, and then Security can close up. That is the idea<br />
motivating some honorable members opposite. I do not mean all<br />
of then. I do not mean the Leader of the Opposition ( Mr.<br />
Calwell) or the Deputy Loader. They take a different view.<br />
But there are honorable nembers opposite who would dearly love<br />
to force the publication of information coning to the Government<br />
in relation to the proper security interests of this<br />
country or-its Territo. ry, in order that its sources of<br />
information would thereafter dry up. Lot ie say that I,<br />
accepting all the responsibility that attaches to my office, am<br />
not going to take any step which would involve us in the loss<br />
of access to infornation bearing on the security, the territorial<br />
integrity and the political integrity of Australia. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
