<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6042</transcript-id>
    <title>LABOR&#039;S POLICIES ARE FALLING APART</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/03/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006042.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA FRIDAY 4 MARCH 198 3<br />
LABOR'S POLICIES ARE FALLING APART<br />
This week, the election campaign has focused on the real issues.<br />
And Labor's policies have not stood up to the test.<br />
Labor's policies are falling apart. The rash of contradictions<br />
in recent days show what a fraud those policies really area.<br />
Their prices and incomes policy is supposed to be a strategy<br />
to fight inflation and industrial relations problems. Events<br />
in the last few days have shown not only the policy is<br />
contradictory, but that it is a total fraud. Mr Crean, a<br />
Vice President of the ACTU has revealed that Labor and the<br />
unions have done a secret deal which, if Labor were to win<br />
tomorrow, would give the oil workers an 8 per cent pay rise.<br />
That pay rise would he a pacesetter for wage increases everywhere.<br />
Once more we would have a wage explosion.<br />
So the policy is not a policy to fight inflation and to improve<br />
industrial relations to the benefit of all Australians. It is<br />
a guarantee to the unions that they can grab what they want.<br />
The contradictions in Labor's policies can be seen everywhere.<br />
Mr Keating, last Thursday, claimed that "~ we have not advocated<br />
price control at all". That statement is totally misleading.<br />
It contradicts the prices and incomes policy which says Labor<br />
would set up a pricing authority.<br />
Mr Hlawke claims to be a man of reconciliation. When his policies<br />
were criticised by the Confederation of Australian Industry, the<br />
body representing a large number of employers in key industries,<br />
Mr Hawke abused the organisation by calling them a destabilising<br />
organisation..." How can Mr Hawke claim to be bringing Austral. ians<br />
together when he is so ready to launch a broadside against the<br />
major employers organisation. The list goes on. Labor argues<br />
passionately for Australian ownership of its own resources.<br />
When SHP announced its takeover of the American Company Utah<br />
International, Senator Walsh said " The Labor Party welcomes<br />
BHP's plans to takeover Utah International". That seemed to<br />
be in line with Labor's policy. Yet on Wednesday, Mr Barry Jones<br />
described that takeover as absolutely scandalous 9'<br />
That contradiction is incomprehensible and irrational.<br />
The contradictions in Labor's policies give Australians a plain<br />
message. Labor offers Australians nothing at a time when prudent<br />
and responsible policies are critical.<br />
oooOO0oo---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
