<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1297</transcript-id>
    <title>ANZAC DAY SPEECH MADE BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR, HAROLD HOLT TO AUSTRALIAN AND NEW ZEALAND FORCES AT BIEN HOA, SOUTH VIETNAM  25 TH APRIL 1966</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/04/1966</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001297.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIJE MINISTER' S TOUR OF SOUTH-EAST ASI A<br />
ANZAC DAY SPEECH M1ADE BY THlE PRILE h1INISTER.<br />
IMR. HAROLD HOLT TO AUSTR', LI. AN AN-' ZE1;' JLNA' D FORCES~<br />
AT BIEN HOA, SOUTH VIETNAM~. APRIL, 1966<br />
It is 51 years today since Australian, New Zealand,<br />
other British and allied forces stormed the heights of Gallipoli<br />
and together wrote an imperishable chapter in the history of our<br />
two countries. It wasn't a military success in that the objectives,<br />
the military objectives, were not achieved, but it was a victory<br />
of the spirit it revealed in young countries which hrnd not been<br />
tested in a national strife of this kind before.<br />
It tested qualities of character, of mateship of<br />
manhood and the resolution to go on with the military task, and<br />
because it developed so much significance for Australia and New<br />
Zealand and because it ma~ rked our comradeship together in arms<br />
and it crried with it the lessons for our couantrymnen of what the<br />
cause of freedom can mean to a liberty-loving people.<br />
Ye hove, from that time on, celebrated Anzac Day as<br />
perhaps the most significant commemoration in our national<br />
calendar, and wherever Australians and Nowi Zealanders are to be<br />
found around the world today, they will be pauising and<br />
commemorating this . nzac Day observance.<br />
They will be commemorating the fallen, those who gave<br />
their lives that we, in our turn, could know the blessings of<br />
liberty. But they will also be coimmemorating the national<br />
progress that we have mnadte, the progress that has bcen largcly<br />
influenced by the inspirations that flowed out ol' the Gallipoli<br />
tradition. And for you and for our own poople in our countries,<br />
and those that are in other parts of the world, Anzac Day today<br />
will be taking on a deeper significance in that here gathered<br />
again on a field of battle remote from their own countries the<br />
Anzacs are together again, fighting again, for the cause of<br />
freedom. It is characteristic of this precious boon of freedom<br />
that the battle for it is never finally won at any time or by any<br />
generation of people: each generation in their turn have to take<br />
up the challenge, the price of liberty is still eternal vigilance,<br />
and our two peoples h! ave never waited for the battles to come to<br />
them. They have clearly recognised the threat to liberty<br />
when it has emerged and they have quickly responded to. the need<br />
to come in resistance to it and again here today we see the<br />
evidence that our two countries have recognised clearly in this<br />
struggle in South Viet Nan a challenge to liberty not merely the<br />
liberty of the South Viotnamese people, but to the liberty of free<br />
peoples everywhere. </p>
<p>That is one of the factors which makes this, in my<br />
judgment, an historic struggle because if success can be achieved<br />
here then that will influence the lives of literally hundreds of<br />
millions of people throughout Asia and, perhaps, less ciirectly<br />
but importantly, it will influence what occurs around the rest of<br />
the world. So you may feel that you are engaged in an historic<br />
struggle and it is historic for one other good reason: that is<br />
that, on few occasions, can it have been said in earlier military<br />
history thant those who were actively enga gcd in the military tasks<br />
have at the same time regarded as vital to complete success, that<br />
they should engage in the constructive, positive task of assisting<br />
the people of the threatened country to build~ a better order of<br />
life for themselves. ';-hat yo-have been doin.. in your helpful, friendly<br />
positive and constructive way to assist the people of the area in<br />
which y'e served towards a better life, itself becomes a mode.<br />
on which we would hope there c'an be build a very much greater<br />
structure. It has been an inspiration to me to iind that in the<br />
Government of South Viet Nam, in the forces of the United States<br />
and other friendly forces and in our own ranks, there is this<br />
determination to make the military victory a supplement to the<br />
victory of' peace in building a better standard for the people.<br />
You in your own way have added another bright chapter<br />
to the story of Anzac.<br />
You have conducted yourselves in the finest Anzac<br />
tradition. I have hcaru. nothing but commendation wherever I have<br />
turnG-d for the contribution that the Australian and New Zealand<br />
Forces have xna: Ze.<br />
We may be snail in number but it is the quality and<br />
character of m-anhood that -makes its impact upon the people who<br />
observe what wie are doing anu you have mcasured up to those tests<br />
and have come through splendidly.<br />
Your fellow countrymen feel a pride in you that will<br />
make for them this Anzac Day one of the brightest in our<br />
celebration of that long series.<br />
They will wish that you comc successfully through your<br />
engagemnents and that you will in uue course return to your two<br />
countries which we can tref, sure as countrics of liberty countries<br />
which rank amongst the most splendid in the world for what they<br />
can give to their people.<br />
So good luck to you all and en behalf, not merely of<br />
the Government and peoplc of Australia, but cn behalf of the<br />
Government and people of New Zealand as well, we congratulate you,<br />
we thank you and we are proud of you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
