<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10355</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP LAUNCH OF NATURAL HERITAGE TRUST WENTWORTH FALLS, BLUE MOUNTAINS</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/05/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010355.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
22 May 1997 TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP<br />
LAUNCH OF NATURAL HERITAGE TRUST<br />
WENTWORTH FALLS, BLUE MOUNTAINS<br />
E O E<br />
Thank you very much Senator Robert Hill, the Leader of the Government in the<br />
Senate, and the Minister for the Environment, to my colleagues, Kerry Bartlett and Jim<br />
Lloyd, to other distinguished guests particularly the mayor in the city of the Blue<br />
Mountains, to many in the environment and landcare movement who are here today.<br />
There is no prouder day in the history of Coalition and the environment than today.<br />
The launch of the Natural Heritage Trust which represents the largest single capital<br />
investment in the environmental future of Australia. It is a great milestone in the hard<br />
march of the Australian community towards a greater and more broadly based<br />
recognition of the need to preserve, nurture and repair and build for the environmental<br />
future of this nation. It marks the fulfilment of a major election undertaking of the<br />
Liberal and National parties. I'm personally very proud of today because it is true that<br />
wandering around the beautiful environment of Hawksnest beach which is my regular<br />
habitat, I was certainly engrossed in developing an idea which had its fruition in the<br />
announcement that was made in the Dandenongs during the election campaign, and<br />
fittingly enough, given the proximity of the Blue Mountains to my home town of<br />
Sydney, fittingly enough it is formally launched here in this environmental hut at<br />
Wentworth falls.<br />
Environmental protection and building for the environment is for ever a mainstream<br />
issue in Australian politics. The days when it belonged to a radical or elite or<br />
marginalised or noisy fringe minorities, those days are gone for ever. It is now<br />
something that occupies centre stage as far as the Coalition is concerned and it is<br />
something that has drawn the support of all generations. It is not just an issue in which<br />
the young are particularly concerned, although they are deeply concerned in and<br />
committed to the future of Australia's environment, but it is one that draws the interest<br />
and the concern of all sections of the Australian community and all age groups and all<br />
socio-economic groups. And it is no longer just about forests, although they remain<br />
very important, it covers the full gamut of issues that any responsible government has<br />
to deal with. Governments must now deal with air pollution, forest biodiversity,<br />
oceans, rivers, salinity and land use to name but a few and the problems are immense.<br />
Salinity and erosion are destroying productive land on the eastern and western<br />
seaboard at a growing rate. Algal blooms threaten water supplies to towns and<br />
destruction of habitats, threatens fisheries resources. The Natural Heritage Trust of<br />
Australia is a mechanism, a very substantial mechanism for attacking these problems in<br />
a concerted and effective way. It will have five independent environmental packages.<br />
They will cover vegetation, rivers, biodiversity, land, coasts and clean seas. The<br />
Natural Heritage Trust of Australia is about the shared goals of all Australians. It's<br />
about a partnership between Australians which draws together our knowledge in areas </p>
<p>of government, science, the rural community, environment groups and the broader<br />
Australian community.<br />
It will of course make a very significant contribution to reducing unemployment.<br />
There are thousands of jobs involved in the spending proposals under the Natural<br />
Heritage Trust of Australia. This is not just an exercise in feel good. It is an exercise<br />
in tackling actual problems, building for the future in a sustainable way and in the<br />
process employing thousands of Australians, particularly in the rural and regional areas<br />
of Australia. So it is a positive thing for the Australian community on every score.<br />
Now, we had a bit of delay in getting it through the Senate because of the opposition<br />
of other parties of its establishment but I am very proud to announce its inauguration<br />
today. Of course there will be many major projects funded out of the Natural Heritage Trust<br />
of Australia, and nothing of course will be more important than the clean up of the<br />
Murray-Darling basin. Of all the things that we can do for the environmental future for<br />
Australia, making a major and effective investment in repairing the problems of the<br />
Murray-Darling basin as a centenary present to the environmental future of Australia,<br />
nothing could be more important than that, and I know that that project is one that will<br />
draw the support of all governments concerned, not only my own government but also<br />
the governments of NSW, Victoria and South Australia. And I know right across the<br />
political spectrum there will be a head nod in favour of the investment that has been<br />
made out of the Natural Heritage Trust in the rebuilding of the Murray Darling basin<br />
which is so important to the productive future of Australia, so important to the<br />
agricultural future of Australia and that is the point that Robert made that we have<br />
seen a fusion of the environmental and agricultural interests. No longer do they see<br />
themselves as competitors, they see themselves as partners in building for Australia's<br />
future. It also of course is a trust which is about a number of smaller, but nonetheless<br />
important projects, and it Is a downpayment as it were on the future investment of the<br />
Heritage Trust of Australia, I am announcing some expenditure of $ 1.5 million today<br />
to cover such things as $ 102 000 to inaudible.., recovery plan in Western<br />
Australia, in South Australia for the Kangaroo Island Black black cockatoo recovery<br />
plan and in Tasmania the Swiss Parrot recovery plan, and also an $ 800 000 to<br />
Queensland for control of rubber vine and prickly acacia as part of the national weeds<br />
strategy and we've allocated $ 922 000 for aerial survey of salinity management,<br />
something that is tremendously important. The whole challenge of salinity<br />
management both in Western Australia and also on the Eastern part of our continent is<br />
going to enable us to get a better handle on the extent of the salinity problem and allow<br />
us to forecast where future problems will occur. And it's vital information in any<br />
attempt to combat salinity and I will also be announcing, conscious of where I am, I<br />
will be announcing later today special allocation for the Hawkesbury/ Nepean regional<br />
strategy which is tremendously important for this particular area.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen, they are some of the smaller but nonetheless important details<br />
of the Natural Heritage Trust but the important message out of today is that the<br />
Government has fully delivered indeed in money terms, has slightly over-delivered on<br />
the commitment that was made in the lead up to the last election campaign.<br />
No matter what view you have about the economic management of Australia, and<br />
there is room for legitimate debate about that and I respect the range of views that<br />
exists in the Australian community, there can never be any argument that no matter </p>
<p>what view you have about the levels of Government spending and the size of the<br />
budget deficit and the investment here or there, there is always a strong argument for<br />
investing capital in rebuilding the natural assets of this country and the environment of<br />
course by definition is our greatest natural asset. It has been wasted, it has been<br />
degraded, it has been attacked, it has been spoilt and it has been badly neglected and<br />
that is a fault of all of us and it's a responsibility that the entire community must carry.<br />
What this Natural Heritage Trust does is to set aside a sum of $ 1.25 billion to be spent<br />
prudently over a period of five years in attacking some of the problems and some of<br />
the legacies of that neglect and that natural erosion. It is very much something that<br />
builds for the future of Australia. It is something that endeavours to attack the<br />
environmental challenges of our nation in a practical, on-going, sustainable fashion.<br />
It is not about the flashy, transient side of the environmental debate. It is very much<br />
about the patient, mature building approach to the environmental debate and if a<br />
government could hope in the years to come to leave behind a legacy of having done<br />
something really substantial it couldn't be doing anything prouder and more effective<br />
than this because we have recognised some problems. Over the years the quality of the<br />
investment that we're going to make will become more and more apparent and I think<br />
it will leave a great legacy for future generations.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen, I am very pleased and very proud to formally launch the Natural<br />
Heritage Trust of Australia. I want particularly to thank my colleagues, Senator<br />
Robert Hill, the Minister for the Environment and Leader of the Government in the<br />
Senate and John Anderson, the Deputy Leader of the National party and the Minister<br />
for Primary Industries and Energy. Their partnership in getting together the legislation<br />
for the Natural Heritage Trust, their partnership in making decisions about the projects<br />
which are to be funded and their partnership in symbolising the fusion of interests and<br />
the fused future of the environment and the land in Australia is something that's been a<br />
very important driving force behind this project and I warmly thank Senator Hill and I<br />
warmly thank John Anderson for the political leadership that they have given and I<br />
want to thank so many of you who have come today, some a very long distance for<br />
this little ceremony because your presence here today, so many of you holding<br />
positions of great esteem and respect in the environmental landscape here in Australia,<br />
your presence here today is very encouraging to me and very encouraging to my<br />
Government. I feel very genuinely and very enthusiastically that we have entered a new era in the<br />
environmental saga of Australia. I feel as if we are now, we have now reached the<br />
stage where we can address ourselves in a practical way to solving some of the long<br />
term problems and the long term challenges but the area of political flashiness is<br />
smaller and the area of practical achievement is greater and I think that is enormously<br />
important for the future of this country, it's enormously important for the future<br />
particularly of the younger members of our audience and I am delighted to welcome<br />
them here today as well.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen, thank you very much for your presence and I have very great<br />
pleasure in declaring open, declaring the launch, declaring and finally establishing and<br />
finally arrived, the Natural Heritage Trust of Australia.<br />
Thank you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
