<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>41635</transcript-id>
    <title>Turnbull and Hodgman Governments committed to Cradle Mountain tourism infrastructure</title>
    <prime-minister>Turnbull, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20150915 - 20180824</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/05/2018</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Turnbull and Hodgman Governments will generate jobs and tourism in Tasmania by providing $60 million for the Cradle Mountain cable-way.</p>
<p>This is a significant and game-changing investment in Tasmania’s future.</p>
<p>The cable-way will ensure a world-class visitor experience at Cradle Mountain by providing hundreds of thousands of visitors with all-year, all-weather transport between the Gateway Precinct and Dove Lake.</p>
<p>It will cement the Cradle Mountain–Lake St Clair National Park as a national natural treasure, in the same category as the Great Barrier Reef and Uluru-Kata Tjuta National Park.</p>
<p>Critically, the project will help to protect the area for generations to come and discounted tickets will be offered for the benefit of local residents.</p>
<p>Last year, more than 1.26 million people visited Tasmania, spending a total of $2.33 billion on accommodation, attractions, tours, transport and other goods and services, at an average of $1,844 per visitor.</p>
<p>In total, tourism directly and indirectly contributes more than $3 billion a year to the Tasmanian economy.</p>
<p>The cable-way will further strengthen the industry and is expected to help attract an additional 60,000 visitors a year to this important regional area.</p>
<p>It will also help to create more jobs in the tourism industry which already directly and indirectly supports around 38,000 jobs in the state through approximately 2000 businesses.</p>
<p>The Turnbull Government's $30 million investment in the cable-way follows a $30 million commitment from the Hodgman Government as part of its $35 million Cradle Mountain Experience policy at this year’s state election.</p>
<p>The joint investment will mean that more than $86 million will be invested by the Turnbull and Hodgman Government's into the Cradle Mountain Master Plan.</p>
<p>It is yet another demonstration of the commitment from both governments to improve the Tasmanian economy and create more jobs, with 17,000 more jobs having been created throughout the state since September 2013.</p>
<p>The Turnbull Government’s commitment to the Cradle Mountain Master Plan is the result of strong advocacy from independent Tasmanian Senator Steve Martin, who has lobbied passionately for additional tourism infrastructure in the region, as well as the Liberal Tasmanian Senate team.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
