<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2666</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT HON WILLIAM MCMAHON CH MP, IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES, CANBERRA - ENQUIRY INTO POVERTY - 29 AUGUST 1972</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/08/1972</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002666.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON.<br />
WILLIAM McMAHON, CH. mp, JN THE HOUSE OF<br />
REPRESENTATIVES, CANB3ERRA<br />
ENQUIRY INTO POVERTY<br />
29 AUGUST 1972<br />
I am pleased to announce that Professor R. F. Henderson,<br />
Director of the Institute of Applied Economic and Social Research<br />
3 in the University of Melbourne, has undertaken to conduct the<br />
Enquiry into Poverty on behalf of the Government.<br />
The terms of reference of the Enquiry are as<br />
follows: To investigate-The extent of poverty in Australia, including<br />
changes in its level;<br />
The incidence of poverty in Australia upon<br />
special c~ tegories of persons or localities;<br />
Factors which cause poverty in Australia;<br />
The ways in which Commonwealth and State<br />
Governments, Local Government bodies and<br />
other bodies apd persons currently assist<br />
the alleviation of poverty in Australia;<br />
the extent and effpctiveness of existing<br />
measures and services; and differenqes between<br />
and within States in the efforts of State<br />
Government, Local Government bodies and other<br />
bodies and Persons to alleviate aspects of<br />
poverty in Australia;<br />
Any diesirable changes that would contribute to<br />
the reduction of poverty in Australia; and<br />
Any associated matters relevant to the general<br />
objects of the Enquiry.<br />
The Government will ensure that Professor Henderson<br />
has the necessary supporting staff and that relevant Commonwealth<br />
Departments provide him with assistance where practicable. ./ 2 </p>
<p>Prolfessor IRenderson will himself determine the<br />
method of Enquiry to bo adopted, and the time necessary for<br />
the work to be finalised.<br />
Professor Henderson is well known for his work on<br />
poverty. Honourable Members w-, ill be aware that he and the<br />
Institute of which he is Director were responsible for " People<br />
in Poverty: A Melbourne Survey which has been of great use<br />
to all those interested in the dimensions and quality of the<br />
problem of poverty in our land. The Government is, I think,<br />
fortunate to have obtained his services for this Enquiry.<br />
It will be seen that the terms of reference for the<br />
Enquiry are very wide, having been drawn so as to enable the<br />
Enquiry to be as far-reaching as possible in its field, whilst<br />
concentrating on the solution of the immediate problem of<br />
reducing poverty in Australia.<br />
I feel confident that the decisions which I have<br />
just announced wi11 commend themselves to both sides of the<br />
House. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
