<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>17160</transcript-id>
    <title>Prime Minister Minister for Climate Change, Energy Efficiency and Water Minister for Resources and Energy Prime Minister appoints energy efficiency advisory group 30 March 2010</title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/03/2010</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Nine industry and non-government sector experts have today been announced as advisers to the Prime Minister's Task Group on Energy Efficiency.</p>
<p>Energy efficiency is a key plank of the Rudd Government's climate change agenda. Improvements in energy efficiency will help to reduce our emissions and move Australia to a low-carbon economy.</p>
<p>The Task Group comprises representatives from the Department of Climate Change and Energy Efficiency, the Department of Prime Minister and Cabinet, the Treasury, and the Department of Resources, Energy and Tourism.</p>
<p>The role of the Task Group is to:</p>
<p>     * report on the most economically and environmentally effective mechanisms to deliver major improvements in Australia's energy efficiency; and</p>
<p>     * consult with industry and community groups and seek their input on policy ideas and mechanisms to drive these changes.</p>
<p>The Task Group is today releasing an Issues Paper that will promote a broad discussion on how to achieve ambitious improvements in energy efficiency.</p>
<p>The closing date for submissions to this Issues Paper is 3 May 2010.</p>
<p>The Task Group - announced in November 2009 following extensive negotiations with the Opposition on the Carbon Pollution Reduction Scheme - will provide its findings to Government in mid-2010.</p>
<p>Further information is available at: <a href="http://www.climatechange.gov.au">www.climatechange.gov.au</a>.</p>
<p>Advisory Group Members:</p>
<p>John Connor The Climate Institute</p>
<p>Greg Bourne WWF</p>
<p>Sharan Burrow Australian Council of Trade Unions</p>
<p>Neil Marshman Rio Tinto</p>
<p>Clare Martin Australian Council of Social Service</p>
<p>Karen Moses Origin Energy</p>
<p>Rob Murray-Leach Energy Efficiency Council</p>
<p>Cameron O'Reilly Energy Retailers Association of Australia</p>
<p>Brian Spalding Australian Energy Market Commission</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
