<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9884</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P J KEATING, MP VAGUE IS BEST - JOHN HOWARD&#039;S VIEW OF NATIONAL IDENTITY</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/12/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009884.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
1/<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
VAGUE IS BEST JOHN HOWARD'S VIEW OF NATIONAL IDENTITY<br />
Mr Howard's " reflection" on Australia's national identity will go down in history<br />
as one of the most vapid statements about Australia ever delivered by an<br />
Australian political leader..<br />
It was ultra conservative ideology thinly and soporifically disguised as<br />
thoughtfulness and moderation. Mr Howard sneaks around the great issues<br />
facing Australia, offering everything but an indication of what direction he and<br />
the Coalition intend to take. On some of these key issues, Mr Howard is<br />
glaringly exposed again as a policy-free zone. For instance, Mr Howard<br />
appears to be still sitting and " reflecting" on our relationship with Asia while<br />
this real, dynamic and irreversible fact of our national life streams past him.<br />
He hangs his " reflections" not on any positive thoughts or plans he has for his<br />
country, but on a pathetic and malevolent misrepresentation of the<br />
Government's record on matters concerning Australia's Constitution and<br />
identity. The Coalition has long run a campaign of misinformation on this<br />
issue. I am flattered by his frequent references to me but they are almost<br />
without exception completely false.<br />
For the record, no one has attempted a " heist" of Australian nationalism and<br />
no fair reading of the record since I became Prime Minister could lead to that<br />
conclusion. Never have I attacked earlier generations of Australians, rather I<br />
have honoured them and made strenuous attempts to keep them in the<br />
forefront of our national consciousness. Nor for that matter, have I ever<br />
attacked the British people or the great heritage Britain left to us.<br />
Let me give him a couple of examples of what I think in fact, rather than that<br />
which is ascribed to me by the contemporary urban myth Mr Howard has<br />
attempted to manufacture. In my first speech as Prime Minister, on Australia<br />
Day 1992, I said:<br />
" Perhaps we should not be surprised if these and other profound<br />
cultural and economic changes have made many Australians wonder if<br />
the traditions of their country, the values for which they have worked 149/ </p>
<p>and fought, are not under attack. I suspect there are many Australians<br />
who are wondering if their Australia will survive the changes if there<br />
will be a place for the " old Australia" in the new.<br />
I have no doubt that the best of Australia will survive in fact it must.<br />
The hard-won traditions of democracy, of fairness and equity,<br />
individual opportunity and personal security, our way of life and those<br />
institutions which guarantee our freedom, will remain the guiding<br />
principles of Australia."<br />
In calling for an Australian Head of State, in my speech to Parliament on 7<br />
June 1995, 1 said: ' This is not because our generation lacks respect for the<br />
British monarchy, or the British people, or our British heritage, or the British<br />
institutions we have made our own, or our long friendship with the British in<br />
peace and war. On the contrary, Australians everywhere respect them, as<br />
they respect The Queen."<br />
On the arts and multiculturalism, Mr Howard offers the same clueless mixture<br />
of vapid motherhood statements and cynical misrepresentation. On the<br />
republic, if anything, he appears to be retreating. He sneaks around the<br />
issue and it is not easy to tell precisely in which direction he is pointing. The<br />
only definite thing asserted is his determination to hold a Constitutional<br />
convention a device which he himself has described as the means by which<br />
he would " kick the republic into touch".<br />
John Howard has an identity crisis. In trying to be all things to all people, he<br />
succeeds only in standing for nothing to anyone. His latest " Headland"<br />
speech is not so much about Australia's future as about John Howard's past.<br />
Howard-watchers will smile wryly at his re-visiting the Future Directions policy<br />
document of 1988. The derision with which this document was greeted when<br />
it appeared, as one of the most conservative and least original policy<br />
statements seen up to that time, no doubt helps to explain why the Leader of<br />
the Opposition is so petrified today of venturing anew into the dangerous<br />
territory of policy substance and ideas.<br />
Finally, if John Howard is unable to answer the big questions, perhaps we<br />
can help him with the small ones.<br />
First, who is the " Australian" historian, Charles Wilson, referred to in his<br />
speech? Answer an English historian who made a brief visit to Australia in<br />
the 1970s.<br />
Second, where can we find the prejudice against other than orthodox families<br />
Mr Howard challenges us to find in his utterances " over the past 20 years"?<br />
Answer try the Sunday Program, 12 November 1995.<br />
CANBERRA 13 December 1995 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
