<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5750</transcript-id>
    <title>&#039;ARRIVAL OF NATURAL GAS&#039; CANBERRA</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/02/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005750.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR MEDIA THURSDAY, 18 FEBRUARY 1982<br />
" ARRIVAL OF NATURAL GAS"<br />
CANBERRA<br />
I did not think I would be back in 19 months from having<br />
turned the sod because I thought it would take a little<br />
longer than that for the enormous amount of work that had to be<br />
done to be completed. I am glad that it has gone forward so well,<br />
so speedily and I must say that it is just as well that ~ t<br />
has gone forward well, and speedily because natural gas might<br />
be required this winter in the city of Canberra much more than<br />
it would have been under other circumstances. Perhaps I could<br />
say something about that in a moment.<br />
Natural gas is a great success 9tory for Australia. It was<br />
first discovered I think about 70 years ago, or a little more<br />
in 1910 and in 1969 Adelaide, Brisbane, and Melbourne had<br />
access to natural gas and in the years since of course, there<br />
has been very significant extensions into<br />
country areas. In 1980 the demand was five times the demand<br />
of 1971 and that obviously is as a result of greater access<br />
to natural gas by more communities, but also as a result of<br />
changed energy pricin gwhich in many ways has encouraged<br />
greater use of natural gas.<br />
I think in broad terms our energy policy is working and workingr<br />
well. In 1981 there was a projected expenditure of $ 14 billion, in<br />
1982 it is estimated to be double that at $ 2 billion exploration<br />
and developmrent and that really is a record figure, in money<br />
terms and In. real terms. It is<br />
five or six times the amount of exploration of development<br />
that was taking place in 1975 and that indicates I think, the<br />
growth of confidence in this industry since those times.<br />
The arrival of natural gas in Canberra is a significant development<br />
for this city, and-Queanbeyan. It is not just going to<br />
help housewives with their cooking and whatever, but it will<br />
provide priv,; ate enterprise in Canberra with an opportunity<br />
to attract greater numbers of industries to Canberra and to help<br />
in the drive! in making the private sector less dependent than<br />
it now is on governments, what governments do and what<br />
governments spend. I know that is very much-the wish of / 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
private enterprise in the ACT and I hope that natural gas,<br />
being available will be a useful, significant help in that<br />
regard. I There is going to be a significant fuel<br />
oil saving as a result of this move of 30 million litres in<br />
this year and nearly 70 million litres by 1987. Those figures<br />
might prove to be conservative because I believe that natural<br />
gas for the citizens of Canberra, the industries of Canberra<br />
will have reliability of supply. That I think, is encouraging<br />
and it is obviously very important. I don't know how many<br />
of you are aware that the Minister, Michael Hodgman is going<br />
to have to introduce legislation to give us powers for emergency<br />
rationing through this winter because there is no reliability<br />
of supply from NSW. It is an unusual fact that 20% of<br />
Canberra's current supply comes from Victoria and if it wasn't<br />
for the increased power output from my own State, the citizens<br />
of Sydney would be feeling the present power situation in NSW<br />
very seriously indeed.<br />
I don't know how many of you know really what has happened<br />
but there are four major generators in Lydell, the major<br />
NSW supply station, and three of those generators have<br />
gone out of action at one time. If it is a generator in a<br />
motor car we just take it off and get it re-wound relatively<br />
quickly, but for this operation 40 or 50 people have had to<br />
come out from the United Kingdom, quite specifically to re-wind<br />
these generators and I am sure it would their view that if<br />
there had been proper maintenance that would not be necessary.<br />
It is an odd thing in a country like Australia when, I hope<br />
you won't mind me saying this because it is really a factual<br />
situation rather than a political one, governments have to<br />
advertise the immorality of having showers, trying to suggest<br />
that people should only have a very brief shower.<br />
If that fourth generator went, and there must be a great fear<br />
in the NSW system that that would happen, the supply situation<br />
in NSW would obviously be enormously and immediately serious.<br />
In these circumstances, the rationing that has been<br />
projected as a possibility for industry would probably become<br />
a reality. These are matters that are obviously going to<br />
take some time to overcome. It is not a question of installed<br />
capacity, it is a question of being able to maintain the<br />
capacity that has been installed and to get a reasonable<br />
amount of power generation out of it. Because Canberra up<br />
to this point has been so dependent on NSW, the arrival of<br />
natural gas at this point is obviously welcomed and if<br />
electricity fails I would imagine that we can guarantee that<br />
natural gas will flow through the course/ this year and through<br />
this winter. of question<br />
I would like to congratulate you for bringing this/ to completion<br />
so successfully and so quickly. It is timely and it is an<br />
effective move and so I would like to thank everybody who<br />
has been involved in it for bringing it to this point so<br />
speedily and so efficiently. 000... </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
