<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7390</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER PARLIAMENTARY LUNCHEON IN HONOUR OF THE PRIME MINISTER OF WESTERN SAMOA, TOPILAU ETI ALESANA CANBERRA - 30 AUGUST 1988</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/08/1988</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007390.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
PARLIAMENTARY LUNCHEON IN HONOUR OF THE<br />
PRIME MINISTER OF WESTERN SAMOA,<br />
TOFILAU ETI ALESANA<br />
CANBERRA 30 AUGUST 1988<br />
Prime minister Tofilau Eti Alesana and Mrs Tofilau<br />
Minister for Economic Affairs Tanuvasa Livi and Mrs Tanuvasa<br />
Distinguished guests<br />
Ladies and gentlemen<br />
Last year I had the pleasure of paying a visit to<br />
Western Samoa to attend the meeting of the South Pacific<br />
Forum. Over the years the Forum has proven an invaluable sounding<br />
board for Pacific leaders to discuss the many issues which<br />
confront our region. Last year, meeting in the wake of the<br />
tragic events in Fiji, the Forum had a particularly<br />
important role to play and our meeting was a particularly<br />
successful one.<br />
It showed the constructive role which Western Samoa plays in<br />
our region. It also gave me the opportunity to renew my<br />
acquaintance with you, Prime Minister, and with other<br />
distinguished Western ' Samo-an leaders.<br />
It is a particular pleasure to welcome yoU and Mrs Tofilau<br />
and your party to Canberra today. This is your third<br />
official visit to Australia in five years, Prime Minister.<br />
We recall with pleasure your earlier visits to attend the<br />
Forum meeting in Canberra in 1983 and your working visit in<br />
1985.<br />
Australia and Western Samoa enjoy a close and cooperative<br />
relationship, both bilaterally and on regional issues. Our<br />
two countries have maintained diplomatic relations since<br />
Western Samoa achieved formal independence in 1962. we<br />
maintain a friendly and productive dialogue on a wide<br />
variety of issues ranging from trade to aid, and from<br />
cultural cooperation to defence cooperation. And I night<br />
say, Prime Minister, that Australians have developed a great<br />
respect for rugby players from your country and we are<br />
looking forward to the tour which the Western Samoan team<br />
will make here next year. I 1583 </p>
<p>As well as in the Forum, we have worked closely together in<br />
the South Pacific Commission. Together with our regional<br />
neighbours we achieved' an important regional objective with<br />
the Treaty of Rarotonga, which established the South Pacific<br />
Nuclear Free Zone. We have also worked to achieve the<br />
Convention for the Protection of the Natural Resources and<br />
the Environment of the South Pacific region, and our work on<br />
the Law of the Sea and regional fisheries issues further<br />
shows how constructively we can work together.<br />
Prime Minister,<br />
Australia is this year celebrating the 200th anniversary of<br />
European settlement on this continent. We are celebrating<br />
the creation of a nation which is free, prosperous,<br />
independent and democratic -but we have also come to a<br />
clearer recognition of just how short those two centuries<br />
are in terms of the history of our own continent as well as<br />
in regional terms.<br />
The culture of Atistralian Aboriginal and Islander people<br />
extends back over more than 40,000 years, and I believe<br />
non-Aboriginal Australians are increarsingly coming to<br />
recognise and to appreciate the richness of that culture.<br />
In regional terms, sophisticated and prosperous Pacific<br />
island societies were in existence long before they were<br />
discovered by the Europeans.<br />
A thriving Samoan society, a proud sense of Samoan identity<br />
and a rich and unique Samoan cultural tradition, have<br />
existed for many centuries.<br />
The struggle to preserve or regain independence from foreign<br />
domination has been a recurring theme in Samoan history. It<br />
is therefore no surprise that-when in 1962 western Samoa<br />
achieved independence it was the first Pacific Island<br />
country in this century to do so.<br />
So today, Prime Minister,' Ilpay tribute to the long history<br />
of the Samoan people and to their considerable achievements<br />
in building an independent and free nation.<br />
In our Bicentennial year, we are grateful for the genero Ius<br />
involvement of our friends from overseas in many<br />
Bicentennial events, in particular at the World Expo 88 in<br />
Brisbane which you will be visiting shortly.<br />
One of the very memorable features of Expo is the combined<br />
South Pacific village, lagoon and entertainment area to<br />
which western Samoa has contributed.<br />
At the 5th Festival of Pacific Arts in Townsville wh~ ere<br />
Western Samoan men and women performed traditional songs and<br />
dances we were given another insight into your rich culture.<br />
8 4 </p>
<p>4<br />
3.<br />
Through its involvement in these events, Western Samoa has,<br />
with justifiable pride, given many thousands of Australiansthe<br />
rare and important chance to experience and to<br />
understand the culture of the South Pacific. We are<br />
grateful to you for that..<br />
Prime Minister,<br />
Our two Governments share a common vision of a Pacific<br />
region that is peaceful, politically stable and firmly on<br />
the road of economic and social development for the benefit<br />
of all its peoples.<br />
our region is currently in the process of far-reaching<br />
change perhaps of a magnitude which will exceed the impact<br />
of European culture and technology in the last century.<br />
We cannot foresee the full impact on our region of current<br />
economic, social, cultural and technological developmentsnor<br />
can we predict the political consequences of such<br />
change. But Western Samoa demonstrates how successfully traditional<br />
Pacific societies can achieve economic development, while<br />
preserving the central values and elements of their culture.<br />
That is a very significant lesson to us all.<br />
Prime Minister,<br />
I again welcome you to Austral ia. Your presence reminds us<br />
of the diversity of our Pacific region, and of the<br />
substantial history and achievements of our Pacific.<br />
neighbours. I am confident the cooperative, Pacific<br />
partnership that has evolved between Western Samoa and<br />
Australia will prosper to the mutual advantage of our<br />
peoples. I d<br />
1 8, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
