<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>24051</transcript-id>
    <title>Remarks at ecumenical church service, Melbourne</title>
    <prime-minister>Abbott, Tony</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130918 - 20150915</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/12/2014</release-date>
    <release-type>Transcript</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Reverend fathers, Your Excellencies, ladies and gentlemen. To President Petro Poroshenko, my friend, thank you for that splendid address. A little bit of it was translated to me and all I can see in response is that shirtfront must have translated well!</p>
<p>In the summer of 1982, I was walking the streets of Kiev. I heard music coming from a church, not unlike this. I went inside and was utterly spellbound by the singing. It was truly the voice of men and angels and it is such a pleasure to hear it again today.</p>
<p>I thought to myself then it may be only people who suffer for their faith that truly know what faith is.</p>
<p>Stalin used to boast that religion would die out in the Soviet Union because Russia would one day run out of grannies. Well, Russia never did, no country ever has and each generation in turn has found its faith because faith arouses something deep in the human heart.</p>
<p>I'm reminded of the story of the funeral of the Russian dictator, Leonid Brezhnev. He had devoted his life to an ideology that stamped out all opposition, persecuted those of faith and sought to impose the will of large countries on small ones.</p>
<p>But at his funeral, after the last regiment had marched past and the last state anthem had been sung and as the open coffin was about to be closed, his widow leaned over and made the sign of the cross on her husband's chest.</p>
<p>The survival of faith, the flourishing of faith and the survival and the flourishing of the nations that are sustained by it – what a marvellous story.</p>
<p>Here, in this splendid church, I should acknowledge the part that faith has played in our culture and in our public life, in the culture and public life of civilised countries. Our democracy is inspired by the gospel insight that every human being is born with equal rights and dignity in the eyes of God. Our justice is inspired by the gospel insight that each of us should treat others as we would have them treat us in turn.</p>
<p>Today, we pray for the victims of the MH17 atrocity. We pray for all 298 of them. We particularly pray for the 38 Australians who are amongst them. We pray for their families in their time of grief and loss.</p>
<p>We acknowledge the Ukrainian people who did so much for them in that terrible time and who continue to work with Australians, Dutch and Malaysians to ensure that the perpetrators of that atrocity are brought to justice.</p>
<p>I particularly acknowledge today the President of Ukraine, Petro Poroshenko.</p>
<p>Israel aside, there would hardly be a country on earth so subject to existential threat as Ukraine is.</p>
<p>If the freedom of one country is diminished, the freedom of all is diminished.</p>
<p>I have come to know Petro Poroshenko quite well over the last few months and I want to say that not just Ukraine, but freedom has a great champion in Ukraine's President.</p>
<p>Today, in this cathedral, we pray for all countries and all peoples striving for peace with freedom. We pray for all people striving for rights and respect. We pray for them all and we ask that the good Lord, the living God, will give them strength and success.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
