<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4761</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/07/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004761.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS 23 July 1978<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
At a time of economic difficulty, the jobs of thousands of<br />
Australians are in jeopardy because of the calculated<br />
activities of a secion of the union movement.<br />
Existing jobs are now at risk, while opportunities for the<br />
unemployed are being shut out because of the continuing drive<br />
by key unions for wage increases clearly outside Conciliation<br />
and Arbitration guidelines.<br />
This selfish campaign is an attempt to frustrate the Government's<br />
efforts to restore economic health to Australia and is directly<br />
contrary to the interests of Australian workers.<br />
Latest of ficial figures show that inflation in the 12 months<br />
to March was running at an annual rate of 8.2 percent. In<br />
that same period, wages, salaries and supplements are shown<br />
in the national accounts as having grown by 9.5 percent.<br />
Figures also show that average minimum wage rates for the<br />
March quarter, 1978 were over 9 percent higher than for the<br />
March quarter last year.<br />
This evidence exposes the union claims as an exercise at<br />
running full steam ahead in an " I'm all right Jack" attitude.<br />
if this-campaign succeeds, more jobs will be lost and others<br />
put at risk.<br />
In talks I have had with factory, office and farm workers it is<br />
clear that this kind of activity simply does not have rank and<br />
file support. They know from bitter experience where. this<br />
kind of mad exercise leads industries become uncompetitive<br />
and jobs are lost.<br />
In 1974 and 1975, wages increased by over 50 percent. This<br />
priced industry out of business, and put thousands of people<br />
out of jobs.<br />
That is why we have, from our first days in office, argued<br />
strongly and consistently before the Arbitration Commission<br />
for wage restraint.<br />
Clearly, in this kind of climate, the ACTU must be prepared<br />
to stand up and accept responsibility for the strike damage.<br />
The ACTU invited these disputes by passing official resolutions ./ 2 </p>
<p>2.<br />
in March and July this year, urging affiliated unions to<br />
carry out on-the-job campaigns for more money in defiance of<br />
decisions of the Conciliation and Arbitration Commission.<br />
This shows a disregard for-the responsibility the ACTU should<br />
have to its members those with jobs, and those looking for<br />
jobs. It is hypocrisy for the ACTU to talk about high unemployment<br />
and to blame Governments and employers while it condones this<br />
kind of behaviour.<br />
The ACTU is in a position to step in and stop this needless<br />
disruption. It has previously said it will not support wildcat<br />
strikes which disrupt public life.<br />
The Government hopes and I am sure we are supported by most<br />
Australians that the ACTU will show it is genuinely concerned<br />
to protect the interests of all Australian trade unionists.<br />
They can do this quite easily by calling a stop to these damaging<br />
strikes. The disputes I am talking about have been all too familiar.<br />
They have hit in key areas, with a minimum number of people<br />
involved and causing maximum disruption.<br />
The current list of industrial disputes demonstrates this point.<br />
The Metal Trades Unions have imposed a series of work bans;<br />
The Vehicle Builders Employees Federation have joined them<br />
with bans including an indefinite overtime ban. This is<br />
despite a warning by the Arbitration Commission that they would<br />
threaten the jobs of more industrial workers by so doing;<br />
Railway and Transport Unions are campaigning for wage claims<br />
clearly outside the guidelines; The umbrella Central Mining<br />
Unions are involved in wage disputes with the Utah Company.<br />
one recent invidious, practice is that of " guerilla" action<br />
where ! ielective and discriminatory pressure is put on a company<br />
that refuses to negotiate outside indexation guidelines. The<br />
Storeman and Packers Union seems particularly disposed to this<br />
tactic. Such pressure must be resisted if we are to prevent a renewed<br />
outbreak of wage escalation and inflation in Australia.<br />
Companies involved deserve our unanimous and whole-hearted<br />
support and encouragement.<br />
The Builders Labourers Federation also continues to engage in<br />
senseless guerilla tactics. In recent days it has placed bans<br />
on a $ 150 m. bank building project in Melbourne. Building<br />
work has now stopped and workmen have been stood down. On<br />
top of that, there are other building projects not proceeding<br />
because of the tactics of that particular union.<br />
Clearly, that union is continuing with deliberate attempts to<br />
thwart the Government and to stop builders labourers from working<br />
and from keeping jobs. ./ 3 </p>
<p>3.<br />
While this kind of attitude persists within the trade union<br />
movement and irrespective of any Government's industrial<br />
relations policies the job of reducing unemployment will<br />
be made very difficult.<br />
How can employers take on new workers when unions take action<br />
to raise excessively the price of their own labour?<br />
This kind of selfish campaign not only hits at their own<br />
membership but at the heart of national interest.<br />
Australia will not overcome economic problems and reduce<br />
unemployment until all sections, all groups work together<br />
in a common commitment.<br />
Every Australian and especially every leader, every government<br />
has a part to play in arousing that spirit.<br />
At this time, as a nation, we cannot afford to put selfseeking<br />
sectional interests on a pedestal and pursue them regardless<br />
of cost or consequence.<br />
What Australia has built and achieved what our country<br />
promises is too precious, too rare to risk losing.<br />
o0o---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
