<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1931</transcript-id>
    <title>PATERSON FEDERAL ELECTORATE CONFERENCE ANNUAL DINNER AT MAITLAND TOWN HALL - MAITLAN, N.S.W. - 30 SEPTEMBER 1968 - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. JOHN GORTON</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/09/1968</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001931.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PATERSON FEDERAL ELECTORATE CONFERENCE<br />
ANNUAL DINNER AT MAITLAND TOWN HALL<br />
MA rILAND, N. S. W. SEPTYEMBER 1968<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister, Mr. John Gorton<br />
Mr. Chairman, Allen, Sir Alister, Distinguished Guests and Ladies and<br />
Gentlemen: When I first received a suggestion that I might come and<br />
talk to you tonight, I saw with a certain amount of horror that it was<br />
suggested that there should be no limit on my speech.<br />
Before I come to talk to any gathering of this kind, my wife<br />
keeps reminding me of a quatrain which I think it would be a good thing<br />
for all politicians to remember all the time, and that quatrain is:-<br />
" I love a finished speaker,<br />
1 really, truly do,<br />
I don't mean one who's polished,<br />
I just mean one who's through.<br />
And so it won't be without limitation of time before I am through.<br />
I would like to say some few things to you. Cne is that<br />
speaking for my wife and myself, we have felt, on this visit to Maitland,<br />
both during the Civic Reception and during the time we have spent with<br />
you and during the time we have talked with the too few of you with whom<br />
we have been able to converse, that in a way we feel at home because we,<br />
too, come from country areas, country areas not quite so blessed as this,<br />
After all, we have where we come from, an eleven-inch<br />
annual rainfall -when we get it, and we don't often get it -and you have an<br />
annual rainfall which apparently varies very considerably, but which by and<br />
large enables ( except when you are sailing dinghies in the Town Hall here<br />
where I stand today) more production and more ease of production than occurs<br />
in the rather hot dry area we come from.<br />
But the feeling has been the same, the feeling of people who<br />
are out, by and large, on the land, doing things on the land, coping with<br />
natural disasters, coping with the difficulties of price, of production, of<br />
season, and carrying on, as Australians have carri~ d on for a couple of<br />
hundred years now. Carrying on against the flood and fire and famine which<br />
are a part of what is, basically, a rather hard land, and people who perhaps<br />
as a result of that, or perhaps because of some innate Australianism I<br />
don't know say, " All right. Well, it's tough this year, but it will be better<br />
next year. There is always going to be another season. Maybe the prices<br />
will go up. Maybe there will be better production, and who through it all<br />
have a kind of friendly relationship which extends throughout the areas of<br />
the country of Australia. We have felt at home with you, and I can only hope<br />
that during this brief visit you have begun to feel at home with us. </p>
<p>-2<br />
You have got, if I may say so, one of the best Federal<br />
representatives in Canberra of any electorate in Australia. Indeed, for<br />
myself, who tends to fly off a little at angles, who tends to get swept<br />
away with enthusiasm, it is of immense advantage to have somebody who<br />
says, " Yes, that's wonderful, but just a moment, let's look at the<br />
practicalities of this situation. Let's see whether it will work or not.<br />
Let's see whether this in fact is going to turn out the way you want it to<br />
turn out. It is of enormous advantage, and I am always prepared to<br />
recognise that there can be two points of view mine, and onae that is<br />
probably wrong: I am happy to say that on most occasions, mine and<br />
Allen's tend to coincide, and those who as he explained to you happens<br />
in a Cabinet those who have quite properly other questions to raise are,<br />
for the most part, probably wroing. When they are not wrong, I think<br />
both of us agree with the majority and we come out as he has said we do,<br />
with a Government policy backed by all of us, whom you have elected, to<br />
try and govern this country.<br />
We both came in, Allen and I, and Sir Alister, in 1949, and<br />
this is now some twenty years ago two decades. We only came in under<br />
the leadership at that time because people who are in this room today, or<br />
people who have taken the place and had the same ideals as people who<br />
were in a room like this in ! 949, brought us in to off ice at that stage, and<br />
we took over a nation which then was comparatively small. I don't know<br />
the precise numbers maybe seven million, maybe seven million and a<br />
half but we took over a nation which our opponents at the time said was<br />
a nation which if it had seven per cent of unemployed, then had reached<br />
the best ratio of employment the nation could hope to have; took over a<br />
nation in which government interfered, greatly, in almost all aspects of<br />
individual endeavour; took over a nation in which development had hardly<br />
started. And because of what those who are now in this room did, and the<br />
ideals they had, and the ideals their successors are still propagating, we<br />
have in the course of two decades, we and you raised the nation from<br />
seven and a half to twelve million, stopped interference in too great detail<br />
with the individual initiative which alone can enable a country to progress.<br />
Given a climate which enables those who are prepared to take risks, to<br />
take risks, and to garner the fruits of the risks they take or accept the<br />
losses of the risks they take personally, and which because individuals<br />
are enabled to do this to garner the fruits or to talke the risks have<br />
brought this nation to a point of international take-off which would have<br />
been unthought of two decades ago.<br />
I don't mean that in that period of time there have not been<br />
some mistakes made by government. If there is anybody in this room today,<br />
whether he be an industrialist, a manager, somebody on a farm, who can<br />
look back for two decades and say at no stage did I make a mistake, then<br />
that man is a miracle man because almost always, over a long period of<br />
time when decisions have to be made, some of them will, in the light of<br />
future circumstances, be wrong. But I believe that I can say on behalf of<br />
the Government to which Allen and I and Sir Alister belong, that though<br />
there have been on occasions some decisions which might not stand up to<br />
examination afterwards, there have probably been fewer decisions of that<br />
kind than have been taken by any government I know of in any country in the<br />
world. And when I say this, this is no tribute to me, for I have just lately<br />
taken up this position. This is a tribute to the people you have elected to<br />
the national parliament and to the way they have worked together and to the<br />
vision they have had of what Australia ought to be. And this is something<br />
which in the future can only be continued and will be continued, I know, from<br />
this gathering tonight, by the support given by those who say, " I think these </p>
<p>S.<br />
people have the right idea. I think these people have an objective for our<br />
nation which is the objective which I in my heart have got. I will work for<br />
them. I will ( as somebody said to me tonight) come hail, come snow, come<br />
rain, hand out how-to-vote cards for them. I will argue for them, because,<br />
in the main and on the whole, we have the same objectives. This is one<br />
of the great sustenances of a Prime Minister that there are, throughout<br />
Australia, so many people of the kind who are here tonight who will do this<br />
work, who will give this trust because they believe that what they want will<br />
eventually be achieved. We, as is common with all nations at all times, have great<br />
problems before us at the moment. It is probably true that in Australia<br />
we have reached a watershed, a time of decision in many, many fields,<br />
and that those tenets on which previously we built our policy are not any<br />
longer to be accepted without question.<br />
In the field in which your Member is particularly interested,<br />
that of Defence, we find ourselves in Australia in a completely changed<br />
world situation. For almost two hundred years we lived under the protection<br />
of the British Navy and England, and we did little or nothing to help ourselves<br />
in between the crises that occurred in the world. We left it to others to<br />
protect us, except, of course, that when the Boer War'broke out, or the<br />
First World War broke out, or the Second World War broke out, or the<br />
Malayan emergency broke out, or the Korean war broke out, then we came<br />
in as a people, wholeheartedly and completely. And though in between<br />
times we did not pay much attention to it, I still think, looking back on that<br />
history that " if blood be the price of admiralty, Lord God we have paid<br />
in full". But that has changed. We do not have and will not have this<br />
protection from abroad any more. We ourselves must protect ourselves,<br />
and this calls for resources which I do not myself wish or like to give<br />
resources that must be diverted to ships and soldiers and aircraft and<br />
guns and ammunition resources I would prefer to devote to development<br />
and to social progress. But these resources must be diverted, according<br />
to the judgment of your Government if we are, in the changed situation of<br />
the world, to be able to take the first brunt of any attack which in the<br />
future may fall upon us and to help in maintaining stability in the area to<br />
our north a situation which has never faced this nation before but which<br />
now faces us in all stark reality.<br />
And as that occurs, we have before us the challenge of<br />
developing the nation itself, a challenge which holds before us a vision<br />
that previously was never known to the people of this country. Gradually<br />
we have grown since the first settlement was made at Port Phillip, gradually<br />
the tempo of our growth has increased, but latterly the tempo of our growth<br />
has almost got out of control. We are growing in geometric progression.<br />
The things that we need to do and can do, and the opportunities before us<br />
are flowering in a way they have never flowered before.<br />
And so we find that in Bass Strait we strike oil which gives<br />
us defence capacity, which gives us a saving of overseas exchange, which<br />
gives us a control of our own capacity, which people once thought we would<br />
never have. And so we have in Western Australia, in the Northern Territory,<br />
in Queensland, great new mineral prospects opening up which will require<br />
billions of dollars orf private capital to bring to fruition, which will require<br />
not only the tearing from the earth of the ore and the resources which are<br />
there but the fabrication of the ore and resources through the various / 4 </p>
<p>4-<br />
processes to the finished product. This will make us, God willing, one<br />
of the great industrial nations of the world, but requiring billions of private<br />
capital, hundreds of millions of governmental capital something which<br />
two decades one decade previously was unthought of in this nation.<br />
And we have, I think, a public conscience which has woken,<br />
and which says, yes, in the years past we have said a government ought to<br />
take note of those who are ill and those who are aged and those who are<br />
handicapped; a government ought to contribute towards the maintenance<br />
of these people, but it should only contribute, and it should take the stand<br />
that families and charities should provide and a government should only<br />
add the topping to what is provided; a public conscience which says this<br />
is no longer good enough we ought to see if we are an affluent society,<br />
that there is no-one in this land who does not have the capacity for a frugal<br />
living when they are old or when they are ill or when they are in some other<br />
way suffering the slings and arrows of outrageous fortune.<br />
For myself, I have left the concept of a contribution towards<br />
the living costs of people of this kind and accepted on behalf of the<br />
Government and of the Liberal Party that what is required is to see thal<br />
nobody starves, that nobody has to have blankets bought for them, that<br />
people of that kind can live in reasonable dignity and with frugality and<br />
are provided with enough for that. And this is something which is different<br />
from that which previously was accepted.<br />
I have sketched in only a few of the challenges which face<br />
us now. With these before us as a people, it is necessary to look again<br />
at some of the dogmas which two decades ago were uncritically accepted,<br />
because perhaps two decades ago, they were valid, they were reasonable,<br />
and this is something which we as a party have got to do. I speak as a<br />
party now, not so much as I have been in the past few minutes, as a people.<br />
When we formed the Liberal Party in 1945, when we came<br />
to Government in 1949, two decades ago, all of us accepted and all of us<br />
believed that the sole task of an Australian Government was to act in a<br />
sense as an honest broker, and that the governments of the various divisions<br />
of Australia ought to take the full responsibility for the educational requirements<br />
of a State, for the hospital requirements of a State, for the road<br />
requirements, for all the other matters which were then, and still are, for<br />
a large part, their responsibility.<br />
But in that period of two decades, there has grown up in<br />
the minds of the Australian people, as I believe I may be wrong, but<br />
as I believe a requirement that an Australian Government should see<br />
that no matter in what part of this nation a child may be born, it should<br />
have the same facilities provided for its education as are provided i~ n any<br />
other part of this nation. There has grown up as I believe a requirement<br />
that if a person gets ill in any part of this nation, then an Australian<br />
Government should see that the opportunities for treatment of that illness<br />
are the same in any part of this nation. There has grown up a requirement<br />
for an Australian Government to take a responsibility, a financial<br />
responsibility to see that these things happen.<br />
And what we need to question now are the dogmas of twenty<br />
years ago and to see how, if a change is necessary and I think it is how<br />
such a change can be worked out, to see that the facilities for education,<br />
that the facilities for health, that t-he facilities for roads, that the facilities<br />
in other directions are the same, while avoiding centralist administrative<br />
coatrol from Canberra. This is going to be one of the siginif icant questions<br />
to be decided in this nation of ours in the future. This </p>
<p>is one of the questions that those who support the Liberal Party should<br />
consider and to which they should direct their minds, not with adherence<br />
to dogma, but with questioning of everything, with questioning of what a<br />
State Government puts forward or a Commonwealth Government puts<br />
forward, but with an attempt to arrive at a solution which will in the end<br />
be best for the nation as a whole.<br />
For if there is one thing of which I am convinced, it is this,<br />
that we have reached a stage in our national history when there is in the<br />
hearts of Australians in Western Austrcalia, in Quee-nsland in Tasmania<br />
or wherever it may be, a burgeoning belief in our nationalism, a burgeoning<br />
faith in ourselves as Australians first. There is a knowledge that what<br />
happens in great development in any part of this continent benefits all parts<br />
of this continent, and a feeling I believe a justified feeling that we should,<br />
as nationals of a country which has much to be proud of, hold up our heads,<br />
be proud of what we have done in the past, look forward with faith and hope<br />
to the future, not as New South Welshmen, not as Victorians, not as West<br />
Australians, but as people who belong to the nation of Australia first.<br />
If I can spread throughout the confines of this continent<br />
that belief which I think is held in the hearts of the people who live in it,<br />
if you can help me spread throughout the confines of this continent that<br />
belief, then I think we will have made the greatest step forward since<br />
this nation was first founded so short a time ago.<br />
I remember and for light relief I tell you this story<br />
something which was told to me when I was at Mt. Tom Price not long ago,<br />
when Mr. Heath, the Leader of the Opposition in the United Kingdom, was<br />
out here. He was being taken around Mt. Tom Price by Mr. Court, the<br />
Minister for Industrial Development in Western Australia. Mr. Heath<br />
particularly wanted to meet an Australian working at Mt. Tom Price.<br />
Mr. Court took him to a group of men who were working there, and he<br />
went to one and said " Are you an Australian?" and he said, " No, I come<br />
from London. He went to another and said, " Are you an Australian?"<br />
and he said, " No, I come from Poland. I only came out here a short time<br />
ago. He went to another one and he said, " No, I'm not an Australian. I<br />
come from Czechoslovakia. Finally, they came to somebody who clearly<br />
was an Australian. I don't know how to describe it, but you know what an<br />
Australian is he talked like an Australian, he looked like an Australian,<br />
he rolled a cigarette like an Australian, he leant against things like an<br />
Australian Finally Charles Court thought he had got Heath to meet an<br />
Australian. He said, " Well, here you are. Surely you're an Australian.<br />
The bloke said, " No, I'm a Victorian. So he gave up. But I haven't given<br />
up. You haven't given up. Because the real future of this country, the<br />
achievement of what is possible for us is if we all first say we are Australian,<br />
and then we are New South Welshmen, and then we are people from Maitland<br />
but first, we are the members of a nation destined to be great.<br />
This is what, I think, the Liberal Party as such should seek<br />
to achieve, and in achieving it because, perhaps, I have spoken in<br />
generalities must keep in mind what was one of the first tenets of this<br />
party when it was formed, and that was that it was dedicated to individual<br />
freedom and the greatest possible amount of individual initiative, that<br />
people could take risks and reap rewards, or that people could take risks<br />
and if they made bad judgments, reap the consequences.<br />
But what do people want? What do those Australians of whom<br />
you are representative want? What should a-political party seek to give<br />
them? Well we know some of the answers. We know the material answers.,<br />
/ 6 </p>
<p>6-<br />
We know they want more development. We know they wan,,-t better hospitals.<br />
We know they want better education. We know they want better townplanning.<br />
We know they wiant more sewerage or at least I am told so<br />
by the Leader of the Cpposition well, it may turna out that we have<br />
an argument as to whether we want an affluent or an effluent society. But<br />
I think that over and above these things on which we can argue, and discuss<br />
and argue properly, that people want more than that.<br />
They want, I think, a feeling that in what they are doing in<br />
their daily life they are not only seeking their own material advancement,<br />
they are not only wanting to improve the farm on which they live or expand<br />
the business in which they are employed though these are important both<br />
for themselves and for the nation but they want a feeling, I think, that<br />
the efforts that they put in are for an end which is above and beyond their<br />
own particular material advancement. They want a feeling that what they<br />
are doing is not only helping themselves but contributing to the community<br />
in which they live, that they are helping the advancement of the community,<br />
that they are bringing into existence, perhaps, a nation which can be great<br />
materially, which can be great in terms of strength of defence, which cans<br />
be great in compassion, which can be one step forward along the road<br />
towards which nations throughout history have striven but so far have<br />
striven in various degrees in vain but which I think we here have the<br />
greatest opportunity of any nation in history, ultimately, to achieve.<br />
This is what I think people want to be called on for sacrifice<br />
as well as to be given the opportu-.-ity for individual betterment, and this<br />
is what, w~ ith your support and the support of my colleagues, this Government<br />
will seek to bring about and will seek to evoke in the hearts of the Australian<br />
people. A long time ago somebody it may have been Banjo Paterson<br />
think it was wrote these lines about Australia:-<br />
" We see the vision splendid of the sunlit plains extended<br />
And at night, the wondrous glory of the everlasting stars."<br />
We can and are gettinrg ito our hearts and minds the vision splendid of what<br />
this nation can be, and if we do not reach the stars, at least we can aspire<br />
towards them, and strive towards them, and according to the degree of our<br />
competence, of our efforts, according to the degree to which we reach them,<br />
so we will have contributed not only to this nation but to the evolution of<br />
mankind towards the kind of world we all want to live in.<br />
You have helped in this. You have helped me tonight by<br />
coming here. I look to you to continue this help in the future.<br />
Thank you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
