<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1686</transcript-id>
    <title>Joint Communique – Discussions with the Prime Minister of Japan</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/10/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001686.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>At the invitation of the Government of the Commonwealth of Australia, Mr Eisaku Sato, Prime Minister of Japan, accompanied by Mrs Sato, is visiting, Australia from October 11 to October 14, 1957.</p>
<p>During his stay in Australia, Prime Minister Sato is visiting Canberra, Melbourne and Sydney. Mr. Sato met Mr Holt and other Ministers, and a frank exchange of views on current international problems and other matters of common concern to Australia and Japan took place. The discussions were held in a most cordial atmosphere, contributing greatly to the deepening of mutual understanding between the two countries.</p>
<p>The Prime Ministers reaffirmed that the maintenance of peace and stability in Asia was the common aspiration of their two countries. In this respect the situation in Viet Nam was of deep concern to both countries. The two Prime Ministers discussed ways and means of bringing about an early and just settlement of the conflict.</p>
<p>The Prime .Ministers affirmed their resolve to strengthen further their support of the United Nations so as to enable this organisation to contribute more effectively to the maintenance of peace, and expressed their hope that in the field of disarmament a non-proliferation treaty of nuclear weapons will be concluded at an early date in such a form as to enable as many countries as possible to join the treaty.</p>
<p>The Prime Ministers, affirming that economic development in Asian countries was the basis of their political stability, emphasised the need for developed countries to assist developing Asian nations in their efforts to achieve faster rates of economic growth. In this connection, the Prime h1inisters stressed the importance of co-operation for the prosperity of the Asian and Pacific region. They agreed to continue their efforts to support the various activities of such organisations as ECAFE, (Economic Commission for Asia and the Far East) the Colombo Plan, the Asian Development Bank and ASPAC.</p>
<p>The Prime Ministers expressed their satisfaction at the fact that the friendly and co-operative relationship between the two countries was being further strengthened in recent years in the political, economic and cultural fields. They noted, in particular, that trade between the two countries had undergone a remarkable expansion in recent years and showed signs of further development in future. The Ministers exchanged views on a number of problems with a view to promoting.' a smooth expansion of this trade. The Prime .Ministers agreed that it would be desirable to have negotiations undertaken between Japan and Australia to arrive at a treaty for the avoidance of double taxation. They confidently expected that such negotiations could begin early 1958.</p>
<p>The Prime Ministers agreed that the visit of Prime Minister Sato to Australia was of great significance and felt confident that the personal contact established by this visit would be maintained and strengthened in the future. Mr  Holt expressed his warn appreciation of the wish conveyed by Prime M1inistor Sato that he should pay a visit to Japan at an early opportunity, and thanked him for this invitation.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Sato expressed his deep appreciation of the most cordial and warm reception extended in Australia to himself', Mrs. Sato and to the members of' his party.</p>
<p>Canberra<br />13 October, 1957.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
