<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>16808</transcript-id>
    <title>The Hon Duncan Kerr SC MP    </title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/09/2009</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Parliamentary Secretary for Pacific Island Affairs, the Hon Duncan Kerr SC MP has announced that he will not recontest the next federal election.</p>
<p>During his 22 years of public service as a Federal Member of Parliament, Mr Kerr has made an outstanding contribution both as a Minister and as the representative of his electorate of Denison in Tasmania.</p>
<p>As Parliamentary Secretary for Pacific Island Affairs, Mr Kerr has played a key role in strengthening Australia's presence in the Pacific, best demonstrated during the 40th Pacific Islands Forum, which I hosted in Cairns last month.</p>
<p>Mr Kerr was formidable during the 11 years in Opposition from 1996, where he held several shadow portfolios including Immigration, Environment, Justice and the Arts.</p>
<p>He also made a significant contribution to reforming Australia's legal system in areas such as criminal and evidence law while serving as Justice Minister and Attorney-General in the Keating Government.</p>
<p>Prior to entering politics, Mr Kerr was a distinguished figure in the legal profession. He has appeared before the High Court on a number of landmark constitutional cases and was appointed Senior Counsel in 2004.</p>
<p>I applaud Mr Kerr's commitment to the Australian Labor Party. The Australian Government today holds all five federal seats in Tasmania due to the tireless effort of people like Mr Kerr.</p>
<p>Mr Kerr will step down from his role as Parliamentary Secretary at the end of October.</p>
<p>I wish Mr Kerr and his family well in his future career and thank him for his invaluable work for the Australian Government.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
