<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10224</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP LUCHEON ADDRESS TO THE GOLDEN CITY PADDLE STEAMER MUSEUM SOCIETY BALLARAT, VICTORIA</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/01/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010224.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
I Fax from 29 January 1997 TRANSCRI PT OF THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP<br />
LUNCHEON ADDRESS TO THE GOLDEN CITY PADDLE<br />
STEAMER MUSEUM SOCIETY<br />
BALLARAT, VICTORIA<br />
E&amp; OE<br />
Ladies and gentlemen, I'd like to thank Michael very warmly for that welcome; to<br />
acknowledge Mr fam Bell who's Chairman-of the appeal; to Councillor Coghian, the<br />
Mayor of the city of Ballarat; to Mr de Fegely, the State member, and his wife, and all<br />
the other very distinguished guests, ladies and gentlemen.<br />
It is true that over the years that I've been in politics I've come to Ballarat on<br />
numerous occasions. There's a variety of reasons for that. The local members have<br />
invited me from time to time. There was a period when I wasn't invited as regularly as<br />
I am now and I am delighted to say that the invitations have resumed. And on top of<br />
that, of course, Ballarat has always played a very special role in the recollections of<br />
anybody who's interested in the history of Australia. And I remarked at the unveiling<br />
of the bust, if you can put it that way, I remarked that as we approach the Centenary of<br />
Federation, Australians are becoming more and more interested in the history of our<br />
country. And not only at a national level, but every local community is looking back<br />
through its memorabilia and looking back through its history and getting together<br />
stories. And they're all fascinating and they've all got their share of romanticism and<br />
they al have their share of heroes.<br />
Every community is building a history of what has gone before us. And I think one of<br />
the characteristics of the celebration of the Centenary of Federation in Australia will be<br />
quite literally an outpouring of local, historical recollection. Every community in<br />
Australia that has any kind of identity separate from the next community will be doing<br />
that. And one of the many ways in which we can celebrate the Centenary of the<br />
Federation of Australia is of course to encourage every local community to dig into its<br />
history because every local commaunity has marvellous history. And, of course, that is<br />
what this, I feel, the Golden City Paddle Steamer appeal and this museum is all about,<br />
it's recalling and recreating the history of this district. I rR3/ 81/ 1917: 47 Pg: 1 </p>
<p>Fax from The paddle steamer that I travelled on was built in 1885. That's 112 years ago. There<br />
aren't many vehicles that you travel on that are 112 years old. I hope none of the<br />
planes I travel on are 112 years old! And it is really quite a thing that you can have<br />
preserved a mode of travel. You can recreate the atmosphere as best one can given<br />
the passage of more than a century. And that the driver, the Captain of the vessel<br />
however he may choose to be described is the Grandson of the person who built it.<br />
Now that is to you that old cliche that is living history. And the point I make, lades<br />
and gentlemen, is that there are hundreds and thousands of stories like that in cities and<br />
in towns and in villages and hamlets all around Australia, and one of the things that I<br />
do hope we as a nation do over the next three or four years is in every part of the<br />
Australian community we gather together our historical recollections.<br />
There are a lot of reasons why Ballarat, of course, is very much on the map when one<br />
thinks of the history of Australia. The more famous episodes are very well known in<br />
Australian history. Of course it's produced some very famous sportsmen and women,<br />
the city of Balarat. I don't think it's produced too many rugby league players.<br />
Although I remember going to Benalla and launching the Weary Dunlop Memorial at<br />
Benialla and one thing I was very happy to remind that audience of was the fact that he<br />
was the first Victorian to ever play rugby union for Australia which was a pretty<br />
remarkable achievement and shows that, you know, there is some seepage, Michael,<br />
across the boarder. You have to bear that in mind, Gasnier is a very famous name in<br />
rugby league, Michael, a very, very famous name.<br />
Of course, coming right up to date I was delighted to meet the Chairman of the local<br />
conservation organisation which has won the contract to operate the Green Corps<br />
which was one of the election promises that we made before the last election. And I<br />
really am delighted to acknowledge the presence of the Chairman of that organisation<br />
here today. This is an amazing organisation which acts as a facilitator between people<br />
who want to give up their time for nothing in return to cure for the environment<br />
matching those with organisations that want people to provide those services. And<br />
again some pretty fierce competition the organisation, a Ballarat organisation, won<br />
from the Federal Government the contract to run the Green Corps which is going to<br />
put, initially, some two to three thousand young Australians to work on projects that<br />
inv * olve caring for the environment. They'll receive very, very good training and also a<br />
contribution at the end of the period of their training towards their future education<br />
expenses. And the headquarters of that is going to be here in Ballarat. It's not going<br />
to be in Canberra. Although it's a volunteer organisation, in a sense it's indulged itself<br />
in, I suppose, the practises and the achievements of a small business because it's won a<br />
contract against fierce competition.<br />
And that, of course, brings me to a brief but nonetheless heartfelt reference to<br />
something that's very important to me and very important to my Government and I<br />
know is very important to the city of Ballarat, and that is the place and the role of<br />
small business in the fife of this city and in the life of so many areas of provincial<br />
Australia. I said over a year ago during the election campaign that I regarded getting small<br />
business going in an even stronger fashion as being the long term solution, as best we<br />
Fa om30/ 01/ 97 11: 47 Pg: 2 </p>
<p>I Fax from could find it and as best as a community we could find it, to the challenge of high<br />
youth unemployment. And whatever our political beliefs are, this is not a party<br />
political occasion, it's a community occasion, we have a concern about the level of<br />
youth unemployment within our society. And it's not just an economic and a political<br />
challenge but it's also a social challenge. And I do believe very sincerely that doing all<br />
we can to create more opportunities, provide more incentives, provide more<br />
encouragement and provide more support for small business will do more than any<br />
other single thing to reduce youth unemployment, not only here in Ballarat but through<br />
the whole of Australia. And so many of the initiatives of my Government have been<br />
directed towards that and I want to take the opportunity of saying what enormous<br />
importance my Government does attach to continuing to confront the challenge of high<br />
youth unemployment and continuing against the difficulties that it represents,<br />
continuing to do ali we can to bring it down. It's not easy. I don't pretend to have<br />
overnight instant solutions but it does remain a very significant social as well as an<br />
economic and political challenge.<br />
One of the characteristics that binds Australians together is the tradition of volunteer<br />
effort and the society and the organisations, behind the society whose appeal I formally<br />
launched today is yet another example of how a group of volunteers in the community<br />
develop a good idea. That idea captures the imagination and the attention of the local<br />
community and for no material reward, those people like Mr Bell and all of the other<br />
people in his organisation, they set their minds to raising flunds to recreate some history<br />
to provide a focal point for community activities,<br />
And I want to encourage all of you to support the museum to support the appeal. I<br />
am delighted to launch it. As I look around in this restaurant today I see so many<br />
aspects of the community of Ballarat represented. I see its federal and State political<br />
representatives; I see the Mayor of city of Ballarat; I see local business leaders. I had a<br />
stroll through the museum earlier and it's an attractive focal point, a reminder of the<br />
connection between the history of the city of Ballarat and the lake. I was reminded by<br />
the Mayor as we steamed through, of course, that this was the which I had<br />
momentarily forgotten this was the site of all the rowing events in the 1956 olympic<br />
games. I remember 1956 very well because I was doing my leaving certificate in the<br />
middle of the olympic games and it's an end of year I remember very, very vividly.<br />
But what this luncheon represents is the beginning of a very, very important appeal to<br />
raise flunds to recapture, recreate and preserve for the Muure a very important part of<br />
the history of a very significant part of Australia. Ballarat is not just a possession of<br />
the State of Victoria, it is a possession of the entire nation because it's inextricably<br />
bound up with the history of this country, the formation of some of the attitudes of this<br />
country, some of the myths, some of the traditions and the legends of Australia and it<br />
has a permanent and quite indelible part in place in the history of Australia and this<br />
appeal wil make a very important contribution towards strengthening that place and<br />
that role and that appeal. I warmly commend it and I have very much pleasure in<br />
launching it.<br />
Thank you. Fa om30/ 01/ 97 11: 47 Pg: 3 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
