<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1625</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS:  PM.NO.73/1967  POSTAL DIPUTE</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/07/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001625.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS: 9 JUL 967<br />
L PM No. 73/ 1967<br />
POSTAL DISPUTE<br />
Following are texts of telegrans exchanged today between<br />
the Prime Minister and Mr Albert Monk, President of the ACTU<br />
Telegram from Mr Monk<br />
" EXECUTIVE OF ACTU DEALT WITH POSTAL WORKERS<br />
DISPUTE LATE YESTERDAY AFTERNOON AND RESOLVED AS FOLLOWS<br />
QUOTE THE ACTU OFFICERS ADVISE THE UNIONS INVOLVED IN<br />
THE POSTAL WORKERS DISPUTE THAT EVEN AT. THIS STAGE THEY<br />
HAVE A DUTY TO NOTIFY THE ACTU IN ACCORDANCE VW! TH RULE 14<br />
STOP THIS EXECUTIVE IS FURIOUSLY CONCERNED V. ITH THE PENALTIES<br />
IMPOSED ON INDIVIDUAL MEMBERS AND CALLS UPON THE<br />
GOVERNMENT TO WITHDRAW THESE PENALTIES STOP WE REQUEST<br />
THE GOVERNMENT TO CONVENE AN ALL-IN CONFERENCE<br />
COMPRISING THE GOVERNMENT THE ACTU THE POSTAL UNIONS AND<br />
T HE PMG DE PARTMENT TO DISCUSS ALL ASPECTS OF THE DISPUTE<br />
UNQUOTE WOULD APPRECIATE EARLY ADVICE AS TO WHAT YOUR<br />
ATTITUDE IS TOWARDS OUR RECUEST STOP WILL ENDEAVOUR TO<br />
CONTACT YOU BY PHONE AFTER YOU HAVE HAD AN OPPORTUNITY<br />
OF RECEIVING THIS WIRE."<br />
The Prime Minister replied as follows<br />
" I HAVE RECEIVED YOUR TELEGRAM. AS YOU KNOW,<br />
THE MATTER INVOLVED HAS BEEN THE SUBJECT OF PREVIOUS<br />
CABINET CONSIDERATION AND I AM THEREFORE PROPOSING TO<br />
ARRANGE FOR YOUR MESSAGE TO BE PUT TO CABINET AT ITS NEXT<br />
MEETING, W! HICH WILL BE ON TUESDAY, FOR ITS CONSIDERATION."<br />
CANBERRA, 14th July, 167 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
