<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5160</transcript-id>
    <title>APPOINTMENT OF MR ERNEST S EVERS, OBE, AS ASSOCIATE MEMBER, COMMONWEALTH GRANTS COMMISSION</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/10/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005160.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
MEDIA STATEMENT BY THE HON. WAL FIFE, M. P.,<br />
MINISTER ASSISTING THE PRIME MINISTER IN FEDERAL AFFAIRS<br />
Appoiutment of Mr Ernest S. Evers,. O. B. E.,<br />
us Associate Member. Commonwealth Graifts Commi. ssion<br />
The Hon. Wal Fife, Minister Assisting the<br />
Prime Minister in Federal Affairs today announced the<br />
appointment of Mr Ernest S. Eyers, as Associate<br />
Member of the Commonwealth Grants Commission from 1 October 1979<br />
to 30 June 1981.<br />
Mr Fife said that Mr Eyers' appointment was to<br />
one of.-the two part-time offices of Associate Member<br />
nominated by the Premiers of Queensland, South Australia,<br />
Western Australia and Tasmania to assist in the inquiry being<br />
undertaken by the Commonwealth Grants Commission into State<br />
relativities referred. to in section 13( 4) of the States<br />
( Persona]. Income Sharing) Act. The inquiry began earlier<br />
this year and the Commission is bound to report before<br />
June 1981. Mr Eyers has held numerous posts in banking and<br />
industry including Adviser to the Reserve Bank of Australia.,<br />
Chairman of the Housing Loans Insurance Corporation, London<br />
Manager of the Commonwealth Bank of Australia and Manager of<br />
the Commonwealth Trading Bank of Australia. He is Director<br />
of Australia Netherlands Holdings Ltd and of Lead Industries<br />
( Aust.) Pty Ltd and Chairman of Conit Consulting ( Aust.)<br />
Pty Ltd. Mr Fife said that Mr Eyers would be bringing<br />
wide experience to the work of the Commission. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
