<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8156</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF JOINT NEWS CONFERENCE WITH PREMIER NICK GREINER, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA, 8 OCTOBER 1990</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/10/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008156.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
KJ<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF JOINT NEWS CONFERENCE WITH PREMIER NICK<br />
GREINER, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA, 8 OCTOBER 1990<br />
E OE PROOF ONLY<br />
PM: Ladies and gentlemen. I will make a few remarks then<br />
Nick will follow me and then we'll be available for<br />
questions and I think there's some experts available here to<br />
go into any particular details that you might want to<br />
address. Today the Commonwealth and NSW Governments reached agreement<br />
on the South East forest issue. That agreement was reached<br />
on the basis of a thorough scientific study of the<br />
biological values of the South East forests.<br />
However, we didn't just rest alone on that. There was<br />
further consultation between my Ministers and Nick Greiner's<br />
Ministers and there was a drawing upon the advice of<br />
relevant Commonwealth and NSW agencies. In our case the<br />
Australian Heritage Commission and in the case of NSW the<br />
NSW National Parks and Wildlife Service.<br />
Out of all that we have agreed to reserve a somewhat larger<br />
area than came out of the joint scientific study. Nearly<br />
of each of the main National Estate areas will be<br />
protected. Those areas are Tantawangalo, Coolangubra and<br />
Yowaka. With the remaining area, one of them, that's<br />
Tantawangali to be determined after a five year hydrological<br />
study. In total the amount of additional resources that<br />
have been withdrawn will be about ll That gives you the<br />
emphasis within the agreement of our concern, our mutual<br />
concern for environmental conservation issues.<br />
It's important to understand that as a result of the<br />
agreement it: will ensure that the region will continue to<br />
have a viable sawmilling industry. I want to point out that<br />
through the industry restructuring proposals that<br />
Alan Griffiths will be pursuing with his NSW counterpart,<br />
Mr West, and with the industry itself will be encouraging<br />
the use of the forest residue in value-added processing<br />
rather than its export as woodchips.<br />
In summary, I believe it's fair to say that the agreement<br />
that we've reached between us means much greater protection<br />
for the South East forests than existed before. It means a<br />
viable sawlog industry and it means an encouragement of<br />
value-adding. </p>
<p>I am glad that through a long and somewhat tortuous and<br />
complex process, Nick, that we've been able to reach this<br />
position. GREINER: Thank you. Could I just add the NSW Government<br />
believes that: this is an important agreement. These things<br />
tend to be seen as wins and losses and no doubt some of you<br />
will be succumbing to the temptation to try and ascribe wins<br />
and losses to people and positions. The truth is this is<br />
about as close as you can get to a win-win resolution of a<br />
land use conflict.<br />
All of the ma~ jor natural heritage values of the area are<br />
being, on any reasonable assessment, satisfactorily<br />
preserved. There will-be, as the Prime Minister said,<br />
guarantees of a continuing viable sawmilling industry in the<br />
area. It's my Government's concern to ensure that the job security<br />
and the industry security is maintained and indeed the<br />
declaration, the dedication of the National Parks won't be<br />
taking place until such time as we're satisfied that the<br />
details of that are in place.<br />
So the essence of what we have tried to do in co-operation<br />
with the Commonwealth is to reach a win-win situation. We<br />
think that has happened. I think any fairminded assessment<br />
of the outcome would suggest that the preservation of the<br />
main environmental values, not only for this generation but<br />
future generations has been achieved. And equally that for<br />
the first time, for the first time ever the industry in<br />
South Eastern NSW will have a longterm future which will<br />
enable people to make investment decisions, enable jobs to<br />
be secure and families and towns to have some sort of<br />
certainty rather than the sort of uncertainty that they've<br />
been bedevilled with for the last decade or more.<br />
I think that's really as much as I would like to say other<br />
than that I -think it has been a good model of cooperation.<br />
It is important that these sorts of decisions don't become<br />
party political footballs because they're not susceptible to<br />
being very effectively handled if they become party<br />
political footballs. I think this has been a good exercise<br />
in cooperation between, if you like, the environmental<br />
departments and the resource departments and indeed between<br />
the two Governments that happen to be of opposite political<br />
persuasion. JOURNALIST: Prime Minister the Conservation Foundation says<br />
that this won't resolve the conflict in the forests, that<br />
the situation, well the decision's unacceptable. What do<br />
you think it's going to take for the conservation societies<br />
to be made happy?<br />
PM: I think when you're talking about the conservation<br />
movement in this country, Peter, that you've got to<br />
understand that it's a very varied movement. I believe that </p>
<p>there is much the conservation movement, if they study the<br />
decisions that have been taken, and the fact that we've<br />
extended even beyond the scientific study the degree of<br />
protection something like, as I say, 60% of each of the<br />
main National Estate areas any objective judgement would<br />
say that both my Government and the Government of NSW have<br />
been conscious, as we ought to be, of our environmental<br />
obligations to this and future generations. It's also the<br />
case, Peter, that I think there are some parts of the<br />
environmental movement who will never be satisfied unless<br />
they get 100% of their ambit claims. Now in one sense it<br />
would be very satisfying to feel, I guess, it would feel the<br />
same to be able to sit back with a warm glow and say well<br />
yes nothing's going to be touched. But the glow wouldn't<br />
last for too long because this country has got to have<br />
growth, economic growth, if it's going to satisfy the<br />
aspirations of its population. We've also got external<br />
account problems and the dimensions of those are pretty<br />
large including in our nett import position of forest<br />
products. So in these days no government has the luxury<br />
whether it's the level of the federal government or the<br />
level of the state government, no government has the luxury<br />
of Just being able to have one criterion in the decisions<br />
you make about these sorts of issues. You'll never be able<br />
to persuade everyone that you've got the balance absolutely<br />
right. But in the case of my Government, and Nick of course<br />
can speak for his own, but in the case of my Government I'm<br />
proud to look back over the 7h years on our environmental<br />
record of the rainforests in Daintree, in Tasmania, our<br />
decisions in. regard to Kakadu and so on. We've got an<br />
environmental record, I think, second to none around the<br />
world but on. this issue it was a tough one but all I can say<br />
to the environmental movement, we have tried to go as far as<br />
we can in discharging the obligation we feel we have in<br />
regard to the environment.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister the statement mentions a<br />
contribution. to the total annual trade deficit of the timber<br />
products area. What do you think is an acceptable level for<br />
that figure? And are you aiming for the elimination of that<br />
deficit in that area?<br />
PM: I don't know about the elimination of it, Glen. I<br />
haven't got and I don't think anyone has got a specific<br />
percentage figure. But I think the real answer to your<br />
question is just a brief elaboration of what I said in<br />
answer to Peter. That is that what we'Ire trying to do, and<br />
we'll try and do it in cooperation with the states, to get<br />
acceptable guidelines within which we will see an increase<br />
in the value-added process of our forestry industries in<br />
this country,. I think we are going to be able to reach that<br />
position where we will be able to make significant in-roads<br />
on to those figures. But I haven't got a percentage figure<br />
in my mind.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister there's the perception in the<br />
environmentaLl movement that had Graham Richardson retained </p>
<p>the portfolio then the outcome from their point of view<br />
would have been much better.<br />
PM: That's very unfair. I had cause in an interview I did<br />
on the weekend to address a similar sort of point. There is<br />
no doubt that: Graham Richardson was an outstanding Minister<br />
for the environment and he was able to get very significant<br />
runs on the board not just for Graham Richardson and not<br />
just for the Government but I think for the future of this<br />
country. He is to be congratulated for what he did there.<br />
It was inevitable that whoever followed in Graham's<br />
footsteps is going to have a very difficult job. For two<br />
reasons, one, he was by his whole background a very high<br />
profile personality and Minister from his whole experience<br />
and background. Secondly, because there were decisions with<br />
which he was associated. Now I think it's totally unfair to<br />
Ros Kelly to say that Graham Richardson or anyone else would<br />
have done better from the environmental point of view. I<br />
don't think there is any evidence for that. She was<br />
assiduous both in our Cabinet, and as you can attest Nick,<br />
in the discussions with the NSW Ministers, she was assiduous<br />
in pursuing hier concerns. I think the comparison is unfair,<br />
invidious and quite unjust to Ros Kelly.<br />
GREINER: Could I just add something relevant to that point.<br />
The option of a significantly more green outcome is simply<br />
not an option. It's nonsense to suggest it was. My<br />
Government cl. early would not have been part of it. We have<br />
for 5 or 6 years believed that this was a case where in a<br />
sense you could have your environmental cake and your<br />
economic cake at the same time. We had clear cut<br />
commitments that we weren't about to dishonour to the<br />
maintenance or indeed the creation of a viable industry. So<br />
there were only two options available in this. There was<br />
the sort of outcome which has been reached or a continuing<br />
brawl almost coop by coop. Anything else simply wasn't<br />
available as an outcome. So it was either a matter of<br />
reaching a resolution, which as I say a fairminded person<br />
would say was a very fair dinkum attempt to reach a longterm<br />
outcome or settle down for another X years of having fights<br />
in each little bit of forest as it went. So it ought to be<br />
clear that the notion of a " win" in the sense of<br />
preservation of all the old-growth forest was never on. I<br />
think without being unfair to Mr Toyne and other leaders<br />
who've spoken to me as they have to the Prime Minister about<br />
this, the responsible leadership of the conservation<br />
movement never imagined that it was going to get 100%<br />
preservation of old-growth in the South East forests. Nor<br />
to be fair to) the South East Forest Alliance who perhaps are<br />
less responsible. So it just ought to be in context of the<br />
previous question to the Prime Minister. The notion of a<br />
much greener outcome simply wasn't available as a finite or<br />
a permanent resolution.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, Bob Carr the State Labor leader<br />
do you think you'll be able to persuade them to support your<br />
position? </p>
<p>PM: There comes times, as Nick will be able to say from his<br />
point of view, where you can't always get an identity of<br />
view between the Federal Party and the State Party. You've<br />
experienced that, Nick, on some issues. I don't want to go<br />
to them. But they'll be clear in people's minds. It's<br />
unfair to go back to them. There are occasions when from<br />
the perspective of the Federal Party you've got to say well<br />
this is what we believe is the right outcome. If your State<br />
counterparts don't share that view well that's unfortunate.<br />
Of course I haven't gone in this with a view to try and<br />
create a problem for Mr Carr. I would simply make the same<br />
point there that I did in regard to Peter's question. I<br />
think any fair analysis of what's been done should lead to<br />
the conclusion that both Governments have attempted<br />
responsibly to take into account their obligations both in<br />
regard to economic development and environmental<br />
responsibility. JOURNALIST: Will you be holding talks with him on that<br />
subject PM: I'm sure he'll want to talk with me and I'm more than<br />
happy to talk with him.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, how are you going to handle the East<br />
Gippsland dispute and does today's agreement provide some<br />
model for settlement down there?<br />
PM: Well the discussions are now to go on in regard to East<br />
Gippsland and I don't want to pre-empt those discussions. I<br />
guess they'll be difficult. It may be that there are some<br />
elements of what we've been able to do here that will<br />
provide guidance, if not a model there. There is a sense in<br />
which, as I think you appreciate from the question, that if<br />
you're looking at the whole resource and environmental<br />
responsibilities, there is a connection between the South<br />
East forests and East Gippsland.<br />
JOURNALIST: How much will the industry restructuring<br />
package cost and how will the cost be split between the two<br />
Governments? PM: Well the first question is to be answered by saying we<br />
don't know. The decision that we made today authorises our<br />
Minister, Mr Griffiths, to continue discussions with NSW and<br />
I think in the spirit that's been shown in the discussions<br />
so far between the two Governments that we'll be able to<br />
resolve this in a way which is mutually acceptable.<br />
GREINER: If I can just add to that, Paul. One of the<br />
outcomes of this decision if it's followed through to its<br />
finality as I imagine it will be is that the private<br />
sector will for the first time in living memory feel free to<br />
invest in, as the Prime Minister said at the end of his<br />
introductory remarks, in value-added in that South East<br />
area. In terms of the question that was asked before, I<br />
mean I would see NSW and Victorian forests as part of a<br />
South East Australian regional forest area. I mean it's </p>
<p>6.<br />
part of the matter the Prime Minister and I are going to<br />
discuss privately after this conference. I mean it is a<br />
nonsense to have a NSW forest industry and a Victorian<br />
forest industry that happens to be on the other side of a<br />
line on the map. It is clearly part of a which doesn't<br />
mean that the outcomes have got to be identical in resolving<br />
the conflict: but of course it's one region. I think the<br />
point in terms of restructuring is that there is not a huge<br />
Government expense appropriate because what the decision<br />
means in terms of resource availability and security means<br />
that the private sector will be in a position and I'm sure<br />
will in fact invest in the industry itself. So it's not a<br />
matter of trying to sort of save the industry, it in fact<br />
gives it the opportunity to develop in a value-added way,<br />
which to be fair to the conservationists is what many of<br />
them argue which is that we ought to get more bang for our<br />
buck in termis of our natural resources.<br />
JOURNALIST: But have you got a compensation figure? The<br />
industry were talking about compensation Is there<br />
anything that comes out of this decision<br />
GREINER: I think the Prime Minister's answered that. There<br />
will be further discussions between the Resource Ministers.<br />
I would not expect the Government compensation to be<br />
significant. I think it's in fact an opportunity for the<br />
industry. JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, the Wilderness Society has already<br />
condemned this as irresponsible and short sighted. How<br />
concerned are you about both a threatened withdrawal of<br />
their political support and their threatened withdrawal from<br />
the sustainable development process?<br />
PM: Well two separate questions there. On the question of<br />
political support, I will be prepared whenever we go to the<br />
next election I'm talking federal here, Nick, not state<br />
but at the next federal election I will be more than happy<br />
to have my record tested against the record of my federal<br />
political opponents as well as the policy positions of my<br />
Government compared to those of my federal political<br />
opponents. The people in Australia and in the electorate<br />
who have environmental considerations as their major<br />
criterion as to how there determinative vote should fall<br />
will have a clear choice, I believe. And I repeat on that<br />
point that the record of my Government in 7h years, I think,<br />
is second to none. Now in regard to the second part of your<br />
question, I very much hope that the relevant environmental<br />
and conservation organisations will continue to play a role<br />
in the sustainable development program and the Resource<br />
Assessment Commission programs because for two reasons I say<br />
that. Firstly, that the processes will be the better if<br />
there is an input to them from all points of view. And<br />
secondly, fro0m their point of view they are going to<br />
maximise their chance to have an impact on subsequent<br />
decision making processes if they have been part of what<br />
leads up to the decision. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: But just on that point, Mr Hawke, you've both<br />
expressed today in the extent of the cooperation of cross-<br />
Governments and also between parties, do you think therefore<br />
that the environment debate is changing in a way where the<br />
differences between the major parties are in fact<br />
diminishing? PM: Well it's impossible from this particular episode if<br />
I can describe our processes I think it's impossible to<br />
translate that into a federal level. I don't know what<br />
position the federal parties, Federal Liberal Party and<br />
National Part~ y will take. I mean I've been dealing with a<br />
State Liberal Premier and that's for the future to tell. I<br />
would say this point more generally, Paul, make this point<br />
more generally, however, that I think it is the case that<br />
the relatively easy decisions none of them have been easy<br />
but the reJlatively easy decisions have been already taken<br />
and now that we've got the Daintree, going back we've got<br />
the Franklin,. the Daintree, Tasmanian forests, Kakadu, those<br />
decisions behind us. It's going to become more difficult I<br />
think to get the balance between environmental and economic<br />
considerations right now. That's why precisely I've<br />
attempted over the last couple of years to get in place<br />
processes like the Resource Assessment Commission, like the<br />
sustainable development groups, so that we can by attempting<br />
to attract a range of interests the developers, if I can<br />
put that broadly, environmentalists and the States if we<br />
can get these processes going with input from all concerned<br />
then conceptually while the decisions are going to be<br />
somewhat harder, we will have got processes in place which<br />
should mean a minimisation of political differences because<br />
I would hope that if the processes that I've established<br />
with my colleagues work then at the end of them people are<br />
going to be able to say, well look, there's a very, very<br />
fair process, a very fair opportunity for people to have<br />
their input and then the recommendations for decisions that<br />
come out of -that, it seems to me should be more broadly<br />
acceptable. I hope that's true.<br />
JOURNALIST: Well just on that point though, if in fact it's<br />
going to be more of a process of dialogue, compromise<br />
would you expect the conservation movement to reassess then<br />
and stop seeking the product of 100% solutions, which it's<br />
been interested in to this stage?<br />
PM: To be fair I don't know, I think there was something<br />
that Nick said would also support this. To be fair to the<br />
environment it's not inhabited by total 100% zealots, if I<br />
can say that, who are all of them against development. I<br />
mean it's a varied movement.<br />
JOURNALIST: Well would you want to see some reassessment on<br />
the part of the conservation movement then towards this sort<br />
of process you're talking about?<br />
PM: Well I would want to I would hope, Paul, that they<br />
will fully involve themselves in the processes. To this<br />
point they are in the RAC processes, they are, I think, </p>
<p>going to commit themselves although not all of them but<br />
I think a significant part of them are going to commit<br />
themselves to the sustainable development processes. I<br />
would hope they all would for the reason I said before.<br />
They're not going to help their own case, it seems to me, if<br />
they refuse to participate in those processes.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, you've stressed the importance of<br />
value added exports, do you foresee the phasing down of<br />
exports of raw woodchips and what implications, if any,<br />
would that have for the operations of Harris Daishowa?<br />
PM: There's nothing new about what I say here. We have<br />
made it clear and in fact it's part of the lease<br />
arrangements with Harris Daishowa that we require them to<br />
put forward proposals for further value-added operations in<br />
this country. What you've got to remember about this area<br />
that we're talking about is that we're not making these<br />
decisions for the woodchippers. Woodchipping is a residual<br />
of the sawlogging industry. There will be some attempt by<br />
those who are not too interested in facts to say that what<br />
Hawke and Greiner have done is to just open up the forest to<br />
be cut down for woodchips to be sent away to Japan.<br />
Woodchipping is a residual to the sawlogging industry and in<br />
regard to woodchipping in general and Harris Daishowa in<br />
particular, we will, as I've said in my opening statement,<br />
be pressing for further value-adding by those who are in<br />
that industry.<br />
JOURNALIST: Does that include the new pulp and paper<br />
mill that's been this decision?<br />
PM: Well the question about the large new pulp and paper<br />
mill is something that is for the future. Obviously it's<br />
not going to be unrelated to the discussions in regard to<br />
East Gippsland. Because as I've said and as Nick has<br />
agreed, if you're going to be looking at this whole issue<br />
and this whole industry, the line on the map is very<br />
artificial. JOURNALIST: Would you support..<br />
PM: I support the processes of investigating projects which<br />
will take account of our economic requirements and our<br />
environmental responsibilities. We have established the<br />
processes for trying to get guidelines for such mills, which<br />
is indicative of the fact that we conceptually see that<br />
there's a pl. ace for them.<br />
JOURNALIST: structures in place to resolve these sorts<br />
of conflicts Was it not possible to wait until RAC<br />
reported on forests<br />
PM: We made it quite clear at the establishment of RAC and<br />
may I say a] lso of the establishment of the sustainable<br />
development processes that that would not involve a<br />
moratorium on decisions that had to be taken. That was </p>
<p>understood I believe by everyone at the time that these<br />
processes wer: e established.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, just on another matter. Did<br />
you on September 13 either deliberately or inadvertently<br />
mislead the House in regard to the monies going to the<br />
Victorian Sporting<br />
PM: I've never attempted deliberately, I've never in my<br />
life attempted deliberately to mislead anyone, whether it's<br />
the House or elsewhere. However, as a result of the<br />
statement I dlid make there was certainly some confusion. I<br />
acknowledge that and I will take the first opportunity,<br />
which will be tomorrow in the House, to clarify that<br />
position. JOURNALIST: Can we get your reaction to the ANZ job<br />
statistics today Prime Minister?<br />
PM: I'll just briefly say that they are further evidence of<br />
the fact that our intention of slowing down the economy,<br />
which was necessary, is occurring. We will continue to<br />
monitor what's happening with a view to ensuring that we<br />
have an outcome which is going to be consistent with our<br />
requirements for growth and meeting the challenges of the<br />
external account and inflation.<br />
JOURNALIST: Would you support an inquiry into the newspaper<br />
industry?<br />
PM: I didn't get terribly carried away about that before.<br />
It seems to be getting people are attempting to get some<br />
more legs on that because there has been a collapsing of<br />
four publications into two. I don't think the collapsing of<br />
four publications into two has made any intrinsic difference<br />
to the situation that's been in existence for some time now.<br />
I don't see that of itself as creating any new reason for<br />
such an inquiLry.<br />
JOURNALIST: On the previous question Mr Hawke, do you<br />
accept that you inadvertently misled the House over those<br />
PM: There was some inadvertent, on my part there was an<br />
inadvertent mnis-stating of the position. But I stated the<br />
correct position and an incorrect position. I of course<br />
would never iLntend to do that. I think you know now<br />
Michelle, from 7h years I haven't got a reputation, and<br />
deservedly haven't got a reputation for misleading the<br />
House. It is something I would never<br />
JOURNALIST: Can you just clarify how<br />
PM: I will clarify it to the House tomorrow. It will be<br />
the first opportunity I will have had because I went off to<br />
Japan in the next week and I wasn't in the House. But I'll<br />
take the first </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Can you sort it out now for us.<br />
PM: I think it's appropriate that as it occurred in the<br />
House I will do it then.<br />
JOURNALIST: Will you apologise to Senator Walsh?<br />
PM: Will I what?<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you feel you have anything to apologise to<br />
Senator Walsh for?<br />
PM: I have -very little to apologise to Senator Walsh for.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, on the part of the rural sector, if I<br />
can, both wool growers and wheat growers are desperate to<br />
get a reduction in interest rates for their survival. Are<br />
they likely -to get that?<br />
PM: I think I can answer that in this way. I said to the<br />
Australian people, as did Paul, during last year when we had<br />
to tighten monetary policy, I said that we would, as<br />
circumstances permitted, lower interest rates. We have at<br />
the official level done that on several occasions already<br />
this year by four percentage points. So clearly our<br />
commitment i~ s to have a lowered interest rate regime but<br />
only at a time where in the interests of the people that you<br />
are talking about as well as the interests of the people as<br />
a whole such a lowering will be consistent with overall<br />
community objectives. I mean you just can't say in running<br />
an economy like this, oh, interest rates are causing a<br />
problem therefore we'll chop them in the belief that in<br />
doing that you wouldn't create another series of problems<br />
which could ' be even more overwhelming. We will reduce<br />
interest rates as to do so is consistent with our overall<br />
economic responsibilities.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, you have said that there won't be an<br />
inquiry into newspapers in Australia but do you see any need<br />
to fine tune your media policies, especially in relation to<br />
foreign ownership of TV and newspapers?<br />
PM: No, I would've made decisions about that recently. I<br />
don't feel any compulsion about that.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, the present political crisis in the<br />
United States, could you tell us what sort of impact you<br />
expect that to have on the Australian economy. Is it likely<br />
to PM: We hope it's a very short-term one. I would believe<br />
from afar that the Administration and the Congress will sort<br />
this one out. It's going to be a bit messy for a while by<br />
the look of it. It's going to cause some pain. I'd be very<br />
surprised if it's not sorted out in the short-term.<br />
JOURNALIST: So no impact on the Australian economy? </p>
<p>* L 11.<br />
PM: The fact that there's some unhappiness caused for a<br />
range of people within the United States, visitors going to<br />
places which are now closed and public servants having to<br />
wait perhaps for a little while for their pay. I mean<br />
that's a problem for those that are involved. But it<br />
doesn't have any impact at all internationally if it is<br />
resolved in the short term, as I believe it will.<br />
JOURNALIST: It appears there's some chance that the<br />
Opposition will attempt to block at least parts of your<br />
pharmaceutical benefits legislation coming up. What<br />
repercussions would that have?<br />
PM: That's a hypothetical. You've got no chance on that<br />
one. JOURNALIST: Mr Greiner has made a statement outside the<br />
Royal Commission into the building industries. He's<br />
prepared to go to gaol unless the Government allows legal<br />
aid. Is the Government's position unchanged<br />
GREINER: Yes of course. John's an old mate of mine. He's<br />
just posturing. The Royal Commission will look after<br />
itself. The unions would be well-advised to take a<br />
pro-active approach rather than a negative one. But that's<br />
highly unlikely to influence my judgement.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
