<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10729</transcript-id>
    <title>22 April 1998                                 TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                  THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                  RADIO INTERVIEW WITH JOHN LAWS                RADIO 2UE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/04/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...............................................</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, good morning and thank you for your time.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It's very good to be on your programme again, John.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>Thank you, that's nice of you. You've got your hands</p>
<p>   full, really full now, haven't you?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes, but I never thought the cause of waterfront reform was going</p>
<p>   to be easy. And we've got to remember that what is at stake</p>
<p>   here is whether Australia will have a productive, world-class waterfront</p>
<p>   or whether we'll continue, in that area, to be the laughing</p>
<p>   stock of the world.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>How far will the Government go in this dispute? I mean, what avenues</p>
<p>   are open, for example, if the court action this afternoon fails?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, the Government's not part of that court action this</p>
<p>   afternoon.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>Well, indirectly.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, it's not - none of the orders made yesterday affected</p>
<p>   the Commonwealth. The Government's role is that of achieving</p>
<p>   a policy objective that we've never disguised. And that is</p>
<p>   to give Australia a more productive waterfront to end the situation</p>
<p>   where our crane rates are 18 against 30 for our competitors, the</p>
<p>   50 per cent over-manning, the rorts, the feather-bedding and all</p>
<p>   the things that cause the most respected economic magazine in the</p>
<p>   world, The London Economist, to say this week that the time</p>
<p>   has long passed where old-fashion union practices can be part of</p>
<p>   a forward-looking Australia. So we've got to remember, amidst</p>
<p>   all the tooing and froing - and let's face it, there's</p>
<p>   going to be a lot of court actions, you're going to win some</p>
<p>   and you're going to lose some, but people should not lose sight</p>
<p>   of the fundamental objective and that is that it is in Australia's</p>
<p>   national economic interest to have a modernised, reformed, competitive,</p>
<p>   productive waterfront.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>Yeah. I think...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>And I think 97 per cent of your responders yesterday demonstrated</p>
<p>   that. And that is the Government's objective. You ask me how</p>
<p>   far will the Government go. The Government will do all it legitimately</p>
<p>   can to achieve that objective and I have always said that.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>Okay but with respect Prime Minister, we've heard the rhetoric</p>
<p>   about the problems on the waterfront...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It's not rhetoric, it's reality.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>Well, but it's still rhetoric. I mean, we've had it repeated</p>
<p>   time and time again.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, are you suggesting it's just rhetoric that Australia</p>
<p>   has an uncompetitive waterfront?</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>No, no, we've constantly said that as the case.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>But I think it's important, amidst all of the tooing and froing...</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>Well, I think Australia knows that 97 per cent of the people...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>...I think it's very important, even in that you asked me</p>
<p>   what does the Government intend to do.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>That's right. Well, how far is the Government prepared to</p>
<p>   go? I mean, if this court action today fails, if the appeal by Patricks</p>
<p>   fail then obviously the Government has a problem, whether it wants</p>
<p>   it or not or whether it's part of it or not, it will become</p>
<p>   part of it.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>The Government will continue to support the cause of waterfront</p>
<p>   reform and will continue to support the principle of voluntary unionism</p>
<p>   on the Australian waterfront and will continue, within the law,</p>
<p>   to support anyone who pursues those objectives irrespective of the</p>
<p>   outcome of the court case today or, indeed, the outcome of any other</p>
<p>   court decision. </p>
<p>You see, courts don't determine government policy, courts</p>
<p>   interpret the law as determined by Parliament and that is their</p>
<p>   role and it is our role to set objectives and to pursue policy changes.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>But court decisions can affect government policy.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Court decisions can determine the legal parameters of the behaviour</p>
<p>   of people including governments. Now, I have said all along, John,</p>
<p>   that we will, in pursuing our objective of a reformed Australian</p>
<p>   waterfront, we will support any company or any group of individuals</p>
<p>   that pursues that objective provided they act within the law.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>Well, you've certainly supported Patricks.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>In the sense of saying that, to the extent that they are committed</p>
<p>   to waterfront reform, yes. The question of their own individual</p>
<p>   conduct, of course, is a matter for them.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>That's right. But in discussions I had with Peter Reith he</p>
<p>   made it very clear to me that he'd had lengthy discussions</p>
<p>   with Patricks. So obviously...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, of course, he's had discussions...</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>Prior to this taking place.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>But it is the job of a Workplace Relations Minister.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>No, I'm suggesting there's anything untoward about it.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>And, of course, he had lengthy discussions with the MUA until the</p>
<p>   MUA walked out on those discussions.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>I'm not suggesting there's anything untoward about it.</p>
<p>   I'm simply saying, as he has had discussions, you said that</p>
<p>   this court decision this afternoon won't affect you, well,</p>
<p>   it'll affect him and he's part of your Government.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, no, it won't affect him in the same sense that it won't</p>
<p>   affect me. I mean, you're asking me whether the court decision</p>
<p>   this afternoon will in any way affect my commitment or the commitment</p>
<p>   of my Government. And it's not just a commitment...</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>No, I didn't ask you that. I didn't ask you that. I just</p>
<p>   said: how will it affect you.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I'm saying how it won't affect me is that it won't</p>
<p>   divert us. It won't divert us from our objective of pursuing</p>
<p>   waterfront reform. But, I mean, if we're going to spend 20</p>
<p>   minutes or so talking about how we are going to hypothetically respond</p>
<p>   to a decision that hasn't been handed down - I mean, we can</p>
<p>   have all sorts of hypothesis. I'm going to wait until I get</p>
<p>   that decision.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>Well, I can assure that's not my intention, to spend 20 minutes</p>
<p>   doing anything. All I'm seeking is an answer.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, my answer is that I will respond or my Minister will respond</p>
<p>   to the court decision when it's known.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>How do you respond to Justice North saying there is an arguable</p>
<p>   case that Patricks have engaged in an unlawful conspiracy?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I don't think it's appropriate at this stage for</p>
<p>   me to respond to that because all he has stated is that there is</p>
<p>   a case to go to trial. And, in the meantime, the interlocutory injunctions</p>
<p>   that he has granted against parties other than the Commonwealth</p>
<p>   are being appealed by those parties.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>Yes.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I mean, I'm not going to try - I'm not going to publicly</p>
<p>   debate at this stage, particularly against the background of an</p>
<p>   appeal. What he said - look, John, through the whole course of this</p>
<p>   dispute there are going to be allegations. He hasn't made a</p>
<p>   finding of illegality and he hasn't told Patricks to do anything</p>
<p>   that they are refusing to do, unlike the Supreme Court of Victoria</p>
<p>   which has told the MUA to stop blocking the removal of goods from</p>
<p>   the East Swanson Dock.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>And they have defied that.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>They have defied that. And they are supported in that defiance</p>
<p>   by Kim Beazley and by the Australian Labor Party.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>Yes, well, I wonder, could one say, perhaps, that there is a conspiracy</p>
<p>   between the Maritime Workers and the Australian Labor Party?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, look, it's simpler than that. I'm not making an allegation</p>
<p>   - I mean, whether there's a conspiracy or not, the allegation</p>
<p>   I make is that the Leader of the Opposition in Australia and the</p>
<p>   New South Wales Premier are encouraging people to defy lawfully</p>
<p>   made orders of courts of competent jurisdiction in this country.</p>
<p>   They are encouraging the Maritime Union of Australia to behave above</p>
<p>   the law. They are giving comfort and aid and public sucker to people</p>
<p>   who are thumbing their noses at the courts of the country. You see,</p>
<p>   when Patricks copped an adverse decision yesterday...</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>They copped it.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>...you didn't hear me and you didn't hear Peter Reith</p>
<p>   saying to Patricks: you defy that decision. We said: you've</p>
<p>   got to obey it. Now, has Kim Beazley told the MUA to obey the decision</p>
<p>   of the Supreme Court of Victoria? Could you get Kim Beazley this</p>
<p>   morning on radio, Greg Combet, Mick O'Leary or John Coombs</p>
<p>   on television last night or this morning to give an undertaking</p>
<p>   that if any of the court decisions went against them they would</p>
<p>   obey those decisions - no. They, in fact, said that if they lose</p>
<p>   in the courts they'll continue the civil disobedience in the</p>
<p>   streets.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>Now, amongst other things that Kim Beazley said yesterday, he said</p>
<p>   this - I'd like a comment on this:-"John Howard takes</p>
<p>   the ball. There is no reason why all that material on the docks</p>
<p>   could not move tomorrow and everybody be back at work."</p>
<p>Is that correct?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, this is the man who for 13 years sat down and had meetings</p>
<p>   and delivered the world's laughing stock of a waterfront. I</p>
<p>   mean, he's saying that we ought to try what they try and, through</p>
<p>   that method, fail to achieve. I don't remember him, incidentally,</p>
<p>   using that language when the pilots dispute was on. He was in there</p>
<p>   as Mr Gung Ho' Defence Minister using the resources of</p>
<p>   the Royal Australian Air Force to smash the pilots federation, which</p>
<p>   was a union...</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>Yes, now all of this is true, Prime Minister, but we both have</p>
<p>   a problem with time. I don't want to hear about his frailties,</p>
<p>   I want to hear about your strengths. I mean, can you do what he</p>
<p>   said you should do?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, his argument - what he's saying to me is that I should</p>
<p>   do, as a response to this dispute, what he did and what his Prime</p>
<p>   Ministers did and failed to deliver a dispute. I mean, he says we</p>
<p>   should have a meeting.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>He says you could get them back to work.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh yeah, look, clearing the docks of the accumulated goods is one</p>
<p>   short-term, immediate and very important problem. But the greater</p>
<p>   problem, the long-term problem, is how we are going to have a productive</p>
<p>   waterfront. And you do not achieve a productive waterfront in this</p>
<p>   country by adopting the methods employed by the Labor governments</p>
<p>   of the past which have completely failed. And, in any event, why</p>
<p>   should the Government of this country, whether it's Labor or</p>
<p>   Liberal, why should the Government of this country sit down and</p>
<p>   negotiate with people who continue to openly defy orders made against</p>
<p>   them and findings inter alia of illegal conduct, findings of illegal</p>
<p>   conduct made by the courts of this country. I mean, what kind of</p>
<p>   example does that set? What kind of ethics...</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>Okay, Prime Minister, can we just go back to Kim Beazley. Just</p>
<p>   hear again what he said:- "John Howard takes the ball.</p>
<p>   There is no reason why all that material on the docks could not</p>
<p>   move tomorrow and everybody be back at work."</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I could equally - I mean, you know that the best way to remove</p>
<p>   the material on the docks.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>Tell me.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Not by having a meeting, is by everybody in this country obeying</p>
<p>   the law.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>And if everybody obeyed the law?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>If the MUA obeyed the law in 30 minutes time that material could</p>
<p>   be removed from the docks. You don't need a meeting to clear</p>
<p>   the docks. I mean, that is Beazley covering for his union mates.</p>
<p>   You don't need a meeting to clear the docks. All you need is</p>
<p>   for people to obey the laws as handed down by the Supreme Courts</p>
<p>   of New South Wales and Victoria. In both of those courts injunctions</p>
<p>   have been issued forbidding people from interfering with others</p>
<p>   carrying out their lawful business. Now, if those injunctions were</p>
<p>   obeyed, that is all that is needed. You don't need a meeting.</p>
<p>   You don't need the Prime Minister to intervene. You don't</p>
<p>   need anybody else involved. All you need...</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>What about Justice North's ruling?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Justice North's ruling in no way affects the injunctions of</p>
<p>   the Supreme Courts of New South Wales and Victoria because Justice</p>
<p>   North has not made a finding of illegal conduct. I'm sorry,</p>
<p>   John, it is a very simple situation.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>But he has suggested that there is room to investigate that conduct.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, what he said is that there is a case to go to hearing.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>That's right, room to investigate.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, John, he has not ordered people to do other than the interlocutory</p>
<p>   orders that are now the subject of potential appeal by Patricks.</p>
<p>   But let me go back to the tape you played of Kim Beazley, twice.</p>
<p>   What he said was, all John Howard's got to do is to pick up</p>
<p>   the ball and run with it. My reply is that if you want the docks</p>
<p>   cleared, Kim Beazley, you tell the MUA to obey the decision of the</p>
<p>   Supreme Court of New South Wales and the Supreme Court of Victoria.</p>
<p>   Because if those blockades were lifted, if the illegal nature of</p>
<p>   the pickets were removed in both Sydney and Melbourne, those millions</p>
<p>   of dollars of goods on those wharves would be removed. You don't</p>
<p>   need a meeting. You don't need prime ministerial intervention.</p>
<p>   All you need is for the Leader of the Opposition to do something</p>
<p>   he has failed to do so far during this dispute and is to exhort</p>
<p>   his fellow Australians to obey the law. He should stop being a ventriloquist</p>
<p>   dummy of the trade union movement in this dispute.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>Well we've always understood that the Labor Party is the political</p>
<p>   wing of the trade union movement anyway.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well as Graeme Richardson said in the Bulletin on the 10th of February,</p>
<p>   the unions still own a majority of the stock in the ALP.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>It's now being shown.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>And it's being shown and the MUA is behaving above the law.</p>
<p>   And Kim Beazley does not have the guts to say whatever the rights</p>
<p>   and wrongs are, John Coombs, you like everybody else as a citizen</p>
<p>   of Australia, must abide by the laws of Australia. And I say again</p>
<p>   to Mr Beazley, forget about a meeting, forget about this rhetorical</p>
<p>   invitation to me to convene a meeting, you just get your union mates</p>
<p>   to obey the law and all of those goods that are lying and rotting</p>
<p>   on the docks in Australia at the present time can be cleared overnight.</p>
<p>   That's all you need, you need people to obey the law. You need</p>
<p>   people to behave like civilised people in a civilised society and</p>
<p>   not adopt this heads I win, tails you lose approach to court decisions.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>While speaking of John Coombs, Mr Coombs yesterday said this:-</p>
<p>   "John Howard will be remembered for the quote that these people</p>
<p>   were sacked because they were members of the Maritime Union of Australia</p>
<p>   and for no other reason."</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I never said that.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>Well I didn't think you did.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, never. I have never, I mean he allows me to make it very clear</p>
<p>   that our policy objective does not include the destruction of any</p>
<p>   union including the Maritime Union of Australia. The only goal that</p>
<p>   we seek generically, so far as unions are concerned, is to have</p>
<p>   voluntary unionism on the Australian waterfront. In other words</p>
<p>   to have a situation where both members of the MUA and other people</p>
<p>   can work on the Australian waterfront. I mean for example at the</p>
<p>   moment, members of the MUA are employed on the Australian waterfront</p>
<p>   by P&amp;O.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>And they are still working.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, no, no. I mean, I'm not saying....</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>But they're working.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Exactly. And at no stage, at no stage, have I ever argued that</p>
<p>   you should replace the MUA closed shop on the Australian waterfront</p>
<p>   with a situation where people who belong to unions can't be</p>
<p>   employed on the Australian waterfront. And at no stage have I ever</p>
<p>   admitted, at no stage have I ever advocated, that people should</p>
<p>   be sacked because they belong to a trade union because that would</p>
<p>   be against the law that we brought in in 1996.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>Okay, can we just go back to the suggestion of conspiratorial action.</p>
<p>   You did mention it yesterday, let me just remind you of what you</p>
<p>   said:</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>We certainly didn't conspire to break the law. We certainly</p>
<p>   didn't conspire in the sense that that is understood in the</p>
<p>   law.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>When you say you didn't conspire in the sense that it's</p>
<p>   understood in the law, do we read into that that you did conspire</p>
<p>   in some way?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, no, it's just my way of answering the question. Look,</p>
<p>   there hasn't been any conspiracy. </p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>None at all?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, no, of course not.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>Are you concerned that the Consumer and Competition Commission</p>
<p>   is also looking at the possibility that the Government and Patricks</p>
<p>   did break the law?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I don't mind who looks at anything. I mean we are an open</p>
<p>   book on this.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>If they were to take, I thought you were.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I mean, John, you have known me for a long time and I think you</p>
<p>   would agree that one thing I have always believed in is changing</p>
<p>   the industrial relations system in Australia.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>I know that. You and I have discussed it.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>And I don't think anybody should say I kidded the Australian</p>
<p>   public before the last election that I would do it if I became Prime</p>
<p>   Minister.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>No, nobody could say that.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>And I had never disguised the fact that we would firstly change</p>
<p>   the law and secondly anybody who tried to take advantage of those</p>
<p>   changes in the law to achieve our reform objectives on the Australian</p>
<p>   waterfront, would have our understanding and our support and encouragement,</p>
<p>   provided, now I said this in Parliament on several occasions over</p>
<p>   the month, provided they acted in accordance with the law.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>But did you hold talks with the shipping companies? For example,</p>
<p>   I know, as you say, I've know you a long time and we've</p>
<p>   talked about waterfront reform for years and years and years. When</p>
<p>   you talked about it before, when you intended doing it before, did</p>
<p>   you talk to shipping companies then?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh look John, I'd have to go back over all of my records,</p>
<p>   but over the years I would have talked to everybody.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>Including stevedoring companies?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Including stevedoring companies at some stage. I don't think</p>
<p>   I've had more than one or two or three discussions at the most</p>
<p>   with stevedores since I've become Prime Minister. I can't</p>
<p>   remember precisely how many but so what. I am</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
