<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>19081</transcript-id>
    <title>Clean-up grants for severely-affected primary producers in NSW</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/02/2013</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Adelaide</p>
<p>Clean-up and recovery grants of up to $15,000 are now available for primary producers in areas severely affected by bushfires in New South Wales.</p>
<p>This assistance, available under Category C of the jointly funded Federal/State Natural Disaster Relief and Recovery Arrangements (NDRRA), will initially apply to primary producers in Warrumbungle, Coonamble, Gilgandra, Harden, Yass Valley and Cooma-Monaro. The Commonwealth and New South Wales Governments will continue to assess the impact of the fires on other areas to see if this assistance should be activated elsewhere.</p>
<p>The assistance is designed to help with the economic impacts that these devastating fires have had on local farms and the wider community.</p>
<p>The activation of Category C assistance is in addition to the range of support already available, including personal hardship and distress assistance, loans to primary producers and small businesses, assistance with essential public asset restoration and freight subsidies for primary producers.</p>
<p>There are now 71 local government areas eligible for various types of assistance across New South Wales, including:</p>
<p>Albury, Bathurst,Bega Valley, Berrigan,Bland,Blayney, Bogan, Boorowa, Bourke, Brewarrina, Cabonne, Carrathool, Central Darling, Cessnock, Cobar, Conargo, Coolamon, Cooma-Monaro, Coonamble, Cootamundra, Corowa, Cowra, Deniliquin, Dubbo, Eurobodalla, Forbes, Gilgandra, Goulburn-Mulwaree, Greater Hume,Griffith,Gundagai, Gwydir, Harden, Hay, Jerilderie,Junee, Lachlan,Leeton,Lithgow, Lockhart, Mid-Western Regional, Moree Plains, Murray, Murrumbidgee, Muswellbrook, Narrabri, Narrandera, Narromine, Oberon, Orange, Palerang, Parkes, Queanbeyan, Shoalhaven, Singleton, Snowy River,Temora,Tumbarumba, Tumut, Unincorporated NSW, Upper Lachlan, Urana, Wagga Wagga, Wakool, Walgett,Warren,Warrumbungle, Weddin, Wellington, Yass Valley and Young.</p>
<p>Primary producers in the fire affected parishes should contact the NSW Rural Assistance Authority on 1800 678 593 to see if they are eligible for the grant.</p>
<p>Information on disaster assistance in NSW can be found at <a href="http://www.mpes.nsw.gov.au">www.mpes.nsw.gov.au</a>.</p>
<p>Information on the range of assistance that is available under the NDRRA can be found at <a href="http://www.disasterassist.gov.au">www.disasterassist.gov.au</a></p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
