<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8830</transcript-id>
    <title>THE COST OF A 15 PER CENT GST ON AN AVERAGE FAMILY</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/02/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008830.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
THE COST OF A 15 PER CENT GST ON AN AVERAGE FAMILY<br />
An average family with children with both husband and<br />
wife in employment and an income between them of $ 50,000<br />
would be $ 75 a week worse off because of a 15 per cent<br />
CST. This figure assumes that basic tgQdis untaxed and that<br />
per cent of the abolition of-the -wholesale sales tax<br />
is passed on to consumers.<br />
This means that consumers potentially face a rise of 9.2<br />
per cent in prices because of a 15 per cent CST before<br />
receiving aiij' dupposed relief through the abolition of<br />
payroll tax and lower fuel excise. This is based on Dr<br />
' Hewson'Is e-stimates of whfat revenue -a 15 per cent GST<br />
would raise after the wholesale sales tax is abolished<br />
allowing for the exemption of basic food. It is also<br />
based on estimated private final consumption expenditure<br />
in 1990-91 adjusted for taxes.<br />
This S75 loss to an average family is absolutely<br />
guaranteed if Dr Hewson is elected on 13 March 1993.<br />
What is not guaranteed is that Australian families will<br />
be fully compensated.<br />
Dr Hewson' s compensation _ packagep cannot be funded. This<br />
was always the case but -in the last few days any<br />
semblance of plausibility has been stripped away with the<br />
discovery that Dr Hewson has an S8 billion hole coming<br />
from the fact that Telecom is only worth $ 12 billion, not<br />
the $ 20 billion he has claimed.<br />
On top of that, consumers are most unlikely to benefit<br />
from lower petrol prices.<br />
The States will be forced to put up their petrol taxes<br />
because Dr Hewson will cut State arants and will not<br />
properly compensate them for the abolition of State<br />
payroll tax. As the NSW State Treasury has informed<br />
Premier Fahey, the NSW State Budget will be out of pocket<br />
by between S300 and S400 million per annum because of Dr<br />
Hewson' s policies. 6673 </p>
<p>Dr Hewson will also impose a road user charge after the<br />
election although he will de~ ny tis.<br />
Now Dr Hewson is claiming that not only will families be<br />
fully compensated for the GST, they will actually be $ 56<br />
a week better off.<br />
He is also saying that the GST will lead to a $ 20 billion<br />
boost for business.<br />
Dr Hewsont s fantasies know no bounds.<br />
There is no way that Dr Hewson's numbers can add up.<br />
Everyone cannot magically be better off with a big new<br />
tax of 15 per cent on nearly everything people buy.<br />
There is no magic pudding.<br />
What is real is that with a Hewson Government, Australian<br />
families will start $ 75 a week worse off because of the<br />
GST and they will be on their own as they try and get<br />
this back from Dr Hewson.<br />
There is no way in the world that Dr Hewson can deliver<br />
compensation of this magnitude. It cannot be afforded by<br />
Dr Hewson and what relief he does grant will disappear<br />
into the pockets of desperate businesses trying to<br />
weather the storm of the GST and -into . t he hands of State<br />
Governments trying to balance their books after they have<br />
been ravaged by Dr Hewson's cuts.<br />
As in Canada, all that a GST offers Australia is the<br />
stalling of the recovery, higher unemployment and lower<br />
living standards.<br />
Unlike Canada, Australia can still avoid making a change<br />
for the worse by ensuring that Dr Hewson never becomes<br />
Prime Minister.<br />
MELBOURNE February 1993<br />
6 67 4 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
