<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7355</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER PARLIAMENTARY DINNER IN HONOUR OF THE TAOISEACH, CHARLES HAUGEEY CANBERRA - 12 JULY 1988</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/07/1988</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007355.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
PARLIAMENTARY DINNER IN HONOUR OF THE TAOISEACH,<br />
CHARLES HAUGHEY<br />
CANBERRA 12 JULY 1988<br />
Taoiseach, Distinguished guests,<br />
Ladies and gentlemen.<br />
Some Australians have not a drop of Irish blood flowing in<br />
their veins.<br />
Some Australians have rectified that shortcoming by marrying<br />
into an Irish family and I include myself in this<br />
category.<br />
And some of us have the great good fortune of being able to<br />
claim Irish blood by birth or ancestry. Indeed almost one<br />
in every three Australians can make the proud boast of<br />
having been born in Ireland or into an Irish family.<br />
I speak for all Australians, however, regardless of the<br />
nature or degree of their Irishness, in extending to you,<br />
Taoiseach, and your wife, the warmest of welcomes to<br />
Canberra. This is the first visit of an Irish Prime minister to<br />
Australia. Maureen, this is your second visit this year, as<br />
you represented Ireland at our Australia Day celebrations.<br />
These visits coincide with Australia's nationwide<br />
celebrations of our Bicentenary.<br />
Your visit gives us an opportunity therefore, as part of our<br />
national process of stocktaking afforded by the Bicentenary,<br />
to more fully understand the length and strength of the<br />
Australian-Irish relationship.<br />
It was Arthur Caiwell, a great leader of the Australian<br />
Labor Party and a man deeply imbued in Irish culture, who<br />
most eloquently described the nature of the Irish<br />
contribution to Australia.<br />
Arthur Caiwell was the architect of Australia's great<br />
post-war immigration program and was a giant of the labor<br />
movement. It was on St Patrick's Day in 1952 that he had this to say<br />
of Ireland's role in world affairs: 303<br />
a, </p>
<p>" from the dawn of history and even from the mists that<br />
preceded that dawn, Irish men and women have gone from<br />
Ireland to many countries. They went as colonisers but<br />
never as conquerers; they went as educators but never as<br />
exploiters. They never were imperialists, and they<br />
never took away another people's freedom. They brought<br />
their culture and their virtues with them to enrich the<br />
heritage of whatever land they chose to dwell in".<br />
Last year, I was given the honour of addressing the Dail in<br />
Dublin. Drawing on those insights I have just quoted, I<br />
said that Ireland is in fact the head of a huge empire an<br />
empire acquired not by force of arms but by force of Irish<br />
character an empire not of political coercion but of<br />
spiritual affiliation, created by the thousands upon<br />
thousands of Irish men and women who chose to leave their<br />
homeland, or who were banished from it, to take part in the<br />
building of new nations overseas.<br />
A greater number of Irish have gone to the United States<br />
than have come to Australia but they form a smaller<br />
proportion of the total population there than in Australia.<br />
So Australia is the principal province of that Irish empire,<br />
having been endowed as no other country has been with the<br />
hard work and determination of generations of Irish men and<br />
women. If this is true, as I firmly believe it to be, then surely<br />
the epicentre of that Irish empire in Australia must be the<br />
Australian trade union movement and the Australian Labor<br />
Party which I have the honour to lead.<br />
Because from its earliest days the labor movement in this<br />
country has been enriched by those enduring characteristics<br />
of the Irish people: their commitment to justice, their<br />
overwhelming egalitarianism, their enduringly loyal<br />
comradeship. Indeed the fact that Australians were among the first in the<br />
world to form trade unions and to build an industrial<br />
framework for the protection and enhancement of working<br />
conditions was due in no small measure to the vital presence<br />
of the Irish Australians. I<br />
Australia's greatest Prime Ministers were Labor men of Irish<br />
extraction: John Curtin and Ben Chifley.<br />
Even today, my own ministry has a strong Irish<br />
representation.<br />
But it, is not just in politics that Irish surnames keep<br />
cropping up.<br />
In literature and the arts, in education, in the law, in<br />
sports, throughout Australia's history and throughout<br />
contemporary Australian society, our proud Irish streak is<br />
clear to see from Charles Gavan Duffy to Ned Kelly, from<br />
the Wild Colonial Boy to Clancy of the overflow, from C. J.<br />
Dennis to Tom Keneally and from Bill O'Reilly to Sidney<br />
Nolan.<br />
304 </p>
<p>Taoi seach,<br />
For all these reasons, when I arrived at Dublin at the start<br />
of my visit to Ireland last October, I felt immediately at<br />
home. The truth of that initial impression was thoroughly borne<br />
n out over the succeeding days of my visit.<br />
n For the Irish and Australian people are united by ties of<br />
history and of kinship ties which span the oceans that<br />
separate us.<br />
Those ties were first formed by the thousands of Irish<br />
e convicts and settlers who came to settle in Australia; today<br />
they are daily renewed by the many Australians who visit<br />
Ireland each year and by those engaged in business between<br />
US. It is good to see an increasing pace of political exchanges<br />
between us.<br />
e, In 1985, President Hillery became the first Irish head of<br />
d state to visit Australia. My visit last year was the first<br />
by an Australian Prime minister. Parliamentary delegations<br />
and ministerial meetings have multiplied.<br />
e So it is my sincere hope, Taaiseach, that while you are in<br />
Australia you too will feel you are among friends. I can<br />
assure you that you, and your wife and party, are very<br />
welcome visitors.<br />
s Taoiseach, It is a pleasure to welcome you to the new home of the<br />
Australian Parliament. You are the first Head of Government<br />
. he we have hosted at dinner in this building.<br />
These Parliamentary chambers like those in which I had the<br />
honour of speaking in Dublin represent the democratic<br />
ice values which Ireland and Australia hold firmly, our shared<br />
commitment to vigorous and open debate, and our common view<br />
that the people are best governed when they govern<br />
. sh themselves. It is those fundamental values which provide<br />
the deepest of the links between us.<br />
Of course, the creation of a free and democratic state of<br />
Ireland is the more remarkable an achievement because it was<br />
only possible after a prolonged struggle for independence<br />
and the horrors of a civil war.<br />
we applaud, Taoiseach, your commitment to seeking a peaceful<br />
resolution to the troubles in Northern Ireland. We welcome<br />
the mechanisms such as the Anglo-Irish agreement, which<br />
provide a framework to facilitate positive change. We<br />
completely endorse your Government's actions against those<br />
who blindly see violence as a solution. 305 </p>
<p>~-rI<br />
And I repeat what I said in Dublin: the Australian<br />
Government will do all within its power to discourage any<br />
Australian citizen from adding in any way to the violence in<br />
Northern Ireland.<br />
You will find, Taoiseach, as you travel around Australia,<br />
that Australians of Irish descent have largely left the<br />
bitterness behind them. Instead, like so many people who<br />
have cone to settle in Australia from overseas, while they<br />
retain the love of their land of origin it is commitment to<br />
their new home that is paramount.<br />
Taoi seach,<br />
Both Ireland and Australia have found that economic<br />
challenges must still be overcome if we are to safeguard the<br />
prosperity we have enjoyed. We have, both had to take hard<br />
decisions to secure the longterm prosperity of our<br />
countries.<br />
Australia has a newfound determination to tackle our<br />
underlying economic problems, to diversify our economy and<br />
broaden our work skills so we become a more competitive and<br />
more outward looking country, venturing on to world markets<br />
rather than sheltering behind the constricting barriers of<br />
protection.<br />
We see a need to lower such trade barriers. We are doing<br />
just that at home and because trade for Australia as for<br />
Ireland is vital we are urging abroad a new effort to<br />
safeguard the international trading system, through the<br />
Uruguay Round of Multilateral Trade Negotiations.<br />
Taoi seach,<br />
Both Australia and Ireland have earned reputations around<br />
the world for our efforts to lessen conflict and tension,<br />
and to control and reverse the arms race.<br />
We live in a time when the stakes are higher than ever<br />
before, in that world conflict could well lead to the<br />
obliteration of mankind. But we have seen in recent months<br />
a significant easing of tensions between the superpowers.<br />
The signing of the first treaty-ever to eliminate a class of<br />
nuclear weapons the INF Treaty and the generally<br />
positive dialogue conducted at the Summits between President<br />
Reagan and General Secretary Gorbachev give us all some<br />
cause for hope. And, to the extent that we have encouraged<br />
the leaders of those nations, they give Australia and<br />
Ireland some particular cause for satisfaction.<br />
Taoi seach,<br />
As you know, 1988 is both the Australian Bicentennial year<br />
and the millennium of the City of Dublin a fact that<br />
dramatically emphasises how recently Europeans came to this<br />
continent.<br />
306 </p>
<p>The Irish contribution to our Bicentenary celebrations has<br />
been a generous and valuable one.<br />
The Irish sail training vessel, the Asgard II,' participated<br />
in the Parade of Tall Ships. There has been a tremendous<br />
number of exchanges in the artistic and scholarly fields.<br />
And only this afternoon, Taoiseach, you presented the<br />
computerised records of some 40,000 Irish men and women<br />
transported to Australia in the eighteenth and nineteenth<br />
centuries. These records will provide an invaluable<br />
resource for scholars and for those many Australians seeking<br />
to trace their Irish ancestry.<br />
But that is not the end of the Irish Bicentennial presence<br />
in Australia.<br />
when I was in Dublin, the Irish Government hosted am<br />
official dinner which was memorable in every respect. We<br />
sat down in the magnificently refurbished Royal Hospital<br />
Kilmainham. we were very well fed. Those of us who drink<br />
were very well drunk.<br />
And we were superbly entertained with singing and dancing.<br />
I was particularly impressed with a group called Siamsa<br />
Tire, which performs Irish folk dances, and I made the<br />
promise then that I would see to it that Siamsa Tire was<br />
able to perform before Australian audiences sometime during<br />
1988. It is my pleasure to announce that arrangements for the tour<br />
are now firm. Siansa Tire will visit nine Australian cities<br />
for performances in October and I wish them well for a<br />
successful tour. I look forward to attending one of their<br />
performances myself. I want to express my appreciation to<br />
Qantas, Australian Airlines and the Australian Bicentennial<br />
Authority for their support of the tour.<br />
Taoiseach, Ireland has produced a pantheon of great writers over the<br />
last one hundred years and one of the greatest of them was<br />
Oscar Wilde.<br />
Australians, of course, were from time to time the butt of<br />
Wilde's satire. A character in Lady Windermere's-Fan said<br />
she thought Australia must be so pretty " with all thFe dear<br />
little kangaroos flying about".<br />
But in a serious vein, Wilde once described what he called<br />
the great drama of his life. " It's that I have put my<br />
genius into living my life; all I've put into my works is<br />
my talent".<br />
Australians can be proud and it's proper tonight that we<br />
express our sense of debt that our country has received in<br />
unequalled measure both the spark of genius and the vast<br />
resource of talent that characterise the Irish people. 307 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
