<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3613</transcript-id>
    <title>SENATE VACANCIES AND THE STATES</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/02/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003613.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
l~ A U STALIA Press Statement No. 449<br />
12 February 1975<br />
SENATE VACANCIES AND THE STATES<br />
Earlier today I released the text of a letter<br />
dated 10 January 1952, from the then Premier of Western<br />
Australia, Sir Ross McLarty to the then Premier of<br />
South Australia the Hon. T. Playford. Mr Eric Reece<br />
has now confirmed that an identical letter was sent<br />
to the then Premier of Tasmania, the Hon. R. Cosgrove,<br />
M. H. A. Mr Cosgrove replied in the following terms:<br />
" I thank you for your letter of 10th January<br />
with regard to the vacancy whic. has arisen<br />
in the Senate because of the death of<br />
Senator Nash of Western Australia. I agree<br />
with your opinion that, in view of the fact<br />
that proportional representation is now the<br />
method of election to the Senate, a member<br />
of the same Party, nominated by the<br />
Executive of the Party, should be appointed<br />
when future vacancies arise, through death<br />
or other causes."<br />
I have sent a telegram to Sir Charles Court,<br />
the Premier of Western Australia asking him to release<br />
-the 1952 correspondence with all Premiers relating to<br />
this matter. Over 23 years ago there was an agreement<br />
among all the Premiers that casual vacancies in the<br />
Senate would be filled by a member of the same party.<br />
For 23 years State Governments of all political<br />
complexions have honoured this agreement. Now, for the<br />
first time, the new Premier of N. S. W. threatens to break<br />
this Constitutional convention. This is not a matter<br />
between the Australian Government and State Governments.<br />
The agreement in question was made among the State<br />
Governments themselves. The Premier of N. S. W. is<br />
threatening to break an agreement which Premiers in every<br />
State and of all parties have scrupulously observed<br />
since 1952.<br />
CANBERRA. A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
