<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4199</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA AT THE OFFICIAL DINNER IN HIS HONOUR HOSTED BY PRESIDENT FORD - 27 JULY 1976</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/07/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004199.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
~ 14
PRIME MINISTERI<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA AT THE OFFICIAL<br />
DINNER IN HIS HONOUR HOSTED BY PRESIDENT FORD 27 JULY 1976<br />
Mr President, thank you for your invitation to join<br />
you on this occasion, for your generous hospitality and for<br />
the opportunity it has given us to see America celebrating her<br />
Bicentennial. We were delighted to have your Vice-President and<br />
his wife in Australia a short while ago. During his visit we<br />
reaffirmed the friendship that has long existed between our<br />
p) eoples. I would like to say, Mr President, that your Vice-<br />
President was a warm and gifted Ambassador for your country,<br />
and the discussions we had were constructive and useful.<br />
Earlier this year we were also delighted to welcome<br />
Mrs Kissinger. I would also like to express our appreciation<br />
to Secretary Kissinger for making himself so frequently<br />
available for discussions between my Foreign Minister and<br />
himself. 0 Australians probably have more cause to celebrate<br />
the Bicentennial with you than any other country. If it had<br />
not been for your successful War of Independence against the<br />
British, it is most unlikely that the British would have<br />
settled Australia when they did.<br />
I know I speak for the many Australians here when<br />
I say how pleased we have been to make some contribution to<br />
your Bicentennial celebrations. Amongst the many different<br />
contributions that were made I would like to mention the<br />
Australian Ballet. I hope that those of you who saw their<br />
performance enjoyed it.<br />
Mr President,, we did have cause to be grateful to<br />
the United States even in the early days0 There are many<br />
who think that our nation's beef trade is a recent development.<br />
But in 1792 the struggling Colony of Port Jackson received an<br />
important shipment from the American ship ' Philadelphia'. The<br />
voyage took nine months so by the time it arrived the cargo of<br />
barrels of American beef was well cured. Our local crops had<br />
not been very successful and your beef was greeted enthusiastically.<br />
It is a shipment we are prepared to return a thousand-fold. o </p>
<p>Mr President, Australia, and America have many<br />
things-i ri commoni our : rroni ter experience atid the Cact<br />
that we atc b) oth migrant nations. We both valute our<br />
ifl( I C pendei'' 0Cc and oi demo c rant ic inst ituti ons~, oiir-ide'' al . s<br />
of' freedlom and] oppor-tunity.<br />
Our histories have taught us both that we have<br />
our freedom not as of right, but only so long as we remain<br />
vigilant and resourceful. I know that in support of our<br />
ideals we will work together in the future as we have in<br />
the past,. In our countries the State is regarded as the<br />
servant of the people. In other countries these values<br />
are set aside the State is paramount. Such differences<br />
have often led to conflict. The great challenge of the<br />
next twenty five years will be whether or not countries<br />
with differing social systems can learn to live together,<br />
and resolve their international differences by negotiation.<br />
In the uncertain world which faces us the need<br />
for co-operation is strong,. This is especially so bccause<br />
over recent years there has been criticism where there<br />
should have been understanding.<br />
We are aware that there has been vigorous debate<br />
within the United States on your world role. We believe<br />
that out of such debate emerges a stronger and a freer<br />
nation one more able to provide the leadership the world<br />
requires. We appreciate the manner in which the United States<br />
has persisted. In future years the resolution of the American<br />
people is going to be more important for securing the peace of<br />
the world than it has ever been.<br />
That is by no means to suggest that countries such<br />
as mine do not have responsibilities. Whatever others may<br />
feel, no Australian assumes that we are entitled to a free<br />
ride, that your efforts are a reason why we should be<br />
complacent or negligent about our responsibilities. It is<br />
merely recognition that as the world's greatest free power,<br />
there are many things that only the United States can do.<br />
If the United States does not do them they will remain undone,.<br />
Others may contribute, but your strength is indispensable in<br />
supporting the diplomacy and negotiation essential for the<br />
building of peace. The fact that your nation attracts<br />
criticism in its international role is much less important<br />
than the fact that the task is done,. * oo/ 3 </p>
<p>Mr President, over the last two hundred years<br />
there haive been many revolutions, But whatever some other<br />
ideol ogic. may claim for thelir revol. ulioin, youtr. s is<br />
distinguished by its unequalled democratic character, by<br />
its purpose and by its morality,<br />
The ideas contained in the Declaration of<br />
Independence still stir the hearts of men and women around<br />
the world. We can find in that Declaration the philosophy<br />
of the best social reforms that have taken place in the<br />
years since. Mr President, we know the great responsibility<br />
that rests on democratic leadership. That is one of the<br />
reasons why meeting the demands of the Office you hold<br />
must be the most difficult but at the same time the most<br />
rewarding task in the world.<br />
Your country, Mr President, has made an immeasurable<br />
contribution to world peace, and to the ideal of liberty,<br />
There has never been a time when support of these ideals<br />
has required more dedication, more firmness, more persistence<br />
than now, My wife and I are honoured to be here and I ask<br />
you now to rise and drink the toast:<br />
The President of the United States'. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
