<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4090</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS TO TEH INSTITUTE OF DIRECTORS</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/04/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004090.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
F76/ 61<br />
EMBARGO: .8.00 p m. ), ASLI<br />
FOR PRESS 1 April 1976<br />
ADDRESS TO. THE INSTITUTE OF DIRECTORS<br />
Tonight I want to set out the problems the Government<br />
confronted on coming to office, the Government's strategy<br />
to restore prosperity to Australia, and to show how the policies<br />
the Government has adopted and will adopt fit in to the<br />
basic strategy.<br />
When we can to office Australia was facing an unprecedented<br />
set of economic problems.<br />
Government spending had grown enormously, financed by a<br />
heavier tax burden on individuals and massive erosion of company<br />
profits. We faced a deficit far above the announced deficit<br />
of. the Hayden Budget of $ 2,800 million. Unemployment was at record<br />
levels. Rapid inflation was eroding savings and income levels<br />
and generating inflationary expectations. Liquidity was<br />
excessive and the money supply was increasing at a rate of<br />
percent per annum. or more. Consumers, uncertain about<br />
the future, were saving a substantially higher proportion of<br />
thleir incomes. Businesses, for reasons of confidence and<br />
finance, were reluctant to invest.<br />
In the view of the Government the principal source of these<br />
problems has been appalling domestic mismanagement.<br />
At the heart of the problem, in our view, has been the enormous<br />
rapid increase in Government spending.<br />
The tax burden on individuals inevitably stimulated wage<br />
demands. The tax burden on companies resulting from the<br />
combination of inflation, accounting practices, and the tax<br />
system, has been eroding the nation's capital base, and<br />
absorbing the funds needed for business. expansion. Combined with the<br />
wage and salary costs of the previous years, there was a<br />
major obstacle in the way of new investment.<br />
Alongside the tax burden the Government had sought to regulate<br />
business more and more often without regard for the costs<br />
of this regulation or whether it was in fact achieving its<br />
stated objectives. 2 </p>
<p>Indeed, many people came to believe that there was a concerted<br />
effort to undermine private enterprise in Australia to provide<br />
the scope fcr yet further Governmient intervention and control.<br />
Our strategy and the programme we have developed is<br />
designed to tackle these central problems in a balanced and<br />
predictable way.<br />
Our broad objectives are firstly, to restrain Government<br />
spending and on the basis of such restraint transfer<br />
resources back to private enterprise and individuals.<br />
In this way the real value of people's incomes can be<br />
protected and private enterprise which provides threE out<br />
of ' Lour jobs can have once again the confidence and the<br />
resources to invest.<br />
This transfer of resources is a key element in realising our<br />
objectives of easing the pressure on wages and salaries<br />
and creating conditions for an expansion of employment<br />
opportunities. While providing real protection for the consumer a further<br />
objective is to free business of unnecessary, inefficient, and<br />
excessive regulation.<br />
In our view private enterprise needs room to breathe, to<br />
grow, to expand. Australia must once more become a country<br />
which offers rewards for initiative, enterprise and hard<br />
w~ rk.<br />
The Government also wants to generate a climate of national<br />
responsibility in which business and trade unions will both<br />
act with a principal regard for the national interest.<br />
We aim to achieve this in part by emphasising consultation<br />
with all sections of the community and by an announced<br />
and known strategy on the basis of which our policy decisions<br />
will be madie. The experience of the last three years<br />
demonstrates that unreasonod changes in policy do nothing but<br />
impede growth, destroy confidence, and create further'<br />
uncertainty. It is the view of the Government that business recovery and<br />
consumer confidence are both impeded by the same fact an<br />
anxiety about the future which it is the over-riding objective<br />
of our policies to dispel.<br />
Let me now mention the policy decisions and actions we have<br />
taken and intend to take to give effect to our strategy.<br />
Immediately after the election we took action to cut back<br />
on Government spending and unnecessary bureaucracy and to<br />
improve administrative efficiency. We have already made a<br />
large number of economies in administrative expenses and<br />
spending programmes starting with the spending of Ministers<br />
and other M. P.' s. / 3 </p>
<p>There is clearly a limit to the number of major savings<br />
which can be made in the last part of A financial year<br />
but we have already announced economies worth $ 360 million.<br />
In terms of annual rates these economies are equivalent to<br />
savings of approximately $ 1 billion.<br />
We have halted the growth of the Federal Public Service. In<br />
fact there will be 17,480 fewer people employed in the Federal<br />
bureaucracy by the end of June than under the ceilings set by<br />
the previous Government. The review of spending and<br />
administrative efficiency-is continuing. At present<br />
the Government is of course, examining all its expenditure<br />
commitments in the course of Budget planning.<br />
Restraining Government expenditure is an enormous task. These<br />
measures will ba essential steps in our strategy of recovery.<br />
I ~ do not wish to pretend that the cuts in Government spending<br />
will be easy or painless. The Government is fac~ ing very<br />
difficult decisions. Responsible and determined choices will<br />
have to be make. Australia simply cannot afford all the<br />
programmes politicians tend to promise.<br />
The truth is that in order to bring inflation under control<br />
and expand productive employment the Government has to face up<br />
to these problems. If we succeed in this, Australia can<br />
once again be the great country we know that it is.<br />
I want it to be very clearly known that the Government<br />
places priority at this critical time on stopping the erosion<br />
of individuals and business incomes through inflation.<br />
We have-undertaken to begin the implementation of personal<br />
income tax indexation and inflation adjustments in the<br />
company tax area. We want to assure all Australians that there<br />
will be the restraints we have undertaken so that the largest<br />
possible step towards tax indexation can be taken.<br />
Tax indexation serves to assist in preventing the erosion<br />
of peopl&amp;' s incomes. By contrast money wage rises in line<br />
with past price increases simply stimulate more inflation and<br />
erode investment funds.<br />
Restraint in Government spending has been accompanied by measures<br />
designed to facilitate investment and reduce the cash crisis<br />
for many businesses.<br />
These measures incliude the 40 percent investment allowance.<br />
This allowance is a long-term policy which will boost Australia's<br />
future productive capacity. So that businesses can-plan securely<br />
on the basis of the measure, we have announced that the allowance<br />
has been introduced for a 7 1/ 2 year period beginning 1 January<br />
this year, at a rate of 40 percent for the first 2 1/ 2 years<br />
and 20 percent thereafter. Neither this, nor any other<br />
policy is going to produce overnight miracles. But there is<br />
no doubt that it is going to provide a strong indiicement<br />
to private sector activity. </p>
<p>A second measure towards the objective of easing cash<br />
flow problems has been the suspension of quarterly tax<br />
instalments.<br />
Every sector of the Australian economy is interdependent<br />
and we have taken a number of measures to assis; t rural*<br />
industry on the basis of IAC reports.<br />
As an expression of our detarmination to free business of<br />
unwise and-unnecessary regulation which is not in the public<br />
interest we have this week announced an inquiry into the<br />
operation of the Restrictive Trade Practices legislation.<br />
In the area of monetary policy we believe it is important<br />
that the Government's long-term intentions for the growth<br />
of the money supply should not be in doubt.. There is a<br />
clear, demonstrated relationship between excessive growth of<br />
the money supply and high rates of inflation. Unless the<br />
Government is prepared to tackle this problem there is no<br />
hope for a reduiction of*. inflation. in the medium and long term.<br />
W introduced earlier this year a comprehensive and flexible<br />
monetary package which has already'set us on course to<br />
achieving this objective. However, it is clear that the<br />
changes in money supply bought about by the policies of the<br />
previous Government did great damage to business.<br />
Out appraoch will ensure that the private sectors will have the<br />
ability to finance economic recovery. Normal seasonal needs for<br />
liquidity in the coming months will be met.<br />
The Government is determined to do its part in the fight<br />
against inflation. But the Government cannot win the battle<br />
against inflation alone.. Australians will show, the kind of<br />
people they are by their preparedness to cooperate in the<br />
fight against inflation. In such a vital national effort, no<br />
section of the community can afford to look at-its own<br />
interests in isolation.<br />
One fact has emerged v-ery clearly from the experience of<br />
the astLhre yers al sections of the Australian communi-ty,<br />
all sectors of the Australian economy, are interdependent.<br />
At any one time the total resources of Australians are limited.<br />
One section of the community cannot greatly increase its<br />
share except at the expense of other sections; ' decisions<br />
taken by one group affect many others who have no say in those<br />
decisions. Powerful trade unions can only greatly increase the real<br />
resources going to their members by eroding the value of<br />
incomes and savings of the weaker sections of the community,<br />
or by absorbing resources which could be used to create jobs.<br />
Large companies have to keep in mind that decisions they<br />
take with respect to their own employees may have repercussions </p>
<p>far beyond their own business. Such companies have. a<br />
responsibility to consider the consequences of those decisions.<br />
They ignore this responsibilty at their peril.<br />
Government has a responsibility to ensure that its programmes<br />
do not unnecessarily absorb resources which are needed by<br />
individuals and families to meet their own needs. When the<br />
Government fails to take this into account, it directly<br />
encourages pressures for higher real wages.<br />
Every part of the community, every institution concerned<br />
with economic life, has a responsibility to help bring<br />
inflation under control and expand employment opportunities.<br />
In the return to a non-inflationary prosperity the role of<br />
the Arbitration Commission is of major importance.<br />
Wages must be at a level that the economy can pay at a<br />
level which will not add to inflation and unemployment.<br />
The Government has a responsibility to put its views on the<br />
economy to the Commission in strong terms. Other parties<br />
have a similar responsibility.<br />
Ultimately of course, the decision on any particular case<br />
is the Arbitration Commission's. But in reaching its<br />
decision the Commission itself must take into account the<br />
general state of the economy and social justice.<br />
Justice in present circumstances is on the side of those<br />
thrown out of employment by excessive wage increases.<br />
Business leaders, leaders of the trade union movement, and<br />
Governments all have a critical role to play in the<br />
control of inflation and the revival of employment opportunities.<br />
I believe there is a growing recognition of this fact<br />
throughout Australia.<br />
Great numbers of people on the shop floor are becoming<br />
aware in a way they have not been before, that money paid<br />
in excessive increases in wages and salaries is not available<br />
to creaite new jobs, or even to support existing jobs. In fact<br />
many rank and file members of trade unions are probably more<br />
aware-of this fact than some trade union leaders. one of the<br />
most important contLributions that can be made to economic<br />
recovery by business is to encourage a greater awareness of<br />
this basic fact.<br />
I do not need to emphasise before this audience how critical<br />
industrial relations are to bringing inflation under control.<br />
There can be no stronger foundation for good industrial<br />
relations than widespread understanding of the true nature of<br />
the problems that face us.<br />
Talking about the need for a national cooperative effort has<br />
to be matched by cooperative action. Effective cooperative<br />
action has to be based on frank discussion, mutual consultations. / 6 </p>
<p>Some companies have very good procedures for discussing<br />
matters with employees. This is a time more than ever,<br />
when the example of the best should b2 followed by everyone.<br />
If employees can get a ciear picture of the impact of their<br />
wage and salary demands on their own firm, I have no doubt<br />
that people will wish, of their own account, to act with<br />
great responsibility.<br />
There is no substitute for direct and frank face to face<br />
discussions and exchange of information to build a spirit<br />
of understanding and cooperation.<br />
For many years now, those who believe that the free enterprise<br />
system is best for all Australians have been less active than<br />
we should in puttinq the case. TJ-hat is one reason why we<br />
have suffered the experience of the last three years.<br />
It is good to see that an increasing number of people are<br />
taking action to ensure that there is a growing appreciation<br />
of the common-interests of everyone in a profitable and<br />
efficient private sector.<br />
1believe-it is important to remember that understanding<br />
is advanced not only by the availability of high quality<br />
objective material but even more importantly by relations within<br />
the particular-firm and by the effort that management<br />
makes there. It needs to be explained clearly that new<br />
plant, new equipment,, new jobs, are created out of profits.<br />
It also needs to be explained that in a country like Australia,<br />
profits are very widely distributed directly-to shareholders<br />
and indirectly to the millions of holders of insurance and<br />
superannuation policies.<br />
There needs to be a much clearer understanding of the central<br />
role of private enterprise in providing through taxation,<br />
the resources for Government to spend on such. things as<br />
social welfare, education, roads, defence and -so on.<br />
In the current year, for example, private enterprise will<br />
directly contribute ( through company taxes over $ 2,000 million<br />
to Government more than enough to cover the entire expenditure<br />
of the Commonwealth Government on education.<br />
Real expansion in social programmes which is not financed<br />
simply by transferring resources from some other group in the<br />
community must be financed out of growth. Real growth<br />
depends on a healthy and vital private enterprise.<br />
Private enterprise does not merely provide the resources which<br />
Government can-use to improve its provision. A healthy<br />
private enterprise is an essential part of the life Australians<br />
value. Private enterprise provides the greatest opportunities. it<br />
provides a choice of rewarding jobs, a choice of products and<br />
a choice of services, / 17<br />
L </p>
<p>It is the system which gives the man in the street the<br />
greatest control over what is produced. In this sense,<br />
it is the most democratic system the system which is<br />
most compatible with the freedom Australians value.<br />
Under the Labour Government, the survival of private<br />
enterprise was endangered. We were well on the way to<br />
a conformist, centralised society in which the real wealth<br />
of Australia, the productive energies and initiative of<br />
the Australian people were suppressed.<br />
The strategy the Government has adopted, the measures we<br />
have already announced, and will announce in the coming<br />
months, will ensure that that does not happen.<br />
I am confident that our approach is already providing<br />
a solid basis for the revival of prosperity in Australia,<br />
and for the development in Australia of a society in which<br />
the interests of all Australians are truly served. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
