<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7322</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER CELEBRATION FOR FORMER REFUSENIRS MELBOURNE - 17 MAY 1988</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/05/1988</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007322.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MAINISTE<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
CELEBRATION FOR FORMER REFUSENIKS<br />
MELBOURNE 17 MAY 1988<br />
Isi Leibler,<br />
Edgar Bronfman, President World Jewish Congress,<br />
Ladies and gentlemen<br />
At 5.15 pm on December 2nd last year Hazel and I were just<br />
preparing to leave the State guest house in Moscow to drive<br />
to the airport with Soviet Prime Minister Ryzhkov for our<br />
return to Australia. The phone rang with a message that the<br />
personal emissary of Mikhail Gorbachev was on his way to see<br />
me. Perhaps you can begin to imagine the emotion I felt when the<br />
messenger told me that Mr Gorbachev personally authorised<br />
him to say that Rosa and Alex Ioffe and their daughter Anna<br />
and Marta and Pavel Abramovich five on the list I had<br />
presented to the Secretary General were to be allowed to<br />
leave the Soviet Union.<br />
Naturally my thoughts flashed back nine years, to 1979, to<br />
the time of high hopes at the end of my previous visit<br />
followed by the agonising despair of dashed expectations.<br />
And perhaps you can understand that I allowed myself the<br />
luxury of a little exultation at a mission, long frustrated,<br />
now partly accomplished.<br />
But overwhelmingly my friends, my feelings then, as are<br />
yours tonight, were of unqualified joy for the bravest of<br />
people. Nothing can eclipse for me, for you, the sheer joy<br />
and sense of relief that we all feel now at seeing so many<br />
friends, so many brave people, and knowing that they have at<br />
last been permitted to live in freedom.<br />
These five had been among some thirty Refuseniks who<br />
attended a memorable reception held that morning at the<br />
Australian Embassy.<br />
At that reception it was Alexander Lerner, whom I met in<br />
such frustrating circumstances in 1979, who spoke on behalf<br />
of the Refuseniks. 006454 </p>
<p>2.<br />
His were the words of a brave and selfless man. By acting<br />
as spokesman over the years, Alexander Lerner had helped the<br />
general cause at considerable risk to his own interests.<br />
Tonight I want to thank him again for his inspiring words of<br />
hope on that occasion a message which I know inspired<br />
Hazel and me and all the membe., s of the travelling party.<br />
And I want to say publicly that, even though it is now 1988<br />
rather than 1979, even though nine years have passed since I<br />
first believed Alexander Lerner would be free, it is still a<br />
precious pleasure to welcome him to Australia tonight.<br />
I should mention also Yosef and Inna Begun, who had been<br />
Refuseniks since 1971 and who, though granted permission to<br />
leave, stayed until their son could also leave. Anna and<br />
Alexander Kholmyansky and Elena and Vladimir Prestin were<br />
also at the Embassy reception. Elena and Vladimir had<br />
already received permission to leave and I am delighted that<br />
Anna and Alexander subsequently did so.<br />
Leonid and Ludmilla Volvovsky and Maria and Vladimir Slepak<br />
are also very welcome guests tonight.<br />
But there is one further piece of good news with which some<br />
of you may not yet be familiar.<br />
Among the guests at that Embassy reception were Isolde and<br />
Vladimir Tufeld.<br />
Isolde, as you know, was very ill, and she has since been<br />
given permission to get medical treatment in the United<br />
States. I have continued to make representations on their behalf.<br />
I was delighted tor be informed last week by the Soviet<br />
Embassy in Canberra that Vladimir Tufeld has been given<br />
permission to join his wife in the United States. I know I<br />
speak for all of us when I express my relief and<br />
appreciation at their release.<br />
our sense of joy for those I have mentioned, for all those<br />
who are withfus tonight, is of course tinged with sadnessfor<br />
we all kgow those many more who deserve to be here but<br />
who are stilf denied the basic human right to emigrate.<br />
As we embrace with you in joy tonight so too do we remember<br />
those in sorrow.<br />
My friends, it is sensible to ask ourselves why it is<br />
possible both to have this occasion for celebration and,<br />
cautiously, to think with some degree of hope for those<br />
others whom, as I say, we also remember tonight.<br />
First, and above all else, is the continuing indomitable<br />
splendour of the human spirit displayed by the Lerners, the<br />
Prestins, the Beguns, the Slepaks, the Ioffes, the 006455 </p>
<p>3.<br />
Abramoviches and their kind. If in the darkest days, they<br />
had given up hope, no other force would have availed. Their<br />
strength, their courage, their determination has been the<br />
foundation on which everything else has been developed.<br />
Second, there has been the sustained and principled support<br />
and commitment of the world Jewish community, through<br />
leaders like Edgar Bronfman, for their brothers and sisters<br />
in the Soviet Union.<br />
In this effort, the Australian Jewish community can take<br />
great pride in what it has done. I want to pay particular<br />
tribute to Isi Leibler for his personal efforts over many<br />
years. I venture to say, Isi, that nobody has made a<br />
greater individual contribution than have you.<br />
Third, that we are able to meet tonight in celebration and<br />
hope is a tribute to the way in which a number of Western<br />
countries, including Australia, have placed the issue of<br />
human rights, including the situation of Soviet Jews, not at<br />
the periphery but in the mainstream of their reI~ tions with<br />
the Soviet Union.<br />
Speaking for Australia, both Bill Hayden as he did in<br />
Moscow in 1984 and I have raised these issues with Soviet<br />
diplomatic representatives in Canberra and with the Soviet<br />
Foreign Minister, Mr Shevardnadze, on his visit to Australia<br />
in March last year.<br />
Joan Child, the Speaker of the House of Representatives, on<br />
her visit to the Soviet Union in July 1986, presented a list<br />
of Refuseniks to the Chairman of the Council of<br />
Nationalities of the Supreme Soviet.<br />
And, as you know, the issue was a central part of my<br />
discussions with General Secretary Gorbachev last year. I<br />
presented Mr Gorbachev with a list of special cases which we<br />
believed warranted particular attention.<br />
I used the words " speaking for Australia" deliberately,<br />
because I have been gratefully conscious that when I and my<br />
colleagues have been making these representations I know<br />
that I have been speaking with the full support of the<br />
Opposition and the overwhelming majority of the Australian<br />
people. The United States, too, has been at the forefront on this<br />
matter. In a recent speech my friend Secretary of State<br />
George Shultz noted that human rights and humanitarian<br />
issues had become an established and regular part of<br />
US-Soviet negotiations.<br />
He described his latest talks with his counterpart, Mr<br />
Shevardnadze, as the most searching set of discussions ever<br />
on human rights.<br />
Fourth, there is no doubt that our capacity to advance this<br />
cause is, in large part, a function of changes in the Soviet 006456 </p>
<p>Union associated with the Gorbachev era. Tonight is not the<br />
occasion to dwell at length upon the enormous com plexities<br />
and implications of these changes but certain th~' igs should<br />
be said.<br />
The new Soviet leadership is not about the creation of a<br />
western style liberal democracy. But it is about attempting<br />
to embark on a massive, and certainly overdue, reform of the<br />
Soviet economy. The concepts of perestroika and glasnost<br />
are instruments of that intention and process of-~ reform.<br />
There is a recognition by the Soviet leadership that<br />
effective internal econamic reform~ cannot ultinzate1lj occur<br />
without the Soviet Union becoming an organic part of the<br />
international division of labour.<br />
implicit in this is their understanding that the necessary<br />
degree of international economic integration cannot occur<br />
without a corresponding measure of political accommodation.<br />
The Washington Summit between Mr Gorbachev and<br />
President Reagan, their signing of the INF Treaty, the<br />
impending withdrawal from Afghanistan and the upd'oming<br />
Moscow Summit are all signs that we may be entering a<br />
significant new era of East-West communication in which<br />
hostility is replaced with a constructive willingness to<br />
negotiate. So clearly, we are seeing a period of very important, and<br />
fascinating, change in the Soviet Union.<br />
We should recognise the connection that appears to exist<br />
between progress on human rights and the development of a<br />
constructive dialogue on broader issues between East and<br />
West. In the Gorbachev era, that dialogue has been unusually<br />
intense and generally positive.<br />
In approaching human rights issues, Mr Gorbachev and his<br />
colleagues appear to be serious about minimising impediments<br />
standing in the way of a closer relationship with the West.<br />
That is why Australia and other Western countries were right<br />
in putting human rights at the centre of their dialogue with<br />
the Soviet Union.<br />
I believe we should respond positively, constructively and,<br />
in the light of history, with appropriate caution to this<br />
new, and in so many ways promising Gorbachev era. We would<br />
be churlish if we did not recognise the advances, naive if<br />
we ignored this need for caution.<br />
In human rights as in all areas of our relationship with the<br />
Soviet Union, we will judge them by their actions, not<br />
simply by their words. 006457 </p>
<p>Australia will continue to press the Soviet Union on<br />
individual Refusenik cases.<br />
As George Shultzput it in his talks with Mr Shevardnadze,<br />
we want to see a situation where emigration is handled<br />
according to established and legal arrangements and not, in<br />
his words, according to the whim of the moment.<br />
My friends,<br />
Those with whom we celebrate tonight have achieved their<br />
cherished dream in the year of the 40th anniversary of the<br />
foundation of the State of Israel.<br />
our sense of celebration is necessarily muted to some degree<br />
by our consciousness of the magnitude of the problems<br />
confronting the people and leadership of Israel today.<br />
I do not need in this audience to reaffirm my strong and<br />
undiminished commitment, or that of my Government to a<br />
secure and peaceful Israel.<br />
Last year, at the Hebrew University in Jerusalen,-I argued<br />
that now was the time for Israel, having courageously and<br />
successfully weathered the challenge of war, to" Tace a<br />
different and, paradoxically, tougher challenge the<br />
challenge of peace.<br />
The subsequent tragic events in the West Bank and Gaza have<br />
further convinced me that the democratic, humanist<br />
principles on which Israel was built do not sit easily with<br />
the role of master of occupied territories and subject<br />
peoples. The Palestinian in the occupied territories, as the Jew in<br />
the Soviet Union and the black in South Africa has his<br />
aspirations to be fully free.<br />
The friends of Israel, around the world, are fearful that in<br />
a real sense we may be witnessing again after thousands of<br />
years a giant eyeless in Gaza. Is there not emerging the<br />
danger of Israel being blinded to the threat to its very<br />
soul and the vision of its founders?<br />
I have spoken in Israel and here that the time bomb of<br />
demography is ticking away remorselessly. within a<br />
generation, if Israel seeks to maintain its hegemony in the<br />
occuped territories the Jews of Israel face the certain<br />
prospect of being a minority in their own land. They will<br />
face the stark choice of being a democratic State or a<br />
Jewish State they will not be able to be both.<br />
This is not the time to rehearse in detail my proposal<br />
outlined in Israel last year for an international<br />
conference and an act of simultaneous mutual recognition on<br />
acceptable conditions between Israel and the PLO, as a basis<br />
for resolving the Palestinian problem. 006458 </p>
<p>Those conditions are that the PLO must recognise Israel's<br />
right to exist within secure and internationally recognised<br />
borders; it must pccept Resolutions 242 and 338 as the basis<br />
for any settlement; and it must reject unequivocally the use<br />
of terror and accept the process of negotiation. In return,<br />
Israel would acknowledge that the PLO has a representative<br />
capacity. I was very pleased to see that recently John Howard accepted<br />
precisely this formula.<br />
Australia can speak to the world with a truly bipartisan<br />
voice on this important issue of concern to us all.<br />
An international conference such as I have outlined offers<br />
the best chance of peace in the region.<br />
It holds out the best means of avoiding further needless<br />
bloodshed and heavy handed repression in the occupied<br />
territories.<br />
And it offers Israel the sure means of survival in the<br />
democratic Jewish form which its founders intendedA<br />
That form still inspires its friends around the world, no<br />
one more than myself. And that form still acts as an<br />
inspiration for those Jews in the Soviet Union who seek<br />
freedom. Israel must not let that inspiration be dimmed.<br />
My friends,<br />
You have done me a very great honour by allowing me to speak<br />
this evening on these matters which are so close to my heart<br />
and which are so important for Australia's international<br />
relationships. In particular, Edgar Bronfman, you have honoured me by<br />
presenting me with an award on behalf of the World Jewish<br />
Congress. I want to repeat my deep appreciation for the unremitting<br />
efforts and support which the Jewish community and you<br />
personally, Isi, have extended on behalf of the Refuseniks.<br />
I know well the overwhelming emotion which you are<br />
experiencing on welcoming Alexander Lerner and his<br />
colleagues among us in Australia. And I repeat that without<br />
your efforts, the results which Governments such as ours<br />
could achieve would be negligible.<br />
my friends,<br />
The story of the Soviet Jews is a human drama of vast<br />
proportions. 0 06G4-99 </p>
<p>That is why the real guests of honour tonight are the heroes<br />
and heroines of this drama, the men and women who have<br />
endured great hardship and overcome years of injustice , to be<br />
with us tonight.<br />
I am proud, and I think all Australians are proud, to have<br />
played a part in their achieving victory in that struggle.<br />
But it is their victory they paid the price in the long<br />
years of waiting and the wasted opportunities and they are<br />
the ones. who with our best wishes are now able to live in<br />
peace and freedom. 006460 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
