<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6012</transcript-id>
    <title>IMPLEMENTATION OF THE OFFSHORE CONSTITUTIONAL SETTLEMENT</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/02/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006012.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
U S&gt;; AUALLL<br />
PRIME MINM3TER<br />
FOR MEDIA FRIDAY, 4 FEBRUARY 1983<br />
IMPLEMENTATION OF THE OFFSHORE CONSTITUTIONAL SETTLEMEN4T<br />
The Commonwealth, after extensive consultation with the States,<br />
has completed implementation of measures which achieve a<br />
significant adjustment of powers and responsibilities in the<br />
offshore area.<br />
The remaining key elements of the Offshore Constitutional<br />
Settlement reached at the Premiers' Conference in June 1979<br />
have been proclaimed to come into effect on Monday<br />
14 February 1983. From that date, the re-ordering of powers<br />
and responsibilities in the offshore area, as agreed by the<br />
Commonwealth and the States, will be fully operative.<br />
The measures to commence on 14 February 1983' are:<br />
-the Coastal Waters ( State Title) Act 1980,<br />
-the Coastal Waters ( Northern Territory Title) Act 1980,<br />
-the Petroleum ( Submerged Lands) Amendment Act 1980 and<br />
associated Acts,<br />
-the Fisheries Amendment Act 1980, and<br />
-new baselines from which the breadth of Australia's<br />
territorial sea is to be measured.<br />
These measures are additional to the Coastal Waters ( State<br />
Powers) Act 1980, the Coastal Waters ( Northern Territory Powers)<br />
Act 1980 and the Seas and Submerged Lands Amendment Act 1980<br />
which came into force on 1 January last year.<br />
The Settlement represents the completion of a most successful<br />
exercise in co-operative federalism.<br />
The High Court's decision in the Seas and Submerged Lands Case<br />
in 1975 meant that the Commonwealth could have exercised legal<br />
dominance in the offshore area, denying to the States any say<br />
in the resources of the offshore area and in the regulation of<br />
activities that take place in that area. The Government,<br />
however, adopted a course of consultation and co-operation<br />
consistent with its belief that the territorial sea is an area<br />
which has traditionally been a State responsibility and is<br />
best left for local jurisdiction except on matters of over-riding<br />
national or international significance. 2 </p>
<p>2.<br />
The Settlement will enable us all effectively to exercise our<br />
rights'and responsibilities with regard to offshore Australia<br />
and will be of benefit to all governments and to the people<br />
of Australia.<br />
My colleagues the Attorney-General, and the Ministers for<br />
National Development and Energy and for Primary Industry, will<br />
be issuing separate statements on the details.<br />
000---<br />
r<br />
s </p>
<p>PR AM A ND4YJUT OR TH MINISTERFO<br />
PRIMARY INDUSTR1Y<br />
MEDRI IEEAS~ ~. CANBERRA<br />
PI 83/ 15. 4 February 1983.<br />
OFFSHORE CONSTITUTIONAL SETTLEMENTFISHERIES<br />
ASPECTS<br />
The Prime Minister's announcement of the<br />
commencement of the Offshore Constitutional Settlement<br />
was a landmark in the history of Australia's fishing<br />
industry, Mr Peter Nixon, the Minister for Primary<br />
Industry, said today.<br />
tMr Nixon said the Settlement offered a real<br />
prospect of removing many of the Commonwealth/ State<br />
jurisdictional divisions in Australian waters.<br />
" The way is now clear for the Commonwe al th and<br />
the States to work toward removing as many of the<br />
jurisdiction lines as possible, using the new Part IVA<br />
of Ithe Commonwealth Fisheries Act and the matching<br />
provisions of State laws," INr Nixon said.<br />
" Commonwealth and State fisheries officials have<br />
already begun discussions aimed at formulating recommendations<br />
about the application of a single law, Commonwealth or<br />
State, for the management of particular fisheries from,<br />
low-water mark to the outer edge of the 200 mile Australian<br />
fishing zone and the exercise of executive functions<br />
under that law."<br />
M r Nixon said the outcome of these discussions<br />
would be expressed in formal legal arrangements between<br />
the Commona: ealth and the States. </p>
<p>/ 2. " It will take some months to complete the<br />
discussions, including consultation with the fishing<br />
industry." Mr Nixon said that while there were some fisheries<br />
which were best managed by the States, the Government<br />
saw a continuing role-for the Commonwealth in the<br />
management of fisheries.<br />
He said the only immediate change to fisheries<br />
jurisdiction would result from the proclamation of<br />
straight baselines under the Seas and Submerged Lands<br />
number of areas of waters that were formerly under<br />
Commonwealth jurisdiction. In all other cases, until<br />
a Commonwealth/ State arrangement comes into force,<br />
the status quo, of State fisheries laws applying in<br />
* e i s. s tt aa t: bm. ha1 s. e. ate ar. k he. r<br />
no straight baseline has been proclaimed) and<br />
Commonwealth laws applying in proclaimed waters beyond<br />
coastal waters, will continue.<br />
Mr Nixon said the new fisheries provisions<br />
were an important element of the offshore settlement,<br />
establishing a framework for future Commonwealth and<br />
State co-operation in the management of an important<br />
primary industry. In 1981/ 82, the fishery-based industries<br />
contributed more than SA 300 million to national export<br />
earnings, as well as providing an important component<br />
of domestic food supplies. </p>
<p>PRESS RELEASE BY THE ATTORN EY-GENERAL<br />
AUSTRALIA i OxHOFR ArFFS EUE : ECu AC i r E7J~ MINT<br />
The Attorney-General, Senator Peter Durack, O. C. 9<br />
said that-thp final steps announced tocay to implement the<br />
ro: a inin key elements of the Offsho--e Constitutional<br />
Settlement completed a unique achivement in the history of<br />
r ederal/ State relations.<br />
The Offsh6re Settlement brourht an end to a longterm<br />
dispujte between the Commonwealt!-and the States.<br />
Cc'ip!. l cxand contentious iSSUe. S; a. SSOC. iattcd with<br />
th. e-orffsore area had bedevilled Cornonwealth/ State relations<br />
in 1tr l ia for cver a decade. The basic constitutional<br />
iszu! es w; cro ro sol ed by the High Court in the Seas and<br />
Lands Case in 1975 in favour of tihe Commonwealth.<br />
t-e o t ion elther to assert to the full its legal dominance<br />
. n th-2 offshore area, or' to adlopt a courstj of , o-operation and<br />
restraint tihat would lead to an ap. procpriate allocation of<br />
r'c-r's and resconsi bil i ties an: og all Govern: 71ent s in-<br />
A. 3stralia. Tihe second course Cnosase r, culminating in the<br />
Ci) ffSnc cLn sr: Z o n a1 et t1 e a r e edo at thc re;: 1i 1, s<br />
e, . r e ne 1 79<br />
re Standi Corm!: ni. ttee C' t. tcrncy's-Cen e,-a3 I p Y f<br />
enral role in dovisingF inMoiv-ive resures to carry out<br />
the areed arrangements.<br />
f. mc-nwealth legislation to erfsure that he Sts<br />
n 1re J ern T errn toy-yoss'Pc O ec c':: E: stidj tuir. a' itt<br />
:-.: cfshore a ra c amc in o f'orce on 1 J ara r: T sT<br />
d C. a S a -a L Si's a 0 E. r S c t I=~ 7~<br />
z r'rn r c. P c:: t! z r Act 8# C and<br />
t' fuP fi s e: </p>
<p>/ legislation and thO suc* c--?~ f ul compl eti on of further<br />
consultations on i-plement-a'ion with ' Ln State-, and thle<br />
Northern Territory, r." de possi ble the steps tha_ t were<br />
being announced : cday.<br />
The s-, eps announced by the Prime ~ i: s: rtoday<br />
consisted of the proclamation of the commencement from<br />
Monday, 14i February 1993, 9of the following Commonwealth Acts:<br />
Coastal Waters ( State Title) Act 1930<br />
Coastal Waters ( Northern Territory Title) Act 1980<br />
Petroleumn ( Submerged Lands) Amendment Act. 1980 and<br />
associated Acts<br />
Fl~ geri( s Amendrinnt. Act .1 98..<br />
A mst s i cn i fic related step that *: sannounc-ed<br />
Act 1073 oCr. now la n es : om . hich Le' b r c Pdt ft he<br />
; territorial sea of Australia is to be measured. This<br />
Aroclamation woild also comre into force * on Nc&gt; ndrya 1F6uaY.<br />
Adoption of these baselines, whichhd been prepared In<br />
consultation with the States as p) art of the O f fsh o re<br />
Cons titutional Settlement would mean a * signif icant enlargemer. t<br />
of the areas which com~ e directly under Plustralian -, ovcrei--n y<br />
The Government believed that the self -governin~ g<br />
status that the Northern Territory ac hieved in 1973 made it<br />
appropriate that the Northern Territory also should share in<br />
the benefits of the Settlement. It therefore shares in thle<br />
measures the commrencement of which is announced today.<br />
Commencement of the Commonwealth Acts would trigger.<br />
* the commen cemen' o f t he c-, 7 DI me n. a ry I eg is' at ior, pa. s seb<br />
all1 th e .3 a tes an d -he NoI-r,-e rn Ter!-tory con c e ri n~ of0f sho -e<br />
pe trol eurm min ing an fs hc. r ie. Th is efgi slat ion and the<br />
Commonwealth peltroleui-and f ti;* t ~ ervsinf:<br />
the : cstabliishment and coeration-o" j: Ltto r, i as a s ae<br />
L u nd er ,. he. f ~ hrlr " 1 " 4 ilet </p>
<p>Ar Title Acts<br />
I: The Title Acts will vest in each of the States<br />
and the Northern Territory proprietary ri. ghts and title in<br />
respect of the sedbed of the adjacent territorial sea. This<br />
measure, by conferring rights of ownership, will support the<br />
grant already made of legislative powers, and provide an<br />
assurance to the States that the Offshore Settlement will<br />
have permanency and stability.<br />
The Commonwealth's international obligations in<br />
the offshore area will not be affected. The seabed owned<br />
or used by the Commonwealth or an authority of the Commonwealth<br />
for any. specific Commonwealth purpose is not included in the<br />
9f2TCtAPI' t L. 2 41 * mmO-I'" a. C" I I 5 h t. to.-Ats. 6 t -C-*<br />
I<br />
s'eabed -fdr naticnal purpos&amp; s,-Sdieth-. as de n e' oiria. v. igati.-Ynai<br />
I. t 11a -b en expi.-ss-. rav. vce&amp; that.<br />
the right and title convoded b the Stateic} bj'eCt-' ti<br />
to the operation of the Great Barrier Reef Marine Park Act 1975.<br />
Nle\ Bas'eiines For the purpose of the Title Acts and for other<br />
purposes, the baselines from which the territorial sea is<br />
now to be draw.. n will be the new baselines the proclamation of<br />
which is to come into force on Monday, 14 February. Up till<br />
now, our territorial sea of 3 miles has been mainly drawn from<br />
low water, normally understood as mean low water. The new<br />
baselines adopt instead the low water datum known as Lowest<br />
Astronomical Tide ( LAT), which is the lowest level which can<br />
be predicted to occur under average meteorological conditions.<br />
The choice of LAT, rather than mean low water, means that<br />
significantly greater areas will come under Australian<br />
sovereignty, particularly along the northern coastline of our<br />
continent where the tidal fluctuations are miost marked.<br />
In accordance with international legal principles,<br />
straight baselines have also been drawn where the coastline<br />
is 30e] 1y indented or there is a frinoc of islands or a bay </p>
<p>. is not more than 24 miles wide. The waters involved include<br />
J such large areas as Spencer Gulf, Gulf St. Vincent and<br />
K? Investigator Strait adjacent to the coast of South Australia,<br />
Shark Bay and the Bonaparte Archipeligo adjacent to the coast<br />
of Western Australia, the waters of or connected with the<br />
Van Dieman Gulf off the Northern Territory coast, and large<br />
areas off the coast of Queensland.<br />
Some of the waters enclosed by the straight baselines<br />
are or may already be part of Australia as historic<br />
bays or waters over which Australia already has sovereignty.<br />
The new baselines will serve to underline the status of such<br />
waters as part of our national territory. Consideration is<br />
bei-g -' given to the"' sta-tu-s of-. cer. tain . wate: r. s o. ff, . Su. t. h.. Aus. tr. ali. a.<br />
. the Seas and Su-. me. rged Lands Act 1" 973 as b. eing historic . bays<br />
. or waters . and the. present.. proclamation should not be taken in<br />
any atse h* co" o . a . a o n; 1<br />
more than it could or should be taken to prejudice future clain: s<br />
thdim ayi -I i t : ie b o<br />
, that ay .' ld''' a-by. Austral ia in fh rgit; dee. i<br />
the international law of the sea.: " The South Australian iwaters.'.<br />
are to be considered by a group consisting of the Commonwealth<br />
Solicitor-General and Mr P. Brazil, Deputy Secretary of the<br />
Attorney-General's Department, and of the South Australian<br />
Solicitor-General and a person to be nominated by South<br />
Australia. This group is to be asked to report to Attorneys-<br />
SGeneral within 6 months from the commencement of its examination.<br />
The steps announced today in relation to baselines<br />
are major and significant, and are designed to advance the<br />
interests of Australia as a whole, and with that the interests<br />
of the States and the Northern Territory.<br />
In view of the provisions of the Torres Strait<br />
Treaty, the Commonwealth has prepared a separate Proclamation<br />
under the Seas and Submerged Lands Act 1973 declaring the outer<br />
limits of the territorial sea around certain islands in the<br />
Torres Strait to be the limits provided in respect of those </p>
<p>island by the terms of the Treaty. That in itself is a<br />
significant step towards implementing the Torres Strait<br />
Treaty as soon as possible.<br />
In the implementation of the Offshore Constitutional<br />
Settlement the Commonwealth and the States have shown what<br />
can be achieved, through negotiation, in practical sharing<br />
of power between Governments. The Settlement achieves a<br />
significant adjustment of powers and responsibilities between<br />
the' O6-m; oiweal. th.. and-.. t. he StateI. does t.) his, within the<br />
or other formal action to alter our donstitutional sti'ucture<br />
itself. The Commnonwealth and the States, by their<br />
S co-oparatidn," * Hve brougnt V'b'd t":' a" c. mOre'en . si." e t. tle.. t.<br />
of problems that have caused difficulties in Commonwealth/ State<br />
relatiio ns b" fr . dell ' b1-ve. ' decade.. The. Settement . will:. provide.<br />
' benefits to all Governments and the people Qf Ast. r'ali. it':<br />
will enable us all to exercise effectively our rights to the<br />
resources of offshore Australia as w. ell as our right and<br />
responsibility to preserve and protect our marine environment.<br />
CANBERRA<br />
4 FEBRUARY 1983<br />
14/ 83 </p>
<p>PPR 1E, f" S S STAT EAIENT T 83/ 8<br />
PROCLAMATION OF PET-COLEUM ( SUBMEURGED LANDS) AMEND1MENT ACT<br />
1980 AND ASSOCIATED ACTS<br />
The Minister for National Development and Energy;* Senator Sir<br />
John Carrick, today gave further details of amendm. ents of the<br />
Petroleum ( Submerged Lands) Act 1967 and associated legislation<br />
introduced as part of the Offshore Constitutional Settlement.<br />
The Prime Minister announced earlier toda-, y that the legislation<br />
will come into force on 14 February 1983.<br />
amendinei ts passed i1il8~ and 1981, viil-Togut-rhe<br />
pelt-roleuin actilv: itios on Australia's continental shelf in areas<br />
t. v 4 djacci eCti ia~: tie4oTteernrpr itory Ieod h<br />
three mi le territor: ial sea and in arei urio n~<br />
Commonwealth Trritories of Ashinore and Cartier Islands, the<br />
Coral Sea, * leard and M cDonald Islands an~ d . Norfclk Island. New,<br />
State and Northern Territory legislation, wiih will come iThto<br />
force on the samr~ e dahy as the Co-nnc, eallth legislation, will<br />
regulate offshore petroleum activities within their respective<br />
three mile territorial seas.<br />
The two sets of legislation contain a commnon minirg code which<br />
will govern all aspects of exploration for and p--, duction of<br />
petroleum, such as the grant and renewal of titles, the work<br />
obligations of explorers and safety requirements. This means<br />
that explorers for petroleum will be subject to the same rules<br />
in all the offshore areas of Australia. The mining code is<br />
substantially the same as that contained in the 1967 legislation<br />
* but the opportunity has been taken to amend sompe provisions<br />
shown by experience to be defective or inadequate in so-ne ,, ay.<br />
The opportunity has also been taken to increase the fees and<br />
penalties which had.. not be changed since 1967.<br />
The amendments not affect the1shari4ng of royalties from offshore<br />
Petroleum opEraltiorls which~ will continue to be on the same<br />
basis as under the 1967 legislation. </p>
<p>I,. 4. Administration of the legislation will continue to be the<br />
responsibility of the State and Northern Territory Ministers,<br />
x a t n u. an.<br />
a-as DAna-ted. underrA ththriieti esl egislation, ana. heir<br />
Departments will continue to handle day-to-day matters and to<br />
supervise. offshore operations. . Matter's requiring decisions<br />
by a -Joint Authority \ il. . be: r. efrred. by: . the State't the\<br />
Commonwealth. Amendments to the Act also extend the legislati6n to Offshore"<br />
areas not presently covered by the legislation. These areas<br />
are the Coral Sea and areas adjacent to Norfolk Island and to<br />
Heard and McDonald Islands. All petroleum activities in areas<br />
adjacent to the Territories of Heard and McDonald Islands and<br />
Norfolk Island will be administered by the Commonwealth. Early<br />
steps will be taken to release these areas for petroleum<br />
exploration to assess their potential.<br />
Senator Carrick stressed that special care has been taken to<br />
ensure continuity in the administration of offshore areas.<br />
Transitional provisions under the Commonwealth and the State<br />
and Northern Territory legislation will ensure that there is no<br />
disruption to ongoing projects and that the rights of the<br />
existing permittees and licensees are fully protected. Existing<br />
title holders whose title areas straddle the three mile<br />
territorial sea boundary line will be able to continue operations<br />
on conditions not less favourable than the existing ones for the<br />
remaining title period. The rights of title holders on renewal<br />
2.<br />
The Commonwealth legislation establishes Joint Authorities for<br />
each State and the Northern Territory adjacent areas consisting<br />
of the Commonwealth Minister for National Development and Energy<br />
and the relevant State or Northern Territory Minister. The<br />
Joint Authorities will decide important questions of title under<br />
the legislation, including the grant, renewal and transfer of<br />
exploration permits and production licences and safety issues.<br />
Decisions in matters within the responsibility of the Joint<br />
Authorities will rest fina'lly with the Commonwealth Minister<br />
ensuring that the Commonwealth will exercise its proper<br />
Constitutional responsibilities. </p>
<p>2<br />
.7 3.<br />
of existing titles to be carried out under the provisions of<br />
the relevant Commonwealth, State and Northern Territory Acts<br />
are similarly protected.<br />
Senator Carrick said that existing or prospective title holders<br />
wishing to clarify aspects of the legislation should approach<br />
the relevant Commonwealth, State or Northern Territory<br />
Department. CANBERRA Enquiries: J. Starkey<br />
4 February 1983 ( 062) 453216 ( Te)<br />
.554 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
