<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4310</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS AT THE PERTH CHAMBER OF COMMERCE AND CONFEDERATION OF INDUSTRY</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/02/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004310.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 2 FEBRUARY 1977<br />
ADDRESS AT THE PERTH CHAM4BER OF COMMERCE AND CONFEDERAT ION OF<br />
INDUSTRY<br />
I welcome this opportunity to talk to you about the economic<br />
progress Australia has made in 1976, this Government's first<br />
full year in office, and about the Government's economic<br />
policies. We all remember that under Labor Australia's economic situation<br />
was grave, and getting worse. There were no quick andq easy<br />
solutions to the problems of high inflation, of high unemployment,<br />
and declining activity which were besetting Australia a year ago.<br />
The Government's clear goal has been to bring about a sound<br />
economic recovery to create the conditions for sustained1 economic<br />
growth and to expand employment opportunities.<br />
As the main stumbling block to the achievement of this goal<br />
was the rampant inflation inherited from the previous Government,<br />
our first task was to bring all the arms of economic policy<br />
budgetary, monetary, external and wages policy to bear on<br />
combatting inflation.<br />
In the course of last year, we imposed the most rigorous restraint<br />
on Government spending, reducing the deficit and providing<br />
incentives to industry to resumne expansion and getting job<br />
opportunities going. We moved to limit the inflationary growth<br />
in the money supply. We argued strongly for wage restraint<br />
before the Arbitration Commission. We maintained the exchange<br />
rate through toe November.<br />
1976 was a year of substantial progress in the three-year task<br />
we set ourselves of bringing Australia's economic problems under<br />
control. The extent of this progress has not been widely recognised.<br />
Inflation has been significantly moderated. In the first three<br />
quarters of 1976, the C. P. I. rose by and 2.2% compared<br />
with an average rise of 4% per quarter in 1974/ 75. T~ he C. P. I.<br />
of course records price movements in only part of the economy.<br />
What has not been general~ ly appreciated is that the downward<br />
trend in the rate of inflation is shown similarly or even more<br />
markedly by other indicators.<br />
For instance, in the first three quarters of 1976 the deflator<br />
for the major components of gross national expenditure rose by<br />
4.0% 9 This compared with an average rise of over<br />
4% in 1974 and 1975. In the three months to October, the price<br />
index of the articles produced by manufacturing industry<br />
registered a rise of 2.0% compared with 2.7% and 2.9% in the two<br />
preceding three-monthly periods. / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
The effects of the changod arrangements for health-insurance<br />
will of course boost the CPI for the December quarter. Most<br />
commentators will focus on this. This " once and for all" effect<br />
should not distort our awareness of the steady underlying<br />
improvement in the rate of inflation. The more broadly based<br />
deflators derived from the national accounts, which will not<br />
be affected by Medibank will provide a much better guide to<br />
underlying trends.<br />
Partly because of our success in the fight against inflation other<br />
necessary precond itions Lfor sustainable growth have beeii gradually<br />
emerging. The massive distortions caused by the disastrous<br />
ves of 1974/ 75 to a number of key economic relationships,<br />
particularly the saving ratio and the wage profit sharp have begun<br />
to be corrected. The rise in business profitability is shown by<br />
the shift in the ratio of the gross operating surplus of trade<br />
companies to gross non-farm product from 10.5% in the final quarter<br />
of 1975 to 12.6% in the September quarter of 1976. The September<br />
quarter profit share was still below the longer run norm, But<br />
an encouraging start has been made.<br />
This restoration of the profit share from the very depressed level<br />
to which it was driven in 1974 and 1975, is central to the revival<br />
of business confidence, the willingness to invest and ultimately in<br />
the creation of more employment. Other indications of economic<br />
recovery can be seen in the fact that aggregate expenditures and<br />
product began to grow in 1976; the national accounts figures show<br />
a 7.5% rise in real gross non-farm product between the December<br />
quarter of 1975 and the September quarter of last year. This<br />
figure is subject to revision, but it is very much better than<br />
the 4% decline during the seven quarters to the end of 1975.<br />
I am not suggesting that economic activity is booming. The rise<br />
has been uneven, but though recovery has been slower in other<br />
areas, it is still apparent. Real consumption expenditure increased<br />
moderately in the first nine months of 1976. Private investment<br />
in plant and equipment benefited from substantial taxation<br />
incentives, particularly in the first half of the year. Tlhe<br />
depressed non-residential building and construction sector also<br />
showed signs of improvement in the second half.<br />
Before we camne into office, employment opportunities were<br />
declining. We have arrested this trend. The modest increase in<br />
private employment is characteristic of the early stages of<br />
recovery, during which employers first of all make fuller use<br />
of existing employment. The result is that the rise in employment<br />
has no more than kept up with the growth in the labor force,<br />
so that unemployment has virtually remained unchanged.<br />
At the present high levels of labor costs, an employer wil~ l<br />
seek out every alternative means of increasing his output before<br />
hiring additional full time workers. We have thus seen increases<br />
in overtime and part-time employment.<br />
More noticeable progress on the employment front should begin<br />
to emerge as the recovery spreads and consolidates. The<br />
Government's object is, and must be, to get people back into jobs.<br />
Unemployment causes people to lose their dignity and self-confidence<br />
and contributes to severe social problems. It also prevents the ./ 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
expansion of living standards and the strengthening of the<br />
nation as a whole. The Government is particularly con-cerned<br />
at youth unemployment and has initiated a number of innovative<br />
schemes to assist with this problem. Ultimately, the speed<br />
with which we can reduce unemployment depends on the degree<br />
of wage restraint which is achieved in the course of this yearand<br />
I will return to this later,<br />
Your State's economic performance in 1976 was better than that of<br />
' Australia as a whole. This is an impressive record of achievement<br />
and is a tribute to the sound economic management which Sir Charles<br />
Court's Government has given to your State. Western Australia's<br />
economic activity is more export-oriented than in most other<br />
states, and on that account you have been reaping benefits<br />
particularly in the minerals area. Devaluation will fiirther<br />
strengthen this trend. Last year the residential construction<br />
sector recovered strongly in Western Australia new dwelling<br />
approvals increased 23%. Registration of new motor vehicles<br />
in 1976 grew by 9% in Western Australia compared with the<br />
national figure of just over The value of non-residential<br />
building approvals in the three months to November stood<br />
above the level of the same period in 1975 again much better<br />
than Australia as a whole.<br />
The State's unemployment rate of 4.6% at the end of Decemnber was<br />
the second lowest among all the States, and represented a slight<br />
decline since December 1975.<br />
Major expansion of iron ore developments in the Pilbara is<br />
projected. The Agnew Nickel Project and smelter expansion near<br />
Kalgoorlie, the Alco-Reynolds Bauxite/ Alumina project south of<br />
Perth, and of course the massive north vest shelf natural gas<br />
project.<br />
Several hundred million dollars is likely to be spent in this<br />
State in the next 2/ 3 years. An audience of businessmen from<br />
this State would be well aware that the development of mineral<br />
resources is not something which can be turned on quickly. The<br />
development phase must be preceded by a long lasting preliminary<br />
phase of exploration not less than five years, and usually<br />
much more. We recognise this fact and have done a great deal to<br />
restore the incentives necessary to revive exploration. This<br />
will contribute significantly to overcoming Labor's policies<br />
which not only held up development, but stamped out exploration.<br />
We have adopted a more flexible policy towards foreign investment.<br />
The co-operation of the States has been actively sought towsards<br />
issuing permits over vacant off-shore areas, The $ 2 a barrel<br />
levy on oil from new discoveries has been removed, and generous<br />
taxation incentives were announced in the 1976 Budget.<br />
I am glad to say that exploration is recovering. Last year, 21<br />
exploration wells were drilled throughout Australia. Only 6 of<br />
these were in Western Australia. This year, the number of<br />
exploration wells is expected to be up to 44. Up to 19 of -them<br />
will be in Western Australia. This threefold anticipated increase<br />
in exploration drilling in this State is particularly encouraging.<br />
The discovery of additional reserves of petroleum ranks high<br />
amongst the objectives of my Government. </p>
<p>-4-<br />
I am also pleased to say that base-metal exploration has begun<br />
to revive, and that in parts of this State, valuable discoveries<br />
continue to be made. A key element in our philosophy of<br />
Government is that economic progress does not depend upon<br />
Government owning and actively carrying out the work of exploration,<br />
mining and processing.<br />
We believe that if the Government provides the right climate,<br />
the private sector, at times together with overseas partners,<br />
can be entrusted to develop Australia's resources, and that<br />
the fruits of this development will be of benefit to-the economy<br />
as a whole.<br />
The policies and philosophy of both your State Government and the<br />
Commonwcalth Government have created the conditions forlmineral<br />
exploration to start again in Australia. The extent of progress<br />
made is as much as we could reasonably have hoped for.<br />
Australia's overall economic performance has followed the course<br />
the Government has charted a decline in the inflation rate,<br />
combined with a progressive recovery in activity which have laid<br />
the groundwork for future improvements.<br />
Managing the economy is a continuous process and the balance<br />
between the different arms of policy must be constantly kept<br />
under review.<br />
Towards the end of 1976 a modification was required in the<br />
exchange rate. The immediate background to this was the<br />
persistent speculation against the Australian dollar. The position<br />
had been reached where continued and substantial Governmeni'<br />
borrowings overseas to offset the drain on the reserves would have<br />
been counter productive. There was a risk that such borrowing<br />
would have advertised the vulnerability of the existing rate and<br />
heightened speculation. This was not, of course, a new development.<br />
It was one of the first problems we encountered upon coming into<br />
Government. Speculation was based on the fact that under the<br />
previous Government, Australians costs and prices had risen well<br />
above those of competing countries.<br />
The costs of maintaining the exchange rate in such circumstances<br />
were high. It meant the continuing displacement of some Australian<br />
production by imports, with resulting difficulties in maintaining<br />
employment opportunities. It was aggravating the position of some<br />
parts of the rural sector.<br />
As 1976 proceeded, it also became clear that, at the existing<br />
exchange rate, a range of major mineral projects would be of'<br />
doubtful economic viability. Generally, investment decisions<br />
were being postponed. While speculation continued about the<br />
exchange rate, Australian industry faced severe difficulties<br />
in raising new funds from overseas sources.<br />
Nevertheless, we decided to maintain the existing trade-weighted<br />
parity of the Australian dollar, through most of 1976 in the<br />
overriding cause of maintaining downward pressure on inflation. </p>
<p>Bu~ t the paint was reached where the escalating outflow of our<br />
reserves, and the disadvantages which stemmed from the overvaluation<br />
of the dollar made change inevitable. This change did not mean<br />
that our objective of breaking inflation was changed or altered.<br />
What was involved was a necessary adjustment of policy to see<br />
that there would be a broad based recovery across a wide range<br />
of Australian industry.<br />
Our export and import competing industries were bearing a<br />
disproportionate burden and some sections of manufacturing<br />
indust ry in particular just did not have a chance under the old<br />
exchange rate of the Australian dollar.<br />
These industries can now play their part in providing important<br />
new investment and expanded employment opportunities. Their success<br />
in finding growing markets for their products will largel determine<br />
the pace of the continuing recovery and rising productivity. This<br />
will, in turn, allow economies in unit labour costs and ease<br />
inflationary pressures.<br />
Once we had made the inevitable decision to devalue there were<br />
a number of options open to us on the extent of devaluation and<br />
on the form of the new exchange rate system.<br />
We could have moved to a new fixed rate which would, at some<br />
future time perhaps require a further significant alteration<br />
in the exchange rate. A move, which, as the devaluation<br />
demonstrated, is attended by major public concern.<br />
2. We could have a market determined rato which would make<br />
fluctuations possible on a daily basis similar to the<br />
majority of OECD countries.<br />
3. We could have an administered and controlled management<br />
of the exchange rate which would avoid daily fluctuations<br />
but still leave us with the ability to make gradual<br />
adjustments in the rate.<br />
A further question requiring very careful consideration wras the<br />
magnitude of the initial change in the rate which would be made.<br />
The choice before us was either to make a move which would<br />
decisively end further speculation against the downward movement<br />
of the dollar. Or, on the other hand, a move which would leave the<br />
way open for speculation about a further devaluation perhaps in<br />
the not too distant future.<br />
The Government took the view that it was essential to end definitively<br />
further speculation against the dollar, and to establish a regime<br />
which would in future permit the exchange rate to adjust to changing<br />
circumstances. The benefits of devaluation are clear: increased opportunity<br />
for Australian manufacturing industry to compete against imports<br />
in the domestic market; the bringing forward of some major<br />
resource projects; arid an improvement in the position of primary<br />
industry. ./ 6 </p>
<p>-6-<br />
Devaluation will also facilitate capital raisings by indus-try and<br />
the Government has deliberately exempted longer term borrowings<br />
for high priority capital investment from the capital inflow control.<br />
We intend that resource development projects of the kind proceeding<br />
in your State should have the benefit of the lover cost of capital<br />
overseas and the special facilities available in overseas markets<br />
for borrowing long term capital. Mining companies with existing<br />
contracts expressed in overseas currency will benefit from<br />
devaluation through improved cash flows. With these additional<br />
funds they will be in a sounder position to finance their new<br />
development projects.<br />
The advantages of devaluation are many and can bring great rewards,<br />
but there are also dangers if the other arms of economic pol'icy are<br />
relaxed. We intend to retain the benefits of devaluation by making<br />
the appropriate adjustments in the other arms of policy.<br />
There will be some moderate direct price and cost effects front<br />
devaluation. These will register in the broad price indexes,<br />
primarily in the March and June quarters. But this needs to be<br />
seen in the context of the fall in inflation in 1976 and the further<br />
potential for recovery in profitability.<br />
The Government will not countenance any reversal of the underlyin<br />
downward trend in inflation which was established last year.<br />
Let me be quite clear on this point. The fact the Government has<br />
been forced to take a decision which has some inflationary cons; equences<br />
can not be adduced as evidence that the anti-inflationary strategy<br />
has been abandoned. In balancing the arms of policy, the Government<br />
considered and still considers inflation as the number one<br />
impediment to economic recovery and thus the number one priority.<br />
But we have never intended that it was the only priority. What is<br />
now required is that we do not relax our efforts to get on top of<br />
inflation. If ire did relax, the substantial progress in achieving<br />
economic recovery I outlined earlier wrould be quickly undone, and<br />
the potential benefits of devaluation would not be realised.<br />
This will happen if first-round effects were permitted to snowball,<br />
through wage indexation and a lax fiscal and monetary environment,<br />
into a renewed inflationary surge. We will ensure that the tots. l<br />
anti-inflationary thrust of all the main arms of policy is not diminished.<br />
Let me outline the steps already taken. In budgetary policy: the<br />
Government has announced further savings in outlays for the current<br />
financial year of $ 250 million; for 1977/ 78 outlays will be kept to<br />
within zero " real"' growth and-the deficit will be reduced further;<br />
Commonwealth Public Service ceilings will be reduced by another 700<br />
as at June 1977.<br />
In monetary policy: the Government has moved to prevent excessive<br />
easing in monetary conditions, the Reserve Bank has increased<br />
statutory reserve deposits; bank lending has been contained<br />
within firm guidelines; lending by non-bank institutions is being<br />
watched closely so that it will not be excessive. </p>
<p>While carrying out these steps, monetary management has been<br />
concerned to ensure an orderly June quarter. The authorities<br />
have been counselling the need for adequate preparation in<br />
anticipation of the seasonal tax collections.<br />
Indications are that substantial preparation has been made. The<br />
more attractive terms offered for Treasury Notes have resul-1ted in<br />
an increase of more than $ 2 billion in non-official holdings since<br />
early September.<br />
Measures also aimed at slowing growth in the domestic money supply<br />
have been taken to restrain the inflow of capital from abroad. It<br />
might be asked why we are concerned about excessive capital inflow.<br />
The answer is that excessive capital inflow can give rise to excessive<br />
liquidity in the economy and fuel inflation in much the saie way as<br />
a budget deficit.<br />
The reason for the high rate of capital inflow is clear. Capital<br />
can be obtained overseas at interest rates which are very lov by<br />
Australian standards. Hence, there is a major incentive perhaps<br />
in some cases amounting to up to a 50% saving in interest. for<br />
Australian-based companies to borrow overseas,<br />
There could be no assurance that conventional monetary policy<br />
techniques would be sufficient to prevent this while interest<br />
rate differentials remain as large as they are.<br />
If the Australian exchange rate were adjusted so as to neutralise<br />
interest rate differentials between Australia and overseas capital<br />
markets, some Australian manufacturing industries would again find<br />
it difficult to compete and jobs would be exported overseas.<br />
Thus the new capital controls were necessary in the present<br />
circumstances to assist the overall task of firm restraint on<br />
money supply growth. This is not a matter of achieving a numerical<br />
objective for the money supply for its own sake. It is a concern with<br />
the broader implications of an over rapid expansion of credit and<br />
the availability of finance in the economy.<br />
In the long run, of course, the best way of removing this differential<br />
and easing the threat to domestic monetary management will be to<br />
further reduce the rate of inflation in Australia. This, as I have<br />
already outlined, remains a major objective of policy.<br />
On the wages front, the Commonwealth will intensify its efforts<br />
to convince the Conciliation and Arbitration Commission of the<br />
absolute economic necessity in present circumstances of considerably<br />
less than full wage indexation. Nothing would more quickly and surely<br />
undermine the progress we have already made than a flow-on of the full<br />
C. P. I. increase into wages. This would increase the problem of<br />
inflation. It would increase the problem of unemployment. It would<br />
erode the benefits of devaluation the increased investment, more<br />
healthy growth and increased job opportunities. V../ 8 </p>
<p>In this area, the Government cannot achieve success on its own it<br />
will need the support of the community at large. I believe that<br />
this support exists in the community, and amongst most of the rank<br />
and file unionists who realise the costs inflation is havinag on<br />
employment opportunities.<br />
Those union leaders who refuse to face reality and keep demanding<br />
excessive wage increases aro, in the current economic envi: xonment,<br />
putting men out of work.<br />
Final~ y, I must comment upon the many calls for cuts in taxation.<br />
The Government is committed to taxation reforms. This commitment<br />
is demonstrated by the number and significance of the reforms already<br />
made. There is tax indexation the most important refori in the<br />
history of our taxation system; the new arrangements for Commonwealth<br />
Estate Duty; new system of income equalisation deposits; the<br />
investment allowances; incentives for the mining industry; the easing<br />
of distribution requirements for private companies; the trading stock<br />
valuations and investment. In terms of revenue forgone, these amount<br />
to very large taxation reductions -over $ 3000 million by 1977/ 78.<br />
( See Attachment Ela)<br />
/ 8a </p>
<p>3 a COST<br />
1976/ 77 Tax indexation -the most ' important 1977/ 78<br />
reform in the history of our<br />
990 taxation system 1050<br />
The new arrangements for<br />
2 Cornmonwealth estate duty<br />
New system of income equalisation<br />
2 deposits4<br />
200 The 40% investment allowances 550<br />
0 incentives for the mining industry<br />
The easing of distribution requirements<br />
I for private companies<br />
The trading stock valuations.<br />
0 and investment 400<br />
1195 -Total -2079 </p>
<p>9 9 -9-<br />
We are committed to reform of the taxation system. We havre<br />
made substantive reforms and will go further in reforming the<br />
personal tax area when it is responsible to do so.<br />
The one question which must be asked of those demanding fL~ rther<br />
immediate tax cuts is: how is the resulting increase in the deficit<br />
to be financed?<br />
There are, as you know, only four ways. First, through a reduction<br />
in Government spending by au amount sufficient to cover the costs<br />
of the tax cuts. Although we have made very substantial cuts<br />
in Government expenditure. I have head no one advocate cu-ts of<br />
thism ' agnitude.<br />
Second, through an increase in other taxes and we have heard<br />
of no suggestions for this.<br />
Third, by an increase in Government borrowings from the private nonbank<br />
sector. But this would be at the expense of the funds available<br />
to finance investment by the private sector and would involve a<br />
significant increase in interest rates.<br />
None of the proponents of tax reductions have advocated these policies.<br />
Some have even suggested that interest rates should be reduced at<br />
the same time as tax was lowered.<br />
But even if it were suggested that interest rates should ris; c in order<br />
to fund the deficit through higher bond sales, it would be necessary to<br />
think through the implications for building societies ( financial<br />
intermediaries) the housing and building industries, and bus~ iness<br />
generally. The momentum behind the call for the immediate tax cuts could quickly<br />
subside if it were realised that its consequence is higher interest<br />
rates. But those calling for tax cuts do not mention the need for<br />
higher interest rates. That leaves only one other way of funding<br />
a higher deficit. By borrowing from the Reserve Bank. That is,<br />
by printing money.*<br />
When it is put this way, how many people would concede that this is<br />
what they are asking for. There is no surer, faster. way to national<br />
disaster. We have no intention of taking this path.<br />
Against this background, the Government decided a fort night ago that<br />
tax cuts would be quite inappropriate at this time. The Governmentts<br />
decision to keep Government outlays to within zero real growth and<br />
to further reduce the deficit is designed to provide the maximum<br />
room to make further income tax reforms, as is appropriate.<br />
People have made their preference for tax cuts over increases in<br />
Government expenditure well known and we intend to move as quickly<br />
as is responsible on this path. As I have said before, the inevitable<br />
consequence of several years of gross mismanagement of the economy is<br />
that it will take an equal period of time to recover our equilibrium.<br />
In the last year, we have been able to make a substantial progress<br />
in righting the economy. This year, we have set out policies in<br />
position to fight inflation and to continue this progress. But<br />
policies do not work by themselves no Government can be successful<br />
if its policies do not get the support of the community. I believe<br />
that we have this support we will be successful. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
