<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10064</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP NIGHTLINE WITH PAUL LYNEHAM</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/08/1996</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010064.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Fax from: PRIME MINISTER<br />
7 August 1996 TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP<br />
NIGHTLINE WITH PAUL LYNEHAM<br />
UNEDITED CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY**<br />
E&amp; O E<br />
LYNEHAM:<br />
Prime Minister, welcome again to Nightline.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Pleasure always Paul.<br />
LYNEHAM: Well, you welcomed our athletes back from Atlanta this morning, a fairly happy job I<br />
imagine. PRIME MINISTER<br />
A very happy job. It's one of the sort of really pleasurable tasks of a Prime Minister.<br />
They did tremendously well and they gave a lot of hope and inspiration and a lot of<br />
unity to the Australian people while they were there and they deserve all the praise<br />
they're going to receive.<br />
LYNEJAM. What was your highlight of the Games? 87/ 88/ 96 19: 38 Pg: 1 </p>
<p>Fax from67/ 68/ 96 19: 38 Pg: 2<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I guess that great fightback on the Saturday morning in the swimming-There had been<br />
some pretty negative newspaper comments about them that morning.<br />
LYNEERAM: We're pretty quick to knock aren't we?<br />
PRIM MINISTERVery,<br />
and I think that's a great pity because it was almost as if that inspired them to<br />
adopt a sort of ' in your face' attitude and from there on it was all gold. It was terrific.<br />
LYNEHA M:<br />
Now, the closing ceremony, the inflatable Kangaroos on their bicycles are you a<br />
Kangaroo man or a black skivvy and cappuccino mian?<br />
PRIME MINISTERWell<br />
I'm a, " no matter what you do you can never win man", with that sort of thing.<br />
Look, it's easy to knock. No matter what you do with those sort of ceremonies you're<br />
always going to get some knockers. I thought I agreed with the comment John<br />
Williamson made in the Daily Telegraph this morning that you do need to represent<br />
what is atypical of your country, what is special about your country and not just<br />
projected as an element of a monolithic cultural movement right across the world. So,<br />
if that puts me in either camp I'll leave you to draw your own conclusions.<br />
LYNEHAM: And now, of course, the baton's been passed to Sydney. Do you, when you think of<br />
four years to go, do you get that little knot in the stomach? I mean, the airport, the<br />
roads, the rail are we ready for this?<br />
PRIMIE MINISTER:<br />
Oh, I think Sydney will handle it. I think Australia and Sydney will handle it. Sydney<br />
is a tremendous international city, it's very...<br />
LYNEHAM: The airport will handle it?<br />
PRIM ] MINISTER:<br />
Oh look, I'm sure in our classic ' get it right' way, we'll be able to handle it. Look, it's<br />
a lot of work and there'll be a lot of cooperation, and politics will. be forgotten<br />
2<br />
I </p>
<p>Fax from 07/ 08/ 96 19: 38 Pg: 3<br />
between the Federal and State Government and the Sydney Council and we'll all work<br />
together. I have made it clear to Bob Carr that we want to help.<br />
LYNEHAM: That's writing cheques?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
No, no, it doesn't mean to say that every single thing that has Olympic in front of it<br />
we'll say yes, I mean, otherwise State Governments would salivate, but equally we've<br />
guaranteed the funding commitments we made before the election. They hold good<br />
about the preparation of the athletes, and we'll want to cooperate recognising that he<br />
who signs the cheques is entitled to be totally satisfied that money is being well spent.<br />
LYNEHAM: We'd look awful stupid if we blew it wouldn't we?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
We won't. I believe this will bring out the best in the cooperative spirit of Australians<br />
and I don't believe for a moment we'll blow it. I think they'll be very memorable.<br />
LYNEHAM; And the funding for the athletes will be there?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Absolutely. LYNERAM: Cheryl Kernot's had a big whack at the Government today in a speech at the National<br />
Press Club. She says we're heading for a budget that looks like being Fightback<br />
exhumed. She says you went into the election clothed in the rhetoric of inclusion and<br />
moderation and now you've gone all tough and nasty again.<br />
PRJME MINISTER:<br />
Well, I think she ought to have a look... wait until the budget comes out. I don't think<br />
it will have a lot of resemblance to Fightback. There'll be some things in it that were in<br />
Fightback. A fair lot that was in Fightback won't be in the budget I mean, there<br />
won't be GST in the budget. There won't be a lot of other things that were in<br />
Fightback; we won't be knocking people off unemployment benefits after nine months;<br />
we'll be maintaining the twice yearly indexation pensions; we'll be maintaining the<br />
safty net that I've told ACOSS in October of last year that we would maintain. So, I<br />
suggest that Senator Kernot hold her fire, have a look at what is in the Budget and<br />
3 </p>
<p>Fax f'rom 07/ 88/ 96 19: 38 Pg: 4<br />
then apply fairness, which she says she represents, to the measures, and if she does I<br />
think she'll find she could support most of what is in the Budget.<br />
LYNEHAM: She says you don't really know, no one really knows what the deficit is going to be<br />
next year, that you are rushing in driven by ideology when you could in fact be making<br />
unemployment worse, which will make the budget deficit worse in the long run.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, I will know as much about next year's budget deficit as any Prime Minister has<br />
ever known about the next year's budget deficit, so I'm not rushing in. The best<br />
advice we have, from the same people who advised the former Goverrnent is that<br />
there is a black hole of $ 8 $ 10 billion dollars.<br />
LYNEHAM. It's the same Treasury who's got it wrong so many times in the past...<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, they haven't always got the forecast wrong. What was got wrong was that the<br />
former Gyovernment allowed expenditures to run out of control in a time of very strong<br />
economic growth-We will bring about a very big improvement in the Budget deficit<br />
but we'll do it in a way that doesn't disappoint people in the fam.. ily area and health<br />
insurance area and in a way that doesn't tear asunder the social security safety net of<br />
this country. We are absolutely committed to maintaining the essential social security<br />
safety net in Australia and any suggestion that I'm on some kind of ideological mission<br />
to rip up the social security safety net of Australia is nothing more than oppositionist<br />
rhetoric nothing more.<br />
LYNEHAM: Do you accept though that there is an unusual amount of pre-budget anxiety and<br />
uncertainty in business, in a lot of areas.. The Tasmanian Premier for example was<br />
concerned about cuts to labour market programmes?<br />
PRIE MINISTER:<br />
I think you always get this with a new Government when that new Government signals<br />
a change of direction. This is the first budget in 13 years that hasn't been brought<br />
down by a Labor treasurer so naturally people look at things differently and they take<br />
on anxieties that they wouldn't take on if the former Government were bringing down<br />
the budget simply because it was the same Government that brought down last year's<br />
budget. 4 </p>
<p>Fax from 07/ 08/ 96 19: 38 Pg:<br />
LYNEHAM: And of' course we haven't seen your cards yet have we? I mean, really, until you<br />
deliver that budget....<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Of course, of course, and it will1 be fair but it wilt be firm and it will meet the fiscal<br />
objectives that Australia has at the present time. I mean we won't be squibbing some<br />
firm decisions that have got to be taken and I will be able to look any group in the eye<br />
after the budget and say even though you may not like that decision, it has been a fair<br />
decision. LYNERAM: Senator Kernot also said that any sensible budget approach would look at revenue<br />
more vigorously than you are doing, both getting the tax cheats more stringently and<br />
looking at tax reform.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, certainly as far as tax cheats are concerned, we'll go after them. I saw a funny<br />
report in the paper this morning that suggested that we were going to turn a blind eye<br />
to that. Well, that's wrong. The Howard Government will not turn a blind eye to tax<br />
cheating. LYNEHM. Including the very wealthy?<br />
PRIM1E MINISTER:<br />
Including the very wealthy. Look, people who are rorting the system no matter where<br />
they are aren't doing any of us a good turn and just as we don't want people rorting<br />
the unemployment benefits, we don't want very wealthy people rorting the taxation<br />
system and we'll use whatever weapons properly can be used to stop that happening,<br />
so I just send that very clear message. Nobody should imagine that we are going to be<br />
a soft touch in tax rorting we are not.<br />
LYNEHAM. If on the day you think Prime Minister that we still have a tax structure that's the same<br />
ramshackle nonsense we've got today, are you going to be able to look yourself in the<br />
mirror? PRIME MINISTER:<br />
That's one day I haven't contemplated in the last five months and that is the day I<br />
cease to be Primc Minister. I've only just got here! </p>
<p>Fax from LYNERAM:<br />
Do you see it as a job that's to be done in the longer term?<br />
PRIE MINSTER:<br />
Well, Paul, I know you are asking me about the GST.<br />
LYNEIIAM: No, I'm asking about tax broadening the tax base.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well exactly. That's a euphemism for OST. We had a policy on that at the last<br />
election. That policy stays. We were elected for this term on that basis and you know,<br />
I can't say anymore than that.<br />
LYNE HAM:<br />
Middle class welfare. Some have said that there's a ( inaudible) for example. It's time<br />
the middle class got their snouts out of the trough, childcare funding, all that sort of<br />
thing. PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, I guess it depends how you define it. I don't regard for example, the tax systemn<br />
recagnsing that it costs more when you've got children than when you didn't have<br />
children. I don't regard that as middle class welfare. I think people who put those<br />
sorts of labels on that kind of arrangement really are socially insensitive and are out of<br />
touch with the real world. Everybody knows that when you have children your<br />
expenses go up and often one or half of your incomes disappears. So people who<br />
classify that as middle class welfare really don't understand the real world.<br />
LYNEHAM: Yes, but there are homeless people, there are people who... Aboriginal babies dying at<br />
birth. People would say that's much more important.<br />
PRIE MI] iSTER:<br />
Well, certainly they are very important, and a sensible system can accommodate caring<br />
areas like that and I think as far as the Aboriginal area is concerned, people are baffled<br />
as to why after the expenditure of billions of dollars over a period of time the situation<br />
doesn't appear to be any better. 63 07/ 08/ 96 19: 38 PS: 6 </p>
<p>Fax from : 7/ 08/ 96 19: 38 PS<br />
LYNEHAM: We've had students marching through the streets of Sydney today. Amanda Vanstone<br />
does seem to have got a lot of anxiety out there in the higher education community.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, they marched against the former Government. I guess that's part of the scene. I<br />
think people ought to see the colour of what we are doing in that area. It will be<br />
comprehensive. It will obviously contain some measures that people won't like but in<br />
the totality, fair minded people will see it as the higher education sector making a<br />
reasonable and an affordable contribution to the budget problem.<br />
LYNEHAM:<br />
Within what would still be a commitment to a clever country?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Oh absolutely. It won't be anything in the higher education area that will cripple the<br />
capacity and demean, diminish the capacity of Australia to be a clever country.<br />
LYNEHAM: And if you run into difficulties in the Senate with the budget or other measures later in<br />
the year, would it really be your view as Tony Abbott has been suggesting, that you<br />
might try to find a new way to have the Senate elected?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I have a very strong view about fiddling the system. I am against it. I am totally<br />
opposed to any increase in the size of the Parliament. I think the Australian public<br />
probably if it hadn't struggled would have fewer and not more politicians and I think it<br />
was a great mistake that the Parliament was increased 12 years ago but there's nothing<br />
we can do about that now. I'm not in the business of fiddling the system. I would like<br />
to get our legislation and our budget through. I will be talking to Senator Kernot next<br />
week about, how shall I put it, the interface of the Government and the Australian<br />
Democrats and I will approach those discussions in a positive frame of mind, and I<br />
know that she will too.<br />
LYNEHAM: Long overdue she says. No one's talked to her really since day one.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
That's not quite right, Paul, to be fair. Peter Reith has talked to her quite regularly. I<br />
had quite a lengthy discussion with her after the election so it's not quite right to say<br />
that nobody's talked to her. 7 Irv 7<br />
i<br />
i. </p>
<p>Fax from 07/ 88/ 96 19: 38 Pg: 8<br />
LYNEHAM: Finally Prime Minister, your wife Janette. How has she recovered?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well we're hopefil that she's recovering well. She will be home from hospital soon,<br />
we hope and I have been very greatly helped by a lot of expressions of support from<br />
people all around Australia, and also can I thank the media in Australia for the way in<br />
which they have handled it and have responded to my requests to maintain the privacy<br />
of the matter to my wife and my family. I am very deeply appreciative of that.<br />
LYNEHAM:<br />
Prime Minister, thanks for your time.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
It's a pleasure.<br />
end -r S </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
