<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7676</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, MEDIA CENTRE, SOUTH PACIFIC FORUM, TARAWA, KIRIBATI, 10 JULY 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/07/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007676.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, MEDIA CENTRE, SOUTH PACIFIC<br />
FORUM, TARAWA, KIRIBATI, 10 JULY 1989<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister what do you hope will be the<br />
effect of the $ 6.25 million initiative to study the<br />
Greenhouse effect<br />
PN: Well, a basic service that we want to provide is the<br />
assurance to the countries in the region that we are not<br />
just looking at this from a point of view of large countries<br />
like Australia and Europe and North America, but that we<br />
have a very real understanding that for some of then this is<br />
literally a matter of life and death and that what we are<br />
going to do is to provide a capacity for measurements in the<br />
region, we'll provide monitoring stations, we'll train their<br />
own people to service these monitoring stations and that<br />
will be intrinsically useful for the global measurement of<br />
the Greenhouse effect but it also I hope will be reassuring<br />
to the countries of this region countries particularly<br />
like Kiribati. You only have to be here to see that you<br />
don't need much of a rise in the ocean level and you're<br />
talking about goodbye Kiribati. So they have we'* re not<br />
yet on to this item in detail in the meeting, I0ll be coming<br />
to talk to them in more detail about that later in the<br />
meeting, but certainly last year they were very responsive<br />
to the concept. We're now, since that meeting we've had the<br />
committee of experts look at this and I'll be able to give<br />
them the details of what we intend to do.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, have you been able to get<br />
agreement on a proposal for regional approach to driftnet<br />
fishing PM: Yes, we're on to that item now and as far as I can<br />
see there is a very positive response to the proposed<br />
declaration that I'm suggesting. I've made the point in<br />
introducing the item that it seem to me that what we're<br />
dealing with here is of such fundamental importance that it<br />
warrants more than merely a mention in our overall<br />
communique. we believe there should be a declaration coming<br />
out of this meeting which is aimed at developing a regime<br />
for the management of albacore tuna with a view to achieving<br />
a-ban on driftnettinq and through that purpose to have a </p>
<p>( PH cont): meeting of experts to prepare the outline of the<br />
convention which would achieve that objective, expressing<br />
our hope for that action here leading to a more<br />
comprehensive ban around the world. In the meantime while<br />
that convention, or the preparation of that convention is<br />
taking shape, the resolution that I propose would commit us<br />
individually, as members of the Forum and collectively, to<br />
take whatever action against the driftnetters was possible,<br />
whether by banning them in national waters or denying them<br />
access, doing whatever we could to make it difficult for<br />
them to profit from their activities. Also the declaration<br />
proposes that we should, as we work towards the<br />
establishment of such a convention, do whatever we could in<br />
other international forums to try and bring an end to this<br />
practice because, as I've said before, what you're talking<br />
about here is not just something incidental as I said in<br />
introducing the resolution in a diversified economy like<br />
Australia. if one particular sector of our economy is<br />
adversely affected by some international development or<br />
other occurrence, we have the opportunity of turning to<br />
other sectors of the economy, adding to activity in other<br />
areas, but for some of these economies here in the Pacific<br />
if they lose their fishing resource they've virtually lost<br />
everything. JOURNALIST: Would the convention be a regional convention<br />
PM: You'd be moving to a much wider, more wide convention<br />
than that because it's no good, in other words, just trying<br />
to do something here and shifting the driftnetters to the<br />
Indian ocean, for instance. I mean they have been wiping<br />
out the source of our blue fin tuna for instance.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, do you think Taiwan and Japan will<br />
respond to the views of the region or do you think it will<br />
take concerted pressure on those countries to stop them from<br />
PH: Well, I think you've got to say it requires pressure<br />
because just very recently there was a meeting at-the<br />
officials level of the Forum Fisheries Agency and the<br />
driftnetting nations and Korea, to it's great credit, has<br />
responded positively and is withdrawing its vessels,<br />
but Japan and Taiwan have to this point refused. So, as Isaid,<br />
it's gone beyond the level of officials. I-think<br />
there's an obligation upon the political leaderships here<br />
now to take action. I would think that opinion is capable<br />
of being mobilised on this issue. I.. say that for two<br />
reasons, one, I think the potential cost of the continuationof<br />
this activity is so obvious and secondly, I based it upon<br />
the fact that in my recent visit to France, the United<br />
Kingdom, United States and West Germany. I raised this<br />
issue and I got positive responses to it in the sense they<br />
-~ A PX </p>
<p>3.<br />
( Pm4 cont); recognise that this was a practice which was<br />
both environmentally and economically not acceptable.<br />
JOURNALIST; Prime Minister, is there a danger that Japan<br />
would use it's economic muscle to undermine this initiative?<br />
PM: Well, let me put it this way, to this point the Japanese<br />
have been unresponsive as compared with Korea but I think<br />
it's one of those issues where you have to keep, not just<br />
keep, but increase pressure upon them. -It seems to me<br />
obviously unacceptable that you can have a practice which<br />
is not just operating to provide some need for the countries<br />
which are doing the fishing, but which if continued will<br />
wipe out the resource. I mean, the catches are now, it's<br />
suggested, at something like twice the sustainable yield.<br />
Now that, getting rid of the economist jargon, if you<br />
say, that they are taking out twice the sustainable yield,<br />
what that simply means is that they are going to wipe out<br />
the resource. And that seems to me something that.<br />
international pressure should'be capable of developing<br />
inco a position where the countries which are practising<br />
this driftnet fishing will come to understand that it is<br />
not acceptable.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke your talks with Mr Lange this morning,<br />
are you now confident of or do you feel he will buy more<br />
Australian Naval frigates in the near future? I<br />
PM4, I wouldn't put it that way but let me say that I think<br />
its reasonable to put it that I have the impression that<br />
a positive view on New Zealand's participation is fairly<br />
JOURNALIST: What?<br />
PM: Well I could just have had a microphone there so you<br />
could have listened in to all the conversation I don't<br />
think that would be fair to either David or myself.<br />
JOURNALIST: Have you put pressure on Mr Lange?<br />
PM: Look I'm a soft, reasonable, easy-going sort of bloke<br />
I have never been known to put pressure on anyone in my<br />
life. Were my lips moving then?<br />
JOURNALIST% Mr Hawke how much pressure are you prepared<br />
to put on Japan and Korea? How far would you go to get<br />
the fishing stopped?<br />
PM4: Well it's not a question of how far I'm prepared to<br />
go. I hope that the Forum countries will agree to the<br />
concept of a Declar~ ation. I am simply saying that my<br />
assessment from discussions I have had very recently with<br />
significant countries is that there will be a positive<br />
response to any such initiative by the Forum now as a result<br />
of the-suggestion that I have made for a. declaration coming,.-.<br />
out of-ithe-Forum -and I think we ought to use all. diplomaticpressureszpassible<br />
upon Japan and Taiwan to-act-sensibly<br />
in this matter. </p>
<p>4.<br />
JOURNALIST: ( inaudible)<br />
PM: I think we will resolve the issue today, I think so.<br />
JOURNALIST: ( inaudible)<br />
PM: Well look I think the easiest thing to do is if I<br />
read you the actual terms of the proposal so there can't<br />
be any doubt about it. We say that we resolve to seek<br />
the establishment of a regime for the management of alba<br />
core tuna in the South Pacific that would ban driftnet<br />
fishing from the region as a first step towards a more<br />
comprehensive ban and then go on to say determines to<br />
this end to convene an urgent meeting of regional diplomatic,<br />
legal and fisheries experts to prepare the outline of the<br />
convention designed to give affect to its common resolve<br />
to create a zone free of driftnet fishing and to ensure<br />
such proper management, and calls on the international<br />
community to support and co-operate in the urgent<br />
establishment of the zone and the drawing up of the<br />
convention. Now to say we would see that as a step towards,<br />
while in the first place, directed towards the regiun would<br />
as the earlier language of the declaration suggests lead<br />
to a more comprehensive ban.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
