<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>958</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: P.M. NO. 51/1964 - ECONOMIC CONSULTATIONS - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. JOHN MCEWEN</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/07/1964</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000958.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
6 / 00<br />
FOR PRESS P. M. No. 51/ 1964<br />
ECONOMIC CONSULTATIONS<br />
Statement by the Acting Prime Minister, the Rt. Hon. John McEwen<br />
The Acting Prime Minister, the Rt. Hon. John McEwen,<br />
and senior Ministers had discussions this afternoon on the economic<br />
situation with representatives of a group of national organizations.'<br />
After the meeting, Mr. McEwen said that these talks, which were<br />
first instituted in 1962, had again been most useful.<br />
Mr. McEwen said that the Government would continue<br />
to hold such economic consultations at regular intervals.<br />
The various representatives reported a satisfactory<br />
level of activity over the whole economy. They considered there<br />
was no need for further stimulation of the economy, nor was there<br />
need for any drastic restraint. Efforts should be mede to contain<br />
pressures making for increased costs rather than to red. uce demand.<br />
Increased productivity could make a major contribution to price<br />
stability. Some organisations, while accepting the concept of<br />
Restrictive Trade Practices legislation, sought opportunity for<br />
further consultation. Ministers present, in addition to the Acting Prime<br />
Minister, wer-e<br />
The Right Honourable. Harold Holt, Treasurer.<br />
The Honourable W. McMahon, Minister for Labour<br />
and National Service,<br />
Senator the Honourable Shane Paltridge, Minister<br />
for Defence an" d Leader of the Government in<br />
the Senate.<br />
Senator the Honourable Harrie Wade, Minister for<br />
Health and Acting Minister for Primary Industry.<br />
Representatives who attended the meeting were<br />
Mr. L. Atkinson, President, Associated Chambers of<br />
Commerce of Australia.<br />
Mr. R. V. Allison, President, Associated Chambers<br />
of Manufactures of Australia.<br />
Mr. J. P. Heffernan, President, Australian Primary<br />
Producerst Union.<br />
Mr. T. M. Scott, Vice-President, Australian Woolgrowers'<br />
and Graziers' Council.<br />
Mr. A. F. Havard, President, National Farmers' Union.<br />
Mr. L. M. Ridd, Vice-President, Australian Wool and<br />
Meat Producers' Federation.<br />
Mr. H. F. Clarke, Chairman, Australian Bankers'<br />
Association. / 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
Mr. K. G. Hooker, President, Master Builders'<br />
Federation of Australia.<br />
Mr. N. W. Lawrance, President, Federal Chamber<br />
of Automotive Industries.<br />
Mr. Theo Kelly President, Australian Council<br />
of Retailers.<br />
Mr. McEwen said that Ministers would be having<br />
discussions with representatives of the A. C. T. U. on the morning<br />
of 14th July and would also have separate meetings with the<br />
Manufacturing Industries Advisory Council and the Export<br />
Development Council that afternoon.<br />
CANBERRA, 13th July, 1964. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
