<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9338</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP SACKING OF DR HEWSON</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/08/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009338.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ KEATING MP<br />
SACKING OF DR HEWSON<br />
The striking down of Dr Hewson by Mr Downer today means that the divisions<br />
in the Liberal Party which have persisted since 1983 are destined to remain.<br />
The Liberal Party has one elected leader and three former leaders in the<br />
wings, and the only thing they can agree upon is that their interests will never<br />
coincide. This continues to rob the Liberal Party of cohesion, coherence and<br />
a sense of purpose.<br />
Dr Hewson correctly believes that policies are the stuff of politics: that without<br />
policies there can be no substance to public debate and no political morality.<br />
Mr Downer told a business dinner in Sydney last week that Dr Hewson's<br />
mistake in 1993 was to reveal his policies and that he has no intention of<br />
doing the same. It is not that he doesn't have policies it is simply that he<br />
knows that the public won't like them.<br />
Mr Downer believes that he can participate in the public debate without<br />
policies that is, without revealing his policies.<br />
This action today shows Mr Downer in his true colours as a 1950' s style<br />
politician who believes that it is sufficient to serve up political rhetoric and<br />
loose ideology without addressing Australia's continuing need for reform.<br />
Mr Downer is as far removed from the needs of the modern Australian<br />
political system as it is possible to be.<br />
The contest between Dr Hewson and Mr Downer is a contest over the central<br />
idea that modern Australian society needs change and that the contemporary<br />
electorate deserves a right to evaluate and adjudicate on policy.<br />
Mr Downer may have displaced Dr Hewson from the front bench, but he<br />
cannot displace the need for policy substance and policy integrity.<br />
CANBERRA<br />
26 August 1994 79/ 94 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
