<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2036</transcript-id>
    <title>ANNIVERSARY OF INDEPENDENCE OF ISRAEL - FESTIVAL HALL MELBOURNE - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. JOHN GORTON</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/04/1969</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002036.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
ANNIVERSARY OF INDEPENDENCE OF ISRAEL<br />
Festival Hall, Melbourne 22 APRIL 1969<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister, Mr. John Gorton<br />
Mr. President, Mr. Ambassador and Fellow Australians of Jewish<br />
Faith or Jewish Descent:-<br />
We stand here to give greetings to you all on a stage<br />
from which those bright banners have just been carried banners<br />
which symbolically bore the stars of the Southern Cross and the Star<br />
of David. And how proper that is, for this association is not a recent<br />
one. Back in the 1914-18 War, Australian soldiers, many of<br />
Jewish descent, rode and fought with Jews in Israel. In the last Great<br />
World War, two of the best-known Jewish soldiers today served with<br />
Australians in the Syrian campaign. I am told, and I believe it is true,<br />
that General Moshe Dayan lost his eye while with an Australian patrol<br />
in the Syrian campaign. He was using a pair of binoculars to help<br />
his-Australian comrades, and was hit by an enemy bullet.<br />
And I know that Brigadier General Allon served in a<br />
little-known but gallant action where he guided and led an Australian<br />
patrol behind the enemy lines to hold and seize a bridge and prevent<br />
its destruction so that Australian and other troops coming along from<br />
behind could cross that bridge. They were to hold it for eighteen<br />
hours. They held it for four days.<br />
This is the sort of association in fighting, in war, that<br />
has gone on between Australians and Jews in Israel, so how right it<br />
was that today the flags should bear the stars of both our nations.<br />
And what a special cheer there was, of course, for the<br />
reference to the Six-Day War, a war which, I suspect, must have<br />
benefited the Israeli Treasury immensely because I know that a third<br />
of the budget of Israel is spent on defence but I imagine that at least<br />
another third of its defence material has been made available from<br />
other sources: But that was some years ago, and while it did what wars<br />
can do, and that is settle immediate problems and fighting and wars<br />
can do that, no matter what anyone may say it has not settled the<br />
continuing problem. And since that time I think there have been<br />
one-quarter as many casualties as occurred in that Six-Day War,<br />
many of them children blown to pieces or maimed by button mines,<br />
/ 2 </p>
<p>2-<br />
many of them peasants working in their fields suddenly the target of<br />
mortar or machine gun attack, for Israel is still a beleaguered nation.<br />
That nation still must work, wherever it may be working, with the<br />
tool of its trade in one hand and the sword and the rifle within grasp<br />
for the other. It still must seek to hear all the time above the noises<br />
of the market place the possible call of the tocsin to defend what has<br />
been won, because that must be defended.<br />
War is horrible. Fighting is horrible. But they are<br />
not the worst things that can happen, and who could possibly know this<br />
better than the people now in Israel, with the thousands of years of<br />
persecution in all the lands in which they sought to make their home,<br />
having been driven out from their own. With all those years of<br />
persecution culminating in Nazi aggression who could know it better?<br />
And who could know better that if the choice eventually<br />
has to be made between a battlefield and a Belsen, then free men and<br />
women must choose a battlefield every time.<br />
What we all want is for it to be recognised throughout<br />
the world that Israel is there to stay, and that Israel is a free and<br />
sovereign and independent nation as of right. And we want Israel to<br />
be allowed to divert that money that now must be put into defence to<br />
be used for the further increase of the miracles it has wrought in the<br />
arid land to which it has gone.<br />
Sometimes, it almost makes one despair when one thinks<br />
of what has been wrung from the desert, when one thinks of the forests<br />
which have grown and are growing, where previously erosion held sway,<br />
where one sees the factories and industries springing up where<br />
previously was nothing but nomadic wandering, where one sees not two<br />
but ten blades of grass where only one grew before. It almost makes<br />
one despair to think that that example can be the subject of such threat<br />
and such attacks rather than be followed for the benefit of all those<br />
who live in that region of the Middle East.<br />
What all Australians want, I believe, is that it should<br />
be possible for an enduring peace to be made; that the Arab nations<br />
should sit down and talk and discuss and reach agreement. What that<br />
decision or result will be, I do not know or seek here to indicate, as<br />
long as it brings to all those people living there the chance to progress,<br />
the chance to live in peace, the chance to take care of refugees, the<br />
chance to give human beings in that part of the world happiness,<br />
confidence in the future and a knowledge which you have and which I<br />
have which is quite ineradicable. That is that though the State of<br />
Israel may be 21 today and has attained its majority, it will go on<br />
forever. / 3<br />
11 6 </p>
<p>-3'<br />
What I have outlined could be achieved if the two great<br />
powers not four great powers but two great powers in the world<br />
the United States of America and the U. S. S. were to say, " Enough<br />
of this. Turn your swords into ploughshares. We are strong enough<br />
to see that one will not be attacked by the other and we in concert will<br />
help to hold the peace." This could be done.<br />
For ourselves for myself, for my Government, for<br />
Australians, we are small and therefore perhaps sympathetic<br />
particularly to Israel which also is small. But that which we can do<br />
we will do to support it. That which we can say we will say. That<br />
influence we can bring to bear, such as it is, will be brought to bear<br />
for this end. And I cannot better express that approach than by<br />
reading to you part of a message sent by us to the Executive Council<br />
of Australian Jewry in the Sydney Town Hall some time ago. And this<br />
is our belief as a Government and my belief as a Prime Minister:-<br />
" We believe that all parties to the dispute should<br />
without delay sit down around the conference table<br />
and begin discussions aimed at restoring peace and<br />
stability to the Middle East. Any such settlement<br />
must be formally based on the acceptance of Israel<br />
as a sovereign nation, existing as of right, entitled<br />
to live and develop in security, free of constant<br />
threat, posing no threat to its neighbouring countries<br />
and using for the good of all, rights and opportunities<br />
so dearly bought."<br />
I thank you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
