<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8386</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J. KEATING MP DOORSTOP, SYDNEY, 20 JANUARY 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/01/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008386.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
E OE PROOF COPY ONLY<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
DOORSTOP, SYDNEY, 20 JANUARY 1992<br />
PM: I'm doing today what I did last week and that is going<br />
out into the community and listening to what they have<br />
to say and I think it has been a good process. I notice,<br />
by the way,, that Dr Hewson said in Tasmania last week<br />
that I shouldn't be listening, that the business<br />
community were only after handouts and obviously what he<br />
believes one should do is hand down tablets from on<br />
high, don't ask or don't speak to anybody and then slap<br />
everybodly with a 15 per cent tax on their food and then<br />
regard that as reform. So what we're doing is going to<br />
business, all sectors of business, and to the trade<br />
unions and saying, well, what do you believe should be<br />
the steps of reform7. How do you believe a recovery ought<br />
to be promoted? And that is what I have been doing. Now,<br />
on the wreekend we had a very interesting episode in<br />
politics: in Australia where in a by-election, upon which.<br />
the balance of the State Parliament was held, the Liberal<br />
Party lost the seat and Dr Hewson said in the course of<br />
the by-election campaign that " let this be a test of the<br />
GST". Well to the extent it was a test to the GST, it<br />
was a slap on the face of Dr llewson. Now it was a State<br />
by-election, I didn't involve myself in it. It is a<br />
great compliment to Bob Carr and the NSW Labor Party.<br />
And it was a slapping down for the Coalition. But the<br />
extent that Dr Hewson and John Howard campaigned in the<br />
by-election, and Dr Heweon said, " let this be a test of<br />
the CST' a very flat refusal to the politics of<br />
GST and all that came with it. So I just want to say<br />
this to Dr Hewson: I'm not taking his advice. That is,<br />
to not talk to people. I am going to talk to people<br />
. ome of our largest and smallest companies, some of our<br />
largest and smallest trade unions and I'm going to See<br />
that at least the people's views are listened to,<br />
weighed -and sifted through carefully.<br />
ENDS </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
