<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4998</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/03/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004998.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS 25 MARCH 1979<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
These days Australians understand that any call f or Government<br />
to spend money is nothing less than a call to dig into peoples<br />
pockets. One way or another, the taxpayer foots the bill for<br />
every government spending decision. Money for new programmes,<br />
incentives, or special help, is money collected from the pay<br />
packets of Australian working men and women.<br />
As Prime Minister I am often asked publicly, and privately in<br />
my office, to shell out dollars for this project or that. I<br />
make the point this is a request not so much of the Government,<br />
but of a neighbour.<br />
We learnt many bitter lessons from the Labor years. Above all,<br />
we learnt that governments which throw money around with<br />
abandon taxpayers money create a paralysis that. strikes<br />
at the heart of a nation's economy. They create a paralysis<br />
that takes years to cure.<br />
The Coalition Government has been responsible in the management<br />
of taxpayers dollars. We have been prudent with Government<br />
spending. Compare our record against our predecessors. In<br />
Labor's first year in office Government spending rose by<br />
In 1974-75 it went through the roof, jumping by 46%, while in<br />
1975-76 it still increased by nearly 24%. That's a 115%<br />
increase in Government spending in three years.<br />
By contrast, in our first year we controlled increases in<br />
Government spending to 103 to 11% in 1977-78, and this<br />
year the growth is estimated at under 8% the lowest increase<br />
for ten years. This prudent, careful use of taxpayers funds<br />
has allowed us to implement wide ranging and substantial<br />
tax reforms. In our second Budget we reformed the personal<br />
income tax scales. This was a major and far reaching tax<br />
reform, which we were able to carry out only because we had<br />
been prudent with the way we spent your money.<br />
Under Labor the wage earner on $ 10,000 was taxed 45 in the<br />
dollar, and the wage earner on $ 16,000 was taxed at 55 in<br />
the dollar. Under our reform these rates have been cut to 33.5%.<br />
zo-C/ </p>
<p>-2<br />
Just remember the days when people didn't want to work overtime.<br />
It wasn't worth their while because of the tax slug. Today,<br />
under our tax scales, there is a built-in incentive because our<br />
33 standard rate applies to incomes up to $ 16,600. On top<br />
of that our Family Allowance Scheme, one of Australia's greatest<br />
social reforms of the century means direct payments to mothers.<br />
Family Allowances have meant that 300,000 low income families,<br />
with nearly a million children, have been helped. Because of<br />
their limited incomes these families had not qualified for the<br />
inequitable tax rebate of earlier times.<br />
In terms of take home pay, our reforms have meant that the<br />
average bloke with a wife and two children, earning about<br />
$ 230 a week that's average weekly earnings is $ 15 a week<br />
better off. This tax bonus applies despite this year's tax<br />
surcharge.<br />
What is also often forgotten when we talk about benefits to<br />
taxpayers is that we have protected the less well-off by<br />
relieving them of the need to pay any income tax at all.<br />
Under our scales up to half a million Australians no longer<br />
have any need to pay income tax, because we lifted Labor's<br />
tax threshold.<br />
Bringing it all together, it means Australians are paying<br />
$ 3,000 million less tax this year than they would have if the<br />
Hayden tax scales still applied. That is the fact that Mr Hayden<br />
is unwilling to face. He won't admit that Labor allowed personal<br />
income taxes to explode. In 1973-74 Labor increased the tax<br />
take by more than 34%, in the next year it jumped by more<br />
than 40%, and in the next again it increased by a further<br />
Compare that to the last three years. In 1976-77 taxes increased<br />
by 14%, the next year by while this year they are estimated<br />
to increase by a fraction over 7%.<br />
That's not a bad tax record. It is a record of managing the<br />
dollars we collect from taxpayers with care and responsibility,<br />
and we flatly reject the big spending and high taxation approach<br />
to economic management.<br />
Remember the last election when Labor was going to abolish our<br />
tax reforms to cut payroll tax for big companies. Their strange<br />
ideas on tax haven't altered. Mr Hayden has refused to deny to<br />
me that he would guarantee that no pensioner, no small businessman,<br />
no householder, or no owner of a farm under 100 acres would not<br />
be hit by his Capital Gains Tax scheme. He also wants a<br />
Resources Tax. He wants a special tax on oil companies. These<br />
are the kinds of policies that brought development in Australia<br />
under Labor to a dead stop.<br />
our policies are getting Australia moving again, and we are going<br />
to keep it that way. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
