<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10358</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP BRADFIELD FEDERAL EXECUTIVE COUNCIL AUTUMN LUNCH, BRADFIELD</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/05/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010358.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Fax from 3 It 26/ 05/ 97 10: 53 Pg: 13<br />
MAPY 26 ' 97 10: 49 PRIME MINISTER<br />
May 1997 ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP<br />
BRADFIELD FEDERAL EXECUTIVE COUNCIL<br />
AUTUMN LUNCH, BRADFIELD<br />
E&amp; OE<br />
Thank you very much Brendan, to Tony Staley the Federal President of the Liberal<br />
Party and to my Federal and State parliamentary colleagues and particularly to Dr and<br />
Mr Smith, the headmistress and husband of Ravenswood School and Mr James Miller,<br />
the Chairman of the School Council.<br />
Can I unashamedly and risking all of the inevitable partisan hostilities that I will incur<br />
in saying it, our daughter had five years of outstanding education at this school. It is a<br />
great place and Kerry I had momentarily forgotten. The thing I remember about the<br />
of May 1991 it was a Saturday and Shore Under 14 beat Riverview 2 1 in the<br />
soccer.<br />
But it is a great delight to be here and can say that the schools on the North Shore<br />
are bipartisan when it comes to inviting Prime Ministers. I well remember back in<br />
1973 when Gough Whitlam was Prime Minister of Australia, he was invited to a Knox<br />
Speech Night and he said it was the biggest gathering in the electorate of Bradfield<br />
ever addressed by a Labor leader. So it is a very, very fine bipartisan tradition and it is<br />
great to be here.<br />
But even more importantly than that it is great to be amongst so many old friends.<br />
And it is great to acknowledge the contribution through the years of the Federal<br />
Division of Bradfield to the organisation of the party here in New South Wales, and of<br />
course I cannot let the opportunity go by without particularly acknowledging the<br />
presence of my old friend John Carrick and his wife, Angela. Nobody under this great<br />
marque has done more for the Liberal cause in Australia than that man and I very, very<br />
happily acknowledge it. </p>
<p>Fax from 3 11 26/ 05/ 97 10: 53 Pg: 14<br />
MA1Y 26 ' 97 10: 49 -1<br />
2<br />
1 also want to thank Brendan for his very kind words and endorse what Robert said<br />
about the contribution that he is making and also the remarks that were made by Kerry<br />
Chikarovski. Brendan has proved to be a very energetic and articulate representative<br />
of the Division of Bradfield. H-e is very pugnacious and hard working and loyal but an<br />
intelligent contributor to the deliberations of the parliamentary party and the<br />
parliamentary party is the stronger for having Brendan Nelson. And I think it is also<br />
important today that there are a number of members here who represent electorates<br />
that we have not always held. We have always held Bradfield and Bennelong and<br />
North ( no we have not always held North Sydney, we lost it for a while) but we have<br />
certainly held Bradfield and Bennelong for a very, very long time but we did not win<br />
Gilmore the first time up and we should have. And of course Parramatta has gone<br />
back and forth. And it really is important that we are all reminded that the fuature of<br />
the Liberal Party at a Federal level depends on getting people like Ross Cameron and<br />
Joanna Gash re-elected at the next Federal Election.<br />
We are sort of half way through our first term in Government and I spoke yesterday<br />
about keeping faith with the promises that we made at the time of the last election.<br />
And I spent a little time at the State Council meeting reminding people of how much of<br />
the agenda that we spelt out before the election had in fact been delivered. And I am<br />
very proud of the fact that in the last Budget for the first time in the history of<br />
Australia, a Federal Governiment has actually given an across-the-board incentive for<br />
people to save. For years I have gone around to meetings and I have been told by<br />
people that what you have got to do is fix the taxation system to the extent that you no<br />
longer tax people when they earn their income and tax them again when they receive<br />
some interest on the investment of what is left over out of their income. And the<br />
fifteen percent across-the-board tax break that was announced in the Budget is the first<br />
recognition by any Federal Government that that kind of change to the Australian<br />
taxation system ought to be made and it will act as a very powerfl~ l incentive and a<br />
very important reward over the years for people who are thrifty enough to save.<br />
Now Brendan spoke in his kind introduction about privatisation, And of course one<br />
cannot let an opportunity like this go by without reminding oneself of the incredible<br />
hypocrisy of our political opponents on privatisation. I mean I have been a consistent<br />
supporter of privatisation as has Nick Greiner and many others under this marque for a<br />
very long period of time. And I remember when I first advocated that we privatise<br />
Qantas and TraitsAustralia Airlines as it then was and sort of half raised the possibility<br />
of privatising the Commonwealth Bank that Bob Hawke went to Bathurst in May and<br />
delivered the Ben Chifley Memorial Lecture and said that one of my predecesors<br />
Ben Chifley, who I think in some respects was a more loved Labor Prime Minister than<br />
some of his successors, he said that Ben Chifley would roll in his grave if anybody<br />
thought of selling the Commnonwealth Bank.<br />
And of course before the 1987 election, they swore they would not do it. Before the<br />
1990 election they swore they would not do it. Before the 1993 election they swore<br />
they would not do it And of course before the 1996 election they swore they would<br />
not sell Telecom either. Or Telstra as it is now called. But we all know that having<br />
sworn not to sell the Bank before those elections, they finally ended up doing so and<br />
we also know that if the Australian people had been unfortunate enough to re-elect a </p>
<p>Fax f rom~ 3 It 26/ 85/ 97 10: 53 Pg:<br />
MAPY 26 ' 97 10: 50P. T 3<br />
Labor Government in 1996 a re-elected Labor government would not have sold a third<br />
of Telstra, they would have sold the whole lot. And I am reminded of that by this<br />
extraordinary little exercise that is going on here in New South Wales. Now I am all in<br />
favour of privatising the power system in New South Wales. I think it is aneminently<br />
sensible thing to do. But why on earth can't you say that before the election and not<br />
sort of kid, try and kid the Australian public, that you are not going to do it. I think it<br />
is just sort of completes the circle. Finishes the loop as far as their hypocrisy is<br />
concerned.<br />
Now over the last 14 months we really have gone a tremendous distance between<br />
implementing the agenda on which we were elected. There are a few things that have<br />
come up as inevitably things do when you are elected that you did not anticipate. And<br />
governments are required as well as implementing the things that they promised to do<br />
they are also required to respond to some of the unexpected things. And we have had<br />
such things to do with such as the issue of national gun control legislation last year, the<br />
rather unexpected requirement to deal with a decision by the High Court of Australia<br />
in the Wik case that many predicted might go in the other direction. But the main<br />
agenda that my Government has had and the main agenda that my Government will<br />
continue to have between now and whenever the next election is held is to keep faith<br />
with the essential commitments that we made to the people of Australia to the<br />
mainstream of the Australian community before the last election. And that is about<br />
giving to families a greater sense of security, it is about giving to individuals greater<br />
incentive, greater incentive to work, greater incentive to save, greater incentive to take<br />
nisks. It is also about tackling the chronically high levels of unemployment, particularly<br />
amongst the young, that we still have in Australia. And none of us, particularly in<br />
electorates on the North Shore of Sydney, should lose sight of the fact that there are<br />
areas of Australia that suffer tragically high levels of unemployment where the endemic<br />
character of unemployment is such that it is being passed now from grandfather to<br />
father to son and that it has become intergenerational.<br />
We do require policies that will regenerate some of the regional areas of Australia.<br />
That is why in the Budget wve announced that we were going to establish a $ 1 billion<br />
Federation Fund which will be used not to finance the building of a thousand little<br />
monuments in every suburb and every hamnlet of Australia but is going to be used to<br />
finance the construction of major infrastructure works which will be of long term<br />
benefit to the future of Australia particularly to the regions and to the rural area of<br />
Australia. But in that context, one of the other responsibilities of a government is always to keep<br />
its eye on necessary reform. Quality government and quality political leadership is<br />
about on the one hand, holding onto and consolidating those things in the commnunity<br />
that are important and ought to continue. And I have always believed that what one<br />
ought to be in politics is either a discerning conservative or a selective radical or<br />
should I say a selective conservative and a discerning radical. In other words, you<br />
hang onto those things that are working well, you do not throw out something that is<br />
working well just for the sake of change. But on the other hand, when something is<br />
not working well you are zealously and you are energetically committed to bringing </p>
<p>Fax 1f1 2r6il / 05/ 97 10: 53 Pg: b<br />
MAY 26 ' 97 10: 51 P1<br />
4<br />
about change and bringing about reform. And that is why in the early 1 980s I set my<br />
sights on reforming Australia's industrial relations system because I thought it was out<br />
of date. I though it was discredited. I thought it was holding back the potential<br />
growth of Australia. I thought it was too heavily dominated by the trade union<br />
movement and worst of all I thought it was skewed irrevocably against the interests of<br />
small business in Australia.<br />
It was an industrial relations system that had been built to accommodate large<br />
company large work forces heavily unionised, overwhelmingly male, and<br />
predominantly blue collar. And of course the character of Australia has changed so<br />
much that that sort of paradigm no longer works and is no longer relevant to Australia.<br />
So we set ourselves the task of changing industrial relations and one of the big changes<br />
that I am very proud of, that my government has brought in is industrial relations<br />
change. And as the weeks and months go by and the value of the changes that were<br />
brought in by Peter Reith in his workplace relations legislation work their way through<br />
the Australian economy the legislation has only been operating now for a little under<br />
six months. We took a bit longer to get it through the Senate and we only got through<br />
about eighty per cent of what we would have liked but that eighty per cent is an infinite<br />
improvement, an enormous improvement on the system that it replaced.<br />
And one of the great benefits of that legislation is that it has given to small business a<br />
lot more flexibility and a lot more room to move and a lot more opportunity to make<br />
agreements at a workplace level, But that task of reform is never of course finished.<br />
So one of the other issues that governents and political leaders and business leaders<br />
and leaders of other organisations in this country have got to face, and that is the need<br />
to reform Australia's taxation system. Now I do not make any apology at all for<br />
raising the issue of reform of Australia's taxation system. Anybody who imagined that<br />
it was something that could lay dormant in the political comner for the next ten or<br />
fifteen years has no understanding of the needs of this community and no<br />
understanding of the wvay in which the taxation system we presently have is becoming<br />
less and less relevant to the kind of modern Australian economy that we are trying to<br />
build. But it is very important that as we continue to debate taxation reform we do not<br />
make the mistake that I think we have made in the past and that is becoming obsessed<br />
with the system of taxation reform-rather than the outcomes of taxation reform. We<br />
must not become obsessed with building a perfect econometric model to the detriment<br />
of asking ourselves what are the goals of taxation reform.<br />
And I think there are three goals and there are three questions you have to ask<br />
yourself. The first question you have got to ask yourself is what reform of the<br />
Australian taxation system is needed to generate more jobs. That is the first question.<br />
I think the next question you have to ask yourself, given the importance of trade to<br />
Australia, is what reform to the Australian taxation system is going to generate more<br />
exports? And I think that is a tremendously importantly thing. And finally you have to<br />
ask yourself what change to the Australian taxation system is going to generate higher<br />
living standards and encourage people to greater risk taking and provide people with<br />
greater incentives?<br />
Now they are the three tests that we have to apply. And it is not a debate that the<br />
Liberal Party should walk away from. It is not a debate the Liberal Party should turn </p>
<p>F3a1xf1rZm6 / 05/ 97 10: 53 rg:<br />
tiPy 26 ' 97 10: 51 1<br />
its back on, And those on the political spectrum who believe that an essentially<br />
negative, backward-looking fear campaign is the only response to the issue of taxation<br />
reform I think are making a very, very serious mistake. Now I know that this issue<br />
was raised in the past and I am aware as anybody else in this gathering of the debate<br />
that followed the result in 1 993. 1 think there were some errors, let me put it this way,<br />
there were some errors of emphasis and some errors of presentation and there were<br />
some other errors of timing in relation to that, which are entirely different now.<br />
Now, let me say to you that our commitment not to introduce anything remotely<br />
resembling a goods and services tax during our first term of government remains<br />
absolutely rock solid. I gave that guarantee to the Australian people before the last<br />
election and I have no intention from walking away from that anymore than I have an<br />
intention of walking away from other commitments that I made to the Australian<br />
people. But I have never said that we would never look at taxation reform. And I<br />
think we would be a very odd government, we would fail the Australian people<br />
completely if we turned our backs on the necessity of reform in this very, very<br />
important area.<br />
I can remember at the end of the 1 970s, as Treasurer, being invited to give a speech<br />
about the challenges of reform, economic reform in Australia in the 1980s. And I said<br />
that we needed to reform our financial system. Well, ultimately we did. And that<br />
received support essentially from both sides of politics. We needed to embark upon<br />
reform to our taxation system. Well, have bisrnaly failed as a nation to do that. And<br />
we needed to look increasingly at our industrial relations system and see what areas of<br />
change and reform were needed there. So we still have, if you are looking at the<br />
reform agenda, and all governments have got to do that, you are not elected to occupy<br />
positions of power without using that power wisely for the benefit of people. I have<br />
been in politics a very, very long time now, but I have always thought that the profit of<br />
winning office is to do good things for the country and not just the satisfaction of<br />
exercising that political power. So part of our job, part of our responsibility is to keep<br />
the torch of reform in certain areas going, but to do it in a way that is related to the<br />
outcomes of that reform.<br />
Politicians who get caught up with process and not outcomes lose the capacity to<br />
communicate with the Australian people. The Australian people want to know why a<br />
reform is good, they want to know how it will affect them, they want to know whether<br />
it will make it better for them and make it better for their children and make it more<br />
likely that their teenage children will get a job and that their elderly parents and other<br />
members of their family have a sense of stability and a sense of security. It is the<br />
outcomes. It is the product of change rather than the tactical value of that change<br />
which isth e important thing that we as political figures, political activists should<br />
always work towards.<br />
The last thing that I want to say to you, ladies and gentlemen, is that it is always a<br />
great pleasure to come back to the grass roots of the Liberal Party. I of course have<br />
been a member of the New South Wales division of the party since about 1958 when I<br />
joined a branch in Eariwood, the suburb in which I grew up, and I owe everything that<br />
I have achieved in politics to the Liberal Party. I would never have been a member of<br />
parliament without the Liberal Party. I would never have been a leader of the party </p>
<p>Fax from 3 11 26/ 05/ 97 10: S3 Pg: 18<br />
MA~ Y 26 ' 97 10: 52 6<br />
without the support and understanding of the Liberal Party and of course I would<br />
never have become Prine Mnister of Australia without the support and nourishment<br />
and loyalty of people in the Liberal Party and as I look around this room I see people<br />
that I have been associated with now for 25, 30 and in some cases even a little longer<br />
than that years. And it is a very great privilege to have that opportunity.<br />
I want to thank all of you for the support that you have given over the years in so<br />
many different ways to the Liberal Party cause here in Sydney and all around Australia.<br />
We waited a hell of a long time in Opposition. We lost more elections than we should<br />
have. We knocked on in front of the try line far more frequently than any group of<br />
people should have done and on occasions I sort of wondered as though somehow the<br />
world had been turned on its head and there was absolutely no justice in politics as in<br />
sport. It is like last night when I was watching the second one dayer. I mean I thought<br />
English cricket teams were meant to feel like Englishmen not like South Africans. And<br />
I mean there is something wrong when you cannot rely on the English to feel like<br />
Eng), ishmen. There really is. You know. The world is not the same. It sort of<br />
shattered my faith in the predicability of some of those constants.<br />
But. anyway, ladies and gentlemen, can I say to you again that I do appreciate all of<br />
your support. It is infinitely better to be in Government than in Opposition and we<br />
need your continued support but we need your support, your quality support. We<br />
need your resources, we need your manpower, but we also need on occasions your<br />
advice. I mean politics is about listening to advice. It really is. And one of the<br />
reasons that I think my predecessor lost the last election that he lost the capacity to<br />
listen and he lost the capacity to understand what the proverbial man in the street or<br />
man and woman in the street really wanted out of their political leaders. Now I will try<br />
very hard to avoid that trap and my colleagues will try very hard to avoid that trap.<br />
And it is your obligation privately and discreetly of course when you think we are<br />
falling into that trap to remind us of it. But thank you again for your tremendous<br />
support and loyalty. And once again congratulations to the most consistently blue<br />
ribbon electorate in the whole of Australia for the Liberal Party cause, that is the<br />
DivIsion of Bradfield. Thank you very much for all that you have poured into the<br />
Party over the years and all that you will undoubtedly pour into it in the years to come.<br />
I am both retrospectively and in the future very, very grateful for all of that support.<br />
Thank you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
