<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7147</transcript-id>
    <title>RRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, 1 APRIL 1987</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/04/1987</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007147.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, 1 APRIL 1987<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
PM: I have stated consistently that I prefer the Parliament to<br />
run its full term.<br />
The leadership vacuum and chaos within and between the<br />
Opposition Parties, together with their imminent rejection<br />
of the Australia Card legislation for a second time, have<br />
presented the option and may I say frankly, the temptation,<br />
of an early election.<br />
I am confident that Labor would win an early election. I<br />
have decided, however, that the election will be held<br />
towards the end of this year or early next year.<br />
The Australian people want continued strong leadership and a<br />
Government that will continue to guide them through<br />
difficult economic times into renewed prosperity. To have<br />
an early election. may have brought into question the<br />
Government's resolve to make the tough decisions needed to<br />
meet the economic challenge facing this country.<br />
Let me repeat the dimension of this challenge. Through<br />
paying drastically lower prices for many of our exports the<br />
world has cut more than $ 6 billion off the nation's income;<br />
that is, we are poorer to the tune of $ 1500 per Australian<br />
family. As a nation we have no responsible alternative to<br />
adjusting to that reality.<br />
I want to tell the Australian people that we will not shirk<br />
our responsibilities in making the unpalatable, though<br />
necessary economic decisions: the May Statement will be<br />
tough but fair.<br />
The Australian people overwhelmingly reject the deceptive<br />
voodoo economics being espoused by the opposition Partiesbigger<br />
handouts, bigger deficits; that is, a certain recipe<br />
for higher interest rates, higher inflation, massive<br />
increases in unemployment total economic disaster.<br />
When the Opposition Parties reject the Australia Card<br />
legislation in the Senate later this week, they will stand<br />
condemned by the Australian people for denying to the nation<br />
this fundamental instrument for dealing decisively with tax<br />
cheats and welfare frauds. This denial of more than $ 800m a<br />
year to the public purse from those who should be paying is<br />
simply a continuation of the traditional<br />
Howard/ Sinclair/ Bjelke Petersen philosophy protect the<br />
privileged and increase the burden on the great honest<br />
majority of the Australian people. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, the Labor Party's private sampling from<br />
the weekend tells you that the vast majority of Australians don't<br />
want an early election and that might be bound on you?<br />
PM: I don't know because my meeting with our pollster is later<br />
today. All I can say is that the very brief preliminary<br />
discussion that I've had, is consistent with my assessment of all<br />
the other polls, that Labor would win an early election.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke why did you announce that there would be no<br />
early election before I. D. card legislation had been through the<br />
Senate? PM: Once I had made up my mind that there should not be an early<br />
election and that the Government should go the full term, I saw<br />
no reason to hang around and wait on what might happen in that<br />
place. I assume that they are going to defeat the legislation.<br />
That is what they say they are going to do.<br />
JOURNALIST: Are there any circumstances which would make you<br />
change your mind?<br />
PM: We have been through all this now don't start it again no.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, Mr Howard will say you're a whimp<br />
PM: Will he, I see. It is very difficult to chart Mr Howard<br />
isn't it. It's impossible, he is not consistent from one day to<br />
another. But he said, as I recall, that Mr Hawke would be guilty<br />
of the most massive act of hypocrisy in living memory if I were<br />
to have an early election. One deduces from that, that his<br />
judgment is that I should not call an early election. Now if he<br />
says what you say he'll say the implication is that I didn't have<br />
the courage to earlier and I should have gone earlier. So if he<br />
comes out and says that, I'll welcome him saying it because it<br />
will be totally consistent with the pathetic apology for<br />
leadership which he is offering this country.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke do you believe your decision will provoke a<br />
split in the National Party now and are you are you concerned<br />
that John Stone has joined Joh's team?<br />
PM: Thank you for the question, it is not a Dorothy. The<br />
question assumes that there is not a split in the National Party<br />
and there is. A massive split in the National Party, so I don't<br />
know that my decision adds to that, whether it narrows or widens<br />
the split. Now as for this person that you talk about, John<br />
Stone, well look we could go for hours about him couldn't we.<br />
But we won't. I understand, I have not read the report, but I<br />
understand that he is to become the professional consultant on<br />
tax to Joh Bjelke-Petersen. It will be interesting if we could<br />
have the record of the things that the same John Stone has said<br />
about the same Joh Bjelke-Petersen. And who knows perhaps they<br />
may emerge. I think the fairest thing that we can say is that<br />
they deserve one another. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: At what stage over the few weeks were you most<br />
tempted to call an early election?<br />
PM: I'm a person who has lived with temptation all his life.<br />
And have a very great record of resisting it, generally speaking.<br />
I don't think there was any point at which the devil prodded me<br />
more strongly than another. But I just want to be honest with<br />
you all and with the Australian people. It was a very real<br />
temptation, because I firmly believe that we would win. But the<br />
temptation never assumed the dimensions that it could overcome my<br />
concern for what I think is right.<br />
JOURNALIST: John Howard this morning painted a picture of you as<br />
a man going through public agony unable to make up his mind. Why<br />
has it taken this long for you to decide that you should not have<br />
an early election?<br />
PM: I would have thought that you have seen me, not just<br />
yesterday, but recently. I am told that the image I'm projecting<br />
is one of not merely a healthy, fit Prime Minister, which is<br />
true, but a very relaxed one. That is true, I have never felt<br />
more relaxed than I have in the last few months. I have not felt<br />
under, or believed I have been under any tension. I can assure<br />
you I don't feel under any tension.<br />
JOURNALIST: You are confident in your policies and confident<br />
that you would win. Why not now go to the electorate for a<br />
renewed mandate of three years?<br />
PM: There are number of points that I think are relevant to that<br />
very pertinent question. First of all, if I were to decide on an<br />
early election and base it in part, a substantial part, on the<br />
rejection of the I. D. card, you would have to wait until the<br />
Senate finished its consideration, made its decision. Now who<br />
knows when that is going to be. At best it may be the end of<br />
this week. Then once that i's made you go to the Governor-General<br />
and you get the decision of the Governor-General. And then there<br />
is quite a long period. Now it seems to me that in that period,<br />
given the sort of volatility of which you are aware, of the<br />
markets and so on, that period of instability could be adverse to<br />
the country. That was very much a consideration in my mind.<br />
Also I think people were entitled to say if I had gone earlier,<br />
they would have available to them an argument saying, Mr Hawke<br />
you have got a mandate, you were elected, the normal period is<br />
three years, use that mandate. So I think those considerations<br />
are the ones relevant to answering that question.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, you said on Friday that the Australia Card<br />
legislation was fundamental . have you backed away from that? </p>
<p>PM: Of course I haven't. I can assure you that from the point<br />
at which this infamous combination of Liberals and National Party<br />
and Democrats reject that legislation, they will wear that<br />
rejection from that day until the election day. I can't get it<br />
through apparently. That is not the end of it. Their rejection<br />
of the legislation, whenever the election is held, at the end of<br />
this year, or early next year, that will be a central part of<br />
this campaign, because it is clear that the legislation is right<br />
and beneficially it is also clear that the overwhelming majority<br />
of the Australian people understand that it is right and want<br />
that legislation.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke it is one thing to rule out an early<br />
election which is what you have done. It is another thing to cut<br />
off your other options and say that you will go the full term,<br />
which also rules out the prospect of a double dissolution and the<br />
chance of getting the Australia Card through the joint<br />
sittings. Can you tell us why you have taken the second step as<br />
well? PM: I believe that all the arguments I have put for going the<br />
course that I am talking about, are valid. And I am making the<br />
judgment that when we do have the election we will be returned<br />
with a very clear majority and that in those circumstances, in<br />
which the election will in part have been fought on the issue on<br />
the Australia Card, that we will then in those circumstances<br />
after we have won, and in which the Australia Card has been part<br />
of the election, we will be able to get through the next<br />
Parliament that legislation. </p>
<p>JOUJRNALIST: Mr Hawke, you ate thFe one w. ho floated the option<br />
olt an early election and kept t~ hat fioating and maintained<br />
the importanice of the ID card legislation and gettincl<br />
it through the Senate. in view ot the decision that. you have<br />
reached now, what was the point ot all that?<br />
PM: No, you are wrong, Feather, to say iLhat I was the one<br />
who floated<br />
JOURNALIST: You kept the option alive'?<br />
PM: I answering the question as you put it. I didn't float<br />
it, it was there in the public arena. And I said you can't<br />
get ]. 10t honesty, you have got 100-t honesty from me. Ihave<br />
said it has been a temptation. The ID card has been there in<br />
context of this historical level of chaos within the Liberal<br />
Party, within the National Party and between the National<br />
Party and the Liberal Party. And quite honestl. y it has been<br />
a temptation to take adv~ antagje of that. And so my talk about<br />
the possibility of an early election has been related,<br />
obviously as it must be, to the Australia Card because that<br />
would have been the trigger. But, as I[ say, I have resisted<br />
the temptation.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, you will still have that trigger<br />
at the time you call an election, will it be a double<br />
dissolution that you have then?<br />
PM: Read your Constitution. The capacity for a double<br />
dissolution runs out, I think, in August sometime. Because<br />
you can't have a double dissolution within the 6 month period<br />
of when you are required to call an election to the House of<br />
Representatives. JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, you referred to the voodoo<br />
economics of the Opposition. Do you think John Stone is a<br />
voodoo economist?<br />
PM: It is very hard to understand what sort of an economist<br />
Mr Stone is. It is the same Mr Stone who was the economic<br />
adviser to Mr Howard and we know what the economic policies<br />
of that period inflicted upon Australia the worst recession<br />
years. And we have an idea of what the views of Mr<br />
Stone were at that time in the taxation area. Presumably,<br />
from all we can gather, he Is now a flat-taxer. That is<br />
certainly voodoo economics. But I think it is probably<br />
wisest that I don't go into details about my opinion of Mr<br />
Stone. JOURNALIST: On a similar subject, Prime Minister, have you<br />
sent Neil Brown his retraction andi apology?<br />
PM: No.<br />
JOURNALIST: Are you going to?<br />
PM: The matter is in the hands of my lawyers.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, part ( if the temptation for an election<br />
presumably was the possibility of having an election and then<br />
making the tough economic decisions. it is now the other way </p>
<p>round you are 9q'ing to make the tough economic decisions<br />
and then have an election<br />
PM: That is right.<br />
JOURNALIST: Dloes that make it harder to make it harder to<br />
make those tough decisions?<br />
PM: I guess, yes, it would have been easier if you had an<br />
election and explIained again the facts as I have been doing<br />
it consistently for some time. But the point of my statement<br />
the relevant paragraph, CGeoff,-is that I am assuring the<br />
Australian people now that the necessary tough decisions will<br />
be taken. I said in my Address to the Nation and I have said<br />
it since, and it is relevant to say it again, I would rather<br />
lose that next election, when it. is held, 1 would rather lose<br />
than go soft in economic decision-making because let it be<br />
understood when you have a problem of that dimension, if you<br />
go soft now, a la the voodoo economics of Howard and<br />
Sinclair and Bjelke-Petersen, what you would be doing would<br />
be condemning, not just this generation, but the next<br />
generation and the generation beyond that. I have been too<br />
long in public life and I have too much of a commitment to<br />
this country to do that. So I will be making the tough<br />
decisions. In the end, I repeat, I have got sufficient faith<br />
in the good sense of the Australian electorate to believe<br />
that they will both understand and accept those decisions.<br />
It is that belief in the Australian people that has informed<br />
my thinking in just about 30 years in public life. I am not<br />
going to change it now.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, will. those tough decisions include<br />
keeping spending to no real growth in the Budget?<br />
PM: You will see the form, the substance and the totality<br />
of those decisions when the Treasurer delivers the May<br />
Statement on the 14th of May.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, when you had your cappuccino this<br />
morning with Mr Hunt and Mr Sinclair, did you happen to tell<br />
them of your decision not to hold an early election or did<br />
you give them any other advice?<br />
PM: I didn't tell them of my decision not to hold an early<br />
election. And for me to give themi advice you know I<br />
wouldn't be that presumptitolis, Niki. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: What did they tell you about the future?<br />
PM: I think our conversation should remain confidential.<br />
JOURNALIST: How important was it in your final decision you<br />
could not get broad support within your party to go to an early<br />
election? PM: It was not very significant. Let me say this, I hadn't<br />
really been sounding out all the Party as is the case that some<br />
reports came back to me. But I was totally confident if I made<br />
the decision to call an early election the whole of the Party<br />
would have fallen in behind me. Let me answer it in another way.<br />
If all the elements of the Party had been saying to me, we want<br />
to go now, I wouldn't have made that decision. I would have made<br />
the decision I made now.<br />
JOURNALIST: In what way did you fear the prospect of an early<br />
election may bring into question the Government's resolve to<br />
bring down these tough decisions?<br />
PM: It goes back to the answer I gave to Greg earlier. We are<br />
living in very volatile times and damage can be done to the<br />
exchange rate, therefore to interest rates, quite quickly. If<br />
you had a situation where the country were in an election mode<br />
for something like two months, broadly speaking, quite an amount<br />
of damage could be done in those terms. I didn't think it was<br />
right to run that risk.<br />
JOURNALIST: If you had been given different economic forecasts<br />
for this year, might your decision have been different about an<br />
early election?<br />
PM: What should be understood is that the analysis and the<br />
judgments that were conveyed to me on Sunday night were<br />
precisely, they were identical with the judgments that I had been<br />
making myself. Those judgments are a matter of record, actually,<br />
but it's precisely in lihe with what I'd been saying to my own<br />
advisers. I put a fair bit of faith in my own capacity as an<br />
economist. JOURNALIST: Would you have been a hypocrite to go ahead with an<br />
early election given your repeated commitment not to call one?<br />
PM: I think there would have been an attempt to say there's an<br />
hypocrisy. This was some concern on my part. I attach<br />
considerable importance to my own integrity. I do think that<br />
there are valid arguments for going early and they've been<br />
involved in some of the questions. It could be said that if you<br />
went early, got a new mandate, then you had no inhibitions, no<br />
need to take account of political concerns about a decision here<br />
or a decision there. I think it is possible to mount a valid<br />
argument for an early election. On balance, for the reasons I've<br />
given, I thought the balance of argument comes down on the side<br />
of the decision that I've taken. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Did you take into consideration the possibility that<br />
Andrew Peacock could do a Hawke 83 and get up just before the<br />
election? And would you prefer to go to an election against John<br />
Howard rather than Andrew Peacock?<br />
PM: Let me modestly say in response to the first part of your<br />
question, Andrew Peacock is no Bob Hawke. I will, with all the<br />
modesty I can gather, just point out that Andrew Peacock doesn't<br />
come within a bulls roar of my understanding of this country, its<br />
economic structure, of economic policy, what's required to deal<br />
with these sorts of things. He's light years away. Andrew<br />
Peacock is not Bob Hawke. The second part of your question,<br />
would I prefer to go against John Howard or Andrew Peacock? I<br />
can beat either of them and it's not certain, obviously, who it<br />
will be that I will be facing when the election comes. You know<br />
I'm a bit of a punter. I'd hate to be framing the chart at the<br />
moment, I really would hate to be framing the chart. one thing<br />
you could say is that John Howard is no odds-on-favourite to be<br />
the person that I'll be up against, but you wouldn't be putting<br />
the odds very short about Andrew getting the leadership. And of<br />
course we've got the fascinating scenario emerging, perhaps it<br />
will be someone else. Now I can't say anything about the third<br />
man in terms I said yesterday because this is now a matter of the<br />
law. But there's no end to the speculation. If you look at the<br />
seat of Higgins, there is a suggestion that it could be Mr<br />
Elliot. Well that would be fascinating too. The point you've<br />
got to understand is this. An election is not just about<br />
leaders, although obviously leaders are very important. The<br />
fundamental problem in conservative politics today, in this<br />
country, is that they are rent asunder because they have no<br />
philosophy, they have no policies, they have no constancy of<br />
positions in regard to policy matters. The only constant in<br />
conservative politics is their commitment to restore privileges<br />
to the few. Their only argument is about how they restore the<br />
privileges to the few and impose the greater burden upon the<br />
majority. And that fact is not an argument, it is a fact and<br />
that is being exposed more and more. So whether it is John<br />
Howard, or Andrew PeacocK, or John Elliot, or McLachlan, or<br />
whoever it is, Bjelke-Petersen, the divisions, the fundamental<br />
divisions will be there as they try to cobble together an apology<br />
for this only constant they have. That is, let's restore<br />
privileges. Let's make sure the burden of economic adjustment<br />
falls on the honest majority. Now that is the problem for the<br />
conservatives and until they face up to the fact that they are<br />
now living in an economic and political environment within which<br />
they must have relevant policies, until they wake up to that it<br />
doesn't matter if it's Howard, or Peacock, or Elliot, or whoever<br />
it is, because what they're operating on is the assumption that<br />
the Australian people are fools. That they'll buy this $ 16<br />
billion credibility gap. That in a situation that we are the<br />
poorer for the amount of $ 1500 per Australian family, that those<br />
families are going to buy the nonsense they're being told<br />
here's another handout, here's another handout, here's a deficit<br />
of 12 billion odd dollars, which is what's involved in the $ 16<br />
billion credibility gap. That they'll buy the nonsense of those<br />
things which mean, as I say in my statement, inevitably higher<br />
interest rates, higher inflation, massive increases in<br />
unemployment, total economic disaster. Until they understand<br />
that the people of Australia won't buy that nonsense it doesn't<br />
matter who they have leading them. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, are you telling us that when the election<br />
is held the economy will be in better shape than it is now? And<br />
if you are telling us that, can you give the Australian people a<br />
guarantee that come election time the home loan rates and the<br />
inflation rate and the unemployment rate will all be lower than<br />
what they are now?<br />
PM: The first part of the question, will the economy be<br />
improving, my strong judgment is that it will be. I've been<br />
through that yesterday, I don't think you want me to go through<br />
the details of my analysis. I have had the caveat which any<br />
rational economic thinker must put on, that while I make that<br />
analysis, in terms of my judgment, that the impact of Australia's<br />
internal economic policies producing that result, you must have<br />
the caveat about what may happen overseas. But I repeat, I am<br />
basically optimistic that the external situation will not produce<br />
a contrary outcome to the one I'm talking about. If I'm right in<br />
that assessment then I have no reason to believe that, in regard<br />
to the particular matter that you raise about mortgage rates, it<br />
will be a deteriorated situation. To say that would not be<br />
consistent with the general analysis that I've put.<br />
JOURNALIST: And inflation and unemployment?<br />
PM: Inflation I've said, I repeat again, I have no doubt that<br />
the inflation rate will trend down in 1987. So if you're talking<br />
about an election in March of 1988, the last CPI figures you'd<br />
have, therefore, would be for the December quarter 87. My<br />
judgment, and not just my judgment, it's certainly the judgment<br />
of others who are talking to me and I would observe also the<br />
judgment of the OECD report, that we should be looking at an<br />
inflation rate at the end of 1987 of about six per cent. In<br />
regard to unemployment, it would be my assessment that we can<br />
hold the unemployment situation at the rate of growth that has<br />
been talked about, would involve a level of employment increase<br />
that would enable us to hold the unemployment situation.<br />
JOURNALIST: What else did Mr Cameron tell you in the brief<br />
discussion that you had with him today, other than the fact that<br />
you'd win the election?<br />
PM: I haven't had, as I recall, a brief discussion with him<br />
today. It was a very brief telephone conversation last night.<br />
JOURNALIST: Could you elaborate on the conversation?<br />
PM: Well I suppose I could, but I could also say no one would be<br />
more surprised than you if I did. Let me say this, however, it<br />
was a fairly brief conversation. That conversation did nothing<br />
to change my judgment that we could win an early election.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
