<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6319</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S PRESS CONFERENCE AT STATE GUEST HOUSE, 9 FEBRUARY 1984</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/02/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006319.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT -PRIME MINISTER' S PRESS CONFERENCE AT STATE GUEST<br />
HOUSE 9 FEBRUARY 1984<br />
E AND 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
PJI.: WELL LADIES AND OENTLEMEN I'll VERY PLEASED TO0 BE ABLE TO<br />
ANNOUNCE A SIGNIEFICANT DEVELOPMENT OUT OF OUR DISCUSSIONS T1HIS<br />
MORNING WHICH HAS. VEIRY GREAT P': ITENTIAL FOR AUSTRALIA A* ND ALSO, I<br />
BEL-IEVE, FOR CHINA. I PUT TO PREMIER ZHAO THE POLICIES OF OUR<br />
GOVERNMENT IN THE ECONOMiC FIEL. D NOT ONLY IN : REGARD TO THE IM ' EDIATE<br />
OBJECTIVES THAT WE' D HAD OF TURtliNG OUR !-. CONqOrY' AIRO. U. ND I-U1 OF ALSO<br />
TRYING To ENSURE THAT THE ECONOMIC DEVEL;) Pf'! E. N1 OF AUSTRALIA COULD<br />
BE RELATED AS EFFECTIVELY AS POSSIBLE To THE RTEGION OF WHICH WE<br />
ARE PART SO TH -AT AS YOU'VE HEARD ME SAY BEFORE WE COULD œ ECoNiE<br />
ENMESHED. ' 1N' . THF_ DEV ELOPmENT OF THE REGION 1N A WAY WHICH WOULD<br />
ENABLE US ' T0 DERIVE BENEFIT FROM THE DYNAMISM' OF THI'. Z REGION AND IN<br />
TURN MAKE A CONTRIBUTION TO IT.<br />
IN THAT CONTEXT I PUT TO PREMIER ZHAO THAT WE, OF COURSE, WISHED TO<br />
BECOME A STIGNIFICANT SUPPLiER OF RAW MATERIALS T'O CHINA'S<br />
DEVELOPING IRON AND STEEL INDUSTRY IRON ORE AND ALSO COAL. 1 PUl<br />
TO TH'E PREMIER THAT IN ADDITION TO BEING SUCH A SUPPLIER OF -RAW<br />
MIATERIALS IT' HAD OCCURRED TO NE THAT WE OUJGHT TO EXAMINE THE<br />
POSSIB~ ILITY OF AUSTRALIA. SUPPLY1NG RAW MATERIALS9 IF YOU LIKE..<br />
AT A MORE DEVELOPED STAGE. THAT IS OF PIG IRON, SLABS AND BILLETS,<br />
% OHCU DB THEN FINALLY PROCESSED INTO THE REOU1RED FINAL<br />
PRODUCT IN CH4INA. I POINTED OUT TO PREMIER ZHAO THE MUTUAL ? ENE_: FI13<br />
INVOLVED IN SUCH AN APPROACH. THE ADVANTAGES FOR AUSTRALIA ARE<br />
OBVIOUS AND DON'T RE?; UIRE ANY ELABORATION Of-, M" PART TO YOU OF THE<br />
VERY SIGNIFICANTf ENEF-1TS FOR AUSTRALIA: A SIGNIFICANT STAGE OF<br />
MANUFACTURE. THE BENEFITS TO CHINA I POINTED OUT WERE THAT IT WOULD<br />
NOT INVOLVE ANY INCREASE IN TOTAL IMPORTS ON THEIR PART, I N OTHER<br />
WORDS THEY ' WOULD NEED rO IMPORT LESS ST~ E'_ WHICH THEY ARE CoN. 1, TElM'pLAT-.<br />
ING HAVING TO. DO. BUT THE INCREASED IMPORT OF THE eBASIC PRO. DUCT<br />
1ROM AUSTRALIA WOULD BE OFFSETr BY LESSER IPORTS OF STEEL ON TH4EIR<br />
P: 1ART. SECONDLY, IT WOULD BE OF BENEFIT IN REDUCING TRANSPO', RT<br />
BOTTLENECK S IN THIS COUNTRY LEAVING TrHE RA-W MATERIAL ARO) UN,. D FRt'N1<br />
THE SOURCE OF THE RAW MATERIAL TO THE ENTERPRISES. THIRDLY, IN%<br />
RESPECT OF TRANSPORT INTO CHINi'A iT WILL MORE EFFI ; IENT TO ? RN<br />
IN THE PRODUCT IN THE FORM, THAT I MENTIONED BECAUSE IT WOULD B E<br />
ABLE TO BE CARRIED IN SHIPS WHICH WOU,; LD BE ABLE TO-HAVE ACCE~ iS VERY<br />
READITLY TO THEIR PLANT, 1S THA~ N THE LARGE BULK -CARRIE RS. AND FINALLY<br />
: i N EC 0ON. MI C TE RMS 1' JL'( F RO) M CH; INA' S POINT O: VIEW THEY UL<br />
GET MORE VALUE PER UNIT OF: INVESTNENT IN-THIS IWAY AND WOULD<br />
:: NVOLVE SAVINGS IN FOPREIGN EXCHANGE.<br />
J'' M VERY PLEASED To SAY THAT P?. E" I1ER ZHA() HAS RESPONDED POSITIVELY<br />
I O THAT PRO-. POSCAL ( AND ' WE HAVE A'GREE! D' TO__ E " Sfr ABLISH A iJINT 1<br />
STUDY TO DEVELOP T iE PROP'MSAL. 1 PUT TO YOU THAT THIS ! S A DEVELOPrINT(<br />
F VERY IMPORTANCE OF GREAT PO) TENTiAL. BE7NEFIT TO CUR<br />
(: oUr! T'Y AN.) AS I SAY ALSO' TO CHINA. AND IT INVOLVES As I PUTYO<br />
HIHNES E REIIERA ROC E,_ B SEEN NiE . LY iN TERiE O<br />
ADDING TO TRADE BETWEEN OUR COUNTRIES LI~ ul ALSO VERY IMPO) RTANTLY<br />
To BE SEEN AS AOE) i Tu THE COrIPLE! IEN1 AR11TY OF OUR ECONONIC<br />
IDEVELOPMENT PROGRAMS. </p>
<p>THAT WAS A mAJUR DEVELOR! IENT TODAY. WE COVERED-ALSO A RANGE 0;:<br />
CTHER MATTERS. AND PERHAPS I COULD SREYXLFSVGFU~ F GH<br />
BJPOILOXDWE OPENED<br />
BY CONTINUING: DISCUSSIONS IN THE INTERNATIONAL AREA. I REFERRED TO<br />
THE FACT THAT BEFORE COMING HERE&amp; AS WELL AS HAVING GONE TO KOREA$<br />
A SUBJECT THAT WE COVERED YESTERDAYi I HAD ALSO BEEN TO HONG K ONG<br />
AND JAPAN.<br />
I. N RESPECT OF HUNG KONG I INDICATED THAT IT WAS. A CLEAR VIEW OF THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT THAT THE NEGOTIATIEONS IN RESPECT OF HONG K( ONG<br />
WERE PURELY A MATTER BETWEEN CHINA AND THE UNITED KINGDOM AND WE<br />
BELIEVE THAT THERE WOULD BE A-SATISFACTORY OUTC: OME OF THOSE<br />
DISCUSSIONS. THIS IS A VIEW THAT I PUT IN JONG KONGi AND THAT I'VyE<br />
CONSISTENTLY HELD. AND I MUST SAY THAT THE EXPOSITION THAT WAS<br />
GIVEN BY PREMIER ZHAO TOTALL\, v CONFIRMED THE ANAL. YSIS THAT I HAVE<br />
MADE. I. REFERRED TO JAFAN HERE I SAID THAT JAPAN WAS AN IMPORrANT. TRADING<br />
PARTNER OF AUSTRALIA. THAT IWELC(:? iED THE INCREASING WARMTH IN<br />
RELATIONS. SETW EEWi C. INA AND JAPANi THAT THE THREE COUNTRIES SHARED<br />
PERCEPTIONS IiN'REGARD TO THE SECURITY ISSUES OF WORTH EAST ASIA<br />
AND " OTENTIAL 1HREATS. I REFERRED. TO WHAT I HAD TO SAY ABOUTr THE<br />
JAPANESE DEFENCE POSITION AND TH-ERE WAS AN AGREEMENT BETWEEN<br />
PREMIER ZHAO AND MYSELF ON THAT ISSUE. WE ALSO SPOKE THEN FINALLY<br />
. IN RESPECT OF INTERNATIONAL MATTERS ABOUT 11400-CHINA AND<br />
KANPUCHEA I HAVE SEEN THE TRANSCRIPT OF THE MEETING THAT YOU HAD<br />
AS A RESULT OF OUR ARRANGEMENTS WITH PREMIER ZHAO. THAT STATEMENT<br />
PUTS CLEARLY THE POSITION AND AS YOU WILL SEE THERE IS A VERY LARGE:<br />
MEASURE OF AGREEMENT BETWEEN US ON THAT iSSUE.<br />
THE REST OF THE TIME AFTER-WE DEALT WITH THOSE INTERNATIONAL<br />
MATTERSs OF COURSEi WAS SPENT ON BILATERAL ISSUES. I SPOKEN OF THE:<br />
MOST IMPORTANT DEVELOPiIENT IN THAT AREA. WE CONDUCTED THESE<br />
DISCUSSIONS ON THE 3ASIS THAT THERE ALREADY EXISTS A VERY STRONG<br />
RELATIONSHIP BETWEEN OUR TWO COUNTRIES. YOU WILL KNOW THAT I HAVE<br />
SAID ON A NUMBER OF OCONiSIONS IN AUSTRALIA THAT THERE IS NOD RELATICIN-i<br />
SHIP WHICH IS HORE IMPORTANT TO US THAN OUR RELA~ lONSHIP WITP CHINA.<br />
IT IS STRONGLY BASED IN TRADE AND ECONOMIC TERNSi IN POLITICAL<br />
TERMSi IN TERMS OF CULTURAL EXCHANGES, IN TERMS OF ASS16TANCE<br />
PROVIDED IN TECHNICAL AREAS. IN REGARD TO AGRICULTUREi I CONPIRKED<br />
WITH PREMIER Zs-AO TFHAT PRIMARY INDUSTRY MINISTER KERIN WILL VISIT<br />
CHINA IN NAY AN'. D AT THAT TIME lT IS EXPECTED THAT WE WILL SIGN AN<br />
AGRICULTURAL UMB. RELLA AGP. EE 1ENT BY WHICS~ I MEAN THAT ALREADY THERE<br />
ARE A RANGE OF PROGRAMS BSTWEEN' US IN T: nE FIELD OF RESEARCH AND<br />
BIOLOGY AND OTHER AGRIC'JLYURAL PROGRAMS BETWEEN US. AND IT IS AGREED<br />
THAT IT 16 APPROPRIATE THAT THAT RANGE OF CO-OPERATlVE PROGRAnS<br />
THAT DO EXIST SHOULD BE BROUGHT rOGEYHER NOW UNDER AN OVERALIL<br />
UMBRELLA AGREEMENT WHICH WILL ALSO EMBERACE REFERENCE TO OUR INTENTIONix<br />
TO * HAVE CLOSER RELATIONS WITH THE R~ ELEVANT AUTHORITIES IN CHINA<br />
THROUGH OUR AUSTRALIAN AGRICULTURAL INTERNATIONAL RESEARCH COUNCIL.<br />
WE CONFIRMED THE INTENTION TO ADD TO TKE ALREADY EXTENSIVE CULYURAL.<br />
RELATIONS BETWEEN US-AND ALSO 1WTX FIELD OW SPORTiWO CO;. TAC-THERE<br />
! S AN ARRANGEM1ENT = OR A REGUL AR AU97R; AL: A/ CHl: Th SOCCER CO" 9EZNT </p>
<p>IN THE FIELD OF SCIENCE AND T; E ;: NOLOGY H~ CIEEEMIE ! DCT<br />
THEt--R GRAT[ ITUDE FO.' R T1HE C0--C'? ERAY1( uN THAT S A,_ REA; 1, Y 2BEEI\ ACHIEVE<br />
Ai AGAIN &gt;. iY 1 1W . ISTER FOC. R SJIENC AND. TECHNOLvGYi MR Wii-,-I<br />
BELIEVE BE VISIT'iiNG CHiNA LATER T,-4IS YEr7A R AS I THIN,\ PR( SASLV WL L<br />
BE OUR MI, 1NISTER FO() R E DU C ATIOC N, A XD OU R M1: NI ST ER FO0R A RTS AN<br />
ENIV R ONM E NT JUST ' W; ATf THA RGA V1IITF ZWILL @ E IS NOT S1E; JEC<br />
TO FINIAL ' DETERNINATICON. THF ONLY CERTAIN AS TO TliIIWIG IS THE<br />
0N I' 11V E ei EN T 1, iOE L) M R fKE R.<br />
THE CHINESE PREM1IER ALSO EXPRESSED HIS GRA TITUDE TO THE EFcFICIENCY<br />
WITH WHICH ' WEHAD ' i0VEC AF'E'-:-1S VlSi*' To US LAST APRIL TO<br />
ESTABLISH THE CHINA. ACTION! r'LAN iN THE-. FIELD OF TRAD'S ArD OF THAT<br />
OTH R ACTION PLAN. OUR DEPAR TMENT OF TRA-DE 1HAS PREPARED A VERY<br />
EXTENSIVE ANALYSIS OF POSS1* 2LE AREAS OF EXPANSION WITHIN OUR TOTAL<br />
IrIR,;: oRT PRoGRAM FOR CHINA. A VERY VERY EXTENS1IVE ANALYSIS HAS BEEN<br />
SUBMI TTED TO THE CH: LNESE: AUTHOrRITIE-S A! WrHV NDCTDTHTOC<br />
THEY HAVE AiNALYSED THAT M" ASS 0-7 ' MATE RI1AL AN HAVE: GONE TO0 PARTICULAR<br />
AREAS OF 1NTEREST TO * fHEM, WE WILL THEN UNDERTAKE NORE DETAILED<br />
MAR~ KET ANALYSIS FO! R THEM AND WI L E AN A S I SAY pp= EMI R ZA<br />
HAS EXPRESSED HIS SATISFACTION iN REGARD TO) THAT.<br />
GENERALLY, THAT', S' COVERED THE ISSUES THAT WE TfRA VEiRSED 1N MOKDRE THAN<br />
THREE HOUR* DISCUESIO: JS* TOD'AY~. T WOULD SAY IN SU IiMARY OF THE NEARLY<br />
SIX HOURS' DISCUSSIONS THAT WE'VE HAD OVER THEE TWO [ JAYS THAT THOSE:<br />
DISCUSSIONS KAVE IN A VERY REAL SENSE CONFLRIIHD THE R~ ELATIONSHIP<br />
E_: TWE2EN OUR TWO COUNT-iRIES THE STRENIGTH AND THE WARNTH OF THE<br />
REL. ATIONSHIP AND IN TERMS OF PERSONAL VISI. TS WE HAVIE EXTENjDED: AN<br />
' 10I1VITATION" TO SECRETARY-GENERAL HU HAOE. ANG AND HEHOPE THAT HE-141ILL<br />
BaL ABLE TO V152: T TO AUSTRALIA LATER THIS YEAR.<br />
I REPEAT THAT PARTICULARLY TODAY I THINK THAI POTENTIALLY FOR<br />
AUSTRALIA THE JOINT STUDY THAT 11E WILL U! ND RTAR IN REETOTH<br />
PROPOSAL F: OR THE EXPORT To CHINA OF PRIMARY PROCE: SSED PRODUCT IN<br />
THE FORM OF PIG IRON\, SLABS AND BILLETS FOR THE CHINESE IRON AND<br />
STE: EL IND USTRY IS A MATTER OF POTENTIALLY VERY GREAT ADVANTAGE<br />
TO AUSTRALIA. AND INDEED TO C H INA.<br />
J OU RNAL IST: MR HAWKE HAVE YOU ANY IDEA WHAT WI1LL BE THE SORT OF<br />
QRUANTITIES -INVOLVED AND WHAT Do YOU SEE AS THE IMPLICATIONS FOR<br />
THE' AUSTRALIAN STEEL INDUSTRY?<br />
: WE CAN'T SPECIFY QUANTITY AT T HI S STrA GE. BUT CLEARLY ' W-H-N<br />
YOU' RE TALKING ABOUT A NARKET OF THE SIZE OF CHINA AND A%<br />
COUNTRY WHICH IS G-01NG5 TO HAVE EP. IU 31NSFOR STEEL IT ITS<br />
DEVE= LOPME NT 0 ROG RAN WE C; TE NTI ALLY BE RY SUBS TANT I Al-C'AT! ES.<br />
YYO U SA Y WH A T DO ES I T N EA N F R T AA US T. RAL AN I ROIN A ND STE<br />
INDUSTRY IT It1EAX. S POTENTIALLY A VERY GREAT ANfD I WO) ULD<br />
POINT OUT THAT IT IS WHILE OF I. MPO-RTANCE TO IJ RON<br />
INDUST RY IN AUSTRALI A GEErR A'-LY OF I~ R TA NC EIWOL AL-SO' I<br />
WOULD 1USAG INE POTENTIALLY VE GREAT* S IGN I FICAN'CE Fr-IESTER<br />
AUSTRALIA IN THAT YO-. U W I LL AP PREC I-TE THAT T ERE iS IN<br />
EXISTENCE AT KWI,\ NANA A COMPLEX WHIC H PROIlDUCED ' fHE-: IT E MS TO( W HI H5 I<br />
HAV AANEDE REW HH lS CA PA-' LE OF-_-EINEG U. LI Z NTO0 PR ccIJT t11)<br />
AGAIN WITH REL. ATIVE EA S~~ W R X LTE) Y BU I<br />
ID1USTRY AND I ' WOULD SUGET O . CUR ECOrNO;, AS A W " oL E ECj SE<br />
IT IS A VERY CLEA R E XAPIPLE I NLDSAY Or-STRH IN T. NH AT 1 H; AVE<br />
BEEN TRYING TO E: XPOUND FOR SCO: 1E TIE IN AUTI I AN-ON THSTR<br />
T HAT VE H AVE TO( 1 -BE TI! A CT\, A TiVS IZ TALK'ImG AB! OU( T 11: 1W TNDU'STr1, E S<br />
AND THE D: E: VELOP1E NT OFEXIST! INQG LNL'UE. R1E&amp; L. i AAT W HE N YU T ALK_ </p>
<p>ASOUT RESTRUCTURING IT TS ANNES TO: ABOUT ? i ESY U C IUR31G<br />
TERNS OF SIMPL,, Y AS PEOIPLE HAVE TlN: DEKi TO_ OF REST 3U C T UJP IGF<br />
A' LOSS OF JCE'S. N E H AS TO) EPE V ER Y P O'S iTIV E A SCU' IH. S AND T H S 1S<br />
A STRIKING lLLUST ATIOt,, OF THE CONCEPT 1 HAT I HAVE BEEN TRYIN( 3 REALLY<br />
FOR MANY YEARS TO TALK AGOUTt THE SORT O TH1NIG ' fHAT WE ALLUDEDTO<br />
IN THE CRAWFORD REPO) RT. A ND NOW,.-I T' S A MA mfEP 0OF V E RY CONES IDE RABLE<br />
GRATI! F-l CAT IO. N To ME AS P RI r. Z I NIS T ER THA T A S A RES' OLTF<br />
T HE SE DI1S C U SSIONS tE C AN\ S EE PO() SSIB. 5L Y I N C0N C R ETlE t R11s-N oW A<br />
RE f7L EC TION T H ) S E SO) R T OF: P T SIN A STRALIA IT IS A Et-Y<br />
SPECIFIC ILLUSTRATION OF T-: E SORT OF THIN VY 1 ' E T1AEL K7Kl A:. urT<br />
THE ENMESHING OF A'US TIRA L IAiN E C O M I C DEVELOPf'ENTl INTO THE-:<br />
DEVELOPM" 1ENT OF T HIS REGIN<br />
j'OURNALITST: MiR HAW'r* E DID YOU TALK TO ANY AUSTRALIAN' COMli'PA! N Y<br />
AB~ OUT TH.: S BEFORE YOU LE,: T AND IF 14-. ICH ONE?<br />
NO I DIDN' T TALK TO0 A N, Y AUSTRALIAN COMPANIES 2Eri~ c-zEFT<br />
BUT SINCE WE HAVE L EFT AU SO L E 0 F OFF _ 7C HAVEl IN F ACT<br />
BEEN ENGAGED IN SUCH DISCUSElTONS. AD I CAN ASSURE YOUJ THA-(-T TH 1=-Y<br />
WE LCOME VERq Y ST~ THE CoINCEP r THAT I HAVE: NOW TAA EN TO TH c<br />
ST A GE WlT H TH E HI ' EE SE<br />
JOURNALIST:'*-CN A U -ILE)<br />
P. M. WELL THERE' LL BE A SZEOETBRIEF.-ING AND DR C-ARNVAUT MAY SE<br />
AEILE TO Go INTO MORE DETAILS WITH YOU ON THAT.<br />
OURNALIST: WILL THIS BE ! N ADDITION TO0 P'ROPCISALS FOR CHINA TrO Buy-<br />
MIORE IRON ORE..<br />
P. M1.: YESi IT'S A TWO-PRONGED APPROACH. TO AUSTRALIAN ASSOCIA-fTIO'N<br />
WITH THE DEVELOPMENT OF THE CHINESE IRON AND STEEL TUSTRY ANE<br />
INDEED IN THE DICUSSIONS THIS rORNING PREMIER ZRAO INDICATED T; HAT<br />
THEY WOULD WELCOME THE POSSIBILITY OF AUSTRALIAN T\ IVEFTMENT '-ERE IN<br />
CHINA IN THEIR IRON AND STEEL TNDUSTRY. SO) WE REALLV ARELOIN<br />
AT A COMPLEX, IF YOU LIKE7 OF AtU STRALIAN! RLLA* TIO&gt; S3I Ps WITrH THEF<br />
DEVELOPMENT OF. THE CHINESE IRO N AND STEEL_ iNDIJSTQV L ET;-MI. E MH AS I S<br />
THAT WHAT HAS zS'EFEN AG; R'_ ED TO IS A JOINT h1, m GiROUP STUDY C TH!-<br />
ISSUE AND THIERE WILL BE A CONS IDERAi2LE AHOUNT O.' F 7A-; TOO<br />
BE DON! E. THE PO I iT I ' M tAI NG I S THAT ON TS-FACE-T. HERE IS VERY<br />
CONSIDERABLE ADVAtN. TAGE FORl) BOTH AUSETRAI HN 4NN AICT<br />
CONCEPT TH-ROUGH TO FRUITIOr'i.<br />
J JURNAL15IT S TT RE A : LLY A GREE", l EN7T INFP R IN CI PLE OF DfO N Ul1 AND<br />
THE STUDY OR IS IT1'<br />
M O TIKTH ' CURATcE WAY TO PUT IT HIS AS I :, UT 17-<br />
I RAISED THE COINCEPT ' W-ITH PPl'IER ZHAO AN-) PU~ T'E REAS0O"! S WH'-Y<br />
T i POIN1 qT C) F VIEW OF: AUSTRALItA' AN-D F~ THE POIN~ T OF k) TN<br />
CHINA THAF 1 7 R'EPRES=-NTS A PROPOSAL OF Z R ST-Z,' 1T I AT ' UTAL<br />
NT A G AN BE NEFiT1. R~ IE ZHAOf AG REHJ O) RECEITVING! THF RO 1: A<br />
'( H-AT HE COULD SEE AT THE PRO) POSAL SUC! AA&gt; -UEAAA: V', N! DAES<br />
CCA: U SE L4' E SAW I T A5 -JR H W H IMEMCA. T L Y TO VV 7 C<br />
SETTING Ui? 0 F A JOCI 1T1 S GRtOU. 1ON THE RPS' . ADOOUv<br />
iS TH-* AT BECAUS7 i T M AIN1FE= Ec. IY DOE L! AVE A ' ATAGS I0T<br />
AUSTAL _ 7A ANK D CHI NA T AT HAVE REASON TO P~' SI 7,<br />
-OU T<br />
t; CO0ME SS-U CH A S TUD1) Y.<br />
jOURNALISTD ( INAUDIBLE) </p>
<p>THKE A NS WE R S~ E1 N EiE7 R CA N0R 1-DFE -S: RET I v! F-0S E<br />
TIMlE LltiuiT. I SIMPL' 7 SAY THISs 0JH4 ARE READY TC K.' Y.<br />
CHINA IS RICHT1 TriE ', Il[! L" TOF ITS DE~ ~~ TPRC'G7* A: FO ITS I SC j-<br />
A! ND STEELr riEVELOF~ N SO H&amp; C HT EAETH1~ RC Ifr) iL !<br />
LOOc\** NG AT A. LcN\ G PERIOD OF Tit
THESE TH TN aS HOWEVER TO NiAME SURE TH-AT YIOUF1O ALL THE : dORK TH A' S<br />
NECESSARY. AND 1 HAVE A j 7i TLNG FRO:'! THE Vz * FY PoSITIVEl= DCS; IONS<br />
THAT WE HAD ON THI! S . LSSUE7 TH-AT TH'-E CHINESE 1.4( ULD SHJAR: E THAT V! E<br />
T11HAT IS, THEY tv'OULD WANT START t. OR09K ON THE STUDY GROUP T! LTH<br />
\ JE-AR FUTURE AND THAT THEY W'. OULD APPLY TO IT THE SAIME-: IMPORTANCE, AN':;<br />
PRIORITY AS WE Di,. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
