<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8065</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA HON R J L HAWKE DELIVERED AT THE DINNER HOSTED BY M. LOUSI LE PENSEC MINISTER FOR OVERSEAS DEPARTMENTS AND TERRITORIES NOUMEA - 27 JULY 1990</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/07/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008065.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHECK AGAINST DELI. VERY EMBARGOED UINTIL, nDELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA<br />
HON R J L HAWKE<br />
DELIVERED AT THE DINNER HOSTED BY<br />
M. LOUIS LE PENSEC<br />
MINISTER FOR OVERSEAS DEPARTMNENTS<br />
AND TERRITORIES<br />
NOUMEA 27 JULY 1990<br />
At some stage every Australian ponders that great<br />
unanswerable question of French and Australian history:<br />
" What if La Perouse had arrived a few days earlier<br />
How different things would be if La Perouse had beaten<br />
Captain Cook, and if Australia had been claimed for France<br />
rather than England.<br />
One of the unintended consequences would have been that I<br />
would not have needed an interpreter for my remarks tonight.<br />
But of course, history could have taken other twists. In<br />
some accounts of the history of New Caledonia, the tragic<br />
figure of Captain Denham appears as a British version of La<br />
Perouse, failing by only a couple of days, because he had<br />
dallied in Sydney, to claim these islands for England.<br />
So perhaps an interpreter would have been necessary anyway,<br />
to allow my fluent French to be understood by my<br />
New Caledonian audience of Anglophones.<br />
Regardless of the language in which it is expressed, I trust<br />
my gratitude for the warmth of your welcome this evening,<br />
and for the generosity of your hospitality, is clear to you<br />
all. As any map of our region shows, New Caledonia forms part of<br />
the very closest circle of Australia's neighbours in the<br />
South Pacific.<br />
We stand on each other's doorsteps, with Canberra and Noumea<br />
separated by only a few hours' flying time. For someone who<br />
frequently flies greater distances without leaving<br />
Australia, let me say it is a pleasure to realise on this<br />
journey just how narrow, relatively speaking, is the stretch<br />
of water that separates us from you. </p>
<p>It was our proximity of course that, during the dark days of<br />
the Second World War, reminded Australians and New<br />
Caledonians of our vital importance to each other.<br />
That was why in 1940 exactly fifty years ago Australia<br />
opened its consulate here in Noumea: the first diplomatic<br />
post we established outside the United Kingdom and North<br />
America. It is a little remembered fact that, in September 1940,<br />
close cooperation between Australia and the Free French<br />
leader General de Gaulle led to the installation of a Free<br />
French governor in Noumea, allowing this territory to play a<br />
vital role in the Allied war effort in the Pacific.<br />
In the following year, Bob Menzies became the first<br />
Australian Prime Minister to visit these shores.<br />
Over the decades that followed, Australia and New Caledonia<br />
did not, for a number of reasons, build the close ties that<br />
the map suggests should have been automatic ties of trade,<br />
cultural exchange, and political consultation that<br />
flourished through much of the rest of the South Pacific.<br />
Until today, Bob Menzies remained the only Australian Prime<br />
Minister to visit New Caledonia.<br />
Today however we can take pride and satisfaction from the<br />
knowledge that we are opening a new chapter in the history<br />
of relations between Australia and New Caledonia.<br />
I want my visit to demonstrate a new recognition that<br />
Australia and New Caledonia have much to offer each other,<br />
and a commitment that for our part we are keen to see more<br />
opportunities emerge.<br />
We want to see more business men and women, more students,<br />
more tourists, more artists crossing and recrossing that<br />
stretch of water just like the neighbours we really are.<br />
There are two, equally important, reasons why we can look<br />
with confidence to these exciting prospects, and why I speak<br />
with confidence about the opening of new chapters.<br />
The first is the attainment here in New Caledonia of a<br />
peaceful and orderly political process under the Matignon<br />
Accords. At the outset of my visit I want to place on record the<br />
unqualified admiration of the Australian Government for the<br />
way in which New Caledonians and the French Government<br />
worked together to reach and implement these Accords.<br />
To someone with my vantage point, the peace and order that<br />
has prevailed in New Caledonia since the Matignon Accords<br />
were signed in June 1988, stand in the sharpest possible<br />
contrast to the futile, dangerous and sometimes brutal<br />
divisiveness of previous years. </p>
<p>For this triumph of common sense over senselessness, I<br />
congratulate you all. And in particular I recall the work of<br />
one of the fathers of this triumphant achievement, the late<br />
Jean-Marie Tjibaou, whose assassination last year, with<br />
Yeweine Yeweine, tragically robbed all New Caledonians of<br />
men of vision and leadership.<br />
Just as important as the process of reconciliation is its<br />
end-point: in 1998, New Caledonians will be able to choose<br />
their own future. Before Matignon, it seemed that this<br />
choice would be denied them. It hardly needs adding that<br />
Australia would have been uncomfortable with that denial.<br />
A genuine act of self-determination is necessary not only<br />
for the rights of the New Caledonian people but also for the<br />
standing of New Caledonia in the eyes of the wider Pacific<br />
community. With the Accords, New Caledonia has brought within its grasp<br />
that which it most needed but which it had previously found<br />
most elusive: a process for a peaceful transition to genuine<br />
self-determination and to a viable long-term political<br />
status. I will be speaking with the participants in the Accords<br />
tomorrow and I will make some further comments specifically<br />
to the New Caledonian community after that.<br />
Tonight, as the guest of the French Minister M. Le Pensec, I<br />
want to acknowledge the value we place on the French<br />
contribution to this achievement not least the involvement<br />
of my friend the Prime Minister Michel Rocard and Minister<br />
Le Pensec, whose personal commitment to the Matignon Accords<br />
has been a vital element in the success.<br />
Indeed, from Australia's point of view, and surely from that<br />
of New Caledonia, the political and legislative basis for<br />
the peace and progress now being enjoyed in New Caledonia is<br />
one of the great achievements of the Rocard Government.<br />
And that of course brings me to the second reason for the<br />
new chapter in Australia-New Caledonia relations: the fact<br />
that, after some difficult times, relations between<br />
Australia and France have once more attained the warmth and<br />
fruitfulness that one could expect of two nations that share<br />
so many fundamental values and aspirations.<br />
My visit to Paris last year, and the very successful return<br />
visit to Australia by M. Rocard, have confirmed that a new<br />
spirit of cooperation exists between Australia and France<br />
broad, strong, positive and productive.<br />
In the wider international sphere, we are working together<br />
in the search for peace in Cambodia, and taking the<br />
initiative in seeking to ban mining from Antarctica so that<br />
it can be preserved as a nature reserve and land of science. </p>
<p>Tonight, let me spend a few minutes reviewing how this new<br />
spirit between Australia and France is felt here in the<br />
South Pacific.<br />
Because inevitably, Australia's view of France is<br />
significantly affected by the prism of the South Pacific.<br />
This is where we are; this is where our immediate interests<br />
lie; this is where French decisions taken on the other side<br />
of the globe will impact on us and on our neighbours.<br />
No one could deny that France plays an important role<br />
cultural, economic, political in the Pacific.<br />
What has happened over the last two years is that we have<br />
seen that role not just acknowledged but, increasingly,<br />
welcomed by Australians and by all those who care for the<br />
future of this region.<br />
And the clearest proof of that tremendous transformation is<br />
here in New Caledonia.<br />
To anyone who might question whether France can play a<br />
legitimate and constructive role in the Pacific, I now say:<br />
look at its role in the Matignon Accords.<br />
And indeed, one can point to a positive French role in wider<br />
Pacific issues.<br />
Last August, Prime Minister Rocard and I declared our<br />
intention of working together on combatting the barbaric<br />
practice of driftnet fishing reflecting the concerns that<br />
had been expressed by the South Pacific Forum nations in the<br />
Tarawa Declaration.<br />
With the recent decision by Japan not to deploy driftnet<br />
fishing vessels in the South Pacific in the coming season,<br />
we are entitled to derive some collective satisfaction that<br />
the Pacific view is gaining force.<br />
I was pleased to see the statement of M. Rocard that<br />
France's Pacific territories should develop closer links<br />
with other South Pacific countries.<br />
For Australia's part, we remain very keen to expand our<br />
trade with New Caledonia and with the other French Pacific<br />
territories. I hope this visit will remind New Caledonians that Australia<br />
is a competitive supplier for many of the goods needed here<br />
but that artificial trade barriers impede our capacity to<br />
supply them, with consequent costs to the average consumer<br />
here. Of course, there remain areas on which Australia and France<br />
have firm differences. </p>
<p>Australia has opposed the French program of nuclear testing<br />
and we will continue to protest against each test.<br />
Put quite simply, there is no single decision France could<br />
take that would lift its reputation higher throughout this<br />
part of the world than to support the South Pacific Nuclear<br />
Free Zone.<br />
At the wider international level, Australia also has severe<br />
disagreements with France and its fellow members of the EC<br />
over the folly of agricultural protectionism an issue that<br />
must, if we are not to threaten the entire structure of<br />
world trade, be resolved in the current round of<br />
Multilateral Trade Negotiations.<br />
This is not some peripheral issue for my country but one<br />
which is central to the health of our economy.<br />
Such issues aside, the scope of cooperation between France<br />
and Australia is expanding steadily, and I want it to go on<br />
expanding. I am confident that is a shared objective.<br />
We are finding an identity of view and a commonality of<br />
purpose that promises many positive outcomes in the future.<br />
It is our genuine desire that the sort of practical<br />
cooperation that has marked our relationship over the past<br />
two years here in the Pacific and more widely will<br />
continue to diversify and to grow stronger.<br />
So I certainly trust that New Caledonians won't have to wait<br />
another fifty years for a third visit by an Australian Prime<br />
Minister. I thank you for your generous hospitality and for<br />
the warmth of your welcome. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
