<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>22487</transcript-id>
    <title>New Chemotherapy Equipment for Victoria&#039;s Northern Hospital  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/09/2006</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Cancer patients in regional areas north of Melbourne will have access to chemotherapy equipment at the Northern Hospital for the first time as a result of community fund raising efforts supported by the Australian Government.</p>
<p> I am pleased to announce today a contribution of $200,000 towards the community fund that will enable the purchase of chemotherapy equipment for the Northern Hospital in Epping.</p>
<p> With this equipment in place, cancer patients living in regional areas north of Melbourne will no longer have to travel into the city to have chemotherapy treatment. Currently local cancer sufferers undergo specialist procedures at the Northern Hospital but then have to go somewhere else for chemotherapy.</p>
<p>  This funding will enable cancer patients to receive treatment closer to home which reduces the trauma caused by long journeys for patients and their families</p>
<p>By the age of 75, one in three men and one in four women will be diagnosed with cancer.  For those who live in rural and regional Australia, treatment often involves regular and long journeys into a capital city for specialist medical attention.</p>
<p>This initiative is part of the Australian Government's ongoing commitment to improve the health of Australians.</p>
<p>I congratulate the Chemotherapy at the Northern - Day Oncology (CANDO) group and the local residents, businesses and organisations for the fund raising they have undertaken to improve cancer treatment for regional Victoria.  </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
