<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8786</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PAUL KEATING, MP THE RT HON SIR PAUL HASLUCK KG, KCMG, GCVO</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/01/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008786.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
T1EL1: . Jan. 93 15: 16 No. 013 P. 01/ 01<br />
4/ 93<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PAUL KEATING, MP<br />
THE RT HON SIR PAUL HASLUCK KG, KCMG, GCVO<br />
The death of Sir Paul HagluCk is a sad moment in the life<br />
of this nation.<br />
Few Australians this century have had more distinguished<br />
careers. Few have made more profound and permanent<br />
contributions. As a member of the Liberal/ Country Party government from<br />
1949-1969 Sir Paul held a number of high ministerial<br />
offices, including, from 1964 to 1969, External Affairs.<br />
As Governor-eera from 1969 to 1974 he carried out his<br />
duti-es wih in-tegrity, dignity and complete impartiality.<br />
While he is best remembered for the roles he played in<br />
Australian public life, his contribution to the writing<br />
of our history and our understanding of Australia's place<br />
in the world was no less cons~ iderable.<br />
He wrote on subjects as various as international<br />
relations and the Aborigines of Western Australia. He<br />
wrote a two volume history of Australia in the Second<br />
World War and a splendid memoir called Mguing4IaQq4 He<br />
wrote always with a deep respect for our institutions,<br />
our history and for the people of Australia.<br />
Towards the end of his autobiography Sir Paul wrote that<br />
one of the guiding influences on his life had been the<br />
words of Montaigne: " I care not so much what I am in the<br />
opinion of others as what I am in my own."<br />
He shunned praise in life, but with his passing it can be<br />
said with certainty that in the opinion of his fellow<br />
Australians he gave great service to this country and<br />
that his unique contribution will be lasting and long<br />
remembered. on behalf of the Government I extend my deepest sympathy<br />
to Lady Hasluck and her family.<br />
CANBERRA 11 January 1993 TEL </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
