<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10675</transcript-id>
    <title>16 August 1998                                 TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                  THE HON. JOHN HOWARD MP                  TELEVISION INTERVIEW WITH PAUL LYNEHAM                60 MINUTES, CHANNEL 9</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/08/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE....................................................................................................</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>I would think it's gone down well for the first few days but</p>
<p>   you haven't got a sort of huge bounce have you  there's</p>
<p>   not conga lines of enthusiastic people in the streets of suburban</p>
<p>   Australia are there?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I must say, in Adelaide yesterday a lot of people stopped</p>
<p>   me  a lot of elderly people stopped me outside the Commonwealth</p>
<p>   Bank  and said that it was a good plan, people were honking</p>
<p>   their car horns a bit. Look, I wasn't the boss when Fightback</p>
<p>   was released so I can't compare it, a different situation.</p>
<p>   But I'm very reassured by the response.</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>But even after John Hewson hammered away for months, many people</p>
<p>   still didn't understand some of the basic concepts.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, John Hewson was a long way in front for a long time. It was</p>
<p>   only towards the end that he lost.</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>Then it says: here's what's in it for you, doesn't</p>
<p>   this sound a bit like a sales pitch as much as an explanation from</p>
<p>   your Government and should we, the taxpayers, be paying for that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Paul, people want to know what's in this plan. I mean, you</p>
<p>   can't, on the one hand, say, oh look, it's complicated</p>
<p>   and then criticise us for trying to make it simple.</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>But if the Liberal Party wants to sell it to them prior to an election,</p>
<p>   shouldn't the Liberal Party foot the bill for the sales pitch?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>There's no election been called. It has long been the case</p>
<p>   that if a government announces a new policy, a new plan, it provides</p>
<p>   basic information. If the material contained an attack on the Labor</p>
<p>   Party, it would be a different matter, your criticism would have</p>
<p>   more point.</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>So, you're saying this isn't all now occurring in a pre-election</p>
<p>   context?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Paul, no election has been called. I have not decided when the</p>
<p>   election will be.</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>Would you like to rule out an October election, for example?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I'm not ruling anything in or out. I'm accepting regular</p>
<p>   dinner engagements right through the coming months.</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>We had 120 uncommitted voters who were very, very positive as they</p>
<p>   heard your Address to the Nation but, in the end, a majority of</p>
<p>   them said they weren't buying what you were selling. Does that</p>
<p>   concern you?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, there'll be a plethora of polls and surveys between now</p>
<p>   and whenever the judgement day may be, politically speaking, and</p>
<p>   I believe we'll end up selling this to the Australian public.</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>So the sell goes on?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Sure does.</p>
<p>[Ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
