<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11530</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER            THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP            RADIO INTERVIEW &amp;#150; COUNTRYHOUR, ABC RADIO                     SUBJECTS: Rural trip; primary industries; taxation reform; job providers;             Government services; Telstra; water; infrastructure.</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/02/2000</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE....................................................................................................</p>
<p>DANIEL:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, thanks very much for joining us today.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>You are very welcome Zoe.</p>
<p>DANIEL:</p>
<p>What exactly have you learnt from your tour?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I have learnt that the regions contain some very good stories and a lot</p>
<p> of optimism as well as quite a deal of despair and a very genuine situation</p>
<p> of ongoing difficulty for many of our basic industries.</p>
<p>So I have had reinforced some views I already had but I have learnt a</p>
<p> great deal more. There's clearly a great interest in the regions</p>
<p> about the maintenance of Government services. I have found, generally</p>
<p> speaking, there's quite a lot of support for tax reform. I haven't</p>
<p> encountered any deep-seated hostility to the tax reform plan, put aside</p>
<p> the organised demonstrations which are not really an expression of mainstream</p>
<p> opinion. I have actually found that there's quite deep understanding</p>
<p> of tax reform. People in the regions appreciate that fuel will be cheaper.</p>
<p> They understand that it's a big plan and it's not just a goods</p>
<p> and services tax. So I have been quite pleasantly surprised at the level</p>
<p> of support for tax reform in the regions.</p>
<p>DANIEL:</p>
<p>You mentioned the despair that you did get a sense of in some places.</p>
<p> What was that related to specifically?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It's really related to the traditional primary industries. Areas</p>
<p> that have relied historically on wool and wheat and beef and dairy are</p>
<p> doing it very hard. Not everybody in those areas are doing it hard, there</p>
<p> are still very successful people in all of those areas. But they are the</p>
<p> communities that are doing it hardest and that's really the toughest</p>
<p> problem because no government can do anything about international commodity</p>
<p> prices. We've been campaigning for 25 years to get a better deal</p>
<p> on the trade front. We've made a lot of progress but, gee, we still</p>
<p> have a long way to go and the Europeans and the Americans still continue</p>
<p> to clobber us. They're much bigger than we are and they still continue</p>
<p> to have a pretty indifferent attitude to agricultural exporters such as</p>
<p> Australia. We are intensely disappointed at the Seattle outcomes. We don't</p>
<p> think there was enough leadership displayed there and we are going to</p>
<p> continue to persevere on the world trade front but it's still very</p>
<p> front.</p>
<p>DANIEL:</p>
<p>There's been much comment around in the press and the electronic</p>
<p> media about how you were received. How did you feel that you were received</p>
<p> by country people?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I was received in a very friendly way by country people, there's</p>
<p> no doubt about that. There were the usual organised demonstrations from</p>
<p> the usual suspects but they didn't really speak on behalf of country</p>
<p> people. But those people who received me with their normal courtesy and</p>
<p> friendliness a number of them also put their point of view and expressed</p>
<p> their concerns. But it was an immensely valuable exercise and people do</p>
<p> appreciate their leaders, their Prime Minister coming to them. It is important</p>
<p> to spend large blocks of time - not just a flying visit - with some kind</p>
<p> of patronising, symbolic gesture but genuine blocks of time travelling</p>
<p> around the regions and getting to understand them. And also having reinforced</p>
<p> the fact that regional Australia's very diverse. There's the</p>
<p> genuine bush with small communities, there's the coastal towns, many</p>
<p> of them such as Port Lincoln are doing very well, others not so well.</p>
<p> And then there are the large sponge or hub cities such as Dubbo which</p>
<p> again have different challenges.</p>
<p>So the big investment of time that I made in travelling around, and I'll</p>
<p> be doing it again in other parts of the country, was very valuable.</p>
<p>DANIEL:</p>
<p>You made an undertaking earlier this week that you are planning on putting</p>
<p> a floor on the withdrawal of Government services. How are you planning</p>
<p> on enforcing that on departments and also across State boundaries?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I am talking about Commonwealth services. I can't be accountable</p>
<p> for State government services. And one of the things that I have told</p>
<p> audience after audience is that they should make the three levels of government</p>
<p> accountable for the things that they provide and not allow one level of</p>
<p> government to say: well, I can't do that because another level of</p>
<p> government is not doing its part. I'll be held accountable for Commonwealth</p>
<p> Government services. I am writing to all of my Ministers in effect instituting</p>
<p> a red light system that if a decision is likely to result in a diminution</p>
<p> of service that's not to say you mightn't change the way the</p>
<p> service is being delivered then it oughtn't to occur.</p>
<p>DANIEL:</p>
<p>Closing the stable door after the horse has bolted though isn't</p>
<p> it?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, it's not because there are a number of areas where we are, in</p>
<p> fact, increasing service provision to the bush. I was in Maclean yesterday</p>
<p> and was able to point out that for the very first time in the town's</p>
<p> history it would have a job network provider. It had never had a CES office,</p>
<p> it had never had any assistance under the first tender round of the Job</p>
<p> Network but under the second tender round it will have a job provider.</p>
<p>DANIEL:</p>
<p>Given the seriousness with which you took the issues when you were travelling,</p>
<p> why was it necessary to bring up the concept of tying the further sale</p>
<p> of Telstra to rural infrastructure?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I didn't tie the further sale of Telstra to the expenditure</p>
<p> of any further money on rural infrastructure. There will be more money</p>
<p> spent on rural infrastructure even if we don't sell the final...we</p>
<p> can't get Parliament's approval to sell the final part of Telstra.</p>
<p> The point I was making was that if we were able to sell the final part</p>
<p> of Telstra we'd be in a position to provide more by way of infrastructure</p>
<p> support because we would have paid off our Commonwealth Government net</p>
<p> debt and we'd have a stronger fiscal base on which to undertake at</p>
<p> an accelerated rate further expenditure on infrastructure. So I thought</p>
<p> it was very necessary to do that. I am a great believer in these situations</p>
<p> of laying everything out on the table and not taking, as it were, the</p>
<p> easer option and just engaging in a public relations exercise. And I found</p>
<p> in the bush, although there are still a lot of people who are sceptical,</p>
<p> a growing recognition that maybe it isn't sensible to tie up tens</p>
<p> of billions of dollars in a telecommunications company and perhaps it's</p>
<p> better to invest that money in additional infrastructure at an earlier</p>
<p> date. I also made it clear in my discussions that any further sale of</p>
<p> Telstra will be absolutely conditional on it being demonstrated to the</p>
<p> Government's satisfaction that Telstra had met its community service</p>
<p> obligations and we are going to investigate that in a benchmarking study</p>
<p> that will be commencing shortly.</p>
<p>DANIEL:</p>
<p>Could I put it to you that by even mentioning though the possibility</p>
<p> that the sale of Telstra would lead to increased infrastructure funding</p>
<p> that that somehow cheapened the goodwill that you'd created by embarking</p>
<p> on this regional tour in the first place?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, I don't think it has. I think it's had, in fact, the opposite</p>
<p> effect.</p>
<p>DANIEL:</p>
<p>What evidence do you have to demonstrate that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, just the reaction of people. I did not find as much opposition</p>
<p> to the sale of the final part of Telstra as I expected. I found a good</p>
<p> deal but there are quite a lot of people on the other hand. For example,</p>
<p> the Mayor of Dubbo, Mr Peacocke, said: look if you can demonstrate that</p>
<p> the community service obligations are being met then there's some</p>
<p> merit in the proposal. Others have a different view but it wasn't</p>
<p> the hostile bone of contention that your question implies.</p>
<p>DANIEL:</p>
<p>Speaking of guarantees and speaking of funding being directed to rural</p>
<p> Australia, the Regional Australia Summit steering committee will soon</p>
<p> report to the Government with its recommendations. What funding and resources</p>
<p> has the Government set aside to implement hose recommendations?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well that's something we'll consider in the lead up to the</p>
<p> budget in the normal way. I'm not, quite deliberately I'm not</p>
<p> going to make funding commitments on the run. We'll get the report</p>
<p> of that committee. I will have as a background to the consideration of</p>
<p> that report, I will have the experience of my weeklong visit to regional</p>
<p> Australia. I'll therefore be far better prepared to take sensible</p>
<p> decisions on what we ought to do. But the level of any funding and where</p>
<p> it's going to go is something that we'll be deciding in the</p>
<p> normal way and that process starts very soon. So we'll be looking</p>
<p> at that matter quite soon.</p>
<p>DANIEL:</p>
<p>Interestingly the steering committee's already put out a document</p>
<p> looking at the possibility of a vision statement, a more long term strategy</p>
<p> for rural Australia for the next say five to ten years. Would you consider</p>
<p> that sort of thing as an option to set a more long term agenda for rural</p>
<p> Australia that won't get changed as government's change?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well you can't ever guarantee that policy won't change when</p>
<p> there's a change of government. That's just unrealistic. We</p>
<p> can't control what any future government will do any more than the</p>
<p> previous government could control what we've done. But I'm not</p>
<p> against some long-term statement. People however in the end, while statements</p>
<p> may be nice, they really want practical decisions that provide them with</p>
<p> identifiable assistance or incentives. But again we've got to keep</p>
<p> in mind that there are a lot of good news stories in the regions. A number</p>
<p> of the centres I mentioned are doing well. A number of the centres I visited,</p>
<p> I visited such as Bourke have turned their situation around and have now</p>
<p> built thriving alternative industries. So it's not just unrelieved</p>
<p> gloom. There's a lot of brightness on the horizon. And there are</p>
<p> a lot of areas of very strong economic activity in the regions. But it</p>
<p> varies. Once again it's really the areas that have been very heavily</p>
<p> dependent on the traditional commodities, areas that have been most badly</p>
<p> affected.</p>
<p>DANIEL:</p>
<p>One of the other things that's been put up, Mr Howard, is the possibility</p>
<p> of an actual legislated bill of rights for rural Australia. Is that something</p>
<p> that's completely out of the question [inaudible]?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well nobody raised it with me.</p>
<p>DANIEL:</p>
<p>So does that mean you don't think it's a possibility?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No I'm just saying that it's the first time anybody's</p>
<p> put it to me. You're the first person that's ever raised it</p>
<p> with me.</p>
<p>DANIEL:</p>
<p>Right. Well it's been raised with me before.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well you know, I can only answer honestly. I've spent a week travelling</p>
<p> around the regions and I have met literally hundreds, indeed perhaps thousands</p>
<p> of people and at no stage has anybody said the answer to our problem is</p>
<p> to have a bill of rights. It doesn't sound to me as though it's</p>
<p> come out of the heart of the bush.</p>
<p>DANIEL:</p>
<p>Well that's probably your opinion.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, well that's the only opinion I can give you. You've asked</p>
<p> me a question, I've given you an honest response. Nobody has raised</p>
<p> it with me.</p>
<p>DANIEL:</p>
<p>Fair enough. One of the other issues that you've brought as being</p>
<p> significant in your tour was water use and water sustainability. What</p>
<p> sort of plans is the Government able to make on that front because salinity</p>
<p> is certainly probably one of the prime issues that rural Australia is</p>
<p> facing at the moment.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes salinity is a huge issue although even there you get a mixture of</p>
<p> views. Some people put very strongly the view to me in Bourke that some</p>
<p> of the impacts of salinity have been exaggerated by some. I got a very</p>
<p> different view in South Australia. We have a responsibility to work with</p>
<p> the State governments to try and get a fair outcome. It's a very</p>
<p> big issue in Australia - water, very big issue. I hope the States adopt</p>
<p> a sophisticated mature approach and don't just say I'm from</p>
<p> New South Wales and to hell with rest of the country, or I'm from</p>
<p> South Australia and the same. We really do have to have a bit of give</p>
<p> an take on this issue and that I guess is where the national government</p>
<p> comes in and I'll try and do that.</p>
<p>DANIEL:</p>
<p>One of the things I'm trying to get a sense of, and please don't</p>
<p> think that I'm trying to be smart, is what sort of long-term plans</p>
<p> can be put in place not only by government but also with consultation</p>
<p> with rural communities on these sorts of things  environmental planning,</p>
<p> the vision statements for rural Australia, social responsibility. Is it</p>
<p> time that these things were looked at with a little more long term vision</p>
<p> rather than just looking ahead to the end of the term of the current government?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well that is already happening in these communities as far as social</p>
<p> problems are concerned. I didn't think in Bourke for example in relation</p>
<p> to the relations between Aborigines and other Australians. I didn't</p>
<p> think you needed a long-term vision statement. I thought you needed a</p>
<p> continuation of the spirit of tackling the problem as a community. If</p>
<p> that were to go on then I think you had the basis of providing some long</p>
<p> term solutions. What did impress me in a lot of areas was the way in which</p>
<p> problems were being tackled by the whole community. I deliberately avoided</p>
<p> separate meetings with interest groups. I met interest groups as part</p>
<p> of an aggregate community and you get a far more genuine community based</p>
<p> response if you do that. I am a great believer that the Australian public</p>
<p> has a capacity to challenge and solve social problems if only the different</p>
<p> interest groups would work together and not see themselves as bargaining</p>
<p> with each other for a share of the outcome.</p>
<p>DANIEL:</p>
<p>Can people in the country look forward to the coming budget do you think?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well people in the country are now living in a nation whose general economic</p>
<p> settings are very strong. I kept pointing out to people as I went around</p>
<p> that at a national level our economy has rarely been stronger and that</p>
<p> the reform programs of the government, particularly in the area of taxation,</p>
<p> will bring major benefits for the entire economy including the rural economy.</p>
<p> So I don't think we should be fixated on what this or that budget</p>
<p> will deliver, although there are obviously particular measures that will</p>
<p> be considered in the lead up to the budget. Economic policy is more than</p>
<p> the annual budget. Economic policy is the aggregate way in which you handle</p>
<p> the national economy.</p>
<p>DANIEL:</p>
<p>You said you'll take another tour soon. Have you planned it yet?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No I haven't planned it yet. But I don't want people in other</p>
<p> parts of Australia to think that they're going to be neglected, but</p>
<p> then I haven't neglected it. Last year I undertook a number of trips</p>
<p> to rural Victoria extending over a couple of days. I don't think</p>
<p> I've undertaken a trip which has been as long as this in one block</p>
<p> of time. But I'll be visiting the other States and I'll be going</p>
<p> to other regions in other parts of Australia to get their views and to</p>
<p> do essentially what I've done. And no doubt I'll encounter organised</p>
<p> demonstrations there from the usual suspects and once again they won't</p>
<p> represent mainstream opinion.</p>
<p>DANIEL:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, thanks for talking with us.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Thanks a lot.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
