<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6836</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/02/1986</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006836.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA 10 February 1986<br />
Federal Cabinet today agreed on action to assist the people of<br />
Queensland affected by Cyclone Winifred which devastated large<br />
areas of the North Queensland coastline a week ago.<br />
The Government received today a report from the Minister for<br />
Primary Industry, Mr Kerin, on his inspection of the damage<br />
arising from Cyclone Winifred and on his discussions with local<br />
Government officials, cane and banana growers and community<br />
groups. Cabinet also had available a report on discussions held last<br />
Friday between Commonwealth and Queensland officers which<br />
considered the particular circumstances of the cyclone damaged<br />
area. The officials discussed the arrangements that might be put in<br />
place, and in particular discussed the operation of the<br />
Commonwealth/ State Natural Disasters Relief Arrangements.<br />
At this stage the full impact and extent of damage and hardship<br />
is not available to either the Queensland or the Federal<br />
Government and it has been agreed that further consultations will<br />
be held when more information comes to hand.<br />
Under the new Natural Disaster Arrangements introduced on 1 July<br />
1985, and agreed to by the States, Queensland meets the first<br />
$ 10.48 million of expenditure in 1985/ 86. Since the Queensland<br />
Government has already spent more than this amount on natural<br />
disaster relief this year, further payments will be shared<br />
equally by the Commonwealth and Queensland Governments for the<br />
next $ 7.86 million of assistance. Thereafter the Commonwealth<br />
will fund three quarters of additional expenditure. In the<br />
circumstances it is expected that the Commonwealth will be<br />
meeting at least 50 per cent of the total disaster relief<br />
assistance in Queensland during 1985/ 86.<br />
In addition to this the Government has agreed that funds will<br />
also be provided to various local Councils through the<br />
Commonwealth element of the Community Employment Program for a<br />
Cylcone Winifred Special Area Rehabilitation Project. The<br />
Project, to be sponsored by the minister for Local Government and<br />
Administrative Services will aim to assist in the restoration and<br />
improvement of public parks and gardens, and at the same time,<br />
provide employment opportunities for the long term unemployed and<br />
other disadvantaged job seekers in the area. </p>
<p>2<br />
To provide practical help to the two Shire most severely<br />
affected, Johnstone and Cardwell Shires, we have arranged under<br />
my Government's Local Government Development Program for Mr<br />
Duncan Beggs, the City Engineer from Darwin, to be available for<br />
several weeks at Commonwealth expense to help organise clean up<br />
and reconstruction work. He was responsible for rehabilitation<br />
in the aftermath of Cyclone Tracy, and provided excpert assistance<br />
after Cyclones Gretel and max in Northern Australia and the<br />
Macedon bushfires in Victoria. As well as providing immediate<br />
assistance in the Shires, the visiting expert will advise on<br />
longer term strategies.<br />
The Prime minister also commended the establishment of a national<br />
appeal for victims of Cyclone Winifred and said that under the<br />
income tax law donations of over $ 2.00 to a public fund for the<br />
relief of cyclone victims in need, would be an eligible tax<br />
deduction. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
