<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7291</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/02/1988</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007291.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA 17 FEBRUARY 1988<br />
The Structural Adjustment Committee of Cabinet met today<br />
with the principal players in Australia's waterfront<br />
industry. The reduction of shore-_ based shipping costs is<br />
crucial to Australia's international competitiveness, and a<br />
central element in the Government's general economic reform<br />
strategy.<br />
Thirteen Ministers, including all the senior economic<br />
Ministers, attended the two hour meeting with participants<br />
in the Government's Waterfront Strategy group, who between<br />
them represent the full spectrum of importers, exporters,<br />
port managers, stevedoring companies and the waterfront<br />
unions. The Committee received full reports on the progress that has<br />
been achieved over the fifteen months since the Strategy<br />
process was set in train. While it was acknowledged that<br />
there continue to be real problems on the waterfront, in<br />
port administration and in linkages with land transport, it<br />
was made clear that very real progress had already been<br />
achieved, including:<br />
successful second tier wage negotiations under the<br />
co-ordination of the Stevedoring Industry Review<br />
Committee, involving for the first time port by port<br />
discussions and agreements leading to significant<br />
improvements in work and management practices,<br />
reductions in manning and other efficiency measures;<br />
implementation of productivity based container packing<br />
operations at depots in Melbourne and Sydney;<br />
joint venture initiatives by the waterside Workers<br />
Federation at small ports in Queensland, Victoria and<br />
Tasmania which in some cases have halved the cost of<br />
stevedoring of grain and other cargoes; and<br />
improvements in truck-queuing and related problems.<br />
The Committee was impressed with the general degree of<br />
optimism that was expressed by the industry representatives,<br />
all of whom expressed confidence in the possibility of<br />
achieving significant improv ements in waterfront and port<br />
efficiency, productivity and reliability. 004445 </p>
<p>All of the industry representatives emphasised the<br />
importance of continuing with the present process of<br />
extensive consultations with both users and providers of<br />
port stevedoring services, under the umbrella guidance of<br />
the Inter-State Commission. A draft report is expected from<br />
the Commission in July, which will outline the possible<br />
elements of the major package of industry reform measures.<br />
On the industrial relations front while problems still<br />
remain, it was recognised by all parties that significant<br />
progress has occurred in recent years and, further, that all<br />
parties are committed to further improvements within the<br />
framework of the Waterfront Strategy and bilateral<br />
arrangements like the Stevedoring Industry Review Committee.<br />
The Government will continue to liaise very closely with the<br />
Waterfront Strategy group through the Minister for Transport<br />
and Communications. Ministers were impressed by the evident<br />
commitment of all parties and their willingness to work<br />
co-operatively to achieve change. Accordingly there is a<br />
firm basis for hope that the consultative processes that<br />
have been set in train should result not only in the<br />
resolution of a number of smaller obstacles to efficiency<br />
along the way, but the achievement by the end of the year of<br />
a broad package of measures that will achieve industry,<br />
trade union and Government acceptance.<br />
Attending the meeting with ministers were:<br />
Sir John Moore, Chairman of the Stevedoring Industry<br />
Review Committee<br />
Mr Ted Butcher, President of the Inter-State Commission<br />
Mr Ivan Deveson, Managing Director, Nissan Australia and<br />
Chairman of the Importer/ Exporter Panel<br />
Mr Ian Webber, Managing Director, Mayne Nickless, and<br />
Chairman of the Industry Committee of the Waterfront<br />
Strategy group<br />
Mr John Jenkin, President of the Association of<br />
Australian Ports and Marine Authorities<br />
Mr Tas Bull, General Secretary of the Waterside Workers<br />
Fede ration<br />
Mr Colin Coventry, Executive Director of the Association<br />
of Employers of Waterside Labour, and<br />
Mr Ian Court, Industrial officer, ACTU 004446 </p>
<p>Industry Committee<br />
Committee will Oversee working parties comprising<br />
representatives drawn from<br />
transport opertars<br />
stevedoring companies<br />
freight forwarders<br />
unions importer%/ exporters<br />
port authorities<br />
other government agencies<br />
Role a To bring action to bear on day-to<br />
Inhibiting efficiency particulorl,<br />
arrangements and co-ordination be<br />
various elements of the industry.<br />
Importer/ Exparter Panel<br />
Membership Representatives of major importer<br />
of rural, mining and manufacturin<br />
Role To bring forward for consideratioi<br />
committees and the ISC Issues caum<br />
or Increasing costs to Importers<br />
To liaise with committees on the<br />
made on considering Issues and pri<br />
solutions to overcome problems fa4 SHORE BASED SHIPPING STRATEGY.<br />
Inter-Stato Commission<br />
Role Oversee and report to Goverameat as progress<br />
of the Committees.<br />
Assist the Committees and the panel developing<br />
solutions to problems.<br />
Develop comprehensive'data bae to allow<br />
Iefficiency of the Industry to be assessed.<br />
Draw up long term integrated plan for development<br />
of the Industry. Stevedorina Industry Review Committee<br />
Mambe rs<br />
Association of Employers of Waterside Labour<br />
Waterside Workers' federation of Australia<br />
Australian Stevedores' Association<br />
Australian Foreman Stevedores' Association<br />
Federated Miscellaneous Workers' Union of<br />
Australia<br />
-Australian Council of Trade Unions<br />
Role To consider all aspects of Improving efficiency<br />
-day problems and productivity in the stevedoring Industry.<br />
y Communication a To Implement changes to management and work<br />
tween the practices as necessary to achieve Improved<br />
efficiency.<br />
Australi1an Transport Advisory Council's Standing<br />
Camrtte Transport<br />
and exporters Members<br />
ggoods federal and State Transport and Marine Officials<br />
aby other<br />
sing problems<br />
and exporters.<br />
progress being<br />
opos ing<br />
cod by shippers. RoleC a To oversee action being undertaken on port and<br />
rail matters. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
