<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>898</transcript-id>
    <title>PACIFIC AREA TRAVEL ASSOCIATION 13TH ANNUAL CONFERENCE, MARCH 2-6, 1964 - KEYNOTE ADDRESS BY THE RT. HON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES, KT, CH, QC, MP, PRIME MINISTER OF THE COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/03/1964</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000898_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
IL A. 1<br />
Pacific Area Travel Association<br />
13th Annual Conference<br />
March 2-6, 1964 KEYNOTE ADDRESS<br />
by The Rt. Hon. Sir Robert Menzies, M. P.,<br />
Prime Minister of the Common-ealth of Australia.<br />
Well, Sir, Ladies and Gentlemen, they say that confession is good<br />
for the soul. I wiant'to admit at once that I don't know just what<br />
a " Keynote Address" is. I think this is an importation from the<br />
United States of America, but I don't mind declaring the Conference<br />
open. There I amn on the home ground as you might say. Of course,<br />
it is a very pleasant occasion for me because when I look around<br />
and I remember all the notes I have read and everything that the<br />
Trade Department has told me, I realise that I ari looking at a<br />
group of people, mary of whom might be regarded as invisible<br />
exports, and I like this very much.<br />
Since 1957, apart from the fact that I have been re-elected a<br />
couple of times once rather faintly the most exciting thing<br />
is that in 1957 the estimate of income earned in Australia from<br />
tourist trade was œ 6 million, that is to say external money coming<br />
in, and today it is œ 27 million. Now, of course, to some of you<br />
who may come from larger countries that may not be any great matter,<br />
but I venture to say that in 1957, wie were hardly contemplating<br />
although you, Mr. Bates, were always the greatest of optimists such<br />
a great expansion in this period of time. Of course, this is just<br />
the beginning of it. I wonder why our figure was so small in 1957,<br />
and of course very much smaller before that almost non-ezistent.<br />
WThy was it? Was it because Australia had nothing to show? ' VIell,<br />
no Australian w--ill admit that. You know that this is a land of<br />
infinite variety. You have already experienced the glittering<br />
sunshine of Melbourne and now you are experiencing the overcast<br />
inftry skies of Sydney, so wie are a land of infinite variety.<br />
17o have so much to show. Scenery, yes, masses of it, an immnense<br />
variety. Every country is different from c-very other one and we do<br />
not always realise there is some particular attraction for people<br />
who come from the green landscapes of some of the counties of the<br />
Old Country or Nev Zealand quite a pleasant change for them to see<br />
the rather burnt, dry, yellow;, pastel shaded sweeps of country that<br />
you find in many parts of Australia.<br />
Variety is literally, from that point of view, the spice of life.<br />
But I do not believe th. a: t the only thing to see, to meet, to<br />
encounter, is the scenery. Primarily it is the people, and what<br />
they are like, and what they do. And wie are all different people.<br />
Many of us speak English, of a kind. And many of us do not. But<br />
the differences of language, I think, tend to fall away a little<br />
and people do manage to get to know each other. And I think if I<br />
may offer a complete truism that nothing could be more remarkable<br />
than the impact on the ordinary mind, of a visit to another country and<br />
of moving around even for a few days or a few weeks, among other<br />
people, sensing the atmosphere of the place, getting an impression of<br />
what people are really likie, and above all, discovering that they<br />
are all human beings.<br />
This century of ours has been disfigured by prejudice and hatred<br />
more than any other century, I believe, en record, far exceeding<br />
in these things the iorst period of the Midile Ages. There is no<br />
cure for prejudice half as good as getting to know the person or<br />
race, or commnunity about which you have been prejudiced. / Now </p>
<p>II. A. 2<br />
CONFERENCE<br />
THE PT. HON. SIR ROBERT 1NZIES. M. P.<br />
Now, Mr. Bates, the Chairman of this Conference, is of oourse the<br />
embodiment of the tourist industry. He has been the head of the<br />
Australian National Travol Association to which I assure him I came<br />
well prepared to pay the warmest tribute. Indeed vie have been<br />
paying tribute to him for years. I would be saying far less than I<br />
should if I did not say that, in my opinion, and in the opinion of<br />
the Government, the Australian National Travel Association is doing<br />
magnificent wiork, and very glad I am to say that although only a<br />
few years ago a lot of business people in Australia who I would have<br />
expected to have 1anoun something of the significance of tourism<br />
were rather indifferent to the needs, some conspicuous. But I am<br />
delighted to find that since 1957, the number of private contributors<br />
to tho travel association here has increased five times.<br />
This is something that we are all in. There is a bit of a disposition<br />
in my ovm country I knoi-w it doesn't exist in any of yours to t. ake<br />
things to the Government in prayer, and say well why doesn't the<br />
Government do something about it, and there are many things about<br />
which the Governm-ent ought to do a great deal, but a motter of this<br />
kind requires, in the highest degree, the co-operation of Government<br />
and private industry, and for one very great reason. This is :. n<br />
industry. This is a commonplace remark, but it is almost<br />
revolutionary in my country to regard the tourist trade as an industry.<br />
I have to go around Australia a good deal and rcceive requests of<br />
one kind or another, and you would be surprised to kniow how frequently<br />
one finds that people, ahen they speak of wanting an industry in their<br />
State or in their community, wiant something that has a factory<br />
connected with it, something that has chimney stacks, something that<br />
has great lorries running round taking in materials and taking out<br />
the finished product. This is the popular idea of what an industry<br />
is, yet here we have an industry -, hich at present produces in real<br />
terms from my own country as invisible exports the ninth largest<br />
amount among the major export industries. It will stand very much<br />
higher in the list as more and more iwe get to understand the<br />
tremendous importcence of it.<br />
There are areas in Australia w.-here the tourist trade, if it were<br />
even more understood than it is now, could be a very great industry<br />
and that trade could be developed out of sight, by better roads<br />
and accommodation.<br />
All this, I believe, is improving. But it will need to go on<br />
improving and it will go on improving so long as the people who<br />
provide accommodation a. nd facilities and transport in the receiving<br />
country understand that this is one of the great national industries,<br />
and that they must contribute to it by skill and good management,<br />
and good capital provision, just as much as they would when they<br />
established some modern factory to produce electronics or some other<br />
modemn device. This is a matter of broad understanding, and so of<br />
course you have a Conference of this kind, magnificently representative<br />
of the countries around the Pacific, and you are here to encourage<br />
tourism, to encourage it in every direction, particularly in your<br />
area. I hope that nobody will fall to the comfortable and social<br />
temptation, to be ever-polite to each other in a Conference of this<br />
kind. The developments of tourism in the world, and particularly<br />
in these newer parts of the world, as vie see ourselves, is dependent<br />
upon hearty criticism. / Let us </p>
<p>II. A. 3<br />
CONFERENCE<br />
THE RT. HON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES, M. P.<br />
Let us, in Australia let all the people who exe here who are<br />
Australians who have some contact with some aspect of' the tourist<br />
business understand what is wrong. They will tell you vha-t is<br />
right. You need not worry about tha~ t. But you must tell them %-. hat<br />
is wirong. Because there was a good deal wrong once; there is a<br />
good deal wrong now, but it would be a miracle if there were not<br />
still plenty of' ways in which we could improve our capacity to<br />
roceive and deal with and entertain tourists.<br />
When people go around the world, eaither on business, which I believe<br />
some do, or on pleasure, which I believe some do, or on business<br />
and pleasure, which I am sure a great number of' people do, they<br />
are consciously or unconsciously doing something much needed in this<br />
century. First of' all, they are extending the boundaries of' their<br />
o,: m knowledge of' other people. I have said something about that,<br />
and by extending those boundaries, they are breaking dovam some of' the<br />
prejudcies and hatreds that have disfigured our tine. And in the second<br />
place, they are extending the borders of economic co-operation with<br />
other countries. W.. hen somebody from Japan comes over here to buy wool,<br />
or somebody from Australia goes to Japan to buy some textiles, they<br />
would bhoth think it rather pompous to be told they were extending the<br />
boundaries of' economic co-operation between the tw,, o countries.<br />
One says, " I em here to buy wool", and the other says, " Well, I am~<br />
here to buy textiles". But as they are intelligent people, and<br />
I assume that they are, they will realise tha t what they are doing<br />
is dealing with one facet of a whole complex of' an economic co-operation<br />
between two nations two-way trade. All the economic and financial<br />
considerations that are involved, in two-way trade, and this of' course<br />
is a tremendously valuable thing where people have business dealings<br />
together, where everything has become completely normal in their<br />
context, where they have learned to trust each other, and have had<br />
years of' honourable dealing with each other, the chances of'<br />
hostilities between them, I believe, are sensibly diminished<br />
and therefore this trade which I shall call the tourist trade for this<br />
purpose is of' tremendous importance as a. remover of sources of<br />
international friction. Similarly, on the political side, suppose<br />
you have somebody who visits another country in the Pacific area,<br />
with all sorts of preconceived ideas. He may be there purely on a<br />
holiday but he has time to move around to see people, to do a Little<br />
reading about what goes on if he has the language of the country<br />
that he goes to to acquire some friendships, to find out wrhat the<br />
local man thinks about the local man which is always so important<br />
and he comes backc even after a relatively brief' journey with his<br />
mind enriched. There is one thing that must be said about all of<br />
as when we travel ( unless it is exclusively on business) one thing to<br />
be said about us when wie get homie vie are not silent about where rie<br />
have been. I have yet to meet a taciturn tourist, and now that we all<br />
have expensive cameras, the tourist goes and he sees and records<br />
and he comes back ( and in this case " he" includes " she") and in due course<br />
we tell our neighbours and vie tell our friends about it so<br />
incessantly that run serious risks of' losing their friendship.<br />
This is a secondary effect of travel. Not only does the tourist<br />
himself' learn something and have something to remember, but other<br />
people through them will learn something and will want to go and want<br />
to see for themselves.<br />
Now this is in our time, I believe, a. magnificent social international<br />
revolution. Nothing better could be going on, socially, politically,<br />
economically. All this travel that you are encouraging for which<br />
so many of your constituent members are providing all of' this is<br />
I believe one of' the civilising influences in the modern world.<br />
Allen I </p>
<p>II. A. 4<br />
CONFERENCE THE RT. HON. SIR ROBERT TENWZIES, M. P.<br />
V. hen I was a snail boy it was considered a phenomnnal thing for<br />
anybody to move into another state on a visit. V. e were parochial,<br />
but today with all the facilities of transport, with all the<br />
revolution that has gone on, assuming we can pay the fare, we have<br />
no excuse for riot travelling. The average man and woman today is<br />
immeasureably better able to pay for some travel than their<br />
grandparents ever thought of being. Therefore there is opportunity,<br />
Pand in the case of our ovm country, thousands and thousands of<br />
people coming in, and thousands and thousands of people going out,<br />
all engaged, whether they realise it or not, in this ameliorative<br />
work in relation to our contacts with other countries.<br />
This is a Conference of enormous importance. The industry will<br />
continue more and more to produce these great results if there is<br />
more and more and more co-operation between all those particular<br />
segments which go to make up this complex or to serve it-, and<br />
governmcnts, more and more co-operation, more and more understanding,<br />
and ( above all) more and more completely frank criticism of what<br />
we see . nd what goes on.<br />
I hope that from this Conference as from all the others you have<br />
had you will, on the basis of a riost frank examination of<br />
what goes wrong here or there, come out with an improved organisation,<br />
with an improved prospect of serving the people, because first<br />
and last let it be remembered that this is not just a source of pleasure,<br />
Sir, in declaring the Conference open. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
