<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8688</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ KEATING, MP NATIONAL COMPETITION POLICY REVIEW</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/10/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008688.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL: 6. Oct. 92 12: 51 No. 011 P. 02/ 06<br />
PRIME MINISTER 110/ 92<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
NATIONAL COMPETITION POLICY REVIEW<br />
I have today established a major independent inquiry into competition policy in Australia<br />
with specific emphasis on areas currently outside the Commonwealth Trade Practices Act.<br />
The inquiry will be chaired by Professor Fred Hilmcr, Dean of the Australian Graduate<br />
School of Management in the University of New South Wales; Mr Geoff Taperell, a<br />
partner in the law firm of Baker McKenzie; and Mr Mark Rayner, Group Executive,<br />
CRA Ltd.<br />
This inquiry is an important step in continuing the vital task of micro economic reform in<br />
Australia. It will examine a number of significant axmas of economic activity not now<br />
subject to competition policy, such as many government instrumentalities and the<br />
professions. I have asked the Review team to cover issues including:<br />
the best means of providing consistent, nationally applicable competition rules to<br />
allbusijLesses-in Australia regardless of ownership or corporate status<br />
transitional mechanisms necessary to bring businesses currently outside the scope<br />
of national competition rules within those rules.<br />
potential improvements to the Commonwealth Trade Practices Act in the new<br />
environment of conietition-law to be recommended by the Review; changes to<br />
related legislation, for example in relation to prices or consumer interests; and the<br />
legal environment in which the Trade Practices Act is applied. </p>
<p>T6EL. O: ct. 92 12: 51 No. 011 P. 03/ 06<br />
2<br />
Clearly the review and its recommendations will have major implications for the States<br />
and Territories as well as the Commonwealth. As a rcsult, I and my Department have<br />
consulted closely with the Premiers and State officials as well as with the Attorney-<br />
General,, the Treasurer, and other relevant Ministers. The terms of reference attached have<br />
been developed in consultation with the States. The principles outlined in the terms of<br />
reference provide a very solid basis for the Review and were agreed at an earlier stage by<br />
the Premiers and Chief Ministers. The membership of the Review team has also been the<br />
subject of close consultation.<br />
I have asked Professor 1-ilmer and his colleagues to undertake as a matter of priority<br />
discussions with States and Territories. I have today written to State and Territory leaders<br />
suggesting that Professor Hiliner is available to see them as soon as practical.<br />
I am aware that the Review has thc strong support of the Business Council of Australia<br />
and I believe other busiess groups also support the concept of consistent national<br />
competition rules applicable to all parties in a market. The Review will shortly call for<br />
Submissions and I ask these groups, and other interested partics, to put forward their views<br />
as soon as possible.<br />
Thc review is to report to me in May 1993. Premiers, Chief Ministers and I[ will consider<br />
its findings prior to public release.<br />
CANBERRA 4 OCTrOBER 1992 TEL </p>
<p>TEL: 6. Oct. 92 12: 51 No. 011 P. 04/ Ub<br />
REVIEW OF THE APPLICATION OF THE TRADE PRACTICES ACT 1974 TO<br />
MATTERS CURRENTLY OUTSIDE ITS SCOPE<br />
1. 1, Paul John Keatingo Prime Minister of the<br />
Commonwealth of Australia, having regard to the agreement<br />
between myself and the Premiers of the States of New South<br />
Wales, Queensland, South Australia, Tasmania, Victoria and<br />
Western Australia and the Chief Ministers of the Australian<br />
Capital Territory and the Northern Territory that national<br />
competition policy and law should give effect to the<br />
following principles:<br />
no participant in the market should be able to engage<br />
in anti-competitive conduct against the public<br />
interest; as far as possible, universal and uniformly applied<br />
rules of market conduct should apply to all market<br />
participants regardless of the form of business<br />
ownership; conduct with anti-competitive potential said to be in<br />
the public interest should be assessed by an<br />
appropriate transparent assessment process, with<br />
provision for review, to demionstrate the nature and<br />
incidence of the public costs and benefits claimed;<br />
any changes to the coverage or nature of competition<br />
policy should be consistent with, and support, the<br />
general thrust of reforms:<br />
to develop an open, integrated domestic market for<br />
goods and services by removing unnecessary barriers to<br />
trade and competition; and<br />
( ii) in recognition of the increasingly national<br />
operation of markets, to reduce complexity and<br />
eliminate administrative duplication;<br />
appoint Professor Fred Hilmer to Chair the Committee of<br />
Review of the Application of the Trade Practices Act 1974,<br />
and Mr Geoff Taperell and Mr Mark Rayner as the other two<br />
Committee members.<br />
2. The Committee is to inquire into, and advise on<br />
appropriate changes to legislation and other measures in<br />
relation to: </p>
<p>TEL 2<br />
whether the scope of the Trade Practices Act 1974<br />
should be expanded to deal effectively with anticompetitive<br />
conduct of persons or enterprises in areas<br />
of business currently outside the scope of the Act;<br />
alternative means for addressing market behaviour and<br />
structure currently outside the scope of the Trade<br />
Practtces Act 1974; and<br />
other matters directly related to the application of<br />
the principles above.<br />
3. in conducting the review the Committee should consider,<br />
against the background of the nature of markets in Australia<br />
and influences upon them:<br />
whether the authorisation and exemption provisions of<br />
the Trade Practices Act 1974 have sufficient scope,<br />
flexibility and transparency;<br />
the need for, and approaches to, the transition of<br />
government regulatory arrangements -including any<br />
associated revenue impact on States -to more<br />
competitive and nationally consistent structures;<br />
the best structure for regulation including price<br />
regulation, in support of:<br />
pro-competitive conduct by government business and<br />
trading enterprises and in areas currently outside the<br />
scope of the Trade Practices Act 1974; and<br />
( ii) the interests of consumers and users of goods and<br />
services; and<br />
the past and present Justification for the current<br />
exemptions from application of the TPA.<br />
4. In performing its functions, the Committee is to:<br />
take into account:<br />
the principles stated in paragraphs 1( a) to ( d)<br />
inclusive; ( ii) legislation other than the Trade Practices Act and<br />
other arrangements that affect market behaviour and<br />
structure; and TL: 6. Oct. 92 12: 51 No. 011 P. Ut)/ Uu </p>
<p>TEL 3<br />
( 111) the fact that some government business and<br />
trading enterprises may operate in industries having<br />
aspects, including pricing, of natural monopoly; and<br />
( iv) current moves to reform government trading<br />
enterprises; and<br />
overseas experience.<br />
take written submissions; and<br />
consult interested parties where necessary.<br />
The Committee is to report to me by May 1993.<br />
6.0ct. 92 12: 51 No. Oll P. 06/ 06 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
