<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8669</transcript-id>
    <title>THE HONOURABLE PAUL KEATING PRIME MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA AND HIS EXCELLENCY MR KIICHI MIYAZAWA PRIME MINISTER OF JAPAN</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/09/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008669.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
/ 0/<br />
THE HONOURABLE PAUL KEATING<br />
PRIME MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA<br />
and<br />
HIS EXCELLENCY MR KUICHI MIYAZAWA<br />
PRIME MINISTER OF JAPAN<br />
JOINT PRESS STATEMENT ON ASIA-PACIFIC PERSPECTIVES<br />
At their meeting today Prime Ministers Keating and Miyazawa affirmed<br />
the value of theAustralia-Japan relationship and their confidence in the future<br />
benefits it will bring to both countries and to the Asia-Pacific region._<br />
2. A major theme of the discussion at the meeting was shared recognition<br />
of the momentous changes in the Asia-Pacific region following the end of the<br />
ColdWar. The two leaders noted especially that new opportunities and<br />
c hallenges also derive from the continuing dynamism of Asia-Pacific<br />
economies and increasing moves towards regional t rading arrangements. They<br />
confirmed their resolve to address the changes now unfolding in the region<br />
from a long-term perspective, and in ways that further promote the cooperative<br />
relations that have been nurtured so far in the region. They reaffirmed their<br />
readiness to cooperate jointly with other Asia-Pacific nations in the furtherance<br />
of peace and prosperity in the region.<br />
3. The two Prime Ministers reiterated the view of their Governments that<br />
the engagement of the United States is of fundamental importance to the peace<br />
and prosperity of the Asia-Pacific region, with the presence of US forces ' in the<br />
Western Pacific serving as a stabilising factor. They noted that the respective<br />
defence relationships of Australia and Japan with the United States, including<br />
Japan's substantial host-nation support for US forces, made a significant<br />
contribution to regional stability.<br />
4. The two leaders affirmed that Australia and Japan are resolved to<br />
cooperate where feasible in the resolution of regional issues of conflict. Prime<br />
Minister Keating supported a more active Japanese international role and<br />
welcomed Japan's decision to participate inUnited Nations peace-keing<br />
activities. The two Prime Ministers reaffirmeid their'fu* lsupport for the role<br />
played by the United Nations in Cambodia. They confirmed that Australia and<br />
Japan would continue to cooperate closely in efforts to move the peace process<br />
forward. </p>
<p>They welcomed the improved diplomatic environment on and<br />
surrounding the Korean peninsula,_ and expressed hope for a further reduction<br />
of tension. They underlined their grave concern about North Korea's suspected<br />
nuclear weapons _ program, and insisted on the necessity of the full<br />
implementation of the IAEA Safeguards Agreement and of an effective<br />
bilateral inspection regime.<br />
6. Prime Ministers Keating and Miyazawa welcomed the valuable<br />
contribution of the Association of South-East Asian Nations ( ASEAN)<br />
towards regional cooperation. They noted the growing significance of the<br />
ASEAN Post-Ministerial Conference process as a forum for dialogue on<br />
regional security. They supported regional security dialogue in order to<br />
improve mutual reassurance and stability, while recognising the importance of<br />
existing sub-regional approaches for the resolution of specific disputes.<br />
7. In discussing the outlook for the world economy and the implications for<br />
the Australian and Japanese national economies, they noted that the Asia-<br />
Pacific region contains some of the fastest growing economies in the world,<br />
and * that its future prosperity would depend significantly on trade growth. They<br />
also recognised that the region's economic success to date dem-onstrated the<br />
benefits of the globalisation of economic activity through worldwide<br />
integration of trade, investment and technology.<br />
8. The two leaders reaffirmed the fundamental importance Australia and<br />
Japan attach to the maintenance of an open, non-discriminatory, multilateral<br />
trade systemq. They accorded priority to an early and successful conclusion of<br />
the Uruguay Round, which will provide a significant and needed boost to the<br />
world economy. They noted that a balanced outcome was within reach,<br />
involving positive results for industrial and agricultural products, rule-making<br />
areas, and new areas such as services. They stressed that a demonstration of<br />
political will by all participants will be needed if these benefits for the world<br />
economy are to be realised in good time.<br />
9. In noting the increasing trend towards regional trading arrangements, the<br />
two leaders emphasised the view of their Governments that such arrangements<br />
should be open and consistent with GATT and other international obligations,<br />
and should contribute to expansion of the world economy without adversely<br />
affecting the interests of third countries in trade and other areas.<br />
Both Prime Ministers reaffirmed their support for Asia-Pacific<br />
Economic Cooperation ( APf~ g _ as an essential mechanism for open regional<br />
economic cooperation. They also reaffirmed their intention to continue<br />
promoting its role in the liberalisation of trade. </p>
<p>11. The two Prime Ministers discussed the need for international and<br />
regional institutions to reflect better the growing weight of the Asia-Pacific<br />
region in world affairs. They called for increased attention to Asia-Pacific<br />
issues at the annual G7 economic summits. Prime Minister Keating briefed<br />
Prime Minister Miyazawa on the reactions so far of other regional leaders to his<br />
proposal for establishing over the medium term a process of periodic headsof-<br />
government meetings based on APEC membership. Prime Minister<br />
Miyazawa said he regarded the proposal as very significant in view of the<br />
rapidly changing international environment and the increasing importance of<br />
the region. He welcomed Australia's initiative and agreed that the idea be<br />
pursued further in consultation with other members of the region. Prime<br />
Minister Keating affirmed Australia's support for Japan's permanent<br />
membership of the United Nations Security Council so as to have the United<br />
Nations better reflect changed international circumstances.<br />
Tokyo 21 September 1992 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
