<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8808</transcript-id>
    <title>SOUTH AUSTRALIA</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/02/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008808.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
4. Feb. 93 11: 17 No. 02' 0 P. 01<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
SOUTH AUSTRALIA<br />
All Australians at present should be thinking about which political party has the best<br />
policies for Australia.<br />
It is fair to say that South Australians have good reason to be thinking more deeply than<br />
most. South Australia has some great strengths, including some of Australia's best industries<br />
industries with excellent prospects for expansion both domestically and overseas.<br />
However, South Australia has problems which the rest of Australia does not face and these<br />
have to be addressed.<br />
I do not say this lightly.<br />
It is the reason why I have taken the opportunity to talk about South Australia and its<br />
future.<br />
Unless these problems are addressed properly, this State faces an uncertain future,<br />
regardless of what happens elsewhere in Australia.<br />
South Australia's additional problems stem from two principal causes.<br />
First, its relatively narrow cconomic base has made it difficult to respond to the forces of<br />
structural change.<br />
This has been a problem bedevilling South Australia for the past two decades.<br />
Since 1978 Australian employment has risen by 28 per cent.<br />
Employmecnt in South Australia has risen by 15 per cent.<br />
TEL: </p>
<p>TEL: 4. Feb .93 11 : 17 tNz). 020 P'. 02/<br />
2<br />
Unfortunately for South Australia, many of Australia's expanding industries have tended<br />
to be located elsewhere.<br />
Queensland's employment has risen by 53 per cent Over the same period.<br />
Western Australia's by 44 per cent.<br />
The second cause of South Australia's additional misfortune is more recent and relates to<br />
the State Bank.<br />
I don't want to revisit all the traumia associated with that sorry debacle.<br />
When John Bannon told me back in January 1991 of the losses of the State Bank it<br />
seemed such an utter waste of public resources.<br />
On that occasion, like many pcoplc I am sure, I fclt an immediate contempt for those who<br />
managcd it.<br />
Since then the losses in the State Bank have proved to be much larger than those that John<br />
Bannon was made aware of in January 1991.<br />
With the latest conimitmcnt of $ 850 million in the 1992-93 S1atc Budget the total amount<br />
of assistance to the State Bank now stands at $ 3.15 billion.<br />
This has imposed an enormious cost on thc State's public finances.<br />
Inevitably it has restricted the State Government's ability to respond to the rcccision.<br />
Nct public debt is now around $ 8.25 billion in South Australia, nearly 30 per cent of Gross<br />
State Product, after having been around 15 per cent as recently as 1990.<br />
Interest payments will take up 15 per cent of State revenue in 1992-93 even though<br />
interest rates are much lower.<br />
The drain on State resources of the State Bank is immense.<br />
It may bc of a similar dollar amount as thc losscs in SB3V and Tricontinental, but the<br />
revenuc base of the State of Victoria is more than 3 times larger.<br />
And while Jeff Kennett is approaching the task wvith minimal finesse and maximum<br />
disruption, Victoria does have scope to put its financial house in order.<br />
The South Australian Government, on the other hand, ran a tight fiscal ship in the 1980s<br />
and, apart from the State Bank, enjoyed a wcll-carned reputation as responsible fiscal<br />
managers. </p>
<p>TEL: 4. Feb. 93 11: 17 No. 0<br />
3<br />
This is good news in one scnse, as the State in terms of its recurrent budgets has been well<br />
managed, but the bad news is that there is little fat in the South Australian budget to carry<br />
the State Bank.<br />
The State Bank's difficulties have sapped community and business confidence which has<br />
added to South Australia's problems.<br />
All of this has meant that the recession which has hit Australia badly has hit South<br />
Australia particularly heavily.<br />
Between July 1990 and Decmbcr 1992 employment in Australia fell by about 3 1/ 2 per<br />
cent. In South Australia, the peak to trough fall was 5.1 per cent.<br />
To get some perspective on how the recession has had a differing regional impact<br />
employment in Wcstcrn Australia fell by well less than average at 1.7 per cent, while<br />
employment in Queensland actually rose by 2.4 pc ccnt over the same period.<br />
In thinking about the future, all South Australians should take as their starting point the<br />
narrowness of the industrial base of the State and the financial burden of the State Bank.<br />
But this is not the end of the stor)'.<br />
South Australians should also recognise that two other potential calamitics hang over their<br />
hcads. They will come care of Dr Ifewson and a Coalition Govcrnment if that misfortune were<br />
ever to happen.<br />
The first casualty would be South Australia's car companies.<br />
For Dr Hcw'son's election would mcan an immediate and sharp setback for the car<br />
industry. With two of Australia's car companies located in Adclaide that would be grim news for<br />
South Australia.<br />
Twenty thousand jobs would immediatcly be at risk.<br />
Dr Hcwson's commitment to negligible tariffs by the y'ear 2000 and zero thereafter would<br />
stall the investment plans of both GMH and Mitsubishi.<br />
With excess car capacity all around the world, ncither GMIH nor Mitsubishi is going to be<br />
willing to commit new resources to Adelaide if the long run viability of the car industry in<br />
this country is made so unccrtain with zero tariffs. </p>
<p>TEL: 4. Feb. 9? 3 11: 17 No. 020 P. 04/:<br />
4<br />
No car company is going to invest in Adelaide in the naive hope that Dr Hcwson's GST<br />
will magically enable them to compete.<br />
This is what the car companies have been saying and South Australians should heed their<br />
warnings. But the potential problem is worse than that.<br />
It is not just the car companies themselves that arc at risk from Dr Hewson's zero tariffs.<br />
South Australia could well lose the impetus of the component industry as well.<br />
The component industry is now operating at a tariff of 15 per cent. Over the last 5 years<br />
these manufacturers have seen their tariff come back from 35 per cent, 25 per cent or<br />
per cent to this level.<br />
The important point is that under the Government's Car Plan these component<br />
manufacturers will continue with a 15 per cent tariff from here on.<br />
Under Dr Hlewson this tariff would be reduced to zero.<br />
This sector of industry holds out great promise for South Australia with a number of key<br />
companies already successful in manufacturing and exporting.<br />
This is where Adelaide's future lies: building successful internationally-competitive,<br />
export-oriented industries such as the motor vehicle component industry.<br />
But as the component companies all Stress, they need the 15 per cent tariff and export<br />
facilitation to make it all work.<br />
Without such support the component industry is nowhere.<br />
And unfortunately so is Adelaide.<br />
This city will be denied the opportunity of building new industries and new export<br />
markets in one of the key areas where Adelaide has expertise and has had recent success.<br />
And these successes arc real.<br />
Britax Rainsfords, for example, have doubled its sales over the past three years through<br />
export success. Half of its sales now go offshore. ROHI Industries, Castalluy and Clyde<br />
Apac are all small to medium size component companies who have built up successful<br />
businesses through exporting.<br />
The second great danger for South Australia is less obvious. </p>
<p>TEL: 4. Feb .93 11 : 17 No .02O<br />
But just like zero tariffs and the automotive Industry, it too has the potential to deal South<br />
Australia another body blow.<br />
Here I am talking about fiscal cqualisation the method by which Commonwealth<br />
payments to the States arc distributcd in a way that benefits the smaller States.<br />
It sounds complex, but when it is explained it has very disturbIng implications for South<br />
Australia. In 1992-93 the Commonwealth will maike financial assistance grants to the States of<br />
$ 17.3 billion.<br />
Ilhcsc will be distributed amongst the States in a complicated fashion designed to even up<br />
the fiscal disabilities faced by somc Statecs.<br />
South Australia is a winner from this process to the tunc of $ 385 million in 1992-93.<br />
In fact, over recent years the two largest States have become increasingly strident about<br />
thc supposed burden upon their finances brought about by fiscal equalisation.<br />
Victoria in particular has challenged the whole bañ sis of fiscal cqualisation, on the grounds<br />
that it was originally designed as the quid pro quo that Victoria had to pay because of the<br />
cost of the tariff to thc States which do not have a manufacturing base.<br />
According to the Victorians, as the tariff declines in importance so too should fiscal<br />
equal isat ion.<br />
The very real risk for South Australia is that a iewvson Government will accede to<br />
pressure from his Liberal counterparts, Fahey in Sydney and Kennett in Melbourne, and<br />
start the process of winding back~ fiscal equalisat ion.<br />
Fahey and Kennett may already have an understanding from H-cwson that he will look<br />
sympathetically at their claimsh.<br />
This spells massive problems for a South Australian budget already staggering under the<br />
burden of the State Batik.<br />
The State Batik is costing the South Australian budget about $ 280 million every year and<br />
the burden of that cost is obv-ious.<br />
Any further loss coming from thc phasing out of the $ 385 million of fiscal cqualisation<br />
money would do enormous damage to South Australia.<br />
Dr Hewson will of course say that he has no intention of removing fiscal equalisation.<br />
South Australians have to ask can you trust him? </p>
<p>TEL: 4. Feb. 93 11: 17 No. C2C P.. 2 1<br />
6<br />
Can you trust him when Fahey and Kennett will be on his back with their fiscal problems?<br />
And can you trust him when he is philosophically opposed to notions of burden sharing?<br />
He believes in straight per capita funding no allowance for evening up.<br />
It would be a very brave South Australian who puts his trust in Dr Hcwson, and who<br />
believes that Dr Hewson will fight for South Australia's fiscal rights at the expense of the<br />
fiscal position of John Fahey and Jeff Kcnnett.<br />
The obvious question to all of this is what can South Australia cxpect from a re-elected<br />
Keating Govcrnment?<br />
What would a Keating Govermcnt do for South Australia and how would it help South<br />
Australia overcome its special difficulties?<br />
There are no magic solutions but there arc things that can and should be done.<br />
We will ensure that the Australian economy continues to strengthen and grow.<br />
We will work to build new industries and forge the necessary links with the Asia Pacific<br />
to generate jobs and exports.<br />
But South Australia needs more than this.<br />
The unfortunate reality is that even in a national rccovcry South Australia can bc left with<br />
its particular problems.<br />
It will still have to deal with its narrow industrial base and the need to build new industries<br />
and strengthen old ones.<br />
it will still have to absorb the Statc Bank losses.<br />
The simple truth is that this can only be done with Federal assistance.<br />
" rhc choice for South Australians is who will do this more sympathetically and effectively<br />
a Keating Labor Government or a Hcwson Coalition Government?<br />
Would Dr Hewson find additional Commonwealth funds for South Australia when he Is<br />
committed, as he is, to a 5 per cent cut to general purpose payments to the States and to<br />
total cuts to Commonwealth outlays of $ 9.4 billion?<br />
Would Dr Hewson commilttd, as he is, to the doctrine of ' restructure or perish', find the<br />
resources to help South Australian industry restructure? </p>
<p>TEL: 4. FeL). 9. 11: 17 No C:_) P. 07;<br />
7<br />
Would Dr Hewson committed, as he ist, o the doctrine of non-intervention intervene for<br />
South Australia?<br />
When the same question is asked of the Keating Governmcnt, the record is perhaps more<br />
eloquent than any claims.<br />
For a start the Government for a decade has supported fiscal equalisation to help the<br />
smaller states including South Australia.<br />
The Government has also been prepared to take active measures to build new industries in<br />
South Australia in recognition of the particular difficulties facing that State.<br />
And we will do morc in the future.<br />
That is why we argued that the Australian Submarine Corporation be based in Osborne. It<br />
now supports about 1200 jobs in South Australia and will inject some $ 1.8 billion into the<br />
local economy over the 14 year construction period.<br />
It will also crcatc a viable Australian ship building capability into the 21st century,<br />
The Commonwealth has allocated over $ 50 million towards the cstablishmcnt of the MF:<br />
and is pleased to bc associated with this important projcet.<br />
The Commonwealth has also agrccd to:<br />
build a standard gauge railway from Adclaide to Mclbourne linking South<br />
Australia more into the eastern states economy<br />
upgrade AN's Islington and Port Augusta workshops, at a cost of $ 7.9 million; and<br />
refurbish the Indian Pacific, at a cost of $ 12 million.<br />
On the roads front, the Commonwealth has providcd:<br />
$ 35.8 million in 1992-93 for major arterial road projects including reconstruction<br />
of South Road, the Salisbury Highway extcnsion, and the Western Gawler Bypass;<br />
$ 27.3 million in 1992-93 for local roads as part of South Australia's general<br />
purpose assistance allocation; and<br />
$ 12.9 million under the three year Urban Public Transport program.<br />
The Commonwealth has also assisted the wine industry through the Export Market<br />
Development Grant scheme which has been used successfully by several wine exporters in<br />
recent ), ears, and th e. stablishmcnt of the Co-operative Research Centre for Viticulture<br />
which will receive $ 12.4 million in Commonwealth funding over seven ycars. </p>
<p>TEL: 4. Feb. 93 11: 17 No. C200 P. O.<br />
8<br />
South Australia will receive up to $ 69 million over the five years 1991-92 to 1995-96<br />
under this Government's Building Better Cities Program.<br />
This Program supports strategics designed to bring about effective and interactive urban<br />
development and redevelopment in three areas Elizabetlh/ Munno Para, the MFP core<br />
Site/ North West Crescent, and the Inner West of Adelaide. A southern area strategy is also<br />
under consideration by the Commonwealth.<br />
In the Elizabcth/ Munno Para area, for instance, Commonwealth funds arc being used to<br />
encourage home ownership, create a more efficient city centre, Improve the housing stock<br />
and better the physical environment through stormwater management and tree planting<br />
programs. The key point is that Dr Hcwson in Fightback I is committed to abolish all of this.<br />
South Australia fared very well out of the Commonwealth Local Capital Works Program,<br />
relative to its proportion of the population, receiving $ 35.4 million ( over 10 per cent).<br />
Among the areas to receive funding were:<br />
S Northern Adelaide ($ 12.0 million) including Salisbury, Elizabeth and Gawler;<br />
S Western Adelaide million) including Port Adelaide, Woodville and West<br />
Torrcn. s;<br />
Noarlunga million);<br />
S the inner urban municipalities of Adelaide, Prospect and Glcnclg ( each between<br />
million and $ 1 million) and<br />
Whyalla, Port Pirie and Port Augusta ( again each between $ 0.5 million and $ 1<br />
million).<br />
South Australia has also successfully hid for several of the co-operative research centres<br />
the Commonwealth has partly funded under the CRC program.<br />
In all, eleven centres have activities based in South Australia, of which four are fully<br />
based in South Australia:<br />
S the CRC for viticulture I discussed earlier. This centre will concentrate on<br />
improving the production of grapes with minimum chemical residues, and<br />
developing techniques to process grapes with the minimum use of preservatives; </p>
<p>TEL: 4 Feb .93 11 : 1I No . CC F09,<br />
9<br />
the CRC for sensor Signal and information processing. The rcscarch covers signal<br />
processing technologies, principally for nmicrowave and high frequency radar.<br />
Commonwealth funding is $ 12.4 million over sev en years;<br />
the CRC for tissue growth and repair to advance the manufacture and testing of<br />
bloactivc proteins. C'ommronwealth funding is $ 10.2 million over seven years.<br />
Dr Hewson will abolish most of these programs and the fu. ture of all of them is in doubt.<br />
A Keatinig U ibor Government will sit down with the SoL~ h Australian Government after<br />
the Federal election and help them deal with their fiscal problems and stabilise South<br />
Australia's debt.<br />
For a start, South Australia should sellI the State Ba3nk.<br />
This is a view that I put to John Bannon and I know is sh3red by Lynn Arnold.<br />
To assist this a Keating Government will negotiate tax COMPI] eSatiOn for South Australia<br />
in return for the gain to Commronwealth reve-nucs.<br />
Indeed, discussions between our twvo Govcnmcnts are already underway. Compensation<br />
will be negotiated on the basis of current arrangcmcnts.<br />
Lynn Arnold is committed to helping South Australia restructure and I believe he has the<br />
strength and courage ( o do it.<br />
I am prepared to lend him cvcry possible assistance in this.<br />
A Keating Govcrncnt remains committed to fiscal cquiisatioll as an1 appropriate and fair<br />
means of distributing, Commonwealth grants to thc Stts.<br />
A Keating Government believes in an Australian car induistry and will not sacrifice a<br />
major South Australian industry in the narrow pursuit of zero tarilffs and the level playing<br />
field. In fact this Government believes in working wvith industry, providing a helping hand<br />
where it is warranted to build a new industry or to expand an existing one.<br />
Much ha3S been done already and nmore will bc done in the near future.<br />
The problems for South Australia are bY no means insurmountable.<br />
There arc signs of a pick-up in thc South Australian economly and after thc debilitation of<br />
recent years attitudes sem to be growing mnorc positive. For this Premier Arnold descrvcs<br />
credit. </p>
<p>TEL: 4 Fe-No 0 PF'.<br />
Since its trough in May 1992 employment in South Australia has been steadily improving<br />
and has now risen by 1.0 per cent.<br />
Much of this appears to be due to a strengthening of the car IndustrY in South Australia.<br />
I am confident that South Australians can turn their State around.<br />
They need the opportunity and the assistance to build new industries, to generate thc<br />
income to deal with their problems and create jobs.<br />
South Australians have done it hard over recent years.<br />
Today I would ask them to think. carefully about which of the political partics will stand<br />
by South Australia and its essential industries in the years ahead.<br />
ADELAIDE/ CANBERRA<br />
4 February 1993 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
