<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9895</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP SPEECH A THE LUNCH HOSTED BY NEVILLE NEWELL MP, TWIN TOWNS SERVICES CLUB, TWEED HEADS, 20 DECEMBER 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/12/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009895.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
SPEECH AT THE LUNCH HOSTED BY NEVILLE NEWELL MP,<br />
TWIN TOWNS SERVICES CLUB, TWEED HEADS, 20 DECEMBER 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
Well we are going to run a little quiz. Why do you think we are here? You<br />
guessed it. We are here for the thing that Neville [ Newell] and Harry [ Woods]<br />
and Bob [ Home] have been on our backs now for about three years and that<br />
is the Pacific Highway. And it is, of course, the major civics works project of<br />
the East Coast of Australia and it has been in its current state the major<br />
inhibitor to development and, of course, the cause of so many deaths.<br />
Now we have reached a point in our history where we are now as a<br />
Commonwealth Government doing things with the States. We have<br />
recognised, all of us, that the responsibilities to the nation, the communities,<br />
the regions, go beyond anyone's sphere of Government. And in the Council<br />
of Australian Governments, we have put together a tri-partite body which is<br />
the Commonwealth, the States and Local Government. And, today, we are<br />
working that same model across the sectors to do another great public work<br />
and that is to modernise and renovate the Pacific Highway.<br />
You understand the Commonwealth has now for many years, as a result of<br />
the Council of Australian Governments processes, divided our responsibilities<br />
between the national highway system and the urban and arterial roads which<br />
were formerly, in part, managed financially by the Commonwealth. So that<br />
they are the responsibility of the States and we carry the national highway<br />
system. And the national highway running between Sydney and Brisbane is the<br />
New England Highway and it is the highway for which the Commonwealth has<br />
taken responsibility. But the development and the movement of people, of<br />
course, in this State and in Southern Queensland, is along the coast. And<br />
while this Pacific Highway has been the responsibility of the States of<br />
Queensland and New South Wales, the financial responsibility and cost of<br />
bringing it to the status of a major highway, are beyond the financial capacity<br />
of any one State. </p>
<p>So my colleague, Laurie Brereton, brought to the Cabinet a proposal to fund<br />
a dollar for dollar funding arrangement with the States of New South Wales<br />
and Queensland, an augmentation of the national highway responsibilities<br />
and road programs of the Commonwealth, in a way where we could attempt<br />
to undertake this major work.<br />
Now you might recall that the NRMA published a report, I think it was in July<br />
this year, about the Pacific Highway and I understand it is about to publish<br />
another. And it talks about the highway being the spine of the continent's<br />
East Coast and the need to upgrade and renew it. And I think, by and large,<br />
given that the Bureau of Transport Economics has now published quite a lot<br />
of data on this project, that we will find probably in a reflection in the NRMA<br />
report our own understanding of the costings of the project.<br />
Essentially, what the Commonwealth is proposing today is that we will offer<br />
$ 750 million in ten annual instalments of $ 75 million each to the States of<br />
New South Wales and Queensland for the fast tracking and duplication of the<br />
highway over ten years.<br />
The offer is conditional on New South Wales and Queensland maintaining<br />
their existing levels of commitment to the Pacific Highway and agreeing to<br />
match the Federal Government's contribution dollar for dollar and we have<br />
indications from both Governments that they will so make those contributions.<br />
And just to make sure they will, we have got their name on the maker's, label<br />
here. We have tied them right in.<br />
Now what this will mean is, of course, that we will see $ 750 million from the<br />
Commonwealth and $ 750 million from the two States and that will mean an<br />
additional $ 1.5 billion will be spent on the highway over and above existing<br />
State commitments. So there is already a State program. This will be rolled<br />
together with this new program, but rather than simply dealing with black<br />
spots and some of the more difficult areas, with the current program and<br />
maintenance we would be looking at, of course, a complete rebuild of the<br />
highway. New South Wales and Queensland will retain responsibility for the Pacific<br />
Highway and we will maintain our commitment, of course, for the National<br />
Highway system including the New England. But we realise, I think, that the<br />
reconstruction of the Pacific Highway is a national transport priority and we<br />
are prepared to pull our weight in it. We are very pleased by the indication of<br />
cooperation from the two States.<br />
This represents one of the largest public investments in the Commonwealth,<br />
an investment especially in the future of Queensland and the north coast of<br />
NSW. The Pacific Highway reconstruction project will develop a world class<br />
highway up the Pacific edge of Australia. Currently only about 16 per cent of<br />
the highway features dual carriageways and even if we continued funding at<br />
present levels for the next 10 years, coverage would be less than 20 per cent.<br />
So, even if we carried on as we are, we would only have 20 per cent of it as a<br />
dual carriageway in a decade. But, under this new proposal 81 per cent of </p>
<p>the highway will feature dual carriageways by 2005 and 2006. All 192<br />
kilometres of poor alignment and all 206 of narrow pavement will be removed<br />
all of it removed. All 63 narrow bridges will be eliminated and all major<br />
towns will be bypassed by the highway. This, of course, will make them more<br />
safer and more pleasant places in which to live, which will increase tourist<br />
potential. They are, of course, Nerang, Coolangatta, Tweed Heads,<br />
Chinderah, Brunswick Heads, Ballina, Woodburn, Cowper, Ulmarra,<br />
Woolgoolga, Coffs Harbour, Uranga, Kempsey, Kew, Taree, Bulahdelah,<br />
Karuah and Raymond Terrace. None of them will have the highway running<br />
through them.<br />
In other words, we can get on with, essentially, recognising the needs of a<br />
dual carriageway highway, a safe road for conveyance and one which will be<br />
an artery which provides the building of greater communities along the coast<br />
as the natural shift to the coast takes place. As we see the growth in<br />
population and the growth in demand, we will be able to put this major<br />
national asset into place.<br />
There are, I think, many people have been supportive of this being done for<br />
many years. My colleagues have made an enormous difference in this<br />
debate and I want to acknowledge that. There are things said in public life,<br />
people say things about members of Parliament in the due course of events,<br />
but let me assure you that Neville, Harry and Bob have made this, I suppose,<br />
amongst all of the things in which they have been involved perhaps the<br />
principal thing which they knew the Commonwealth had to be involved with.<br />
So, the point of electing local members of Parliament to take their place in the<br />
national Parliament and in the government is to be able to decipher what is<br />
needed, what can be delivered, what should be done by the Commonwealth,<br />
what other things should be left by the States or how we do things<br />
collaboratively. They have worked together and as a consequence of their<br />
membership of the government, this project is going to happen. I would like<br />
to acknowledge that. I would like to also acknowledge Laurie Brereton's role<br />
in this. Laurie has put down more cubic metres of concrete, built more<br />
bridges, more roads and had more local and regional arguments than anyone<br />
in the country I think. Maybe I could rival him, but the fact is I need to say, in<br />
NSW, " Mr Builder, thank you." I actually think that is going to be the case<br />
here again. Of course, he has seen the need for this to be done and neither<br />
he or I are into the semantics of what is a national highway and what isn't.<br />
There is a major need here and that is what we are responding to. We are<br />
not trying to find characterisations. I'd like also to acknowledge the work of<br />
the NRMA. I am delighted that Don MacKay could be with us today, for the<br />
conscientious effort as a Roads and Motorists Association, you represent the<br />
interests of people in the most difficult stretch of road in the country. They<br />
have done that consistently and conscientiously and their views about this<br />
have been material to the way in which the government has responded. I<br />
want to take this opportunity to thank Don and the Association.<br />
But, I think, what it means, more than all of the technical things, is an<br />
endorsement by the Commonwealth, again, of the importance of this region of<br />
Australia. It is such a beautiful area. We were sifting in the plane coming up, </p>
<p>we were just to the landward of the coast on the way up, looking at all of the<br />
coastal towns as they came by and also the river mouths. And you see what<br />
a wonderful stretch of coast it is. It has got to be one of the most naturally<br />
beautiful places in the world and what a great bequest we have been left as a<br />
nation, to manage this coast line well, to give people their enjoyment of it and<br />
at the same time secure it as economic assets for the States and for the<br />
country. This is, I think, where we have seen a very big change in the<br />
government's policy with Better Cities. I was here just a week ago taking the<br />
first ride on the train from Robina back towards Brisbane were it will link up<br />
with the main electrified line out of Brisbane and I'm sure we are going to see<br />
a time too when that railway will come down here to Tweed Heads.<br />
This is another thing that both Neville and Harry have been talking about now<br />
since under the Better Cities program we join with Queensland in the funding<br />
of the railway from Robina and given that this area of coast, particularly from<br />
Brisbane to Coolangatta, is the fastest growing area of Australia and, of<br />
course, the area from Tweed Heads down through Grafton et cetera has also<br />
got the same buoyancy of growth. What we do need to see in place are the<br />
appropriate bits of public infrastructure and the good thing about the railway,<br />
for instance, is that it is actually going to design the way in which the<br />
development moves around it. In other words, it is not coming simply at the<br />
end of the process, even though we have seen a lot of development in the<br />
Gold Coast and the hinterland, it is going to define, in fact, the way in which a<br />
lot of this development occurs.<br />
So, there is a role for the Commonwealth. We see it under Better Cities. We<br />
have seen it where we have introduced stimulatory statements like<br />
One Nation, where we have put funding into various projects that are beyond<br />
a municipal government's capacity or the states's capacity and we have got<br />
now some very large rolling programs running as well. The main message is,<br />
I think, that we are very interested in the north coast of NSW and this area<br />
between Tweed Heads, Coolangatta and Brisbane. We have been happy to<br />
join with the Government of Queensland and now the Government of NSW in<br />
doing these things.<br />
The one bit left undone was, of course, the highway and, with this<br />
announcement today, that will be done as well. As a consequence we can<br />
start thinking in a unitary way of the whole region. That has come by virtue of<br />
the fact that the Commonwealth recognises and has a role in these regions<br />
with the States and with local government.<br />
So, I think, this is a very big change and it also recognises the urbanisation of<br />
the coast and how important it is for us to get it right and how the devotion of<br />
public assets can be important. There is a place for private growth and<br />
private assets, a place for the public ones and invariably where the public<br />
ones are set, it will set the pattern of development which then follows it and<br />
this is what we have been seeking to do. As well as that, can I just mention<br />
that you might recall our Working Nation program which is a statement<br />
designed to deal with long term unemployment. Simon Crean announced<br />
recently under our New Work Opportunities project that we are going to see </p>
<p>1750 jobs created in the region here under that program and also we<br />
supported under Working Nation, Regional Economic Development<br />
Organisations. We have established one in northern NSW and the point of<br />
that is to focus on what the region needs and how best it should develop. We<br />
have found in the McKinsey study that the regions doing best and there are<br />
many regions of Australia growing faster than the capital cities the ones<br />
doing best are the ones that are locally led by the Federal members, by State<br />
members, by local government, by the business organisations, by unions, by<br />
non government organisations coming together and providing leadership.<br />
In other words, if a community knows what it wants itself then it will draw its<br />
own investment to it and what we find happens is that most of the investment,<br />
in fact, doesn't come in from outside, it actually comes from the region, that<br />
existing businesses grow faster and it is giving a signal to the State and to<br />
the Commonwealth governments about what they might do with the area.<br />
One of the great challenges, but I think one of the most exciting prospects for<br />
us, is to do all these things but to do it with an eye to nature and a beauty.<br />
The first thing you always think about flying in here is the nature and the<br />
beauty of it because it is an absolutely exceptional part of the country. It<br />
doesn't matter where you go in the world, when you come back here it always<br />
strikes you.<br />
Just three weeks ago we made key decisions about the forests of this<br />
country. In what must be the biggest public decision in respect to the forests<br />
ever, six million hectares of Australian native forests have been reserved<br />
under Deferred Forest Areas for broader assessment into Regional Forest<br />
Agreements. In doing this, we will see I hope, the dual commitments to the<br />
environment, to representative stands of native species of trees and to the<br />
forest products industry, so we can have a sustainable forest products<br />
industry. And where those two objectives clash, we are going to have a very<br />
large reconstruction package of financial measures to support those<br />
industries and the people in those industries who have got difficulties dealing<br />
with the reconstruction of the forest industries arising from that package. But,<br />
I think we can do it and, in doing it, I know there are two things here: there is<br />
substantial environmental conscientiousness, as naturally you would expect,<br />
given the beauty of it and the forest resources in this region of Australia.<br />
I think, people should be assured that no government has ever done more<br />
and more conscientiously something to actually keep important<br />
representative stands of forests in this country. But, we are also conscious of<br />
the jobs and the employment and the costs of reconstruction of these<br />
industries. And on this occasion we have been, I think, very cognisant of that<br />
and the financial commitments and adjustment packages we have announced<br />
recognise that too.<br />
So, if you take the region as a whole, just looking at the difficulties of, say,<br />
development from Newcastle up to Brisbane, all the demands for population<br />
growth, all the demands for traffic, the settlement difficulties along the coast,<br />
the importance of the preservation of the hinterland, the importance of </p>
<p>agriculture and timber industries, what we are seeking to do is to do it<br />
together as a whole policy, and to focus that on the whole region. I think,<br />
what we are talking about today, the transport spine, the link that runs<br />
through it, important as that is going to be to all of these communities, what is<br />
I think, important beyond that is how we approach the whole region and we<br />
underline the beauty and preserve it, we secure the prime natural assets and<br />
we develop the place for the quiet enjoyment of those who have chosen to<br />
live here.<br />
Can I thank you very much for coming to lunch today, to be here at this<br />
important announcement and let me again thank my colleagues Neville<br />
Newell, Harry Woods and Bob Home for their interest in this and say that<br />
when communities get serious about their own needs and prospects, and<br />
they get serious members who know they have got to earn their freight and<br />
are not sitting there with some sort of God-given right or to be hearing voices,<br />
of being tapped on the shoulder by some supernatural force to represent the<br />
rest of us, that people are actually out there working and doing, this is the<br />
result of that sort of representation.<br />
Thank you very much indeed.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
