<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18095</transcript-id>
    <title>$475 million more for regional health facilities</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/08/2011</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Patients and families in regional communities across Australia are set to benefit from the next round of the Gillard Government's $5 billion Health and Hospitals Fund, with applications now open.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister said this new round of the HHF would see $475 million invested in regional hospitals around Australia.</p>
<p>These funds will go towards projects such as new equipment or better buildings for local hospitals, new chronic disease management services and new or expanded mental and dental health services.</p>
<p>Minister for Health and Ageing Nicola Roxon said the Gillard Government's Health and Hospitals Fund was providing communities with 21st century health systems that can meet patients' needs.</p>
<p>This capital funding round will complement the 148 other Health and Hospitals Fund projects totalling some $4.5 billion that are already underway in health services and hospitals all around Australia.</p>
<p>Minister for Regional Australia Simon Crean said this new round was the third to give priority to regional, rural and remote areas.</p>
<p>More than 50 per cent of the HHF funding already allocated is being directed towards regional Australia, helping to make a big difference in the day-to-day lives of country Australians.</p>
<p>When this latest round is allocated, regional and rural areas will be assisted by health projects worth more than $2.9 billion through the HHF to help close the gaps that exist between health services in the city and the country.</p>
<p>The guidelines for this new funding round will be largely the same as those drawn up for the 2010 Regional Priority Round, with projects with local community support being a priority.</p>
<p>All projects funded under the regional priority round will be fully offset by savings measures to meet the Government's fiscal rules. </p>
<p>Applications close on 19 October 2011 and will then be assessed by the independent, expert HHF advisory board. Successful projects will be announced as part of the 2012 Budget.</p>
<p>Further information about the HHF is available from: <a href="http://www.health.gov.au/hhf">www.health.gov.au/hhf</a></p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
