<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9917</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP NATIONAL MUSEUM OF AUSTRALIA</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/01/1996</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009917.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER 5/ 96<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
NATIONAL MUSEUM OF AUSTRALIA<br />
The next major extension stage of the National Museum of Australia will be<br />
the development of the social, political and constitutional theme at Old<br />
Parliament House.<br />
A national competition to build the environmental component of the National<br />
Museum network at Yarramundi in Canberra will also be held.<br />
The National Museum of Australia will be a museum which reaches all<br />
Australians in their own communities, their schools and libraries and on their<br />
own computers and in Canberra, other capitals and regional centres.<br />
Exhibition sites will be developed in Old Parliament House, at Yarramundi<br />
and at the Gallery of Aboriginal Australia on Acton Peninsula. The Museum<br />
will also produce on-line and interactive material which will be widely<br />
available in all schools and libraries and will develop partnerships with State<br />
and regional museums to operate an extensive program of travelling<br />
exhibitions and educational projects.<br />
As part of the first stage of the physical network of the National Museum of<br />
Australia, Creative Nation announced that the Government will build the<br />
Gallery of Aboriginal Australia on Acton Peninsula. A new facility for the<br />
Australian Institute of Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander studies is to be colocated<br />
with the Gallery. Building will commence on the site later this year.<br />
Old Parliament House holds great significance for all Australians and the<br />
Government will provide $ 12 million over 3 years to extend exhibition areas<br />
for the National Museum of Australia, the National Portrait Gallery and the<br />
Australian Archives. This will allow the Museum to develop exhibitions which<br />
are specifically designed to explore Australia's social, political and<br />
constitutional history in the Old Parliament House context.<br />
A similar extension of the National Portrait Gallery and the Australian<br />
Archives will complement the National Museum presence and confirm Old<br />
Parliament House as a vibrant celebration of our history. </p>
<p>The Government is also foreshadowing the stage three development of the<br />
National Museum at Yarramundi in Canberra. The site and nature of the<br />
facility is such that the Government will organise a design competition for this<br />
building and site landscaping.<br />
The Yarramundi facility will provide an environmental focus on our history<br />
and contemporary life. This will be developed so as to provide links with the<br />
National Botanical Gardens and to develop public programs in conjunction<br />
with bodies such as the CSIRQ, the Australian Heritage Commission and<br />
Greening Australia. The 88 hectare site at Yarramundi provides an<br />
outstanding opportunity to explore, illustrate and educate on environmental<br />
issues.<br />
To further extend access to the Museum beyond Canberra, $ 6 million will be<br />
allocated to the Museum over the next three years to facilitate the funding of<br />
a number of specific partnership projects with State and regional museums, to<br />
increase the rate of their digitising program to enable more Australians to get<br />
in touch with their cultural heritage and to extend the range of travelling<br />
exhibitions developed and toured by the Museum.<br />
It is critical thit in addition to a strong Canberra base, the Museum should<br />
work collaboratively with State and selected regional museums to develop a<br />
national network which maximises the effective use of the distributed national<br />
collection and recognises the significant and active role which regional<br />
centres have to play in Australia's cultural life.<br />
Since the Creative Nation commitment to extend access to our national<br />
collections through new communications technology, the National Museum<br />
has worked within the Australia on CD program and will have a critical role in<br />
the recently announced $ 10 million program, Australia's Story Our National<br />
Collections On Line, which will begin the task of digitising the collections of<br />
our national cultural institutions.<br />
The Government believes that a modern National Museum must go beyond<br />
the notion of a single facility in the National Capital. The National Museum of<br />
Australia will give all Australians everywhere the opportunity to experience<br />
their country's cultural heritage.<br />
CAN BERRA<br />
January 1996 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
