<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8142</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF UNEDITED INTERVIEW WITH PAUL LYNEHAM, 7.30 REPORT, 24 SEPTEMBER 1990</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/09/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008142.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF UNEDITED INTERVIEW WITH PAUL LYNEHAM, 7.30<br />
REPORT, 24 SEPTEMBER 1990<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
LYNEHAM: What do you say to those ALP members who will<br />
inevitably be saying tonight that by diluting the<br />
commitment to public ownership, Labor's sold part of its<br />
soul? PM: Well they'd be wrong. The fact is that in the<br />
telecommunication industry we've strengthened the public<br />
telecommunication facility. For the first time now<br />
Australia will have a fully publicly owned<br />
telecommunication facility operating across the whole of<br />
the international and domestic network.<br />
LYNEHAM: But with top to bottom competition from private<br />
consortiums? PM: And so it should, and so it should. But as a result<br />
of what we've done I think the publicly owned facility<br />
will be more securely anchored, as I told the conference,<br />
more securely anchored in the public sector than it ever<br />
has been or could be.<br />
LYNEHAM: There was a challenge to you today, why don't<br />
you put this to a referendum of the rank and file. if<br />
you did you wouldn't get it through, would you?<br />
PM: Leadership, leadership is about leadership. If in<br />
this world all you did was to say there are my people, I<br />
am their leader, I must follow them, nothing would be<br />
done. LYNEHAM: So it wasn't a shot gun conference as one of<br />
your delegate's says?<br />
PM: No, certainly not. Kim Beazley in fact incurred the<br />
wrath of some of his Cabinet colleagues because he took<br />
so long to come to the Cabinet and that was because he<br />
was in fact conducting an unparalleled degree of<br />
consultation within the labour movement politically and<br />
industrially. LYNEHAM: And yet even he said today that everyone<br />
sitting around there was a bit like amateurs trying to<br />
tackle brain surgery and he said he was one of the </p>
<p>amateurs too. I mean has there been enough really<br />
informed debate about this?<br />
PM: In some quarters it has been very uninformed but I<br />
don't remember any issue in the seven and a half years<br />
I've been in Government in which so many sections of the<br />
Party, from Cabinet Ministers right through to rank and<br />
file, has so seriously attempted to inform themselves on<br />
what admittedly is a very complex subject.<br />
LYNEHAM: When you get a vote of 58 to 43 though that's<br />
not consensus, is it? That's a split almost down the<br />
middle. PM: Of course it's not consensus any more than the 60/ 39<br />
was on the airlines. That's not consensus.<br />
LYNEHAM: Is there a future danger in there for the<br />
Party? PM: No, no. The danger for the Party would've been if<br />
we had in fact shown ourselves incapable of facing up to<br />
the necessity for a change. That wouldn't only have<br />
been dangerous it would've been deadly.<br />
LYNEHAM: But you've got two groups in the Party with<br />
very different ideas of where this country ought to be<br />
going PM: Well let me say this; I have never seen the Left on<br />
an issue with its heart so much out of the debate and let<br />
me say that at the end of the conference very many of<br />
them came up to me and said well done.<br />
LYNEHAM: Well done?<br />
PM: Yes, sure.<br />
LYNEHAM: What's the<br />
PM: Because I mean in the sense I mean I hope it's<br />
very clear that in none of this am I in any sense<br />
gloating. I mean I feel the very opposite of gloating<br />
about this issue. Where I'm very, very happy is not just<br />
about the decision but the way in which it was conducted.<br />
I mean really those sections of the Party that weren't at<br />
one with us basically, however, recognise the integrity<br />
of our position and I believe now-that the decision is<br />
taken they will work harmoniously to see that the best<br />
effect is given to it.<br />
LYNEHAM: How would you describe tonight the future of<br />
the Left in the ALP?<br />
PM: The Left I think has always got a place in the<br />
Party. I think some of them were upset about some of<br />
their internal processes. But let me say this; I mean<br />
the Left has in the earlier stages has had no more </p>
<p>implacable opponent I suppose than me on a number of<br />
issues. But I pay them credit over the last few years<br />
for having been much more constructive in their approach<br />
to the Government and that's been reflected at the level<br />
of their members of the Cabinet, the Ministry and the<br />
Caucus. They have been a very, very constructive cooperative<br />
element of Government. Now to a large extent<br />
that's been reflected out in the Party generally on this<br />
issue. On this issue there were some-strong feelings but<br />
even within the Left there was a lot of very constructive<br />
contribution on this issue.<br />
LYNEHAM: Will you reaffirm tonight your pledge that noone<br />
will be worse off as a result of the competition in<br />
telecommunications? PM: Yes, I see no reason not to because what we've<br />
indicated now that it's confirmed in the conference<br />
that in the area of CSO, that's Community Service<br />
Obligations, they will be adhered to. The concept of a<br />
price protection will be adhered to by the CPI minus X<br />
formula. Of course, the fact is that all overseas<br />
experience shows that where you get competition in even<br />
the threat of competition you get the reduction in<br />
prices. LYNEHAM: And yet here we'll have foreign investors who<br />
will have put up a lot of money and will be keen to try<br />
to maximise their profits. I mean they're not mugs.<br />
PM: Of course they're not mugs.<br />
LYNEHAM: How are they going to do that while you protect<br />
everybody as well?<br />
PM: Because you have the impact in this industry of new<br />
technology which is, you know, coming in at a rate which<br />
is almost beyond description and you're going to have a<br />
0 growth in the market. As Kim Beazley has indicated, the<br />
experience everywhere has been when you get this<br />
competition there is a very, very considerable growth in<br />
the market. So it's a combination of growth and market<br />
size, new technology and just the impact of competition<br />
you will be able to achieve both.<br />
LYNEHAM: Your critics say Cabinet's got a blind faith in<br />
the virtues of competition. That it didn't work with the<br />
banks, as many people with mortgages will tell you. it<br />
hasn't worked in the television industry. It didn't work<br />
with some of our more famous paper shufflers. Why should<br />
it work now in<br />
PM: Is the logic of that, Paul, let's take the<br />
television industry, that the Government introduced<br />
competition and competition has failed. You know very<br />
well that, it's a good Dorothy Dixer for me and I thank<br />
you for it, but you know very well that what happened in<br />
the television industry is that some ambitious players </p>
<p>paid ridiculous, irrelevant prices for the assets.<br />
Prices which were incapable, given the interest<br />
obligations that were associated with that debt. Gave<br />
you a situation in which profitability was impossible.<br />
That outcome was not the result of Government decisions<br />
it was the result of stupid entrepreneurial decisions.<br />
LYNEHAM: But they thought it was a license to print<br />
money. PM: They thought and they were wrong.<br />
LYNEHAM: But why wouldn't some of these foreign<br />
consortiums think this is a license to print money. And<br />
then come to you whingeing later and say oh look we've<br />
got these big debts Prime Minister we'd better put up the<br />
price PM: Absolutely no analogy. None at all.<br />
LYNEHAN: So if they come later and start squealing to<br />
you and we'd better put up domestic call charges or have<br />
timed local calls, the answer will be no?<br />
PM: What they will be in will be a competitive situation<br />
where they will be able, because of new technology and a<br />
growing market they will be able, and under the<br />
regulatory framework of AUSTEL, they will be able to both<br />
make their investments and over time do that profitably<br />
and in a situation which is compatible with lower prices<br />
to consumers.<br />
LYNEHAM: The Telecom union is still talking tonight of<br />
industrial action. They can make it unworkable. Can't<br />
they? PM: Some of them are. No they will not be able to make<br />
it unworkable. Let's be quite clear about that. The<br />
Government will govern this country. Not a<br />
telecommunications union. I say to the telecommunication<br />
unions quite directly these things. The interests of<br />
those who work in the telecommunication industry were<br />
very much in our mind in this issue. But I am not going<br />
to have a situation where one union in the<br />
telecommunication industry is going to say to its fellow<br />
trade unionists in this country, it's all right for you,<br />
if you're in the metal trades or the construction<br />
industry or the food industry to live and operate in a<br />
situation of competition but we uniquely are going to be<br />
protected from competition at the cost of you our fellow<br />
workers. So let the members who work in Telecom be quite<br />
aware of that. The Government will govern and they will<br />
not be given a unique position against all other workers.<br />
Secondly, I say this, just think of the realities. As a<br />
result of what my Party has done today in setting up a<br />
fully publicly owned telecommunication facility operating<br />
across the total spectrum internationally and<br />
domestically the first time that's been done. We will </p>
<p>secure, I think, indefinitely into the future public<br />
ownership of such a facility. They can make their<br />
choice. Do they want to support a government which has<br />
done that or facilitate the entry into government of a<br />
group of parties which is dedicated to the total<br />
privatisation of the telecommunication industry. Make up<br />
their mind.<br />
LYNEHAM: Given the fact that it's a very decentralised<br />
industry, five or 6,000 telephone exchanges, and a highly<br />
technical one. It won't be too hard for them to throw a<br />
spanner in the works if they want to.<br />
PM: I don't believe that in the end their leadership<br />
will support or endorse that position because it would be<br />
against their interests. I Just say this, this country<br />
will be governed by the Government in this important area<br />
of telecommunications. We will not be dictated to by a<br />
union. LYNEHAM: The Democrats say<br />
PM: Nor may I say will the rest of the trade union<br />
movement tolerate it.<br />
LYNEHAM: The Democrats say they'll block it in the<br />
Senate, the Opposition we were told today would much<br />
prefer the present situation<br />
PM: Of course they would. Of course they would.<br />
LYNEHAM: to the one you've arrived at tonight. So<br />
they've got an interest to block it too.<br />
PM: Well have they? Have they? The Opposition have got<br />
to face up to a very real issue. They've wanted<br />
competition. That's what it's about, they say,<br />
competition. Now are they going to say that they are<br />
going to block legislation which brings in competition<br />
and which keeps a total public monopoly. It's going to<br />
be fascinating to see.<br />
LYNEHAM: But they'll say it doesn't go far enough.<br />
PM: Well will they? Instead of it not going far enough<br />
they will therefore vote to retain a situation of total<br />
public monopoly. That's going to be fascinating.<br />
LYNEHAM: Would you be happy to fight this as an election<br />
issue? PM: What I want to see is the legislation passed which<br />
will bring the best results for Australia and that's what<br />
we'll be If the Opposition, if the Opposition want<br />
to say that they will use their vote to reflect upon<br />
Australia, a continuation of a total public monopoly,<br />
I'll fight that one. I mean I'll fight them whichever<br />
way they go. Because if they pass the legislation, which </p>
<p>6<br />
they must in all principle do, and then say well we'll<br />
fight the next election on what we think's better, I<br />
certainly look forward to that. Because it will be a<br />
simple question of the Labor Government saying in regard<br />
to this critical area of telecommunications, our position<br />
is a totally publicly owned telecommunication facility<br />
with full private competition against which the Tories<br />
will be arguing, no, total privatisation. I look forward<br />
to that argument. But if they are going to also give me<br />
the position of saying that they will keep a total public<br />
monopoly and stop competition then we'll take them on on<br />
that one too.<br />
LYNEHAM: The airlines Prime Minister. Do you think<br />
there might be more public sentiment about the airlines<br />
given that it's sort of easier to love an airline than<br />
something like Telecom?<br />
PM: No. Let's be real about this. What are the<br />
statistics? Less than ten per cent of Australians use<br />
the airlines. No-one goes around, no politician goes<br />
around this country more than I do, and let me tell you,<br />
I haven't had one person come up to me and say you<br />
mustn't sell the airlines. Why? Because the Australian<br />
people out there are not mugs. They are not mugs. The<br />
overwhelming majority of them don't use the airlines and<br />
they know that it's much more sensible for Government to<br />
use its scarce resources in doing things that the private<br />
sector won't do.<br />
LYNEHAM: They might if they were a bit cheaper after<br />
deregulation. PM: But they already are. Look at the price falls that<br />
are now occurring as a result of what my Government did.<br />
You had all those years of Tory government and a Toryimposed<br />
two airline policy. It was a Hawke Labor<br />
Government which brought that to an end, brought in<br />
deregulation and prices are diving as a result.<br />
LYNEHAM: Wouldn't though a Government-owned Australian<br />
Airlines still make you a player in the market, like the<br />
Commonwealth Bank in banking?<br />
PM: Mate, I've been in office for seven and a half years<br />
and let me let you in to a well-kept State secret. In<br />
seven and a half years owning Australian Airlines, not<br />
once in seven and a half years have we been called upon<br />
to make any decisions about the running of those<br />
airlines. LYNEHAM: What will happen to the proceeds of the sales?<br />
PM: The proceeds of the sales will be used to reduce<br />
public debt interest which is to the benefit of the<br />
country and it will be legitimate to then look at how the<br />
reductions in public debt interest, that on-going benefit<br />
of the reduction of the public debt, can be used for </p>
<p>investment in other areas of much greater value to the<br />
Australian people.<br />
LYNEHAM: A few quick examples.<br />
PM: Well one area that I'm obviously interested in and<br />
so are my colleagues is the public transport<br />
infrastructure. I mean Australia depends for its<br />
economic competitiveness and efficiency more than a lot<br />
of other countries on having a very efficient public<br />
transport infrastructure. There's a lot needs to be done<br />
in the area of rail for instance. I think there's a good<br />
deal of investment that ought to be considered there.<br />
LYNEHAM: What does Labor stand for tonight,<br />
ideologically? I mean if Ben Chifley had been in the<br />
hall today, what would he be saying?<br />
PM: He would've voted for us for a very simple reason<br />
that, as I said in the debate, there's been one enduring<br />
unchallengeable goal of the Australian Labor Party in its<br />
nearly hundred years of existence. And that is to try<br />
and improve the lot of the ordinary Australian. The goal<br />
has never changed. The goal is valid today. The means<br />
for achieving that goal obviously must change in a world<br />
which is changing dramatically. It made sense at the end<br />
of the war in a country which was going to be exploding<br />
economically and in which air transport was going to be<br />
an integrally important part of that expansion to have a<br />
publicly owned domestic airline which would undertake<br />
routes that a privately owned airline driven only by the<br />
profit motive wouldn't undertake. To have it in there<br />
setting up safety standards<br />
LYNEHAM: Paul Keating thinks it's now the reverse, that<br />
Ansett's the people's airline.<br />
PM: He's saying that they are concerned more with lower<br />
income flyers than Australian. I don't need to make that<br />
point. I'm making the point in answer to your major<br />
question, that in the 1940s in the immediate post-war<br />
situation, to have a public owned domestic airline made<br />
sense. It makes absolutely no sense now. It is an<br />
economic nonsense. It's perversion of the use of scarce<br />
public resources.<br />
LYNEHAM: So a youngster comes up to you and says Mr<br />
Hawke, I'm thinking of supporting a political party. Can<br />
you tell me in one sentence what you stand for?<br />
PM: I'd say I stand for the party which, young man, when<br />
I came to office in ' 83 looked at you and the young kids<br />
of Australia and saw one in three of you, one in three of<br />
you, going on in education beyond the compulsory level.<br />
As a result of the priorities of my Party and my<br />
Government there's now two out of every three of you<br />
going on in education. That's what I stand for young<br />
man. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
