<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>40607</transcript-id>
    <title>Radio interview with Greg Jennett, ABC AM</title>
    <prime-minister>Turnbull, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20150915 - 20180824</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/11/2016</release-date>
    <release-type>Transcript</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p><strong>GREG JENNETT: </strong></p>
<p>Prime Minister, you’ve wrapped up a lengthy conversation with Barack Obama. He is almost yesterday’s man. What is it that you seek to influence or achieve by talking through an outgoing President about important bilateral issues?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>Well, few people have as great an insight into world affairs than Barack Obama. He’s been President of the United States for eight years and his understanding of the big issues that we face are vitally important for us to share with him. He’s also able to provide us with an insight into the new administration and he’s engendered confidence, he believes, he’s made the point here that the new Donald Trump Administration can be expected to resolve the big issues that confront it in line with, much more in line with traditional American policies than many people have speculated.</p>
<p><strong>GREG JENNETT:</strong></p>
<p>So he actually errs towards the view that says Donald Trump in office is not the Donald Trump in campaign?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>Well, I think he agrees with that great sentiment I quote a lot by Mario Cuomo, “We campaign in poetry and govern in prose.”</p>
<p><strong>GREG JENNETT: </strong></p>
<p>It’s a two way relationship though and Barack Obama is heading out. Does he look to you to do anything to bring your voice to bear on the Trump Administration?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>He certainly believes that centre-right governments like the one I lead will be influential in Washington in the years ahead but Australia is always well respected and always influential in Washington.</p>
<p><strong>GREG JENNETT:</strong></p>
<p>Can we go through the issues? Obviously the Middle East and military conduct there was discussed – what’s your view or indeed the President’s on what’s likely to happen as Donald Trump makes good on his promise to quote: “Take out ISIS”?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>Well the campaign against ISIS is well underway as you know. The Mosul campaign is occurring right now and we’re confident it will be successfully concluded. We do believe, as does the President that the Coalition of which we are part will succeed in eliminating Daesh from Mosul and then from its base in Raqqa in Syria.</p>
<p><strong>GREG JENNETT: </strong></p>
<p>By transition on the 20th of January?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>We haven’t discussed that date, no.</p>
<p><strong>GREG JENNETT:</strong></p>
<p>Is that not critical; are there benchmarks that are sought to be achieved under the Obama leadership before Donald Trump comes in?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>Well there certainly are military timetables and objectives but they’re not being geared towards political dates in the political calendar.</p>
<p><strong>GREG JENNETT:</strong></p>
<p>Did you canvas any expectations about a greater Australian military commitment?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>No we did not discuss any increase in Australian commitment but I have to say the President acknowledged as he did publically at the close of the meeting, his very deep gratitude for the courage and professionalism and the steadfast commitment of Australia’s defence forces, the servicemen and women who are there in the Middle East with their American comrades in arms and indeed all of our allies in this battle against terrorism.</p>
<p><strong>GREG JENNETT:</strong></p>
<p>Now you are shortly to return to Australia and Parliament with much conversation at home about your industrial bills. What level of confidence do you enter this final sitting fortnight that you can get those signature pieces of legislation passed?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>Well we believe we’ve made a very strong case for the passage of the bills and we look forward to the support of the crossbench for the legislation. But of course we absolutely respect the right of every Senator to consider the legislation on its merits and we will see how the Senate deliberates in the week ahead.</p>
<p><strong>GREG JENNETT:</strong></p>
<p>But you wouldn’t have brought them in unless you thought there at least a 50/50 chance of their passage?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>Well we brought them in because we believe we have a good prospect of them being passed but again I’m not going to quote odds for you. Can I just say, getting back to this conference, the big issue here really is global trade. APEC is an economic forum as you know. What we’ve seen, with respect to the TPP is a very strong commitment by all the countries that are parties to the TPP to continue the ratification process.</p>
<p><strong>GREG JENNETT:</strong></p>
<p>Including any lame duck session effort that the President may be able to assist with?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>I think it’s accepted that the ratification of the TPP and the United States, if it is to occur, will be something will have to be conducted under the new Congress and the new President.</p>
<p><strong>GREG JENNETT:</strong></p>
<p>And why would that happen?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>Well let me just say to you, there are 12 nations that are parties to the TPP. The United States is one of them but I can say with respect to the other 11, leaving aside the future attitude of the Trump Administration – with respect to the other 11 there is very continued, very strong commitment to and enthusiasm for the TPP here.</p>
<p><strong>[ENDS]</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
