<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5748</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/02/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005748.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA SUNDAY, FEBRUARY 14 1982<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
With the Autumn Session of Parliament about to * commence,<br />
I would likE! to take the opportunity of speaking to you<br />
about Australia's priorities and prospects, about the<br />
challenges we face as a people over the coming months.<br />
We need a proper perspective on our achievements in the<br />
economic arEna because the underlying strength of the<br />
Australian economy is great, and we have the right policies<br />
in place to keep it well on course.<br />
We need to understand that Australia's economy has been<br />
growing, while many other economies have been stagnant or<br />
shrinking, a~ nd the OECD predicts further growth of over 3%<br />
for Australia in 1982, compared with an OECD average of just<br />
over We need to understand the consumer demand remains<br />
strong. The value of retail sales last December was ' 13%<br />
higher than in 1980. We need to understand that 83,000<br />
new jobs were created in 1981, that the average unemployment<br />
rate throughout 1981 was the lowest for four years, and that<br />
while the January unemployment rate was too high, it was still<br />
below last year's January rate. We need to understand that<br />
business expects continuing strong investment growth this<br />
financial year, and that following the projected record of<br />
$ 1.25 billion on petroleum exploration and development in<br />
1981, the projected figures for 1982 almost doubles that<br />
again to nearly $ 2.5 billion.<br />
We need to understand that this level of investment would<br />
not occur unless there was confidence in Australia's economy.<br />
We need to understand that over six years, the Commonwealth<br />
has consistently held down its own spending, both in absolute<br />
terms-and aS a proportion of Gross Domestic Product in a way<br />
which our major trading partners have not rivalled, and that<br />
the recent tightening of budgetary expenditure has been<br />
designed to maintain that overall restraint, especially in<br />
the face of some unexpected large wage increases.<br />
We need to understand that real household disposable income<br />
after tax rose by nearly $ 3 billion in 1980/ 81, and that in<br />
the two years to last December quarter, average weekly earnings<br />
have increas3ed by over $ 13 in real terms. We * need to understand<br />
that total -taxation revenue as a proportion of GDP, is lower<br />
in Australia than for all our major trading partners with the<br />
exception of Japan. And the Commonwealth budgetdeficit as a percentage<br />
of GDP has been less in Australia than that of all our major<br />
trading partners in 1979/ 80. </p>
<p>-2<br />
There is no doubt whatever that Australia's position in relation<br />
to economic management and development is the envy of many other<br />
countries because we pioneered and stuck to policy approaches<br />
which are increasingly widely recognised as appropriate in the<br />
1980s. The Government's economic ' policy has the enduring objectives<br />
of curbing inflationary pressures, achieving continuing<br />
private sector recovery, and gaining sustained improvements<br />
in living standards for all Australians.<br />
There are obviously challenges and threats to these objectives,<br />
both at home and overseas, and the Government has been<br />
responding to these challenges. People are fed up with the<br />
kind of strikes and unreasonable wage demands which have been<br />
all too common, especially in the second half of the past year<br />
which have damaged our international competitiveness, have thrEatened<br />
investment, and have destroyed job prospects for many young peo~ ple.<br />
There were twice as many working days lost through strikes in<br />
the 1981 September quarter as in the corresponding period<br />
in 1980. The Minister for Industrial Relations, Ian Viner,<br />
is bringing forward three measures to address the present<br />
industrial situation, both immediately and in the longer<br />
term. I have. no doubt that these measures are sound.<br />
They will help to equalise legal responsibilities and balance<br />
the bargaining positions of. unions and employers. And I believe<br />
the communit~ y will give them the support they deserve.<br />
Accelerating, wages are the main danger to continued economic<br />
recovery, an~ d it is essential that all parties to wage<br />
bargains exercise restraint. If wage rises are allowed to<br />
exceed the capacity of the economy to pay, Australia will<br />
price itself out of international markets, causing loss of<br />
jobs and confidence. Consistent with its philosophy, the<br />
Government supports wage settlements proceeding on an industry<br />
by industry basis. The Government believes that employers and<br />
unions bear the prime responsibility for wage settlements,<br />
and agreements which ignore the total economic environment<br />
can only lea~ d to unemployment and lower growth.<br />
The depressed condition of the world economy also poses<br />
a challenge to Australia's economic pos-ition. The Australian<br />
economy dEtrives enormous benefit from overseas trade and<br />
from access to overseas capital markets. At the same time,<br />
if overseas economic conditions are poor, if overseas interest<br />
rates are high, the Australian economy is bound to be effected.<br />
The Government can't totally insulate the Australian economy<br />
from the effects of overseas trading, but we can and already<br />
have shaped our policies in response to the challenges that<br />
they pose. One clear indication of the impact of poor economic<br />
conditions o~ verseas can be seen in our balance of payments<br />
B~ ecause of our strong growth of real incomes, and the demands<br />
created by resource development, our import bill has been rising<br />
significantly, but because of depressed world trade, and falling<br />
commodity p rices, our export earnings have been falling. In this<br />
connection, exchange rate management is critical. The Government's<br />
approach in this area is one of a carefully managed exchange<br />
rate with very gentle, sometimes almost imperceptible adjustments<br />
according to the overall state of the balance of payments,<br />
but also wi-: h an eye to other important considerations such<br />
as inflationary implications. ./ 3 </p>
<p>3<br />
SWe will continue to follow this practice, ad adjust the<br />
exchange rate on a gradual basis in line with market<br />
circumstances. The exchange rate has already been devalued<br />
by 5% against the trade weighted index since early August<br />
1981, and by 5.6% against the United States since early<br />
December 1981. The Government recognises that economic<br />
management is a continuing process of facing new circumstances,<br />
anticipating new challenges and adapting to them.<br />
In the final analysis, the best service the Government can<br />
provide to the Australian economy is to create conditions<br />
conducive to sustained economic growth by continuing to bear<br />
down on inflation and by minimising Government demands on the<br />
private sector. This is the foundation on which are policies<br />
are built and it provides the only basis for Australia's<br />
continued economic success. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
