<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3510</transcript-id>
    <title>INTERVIEW WITH MR AND MRS WHITLAM ON WBQ8 MARYBOROUGH FOR REPLAY &#039;A CURRENT AFFAIR&#039; 2 DECEMBER 1974</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/12/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003510_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
INTERVIEW WITH MR AND MRS WHITLAM ON WBQ8 MARYBO:, OUGH<br />
FOR REPLAY " A CURRENT AFFAIR" 2 DECEMBER 1974<br />
QUESTION: Since I last interviewed you, your title has changed,<br />
you haven't you're still tall and gorgeous. What's so great<br />
about being Prime Minister?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: It's the opportunity to do things or try to do<br />
the things that you were dreaming about doing before you got<br />
the job.<br />
QUESTION: But some of the things have been more or less trial<br />
and error haven't they?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: There's a hell of a lot of things you can't do<br />
because circumstances change. It's more difficult to do them<br />
but on the other hand there has been an immense number of things<br />
that you can get the satisfaction of at last having seen done,<br />
or got done in your country.<br />
QUESTION: Mrs Whitlam any political decisions of the Prime Minister<br />
that you've disagreed with?<br />
MRS WHITLAM: Inevitably.<br />
QUESTION: Do you tell him?<br />
MRS WHITLAM: Sometimes.<br />
QUESTION: Who has last say?<br />
MRS WEITLAM: Naturally he does. He is the Prime Minister. He's<br />
the political person. I'm not, as I hasten to tell you and<br />
everyb -v else.<br />
QUESTION: , ny do you think you're so good for each other?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well we've had to make do with each oth for<br />
over 32 years now. ( Mrs Whitlam: Thanks very much.)<br />
QUESTION: What attracted you to each other at first?<br />
KR WHITLAM: It would be indelicate of me to say.<br />
PRIML MINISTER: I suppose it was reassuring for me all those years<br />
ago to find somebody who was much the same height and also who<br />
had plenL-nf confidence and go and so on.<br />
QUESTION: Still got plenty of confidence and gc?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes, yes, yes.<br />
QUESTION: What do you like doing together?<br />
MRS WHITLAM: We don't get much opportunity to do anything together.<br />
QUESTION: When do you have the opportunity?<br />
MRS WHITLAM: We like going to concerts, listening to music.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Getting away to places like Hervey Bay. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
MRS WHITLAM: Sitting in the sun.<br />
QUESTION: What don't you like doing together?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: You don't take time off to think. There is a<br />
very great number of things that you're doing because you should<br />
be doing them and some of them you like and some of them I suppose<br />
you wouldn't bother to do that goes with the job. But you<br />
don't really stop to say ' Do I like this or not?' You're involved,<br />
it's part of the job and you obviously like the job. If you<br />
set out in this life, this is the best job in it.<br />
QUESTION: There seems to be so many problems in the press like<br />
' Whitlam: Problems Mount'....<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I saw that in yesterday afternoon's Brisbane<br />
paper. QUESTION: I'm wondering if battling with the Premier is a<br />
breeze compared to the problems in Canberra. Is it?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: That heading I noticed in the Brisbane paper<br />
yesterday. It's just a beat-up of something that was in one of<br />
the papers that morning. I mean its just a beat-up there's<br />
nothing to it.<br />
QUESTION: But is it better being up here battling with the<br />
Premier?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Oh I don't know. There are a number of things<br />
that can only be done in Australia since we have a Federal system<br />
it the Federal Government and the State Governments co-operate. I<br />
fr,. nkly think we aren't, here, but in every other State we are.<br />
QUESIOi, We've had a few political handouts in the last few<br />
months hei " rom the Federal Government?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: And you would have had many more, as el . aer<br />
State has, if you had taken them.<br />
QUESTION: But a lo; of these political handouts come at election<br />
time. PR. MINISTER: No, no.<br />
QUESTION: Not just your party<br />
PRIME MINIb.' R: For instance, we were elected two yea:: s ak.<br />
Monday and at , hat time nobody expected that thc : e would btelection<br />
for three year after that. Now in fact there was or<br />
six months ago. Now any . andouts, as you call them, which ar(<br />
taking place this year would 1-ive been done I s i-i 7-<br />
of an election because you ordinaL_ õ expect to bt: r. rur J<br />
and we have a good majority in the House of Represe.. atives and<br />
of course, we still have. One would not expect there to be anot'<br />
election for another 2 years in the House of Representative-, sG<br />
what you say are handouts are part of a continuing program and<br />
the program is in acts of Parliament or in reports which we've<br />
sought and which we've published. They've not just becn in<br />
anticipation of an election and we shouldn't. be having one for<br />
another 2 years. i. </p>
<p>QUESTION: Wt. are having one here.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Oh a State one.<br />
QJESTION: I feel Mr Perc Tucker has been slightly overshadowed<br />
because all the big guns and the big stars have been coming<br />
up from Canberra. Do you think he's going to be lost in the<br />
glitter of it all?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well I don't know how much attention is being<br />
given to various people things often get mesmerised or<br />
concentrated in this way. But what you're talking about, you know,<br />
handouts which are part of programs are being run in other<br />
States too, and they're not having elections. There are a lot<br />
of things that should be being handed out here which are not<br />
being accepted.<br />
QUESTION: I'm sure you would be grossly disappointed if I<br />
didn't mention your relationship with Mr Hawke.?<br />
PRIME MINISTER. ' yes.<br />
QUESTION: What have you disagreed about most strongly?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: There was, I suppose, the Prices/ Incomes Referendum<br />
a year ago. That was actually the only one I can think of where<br />
there was a substantial difference of opinion.<br />
QUESTION: What have you agreed on?<br />
Phi E MINISTER: Naturally enough I am very often in contact<br />
wirh Mr Hawku. I suppose usually a week wouldn't go past,<br />
certainly not a fortnightwhere we didn't have a conversation<br />
face -o -ce or on the telephone, but this is to be expected.<br />
Now there lways a lot of publicity given to any conversa<br />
I have with Mr Hawke but I'm regularly conversing, co. re<br />
with a very great number of people in Australia as you w d<br />
expect. QUESTION: You're so vocal about your meetings, I. er that<br />
he is going to see you at the week end?...<br />
PIT ? 7 MINISTER: Yes.<br />
QUESTION: Exactly how is it when you do get together? fDoes<br />
come in -" ring like a bull or do you sit down and have a ch,<br />
PRIME MINISTER. Oh no, ' ue know each other very ' ell. It is i<br />
there's always a great C-il of publicity if he calls on me. N<br />
other people would call c -i on the same day and not y'et the<br />
same publicity at all. No, 1 publicise the . ieeti-. gs T<br />
have with anybody nor i ta -ct Leca-ise un'.-dIy<br />
watch anybody calling at rny offii: : ini iarliament Housc or at the<br />
Lodge in Canberra or Kirribilli anybody can watch bat they<br />
don't notice. Recently in Sydney there was a group ( f peopl.<br />
calling in the morning to discuss the uranium developm k-nts<br />
in -h i) o1 i T ritor'-; thr-people who were out . t tne<br />
gate to filEi. h 1w ent didn't identify who<br />
these people were. It would have been the biggest story imaginable<br />
if they'd identified them. That day these people didn't announce </p>
<p>that they'd come; I didn't announce that they'd come but<br />
Ministers concerned were all present and nobody dropp,-2!.<br />
what it was. And the next time. in fact, was quitc a lac_.. sessitoi<br />
at the Lodge in Canberra and the following day we announced it<br />
to everybody's surprise. So it is true that you hear a great<br />
deal about meetings or conversations I have with Mr Hawke,<br />
because they're well publicised. But my job inevitably means<br />
that I'm talking to a lot of people all the time, pretty well<br />
every day of the week.<br />
QUESTlON: Also well publicised are your tours and in two weeks<br />
you'll be off on another overseas tour and there's been criticisml<br />
about the fact that you are overseas when you should be at home<br />
say your visit to the U. S. when the econamy was falling apar-t<br />
say when you visited Indonesia and we had the floods in Queensland.<br />
When do you consider you were in the wrong place at th. wrong<br />
time? PRIME MINISTER: The fact is there are some things that can only<br />
be done on behalf of a country by the Head of Government of that<br />
country and there's not a single visit I've made overs'eas that<br />
people would say was not justified. You see, obviouslv. I sh,. ull<br />
visit the U. S. or t-he U. N. or Britain or Japan or Europe or<br />
Indonesia or New Z: c . land or get togaether with the heads of<br />
other countries it -he British Corlamnealth. Now, that is myjob<br />
to do it. I should do it. It's very easy to criticise some<br />
Head of GovernmTent for not being in a particula. L place at a<br />
particular timae. ff onec acceptc&amp; J-all those cirticisms you'd<br />
never budcje you'd be s' : yirkg ' hWill atiat's he doing lip<br />
ir, Queensland in a State election?' e<br />
QUELTION: I teol sure they are.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: At the same time, my Goverment's objects are<br />
quite c-' ralto this campaign. This is the only Governi. t in<br />
Australia r' ch hasn't co-operated withi my Gov_-rn-, uent and<br />
is a very ma~ terial theme to the campaign.<br />
QUESTION: in this area 1 don't ti-ink x: eally terrn .,) r-. ied<br />
about what t'arty i is. It's going to be " he rmn far a.<br />
we're concerned and we kn~ ow the lo-' al andidat:. So 1 can' t<br />
see that you're going to: aftezt ouc decoi* Lion !, ec-( al-. sc in a countrit<br />
is so important that th man i rig',-<br />
PRI_ That may be, but. nevertheles-, iiu<br />
centL of pe:; ple certainly 80 per cont , uld -' ote<br />
accoic 9olitLical party. i ion'It think there's : h d( k<br />
about that. I tflin its quiLtu aji dlpropriate thing if peopl<br />
want to ' 1. inow ,7 -Ll-meafrer th-.. z celect will votr or Peak.<br />
of us would be if i7, roc t meithb. rs of politi<br />
parties. None of us. u. one member CQuc-ns. L iC<br />
Parliament is in without be4--a -member of a Part,,,, In the T<br />
of fepresentativos it is yszars . years since th. -e w: -3 E<br />
whLo d.. drn't belong to a poiitical pa., ty. So it's t. L. that<br />
membership of a pc. irical party would make all ti~ e di-forenceperhaps<br />
20 per cc-nt of their J~ ote ccenia be 1,, er..-oyaI. ano. 80 pe ' r~ t<br />
would be uependenit on their being members of a pc'litical party.<br />
QUESTION: Wh-t do yo-u think of independents?<br />
MRS WHITLAM: You are not indepeiclknt if you are connected with<br />
a political party at all. That is a deceit that is often practised. </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTt.': There are some issues on which our Par. I and in<br />
fact dii Varics Allow~ members to vote its they wish on some<br />
social issues but in general what makes the parliamentary<br />
system work is the party system. This is the way it works in<br />
US., N. Z. there's nothing to be apologetic about or<br />
ashamed about. Nobody can afford to stand for Parliament unless<br />
he is a member of a political party even a very rich man<br />
couldn't afford it, would not get elected to Parliament, unless<br />
he also had the support of a political party. A very good man or<br />
a very rich man might make the difference where things were close.<br />
QUESTION: Mr Nixon said " I've always thought that politics was<br />
much harder for the wives than it is for men. They can fight<br />
the battles whilee the wives suffer on the sidelines." Have<br />
you ever had to suffer, Mrs Whitlam?<br />
MRS WHITLAM: Quite often.<br />
QUESTION: When? How?<br />
MRS WHITLAM: I'm not going to say, or give instances. There are<br />
many occasions on which I and other wives have been hurt by the<br />
actions well, not so much by the actions as the reactions to<br />
actions of our husbands or our Parties.<br />
QUESTION: What do you think the perfect politEicians wife<br />
should be?<br />
MRS WHITLAM: I think she should just be a wife. I don't think<br />
she should be any different than other wives. If she has a goal<br />
in ilife she should be left to pursue that goal. If she has not,<br />
shi shjuld be left alone also. She shouldn't be plagued because<br />
she dc.! sn't want to do anything. She shouldn't be plagued<br />
becau,. -he does want to do something.<br />
QUESTION: -think you said in your diary that you were si<br />
of people talking about how much money you got and I dor kwhether<br />
it was really that or the fact that they were cr. (. sing<br />
the fact that you have jobs, positions and they would have liked<br />
to see you doing " goody goody" work.<br />
MRS WHITLAM: I do what you call ' goody goody work' as well. B..<br />
yi) i can't do that all the time.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: You see the thing is that a poiiticanr, wife 1I<br />
do an i----nse amount of work for which she's not paid can"~<br />
be paid. -instancq, my wife goes to an immense number of<br />
functions in electorate which I can't go to r w because rcf<br />
I'm more tied up than E and if Margaret goes ~ o some functi.;<br />
elsewhere in Australia, L. c doesn't get paid. Sure, she gets<br />
her fare-paid, but if she stavp overnight she has to pay her<br />
accommodation. She gets no aii. r-e for that. 11olic,<br />
wife is a full time job for which he alone is paid.<br />
QUESTION: Getting back to your electorate, do you think its a<br />
disadvantage to have a Prime Minster as a representative?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I think it's compensated for by the fact that<br />
having a Prime Minister for your local member is likely to bring about<br />
more weight for what he says. You can't say that a thing should<br />
be done just because a Prime minister asks for it to be done. </p>
<p>-6-<br />
It ought to be done because it should be done, whoever asks.<br />
Nevertheless, I suppose it is a fact that if the Prime Minister<br />
asks a Department to look into a particular matter, the Department<br />
is more likely to jump to-it than if a private member asks about<br />
it. So its compensated for. The matters you take up are<br />
likely to have more punch behind them. You were worrying about the<br />
lot of a politician's wife. The thing that worries me more,<br />
probably, is that the kids cop it. Now you quoted that heading<br />
there in an afternoon paper. Well, afternoon papers are not<br />
terribly serious publications but nevertheless you're likely to<br />
have some hoarding~ on the streets. Now if your children are young<br />
and we still have a daughter who's only 20 if she sees some<br />
of these things, she's likely to have a clutch at the heart<br />
and say " Oh, what's this." They cop it much more.<br />
QUESTION: What qualities have you tried to instill in your<br />
children?<br />
MRS WHITLAM: I think the qualities I admire most in children are<br />
obedience and politeness.<br />
QUESTION: Have they ever let you down?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: On both scores. No, they're good kids. They've<br />
been very satisfactory. But they' re independent persons.<br />
MRS WHITLAM: But they were well disciplined weren't they?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes, we were tough.<br />
QUESTION: Do you believe in the occasional smack?<br />
MRS WKITLAM: Oh certainly. I was always the one who had<br />
to do L. smacking, though, because he wasn't there.<br />
PRIME MINIS~ rR: When I was home I took the brunt of that.<br />
run to you as a court of appeal, sort of thing.<br />
QUESTION: Mrs Whitlam is your television program " With Margaret<br />
Whitlam" finished yet?<br />
MRS WHITLAM: Yes for this season it has.<br />
QUE. Is it a sore point with you?<br />
MRS WH7T'NM: What do you mean? I enjoyed it; it was fun.<br />
QUESTION: We_ you very disappointed about the ratings and -L.<br />
fact that they removed y-' i from a prime time?<br />
MRS WHITLAM: The ratings situaition was very unfair. That was<br />
unfair. I was disappointed in attitude. I wa.-very please,<br />
with the way the program went.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Did they show it up here?<br />
QUESTION: No.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: You should have.<br />
QUESTION: Why? </p>
<p>-7-<br />
MRS WHITLAM: Why no;.?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: It was great.<br />
QUESTION: Did you watch it?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: It was easier after 10 I think, but I wouldn't have been<br />
home to see it more than once. No, I've seen it a couple of t. imes.<br />
I think it turned out very well.<br />
QUESTION: What would you rather see her as: an interviewer or<br />
an interviewee?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Oh, both, both. I mean, she's got a lot of<br />
experience now. She's a human person, so either way.<br />
QUESTION: You mentioned in the press that you'd learnt a lot<br />
during the program?<br />
MRS WHITLAM: Certainly, because I knew nothing about the workings<br />
of a program like that and I like to know how its done and I'd<br />
know how to approach it another time. And/ alsoI'd know what<br />
to be wary of on your side of the clipboard.<br />
QUESTION: Are you passing hints on to Mr Whitlam?<br />
MRS WHITLAM: No, no, he's my mentor.<br />
QUESTION: What would you really like to be good at?<br />
MRS WHITLAM: Oh, I don't know, do you mean I or we?<br />
QUESTION: Both.<br />
MRS WHIP-AM: Something new or something old?<br />
PRIME MINIS17it: I think we're all right at what we're doing.<br />
QUESTION: You wouldn't like to be a champion knitter?<br />
MRS WHITLAM: I am.<br />
QUESTION: Nothing else like that?<br />
PRIR._ ' 11NISTER: She's an excellent knitter. She really is.<br />
QUESTION: I think you mentioned that last time you were here.<br />
MI WHTTLAM: Wll, you Must have asked me.<br />
QUESTION: I was asking a. it who chooses clothes and who had the<br />
greatest say. With yourwhole livesjis there anything you'd like to<br />
change?<br />
MRS WHITLAM: Past or present?<br />
QUESTION: Past.<br />
MRS WHITLAM: I suppose you wish there were things you hadn't done<br />
and things that you wish you'd had time to do. Overall I think<br />
I'd really wish for moreto do it all in. </p>
<p>-8-<br />
QUESTION: Politicans are a cartoonist's delight. Have you ever<br />
kept any of their masterpieces?<br />
MRS WHITLAM: I wouldn't say they were always masterpieces.<br />
QUESTION: Which ones appeal to your sense of humour?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Oh there are dozens. But the funniest are always<br />
those about other people.<br />
MRS WHITLAM: The thing about cartoons is that they date so. You<br />
know, you keep them for a couple of years thinking they're absolutely<br />
marvellous and then you wonder what it was all about.<br />
QUESTION: Have you heard any good jokes about yourself lately?<br />
People do use your name for a joke. Do they tell it to your<br />
face?<br />
MRS WHITLAM: It depends what jokes you're talking about. Tell us<br />
one now.<br />
QUESTION: No, I'm not good with jokes, I can't remember them.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: A lot of jokes, I now find, people attach my name<br />
to a terrific number of jokes I can remember being used about<br />
Billy McMahon and Bob Menzies. I can't say they fit to me<br />
the jokes they told about John Gortin. But particularly the ones<br />
about Menzies and McMahon. When you're been in politics for a<br />
fair time they crop up again. Whether you like it or not it happens,<br />
so there's no use complaining. It doesn't really worry me.<br />
QUESTION: What never ceases to amaze you about Mr Whitlam?<br />
MRS WHITLAM ( unclear)<br />
QUESTION: What never ceases to amaze you about Mrs Whitli<br />
PRIME MINISTER: " Custom never stales her infinite variety".<br />
MRS WHITLAM: i say!<br />
QUES'" ION: What do you think Mc. z ' qhitlam looks good in?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I'm not particularly good at describing these<br />
things.<br />
QUESTION: Have:.' t you ever said ' That's the be:; t thing I've<br />
ever seen you in. Wear it dress again.'<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I'm not vex2 . t describing materials or<br />
colours. I remember for instance, _ wout 10 years ago I'd<br />
brought her back some Thai silk maybe blue Thai silk and it made<br />
up superbly. On a formal occasion she would stand out very<br />
elegantly. Well I suppose you've caught me. I just don! t think<br />
very often of this sort of thing.<br />
MRS WHITLAM: He mentions it at the time and then forgets. He's<br />
generally more impressed by women in evening dress than in<br />
any other dress. </p>
<p>Q -9-<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes that would ie so. If I've cihosen something,<br />
naturally enough I'd notice it bo.'' use I'v sometimes brought<br />
back things.<br />
QUESTION: Is there anything he's brought back you thought was<br />
absolutely ghastly.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I don't overdo it. If she doesn't like it, then<br />
that's alright as far as I'm concerned.<br />
MRS WHITLAM: They just go to the bottom of the pile of things<br />
to be made up, that's all.<br />
QUESTION: After elections these days, they usually play a<br />
song appropriate to the occasion. Mrs Whitlam what song title<br />
would you choose for your husband?<br />
MRS WHITLAM: I'm not anticipating him going out, anyway, and<br />
requiring a song.<br />
QUESTION: I don't mean it to be a swan song. Just something<br />
like, " You're just too good to be true" or " Baby face" or<br />
something. PRIME MINISTER: Oh no, forget that!<br />
MRS WHITLAM: Actually the titles of pop songs these days don't<br />
always indicate the contents.<br />
QUESTION: Have you got a song that means something to both of<br />
you. Advance Australia Fair?<br />
MRS WHITLAM: No, I'm afraid we don't. Perhaps the love theme<br />
from " Tr'ristan and Isolde" the love duet....<br />
PRIME MINIL'Fq: Or at our age, " Never on Sunday"!<br />
QUESTION: What are your Christmas plans? You will be overseas<br />
won't you?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: We'll be in London for Christmas.<br />
QUESTION: What would be your best Christmas preseint?<br />
MRS 2LAM: Actually the best Christmas pr ; s-. cL xiolid b to<br />
have everyone together, which is just about the most impossible<br />
thing fo-. ir family because there are four children who are not<br />
all over the .: orld now, but who always seem to be and they are<br />
here. PRIME MINISTER: The first time they were all together for 10 years<br />
was at Easter last year in We went over to see Mr Heath<br />
and the Queen about some Constitutñ orn.-l things and they all<br />
happened to be there at the one time. The first time for 10 years.<br />
Not that they're so old. The eldeit is only<br />
MRS WHITLAM: Only!<br />
QUESTION: What would be a beaut Christmas present for you then. </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTEP: I don't know. You throw me so much with these<br />
questions you ask.<br />
QUESTION: You don't need a new razor or something like that?<br />
MRS WHITLAM: He always needs a new razor.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes, yes.<br />
QUESTION: I do hope it is a most enjoyable and happy time for<br />
you for the festive season, and that politics are not too much<br />
of a problem during that time for you and my very sincere thanks<br />
to you, Mrs Whitlam and Mr Whitlam for appearing on the program. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
