<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1633</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: PM. NO. 79/1967 - TALKS WITH UNITED STATES MISSION</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/07/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001633.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS: PM. NO. 79/ 1967<br />
TALKS WITH UNITED STATES MISSION<br />
The Frime Minister tonight described as " very valuable<br />
and informative" the talks held today between representatives of the U. S.<br />
Government and senior members of the Australian Cabinet.<br />
The talks, which were held at The Lodge, ran from<br />
11 a. m. to 6 p. m. The U. S. group comprised Mr Clark Clifford, General<br />
Maxwell Taylor, the United States Ambassador, Mr Clark, Mr R. C. Steadman<br />
of the U. S. Defense Department, Mr H. Freeman Matthews, State<br />
Department and Mr E. Cronk, Counsellor, U. S. Embassy. The Australian<br />
party was made up of the Prime Minister, Mr Holt, the Minister for Trade<br />
and Industry, Mr McEwen, the Treasurer, Mr McMahon the Minister for<br />
External Affairs, Mr Hasluck, the Minister for Defence, Mr Fairhall, the<br />
Secretary of the Prime Minister's Department, Sir John Bunting, and the<br />
Australian Ambassador to the United States, Mr Keith V 7aller.<br />
The Prime Minister said that the talks were extensive<br />
and had ranged over all those aspects of the Vietnam situation which the<br />
representatives from both groups had raised.<br />
He and his colleagues would be reporting on the<br />
discussions to Cabinet. No decisbns had been sought or taken on any aspect,<br />
but the exchange of information and views would be helpful to further<br />
consider ation by the Governments of both countries.<br />
CANBERRA 3Cth July, 1967 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
