<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9199</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P J KEATING MP APEC BUSINESS FORUM: AUSTRALIAN REPRESENTATIVES</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/04/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009199.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINJISTER3/ 9<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
APEC BUSIN~ ESS FORUM: AUSTRALIAN REPRESENTATIVES<br />
At our meeting last year in Seattle, APEC leaders agreed to establish an APEC<br />
Business Forum to " identify issues APEC should address to facilitate regionaf ijide7<br />
and investm ent and encourage the future development of business _ netwo~ rks*<br />
thioughout the region".<br />
The APEC Business Forum will bring together one representative of large business<br />
and one of small to medium enterprise from each APEC member economy and will<br />
report to the 1994 APEC leaders' meeting in Indonesia. It will play a vital role in<br />
providing leaders with a business view of constraints to the further development of<br />
trade and investment in the region and ways in which APEC can assist in overcoming<br />
them. It will also consider ways of involving business much more closely in APEC's<br />
work. I am pleased to announce that Australia's representatives on the Forum will be<br />
Mr Philip Brass, Managing Director of Pacific Dunlop, and Mrs Irnelda Roche,<br />
Managing Director of Nutri-Metics International. Both Philip Brass and Imelda Roche<br />
have extensive business experience in the Asia-Pacific region as well as in Australia<br />
and I believe they will make a strong contribution-to the Forum's work.<br />
Pacific Dunlop is one of Australia's largest international companies and has an<br />
increasing proportion of its operations in the Asia-Pacific region. As the Australian<br />
representative at the APEC Business Roundtable meeting in Seattle last year,<br />
Philip Brass has already made a significant contribution to dialogue between business<br />
in APEC's member economies. He was also a member of my APEC Business<br />
Consultative Panel which gave me valuable assistance during my preparations for the<br />
Seattle meeting. Philip Brass was BRW Australian Businessman of the Year in 1984.<br />
Under the joint leadership of Imelda Roche and her husband, Bill Roche, Nutri-Metics<br />
International initially expanded throughout the Pacific region to New Zealand, Japan,<br />
Singapore, Malaysia, Brunei and Thailand and more recently to Hong Kong and<br />
China. </p>
<p>2<br />
Mrs Roche led the recruitment and development of the Nutri-Metics Asia-Pacific sales<br />
force and was awarded the Australian Pursuit of Excellence Award in 1986 for her<br />
role in the direct selling industry. She was named Australian businesswoman of the<br />
year in 1991. In 1993 Imelda Roche was appointed chairman of the World Federation<br />
of Direct Selling Associations and Nutrimetics was named BRW retailer of the year. I<br />
attach a high priority to strengthening APEC's policy dialogue on small and mediumsized<br />
businesses and am looking forward to working with Mrs Roche on this.<br />
The APEC Business Forum is expected to meet twice before November 1994. A date<br />
has not yet been set for the first meeting.<br />
CANBERRA April 21, 1994 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
