<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2457</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE RT HON W MCMAHON MP ON SUSPENSION OF STANDING ORDERS</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/08/1971</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002457.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA<br />
SPEECH BY<br />
The Rt Hon. W. McMAHON, M. P.<br />
ON<br />
SUSPENSION OF STANDING ORDERS<br />
[ From the ' Parliamentary Debates', 17 August 1971]<br />
Mr McMAHON ( Lowe-Prime Minis-<br />
-ter) ( 4.32)-On another occasion I<br />
described the Leader of the Opposition<br />
( Mr Whitlam) as an extraordinarily feline<br />
person. I have no wish to change my views<br />
after today. I have every intention of trying<br />
to deal with the facts, and I want to<br />
mention -the constructive actions that have<br />
been taken by this Governmeni, whether it<br />
has been led by the right honourable member<br />
for Higgins ( Mr Gorton) or by myself.<br />
I want to mention what we are doing to<br />
ensure the greatness of this country. I have<br />
no intention to degenerate into personalities<br />
in the way that the Leader of the<br />
Opposition, this feline person, has done.<br />
Let me mention one or two facts. Not<br />
one of the statements that the honourable<br />
gentleman made about me is true in substance.<br />
Let me deal first of all with the<br />
question of my association with Sir Frank<br />
Packer over 40 years. It is true that on 8th<br />
November 1932 or somewhere about that<br />
time I did sign the memorandum and<br />
articles of association of his company. I<br />
was then an articled clerk in Allen, Allen<br />
and Hemsley. I had never met Frank<br />
Packer; I had never met his associates. I<br />
did not know who he was. The men to<br />
whom I was clerking, Sir Norman Cowper<br />
and Mr Arthur Hemsley, asked me to sign<br />
the document. Of course I signed it. Any<br />
person with a knowledge of law and a<br />
knowledge of the way companies are<br />
formed would have done exactly as I did.<br />
Secondly, the Leader of the Opposition<br />
referred to the statement relating to the so<br />
called payment for the articles that had<br />
been written by the right honourable mem-<br />
1432 1/ 71 ber for Higgins. I did not ask the right<br />
honourable member whether he was being<br />
paid. For a fact, I did not think he was.<br />
But I see no reason in the world why I<br />
should ask him, particularly after I had<br />
read the article. It was no business of mine.<br />
If people want to ask him, he can be<br />
asked and I am sure he will give the kind<br />
of answer that he feels appropriate to be<br />
given. The honourable gentleman also referred<br />
to the fact that in some article in the<br />
' Daily Telegraph' -there was a forecast of<br />
some further action to be taken. I will give<br />
the author of -that article complete liberty<br />
to state positively, without any recrimination<br />
from me, whether he had discussed<br />
this matter with me or had let me know<br />
that the article was to be written. No<br />
member of the ' Daily Telegraph' contacted<br />
me prior to the publication of the article,<br />
and in fact I had not talked to Mr Alan<br />
Reid for at least 3 weeks prior to that, and<br />
I have not spoken to him since his return<br />
from Fiji. This is the kind of rumour and<br />
nastiness that are inherent in the mind of<br />
the honourable gentleman. I intend for the<br />
rest to ignore them completely and to get<br />
on with the job of governing this country<br />
and doing the best we can to contribute to<br />
its greatness.<br />
The Leader of the Opposition referred<br />
to the fact that during the last session he<br />
also moved a censure -motion on me. He<br />
has lost no time for a second one although<br />
we wanted to give him more time for his<br />
censure motion. I repeat that he is not<br />
only showing his inherent nastiness but is<br />
also attempting to obstruct the business of </p>
<p>this House and is trying to prevent us<br />
from getting on with the constructive work<br />
of government. This is the device of a man<br />
and a party with nothing to off er and a<br />
great deal to be ashamed of. When the<br />
Minister for Foreign Affairs ( Mr N. H.<br />
Bowen) brings forward his paper on<br />
foreign affairs, I for one will participate in<br />
the debate, and I believe that I will be able<br />
to show not only that the Leader of the<br />
Opposition is dangerous to the security of<br />
this country but that wherever he went on<br />
his recent overseas trip he created an<br />
impression which was bad for Australia<br />
and which brought him into ridicule. I<br />
believe that in every country he visited he<br />
left a most unfavourable, even bad,<br />
impression. Mr Shery-I raise a point of order.<br />
The Prime Minister has just referred to the<br />
Leader of the Opposition being a danger to<br />
this country. This is impugning the character<br />
and the responsibility of the Leader of<br />
the Opposition and I ask the Prime Minister<br />
to withdraw -the remark.<br />
Mr SPEAKER-Orderi I do not think<br />
that the Prime Minister at any stage<br />
impugned the personal character of the<br />
Leader of the Opposition. I think the honourable<br />
member is perhaps confused as to<br />
the substance of the Prime Minister's<br />
remarks about security.<br />
Mr Sherry-Mr Speaker, with all due<br />
respect -to your ruling, if the Prime Minister.<br />
has referred to the Leader of the<br />
Opposition as being a security risk, this is<br />
certainly in my view a reflection on the<br />
character of the Leader of the Opposition<br />
and I ask the Prime Minister to withdraw<br />
the remark.<br />
Mr SPERAKER-Order! Of course I<br />
have not a verbatim note of what the<br />
Prime Minister said, * but from listening to<br />
him I do not think that he said that the<br />
Leader of the Opposition was a security<br />
risk. SMr McMAHON-This is the device of<br />
a man and a -party with nothing to offer<br />
and a great deal to be ashamed of. It is<br />
the attitude of a party that has been conditioned<br />
by 22 years on the Opposition<br />
benches to think only destructively.<br />
Obviously it has no mind for constructive<br />
contributions to the work of Parliament<br />
and it has no stomach, as I said before,<br />
for facts. It prefers to perform by innuendo, suspicion and false statement. Let this<br />
be known: We in the Liberal-Country<br />
Party Government want to get on with -the<br />
real business of government. We believe<br />
that Australia is a country with a tremendous<br />
future. We know that the people are<br />
sound at heart and we know that they are<br />
sensible. It is our task to represent them<br />
here in this Parliament, and we must not<br />
be diverted from that task * by tawdry personal<br />
issues raised by the Opposition. We<br />
must -take initiatives in nation building on<br />
their behalf. We are doing that and we will<br />
continue to do it.<br />
The Leader of the Opposition is upset<br />
because I have made some ministerial<br />
changes. What has this to do with<br />
him? This is the business of the Government,<br />
and we do not want him interfering<br />
with what are exclusively our affairs. He<br />
has plenty -to do trying to get his own<br />
Party into shape and, if I can go a stagc<br />
further, in coming to terms with the<br />
President of the Australian Council of<br />
Trade Unions, who keeps rocking -the boat<br />
with his excursions into what should be<br />
the Labor Party's exclusive preserves. It<br />
has been said-and I repeat this againthat<br />
I am influenced by the Press. I have<br />
been in Parliament a long time. I have held<br />
a great number of port fol ios-more, I<br />
think, than any other person in the House.<br />
I make up my own mind what I personally<br />
should do in the interests of the nation,<br />
not in the interests of anyone else. Of<br />
course, I listen to advice from my colleagues<br />
in the Ministry, in the Cabinet and<br />
in my Party. I have consultations with<br />
industry. I meet the Press and I meet the<br />
people. But of ' this honourable members<br />
may be sure: I have never taken and will<br />
never take any action designed to please the<br />
Press people. I suppose that I have had<br />
more quarrels with them than has any other<br />
person in this House. Of course, on many<br />
occasions -they have -been in praise of me.<br />
If we look over the long term, I think the<br />
criticism has been pretty strong too. But<br />
who in this House has not gone through<br />
exactly the same experiences?<br />
The second point that is referred to by<br />
the Leader of the Opposition is tbat of<br />
leadership. I and . my former colleague know<br />
-we are probably the only 2 in this<br />
House who do kncew-that it carries very<br />
great responsibilities. But I want to ask<br />
this question: What leadership does the </p>
<p>honourable member for Werriwa give to his<br />
Party today? This is the man who incited<br />
young men inducted for national service to<br />
refuse to serve in Vietnam when it was<br />
their duty to do so. This is the man who<br />
approved the attempt by some unions to<br />
interfere with the legitimate trade of this<br />
country. This is the man who gave tacit<br />
support to the left wing unions and the<br />
professional dissenters during the recent<br />
rugby tour. This is the man who went to<br />
China to play party politics with wheat<br />
and finished up by being a total advocate<br />
for the -policy of -a foreign power-the<br />
greatest Communist power in Asia.<br />
The Budget that the Treasurer ( Mr<br />
Snedden) will bring down tonight involves<br />
a motion of real substance. The motion<br />
before the House this afternoon -has none.<br />
The Budget presents fiscal policy and an<br />
explanation of monetary policy for Australia<br />
for the whole of 197 1-72. It is therefore<br />
a paramount importance and should<br />
be treated accordingly. It is right, I know,<br />
for the Leader of the Opposition to talk<br />
about unity and good government. We talk<br />
about it. But we talk about it because we<br />
know what it means and we know the contribution<br />
we will be able to make. They<br />
are, I believe, the qualities that a well<br />
ordered country needs and that, I believe,<br />
Australia is getting in full measure from<br />
the Liberal-Country Party Government.<br />
Let me remind honourable members of<br />
the performance of my Government in<br />
recent months. it * has been here just on 5<br />
months and in that time it has brought<br />
down a solid list of domestic legislation. It<br />
has broken completely new ground in<br />
foreign affairs. It has tackled a range of<br />
problems, not of its own making, including<br />
inflation and the fall in the price of wool,<br />
which are pressing heavily on the country<br />
today. I believe that they will be dealt with<br />
effectively, providing we can have continuitv<br />
and steadiness in government. I believe,<br />
too, that it is of importance to make the<br />
federal system of government work effectively.<br />
That great spirit of free enterprise<br />
which has served Australia so well through<br />
all its history should not be stifled by controls<br />
and directions from Canberra.<br />
I have said that we believe in co-operation<br />
as the basis for unity. In 5 months we<br />
have established, I believe, a new relationship<br />
with the States. What we did, in addition,<br />
was to give them a general growth tax. We gave them payroll tax which was<br />
designed to stop them from coming. to<br />
Canberra cap in hand and begging us to<br />
give them increasing access to funds. I<br />
emphasise that what we have done all this<br />
while is to continue the development of<br />
this country and we have also-this will be<br />
reflected in the Budget tonight-developed<br />
policies which are directed at reducing<br />
inflationary pressures because inflation is<br />
one of our greatest problems. Success here<br />
is the basis on which we can successfully<br />
plan for the future.<br />
We must contain and, I believe, we must<br />
reverse the serious escalation of costs and<br />
prices. We have begun investigations as to<br />
how arbitration -procedures might be<br />
improved. We have done this to give<br />
greater emphasis in wage decisions to the<br />
economic consequences of the Commonwealth<br />
Conciliation and Arbitration Commission's<br />
awards. We have also investigated<br />
what broader measures we might<br />
take to bring about the needed restraints in<br />
wage increases and in wage costs. We have<br />
come to grips with the crisis in some of<br />
our rural industries, particularly in the case<br />
of wool. Already, we have adopted reconstruction<br />
and special aid policies in order<br />
to assist -them. We have reduced the<br />
migrant intake to contain costs and to<br />
allow a greater concentration on personal<br />
quality. We have passed legislation controlling<br />
resale price maintenance and we are<br />
reviewing the Trade Practices Aot so that<br />
we can strengthen it and encourage much<br />
more vigorous competition.<br />
On the advice of the Tariff Board the<br />
Government also has accepted the need for<br />
a systematic review of tariffs and this is<br />
proceeding. My Government has also<br />
reviewed important aspects of social welfare.<br />
We have done so because we consider<br />
it a prime duty to do more for the needy<br />
and the neglected. We want to clean out<br />
the pockets of poverty wherever they<br />
appear. The effective development of an<br />
adequate social welfare system, to which I<br />
have pledged my Government, depends<br />
heavily on a good working arrangement<br />
between the Commonwealth and the<br />
States. That is another reason why our new<br />
understanding with the States is so important.<br />
In March we gave pensioners a supplementary<br />
increase. We did so because we<br />
thought social justice demanded a rise to </p>
<p>offset the sharp increase in living costs<br />
which was causing unexpected hardship.<br />
We also secured a satisfactory arrangement<br />
with the Australian Medical Association<br />
about fees to make the revised medical<br />
benefits scheme operate effectively, and we<br />
overhauled hospital insurance benefits to<br />
give a more extensive cover to fund members.<br />
So many of these activities bear on<br />
the quality of life which must ' be of<br />
increasing concern to everyone in Australia.<br />
We are, after all, searching for a<br />
quality of life which will be better than the<br />
one that we have today. This is the end<br />
objective of all our efforts, because the<br />
quality of life is just about everything that<br />
belongs to and relates to man. It is his<br />
place in the environment-the good he<br />
does, how he lives with his neighbours and<br />
the measures of his contentment-but at<br />
the same time we must preserve our freedoms<br />
and our civil liberties. ( Extension of<br />
time granted) We must tackle the congestion<br />
and pollution of our cities. Now,<br />
having said that, I turn briefly to our<br />
record in foreign affairs. The Minister for<br />
Foreign Affairs will deal with the subject in<br />
detail later-I hope tomorrow but at the<br />
latest on Thursday.<br />
Mr Daly-Mr Speaker, I take a point of<br />
order. My point of order is that this is all<br />
very interesting, but what does it have to<br />
do with the motion?<br />
Mr SPEAKER-Order! There is no substance<br />
in the point of order.<br />
Mr McMAHON-What does the socalled<br />
censure motion have to do with the<br />
House? As I said, the Foreign Minister will<br />
deal with the subject later. In the past<br />
months we have made considerable progress<br />
with the prospect of getting our<br />
troops home from Vietnam as the operation<br />
there winds down. You will recall, Sir,<br />
that I announced further withdrawals at<br />
the end of March. I will state the Government's<br />
policy in the House this week. We<br />
have completed new appraisals of our -relations<br />
with Japan, Russia and China. These<br />
appraisals took place over a year or more<br />
but they have brought us to new decisions<br />
in respect of all 3 countries in the last few<br />
months. I will not repeat them now. They<br />
speak well for our future in the international<br />
community.<br />
Our aid programmes particularly in the<br />
Asian -and the Pacific region continue at a high level. We have also made progress<br />
with the 5-power defence arrangements for<br />
Malaysia-Singapore and we have become a<br />
member of the Organisation for Economic<br />
Co-operation and Development. Wha~ t contribution<br />
has the Opposition made to<br />
national progress? Absolutely none.<br />
Indeed, by i-ts actions and its abstentions it<br />
has aggravated the problems of the day.<br />
The Labor Party has encouraged a contempt<br />
for law and order and the rights of<br />
individual citizens. A clear example can be<br />
seen on the industrial scene and the<br />
increase in political strikes. We have had a<br />
rash of industrial strikes and stoppages<br />
which last year cost the work force nearly<br />
$ 31m in wages. The loss to the nation in<br />
output and the consequent effect on prices<br />
is enormous. We must not forget that the<br />
number of man days lost * by individual<br />
disputes has gone up 21 times in the last 3<br />
years. Now, I want the House to answer<br />
this question: What has the Lepder of the<br />
Opposition done about this? The answer<br />
is positive-nothing at all. In all of this<br />
he has been silent, and by his silence<br />
he has given consent. He has stood<br />
by help~ essly while his authority has been<br />
eroded and his bailiwick invaded by Mr<br />
Bob Hawke, the President of the Australian<br />
Council of Trade Unions, another<br />
leader who is causing responsible people in<br />
the trade union movement a great deal of<br />
activity. Another question I want to pose is<br />
this: Who is really speaking for Labor? It<br />
is not a question of who runs the country;<br />
it is a question of who runs the Labor<br />
Party. Mr Jacobi -Ask Frank Packer.<br />
Mr McMAHON-He would give the<br />
same answer on this occasion because he<br />
cannot decide, as no-one else can decide,<br />
who is running the trade union movement.<br />
I want to say more about the Leader of<br />
the* Opposition, but I think it best to leave<br />
to the judgment of the House what it<br />
thinks about his censure motion, and him.<br />
I believe that answer will be given before 6<br />
o'clock tonight.<br />
Let me return to the overseas visit by<br />
the Leader of the Opposition. He went on<br />
a disastrous-I use the word deliberately-<br />
visit to Peking after he had given<br />
his tacit support to protests against the<br />
South African football tour. In China he<br />
conceded every single point the Chinese </p>
<p>made to him, and he did so in public. This<br />
was a disservice to Australia without any<br />
precedent. His performance is written into<br />
the record for all to read and for history<br />
to see. More will -be said about China in<br />
the foreign affairs debate this session, but<br />
let me say just this: I believe his visit<br />
compromised discussions which the Australian<br />
Wheat Board was just about to<br />
begin with the Chinese when he announced<br />
his intention to go to China. I believe he<br />
compromised the -first moves we were making<br />
through diplomatic channels to open<br />
up a dialogue with China. As a result of<br />
some cocktail gossip with a foreign representative<br />
in China, he caused more havoc<br />
than any man could have caused either in<br />
Australia or in any other part of the<br />
world. I believe it is the first time in Australia's<br />
history that a Leader of the Opposition<br />
has been the total advocate for<br />
another country's cause. I believe it is also<br />
the first time that any Australian political<br />
leader has presumed to tell other countries<br />
horw they should run their business, and he<br />
did so publicly. He discredited the President<br />
of the United States of America by<br />
telling him he would be kicked out. He told<br />
Japan that it should cancel its treaties. Later<br />
when I have an opportunity to speak in the<br />
foreign affairs debate I will disclose more<br />
of his tactics and more of the mischief he<br />
has caused.<br />
I have visited every State in Australia-<br />
some several times-in the last few<br />
months. I have seen great progress in<br />
national development wherever I have<br />
been. As I1 went around I ' became aware<br />
that many people are deeply troubled by<br />
some ol the trends developing in Australia<br />
today. They are concerned with the<br />
increase in industrial disputes and lawlessness.<br />
They * are concerned about the issue<br />
of -law and order. They want to retain<br />
their right to dissent, but they do not want<br />
their civil liberties interfered with ' by mass<br />
protests or professionally promoted demonstrations.<br />
They do not want their right of<br />
choice within the law interfered with. They<br />
expect their parliamentarians to take note<br />
of these issues and to give them a lead.<br />
This, 11 -believe, my Government is doing<br />
and is doing with strength.<br />
May I now return to the principles relating<br />
to constitutional law and practice? So<br />
much doubt has been cast these days on<br />
the Cabinet system that I felt it would ' he appropriate for * me to make some statement<br />
about it. Of course, it is the Opposition's<br />
policy to cheapen and denigrate<br />
Cabinet. But I have another attitude<br />
altogether, and a far better one. I affirm<br />
my faith in the principle of Cabinet government.<br />
It is central to my own Administration.<br />
It is the practice which ' best suits<br />
the executive in our democratic parliamentary<br />
system. It must work effectively,<br />
whether as a Cabinet, as a ministry or<br />
through the system of committees which<br />
has recently been reconstructed, if parliamentary<br />
democracy is to ' be sustained. My<br />
concern as Prime Minister relates to policy.<br />
Cabinet is the proper instrument for<br />
the development of that policy. A change<br />
in party leadership and Ministers does not<br />
invalidate the Government's authority. It<br />
has not done so in the past and it does not<br />
do so now. It is the coalition Government<br />
of the Liberal Party and the Country Party<br />
which the people put back into office less<br />
than 2 years ago. ( Extension of time<br />
granted) It is the coalition Government<br />
that I lead, and its authority continues in<br />
force. It has operated and will continue to<br />
operate with due respect to law and with<br />
due respect to process in the area of the<br />
Cabinet system, in the relationship with the<br />
States -and with the electorate.<br />
I can understand the disappointment of<br />
the Opposition that a change in leadership,<br />
and the other changes that have been<br />
made, have nort brought about some reduction<br />
in our capacity to govern, our intention<br />
to govern or our right to govern. The<br />
motion that is before the House is, I<br />
believe, a product of that disappointment.<br />
A similar motion was moved in vain in<br />
March when I took over as Prime Minister.<br />
I repeat that today's motion will be in<br />
vain. I am perfectly confident that the<br />
people of Australia understand what I am<br />
saying. They understand, firstly, that they<br />
gave us authority to govern and that we<br />
still have that authority. They understand.<br />
secondly, that we are thoroughly capable<br />
to exercise that authority to their satisfaction.<br />
They understand, thirdly, ' that it<br />
would be folly to transfer this authority to<br />
another party unqualified and totally<br />
unable to discharge it effectively. I suspect<br />
they understand that the whole of today's<br />
exercise by the Opposition is nothing else<br />
but humbug. </p>
<p>I must remind the House that we are<br />
known abroad in the great majority of<br />
countries. Despite what the Leader of the<br />
Opposition said, we have given this<br />
country great national responsibility and<br />
stable and progressive administration over<br />
a period now running into 22 years, close<br />
to a quarter of a century. This is known<br />
and respected overseas, as it is here. This<br />
administration is not upset by changes in<br />
leadership, by ministerial re-arrangements or by any statements the Leader of the<br />
Opposition might make. I want to state to<br />
you positively, Sir, that you will see evidence<br />
of unity in this Government. You<br />
will find that the Liberal Party which I<br />
lead, with the Country Party standing<br />
behind us, will give to this country ' the<br />
kind of government that it needs and<br />
which will take it to a very much higher<br />
destiny than we know at the moment or<br />
that -the Labor Party could ever think was<br />
realistically possible.<br />
W. 0. MUUAY, Government Printer. Canberra </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
