<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6216</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, OPENING OF WORLD TRADE CENTRE, MELBOURNE, 30 SEPTEMBER 1983</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/09/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006216.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
J A LIA<br />
P-7<br />
SPEFCH DY THE PRItME NIIiER<br />
limuaE eautas? t2ni<br />
ELR 0STh198<br />
1 AM SURE YOU SHARE WITH ML THE SENSE OF PLEASURE ANI)<br />
GRATIFICATION AT BEING ABLE TO ATTEND THIS CERENONY.<br />
THE MELBOURNE WORLD TRADE CENTRE IS THE FIRST WORLD TRAD<br />
CENTRE TO BE ESTABLISHED IN AUSTRALIA. IT IS PART OF AN<br />
IMPRESSIVE NETWORK. SINCE THE FORMATION CF THE OrLD<br />
TRADE CENTRES ASSOCIATION IN 1968, 33 WORLD TRADE CENRES<br />
HAVE BEENBUILT, 8 MORE ARE UNDER CONSTRUCTION, AND 29 f\ RQj<br />
BEING PLANNED. THIS IS AN IMPRESSIVE RECORD OF SUCCESS.<br />
OF COURSE THE ASSOCIATION IS NOT ONLY ABOUT BUILDINGS AND<br />
THIS ONE IS TRULY IMPRESSIVE IN ITS CONCEPTION AND DESICN,<br />
THE ASSOCIATION ALSO AIM3 TO ENCOURAGE MUTUAL ASSISTANCE AND<br />
CO-OPERATION AMONGST MEMBERS AND TO PROMOTE INTERtIATION! AL<br />
TRADE. IT IS LOGICAL THAT THIS FIRST WORLD TRADE CENTRE BE<br />
ESTABLISHED IN MELBOURNE. MELBOURNE IS THE BASE FOR<br />
ABOUT HALF AUSTRALIA'S BUSINESSES AND THE PORT OF<br />
MELBOURNE IS THE LARGEST CONTAINER PORT IN THE SOi1HERN<br />
HEMISPHERE HANDLING ABOUT 40% ( IN 1981/ 82) OF AUSTRALIA'S<br />
CONTAINER CARGO TRADE. </p>
<p>I I. 2.<br />
IN THE FUTURE I WOULD EXPECT AN INCREASING EMPHASIS UPON<br />
' USING WORLD TRADE CENTRE FACILITIES, I HOPE THAT THE<br />
CONCEPT, AS IT IS DEVELOPING, GOES FROM STRENGTH TO<br />
STRENGTH AND THAT THE ASSOCIATION IS CONTINUALLY ABLE TO<br />
ADAPT ITS FUNCTIONS AND ACTIVITIES TO MEET THE NEEDS AND<br />
OPPORTUNITIES WHICH ARISE IN THE INTERNATIONAL TRADING<br />
SPHERE, THE OPENING OF THE CENTRE COINCIDES WITH A RECOVERY IN<br />
U, S, ECONOMIC ACTIVITY, ONE THAT HAS BEEN QUITE VIGOROUS<br />
IN ITS EARLY STAGES. THIS RECOVERY CAN BE EXPECTED,<br />
IN TIME, TO SPREAD . TO OUR OTHER MAJOR TRADING PARTNERSj<br />
BRINGING WITH IT THE PROSPECT OF IMPROVED GROWTH IN ' ORLD<br />
TRADE, ALREADY THIS HAS BEEN REFLECTED IN IMPROVEMtENTS<br />
IN SOME COMMODITY PRICES A SHIFT OF DIRECT BENEFIT TO<br />
SOME AUSTRALIAN EXPORTING INTERESTS.<br />
AT THE SAME TIME WE SHOULD BE WARY OF EXAGGERATED<br />
OPTIMISM ABOUT THE RECOVERY, THE LONG AWAITED WORLD<br />
RECOVERY WILL BE ACCOMPANIED BY FIERCE COMPETITION FOR<br />
THE LIMITED SHARE OF ITS BENEFITS. INTERNATIONAL<br />
COMPETITION, EXACERBATED BY FORMIDABLE PROTECTIONIST<br />
FORCES PUT IN PLACE OVER THE LAST DIFFICULT FEW YEARS,<br />
WILL BE INTENSE. </p>
<p>I AM SURE THAT EVERYONE HERE TODAY REALISES THE<br />
IMPORTANCE OF INTERNATIONAL TRADE TO AUSTRAI IA. I<br />
I HAS BEEN<br />
REGRET THAT AUSTRALIA S TRADE PERFORMANCE IN A SERIOUS<br />
DECLINE WITH OUR SHARE OF WORLD EXPORTS FALLING FRef'l<br />
1.7% IN 1970 TO1,3% IN 1982. AUSTRALIA HAS SLIPPED<br />
FROM 13TH TO 16TH PLACE AS A WORLD TRADING NATION<br />
* IN THE SAME PERIOD,<br />
THE PICTURE IS THE WORSE WHEN IT IS REALIZED THAT FOR<br />
MUCH OF THIS PERIOD WORLD TRADE HAS ITSELF BEEN SEVERELY<br />
DEPRESSED AND THE IMMEDIATE OUTLOOK IS NOT BRIGHT,<br />
ACCORDING TO THE GATT THE VOLUME OF WORLD TRADE GREW<br />
HARDLY AT ALL IN THE FIRST HALF OF THIS YEAR AND IS<br />
LIKELY TO GROW BY ONLY 2% IN THE SECOND HALF, THIS<br />
COMPARES WITH WORLD TRADE GROWTH OF 11% IN 1976 WHEN<br />
ECONOMIES RECOVERED FROM THE 1974-75 RECESSION.<br />
OBVIOUSLY THE PATH AHEAD WILL NOT BE AN EASY ONE.<br />
MY GOVERNMENT'S OVER-RIDING CONCERN HAS BEEN TO ESTABLISH<br />
THE BASIS FOR A SUSTAINED ECONOMIC RECOVERY IN AUSTRALIA,<br />
THE CONTINUING HEALTH AND WELL-BEING OF OUR ECONOMY RESTS<br />
TO A GREAT EXTENT UPON OUR ABILITY TO TRADE COMPETITIVELY<br />
ON INTERNATIONAL MARKETS,<br />
1 </p>
<p>IT IS VITAL THAT WE INCREASE THE CONTRIBUTION THAT EXPORTVS<br />
MAKE TO GROWTH IN AUSTRALIA' Is GNP, INCOMES AND AR~ OYMENT,<br />
&gt; THE FALLING OFF I1N OUR EXPORT PERFORMANCE HAS TO BE CORRECTED<br />
AND I SEE THIS AS BEING ONE OF THE MAJOR TASKS OF My<br />
GOVERNMENT IN CLOSE COLLABORATION WITH AUSTRALIAN EXPORTING<br />
INTERESTS. DECISIONS WE HAVE ALREADY TAKEN ON FISCAL,)<br />
MONETARY AND INCOMES POLICIES SHOULD CONTRIBUTE SIGNIFICANTL&amp;<br />
TO RESTORING AND MAINTAINING THE INTERNATIONAL COMPETITIVENESS<br />
OF OUR EXPORT AND REVITALISE OUR EXPORT PERFORMANCE,<br />
MlY COLLEAGUE LIONEL BOWEN, THE M'INISTER FOR TRADE,<br />
HAS-RECENTLY ANNOUNCED A NUMBER OF ADDITIONAL MEASURES<br />
DESIGNED TO SECURE AN IMPROVED CONTRIBUTION BY AUSTRALIAN<br />
EXPORT INDUSTRIES TO EMPLOYMENT AND INCOME, AN INCREASED<br />
TRADE PROMOTION EFFORT AND AN UPGRADING OF SUPPORTING<br />
SERVICES FOR OUR EXPORTERS IS ENVISAGED,<br />
TO Tq( IS END THE BUDGET PROVIDED FOR INCREASED EXPENDITURE<br />
TO UPGRADE TRADE PROMOTION PROGRAMMES IN ASIA, THE MIDDLE EAST,<br />
NORTH AMERICA AND NEW ZEALAND. A MORE TARGETTiED APPROACH TO<br />
EXPORT DEVELOPMENT ACTIVITIES IN THESE AREAS IS PLANNED,<br />
AN INTENSIFICATION OF TRADE MISSION ACTIVITY IS ALSO<br />
ANTICIPATED. THE OVERALL PROVISION FOR TRADE PROMOTION AND<br />
MARKET RESEARCH ACTIVITIES HAS BEEN INCREASED TO<br />
MILLION IN~ 1983/ 84~ AN INCREASE OF 50% OVER 1982/ 83. </p>
<p>AS A MAJOR TRADING NATION AUSTRALIA HAS A PARTICULAR<br />
SINTEREST IN SUSTAIHING AND DEVELOPING CONDITIONS FOR<br />
MUTUALLY BENEFICIAL TRADE. JAPAN., WHICH ACCOUNTS FOR<br />
27% OF OUR TOTAL EXPORTS AND 21o OF OUR TOTAL IMPORTS,<br />
MUST RANK HIGH IN ANY ASSESSMENT OF THIS INTEREST, WE<br />
SHOULD NOT BE TAKING THAT RELATIONSHIP FOR GRANTED.<br />
SIGNIFICANT STRUCTURAL CHANGES HAVE TAKEN PLACE IN THE<br />
JAPANESE ECONOMY. AUSTRALIA MUST RECOGNISE THEIR<br />
IMPLICATIONS AND ADJUST Tu THEM.<br />
THE RECENT AGREEMENT BETWEEN MR BOWEN AND JAPANESE MINISTERS<br />
TO ESTABLISH A DIALOGUE AIMED AT EXAMINING CONCRETE WAYS<br />
OF ASSISTING AUSTRALIAN EXPORTERS TO IDENTIFY OPPORTUNITIES<br />
AND MEANS OF PENETRATING THE JAPIANESE MARKET OFFERS SOME<br />
WITH<br />
PROSPECT OF AUSTRALIAN INVOLVEMENT PREVIOUSLY UNTESTED<br />
SECTORS OF THAT MARKET. IN THE FINAL ANALYSIS, HOWEVER,<br />
ONLY AePLICATION OF GREAT RESOURCEFULNESS ANDIMAGINATION<br />
BY AUSTRALIANS WILL CONTRIBUTE TO THE REALISATION OF THE<br />
FULL POTENTIAL OF THE ECONCMIC AND TRADING RELATIONSHIP<br />
WITH JAPAN, MORE GENERALLY<br />
THE SAME IS TRUE/ OF OUR TRADING RELATIONSHIP WITH THE<br />
COUNTRIES OF THE WESTERN PACIFIC REGION, WHILE THEIR SHARE<br />
OF AUSTRALIAN EXPORTS HAS RISEN FROM 37% IN 1962/ 63 TO<br />
54% IN 1982/ 83 THE INTENSELY COMPETITIVE CHARACTER<br />
OF THOSE MARKETS COMBINED WITH THEIR RELATIVELY HIGH<br />
GROWTH RATES PUTS PARTICULAR PRESSURE ON THE INGENUITY<br />
AND DRIVE OF AUSTRALIAN EXPORTERS, a 6/. </p>
<p>THERE IS A NEED TO HAVE A CLEAR UNDERSTANDING OF THE<br />
CHANGING TRENDS IN THE ASIAN REGION AND WHAT MARKETS<br />
ARE LIKELY TO OPEN FOR GOODS AND SERVICES PRODUCED IN<br />
AUSTRALIA. TO * THIS END WE HAVE PROVIDED $ 1.5 MILLION<br />
FOR BASIC MARKET RESEARCH. THIS SHOULD<br />
ASSIST TRADE COMMISSIONERS AND AUSTRALIAN COMPANIES TO<br />
UNDERTAKE NEW PRODUCT DEVELOPMENT AND MARKET RESEARCH IN<br />
OVERSEAS MARKETS.<br />
OUR TRADE COMMISSIONERS HAVE AN IMPORTANT ROLE TO PLAY.<br />
A STRONG, RESOURCEFUL AND ADAPTABLE TRADE COMMISSIONER<br />
SERVICE IS ESSENTIAL IF WE ARE TO TURN THE TIDE ON OUR<br />
DECLINING TRADING PERFORMANCE, THE REVIEW INITIATED<br />
BY THE MINISTER FOR TRADE ON THE TRADE COMMISSIONER<br />
SERVICE IS I BELIEVE TIMELY, WE NEED TO CONSIDER<br />
CAREFULLY BOTH THE IMPLICATIONS OF DEVELOPMENTS IN THE<br />
WORLD TRAD ING ENVIRONMENT FOR THE SERVICE AND.&gt; AGAINST<br />
THE BACKGROUND OF AN APPRECIATION OF THE. EXPECTATIONS'<br />
OF THE BUSINESS COMMUNITY, THE MEASURES NECESSARY<br />
TOJMPROVE THE OPERATION AND EFFECTIVENESS OF THE<br />
SERV ICE.<br />
MY GOVERNMENT IS KEEN TO BREAK DOWN UNNECESSARY BARRIERSBOTH<br />
INTERNALLY AND EXTERNALLY TO THE EXPANSION OF TRADE.<br />
H-OWEVER, PROGRESS IN THIS AREA REQUIRES CO-OPERATION BETWEEN<br />
FEDERAL AND STATE GOVERNMENTS, THE ATMOSPHERE FOR SUCH<br />
CO-OPERATION HAS IMPROVED RECENTLY AND MY GOVERNMENT HOPES<br />
s7/ 1s </p>
<p>TO ENCOURAGE FURTHER CO-OPERATION BY ESTABLISHING JOINT<br />
TRADE PROMOTION CAMPAIGNS IN COLLABORATION WITH THE STATES,<br />
4THIS PROGIAM WILL COVER EXPORT PROMOTIONAL ACT! IVITIES<br />
OF PARTICULAR INTEREST TO THE STATES SUCH AS MISSIONS<br />
TO OVERSEAS MARKETS, INVOLVEMENT IN OVERSEAS FAIRS AND<br />
DISPLAYS, SPECIAL TRADE VISITS AND TRADE PUBLICATIONS,<br />
THE GOVERNMENT IS VERY CONSCIOUS THAT MORE EFFECTIVE EXPORT<br />
CREDIT POLICIES ARE NEEDED IF AUSTRALIAN EXPORTS ARE TO BE<br />
MADE SECURE AND DEVELOPED TO THEIR FULL POTENTIAL. THE<br />
INTENSIFICATION OF CREDIT COMPETITION IN INTERNATIONAL.<br />
TRADE IS A STRIKING FEATURE OF THE CONTEMPORARY WORLD<br />
TRADING ENVIRONMENT. ACCORDINGLY IMPROVING THE<br />
SUPPORTING SERVICES AVAILABLE THROUGH THE EXPORT FINANCE<br />
AND INSURANCE CORPORATION ( EFIC) IS COMMANDING OUR<br />
PARTICULAR ATTENTION.<br />
THE GOVERNMENT CURRENTLY HAS UNDER CONSIDERATION A NUMB3ER<br />
OF PROPOSALS DESIGNED TO IMPROVE THE EFFECTIVENESS TO<br />
EXPORTERS OF FACILITIES PROVIDED BY THE EFIC. THESE<br />
PROPOSALS GO TO SUCH MATTERS AS:<br />
THE OPERATING POLICY OF EFIC;<br />
EFIC COVER AGAINST THE RISK OF NON-PAYMENT<br />
ARISING FROM POLITICAL CAUSES) 112 </p>
<p>-THE RESTRICTIONS WlHICH GENERALLY LIMIT EFIC's<br />
SERVICES TO THOSE NOT NORM* ALLY AVAIL. ABLE FROM THE<br />
PRIVATE SECTOR;<br />
FOREIGN CURRENCY FINANCING THROUGH THE PROVISION'<br />
OF GUARANTEES TO AUSTRALIAN OR OVERSEAS LENDERS<br />
AND THE APPLICATION OF INTEREST RATE SUBSIDIES TO<br />
SUQH FINANCING;<br />
LENDING IN A FOREIGN CURRENCY;<br />
-FUTURE AVAILABlILITY OF FUNDS UNDER THE DEVELOPMENT<br />
IMPORT FINANCE FACILITY;<br />
-EXCHANGE CONTROL APPROVALS; AND<br />
-THE MATTER OF AN INTERNATIONAL ARRANGEMENT UNDER THE<br />
AMB . ITOF THE OECD TO LIMIT PROVISION OF OFFICIALLY<br />
SUPPORTED CREDIT FOR THE EXPORT OF AGRICULTURAL PRODUCTS.<br />
SOON<br />
DEISIONS1To BE TAKEN ON THESE MATTERS SHOULDi I BELIEVE,<br />
BE OF SUBSTANTIAL ASSISTANCE TO AUSTRALIAN EXPORTERS.<br />
THESE MATTERS SHOULD ALWAYS BE VIEWED WITHIN THE CONTEXT<br />
OF A SOUND INDUSTRY POLICY, SUCH A POLICY WILL BE DIRECTED<br />
TO ACTIVELY DEVELOPING INDUSTRIES WHICH HAVE A POTENTIAL </p>
<p>NOT ONLY TO SATISFY LOCAL REQUIREMENTS BUT TO MEETING<br />
THE INCREASINGLY VARIED DEMANDS, OF THE STRONGLY GROWING<br />
ECONOMIES OF OUR REGION, IMPORTANTLY THIS WILL MEAN BOTH<br />
NEW AND EXISTING INDUSTRIES MAKING EFFECTIVE USE OF NEW<br />
TECHNOLOGIES, WHETHER DEVELOPED IN AUSTRALIA OR ADOPTED<br />
FROM ABROAD,. IN RESPONSE TO BOfH NEW TECHNOLOGICAL<br />
AND TRADING OPPORTUNITIES SOME MEASURE OF STRUCTURAL<br />
CHANGE IN THE ECONOMY IS INEVITABLE.<br />
TH'E WORLD TRADE CENTRE CAN PLAY AN IMPORTANT ROLE IN<br />
FOCUSSING AUSTRALIAIS ATTENTION ON WORLD TRADE. THE<br />
CENTRE HAS ESTABLISHED A GROUPING OF ORGANISATIONS<br />
INTERESTED IN INTERNATIONAL TRADE IN A WAY THAT HAS NOT<br />
BEEN POSSIBLE BEFORE IN MELBOURNE OR INDEED IN AUSTRALIA.<br />
FOR THE FIRST TIME A TOTAL SERVICE TO EXPORTERS IS<br />
POSSIBLE UNDER THE ONE ROOF, IN A VERY REAL SENSE THE<br />
WORLD TRADE CENTRE IS A ONE-STOP TRADE SHOP WHICH COULD<br />
BE O'F. REAL VALUE TO THE AUSTRALIAN TRADING COMMUNITY.<br />
THIS MUST LEAD TO GREATER EFFICIENCY IN OUR EXPORT EFFORT,<br />
PARTICULARLY THROUGH THE EXCHANGE OF INFORMATION ON<br />
COMMERCIAL PRODUCTS AND SERVICES, OVERSEAS MARKETS ETC.<br />
THE ESTABLISHMENT OF THIS CENTRE IS A FURTHER EXAMPLE OF<br />
CO-OPERATION BETWEEN THE COMMONWEALTH AND STATE GOVERNMENTS<br />
AND PRIVATE ENTERPRISE ORGANISATIONS INVOLVED IN ALL FACETS<br />
OF EXPORT. IF THE SPIRIT OF CO-OPERATION CONTINUES INTO THE<br />
DAY-TO-DAY BUSINESS OF THE CENTRE IT IS ASSURED OF SUCCESS.<br />
0* 0 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
