<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>17163</transcript-id>
    <title>New Minister for Population 3 April 2010   </title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/04/2010</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>To help guide the development of policies to meet Australia's future population needs, I have recommended to the Governor General that she appoint the Hon Tony Burke MP to the new office of Minister for Population in the Treasury Portfolio.    </p>
<p>Minister Burke's first task will be to develop Australia's first comprehensive Population Strategy.</p>
<p>In his new role, Minister Burke will consider the likely trajectory of population growth and the challenges and opportunities this will create. Minister Burke will also be tasked with developing the cross government frameworks that will be required to make the most of the opportunities, and minimise the risks, associated with population growth. </p>
<p>Australia's first Population Strategy will consider the social and economic infrastructure Australia will need to support a growing population, including the roads, housing and service delivery network. </p>
<p>It will also consider, as an early priority, the opportunities a growing population will create for economic growth and to further develop and grow Australia's regional towns and communities.  The policy will bring a whole-of-government perspective drawing on input from all portfolios.</p>
<p>The strategy will also seek to address the challenges associated with population growth, including the impact on the environment, water, and urban congestion.  </p>
<p>It's expected that it will take 12 months to develop the strategy. There has always been a bipartisan approach on issues of population.  We would hope this work continues whoever wins the next election.</p>
<p>Minister Burke will address these through an open dialogue about what we want for the future of Australian society.</p>
<p>Mr Burke will retain his current portfolio of Agriculture, Fisheries and Forestry.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
