<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18202</transcript-id>
    <title>Prime Minister&#039;s taskforce on manufacturing</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/10/2011</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Prime Minister Julia Gillard and Innovation Minister Senator Kim Carr today announced the membership of the Gillard Government's new Manufacturing Taskforce, announced at last month's Future Jobs Forum.</p>
<p>The new high-level Taskforce will map out a shared vision for the future of Australia's manufacturing sector and help strengthen local firms as they adapt to changes in our economy, including the rise of Asia.</p>
<p>We want to see the sector move up the value chain. To do this we need to build the skills and innovation that the sector needs for a new era of manufacturing. </p>
<p>The Prime Minister will personally chair this taskforce, with Minister Carr as deputy chair.  Because this is a whole-of-government task, a number of other senior ministers will work on the taskforce.</p>
<p>Membership of the new group will also include manufacturing industry leaders, academics and unions.  The list of initial members of the taskforce is below.</p>
<p>Senator Kim Carr said the new taskforce would help ensure manufacturing remains a key part of our economy for generations to come.</p>
<p>It will identify a plan for how best to leverage existing efforts, including Government policies and programs, to best capture the opportunities and respond to the challenges facing manufacturing.</p>
<p>The taskforce will meet for the first time in November 2011. </p>
<p>Prime Ministers Taskforce on Manufacturing - Members</p>
<p>Government</p>
<p>The Hon Julia Gillard MP, Prime Minister (Chair)</p>
<p>Senator the Hon Kim Carr, Minister for Innovation, Industry, Science and Research (Deputy Chair)</p>
<p>The Hon Wayne Swan MP, Deputy Prime Minister</p>
<p>Senator the Hon Chris Evans, Minister for Tertiary Education, Skills, Jobs and Workplace Relations</p>
<p>Senator the Hon Penny Wong, Minister for Finance and Deregulation</p>
<p>The Hon Craig Emerson, Minister for Trade</p>
<p>The Hon Jason Clare MP, Minister for Defence Materiel</p>
<p>Industry</p>
<p>Mr Philip Binns, Vice President and General Manager, Agilent Technologies</p>
<p>Mr Geoff Plummer, CEO, OneSteel</p>
<p>Mr Ian Thomas, President, Boeing</p>
<p>Ms Heather Ridout, CEO, AiG</p>
<p>Mr Mike Devereux, Chairman and Managing Director, Holden</p>
<p>Mr Chris Jenkins MD Thales</p>
<p>Mr Phil Butler, MD, Textor Technologies</p>
<p>Ms Rebecca Dee Bradbury, CEO, Kraft Australia</p>
<p>Unions</p>
<p>Mr Jeff Lawrence, ACTU</p>
<p>Mr Paul Howes, National Secretary, Australian Workers Union</p>
<p>Mr David Oliver, National Secretary, Australian Manufacturing Workers Union</p>
<p>Mr Michael O'Connor, CFMEU</p>
<p>Mr Charlie Donnelly, NUW</p>
<p>Ms Michele O'Neil, TCFUA</p>
<p>Science and Technology</p>
<p>Professor Roy Green, Professor and Dean of the Faculty of Business, University of Technology Sydney</p>
<p>Dr Megan Clark, Chief Executive, CSIRO</p>
<p>Professor Jonathan West, AIRC, University of Tasmania</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
