<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6338</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/03/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006338.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
-, USRAL IA<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA 8 March 1984<br />
To mark International Women's Day the Prime Minister, Mr Hawke,<br />
today announced four important Government initiatives for women.<br />
Mr Hawke said the Government had already demonstrated its commitment<br />
to advancing the status of women in many areas.<br />
Government business was arranged so that the Sex Discrimination<br />
Bill completed its passage through the Parliament by International<br />
Women' s Day.<br />
Mr Hawke announced the establishment of a Working Party on Women<br />
in Sport, the membership of which will be announced<br />
shortly. The Working Party which will be headed<br />
by a prominent sportswoman, will draw the attention<br />
of the media to the accomplishments of women in sport<br />
and the popularity of women's sporting activities,<br />
especially team events, and will report to the<br />
Government on problems encountered by women's<br />
sporting bodies.<br />
the establishment of Women's Telephone Information<br />
Services in each State capital city. Thirteen<br />
women have been employed under the Community<br />
Employment Program ( CEP) for an eight month<br />
period to answer telephone calls from the public<br />
about Government policies for women. The WTIS<br />
will specifically answer que-ries about the<br />
Government's affirmatiye action proposals once<br />
the Green paper is released for public debate<br />
and discussion.<br />
the employment of 11 Aborigintal women throughout<br />
Australia to act as regional. co-ordinators to assist<br />
the Aboriginal Women's Task Force, which operates<br />
from the office of theStatus of Women and which<br />
is engaged in Austra~ 1ia-widE consultations about<br />
the needs of Aboriginal women as they see them.<br />
The regional co-ordinators aire also employed under<br />
the CEP Program.<br />
the funding of seminars in each capital city to inform<br />
women's organisations of the contents of the Sex<br />
Discrimination Act. The conferences will be chaired<br />
by women Caucus members and women's organisations in<br />
each State will be invited to hear speakers from the<br />
office of Status of Women, the Human Rights Commission<br />
and the Attorney-General's Department explain the<br />
contents of the legislation. / 2 </p>
<p>The WTIS in each State can be contacted as follows:<br />
Aboriginal Women's Task Force Co-ordinators<br />
Adelaide ( 08) 2240004<br />
Broome ( 091.) 921800<br />
Perth ( 09) 3258981<br />
Cairns ( 070) 519959<br />
Melbourne ( 03) 8185764<br />
Canberra ( 062) 724960 Hobart ( 002) 348941<br />
Darwin ( 089) 277811<br />
Sydney ( 02) 2124831<br />
Brisbane ( 07) 2315394<br />
Alice Springs ( 089) 527083<br />
Women's Telephone Information Service<br />
Adelaide ( 08) 2240004<br />
Melbourne ( 03) 8188248/ 8188112<br />
Sydney ( 02) 2124831/ 2125589 Perth ( 09) 3258744<br />
Darwin ( 089) 277166/ 277266<br />
Hobart ( 002) 348308 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
