<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4969</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS AT THE ANTARCTIC BASE, KINGSTON, TASMANIA</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/02/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004969.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
AUS T R A L I Ai" L!<br />
iit<br />
FOR PRESS 26 FEBRUARY 1979<br />
Address at the Antarctic Base, Kingston, Tasmania<br />
It gives me great pleasure to be in Kingston today.<br />
This complex, for the Antarctic Division of the Department of<br />
Science and the Environment, will establish this Commonwealth<br />
activity in Tasmania.<br />
The Government decided to locate the Antarctic Division here<br />
because Hobart is the closest Australian capital city to the<br />
Antarctic, and the logical springboard for our scientific<br />
interest there. The Government's decision is consistent with<br />
recommendations of the 1977 Callaghan Report which led to<br />
decisions to provide help for Tasmania such as freight<br />
equalisation. The. Government-has also begun other initiatives<br />
to help industry and employment conditions in Tasmania.<br />
The contract for this building has been let with a company,<br />
Watts Construction Division, which has been long established<br />
in Hobart, and the project will assist many local industries<br />
and professional consultants. In addition, of course, the<br />
estabilishment of this Division at Kingston will give a<br />
substantial boost to the area's shopping tuade, housing<br />
industry and general amenities. The buildings to be constructed<br />
on this site will include an administration section, laboratories,<br />
display and conference areas, and stores and workship buildings.<br />
Every effort will be made to blend the buildings into the<br />
surroundings. In particular the height of the buildings has<br />
been restricted to two stories. And special provision has also<br />
been made for an historical display area, open to the public,<br />
where exhibits associated with Australia's long involvement<br />
in the Antarctic area will be displayed.<br />
Australians have been associated with the history of Antarctica<br />
since Lelast c~ ntury. A Tasmanian scientist Louis Bernacchi<br />
was a member of the first expedition to Winter in the Antarctic in<br />
in 18. In 1911 Si-r Douglas Mawson led an Australasian scientific<br />
expedit.-ion to the Antarctic, departing from Hobart, and he returned<br />
to the Antarctic with a second expedition in 1929-31.<br />
In 1947 the Antarctic Division was set up to support Australian<br />
activities in Antarctica including our three Antarctic stations. / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
The work of our scientists in Antarctica helps us understand<br />
the potential resources of the region, the last great unexplored<br />
land mass of the world. In Antarctica, our biologists,<br />
physicists, glaciologists, geologists, meteorologists<br />
and cartographers are pursuing work of major scientific<br />
importance. Their investigations into the Antarctic and its<br />
resources will deepen our understanding of the environment<br />
of Antarctica, and will develop our knowledge of, to name a<br />
few areas, climate, the w.-eather, geological mapping, glaciology,<br />
wildlife and marine life.<br />
To ensure Australia conducts an effective and balanced programme<br />
of research in Antarctica, the Government recently established an<br />
Antarctic Research Policy Advisory Committee ( ARPAC). I am pleased<br />
to announce that Professor Caro, the Vice-Chancellor of the University<br />
of Tasmania, has consented to be Chiarman of this Body. The<br />
Committee has the task of advising the Government within six months<br />
on the organisation and priorities for scientific and technological<br />
research in the Antarctic.<br />
The Government is also considering a submission by the University<br />
of Tasmania which proposes a national post-graduate centre<br />
in marine science and Antarctic science. The University of<br />
Tasmania and the Antarctic Division already work together on<br />
cosmic ray research. The proposal by the Tasmanian University<br />
will also be considered by ARPAC.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen, as you know, Tasmania has a strong Liberal<br />
conti-ngent in the Federal Parliament. With two M11inisters)<br />
Kevin Newman and Ray Groom and with a group of enthusiastic<br />
backbenchers Tasmania' s interests are ably represented.<br />
We recognise the unique problems faced by Tasmania and the need<br />
for special initiatives to cope with Tasmania's situation. In<br />
this regard I should mention that the Commonwealth has given<br />
substantial financial assistance to the Mount Lyell Mining<br />
and Railway Company. Since August 1977 the company received<br />
a net $ 3.3 million from the Commonwealth in interest free<br />
loans. These funds ensured that the mine would remain in<br />
operation and saved hundreds of jobs.<br />
Today the wisdom of the Commonwealth's decision to help the mine<br />
has been borne out by the recovery in copper prices. The<br />
price of copper is now at its highest level since 1974, and<br />
on the basis of these trends the company may not need further<br />
assistance in 1979.<br />
We have commenced a programme of rehabilitation and development<br />
of the Tasmanian railways. And in this year's budget we<br />
provided an amount of $ 26 million for the Tasmanian Freight<br />
Equalisation Scheme, encouraging trade and keeping down prices<br />
in Tasmania.<br />
Overall, the Commonwealth Government's economic policies are<br />
putting Australia and Tasmania on the path to recovery. We are<br />
encouraged by the signs of economic progress in consumer confidence, 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
in rising production, in investment and new resource projects.<br />
In July I shall be opening a $ 30 million expansion of pulp-making<br />
facilities at APPI41s Burnie Mill, an encouraging new development<br />
for northern Tasmania, which I believe is based to a large degree<br />
on frieght equalisation.<br />
Employment opportunities have been growing too slowly in Tasmania,<br />
but the latest statistics show some early signs of recovery.<br />
Overtime worked in Tasmania reached an average of 2.6 hours in<br />
December rising consistently over the first half of the current<br />
financial year. In the December quarter total employment increased<br />
by in Tasmania, a little above the growth Australia-wide of<br />
These are tentative early indications, but they are encouraginc<br />
To help the unemployed, the Tasmanian branch of the Commonwealth<br />
Employment Service commenced on 22 January, 1979 a special drive<br />
to identify vacant job opportunities, entitled " Job Search 1979".<br />
In the month following this drive vacancies rose by 18%, and<br />
I am sure this will prove an example of the importance of the<br />
co-operation between the community and Government.<br />
In assessing our economic prospects we should not forget that<br />
for Tasmania, as for the rest of Australia, the revival of our<br />
rural industries and rising commodity prices should make 1979<br />
the best year for a number of years.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen, the Commonwealth Government looks forward<br />
to seeing the Antarctic Division operating in its new location.<br />
This project is one of my Government's most important current<br />
initiatives for Tasmania. It will play its part in helping<br />
recovery in Tasmania. In developing Australian scientific<br />
research and knowledge of the Antarctic continent, I am sure<br />
that the work of the Division will be of major importance<br />
to Australia.<br />
It gives me great pleasure to lay this foundation stone at the<br />
commencement 0of construction of the Headquarters of the Antarctic<br />
Division. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
