<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11704</transcript-id>
    <title>Address to the Israel-Australia New Zealand and Oceania Chamber of Commerce, Jerusalem                           </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/04/2000</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Subjects: strength of the Australian economy; Aus</p>
<p>E&amp;OE ....................................................................................</p>
<p>  Before I deliver my remarks, I would like to take this</p>
<p> opportunity as I sometimes do when abroad to formally confer the award,</p>
<p> of an honorary award in the Order of Australia and I would like to invite</p>
<p> Gurion Meltzer to come forward to participate in this very small but very</p>
<p> important ceremony.</p>
<p>  On behalf of the Governor General of the Commonwealth</p>
<p> of Australia and at his request, it is now my privilege and pleasure to</p>
<p> present with his insignia, one whom Australia has been very pleased to</p>
<p> honour. Gurion Meltzer, I appoint you as an honorary officer in the general</p>
<p> division of the Order of Australia for very long and meritorious service</p>
<p> to Australian-Israeli relations. Congratulations.</p>
<p>  Dr Meltzer...</p>
<p>  Well can I say, ladies and gentleman, to all of you and</p>
<p> to all of the very distinguished guests how delighted Janette and I are</p>
<p> to be amongst you and to have the opportunity of addressing a few remarks</p>
<p> about not only the strength of the Australian economy and how we see the</p>
<p> world economically but also the importance of economic and commercial</p>
<p> relations between our two communities.</p>
<p>  Israel and Australia have a multi-faceted relationship.</p>
<p> It is a relationship that has a lot of history. It is a relationship that</p>
<p> is based upon common values. It's a relationship that is constantly</p>
<p> nourished and supported and renewed by the free flow of people between</p>
<p> our two societies and I was reminded at the University this morning as</p>
<p> I moved around and met the people who were there just how many Australians</p>
<p> there are studying in Israel, just how many Australian business men and</p>
<p> women spend considerable periods of time in your country and just how</p>
<p> long and close are the bonds that bring us together.</p>
<p>  But I speak particularly today of the economic environment</p>
<p> in which both of our communities operate. The world at present is enjoying</p>
<p> one of the most sustained periods of economic growth of industrialised</p>
<p> nations that we have seen in 50 or 60 years.</p>
<p>  The strongest economy in the world, the United States,</p>
<p> is enjoying an unprecedented level of economic growth and prosperity.</p>
<p> There are welcome signs that the major economies of Europe are recovering.</p>
<p> There are signs that the weakness evident in the Japanese economy in recent</p>
<p> years is coming to an end and while we're not going to see a resumption</p>
<p> of American style growth in Japan, there are signs that the recessionary</p>
<p> tendencies of the Japanese economy are now behind us.</p>
<p>  The other good news on the world front is that the economies</p>
<p> worst hit by the Asian downtown in some cases are now beginning to enjoy</p>
<p> recovery. Our own country is experiencing its strongest period of economic</p>
<p> growth since the late 1960's and in many respects that economic growth</p>
<p> now in Australia is more sustainable and more broadly based than what</p>
<p> it was in the late 1960's because we no longer operate behind such</p>
<p> high protective walls, our economy is more open, it's more competitive</p>
<p> and we are beginning to enjoy the benefits of a series of economic reforms</p>
<p> undertaken by governments of both political persuasions over a number</p>
<p> of years.</p>
<p>  So the economic settings in which we operate at the present</p>
<p> time around the world as far as industrialised countries are concerned</p>
<p> and that of course includes both Australia and Israel are about as propitious</p>
<p> and encouraging as they have been for decades.</p>
<p>  The common catch cry of the world, and it's true,</p>
<p> is that we live in a globalised economy and that globalisation takes many</p>
<p> forms. I was reminded of one of the forms of that globalisation some weeks</p>
<p> ago when I went on a tour around country areas of Australia, when I visited</p>
<p> a place called Bourke and, as the Australians in the audience will know</p>
<p> and many Israelis in the audience will know, there's no expression</p>
<p> quite as Australian as to say that you've been to the 'back</p>
<p> of Bourke'. And when I went to the back of Bourke, what did I learn?</p>
<p> I learnt a great deal about Israeli irrigation techniques. Because one</p>
<p> of the burgeoning industries back of Bourke now is of course the cotton</p>
<p> industry and we have seen what used to be a community depending very heavily</p>
<p> on wool and other basic commodities or traditional commodities, we've</p>
<p> seen that community now turn its hand to the development of a cotton industry</p>
<p> and a very prosperous cotton industry.</p>
<p>  And of course it's drawn very heavily on the expertise</p>
<p> of Israelis so far as irrigation is concerned. Now that's perhaps</p>
<p> not the most immediate example you think of when you talk about a globalised</p>
<p> economy. You tend to think of those people who look at screens all day</p>
<p> and all night and watch the movement of numbers as seamlessly currencies</p>
<p> change and resources flow across nations in this borderless, seamless</p>
<p> economic environment in which we operate. But in so many ways now, we</p>
<p> are all citizens of the one economic world and there is no turning back.</p>
<p> Any idea that any of us might have that you can go back to some kind of</p>
<p> comfortable, more cloistered domestic economic environment is totally</p>
<p> unreal. The nature of the world in which we live now means that all countries</p>
<p> can no longer do other than simply compete and compete and compete again</p>
<p> in order to stay in front of or at least equal with their economic rivals.</p>
<p> It's of no comfort to say to yourself we're doing better than</p>
<p> we were doing 10 years ago or 20 years ago. That's irrelevant. The</p>
<p> only thing that really matters now is whether you are doing better as</p>
<p> against those that seek the same markets as you seek in these early years</p>
<p> of the 21st Century.</p>
<p>  And that's the reason why the government I lead</p>
<p> has set about in the four years it's been in government undertaking</p>
<p> some major economic reforms. There have been some economic reforms carried</p>
<p> out in Australia in the past which have helped to open up and strengthen</p>
<p> our economy and I have never been unwilling either at home or abroad to</p>
<p> give credit to the former government for some of the decisions it took</p>
<p> particularly the freeing of the exchange rate and the deregulation of</p>
<p> our financial system.</p>
<p>  And those reforms made possible in part by the co-operation</p>
<p> that government enjoyed from the then opposition. And other changes have</p>
<p> added to the momentum for strengthening and change of the Australian economy</p>
<p> over recent years. And one of the other features that I find interesting</p>
<p> about the global economic environment in which we now live is the far</p>
<p> greater convergence between the political attitudes towards running an</p>
<p> economy across the political spectrum. One goes around the world and talks</p>
<p> to a Prime Minister or a President who is formerly of the centre right</p>
<p> or formerly of the centre left and you talk about economic issues and</p>
<p> economic challenges. The answers you get on many of the questions you</p>
<p> raise are not all that different and it indicates that the realities of</p>
<p> the modern world are such that the solutions that commend themselves are</p>
<p> solutions that commend themselves to people who might in a formal sense</p>
<p> have different political philosophies.</p>
<p>  But we have set about making our economy more competitive.</p>
<p> Leon was kind enough to recite some of the changes for which we have been</p>
<p> responsible. And can I interpolate here by acknowledging one of the achievements</p>
<p> to which Leon and his colleagues in the Australian Israeli Chamber of</p>
<p> Commerce in Australia have been responsible and that is that they were</p>
<p> responsible for organising the largest ever sit down lunch that I have</p>
<p> addressed in Australia. There were 1400 of you at the Crown Casino in</p>
<p> Melbourne and then I think you had television hook-ups all around Australia</p>
<p> and I was reliably informed by Leon that the total number of people viewing</p>
<p> that lunch was in the order of 3500 and it really does take the prize</p>
<p> for being the largest sit down lunch that I have ever addressed in my</p>
<p> time as Prime Minister.</p>
<p>  Leon was kind enough to mention some of the reforms that</p>
<p> we have undertaken and far and away the most important of those is the</p>
<p> introduction of a new taxation system on the 1st of July this</p>
<p> year to which I'll come to in a moment. But I wouldn't want</p>
<p> you to think that I regard that as in any sense the only major economic</p>
<p> change. He talked about the importance of industrial relations reform.</p>
<p>  We inherited an industrial relations system when we came</p>
<p> to government that was too heavily dominated by formal award structures.</p>
<p> We inherited an industrial relations system where too much of a monopoly</p>
<p> of bargaining power was given to trade unions and too little room was</p>
<p> left for direct negotiation between individual employers and employees.</p>
<p>  We have changed that. We have not taken away people's</p>
<p> right to join or not to join a labour organisation, but we have promoted</p>
<p> the idea that if people want to make direct bargains with their employers</p>
<p> they should, without the intervention of a union, they should have the</p>
<p> right to do so. And one of the reasons why productivity in our country</p>
<p> has risen and why workers in Australia are better off in real terms than</p>
<p> they were a few years ago is that the industrial relations system is far</p>
<p> more conducive to higher productivity.</p>
<p>  We've also committed ourselves to the privatisation</p>
<p> of those government business enterprises that should no longer be in government</p>
<p> ownership. We are about half way there with Telstra, our major telecommunications</p>
<p> provider. We face domestic political opposition but we intend to pursue</p>
<p> our policy of selling the remaining 50.1 per cent in that telecommunications</p>
<p> carrier. We see no virtue at all in a government owning 50.1 per cent</p>
<p> and investing something in the order of $50 billion Australian dollars</p>
<p> of public money in a telecommunications company, believing that those</p>
<p> resources could be better invested either through debt retirement or elsewhere</p>
<p> for the benefit of the Australian community.</p>
<p>  But it is of course in the area of tax reform that most</p>
<p> publicity about our economic reform program has been generated and the</p>
<p> changes are mammoth. They touch every section of Australian economic development</p>
<p> and activity. We will after the 1st of July move from a corporate</p>
<p> tax rate of 36 cents in the dollar in two stages to 30 cents in the dollar.</p>
<p> We will virtually halve the capital gains tax. We will abolish provisional</p>
<p> taxation which is of great benefit, the abolition, of great benefit, to</p>
<p> retired people. We will sweep away existing indirect taxes and replace</p>
<p> those indirect taxes with a single rate value added or goods and services</p>
<p> tax of 10 per cent and that will be accompanied by major reductions in</p>
<p> personal income tax that will mean that something in the order of 80 per</p>
<p> cent of Australian tax payers will be on a top marginal rate of no more</p>
<p> than 30 cents in the dollar.</p>
<p>  Importantly in a federation we will introduce a system</p>
<p> whereby the total proceeds of the goods and services tax will go to the</p>
<p> six States of Australia and the two Territories of Australia which will</p>
<p> enable them to more adequately fund on an ongoing basis those essential</p>
<p> bread and butter services such as public hospitals, government schools,</p>
<p> police services and roads, which are the direct responsibility in our</p>
<p> arrangement of state governments.</p>
<p>  That is important in the Australian political context</p>
<p> because debate and argument between Federal and State Governments has</p>
<p> been a long running political and economic source of discontent and debate</p>
<p> for many years.</p>
<p>  So it does represent a major reform. It will transform</p>
<p> the taxation environment in which the Australian economy operates. Overall</p>
<p> we're watching an Australian economy at the present time that continues</p>
<p> to grow at over 4 per cent a year or thereabouts. There are some signs</p>
<p> in some areas of some slowing, but overall the projection is for continued</p>
<p> very strong growth.</p>
<p>  Our budgets for the last two years have been in surplus</p>
<p> and it remains a commitment of the government to retain the budget surpluses.</p>
<p> We don't, of course, regard this achievement as being something to</p>
<p> be complacent about. Economic progress and economic growth is something</p>
<p> that governments should continue to strive to maintain and to improve.</p>
<p>  Earlier speakers have mentioned the linkages between</p>
<p> the responsibilities of government and the responsibilities of business</p>
<p> in providing for a healthy economy. It is not the role of government to</p>
<p> pick winners or to play favourites in business activity. It is the role</p>
<p> of the government to provide a benign, if possible, economic climate,</p>
<p> to set the best set of corporate governance rules they can. To provide</p>
<p> a well regulated and stable banking system. To provide as competitive</p>
<p> an economic environment as they can and then leave it to individual companies</p>
<p> to make their commercial decision. And that of course has been the attitude</p>
<p> of my government and as I know been the credo of the Australian Israeli</p>
<p> Chamber of Commerce.</p>
<p>  Israel and Australia have a significant trading and economic</p>
<p> relationship. It is not, of course, as extensive as our economic relationship</p>
<p> with countries such as Japan and Korea and the United States. The size</p>
<p> and disposition of our two economies militates against it being as close</p>
<p> and as extensive as that. But the opportunities for growth and improvement,</p>
<p> particularly in areas of information technology, in areas of research</p>
<p> and development, and in areas which bear upon the intellectual capital</p>
<p> of the two countries, the opportunities for advancement in that area are</p>
<p> very extensive.</p>
<p>  We share a lot of things in common. We are both sophisticated</p>
<p> societies. We are societies that believe very firmly that companies are</p>
<p> entitled to operate in a clear, open, readily understood environment of</p>
<p> corporate regulation. And we are societies that believe very strongly</p>
<p> in the rule of law applying not only in relation to personal conduct,</p>
<p> but also in relation to business conduct. And the climate in which business</p>
<p> operates is of no lesser importance now than it was 20 or 30 years ago.</p>
<p> And one of the lessons that we must learn from the Asian economic downturn</p>
<p> is that when the view is taken that the need for clear rules of corporate</p>
<p> governance and a clear separation of the responsibilities of government</p>
<p> and the responsibilities of the private sector when the view is taken</p>
<p> that those requirements can be sidestepped or ignored that that is one</p>
<p> of the reasons why economies fall into decline and get into economic difficulty.</p>
<p> So one of the great things that our two societies have in common is a</p>
<p> belief that we should operate in the same kind of general economic and</p>
<p> regulatory environment.</p>
<p>  The other great asset that Australia and Israel have,</p>
<p> of course, is the very frequent interchange between our leading business</p>
<p> identities and personalities. And the series of economic missions that</p>
<p> have come to Israel, some of them led by Ministers, others led by leading</p>
<p> businessmen, all of them have made a contribution and in the process I</p>
<p> believe that the opportunities for an expansion of economic exchanges</p>
<p> and trade and investment must over a period of time grow very significantly.</p>
<p>  I can assure you that the reputation of this country</p>
<p> for expertise in information technology, the reputation of this country</p>
<p> of being a high performer and something of an example to follow in areas</p>
<p> of research and development that that reputation is widely noted and respected</p>
<p> within Australia. The sophistication and capacity of Israel and Israelis</p>
<p> in many areas of technology is also something which is very widely and</p>
<p> warmly understood.</p>
<p>  Can I finish ladies and gentlemen in saying how important</p>
<p> I regard the contribution of the various chambers of commerce within our</p>
<p> society and within Israel. In both cases what the organisations do is</p>
<p> to bring together in an appropriate way the influence and the role of</p>
<p> government and the influence and the role of business communities. The</p>
<p> commitment of the chamber in Australia not only to developing very good</p>
<p> political and person to person relations between Israel and Australia</p>
<p> is well known and widely admired. And of course, the constant entreaties</p>
<p> they make, the constant submissions they put to the government on behalf</p>
<p> of improving economic relations between our two communities is also of</p>
<p> very great importance.</p>
<p>  I have been very warmly received in Israel and whenever</p>
<p> political or business leaders of Israel visit Australia they are also</p>
<p> very warmly received. And that occurs because there is a very genuine</p>
<p> warmth between our two societies. It's a warmth which I said at the</p>
<p> beginning of my speech is rooted in history but it's also rooted</p>
<p> in some very important values that we share in common and some of the</p>
<p> contributions of that warmth I know is very much due to the activity of</p>
<p> the two chambers and that is why I'm delighted to have had this opportunity</p>
<p> of addressing you. But saying to all the business men and women of Israel</p>
<p> that I speak as Prime Minister of an economy and a country which is very</p>
<p> strong, which continues to grow, which has seen its unemployment rate</p>
<p> come down, which believes in an open economic environment, that strives</p>
<p> to be more competitive, is willing to undertake major economic change</p>
<p> and is prepared to take political risks in the process of doing that.</p>
<p>  I think these attitudes and these views have some resonance</p>
<p> and some receptivity here in Israel and on that basis I believe that not</p>
<p> only our political and person to person relationship in the years to come</p>
<p> but also our economic relationship will indeed be very strong.</p>
<p>  Thank you.</p>
<p>  QUESTIONS &amp; ANSWERS</p>
<p> QUESTION:</p>
<p> Prime Minister what are your plans for telecommunications</p>
<p> vis-a-vis distance education in rural areas of Australia?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p> Well the telecommunications infrastructure in rural Australia</p>
<p> is what you would in a masterstroke of understatement in Australian politics</p>
<p> call a big issue. It gets a big run. Sometimes it gets a bigger run than</p>
<p> it deserves because some of the issues that are talked about are a little</p>
<p> exaggerated. But let me say that I think Australians living in remote</p>
<p> areas of our country, and we have quite a few of those, are entitled to</p>
<p> good communications and they are getting better communications. We have</p>
<p> invested a lot of the proceeds of the partial sale of Telstra into providing</p>
<p> better communications and I think that over the next year you're</p>
<p> going to see quite a significant improvement in the provision of those</p>
<p> communications.</p>
<p>  One of Australia's most eminent historians coined</p>
<p> a phrase some years ago which is very evocative to most of us in Australia,</p>
<p> when he spoke of the tyranny of distance and what has happened, I believe,</p>
<p> with information technology and the modernisation of communications is</p>
<p> that in a way that wasn't previously possible we have a means at</p>
<p> our disposal to demolish or remove the tyranny of distance for many people</p>
<p> who live in the less populated areas of our country.</p>
<p>  One of the remarkable things about Australia is that</p>
<p> although it is a big country, and it's well known around the world</p>
<p> for the bush, for rural and country areas, yet something like 85 per cent</p>
<p> of the population of Australia lives in major cities which are very light</p>
<p> in density and so forth than the major cities of Europe. It's one</p>
<p> of the paradoxes, the contradictions, it's part of the variety of</p>
<p> the country. Communications in the bush are very important. If I lived</p>
<p> in the bush I would want very good communications and as Prime Minister</p>
<p> for people who live in the country areas of Australia, I'm determined</p>
<p> that they will get it.</p>
<p> QUESTION:</p>
<p> How do you see Australia's telecommunications role</p>
<p> in Asia in the future?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p> Well I would not see Australia's future role in</p>
<p> Asia in telecommunications separately from Australia's future economic</p>
<p> role in Asia generally speaking. The Asian Pacific region is obviously</p>
<p> the most important region in the world for Australia economically. And</p>
<p> the fact that I'm in Israel and I've been in Europe and that</p>
<p> I sought in the time that I've been Prime Minister to get a slightly</p>
<p> better balance in our relations with the different regions of the world</p>
<p> in no way alters the fact that I see Asia and the Asian Pacific region</p>
<p> as being far and away the most important market destination for Australian</p>
<p> goods and services but also the area where we have so much to offer given</p>
<p> our particular strengths. We have a lot to offer because of a very well</p>
<p> educated, sophisticated workforce. There are 800,000 Australian citizens</p>
<p> who speak Asian languages and that is an enormous asset in our dealing</p>
<p> with the Asian economic arena. We have seen a fall in economic activity</p>
<p> in Asia over the last few years but it is rebounding. Of our three best</p>
<p> customers undeniably the first is Japan. Our second best customer is either</p>
<p> the United States or Korea and there are other very significant markets.</p>
<p> So I make the general point that although Europe and America and the Middle</p>
<p> East are very important to Australia but no Australian Prime Minister</p>
<p> gainsays the particular and special importance of the Asian Pacific region.</p>
<p> I think the capacity of our telecommunication companies to effectively</p>
<p> compete in the Asian Pacific region would of course be enhanced if the</p>
<p> one owned 50.1 per cent by the government were fully owned by the private</p>
<p> sector and that's one of many reasons, including debt retirement</p>
<p> and a better use of that big public investment that I believe that privatisation</p>
<p> should proceed, but that is a matter for political debate and political</p>
<p> resolution within Australia.</p>
<p>  But we have a highly sophisticated workforce. I also</p>
<p> recognise that a number of Asian countries have very highly sophisticated</p>
<p> and IT literate citizens, particularly countries such as India, but not</p>
<p> only India but Singapore and Hong Kong and China - all of them -</p>
<p> and we have an approach to business migration and a general approach to</p>
<p> investment that I think enables us to take full advantage. So I see us</p>
<p> having a very active economic future in the region and that very particularly</p>
<p> includes investment in the area of telecommunications.</p>
<p> QUESTION:</p>
<p> (inaudible)?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p> Look we are, we are generally pragmatic about trade opportunities</p>
<p> and being pragmatic about trade opportunities we have thus far taken the</p>
<p> view that the best way to get a better trade deal for Australia is to</p>
<p> try and make the multi-lateral trade mechanisms and trade forums work</p>
<p> effectively and that's why we're pushing very, very hard for</p>
<p> a new world trade round that can particularly provide roughly comparable</p>
<p> treatment for the things that we export very efficiently, like agriculture,</p>
<p> compared with the way in which manufactured goods are treated by the trading</p>
<p> nations of the world. And we were very disappointed at the Seattle meeting,</p>
<p> we thought that was a very disappointing event indeed and we're pushing</p>
<p> very strongly.</p>
<p>  So our preference has been rather than having a series</p>
<p> of free, bilateral, free trade arrangements, our preference for a very</p>
<p> good reason has been to try and improve the whole multilateral environment</p>
<p> and we will continue to do that.</p>
<p>  We never rule anything out. You never do. You are utterly</p>
<p> pragmatic when it comes to these trading arrangements. Most nations are</p>
<p> and Australia is no exception but to date we've had a preference</p>
<p> for a multi-lateral approach.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
