<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4912</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER INTERVIEWED BY GRAHAM DOBELL, ABC, AT BELCONNEN MALL VISUAL ARTS DISPLAY BY SOUTHWEST TOURIST AUTHORITY OF VICTORIA</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/12/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004912.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PR ErSS OFFI CE T R
Minister Interviewed by Graham Dobell, ABC,<br />
at Belconnen Mall Visual Arts Display by Southwest<br />
Tourist Authority of Victoria.<br />
Question How do you think you are going as a tourist promoter?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
I think Western Victoria is starting to go very well as<br />
a tourist promoter because steadily and surely over the<br />
last, I suppose, 10-15 years a great deal of attention has<br />
been paid to facilities to bring to light and make people<br />
aware of many items of interest in Western Victoria. The<br />
facilities are there the hotel, the motel, the beaches,<br />
lakes and the many things which are part of the natural<br />
environment. Also there is a very real attempt to build<br />
up items of historical interest Flagstaff Hill at<br />
Warrnambool, you've got the exhibition here on that, which<br />
goes back into some Australia's early history and past and<br />
some of the interesting things that have occurred. This<br />
is getting a response because, especially on the coastline<br />
Warrnambool, Port Fairy, Portland, do attract many many<br />
thousands of tourists in the summer months especially.<br />
Question<br />
Would you, for instance, consider opening Nareen as<br />
a tourist attraction at some stage?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
I would have one reservation about that because Nareen to me<br />
is a sanctuary. It's a place where~-. can-and) you can recharge<br />
your own batteries and whatever. If it was opened as a tourist<br />
resort or something well I think that might disappear. Nareen<br />
has been open sometimes for fetes and and charities and one<br />
time had 4,000 or 5,000 people through in one day. I've got no<br />
doubt that will occur from time to time. I think it's important<br />
for me to have some place where I can go which is quiet and<br />
out of the way to be with the family occasionally.<br />
Question How important is tourism to country areas, as an industry?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
I think it's very important. One of the things which made<br />
a number of local communities look to tourism much more was<br />
the fall-off in rural fortunes and rural profitability in<br />
farms. Many people in country towns came to understand that<br />
if their only livelihood was going to be servicing dairy<br />
industry, or the wool industry or the beef industry, then they<br />
could be having an unpredictable future. So a lot of people / 2 </p>
<p>BELCONNEN MALL, A. B. C. INTERVIEW 2-<br />
Prime Minister: ( continued)<br />
with foresight, and Councillor Brophy from Port Fairy is<br />
one who has been right in the fore of this movement, thought<br />
" that's just not good enough, we've got to build up our own<br />
future. Our town's got its own heart" and Port Fairy,<br />
Warrnambool, Portland and other towns in Western Victoria<br />
have really done just that. They are delightful places to<br />
go for a holiday, to take your family, and to get a way from<br />
it all for a while. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
