<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8482</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON  P J KEATING MP CAMBODIA PEACEKEEPING</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/04/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008482.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
EMBARGO: AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
CAMBODIA PEACEKEEPING<br />
Mr Speaker<br />
it LB appropriate that the House focus today on the subject<br />
of Cambodia, and on the prospects for 8 lasting peace in<br />
that long-suffering country.<br />
Great crimes have been committed against the Cambodian<br />
people. The tragedy of the conflict has been brought home<br />
to us all through the personal wItness of many Cambodian<br />
Australians. On 28 February, the United Nations Security Council passed a<br />
resolution formally creating the United Nations Transitional<br />
Authority in Cambodia or UNTAC, the body responsible for<br />
implementation of the historic Comprehensive Political<br />
Settlement of the Cambodia Conflict.<br />
In response to the UN Secretary General's request for<br />
contributions to UNTAC's operations, Australia has agreed to<br />
provide 495 Defence Force personnel to form the Force<br />
Communications Unit..<br />
This total includes 65 communicators already deployed as<br />
part of the UN Advance Mission in Cambodia.<br />
If conditions are rigpt in Cambodia, the Government expects<br />
. that-thainsin Australian contingent will begin deploying<br />
during this month.<br />
They will be joined in the field by 40 signallers from the<br />
New Zealand Defence Force.<br />
Furthermore, Australia has provided UNTAC'S military<br />
commander, Lieutenant-General John Sanderson, who commenced<br />
duty in Cambodia on 15 March.' Australia will contribute six<br />
staff to his headquarters unit. </p>
<p>LL* 2<br />
The Government also expects to contribute to UNTAC's<br />
civilian component, whose composition is still under<br />
consideration by the United Nations.<br />
As part of. this, we have decided to provide ten police<br />
officers. in addition, Mr Michael Maley, an officer of the Australian<br />
Electoral Commission, has taken up duty in Phnom Penh as<br />
Deputy Electoral Commissioner for UNTAC.<br />
Mr Speaker<br />
The creation of UNTAC is the Culmination of years of complex<br />
and difficult negotiation.<br />
The peace plan embodied in the remarkable agreements signed<br />
in Paris on 23 October 1991 provides a way of ending the<br />
nightmare of Cambodia's recent past.<br />
The main objectives of the settlement are to end the civil<br />
war, and to allow the Cambodian people to choose a new<br />
government through genuinely free arnd fair elections.<br />
Reflecting the complexity of the Cambodian conflict, the<br />
Paris agreements provide for an unprecedented and ambitious<br />
role for the United Nations In the implementation of the<br />
peace plan.<br />
UNTAC will have a peacekeeping role supervising, monitoring<br />
and verifying the cease-fire, partial demobilisation of<br />
armed forces, and the cessation of external military<br />
assistance.<br />
UNTAC most definitely will = t have a role enforcing or<br />
imposing the peace if hostilities break out.<br />
In the civilian sphere, not only will UNTAC have a role in<br />
organising and conducting the elections, it will also play a<br />
role in monitoring and supervising the interim<br />
administration of the country to ensure a neutral political<br />
environment for the elections.<br />
in addition, the United Nations will be responsible for<br />
coordinating and assisting the repatriation and resettlement<br />
of some hundreds of thousands of Cambodian refugees and<br />
displaced persons.<br />
Mr Speaker<br />
The Cambodia peace settlement is a striking demonstration of<br />
the fundamental changes that have occurred in the<br />
international System.<br />
Unprecedented cooperation between the Permanent Five members<br />
of the Security Council has greatly enhanced the scope for<br />
resolving regional conflicts. The UN system has been able<br />
to harness broad-based support for its peacekeeping role.<br />
i n p I 4 L L, 14 ci u u r u z,, </p>
<p>1. FHpr. 92 13: 33 No. 005 P. 03/<br />
3<br />
The subtle and dynamic balance of interests in the Cambodia<br />
peace agreements reflects the close involvement and<br />
cooperation of the Permanent Five members of the Security<br />
Council in the negotiating process.<br />
The efforts of the Indonesian and French governments deserve<br />
special mention. Their initiative, courage and persistence<br />
were essential to the success of the peace plan.<br />
Great credit must also go, of course, to the Cambodians<br />
themselves. Those of us who have not known their suffering,<br />
or seen the evil they have seen, can only wonder what human<br />
qualities it takes to sit down and talk about the future,<br />
about peace, and about national reconciliation.<br />
Mr Speaker<br />
Australia played 8 significant role in the long process<br />
leading up to the Puris agreements.<br />
In the mid 1980s, former Foreign Minister Hayden was active<br />
in regional diplomacy which sought to identify a basis for<br />
dialogue between the parties to the Cambodian conflict.<br />
In late 1989, Senator Evans played a key role in breaking<br />
the impasse following the first Paris Conference on Cambodia<br />
in July anid August 1989. The Core of Senator Evans's<br />
proposal, which was taken up by the Permanent Five members<br />
of the Security Council, was an enhanced role for the United<br />
Nations in the transitional period preceding elections in<br />
Cambodia. Senator Evans's resourceful and energetic pursuit of peace<br />
in Cambodia has earned him nomination for the Nobel Peace<br />
Prize. It has also earned international respect for<br />
Australia. Mr Speaker<br />
in moving this resolution today I pay regard to the<br />
achievement of Senator Evans and his Department.<br />
In light of our diplomatic contribution, it was appropriate<br />
that Australia was the first country to establish<br />
accreditation to the Supreme National Council, the interim<br />
body in which Cambodian sovereignty has been vested during<br />
the transitional period.<br />
Australia was also among the first to supply troops to carry<br />
out the vital task of establishing communications and<br />
infrastructure in preparation for the deployment of the main<br />
UNTAC force.<br />
It is appropriate that we now help to see the process<br />
through.<br />
I </p>
<p>4<br />
The return of Australian soldiers to Indo-China in the cause<br />
of peace is a matter for us to reflect on with justifiable<br />
pride. With peace secured in Cambodia, we shall be able to welcome<br />
the countries of Indo-China back into the mainstream of<br />
regional activity.<br />
We can confidently expect them to become part-of the<br />
dynamism of Asia.<br />
Vietnam will now be able to emerge from its isolation and,<br />
with Cambodia, play its part in regional and international<br />
affairs. in parallel with the improved prospects for peace in<br />
Cambodia, Australia will resume direct bilateral aid.<br />
The minister for Trade and Overseas Development announced<br />
today that, over the next four years, Australia will provide<br />
approximately 49 million Australian dollars in development<br />
assistance to Cambodia. This total includes 23 million<br />
dollars for new bilateral aid.<br />
In addition, during this financial year, we are providing<br />
approximately 7.7 million Australian dollars in disaster<br />
relief and assistance to displaced Cambodians.<br />
Mr Speaker<br />
Aspects of the comprehensive settlement have been criticised<br />
by some observers.<br />
it is suggested that it would somehow have been better to<br />
exclude the Khmer Rouge from the peace process because of<br />
their responsibility for the atrocities committed by the<br />
former Po1 Pot regime.<br />
Involvement of the Khmer Rouge in the process does Dot<br />
ref lect a judgment by the Australian or other governments<br />
that the Khmer Rouge can now be trusted. Rather, it<br />
reflects a realistic assessment that the only available<br />
aff~ etivA way of containing the military threat they pose,<br />
and of ending the civil war, was to involve them and their<br />
main backers China as parties to the agreement.<br />
Put simply, a peace settlement without the Khmer Rouge and<br />
China would not be a. peace settlement at all.<br />
It has also been suggested that the settlement could have<br />
been improved by providing for 100 per cent rather than for<br />
at least 70 per Cent demobilisation of the armed forces of<br />
the Cambodian parties.<br />
obviously such a provision would have been preferable, but<br />
the outcome set out in the Paris agreements is the best that<br />
could be negotiated. I--1 </p>
<p>it is the judgment of the United States, Russia, China,<br />
France, Britain, 811 significant Asian states and Australia<br />
that the Paris settlement represents the best available,<br />
realistic basis for a just and durable peace in Cambodia.<br />
Mr Speaker<br />
UNTAC Will be the costliest, as well as the most<br />
comprehensive peacekeeping operation yet undertaken by the<br />
United Nations.<br />
It is expected to involve approximately 15,900 military<br />
personnel, 3,600 civilian police and 3,300 civilian<br />
administrators. More than 50 countries have been requested<br />
to contribute to this complex undertaking.<br />
The initial UN estimate of the cost for a duration of 18<br />
months is 1.9 billion US dollars. Australia's share of<br />
assessed contributions for this amount is 1.51 per cent or<br />
28.7 million US dollars.<br />
I should also advise the House that Cabinet agreed in<br />
October 1991 to provide supplementation to the Defence<br />
Budget of 49 million Australian dollars to fund the<br />
estimated costs involved in making our contribution to UNTAC<br />
and the United Nations Advance Mission in Cambodia. This is<br />
separate from our assessed contribution to UNTAC's budget,<br />
described above. We expect this will eventually be<br />
partially offset by reimbursements from the UN of some 19.7<br />
million Australian dollars, but this will take some time to<br />
materialise. The final UNTAC plan and budget are now being scrutinised in<br />
New York by representatives of major donors including<br />
Australia. It will be some weeks before the final budget is<br />
approved.<br />
Along with other donors, Australia hopes that, as<br />
implementation of the settlement proceeds, an increasing<br />
habit of cooperation among the Cambodian parties will allow<br />
savings in UNTAC personnel and costs.<br />
Mr Speaker<br />
Generally speaking, the settlement is working.<br />
In the five months since it was signed, the remarkable thing<br />
has been not the number of violations or the number of<br />
disputes, but the way in which the Paris agreements have<br />
held firm, and the way in which the parties have repeatedly<br />
reaffirmed their commitment to the settlement in all its<br />
detail. Of course, there have been incidents Which threaten the<br />
whole process, and the Government has viewed with particular<br />
concern the recent fighting in Kompong Thom province. But<br />
we must look beyond these hurdles without in any sense<br />
trivialising them. 4" </p>
<p>Implementation of the peace plan may well prove more<br />
difficult than its negotiation.<br />
There are bound to be further setbacks.<br />
We should expect them and not be disheartened when they<br />
occur. The Government's decision to commit Australian forces to the<br />
Cambodian peacekeeping operation was not taken lightly.<br />
The UN forces will face risks from mines, from disease, from<br />
banditry, and possibly from fresh outbreaks of fighting.<br />
The Government has assessed these risks and has weighed them<br />
carefully. It does not underestimate them, or the need to<br />
take every prudent precaution to protect our troops.<br />
We have made this commitment, however, because the<br />
opportunity to help restore peace to Cambodia is one which<br />
the international community cannot lightly let go.<br />
The UN commitment to help Cambodia also serves Australia's<br />
direct interests, and those of our neighbours, by helping to<br />
create a more peaceful and prosperous region.<br />
But it is important to emnphasise again that Australian<br />
forces will n= a be participating in the UN operation in<br />
order to 2nñ DXsu or impose~ the peace in Cambodia.<br />
That is a task beyond the UN mandate.<br />
Rather, the Australian forces will be in Cambodia to help<br />
keaep a peace on which the Cambodian parties themselves have<br />
agreed. That is the condition under which UNTAC is being deployed.<br />
it is the whole basis of the Paris peace accords. It is the<br />
condition under which Australian troops have been offered to<br />
the United Nations.<br />
if we conclude that there is no longer a peace to keep in<br />
Cambodia, the Australian and other UN forces will have to be<br />
withdrawn. But we do not expect that to happen. All sides in the<br />
conflict have invested so. much effort in the peace process,<br />
and the Cambodian people have so much to gain from its<br />
success, that we think the prospects for a successful<br />
outcome remain promising.<br />
If we turn our backs on this opportunity to help consolidate<br />
the hard work of the peace-makers, we shall be sentencing<br />
the Cambodian people to further years of cruelty and<br />
suffering. </p>
<p>I LL. 7<br />
Mr Speaker<br />
As I already mentioned, UNTAC'S primary military functions<br />
will be supervising and verifying the cease-fire, partial<br />
demobilisation of armed forces, and the cessation of<br />
external military assistance.<br />
UNTAC will also assist in the clearance of hundreds of<br />
thousands of mines.<br />
Australia's contingent will provide the crucial<br />
communications network for the UNTAC military operation.<br />
Our service men and women will be operating in a difficult<br />
and sometimes dangerous environment.<br />
Already Lieutenant-Colonel Russell Stuart has been wounded<br />
in the course of his duty with the UN Advance Mission in<br />
Cambodia. That incident underlines the risks which the<br />
peacekeeping personnel face.<br />
But Australians can be proud of the skill and<br />
professionalism which Australian Defence Force units have<br />
brought to UN peacekeeping and other operations around the<br />
world from the Sinai, Iraq and the Red Sea, to the Western<br />
Sahara and the Afghan border.<br />
Their reputation is reflected in the UN Secretary-General's<br />
decision to appoint Lieutenant-General Sanderson commander<br />
of UNTAC'S military force.<br />
I am sure all members of this House will join me in<br />
extending congratulations to General Sanderson on his<br />
appointment and in wishing him well in his assignment.<br />
I am equally sure members will want to express their<br />
confidence in and support for the Australian Defence Force<br />
men and women deployed in Cambodia.<br />
There is no more honourable duty than the one they will go<br />
to perform to preserve the peace.<br />
We know they will serve Australia and the cause of peace<br />
with distinction, and we look forward to their safe return.<br />
Mr Speaker, we hope that return will not be long delayed.<br />
The aim of the United Nations presence in Cambodia is not to<br />
oversee developments there Indefinitely but to manage a<br />
transition from war to peace, from factional distrust to<br />
national reconciliation.<br />
May 1993 has been set as the target date for the UNorganised<br />
elections. The UN Secretary-General intends<br />
withdrawing UNTAC about six months after that date.<br />
I rip C jz-I'D , DD 140 U" r u </p>
<p>8<br />
I know it is the earnest desire of all members of this House<br />
that the Cambodian people will seize this opportunity to<br />
establish a j~ ust anld lasting peace in their country.<br />
I commend the motion to the House.<br />
CANBERRA 1 APRIL 1992 </p>
<p>CAMBODIA PEACEKEEPING: PARLIAMIENTARIY RESOLUTION<br />
That this H-ouse<br />
recalls the long suffering of the Cambodian people<br />
notes the remarkable diplomatic achievement enshrined<br />
in the Agreements on the Comprehensive Political<br />
Settlement of the Cambodia Conflict signed in Paris on<br />
23 October 1991.<br />
zre cognises the difficult task ahead of the United<br />
N-ations Transitional Authority in Cambodia ( UNTAC),<br />
affirms Australia's commitment to assist the Cambodian<br />
people to take control again of their own affairs and<br />
return to peaceful and productive lives<br />
affirms Australia's support for the United Nations in<br />
its new arnd enhanced role in promoting world peace and<br />
solving long-standing regional conflicts<br />
affirms its support for Australia's positive response<br />
to the request made by the UN Secretary General for<br />
support in implementing the Cambodian peace accords<br />
expresses its full confidence in, and support for,<br />
Australian Defence Force men and women deployed for<br />
peacekeeping in Cambodia and looks forward to their<br />
safe return<br />
congratulates Lieutenant-General Sanderson on his<br />
appointment as UNTAC military commander and wishes him<br />
well in his assignment n 1. 1 L. I I W F </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
