<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6089</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY PRIME MINISTER AT LUNCH IN HONOUR OF PREMIER ZHAO ZIYANG, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA, 18 APRIL 1983</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/04/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006089.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY PRIME MINISTER AT LUNCH IN HONOUR OF<br />
PREMIER ZHAO ZIYANG, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA<br />
18 APRIL 1983<br />
MR PREMIER<br />
FOREIGN MINISTER WU<br />
DISTINGUISHED CHINESE AND AUSTRALIAN GUESTS<br />
Your visit, Mr Premier, the first to our country by a<br />
Chinese Head of Government, marks an important step<br />
forward in relations between Australia and China.<br />
The first step was taken by my distinguished<br />
predecessor, Gough Whitlam, who as Leader of the<br />
Opposition made a pioneering visit to Peking in July<br />
1971. In December 1972, the Whitlam Labor Government<br />
established relations with the People's Republic of<br />
China and in October 1973, Mr Whitlam made the first<br />
visit to China by an Australian Prime Minister. </p>
<p>I am happy to say that the relationship forged in that<br />
period was carried on by the Fraser Government with the<br />
result that today, a decade later, friendship with China<br />
has become a significant element in the foreign policies<br />
of all Australia's major political parties and enjoys<br />
widespread support in the Australian community.<br />
In the ten years since we established relations there<br />
has been a remarkable growth not only in our links with<br />
China but also in China's contacts with the<br />
international community. The policies of containment<br />
and isolationism of the 1950' s and 1960' s are no more<br />
than a bad memory. China now participates actively in<br />
international organisations including the United Nations<br />
Security Council and I might mention that I am looking<br />
forward to addressing the International Labour<br />
Conference in Geneva later this year, where a Chinese<br />
delegation will participate for the first time; China's<br />
scientists are respected participants in international<br />
conferences; its students study abroad ( there are 250<br />
in Australia); its cultural richness is being seen<br />
abroad through exhibitions, and China has developed<br />
economic policies which have facilitated trade and<br />
commercial activity. </p>
<p>China' s lea~ ders have also opened the political door.<br />
They have sought an active dialogue with other nations,<br />
as, Mr Premier, your presence here today, and earlier<br />
visits by Vice-Premiers Li and Chen, attest. The past<br />
ten years have witnessed the establishment of relations<br />
between China and Japan and the normalisation of<br />
relations with the United States. Relations with ASEAN<br />
have improved significantly. Most recently China has<br />
also entered discussions with the Soviet Union to try to<br />
improve the difficult relationship they have had with<br />
each other. As a reflection of China's interest in the<br />
Third World, you have recently visited eleven countries<br />
in Africa.<br />
Australia welcomes this active approach to international<br />
affairs. I have mentioned it in order to underline the<br />
importance of nations being in dialogue. it is<br />
essential that nations seek to understand each other,<br />
even if it is only to understand where the differences<br />
lie. With a better understanding of those differences<br />
there lies the hope of reconciliation, compromise and<br />
accommodation. It is Australia's deep belief that the major problems<br />
confronting the world, the threat of nuclear war, the<br />
differences between rich and poor, and the economic<br />
recession, are all issues on which nations must work </p>
<p>4.<br />
together to find solutions. Without having any<br />
exaggerated view of our own dimension on the<br />
international scene, my Government is willing to<br />
participate constructively and energetically in seeking<br />
the resolution of these problems and to pursue the path<br />
of reconciliation abroad as at home.<br />
Premier Zhao, we have talked this morning about the<br />
state of the world. We both want to see peace and<br />
stability as a basis for development of our region. The<br />
Asia-Pacific reqion is an area of dynamic economic<br />
growth, whose vitality is critical to global economic<br />
recovery. North Asia is certainly~ vital to Australia's<br />
economy, as the destination of almost 40% of our<br />
exports. Between us lies Southeast Asia. There we can<br />
observe the positive fact of the prosperity and success<br />
of the ASEAN countries. But we can also observe the<br />
tragic differences which have prevented Vietnam from<br />
taking a legitimate place in regional affairs and<br />
cooperating with its neighbours.<br />
There are other outstanding strategic and political<br />
problems in the region in Korea, between Japan and the<br />
Soviet Union, and in the tension still existing between<br />
China and the Soviet Union. For the long term it is<br />
essential that full regional harmony be established and<br />
Australia would welcome the development of a close<br />
political dialogue with China that could help to achieve<br />
this goal. There are no ready solutions to these </p>
<p>1<br />
problems. But the region today is tar more stable and<br />
prosperous than it was a decade ago, and one can<br />
approach its future with optimism. Much of the credit<br />
for this enhanced stability and prosperity must belong<br />
to your country and the policies you have followed in<br />
recent years. The broadening of China's relationships<br />
throughout the region since the early 1970' s has<br />
contributed greatly to the present improved scene.<br />
Tomorrow we will hold further discussions, about our<br />
respective approaches to national development and<br />
aspects of bilateral relations. I am pleased that you<br />
will then be travelling to see something of our cities,<br />
our agriculture and our mineral development. T would<br />
like you to leave Australia with an appreciation of our<br />
skills and our dynamic prospects.<br />
I look forward to hearing from you about China's<br />
achievements in readjusting and modernising its economy.<br />
We appreciate the great differences in scale and<br />
complexity between your development and our own. But<br />
there is a basis for economic partnership through which<br />
we stand ready to contribute to your modernisation<br />
programs. The trading relationship is valuable to us<br />
both. We will remain a reliable supplier for you of<br />
agricultural products and mineral resources.<br />
I hope that we will be able to find practical<br />
opportunities for investment in each other's countries. </p>
<p>Beyond economic cooperation, we have many other<br />
important exchanges. Our largest government sponsored<br />
sporting exchanges are with China. Our cultural<br />
exchange with you is one of our largest. Two major<br />
Chinese exhibitions have' been here this year. We<br />
exchange teachers and students, a number of your<br />
scientists have been working at Australian Antarctic<br />
bases, and we have technical co-operation projects.<br />
These exemplify the fact that while some larger<br />
industrial countries may have large scale technologies<br />
available for transfer, Australia, with its size and<br />
skills, has much of direct relevance and on a scale<br />
often more directly applicable. This evening, you will<br />
be meeting a number of Australian businessmen. You will<br />
learn from them the importance which the Australian<br />
private sector attaches to the development with China of<br />
a variety of exchanges of mutual benefit and profit in<br />
the spheres of management and technology.<br />
Mr Premier, the progress in relations in recent years<br />
has seen new agreements in science and technology,<br />
agricultural exchanges, technical co-operation and<br />
cultural exchange. The pace has been quick and </p>
<p>7.<br />
satisfying. We are committed to consolidating these<br />
successes,, to ensuring the effectiveness and value of<br />
these various agreements.<br />
We are approaching the broadening of relations from the<br />
basis that our national futures are linked, and that our<br />
qovernments and peoples must work for increased<br />
political, economic, commercial and cultural exchange.<br />
My welcome to you and your colleagues today is thus<br />
extended in a spirit of warm friendship. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
