<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8372</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON. PAUL KEATING, 27 DECEMBER 1991</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/12/1991</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008372.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
-An<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON. PAUL KEATING,<br />
27 DECEMBER 1991<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF ONLY<br />
PM: Thank you for coming. You by now have a copy of the<br />
press statement announcing the Ministerial arrangements and<br />
changes. The first point I'd like to make to you is that<br />
we've got a very experienced and intelligent group here and<br />
each has been aligned to an area of natural expertise and<br />
experience, so that in the places where Ministers are I<br />
believe as a Cabinet, as a Ministry, we'll be able to hit<br />
the ground running and not have Ministers spend six months<br />
or so learning an entirely new area or policy. Each person<br />
there has either had some experience, contact of, natural<br />
association with an area of policy, and I believe it's a way<br />
of maximising the efficiency, in an efficient way, the<br />
natural capacities of the Ministry and the Cabinet. The<br />
principle objective here, of course, is to promote a<br />
recovery and to restart growth and employment as quickly as<br />
possible. Now the key changes are:<br />
Mr Dawkins will be Treasurer;<br />
S Mr Willis will be the Minister for Finance;<br />
S Mr Beazley will be the MInister for Employment,<br />
Education and Training;<br />
Dr Blewett will be Minister for Social Security;<br />
Senator Richardson will be Minister for Transport<br />
and Communications;<br />
Mr Kerin will be Minister for Trade and Overseas<br />
Development; Mr Griffiths will be Minister for Tourism and brought<br />
into Cabinet; and<br />
Senator Collins will be Minister for Shipping and<br />
Aviation, and also brought into Cabinet. </p>
<p>Now, Of cour7se, there are other consequential changes, but<br />
they will be very evident to you as I know all you<br />
specialist Ministry watchers will understand very quickly.<br />
So I'd be happy to take questions at this point.<br />
J: Mr Keat~ ing, what is it that recommends Mr Dawkins' as<br />
Treasurer? PM: That was a very hard decision for me to make. I spent<br />
eight and a half happy years with both Mr Willis and<br />
Mr Dawkins, and each have their strengths. Mr Willis is a<br />
technically very well-equipped person who has shown great<br />
service to the Government. Mr Dawkins has been very<br />
creative in the portfolios he has had. And it's an on<br />
balance judgment which I made in Mr Dawkins' favour. But<br />
I'm very pleased that Mr Willis has agreed to vest<br />
Government writh his experience and ongoing knowledge as<br />
Minister for Finance.<br />
J: Mr Keating, why did you decide to take Mr Kerin from<br />
the Cabinet?<br />
PM: Well, it was always somewhat of an anomalous position<br />
in the sense; that we had the Trade portfolio represented in<br />
the Cabinet by the portfolio Minister, Senator Evans, and<br />
formerly by Dr Blewett. That was principally to do with the<br />
GATT Round, which is now drawing to a close, and with the<br />
Dunkel Package the issues are now encapsulated in that<br />
package. And as we found, whenever the issue needs to be<br />
considered it will be considered by Senator Evans, but<br />
naturally Mr Kerin will come to Cabinet whenever the matter<br />
needs to be discussed. So in practical terms, it leaves him<br />
free to take part in the balance of the Round and the bilateral<br />
trade negotiations which are a permanent part of the<br />
international landscape, and not to be burdened with the<br />
other Cabinet responsibilities which don't go to this<br />
external position.<br />
J: Prime Minister, do you anticipate any changes to this<br />
line-up before the election, and have you given guarantees<br />
to Senator Button and to Mr Hand that they will retain their<br />
positions until then?<br />
PM: I don't have to give guarantees. Senator Button and Mr<br />
Hand have both said they won't be contesting their positions<br />
at the next election, but both said they wanted to continue<br />
as Ministers in their respective roles until then, and<br />
that's the position I'm entirely at ease with.<br />
J: So this Ministry will stay as is until the next<br />
election? PM: Yes, unless somebody left of their own volition.<br />
J: There's no value in the New South Wales argument that<br />
they should make way for new faces in the front bench? </p>
<p>PM: There are two new Cabinet Ministers here, and they are<br />
among the younger Ministers. They are Mr Griffiths and<br />
Senator Coll~ ins. And both have very heavy and senior<br />
responsibilities. I have, in this arrangement, created a<br />
Department of Tourism, taking it away as a branch, or<br />
division, of DASETT and made it into a Department and given<br />
it Cabinet status, which befits its position as one of the<br />
fastest growing industries in Australia, which will then be<br />
attended to by a Minister of Cabinet rank. And for Senator<br />
Collins, he has Shipping and Aviation and there will be an<br />
area of grea~ ter discretion available to him than there was<br />
as Aviation Support. And because a lot of the micro debate<br />
is still in that area of transport and communications, and<br />
shipping and waterfront, and aviation in particular, then I<br />
think it is entirely apposite that he joins the Cabinet too.<br />
So we have two younger Ministers of the Ministry joining the<br />
Cabinet in two senior and important areas of policy.<br />
J: Mr Keating, why was Codd moved from PM&amp; C?<br />
PM: Well, hie wasn't moved out. That's not right. He said<br />
look, quite forthrightly to me, I've been here for six<br />
years. Mr Codd and I were party to the guidelines and<br />
arrangments years ago where there was a view that after<br />
about five years a Permanent Head's position should be<br />
reviewed either by himself or herself or by the<br />
Government. And he had had six years there, and the head of<br />
the Government had changed, his Ministerial head had<br />
changed, and I thought it was both considerate and sensitive<br />
of him to ra~ ise it, and I thought it would be an opportunity<br />
to make a change. But can I just record my appreciation to<br />
Mr Codd as a most professional public servant someone who<br />
has brought great professionalism to the Department of Prime<br />
Minister and Cabinet, to the Cabinet Office and the<br />
efficient working of the Cabinet system. And it is with the<br />
Government's blessing and good graces that he resigns, but<br />
not only that, that in doing so it appoints him to the Board<br />
of the former Telecom and also Qantas. And I think given<br />
the fact that he is still a relatively young man, Mr Codd<br />
has the opportunity to make another life for himself, but<br />
also still serving the public in those important positions,<br />
and giving u~ s in the Government the opportunity of a further<br />
change for the value of change in itself in the management<br />
of this very onerous administrative area.<br />
3: Mr Keating, could you explain why Senator Richardson<br />
has gone to the Transport and Communications portfolio?<br />
PM: Well it's a n area firstly that he has always liked.<br />
It's an area. which he had in the past asked for. It's one<br />
which, I think, given the balance of arrangements Mr Kerin<br />
was better doing the Trade job, given the fact that he comes<br />
to it with a natural background, particularly from the<br />
agricultural negotiations, and the fact that agriculture is<br />
still very much part and parcel of the debate around the<br />
Dunkel Package and the completion of the round. And for Mr<br />
Kerin it meant climbing over a domestic portfolio, learning<br />
that issue, whereas Senator Richardson had had a reasonably </p>
<p>long-standinrg interest in much of the subject area of<br />
Transport anrd Communications. The other thing is, Senator<br />
Richardson hiad completed a couple of years of Social<br />
Security Minister, a difficult and onerous portfolio, with<br />
distinction, as he had before that propogated the Labor<br />
Party's policies in relation to the environment. So he has,<br />
I think, an impressive track record and one thing he has<br />
proven is thrat he can raise the public consciousness about a<br />
subject, he can reform an area, and in an area where<br />
microeconomic change will continue to need reform I thought<br />
he was the most appropriate person to employ.<br />
J: Mr Keating, will you be having any discussions with Mr7<br />
Hawke about his future? Do you have any thoughts about what<br />
you might like to see him doing?<br />
PM: No, I haven't. I had about an hour and half with Bob a<br />
couple of days after the leadership changed, and we were<br />
just talking about the future together, what he might do,<br />
and about thie country generally.<br />
J: Prime Minister, no Queenslander is in the Cabinet Mr<br />
Beazley, I t: hink, is taking responsibility for that State.<br />
Will you continue that system?<br />
PM: What I would like to do, and will do, is ask Mr<br />
Humphreys to represent Queensland and be co-opted to the<br />
Cabinet whenever a matter affecting Queensland is debated.<br />
And he has ( liven me the assurance that he would be pleased<br />
to co-operat~ e in that arrangement. And also, in the<br />
Parliamentary Secretaries I have appointed Mr Johns also as<br />
a Parliament~ ary Secretary from Queensland. Now,<br />
Parliamentary Secretaries, of course, don't have Ministerial<br />
status or the responsibilities of a Minister, but I think<br />
where issues of material interest to Queensland arise, and<br />
they will form time to time obviously, then Ben Humphries is<br />
I think well. placed to represent Queensland's interests in<br />
the Cabinet.<br />
J: Mr Keating, do you expect now that with Mr Dawkins as<br />
Treasurer, hie will be seeking to put in his policies, some<br />
of things hEt's been pushing this year, such as, export and<br />
development schemes or measures to have more influence over<br />
the exchange rate?<br />
PM: No. I'm sure Mr Dawkins will be as a Treasurer very<br />
much in the tradition of the Cabinet system of Government.<br />
That is, his: views will matter but the Cabinet views will<br />
always matter too, as they did with me when I was Treasurer.<br />
And some of things which Mr Dawkins has spoken of have in<br />
one way shape or form been addressed over the last few<br />
months, others perhaps not. But, again, he has got to make<br />
his own decisions as Treasurer, rather than somebody from<br />
outside the Treasury portfolio without the advice of the<br />
Treasury abo'ut some of these subjects. But I have found him<br />
to be a most careful, creative and competent person in<br />
assessing issues and giving them their appropriate weight </p>
<p>and responses. And I've got no reason to believe he won't<br />
be at his best as Treasurer.<br />
J: ( inaudible) March.<br />
PM: Well, I can't give you anymore advice, Michelle, than I<br />
gave you last time. It will be sometime in the early part<br />
of the New ' Year.<br />
J: Should Cabinet review the Coronation Hill decision?<br />
PM: Well, this is not an agenda item for me and hasn't<br />
been. I don't see it being a matter for review. Its not<br />
been something to which I've addressed myself.<br />
J: Do you believe there is any role for the Government in<br />
the Compass affair?<br />
PM: In terins of a corporate financial role, no, but I<br />
thought a role in relation to the passengers and the<br />
families of those passengers, and that's why the Government<br />
was at pains to make sure as many people were uplifted and<br />
taken to the~ ir holidays and returned, and that will happen.<br />
But the future of Compass will depend upon the shareholders<br />
and the creditors of Compass, not on the Federal Government.<br />
J: Do you expect Mr Hawke to leave Parliament very soon?<br />
PM: No. I think that's a matter for Bob, not for me. And<br />
I can only repeat to you what he has said himself, that is,<br />
he intends -to stay around until such time as he advises<br />
otherwise. J: Mr Keating, on Sunday Dr Blewett announced the GATT<br />
position for Australia, and said he hoped to be meeting with<br />
President Bush. Because of his previous expertise will he<br />
still be involved in these meetings, and also do you plan to<br />
set any new trade agenda in Australian relationships with<br />
America, at these meetings?<br />
PM: Well, obviously, the GATT round is going to be<br />
important to Australia and to the United States. There has<br />
probably never been a greater lift in wealth than that which<br />
has come from the multilateral trading system in the past<br />
war years, ] particularly in manufactures after the Kennedy<br />
round, and Australia has regarded this round as being<br />
particularly important because it broadened the field into<br />
agriculture, interlectual property rights, services and<br />
other things in which we had an interest as a commodity<br />
trader and a trader in services, and which the United States<br />
of course has had an interest. And the United States<br />
interest goes even beyond the questions of market access; to<br />
its own fiscal policies and the burden which it's bearing<br />
itself by virtue of the European agricultural subsidies.<br />
So, the United States has a great stake in the GATT round<br />
and the importance of it was always evident to me by the<br />
Ministerial attention it received at GATT meetings, at the<br />
OECD, at the IMF etc. Now, we are reaching the end of the </p>
<p>round and while we are very much encouraged by Mr Dunkel's<br />
package, as Dr Blewett said, the devil is in the detail and<br />
we'll have to go through the detail to see where we stand.<br />
We've got some, the European Commission have said that parts<br />
of it are unacceptable, although the British and the Germans<br />
have said some favourable things about it. We have not<br />
said, and won't say at this stage that we accept it, we want<br />
the right to examine it, but we'll certainly be raising it<br />
in its context with President Bush during his visit to<br />
Australia. J: Are you taking any kind of a hard line with Mr Bush on<br />
the EEP subsidies and the effect they are having on<br />
agriculture in Australia?<br />
PM: Well, I'll be having, I hope, a productive discussion<br />
with the President, and that will obviously be an issue<br />
under discussion.<br />
J: Are yolu satisfied with the outcome of the inquiry into<br />
the Dili massacre as a credible one?<br />
PM: Well, .1 think the preliminary report was much more<br />
credible than that which we've seen before, and I think we<br />
regard it as an encouraging document. The Foreign Minister<br />
said it was very encouraging and better than expected. I<br />
think the important thing isthoughwhat the final report<br />
says and what the Government of Indonesia's consideration of<br />
the report will produce.<br />
J: You didn't have any more consideration to when you<br />
might visit Djakarta?<br />
PM: No I haven't because it wasn't the scheduled visit<br />
which Bob Hawke had was very inopportune for me, that is,<br />
becoming PriLme Minister of Australia at this time. So<br />
that's some-thing which I can consider in the future.<br />
J: Mr Keating, at one stage you were interested in having<br />
a Minister iLn charge of competition policies. I notice you<br />
haven't done that in this reshuffle. Why did you decide<br />
against that?<br />
PM: Well, was interested in competition policy rather<br />
than a Minister for Competition Policy. And competition<br />
policies have been coming together under the Attorney-<br />
General. We have brought the TPC and the PSA together, and<br />
I think that: that has been progressing in my absence from<br />
the Ministry. And I think that given the time-frame I have<br />
now, and the fact that I wanted the Ministry in place as<br />
quickly as possible, to get policy changes moving this year,<br />
I didn't have the luxury of a long time to debate whatdepartmenta.<br />
l structure might best suit the competition<br />
issue. But I've been prepared to accept at face value that:<br />
it has been progressing, and has been progressed, by the<br />
Attorney-General within the Attorney-General's portfolio. </p>
<p>-7.<br />
J: Mr Keating, Senator Walsh this morning called for the<br />
immigration intake to be slashed. Do you think there are<br />
grounds for this to be reviewed?<br />
PM: Well, look, I don't want to go round the world for<br />
sport, Peter. I'm essentially here to talk about the<br />
Ministry and the Ministerial arrangements. It's obviously<br />
an issue in public life in Australia, and it has been an<br />
issue within the Government, and Senator Walsh's views on<br />
this issue are well known to everybody. And he raises it<br />
with some regularity.<br />
J: Why have you increased the number of Parliamentary<br />
Secretaries? And are these effectively people who are<br />
Ministers in waiting? I mean, can you see them being in the<br />
next... PM: Not necessarily, no. But I think it is a very good<br />
basis for experience for members of the backbench of the<br />
Government, and in some Parliaments all Ministers have<br />
Parliamentary Secretaries. In the British Parliament, the<br />
British Government, I think most Ministers have<br />
Parliamentary Secretaries or numbers of Parliamentary<br />
Secretaries. And I think it is a superb way of giving<br />
backbench members or former Ministers in other Governments<br />
some experience of the Commonwealth realm and its<br />
administration. As you know, a Parliamentary Secretary is<br />
not paid anymore than a backbencher. It is essentially<br />
volunteering a greater effort in the interests of the<br />
Government and the Commonwealth, and I think it's a<br />
particularly good thing to do.<br />
J: How long would Senator Bob McMullan be expected to<br />
remain a Parliamentary Secretary, if you are talking about<br />
experience and developing new talent?<br />
PM: Well, you are really asking me for a pecking order for<br />
changes to -the Ministry, and I can't give you that. But,<br />
Senator McMullan has brought a lot of experience to taxation<br />
policy, and it is an area of great complexity and I know<br />
he's earned the respect and trust of the Taxation<br />
Commissioner and his office, the Australian Taxation Office,<br />
as also the Tax Policy Division of the Treasury. So, I<br />
could say when I was Treasurer I was very happy to have Bob<br />
in that job, and because he is now so full bottle in this<br />
area it was,. I think, entirely sensible to leave him there,<br />
and he likes it.<br />
J: ( inaudible) some people might suggest that you have<br />
rewarded people who were your closest supporters for your<br />
campaign. What do you say to that? And secondly, can you<br />
say that didn't play a part?<br />
PM: Well, by the same logic you would have to say I<br />
rewarded those who played a key role in Mr Hawke's campaign.<br />
J: Mr Keat~ ing, you've left Senator Evans in the position<br />
as Minister for Foreign Affairs. Does this indicate that </p>
<p>you have no particular plans to change any foreign policy<br />
issues? I mean, in particular, the Middle East where Mr<br />
Hawke's special interest had a great influence, I think, on<br />
attitudes towards Israel?<br />
PM: I think Senator Evans has been a particularly competent<br />
Minister for Foreign Affairs. He has reflected glory upon<br />
the Government, and it would have been, he is the obvious<br />
choice for Foreign Minister. And I would expect, naturally,<br />
because the Prime Minister has perogatives in foreign policy<br />
that other Ministers don't have, to discuss those, as needs<br />
be, with the Foreign Minister bearing in mind his<br />
specialisation and his primary responsibility for foreign<br />
policy. J: Prime Minister, could I ask a question, perhaps in two<br />
parts? Prime Minister Whitlam's first visit, on becoming<br />
Prime Minis-ter, overseas was to New Zealand. Prime Minister<br />
Hawke's first visit was to Indonesia. Where will your's be?<br />
And secondly, the vitally important environmental mission to0<br />
Rio, that Mr Hawke was going to take us all along on, is<br />
that still happening?<br />
PM: Well, if you are enquiring about your travel itinerary,<br />
I can't really help you. I don't think there is any<br />
protocol here, it's a matter of when people inherit these<br />
positions, and what issues are on at the time. Much of the<br />
debate aboult the trade and investment in the industrialised<br />
world has taken place in the northern hemisphere, which has<br />
occasioned Ministers of Australia to be travelling to the<br />
northern hemisphere. But, in the last decade there has been<br />
much greater focus on the Asia/ Pacific, as I believe, there<br />
should be. We are an Asia/ Pacific power and it is in the<br />
Asia/ Pacific that our primary focus should be. So, while I:<br />
couldn't say what my travel plans would be, certainly, this,<br />
area will be receiving the priority.<br />
J: Mr Keating, why did you decide not to have a spill to<br />
get some new blood in. And given that you decided that, do<br />
you think there will be uncontrollable resentment amongst<br />
some of you3r backbench supporters about that decision?<br />
PM: No, it's not for the Leader to decide whether there<br />
should be a spill. If there is a view within the Caucus<br />
that it's ti~ me for all positions to be declared vacant they<br />
generally are declared vacant. But, there was in the Labor<br />
Party, the Parliamentary Labor Party's rules for one<br />
Parliament only, between 1975 and 1977, a rule which said,<br />
in the middle of the term all positions be declared vacant,<br />
that rule only lasted one Parliament. And that was removed,<br />
and there has not been any clear view coming from the Caucus<br />
or any part of it that there should be a spill of positions.<br />
And therefore, I am doing what all Leaders have done in the<br />
past, and that is, to allocate portfolios from the people<br />
chosen by the Caucus, and this Government has won four<br />
elections, and won them well, with personnel some of whom<br />
are still members of the Ministry, others of which have been<br />
added after our third and fourth elections well, second, </p>
<p>third and fourth elections, and it has made us stronger and<br />
better. We: kept the changes coming through, the Cabinet<br />
personnel has dramatically changed from the Cabinet of 1983.<br />
And obviously, as time goes by it will change further.<br />
J: Mr Keating, Mr Willis has been Treasurer in waiting for<br />
almost 9 years now, and has only had the job for 3 weeks.<br />
Do you think you've been a bit rough on him? And how do you<br />
think he will take this decision?<br />
PM: Well, it was not an easy decision for me because we all<br />
grow close to one another in a Government, particularly, a<br />
reformist Government like this one has been. In the<br />
expenditure review rounds we sat in each other's company for<br />
or 12 hours a day, sometimes for 2 and 3 months at a<br />
time, over years. I mean, I can't imagine any other Cabinet<br />
effort, Cabinet level effort, where line items of the Budget<br />
are reviewed twice a year for eight years, in any other<br />
country. We did that as a group of Ministers and, of<br />
course, it has produced a great bond between us all. So, : Lt<br />
is very difficult to make these choices, and it is, I think,<br />
to Mr Willis' great credit that he has done, not only not<br />
taken his bat and ball, but decided to put his shoulder to<br />
the wheel to one of the toughest jobs in the Cabinet which<br />
is Finance, which he knows well, which he's proven he knows<br />
well. J: Mr Keating, it is often said that Mr Hawke saw the<br />
Prime Ministership as a sort of Chairman of the Board role,<br />
and Mr Fraser in a much more interventionist sense. Can you<br />
tell us something of how you see the role, and particularly,<br />
how activist you see yourself being as Prime Minister in<br />
economic po: licy Are you inclined to leave a fair bit of<br />
initiative to your Treasurer, or because of your background<br />
do you see yourself being more activist in that area than<br />
say Mr Hawke was when you were Treasurer?<br />
PM: No, I'd say the former rather than the latter. That I.<br />
would be inclined to leave policy to Ministers, but I think<br />
it is the Pr-ime Minister's duty, the Leader's duty to sketch<br />
out the dire ctions, and where we are not certain of those<br />
directions, to debate them within the Cabinet to make<br />
certain thait the directions are right and clear, clear and<br />
correct. Now, that is a responsibility of leadership.<br />
Beyond that, I think, Ministers should have a particular<br />
freedom to creatively develop the work within their<br />
portfolios but within the Cabinet system. The Cabinet<br />
system does work well. I mean, it is an efficient<br />
mechanism, i~ t has worked well for this Government and for<br />
Australia. And ' there is always that nice balance between<br />
the perogatives of the Leader and the Prime Minister and the<br />
Ministers. Now, all Prime Ministers will be different, all<br />
Leaders will be different, some will have a more hands on<br />
approach, an~ d some less, some chairmen of the board, some<br />
more managing directors, if I can use that, some with a more<br />
executive bent. But I think time will tell how any one of<br />
us react to these circumstances. </p>
<p>J: So, are you more inclined to the chairman of the board,<br />
or the managing director?<br />
PM: I'd say I'm somewhere half way in between, if there is<br />
such a position.<br />
J: Mr Keating, will you be sharing your thoughts on urban<br />
development and so forth, which you've expressed fairly<br />
strongly in the last few months, with Mr Howe? And does his<br />
Better Cities program carry on as he sketched it out?<br />
PM: Well, Brian and I. I'd like first of all to find out<br />
about the Better Cities program exactly what is happening<br />
within that area. But, as you know, I regard urban<br />
development issues very importantly. I think how we live,<br />
the cities we live in, how they develop, the choices in<br />
housing, the beauty of the places we live, are very<br />
important issues. And Brian, I think, has also regarded<br />
them, for sometime now, as importantly as I have. But, it<br />
is true that we don't have an urban facility within the<br />
Commonwealth bureaucracy. What we had in the seventies is<br />
largely rundown, and we are constructing something from the<br />
ground up, and that task has fallen to Brian Howe, and it's<br />
not easy. But, to the extent that he has begun it with the<br />
Better Cities policy, I'll be taking an interest in what in<br />
practical terms that policy entails, implies, and I look<br />
forward to having a chat with him about it.<br />
J: Mr Keating, did you give any consideration to moving Mr<br />
Howe from H-ealth given his association with the co-payments<br />
scheme? PM: No, Mr Howe expressed every willingness to continue as<br />
Minister for Health and Community Services. And, of course,<br />
as Deputy, ' Deputy's have a sort of acknowledged right in the<br />
system to decide what they think is in their best interests.<br />
J: Prime Minister, will you be getting out and about<br />
tripping over the camera cables in supermarkets?<br />
PM: Well, I'll live principally in Canberra, as I think all<br />
Prime Ministers have done since the Parliament moved to the<br />
Capital in .1927. But I've always got about Australia as<br />
much as I could and I've always done a lot of shopping.<br />
I've seen many of you at the Fyshwick markets, as you know.<br />
I might have been an ungainly box carrier, but I've done it:<br />
with might and main, and with good grace. For years I've<br />
bought the bird seed and I've bought the fish, and the odd<br />
record. ENDS </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
