<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4070</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER - ADDRESS IN REPLY</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/02/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004070_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
P76/ 42<br />
PF 12 P ' A M I EMBARGO: 2000 hours,<br />
Check against delivery<br />
26 February 1976<br />
PRIM4E MINISTER-ADDRESS IN RE-PLY<br />
In -the last three years, a serious econoioic crisis has been<br />
needlessly brought on Australia, an economic crisis which has<br />
harmed all Australians and has harmed the weak and poor most<br />
of all.<br />
The crisis was principally caused by a failure on the part of<br />
Goverrnent to plan and act responsibly by an unrealistic attitude<br />
to what Government can effectively achieve.<br />
To restore prosperity there must be a much more realistic<br />
appreciation of what Government can and cannot do.<br />
At the heart of Australia's current problems is a lack of<br />
realism about one simple basic fact the fact that at any one<br />
time Australians' resources are limited.<br />
This fact should be obvious, when we address ourselves to it.<br />
It is obvious, but despite this, it has been persistently<br />
and dangerously ignored.<br />
Because our resources are limited, we are -or ought to beconstantly<br />
faced with choices about how those resources will<br />
be used. / 2 </p>
<p>Those choices are often very difficult to make.<br />
It would be more comfortable for us all if we did not<br />
have to face the~ q But if we ignore them, if we pretend<br />
that we do not have to choose, we do so at our peril.<br />
Real improvements which are no'c-at the expense of other<br />
people, other areas, are restricted by the'rate of real economic<br />
growth. The fact that our resources are limited presents hard<br />
choices in many areas. There is an obligation on all of us<br />
to face up to those choices.<br />
The need to choose how our resources will be used, confronts<br />
us all. I want to discuss tonight, three areas where the need<br />
to choose is pressing.<br />
The three areas are government expenditure, wagcs and salaries,<br />
and social security spending.<br />
First, government expenditure.<br />
Because our resources are limited at any one time, we have<br />
to choose which of the many worthwriile things that need to be<br />
dlone we will do now, and which we will leave for the Zfuture.<br />
It is crucial. to understand that these choices are not just<br />
choices between different areas of government expenditure.<br />
They are also even more importantly choices between<br />
government spending on the one hand and spending by individuals<br />
and private enterprises on the other.<br />
The more Government decides to spend on goods and services<br />
the less real value the wage and salary earner can expect<br />
to have in his pay packet. The more politicans decide how<br />
People's earnings are to be spent, the less discretion do people<br />
have over their own income. / 3 </p>
<p>A resonsible. Governrent must be prepared t--o take the very<br />
difficult decisons between different kinds of public<br />
expenditure . A government which vatlues the independence<br />
and capacity of Australians to make as they wish the<br />
important decision of their lives, will not pre-empt. too large a<br />
proportion 6f people's incomes for Government programmes.<br />
I[ n the end, of course, there is no escape from responsibility.<br />
The pressure from limited resources is ultimately inescapable,<br />
as... we are now finding to our cost, and as other countries<br />
such as Great Britain, are finding to their cost.<br />
In the last three years, there have been quit-e extraordinary<br />
increases in Government spending. Just because Australians'<br />
wealth is limited, this has required a massive transfer<br />
of resources from individuals and private enterprise to<br />
Govcrnment.<br />
Looking over the last three years, at the many new costly<br />
programmes which have been undertaken, we should remnember<br />
how they have been paid for, and who has paid for them.<br />
Enormous expenditures were made which were quite unrelated<br />
to the Government' s revenue.<br />
The deficit for the last two financial years is of the brdei<br />
of $ 7,000 million. The new Government has inherited a<br />
deficit which the Australian people were told in August would<br />
be $ 2800 million but which was rising out of control t'owards<br />
$ 5000 million by the end of the year. Since the revenue<br />
was inadequate to cover this massive expenditure, it has<br />
been financed out of inflation.<br />
The people who have paid for this expenditure are those whose<br />
real income and savings have been eroded by inflation. The<br />
burden has fallen most heavily on the productive sector of the<br />
economy, on those people who have lost their jobs, and on -the<br />
weaker and poorer sections of the community. </p>
<p>The report of the inquiry into poverty states;. " Inflation<br />
favours the active and the powerful: the position of<br />
poor people deteriorates.'<br />
Many of the previous Government's programmes were introduced<br />
in the guise of helping the disadvantaged. The fact that many of<br />
these programmes have been financed out of intlation makes<br />
a mockery of these pretensions. The report of the poverty<br />
inquiry stated quite plainly that inflation contributed to poverty<br />
in Australia.<br />
" No country with a continuing inflation rate of over 10% has<br />
been able to prevent this causing grave hardship to<br />
important groups of poor people."<br />
On-Tuesday, we heard an impassioned attack from the Leader<br />
of the Opposition on the programme of the. present Government.<br />
So distant is the Member for Werriwa's touch with reality that<br />
he forgot the reality of his years of misrule anid represented it as<br />
a progressive Government full of compassion for the disadvantaged,<br />
a Government which took concrete action to assist those in need.<br />
The real record of his Government is far from this.<br />
The former Labor Government, despite its protestations, in effect<br />
sacrificed its claims for concern for the disadvantaged<br />
to its dream for the centralisation of power.<br />
Let's look at the most blatant fact unemployment. An<br />
unemployment directly consequential on Labor's disregard for the<br />
fact of life; an unemployment which hamned most of all the weak)<br />
the migrants, the poor those sections of the Australian community<br />
which have sometimes looked upon the A. L. P. as their protector.<br />
These people were sacrificed by Labor to unemployment. The<br />
Labor Party refused to face the fact that the more Government spent,<br />
the less there was for private enterprise to use in creating job<br />
opportunities. These social democrats, these so-called protectors,<br />
of the weak and poor, brought the highest unemployment to Australia<br />
since the Great Depression. </p>
<p>The Leader of the Opposition certainly cannot. be criticised<br />
for allowing the facts his Government created, to<br />
weigh too heavily on his mind. In migration the reunion<br />
programme nullified pensions. The Labor Government<br />
abandoned its commitments to increase pensions according<br />
to average weekly earnings. His last Treasurer deferred<br />
the-pension increase by a month. His last Minister for<br />
Social Security conducted an attack on voluntary<br />
welfare agencies. In education, his Government was forced<br />
by its own failure to abandon triennial funding and disrupt<br />
important research programmes.<br />
The Leader of the Opposition might well be thankful that his<br />
dismissal and overwhelming rejection by the Australian<br />
population gave him the time and the frame of mind to embroider<br />
the myth of a social democratic Government brought to an untimely<br />
end. The reality is of an elitist political party which has severed<br />
its bases of support in the interest of expanding the power<br />
of a few men. The reality is a political party which has wilfully<br />
spent Australia into the worst inflation and the highest<br />
unemployment for decades.<br />
Excessive Government spending tended to exacerbate inflation<br />
and infaltion has continued to sap confidence throughout the<br />
community. Expectations of inflation have added a big element<br />
of uncertainty to investment decision uncertainty has<br />
damped investment activity. Both the current level of activity<br />
and the long term potential for economic growth have been curtailed<br />
as a result.<br />
Inflation and the fear of unemployment has also contributed to the<br />
reluctance of consumers to spend as reflected in a sharp.<br />
increase in the rate of savings.<br />
Between 1971-72 and 1974-75 the savings ratio in Australia rose from<br />
9.7 percent to 17 percent. The indications are that </p>
<p>individuals react to high Yates of inflation by<br />
seeking higher cash balances to protect theiñ own positions<br />
and ininimise what they view as the risks to their security.<br />
The very things that encourage people tCo save uncertainty<br />
and fear of inflation are the same things inhibiting business<br />
from investing.<br />
The first task is to bring inflation under control.<br />
Pre-eminently, that means asserting a responsible attitude to<br />
Government spending. This means being prepared to tell people<br />
the truth that at any one time there are limits on what<br />
Government can do without damaging the capacity of other<br />
people to achieve their objectives.<br />
The Government believes th-at since resources are limited the<br />
crucial choice between Government and private spending should<br />
be as far as possible an explicit choice' a choice which is<br />
clearly presented to the Australian people.<br />
For that reason the Government had as a major plank in its<br />
election programmie the introduc-tion of tax indexation. For<br />
that reason the Government will begin the implementation of<br />
tax index~ ation in the next Budget. For that reason the Government<br />
will be aiming to take as Ilarge a first step as will be possible<br />
in the econom~ ic and budgetary circumstances.<br />
The Government regards indexation as a major part of its<br />
programme to control inflation and force Governments to be honest<br />
about the costs of their spending programmes.<br />
We believe that the Australian people will appreciate that tax<br />
indexation ( and its accompanying tax reforms) is a far more<br />
effective way of protecting their earnings than seeking even<br />
higher money wages which are soon eroded by price increases.<br />
The Government believes that responsbility with respect to its<br />
own spending, with respect to the claims it makes on peoples<br />
incomes, is the best way to secure responsibility in wage and<br />
salary demands. / 7. </p>
<p>This leads me to the second area where Australians<br />
as a people have to face the consequences of limited<br />
resources the area of wage and salary demands.<br />
The previous Government pretended to people that they could<br />
have higher and higher real wages and salaries at the same time<br />
as real Government spending was rising rapidly. In doing this, it<br />
was failing utterly in its duties . It was an undertaking<br />
a cruel and deceitful fraud which inevitably led to<br />
disastrous inflation.<br />
It is also being now more widely recognised that those people<br />
who have jobs cannot obtain higher and higher wages without<br />
taking money which could be used to provide jobs for those currently<br />
out of work. Often higher wages and salaries are being paid<br />
at the expense of jobs, at the expense of economic recovery.<br />
Likewise, every unjustified increase in price by a business,<br />
places an added strain on the resources of wage and salary<br />
earners.<br />
The Governments looks to business and trade unions to act<br />
responsibly in the national interest.<br />
In the fight against inflation, we will conduct a continuing<br />
dialogue with key groups in the community. One example<br />
of this is the tripartite conference in Melbourne in January<br />
attended by trade union leaders, employers' representatives<br />
and the Government. Such disucssions will contribute<br />
to better policies and to more successful anti-inflationary<br />
performance. </p>
<p>We have also established the Economic Consultative Group,<br />
which consists of 17 business and union leaders and which m'ut<br />
with senior ministers on 6th February as the-first in a regular<br />
series of exchanges of information and views.<br />
Employers have duties imposed by law to their shareholders.<br />
Other laws, and common morality, give them obligations to their<br />
employers and to the public.<br />
The Government expects employers to demonstrate a commitment<br />
to economic'recovery in the national interest. The Government<br />
expects a like commitment from the trade union movement.<br />
The trade union movement, and particularly the must<br />
be concerned with jobs and productivity. The trade union movement<br />
can no longer be too much concerned with higher money wages at the<br />
expense of other legitimate concerns such as the working environmen.<br />
and jobs. An exclusive concern with money wages is to pursue<br />
momentary interest at the expense of jobs and at the expense of<br />
their worKmates.<br />
Lack of wage restraint will. have immediate consequences the loss<br />
of productive jobs as employers lay off staff. It haF long term co:<br />
in that the essential conditions for real improvement in standards<br />
of living are under-mined by inflation.<br />
Increasingly, the rank and file unionist is realising that higher<br />
money wages which undermine the pre-requisite of economic<br />
prosperity are neither in their interests nor in the interests<br />
of other Australians.<br />
No longer can the trade union movement argue that providing jobs is<br />
the sole responsibility of employers. No longer can the trade<br />
union movement regard itself as responsible only for getting more<br />
money for its members. The power of the trade union movement<br />
must involve a broader responsibility. Unless the union movement<br />
discharges this responsiblity, its support amongst its own members<br />
will be eroded. A concern that there . are adequate jobs is a<br />
basic responsibility of the trade union leadership. </p>
<p>A concern to reduce inflaLion and protect jobs has beeni at the<br />
heart of the decisions and action t-akren by the Government since<br />
it was confirmed in office by the Australian electors. It was<br />
the basis of our submission to the Arbitration Commission in the<br />
National Wage Case.<br />
In the general strategy for economic recovery the Arbitration<br />
Commission has a very significant role to play. The Arbitration<br />
Commission is not one of the anonymous commissions that proliferated<br />
under the Labor Government. It is a long established highly respected<br />
institution, one whose actions and their consequences are<br />
closely watched by all the Australian people.<br />
The Arbitration Commission Act require. s the Commission to take<br />
into account the impact of its decisions on the economy. In the<br />
last case before the Commission the Government took the decision<br />
to oppose the passing on of the full 6.4% C. P. I. increase into<br />
wages on the grounds that it would increase inflation and unemployement<br />
and not provide the consumer and investor confidence essential to<br />
a soundly based economic recovery. The Arbitration Commission in<br />
its wisdom did pass the full 6.4% into wages. Flow soundly based<br />
the decision, was for the well being of the Australian economny, for the<br />
well being of the wage and salary earner will soon be discernible<br />
for all to see.<br />
I's there anyone who has argued that the decision. was positively good<br />
for the economy?<br />
We judged that the position we took was one we had to take as a<br />
responsible Government. We told the Commission what we saw to<br />
be in the interests of the community as a whole. Australians wil.<br />
expect and rightly expect that al. l sections of the community<br />
will cooperate in securing a return to prosperity.<br />
With this cooperation, 1976 should be a year of recovery. This<br />
recovery may very well be gradual, but this is all to the good.<br />
We have done with violent swings in policy. A moderate rate of<br />
growth will ensure balance, a lessening of inflation and the<br />
expectations which perpetuate it. </p>
<p>This is the singl. e most important factor in ensuring that<br />
recovery is a lasting one. our policy not only con siders 1076<br />
but the years beyond that as viell.<br />
This brings me to the third area where Australians as a People<br />
have to face the fact of limited resources.<br />
A genuine return to prosperity will require that assistance to<br />
the disadvantaged and those in need is effectively provided.<br />
The Government's approach to social welfare is based on'the<br />
Government's commitment to the value of each person and each<br />
person' s right to dignity and autonomy. It is also based on<br />
the Government's recognition that there are limited resources<br />
to devote to the general welfare area, arid those resources that<br />
are available must be devoted first of all to helping t-hosb who<br />
are disadvantaged.<br />
The Government endorses the principle spelled out by the report<br />
of Inquiry into Poverty, that " need, and degree of need, should be<br />
the primary test by which help given to a person group or community<br />
should be determined."<br />
Failure to observe this principle must mean the diversion of<br />
resources to people who cannot be said to " need" them, at the<br />
expense of the other people and programmes from which the resources<br />
have beern drawn.<br />
The Report of the Poverty Inquiry itself dtew attention to the<br />
fact that:<br />
" Very large sums are being spent by Governments on the pretext that<br />
they are helping poor people when in fact the great bulk of the<br />
money goes to the middle class and poor people get little."<br />
Such a diversion of resources can be positively damaging to those in<br />
real need while having substantial hidden costs in terms of<br />
opportunities forgone in other areas. It may be possible to<br />
substantially improve assistance to those in need while reducing<br />
the overall burden'of some programmnes. </p>
<p>Our aims go much further than the achie. eent of material<br />
prosperity. We wnt to see Government assume a role in tis sociezvt which is<br />
consistent to the development of persoral fr-adam and individual<br />
initiative. To the development of nerson:-freiom and individual<br />
initiative. To quote his Excellency, the Governor General<br />
we aim to develop a " role for Government. which oilaces more<br />
reliance on the commonsense and reason of t-e Australian people".<br />
We do not believe that the Australian Deonle want a Government<br />
which takes over from them their reszonsfi lity for decisions<br />
concerning the manner in which they live. do not believe<br />
they wish to forfeit their individualisi to an all-pervading<br />
paternalistic Government.<br />
The long term objective of the Gov . rnment is to encourage the<br />
development of an Australia in which peoepe are free and encouraged<br />
to achieve goals in life which they set for themselves.<br />
It would be an Australia in which Govern-'. :. ts recognise that they<br />
cannot presume to live people's lives for hcm. That recognising<br />
the dignity of people means valuing the inependence of people<br />
to take the important decisions of thc. ir ves for themselves.<br />
It would be an Australia where ther_ is a c-ni: ine concern to assist<br />
those in real need, those who are idsL.' antage1 an Australia<br />
where effective action is taken to ) s-is: thE disadvantaged.<br />
It would be an Australia in which piwerful interests recognise<br />
their responsibilities to the indi'i uals t: ivy serve and to the<br />
wider community.<br />
It is our unqualified policy to rcz; tOre Svernment to a role<br />
in Australia consistent with fr4ee.&gt; s true democracy. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
