<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6611</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S SPEECH, COMBINED MEETING OF ECONOMICS SOCIETY AND INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS SOCIETY, CANBERRA, 14 MARCH 1985</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/03/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006611.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
PRIME MINISTER'S SPEECH<br />
COMBINED MEETING OF ECONOMICS SOCIETY AND INDUSTRIAL<br />
RELATIONS SOCIETY CANBERRA 14 MARCH 1985<br />
Since the Labor Government came to office two years ago<br />
committed to relieving this country of deep and<br />
worsening recession, there has been a recognition, both<br />
wi'thin Australia and internationally, of the very<br />
significant success which has attended its management of<br />
the economy. This recognition has been positive and<br />
widespread. It has been reflected in the almost<br />
deafening silence in the last Parliament of our<br />
political opponents in the area of economic debate.<br />
In these past two years we have steadily been<br />
.1 implementing policies directed at restoring economic<br />
growth and moderating inflation, which we have<br />
U describedas fighting unemployment and inflation at the<br />
same time.<br />
And from the beginning we have given equal priority to<br />
the development of pol-icies directed at removing<br />
structural impediments to improving Australia's longterm<br />
growth performance.<br />
The main elements both of our short-term macro-economic<br />
policies and of our long-term growth policies are well<br />
C known to a group like this, and it is not necessary to<br />
Ii traverse in any depth that-old territory.<br />
But it is necessary to say this by way of preface. Our<br />
policies have been successful for two basic reasons.<br />
a One, they have been intrinsically correct, and relevant,<br />
in economic terms. Two, they have been well founded in<br />
a clear understanding of, and a preparedness to work<br />
within, the realities of our economic and industrial<br />
system. Problems will arise because we live and operate in the<br />
complex real world, a world of prejudice, of passion, of<br />
preconceptions and of power power which will not<br />
always be exercised by individuals and groups within the<br />
economic system according to what may be adjudged </p>
<p>-2<br />
impartially to be in the national interest.<br />
That leads me to make this point which I believe is<br />
compellingly true while a Government is entitled to be<br />
questioned, criticised, about the implication of its<br />
policy decisions there is a corresponding obligation to<br />
test alternative policy prescriptions with similar<br />
rigour. To give a specific example, I find it only<br />
slightly less than ludicrous to hear it suggested that<br />
the Government's wage policies are inappropriate because<br />
they will lead to undesirable wage increases. It may be<br />
true that the policies may lead to some wage increases<br />
which from some perspectives are undesirable. What is<br />
absolutely certain is that the muddle-headed<br />
prescriptions of our opponents for the abandonment of<br />
the regulated centralised system in favour of<br />
decentralised bargaining would be a recipe for a<br />
devastating wages explosion. The critics ignore<br />
Q history, they ignore reality.<br />
That said, I want in this real context, to use our time<br />
tonight to discuss some of the major challenges that we<br />
face this year in maintaining the economic recovery<br />
without a resurgence of inflation, and to improving<br />
Australia's long-term growth performance.<br />
Our policies for fighting unemployment and inflation at<br />
the same time have embodied mutually supportive<br />
approaches to fiscal, monetary and wages policy.<br />
Our fiscal policies were initially highly expansionary,<br />
making substantial changes to the direction but only<br />
slightly reducing the magnitude of the fiscal stimulus<br />
implicit in our conservative predecessors' economic<br />
policy U-turn in the nine months before they lost<br />
office. We made it clear in those early days that we<br />
would reduce the budget deficit as private investment<br />
C expanded in the course of economic recovery.<br />
The fiscal expansion of 1983-84 contributed to the<br />
strong recovery that commenced in the September quar: er<br />
of that year. In our second budget, 1984-85, we<br />
provided for. a reduced rate of growth in Government<br />
outlays and a lower budget deficit in money terms, vw* iichn<br />
reduced the Commonwealth deficit as a proportion of CDP<br />
from 4.3 per cent to 3.3 per cent. In the confident<br />
expectation of continued economic recovery, and<br />
therefore of continued increases in private investment<br />
demands on financial markets, prior to last year's<br />
election I pledged my Government to:<br />
Further reductions in the deficit in money terms in<br />
1985-86 and as a proportion of GDP over the life of<br />
the current Parliament; </p>
<p>-3<br />
* No increase in Commonwealth tax revenue as a<br />
proportion of GDP in 1985-86 and over the life of the<br />
Parliament; and<br />
* A reduction in Government expenditure as a proportion<br />
of GDP in 1985-86 and over the life of the<br />
Parliament.<br />
Since the election we have moved quickly to give effect<br />
to these undertakings. The whole process of budget<br />
preparation has been accelerated and the Government is<br />
currently well advanced in designing a budget with a<br />
deficit significantly below the current year in money<br />
terms. This further substantial reduction in the<br />
Commonwealth deficit, from 3.3 per cent to approaching<br />
two and a half per cent of GDP, will have been achieved<br />
entirely through the combination of expenditure<br />
restraint and economic growth, without any increase in<br />
the overall tax burden.<br />
We have consistently applied monetary policy designed to<br />
support strong growth but not any resurgence of<br />
inflation. There has been no change in our application<br />
of firm monetary policy within this approach since we<br />
suspended the monetary projections in January, when it<br />
became clear that deregulation was seriously distorting<br />
monetary measurement-~<br />
And underpinning all of our policies for economic<br />
recovery, and making it possible to implement fiscal and<br />
monetary policies for growth, is the Prices and Incomes<br />
Accord. The Accord has always had its detractors. There were,<br />
of course, those who said it could not work because the<br />
ACTU could not deliver. Others argued on doctrinal<br />
grounds that incomes and prices policies cannot succeed.<br />
Even in the face of its obvious success there are th--se<br />
who contend that a slower rate of wage increase,<br />
purportedly more appropriate to current economic<br />
circumstances, would have been generated within a<br />
decentralise. d system without the Accord.<br />
The evidence is against the detractors. The decline in<br />
real unit labour costs to the levels of the late 1960s<br />
and early 1970s and the halving of the rate of infla~ tion<br />
over the past two years, through a period of strong<br />
economic growth, are against them. The continued<br />
commitment of the overwhelming majority of the trade<br />
union movement to wage moderation within the Accord is<br />
against them. And the Australian historical experience,<br />
when time after time incipient economic recovery has<br />
been dissipated in unrealistic income claims and a </p>
<p>4<br />
resurgence of inflation, is against them.<br />
With two years of reduced inflation and moderated wage<br />
demands behind us, there is no doubt at all that the<br />
Accord, combined with the Labor Government's other<br />
policies, has produced a marked break in inflationary<br />
expectations. The wages policy dimensions of-the Accord do not exist<br />
in a vacuum. Crucially, they are supported by the<br />
Government's commitments to consultation and consensus,<br />
to the equitable distribution of the benefits of<br />
economic growth, and to the achievement of sustained,<br />
strong non-inflationary growth. I have always seen<br />
these three commitments as inter-related parts of the<br />
one great program.<br />
No progress can be made on any one of the three without<br />
support from the others.<br />
Without sustained non-inflationary growth, there can be<br />
no progress towards any other objective.<br />
Without sustained growth, high and rising unemployment<br />
will increase the number of Australians living in<br />
poverty. Without sustained growth there will be<br />
insufficient resources to provide adequately for<br />
Australians in need..<br />
But equally, only an Australian society that is broadly<br />
united on the great national goals, and which is seen by<br />
most of its citizens as a fair society, will embrace the<br />
changes which are necessary for sustained growth.<br />
This is the essential context of the Accord and the<br />
fundamental reason why the Accord is equal to the<br />
challenges that inevitably lie along the path to<br />
establishing sustained non-inflationary growth in<br />
Australia. The immediate challenge is the re-establishment of<br />
stable conditions, favourable to non-inflationary<br />
economic growth, in financial markets, and to ensure<br />
that the recent fall in the international value of the<br />
Australian dollar does not give rise to a resurgence of<br />
inflation. And the greatest challenge to our long-term<br />
aims of establishing Australia as a fairer, growthoriented<br />
society is the implementation of a progressive<br />
reform of the Australian taxation system; reform wizhin<br />
the constraints of the trilogy and the Nine Princip'es<br />
that I announced during the election campaign, and which<br />
does not threaten the gains we have made in reducing<br />
inflation. Later, I will deal with each of these in<br />
some detail. </p>
<p>There were good grounds for expecting a third year of<br />
strong growth in 1985-86, even before the recent<br />
depreciation of the Australian dollar. Real<br />
depreciation if maintained will provide an impetus<br />
to expansion of exports and substitution of domestic<br />
production for imports, which should add progressively<br />
to output growth over the next year or two. The dollar<br />
depreciation has other less favourable effects to which<br />
I will return. But first I would like to say more about<br />
the facts that justify confidence that the recovery in<br />
the real economy is on course.<br />
National Accounts estimates for the December quarter are<br />
not expected for another month. However, partial<br />
indicators point to a strengthening in private sector<br />
demand in the December quarter and to the continuing<br />
I. good prospects for the remainder of this financial year<br />
C and through 1985-86.<br />
The value of retail sales rose 2.9 per cent in the<br />
December quarter ( perhaps as much as 1.5 per cent in<br />
real terms), following a 2.4 per cent rise in September<br />
( 1.1 per cent in real terms). Another significant<br />
component of private final consumption expenditure that<br />
is not covered by the retail sales series is motor<br />
vehicles, and vehicle registrations grew by 3.5 per cent<br />
in the December quarter.<br />
You will recall that the Budget forecasts provided only<br />
for 2 3/ 4 per cent volume growth in private<br />
consumption after abstracting from the impact of<br />
Medicare on the measurement of that aggregate. The<br />
recent data confirm the Government's comments during the<br />
election campaign that this forecast seems likely to be<br />
comfortably exceeded.<br />
Following a fall in the September quarter, business<br />
investment appears to be strengthening on a path that<br />
will see the Budget forecasts exceeded, and that wi.. i<br />
provide further strong growth in 1985-86. The late~ z<br />
ABS survey figures, covering around 85 per cent of<br />
business investment, indicate 3.8 per cent growth in<br />
investment in the December quarter, with even stroncar<br />
growth projected over the remainder of 1984-85 and into<br />
* next financial year, again as was indicated during the<br />
election campaign.<br />
Housing activity led the recovery in 1983 and remains<br />
strong. Today's figures on building approvals show<br />
continuing strength through to January. Commencements<br />
grew by 2.1 per cent in the September quarter, and looks<br />
set to meet or exceed the total of 145,000 mentioned in </p>
<p>-6<br />
the Policy Speech. A flattening out in the vicinity of<br />
this high level is desirable, and consistent with the<br />
Government's expectations of continued strong overall<br />
private sector growth in the next financial year.<br />
Employment growth had been extraordinarily strong<br />
through 1983-84 but, as measured in the ABS survey,<br />
weakened early in this financial year. Since then,<br />
there has been a return to strong growth in employment.<br />
One hundred and ten thousand jobs have now been created<br />
in the first eight months of this financial year. The<br />
Jeremiahs seized with glee the weaker figures early in<br />
the financial year as indicating that the budget<br />
forecasts were wildly over-optimistic. With today's<br />
figures from the Statistician, employment has already<br />
expanded by almost 2 per cent in the first 8 months of<br />
the year, and the Budget forecast of about 2 1/ 2 per<br />
cent now seems well within range.<br />
Today's Labour Force figures bring total employment<br />
growth in the twenty two months since we changed the<br />
course of Australian economic history at the National<br />
Economic Summit Conference to 360,000. We are running<br />
ahead of our target of half a million new jobs in our<br />
first three years of office.<br />
The dramatic contrast between the experience of<br />
employment growth under the Labor Government, and that<br />
under the conservative government which we replaced, is<br />
a measure of the relative success of the two<br />
governments approaches to economic policy.<br />
In less than two years under our policies, 360,000 new<br />
jobs have been created. in seven years and four months,<br />
a total of 340,000 new jobs were created under the<br />
policies of our predecessors.<br />
Perhaps this is not a fair test of the performance off a<br />
conservative government that was dedicated to fightinga<br />
inflation first, and which explicitly allocated lower<br />
priority to expanding employment and reducing<br />
unemployment. Unfortunately for the conservatives, the comparison of<br />
performance on inflation is equally favourable to the<br />
Labor Government. The conservative administration,<br />
after over seven years of fighting inflation first, left<br />
Australia with an annual inflation rate over 11 per cent<br />
or about twice the OECD average. After two years of<br />
fighting unemployment and inflation at the same time,<br />
the inflation rate has fallen by half, to a level close<br />
to the OECD average. </p>
<p>-7<br />
Through the recent period of strong growth there has<br />
been one weakness in the real economy : the growing<br />
deficit in the current account of the balance of<br />
payments. A surprisingly high proportion of the growth<br />
in domestic demand has been flowing into imported goods<br />
and services, as reflected particularly in rising shares<br />
of imports in domest ic demand for manufactured goods.<br />
At the same time, after strong growth in 1983-8, export<br />
growth, particularly for manufactured goods, has slowed<br />
appreciably in recent months. Concern about this<br />
weakness came into sharp focus with the publication of<br />
the December quarter balance of payments statistics,<br />
which contained substantial upward revisions to previous<br />
estimates of imports. This weakness, together with<br />
anxieties about a-temporary break in the improved<br />
industrial relations that have generally prevailed since<br />
the change in Government two years ago, and other<br />
sources of uncertainty, combined to generate sudden<br />
weakness in foreign exchange and, less markedly, bond<br />
markets. Some observers have seen this combination of<br />
events as threatening recovery, particularly through<br />
their potential for rekindling inflation.<br />
Certainly the combination of a weak Australian dollar,<br />
and a return to unsustainable rates of wage increase,<br />
would have the potential for rekindling inflation and<br />
undermining recovery. The Government recognises the<br />
risk and is committed to ensuring that this challenge to<br />
recovery is effectively met.<br />
The fall in the international value of the Australian<br />
dollar in itself is not a threat to recovery. Indeed,<br />
it is the most effective instrument for correcting the<br />
rapidly expanding current account deficit. The rapid<br />
increases in the import shares of many categories of<br />
domestic demand and the disappointingly weak export<br />
performance of the manufacturing sector are clear<br />
indications that the depreciation in Australia's real<br />
effective exchange rate through 1983 and 1984 had not<br />
been large enough to remove the huge deterioration in<br />
our international competitiveness that had occurred<br />
through the-. period of the wages explosion and<br />
artificially high exchange rates in the early 1980s.<br />
This would seem to be part of the explanation for the<br />
apparently low ( although positive) manufacturing output<br />
growth over the past year.<br />
I should add in passi ng that the major adjustment which<br />
has occurred relatively painlessly this year under the<br />
floating exchange rate, could have been achieved only<br />
with great trauma, domestic financial instability and<br />
economic disruption under the old managed system which<br />
we inherited in March 1983 and abandoned nine months<br />
later. </p>
<p>8-<br />
If the recent real depreciation is sustained, it will<br />
have a major effect in strengthening our international<br />
competitiveness, including in manufacturing.<br />
At the same time, the depreciation will raise the price<br />
of a range of imported, exportable and import-competing<br />
goods, directly raising the average domestic price<br />
level. This price effect is an inevitable accompaniment<br />
of depreciation, and in itself does nothing to impair<br />
the associated improvement in competitiveness. It will<br />
lead to higher CPI increases than would otherwise have<br />
been observed over the next year or so.<br />
The important challenge for the maintenance of recovery,<br />
is to ensure that this initial rise in consumer prices<br />
does not initiate a debilitating upward spiral of costs<br />
and prices. We will be working to ensure that the<br />
depreciation does not reduce the substantial gains that<br />
we have made in lowering the underlying inflation rate.<br />
Much public discussion of this issue has focussed<br />
narrowly on the possibility of discounting wage<br />
indexation for the component of inflation that is<br />
contributed directly by the price increases associated<br />
with the depreciation.<br />
The Accord provides a cooperative forum within which<br />
appropriate responses to problems like the current<br />
threat of a resurgence in inflation can be discussed.<br />
If the Government came to believe that the discounting<br />
of wage indexation increases for the direct price<br />
effects of depreciation was the most effective way of<br />
responding to this prospect it would raise the matter<br />
within the consultative processes of the Accord.<br />
But as I said in the Parliament two weeks ago, the<br />
discounting of wage increases is only one of a number of<br />
ways of ensuring that the depreciation does not ignite a<br />
new inflationary spiral.<br />
Strict compliance with wage increases determined within<br />
the centralised system is obviously more important than<br />
ever. In this context, some reassurance can be drawn<br />
from the fact that the dispute involving public service<br />
unions was the only one of the major industrial disputes<br />
which we experienced earlier this year which involved a<br />
direct challenge to the centralised approach to wages<br />
policy within the Prices and Incomes Accord. Now that<br />
the public service dispute is back before the<br />
Arbitration Commission, all of the influence and power<br />
of Government will be applied to ensure that the<br />
Commission ' s decision is effective.<br />
The inflationary threat, the need to preserve the recent </p>
<p>9-<br />
improvement in Australia's international<br />
competitiveness, and the deterioration in Australia's<br />
terms of trade which was one of the underlying causes of<br />
the Australian dollar's depreciation, are all relevant<br />
to the deliberations of the Arbitration Commission in<br />
any future productivity hearing.<br />
In preventing the depreciation from leading to an<br />
increase in the underlying rate of inflation, the<br />
Government will explore every option available to it to<br />
ensure that the depreciation does not lead to a<br />
continuing spiral of increases in business costs and<br />
inflation.<br />
Since the first relevant wage indexation increase will<br />
not occur for over six months, there is time for the<br />
Government carefully to weigh the alternatives. But you<br />
should know that the Government is determined to<br />
6 preserve the competitive benefits of any sustained<br />
depreciation, and to prevent the depreciation leading to<br />
a new inflationary spiral.<br />
Looking to longer term economic performance, nothing is<br />
more important than the review of the taxation system<br />
that is now in process.<br />
As a minimum, the review must come to grips with four<br />
flaws in the current taxation system.<br />
It must address the widespread avoidance and evasion,<br />
especially by people with income well above the<br />
Australian average, which has caused a large proportion<br />
of the Australian community to believe that the system<br />
is unfair.<br />
It must address poverty traps. I refer to the<br />
difficulty for people dependent on welfare payments to<br />
earn additional after-tax income, and the associated<br />
disincentive to work, resulting from the interaction of<br />
substantial marginal tax rates at low levels of income<br />
with the social security system.<br />
The review must address the unfairness and the<br />
associated effects on work effort of workers on average<br />
incomes paying the current 46 per cent marginal tax rate<br />
on incomes above $ 19,500.<br />
And while the evidence is more ambiguous on<br />
disincentives to incremental work effort high in the<br />
income scale, the review must address the powerful<br />
distortions to resource allocation inherent in a 60 per<br />
cent marginal tax rate cutting in at less than twice<br />
average weekly earnings, within a system that provides<br />
ways for turning taxable income into untaxed benefits. </p>
<p>10<br />
It has been clear from the first discussion of tax<br />
reform in EPAC nearly two years ago, that reform would<br />
have to focus on integrated packages to be considered as<br />
a whole, which are likely to commend themselves to broad<br />
sections of the community. No doubt every interest<br />
group would prefer to exclude or vary some elements of<br />
any such package. But there is no way that we will<br />
achieve community understanding and agreement if debate<br />
focuses on single components and does not address<br />
overall packages, and their total effects.<br />
Over the next couple of months, the Government will be<br />
considering the components of possible packages of<br />
reform measures consistent with the Nine Principles. In<br />
deciding among these the Government will be concerned to<br />
promote economic efficiency, fairness and simplicity.<br />
We are not engaged in a search for some simple technical<br />
solution to the tax problem. We know that no single,<br />
unambiguously best answer to the great taxation<br />
questions is waiting to be grasped. It is our intention<br />
to move us as far as possible towards efficiency,<br />
fairness and simplicity according to the perceptions of<br />
a large proportion of Australians. And the perceptions<br />
of Australians will develop through the process of<br />
discussion which will occur through this year.<br />
In our efforts to reform the tax system, we are aware<br />
that it is dangerous to allow the best to become the<br />
enemy of the good. It would be a tragedy for Australia<br />
if there were no tax reform at all because every<br />
political group and every interest group, each from its<br />
own entrenched position, was insisting on its version of<br />
the best package, even when this package was unable to<br />
win widespread community support during the period<br />
within which the taxation issue must be debated and<br />
settled.<br />
We do not underestimate the magnitude of the task.<br />
W6 are fully aware that the main reason why tax refczm<br />
has so long been ignored, is that it is hard. We know<br />
that even this time, with the Government committed to<br />
reforms that make Australia a fairer society better able<br />
to realise its potential for strong economic growth,<br />
reform might not be possible.<br />
We are very much aware of the constraints on policy<br />
imposed by established perceptions and the political and<br />
vested interests to which I referred in the opening<br />
paragraphs of this speech.<br />
We cannot hold out for the nirvana of unanimous </p>
<p>11<br />
agreement in this difficult area, but, unless we can win<br />
broad-based community support, the package will be<br />
denied the foundation it needs for effective<br />
implementation.<br />
As we see it, the challenge presented by the need for<br />
tax reform is not just for the Government.<br />
It is a challenge for the whole Australian community.<br />
The debate surrounding tax reform as we approach the<br />
Summit in early July will be a test of the maturity of<br />
the Australian political process, and of our ability to<br />
approach complex issues calmly and analytically.<br />
The community debate is a serious and major part of the<br />
decision-making process on tax reform.<br />
Through this meeting, I would like to affirm with the<br />
Australian people, the undertaking that I gave during<br />
the election campaign and which is embodied in the Nine<br />
Principles : the Government will not proceed with the<br />
legislation of a taxation reform package which does not<br />
have broad community support.<br />
In return for this commitment I seek from Australians a<br />
climate of rational, calm discussion and genuine<br />
examination of proposals. I ask that any components of<br />
alternative packages be examined as part of the whole<br />
and not in isolation and, above all, that people avoid<br />
pre-judging either the process or the issues until the<br />
facts have been presented comprehensively.<br />
Certainly the degree of consensus within the Australian<br />
community on tax reform will be greater the more tax<br />
reform represents some reduction in total taxation<br />
levels. We have made a firm commitment to the<br />
Australian people that we will not increase the overall<br />
tax burden. We will be working to ensure that there is<br />
some reduction in the overall tax burden for most<br />
Australians. This can most readily be achieved if we<br />
make a comprehensive assault on tax avoidance and<br />
evasion as part of a reform package. But whatever<br />
approach is taken it seems likely that ordinary<br />
Australians will win on some components of a reform<br />
package, lose on others, and overall come out on top.<br />
The debate about the overall tax burden also has to be<br />
put in perspective. In the end it can only be<br />
effectively contained through expenditure restraint. it<br />
will be a major test of how serious the Opposition is<br />
about reducing taxes while reducing the deficit, to see<br />
whether they support the hard measures on expenditure<br />
that we will be implementing in the coming Budget and if </p>
<p>12<br />
4 they oppose these, to see whether they suggest<br />
substantial alternatives.<br />
Successful tax reform, with broad community support, is<br />
important to economic efficiency, to equity, and to<br />
restoring a sense of common purpose to the Australian<br />
community. It stands beside, and in some ways above,<br />
the other structural reforms that we are undertaking to<br />
lift Australia's performance as a dynamic economy and<br />
society offering full opportunities for participation to<br />
all its citizens the efforts to increase the<br />
availability, quality and relevance of education; the<br />
review of labour market, training and related youth<br />
programs; the industry policies directed at building on<br />
our competitive strengths and reducing reliance on<br />
barriers to imports; the active trade policy, directed<br />
particularly at making the most of opportunities in the<br />
dynamic Western Pacific region; the financial sector<br />
reforms; and the redirection of social security<br />
expenditure towards Australians in genuine need.<br />
Successful tax reform will require broad community<br />
support. In particular, if it is to avoid igniting an<br />
inflationary spiral of huge and unsustainable<br />
proportions, it will require the active cooperation of<br />
the trade union movement.<br />
I will be looking for the same sort of cooperation from<br />
the Australian community that has been given so readily<br />
over the past two years, to the great task of economic<br />
recovery. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
