<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4467</transcript-id>
    <title>DEATH OF PRESIDENT MAKARIOS, 16 AUGUST 1977</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/08/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004467.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
F77/ 176<br />
PRIME MIISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 16 AUGUST 1977<br />
DEATH OF PRESIDENT MAKARIOS<br />
It is with deep regret that I inform the House of the death<br />
on 3 August 1977 of His Beatitude Archbishop Makarios III,<br />
President of the Republic of Cy-prus.<br />
I move: that the House records its sincere regret at the<br />
death of His Beatitude Archbishop Makarios III, President<br />
of the Republic of Cyprus and expresses its profound sympathy<br />
to the people of Cyprus.<br />
Following the news of his death, the Governor General and I<br />
sent messages of condolence to the Acting President of<br />
the Republic of Cyprus, Mr Spyros Kyprianou, and the<br />
Minister of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Cyprus,<br />
Mr John Christophides.<br />
The Australian Government was represented-at the President's<br />
funeral by the Minister for Immigration and Ehtnic Affairs.<br />
The Leader of the Opposition and our High Commissioner to the<br />
Republic of Cyprus were also present.<br />
The late President was the inspiration of the modern state of<br />
Cyprus and represented it in the world community with wisdom<br />
and distinction. He was ordained deacon and priest in 1938.<br />
On his return to Cyprus in 1948, he was consecrated bishop<br />
and began intensive religious social and national work11 in his<br />
See. At this time he began his vigorous campaign for<br />
nationhood for Cyprus. In 1950, he was elected both as<br />
Archbishop and Ethnarch national leader of the Greek people<br />
of Cyprus.<br />
It is a tribute to his qualities that he was elected as both the<br />
spiritual and political leader of his country.<br />
In 1952 he began his campaign at the United Nations General<br />
Assembly,, for international -recognition of Cyprus.<br />
During the following years of the decade he fought courageously<br />
to achieve his goal, enduring even exile from his country.<br />
Following the London Agreement in 1959 that Cyprus would<br />
become an independent Republic, he returned to Cyprus and<br />
was elected its first President. / 2 </p>
<p>2.<br />
President Makarios played a unique and distinguished<br />
role in his country's national and international affairs.<br />
He visited many countries in his quest for a solution to<br />
the problems of Cyprus. He tirelessly represented his country<br />
at many international conferences as well as at the U. N.<br />
and at meetings of Commonwealth Heads of Government.<br />
His remarkable personal qualities earned him an eminent place<br />
amongst world statesmen. His counsels will be particularly<br />
missed at Commonwealth Heads of Government Meetings in which<br />
he had actively participated for many years.<br />
I had the honour of meeting with him privately during the recent<br />
Commonwealth Heads of Government Meeting in London.<br />
At that time we discussed his forthcoming state visit to<br />
Australia in November this year. This visit would have been<br />
a fitting symbol of the development of longstanding and<br />
excellent relations between our two countries.<br />
The Australian Government greatly looked forward to it.<br />
I am sure that not only those Australians whose country of<br />
origin is Cyprus but all Australians will share my regret that<br />
it cannot take place.<br />
We therefore wish to record our deep sympathy in the Parliament<br />
to the people of Cyprus. They have lost a statesman of great<br />
eminence who had long personified his people's quest for<br />
identity and independence.<br />
We also hope that the search for a peaceful and lasting<br />
solution to problems in Cyprus, to which the late President<br />
had devoted so much of his life, will be pursued with determination<br />
despite his untimely death. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
