<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10843</transcript-id>
    <title>TASK FORCE ON INTERNATIONAL FINANCIAL ISSUES</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/10/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p> The first meeting of the Prime Minister's</p>
<p> task force on international financial issues will take place tomorrow</p>
<p> in Sydney.</p>
<p>I will attend the first meeting. I have asked the Treasurer to chair</p>
<p> the ongoing work of the task force.</p>
<p>I am pleased that some of the most senior banking and financial services</p>
<p> figures in our country have agreed to be members.</p>
<p>They will make up half the task force alongside the heads of several</p>
<p> senior government departments and the Governor of the Reserve Bank.</p>
<p>I announced the task force during the election campaign and it is</p>
<p> a key part of my government's efforts to address the international</p>
<p> financial crisis.</p>
<p>The international debate about the ways to return to higher growth,</p>
<p> improve standards of living, create jobs and prevent future crises</p>
<p> must be brought to practical conclusions as soon as possible.</p>
<p>I will ask my task force for substantive and imaginative suggestions</p>
<p> for Australia to pursue in appropriate international forums. The expertise</p>
<p> of the private sector members will be useful given the significance</p>
<p> of private capital flows in the world's economy.</p>
<p>The task force will consider issues such as transparency and accountability</p>
<p> in the private sector, improved financial sector monitoring and supervision,</p>
<p> and measures to strengthen international financial institutions.</p>
<p>I have asked the task force to report by the end of the year.</p>
<p>A list of task force members is attached.</p>
<p>   MEMBERS OF THE PRIME MINISTER'S TASK FORCE ON INTERNATIONAL FINANCIAL</p>
<p> ISSUES</p>
<p>Mr David Murray</p>
<p> Managing Director</p>
<p>Commonwealth Bank of Australia</p>
<p>Mr George Trumbull</p>
<p>Chief Executive Officer</p>
<p>AMP Ltd</p>
<p>Mr Bill Shields</p>
<p>Executive Director</p>
<p>Macquarie Bank Ltd</p>
<p>Mr Malcolm Irving</p>
<p>Director</p>
<p> Telstra Corporation Ltd</p>
<p>Mr M John Phillips</p>
<p>Chairman</p>
<p>IBJ Australia Bank Ltd</p>
<p>Mr Max Moore Wilton</p>
<p>Secretary</p>
<p>Department of the Prime Minister and Cabinet</p>
<p>Mr Ted Evans</p>
<p>Secretary</p>
<p>Department of the Treasury</p>
<p>Dr Peter Boxall</p>
<p>Secretary</p>
<p>Department of Finance</p>
<p>Dr Ashton Calvert</p>
<p>Secretary</p>
<p>Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade</p>
<p>Mr Ian Macfarlane</p>
<p>Governor</p>
<p>Reserve Bank of Australia</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
