<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10746</transcript-id>
    <title>26 June 1998                                                 TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                ADDRESS TO PUBLIC MEETING                HERVEY BAY - QUEENSLAND</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/06/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE....................................................</p>
<p>Thank you very much, Mr Chairman. To the Mayor of Hervey Bay, to the</p>
<p> Federal Member for Wide Bay and Minister for Customs, Warren Truss,</p>
<p> to Mrs Lyn Truss, ladies and gentlemen.</p>
<p>I only intend to make a very short speech, because I've really</p>
<p> come to talk to you rather than talk at you. I'll say a few words</p>
<p> and then I'd be very interested in answering your questions,</p>
<p> because in the nature of a short visit to the area, there's only</p>
<p> a limited amount of time in each town, and I don't want to occupy</p>
<p> all of that limited time with a speech.</p>
<p>Last night I addressed a gathering in Wondai, and then I'll be</p>
<p> going on to Maryborough after this gathering. And the purpose of my</p>
<p> being here is to hear what you've got to say, to acknowledge</p>
<p> the need for an even greater level of communication and accountability</p>
<p> between the Government and the people of Australia, and also to acknowledge</p>
<p> the fact and to express my understanding and concern for a number</p>
<p> of the economic and social problems that rural and regional communities</p>
<p> around Australia is suffering. Also to be honest with you in saying</p>
<p> that there are some things that this Government can do and there are</p>
<p> some things that this government, indeed no government, no matter</p>
<p> what political persuasion it might be, can do. It's very important</p>
<p> at this time for people to be direct and candid. You be direct and</p>
<p> candid to me, and I'll be direct and candid in response.</p>
<p>I believe that the process of public meetings such as this is still</p>
<p> the best method of political communication there is. It is less isolated,</p>
<p> it is less antiseptic, it is less unreal than interviews in television</p>
<p> studios. And that is one of the reasons why in all my political career</p>
<p> I've done a great deal of those such meetings. I know that in</p>
<p> communities like Hervey Bay, unemployment is high. I know that some</p>
<p> of your industries that have relied on commodity sales, are suffering</p>
<p> import penetration such as the pork industry. I also know that rural</p>
<p> Australia, and of course rural Queensland depends very heavily on</p>
<p> the jobs generated and the income earned from the exports that we</p>
<p> send to other nations and that in our policies we have to be sensible</p>
<p> to ensure that we don't jeopardise those exports because if we</p>
<p> do that, we jeopardise the jobs the tens of thousands of more Australians.</p>
<p>I also know that sound economic conditions are the important foundation</p>
<p> of a good business climate. That if you don't have low interest</p>
<p> rates and low inflation and that if you don't reduce your spending</p>
<p> as a government, that undermines the strength of the economy. And</p>
<p> I make no apology for the fact that we have put a huge priority on</p>
<p> reducing the budget deficit that we inherited. If we hadn't have</p>
<p> done that, interest rates now would be much higher than what they</p>
<p> are and the economic conditions, which many of you find very unsatisfactory,</p>
<p> would be even worse than what they are now. And I think it is very</p>
<p> important that we do preserve that sense of perspective. I think it</p>
<p> is also important as we acknowledge within our community that there</p>
<p> is economic and social change, that we achieve the right balance between</p>
<p> hanging onto those things from our past that are important and but</p>
<p> also embracing those areas where change is needed.</p>
<p>And there is much about Australia's past that is valuable and</p>
<p> precious and worth preserving. The flag behind me, for example, is</p>
<p> a symbol of the past and the present, and as far as I am concerned</p>
<p> should also symbolise our future because it is an emblem in which</p>
<p> I've always believed. And there are other great Australian values</p>
<p> that we've inherited and that we should hang on to, but like</p>
<p> any society there are areas of our community that need change. I,</p>
<p> for example, have championed the cause of industrial relations reform</p>
<p> and change. I also believe that it would be good for Australia if</p>
<p> we had a fairer taxation system and we'll have a debate about</p>
<p> that in the weeks and months ahead, and the rural community of Australia</p>
<p> will be a beneficiary of a fair and better taxation system, because</p>
<p> apart from anything else, a new taxation system would take the burden</p>
<p> off our exporters that disadvantages them in relation to their competitors</p>
<p> from other countries. These are but some of the issues that I want</p>
<p> to talk not only to this gathering of my fellow Australians but also</p>
<p> to other gatherings of my fellow Australians around our country. But</p>
<p> it is now twelve minutes past nine, and therefore in the interests</p>
<p> of giving you as much opportunity of having your say and asking your</p>
<p> questions, I'll conclude my introductory remarks and I'll</p>
<p> be very very happy to answer your questions, to hear your comments,</p>
<p> your observations, your criticisms, any thing you like. Thank you.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>This is about taxation. There's a lot of people in Australia</p>
<p> who earn 20, 000 a year. This is about $400 a week. I believe that</p>
<p> those people should never fill in a tax return. For example, if they've</p>
<p> got that sort of money, they spend it all locally. When you get over</p>
<p> $20,000, say $25,000 fives, from about two-and-a-half, till you get</p>
<p> to the top figure, the tax department could work out how many in those</p>
<p> categories...(inaudible)... there should be more money in people's</p>
<p> hands instead of being down to Canberra where it goes...(inaudible)..to</p>
<p> help people like us and all the other communities.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I won't give a long answer to that. I simply say that we will</p>
<p> take all of those issues into account in the reform process.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>...(inaudible)...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes, I understand the point of view. Can I give you my very quick</p>
<p> response. My very quick response is that we believe in as open a trading</p>
<p> system as possible, not because of regional security, because it is</p>
<p> in our own national self-interest.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>That's rubbish.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, you may say it's rubbish, but can I say... look this is,</p>
<p> no, I'm sorry, there is absolutely nothing achieved if you imagine</p>
<p> that I am going to sort of stop giving an answer because of an interjection,</p>
<p> then please hear me out, and then you can have your say. That is the</p>
<p> civilised Australian manner. (Applause)</p>
<p>Now I was asked a question, and my answer is that it is in Australia's</p>
<p> interests to have an open trading system because we are a great primary</p>
<p> production nation and if we adopt a more restrictive trading system,</p>
<p> there will be retaliation against our rural exports and I swear to</p>
<p> you, tens of thousands of more Australians in the regional centres</p>
<p> of our nation will lose their jobs, lose their wealth, lose their</p>
<p> livelihood and lose their family security. I mean, if you lose the</p>
<p> beef exports, the sugar exports, if you lose the rice exports, and</p>
<p> all the other exports that go, not only to Asia, but go not only to</p>
<p> Asia but go to other parts of the world, if you lose the wine exports</p>
<p> from South Australia, and lose all of those great primary production</p>
<p> exports, then our rural communities and our regional communities will</p>
<p> be even more impoverished than what they are now. Now, that's</p>
<p> my response Sir.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>I have an 18 year old pre-lingual deaf boy here. I'd like to</p>
<p> know why your Government policy will pay my 18 year old son an amount</p>
<p> if he gets a girl pregnant and lives with her, to play mummies and</p>
<p> daddies, but your Government will not pay him a disability pension</p>
<p> when he is more than 20% disabled. He doesn't speak, doesn't</p>
<p> hear, and he signs. And I'd like to know why.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I would be very happy if we can get the details of your case.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>I did send you a letter, and yesterday Paul Neville got me to fax</p>
<p> it to Canberra so that you would read it...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I'm sorry, but I would be very very happy, and I'll</p>
<p> get a member of my staff to speak to you after the meeting. I don't</p>
<p> know of course all of the details of your particular case. Could I</p>
<p> just say...</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>I've been sending you information for two years.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Can I just say two things. That we did make a number of changes in</p>
<p> the disability allowance. We did make them a lot more generous in</p>
<p> the last budget. You make the observation about paying somebody a</p>
<p> pension, or paying them support if they get a girl pregnant and play,</p>
<p> as you put it, mummies and daddies'. It is true that there</p>
<p> are benefits for single parents. One of the reasons that those benefits</p>
<p> exist is that no matter what judgement people may make about the sense</p>
<p> of responsibility or irresponsibility of the parents who bring children</p>
<p> into the world, the community does have an obligation to the innocent</p>
<p> children, and the idea that you don't disadvantage babies and</p>
<p> disadvantage young children by cutting off pensions is I think something</p>
<p> that can be challenged. The other thing I would say is that, contrary</p>
<p> to popular belief, more than 80% of people who receive the sole parents</p>
<p> benefit in Australia are deserted mothers.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>It is very hard when that....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Ma'am, I do understand....</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>.. if this is the way to get a benefit...It's not very moralistic...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I'm not making a... I don't encourage it. I have a very</p>
<p> sort of traditional view about family life and about marriage. I think</p>
<p> marriage is one of the great social bulwarks of our society and I</p>
<p> believe in policies that always give what I call a margin ...(Applause)...</p>
<p> I believe in giving a margin to marriage. I think it is a great show,</p>
<p> and I would like to investigate your particular circumstances and</p>
<p> obviously I think everybody in the room would identify very strongly</p>
<p> with your particular situation and I'm very glad that you've</p>
<p> raised it.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>...(inaudible)....a man and a woman, nearly always they are classed</p>
<p> as a de facto relationship. In a defacto relationship then they get</p>
<p> less social security than two other people such as two women, two</p>
<p> men, or two any other class, or as a matter of fact, six people living</p>
<p> in a house. The two people who are married are being victimised with</p>
<p> less social security payments. Why, and you say believe in the family</p>
<p> and marriage. You are only encouraging people to break the families</p>
<p> up, for monetary gain and okay...I'll continue.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>That's up to the Chairman but I think there's a few people.</p>
<p> Two's enough.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>This is just a suggestion.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>All right, two questions and a suggestion.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Okay. Small business needs help. There's no doubt about that.</p>
<p> Lower interest rates would be a great help, particularly from banks</p>
<p> etc... which lead to... take a lot of their profits out. However,</p>
<p> your work-for-the-dole scheme. Now, this strikes me funny that you</p>
<p> will... there seems to be work out there for people that are prepared</p>
<p> to work for the dole, and I don't say this is wrong or right.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Are you in favour of work-for-the-dole?</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Yes. Yes.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Good. Well, we brought it in. The Labor Party would throw it out.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Fair enough. But the way it is implemented. If there is enough work</p>
<p> out there for them people to do two days work for a week, at the rate</p>
<p> that they are paid, why not pay four people the full wage to do this</p>
<p> work, which then, they would be fully employed, gainfully employed.</p>
<p> They would get a full wage, which at the end of the week, they might</p>
<p> have a little bit of money left to go and support a small business</p>
<p> who in that turn they may be able to employ another person. As it</p>
<p> is, the people who are getting their $170 a week on the dole, don't</p>
<p> have enough to put anything into small business and so it stops, the</p>
<p> money going around stops when they get their $170 a week because there's</p>
<p> nothing left after that to spend anywhere else.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, sir, I'll try and deal with those briefly. Why haven't</p>
<p> we brought in tax reform yet? Well, we'll be unveiling the plan</p>
<p> very soon. You can't bring about a fundamental change to a taxation</p>
<p> system overnight. We have a number of other priorities that we said</p>
<p> we'd attend to when we got into office and I reckon if at the</p>
<p> end of our first term in office we can look back and say we've</p>
<p> got the Budget back into balance after it's been in the black</p>
<p> $10.5 billion. We've had a real go at reforming the industrial</p>
<p> relations system. We've reduced massively that almost $100 billion</p>
<p> Federal Government debt that we inherited and we' ve also presented</p>
<p> a comprehensive plan for taxation reform. Well in the short space</p>
<p> of two-and-a-half or three years that's not a bad record. (Applause)</p>
<p>You asked me about people living together and marriage and so forth.</p>
<p> I've stated my views on that. I'm the Prime Minister. I</p>
<p> don't run around making snap moral judgments on the behaviour</p>
<p> of individuals in Australia but I do express my very strong preference</p>
<p> for the stability that marriage brings to family life and the stability</p>
<p> that marriage brings to the raising of children. Successful united</p>
<p> families in marriage is still the greatest personal security that</p>
<p> any young person can have and those that have had it are greatly advantaged</p>
<p> as compared with those who haven't. But we do have obligations</p>
<p> to those in our community who have not been as fortunate to grow up</p>
<p> with, in a situation where they've had a very loving and supportive</p>
<p> environment. For time immemorial we've sort of recognised that</p>
<p> if people are living together, historically almost always in marriage,</p>
<p> these days not as often as in the past, that it is obviously less</p>
<p> expensive for two people to live together than for two to live separately</p>
<p> and of course that is the reason why historically you've had</p>
<p> a marriage rate which has not been exactly double the single rate</p>
<p> of a person. Now over the years of course, I think the point you're</p>
<p> making is that more and more people are living together who aren't</p>
<p> married and that that is representing a discrimination against the</p>
<p> married people. I understand the point you make and it does raise</p>
<p> a significant number of difficult social judgments that a Government</p>
<p> has got to make and I don't have an easy answer to that. I understand</p>
<p> why a lot of married people feel that they may be discriminated against,</p>
<p> but of course people get married for a combination of reasons and</p>
<p> most people I know don't get married primarily for economic reasons</p>
<p> although perhaps there are some in the audience who might be cynical</p>
<p> enough to imagine that that does occur on occasions. I'm still</p>
<p> old-fashioned enough to believe that people get married for other</p>
<p> reasons and they get married because they want to spend the rest of</p>
<p> their life with somebody and that remains the principal reason why</p>
<p> people do it. I don't think you can put an economic value judgement</p>
<p> on that but I've been accused of a lot of things in my political</p>
<p> career. I'm not often accused of somebody who's trying to</p>
<p> break up marriages.</p>
<p>MC:</p>
<p>Could I just make a comment please. We will have to shorten the time</p>
<p> that people are spending on asking questions. If you've got a</p>
<p> list of questions, I suggest you look at the most important one on</p>
<p> your list and ask that one. We will limit it to one question per person</p>
<p> and make it very brief otherwise we'll never get through.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>I welcome you here today, Mr Prime Minister. Thank you for giving</p>
<p> me the chance to speak to you. I've come here to make a request</p>
<p> of you to match the grant that our State government gave the City</p>
<p> Council here to refurbish or rebuild our historic pier we have here</p>
<p> as most people know. We want you to match Rob Borbidge's $500</p>
<p> 000 grant. Thank you very much. Tell you what, make your way up here</p>
<p> some time, and I'll supply you a rod, and I take you out on the</p>
<p> jetty and I'll guarantee you'll catch a fish. Thank you.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I'll add that to the list and consider what you've said.</p>
<p> All right, I'll think about it.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>What I'd like to draw to your attention is the matter of apprenticeships.</p>
<p> I don't think we have enough apprenticeships in this country.</p>
<p> I read a letterbox drop the other day where you didn't dictate</p>
<p> having more apprenticeships.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, we've created 200,000 since we've been in office.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>200, 000.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I mean, yes, I noticed that somebody was running around in the Queensland</p>
<p> election campaign talking about creating 1000 apprenticeships. Under</p>
<p> our Government we have created 200,000 traineeships and apprenticeships</p>
<p> since we came to power. That is a fact and I mean I'm sorry that</p>
<p> that is not as widely known as it should be.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Well, you have now made it know and that's very highly commended.</p>
<p> However, how much longer do we have to wait to get these young people</p>
<p> who are forced to stay at school for an extra two years, then may</p>
<p> not have any academic inclinations. It's a concern to the parents,</p>
<p> it's a cost to the parents. When are you going to, or any Government</p>
<p> that we have in power, when are they going to give small business</p>
<p> and industry the money to create these apprenticeships so we have</p>
<p> future employment and, therefore, at the end of the day, bigger exports?</p>
<p> Thank you.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, we have, as I say, in the two-and-a-quarter years, under our</p>
<p> new training and apprenticeship system, created 200,000 in that period.</p>
<p> Now, of course, we can always create more. Under our youth allowance</p>
<p> system, which comes into operation on the 1st of July, we are going</p>
<p> to alter the incentives for people, for young people. We're going</p>
<p> to, instead of encouraging people as the present system does, to leave</p>
<p> school without a job, we're going to encourage people, because</p>
<p> of the way the allowance will operate, to choose a traineeship or</p>
<p> staying at school in preference to going on the dole. And one of the</p>
<p> other advantages of the new system....</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, may I interject there?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Sure.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Are you saying that these children you are going to leave at school</p>
<p> rather than put them in an apprenticeship?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, I'm not saying that, no, no. If they've got an apprenticeship</p>
<p> to go to that's fine. But what I do want to stop is this situation</p>
<p> where people leave school with no prospect of a job and go straight</p>
<p> on to the dole. I think that is the worst, most soul-destroying, most</p>
<p> socially...</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>How are you going stop that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, one of the ways to stop it is to take the incentive out the</p>
<p> present system which encourages young people to choose the dole over</p>
<p> staying at school, doing a traineeship, or some other apprenticeship</p>
<p> or some other kind of training or study. At the moment there is an</p>
<p> incentive in the system because of the levels of payment for many</p>
<p> people to leave school without the prospect of a job. And I want to</p>
<p> change that. That's the first step.</p>
<p> QUESTION:</p>
<p> That's true. But this is what we need to get rid of, that</p>
<p> incentive for children to leave school ...[inaudible] ...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Without a job.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>We need those apprenticeships. We need children to be assured that</p>
<p> when they leave school they are going to in to...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look, I agree with that and that is what our policy is designed to</p>
<p> do. And the new youth allowance [applause]...</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, Mr Prime Minister, the question I want to ask you is how</p>
<p> are you going to cope with the pensioners when you bring in GST?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>They will be fully compensated, you watch. They will, they will. And</p>
<p> I tell you what, the other thing... I'm, sorry. You've pushed</p>
<p> a button. I sort of...</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>On your show the other day you said that New Zealand, take New Zealand.</p>
<p> They give them $50 and the $50 was put away and put away until they</p>
<p> start to drag into the pensioners. Is the Australian Government going</p>
<p> to do that to us too?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I didn't mention anything about $50 in New Zealand. I may</p>
<p> have mentioned New Zealand in the general sense of the system that</p>
<p> was introduced. But sir, can I say to you very directly that when</p>
<p> we bring down the new taxation policy, one of the things that we will</p>
<p> do comprehensively is to fully c</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
