<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7818</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, PUBLIC BUILDINGS, HOBART,18 NOVEMBER 19898</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/11/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007818.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFRENCE, PUBLIC BUILDiNGS, HOBART,<br />
18 NOVEMBER 1989<br />
H OE PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: What have yol dIACided regarding the<br />
international Antarctic Centre. Is the Commonwealth going<br />
to re-look at the Centre?<br />
PM: What we agree our priority should be is concentrating<br />
on trying to ensure that Tasmania, Hobart in particular, is<br />
given as much work as it can be given in terms of this being<br />
a base for vess oing to the Antarctic. That has a<br />
number of ramifications, including a consideration of the<br />
r~ zsr, that govern the anr~ nA to Australian ports of foreign<br />
research vessels and 1 have instructed my Foreign Minisfter<br />
to review those guidelines in a way which will try and<br />
ensure that as much opportunity be given for access to<br />
Hobart. That's the emphasis that we want to give at this<br />
taLge and if we van build up HuiJLt as a centre, as a port<br />
for the servicing of activity in the Antarctic, then down<br />
the line following that it may be appropriate to look at the<br />
question of a Centre.<br />
JOURNALIST: So you still leave the question open of whether<br />
or not the Centre will be built?<br />
PM: Yes, but it's, to be honest, I don't in other words<br />
want to have five buob eull way &amp; ad say yes its there just<br />
around the corner, but saying its not the thing on which we<br />
concentrate now, it makes more sense to give the priority<br />
that I. have suggested. But then 1iti y well be that if<br />
we're successful, as I trust and hope we will be, in<br />
building Hobart up in this other way, then in that context<br />
we could perhaps more realistically look at the sort of<br />
centre that's been talked about.<br />
JOURNALIST: Will the Federal Government support Hobart's<br />
hid for thin Ruminin fishing fleet?<br />
PM: I've made it quite clear that Hobart is to be a port<br />
for availability of the fleet. </p>
<p>JOURNHALIST: Will that worry the other States?<br />
PX: Well, as to where the vessels would go in the end that<br />
would be a matter for the Soviets to decide what's most<br />
Appropriate in terms of their activities but from what I<br />
understand it would be regarded as a priority port. But let<br />
me say where we are on it. We have really, as far as the<br />
fisheries part of the negotiations, got a draft agreement<br />
there but you will understand that in terms of Australia's<br />
interests we identified the negotiations in regard to<br />
fisheries with negotiations in regard to a commodity<br />
agreement and we've got to finalise that part of the total<br />
agreement. I understand from my officials that that's going<br />
to be done in the very near future. so we're approaching<br />
the point where the actual agreements with the Soviets<br />
should be finalised before very long. Then once that's<br />
done, I'm quite confident that Hobart will before long be a<br />
significant beneficiary.<br />
JOURNALIST: What was the outcome of your meeting on the<br />
tourism reconstruction funding?<br />
PM: It was a very very useful meei-ing, i found it any rate,<br />
and I want to ay at the u~ t: L LhaL r u'cnmgratulate the<br />
Premier and the Government of ' rAsrania in the way in which<br />
they have co-ordinated with the people in thA industry<br />
across a broad spectrum. It was a very constructive<br />
Meting. There was understanding of the reasons for the<br />
problems. In other words, we as the Federal Government, at<br />
all points, have eought to have the pilots operating within<br />
the system so that they would have negotiated their claims<br />
within the system. They wouldn't do that and therefore we<br />
couldn't have allowed them to have their 30% because<br />
that would have created an enduring and disastrous problem<br />
for the Australian economy as a whole and for Tasmania in<br />
jpArticular. On that bacsic I have indicated that Tabwuaaila<br />
will be a significant beneficiary of the substantial package<br />
of assistance to the tourism industry. Let me make it clear<br />
what the elements of it are. It's a $ 30 million package<br />
made up in this way. There will be $ 18.5 million for an<br />
intensive international advertising campaign which will be<br />
for the whole of Australia and advising potential tourists<br />
around the world of the attractions of Australia in general<br />
and of course, Tasmania will be very much included in that<br />
very, very substantial international advertising. Secondly,<br />
of the $ 11.5 million remainder of the package, $ 5 million of<br />
that will be for an Australia-wide sort of generic<br />
advertising campaign urging Australians to take their<br />
holidays in Australia, to tour Australia and Tasmania will<br />
obviously be in part a benificiary of that. Of the<br />
million of the rest of the package, there were arguments put<br />
to me that it was really the north of Australia that needed<br />
to be dealt with because their high point of the tourist </p>
<p>( PM cont) season had coincided with the worst part of the<br />
problems in the airline industry and that that wasn't true<br />
of Tasmania. I said well I don't accept that and I insisted<br />
and so that's what's happening. That $ 6.5 million will be<br />
divided equally between the Northern Territory, North<br />
Queensland and Tasmania. So Tasmania will get $ 2.2 million<br />
for its specific advertising. So Tasmania is going to<br />
benefit in those three ways, international advertising, the<br />
general Australian advertising, but $ 2.2 million for itself.<br />
I also pointed out to the meeting that I had raised the<br />
issue of tax payments with the Taxation Commissioner and<br />
I've informed the meeting that any operators or people who<br />
can show that they have been directly and adversely affected<br />
by the problems in the airline industry in a way which have<br />
created difficulties for them in meeting their tax payments,<br />
that those considerations will be taken into account<br />
sympathetically by the Tax commissioner?<br />
JOURNALIST: Ian Macphee said today that he intended to ask<br />
the National Crime Authority to re-open inquiries into<br />
currency dealings by Sir Peter Abeles. Would you have any<br />
comment on that?<br />
PH: I think in these areas that Mr Macphee sort of gave<br />
some indication of what he's worth by his performance in the<br />
Lakeside Hotel the other night. That's about how much<br />
importance you can attach to him. These issues are old hat<br />
and have been looked at by the last Head of the National<br />
Crime Authority, Mr Justice Stewart, and been found to be<br />
totally lacking in substance.<br />
ends<br />
0 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
