<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6417</transcript-id>
    <title>JOINT COMMUNIQUE, ISSUED HOBART, 26 JUNE 1984</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/06/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006417.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
JOINT COMMUNIQUE -ISSUED HOBART -26 JUNE 1984<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr Hawke, and the Premier of Tasmania,<br />
Mr Gray, signed a Memorandum of -Understanding in Hobart<br />
today which covers the arrangements for Commonwealth assistance<br />
to Tasmania consequent on cessation of the Gordon-below-<br />
Franklin scheme.<br />
The signing of the Memorandum of Understanding represents the<br />
culmination of 12 months of negotiations. The key elements<br />
of the settlement have been agreed following a number of<br />
discussions over recent months between Mr Hawke and Mr Gray.<br />
The agreed arrangements are set out below:<br />
Creation of Alternative Employment Opportunities<br />
The Commonwealth will make available a further and final amount<br />
of $ 15 million for employment-generating purposes. $ 3 million<br />
of this will be used for the upgrading of Hobart Airport<br />
to limited international operation standard, with the balance<br />
to be allocated to projects to be agreed between the two<br />
Governments. Under the Interim Financial Agreement previously concluded<br />
between the two Governments, a total of $ 34 million has<br />
been spent or committed for employment creation purposes.<br />
In addition, another amount of $ 3 million has already been<br />
spent by the Commonwealth in upgrading Hobart Airport in a<br />
project brought ahead of schedule specifically to help create<br />
employment after work ceased on the Gordon-below-Franklin scheme.<br />
In total, therefore, $ 52 million has been allocated by the<br />
Commonwealth directly for the creation of alternative<br />
employment opportunities.<br />
7 r1 </p>
<p>Electricity Subsidy<br />
The Governments have accepted that the King and Anthony power<br />
development schemes represent at this stage replacement of<br />
112 MW of electricity that would have been produced by the<br />
Gordon-below-Franklin scheme. The Commonwealth has agreed<br />
to pay an amount of $ 200 million ( valued in January 1984 prices)<br />
as a subsidy to be used by the Hydro-Electric Commission to<br />
reduce the cost of producing 112 MW of electricity to the<br />
cost of electricity that would have been produced by the<br />
Gordon-below-Franklin scheme.<br />
This financial assistance will be paid in 10 annual instalments<br />
with each instalment being adjusted to take account of changes<br />
from 1 January 1984 in the implicit price deflator for<br />
non-dwelling construction.<br />
The Commonwealth has also undertaken to provide a subsidy to<br />
reduce the cost of a further 68 MW of electricity to the cost<br />
of electricity that would have been produced by the Gordonbelow-<br />
Franklin scheme, if and when the need for that electricity<br />
has been demonstrated, provided that the 68 MW of electricity<br />
is not incorporated in a hydro-electric scheme on the<br />
Gordon or Franklin rivers.<br />
Expenses incurred on the Gordon-below-Franklin Scheme<br />
The Commonwealth is providing an ex gratia payment of<br />
million to the State for payment to the Hydro-Electric<br />
Commission for expenses incurred on the Gordon-below-<br />
Franklin scheme. This will avoid the need for any increase<br />
in electricity prices as a consequence of the bringing to<br />
account of past expenditures by the Commission on the Gordonbelow-<br />
Franklin scheme.<br />
Mr Hawke and Mr Gray also signed financial agreements covering<br />
the $ 200 million electricity subsidy and $ 25 million payment<br />
in respect of work done on the Gordon-below-Franklin scheme. </p>
<p>4 3.<br />
The State has acknowledged that, upon implementation of the<br />
Commonwealth's commitments set forth in the Memorandum of<br />
Understanding, the Commonwealth will have honoured completely<br />
its commitments concerning assistance to the State in<br />
relation to termination of the Gordon-below-Franklin scheme.<br />
Commonwealth and State officials will meet as soon as possible<br />
to examine and report to the two Governments on the options<br />
for the Commonwealth subsidy in respect of a further 68 MW<br />
of power. Other action to be completed includes<br />
further extensions to the Interim Financial Agreement<br />
to cover arrangements for the additional $ 15 million<br />
in employment assistance. This will represent the<br />
second extension of the Agreement, following the<br />
recent signing by Mr Hawke and Mr Gray of a Supplemental<br />
Agreement covering arrangements made since the<br />
Agreement was signed last year;<br />
long-term management arrangements for -the World Heritage<br />
Area in the South-West. Tasmania recently put forward<br />
detailed proposals for the Commonwealth's consideration.<br />
While these are under study, the Commonwealth has<br />
agreed to extend the funding of interim arrangements,<br />
under which the Commonwealth had made a grant of<br />
$ 500., 000 for the employment of additional rangers and<br />
for ancillary measures to provide added protection<br />
for the Area during 1983-84.<br />
Mr Hawke and Mr Gray said that the completion of the Memorandum<br />
of Understanding was a major achievement that symbolised the<br />
ending of a sometimes difficult period in the relationships<br />
between the two Governments. Through the arrangements that<br />
had been agreed, lasting benefits would be achieved for<br />
Tasmania. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
