<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11738</transcript-id>
    <title>Interview with Helen Dalley, A Current Affair</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/01/2001</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Subjects: The Centenary of Federation; Australian achievements; republic</p>
<p>E&amp;OE................................</p>
<p>PRESENTER:</p>
<p>Prime Minister welcome to the program. Why is celebrating Federation so important?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well because of what we have achieved as a country over 100 years. We're one of a very few countries in the world that's remained democratic through that whole period. We're very cohesive. We've taken people from all around the world, and we've developed our own distinctive identity. We have so much to celebrate and we ought to be filled with a great deal of pride and gratitude on an occasion like this. It is a very special day, the beginning of a very special year in the life of our nation.</p>
<p>PRESENTER:</p>
<p>It really was the birth of our nation wasn't it?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It was, and it happened peacefully. We didn't have to fight the British, we didn't have to go to war. It wasn't like America where there was a war of independence. It all happened quite smoothly and you ought to remember, a lot of people don't understand this, that the Australian people at the time actually voted for the constitution that we now have.</p>
<p>PRESENTER:</p>
<p>Now our founding fathers, as I read our history, were full of hope for dazzling promise for the united Australia. Do you think we've achieved that promise or are we still fulfilling it?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well no country is ever sort of completely fulfilled. The only fulfilled countries are those that are not going forward. Every country is a nation in transition, it's got a future. But I think we have met their expectations and in many areas exceeded it because this country is very cohesive, it's very united, it's changed yet it's kept things that are of continuing value. One of the clever things about Australia is that we've been able to pick the good bits from our past and hang onto them but get rid of the bad bits of our past.</p>
<p>PRESENTER:</p>
<p>What do you nominate personally as some of the great achievements of this century?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I think the maintenance of democracy and the rule of law for 100 years; the role that Australia played in defending freedom around the world in two World Wars. Our great achievements as a sporting nation; but also our achievements in the scientific and cultural area. I mean the contributions of people like McFarlane Burnet and Victor Chang to medicine. We've always punched above our weight when it comes to medical science. We've only got 20 million people, yet we contribute far more proportionally than that 20 million would suggest.</p>
<p>PRESENTER:</p>
<p>What could be, or should be the great achievements of this century?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well if we can continue our social cohesion, and if we can continue to relate to our part of the world, that's the Asia-Pacific region, and at the same time hang onto those good bits of our traditional past that are still valuable, I think if we can keep that balance. Balance is always important in a country. You never want to go too overboard, and that's another good thing about being an Australian. We're not as gullible as other people and we're a bit cynical about people who try and take us for a ride down a particular path. I mean it's a very healthy scepticism.</p>
<p>PRESENTER:</p>
<p>Now we're in this beautiful park today but this year isn't exactly going to be a walk in the park for you is it? It's an election year. Are we going to see some real policy initiatives or maybe just.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>You want a bit more? You want another bout of tax reform do you or something like that.</p>
<p>PRESENTER:</p>
<p>Well or are we going to (inaudible) marginal electorates.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>There'll be, there'll always be a few surprises Helen, but today is a day of national unity. It's not a day of partisan political point scoring.</p>
<p>PRESENTER:</p>
<p>But it will be an interesting year.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes I know but I'll come back and talk to you about politics. But on a day like this the things that unite us as Australians are a lot more important than the things that divide us.</p>
<p>PRESENTER:</p>
<p>Mr Beazley has today said that we should get back to debating big picture issues, and he's put the republic firmly back on the agenda.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I've heard that before and the Australian people had a vote on that and if the Australian people want to have a vote on it some time in the future they will. What you've always got to remember with these things is that in the end.</p>
<p>PRESENTER:</p>
<p>You don't think it's worth talking about again?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I think people had a good bash at it a few months ago and I would have thought that right at the moment it's not the top of the pops.</p>
<p>PRESENTER:</p>
<p>Going into this election year do you respect Kim Beazley as your opponent as the leader of Labor?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I don't denigrate him as a person, but I'm not going to get dragged into political comments today, I'm really not. Try, keep trying but I'm not going to.</p>
<p>PRESENTER:</p>
<p>This day, Federation, is really not about just today is it, and it's not just about Sydney? It's going on for the whole year.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh no no, this is an event for the whole country. And there'll be a great event in Melbourne on the 9th of May that will commemorate the first sitting of the national parliament. There'll be a great commemoration in Darwin which reminds Australians of the bombing of the Australian mainland during World War Two. There'll be a wonderful indigenous gathering in December. So there's a whole year of events. But this is the kick off and it's a day that we should put aside our political differences and celebrate the joy of being an Australian.</p>
<p>PRESENTER:</p>
<p>So a lot of other areas, regional and cities, will be able to celebrate..</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Everybody will get a share and I think that's fantastic and I hope it is a people's year because the Australian people have made this country a success.</p>
<p>PRESENTER:</p>
<p>Prime Minister thanks for joining us.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Pleasure, thank you.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
