<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2032</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE RT. HON. J.G. GORTON, M.P. ON AID TO MALAYSIA AND SINGAPORE</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/04/1969</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002032.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA<br />
SPEECH BY<br />
The Rt Hon. J. G. GORTON, M. P.<br />
ON<br />
AMl TO MALAYSIA AND SING 0<br />
( Ministerial Statement<br />
-[ From the ' Parliamentary Debates', 1S April 1969]<br />
Mr G40RTON ( Higgins-Prime Minister)-<br />
by leave-In the course of my statement<br />
to this House on 25th February I<br />
said: we shall continue our efforts to help with<br />
the training of local Malaysians and Singaporean<br />
forces which we expect will be increased in size<br />
and capacity, and to provide financial assistance<br />
for defence aid aimed at assisting Malaysia and<br />
Singapore to build up their own defence capacity.<br />
We have been actively pursuing these purposes.<br />
I am now happy to say that<br />
following discussions with the Malaysian<br />
Government we will make a gift to<br />
Malaysia of ten of our Sabre aircraft,<br />
together with spares, ground support equipment<br />
and a simulator for training purposes.<br />
When the Sabres are delivered they will, be<br />
in Al condition with an operational life<br />
before them of at least 6 years. To train<br />
Malaysian pilots and ground staff to fly and<br />
maintain the Sabres we will send to Butterworth<br />
nearly ninety Royal Australian Air<br />
Force instructors and personnel. The aircraft<br />
with their spares and so on will, be<br />
by way of addition to our current Defence<br />
Aid Programme. The costs involved in<br />
operating the aircraft will naturally be<br />
borne by the Malaysian Government and<br />
the other costs involved will be met from<br />
the present uncommitted portion of our<br />
Defence Aid Programme for Malaysia. As<br />
pilots and-ground staff are trained, the<br />
Royal Malaysian Air Force will be able to<br />
14857/ 69 convert the squadron of Sabres from a<br />
training to an operational fighter unit.<br />
, We believe that this contribution on our<br />
part will be of help to the Malaysian<br />
Government in that it will provide an<br />
essential transitional step towards the<br />
eventual acquisition of supersonic aircraft<br />
which we understand the Malaysian<br />
Government has as its long-term aim.<br />
Further, it will enable this step to be taken<br />
without the necessity for the Malaysian<br />
Government to divert very considerable<br />
resources away from the programme of<br />
social and economic development which it<br />
rightly regards as essential to the stability<br />
of the region. Malaysia is also seeking our<br />
help in training operators and technicians<br />
for the radars it is acquiring-themselves<br />
costl-y enough-and in basic training for its<br />
pilots. These requests are under study-and<br />
I merely say at this stage that we will do<br />
what we can to help.<br />
We have also had certain discussions<br />
with the Singapore Government about<br />
directions in which we might aid Singapore<br />
defence plans. I mention here only one<br />
particular aspect. It is that we have notified<br />
our willingness to help the Singapore<br />
Government with the training of certain<br />
operators and technicians required for the<br />
Bloodhound defensive missiles which the<br />
Singapore Government is proposing to<br />
acquire from the United Kingdom Govern-</p>
<p>ment. These actions on our part should be<br />
seen in the context of our continuing<br />
association with our four partners in the<br />
Five Power arrangement-New Zealand,<br />
Malaysia,, Singapore, and the United<br />
Kingdom-and also of our and their<br />
common concern with the security of the<br />
South East Asia region. As I made clear in<br />
my statement to the House on 25th<br />
February 1969, our activities are in no way<br />
directed against the interests of any other country in the region but are intended to<br />
strengthen the stability of the whole; this<br />
we believe is well understood and accepted.<br />
What we are doing now is in fact making<br />
one more contribution to our long-standing<br />
defence aid programme, the purpose of<br />
which is to strengthen the defence capacity<br />
of Malaysia and Singapore within the<br />
framework of a broad concept of regional<br />
security and regional co-operation.<br />
Printed for the Government of the Commonwealth by W. G. MUR Y at the<br />
Government Printing Office, Canberra </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
