<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6721</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF PRIME MINISTER&#039;S PRESS CONFERENCE, PORT MORESBY AIRPORT, 15 SEPTEMBER 1985</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/09/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006721.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
41AUSTRALIA.-<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF PRIME MINISTER'S PRESS CONFERENCE<br />
PORT MORESBY AIRPORT 15 SEPTEMBER 1985<br />
JOURNALIST: -Prime Minister, on a domestic issue, has agreement<br />
been reached on the package of taxation reform?<br />
PM: Well they were well on the way when I left them at 1050<br />
this morning. It will be announced in due time.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you think it will be achieved this weekend?<br />
PM . We will be ale -to announce it this w ek I believe.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, you apparently sewed up a capital gains<br />
tax yesterday, at yesderday's meeting. Can you give any idea<br />
whether this is going to be at a marginal rate or a flat rate.<br />
PM: I know you would expect me to announce the details of capital<br />
gains tax here in New Guinea before the package, and I am sure you<br />
expect me answer that question.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, have you headed off che revolt over<br />
: MP's fringe benefits?<br />
PV: What revolt?<br />
JOURNALIST: What appeared to be a potential revolt?<br />
PM: You may have written it up as a revolt but the facts don't<br />
always correspond with your fervent imagination.<br />
JOURNALIST: Does it have unanimous support Prime Minister?<br />
Are there objections to it?<br />
PM: Well the decision is still to be taken. We hadn't dealt with<br />
that when I left. I have no worries about that area of the package<br />
JOURNALIST: On that particular-t Prime MInister. ARe you<br />
confident that the principle will be maintained that politicians<br />
will make a similar sacrifice to what they ask the community to<br />
make. PM: At least a similar one. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: It could be more.<br />
PM: Well, I am not going to depart from what I have said. I<br />
am not going into the details of a package which has not been<br />
finalised-. And I know all our time is valuable. But you keep<br />
asking me the questions about the package if you like, I am not<br />
going to the details.<br />
JOURNALIST: Are you confident that the package will be electorally<br />
acceptable? And how do you reconcile this with giving the income<br />
tax at the top end?<br />
PM: It will beat the hecll out of whatever th6 Liberals will be<br />
forced to come up with I can assure you of that.<br />
What about the local media. I hope you haven't been intimidated<br />
by my rough and ruthless colleagues from Australia.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, the patrol boat program.<br />
change his position.<br />
PM: Well, they had a position in 1984. There seems to be some<br />
indication that they may have changed from that. Whether they<br />
have changed back to the 1984 position I am not sure. But they<br />
is a maTfl e? that I will be discussing with the Prime MInister<br />
while I aml here.<br />
JOURNALIST: Are you at all confident that there waight be<br />
a change of view of this matter?<br />
PM: Well I thin% it is presumptuous to advance speculation on<br />
that before I talk to Mr Somare. I hope ' that we can arrive<br />
at common ground on it.<br />
JOURNALIST: Sir, the Papua New Guinea Cabinet has decided<br />
against it. Has this affected relations or the Australian<br />
stand on going ahead?<br />
PM: No we had been proceeding on a certain assumption about a<br />
number of boats for Papua New Guinea. Now there does seem to have<br />
been some change there. Now, a11' I can say is that the Prime<br />
Minister has indicated that he wants to discuss this matter<br />
with me and I am more than prepared to discuss it with him.<br />
JOURNALIST: So you will change your stand?<br />
PM: I will change my stand?<br />
JOURNALIST: The Australian Defence Minister said that<br />
Papua New Guinea didn't want these boats then they will forget it,<br />
that was the end of it.<br />
PM: We conveyed our position to them. Subsequently to us<br />
conveying our position to them I had a communication from<br />
Mr Somare saying he would like to talk to me about it. I<br />
am always a model of decency and good behaviour and so on.<br />
And -if someone wants to talk to me, indicates they want to<br />
talk to me, I will. talk to them. And I intend to 6o that.<br />
JOURNALIST: So there _ 4z a possibility that things could change<br />
both on youki! side and the Papua New Guinea side. </p>
<p>PM: Well, we are going ahead with our program.<br />
JOURNALIST: And I take it we are not changing our program.<br />
We are not changing the specifications of our boats.<br />
PM: No, there will be no change in the basic specifications<br />
of the boat.<br />
JOURNALIST: If all the other Pacific Island countries who are<br />
party to the patrol boat program, if they had taken the same<br />
stance as Papua New Guinea did, would-that make any difference<br />
to the Australia<br />
PM: Well, that is like, if I may say so, if your aunt had a<br />
different anatomical construction she would be your uncle.<br />
It is no good asking questions like that. We are dealing with<br />
the'position as it is.<br />
JOURNALIST: Yes, but Papua New Guinea seems to be the only<br />
country that, apart from Fiji, seems to be the only country that<br />
dissented from the program. They want a specific specification.<br />
PM: We have a clear arrangement with a number of countries of<br />
the South Pacific. We will be going ahead with the program<br />
in line with the arrangements we have made with them which were<br />
the same arrangements that we made with New Guinea last year.<br />
JOURNALIST: AS well as talking to Mr Somare about patrol boats,<br />
will you be disqussing matters of mutual interest such as<br />
the Irian Jayan refugees and Australian a~ id to Papua New Guinea?<br />
PM: Yes we will be discussing those matters. And a number of<br />
others I would think.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, have you any advice for Mr Somare on<br />
his domestic political problems, given your own experience?<br />
PM: Given my own experience in being able to solve all my own<br />
problems advice.<br />
JOURNALIST: facing a no confidence motion?<br />
PM: Oh, look it would be quite improper for me to come in<br />
here and intrude myself in domestic politics. I believe the<br />
Prime minister nor the Leader of the Opposition would welcome<br />
that. And I don't intend to do it.<br />
ENDS </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
