<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10811</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                  THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                  DOORSTOP INTERVIEW - MEADOWBANK, SYDNEY</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/06/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE....................................................</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Any questions?</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Mr Prime Minister, should banks look at lowering fixed home loan</p>
<p>   rates now the financial markets have come back from their ....(inaudible)...?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  I don't talk about the future level of interest rates. I merely</p>
<p>   observe that interest rates now for homebuyers and small business</p>
<p>   are lower than they have been for 30 years. But as for what happens</p>
<p>   about he future level of interest rates, well, that is something</p>
<p>   that is determined by markets and I am not going to speculate about</p>
<p>   future levels in either direction.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Prime Minister, what's your message to people of North Sydney</p>
<p>   who feel somewhat let down by the fact that Government's LTOP</p>
<p>   targets have not been reached?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  My message to them is they are infinitely better off than they were</p>
<p>   under the former Government. We are driving towards those targets</p>
<p>   and any suggestion from press reports this morning that we are abandoning</p>
<p>   those targets or that we are not committed to them is completely</p>
<p>   wrong. I have made no such admission and I found that report in</p>
<p>   the Sydney Morning Herald extraordinary. I've made no such</p>
<p>   admission.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Tony Abbott says that the Liberal Party should put One Nation last</p>
<p>   on preferences.....(inaudible)...?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  That is a matter for the party organisations to decide. I think</p>
<p>   everybody should just exercise a little bit of self-control on this</p>
<p>   issue. There is a process going on, the Victorian division and the</p>
<p>   South Australian division has already announced that in those States</p>
<p>   One Nation will be last. There is quite a vigorous process of consultation</p>
<p>   going on within the New South Wales division between the party organisation</p>
<p>   and the Federal Members. The same thing is occurring in Queensland</p>
<p>   and Western Australia and that process is producing interesting</p>
<p>   reactions and I think you ought to, to use the modern jargon, you</p>
<p>   should be willing to listen to the views of the members involved.</p>
<p>   I might have something further to say about this issue over the</p>
<p>   weekend but the process is going on. But I will have something further</p>
<p>   to say about this issue over the weekend.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  .... Mr Howard, it's fairly straightforward given that without</p>
<p>   the support of the Coalition, One Nation would have only won one</p>
<p>   seat in Queensland.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Mr Howard, what about your own seat in Bennelong? Can you give us</p>
<p>   a pledge now that you'll put One....?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well I've discussed, I've expressed a view to the party</p>
<p>   organisation about that. Look, I'll say something further over</p>
<p>   the weekend.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Can you tell us now will you put them last in Bennelong?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Look, I have discussed that matter with the party organisation.</p>
<p>   They know my view and my senior colleagues know my view, but I think</p>
<p>   it's a bit rich if a leader says that other people should exercise</p>
<p>   a bit of discipline and hold his peace and allow the proper processes</p>
<p>   to work and then he breaks that rule himself. But I think it's</p>
<p>   very important, I think it is very important that the processes</p>
<p>   of the Party be allowed to work. The Liberal Party is different</p>
<p>   from the Labor Party. We don't, from on high, lay down directives</p>
<p>   on certain things, we consult people and we produce a result.</p>
<p>  And what matters on this issue is to get the right results and not</p>
<p>   for people to break out and express their own personal views. I</p>
<p>   think the process of consultation should go on. My own view has</p>
<p>   been, in relation to what you ask, has been known for some time</p>
<p>   by senior colleagues and by senior people in the organisation, but</p>
<p>   I respect the process of the Party. I think other people should</p>
<p>   respect the process of the Party and as I say I can tell you that</p>
<p>   that process has been now going on for some time and it's working</p>
<p>   very well and it's producing some very interesting reactions</p>
<p>   and I say I'll have something further to say about it at the</p>
<p>   weekend and I don't intend to answer any further questions</p>
<p>   on that subject.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  ...One Nation's ... League of Rights. What's your reaction</p>
<p>   to that?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well my reaction is that the Liberal Party should identify and pursue</p>
<p>   the dangerous policies to Australia's future, of the One Nation</p>
<p>   Party. There is no doubt that for a long time on the Australian</p>
<p>   political scene there have been some very odd views on economics</p>
<p>   being espoused by the League of Rights and other organisations.</p>
<p>   I think what is interesting is that the head of the League of Rights,</p>
<p>   I understand, expressed a preference for Mr Campbell's party</p>
<p>   in the Queensland election and that party received the preferences</p>
<p>   of the Australian Labor Party in 12 of the 89 seats in Queensland</p>
<p>   so you might like to ask Mr Beattie and the Labor Party why it was</p>
<p>   that they gave preferences to a party which, according to Mr Eric</p>
<p>   Butler, has views that are closer to the views of the League of</p>
<p>   Rights than the views of One Nation. I mean we've had a lot</p>
<p>   of lectures from the Australian Labor Party about preference arrangements</p>
<p>   in Queensland. What happened in Queensland was that Mr Beattie's</p>
<p>   party gave preferences to Mr Campbell's party and Mr Butler</p>
<p>   of the League of Rights is now saying that Mr Campbell's party</p>
<p>   is closer to the League of Rights than One Nation.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  ...(inaudible)...</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well that's a matter for him. I don't think it aids the</p>
<p>   political process for people to be giving gratuitous advice to Premiers,</p>
<p>   gratuitous advice to party leaders in other parts of the country.</p>
<p>   So far as the Federal Parliamentary Party is concerned and the Federal</p>
<p>   organisation is concerned, we have a process for resolving preference</p>
<p>   issues. That process is working very effectively. I think, collectively</p>
<p>   speaking, people should keep their shirts on for a while and sort</p>
<p>   of exercise a bit of collective discipline on this issue and allow</p>
<p>   that process to work. And at the end of the day what really matters</p>
<p>   is that we get the right result and you'll only get the right</p>
<p>   result if you allow that process to work and it's working very</p>
<p>   effectively.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Should Mr Abbott then be disciplined?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Oh look, I'm not talking about that....Tony's an exuberant</p>
<p>   soul, he always has been. He likes writing too. He writes on many</p>
<p>   subjects and he is a very good friend of mine and I think he makes</p>
<p>   a terrific Parliamentary Secretary and he makes a great contribution.</p>
<p>   But like all exuberant characters, occasionally they should be a</p>
<p>   little more restrained.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Are you lobbying behind the scenes Mr Howard, that One Nation be</p>
<p>   put last?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Look, I don't talk publicly about the discussions I have with</p>
<p>   the party organisations. I have said repeatedly, and can I say it</p>
<p>   again, that there is a process. It's different from the Labor</p>
<p>   Party. You don't get results in the Liberal Party on organisational</p>
<p>   matters by shouting from the rooftops. What you do is you respect</p>
<p>   the processes of the Party and you allow them to work.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  But aren't the Australian people crying out for you to show</p>
<p>   leadership, isn't that one of the main criticisms?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  I think the Australian public is crying out for major political</p>
<p>   parties, all political parties and political leaders, to focus on</p>
<p>   policy issues. I think they are fed up with the trivia of politics.</p>
<p>   They are fed up with the lack of focus on policy. They are fed up</p>
<p>   with the confrontational nature of Australian politics. I think</p>
<p>   one of the messages that came out of Queensland is that many people,</p>
<p>   many decent Australians, don't like the style of Australian</p>
<p>   politics. They want a change in style, they want less emphasis on</p>
<p>   personalities, less emphasis on trivia, less emphasis on the morning</p>
<p>   headline and a bit more emphasis on the long-term future of our</p>
<p>   country. And I think any political leader who ignores that message</p>
<p>   out of Queensland, and that has nothing to do with extremism, it's</p>
<p>   got everything to do with a feeling on the part of many ordinary,</p>
<p>   decent Australians that we need a change of pace and we need a change</p>
<p>   of style and a greater emphasis on issues that are important for</p>
<p>   the future of our country - less emphasis on trivia, less emphasis</p>
<p>   on personal encounters and personal confrontation. I'll take</p>
<p>   one more question.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Malcolm Fraser says One Nation should be put last on the ticket</p>
<p>   unquestionably right across the board....(inaudible)?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  I haven't commented on Malcolm Fraser's comments for some</p>
<p>   years. Thank you.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
