<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>222</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER ON REPORT OF THE NATIONAL RADIATION ADVISORY COMMITTEE</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/08/1959</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000222.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER ON<br />
REPORT OF THE NATIONAL RADIATION ADVISORY<br />
COMMITTEE.<br />
In tabling this Second Annual Rep~ ort of the<br />
National Radiation Advisory Committee, I do not wish to say<br />
a great deal because the report speaks most ably for itself.<br />
The members of this Committee are, as you know, among the<br />
most eminent scientists in this country, so that what they<br />
have to say in this report must carry great weight. The<br />
report is expressed in the most simple lay language and the<br />
story tells is enormously reassuring. We have, as the<br />
report says, been fed a diet of news and reports about<br />
radiation and its hazards which, to say the least, has been<br />
alarming. It is cheering then to learn from these eminent<br />
scientists that their painstaking investigations over the<br />
last year have shown that Australia is one of the " cleanest"<br />
countries in the world. Indeed, to take a case, the report<br />
establishes that the average accumulation of strontium 90 in<br />
Australian soils in August, 1958, was about one third of that<br />
found in the United Kingdom, one fourth of that found in most<br />
areas of the United States, and only one seventh of that in<br />
mid-western United States. The report goes on to say<br />
that the maximnam permissible concentration of strontium 90 in<br />
the human body laid down-by the Committee of the International<br />
Commission on Radiological Protection is 110 times gre Lter<br />
than the concentration measured in Austral-Imi infants and<br />
660 times that in adults.'<br />
These are only two examples which I have culled<br />
from this report. I commend the whole text to you so that<br />
you may make your own evaluation of the " scare" stories to<br />
which we have been subjected.<br />
Two other points in the report to which I feel<br />
I should refer concern the use of x-rays in medical practice<br />
and the whole question of control of ionizing radiation.<br />
e 9/ 2 </p>
<p>Ar. 2.<br />
Concerning the use of x-rays in medicine, the<br />
Committee has pointed out in its previous report the dangers<br />
that can be associated with the use of x-rays. In this<br />
report they repeat their warnings, but also refer again to<br />
the equal dangers which could obtain if public alarm<br />
became so great that people were toc:-becnme unwilling to<br />
avail themselves of the necessary use of x-rays in medical<br />
practice. I mention this point because I feel that it<br />
should be underlined so that people will not subject<br />
themselves unnecessarily to even greater dangers through-not<br />
using this important aid to medical practice.<br />
So far as the control of the uses of ionizing<br />
radiation is concerned, the Committee recommends that the<br />
Commonwealth Government should accept respornsibility for<br />
the legislative control of all uses of ionizing radiation<br />
throughout Australia. Honourable Members will understand<br />
that this presents constitutional problems as well as other<br />
problems, but the Committee's recommendation will be<br />
considered by the Government and discussed with the States.<br />
The Committee alsrn reports the resignation of<br />
Sir Macfarlane Burnet who has been Chairman of the Committee<br />
since its inception. Sir Macfarlane has found that increasing<br />
personal commitments make it impossible for him to continue<br />
on the Committee. However, Honourable Members well know the<br />
contributions he has made to the Committee already have been<br />
of outstanding value. I venture to say that only his great<br />
sense of public duty has made him find the time which he has<br />
already devoted to the work of the Committee. In a period<br />
when, with all the great modern developments of this nuclear<br />
age, we have been alarmed by conflicting stories of dangers<br />
of radiation, Australia owes much to Sir Macfarlane ( and, of<br />
course, to the other members of the Committee) for the work<br />
put into this and the previous report. </p>
<p>[Date confirmed]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
