<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11604</transcript-id>
    <title>Pacific Patrol Boat Project to be Extended </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/10/2000</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I am pleased to announce that Australia will extend the Pacific Patrol Boat Project for a further 25 years, helping Pacific countries protect their fisheries and to build a better and more prosperous future. The project began in 1987 and has been a considerable success.</p>
<p>This life extension program will extend Australia's involvement in the project out to 2027 at an estimated cost of $350 million.</p>
<p>With the first Pacific Patrol Boat due to reach the end of its planned 15 year life in 2002, Australia will offer to extend the life of each of the 22 Pacific Patrol Boats so that they are able to operate for a total of 30 years.</p>
<p>Extending Australia's involvement in the Pacific Patrol Boat project represents Australia's most significant defence commitment to the South Pacific and illustrates Australia's strong commitment to meeting the resource management and security challenges of the region.</p>
<p>The boats provide Pacific Island countries with a credible maritime surveillance capability, without which they would be unable to protect their vast maritime territories. Fisheries remain the major resource for most Pacific countries and it is vital that fish stocks be managed sensibly to ensure both their survival and a fair return for island governments.</p>
<p>The boats have also been used for other purposes - such as search and rescue, customs and immigration work - and have made a great contribution to nation building within the region.</p>
<p>The life extension programme will involve a major capital upgrade to each boat, and Australia will continue to provide training, advisory and maintenance support over the period of the life extension programme.</p>
<p>30 October 2000</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
