<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8209</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH DOUG AITON, RADIO 3LO 21 NOVEMBER 1990</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/11/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008209.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF' INTERVIEW WITH DOUG AITON, RADIO<br />
21 NOVEMBER 1.990<br />
E OE PROOF ONLY<br />
AITON: Prime Minister Bob Hawke. Welcome to 3L0 again.<br />
PM: Pleasure Doug.<br />
AITON: What did you mean? Could you elaborate on the<br />
school educat~ ion we just heard.<br />
PM: Yes. What I was talking about there was that when we<br />
came to office in 1983 we inherited this monstrous situation<br />
that only one in 3 of Australian kids stayed on the<br />
education system to years 11 and 12 which was a pattern of<br />
privilege. It meant the kids of the wealthy and well to do,<br />
they went on but the kids from low income and low to middle<br />
income families, more often than not, didn't. Now in seven<br />
years we've -transformed that from one in 3 to now two in 3<br />
of kids are staying on. What I was saying there today was<br />
that by the end of this century we'll create a situation as<br />
a society, if we can move on like this, that really,<br />
whatever kids want to, go on into the education system<br />
they'll be able to. I mean, that doesn't mean that everyone<br />
will of course. But we'll have created the situation where<br />
they'll be able to. That seems to me the most important<br />
thing that any society can do.<br />
AITON: Yes well I've always thought that it was a bit of<br />
pity that that child poverty statement got out of hand<br />
because you were doing more than anyone else had as far as<br />
child poverty is concerned. Your statement was probably too<br />
extravagant in pure words.<br />
PM: What I said we set ourselves in my spoken speech we<br />
set ourselves the goal that by 1990 no child need live in<br />
poverty. The words in the accompanying document were more<br />
explicit. We said we'd remove the financial need. All the<br />
people in the social welfare community have been generous in<br />
acknowledging that we kept that promise. That we met our<br />
targets. When you think, the fact is, that we are now<br />
spending just in those Family Allowance Supplements<br />
$ 1.2 billionL which is going to half a million low income<br />
families and about 1.2 million kids. I mean, it just is<br />
remarkable that where this Government has done what is now<br />
being recognised as more than any other government has done<br />
anywhere. That, you know, we have that mindless thing<br />
thrown at us. Now I've got to accept some responsibility </p>
<p>for imprecision of spelling out precisely what was in the<br />
document. But I'm proud of the fact that we have done more<br />
than any other government to make sure that the finance is<br />
there for those low income families in need.<br />
AITON: I was working things out today. It seems to me I<br />
don't know if I missed something around July but it seems<br />
to me that about July the 1st this year you became the<br />
second longest serving Prime Minister in this country's<br />
history. PM: Yes. I did. I passed Malcolm Fraser.<br />
AITON: Now, John Curtin became Prime Minister on the 7th of<br />
October 1941. Menzies knocked of f Ben Chifley at the<br />
election of 1.949. I think it was the 10th of December.<br />
PM: It was i~ n December. The end of the year.<br />
AITON: Now according to my calculations you've got about<br />
six months to go before you exceed the longest Labor period<br />
in Australia's history, that is Curtin and Chifley combined.<br />
PM: Yes. I guess, yes I haven't really thought about that.<br />
Yes. That was when you put those two together it was 41,<br />
49, December.. Yes that's right.<br />
AITON: Yes ,%, ou've got six months.<br />
PM: Yes about that. I hadn't really thought about it.<br />
AITON: Will you chuck it in soon after that, do you think?<br />
PM: No.<br />
AITON: How long will you go for? Everyone's asking I know.<br />
PM: Yes. Doug, I'd like to take the Party into the next<br />
election. Then we'd see after that.<br />
AITON: Sometimes I wonder why everyone does ask you that<br />
all the time because you're about to turn 61.<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
AITON: Now in some countries, and certainly some ages in<br />
the past, you wouldn't be old enough yet to be Prime<br />
Minister. PM: Yes. I suppose in Japan they have usually been older<br />
than that. Although the current Prime Minister is younger.<br />
AITON: Yes. Are you feeling as well as ever physically?<br />
PM: Never felt better, Doug.<br />
AITON: Yes. You'd be too young to be Pope by the way.<br />
You'd be the: youngest Pope in history. </p>
<p>PM: I have certain other disqualifications too.<br />
AITON: Certainly. The Accord, or the continuation of the<br />
Accord released by Paul Keating, yesterday or the day<br />
before, it appears to signify that you and Keating believe<br />
that the economic crisis that this country is facing, and a<br />
lot of responsible people have said that it actually is in<br />
recession. What you've announced appears to be a prelude to<br />
the fact that it's coming to an end.<br />
PM: Yes. What both Paul and I have been saying, Doug, is<br />
this, that we expect the cycle of recovery to be clear by<br />
the middle of next year. We knew that we had to slow the<br />
economy down. What we've been undertaking is this very<br />
delicate task of slowing activity down but not in a way<br />
which is going to bust the economy. Now obviously some<br />
people have been hurt in the process and I've never tried to<br />
disguise that. But what we've got are the fundamentals<br />
moving in the right direction. That is interest rates are<br />
coming down, inflation going down, wages growth being<br />
contained. We are now, as far as inflation is concerned,<br />
Doug, in this situation where Australia's inflation rate is<br />
coming down the rest of the world basically is going up and<br />
we're narrowing very substantially that gap between<br />
ourselves and our major trading partners. That means, in<br />
our judgement, that we will, in 1991, be able to resume a<br />
sustainable growth path and resume stronger employment<br />
growth and that's what it's all been aimed at.<br />
AITON: Well Paul Keating has claimed that we are now the<br />
only OECD country with inflation actually decelerating.<br />
We're down to six per cent, about.<br />
PM: That's what we've got now. In fact, we pointed out,<br />
when this last CPI came out which gave us 0.7 per cent, that<br />
since 1971 the Treasury has been measuring what they call<br />
the basic underlying rate of inflation which takes out<br />
extraneous temporary factors. According to their measure we<br />
now have the lowest inflation figure we've had since that<br />
series started at the beginning of the<br />
AITON: Now on the celebrated day on the 5th of March 1983<br />
when you were voted Prime Minister I think you inherited<br />
11 per cent inflation.<br />
PM: Yes. Double digit inflation and double digit<br />
unemployment. In our period we've never got back into<br />
double digit, either inflation or unemployment and we're not<br />
going to.<br />
AITON: On the other hand you inherited $ 21 billion overseas<br />
debt which is now 150 billion.<br />
PM: We also inherited a situation where the Commonwealth<br />
Government, where the people of Australia as the Government<br />
were part of that debt. What we've done is to do what's<br />
never been done before. We've had successive surpluses and<br />
we've wiped out, entirely, Commonwealth Government debt.<br />
There is no Commonwealth we are in fact nett international </p>
<p>creditors. We've paid of f debt. Now overwhelmingly that<br />
debt is in the private sector. It represents decisions that<br />
have been taken, Doug just let me give you an example;<br />
part of that debt profile is money that was spent during<br />
that period on building up the North West Shelf. Now we had<br />
to carry that. But now that's earning us very significant<br />
export income. Now that's part of what's been happening.<br />
There's money been spent to restructure the Australian<br />
economy and the economy is going to get the benefits of<br />
that. AITON: When you were last here I said that I thought that<br />
during the HEawke years the people who had suffered most were<br />
the young people who were not able to get into houses like<br />
you were able to, and I a little later was able to, and<br />
these days they can't so easily. That's interest rates<br />
we're talkingr about.<br />
PM: Yes. Well1, of course, that's true, I mean, what we've<br />
seen in this country was a situation where, when we came to<br />
office, in that last year before we came to office, the<br />
housing starts were 106,000 now we lifted that enormously.<br />
It got up to 180,000 which was unsustainable. Although the<br />
demand was there, I mean, really you couldn't have an<br />
economy along at that level of activity. We've brought<br />
it back now but even down at this deliberately lowered level<br />
of activity the starts have only got down to about 130,000<br />
which never approached the 106,000 that was there when we<br />
came in. Now it is the case that in this period with higher<br />
interest rates in the latter period. The inability of the<br />
States and local government to open up as much land for<br />
housing as they should have so that the land prices were<br />
high. It is true that affordability of housing suffered.<br />
But now the index is coming down as the rate of interest is<br />
coming down and coming down further again today with the<br />
reduction by Westpac.<br />
AITON: Westpac was good news today. Certainly it looks as<br />
though more people will be able to get into houses. The<br />
other thing I'd add to people suffering, to last time that<br />
we met in this studio, would be the rural sector. Now they<br />
may have bee~ n suffering then, certainly are now and it goes<br />
largely unnoticed. I don't think the media has really<br />
caught onto the suffering out in the rural sector because<br />
we ' ye always thought they have nice big farms with big<br />
homesteads on them they must be okay.<br />
PM: Well it's unfair. You do touch on a real point.<br />
There's a lot of people in the rural sector who are<br />
suffering badly and the tragedy what sticks in my craw so<br />
much about it is that basically the problem is that they're<br />
not getting a fair price for what they produce. I mean,<br />
Australian rural producers are the most efficient in the<br />
world. If we had a fair liberalised international trading<br />
system, Doug, these people would get significantly more for<br />
what they so efficiently produce. That's why I'm putting so<br />
much of my time now in trying to do what we can to rescue<br />
this Uruguay Round which is about, I mean without being<br />
technical for your listeners, what that Round has been going </p>
<p>since 86, it's a four year Round and it's aimed at freeing<br />
up international trade. Now it's in the area of<br />
agricultural trade that we have the least freedom. I mean,<br />
the Europeans I mean this is a staggering statistic, Doug,<br />
but between them the Europeans and the Americans spend about<br />
$ 200 billion, $ 200 billion per annum in production and<br />
export subsidies. Now that's stopping our producers getting<br />
access to some markets and getting a fair price in all the<br />
markets they go to. Now the stupidity of course is, that if<br />
the Europeans; and the Americans didn't do that then they'd<br />
be better off' because their whole cost and price structure<br />
would be lower and you'd have a decent sort of access for<br />
our people. So that's what<br />
AITON: They don't seem to see it that way though, do they?<br />
PM: Well, this is ultimately the most frustrating thing,<br />
Doug, I sat ( town in my office with Chancellor Kohl from<br />
0 GIe rumnadneyr staandn d hwahmamte reydo u'hriem saabyoiuntg , t hiIs . u ndHeer stsaaindd, whBoabt, yhoeu ' rseaid,<br />
saying, you'r-e right. But he said, I've got these farmers<br />
and they've ( lot votes and I've got to watch them. And the<br />
French say thie same thing. If they didn't understand your<br />
argument that'd be one thing but when they know that what<br />
you're putting is right and then they tell you, oh yes but<br />
we've got to worry about our farmers' votes. That's what<br />
sticks in your craw.<br />
AITON: Isn't the problem this; the European community has<br />
become the most wealthy economic unit in the world. They<br />
therefore can afford to subsidise farmers who otherwise<br />
wouldn't be making a quid, or a Mark, or a Franc. So<br />
they're doing that and we're objecting to it saying, look we<br />
can't subsidise our rural community it's not fair. And<br />
they're saying we don't care what you can do.<br />
PM: Well that's not an unfair summary of what you're<br />
putting. And again what's so damned annoying about it was<br />
0 that if in fact they wanted to help their poorer farmers<br />
no-one would object to that but don't do it in an<br />
inefficient way. Give them a direct income support but<br />
don't do it by way of production subsidies and export<br />
subsidies. But the way it is now it's not the poorest<br />
farmers who get the greatest help it's the richest.<br />
AITON: Sure. But the point I'm making<br />
PM: And you're right that they are so rich, so powerful<br />
that, in a sense, they can say well, you know, get nicked.<br />
AITON: And they are continuing to say that.<br />
PM: Unfortunately. I've just written, earlier this week,<br />
to all the Heads of Government in Europe and it's a tough<br />
letter. I spoke to Bush, President Bush at the end of last<br />
week. To be: fair to the Americans on this, while they are<br />
doing the same sort of thing they don't want to. I mean, in<br />
the Uruguay Round they've said, they've put up a proposal<br />
very similar to what Australia and the Cairns Group have put </p>
<p>up. That is that over 10 years you'd knock all these things<br />
out. But what they say, is while the Europeans are doing it<br />
then they are. not going to have their people knocked around.<br />
And I say well that's beaut. The actual language I used to<br />
them I said, you say you're not intending to shoot us it's<br />
the Europeans: but if you get hit in the head with a bullet<br />
it doesn't hurt any less if you're told that it was meant<br />
for someone else, it still hurts.<br />
AITON: And they're still not going to take any notice even<br />
with colourful phraseology like that because, as you say,<br />
since 1986 the GATT talks have been going on. They're just<br />
about to continue to tell us, we don't care what your<br />
problems are. What I'm saying is we're not getting<br />
anywhere. PM: Well I think that's basically true on the evidence.<br />
Except that there is now and to be fair to Margaret<br />
0 oTnh attchhienrgs,, anbdu t yosuh e knhoaws pIl ahyaevde aa lgooto d ofr oldei fferentchee s Ewuirtohp eahnesr.<br />
I mean, she's told them that this is crazy. There's a lot<br />
of pressure coming from the United States. When I had this<br />
long talk wit~ h George Bush last Friday he said that they<br />
were going to continue to press hard. They'd send Baker<br />
over there arid he's pressing them. And he's pressing them<br />
himself personally over in Europe at this present time. The<br />
Germans have their election on the 2nd of December. It may<br />
be that once that's out of the way once that's out of<br />
the way Chancellor Kohl may be prepared to look at this a<br />
bit more reasonably. So I haven't given up hope. We're in<br />
there fighting.<br />
AITON: On that matter, going back to the matter of the<br />
overseas debt which may well be, as you say, to do with the<br />
private sector, it may be that the Government's been<br />
involved in ' Letting it blow out to $ 150 billion. The point,<br />
I think, on -this is, can the Government do anything to<br />
contain it or reduce it and is it something that makes you<br />
anxious? PM: Yes.<br />
AITON: Because people don't seem to<br />
PM: Oh no. We are concerned about it. We said in the<br />
Budget that we would reduce the current account deficit from<br />
the previous year and bring it down from the level it was to<br />
about $ 18 billion from the much higher figures it was last<br />
year. So far this financial year we're on target there. So<br />
that the current account deficit as a proportion of the<br />
gross domestic product will come down by a percentage point<br />
or more. But we can't rest on our laurels on that. I think<br />
that we are seeing, importantly, which should encourage us<br />
as Australians, a significant increase in the exports of<br />
manufactured goods. So that we're not just going to be<br />
relying on our rural products, as important as they will<br />
continue to be. So we're becoming more diversified in our<br />
exports and we've got to make sure our challenge as a<br />
community simply, though, is this Doug, that for a number of </p>
<p>years ahead of us we've got to make sure that our growth in<br />
production outstrips our growth in demand. That's-what<br />
we've got to do. It's only in that way that we'll gradually<br />
bring down our current account deficit and our debt.<br />
AITON: Is John Hewson going to give you the biggest run for<br />
your money ofE the four, you've won four in a row which is an<br />
unprecedented record for Labor of course<br />
PM: Let me say this, if we'd had to go to an election<br />
straight after we'd won the last election, the answer to<br />
your question would be yes. Because there is no doubt the<br />
Australian electorate breathed the collective sigh of relief<br />
when, as I puat it this mad hurdy gurdy, merry-go-round of<br />
Howard, Peacock, Howard, Peacock, Howard, Peacock when it<br />
came to an end and there was a new face in there. And if<br />
you had to go to an election then it would have been<br />
difficult. But it's fascinating to see how this man is<br />
operating under pressure. Could I recommend to you as<br />
compulsory reading for someone who is interested in politics<br />
and political analysis, get the full transcript of his last<br />
press conference. You know I geed him up a bit in the<br />
Parliament and said come on and we'll have a press<br />
conference, John, and then I looked up at the Gallery and<br />
said they're not bad people. Don't be so frightened of<br />
them. He'd been dodging them. And when you read this<br />
transcript of his press conference you will see why. The<br />
fascinating thing, a man who's supposed to be intellectually<br />
equipped to deal with ideas and answer questions of policy.<br />
He dodged every question from the press about policy issues.<br />
I think you are going to find, in the period ahead, that<br />
with the combined pressure of the Government and of a media<br />
which responsibly wants to know what he's standing for, that<br />
Dr Hewson is going to be under considerable pressure. Now I<br />
don't say that with any sense of gloating satisfaction, I<br />
mean, I like to see a good Opposition. But I believe that<br />
he has been found wanting domestically and of course,<br />
whoever is advising him in the area of international<br />
affairs, I mean, he ought to sack them now. I mean, the<br />
questions that are prepared for him and the statements that<br />
are prepared for him, really they are just embarrassing and<br />
embarrassing his own colleagues. So he is not performing<br />
well under the pressure of the Parliament. Now I accept<br />
Doug that we; should never, we people operating in Canberra,<br />
should never think that politics is just about Canberra and<br />
just about the Parliament and I am not making that mistake.<br />
But I am saying, that as the pressures upon the Leader of<br />
the Opposition to develop his policies and the details of<br />
them, as tho'se pressures develop, I think you'll find that<br />
he is going to have a somewhat different status than he has<br />
enjoyed in this period since the election.<br />
AITON: Well., you and Paul Keating have tried, I think I'm<br />
right in saying that you have tried to get through to the<br />
public that you believe that Dr Hewson is an admirer of the<br />
Thatcher approach to things and that the UK at the moment<br />
has a higher wages growth, must be up to about 15 per cent<br />
PM: Very high, very high. </p>
<p>AITON: I think inflation is 11 per cent, unemployment much,<br />
much higher than ours of course, and that therefore unlike<br />
what Paul Keaiting announced the other day to do with wages<br />
tax trade-off, if we went the Hewson way, if he were in<br />
Government, wre would end up with a situation like that<br />
Britain is grappling with at the moment, much worse than<br />
ours. Is thatt what you are saying?<br />
PM: Well, I am not necessarily just relating it to<br />
Mrs Thatcher. What I am making the point I am making and<br />
Paul's also making, is that in the conduct of economic<br />
policy, in particularly in a country like this which is so<br />
exposed to the great variation of movement in the prices for<br />
our international commodities that we sell. You can't<br />
basically run a successful economic policy if you haven't<br />
got a wages policy. Without sort of trying to get<br />
theroetical about it, let's go back to the period when they<br />
were last in office. They were there 82-83 we won in ' 83<br />
and you remember that John Hewson was an economic adviser<br />
to John Howar-d at that time.<br />
AITON: Who was Treasurer at that time.<br />
PM: That's right. Now they had high interest rates<br />
interest rates reached a higher peak so they had to rely<br />
very, very heavily on monetary policy even more heavily<br />
than we did and one of the reasons why the whole thing<br />
exploded on them was that they didn't have a wages policy,<br />
they had a 17 per cent growth in wages. Now, the secret of<br />
the conduct of macro-economic policy is that you have got to<br />
be able to have your organised trade union movement being<br />
prepared to accept lower increases in nominal wages.<br />
Otherwise you are going to have unsustainably high inflation<br />
which will then reflect itself through into your levels of<br />
activities, ylour exchange rate adjustments, interest and<br />
monetary policy. The real secret of the success that we<br />
have had in creating 1.6 million new jobs 90 per cent of<br />
them in the private sector and a rate of job creation five<br />
times faster than when Howard was there with Hewson advising<br />
him is that we have had the co-operation of the trade union<br />
movement. No 17 per cent wages blow-outs. Now that's what<br />
I am saying I am not worried about going to Thatcherism,<br />
although the figures that you quote are right, but that's<br />
where the big advantage for this country is of having a<br />
government, the Labor Government, that can get responsible<br />
wages outcomes from the trade union movement. Dr Hewson has<br />
got no wages policy and he could never have one.<br />
AITON: Are you saying that the Liberal Party by its very<br />
nature could never have a good relationship with the trade<br />
union movement?<br />
PM: Well it's not so much that I am saying that they<br />
couldn't have a good relationship because of, you know, the<br />
way they look or who they are but what I'm saying is it's<br />
the philosophy. I don't want to get into a I mean you<br />
know from the things I've said about Dr Hewson, I have been<br />
trying to go to what he has been talking about, not about </p>
<p>the man as such. I don't want to attack him as a man. What<br />
I'm trying to say, Doug, is that the ideology and the<br />
philosophy of the Liberal Party, and he has reflected no<br />
difference in, this at all, is that you don't have cooperation.<br />
You don't say, well we as a Government will<br />
assume part cif the responsibility of satisfying your<br />
aspirations by what we will do in the area of education,<br />
what we will do in the area of health. You see, why the<br />
trade union movement with Labor has been prepared to modify<br />
its wage claims has been because we have accepted our<br />
responsibility to satisfy their aspirations by bringing in<br />
universal hea~ lth care, by doing what we have done in<br />
education and by massive improvements in the area of social<br />
security. Arnd the trade union movement has said to the<br />
Labor Government, alright, you do those things, then we<br />
don't need to have such big increases in money wages. Now<br />
that's our philosophy but it's not that of the Liberal Party<br />
and that's why they can't have an effective relationship.<br />
0 AITON: After seven years, you might be getting a bit<br />
contemplative and philosophical about what, how you are<br />
going to be remembered looking back to the 1940s, the<br />
Chifley Government is still remembered for the Holden, for<br />
the Snowy Mountains Scheme. Is there going to be a monument<br />
like that that the Hawke Government can achieve? We have<br />
talked about economic matters<br />
PM: Physical monuments?<br />
AITON: Well not so much physical<br />
PM: The monument that I will be proudest of leaving within<br />
this country is what I was talking about before. The<br />
conservatives were in Government for seven years before I<br />
came in. In that seven years, they increased the<br />
participation rate in education by two percentage points<br />
from 34 per cent to 36 per cent. So they walked out of<br />
office after seven years leaving just about the worst<br />
participation rate of any developed country in the OECD.<br />
After, now seven and a half years with the Hawke Government,<br />
I have virtually doubled that not up by two percentage<br />
points but viLrtually doubled it. If I want to leave one<br />
thing that I am going to be proudest of, internally, it will<br />
be that we have revolutionised the landscape of educational<br />
opportunity. No longer after this Government has finished<br />
will you have to say of Australian education that its only<br />
basically the kids of the rich and the well to do who will<br />
stay on in school. Because you will be able to say after my<br />
Government that kids from the western suburbs, kids from low<br />
income families, kids from low to middle income families are<br />
going to have the same sort of opportunity. You can't do<br />
anything more important than that because in a longterm<br />
sense, the quality of this country depends upon the equality<br />
of educational opportunity.<br />
AITON: How mnuch credit would you give to Bob Menzies for<br />
doing exactl-y what you are talking about? Not exactly, I'm<br />
sorry, not eXactly but for what he did for education in this<br />
country from the point that he had to start at? </p>
<p>PM: I have always tried to be fair in the assessment of my<br />
opponents. I had profound differences of opinion and<br />
philosophy with Bob Menzies on so many things, but he<br />
deserves credit in the area of education for seeing that<br />
there is a responsibility for a Commonwealth government to<br />
look at the needs of the whole community irrespective of<br />
whether kids are in a State education system or within the<br />
Catholic education system. He deserves credit for that. it<br />
was looked at: by some as political opportunism. Now I don't<br />
know what moved him but nevertheless the fact that he moved<br />
the country towards understanding that the nation as a whole<br />
must accept responsibility for the education of all<br />
children. I give him credit for that. One other area which<br />
is not the same you mentioned, I have always given Bob<br />
Menzies credit for the fact that he had a vision of a<br />
national capital for Australia. If it hadn't been for Bob<br />
Menzies and. some people might cynically say this is a<br />
minus against him but he did have a vision of Australia<br />
having a great national capital of which it should be proud.<br />
And when he became Prime Minister in 49, there was still<br />
those who would have liked to say let's cancel the<br />
experiment, let's wipe it out. Now, I think in, as we go<br />
into the 21st century, Australians are going to be proud of<br />
the fact that we have got one of the great national capital<br />
cities of the world and Bob Menzies deserves a lot of credit<br />
for that.<br />
AITON: Did you know him well?<br />
PM: No.<br />
AITON: Did you meet him<br />
PM: Yes I met him. I met him at the cricket occasionally,<br />
so we knew one another but I didn't really have the<br />
opportunity to have discussions with him of any<br />
significance. AITON: Were you reasonably prominent at that time? You<br />
would have been in the ACTU, wouldn't you?<br />
PM: Well you see, he went out I was the research officer<br />
and advocate by the time I became President of the ACTU,<br />
he, of course, had finished-<br />
AITON: He'd gone.<br />
PM: Finished his Prime Ministership.<br />
AITON: What has made you most angry during 1990? We all<br />
know you can get angry.<br />
PM: Yes, I can get angry and I guess, you know, people in<br />
positions of responsibility, if there are no things that can<br />
make them angry, I don't think they are very real sort of<br />
people. Well, you touched upon it before to some extent<br />
it's a mixture of anger and sorrow that when I look at the<br />
Opposition that they scream out this business, no child live </p>
<p>in poverty by 1990, and the refusal of them to, you know<br />
they quote Archbishop Hollingworth at me but they won't<br />
listen to what Archbishop Hollingworth said, who said, Hawke<br />
delivered on his promise, that the financial targets would<br />
be met. He said further that the Opposition should cease<br />
being opportunistic about this and they should give credit<br />
to the Government for what has been done. It's a mixture of<br />
anger and sadness that what I see as one of the great<br />
achievements of this Government has been belittled in this<br />
unfair way.<br />
AITON: The Aborigines seem to have disappeared as an issue<br />
to me. Am I wrong there do you think?<br />
PM: Yes you're wrong in saying they disappeared as an<br />
issue. They haven't and they should never disappear as an<br />
issue. I just had my Minister for Aboriginal Affairs,<br />
Robert Tickner, in the other day and had a very, very long<br />
conversation with him. We were mapping out just where we<br />
0 were going and the whole range of our programs for the<br />
Aboriginal people including how we are going to handle this<br />
question of looking at the reconciliation, if I can put it<br />
that way, of the Australian nation with its Aboriginal<br />
population. You know, I have talked about this for some<br />
time if there is an instrument to be an instrument of<br />
reconciliation, well that is something that we can discuss.<br />
But the important thing is the process of trying to bring<br />
about a state in this nation where the Aboriginal people<br />
accept that the non-Aboriginal population acknowledges the<br />
short-comings, the wrongs that have been done in the past,<br />
that they on their part the Aboriginal people accept<br />
that and are going to say alright well we accept the<br />
commitment of the Australian community as a whole to move to<br />
rectify these wrongs of the past. And I give credit to<br />
other political leaders that I have written to them,<br />
including the Leader of the opposition and I have said,<br />
look, let's try and get a bipartisan approach in this way<br />
and I give them credit that their responses have been fairly<br />
0 positive. I think that there is a considerable amount of<br />
hope now to move ahead as a nation to do the things we ought<br />
to do in this area.<br />
AITON: I sometimes wonder if anything has happened at all<br />
since the war-, as far as the well being of the Aboriginal<br />
people is concerned.<br />
PM: Oh yes, a great deal has been done and again while I<br />
would have thought that the previous Government could have<br />
done more. They did things we have very, very substantially<br />
increased in real terms the funding that's been provided,<br />
much more has been done. I mean, if you look at education,<br />
I mean I can look at the period that we have been in<br />
Government and the participation of Aboriginal children in<br />
the levels of' education has increased enormously, our<br />
expenditure on Aboriginal health programs has increased very<br />
much and on Aboriginal housing. They are very important<br />
areas and also employment opportunities. So you can look at<br />
employment, education, and housing, and health very, very<br />
big increases; have been made in funding terms. There are </p>
<p>12.<br />
improvements in their condition but we have got no basis,<br />
Doug, for being complacent. Very importantly, what we have<br />
done, and we've just now had the election, we have<br />
established the Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islanders<br />
Commission which is going to now establish for the first<br />
time a democratically elected commission of Aboriginal<br />
people themselves. The concept there is that rather than us<br />
sitting in Canberra and saying well, here we are going to<br />
spend this much on education, this much on health, this much<br />
on housing. We are going to be saying well we are making as<br />
much money as: we can available in bulk and the various<br />
communities around Australia who will have different needs<br />
in some areas, housing will be a more important issue than<br />
health for instance. They are going to have the apparatus<br />
now for determining the priorities of expenditure in their<br />
various regions. I think this is a very important move.<br />
But as I say, none of us are entitled to be complacent.<br />
AITON: I reckon the thing that troubles me most from my<br />
area and a lot of my colleagues, and I think a lot of the<br />
public too, to summarise and put it into a nutshell is that<br />
of the ten city newspapers that we now have throughout this<br />
country, seven of them are controlled by Rupert Murdoch and<br />
that's indicative of all sorts of things to do with media<br />
ownership. PM: Well let me say this about media ownership generally.<br />
No Government, and I think you wouldn't argue with this, no<br />
Government has done more by legislation to deconcentrate<br />
ownership across the media than we have because by<br />
legislation we stopped what the situation was before. That<br />
is that one man or one company could in particular areas own<br />
the newspapers, the television, the radio stations. We<br />
brought that to an end. Now if you're talking about<br />
concentration that was the real objectionable feature in<br />
this country, that one man, one company in a particular<br />
region could have all the outlets. I mean the newspapers,<br />
radio and television. Now we've brought that to an end.<br />
AITON: Yes, that's gone and I accept that.<br />
PM: Now in regard to newspapers, well if you were looking<br />
at the sort of ideal situation I guess you would say you'd<br />
like to see some greater diversification. But we have taken<br />
the view that essentially we've wanted in regard to the<br />
economy as a whole, to have a more deregulated sort of<br />
environment where market forces operate and this has been<br />
useful to the economy generally speaking. Now if you take<br />
the State of Victoria, now you had an afternoon newspaper<br />
and a morning newspaper, the Sun and the Herald. Now that's<br />
gone, you've only got one so that in a sense can be said<br />
you've got more concentration. But is there any difference<br />
in as far as Melbourne's concerned, in the capacity of the<br />
ownership to influence the population because there's one<br />
newspaper rather than two? I mean how far should a<br />
Government intervene, Doug, in determining what the number<br />
of newspapers is going to be? </p>
<p>13.<br />
AITON: I don't know but I'd like to know if you're happy<br />
with the particular man, Murdoch, having seven out of ten<br />
across the country, metropolitan newspapers, dailies?<br />
PM: Well I've got to look at the newspapers. If what I<br />
saw, Doug, and you'll appreciate that I look at the<br />
newspapers pr: etty closely, if what I saw was one monolithic<br />
Murdoch view then I'd be terribly disturbed. But I don't<br />
see that.<br />
AITON: No, but it's potentially there.<br />
PM: Well I suppose it's potentially there and if one had a<br />
position when you saw that sort of thing emerging where one<br />
man or one or7ganisation was going to say I am going to<br />
imprint one view upon the Australian population then you<br />
might cause for But I look at the Murdoch newspapers<br />
and what I find, I mean you take Sydney. I wake up there<br />
and I pick up what was the Telegraph and the Australian. I<br />
get my bum kicked to death in the Australian<br />
AITON: Well you usually do.<br />
PM: But getting ticks and pluses in the Telegraph. Now you<br />
see the point: I'm making<br />
AITON: I do. You're making the point that this particular<br />
proprietor is not misbehaving. That's what you're saying.<br />
But I'm saying the potential is there theoretically.<br />
PM: Theoretically the position is there but I'm not sure<br />
given what it: costs now to own and operate a newspaper<br />
whether there are large numbers of potential Australian<br />
purchasers. You know we stopped Maxwell trying to get<br />
control of The Age here because we thought that wasn't a<br />
very good idea. So if you're saying it's not a bad idea to<br />
look at Australian proprietorship and of course Murdoch<br />
started off as an Australian and I think in a sense I<br />
still in a sense regard him as Australian although he took<br />
out American citizenship. I don't think there are a great<br />
number of potential purchasers in this country at any rate<br />
now. AITON: No, there are not. But off hand anyway we've argued<br />
that one. It seems to me that you're still the vote winner<br />
and Paul Keating has a trouble attracting votes.<br />
PM: Well let: me be fair in regard to Paul Keating. I think<br />
firstly, one should make this point that historically, as<br />
you would know, Treasurers, they find it fairly difficult to<br />
be popular. Secondly, Paul is a pretty single minded bloke<br />
in terms of pursuing his economic objectives. He's a hard<br />
worker and hel's been about pursuing what he sees as the<br />
basic needs of economic management and economic<br />
restructuring and it's neither been his job nor in a sense<br />
his inclination to be out explaining himself and explaining<br />
the Government, that's more the Prime Minister's job.<br />
Thirdly, I MEan it is, I think, the case that by nature I'm<br />
more gregarious, easily gregarious than Paul. I think </p>
<p>14.<br />
people really do him less than justice in many ways, in that<br />
when you do I mean he projects this image of arrogance I<br />
suppose as people say, some sort of contempt for others.<br />
That's projected in some way or people project it of him.<br />
But when you know the bloke he's a I mean he can be a<br />
delightful and congenial companion and I think that as<br />
people get to know him better they'll find these other<br />
aspects of his character. But they don't come out easily in<br />
his present position.<br />
AITON: Have you had some rocky times, the two of you?<br />
PM: I suppose really there have been two occasions of any<br />
significance when it got a bit rocky but that was at the<br />
time of the tax summit, there was a little bit of a problem<br />
there, it didn't last long. And then last year, early in<br />
the year there was a little bit of a confrotente<br />
AITON: Over what?<br />
PM: That was a feeling that Paul had that I was thinking he<br />
was dispensable, which I hadn't expressed. But I concede<br />
that in the language that was used he could've had that<br />
feeling and he was a bit hurt about that.<br />
AITON: And you didn't mean it that way?<br />
PM: No, I didn't. But that upset things a bit. But having<br />
said that, just two occasions on and it's getting on for<br />
eight years I would think the history books will show that<br />
there hasn't been a more effective Prime Minister/ Treasurer<br />
combination than Hawke and Keating.<br />
AITON: We've gone for nearly an hour and I think you've<br />
given me enough of your time. Thank you very much indeed.<br />
PM: As always, Doug, I've appreciated it very much. Thank<br />
a you. ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
