<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>15245</transcript-id>
    <title>theradio.com Weekly Message - Scouts Australia</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/05/2007</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...</p>
<p>  Listen to this Speech (MP3 -   1.39Mb - 90secs)</p>
<p>Good morning,</p>
<p>Scouts make an important contribution to Australian society by instilling positive social values in our young people and assisting many others in our community.</p>
<p>With about 60,000 Scouts across the country, and more than 2 million people who have been part of Australian scouting in the last 100 years, the Scouts have become the largest youth development organisation in the nation. </p>
<p>To mark the centenary of scouting in Australia and to further assist urban communities deal with the current severe water shortages the Commonwealth Government has decided to provide almost $18 million to Scouts Australia for the installation of rainwater tanks across the nation.  </p>
<p>This funding will help the scouts generate significant water savings and is another example of the Government's practical approach to Australia's water crisis.</p>
<p>Through a number of water programs, the Government is helping to conserve and better manage water at a grass roots level.</p>
<p>The Government's highly successful community water grants program - a $200 million component of the $2 billion water fund - has already funded projects that have saved 27,000 megalitres of water. That's about the average annual water use of 100,000 households.</p>
<p>The third funding round of the community water grants program has just been announced and I encourage all communities with good water saving plans to apply.</p>
<p>  Listen to this Speech (MP3 -   1.39Mb - 90secs)</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
