<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>22183</transcript-id>
    <title>Investments of $1 billion in Australia&#039;s water future  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/03/2006</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>On World Water Day it is important to remind ourselves of the challenge that all Australians have to ensure that our precious water resources are managed sustainably.</p>
<p>I am pleased to announce that the Australian Government has committed to supporting 28 water conservation projects across Australia involving initiatives worth over $1 billion with contributions from the Australian Government's Water Fund of $392 million.   Twelve of these projects have already been announced.  I am delighted to announce a further four projects today.  Further announcements will be made shortly.  Four projects in New South Wales worth $70 million will receive more than $17 million from the Australian Government's Water Smart Australia programme.</p>
<p>The Australian Government is providing $6.61 million as part of a total investment of $37.76 million to ensure sustainable future water supplies for the rapidly growing Gosford-Wyong and Hunter regions.  This will be achieved through the construction of a pipeline that will enable water transfers between the systems, making better use of these water resources.</p>
<p> The Australian Government will invest $7.39 million in a $22.16 million project which will result in 33 NSW Regional Water Utilities, coordinated by the Water Directorate, recovering up to 15 000 megalitres of water a year by better identifying, prioritising and undertaking on-ground work to reduce water leakage across council owned town water systems.</p>
<p>A $5.64 million stormwater harvesting project in the centre of Chatswood to reduce potable water consumption in the Civic Place development by 81 per cent, compared to standard practice, will be supported by an Australian Government grant of $1.88 million.  Stormwater discharge to local creeks and Middle Harbour will also be reduced by 14 per cent as a result of this project.</p>
<p> The Australian Government will also invest $1.5 million towards a $4.96 million project towards for the extension of a reclaimed effluent system for irrigation and non-potable household use around a housing estate in Albury.</p>
<p>  Funding will also support water conservation work at a nearby school and new systems to use reclaimed water from the Norske Skog Paper Mill outside Albury.  These measures will reduce water extracted by Albury City from the Murray River by seven per cent. The 900 megalitres per annum of water saved from this project will be transferred to the Living Murray Initiative.</p>
<p> In addition to funding for major water infrastructure and conservation projects, my Government has also recently announced funding of $61 million for 1750 community water projects under the Community Water Grants Programme.</p>
<p> Through these projects approximately 18 billion litres of water - equivalent to 18 000 Olympic swimming pools - will be saved across Australia.  These projects demonstrate that all Australians including local communities, local businesses and local government can play an important role in the efficient use and storage of our precious water resources.</p>
<p>Both the Water Smart Australia and Community Water Grants programmes are part of the $2 billion Australian Government Water Fund, an investment by the Australian Government in better water management for all Australians.</p>
<p>A further call for funding proposals under the Water Smart Australia programme is expected today and guidelines and further details can be obtained from the National Water Commission website at <a href="http://www.nwc.gov.au">www.nwc.gov.au</a></p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
