<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5179</transcript-id>
    <title>SUMMARY OF ABC&#039;S 12.30PM NEWS</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/10/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005179.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER-THURSDAY, 18 OCTOBER 1979<br />
From the Press Office<br />
SUMMARY OF ABC'S 12: 30 pm NEWS<br />
Full transcript of item:<br />
The Federal Government is not changing its position over<br />
amendments to industrial law. The Federal Minister for<br />
Industrial Relations, Mr. Tony Street, has issued a statement<br />
about his talks on the matter last night with the President<br />
of the Arbitration Commission, Sir John Moore. Mr. Street's<br />
statement said the Federal Government would make no changes<br />
to the Conciliation and Arbitration Amendment Bill. Mr. Street<br />
said he told Sir John Moore that the object of the consultative<br />
procedures was to get the maximum possible consistency in<br />
Commission decisions. Sir John had pointed out that the<br />
Consultative procedures could result in delays in getting<br />
decisions and asked whether the requirement to consult might be<br />
limited. Mr. Street said he replied that any qualification on<br />
the need to consult would obviously carry an increased risk<br />
of inconsis * tency and Sir John had acknowledged this point.<br />
The Minister said Sir John had told him of concern within the<br />
Arbitration Commission about the autonomy of the Commissioners<br />
and asked specifically whether the consultative proposals would<br />
enable a Deputy President to direct a Commissioner. Mr. Street<br />
said he assured Sir John that Commissioners retained the right<br />
to make a final decision on their cases. They would not be<br />
subject to direction by a Deputy President nor would their<br />
decision be subject to approval by a Deputy President. Sir John Moore<br />
had said the requirements would put an extra workload on the<br />
Commission and it would require more people if there-were not<br />
to be delays. Mr. Street said the Government would await advice<br />
from the President of the Arbitration Commission on the need for<br />
more people. Mr. Street has also rejected a request by the<br />
ACTU leader, Mr. Bob Hawke, for further talks on the amendments.<br />
Mr. Street said Mr. Hawke had contacted him seeking further<br />
consultation before the legislation passed through Parliament.<br />
Legislation will be introduced in the N. S. W. Parliament next<br />
week requiring all MPs to declare their pecuniary interests.<br />
In Parliament today, the Premier Mr. Wran announced that<br />
registers will be set up in both the Legislative Assembly and<br />
the Legislative Council, in which Members would have to record<br />
their financial interests and those of their spouses and<br />
dependent children. Failure to comply with the regulations<br />
would be regarded as contempt of Parliament, leaving Members<br />
open to expulsion.<br />
In a show of American military power, more than 2,000 Marines<br />
have begun a month of exercises at the U. S. military base in<br />
Cuba. The Air Force is gearing up for Australia's biggest military<br />
airlift since the Cyclone Tracy relief effort to Darwin. It is<br />
part of Kangaroo III, the military exercise in Queensland. </p>
<p>2<br />
South Korea's second biggest city has been put under<br />
emergency martial law after students took part in one of<br />
the biggest anti-government demonstrations in 19 years.<br />
The front line States confronting Zimbabwe Rhodesia have blamed<br />
Britain for the hold-up in the constitutional conference in<br />
London. The Presidents of Tanzania, Zambia, Botswana and<br />
Mozambique levelled the blame after a meeting. A statement<br />
said the Patriotic Front guerillas were correct in seeking<br />
assurances that money used to compensate white farmers who might<br />
lose their land in an independent Zimbabwe should not come from<br />
the pockets of the people there. It also said that while the<br />
Presidents were happy about-progress in the London talks<br />
no workable solution could possible emerge from negotiations<br />
which continued to exclude the Patriotic Front.<br />
A Federal Judge in Washington has ruled that President Carter<br />
had no authority on his own to end the mutual defence treaty<br />
with Taiwan. Judge Oliver Gash said the President, before<br />
breaking a defence treaty must gain approval from either two<br />
thirds of the Senate or a majority of both Houses of Congress.<br />
Two prominent East German dissidents have arrived in West Germany<br />
after their release from prison last week under an amnesty<br />
to mark East Germany's 30th anniversary.<br />
Japan cancelled more than 100 domestic air services today as a<br />
typhoon rolled across the Pacific towards Japan.<br />
Part of Australia's most famous fence is to be electrified.<br />
The Queensland Land Minister told State Parliament today he had<br />
approved a pilot scheme to electrify 68 kms of the main<br />
Dingo Barrier Fence which extends hundreds of kilometres<br />
across Queensland. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
