<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9803</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP SUPERANNUATION APPOINTMENT - THE HON CON SCIACCA, MP</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/10/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009803.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
SUPERANNUATION APPOINTMENT THE HON CON SCIACCA, MP<br />
I am delighted to announce, particularly while here in Queensland, that the<br />
Hon Con Sciacca MP, Minister for Veterans Affairs, is to take on the<br />
additional job of Minister Assisting the Treasurer for Superannuation.<br />
The comprehensive system of superannuation introduced in the last Budget<br />
will substantially lift national savings and improve financial security for<br />
individuals in retirement.<br />
These changes are far-reaching. It is, therefore, important that they are<br />
widely understood so that individual Australians appreciate more clearly how<br />
they will benefit.<br />
Con Sciacca's achievement in developing and promoting the Australia<br />
Remembers program, which reached its climax here in Brisbane in August<br />
this year, was outstanding.<br />
He has earned the thanks and respect of the Government, the Opposition,<br />
and all Australians, whatever their political persuasion, for his efforts in<br />
bringing our people together to commemorate the historic events of<br />
Australia's involvement in the Second World War.<br />
Con has the personal skills to do an outstanding job consulting with<br />
Australians and explaining the importance and value to them of the<br />
Government's superannuation policies. These skills will complement the<br />
established expertise of the Treasurer, Ralph Willis, and his Parliamentary<br />
Secretary, Paul Elliott.<br />
OCTOBER 1995<br />
Brisbane </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
