<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3910</transcript-id>
    <title>INTERVIEW WITH THE PRIME MINISTER BY CHANNEL 7 - BRISBANE, 4 OCTOBER 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/10/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003910.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
flNTERVI-, lW WITH THE P= IME= hSTER BY CY-AIN 7 -BRISBANE 4 OCTOBER 1975<br />
Q( JESIO: Mr hitlam, has the Senate any right to reject Supply?<br />
PM It's very dubious no Senate has ever refused Supply to the<br />
Government in the Australian Parliament, and this would<br />
not now happen anywhere in the world. It's not been<br />
possible, for instance, in Britain for the House of<br />
Lords to do this since 1911.<br />
QUESTION: Supposing they do force an election on these grounds?<br />
PIM : Oh, well when you say force an election, it is for me to<br />
advise the Governor-General whether there should be an<br />
election fLo--the House of Representatives or when he should<br />
ask the State Governors to issue writs for an election for<br />
half the Senate. That can be done at any time between<br />
now and the end of June when there has to be an election<br />
Kfor half the Senate. Or it's my job to advise the<br />
Governor-General whether there should be a double dissolution,<br />
an election for the whole of the Senate as well as the<br />
House of Representatives.<br />
,, JESTIOW: Nowi the Liberal, th olto seems to be basing its<br />
hopes on a double taxation system. Do you think that<br />
will catch votes?<br />
PM No, I think this will lose votes because don't -' believe<br />
that Australians want to go back to the ' system. '. which<br />
applied in Australia before the war, and which still<br />
applies in Cana'aa. This system where you have Federal<br />
income taxes, evarybody in Australia has to pay them,<br />
but on top of -t:-at the-people in each State have to pay an<br />
additional State income tax. And -in Canada still, and in<br />
K A ustralia before the war, this meant that the people<br />
paid diffe:: ent taxes in each State. For instance, the<br />
big States like New South Wales and Victoria paid a lower<br />
rate of State income tax; all the other States, including<br />
Queensland, pain a higher rate of State income tax. The only people<br />
who benefited were the people in Canberra, because they didn't<br />
have to pay State tax. So that's the reason why Sir Gordon<br />
Chalk, the Liberal leader here, the Treasurer, and people<br />
like Kevin Cairns, one of the Liberals MHR's from Queensland,<br />
have expressed such misgivings about this proposal to go<br />
back to double taxation. It's really a system of unequal<br />
taxation.<br />
QUESTION: Thank you Mr WNThitlam </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
