<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9550</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J.KEATING MP DOORSTOP, CAIRNS INTERNATIONAL HOTEL, TUESDAY, 18 APRIL 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/04/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009550.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL: 18. pr. 95 1: 23 No. 005 F. 01/ 0<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTERs THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
DOORSTOP, CAIRNS INTERNATIONAL HOTEL, TUESDAY, 1S APRIL 19115<br />
MWE PROOF COPY<br />
PM: When you are ready, I am basically here for you. You ask~ thte quva Ions<br />
and I'll answer them. I have a lunch to do, so we are not hema frevet, but<br />
well try to do our best for you.<br />
J ( Inaudible) Jobskille..<br />
PM Welt, what it is doing Is taking the long term unemployed who withouli this<br />
sort of program would be forgottn by society and giving them a useful role<br />
in our lives.-In work. In training and bringing those skills to the laowur<br />
market which are now becoming In short sup* t. And when skills g st in<br />
short supply, say In building, building costs rise and you become<br />
uncompettive. So, it is an efficient thing to do to get long iterm<br />
unemployed people back Into the labour market and, of course, it. is a<br />
humane and fair and decent thing to do as well. That Is, this Govern: nent<br />
has said, I said after thie election, we are not going to leave the<br />
unemployed behind. So. the Commonwealth labour market prog-arms<br />
provide a Jobs subsidy ariJ training to got those people back to work and<br />
that Is what we have seen today.<br />
J: -( inaudible) Mr Wiser, intent on damaging Carmen Lawrence.<br />
PM: Well, Mr Wilson said something today whiCh I thought was very reveliing.<br />
He said this issue Is not capable of resolution. He sai t wIllealways b-tiy<br />
word against othiers or others words against his. He admitted this "~ as a<br />
meoeting where no notes were taken by note takers. So, by Mr WIsons3<br />
own admission no inquiry can reveal more than his claim or C~ rmon<br />
Lawrence's counter-clim. And, I think, that is the point about this, it Ii. just<br />
one of those he-: kneyed political issues. The reewo It has been raiswd is<br />
to obscure the fadt that the Wvestern Australian Liberal Party is tiflaliy </p>
<p>TEL: 1 l. Hpr 5 1 : 23 NO.-005 F. 02/( l<br />
2<br />
divided. The Liberal Party is not a national party. It Is a collection of state<br />
parties, but whets It has a State Government In Western Australia which is<br />
Important to It Widmi11', fhe' ire hooelesi d~ v~ d~ d, Two of Mr Howard's<br />
supporters wore defeated last week that is Mr Rocher and Mr Filing two<br />
of Mr Howard's closest supporters were defeated. Can I Just say Mr<br />
Crichton-Browne still hasn't resigned as Acting President of the Senate.<br />
He Is still today Acting President of the Senate. me is still on the Saladie$<br />
and emoluments of the Acting Presidency of the Senate. So, it shows you<br />
the utter contempt he and the Western Australian Liberal Party hold for Mr<br />
Howard, that he still hasn't resigned.<br />
J: If Carmen Lawrence Is right, why are you not willing to call an inquiry?<br />
PM: But the question Is why for? You don't have inquiries for nothing. This Is<br />
essentially, I think, Mr Wilson's latest reference saying that he thinks this Is<br />
Incapable of resolution, It will always be his word against others. I just<br />
think the others have got a more credible case,<br />
J: Do you think there is some Justification for an Inquiry then?<br />
PM: No. Look, let me just say this. This Is all noise and no substance. Now,<br />
what the Liberals think Is, If they can have three or four days of noise,<br />
somehow that noise turns into substance. Noise, noise. Claim, claim.<br />
Newspaper headline, nespaper headline. It doesn't amount to anything<br />
unless there Is some substance. So, the substance here, why are they<br />
running with it? Because of the divisions In the Western Australian<br />
branch. Why Is that Important? Because unless they get them resolved<br />
they have got nil chance of winning the next federal electon. That Is the<br />
Issue here.<br />
J: Why not prove it by holding an Inquiry?<br />
PM: Well, there would be no point for an Inquiry. Why would the<br />
Commonwealth want to hold an Inquiry? This is a matter In the State of<br />
Western Australia, what is it to do with the Commonwealth? Nothing what<br />
so ever.<br />
J: So. do you think Mr Court should put his money where his mouth Is?<br />
PM: No, I think, Mr Court should basically, I mean Western Australians I think,<br />
are absolutely filled to the brim with Inquiries. The West Australian people<br />
have had enough of Inquiries. They had the Royal Commission running for<br />
years and I think no good is going to come from It. I mean, take the<br />
claimant. The claimant has said today, that Is Mr Wilson, this matter is<br />
incapsole of resolution. So, If he says it what is the point of any inquiry, </p>
<p>TEL: 18Hpr .95 1: 23 No. 005 P. 03,.<br />
3<br />
J: Are you confident the Government's wood chipping policy is adecluate.<br />
You are going to face a protest In just a moment?<br />
PM: Well, lot me just say here. The Government's environment credentials are,<br />
I think, more than adequate. I mean, for a start just take Cairns. This<br />
Government put away the Paintree Rainforest for posterity. It Is one of the<br />
great tourism assets of this city, of this region. In this lost Budget. we put<br />
money away for a $ 24 million scheme to buy beck the hole In the heart of<br />
the DaIntree. We hove given Douglas Shire the money to put the road<br />
through, a sealed road up to the Daintree. In the last year, we put away<br />
for posterity Shoalwater Say neaw Rockhampton. In the lest year Jervis<br />
Bay of t coast of NSW and we have also said that we are reserving 264<br />
coupes for further examination for a representative forest system. Last<br />
year It was 17 coupes. This year it Is 284 and I have said that we will be<br />
cutting the exports of wood chips down by 20 per cent a year from 6 million<br />
to 5 million to 4 million et cetera. And we have just succeeded In-getting<br />
Tasmania to sign for the first time, the National Forest Policy Statement.<br />
So, It Is only Labor that is going to have the solution to set up<br />
representative reserve systems under Regional Forest Agreements to look<br />
after the native forests of this country. it will take a while for that to got<br />
through, but peopl will understand that. The only party capable of<br />
deliveting on the environment Is the Federal Labor Party.<br />
J: Just with Jobskills, ACOSS has concerns you are going to be cutting back<br />
onl funding<br />
PM: Well, look, that is only a Budget question. Budget quastions are beat<br />
answered on lBudget night.<br />
J: You can't give any reassurances?<br />
PM: Well, the reassurance is I sWd at the election we will not leave the<br />
unemployed behind and we set up a $ 1.6 billion scheme called Working<br />
Nation to support them. And it Is that which we were doing here today.<br />
So, the proof of the pudding, I think, Is in the eating. Thank you.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
