<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3467</transcript-id>
    <title>RURAL LOCAL ROADS - 17 NOVEMBER 1974</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/11/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003467.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PiE i LL2A31E<br />
RURAL LOCAL ROADS<br />
During a visit to Redland Bay, the Prime Minister said<br />
he had been informed that the local Redland Shire Council had<br />
been forced to stop road work on Stradbroke Island by a delay<br />
in the allocation of funds provided by the Australian Government.<br />
To date this financial year, the Australian Government<br />
has provided $ 23.4 million to the Queensland Government for<br />
road construction and maintenance. This represents four months'<br />
allocation of the total amount to be provided to the Queensland<br />
Government for the 1974-75 year.<br />
Queensland has received its instalments in exactly the<br />
same way as the other States. There has been no delay on the<br />
Australian Government's part in the provision of those necessary<br />
funds. Of the $ 23.4 million provided, about $ 5 million has<br />
been for rural local roads. These funds are provided with no<br />
strings attached. How and when it is shared among local<br />
governments is the responsibility of the Queensland Government.<br />
If the Redland 0-hire Council, or any other shire council, has<br />
been starved of funds, it is fairly and squarely the fault of<br />
the Queensland Government.<br />
Mr WllTitlam said that the arbitrary bottleneck created<br />
by the Queensland Government meant a decline in the quality of<br />
rural services, and resulted in council staff being thrown out<br />
of work.<br />
17 November 1974 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
