<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4981</transcript-id>
    <title>PARLIAMENT HOSUE CONSTRUCTION AUTHORITY BILL 1979</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/03/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004981.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
A( STALA<br />
7PRIN1E MISTER<br />
FOR PES8 March 1979<br />
PAR. LIIA ENT HOUSE CONSTRUCTION<br />
AUTHORITY BILL 1979<br />
This bDill reflects in legislative form the proposals concerning<br />
the construction of the new Parliament House which were announced<br />
by me in November last year.<br />
Since that announcement the Government has taken a number of steps<br />
in order to get the project underway. The names of the persons<br />
who have been invited to form the new authority for ttie design<br />
and construction of the House have been announced and a number<br />
of preliminary meetings have taken place.<br />
The panel to assess the competition to select a designer<br />
for the new Parliament House has been chosen. A stage has now<br />
been reached where it will be possible to proceed with the<br />
competition. Before it proceeds, however, it is necessary<br />
to establish the authority which will control the design<br />
and construction of the new House.<br />
The purpose of this Bill is to establish it. It will be known<br />
as the Parliament House Construction Authority.<br />
Since 1927 the Parliament has operated in a building intended to<br />
accor. nodate it for a temporary period. The growth of the nation<br />
since 1927 has b-ra ught with it increased representation of<br />
the people and more complex functions of Government.<br />
As a result the temporary Parliament House has become<br />
increasingly unsatisfactory as a working place for Members and<br />
Senazors, the staff who service the Parliament and the support<br />
ser-vices required to operate from Parliament House.<br />
From 1955 to the present day successive Parliaments and<br />
successive Governments have considered the question of a<br />
new Parliament House. In 1965, a Joint Select Committee<br />
was appo nted. Its main recommendation was to proceed with<br />
the new and permanent Parliament House.<br />
To facilitace this it recommended the establishment of a<br />
itclient" committee which in due course resulted in the setting<br />
up of a Joint Standing Committee on the New and Permanent<br />
Parliament House. 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
For a considerable time agreement could not be reached<br />
on a site for that new building. This question was resolved<br />
in 1974 with the passage of the Parliament Act which declared<br />
that the new and permanent Parliament House will be on<br />
Capital Hill.<br />
Since 1975, successive Parliaments have appointed the<br />
Joint Standing Committee on the New and Permanent Parliament<br />
House and the Comnittee has undertaken the onerous task<br />
of preparing the users' brief for the building.<br />
With r. ne background of the several reports of the Joint<br />
Standing Committee, it has been decided that it is futile<br />
to proce. ed with short-term stop gap extensions to the<br />
existing building.<br />
As was announced by me in November last, the Government has<br />
accepted the advice of the Joint Standing Committee and<br />
has decided to proceed with the design and construction of<br />
a new Parliament House with a view to it being opened on<br />
Australia Day 26 January 1988.<br />
To give effect to this decision a powerful and competent<br />
authority will be established to undertake and carry out the<br />
design and cons. truction of the project. The authority will<br />
consist of a Chairman and five members.<br />
Five prominent Australian professionals and businessmen have<br />
already indicated their willingness to undertake the task.<br />
They are: Sir Bernard Callinan Chairman and a leading<br />
engineer; Sir John Overall an architect and formerly<br />
Comissioner of the Mr. R. Ling Chairman of<br />
Hill Industries Limited; Mr. N. MacPhillamy, lawyer and<br />
businessman, and Mr. L. Muir stockbroker and financier.<br />
The sixth member of the authority is the Commissioner of<br />
the currently Mr. A. Powell.<br />
The persons chosen to form the assessment panel are also men<br />
of great experience. They are Sir John Overall, Chairman,<br />
Mr. Jchn Andrews, architect of Sydney and Professor Len Stevens,<br />
engineer of Melbourne.<br />
The Parliament will be represented on the panel by Senator Gareth<br />
Evans and by the Member of McMillan, Mr. Barry Simon.<br />
One fu--rther assessor ( an architect) has to be chosen from<br />
overseas and it is hoped that this name will be announced shortly.<br />
The authority will be a body corporate and in carrying out<br />
its task will have access to the skills and expertise of<br />
officers of the National Capital Development Commission, other<br />
Commonwealth bodies and persons outside the Commonwealth Service.<br />
The authority will have an Executive Officer who will be<br />
appointed by the Governor-General.<br />
Provision is being made for the authority to engage specialist<br />
consultant services to supplement its resources as necessary.<br />
Appropriate statutory recognition is given to the fact that<br />
the Parliament is the client for the new Parliament House<br />
and the authority is required to have regard to any advice provided<br />
by the Joint Standing Committee on the New and Permanent Parliament<br />
House../ 3 </p>
<p>3<br />
That Cornittee will be the watchdog on behalf of the Parliament<br />
and continue the role it has played over the years in the<br />
develoDment of the architectural brief.<br />
A resolution amending the terms of reference of the Committee<br />
will be presented to both Houses when this Bill has been<br />
passed by the Parliament.<br />
The authority will of course be under the control of the<br />
Parliament and the Bill provides that the authority must<br />
compy with any resolution passed by both Houses of the<br />
Par1z_: ment in relation to the design or construction of<br />
the building.<br />
It a! so provides that the responsible Minister may give<br />
direz-ions to the authority on any matter of policy,<br />
but these must be tabled before both Houses and shall not<br />
become effective for a period of five sitting days during<br />
which time they may be disallowed.<br />
Provision is made for both Houses of the Parliament to pass<br />
a resolution in each House by way of authorisation of stages<br />
of the building proceeding.<br />
The authority will have paid to it, for its operations, such<br />
amounts as are appropriated by the Parliament for that<br />
purpose and the accounts of the authority will be subject to<br />
the scrutiny of the Auditor-General.<br />
I am confident that through this legislation the design and<br />
construction of the new Parliament House will proceed to<br />
completion in 1988.<br />
The work of the Joint Standing Committee and the nominated<br />
members of the authority, have already set the scene for<br />
an architectural competition to select a design.<br />
It is the expectation of the Government that the new Parliament<br />
House will be truly the crowning achievement within the<br />
Parliamentary triangle where already we have our great<br />
National Library and where the New National Gallery and High<br />
Court are already under construction.<br />
It . s appropriate that the new Parliament House should become<br />
the focus of the Bicentenary celebrations in 1988 as is the<br />
Government' s intention.<br />
The new Parliament House will be a place for the efficient<br />
conduc-of the Parliamentary affairs of the Commonwealth.<br />
It will be a symbol of the unity of all Australians.<br />
I conmend the Bill to the House. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
