<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9900</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE ACTING PRIME MINISTER, THE HON KIM BEAZLEY MP AMANDA VANSTONE AND DR GOEBBELS </title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/01/1996</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009900.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
7,; i<br />
ACTING PRIME MINISTER<br />
STATEMENT BY THE ACTING PRIME MINISTER, THE HON KIM BEAZLEY MP<br />
AMANDA VANSTONE AND DR GOEBBELS<br />
It might have been hoped that Senator Vanstone would realise that her vilification<br />
of the Prime Minister by an extended, pseudo-scientific comparison with Goebbels,<br />
the infamous Nazi propaganda chief, anti-Semite and mass murderer was a<br />
serious error of judgement. Instead, she has chosen today to repeat her<br />
disgraceful attack.<br />
Apart from its absurdity, Senator Vanstone's speech on Monday was deeply<br />
offensive to Australia's Jewish community because it had the effect of trivialising<br />
the unspeakable horrors of the Nazi era, She and apparently John Howard, who<br />
has endorsed her behaviour are unable to distinguish between the vigorous<br />
rough and tumble of Australian democratic life and the vicious, inhumane and<br />
genocidal politics of Nazi Germany.<br />
Nothing could more clearly underline how desperately out of touch with reality the<br />
Liberals are, or how profoundly oblivious they are to the sensitivities of<br />
Australians. Senator Vanstone's behaviour is the more reprehensible for being so<br />
far from the balance, moderation and judgement which people have the right to<br />
expect in a Shadow Attorney-General.<br />
Senator Vanstone's speech has deservedly brought condemnation from t Jewish<br />
community, which has asked her to acknowledge the offensiveness of her<br />
statements. Her response has been to repeat them.<br />
I call upon Senator Vanstone to apologise for the deep offence she has caused to<br />
all Australians and in particular to those who were victims of Nazi atrocities.<br />
I1 IJanuary 1996e </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
