<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>41645</transcript-id>
    <title>Australia-EU Trade Agreement</title>
    <prime-minister>Turnbull, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20150915 - 20180824</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/05/2018</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Turnbull Government welcomes the Council of the European Union agreeing to open negotiations for a landmark job creating Australia-EU trade agreement.</p>
<p>We look forward to welcoming EU Trade Commissioner Malmström to Australia next month to formally launch negotiations.</p>
<p>The Turnbull Government will seek an ambitious and comprehensive Free Trade Agreement (FTA) to drive Australian exports, economic growth and create new Australian jobs.</p>
<p>We will be working to secure better access for Australian food and agriculture products, creating the framework for open, fair and equitable trade.</p>
<p>The Liberal National Government will also be working to lock in better access for Australian services exporters; expand two-way investment flows; and deliver a more seamless business environment.  </p>
<p>We will explore rules and initiatives to support the digital economy and innovation, which are important for small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs).</p>
<p>An FTA with the EU has the potential to set the benchmark for what can be achieved between like-minded partners. Australia and the EU share a commitment to the rules-based global trading system and to open markets.</p>
<p>As a bloc, the EU is Australia’s second largest trading partner; third largest export destination; and second largest services export market. The EU was Australia’s largest source of foreign investment in 2017.</p>
<p>An FTA with the EU will open up a market for Australian goods and services of half a billion people and a GDP of US$17.1 trillion. It would potentially be Australia's biggest FTA once concluded</p>
<p>The Turnbull Government is pursuing Australia’s most ambitious trade agenda to open more markets, create a stronger economy and more Australian jobs.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
