<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1808</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH  BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR . JOHN GORTON</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/03/1968</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001808.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
HOBART JOURNALISTS' CLUB LUNCHEON<br />
HADLEYS HOTEL, HOBART March 1968<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister, Mr. John Gorton<br />
Mr. President, Ladies ana Gentlemen:<br />
It's nice for me to be able to be with the Journalists'<br />
Club at this midday gathering. It's nice to meet the exjournalists;<br />
it's nice to meet the wives; it's nice to meet<br />
the guests; it's nice to meet the journalists, particularly<br />
since one relies so much, in this situation which I somewhat<br />
unexpectedly find myself, on interpretations made by journalists<br />
whether they are writing directly for newspapers, whether they<br />
are writing columns I suppose that's directly with newspapers<br />
but every editor I know says it's indirectly; they haven't<br />
got any control over it or whether it's commenting, or whether<br />
it's on this new media, T. V. Because the opportunity for<br />
presentation of personality in the political scene on all sides,<br />
does, I think, give the public a chance to judge to judge<br />
between arguments advanced for this or for that, to judge<br />
between whether one believes what one is saying or is saying<br />
what one is saying because a consensus of Party opinion wants<br />
it to be done, to make an assessment and to present it to the<br />
public which then accepts or rejects the assessment so made.<br />
As far as I am concerned, the assessments that have<br />
been made whether they are pro or con are not assessments with<br />
which I have been able to find myself able to quarrel. If there<br />
have been in my association with journalists those who are<br />
critical, there has seemed to me that the criticism has been<br />
based on argument. I might not accept the argument, I might<br />
not accept the premise,, and therefore obviously I might not<br />
accept the conclusion. But it seems to me to have been based,<br />
at any rate in this brief period in which I have been so closely<br />
associated, on assessment by journalists, on argument by<br />
journalists, and not on prejudice by journalists. And this I<br />
think is very important.<br />
I suppose I can't talk to you today in the same way<br />
as someone could talk . was it the Gridiron Club the<br />
original Journalists' Club, the one in ' Washington where people<br />
went who were oither highly significant American politicians<br />
or visiting Heads of State and spoke off the record and thon<br />
had everything they said reported on the next day? I suppose<br />
this is quite different. But it is good to find, I think, and<br />
I have only so far found it perhaps because I haven't been asked,<br />
I have only so far found it in Canberra and found it here, that<br />
journalists would form this kind of association, would meet<br />
together for these luncheons, would have people come before<br />
them and talk to them and subject themselves to questioning by<br />
them. It may be that in-this assessment I have some nostalgia<br />
because I am a journalist manque myself. " When I first came<br />
back from England, as a very young man, I came back to be a<br />
journalist. But my father died before I was in Australia more<br />
than a couple of months and I had to take over a bankrupt<br />
property and try and build that up instead of being a journaliist,<br />
which is probably just as well because I expect I'd have been<br />
a sub-editor or something by this stage. I might not have had<br />
quite as much fun, although from all I have seen there is a<br />
certain amount of fun in this occupation anyway. 2 </p>
<p>I think that rather than talk to you on any specific<br />
subject of national importance, or state importance, that it<br />
would be better for me to subject myself to any questions which<br />
any of you here may wish to ask. I warn you I will answer them<br />
quite definitely if I think I've got an answer that I wvant to<br />
give and that it is satisfactory to me. If it is in an area<br />
where I am not quite sure of the answer, I will say I am not<br />
quite sure of the answer. If it is in an area where I think<br />
an answer at this stage ought not to be given, I'll do my best<br />
without you noticing, to answer it in such a way that I won't<br />
be giving an answer and you won't notice I'm not. But at least<br />
I'll be subjecting myself to something I know is of interest to<br />
those who are in this room and this I will do in just a matter<br />
of a very few minutes.<br />
I have spoken this morning at an opening of the<br />
Chambers of Commerce here and very briefly skctched in the<br />
choices which have to be made in a community such as ours the<br />
requirements of the community for defence, for social services,<br />
for education, for technological advances, for scientific<br />
advances, for development, for a million things rnnd also the<br />
requirement that a government should not so take from individuals<br />
so much in order to meet these requirements that the individuals<br />
just stop working and you can't meet any requirements. The<br />
balance I have spoken about there and some of you may have heard<br />
it, some of you may wvish to ask about it.<br />
Our role as a country in the international field, some<br />
of you may wish to ask about. The future which is possible for<br />
us, some of you may wish to ask about, because we are now and<br />
will be for the next two or three years in a period that I call<br />
for this nation the tantalising years. Soon, but not yet, we'll<br />
be reaping the benefit of the mineral discoveries we have made<br />
and we will be exporting in the way of nickel and of iron ore<br />
and of alumina, things which will put the wool industry on which<br />
we have previously almost entirely relied into a much lower area<br />
of importance in our national life. Soon we will be replacing<br />
those things which we have had to bring from abroad and oil<br />
is tho great example with oil from Australian resources and<br />
some of these things you may wish to ask about.<br />
We haven't got those benefits yet, we won't get them<br />
for a couple of years but they arc there), they are coming, they<br />
are beckoning, and for two tantalising years we must wait for<br />
those full benefits to come before we can get a great I don't<br />
like to use this word, because it is used by someone with whose<br />
political opinions I don't agree but the great leap forward<br />
which I think faces Australia; there will be advances but the<br />
great leap forward when these things come in. Now there it is.<br />
I am here to be questioned. I am here to the best of<br />
my ability to try and answer those things which are in your minds.<br />
And so may I ask you, having thanked you for this function,<br />
having thanked you for the opportunity to meet you, to put it<br />
now to the best advantage by cross-questioning me on those<br />
things which arc of interest to you.<br />
Q. With the current.-American elections coming up, if the President<br />
is ousted by either Eugene McCarthy or Robert Kennedy and radical<br />
changes in Vietnamese policy are made by the United States, will<br />
Australia~ make these changes as well? / 3 </p>
<p>PM. Well, if there were and this is an awfully what President<br />
Roosevelt always used to call an " iffy"' question, but if there<br />
were great changes in the United States involvement in Vietnam<br />
I think the Australian people would be forced to accept those<br />
changes. We cannot, as a nation of 12 million people, and a<br />
nation making, I think, a very significant contribution for<br />
its 12 million people, we cannot as a nation of 12 million<br />
people hope, of ourselves, to achieve a result without the full<br />
involvement of the United States and its other allies and if<br />
there were, as you have suggosted, there might be a bouleversement<br />
complete change in policies, then, since we could not, of<br />
ourselves, hope to achieve things by ourselves, I think we would<br />
have a decision forced upon us not to try to do things of<br />
ourselves.<br />
Q. Mr. Prime Minister, is it possible to ostablish a minimum<br />
standard of living in Australia and is it possible to work up<br />
machinery to make sure that nobody lives below that standard?<br />
PM. I think it is possible to establish a minimum standard of living.<br />
I don't think that there will ever be a time when there will not<br />
be arguments as to whether that minimum standard of living so<br />
established is high enough or there is no room for argument<br />
that that standard of living should not be improved. Indeed,<br />
I hope there never would be. I hope that in a developing<br />
community, such as we have been and will be, that there will<br />
be argument as to whether those on the lower standard of living,<br />
the minimum standard of living, should not be able to be provided<br />
by the community with something more. But yes, I think there<br />
could be a minimum. The argument would then be whether the<br />
minimum was enough or wasn't enough.<br />
Q. Mr. Prime Minister, on the matter of the 20uropean Common Market,<br />
do you in the future perhaps see an Eastern Common Market where<br />
we can raise our own tariff barriers say against Europe in our<br />
particular area?<br />
PM. Well, I would rather not touch on the matter of whether we raise<br />
tariff barriers against Europe-as such, because who knows what<br />
the future of Europe is going to be. Yes, there is an EEC now,<br />
but it doesn't cover all the countries of Europe. One wouldn't<br />
want to say " Yes, we'll raise tariff barriers against Europe",<br />
I think you would have to oxamine that country by country<br />
according to what they were doing in relation to our own desire<br />
to export and to their own involvement in the European Common<br />
Market. But what I would think was a possibility was this. If<br />
by our smallish efforts and they must be smallish ( always<br />
remember we are not a great power), but for our size significant,<br />
coupled with efforts of the United States, United Kingdom and,<br />
for that matter, the European powers, we could improve the<br />
economies of the Asian countries near to us and thereby improve<br />
the standard of living of the peoples of those countries near<br />
to us and thereby improve the demand for better things from those<br />
countries near to us, then we could, I would hope, see that in<br />
these areas the same kind of demand for our own products would<br />
arise as has arisen in Japan because the economy has gone up and<br />
the living standards have gone up and the demands have gone up.<br />
If we could do that in these densely populated areas of Indonesia,<br />
Malaysia, Singapore, the Philippines, Thailand these are the<br />
countries nearest to us but you can fill in the others further<br />
away then if that could happen, there would be an immense<br />
market for what we could produce and we would benefit ourselves<br />
by being able to sell from and buy from that market.<br />
In the last ton years, in our Japanese trade alone, ( the figures<br />
/ 4 </p>
<p>have gone out of my mind now) there has been an immense<br />
expansion in what we have been able to sell to the Japanese<br />
and what we have bought from them, to our mutual benefit with<br />
Japan. Now, with the other countries around, that same sort<br />
of thing could happen, it could bc to our common benefit.<br />
Q. On 2 February at a Canberra Press Conference, it was reported<br />
you said Australia would not increase the size of its Vietnam<br />
force. You are reported as saying that as far as you were<br />
concerned this was a permanent statement. But on 13 March in<br />
the House of Representatives in reply to a question about your<br />
previous statement, you opened the way for an increase in the<br />
number of Australian troops in Vietnam. Was this a change of<br />
policy; was it pressure from the United States which influenced<br />
you, or was it, as Mr. Connor, Labor, New South Wales, suggested<br />
in Parliament on Thursday night that " the back room boys got at<br />
you". What is your present policy on Vietnam?<br />
PD1. Well, I think that if I could answer that this way. First, it<br />
wasn't a change of policy and the back room boys hadn't got at<br />
me and it wasn't a result of any request from the United States.<br />
I was asked at the Press Conference to which you refer which<br />
was held at the time when the Tet Offensive was breaking out<br />
you remember, and people were pouring into the Vietnamese cities<br />
and so on, would this lead to an increase in the U. S. commitments<br />
in Australian commitments, and I said no, it wouldn't. And in<br />
the statement in the House to which you refer but which was not<br />
a full quotation because you left this bit out, I said yes. I<br />
said that and what I said stands. This was in the answer to the<br />
question in the House of Representatives. But I can't look years<br />
into the future. There may be completely unknown developments<br />
which no man in charge of the Government could bind himself to<br />
ignore, but I do not know what they could be and I think that<br />
we are, as a nation of 12 million people, with unknown requirements<br />
as yet to help in Singapore and to help in Malaysia, with known<br />
requirements for developments of our own nation, providing very<br />
significant assistance at the present level at which we are<br />
providing it and that seems to me to be the answer to your<br />
question.<br />
Q. Mr. Prime Minister, Sir Wilfred Kent Hughes has suggested that<br />
there ought to be censorship on views coming out of Vietnam.<br />
Now do you, Sir, personally support this view or does the Cabinet<br />
support this view?<br />
PM. WIell, the Cabinet hasn't discussed it and anything that I say<br />
to you would just be a matter of my own approach to it. But<br />
I would have thought that one should agree that when one's<br />
forces are engaged in war whether declared or undeclared, there<br />
ought to be some censorship, indeed I am not sure there isn't.<br />
But there ought to be some censorship, for example as to where<br />
one's forces are going to go,. where an operation is going to<br />
be carried out, how many troops are engaged in that operation,<br />
what sort of back-up there is. In other words, things which<br />
could be of use to an enemy commander whether guerilla or<br />
regular would not in any war of which either had been cognizant<br />
been allowed to be freely published and to that extent that<br />
sort of censorship I think really ought to be imposed although<br />
it doesn't seem to be imposed by most of the people up in<br />
Vietnam and they are not necessarily our o,. wn people. Well<br />
if you were to talk about censorship in that sense, I would<br />
say my predilection was towards it if it was able to be imposed<br />
by Australians.<br />
There are other areas of opinion to be reported where it's </p>
<p>not quite so clear, to me at any rate, that censorship ought<br />
to be put in, but my impression of' what Sir Wilfred Kent Hughes<br />
was talking about was more about reporting of troop movements,<br />
of operations which, if they were reported prematurely, could<br />
prejudice those operations and the lives of Australian troops,<br />
and I would have a predilection towards that kind of censorship<br />
if we could impose it.<br />
Q. Mr. Prime Minister, last year, largely we understood through<br />
the personal interest of your predecessor the late Mr. Holt,<br />
there was a national fitness campaign programme introduced<br />
through the Federal Government. Is it envisaged that this will<br />
continue under the present Cabinet?<br />
PM. Well, I haven't turned my mind to that but in my present state<br />
of physical health, it is probably time I did.<br />
Q. Mr. Prime Minister, how do you see the future of the National<br />
Shipping Lines? Do you see it going overseas? Do you see<br />
that Australia will be penalised if it doesn't?<br />
PM. Well this is a question of policy. Let me just say this in<br />
answer to you. I would think that that was a possibility<br />
that is the question of an Australian shipping line going<br />
overseas or getting some overseas link or something of that<br />
kind. It is a question of policy which ought not to be ruled<br />
out as a possibility.<br />
Q. Mr. Gorton, the Adelaide journalist, Ian Mackay, says that in<br />
Vietnam the Australians are killing wounded Vietcong. Now<br />
what are you doing to investigate this? Are you in a position<br />
to say whether or not it's true and how do you feel in general<br />
about these allegations against our troops?<br />
PM. well I'm not doing anything to investigate it myself and if it<br />
were brought to me on a third-hand report which I understand<br />
is the kind of report, I wouldn't undertake to even think of<br />
investigating it. What I feel about allegations against our<br />
Australian troops are these, having been an Australian troop:<br />
that there are some individuals who from time to time may do<br />
things which the Australian nation or the Army as a whole would<br />
not support and this has always been so in all wars. But I<br />
would have the greatest reluctance and repugnance to holding<br />
up a service to some kind of ( an investigation, legal investigation<br />
by a judge and people of that kind, where any allegations can<br />
be made by anybody without any backing, where headlines will<br />
naturally be given to those allegations and where if at some<br />
later stage those allegations are shown to be without any<br />
substance whatever, the damage to the Service and the morale<br />
of the Service will have already been done. Now that's my<br />
answer to you.<br />
Q. Mr. Prime Minister, are our external commitments, Vietnam's<br />
especially, hindering this great leap forward you spoke of<br />
for Australia?<br />
PM. Woll I think, taking together our defence commitments Vietnam<br />
is one, requirements for assistance from Singapore and Malaysia<br />
are others, our own need to maintain some defence capability<br />
ourselves inside our own country and this changing world are<br />
others nobody could say that the requirement to divert<br />
resources to those things did not mean that there were less<br />
resources to devote to other things. We have gone on for a<br />
long time in the past with an average annual expenditure on<br />
defence of around about $ 400 million, if my recollection is </p>
<p>right. All right, now it's risen to $ 1200 million. W1ith<br />
commitments already accepted it's likely to go up more, almost<br />
inescapably, but I hope not too much more. Now this is a mere<br />
matter of arithmetic, that if those resources are devoted to<br />
that end, then they are not available for many of the other<br />
things that we would like to see done in Australia and so I<br />
suppose to take the words you asked me, it is limiting advances,<br />
leap forwards in other fields. But on the other hand I think<br />
it could also be said that it is an insurance policy to see<br />
that such advances as are made may be maintained and may be<br />
permanent, just as in the case of an individual, the payment<br />
of a life insurance premium prevents him from getting more<br />
household goods or providing better education for his students<br />
but is something he thinks ought to be done for safety's sake,<br />
as I think this should be.<br />
Q. Mr. Gorton, the late Prime Minister, Mr. Holt, in the time of<br />
the Palestinian W! ar made an offer to the Arab refugees of a<br />
place-. in Australia. Since then there's been nothing about it.<br />
Now, I don't want to know whether they want to come here or not<br />
but is the present Government of a mind to allow people such<br />
as these into Australia?<br />
PM. I'm not quite sure, if you will forgive me, whether you stated<br />
the question quite accurately at the beginning. I didn't think<br />
the late Prime Minister, Mr. Holt, did say we will take Arab<br />
refugees into Australia period. I thought what he said was, if<br />
there was an international plan in which a whole lot of countries<br />
will involve themselves and they will all take some portion of<br />
these refugqos into their countries, then we would consider<br />
taking part in that plan. But as far as I know, there has been<br />
no such plan agreed to by other nations.<br />
Q. If there was a plan would you consider it?<br />
PM. If there was a plan I would consider it.<br />
Q. We are about to finish a trial period on daylight saving in<br />
Tasmania. I would like to hear your opinions on daylight saving<br />
and whether you would like to see it introduced into other States.<br />
PM. Well you know I haven't had enough time to talk to all the dairy<br />
farmers, and apple growers and I would rather wait until I had,<br />
before I expressed an opinion.<br />
Q. Mr. Prime Minister, I am wondering whether you feel there is<br />
sufficient communication between Government and the people in<br />
Australia through the press, television and radio, whether you<br />
feel that people are well enough informed about policies and<br />
practices of the Federal Governmcnt?<br />
PM. That's an extraordinarily interesting question and a hard one.<br />
We do our best tt as a Government we do our best to try and<br />
see that people are informed but of course as you would well<br />
realise, onc of the ways by which Government Departments do<br />
this is by handouts as to what it is that they are proposing<br />
to do and how wonderful it is that they are able to do it.<br />
These get regarded with some cynicism, I think, after a while<br />
by those to whom thce handouts are given. Perhaps more cynicism<br />
than they should be, but I think they do tend to be relegated<br />
to a spike instead of analysed to see whether there's anything<br />
in thern or not. How better things could be done to get this<br />
communication, I'm not sure. When I was a Minister and not a<br />
Prime Minister, my door was open always to journalists to come<br />
o/ 7 </p>
<p>7.<br />
in and question about handouts, to come in and question about<br />
things they had heard around the market place and were they<br />
true or weren't they true and all that kind of thing and this<br />
seems to me to be the best method of communication that can be<br />
devised other than interviews or interviews with press people<br />
or interviews with television people, And provided a Government<br />
can establish a reputation that what it says is designed to<br />
provide information and not to suppress information, then that<br />
kind of channel would be open. But it's not easy, partly from<br />
a Governmental Department point of view because if there's some<br />
kind of thing that they think could reflect criticism it is<br />
sought to be suppressed. It's not altogether easy from a<br />
Government's point of view vis-a-vis journalists because very<br />
often some journalists will seek to take something and twist<br />
it round a little bit and both ways tend to cause difficulties<br />
in communication. I'm not satisfiod that the best method of<br />
doing this has been arrived at. I am satisfied that we should<br />
both try to see that it is arrived at because it seems to me<br />
to be tho proper basis of a public judgment and a public<br />
judgment seems to me to be the proper basis of a democracy<br />
I mean a judgment on facts.<br />
Thank you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
