<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3850</transcript-id>
    <title>RECORDED MESSAGE FROM THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON EG WHITLAM QC MP, FOR THE WIRELESS INSTITUTE OF AUSTRALIA&#039;S 1975 REMEMBERANCE DAY CONTEST, 16 AUGUST 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/08/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Message</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003850.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
RECORDED PMESSGAE FROM THE PRiI" IE MINISTER.<br />
THE HON. I E. G, tlHITLAM, QC, MP.,<br />
FOR THE WIyI1RELESS INSTITUTE OF AUSTRALIA'S<br />
1975T-REMEMBERANCE DAY CONTEST<br />
16 AUGUST 1975<br />
I AM HONOURED BY YOUR INSTITUTE'S KIND<br />
INVITTATION TO DECLARE OPEN YOUR 1975: RE-PEMBERANCE DAY<br />
CON. TEST, IT IS RIGHT THAT WE SHOULD REMEMBER THE<br />
AMATEUR -RADIO OPERATORS WHO LAID DOWN THEIR LIVES FOR<br />
A us -PIRAL A'D U -IOi. Tl,,' Sf? iCtffY'<br />
THS OCCASION HAS TAUG,+ T ME. A. LITTLE MORE<br />
ABOUT YOUR USEFUL AND REMARKABLE HOBBY. PERHAPS THE<br />
-" HCz~ 3. A iiMER.' FOR. -SUCH A VARIED LEISUR-E.-<br />
A I1V-ITY, ' IUR ' C0TACTS
WOR D-, LI fDE As MATEUSS YO' HAVE BEEN EXPERI IMENTING<br />
FOR MANY YEARS WITH YOUR OWNllS ATELLITES AND COMMJ. NICATINGV.<br />
4TH-1 OTHER AATEURS AS FAR AFIELD AS AFRICA AND JAPAN.<br />
WITH THE NEXT GENERATION OF AMIATEUR SATELL. ITES YOU WILL<br />
BE AB-E TO CONTACT YOUR FRIENDS PIUCH FURTHE-R<br />
-AFIELD IIN THE US. A. AND ELSEWHERE. * 1<br />
t </p>
<p>2.<br />
IN THESE DAYS OF DEVELOPING COMMUNICATIONS<br />
AUSTRALIANS CAN PICK UP THEIR TELEPHONES AND HAVE<br />
DISCUSSIONS WITH PEOPLE AROUND THE GLOBE AT ANY TIME,<br />
BUT THE PROCESS IS EXPENSIVE, IT IS SURPRISING INDEED THAT YOU<br />
IN YOUR ' SHACKS' CAN TALK AT ALMOST NO COST WITH OLD<br />
FRIENDS AND MAKE NEW ONES ANYWHERE IN THE WORLD,<br />
YOU ARE TRULY PRIVATE AMBASSADORS-FOR AUSTRALIA AND<br />
I HAVE NO DOUBT THAT THE WORLD-WIDE NETOWRK OF AMATEUR<br />
RADIO COMMUNCATIONS MAKES A VALUABLE CONTRIBUTION TO<br />
INTERNATIONAL UNDERSTANDING.<br />
I COMMEND YOUR. WORK IN PROVIDING COMMUNICATIONS<br />
WITH STRICKEN AREAS AND YOUR ABILITY TO MOVE INTO<br />
ACTION QUICKLY WHEN A NATURAL EMERGENCY ARISES, MY<br />
COLLEAGUE, SENATOR BISHOP, THE POSTMASTER-GENERAL,<br />
ASSURES ME THAT EVERY POSSIBLE FACILITY IS GIVEN TO<br />
AMATEURS INVOLVED IN EMERGENCY TRAFFIC, I HOPE THE USE<br />
OF AMATEUR. SATELLITES FOR COMMUNICATIONS IN EMERGENCIES<br />
WILL: BE MORE FULLY EXPLOITED,<br />
AT PRESENT YOU HAVE TRAINING SCHEMES FOR YOUR.<br />
MEMBERS, PARTICULARLY IN YOUTH RADIO CLUBS, BUT I HOPE'<br />
YOU WILL TRY TO WIDEN YOUR EDUCATIONAL PROGRAMS AND BRING<br />
KNHOWLEDGE AiND EXPERIENCE OF YOUR EXCITING WORK TO THE<br />
W!. DEST POSSrBLE AUDIENCE, YOUNG PEOPLE TODAY, WITH THEIR<br />
NATURAL INTEREST IN SCIENTIFIC KNOWLEDGE AND ADVANCEMENT,<br />
WOULD-WANT TO KNOW MORE OF YOUR -WORK AND HOW THEY MAY<br />
PARTICIPATE IN IT. S,,/ 33 . </p>
<p>3,<br />
IHAVE MUCH PLEASURE IN DECLARING OPEN<br />
THE WNIRELESS INSTITUTE OF AUSTRALIA'S 1975 REMEIMBERANCE<br />
DAY CONTEST. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
