<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5106</transcript-id>
    <title>TELECOM</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/07/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Correspondence</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005106.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR MEDIA 12 JULY 1979<br />
TELECOM<br />
The Prime minister sent the following telex to Premiers<br />
this morning:<br />
" My dear Premier/ Chief Minister,<br />
I am writing to you because of my concern about the<br />
gravity of the situation that might exist throughout Australia<br />
if a continuation of the bans by the Australian Telecommunications<br />
Employees Association leads to a breakdown of the Telecom<br />
system. So far, problems have been principally confined to<br />
interstate communications. Further continuation of the bans,<br />
however, could lead to a degradation of local services.<br />
If other unions become involved, the entire system could be<br />
affected. If the bans continue many in the community could be put<br />
at risk. Some essential services such as the electricity and<br />
gas networks depend, to an extent, on Telecom services. Many<br />
individuals in the community depend on communications for their<br />
health, and in the extreme, their lives. I am thinking<br />
particularly of the old and the infirm, the very young and<br />
the handicapped. Without communications, the house-bound<br />
will be unable to call for medical assistance, fire services,<br />
and help of other kinds.<br />
The Commonwealth is giving careful thought to the ways<br />
in which assistance might be provided to those in the community<br />
who would be put at risk by the continuation of the bans.<br />
I assume that you are giving consideration to these matters.<br />
I should make it clear that we are not only thinking<br />
about plans to cope with emergencies that might arise,<br />
if the bans continue. The Commonwealth Government is working<br />
actively to ensure that good sense prevails and that'the<br />
relevant unions are persuaded to see that penalising<br />
the community in this way will not achieve their industrial<br />
objectives. No country can contemplate a situation in<br />
which essential services cannot be performed or are<br />
continually at risk. The community pays heavily for essential<br />
services and is entitled to see that they are provided.<br />
We shall do what we can both to ensure that essential<br />
services are provided and to ensure that any emergency is<br />
minimised. </p>
<p>2<br />
" I shall be in touch with you shortly about<br />
possible arrangements for co-ordination of Commonwealth,<br />
State, Local Government and community-based assistance,<br />
should the continuation of the bans make that necessary.<br />
Yours sincerely,<br />
MALCOLM FRASER."<br />
o00o---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
