<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6946</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR MEDIA 6 JUNE 1986</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/06/1986</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006946.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIMEST AINIE<br />
FOR MEDIA 6 JUNE 1986<br />
I am pleased to announce the launch of a competition to select a<br />
design for a memorial to the Australian Army. The establishment<br />
of the memorial in Anzac Parade, Canberra, has been approved by<br />
the Canberra National memorials Committee, of which I am<br />
Chairman. The memorial is to be completed in 1988 for an<br />
official unveiling as part of the Bicentennial celebrations.<br />
The National Capital Development Commission, which is conducting<br />
the competition on behalf of the Commonwealth Government, will<br />
invite suitably qualified Australian residents or Australian<br />
citizens abroad to register their interest in being considered<br />
for a limited two stage design competition.<br />
A panel of assessors will review the applicants and select up to<br />
entrants to submit preliminary design proposals. The<br />
assessors will then select up to five designs to progress to the<br />
second stage and to be developed as final proposals. The final<br />
entrant will be selected by the assessment panel from these<br />
designs and the design submitted to the Canberra National<br />
Memorials Committee for approval. Subject to the Committee's<br />
approval, the winning entrant will be commissioned to construct<br />
the memorial.<br />
The panel of assessors are:<br />
Mr M M B Latham, Comissioner, National Capital Development<br />
Commission Chairman;<br />
Mr P J Galvin, Secretary, Department of Arts, Heritage and<br />
Environment;<br />
General Sir Francis Hassett AC, KBE, CB, DSO, MVO, former<br />
Chief of the Defence Force Staff;<br />
Major General G J Fitzgerald, Chief of Personnel Army;<br />
Major General J M L Macdonald AO, MBE, RFD, ED, former<br />
Citizens Military Forces Member of the Military Board;<br />
Mr L Parr, AM, sculptor;<br />
Mr G Sturgeon, Director Artbank, Department of Arts, Heritage<br />
and Environment.<br />
The NCDC has prepared an information booklet for prospective<br />
entrants to the competition.<br />
The memorial will be a significant and enduring means by which<br />
Australians can honour the service and sacrifice to the nation of<br />
the Australian Army.<br />
The commission for the memorial will be a significant artistic<br />
opportunity, offering Australian artists a unique opportunity to<br />
design a major work for public display. The commission will be<br />
amongst the most valuable ever awarded in Australia. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
