<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7534</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW, BERT NEWTON SHOW - 20 MARCH 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/03/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007534.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW, BERT NEWTON SHOW 20 MARCH 1989<br />
E 0 E -PROOF ONLY<br />
NEWTON: Prime minister, welcome.<br />
PM: Thank you very much Bert. Good luck too.<br />
NEWTON: Thank you very much indeed. You're there in Sydney<br />
today and I guarantee you were there in Sydney on Saturday<br />
too, were you not, at the Golden Slipper?<br />
PM: I was indeed Bert.<br />
NEWTON: Did you stick with the Golden filly?<br />
PM: I did, and I tipped it and I backed it.<br />
NEWTON: Good on you because I thought last week you might<br />
have been a bit stiff actually. I thought you might have<br />
gone for the wrong Colin Hayes horse. Did you?<br />
PM: Yes, yes, but that was last week.<br />
NEWTON: That's right. Speaking of last week, we've just<br />
been talking to Peter Allen and he's had quite an horrendous<br />
couple of weeks and his attitude is just absolutely<br />
wonderful. A bloke like yourself, when you get a bad press,<br />
how do you handle it? Do you read it for a start?<br />
PM: Yes, it's no good in my job dodging the bad news. I<br />
try and face up to it and read it. If it's fair and<br />
constructive in what they've said, I hope to learn from it<br />
and I hope I'm intelligent enough to do that. If it's<br />
crook, if it's badly motivated and not fair, then I put that<br />
aside. You'd be very silly not to try and learn from<br />
criticism. NEWTON: What about the criticism at the moment that the<br />
financial state of the country is not as good as you<br />
promised it was going to be. Are you at all, do you believe<br />
on time with the plans that you a couple of years ago?<br />
PM: Yes. With just basic things we're ahead. The thing<br />
that I'm proudest of and which is going well is employment.<br />
We've created 1.3 million new jobs Bert in our period in<br />
office. That's four times faster than Howard and Fraser<br />
when they were in office, four times faster. We're creating<br />
jobs twice as fast as the rest of the industrialised world. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
PM ( cant): We're right on track there but it is true that<br />
we've got to have a tight monetary policy now and I think<br />
most Australians understand we just can't keep sucking in<br />
imports with too high a level of activity so we've got to<br />
cool it down a bit.<br />
NEWTON: Delivering those tax cuts in a couple of weeks<br />
time. Can the country afford it?<br />
PM: I believe so. We've had to ask ordinary Australians,<br />
your normal viewers, the lower to middle income Australians<br />
to exercise a lot of restraint which has enabled us to<br />
create all those jobs. I think the time has come when we've<br />
got to give something back so that they're able to gradually<br />
improve their standards. And we're going to do it.<br />
0 NEWTON: What about your promise, the one that comes back to<br />
visit you all the time about 1990 and not a starving child<br />
in Australia? Do you wish in some ways you hadn't said<br />
that? PM: Not at all. Do you think I should be unhappy about a<br />
situation where we've brought in a policy under which<br />
something like $ 1.5 billion will be spent on family<br />
allowance supplements to the lower income people in this<br />
country, which will mean by the end of this year as we go<br />
into 1990 that we'll deliver on the real pledge I delivered,<br />
that is that there'll be no financial need for any child to<br />
live in poverty. I've never been able to this is not a<br />
dictatorship, I can't dictate that no parents will behave<br />
awfully which will lead kids to run away from home. But<br />
what I can deliver on is the promise I made and that is that<br />
the money will be there so that there'll be no financial<br />
need to live in poverty. What we've done Bert is bigger<br />
than has ever been contemplated before in this country,<br />
hasn't been attempted in any country anywhere in the world.<br />
That sort of money that we'll be putting out to the lower<br />
income people in this country will mean that we will have<br />
delivered on the pledge that there'll be no financial need.<br />
Now, as I say, we don't run a dictatorship. I can't control<br />
every domestic situation in this country, I never believed I<br />
could. But what I can do is to make sure that as far as<br />
what government does, a concerned and compassionate and<br />
caring government, that the money will be there, that<br />
there'll be no financial need for poverty for kids.<br />
NEWTON: I don't know if you realise or not, your supporters<br />
of course would declare that you've created many firsts<br />
since you've been in government, since you've been our Prime<br />
minister. But do you realise that you're about to become<br />
the Prime Minister in Australian history with the most<br />
grandchildren? PM: Is that right?<br />
NEWTON: You've got six coming up haven't you, number six? </p>
<p>-3-<br />
PM: The sixth is coming up.<br />
NEWTON: Whose is that?<br />
PM: Sue's. She's been around with us this weekend at<br />
Kirribilli and she's very close, very close. That will make<br />
six, yes. We started with none when I was Prime Minister.<br />
It's been a very prolific prime ministership.<br />
NEWTON: I think it's been one for every year.<br />
PM: That's how it's worked out, yes.<br />
NEWTON: So whilst you've been busy as Prime Minister, the<br />
family obviously has been busy too.<br />
PM: They are the joy of my life too Bert.<br />
NEWTON: I'm told that one of your great pleasures when<br />
you're with them is to tell them stories. Now a lot of joke<br />
writers would make a lot of that. What sort of stories do<br />
you tell them?<br />
PM: I try, when I sort of make up stories, really what I<br />
try and talk about is stories about people so that they have<br />
no concept of prejudice in their minds at all about colour,<br />
of people of difference races and origins. I try and talk<br />
to them in ways which makes them understand that we're all<br />
in the end in this world brothers and sisters, we are. I<br />
think you can't get that story into the minds of little<br />
children too early. I think it's a lesson we all have got<br />
to understand and some of we adults haven't learnt it<br />
properly I'm afraid.<br />
NEWTON: Some people in the public life seem to treat their<br />
grandchildren as they wanted to treat their children because<br />
of the value of time that wasn't able to be given to the<br />
kids. Are you in that boat?<br />
PM: Absolutely. I feel some sense, I mean I'm quite honest<br />
about it, I feel some sense of guilt about the fact that in<br />
the pursuit of my career in the trade union movement and<br />
then later on and always with politics intertwined that I<br />
didn't spend the time that I think I should've done in<br />
hindsight. So there is a sense in which I think you<br />
compensate, or try to compensate a bit. You can never make<br />
up for what you should've done with your own children but<br />
that's consciously and subconsciously I think part of it.<br />
But kids are just beautiful anyway, and grandchildren,<br />
there's something special about them.<br />
NEWTON: Just finally, how do you feel about the press<br />
releasing the story on Hazel and her facelift? </p>
<p>PM: I was quite relaxed about that. But let me say in<br />
regard to the vicious, untrue piece in yesterday's Sunday<br />
press, viciously untrue, that Hazel did this under pressure<br />
from the Party. There is not a skerrik of the beginning of<br />
an element of truth in that. It is false, it is malicious<br />
and I can assure you that those who've written that have not<br />
heard the end of it.<br />
NEWTON: Have you every considered you know what?<br />
PM: No, no,. face, I'm happy enough with it mate.<br />
NEWTON: I can only speak on hair transplants and it's quite<br />
PM: it just keeps growing faster and faster. I haven't<br />
had any trouble with it.<br />
NEWTON: You're doing ok. Thanks for your time. I really<br />
appreciate it.<br />
PM: I've loved being on and may I say to you, really, I<br />
wish you the very very best indeed.<br />
NEWTON: Good luck to you.<br />
PM: Thanks mate.<br />
NEWTON: Thank you.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
