<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5494</transcript-id>
    <title>AN ELECTORATE TALK TO RADIO 3HA HAMILTON, BY THE MINISTER FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRS, THE HON AA STREET</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/12/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005494.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
,7 a-<br />
6 December 1980<br />
An Electorate Talk to Radio 3HA Hamilton, by the<br />
Minister for Foreign Affairs, the Hon. A. A. Street<br />
The Australian Government is closely following developments<br />
in and around Poland. we are aware of the very widespread<br />
international concern about the trend of events in that<br />
country and about the possible reaction to them by the<br />
Soviet Union. As I told the Parliament on Tuesday, this<br />
concern has led to clear warnings being given to the Soviet-<br />
Union. Since my remarks to the Parliament, the Heads of<br />
Government of the European Community,, the President of the<br />
United States and the President-elect, Mr. Reagan, have all<br />
given very clear warnings to the Soviet Union that it should<br />
not intervene. If the Soviet Union did intervene with force<br />
we and our Western partners have no doubt that very serious<br />
consequences would-arise for East/ West relations, for<br />
US/ Soviet relations, and for the wide range of interdependent<br />
cooperation that exists, particularly in Europe.<br />
Given ' the Soviet Union's record of behaviour in such matters,<br />
most recently of course in relation to Afghanistan, it is not<br />
surprising that there should be widespread apprehension about<br />
the situation in Poland. I cannot say whether or not Soviet<br />
intervention in Poland is imminent or indeed inevitable. All<br />
I -can do, as I did in-the Parliament, is express-in the<br />
strongest possible terms my hope that it does not. At the<br />
same time, however, we would be unwise to ignore that<br />
ominous possibility.<br />
We in Australia do not accept that the Soviet'-Union has an<br />
automatic right to intervene in any country whether or not.<br />
-it considers that country to be in its sphere of influence.<br />
This point has been brought home to, the. SovietGovernment,<br />
Against thi Is background, I asked the Secretary of the Department<br />
of Foreign Affairs to bring to the attention of the Soviet<br />
Ambassador and through him to the authorities in Moscow.<br />
Australia's concern about the current situation. We did thiLs so<br />
that the Soviet authorities would be in no doubt about what<br />
might be at stake for the international community and. for Australia,<br />
Australia would not be immune from the consequences which would<br />
flow from a Soviet intervention. No country would be. The<br />
Soviet Amibassador was informed of our views on 3 December.<br />
As for Poland itself, we firmaly believe that it is for<br />
the people of Poland to solve the current difficulties<br />
themselves. In the present circumstances I can appreciate<br />
and sympathise with the understandable concerns of the<br />
large community of Polish born people in Australia.<br />
* We are hopeful that'Poland will be able to overcome its present<br />
difficulties in keeping with its great tradition of<br />
independence. Australia has sound relations with Poland.<br />
We value those relations and we look forward to developing<br />
them. It is for these reasons that Australia has made its<br />
position abundantly clear to the Soviet Union in the same<br />
way that many ' of our Western partners have. We shall continue<br />
to watch developments in Poland very closely. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
