<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8847</transcript-id>
    <title>OPENING OF PARLIAMENT</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/04/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008847.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER 51/ 93<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
OPENING OF PARLIAIENT<br />
I have received a letter this week from the Leader of the Opposition, Dr. Hcwczn,<br />
rejecting the Government's proposed modernisation of the ceremonial opn ing f the 37th<br />
Parliament on May 4.<br />
I find it disappointing that Dr Hcwson, who sought to make the reform of Parliament an<br />
election issue, should mulishly resist such a sensible reform proposal so early in the new<br />
Parliamentary term.<br />
Some of the existing procedures in the ceremonial opening arc unnecessarily time<br />
consuming. For example, Members of the House of Representatives arc required to move<br />
from their chamber three times in the course of the day, twice to the Senate and once to<br />
the Members' 11all.<br />
The Government's proposal that the Governor-Gcncral's Speech be delivered in the G. t<br />
-lallrcduced the amount of traipsing through the building but, more importantly, would<br />
provide a better reflection of the Constitutional equality of the two houses in our system,<br />
and cmphasise the unity of Parliament. The Government believed all Members and<br />
Senators would want the opening ceremony of Parliament to be seen as relevant, modem<br />
and meaningful to all Australians.<br />
But the Government has more to do than spend its time coaxing the Opposition into the<br />
late 20th Century. Whatever the importance of ceremonial arrangements, the Government<br />
is dctermined that they will not interfere with the real business of the nation, so therefore<br />
the ccrcnony will go ahead as before.<br />
Contrary to Dr Hewson's asqertion in his letter, the proposed changes were hardly " the<br />
result of somc last minute initiative." </p>
<p>I remind Dr llewson that he was a member of the Opposition in March 11988 when it<br />
supported a motion of the House calling for thc opening and the Covcrnor-Gcncral's<br />
speech to be mnoved from the Senate.<br />
Thc Opposition also participated in, and agreed with, the recommendations of the House<br />
of Representatives procedure committee report in June 1991 on which the proposed<br />
changes arc closely based.<br />
It was always intended that the Great Hall in the new Parliament House should be used for<br />
important ceremonial occasions. It was thc for-um for the official opening of the building<br />
by Her Majesty Queen Flizabcth in 1988.<br />
According to Dr Hcwson, thc Opposition is not opposed in principle to sensible and<br />
responsible changes to the cxisting arranigements for the opening of Parliament. The<br />
Government intends, therefore, to provide an early opportunity for thc Opposition to<br />
exprcss such support by moving a motion in each chamber to amend standing orders to<br />
allow the opening ceremony to take placc in the Great Hall for the 3Uth Parliament and<br />
beyond. The point of all this is that at thc first hurdle of Parliamentary reform Dr Hewson and his<br />
Opposition have baulked.<br />
CANBERRA<br />
21 April, 1993 </p>
<p>Leader of the Opposition<br />
2 0 APR 1993<br />
The lion P J Keasting MP<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Parliament House<br />
CANBERRA ACT 2600<br />
Dear Prime Minister<br />
I understand that your Office contacted mine on 15 April 1993 to<br />
advise that the Government is reviewing arrangements for the<br />
Opening of Parliament on 4 May and to seek * greement to changes<br />
which would include the location for delivery of the Governor-<br />
General's speech.<br />
Z wish to n.' te at the outset that I regard the way in which the<br />
Government has consulted with the Opposition on this issue to<br />
have been quite inadequate and inappropriate. in view of the<br />
significance of some of the proposed changes, the appropriate<br />
channel for preliminary communications about possible changes to<br />
the Opening of Parliament is directly between you and me ( rather<br />
than at staff level between our offices), and the proper forum<br />
for consideration of any proposed changes is the Parliament<br />
itself. I should also add that I regard the briefing paper titled<br />
" Opening of Parliament" which your Office provided to be a quite<br />
misleading, incomplete and inappropriate account of existing<br />
procedures for the Opening of parliament and an inadequate basis<br />
for the changes proposed.<br />
The GovernmSnt's handling of this issua gives every sign of undue<br />
haste. There has been inadequate provision uf opportunity for<br />
proper and effective consultation. And the case for the changes<br />
proposed has not been made out.<br />
Accordingly, the Opposition does not agree at this time to the<br />
changes in arrangements for the Opening of Parliament which were<br />
conveyed by your Office last week,<br />
Parliamrnnt Hous,., Canberra, A. CT 2600Phone 27" 4022 </p>
<p>2.<br />
I want to make, it clear, however, that the Opposition is not<br />
Opposed# in principle, to changes in existing arrangements for<br />
the Opening of Parliament what* ouch changes are Sensible and<br />
responsible, But we are opposed to changes that are the result<br />
of somes last minute initiative, Or that are not fully Considered<br />
and approved by the Parliament, or that seek to break with<br />
Parliamentary tradition for the sake of it, or that are somehow<br />
meant to symbolise, or foreshadow, some broaer constitutional<br />
change. The fav. t 13 that the Opening of Parliament Is a Parliamentary<br />
occasion and not a matter for the Government alone to change,<br />
Change should only be made with the agreement of both the Senate<br />
and the House of Representatives and only after there has been<br />
adequate opportunity for changes to be fully considered anid<br />
debated in bo~ th Houses. To im! pOaa change through other means<br />
would be an abuse of Executive power.<br />
An I have indicated, the Opposition is not opposed, in principle,<br />
to changes in the procedural arrangements for the Opening of<br />
Parliament where those changes are responsitble and appropriate,<br />
and where the proper processen are observed. Accordingly, the<br />
Opposition woul1d support a Joint Commnittee of the ParlIanent<br />
addressing in a proper way existing procedural aztrangements for<br />
the Opening of Parliament. We believe that, before the<br />
poaibility of any proposals for ehange going torward to the<br />
Parliament f or del iberati~ on I detailed and e f fective Consideration<br />
of this kind is the only appropriate courso of action.<br />
Yours sincerely -JvvC4 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
