<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>413</transcript-id>
    <title>BROADCAST BY THE PRIME MINISTER ( THE RT. HON. R.G MENZIES ) OVER NATIONAL STATIONS AT 6 P.M. WEDNESDAY. DECEMBER 6. 1961</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/12/1961</release-date>
    <release-type>Broadcast</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000413_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FINAL BROADCAST.<br />
BROADCAST BY THE PRIME MINISTER ( THE RT. HON. R. G. MNZIES)<br />
OVERNATIONAL STATIONS AT 8 Dm0<br />
WEDNESDAY. DECEMBER 6~~<br />
In a very remarkablo series of meetings and in my previous<br />
broadcasts, I have dwelt upon thn great national tasks in hand, the<br />
wonderful growth of the last decade, and the immense prospects for<br />
the future, provided we adhere to the policies that are serving<br />
our country so well0<br />
In this final broadcast, p. most at the end of the<br />
campaign, I want to put to you some of the elements which should<br />
determine your vote.<br />
Our opponents, by common consent the maost unimpressive<br />
and divided. Opposition ever to sit in the Commaonwealth Parliament<br />
even our recently converted newspapers critics have always<br />
conceded this! are asking you to vote out of office myself and<br />
my oxperionced and loyal band of i 1inisters, and hand over to them<br />
the government of Australia for all purposes local and international.<br />
It is your choice, and I know that you will make it with<br />
the true interests of our country at heart.<br />
The only way in which you can express your choice is by<br />
your vote in your particular House of Representatives seat, and<br />
your vote for the Sonate. if, for some reason you vote for a<br />
Labour candidate on personal grounds, though you support the<br />
Government in general, you are voting to put the Government out.<br />
Think that over*<br />
In making your choice*, I suggest that you look first at<br />
Australia's position in the world, at our relations with other<br />
countries, and at what your present government has done about<br />
these matters, Our policy and record are quite clear. While loyally<br />
observing our duty to the United Nations, and playing a substantial<br />
part in Colombo Plan aid and in the civilised development of<br />
Papua and New Guinea, we have sought to assure the safety of<br />
Australia by developing treaty agreements with the great democratic<br />
powers and by bringing our own defences to a modern and efficient<br />
condition not previously equalled in time of peace. Our relations<br />
with the U. S. A. have become close and intimate. In both London<br />
and Washington, our views are constantly sought and offered.<br />
Australia's standing in significant quarters overseas is both<br />
high and useful. Would you trust Labour to imnprove this state<br />
of affairs? Or will Labour's position be as ambiguous in office<br />
as it has been in opposition?<br />
We are not a neutral or unaligned government. We know<br />
what side we are on, and have always recognised that if we are to<br />
look for help and protection to great powers, we must accept<br />
mutual obligations. But in the present Labour Opposition there are<br />
influential members and aspiring Il1inisters who are deeply tainted<br />
by neutralism, uncritical of the Communist aggressors, sometimes<br />
their apologists, constantly critical of our allies, by no means<br />
favourable to SEATO and ANZUS.<br />
I want to tell you, with great gravity, that I believe<br />
it would be a disaster for Australia's relations with the free<br />
world to be handed over to the present Labo-ur Party.<br />
Let me illustrate by saying something about the<br />
position of Commnunist China. It is well-known that any diplomatij;<br />
recognition of that aggressive country, or any movement to instal<br />
it in the United Nations would be unacceptable to the Communists<br />
unless it conceded China's claim to Formosa, Yet our Labour </p>
<p>opponents have regularly, in Parliament, advocated the recognition<br />
of Red China, knowing that this would involve recognising its<br />
right to take over the anti-Communist nation of Formosa! The<br />
adoption off such a policy would, of course, damage our relations<br />
with the U. S. A. Worse still, it would give a diplomatic victory<br />
to China which wculd gravely weaken SEATO, encourage Chinese<br />
aggression in South-East Asia, and discourage res~ btance to<br />
Communism in those Asian nations which are our nearest neighbours.<br />
Are you going to vote for this?<br />
Turn back home, to this happy and prosperous land.<br />
Mr. Calwell is, as usual he has done it before every<br />
election making great play of unemployment, which he appe~ ars to<br />
want me to make the dominant, if not the sole issue in this election,:<br />
I have refulied to play his game for him. That there is, in total<br />
terms, some small degree of current unemployment is true, The<br />
special financial provisions we have made for housing and State<br />
works are already producing a marked improvements The great<br />
national works in various States to which we have already agreed<br />
to make massive Commonwealth contribution will undoubtedly lead<br />
to further employment. In his policy speech, Mr. Calwell promises<br />
" to restore full employment within 12 months" t. Without any of his<br />
grossly inflationary policy, we expect the same position to be<br />
achieved under our administration,<br />
We do not forget that the over-all statistical position<br />
of employment, so much better here than in the U. S. A. and Canada,<br />
provides no comfort to the willing and competent man who is at<br />
present without a job.. We want to see him in a job as soon as<br />
possible. Meanwhile, we have made a great improvement in<br />
Unemployment Benefits<br />
The conditions for obtaining it are today precisely<br />
those laid down and operated by the Government in which Mr. Calwell<br />
served. The one difference is in the amount paid.<br />
Under Labour, in 1949. the Basic Wage was Z699.0 por<br />
week. For an unemployed man with a wife and child, the<br />
unemployment benef'it was Z2.10.0 a week, or a little over<br />
of the Basic Wage.<br />
Under us, in 1961, the Basic Wage is œ C14.8. O per week.<br />
For an unemployed man with a wife and child, the<br />
unemployment benefit is œ 7 per week, or just under half of the<br />
Basic Wage. Yet we are told that we are indifferent to the plight<br />
of the unemployed., But I will go further. The Labour Policy, if cai'ried<br />
out will increase unemployment. My reasons for this statement<br />
can be shortly stated.<br />
Labour's programme will add hundreds of millions to the<br />
already steadily rising Commonwealth expenditure. I understand<br />
that Mr. Calwell says " no increased taxation". What then, is he<br />
going to use for money, unless he forces upon the Reserve Bank<br />
the creation of vast sums of new money, not matched by new<br />
production., The effect of this can be imagined. Inflation<br />
would gallop. Costs would rise rapidly, The export industries,<br />
which cannot pass on inflated costs, and upon whose solvency<br />
Australia's solvency largely depends, would suffer. Labour's<br />
proposal to restore automatic quarterly adjustments of wages<br />
would accelerate the process. These things would inevitably<br />
lead, in the absence of strong corrective measures, to loss of<br />
confidence, collapse and unemployment. </p>
<p>But the truth is if Labour wants to spend real money,<br />
created by productive effort, it must, to honour its proi-ised<br />
expenditures, increase taxation veir much. What would be the<br />
effect of this on savings, industrial investment, and employment?<br />
But the whole story is not yet told. One of the<br />
reasons for record high eimployment in Australia over our term of<br />
office is the high degree of indtlstrial peace and therefore<br />
continuity of production thait nave beer maintained. A gr~ e;<br />
contributor to this has been our legislation to help to get rid<br />
of Communist influence in key unions. The Secret Ballot<br />
legislation, which Labour opposed in Parliament, and which<br />
Labour is under direction to repeal, provides that a substantial<br />
group of union members can apply for a court-conducted secret<br />
ballot for union office. This was designed to gez rid of the<br />
stand-over tactics of Communist minorities. It has had a great<br />
deal of su -ess, and would have had much more but for the<br />
discouraging attitude of the and its feeble treatment of<br />
Unity Tickets. Labour's policy uo repeal it would give great<br />
pleasure and encouragement to Communist leaders, and would jsher<br />
in a period of Comranist-promoted industrial disorder. Has<br />
Mr. Calwell forgotten that in 1949, when he was a Minister, a<br />
Communist-led coal strike did such damage that 118,000 people<br />
the highest number ever were on umremployment benefit?<br />
But on top of all this, Labour, again yielding to a<br />
Communist uampaign which, as you all know, has been going on for<br />
years, has promised to repeal the laws providing for penalties<br />
for industrial offonces. Such a repeal would be a direct<br />
incitement to strikes and lock-outs. Over-all production would<br />
fall, and employment with it,<br />
I have time to deal with just one more element.<br />
Great industries, and employment for many scores of thousands of<br />
Australians, have over these years been provided by the industrial<br />
investment in Australia of hundreds of millions of pounds and<br />
much technical skill from outside, chiefly from the U. K. and the<br />
U. S. A. Labour is very critical of such investment, and will<br />
discourage it. Yet without this much-needed capital a large<br />
country like Australia, with a relatively small population,<br />
cannot be rapidly and adequately developed. The political<br />
and economic climate which has attracted investors to come here<br />
has taken years to establish. It can be destroyed over-night,<br />
with growing unemployment th_ inevitable consequence.<br />
In short, Labour's so-called attractive policy of gifts<br />
all round is both dangerous and deceptive. It is dangerous<br />
because it will create the very evils which Mr. Calwell wrongly<br />
charges to us. It is deceptive because you, who are offered the<br />
gifts, will in one way or another, pay for all of them yourselves.<br />
Our continuing policy, the notable results of which<br />
you have seen and appreciated for a decade, is not, I hope and<br />
believe, lightly to be abandoned by you. If you want it to go<br />
on; if you want to be represented in the councils of the world<br />
and in the Common Market negotiations of which I have had much to<br />
say during the campaign, by your present experienced leaders; if<br />
you want the credit of Australia to continue to stand high; if<br />
you want the outside world to go on regarding Australia as one<br />
of the most attractive countries in the world, building, growing,<br />
full of opportunity for people of enterprise, you will vote for<br />
the Government in both Houses, Senate and Representatives, and<br />
send us once more to our great tasks, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
