<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1095</transcript-id>
    <title>FEDERAL COUNCIL OF THE LIBERAL PARTY OF AUSTRALIA HELD AT HOTEL CANBERRA, CANBERRA - 12TH APRIL 1965 - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/04/1965</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001095_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FEDERAL COUNCIL OF THE LIBERAL PARTY OF AUSTRALIA<br />
HELD AT HOTEL CANBERRA. CANBERRA 12TH APRIL, 1965<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister, the Rt. Hon. Sir Robert Menzies<br />
We are twenty-one today and we have the key of the<br />
door. That's something we ought to remember, politically.<br />
We have indeed been either fortunate or wise, or a-mixture of<br />
both because one of the outstanding things about this party,<br />
twenty-one years old, is that it has secured the support in<br />
Australia, I am quite convinced, of the young and ardent who are<br />
ambitious and self-reliant. ( Hear, hear) That, I think is a<br />
pretty good thing to be able to say and a better thing If we<br />
maintain its truth. We attract the young and the ardent with<br />
ambition and self-reliance. It is worthwhile recalling every<br />
now and then that Australia would not have made the enormous<br />
advances it has made if it had been a communitrof people with<br />
dependent minds. The fact that Australia has grown as it has<br />
demonstrates that we have people of independent minds who aim<br />
to be contributors as well as beneficiaries.<br />
I think when I have said that I have probably said<br />
what is at the very heart of our own approach, of our philosophy<br />
and, as I will set out to prove to you, of' our practice.<br />
Now I know that if the leader of a party and if the<br />
leader of a government in particular talks about what has<br />
happened, he is told that hie is living on the past, I have no<br />
desire to live on the past. I have no particular desire to<br />
live in the past, but I think that it is worthwhile recalling<br />
a few things because they may explain to us everyone of us,<br />
' why we have had this remarkable success, politically, and the<br />
reasons for what we must do if we are to continue because the<br />
past is never to be ignored, the future is never to be regarded<br />
as something that is entirely dominated by the past.<br />
Itts very interesting to me, looking back over these<br />
years, looking back to that time when to be the Leader of the<br />
Opposition was not a frightfully lush occupation. I had a<br />
secretary and a typist and I received a private member's salary<br />
and a handsome allowance of œ 3O' a year for being Leader of the<br />
Opposition. These times have changed very much and, I think,<br />
for the better but in those days it wasn't easy.<br />
And I remember all the preliminary work of creating<br />
the party being put in hand in my office and I remember that<br />
my then Private Secretary Eileen Lenihan, who did so much<br />
tremendous work at that time, was ultimately presented by us,<br />
when we became a party, with a silver dish with a suitable<br />
inscription. This was rather single-handed business at that<br />
time, and for no strange reason, my old friend, Mr. Anderson,<br />
who has been one of the great valiants in this party ( hear, hear)<br />
( applause) will remember well that when I set out on this<br />
expedition and first of all found out how many different<br />
organisations there were, he was thie leader of one which I<br />
think was called the Service and Citizens. And there he was,<br />
never in much doubt about his own mind, Bill, and therefore<br />
when he came along, I knew that he would speak to his people.<br />
We had a conference over there in that improbable-looking<br />
place along the road and we ultimately began, as the President<br />
has reminded us, </p>
<p>2-<br />
Now the first thing we did, the thing that our<br />
opponents have not done, was to say, " Well, what do we learn<br />
from our vicissitudes?" vie had been almost butchered in<br />
194+ 3, 1 can speak about this with some detachment because<br />
contrary to the public impression, I was a private member<br />
at the election of 194+ 3, for a variety of reasons I needn't<br />
go into. And there we were with a battered remnant in the<br />
Parliament. I think that at that time that out of a House<br />
of 74+, we had 17, After the following election we had<br />
perhaps 20 and I will venture to say that there never was a<br />
better Opposition in the world, ( hear, hear) because we set<br />
aboutit the right way.<br />
We said, " Now, here we are, despised and rejected"<br />
and we were of course, at that time led by a leader whose<br />
political life was regarded by most people as finished,<br />
So we had no great assets either in the front or otherwise,<br />
but we made up our minds Zhat we would come back, that we<br />
would unify ourselves, that we would do the things that had<br />
to be done folrget about the past and say to ourselves " 1we<br />
must have one party full of unity and fire, and we musi have<br />
a programme, a plati'orm, which will make people understand that<br />
we have been thinking in the future." We set about it in<br />
19.44. and 194+ 5 and we produced a new look if I may use that<br />
phrase, for the nev party, and the effeci of this forward<br />
thinking this liveliness, this being modern, being prepared<br />
to be a little adventurous was that although we didx. It win<br />
more than two or three seats in 191+ 6 ( and I remember it so well<br />
because the cry went up in all the club armchairs: " You will<br />
never win with Menzies") we went on and, in 194+ 9, had one of<br />
the historic victories ol Federal politics.<br />
What I want to say to you about that aspect of the<br />
matter is that I don't mention it as if we might pat ourselves<br />
on the back and be boastful. I want to ask you why, why we<br />
won in 194+ 9 and why we have gone on winning ever since.<br />
Now why? There is no simple answer to this, There is an awful<br />
lot of luck one way and the other in politics but I want to<br />
tell you that my belief is that over the whole of this period<br />
of fifteen, sixteen years, we have won because we have been the<br />
party of innovations. Not the party of the past, not the<br />
conservative party dying hard on the last barricade, but the<br />
party of innovations. And a number of the innovations that<br />
have been made I don't think would have presented themselves<br />
to the minds of most of us in 194+ 9.<br />
Now I really haven't the time, nor have you the<br />
patience for me to be going through a list, but I am mentioning<br />
them in Lhis connection. These were innovations, these were<br />
evidences of a lively mind and a forward-looking heart. This<br />
is the whole thing that we must remember and that we must<br />
continue to remember and act on in the years to come,<br />
You take social services, They had a stock pattern.<br />
Our opponents thought that they had a monopoly of interest in<br />
social services, but you just look back on it and think of the<br />
things that we p . uduced not our opponents the things that<br />
we produced, the innovations in this field: The Aged Persons<br />
Homes Act, one of the great social measures of our times ( hear,<br />
hear), the Medical Health Scheme, the Pharmaceutical Scheme,<br />
housing loans, housing insurance, these matters being handled<br />
with great distinction if I may say so, and a meticulous<br />
attention to detail by my colleague, the Minister for Housing.<br />
( Applause) Ott S**/ 3 </p>
<p>S3<br />
Foreign policy. We were told that we were just a lot<br />
of dead and gone people, we had no foreign policy. It had never<br />
occurred to us in Opposition to be offensive to our great friends<br />
and therefore we had no foreign policy,-And yet, in our time,<br />
what has happened? We have had the Colombo Plan and never forget<br />
that it was devised by Australia. We have had the A1? IUS pact in<br />
which we played a crucial part and we have had the South-East Asian<br />
Treaty, now under some ecclesiastical fire ( Laughter) but I still<br />
venture to think a remarkable treaty in that it exhibits the will<br />
of nations free nations, to help to preserve the freedom of other<br />
people. hese are three pretty considerable achievements, I think,<br />
in the field of foreign affairs, and we are not exhausted by them<br />
because quite recently my colleague, the Minister for External<br />
Affairs made a speech, a statemdent in the House which I will venture<br />
to describe as the finest statement on foreign policy to be heard<br />
in the Federal Parliament. ( Applause)<br />
In the world of finance, I have heard what my old friend,<br />
the Premier of Victoria, had to say with great vigour this afternoon,<br />
but I would remind all of you that when we came into office, the<br />
financial agreement had been operated in such a way that when the<br />
Loan Programme had been arranged and had been allocated, the duty<br />
of the Commonwealth came to an end. We were the first government<br />
to come to the aid of the States on their Works Programme by, in<br />
effect I don't use the word technically underwriting the'<br />
approved Works Programme for the year.<br />
My colleague said something this afternoong I thought<br />
rather honest about this, We have been called on to subscribe out<br />
of revenue which we have to raise the shortfall in the Loan<br />
Programme. If we look back over the period of office of this<br />
Government, we would find that the shortfall of subscriptions by<br />
the Commonwealth must have amounted to œ-700M. or œ. 800M, over the<br />
whole of that time. This was a novelty.<br />
I dontt know what the professors of political science<br />
teach, except that I have always thought that it was perhaps not<br />
very political and not very scientific ( Laughter), but that is a<br />
mere discourteous remark on my part. I don't quite know what it is<br />
that they teach but if they are interested in the history of<br />
government relations in a Federation, then they ought to recall that<br />
it was a Liberal Government, it was our Government, which for the<br />
first time departed from the strict letter of the law under the<br />
financial agreement. Wie did indeed, and undertook voluntarily a<br />
policy which would help the States whose responsibilities on public<br />
works are so high and who, if i may say so, attend to those<br />
responsibilities so well so that we might be able to say, " Well?<br />
we don't want you to be scrambling through the year wondering how<br />
tmuch the Loan market will produce. If we agree on a works programme,<br />
you may have the whole of the proceeds of the Loan market and if<br />
there is a shortfall on the borrowing market then we will see you<br />
through." Now I mention this, I don't wa-to argue about it,<br />
I merely recall it to remind you that this was a revolutionary change<br />
in the relations betveen the Commonwealth and the States in respect<br />
of Loan raisings. Now so far, it's not too bad is it? These are<br />
revolutionary changes. These weren't produced by conservatism,<br />
these were produced by dynamism in a conception of what the<br />
Commonwealth meant and what the nation meant and required.<br />
You will recall I don't need to elaborate it what<br />
we have done in the educational field. I am quite accustomed now<br />
to being told by all sorts of people, professorial or otherwise,<br />
that we are falling down on our job. What was our job when we oame<br />
0 a0*/ 0 </p>
<p>back into office at the end of 194+ 9? It had nothing to do with<br />
maintaining universities. Nothing whatever. We were the first<br />
people to say, after the war with all this clamant demand for<br />
University training with all this healthy desire on the part of<br />
thousands, scores ol thousands of people to get a better education<br />
and to be better citizens: " We will come into this field." i The<br />
first Commonwealth scholarships were produced by us, The first<br />
grant to the universities was produced by us a very small one, a<br />
little quiet, tactful thing of about Vi~ m., Lut we produced it.<br />
And then we appointed the Murray Committee and then later<br />
on the Universities Commission and then later on the Martin Committee<br />
on Tertiary Education. And what was regarded as an innovation in<br />
1950 LiM. or œ 1 M. has now become œ 30M. a year. I know that<br />
this produces its disadvantages, in a sense, for the States because<br />
none of our programme could succeed without the co-operation of the<br />
States, and therefore I am not saying that we are solely responsible,<br />
but I am saying that we were -the first people to come to the<br />
conclusion that tertiary education in Australia was of such overwhelming<br />
importance for the future of the nation we must forget<br />
all about constitutional inhibitions. We must simply set out to<br />
use our financial resources to bring about a new era in the<br />
university world, I don't care much what undergraduates say in a<br />
noisy way at a meeting -I used to be an undergraduate myself an.<br />
no doubt reasonably noisy but I do know that whenever I go round<br />
Australia and look at a university and see the great buildings rising<br />
to the sky, I take some pleasure in the fact that it is our<br />
Government and our party that has produced these phenomenal results.<br />
Science teaching, technical schools I don't need to go<br />
through the whole gamut of this. I have made far too many speeches<br />
, in it. I hope you will all have it in mind, but the point that<br />
I am making is that this has happened because when wie were out and<br />
broken and beaten, we didn't simply sit down and decide to refurbish<br />
the slogans of the past, but we did decide that in the new world<br />
we must have new ideas, forward-looking ideas, drive and imaginahion,<br />
and all of these things are the result* This is what I beg of you<br />
not to forget. It is not a matter of resting on your oars as they<br />
sometimes say, and saying, " Well, look what a good job we have<br />
done." Yes, we have done a few good things but I want to remind<br />
you that the whole point of this is, that being out and looking<br />
forward to being in we set about developing fresh ideas and drive<br />
and imagination. And all of these things I have mentioned<br />
illustrate it to you. I could give you a long list in the field<br />
of trade and payments, the balance of trade and payments, what has<br />
been done in the trade world with treaties and commissioners, what<br />
has been done in the mineral world, to which David Fairbairn made<br />
some short but valuable references this afternoon, I don't want<br />
to take up your time with details on those matters except to say<br />
one thing about the balance of trade and payments.<br />
A campaign goes on from time to time in Parliament and<br />
out of it to the effect that my distinguished colleague, Mr. Holt,<br />
whose services to this party are beyond praise, ( hear hear)<br />
( applause) is constantly assailed because it is sail that he<br />
doesntt care what happens, He will take overseas money on any<br />
terms and under any circumstances. This is an awful lot of<br />
nonsense. There are all sorts of attempts made to create divisions<br />
and they are created by people who have never read what he said<br />
or what I said in a policy speech, but they are anxious to create<br />
a countervailing rift in the Government to match that obvious<br />
rift or is it two rifts? or three rifts? which exist in the<br />
Opposition. sO~ g </p>
<p>I just want to remind you of one thing. It is quite<br />
true that in a perfect world, and if we had fifty million people in<br />
Australia, we would sell our goods abroad, we would buy imports,<br />
we would hope always to have some slight baance in our favour on<br />
the balance of trade, and then, of course, everything in the garden<br />
would be lovely, Anybody who is out of the kindergarten knows<br />
perfectly well that eleven million people with this enormous<br />
continent to deal with with new resources being turned up every<br />
month, every year, can~ t deal with these matters, can't develop<br />
resources alone, They would have to rely exclusively on their<br />
own savings. It can't be done, and therefore we have adopted tti e<br />
view, and I am sure you have too, that Australia has great valueto<br />
gain by being able to attract investment capital and in part* icular<br />
private investment capital into this country so that we may develop<br />
the country and be fruitful and multiply and inherit our part of<br />
the earth. Well, we are told that this is all wrong. I just want<br />
to tell you that although we would always wish to see Australian<br />
equity interests in overseas capital invested here and quite a<br />
number of people who bring capital in understand that and act on<br />
it the fact is that but for the inpouring of private capital<br />
into Australia in the last dozen years, our development would have<br />
stopped far short of what it is today. ( Hear, hear) ( Applause)<br />
I did notice the other day that, reading Hansard<br />
I don't know whether you read Hansard; I occasionally do I read<br />
a powerful speech by somebody who gave me to completely understand,<br />
an Opposition Member I hasten to say, you don't need overseas<br />
capital. All you do is to create it inside Australia, You know<br />
a nice docile Reserve Bank, plenty of money for nothing. Inflation?<br />
V'ell, what does it matter? Ladies and gentlemen, I think we have<br />
some reason to be proud and therefore you have some reason to be<br />
proud of the extent to which development has occurred in Australia<br />
with the blessing and practical support of people overseas,<br />
The one thing I want to put into your minds about it<br />
is this. If we don't have confidence in ourselves in Australia,<br />
if we really don't believe in all the basic elements that make a<br />
country like this, we can't expect other people to have confidence<br />
in us and if other people had had no confidence in us nobody would<br />
have Leen arguing about overseas investment, because ii wouldn't<br />
have happened. It wouldn't have happened, They do this not because<br />
they love our beautiful blue eyes or whatever wretched colour they<br />
may be, not for a moment. It is because they look around the world<br />
and they see Australia and they say, " Well, now this is a country<br />
that has stability and a great future and resources, with a future<br />
development of resources, This is the place for us to go with<br />
our money." I don't take exception to that, do you? I think that<br />
is rather an agreeable state of affairs, and therefore I ask you<br />
to remember that because this again is one of the reasons for what<br />
has happened in the last fourteen or fifteen years. This has been<br />
going on and one of the basic reasons for it is that we have been<br />
able, with imagination and a forward-looking eye, to produce an<br />
economic climate, a temper of opinion, a temper of hope, which has<br />
persuaded people that this is the place to be.<br />
I'm putting all this to you, not as one who looks back<br />
and says, " Well, I did rather well, and although I am doing rather<br />
badly now, I hope you will hold it in my favour." 1 This is not the<br />
point at all. When any government gets to that state, it is time<br />
it was changed, and all these things have been done because we<br />
haven't looked at it in that way. lie have gone on and on and on<br />
with new ideas, with new drive, with a new vision for our country.<br />
.1 6<br />
5 </p>
<p>6-<br />
And so, Sir, that is the lesson of the whole thing,<br />
looking back over the twenty-one years complete re-thinking, a<br />
revived attack on the future, modern and progressive ideas, but for<br />
those things, we might have succeeded once on a catch vote. We<br />
never could have succeeded in seven consecutive elections because<br />
the people of Australia are not fools.<br />
Now that is all I want to say about the domestic scene.<br />
There is one other aspect of this matter that I thought I might<br />
trouble you about in a rather disorderly sort of fashion and that<br />
concerns our external policy, I think a policy in relation to the<br />
United States, in relation to South-East Asia which is, if I may<br />
use the expression, unanswerably correct,<br />
I was rocked recently in the House of Representatives<br />
when this was under discussion to hear the Leader of the Opposition<br />
say that there never could be a bipartisan policy because on all<br />
these matters the Labor Party could never agree with us, and I<br />
wondered what it was about our policy with which the Labor Party<br />
couldntt agree and what the Labor Party would itself do in<br />
substitution for these policies if it were in office, and I can't<br />
tell you the answer. Would it get out of the ANZJS pact? Would it<br />
abjure our responsibilities under the SEATO treaty? Would it leave<br />
Malaysia to fend for itself? Would it ignore South Vietnam and<br />
this historic battle confused by all sorts of difficult things<br />
but this historic baitle for the freedom of man in South East<br />
Asia? I wish it would get up sometime and tell us what it would<br />
do because it can't agree with us and therefore it must do something<br />
apparently materially different.<br />
Now, we have had a few discussions lately on Vietnam.<br />
I have enjoyed the receipt of some correspondence from dignitaries<br />
of the Church of England which I have received with great respect<br />
although I am Presbyterian myself ( Laughter) but that doesn't<br />
matter. I have now received another letter and within the next<br />
day or two when I have become free of my engagements here I will<br />
no doubt compile another answer. But it is quite clear tF~ t there<br />
are mixed feelings about South Vietnam and at the last moment, the<br />
Opposition has pretended to discover, and has been encouraged by<br />
some headlines in the newspapers, that we are completely at outs<br />
with the American Government, the American Administration, in<br />
relation to Vietnam, and so perhaps at the risk of wearying you,<br />
I ought to remind you of two or three things.<br />
First of all, of course, Mr. Hasluck made a statement<br />
in the House in which he stated all the views extremely well which<br />
I ' repeated later on, perhaps indifferently, but he stated the<br />
policy of the Government in relation to this matter. All I can<br />
tell you is that I have every reason to know that his speech was<br />
received with very great pleasure in dashington and with warm<br />
approval. ( Hear, hear) ( Applause)<br />
Well, then, I went down, making one of these weekend<br />
speeches of which there are too many and which I am endeavouring<br />
to eliminate, and I spoke at a place called Cheltenham in Victoria,<br />
My. colleague, Don Chipp was there, In fact he took me there.<br />
And as part of another theme that I was talking about, I undertook<br />
to say something about the American actions in Vietnam.<br />
I asked them why they thought the United States of<br />
America was sending its men into Vietnam and spending vast sums and<br />
producing vast stores of equipment, and I said, " Why do you suppose<br />
they are doing it?" This is not a bad question, I put to you:<br />
I hope I won't have anybody suppose that they are doing it because<br />
they want to make South Vietnam an American colony, That would be<br />
too silly for words. That would be, in the homely phrase, buying<br />
* a00a / 7 </p>
<p>-7-<br />
trouble. I don't think any of us would want to have one of these<br />
countries as a colony. Of course not. Is it because the Americans<br />
have enormous financial interests in that country? I venture to<br />
think they have practically none. Then why are they doing it?<br />
W iy are they, with all the temptations in the world to be isolationist<br />
sa. ing " Well, we won't protect our own interest at home so much.<br />
We have the wide seas on each side of us but we won't allow that<br />
to influence us," WVhy are they doing it? They are doing it because<br />
they believe that what is at issue is human freedom and they believe<br />
that human freedom ought to be defended wherever it is challenged<br />
and that they, as the greatest power in the world, should accept the<br />
greatest responsibility for it.<br />
Now I hope nobody thinks that to talk about human freedom,<br />
after all the experiences of this century, is to talk high-falutin'.<br />
This great issue, this basic issue of human freedom has wracked the<br />
world twice in this century, '. as cost millions of lives and distorted<br />
the whole economic history country after country. Don't let us<br />
treat it as if it were an ex;.. ndable commodity. And I take off my<br />
hat to the Americans who onl. y fifty years ago were deeply sunk in<br />
isolationism, who had the Mon.:-oe Doctrine around them I take off<br />
my hat to them because twircc not, in particular since the last<br />
war, they have assumed encrimicas res-ponsibilities for the preservation<br />
of human freedom including our own. ( Hear, hear)<br />
Well this of cou:-se, was regarded by our opponents,<br />
particularly those of wat I believe is called the Left Wing, was<br />
regarded as absolutely sabre-ratt'.: g stuff you know, no relation<br />
to the facts of life. And then Pr~ sid nt Jolhnson made a speech,<br />
but before he did I , is asked a qucst-ion oh, this was a gaffe as<br />
I have gathered since, an awful gaffe by me. So I thought well,<br />
I am as capable of making a gaffe as the next fellow T will have a<br />
look in the Hansard to see what it was because I had been asked<br />
whether I was prepared to urge on the inited States that they should<br />
negotiate a peace. Urge on the United States....... Nobody would<br />
be silly enough to ask me to urge something on Peking because I<br />
don't suppose they ever heard of me. I don't suppose they will ask<br />
me to urge something on Ho Chi-Minh at Hanoi because we are not on<br />
the closest of terms and therefore it was America. We had to say,<br />
" Come, come" and so I was asked a question and I said, " What I was<br />
directing myself to on each of these occasions was a suggestion,<br />
about which some people have been quite vocal, that the United<br />
States, instead of fighting should negotiate." I emphasise those<br />
words " instead of fighting should negotiate.... negotiate<br />
with an enemy which has violated its obligations in relation to a<br />
cease-fire, negotiate with a country that has ignored its international<br />
obligations, and negotiate with people who keep on shooting<br />
when the Americans have stopped shooting." I see nothirgin that<br />
that I would want to withdraw or qualify for half a minute.<br />
Well then, of course, the fat was in the fire because<br />
they said, " Well, the President three or four days later, he<br />
said, ' Yes, I'll negotiatetIt hit the headlines, quite misleading<br />
headlines and in case you have been beguiled by them, I think I<br />
ought to Zell you what the President said. I have the full text<br />
before me. What the President said at Johns Hopkins was almost,<br />
word for word, what Paul Hasluck had said and what I had said in<br />
the speeches that I made. He went on to talk about the principle<br />
for which Americans were fighting in the jungles of Vietnam<br />
" Tonight, Americans and Asians are dyihg for a world where<br />
each people may choose its own path to change."<br />
That was well spoken if I may say so. / 8 </p>
<p>408 I<br />
" Only in such a world wil-L our. own. freedom be finally seue"<br />
Th-at is worth recalling. If I may say so I can imagine a state of<br />
af'fairs in which the United States of America could maintain its<br />
safety and security with South East Asia in communist hands. I can't<br />
imagine such a thing in the case of Australia, and therefore everything<br />
that he says can be accented two or three times for us.<br />
" Only in such a world will our own freedom be finally'<br />
secure, This kind of world will never be built by bombs<br />
or bullets yet the infirmities of man are such that force<br />
must often precede reason and the waste of war the works<br />
of peace. 1<br />
This is the President at Johns Hopkins. Then later on he told what<br />
was happening " Trained men and supplies, orders and arms flow in a<br />
constant stream from the North to the South...."<br />
( the North the innocent party I gather some people think) From North<br />
Vietnam into South Vietnam, replenishing the Vietcong, already with<br />
powerful formations of troops, the oommunists in their pockets in<br />
South Vietnam and over the border into Cambodia, and the North feeding<br />
them., And who feeds the North? ., fell, I dontt need to answer that<br />
question. " Simple farmers are the targets of assassination and<br />
kidnapping, ( This is Lyndon Johnson not myself)<br />
Women and children are strangled in ihe night because<br />
their men are loyal to the Government. Small and helpless<br />
villages are ravaged by sneak attacks."<br />
don't need to go on, He gave a vivid account of what is occurring<br />
and then he put the same question as I had put to the worthy<br />
citizens of Cheltenham. He said<br />
" Why are we in South Vietnam? We are there because we<br />
have a promise to keep,"<br />
So have we dontt forget, ladies and gentlemen. The South East<br />
Asian treaiy is a treaty which imposes upon us obligations which are<br />
several as well as joint and South Vietnam is one of the protocol<br />
states whose security is guaranteed by the South East Asian Treaty.<br />
Therefore this applies to uss<br />
" Why are we in South Vietnam? We are there because we<br />
have a promise to keep. Since 1951+, every American<br />
P'resident has offered support to the people of South<br />
Vietnam. lie have helped to build and we have helped<br />
to defend, Thus over many years we have made a national<br />
pledge to help South Vietnam defend its independence"<br />
and he went on to say ( so far from running for cover as some of<br />
these critics thought he should) he went on to say,<br />
I intend to keep that promise. To dishonour<br />
that pledge, to abandon this small and brave nation to<br />
its enemy and to the terror that must follow would be<br />
an unfortunate wrong. We are also there to strengthen<br />
world order. Around the globe from Berlin to Thailand are<br />
people whose well-being rests in part on the belief that<br />
they can count on us if they are attacked. To leave Vietnam<br />
to its fate would shake the confidence of all these people<br />
in the value of an American commitment and the value of<br />
America's word...... We must stay in South-East Asia as we<br />
did in ] 3urope. In the words of the Bible, ' Hitherto shalt<br />
thou come but no further". 000060/ 9 </p>
<p>9-<br />
Now I think somebody would need to have a great deal of<br />
ingenuity and almost genius for falsification to find any difference<br />
between that and what we have been saying, and that is why what<br />
we have been saying has been received with such warm approval in<br />
Washington. Then the President goes on a little later<br />
" What is our objective in Vietnam? Our objective is<br />
the independence of South Vietnam and its freedom<br />
from attack, We want nothing for ourselves, only that<br />
the people of South Vietnam be allowed to guide their<br />
own country in their own way. We will do everything<br />
necessary to reach that objective and we w~ ill do only<br />
what is absolutely necessary. In recent months, attacks<br />
in South Vietnam were stepped up. Thus it became<br />
necessary for us to increase our response and make<br />
attacks by air. This is not a change of purpose.<br />
It is a change in what we believe that purpose requires.<br />
We do this in order to slow down aggression. We do<br />
this to increase the confidence of the brave people<br />
of South Vietnam who have bravely borne this brutal<br />
attack for so many years and with so many casualtieso... 6<br />
We will not be defeated, We will not grow tired. We<br />
will not withdraw either openly or under the cloak of<br />
a meaningless agreementil<br />
That's what he said that is what he means. That is<br />
what the people of America siand for, and later on he came to the<br />
question that has vexed some people well-meaning people people<br />
of the highest intentions. He sail, " Should we negotiate?"<br />
Well, of course, having regard to what he said, to negotiate in<br />
the sense of abandoning the position would have been unthinkable.<br />
Unthinkable. And he knew perfectly well that the one condition<br />
that has been put forward by North Vietnam, by its communist<br />
backers is that they won't talk about anything unless the Americans<br />
get out. In other words, unless the Americans abandon South<br />
Vietnam to their clutches. That has been their condition*<br />
And therefore he said<br />
" We have stated this position over and over again fifty<br />
times and more to friend and foe alike and we remain<br />
( no change of policy here) we remain ready with<br />
this purpose for unconditional discussion."<br />
That is to say, for discussions which dontt involve the condition<br />
that has been put forward and which has now, I noticeg been<br />
violently repeated, that we get out because we are not getting<br />
out. We are there, and we are there to do our job and we will<br />
do it. But if, under some circumstances, discussions could occur<br />
which meant that we didn't abandon South Vietnam and that they were<br />
not left exposed to violent attack from the north, then of-course<br />
we have no abmition to have our men killed, we will be prepared<br />
to discuss, This, in effect, is what the President said.;<br />
This is so elementary, isn't it so simple that it is<br />
hard to believe how it could be distortel or misinterpreted.<br />
The speech by the President ought to be made compulsory reading,<br />
I have read only a bit of it. It ought to be made compulsory<br />
reading because I will venture to say that if the President of<br />
the United States has no other claim to being celebrated in the<br />
history of his country, he would have established a right by<br />
this one speech and by this one simple policy. as~ go~ e </p>
<p>Dontt be misled by the superficial readers or the headlineclutchers<br />
who think there is a division between us, I am happy to<br />
say that I have had very good messages myself from Washington about<br />
what I have had to say and as I have indicated, Paul has too.<br />
There is no Aifference between us on this matter. We<br />
are in the closest, most constant contact. It is perlhaps one of<br />
the things that our Government has done in these years that I have<br />
been describing that beginning with a somewhat dubious relationship<br />
with the United States, we have established an intimacy of contact,<br />
a daily exchange of views in Washington on the most friendly terms<br />
ihich I can only regard as one of the invisible but all-powerful<br />
elements in the security of our country.<br />
Now I am sorry to-have taken up so much of your time<br />
on that. I hope I have been sufficiently clear in what I have<br />
said because I set off to review the past and to remind you that<br />
it was the result of an activity and imagination which must continue<br />
for the future, and in the second place I wanted to deal with this<br />
current matter to de monstrate to you that the foreign policy of<br />
this government is one which may incur some momentary hostility<br />
with other people but which involves the deepest friendship, the<br />
deepest co-operation, the deepest mutual understanding, with the<br />
great nations of the world.<br />
OL a F </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
