<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4533</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS TO AUSTRALIAN COUNCIL OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT ASSOCIATIONS, 7 NOVEMBER 1977</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/11/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004533.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS 7 NOVEMBER 1977<br />
ADDRESS To AUSTRALIAN COUNCIL OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT ASSOCIATIONS<br />
I particularly welcomed your invitation to speak to you today as<br />
At provides me with the opportunity to congratulate you on the<br />
way in which local government in all States is adapting so well<br />
to the changing needs and demands of our society. This occasion<br />
also provides me the opportunity briefly to speak of the<br />
increasingly important role of local government in our Federal system.<br />
The advantages of a properly functioning Federal system to a<br />
country as large and varied as Australia are many: diversity in<br />
government services to satisfy local preferences and needs;<br />
decentralisation of decision-making; greater proximity of<br />
administrators to the people they serve.<br />
At the same time, the national Government retains sufficient powers<br />
to enable management of the economy, and to implement uniform<br />
policies for all Australians where social or economic factors<br />
so require.<br />
Alongside the Commonwealth and the States local government is the<br />
third arm of Australian Federalism. It is only through active,<br />
efficient and sensitive government at the council or shire level<br />
that the full advantages of a decentralised, Federal system of<br />
government can be fully realised. Local government on the<br />
whole has been responding well to this challenge in the range<br />
of services offered, in the willingness of councils and shires<br />
to cooperate . voluntarily on a regional basis to provide<br />
a particular service which is beyond the means of any one body,<br />
and in greater awarenessof the need to prote-ct our environment.<br />
The capacity of local government to meet its responsibilities and<br />
provide expanded services has been greatly assisted by the new<br />
tax sharing arrangement introduced by my government.<br />
General revenue assistance to local government in 197 6/ 77 was<br />
percent higher than the previous year, and this year,<br />
funds have increased a further 18 percent to over $ 165 million.<br />
All these funds are of course untied, with no strings or conditions. </p>
<p>In addition, we have sharply increased funds for local government<br />
roads, particularly in rural.. areas. In 1976/ 77, $ 109 million<br />
in Commonwealth funds were allocated for rural roads.<br />
This year, an additional $ 52 million has been provided, raising<br />
the total to $ 161 million.<br />
It is because of our commitment to a strong Federal system<br />
in which local government forms-an integral and essential part<br />
that we have sharply increased funds, to local government,<br />
even though the last two years have necessarily required great<br />
restraint in government expenditure.<br />
one pleasing result of these policies has been the increased<br />
capacity of local government' to hold back rate increases.<br />
Initial estimates bythe Bureau of Statistics show that in 1976/ 77<br />
average rate increases have been sharply reduced. For example,<br />
in Victoria,. in the three financial years from 1973/ 74,<br />
to 1975/ 76, rates rc: 3e byan average of 20 percent,. 30 percent<br />
and 19 percent respectively. In 1976/ 77 the average increase<br />
in rates was contained to 10.2 percent.<br />
Similar financial benefits have been received by each of the States<br />
as the recent State budgets so clearly show: no State has<br />
b~ udgeted for a substantial deficit; all states have introduced<br />
some new programmes or extended existing programmes; and every<br />
state , without exception, has provided substantial tax concessions.<br />
I am aware of representations which have been made for an increase<br />
in local government's percentage tax share, the present entitlement<br />
of 1.52 percent of the previous year's income tax collections<br />
is not an immutable figure. But on the whole local government<br />
has been treated generously in the last two years, and it should<br />
not be forgotten that, as the economy strengthens, the value of<br />
the present entitlement will rise significantly.<br />
Our Federalism policies have not only increased the financial<br />
strength of local government. The status and recognition<br />
of local government as an integral part of our Federal system<br />
has also been enhanced, principally through local government<br />
representation on the Advisory Council for Inter-Government Relations<br />
which met for the firsttime in June.<br />
Local government,--trougb__. trhd P-emthir. Conference, has theopportunity-<br />
to sugrgest. subj-ects--to be referred to the<br />
Advisory Council, and the Advisory Council reports directly to<br />
this Council as well as to the Comm~ onwealth and each State.<br />
We see the Advisory Council as making a most valuable<br />
contribution in improving coordination and cooperation between the<br />
three spheres of government. one of the first references to be<br />
considered by the Advisory Council an examination of the<br />
relationshipos which should exist between Federal, State and<br />
local goverrnments should be of considerable interest to all of<br />
you here. In its first annual report, the Advisory Council<br />
comments that it acts " as a kind of continuing committee of<br />
inquiry into problems of Australian Federalism". That strikes<br />
me as a very apt description.<br />
p </p>
<p>3.<br />
The Government is determined: to strengthen our Federal system<br />
of government, and the increased financial reponsibility of<br />
the States and local government is a major step in achieving this<br />
goal. The interests of local government will never be overlooked<br />
by my government.<br />
Mr Chairman, I have great pleasure in opening this annual<br />
conference of the Australian Council of Local Government Associations. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
