<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9047</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON. PJ KEATING, MP -SEATTLE, USA FRIDAY 19 NOVEMBER, 1993</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/11/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009047.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
E OE PROOF COPY<br />
TRANSCRtIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON. P J<br />
KEATING, SE~ ATTLE, U. S. A.<br />
FRIDAY 19 NOVEMBER, 1993<br />
PM-. This morning T had meetings with Prime Minister Chaun of T'hailand, President<br />
Jian&amp; Zemin of China and President Kim Young Sam of Korca. Another ve~ y<br />
useful do vclopment of APEC, that onc has the capacity to have bilateral<br />
discussions. At each of those meetings we were able to discuss APEC, whlat it<br />
means, Its development and also bilateral issues between us. There are, of course,<br />
as you know many bilateral Issucs and I was able to discass dcvclopmcents in the<br />
Australian economy; developments between Australia and Its economy and<br />
China; thc growth of trade last year of 40 tie progress we ate making in trade<br />
talks recently, the progress we are mnaking on wool for instance; as well as talking<br />
about API C, the prospects for this meeting, its future and its institutional<br />
NtTucturc. In my discussion with President Kim Young Samn we r-anged uver those issues<br />
again that is, the APE-C pecLuliar issucs, as Well as Australiaes support for South<br />
Korea's position with North Korea over nuclear weapons. And lie also usked me<br />
ubout our likely support otKorea for a place in the . J'N Security Council,<br />
representing Asia. It was a useful and interesting morning.<br />
J: Did you get any sense from the Chinese President of how they arc going to<br />
respond to President Clinton's entreaties oil human tights?<br />
PM; No, 1no 1 met Presidcnt Jiang /. emin before President Clinton would have met him<br />
and I also indiuuted because I don't think it is as well understood outside of the<br />
United States or outside of wtintrics like Australia as here therc is some still<br />
body of opinion In the 1. Jnited States that says they shouldn't tic thcir hands in a<br />
Multilateral structure, that they should miaintain the right to do things unilaterally<br />
and bilaterally)-also a great dichotomy of view often between the Pres~ idency, the<br />
President, and thc Congress. And I think that our Chinese friends need to take </p>
<p>-2-<br />
that into account. That this is not a monolithic debate in the United States, and<br />
getting a United States President interested in trade ill the Pacifc and looking<br />
Wcstward doesn't mean the whole monolith goes with him. But those of us who<br />
are interested in securing US support for developments in the Asia Pacific aren<br />
have to also encourage the Congress and other elements of the administration as<br />
well. So. I took the opportunity to give himi these views which may havc been<br />
useful ahead of him meeting the President.<br />
Blut from China's point of view they have got a massive trade surplus with the US,<br />
in one way the StMtuS quo suits them just finely doen't Vt<br />
PM: Well thiese economics are going to grow so rapidly, their ifastructure demands,<br />
their energy demands, their environmental problems are going to he so prtfound,<br />
that unless they get the institutional arrangement-; in place to see this sort of<br />
development, they are tnt going to grow as fast as they otherwise would. They<br />
would then experiece the same kind of trade prcs~ surcs Wili the United States<br />
which Japan is experiencing. So you've got to let the United qtte,; be able to<br />
tradc in the area to see its exports rise.<br />
And this is thc point President Clinton continually makes about growth and jobs<br />
in the United States for the export growth which hits the potential of reaching in<br />
the Asia Pacific areat. In othier words, the US has got to be allowed to freely<br />
exerise its commercial possibilities in the area so that it is not living with very<br />
large trade imbalances against it. Now, that is why getting these structures right<br />
and thinking about them ahead of time is important.<br />
J. Are you disappointed that the Ministerial Statement didn't embrace the 1996 JITO<br />
target on free trade, agrement on free W-ade? And if! T could ask one more thing,<br />
the Chinese Foreign Minister in answer to questions about that meeting<br />
upecirically rejected the idea of it namec change to community or any sense of a<br />
community?<br />
PM: Well let me deal with the second one first. T've sdid to you oflcn there is no road<br />
map with APEC, we have got to explain it as we go along. ' Mere is a concern that<br />
the word community implies a Brussels-lypc supra-national structure. Now, it<br />
doesn't. None of are thinking about a European community Brussels-type<br />
bureaucrucy which makes national decisions, or supra-niational decisions, or<br />
decisions for Nation's. APEC is a much looser, co-operaivc structure than that,<br />
and it won't have those formial arrangcmcnts. So the word community doesn't<br />
have the samec connotation as lRuropean community.<br />
B~ ut again, the main thing is, as I said to you yustcrday, that the member states<br />
here adopt the work programns and go on positively with the main substantial work </p>
<p>-3-<br />
of APEC. Some at thle moment seem to be more worried about the form than thc<br />
substance. When you get down to substanc they have no worrics. When you<br />
talk about the formn they seem to have worrics. Well, OX, let's focus oil<br />
substance, the form will look aftcr itself.<br />
And the question about the LVC1 and the 1996 date?<br />
PM: Well. again, this is another point. You see, we don't envisage tat AI'LC should<br />
be displacing the (. iAFJfor trade liberalising things. We see tht OATT as having<br />
primacy in global terms, in terms of goods, services, intellectual property rights<br />
etc., But what CIAICaniL do is basically get inlto things like trade facilitation,<br />
that is encouraging the development of a bcttcr legal background in countries for<br />
investment, better protection for propwry, the rights to litigate on equity issuex,<br />
customs procedurcs, company law standardisation, standardisation of profesional<br />
siandards, standardisation of food standards, standardisation of electrical and<br />
telccommunicahion standards, these are not G~ ATT things. But, these arc very<br />
imrnltant things to this region. They arc one of the things that will help, for<br />
instance, trade from all of us into the area&amp;<br />
So it's a case or showing what GMJT= c do and what APEC can do so that the<br />
trade facilitation, I've always said to you, the trade raili~ ation agenda will be up<br />
the front and the trade liberalising agenda will follow, B~ ut because, I think,<br />
countries of the -rea see the trade posibilitiesl they are already doing it. It was<br />
like the tariff changes in Australia. We announced the tariff cuts in 1988, by 1989<br />
companies were already looking to adjust for the end points, even though they<br />
were years away. In the same way Indanesia. this year for instance, is now<br />
introduving a very large package of deregulation and boardcr protection reforms.<br />
If we keep on the trade facilitation and if we focus on what we can all do together,<br />
L think the trade liberalisation will come along as well as through the OATT, not<br />
only through the CYATT, but by unilateral decision% which countries will takc to<br />
open Up their markets.<br />
J: Arc you happy with the message that is now being sent through t) OATT from<br />
APE. C?<br />
PM: Well I think so, an(] you mnay have seen today's release, if you have it, the<br />
commitmenits which the various APLC countries have been prepared to put their<br />
namec to. which have been negotiated in G'eneva under tht aUSPiCC3 Of the G7AIT-1.<br />
Now, in Australian termns they arc off a 1989 ba-se, and, of course, after then we<br />
introduced thc tariff chunges or 1988 to 1991 and then the tariff changes of 1991<br />
to 1 996. So we are In the happy position of being able to comply with all of these<br />
commitnienis without, in ract, changing the policy we ulready have in place. </p>
<p>.4-<br />
J: Does it involve any concessions on our part?<br />
PM: Not beyond that which we have announced years ago.<br />
J: One of the things you want to come out of this conference is to make them a<br />
regular event, a regular summit, do you think from the talks you have had so far<br />
hero that it is likely to come oil.<br />
PM: I think so. I think that It's likely that tomorrow it may be proposed that there be<br />
another meeting again next year. And I think that is likely to succeed.<br />
J: Who will propose that?<br />
PM; I don't know. This is another thing, that the dynamics of the Leaders' meeting is<br />
going to be quite important, because it is not pre-cooked or scripted. Thecrcfore it<br />
is likely to have an impetus, in fact, some of the leaders are stronger on this than<br />
their foreign ministries are. And this is why, I think, it will be important to see<br />
how the chemistry of the meeting runs itself.<br />
J: Would that be in Jakarta?<br />
PM: Well, next year is in Jakata. The next ministerial meeting is in Jakarta. But,<br />
again, there would need to bc a consensus for it. I think in the cvcnt that there's a<br />
consensus I'd be pretty surprised if President Suoharto wouldn't issue an invitation<br />
but there would need to be a consensus.<br />
J: Given what you've said about the meeting tomorrow, do you hope the Leaders'<br />
meeting can push forward in the arcas that the Ministers' meeting met resistance?<br />
PM: In what areas?<br />
J: The name change, the EPG, things like that.<br />
FPM Well, again, the main thing is to keep broadening the understanding of what<br />
APF. C is and what it can do. And to then summon the consensus for that and<br />
move on. In other words, you gather up a bit more each time and then you move<br />
along. This has come a long way from nothing, in four years. When I first started<br />
talking about giving APEC more authority with 1Leaders' mectings was when I<br />
met George Bush in January 1992. This is the end of 1993, it's only two years<br />
and you've got half the world's leadership. </p>
<p>3: Werc you hatppy about the recognition of Australia's pivotal role in setting up<br />
APE C, tbrough Bill Clintoo's acknowledgement of [ Bob I lawke, today?<br />
PM: Oh ycs. I think Australia is very clearly identified with authorship of APFC wq a<br />
grouping. Ii's all now a matter about what it is and how deep it is. And the APEC<br />
we're talking a~ bout now is more than just an informnat ion secretariat. Tt's<br />
something which is lookin~ g at these trade facilitating things and just by<br />
summoning the leaders to it naturally gives it more attention national attention<br />
and morc focus in all of these national bureaucrAcies and, of course, in their<br />
communities. So API2C will, therefore, be very much stronger as a result of* thjs<br />
change.<br />
J: Is it correct that teams lik~ e the ten working groups inaudible have actually<br />
done a lot of work in Identifying trade barriers, other tariff barriers and so on.. the<br />
work's there, there's a stack of books this thick. And it was tip to this meeting,<br />
thought to be up to this rnccling to actually give it the policy impetus to mnake<br />
decisions on how to actually lower or eliminate those sort of barriers and in fact,* it<br />
soorms as thought that impetus is not there.<br />
P'M: No, no. Thars not right. This inecting never envisaged adopting wholesale the<br />
Whole trade libcralising agenda. The mecting does not have enough ol* it history<br />
as an executive group, I think in this time, to izontcmplatc: ( hat sort of wholesale<br />
adoption. in other words, no-one is considering notihstanding the fact that<br />
one can easily collate where tarifE or other non-tairiff barriers might be no-one<br />
is believing that this mneefing is going to be, in fact, adopting an cxecutive role<br />
which then says, " Ohi yes, we'll lick these binding changes t) national economics'<br />
borders." That's not what is envisaged hbrm.<br />
But what is cnvisagcd here is to give APEC more authority, that is, to make clear<br />
that the lcadcrs' want it to have a role doing things more than simply exchangin<br />
Wnorpiation and, in the first instance, ito look at these trade facilitation programs.<br />
Which I think it tcan do. And it will do those things but, I think, on trade<br />
liberalisation everyone W! Il sit back and see where the GIATT goes. Now, irthe<br />
GATl succeeds and there's a great change in thc GAiT ' and there's a lot of<br />
liberalising people then say, " Well, what else can we do". And in a year or two, a<br />
fcw years after thui, I ihtink we can follow it up.<br />
J1: you've slid that you're going to invite President Clint-on to Australia on this trip.<br />
When will you issue this invitation?<br />
pM: Well, obviously 7' ll be seeing him a number of tinics ovcr this weekend and in the<br />
event, of course, that the meeting were to deuitdc that there would tie another </p>
<p>16-<br />
mfecting, irt the S. outhern Hemisphere in Indonesia I would say, " Well, look,<br />
if You're there, come and see us." Whether he cun... it President's schedule is<br />
always fully booked so whether you can jUSt issuc and invitation and expect to get<br />
an acceptance is a different matter. But, I'll certainly ask hin.<br />
J: insudible Christopher indicated there could be somec soil of developments on<br />
the Korean Peninsula. In your discussions with the South Korean President today,<br />
did he indicate anything happening in that regard? Sumv. sort of breakthrough or<br />
some behind the scencs development?<br />
PM: No, I think their preoccupation seems to be with nuclear issues in the North and<br />
continuing world support for their position. That is, pressure onl North Korea to<br />
open themselves up for IAFA inspections and to keep pressure onl them so as to<br />
see them not got to the rcproccssing business. But now, no doubt there is a lot of<br />
bilateral business between Korea and the United State.% b ut thiuy'll announce all of<br />
that in their own good time. And it's their business.<br />
J1: Mr Keating, there's been a bit of contioversy in Australia over the agreement you<br />
made with, apparently. with Mr J0lack, on Fairfax. How can wc be sure that, in<br />
future mecdia decisions that your Government has to make, that you won't make ak<br />
shnilar agreement or deal with, say, the Pay TIV contracts?<br />
PM: It's not a matter of making similar... Look, t~ here's no group more sel f-interested<br />
than the Fairfax journalists in the affairs of Fairfax. The only rivals arc the ABC<br />
and thc affairs of the ABC. Outside of these two very articulate and selfinterested<br />
groupings, the rest of* us arc bystanders to the general media debate. I<br />
was asked yesterday about M~ r Black and our decision to increase his holdings to<br />
Obviously, no government is going to give such and agreement to a<br />
proprietor who behaves in a paisan way, or immnaturely. And the last election<br />
ww; a reasonable test of how the ncw management proprietorship and<br />
management would behave in that environment. And that's the sum total of it.<br />
Beyond thazt, Mr Black has not formally put any proposuls to the Government so<br />
therefore, there's nothing to consider.<br />
J7: So, will you be applying, that same criteria to future, potential media owners in<br />
Australiat? Particularly with Pay TV?<br />
PM: No. Because, well, Pay TV is not the principal broadsheets of the country. But,<br />
obviously, I don't think anyone in Australia should wclcolicb eavy handed<br />
proprietorship. I remember the whole of thc Fairflax employees talking about. the<br />
rights to write and have printcd that which they bclicvc and 11ot have prOPrietorial<br />
intervcntion. And it was tha point that I was~ making. </p>
<p>.7-<br />
J: On thc subject of proprietorial intervcntion, you put a bit of a bucket on the<br />
British tabloids the other day when sitting right next to you was Rupert Murdoch.<br />
Did he say to you afterwards anything about the Lizard of Oz?<br />
PM: No, of course it took mc a while to make the link between thc Sun and him. His<br />
newspaper empire is so extensive that one needs to have an encyclopedic memory<br />
to remember all the titles.<br />
J: Just on Fairfax, Mr Keating, who made the judgemnent about whether they were<br />
balanced or not. Was it you alone or was it other ministers as well?<br />
PM: Oh look, I don't think I need to take that debate any further. I mean, Mr Black<br />
made the point that it was very hard to manage the newspaper with 14.9% of the<br />
stock and it's a pretty reasonable point to makc. We've given him 25% and<br />
is nowhere near a commanding position in tenns of the cquity but it gives him the<br />
authority to manage it.<br />
PM: Do you think, for instancc, that a Liberal Prime Minister might make a different<br />
judgement of balance as a Labor Prime Minister?<br />
PM: I shouldn't think so. I mnan, I don't think it's an unrecasonable thing to require of a<br />
newspaper that it be balanced.<br />
J: Wcrc you pleased with thc way Conrad Black thrust your discussions into the<br />
public domain?<br />
PM: I was absolutely delighted.<br />
INDS,. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
