<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11206</transcript-id>
    <title>Doorstop Interview on Departure for Papua New Guinea, RAAF Base Fairbairn, Canberra </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/10/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects>Wounded Australian soldiers, Senator Minchin’s speech</subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p><strong>7 October 1999</strong></p>
<p>E&amp;OE……………………………………………………………………………………….</p>
<p><b>JOURNALIST:</b></p>
<p>Mr Howard, how concerned were you when you heard what happened in East Timor with the Australian soldiers involved in a firefight?</p>
<p><b>PRIME MINISTER:</b></p>
<p>Well, I think it’s a reminder to all of us that this is a dangerous operation. I don’t want to talk about the operational aspects of it. They’ve been admirably handled by Major General Cosgrove. I expressed my immense relief that the wounds suffered by the Australian soldiers were not severe and that they will make a full recovery. I regret the loss of life on the militia side. A loss of life of anybody in this situation is regrettable and we hope that the militia will co-operate with the INTERFET forces who have a clear and unambiguous United Nations’ mandate.</p>
<p><b>JOURNALIST:</b></p>
<p>Does it raise the issue of hot pursuit again because of the fact that East Timor [inaudible]…?</p>
<p><b>PRIME MINISTER:</b></p>
<p>Look, the matter, the operational aspects of the matter were fully covered by Major General Cosgrove and also the local spokesman for the Australian Defence Force. I am not going to get into commenting on the operational aspects of it. They are best dealt with by the military. They understand the circumstances of it.</p>
<p><b>JOURNALIST:</b></p>
<p>But has the reality of East Timor hit home for Australians now that two of our soldiers have been injured?</p>
<p><b>PRIME MINISTER:</b></p>
<p>Well, I think Australians always understood that this was a dangerous mission. I’ve never disguised that fact. I made it very clear from the very beginning. I’m relieved, immensely relieved, that the wounds suffered on this occasion appear not to have been severe and that both of our blokes will make a full recovery. Now, that’s good but it is dangerous and that has always been the case and we have to keep our fingers crossed and our thoughts constantly with them.</p>
<p><b>JOURNALIST:</b></p>
<p>Mr Howard, did Senator Minchin get involved in a slanging match with Peter Costello [inaudible]…?</p>
<p><b>PRIME MINISTER:</b></p>
<p>I haven’t read Senator Minchin’s speech.</p>
<p><b>JOURNALIST:</b></p>
<p>What did you make of the intervention of Sir Gerard, Sir Anthony and Sir…</p>
<p><b>PRIME MINISTER:</b></p>
<p>Well, as you know, Alison, I haven’t made a habit up until now and I’m not going to change this morning of giving a running commentary on other people’s contributions. At an appropriate time I’ll have something to say about this issue but this is not the appropriate time. Thank you.</p>
<p><b>JOURNALIST:</b></p>
<p>Are you going to read Senator Minchin’s speech [inaudible]…?</p>
<p><b>PRIME MINISTER:</b></p>
<p>I’m going to go and talk to the Prime Minister of Papua New Guinea.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
