<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18512</transcript-id>
    <title>Prime Minister to visit Singapore and Turkey</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/04/2012</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Prime Minister Julia Gillard will travel to Singapore and Turkey from 22 to 28 April.</p>
<p>Singapore is one of Australia's closest regional partners.  It is Australia's fifth largest trading partner and a key strategic and economic friend in the Asia Pacific region.</p>
<p>In Singapore, the Prime Minister will meet Prime Minister Lee Hsien Loong to discuss ways in which we can strengthen bilateral and regional cooperation, boost bilateral trade and investment and reaffirm our already solid defence ties.</p>
<p>This year marks the 70th anniversary of the Battle for Singapore, in which more than 1,000 Australians were killed or missing in action and over 15,000 Australians became prisoners of war.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister will pay her respects at the Kranji War Memorial, which honours the sacrifice of allied service men and women in the Second World War.</p>
<p>In Turkey, the Prime Minister will join Australians who have travelled to Gallipoli to commemorate the landing of our troops at Anzac Cove. This is the 97th anniversary of the historic landings and will be a memorable event for all Australians.</p>
<p>On this day the Prime Minister will attend services at the Anzac Day Dawn Service, the Australian Memorial at Lone Pine and the New Zealand Memorial at Chunuk Bair.</p>
<p>The following day, the Prime Minister will hold talks with Turkey's Prime Minister Recep Tayyip Erdogan.</p>
<p>Australia and Turkey have longstanding historical ties that are close to the heart of Australians and Turks alike. These ties are reinforced by our strong community links and a vibrant Turkish community in Australia.</p>
<p>Australia and Turkey are strengthening our cooperation on a range of significant international issues. </p>
<p>We are partners in the transition in Afghanistan and work very closely together in the G20, which Australia will host in 2014 and Turkey will host in 2015.</p>
<p>This will be Ms Gillard's first visit to Turkey as Prime Minister and the first visit to Gallipoli by an Australian Prime Minister since 2005. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
