<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8828</transcript-id>
    <title>LABOR TO FUND TOURISM GROWTH IN REGIONAL AUSTRALIA</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/02/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008828.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
JOINT STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER,<br />
THE HON P. J. KEATING, MP AND THE MINISTER FOR TOURISM, THE<br />
HON ALAN GRHIFFIS, MP<br />
LABOR TO FUND TOURISM GROWTH IN REGIONAL AUSTRALIA<br />
A $ 42 million plan to develop tourism in regional Australia is the centrepiece of the<br />
Labor Party's Tourism Policy, released today in Bendigo by the Prime Minister, Mr<br />
Paul Keating, and the Minister for Tourism, Mr Alan Griffiths.<br />
Labores record on tourism is unsurpassed.<br />
Under Labor, international tourism has increased over 150 per cent, with tourism now<br />
worth $ 8.2 billion* in export earnings.<br />
Nearly half a million Australians many of them young Australians are employed in<br />
the tourism indu~ str. A hfuther 200,000 are expected by the end of the decade.<br />
International tourism grew by 9 per cent in the first 11 months of 1992, with<br />
significant gains for employment and the economy.<br />
However, less than one in three of our international visitors spends any nights outside<br />
capital cities and major international gateways.<br />
There is a rich diversity of tourism experiences throughout Australia, but we need to<br />
improve the capacity of regional areas to attract foreign tourists. At the same time we<br />
will be improving the tourism infrastructure for the domestic market.<br />
Under a program of regional tourism development,$ 20.75 million will be spent over<br />
four years on strategic planning and tourism infrastructure in regional Australia.<br />
In addition, Labor will provide $ 4 million over four years to help develop and promote<br />
register of farm-stay accommodation. This will help rural and regional Australia<br />
attract the tourist market it deserves, just as has been the case in many overseas<br />
countries. We will also spend $ 10 million over four years on ecotourismi, and $ 4 million for the<br />
co-operative promotion of the backpacker market. 6669 </p>
<p>To capitalise on the natural advantages of Australia as a centre for marine tourism,<br />
Labor will spend $ 1 million to develop a coastal cruising strategy.<br />
Compare Labor's record of achievement in tourism to the Opposition, whose only plan<br />
is to introduce a new tax which would savage the tourism industry.<br />
Prices for tourist accommodation will rise by between 10 per cent and 14 per cent,<br />
reducing demand and causing job losses.<br />
T-he Opposition has conceded there would be " winners and losers" under Coalition<br />
policies. In Townsville last week they admitted there would be increases in costs in areas " like<br />
mums-and-dads' motels".<br />
Mums-and--dads' motels, and the other small businesses that make up 85 per cent of<br />
the tourism industry, would undoubtedly be worse off under the GST regime.<br />
We have said so all along. Now the Coalition admits it.<br />
BENDIGO February 1993<br />
6710 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
