<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5258</transcript-id>
    <title>PRESS OFFICE TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH CHANNEL 2 MELBOURNE, WEDNESDAY 13 FEBRUARY 1980</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/02/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005258.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS OFFICE TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH CHANNEL 2 MELBOURNE<br />
WEDNESDAY 13 FEBRUARY 1980<br />
Question Sir on what basis was yesterday's Cabinet decision taken?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Well which one do you mean? There were many decisions yesterday,<br />
which part of it?<br />
Question Not to impose trade sanctions against the USSR.<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Well we do have trade sanctions and there was a particular aspect<br />
of yesterday's decision referred to. I think you need to remember<br />
that scientific and cultural exchanges have ceased, that there are<br />
sanctions in relation to the grains, that fisheries<br />
arrangements have been cancelled. Some of those obviously involve<br />
considerable costs~ in different ways. Now one of the things that<br />
I sought to do ove~ rseas and there were senior officials from the<br />
Trade Department with me, which enabled them to have consultations<br />
in the United Stat~ s and in the United Kingdom about the kind of<br />
sanctions and emba ' rgoes that other countries, specifically the<br />
United States and the United Kingdom, believe necessary in the<br />
present circumstances. There is a list of high technology items<br />
called a ' Cocom' list in the jargon which broadly the European<br />
countries adhered to and also Britain and the United States. Now<br />
in our discussions we found quite plainly that broadly in relation<br />
to commodities, there are not on the list. They are not embargoed<br />
by others. There is no point in Australia maintaining an embargo<br />
or a sanction which is not supported by other significant trading<br />
nations. Because that would then be placing the cost on our people<br />
and no cost at all; on the Soviet Union.<br />
Question Well our major dollar earning commodities aren't under a<br />
sanction. Doesn't' that contradict the situation.. Olympic boycott.<br />
Prime minister<br />
No not at all. No because if you want to talk about the Olympic<br />
boycott the important point is, is that this is very evident to the<br />
Soviet people. Trade sanctions can be hidden, especially if they<br />
can buy their commodities somewhere else. But it is the Soviet<br />
Union that has said that the awarding of the Olympic Games to Moscow<br />
in 1980 is a mark of support, a mark indicating the correctness of<br />
the Soviet Union's foreign policy. Now in those terms the Soviet<br />
Union is saying that it is a great social and political event, not<br />
a sporting event. The Soviet Union therefore is<br />
claiming a credit because the Games are in Moscow, which they<br />
certainly do not deserve in the face of their invasion of Afghanistan.<br />
If all our athletes and athletes in the United States and Britain<br />
and Europe go to Moscow, it is not what those athletes say which is<br />
going to be important, it is what the Soviet Union will say to<br />
their own people, because of their presence. And they will say that<br />
2 </p>
<p>that because of their presence those athletes are repudiating the<br />
leadership of the West and supporting the activities, which<br />
includes the foreign policy activities of the Soviet Union. Now.<br />
in the face of Afghanistan, and assuming that their forces are<br />
still in Afghanistan, I really do not see how people can allow<br />
themselves to be put in that position.<br />
Question Well do you think Australia's athletes individually will be<br />
prepared to bear the brunt of Australia's protest by not going...<br />
Prime Minister<br />
It is not the brunt of. Scientific and cultural exchanges have<br />
ceased. That is very important to scientists. It is very important<br />
for artists. It is just as important as the Olympic Games are for<br />
athletes. But it is the Olympic Games which happens once in four<br />
years, the greatest sporting event in the world meant to be nonpolitical.<br />
But le me put it again in another way. How many<br />
Olympic Committees, how many athletes would have gone to Berlin in<br />
1936 if they had known the use to which their presence was going<br />
to be put by Nazi Germany in 1936. These are the sorts of questions<br />
that need to be asked. How importantly does the average person<br />
regard the invasion of Afghanistan? If it was an invasion closer<br />
to us, of Indonesia, of Papua New Guinea, would there then be any<br />
doubt? Does that say that an Afghan life is less important than<br />
another life? How many people have to be killed? How many tens<br />
of thousands of Soviet military people have to be invading in a<br />
country before it is of sufficient importance for people to say<br />
universally, the Olympic Charter has been defied. -The objective of<br />
the Olympic ideal has been despoiled by the host nation.<br />
Question The International Olympic Committee has rejected that idea.<br />
Prime Minister<br />
I know they have. And I believe they are placing sport before the<br />
freedom and indeper~ dence of peoples. And that is not the kind of<br />
priority that governments we have not got the licence to have<br />
that kind of priority.<br />
Question You've said you won't take the passports of Australian athletes.<br />
Will you be embarrassed if they decide to go individually?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Well our own Olympic Committee has to make a decision finally.<br />
As to other Olympic Committees, I will be in discussions with them.<br />
Ellico~ tt will be. And we will have to see what comes out of that. But we<br />
have said basically that we will be putting our views and persuading<br />
as strongly as we possibly can. But we do not want to use the<br />
tactics of the Soviet Union and deny our citizens passports. That<br />
would be using Soviet tactics to achieve our objectives. Obviously<br />
under present circumstances those troops are in A-fghanistan, the<br />
Australian Government will be vastly disappointed if our Olympic<br />
Committee or athletes go to Moscow. We certainly would not do </p>
<p>Prime Minister ( continued)<br />
anything to assist them to go to Moscow. But the arbitrary Soviet<br />
type measures would not be taken. It is designed to keep them away.<br />
Question Do you believe there is any possibility of a Soviet withdrawal by<br />
February Prime Minister<br />
Not really no. They are starting to speak of withdrawal. And the<br />
very fact that they are starting to speak of withdrawal indicates<br />
that the worldwide condemnation of what they have done is starting<br />
to bite. And that is all the more reason to maintain the strength<br />
of that combination and not say because it happened so many weeks<br />
ago, because we are getting used to it, because there is not quite<br />
so much on the television screen, it is therefore less important.<br />
A life lost seven weeks ago remains just as important as it was<br />
seven weeks ago. And we ought not to allow ourselves to diminish<br />
its importance because we get used to the idea and because more<br />
lives have been lost and because the invasion continues.<br />
Question Do you believe continued opposition will be able to retrieve<br />
detente? Prime Minister<br />
I believe it is the only way ultimately of securing integrity and<br />
the peace of the world. Detente, whatever it meant, applied much<br />
more to Europe than in other parts of the world. Over the last<br />
decade the Soviet Union has pressed, either directly or indirectly<br />
through Cuban mercenaries in Africa. In South West Asia, as we<br />
have seen, it has always been their support for Vietnam that has<br />
given Vietnam the military strength to do what it did to do what<br />
it has done. So all of history tells us that if only the democracies,<br />
if only independent minded nations will affirm their position<br />
and support their position early enough, then peace can and will be<br />
secured. But if they say this is not important, we don't have to<br />
worry about this, it doesn't require a reaction, they will get<br />
moved closer and closer to the ultimatedalger-And as I understand it<br />
what President Carter is seeking to do, what major European leaders<br />
in France and Germany and the United Kingdom are seeking to do is<br />
to establish the circumstances in which the world is not moved to<br />
that ultimate danger to prevent it, so that we can secure respect<br />
for the integrity and independence of people.<br />
Question Has your trip convinced you that Australia should adopt a stronger<br />
attitude to Soviet aggression than it has already?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
I think the attitudes that we have taken and the attitudes that we<br />
have expressed have been responsible. I think they are in accord<br />
with the kinds of measures that the United States and many countries<br />
of Europe have taken. We have made some adjustments in the </p>
<p>Prime minister ( continued)<br />
commodities areas as a result of what we learned that other<br />
countries are doing or not doing. That was necessary. But by and<br />
large, what we have done to this point I think is responsible and<br />
I believe it is about right. Over the longer term when I make a<br />
statement to Parliament we will be announcing other measures of a<br />
long term kind in relation to aid to the South Pacific and<br />
increasing defence preparedness. Now these are long term matters.<br />
That will be with us, as I believe, not for a matter of weeks or<br />
months but for years.<br />
Ques tion<br />
So were you disappointed that in certain areas France and West<br />
Germany adopted slightly less hawkish stands than you and President<br />
Carter? Prime minister<br />
I do not think that they have. If you read that communique that<br />
was issued and in reading communiques and looking at words, you<br />
have got to understand the historical perspective with which nations<br />
says things, the way in which they say them and geography imposes<br />
its own differences, history imposes its own differences but<br />
that joint communique between France and Germany was a very strongly<br />
worded communique indeed. It made it perfectly plain, as did<br />
President Carter's State of the Union Message, that if there was<br />
any further move by the Soviets, then obviously France and Germany<br />
stand as one with the United States. It also made it perfectly<br />
plain that all their commitments under the Western alliance would be<br />
met in the discharge of their own responsibilities. That document<br />
was a very severe warning to Moscow. ( end of interview)<br />
CHANNEL 7 MELBOURNE<br />
Question The IOC seems certain to go ahead with the Moscow Olympics. Can<br />
and will Australia modify her stand?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
The Australian Government has stated the view very strongly and we<br />
adhere to that view. Because we believe that the Soviet Union is<br />
not only defying principles on international behaviour. We also<br />
believe that the Soviet Union is defying the basic principles of<br />
the Olympic movement. It is the Soviet Union which has said that<br />
the holding of the Games in Moscow is a great social and political<br />
event. It is the Soviet Union that has said ( and I am not taking<br />
your words) the awarding of the Games to Moscow is a mark of the<br />
correctness of their foreign policy. Against that background I<br />
think it places olympic committees and athletes in enormous<br />
difficulty, but it is not a question of what they say. When you<br />
look at what the Soviet media will be saying to their own people<br />
they will be saying, because these people are here in Moscow, they<br />
are affirming support for our foreign policy and repudiating those<br />
terrible people in the West whether it is Europe, America or<br />
Australia. So in that sense the Soviet Union have politicised the<br />
Games very greatly. </p>
<p>Question But it we go ahead and sell rutile on the basis that if we don't<br />
sell it to them somebody else will doesn't the same argument<br />
apply to the Olympics?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
I think it needs to be understood that decisions we have made in<br />
cultural areas, scientific exchanges, in grains embargoes, in the<br />
ending of fisheries arrangements these represent a very<br />
considerable degree of support for international sanctions where<br />
those sanctions are also getting support of other nations. There<br />
is, what's called in the jargon, a 46ocon-) list, which is a European<br />
list of things that will not be traded with the Soviet Union. Now<br />
one of the things that I was doinq is to establish close consultations<br />
especially with Britain and the United States in these particular<br />
matters. We would want to be basically supporting that general<br />
position. But there is no point, no point at all in Australia's<br />
taking a position in relation to other matters which are not going<br />
to be supported by the wider trading community. That would be an<br />
exercise in futility. But the Olympic Games against the background<br />
of the politicisation of the Games by the Soviet Union is a very<br />
obvious thing, it can not be hidden from the Soviet people. One<br />
of the newspaper columnists this morning referred to the fact that<br />
an earlier Olympic Committee had taken the Games away from Tokyo<br />
because of invasions in another place. How many troops have to be<br />
involved? How many people of a foreign country have to be killed<br />
by the host nation before it is inappropriate for that host nation<br />
still to be host. If I could be hypothetical for a<br />
minute if it was Indonesia that had been invaded or Papua New<br />
Guinea I don't think there would be any doubt. But is there a<br />
qualitative difference between an invasion of Afghanistan and the<br />
invasion of a country closer to home? One has happened and the<br />
other has not and it is a hypothetical circumstance I know. But<br />
I do not think there is any qualitative difference. A life is a life<br />
whose ever it was. And one life is not really more important than<br />
another. But if it was an event closer to home, I do not think any<br />
one in this nation would want to go to Moscow.<br />
Question Fourteen nations boycotted the Melbourne Olympics over Hungary.<br />
Can you expect that many nations to boycott Moscow?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Well let me only say that while I am not at all surprised at the<br />
decision of the International Olympic Committee, I found, not only<br />
in the United States but in the United Kingdom, but also in Europe,<br />
a much greater strength for the opposition to the Olympics than I<br />
think one might gain from reading the newspapers. There are certain<br />
things that have been said about France and Germany. But the<br />
German Foreign Minister has said in very-plain terms if we want<br />
American support over Berlin we are not going to be divided from<br />
the United States ultimately over matters such as the Olympic Gamnes.<br />
Now that seems to me a pointer for an ultimate German position.<br />
Question Bluntly, do you expect as many as 14 nations to boycott. </p>
<p>6<br />
Prime Minister So far as nations are concerned there are upwards<br />
of about forty who have spoken in favour of boycott or movement of<br />
some of the sports. I would hope ultimately that many more than<br />
the 14 would boycott. Because these are matters of great<br />
significance. The invasion of a small non-aligned country which<br />
was offering no threat to anyone, is a really significant event<br />
and I really do not believe we should give the Soviets the triumph of<br />
having our people ignore that. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
