<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10660</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER             THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                DOORSTOP INTERVIEW                PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/07/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...................................................................................................</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I shall certainly miss Mr Hashimoto. We got on very well. We worked</p>
<p> very hard to make the relationship between our two countries even</p>
<p> better, and I regret very much his departure as Prime Minister of</p>
<p> Japan. And at this crucial time I will naturally be keen to work very</p>
<p> closely with his successor.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What needs to be done in Japan now to keep the momentum going of the</p>
<p> financial restructuring that Mr Hashimoto did?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>There must continue to be economic reform because Japan's economy</p>
<p> is so important to the world and most particularly to our region and</p>
<p> Mr Hashimoto introduced many significant reforms and I will certainly</p>
<p> miss his company at international meetings and the particular contribution</p>
<p> that he made towards our relationship. He was a good friend of Australia's</p>
<p> and he was a helping figure for Australia in international conferences</p>
<p> and for that reason, and others, I regret very much his departure.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What affect is it going to have on Japan do you think?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well it depends on the strength of his successor. I'm quite certain</p>
<p> that there will continue to be an expectation of continued economic</p>
<p> reform in Japan and the world will look to Mr Hashimoto's successor</p>
<p> to continue that process.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Any impact on Australia?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, the Japanese economy is very important to Australia. It's</p>
<p> our best market and Japan's economic performance is always important</p>
<p> to us.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, the Tasmanian election looks certain to be called for the</p>
<p> 29th of August. Will you be visiting Tasmania?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I'll do whatever I'm asked to do but I've been</p>
<p> in very close contact with Mr Rundle and I congratulate him on being</p>
<p> willing to face the people, presenting them with a very clear choice.</p>
<p> He's offering a way forward for Tasmania through getting rid</p>
<p> of the State's debt. I applaud that courage. By contrast the</p>
<p> Labor Party is opposing the removal of debt and therefore is looking</p>
<p> backwards.</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
