<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7378</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/08/1988</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007378.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
AUS= TRALIA<br />
FOR MEDIA 17 AUGUST 1988<br />
The following announcement has been made from Buckingham<br />
Palace: " Her Majesty The Queen has graciously approved the<br />
appointment of the Honourable William George Hayden, MP,<br />
to be her Governor-General of the Commonwealth of<br />
Australia. Mr Hayden will be sworn in as<br />
Governor-General on 16 February 1989 after Sir Ninian<br />
Stephen vacates the office"'.<br />
I warmly welcome Her Majesty's appointment of Bill Hayden as<br />
Governor-General to succeed Sir Ninian Stephen. Mr Hayden,<br />
a senior Minister of the Crown, has had a career of great<br />
distinction in the public life of Australia, and is highly<br />
qualified for the task he is to undertake.<br />
Throughout his long and successful public career Mr Hayden<br />
has served the interests of the Australian people with<br />
dedication and humanity. He has been a senior minister in<br />
two governments and was Leader of the Parliamentary Labor<br />
Party for six years. In his most recent portfolio, that of<br />
Foreign Affairs and Trade, he has assiduously and<br />
successfully promoted and furthered his country's interests<br />
in the international arena.<br />
in all these activities Mr Hayden has enjoyed the support<br />
and understanding of his gracious wife, Dallas, and I know<br />
that their combined talents will ensure that the Australian<br />
people continue to be served, as in the past, with the<br />
utmost dedication, commitment and dignity.<br />
Mr Hayden and Mrs Hayden have a family of one son and two<br />
daughters; Kirk, Ingrid, and Georgina.<br />
on behalf of the Government and people of Australia, I<br />
extend very sincere congratulations to Mr and Mrs Hayden. 1221 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
