<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9502</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP MR OACKER, MR HOWARD AND MEDIA MONOPOLIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/03/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009502.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
1K!,<br />
1 STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER. THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
MR PACKER, MR HOWARD AND MEDIA MONOPOLIES<br />
ov. On, My attention has been drawn to a statement issued by Mr<br />
Olive's Kerry Packer, in which he has categorically denied any<br />
deal with Mr Howard on cross media ownership rules.<br />
Well, of course he would.<br />
ivering . ociety. The truth is that Mr Howard. stands for the relaxation of<br />
on with rules which would allow Mr* Packer to control a television<br />
network and major metropolitan newspapers in the same<br />
city. And he has said so. His statements have provided<br />
irrefutable evidence of the position he has taken. and<br />
ive lost would take in office.<br />
Mr Howard has stated that his public and private views on<br />
ted the this matter are the same. His public view is that the<br />
killa nd cross media ownership rules are unnecessary. He has<br />
galan and ienxcplreusdsiengd Ktheer rys amPea ckveierw. privately to media proprietors,<br />
Whether he expresses it publicly or privately. Mr<br />
arnng of Howard's view is jarringly at odds with his Party's<br />
/ as her policy and with the public interest.<br />
I her toAs I said on Sunday. the Australian public will judge who<br />
is the Packer candidate regardless of Mr Howard's<br />
coyness, or Mr Packer's bizarre pretence that he is being<br />
3gainst intimidated.<br />
-iaison<br />
e First The Labor Government stands for media diversity, and the<br />
icil and Coalition under John Howard does not.<br />
I will be spending the next five days in Germany the<br />
world's third largest economy promoting Australia's<br />
is also Irole as a modern economy at the forefront of information<br />
* ote as technology use and development.<br />
. n andAmong the things I will be saying to German business<br />
ittees. people and others is that this technology must be used to<br />
increase diversity, opportunity and equality. It is a<br />
point which both Mr Howard and Mr Packer should note.<br />
BONN 8 MARCH, 1995 5103 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
