<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18511</transcript-id>
    <title>Passing of Murray Rose</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/04/2012</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Australia has lost one of our greatest Olympians today with the passing of Murray Rose, following his courageous battle with cancer.</p>
<p>Murray was a true pioneer of Australian swimming and his impressive feats in the pool helped to shape Australia's destiny as a successful sporting nation. </p>
<p>At his Olympic debut at the Melbourne Games in 1956, Murray emerged as a national hero winning three gold medals. His success on the Olympic stage helped forge Australia's reputation as a country with dynamic sporting talent and great potential. </p>
<p>Murray won a total of six medals from the 1956 and 1960 Olympic Games, and set an impressive 15 world records during the course of his career. </p>
<p>Born in Scotland in 1939, Murray and his family migrated to Australia following World War II. Australian swimming was indelibly changed by the sporting achievements of an extraordinary Scotsman who paved the way for the next generation of swimmers to achieve on the international stage. </p>
<p>Murray will be remembered fondly as a sporting legend who inspired the next generations of elite athletes and helped to propel Australia's sporting success in future Olympics. </p>
<p>There is no disputing that the Olympian was a champion in the pool, but Murray also made an immense contribution to the community through charity work and as patron of the 'The Rainbow Club' which teaches children with a disability to swim. </p>
<p>As an Olympic legend Murray inspired Australians with his gallant feats in the pool. He was a great athlete, a great role model and a great champion. But above all he was a lovely husband and father who will be missed by his wife, Jodie, and his son Trevor. </p>
<p>The thoughts of the nation are with them as they grieve his passing.   </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
