<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4377</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK - THE VICTORIAN STRIKE</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/04/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004377.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Embargoed until 7.00 p. m. 24.4.77<br />
FOR PRESS 24 APRIL 1977<br />
ELECTORATE TALK -THE VICTORIAN STRIKE<br />
Community life throughout the state of Victoria has been<br />
disrupted by the actions of 230 men. Motorists are going<br />
without petrol because a small section of the Transport Workers<br />
Union is confronting oil companies in Victoria and the<br />
Conciliation and Arbitration Commission, both rejecting<br />
indexation and seeking to impose on employers the cost of<br />
health care for which they have already been compensated.<br />
This is taking place at a time when throughout Australia employers<br />
have voluntarily agreed to hold prices, and at a time when the<br />
Government is asking the ACTU President, Mr. Hawke, and the<br />
representatives of other national union bodies, to join in an<br />
overall income and price pause.<br />
In the past, some commentators have accused the Commonwealth<br />
Government of seeking confrontation with the trade union movement.<br />
This is a ludicrous charge. Nothing is further from the<br />
Government's intentions. We do not want confrontation. The<br />
fact is that these few members of the Transport Workers Union<br />
are confronting the people of Victoria.<br />
What the Government wants is industrial harmony. The Government<br />
seeks a co-operative effort by all members of the community to<br />
work together . vtoJrestore economic activity to those levels<br />
which produced the prosperity we took so much for granted in<br />
. the 1950s and 1960s.<br />
The disruption to life in Victoria, because a handful of men<br />
want industrial conditions in advance of the rest of the<br />
community, is of deep concern.<br />
In these circumstances, I have informed the Victorian Premier<br />
that the Commonwealth is willing to assist him in any action<br />
that the State Government might take.<br />
The Victorian Government has the powers to protect the people<br />
of Victoria from such action as that taken by these 230<br />
transport drivers. / I understand, </p>
<p>-2<br />
I understand, and I am gratified to hear, that the Victorian<br />
Premier is considering the legalities of the matter and his<br />
future action.<br />
The dispute primarily affects Victoria, although there is a direct<br />
impact on interstate trade and commerce. In these circumstances, I<br />
have informed the Victorian Premier that Commonwealth officials<br />
would be made available to meet with State Government officials<br />
forthwith to consider how best to protect the people of Victoria<br />
from state-wide dislocation by a small group of people.<br />
I hope that good sense, and an understanding of the fact that we<br />
are a community, will come through to the striking men, and will<br />
lead to an end to the dispute as soon as possible.<br />
The Commonwealth is prepared to use all resources under its<br />
control to alleviate the hardship of the people of Victoria.<br />
Public opinion has been respected by employers since the seven<br />
heads of government of Australia made a call for a voluntary<br />
income and price pause. For example, on Friday, one large overseas<br />
company, Leyland, responded to public opinion by rescinding a<br />
projected price increase.<br />
Last week, on the other hand, I found the President of the Australian<br />
Council of Trade Unions, Mr. Hawke, and the representatives of other<br />
national trade union bodies, quite impervious to public opinion.<br />
They were not prepared to give any sort of-commitment to the objectives<br />
in the heads of government agreement of income and prices restraint.<br />
The demands of these Victorian Transport Workers for a sharp increase in<br />
pay would overturn the well-established principles of indexation. The<br />
claims of these Transport Union members at this time involve the<br />
repudiation of everything heads of government were calling for.<br />
What is the point to a national conference about restraint when<br />
Mr. Hawke evades the issue and withholds even a personal commitment.<br />
At the same time, another small section of the trade union movemen*<br />
is making demands which greatly inconvenience all Victorians andW<br />
which would make a. jidckery of the wage restraint part of the income<br />
and price pause.<br />
It becomes clear why the Government sees little point in Mr. Hawke's<br />
proposed national conference.<br />
I would like to emphasise again that it is important, whether or not the<br />
trade union laaders allow the wage price voluntary restraint to succeed,<br />
to stay within the overall wage setting system.<br />
The Government will not look kindly on any company which gives in to<br />
union pressure of the kind being exerted in Victoria. Any firm which<br />
surrenders to pressure of this sort should know that the Government<br />
would feel disposed to subject its pricing policy to close examination<br />
through the powers which are available to the Government. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
