<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18307</transcript-id>
    <title>Sir Zelman Cowen</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/12/2011</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Australia has lost one of our greatest statesmen with the passing of Sir Zelman Cowen overnight.</p>
<p>Sir Zelman will be remembered for his service to this country in so many ways, no more so than as the 19th Governor General of Australia.</p>
<p>With great dignity and humility, Sir Zelman entered the role in 1977, determined to bring a ‘touch of healing' to our nation. And he did.</p>
<p>The modern prestige of the office can be greatly credited to his healing touch and for this alone I believe we owe him a debt of gratitude.</p>
<p>Sir Zelman's time as Governor General is just one highlight of a long, distinguished and extraordinary life.</p>
<p>Sir Zelman was a great scholar, teacher, author and advocate. He mentored many of his students who today are lawyers, politicians and leaders in industry and business.</p>
<p>He was a tireless servant of our nation, even delaying his Rhodes Scholarship so he could serve in the Royal Australian Navy during the Second World War, which saw him stationed in Darwin during the Japanese attacks.  </p>
<p>Sir Zelman was a proud member of the Australian community, a proud member of the Jewish community and a leader of both. He was a humanitarian whose ongoing dedication to justice and public welfare will remain one of his great legacies.</p>
<p>We will remember him for his warmth, his humility, his integrity, his compassion and the great dignity he brought to public life.</p>
<p>Above all, Sir Zelman was a loving husband and father who will be missed by his wife of 66 years Anna and his children Shimon, Yousef, Kate and Ben.</p>
<p>The thoughts of a nation are with them today.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
