<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8778</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP ENVIRONMENT STATEMENT LAUNCH - ADELAIDE, 21 DECEMBER 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/12/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008778.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
ENVIRONMENT STATEMENT LAUNCH ADELAIDE, 21 DECEMBER 1992<br />
Ladies and gentlemen<br />
It's a pleasure to be in Adelaide. It always is.<br />
As I have said before, it has always seemed to me to be a<br />
brave city built in an environment which is beautiful and<br />
benign, but very often not easy, and not infrequently<br />
harsh. A city poised between the desert and the deep blue<br />
sea. In Adelaide, one is always aware of both the natural<br />
environment and the built one the natural and the human<br />
heritage. It is the ideal place to launch this statement.<br />
Ten months ago, in a completely different environment to<br />
this one, with the birdcalls coming only from the<br />
Opposition, I announced a package of Government initiatives<br />
under the name " One Nation".<br />
The principle of One Nation was strength through<br />
partnerships. Partnerships of all kinds: between<br />
governments local, State and Commonwealth between<br />
business and government, between employees and employers,<br />
between community and nation.<br />
The idea of One Nation was to lay the basis of a stronger<br />
Australia by calling on all our resources, human and<br />
material, our social and economic strengths, our<br />
intellectual strengths.<br />
To include all Australians in the process of nation<br />
building: and, immediately, in the great effort to bring<br />
on economic recovery and the jobs that will go with it.<br />
Today the effects of One Nation continue to be felt as the<br />
projects we announced get underway.<br />
Just as importantly, I believe, the idea of one Nation has<br />
had some influence on the way we Australians think about<br />
the future.<br />
I think One Nation went some way to extending the idea of<br />
cooperation which in the 1980s had developed so effectively<br />
in important areas of the nation's life.<br />
PRIME MINISTER </p>
<p>I think it had some influence on the way we confront<br />
Australia's problems and work towards our national goals.<br />
I say these things today because I think this Statement is<br />
concerned with one of our great national goals the<br />
protection and rehabilitation of our environment.<br />
I say it because in many important regards the Statement<br />
embodies the idea and the aims of One Nation.<br />
And I say it because the spirit which One Nation invoked is<br />
already there in the national environment effort.<br />
Today's launch is in part a celebration of the work already<br />
being done right across Australia, by local government,<br />
community organisations and individuals.<br />
And I take this my opportunity to salute their work.<br />
Nothing better illustrates the interdependence of<br />
Australians and their communities than the environment.<br />
Nothing more emphatically makes the point that all our<br />
state borders and provincial differences still leave one<br />
fact unassailable that this in one continent and one<br />
nation. And, for good or bad, what we do in one part of it very<br />
often effects another.<br />
What one Australian does to the environment effects another<br />
Australian. It makes the point very clearly what we do against each<br />
other weakens Australia.<br />
What we do in partnership strengthens us all.<br />
If there is a dominant theme in this Environment Statement<br />
it is Australia's soil_ and water.<br />
Soil and water are basics of life. If we cannot guarantee<br />
their ' integrity-we breach a fundamental trust to this and<br />
future generations, and to the land we call our own.<br />
In doing so, of course, we also deny ourselves the product<br />
of the land. The degeneration of our soil and water has<br />
already cost us millions of dollars.<br />
Whether it is in the colour and taste of Adelaide's water,<br />
or the blue/ green algae on the Darling, the consequences of<br />
abuse and neglect also come at an incalculable cost to our<br />
confidence and self-regard.<br />
In truth, I don't think we can spoil the essentials of life<br />
and degrade the land without depressing our spirit. </p>
<p>By now everybody is aware that the main focus of the<br />
Environment Statement is the Murray-Darling our greatest<br />
river system, a huge national resource, and a part of<br />
Australia indelibly inscribed in our history and culture.<br />
Nothing better illustrates the network of environmental<br />
interdependence than the Murray-Darling a national artery<br />
which begins life in Queensland and sustains life in South<br />
Australia. At present the Murray Darling is being seriously degraded.<br />
No one should underestimate the environmental and economic<br />
costs of this degradation.<br />
As the statement says: " This has already cost hundreds of<br />
millions of dollars, poisoned a wellspring of our heritage,<br />
and destroyed huge areas of formerly productive land."<br />
At present, ten towns along the Darling are responsible for<br />
ninety per cent of sewage phosphate entering the river.<br />
This will end.<br />
With Australian technology we will eliminate these sources<br />
of pollution and so improve water quality and reduce the<br />
potential for blue/ green algae.<br />
While the repair and protection of the Murray Darling Basin<br />
is a centrepiece of the initiatives announced today, the<br />
Government's Statement reflects the fact that the<br />
community's concern and the environment's needs are broad,<br />
and getting broader. The Statement announces:<br />
Our intention to create a national system of marine<br />
and land reserves.<br />
A comprehensive study of the environmental and<br />
economic values of the. Shoalwatez-Bay area.<br />
The nomination of the Riversleigh fossil site and the<br />
Naracoorte Caves for World Heritage listing.<br />
More research into alternative energy sources, such as<br />
ethanol and solar energy.<br />
Four more Cooperative Research Centres with an<br />
environmental focus.<br />
An additional eight million dollars for the control of<br />
weeds and feral animals, with another five million<br />
specifically for the control of mimosa pigra which is<br />
threatening to invade Kakadu.<br />
Finance for the purchase of Calperum pasto-ral lease<br />
near Renmark to ensure its protection and<br />
sustainability. </p>
<p>State of the environment reportinct and other<br />
educatio-nal ti6oolsni-essary for Governments and the<br />
community to make informed decisions.<br />
And of course a great deal more.<br />
Not all of these are high profile or controversial matters,<br />
but they are all initiatives of substance, all initiatives<br />
which build on what we have been doing, all links in the<br />
environmental protection chain.<br />
Of course there is more to be done than any Government<br />
could do in a Statement such as this.<br />
But you can be assured that we will keep working away at<br />
the list.<br />
For too long the myth that. jobs-and environmental<br />
protection are incompatible has tended to govern our<br />
thinking. In truth, while some conflicts will inevitably remain for<br />
Governments and communities to resolve, it is increasingly<br />
evident that the economic sustainability of Australia is<br />
dependent on the environmental sustainability of Australia.<br />
Whether you're talking about tourism or our rural<br />
industries, or vital water supplies, we are all now<br />
conscious of the need to maintain our natural resource base<br />
to sustain them.<br />
In other cases, like waste management and re-cycling, the<br />
protection of the environment itself constitutes a booming<br />
industry.<br />
The point is made in the statement: " the drive for<br />
environmentally friendly industries and the protection of<br />
our environment is part of the economic drive part of the<br />
international competitive drive in which Australia is<br />
t engaged." So we will continue to look at ways to achieve the dual<br />
objectives of _ environmental protection and job creation.<br />
I was very pleased to receive recently a proposal for a<br />
" green jobs" strategy jointly developed by the ACTU and the<br />
Australian Co6nservatidon Foundation.<br />
You can be sure that the Government is well-disposed to<br />
this sort of initiative and we will be giving the proposal<br />
our urgent consideration and expect to be able to help<br />
bring the ideas to fruition.<br />
Now no doubt there will those who say that an ACTU/ ACF<br />
_. 1iaison__ 1s an unholy alliance.<br />
But I would argue that in fact it is one of the natural<br />
partnerships on which we can build a national response. </p>
<p>0 Really, it is no longer acceptable, or even possible, to<br />
retreat to ideology or prejudice or slogans as far as the<br />
environment is concerned.<br />
The environment is a central, main game issue in which all<br />
Australians are involved.<br />
Living in the built environment might lead most of us away<br />
from this conclusion but in fact, as the people of<br />
Adelaide would know very well, we who live in the towns and<br />
cities do not escape our relationship with the natural<br />
environment. We depend on it for our resources.<br />
And for the national wealth in which all of us share.<br />
For our recreational pleasure and spiritual inspiration.<br />
For our soil, air and water.<br />
The environment provides us with the basics of life.<br />
This Statement is informed by that simple fact.<br />
All our lives will be better and Australia will be stronger<br />
for the things that it will do.<br />
Thank you for having me today. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
