<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>260</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: AUSTRALIA DAY MESSAGE BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R.G MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/01/1961</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000260.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS AUSTRALIA DAY MESSAGE<br />
BY THE PflIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R. G. MENZIES<br />
To-day, on our 175rd birthday, we can look back with<br />
pride and thankfulness on the vision, energy, and ability<br />
of those who have gone before us. They helped to make<br />
Australia the wonderful country in which we live. It is<br />
our task to carry on their good work in the march to fullest<br />
nationhood. The name Australia is one in which wu should have an<br />
overwhelming pride. Whfien we mention it we should think of the<br />
benefits our country has conferred upon us and our duties to<br />
it, and not be like the few who continuously thirk in terms<br />
of self-interest.<br />
We who live in Australia derive not from the weak, but<br />
from the strong. Our forbears were adventurous people and<br />
their determination carved out the structure which is the<br />
base of our efforts for the future.<br />
In the years ahead we will certainly have problems,<br />
but what nation has not had its problems? We have surmounted<br />
them in the past and we will overcome them in the future.<br />
Growing achievement will require energy and skill, but never<br />
yet has there been an A-ustralian, worthyof the name, who lacked<br />
either of these great qualities.<br />
So, on this our birthday, I ask hundreds of thousands<br />
of newcomers from overseas who are working sidu by side with<br />
us, to share in this heritage of which w4 are so proud.<br />
With the Australian flcS at the masthead, each and everyone<br />
of us should celebrate this great day in a fitting manner.<br />
We should not regard it as just another holiday. It is in<br />
fact a day of joy, but it is above all a day cf dedication.<br />
CANBERRA<br />
January 26, 1961. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
