<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3447</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT ON THE ECONOMY</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/11/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003447_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
* EMBARGO: 8.00 P . M. 7<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
STATEMENT ON THE ECONOMY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON. E. G. WHITLAM.. M. P.,<br />
HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES, CANBERRA, A. C. T.<br />
TUESDAY 12 NOVEMBER 1974<br />
Introducing the Budget in September the Treasurer emphasised<br />
the importance of maintaining the utmost flexibility in responding<br />
to economic developments. The Treasurer stated: " Should the need<br />
arise, we stand ready during the year to take action on the<br />
expenditure or the revenue side of the Budget to give a quick<br />
stimulus to demand and employment".<br />
Our underlying purpose is to create conditions for<br />
co-operation and restraint. The measures I shall announce tonight<br />
are designed to further that aim. The Australian economy is beset<br />
by the twin problems of rapid inflation and rising unemployment.<br />
We share these problems with all comparable economies. The t 4o<br />
problems are universal but their concurrence is unique in modern<br />
times. The Australian Government, therefore, like the Governments<br />
of all comparable countries, faces problems of economic management<br />
of unparalleled complexity, uncertainty a~ nd difficulty. For all<br />
governments and for most nations these are testing times. In the<br />
final analysis the test concerns not the basic strength of national<br />
economies and Australia's basic strength is indisputable but<br />
the strength of nerve and will on the part of governments and people<br />
alike. It is essential therefore that the people of Australia<br />
should understand what is happening and why. Concern, real and<br />
genuine concern, must not give way to despair, for the situation<br />
is '. fficulta nd changes are occurring with unprecedented speed.<br />
They z~ i.-e not beyond control. The problems of the rapid rise in<br />
unemployment and continuing steep rise in prices and costs are<br />
interlocked. The rate of wage and salary increases has easily<br />
outstripped the rate of increase in pri * ces. The consequential<br />
squeeze on profits has been sharp. This has in turn led to a loss<br />
of confidence by business in its ability to obtain an adequate<br />
return on capital in an inflationary environment.<br />
Employees can price themselves out of the market as<br />
effectively as business can. There are signs that this is happening.<br />
As the Treasurer said recently, in current circumstances:<br />
" One -an's larger pay packet may mean another man's job."-<br />
Employt_-. s are economising on labour, scaling down their operations<br />
and their investment and hence the employment opportunities they<br />
provide. The rapid increase in wage costs which businesses have<br />
experienced introduces3 an element of uncertainty in business<br />
oalculations which greatly increases the risk involved in making<br />
new investments. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
The Government's immediate concern must be to stop<br />
and reverse the downturn. The decline in employment and overtime<br />
now evident will reflect itself in a weakening of demand in the<br />
near future. If unchecked, the downturn would begin feeding on<br />
itself. The Government has decided therefore to provide a further<br />
demand stimulus to the economy. The Government also intends to<br />
take action which strikes at the root of the cause of the present<br />
downturn, the high rate of inflation and the decline in business<br />
profitability. What is needed is a stimulus to the economy which<br />
increases demand whilst at the same time abating cost pressures<br />
and enhancing private profitability.<br />
The Government has already taken a number of decisions<br />
on the exchange rate and on the supply of money the most recent<br />
of which were announced on Sunday by the Treasurer -which will<br />
substantially lift business confidence.<br />
These measures add up to a very substantial relaxatioi<br />
obfe commoen etaa rgyo odp oldeiacly aenads iefri nainnc itahle mcoonntdhist ioanhse adc ant hbaen tehxepye ctheadv e tob* een<br />
in the recent past. In the past week the Governor of the Reserve<br />
Bank has written to the banks requesting them to increase<br />
appreciably their rate of new lending and I1 would expect to see<br />
a prompt response by the banks. Some savings banks are already<br />
stepping up the rate of their housing loan approvals.<br />
The new measures I announce tonight are designed to:<br />
Firstly, maintain consumer demand through a substantial<br />
reduction in personal income tax.<br />
Secondly, attack inflation by reducing the pressure for<br />
wage in,.--ases through a substantial improvement in after tax<br />
take home pay next year and specifically to break the wage-price<br />
spiral by giving business a breathing space in wage demands based<br />
on price increases in the December quarter.<br />
Thirdly, enhance profitability by a reduction in company<br />
tax, by requesting the Prices-Justification Tribunal to give<br />
particular consideration to the adequacy of return on capital<br />
and by urgently investigating the implications of rapid inflation<br />
for the taxation of companies; and<br />
Pourthly, support particular industries where special<br />
problems e emerging.<br />
The proposeL. -easures together with the announcement<br />
made by the Treasurer on Sunday night represent decisive action<br />
to stimulate demand and employment, to contain the growth in<br />
money wages and to restore business confidence. </p>
<p>-3-<br />
Personal Income Tax<br />
The Government has decided to reduce further personal<br />
income tax. Honourable Members will recall that in the 1974-75<br />
Budget it was proposed that the rate scale be restructured to<br />
reduce income tax payable by $ 370 million on a full year basis.<br />
We now propose to restructure the rate scale to apply to 1974-75<br />
. income in order to reduce income tax payable by an additional<br />
$ 650 million. In total, then, the rate scale now to apply to<br />
1974-75 incomes involves a tax cut of over $ 1,000 million.<br />
Additional tax relief was provided in the Budget in the<br />
form of a rebate of dependents' allowances for low income<br />
families and deductibility of mortgage interest payments -these<br />
will cost the revenue close to $ 200 million per annurta.<br />
My announcement tonight thus brings the personal incore<br />
tax cuts provided for by the Government this year to about<br />
$ 1,200 million. The new restructuring of the rate scale I am announcing<br />
ton~ ight will have the effect of increasing the take home pay of<br />
most full-time employees earning up to average weekly earnings<br />
by about 3 per cent. There will be lesser reductions at higher<br />
incomes. The precise details of the new rate scale are being<br />
made available separately.<br />
As a consequence of the changes to the rate scale<br />
. announced in the Budget as further modified by my announcement<br />
toniqht, there will be very large reductions in tax payable by<br />
the erage wage-earner. Let me give two examples, both relating<br />
to a 4riyer with a dependant wife and two children and with<br />
other cu~ icessional deductions equal to 10 per cent of annual income.<br />
Such a taxpayer, earning $ 100 a week, would be liable<br />
for an annual tax of $ 568 on the basis of the 1973-74 rate scale.<br />
The new rate scale and the low income rebate will reduce this<br />
liability by $ 304 to $ 264, or by 54 per cent. His after-tax<br />
pay will be about 6 per cent more than it would have been without<br />
the tax cuts. A taxpayer in similar family circumstances earning $ 140<br />
a we would be liable for an annual tax of $ 1,160 on the basis<br />
of the 7 3-74 rate scale. The new rate scale will reduce this<br />
liability $ 283-to $ 877, or by 24 per cent. His after-tax pay<br />
will be over 4 per cent greater than it would have been without<br />
the tax cuts. It is proposed that the new rate scale announced tonight<br />
will be reflected in PAYE deductions on pay days after 1 January<br />
1975. PAYE deductions made from January on to the end of the<br />
financial year will be set at levels designed as far as possible<br />
to give the taxpayer the whole benefit of the new tax reduction<br />
in respect of income year 1974-75 in the January-June half year.<br />
There will be, in consequence, an even more substantial percentage<br />
increase in take-home pay for most employees. </p>
<p>Housing Loan Interest: PAYE Deductions<br />
The scheme of housing interest deductions for income<br />
tax purposes is to apply in-respect of interest payments after<br />
1 July 1974 as announced in the Treasurer's Budget Speech. It<br />
is intended that as from the first pay-day after 1 January<br />
employees will be able to arrange with their employers for<br />
adjustment of pay-as-you-earn instalments to allow for the effect<br />
of the interest deduction. This will reinforce the impact of<br />
general tax reduction by providing a further boost in take-home<br />
pay. INFLATION<br />
These measures are designed to achieve the first<br />
objective I mentioned earlier namely the maintenance of<br />
consumer demand. The substantial reduction in personal income<br />
tax, however, bears directly upon the second objective the<br />
attack on inflaticn by reducing wage pressures.<br />
At present, applications are before the Australian<br />
Conciliation and Arbitration Commission for the introduction<br />
of wage indexation in other words, the automatic adjustment<br />
of wages to price increases. The Australian Government will<br />
play an active and positive role in these proceedings to support<br />
wage indexation on the basis of full compensation for price<br />
increases on a percentage basis up to the level of average<br />
weekly earnings, with a flat rate adjustment for higher incomes.<br />
The recent level of increases in wages and salaries,<br />
bc; in terms of award and over-award rates, has been due in<br />
part A-he need for trade unions to protect their members<br />
agains. ubstantial future price increases.<br />
A system of wage indexation would have the advantage<br />
of protecting the real piirchasing power of wages anad , Aarie. s<br />
generally. Th hearing of claii, coming from the ACT3 ; ind othcr<br />
employee organi,, itions is to proceed during this month and in<br />
December, and the Govrnment is hopuful fcr a " ecision from the<br />
Commission at the earliest possible date.<br />
The Government is aware that tbrrr ri-dy be an understandable<br />
iL t-' ng amongst employees that too long a period will pass before<br />
the i csion is able to announce its decision. The Government<br />
will, thi. efore, -make submissions before the Arbitration Commission<br />
to the effc. t that the changes in the rate of income tax, announced<br />
in my statement ton. should be regarded by the Comiaission as<br />
compensation for the increase in the cost of living which is<br />
expected for the December t 1974. In other words, the<br />
Australian Government will be submitting to the Com-ission, in<br />
connection with the most appropriate date for the introduction<br />
of cost of living adjustments, that the anticipated increase<br />
in the Consumer Price Index for the three months October, November<br />
and December 1974, will be compensated for by the increases in<br />
take-hox: pay resulting directly from the reduction in personal<br />
income tax announced this evening. </p>
<p>The Government expects that the trade union Imovement,<br />
in the interests of its members, will co-operate with it by<br />
seeking the introduction of wage indexation in a way that will<br />
minimise inflationary pressures and avoid unjustified wage<br />
claims. Increases based on price movements in the December<br />
quarter, whether by arbitrated decision or by agreement would,<br />
in the Government's view, not be justified. Present trends<br />
suggest that the commencement of a system of wage indlexation<br />
would be fair and reasonable if it began with the Consumer Price<br />
Index . figure for the March quarter 1975.<br />
The Australian Government will put to the Commission<br />
that it should take particular account of the tax reductions<br />
which are designed to protect the take-home pay of employees.<br />
To introduce cost of living adjustment on the basis of price<br />
increases in the present quarter would involve double countingit<br />
would continue the dangerous cost and price increases<br />
harmful not only to the whole community but to the employment<br />
prospects of wage and salary earners.<br />
Inflation must be restrained to protect jobs as<br />
much as anything else. We will be making it clear wherever<br />
possible that money wage restraint is essential. Employees<br />
and their representatives will be fortified in the knowledge<br />
that steps are being taken in other areas to maintain and advance<br />
real living standards. The re-introduction of cost of living<br />
adjustments would ensure that the real wages of employees are<br />
protected in the years ahead. In the transition period the<br />
Government tax cuts will preserve the value 6f their take-home<br />
pay. The Budget tax cuts took effect in PAYE deductions this<br />
month January pay packets will in addition reflect broadly<br />
double the cut we have now made in the rates announced in the<br />
Budget. Those employees arranging with their employers for<br />
adjustment of PAYE instalments to allow for the effect housing<br />
interest paymel-. : s will enjoy a further increase in take-hom-e pay..<br />
These benefits and the submission to be made to the<br />
Arbitration Commission about the appropriate date for commencing<br />
col-t of living adjustments, are actions and proposals which<br />
e,. sentially go hand in hand and are meant to be related to each<br />
other. They will give the business community a brea-thing space<br />
from claims whilst ensuring that real wages are more than<br />
maintaine). We have to break the vicious circle of prices chasing<br />
wages and w-ges chasing prices.<br />
The Government is concerned that all employee organisations,<br />
all of Australia's employE-o-. ' Thould understand an&amp;. be fully<br />
informed of the Government's policy on pay fixation and related<br />
issues. The policies outlined in the Budget and thzo new measures<br />
announced tonight will improve the real wages of employees and are<br />
in this sense an-alternative to wage claims. This approach will<br />
be discuISsed with employee organisations of all types and needs<br />
to be explained to all trade union members. In looking at the<br />
Government's proposal to offer a tax cut in compensation for the<br />
cost of living changes for October, November and December of this<br />
year, it must not be overlooked that under this Labor Government<br />
wages and salaries have, in fact, more than kept pace with price<br />
increases. </p>
<p>-6-<br />
The past year has been a year in which very substantialV<br />
wage claims have been granted. In the 12 months to August 1974,<br />
the average award rate has risen by 43 per cent for adult females<br />
and by 27 per cent for adult males. The latest Consumer Price<br />
Index figures available show an increase in prices of 16 per cent<br />
in the year to the September quarter 1974. The important fact is<br />
that, despite a period of rising prices, wage earners have had a<br />
good increase in their standard of living in that time.<br />
I intend to encourage a program of visits by Ministers<br />
and Government Members of Parliament to speak at trade union<br />
forums. They will outline the policies and objectives of the<br />
Government. This program of visits is in keeping with the<br />
principle of consultation and discussion which trade union<br />
organisations have often emphasised as being desirable.<br />
The visits to trade union organisations will be a twoway<br />
process, with Ministers or Labor M. Ps also receiving<br />
comments and questions on matters of interest and concern. It<br />
is expected that visits will be made to a variety of employee<br />
organisations including Trades and Labour Councils in each State,<br />
White Collar and Public Service Organisations, Annual Conferences<br />
of trade unions, Federal and State Executive meetings, and also<br />
meetings of rank and file members during factory lunch-time periods<br />
etc. Members of this Government have, of course, addressed<br />
many such gatherings. The opportunity which the Government's<br />
new proposals gives us to break the wage-price spiral requires<br />
a more systematic effort in the areaof contact and consultation<br />
with trade union organisations.<br />
The ] L i. vate Sector<br />
xhe third objective I stated earlier is to restore<br />
business confidence by enhancing profitability. The Government's<br />
decision to cut personal taxes for some wage increases is<br />
particularly sicnificant for the private sector, both in terms<br />
of costs and demand.<br />
Business profits are being adversely affected by<br />
flagging demand and by the effects of inflation on cash flows<br />
and the replacement costs of assets. One consequence of declining<br />
profitability of business generally has been that the capacity<br />
and williingness of business to undertake new investment have been<br />
eroded. The Government recognises these problems and is<br />
determined to correct Lhem. The measures I have already<br />
announced should adequately deal with the decline in demand,<br />
even if, as is always the case, their full impact will be felt<br />
only after a lag. However, ultimately these measures will be<br />
ineffective unless they are accompanied by restored business<br />
confidence and profitability. It is an essential part of the<br />
Government's present strategy that we should stop the profits<br />
slide, restore confidence and encourage renewed private investment.<br />
7" 7 </p>
<p>-7-<br />
The Treasurer announced in his Budget Speech that the<br />
rate of tax on both public and private companies in 1974-75, in<br />
respect of 1973-74 income, was to be 47 per cent. The public<br />
company rate was already at that level and, as foreshadowed in<br />
the 1973-74 Budget, the private company rate was to be increased<br />
from 45 to 47 per cent to bring the private and company rates<br />
together. The Government has now decided that the rate on public<br />
and private companies in respect of 1973-74 income will be<br />
per cent instead of 47 per cent. The public company rate will<br />
therefore be reduced to 2 per cent below last year's level, and<br />
the proposed increase in the private company rate will not take<br />
place. The Budget proposal would have applied a common rate to<br />
public and private companies; that will still occur, but the<br />
common rate will be 45 per cent and not 47 per cent. A consequential<br />
reduction will be made to the rate on 1974-75 income of a<br />
superannuation fund that does not observe the 30/ 20 rule.<br />
The 1974-75 financial year rate for taxable income of co-operative<br />
and non-profit companies in excess of $ 10,000 will be 45 per cent<br />
in lieu of 47 per cent.<br />
Prices Justification Tribunal<br />
I now turn to the continuing role of the Prices<br />
Justification Tribunal. Since the Tribunal came into operation<br />
in August 1973, it has played an important part in our efforts<br />
to curb inflation. I believe that it has been very effective<br />
in concentrating the attention of companies on the need to restrain<br />
cost and pr. ice: increases C mpanies with wage and other cost<br />
increases in the pipe-line are now finding that these increases<br />
ar,. -eing. examined more critically than they may have expected.<br />
Thert -a be no doubt that the Tribunal has been successful in<br />
restra_ _ ng prices below the level to which they would have risen<br />
if the Government had not established the Tribunal.<br />
The inflationary problem is now more complex than when<br />
the Tribunal wds established. Rapid inflation is now accompanied<br />
by rising unemployment and a falling away in the private investment<br />
on which economic growth and our continued prosperity greatly<br />
depend. One of the problems is that, in Considering new investment<br />
pro4* Acts, business is concerned about the prospects of maintaining<br />
wortnv. " le returns, not just in the immediate future, but over the<br />
whole eco'-mic life of the investments concerned, subject, of course,<br />
to normal market risks. The rapid inflation that we have experienced<br />
has added to the un. rtainties.<br />
I am therefore writing to the Prices Justification<br />
Tribunal to indicate the Government's view that, in the present<br />
economic circumstances, it should now give particular attention<br />
to the problems of sustaining and stimulating an adequate level<br />
of private investment and of maintaining rates of return on capital<br />
which will induce the new investment required to maintain economic<br />
growth and employment. </p>
<p>-8-<br />
The Tribunal will1 of course continue to act in accordance<br />
with its statutory responsibilities to ensure that prices are not<br />
set at levels which are higher than are properly justifiable and<br />
that companies are not passing on in priL'ces avoidable increases<br />
in costs.<br />
Tax Inquiry It is well known that rapid infl~ ation has a distorting<br />
effect on the taxation paid by persons and, in some circumstances,<br />
companies. The Government recognises that companies can be<br />
adversely affected by taxation treatment of depreciation and st-ck<br />
valuations. The tax measures I have announced tonight are direted<br />
towards meeting a particular situation but, in the longer run, it<br />
is important that attention in depth be paid to the question of<br />
whether there ought to be any changes in our taxation system to<br />
take account of the effects of inflation.* Accordingly, the<br />
Government proposes to appoint a panel to report, by May 1975,* on<br />
questions relating to the effects of inflation on taxation paid by<br />
persons and companies. Membership of the panel and the detailed<br />
terms of reference will be announced at a later date.<br />
The fourth group of measures which I wish to mention<br />
this evening invovles support for particular industries where<br />
special problems are emerging. The Government is concerned to<br />
preserve employment opportunities whilst ensuring that these<br />
interests are balanced against the nation's longer term economic<br />
interests. Housing The Government has decided to increase further the<br />
availa Lity of finance for housing.<br />
I mention that the Government has already approved no<br />
less than $ 310 million for welfare housing purposes in 1974-75<br />
and, after carefully reviewing the situation in Queensland, we have<br />
now agreed to provide a further $ 8 million for welfare housing in<br />
that State. These funds, which include $ 127 million to be channelled<br />
primarily through terminating building societies, are over 40 per<br />
cent more than those made available last year.<br />
In the private sector considerable scope for increased<br />
lendinñ, for housing by the savings banks was provided in early<br />
Septembez with the amendments to the Banking ( Saving Banks)<br />
Regulations. At the same time the savings banks were requested<br />
to increase their lc7, n approvals for housing.<br />
These amendments ha--e enabled the savings banks to increase<br />
substantially their lending for housing and, on present indications,<br />
loan approvals by the banks in the December quarter could be as much<br />
as 50 per cent higher than in the September quarter. </p>
<p>-9-<br />
In addition to the stimulus being provided to housing<br />
activity in both the public and private sectors by these measures,<br />
we consider there is a need to further supplement the flow of<br />
finance for housing. Accordingly, we now irntend to introduce<br />
legislation at an early date to appropriate $ 150 million to the<br />
savings banks for lending for housing.<br />
The detailed arrangements will be discussed with the<br />
savings banks but the funds will be provided directly to them<br />
by the Government on terms and conditions to be agreed with the<br />
banks. They will be lent by the savings banks on the same terms<br />
and conditions as apply to normal savings bank -loans financed<br />
by the banks from their own sources. They will be available to<br />
men and women for the acquisition or erection of homes and for<br />
extensions to existing homes.<br />
I should make it clear that we gave careful considerat. i' 7n<br />
to the possibility of channelling some of these funds through'the<br />
permanent building societies. However, in view of the more even<br />
geographic spread of savings banks and for ease of administration,<br />
we have decided to limit the scheme to the savings banks. The<br />
permanent building society movement has the Government's full<br />
support in the role it is playing in provjiding home finance and<br />
we hope that societies will be able to expand lending from their<br />
own resources. The purpose of the additional $ 150 million is to provide<br />
an additional quick-acting stimulus to activity and employment<br />
in the home building industry. The funds made available to them<br />
under this measure will be used by the savings banks to increase<br />
further their rate of housing lending beyond the increased rate<br />
th, have already been asked to achieve following bhe recent<br />
amenu -ts of the Banking ( Savings Banks) Regulations.<br />
The measure will provide an appropriate additional<br />
stimulus to the building industry at this time. It is a shortterm<br />
measure neared to current circumstances. The Co%;-rrrnevt is<br />
determined, however, to avoid a return to the boom conditions<br />
which were beneficial neither to the community nor to the industry.<br />
Home builders can plan ahead w ' ith confidence that the<br />
vernment intends to ensure that loans w b~ e available to<br />
:. ome purchasers and that the significant increase in take-home<br />
pa. -~ articularly from home interest tax deductibility, will<br />
7 enabj. L,. lirchasers to service their loans. </p>
<p>Motor Vehicles The Government has been considering the long-term<br />
future of the motor vehicle industry for many months. The<br />
public debate and inquiry has been more open and intensive<br />
than any other industrial decision making process.<br />
I am pleased to announce that the Government has<br />
approved in principle a long-term motor vehicle policy. In<br />
essence, the existing motor vehicle plans will be replaced<br />
by a single, simplified, lower content plan which will encourage<br />
longer production runs by both vehicle manufacturers and component<br />
producers. In addition, the Japanese motor vehicle industry has<br />
been invited to examine the new policy with a view to expanding<br />
its operations in Australia. As part of the long run policy and<br />
also because of the very high level of car imports ( comprising<br />
over 40 per cent of registrations), relevant import duties will<br />
be generally increased by 10 per cent. These duties will be<br />
lowered again when imports fall to or below 20 per cent of<br />
registrations over a designated period. Details of the proposals<br />
will be announced in a separate statement.<br />
This decision should have an immediate effect but I wish<br />
to emphasise that this effect will occur within the context of<br />
a long-term plan for the development and rationalisation of the<br />
industry. Textiles* The Government has paid particular -attention to the<br />
present difficulties of the textile industry. It has established<br />
th, " 1exti' les Authority within the Industries Assistance Commission<br />
to " nine cases, under the GATT arrangement regarding international<br />
trade textiles, for restraints by countries exporting textiles<br />
to Australia. Following the Authority's first report in July,<br />
restraints have been negotiated for a wide range of knitted and<br />
woven apparel. I have just received the Authority's s:: cond report<br />
covering yarns, knitted fabrics and towelling and will announce<br />
action on this in the very near future. I expect to refer further<br />
textiles matters to the Authority later this week. At the same<br />
time the Commission is reviewing the whole of the long-term<br />
tective requirements of the Australian c?. bthing industry.<br />
m. L-e textiles industry is, of course, vitaliy important to the<br />
e'-c-n my of a number of country areas and the Government has<br />
recel1announced a scheme of special assistance, including the<br />
direct pc;_ ment of subsidies, to firms which have been affected by<br />
certain Government decisions.<br />
Beef Another industry in which there is very great uncertainty<br />
at the present time is the cattle industry. We are aware of the<br />
very severe problems which have been caused by the closing off of<br />
many overseas markets. We are examining as a matter of urgency<br />
representations we have received from the industry seeking help<br />
for those producers who have been hardest hit by these developments.<br />
Any such assistance of course needs to be administratively feasible<br />
and directed to those least able to meet current problems. </p>
<p>-11-<br />
Loan Guarantees The Government's adjustment assistance program is<br />
designed to assist firms to restructure their activities from<br />
uneconomic to economic areas of production. Loan guarantees<br />
are an integral part of the structural adjustment assistance<br />
measures announced on 23 April 1974. Like the Government's<br />
other structural adjustment measures, they are available to firms<br />
adversely affected by prescribed structural changes under the<br />
criteria announced on 23 April 1974.<br />
It was the Government's original intention to<br />
introduce legislation providing for loan guarantees with the<br />
legislation to establish a Structural Adjustment Board.<br />
However rather than wait for the legislation to establish the<br />
Structural Adjustment Board, which will take some time to prep':.<br />
the Government has decided to introduce separate legislation<br />
providing for loan guarantees in the current Parliament session.<br />
Conclusion The Australian Government fully recognises the crucial<br />
importance of the private sector in the development of Australia.<br />
It is not just the importance we attach to the private sector as<br />
the greatest source of employment. We are deeply aware that in<br />
a mixed economy such as ours the prosperity of the private sector<br />
is basic to the Government's social objectives. The program of<br />
social reform embarked upon by the present Government cannot be<br />
achieved without a strong and growing private sector. Nothing<br />
could be further from the truth than that we are anti-business<br />
or stile to business; we recognise the interdependence of all<br />
secto f the economy.<br />
It is no solution to our current problems, as some would<br />
have it, that we cut Government spending. If we were to take such<br />
a decision now we would risk aggravating unemployment-, not to mention<br />
undermining the confidence of that section of the business sector<br />
which depends on Government orders. A reduction of Budgetary<br />
expenditure would of necessity have a primary impact upon areas<br />
which provide demand for products of the private sector. Cuts<br />
in Government spending will simply aggravat: . jur present problems.<br />
Our program of government expenditure has been achieved without<br />
excc-"-ive increases in the number of public servants. The staff<br />
ceilin, ' ontrol on the Australian Public Service will be retained<br />
in a modi-ed form. This will be the subject of a separate stazement.<br />
Further, an. it cannot be stressed too often, the<br />
quality of life in Australia the real standard of living of all<br />
Australians cannot be main-ained, let along rai. ed, unless<br />
governments accept responsibility for community services which<br />
individuals can no longer provide adequately for themselves.<br />
L^ </p>
<p>-12-<br />
Mr Speaker: The Government will have to maintain its close<br />
surveillance of the economy and retain its flexibility for<br />
the months ahead. We believe the new stimulus to the economy<br />
is appropriate to the problems we face. We must be wary of<br />
the possible re-emergence of excess demand pressures within<br />
our economy. The new measures announced tonight are designed<br />
to ensure that the private sector* continues to grow.<br />
Equally we believe these measures, building upon<br />
the continuing program expressed in the Budget, provide a<br />
sound basis for co-operation with all sections of the community<br />
and between all sections of the community in the undoubtedly difficult<br />
days which lie immediately ahead. The requirements of a mixed<br />
economy in a democratic society are never simple, never easy.<br />
The whole nature of such a society involves a tremendous range of<br />
competing choices in making decisions the decisions made bygovernment,<br />
the decisions made by organisations, the decisions<br />
made by individuals. The pressures created by these competing demands are<br />
now world-wide. Not for the first time, aLn Australian Labor<br />
Government finds itself in power at a time of profound international<br />
difficulty. As in those other times, the spirit of the nation is<br />
as important to ultimate success as the policies of the elected<br />
government. Quite apart from their economic thrust, the measures<br />
I have announced tonight are aimed at strengthening the spirit<br />
of national co-operation and confidence, by . showing Australians<br />
that they have elected a government firm and vigorous in meeting<br />
the challenges of our time difficult times indeed, yet like allsuchi<br />
time-s, a test for the essential great qualities of this nation,<br />
a tes* which together, Government, Parliament and people, I am<br />
confidt-at we shall meet. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
