<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11452</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER            THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP            DOORSTOP INTERVIEW, DUBBO                     SUBJECTS: East Timor, General Wiranto, services in the bush, Employment             National, BHP, David Irving, Badgery&amp;#146;s Creek, Telstra.</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/02/2000</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...................................................................................................</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What's your reaction to the events in Indonesia, Mr Howard?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I think the whole world would like to give Indonesia an opportunity</p>
<p> of going through an effective examination of what occurred and the signs</p>
<p> at this stage are that that is occurring. I can't prejudge the outcome</p>
<p> of that. There were obviously violations of human rights in East Timor.</p>
<p> Indonesia has recognised that by establishing their own investigation</p>
<p> as to the possible implication of individuals in that I'm not going</p>
<p> to pre-empt the outcome of the tribunal examination any more than anyone</p>
<p> should but I am pleased, as indeed the whole world is pleased, that Indonesia</p>
<p> is applying herself to that issue and it's to the credit of Indonesia</p>
<p> and a credit to the new government in that country that that is occurring.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, Australia [inaudible] provide intelligence material. Would</p>
<p> it do that to a domestic Indonesian tribunal and not just the international</p>
<p> tribunal?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, we'll examine that. I think Mr Downer has laid down the approach</p>
<p> in relation to that and we have tried in the past to adopt a sensible</p>
<p> balance between helping the due investigation without wanting to compromise</p>
<p> sources and I think that sort of principle can be applied.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, what's your view of the actual situation now in [inaudible]...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, Mr Downer was asked that question this morning and what he stated</p>
<p> was not only the Government's position but the Government's</p>
<p> state of knowledge and state of mind. Indonesia is going through a difficult</p>
<p> period of transition and deserves the understanding of the Australian</p>
<p> Government and of the Australian community. It's important that we</p>
<p> build the relationship with Indonesia. We see it as a new beginning, with</p>
<p> a new leader or a new government and a new embrace of democracy, a more</p>
<p> open society and that's to be encouraged. We should keep in mind</p>
<p> just how difficult it is to run a country of that size and what an enormous</p>
<p> challenge it is.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What do you think of President's Wahid's actions in relation</p>
<p> to General Wiranto?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well that is asking me in effect to comment on the possible implication</p>
<p> of an individual and I'm not going to do that. All I do is to encourage</p>
<p> the Indonesian authorities to have a transparent, open process and the</p>
<p> consensus of the world opinion is that Indonesia should be given an opportunity</p>
<p> of doing that and we should not be prematurely critical of the process</p>
<p> which is being adopted.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, should the States match your pledge to put a floor under government</p>
<p> services in the bush?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, the States have responsibilities and there are state services that</p>
<p> are being withdrawn from the bush. I'll get around to saying what</p>
<p> I think States ought to be doing in due time. I'm focussing at the</p>
<p> moment on the Commonwealth's responsibilities. One of the things</p>
<p> I would like to point out is that we're not only in the business</p>
<p> of ensuring that no further Commonwealth services are taken away but we</p>
<p> are also in the business of improving Commonwealth services. For example</p>
<p> the recent Job Network tender resulted in an increase of 50% in the number</p>
<p> of providers in regional Australia  a 50% increase. So that it is</p>
<p> increasing services, that is new services going into the bush, into regional</p>
<p> Australia, into country areas and there are 300 towns alone that under</p>
<p> the new Job Network tender will have providers that weren't there</p>
<p> before. So not only are we about preventing the withdrawal or the diminution</p>
<p> of services, we are also, where possible, in the business of providing</p>
<p> additional services. I'm standing in front of one that's the</p>
<p> recipient of it. The Job Network is a live example. The Job Network has</p>
<p> outperformed the CES by 50% on the available evidence. There are more</p>
<p> services available in the bush under the second Job Network tender. Now,</p>
<p> that is very good news.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What about in the case of Employment National? Will you be putting the</p>
<p> floor of the withdrawal of government services in an application to Employment</p>
<p> National?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>The Government service is delivered by the Network. You don't measure</p>
<p> the quality of the government service by providing, by looking at the</p>
<p> performance of one individual provider because you've got to remember</p>
<p> that the contracts that are won by the private providers are funded by</p>
<p> the Government. So the service provided by the government there is not</p>
<p> restricted to the running of Employment National. The service provided</p>
<p> by the Government is the entire Job Network and if you want to measure</p>
<p> whether the Government service is available you look at the whole Job</p>
<p> Network, you don't just look at the Employment National, that is</p>
<p> just quite wrong.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, at the next election, to strengthen you case on the sale of</p>
<p> Telstra, are you willing to detail the infrastructure projects that could</p>
<p> be financed out of that sale?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well Michelle, the next election is not scheduled until the end of next</p>
<p> year and I'm certainly not in campaign mode and I don't intend</p>
<p> to anticipate what I might say at the end of next year.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Well, before then.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Or even before then. Well, what I might say I will say at the appropriate</p>
<p> time but I don't have at this stage anything to add to what I've</p>
<p> been saying over recent days and that is that it is ludicrous to have</p>
<p> tens of billions of public dollars tied up in a telecommunications company</p>
<p> when that money could be more effectively used for a lot of other things</p>
<p> over and above what we might otherwise be able to do in normal Government</p>
<p> spending.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>But rural people might be a bit sceptical of the generality of that undertaking.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think rural people will understand that I'm developing an argument</p>
<p> about the application of public investment and then in time if we think</p>
<p> it's appropriate to be more specific we will but I'm not foreshadowing</p>
<p> at this stage at what point I might be more specific.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, would you envisage putting in the Telstra sale contract an</p>
<p> obligation on the owners, the private owners to continue to provide community</p>
<p> service ...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well we'll legislate. I mean, legislation is far more effective</p>
<p> than having something in a contract.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>So that would be specific...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>We will legislate, of course we will. We will require community performance</p>
<p> of community obligations. It's a matter of legislation, not a matter</p>
<p> of contract.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What's your response to Meg Lees' comments that you're</p>
<p> obliged to try and link infrastructure [inaudible]...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well it's certainly not [inaudible].. It's a statement of the</p>
<p> obvious. Look we have ongoing responsibilities. There is a certain amount</p>
<p> that we will be able to do in relation to infrastructure out of future</p>
<p> budgets and it should be made clear that it's not necessary to sell</p>
<p> the rest of Telstra to have some infrastructure spending. The point I'm</p>
<p> making is that you can do more sooner if you get rid of Telstra and what</p>
<p> I'm confronting the Australian community with is the choice. Do you</p>
<p> want to have tens of billions of dollars invested in a telecommunications</p>
<p> company or do you want more upgrading of infrastructure including in the</p>
<p> regions at an earlier date to a greater extent? That is not a bribe, it</p>
<p> is a statement of the obvious and what I've initiated is a debate</p>
<p> in the country about what our priorities are. Is a priority for the next</p>
<p> ten years to keep tens of billions of public dollars tied up in a telecommunications</p>
<p> company or is it a priority to use that money to pay off national debt</p>
<p> and to invest more rapidly and more comprehensively in public infrastructure</p>
<p> around the country including in the bush. Now there's no bribe in</p>
<p> that, it is a statement of the obvious and it is my obligation to lay</p>
<p> out these choices and to seek to persuade the Australian community to</p>
<p> the wisdom of our position.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do you plan to approach the Australian Democrats?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I don't flag when I talk to the Democrats or indeed anybody else</p>
<p> at news conferences. I talk to the Democrats on a regular basis so if</p>
<p> I have a particular reason to talk to them I will but I won't be</p>
<p> flagging it here.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>BHP lost the Federal Court case against providing individual contracts</p>
<p> in the Pilbara region - a set back for industrial relations reform? Well</p>
<p> it's too early to make that judgement. What's happened is that</p>
<p> an injunction's been granted. The thing hasn't been finally</p>
<p> resolved. It's not for me to give a running commentary on litigation</p>
<p> between companies and unions...</p>
<p>JOURNLIST:</p>
<p>[Inaudible]</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well it's a court case that was granted an injunction. I'm</p>
<p> not going to start putting degrees of outcome on it. I'm not going</p>
<p> to put any particular spin on it. It was an interlocutory, it was an application</p>
<p> for an injunction and as to what the final outcome is, you never know</p>
<p> with these things.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[Inaudible]...</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No I don't, he is entitled to take his own counsel. I'm not</p>
<p> going to start commenting on every single thing that is in the newspapers.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, the Australian dollar took a bit of a tumble over the weekend</p>
<p> and some commentators attributed that to interest rates...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well they were very uninformed, ignorant, ill-advised commentators.</p>
<p>JOURALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, on the issue of the historian, David Irving, he's proposing</p>
<p> to come back into Australia. What do you think about that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, we have a view that because of his record he shouldn't come</p>
<p> to Australia.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[Inaudible]..</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>So he will not be able to come even though...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, Michelle, we took a decision and we will give effect to that decision</p>
<p> in a lawful manner.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, Badgery's Creek  if it goes before the Cabinet</p>
<p> when it sits later this month [inaudible]...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>You are asking me to reveal a Cabinet agenda? Heaven's above. I</p>
<p> thought you normally had your ways of obtaining it but you are asking</p>
<p> me to reveal it. I think we have now got towards the terminal phase -</p>
<p> one more question.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>On Telstra, on the timeframe, do you envisage...when would you expect</p>
<p> to introduce legislation for the further sale of it? Do you have a, sort</p>
<p> of, a timeframe...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>We've laid it down. I mean, the policy is that we have this benchmarking</p>
<p> exercise and that is being established and being underway. And then if</p>
<p> that turns up okay we will then introduce legislation. Now, that will</p>
<p> be presumably during this term, exactly when I don't know. It depends</p>
<p> on how long the benchmarking study takes. Thanks.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
