<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10993</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                   THE                   HON JOHN HOWARD MP                 RADIO INTERVIEW WITH JOHN MILLER, 4BC</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/03/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE................................................................................................</p>
<p>MILLER:</p>
<p>We've got a lot of matters to cover today Prime Minister. But</p>
<p> first of all I think we've got to talk about John Elliott's</p>
<p> outspoken comments at a luncheon in Melbourne yesterday where, well</p>
<p> he hasn't missed anybody has he? He's given a sort of a</p>
<p> back hander describing you as boring but saying you're doing</p>
<p> a good job. But saying that Australians have for too long have been</p>
<p> distracted with what he calls side issues. Now, I can't agree</p>
<p> with him that drugs is any sort of a side issue. But things like the</p>
<p> republic, and remarks that I think a lot of people will find marginally</p>
<p> if not extremely offensive, and that is an apology to a forgotten</p>
<p> people.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I think you'll be aware that over the years, over the last</p>
<p> five or ten years I haven't really responded to any remarks Mr</p>
<p> Elliott has made on public affairs and having listened to what he</p>
<p> said yesterday I think my judgement has been absolutely correct. Everybody</p>
<p> knows our position. I do regard drugs as an important issue. I think</p>
<p> governments are capable of, and ought to be capable of and they have</p>
<p> a responsibility of not only looking after economic issues but also</p>
<p> responding on important social issues. And the drug problem is an</p>
<p> important social issue in this country and I make no apology for the</p>
<p> emphasis that I've placed on it. No part of the Australian community</p>
<p> is or should be forgotten. Everybody in this community is entitled</p>
<p> to an equal dignity and an equal respect. People will know our position</p>
<p> in relation to matters concerning reconciliation. They'll also</p>
<p> know my views in relation to the debate regarding the Human Rights</p>
<p> Commission report on the stolen children, and the views I have about</p>
<p> formal apologies. But our views are all well known on those issues.</p>
<p> We are running the economy extremely well but it's possible while</p>
<p> you're running an economy well to also give a lead on important</p>
<p> social issues. And tackling the drug menace is a very important social</p>
<p> issue.</p>
<p>MILLER:</p>
<p>Mr Elliott says he thinks a lot of Australian voters are stupid, that</p>
<p> we vote with our hip pocket. By that I mean, I interpret that that</p>
<p> as what he's trying to say in a fairly blunt, and as I said probably</p>
<p> offensive fashion, is that we don't look at the big picture when</p>
<p> we vote. Sometimes we do not look at what is good for the country.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I have a very high opinion of the common sense of the Australian</p>
<p> voter, a very high opinion.</p>
<p>MILLER:</p>
<p>All right. Well let's leave that there. Moving on, are you at</p>
<p> the end of your rope with Brian Harradine?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well no. Brian Harradine always makes up his mind on the merits of</p>
<p> individual issues. I don't agree with Brian Harradine on a lot</p>
<p> of issues. I agree with him on a lot of others. And his voting against</p>
<p> our bill to entrench junior wage rates didn't surprise me. He'd</p>
<p> made it fairly clear in earlier speeches that that is where he stood.</p>
<p> I'm disappointed that the Labor Party and the Democrats and Senator</p>
<p> Harradine have voted against our bill because the defeat of that bill</p>
<p> will put at risk tens of thousands of jobs for young people. And the</p>
<p> reason that we've pursued that issue is that we're trying</p>
<p> to do something about youth unemployment. Everybody agrees that unemployment</p>
<p> is still the major social and economic challenge in this country.</p>
<p> It's a lot better now than it was. It's 7.5% and that's</p>
<p> a huge improvement but we'd like it to be even better. And one</p>
<p> of the ways of making it better is to prevent a situation where the</p>
<p> cost of employing young people increases. And we've tried to</p>
<p> do a number of things on this front and we've been blocked at</p>
<p> every turn by the Senate. We've been blocked on the unfair dismissal</p>
<p> law that would, if passed, would have improved the job opportunities</p>
<p> of young people in small business. We've now been blocked on</p>
<p> junior wages. And really what the Senate has done is to attack our</p>
<p> basic attempts to do something about youth unemployment. Now you couldn't</p>
<p> have a more central issue in the political debate in Australia at</p>
<p> the present time. And we're not alone in arguing the consequences</p>
<p> of this. Look at what McDonalds have said, look at what the ACCI has</p>
<p> said, look at what the retailers have said. They've all argued</p>
<p> that if you don't go down the path we're advocating then</p>
<p> you're putting at risk the jobs of tens of thousands of young</p>
<p> people. And frankly we'll continue to push our case. We're</p>
<p> disappointed in the attitude taken by the Labor Party and the Democrats</p>
<p> and others. But we'll persevere because we believe the Australian</p>
<p> public understands that we're fighting for the employment security</p>
<p> and the employment opportunities of young Australians.</p>
<p>MILLER:</p>
<p>But where do we go to from here Prime Minister? I mean you have had</p>
<p> Senator Harradine block two key Government policies in 24 hours. As</p>
<p> you mentioned the unfair dismissal and the youth wages and of course</p>
<p> the privatisation, or sale of Telstra. How are you going to get these</p>
<p> things through? I mean they're all central to your Government's</p>
<p> whole package of reform.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well bear in mind that he did vote for something else that was central</p>
<p> to the last election campaign and that's the 30% private health</p>
<p> insurance rebate. We have to deal with the fact that the Australian</p>
<p> people did not deliver a majority, although they returned the Government,</p>
<p> that we don't have a majority in the Senate. We have to deal</p>
<p> with that fact. Now we believe that the Senate should honour the mandate</p>
<p> we received. Governments are made and broken in the Lower House, not</p>
<p> in the Upper House. But the Labor Party and the Democrats and others</p>
<p> refuse to honour that mandate on certain issues. All we can do is</p>
<p> persevere. We were reelected only five months ago and we're getting</p>
<p> on with the job. We're addressing the issues. We're arguing</p>
<p> the cause of reducing unemployment. We're trying to do something</p>
<p> about youth unemployment. We're trying to get our taxation package</p>
<p> through and I'm certainly not in any way depressed about our</p>
<p> prospects in that area. I remain hopeful that both Senator Harradine</p>
<p> and Senator Colston will support our taxation plan because we laid</p>
<p> it out in clear detail to the Australian people and we were returned</p>
<p> to Government and we therefore have a mandate, a clear unambiguous</p>
<p> mandate to implement that policy. And I hope when it comes to the</p>
<p> crunch, before the 30th of June, that both of those gentleman</p>
<p> will support the Government's policy and give effect to the mandate</p>
<p> and the support we received from the Australian people.</p>
<p>MILLER:</p>
<p>All right. Well you have hinted, maybe I'm mistaken, but I've</p>
<p> perceived that you've hinted that you might be prepared to play</p>
<p> around the edges with the GST. Would you be prepared to lose the GST</p>
<p> rather then, for example, negotiate on food?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well we're not prepared to take food out of it. What I've</p>
<p> said is that fine-tuning is one thing, any fundamental alterations</p>
<p> are another thing. Obviously some fine-tuning necessarily occurs with</p>
<p> a package as big as that and that has never been ruled out and oughtn't</p>
<p> to be ruled out and we've made a couple of minor changes ourselves</p>
<p> along the way. Given it's such a huge package that is to be expected.</p>
<p> But we're not going to fundamentally compromise it because it</p>
<p> is an integrated whole and it's what we took to the Australian</p>
<p> people. We have a very clear issue here. We're suppose to be</p>
<p> a Parliamentary democracy where parties campaign every three years,</p>
<p> put their policies on table, seek support for those policies. We did</p>
<p> all of those things. I was interviewed by you probably three times</p>
<p> during the election campaign and I was asked scores, hundreds, indeed</p>
<p> thousands of questions about the GST over a period of seven weeks.</p>
<p> It was the most intensive period of political campaigning that I have</p>
<p> ever been involved in in my 25 years in Parliament. And at the end</p>
<p> of that process the Australian people returned my Government and returned</p>
<p> me as Prime Minister and they returned us to do the things we said</p>
<p> we would do during the campaign. Now that is how our system is meant</p>
<p> to work. And I say to your listeners that that is how we will behave.</p>
<p> We will implement the mandate we were given and we ask the Senate</p>
<p> to honour that mandate and to pass our legislation. I can't answer</p>
<p> you in any other way.</p>
<p>MILLER:</p>
<p>Sure. Prime Minister what happens though if they stay intransigent,</p>
<p> if they won't put it through? I mean is your only option then</p>
<p> to go back to the people?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I don't....we just had an election. I don't think</p>
<p> anybody wants another election.</p>
<p>MILLER:</p>
<p>Not going to give you that.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Heavens above we just had one. It's only, less than six months.</p>
<p> And I don't want to hypothesise about what might happen, what</p>
<p> we do if people remain obstinate. I'm thinking in a positive</p>
<p> frame of mind. I'm optimistic, I'm hopeful, I'm positive</p>
<p> about our prospects of getting it through. I don't know and Senator</p>
<p> Harradine will keep his counsel. Senator Colston will keep his counsel</p>
<p> on the tax plan til the end. I understand that, I respect that.</p>
<p> They both have a right to do that and there's no point in trying</p>
<p> to box them into corners. They're both too astute and skillful</p>
<p> for that, and I understand that. We will argue our case publicly.</p>
<p> I'll keep reminding everybody who cares to listen that we had</p>
<p> an intensive seven week debate, the length and breadth of Australia</p>
<p> on this issue. And then we had a vote on the 3rd of October</p>
<p> and the Australian people returned the Coalition Government with a</p>
<p> majority of 12. And the centrepiece of that election campaign and</p>
<p> the centrepiece of our return to power was the GST plan.</p>
<p>MILLER:</p>
<p>Okay. Let's move on a little bit. We have got a budget coming</p>
<p> up. The Treasurer says it's not a time to go soft. What are the</p>
<p> parameters of this budget?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I think the Treasurer's put it very fairly. We are in a</p>
<p> strong budget position, we turned a deficit of $10.5 billion into</p>
<p> a surplus in three years. And that's one of the reasons why our</p>
<p> economy is performing so strongly, one of the reasons why our interest</p>
<p> rates are low, our inflation is low and we are seen by the rest of</p>
<p> the world as almost a role model of economic strength in a region</p>
<p> that's been racked by economic collapse. Now, in those circumstances</p>
<p> the last thing you do is squander the very strength that you have</p>
<p> accumulated. So whilst we are not in the business of being mean or</p>
<p> unfair, and we certainly won't be delivering a budget that's</p>
<p> anything other than fair and balanced and sensible, now is not the</p>
<p> time to relax the purse strings.</p>
<p>MILLER:</p>
<p>Okay. Business confidence they say highest since the 1980s but the</p>
<p> current account deficit has blown out and that was what tipped us</p>
<p> over the edge in the 80s, how long before you have to act on that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, the current account deficit now is much lower than what it was</p>
<p> in the 80s. You don't compare current account deficits by making</p>
<p> dollar comparisons, you have to look at them in the percentage of</p>
<p> the annual wealth generated by the country each year. Obviously in</p>
<p> dollar terms the current account deficit now is going to be higher</p>
<p> than what it was 15 or 20 years ago. But now it is much lower in percentage</p>
<p> of wealth terms than it was in the 1980s. And in addition, in the</p>
<p> 1980s we had high interest rates, high inflation, high budget deficits.</p>
<p> We have none of those now. And the current account deficit that we</p>
<p> have at the present time, whilst we would like to see it come back</p>
<p> again, is certainly very manageable. And most importantly we can pay</p>
<p> for it now. We are in a much better position to pay for it than we</p>
<p> were in the 1980s. And the critical thing with a current account deficit</p>
<p> is the percentage of your annual export income that is needed to service</p>
<p> the debt and that is now about 9.6 per cent. It used to be hovering</p>
<p> around 20, it's lower now than it's been since 1984. So</p>
<p> the current account deficit we have now is not only lower than what</p>
<p> is was under Labor, much lower in properly compared terms, but our</p>
<p> other economic conditions are stronger and our capacity as a nation</p>
<p> to pay for it through drawing off our export income is much better.</p>
<p>MILLER:</p>
<p>So I guess in simple terms the overdraft is a whopper but we can manage</p>
<p> it.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, the overdraft is more than covered by our earnings. Our capacity</p>
<p> to service that overdraft is well within the....our ability to</p>
<p> service is well within our earning capacity, well within it and more</p>
<p> in our earning capacity than what it was 15 years ago. Even though</p>
<p> the dollar terms...I mean, your nominal wage now, I assume, is</p>
<p> higher than what it was 20 years ago but the question of whether you</p>
<p> are better off or worse off depends on what it will buy. Now what</p>
<p> I am saying to you is that right now the capacity is much better to</p>
<p> service the debt.</p>
<p>MILLER:</p>
<p>Okay. Well, that brings me onto another subject that has been a subject</p>
<p> of a lot of debate on this programme and I know on Alan Jones'</p>
<p> programme as well. When can we expect to see, or can we expect to</p>
<p> see, more encouragement for single income families through either</p>
<p> the taxation system or other reforms that will allow families to return</p>
<p> to the more traditional situation where mum can stay at home and look</p>
<p> after the kids?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, can I just say something on the philosophy of that, and I am</p>
<p> and my Government is in favour of giving both men and women choice,</p>
<p> we don't believe that it's the role of the Government to</p>
<p> say to families, look, one of the parents should stay at home while</p>
<p> the children are young or both of the parents should be in the workforce.</p>
<p> That's for parents to decide and it will vary from family to</p>
<p> family. Many parents with young children would like the opportunity</p>
<p> for one of them to stay at home for a few years while the children</p>
<p> are very young, if they can afford to do so. But many people can't</p>
<p> do that anymore. Others say that it suits their lifestyle and their</p>
<p> aspirations both as individuals and as families for both to be in</p>
<p> the workforce from the beginning. Now, we respect all choices but</p>
<p> what we are trying to do is to make it more affordable for people</p>
<p> to be single income families if they want to be.</p>
<p>Now, you say what are we doing to help. Well, we helped with our family</p>
<p> tax initiative introduced two-and-a-half years ago promised in the</p>
<p> 1996 campaign that gave for the first time some extra help for people</p>
<p> with only one income where at least one of their children was under</p>
<p> the age of five. Now, we are going much further, we are building more</p>
<p> on that in our taxation plan. And if we can get our GST through the</p>
<p> Parliament we'll be able to deliver a lot of additional assistance</p>
<p> to all parents with young children. But over and above that assistance</p>
<p> we'll be giving a little bit more to those again where one child</p>
<p> is under five and one of the parents is at home. What we seek here</p>
<p> is a situation where people can exercise a choice. We are not telling</p>
<p> people what they should do. I don't believe in stereotyping what</p>
<p> people should do but equally I don't want a situation where people</p>
<p> who would like to have mum or dad at home when the children are young</p>
<p> find they can no longer afford to do so. I think that's quite</p>
<p> unfair and inimical to the kind of free choice in our society that</p>
<p> I would like to see developed.</p>
<p>MILLER:</p>
<p>Okay. Prime Minister, I know your time is limited but one more question</p>
<p> before we go. Yesterday Independent Peter Andren released figures</p>
<p> showing that our Parliament now costs something like $346 million</p>
<p> a year to run, $200 million of which goes on MPs salaries, entitlements</p>
<p> and other costs. With the lap of honour' business that</p>
<p> was talked about in the weekend press, I mean, can you understand</p>
<p> how people are annoyed, are jaded, who seem to think that there is</p>
<p> one rule for you folk in Parliament and one rule for the rest of us?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, if that were true I can...look, I can understand why people</p>
<p> get critical of these things because they are constantly bombarded</p>
<p> with stories, some of which are fair and some of which are unfair.</p>
<p> I mean, there is nothing unusual about the major cost of running something</p>
<p> being salaries. The major cost of running many businesses is salaries.</p>
<p> Of course it costs a lot of money if you have 148 members of the House</p>
<p> of Representatives and you have 76 members of the Senate and you employ</p>
<p> staff and you have a big country like Australia. It costs a lot of</p>
<p> money to travel from Far North Queensland to Canberra, from Western</p>
<p> Australia to Canberra. Of course it does, there is no way of avoiding</p>
<p> it. I mean, the only way you could avoid that is not have a national</p>
<p> Government at all, forget it. Now, some people might say that's</p>
<p> a great idea. I don't, I think there is greater waste at other</p>
<p> levels of government in this country. So, I mean, it's a very</p>
<p> simplistic argument that really proves nothing for somebody to say,</p>
<p> look at how much it costs to run Parliament. You can equally say look</p>
<p> at how much it costs to employ teachers, look at how much it costs</p>
<p> to employ police. I mean, it's all part and parcel of employing</p>
<p> people in our community to run our society. It's a question of</p>
<p> what is fair and reasonable. Now,....</p>
<p>MILLER:</p>
<p>Well, that's what I was trying to get to.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>And, look, the average salary of a Member of Parliament when you look</p>
<p> at the responsibilities and the way that most of them work is not</p>
<p> unreasonable. Many people of great ability in Parliament could probably</p>
<p> earn more outside. Some couldn't, it varies according to the</p>
<p> individual. But I think the average income is reasonable. I don't</p>
<p> think...I think they are quite well paid by community standards</p>
<p> but they are not overpaid by comparison with people who hold senior</p>
<p> business positions, senior media positions or some of our more successful</p>
<p> sportsmen. Now, when people abuse privileges they bring disrepute</p>
<p> on the whole system. And we have had a few examples of that and I</p>
<p> condemn those people whether they are, no matter what party they are</p>
<p> in. I was asked yesterday about superannuation and I certainly don't</p>
<p> have a closed mind in relation to changes in that area but I think</p>
<p> it's important to look at superannuation not in isolation but</p>
<p> as part of the overall remuneration package. Most Members of Parliament</p>
<p> I know work hard. That's not a popular thing to say but I'll</p>
<p> defend them on both sides for the fact that most of them work very</p>
<p> hard. Some let the show down as happens in any other walk of life.</p>
<p> But the great majority of Members of Parliament, I know, try hard</p>
<p> believing what they are there for and work on average 60 to 80 hours</p>
<p> a week.</p>
<p>MILLER:</p>
<p>But is it fair that a Member who is retiring in six months takes a</p>
<p> taxpayer funded overseas trip?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, it is fair that he take what he is entitled to while he is a</p>
<p> Member of Parliament. I know the article you are referring to. The</p>
<p> implication in that article was that this was some additional privilege</p>
<p> that those people were being given. It wasn't, it was quite unfair</p>
<p> in that sense. These were entitlements that those people had. I mean,</p>
<p> if you are going to argue that then what you are really arguing is</p>
<p> that any person within a certain period of retirement should not receive</p>
<p> from his employer any kind of hospitality to which he is normally</p>
<p> entitled. I mean, the trips that those people undertook, as I understand</p>
<p> it, were trips that they were entitled to during their three year</p>
<p> period as a Member of Parliament and they weren't getting something</p>
<p> extra because they were about to retire, that was my understanding.</p>
<p>MILLER:</p>
<p>All right. Prime Minister, we are going to have to leave it there</p>
<p> but thank you very much for your time this morning and I look forward</p>
<p> to doing it again soon.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
<p>  [ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
