<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>22264</transcript-id>
    <title>Doorstop Interview Four Seasons Hotel, Sydney </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/05/2006</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p> Mr Howard the Director General of ASIO today made some comments about the need for more security in restaurants, or that restaurants and hotels are vulnerable to terrorist attacks. Do you have a view on this at all?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p> I haven't seen the comments so I'm not going to say anything.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p> On IR and the High Court today, what's your view on that. Do you think, are you confident that the Federal Government's point of view on this will win through?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p> Well the matter is before the High Court. We had strong advice that what we were doing was constitutional, but now that the matter is before the court, I will leave it to their Honours to discharge their constitutional function. I'm not going to give a running commentary on a constitutional case before the High Court.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p> Is Mr Minchin still of the view that he has doubts about that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I'm not giving any further comment. We have strong advice, we accepted that advice, we believe that advice, but now that the case has started, I don't intend to give a commentary on the case itself.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p> Is the Federal Government eyeing off any state responsibilities other than IR?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p> We have plenty on our plate at the present time.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p> Mr Kennett, would you like to see him make a return to state politics?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p> I've never thought politics has left Jeff Kennett's blood, never, and if he comes back that will be a good thing for the Liberal Party in Victoria. But it's a matter for him and Felicity to decide and I'll leave it to them to make up their minds. But if he did decide to come back it would be a real plus for the Liberal Party in Victoria.</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p> Given the relations between he and Mr Costello, would it change your plans as far as the future of the Liberal Party goes?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p> What's the next question?</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, can I get your reaction to the new Solomon Islands Prime Minister?</p>
<p>PRIME MINSITER:</p>
<p> Well, we will work with him. He's been elected in a constitutional way. We'll continue to support the RAMSI operation, we'll continue to provide what assistance is needed to maintain law and order, support democracy, spread good governance and eliminate corruption. The last mentioned issue is very important. We won't get anywhere in the Solomon Islands without a significant reduction in corruption and an improvement in good governance.</p>
<p> [ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
