<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11279</transcript-id>
    <title>INNOVATION ONE OF THE KEYS TO AUSTRALIA&#039;S FUTURE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/11/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>  Today's meeting of the Prime Minister's Science, Engineering and Innovation<br />
   Council has focussed on the importance of innovation to Australia's future<br />
   as a can-do country.</p>
<p>  The Council's fourth meeting, held in Canberra, discussed the National Innovation<br />
   Summit, to be held in Melbourne in February 2000.</p>
<p>  The Summit will identify concrete steps for the development of a more innovative<br />
   culture in Australia, translating ideas and research into new jobs and new<br />
   opportunities. The three themes of the Summit are investing in ideas, creating<br />
   a competitive environment and building industry - research linkages.</p>
<p>  Today's PMSEIC meeting also identified the success of the Australian wine<br />
   industry as a great example of how research that is closely aligned with<br />
   industry needs and effectively transferred into practice can play a key<br />
   role in industry development.</p>
<p>  It was agreed that other industries should be encouraged to develop close<br />
   linkages with research bodies and effective ways of adopting new practices<br />
   and technology.</p>
<p>  Valuable ideas for developing a more co-ordinated national strategy for<br />
   science and technology awareness were also discussed. The proposition that<br />
   'champions' and 'ambassadors' of science and technology be adopted to promote<br />
   awareness will be further investigated.</p>
<p>  A presentation was made to the Council on nanotechnology, an exciting new<br />
   frontier in science and technology which is already generating real opportunities<br />
   in biomedical, computing and materials applications.</p>
<p>  The Council is the Government's principal source of advice on issues in<br />
   science, engineering and innovation and aspects of education, research and<br />
   training. Members are drawn from Australia's business, research and engineering<br />
   bodies.</p>
<p>  Copies of the papers presented to Council members can be found at the PMSEIC<br />
   homepage, under details of the fourth Council meeting at:</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
