<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8045</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTERS OPENING REMARKS 1990 PREMIERS CONFERNCE CANBERRA - 28 JUNE 1990</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/06/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008045.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
PRIME MINISTER'S OPENING REMARKS<br />
1990 PREMIERS CONFERENCE<br />
CANBERRA 28 JUNE 1990<br />
Premiers and Chief Ministers, I extend a warm welcome to you<br />
all. There are certainly a number of new faces around the<br />
table since we last met: Wayne Goss, Michael Field, Trevor<br />
Kaine and, of course, Australia's first woman premier, Carmen<br />
Lawrence. The older hands are welcome back too; I am pleased<br />
to see John Bannon, John Cain, Nick Greiner and Marshall<br />
Perron joining us once again.<br />
On this year's agenda I see two major issues: the need for<br />
continuing fiscal restraint by all levels of government and<br />
the need for Commonwealth-State co-operation on micro-economic<br />
reform. These issues are critical, and not unrelated.<br />
The end product of micro-economic reform is greater<br />
efficiency: the provision of better services at lower cost.<br />
That is a desirable end in itself both for us as service<br />
providers and for the members of the community for whom the<br />
services are provided. But pursued in tandem with fiscal<br />
restraint, micro-economic reform is also essential if we are<br />
to make progress in improving Australia's long-term economic<br />
outlook. So this Premiers' Conference is again focussing on the<br />
essential fundamental national tasks and that is as it<br />
should be.<br />
Let me now address these two elements separately.<br />
You are all aware of the Commonwealth's views about and<br />
commitment to fiscal restraint. The serious economic problems<br />
confronting Australia require a continuing indeed a renewed<br />
fiscal effort from all levels of government.<br />
My Government has been taking steps on all policy fronts to<br />
tackle our major immediate economic concerns, namely inflation<br />
and the balance of payments. An integral part of our policy<br />
approach has been to push the Commonwealth budget into<br />
surplus. We have done this to give the domestic private<br />
sector greater scope to fund the recent strong investment<br />
surge, and so reduce the demand for foreign savings. This<br />
will help the balance of payments in the short-term and in the<br />
long-term, the benefits of that investment will filter through<br />
in the form of more import substitution and production for<br />
export. </p>
<p>2./<br />
However, the impact of this strategy on total public sector<br />
savings was frustrated in 1989-90 by an increase in borrowings<br />
by the States. The statistician estimates that the<br />
Commonwealth sector's net financial surplus in 1989-90 will be<br />
$ 5.6 billion. In contrast, it is estimated the States will be<br />
in deficit to the extent of $ 3.6 billion.<br />
Given present economic circumstances, I believe the<br />
Commonwealth offer before you is a fair and reasonable one.<br />
It proposes that, while general purpose payments decline, net<br />
payments to the States increase in real terms, and that global<br />
borrowing limits be maintained, at least in nominal terms.<br />
As managers of nearly half of the total public sector outlays<br />
in Australia, you understand the impact your actions and<br />
decisions have upon the economy. The crucial role you play in<br />
the economy is also very evident when we consider the need for<br />
concerted action on micro-economic reform. Inefficiency has<br />
been rife at all levels of government in post war Australia.<br />
We have a sorry record of ill-considered interference to look<br />
back on: over-regulation, heavily subsidised Government<br />
business operations, price and marketing controls. We could<br />
all add many items to this list.<br />
My Government firmly believes that there is much to be done to<br />
improve the efficiency of our economy; to improve the<br />
competitiveness of our industry; to improve the way in which<br />
Government delivers services to the public.<br />
To that end, my Government embarked on a substantial program<br />
of micro-reform in our last term and we're committed to<br />
further progress now. Some of you have also taken initiatives<br />
in this regard.<br />
There is much more that remains to be done. We must get<br />
better returns out of scarce public resources.<br />
Inefficient production in the public sector can impose major<br />
cost penalties on the private sector. Charges for<br />
electricity, rail transport, shipping and port services,<br />
communications, and so forth, feed into the cost structure of<br />
local industries. Our export industries are particularly<br />
disadvantaged by such cost penalties, since they have to sell<br />
into competitive world markets.<br />
By improving efficiency in the public sector we can therefore<br />
free up resources for productive use elsewhere in the economy,<br />
and remove implicit cost penalties that we currently impose<br />
through regulation or excessive charges on the private sector,<br />
especially export industries. This is a contribution that we,<br />
as Governments, must make to a more efficient, more<br />
productive, more competitive Australian economy. </p>
<p>3.<br />
In asking for your co-operation on micro-economic reform, I am<br />
asking you to join us on a difficult task. It involves<br />
changing your fundamental outlook on what Government can and<br />
should do. It involves tackling entrenched interests, and<br />
pricing services according to realistic economic criteria.<br />
Most importantly, it involves assessing the total impact of<br />
decisions on the community as a whole: not only on the groups<br />
or industries directly involved.<br />
Later in the day I will be seeking your agreement to joining<br />
us in a special Premiers' Conference to be held later this<br />
year, and I will be writing to you suggesting a mechanism to<br />
co-ordinate work in preparation for such a conference. I make<br />
it very clear that I am not proposing Commonwealth hand-outs<br />
to increase capital infrastructure expenditure, because to<br />
inject money without taking steps to reform basic structural<br />
defects would be a waste of public resources. But I do<br />
believe we can, through co-operation and further discussion,<br />
significantly improve the use we make of the resources<br />
available to us.<br />
Having outlined these immediate issues facing us, I want to<br />
make very clear that I and my colleagues in the Commonwealth<br />
Government fully recognise that there are other aspects of<br />
Federalism other issues in the management of<br />
Commonwealth/ State relations which are of great importance.<br />
The economic and social health of our nation is in no small<br />
part dependent upon the most efficient possible management of<br />
relations between our Governments relations beyond the scope<br />
of our fiscal ties and our micro-economic co-operation, as<br />
fundamental as they are. We are all participants in a Federal<br />
system of great breadth that has substantial impact in<br />
virtually every area of daily life. We all have an obligation<br />
to make that system work as well as we possibly can.<br />
This is no longer merely an imperative in terms of trying to<br />
ensure the most efficient delivery of the services provided by<br />
government programs to Australians who need them, but an<br />
imperative in terms of our aspiration for an Australia in the<br />
best possible shape to face the 21st Century. I have no doubt<br />
that that is an aspiration shared by all of us around this<br />
table. I am concerned that we should manage our relationship across<br />
the wider range of Federal issues more effectively and<br />
co-operatively than in the past not solely longstanding and<br />
important issues of Commonwealth-State relations such as the<br />
allocation of functions, but newer issues facing governments<br />
at all levels, of which the protection of the environment is<br />
perhaps the clearest and most important example. Indeed I<br />
would like to believe that there is scope in 1990 only a<br />
decade or so away from the centennial of the Australian<br />
Federation not merely to correct this or that particular<br />
defect in the relations between our Governments but to begin a<br />
process leading to a genuine partnership, a modern<br />
partnership. </p>
<p>4. 9<br />
I have been giving careful, quiet consideration and reflection<br />
for some time now to the need for such a partnership and how<br />
we might make progress towards it. It is clear from comments<br />
a number of you have made, and from discussions I have had<br />
with several of you that you have been thinking to some extent<br />
along parallel lines. This is very healthy and I welcome it.<br />
So I say to you that these wider matters have not been<br />
forgotten or neglected, despite our necessary but narrower<br />
focus on fiscal restraint today, and that I shall be<br />
elaborating upon them in a major speech I shall be giving in<br />
the near future.<br />
I'll now ask the Treasurer to speak in greater detail about<br />
the economic outlook to help us get a clearer picture of the<br />
situation within which we must consider our agenda today. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
