<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2433</transcript-id>
    <title>&#039;THIS DAY TONIGHT&#039; - TELEVISION INTERVIEW ON ABC NETWORK GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR W MCMAHON - INTERVIEWER: RICHARD CARLETON - 18 JUNE 1971</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/06/1971</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002433.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGOED UNTIL 7.30 PM<br />
' THIS DAY TONIGHT"<br />
TELEV! SION INTERVIEW ON ABC NETWORK GIVEN BY<br />
THE PRIME MINISTER, MR W. McMAHON<br />
Interviewer: Richard Carleton 18 JUNE 1971<br />
Q4 ' Mr McMahon, rather than ask you what you have achieved<br />
in your f-Irst 100 days, let me ask you instead What have you<br />
failed to ch3eve in that time?<br />
PM: i. s very little that I've set out to achieve that<br />
hasn't beer_ Jone, Very little. That must be judged against the<br />
backgrour,., d tof. problems as I saw them at the date I took over<br />
the Primer ?' Asi : crship. Most of those prob . ems have been either<br />
removed or to a considerable extent the tensions have been taken<br />
away.<br />
Q. You are a fit and healthy man, Sir, at the age of 63. But<br />
has the office been a strain on you physically?<br />
PM: No, no physical strain no. It's been a lot of work yes.<br />
But I couldn't concede that it's been a physical strain, dnd in fact<br />
I think I feel a little better today than I was wheA I started. So<br />
that while you keep going ccntinuously, the word " sttfain" doesn't quite<br />
fit in. You do, of ourse, on occasions, get a little bit disturbed<br />
because of the rush you haven't got enough time to think of the<br />
problems and give the right answers. But it hasn't been to an<br />
extent that I would regard it as doing any harm to myself personally.<br />
Q. Mr McMahon, your term as Prime Minister 100 days<br />
has been active and possibly Volatile. Many major economic and<br />
political issues have arisen. And some of them remain to be<br />
resolved. Can I go through with you now some of those issues and<br />
ask you to comment on Australia's changing positions?<br />
PM: Yes, of cotrse you can.<br />
Q. Well, let me start with China. In the past three months,<br />
Austrglia's dttitude to China has done an almost volte face. On<br />
the 27 May you said that you've taken steps to open up a dialogue<br />
with China. How far has that gone?<br />
PM: May I first remind you that a little over eighteen months<br />
ago I became the Foreign Minister of this country. A. nd that gave me<br />
a deeper insight into -oreign affairs than I had previously had.<br />
And I felt then that we ought to have a look at our relationships between<br />
the Mainland of China, Japan and the Soviet, in order to see if we<br />
couldn't come to a more pleasant accommodation with them. The<br />
whole three were interlocked. Particularly, we wanted better / 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
relationships and better trade with Japan because this was of<br />
enormous material importance to us and our economic success.<br />
But I also felt there was one great country of over 700 million<br />
people and that is Mainland China, that ought to be brought into<br />
the comity of nations and we should try and find out what China<br />
was up to and what it intended to do in the future, knowing that it<br />
has been a source of great embarrassment to many of the countries<br />
immediately to the North of us, because obviously they have inspired<br />
insurrection and insurgency in those countries or many of those<br />
countries. So I knew that I had to embark on new policies,<br />
initiated from Australia, for the benefit of Australia. And we've '! one<br />
all that. So I did announce that we wanted to open up a dialogue<br />
to have better bilateral relationships and we have been making<br />
whatever soundings we could in international embassies throughout<br />
the world to see the wisest courses we could follow. Admittedly,<br />
I can't go too far and tell you explicitly what we have done because<br />
I think if I did it would undo all the good that has been achieved<br />
already.<br />
Q. But just let me ask specifically one point on that. In<br />
the last three months, as a result of that time, are we now closer<br />
towa) ds recogrising Mainland China?<br />
PM: I don't think so. We've taken all the initiatives. We<br />
haven ot as yet received any favourable replies from the Peking<br />
Government.<br />
Q. Before we leave China, Mr McMahon, could I put one question<br />
to you Mr Whitlam is to go into China two weeks from today.<br />
Still Australia has no wheat order from China for this year. Do<br />
you still expect one?<br />
PM:-No. I don't expect one, but I'm not in a position where<br />
I'd be a good judge. And other people who are much better judges<br />
than I am think that there is a prospect of getting an order. But<br />
might I put this into perspective, because I'm sure you don't want<br />
to get a false impression. It doesn't matter to us this season<br />
whether we have substantial sales of wheat to China or not.<br />
Q. It would be preferable though.<br />
PM: It A ould be preferable, yes. But we're selling very large<br />
quantities in other parts of the world, and I think we've got better<br />
sales this year, in this crop year, than we've ever had previously<br />
in our history. So we're doing very well. And only in the last<br />
twenty-four hours, we've been able to announce sales of flour, to<br />
South Korea and to Taiwan. Our carry-over will be much smaller<br />
than in the last few years, so we're not very worried about whether<br />
or not we have substantial sales of wheat to China. But I've gone through<br />
all of this before, but I don't think it's really a question of great<br />
political importance in Australia today. / 3 </p>
<p>-3<br />
Q. Well, I won't persist with the wheat industry, but may<br />
I ask another question about the rural industry the wool industry<br />
in particular. In many people's eyes, the wool industry is in<br />
queer street. Is your Government going to spend millions of<br />
dollars now rescuing the farmers that are in hopeless straits?<br />
PM: I've got to put this in three different ways to you if I<br />
can. The first one is, of course we are worried about wool, and<br />
we are worried about ot her rural industries as well. I've<br />
appointed an inter-Departmental Committee of the top, efficient<br />
people to look into it and to give recommendations to us as to what<br />
we can do to help. Secondly, I have had, within the last few days,<br />
discussions with Sir William Gunn, the Chairman of the Wool<br />
Board, aud with Mr Vines of the Commission that is, the<br />
Wool Commission. I have had their advice. I will shortly be having<br />
Cabinet together to be able to consider what I know and the papers<br />
that are presented by the various Departments, and then we'll make<br />
up our minds what we're to do.<br />
Q. As a basic principle, would you reject the idea of spending,<br />
say, $ 200 million to rescue the wool industry?<br />
PM: I will not make up my mind, or announce it until I've got<br />
the recommendations of the various Departments. I'm not one of<br />
those who believes in going off half-cocked or making instant coffee<br />
decisions. When I get the reports, when I discuss them with my<br />
colleagues, and we come to a common conclusion, I can assure you<br />
I'll make an announcement to the Australian people. But I want you<br />
to understand we know their problems, I think. We know them, we<br />
are anxious to help, and we've already shown by the fact that we've<br />
appropriated $ 100 million for reconstruction schemes, of our<br />
anxiety and willingness to help when we know we're on the right track.<br />
Q. Sir, let me turn to a major, and continuing issue. The<br />
South African sporting teams tours. They are due here next<br />
week. Now let me paraphrase something you said on 15 April.<br />
You said " If I have to take some action, it's best to leave it until<br />
the last moment." Well, it's almost the last moment. What are you<br />
going to do about it?<br />
PM: I don't think it is the last moment, and I'm not prepared<br />
to say what we as a Government are likely to do. But I will repeat<br />
what I said before, because I believe in it today just as much as<br />
I did then. We don't believe that the ACTU should be poking its nose<br />
in what is political business, or the business of the Australian<br />
community, outside their industrial functions. / 4 </p>
<p>4-<br />
Q. But given that they are doing that....<br />
PM: Given that they are. Yes, and we'll do all that we<br />
can when we decide that it is wise for us to act to do what we<br />
as a Government regard as sensible to let the Australian<br />
people themselves have the opportunity to make up their minds<br />
whether they want to go to the sporting functions or not.<br />
Not to be prevented by the ACTU, but to let the Australians<br />
decide whether they want to go. And if they want to go why<br />
shouldn't they, why should they be intimidated into not going?<br />
So I repeat what I said before, with emphasis, that I don't<br />
believe that these movements should get into the politics of<br />
Australian life. I don't think politics should ecome involved<br />
in sporting enterprises, and I see no reason why these people<br />
should be punished because of the actions of the South African<br />
Government. And I believe that if you look at the Gallup Polls,<br />
the true Gallup Polls, most Australians share that view too.<br />
Q. Sir, let me turn to what might be called your favourite<br />
area now the economy. For six months now, the Government<br />
has been warning of inflation. The Treasurer threatens a tough<br />
Budget. The Government cnlls for restraint and even possibly<br />
austerity. Let me ask, just what's wrong with our economy?<br />
We're supposed to be a booming nation, and overseas our own<br />
publicity says we're a land of milk and honey.<br />
PM: We are a great country, and we are developing well.<br />
If it had not been for the unbelievably high wage increases that<br />
have occurred in Australia in the last year, we would have had very<br />
few problems. In fact, we would have been under real booming<br />
conditions, with everyone joining in the advantages of the boom<br />
conditions. But what is happening now is because of the National<br />
Wage Case, and because of the over-award payments that are<br />
occurring outside the ArlVitration Commissbn, costs are going up<br />
too rapidly, prices are increasing too rapidly, and instead of<br />
getting the real benefit of growth and progress, too much is being<br />
dissipated in higher prices.<br />
Q. Mr McMahon, you seem to put all the blame on the<br />
Arbitration Commicsion. But the Arbitration Commission is a<br />
properly constituted body. If this is not going to happen, must<br />
you now change the Arbitration Commission?<br />
PM: I didn't put all the blame on the Arbitration Commission.<br />
I said it had to take a fair measure of responsibility for giving<br />
a 6 per cent increase in the National Wage Case. That I believe<br />
was economically foolish. I go further than that though, and say<br />
that there has been a 40 per cent wage drift. In other words, e. </p>
<p>not only have the Trade Unions taken advantage of the Arbitration<br />
system, but outside the system, they have been enforcing big<br />
increaises in wages by use of the strike methods and intimidation.<br />
So I didn't put all the blame upon the Arbitration Commission. I have<br />
gone further and I have said the time has come when we must have<br />
a good look at the Arbit ration system and we are doing this now.<br />
But this is a case where you cannot make judgments in a moment. It<br />
requires the most detailed and croteful thought, and we will give it that<br />
detailed and careful thought before we move any further.<br />
Q. Sir, the front page story on every Australian newspaper<br />
today is the McNamara papers on Vietnam. Have the revelations of<br />
the New York Times cast doubt on the propriety of our original<br />
commitment announced by Sir Robert on 29 April 1965?<br />
PM: No, I don't think they have. I don't thin~ k they touch us other<br />
tha n at the edges. And I want first of all, though, to put this in<br />
perspctive. We had our reasons for putting troops into South<br />
Vietnam, and I do know the history just as well as onyone, with the<br />
possible exception of Sir Robert, because I believe I was at every<br />
Cabinet discussion that dealt with this problem. So I know it well. I<br />
know all the cables and I know the history and the background of it.<br />
So first of all we were there we were there because we felt there<br />
was a real danger at that time of the whole of South-East Asia falling<br />
to Communism. South-East Asia has been saved. So let us remember<br />
this. Secondly, we wanted to join with our very great friends and<br />
allies, the United States a great liberal democracy with which we<br />
have the ANZUS Treaty that v irtually guarantees our freedom.<br />
And, thirdly, we want and this is a great principle with me and my<br />
Government we want the smaller oountries of South-East Asia to<br />
determine their own future. This is why we were there<br />
Q. Sir.<br />
PM: Wait a minute, because unless I put it in perspective, it<br />
wont t be understood. So what happens then the McNamara papers<br />
come out. Sir Robert made his statement yesterday, I have referred<br />
the whole problem to the Defence Committee; the highest officials<br />
we have got in Defence and Foreign Affairs will report to me,<br />
and shortly I will be able to make a comment on it. But at this stage,<br />
to my personal knowledge, everything that Sir Robert said was<br />
correct. We received our first request through Mr Howson and with<br />
our Ambassador up there Mr Anderson now in our Foreign Office<br />
that the South Vietnamese Government wanted us to help them and give<br />
military assistance.<br />
Q. Well on this point, Sir, can I ask you, I think fairly, for a<br />
' Yes" or " No" answer to the question: Is there a piece of paper in<br />
the Government archives that has come out of Saigon signed by the<br />
Saigonese Government, to Australia, saying: " Please give us one<br />
battalion of troops" / 6 </p>
<p>not only have the Trade Unions takenadvantage of the Arbitration<br />
system, but outside the system, they have been enforcing big<br />
increases in wages by use of the strike methods and intimidation.<br />
So I didn't put all the blame upon the Arbitration Commission. I have<br />
gone further and I have said the time has come when we must have<br />
a good look at the Arbit ration system and we are doing this now.<br />
But this is a case where you cannot make judgments in a moment. It<br />
requires the most detailed and cateful thought, and we willI give it that<br />
detailed and careful thought before we move any further.<br />
Q. Sir, the front page story on every Australian newspaper<br />
today is the McNamara papers on Vietnam. Have the revelations of<br />
the New York Times cast doubt on the propriety of our original<br />
commitment announced by Sir Robert on 29 April 1965?<br />
PM: No, I don't think they have. I don't think they touch us other<br />
tha n at the edges. And I want first of all, though, to put this in<br />
perspective. We had our reasons for putting troops into South<br />
Vietnam, and I do know the history just as well as enyone, with the<br />
possible exception of Sir Robert, because I believe I was at every<br />
Cabinet discussion that dealt with this problem. So I know it well. I<br />
know all the cables and I know the history and the background of it.<br />
So first of all we were there we were there because we felt there<br />
was a real danger at that time of the whole of South-East Asia falling<br />
to Communism. South-East Asia has been saved. So let us remember<br />
this. Secondly, we wanted to join with our very great friends and<br />
allies, the United States a great liberal democracy with which we<br />
have the ANZUS Treaty that v irtually guarantees our freedom.<br />
And, thirdly, we want and this is a great principle with me and my<br />
Government we want the smaller wtuntries of South-East Asia to<br />
determine their own future. This is why we were there<br />
Q. Sir.<br />
PM: Wait a minute, because unless I put it in perspective, it<br />
won't be understood. So what happens then the McNamara papers<br />
come out. Sir Robert made his statement yesterday, I have referred<br />
the whole problem to the Defence Committee; the highest officials<br />
we have got in Defence and Foreign Affairs will report to me,<br />
and shortly I will be able to make a comment on it. But at this stage,<br />
to my personal knowledge, everything that Sir Robert said was<br />
correct. We received our first request through Mr Howson and with<br />
our Amibassador up there Mr Anderson now in our Foreign Office<br />
that the South Vietnamese Government wanted us to help them and give<br />
military assistance.<br />
Q. Well on this point, Sir, can I ask you, I think fairly, for a<br />
" Yes" or " No" answer to the question: Is there a piece of paper in<br />
the Government archives that has come out of Saigon signed by the<br />
Saigonese Government, to Australia, saying: " Please give us one<br />
battalion of troops" / 6 </p>
<p>6-<br />
PM: L There are all the cables coming through diplomatic sources,<br />
commencing in December 1964, requesting us to give military<br />
assistance to the South Vietnamese.<br />
Q. Is there a specific paper from the Government....<br />
PM: I will as soon... * as I said to you, I don't move quickly.<br />
I move when I know exactly what I am dcing and I am able to verify<br />
evt~ rything, and I will, as soon as the Defence Committee has<br />
reported to me, then I will make another statement about what has<br />
hapr-ened. But I verify now, and this can come out from personal<br />
evidence of two people, the Ambassador up there, Mr&amp; A nderson, and<br />
the Minister for Air, Mr Howson, and they can both testify that they<br />
were requested by the then Premier of South Vietnam to supply<br />
military assistance to South Vietnam<br />
Q. Sir.<br />
PM: No, look, wait a minute. Let me tell my story because I<br />
don't want to be interrupted and get a hal-story across. And I w~ on't<br />
permit it in fact. From then on we gave several. we had several<br />
meetings of the Cabinet Sub-Committee, the Defence and Foreign<br />
Affairs Committee on it. I was at each one and we decided that we<br />
would be prepared to provide troops, providing only the Americans<br />
thought it was wise and wl got an official request from the South<br />
Vietnamese Goverment<br />
Q. Can this be produced in writing? The official request.<br />
PM: I've said to you that I have to wait until I get the report of the<br />
Defence Committee. What I can say is that the best evidence that you<br />
can bet in the land, particularly the kind of evidence that would be<br />
accepted in a Court of Law, is the witness of those who get the request.<br />
And we have the two witnesses.<br />
Q. Sir, let me turn now to three quick straight political qte stions.<br />
Mr Gorton is your Deputy Leader in the Liberal Party. What help<br />
is he to you?<br />
PM: He plays his part in Cabinet as the Minister for Defence and<br />
does it well. He is there, elected by the members of the Party to be<br />
the Deputy Leader. He wanted to be the Deputy Leader, he was entitled<br />
to stand as the Deputy Leader and he has been appointed. And he comes<br />
into Cabinet as the Deputy Leader and the Minister for Defence and<br />
he plays his part there and does it as you would expect him to do it.<br />
Q. Is he a help to you?<br />
PM: Of course he's a help to me. He's a very efficient Minister for<br />
Defence. e. ./ 7 </p>
<p>-7<br />
Q. Mr MoMahon, the day you became Prime Minister, half the<br />
Liberal Party, 33 men, voted confidence in Mr Gorton. Of those<br />
33 men, how many have you now swung round to your point of view?<br />
Pn Look, I don't want to be going over the past like this and I'll<br />
andwer this in an indirect way because I haven't counted heads and I've<br />
no intention of doing it. What I do know is that the relationship between<br />
the Country Party and the Liberal Party couldn't be better. tve Deen<br />
mending whatever fences had to be mended between the Parliamentary<br />
and the organisational. wings of the Party, and I believe it is in<br />
remarkably good shape, and I think my own Party is in remarkably<br />
good shape, too. IM other words, if I had had my way a few months<br />
ago, I would have been having an election round about now, and I<br />
would have guaranteed we would have won several seats.<br />
Q, That's an interesting point, Sir....<br />
PM! And that's what I feel. I feel the position<br />
Q. You've never said before that you did hope to have an election<br />
PM: Well, I left it vague, yes. I left it vague, that's true, because<br />
I never believe in giving away your tactical advantage until you have<br />
to do so.<br />
Q. In hindsight now, with hindsight, was that a mistake not to<br />
call an election now?<br />
PM: No, I don ' t think so, because I think we are going from good<br />
to better an I don't worry very much about 4t<br />
Q. Sir, if it was not for Mr Malcolm Fraser's resignation, you<br />
would almost certainly not be Prime Minister now. On the 10th of<br />
March you said of Mr Fraser: He's an able, perhaps a very able<br />
man. Is there no room for thTr man in your Cabinet?<br />
PM: Of course there will be room for Mr Fraser in the Ministry<br />
when the opportunity arises. He is an able man. I've expressed<br />
my views about his ability but, at the moment, there isn't a position<br />
that I could fit him into. I will constantly keep him in mind. 0 0/ 8 </p>
<p>-8<br />
Q. Sir, to conclude with, whether you acknowledge it publicly<br />
or not, many people believe that you have now achieved your life-long<br />
ambition to be Prime Minister. Now that you have sat in that<br />
seat for 100 days, is it all that you expected it to be?<br />
PM: I haven't looked at it in that way. This is a novel way of<br />
putting this question to me. But it is not very much different from<br />
what I expected it to be other than in the sense that previously I had<br />
much more time to think. In other portfolios, you can call your<br />
officials in and you can cross-examine them and then come to a<br />
conclusion as to what you should do, But you have only one<br />
portfolio to think of.: In this portfolio, that is the Prime Ministership,<br />
you have every other Minister's portfolio and Cabinet business as<br />
welt, So every day you have got half a dozen different kinds of<br />
questions to which You have to give an immediate answer. In other<br />
words, here it is long experience and the experience that I have<br />
had in.. what is 13 or 14 portfolios, that has stood me in good<br />
stead. So it is the rush and the need to make quick decisions that<br />
are so important in the Prime Ministership, and I am making them<br />
constantly and I hope I am making them fairly well.<br />
Q. Mr McMahon, thank you.<br />
PM: PGM. ood, thank youj too. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
