<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9525</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J.KEATING MP SPEECH AT THE OPENING OF THE DANDENONG RAILWAY STATION, FRIDAY, 24 MARCH 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/03/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009525.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
SPEECH AT THE OPENING OF THE DANDENONG RAILWAY STATION,<br />
FRIDAY, 24 MARCH 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
Distinguished colleagues and we have many of them here today Michael<br />
Duffy, of course, well known to everybody here as the Member for Holt and<br />
my colleague Gareth Evans, who before too much longer will be the Member<br />
for Holt. I mean it's a good thing for Senators getting out and meeting<br />
people, but he does it so well. And Rob Maclellan, Minister for Planning, Ian<br />
Cathie and Mrs Cathie, and distinguished guests, and Members of Parliament<br />
from both sides, and ladies and gentlemen.<br />
Thank you very much for a very nice welcome and most particularly to<br />
Worawa Aboriginal College. I met a group of Aboriginal people in Adelaide<br />
yesterday and the one thing I think, you can say about Mabo or the Land<br />
Fund, the Native Title and the rest of it, it has no doubt got us to the point<br />
where if not in the past most Australian people think when they see an<br />
Aboriginal dance group or Aboriginal people they say they are our people<br />
our people. And it has made us one country and one nation, more than we've<br />
ever been and thank you very much for that welcome.<br />
But you get all sorts of welcomes. I had a pretty mixed welcome yesterday in<br />
Adelaide. I was clutched and grabbed by admiring and devoted supporters in<br />
one place and attacked in others. And then I had Tim Fischer, of course, Tim<br />
was running around picking up the lines from some toffy little stringer for the<br />
BBC, bagging our Parliament and I said, I thought about saying, fair crack of<br />
the whip Tim, when it comes to the House of Commons, I mean, Tim still<br />
thinks a fishnet is for catching yabbies, of course. But for the rest of us, we<br />
now know and, of course, in our Parliament, we used to often wonder what a<br />
three line whip was in the House of Commons well, we all know about that<br />
these days. </p>
<p>At any rate, thank you very much for the welcome today and for coming to<br />
this, I think, very important event. Transport and intermodal transport is a key<br />
to modern living, particularly as the motor vehicles and with the capacity for<br />
the rail system to do new things and I was very interested in a couple of<br />
things that Alan said, most particularly, his point I think about Dandenong<br />
being, where once it was on the periphery of Melbourne, now being much<br />
more part of the centre of what will be this development out at Pakenham and<br />
Cranbourne and Berwick. And so we need here in Dandenong, and we see<br />
just behind us the Australian Taxation Office which has seen the<br />
decentralisation of the tax administration to the central place just as he made<br />
the point about Parramatta being in a similar position in Sydney which has<br />
these decentralised facilities, the Tax Office, the transport and what have<br />
you. This is going to be the case here. Under the Better Cities Program of<br />
the Commonwealth, it is a way of bringing and changing some of the gloom<br />
about urban decay and how we make urban areas better. Now Alan Brown<br />
said to me, this place, this railway was an armpit of a place. Now, that is very<br />
descriptive, I'll use that one in the House, Alan. Can I have that one? And it<br />
probably was because mostly I take my media etiquette from Jeff Kennett<br />
these days, but I'll take some of the lines from you.<br />
But, the station and the capacity to do this, I think, shows that we in the<br />
Commonwealth believe that urban planning and urban problems or urban<br />
decay can be overcome by dealing with the three tiers of government State<br />
and local and to get something done which is good. To have a building like<br />
this which will not only be functional and efficient, but which is light and bright<br />
and airy and there are no dark corners where people could be molested and<br />
we have got something like 25 television monitors around the building so that<br />
it can be watched, there are people coming in and out of it all of the time.<br />
I think urban renewal is critical to the happiness of most people. We talk<br />
about it a lot in the Federal government because 85 per cent of Australians<br />
live in cities and so to make life better for them is about making life more<br />
comfortable, more pleasant and to live in areas which are more beautiful. So,<br />
that is why the issues like the quality of life and peace of mind matter and it is<br />
why my colleague, Brian Howe, has been steward of this program Better<br />
Cities and why we have around the country and urban areas, such as<br />
Dandenong, been able to move towards improvements in areas which are<br />
getting beyond the capacity of State governments or local governments. So,<br />
this interchange is, I think, going to be an important one for the regeneration<br />
of transport in this area and it means that we can make public transport more<br />
competitive, more efficient and more likely to be chosen as the mode of daily<br />
movement than motor cars. Of course, with motor cars we are continuing to<br />
destroy a lot of urban areas with arterial roads and we all know the better the<br />
road the more cars that move on them. So, this is an important thing to be<br />
doing. I must make a few remarks now about the design of this station and just thank<br />
the community for being part of the extensive public consultations about it<br />
and to the architects Hassall Pty Ltd/ Forbes Fitzharding and the structural </p>
<p>engineers Ove Arup and Partners. They have done a great job marrying<br />
together function and technology into producing a new and important place<br />
for Dandenong.<br />
This is a model of co-operation in what can be done with the State and<br />
Commonwealth governments together with local government as well and<br />
what we see as a consequence is in a very key part of the city of Melbourne,<br />
in this area of great growth, in this hub of Dandenong, we see this capacity to<br />
do something good. And, now with the recovery in full swing, with the job<br />
growth coming through strongly, with again where Dandenong has suffered<br />
quite substantially in terms of unemployment, we are starting to see that<br />
improve and see new businesses starting again and we can make some of<br />
these key centres core centres in our capital cities as is happening here with<br />
the Taxation Office, other state and commonwealth facilities in Dandenong<br />
and with this intermodal change to make it easier to go from rail to road to<br />
bus et cetera.<br />
So, can I thank lan Cathie and Alan Brown and Michael Duffy who has been<br />
involved with this project from the beginning and to those other members of<br />
the community who have been involved with it, this is quite a great and a<br />
good thing to be doing together in the city of Melbourne, in the city of<br />
Dandenong where I am very pleased to be on this very happy occasion. It is<br />
my pleasure now to join with Alan in unveiling this plaque.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
