<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8612</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ KEATING MP VISIT TO JAPAN, SINGAPORE AND CAMBODIA</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/08/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008612.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIM MINSTER86/ 92<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ. KEATING MP<br />
VISIT TO JAPAN, SINGAPORE AND CAMBODIA<br />
As the guest of the Japanese and Singaporean Governments, I shall be visiting Japan from<br />
to 24 September, and Singapore from 24 to 25 September. If circumstances allow, I<br />
also propose making a one-day visit to Cambodia on 26 September.<br />
The primary purpose of my visit to Japan will be to exchange views with Prime Minister<br />
Miyazawa, his Ministers, and senior financial and business leaders on Australia-Japan<br />
relations and the wider outlook for our two countries' interests in an increasingly fluid<br />
international political and economic environment.<br />
Japan has been Australia's leading trading partner for many years and is a major source of<br />
investment into Australia. In keeping with the mature relationship between our countries,<br />
the two governments maintain a vigorous dialogue on a wide range of regional and<br />
international issues of shared concern.<br />
In Singapore, I shall have an opportunity for detailed discussions with Prime Minister Goh<br />
ACbpk Tong and his Ministers. Singapore is Australia's fourth largest export market and a<br />
longstanding regional partner of considerable importance. My program and discussions<br />
will reflect the range of interests we share with Singapore including in the commercial and<br />
defence areas.<br />
My proposed visit to Cambodia is intended to underline Australia's firm support for the<br />
peace process at a time when serious difficulties have been encountered. I shall have an<br />
opportunity to meet His Royal Highiness Prince Sihanouk, other members of the Supreme<br />
National Council and senior United Nations representatives. I also look forward to<br />
reaffirming the Government's appreciation of the efforts of the Australian military and<br />
civilian personnel serving with the United Nations Transitional Authority in Cambodia.<br />
CANBERRA 7 August 1992 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
