<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7850</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF QUEENSLAND AND ANSWER SESSION, NATIONAL PRESS CLUB, 7 DECEMBER 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/12/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007850.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
t 0 TRANSCRIPT OF QUESTION AND ANSWER SESSION, NATIONAL PRESS<br />
CLUB, 7 DECEMBER 1989<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, as the first member of the Press<br />
to ask you a question, may I take the opportunity to wish<br />
you a happy birthday?<br />
PM: Thank you very much indeed.<br />
JOURNALIST: Could I ask you two questions?<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
JOURNALIST: The first one, we have reports in the paper<br />
this morning that the Indonesian Foreign Minister, Mr Ali<br />
Alatas, said there'd be further talks, Cambodian peace<br />
talks. Can you tell us what status Australia's proposal<br />
for a UN group to supervise elections will have at those<br />
talks? And, secondly, could I ask you that on reaching<br />
the age of 60, does that give you a new perspective on a<br />
compulsory retirement age of 60 for women and 65 for men?<br />
PM: Well, let me take the first. Obviously, I think you<br />
will understand, that it's not open to me to go into all<br />
the details of some of the consultations and discussions<br />
that we've been having on this issue, but I can say<br />
generally this, quite precisely. That there has been a<br />
remarkably, in my judgement, positive reaction to Gareth<br />
Evans' proposal which he's advanced on behalf of<br />
Australia. But we are under no illusion about the<br />
difficulties that are involved in such a proposal. It<br />
hasn't been proposed on the part of the Australian<br />
Government in any sense that here is an easy fix. The<br />
concept of a UN administered body in that interim period<br />
very difficult, but what you have to say against that<br />
is that. -every-other-proposal -thati-s been on the table has<br />
proved equally incapable of bringing the parties to a<br />
resolution. Now I don't say that with any sense of<br />
pessimism, but rather that if we are realistically, as I<br />
say, as Australia going to understand our region and be<br />
part of not being reactive to it to try and help the<br />
shape, then we must first of all understand the nature of<br />
the difficulties, be prepared then to have a status and a<br />
capacity to talk with the major players involved. We<br />
have established that capacity. We are listened to with<br />
respect by the ASEAN countries and there has been, I may </p>
<p>say, within them a quite positive range of response to<br />
the proposal as there has been in other countries<br />
outside, including the French for instance and the United<br />
States. So what we will be doing constructively is to<br />
say, we're not trying to impose something because that<br />
would be stupid, it would be futile, but at least look<br />
and see whether this provides that necessary link. The<br />
whole problem about the resolution of Cambodia is to get<br />
that, that linking period between the state of conflict<br />
now and up to the conduct of free elections so that a<br />
properly conducted election can throw up a government<br />
which will be recognised and effective. It's getting<br />
that bridging point how you have the affairs of<br />
Cambodia conducted in that period and allow that<br />
transition which is a critical issue. And Gareth Evans'<br />
proposal on behalf of Australia is relevant to that, it's<br />
seen as relevant, we'll continue to push it and I think<br />
with a considerable degree of support. Now, on your<br />
second question about retiring ages. I think it's fairly<br />
difficult to project to others on the basis of how you<br />
feel yourself and what you feel capable of doing<br />
yourself. All I'd say on that is that I feel very well,<br />
physically and intellectually and in terms of energy and<br />
any sort of retirement at this stage would be appalling<br />
for me. I think it won't arise. Let me make very<br />
briefly a serious point. I think the community has now<br />
got a somewhat different attitude about the question of<br />
retirement ages. If you look back to the beginning of<br />
the 80s, we were then plagued by massive unemployment,<br />
growing unemployment, the last year before we came into<br />
office another quarter of a million thrown on to the<br />
unemployment scrap heap. In that context people were<br />
then talking about the idea, well it makes more sense to<br />
try and get the elderly people in the workforce out to<br />
create more room for the young. But how things have<br />
changed. With the creation of about 1.6 million new jobs<br />
in this country, there's a change in thinking. The kids<br />
are staying in the education system much longer. Very,<br />
very much longer, more of them. And so the fundamental<br />
structure of the debate and the discussion about how long<br />
W people should stay in the workforce has changed and I<br />
don't think the same sort of considerations about, sort<br />
of facilitating early retirement are as strong as they<br />
used to be.<br />
JOURNALIST: Amanda Buckley from the Daily Telegraph, Mr<br />
Hawke. I want to ask you about the big swing against<br />
Labor-at--the-South Australian--election a fortnight ago.<br />
It's been overshadowed by the big win you had in<br />
Queensland, but it did seem to show a people very tired<br />
and fed up with the Federal Government's economic<br />
policies and I'm wondering how, in the new year, you're<br />
going to better be able to explain a very complicated<br />
message about why interest rates and falling living<br />
standards are in fact a good thing for people?<br />
PM: I think, Amanda, that's for us, for the Government,<br />
a critically important issue. I have tried in a sense </p>
<p>today to adumbrate, if I can put it that way, the answer.<br />
Let me briefly, because I know there are other questions,<br />
go to what I think has to be done. As I tried to say in<br />
the speech here today, Australians have got to understand<br />
and this is not just in terms of the election. It's<br />
true for us as we restructure the future. We've got to<br />
understand that there is, as I say, no one single<br />
yardstick. If we say interest rates are hurting us and<br />
make our judgement on that, then we fail ourselves. I'm<br />
not saying that it might throw me out of office or<br />
someone else, but we fail ourselves as a country if we<br />
just take that, that one judgement. Similarly if we just<br />
say debt is rising, make the judgement on that, you can't<br />
answer it. The Australian people have got to understand<br />
this, that what we fundamentally have to do in Australia<br />
is to restructure our economy. There's got to be more<br />
investment so that industry is re-equipped. If we allow<br />
ourselves to have a profile of exposure in the<br />
international trading system which flows from the fact<br />
that we overwhelmingly depend on exports of primary<br />
products and minerals, then we're doomed to further and<br />
further decline. So, if you're going to restructure the<br />
economy, that requires more investment. It's got to be<br />
the re-equipment of the Australian economy. It means<br />
Australians generally have to be prepared to accept the<br />
decisions which allow that to happen. Now how do you do<br />
it? And this is where you get back to the absolute<br />
centrality of wages policy. What we have done is to get<br />
a bargain with the Australian community via the Accord.<br />
And it's a bargain that in some obvious senses has been<br />
hurting. It's been hurting in the sense that real wages<br />
have moved down, but it's the very movement downwards in<br />
real wages which has meant the increase in profits. So<br />
it's moved from wages, the shares have moved from wages<br />
to profits, from profits to record investment and that's<br />
creating a basis for Australia's future. But in the<br />
process we ' ye now got a level of economic activity which<br />
is so high that we're sucking in imports which, if we<br />
allowed that to happen, would destroy the Australian<br />
economy. Now, therefore, proper government must be about<br />
having the three arms of policy fiscal policy and wages<br />
policy and monetary policy sufficiently tight to bring<br />
down the level of activity to a point in which you can<br />
get a balance between a sustainable level of imports and<br />
a rate of growth which will maintain employment. So the<br />
hurt, yes, is there in interest rates. As I've tried to<br />
say, the things that have allowed that to happen not only<br />
-don' t-hurt, -but -they' re-beneficial. The -massive increase<br />
in education participation, Medicare, the nearly<br />
billion additional programs in social justice on a per<br />
annum basis. All these things are part, they've only<br />
been able to have been done because of a reduction in<br />
real wages and those other moves. Now the question is<br />
Australians, not just in the context of the next<br />
election. Let me go beyond that. Australians must<br />
understand that those are the issues. I just take myself<br />
out of the electoral consideration Let's go past<br />
when it's going to be. If Australians don't understand </p>
<p>that in some senses you can't satisfy every aspect of<br />
your aspiration. You can't have rising real wages like<br />
that, the profit share going down and investment<br />
collapsing. You can't have everything. But what you<br />
must have is if real wages are declining somewhat then<br />
there must be the compensation in these other areas which<br />
are both beneficial in terms of families and are the<br />
building blocks for Australia's economic reconstruction.<br />
Now you are quite right, Amanda, that is not a simple<br />
message. But irrespective of the electoral cycle, it's a<br />
message which if Australians don't understand, if they<br />
fall for the alternative of this three card trick, that<br />
you can have everything, then Australia would be doomed.<br />
To put it in the context of the electoral situation, if<br />
they were to buy the Opposition policy, Australia is<br />
doomed because in the critically important area, that is<br />
of wages policy, well you saw the alternative Prime<br />
Minister, when asked the centrally important question<br />
about the future of this country, that is what will<br />
happen to wages outcomes, that's the central feature<br />
because if wages outcome go like that that the whole<br />
thing collapse. You know what his answer ' who's to<br />
know'. A devastating indictment of any alternative<br />
government. JOURNALIST: Dennis Grant, Prime Minister, from the Seven<br />
Network. We won't let this occasion go by without giving<br />
our best to Mrs Hawke, of course, as well.<br />
PM: Thank you very much.<br />
JOURNALIST: My question is about an important aspect of<br />
the Australian economy.<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
JOURNALIST: The rise and increasingly, these days, the<br />
falls of our Australian entrepeneurs.<br />
PM: Said with feeling.<br />
JOURNALIST: I probably don' t need to Are you<br />
concerned about authoritative evidence that more falls<br />
are on the way? Do you worry at the signals that it<br />
sends to the rest of the world? Are you in the least bit<br />
concerned about the havoc that it wreaks within the<br />
Australian industries involved?<br />
PM: Thank you Dennis. Obviously it would be stupid for<br />
a Prime Minister of a country like this where you have<br />
entrepeneurs whose operations are not only within<br />
Australia but in a number of other countries to say oh<br />
well, I have no concern if some of them are in trouble'<br />
Yes, I do have concern. Concern comes into two parts<br />
Denis. There is you've got to ask yourself the<br />
question intrinsically what does a possible collapse of a<br />
particular entrepeneur mean for the Australian economy?<br />
Does that mean that you're going to have for instance an </p>
<p>enterprise closed down, employment lost and those sorts<br />
of things. So you must ask yourself that question.<br />
You've also got to ask yourself secondly now what sort of<br />
Judgement will the international community make about<br />
Australia as a result of something like that happening if<br />
it does. So those two things you have to take into<br />
account. Now on the first, I would believe on the<br />
evidence and obviously invidious and you don't intend<br />
me to go to particular individuals and empires but as<br />
far as one can see in regard to the areas which would be<br />
in question, if the individuals concerned were to<br />
collapse I believe the enterprises would still go on. I<br />
think, if I may say so, in the television industry there<br />
may be a sort of fining down in some employment areas in<br />
numbers and in perks. And I know that that may be a<br />
matter of individual concern but it is not very relevant<br />
to the national economy. And I hope it won't colour any<br />
people's judgements who may be affected. But I'm making<br />
a serious point that I believe the actual enterprises<br />
would basically go on. So in that sense I don't think we<br />
need have a concern. As to the second point, the<br />
judgements that will be made by the international<br />
community. I think basically, if anything, there might<br />
be some smirks of satisfaction in certain places who've<br />
regarded Australian entrepeneurs as somewhat bumptious<br />
and intrusive. In terms of the judgements they'll make<br />
about the strength of the Australian economy I don't<br />
think it will be disadvantageous.<br />
JOURNALIST: Bob Bowden, SBS Television, Prime Minister.<br />
Assuming your Government is re-elected at the election<br />
next year, you'll have the opportunity to make some<br />
important changes to your front bench. Would you foresee<br />
that Paul Keating would remain as your Treasurer for the<br />
entire duration of your fourth term or would you see it<br />
as appropriate, particularly in the light of Mr Keating's<br />
ambition to lead the Party, that he be given some wider<br />
experience perhaps in a change of portfolio?<br />
PM: Interesting question. It's one which in fact some<br />
time back Paul and I have thrown these ideas around. I<br />
think these points are relevant. He is an outstanding<br />
Treasurer and he enjoys Treasury. I've simply said to<br />
him that if Paul, you, would like in that period to have<br />
some further experience, of course that would be done.<br />
But the choice would be his because if he would prefer<br />
as I think he would -to remain as Treasurer then that<br />
*. would~ be ok.-<br />
JOURNALIST: Laurie Wilson from the Seven Network, Prime<br />
Minister. You said a few moments ago that the<br />
fundamental task facing government was to restructure the<br />
Australian economy. You've been there for some time now<br />
and the Australian people might well wonder why is it<br />
taking so long? Senator Button told us yesterday that<br />
things aren't going to be too easy for another five or<br />
ten years. And John Kerin told us today that he thought<br />
that what Senator Button was reflecting a view that was </p>
<p>kicked around the Cabinet table earlier this week. Can<br />
you be open with us and tell us just how hard you think<br />
things are going to be for the next decade or so?<br />
PM: You're running together two things there. You<br />
started off by talking about restructuring and so on as<br />
though things weren't being done there. Now Button<br />
wasn't talking about that. I just refer you again to<br />
that list that is available here about the restructuring<br />
that has taken place. It's been, as I say,<br />
unprecedented. The task, the fundamental task of<br />
restructuring the Australian economy has been and is<br />
being undertaken at a rate and a size of change<br />
unprecedented in this country. And I'll come to your<br />
second point about what Button said in a moment. But<br />
just let me make this point about the rate and size of<br />
change. You will have heard me say in the Parliament and<br />
elsewhere that for 30 of the 33 years before we came to<br />
office the conservatives were in government. They<br />
established the basic structures and attitudes and<br />
assumptions of the Australia that we inherited. And that<br />
years of inaction, it really has two aspects to it.<br />
Of itself it created the necessity for us to grasp the<br />
nettle and move as we have in this unparalleled way. And<br />
secondly of course that 30 years of inaction provides its<br />
own demolition of the empty rhetoric that they now mouth<br />
about structural reform. Now on the other point about<br />
John Button's observations about the toughness of the<br />
period ahead, that should be seen in the light of what<br />
I've said today. I mean my speech has not been a bed of<br />
roses speech. What I am saying to the Australian people<br />
and I'll say this inside or outside an electoral cycle.<br />
I'll be continuing to say it when I retire hopefully<br />
after the fourth Labor Government. But Australians have<br />
to understand the truth of what I've been saying about<br />
the dynamic changes in the world in which we live. Just<br />
let me very briefly make this point. What happened<br />
Laurie of course was that in that period after the war<br />
when I talked about that decade of lost opportunity, the<br />
conservatives thought it was all just going to fall into<br />
our laps. We just sold our wheat and our wool and our<br />
meat and then we found some more iron ore, we dug that<br />
up, shoved it off and all was easy. But the world now<br />
doesn't need, at the same price level, our agricultural<br />
products. We're battling to sell the damn stuff. We<br />
will because we' re competitive and hopefully change the<br />
international trading laws. But the fundamental thing is<br />
for-Australians -to understand--if-4-hey-' re -going to have<br />
the basis maintaining and improving their standard of<br />
living then they've got to restructure the economy.<br />
They've got to create industries and sectors which are<br />
capable of beating the rest of the world in regard to<br />
imports and also to compete in the export markets. Now<br />
that's going to mean we' re going to need capital coming<br />
into this country and what Button and others, including<br />
John Howard this morning who totally endorsed Button's<br />
comment and he did it and I congratulate Howard for it.<br />
He did it in a non-partisan point-scoring way. He said </p>
<p>these fundamental things are there and are going to<br />
require Australians to understand that in the area of<br />
interest rates for instance, because we're going to need<br />
apples from abroad then marginally, relatively, our<br />
interest rate structure will need to be a bit higher.<br />
That doesn't mean that we can't have it coming down from<br />
the levels it is now. It will come down. But while<br />
those fundamentals are there, while we've got to<br />
restructure our economy, capital from abroad to help us<br />
in that situation while we've got levels of debt, then<br />
those difficulties will be there in relative terms. Now<br />
that's not something which is just understood now, or<br />
something that needs to be said in the context of the<br />
next election. Those things are absolutely fundamental<br />
if Australians, irrespective of partisan considerations,<br />
are going to come to the conclusion that they want to do<br />
what is necessary to provide the best future for their<br />
children. There's no easy cop-out.<br />
JOURNALIST: Steven Burrell from the Australian Financial<br />
Review, Prime Minister. I'd like to take up the<br />
implications of what you just said in line with the<br />
comments of Senator Button, Mr Keating, yourself and now<br />
Mr Howard. It's clear that we're going to have at least<br />
half a decade of tight fiscal policy, tight monetary<br />
policy and very profound structural change. In other<br />
words living standards simply cannot grow at the pace<br />
that Australians have come to accept over the past 20 or<br />
years. What implications does that have for the<br />
survival of the Accord and what sort of modifications may<br />
need to be made to it to make it relevant to your<br />
potential next term of government and beyond?<br />
PM: Steve, that essentially was what a large part of the<br />
speech was about. The Accord is central to the<br />
achievement of overcoming that challenge and<br />
restructuring the Australian economy. Let me try and get<br />
outside the economic jargon if I can so that we get it<br />
down right to the terms of people. What life and the<br />
conduct of an economy is about after all is how do you<br />
best organise your affairs and your activities in a way<br />
which are going to give the greatest degree of<br />
satisfaction to the people in that society? books,<br />
but that's what economics and politics is about. Now<br />
you've got to ask yourself are you just doing in<br />
Australia are we just faced with a situation where we<br />
could make a set of decisions to maximise happiness and<br />
-the--opportunities for. fulfilment.-4ust-within--this group<br />
of 17 million people. Or is it the fact that we live in<br />
a world of over five billion people and we' re<br />
inextricably interwoven with those, so that our<br />
capacities to satisfy ourselves depend upon how we<br />
interact with the rest of the world. Now when you<br />
understand that the answer is, of course, we are part of<br />
the world and increasingly so, then that determines and<br />
constrains the decisions that you can take. OK, now<br />
we'll get it back to the day to day life of our ordinary<br />
fellow Australians. They go to work. Basically people </p>
<p>in this country and we divide it into three groups in<br />
terms of how they derive their income or their capacity<br />
for satisfaction. Three, three groups. There are those<br />
who-employ and so derive their capacity for doing things<br />
that they want to do out of the profit they derive as<br />
employers. There are those who are employed and,<br />
thirdly, and most importantly, which too often in the<br />
past have tended to be forgotten, there are those who for<br />
one reason or another are not part of the productive<br />
process and they derive their income that way, and that<br />
is the young, the old, the disadvantaged. They depend<br />
for their capacity, for satisfaction on what's the<br />
attitude of the community and the preparedness of the<br />
community to look after them. OK. In this Australia in<br />
which we live today and the Australia we're going to live<br />
for the next decade and the Australia that's going into<br />
the twenty first century, the capacity of the ordinary<br />
Australian who's employed, to have his aspirations<br />
satisfied can, if you like, in the immediate sense be<br />
determined by saying I will use my muscle if I'm in a<br />
negotiating position to grab a higher money wage. He<br />
will think that if he grabs a higher money wage, that's<br />
going to enable him to buy some more things which will<br />
satisfy him. And if you replicate that amongst all the<br />
Australians that are working, then what happens then very<br />
simple because the pattern of the past which would be<br />
infinitely sharper in the future is that that is a<br />
certain prescription for recession and for deep<br />
recession. It's what's happened before and the secret, I<br />
mean you look, you know the page of the Budget papers,<br />
what's happened is that we've flattened wages growth,<br />
we've said not by diktat but through the Accord we've<br />
said now there is the second way, the second way in which<br />
this is what the essence of the Accord the essence<br />
of the Accord is there is another way of satisfying some<br />
of your aspirations rather than just getting a massive<br />
money wage increase. The Government is prepared, under<br />
the Accord, to do things which they will be able to do<br />
because of your wage restraint. Therefore, in this<br />
period that you're talking about in five years, there'll<br />
be even more reason for that to be done. I believe that<br />
the trade unions will do it because they will see that to<br />
have now 61 percent of our kids staying on in school is<br />
just about the most fundamentally important thing for<br />
them. We've shifted it, as you know, from the 36 percent<br />
of the conservatives to 61 percent and those kids that<br />
are staying on in the education system are predominantly<br />
. now . coming--from -their-homes,-from-the.. homes -of workers<br />
who previously didn't stay on. Now how do you measure,<br />
in terms of family welfare and decency and building<br />
blocks for the future, how do you begin to measure, ever,<br />
the importance that the kid from the working class family<br />
is now staying on in the education system and wasn't<br />
before and is now going to be able to go on from then<br />
into the 150,000 new university places that we've<br />
created, as against the 26,000 How do you begin to<br />
measure the importance, in terms of welfare for that<br />
family now and into the future and how do you begin to </p>
<p>measure the importance of that as a building block for<br />
future reconstruction? So people get their aspirations<br />
satisfied in more than one way. You can do it<br />
temporarily, but disastrously in the medium to long term<br />
by grabbing more money wages. But in a permanent sense,<br />
you are going to be directing your issues to the real<br />
concerns if, at a reduced level of money wage increase<br />
you enable profits to grow, to go into investment and<br />
create sustainable employment while you're training your<br />
kids, educating them, having a Medicare system which<br />
removes the blight of fear from not being covered.<br />
Looking after your aged, that third group, by putting<br />
another $ 10 billion per annum into social justice<br />
programs. In that way the community is looking after<br />
that third group so employers, workers and those<br />
dependent upon the community get looked after. So the<br />
Accord is central, Steve, and I believe that people will<br />
understand it. Not suggesting it's easy to get the<br />
message across, but I say forget electoral cycles. If we<br />
don't understand that then Hanrahan' s not far wrong.<br />
JOURNALIST: I'd like to turn briefly to the millions of<br />
dollars that the Pilots Federation is potentially facing<br />
in terms of damages as a result of the Victorian Supreme<br />
Court decision, what's view of that decision a couple<br />
of weeks down the track and would you regard it as unduly<br />
provocative to the ACTU for the airlines to try to seek<br />
to collect that money given the support that the general<br />
union movement has given both to your Government in this<br />
dispute and also to the airlines?<br />
PM: Thanks Jim. I want to answer quite directly a<br />
question there. I wonder if you'd excuse me if I just<br />
use that as a peg to hang a couple of observations about<br />
what's been happening in the airline industry and then<br />
come directly to answer that question. Let me say that<br />
if I look back on this now seven years of my Prime<br />
Ministership, I would think probably just about the<br />
saddest, one of the saddest parts of it has been this<br />
whole development within the airline industry, the claim<br />
for the 30 percent and the actions that have had to be<br />
taken to rebuild the airline industry. As I said in my<br />
speech, in that decade from, of the 70s, I think it's<br />
acknowledged that the essence of my approach to<br />
industrial relations is one of conciliation and<br />
consensus, trying to get people together. It grieved me<br />
more than I can say that in this circumstance I wasn't<br />
-able-. to.. play-that. role..--I-mean,. you. had-a-situation<br />
where a group, and I'm not engaging in incriminations<br />
now, but you had a situation where a group made a<br />
decision that having benefited from the Accord that we'vye<br />
been talking about so much because they benefited, the<br />
reduction, negotiated tax reductions as part of the<br />
Accord, pilots they got the benefits of it. In the<br />
area of superannuation they've done enormous and so<br />
on. But they said no we are going outside the system.<br />
Now the simple fact was there that if they had been<br />
allowed to succeed with that claim, it wasn't just the </p>
<p>percent thing for pilots. We know and it was said if<br />
that is allowed to happen then the whole Accord that I've<br />
just been discussing with Steve was gone. That was not<br />
just the pilots getting 30 percent. That was the<br />
destruction of the future of this country that I've been<br />
talking about because the Accord was gone, if the Accord<br />
was gone then we were back into the awful pattern of the<br />
past. So I wanted them not to do it, I asked them not to<br />
and when they were absolutely committed to going ahead<br />
with that dispute and taking on as they'd promised to do<br />
in the, in February to take on the Government, the<br />
airlines, the Commission, the trade union movement, then<br />
firmness, toughness was necessary. I must say that, you<br />
know, looking back that perhaps at some point some of the<br />
language I used may have been better phrased well,<br />
years old? I mean, you can never, 60 years old, I'm not<br />
saying but in 60 years, I mean, if you could look<br />
back I guess there are many times which you would have<br />
phrased some things differently. But, OK, I don't resile<br />
at all from a fundamental point. The AFAP had to be<br />
opposed once that was their position because what you<br />
were fighting was the AFAP as such, but you were fighting<br />
for the Accord and I deeply regret that I, in those<br />
circumstances, there was no role for a conciliator. But<br />
now I come from that background, Jim, to your question.<br />
At no point have I wanted to see the destruction of the<br />
AFAP. I mean that would be anathema to my whole life, to<br />
talk about destroying a union. I think the airlines<br />
almost had to take the action they did and they had our<br />
support. But not from my point of view to exact<br />
retribution. What has come out of that case now is an<br />
independent judicial finding repudiating the pilots<br />
propaganda that here was some conspiracy between the<br />
Government, Hawke, the airlines. I mean that was always<br />
a nonsense, but the propaganda fed out, fed out, fed out.<br />
Now you have a judge of the Supreme Court saying that's<br />
wrong, if anyone was spoiling for a fight, it was the<br />
AFAP. Now I think it's fundamentally important that that<br />
has been established, but let me say this. I believe it<br />
would be wrong for the airlines to collect damages<br />
against the union and it will be my very strong<br />
recommendation to both airlines that they not attempt to<br />
collect damages against the union. What we need now is,<br />
OK they wanted to fight the system, that has been<br />
defeated. I think there's no doubt about that now,<br />
that's been defeated. The important thing is the great<br />
Australian airline industry be rebuilt and that we get<br />
. decent relations -back in -there. -That can happen, but<br />
imposing damages on the AFAP is not my cup of tea and<br />
I'll be strongly recommending to both airlines that they<br />
not proceed to try and get those damages.<br />
JOURNALIST: Geoff Kitney, Australian Financial Review,<br />
Mr Hawke. In your speech you made no particular<br />
reference to the need for Australia to lift its level of<br />
productivity. Given that one of the great criticisms of<br />
the Accord is our poor productivity performance, is it </p>
<p>not the case that one of the great requirements for the<br />
in Australia is that Australians work harder?<br />
PM: Well, Geoff, it's always important to refer to<br />
productivity and I notice that the Leader of the<br />
Opposition, sort of shadow prime minister shadowing a<br />
Press conference because he's not too keen on, you know,<br />
actual ones, prepared a list of questions that ought to<br />
be asked and productivity was one. I'm not saying that<br />
you ask it for that reason. I mean it is a no<br />
seriously, I mean, it's an important question. But I<br />
think these things need to be understood. If you look at<br />
what's been happening in Australia in the period since<br />
the mid 70s that there has been somewhat the growth<br />
in labour productivity and that's in line with experience<br />
in a number of OECD economies. But what you've got to<br />
understand in respect of this period of Government is<br />
that the very significant reduction in real unit labour<br />
costs, and that's at the order of 11 percent, 11.2<br />
percent I think, that signficant reduction in real unit<br />
labour costs has resulted in employers being able to use<br />
labour more beneficially with a given amount of, given<br />
amount of capital just by definition. What has followed<br />
from that, of course, is that that's clearly enhanced the<br />
total productive capacity by the stimulus that's been<br />
provided both to employment, to employment and to<br />
investment. So when you've had this massive increase in<br />
employment. If you have a massive increase in employment<br />
as we have had, and you know the dimensions of it, five<br />
times faster than before, twice as fast as the<br />
industrialised world. Then, when you have that massive<br />
increase in employment, you are going, as a result of<br />
that fact to tend to show lower productivity improvement<br />
figures. I mean, it's just an arithmetical fact. Now,<br />
as a result of what's been happening in this period,<br />
Geoff, what we're going to have is with this enormous<br />
increase in investment that's taken place and as you<br />
know, at 13.5 percent of GDP investment is at the<br />
highest proportion of GDP since records have been kept.<br />
Now that's going into making our industry more efficient<br />
and more competitive, so you are going to have as a<br />
result of the massive increase in employment which has<br />
been accompanied by reduction in real wages, as I've<br />
said, which has allowed profits into investment. That's<br />
creating a situation in which productivity will be able<br />
to increase further in the years ahead. But I then come<br />
to your final point. I don't disagree with the concept<br />
that.-we.--all-ought--to-work--as.. hard-as we -possibly can. I<br />
mean, we've got to understand that out there in that<br />
region of which we are part and you're looking at rates<br />
of growth in the industrialising countries, you<br />
know, averaging eight, nine, ten percent rates of growth.<br />
Now, adding to what had previously been relatively very,<br />
very lowly paid in employment on top of that the<br />
most sophisticated technology and now labour rates are<br />
increasing as we've seen in Korea, for instance. You're<br />
getting competition out there as well as in Europe and<br />
the United States of the sort we haven't seen before. So </p>
<p>we can't be complacent about the fact that we're doing<br />
very much better now than we have in the past, by any<br />
standards doing very much better. But we've got to<br />
understand the world out there is also improving it's<br />
game. So, if we are going to stay up there and try and<br />
get ahead in sectors in which we have natural advantages,<br />
as we do, then we've got to work as hard as we can.<br />
There's one other technical point I think that ought to<br />
be made about productivity measures, Geoff, and I think<br />
you'd appreciate this. That in the last seven years<br />
there's been very, very, very large increases in<br />
employment and growth in the services sector and that<br />
doesn't lend itself to, as you know, in technical terms<br />
is not picked up in productivity measurements in the same<br />
way. Often the assumption in regard to the services<br />
sector was zero. So if, by definition I'm sorry this<br />
is a somewhat technical economic point, but this is a<br />
fact if your economy is growing particularly in the<br />
services area where there is assumption about zero<br />
productivity, you won't get the same reflection of<br />
productivity growth.<br />
JOURNALIST: Robert Hadler from the Australian newspaper,<br />
Mr Hawke. I understand that you and other senior<br />
Ministers are to shortly meet with representatives of the<br />
mining, farming and environmental lobbies. Do you think<br />
it's possible that at that meeting and in the future, the<br />
Government can help to developing a genuine accord on the<br />
issue of sustainable development and that does it require<br />
a more interventionist approach from the Government?<br />
PM: Thanks, Robert. Well, yes, I'm hopeful that we can<br />
get agreement and that gives me the opportunity of<br />
saying, ladies and gentlemen, that when I go back from<br />
here to the office, I'll be holding a very, very<br />
significant meeting which will involve a number of my<br />
Ministers, representatives of industry and the<br />
conservation movement and the trade union movement on the<br />
issue of sustainable development. Now we've deliberately<br />
not wished to publicise that meeting and I'll give you,<br />
and I'll go to tell you the people that are attending,<br />
just give you some idea of the significance of it. Let<br />
me go to that straight away. The people I'll be meeting<br />
will be Lachlin McIntosh of the Australian Mining<br />
Industry Council, Ric Farley of the National Farmers<br />
Federation, Rob Bain of the National Association of<br />
Forest Industries, Phillip Toyne of the Australian<br />
Conservation-. Foundation,. . Judy.-Lambert-of the Wilderness<br />
Society, Simon Crean representing the ACTU and I will<br />
have there my Ministers Kerin, Richardson, Cook and<br />
Button and also attending will be Sir Ninian Stephen, our<br />
Ambassador for the Environment and Ralph Slatyer, my<br />
Chief Scientist. Now you can tell that by any standards<br />
that's a very, very significant meeting. Now we<br />
deliberately haven't publicised it because what we're<br />
about is results and not publicity. I think the fact<br />
that those people have agreed to come and meet with me is<br />
a matter of very, very considerable significance. I </p>
<p>mean, that's just not rhetoric. I mean, the fact that<br />
they are prepared and come to meet together is relevant<br />
to your question. I think it offers some degree of hope<br />
that if we approach this sensibly, we may be able to get<br />
some basis of agreement and that's very important for<br />
Australia because, as I said in the speech, we must not<br />
as a country get into the dichotomy concept of it's<br />
either development or the environment. We've got to have<br />
both and we'll have both in the best possible way if we<br />
can get a basis of agreement and we've got a fair bit of<br />
work ahead of us. I don't think there'll be a magic<br />
outcome just at the end of the meeting today, but I hope<br />
it will provide the building blocks for the future.<br />
JOURNALIST: Michelle Grattan of The Age. Mr Hawke,<br />
you've mentioned that you distributed a very long<br />
document to us on micro reform achievements, but the<br />
Industries Assistance Commission last week, in a couple<br />
of reports stressed that Australia must work a lot harder<br />
and move a lot faster in the areas of micro reform<br />
concerning Government business enterprises and also the<br />
airlines industry. I wondered if you could give us your<br />
comments on those reports? And secondly, there seems<br />
some uncertainty about what the Government envisages for<br />
enterprise agreements under your wage system. Mr Keating<br />
has touched on this but not clarified it. Could you do<br />
that for us?<br />
PM: Yes. Well taking the first point, Michelle, I think<br />
that the IAC reports, if they were somewhat less than<br />
adequate in their acknowledgement of what has already<br />
been done, but I don't quibble about that. On the<br />
substance of that first part of your question, the<br />
Cabinet is going to be considering further submissions,<br />
particularly from Mr Willis under who many of the<br />
Government business enterprises come, as to how we can<br />
make even more efficient the operation of those<br />
enterprises and the contribution that they can make to<br />
the essential infrastructure of the country. We will be<br />
considering further reports from him and I can assure you<br />
that we will be prepared to act. I just, in passing,<br />
before I go on to your second question, make the point<br />
that it's extremely easy for people to sit in boardrooms<br />
or bureaucratic chairs and say do this, do that, do that.<br />
You've got to, if you're going to maximise your chances<br />
as a nation of making lasting non-disruptive effective<br />
reform, try and take the parties who are involved with<br />
you. Now-that-doesn't-mean-, and--I -make it quite clear,<br />
take this opportunity to say it, that doesn't mean that,<br />
that without agreement in every situation, then nothing<br />
can be done. We will try and get the agreement of those<br />
involved for the changes that are necessary and hopefully<br />
we'll always be able to get it, but there may come a<br />
point at which that's not possible. If that's the case<br />
we won't shirk taking the decisions that may be necessary<br />
in those circumstances. But coming to the second<br />
question you asked about enterprise based bargaining.<br />
What needs to be understood, Michelle, is that both under </p>
<p>the processes of award restructuring and under our 1988<br />
industrial relations legislation, both of those provide<br />
mechanisms, such as, for instance, under that legislation<br />
the idea of enterprised based certified agreements.<br />
That's there and that mechanism is provided. So that<br />
under both the award restructuring process and our 1988<br />
amendments, the mechanisms are there and they are<br />
supported by the ACTU for a more concerted move towards<br />
arrangements which better reflect the needs of individual<br />
industries and enterprises. So this is not something<br />
that we have to be persuaded about. We both introduced<br />
the legislation to facilitate it and under the wage<br />
principles in which we've been deeply involved, the<br />
processes for greater orientation towards enterprise and<br />
industry negotiation is there and it's happening. Now<br />
let me, there but go to the next point. The great gulf<br />
between us and the conservatives is that as well as<br />
having the mechanisms for facilitating that sort of<br />
approach, you must, if you are concerned about proper<br />
control and management of the economy and the preparation<br />
for the future, you've got to have a mechanism which<br />
deals with aggregate wages outcomes. So what we've got<br />
is a mechanism under the legislation and under the wage<br />
fixing principles with is increasingly providing the<br />
mechanisms for enterprise oriented wage negotiations.<br />
But at the same time, under the centralised system, which<br />
is giving an impetus to those things, we have the<br />
mechanism for controlling aggregate wage outcomes. This<br />
is where what you witnessed last week was not just some<br />
sad joke about a man wanting to be the Prime Minister of<br />
this country, when asked that central question, will more<br />
of it come out of enterprise bargaining or more out of<br />
system, threw up its hands in hopelessness and said<br />
' who's to know', really, I mean, ' who's to know'. As you<br />
understand, he on that simple question about enterprise<br />
bargaining was saying well I don't know whether this is<br />
not going to blow the economy through the roof. Now<br />
that's the difference. We have the mechanisms for, which<br />
are being employed to move to enterprise bargaining, but<br />
as distinct from our opponents, we have the mechanism for<br />
ensuring acceptable and responsible aggregate outcomes.<br />
How are we going?<br />
BARTON: David Barnett. We're almost at the end of the<br />
first page of questions and we've got a second.<br />
PM: I'll be here for my<br />
JOURNALIST: Are you aware of the views coming from some<br />
economists which associates the blowout in the deficit on<br />
the current account with the rise in the level of<br />
immigration, both of them taking place over the past six<br />
or seven years? Have you given any consideration to<br />
these concerns and have you come to any conclusions?<br />
PM: Good question David. I know that for a very very<br />
long period now in the economics profession there has<br />
been a quite fundamental division of opinion about the </p>
<p>economic impacts of migration. I've been associated with<br />
that debate, followed it over a very very long period of<br />
time and there are those who say that economic<br />
benefit, others who say that it's not. Bringing it to<br />
the present situation David I think you'd have to say<br />
this. That it is the case that where we now have<br />
considerable pressure upon our resources and with high<br />
economic growth rates, high employment growth rates, that<br />
you can argue that higher rather than lower immigration<br />
levels are going to exacerbate demand and to the extent<br />
that that happens that that will put more pressures on<br />
our external accounts problem area. And against that<br />
you've got to, as always in economics, you've got to look<br />
at the other side and ask yourself the question does<br />
Australia need to build up its population so that<br />
enterprises within this country have a larger market so<br />
they get the benefits of larger scale production, the<br />
economies of large scale production, which makes them<br />
more competitive against imports and more competitive on<br />
export markets. And David there is no definitive answer<br />
to that question. I think I would put it this way. If I<br />
were to state my long term view, my medium to long term<br />
view, I would believe that Australia is better off, its<br />
future is going to be more secure and more prosperous, if<br />
we have an accelerated population growth. I think, as I<br />
said in some interview I did recently, that if you look<br />
at Australia and Canada and look at that<br />
approximately $ 8 million difference, there's a sort of<br />
critical mass difference in that area. I know of course<br />
the benefits they have from being adjacent to the largest<br />
market of the United States. But I do think Australia<br />
would be better off with a larger rather than a smaller<br />
population. But I emphasise, that's a medium to long<br />
term view. It's also said in that interview I think if<br />
we are going to even think about that, and I'm saying no<br />
more that that should be a matter of debate and<br />
discussion in this country, then we have to look at the<br />
question of housing. While Australians have a<br />
commitment, as they historically tend to do to the<br />
quarter acre block, separate quarter acre block, that<br />
imposes much greater demands upon resources than a<br />
society which has got perhaps a greater proportion of its<br />
population wanting to be involved in medium density<br />
housing. Now let me make it quite clear so there can be<br />
no misrepresentation of what I'm saying. What we did at<br />
the Premiers' Conference David was to say there let's<br />
look at some pilot projects, let's look at the question<br />
of. regulations -as . to. whether-medi-um.. density housing in<br />
the areas can,-be developed. I happen to think<br />
there's a lot of Australians would prefer that, would on<br />
balance prefer that to the distance they have to go now<br />
in major cities. So if we can get a greater acceptance<br />
in Australia of that sort of concept, willingly, knowing<br />
that many people still want the separate quarter acre<br />
block and are entitled to have it and should be able to<br />
proceed for it. But if we get that sort of change in our<br />
community on housing attitudes then we can, in relation<br />
to your question, contemplate high levels of population </p>
<p>with a greater degree of equanimity. But right at this<br />
time I don't think that it would be sensible to increase<br />
the immigration levels. What we are may I make this<br />
point finally on this question what we are of course<br />
doing is to continuously look at the composition of our<br />
immigration and we hope that we will be getting many<br />
people here under the business migration program who will<br />
start enterprises which will be productive and which in<br />
net terms will obviously benefit our external account<br />
position. We also hope that in the areas of skilled<br />
shortages we'll be getting people in who will help us in<br />
that respect. But we'd still retain the necessity in<br />
this community to have a family reunion program and I<br />
hope that all Australians would accept the necessity for<br />
that component in our immigration program which is<br />
humanitarian. I've taken a little bit of time to answer<br />
that but I want to say that I think therefore David that<br />
if you're really going to address this question you need<br />
to separate the immediate term from the longer term. In<br />
the longer term I am a larger population man provided we<br />
take account of these other things. In the immediate<br />
term I think there is no case for increasing it.<br />
JOURNALIST: Niki Savva from the Melbourne Sun, Mr Hawke.<br />
You've recently from the Access Economics survey of a<br />
billion surge in investment. Have you or other<br />
Ministers studied these figures to determine where this<br />
investment is going, especially given Dr Shand's<br />
remarks earlier this week that much of it is not going<br />
into tradeable industries?<br />
PM: Well the Access Economics itself identifies a number<br />
of these and we have also. I haven't got the document in<br />
front of me but I think you'll recall Niki it's broken up<br />
into, I think I say this subject to recollections<br />
about 30% in manufacturing, and a similar sort of<br />
proportion in tourism, and others in the areas of the<br />
service sector and obviously another proportion into<br />
mining. All I know is that Access Economics has made<br />
this calculation. It said of the $ 90 billion investment<br />
projects which they identify, just under $ 50 billion are<br />
in the category of ' under construction' or ' committed',<br />
the balance in ' under serious consideration' and their<br />
calculation is that of the former two categories ' under<br />
construction' or ' committed', which is just under<br />
billion, that that will produce export earnings in the<br />
near future of the order of an additional $ 5 billion per<br />
annum.-And-they-say that.-if. the--$ 90-billion comes on,<br />
and they see no reason why it shouldn't, that that will<br />
produce export earnings, additional export earnings of<br />
billion per annum. Now we have no reason to question<br />
the accuracy of those figures. In other words whether it<br />
is in actual manufacturing or in tourism, the<br />
contribution to our external account position is on their<br />
calculation $ 10 billion per annum additional. I've had<br />
no analysis put before me which would suggest that those<br />
calculations of Access Economics are inaccurate and I<br />
would be profoundly surprised if the Leader of the </p>
<p>Opposition is going to question the accuracy of Access<br />
Economics. It'd be interesting if he does.<br />
JOURNALIST: Don Woolford from Australian Associated<br />
Press, Prime Minister.<br />
PM: You had your run yesterday mate.<br />
JOURNALIST: You've spoken with pride about your<br />
industrial relations and wages policy and the centrality<br />
of the Accord, yet trade union membership is declining.<br />
The decline is most obvious in the areas where your<br />
Government has been most successful in job creation. Why<br />
do an increasing number of rank and file unionists seem<br />
to be regarding the movement as irrelevant and could this<br />
be one of the costs of your Government's very close<br />
relations with the ACTU leadership?<br />
PM: To answer the last part first, no I don't think so.<br />
If you look at the position of trade union membership<br />
figures around the world what's happening in Australia is<br />
not unusual. Indeed in Australia we have a very, by<br />
world average standards, still a very very very much<br />
higher proportion of workers in trade unions than in<br />
other industrialised countries. So it's not a position<br />
of gloom. I mean if you for instance look at the United<br />
States, it's a devastatingly different, much worse<br />
picture there from the unions' point of view. So no, I<br />
don't think that there is that simple relationship. Let<br />
me say this. I think one of the problems, trade<br />
unionist leadership, and therefore in a sense perception<br />
of workers is that it is the case and you simply can't<br />
argue otherwise it is the case that under the Accord<br />
processes much of the traditional function of trade union<br />
leadership has been changed. Because under this system,<br />
instead of as I was saying in a fairly long answer I<br />
gave to Steve instead of the satisfaction of<br />
aspirations being done purely through the avenue of<br />
increased money wages, and battling for improvements in<br />
conditions and so on, now that is being done through the<br />
social wage area and through the centralised wage fixing<br />
system. And unions give a commitment to a no further<br />
claims position. So it is the case, unarguably it is the<br />
case that in this seven year period the role and<br />
functions of trade unions have changed. Because if you<br />
have commitment, as they've given, to a centralised wage<br />
fixing system, the aggregate outcomes are determined<br />
there -and-they-make-. a commitment--to-no further claims, as<br />
they do, and a lot of their other conditions are<br />
satisfied for the social wage, by definition the area of<br />
activity open to trade unions has by their own decision<br />
been closed of f. Now it may be I mean I haven't<br />
analysed it it may well be that that fact of itself has<br />
had some impact upon the relevance that workers may see<br />
for individual trade union activity. I mean I would like<br />
to see that examined. But the important logical<br />
conclusion that follows from that is that if that is a<br />
factor in declining membership it's not a reflection of </p>
<p>inadequacy on the part of the trade union movement. It's<br />
a great paradox that they are losing members because they<br />
have been so responsible and effective.<br />
JOURNALIST: Tim Colebatch from The Age, Mr Hawke. You<br />
said in your speech a moment ago that your Government<br />
PM: Seems like two hours ago mate.<br />
JOURNALIST: Two hours ago. You said I take it it's<br />
still current.<br />
PM: I was going not to the currency of the speech but,<br />
you know, the physical condition.<br />
JOURNALIST: At the time of it, anyway, you were<br />
committed to a quote unyielding defence of a fair and<br />
efficient taxation system.<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
JOURNALIST: Last week the Taxation Commissioner<br />
published statistics which showed that income<br />
millionaires that's people with incomes of $ 1 million<br />
or more a year were paying a lower rate of average tax<br />
than most of the people in this room. About 29% compared<br />
with say 35% for people around $ 100,000. And most of<br />
that was due to the tax break you gave them, the dividend<br />
imputation scheme.<br />
PM: Dividend imputation, yes that's right.<br />
JOURNALIST: Is that what you regard as a fair and<br />
efficient taxation system? If so, why? And if not, do<br />
you propose to change it?<br />
PM: I certainly don't propose to change the full<br />
dividend imputation for the very simple reason that that<br />
was done to make investment in enterprises more<br />
attractive. We had a question before you'll recall about<br />
the possible collapse of some our big enterprises which<br />
of course impart a reflection of their massive<br />
overgearing. It's obviously very much in the interests<br />
of Australian enterprises and of the Australian economy<br />
generally that you make equity investment in enterprises<br />
more attractive. This is not something to be seen as a<br />
handout to a particular group of people. It is a<br />
fundamental--structural -reform-that-you have a situation<br />
where people find-it more attractive to invest in equity<br />
terms in enterprises in this country. And it may just as<br />
well say, in terms of that simplistic sort of analysis<br />
that was underlying that question, that isn't it awful<br />
that you've had a move from wages to profits. Isn't that<br />
terrible? It's going to the poor workers into the hands<br />
of those filthy capitalists. That sort of analysis, you<br />
know, it's old hat. The trade union movement understands<br />
that it's old hat. The important thing is if you make<br />
these changes, these changes in policy, that they be </p>
<p>related to the overriding goal of the restructuring of<br />
the Australian economy. That's got to be the fundamental<br />
concern that you're about. That's what the Accord's been<br />
about-fundamental restructuring. We don't simply end<br />
the analysis by saying ' wages share down, profits share<br />
up, terrible, terrible, terrible, isn't that awful'. I<br />
mean that would be nonsense because that has been the<br />
means, the root to getting the investment which is going<br />
to involve the restructuring of the economy. Similarly<br />
with the tax changes. Imputation wasn't given to say we<br />
want to provide more money to privileged people. It was<br />
an instrument which was brought in to ensure as part of a<br />
total approach to macroeconomic policy that you made it<br />
more attractive for people to invest in equity terms in<br />
Australian enterprises. That is what's happening. If<br />
you want to go to the question of the overall impact of<br />
our taxation reforms in terms of equity, that is an<br />
argument or debate I'll have anywhere, anytime. Because<br />
the simple facts are, and let me remind you of what we've<br />
changed in that respect. You don't have the statements<br />
now that characterise the end of the previous<br />
conservative administration, the two statements that the<br />
fastest growing industry in Australia is the tax<br />
avoidance industry Costigan or Mathews that<br />
increasingly it's becoming a matter of choice for the<br />
rich as to whether they pay their taxes. That was the<br />
devastating, damning indictment of the conservatives<br />
after seven years. But under us, because we've brought<br />
in the instruments, people are now paying taxes that they<br />
wouldn't otherwise pay. Most importantly of course the<br />
capital gains tax and the fringe benefits tax. Now if<br />
the conservatives were to have their way on that, as you<br />
know that would involve the massive redistribution to the<br />
rich from the poor and middle income Australia that we ' ye<br />
ever seen in this country. And that won't happen.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, we're in your hands. We've<br />
got a lot of questions to go. Do you want to go on or<br />
PM: Just a minute. What time is this meeting that we're<br />
having? Say another ten minutes.<br />
JOURNALIST: Peter Rees, the West Australian, Prime<br />
Minister. You spoke of vision in your speech. One of<br />
your former State colleagues, Brian Burke, also had a<br />
vision, WA Inc, which turned sour. How concerned are you<br />
about the electoral impact of that federally given that<br />
Joe--Berinson -revealed. yesterday that * the-losses from WA<br />
Inc will cost the-State's taxpayers $ 446 million? And<br />
what do you think that says about governments getting<br />
close to big business?<br />
PM: Well let me go through it in sequence. Firstly,<br />
obviously if the West Australian Labor Government is<br />
being hurt by what is emerging in regard to that area of<br />
activities, if they are being hurt by that that is not<br />
good for us. I mean, simple. I've got no more to say<br />
about that. I mean obviously if they are being hurt, to </p>
<p>some extent, to some extent we'd be hurt. Although I<br />
think that the West Australian electors would basically<br />
distinguish the federal issues from the state there. I<br />
believe that that would be the case. But marginally,<br />
obviously Peter there must be some adverse spin-off on<br />
us. Secondly, about getting close to big business, well<br />
I just simply don't know what you mean by that. There<br />
are ways and ways of getting close to big business. It<br />
can be done unwisely, it can be done wisely. So if<br />
there's some sinister, you know, covert, unstated<br />
implication in the tail of your question that are we in<br />
an improper way close to big business, answer no.<br />
JOURNALIST: Peter Bowers, Sydney Morning Herald. Happy<br />
birthday Prime Minister.<br />
PM: G'day Peter, how are you?<br />
JOURNALIST: I must say I'm relieved that I get the<br />
opportunity to ask this question while we're still both<br />
on the safe side of<br />
PM: Yes. a bit safer than you mate.<br />
JOURNALIST: Pardon?<br />
PM: I look a bit safer than you I might say.<br />
JOURNALIST: We'll see about that.<br />
PM: We'll see about that. Don't you worry about that<br />
Peter, don't you worry about that.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, I've outlived quite a few<br />
Prime Ministers in my time.<br />
PM: By gee if you had to face your bloody electorate<br />
it'd be a different story mate.<br />
S JOURNALIST: I face my constituency every Saturday.<br />
Prime Minister, in keeping with the reflective mood of<br />
your speech I'd like to ask you about migration. Would<br />
you agree that Australia's post-war migration has been<br />
one of the great, if not the greatest success stories of<br />
our time and if so, would you also agree that the<br />
throwing open of Eastern Europe to the West, a miracle, a<br />
peaceful miracle we never believed we'd see in our time,<br />
* offers-us a wonderful opportunity to increase quality<br />
migration from that area? And by quality migration I<br />
mean young people, young couples, young families, with<br />
skills and a future that Australia could well use.<br />
PM: Let me say Peter I absolutely agree and in regard to<br />
the first part of your question about Australia's postwar<br />
immigration program I've said on a number of<br />
occasions that one of the things that moved me into the<br />
Australian Labor Party in my first year at university<br />
when I started thinking about these things was the sense </p>
<p>of excitement that I had about the great adventure that<br />
was being undertaken by the Labor Government of that<br />
period in opening up Australia. And as a student at<br />
university I committed myself then, not only through my<br />
membership of the Labor Party to that support, but I<br />
also, may I say, in those years at university when we had<br />
so many students coming under the Colombo plan, I went<br />
out of my way there to establish mechanisms and so on to<br />
try and ensure that those people who were coming to our<br />
country from Asia also were given the best possible<br />
chance of melding into our society. So for me, yes<br />
Peter, that was one of the motivating forces in me<br />
getting involved in the Labor Party, because I was<br />
thrilled with what they were doing there. And there is<br />
no doubt there was a country at the end of the Second<br />
World War, seven million people. And what John Curtin<br />
and Chifley understood was, as they were fighting during<br />
that Second World War Australia, that it had to be a<br />
different Australia. They didn't want to just go back to<br />
the old. And the essential ingredient in creating the<br />
new Australia was that vast migration program the<br />
dimensions of which are probably best understood by, if<br />
we say and remind ourselves we should never cease to<br />
remind ourselves of the dimension. As of this day four<br />
out of every ten Australians were either born overseas or<br />
the child of a parent born overseas. I mean that's the<br />
dramatic illustration Peter of what you're talking about.<br />
That's the dimension of the economic and social<br />
significance of immigration in this country. And yes<br />
it's the most important thing that's happened. Now going<br />
to the second part of your question. ours is a nondiscriminatory<br />
immigration policy. And to the extent<br />
that people, and particularly young people, from these<br />
countries of Eastern Europe want to come to Australia,<br />
the opportunity will be there for them. But I want to<br />
make this and they will be welcome because I think many<br />
of them would have a great contribution to make. But let<br />
me make this point. I think in the great sense, the<br />
proper sense of excitement that we have about the<br />
momentous, and as you rightly say, hitherto perhaps<br />
unimaginable changes that are occuring there, I would<br />
hope that a lot of these people would say if those<br />
changes are going to be able to have their fullest<br />
flowering that they will want to be part of it. I mean<br />
the great challenge now, I think, for the peoples of<br />
Eastern Europe is to say a) we are going to make sure<br />
that these reforms stick and are extended so that people<br />
will-have-freedom and liberty-and..-that we have a more<br />
competitive economic society in which there can be the<br />
release of talent so that they will feel a political<br />
opportunity and that they will want to be part of making<br />
their countries greater and more significant as they can<br />
with this new-found freedom. And my own judgement is<br />
that that's what so many of them will want to do. But I<br />
repeat, if there are those who want to come to Australia<br />
they will be welcome.<br />
BARTON: Last question from Bruce Juddery. </p>
<p>PM: Couldn't be a Press Club without a question from<br />
you, Brucey.<br />
JOURNALIST: inaudible<br />
PM: declaration mate.<br />
JOURNALIST: So you'll be happy I'll make it a double<br />
header. Prime Minister, in the last few weeks a number<br />
of the Government's senior advisers have dropped little<br />
hints that perhaps some of the assumptions of the Hawke<br />
Government are under question or being re-examined. For<br />
instance, Fred Argy of the Economic Planning Advisory<br />
Council has pointed out that if the real truth that<br />
regulations are to be taken seriously which Germany<br />
would be a basket case and Chris Higgins of the<br />
Treasury has suggested that we can't keep on starving<br />
infrastructure investment further, we're going to have to<br />
start channelling some more money back in that direction.<br />
At the Cabinet level, is there yet similar examination of<br />
the truths of the Hawke years and are we likely to hear<br />
about the results of the re-examination before the<br />
election? And second question, have you had a look at<br />
the terms of trade suffered a sudden sharp downwards<br />
in the last national accounts figures. Are you concerned<br />
about that? If it's a downward trend after two years of<br />
improvement would that mean a complete finish to any<br />
chances of reducing interest rates between now and the<br />
next election?<br />
PM: Well as to the first question, no I have no<br />
apprehension Bruce, that the sort of people that you're<br />
talking about are questioning the fundamental truths. On<br />
the contrary I notice that there is some almost adverse<br />
comments in the Press recently that the Higgins to whom<br />
you refer and the Fraser Bernie Fraser that is<br />
although Malcolm's quite good in his statements most days<br />
-true in support but that there is some criticism<br />
almost that the Higgins and the Frasers were far too<br />
explicitly supportive of what the Government was doing.<br />
So I discern no view amongst the mandarins, or however<br />
you want to describe them, of a disaffection with or predirection<br />
to change direction. As to the second part<br />
about the terms of trade, obviously Bruce, let me make it<br />
clear I'm answering this question I'll come to the<br />
national accounts in a moment if Australia were to<br />
suffer a--continuing-significant-. reversal in the terms of<br />
trade we know that creates problems. God, we've been<br />
there in 85/ 86, wiped what it was $ 11B, I think I<br />
remember that phrase from the 1987 campaign, I guess some<br />
of you remember it too, I mean I had to keep saying it, I<br />
just wasn't speaking to you all the time, wiped $ 11B off<br />
our national income. If that sort of thing happens then<br />
it creates difficulties and economic management has to be<br />
adjusted. But let me say I'm not expecting that. The<br />
best indications that we can have are optimistic about in<br />
aggregate, it doesn't mean that there won't be some </p>
<p>23<br />
elements of our exports that may not have the price going<br />
down, we've certainly had some difficulties about people<br />
staying out of the wool market to this stage, we hope<br />
that's going to be changed. But Bruce, the fundamental<br />
question there is the fundamental response to your<br />
question is we don't anticipate any significant problem<br />
arising from the area that you're talking about. You<br />
mention the national accounts, just let me sort of go to<br />
the of certain trends that can appear over the last<br />
twelve months. If you look at the question of exports<br />
for the last three quarters, March, June and September,<br />
increase in exports and this is in constant prices as<br />
being March quarter 2.1% in June 89, 2.6% in<br />
September 89. So a rising trend of exports against the<br />
situation of imports, 9.3, 1.7, minus 0.8. So if you<br />
look at the most recent sort of figures in aggregate<br />
terms we have an improving export position and imports<br />
coming down. So if you're looking at these external<br />
influences, while you can't afford to be complacent in<br />
any area of economic policy making but I'm not disturbed<br />
by the potential element that you're talking about.<br />
ends<br />
0 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
