<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10686</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                PRESS CONFERENCE                PRIME MINISTER&amp;#146;S COURTYARD, PARLIAMENT HOUSE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/12/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE....................................................................................................</p>
<p> Ladies and gentlemen, I've called this news conference</p>
<p> to make a short statement about the military action taken by the United</p>
<p> States and the United Kingdom against Iraq. This military action has,</p>
<p> on all of the evidence available to the Australian Government, become</p>
<p> necessary as a result of Iraq's failure to comply with the understanding</p>
<p> that was entered into some weeks ago when Saddam Hussein said that</p>
<p> his regime would allow UN inspectors.</p>
<p>It is plain from a reading of Mr Butler's report to the Secretary-General</p>
<p> that the United States and the United Kingdom have been left with</p>
<p> no alternative. I have examined that report. It is stark and unambiguous.</p>
<p> Not only does it detail the fact that Iraq has refused to honour the</p>
<p> undertakings entered into several weeks ago but, on top of that, Iraq</p>
<p> has, in fact, sought to impose further restrictions and further conditions</p>
<p> on the inspection teams. Now, in those circumstances, regrettable</p>
<p> though it may be, any use of force is always to be regretted and is</p>
<p> always a sad event, I do not believe, and the Australian Government</p>
<p> does not believe, that the United States and the United Kingdom have</p>
<p> been left with any alternative. This has been very much a case of</p>
<p> it being unavoidable and inevitable that if Iraq failed to comply</p>
<p> with the earlier undertakings then some military action to degrade</p>
<p> Iraq's military capacity, particularly in relation to her near</p>
<p> neighbours, would eventuate. And the sequence of events has been very</p>
<p> clear. The Australian Government has been kept informed over past</p>
<p> weeks of developments.</p>
<p>But I say again that if you examine the report of Mr Butler to the</p>
<p> Secretary-General it is clear, it is quite stark and quite unambiguous,</p>
<p> there's been a total failure by Iraq to honour the undertakings</p>
<p> and worse still Iraq has sought to make it even harder for UNSCOM</p>
<p> to inspect sites that may house weapons of mass destruction.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, you say that the United States and the United Kingdom</p>
<p> were left with little choice. What about Australia, what involvement</p>
<p> will we have?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, Australia is not involved militarily but naturally as a country</p>
<p> concerned about the activity of Saddam Hussein and a country that</p>
<p> participated in earlier military actions and made forces available</p>
<p> a few months ago in order to support an allied action, naturally we're</p>
<p> asked for a view. And I'm expressing the view of the Australian</p>
<p> Government that we believe the American and British action is justified</p>
<p> and we support that action.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Have you been asked to participate?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Will you consider involvement?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, we haven't received a request. I don't expect that</p>
<p> we will receive a request. But if we were to receive a request, of</p>
<p> course we would consider it but I do not expect that any request will</p>
<p> be forthcoming.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What's the difference between this time and last time when we</p>
<p> did participate, why are we not being asked this time?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, because, well, the last time is really the one a few weeks ago</p>
<p> where we got very close to a strike and then at the last minute Saddam</p>
<p> said that he would let the inspectors in and, of course, he hasn't</p>
<p> honoured the undertakings. Now, on that particular occasion, for all</p>
<p> the reasons that were obvious then that what was involved was an air</p>
<p> strike, that Australia was not asked. I mean, I'm not going to</p>
<p> sort of debate reasons as to whether we may or may not be asked on</p>
<p> particular occasions. We look at each situation according to the Australian</p>
<p> national interest. Now, the situation on this occasion is very simply</p>
<p> that on the last occasion that we got to the brink, right at the last</p>
<p> moment there was a diplomatic breakthrough and Saddam Hussein indicated</p>
<p> a willingness to allow the inspection teams in and on condition that</p>
<p> they were allowed in and they were allowed access the Americans and</p>
<p> the British suspended any military strike. Now those conditions have</p>
<p> not been fulfilled and it is plain and clear from a reading of the</p>
<p> Butler report that there's been a total failure by Iraq to co-operate.</p>
<p> In those circumstances the situation really reverts to what it was</p>
<p> some weeks ago when Iraq, at the last minute, climbed down.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, have you been contacted directly from the White House</p>
<p> this time?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, I haven't. There was really no need on this occasion for</p>
<p> any personal communication between the President and myself. Firstly,</p>
<p> Australian forces are not involved and, secondly and I think more</p>
<p> obviously, the action taken by the Americans and the British became</p>
<p> inevitable once Iraq refused to participate. I mean, obviously we</p>
<p> were informed at an official level in Washington of when the strike</p>
<p> took place but I haven't had any personal contact with the President</p>
<p> nor did I, on this occasion, expect it.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do you have any concerns that the timing of this attack could erode</p>
<p> America's standing internationally?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, I don't. It ought not to erode America's standing internationally.</p>
<p> If you are referring to domestic matters in the United States, I think</p>
<p> they have to be kept quite separate from this. I look at the available</p>
<p> evidence and the available evidence is the manifest refusal of Iraq</p>
<p> to honour the undertakings it gave about inspections. If I were in</p>
<p> any doubt about that then I would have a different view. But the test</p>
<p> of the bona fides of the American and British action is whether Iraq</p>
<p> has complied or not complied with the undertakings given some time</p>
<p> ago and, plainly, from the Butler report - and there's no suggestion</p>
<p> that it's anything other than totally accurate - Iraq has not</p>
<p> complied. Now, in those circumstances, unless you are to roll over</p>
<p> to Saddam and allow him to retain his weapons of mass destruction</p>
<p> and give him an enormous diplomatic and moral victory, not only in</p>
<p> the middle-east but also around the world, plainly you have to take</p>
<p> the action that the Americans and the British have taken. And from</p>
<p> Australia's point of view it's appropriate that I indicate</p>
<p> publicly, as much as we always regret any military action, that we</p>
<p> support the decision.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What future do you think the UN inspection regime now has?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I beg your pardon?</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What future do you think the United Nations' inspection regime</p>
<p> now has?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I think its future must be under an enormous cloud because unless</p>
<p> you get co-operation from Iraq it's very difficult to see it</p>
<p> having any real future. But the ball has been squarely in Saddam Hussein's</p>
<p> court for some weeks now. And we got to the brink before and then</p>
<p> we pulled back because he said he'd let the teams in. The teams</p>
<p> went in and then he reverted to type, and if you read the Butler report,</p>
<p> he went a step further. He actually made it even harder on this occasion</p>
<p> than it had been on earlier occasion. Now, in those circumstances</p>
<p> I don't really know what other action the Americans and the British</p>
<p> could have taken.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Given the gravity of this situation, do you think that the impeachment</p>
<p> process currently underway in the States should be put on hold or</p>
<p> abandoned altogether?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>That is a matter for the Americans. I don't give gratuitous advice</p>
<p> to the Americans as to how to conduct their domestic politics. I'm</p>
<p> not going to make any comment on that or give any advice. That is</p>
<p> a matter for the congress of the United States and the President of</p>
<p> the United States, not for the Prime Minister of Australia.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[Inaudible] of this strike?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, it was inevitable, Tony, that this was going to happen once</p>
<p> the process broke down. I mean, we knew that.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[Inaudible]</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, no, we were told at the time the strike was launched but I was</p>
<p> also warned last night from our usual sources that it was imminent</p>
<p> because of what had happened. I mean, if you have a situation where</p>
<p> you are about to launch a strike and right at the last minute Iraq</p>
<p> says, well hang on, we'll let the inspection teams in and on</p>
<p> that condition you put the strike into suspense, it follows as a matter</p>
<p> of common sense that if Iraq then reneges on what it has said it's</p>
<p> going to do and, in fact, turns the notch up one it makes it even</p>
<p> harder that once that happens well you are back to where you were</p>
<p> a few weeks ago. I mean, that was plainly obvious to us several days</p>
<p> ago.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>In the light of what you have just said about the future of the inspection</p>
<p> regime and Saddam Hussein's recalcitrance...[inaudible]...first,</p>
<p> where do we go from here and secondly, what should the objective of</p>
<p> this action be, just to degrade the weapons or to somehow displace</p>
<p> the Saddam Hussein regime in Iraq?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, the stated objective is to degrade their military capacity.</p>
<p> I am not going to at this stage speculate further as to what might</p>
<p> happen in relation to Saddam Hussein. I mean, I understand that from</p>
<p> a reading of what the President said in his press conference and also</p>
<p> from what the British Prime Minister have said that their objective</p>
<p> is limited to a degrading of military capacity. I think that is appropriate</p>
<p> at the present time.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, ... the department of Foreign Affairs have issued</p>
<p> a warning to Australians not to travel to Iraq and urge those there</p>
<p> to leave, what information do you have about the number of Australians</p>
<p> who are in Iraq and what if any assistance will the Australian Government</p>
<p> be giving?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, we'll give all the assistance that we can through consular</p>
<p> and other means. And there is a very small number of Australians in</p>
<p> Iraq and I understand all the members of the inspection team have</p>
<p> left and, I mean, in these circumstances we'll do everything</p>
<p> we can.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>You don't have an embassy in Iraq.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, but we have consular arrangements with another country.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do we have any other military involvement in this operation, for example,</p>
<p> through our joint facilities?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I never comment on the use of the joint facilities.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>There are no other military personnel active in the American forces</p>
<p> from Australia?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, there are no Australian forces deployed in this operation.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[Inaudible] contingency plans...?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, the Australian defence forces always have a capacity to respond</p>
<p> in these circumstances if the Government think it is appropriate.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[Inaudible]</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, look, it would be quite foolish of me to even try and answer</p>
<p> that sort of question. There is no request of Australia for involvement.</p>
<p> I do not anticipate receiving a request for Australian involvement.</p>
<p> I simply make the point, Bernard, that if a request were received</p>
<p> the operational readiness of the ADF is such that we could respond</p>
<p> to that request if the Australian Government thought it were appropriate</p>
<p> to do so. But I do not expect to get that request.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[Inaudible] undermine western interests?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>In which region?</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>In the Middle East.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, you have to look at the merits of what is occurring and the</p>
<p> merits are very plain. The Americans and the British with our support</p>
<p> went to the brink before and pulled back and Saddam Hussein has once</p>
<p> again thumbed his nose at proper process and left them with no alternative.</p>
<p> And in those circumstances you have to argue your case and there will</p>
<p> be mixed reactions from Arab countries as there has been in the past.</p>
<p> But Arab countries have suffered very much at the hands of Saddam</p>
<p> Hussein and I would hope that those countries would keep that in mind.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, what do you think is the long-term solution?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, the long-term solution is for him to begin behaving in a tolerably</p>
<p> civilised fashion.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>That is extremely unlikely.....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I think it is extremely unlikely.....</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[inaudible] to get rid of Saddam Hussein.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, look once again I am not...I haven't called this news</p>
<p> conference to start declaring, you know, what happens in detail inside</p>
<p> individual countries. We have been confronted with a clear choice</p>
<p> between rolling over to a dictator who has in his possession weapons</p>
<p> of mass destruction or not. And his behaviour and the behaviour of</p>
<p> his regime has left the rest of the world, particularly the Americans</p>
<p> and the British who are deploying the forces, with no alternative.</p>
<p> And that's why it's appropriate that Australia give her</p>
<p> support.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[Inaudible] Andrew Peacock?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes, yes, I saw him.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Did he brief you on the.....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, I saw him in another circumstance and I will be seeing him in</p>
<p> Sydney on Monday morning.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>He didn't brief you at all about what was the upcoming strike?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I was being briefed about it from other sources.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, when did Australia have access to Mr Butler's report</p>
<p> and when did you ...?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I read it this morning and my advisers had access to it earlier,</p>
<p> precisely when I can't tell you, but earlier. Thank you.</p>
<p> [ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
