<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5775</transcript-id>
    <title>THE INAUGURAL EDMUND BARTON LECTURE - THE STRENGTH OF LIBERALISM</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/03/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005775.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGOED AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
PRIME MAINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA ' FRIDAY, 19 MARCH 1-982<br />
THE INAUGURAL EDMUND BARTON LECTURE:<br />
THE STRENGTH OF LIBERALISM<br />
I am honoured to have been asked to deliver the first Edmund<br />
Barton Memorial Lecture. I congratulate the Liberal Club<br />
of the University of Sydney for establishing the lecture.<br />
Edmund Barton deserves to be remembered, not only as Australia's<br />
first Prime Minister, but as one of the founding fathers of<br />
the Australian nation. In establishing this lecture the<br />
Sydney University Liberal Club is drawing attention to one<br />
of the greatest achievements of the Liberal movement in<br />
Australia the Federation of the six colonies into one<br />
vital and dynamic nation.<br />
Barton was one of that select group of outstanding men who<br />
had the vision, the character, and the persistence to bring<br />
this nation of ours into existence: to draw up a<br />
constitution which would make possible the coming together of<br />
states, and the skill to put in place the first functioning<br />
Commonwealth Government. It was Barton the acknowledged<br />
leader of the Federal movement who made the famous declaration:<br />
" For the first time in the world's history, there will be a nation<br />
for a continent and a continent for a nation"<br />
It was Barton's Government which established the machinery of<br />
the Commonwealth of Australia itself. It is a measure of<br />
Barton's quality that he had such regard from the outstanding<br />
men in the Federal movement that he was regarded as the<br />
logical and obvious man to first lead the new nation.<br />
A modern Australian Prime Minister cannot but regard with awe<br />
a man who could lead a Cabinet * which contained six past or<br />
present state premiers William Lyne of New South Wales,<br />
Sir George Thurner of~ Victoria, Charles Kingston of So. uth<br />
Australia, Neil Lewis of Tasmaniaf Sir John Forrest of Western<br />
Australia and Sir James Dickson of Queensland, and what<br />
is more, encouraged them to agree to work together to<br />
build up a Federal Government.<br />
Barton was a man who believed in rational and sound argument<br />
rather than the emotive displays of the platform orator.<br />
As a leader of the Federal movement, Bar ton's--techniques<br />
are described by his biographer as " quiet organ isation,<br />
persuasion~ and argument". These techniques were effective c 2) </p>
<p>-2-<br />
in realising the vision which moved Barton through the great<br />
constitutional conventions. Barton's was a quiet passion, but<br />
a passion it was nevertheless. As he said during a speech in<br />
the New South Wales House of Assembly in 1891: " There is<br />
one great thing which ranks above any others in my political<br />
life, and will activate me until it is accomplished, and this<br />
is the question of the union of the Australian colonies" 1<br />
Barton's Liberal ambitions are reflected in the program<br />
his Government presented to the first Parliament. It included:<br />
federal old-age pensions;<br />
a Commonwealth revenue tariff;<br />
protection for-Australian industry;<br />
a federal conciliation and arbitration law;<br />
a transcontinental railway;<br />
manhood and womanhood suffrage;<br />
establishment of the High Court; and<br />
the Commuonwealth Public Service.<br />
With the exception of legislation for the White Australia Policy<br />
which has now passed into history, we see in the legislative<br />
program of Barton's government the ideals of a strong,<br />
independent, developing Australia in which there was a<br />
genuine concern for those in need. And the same ideals, have<br />
continued to-motivate Liberal governments to the present time.<br />
Some of the Barton government's legislative objectives took<br />
several years to achieve but the lasting triumph of that<br />
first Parliament was the building of the federal machinery<br />
which had been the objective of the visionary movement for<br />
a single Australian nation.<br />
In 1903 Barton left the Prime Ministership to become a member<br />
of the first bench of the High Court. It is a further<br />
illustration of Bartonds stature that before resigning he offered<br />
the Chief Justiceship to Sir Samuel Griffith, who accepted.<br />
It is my belief that the Liberal movement, of which Barton<br />
and Deakin, Australia's first two Prime Ministers, were<br />
then the leaders has been the great constructive political<br />
movement in Australia's history.<br />
Not only was it responsible for the birth of Australia as a<br />
nation, but it has been responsible for establishing our<br />
institutions of government the Federal Parliament, the High<br />
Court, and the Commonwealth Public Service, and for most of<br />
the great achieveme-n ts which Australian governments have set<br />
in place: ./ 3 </p>
<p>-3<br />
the arbitration system<br />
the old age and invalid pension . schemes<br />
child endowment and family allowances<br />
health insurance<br />
the Grants Commission and the financial agreement.<br />
with the States<br />
restrict~ ive practices legislation<br />
But the claim of the Liberal movement in Australia to be the<br />
great constructive political force does not rest only, or<br />
even primarily, on these achievements impressive though<br />
they are. The greatest contribution of the Liberal<br />
movement to -the building of modern Australia has been its<br />
ability to define and keep to a role for government which<br />
permits the Australian people to express in action their<br />
values and their abilities.<br />
Liberalism has recognised what the Socialist Labor Party<br />
has never recognised that Australia can be great, can be<br />
strong, prosperous and humane only if the capacities<br />
of the Australian people are used to the full. That does<br />
not mean policies which lead to an inexorably rising tax<br />
burden, constantly expanding bureaucracy, a growing<br />
centralisation of power in Canberra, an ever heavier<br />
and more costly burden of regulation the hall marks of<br />
Labor's approach to the solution of any and every problem.<br />
It does not mean the suspicion and envy directed towards<br />
every expression of enterprise, achievement, and excellence<br />
so characteristic of Labor's socialists whose ideal is a<br />
nation where' equality means conformity and the Labor Party<br />
and the trade unions reign over all.<br />
Liberals, by contrast, have pursued policies designed to<br />
let Australians as consumers express themselves through<br />
free choices in the market place, streamline and make<br />
more efficient the federal bureaucracy, encourage the<br />
development, capacities and efficiency of the States,<br />
reduce, wherever clear benefits are to be gained, the<br />
burden of regulation, simplify and lighten the burden of<br />
taxes, protect the public interest against the power of<br />
sectional interestg, protect the rights of individuals against<br />
both governments and powerful private interests.<br />
Each of these policies has had as its aim the unleashing.<br />
and mobilisinig of the talents and abilities of the Australian<br />
people themselves, in the sure knowledge that this is the<br />
one way in which Australia can provide a decent life for<br />
all its people, maintain its independence and be strong enough<br />
to make a constructive conLribution to the massive problems<br />
of poverty, disease and oppression which exist in other countries. ./ 4 </p>
<p>-4<br />
The constructive achievements of Liberalism grow out of<br />
a vision of what this country can be, and the belief that<br />
it is only through Liberal policies that this vision can be<br />
realised. Australians now find themselves, in a world in<br />
which the strength that Liberalism can bring to a country<br />
is more needed than ever. The world situation is<br />
troubling on at least two counts. In the first place,<br />
there is the relentless, militarism and opportunism<br />
of the Soviet Union. The Soviet push concerns not only<br />
the West but Third World states in and outside the Commonwealth,<br />
and now other communist countries in Eastern Europe and China.<br />
In Poland, and in the Soviet Union itself, the reasons for<br />
Russia's reliance on force and coercion is apparent. Russia's<br />
rulers are unwilling to accommodate change. Their economic<br />
policies are impoverishing the communist nations precisely<br />
because they crush that enterprise and initiative which the<br />
institutions of the West encourage and on which Western<br />
prosperity is built. Out of this impoverishment arise the<br />
forces for change, demanding greater freedom. Poland,<br />
before martial law, showed that evolution towards greater<br />
freedom could occur in communist states.<br />
But Russia's rulers are far too rigid to allow such evolution<br />
to take place. In their inability to bend, they run the<br />
risk of breaking when the winds of change blow strongeras<br />
they surely will.<br />
The second aspect of the international situation which gi ' ves<br />
rise to concern is the world recession. Between 1963 and<br />
1970, while the volume of world output grew at an average<br />
rate of the volume of world exports grew by 8.6%<br />
per annum. But during the 1970s, the growth of world output<br />
and exports both significantly slowed and as a result<br />
unemployment in many countries started to rise.<br />
Even before the first oil price increase in 1973, inflation<br />
had become more or less endemic in most industrialised<br />
countries. Excessive growth of government spending and<br />
inappropriate use of deficit financing played a major part<br />
in this. The oil price increases compounded these problems,<br />
making growing unemployment and growing inflation the order<br />
of the day. Even then, most countries did not recognise what<br />
was needed in terms of restraint of government spending, in.<br />
terms of firmness of monetary policy and in terms of wage<br />
restraint. Although there are now signs in a number of countries of a<br />
determination to pursue more economically realistic policies,<br />
natural ecoromric processes have run-atheir course. In Europe<br />
and North Amterica, economic growth has virtually come to<br />
a standstill. in the last two years and unemployment is<br />
high, and rising. In France unemployment is 8 in the<br />
USA it is in the United 1lingdom it is 11.7%. Because<br />
of the interdependence, betwecn our trading countries Australia<br />
cannot help but be affected by these trends. Nevertheless<br />
Australia is able to regard the future with a confidence<br />
not possible in some oter countries because we are now moving<br />
into the seventh year of a period in which constructive liberalism<br />
has once again guided national policy. </p>
<p>This inaugural Edmund Barton lecture provides an opportunity<br />
to set out the ideals for Australia which motivate Liberalism<br />
today to record the practical expression of those ideals in<br />
concrete policies, and to sketch out some of the implications<br />
of those ideals for the future.<br />
1. The first ideal is one I have already mentioned, but<br />
which I refer to again here, because it is at the very<br />
heart of Liberalism in this country: a belief in Australia,<br />
in Australians and in what the Australian people &amp; an<br />
achieve when government permits them to strive after<br />
. the things they value, rather than trying to impose<br />
some political ideology onto them.<br />
It is impossible to think of a field in which Australians<br />
have not recorded outstanding achievement, but there is one<br />
field where achievement underpins opportunities in most<br />
others the field of economic life. Government can and should<br />
encourage and. provide incentives but excessively big government<br />
can cause damage where it means to help.<br />
our policy of' rei ning in government has had pro foundly positive:<br />
objectives to * make room for the private initiatives so vital<br />
to increase Economic growth, job opportunities, and real<br />
incomes. one fundamental lesson can be drawn from the<br />
experience of the last six years. We have shown that economic<br />
growth can arid does take place when government expenditure<br />
is reined in. More than that, economic growth in modern<br />
circumstances requires restraint in government spending.<br />
Until we argued this case in 1975 the Labor Party had<br />
deceived itself, and attempted to deceive the Australian<br />
people that it was government spending that stimulated<br />
economic actiLvity.-/ 6 </p>
<p>-6<br />
In 1975, we set out to show the fallacy, the two fallacies,<br />
in Labor's vi. ew of the worla. What had been forgotten, and<br />
is still forgotten today by Labor, is that higher Government<br />
spending can only come about in two ways; by higher taxes,<br />
or be deficits and printing money.<br />
The first leads to higher . wage demands to compensate : for<br />
the higher taxes, stifles initiative and weakens the incentives<br />
so essential to private enterprise and economic growth.<br />
The second also leads to inflation and the two combined, taxes<br />
and inflation, destroy profits, capital and jobs.<br />
In doing so, such policies actually destroy growth, reduce real<br />
incomes, and impoverish-the country. That was their effect<br />
between 1972-75 and that would be their effect if ever that<br />
philosophy were to guide government in the future.<br />
In the last three years Australia has swum against the tide<br />
of the world recession. Our economy has grown, real incomes<br />
have grown and almost 400,000 new jobs were createa in the<br />
three years to the December quarter, almost 90% of them in the<br />
private sector.<br />
This has taken place at a time when a tighter rein has been<br />
kept on cjovernment spending in Australia than in probably<br />
any other industrial country.<br />
over the last six years Federal Government spending in AustraliLa<br />
has grown in real terms by about 1.5% per annum, a rate<br />
much less than growth in the economy as a whole. Over the same<br />
time the economy has grown by about 2.5% We have shown the<br />
key requirement for growth is not government pump printing, but<br />
the creation of conditions in which business has the confidence<br />
to invest, arnd in which individuals have the confidence to<br />
spend. Australia faces the world recession with an economy which i s<br />
far stronger than in 1975, in which growth is soundly based,<br />
in which inflationary pressures are less, in which exploration<br />
and development is pushing ahead at historically high levels,<br />
aFnd in which the huge domestic deficit left by Labor has at last<br />
been eliminated.<br />
It is of the greatest importance for Australia that these gains<br />
should be maintained and strengthened. That we should redouble<br />
our determination to live within our means as a nation, and<br />
reject the fantasy that letting spending run out once more will<br />
stimulate the economy.<br />
In the last si. x years a massive renovation in the economy ha~ s<br />
taken place, and the cracks in the foundations repairedl. Sound<br />
Iovernment has made it possible by unleasing the abilities and<br />
enterprise of the Australian peopl. e themselves. / 7 </p>
<p>7<br />
2. A second ideal which motivates Liberals is a belief in<br />
excellence.<br />
We believe it is in the interests of everyone if individuals<br />
are encouraged to achieve to their utmost according to their<br />
abilities.<br />
Many of our policies have expressed this ideal. In fact we<br />
hav. e given such high priority to the pursuit of excellence that<br />
there are a number of areas where we have actually increased<br />
spending, within the context of our overall policy of restraint.,<br />
to achieve this goal.<br />
Excellence has had priority and we have transferred resources<br />
to where excellence can be encouraged. The Government has<br />
fully backed the great revival in Australian films. In sport,<br />
we established and have funded the Australian Institute of Sport.<br />
In medical research, NHMRC grants have increased from $ 14 million<br />
to $ 26 million in the last two years. We have just announced<br />
grants for centres of excellence in Australian universities.<br />
Beyond this focussed support for excellence, in the field of<br />
tertiary education more broadly, we have held a tight rein on<br />
spending. Believing that after the rapid expansion of the<br />
sixties and early seventies, a period of consolidation and<br />
internal re-adjustment is warranted.<br />
Here our priorities also show in the pattern of spending.<br />
We have emphasised the expansion of opportunities for young<br />
Australians to acquire the technical and other skills they<br />
need to take full advantage of the resurgence of enterprise<br />
and development our policies have encouraged. Since 1975,<br />
Commonwealth spending on technical and further education and<br />
on training schemes has increased by 83.2% in real terms.<br />
3. A third belief which underlies the policies of modern<br />
Liberalism and which has found expression in many ways is the<br />
belief that the cultural and ethnic diversity of Australia-can<br />
be a souirce of great strength and creativity.<br />
This ideal has led us to try to change attitudes and perceptions<br />
of Australia born ill the old days of A~ nglo Saxon dominance,<br />
and to put in their place the ideal of a multicultural Austral~ ia.<br />
Recognising the value of diversity is one of the main supports<br />
of the Liberal belief in freedom and is in no way incompatible<br />
with a common commitment to Australia on behalf of all Australians,<br />
whatever their country of origin.<br />
The ideal of the multicultural society has been expressed in<br />
many ways in our policies. I mention here thc range of policies<br />
implemented under the Galbally Report on migrant serviceswhh<br />
we commissioned the establishmeiit of the Institute of Mlulticu] Aural Affair<br />
./ 8 </p>
<p>8-<br />
which is helping people to understand the value of cultural<br />
and ethnic diversity in Australian life, the establishment<br />
of multicultural television, immigration from a<br />
wider range of countries, including Asian countries;. the<br />
National Aboriginal Conference and the Aboriginal Development<br />
Commission, which are doing so much to promote the interest of<br />
the Aboriginal members o~ f our community and self-management by<br />
Aboriginals of their affairs.<br />
I believe the scope of our policies in this area is wi ' thout<br />
parallel in the world and Australia is undoubtedly deriving<br />
great strength from the rich cultural resources now to be<br />
found among the Australian people.<br />
4. A fourth ideal which has motivated this Government is a<br />
strong and safe Australia.<br />
Strength and. safety are to a significant extent, of course,<br />
functions of' defence and foreign policy. Our commitment to<br />
the Western alliance, and to the modernisation and build-up<br />
of our independent military forces is well known. We are<br />
now in the middle of a defence re-equipment program costing<br />
more than $ 5 billion. our priority here is shown by the fact<br />
that defence! is one of the very few areas of the Budget that<br />
is increasing substantially each year.<br />
Beyond defence forces and alliances, our security as a nation<br />
depends to a great extent on our unity at home and our ability<br />
to arrive at a common assessment of international events.<br />
It is not necessary for a government and an opposition to<br />
agree on everything for there to be a substantial bi-partisanship<br />
in foreign and defence policy.<br />
I believe it is a matter of genuine national concern that the<br />
Opposition alone among major Western socialist parties has<br />
chosen to denigrate peace-keeping efforts'in the Middle East<br />
( and to call Mr Begin the greatest threat to world peace).-<br />
That it derides the Commonwealth, which represents a quarter<br />
of the world's people, and attacks aspects of our relations withthe<br />
United States.<br />
The influence of the Socialist Left with its P. L. O. sympathies<br />
on Labor foreign and defence policies is clear and damaging,<br />
and has produced a divergence between the parties which is<br />
unnecessary and troubling.<br />
Our commitment to a safe and secure Australia is linked<br />
to a fifth ideal which has motivated the policies of this<br />
Government. The ideal of an Australia-which can do something<br />
positive to help in relieving the terrible conditions of poverty,<br />
disease and oppression wh~ ich exists for hundreds of millions of<br />
the worl~ d's people. / 9 </p>
<p>9-<br />
In the last six years Australia has been , a leader among<br />
industrialised countries in getting a fairer deal for developing<br />
countries in world markets. It was Australia that helped break<br />
the dead lock on the common fund. Through the Commonwealth<br />
of Nations, Australia has been a leading source of initiatives<br />
including the investigations into protection and into North-South<br />
negotiating processes.<br />
The historic Melbourne declaration camne at a strategic moment<br />
last year before the Cancun Conference.<br />
Australia has also become known as one of the leading opponents*<br />
of racism, in South Africa and elsewhere. At home the Government<br />
has bean a consistent and strong supporter of Aboriginal<br />
land rights and of Aboriginal self -mangement. At home and<br />
abroad every action of this Government has been aimed at<br />
strengthening human rights and combatting racism. A Minister<br />
who sought to qualify the Government's stand on these matters<br />
was immediately dismissed.<br />
That our constant pursuit of these ideals has had a great<br />
effect on the understanding of Australia overseas was evident.<br />
in comments made at the Commonwealth Heads of Government<br />
meeting in Melbourne.<br />
I will quote only one of these, the comment of President<br />
Kenneth Kaunda of Zambia: " Before this Government", said<br />
President Eaunda,<br />
" I personnally did not know what Australia was except,<br />
as a country where there was indifference to suffering<br />
people of th " e rest of the world. I am being very frank,<br />
you l. ave brought us to an Australia that we never knew<br />
of dEcent human beings an Australia with which we are<br />
very proud to be associated".<br />
Australia's capacity to help people in other countries as well<br />
as at home is very much related to our economic strength. The<br />
solution to proverty is not higher taxes and bigger bureaucracy,<br />
it is economic growth and a proper concentration of help on those<br />
in need.-<br />
6. This brings me to a sixth ideal -reflected in the priori-ties<br />
of modern Liberalism the ' ideal of an Australia where<br />
economic strength enables ever improving Ipro vision for the<br />
disadvantaged and those in needi.<br />
As Liberali[ sm in Australia established the system of federal old<br />
age and invalid pensions, modern Liberalism remains committed to<br />
a strong and effective system of social security. </p>
<p>Our priorities are indicated by the fact that social security<br />
and welfare spending is the largest single item in our Budget,<br />
and amounts 1to $ 11.4 billion.<br />
Despite economic conditions and despite the great increase in<br />
social security and welfare spending in the early seve ' nties<br />
we have actually increased the total real level of spending in<br />
this area ( even excluding family allowances and unemployment<br />
benefits) while concentrating assistance more on those in need.<br />
The replacement of the tax deduction for dependent children<br />
by the family assistance scheme was of direct benefit to<br />
300,000 low income families and 800,000 children.<br />
The income testing of the increase in the pension for those<br />
over 70 is directly helpful in securing the concentration on<br />
resources of those in need.<br />
We have given particular priority to helping the handicapped<br />
and disabled and in the last six years assistance has increased<br />
34% in real -terms.<br />
The principle of concentrating assistance on those in real need<br />
is also expressed in the health insurance scheme, which provides<br />
for completely free health care for three million Australians,<br />
while giving incentives to those on higher incomes to insure<br />
for themselves.<br />
Australia has one of the most comprehensive income support<br />
systems in the world. Practically everyone, other than those<br />
who are able, buE choo'se not, to work are guaranteed an income.<br />
This system has always been supported by Liberal governments and<br />
always will be. Its maintenance and imiprovement has been, and<br />
remains, one of the top priorities of miodern Australian Liberalism.<br />
7. Liberal programs have expressed another ideal which is now<br />
added to the list: The ideal of'an Australia which is<br />
governed in the interests . of all,* in the public interest.,<br />
and not on behalf of special-interests.<br />
The pressure on government by special interests for privileges<br />
is unceasing. A government which believes in ever more<br />
regulation cr ever higher spending is particularly vulnerable<br />
to such pressures. By conceding a privilege in the form of<br />
restrictive legislation or a new concession, such a government<br />
not only satisfies its philosophy but gains a client. In the<br />
end the public interest is submerged as spending gets out of<br />
control and restrictive regulations multiply inefficiency.<br />
Most interests argue, and believe, that they are acting in the<br />
public interest, but the truth is they are often acting in their<br />
own. / 11 </p>
<p>11<br />
While we have been uncommonly successful in holding spending ill<br />
check, these pressures remain and resisting them has I belive,<br />
been one of the real achievenents of the Government.*<br />
I believe we have had real success in spreading a greater<br />
sense of realism in the community about what is possible and<br />
desirable. A government which does not support and strengthen this sense<br />
of -realism not only imperils its own survival but the health<br />
and well-bein: g of the country it tries to govern.<br />
Labor is of course, particularly vulnerable here, not only<br />
because demands for more money and restrictive regulation are<br />
music to its ears, but because it is actually the political<br />
agent for one of the most powerful interests in the country,<br />
the trade union movement.<br />
8. This brings me to another of the ideas we have sought to<br />
realise in government the ideal of a society in which<br />
there is a balance in the power of the large private<br />
institutions of business and trade unions, in which neither<br />
is strong enough to dominate, and in which both are checked<br />
by the power of government, the rights and freedoms of<br />
individuals, and their own good sense and co-operative attitudes.<br />
Up to 1975 Australia saw a great increase in the power of trade<br />
unions in our society.<br />
Under Labor, Government became a partisan on behalf of the<br />
trade union movement, supporting massive wage increases and<br />
the obstruct-ion of business profits, and granting new legal<br />
privileges t~ o the union movement.<br />
The Government believes that the excessive power of unions<br />
relative to other interest groups in Australia was one of the<br />
deep-seated sources of cost push inflation in Australia during<br />
the 1970 Unions were encouraged to seek, and had the power7<br />
to obtain wage increases far above those the economy could<br />
afford. Righting the balance is a complex task because power has many<br />
facets and sources. The ideal of achieving a better balance<br />
has been expressed in many policies. Some have sought to<br />
increase the relative Power of the arbitral authorities and the<br />
courts, Some to increase the ability of union members to choose<br />
leaders who will express more accurately the views of the rank<br />
and file, s; omc to diminish the ability of unions to coerce<br />
individua. members, non-members and third parties to disputes,<br />
! some to incrcease the relative powers of employers in disputes,<br />
and some to expand the relative powers of government in disputes. </p>
<p>12<br />
The list of measures aiming at these objectives includes the<br />
Industrial Relations Bureau to better sec~ re the enforcement<br />
of aw ards and to act as an ombudsman, secret postal ballots<br />
in union elections conducted by the electoral office, the<br />
concept of conscientious objection to union membership, the<br />
C. E. E. P. Act.<br />
We are presently proposing measures to give employers the<br />
right to stand down employees who cannot be usefully employed<br />
due to industrial action, encourage-the formation of enterprise<br />
and industry unions, and to assist voluntary unionism.<br />
We are also addressing a number of industrial relations issuesin<br />
co-operation with the States, including the options to<br />
facilitate handling of demarcation disputes and the development<br />
of a complementary industrial relations system.,<br />
It is, of co~ urse, entirely predictable that Labor as a special<br />
interest party has undertaken to repeal much of our legislation,<br />
and remove t~ he checks and balances we are building into the*<br />
system in the public interest.<br />
A future Labor Government would mean a massive turning back of<br />
the clock and the shelving of the ideal of re-asserting a<br />
proper balance between the large institutions of Australian<br />
society. In the Liberal view it is only under such conditions of<br />
balance that we will see conflict more often replaced with a<br />
spirit of compromise and conciliation. Such a willingness<br />
to compromise and** co-operate is necessary if, for example,<br />
there are to be realistic prospects of extending collective<br />
bargaining in Australia.<br />
9. Strengthening -the rights of individuals against large<br />
organisations whether business, union or government -has<br />
long been a Liberal ideal.<br />
Apart from the measures in the trade union field I have mentioned,~<br />
we have taken a number of historic measures designed~ to protect<br />
individual rights.-<br />
We set up the Comnionwealth Ombudsman and the Administrative<br />
Appeal Trih-unal. We established last year the Human Rights<br />
Commission which will help promote the observance of human<br />
rights and our Freedom of Information Legislation will be<br />
the first to come into place nationally in a Westminster system.<br />
Our belief in ensuring that right-s and freedom are protected<br />
and power is decentralised has particular bearing on our ideals<br />
in relation to the structure of government itself.<br />
Our ideal ' s clovernment which is strong, efficient, economical<br />
and effective, but not centralised in Canberra; not bureaucratic<br />
or dorainee:-ing. ./ 14 </p>
<p>13<br />
I mention two of the major ways in which we have given practical<br />
expression to this ideal for government iri the last six years.<br />
one is by returning to the states significant independent powers<br />
in financial matters, and in the control of offshore lands.<br />
Between 1975-76 and 1981~-82 the proportion of untied Commonwealth<br />
payments to the States has risen from 51% to over 65%, and the<br />
proportion of total Commonwealth Budget outlays accounted for<br />
by-untied payments to the States has also risen.<br />
The other has been through the most extensive ministerial review<br />
of the functions of the Commonwealth Government in the history,<br />
of Australia. The Review of Commonwealth Functions.<br />
As a result the number of Commonwealth employees under staff<br />
ceilings is now actually smaller than it was six years ago,<br />
and many activities previously undertaken by Government are<br />
now contracted out to private enterprise.<br />
It is characteristic of Liberalism that it shoul * d always be<br />
prepared to review the achievements of the past and to adjust<br />
them to modern requirements.<br />
It is evident from what I have said that Liberals in Australia<br />
have aspirat~ ions for the country which are by no means fully<br />
realised, but which are better and better realised as Liberal<br />
programs of reform are developed and implemented.<br />
The historic commi tment of the Liberal movement in Australia<br />
to moderate and evolutionary reform has been an essential<br />
element in putting together its record of constructive achievement.<br />
The commitment of Edmund Barton to high ideals realised by<br />
" iquiet organistion, persuasion and argument" epitomises the<br />
Liberal approach to reform.<br />
It is a realistic approach which builds on the achivement of the<br />
past, while striving towards ideals yet unrealised.<br />
It is appropriate in this inaugural Barton lecture to make a<br />
few comments on reforms of the Constitution itself.<br />
Liberal Governments have a good record of constitutional * refcrm,<br />
Of the 17 constitutional amendments put before the people by<br />
Liberal giovernments since Federation, seven have been successful,<br />
and the Government I lead has introduced more successful amendments<br />
to the Constitution than any Government in Australia's<br />
history. I cannot refrai. n from saying that Labor's record has been<br />
remarkably poor. Of 19 amendments placed before the people,<br />
by Labor, only one has succeeded. There is a reason for this<br />
contrast. / 13 </p>
<p>b 14<br />
Successful constitutional reform requires that the proposed<br />
amendments express, or are not obnoxious to, the values of the<br />
Australian pe! ople. The Australian people value the regime<br />
of decentralised Federal Government bequeathed to us by<br />
Barton and his colleagues, and have rejected again and again<br />
Labor's proposals to concentrate more power in Canberra's hands.<br />
Effective constitutional change can of course come about by<br />
judicial interpretation and by new financial arrangements<br />
between Commonwealth and'States.<br />
Through deliberate amendment and by other techniques the<br />
Australian Constitution has actually evolved so that it<br />
differs in significant ways from the original intent of<br />
the founders.. In effect, it is not the saime instrument now<br />
as it was in 1900 because of the development that has taken<br />
place. It iS proper that our Constitution should evolve<br />
and that it should continue to evolve. It is unrealistic<br />
to think it can change in any other way.<br />
S There is no lorospect of a new constitution by 1988 as some<br />
are suggesting. Nor is a totally new constitution in any<br />
way required. The effort to achieve such an objective is<br />
indeed one of the most divisive proposals that can be<br />
contemplated in Australia. There are many real and pressing<br />
problems and choices which Australia faces in the next few<br />
years a ne-w constitution is not among them. It is a matter<br />
which can only distract the nation's attention from issues of<br />
substance. Alfred Deakin wrote of the immense di f ficulties in<br />
producing the origjinal Constitution:<br />
" Regarded as a whole, it is safe to say that if ever<br />
anything ought to be styled providential it is the<br />
extraordinary** combination of circumstances, per sons<br />
and their-most intricate interrelations of which the<br />
Commonwe~ dth is about to become the crown. To say it<br />
was fated to be is to say nothing to the purpo~ ie. Any<br />
one of a thousand minor incidents might have deferred<br />
it for years or generations<br />
" To thcse who watched its inner workings, followed its<br />
fortunEts as if their own, and lived the life of devotion<br />
to it day by day, its actual accomplishment must always<br />
appear to have been secured by a series of miracles"<br />
( Federal Story, p. 173)<br />
In its day, the federal movement dominated Australian politics;.<br />
We are fortunate that the founding fathers were so skilled<br />
in their task that they achieved the intricate balance of<br />
circumstance! s which our Constitution contains, and which<br />
has been so instrumental in making Australia a stable,<br />
prosperous and progressive nation. There are too many<br />
other important issues for constitutional change to loom<br />
so large again. A new constitution is hot a. priority nor<br />
a goal for Liberalism in Australia. Our goal is a continuance<br />
of the process of evolutionary constitutional reform where<br />
change is needed. </p>
<p>15<br />
12. This brings me to the last of ideals we have sought to put<br />
into practice in the last six years the ideal of an<br />
Australia which has the foresight to conserve its heritage<br />
and to hand on what is of value to future generations.<br />
In referring to conservation we automatically think of the<br />
natural environment and our historic heritage. Our record<br />
in conserving Australia's -magnificent natural heritage takes<br />
second place to no Australian government, federal or State<br />
at any time. Fraser Island, Kakadu National Park, the Great<br />
Barrier Reef Marine Park, anti-whaling legislation and many<br />
other initiatives all stand as symbols of a practical ideal<br />
realised, despite opposition in some instances from selfish<br />
and powerful private interests.<br />
But there is more to our historic heritage than our natural<br />
environment, or historic artifacts and buildings. Our most<br />
valuable inheritance from the past, and the most valuable<br />
bequest we can make to the future is the heritage of humane<br />
values and ideals, passed on to us by men such as Barton and<br />
Deakin, and passe ' d down through their families by all those<br />
who came to Australia seeking freedom, opportunities, and<br />
self-respect for themselves and their families.<br />
Those values are our real treasure. Tens of thousands of<br />
Australians have died to defend them, and if we were ever<br />
to lose them it would be because one generation failed to<br />
re-commit itself to them. We who practice our policies in<br />
the Liberal tradition believe that it is Liberalism whose<br />
ideals and understandings can best realise those values.<br />
Our political opponents believe otherwise. Because each<br />
Australian generation has re-dedicated itself to those<br />
fundamental values, and has passed on that vision of Australia,<br />
you have the right to decide who is right, and you also have<br />
the obligation to make a decision which will preserve for<br />
your children the same right. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
