<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>15605</transcript-id>
    <title>Doorstop Interview, Sydney</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/03/2007</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Subject:<br />
Visit to Japan, Indonesian plane crash, cyclone George</p>
<p>E&amp;OE...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>...I leave shortly to go to Japan. This is the 50th year since the signing of the commerce agreement in 1957 which laid the foundation for what has become a very valuable and enduring partnership between our two countries.  Japan is a great Pacific democracy. Japan remains Australia's best customer.  The people to people links between our two societies are very extensive and it's important that we nourish that relationship on a regular basis and the negotiations for a comprehensive free trade agreement will be starting at an official level very shortly.  There's a lot in the relationship for both countries and when one thinks of the history many years ago of relations between Australia and Japan it is a remarkable compliment to the willingness of both countries to put the past behind them whilst never forgetting what occurred in the past and we must never do that, but to look to the future and work together in partnership in our part of the region.  </p>
<p>Could I just also briefly mention two other matters. The first of those is that tragic though all of the circumstances surrounding the plane crash in Yogyakarta may be, it is moving on and a relief for the families involved that the victim identification process has been completed.  It will now be possible for bodies of the Australians who died to be returned home, the Government will assume responsibility and has assumed responsibility for those arrangements naturally. The wishes of family and other loved ones will be fully respected in relation to those arrangements and finally the cyclone in Western Australia which has caused so much devastation and sadly some loss of life, I've had a lengthy discussion with the Western Australian Premier, the automatic natural disaster arrangements are in place.  The Army has offered to assist if it is needed and I've told Mr Carpenter that any additional assistance reasonably required will be made available by the Commonwealth.  Fortunately the agencies of both the Commonwealth and the States work together very closely and very quickly when these emergencies arise and everything will be done at both a Commonwealth and at State level to ensure that assistance is properly made available. Any questions?</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>On the security declaration with Japan, there are some sensitivities from other countries. Do you understand their concerns?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes, but we have to look at our own interests in respect of countries we have relations with.  Reference is made to China, I don't think anybody in their wildest imagination would suggest that our relations with China aren't very good and very close, but our relations with Japan are very good and very close and bear in mind that Japan is a democracy who shares many things with us that are special. Because of that I don't expect there will be any enduring sensitivities on the part of China any more than there any enduring sensitivities on the part of China in respect of our close alliance with the United States.  We couldn't have a closer alliance with the United States. The phenomenon of the last 10 years is that whilst our relationship with the United States has got closer so has our relationship with China.  Well by extension I don't think there's any real problem in relation to Japan.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Will this agreement also include sharing of more intelligence and perhaps joint exercises?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well it could involve the sharing of intelligence. I think it's a bit early until it's been signed and Mr Abe and I have had discussions to start speculating about other things.  </p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>During the course of any free trade discussions Prime Minister will you bring up Japanese whaling, for instance.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I will be raising the whaling issue anyway.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>In terms of an FTA with Japan, how important is that. What kind of benefits would we see?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well it will be beneficial if we can get greater access for our exports and of course we have to give something in return.  The free trade agreement will involve quite lengthy negotiations; it's quite a difficult issue.  The point should be made that even without the free trade agreement Japan is our best customer, so we're seeking here to make a very good situation even better.   Thank you.</p>
<p>[ends]  </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
