<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8357</transcript-id>
    <title>OPPOSITION&#039;S CONSUMPTION TAX PACKAGE</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/11/1991</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008357.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>FOR MEDIA 25 NOVEMBER 1991<br />Dr Hewson's consumption tax package raises a fundamental<br />question: is Dr Hewson serious about microeconomic reform<br />and achieving the fundamental changes he claims are so vital<br />for the Australian economy? If so why has he made no<br />allowance for road user charges in his calculations and<br />policy design?</p>
<p><br />Dr Hewson's package attempts to paint a picture of a new,<br />dynamic Australia where business has been freed from<br />supposed constraints and operates in a revamped environment<br />that promotes a vastly enhanced level of efficiency.<br />In Table 4.1 on page 33 of the summary document, Dr Hewrson<br />enthusiastically embraces the estimated benefits from<br />microeconomic reform prepared by the Industry Commission<br />( IC) and others. Here, and elsewhere, much is made of the<br />benefits from reform of transport. Indeed Dr Hewson becomes<br />quite lyrical about the importance of an efficient transport<br />system to Australia.</p>
<p><br />" If Australia is to compete effectively on world<br />markets it must not only deal sensibly with the<br />" tyranny of distance" between us and our overseas<br />markets. It must also deal sensibly with our very own<br />domestic " tyranny of distance". ( Supplementary<br />Paper 8, p. 1)</p>
<p><br />Dr Hewson's commitment is also quite specific and detailed:<br />" The incoming Coalition Government, therefore, will<br />request the newly established National Road Transport<br />Commission to review a national system of road user<br />charges to apply following the implementation of our<br />tax reform package. The Commission would be guided by<br />the need for the system of road user charges to be<br />equitable, efficient and simple to administer. The<br />Commission would be free to recommend that charges take<br />any form or combination of forms.<br />3242 A<br />A494W</p>
<p>These changes to the arrangements for road funding will<br />ensure that all revenue raised by user charges will be<br />spent on road maintenance and construction. The<br />overall level of road user charges and road<br />expenditures will be the responsibility of the National<br />Road Transport Commission. Charges and taxes on road<br />users and the level of expenditure on roads will no<br />longer be subject to the vagaries of the political or<br />budget processes which have produced wild fluctuations<br />in rates of charge and levels of expenditure in past<br />years." ( Main document, pp. 82-3)<br />The package specifically recognises the revenue implications<br />of the introduction of road user charges:<br />" The funding of road expenditure by road user charges<br />has the potential to improve the budgetary position of<br />the Commonwealth and to this extent the fully funded<br />proposal contained in this package is very<br />conservative." ( Supplementary Paper 8,<br />In fact the revenue raised under the system proposed in the<br />report on road user charges by the InterState Commission<br />( ISC) would be about $ 4 billion.<br />But when it comes to reccgnising that the imposition of<br />these charges has implications for the price of fuel, Dr<br />Hewson's document is strangely silent. Page 82 of the main<br />document contains the inaccurate excuse:<br />" At the present time the Federal Government and the<br />States are in this process of negotiating a new<br />approach to road funding. These negotiations are<br />however hampered by the Commonwealth reliance on fuel<br />excises as a source of general revenue and by the<br />increased reliance of the States on fuel-related<br />franchise fees as a milch cow for general revenue.<br />At the time of developing this proposal the final<br />nature and design of the new arrangements is unknown.<br />The Coalition therefore is not now in a position to<br />assess the adequacy or otherwise of the new road user<br />charges that are expected to be implemented next year<br />or beyond." 3243</p>
<p>3.<br />In f act a great deal of work has been done and pb2LJ~ C,<br />released by the ISC ( two reports) and the Premiers'<br />Conference Over-arching Group on Land Transport ( CAG). On<br />the basis of this work the Commonwealth and the States have<br />concluded an agreement covering the introduction of road<br />user charges for heavy vehicles and legislation-gñ izinn<br />Affect-to thin gareemnt wan Intoud in he erZ QflU<br />NnvpImb2Z. The details of this agreement, going to<br />mechanisms for setting and collecting these charges and to<br />their likely magnitude, were annoinnnd in the rnm~ imnique<br />from the Jtuly Rpecial PeMiersI Cofrnn and quifloti ng<br />documpntation. The details run to a number of pages but a<br />key paragraph demonstrates that road user charges on fuel<br />would be absorbed into the existing excise and not levied as<br />an extra charge:<br />" Registration charges and the road use charge component<br />of Commonwealth excise on diesel are to be adjusted in<br />future by the National Road Transport Commission in<br />line with the amount of national road system costs<br />attributable to heavy vehicles. Accordingly, State<br />fuel franchise fees and the taxation component of<br />Commonwealth diesel excise are to be separately<br />identified and adjusted in future by separate<br />mechanisms." ( July communique,<br />Dr Hewson chose to ignore this wealth of material that could<br />have provided an entirely satisfactory basis for factoring<br />road user charges into his calculations.<br />Why? Could it be that the conclusions of such an analysiLs are<br />unpalatable and unacceptable to the National Party?<br />The impact on his calculations and claims are certainly<br />dramatic and far reaching. Let me illustrate.<br />The work by the ISC and the OAG, referred to earlier,<br />concludes that an element relating purely to distance<br />travelled is essential in any system of road user charges<br />and that the only effective and efficient way to achieve<br />this is through a charge on fuel. Their work suggested that<br />a charge of around 16c a litre would be required on both<br />diesel and petrol.<br />With such charges in place, Dr Hewson's maximum scope for<br />reduction of the then remaining petrol and diesel excises is<br />9.8c a litre. This would be the maximum fall in fuel prices<br />he could offer business users. Private motorists are<br />subject to the 15 per cent consumption tax, estimated at 7c<br />a litre in Dr Hewson's document, and, therefore, would see<br />falls of no more than 2-3c a litre.<br />32414</p>
<p>4.<br />The savings for the average family that Dr iHewson makes so<br />much of would be reduced from $ 11.40 for a 60 litre tank of<br />petrol to $ 1.20-1.80, a dramatically different story the<br />sort of savings that can be made in periods of petrol price<br />discounting. The savings in business costs flowing from reductions in<br />fuel prices that he refers to repeatedly throughout the<br />document would be cut by about two thirds.<br />Dr Hewson's CPI calculation would require significant<br />correction. The removal of 16c from the proposed reduction<br />of 25.8c in the excise on a litre of fuel cuts the 1.3<br />percentage point price level reduction from this source<br />( reported in Table 8.1 on page~ 134 of the main document) to<br />percentage points. Hence, on Dr Hewson's own figures,<br />the impact of the package on the CPI is not an increase of<br />4.7 per cent but an increase of 5.5 per cent, with obvious<br />implications for the adequacy of the so-called compensation<br />package. Will Dr Hewson fall at the first hurdle of microeconomic<br />reform because of the National Party veto?<br />Which do we take seriously, Or Hewson's vision for a more<br />efficient Australia based on a Government prepared to take<br />tough decisions or the calculations and assertions about the<br />impact of the package in Dr Hewson's " carefully prepared"<br />document? 3245</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
