<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5202</transcript-id>
    <title>SUMMARY OF &#039;PM&#039;</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/11/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005202.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER TUESDSAY, NOVEM4BER 20, 1979<br />
from the Press Office SUM4MARY OF<br />
Mr. Murdoch has made a shack takeover bid for the Herald and<br />
Weekly Times Group, which if successful would make Mr. Murdoch's<br />
company News Limited the most powerful media organisation in<br />
Australia. The Opposition has called for intervention by the<br />
Federal Government until a full enquiry is conducted into media<br />
ownership. -Jane Singleton reports from Sydney.<br />
Question: How much of Herald and Weekly Times does Mr. Murdoch<br />
already own?<br />
Singleton: It is very hard to give an exact figure but from ringing around<br />
the stock brokers this afternoon about 30% that is of a total<br />
$ 126 million bid.<br />
Question:<br />
What does he own already in terms of newspapers, radio and T. V.<br />
outlets and what will he gain from the Herald and Weekly Times?<br />
Singleton:<br />
Well of course he has got the Australian and in Sydney the Daily<br />
Telegraph arnd the Daily Mirror. There is the Truth and a number<br />
of Sunday papers. If he is successful he will add about a dozen<br />
metropolitan dailies and the big ones are the Herald and Sun* News<br />
Pictorial in Melbourne, the Courier Mail and the Telegraph in<br />
Brisbane, the Australian and the Daily News in Perth andthe<br />
Mecu in Hobart. He will get an amazing nine radio stations to<br />
add tohs existing four but it is in television he will have to<br />
do some rationalising. He is at present negotiating to sell his<br />
Channel 9, that's NWS in Adelaide and that leaves him with only<br />
Channel 10 in Sydney but according to the Secretary of the Australian<br />
Broadcasting Tribunal, Mr. Connelly, he may only-own two under the<br />
Broadcasting and Television Act. Now the Herald and Weekly Times<br />
brings him four so he would have to sell of f three of them and<br />
reports at the moment suggest he would keep Channel 7 in Melbourne<br />
and sell off the rest.<br />
Question:<br />
How has Herald and Weekly Times itself reacted?<br />
Singleton:<br />
Well very early today they instructed their shareholders not to<br />
sell, directly after the announcement was made on the floor of<br />
the Stock Exchangel in Melbourne.<br />
Question: And the Stock Exchange of course has reflected what they thought of<br />
the situation. </p>
<p>2<br />
Singleton:<br />
Yes they went up very quickly, Herald and Weekly Times shares went<br />
up to about $ 3.78 by lunchtime, they stabilised a bit lower by the<br />
end of trading today and of course News Limited went down a bit.<br />
Question: And Mr. Murdoch in fact told ( inaud.) New Limited has offered<br />
$ 4 a share for Herald and Weekly Times shares. Has Mr.. Murdoch<br />
himself commented at all?<br />
Singleton: Yes, he's said that it is a life time dream of his to control the<br />
Herald and Weekly Times but he does say that in some ways it was<br />
an unrealised dream, a subconscious dream. But he has said that<br />
he is confident of getting the 50 percent and that he has got<br />
enough money to complete the raid.<br />
Question:<br />
And typically perhaps of his character he walked unannounced to<br />
the Herald and Weekly Times building. this morning to tell them<br />
his plans to take them over. Any sign that the Herald and Weekly<br />
Times intend to fight back?<br />
Singleton:<br />
Yes-indeed. From reliable sources we have learnt that Herald and<br />
Weekly Times Directors plan to make a counter offer which may<br />
defeat Mr. Murdoch's bid very soundly.<br />
Question: And I suoocse it wouldn't be surprising if the Melbourne establishment<br />
took a degree of exception to a takeover to the Herald and Weekly<br />
Times? Singleton: They might indeed.<br />
To look at some of the implications of the takeover bid Peter<br />
Jefferson is speaking to Dr. Patricia Edgar, Senior Lecturer in<br />
the Media Centre at the School of Education, Latrobe University,<br />
who tomorrow launches her new book ' The Politics of the Press'.<br />
Interviewer:<br />
Well Dr. Edgar what is your reaction? Is is a healthy sign for<br />
Australia? Edgar:<br />
No I think it is quite staggering. I was stunned. I think it is<br />
most unhealthy prognosis. .3 </p>
<p>Interviewer: If it went through what would sort of power would Mr. Murdoch have?<br />
Edgar: Well if you look at the control which already exists with the<br />
Herald and Weekly Times, which is a monopoly in Perth, Brisbane,<br />
Hobart you add this to the control that Mr. Murdoch has already<br />
got through his papers and you have vested within one man enormous<br />
amount of potential power to manipulate the public through the<br />
press. Now of course day to day the paper comes out it' pretty<br />
much the same but when you get to elections, to political events,<br />
power broking, it becomes much more significant.<br />
Interviewer:<br />
Can one man manipulate the press like that? Given that he is in<br />
control of it can he really manipulate the press?<br />
Edgar: Well it's a matter of speculation but you look at what happened in<br />
South Australia and you look at the enormous change in public<br />
opinion and the fact that one government went out which wasn't<br />
expected . to and a lot of that has been credited to the role which<br />
Mr. Murdoch's paper played in South Australia.<br />
Interviewer:<br />
How would he use this power if he got it?<br />
Edgar: It is a potential power. Mr. Mur-doch has a reputation for being<br />
active as a newspaper man and he doesn't claim to be disinterested<br />
and so it's a question of that many newspapers in one country being<br />
in the control of one person who may wish to put his support in<br />
any direction, it doesn't matter which party it is.<br />
Interviewer:<br />
Would he try and make and break governments? * You've cited one case.<br />
But would he try and do it on a federal level?<br />
Edgar: Well he certainly has a reputation for doing that and that was<br />
( inaud.) the 75 election and again I repeat South Australia. But<br />
this would be the highest concentration of press ownership in any<br />
Western country.<br />
Interviewer:<br />
What do you think is really going on for Mr. Murdoch? What do you<br />
think he is really trying to do?-Is is a case of simply increasing<br />
his power Does he want more money? What's in it for him? What's<br />
the underlieing play in this whole deal? 4 </p>
<p>4<br />
Edgar: I couldn't possibly speculate on Mr. Mudc~ personal motives<br />
but it is certainly possible that there are other interested<br />
parties involved. There has been speculation that Mr. Holmes a<br />
Court is interested in the West Australian which is a Herald and<br />
Weekly Times paper. There is also speculation that he is interested<br />
in Channel 7 Perth and -so it may bae -that this whole thing is part<br />
of a much wider deal.<br />
Interviewer: Involving perhaps the Ansett takeover?<br />
Edgar: It could be. The whole scenario is yet to be played out. ( end)<br />
The Federal Opposition has called for an enquiry before the takeover<br />
goes through. Geoff Duncan spoke to Mr. Staley.<br />
Question: Mr. Staley how disturbed is the Government at this potential<br />
takeover? Mr. Staley:<br />
Well I'd emphasise that these matters are for the Broadcasting<br />
Tribunal and the law of this land provides that there are quite<br />
stringent controls of the ownership of radio and television in<br />
Australia. And these controls are administered by the Broadcasting<br />
Tribunal and they have been well known for a long time. And I must<br />
say I haven't heard any particular suggestions of any ( inaud.)<br />
coming from the opposition or from anyone about how they ought to<br />
be altered eith1-er now or in the future.-<br />
Question: Well of course as you know they are asking-for a freeze that<br />
there should be an enquiry to examine the whole operation at the<br />
moment. Mr. Staley:<br />
Yes. But I'd emphasise that neither when they were in government<br />
did they act in this respect nor subsequently have they developed<br />
any policy to suggest how the actual how the actual ownership and<br />
control provisions could be changed, bearing in mind the fact that<br />
Commonwealth Government is not by the Constitution given power over<br />
press matters. Now that means that we can't place controls, as<br />
I am advised on press ownership and of course that-has its good<br />
side, because it does mean that governments don't get into the<br />
business of censoring the press, and I think all Aust ' ralians regard<br />
that as a great thing in a democracy. And it seems to me that you<br />
don't alter the rules of the game when the ruckmen are in the air.<br />
Question: But in terms of philosophy would the Government concede that it is<br />
a bad thing to have too much concentration of media power? </p>
<p>Mr. Staley:<br />
Well we do. And what we've done of course over the years, over<br />
many years, is we've acted, and in recent decisions. We've acted<br />
so as to further diversify media ownership in Australia. And what<br />
I am saying is that there are vacuous calls being made now in areas<br />
where we do not have the constitutional power to act. And Mr.<br />
Murdoch, as I understand it, has made it quite plain that if his<br />
bid is successful, and goodness knows whether it will be or not,<br />
that if his bid is successful then he will live within those quite<br />
stringent controls as they relate to radio and television in<br />
Australia where we do have the power to act, have acted, and will<br />
continue to act, and of course, in particular cases, the Broadcasting<br />
Tribunal * will decide whether those quite stringent provisions are<br />
lived up to in practice.<br />
Interviewer:<br />
To get back to what you said earlier. Does that mean the Government<br />
is philosophically opposed to a move of this type?<br />
Mr. Staley:<br />
No. I am not going to argue that we're philosophically opposed.<br />
I'm not going to comment on things that are for private enterprise<br />
and the free market where we do not have the constitutional power<br />
to act. ' It seems to me to be quite foolish for me to develop some<br />
sort of position where we do not in fact have the power to act.<br />
Interviewer:<br />
How satisfied are you that the Tribunal itself has both the teeth<br />
and the fortitude to resist such a move.<br />
Mr. Staley:<br />
I believe -the Tribunal has shown in its decisions that it's a<br />
responsible body prepared to act in accordance with its powers<br />
when it's called upon to do so.<br />
Interviewer:<br />
But given that general Government opposition philosophically to the<br />
idea of the concentration of too much media power would you be<br />
surprised if the Tribunal did uphold the takeover?<br />
Mr. Staley:<br />
Well that is for the Tribunal to judge and I make it quite plain<br />
that I am not going to comment on run in an area which is absolutely<br />
and ultimately the responsibility of the Tribunal.<br />
Interviewer:<br />
Given that this an issue with major implications, do you think that<br />
the Government would be wise to institute some sort of' an enquiry<br />
as Senator Ryan has suggested?<br />
Mr. Staley:<br />
I have said already that I believe that this whole question is a </p>
<p>6<br />
very complex one. It's a very important one. I don't believe<br />
you take decisions on the run and I haven't heard frankly many<br />
constructive suggestions about how to handle it. I am prepared<br />
when we look at a major review of the Broadcasting Act, to<br />
consider whether it would be wise, at that stage, after proper<br />
and mature consideration to undertake some particular enquiry<br />
into-the ownership and control provisions.<br />
It was revealed in evidence today that 6 or 7 other witnesses<br />
apart from the key Crown witness, Mr. Nakos, had been promised<br />
indemnity to testify in the so-called Social Security fraud case.<br />
Detective Chief Inspector Thomas today was cross-examined on the<br />
relationship between. the Commonwealth Police and the Government<br />
over payment of a reward to Nakos. Christopher Sweeney was at<br />
the court for PM. The original police investigation into the<br />
fraud has involved two Government departments as well as the<br />
Commonwealth Police and from evidence produced in court today it<br />
is clear that there was considerable rivalry and distrust between<br />
them. Notes were taken of telephone calls down to the exact<br />
minute. Records were carefully filed of all conversations with<br />
other departments and at times there were investigations within<br />
investigations. The result was that subpoenaed documents, like<br />
those produced today, have disclosed details of how other enquirie's<br />
were going and in the process provided a wealth of damaging<br />
information for the Defence. The most politically important is a<br />
confidential minute used as the basis of the cross-examination of<br />
Thomas, the man who organised the investigation and led the arrests<br />
of over 180 people from the Greek community-in April last year.<br />
The document was from the headquarters of the Commonwealth Police<br />
to the N. S. W. Division and was intended as a-note on progress so<br />
far. It was written by Thomas, but scrawled on the top in the<br />
handwriting of the Assistant Commissioner were the words " Mr.<br />
Corrigan has again been in touch with the informant's solicitor<br />
why hasn't Sydney reported this yet please.' The significance<br />
of this lies in the position of Mr. Corrigan, First Secretary of<br />
the Department of Social Security. ' TIhe note indicates that iHr.<br />
Corrigan had been in discussion with the solicitor for the Chief<br />
Prosecution witness and self-confessed police informer, Nakos<br />
after November 3rd while Commonwealth Police were still discussing<br />
with the same solicitor, the question of a possible payment of up<br />
to $ 200,000. When asked today Thomas said that he's been not<br />
aware at the time that top civil servants had been in contact with<br />
the solicitor. The significance of the note lies in replies to<br />
questions last week by Senator Guilfoyle and her Director General, Mr.<br />
Lannigan whose involvement with the whole case was again raised<br />
prominently in court today. Marcus Einfeld took Thomas point by<br />
point over statements made in Parliament on the question of the<br />
involvement of the Department of Social Security. Asking whether<br />
he'd ever been told by Mr. Lannigan or Mr. Corrigan that their<br />
Department did not want to be part of negotiations over the reward<br />
to the police informer, Thomas said that he'd never been told thisnot<br />
in those words. He also said that he could not agree -with the<br />
assertion that the Department had wanted nothing to do with<br />
negotiations for the reward. During the cross-examination the<br />
-question of the roles of Minister of Social Security and her civil<br />
servants was obvious but unspoken. Lawyers and the Magistrate<br />
himself referred many times to what they called ' that other place'.'<br />
The Crown raised objections on a number of occasions on the grounds<br />
that the evidence in court might reflect on what was happening in<br />
Parliament. The whole issue of the reward payment has now become 7 </p>
<p>embroiled in just who was conducting negotiations at what time<br />
police, Mr. Corrigan or Mr. Lannigan. In answer to other questions<br />
though Thomas also disclosed today that six or seven other<br />
witnesses had now been promised an indemnity if they testified in<br />
the case. He said that these witnesses were now under police<br />
protection and I quote ' might well be in holiday resorts'. None of<br />
them has so far given evidence -but the disclosure caused a<br />
considerable stir following the revelation ten days ago that the<br />
chief witness, Mr. Nakos, was in fact a police informer who had<br />
received a pardon from the Governor-General.<br />
There were ugly scenes in Federal Parliament today during a censure<br />
motion against the Government over the Social Security fraud case.<br />
Members of the Opposition clashed heatedly with the former<br />
Attorney General Mr. Ellicott. Geoff Duncan reported.<br />
Allegations that a number of Queensland politicians are involved<br />
with known dealers in illicit drugs surfaced in the Queensland<br />
Parliament today. Mr. Casey said he had spoken to an agent ot<br />
the Federal Narcotics Bureau who had confirmed that a number of<br />
Government members were named in Bureau files as having connections<br />
with people in the drug smuggling world. Mr. Casey said that he<br />
had learnt that the Narcotics Bureau in Sydney had a taped record<br />
of an interview with a notorious inter-national drug runner which<br />
referred by name to a senior members of the Queensland Coalition<br />
Government. Peter Cave reported. The Opposition is demanding<br />
that Quee nsland set up its own Royal Commission into illicit drugs.<br />
In Sydney today the High Court finished hearing submissions in a<br />
major challenge of the Federal Government's 1976 Aboriginal Land<br />
Rights legislation. The action was brought by the Northern<br />
Territory Government which has asked the High Court to set aside<br />
ruling by Aborig inal Land Rights Commissioner, Mr. Justice Toohey,<br />
that he could hear a claim for the transfer of a lease over Utopia<br />
Station to freehold Aboriginal ownership. Kerry Wheel reported. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
