<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6755</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE, AUSTRALIAN BIDENTENNIAL AUTHORITY, 3 OCTOBER 1985</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/10/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006755.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
F. 1rior' ONI.' i<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE, AUSTRALIAN BICENTENNIAL AUTHORITY<br />
3 OCTOBER 1985<br />
JOURNALIST: Are we any closer to a new Chairman, Prime Minister?<br />
PM: Yes every day brings u-S closer to the new Chairman but<br />
we are very fortunate that in the mean Lime we have an admirable<br />
interim Chairman in John Utz. And not only I, and the Government,<br />
but I think the people of Australia are indebted to him for<br />
moving in in these circumstances. And we appreciate it very<br />
much indeed.<br />
JOURNALST: When will the new Chairman be announced, Sir?<br />
PM: I can't put a date on it. The important thing immediately<br />
is to continue the processes to find a new Chief Executive.<br />
And it is the objective of the Government and of the Authority<br />
to see that these two positions are filled as soon as possible.<br />
JOURNALIST: public accountability.<br />
PM: Well, you already have a sense of public accountability<br />
in the reqUirement of the Auithority t~ o have its accounts cleared<br />
by the Auditor-General and they have, in the past, been so cleared.<br />
In regard to the relationship between the Government and the<br />
Authority we, following discussions with John and the Board,<br />
will have a position where there will be a representative of<br />
the Government sitting in as observer and liaison person at<br />
meetings of the Board. There will be monthly reports coming<br />
to the Government from the Board on progress. And we will<br />
be getting quaterly statements of account from the Board. so,<br />
what we have to do, you see, and what we have succeeded in doing<br />
is to operate under the legislation that we inherited which<br />
separated the Board, the Authority, from the. Government and<br />
the Parliament. Now with~ booc sense discussions with the new<br />
Chairman and the Board, they have accepted that within those<br />
constraints, those legislative constraints that we have inherited,<br />
we will. in this way that I have indicated get the new form of<br />
relationshlip and accountability which I think is necessary.<br />
JOURNALIST: Will Mr Armstrong have to give any of his money<br />
back?<br />
PM: I at this stage only have an interim report from the Solicitor-<br />
General. Perhaps by the end of the day that will be put in<br />
final form. And it is not fair to either Dr Armstrong or anyone<br />
else to make any comment on that until I have had the opportunity<br />
of studying that final document from the Solicitor-General. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: On another issue<br />
PM: Just before we go to other issues, I am not going to..<br />
If there are any other questions on this issue, let's have them<br />
and then we will go to another one.<br />
JOURNALIST: Are you happy that all other aspects of the ABA<br />
are functioning well?<br />
PMt": Yes well look, in an Authority of this magnitude there<br />
will probably be some elements that could be in a better position.<br />
I think the Authority and the Board itself recognise that.<br />
The important thing to be said is this that a great deal of<br />
good and valuable work is being done. There are over 520 community<br />
committees established around Australia. And I have no doubt<br />
at all, that on the basis of the work that has been done, the<br />
new arrangements that will be made, and the new r--o~<br />
that will be in senior positions, that Australians can be totally<br />
confident that as we come to 1988 we are going to have a great<br />
bicentennial year.<br />
JOURNALIST: What is your impression of the morale in the Board?<br />
PM: Well I had a very useful, friendly constructive interchange<br />
of views with the Board. And I whs certainly left with the<br />
impression two things. One, that they are looking to the<br />
future. They have a total and shared commitment with the Government<br />
that we have a shared responsibility to ensure a great 1988.<br />
And secondly, that they are going, as a Board, to do everything<br />
they can in their power to achieve that objective with us.<br />
JOURNALIST: Any anger up there, Sir, about the sacking of John<br />
Reid? PM: None conveyed to me.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you think the Authority can still continue<br />
to act effectively while controversy still surrounds Dr Armstrong's<br />
departure.<br />
PM: Well I think that controversy that you refer to is diminishing.<br />
I have made it quite clear that it was a decision that had to<br />
be taken. It has been taken. And there is now another decision<br />
that has flowed from it which means that there has to be a new<br />
Chairman. Now, as Prime Minister it has given me no joy to<br />
have to initiate and take those decisions, but I have a responsibity'<br />
to do it. It has been exercised and I am sure now that in the<br />
event that the Bicentennial is going to be a great success.<br />
And I repeat again that we are singularly fortunate that in<br />
these circumstances Mr Utz has stepped in to fill the role of<br />
Chairman in those circumstances.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, one of the great criticisms of<br />
the older regime was that they were spending a lot of money<br />
and going on overseas junkets. Have there been any concrete<br />
proposals accepted now to reduce that so-called extravagance? </p>
<p>PM: Well there is the allegation about extravagance. I have<br />
referred to the arrangements that are now being made for an<br />
involvement by the Government to see what is going on. And<br />
I repeat, the elements of those are three. Firstly, there will<br />
be a representative of the Government who will be at the meetings<br />
of the Board. Secondly, there will be monthly reports to the<br />
government on the progress. And there will be quarterly statements<br />
of account to the government. Now I believe taking those three<br />
specific measures into account, plus the heightened awareness<br />
that will exist within the Authority of the concern that there<br />
shall be an accoun taib i 1 i n thc usc of puiblIi c Funds, T cnnl<br />
confident thau there will be no cause for concern in regard<br />
to that issue.<br />
JOURNALIST: Did your discussions with the Board today confirm<br />
that they needed a new leader?<br />
PM: Well they have, as I said, I think, accepted what has happened.<br />
And they are looking to tlie future and looking to it with confidence.<br />
So there is no point for anyone in trying to re-hash the past.<br />
That as far as the Board is behind them.<br />
JOURNALIST: Just briefly on the lands issue, the naval lands.<br />
Do you support the transfer of the naval lands in Sydney Harbour<br />
to Jervis Bay?<br />
PM: Well, that is a totally unfair question to ask me whether<br />
I support it. I initiated it when I had to assume the office<br />
of the Prime Minister and come and live in this beautiful city<br />
of Sydney temporarily in the Kirribilli headquarters. I looked<br />
out across Sydney Harbour and it just struck me as an absurdity<br />
in this day and age that you should have a major naval concentration<br />
in the middle of a great populous city like this. It struck<br />
me immediately and I have talked to my colleagues about i t.<br />
And so, what is happening is that a study is being undertaken<br />
of the implications of transferring the navy from Sydney to<br />
Jervis Bay. Now clearly there is a lot of work that has to<br />
be undertaken because we have these considerations to take into<br />
account. Firstly, the defence interests of this country, and<br />
so any change in that way has to be handled in terms that will<br />
not in any sense compromise, but will add to our defence capability.<br />
And secondly you have to take into account then how the released<br />
land will best be made available for the benefit of the people<br />
of Sydney. And I must say in this regard, that from the earliest<br />
point I have shared my thoughts on this matter with the-. Premier<br />
of NSW who totally shares my view that this move is overwhelmingly<br />
in the interests of the people of Sydney and of NSW.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke when is it likely to go ahead?<br />
PM: Well, you can't put ane xact timetable on it, because,<br />
I repeat, there are lots of considerations that have to be taken<br />
into account, but the work has been done now. The Ministers<br />
have initiated enquiries. They are going ahead. And I think<br />
the only thing one can say is that conceptually it is clear<br />
that this ought to happen. When we get the detailed reports<br />
we will then ' consider it in Cabinet, and I hope, on the basis<br />
of the report that we get, we will be able to initiate the moves<br />
in the relatively near future. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Inaudible.<br />
PM: I say initiate because You will. appreciate that what is<br />
involved is a lengthy, long-term process.<br />
JOURNALIST: Is the Navy in favour of the move?<br />
PM, 1: Wel. l, I don't know that there is such a thing monolithically<br />
the Navy. I can imagine that some elements of the Navy might<br />
no t1. be en tirel] y enamow r-ec ofF he p rospect. of rmo v inrg, but. I Lh i nk<br />
that those who are concerned, as there overwhelming would be,<br />
with the best interests of the Navy, and getting the most efficient<br />
setting for their operations. And that in the same context<br />
as ensuring the best interests of the civilian community, I<br />
am sure that they would regard it as appropriate.<br />
JOURNALIST: governor-General accepted free overseas<br />
PM: If you were in the Canberra Gallery you would know that<br />
one thing I don't answer is hypothetical questions. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
