<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10450</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS AT THE LAUNCH OF TOYOTA&#039;S NEW V-6 AUTOMOBILE EXPORT, MELBOURNE </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/08/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010450.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>18 August 1997 TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE HON. JOHN HOWARD MP<br />
ADDRESS AT THE LAUNCH OF TOYOTA'S NEW V-6<br />
AUTOMOBILE EXPORT, MELBOURNE </p>
<p>E O E<br />
Mr Okuda, Mr Conomos, Mr Komori, my colleague, John Moore, the Minister for<br />
Industry, ladies and gentlemen. I would like first of all to thank the Toyota company<br />
for the announcements that have been made this morning but more importantly, for the<br />
commitment to the future of motor manufacturing in Australia which they represent.<br />
Today's announcements are extremely good news for investment and jobs in Australia<br />
and locally here for the Victorian economy, particularly good news as well. This<br />
announcement is a vindication of the decision taken by my Government two months<br />
ago in relation to long-term policy for the motor manufacturing industry in Australia.<br />
We took a decision in June to maintain our commitment to the APEC goal of free<br />
trade by the year 20 10 but we also recognise that in the interim, a greater degree of<br />
predictability and certainty and stability were needed and that was the foundation of<br />
the decision that was taken to hold tariff levels after the year 2000 without alteration<br />
until the year 2005 and other particular decisions which accompanied that core<br />
announcement. We believed then that it would give to the industry predictability. We believed then<br />
that it would attract investment. We believed then that it would stabilise the<br />
employment market and create new jobs and this morning the Toyota announcement<br />
has demonstrated the wisdom of that policy and the Toyota announcement responds to<br />
that policy in a very positive fashion.<br />
I acknowledge the contribution that Toyota as a corporate citizen has made to<br />
Australia over a long period of time. Your company, Mr Okuda, has been a very fine<br />
corporate citizen in Australia. it has employed over the years thousands of Australians.<br />
It has invested large amounts of money in the fuiture of this country. I am particularly<br />
excited with the expansion of the export component of your activity here in Australia<br />
and I am also of course delighted that you have foreshadowed the manufacture in </p>
<p>Australia of an entirely new vehicle which you anticipate will come onto the market in<br />
the year 2000.<br />
At a time when it is incumbent upon Australia to be in the world competitive race,<br />
when it is incumbent upon Australia to present the economic and industry policy<br />
conditions which attract investment into Australia, the announcement that you have<br />
made this morning is of course very welcome news. It's also an opportunity for me as<br />
Prime Minister of Australia in a bilateral sense to reaffirm the tremendous importance<br />
of the economic association between Australia and Japan.<br />
You reminded us that this is the 60th year of the foundation of the Toyota Company. It<br />
is also of course the 40th anniversary of the signing of the Australia-Japan Commerce<br />
Agreement in 1957, which represented the first and probably the most important<br />
foundation stone of the economic relationship between Australia and the Asia Pacific<br />
region and out of that arrangement made in, that agreement signed in 1957, has grown<br />
Australia's most important bilateral economic relationship. It is a relationship that has<br />
delivered enormous benefits to Australia and I know it is a relationship which is very<br />
highly valued by the Prime Minister of Japan, Mr Hashimoto, with whom I have had<br />
very regular discussions and constant communication since each of us assumed our<br />
respective positions but it Is a relationship that like all good relationships ought to be<br />
kept in fine repair and individual examples of how important it is, such as your<br />
announcement this morning, are always welcome.<br />
And I therefore say that this morning, Mr Okuda, it is a very good day for Australian<br />
industry. It's a very good day for the industrial future of Australia. It's a reminder of<br />
the fundamental importance of long-term, predictable investment in Australian industry<br />
arnd it sends a very powerful, positive and optimistic signal because today's<br />
announcement represents large-scale, long-term, fresh investment in Australian<br />
manufacturing industry. It has already represented the creation of 400 additional jobs<br />
and it also holds the prospect over the years ahead of the creation of hundreds of more<br />
additional Australian jobs and it's therefore a very positive and a very welcome<br />
announcement. I thank you for being here. I hope you enjoy Australian hospitality, Mr Okuda, over<br />
the remaining days of your visit.<br />
Thank you. </p>
<p>_ QUESTIONS AND ANSWERS<br />
JOURNALIST: Could I ask the Prime Minister, Prime Minister did you know about Toyota's plans<br />
before the car tariff decision was made and if so, how much that influenced the<br />
Government's decision?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
We were told both publicly and privately that the decision that we were going to take<br />
would have an influence in general terms on the long-term investment plans of all of<br />
the companies and I don't, myself, recollect getting down to the specific detail of<br />
saying-well if this particular decision is taken we will have or number of<br />
jobs or or hundreds of millions of dollars of investment. But quite plainly, as<br />
I said in my remarks, the global environment in which we now exist, where there is a<br />
large amount of footloose, multinational investment, is heavily influenced by the<br />
individual investment climate and industry policy stability in individual countries and it<br />
was a factor that was taken on board and borne in mind.<br />
I mean, we were generally aware that if we provided the sort of stability that we have<br />
provided then it would be more likely, much more likely that we would have the sort<br />
of long-term investment that has been announced this morning but my recollection is<br />
not that we actually got down to the specifics of it. I mean, that is not my recollection.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Howard, the car market has been relatively stagnant for some years now. Will the<br />
restructuring of the tax system that you've now put in train be an opportunity to<br />
reverse that situation?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I think if we end up, which I am determined we will, with a new and better taxation<br />
system, that will be extraordinarily good news for industry generally because if we<br />
have a more efficient, indirect tax system that will remove some of the manifest<br />
distortions that exist within the existing taxation system.<br />
You mention that the market has been stagnant. Well as far as volume is concerned,<br />
the indications are that this year will be a lot better than some of the years that have<br />
preceded it and there are some real prospects that it could end up being the secondbest<br />
year on record from what I have been told in terms of overall sales volume.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you envisage any significant retail benefit from your taxation plans for the motor<br />
. industry? </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I am not going to at this stage get into specific commitments about particular<br />
industries. That invites me to, I guess, imply certain outcomes of the review. I am just<br />
not going to do that at this stage. We are aiming to have a better taxation system. We<br />
are obviously, as I announced last week, looking at replacing some or all of the<br />
existing indirect taxes with a broad-based, indirect tax as part of the overall overhaul.<br />
There are other components to it but I am not going to at this stage start saying: it's<br />
going to have a particular benefit here or a particular benefit over there.<br />
We think if you have a more efficient, a more uniform, indirect taxation system you<br />
produce very significant benefits right across industry and that could involve retail<br />
benefits. It depends upon the character of those individual decisions.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Howard, I was wondering whether you expected similar investment from the other<br />
car makers in Australia?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I expect a broadly positive response from the industry given the balance and far<br />
sightedness of the decision we took in June.<br />
[ ends] </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
