<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6661</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE, 30 JUNE 1985</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/06/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006661.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
4,. AUST1: AL1A -U<br />
E. O. E. PROOF ONLY<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE 30 JUNE 19a5<br />
PM: Ladies and Gentlemen, we now meet on the eve of the<br />
Summit. The Government goes into the Summit certain that<br />
the overwhelming majority of Australians believe that the<br />
existing tax system has virtually disintegrated, certainly<br />
to the point where they desi:-e to have a different system<br />
one which is fairer and more efficient and more easily<br />
understood. On the basis of that belief we have done the<br />
hard work of analysing that system and showing the ways in<br />
which we believe that the Australian community can achieve<br />
a better system. We look to the Summit now as the<br />
culminating process of the participation by the Australian<br />
community in the task of government and conumunity working<br />
together to achieve a system which ., ill meet the requirements<br />
of the cc-amunity. I believe that onus is now upon Lhe<br />
representatives of the community who will gather tomorrow<br />
and the days ahead'to analyse what has been put forward on<br />
the basis that the packages are made up of many elements<br />
and trust and indeed believe that the Summit will be a<br />
sensible process of analysis of the White Paper with a view<br />
to achieving the desired outcome. Certainly the Government<br />
goes into the Summit, as I have said throughout the last few<br />
weeks, prepared to' listen closely to what is put. As I<br />
said, we have discharged our obligation to do the initial<br />
work. The obligation is now upon others to participate and<br />
further the obligation upon us to be receptive to what is<br />
put. Because I believe those things will be done, I am<br />
looking forward toithe days of the Summit and I am certain<br />
that as a result of the Summit itself, the Government will<br />
then be in a position to make the decisions which will be<br />
necessary to bring about a more acceptable and efficient<br />
tax system in this country.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, if there was a general support for<br />
a consumption tax,' but not at the rate of 12 say it is<br />
a lower level 7 would you embrace that?<br />
PM: Well you started off with a hypothetical question. And<br />
you know I'm not terribly keen on those. But I think the<br />
comments I have made already are relevant to that question<br />
that is we are going to listen to what people have got to<br />
say. And if that was something that was to emerge quite<br />
clearly, then obviously the Government would have to take<br />
that seriously into account.<br />
,0 I </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, the Treasurer said he has killed<br />
of f that option.<br />
PM: Well I didn't see all of the Treasurer this morning on<br />
your program, Laurie,, but the part I saw didn't leave me with<br />
the impression that he was saying that he had killed off<br />
anythinq.<br />
JOURNALIST: He said a week ago he'd rather<br />
PM: Sunday was today', not a week ago.<br />
JOURNALIST: It doesn~ t change every day, does it, Sir?<br />
PM: No it doesn't. I listened to what he had to say this<br />
morning. What he had-to say this morning was totally<br />
consistent with what I have just Le en saying, and saying<br />
right through. That the Sumxnit. is real as far as we are<br />
concerned. We . are going to listen to what is said. And any<br />
part cnf what has been put by the Government is open for<br />
consideration. And if we could be persuaded that there was<br />
a better way of doing it., then that would be done.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, are there any circumstances in which<br />
you would ahead with a package with which the ACTU explicitly<br />
disagreed? PM: ' tell again, all the questions are in this hypothetical<br />
vein. I mean, I have made it cl~ ear that one of the nine<br />
principles that is the seventh principle is the sensible<br />
one that would require the support of the trade union<br />
movement to avoid any suggestion of double dipping or double<br />
compensation. Now I can't contemplate a position where even<br />
if the ACTU didn't entirely agree with everything that came<br />
to be included in the subsequent Government decision, that<br />
they would recant on the clear statements they have made<br />
through their Secretary that there is no way in which the<br />
trade union movement can look at double compensation. And I<br />
believe that that covers the situation which you are talking<br />
about. This Government is not going to be adopting a positionnor<br />
was principle seven ever meant to be one that we would<br />
only do what the ACTU agreed with. It has never been our<br />
position on any other issue and it is not on this. And if a<br />
situation emerged where a package was different from what the<br />
ACTU was saying was its totally preferred position, I still<br />
would not expect them to move away from the clear statement<br />
that they made before!. Youi couldn't have compensation via the<br />
tax system and then seek to get it another way as well<br />
through wages.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, do you think that the ACT2U is moving<br />
towards accepting Option C or moving away from that?<br />
PM: Well I don't really know. They are meeting here today.<br />
/ 3 </p>
<p>JOURNALTIST: You had a meeting with them last Wednesday<br />
though so you should<br />
PM: I spoke to some of them last week. They will have their<br />
meeting today. Itwould sti'll be my view that the ACTU will go<br />
into the Summit with its options open, that it will want to<br />
listen to what is said. It won't have a final position before<br />
going into the Summit, nor I imagine will it have a final<br />
position on Friday at the end of this week. If it is<br />
sensible and I believe it is it will listen to all of the<br />
arguments, all of the expositions and will consider them<br />
subsequently. So what they are moving to, I'm not sure. I<br />
believe that they will have been testing, and have had tested<br />
some options of thei. own. They will be wanting to make<br />
judgements about the outcome of that -Lesting, I would think.<br />
JOURNALIST: When is the latest -Aate theyshould make a<br />
decision do you think?<br />
PM: I don't understand your question.<br />
JOURNALIST: on their preferred position.<br />
PM: I don't understand your question. When should they. It's<br />
not for ic; t-o tell them when they should.. That is theii.<br />
business. JOURNALIST: Is it true on Thursday night, Mr Hawke, that<br />
Mr Kelty told you that Option C was not on?<br />
PM: I don't intend to go to any of the discussions that<br />
were details of the discussions that were held.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, are there any arguments you have heard<br />
over the last four weeks which would convince you that Option<br />
C is perhaps not the best route to take?<br />
PM: No, it is one of the interesting things that has emerged.<br />
N~ o-one has come out with a clear alternative. Understandably<br />
there have been questions about elements of the OPtion C<br />
as to whether the judgements that have been made about the<br />
inflation rate are correct; whether the savings ratio and<br />
expenditure patterns are appropriate; and other elements about<br />
the compensation package. Now, all I can say is that I have<br />
looked at the arguments that have been put and to this stage<br />
none of those arguments about the important elements of C<br />
have destroyed my qonfid~ nce in the adequacy of the assumptions<br />
in. C or the adequacy of the compensation package. Now that<br />
doesn't mean that in the days ahead there may not be more<br />
work emerges the . result of more work. But I must say that<br />
at this stage I believe that the option C looks as though it<br />
is the best way of going about it, if you are in fact going<br />
to achieve the most substantiLal cuts in direct taxes that &amp; MTC<br />
possible and also'ensure that those who currently don't pay<br />
any tax are brought, as far as possible, into the taxation net.<br />
But I repeat, I will be listening closely to what everyone<br />
has got to say during this week and it may well be that some<br />
modification is required. / 4 </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Do you concede that the week could en'd without<br />
agreement at all?<br />
PM: I have said all the way through that I regard it as<br />
unlikely that you could got consensus at this Summnit. I<br />
don't think on an issue like tax reform that you will get<br />
total agreement on ' anything other than the issue that the<br />
existing system is po good and needs to be changed. I think<br />
you will get just about total agreement on that.<br />
JOURNALIST: Well what is your definition then of broad<br />
support. Does it have to be 60% of the Summit agrees to<br />
Option C*:, or what?<br />
PM: I said quite clearly very early in the piece that I don't<br />
think the Summit is' going to be one in which you have hands<br />
being put up. And ' I said quite clearly before that you just<br />
look at the comoosition of the Summit and it is not one that<br />
will lend itself to that arithmetic sort of judgement.<br />
JOURNALIST: What will have to happen at the Summit for you<br />
to consider it to he a success?<br />
PM: Well, firstly, there would need to be an approach by the<br />
participants which went beyond just pushing of their own<br />
particular barrows or self interests. I mean, if we just got<br />
a succession of speakers getting up and putting their own case,<br />
their own constituencies case, then it would not have been a<br />
success. It follows that what you will be wanting is a Summit<br />
in which people are certainly putting their views putting<br />
themn strongly and explicitly where they are prepared to<br />
listen to the points of view of others and I think if that<br />
happens then you will ha~ ve the elements of a successful Summit.<br />
Certainly from ouripoint of view as a Government, we want to<br />
hear people getting up therc, not simply saying indirect<br />
taxes are regressive, because after all we do know that. What<br />
we would want to hear is detailed argument as to why the<br />
compensation package didn't meet adequately if it was so<br />
believed, the needs of those who would . otherwise be hurt<br />
by the regressiveness of an indirect tax package. Now, if<br />
people contribute,. as I believe they will, to the Summit<br />
in that way then Ibelieveit will be a success. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: What will you be saying to the farmers<br />
tomorrow. PM: Well I'll be doing them the justice of not<br />
having it put out ih the papers for them to read in the<br />
morning. I'll be talking to them directly, not second<br />
hand. JOURNALIST: How will you in the end assess the degree<br />
of public acceptance that you say is a prerequisite for<br />
implementing any substantial changes. Will this be<br />
by opinion polls or political intuition.<br />
PM: I don't knpw that it will be by opinion polls.<br />
Its a very importailt question, it is similar to the one<br />
that was asked befdre. I guess it will be a combination<br />
of things. It will, certainly be a listening to, and then<br />
a subsequent reading of all the things that are said at the<br />
Summit. It would involve, 1 would suggest, also following<br />
the Summit, the testing out number of people, wnether<br />
i, e havlA listened to what was said and that having raised<br />
in the minds of the Government certain question marks of<br />
the total adequacy of what we were doing, and then said<br />
to them, now would this, perhaps, adjustment meet your<br />
concern. Thc/ 1 picking up their reaction to thnat. so it will<br />
be a ntixti. 1re of processes that we'll have to go through<br />
to try and satisfy ourselves, following the Summit, 11hat<br />
we have taken into-account, as sensibly as we can, those<br />
things which do seem to have a fairly substantial body of<br />
backing. And we're cortainly not going to be adjusting<br />
to every single thing that's said. I mean that's not the<br />
way to go about Government. But if in fact you did<br />
see that there was something of fairly specific concern<br />
and you thought that you could Meet that concern, then<br />
subsequent to the Summit you would be testing people out,<br />
and getting ther reactions.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Ministe2r how would the Government<br />
respond if it went'ahead with Option C, and subsequently<br />
found that one or more unions attempted to double dip<br />
What mechanism have you got for dealing with that.<br />
PM: Wel. you've got this stage first of all.<br />
But of course you would be saying to the Commission clearly<br />
what the position of the Government was, and the position of<br />
the ACTU. As has already been said, that is that double<br />
compensation is not on. And so you would be attempting to<br />
use the authority of free institutions, the Government,<br />
the Commission and. the AtTU to ensure that didn't happen.<br />
And I would expect that employers would be singularly<br />
reluctant to admit a claim for an adjustment of wages where<br />
it could be clearly established that that amount had already<br />
been more than provided by the tax system. </p>
<p>6.<br />
JOURNALIST: But if the employer caved in would you envisage<br />
sending a reference on to the Prices 6vfv-i1', wc Tribunal.<br />
PM: Oh I mean w4e haven't got that far dowi the track.<br />
JOURNALIST: All things considered Prime Minister do you<br />
think this will be the last sum-nit on any topic?<br />
PM: No I don't ' see why it should be. I mean that seems<br />
to imply that one wouldn't have wanted to go ahead with this<br />
Summit if you'd had your thinking again. I've said on a<br />
number of occasions in the last few weeks that nothing has<br />
happened in any way; quite the contrary, I'm more than<br />
ever persuaded that its. sensible to have this Summit. Now<br />
I haven't in my mind at th.-Ls stage any other particular<br />
issue that I can see down the track which would requi-Lre it.<br />
But it could be, I don't know, I haven't got anything else<br />
in my mind at this stage. But* I'm certainly glad that we're<br />
having this Summit, and I'm sure that the Governent's<br />
thinking in meeting the wishes of the Australian people,<br />
will be assisted by it. I mean after all, I mean just<br />
think of the facts of what we're dealing with. If there's<br />
one thing that certain about the whole tax debate, it is<br />
that the community wants change. That's certain. Now,<br />
the imposition of changes in the past, by the Conservative<br />
parties, has resulted in a total, not merely a mess, but<br />
a system which is mr anifestly against the i~ eiterests of'toe<br />
peopl. e of Australia.. Now to give Lhe people of Australia,.<br />
through their representative organisations, tne opportunity<br />
of participating in the creation of a useful and fair,<br />
and efficient tax s ystem, is obviously sensible. An-1 I'm<br />
not only glad, but . proud of the fact that we've initiated<br />
that process to give the people that chance.<br />
JOURNALIST: Can we take it from your earlier comments<br />
that you don't expect agreement on any specific package?<br />
PM: Not on a package, Michael, I've said that right<br />
from the beginning.' I don't think you could get a consensus<br />
at a Summit like that upon a total package. I think there<br />
will be elements that would~ come through as quite clearly<br />
as having a clear majority support. But it will be the<br />
job of the Governm~ nt after the Summit to draw the elements<br />
together.<br />
JOURNALIST: Isn't that inconsistent with Principle Nine<br />
when you refer<br />
PM: No its not.<br />
JOURNALIST: Which.. particular elements do you think there<br />
will be general agreement on?<br />
PM: It would seent to me that one element that has<br />
been talked about in the White Paper and has been discussed<br />
a fair bit in the . community, on which I would think there<br />
would be not absolute agreement, but general agreement,<br />
would be the concept of a national identity card. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Prime Minister to what do you attribute<br />
the reported drops in Government popularity as expressed<br />
in the Cameron Poll?<br />
PM: Well I won't go into the details of that, but<br />
quite clearly the element of uncertainty about a tax reform<br />
has been part-of it.' But I'm more than confident, as I've<br />
said, during the last couple of weeks when I've been asked<br />
about this, that I believe that as we go up to the<br />
end of our term that the question of tax will be a very<br />
significant plus for this Government, and an equally<br />
significant minus for the Opposition.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister was the ANOP research financed<br />
by the tax payer, ai~ d if so will you make it public?<br />
PM: I think it: will be made public at an appropriate<br />
time.<br />
JOURNALIST: When is that sir?<br />
PM: I haven't addressed my mind to that.<br />
JOURNALI T: Mr Hawke you've said previously that you<br />
didn't," here would * be sufficient timce, foll~ owing the Summit,<br />
to allow for any changes i^ the August Budget, do you-still<br />
stick wit!, that view?<br />
PM: What we've said all along is that some elements,<br />
its possible that some elements, of tax changes could come<br />
in then, but substantially it would be post-budget. Its<br />
what we've said all along and I think the point's made in<br />
the White paper.<br />
JOURNALIST: When would you expect a final decision upon<br />
the 4.5% consumption tam.<br />
PM: Well, I would expect it at the same time as we<br />
finalised our position on the whole tax package. And I've<br />
indicated before that we would be expecting to finalise our<br />
position on these matters within a matter of weeks after<br />
the end of the Summit.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you see any need, Prime Minister, for a<br />
special Caucus meeting to discuss that decision.<br />
PM: I would think that there would be more than one<br />
Caucus meeting.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister you said last week that you were<br />
asking,. officials to check some of the White Paper's<br />
assumptions particularly into the macro 6coriomic<br />
CPI effect. Have you done that? </p>
<p>PM: Yes I already indicated in answer to a previous<br />
question that I had looked at this. And nothing that I've<br />
seen to this point, since I've come back to Canberra, and<br />
read on this subject, causes me in~ any substantial way<br />
to change the confidence that I previously had in these<br />
matters. But I will be continuing to look at further<br />
work on this,, right uip to and during the Summit.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister what hope do you have for<br />
getting some form of communiquc out of the Summit, even in<br />
broad terms?<br />
PM: Oh I've never thought really that any substantial<br />
communique would be likely. Certainly not comparable to<br />
the April 1983 Summit.<br />
JOURNALIST: Can you give us some odds for Option C<br />
surviving?<br />
PM: No.<br />
JOURNALIST: ' Prime Minister, Mr Keating said he's killed<br />
off any prospects of exemptions for food. If there is<br />
an overwhelming call for that at the Summit are you<br />
prepared PM: was in line with your previous question,<br />
Laurie, I give the same answer that I did before. That<br />
we will be listening to everything that is said, and all<br />
the elements of our proposals are open for consideration.<br />
JOURNALIST: So nothing's actually<br />
PM: Now come on, I've said it twice.<br />
1 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
