<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>20932</transcript-id>
    <title>Medicare - For All Australians  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/10/2003</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
 Today is the 20th anniversary of Medicare - our world-class public health system, which delivers universal health care for all Australians.</p>
<p>All Australians have the right to universal access to the three pillars of Medicare: a universal Medicare rebate for medical services; a universal Pharmaceutical Benefits Scheme; universal access to free public hospital care.</p>
<p>The Australian Government remains firmly committed to the principles of Medicare, which have guided it over the past two decades.</p>
<p>Not only is the Australian Government absolutely committed to the maintenance and strengthening of Medicare, unlike the Labor Party, it is totally supportive of the private health insurance rebate.</p>
<p>Not withstanding endorsement of the private health insurance rebate at the 1998 election, Labor opposed it in the Senate. If elected, there is no doubt Labor would take an axe to it.</p>
<p>A world-class system is one that helps us all stay healthy, provides support and treatment when we need it and is financially sustainable. The Australian Government is committed to ensuring that Australia has such a system, now and in the future.</p>
<p>Australia has a balance between public and private health care provision, which serves us well. We have one of the best health systems in the world delivered across great distances to populations ranging from 20 people in Summervale to more than 4 million in Sydney. It is a world class system by all comparisons.</p>
<p>Australia continues to have services and health outcomes well above the OECD average. We have one of the lowest mortality rates in the OECD, improving from 16th in 1969 to 3rd in 1999. Australia ranks 4th in the OECD on quality of life indicators published by the World Health Organisation.</p>
<p>It is appropriate the mark the 20th anniversary of Medicare. It is also vital that we have plans to keep Medicare up to date and able to cope with the modern demands facing all health systems across the world.</p>
<p>There are important differences between 1984 when Medicare was introduced and 2003. Worldwide health care systems are under challenge and in a state of constant change. There are ever increasing demands on health budgets.</p>
<p> Rising healthcare expectations, technical breakthroughs, changing age demographics and new medications are all placing new demands on Medicare.</p>
<p>We must be willing to find new solutions to allow people to access doctors and nurses wherever they live in an affordable manner so we can continue to provide the best possible health care for all Australians.</p>
<p>My Government has a proud record of practical achievement and the commitment of record resources to Medicare to provide a universal and equitable health insurance system for all Australians.</p>
<p>The Australian Government';s commitment to Medicare is underlined by our record:</p>
<p> Since 1996 spending on Medicare has increased by almost $2 billion – from $6 billion to almost $8 billion a year. Australian Government expenditure on General Practice (including Medicare rebates, the Practice Incentive Program and the General Practice Immunisation Incentives) have increased by about 30% over the past six years.</p>
<p> A record $42 billion funding commitment to State public hospitals to help ensure that all Australians are eligible to free treatment. This is a $10 billion increase and gives the public greater certainty because the States and Territories have for the first time given funding commitments for five years instead of one year and have agreed to at least match the Australian Government';s rate of funding growth.</p>
<p> Record funding for Australia';s world-leading Pharmaceutical Benefits Scheme. In 1991, the cost of the scheme was $1 billion and it is now nearly $5 billion. The PBS gives affordable access to medicines for all Australians.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
