<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2847</transcript-id>
    <title>CREATION OF A SECOND ASIA DIVISION IN THE DEPARTMENT OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/03/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002847.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
A AAF -b~ k<br />
NQ DATE<br />
M/ 51 9 March 1973<br />
CREATION OF A S'RCOND ASIA DIVISION<br />
IN THE DEPARTMENT OF FORIGN AFFAIRS<br />
~ The Minister for Foreign Affairs, Mr Whitlam, announced<br />
today that a second Asia Division would be established within the<br />
Department Foreign<br />
Tho iitrfo Afefaigrs, rWilm none<br />
It is expected that the new Division will become<br />
operational in April.<br />
Until now, there has been only one Division in the<br />
ODepartment dealing with the whole Asian Continent.<br />
The new divisional structure will enable the Department<br />
to handle more effectively the work-load and policy requirements<br />
of Australia's relations with Asia.<br />
One of the Asia Divisions will be responsible for North<br />
and West Asia and the other for South Asia, including South-East<br />
Asia. In addition to some rearrangement of Branch and Sectional<br />
responsibilities the changes also involve the creation of a new Branch<br />
/ 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
and a special Section to deal with regional developments,<br />
Mr Whitlam said: " I have emphasised, both before assuming<br />
office and since, the importance of achieving an independent stance<br />
in Australia's foreign policy and the imnortance we attach to<br />
Australia's position in the Asian/ Pacific region.<br />
" The structural changes which have been introduced into<br />
the Department of Foreign Affairs are intended to facilitate the<br />
implementation of the foreign policy initiatives which I have<br />
decided to introduce.<br />
" The establishment of relations with China will entail<br />
increased erfort particularly at the policy level. Our expanding<br />
relations with Japan also require increased attention. The same<br />
will be true with regard to my priorities for the development of<br />
relations with Indonesia within the wider South-East Asian<br />
context. " I have also announced my intention of seeking new forms<br />
of regional co-operation geared to the situation in the Asia/<br />
Pacific area following the Viet-Nam ceasefire, and to the realities<br />
of the </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
