<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4131</transcript-id>
    <title>ECONOMIC DEBATE</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/05/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004131.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
J ASRAIJ I<br />
FOR PRESS / J<br />
F76/ 100<br />
MAY 27, 1976<br />
ECONOMIC DEBATE<br />
A week ago, the Treasurer announced a number of major measures<br />
designed to take. Australia a further substantial step towards<br />
prosperity and to help in securing that prosperity for all<br />
Australians. The strategy expressed through these measures has been stated<br />
by the Coalition. Parties on many occasions: in Opposition,<br />
during the election campaign, and in Government.<br />
Our constantly reiterated strategy has been: to bring Government<br />
spending under control, to free resources to the private sector<br />
and to individuals, to pursue a responsible monetary policy with<br />
clearly announced goals, and to generate a climate of national<br />
responsibility in which wage and salary restraint will be possible<br />
and in which both business and unions will act with a principal<br />
regard for the national interest.<br />
The de ' bate over thI-e last week shows that the Labor Party has<br />
no coherent alteinative to offer.<br />
The debate has shown that only the Opposition is still unable<br />
to face the realities of responsible Government.<br />
When the Liberal and Country Parties were overwhelmingly<br />
endorsed by the Australian people last December, we faced aset<br />
of economic circumstances which should never have occurred<br />
in Australia.<br />
They were circumstances in which the opportunities of hundreds<br />
of thousands of Au~ stralians had been curtailed and in which the<br />
weakest sections of the community had suffered most of all.<br />
The fundamental reason why we faced those problems, why so many<br />
Australians were damaged was the approach to policy making<br />
of the previous Government.<br />
For three years the former Government took and encouraged<br />
the attitude that the old restraints on Government spending<br />
the limitations on the resources available no longer applied. I<br />
PRINAE MINISTER </p>
<p>-2-<br />
Difficult choices no longer had to be made between alternatives<br />
which were all desirable in some decgree the attitude was<br />
that if something was desirable, it was fair enough to print<br />
money to pay for it.<br />
The final report of the Social Welfare Commission noted this<br />
very attitude.<br />
" There was an expectation that expert commissions could put<br />
forward proposals for expenditure which would be automatically<br />
adopted." Exactly the same attitude of mind was exhibited by the Leader<br />
of the opposition in this debate on Tuesday.<br />
Again he demonstrated a total incapacity to understand the<br />
basic fact that responsible Governments must set priorities,<br />
must make choices. 0<br />
Now he regards all the expenditures of t-he previous administration<br />
as essential this is evidence not of real concern but of<br />
characteristic unwillingness to face reality.<br />
The Leader of the Opposition went so far as to describe our<br />
package as an attack on the living standards of Australiansthis<br />
from the man whose Government achieved the first real<br />
decline in Australia's gross domestic product for decades.<br />
To the previous administration, indivdual spending was not<br />
e~ sentia. Government spending was.<br />
It never seemed to occur to the members of that disastrous<br />
administration that other Australians did have prioritiesthat<br />
individuals also had needs and that they were entitled<br />
to some certainty in the proportion of their earnings they could<br />
retain to meet these needs.<br />
The Shadow Treasurer showed precisely the sam~ e frame of mind.<br />
I need refer only briefly to one part of his speech which<br />
demonstrates this.<br />
In discussing a package of measures which might have been<br />
acceptable to the Labor Party, he stated:<br />
" caution with the money supply, personal tax indexation, and<br />
increased child endowment might well be part of that package,<br />
brut so too would be the continuation and expansion of the<br />
effective expenditure programmes begun by the Labor Government."<br />
In other words he now accepts the historic reforms of-the<br />
Government's package, but refuses to accept the expenditure<br />
restraint which made them possible. In fact, he wishes<br />
simultaneously to expand Labor's programmes. </p>
<p>The Labor Party is apparently prepared to contemplate a<br />
deficit of $ 6,000, or even $ 7,000 million, required to<br />
finance an expansion of Labor's programmes plus the<br />
introduction of full personal income tax indexation.<br />
This is the programme the Shadow Treasurer imaginatively<br />
describes as spending our way " gently but firmly" out of<br />
stagflation.<br />
The Opposition has failed to understand one cardinal fact.<br />
W~ hen there is high inflation and high interest rates, the<br />
Gcver--ent cannot spend the nation out of unemployment.<br />
A strategy based on greater Government spending is relevant<br />
to conditions of high unemployment, low inflation,. and low<br />
interest rates.<br />
These are the circumstances for which the Keynesian pump<br />
priming approach was devised and in which it can succeed.<br />
They are not the circumstances which face us now.<br />
To apply this approach to a situation of high inflation and<br />
high interest rates, is a recipe for disaster.<br />
Labor tried that and it failed.<br />
Their spokesmen are still advocating that approach.<br />
They have learnt r'. ctnlng.<br />
To make possible the introduction of full personal tax<br />
indexation and lay the ground for a responsible budget, very<br />
ajor reductions on f'orward estimates have been necassary.<br />
ministers have outlined detailed savings in excess of $ 1500<br />
million in their own statements.<br />
Additional budget savings will arise from the Administrative<br />
Review Committee, from the ongoing attack on extravagance and<br />
duplication and from other more detailed savings from<br />
Departments. med-bank savings on the expenditure side will further relieve<br />
the budget.<br />
In all, savings of $ 2,600 million have been achieved as a<br />
result of a new ranking of Government priorities in expenditure.<br />
This exercise has been one of the most wide-ranging and<br />
comprehensive of its kind performed by any Government.<br />
imposing restraints on Government spending has inevitably<br />
meant that many desirable programmes can only move ahead at<br />
a slower pace than we might have hoped.<br />
Unfortunately, there has been no alternative. </p>
<p>In making choices we have been concerned to protect areassuch<br />
as welfare payments where * people are affected as<br />
individuals or areas especially important to opportunity<br />
such as education.<br />
Our Medibank reforms show our concern that the poorest people<br />
in our community should have access to high quality medical<br />
care.<br />
The Medibank Scheme requires no payment at all from those on<br />
lowest incorges. It places the burden of medical costs on<br />
the shoulders of those who can best afford to meet them..<br />
The Government has acted to restrain Government spending<br />
because only in this way can resources be freed to individuals<br />
and to companies.<br />
The package of measures brought down by the Government will<br />
give certainty to People in several ways.<br />
The expenditure restraints mean that for the first time in<br />
several years, both individuals-and business can have confidence<br />
that public sector spending is at last under control.<br />
Full personal tax indexation at last provides an assurance to<br />
all wage, salary and income earners that there will be no increase<br />
in the tax burden without deliberate and public decision.<br />
The family allowances scheme shows the Government's determination<br />
to work in the interest of all Australians.<br />
It shows above all, our concern for the disadvantaged in the<br />
Austra lian community.'<br />
These are solid foundations for confidence.<br />
A guarantee that wages will be protected from unlegislated<br />
increases in taxation has been, of course, a major concern<br />
of the trade union movement.<br />
The trade union movement has taken a consistent view that the<br />
certainty provided by tax indexation would be a major falztor<br />
in wage restraint.<br />
The protection afforded by the family allowances to w,. age earners<br />
near the minimum income with large families, has also been a longstanding<br />
concern of the tr , de union movement.<br />
A responsible control over Government spending can only<br />
be one element in a national effort to restore prosperity.<br />
There is a growing awareness that in recent years excessive<br />
increases in wages and salaries have imposed too great a cost<br />
on many businesses.<br />
The result has been the elimination of many jobs and continuing<br />
price inflation. </p>
<p>6 5-<br />
Wage restraint is necessary so that the private sector can<br />
become profitable once more, in the interests of job<br />
opportunities and price stabilitit.<br />
Other ise there will continue to be high unemployment, there<br />
will continue to be price inflation.<br />
Bringing inflation under control is not just a job for the<br />
Government. Restoring -full employment is a responsibility which falls as<br />
much on the trade unions and businesses, as i-L does on the<br />
Go ve rnme nt.<br />
The packa ge of measures announced by the Government last week,<br />
provides an unparalleled basis for national cooperation.<br />
The great majority of Austral ians are sick and tired of inflation<br />
and unemployment.<br />
People want the merry-go-round to stop.<br />
The approach of the previous Government rei terated in this<br />
House this ieek has not worked. It has instead been a<br />
principal cause of' the problems we now face.<br />
The Government's strategy is working. The present measures<br />
will help to sustain and support the economic recovery which<br />
is now occurring.<br />
With goodwill on all sides they will provide a solid basis<br />
for national cooneration. 000000000000 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
