<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18815</transcript-id>
    <title>Intervention - The New Deal: g7+ Perspectives and Experiences</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/09/2012</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>New York City, USA</p>
<p>It's a great honour to take part in this panel discussion on the New Deal.</p>
<p>I'm reminded that in 2012, we mark 80 years since Franklin Roosevelt proclaimed the original New Deal:</p>
<p>That remarkable extension of hope to a people afflicted by the misery of unemployment, poverty and homelessness.</p>
<p>High ideals entrusted to practical and achievable measures.</p>
<p>Hope that could, in FDR's words, only be delivered with "statesmanship and vision".</p>
<p>That could just as well serve as description of the New Deal initiative.</p>
<p>It is a timely and ambitious agenda, and the g7+ members should be proud of the progress achieved to date  -  and determined to do more.</p>
<p>Australia was proud to be a founding member of the International Dialogue on Peacebuilding and Statebuilding which led to the New Deal.</p>
<p>It is sobering to think that there are more than 1.5 billion people living in fragile and conflict-affected countries  -  more than one in five of all the world's people.</p>
<p>And that, on present trends, it is likely that not a single g7+ country will achieve even one Millennium Development Goal by 2015.</p>
<p>Nothing could better illustrate the vital relationship between ending conflict and achieving development.</p>
<p>People living in conflict-affected and fragile countries are twice as likely to be undernourished.</p>
<p>Their children are three times more likely to not attend school.</p>
<p>Unemployment is too high, economic opportunities too few and tragically, life expectancy too short.</p>
<p>These stark realities compel us to do more to build peace, to strengthen state institutions, to engage civil society and local communities and support country-led transitions out of fragility, to manage our aid better.</p>
<p>The New Deal Initiative offers real promise to achieve that  -  in turn, offering real promise to accelerate progress toward the MDGs in fragile and conflict-affected states.</p>
<p>As co-chair of the Secretary-General's MDG Advocacy Group, I have made a personal pledge to advocate for development in conflict-affected and fragile states.</p>
<p>Building the resilience of fragile states also remains a key focus for Australia's aid program</p>
<p>In 2012-13 more than 55 per cent of our bilateral and regional aid  -  almost $1.8 billion  -  will go to fragile or conflict-affected states.</p>
<p>Seven of the top ten recipients of Australian aid are fragile or conflict-affected countries.</p>
<p>We are proud to be the lead donor supporting the New Deal pilot in Timor-Leste  -  through a new partnership arrangement with the Timorese government.</p>
<p>By the end of this year, we will have provided access to safe water for an additional 90,000 people as well as access to basic sanitation for 35,000 rural people.</p>
<p>Together we are working towards the goal of rehabilitating all rural roads by 2015, creating some 52,000 jobs by 2016 and bringing opportunities to the rural poor.</p>
<p>By 2015 we aim to be providing quality basic education to 93 per cent of children aged between six and fourteen  -  and to reduce the drop-out rate to just five per cent.</p>
<p>Building on our work in Timor-Leste, we are moving to align our work in other fragile states with the New Deal.</p>
<p>In Afghanistan, for example, we recognise the importance of Afghan Government leadership and capacity. As proof of this, we now deliver 50 per cent of our assistance through Afghan Government systems.</p>
<p>These are not only good examples of Australia's commitment to the collective enterprise of building peace and fostering development.</p>
<p>They illustrate that the goals and ambitions of the New Deal are achievable.</p>
<p>Together we can deliver change. Our commitment to the New Deal must not waver. The world's poorest and most vulnerable need us now.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
