<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7112</transcript-id>
    <title>OPENING OF RAINBOW STREET CHILD CARE CENTRE SYDNEY - 13 FEBRUARY 1987</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/02/1987</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007112.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
It ' v U TRA A<br />
PRIME M<br />
EMBARGOED UN IL DELIVERY CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
OPENING OF RAINBOW STREET CHILD CARE CENTRE<br />
SYDNEY 13 FEB3UARY 1987<br />
FEDERAL AND STATE LABOR GOVERNMENT COLLEAGUES,<br />
MAYOR OF RANDWICK,<br />
ALDERMAN SCUE. LION,<br />
DISTINGUISHED GUESTS,<br />
LADIES AND GE NTLEMEN.<br />
IT IS A GREAT PLEASURE TO BE EERE TODAY TO OPEN THE RAINBOW<br />
STREET CHILD CARE CENTRE. WE ARE CELEBRATING A HISTORIC<br />
OCCASION TODAY, FOR THE RAINBOW STREET CHILD CARE CENTRE IS<br />
THE 100TH CU27LD CARE CENTRE COMPLETED UNDER THE CO-OPERATIVE<br />
PROGRAM Bt4EN THE COMMONWEALTH AND NSW GOVERNMENTS.<br />
WITH EVERY 2,; ILD CARE CENTRE THAT IS OPENED, ANOTHER STEP IS<br />
TAKEN TOWARD3 ACHIEVING A NUMBER OF MY GOVERNMENT'S MOST<br />
IMPORTANT POLICY GOALS: EQUAL EMPLOYMENT OPPORTUNITY FOR<br />
WOMEN, SUPPORT FOR THE WELL BEING OF AUSTRALIAN CHILDREN,<br />
AND SUPPORT ! OR THEIR FAMILIES.<br />
THIS CENTRE ALSO ILLUSTRATES THE ACTIVE SUPPORT FOR CHILD<br />
CARE WHICH EXISTS AT ALL THREE LEVELS OF GOVERNMENT. I HAVE<br />
MENTIONED TAE CO-OPERATIVE ARRANGEMENTS BETWEEN THE<br />
COMMONWEALTH AND NSW GOVERNMENTS, BUT I WOULD BE REMISS IF I<br />
FAILED TO PAY TRIBUTE ALSO TO THE RANDWICK MUNICIPAL COUNCIL<br />
WHICH SPONSORS THE RAINBOW STREET CENTRE AND TWO OTHER CHILD<br />
CARE CENTRES IN THE RANDWICK LOCAL GOVERNMENT AREA.<br />
WHEN MY GOVERNMENT CAME TO OFFICE THE COMMONWEALTH FUNDED<br />
ONLY 46,000 CHILD CARE PLACES. BY JUNE 1988 WE WILL HAVE<br />
APPROVED AND FUNDED A TOTAL OF 60,000 NEW PLACES MORE THAN<br />
HAVE BEEN FUNDED BY ALL PREVIOUS GOVERNMENTS COMBINED.<br />
IN THE LAST YEAR OF THE FRASER GOVERNMENT $ 65 MILLION WAS<br />
SPENT ON CH2LD CARE. THIS FINANCIAL YEAR MY GOVERNMENT IS<br />
SPENDING JUST UNDER $ 200 MILLION FOR CHILD CARE.<br />
BUT IT'S NOT JUST A QUESTION OF INCREASING THE RAW RESOURCES<br />
AVAILABLE TO CHILD CARE.<br />
WE HAVE ALSC TRIED TO PROMOTE A MIX OF SERVICES IN RESPONSE<br />
TO THE VARIETY OF CHILD CARE NEEDS IN THE COMMUNITY. </p>
<p>IN PROVIDING FUN4DING FOR LONG DAY CARE WE HAVE RESPONDED TO<br />
THE NEEDS OF PARENTS WHO WORK OR WHO ARE SEEKING WORK. WE<br />
HAVE DONE MORE TO PROVIDE CHILD CARE TO SUPPORT WORKING<br />
WOMEN THAN ANY OTHER GOVERNMENT HAS.<br />
WE ARE ALSO EXPANDING SERVICES WHICH ASSIST PARENTS WHO STAY<br />
AT HOME WITH CHILDREN. BY JUNE 1988 WE WILL HAVE<br />
ESTABLISHED AN ADDITIONAL 3,000 OCCASIONAL CARE PLACES TO<br />
PROVIDE THESE CAILDREN A FEW HOURS OF CARE A WEEK OUT OF<br />
THEIR HOMES.<br />
AND IN BUILDING CHILD CARE CENTRZS LIKE THIS ONE AT RAINBOW<br />
STREET WE ARE ,) ISPLAYING OUR DETER1INATION TO ENSURE MAXIMUM<br />
ACCESS TO CHILD CARE SERVICES BY PEOPLE WHO NEED THEM MOST.<br />
RANDWICK HAS 13-: ZN IDENTIFIED BY "" HE NSW STATE PLANNING<br />
COMMITTEE AS DZING IN HIGH NEED OF CHILD CARE FACILITIES.<br />
AS WELL AS RAIN3OW STREET, THREE OTHER CHILD CARE CENTRES<br />
HAVE BEEN APPROVED IN THE RANDWICK LOCAL GOVERNMENT AREA<br />
UNDER THE CCil . HWEALTH/ STATE PLAN.<br />
WE ALSO TRY TO -NSURE THAT CHILD CARE IS AFFORDABLE BY LOW<br />
AND MODERATE INCOME EARNERS. UNDER A FEE RELIEF SYSTEM, THE<br />
GOVERNMENT'S CONTRIBUTION FOR A SINGLE CHILD CARE PLACE CAN<br />
RISE FROM AN AVERAGE OF $ 35 A WEEK TO AS MUCH AS $ 90 A WEEK.<br />
IT'S CLEAR X THINK THAT THE COMHONWEALTH AND NSW HAVE A GOOD<br />
RECORD IN WORA-NG TOGETHER TO INCREASE THE PROVISION OF<br />
CHILD CARE.<br />
NSW WAS NOT CNLY THE FIRST STATE TO BECOME INVOLVED IN WHAT<br />
WE KNOW AS THE COMMONWEALTH/ STATE CO-OPERATIVE ARRANGEMENTS<br />
BUT ACTUALLY SUGGESTED, BACK IN 1982, THAT THE STATE AND<br />
COMMONWEALTH GOVERNMENTS WORK TOGETHER TO SHARE THE COSTS OF<br />
CONSTRUCTING CHILD CARE CENTRES. BY JUNE 1988 THE NUMBER OF<br />
CHILD CARE CENTRES IN NSW WILL HAVE RISEN TO 177<br />
REPRESENTING NORE THAN 7000 ADDITIONAL CHILD CARE PLACES.<br />
ALL THESE FIGURES SHOW CLEARLY THAT CHILD CARE IS A COSTLY<br />
SCHEME. BUT IT IS EQUALLY CLEAR THAT THE CENTRES WE ARE<br />
ESTABLISHING FULFILL A VERY REAL NEED IN THE COMMUNITY. WE<br />
ARE PROUD OF OUR RECORD SO FAR AND I WANT TO STATE WE WILL<br />
NOT BE DETERRED FROM CONTINUING TO THE MAXIMUM EXTENT<br />
POSSIBLE TO NEZT WHAT ARE PRESSING AND WIDESPREAD COMMUNITY<br />
NEEDS. I WANT IN CLOGZNG TO SINGLE OUT THE NAMES OF THREE PEOPLE<br />
FOR SPECIAL THANKS.<br />
FIRST, SINCE THE RAINBOW STREET CHILD CARE CENTRE HAS BEEN<br />
OPERATING SINCE 1 SEPTEMBER LAST YEAR, I WANT TO<br />
CONGRATULATE ANNE MXZON, THE DIRECTOR OF THE CENTRE, AND HER<br />
STAFF, ON THE PLEASANT AND CREATIVE ATMOSPHERE THAT IS<br />
APPARENT HERE.<br />
SECOND, I WANT TO RECOGNISE THE CONTRIBUTION MADE TO RAINBOW<br />
STREET AND INDEED TO THE ENTIRE FEDERAL ELECTORATE OF<br />
PHILLIP BY YOUR LOCAL MEMBER, JEANETTE MCHUGH. SHE IS A </p>
<p>VERY ARTICULATE AND VERY DETERMINED LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE AND<br />
I KNOW DETTER THAN MOST A VERY EFFECTIVE DEFENDER IN<br />
CAUCUS OF HER CONSTITUENTS' INTERESTS.<br />
FINALLY, I SUST ACKNOWLEDGE A PERSON WHOSE CONTRIBUTION TO<br />
RAINBOW STREET AND TO EVERY OTHER CHILD CARE CENTRE WE HAVE<br />
ESTABLISHED AROJND THE NATION HAS BEEN GIGANTIC. I AM<br />
TALKING ABOUT DON GRIHES, WHO AS MINISTER FOR COMMUNITY<br />
SERVICES AND BEFORE THAT AS SOCIAL SECURITY MINISTER, IS<br />
HORE THAN ANYONE ELSE ABLE TO CLAIM RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE<br />
GROWTH OF CHILD CARE SERVICES BY MY GOVERNMENT.<br />
NEXT MONDAY, DON GRIMES IS FORMALLY TO RESIGN FROM HIS<br />
MINISTERIAL POST:. HE WILL THUS BECOME THE FIRST MINISTER TO<br />
LEAVE MY MXNISTRY SINCE WE WERE ELECTED WHICH I MIGHT ADD<br />
MEANS THE COHPOSITION OF MY MINISTRY HAS BEEN THE MOST<br />
STABLE OF ANY SINCE FEDERATION.<br />
WITH DON'S DEPARTURE GOES A MAN WHOSE CONTRIBUTION TO THE<br />
NATION HAS BEEN INMENSE. HE HAS BEEN A SYMPATHETIC AND<br />
BRILLIANTLY XNORMED MINISTER IN THE HUGE WELFARE AREA. HE<br />
HAD WON TEiE DESPECT OF WELFARE ACTIVISTS LONG DEFORE WE CAME<br />
INTO OFFICE ; ND HIS WORK IN OFFICE HAS VINDICATED THAT<br />
RESPECT. THE 100TH CHILD CARE CZNTRE BUILT IN NSW UNDER THE<br />
JOINT FEDERAL-NSW PROGRAM MUST STAND AS AN ENDURING MONUMENT<br />
TO HIM.<br />
I NOW OFFICIALLY DECLARE THE RAINBOW STREET CHILD CARE<br />
CENTRE OPEN AKD WISH YOU ALL WELL IN THE OPERATION OF THIS<br />
IMPORTANT COEr: IUNITY RESOURCE.<br />
^ fio0aa* f 0 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
