<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4362</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S ADDRESES AT OPENING CEREMONY OF IPU</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/04/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004362.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 11 APRIL 1977<br />
PRIME MINISTER'S ADDRESS AT OPENING CEREMONY OF I. P. U.<br />
I am very pleased to join with His Excellency, the Governor<br />
General, the Chairman, and President, in welcoming all of you<br />
to Australia.<br />
Your five study groups, which will meet in our National<br />
Parliament this week, in preparation for the 64th Annual<br />
Conference of the IPU, are discussing issues of great<br />
importance to every country and to all people.<br />
The five subjects you will examine are diverse: disarmament;<br />
world economic development; decolonisation; and two issues<br />
of world resources, the law of the sea, and water management.<br />
Yet they have a common theme. Each in its own way vitally<br />
concerns the world's peace and security. In each area,<br />
progress is urgently required.<br />
The maintenance of international peace and security and the<br />
achilevement of significant arms limitation, hold a hiq. h<br />
priority in the Australian Government's foreign policy.<br />
The immediate task of arms control is to ensure greater<br />
stability in international relations. We should strive to<br />
set military balances at the lowest possible levels compatible<br />
with general defence requirements; and we should seek the preven.<br />
rtion of the proliferation of destabilising weapons systems<br />
which can contribute to arms races.<br />
It is encouraging that over one hundred countries have ratified<br />
the Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty. Despite its imperfections,<br />
that Treaty offers the best prospect of containing the spread of<br />
nuclear weapons.<br />
Australia has welcomed the progress that has been made thus far<br />
in the strategic arms limitation talks between the USA and the<br />
USSR, and we hope that the problems encountered duringr the recent<br />
visit of Mr. Vance to the USSR do not deter either party from<br />
continuing negotiations. We attach great importance t~ o the<br />
achievement of an agreement which would end nuclear weapons<br />
teSting in all environments. / Mankinid is </p>
<p>-2<br />
Mankind is also faced with pressing resource problems.<br />
The world community is gradually coming to grips with the<br />
problem of safeguarding the environment in which we live,<br />
and of developing more rationally our scarce natural resources.<br />
The deficiencies of water supplies, both in quantity and quality,<br />
looms as one of the great issues in economic and social development<br />
over the next twenty five years. It is within this context<br />
that the importance of the IPU's study group on water must be<br />
seen. I hope that the group will be able to alert the broader community<br />
to the fact that a higher priority must be given to water conservation,<br />
and shed some insight on how this awareness can be translated<br />
into practical policies.<br />
The study group dealing with the Law of the Sea is a prelude,<br />
not only to the IPU's meeting at Sofia later this year, but to<br />
the next session of the Law of the Sea Conference, which will<br />
begin in New York next month.<br />
That Conference is now faced with an impasse on the important<br />
issue of the seabed-beyond national jurisdiction. Australia is<br />
anxious to see this impasse broken. It is apparent that, ' unless<br />
there is a resolution of this issue, the agreements which have<br />
already been tentatively reached on many of the other issues<br />
being considered by the Conference, may very well break down.<br />
If this happens, an historic opportunity to make a widelyaccepted<br />
comprehensive convention, will have been lost.<br />
Australia believes all nations should make every effort at<br />
the forthcoming session to reach accommodation on this vital issue.<br />
Australia takes a strong interest in the continuing dialogue<br />
between developed and developing countries on a new international<br />
economic order.<br />
We are sympathetic to the economic problems and aspirations<br />
of developing countries, and we recognise the need to help<br />
speed up the pace of economic development in the developing<br />
nations. Aid to the developing countries has an essential<br />
contribution to make to this process.<br />
Australia believes that there are improvements which could be<br />
made in this area, Fe have argued that wherever possible,<br />
official aid should be provided in ways that avoid adding<br />
to the recipient's debt burden.<br />
While Australia<br />
believes that the essential framework of the present international<br />
economic system is sound, there is a clear need to endeavour to<br />
identify realistic and practical ways in which it can be improved,<br />
to the benefit of all countries. / The IPU </p>
<p>3<br />
The IPU because it provides a forum for informed and<br />
constructive dialogue between representatives of developing<br />
and developed countries, is'well placed to take part in the<br />
international consideration of this vital issue.<br />
One subject that is at least as important as all of those I<br />
have mentioned, is the question of human rights. One of the<br />
study committees will be examining a key aspect of this question<br />
when it looks at decolonisation. Australia takes an active<br />
part in the international debate on this subject. In<br />
particular, through its membership of both the UN Special<br />
Committee on Decolonisation and the UN Council for Namibia.<br />
I reaffirm the Australian Government's resolute opposition to<br />
all forms of racial discrimination, and its support for those<br />
practical measures, in conformity with the charter of the<br />
United Nations, designed to end apartheid and other forms of<br />
racism. Ladies and gentlemen, you have much to discuss. I wish your<br />
deliberations well, for in each of the areas to which I have<br />
referred, greater understanding and new initiatives are<br />
urgently required. </p>
<p>EDITED EXTRACT FROM THE PRIME MINISTER' S OPENING ADDRESS<br />
AT THE I. P. U. -CANBERRA, 11 APRIL 1977<br />
There are still some who argue that sport and politics<br />
have no relationship.<br />
They aLrgue that as sporting teams come and perform<br />
teams selected on a racial basis that is not something<br />
which should concern governments or in which governments should<br />
take some action.<br />
That kind of view is no longer credible today.<br />
It is not the government of the host country that has<br />
introduced sport into politics. It is the government of the<br />
other country that has made arrangements for sport to be so<br />
structured internally that people of one race alone can<br />
part icipate.<br />
Accordingly, if a government operates its own social and<br />
economic system in that form, other governments cannot be<br />
expected to continue with the outdated proposition that<br />
sport is separate from politics.<br />
It is clear that where a sport is practiced on a racist basis,<br />
goverrnments must carry responsibility. It is the government that<br />
has then introduced politics into sport. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
