<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6604</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/03/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006604.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA 4 March 1985<br />
As host of the ANZUS Council due to meet in Australia in July the<br />
Government has decided that it is necessary at this point to<br />
announce the postponement of the meeting.<br />
The serious difficulties between the United States and New Zealand<br />
have arisen following the New Zealand Government's decision on<br />
United States naval vessels.<br />
In the light of the New Zealand decision, the United States<br />
response to that decision, and other recent developments including<br />
the curtailing of intelligence exchanges between the United States<br />
and New Zealand, it is clear that the holding of a regular ANZUS<br />
Council Meeting at the present time would be impracticable.<br />
These developments need to be kept in perspective. As I said at<br />
the White House on 7 February, an important aspect of the ANZUS<br />
relationship has become a matter of close concern. But the ANZUS<br />
Treaty remains. It needs to be emphasised that this point is not<br />
in dispute between any of the ANZUS partners.<br />
The pre-eminent responsibility of the Government is to ensure the<br />
protection of Australia's essential national security interests,<br />
and it will now do this through bilateral channels with both<br />
partners while the present circumstances prevail.<br />
In the case of the United States, the Australian Government has<br />
been reassured by views expressed to it publicly and privately by<br />
President Reagan and other senior representatives of the<br />
Administration, that the Australian/ United States Alliance under<br />
ANZUS remains as strong as ever.<br />
In the case of New Zealand, we propose to pursue our important<br />
defence relationship on a bilateral basis reflecting both our<br />
traditions and the common need to respond to regional security<br />
requirements.<br />
Further announcements on specific arrangements in regard to both<br />
relationships will be made shortly. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
