<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>489</transcript-id>
    <title>WEST NEW GUINEA - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R G MENZIES IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES - 29TH MARCH 1962</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/03/1962</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000489.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
WEST : WGUINFA<br />
SPEECH BY ThE PRIME MlSlfR, HE R5. ' ON. h,. Kl. T'S<br />
IN -TH O b Z Nj-' DIT ' S<br />
29TH MHaCH. 196<br />
Mr. Speaker, I think I ought to begin by<br />
congratulating my honourable friend the Leader of the Opposition<br />
( Mr. Calwell) on his speech. After all, he has had great<br />
difficulties on this matter and we have witnessed them from afar<br />
how was he going to reconcile the very war-like utterances, so<br />
dramatically described in the " Sydney Morning Herald" with the<br />
well-kno nm views of some of those who sit, metaphorically,<br />
behind him? And so we have been vaiting anxiously to see the<br />
grand reconciliation. I do want to congratulate him on the way<br />
in which he has escaped from his known difficulties, by diving<br />
into a nimbus of words, because that is what he has done tonight.<br />
But in my limited time I cannot deal with all the<br />
points I would like to deal with. I hope I will be excused by<br />
the House for a little recollection of my earlier, and what some<br />
of you may think my more respectable, days at the Bar. We had a<br />
broad rule, as cross-examinors, that if you could bowl a witness<br />
out in a really good cold-blooded lie you ought not to worry<br />
about him much longer thereafter. Bearing that little principle<br />
in mind I just take one statement among the many made by the<br />
honourable gentleman in the course of his speech. " Have we ever<br />
insisted on the principle of self-determination" he said. " eo"~<br />
( the Government) " Oh, no,"' bo says " the Prime Ministor has'<br />
himself ami. tted that the Government has not", and he then<br />
proceeds to quote from a speech of mine made in this House on<br />
27th April, 1961, after the visit of General Nasution, and he<br />
quotes two passages, torn out of their context; one of them<br />
referring to sovereignty and the other of them referring to<br />
domestic jurisdiction. And with a triumph of eloquence, or what<br />
passes for eloquence, he says " Here you are. This is an admissim<br />
by the Prime Minister that the principle of self-determination,<br />
to which the Labour Party is now so devoted, has been abandoned<br />
by him and is not worth a mention".<br />
I sent out for my statement of 27th April. I invite all<br />
members to read it, if they want to judge the truthfulness of the<br />
Leader of the Opposition. Read it it is in " Hansard" at page<br />
1247 and the following pages because in the course of this<br />
statement I think it might be desirable to remind honourable<br />
members of it; I will not quote .1l the passages, because there<br />
were many passages on this matter I went on to explain this<br />
is to General Nasution what we w. ere doing in our section of New<br />
Guinea in pursuit of our long-held goal of improvement of living<br />
standards, education and health to a point where the population<br />
would freely determine its own future. Then later on I referred<br />
to the fact that the Government of Australia, under my own<br />
Prime Ministership, and the government of the Netherlands had<br />
made an agreement in which they jointly declared that they are<br />
therefore pursuing and will continue to pursue policies directed<br />
towards the political, economic, social and educational<br />
advancement of thopooples in their territories in a manner which<br />
recognizes their affinity, I said further<br />
" In so doing the two Governments are dutermined to prorote<br />
an uninterrupted development of this process until such<br />
timo as the inhabitants of the territories conc. rned will<br />
be in a position to determine their own future".<br />
Then again I will not read it all because I have not time; I<br />
think I have only twenty minutes I wont on to add </p>
<p>" In our own New Guinea Territories our policy is, by steady<br />
dogroos and up to the limits of our financial and<br />
Ldministrative capacity, to proote the advancement of the<br />
people so that ultirctely they 1i; ill choose for thomselves<br />
their own constitution and their future relationship with<br />
us. ' Je will respect their choice whatover it may be.<br />
This, for us, is not a new policy. 0e have pursued it for<br />
years. It arises from our sense of responsibility, a<br />
responsibility which ca-nnot be suddenly or prematurely<br />
abandoned if our trusteeship is to be honourably performod'.'<br />
Sir, those are three out of half a dozen references, in<br />
my statement of that date, to this problem in this House. And yet<br />
the bodovilled Leader of the Opposition, bomused by brawls in his<br />
own party, has the nerve to stand up here and say that this<br />
principle is something for which wo do not speak, something for<br />
which we do not stand, and which apparently I am supposed to have<br />
abandoned specifically in the throe statements from 7which I have<br />
read excerpts to the Houseo. Sir, I recall the old principle of<br />
cross-examination to which I referred and if he were the witness<br />
I would say, " I leave it there",<br />
Now, Sir, lot me go on a little. I will not leave it<br />
there, for this purpose: The honourablo gentleman, so pressed by<br />
his own domestic party anxioties, has thought fit as usual, to<br />
deliver a torrent of personal abuse at me. I want to make it<br />
clear that he almost invariably apologiss in private. But he<br />
has done it. I made an awful fool of rysolf at Suez. Really, it<br />
is about time that people understood that it is not an insult to<br />
a Prine Minister of Australia for him to be invited by eighteen<br />
nations in the world to present their views to the President of<br />
Egypt. It is not an insult to the Prinm. Minister of Australia,<br />
It is not a job that anybody would covet. If anything would make<br />
one sick, it is this crawling, -pologotic attitude that you should<br />
never take on any responsibility in the world, oven on behalf of<br />
your most powerful friends, unless you have it underwritten for<br />
success in adv. nco. I amn happy to say that I am not made that<br />
way and neither are my colleagues.<br />
This is the irony of it all: The honorable gentleman<br />
loves to quote what somebody said about my appearance at the<br />
United Nations in November, 1960. I want to tell lonourable<br />
menbors that at that appearance I r. ade a speech which was as<br />
strong as a speech could be about the principle of solfdeotermrination<br />
and about what we wero doing in Papua . nd New<br />
Guinea. In that speech I made an attack. on the villainous new<br />
colonialism of the Soviet Union. The Leader of the Opposition<br />
does not worry about that speech. It w:-s not in his official<br />
newspapor; it was suppressed. But that was the speech I mado.<br />
Yet he comas back to it and says, " The Prime Minister was never<br />
fit to be Minister for itrnal Affairs. Instead of cultivating<br />
the friendship of great countries likoe the United States of<br />
Amrica and the United. Kingdor ho _ ught to be cultivating the<br />
friendship of the governnonts and Peoples of Asia". That was the<br />
theory that was put into his mouth at that tine. I do not want<br />
to repeat what I said on an earlior occasion, but I remind<br />
honourable mealbers that only a ooorn thtw o ago the honourable<br />
gentleman, goadd on by his fri-nds in Sydney, mado a dramatic<br />
statoeent the only signiicanco of which was to say that, instead<br />
of cultivating the friendship of the Asian people all of whom<br />
support the Indonosian clair, I sDhould have been prepared to<br />
declare war on tho, not over the Australian torzitory of Papua<br />
and lw Guinea, for which 11 of us will fight, but over West New<br />
Guinea. What a it is to h: ve cl1. l this vulgar abuse about<br />
the Prime Minister, a-c the tinome being also Minister for External<br />
Affairs, not oakfirnige nds with Asi.. I vonture to say that no<br />
nn has done more to embitter our relationship with the Asian<br />
countris in the last six m: nths than the over-oxcited Loa.. of<br />
the Opposition. </p>
<p>There is really not i. luch occasion to alaboorate this<br />
matter. But so I may .:. cko it quite clear that the second ooint<br />
which I have been inaking is firmly based, I ronind honourable<br />
mInrnibers once more that I and later my collen: ue, the Minister for<br />
Zxternal Affairs ( Sir Garfield Biarwick), i: made statenoints in which<br />
we indicated, not for the first time, our views on this matter.<br />
. o stat d where we stood on such mattors as peace being the groat<br />
principle adopted by the United Nations, no threats, no xacd<br />
force, ond the assurances that had been given to us. We stated,<br />
secondly, our belief that this matter jught to be discussed<br />
peacefully and negotiated betwoen the Netherlands and Indonesia.<br />
If the Oppsition disapprovos of that, it is new to no. I can<br />
remomber the tiCe when Mr. Chifley, forimer Prime Minister whose<br />
name honourable nonbors ' opposit invoke, and cnother frimor leader<br />
in the porson of Dr. Evatt boastod clearly, and I thought proper: ly,<br />
that this was a matter betwoon the Notherlands and Indonesia.<br />
Apparently all that is gone. Those gentlemen must have turned out<br />
to be wrong. We on this side of the House have stated our views. We<br />
ha.' e stated that we desire a peaceful settlement, that we are not<br />
a party principal and that we will respect an agreement made<br />
freely and not under threat of war. But above all things, we<br />
stand for the principle of self-determination of the future of the<br />
Papuan people whether they are in -West New Guinea or East New<br />
Guinea. These views have been stated by us here, in the Press<br />
and in the United Nations. They have been debated all around the<br />
world. Our vieis are quite well knoim. Does the Loader of the<br />
Opposition quarrel with them?<br />
Mr. Leslie I do not know.<br />
Mr. Menzies Thank you. I do not know clearly. If he does not<br />
quarrel with them, what is he quarrelling about? If these views<br />
constitute the policy of the Labour Party, what is the uproar<br />
about? If they are not part of the policy of the Labour Party,<br />
let honourable members opposite rise and plainly and<br />
unambiguously say so. Let them snap out of this compromising coma<br />
into which they have Iallon, rise one by one even my friend the<br />
Leader of the Opposition and say whro they stand on this<br />
matter and what they would do that we have not done,<br />
The only answer that comes up as repetitively as the<br />
beat of a metronome in the spoech of the Leader of the Opposition<br />
is " The United Nations, the United Nations, the United Nations".<br />
Does he know that this matter has been before the United Nations?<br />
Does not he know that if this matter were taken to the Security<br />
Council a dozen times the Soviet jnlon would veto whatevor view<br />
was taken. Does not he know that this matter has boon the subject<br />
of resolution after resolution in the General Assembly? This idea<br />
of transferring your burden to the United Nations is no policy at<br />
all. It becomes worse than no policy at all if, as the honourable<br />
gentioman did, one sets about joering at what he calls the oower<br />
blocs and log-rolling campaigns by interested parties. Of course<br />
honourable members will understand that that is a referonco to<br />
our old-fashioned belief that when it comes to peace or war in<br />
this part of tohe world Great BErhietraei n and the United Statcs<br />
stand is of vital moment to this country. According to honourae<br />
members opposite this is old-fashioned stuff. In theioir view we<br />
should not be interested in Twhat a describes as power--blocs.<br />
Thank God we have a powo:. bloc in the .! orld. It will be a poor<br />
day for Australia if, in the name of somo thooroticel idea, about<br />
the United N-_ tions, we abandon our lines of communication with,<br />
to repeat my own phr:: s, our reat and powerful friends. No<br />
country in the world more than ours : x-ds great and powerful<br />
friends. I am all for them, I biave that the people of<br />
Australia are for them, and I believe that any policy pursued by<br />
us which would put at risk our friendship with those friends<br />
would be rejocted by evry scnsible person in tho cuntry. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
