<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8726</transcript-id>
    <title>PARTIAL TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ KEATING MP, DOORSTOP, ST VINCENT DE PAUL CENTRE, TOWNSVILLE, 15 NOVEMBER 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/11/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008726.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL: 16. Nov. 92 11: 39 No. 008 P. 03/ 03<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
P'A1TIAL TRANSC I PT OF TH-E PRIME MINISITPM, TJlE 11ON P J KEATING<br />
MP, DOORSTOP1, ST VINCENT W, P'AUL CENIH I, T0WNSVIThlE, 1s<br />
NOVEM1WR 1" 92<br />
E P1~ IROO1) COPY<br />
J: Aire you capitalising on problems in V'ictoria o1 thc K~ enne~ tt Gciverranena?<br />
PM: The Kewlett Government has got no re'spocl for its community. It's taking away<br />
b&amp;. nieftt that people have 4eemed o\, ur a e" nTuy, not ncgotiating dhem away but takinS<br />
them, away in the dead of night by legiglation. They tiever had the courage to mention<br />
Ithem in an clection caimpaign. So when G( 3ovvnixnerfs decide to do those sorts of<br />
things they forfeit commuunity regard.<br />
J: Do you think industial actionu shold spread ouigift of Victotia?<br />
PM;-Apparently Mr Howard has 4. aid today th~ at hu endories the Kennett ( ovonnment14<br />
industrial-relations poli~ y s-ei thoef aclw ays did, What thu Konnen Government<br />
har, Ls a policy of stealth theyVe crept up) on pwplc in the middle of the night without<br />
telling them. This naturally is sending very ' bad signals across the wholt; of Ihv,<br />
woi1kforce of Nbs counrtry, who are worried about their terms and -; Mditions of<br />
eniployrnent ' Ibis is not an unnatral thing.<br />
I: Arc the unions; actingj politically in flexing their musclus!<br />
P1M: If the unions are politically flexing their muscles, it's niothing likc the political mus. clcflexing<br />
that Mr Ketuiett is doing. Ile is aiwiing entirely politically In thoend,<br />
( hovernmcnti when they securc. a majotity in the t'artianient, don't get the rioht to war<br />
14% ng down unless there's conutnunity &amp; iappor1 for it. There's boen no community<br />
support for this soit of policy. tIhey are garnering, they are taking mom than tht<br />
mandate gAvc theml. so of crourc naturay thce is a public reaction.<br />
J: Would you be prepared to suppofl national IndustiiM atioun?<br />
PM: Ill wee what cone of it. This 4itpute has becn made by Mr Kenneit, . ot by us.<br />
We'vt; had a deca&amp; e long break out of industrial pcace.-It's boon upset by the Liber<br />
Party of Australiz. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
