<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4705</transcript-id>
    <title>ZIONIST COUNCIL OF VICTORIA, 30TH INDEPENDENCE DAY OF THE STATE OF ISRAEL, 10 MAY 1978</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/05/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004705.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EfIBUGO: _ Ui4TLJELYERY<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 10 MAY 1978_<br />
ZIONIST COUNCIL OF VICTORIA<br />
INDEPENDENCE DAY OF THE STATE OF ISRAEL<br />
It is a very great honour for me to participate in this<br />
celebration of Israel's 30th Independence Day.<br />
It is just over a year ago since I last addressed a part of<br />
Melbourne's Jewish Community at the opening of the Sephardi<br />
Synagogue and Community Centre. On that occasion, I quoted<br />
the following words from Gad. Ben-Meir's invitation. " The<br />
significance of the achievement lies not in * the size or splendour of<br />
the. centre, but in its being an expression of the opportunity<br />
our free country offers its citizens to maintain their age-old<br />
traditions and their religious and cultural individuality".<br />
Much the same can be said of Israel. As a state, it is in fact<br />
small, but it stands in today's world as a beacon of democracy<br />
and freedom and its existence affords its people the opportunity<br />
and freedom to maintain their age-old traditions.<br />
At the time Israel was recreated, the world had just experienced<br />
a war demonstrating the depths of man's capacity for<br />
inhumanity. The crimes against the Jewish people, the crimes<br />
against humanity perpetrated by the monstrous Nazi Regime,<br />
were one element in arousing the nations of the world to accept<br />
the age-old Jewish dream of a return to Zion.<br />
There were other elements. I think of the pioneering work of<br />
those who had been returning to Israel since the end of the<br />
last century, returning not just to die there as had been done so<br />
often in the last two thousand years, but to live there and<br />
make the land live again as it had in biblical times. In the<br />
aftermath of the war many of the surviving European Jews turned<br />
their eyes towards Israel.<br />
Although it was the U. N. which gave international standing to<br />
the Jewish State it was the courage and creativity of its modern<br />
pioneers which brought Israel into being. They made Israel a<br />
nation whose greatest resource is its people and their two<br />
thousand year old dream a dream whose realization we have been<br />
privileged to witness. / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
The Jews who emigrated to Israel and those who were born<br />
there are not however . the only ones who have made a<br />
contribution to Israel. Australian Jews, too, have played<br />
their part in building the State of Israel and in providing<br />
it with the material and moral sinews of survival. This<br />
commitment to Israel has in no way qualified the commitment<br />
to Australia.<br />
Australian Jews have found in Australia the freedom from<br />
oppression that is the right of all men and women, regardless<br />
of race,, religion, and culture; they have excelled in all<br />
areas of Australian life.<br />
The Jewish community has been a major force in this society<br />
creating a network of synagogues, schools and welfare<br />
organizations which have contributed to the well-being of our<br />
whole society. You have enriched this country, just as you<br />
have contributed to Israel.<br />
Australian in turn, has not stood by as a spectator in the<br />
momentous events which have shaped the formation and survival of<br />
the' State of Israel. The Australian Government reflecting<br />
the wishes of its people, actively supported Israel's creation.<br />
Since the afternoon of the 14th of May, 1948, when David Ben Gurion<br />
stood in the Tel Aviv Museum and proclaimed the establishment of<br />
the State of Israel, Australia has had a firm commitment to Israel's<br />
right to exist and to enjoy full international rights.<br />
My Government's support for Israel is clear. We have resisted<br />
attempts to exclude Israel from U. N. activities. We have rejected<br />
the repugnant attempts to link Xionism with racism. We will<br />
continue to do so.<br />
Much has happened in this thirtieth year of Israel's existence.<br />
The most momentous event was, of course, President Sadat's<br />
visit to Jerusalem, where he addressed the Knesset and renewed<br />
his pledge that Israel and Egypt should no longer attempt to<br />
settle their differences by war.<br />
In that one visit Israel achieved the implicit recognition of<br />
a major Arab nation. and new and exhilirating prospects of real<br />
and lasting peace.<br />
Australia welcomed President Sadat's courageous initiative<br />
because it represented the first real breakthrough in 30 years<br />
of continual warfare. It opened a new path which Israel has<br />
always wanted but which had hitherto seemed inaccessible; the<br />
path to negotiation. I have said repeatedly that the only<br />
future in the Middle East lies in negotiation. </p>
<p>-3-<br />
The alternative of war has been with us for three decades.<br />
It has solved nothing, it can solve nothing.<br />
In its first thirty years, modern Israel has demonstrated its<br />
courage, its capacity to survive against the odds, to achieve<br />
many things despite the threat of destruction, but the costs<br />
of the constant struggle for survival have been great.<br />
The opportunity is at hand for the threat to be lifted so that<br />
Israel may turn its full energies to even greater achievements.<br />
I wish the State of Israel and the people of the Middle East<br />
a fruitful, and above all, a peaceful future.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
