<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6131</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/06/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006131.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
ACTING PRVIE MIN STER<br />
FOR MEDIA 8 JUNE 1983<br />
The Acting Prime Minister, Mr Bowon, today affirmed the<br />
Government's commitment to the detailed development of the<br />
program of national and international events proposed by the<br />
Australian Bicentennial Authority for the celebration of<br />
Australia's Bicentenary in 1988.<br />
He said the celebration of the Bicentenary had received strong<br />
bipartisan support in the past and he hoped that this ' ould<br />
continue. Mr Bowen emphasised, however, that while the previous<br />
Government's commitment of $ 166 million ( at July 1982 prices)<br />
for the 1988 program would stand, there was at this stage no<br />
commitment to individual items in the proposed national and<br />
international program which had been developed by The Australian<br />
Bicentennial Authority.<br />
The emphasis would be on items of lasting benefit to the community<br />
and the matter would be subject to consideration by the<br />
Government in early 1984 following further development and costing<br />
by The Australian Bicentennial Authority and widespread<br />
consultation with the community and interest groups.<br />
In the further development of the Program, the Authority has been<br />
requested to give particular emphasis to Aboriginal involvemnent<br />
and to aspects of concern to women.<br />
The Authority has also been requested to review the program to<br />
examine the auestion of Commonwealth support for the participation<br />
of local government and community groups in the Bicentenary.<br />
Government Departments and Authorities have. been requested to<br />
work closely with the Authority in the development and<br />
implementation of the program. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
