<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4414</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S ADDRESS TO THE ROYAL COMMONWEALTH SOCIETY, LONDON, 3 JUNE 1977</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/06/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004414.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
F 77/ 131<br />
FOR PRESS<br />
PRIME MINISTER'S ADDRESS TO THE ROYAL COMMONWEALTH SOCIETY, LONDON<br />
3 JUNE 1977<br />
I am grateful for the opportunity to speak to you today, just five<br />
days before the 1977 Commonwealth Heads of Government meeting opens<br />
at Lancaster House. It will be the first time that I will have<br />
attended one of these meetings. No doubt, I will be better equipped<br />
to speak about the Commonwealth Heads of Government meeting after it<br />
is over. But as so often happens, it is the demands of the itinerary<br />
rather than logic which determines the order of these things.<br />
Perhaps from the start I should make it clear where the Australian<br />
Government stands in respect to the Commonwealth of Nations. I<br />
know there has, in the recent past, been some disappointment at<br />
Australia's apparent reluctance and coolness towards the modern<br />
Commonwealth. My Government, by contrast with the past, takes a<br />
positive constructive approach to the Commonwealth association.<br />
The Commonwealth obviously has its limitations, but within those<br />
limitations it has the scope and the potential to play a distinctive<br />
part in world affairs.<br />
The members of this society must have heard millions of words on<br />
this subject, expressing attitudes towards the Commonwealth ranging<br />
from the reverent to the sceptical. I intend to add a few more on<br />
Australia's perspective on the Commonwealth and international affairs.<br />
This perspective seeks to be as realistic and purposeful as possible.<br />
It does not equate realism with a fatalistic acceptance of things<br />
as they are. Far from it. But it does accept that progress can only<br />
be made on the basis of an objective appraisal of reality. It<br />
recognises that the golden age of international peace and security<br />
still evades our grasp super power rivalries persist; nations<br />
still resort to the threat and use of force; human rights are still<br />
flagrantly violated in many areas; problems of basic human deprivation<br />
-starvation, disease, illiteracy and over-population continue<br />
to affront the conscience of the world.<br />
Given the composition of the Commonwealth, these problems are acutely<br />
relevant to our forthcoming meeting. Power in the material sense<br />
military and economic strength, population, access to sources of<br />
energy and raw materials still remains the major factor of<br />
international affairs. / But </p>
<p>But realism requires that we recognise that power is not based<br />
only on material resources. Power also flows from courageous and<br />
imaginative leadership, from the ability to articulate mankind's<br />
deepest aspirations, and to inspire people to confront great challenges<br />
with purpose and determination. In this respect, the Commonwealth of<br />
Nations has a significant potential. In a period where most organisations<br />
are linked by common ideology, regional and economic interests,<br />
the Commonwealth appears to some as an anachronistic relic of Empire.<br />
To others, as a puzzlingly diffuse institution. The bonds that once<br />
united the Commonwealth: a common monarchy; a common citizenship; the<br />
Westminster system; the contacts fostered by the British Empire; a<br />
common language; the great tradition and practice of English common law;<br />
have either disappeared or are receding into the background. Yet, the<br />
Commonwealth has survived. It has done so because, transcending its<br />
origins, it has developed as an autonomous grouping of nations. A<br />
few decades ago, it consisted of a few white countries it was tightlyknit,<br />
homogenous and essentially British. Now with a membership of<br />
three dozen, it is one of the largest international associations.<br />
Homogenity has given way to diversity. The dominant role of one nation<br />
has been supplanted by an egalitarian relationship. A largely Anglo-<br />
Saxon group has become a truly multiracial group. The very diversity<br />
of the Commonwealth, which some regard as a source of weakness, is in<br />
fact the key source of its strength. There can be no doubt of the<br />
Commonwealth's significance. It is manifest in the Commonwealth Heads<br />
of Government meeting. In terms of the number of nations involved, and<br />
the population that is represented by them; and in terms of gen'uine<br />
diversity of race, of regional representation, of size, and of stage<br />
of economic development, it has few rivals.<br />
The Commonwealth Heads of Government meeting is a unique occasion on<br />
which up to three dozen leaders take more than a week from their normal<br />
duties to attend. They attend not because of habit but because the<br />
meeting provides an unparalleled opportunity for extensive discussion<br />
of vital issues.<br />
The Commonwealth provides. the opportunity to test our views in a forum<br />
in which nearly all interests are represented in which there is a<br />
greater intimacy and equality than exists in the United Nations; and<br />
where the rivalries engendered by the presence of superpowers are more<br />
distant. Because meetings do not try to reach binding decisions, members are not<br />
obliged to adopt hard negotiating positions. We can enjoy the rare<br />
privilege of talking to each other, not at each other. We can derive<br />
the greatest value from personal contact between Heads of Government<br />
aimed at exploring and understanding each other' s viewpoints.<br />
The Commonwealth has shown a remarkable resilience and capacity to<br />
adapt to change, both in the international environment, and in-its<br />
own nature, function, and range of concerns. Given the magnitude of<br />
softe recent changes and the diversity of nations and cultures<br />
represented in the Commonwealth, survival is no mean achievement.<br />
Survival, however, is not enough. / The. real<br />
2 </p>
<p>-3<br />
The real question is " Survival for what?" There are many things<br />
the Commonwealth can achieve if we, its members, have the will and<br />
determination not to submit to the effects that habit,. routine<br />
and repetition can have on our enthusiasm and energy. We can more<br />
effectively use the Commonwealth not by trying to convert it into<br />
something it is not; not by altering its essential characteristics;<br />
but by using them more extensively. For example, it may be that we<br />
can become more effective if we can expand our consultations on a<br />
regional basis as a supplement to plenary Commonwealth Heads of<br />
Government meetings.<br />
Before coming to London, I consulted with Commonwealth leaders in<br />
the South East Asia-South Pacific region in order to gain the benefit<br />
of their views before the Commonwealth Heads of Government meeting.<br />
My aim was not to develop an Asia-Pacific Commonwealth " bloc", not<br />
to pursue narrowly conceived interests or compete with other groups.<br />
Rather, it was to identify common ground and possible areas of<br />
disagreement, and to get the maximum benefit from the Commonwealth's<br />
tradition of informal discussion.<br />
I found the discussions most useful, and I think there may be value<br />
in expanding the process of informal regional consultations among<br />
Commonwealth countries. I see no need, however, for new standing<br />
bodies nor for a regular timetable or fixed attendance for such consultations.<br />
Meetings should take place only as the need for them is<br />
identified, and attendance should be determined by the interest of<br />
members in the subject under discussion. In this way, the Commonwealth<br />
could come to play a valuable role As a channel of communication<br />
within the region and between the region and the wider international<br />
community. I stress that I am not thinking in terms of concerted policies,<br />
which would be inappropriate and completely unworkable. My main<br />
concern is that the Commonwealth should realise its potential as<br />
the generator of ideas and initiative; as the promoter of a spirit<br />
of urgency and determination in approaching critical problems; as<br />
an example and as a goal, both to its other members and other<br />
countries. I now turn to two issues which will be very prominent on our agenda<br />
next week: Southern Africa and the new international economic order.<br />
Southern Africa is the most pressing area for action to secure human<br />
rights. Policies based on the false and pernicious premise of one<br />
race's superiority over another, one race's right to subjugate another,<br />
are the most flagrant violation of fundamental human decency. They<br />
offend the moral sense of every person, every nation, concerned about<br />
the dignity and quality of man. Their continuance diminishes the<br />
humanity of every one of us. Apartheid cannot succeed even in terms<br />
of its own logic. A policy that pretends to foster equal social<br />
development but which involves permanent separation of the races<br />
and imposes permanent political inferiority on one race will not,<br />
and cannot, succeed. The proponents of apartheid claim that they<br />
are pursuing policies of educational and economic equality. Even<br />
if this claim is taken at face value, apartheid must fail. The more<br />
/ people </p>
<p>.4-<br />
people achieve educational and economic equality, the more they will<br />
reject political inferiority. There should be a rapid move towards<br />
majority rule in Zimbabwe. A failure to achieve this and achieve it<br />
quickly will most likely lead to disaster.<br />
All reasonable people believe that the overwhelming majority of<br />
African leaders despite their abhorrence of racism still want<br />
an equitable solution based on negotiation and reason. Resolving<br />
the problem by violence would leave scars not only on the participants<br />
in the violence but on all the nations of Africa for as long as we<br />
could see into the future. We must not allow racism to poison<br />
international politics in the way that religious fanatacism poisoned<br />
them in earlier centuries.<br />
The Commonwealth's present composition and its past associations<br />
place the Commonwealth in a good position, to make it clear that<br />
there is no international support for policies that seek to maintain<br />
the superiority of one race over another.<br />
Apart from the other grounds on which racism can be condemned, it has<br />
prevented single minded attention being paid to the real and intractable<br />
problems of economic development, and the material relief of human<br />
suffering. No Government can turn its back on these problems. No<br />
one can assume that they are somebody else's responsibility.<br />
Developing countries must examine whether the best use is being made<br />
of their resources. Developed countries must accept the necessity of<br />
a process of adjustment. In this respect, aid, trade and commodity<br />
policies need to be examined. These are among the issues encapsulated<br />
in developing countries' call for a new international economic order.<br />
The Commonwealth has a continuing and substantive involvement in these<br />
issues, of the Commonwealth's thousand million people, nearly 90% are<br />
from developing countries, and a large proportion of these are countries<br />
where per capita incomes are ' extremely low. The Commonwealth should<br />
promote constructive responses to the more pressing economic concerns of<br />
the international community. These concerns have been staring us in the<br />
face for years. Politicians and officials have spoken about them in<br />
meeting after meeting. But talk can become a substitute for commitment<br />
for really facing problems. What is needed is a real determination to do<br />
something about inequality and deprivation. Aid is one issue which has<br />
for many years figured as a substantive element in relations between<br />
members of the Commonwealth. Recently, the form and terms of aid have<br />
become the subject of close scrutiny. This is partly because the problem'<br />
of aid and debt are interlinked and the debt burden of developing countri<br />
is a pressing issue. This is one area in which change is possible, and<br />
in this respect Australia's record is relevant. Our aid is provided<br />
overwhelmingly in the form of grants. Consequently, it has not contributed<br />
to developing countries debt problems. Given the seriousness of<br />
the debt burden of many developing nations 0it might be desirable that<br />
others consider adopting the same policy. Similarly, consideration shoul<br />
be given to the untying of aid. Untied aid is more beneficial to the<br />
recipient than tied aid which sometimes is little more than an indirect<br />
subsidy to donors own industries. Even where circumstances dictate that<br />
aid must be in the form of a loan, there may be scope for other donors<br />
at their own initiative, to liberalise the terms of their aid, including<br />
official development assistance loans. / Another </p>
<p>Another important aid development is the agreement reached at the<br />
Conference on International Economic Co-operation ( CIEC) to establish<br />
a special action' programme designed to alleviate the balance of<br />
payments difficulties of developing countries. The principal developed<br />
nations will provide a total of $ 1 billion in the form of quickly<br />
disbursable aid. Australia regards this programme as important and<br />
will contribute to it.<br />
The transfer of resources between rich and poor is only one aspect of<br />
the developed world's response to the problems of development. The<br />
problems developing nations have in gaining access to the markets of<br />
developed countries are at least of equal importance. Many developing<br />
countries are vitally dependent on the earnings of a limited range of<br />
commodity exports. Restrictions on market access and sharp fluctuations<br />
in export earnings seriously erode the developing countries' capacity<br />
to pursue appropriate development strategies.<br />
Australia can understand the problems faced by developing countries<br />
that want stability for their agricultural commodities and reliable<br />
access to markets. We have felt the impact of the combined effect of<br />
our products being excluded from traditional European markets and the<br />
effects of excessive E. E. C. subsidisation of produce on our exports to<br />
third markets.<br />
Closely tied to the problems of market access is that of commodity price<br />
stabilisation. It is of the utmost importance to ensure that prices<br />
are maintained at a level fair to producers and equitable to consumers.<br />
Accordingly, the highest priority should be attached to successfully<br />
concluding the current round of negotiations for individual commodity<br />
agreements. These negotiations have in recent months been overshadowed<br />
by debate on the establishment of a common fund. This is a complex<br />
and important issue which deserves close scrutiny. Should such a<br />
fund be established and we support this in principle care must<br />
be taken that it preserves the autonomy of individual commodity<br />
agreements. A fund may also take due account of the appropriateness<br />
and feasibility of buffer stock financing in respect of the individual<br />
commodities involved. Any common fund which may be established should<br />
be workable and appropriate to its purpose.<br />
Finally, there is one issue more compelling and more fundamental in<br />
human terms than any other that of malnutrition and in some cases<br />
outright starvation. It is an intolerable situation that some<br />
of the third world's children are undernourished. There are various<br />
approaches to the problem. The International Fund for Agricultural<br />
Development ( IFAD) is directed to a significant expansion of agricultural<br />
production in the developing countries. Implementation of the<br />
1974 World Food Conference resolutions will ensure increased food aid<br />
flows to the most needy. Improving trading arrangements for grains,<br />
for example through the successful negotiation of a new International<br />
Wheat Agreement, will create the basis for a more predictable and<br />
reliable market in foodstuffs.<br />
Action on all these fronts is necessary. Here the Commonwealth<br />
should also be able to make a distinctive contribution. Both food<br />
surplus and food deficit countries are represented among its members.<br />
Their experience should be pooled in a common effort to seek to<br />
/ identify </p>
<p>-6-<br />
identify the major factors that need to be taken into account<br />
in improving national and global food security.<br />
The magnitude of the problems I have referred to could easily<br />
provoke despair. They must not do so. What is required is commitment,<br />
determination and imagination. There are many developing<br />
countries including several Commonwealth members which have achieved<br />
sustained and impressive economic expansion. Their success reminds<br />
us that for some at least the international economic system has not<br />
proved to be a barrier to growth. It is also a reminder that the<br />
division between developed and developing countries is not fixed<br />
and unchanging.<br />
If the Commonwealth is to convince the world of its relevance and<br />
vitality, it must do so in terms of its contribution to the major<br />
issues of our time. It is well equipped to do so. In the last quarter<br />
century the Commonwealth has demonstrated its resilience and flexibility.<br />
It is now time to demonstrate our capacity to make a<br />
constructive, positive contribution to resolving the economic<br />
and social problems which are emerging as the dominant ones of<br />
the next quarter century.<br />
I hope that I have said enough to give an insight to current<br />
Australian thinking on the Commonwealth of Nations, and to identify<br />
some of the opportunities that I believe the association offers to<br />
help create a better world. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
