<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1590</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: AUSTRALIAN CONSULTANTS WITH U.N. CONTRACT - (STATEMENT BY MR. J. MCEWEN, ACTING PRIME MINISTER AND MINISTER FOR TRADE AND INDUSTRY)+</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/05/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001590.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
S8JUN1~ 96<br />
FOR PRESS: * 410<br />
k/ BRAR,<br />
AUSTRAIANPJ CONSULTANTS WIN U. N. CONTRACT<br />
( Statement by Mr. J. McEwen-, Acting Prime Minister and Minister<br />
for Trade and Industry)<br />
An Australian firm had been awarded a large United Nations contract<br />
to act as consultants during preparation of a 5A4.6 million<br />
master-plan for intensive urban and industrial development of<br />
Singapore, Mr. J. McEwen, Acting Prime Minister and Minister for<br />
Trade and Industry, announced today.<br />
The firm, Crooks, Michell, Peacock and Stewart of Chatswood, N. S. W.,<br />
was believed to be the first Australian group to win a contract<br />
of this magnitude and of this type.<br />
Mr. McEwen said the contract, awarded in the face of strong overseas<br />
competition, particularly from Euarope and North America, highlighted<br />
the standing of Australian professional consultants. It underlined<br />
the significance of the Government sponsored Mission which<br />
recently surveyed prospects for Australian professional consultants<br />
in South East Asia and the Middle East.<br />
The number of Australian firms registered for consultancy work<br />
with the United Nations and the World Bank had increased rapidly<br />
over the last two years and numbered 32 at present. It was<br />
hoped confidently that more contracts for work in South East<br />
Asia would be won by Australian consultants.<br />
Mr. MoEwen said the work associated with the first contract<br />
would complement Australia's continuing drive to become one of<br />
the major suppliers of goods and services to South East Asia.<br />
Crooks, Michell, Peacock and Stewart would collect and analyse<br />
data relevant to all aspects of planning, develep Singapore's<br />
planning departments and train personnel to take over comprehensive<br />
city planning and conduct extensive surveys. Such surveys would<br />
;. over community environments, activities, goals, values and<br />
economic -problems. Traffic and transport studies to enable </p>
<p>-2-<br />
effective future development would also be undertaken.<br />
The firm would be associated in its work by up to four<br />
universities, " The University of New South Wales would provide a<br />
traffic consultant, Professor R. Blunden, also research<br />
facilities at the N. S. W. Institute of Traffic and<br />
Highway Research.<br />
The University of Sydney would provide two consultants<br />
and an urban geographer from its Department of Town<br />
and Country Planning.<br />
" Macquarie and Queensland Universities would provide<br />
assistance where required.<br />
Mr. McEwen said most overseas consultants received active support<br />
from their Governments in efforts to participate in such<br />
projects and the Department of Trade and Industry was prepared<br />
also to assist firms interested in such export activity.<br />
Canberra, A. C. T.<br />
May, 1967 39/ 67T </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
