<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>381</transcript-id>
    <title>SECOND READING SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R G MENZIES IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES, CANBERRA, WEDNESDAY 18TH OCTOBER 1961 - WESTERN AUSTRALIA (BEEF CATTLE ROADS) BILL 1961</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/10/1961</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000381_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SECOND READING SPEECH<br />
by<br />
THE PRIE MINISTER. THE RT. HON. R. G. DENZIES<br />
IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES. CANBERRA, WEDNESDAY. 18TH OCTOBER. 1961<br />
WE-STERN AUSTRALIA ( BEEF CA1TTLE ROADS) BILL, 1961<br />
The purpose of this Bill'is to seek the approval of the Parliament to<br />
a grant of financial aasistance to the State of Western Australia for the<br />
carrying out of certain road and bridge works in the northern part of that<br />
State, connected with the transport by road of beef cattle.<br />
In introducing a similar measure relating to roads in Queensaand I<br />
mentioned the several steps being taken by the Government to assist in the<br />
development of roads across the north of Australia. I referred also to the<br />
importance of general development and expansion of the beef industry, and the<br />
significant role which roads could play. I need not repeat what I then said,<br />
as the remarks have general application to Itestern Australia as well as to<br />
QIueensland and the Northern Territory.<br />
The assistance proposed for Western A-ustralia is a grant of<br />
œ 500, 000 in respect of expenditure by the State in the financial year 1961/ 62<br />
on two specified roads and two specified bridges in the Kimberleys. The four<br />
projects are inter-related in that both roads lead from beef cattle areas to<br />
the meat works and port at Wyndham ( from Nicholson in one case, from HallIs<br />
Creek via Turkey Creek in the other), while the two bridges will allow the<br />
Wyndham-Nicholson road to be taken across the Ord and Dunham Rivers and so<br />
eliminate an existing low level crossing over the Ord, which puts this road out<br />
of commission in times of flood, Incidentally, the bridges ( one of which is to<br />
be superimposed on the Ord River Dam at Bandicoot Bar, which itself is being<br />
constructed with the assistance of Commonwealth funds), and the improved road<br />
between the Ord Dam and Wyndham, will be of great assistance in the development<br />
of the areas opened up for settlement by the Ord project.<br />
When we discussed the question of roads with the Western Australian<br />
Government, we were impressed by the amount of self help in developing<br />
communications in the north being undertaken by the State from its existing<br />
road funds. As I announced at the time we agreed to ossist the State, the<br />
Commorwealth grant is " matching corresponding provisions by Western Australia<br />
in relation to roads in the Kimberleys". This concept is written into the<br />
Bill, which requires the State to undertake to spend not less than œ 500,000<br />
from other sources on road works in the northern part of the State ( d-, fined as<br />
north of 20 degrees of south latitude) during 1961/ 62. I might add that this<br />
is by no means an onerous provision, as the inforrmation provided by the State<br />
indicated that its 1961/ 62 programme of road works included an alloca-tion of<br />
muro than œ lmil-lion to that area, including over Z800,000 in the Kimberleys.<br />
The detailed arrangement is that the Commoriealth will provide 50% of<br />
expenditure on the two bridges in 1961/ 62 ( estimated at œ 320,000, calling for<br />
a Commoriealth contribution of œ 160,000), and the whole of the expenditure,<br />
also in 1961/ 62, on improving the two roads. If the expenditure on the<br />
bridges accords with the estimate, this will mean that Pœ 340,000 is available<br />
for the road works. However, within the agreed limit of œ, 500,000 we have not<br />
specified expenditure limits on either of the two groups.<br />
I might mention also that the availability of the Commorw4ealth grant<br />
will allow the State to release, for other road works in the area, the funds<br />
already allocated in its programme to the two roads, plus half of the amount<br />
allocated to the construction of the two bridges.<br />
Other provisions in the Bill are similar o those in the Queensl~ and<br />
measure, including the power of approvasl of standarcls of design pr<br />
construdtion which the Treasurer may exercie<br />
Western Australia is receiving very substantial assistance from the<br />
Commowealth in its railway plans, which essentially will benefit the southern<br />
part of the State. This measure provides for a considerably smaller but<br />
nevertheless significant, grant of assistance for the development of the beef<br />
cattle industry in the far north.<br />
I commend the Bill to the House. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
