<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9540</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J.KEATING, MP WALTZING MATILDA CENTENARY CELEBRATIONS WINTON 6 APRIL 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/04/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009540.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
"* EMBARGOED UNTIL 8: 30PM**<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING, MP<br />
WALTZING MATILDA CENTENARY CELEBRATIONS<br />
WINTON 6 APRIL 1995<br />
This is a great honour. It is one to tell our grandchildren about: we were in the<br />
North Gregory Hotel when Australia celebrated the first performance of Waltzing<br />
Matilda 100 years ago.<br />
And we were all in evening dress. Which is something the swagman would have<br />
found amusing but maybe the squatter, the troopers and Banjo Paterson would<br />
have appreciated it.<br />
I'm sure they all would have liked the irony in it.<br />
It is a great pleasure to be here and to see for the second time in two days the<br />
spirit of rural Australia.<br />
I was in Bourke yesterday another place in the romance of the swag. And<br />
another place suffering the drought.<br />
Yesterday in Bourke the town was gathered for an extraordinary event an<br />
international marathon race from Bourke to Parramatta to raise money for the<br />
Fred Hollows Foundation.<br />
Fred Hollows is buried in Bourke and they celebrate his memory as a man who<br />
loved the bush and the values of the people who live there.<br />
His work was, in many ways, an extension of the old idea of mateship, and<br />
through it he lifted all our spirits and raised our goals.<br />
Here in Winton, in an altogether different way, these ceebrations are reminding<br />
us of the same things. </p>
<p>They are reminding us of the spirit of the bush and commemorating a song which<br />
has lifted our spirits for 100 years.<br />
There are no limits to the power of a good song.<br />
I read on the way up here that 10,000 people would be in Witon this weekend:<br />
so this has to be a very considerable boost to Winton as it struggles through the<br />
drought. You see, music has more than charms it has profound economic effects.<br />
In times like this it is not as good as rain, but it may well be the next best thing.<br />
Waltzing Matilda was born in a drought era of course, and it is not hard to imagine<br />
that this might have had some effect on the melancholy theme of the song. And<br />
there is equally no doubt that in all the varieties of hard times Waltzing Matilda<br />
has galvanised the spirit of counless Australians.<br />
If culture is that which defines a people, if it is the expression of their collective<br />
sentment, Waltzing Matilda sits at the centre of gI~ culture it's a well-spring of<br />
the national sentiment, a pool, a billabong.<br />
I suspect there is no one here who has not at some time, somewhere in the<br />
world, heard or remembered the tune and felt deeply affected by it<br />
I'm sure it has brought Australians home before they intended to, and given<br />
others the strength to stay away a bit longer. For a century it has caused<br />
Australian hearts to beat faster.<br />
I venture to say it has caused more smiles and tears, and more hairs to stand up<br />
on the backs of Australian necks than any other thing of three minutes duration in<br />
Australia's history.<br />
It has long been our unofficial national song. Not our anthem as I've said<br />
before, one can't sing too solemnly about a jumbuck. But Waltzing Matilda is<br />
Australia's song and it always will be.<br />
Think what it has withstood down the years. Wave after wave of American and<br />
British popular music. The cultural cringe and all that post-colonial posturing.<br />
The urbanisation of Australia which might have been expected to dilute the old<br />
bush sentiments. Mass immigration and multicultural Australia which changed<br />
the face and the fabric of our society.<br />
Watzing Matilda has endured them all. It has endured through wars and<br />
depressions, good years and bad. It has endured some terrible renditions by<br />
both local and overseas performers. </p>
<p>I don't think we should make it official and issue some kind of decree; but I think<br />
% w all know that Waltzing Matilda is at least as beloved as the anthem. It is to we<br />
Australians what Land of Hope and Glory is to the British, or AmerIca the<br />
Beautiful and God Bless America are to the people of the United States.<br />
Anid, entirely without prejudice to the status of Advance Australia Fair, we might<br />
sing Waltzing Matilda at a lot more public occasions than we presently do.<br />
I hope these celebrations serve as a bit of a trigger for this.<br />
I have no doubt that all through these celebrations people will be talking about<br />
why Waltzing Matilda endures. Why ft means so much to us.<br />
I know some will also be asking who the swagman was and what, therefore, the<br />
song was meant to signify. I won't be buying into the historical debate, but I<br />
suppose every Australian is entitled to say even obliged to say what the song<br />
means to him or her.<br />
I don't think I was the only Australian kid who wondered when he learned the<br />
words at school what sort of swagman is this? Jolly one minute, drowning<br />
himself the next?<br />
These questions about the psychology of the swagman have never had the<br />
weight of the social and political interpretations the ideological interpretations.<br />
Paterson's words describe a class struggle, and if ever there was a class struggle<br />
in Australia it was in the 1890s.<br />
Its not hard to see the song as an affirmation of the idea of the fair go, which still<br />
strikes a powerful chord in Australians. And may it always do so.<br />
It is also about freedom. The swagman is a free spirit.<br />
We can interpret Waltzing Matilda as a celebration of our rebellious nature, as<br />
part of the tradition which began with the convict rebellion at Castle Hill and runs<br />
all the way through Frank the Poet, the Eureka Stockade and Ned Kelly. We can<br />
think of the swagman's jump into the billabong as an Australian statement of<br />
liberty or death.<br />
But, the truth is, none of these things come into my mind when I hear it sung.<br />
They didn't come into my mind when the entire crowd gathered in Croke Park in<br />
Dublin sang it before the Gaelic football final when I was there two years ago. </p>
<p>I don't know what came into my mind then I think the experience emptied it of all<br />
rational thought. But afterwards I was aware of the extraordinary power of this<br />
song on an Australian's senses.<br />
All sorts of music can move us, but to hear Waltzing Matilda sung so fervently<br />
and beautifully by the people of another country 12,000 miles from home is to<br />
know that nothing can move us like our own song.<br />
It is to know that a national song is not something to be interpreted intellectually.<br />
When you hear it, you don't think about a political position, or social and<br />
psychological issues. You don't think about the historical context.<br />
What Waltzing Matilda tells us in an entirely uncomplicated way is that we are<br />
Australian. And it tells us in a way that I think is equally Australian in character it<br />
tells us without beating drums or waving flags, or pounding our chests. It tells us<br />
with a simple melody and a story, and a whimsical and ironic story at that.<br />
There is no national song I know of quite like it in the world.<br />
I'm sure what happened with Banjo Paterson and Waltzing Matilda happened in<br />
the realm of the spirit.<br />
I think he wrote a story to a tune which quite mysteriously in ways we'll never<br />
know picked up the spirit of the place as Awt as then; and, like the ghost of the<br />
swagman, it never died.<br />
And it touches us as a ghost might. As the spirit of the bush might.<br />
When we were kids the other line I think we used to wonder about was the one<br />
which says that " his ghost may be heard as you pass by the billabong". I confess<br />
to wondering what you would hear. What sort of noise would the old swagman<br />
make what does it sound like when you stuff a jumbuck in a tucker bag?<br />
It took me ages to realise that this was Banjo Paterson's whole trick the son is<br />
the ghost of the swagman, and a hundred years later we are hearing it as loud as<br />
ever. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
