<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3358</transcript-id>
    <title>ROYAL COMMISSION INTO HUMAN RELATIONSHIPS</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/08/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003358.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
4i AUSI K A<br />
PRIME MINISTER PRESS STATEMENT NO. 306<br />
21 August 1974<br />
ROYAL COMMISSION INTO HUMAN RELATIONSHIPS<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr. Whitlam, today announced<br />
the appointment of the Royal Commission into Human Relationships.<br />
The establishment of this Commission follows a<br />
resolution of the House of Representatives in September 1973<br />
that an inquiry of this nature should be undertaken.<br />
The Chairman of the Commission is the Hon. Elizabeth<br />
Evatt, a Deputy President of the Australian Conciliation and<br />
Arbitration Commission, and the other members are the Most<br />
Rev. Felix Arnott, Anglican Archbishop of Brisbane and<br />
Metropolitan of the Province of Queensland, and Anne Deveson,<br />
a prominent Sydney journalist.<br />
The Commission will commence its task immediately.<br />
However, it is not expected that Justice Evatt's commitment<br />
to the Chairmanship will be full-time until early next year.<br />
Mr. Whitlam said that the Commission's task is to<br />
look into and report upon the external pressures existing in<br />
our society which place a stress upon relationships between<br />
people. The terms of reference include such matters as sex<br />
education and family planning, related medical training and<br />
services and the position of women in relation to these subjects.<br />
." These matters are relevant to the every day life of<br />
Australians and the Government considers that the establishment<br />
of the Commission will allow all interested parties to put their<br />
views freely and frankly. The interim reports to be presented<br />
by this Commission will enable us to identify those stresses<br />
which society places on individuals and relationships and the<br />
ultimate recommendations of the Commission will offer ways and<br />
means for the people of this country to be better able to meet<br />
the greater pressures arising from technological and social<br />
change which we find in the world around us."' </p>
<p>-2-<br />
" The three Commissioners are well suited to consider<br />
the matters under reference and I am confident that considerable<br />
benefit will derive from their inquiries."<br />
A copy of the terms of reference is attached.<br />
CANBERRA, A. C. T. </p>
<p>Royal Commission into Human Relationships<br />
Terms of Reference<br />
To inquire into and report upon the family, social,<br />
educational, legal and sexual aspects of raale and female<br />
relationships, so far as those matters are relevant to the<br />
powers and functions of the Australian Parliament and<br />
Government, including powers and functions in relation to<br />
the Territories: To g-ive particular emphasis to the concept of<br />
. responsible parenthood, to have regard to experience in other<br />
countries and to include in your inquiry the following aspects<br />
of the said matters:-<br />
the extent of relevant existing education programs,<br />
including sex education programs, and their<br />
effectiveness in promoting responsible sexual<br />
behaviour and providing a sound basis in the<br />
fundamentals of male and female relationships in<br />
the Australian social environment;<br />
the extent of relevant existing programs in medical<br />
schools and their adequacy to provide comprehensive<br />
medical training in contraceptive techniques, in the<br />
physical, psychological and sexual problems<br />
experienced by women in adapting to marriage and<br />
before, during and after menstruation, and in matters<br />
relating to pregnancy, fertility control, spontaneous<br />
and induced! nbortions nnd childbirth and to encourage<br />
acceptance by the medical profession of its </p>
<p>responsibilities in the field of contraceptive<br />
counselling;<br />
the provision, pdequacy and effectiveness of existing<br />
family planning facilities, educational and<br />
activational. informa~ tion on family planning,,, and<br />
methods of evaluation of all family planning techniques;<br />
the social., economic, psychological and medical<br />
pressures on women in determining whether to proceed<br />
with unplanned or unwanted pregnancies, h-aving regard.<br />
to: Ci) the rdnquacy of hou3ing, child-minding<br />
centres, pre-school centres, domestic<br />
azcsis tance for families and working mothers,<br />
ansi. stance to single parent families, other<br />
form. s of assistnnce'for mothers employed in<br />
industry, and adoption procedures;<br />
( ii) the disabilities of families with handicapped<br />
children; and<br />
( iii) the social status of women in the community;<br />
the social, psychological and medical results<br />
of terination of, or and failure to terminate<br />
such pregnancies;<br />
the adequacy Rnd offectivenes of existing medicolegal<br />
determinations in relation to termination of<br />
pregniancy, Lhe incid] ence of such terminations, the<br />
factors influencin' thei~ r occurrence, the adequacy<br />
of medical. training i~ n and evaluation of methods of </p>
<p>terminition, consultative rights of the family or<br />
other persons concerned and the adequacy and<br />
effectiveness of pregnancy support services; and<br />
any other matters in relation to the family, social,<br />
educational, legal and sexual aspects of male and<br />
female relationships to which the attention of the<br />
Commission is directed by the Prime Minister in the<br />
course of the inquiry.<br />
To make recommendations as to measures that are desirable<br />
with respect to the foregoing matters under existing or future<br />
laws of the Australian Parliament or of the Territories ( including<br />
laws providing for grants to the States) and to indicate whether<br />
these measures should be implemer ted through existing bodies or<br />
through government instrumentalities to be created.<br />
The Comrission may present interim reports on any aspect<br />
of its terms of reference. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
