<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>707</transcript-id>
    <title>OPENING OF THE VASEY HOUSING AUXILIARY HOMES AT MANNINGTREE ROAD, HAWTHORN, VICTORIA, ON 17TH MARCH, 1963. - SPEECH BY THE  PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/03/1963</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000707_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
OPENING OF TH; VASiX HOUSING AJXILIARX<br />
HOMES AT MANiINTJTRE ROAD, HAdTHORN,<br />
VICTORIA, ON 17TH MARCHi, 1963.<br />
Skeech by the Prime Minister,. the Rt. Hon. Sir Robert Menzies<br />
Mrs. Vasey and Ladies and Gentlemen t<br />
I don't really have to make a spLeech to you this<br />
afternoon because I have a variety of very good reasons for<br />
being delighted to be here. After all, this is in Manningtree<br />
Road and aboat two doors along many years ago, I used to be<br />
Lound hanging around with a rather sheepish look you know<br />
because my wife lived there. ( Laughter) Between her charms<br />
and the smell of the pittosporua hedge, I was a " goner".<br />
( Laughter) Well, that I think, is a very interesting thing<br />
to remember. And then I have been fascinated to feel that I was<br />
coming here this afternoon because something was going to be<br />
done on behalf of war widows, strongly promoted by a very<br />
famous war widow, Mrs. Yasey herself. ( Applause) I had the<br />
singular good fortune to be a friend of her late husband, one<br />
of the most famous fighting soldiers in the history of<br />
Australia. ( Applause) I always remember with some satisfaction,<br />
when I first went out of office I know you are all looking<br />
forward to the second occasion ( Laughter) but when i first<br />
went out of office I met George Vasey who was known as " Air"<br />
when we were at school together " Air" Vasey Allan. He<br />
addressed me in a public place in language that would have<br />
done credit to Mr. Rose at Alice Sprinks. ( laughter) And he<br />
wanted to know why I wasn't still Prime Minister. I remember<br />
this vividly because he was the only man who thought that way<br />
at that time. But Mrs. Vasoy, I would hate this occasion to go by<br />
without me saying on behalf of everybody here and hundreds<br />
and thousands of people who are not here, that your spirited<br />
and splendid work for war widows is one of the great things<br />
in the contemporary history of Australia. ( Applause) I am<br />
sure that you very frequently disagree with me, but I rwer<br />
disagree with you. ( Laughter)<br />
Now the third thing I want to say is that the pretty<br />
girl I was what's the old-fashioned expression? courting<br />
is that out of date now? in Manningtree Road made the grat<br />
error of marrying me and then in due course I became a politician<br />
and she survived that and so it went on. And one morning, years<br />
and years ago, sho said to me, " Xou know, you talk about social<br />
services but the one thin" that really matters is housing for<br />
old people. This is, I think, a great social problem." And for<br />
once in my life I listened to my wife husbands don't always,<br />
you know and so I gave it a little thought, and I finally<br />
went to my Cabinet and said, " Let's have some scheme under<br />
which housing can be provided not institutional housing, not<br />
these great barracks of places in which people feel they are<br />
numbers and not human beings but let's have some system under<br />
which houses can be built or flats or whatever it may be, so that<br />
people live as individuals and mingle socially as they would in<br />
their ordinary private days." 0 0 </p>
<p>2-<br />
And so we began this scheme and whatever ugly<br />
things may be stated in my obituary ( and 1 can well imagine<br />
them), I am hoping that even in some of the obituaries this<br />
great scheme may find a place; because we began by saying,<br />
with that almost mechanised reaction that governments have<br />
" pound for pound". It is like saying, " one man une vote."<br />
You know " pound for pound" and " we'll find a pound for a<br />
pound" and since then, as you know, we've improve3d on it.<br />
It is very interesting to realise that although this was a<br />
highly experimental matter when? 5t 6 7 years ago,<br />
somewhere around there, we have at present, commitments<br />
ourselves as a Government of œ 1614. And that means, if I am<br />
rightly informed by the learned clerks in my office, that<br />
when the present approved grants have been expended, there<br />
will have been accommodation provided for 1 5,000 people.<br />
( Applause). Well, of course, I can hardly refer lightly to<br />
the Vasey Housing Incorporated because to tell you the<br />
truth I was always more frightened of Mrs. Vasey than I<br />
was o1George ( Laughter) and she has a habit of getting<br />
her own way, and quite rightly. She is a charming pirate<br />
when it comes to dealing with governments. But the best<br />
proof of this is that when the current project is completed,<br />
Commonwealth grants in favour of this auxiliary will have<br />
totalled just on a quarter of a million pounds. Now this,<br />
I think, does some trifling credit to the Commonwealth,<br />
which usually gets so little that it might as well claim<br />
some, but above all things, it demonstrates the enormous<br />
energy and enthusiasm and imagination that has been put<br />
into this scheme. And this, of course, is quite right.<br />
I am getting along in years myself. I read<br />
in one of the Melbourne papers the other day when I was<br />
honoured by Her Majesty that perhaps this would be a good<br />
opportunity to make way for a younger man. ( Laughter)<br />
I think it is. Bring him along, please. Lt3ut, anyhow,<br />
we are all not any younger than we were, btI have felt for<br />
years now that I would hate, towards the end of my own<br />
life, whatever my circumstances might be, to be regarded<br />
as one of a regiment of people.<br />
I wonder if I might say something to you that<br />
I have said before, but not to you. ' When I was a schoolboy<br />
in Ballarat, I lived with an old 3cots grandmother who had<br />
restricted views, being a good Scots grandmother about life<br />
and about what I ought to do and all this kind ol' t*; ing,<br />
but over the road from the cottage in which she lived 3was<br />
the benevolent asylum, curtly known in those days as AThe<br />
Benev." Corrugated iron fence, horrible-looking old building<br />
everything rather musty, horrible as I now know, institutionalised<br />
all that has gone and nothing has done more to dispose<br />
of it than this great scheme and the work that people have<br />
done, Nobody in this pl~ ace will feel obliged or<br />
institutional in any way. This is the answer to it, that<br />
people should live in their own homes, whether those homes<br />
are houses or fiats or whatever they may be that they should<br />
live, as Mrs. Vasey beautifuilly put it, in li gnity and not<br />
oee * 9 e. e / 3 </p>
<p>3<br />
in dependence living their own lives,, living among their<br />
own friends, f'eeling that this is something which continues<br />
their citizenship of the country and which doesn't bring<br />
it to an end. Nov this to soe, is a marvellous thing. It<br />
has every human appeal In the world. And it is for that<br />
reason, above all things, that I am delighted to be here.<br />
Of course, I would be here if I were not delighted even,<br />
because I an a little nervous about Mrs. Vasey and so if<br />
she had said, " Nov come on my boy," I would have " come on,<br />
my boy," you see. % aughter<br />
But putting all that on one side, I am delighted<br />
to be here, because the great social problem of our times,<br />
the great social problem of the last ten years, fifteen<br />
years, has been to create in our social services an abiding<br />
and warm sense of humanity not of charity, but of loving<br />
kindness in the true sense, of friendliness. So that everybody,<br />
whether he's living or she's living in a great mansion<br />
on inherited riches or living here or living somewhere else,<br />
will feel that there is an atmosphere of humuan kindness and<br />
that we, the people of Australia, are not being charitable or<br />
condescending, but that we are friends together. Now this,<br />
to Me, is the great secret of this matter and it stands to<br />
the credit of Mrs. Vasey and all those who have worked with<br />
her that instead of regarding themselves as people who<br />
exercise pressure on governments which they do occasionally<br />
very courteously they have primarily regarded themselves<br />
as concerned with the continuing good life and good living<br />
of the women for whom they speak.<br />
The last thing I vant to say to you is wery now<br />
and then I hear arguments about widows and trying to classify<br />
widows I am not going into this business of classifying<br />
widows but for myself there is a very special place in my<br />
heart for women who are widows because their husbands served<br />
this country to the last extremity of death. This is something<br />
not to be forgotten. And it is because in my own imperfect<br />
way I have been remembering it that I was proud and honoured<br />
to come here today to declare this new group of buildings<br />
open and to observe the command of my old friend, Mrs. Vasey. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
