<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11083</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                   THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                   RADIO INTERVIEW WITH LEIGH MCCLUSKY AND                TONY PILKINGTON - RADIO 5AA, ADELAIDE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/03/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE................................................................................................................</p>
<p>LEIGH MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>Good morning to the Prime Minister</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Good morning, Tony, Leigh.</p>
<p>LEIGH MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, the ETSA sale.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes.</p>
<p>LEIGH MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>I see that you that you have now effectively weighed into the debate,</p>
<p> saying yes, it should be sold. What's prompted you to be drawn</p>
<p> on that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I was asked about it. And I believe that governments are better</p>
<p> out of commercial undertakings. There is plenty of evidence that consumers</p>
<p> benefit and there is a better deal all round if those sorts of assets</p>
<p> are privatised. So, I've had a very consistent view on this,</p>
<p> I've argued the cause of privatisation going right back to the</p>
<p> middle 1980s when it wasn't very fashionable and I've kept</p>
<p> steady support for the privatisation of government business undertakings</p>
<p> either at a Federal or State level.</p>
<p>LEIGH MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>I think many South Australians, though, feel historically very nervous</p>
<p> about selling off what they see as the family silver.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>They shouldn't because if you look at the experience of the United</p>
<p> Kingdom and the experience of Victoria, you will find the consumer</p>
<p> gets a better deal. And the idea that if you leave everything in State</p>
<p> ownership, you never have any break downs, you never have any failures</p>
<p> is disproved by a century of experience. I mean that is the greatest</p>
<p> furphy of all about the maintenance of public ownership, this idea</p>
<p> that if you keep it in public ownership you never have any break down.</p>
<p>LEIGH MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>You talk about the Victorian experience and I know that the Kennett</p>
<p> Government is about to issue or has issued a payback where households</p>
<p> in Victoria are receiving a cash amount back. But in terms of the</p>
<p> quality of the service and the price they're paying on an ongoing</p>
<p> basis, is it a better deal?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes it is. It's a better deal all round, and that's been</p>
<p> the experience in the United Kingdom as well. And the argument in</p>
<p> favour of privatising assets like ETSA is an argument about consumer</p>
<p> benefit, it's not, but there are also other benefits. The proceeds</p>
<p> of the sale would equal the non-commercial debt of this state. And</p>
<p> you can't ignore the probably $500 to $550 million a year that</p>
<p> would be save on an ongoing basis.</p>
<p>LEIGH MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>So are you for the sale of ETSA because that's an ideology that</p>
<p> you would deliver [inaudible].</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, I'm for the sale of ETSA for the reasons I've just explained,</p>
<p> and they're not ideological, they're good common sense reasons.</p>
<p> Consumers benefit, as demonstrated in Victoria and the United Kingdom</p>
<p> and the State will benefit and this State does have a big debt.</p>
<p>LEIGH MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>Absolutely.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>And a lot of it was racked up a few years ago, you know how. And it's</p>
<p> really beholden on those who are responsible racking up that debt</p>
<p> to let this sale go through.</p>
<p>LEIGH MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>Was it fair to have a swipe at Nick Xenophon?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>What do you mean to have a swipe at him?</p>
<p>LEIGH MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>Well to say that he doesn't have a mandate to hold this up?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I think anything that makes common sense and is beneficial for</p>
<p> the state ought to be supported.</p>
<p>TONY PILKINGTON:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, just on the getting onto the drug issue, you met with</p>
<p> FBI Director Louis Freeh I mean the result of those, that conversation,</p>
<p> you're still opposed to the idea of heroin trials?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes but I, I didn't really form that opposition, or develop that</p>
<p> opposition as a result of talking to Mr Freeh. I listened to what</p>
<p> he had to say. He agreed with me that a heroin trial would be inadvisable.</p>
<p> He also said that the policing methods described as zero tolerance</p>
<p> policing methods had been successful in reducing violent crimes in</p>
<p> many parts of the United States and that it hadn't resulted in</p>
<p> the crime problem being shifted from one spot to another. There's</p>
<p> a mistaken view around that I've sort of suddenly developed views</p>
<p> on some of these things as a result of talking to Mr Free or this</p>
<p> or that person, I've really had these views for some time.</p>
<p>LEIGH MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>What's your main objection to a heroin trial. Why don't</p>
<p> you think it would do anything to help the [inaudible]?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I've got a number of reasons why I object to it. One of</p>
<p> them is that it would send entirely the wrong single to people. In</p>
<p> one sense you are saying to people, don't touch it, its absolutely</p>
<p> lethal, dangerous, and you could be an addict for life. And then in</p>
<p> the next breath you are, no matter how you dress up a heroin trial,</p>
<p> in effect saying, well look it's not really all that bad, we</p>
<p> are going to in fact supervise your using the drug. There is a, to</p>
<p> me there is an enormous conflict in that. The second observation I'd</p>
<p> make is that I understand that people who are, if you did have a heroin</p>
<p> trial you would probably be involving yourself in doses four or six</p>
<p> times a day in some cases. Methadone on the other hand is administered</p>
<p> once a day. From a practical point of view, you start having heroin</p>
<p> trials, what you've in effect got to do over a period of time,</p>
<p> if it expands if it's quote, successful, and it expands, you've</p>
<p> got to provide very, very extensive facilities. There will be pressure</p>
<p> for people to actually take the doses away from the administering</p>
<p> centre. Once that happens you have the problem that they can then</p>
<p> be grabbed and cut down and used and sold and so forth. But my main</p>
<p> objection is that if a substance is so bad that you from the beginning</p>
<p> you are encouraging people not to take it and then in the next breath</p>
<p> you are saying, well we will provide you with a safety net if you</p>
<p> decide to take it. I think that is sending a very conflicting message.</p>
<p>LEIGH MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>Is there, can I take you up on that, because a lot of people might</p>
<p> say, look, what we're saying is not it's okay to take heroin</p>
<p> and we'll help you to do that. But a heroin trial would recognise</p>
<p> that there are people for whom heroin is desperately unsafe and they're</p>
<p> taking it in unsafe surroundings in an unsafe environment that leads</p>
<p> to things like petty crime and low ...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, no, well, I mean, the greatest incidence of crime arising out</p>
<p> of drug use is when people commit crime to get money to buy heroin</p>
<p> or other drugs to feed their habit. So that's the crime element,</p>
<p> the greatest crime element.</p>
<p>LEIGH MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>So if you've got a heroin trial where people ...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>You're talking here, hang on, you're talking here about</p>
<p> administering heroin to a small number of people in a trial. Now what</p>
<p> happens if that trial is judged successful. Are you arguing then that</p>
<p> it should be legalised?</p>
<p>LEIGH MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>Well, I'm arguing then that maybe we have to look at the fact...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No but hang on..</p>
<p>LEIGH MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>If those people involved in the heroin trial are not out knocking</p>
<p> off my house and pinching my TV and video, doesn't that suggest</p>
<p> that there is a link between the potential success of a heroin trial</p>
<p> and petty crime?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>There's not been a case in the world where a heroin trial has</p>
<p> been demonstrated to be successful. Even the much vaunted trial in</p>
<p> Switzerland. The evidence coming out of that at best very, very equivocal.</p>
<p> And I find it quite astonishing that there should be this enormous</p>
<p> focus on a heroin trial and yet there are a number of other substances</p>
<p> which, including methadone, which are a substitute for heroin, the</p>
<p> rapidity with which they must be administered, they don't need</p>
<p> to be administered anywhere nearly as frequently and you do not have</p>
<p> the conflicting message problem. I mean, there is something, you have</p>
<p> to ask yourself a common sense question. You are on the one hand saying</p>
<p> something is lethal and forbidden, verboten etc and it will destroy</p>
<p> your life if you take it. But then in the next breath you send a message,</p>
<p> well, look don't worry if you do get hooked on it we will provide</p>
<p> a more congenial environment for it to be used. I think that's</p>
<p> very conflicting messages.</p>
<p>LEIGH MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>But if you talk about issues like methadone for example, I mean we've</p>
<p> had well yesterday we had an extraordinary number of callers saying,</p>
<p> look forget heroin if you get onto methadone, you cannot get off it.</p>
<p> Methadone is probably...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, in a sense that's an argument against a heroin trial isn't</p>
<p> it. Because what you're really saying ... I mean that is the</p>
<p> very point. I mean that is an argument against any kind. That is an</p>
<p> argument...</p>
<p>LEIGH MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>But if you're saying alternatives...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>That is an argument for having an approach everybody going completely</p>
<p> cold turkey.</p>
<p>LEIGH MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>All right, if we don't have a heroin trail, and you're saying</p>
<p> there is an alternative or a number of alternative substances, such</p>
<p> as methadone, what do we do? Do we maintain the status quo? What is</p>
<p> the plan for those people who are currently addicted to heroin, much</p>
<p> and all as they don't want to be. Not those potential new users,</p>
<p> but the large group of Australians who are addicted to heroin. What</p>
<p> do we do with them?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, the first thing you do is you keep it in proportion. The percentage</p>
<p> of the population that has been touched by heroin directly themselves</p>
<p> in one way or another is less than two per cent, so you have got to</p>
<p> keep the thing in proportion. Now, that is still a very large number</p>
<p> of people, but I think we have got to keep this thing in proportion.</p>
<p> I don't believe that the answer is to embrace something which</p>
<p> has not been demonstrated anywhere else in the world to have been</p>
<p> successful and does involve sending that conflicting signal and in</p>
<p> the one breath saying to a person, well this is a very bad substance,</p>
<p> and you mustn't under any circumstances touch it, but don't</p>
<p> worry if you do there will be some kind of safety net provided. What</p>
<p> those who argue for a heroin trial have not demonstrated to me is</p>
<p> that there is any example around the world of this thing having worked</p>
<p> successfully.</p>
<p>LEIGH MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>Does that mean it couldn't work successfully here simply because</p>
<p> there's no precedent?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, but what it does mean that before you take a leap into that unknown</p>
<p> with all of the drawbacks that are involved, you ought at least take</p>
<p> that into account.</p>
<p>LEIGH MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>All right, well given that situation, what's the alternative?</p>
<p> What are we doing?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, the alternative... well, first of all I don't accept</p>
<p> that a heroin trial is a demonstrated alternative. It would be an</p>
<p> entirely different matter if it had been demonstrated elsewhere to</p>
<p> have really worked and to have really improved the situation. But</p>
<p> I think you have a situation where people are saying because we're</p>
<p> concerned about the present situation let's try something else</p>
<p> just for the sake of trying something else. And I've listened</p>
<p> to some of the advocates of a heroin trial and they've never</p>
<p> really taken the argument any further than that. They've all</p>
<p> said, oh, well look, we might as well try it. Now, I don't agree</p>
<p> with that sort of approach, particularly when there is no field evidence,</p>
<p> practical evidence around the world, and particularly when there is</p>
<p> very, very conflicting messages sent by embracing the trial of something</p>
<p> which ten seconds earlier you were saying is the foulest substance</p>
<p> in the world.</p>
<p>LEIGH MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>Well, obviously you are not a fan of heroin trial and I accept that.</p>
<p>TONY PILKINGTON:</p>
<p>What about Naltrexone as a substitute [inaudible]?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, Naltrexone is now able to be prescribed by doctors. And it's</p>
<p> believed because of the trial and it's been very carefully trialed.</p>
<p> And it's regarded as very effective. Now, I'm not a doctor,</p>
<p> none of us are, and I have to rely on expert advice in areas like</p>
<p> this and that expert advice says that this is suitable for prescription</p>
<p> and it's been prescribed.</p>
<p>TONY PILKINGTON:</p>
<p>Prime Minister on a different tack alltogether when we're talking</p>
<p> about our drug problem, any though of increasing the number of federal</p>
<p> police in countries like Burma? Now [inaudible]</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>We have done that quite recently.</p>
<p>TONY PILKINGTON:</p>
<p>We have yes.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>One of the ...</p>
<p>TONY PILKINGTON:</p>
<p>We get about 97/98 per cent of the...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Ninety eight per cent of it comes out of Burma. A lot of it comes</p>
<p> through China I am told. When we announced our Tough on Drugs Strategy</p>
<p> last year, which involved spending about $290 million over four years,</p>
<p> we included in that the recruitment and postings in Thailand and other</p>
<p> countries of a number of federal police officers. And I spoke to the</p>
<p> Federal Police Commissioner, Mr Palmer about that on Friday.</p>
<p>TONY PILKINGTON:</p>
<p>This is an increased number we're talking about here.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes.</p>
<p>TONY PILKINGTON:</p>
<p>How many. I mean are we talking..</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think off hand, you're talking about 16 agents located in different</p>
<p> countries. That figure may not be exactly right. But I'm, I'm</p>
<p> open minded about additions to that. The stationing of our own police</p>
<p> officers in source countries or near the source countries or transit</p>
<p> countries is a very important element of catching people who are importing</p>
<p> this stuff.</p>
<p>LEIGH MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>I suppose that's what a lot of people might say. Look, we're</p>
<p> putting a lot of focus on the users, and many of them can't help</p>
<p> themselves, are we putting enough focuses, emphasis and attention</p>
<p> on the big boys, on the people who are bringing it in?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, you need a three pronged approach. You need to spend money on</p>
<p> law enforcement and we are putting more into that. You need to spend</p>
<p> money on education, and you also need to spend a lot more money on</p>
<p> treatment. I mean, I am utterly and completely and totally sympathetic</p>
<p> to any person who is addicted to heroin or, indeed, any other harmful</p>
<p> drug. We don't have enough treatment facilities in this country.</p>
<p> It has traditionally been a state responsibility and I don't</p>
<p> think collectively the States have done a particularly good job on</p>
<p> this over the years, but I'm not sort of saying it in any political,</p>
<p> party political sense. And we decided last year for the first time</p>
<p> at a Federal level we would fund treatment programmes. And I get very</p>
<p> upset when I hear and read of people who can't get their son</p>
<p> or their daughter into a treatment programme. That is very distressing</p>
<p> and we want to try and do something more about that.</p>
<p>LEIGH MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, just before we go to the break, I know coming up in</p>
<p> April, here in Adelaide, there is an Australian conference on drug</p>
<p> strategy. Now there is about 500 people coming along to that. And</p>
<p> I believe you can't attend that. Is that right?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, the date, the very moment they want me to address that is a</p>
<p> Cabinet meeting and, I'm trying to organise an alternative date.</p>
<p> I think it goes on over a period of two days and if they can accommodate</p>
<p> me some other time of the conference [inaudible] a different matter.</p>
<p>LEIGH MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>Because I think that they would be certainly very keen.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I understand that. But it's very difficult for Prime Ministers</p>
<p> to miss Cabinet meetings...</p>
<p>LEIGH MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>Funny that.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>When he's meant to chair them when he's in Australia.</p>
<p>LEIGH MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>But obviously you know about it.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I certainly know about it and if I can't go it will be</p>
<p> because the time they want me to address the meeting coincides with</p>
<p> the Cabinet meeting. Now I obviously have to give preference to a</p>
<p> cabinet meeting.</p>
<p>TONY PILKINGTON:</p>
<p>Our guest is Prime Minister John Howard....</p>
<p>[News break]</p>
<p>LEIGH MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, first call this morning is down at Netley from Chris.</p>
<p> Good morning to you.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>Good morning everyone.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Good morning Chris.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>Mr Premier....ah Prime Minister, sorry, I apologise.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>That's all right.</p>
<p>CALLER</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
