<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9739</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J.KEATING, MP FRENCH NUCLEAR TESTS</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/09/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009739.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL: iSep .95 3: 59 No. 015 P. 01/ 05<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING, MP<br />
FRENCH NUCLEAR JESTS<br />
It is almost certain that the French government will very soon possibly within<br />
the next few days detonate an underground nuclear device at Mururoa.<br />
They have no moral right to conduct these tests. It is an expression of<br />
contempt for the people they wish to call their neighbours.<br />
Mururoa Is a French territory, six thousand kilometres from the east coast of<br />
Australia. Scientific opinion generally inclines to the view that the tests are<br />
unlikely to cause immediate harm to our environment, or, indeed, the<br />
environments of countries much closer to the test site.<br />
The Government of France may think we have no cause for concern. If this is<br />
their calculation, they are wrong. Not only are Australia and the countries of<br />
the Pacific outraged at the French action, so are countries everywhere,<br />
including France's European neighbours.<br />
The Pacific environment may not suffer damage from these tests this year or<br />
next but no-one can guarantee this. And no-one can guarantee that there<br />
will not be damage In 20 or 50 or 100 years time. If there was no risk, the<br />
French government would conduct the tests in France itself.<br />
The world is at a crucial stage on the path to a Comprehensive Test Ban<br />
Treaty. France is committed to signing such a treaty, and we welcome that.<br />
But France along with the other nuclear weapon states including China,<br />
whose testing program we also vigorously oppose is also committed to<br />
exercise ' utmost restraint" on testing.<br />
A series of eight nuclear tests by France is clearly not an exercise in<br />
restraint. It is not an action which will encourage the hopes we all hold for a nuclearfree<br />
world. It is not an action which will help to solve the nuclear problems<br />
which lie at Europe's door namely the Chernobyl-style nuclear reactors still<br />
functioning in the former Soviet Union and the nuclear materials and<br />
expertise seeping into illicit markets. </p>
<p>TEL: I. SOep. 95 3: 59 No. 015 P. 02/ Ut<br />
2<br />
Rather it is an action which will give comfort to other countries with nuclear<br />
ambitions, and one which will diminish France's reputation as a great<br />
democracy and a good citizen of the world.<br />
To try to persuade President Chirac to reverse this decision, the Australian<br />
Government has been forced to take the most wide ranging diplomatic<br />
measures we have ever taken against another democracy.<br />
We have frozen defence contacts. We have taken the argument to the<br />
French people directly through the pages of their newspapers and television.<br />
We have acted in concert with our South Pacific Forum partners, and with<br />
them sent a protest delegation to Paris.<br />
We have argued our case in every available international forum. We are<br />
working to bring a resolution on testing before the UIN General Assembly.<br />
We have applied to intervene before the International Court of Justice in<br />
support of New Zealand's attempt to reopen its 1973 nuclear tests case<br />
against France; and the Minister for Pacific Island Affairs, Mr Bilney, is<br />
leading a Parliamentary Delegation to Europe to build a coalition of interests<br />
with those many Europeans who oppose the tests.<br />
But for all the Government's efforts, we know that nothing has more<br />
dramatically brought home the message to the French government than the<br />
protests of the Australian people and the people of the region.<br />
I hope that these protests continue: that they continue to be peaceful and<br />
constructive, and directed where they should be, at the French government<br />
and not the French people. The French people are not to blame for this, and<br />
it is both wrong and counter productive to act in any way which suggests that<br />
they are.<br />
It is not for us to tell the French Government what their national security<br />
interests are. But we must tell them in every possible way that their tests are<br />
an affront. And that it is time for France to recognise that, whatever our<br />
concepts of national sovereignty, we share the world's environment we<br />
share the earth.<br />
Our protests will not end with the first test. Until the tests stop, we will<br />
continue to remind the French government that with every test they conduct,<br />
the good name of France is diminished in this part of the world.<br />
CANBERRA 1 SEPTEMBER 1995 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
