<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10720</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                AND THE TREASURER, THE HON PETER COSTELLO MP                JOINT PRESS CONFERENCE                PRIME MINISTER&amp;#146;S COURTYARD, PARLIAMENT HOUSE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/03/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...............................................</p>
<p>Well, this morning the Premiers and Chief Ministers walked out of</p>
<p> the Premiers' Conference when I made it clear, on behalf of the</p>
<p> Federal Government, that the very generous increase of 15 per cent,</p>
<p> in real terms, in health funding to the States over the next five</p>
<p> years would not be increased. It was a kindergarten stunt. But let</p>
<p> me assure the patients of Australia that they will not suffer as a</p>
<p> result of the kindergarten stunt of their Premiers and Chief Ministers.</p>
<p>The reality is that the Commonwealth will honour in full, to the last</p>
<p> dollar, on time, the offer in regard to health funding that was made</p>
<p> to the States. It's an offer that embraces a 15 per cent increase,</p>
<p> in real terms, over five years. It includes new components to cover</p>
<p> any further slippage of private health insurance to the tune of $80</p>
<p> million a year additional for every one per cent reduction in the</p>
<p> number of people covered by private health insurance. It also contains</p>
<p> other new guarantees.</p>
<p>So it's a very fair offer. It was obvious that some of the Health</p>
<p> Ministers from the States didn't understand the offer. And, indeed,</p>
<p> Mr Refshauge indicated very clearly that he had not understood the</p>
<p> generosity of the offer relating to veterans' affairs. Because</p>
<p> what we have done is to put an additional $750 million, over five</p>
<p> years, on the table for veterans' affairs. But in calculating</p>
<p> the per capita entitlement in relation to hospital funding generally,</p>
<p> we have not taken the veterans out of the calculation of the total.</p>
<p> So, therefore, in effect, there is a double payment from the Commonwealth</p>
<p> in relation to veterans. And it was very clear from his reaction and</p>
<p> his body language that Dr Refshauge had not appreciated that point.</p>
<p>But let me say to the patients of Australia, you will not suffer as</p>
<p> a result of the kindergarten stunt of the Premiers and the Chief Ministers</p>
<p> at this conference. Let me also tell the Australian public that when</p>
<p> the Premiers indicated their intention to walk-out, I asked them to</p>
<p> stay to discuss the issue of gun control reform. They refused to stay</p>
<p> to talk about gun control reforms. They refused, therefore, to discuss</p>
<p> in any way observance of the agreement that was made in 1996. I indicated</p>
<p> to them, before they left the room, that because of that the Commonwealth</p>
<p> reserve the right to use all of the power and authority at its disposal</p>
<p> to ensure compliance with the uniform gun control legislation. And</p>
<p> in that context I am giving consideration to the use of powers available</p>
<p> to us in relation to both sales tax and customs to ensure compliance</p>
<p> in full with that gun control legislation.</p>
<p>I believe it is an issue that transcends the divide between Labor</p>
<p> and Liberal. It's an issue that transcends the divide between</p>
<p> the Commonwealth and the States. And the kindergarten performance</p>
<p> of the Premiers this morning in refusing to even talk about it is</p>
<p> something that I think the Australian people will reject. We can have</p>
<p> our differences on other issues. But to refuse to even talk about</p>
<p> this issue and to have the opportunity, as I wanted them to do, to</p>
<p> reaffirm the agreement that was made in 1996, to have a committee</p>
<p> of, if necessary, Ministers and Chief Ministers to scrutinise the</p>
<p> degree of compliance or non-compliance and then to report back to</p>
<p> COAG on the understanding there would be no further changes to legislation</p>
<p> until that report was received, that was what I intended to put to</p>
<p> them. And that is a proposal that I think the Australian public would</p>
<p> endorse. But they refused point-blank despite my request to even talk</p>
<p> about gun control. I think that is a far more important issue than</p>
<p> posturing in Canberra by Premiers, one or two in particular.</p>
<p>Can I also just say, ladies and gentlemen, that the offer that we</p>
<p> made was a generous one, not only in relation to health but we offered</p>
<p> to increase general revenue assistance by five per cent in an era</p>
<p> of zero inflation. We gave undertakings that there would be no reduction</p>
<p> - I repeat, no reduction - in specific purpose payments. And that</p>
<p> is on top of the proposals that we made in relation to health.</p>
<p>Now, in a climate of zero inflation and given the background of our</p>
<p> own budgetary goals, which are to receive a surplus in the next budget,</p>
<p> that was an extraordinarily generous offer. The Commonwealth was not</p>
<p> prepared to increase our offer on health because what we'd already</p>
<p> offered was very significant and very generous. So I regard their</p>
<p> behaviour this morning as behaviour that would have disappointed their</p>
<p> own constituencies. The Australian public expects its State and Federal</p>
<p> leaders to discuss issues, not take their bat and ball home because</p>
<p> they don't get, within the first hour and a half, what they want.</p>
<p> We were prepared to stay. The meeting was not adjourned. There was</p>
<p> a walk-out by the Premiers and the Chief Ministers.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>This is another nursing home scandal in the making, Mr Howard.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, the only person who's likening this to nursing homes is</p>
<p> Mr Kennett. That is a cheap political shot with no substance. I reject</p>
<p> it entirely. And the fact that he made it before the Premiers'</p>
<p> Conference indicates that he brought, perhaps, an absence of total</p>
<p> good faith to the meeting.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[Inaudible] on the nature of the action you might have to take on</p>
<p> the guns...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, one of the remedies that is available to the Commonwealth, so</p>
<p> I have been advised, is that it could have a prohibitive sales tax</p>
<p> on weapons that are not bought in conformity with the National Police</p>
<p> Ministers' Agreement.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, where to now?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, as far as gun control is concerned, I've spelt that out.</p>
<p> In relation to what?</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>In relation to health.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, we'll continue to honour the agreement - the offer we made</p>
<p> to them. I repeat, no patient will suffer. And, indeed, the only patients</p>
<p> that are going to suffer as a result of the walk-out today are those</p>
<p> people on hospital waiting lists in all of the States and territories,</p>
<p> except the ACT which has signed the agreement. Because every week</p>
<p> that the Premiers refuse to sign the agreement or to agree to it in</p>
<p> principle, they lose access to a pool of $4 million a week which is</p>
<p> available to reduce hospital waiting lists. So I say to all of those</p>
<p> people on hospital waiting lists, get your Premiers to sign up to</p>
<p> the agreement and the lists will come down.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>...The issue now, Prime Minister, seems to be though that from the</p>
<p> stance you are taking, the Premiers after their walkout are now going</p>
<p> to have to come back with their tails between their legs. It gives</p>
<p> them no option.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>We gave them a fair offer. They chose to walk out. I didn't want</p>
<p> them to go.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Is that from your position going to be the end result?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look, our position is that we have a fair offer on the table. In the</p>
<p> absence of agreement by the Premiers, we will unilaterally honour</p>
<p> in full, on time, to the very last dollar, the offer we made in good</p>
<p> faith.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Why do you think the states are playing for more then?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I don't know. I think they are political blame-shifting. It's</p>
<p> the sort of 300 kilometre, flick pass to Canberra if you're the</p>
<p> Premier of New South Wales. It's a bit longer if you're</p>
<p> in Perth or in Melbourne.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do you also honour the 5 per cent in general...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes, yes. We will honour what we put on the table. We came in good</p>
<p> faith to this meeting. There was nothing up the sleeve. There were</p>
<p> no cards in the shirt or in the pocket or behind the ear, and we put</p>
<p> it on the table and we said, here it is fellas. It's a good offer.</p>
<p> Kate Carnell thought it was a terrific offer. She's on our side.</p>
<p> She signed up to the hospital agreement. I think she was a reluctant</p>
<p> walker-out.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>.. was there any room for movement in your offer?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>There was no room for movement. I made that clear last night. I had</p>
<p> a very amiable dinner with the Premiers last night and after we'd</p>
<p> finished talking about the American Civil War, the history of Australian</p>
<p> politics and a whole lot of other things and we talked about the football</p>
<p> and the cricket and the Grand Prix, we then got on to health and I</p>
<p> said very politely and very calmly that I thought it was a fair offer</p>
<p> and we couldn't change our position.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, if you had $120 million available for the waiting</p>
<p> list (inaudible), why not just make it available now so it can get</p>
<p> to the people that need it?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It will get to the people who need it if the Premiers will sign up.</p>
<p> I mean, it is in their hands. Every week that is lost in relation</p>
<p> to the waiting list is now their fault because they refused to access</p>
<p> that incentive pool.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do you think some Premiers were prepared to walk out to avoid a confrontation</p>
<p> on the gun control?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I don't know. You've got to ask them that but my position</p>
<p> is clear. I have always passionately supported that uniform agreement</p>
<p> and I will move heaven and earth to see that that uniform agreement</p>
<p> is honoured.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Was Premier Borbidge wrong when he says that the base funding for</p>
<p> Medicare for his state, and other Premiers backed this up, is in fact</p>
<p> less than what they had last time?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>What happened in 1993 was that Paul Keating did a very, very generous</p>
<p> deal for New South Wales and Victoria and if Queensland has any problem</p>
<p> about its base, it ought to talk to New South Wales and Victoria.</p>
<p>TREASURER:</p>
<p>Let me just say, in relation to Queensland, the general revenue assistance</p>
<p> and the specific purpose payments including health care agreements</p>
<p> is up 3.4% over the course of 1998 on 1997 and in addition to that,</p>
<p> there are also agreements in relation to the cutting of hospital waiting</p>
<p> lists and veterans' services. The truth of the matter is in relation</p>
<p> to this all of the States get increases, all of the states get increases,</p>
<p> increases running in excess of inflation.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>But not necessarily on the Medicare base rate?</p>
<p>TREASURER:</p>
<p>In relation to the overall position, because the Medicare base affects</p>
<p> the general revenue assistance, you have to look at them together</p>
<p> and in relation to them together, for Queensland, they actually increased</p>
<p> the amount which they will receive to $5.852 billion, a 3.4 per cent</p>
<p> increase.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I mean, it's a bit like accessing an automatic teller, you know,</p>
<p> an ATM. You get $500, you get it in different denominations but it</p>
<p> still adds up to $500 and it's the amount that comes out that</p>
<p> matters.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>... last resort, Mr Howard, to take a responsibility for health and</p>
<p> thus stop the constant States' cost shifting and blame shifting?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I can't imagine that the States would ever agree to hand</p>
<p> over responsibility for health, that's not an issue that was</p>
<p> discussed. We are prepared to play our part. We are playing our part.</p>
<p> We have great responsibilities, so do the States, and we should talk</p>
<p> about them in a mature adult fashion and not take our bat and ball</p>
<p> home.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>How will that work? If you make the money available, they say no,</p>
<p> Surely patients are poorly advised?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>If they say no to the money they are directly punishing their own</p>
<p> patients and I can't believe that a Premier would allow his or</p>
<p> her ego to get in the way of looking after their patients.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard is a debacle on health like this a possible liability for</p>
<p> you if it is a possible election year?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, I don't believe so because the Australian public will see</p>
<p> that we were prepared to go on talking. The Australian public will</p>
<p> see that we were prepared to increase the offer. The Australian public</p>
<p> will see that we haven't behaved in a petulant kindergarten fashion</p>
<p> by walking out of a meeting. I mean it is ridiculous. It is now only</p>
<p> 12.40 pm. I mean there is plenty of lunch left and incidentally we</p>
<p> were ready to feed them. I know there was a view being put around</p>
<p> that we weren't willing to feed them but we were.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>So you are not keen to try an wind it up so you can get on to an election</p>
<p> footing?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Wind it up? Well, I mean, we have made an offer and that offer, let</p>
<p> me repeat, despite their petulant performance this morning, that offer</p>
<p> will be honoured in full and time, to the last dollar.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Were you offering any offsets in relation to tax reform?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>They'd gone. Our guests had gone before we even got to the issue.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Were there any options on the table as far as that was concerned?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well it's not, we don't negotiate tax reform with the States.</p>
<p> What we do is we carefully listen to what they have to say and we</p>
<p> continue to be willing to talk to them but at the end of the day,</p>
<p> it is our responsibility after consulting the States and after listening</p>
<p> to other people in the community, to decide how the taxation system</p>
<p> of Australia will be remade.</p>
<p>Let me say to the States that I will continue to listen to what they</p>
<p> have to say, I will continue to consult the Premiers, always. But</p>
<p> at the end of the day it is not something we negotiate with the States</p>
<p> or indeed with anybody, it is something that we ultimately, after</p>
<p> listening to the community, decide what to do.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST</p>
<p>Prime Minister, on another matter, do you still require your Ministers</p>
<p> to divest themselves of shares in their portfolio area?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think that is about Senator Parer, isn't it? I think you know</p>
<p> my position on that.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST</p>
<p>In dollar terms, how much was the five per cent increase in general</p>
<p> assistance worth to the States?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well the Treasurer...</p>
<p>TREASURER:</p>
<p>About a billion.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Thanks a lot.</p>
<p>[Ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
