<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11255</transcript-id>
    <title>NO DECEPTION ON INCOME TAX</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/04/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The claim made by Mr Laurie Oakes on the Sunday programme, and immediately</p>
<p> parroted by the Federal Opposition, that my April 12 Prime Network</p>
<p> address contained a deliberately misleading assertion on income tax</p>
<p> is false.</p>
<p>In the Prime address I said: "According to a recent study by</p>
<p> the OECD, Australian workers on average wages pay more in income tax</p>
<p> than workers in any other industrialised country in the world, except</p>
<p> Denmark ".</p>
<p>This statement is based on Table 2 on page 14 of the OECD report,</p>
<p> "The Tax/Benefit Position of Employees, 1997," which</p>
<p> is attached.</p>
<p>In relation to income tax as a percentage of labour costs, the table</p>
<p> clearly shows Australia second behind Denmark.</p>
<p>That report's findings formed the basis of an editorial in "The</p>
<p> Australian" on April 6 1999.</p>
<p>That editorial made the overall point that "Only Denmark ranks</p>
<p> higher in a survey of the level of income tax paid on an average wage</p>
<p> as a proportion of gross wages in the 28 nations making up the Organisation</p>
<p> for Economic Co-operation and Development."</p>
<p>The OECD report also contained a table (Table 1) which provided information</p>
<p> on the income tax burden measured on a less comprehensive basis. This</p>
<p> appears to have been the table used by Mr Oakes in a bid to discredit</p>
<p> my statement. It is a pity that in the interests of balance, Mr Oakes</p>
<p> did not also flourish Table 2.</p>
<p>Table 1, which is also attached, nevertheless highlights the high</p>
<p> income tax burden imposed on Australian workers.</p>
<p>I specifically reject the assertion by Mr Oakes and the Deputy Leader</p>
<p> of the Opposition, Mr Crean, that I deliberately set out to mislead</p>
<p> the Australian public.</p>
<p>18 April 1999.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
