<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5017</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/04/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005017.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
JbAUST Al 1tA<br />
FOR MEDIA 8 April 1979<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
Today, perhaps more than ever, Australians are aware of how<br />
much we rely on our country's great natural wealth. We are<br />
abundant in minerals; have vast reserves of gas and oil; and<br />
have millions of acres of land under wheat, sheep and cattle.<br />
Our wealth springs from the land. In the past people sometimes<br />
were careless of our natural heritage. Too often people moved<br />
into new areas, settled, knocked down bush, planted crops and<br />
sowed grasses without any real concern for the consequences.<br />
Now we are at a stage where we need to assess the total land use<br />
of this nation. It is our responsibility to make sure it is used<br />
to the best advantage keeping account of both economic and<br />
conservation requirements.<br />
While it is a question of governments having to make deci~ ions<br />
about parklands, conservation policies and the like, policies<br />
would fail without the concern of the general community. In the<br />
last ten to 15 years, Australians have started to show a living<br />
concern about the environment. It is pleasing that people have<br />
the courage to stand up and be counted on these questions.<br />
I sometimes wonder how the physical face of our nation would look<br />
without the efforts of concerned people. At the same time, your<br />
government is aware of the need for practical laws and policies<br />
that allow for protection of the environment.<br />
This week, I announced the government's decision to ban whaling<br />
in Australian waters. Many Australians believe the harpooning<br />
of whales is offensive to the ideals of mankind. On the other<br />
hand, the jobs of a number of Australians depended on whaling.<br />
Early last-year we set up an . inquiry into whales and whaling.<br />
Our decision was to accept all the inquiry's recommendations.<br />
Our decision to ban whaling completely, and to ban the import of<br />
all whale products from January 1981, demonstrates our commitment<br />
to protect this magnificent mammal. We will be arguing strongly<br />
through the International Whaling Commission for our policy to<br />
be followed by other nations. / 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
I pay special tribute to the work of Sir Sydney Frost who<br />
conducted the whaling inquiry, and to the men, women and<br />
children associated with Project Jonah.<br />
Also this week, the Kakadu National Park in the Northern<br />
Territory was proclaimed. This park will become one of the<br />
world's great national parks. Its environment is unique<br />
and precious. Aborigines have occupied the area for thousands<br />
of years. The several hundred rock painting galleries in the<br />
area are recognized amongst the best preserved in Australia.<br />
They rival the prehistoric painted caves in France and Spain.<br />
The Act under-which the park has been set up makes sure that<br />
the traditional Aboriginal land owners are fully consulted<br />
in the management of the park. Opportunities for their<br />
employment in the park will increase as training programs<br />
develop.<br />
Kakadu is not the only unique bushland in Australia. Of f<br />
the coast of Queensland, Fraser Island has a natural environment<br />
of great complexity and fragility. It is the world's largest<br />
sand island, and its lakes, beaches and cliffs of coloured<br />
sands, sandblows and rain forested sand dunes make it<br />
irreplaceable. In 1976, following a full public environmental inquiry, the<br />
government moved to stop the export of minerals from the island.<br />
Since then, the company affected by that decision the<br />
Dillingham Corporation has conducted an international vendetta<br />
against Australia. The company has refused to accept the fair<br />
and reasonable compensation offered by the government. We<br />
make no apology for our firm stand.<br />
The issue was simple. Were we prepared to watch mining proceed<br />
on a unique and fragile stretch of earth? Were we prepared to<br />
endanger the environment? The answer was and is no.<br />
Australia is also setting high standards of nature conservation.<br />
We play a leading role in the International Union for the<br />
Conservation of Nature and Natural Resources; we have signed<br />
the Washington Convention on Trade in Endangered Species and the<br />
Convention for the Conservation of Antarctic Seals.<br />
Australia was the first party to the Convention of Wetlands<br />
of International Importance especially as waterfowl habitat.<br />
Australia and Japan have signed a joint agreement for the<br />
protection of migratory birds. On top of that, your government<br />
has actively supported the establishment of the World Wildlife<br />
Fund in Australia.<br />
Our record of action to protect the environment stands any<br />
scrutiny. We are keenly aware that our children and their<br />
children will judge us by the response we give now to the<br />
on-going challenge of conserving our great natural heritage.<br />
We will not fail them. 000o-</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
