<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10330</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON. JOHN HOWARD MP RADIO INTERVIEW - AM PROGRAMME WITH FRAN KELLY</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/05/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010330.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Fax from S<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
6 May 1997 TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE. HON. JOHN HOWARD MP<br />
RADIO INTERVIEW AM PROGRAMME WITH FRAN KELLY<br />
E&amp; OE<br />
KELLY:<br />
John Howard, Mal Colston has turned on you. He says you've thrown him to the<br />
wolves and he will vote against your legislation in the Senate. Doesn't this threat bear<br />
out what critics of Colston have been saying since he defected that his vote is for sale<br />
and he votes not on principle but according to favours?<br />
PRIM MINISTER:<br />
What are you suggesting, that he's now been bought by the Labor Party?<br />
KELLY:<br />
Well I'm just suggesting that...<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
This outburst by Senator Colston throws up a very interesting challenge to Mr<br />
Beazley. They are now going to take back the vote of the person who they have been<br />
attacking in public, calling a rorter, saying should be out of the Parliament, Are they<br />
going to repeat in 1997 what they did in 1983 and continued to do by re-preselecting<br />
the man, in other words, despite their sort of retrospective distaste for what he's done,<br />
be perfectly happy to take him while he supports the Government, supports the Labor<br />
Party. KELLY: They say it's their vote anyway, that he shouldn't be there. FaaxftI0 6/ 05/ 97 10: 18 Pg: 1 </p>
<p>Fax from PRIM MINISTER:<br />
If he's as bad as they claim, arnd let me say, I think the man is entitled to his day in<br />
court, he's entitled like any other Australian to a presumption of innocence. We did<br />
the right thing. We sent the matter off to the police, something Senator Evans, then<br />
Senator Evans and Mr Deazley deliberately refimsd to do in 1983 and we've also said<br />
in the circumstances we won't accept his vote. Now if that means that the<br />
Government has a tougher time getting legislation through the Senate, so be it,<br />
because it was the right thing to do arnd the right thing for the Labor Party to do would<br />
be to duplicate what we've done but I am certain the Labor Party won't because the<br />
Labor Party will behave without any principle at all on this whole issue.<br />
KELLY:<br />
But if he's turned on you because, as he says, you've thrown him to the wolves<br />
because you've stopped looking after him, does it raise the prospect that you had<br />
offered him something in the past that had convinced him to support you?<br />
] PREME MINISTER:<br />
Fran, the allegations about his travel rorting, alleged travel rorting as far as I am<br />
concerned arose after he had been elected as Deputy President. The Labor Party knew<br />
about it beforehand, I didn't. The first...<br />
KELLY: But he had been voting with you on most...<br />
PRIME NMSTER:<br />
I am sorry, the first, the critical thing is the first I knew about any of these allegations<br />
was in January or February of this year. Kim Beazley and Gareth Evans, the leader<br />
and Deputy Leader, knew about them 14 years ago and did absolutely nothing and<br />
only turned feral when Senator Colston no longer supported the Labor Party. Look,<br />
we've been over all of this. I think the public is bored with the Colston affair. They<br />
want it investigated by the police. They want the man to have his day in court. They<br />
don't want him to continue as Deputy President and they want the Labor Party to<br />
behave with a bit of principle on the issue.<br />
KELLY:<br />
And you're saying that even if he makes good his threat and votes to block all your<br />
important legislation in the Senate, you still won't join those currently calling for him<br />
to quit the Senate.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well he can't be expelled from the Senate. Hie's entitled to a day in court in the same<br />
way as Carmen Lawrence is entitled to a day in court. Nobody is suggesting that<br />
Fafris06/ 05/ 97 10: 18 Pg: 2 </p>
<p>Fax from060/ 71: 8P3<br />
Carmen Lawrence should be thrown out of Parliament. She's been charged with<br />
something. This man has not even been charged with anything. You can't tear up the<br />
rule book no matter how bitter you may feel about the party political defection. We do<br />
have the rule of law in this country and it's important at a time like this when emotions<br />
run high and people are running around saying somebody has done this or that. It's<br />
very important that people remain a bit calm and follow the rules and the rule is that he<br />
is entitled to a presumption of innocence and the Labor Party should support that rule<br />
in relation to him as they support it quite promptly in relation to Carmen Lawrence.<br />
KELLY:<br />
All right, another problem for you right now is Pauline Hanson and her One Nation<br />
party. Two polls out today show her Party making a significant dent in your support.<br />
The AGB McNair poll showing One Nation second preferences flowing to Labor at a<br />
rate that would bundle you out of office if there was an election now. Do you concede<br />
still that she's not, I mean do you concede now finally that she's not a passing<br />
phenomenon, that she is a problem?<br />
PRIE AMSTER:<br />
Those polls don't surprise me. We are going through a period at the moment where<br />
the Government is quite understandably preoccupied with two or three issues which<br />
are not of immediate relevance to all of the voters. I mean one of them is very<br />
important to Aboriginal people and to farmers, that's the Wik issue, but we've been<br />
tied down preparing the budget and I think it's inevitable that at this time of the<br />
electoral cycle that people will sort of say to themselves, you know, what on earth are<br />
they getting involved with all those sorts of things. The fog around those issues will<br />
clear very quickly. Next week's budget will I think cut through and next week's<br />
budget will be very good for jobs, it will be very good for small business and it will be<br />
very good for the regions of Australia. But we have to work our way through these<br />
other issues and I think the other point that's got to be made is that there were<br />
enormous expectations as there are when you have a government replacing a<br />
government that's been in power for a long period of time, and I know there are some<br />
people out there who voted for us in March of last year who would have liked to have<br />
seen more change but the changes that we have brought about are working their way<br />
through the economy, particularly in area like small business, and I think the real<br />
benefits of them will begin to be felt towards the end of this year so I would say to<br />
some of those people who see in the simplistic nostrums of somebody like Pauline<br />
Hanson some kind of alternative deliverance from some of the current day difficulties<br />
to understand that she doesn't have any solutions at all. I haven't heard her articulate<br />
one intellgent alternative policy and as my colleagues have indicated, now that she's<br />
holding herself out as a party leader, any comments that she makes that are damaging<br />
to Australia, that are wrong, will be attacked by me and my colleagues in the samne way<br />
as statements of that kind madle by members of the Labor Party.<br />
] KELLY:<br />
Just in terms of how you will make that attack, last week you stopped short of<br />
labelling Pauline Hanson's views as offensive yet your Foreign Minister described them<br />
06/ 05/ 97 10: 18 Pg: 3 </p>
<p>Fax from as divisive and offensive and your Treasurer said her plan was both divisive and<br />
vicious. Do you agree with those descriptions?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Look, I use my language, they use their's but..<br />
KELLYBut what is the language, how would you describe her?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Anybody... anybody... . well, it depends what particular view. I thought some of the<br />
things that she said in her maiden speech were wrong and I said so at the time. Her<br />
claim that Aborigines were not as a group disadvantaged is palpably wrong and 1,<br />
although I disagree with the claims made by the Aboriginal people in relation to many<br />
of their claims in relation to the Wik debate, nobody can deny they do suffer social<br />
disadvantage. Look, it is a question of attacking the merits of an issue. I understand<br />
why some people are attracted to her simplistic nostrums and my job as Prime Minister<br />
is to point out the error of her arguments, the damage some of her ideas would do to<br />
Australia if they were implemented but also to understand why at a time of very great<br />
social and economice change, why some people in the community with good will would<br />
be attracted to some of the things that she's saying. I think the other thing that you've<br />
got to remember is that one of the features of 13 years of the Labor Government was<br />
the imposition without the opportunity of debate by what did amount to a pofitical elite<br />
in this country on the Australian population of views that many people in the<br />
community simply didn't accept and felt that they had been denied the opportunity of<br />
debating. I think some of the people who have been superficially attracted to Pauline<br />
Hanson are people who resented that process very strongly and I must say that I<br />
ideni* with that and I understand that. But her answer is an answer that would cause<br />
damage to' this country. I mean, you can't appear inward looking, you can't run<br />
policies that however you might superficially explain them away, do appeal to<br />
prejudice within the community, That kind of conduct for any political figure in<br />
Australia is quite irresponsible.<br />
KELLY: I guess the simple question for you then is would you categorise those simplistic<br />
nostrums, to use your word, as divisive?<br />
PRIME MINISTER.-<br />
Well some of them are, yes. Others are just simplistic nonsense. I mean, I heard her<br />
yesterday say that we'd organised the riots against her, or the demonstrations. And<br />
can I say in relation to that to people-. don't demonstrate in an ugly fashion against her<br />
any more than you should demonstrate in an ugly fashion against anybody. All it does<br />
is to boost the stock of the person against whom you're demonstrating. If you want to<br />
hinder Pauline Hanson, don't demonstrate against her. 06/ 85/ 97 16: 18 Pg: 4 </p>
<p>Fax from KELLY: She is causing some problems for you on your backbench though, doesn't she? I<br />
mean, some of your backbench want you to stop attacking her because many of their<br />
constituents like what she's saying, others want you to step up the attack and finish it<br />
off How will you reassure your backbench on Pauline Hanson?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well I think you just have to behave in a sensible fashion. You have to take the<br />
approach that I've taken on this interview this morning. Condemn the silly statements,<br />
condemn the statements that don't help Australia but recognise that the people who<br />
are superficially attracted to her are not themselves bigoted or racist. And those terms<br />
are flung around far too easily in this country, it's been a constant complaint of mine<br />
for a long time now that those tenns are used quite unfairly. This is a tolerant, open<br />
minded, liberal country which has received people of all races into its ranks and<br />
absorbed them very very harmoniously and I do not support this overuse of such<br />
peiorative terms. And it was the overuse of those perjorative terms over a long<br />
period of time under the former government which has produced some of the attitudes<br />
within the Australian community which people are now talking about.<br />
KELLY: One of your backbenchers, Liberal MW, Bill Taylor, who's been a strong supporter of<br />
you in the past, accused you yesterday of not having.., accused the Government under<br />
your leadership of not having enough backbone, said if the Government was doing<br />
more then voter dissatisfaction wouldn't be leading people off to Pauline Hanson.<br />
How concerned are you that members of your own backbench are openly criticising<br />
your leadership like this?<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
Well, I don't know if that was openly criticising my...<br />
KELLY: You don't think it was not enough backbone<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
anyway, you can say it. Look I don't think it, you can say that if you want, that's<br />
fine. Look, I'm not overly concerned about that. I understand why people say that<br />
because... KELLY: Why? Farxom 06/ 85/ 97 10: 18 Pg: </p>
<p>Fax from ] PRIM MINISTER:<br />
Well, because there were huge expectations of overnight change and when you don't<br />
control the Senate and when you, I think, make the mistake of allowing, as we have<br />
done over the last year, unreasonable criticisms of the pace of change from within our<br />
own ranks to go unanswered, then I think perhaps that view builds up. I do want to<br />
make it clear this morning that the process in the past year of turning the other cheek<br />
when people on our own side take gratuitous swipes at what we have done, those days<br />
are over.<br />
KELLY: What will you be doing now if that.. ( inaudible)?<br />
PRIE MINISTERL<br />
Well I will be pointing out the enormous changes that this Government has achieved. I<br />
mean, look at the taxation area...<br />
KELLY: Are you talking about people within your backbench or John Elliott or business<br />
leaders? PRM MINISTER:<br />
I'm talking generally and you can draw your own conclusions about the people to<br />
whom I am referring. I just want to make it clear in the area of taxation, two things.<br />
We made a solemn promise to the Australian people that we wouldn't have a goods<br />
and services tax in our first term and people who constantly cail for that in our first<br />
term either want us to break that solemn promise or are being deliberately unhelpful.<br />
The other point I make is that in areas like capital gains tax reform for small business<br />
this has been a reforming government from the I1st of July this year you will have the<br />
biggest tax break in the capital gains area for small business that this country has ever<br />
seen. You've seen provisional tax relief. You have seen a $ 1I billion family tax<br />
package. From the 1st of July this year there will be a $ 630 million incentive for<br />
Australian families to take out private health insurance. Now, that's in the taxation<br />
area alone. So I want to make it clear that one of the things I will be doing now is<br />
pointing out a lot more vigorously, and my colleagues will, what this Government has<br />
done. KELLY:<br />
Will you be taking action against members of your backbench if they continue to talk<br />
out? Farxom 06/ 05/ 97 10: 18 Pg: 6 </p>
<p>Fax from PRIME MINSTER:<br />
No, I'm not taking... I'm not taking action. I don't engage in that sort of . people are<br />
free occasionally, particularly when there's so many of them, they're free occasionally<br />
to express a point of view providing it is broadly consistent with the good fortunes of<br />
the Government. I think the backbench, given the size and given the difficulties of the<br />
decisions we've had to take, have been incredibly supportive, incredibly well<br />
disciplined and incredibly well commnitted and strongly committed to our goals.<br />
] KELLY:<br />
All right, well another issue likely to flare on your backbench, I understand this<br />
morning, is cross-media ownership. You've indicated you favour relaxing the rules<br />
that would,...<br />
PR]] ME NMSTER:<br />
Well I have indicated that there's quite a strong case for it but we haven't taken any<br />
decision. KELLY: Your backbench commnittee on communications has come out publicly arguing for<br />
more diversity. How can you reassure them that your rules won't result in further<br />
concentration, in other words wouldn't result in Kerry Packer for instance owning<br />
both Channel 9 and Fairfax?<br />
PRIME MUIiSTER:<br />
Well, these are matters that we will in the proper way discuss with the backbench. I<br />
haven't had any discussions with them yet but we will deal with media policy in the<br />
way that we always deal with these things. We discuss themi in Cabinet and if there is a<br />
position for change then that proposed change will be discussed with the backbench<br />
committee and media laws, if there are to be any changes, media laws will be treated<br />
no differently from any other proposals.<br />
KELLY: And would the Australian independent newspapers consortium that you met yesterday,<br />
would that group be a suitable owner of Fairfax in your view?<br />
PRIME MM41STER:<br />
Well that would be a matter I guess for the shareholders and current owners of Fairfax.<br />
KELLY: Were you impressed by their consortium? Fa rom06/ 85/ 97 10: 18 Pg: 7 </p>
<p>Fax from PRIM M1NISTER:<br />
well, I have been the recipient of many callers in the last few weeks about this issue. I<br />
did see them. I saw Mr Cameron O'Reilly from the O'Reilly group; I saw Tom Burton<br />
of the Parliamentary Press Gallery representing the journalists; I've seen Mr Stokes;<br />
I've spoken to Mr Murdoch, I've seen them all, Now, they all put their own point of<br />
view. This is an area where people are not shy in promoting the self interest which I<br />
understand and I respect and what we have to do is to take a decision on whether the<br />
current law, which on one argument is quite restrictive should be changed. But I<br />
understand the arguments about diversity, I hear them. I also understand the fact that<br />
you have a special law in relation to the media and there are many people in the<br />
community who argue that it should be dealt with in accordance with the ordinary<br />
competiton law of this country and it is a bit peculiar that the two wholly Australian<br />
media companies of any size in this country, namely Mr Packer arnd Mr Stokes'<br />
companies are prevented from bidding for any of the assets of John Fairfax under the<br />
present law. Now, that's the argument for change. The argument against change is<br />
that if you bring about fewer players then that has a greater concentration and<br />
therefore that is against the public interest. Now, they are things that we have to<br />
weigh up and we have to try and set one off against the other. I don't think it is<br />
something that should be approached in a sense of paranoia and we will take a decision<br />
which we believe is in the public interest. I know that whatever decision we take will<br />
not be popular with some people.<br />
KELLY:<br />
Mr Howard, we'll have to leave it there. Thank you.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Pleasure. Farxom 06/ 05/ 97 16: 18 Pg: 8 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
