<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1036</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS:  P.M.NO. 2/1965  OVERSEAS TRIP BY MINISTER FOR BEFENCE STATEMENT BY THE ACTING PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. J. MCEWEN</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/01/1965</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001036.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
6 5 / O0<br />
EMBARGO : NOTr TO BE PUBLISHED, BROADCAST OR TELECAST<br />
BEFORE~ 7 PM ( EST)<br />
FOR PRESS: OVERSEAS TRIP BY MINISTER FOR D) EFENCE<br />
Statement by the Acting Prime Minister, the Rt. Hon. McEwen<br />
Mr. John McEwen, Acting Prime Minister, announced<br />
today that the Minister for Defence Senator Shane Paltridge,<br />
would be leaving Australia on 19th January for a visit to a<br />
number of South-East Asian countries, Japan and the United<br />
States. In South-East Asia the Minister will visit Malaysia,<br />
Thailand and Vietnam.<br />
Mr. McEwen said that this would be the first<br />
time that Senator Paltridge had had an opportunity since<br />
becoming Minister for Defence to visit South-East Asia and<br />
to acquaint himself at first hand with the problems relating<br />
to Australia's defence interests there, In Malaysia he<br />
would have discussions with members of the Government on<br />
defence matters of common concern. He will also visit units<br />
of the three Australian Services which are stationed in<br />
Malaysia. In Thailand he will have discussions with members<br />
of the Government and will call upon the Secretary-General<br />
of SEATO at the Organization's headquarters in Bangkok,<br />
He will also visit the R. A. A. F. unit at Ubon.<br />
In South Vietnam he will be discussing with<br />
members of the Government and the United States representatives<br />
there the present situation created by aggression from<br />
Communist-controlled North Vietnam. He hopes also to visit<br />
some of the Australian Service personnel in South Vietnam*<br />
Mr, MoEwen said that during his visit to Japan,<br />
Senator Paltridge hoped to meet Ministers and Service<br />
officers, In the United States the Minister will have<br />
discussions with the Secretary of Defence, Mr. McNamara the<br />
Secretary of State, Mr. Rusk, and other defence authoriiies.<br />
The Minister will also inspect various Defence installations<br />
during his visit including Defoe's shipbuilding yards where<br />
the Charles F. Aclams destroyers ordered by Australia are<br />
under construction and also General Dynamics at Fort Worth<br />
where the F111A strike aircraft, which is being purchased<br />
by Australia, is under construction.<br />
Mr. McEwepn said that on Senator Paltridge's<br />
departure, he would be Acing Minister for Defence until<br />
the return of the Prime Minister.<br />
CANBERBA, 12th January, 1965 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
