<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8342</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER LAUNCH OF THE READY RESERVE SCHEME AND RECRUITINGCAMPAIGN BRISBANE, 2 OCTOBER 1991</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/10/1991</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008342.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHECK AGAINST nET. TZERY K1MARr. OFD UNTIL. nr. TurRy<br />
SPEECH DY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
LAUNCH OF THE READY RESERVE SCHEME<br />
AND RECRUITING CAMPAIGN<br />
BRISBANE, 2 OCTOBER 1991<br />
Minister Dilney,<br />
CDF General Peter Gration,<br />
Major-General John Sanderson,<br />
Distinguished Guests,<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen,<br />
Students, Since coming t~ o office in 1983, my Government has made<br />
far-reaching reforms to foster an outward-looking, confident<br />
Australia which both contributes to, and benefits from, a<br />
stable and prosperous region.<br />
The development of Australia's Defence Force is a vital part of<br />
that approach. The recently completed Force Structure Review<br />
recommended changes to Australia's defence posture to ensure we<br />
enter the next century with a defence force which is relevant,<br />
effective and efficient.<br />
The Review was; conducted on the basis of my Government's well.-<br />
defined policy of defence self-reliance.<br />
In accepting 1: he Review, the Government was persuaded by the<br />
emphasis it gave to three key outcomes.<br />
The first of t: hese is to develop the combat capabilities of the<br />
Defence Force by reducing the number of service personnel<br />
involved in support functions and by contracting out such<br />
functions wherever this is appropriate.<br />
Second, the Review reaffirmed our commitment to improving our<br />
capability to conduct operations in the northern and western<br />
approaches to the Continent. That is being done by extending<br />
western basing for the Navy, increasing the number of Army<br />
units based in the north, and by providing greater capacity for<br />
the Air Force to deploy and operate from northern airfields.<br />
The third key outcome was to make greater use of reserves,<br />
including a new form of service the Ready Reserve. </p>
<p>The principle which underlies all these reforms to the ADF is<br />
the same as that which underlies the Government's reforms in<br />
many areas. In everything we do, Australia must discard<br />
outdated practices and concepts, and look instead for the most<br />
efficient way to do the job. That is what micro-economic<br />
reform is all about. It is vital to the future of our<br />
Industry, and it is vital to the future of the defence force.<br />
The Government's defence reforms have not been a cost-cutting<br />
measure indeed we have maintained defence spending in real<br />
terms. These reforms have been instituted to ensure that we<br />
get the best value for our defence dollar, and that is<br />
important at any given level of expenditure.<br />
The Ready Reserve Scheme is an excellent example of this reform<br />
in action. It is the result of an innovative and imaginative<br />
look at the way the ADF uses its most precious resource<br />
people. It reflects a sophisticated balance of priorities,<br />
which will provide the ADF with a mix of capabilities. This<br />
will give it the readiness and sustainability we need, with the<br />
most efficient use of resources.<br />
The Ready Reserve Scheme will improve our capability to respond<br />
to emergency situations at short notice. It does not replace<br />
or decrease the emphasis given to the very important roles of<br />
the existing reserves. Rather, it increases the depth of<br />
available trained units and personnel in an emergency.<br />
Earlier this year I congratulated the Minister for Defence on<br />
the exemplary work undertaken by the CDF and his colleagues in<br />
bringing together the sweeping and far-reaching package of<br />
reforms contained in the Force Structure Review and the Ready<br />
Reserve Proposal.<br />
At the time I said that much work lay ahead in bringing those<br />
major changes to fruition. The opening of the Recruiting<br />
Campaign for the Ready Reserve Scheme is a milestone in that<br />
regard. In acknowledging that milestone, I am aware that reform is<br />
always difficult in a large organisation. I am sure that the<br />
Ready Reserve Scheme is no exception.<br />
The fact that Defence has been able to work through the<br />
internal and external criticism that seems to be inevitable<br />
with change does the organisation great credit.<br />
Each of the services will take advantage of the opportunities<br />
provided by the Ready Reserve Scheme. With the introduction of<br />
the Scheme, Navy is planning to restructure the whole of its<br />
Reserve organisation to meet its operational needs better.<br />
This means that the reserves will become more involved in<br />
activities which have traditionally been undertaken by members<br />
or former members of the Permanent Naval Force. In this<br />
process some of the traditional roles and functions of the<br />
existing reserves will be replaced by greater opportunities to<br />
be involved in mainstream naval service. </p>
<p>3.<br />
The Army is committed to the total force concept with combat<br />
units trained and equipped to meet a range of contingencies in<br />
the defence of Australia and her interests.<br />
Regular soldiers maintain high standards of collective training<br />
to meet shorter notice contingencies while reservists, through<br />
their part-time commitment, provide individual skills and the<br />
experience base to support the conduct of protracted operations<br />
when necessary.<br />
Army Ready Reserve units will be able to reach and maintain<br />
training standards equivalent to regulars in their specialist<br />
fields. As a result they will be at a higher readiness status<br />
than the general Reserve, which will nevertheless retain<br />
important roles in protection of vital assets and provide a<br />
basis for expansion of our defence effort if required.<br />
Reserve personnel provide a cost-effective and potent part of<br />
the Air Force.<br />
The Ready Reserve Scheme in Air Force will provide airfield<br />
defence squadrons to protect bases during emergencies.<br />
Training will be the same as for regular airfield defence guard<br />
members. But the Ready Reserve Scheme is not just important to the ADF.<br />
The Scheme is a part of our broad philosophy of involving more<br />
of the community in the nation's security.<br />
The Defence Force of the future will need well-trained and<br />
highly motivated people of the highest calibre. So does the<br />
Australian workplace. The Ready Reserve Scheme provides an<br />
opportunity for young people to serve their nation in both<br />
roles. During the last election campaign I said that Australia needed<br />
to become a clever country. I said that cleverness is<br />
something that should permeate the entire society and<br />
especially our workplaces.<br />
I am particularly pleased to see that Defence has responded to<br />
that call with the Ready Reserve Scheme.<br />
The Scheme is clever because it is a unique arrangement to<br />
share the talents of high-calibre young Australians between<br />
Defence and Industry. After an initial period of intense<br />
military training, Ready Reserve members will be encouraged to<br />
focus their attention on civilian careers but they will remain<br />
ready for operational service if required.<br />
It is smart because Defence has seen the advantages of using<br />
its own resources to support the development of civilian skills<br />
as a recruitment incentive. Those skills will be of benefit to<br />
both Industry and Defence.<br />
The Scheme will thereby help us bring out the best in ourselves<br />
as a nation. </p>
<p>The conditions of service and employer-support package are<br />
arguably the best in the world.<br />
The Scheme should be extremely attractive to those considering<br />
a Defence career for the first time, as well as to those<br />
present members of the Defence Force who want to pursue a<br />
second career.<br />
And I believe civilian employers will find much to commend in<br />
the Scheme.<br />
Community support, and especially the support and involvement<br />
of employers, is vital to the success of the Scheme.<br />
While employer financial support will be of practical<br />
assistance, I am encouraged to note that initial feed-back from<br />
employers indicates broad support on both the training of<br />
employees and on support for national defence. A partnership<br />
between the Government and employers nationwide is essential<br />
for a cohesive national security policy particularly with<br />
respect to voluntary reserve service.<br />
To date, the Committee for Employer Support of Reserve Forces<br />
has provided the contact between reserves and employers. In<br />
recognition of the increased emphasis now being placed on<br />
reserves, the role of this committee has been expanded and its<br />
title changed to the " Reserves Support Committee"<br />
Responsibility for supporting the Committee will rest with the<br />
newly established Assistant Chief of the Defence Force<br />
Reserves, himself a senior reserve officer.<br />
The Scheme and this Recruiting Campaign is primarily directed<br />
towards those young Australians who are about to complete<br />
secondary schooling. I commend the Scheme to those of you who<br />
wish to make a significant contribution to your nation's<br />
security. It will also allow you to secure a future in a very competitive<br />
educational and career environment. Thus, your contribution to<br />
Australia's future can be twofold.<br />
Before taking any decisions about whether to join the Ready<br />
Reserve Scheme, the first step is to complete your final<br />
examinations. I wish you every success in this regard and in<br />
those very important career decisions that you will make<br />
shortly thereafter.<br />
As you finish your last term of school, I ask each one of you<br />
to consider the benefits to you and Australia of service in the<br />
Australian Defence Force Ready Reserves.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen, I take much pleasure in declaring open<br />
the national Ready Reserve Recruiting Campaign. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
