<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7407</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER NEW SOUTH WALES ALP STATE CONFERENCE MONDAY - 3 OCTOBER 1988</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/10/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007407.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
EMBARG~ OED UNTIL DELIVERY CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTEC<br />
NEW SOUTH WALES ALP STATE COMIEREC<br />
MONDAY 3 OCTOBER 1988<br />
Nearly fifteen months ago in the last days of the Federal<br />
election campaign I asked the Australian people to determine<br />
two issues of overwhelming importance to the future of<br />
Australia. The questions I asked were crystal clear summations of the<br />
basic differences between the Labor Oovernment and our<br />
conservative opponents.<br />
I asked the people of Australia:<br />
who could provide Australia with the responsible<br />
economic management it needed; and<br />
who could provide Australia with the united and credible<br />
political leadership it deserved.<br />
Responsible economic management and united political<br />
loadership no wonder the electorate's verdict was so<br />
definite. Because these factors, then and now, are the essential<br />
components of good government, and, then and now, they are<br />
the unmistakable hallmarks of the Australian Labor Party.<br />
That's why we won re-election last year to our historic<br />
third tern in office.<br />
And that's why John Cain was re-elected to his historic<br />
third term in Viotoria on Saturday.<br />
At the State and Federal levels in Australian politics today<br />
there is the starkest of contrasts between the quality<br />
performance of Labor and the divisiveness which<br />
characterises the Liberals and Nationals In both their<br />
policy choices and their leadership brawls.<br />
_ 2369 </p>
<p>And that statement lbpplies with as much strongth and<br />
relevance where Labor is in office as-it is in Canberra<br />
and Melbourne and Adelaide and Perth. as it does here in<br />
Sydney now we are in opposition.<br />
As Prime Minister I have the very great privilege of leading<br />
a Labor Government which is dedicated to an unrelenting<br />
program of reform aimed at building the prosperity of the<br />
Australian economy and the fairness of Australian society.<br />
And I claim the very great achievement that no Australian<br />
Government has pursued those goals more successfully than<br />
the one I have the honour of leading.<br />
Despite inheriting in 1983 the worst recession this nation<br />
had extperienced in 50 years, and despite facing a subseguent<br />
massive collapse in our terms of trade, we have been<br />
successful beyond precedent.<br />
We are now approaching the half way mark of our third term.<br />
So let me measure our achievement today by reminding you of<br />
the promises we made in the election campaign last year and<br />
by outlining the actions we have taken to keep those<br />
promises. And, even more importantly$ let me make utterly clear to<br />
you, and through you to the people of Australia, our<br />
absolute determination to maintain the pace of economic and<br />
social reform for the remainder of this term and beyond.<br />
Because just as we have achieved a great deal, so we have a<br />
great deal still to do.<br />
Just as we have proven our capacity in the past to provide<br />
united leadership and responsible economic management, so we<br />
are determined to provide that leadership and that<br />
management into the future.<br />
When I launched our campaign for re-election in June last<br />
year I released a 40-page document which set out in detail<br />
the record of our first two terms in office and our detailed<br />
plans for the future; across every department and in every<br />
area of Government activity from social welfare to defence.<br />
And as I drew the campaign to a close I highlighted twelve<br />
specific items on the Government's immediate economic<br />
agenda. Taken together, those commitments represented probably the<br />
most comprehensive and realistic blueprint for action ever<br />
presented to Australian voters and certainly, given the<br />
chaos of the o10position's tax policy, it was the 2i1 such<br />
blueprint presented to the voters in the 1987 campig. </p>
<p>Today I can state with pride that in the fifteen month.<br />
since the election we have acted decisively and<br />
comprehensively on that blueprint for reform.<br />
We are seeing around us, in the cities and towns and on the<br />
farms and in the factories and home. of Australia, the<br />
undeniable evidenae of progress towards our goals our<br />
Labor goals of greater prosperity and greater fairness.<br />
We promised to eliminate the need for child poverty in T<br />
Australia by 1990 and our opponents scoffed. o b<br />
But we are achieving that goal. We have Introduced the nowC<br />
Family Allowance Supplement to direct to the mothers of some<br />
150,000 Australian families an unprecedented amount of T<br />
tax-free cash assistance. A<br />
We promised we would give those families $ 22 a week for each a<br />
child and $ 28 a week for each teenager between the ages of d<br />
13 and 15. 4e<br />
We met that promise -and in the last Budget we increased<br />
the payments by some 10 per cent. 0<br />
We have also increased support for families renting their o<br />
home or flat on the private market those who are feeling 8<br />
the squeeze of the property boom. W<br />
Let me give you an example of how these two measures the<br />
increased Family Allowance Supplement and the rent a<br />
assistance have improved the lot of low income Australian a<br />
families. C<br />
A family of five three children aged 12, 14 and 15 and two N<br />
parents earning up to $ 16,900 and paying private rent will 11<br />
by the middle of next year be receiving $ 106 a week in<br />
Government assistance from these measures.<br />
That is tax-free Income so it's the same as a wage rise ofa<br />
$ 167 a woek.<br />
That's assistance of an unprecedented nature it's further<br />
proof of our capacity to help the people who really need it, A<br />
even in tines of economic restraint.<br />
Bill Kelty of the ACTO had it right when he said the familyT<br />
package represented such a boost to incomes that it would<br />
have taken fifty years to win through traditional industrial<br />
means. it's an achievement I'm proud of and it's an achievement<br />
that we will improve on again in the 1989-90 budget context<br />
to meet the targets we set ourselves.<br />
2 3 6; 4 </p>
<p>That landmark program-rof assistance to needy families is<br />
Just the latest major Instalment in Labor's sweeping social<br />
justice strategy a concerted effort to make Australia a<br />
fairer cociety a society in which economic resources are taxed<br />
f airly and distributed fairly; and<br />
oociety in which there is fair access to all<br />
essential community services.<br />
The fruits of that strategy are seen in our historic reforms<br />
of the taxation system our capital gains tax and fringe<br />
benefits tax which require the more privileged among us to<br />
contribute resources so the needy can be helped.<br />
They are seen in our steady increases in acost by<br />
Australian workers to superannuation cover.<br />
By the end of the current parliamentary term, we will have<br />
doubled the extent of superannuation coverage from<br />
per cent of Australian workers to 80 per cent: so that<br />
eight workers in ten have the security and certainty that<br />
super providus.<br />
Our social justice strategy has also led to a massive<br />
opening up of new opportunities for young Australians at<br />
schools and universities and in job training.<br />
When we came to office, only about one-third of school kids<br />
were staying on at school past the compulsory age. What an<br />
appalling restriction that represented on the life<br />
opportunities of hundreds of thousands of Australian<br />
children. Now, an a result of the decisions we have made, more than<br />
half the kids 57 per cent of them are staying on at<br />
school. By the early 1990s it will be about two-thirds.<br />
The last budget also allocated funds for 40,000 new places<br />
at universities as well as increasing allowances to<br />
students from disadvantaged backgrounds.<br />
Such reforms not only ensure broader horizons for individual<br />
Australians they also mean a-better trained workforce able<br />
to compete with the world.<br />
The fruits of the social justice strategy are also seen int<br />
our 8.3 per cant real increases to the aged pension,<br />
compared to the 2.5 per cent drop under the previous<br />
Covornment; our increased funding for home and community care, this<br />
year totalling $ 209 million; 23615 </p>
<p>our massive increase in the availability of child care,<br />
with our recent decision to fund another 30,000. places A<br />
taking the total under Labor to 94,000 three times the h<br />
number in existence when we came to of fice; and<br />
our efforts towards equality of opportunity f or women.<br />
Host of all, the fruits of our social justice strategy are<br />
seen in its direct interrelationship with our economic<br />
strategy. Our economic strategy has been and will remain aimed at<br />
generating new prosperity in the community; equally, our T<br />
social justice strategy has been and will remain aimed at<br />
distributing that prosperity fairly throughout the<br />
cmmun ity. p<br />
Tehcaotn omIyn wahnyd tIh ec anc osmtmautnei tyt odaaty lathragte itshe a oputolsoiotki vef oro net. hae iin<br />
Because Australians -all Australians stand to gain from0<br />
the combined effects of our economic and social justice0<br />
strategies. Nowhere is this clearer than in two key economic forecaots: 1<br />
the jobs outlook and the prospects for the intersection of t<br />
wages, taxes and inflation. a<br />
In jobs, our achievements are already massive. T in<br />
In the five years we have been in office, we have createdr<br />
mare than one million new jobs. In the fifteen months since d<br />
we were re-elected to our third term we have created over a A<br />
quarter of a million Jobs. u<br />
In all, our rate of jobs growth is four times faster than el<br />
the Fraser/ Howard Government achieved and it is twice as 13<br />
fast as the Western world. 1<br />
Ait the same time the unemployment rate has fallen from P1<br />
per cent when we came to office to 7 per cent now. A<br />
One million more people in jobs. A falling unemploymont<br />
rate. The great result of the restraint and intelligence<br />
displayed by the trade union movement the proud record of<br />
cooperation between trade unions and the Federal Labor<br />
Government under the Accord.<br />
I am confident that we will continue to create jobs in the f<br />
economy for the remainder of this tern and beyond that we<br />
can continue to provide the best form of income security T<br />
there is: a regular pay packet. d<br />
That leads logically to the second key economic forecast<br />
covering the intersection of wages, taxes and inflation. I </p>
<p>The bottom line is t~ at real wages will be maintained over<br />
tho next 12 months.<br />
As Prime Minister, I recognise that many Australian families<br />
have found it difficult to make ends meet over the last lew<br />
years. In particular, middle and lover income earnern have felt<br />
much of the pain of economic reconstruction so far.<br />
Thlat recognition provides the underpinning for tho wage-tax<br />
trade off which we want to see In 1989go we aim to keep<br />
inflation down without the need to sacrifice the living<br />
standards of Australian workers.<br />
That will mean we cam introduce personal tax outs from the<br />
middle of next year tax cuts that will be structured<br />
particularly towards the needs of Australia's lower and<br />
middle income earners.<br />
How large those cuts can be depends on achioving an<br />
appropriate wages outcome this year and on a stable prospect<br />
of restraint for next year.<br />
Blut I want to affirm again in this audienco that the<br />
legitimate aspirations of workers for the maintenance and<br />
the progressive increase in their living standards can be<br />
and will be met.<br />
Tax cuts, more jobs, more superannuation, eliminating tho<br />
need for child poverty that's what we can achieve in the<br />
remainder of our third term. And that's what we will<br />
deliver. And we can guarantee too that we will continue to make the<br />
underlying reforms to the structures and institutions of the<br />
economy that will sustain that progress.<br />
Because when I speak of-the maintenance and improvement in<br />
living standards I do not do so with any pretence that such<br />
progress comes easily.<br />
Australians have become all too familiar over recant years<br />
with the challenges of the International economy to believe<br />
that we can simply pay ourselves more wages., cut our taxes,<br />
improve our welfare structures, unless we get the<br />
fundamentals right first.<br />
It is our recognition of that fact that differentiates us<br />
from the conservatives, and that explains our political and<br />
economic success in recent years.<br />
The conservatives offered tax bribes in 1987, with complete<br />
disregard to the prior question of whether they could be<br />
paid for. 2367 </p>
<p>We now plan for tax cuto to commence next year in the full<br />
knowledgo that they can be afforded, that they are<br />
responsible and that they are structured especially towards<br />
the lower end of the pay scales.<br />
We can do this because we are pushing ahead with the groat<br />
task of reconhtructing the macro-economy as well as tackling<br />
the thorny issues of the mioro-economy. I will be making a<br />
more detailed statement next week outlining how our momentum<br />
for structural reform will be maintained.<br />
Delegates, At our Party's Federal Conference in Hobart in June I said<br />
that Australia was a stronger country, a fairer country, a<br />
country far better equipped to face the future than it was<br />
when we came to office in 1983.*<br />
It is our task to make sure that over the coming years we<br />
continue to build Australia's strength and fairness and<br />
continue to equip it to neat and master the challenges we<br />
face. As we enter the 1990s that challenge won't evaporate. We<br />
still have obstacles to surmount on the path to secured<br />
prosperity. But our achievements so far, and our determination for the<br />
future, make me confident we will succeed.<br />
Delegates, My confidence in our prospects and in the prospects for the<br />
Australian nation stem not just from the policy record of<br />
the last few years.<br />
It stems also from a deeper source within the heart of this<br />
great Labor Party itself.<br />
I can say, with complete truth, that I have never felt a<br />
greater sense of pride in being the Labor Prime Minister<br />
than I do now.<br />
Because Labor at prosent is meeting the challenges of<br />
Government more effectively and with greater unity than it<br />
has ever done bofore.<br />
In the early days of Government the various faotions of our<br />
Party still had to learn how to understand and get on with<br />
each other.<br />
We had probably been in opposition for such a large part of<br />
the post-war decades that we had come to accept factional<br />
disputes as an affordable luxury.<br />
2 3 6 8 </p>
<p>I recall we tended at times to think that if a mozaber of<br />
another faction did not have exactly the same interpretation<br />
of how to reach our Labor goals, then that other faction<br />
member was somehow not absolutely dinkum.<br />
It took us a while in Government to understand the truth<br />
that each group within our Party has its integrity that<br />
all the groups need each other because they are all<br />
essential components of our great Party.<br />
In my judgement, there has been no period in our poet-war<br />
history in which this Party has worked more constructively,<br />
more coherently, more effectively, with such unity, than it<br />
does now.<br />
That is why we are going to meet the challenges of Labor in<br />
Government. hnd let me say particularly to those who work so hard, day<br />
after day, week after week, in the branches you do not get<br />
a great accolade, but without you it would be Impossible for<br />
us in Government to function.<br />
I have never felt before so strongly that we can record with<br />
pride and justification to our bramch supporters that we are<br />
giving you what you want.<br />
Compare all this with the picture our opponents present.<br />
Earlier this year I warned that the conservatives in<br />
Australia today posed the threat of a resurgence of what I<br />
called the dark side of politics.<br />
Virtually everything our opponents have dome and said since<br />
then has proven the truth of my warning.<br />
You will recall that when we cane to office in 1983 this<br />
country was divided against itself because the conservatives<br />
in government had sought to set Australian against<br />
Australian, It is one of our proudest achievements that we have fostered<br />
a healing process so that Australians are working together<br />
to achieve our crucial national goals.<br />
In theso last few weeks we have witnessed a shameful<br />
resurgence of cynicism and political opportunism by the<br />
leadership of the Federal conservative parties.<br />
We have always known they are hopelessly divided among<br />
themselves. It has now become an accepted fact of political<br />
life that the parties which call themselves coalition<br />
parties are utterly incapable of coalescing. 2 3 6' </p>
<p>9 Tcoo nfa or<br />
of n<br />
They cannot govern themselves so they certainly could not that.<br />
govern the country. And I<br />
the no<br />
But in recent weeks we have seen that leadership weakness the re~<br />
and that disunity translated Into a disgraceful attempt to Party<br />
inject discrimination and racism into our immigration years<br />
policies. return<br />
John Hioward is helping to destroy the Liberal Party by his rosoun<br />
comments on Asian immigration.<br />
well, what happens to the Liberal Party is not our concern.<br />
What is our concern, what is my business as Prima Minister,<br />
Is the -damage those commentsc arc doing to the social fabric<br />
of the community and to the economic prospects of the<br />
nation. It is because of the potential for damage potential which<br />
now is in fact being realised that I have affirmed that<br />
under My Government there will be no revival of the White<br />
Australia policy no backtracking on our commitment to<br />
multiculturalism no restoration of discrimination on<br />
grounds of race.<br />
That is non-negotiable.<br />
I toll the Howards, the Sinclairs, the Stones, all that<br />
motley crew they don't understand the Australian people.<br />
Theirs is indeed the dark side of politics. In the end<br />
Australians won't cop it they will reject the<br />
conservatives' brand of racism and of oonfrontationist<br />
social policies.<br />
So when the Australian people see, and they will, the nature<br />
of the conservatives' dark and divided politics;<br />
When they see on the other hand, as they will, the Federal<br />
Government pressing ahead with its momentum of reform for<br />
the remainder of this term and beyond;<br />
When they see, as they will, that Labor is maintaining and<br />
gradually improving living standards for Australians;<br />
When they hear, as they do, Labor leaders such as myself and<br />
Paul Keating and Premier John Cain and Bob Carr speaking<br />
honestly and straightforwardly about the nature of our<br />
economic challenget<br />
Then the Australian people will have all the evidence they<br />
require to determine that their future well-being lies with<br />
Labor.<br />
2370 </p>
<p>To a State branch of our party which is holding its first<br />
conference in opposition in mare than a decade, I can think<br />
of no message of greater confidence for the future than<br />
that.-And I say specifically to you, with confidence, that when at<br />
the next State election the people of Now South Wales see<br />
the renewal of spirit and commitment of the Noew South Wales<br />
Party and compare that spirit and that commitment with 4<br />
years of the dark side of politics in Government they will<br />
return Labor to Government in New South Wales with a<br />
resounding majority. 2,371 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
