<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8656</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP CHIFELY MEMORIAL LECTURE 12 SEPTEMBER 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/09/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008656.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
/ 0<br />
EMBARGOED: 6pm, 12 September 1992<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON V. 3. KEATING, MP<br />
CHIFLEY MEMORIAL LECTrURE, 12 SEPTEMBER 1992<br />
It is a privilege to be asked to speak to you tonight in<br />
honour of one of the very great men of Australian Labor<br />
one of the great men of Australian history.<br />
It is a particular privilege to speak here in Bathurst,<br />
the town with which the name Ben Chit ley will forever be<br />
identified. It is a privilege to come after him, and it is with a<br />
sense of some humility that I find myself standing here<br />
in the town where an author of our ambitions lived.<br />
Labor's ambitions. Australia's ambitions.<br />
For me this occasion is the more momentous because Just<br />
now we Australians face a decade in which the fate of our<br />
ambitions hangs in the balance.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen<br />
Let me preface this address by saying something very<br />
simple. I believe that Australia is a Country of extraordinary<br />
achievements and equally extraordinary potential.<br />
I believe Australians are people of rare quality.<br />
And I believe that in the next few years, despite the<br />
difficulties and the unc~ rtainties, Australia will<br />
triumph. I feel the need to say this to counter the doomsayers on<br />
the other side of politics who seem determined to<br />
belittle both our achievements and our prospects.<br />
That's why I feel the nead to say it at a time when wQ<br />
have both a need and a right to feel confident, it is, to<br />
say the least strange to hear our altern.. tive leaders<br />
call Australians " lazy" and " embarrassing".*<br />
That's why I feel the need to say it. </p>
<p>74 2<br />
And I know I am right whben I say it.<br />
I will tell you why.<br />
I have watched this last decade as Australia grasped the<br />
nettle as no other developed country did.<br />
I have watched Australians radically transform their<br />
industrial culture, vastly increase their productivity<br />
and pull the country up to levels of competitiveness<br />
unimaginable a decade ago.<br />
Internationally competitive levels.<br />
I have seen them accept the necessity for structural<br />
change. That is what has convinced me that we will succeed.<br />
SU. cs is what convinces mne.<br />
Never have we worked harder and made more progress<br />
towards the reali-Sation Of our ambitions than we have in<br />
the last decade.<br />
Never have we had such an opportunity to reap the rewards<br />
and deliver them to future generations than we have in<br />
the next decade.<br />
And never has all this work and all this hope been so<br />
threatened as it is now.<br />
I am talking about our ambitions for an enlarged and<br />
enlightened social democracy.<br />
An Australia in which energy and opportunity flourish,<br />
where faith in oursslves and our country abounds, and the<br />
nation's capacity to care for a11 its citizens is<br />
paramount. It seems to me that if the last is not true the first two<br />
must also be false.<br />
These, Ben Chifley said, were the things worth fighting<br />
for. The primacy of social justice, social cohesion,<br />
equal opportunity the fair go.<br />
They seem to me to be immutable facts of our nature.<br />
Nothing has moved them in 100 years.<br />
War, depression, booms and busts, outbursts of imperial<br />
jingoism, cold war, cultural invasions of various kinds,<br />
have all at times challenged these beliefs: but they hL~ ve<br />
always re-emerged often in the shape of men like Ben<br />
Chifley. </p>
<p>The longer I stay in public life, the more Australians I<br />
meet, the more I am convinced that the values of this<br />
country were written by the people, by working people.<br />
And that is their strength.<br />
That is why they won't be sold. Those people who<br />
presently want to change them will find implacable<br />
resistance. As a Labor Government, we believe that so long as we<br />
honour those principles, and push on towards our social<br />
democratic goals, even in the face of this recession and<br />
the damage it has caused, Australians will stay with us.<br />
Whenever the duties of his office allowed him, Ben<br />
Chifley used to drive up here from Canberra.<br />
Modern Prime Ministers might envy him both the contact<br />
with the natural landscape and the chance it gave for<br />
reflection. If a man was ever going to see a Light on the Hill this<br />
was the way to do it.<br />
As he drove along and the sun set over the western plains<br />
the " vision splendid of Australia Unlimited" must have<br />
seemed as good as real.<br />
Many things have changed. The Australia Chifley knew was<br />
a vastly different country.<br />
But moro than four decados on, Son Chifley's vision<br />
remains, to a remarkable extent, our own.<br />
He was a nation builder.<br />
As we are nation builders.<br />
His great projects in the national interest, like the<br />
Snowy Mountains Scheme, are our One Nation: our $ 500<br />
million National Standard Gauge Rail Highway linking<br />
Brisbane, Sydney, Melbourne, Adelaide and Perth, and<br />
linking ports, rail and roads; our $ 2 billion dollar<br />
development of the nation's roads: our reforms to<br />
aviation: our National Electricity Grid.<br />
The immigration policy developed in Chifley's time the<br />
most profound social undertaking in our history is<br />
continued in the multicultural policies developed in<br />
ours, the most successful policies of their kind anywhere<br />
in the world.<br />
Chifley was a social reformer.<br />
AS we are social reformers. </p>
<p>His reforms to the health system and social security, are<br />
our Medicare, and our broad network of social programs<br />
developed in the past decade which are at least the equal<br />
of the most advanced nations on earth.<br />
Ban Chifley believed there was a role for government.<br />
So do we we assert it.<br />
His car industry is our car industry.<br />
Much more modern, changing but the same one.<br />
Ban Chifley saw an Australia which was too dependent on<br />
its primary products, too dependent on Britain for its<br />
trade, too short of capital and skills.<br />
Like us, he believed we had to diversify our industry,<br />
look to new markets for our products, raise our capital<br />
and skills base.<br />
We have done these things like no government before us.<br />
Were he here now, in 1992, the Superannuation Guarantee,<br />
the creation of the Australian National Training<br />
Authority, the enormous growth in universities and<br />
secondary education retention rates, would all be music<br />
to his ears.<br />
So too would be the rapid growth in the last decade of<br />
our manufacturing exports which, for the first time in<br />
our history, now exceed the volume of our exports of<br />
minerals and primary produce.<br />
Ben Chifley would be pleased to see that we are making<br />
things for the world to buy, for he knew that this was a<br />
great measure of our progress.<br />
Chifley believed in the principle of gathering all our<br />
strength and all our resources towards a common national<br />
purpose. He had served in that wartime government which, through<br />
cooperation with business and the unions, and through<br />
calling on the best feelings of Australians, set and<br />
achieved national goals.<br />
One Nation is in that tradition.<br />
The Accord is in that tradition.<br />
The lowest number of strike~ s in thirty years is in that<br />
tradition. </p>
<p>In that tradition we have called on Australians to adopt<br />
the principle of partnership between the various tiers<br />
of government, between businass and unions and<br />
communities so that all Australians may participate and<br />
all their energies go toward the common national cause.<br />
Our guiding philosophy is social democratic, by which I<br />
mean democracy of the broadest kind: the maximization of<br />
rights and liberties, the extension of both individual<br />
opportunity and social justice.<br />
In this we are right. Look at the world. The successful<br />
countries are those which have followed this path.<br />
The successful economies have been free market economies:<br />
the successful societies have been those which have<br />
combined this with democratic freedoms and sophisticated<br />
integrated csniaI programs.<br />
They have invested in their own ciuItura. 1 development.<br />
They have cushioned the impact of economic change by not<br />
losing sight of their responsibility to people.<br />
Communism has failed. Less spectacular but no less<br />
emphatic has been the failure of monetarism and laissez<br />
faire economics: under all its appellations<br />
Thatcherite, Reagan and Rogernomic.<br />
It's no accident perhaps that they have both gone down<br />
the same historical chute.<br />
Both have a strain of fanaticism. Both are regressive<br />
and both regress to nineteenth century pseudo-scientific<br />
ideals. Both have failed and if the Liberal Party thinks that<br />
it will succeed in the 1990s in the hands of a Social<br />
Darwinist with new batteries they are wrong.<br />
Desperately wrong. Again.<br />
And we might ask ourselves why it is that the past has<br />
such a magnetic attraction for our conservatives.<br />
Why it is in their nature to frequently advance to the<br />
rear. Why Bob Menzies was drawn to the British Empire long<br />
after it had turned up its toes, and John Howard in turn<br />
is drawn to Menzies and the torpor, wastod<br />
opportunities and withering of our culture in the Menzies<br />
era. </p>
<p>Recognising that Menzies was a bit of a socialist by his<br />
own radical right standards, John Hewson finds he must go<br />
even further back for his ideals to the economic and<br />
social thinking of early industrial capitalism albeit<br />
re-constituted and disgorged in the textbooks of the<br />
business schools of the late seventies.<br />
Why is he attracted to these models which caused such<br />
damage to the fabric of the societies in which they were<br />
applied?<br />
Why, for instance, in a society with one of the most<br />
sophisticated social security systems in the world, does<br />
he want to introduce measures characteristic of societies<br />
in decay?<br />
Why does he say that if we reach back to help the<br />
underprivileged they will rdrag Lis down?<br />
Why, in the last decade of the twentieth century does he<br />
utter the sentiments of the first half of the nineteenth?<br />
Why, if not because he holds ordinary Australians in<br />
contempt?<br />
Why does he paint the efforts of Australians as feeble?<br />
Why do they embarrass him? Why does he paint our<br />
progress as the opposite of progress?<br />
Why does he attack successful Australian businesses as if<br />
they were failures?<br />
Why, as Australians march bravely toward the future does<br />
Dr Hewson point back toward a wasteland and shout<br />
There. Go therel?<br />
Why, if not because he has no vision, only ideology?<br />
Why, if not because he is fanatical?<br />
I have always believed that the Labor Party and Labor<br />
Governments should keep their shoulders against the door.<br />
Reform is what we are here for.<br />
But we are for change anid continuity.<br />
We press forward, but we take society with us.<br />
We build, but we don't destroy.<br />
In the last decade we Australians have learned something<br />
about the art of gathering our resources, about<br />
cooperation, partnership, working together. Principles<br />
which have been fundamental to the success of other<br />
countries, and fundamental to the successas we have had. </p>
<p>In this decade I think we must take those principles<br />
further. I think that we owe it to this and succeeding generations<br />
of Australians to see that an identity entirely our own<br />
has a chance to flourish.<br />
To see that we give these generations the opportunity to<br />
choose those institutions and symbols which reflect their<br />
sentiments and their reality, and not those of a bygone<br />
era. To see that faith in this Australia this liberal,<br />
democratic, tolerant, diverse, independent Australia<br />
has a chance to grow.<br />
I believe we would be derelict in our duty to the future<br />
if we did not give the Australians of this post-imperial,<br />
multicultural stage in our history the same opportunity<br />
as those of a century ago.<br />
I believe it would energise us, I believe it would give<br />
us new faith and inspiration, I believe it would<br />
guarantee the life of our best traditions and<br />
institutions.<br />
And I think we should have the courage to open the debate<br />
on the institutions and symbols of our nationhood.<br />
As I have said, many of the things we have done Ben<br />
Chifley would have hoped to do.<br />
But we have done more than that we've done things in<br />
social, industrial and economic policy beyond the compass<br />
of his imagination.<br />
We have developed policies to benefit Australian women<br />
which have put Australia back in the vanguard of<br />
international progress where we used to be in the days<br />
when Australia was regarded as perhaps the most socially<br />
advanced nation in the world.<br />
Labor has put increasing opportunity and choice for women<br />
back in the centre of social reform.<br />
For example, since 1983, of the 1.5 million new jobs<br />
created 64 per cent or about two thirds have been filled<br />
by women.<br />
And Labor has supported them.<br />
In the last few years our equal pay strategy has narrowed<br />
the gap between men's and women's earnings.<br />
On average women now earn 83 cents for every dollar<br />
earned by men a marked improvement on the 67 cents when<br />
we came to power. </p>
<p>Our affirmative action policies are encouraging employers<br />
to increase women's job opportunities.<br />
Labor has supported women through a fivefold increasa in<br />
the number of child care pieces; through improved access<br />
to superannuation; improved access to education;<br />
increased income Support for families; special programs<br />
addressing women's health needs.<br />
Labor has legislated to protect women against<br />
discrimination. In fact, the United Nations Commission on the Status of<br />
Women declared this year that Australia leads the world<br />
in the implementation of programs to eliminate<br />
discrimination against women.<br />
We will build on these achievements we always build.<br />
Our opponents want to undo them they always want to<br />
undo thoem.<br />
They will abolish the Affirmative Action Agency and the<br />
Equal Pay Unit.<br />
Through their consumption tax they will tax the household<br />
budget for which women are generally responsible. it is<br />
a tax on food, clothing and pharmaceuticals just for a<br />
start. They will tax child care, and they make no commitment to<br />
maintaining fee relief, nor to expanding the number of<br />
places. And under the Coalition's enterprise bargaining system,<br />
women in the workforce can expect their earnings to<br />
erode. Without the protection of the Tndustrial Relations<br />
Commission, which our workplace bargaining system<br />
guarantees, women workers will see their pay relative to<br />
men reduced to the levels existing when we came to<br />
office. That is what happens in the United States, where a<br />
decentralised wages system has kept women's earnings to<br />
less than 70 cents for every dollar earned by men.<br />
The Coalition will reduce support for women. They will<br />
take away eligibility for their family allowance from<br />
100,000 families. Stop paying wives' pensions where the<br />
spouses of disability support pensioners are under<br />
Take away the sole parents' pension when the youngest<br />
child turns 12. </p>
<p>I could say a great deal more about the differences<br />
between Labor and the Coalition. They are as the last<br />
few weeks have clearly demonstrated quite profound.<br />
Week by week over the next few months you will see the<br />
differences grow clearer in every field of economic and<br />
social policy.<br />
Dr Hewson's Fightback, is, after all, a comprehensive<br />
document. The most comprehensive thing ever devised, he<br />
says. It is the Bible of his brave new world.<br />
Nothing escapes it with the possible exception of aged<br />
care which doesn't get a mention.<br />
I will refer to only a couple of areas tonight.<br />
They didn't miss health.<br />
Medicare a quality, affordable, universal system will<br />
be pushed towards the American model which offers care to<br />
only 80 per cent of the population at 50 per cent greater<br />
cost. They will cut the rebate from 85% to 75% and they will<br />
abolish bulk billing except for those with health cards.<br />
Speaking of benefits, the Coalition promises to cut<br />
unemployment benefits after nine months; cut employment<br />
programs; privatise the CES; introduce longer waiting<br />
periods for assistance; and pay young people $ 3 or $ 3.50<br />
an hour for work.<br />
Unemployment is the greatest social problems of our time.<br />
It haunted Chif ley, as it did all those who lived through<br />
the Great Depression.<br />
The high levelu uf unemployment we afe now experiencing<br />
are anathema to a party whose creed has always been full<br />
employment. The disappointment is all the greater because we had done<br />
so phenomenally well to grow 1.5 million new jobs in the<br />
1980S. It is entirely unacceptable that a tenth of the work<br />
force should basically bear all the burden of structural<br />
change and the recession.<br />
The principal aim of all our efforts in the past six<br />
months has been to reduce un~. mployment, to get<br />
Australians who have fallen out of the system back into<br />
it. That is why this year we will spend S1.1 billion on<br />
labour market programs. Why we've spent one per cent of<br />
GDP or $ 4 billion to stimulate the economy and boost<br />
employment. </p>
<p>It's why we held the national summit on youth<br />
unemployment, out of which came a universally applauded<br />
package of employment and training programs for Young<br />
Australians. It's why we established this year, in an educational<br />
revolution, the Australian National Training Authority<br />
to lift the quality and status of technical and further<br />
education to the highest level: the level it must be if<br />
Australians are to have the skills they will need for the<br />
well-paid and interesting jobs, and if modern Australia<br />
industry is to have the skilled workforce it will need.<br />
That unemployment is also why we are determined on a path<br />
of economic growth.<br />
we must have growth. It's the only way we can sensibly<br />
re-structure and~ create jobs.<br />
To survive today as a well-employed nation we have to<br />
trade. To trade we have to be productive.<br />
To be productive means more product from fewer people.<br />
The remedy to this redundancy can only be mnr<br />
production. Our aim then is two-fold greater efficiency and greater<br />
production. Both depend, we say, on mutual understandings on<br />
national agreement about the direction of national<br />
income. Growth of the order we require can only be achieved in a<br />
framework in which business, labour and the Government<br />
agree on these directions.<br />
To an extent that would astonish Ben Chifley who lived in<br />
the long era of habitual conflict, that framework has<br />
been established.<br />
It is generally agreed in Australia now that we can't<br />
have hard-won growth frittered away in senseless price<br />
and wage rounds.<br />
You can't do it without the lower interest rates and low<br />
inflation which an incomes policy alone can harmoniously<br />
provide. Equally we can't have efficiency in a culture of<br />
conflict. </p>
<p>The speed with which this understanding has come to<br />
management and unions alike has surprised even those who<br />
promoted the idea.<br />
The speed of the revolution in work practices has<br />
surprised everyone.<br />
The speed with which our export of elaborately<br />
transformed manufactures has grown, even through the<br />
recession, has surprised them too.<br />
It is why I say that I believe in our future. I believe<br />
in the capacity of the Australian people. I believe in<br />
the path we are taking.<br />
We have done the fundamental things, the brave thi ngs,<br />
and the Australian people have responded bravely.<br />
We have given Australia a chance to grow.<br />
And Australians have seized it.<br />
A decade ago, as we came out of recession we had double<br />
digit inflation. Today we have entrenched our competitive<br />
advantage with one of the lowest inflation rates in the<br />
industrial world.<br />
A decade ago our work and managerial practice was<br />
notoriously bad. Today Best Practice is not just a<br />
catchword, but increasingly a reality and its helping<br />
us to export in ways we never thought possible. In 1992<br />
Australia is exporting motor vehicle engines to Japan.<br />
Both our manufactured exports and service exports have<br />
tripled over the past decade.<br />
A decade ago we imported more goods and services than we<br />
exported. Today we export more than we import.<br />
And increasingly we export goods with high levels of<br />
value adding like motor vehicles atnd motor vehicle<br />
parts, computers, scientific equipment, industrial<br />
machinery, telecommunicati ons equipment.<br />
These goods recorded growth of 216 per cent since 1983<br />
twice the growth of mineral exports, nearly six times the<br />
growth of rural exports.<br />
In that period motor vehicle exports have grown from M2<br />
million to $ 414 million.<br />
Office machines and computers from $ 19 million to $ 41S<br />
million. Industrial machinery from $ 235 million to S' 199 million. </p>
<p>To name a few. And the greater part of the growth has<br />
been in the past two or three years 57 per cent growth<br />
between 1988 and 1991.<br />
Most of the exports been into Asia where so much<br />
potential for Australia lies.<br />
We are making progress on all the important front&amp;<br />
including the wharves where productivity has doubled.<br />
We are developing a food processing industry, estimated<br />
to be worth $ 7 billion by the end of the decade.<br />
There are opportunities for similarly huge development of<br />
our construction industry, our finance and tourism<br />
industries.-These are the reasons why I say that even in these tough<br />
times there is great reason for hope and confidence.<br />
And why I say it is Australians who give us reason for<br />
that confidence for these achievements are due to their<br />
work, their skills, their imagination, their belief in<br />
Australia. In recent days you may have noticed that the Opposition,<br />
which for so long has been saying we are the antithesis<br />
of everything they stand for, have begun to say that on<br />
certain key issues there is very little separating us.<br />
Well, as John Dlawkins reminded them the other day,<br />
imitation is the sincerest form of flattery.<br />
But it's a very poor imitation.<br />
It shouldn't fool anyone.<br />
They're doing the chameleon on tariffs but ask the car<br />
industry if they're fooled. Ask the sugar industry.<br />
There is a fundamental difference on tariffs.<br />
Our starting point is that there shomuld be a car<br />
industry. That there should be a sugar industry.<br />
There's is simply " restructure or perish".<br />
There's is to quote Mr McLachlan, " if we are wrong that<br />
will be a tragedy."<br />
Like I said tell that to the working people of<br />
Adelaide, Geelong and Melbourne.<br />
There's a also fundamental difference on the most basic<br />
relationship in the economy industrial relationS.<br />
Already we have 300 registered enterprise agreements. </p>
<p>By early next year we will have half the workforce<br />
covered. But we also have and this is the great difference the<br />
Industrial Relations Commission setting minimum rates in<br />
awards, and so providing a safety net through which<br />
employees cannot fall.<br />
There is a basic difference on education. It's expressed<br />
most eloquently in these simple figures under the<br />
Coalition, if you want to send your children, or<br />
yourself, to university it's going to cost you $ 24,000<br />
for an arts degree up to $ 150,000 for medicine.<br />
There are basic differences on health policy, women's<br />
policy, environment policy, policy on arts and cultural<br />
development. There is a profound difference about what sort of<br />
community and nation Australia can be.<br />
It is a difference in philosophy we start from<br />
different beginnings and seek different ends.<br />
We start with the Australian people and they will get us<br />
there. Really, no one ever put it better than Ben Chiflep.<br />
" I try to think of the labour movement, not as putting an<br />
extra sixpence in someone's pocket, or making somebody<br />
Prime Minister or Premier, but as a movement bringing<br />
something better to the people, better standarde of<br />
living, greater happiness to the mass of the people. we<br />
have a great objective the light on the hill which we<br />
aim to reach by working for the betterment of mankind."<br />
That is the base, the sentiment from which we begin.<br />
But our ambitions are now greater and so are our<br />
achievements. The light on the hill does not symbolise where we are<br />
going any more. We are past that stage.<br />
It does not symbolise where we have been. We look<br />
forward, not back.<br />
it symbolises why we have these ambitions, these goals<br />
for the Deople, for the nation.<br />
Thank you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
