<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18965</transcript-id>
    <title>Speech to the Gala Dinner - Fortieth Anniversary of Diplomatic Relations Between Australia and The People&#039;s Republic Of China</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/12/2012</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Parliament House, Canberra</p>
<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS OMITTED </p>
<p>In a formal sense, we gather as friends to acknowledge a single diplomatic event in the life of our two countries.</p>
<p>On December 21, 1972, in Paris, the Governments of Australia and China signed a joint communiqué.</p>
<p>A brief document  -  only five paragraphs  -  recognising One China and marking the beginning of a lasting friendship.</p>
<p>Yet in these diplomatic phrases lay a great act of daring.</p>
<p>For two decades, the Government of Australia set its face against recognition.</p>
<p>Yet one man stood firm all his political life  -  Gough Whitlam.</p>
<p>Gough went to China in 1971 not because it was easy, but because it was right.</p>
<p>The war in Vietnam was still raging and the weight of domestic opinion was against him.</p>
<p>But there was a certain grandeur in the courage of his journey.</p>
<p>Stephen Fitzgerald wrote recently that:</p>
<p>“There is nothing in Australian foreign policy history to compare with that China visit. ... It was an expedition of great bravado and exposure but great political judgment and luck.”</p>
<p>So in this Great Hall of the Australian people, we recall a meeting in another Great Hall of another great people, four decades ago.</p>
<p>It was a modest group  -  just six Australian members  -  but its impact on our foreign policy was profound.</p>
<p>The meeting with Premier Zhou Enlai was simple and gracious.</p>
<p>Two statesmen ready to embrace reality and open the doors upon an unlikely friendship.</p>
<p>Whitlam made that journey because he understood China was not a country to be feared.</p>
<p>But a nation seeking to right historic wrongs and engage more widely with the world.</p>
<p>For Australia, engagement with China reflected our more confident voice on the world stage.</p>
<p>Like the rest of the Whitlam venture, it was a time of optimism and new beginnings.</p>
<p>Four decades on, let us never forget how high were the stakes or how great was the prize being sought.</p>
<p>So tonight we honour “those who were there”.</p>
<p>We remember those who shared in the drama of those days but are no longer with us: Margaret Whitlam, Alan Renouf, Tom Burns, Mick Young.</p>
<p>Gough Whitlam cannot be with us in person but he is so very much in our hearts tonight.</p>
<p>So are Graham Freudenberg and Rex Patterson.</p>
<p>With us, though, are others who made this anniversary possible, including Stephen Fitzgerald, who became our first Ambassador to the People's Republic.</p>
<p>The extraordinary evolution of our relationship with China stands on the shoulders of this generation. </p>
<p>Trade levels increased a thousandfold.</p>
<p>Great Chinese cities built with Australian iron ore.</p>
<p>Growing investment.</p>
<p>The tens of thousands of Chinese students and tourists visiting every year.</p>
<p>Today, we welcome China's rise into the rules-based global system.</p>
<p>We value deep relationships with China at every level.</p>
<p>And we understand that with such different cultures and histories, we will occasionally disagree on matters of policy and principle, yet will always express any disagreement with a sense of proportion and respect.</p>
<p>If this is a night for celebrating a remarkable past, it is also a night to look to the future.</p>
<p>For many years now, trade and people-to-people links have formed the bulk of our relationship.</p>
<p>As we approach the half-century of our diplomatic ties in the years to come, we must craft a new and deeper phase of our relationship.</p>
<p>That will mean stronger government-to-government links.</p>
<p>Stronger bilateral architecture to better coordinate the breadth of our modern relationship, including on foreign and strategic issues, the global economy and our trade and investment ties.</p>
<p>A comprehensive country strategy that gives greater clarity and ambition for our shared objectives for our relationship.</p>
<p>And a stronger diplomatic footprint in China, including a new consulate-general in Chengdu, which I announced earlier this year.</p>
<p>And my Government's commitment to a further post to follow later, in Shenyang.</p>
<p>I am the seventh Australian Prime Minister to have visited China since Gough Whitlam became the first in 1973.</p>
<p>And I hope to have the great honour to return next year as China's new leadership moves into place.</p>
<p>Much has changed in both our countries since our diplomatic relations began.</p>
<p>The Australia of 1972 was an insular land.</p>
<p>Asia was unfamiliar to many Australians, and China more so.</p>
<p>Today one in ten Australians speaks an Asian language and China is the largest source of migration to our shores.</p>
<p>The reality of living in Asia is more present to us than ever before.</p>
<p>China can look back on decades of reform and truly say that her people have never been more prosperous.</p>
<p>The land of Mao suits and bicycles has become the nation of shining cities and high-speed train networks.</p>
<p>When we see poverty halved and high school enrolments doubled, we are admiring of your success.</p>
<p>When we see China lead the world in renewable energy, we are confident in your future.</p>
<p>Forty years on, the work begun with such high hopes endures.</p>
<p>Our partnership is now of deep strategic importance to us both.</p>
<p>Our peoples are partners: working together still.</p>
<p>Creating wealth together.</p>
<p>Working for peace together.</p>
<p>And sharing a bright future together.</p>
<p>So tonight I pay tribute to a nation esteemed by Australia and honoured in the world.</p>
<p>Our true and enduring friend: The People's Republic of China.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
