<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6316</transcript-id>
    <title>FOLLOWING IS TEXT OF SPEECH GIVEN BY PRIME MINISTER AT BANQUET HOSTED BY PREMIER ZHAO ON 8 FEBRUARY</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/02/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006316.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>PRIME MSTRAL1LA&amp;<br />
FOLLOWING IS TEXT OF SPEECH GIVEN BY PRIME MINISTER AT LANQUET<br />
HOSTED BY PREMIER ZHAO ON 8 FEBRUARY.<br />
BEGINS.. SPEECH IN REPLY, PREMIER ZHAO'S BANQUET<br />
WEDNESDAY, 8 FEBRUARY 1984<br />
MR PREMIER, DISTINGUISHED GUESTS,<br />
THANK YOU FOR YOUR WARM WELCOHE TO PEKING.<br />
MR PREMIER, I AM VERY GLAD TO BE HERE AND TO MEET WITH YOU AGAIN.<br />
IT WAS A GREAT PLEASURE TO ME THAT YOU HERE THE FIRST<br />
HEAD OF GOVERNMENT TO VISIT AUSTRALIA AFTER MY GOVERNMENT TOOK<br />
OFFICE. I RECALL VERY CLEARLY THE VALUE OF OUR DISCUSSION ON THAT<br />
OCCASION. THE ACCOUNT WHICH YOU GAVE ME THEN OF DEVELOPMENTS IN CHINA<br />
UNDER YOUR GOVERNMENT WAS AN IMPORTANT CONSIDERATION IN MY DESIRE TO<br />
VISIT CHINA NOW.<br />
I WAS THEN AND AM NOW ESPECIALLY INTERESTED IN THE FUNDAMENTAL<br />
SIGNIFICANCE FOR CHINA AND FOR THE WORLD AT LARGE OF THE COMPREHENSIVE<br />
PROGRAM OF MODERNATION YOUR GOVERNMENT HAS EMBARKED ON.<br />
THE CHANGES IN INSTITUTIONS AND ATTITUDES IMPLIED BY THAT<br />
PROGRAM ARE, I SENSE, MOMENTOUS AND HOLD THE PROSPECT OF CHANGING<br />
THE FACE OF CONTEMPORARY CHINA.<br />
THIS I RECOGNISE IS BEING ACHIEVED ON THE BASIS OF AN<br />
ESSENTIAL CONTINUITY OF CH4INESE GOVERNMENT APPROACH. THE PROGRAM<br />
OF ECONOMIC AND SOCIAL CHANGE INVOLVED APPEARS TO BE CAREFULLY CALCULATED<br />
TO PROVIDE FOR CONTINUED HIGH GROWTH AND FURTHER IMPROVED<br />
LIVING STANDARDS. DRAWING AS IT DOES ON4 AN IMPORTANT ESTABLISHED<br />
TRADITION OF WISE POLITICAL LEADERSHIP AS EXEMPLIFIED EARLIER BY<br />
PREMIER ZHOU ENLAI I WOULD CERTAINLY EXPECT CONTINUED SUCCESS.<br />
LAST YEAR, WHEN I OPENED THE EXHIBITION IN CANBERRA OF THE<br />
EMPEROR QIN'S ENTOMBED W4ARRIORS I NOTED THAT THE NEW LEADERS OF<br />
CHINA WOULD LEAVE BEHIND A VERY DIFFERENT LEGACY FROM THE MEMORIAL<br />
MONUMENTS OF THAT EMPEROR. </p>
<p>I BELIEVE THAT CHINA' S CONTEMPORARY LEADERSHIP WILL BE<br />
REMEMrERED NOT ONLY IN CHINA BUT ALSO ELSEWHERE FOR HAVING ESTABLISHED<br />
A WISE AND PRA-) tIATIC SUCCESSION OF LEADERS TO STRENGTHEN AND<br />
LEAD CHINA FORWARD.<br />
THIS NEW STRENGTH IN CHINA GIVES US GREAT CONFIDENCE IN<br />
APPROACHING DISCUSSIONS WITH YOU AND IN BUILDING RELATIONS WITH4<br />
CHINA. IT WILL BE CLEAR TO US ALL THAT MUCH HAS CHhNGED IN OUR TWO<br />
COUNTRIES AND IN RELATIONS BETWEEN US IN THE PAST TWELVE YEARS.<br />
FOLLOWING ON THE 1971 INITIATIVE OF MY DISTINGUISHED PREDECESSOR,<br />
GJOUGH WHITLAM, WE NOW HAVE IMPORTANT AND SUBSTANTIAL LINKS. THESE<br />
ARE BUILT ON' THE RECOGNITION THAT A SUBSTANTIAL RELATIONSHIP WITH<br />
CHINA, ACKNOWLEDGING CHINA'S IMPORTANT ROLE IN THE REGION AND THE<br />
WORLD, SHOULD BE CENTRAL TO AUSTRALIAN FOREIGN POLICY.<br />
OUR FUNDAMENTAL JUDGEMIENT IS THAT OUR RELATIONS WITH CHINA<br />
ARE OF GREAT IMPORTANCE IN THEIR OWN RIGHT. THEY DO NOT COME ABOUT<br />
BECAUSE OF INTERESTS WE MAY HAVE ELSEWHERE. AUSTRALIA AN4D CHINA<br />
ARE PERMANENTLY TOGETHER IN THIS REGION. WE ARE ALREADY OLD<br />
FRIENDS '' ILAO PENGYOU AND WE WILL CONTINUE TO BUILD RELATrIONS<br />
ON TH4AT BASIS. THAT CHINA NOW ALSO H4AS IMPORTANT LINKS WITH OUR<br />
TRADITIONAL ALLIES AND FRIENDS FURTHER FACILITATES AUSTIALIA-CHINA<br />
RELATIONS. I ATTACH PARTICULAR IMPORTANCE TO THE CONSTRUCTIVE DISCUSSION<br />
WE HAVE HAD TODAY ABOUT REGIONAL PRESSURE POINTS SUCH AS KOREA AND<br />
ABOUT THE TASKS IN ARMS CONTROL AND DISARMAMENT.<br />
THE GOVERNMENTS OF THE WORLD SPEND WELL OVER DLRS 1 MILLION<br />
EVERY MINUTE ON ARMS. IN.. A WORLD INCREASINGLY BESET BY PROBLEMS OF<br />
POVERTY AND INEQUALITY, SUCH LEVELS OF DEFENCE EXPENDITURE REPRESENT<br />
A TRAGIC DISTORTION OF H4UMAN VALUES AND PRIORITIES.<br />
CHINA, AS A NUCLEAR POWER, CAN I BELIEVE DO A GREAT DEAL TO<br />
ASSIST IN ENSURING NOT ONLY THAT ARMS CONTROL AND DISARMAMENT<br />
REMAIN TOWARDS THE TOP-OF THE INTERNATIONAL AGENDA~, BUT ALSO THAT<br />
ACTUAL PROGRESS IS MADE.<br />
ALTHOUGH AUSTRALIA'S AND CHINA'S STRATEGIC CIRCUMSTANCES ARE<br />
DIFFERENT, WE HAVE MADE A GOOD BEGINNING IN OUR TALKS TO WHAT I<br />
HOPE WILL BE A SUSTAINED DIALOGUE BETWEEN OUR COUNTRIES ON ARMS<br />
CONTROL AND DISARMAMENT ISSUES. BESIDES ENHANCING UNDERSTANDING<br />
AND COOPERATION BETWEEN US, THIS SHOULD HELP TO SECURE PROGRESS<br />
IN AN AREA WH4ICH IS SO CRUCIAL TO MANKIND'S FUTURE SURVIVIAL AND<br />
PROSPERITY. I HAVE BEEN PLEASED ALSO TO TALK WITH YOU ABOUT TH4E ECONOMIC<br />
DEVELOPMENT OF OUR REGION.<br />
THERE IS NOW WIDESPREAD RECOGNITION THAT THE ASIA-PACIFIC REGION<br />
IS DEMONSTRATING TH4E MOST RAPID AND DYNAMIC ECONOMIC DEVELOPMIENT IN<br />
THE WORLD.<br />
THIS FACT PRESENTS PARTICULAR OPPORTUNITIES FOR ALL OF US WITHIN<br />
TH4E REGION AND PROMISES TO BE OF VITAL SIGNIFICANCE FOR GLOBAL<br />
ECONOMIC PROSPERITY IN THE DECADES AHEAD. </p>
<p>BUT WE SHALL ONLY REALISE THE FULL POTENTIAL. OF THIS REGILIN IF<br />
WE CAN JO-INTLY OR BY PARALLEL PATHS WORK TO SOLVE MAJOR PlPOBLEMS.<br />
LAST YEAR, MR PREMIER, YOU EXPRESSED CONCERN ABOUT THE TRADE<br />
IMBALANCE BETWEEN OUR TWO COUNTRIES.<br />
WE HAVE WORKED HARD ON OUR SIDE TO ADDRESS THE SUBSTANTIVE ISSUES<br />
IN OUR * rRADE AND LOOK FORW4ARD TO MAJOR GROWTH IN THAT RELATIONSHIP<br />
IN THE YEARS AHEAD.<br />
WE SH4ALL BE GOING IN OUR OWN TALKS TOMORROW MR PREMIER, TO THE<br />
SPECIFICS OF WHAT WILL BE INVOLVED IN SECURING THIS RESULT. I<br />
SHOULD SIMPLY AT THIS STAGE LIKE TO OBSERVE THAT UNDERPINNING ALL<br />
OUR EFFORTS MUST BE A COMMITMENT TO MODERNISATION AS A MEANS OF<br />
SECURING NOT ONLY HIGH STANDARDS OF LIVING BUT ALSO A MORE EQUITABLE<br />
SPREAD OF BENEFITS THROUGH THE COMMUNITY AT LARGE.<br />
MODERNISATION IS A PROCESS OF DYNAMIC CHANGE.<br />
WITH IT ONE CAN ANTICIPATE NOT ONLY ENHANCED PROSPERITY BUT<br />
ALSO, OVER TIME, A SUBSTANTIAL UPGRADING OF COMMUNITY SERVICES<br />
SUCH AS HEALTH AND EDUCATION.<br />
. WITH SUCH CHANGE THE GROUND IS ALSO LAID FOR A MUTUALLY<br />
ADVANTAGEOUS RELATIONSHIP BETWEEN COUNTRIES.<br />
ALREADY MUCH PROGRESS HAS BEEN MADE BET1WEEN US.<br />
WE MUST NOT, HOWEVER, RELAX IN OUR EFFORTS.<br />
BY ACCEPTING CHANGE WE, THE COUNTRIES OF THE ASIA-PACIFIC<br />
REGION, WILL ENHANCE THE WELL-BEING OF OUR PEOPLE AND<br />
CONTRIBUTE MUCH4 TO REGIONAL AND GLOBAL PEACE AND PROSPERITY.<br />
ON THIS BASIS, MR PREMIER, I EXPECT THE FRIENDSHIP AND<br />
STRENGTH OF RELATION4S BETW4EEN AUSTRALIA AND CHINA TO GROW.<br />
TOAST DISTINGUISHED GUESTS,<br />
WOULD YOU NOW JOIN ME IN OFrERING A TOAST TO PRESIDENT<br />
LI ZIANNIAN ( LEE SHEN-NYEN) TO PREMIER ZHAO ZIYANG AND TO<br />
THE FRIENDSHIP AND PROSPERITY OF OUR TWO NATIONS AND PEOPLES. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
