<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3697</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S SPEECH AT TARCOOLA, SOUTH AUSTRALIA, FOR INAUGURATION CEREMONIES OF TARCOOLA/ALICE SPRINGS RAILWAY, 12 APRIL 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/04/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003697.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER'S SPEECH AT TARCOOLA, SOUTH AUSTRALIA,<br />
FOR INAUGURATION CEREMONIES OF TARCOOLA/ ALICE SPRINGS RAILWAY<br />
12.4 .1975<br />
Everything we say on this platform is being recorded even if it<br />
is not being amplified. So even if you can't hear us today, I've<br />
no doubt you will play the record of the occasion for the rest<br />
of your lives. Maybe.<br />
We were introduced today by our colleacjue Laurie Wallace, the<br />
M. P. for Grey, in which electorate Tarcoola forms the centre<br />
and it was like old times for him, because he lived in Tarcoola<br />
from 1949 to 1952 with Mrs. Wallace, I hasten to add, and his<br />
first political meetings were in Tarcoola and there were no<br />
amplifiers. He was the secretary of the Progress Association,<br />
and now, now that he has become the Member for the district and<br />
serving under a government of his colleagues he's been able to<br />
ensure the progress of Tarcoola.<br />
Now I had the opportunity last night, in the presence of most of<br />
you, at a dinner at Port Augusta to recite the significance of<br />
this occasion. An immensely-significant week, in the history<br />
of Australian railways, Australian transport, Australia's national<br />
development, unity and progress because earlier this week we made<br />
the agreement to acquire the South Australian Railways, and then<br />
we enacted the Australian National Railways Commission Bill, and<br />
then we introduced the Interstate Commission Bill, all in the one<br />
week. But a year ago, Mr. Dunstan and I signed an agreement to build<br />
the Tarcoola/ Alice Springs Railway. It is not possible for the<br />
Australian Government to build or acquire a railway in any<br />
state without the co-operation of the State Government. Andia<br />
the South Australian Government has been magnificently co-operative,<br />
because a year ago it signed the agreement for us to build the<br />
Tarcoola Railway up to the Northern Territory border. It signed<br />
the agreement for us to build a new standard gauge railway between<br />
Crystal Brook and Adelaide and of course it has now signed the<br />
agreement for us to acquire the non-metropolitan railways in<br />
South Australia. So it has been a most fruitful period.<br />
And I suppose we have to concede that there were some supernatural<br />
forces at work, because had it not been for the fact that early<br />
last year there was -the longest interruption in the old narrow<br />
gauge service between Maree and Alice Springs that there had been<br />
in the history of the service. For nine weeks, the service was<br />
out. Sam Calder, whose presence here* I am very happy to see, the<br />
Member for the Northern Territory, gave us no rest at all and we<br />
thought " Right! We can delay no longer in undertaking this new<br />
railway project" an all weather, national and international<br />
standard railway between the East/ West railway at Tarcoola and<br />
Alice Springs. </p>
<p>2.<br />
And today we are inaugurating, we are commencing this largest<br />
railway project in Australia since Prime Minister Andrew Fisher's<br />
government inaugurated the East/ West railway in 1912. This is<br />
a big occasion. Not only to Tarcoola, not only for South<br />
Australia, and the Centre, but for the nation. A very big<br />
project. $ 100 million. 830 kilometers. And first-rate road<br />
bed and rolling stock. Of course the rolling stock is something<br />
for which I will always remember this day.<br />
I suppose every politician is supposed to be inordinately ambitious.<br />
And I suppose when I became a law student and thought everything<br />
would be terribly easy, I thought " Well, I suppose I'll be<br />
satisfied if I get on the High Court."<br />
It was many years that I was in the House of Representatives<br />
before I thought I'd be able to do this job. I suppose it was<br />
only after for some years I'd been watching people on the other<br />
side. But I never dreamed that my ambition of having a locomotive<br />
named after me would be fulfilled. I<br />
In the early days of federation, the railway stations on the East/<br />
West line were called after Prime Ministers Barton and Reid and<br />
Watson right up to Hughes and so on. But in more recent years,<br />
there have been locomotives called after Prime Ministers, and in<br />
fact, after Ministers of Transport. It started as so many things<br />
did with the Robert Menzies, and since then there's been the John<br />
Gorton, and the William McMahon. All very formal. Then they made<br />
a Ben Chifley, who I think was one of the greatest Prime ministers<br />
and he did in fact know something about locomotives. Then there<br />
was the George McLeay, and the Hubert Opperman, and the Gordon<br />
Freeth, but now, the pride of. the fleet the Charlie Jones and<br />
the Gough Whitlam.<br />
Of course, Jones' initials are C. K. But a lot of people knowing<br />
his addiction to railways think it ought to be the K. C. Caey<br />
Jones a great name in railway history. But be satisfied with<br />
it being called the Charlie Jones.<br />
Now some people have said, unkindly I think, that also locomotives.<br />
ought to be called after leaders on the other side. And in fact<br />
this has commended itself to the railways management because this<br />
would rapidly ensure the replenishment of the whole fleet. I'm<br />
not sure that some of them would be happy about it because they<br />
aren't always happy about people from the wrong side of the tracks.<br />
But Charlie, you needn't worry about my faith in you. Sure I'd<br />
like to be minister-for Transport. But you'd be my second choice.<br />
And you'd do better than some of your colleagues on the platform.<br />
Senator Bishop has been Postmaster-General for quite some time and<br />
he hasn't got me on a postage stamp.* But Charlie Jones has got<br />
me on a locomotive.<br />
Now this is going to be a big occasion. I believe it is going to<br />
take several forms. I have to push a plunger which will, after<br />
some lapse of time, produce an explosion on a neighbouring hillside.<br />
Then, I have to fill a barrel and this gives me the greatest<br />
pleasure, next after naming the locomotive, because I've had to<br />
push one for so many years. All by myself. So I have to go through </p>
<p>that process. Then there is going to be the plaque on the tree.<br />
One of the few trees on the immediate neighbourhood. And then<br />
there is the naming of the locomotive. Now there will be some<br />
interval. Because I am told that after I bash the plunger, the<br />
magazines on the TV will have to be replenished so any delay will<br />
be due to entirely media compulsions.<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen, it is a very great pleasure to be here in<br />
the middle of Australia on this very great occasion, because a<br />
great number of people on the maps of Australia from now on will<br />
find Tarcoola writ large and they will remember April 1975 for<br />
a very great number of things. Symbolised, I think, I am sorry<br />
about the fact, that these locomotives so freshly painted will<br />
have to be repainted again next week to make it Australian National<br />
Railways. But all these things are happening at the one time:<br />
the biggest railway project in Australia since 1912; the creation<br />
of the Australian National Railways; the acquisition of the South<br />
Australian Railways; the introduction of the Interstate Commission<br />
Bill. Ladies and Gentlemen, a lot of us have come a long way. But I<br />
believe this will be regarded as a voyage, a trip very much to<br />
be remembered. Thank you very much for coming here today.<br />
I believe the people of Australia will remember what we've all<br />
worked together to achieve today. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
