<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>16281</transcript-id>
    <title>Joint Media Release with  Minister for Families, Housing, Community Services and Indigenous Affairs - $5.3 billion to better support people with disability  </title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/11/2008</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Australian Government will provide $5.3 billion over five years for a new National Disability Agreement with the States and Territories to improve and expand services for people with disability, their families and carers. </p>
<p>This includes a significant injection of $408 million of new funds for more services and to drive important reforms to create a more effective and accessible disability service system.</p>
<p>The Agreement demonstrates the commitment of the Australian Government to provide additional assistance to people with disability, their families and carers.</p>
<p>The Australian Government is providing the States and Territories with an additional $1.3 billion in funding over five years  -  $408 million for growth and reform and $901 million for more accommodation, respite and in home care.</p>
<p>From 1 January next year the Australian Government's contribution to the National Disability Agreement will be indexed at around 6 per cent over the five-year agreement, compared to the current rate of around 1.8 per cent.</p>
<p>The Australian Government will maintain its oversight, coordination and leadership role in disability policy and will continue to work cooperatively with State and Territory Governments to implement these reforms.</p>
<p>COAG has also agreed to an ambitious program of reforms, including:</p>
<p>     * single access points for entry into the disability service system, with an emphasis on early intervention;</p>
<p>     * nationally consistent assessment processes; and</p>
<p>     * improved quality assurance in line with nationally agreed principles and benchmarking.</p>
<p>People with disability will also have easier access to disability aids and equipment when the reforms are implemented.</p>
<p>The States and Territories will work closely with the Australian Government to improve data collection to better measure the need for disability services.</p>
<p>The new Agreement will come into effect from 1 January 2009 and will include a $70 million sign on bonus for reform of the disability system.</p>
<p>In May, the State, Territory and Federal Disability Ministers agreed to a $1.9 billion package to provide more than 24,000 places in supported accommodation, respite and in home care.</p>
<p>This comprised $100 million for supported accommodation, $901 million for accommodation, respite and in home care from the Australian Government and $900 million from the States. This funding will be incorporated into the new National Disability Agreement.</p>
<p>COAG agreed to undertake further work on roles and responsibilities in community based care over the coming year. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
