<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2812</transcript-id>
    <title>RESPONSIBILITY FOR ABORIGINAL EDUCATION IN THE NORTHERN TERRITORY</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/02/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002812.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS STATEMENT NO. 51<br />
12 February 1973<br />
RESPONSIBILITY FOR ABORIGINAL EDUCATION IN THE NORTHERN<br />
TERRITORY<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr. Whitlam, announced last<br />
night that in future the Education Minister, Mr. Beazley,<br />
would have the responsibility for all special education<br />
including adult education in the Northern Territory.<br />
The decision, Mr. Whitlam said, was the result of an<br />
agreement following discussions between Mr. Beazley and<br />
the minister for Aboriginal Affairs, Mr. Bryant, who<br />
formerly controlled the area.<br />
It would become effective from tomorrow, 13 February.<br />
Mr. Whitlam said the Minister for Education was already<br />
responsible for the community education system in the<br />
Northern Territory.<br />
There would be continuing consultations between the<br />
Ministers and Departments of Education and Aboriginal Affairs,<br />
Mr. Whitlam said, to ensure that the overall policies of the<br />
Minister for Aboriginal Affairs were reflected in the<br />
education programs.<br />
Particular consideration would be given to the special<br />
and sometimes different needs of aborigines, including such<br />
matters as staff/ pupil ratios, teaching in Aboriginal languages<br />
and instruction in Aboriginal culture.<br />
Mr. Whitlam said he was confident that the new<br />
arrangements would provide the most effective means of ensuring<br />
that the Aboriginal people of the Northern Territory had the<br />
best possible educational opportunities.<br />
He said that consultation between the two Departments<br />
had led to a start in the plans for implementing the policy<br />
of teaching Aborigines in their own languages.<br />
Mr. Whitlam went on to say that grouping the formerly<br />
separate educational systems under the Department of Education<br />
would allow an integration of resources and a more effective<br />
approach to the provision of educational facilities in the<br />
Northern Territory. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
