<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7186</transcript-id>
    <title>STATMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER ALP IMMIGRATION AND AFFAIRS POLICY LAUNCH MELBOURNE - 10 JUNE 1987</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/06/1987</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007186.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHECK AGAINS': DEZIVERY EMBARGOED AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
S? ATREM-lET SY TE PRINE MINISTER<br />
ALP XL[. 4j;:\ ION AMD ~ TENMC AFFAIRS POLICY LAUNCH<br />
~ 2LsBOURNE 10 JUNE 1987<br />
Ladies and Cntlemen,<br />
Fellow Austrzlians,<br />
Friends, Since I wao a student at the University of Western<br />
Australia, ' Ie capacity of this great country to accept and<br />
to give op't: rtunities for a decent life as equals in our<br />
society to -ooole from beyond our shores has been a matter<br />
of great pc7 onal importance to me. It was the vision of<br />
Australia, der Chifley and Calwell, opening its doors to<br />
settlers a world ravaged by war, which first inspired<br />
me to join e Labor Party.<br />
The qualito life which we are able to offer to our ethnic<br />
communitic; in one of the most d3cisive measuring sticks by<br />
which any : t: alian Government should be judged. In this<br />
area, this V'vernment has one unbeatable advantage over its<br />
predecessors and its competitors: in Mick Young, we have<br />
one of the ; eat figures of Australian public life, one of<br />
the great pc -sonalities of the ALP, and one of the very<br />
great Immaigtion Ministers in Australian history.<br />
In launching my Government's immigration and ethnic affairs<br />
policy I wa t to emphasise three points:-we are inspired<br />
by the cucc:,: of Australia's immigration program over four<br />
decades and inspired by the role of Labor Governments in<br />
that succenss we are proud of the record of the present<br />
Government o" er the last four years and we are challenged by<br />
the opportun. ties of the next three years and beyond.<br />
Australia has been immeasurably enriched by the contribution<br />
of inmigration to our national life and by the success of<br />
the immigration program. It is one of our nation's greatest<br />
achievements that people have been accepted from a wide and<br />
diverse rangrc of backgrounds, race, religion and culture.<br />
We take pride in the role of Labor Governments in the<br />
success of the migration program. It was a Labor Government<br />
that began the migration program just after the War. It-was<br />
another Labo):: Government the Whitlam Labor Government<br />
which expunged the last traces of discrimination from our<br />
migration policy. COP1~ </p>
<p>2.<br />
It is with t: t great Labor tradition behind me that<br />
tradition of vision, compassion, courage and fairness that<br />
I speak to you today.<br />
The Government is totally committed to the concept of<br />
Australia as a truly multicultural society.<br />
What this nca-s is that we believe that all Australians,<br />
irrespective . f their ethnic or religious backgrounds, their<br />
cultural heritage or their linguistic tradition, should be<br />
able to exercise their rights and obligations as full and<br />
equal membersa o2 the comi. unity. We believe multiculturalicm<br />
is central to any commitment to social justice.<br />
However we nc to translate those beliefs and commitments<br />
into action. That is ultimately the test of any Government.<br />
When I look at the track record of my Government over the<br />
last four year!;, I am proud of what we have achieved.<br />
As with other areas of Government policy, we have got the<br />
fundamentale right.<br />
At times this 1as meant hard and painful decisions but in<br />
the end I be'. ive ev have established the basis for a<br />
multicultura. : instralia.<br />
The main poiltr I would like to highlight are:<br />
An imniig: tion policy which, through community<br />
consulta-tion and careful planning, has steadily<br />
increaced and has given priority to family reunion. My<br />
Government h'as successfully balanced economic, cocial<br />
and hunanitarian considerations.<br />
The carefti development by fick Young and Susan Ryan,<br />
with an input from the Office of Multicultural Affairs,<br />
of a National Policy on Languages a policy designed<br />
both to provide opportunities for al. l Australians to<br />
achieve competence in English and to maintain and<br />
develop Australia's valuable language resources. At the<br />
same time the provision of English courses through the<br />
Adult Higrant Education Program has been vastly<br />
improved. Funding has increased; new education centres<br />
have been ectablished; ancillary child care facilities<br />
have been extended; and the teaching staff have been<br />
transform'-. from a casual to a permanent, professional<br />
workforce.<br />
A commitmrnt to people in need, particularly low income<br />
families. : n contrast to the fall in real disposable<br />
income experienced by poor families under the previous<br />
Howard Government, payments have increased in real terms<br />
during the period of my Government.<br />
Special emphasis, particularly funding increases, in the<br />
provision of welfare services to the ethnic aged,<br />
migrant wo-aen, refugees and ethnic youth. </p>
<p>9 3.<br />
SThe establishment of the Office of Multicultural Affairs<br />
within my own portfolio, giving it the opportunity to<br />
have a policy input at the highest level of Government.<br />
The impleaentation of an Access and Equity strategy,<br />
designed to ensure that people of non-English speaking<br />
background have equal access to and an equal share of<br />
Commonwealth programs and services.<br />
Extensive support for ethnic community organisations.<br />
Under my Government unprecedented financial support has<br />
been given to ethnic community organisations.<br />
Let me repeat that we are proud of our achievements. We<br />
have laid a firm foundation for multiculturalism in<br />
Australia. We now look forward to the challenges and opportunities of<br />
the next three years and beyond. I wish to draw attention<br />
to six major areas of activity in the next three years.<br />
1) Implementation of the National Policy on Languages.<br />
Already we are committed to an integrated package of<br />
initiativoes that will allow the on-arrival component of<br />
the ESL program to be doubled; provide substantial<br />
funding for community, trade and Aboriginal languages;<br />
and tackle the problem of adult illiteracy. To meet<br />
that chalenge we will spend an additional $ 15m next<br />
year, and $ 25t in the following full year. Of theso<br />
figures, an extra $ 5.3m will be available for on-arrival<br />
ESL for oschool-children in 1987-88, increasing to $ 13.6m<br />
in 1988-09.<br />
I should say that the Government is committed to<br />
maintaining sufficient levels of funding flows to<br />
S general ESL programs, in recognition of the need to<br />
ensure that people of non-English speaking background<br />
are not disadvantaged in Australian society, and that<br />
the education and skills they bring to this country can<br />
be fully utilised to the benefit of all Australians.<br />
The national policy on languages is also designed to<br />
maintaiz the community languages that form an<br />
indispensable part of the rich ethnic heritage of<br />
Australia, as well as improving the quality of our<br />
workforco, increasing our tourist potential and allowing<br />
us to e: xpand our trading opportunities.<br />
2) Production of a Green Paper on immigration. This will<br />
examine all aspects of immigration policy including the<br />
points system. The Green Paper will be produced in<br />
consultation and with the full co-operation of the<br />
Community, including ethnic organisations.<br />
t </p>
<p>3) Extension1 of the access and equity strategy. All<br />
Commonwealth Departments and agencies will now be<br />
required to develop three year plans of actions on<br />
measurez they are taking to ensure that all Australians, A<br />
irrespective of their ethnic origin, enjoy a ' fair go'<br />
in accesz to Conmonwealth programs and services.<br />
4) Drawing maximum benefit from the office of Multicultural<br />
Affairs and the Advisory Council of Multicultural<br />
Affairs. The Office, which will have a presence in each<br />
capital city of Australia, will be required to<br />
co-ordinate policy advice, implement the access and<br />
equity atrategy, provide community information and to<br />
consult aextensively with community organisations. The<br />
Council has been asked by me to translate the principles<br />
of multiculturalism into a series of long-term concrete<br />
initiatives a National Agenda for a Multicultural<br />
Australia. Cutting tho delays and backlogs in the immigration<br />
appeals system. lie will do this by increasing the<br />
Immigration Review Panel from 32 to 137 members and by<br />
setting up, for the first time, new Panels in Brisbane,<br />
Adelaide and Perth.<br />
6) Finally, but crucially important to many of you, we will<br />
ensure that with a steadily expanding iumigration<br />
program priority will be given to the reunion of<br />
families.<br />
Those are tho uain elements of what Labor offers over the<br />
next three years. And there is not the slightest<br />
possibility that our opponents will go close to matching it.<br />
The importance nr Howard attaches to these natters can be<br />
seen from the fact that his spokesman on immigration and<br />
ethnic affairs is not only outside the Shadow Cabinet, but<br />
is in fact onec of the most junior members of his Shadow<br />
ministry. And this in a Party which has the widely<br />
respected Ian lqacphee languishing on the backbench.<br />
Moreover, in an environment where the Liberal Party is<br />
threatening huge, unspecified cuts of 2.5 billion dollars in<br />
Government progjrams, it is certain that they intend to<br />
impose a disproportionate and unfair share of the burden on<br />
our ethnic commiunities. Mir Howard has identified certain<br />
areas where his cuts would not fall. Very significantly,<br />
ethnic and multicultural programs are not on the protected<br />
list. Under the Liberals, they are destined to suffer.<br />
We will not allow this to happen. The Labor Party has made<br />
its commitment to multiculturalism, not merely in words but<br />
in effective, on-going programs. We will ensure that help<br />
continues to vyo to those who need it. We are not going to<br />
be party to any redistribution of public wealth from<br />
ordinary Australians to the greedy few in our society. We<br />
stand for an Auatralia, richly diverse but cohesive, in<br />
which every Australian, whatever his or her background, can<br />
enjoy a fair c~ o. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
