<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11270</transcript-id>
    <title>AUSTRALIAN BUSINESSES RECOGNISED FOR EMPLOYING PEOPLE WITH DISABILITIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/10/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>  I am pleased to announce that Jonstyle Pty Ltd and Spotlight Pty Ltd, both<br />
   from Western Australia, are the winners of the 1999 Prime Minister's Employer<br />
   of the Year Award.</p>
<p>  The national winners were selected from State and Territory winners announced<br />
   last week.</p>
<p>  In addition, the University of Technology Sydney (UTS) has won the Higher<br />
   Education category of the awards, and the ACT laboratories of the CSIRO<br />
   Plant Industry has won the Commonwealth agency category.</p>
<p>  The Prime Minister's Employer of the Year Awards recognise businesses that<br />
   have demonstrated an outstanding commitment to employing people with a disability.</p>
<p>  Jonstyle is a furniture manufacturing business<br />
   employing 14 people, seven of whom have a disability. This is the result<br />
   of the Managing Director, Dexter Tennant's personal vow to break down the<br />
   workplace barriers he has faced as a person with a disability.</p>
<p>  Spotlight is one of Australia's largest<br />
   fabric, craft and home interior stores and employs people with disabilities<br />
   in four of its six Western Australian stores. It has developed several staff<br />
   training initiatives to ensure they reach their full employment potential.</p>
<p>  The University of Technology employs 120<br />
   staff with a disability, 35 of whom have significant disabilities requiring<br />
   workplace adjustments. Over the last three years, UTS has initiated a Disability<br />
   Action Plan covering all aspects of university life, from access issues<br />
   to the content of academic curricula.</p>
<p>  CSIRO Plant Industry is one of the world's<br />
   leading research organisations in plant industry science. The ACT site employs<br />
   410 people, 15 of whom have a disability and work in areas ranging from<br />
   lab technicians through to administration, trades and maintenance.</p>
<p>  I commend them all for recognising the potential of people with disabilities,<br />
   for actively promoting workplace flexibility and providing a positive example<br />
   for businesses throughout Australia.</p>
<p>  The government is committed to helping all Australians reach their full<br />
   potential as we move into the next century.</p>
<p>  Our vision is for a strong and fair society that fosters economic prosperity<br />
   and independence but is also compassionate and mutually supportive.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
