<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5133</transcript-id>
    <title>INTERVIEW WTIH 4IP, BRISBANE</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/08/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005133.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS OFFICE TRANSCRIPT THURSDAY 30 AUGUST 1979<br />
INTERVIEW WITH 41P, BRISBANE<br />
( QUESTIONS NOT AUDIBLE ON TAPE ANSWERS ONLY)<br />
Question Prime Minister<br />
A typical Canberra late winter cold morning.<br />
Question Prime Minister<br />
I thought I might have been late for your show.<br />
Question Prime Minister<br />
Well, it obviously makes it much more convenient because you<br />
can use it as an office and get a lot of work done. The main<br />
reason for it of course is security, and there is no way you<br />
can get around that. The captain of the aircraft said that<br />
defence didn't know what to do when I had the aircraft because<br />
they've got so used to using them and the other one was being<br />
serviced and for the two weeks they were without a 707 and<br />
finding it inconvenient for defence itself because they are<br />
using them so much on defence purposes.<br />
Question Prime Mi-ni<br />
Modern international terrorists they are totally mad in<br />
my view. They are totally indiscriminate in their killing.<br />
They want publicity. They don't care what they do. They have<br />
no concern for human life or human decency. They are almost<br />
a contradiction of mankind itself. The IPA, and some elements<br />
of the IRA, have got to be at the very forefront of international<br />
terrorism and everything that is bad about it. It obviously<br />
poses a very real threat to people. We've had aircraft hijacked.<br />
We've had terrorist incidents in many places around the world.<br />
It's a great worry to all authorities, to all governments, who've<br />
got the responsibility of trying to combat this sort of thing.<br />
Australia so far has been relatively fortunate. We had the bomb.<br />
incident at the Hilton. But you never know. The good old statement<br />
" it can never happen here". You just can't rely on that anymore.<br />
You've got to take the most stringent precautions. </p>
<p>2-<br />
Question Prime Minister<br />
Next year there will be a double anniversary -I will be<br />
and 25 years in politics.<br />
Questicn Prime Minister<br />
I think we overlapped for a bit. Oxford is a large place and<br />
we didn't really meet up.<br />
Question Prime Minister<br />
At a personal level, fine. It just depends if he is wearing a<br />
political hat'--at the time.<br />
Question Prime Minister<br />
I don't think I would want to come back as somebody else.<br />
You sometimes wonder I was 23 when I first got pre-selected<br />
and I thought being a politician in a rural electorate would<br />
fit in very nicely with being a farmer. I very soon learnt<br />
that being a politician, even a private Member, was much more<br />
than a full time job. I think it sometimes might be a good thing<br />
that aspiring Members of Parliament don't know what is in store<br />
for-them after they become a Member. If they did, they would<br />
Probazbly never take that first: stCep.<br />
Question Prime Minister<br />
I would never advise people not to. I might say don't expect<br />
too much, you might want to change the world or want to make it<br />
a better place. There will be many frustrations, many difficulties,<br />
A lot of criticism that you will inevitably think that is to a<br />
degree unjust, but if you believe in things it is worth fighting<br />
for. I think, go ahead, because if people won't try and press for<br />
the things they do believe in, trying to make, as they see it,<br />
Australia a better place, well then the political life of the<br />
country is going to be very poor. So I will try and encourage<br />
people but I would try and do it realistically. You can't change<br />
the world overnight. It is a slow process. You've got to </p>
<p>3<br />
Prime Minister ( continued)<br />
persuade other people to share your same beliefs, your same<br />
hopes and aspirations. It sometimes takes years to achieve<br />
a particular objective. But then if it is a worthwhile objective<br />
the fight has been worthwhile.<br />
Question Prime Minister<br />
Thank you. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
