<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5140</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S ADDRESS TO DINNER FUNCTION, DARWIN</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/09/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005140.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR MEDIA FRIDAY, 14 SEPTEMBERJ. 979<br />
PRIME MINISTER' S ADDRESS TO DINNER FUNCTION, DARWIN<br />
-It's good to be here. It's goed to see the progress that<br />
has been made. Something always happens to people whien they<br />
come to have a much greater say in their own Government and in<br />
their own affairs. Decisions start to get made more quickly.<br />
The lines of communication are much shorter and much more effective,,<br />
Of course, I can't allow Paul to take the total credit for<br />
that. I've got to say that our polcies in trying to keep<br />
inflation under control and getting markets for the beef<br />
industry overseas, and other things like that, are designed<br />
to contribute to the well-being of the Northern Territory<br />
and are designed to contribute to the well-bein~ g o-L Australia.<br />
Whatever we do, wherever we are, whether it is in D~ arwin or<br />
Alice Springs or in some other State, what happens in Australia<br />
is in part dependent upon the wider world situation. We are<br />
a great trading nation with up to 30% of our gross national<br />
product dependent upon trade. Therefore, if something happens<br />
overseas -that damages markets, damages prospects for grow,-. th<br />
of the world economy, in the past that had a significant<br />
impact upon Australia. But we've now got to the stage<br />
where no matter what happens overseas, we've got to make sure<br />
that Australia can go forward with strength.<br />
We have the capacity to do that, because we have great resources<br />
in this country; many forms and abundant supplies of many<br />
different forms of energy, of great mineral resources, as well<br />
as beef and wool and wheat and a whole variety of commodities<br />
that the world needs.<br />
We can attract investment from overseas for a whole variety<br />
of reasons, so long as we run our own economy well.. So long as<br />
we make sure that Australia's inflation keeps blow our major<br />
trading partners. Even if world trade does grow slowly, and even<br />
if there isn't much growth in the United States in this year<br />
we are responding and in fact are being strengt-hened.<br />
There is not much growth in Europe. Because of the capacity<br />
of Australia, because we have run this economy well, we can<br />
attract more than our fair share of world investment;, can still<br />
look forward with great and enormous ccnfidence. If the world<br />
outside is having a difficult time, that is no reason for<br />
people in the Territory to be deterred. It is certainly no<br />
reason for Australia to be deterred. I. t just means that we have<br />
to be that much better; that much more competitive, to get<br />
a larger share of what is going so that we can go forward with<br />
great confidence-in the years ahead. ./ 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
The strength of the economy has grown greatly over the<br />
last three to four years. This growth is backed in the<br />
manufacturing sector, in the export sector. Profitability<br />
is up. It can be better still, but has improved greatly<br />
from a few years ago.<br />
Even though there are some renewed inflationary pressures<br />
which concern us all as I know. I think it is fair enough<br />
to look at what's happening in other countries, because while<br />
there is some increased inflationary pressure in Australia,<br />
in the United States, at an annual rate, inflation is now<br />
running at about 14%. In the United Kingdom it is a horrible<br />
figure of about 22% on the latest figures available. I think<br />
that will come down substantially in the months ahead, but<br />
at the moment it is a terrifying thought.<br />
The advanced industrial countries alone are only a fraction<br />
under 13%, with Australia around It's worth noting<br />
those figures. It means even if our inflation is-higher<br />
than we thought a year ago--for reasons that we well know--<br />
we are still becoming more competitive with many<br />
people and many other countries, because the margin in favour<br />
of Australia is improving. That is the very opposite of<br />
what happened when LChe Australian Labor was in power.<br />
They started with an inflation under the world average, ended<br />
with an inflation 5 points above the world average, or the<br />
OECD average, and we've got that back until we are under the<br />
average of those advanced industrial countries once again.<br />
That'is essential if Australia's firms, Australia' s exporters,<br />
are going to be able to get out and get a better share of<br />
the domestic market and a better share of world markets overseas.<br />
It is quite exciting I think, now, to see Australian manufacturers<br />
getting out and beating competition, often beating competition<br />
from developing countries. We are making fishing boats in* PertCh,<br />
Sbeating competition from Singapore, Hong Kong and Taiwan.<br />
How many people would have thought that we could do that with<br />
Australia's labour costs.<br />
Two years ago Jim Killen came along with a contract from a<br />
French firm to build a major replenishment ship for the Navy.<br />
About $ 80 million worth. But wewsaid no, we would like to know<br />
what it would cost to build that at Vicker's Co. Dock in Sydney:<br />
it might cost more. it might mean a subsidy, but we just wanted<br />
to know what the subsidy would have to be so if we could keep<br />
the work in Australia we wanted to. A while ago we got the<br />
tenders from the Australian firm. No question of any subsidy<br />
being needed. The French contract was the best the international<br />
world could provide; the Australian tenders were some millions<br />
of dollars lower. They'd won the contract for a sophisticated<br />
military ship on their merit. That again, is an example of<br />
the growing competitiveness in Australia which I think we can<br />
be very proud about. </p>
<p>-3<br />
We are recognised internationally as a good place for<br />
investment; and last year the largest overseas investment<br />
in this country for the decade -since about 1971 or 1972.<br />
In coal alone, there was $ 2 billion worth of investment.<br />
In bauxite and aluminium there is $ 4 billion worth<br />
of investment. These decisions have all been made in recent<br />
times and they are people voting with their dollars; votes<br />
of confidece in the future of Australia as a good country<br />
to have their assets and a good country in which to invest.<br />
4<br />
In the Northern Territory you are going ahead again, because<br />
with less than 1% of Australia's population, you are getting<br />
or more of the investment projects that are taking place<br />
right around Australia. I think that is also something to<br />
be proud of in the Territory.<br />
In marked contrast to South Australia, with nearly 10% of<br />
the population, under the magnificent policies of the<br />
Australian Labor Party, getting about 2% or less of investment:<br />
holding up mines, holding up opportunities because of<br />
policies that are archaic and outdated as our Chairman indicated.<br />
I am quite sure that Territorians don't want any of that here.<br />
You want a Government that is going to encourage and work in<br />
partnersh~ ip with the Commonwealth and make sure that this<br />
Territory proceeds as rapidly as possible and grows strongly<br />
into the future.<br />
Even though there is much more<br />
strength, even though there is confidence overseas in Australia<br />
of a very vigorous kind, there are still some undesirable<br />
aspects in our situation and worse in the world situation; dangers<br />
that we have to get around, dangers that we have to plan<br />
to avoid.<br />
We all know what happened with inflationary pressures coming<br />
from oil problems in Iran and the Middle East. And also the<br />
inflationary pressures that have come out of higher beef prices.<br />
But I-guess there are many people in the Northern Territory<br />
and other parts of Australia who are prepared to ride with that<br />
because higher beef prices were very needed. If they hadn't<br />
occurred many people would be in great trouble. One of the<br />
great benefits to the Northern Territory, I think, you just had<br />
a record year, a record return, for the beef industry, and<br />
after the difficulties of the last five or six years in the<br />
beef industry, that is certainly something to look forward to.<br />
A large part of our trade<br />
efforts in the Multilateral Trade Negotiations that Doug Anthony<br />
and Vic Garland and myself have been involved in, have been<br />
designed to secure markets overseas for Australia' s major<br />
rural commodities. The arrangements with Japan, with the<br />
United States, and even opening the door a little into the<br />
European community which people originally said wasn't possible.<br />
/ 14 </p>
<p>-4<br />
I think we can look forward to a greater sense of security<br />
in a number of Australia's great rural industries there<br />
are a few I have in mind, but particularly the beef industry<br />
with a greater sense of security than we've known for a<br />
very long while. These numbers have filled out about<br />
million or more in the United States, they are low in<br />
Australia overall, compared to past times. Quite apart<br />
from Japan, the United States, and Europe, there is also<br />
an emerging market coming in other places Korea for<br />
example which I believe gives us reason for confidence<br />
in particularly the beef industry. That is clearly of immense<br />
importance to the Northern Territory.<br />
But when there have been difficult circumstances, inflationary<br />
pressures which are caused by oil or whatever else, we don't<br />
sit back and say something-has happened because something<br />
has happened overseas and wring our hands and say there is<br />
nothing to be done about it. But they are facts of life.<br />
They have to be faced. They are facts of life that<br />
governments have to respond to.<br />
You might have heard of the mini-budget in May. John Howard<br />
didn't like it very much. I didn't like it very much,<br />
I understand one or two other people around Australia<br />
didn't like it all that much. But in view of what had occurred,<br />
it was'necessary. I think people can now understand that<br />
it was. We've had a more recent Budget that's been able to<br />
build on the achievements of the past three or four years<br />
and look ahead again with great confidence.<br />
But if we are going to have that kind of success, we've<br />
got to keep control of Government spending. That's a<br />
continuing story. It is never won. We've got to have wage<br />
moderation and that is a continuing story.<br />
Look at the irresponsibility of the ACTU. The irresponsiblity<br />
of the Adelaide Conference where the sky would be limit and<br />
back to the days when wages went up by 38% in one year in<br />
March 1975. Was it any wonder the Federal Government was in<br />
trouble, any wonder that Australia was in trouble, in those<br />
circumstances. We have provided incentives to investment in manufacturing<br />
industries, in mining industries, in oil search and development<br />
and also in the rural industries. We have provided support<br />
for our exports and better access to market than we had before.<br />
As a result of this, I think that there is a greater sense<br />
of confidence throughout the major sectors of Australia<br />
than there has ever been.<br />
Speaking with Paul, and others here, in the little while I<br />
have been here, it is easy to see and feel that sense of<br />
confidence in the Territory and Darwin as you plan your<br />
own future. </p>
<p>There is never the time for looking ahead, but very<br />
briefly, we need to keep in mind the policies of the<br />
Australian Labor Party. Their policies have been updated.<br />
There was an Adelaide Conference. They have had an<br />
alternative Budget, and we need to remind ourselves that<br />
it is the same old Party, it is the same old policies, that<br />
would kill investment and stop development. We shouldn't<br />
doubt that they can stop development, and we shouldn't<br />
development and investment they did it once before<br />
Amore effectively than anyone would have thought. We shouldn't<br />
doubt their capacity to do it again.<br />
The sky would be the limit on wages. Shortly before an<br />
election in South Australia which he might regret having<br />
called Mr. Corcoran supported a $ 40 a week increase in<br />
the metal trade. I don't know if he thought it would win<br />
him votes or not, but it would certainly destroy the metal<br />
trade industry to have a wage claim of that kind.<br />
You don't have to take my word for it. Because Bob Hawke<br />
said the wages policy at Adelaide was a gutless sell-out to<br />
the Left; as he described Bill Hayden. That leaves<br />
Labor with that great moderate in Victoria, Bill Hartley,<br />
to let the true story out. Jim Roulston of the AMSWU<br />
that thoroughly moderate union has become a principal<br />
economic adviser to Bill Hayden. And as Jin Roulston has<br />
just had a very successful vote in the ACTU Executive,<br />
Is it any wonder there is no economic policy and no<br />
wages policy if the Labor Party is asking for the view<br />
of the AMSWU.<br />
The Budget we've introduced builds on past achievements;<br />
maintains control of expenditure. * There are considerably<br />
increased sumas for defence, and increased funds for some<br />
* areas of social welfare.<br />
When * we are told we don't cut back enough in that area,<br />
I think we need to remember that ten years ago there were<br />
179 pensioners to every 1,000 people in the workforce. Today,<br />
that grown to over 280 for every 1,000 people in the* korkforce.<br />
Is it any wonder that social security costs more than it did.<br />
The Budget has enabled advances defence and social welfare.<br />
It has led to reductions in taxation; led to very considerable<br />
reductions in our own deficit, and that I think, above all, is<br />
the fact that it has led to a great growth of confidence<br />
in the weeks since the Budget because people know that this<br />
economy is moving forward in a sensible and sound manner and<br />
is one that is thoroughly under control and very much on track.<br />
Getting that deficit down, we can get amused by the words and<br />
the rhetoric I suppose. But it is important, and just as<br />
important as if a household spends too much more than its<br />
income. The breadwinner gets a bit annoyed and a bit worried<br />
I suppose, because if it goes on too long you get bankrupt<br />
and you get into * debt and maybe lose your house. That had<br />
been what has been had been happening to Australia. But it takes<br />
a while to work it off and get rid of it and to get rid of<br />
past debts. / 6 </p>
<p>-6<br />
I think that is happening and we are looking forward to<br />
continuing success in that area.<br />
Because uranium is so important to the Territory, let me<br />
just say a word about it. In 1976 I think some people<br />
uranium would never be mined, never be exported. There were<br />
enormous difficulties. There was a Royal Commission Report.<br />
How could all the different considerations<br />
be properly balanced: National parks, the environment,<br />
Aboriginal interests were very legitimate, then the natural<br />
problems with uranium trade, safeguards, bilateral agreements,<br />
and all the rest.<br />
What seemed to be formidable<br />
problems, formidable roadblocks, have been overcome<br />
and the mining is now proceeding very much to the<br />
advantage of Australia.<br />
We are looking now to the feasibility of establishing<br />
a commercial uranium enrichment industry. Consultations<br />
have been taking place with overseas countries, including the<br />
States, with leading Australian concerns. It is a long-term<br />
project, which could involved $ 1,000 million investment.<br />
It would involve a great number of jobs. But there is much<br />
yet to be decided the basis of the technology, the<br />
partners we would have, where the enrichment plan ought<br />
to go.<br />
the attitude of a Government in a State or a Territory<br />
will obviously be a material factor in determining the location.<br />
That would seem to rule out South Australia. I think<br />
I've got to say that Charles Court and Joh Bjelka Petersen are<br />
also in the race. At least here I know what vou want.-<br />
We've now negotiated safeguards agreements with a number<br />
of countries overseas with the United Kingdom, which is<br />
important because it is the first member of the European<br />
Community. We are hopeful we will be negotiating with<br />
EURATUM soon and there is a good future on all the estimates<br />
for export in that trade.<br />
You might have noticed at a meeting in Melbourne that<br />
the ACTU Congress has been mildly irresponsible. Their<br />
former Executive said " yes" , mining and export could go on.<br />
Mr. Hawke said yes. The Congress has said The Labor<br />
Party has said But it is worth noting that Mr. Hawke<br />
said we had done everything that could be done in relation<br />
to safeguards and non-proliferation, and he thinks that we<br />
shouldn't hold up the export of uranium if the workers and<br />
people in government of other countries have made a decision<br />
that they uranium as power for peaceful purposes. This was<br />
one of those occasions I am prepared to say that I think<br />
Bob Hawke is right. The attitude of the Labor Party and<br />
of the ACTU Congress will be one of the things that will keep<br />
the Labor Party in opposition for a very long while. </p>
<p>-7-<br />
We can look to the 1980s with enormous confidence.<br />
I believe we can look to the future of the Territory<br />
with great confidence in your own hands and working<br />
in partnership with the Federal Government. In Australia<br />
we have, I think, people with as much capacity and as<br />
much initiative or more, than people in any other country.<br />
Sometimes we tend to knock ourselves a bit too much say<br />
things from overseas are better than they are in Australia.<br />
I don't believe that is true. I think we can produce with<br />
the best. We can be up with the best and better than the<br />
best overseas. There is a great sense of pride in Darwin<br />
and a great sense of pride in the Northern Territory.<br />
If that could be exhibited to a greater extent right around<br />
Australia, then I think this would be a greater country,<br />
and a better one, and one where people could have a pride<br />
in Australia's achievements. I think a little more of that<br />
and a little less of the knocking would make Australia<br />
move forward more quickly, more confidently.<br />
One of the things over the last three or four years people<br />
overseas have been voting with their dollars and their pounds<br />
and their hearts and all the rest in confidence in the<br />
future of Australia. There have been one or two occasions<br />
when I have thought that they have had more confidence in<br />
the future of Australia than one or two people in this country.<br />
I think it is time that we put that aside, knew where we<br />
were going and marched ahead in partnership Territory and<br />
the Commonwealth, State and the Commonwealth and made quite<br />
sure that we guaranteed the future this nation deserves.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
