<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9187</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P.J. KEATING MP DOORSTOP, TEMPLE OF LITERATURE, HANON, SUNDAY, 10 APRIL 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/04/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009187.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
K<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
DOORSTOP. TEMPLE OF LITERATURE, HANOI, SUNDAY, 10 APRIL 1904<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
J: Prime Minister, how does it feel to be the first Australian Prime Minister to<br />
come to Hanoi?<br />
PM: One feels the obvious senme of occasion and history of it and it is at an<br />
Important time in the histoy of Australia and Vietnam, particularly in<br />
Vietnam's development. I feel the poignancy of coming here, the first<br />
Australian Prime Minister in God knows how long and to sum wh~ at's<br />
happening here and to be relevant to Vietnam's development.<br />
J: What do you think you will achieve out of this visit to Hanoi Mr Keating?<br />
PM: I think we will get a chance to understand what aspirations the<br />
Goyemnment of Vietnam has for the country; how It is proceeding with its<br />
development; Its view of Australia's role here, the Possibilities of Australia<br />
playing an even larger role in the development of Vietnam and also the<br />
view of the Government of Vietnam's role in the region and the chance for<br />
us, me in this case, to talk to the Government about how we see the<br />
region developing and what rale we think we should be playing in it.<br />
J: Is it your anticipation that there will be a meeting with the General<br />
Secretary Do Muoi?<br />
PM: I think we have one scheduled.<br />
J: Prime Minister, people like Tim F ' ischer are saying that you should alter<br />
your schedule to have some sort of commemorative service for the<br />
Vietnam veterans.<br />
PM: I don't discriminate in Australia's commemoration of our war dead, that is<br />
why in ' Kanchanaburi ' at the appropriate time I mentioned those<br />
Australians who died in Vietnam, but when we enquired of our Embassy<br />
what particular focus or point that one might attend or visit, they said that<br />
there wasn't any obvious place because Australia took its war dead home,<br />
there is no cemetery here. So, I can only repeat what I said when our<br />
Vietnam veterans were appropriately honoured in Canberra a year or so<br />
ago that they died with the same faith In Australia and the same belief in<br />
our values as every other service person did in other theatres of war. But </p>
<p>2<br />
again, this in Hanoi and really in the places I am visiting there is no<br />
natural opportunity as there was in Thailand.<br />
J: Do you accept that the Vietnamese might feel that the kinds of acts that<br />
were perpetrated against them were in some way equivalent to the kinds<br />
of things that were done by the Japanese to Australian soldiers in World<br />
War II?<br />
PM: That is for them to know really, but for us to discern. I don't know whether<br />
they feel that or whether they want to put the war behind them. We are<br />
here to help them to develop their country as best we can and to put that<br />
history behind us.<br />
J: Do you have anything to say to the Vietnamese leadership about<br />
Australia's role in the war here?<br />
PM: Not particularly. I don't think they are looking for any acknowledgment by<br />
me of our role here. I saw Prime Minister Kiet in Australia, he made no<br />
such references there and I don't see there is any particular point to make<br />
them now.<br />
J: I have only one question, Australia is now paying much attention to Asia.<br />
Do you bring any message from Australian businessmen to Vietnam this<br />
time?<br />
PM: We see Vietnam having a great opportunity in the countries of Asia to<br />
grow and develop itself and Australia believes it can make a contribution,<br />
It can make a difference in all sorts of ways In our aid program, in<br />
education, in social policies and in commerce and we will be represented<br />
in this country on a very broad basis.<br />
J: Would you like some reciprocal gains like increased aviation rights?<br />
PM: Not at this stage. I am not here in a sense in a bartering role, it is a<br />
general discussion about where our economies are going.<br />
J: Prime Minister, there seems to be large numbers of foreign delegations<br />
passing through Vietnam at the moment, can Australia realistically lay<br />
claim to a special relationship here?<br />
PM: There are very few special relationships in the world anywhere. You have<br />
got to earn your freight, each country has to do that with the other. We<br />
were amongst thle first to give aid to Vietnam after the Cambqdian Accords<br />
were signed. When it most needed support, I think, we were the first to<br />
give it and we are still giving it and we can give a lot more and make a<br />
greater contribution than we have already been permitted to make. Thank<br />
you.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
