<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7788</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, PAN PACIFIC HOTEL, KUALA LUMPUR, 23 OCTOBER 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/10/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007788.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
/ 4.<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, PAN PACIFIC HOTEL, KUALA<br />
LUMPUR, 23 OCTOBER 1989<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, Mrs Thatcher says she's appalled<br />
that anyone would even question her right to put out her<br />
point of view.<br />
PM: Yes, she said that. The position was very clearly<br />
accepted by the rest of the Commonwealth Heads of Government<br />
that an agreed position had been arrived at and that it was<br />
everyone's understanding that that agreed position would be<br />
adhered to. Now I've made my point of view known, as has Mr<br />
Mulroney and may I say that all the other members of the<br />
Commonwealth have quite clearly indicated their support for<br />
the position that we've expressed. Now I don't think any<br />
useful purpose is served by taking it any further. We know<br />
what's happened and the concern that we have expressed has<br />
been endorsed by others. Now no-one's purposes are served by<br />
taking it any further.<br />
JOURNALIST: It's very harmful to the Commonwealth's position<br />
surely, what she's done?<br />
PM: Well I think that if you had a position where the rest<br />
of the world thought that the declaration represented other<br />
than the view of the Commonwealth as a whole with the<br />
qualifications that Mrs Thatcher has wanted to express for<br />
the United Kingdom, it would be dangerous. But the world can<br />
have no doubt that the Commonwealth has expressed a clear<br />
view on South Africa.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, isn't what she's done<br />
effectively an act of duplicity though?<br />
PM: I'm not making any descriptive comments about what Mrs<br />
Thatcher has done. I expressed my view in the Heads of<br />
Government Meeting, I expressed my opposition clearly, as did<br />
Mr Mulroney and as I've said all people who've spoken to us<br />
have endorsed what we've had to say. That was the point to<br />
express a position, I've done that. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
JOURNALIST: But one minute she's says one thing or accepts<br />
one thing and the next minute she says quite the opposite.<br />
That's duplicity.<br />
PM: You are in the media, you have the delightful task of<br />
interpretation for the public. I have a responsibility as a<br />
Head of Government in the meetings of Heads of Government to<br />
put a point of view which I took the lead in doing, no-one in<br />
the room was left in any doubt as to my feelings. But that's<br />
where I'll do it, in the meeting. Now you have the role of<br />
interpretations, you get delightfully well paid for it.<br />
JOURNALIST: Why do you think she put out the statement?<br />
PM: Well you would, again as I've had cause to say at a<br />
previous conference, if you're asking what's in the mind of<br />
Mrs Thatcher I'm not the guardian of her mind. I mean she is<br />
and you'll have to ask her, if you could get through to<br />
asking her. But I'm not trying analysis as to why she's done<br />
what she's done.<br />
JOURNALIST: Don't you agree it's very strange way to do<br />
business though?<br />
PM: It's, as we've said, rather unusual to have an agreed<br />
position and the adoption of that agreed position being moved<br />
by Mrs Thatcher and as a result of that, no further<br />
discussions occuring, and then to have you know, what's<br />
happened, that is unusual. I've described it as unusual.<br />
JOURNALIST: inaudible<br />
PM:. I'm not properly going into a-<br />
JOURNALIST: Do these kind of actions by Britain threaten the<br />
future viability of the Commonwealth, do you think?<br />
PM: No.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, what is your understanding of<br />
Britain's current position in relation to existing sanctions<br />
against South Africa?<br />
PM: I suggest you read paragraph nine, which is very<br />
fascinating. Paragraph nine of the agreed communique says<br />
these things: that all existing sanctions should be<br />
maintained, and the second thing it says is that it calls on<br />
the rest of the world community to apply them. That<br />
paragraph nine has no qualification from the United Kingdom. </p>
<p>-3-<br />
( PM cont) So one would have to say on the basis of the<br />
agreed document moved in its adoption by Mrs Thatcher that<br />
that paragraph nine unqualified by a reservation in regards<br />
to the United Kingdom represents her position. I mean<br />
that's what she moved.<br />
JOURNALIST: Would you see that as a slight shift from their<br />
position at previous CHOGM's?<br />
PM: Well it's a position which I welcome.<br />
JOURNALIST: But she quite clearly accepts that trade<br />
sanctions are reasonable and working.<br />
PM: All I can say is that Mrs Thatcher was the one who at<br />
the Retreat moved the adoption of the statement and I've<br />
referred to you paragraph nine which contains no<br />
qualification. So that's the position which she moved at the<br />
Retreat. JOURNALIST: Do you find this confusing?<br />
PM: I expressed how I found the British position. But I<br />
expressed that as I said, in the Heads of Government meeting..<br />
I'm not going to go into any public observation about what's<br />
happened. I did that in the meeting.<br />
JOURNALIST: Well do you believe that this is a deliberate<br />
strategy by Britain or do you believe it's confusion within<br />
their own ranks?<br />
PM: Oh well, I don't know. If I thought it was helpful to<br />
anyone to engage in a detailed public analysis of what's<br />
happened then I would do that. But I really don't think that<br />
Australia's interests, Britain's interests, but most<br />
importantly the interests of the people of South Africa, of<br />
all the people of South Africa, I don't think any of those<br />
interests are served by me going into such an analysis. I<br />
imagine there's going to be a lot of interpretation done by<br />
others, well that's OK. I honestly don't think that anyone's<br />
interests are served by me undertaking that analysis.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mrs Thatcher seemed to suggest that the<br />
complaints by the other countries were somehow less than<br />
democratic, that she had a right to express Britain's view. </p>
<p>-4-<br />
PM: Yes, she has exercised those rights on the Thursday in<br />
the Heads of Government meeting, her rights were exercised,<br />
she expressed a point of view there. Their rights were<br />
exercised by having her Foreign Minister in the drafting<br />
group where, as you'll appreciate, concessions were made by<br />
us and others in that drafting process, concessions of<br />
language on the basis of accommodating Britain's position.<br />
So they exercised their rights there and exercised their<br />
rights at the Retreat by moving the adoption for the agreed<br />
communique. So all the rights have been exercised as were<br />
everyone else's in the process up to an including the<br />
Retreat. JOURNALIST: In the interests of both South Africa and the<br />
Commonwealth, what would you like to see Mrs Thatcher<br />
do now?<br />
PM: Nothing more, I would think would be the best answer to<br />
that. ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
