<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7352</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/07/1988</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007352.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
) JJUSTALI( A(<br />
FOR MEDIA 8 JULY 1988<br />
In July last I announced that the program of efficiency<br />
scrutinies conducted under the guidance of Mr David Block had<br />
been completed, and that the efficiency scrutiny activity would<br />
be a matter for departments to pursue against the backdrop of the<br />
efficiency dividend required by the Government.<br />
At the same time, I announced that Mr Block would assist the<br />
Government in a number of specific areas of administrative review<br />
over the course of the ensuing months, supported by a small group<br />
within my Department.<br />
Those further reviews have now been largely completed, and<br />
accordingly I have decided, with Mr Block's full concurrence,<br />
that the Administrative Reform Unit within my Department should<br />
be wound up.<br />
The Government is most grateful to Mr Block for his assiduous and<br />
productive work both in relation to efficiency scrutinies and the<br />
broader reviews just referred to.<br />
most of the recommendations arising from both these activities<br />
have been accepted by the Government.<br />
Perhaps even more important, Mr Block has managed to promote an<br />
environment of reform and questioning of established practices<br />
within the Commonwealth administration which will have ongoing<br />
benefit for many years. I am confident that the impetus for<br />
change provided by Mr Block, with the support of the Unit, will.<br />
now be carried forward by individual managers.<br />
Arising from the most recent review activity involving Mr Block,<br />
the Government has decided:-<br />
To locate Commonwealth Employment Service ( CES) and<br />
Department of Social Security ( DSS) offices in the one<br />
building wherever possible, providing some small savings but<br />
more importantly major benefits to those members of the<br />
public dealing with both agencies. Other Commonwealth<br />
service-delivery agencies have been directed to examine also<br />
the possibility of co-location with the CES and DSS offices.<br />
In addition, free direct-line telephones will be provided<br />
from CES offices to the nearest DSS office in towns where<br />
there is no full-time DSS presence. Unemployment<br />
beneficiaries who currently lodge their fortnightly<br />
Continuation Forms by post will be able to lodge the forms at<br />
CSS offices. 265<br />
I </p>
<p>2<br />
To transfer to the Department of Social Security the<br />
administration of living allowances paid under the Adult<br />
Migrant Education Program and those paid to migrants<br />
undertaking English as a Second Language courses at TAFE<br />
institutions. These payments are currently made by the<br />
Departments of Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic<br />
Affairs, and Employment Education and Training respectively.<br />
This decision will provide major public benefits through<br />
access to these programs via the network of Social Security<br />
offices instead of the present centralised capital city<br />
locations. To restructure the NCDC, the decision on which was announced<br />
yesterday.<br />
The Government is indebted to Mr Block for the major contribution<br />
he has made both through the efficiency scrutiny program and<br />
through the broader reviews to which I have just referred. I am<br />
therefore pleased to say that, while the Administrative Reform<br />
Unit will now be disbanded, Mr Block himself will continue to be<br />
available to advise me on an ad hoc basis on public sector<br />
management and administrative reform issues.<br />
266 1 I </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
