<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9251</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON PJ KEATING MP TYPHOON MEMORIAL, NOYERS BOCAGE, FRANCE 6 JUNE 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/06/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009251.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
I I T1fhin aeqi<br />
I cal<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING HP<br />
TYPHOON MEMORIAL, NOYERS BOCAGE, FRANCE<br />
6 JUNE 1994<br />
MUBARGO: ll. OOPM AEST<br />
This is a monument to the good which unites the people of<br />
many nations with the people of France. It unites the<br />
Australian people with the people of France.<br />
It is not the only such monument.<br />
The Australian airmen of World War II whose sacrifice is<br />
commemorated at Noyers Bocage followed that heroic<br />
generation of whom more than forty thousand lie buried in<br />
the fields of France.<br />
By their suffering and sacrifice, their courage and<br />
character, that earlier generation gave birth to a legend<br />
which still inspires and unites Australians.<br />
As brave and selfless as any who came before them, as<br />
devoted to the cause of freedom, as faithful to their<br />
ideals, as full of hope, the Australians commemorated<br />
here lived by that legend and died by it.<br />
Like those who fought at Gallipoli and on the Somme, they<br />
went into battle knowing that death was more than<br />
possible it was likely. And more likely each<br />
succeeding time.<br />
Today in Noyers Bocage we honour the airmen of all<br />
nations who fought and died in the strug-g to liberate<br />
Europe in World War II.<br />
And, because we are Australian, we honour our countrymen<br />
especially. We honour those who left the place and the<br />
people they loved and crossed the world to defend freedom<br />
and advance the cause of justice.<br />
Among those to whom we pay tribute today is Pilot Officer<br />
Don Mason, whose Typhoon was shot down on the eighteenth<br />
of June 1944 and whose aircraft and remains were not<br />
discovered until late 1992. It was this discovery which<br />
brought about Australia's association with the Typhoon<br />
Pilot Monument.<br />
W(-2 Aut Soc Thc haz<br />
And hon vai our We<br />
Nor peo corn nca<br />
goo ocei I ki<br />
liv<br />
havw pool The'<br />
inat ri2) the,<br />
We to as for<br />
Our the<br />
and That val fro<br />
liv 1<br />
it<br />
the sac and </p>
<p>There is a tnreac In AUULLljQ'a hintory whioh has always<br />
linked us to France. What the French called liberty,<br />
equality and fraternity Australians were inclined to<br />
call "' mateship" and the " fair go" for all.<br />
Australians had in mind the same ideal of a free and fair<br />
society. A better place for all men and women.<br />
Those commemorated here, all those who flew those<br />
hazardous missions, know the value of these things.<br />
And their sacrifice made us know them better. When we<br />
honour their memory, when we say they did not die in<br />
vain, we mean that we know they made our freedom safe and<br />
our faith the stronger.<br />
We mean that we will never forget.<br />
Nor can we forget today the trials endured by the French<br />
people. The people of Normandy the people of this<br />
community endured loss and devastation on a terrible<br />
scale. They endured what we in Australia have had the<br />
good fortune never to endure for we have never suffered<br />
occupation and tyranny.<br />
I know that the airmen who fought this war those who<br />
lived and those who died would want it known that we<br />
have not forgotten the support they received from the<br />
people of France.<br />
They would want it known that their own courage was<br />
matched by the French Resistance; by the people who<br />
risked their lives to protect them and help then find<br />
their way to safety and freedom on the ground.<br />
We see this monument to the Typhoon Pilots as a monument<br />
to the courage of the French people as well. We see it<br />
as a memorial to their resilience, and to their desire<br />
for peace.<br />
Our two countries are f ar apart in so many ways. But in<br />
the events of fifty years ago common values were proved<br />
and a story in common was written.<br />
That is the reason for this memorial. It enshrines those<br />
val~ ee and the story of a generation* who so believed in<br />
freedom and justice they were prepared to lay down their<br />
lives. It honours their memory and tolls new generations that<br />
the peace and freedom we now enjoy came by their<br />
sacrifice. It tells us that we must inherit their faith<br />
and pass it on to our children. G3727 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
