<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7629</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, EAGLEHAWK TOWN HALL 7 JUNE 1989 </title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/06/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007629.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE. EAGLEHAWK TOWN HALL<br />
7 JUNE 1989<br />
A 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, do you believe at the moment<br />
that we could be looking at a civil war with the army units<br />
In China moving Into position to fight with each other?<br />
FMi We've been In continuous contact with our embassy there<br />
and while they're saying that the possibility of conflict, of<br />
serious conflict between the armed forces is still there,<br />
they ares saying as in the last report to me that there's no<br />
firm evidence that it's reached that stage yet of serious<br />
significant fighting between units which would constitute the<br />
beginnings of this civil war syndrome that's been talked<br />
about. Nevertheless there is tiring going on still. One<br />
story that we've been told Is that a convoy that was going to<br />
our embassy to pick up luggage of those people that were<br />
flying out was In fact In a situation where there was firing,<br />
It was involved in firing upon it and it had to turn back.<br />
The luggage was In tact not picked up. So that will be<br />
Indicative of the seriousness, the continuing seriousness of<br />
the situation there.<br />
JOURNALIST: It does seem that there wan actually of one<br />
of the diplomatic compounds. That would seem like there's<br />
some sort of animosity at least towards foreigners perhaps.<br />
PM: I haven't received a report. It's different from when<br />
I'm back in the office and I'm getting them fed in In an<br />
almost minute by minute sense what's happening. At the last<br />
report I had which was a couple of hour. ago I hadn't had a<br />
reference to that and certainly if it has happened it would<br />
represent a serious escalation of the danger for the<br />
non-Chinese community.<br />
JOURNALIST: Will the embassy staff In Beijing be remaining<br />
there for the time being?<br />
PN! We have evacuated a lot of the families and I think we<br />
would not be continuing to fully man the embassy there. But<br />
clearly we want to keep in place a capacity to monitor the<br />
situation, to be able to report to us on what's happening. I<br />
must say that the work that's been done so far has been quite<br />
outstanding and those involved are to be congratulated on<br />
their commitment anid tenacity. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST; The situation seems to have deteriorated In<br />
Shanghai as well. Have you had any information on that yet?<br />
PM: Well yes, that it has become more tense there. But the<br />
problem that's plaguing us, not merely in regard to Shanghai<br />
but in Beijing generally Is the lack of absolutely firm<br />
evidence an to the state of play. For Instance the<br />
suggestion that now there is a new Secretary-General and that<br />
that confirms the disappearance of Zhao Ziyang. This has all<br />
been put to us in terms of it looks as though this may have<br />
happened without there being definitive statements, which is<br />
a reflection of the fact of course that effectively there is<br />
no governance of China now. The areat hope must be, as I've<br />
said in the last 24 hours or so, the great hope must be that<br />
the action that's been taken by those who are issuing order's,<br />
including the elements of the army, will not go to the point<br />
where Zhao Ziyang is going to be taken out of the picture<br />
entirely. Because he is in my judgement not merely the voice<br />
for moderation but the person who has the capacity and the<br />
vision to bring China together and to enable it to come out<br />
of this absolute tragedy which In such a short time has set<br />
back the years of constructive work that had preceded It.<br />
JOURNALIST; Are you concerned that he might have been hurt<br />
or in<br />
PM: There was one report at one stage that they were<br />
considering execution. Now that seems not to have been given<br />
effect to, certainly therelve been no repor'ts to confirm<br />
that. It really Is my profound hope that he Is not only<br />
going to be spared but that the forces of moderation will<br />
come through in a way which will see Zhao Ziyang being able<br />
to assutm a position of leadership. Because I think the<br />
welfare of his country very signficantly depends upon his<br />
capacity to survive and to be reinstated into a position of<br />
leadership. JOURNALIST: You're backing Zhao Ziyang against Deng<br />
Zlaoping? PM: Obviously you support a man who has opposed the use of<br />
force, who has counselled moderation and consultation.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you know anything of the man who is supposed<br />
to have replaced him?<br />
PM: Nfo, the only indication that we have is that Waio 5b, has<br />
been connected with the intelligence area. I believe it's<br />
suggested that he may have had a son who spent some time in<br />
Australia but I don't profess at this stage to know anything<br />
more than that general observation that he has been connected<br />
with the intelligence area. I repeat. I can't emphasise too<br />
much the significance that I attach to the survival and<br />
re-emergence to a position of power of Zhao Ziyang. I just<br />
know the qualities of this man and it would be an absolute<br />
tragedy for China if he was removed from a position of<br />
authority. </p>
<p>. B<br />
JOURNALISTz On another issue, it does seem today that the<br />
message is coming on loud and clear that inter'est rates are<br />
hurting. It does also seem from the finance industry, as we<br />
saw then today, they'd very much like you to consider<br />
assistinlg Ausutralians to save more. Can you hasten that<br />
process in any way or<br />
PM: Justt me pick up the two aspects of that. Obviously high<br />
interest rates hurt. I've made it quite clear that I know<br />
that. They're not high because we want them to be high,<br />
they're high at this point because it's necessary that we<br />
lower the level of activity In the country because we can't<br />
sustain the high level of Imports that are associated with<br />
that high level of activity. I think that's Increasingly<br />
understood, I think people know that I wouldn't be stupid<br />
enough to have Interest rates higher than it was necessary to<br />
have them. I hope and believe that they are under'standing<br />
that. I repeat, they will not be kept higher f or one day<br />
longer than is necessary to achieve the economic purpose of<br />
that. As to the second part of your question about proposals<br />
to Increase savings, as I've said, and I really haven't got<br />
anything to say in addition, that Is that we observe, take<br />
account of various proposals 7hat-are--mad_. I* h--them<br />
examined, they are'ldoked at. But You've got to understand<br />
thli9, that while it's easy for some people to say from their<br />
perspective, If you do this that will mean an Increase in<br />
saving of benefit to us in the finance Industry or somewhere<br />
else, but you've got to understand that If that Involves tax<br />
concessions then that is substituting certain savings, the<br />
certain removal from consumption for an uncertain<br />
corresponding saving If that saved taxation concession Is put<br />
back in the hands of Individuals. Now this doesn't mean that<br />
the proposals are not worth looking at. You have to have<br />
that particular point clearly in mind when you refer to these<br />
sorts of proposals.<br />
JOURNALIST: In the longer term do you see any merit In a<br />
scheme which taxes only real interest rather than nominal<br />
interest with the corresponding<br />
PM% On both sides of the ledger. Well. that is one of the<br />
proposals that has been around and it comes within the<br />
category Michelle of'what I said before of It being examined.<br />
But I've got to insist that the fact that we say that these<br />
things are being examined does not mean that they are on the<br />
agenda, that we're deciding that we're going to do theme<br />
things. But It is a responsible thing to do when people<br />
express concerns about these Issues and make suggestions,<br />
it's a reasonable and responsible thing to examine all the<br />
implications of them. That's been done.<br />
JOURNALIST! Can you elaborate on your point earlier today<br />
that it wasn very good advice to say to people to save the tax<br />
cuts? </p>
<p>PH: Well for' the very simple reason that why we have high<br />
interest rates at the moment Is because the level of demand<br />
is too high. if you look at the national accounts figures<br />
for the last 12 months you have a situation where the local<br />
production Is only able to satisfy about 50%, just under<br />
of the growth In demand. So what we need to have Is a<br />
situation where both on the investment aide and the personal<br />
consumption side, there is a reduction in the level of demand<br />
for goods and services. That's why it is better, If people<br />
can, to save the Income that's derived from the tax cuts and<br />
the family welf are payments. We recognise of course that<br />
obviously there's going to have to be some expenditure,<br />
people are going to need to do that. But where there is in a<br />
sense a choice. In their best interests and the best<br />
Interests of the country are Involved in not spending but<br />
saving because that both reduces the level of demand<br />
necessarily, and it also reduces the call upon overseas<br />
savings. The more we can save internally the lesrn we have to<br />
borrow trom abroad.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you think many people have that choice in<br />
realistic terms given the tax cuts are all skewed to midd.<br />
and lower income earners?<br />
PH: TO the extent they are skewed to middle and lower income<br />
earners, that's the direction which you would want the<br />
skewing in term. of giving the greatest assistance.<br />
JOURNALIST: But they are the people with greatest need also<br />
to spend that money higher Interest rates...<br />
PM: But what I'm saying is that they relatively are the ones<br />
who are going to get the greatest benefit. As I wan saying<br />
on television the other night, ift you look at the average<br />
income level with one income and a wife and two kids, the<br />
average picture will be about $ 24 a week derived benefit in<br />
tax reduction which is obviously over $ 100 a month. On<br />
average that would be well in excess of the increased payment<br />
involved for a higher Interest payment. Now, that is an<br />
average picture and I don't f or the moment ignore the fact<br />
that that average will describe some circumstances where<br />
people have much mare to pay out than they will receive. But<br />
on average that will be the situation. What I'm saying to my<br />
fellow Australians in this sort of situation. may I say a<br />
situation that I've been through myself. I remember when I<br />
first went to work at the ACTU I had real problems about<br />
meeting mortgage repayments, so it's not something of which<br />
I'm unaware. I'm simply saying to people that they are going<br />
to get signticiant tax cuts starting in just a few weeks time<br />
in July and I ask them to the extent obviously that they have<br />
to use those to meet additional burdens like mortgage<br />
repayments f or some of them, well obviously that has to be<br />
done. There are some items of outlay which they need to<br />
undertake, I understand that. I really am saying use the tax<br />
cuts to meet the added burden that you may have of interest<br />
repayments for this period, purchase what you've got to<br />
purchase, but to the extent that you've got the choice, save<br />
because that will be in your interest and in the country's<br />
interest and it will make the sooner that point at which we<br />
can look at a reduction of these high levels of Interest<br />
rates which are currently necessary to lower the level of<br />
activity. I hope that's putting it in non-technical jargon<br />
in terms that people can understand. Putting it as simply as<br />
7 what$= hs,. w" v" 4VFV 4T% &amp;, iu4-eMi4m wh-t watr mr%+ 4 h4, y </p>
<p>interest rates is that the level of demand for things that<br />
people are purchasing and the level of Investment by business<br />
Is at such a high level that it's involving bringing in so<br />
many import* that we can't sustain. Therefore we have to<br />
lower the level of activity and If in those circumtances<br />
people get more money coming to them with the tax cuts, the<br />
sensible thing to do Is not to use that to increase the level<br />
of demand but to help us to save more as a community. In<br />
that way there can be co-operation with Government in trying<br />
to bring a situation where we can reduce interest rates<br />
sooner rather than later. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
