<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9266</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J. KEATING MP, PRESS CONFERENCE, HYATT HOTEL, JAKARTA, TUESDAY, 28 JUNE 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/06/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009266.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINJISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
PRESS CONFERENCE, HYATT HOTEL, JAKARTA, TUESDAY, 28 JUNE<br />
1994 E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
PMV: You wanted some details and impressions of the meeting I had this<br />
morning with President Soeharto and I'm very happy to give you an<br />
opening stateme-nt -and I'll take questions.<br />
Well, as you may know I had a meeting this morning with President<br />
Soeharto which lasted two hours which was all business, a very<br />
productive discussion, from my point of view, I think, I could safely say<br />
from the President's point of view as well. We both remarked how<br />
relations between Australia and Indonesia ' had improved very<br />
dramatically in the last few years. This was evidenced by a constant<br />
flow of ministers back and forth, by a greater confluence of our<br />
business interests, the traffic of business people from both countries<br />
one to the other, by the increasing tourism between Australia and<br />
Indonesia, and underpinning that a better understanding of our<br />
respective cultures and the* role that each of us are playing in the<br />
region. I'm giving you a short hand version of these things, they were much<br />
more extensive, of course.<br />
The President and I then discussed the very great progress which had<br />
been made at APEC, -both in Seattle and post Seattle and pre Bogor.<br />
That is, the work of the special assistance led by Mr Bintoro and him<br />
having been joined by the special assistance of other countries to, if<br />
you like, develop further the decisions that were made by the leaders<br />
at Blake Island in Seattle so that they could be brought to a point of<br />
adoption and advancement at the meeting in Bogor. Both of us agreed<br />
on the need for freer trade consistent with GATT and the President<br />
said that he was looking forward to the GATT agreements being </p>
<p>consumnated before January 1995 so that we could see the GATT<br />
agreement coming into force, which would itself be an important thing<br />
the whole GATT regime having been agreed in the lead up to the<br />
Bogor meeting.<br />
Our discussion moved on then to relations between Australia and<br />
ASEAN, indeed between Australia-New Zealand and ASEAN and<br />
there I intimated to the President that the Government of Thailand had<br />
raised with Australia the desirability of Australasia joining AFTA and<br />
that I was interested in the President's view of how he saw AFTA<br />
developing and what role he thought Australia and New Zealand might<br />
be able to play. We had quite a long discussion about this and, I think,<br />
the response that I received on this issue was a very encouraging one<br />
from the President where he thought the developments that have<br />
already taken place, within ASEAN in respect of freer trade, were very<br />
encouraging and what we had done as a country was very<br />
encouraging in terms of reducing our tariffs and, in a sense, there was<br />
a sort of developing natural confluence at any rate of the relations<br />
between our two countries. That is, in trade, remarking as he did, that<br />
two way trade had already reached $ 3 billion.<br />
The President and I spent quite a lot of the time on those two subjects<br />
APEC, AFTA and 9ER. and the bilateral relationship in general. I told<br />
the President that Australia had been very heartened by the initiatives<br />
taken by him and his Government over the last year towards greater<br />
openness including today's reports about further deregulation of * their<br />
product markets and the adoption of an inves-tment -package, a<br />
deregulatory package for greater foreign investment freedoms within<br />
the Indonesian economy. I said, infhe context of that opening up of<br />
Indonesia, that the Government of Australia and I have therefore been<br />
disappointed at recent events with the press closures which appear to<br />
conflict or at least contrast with the openness which had generally<br />
occurred in the Indonesian economy. The President took the<br />
opportunity to explain his perspective on the closures saying that it was<br />
very important that national stability and national unity at this time of<br />
great economic growth and transformation that these things were to be<br />
taken as given in this society and that the journals in question had put<br />
some of things, that is national unity and stability, at risk.<br />
The discussion then ranged back over the forthcoming meeting in<br />
November and the fact that as this will probably be the second, of<br />
maybe a series of meetings, there will be very heavy international<br />
attention on the meeting, perhaps even more than there was in Seattle.<br />
The need therefore for the Special Assistance Groups and he as the<br />
Chair of the meeting to try to draw the strands and the best possible<br />
result from the second leaders meeting towards a set of outcomes for<br />
Bogor which advance the whole cause of the Asia-Pacific and its<br />
trading relations. </p>
<p>So, I'll leave my opening remarks at that and I'll be glad to take<br />
questions.<br />
J: Ian MoPhedran, Canberra Times. Mr Keating, a report due out<br />
tomorrow by the Department of Foreign Affairs warns that East Timor<br />
is the issue most likely to cause difficulties in the bilateral relationship.<br />
Did you discuss East Timor?<br />
PM: It came up in the discussion, but we didn't discuss it in detail.<br />
J: In what context Prime Minister, did it come up in the discussion?<br />
PM: Just talking about how in the past this issue had caused difficulties<br />
between relations between Indonesia and Australia and Indonesia and<br />
the United States. The President being very aware of the problems<br />
which it had caused.<br />
J: Phillip Williams, ABC TV. How would you characterize the response<br />
from the President to your concern regarding the press clamp down?<br />
PM: I said last week that I think I've developed a good constructive working<br />
relationship with the President and in such a relationship one is able to<br />
express oneself in terms of issues of concern and this was a matter I'd<br />
said that was a matter of disappointment to the Australian Government<br />
and to me. I think, he took that seriously and sought then to explain<br />
the decision where he had come from, what he had thought the role<br />
of these journals have been in their societal debate juxtaposed against<br />
the need to keep a singular focus on Indonesia's development and<br />
growth at this particular time.<br />
J: Did you accept that explanation?<br />
PM: I listened to what the President had said. I'd raised and said what I<br />
wished to say and he responded.<br />
J: Geoff Kitney, Sydney Morning Herald. Mr Keating, did President<br />
Soeharto indicate how this issue may be resolved to you?<br />
PM: No, he didn't. No.<br />
J: So, he didn't offer any view about whether these newspapers may<br />
return at some point?<br />
PM: No, he didn't.<br />
J: Indonesian journalist. Prime Minster, did President Soeharto discuss<br />
his visit to Australia because he has been invited? </p>
<p>PM: He has been invited by me a number of times. I didn't reiterate the<br />
invitation today, I didn't need to. But it wasn't discussed. I know the<br />
President has said to a number of people including, I think, some of<br />
our own people here that he would like to go to Australia. But again,<br />
arrangements have just have been inconvenient or they have not been<br />
put into place. He knows there is a general standing invitation, it is a<br />
matter for him to take it up if he chooses.<br />
J: Indonesian journalist. When is the proper time according to your<br />
assessment for President Soeharto to visit?<br />
PM: I think that is for his assessment, rather than mine. You see, it's not for<br />
me to say when he should visit Australia. Governments very kindly<br />
provide general invitations to heads of state and heads of government<br />
to visit and it's up to their discretion and their convenience to take it up.<br />
J: Indonesian journalist. If President Soeharto visited Australia this year,<br />
can you guarantee no demonstrations?<br />
PM: Well, he has not given me any indication that he's coming to Australia<br />
this year.<br />
J: Malcolm Farr, Telegraph Mirror. Prime Minister, has President<br />
Soeharto given any indication at all of his personal timetable for<br />
staying in the leadership or perhaps leaving?<br />
PM: No, he didn't raise it and nor did I.<br />
J: Is that a matter of concern, not concern, but certainly to the<br />
Government? How long he stays in the job.<br />
PM: The Australian Government?<br />
J: Yes.<br />
PM: It is a matter solely for him and the people of Indonesia and I didn't<br />
presume to raise the issue or to put any view. Not that we have a view<br />
about it.<br />
J: Indonesian journalist. You were asked a question on President<br />
Soeharto was he happy or not?<br />
PM: Well, I'm not here to give you I can give you a sense of the<br />
meetings. I'm not here to give you an, if you like, the body language of<br />
the meeting. I said at the start it was a very convivial meeting and<br />
conducted in a relaxed and sincere atmosphere. </p>
<p>J: Mark Baker, Melbourne Age. Mr Keating, on the subject of APEC did<br />
President Soeharto express any concerns about directions of the body<br />
particularly to the extent that he feels perhaps that it is being<br />
dominated by developed nations..<br />
PM: He did say that he thought it was important that APEC develop for all<br />
the countries of the region and that the developed countries should<br />
understand the aspirations of developing countries and consider<br />
developing countries when they think about APEC's charter. Now, I<br />
couldn't agree more with that. I think that is spot on. In fact, one of the<br />
things Australia has always said is that we see the interests of<br />
developing countries and developed countries being well and truly able<br />
to be catered for in such a structure. Now, we did have a discussion<br />
about the World Trade Organisation and about worker rights and what<br />
that may mean in the future. I indicated to the President that we were<br />
very concerned in Australia about the rights of workers. We had award<br />
minimums and we had award standards to protect the work force. He<br />
made similar points about Indonesia, but made the obvious point that<br />
the capacity to pay people in Indonesia depended on the prosperity of<br />
the Indonesian economy and that capacity is going to rise over time.<br />
But, I think, he was well aware as I am that there can be some room to<br />
misconstrue concerns about worker rights in terms of maybe quasi<br />
protectionist devices against developing countries and he is alert to<br />
that. I told him of my discussions of this in Europe and I gave him the<br />
full account of those.<br />
J: Phillip Williams, ABC TV. Prime Minister, part of your mission, I<br />
believe, is to boost business ties between the two countries. Did you<br />
discuss ways that could be done and why do you think Australia and<br />
Indonesia's business relationship hasn't been good in the past?<br />
PM: I think these things flow from general political and strategic<br />
relationships, you know, trading relationships and Australia's is better<br />
now than it has been, I think, probably in the last couple of decades<br />
with Indonesia. As a consequence we are seeing a much better flow<br />
of business interests and the exhibition here, the largest Australia has<br />
ever mounted is, I think, proof positive that we see the relationship<br />
seriously and we want to invest in this country and vice versa.<br />
J: Ian McPhedran, Canberra Times. Did President Soeharto undertake<br />
to take your aspirations for CER and AFTA to ASEAN and did you give<br />
him an indication of your time frame?<br />
PM: No. This is a proposal put to Australia by a member of ASEAN<br />
Thailand. It is not a proposal put by Australia to ASEAN. But, I agreed<br />
at the behest of Thai ministers, Prime Minister Chuan and Deputy<br />
Prime Minister Supachai to raise it with other ASEAN leaders and in so<br />
doing I raised it when I had the opportunity here today. </p>
<p>J: Indonesian journalist. Do Australia and Indonesia have the common<br />
push for the APEC summit?<br />
PM: No, I think any commonality in terms of the APEC summit will emerge<br />
from the special assistance gatherings. And, I think, under the<br />
chairmanship of Mr Bintoro this is proceeding quite well.<br />
J: Wally Brown, Courier Mail. Prime Minister, did you refer to the<br />
republican issue?<br />
PM: No.<br />
J: Geoff Kitney, Sydney Morning Herald. Mr Keating, is it your view that<br />
the matter of the closure of the magazines is essentially a domestic<br />
matter or did you express a view to President Soeharto about how<br />
Australia would prefer to see that issue resolved?<br />
PM: No, it is obviously a domestic matter, but that doesn't preclude us from<br />
expressing our view about it, which I did. Particularly in the context of<br />
the opening up of this economy and society which has been occurring<br />
under his Government. Most obviously again today in a substantial<br />
announcement about further deregulation of their product markets and<br />
the freeing up of foreign investment controls. I pointed to the apparent<br />
tension in that, inconsistency in that, and that led the President to give<br />
me an indication, at least, where he was coming from.<br />
J: So, is Australia's view that we would like to see those magazines get<br />
their licenses back?<br />
PM: I think Australia's view is that the opening up of an economy brings<br />
with it a chance, an opportunity, for the transmission of information<br />
which is best accomplished in a plural media. Therefore, it follows that<br />
as the Indonesian economy opens up and its society opens up, its<br />
media should have the chance to reflect those changes.<br />
J: Mark Baker. Did President Soeharto elaborate in any way on how he<br />
saw these publications threatening, putting at risk the stability..<br />
PM: No, he said that he thought I mean, Indonesia is, again, still growing<br />
quite strongly and it's playing a role in the world, in APEC most<br />
obviously, in the non-aligned movement amongst other things and that<br />
this was, he thought, a time for a clear unity of purpose and not the<br />
nagging away at divisions. Now, that is his view and obviously<br />
juxtaposed against his long history as President of this country.<br />
J: Indonesian journalist. Indonesia would like to have Australia's help in<br />
strengthening ASEAN influence within the structure of APEC. </p>
<p>4 PM: I think, ASEAN has already had Australia's support in seeking a full<br />
place for it within the APEC structure and for member countries. The<br />
fact that the first summit was successful, that's the summit or the<br />
leaders meeting in Seattle, I think, demonstrates that ASEAN had no<br />
trouble finding its place in the organisation, most obviously<br />
demonstrated by the fact that President Soeharto, a leading member of<br />
ASEAN is the chair and Indonesia is the host of the second meeting.<br />
Thank you.<br />
ends<br />
k </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
