<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>21662</transcript-id>
    <title>Address at the Opening of the Lowy Institute of International Policy  Sydney </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>31/03/2005</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Frank, Shirley Lowy, other members of the Lowy family, Allan Gyngell, ladies and gentleman. This is for me both an honour as Prime Minister and a special pleasure as a friend of Frank and Shirley Lowy and their families of many years standing to be here tonight, later to talk about Australia's place in the world.  I am here at the moment to officially open this building of this wonderful institute, to pay tribute to Frank Lowy for everything that he has contributed as a wonderful Australian - to the modern Australia that we have.</p>
<p> I've known Frank for a long period of time.  I have reached that stage in life where I don't refer to old friends - I refer to long standing friends - and Frank is a very long standing friend. Importantly Frank has never been a fair weather friend; you don't last in Australian politics 31 years without experiencing both the highs and the lows. And at all points of the political experience, Frank has been a friend of mine. He's been a person possessed of some wonderful qualities; one of which has been the soaring optimism and enthusiasm about the future of this country and the place that this country occupies in the world. He's also possessed of an extraordinarily open mind; somebody who has his strong views but is receptive to new ideas.</p>
<p> And I remember when he came to me and said he wanted to invest a very large amount in the creation of this institute. I encouraged him and he talked extensively to me about his aims and his goals, the reach of the people that would comprise his board, the sort of subjects that it would deal with, his commitment to intellectual rigour and policy debate and all of that has come together.</p>
<p> So I'm very honoured Frank, and personally delighted that you've given me the privilege of opening this building. It's a wonderful old building and it's housed many activities over the years and this is yet another dimension of what it's going to do. I don't know, somebody was telling me about the cricket field that use to be up the back.  I don't know whether that's going to be re-created but (inaudible) just at the moment Frank and can I say what a terrific job you are doing as the head of... I know you now call it the Australian Football Association.  As an old rugby man I'm still a bit hung up with this soccer description, but whatever it is, to me there last Saturday night with you and to feel the enthusiasm of the crowd in that game between Australia and Iraq was a wonderful experience and I think Frank it's another demonstration of your dedication to this country and what you've been willing to give back to a country that has been so enriched by your personal contribution.</p>
<p> I wish the institute well. I'm sure that in the years ahead I would read a lot of things that it says. I'm sure that I will agree with some of it, I'm sure I'll disagree with others; that is the nature of an institute with proper intellectual rigour.  The important thing is that you are interested in Australia's place in the world and this institute is committed to a better understanding of that and that matters to me, and it matters to all other people who are dedicated to rigorous public debate for the future of our country.</p>
<p> Frank thank you very much for what you've further done for Australia in endowing this institute.</p>
<p>   [ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
