<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7301</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER INTERNATIONAL CONFEDERATION OF FREE TRADE UNIONS MELBOURNE - 14 MARCH 1988</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/03/1988</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007301.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PR 005067<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
INTERNATIONAL CONFEDERATION OF FREE TRADE UNIONS<br />
MELBOURNE 14 MARCH 1988<br />
Dr Narayan,<br />
Simon Crean,<br />
Francis Blanchard,<br />
John Vanderveken,<br />
Delegates. Australians are this year celebrating the Bicentenary of<br />
European settlement of Australia.<br />
This milestone in our national development provides<br />
Australians with a great opportunity to reflect on our<br />
achievements over the past two hundred years, and recognise<br />
as well where we can rectify shortcomings in particular to<br />
work on ways in which we can come to an understanding of the<br />
40,000 year heritage of the prior occupants of this land,<br />
the Aboriginal people.<br />
To celebrate the Bicentenary, the Federal Government is<br />
assisting in an enormous variety of events in many of which<br />
as Prime Minister I have had the privilege of being<br />
involved.<br />
Among these events, I am particularly pleased that my<br />
Government could provide funds to assist the staging of this<br />
Congress. This support was given in recognition of the major<br />
contribution which the trade union movement has made, and<br />
continues to make, to the development of the Australian<br />
nation. For as a Labor Prime Minister and former President of the<br />
Australian Council of Trade Unions, it is my assessment that<br />
this Fourteenth Conference of the International<br />
Confederation of Free Trade Unions is a landmark event.<br />
2<br />
Ah;<br />
-AW11 </p>
<p>2.<br />
The Congress brings us together at a time when the world<br />
economy is experiencing stresses so extreme they threaten to<br />
undo the framework on which the international community has<br />
relied ' since World War II with all the dire implications<br />
such a'reversal would have for the living standards of trade<br />
unionists and their families.<br />
Such a time highlights as never before the interdependence<br />
of the economies of the world the extent to which the<br />
prosperity of one of us depends ultimately on the&amp; prosperity<br />
of us all.<br />
In such a time, international organisations including this<br />
Confederation representating as it does the great<br />
organisations of labour throughout the world assume<br />
monumental importance in their capacity to transcend<br />
sectional barriers and to act as international sounding<br />
boards for the debate and resolution of our shared<br />
challenges. For all these reasons, it is a pleasure to welcome you to<br />
Australia and to the City of Melbourne, and it is an honour<br />
to address this opening session of your Fourteenth Congress.<br />
Despite the diversity of the nations whose trade union<br />
movements we represent, we are united by our shared<br />
commitment to the principles of free trade unionism.<br />
It is regrettable therefore that not all those trade<br />
unionists invited to the Conference have been able to take<br />
their places here.<br />
In particular, I must voice my most profound disappointment<br />
at the decision of the Polish Government to refuse<br />
permission to Lech Walesa and a number of his colleagues to<br />
attend this Congress.<br />
Nobody with any commitment to the trade union movement could<br />
fail to respect the heroic efforts of Lech Walesa and the<br />
Solidarity movement to establish free trade unionism in<br />
Poland. My Government made a number of representations to the Polish<br />
authorities, and I wrote personally to General Jaruzelski,<br />
encouraging them not to stand in the way of Lech Walesa<br />
accepting his invitation to be here.<br />
Allowing him permission to attend this Congress would have<br />
reflected great credit on the Polish authorities, both in<br />
Australia and the rest of the world.<br />
Delegates, The recent attacks on the rights of trade unions in South<br />
Africa deserve our strongest condemnation. 005068 </p>
<p>By its latest measures of repression, the Botha Government<br />
has moved once again to strangle non-violent self-expression<br />
by the black majority and to nullify the capacity of-black<br />
working people to defend their industrial rights.<br />
It is depressing but true that the situation of black trade<br />
unionists in South Africa is no better and in some ways<br />
worse in 1988 than it was at the time of the 13th Congress<br />
in 1983.<br />
The Australian Government fully supports attempts by trade<br />
unionists, church people and others to oppose the draconian<br />
new restrictions on the political activities of<br />
extra-parliamentary opposition, human rights groups and<br />
trade unionists.<br />
Delegates, It is important that the ICFTU has chosen to hold its<br />
Congress in Australia because free trade unionisfi is, and<br />
has been for more than a century, a powerful and,<br />
constructive force in this country and in New Zealand. In<br />
our wider South Pacific region, trade unionism is still a<br />
developing force in the Pacific Island states a force<br />
which we would all wish to support and foster.<br />
That is why the threat to trade unions in Fiji following the<br />
two coups last year was greatly troubling to the Australian<br />
Government and people. We made vigorous representations<br />
about the abuses of civil and political rights following the<br />
coups. The Government welcomes the improved situation for trade<br />
unionists in Fiji over the past several months, as witnessed<br />
by the ICFTU mission in January. We are, however,<br />
monitoring developments closely and we look forward to an<br />
early return to constitutional arrangements which protect<br />
the rights and interests of all the peoples of Fiji<br />
including, of course, trade unionists.<br />
Delegates, I just mentioned Australia's long history of trade unionism.<br />
It's worth recalling at this gathering that our association<br />
with trade unionism in fact dates back to the earliest<br />
decades of the nineteenth century when organised labour was<br />
struggling to emerge in the wake of the English Industrial<br />
Revolution.<br />
As a penal settlement, Australia became the new home of<br />
thousands of men and women expelled from Britain and Ireland<br />
for crimes which today seem, in large part, ludicrously<br />
petty. Other convicts were transported for political crimes<br />
including some whose offences were to have helped found the<br />
modern trade union movement. 005069 </p>
<p>Among them were Tolpuddle Martyrs, for example, who were<br />
convicted in 1833 for the " crime" ' of swearing a secret oath<br />
to establish a trade union. 0<br />
Our convict origins illustrate the harshness with which the<br />
authorities attempted to resist the irresistible new force<br />
of trade unionism. But they also had the beneficial effect<br />
of enlarging the capacity of people in this country to<br />
understand and where necessary to struggle against prejudice<br />
pnd repression.<br />
' Perhaps it was because of this capacity that Australians by<br />
the 1850' s had established one of the earliest and most<br />
successful trade union movements in the world.<br />
That movement attained, over the next fifty years, some of<br />
the world's earliest landmark victories in wages and<br />
conditions. one of the world's first modern trade unions wag-founded in<br />
this city in 1850 when twenty-five stone masons ormed<br />
themselves into the Operative Masons Society.<br />
In 1859 what was claimed to be the world's first Trades Hall<br />
was founded on the site where it still stands in Carlton.<br />
And, most dramatically, workers in Sydney and Melbourne in<br />
1855 and 1856 won the pioneering achievemen-t of the<br />
eight-hour working day, which meant ' a reduction in their<br />
working week from sixty to forty-eight hours.<br />
That achievement is still honoured today throughout<br />
Australia with a public holiday and I can only commend<br />
the organisers of this conference for the coincidence of<br />
timing that brings us together on this Labor Day 1988, 132<br />
years after the first eight hour day was won.<br />
It was during the momentous strikes and lockouts of the<br />
1890s that Australian workers recognised that industrial<br />
action alone could not achieve all of their aims and<br />
concluded that they must exercise political influence. So<br />
they founded one of the world's first labour parties the<br />
Australian Labor Party.<br />
That party has matured into a political movement of national<br />
scope, and I speak with pride today as the leader of a Labor<br />
Party which, only three years short of its hundredth<br />
birthday, holds office Federally and in four of the six<br />
Australian states.<br />
I am sketching this brief history because it is germane to<br />
the theme which I wish to present today, and is in turn<br />
relevant to the theme of your report " The Challenge of<br />
Change" which you will be discussing later in this Congress. 005070 </p>
<p>That theme is the enormous potential for the trade union<br />
movement, in partnership with Government and business, in<br />
managing and resolving essential economic issues confronting<br />
a nation issues which go to the heart of job creation and<br />
living standards.<br />
Few here would question just how large is the challenge of<br />
change. The symptom of the problem is the massive imbalance in the<br />
current account positions of many countries, especially the<br />
largest ones.<br />
The world's major economies, notably the United States and<br />
Japan, have to undertake large scale economic<br />
reconstruction.<br />
In the case of the United States, the need is to become more<br />
export-oriented, particularly in terms of manufactures and<br />
services. For Japan and to an extent Germany the task<br />
is to promote production of non-traded goods and to import<br />
more. And for all of us, developed and develbbping nations<br />
alike, the corresponding challenge is to retain and expand<br />
trading arrangements which are free and non-discriminatory<br />
and to restructure our own economies to take advantage of<br />
new trading opportunities.<br />
Increased protectionism is not the answex. That way lie<br />
only diminished opportunities for all our members<br />
collectively to improve their living standards, not least<br />
for those of our members who come from the poorest<br />
countries. These economic challenges themselves place new demands on<br />
trade unions demands to foster the necessary changes in<br />
the pattern of domestic production and demand while securing<br />
the highest sustainable living standards for all workers.<br />
The need for these changes is buried deep in the conduct of<br />
economic policy by the major economies over many years.<br />
Change postponed has magnified the problem. It is in our<br />
collective interests as free trade unionists to seek to<br />
promote the necessary structural adjustments as quickly as<br />
is feasible so as not to add further to the size and costs<br />
of the eventual adjustment task..<br />
We in Australia have had particular need to address these<br />
problems, because we have also had to contend with a sudden,<br />
sharp deterioration in our terms of trade. And we are proud<br />
of the way we have worked together to meet the challenge.<br />
The trade union move ment and the Federal Labor Government<br />
have forged a partnership and are, together with business<br />
leaders, managing and gradually surmounting our great<br />
national economic challenge.,. 005071 </p>
<p>Our partnership, embodied. in the Prices and Incomes Accord,<br />
has allowed us to embark on e strategy which has produced<br />
economic achievements of fundamental and lasting importance<br />
not only to trade unionists but : to all Australians.<br />
The Accord, drawn up in the period before the Federal<br />
elections of 1983, was based on the realisation by both the<br />
ACTU and the Labor Party, then in Opposition, that the<br />
nation's economic problems would not be solved yithout a<br />
dramatically new approach.<br />
At the time, Australia was passing through a period of<br />
social, economic and technological upheaval. Little had<br />
been done to respond to the challenge posed by those<br />
changes: there was too much confrontation and division; too<br />
many wasted opportunities.<br />
By 1983, the economy was in deep recession. Unemployment<br />
had reached levels which were higher than had been<br />
experienced at any time since the 193-0s. Inflftion stood at<br />
double digit levels.<br />
The basic strategy of the Acc6rd was the substitution of<br />
consultation and co-operation'-for confrontation and<br />
division. The Accord recognised the importance of wage justice. But<br />
it also accepted that wage restraint was -eeded if the<br />
national economy was to recover and if we were to rebuild<br />
our productive capacity.<br />
The strategy has paid off handsomely for Australians first<br />
and foremost, through the creation of jobs at twice the rate<br />
of the OECD average. In human-terms that means we have<br />
together created in five years nearly one million new jobs.<br />
Unemployment has fallen from over 10 per cent when we came<br />
to office to 7.4 per cent today.<br />
Inflation has fallen; interest rates are falling; economic<br />
growth from 1983/ 84 to 1987/ 88 is expected to average around<br />
4 per cent per annum.<br />
Industrial disputation is now-60 per cent lower than under<br />
the previous government. I<br />
I list these achievements before an international audience<br />
not to advance domestic political goals, but to sheet home<br />
the credit for them where it in very large part belongs to<br />
the Australian trade union movement. That role I believe<br />
deserves international recognition and indeed serves as a<br />
distinguished international model in these times of economic<br />
uncertainty. Because it would have been easy for the trade union movement<br />
to view our election in 1983, a. fter seven years of<br />
conservative national government, as the signal for<br />
unrestrained pressure for short term improvements in wages.<br />
005072 </p>
<p>That course would have reflected the traditional priority of<br />
the trade union, movement to assist its existing employed<br />
members through~ iincreased wages.<br />
But the pursuit'of such a priority in the 1980s would have<br />
been tragically shortsighted. It could only have set back<br />
the essential national task of increasing economic<br />
competitiveness and creating jobs for those without them.<br />
To the lasting credit of the trade union movement, it<br />
eschewed that course and instead, through the Accord,<br />
adopted a new and highly constructive approach to the<br />
management of the national economy.<br />
This strategy was the more necessary and its success the<br />
more remarkable because Australia suffered a sudden and<br />
sharp deterioration of our terms of trade. This brought<br />
into even sharper focus the need to improve our<br />
international competitiveness in a sustained way,. by means of<br />
a fundamental restructuring of the economy.<br />
That necessarily demanded short term sacrifices on the part<br />
of all Australians, including wage and salary earners.<br />
Although money wages have continued to increase through the<br />
centralised wage fixing mechanisms, wages in real terms have<br />
fallen since 1985.<br />
This has kept inflation down despite inflationary<br />
pressures fuelled by depreciation while at the same time<br />
helping Australian industries retain the competitive edge<br />
which they gained from depreciation.<br />
The current wage-fixing arrangements also provide for<br />
trade-offs between wage increases and productivity<br />
improvements a means of retaining competitive labour costs<br />
while also increasing wealth-producing workplace efficiency.<br />
The Prices and Incomes Accord also accepted that real wages<br />
are only part of the story. Under the Accord, the<br />
Government committed itself to lifting the social wage in<br />
return for wage restraint. These commitments have been<br />
honoured. Substantial additional Government assistance for low<br />
income families;<br />
An 8 per cent real increase in pensions for the elderly;<br />
Greater incentive for children from lower income<br />
families to continue education. The proportion of<br />
students who complete secondary education has risen from<br />
36 per cent to 53 per cent and is still rising;<br />
A doubling of child care places; 005 073 </p>
<p>Restoration and improvement of the system of national<br />
health insurance, Medicare, significantly reducing the<br />
financial burden of health costs for low income<br />
families; and<br />
Doubling of funds for public housing and a new scheme to<br />
help 270,000 young families into home ownership.<br />
Underpinning all this, we have reformed the taxation system,<br />
ensuring that those who benefit from the returns to capital<br />
pay their fair share of the tax burden, and that other forms<br />
of non-wage income no longer escape taxation. As a<br />
consequence, we have been able to reduce taxation for<br />
ordinary wage and salary earners.<br />
Delegates,<br />
All this proves without doubt that an enlightened<br />
partnership between Governments and trade unions can workand<br />
that it can deliver benefits not just to t~ reunionists<br />
but to all citizens.<br />
In Australia, constructive Government-union relations are<br />
now a fact of life.<br />
They are an essential element of a wider network of<br />
nation-wide consultations involving business and community<br />
groups which are essential to the resoluti-, on of the<br />
important issues of economic management in this country.<br />
I have long believed and my experience in Government has<br />
confirmed that if you make available to the people who are<br />
affected by a decision the information which is necessary<br />
for them to understand the reasons behind that decision; and<br />
if indeed you involve representatives of the people in the<br />
formulation of those decisions you will achieve two things:<br />
A community more readily able to accept decisions,<br />
including decisions which on their face may seem to run<br />
counter to their immediate interests; and<br />
A decision making process which is capable of producing<br />
better decisions.<br />
I know that our societies differ in many ways, reflecting as<br />
they do the differences of history, culture, institutions<br />
and political systems.<br />
However this philosophy of consultation and cooperation<br />
transcends those differences. Indeed without applying it in<br />
our national and workplace structures, I believe we will not<br />
be able to cope with the problems posed by what you rightly<br />
characterise as " The Challenge of Change".<br />
Let me describe three specific areas in which we in<br />
Australia have implemented and found constructive this way<br />
of addressing our national economic problems. 005074 </p>
<p>First, at the level of macro-economic policy, was the<br />
National Economic Summit which I convened immediately after<br />
our 1983 election victory.<br />
This Summit, a conference of Government, unions, employers,<br />
farmers, consumer and other community groups, was a unique<br />
exercise in information sharing and debate about our<br />
economic plight and of methods of resolving it.<br />
one of the lasting achievements of the Summit wa-s the<br />
establishment of the representative Economic Planning<br />
Advisory Council which continues to provide an important<br />
forum for discussion and analysis of economic policy issues,<br />
especially those bearing on Australia's medium to longer<br />
term growth and development prospects.<br />
Second, at the industry level, the tripartite Australian<br />
manufacturing Council provides policy advice to t he<br />
Government on the development of Australian manufacturing<br />
industry<br />
Through consultation, we have established industry plans<br />
that are helping to revitalise and restructure the mature<br />
sectors of Australian industry, such as steel, heavy<br />
engineering, motor vehicles, and textiles, clothing and<br />
footwear.<br />
Third, at the workplace level, we have em ' barked on a major<br />
program to eliminate restrictive work and~ hmanagement<br />
practices practices which had been adopted in easier times<br />
but which now retard the growth of Australian living<br />
standards.<br />
Also at the workplace level, we are keen to promote<br />
increased industrial democracy. Genuine industrial<br />
democracy can increase productivity, decrease confrontation<br />
and strikes, and generally promote a constructive sense of<br />
identification by workers with and involvement in the<br />
decisions which affect a large proportion of their life.<br />
I do not underestimate the difficulties of breaking down the<br />
obstacles in the path towards real industrial democracy.<br />
But we are again through information sharing and<br />
consultation making progress towards this goal.<br />
Delegates, It is apparent from what I have said in this forum and<br />
elsewhere that I believe the world is at a crucial stage<br />
in its economic and political development.<br />
It is, I hope, equally apparent that I believe we in<br />
Australia have developed methods of consultation and<br />
co-operation which, in our context at least, are relevant to<br />
meeting the challenge of change, and which are proving to be<br />
useful means of fairly distributing the burdens and benefits<br />
of change. 005075 </p>
<p>I trust that over the next few days, delegates to this<br />
Congress will be able to address, formally and informally,<br />
the fundamental task of understanding and mastering those<br />
processes of change.<br />
We live in times of uncertainty, but that should only<br />
encourage us in the search for answers.<br />
We can take comfort from the fact that on even the most<br />
fundamental threat facing us the threat of nuclear<br />
annihilation the processes of careful negotiation are<br />
yielding positive results.<br />
The recent agreement by the superpowers to eliminate an<br />
entire class of nuclear weapons gives us hope that future<br />
negotiations may lead to further cuts in the arsenals.<br />
For trade unionists, there could be no more inspiring<br />
prospect than that the resources now consumed by tfre<br />
accumulation of the weapons of war might be redire. ted for<br />
the purposes of peace and development. O 507 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
