<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8894</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J. KEATING, MP SPEECH TO THE LUNCHEON FOR HIS EXCELLENCY DR CENSU TABONE, PRESIDENT OF MALTA, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA, 16 JUNE 1993</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/06/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008894.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
RPRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING, MP<br />
SPEECH TO THE LUNCHEON FOR HIS EXCELLENCY DR CENSU<br />
TABONE, PRESIDENT OF MALTA, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA, 16<br />
JUNE 1993<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
President Tabone, Mrs Tabone, the Deputy Prime Minister and roreign<br />
Minister, Your Excellencies, distinguished guests and ladies and gentlemen.<br />
Mr President It Is my very great pleasure to welcome you to Australia. As<br />
countries of long standing friendships which we have had and with a very large<br />
Maltese born component of our population we have been very much two<br />
countries who have had friendship with one another for a very long period of<br />
time. I am told that almost every family In Malta has some relative in Australia<br />
and so when you come here you came to a place where Malta Is more than<br />
well represented.<br />
The Maltese have made a very significant contribution to this country. It is a<br />
strange but true fact that notwithstanding the fact that Malta is a small country it<br />
has a disproportionate influence on Australia. This has been the case of other<br />
smaller countries too and in the migration program after the war we have seen<br />
Maltese born Australians take their places in Australian society and make their<br />
way and have their families and then watch them grow up and prosper, to take<br />
a mnore complete place In our society as the children of Maltese people born<br />
here.<br />
They have been great contributors and I am sure the Leader of the Opposition<br />
won't mind me saying one of the other great virtues we find In them Is that they<br />
mostly support the Labor party. This Is not an exclusive, we don't have<br />
exclusivity but we have got more than our fair share. I do not know why that Is,<br />
but It seems to be a phenomenon which is true. The fact is though many<br />
people of Maltese decent have been coming here since about 1810 and down<br />
through the years they can be found not just In the capital cities and they seem<br />
to congregate In places like Sydney and Melbourne, but also across the<br />
hinterland of Australia In the townships and the provincial cities. So they wre<br />
very much the pioneers of Australia amongst the pioneers-of. Australia's </p>
<p>economic development: in rural and provincial communities which were small<br />
places where they have played a prominent role and of course since the<br />
Second World War pioneers In our social development.<br />
We were speaking earlier about the multicultural character of the Australian<br />
community and the Maltese community have played no small part In this great<br />
social development in Australia and part of the tolerance of the country and part<br />
of its sense of commitment to Australia on the part of many immigrants there<br />
would be none that have shown a lead more than the Maltese who have come<br />
here and called this place their own. their home and built a life for themselves<br />
here. It has been a very substantial and creative role In our society and in the post-<br />
War development of our cities and we think that this multicultural development<br />
Is a unique thing In the world. This Is not the only multicultural country In the<br />
world but I think we are doing something which Is Important here, we think we<br />
are doing It as well as anyone else and maybe a little better. That we have<br />
managed to produce a society which is diverse but in many respects, well<br />
entirely cohesive as a community and this Is not an easy thing to do, but of<br />
course the Maltese have been part of that.<br />
I suppose if anything probably freshened up our relationship it was the<br />
strengthening that occurred during the Second World War when Australians<br />
helped defend Malta during three continuous years of bombing by the Axis<br />
powers and it is point not well known In Australian that the Deputy Prime<br />
Minister was just saying to me that Malta took greater bombings than the city of<br />
London and took a tremendous pounding from the Axis powers during the war<br />
and of course Australian forces were there to help In the defence of Malta and<br />
this again just added another layer onto this history we have together and the<br />
fact that we have so many things In common.<br />
Last year your Government announced the issue of a medal to mark the<br />
anniversary of the awarj of the George Cross of Malta to some 2000<br />
Australians who I think, are eligible and as far as I know about 14,000 have<br />
taken it up. This was a very nice commemoration and the acknowledgment of<br />
the role played by Australians in the defence of Malta In the Second World War<br />
and we appreciate that gesture very much Indeed.<br />
We were discussing earlier the fact that we are pursuing different paths. In<br />
terms of our geography Malta Is located in that part of the world where you are<br />
an associate member now of the European community and have appied for full<br />
membership. In the same way Australia Is part of the economic order and*<br />
linkages of the Asia-Pacific and we are trying to grow Asia-Pacific institutions<br />
here and be part of that as you are keen to Improve your own Institutional links<br />
with the European community. This offers a challenge to both of us and we<br />
have to think of novel ways In which we may participate more fully in these very<br />
large communities and you were telling me Mr President, that you are<br />
becoming now a much more service orientated socletykand, bjlI ing new </p>
<p>3<br />
industries on the service base which Malta can offer and that led us to talk<br />
about air links between Australia and Malta and the fact that we would like to<br />
see that succeed and In its succeeding just again with the transmission If you<br />
like, the transport system being more convenient than it has been will lead to<br />
not Just the natural flow of Australians of Maltese origin returning to Malta, but<br />
may open up business opportunities for Australian firms participating In the<br />
European area using the service facilities of Malta. This Is a good and sensible<br />
development. You were talking also about the vagaries of the common market, the<br />
development of Maastricht and how the European community might develop<br />
with European integration and the Integration of the Commonwealth of<br />
Independent States more fully In the European family and the challenges which<br />
the Integration of those states into Europe, the strength of that challenge for<br />
European nations to overcome and we see the problems In the post cold-War<br />
era with Iraq and with Bosnia-Herzegovlna and the problems of the old<br />
Yugoslavia already reminding us of the Intractability of European problems and<br />
European unity. We would think as a full partner of the European community or<br />
Indeed even as associate members there Is again that great common sense of<br />
Malta playing a role, having a voice in these very Important world affairs as we<br />
In Australia are having a role In the development of the Asia-Pacific area and<br />
always standing up for sense of democracy and our sense of freedom and<br />
human rights which Is an Important signature which Australia has and which we<br />
think we can bring to this part of the world as well.<br />
Beyond those economic, our economic allegiances In terms of the regions we<br />
beong, nothing has stood In the way of our friendship other than those<br />
thousands of kilometres of sea and of distance and we hope that we can shrink<br />
those again. So with Malta as with all those countries from whence the<br />
Australian people have come, there is a thred of kinship which Is bound to<br />
survive our pursuit of our different destinies in different parts of the world.<br />
Mr President, could I say we welcome you most heartedly to Australia. It Is<br />
great to see you here with your wife and Foreign Minister and we do hope that<br />
you enjoy our hospitality, not just the hospitality of the Australian community in<br />
the broad, but particularly those of Maltese origin who I know are thrilled to see<br />
you visit this country and I am sure as you travel around the country you will<br />
find that the bonds between us are very warm and very strong Indeed.<br />
Thank you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
