<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1788</transcript-id>
    <title>&quot;THIS DAY TONIGHT&quot; INTERVIEW GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR JOHN GORTON FOR A.B.C. TELEVISION.</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/02/1968</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001788.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
" THIS, DAY TONIGHT"<br />
INTERVIEW GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR<br />
JOHN GORTON FCkI'. AB. C. TELEVISION<br />
Interviewers: Mr Frank Bennett<br />
Mr Michael Vlillesee 06 F EBR UA RY 1 c,, 2<br />
Q. Would you have li ked to have made more changes in a new<br />
broom fashion if there had been more talent available In the Ministry?<br />
PM: Well I think that anybody in te position of a Prime Minister<br />
would always find that there were a considerable number of people<br />
among the private members whom one would very much like to<br />
provide with an opportunity, but one would also find that there are<br />
people already carrying out jobs and have been carrying them out for<br />
quite a long time and this creates a difficulty.<br />
Q. Mr Gorton, some commentators have suggested that you<br />
have been influenced by colleagues not to make greater changes. Is<br />
this so?<br />
FM: No, I don't think so.<br />
Q. You are quit e happy at this stage with the extent of your<br />
changes?<br />
PM: This is the C1abinet and Ministry which I think and It Is<br />
for me to think and to take the-responsibility can do the work at<br />
the present time for Australia.<br />
Q. Sir, Mr Chlpp, formerly the Navy Minister and Mr Howson<br />
formerly with the Air portfolio have both been removed from the<br />
Ministry. Can we ask you simply why?<br />
PM: Wlell, I think I can only answer that by saying that In the<br />
position where I am I have to select people, and I did want to give<br />
a couple of newcomers if I can call one of them a newcomer an<br />
opportunity, and there was no way of doing it unless a couple of places<br />
were made for that purpose.<br />
Q. Mr Gorton, wie don't particularly want to push this point<br />
but are you concerned by the suggestions that will be made, in Mr<br />
Hcvison's case, that he went over the VIP controversy, and possibly<br />
in Mr Chipp's case that he went for supporting Mr Snedden?<br />
PM: I don't know what sort of allegations would be made on these<br />
matters. All I can say is I exercised a judgment which may be wrong<br />
but which was a judgment which was necessary. WRell, it was a judgment<br />
which I only could make in the way in which our party Is set up at the<br />
present moment. s. / 2 </p>
<p>Q. Can you amplify, LSir, the kind of portfolio that you see<br />
that you have given to Mr Wlentworth Social Services and Aboriginal<br />
Affairs?<br />
PM: I don' t want you to think that those are lumped together<br />
he has got both those portfolios, that he has received Minister -In-Charge<br />
of Aboriginal Affairs because somehow it goes with Social Services.<br />
This was not the concept at all. I think It Is well known that he has had<br />
a great and continuing interest not only in aboriginal welfare but In<br />
aboriginal history. He has really made a study of this matter. This<br />
will not be a Department of State. It will be something that he<br />
administers In the same way that I administered Education once under<br />
the Prime Minister. In Social Services, I am hoping that he will<br />
bring to bear the talent that he has got for analysing and investigating<br />
and proposing new steps. This Is something in which he might be of<br />
considerable value. An Ideas man.<br />
Q. Despite Mr WItentvworth's talent that you refer to, he has been<br />
overlooked for about 18 or 19 years now. Why is It that he has been<br />
in the back benches for so long and now you have put him In the<br />
M./ inistry?<br />
PM: I think the answer to that is something like the one I gave<br />
you before that each Individual man who preceded me has exercised<br />
his judgment in selecting those he wishes to work with him, and I have<br />
done the same, and It has happened this time to come out differently.<br />
Q. It would seem to go beyond the competence of Mr Wentworth<br />
here. A lot of people would think that neither Sir Robert nor Mr Holt<br />
trusted him. He sounds brilliant but sometimes he sounds erratic<br />
in the House. Are you concerned about that?<br />
PM: No, I'm not. Not In the least. He Is quite brilliant. All<br />
of his Ideas of course, as Is the case with almost any brilliant man,<br />
are not necessarily acceptable, and over the years he has put up a<br />
number of ideas. But some of them have been extremely acceptable,<br />
I think, for example, the unification of rail gauges in Australia owes a<br />
great deal to this kind of approach.<br />
Q. Mr Prime Minister, Senator Wright comes Into your Ministry<br />
with Vorks and Tourism. Hero is a man who has In your mind no<br />
doubt an unfortunate record of voting against the Government. How<br />
did you justify his position under these circumstances?<br />
PM: I felt that we needed In the front benches of the Senate<br />
somebody with good legal knowledge, because a great deal of the<br />
discussion that takes place in the Senate not all by any means but<br />
a great deal Is centred around Committee discussions on Bills and<br />
legal implications, far more than happens In the House of Representativeo<br />
where it tends more to be on broad principles. I felt we needed<br />
somebody with a legal capacity and, if I may put it this way with an<br />
argumentative capacity, somebody with a force of argument, and I felt<br />
that he would be able to fulfil that role. o. / 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
Q. At the moment, you are a bit light on with QC's In the<br />
Senate then?<br />
PM: I think we had one other lawyer, '-enator Laught, but I think<br />
he Is not a QC. As a matter of fact, Senator Wlright Isn't a QC either,<br />
is he? I don't think he is.<br />
Q. Could we ask on Senator Wright if you have come to some<br />
agreement with him about ' his rather wayward voting habits?<br />
PM: Oh, I am absolutely sure that Senator Wright fully realises<br />
that when one becomes a member of a governmental team, one is a<br />
member of the team and one supports the team, and that is a completely<br />
different situation from being a private member, particularly a private<br />
member in the Senate where t1Icels an idea that a thing should be looked<br />
at a bit more closely by private members.<br />
Q But despite this, you have left the Deputy Leadership of the<br />
Senate open, when on capability Senator Wright would appear to be the<br />
man to fill the job?<br />
PM: Before I indicated agreement with that, we want to see how the<br />
Soenate works for some considerable time.<br />
Q. Mr Gorton, Mr Barnes Is now Minister for External Territories<br />
only. Why this distinction?<br />
PM: Because I feel that the problems In the Northern Territory are<br />
different in kind from the problems in Papua-New Guinea, and I feel that<br />
whereas the end result Mr H-asluck plit it that the end which the<br />
Northern Territory must attain Is that~/ being eventually a State of the<br />
Commonwealth of Australia, an integral part of the Commonwealth of<br />
Australia. How far ahead that is, I don't know. But that clearly, Is what<br />
the destiny of the Northern Territory Is. Now it is not at all so clear<br />
that that is what is going to happen in the case of Papua-New Guinea.<br />
Rather, I would see it developing towards a form of self-government,<br />
and then perhaps after that, from the basis of a form of self-government,<br />
whenever that occurs, if It wants a special association of some kind with<br />
A., ustralia, approaching the then Australian Government.<br />
Q. Mr Gorton, you have appointed Mr Lynch to the Army portfolio<br />
at a very young age at a time when our Army Is fighting a war. Do you<br />
have fears about this appointment?<br />
PM: I don't think so. He's 34 or 35 and there Is -usually quite a lot<br />
of energy and drive at this age. I feel he bas had considerable managerial<br />
experience, personnel management experience, business experience,<br />
all of which should be helpful in the administration of a Department.<br />
Cf course, neither he nor any other Minister would affect the fighting<br />
of the Department because that Is a military matter which is done by the<br />
Chief of the Service. * 0a00a/ 4 </p>
<p>9 -4-<br />
Q. Finally, Mr Prime Minister, what can you tell us about the<br />
rumours that indicate a possible change at the Head of your own<br />
Prime Minister's Department?<br />
PM: Merely, that there has been, I think fairly clearly, too big a<br />
load for one man to carry, in seeking to do all the Cabinet Secretariat<br />
work snd be Head of the Prime Minister's Department at the same time.<br />
This has been recognised for some time but we are now carrying out<br />
fairly active sort of investigations as to just how this problem can be<br />
over come.<br />
Q. There Is nothing concrete at this stage?<br />
PM:. Not now, no.<br />
Thank you Prime Minister. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
