<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6750</transcript-id>
    <title>Working Party on Affirmative Action Legislation</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/09/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006750.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p> 30 September 1985</p>
<p>I am pleased to announce that the Government has accepted<br />the recommendations of the Working Party on Affirmative Action<br />Legislation. A~ s a result, the Government will legislate in<br />the autumn session of Parliament in ! 986 for affirmative action<br />for women in higher education institutions and in private<br />sector organisations employing more than 100 people.<br />Senator Ryan, who assists me on issues concerning the status<br />of women, and who convened the Working Party, conveyed the<br />recommendations to the Government today.<br />I am pleased that the Working Party was able to agree on a<br />recommended approach to this important issue. Although some<br />of its members expressed reservations, which will be published<br />in the Working Party's report, all members were prepared to<br />endorse the approach, given the Government's commitment to<br />legislation. The opposition did not agree with the need for<br />legislation but it has supported other aspects of the package.<br />The legislation will be proclaimed in stages. Higher education<br />institutions will be required to comnply from 1987. Private<br />sector compliance will begin early in 1988.<br />The Government welcomes the proposal by business to establish a<br />Council for Equal Employment Opportunity to encourage companies<br />to begin immediately to introduce affirmative action. The<br />Working Party noted this proposal, which is compatible with our<br />approach. The Government will explore ways of co-operating<br />with the Business Council in its efforts to encourage greater<br />awareness within the private sector of the need to improve job<br />opportunities for women.<br />Further information may be obtained from Senator Ryan.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
