<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3345</transcript-id>
    <title>LAND TENURE</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/08/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003345.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
JjjUS; ALIAy<br />
PRIME MINISTER PRESS STATEMENT NO. 296<br />
6 August 1974<br />
LAND TENURE<br />
Cabinet this week supported a recommendation in the first<br />
report of the Commission of Inquiry into Land Tenures uing that<br />
any future capital profits arising from a change of land use<br />
be retained by public authorities rather than by individuals.<br />
The recommendation endorsed by Cabinet was made in the<br />
report of the Commission under Mr. Justice Else-Mitchell tabled<br />
in Parliament on 4 December last year.<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr. Whitlam, said the Australian<br />
Government shared the Commission ' s concern at the economic<br />
and social consequences of the fact that capital profits<br />
being made by individuals on changed land use were reflected<br />
in the price of service land coming on to the market for the<br />
first time.<br />
Cabinet decided to urge the States to consider co-operation<br />
with the Government's new approach on the question of changed<br />
land use.<br />
Mr. Whitlam said Cabinet also expressed regret that the<br />
States so far had been unwilling to help the Commission in<br />
its deliberations. The Australian Government considered there was no warrant<br />
for substantial private profit-taking as a result of unearned<br />
increases in land values occurring through community decisions.<br />
Mr. Whitlam said that the new measures reflected initiatives<br />
taken by the Minister for Urban and Regional Development, Mr.<br />
Tom Uren, to reduce land speculation.<br />
Mr. Whitlam said the Government would continue to study<br />
the feasibility of the system of reservation of development<br />
rights which the Commission in its first report had proposed. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
The Government would discuss the results of its study<br />
with State Governments which would have to pass complementary<br />
legislation if such a scheme were to be introduced.<br />
Considering the Commission's report, Cabinet also agreed<br />
with the recommendation that land for private urban business<br />
use in growth areas and in Government territories should be<br />
available only on some form of leasehold.<br />
The Australian Government and the Governments of New<br />
South Wales and Victoria had already agreed with this principle<br />
in the growth area of Albury/ Wodonga.<br />
Mr. Whitlam said the Australian Government would press<br />
for the implementation of this principle in growth centres<br />
and in all areas acquired under the Land Commission's program.<br />
Cabinet decided that while statutory corporations were<br />
an appropriate body for major urban development and redevelopment<br />
projects, it did not accept the need for corporations to have<br />
a continuing role in the case of existing stabilised urban areas.<br />
CANBERRA, A, C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
