<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2900</transcript-id>
    <title>AUSTRALIA GIVES FOKKER AIRCRAFT TO BANGLADESH</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/04/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002900.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
NQ DATE<br />
27 April 1973<br />
AUSTRALIA GIVES FOKKER AIRCRAFT TO BANGjADESH<br />
The Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs, Senator Willesee,<br />
announced today that Australia had given two Fokker Friendship<br />
F27 Series 200 passenger aircraft to Bangladesh for use by the<br />
Bangladesh national airline, Bangladesh Biman.<br />
Senator Willesee said that the total cost of the<br />
aircraft, together with spare parts, was $ 950,000.<br />
The first aircraft was handed over by the Australian<br />
Ambassador to the Netherlands, Dr Lloyd Thomson, to representatives<br />
of the Government of Bangladesh at Schipol Airport, The Netherlands,<br />
on Wednesday, and the second aircraft is due to be handed over today.<br />
Senator Willesee said that Australian aid to Bangladesh<br />
* was directed to assist the rebuilding of the country's shattered<br />
economy. A major problem was the re-establishment of an internal<br />
transport system, and the two Fokkers would greatly assist in this.<br />
Senator Willesee said that the staff of Bangladesh Biman<br />
was well experienced in the operation of Fokker Friendship aircraft<br />
and had been operating this type on its internal routes.<br />
The Australian gift would enable the airline to extend its<br />
services to more parts, such as Cox's Bazaar, Thakurgaon<br />
Shamsernagar and Rajshahi.<br />
Bangladesh Biman have named one of the aircraft " City<br />
of Canberra". </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
