<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3772</transcript-id>
    <title>QUEENSLAND BROADCAST NO 12 - ACHIEVEMENTS - SUNDAY 8 JUNE 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/06/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Broadcast</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003772.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
QUEENSLAND BROADCAST NO. 12<br />
ACHIEVEMENTS<br />
SUNDAY 8 JUNE 1975<br />
THIS WEEK WE CONCLUDED A BUSY AND PRODUCTIVE<br />
SESSION OF THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES, WE'VE SAT<br />
FOR 432 HOURS SO FAR THIS YEAR THAT'S JUST THREE<br />
TIMES THE SITTING HOURS OF THE QUEENSLAND LEGISLATIVE<br />
ASSEMBLY THIS YEAR. So I THOUGHT TONIGHT I'D TELL YOU<br />
SOMETHING OF WHAT WE ACHIEVED IN THAT PERIOD. YOU<br />
HEAR AND READ SO MUCH IN THE MEDIA_. f4E. SE DAYS ABOUT..<br />
CRISES AND SPLITS '. ANDI PROBLEMS-IN CANBERRA -MOST<br />
C. I<br />
OF IT PRETTY FANCIFUL-AND HIGHLY COLOURED STUFF<br />
THAT IT'S EASY TO LOSE SIGHT OF THE SURE, STEADY<br />
PROGRESS YCUR GO'VERN! MENT IS MAKING TOWARDS A BETTER<br />
AND FAIRER AUSTRALIA. FOR ALL THE DISTRACTIONS AND.<br />
DiVERSIONS WE HAVE FACED IN PARLIAMENT AND OUTSIDE,<br />
FOR ALL THE PROPAGANDA OF OUR OPPONENTS FOR ALL<br />
THE OBSTRUCTION OF THE STATE GOVERNMENTS, AND<br />
VESTED INTERESTS, FOR ALL THE DENIGRATION OF THE PRESS,<br />
THIS HAS BEEN A PERIOD OF GREAT AND POSITIVE ACHIEVEMENT<br />
BY THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT. I ASK YOU TO KEEP THOSE<br />
ACHIEVEMENTS IN MIND, TO KEEP THE RECORD IN PERSPECTIVE,<br />
-TO REFLECT ON THE BASIC STRENGTH AND PROSPERITY OF<br />
THE NATION, THE UNDERLYING STRENGTH OF THE ECONOMY,<br />
THE REAL GAINS WE ARE MAKING IN SOCIAL REFORM AND<br />
SOCIAL JUSTICE AND IN THE LIVING STANDARDS OF THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE. ./ 2<br />
S I Itr </p>
<p>-2-<br />
WE BEGAN THE YEAR IN THE AFTERMATH OF THE<br />
DARWIN CYCLONE THE GREATEST NATURAL DISASTER<br />
AUSTRALIA HAS KNOWN, IT WAS FOLLOWED BY A SECOND<br />
CALAMITY IN HOBART INVOLVING APPALLING SOCIAL<br />
DISRUPTION AND LOSS OF LIFE. THE GOVERNMENT'S<br />
RESPONSE TO THESE CALAMITIES WAS PROMPT AND<br />
-GENEROUS. IN PARLIAMENT ON THURSDAY I PAID<br />
TRIBUTE TO THE NATURAL DISASTERS ORGANISATION<br />
FOR ITS HANDLING OF THE DARWIN CRISIS, AND TO THE<br />
DARWIN PEOPLE THEMSELVES FOR THEIR FORTITUDE AND<br />
UNDAUNTED SPIRIT, YOU WILL REMEMBER THAT THE<br />
GOVERNMENT IMMEDIATELY ESTABLISHED A DARWIN<br />
RECONSTRUCTION COMMISSION AND ENTRUSTED IT WITH<br />
THE MASSIVE TASK OF REBUILDING THE CITY. WE AGREED<br />
TO ESTABLISH A JOINT TASMAN BRIDGE RESTORATION<br />
COMMISSION, WE HAVE COMMITTED MORE THAN $ 58 MILLION<br />
TO THE DARWIN RECONSTRUCTION PROGRAM AND AN INITIAL<br />
GRANT OF $ 6 MILLION FOR HOBART. </p>
<p>-3-<br />
IDON'T NEED TO TELL YOU THAT IN TIMES OF<br />
ECONOMIC DIFFICULTY, DISASTERS OF THIS KIND PLACE<br />
UNPRECEDENTED DEMANDS ON THE NATION'S MATERIAL<br />
AND FINANCIAL RESOURCES. As IN ALL OTHER<br />
COMPARABLE COUNTRIES, OUR ECONOMIC PROBLEMS ARE<br />
STILL WITH US, STILL IWE CAN TAKE HEART FROM THE<br />
SIGNS OF IMPROVEMENT ALREADY APPARENT IN THE<br />
ECONOMY.-OF COURSE IT.' S NO TIME FOR COMPLACENCY;<br />
THERE IS STILL A NEED FOR STEADY JUDGMENT AND A<br />
CALM, RATIONAL-APPROACH TO OUR DIFFICULTIES.<br />
BUT THERE IS GOOD REASON TO BELIEVE THAT ECONOMIC<br />
RECOVERY IS UNDERWAY. CONSUMER CONFIDENCE,<br />
REFLECTED IN RISING RETAIL SALES AND HIGHER<br />
DISPOSABLE INCOMES, HAS SHOWN SIGNIFICANT GAINS.<br />
PRIVATE INVESTMENT IN THE BASIC AREAS OF THE<br />
ECONOMY* IS RISING, UNEMPLOYMENT. CONTINUES TO FALL.<br />
THE IMPORTANT THING TO REMEMBER IS THAT THE<br />
GOVERNMENT'S POLICIES HAVE P UT MO NEY IN THE POCKETS<br />
OF AUSTRALIAZ&amp; ORDINARY PEOPLE ARE MORE PROSPEROUS<br />
TODAY THAN THEY HAVE EVER BEEN. WHENEVER YOU HEAR<br />
CRITICISM OF THE GOVERNMENT' S POLICIES REMEMBER<br />
THIS: THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE HAVE NEVER BEEN<br />
BETTER OFF -BETTER OFF IN THE MONEY THEY HAVE TO<br />
SPEND, BETTER OFF IN THEIR REAL INCOMES, BETTER OFF<br />
IN THE RANGE OF SERVICES AND OPPORTUNITIES AVAILABLE<br />
TO THEM FROM THIS GOVERNMENT'S PROGRAMS. SINCE<br />
DECEMBER 1972 INCOMES OF WAGE AND SALARY EARNERS<br />
HAVE GORWN MUCH FASTER THAN THE COST OF LIVING, / 14 </p>
<p>-14-<br />
AVERAGE MINIMUM WEEKLY AWARD RATES FOR MEN HAV/ E<br />
INCREASED BY' 53 PERCENT; FOR WOMEN BY NO L ESS<br />
THAN 75 PERCENT. REAL AVERAGE W4EEKLY EARNINGS<br />
AFTER TAX FOR ALL WAGE AND SALARY EARNERS HAVE<br />
INCREASED By 7.3 PERCENT SINCE THIS GOVERNMENT<br />
CAME TO OFFICE*. IN ADDITIO'N*, WE HAVE TACKLED<br />
THE GREAT AND DIFFICULT PROBLEM OF WAGE<br />
INDEXATION. IN ITS HISTORIC JUDGMENT FIVE WEEKS<br />
AGO THE CONCILIATION AND ARBITRATION COMMISSION<br />
ACCEPTED THE GOVERNMENT'S CASE FOR A RESTORATION<br />
OF QUARTERLY COST OF LIVING ADJUSTMENTS. WITH<br />
REASON AND GOODWILL WE CAN MADE INDEXATION<br />
WORK WORK TO SAFEGUARD REAL INCOMES, WORK TO<br />
CURB INFLATION. WE HAVE SEEN THIS YEAR A NUMBER OF SIGNIFICANT<br />
GOVERNMENT PROGRAMS BROUGHT TO FRUITION. WE HAVE<br />
SEEN THE CREATION OF MEDIBANK, A GREAT PIONEERING<br />
REFORM WHICH THE RELUCTANT STATES HAVE BEEN DRIVEN<br />
TO ACCEPT, BECAUSE THEY KNOW THEY WILL BENEFIT FROM<br />
IT, AND ABOVE ALL THAT THE PEOPLE WILL BENEFIT.<br />
WHAT A LESSON OUR OPPONENTS HAVE LEARNED FROM<br />
MEDIBANK AFTER ALL THE OBSTRUCTION IN THE PARLIAMENT.*<br />
AFTER ALL THE ATTEMPTS TO DELAY THE MEDIBANK BILLS.-<br />
THE ANTI-LABOR STATES ARE NOW SEE'KING TO JOIN THE<br />
SCHEME, AND IF THEIR ADVERTISEMENTS CAN BE<br />
BELIEVED, EVEN TAKING SOME OF THE CREDIT FOR IT. o </p>
<p>ONE OF THE THEMES OF ALL OUR REFORMS HAS<br />
BEEN TO ASSERT THE PRINCIPLE OF COMPETITIONFREE<br />
AND FAIR COMPETITION IN A MIXED ECONOMY,<br />
PRODUCTIVE COMPETITION BETWEEN PRIVATE AND<br />
PUBLIC ENTERPRISE. I WE HAVE SEEN THE BENEFITS<br />
OF SUCH COMPETITION IN THE AIRLINES AND THE<br />
BANKS, WE SHALL EXTEND IT TO OTHER FIELDS.<br />
WE HAVE PASSED LEGISLATION IN THE HOU SE OF<br />
REPRESENTATIVES TO ESTABLISH AN AUSTRALIAN<br />
GOVERNMENT INSURANCE CORPORATION. IT WILL PROVIDE<br />
THE WIDEST POSSIBLE COVER FOR HOMES AT THE LOWEST<br />
POSSIBLE PREMIUMS AND OFFER A WIDE RANGE OF<br />
INSURANCE SERVICES. WE HAVE DEVELOPED AND EXTENDED OUR<br />
LEGAL AID SERVICE AND THIS WEEK WE INTRODUCED<br />
LEGISLATION TO ESTABLISH THE SERVICE IN PERMANENT<br />
FORM, SIX REGIONAL OFFICES OF TH E AUSTRALIAN LEGAL<br />
AID OFFICE HAVE BEEN OPENED THIS YEAR AND MORE THAN<br />
60,000 PEOPLE HAVE BEEN HELPED. WE HAVE SET UP<br />
AN AUSTRALIAN HOUSING CORPORATION TO TAKE ACTION<br />
IN AREAS WHERE THE EXISTING HOUSING SYSTEM IS UNABLE<br />
TO MEET EXISTING HOUSING NEEDS; ALREADY THIS YEAR WE<br />
HAVE FUNDED THE CONSTRUCTION BY STATE HOUSING<br />
AUTHORITIES OF 13,580 HOMES FOR LOW-INCOME EARNERS<br />
5,000 MORE THAN WERE BUILT LAST FINANCIAL YEAR. THEN<br />
AGAIN/ WE ' yVE PASSED LEGISLATION IT WENT THROUGH<br />
PARLIAMENT ON WEDNESDAY, BUT I DOUBT IF IT GOT<br />
MUCH PROMINENCE IN THE MEDIA -WE'IVE PASSED LEGISLATION<br />
TO ESTABLISH A CHILDREN'S COMMISSION, A BODY TO<br />
ADMINISTER A WHOLE RANGE OF SPECIAL SERVICES FOR CHILDREN,<br />
INCLUDING PRE-SCHOOLDAY CARE AND HOLIDAY SERVICES. </p>
<p>SOME 165,000 CHILDREN HAVE ALREADY BEEN CATERED FOR UNDER<br />
THIS PROGRAM. So THESE AREN'T JUST PIPEDREAMS<br />
THEY ARE LIVING, WORKING PROJECTS, ALREADY<br />
HELPING AUSTRALIANS AND THEIR FAMILIES,<br />
ANOTHER AREA OF OUTSTANDING PROGRESS THIS<br />
YEAR HAS BEEN RAILWAYS, MORE THAN ANY OF ITS<br />
PREDECESSORS, MY GOVERNMENT HAS RECOGNISED<br />
THE NEED FOR A NATIONAL APPROACH TO RAILWAYS. WE<br />
ARE BUILDING THE NEW LINES NEEDED TO LINK EVERY<br />
MAINLAND CAPITAL, AS WELL AS ALICE SPRINGS, TO THE<br />
STANDARD GAUGE, WE HAVE REACHED AGREEMENT WITH<br />
SOUTH AUSTRALIA AND TASMANIA TO TAKE OVER<br />
RESPONSIBILITY FOR THEIR RAILWAYS, WE HAVE CREATED<br />
THEAUSTRALIAN NATIONAL RAILWAYS TO BRING THESE<br />
TRANSFERRED STATE RAILWAYS AND THE OLD<br />
COMMONWEALTH RAILWAYS TOGETHER INTO A SINGLE SYSTEM,<br />
EQUIPPED WITH THE VERY LATEST ROLLING STOCK, AND<br />
TO HELP THE STATES IMPROVE THEIR OWN RAILWAYS, WE<br />
ARE LEASIN6 TO THEM BRAND-NEW WAGONS AND OTHER<br />
VEHICLES. ALL THIS WILL HELP DEVELOP A TRULY MODERN,<br />
EFFICIENT, NATIONAL RAIL SYSTEM. ,1,/ 7 </p>
<p>-7-<br />
THE OPPOSITION LIKE TO TELL YOU THAT THEY ARE<br />
BEHAVING MORE RESPONSIBLY THESE DAYS THAN WHEN<br />
MR SNEDDEN WAS THEIR LEADER., CERTAINLY THEY<br />
HAVE BEEN LESS ROWDY AND DISORDERLY IN THE<br />
CHAMBER, BUT BEHIND THEIR FACADE OF RESPONSIBILITY THE<br />
OLD CAMAPIGN OF OBSTRUCTION HAS CONTINUED,<br />
LISTEN TO ALL THE THINGS THEY'VE CONTINUED TO BLOCK<br />
IN THE SENATE OUR BILL TO MODERNISE AND SIMPLIFY<br />
THE ELECTORAL LAWS, OUR BILLS TO ABOLISH APPEALS<br />
TO THE PRIVY COUNCIL, TO ESTABLISH A SUPERIOR<br />
COURT OF AUSTRALIA, TO DEAL WITH LURKS AND<br />
MALPRACTICE IN THE SECURITIES INDUSTRY, TO ESTABLISH<br />
A GOVERNMENT PURCHASING COMMISSION, TO PROVIDE<br />
SIMULTANEOUS ELECTIONS FOR THE SENATE AND<br />
HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES, AND OF COURSE, THE<br />
CAMPAIGN OF OBSTRUCTION HAS BEEN PURSUED BEYOND<br />
THIS PARLIAMENT, IN THE COURTS AND IN THE STATES, </p>
<p>-8-<br />
I LEAVE YOU TO JUDGE THE OPPOSITION TACTICS<br />
FOR YOURSELVES. THEY WON'T DETER US FROM OUR<br />
GOALS, THE PAST SIX MONTHS HAVE SHOWN WHAT A<br />
DETERMINED GOVERNMENT CAN ACHIEVE IN THE FACE<br />
OF CONTINUING OBSTRUCTION, THIS WEEK, WITH THE<br />
CHANGES I HAVE MADE IN OUR MINISTERIAL TEAM, I<br />
BELIEVE WE HAVE AN EVEN STRONGER GOVERNMENT<br />
A GOVERNMENT THAT WILL GET ON WITH THE JOB THE<br />
PEOPLE ELECTED US TO DO, DESPITE OUR DIFFICULTIES<br />
IN THE SENATE, DESPITE THE ECONOMIC PROBLEMS WITH<br />
WHICH EVERY NATION HAS TO CONTEND, WE HAVE<br />
BROUGHT NEW AND PERMANENT REFORMS TO THE<br />
STATUTE BOOKS; WE HAVE ENHANCED AUSTRALIA'S<br />
STANDING IN THE WORLD,; WE HAVE PRODUCED A<br />
SOCIETY WHICH HAS NEVER ENJOYED GREAT INDIVIDUAL<br />
PROSPERITY, GREATER OPPORTUNITIES, GREATER<br />
PROSPECTS FOR THE FUTURE. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
