<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7614</transcript-id>
    <title>AIR TRAFFIC CONTROLLERS JOINT STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE MINISTER FOR TRANSPORT AND COMMUNICATIONS AND THE MINISTER FOR INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/05/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007614.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR MEDIA 25 MAY 1989<br />
-AIR TRAFFIC CONTROLLERS<br />
JOINT STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER,<br />
THE MINISTER FOR TRANSPORT AND COMMUNICATIONS<br />
AND THE MINISTER FOR INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS<br />
The Government will no longer tolerate the continuing<br />
campaign of industrial disruption and abuse of sick leave<br />
entitlements by Air Traffic Controllers at Sydney Airport<br />
and other airports.<br />
If this disruption continues the Civil Aviation Authority<br />
( CAA) will immediately process the provisions already in the<br />
award which allow for individual fines and/ or stand-downs.<br />
Further, to ensure our capacity finally to resolve this<br />
unacceptable behaviour we have commissioned Mr George<br />
Polites, Mr Peter Newman and Mr Bernie Frawley* to provide<br />
us with an immediate report on other action available to the<br />
Government to put an end to the disruption at these<br />
airports. Following receipt of the report, the Government will, in<br />
consultation with the Civil Aviation Authority ( CAA), take<br />
whatever steps are necessary to give the travelling public<br />
the best service Sydney Airport is capable of providing.<br />
The Government's decision follows a series of attempts to<br />
end the disruption co-operatively. These include:<br />
agreement to process the Air Traffic Controllers' award<br />
restructuring as a special case, providing early access<br />
to wage increases;<br />
agreement to provide, earlier than planned, equipment to<br />
overhaul the Sydney and Melbourne air traffic control<br />
system; acceptance in principle of the need for increased<br />
staffing, a position which will be firmed up once a<br />
report is received from the CAA on specific needs,, due<br />
shortly. </p>
<p>The Government and the CAA have attempted to negotiate with<br />
the Air Traffic Controllers and their union in good faith<br />
and with considerable patience. It appears that some<br />
controllers are not prepared to follow their union's advice<br />
nor do they appear to care about the welfare of<br />
passengers, or the economic health of tourism or the<br />
aviation industry in this country.<br />
Let there be no mistake the disruption at Sydney Airport<br />
is caused principally by the attempts of a group of<br />
self-interested individuals seeking to use their position in<br />
the industry to obtain very large wage rises outside<br />
industrial relations guidelines and the wage-setting<br />
principles which have been agreed with the ACTU.<br />
Mr George Polites is former Executive Director of the<br />
Confederation of Australian Industry and is currently a<br />
member of the Board of Australian Airlines; Mr Peter<br />
Newman is Consultant to the Minister for Transport and<br />
Communications; Mr Bernie Frawley is a First Assistant<br />
Secretary in the Department of Industrial Relations. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
