<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1336</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S VISIT TO US AND UK - PRESS CONFERENCE GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR HAROLD HOLT ON ARRIVAL AT SAN FRANCISCO AIRPORT - 28TH JUNE 1966</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/06/1966</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001336.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER'S VISIT TO U. S. AND U. K.<br />
on arrival at San Francisco Airport. 28th June, 1966-.<br />
MR. HOLT: 1 el1, gentlemen, perhaps you will indicate to me first<br />
what you have in mind as an operation you want to hear<br />
something 0<br />
Q. Anything you would like to say first?<br />
AMR. HOLT: WVell I don't have any major policy statement. If you like,<br />
I could say why I am here and what I intend to do and matters of<br />
that sort. I am, of course, a fairly frequent visitor to the<br />
United States. This is my seventeenth consecutive yearc of<br />
government on the liberal side and so over those years I have been<br />
a very frequent visitor to you. As Minister for Finance, for<br />
example, I have been coming to Washington most Septembersfor the<br />
meetings of the International Bank and Monetary Fund. But this is<br />
the first visit I make as the Head of the Australian Government,<br />
having succeeded Sir Robert IMenzies in that position in January<br />
of this year. It's been a very crowded year including a visit to<br />
South Viet Nam and other South East Asian countries and I think<br />
that aspect provides some interest in the talks that I'll be<br />
having with the President and with the Prime Minister of the United<br />
Kingdom. I think I'm the only non-Asian Head of Government to have<br />
visited South Viet Nam since the hostilities began and I have soine<br />
impressions and I'm sure I'll be very in-1erested to hear what their<br />
views are on events there also. You will probably be aware that<br />
I've been meeting several of the leading figures from the area<br />
in recent days because yesterday morning I formally opened the<br />
Conference in Canberra and in the weekend leading up<br />
to that Opening, I've been talking to the Foreign Ministers as<br />
they've arrived The Prime Minister of New Zealand, Mr. Holyoake,<br />
the Secretary of State, Dean Rusk, and Mrii. Michael Stewart, the<br />
foreign Secretary of the United Kingdom, and of course others from<br />
the Asian or South . hast Asian area who are represented at the<br />
S. E. A. T. O. Conference. We feel that SEATO got away to a very good<br />
start. This has been a good year from the point of view of SEATO.<br />
I think there have been some very hopeful developments emerging<br />
through the year and I Shall be discussing those and in particular<br />
the view as we see it from down under. But this will be done in<br />
mofe detail in the speeches I shall be making to the National Press<br />
Club in V'I'ashington on Thursday and to a meeting of the Arderican-<br />
Australian Association and in other places where I shall be<br />
speaking. Principally, I've come on this particular journey which<br />
won't last much more than a fortnight, in order to have dire. Ct<br />
contact with the President and with the Prime Minister of the United<br />
Kingdom. They've both been kind enough to invite me to have these<br />
talks with them and indeed from the time I took office each of them<br />
invited me to maintain with them the intimate consultation which<br />
they had been in the practice of co iducting with Sir Robert Menzies<br />
while he was Prime Minister, and these communications ha ve proceeded.<br />
between us. </p>
<p>MR. HOLT: ( Cont'd)<br />
But of course there is no effective substitute for the personal<br />
contacts which can come between man and man and I gather that<br />
your President in particular is a National Leader who likes,<br />
to be able to size up the people wzith whom he is dealing. W ell<br />
in the words of that charming song from " The King A nd P"<br />
'" Getting to Know You, Uetting to Know All About You':' This<br />
is what I hope we shall be doing together. I shall only have a<br />
couple of days in W ashington but arrangements have been made for<br />
me to see Mr. McNamara, Mir. George Ball, Mr. Averell Harriman.<br />
I'll be meeting old friends again in 1Mr. Connor and DMr. Fowler.<br />
I used to see both of those in my earlier capacity as Finance<br />
Minister and then I shall move on to New York where I have some<br />
engagements as well some talks with M1r. David Rockefeller,<br />
thc. talk to the American-Australian Association, Mayor Lindsay<br />
is giving a dinner for me I understand in New York, and so it<br />
will be quite a crowded programme before I go on th~ en to London.<br />
And much the same order of compression, concentration will obtain<br />
in London. I shall be passing back across the west coast homeward<br />
bound to Australia in about a fortnight's time.<br />
We have, of course, very many things in common. My own<br />
talks on this occasion while Australia doesn't lack general<br />
interest in what is going on around the rest of the world, my<br />
own talks on this occasion will be concentrated on the area east<br />
of Suez and in particular South East Asia and notably of course<br />
Viet Nam, Indonesia, and the most recent developments in relation<br />
to that. But I came looking hopefully to the period ahead. I<br />
think that evu: nts are going much more hopefully for us in Viet Nam.<br />
I think that over recent years there have been remarkable advances<br />
in the other countries of South East Asia which have been able to<br />
progress and bui~ d their defences under the shield of SEATO and<br />
under the general protection which the United States in particular<br />
has maintained in that area of the -xorld. Indeed I think,<br />
gentlemen, you~ would be doing a service to your own country as well<br />
as to those who read about these things elsewhere if the positive<br />
side of what we are actually achieving in that area of the world<br />
couild be more prominently displayed. There are grim episodes, of<br />
course, and these are reported regularly, but the more positive<br />
constrUCtiva. achievements, less spectacular perhaps and spread<br />
over a much longer period of time, don't seem to get the same<br />
attention. But out of it all is building a stronger and more<br />
secure, more stable area capabl6 of resisting aggression and<br />
capable also of going on with the more positive and constructive<br />
economic, social and pollt* , changes necessary in ordei: to<br />
produce the better world! in sia that is the aspiration of all<br />
the countries in the SEATO Organisation.<br />
Perhaps having said that you might like to put a question<br />
or two to me.<br />
Q. I'll start the ball rolling, Mr. Prime Minister. With<br />
further weakening of Britain's position with the dragging out<br />
of the shipping strike, is she not likely sooner rather than<br />
later to have to reduce her commitments east of Suez. Will you<br />
discuss this and the possibility of new U. S. bases? </p>
<p>MR. HOLT: .,-; hile I'm not able to say with any authority what the<br />
economic effects to Britain will be from this shipping strike<br />
and of course it depends of the length of the strike to some<br />
degree, but the British people are a resilient and strong people#<br />
Icion't regard the shipping strike as a fact which would<br />
materially affect future British policy. I think what is likely<br />
to affect British policy is much more importantly in the minds<br />
of the British Government and its lawmakers on the question of<br />
armed forces east of Suez. Mr. Wilson has been quite specific<br />
on this. As to the future of British forces following some<br />
abatement of confrontation requirements is a mattei, which is<br />
less certain in our minds and this is a matter on whi. cihe may<br />
be able to illuminate my own awareness rather more usefully than<br />
is the situation at the moment.<br />
Q. Mr. Prime Minister, you mentioned you were going to give<br />
the down under views on Viet Nam to President Johnson. Could<br />
you be a little more specific?<br />
MV HOLT: I don't think I should be conducting my conversation with<br />
President Johnson in Public before I've met him. I don't think<br />
he'd appreciate that. It might be more appropriate if I were<br />
to have sol-ae discussion on that afterwards and I will be seeing<br />
the Press Club the following day so to the extent that I feel<br />
I can talk I shall. But I would like to be able to bring to<br />
him, this hopeful picture and brighter picture of the area as seen<br />
by those of us who live in it. And I would certainly be<br />
wishing to convey to him the appreciation of the Australian<br />
people for the greater security that we have felt, the ability<br />
to get on with our own job of developing a vast continent<br />
approximately the size of the United States of Amaerica<br />
well if you leave Alaska out of it, but if you do that then the<br />
territorial dimension of the United States is roughly comparable<br />
with that of Australia. But you've got somiething over 29) 0<br />
million people I think, haven't you almost or you're<br />
getting along that way, and we have less than 12 so that we have<br />
great problems of development and at the sane time we are<br />
trying to make an increasing contribution to defence in the area.<br />
Will Australia contribute more troops to Viet Nan?<br />
R. HOLT: There is no present intention nor on the statements which<br />
Dean Rusk has made since he arrived in Australia is it implied<br />
that that would be necessary. It was known at the time when ' we<br />
increased our last contribution, ( we trebled the military force<br />
there to a task force) and this over a period in which we were<br />
trying to use regular troops at home for the training of<br />
National Servicemen and others, this with our commitments in<br />
Borneo, with a need to give some protection to Papua and New<br />
Guinea and matters of that sort, and with another restless,<br />
turbulent neighbour to our north, this was the contribution<br />
which they felt or at least we suggested this contribution,<br />
and it was welcomed it was not suggested that it was in any<br />
way inadequate.<br />
Q. vgill your Government make any changes in the policy toward<br />
Viet Nan as compared to that of Mr. Menzies? </p>
<p>24.<br />
HOLT: No, we aLre resolutely behind the support for the United<br />
States and the people of South Viet Na~ m and this policy of course<br />
developed in the period that Sir Robert Mllnzies was Prime Minister.<br />
One of the interesting points about our situation there is that<br />
we have a coalition government and in two houses of Parliamevmt and<br />
in the two parties we have a unanimous support for the Governilent is<br />
policy in Viet Nam and in relation to the programme of National<br />
Service by which we are supplementing our regular forces. Now I<br />
think that's a better batting average than can be claimed even<br />
in this country.<br />
Q. Mr. Prime Minister, there has been some pressure to let<br />
foreign banks operate in Australia. Could this meet the need<br />
for investment capital? Is this likely to come about any time<br />
soon?<br />
MR. HOLT: ,~ ell I don't kn~ ow that it would meet the need because the<br />
need is very great and I don't think the banks themselves would be<br />
looking to channel money of the dimension that will be required<br />
for Australian development. It has been put to me fr~ m various<br />
countries that we should enable them to establish a branch of their<br />
bank in Australia. We have a problem there because we feel it is<br />
necessary for the Government and our RP serve Bank to maintain a<br />
general control over credit and we don't have that same control<br />
when the ownership is the hands of foreign bankers. Their<br />
nlational interest or their company interest doesn't always proceed<br />
along the same lines as our own but we have in several instan~ ces<br />
permitted themn to esta~ lish a sort of representative office and<br />
some have done this the Bank of Tokyo has done it, I think the<br />
first\ National City, the Chase Manhattan, but it's not a simple<br />
problem. ' We certainly need the development capital and there are<br />
other financial institutions on which this limitation does not<br />
apply insurance offices and that kind of thing, investment<br />
groups, this is open to the American investor quite freely and<br />
indeed a good deal of investment is still flowing in to Australia<br />
from the United States.<br />
Q. Is thei-e any kind of a peace movement in Australia?<br />
MR. HOLT: Oh, yes, we have the same sort of people that hold up banners<br />
and that kind of thing, but I would say that over recent months<br />
there has baen , I thinkfa more general realisation of the need<br />
for the policies we are ' pursuing in Viet Namn. The greater<br />
sensitivity in Australia developed not so much on the issue of<br />
Viet Nam. I think our people are more sensitive and conscious<br />
to the Viet Nam issue even than the people in the United States<br />
because after all we are very much closer to it, indeed it's<br />
nearer from Darwin to Saigon than it is from, say, Brisbane to<br />
Perth, two capital cities inside our own continent. So this is<br />
something which we see as quite close to us and indeed sin~ ce it<br />
constitutes an element in the total communist threat in that area<br />
of the world then we are even more sensitive I believe than the<br />
American people to its dangers. But where we did have quite*<br />
a stir in Australia for some time was on the question of National<br />
Service for overseas military service. This has not happened in<br />
Australian history before other than in respect of a very limited<br />
area during the second world war and for a time there was qu~ ite<br />
a strong emotional rextion to this, but it has abated considerably </p>
<p>in recent times largely as a result of the reaction of the<br />
young men in the army themselves the young national servicemen<br />
who didn't particularly want to be called up in the first instance<br />
but having gone in with the regular units and having proceeded to<br />
South Viet Nam, have conveyed back a recognition of the importance<br />
of what they're doing and the need to be there.<br />
Q. Have you got dissent in the universities or not?<br />
MR. HOLT: . iell, in the universities you will get debate about it but<br />
you will get opposing groups in the debate. It is by no means<br />
an issue in which there is a majority view hostile to the policy<br />
in the universities. I would say that as of the moment there has<br />
been if not an acceptance, a willingness to accept the undertakirg<br />
which the Government has given that this will be regarded as one<br />
of the vital issues at the forthcoming election. The Opposition<br />
has made it clear that it is opposed to this policy and I think<br />
most members of the public are now prepared to wait and see the<br />
issue fought out at that time.<br />
Mr. Holt: Weli, I think that's just about enough from mie for the<br />
time being<br />
Q. How would a military withdrawal from Viet Nam affect<br />
Australia?<br />
11R. HOLT: I think it would not only affect Australia very seriously,<br />
it would certainly affect every non-communist country in South<br />
East Asia. I mean let's face the matter quite realistically<br />
so,: e people talk about the Domino Theory in reverse, that we<br />
have been building up the strength of countries which earlier<br />
had been comparatively weak both in their defences and in their<br />
economics, and if that process can be sustained then those<br />
countries in turn will be making their own increasing contribution.<br />
You have a hopeful illustration of that in the meeting in Seoul<br />
the so-called ASPAC Meeting just a week cr so ago. This is a<br />
hopeful sign. The Asian Di-velopment Bank is a hopeful sign of<br />
co-operation in the area. So we have got a long way to go but<br />
don't let's take too gloomy an overall picture of what is going<br />
on because in a lot of places we feel that much has been aohieved.<br />
of<br />
Q. What do you think would be the effect/ a negotiated peace<br />
in that area?<br />
MR. HOLT: ' Well, it would depend on the outcome of the negotiations.<br />
If it merely applied a plaster for the time being and the wound<br />
was to open again shortly afterwards, then our last state would<br />
be-' worse than our first. But we support the efforts which the<br />
United States is making for a negotiated peace, quite genuinely<br />
and quite earnestly.<br />
Thank you, gentlemcn<br />
Thank you,. llr. Prime Minister. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
