<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>41267</transcript-id>
    <title>Visit to Israel – Marking the 100th anniversary of the Battle of Beersheba</title>
    <prime-minister>Turnbull, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20150915 - 20180824</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/10/2017</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>This week I will travel to Israel to attend the 100th anniversary of the Battle of Beersheba.</p>
<p>On 31 October 1917 regiments of the Australian Light Horse Brigade captured the city of Beersheba. It was a momentous victory and one of the last great cavalry charges in history.</p>
<p>I am honoured to represent Australia at the 100th anniversary commemorations of this historic charge, where 31 Australians paid the ultimate sacrifice.</p>
<p>This visit will deepen and strengthen Australia’s ties with Israel, and build on the bilateral relationship that our two nations share.</p>
<p>It is an opportunity to cement the commitments made during Prime Minister Netanyahu’s historic visit to Australia in February.</p>
<p>I look forward to reinforcing our increasingly diverse relationship and discussing areas of mutual interest, including science and technology, innovation, security and trade and investment.</p>
<p>Our defence ties have become a vital part of the relationship between Australia and Israel. As a result of this visit we aim to upgrade the cooperation on defence, national security, and the protection of crowded places.</p>
<p>Our nations can learn a great deal from each other in order to strengthen security and keep our citizens safe.</p>
<p>I will be accompanied on this visit by Minister for Veterans Affairs’ and Cyber Security, Dan Tehan.</p>
<p>This year also marks the 70th anniversary of Australia’s bilateral relationship with Sri Lanka, and I am delighted to be able to visit Sri Lanka on my return from Israel.</p>
<p>I had the pleasure of meeting President Sirisena and Prime Minister Wickremesinghe during their visits to Australia earlier this year.</p>
<p>I look forward to continuing our discussions on strengthening our economic links, defence engagement, and our work together to combat trans-national crime, particularly people-smuggling.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
