<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10791</transcript-id>
    <title>5 August 1998                                 TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                  THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                DOORSTOP INTERVIEW - CAIRNS</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/08/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE.............................................................................................</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: </p>
<p>Prime Minister, do you think Bob Katter is trying to get himself</p>
<p>   expelled from the National Party?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I'll leave all of that to the National Party.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[Inaudible]</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I shall leave it all to the National Party.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Have you succumbed to One Nation given the decision on wool overnight</p>
<p>   or yesterday?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>They say you have.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>They would say that wouldn't they.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Are you concerned about the Chevron gas pipeline going ahead if</p>
<p>   Comalco doesn't sign a deal with Chevron soon?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well we are working very closely with the Queensland Government</p>
<p>   and we are working very closely with the company. I spoke to the</p>
<p>   Prime Minister of Papua New Guinea about the pipeline when he was</p>
<p>   here on Monday and we will certainly do everything we can and we're</p>
<p>   quietly optimistic that the project is going to come to fruition.</p>
<p>   But in the end, like all of these things, it is a commercial decision</p>
<p>   and it depends very much on the assessment made by the company of</p>
<p>   the commercial risks and the commercial return.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Has there been any comment on the EIS yet, the Chevron's environmental</p>
<p>   impact statement?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I am sure there's been comment on it. Well, look, we</p>
<p>   are being very cooperative and if this project doesn't go ahead</p>
<p>   it won't be through any lack of interest or support from the</p>
<p>   Federal Government. But, look, I am confident but it's not</p>
<p>   really helpful with these things for Prime Ministers to be giving</p>
<p>   running daily commentaries. I don't think that really helps</p>
<p>   the process at all.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>So Prime Minister, is One Nation wrong to claim credit for your</p>
<p>   decision on wool?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Will you be looking at the upgrading of the Cape York development</p>
<p>   road while you are up there?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>We will certainly be hearing quite a bit about it. Warren Entsch</p>
<p>   has already told me a lot about it, he tells me a lot about it whenever</p>
<p>   we visit here. They know that Mark Vaile, the Federal Transport</p>
<p>   Minister, is coming to the area next week or the week after so no</p>
<p>   doubt he will have very detailed discussions and hear a lot of views.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Prime Minister, the National Union of Students is very concerned</p>
<p>   with the Liberal Government's proposal to introduce up-front</p>
<p>   fees for undergraduate students. I wonder if you might comment on</p>
<p>   that.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well the National Union of Students is completely wrong to claim</p>
<p>   that the Government is going to introduce up-front fees. Completely,</p>
<p>   utterly and comprehensively wrong.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Will the Liberal Government introduce a GST on HECS fees?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well the Coalition Government will be announcing its plan for the</p>
<p>   Australian Taxation System probably at the end of next week so I</p>
<p>   invite you, along with all other Australians, to wait until then.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Bill Skate has asked for an advance on.....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes, yes he has, we are considering that.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Okay, just one more question. Just regarding Employment National,</p>
<p>   are you concerned about the regional employers, they are not terribly</p>
<p>   impressed with [inaudible]?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I think some of the reports have been quite unrepresentative</p>
<p>   of the real situation. I spoke to the Minister about Job Network</p>
<p>   a few days ago and the preliminary indications are that it is doing</p>
<p>   quite well. Obviously with any new scheme there is a settling in</p>
<p>   period but I think many of the press reports have been wildly inaccurate</p>
<p>   and quite baseless.</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
<p>[ENDS]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
