<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>16184</transcript-id>
    <title>Joint Media Release with the Treasurer Minister for Families Australian Families to receive $3.9 Billion in Rudd Government Support  </title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/10/2008</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Rudd Government will invest $3.9 billion to provide immediate financial support to help around two million Australian families.</p>
<p>This decisive action is part of the Rudd Government's $10.4 billion Economic Security Strategy to strengthen the Australian economy and support families during the global financial crisis.</p>
<p>The support will be delivered to families through a one-off payment of $1,000 for each eligible child in their care.</p>
<p>Those who will receive the support include:</p>
<p>     *  1.9 million families who receive Family Tax Benefit (A); and</p>
<p>     *  Families of another 220,000 dependent children who receive Youth Allowance, Abstudy or a benefit from the Veterans Children's Education Scheme payment.</p>
<p>In all, around 3.9 million children will benefit from the $1,000 one off payment.</p>
<p>The global financial crisis is placing increasing pressure on family budgets already stretched by the rising cost of living.</p>
<p>The Rudd Government is taking decisive action to strengthen the Australian economy.</p>
<p>Lower and middle income working families are the driving force of the Australian economy.</p>
<p>It is vital that in times of global financial crisis these Australians have our support.</p>
<p>Most families will receive their full payment automatically in the fortnight beginning 8 December 2008 on each family's regular family tax benefit payment day. These payments will be completed by 19 December.</p>
<p>Families who receive their family payments as a lump sum at the end of the financial year will receive their additional payment when they make their claim.</p>
<p>Payments will be tax exempt and not included for income-testing purposes.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
