<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8932</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP DOORSTOP, CIVIC CENTRE, NAURU 11 AUGUST 1993</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/08/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008932.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
. L I lLA<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIMfE MINISTEIL THE BON p j KEATING, hip<br />
DOORSTOP, CIVIC CENTRE, NAURU<br />
11 AUGUST 1993<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
PM: The Prime Minister and I had a mneeing as you know at the pacific Forum a<br />
yea ago, and in the intervening time he visited Australia. and our bilateral<br />
relationship has been chuffing alonlg very happily since and we arc very pleased<br />
with it, and we resumed defence cooperation and our two way trade is<br />
growing, and things arc developing quite nicely We had a chat about our<br />
bilateral relationship in broad, some of the trade relationships in particular. The<br />
Prime Minister was kind enough to brief me about changes in the political<br />
developments in Fiji, including the prospect of constitutional processes. And<br />
we had then some discussion about trade opportunities, about Spartica and<br />
how it might be better used to do things, and a general chat about our capacity<br />
to get along together and do things together,<br />
J: Mr Keating what were you able to say to Mr Rabuka about his request for an<br />
ending of some of the rules under SPARThCA, the preferential trade<br />
agreement?<br />
SR: I didn' t really ask that, after looking at the statistics available to actually, we<br />
thou~ ht there inight be a need to further look at those statistics and see if we<br />
can have a common base for our officials to have a better understanding. He<br />
gets a picture, I get a picture of the same thing so we thought we would go<br />
back and Sct out people working on basic data.<br />
J-So what would you describe the state of the debate on SPARTECA at the<br />
moment as?<br />
SR: I wouldn't even call it a debate really. It is a very general discussion and I am<br />
happy with the outcome that we have so far<br />
And from your point of view, Mr Keating,. what was that outcome? </p>
<p>I LL* 2<br />
PM: Well as the Prime Minister said, we have got a trade agreement and a trading<br />
relationship which is working, the Fijians product access to Australia, that is in<br />
the textiles, clothing area, grew by about 30 per cent by value in the last six<br />
months as the quotas have come off. And it means that in any growing<br />
dhaning relationship it is sensible for us to talk about it from time to time.<br />
And that's what we have done. And I should hope that we continue to do it.<br />
Wherever we can smooth out a wrinkle, here or there, to make these<br />
arrangements work better, so much the better. But as the Prime Minister said<br />
it Is important for us to have the Samie data so that we are all working off at<br />
the moment there is same variation in our data so we are workinS off the<br />
same data.<br />
ENDS I I rl LA ! J V I I 14 I I U L </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
