<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4735</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS TO CONFEDERATION OF AUSTRALIAN INDUSTRY, 19 JUNE 1978</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/06/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004735.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
STRICT EMBARGO UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
PROME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 19 JUNE 1978<br />
ADDRESS TO CONFEDERATION OF AUSTRALIAN INDUSTRY<br />
The task of Government and industry will be made much easier<br />
now that there exists a top level national organisation covering<br />
the entire spectrum of Australian trade, industry and commerce<br />
primary, secondary and tertiary.<br />
I know that Max Dillon and his committee have worked extremely<br />
hard over a long period to bring this Confederation into being.<br />
I congratulate the Associated Chambers of Manufactures of<br />
Australia and the Australian Council of Employers Federation on<br />
their initiative and foresight in coming together in this way.<br />
As you will know, I returned home today after extensive discussions<br />
in the United States, Europe and South East Asia on the international<br />
economy and world trade. I am now more convinced than ever that<br />
the world economic trade situation is critically balanced.<br />
During the next few months, the world's main trading nations<br />
will be making decisions of crucial importance. It is currently<br />
intended that major decisions will be taken by mid-July in the<br />
Geneva Multilateral Trade Negotiations. The seven-nation<br />
economic summit will be held at Bonn on 17th and 18th of July, and<br />
it is expected that, later this year, the UNCTAD negotiations for<br />
a Common Fund to stabilise world commodity trade will be<br />
reconvened. This then is a year in which decisions will advance world trade,<br />
or resurrect protectionist pressures. This is a year in which<br />
either nations will recognise and act on their mutual economic<br />
interdependence to their common benefit or allow narrow<br />
self-interest to predominate to the detriment of all.<br />
This is a year in which decisions will take the world forward<br />
with more sensible trading arrangements, or slide backwards<br />
into protectionism.<br />
It is imperative that the right decisions be taken, decisions<br />
that will reduce trade barriers and lead to an expansion of world<br />
markets; decisions that will enable mines, farms and factories<br />
to expand their production, their employment, their overseas<br />
trade. If the wrong decisions are taken, then I believe there<br />
would be grave risks of a world-wide retreat to the type of<br />
beggar-thy-neighbour , protectionist policies we witnessed in the<br />
/ 2' </p>
<p>It is in this nation's interest as a country heavily dependent<br />
on world trade to do all in its power to avoid such an outcome.<br />
If these negotiations do fail, it will not be for the want of<br />
trying on Australia's part.<br />
This has been my prime objective, my main concern, in my<br />
overseas discussions which began with Prime Minister Fukuda<br />
in Japan, in April and which I have pursued in ' the United States,<br />
Europe and South-East Asia in the past few weeks.<br />
It is clear that the world economy is far from having recovered<br />
from the setback caused by the excesses of previous years.<br />
The rate of growth in world trade, a key to the full economic<br />
recovery of all nations, continues to be sluggish. It will only<br />
increase if the trading nations improve the conditions under<br />
which trade is conducted in three inter-dependent areas in<br />
manuftctured products, in agricultural products ( meat, grains,<br />
daily products, and fruits), and in other commodities.<br />
In the first two areas, manufactured products and agriculture,<br />
critical decisions will have to be made in the next few weeks<br />
in the Geneva Multilateral Trade Negotiations. All sections of<br />
our economy mining, manufacturing and primary industry will<br />
be affected by these decisions. They will have an impact on<br />
the lives of every Australian, and on our wealth as a nation.<br />
A successful outcome to the negotiations is of vital importance<br />
for the entire trading world.<br />
To date, the negotiations have focussed almost exclusively on<br />
reducing tariff and non-tariff barriers on manufactured products.<br />
Agriculture has been neglected despite the fact that it forms<br />
a most significant part of world trade, and must play an<br />
important role in any broadly-based expansion of trade. The<br />
fact that there has not yet been any movement in reducing<br />
the rigid barriers against many agricultural products is a matter<br />
of deep concern.<br />
The plain fact is that the tentative agreements so far reached<br />
in the Multilateral Trade Negotiations the " MTN" relate<br />
only to certain industrial products. Tariff reductions in<br />
these products would affect 40 per cent of the exports of the<br />
major trading blocs, but only 20 per cent of world trade, and<br />
no more than 5 per cent of the exports of Australia or of many<br />
developing countries. On average tariffs for most industrialised<br />
countries, the proposal would result only in a reduction of half<br />
a per cent a year spread over eight years. Such a limited<br />
agreement plainly could make only a marginal contribution<br />
towards expanding world markets.<br />
If the final MTN agreement is to make a real impact across<br />
the broad spectrum of world trade, it is essential that agriculture<br />
be included. The United States and Australia are united in our<br />
efforts to see that the negotiations are broadened to encompass<br />
trade in agricultural products and incorporate a code of behaviour<br />
on export subsidies. We both want an agreement which is wide<br />
ranging, covering all sectors of trade. Unless agriculture is<br />
/ 3 </p>
<p>included, the US will walk away from the Geneva negotiations.<br />
I received firm and categoric assurances on this in Canberra<br />
from Vice-President Mondale, and in New York from President<br />
Carter's Special Trade Representative, Mr Strauss.<br />
The trade benefits we can achieve for our rural industries<br />
industries which account for half our exports would benefit<br />
all Australian enterprises. Strong rural industries contribute<br />
to a stronger Australian economy, to greater demand, to greater<br />
growth within Australia and to greater markets for Australia's<br />
own manufacturers. More than ever, we need to understand the<br />
essential interdependence of the different sectors of the<br />
Australian economy. Indeed, the wide membership of your new<br />
Confederation itself is a recognition of this central fact.<br />
While many factors have contributed to the sluggish state of<br />
Australia's manufacturing economy, * one major factor the<br />
present impoverished state of much of Australia's rural industriesis<br />
too often overlooked. Achieving a meaningful MTN result which<br />
will lead to a broadly based expansion of world trade will<br />
require the maximum effort and commitment by all trading nations,<br />
and a willingness to look beyond narrow self-interest.<br />
For Australia's part we have decided to make the greatest<br />
contribution we can, for in negotiations of this kind any<br />
additional weight in the right direction can help to make the<br />
difference between ultimate success and failure.<br />
Accordingly, Australia decided to participate in the 40 per cent<br />
formula cut approach for tariffs on industrial products. This<br />
decision differs sharply from the irresponsible 25 per cent<br />
across the board tariff cut of 1973, which was made unilaterally<br />
without exceptions, without reciprocity. Our offer is of course<br />
subject to receiving fully reciprocal benefits, including<br />
reciprocation at last for the earlier unilateral cut.<br />
Like all other countries adopting the formula cut approach<br />
our offer will be subject to appropriate exceptions, it will<br />
be phased in over the next decade, and we will, of course,<br />
retain our existing rights to safeguard under GATT.<br />
Australia has made this positive and prudent offer at the<br />
negotiations because of the importance of a successful MTN.<br />
We have made every effort to bring about a successful outcome<br />
to the negotiations, which would benefit all sectors of Australian<br />
industry. our offer is not a " trade-off" between industry and agriculture,<br />
it offers benefits to all Australian enterprises. A stronger<br />
total economy will give manufacturing industry a better export<br />
capability. Coupled with specific government policies to<br />
assist industry, including our new export incentive scheme it<br />
will help many manufacturers to get back into, or increase their<br />
penetration, of export markets.<br />
By making the formula cut offer we have extended the challenge<br />
of reciprocity to the major industrial countries, a challenge<br />
to offer realistic reductions in their barriers to agricultural<br />
imports. JIA </p>
<p>4.<br />
In this regard, the European Community has a particular<br />
responsibility. As the world's largest trading bloc, it should<br />
ensure that there is a successful outcome to the total trade<br />
negotiations. We shall be using the forum provided by the<br />
MTN to test the EEC's response to our own demands for a more<br />
equitable balance of trading opportunities. At the same time,<br />
Mr Garland will continue our bilateral negotiations with the<br />
Community.<br />
We are resolved to continue the pursuit of a realistic and<br />
equitable trading relationship with the EEC. Unless the EEC<br />
is prepared to move towards an equitable relationship Australia<br />
will have no alternative but to reappraise the totality of<br />
our trading -and commercial relationship with the Community.<br />
I have advised Mr Jenkins, the Pri sident of th~ e EEC, that the<br />
Community would be seriously mistaken if it underestimated<br />
Australia's resolve and determination in this matter. The MTN<br />
does not only hold out a promise of expanding world markets,<br />
from which all nations would benefit, it also presents the<br />
threat of failure and a reversion to protectionism.<br />
In particular, we must strongly oppose an attempt by European<br />
nations to have the principle of " selective" or discriminatory<br />
safeguards accepted in international forums. Such so called<br />
" safeguards' could be reminiscent of the worst features of the<br />
destructive protectionism of the 1930' s.<br />
The most fundamental principle of the General Agreement on<br />
Tariffs and Trade is the most favoured nation rule this<br />
specifies trade rules instituted by one member nation of GATT<br />
must apply equally to all others. GATT members are not<br />
permitted to discriminate against each other. This rule is<br />
the most important single aspect of GATT that protects middle<br />
range developed countries, and the developing nations against<br />
the dangers of arbitrary and discriminatory action against them<br />
by the major trading powers.<br />
If it were to be accepted under international agreements that<br />
nations had the power unilaterally to impose restrictions<br />
on imports from particular countries this would strike at<br />
the very heart of the GATT and the pressure to impose such<br />
restrictions could be irrestible.<br />
If the breach of the most favoured nation principle was conceded<br />
discriminatory rules proposed could be used against smaller<br />
countries, weaker countries, the newly industrialising developing<br />
nations. Discriminatory action could be directed against Australia.<br />
I now turn to the third area in which there is a need for<br />
concerted action to stimulate world trade growth. I refer to<br />
trade in commodities, and the need to take more fully into<br />
account the interests of the developing world. This is not a<br />
matter of charity. It is a matter of self-interest.<br />
Many developing countries rely overwhelmingly on one or a few<br />
commodities for their export earnings. Even when petroleum -is </p>
<p>excluded, commodities account for 55 per cent of the exports<br />
of developing nations. The developing countries represent a<br />
huge potential for new market growth. As their economies grow<br />
an enormous expansion of trade will undoubtedly follow. For<br />
this to happen, their export earnings must be stable and growing.<br />
In the last decade, markets in the developing countries have<br />
grown from about $ 50 billion to $ 215 billion. Over the same<br />
period, our exports to developing countries have grown from<br />
$ 0.73 billion to $ 3 billion over one quarter of our exports.<br />
What has happened is that, as developing countries enter economic<br />
take-off, our trade has grown very rapidly. Ten years ago, our<br />
exports to the Republic of Korea totalled $ 8 million today<br />
they are running in excess of $ 200 million, a graphic illustration<br />
of the scope of the expansion of such markets. On the basis of<br />
such mutual self-interest, Australia has been pressing for a<br />
better deal foi the developing countries, and for a more pragmatic<br />
approach to be taken by both developed and developing countries<br />
on ways of stabilising world commodity prices. This is the issue<br />
symbolised by the concept of a " Common Fund".<br />
Through our own experience with the International Wheat and Sugar<br />
Agreements and our Wool Price Reserve Scheme, Australia believes<br />
that commodity stabilisation arrangements can be made to workand<br />
bring stability to prices.<br />
At the present time, there is a wide divergence of views between<br />
many of the developed and developing nations on this issue.<br />
But I am convinced, that with proper will and determination, a<br />
fair compromise can be reached between the two extreme points<br />
of view. I know that the Commonwealth Secretary-General, Mr Ramphal,<br />
is working particularly hard to achieve such a result.<br />
All these questions will be discussed at the seven-nation<br />
economic summit meeting in Bonn next month. This will be a<br />
meeting of fundamental importance and one of great difficulty.<br />
Most of the principal participants have different objectives.<br />
The United States and Britain want stronger economies, such as<br />
Germany and Japan to pursue higher growth rates; Britain and<br />
France want discriminatory safeguards to form a principal feature<br />
of the new trading arrangements em ergin; from the MTN; the<br />
prime aim-of Germany and Japan is to-ensure that the world does<br />
not slide back into protectionism.<br />
The Australian Government believes that any agreement reached<br />
at Bonn will need to reinforce the efforts of national governments<br />
to put their own domestic economies on a sound basis, so that<br />
long term growth can be achieved without renewing higher rates<br />
of inflation.<br />
Some countries have tended to say that if only the stronger<br />
economies would reflate more weaker economies could be pulled<br />
out of their difficulties. But what has to be understood is that<br />
countries suffering high inflation rates must themselves establish<br />
the essential preconditions for non-inflationary and lasting<br />
growth. / 6 </p>
<p>6.<br />
The Japans and Germanys of this world cannot solve all the world's<br />
economic problems. Even such a powerful economy as that of the<br />
United States will, as President Carter has recently affirmed,<br />
require remedial action if their recent resurgence in inflation<br />
and their imbalance of payments is to be overcome.<br />
It is disappointing that the United States, which has been<br />
maintaining a rate of growth which many of us wo~ l~ d like to see<br />
has slipped back into an unhappy inflationary situation as a result.<br />
The United States is thus once again in the position where it has<br />
to exercise restraint.<br />
The Australian Government believes that the Bonn Summit should<br />
also make a commitment to fairer and more broadly based internatonal<br />
trading agreements reaching a consensus that the final<br />
MTN trade agreement should cover all the major areas of tradenot<br />
just industrial products.<br />
Australia and many other countries also look to the seven<br />
nations at Bonn to fulfill their great international responsibilities,<br />
particularly to the developing world.<br />
There is a need for international leadership, particularly on<br />
the important issue of fairer trading arrangements for commodities,<br />
and the establishment of a Common Fund.<br />
The Bonn Summit presents a challenge to statesmanship. The actions<br />
which these major nations take affect all others. Their views are<br />
critical to achieving a practical and far-sighted resolution of the<br />
current international trading negotiations.<br />
All the discussions I had overseas greatly reinforced my belief<br />
in the appropriateness of the policies which the Australian<br />
Government has steadfastly pursued for the past two and a half<br />
years. Our economic policies have emphasised not the chase after shortterm<br />
growth rates, but getting the fundamentals of the Australian<br />
e , conomy right. In this way, we may be assured of not merely<br />
temporary growth but lasting growth into the 1980' s and beyond.<br />
It has been very encouraging to see the way in which, gradually,<br />
many of the unpalatable inescapable truths of economic policy in<br />
our private enterprise economies are today being accepted internationally.<br />
No less encouraging is the marked change in attitude among foreign<br />
business and financial leaders towards the Australian economy.<br />
When I spoke with foreign business and financial leaders in 1976<br />
and 1977 there was some reserve about whether we could really<br />
put our economy to right again. There was a respect for the<br />
efforts we had been making and the successes which these efforts<br />
were then just beginning to show. But nonetheless there remained<br />
a clear suspension of judgement on whether we would have the<br />
staying power and will to see it through. / 7 </p>
<p>During these past few weeks I have found a very different mood.<br />
These independent observers of the Australian scene and most of<br />
them are very well informed about us are now much more convinced<br />
both of our policies and of the clear progress these policies are<br />
now producing.<br />
I need hardly say how important this is for Austr~ lia, particularly<br />
in view of the immediate prospects for international trade which,<br />
for the reasons I have already outlined will continue to be<br />
difficult for some time yet.<br />
In the rather cold world in which we shall have to go on living<br />
the countries with the best domestic policies will be the ones<br />
best able to withstand and overcome these international chills.<br />
In the weeks ahead, when Cabinet is considering the outlook for<br />
1978-79, we shall be maintaining the same policy attitudes that<br />
have brought us our success to date. We shall in particular be<br />
bringing to our deliberations the most rigorous attitude towards<br />
public spending. For only in that way can we hope to maintain<br />
an appropriate firm grip on the deficit, the growth of the money<br />
supply, and less directly the escalation of wage increases.<br />
If there is one thing which experience has taught us in recent<br />
years, it is that the growth of total demand in the economy is<br />
not helped rather it is hindered, by excessive growth of government<br />
expenditures. Such a route has proved disastrous in its implications<br />
for private business investment which lies at the productive heart<br />
of our economies, and which is an essential prerequesite of raising<br />
our living standards. It is very easy to be seduced into spending<br />
some hundreds of millions of dollars on falsely conceived " employmentcreating"<br />
schemes.<br />
But it ought to be understood that spending by governments in that<br />
way can alter the basic perception of the Australian economy held<br />
by investors here and abroad. The result would be that increased<br />
government spending of three or four hundred million dollars could<br />
reduce private investment and consumer spending by much more than<br />
that. While there would be more people on the government payroll,<br />
there would be fewer people employed overall. That, I believe, is<br />
a bad bargain. It is not one that my Government will entertain.<br />
Mr President, I am delighted to have been able to speak with you<br />
at the inauguration of this Confederation. Australian industry<br />
is a central force in our economy. I know you have been through<br />
a long and difficult period. The world trade and economic scene is<br />
likely to remain difficult not for months, but for years, and we<br />
cannot hide from the hard times ahead. We are a trading nation and<br />
our prosperity ultimately depends upon trade. It is therefore up<br />
to all of us as Australians to commit ourselves to this country;<br />
to commit ourselves to success, to boldness, to innovation; to<br />
seek out and develop new markets here and abroad, not merely by<br />
aping products and tech * niques devised overseas, but by developing<br />
our own products, our own expertise.<br />
We cannot tell with accuracy how the world economy will fare, nor<br />
can we know with certainty what direction the MTN will take, or<br />
how rapidly world trade will grow. / 8 </p>
<p>8.<br />
Of one thing we can be certain. The stronger the Australian<br />
economy, the more we can develop our own products and expertise,<br />
the better we shall be able to withstand the difficulties and<br />
grasp the opportunities which lie ahead.<br />
Our future depends above all upon ourselves upon our capacity<br />
to overcome difficulties, to respond to change to meet future<br />
challenges. Our greatest resource is the skill and capacity<br />
of our people. It is time we used these qualities to the full<br />
to take advantage of our opportunities.<br />
My Government will, through predictable and stable policies,<br />
give Australian industry the effective support and encouragement<br />
it needs.<br />
We will do everything we can to re-establish the basic<br />
relationships which ae essential to your health within the<br />
Australian economy better profits, incentives for investment<br />
and development, and a lower inflation rate.<br />
In this way, industry can once again thrive, invest and make<br />
profits and provide jobs.<br />
I wish your Confederation every success. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
