<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4170</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE RT HON MALCOLM FRASER, PRIME MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA, AT THE BANQUET IN HONOUR OF PREMIER HUA KUO-FENG - 23 JUNE 1976</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/06/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004170.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE RT HON. MALCOLM FRASER, PRIME MINISTER OF<br />
AUSTRALIA, AT THE BANQUET IN HONOUR OF PREMIER HUA KUO-FENG<br />
JUNE 23RD 1976.<br />
Premier Hua Kuo-feng, distinguished Chinese<br />
friends, Excellencies, Ladies and Gentlemen.<br />
Now that our discussions have concluded I want<br />
to express my very great appreciation for the hospitality<br />
you have shown to me, to my wife and to the members of the<br />
Australian delegation. Both you yourself, and those<br />
members of the Chinese people we have been fortunate enough<br />
to meet, have treated us with unfailing courtesy and warmth,<br />
and I know this has been appreciated by us all.<br />
The lengthy discussions we have had over the last<br />
few days have been friendly and candid. We have spoken<br />
plainly to each other which is the only way two nations<br />
wishing to improve their mutual understanding can talk to<br />
each other. We have appreciated the detail with which you<br />
made the Chinese presentation, and we in our turn have sought<br />
to present Australia's Foreign Policy comprehensively. A<br />
major purpose of our discussions has been to advance the<br />
vitally important process of identifying common interests.<br />
This has been achieved. As we have presented our independent<br />
views of the world, we have confirmed that there are many<br />
important matters on which our views are similar. There are,<br />
of course, some matters on which we do not agree, and we have<br />
spoken about these frankly, but areas of agreement have been<br />
very broad and important. We each have spoken of our<br />
commitment to: World peace and security based on respect for<br />
national independence.<br />
The rejection of policies based on the<br />
subordination of one race to another a<br />
subordination which offends the fundamental<br />
principles of human dignity. We all deplore<br />
the events of recent days which have led to<br />
such tragic results. / 2 </p>
<p>Resolution in opposing the attempt of any<br />
great power to dominate other nations, and<br />
The belief that nations should make adequate<br />
provision for their legitimate defence needs.<br />
One basic matter on which there is agreement is the need to<br />
assess the world realistically, to see it as it is and not<br />
as we would like it to be. We for our part will base our<br />
Foreign Policy not on a country's ideology or its social<br />
system but on that country's actions and the extent to which<br />
shared interests can be identified.<br />
The identification of those matters where there<br />
are similar assessments is a crucial part of the process<br />
of implementing a sound Foreign Policy. It is a process that,<br />
in Australia's view, requires greater attention than it has<br />
received in the past. There is a great value in regular<br />
discussions at different levels in advancing the<br />
identification of shared interests and elaborating one's<br />
analysis of the international situation. Australia, I<br />
believe, is well placed to pursue this process because it<br />
has good relations with many important countries concerned<br />
with the Asia/ Pacific area. Australia has close and warm<br />
relations with the A. S. E. A. N. group of countries, with<br />
Papua New Guinea and Nations of the South Pacific. I have<br />
come to Peking from Japan where I signed, on behalf of<br />
Australia, a Treaty of Friendship and Co-operation and where<br />
both myself and our Foreign Minister, Mr Peacock, had<br />
wide-ranging discussions with the Leaders of Japan. Shortly<br />
I will be going to the United States to meet with<br />
President Ford. In all of my discussions I have been, and<br />
will be, seeking further clarification of those areas where<br />
important interests c. re shared.<br />
A realistic view of the world requires that we<br />
place great emphasis on assessing priorities. Particularly<br />
in the current international situation clarification of<br />
priorities is of fundamental importance so that countries<br />
can ensure that all their international dealings at all<br />
levels advance the major objectives that they have set<br />
themselves to achieve. And it may well be that in pursuit<br />
of major objectives some matters of lesser importance ought<br />
to be set aside. For our part our dealings with other<br />
countries will be based on mutual respect and peaceful<br />
co-operation. The chances for international peace and<br />
development will be greatly enhanced if major powers can<br />
base their relations on non-interference in other countries<br />
at all levels. In securing the peaceful development of the<br />
world and the well-being of its peoples China can have a<br />
most positive and constructive role. By her words and by her<br />
actions China can help clarify and advance constructive<br />
relations between States. The future of people everywhere<br />
will be profoundly influenced by the course China pursues. . o ./ 3 </p>
<p>China has a long perspective on the World. In the last<br />
few days I have seen some of the past achievements of the<br />
long Chinese Civilisation. I know that China seeks also to<br />
look far into the future. The present time is an important<br />
one in setting the course for that long journey.<br />
I am confident that our discussions have further<br />
advanced relations between China and Australia and have<br />
established a new stage for further constructive dealings<br />
at various levels in the future. Mr Premier, I am delighted<br />
that both you and your Foreign Minister have expressed your<br />
willingness to pay us a visit at appropriate times. The<br />
members of the Australian Delegation are now looking forward<br />
very much, Mr Premier, to our visit to other parts of China<br />
and to meeting more of the Chinese people. Let me now take<br />
this opportunity to thank you once again most warmly for<br />
your excellent hospitality.<br />
Excellencies, Ladies and Gentlemen I would like<br />
you to join me in a Toast<br />
To the prosperity and well-being of China and<br />
her people<br />
To the health of Chairman Mao Tse-tung<br />
To the health of Premier Hua Kuo-feng, and to the<br />
further growth of friendship and understanding<br />
between China and Australia. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
