<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10908</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                ADDRESS AT LAUNCH OF ADELAIDE RUNWAY EXTENSION                ADELAIDE AIRPORT, SOUTH AUSTRALIA</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/07/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE..........................................................................................</p>
<p>Well thank you very much Mr Baker; to Diana Laidlaw, to my many federal</p>
<p> colleagues and particularly Christine Gallus in whose electorate of</p>
<p> Hindmarsh the airport is located, ladies and gentlemen.</p>
<p>I am delighted to have been asked to come here this morning and to</p>
<p> officially open this runway extension. It is another example of the</p>
<p> commitment of the Federal Government to the building of necessary</p>
<p> infrastructure to support the growth and the expansion of the Australian</p>
<p> economy.</p>
<p>There's always a lot of legitimate debate about the role of Government</p>
<p> in modern society. There are some who see that Government or who argue</p>
<p> that the Government should have a greater role. There are others who</p>
<p> believe that the Government should have a lesser role. There are many</p>
<p> people quite understandably who believe that when governments try</p>
<p> and run businesses, they normally make a pretty significant hash of</p>
<p> it, and that has certainly been the experience of many South Australians</p>
<p> and it was the experience of many people in Victoria and many people</p>
<p> in Western Australia, and it is an ongoing legitimate argument to</p>
<p> put. And I don't think there is any debate across the political</p>
<p> and intellectual divide about the role of Government in Australia</p>
<p> about the proposition that one of the responsibilities of Government</p>
<p> is to provide a decent level of infrastructure within our community.</p>
<p>And that is why the Government I lead committed $100 million to the</p>
<p> construction of the Darwin to Alice Springs railway which is a very</p>
<p> very important infrastructure project to the people of South Australia</p>
<p> and to the people of the Northern Territory. And also might I say</p>
<p> to all the people of Australia, you would be surprised how many people</p>
<p> in Sydney where I grew up, who are very very attracted to the concept</p>
<p> of that particular infrastructure development.</p>
<p>And these runway extensions are very much in the same genre. They</p>
<p> represent a commitment by the Federal Government to the development</p>
<p> of the international capacity of the Adelaide airport, and I am therefore</p>
<p> very pleased to be associated with this project.</p>
<p>The main runway here has been extended by 572 metres and creating</p>
<p> a full-length taxiway and at a total cost to the Commonwealth of $45.7</p>
<p> million. It will bring great benefits to South Australia. It will</p>
<p> give additional freight capacity, particularly to Asian markets. It</p>
<p> will provide greater opportunities for direct exports of perishable</p>
<p> goods, and it will improve international tourism opportunities. And</p>
<p> both of those things, and increased freight capacity, and an increased</p>
<p> tourist capacity are important to the economy of South Australia.</p>
<p>I have long believed that a further significant exploitation of the</p>
<p> great tourist potential of South Australia, particularly surrounding</p>
<p> the great appeal of the Barossa Valley and other parts of the State</p>
<p> associated with the wine growing industry, are one of the important</p>
<p> elements of the future growth and the future development of the economy</p>
<p> of this State.</p>
<p>In a very special way this new air capacity does compliment the proposed</p>
<p> Darwin to Alice Springs Railway, the Adelaide to Darwin rail link.</p>
<p> And it will give many South Australian businesses in the future two</p>
<p> options. Either the new rail or the new air routes to markets and</p>
<p> they both represent new and fresh opportunities. So, it is in every</p>
<p> sense of the word a very important building block for the future growth</p>
<p> and development of businesses in South Australia. It represents a</p>
<p> vote of confidence by the Federal Government in the future economic</p>
<p> development and growth of South Australia. And I am delighted Mr Baker</p>
<p> that you are here, I know that you feel - as you are a native of Manchester</p>
<p> - absolutely acclimatised this morning, absolutely acclimatised. I</p>
<p> am delighted that you're here and I'm delighted to welcome</p>
<p> the contribution that your company, which has had great experience</p>
<p> in operating airports, the contribution that your company is making</p>
<p> to the development to the economy in South Australia.</p>
<p>It will, of course, generate a lot of jobs. And any economic activity</p>
<p> has no meaning at all unless it carries with it the generation of</p>
<p> jobs and the creation of job opportunities for Australians into the</p>
<p> future.</p>
<p>So ladies and gentlemen can I say how very pleased I am, again, to</p>
<p> be here. I want to congratulate Ms Laidlaw and her department and</p>
<p> the South Australian Government on the role that it's played.</p>
<p> I want to thank my own Federal colleagues for their persistent advocacy</p>
<p> - and I remark upon this - their persistent advocacy of the need for</p>
<p> the Federal Government to give a high priority to this runway extension.</p>
<p> I should tell all of you that long before I became Prime Minister</p>
<p> I felt the force of South Australian Federal representation towards</p>
<p> a very significant investment in this upgrade. And I was told my South</p>
<p> Australian colleagues that when it came, (... aircraft flying</p>
<p> overhead...) - it feels like Sydney! - when it came to putting</p>
<p> together our election commitments in 1996 when we were just in Opposition.</p>
<p> When it came to putting together those election commitments we have</p>
<p> to leave room for the provision of funds for this airport. And I can</p>
<p> well remember Senator Hill, the Leader of the Government in the Senate,</p>
<p> and the Senator from South Australia reminding all of us in those</p>
<p> days of the importance of this airport and the role that South Australians</p>
<p> correctly saw the airport playing in the future economic development</p>
<p> of the State and most particularly the business potential and the</p>
<p> business capacity of the city of Adelaide.</p>
<p>Therefore my friends, I know I've got to cut a ribbon or a banner</p>
<p> in a few moments, but let me say how delighted I am to be associated</p>
<p> with this extension. It's been finished ahead of time, a little</p>
<p> below budget, and congratulations to those who are associated with</p>
<p> that. That's always pleasing news, and it shows a commitment.</p>
<p> But of all of those people involved I congratulate them and I wish</p>
<p> all of those associated with the airport great success into the future.</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
