<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4709</transcript-id>
    <title>OCCUPATIONAL SAFETY AND HEALTH CODE FOR COMMONWEALTH GOVERNMENT EMPLOYEES, 14 MAY 1978</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/05/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004709_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO: 4: 00 PM<br />
PRIME MINISTER.<br />
FOR PRESS 14 MAY 1978<br />
OCCUPATIONAL SAFETY AND HEALTH CODE FOR<br />
COMMONWEALTH GOVERNMENT EMPLOYEES<br />
The Government has decided to implement the Code of General<br />
Principles on Safety and Health designed to protect<br />
Commonwealth employees from injury through work accidents<br />
and to promote maximum occupational health.<br />
This decision will give a lead to industry and commerce in<br />
cutting down the one million man weeks now lost to Australia<br />
every year through industrial accidents and injuries.<br />
Absences from work through accident and illness are greater<br />
than from industrial disputes and seriously affect national<br />
productivity. The direct cost to the nation of work injuries is now estimated<br />
to be about $ 1,400m a year. In the area of Commonwealth<br />
employment alone for 1975-76 $ 21m went in compensation payments.<br />
This indicates that there is scope for considerable improvement<br />
in industrial safety and health despite the efforts of many<br />
organisations to safeguard their employees.<br />
The Code provides for control of the physical environment<br />
and also for training, consultation between managers and employees,<br />
and their maximum involvement in accident prevention measures.<br />
It defines the responsibilities of people at various-levels in<br />
Commonwealth departments and authorities in promoting safety<br />
and good working conditions.<br />
The Code of Principles supplemented by detailed Codes of<br />
Practice covers all aspects of industrial health and safety<br />
for Commonwealth employees.<br />
These include the scope and definition of safety measures;<br />
safety co-ordination; provision of a safe and healthy working<br />
environment; machine, plant and equipment safety; personal<br />
protective equipment; hygiene; special measures to protect<br />
employees in the-field or in isolated areas; health, medical<br />
and first-aid services; accident records, statistics and<br />
investigation. </p>
<p>2<br />
The Department of Productivity will be responsible for<br />
generally oversighting and evaluating the Code's effectiveness;<br />
the Director-General of Health will have responsibility<br />
for occupational health recommendations.<br />
The Code is a major step forward in the area of occupational<br />
safety and health for Commonwealth employees. Several states<br />
have adopted Codes which follow it closely with minor<br />
revisions. Indeed, a representative of State Labour Departments<br />
assisted in the development of the Code, as of course did<br />
representatives of trade and Public Service unions.<br />
The Department of Productivity will continue working in<br />
association with State Departments of Labour, unions, employers<br />
and other interested groups in the community to improve<br />
safety and health for people at work.<br />
000---</p>
<p>EMBARGO: 4: 00 PM<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 14 MAY 1978<br />
OCCUPATIONAL SAFETY AND HEALTH CODE FOR<br />
COMMONWEALTH GOVERNMENT EMPLOYEES<br />
The Government has decided to implement the Code of General<br />
Principles on Safety and Health designed to protect<br />
Commonwealth employees from injury through work accidents<br />
and to promote maximum occupational health.<br />
This decision will give a lead to industry and commerce in<br />
cutting down the one million man weeks now lost to Australia<br />
every year through industrial accidents and injuries.<br />
Absences from work through accident and illness are greater<br />
than from industrial disputes and seriously affect national<br />
productivity. The direct cost to the nation of work injuries is now estimated<br />
to be about $ 1,400m a year. In the area of Commonwealth<br />
employment alone for 1975-76 $ 21m went in compensation payments.<br />
This indicates that there is scope for considerable improvement<br />
in industrial safety and health despite the efforts of many<br />
organisations to safeguard their employees.<br />
The Code provides for control of the physical environment<br />
and also for training, consultation between managers and employees,<br />
and their maximum involvement in accident prevention measures.<br />
It defines the responsibilities of people at various levels in<br />
Commonwealth departments and authorities in promoting safety<br />
and good working conditions.<br />
The Code of Principles supplemented by detailed Codes of<br />
Practice covers all aspects of industrial health and safety<br />
for Commonwealth employees.<br />
These include the scope and definition of safety measures;<br />
safety co-ordination; provision of a safe and healthy working<br />
environment; machine, plant and equipment safety; personal<br />
protective equipment; hygiene; special measures to protect<br />
employees in the-field or in isolated areas; health, medical<br />
and first-aid services; accident records, statistics and<br />
investigation. / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
The Department of Productivity will be responsible for<br />
generally oversighting and evaluating the Code's effectiveness;<br />
the Director-General of Health will have responsibility<br />
for occupational health recommendations.<br />
The Code is a major step forward in the area of occupational<br />
safety and health for Commonwealth employees. Several states<br />
have adopted Codes which follow it closely with minor<br />
revisions. Indeed, a representative of State Labour Departments<br />
assisted in the development of the Code, as of course did<br />
representatives of trade and Public Service unions.<br />
The Department of Productivity will continue work ing in<br />
association with State Departmen -ts of Labour, unions, employers<br />
and other interested groups in the community to improve<br />
safety and health for people at work.<br />
000 </p>
<p>I iioa Saet<br />
an Healt<br />
inI Ausrai I I Imen </p>
<p>PREFACE This Code of General Principles on Occupational Safety and<br />
Health in Australian Government Employment was developed<br />
by a Government sponsored Committee comprising representatives<br />
from the following departments and organisations:<br />
Department of Health<br />
Department of Housing and Construction<br />
Department of Labor and Immigration<br />
Department of Manufacturing Industry<br />
Postmaster-General's Department<br />
Public Service Board<br />
Representatives from Australian Council of Trade Unions<br />
Representatives from Council of Australian Government<br />
Employee Organisations<br />
Representatives from the Committee of Chief Inspectors<br />
of State Labour Departments<br />
Australian Government Publishing Service<br />
Canberra 1975<br />
¸ Commonwealth of Australia 1975<br />
Printed by Advocate Press Ply. Ltd.<br />
4ronct-iP-4-109 </p>
<p>CONTENTS PREFACE FOREWORD<br />
SECTION 1 SCOPE AND DEFINITIONS<br />
SECTION 2 OBLIGATIONS OF HEAD OFFICERS AND EMPLOYEES<br />
SECTION 3 STATEMENT OF SAFETY POLICY AND RESPONSIBILITIES<br />
SECTION 4 ARRANGEMENTS FOR JOINT CONSULTATION WITH<br />
EMPLOYEES ON SAFETY MATTERS<br />
SECTION 5 SAFETY CO-ORDINATION<br />
SECTION 6 WORK PLACES AND THE WORKING ENVIRONMENT<br />
SECTION 7 MACHINERY, PLANT AND EQUIPMENT<br />
SECTION 8 SAFE WORK METHODS AND APPROPRIATE TRAINING<br />
AND PLACEMENT OF EMPLOYEES<br />
SECTION 9 OCCUPATIONAL HYGIENE: CONTROL OF HARMFUL<br />
CHEMICAL AND PHYSICAL AGENTS<br />
SECTION 10 FIRE AND EXPLOSION<br />
SECTION 11 PERSONAL PROTECTIVE EQUIPMENT.<br />
SECTION 12 HEALTH, MEDICAL AND FIRST AID SERVICES<br />
SECTION 13 ACCIDENT RECORDS, STATISTICS AND INVESTIGATION<br />
ADDRESSES OF THE IMPLEMENTING AUTHORITY<br />
INDEX </p>
<p>FOREWORD On 10 September 1974, the Australian Government agreed that<br />
Ministers direct departments and statutory authorities for which<br />
they have responsibility, to apply the Code of General Principles<br />
on Occupational Safety and Health in Australian Government<br />
Employment.<br />
The Department of Labor and Immigration has responsibility for<br />
the general oversight in relation to the implementation of the<br />
Code except for occupational health recommendations which<br />
will be determined by the Director-General of Health, Department<br />
of Health.<br />
The purpose of this Code is to protect persons employed by<br />
the Australian Government from accidental injury and to promote<br />
the maximum degree of health and well being. Because any<br />
work injury results from inter-reaction between a worker and<br />
his or her working environment, there is no such thing as<br />
absolute safety. Maximum safety cannot be ensured by control<br />
of the environment alone but demands the understanding and<br />
co-operation of all persons at all levels.<br />
Consequently the Code provides not only for the control of the<br />
physical environment, but for training, consultation between<br />
management and employees, and their maximum involvement<br />
in all accident prevention measures.<br />
The Code also defines the responsibilities of persons at all levels<br />
in departments and instrumentalities in the promotion of safety<br />
and good working conditions.<br />
Only two categories of persons are recognised; head officers<br />
and employees. The latter term therefore includes persons at<br />
all levels in the service, all of whom are seen as having responsibilities<br />
for safety commensurate with their positions.<br />
While the Code of General Principles defines responsibilities<br />
for safety and health and states in broad terms the action that<br />
shall be taken to fulfil them, it does not provide detailed information<br />
on the standards required.<br />
This information is to be provided in the corresponding detailed<br />
provisions. These will be collated from accepted standards and<br />
codes of practice, recommendations agreed by the State Departments<br />
of Labour, State regulations and other information as<br />
applicable. The detailed provisions will be issued as separate<br />
publications. These provisions will be taken as providing the criteria by which<br />
observance of the Code is to be judged. </p>
<p>SECTION 1<br />
SCOPE AND DEFINITIONS<br />
1.1 Scope This Code iays down the measures required by the Australian<br />
Government to safeguard the safety and health of all employees<br />
of the Australian Government while they are at work and<br />
wherever they may be working.<br />
1.2 Definitions In this Code the following definitions apply:<br />
1.2.1 Department any department of the Aus t raIi a n<br />
Government. For the purpose of this code, any establishment,<br />
undertaking, etc., under the control of a permanent head of a<br />
department is considered as part of that department.<br />
1.2.2 Instrumentality any agency of the Australian Government,<br />
other than a department, reporting to a Minister of the<br />
Australian Government.<br />
1.2.3 Head Officer the permanent head of a department, or<br />
the chief functional officer of an instrumentality.<br />
1.2.4 Employee a person of any classification or grade<br />
employed by any department or instrumentality and engaged<br />
in activities for which he receives direct payment.<br />
1.2.5 Accident any event arising out of employment which<br />
results in work injury, damage to property or the possibility of<br />
such injury or damage to property.<br />
1.2.6 Work Injury any injury, poisoning, disease or disability<br />
to an employee, or the recurrence or exacerbation of any such<br />
injury, disease, or disability, which arises out of employment.<br />
1.2.7 Safe, Safety the condition in which persons are protected<br />
from the risk of work injury so far as is practicable in<br />
the light of current knowledge, through control of the working<br />
environment, work methods, machinery, plant and equipment,<br />
and through measures to influence the human factors conducive<br />
to accidents and injuries.<br />
1.2.8 Work Place any place where an employee is required<br />
to be or has occasion to go during the course of his<br />
employment. 1.2.9 Personal Protective Equipment clothing and equipment<br />
intended to be worn or used by employees and designed<br />
to protect against work injury. </p>
<p>SECTION 2<br />
OBLIGATIONS OF HEAD OFFICERS<br />
AND EMPLOYEES<br />
2.1 Head Officers<br />
2.2 Employees Every head officer shall be responsible for ensuring that the<br />
provisions contained in this Code are applied in his department<br />
or instrumentality. Measures to be taken shall include:<br />
2.1.1 The issue of a statement of safety policy and responsibilities.<br />
( Section 3)<br />
2.1.2 The adoption of arrangements for joint consultation with<br />
employees on safety matters. ( Section 4)<br />
2.1.3 The appointment of safety co-ordinators. ( Section<br />
2.1.4 The provision of safe work places and a safe working<br />
environment. ( Section 6)<br />
2.1.5 The provision of safe plant, machinery and equipment.<br />
( Section 7)<br />
2.1.6 The adoption of safe work methods and appropriate<br />
training and placement of employees. ( Section 8)<br />
2.1.7 The adoption of occupational hygiene principles and<br />
control of harmful chemical and physical agents. ( Section 9)<br />
2.1.8 The adoption of measures to minimise the risk of, and<br />
harmful effects of, fire and explosion. ( Section<br />
2.1.9 The provision of appropriate personal protective equipment<br />
and the adoption of measures to ensure its proper use.<br />
( Section 11)<br />
2.1.10 The establishment of medical, health and first-aid<br />
services. ( Section 12)<br />
2.1.11 The maintenance of injury and accident records and<br />
arrangements for accident investigation. ( Section 13)<br />
2.2.1 Each employee shall have responsibility for safe working<br />
consistent with the extent of his control over or influence<br />
on working conditions and methods.<br />
2.2.2 Each employee shall take such action as is within his<br />
competence and responsibility or report or make such recommendation<br />
to a higher level as he deems necessary to avoid,<br />
eliminate, or minimise hazards of which he is aware In regard<br />
to working conditions or methods.<br />
2.2.3 Each employee shall observe all instructions issued to<br />
protect his safety or the safety of others.<br />
2.2.4 Each employee shall make proper use, or to the extent<br />
of his responsibility ensure that proper use is made, of all safeguards,<br />
safety devices, personal protective equipment and other<br />
appliances provided for safety purposes.<br />
2.2.5 No employee shall, or shall cause another employee<br />
to, interfere with, remove, displace or render Ineffective any<br />
safeguard, safety device, personal protective equipment or other<br />
appliance provided for safety purposes, except when necessary<br />
as part of an approved maintenance or repair procedure. </p>
<p>SECTION 3<br />
STATEMENT OF SAFETY POLICY<br />
AND RESPONSIBILITIES<br />
Each head officer shall issue and disseminate throughout his<br />
department or Instrumentality a written statement of safety policy<br />
which he shall periodically review, expressing the aim of safe<br />
working, the requirement to comply with the provisions of this<br />
Code and in broad terms, the means by which compliance will<br />
be achieved and maintained.<br />
The statement shall indicate:<br />
the obligations and responsibilities of employees at all levels<br />
( Section 2.2)<br />
the provisions for employee consultation and participation<br />
in safety activities ( Section 4)<br />
the provisions for co-ordination of safety activities ( Section<br />
SECTION 4<br />
ARRANGEMENTS FOR JOINT CONSULTATION<br />
WITH EMPLOYEES ON SAFETY MATTERS<br />
4.1 Each head officer shall ensure that arrangements for safety within<br />
his department or instrumentality provide for the participation<br />
of employees at all levels, in planning and Implementing safety<br />
policy. Measures shall Include:<br />
4.1.1 The establishment of an occupational safety and health<br />
commi ttee on policy, which will include management, trade union<br />
and other employee representatives. This committee should have<br />
oversight of executive action taken to implement the policy.<br />
4.1.2 The. establishment of occupational safety and health<br />
committees at executive and operational levels, which will include<br />
management, trade union and other employee representatives,<br />
except where the nature of the work, the number of<br />
employees or other organisational circumstances render the<br />
operation of such committees inappropriate, In which case other<br />
standing arrangements agreed by management and the employees<br />
concerned shall be made for joint consultation and<br />
action. 4.1.3 Consultation with appropriate employee representatives<br />
on particular problems of safety and health.<br />
4.1.4 Keeping all employees informed on accident prevention<br />
activities through such measures as written communications,<br />
meetings, lectures, films, departmental newsletters and other<br />
means of communications. </p>
<p>SECTION SAFETY CO-ORDINATION<br />
5.1 Safety Co-<br />
Ordination Responsibility<br />
5.2 Safety Co-<br />
Ordination Duties<br />
5.3 Safety<br />
Officers Responsibility for safety co-ordination throughout the department<br />
or instrumentality shall be included in the functions of<br />
a senior management position having direct access to the head<br />
officer or his deputy.<br />
Safety co-ordination duties shall include:<br />
5.2.1 Formulation and implementation of plans to promote<br />
interest in and action on safety.<br />
5.2.2 Surveillance of accident and injury experience.<br />
5.2.3 Inspections of work areas, continual reviews of safety<br />
measures.<br />
5.2.4 Study and dissemination of relevant information on<br />
safety from sources both inside and outside the department or<br />
instrumentality. 5.2.5 Advice to all levels of management on safety matters.<br />
5.2.6 Preparation of an annual report on safety experience<br />
and performance.<br />
To carry out these duties the head officer shall, as necessary,<br />
appoint other officers who may be employed either full-time on<br />
safety or in association with other duties. The number of such<br />
officers, their qualifications and classifications and their full or<br />
part-time assignment shall be consistent with the size of the<br />
department or instrumentality, the geographic scatter of its locations<br />
and the nature of its operations and hazards.<br />
SECTION 6<br />
WORKPLACES AND<br />
THE WORKING ENVIRONMENT<br />
6.1 Working Environment<br />
6.2 Buildings and<br />
Workplaces Head officers shall ensure that every practicable measure is<br />
taken to provide a safe and healthy working environment for<br />
employees both in fixed locations and in temporary and outdoor<br />
locations. Buildings and where practicable workplaces, shall be planned,<br />
designed, constructed, prepared and maintained so that:<br />
6.2.1 Structures have adequate strength and stability.<br />
6.2.2 Working surfaces are adequately drained and provide<br />
good foothold. </p>
<p>6.2.3 Adequate working space is provided for operational<br />
and maintenance work with a minimum of congestion, obstruction<br />
to movement or risk of collision.<br />
6.2.4 Order, cleanliness and hygienic standards are maintained.<br />
6.2.5 Adequate lighting is provided.<br />
6.2.6 Adequate ventilation and satisfactory thermal conditions<br />
are provided.<br />
6.2.7 Safe means of access to and egress from workplaces<br />
are provided, including quick egress in case of fire or other<br />
emergency and ready access for fire fighting purposes.<br />
6.2.8 There is adequate resistance to the spread of fire and,<br />
where appropriate, safe relief of explosion pressure, adequate<br />
fire fighting and rescue equipment available, clearly identified<br />
and ready for use.<br />
6.2.9 To the greatest extent practicable the design, construction<br />
and layout of buildings and workplaces facilitate measures<br />
taken to reduce personal exposures to harmful physical and<br />
chemical agents.<br />
6.2.10 Electrical, fuel, compressed air, steam or other services<br />
are installed in a safe manner.<br />
6.2.11 There are adequate means of communication so that<br />
safety, health or rescue needs become known without delay.<br />
6.2.12 Adequate sanitary installations are provided.<br />
6.2.13 The use of materials therein and the use of furniture and<br />
fittings are such as to reduce the risk of personal exposure to<br />
harmful chemical and physical agents in the event of fire.<br />
6.3 Confined Special procedures shall be followed based on written instruc-<br />
Spaces tions for the safety of persons required to work in confined<br />
spaces.<br />
6.4 Isolated Special measures shall be adopted to protect the safety and<br />
Situations health of employees required to work in the field or in isolated<br />
situations. </p>
<p>SECTION 7<br />
MACHINERY, PLANT AND EQUIPMENT<br />
7.1 General<br />
7.2 Protection<br />
Against Failure or<br />
Faulty Operation<br />
7.3 Guarding<br />
8.1 Work Methods<br />
8.2 Placement of Employees<br />
8.3 Induction of<br />
New Employees Head officers shall ensure that all machinery, plant and equipment<br />
is safe including mobile or vehicular machinery, plant and<br />
equipment, and portable appliances.<br />
The design, construction, location and maintenance of machinery,<br />
plant and equipment shall be such as to minimise the risk<br />
of, or the harmful effects of, failure of parts, collapse, bursting,<br />
fire, explosion, faulty operation, electrical shock, and exposure<br />
to harmful physical and chemical agents.<br />
Portions of machinery, plant and equipment that are not constructed<br />
so as to be permanently safe shall be guarded or<br />
screened to the greatest practicable extent, and special procedures<br />
shall be implemented so as to prevent injury to employees<br />
or other persons.<br />
SECTION 8<br />
SAFE WORK METHODS AND APPROPRIATE<br />
TRAINING AND PLACEMENT OF EMPLOYEES<br />
Head officers shall ensure that safe methods of work are established<br />
and reviewed from time to time in the light of experience<br />
or changed circumstances. Where unusual or serious hazards are<br />
involved, the proper methods shall be defined in written instructions.<br />
An employee shall be assigned only to a task which he can<br />
perform safely. Where doubt exists, or on request by the employee,<br />
he shall be referred for medical examination.<br />
For tasks in which a high degree of operating skill and correct<br />
procedures are critical to safety, standards of competence shall<br />
be defined and measures taken to ensure that they are met.<br />
Arrangements shall be made for new employees or employees<br />
transferred to new locations, to be instructed in the rules for<br />
safe working in their tasks and advised on any particular hazards<br />
associated with them.<br />
Special measures shall be taken to ensure that new employees<br />
not familiar with the English language fully understand the<br />
training given to them. </p>
<p>8.4 Training Supervision<br />
9.1 General<br />
9.2 Installations and Processes<br />
9.3 Exposure to<br />
Harmful<br />
Chemical Agents<br />
9.4 Exposure to<br />
Harmful Physical<br />
Agents Measurement of Exposure<br />
to Airborne<br />
Contaminants Head officers shall ensure that all employees are trained and<br />
periodically retrained as necessary, in the safe practice of their<br />
employment. Machinery, plant and equipment, the use of which can involve<br />
serious risk of accident or injury to operators or others, shall<br />
be operated only by employees specially trained and qualified<br />
in its operation.<br />
Head offiers shall provide for competent supervision to ensure<br />
that safe procedures are followed and that unsafe methods and<br />
hazards in the workplace are corrected.<br />
SECTION 9<br />
OCCUPATIONAL HYGIENE<br />
CONTROL OF HARMFUL CHEMICAL AND<br />
PHYSICAL AGENTS<br />
Where harmful chemical and physical agents are used, produced,<br />
released, transported, stored, handled or otherwise may be<br />
present, head officers shall ensure that steps are taken to keep<br />
personal exposures to such agents within safe limits and that<br />
such steps comply with recommendations of the Director-<br />
General of Health.<br />
Head officers shall ensure that when new chemical and physical<br />
agents that may be harmful are introduced or when new installations<br />
or processes involve the use, generation or release<br />
of chemical or physical agents that may be harmful, the use of<br />
such agents and the design of such installations or processes<br />
shall comply with the recommendations of the Director-General<br />
of Health.<br />
No employee shall be exposed to harmful chemical agents,<br />
whether by skin contact, inhalation or ingestion at levels exceeding<br />
those approved by the Director-General of Health.<br />
No employee shall be exposed to harmful physical agents such<br />
as dust, noise, vibration, extremes of temperature or radiation<br />
except at levels and under conditions approved by the Director-<br />
General of Health.<br />
Methods for sampling, measurement and reporting o . f concentrations<br />
of airborne contaminants shall be those approved by the<br />
Director-General of Health. </p>
<p>9.6 Controls<br />
9.7 Confined Spaces<br />
9.8 Advice to<br />
Employees Measures for the control of harmful physical and chemical<br />
agents to approved levels shall comply with the recommendations<br />
of the Director-General of Health.<br />
Safe procedures shall be established for the entry of employees<br />
into confined spaces or any location in which air may be contaminated<br />
or deficient in oxygen.<br />
Procedures shall govern conditions for pre-entry, occupancy,<br />
communication, rescue and first aid.<br />
Where it is possible for employees to be exposed to harmful<br />
physical or chemical agents, they shall be Informed and reminded<br />
of the nature of the agents and their adverse health effects<br />
and of any steps they should take to ensure that exposures are<br />
kept within safe limits.<br />
SECTION FIRE AND EXPLOSION<br />
10.1 Fire and<br />
Explosion Risks<br />
10.2 Fire Fighting<br />
Equipment<br />
10.3 Evacuation Where combustible, flammable or explosive substances are used,<br />
produced, released, transported, stored, handled or otherwise<br />
may be present, head officers shall ensure that all reasonable<br />
steps are taken to minimise the risk of uncontrolled escape or<br />
accumulation of such substances and the risk of ignition or<br />
initiation of explosion, and to minimise the spread of fire and<br />
the harmful effects of explosion.<br />
10.1.1 Employees who work with or in the vicinity of flammable<br />
or explosive substances, shall be informed and reminded<br />
of the fire or explosion risk and effectively trained in the steps<br />
they should take to avoid such an occurrence.<br />
10.2.1 In all buildings and workplaces adequate fire-fighting<br />
equipment shall be provided together with means for quickly<br />
calling community fire fighting services where available.<br />
10.2.2 Where required for the safety of persons, adequate fire<br />
detecting equipment shall be provided.<br />
10.2.3 Sufficient employees shall be trained in early fire fighting<br />
so that effective use is made of the equipment available.<br />
In all buildings, and in other work places where appropriate, head<br />
officers shall ensure that there is a plan and an organisation<br />
for the quick evacuation of employees to safe areas. Employees<br />
shall be informed and practice evacuations shall be carried out<br />
at appropriate intervals. </p>
<p>SECTION 11<br />
PERSONAL PROTECTIVE EQUIPMENT<br />
11.1 Use of<br />
Personal Protective<br />
Equipment<br />
11.2 Types and<br />
Specifications of Equipment<br />
11.3 Promotion of Use<br />
11.4 Maintenance of Equipment<br />
11.5 Equipment For Use In<br />
Emergency<br />
13.1 13.2 Records of<br />
Accidents and Injuries Head officers shall ensure that personal protective equipment<br />
is supplied for the protection of employees against hazards that<br />
cannot be controlled satisfactorily by other means.<br />
Personal protective equipment supplied as protection against a<br />
particular hazard shall be in accordance with the recommendations<br />
of the Director-General of Health.<br />
Head officers shall take measures to ensure the proper use of<br />
personal protective equipment including education, instruction<br />
and supervision.<br />
Equipment shall be maintained in a clean, hygienic and effective<br />
condition and kept readily available for use.<br />
In locations where plant failures or accidents could cause conditions<br />
of danger due to harmful chemical or physical agents,<br />
personal protective equipment capable of protecting persons<br />
against such conditions shall be supplied for the use of employees<br />
engaged in repair, fire fighting, or rescue operations.<br />
SECTION 12<br />
HEALTH, MEDICAL AND FIRST-AID SERVICES<br />
Head officers shall ensure that medical, health and first-aid<br />
services are provided in their departments or instrumentalities<br />
in accordance with the requirements and recommendations of<br />
the Director-General of Health.<br />
SECTION 13<br />
ACCIDENT RECORDS, STATISTICS AND<br />
INVESTIGATION Head officers shall arrange for the prompt investigation of all<br />
accidents, the determination of causes and contributory factors<br />
and the implementation of corrective action.<br />
Records of accidents and injuries shall be kept and periodic<br />
returns made in accordance with the requirements of the Department<br />
of Labor and Immigration. </p>
<p>ADDRESSES OF THE IMPLEMENTING AUTHORITY<br />
For further information on the Code, please contact the nearest<br />
office of the implementing authority listed below:<br />
Secretary Department of Labor and Immigration<br />
239 Bourke Street<br />
Melbourne, Vic. 3000<br />
( P0 Box 281 7AA<br />
Melbourne Vic. 3001)<br />
Telephone: 63 0361<br />
Director Department of Labor and Immigration<br />
Australian Government Centre<br />
Chifley Square<br />
Sydney, N. S. W. 2000<br />
Telephone: 20343<br />
Director Department of Labor and Immigration<br />
151 Flinders Street<br />
Melbourne, Vic. 3000<br />
Telephone: 654 3011<br />
Director Department of Labor and Immigration<br />
167 Eagle Street<br />
Brisbane, Old. 4000<br />
( P0 Box 1382<br />
Brisbane, Old. 4001)<br />
Telephone: 33 7011<br />
Director Department of Labor and Immigration<br />
99 Currie Street<br />
Adelaide, S. A. 5000<br />
( P0 Box 2299<br />
Adelaide, S. A. 5001) Director Department of Labor and Immigration<br />
Victoria Centre<br />
2 St George's Terrace<br />
Perth, W. A. 6000<br />
( P0 Box R 1273<br />
Perth, W. A. 6001)<br />
Telephone: 23 0391<br />
Officer-in-Charge<br />
Department of Labor and Immigration<br />
CMIL Building<br />
University Avenue<br />
Canberra City, A. C. T. 2600<br />
( P0 Box 399<br />
Canberra City, A. C. T. 2601)<br />
Telephone: 48 0511<br />
Director Department of Labor and Immigration<br />
Australian Government Centre<br />
188 Collins Street<br />
Hobart, Tas. 7000<br />
( P0 Box 585F<br />
Hobart, Tas. 7001)<br />
Telephone: 20 5011<br />
Officer-in-Charge<br />
Department of Labor and Immigration<br />
Mitchell Street<br />
Darwin, N. T.<br />
( P0 Box 495<br />
Darwin, N. T. 5794)<br />
Telephone: 89 8911<br />
Telephone: 51 0441 On matters concerning health, medical and first aid services<br />
in employment, contact should be made with the Director-<br />
General of Health at the following address:<br />
Director-General of Health<br />
Department of Health<br />
( P0 Box 100<br />
Woden, A. C. T. 2602)<br />
Telephone: Canberra 81 8411 </p>
<p>INDEX ACCIDENTS Investigation, 13.1<br />
Prevention, 4.14<br />
Records, 13.1<br />
ADVICE TO EMPLOYEES, 9.8<br />
BUILDINGS Safety aspects, 6.2<br />
CHEMICAL AGENTS ( HARMFUL) 6.2.9, 9.1-9.6<br />
COMMUNICATIONS, ADEQUATE MEANS OF, 6.2.11<br />
CONFINED SPACES, 6.3,9.7<br />
EMERGENCY EXITS, 6.2.7<br />
EMPLOYEES Obligations, 2.2<br />
EQUIPMENT Emergency use, 11.5<br />
Firefighting, 6.2.8, 10.2<br />
Maintenance, 11.4<br />
Rescue, 6.28<br />
Types and Specifications, 11.2<br />
EVACUATION, 10.3<br />
EXPLOSION RISKS, 10.1<br />
FIRE FIGHTING EQUIPMENT, 6.2.8, 10.2<br />
FIRE RESISTANCE, 6.2.8<br />
FIRE RISKS, 10.1<br />
FIRST AID SERVICES, 2.1.10, 12<br />
FURNITURE AND FITTINGS<br />
Resistance to harmful agents, 6.2.13<br />
GUARDING, 7.3<br />
HARMFUL AGENTS, 6.2.9, 9.1-9.6<br />
HEAD OFFICERS<br />
Obligations, 2.1, 3<br />
HYGIENE, OCCUPATIONAL, 9 INJURIES Records, 2.1.11, 13.2<br />
ISOLATED SITUATIONS<br />
Employee protection, 6.4<br />
LIGHTING, 6.2.5<br />
MACHINERY, PLANT AND EQUIPMENT<br />
Safety measures, 7.1-7.3<br />
PROTECTIVE EQUIPMENT, USE OF, 2.1.9, 11<br />
RESCUE EQUIPMENT, 6.2.8<br />
SAFETY AND HEALTH COMMITTEES, 4.1.2<br />
SAFETY POLICY, 3, 4.1.1<br />
SAFETY CO-ORDINATION,<br />
SANITARY INSTALLATIONS, 6.2.12<br />
SCREENING OF EQUIPMENT, 7.3<br />
SUPERVISION, TRAINING, 8.3-8.4<br />
VENTILATION, 6.2.6<br />
WORKPLACES Safety aspects, 6.2<br />
RM75/ 301 33 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
