<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9060</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP INTERVIEW WITH KERRY OBRIEN, LATELINE, ABC TV 29 NOVEMBER 1993</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/11/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009060.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J K~ EATING, MP<br />
INTERVIEW WNTH KERRY O'BRIEN, LATELINE, ABC TV<br />
29 NOVEMBER 1993<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
KOB: Paul Keating before we go to the broad thrust of this interview I'd like<br />
to start with a couple of issues that are running at the moment, firstly<br />
your dispute with Malaysia's Dr Mahathir. Do you now regret your<br />
comments in Seattle that Dr Mahathir is recalcitrant and that you<br />
couldn't care less whether he comes to APEC meetings or not.<br />
PM: I think the important thing is that we've had no official indication from<br />
Malaysia, that they regard, I mean Dr Mahathir apparently has gone<br />
out of his way to say that he didn't require of me any apology and that<br />
his main interest is getting on with our relationship and that's my main<br />
Interest too. I had a very good talk with him in Limassol during the<br />
CHOGM meeting and since then I wrote to him the day before I left for<br />
the APEC meeting saying we would look at his problem with the Indo-<br />
Chinese boat people to see if Australia could take some of those<br />
people so it was a friendly environment. Since then I have done<br />
nothing except to keep this relationship on a reasonable keel and I<br />
think that is what he wants too.<br />
KOB: In Seattle, the body language that was coming from you that matched<br />
the words was one of frustration. What was coming from you was<br />
frustration, it was like I couldn't care less.<br />
P M We have got Senator Cook going there this week, and Senator Ray.<br />
So, from the Government's point of view we are showing every<br />
willingness to maintain a good businesslike, and might I say, cordial<br />
relationship.<br />
KOB: But that wasn't reflected in those comments. I am curious to know<br />
what sparked them. It surely wasn't just a question... 7 </p>
<p>IL 2<br />
PM: Well I had been asked too many times. I must of been asked this<br />
question I am not the only APEC attendee I am not quite sure<br />
whether every other APEC attendee was asked as often as I was<br />
asked in the previous month or so, about Dr Mahathir's attendance.<br />
KOB: But not every other nation has as tricky a relationship as Australia has<br />
with Malaysia, as sensitive a relationship as Australia has with<br />
Malaysia, and your Government has done a great deal over the last<br />
year or two years to try and heal previous wounds, and previous<br />
perceived slights, haven't you now put that at risk? And isn't that,<br />
given the stress that you yourself are placing on the importance of<br />
trading relations with countries like Malaysia, isn't it somewhat self<br />
indulgent?<br />
PM: Well we are not hearing, there have been no requests from the<br />
Malaysian Government, they are not saying ' we require an apology".<br />
This is all basically..<br />
KOB: What are the signs coming from Malaysia? He says he is<br />
disappointed.<br />
PM: there is a whole lot of basic sort of media chatter about it...<br />
KOO: Dr Mahathir himself said he was disappointed.<br />
PM: in the business of feigned indignation. There are a lot of hard things<br />
been said about Australia and Australians. Now, I don't take weekly or<br />
monthly Indignation at it, I don't go requiring statements to . be made, I<br />
don't go expressing disappointment. That is part of, I think, part of the<br />
rough and tumble of national and international life, and I think that is<br />
fair enough. But the key thing is, Is the core relationship here good<br />
and working well? I think it is.<br />
K01B So when you say " feigned Indignation" you believe that sometimes Dr<br />
Mahathir's expressions about Australia are feigned?<br />
PM: Let me say this, let me leave Dr Mahathir out of it. Most of the<br />
comments that come from Malaysia come from Ministers other than the<br />
Prime Minister, and from other people in the Party and the press.<br />
K01B: But if one of your senior Ministers were to make a public expression<br />
about one of our neighbouring countries. That neighbouring country<br />
would be quite within its rights to see that as an expression of the<br />
Government. So why Isn't it an expression of the Government when<br />
some of Dr Mahathir's Ministers are personally insulting to you, and Dr<br />
Mahathir hasn't distanced himself from those comments. He hasn't<br />
reiterated them, but he hasn't distanced himself from them.<br />
2 0. NOV. IJO 10; 1( NU. V14 r-V4f14 </p>
<p>TEL: 3<br />
PM: He has been given a chance to endorse them, and he Seems to have<br />
let that opportunity go by. I think that Is a sensible sign, and I am<br />
prepared to say and confirm my wish that the relationship continue as<br />
it has been going and our ministers will be there.<br />
KOB: It was reported on the front pages of this morning's papers that Or<br />
Mahathir had privately supported a boycott on some Australian<br />
business. Now, If those signals are real, Is it worth you swallowing<br />
some pride and apologising to Or Mahathir for any perceived slight?<br />
PMV: Well should there be a matching set of multiple apologies for the<br />
slights against Australia? I mean should there? Do you think there<br />
should be? I am asking you, that is what you are putting to me.<br />
KOB: Well I am asking you. Is that how you weigh it up?<br />
PM. No, I am just saying that in international affairs one has got to basically<br />
roll with some of these things, and just get on with the main business.<br />
KGB: Another domestic issue that is running at the moment is Sports<br />
Minister, Ros Kelly's, $ 30 million hand-outs for sporting facilities.<br />
PM: Kerry, look, I am here to discuss the broad picture, I think that was the<br />
basis of the Invitation, not to go down the highways and byways. Was<br />
it or not? Let's make that clear.<br />
KGB: But as I have said to you, well what it was to do was to talk about your<br />
Government in this past year and to look ahead. And there is a<br />
contemporary Issue running, which Is running quite strongly about one<br />
of your senior Cabinet Ministers, and an Auditor-Generals report about<br />
whether she was pork barrelling in handing out $ 30 million. Are you<br />
saying you simply won't discuss it?<br />
PM: No, no. I am not saying that at all. I am just saying that there has got<br />
to be a nook or cranny of the Australian media who we can get across<br />
some of these smaller issues to the bigger Issues. Hopefully this<br />
program remains one of them.<br />
KOB: Well thlere are many people who regard that as quite a significant<br />
issue, and I am prepared to spend about two minutes out of thirty on<br />
this, if you are?<br />
PM: The answer is, those are three or four members of the Opposition<br />
frontbench and half of one side of the corridors press gallery.<br />
KOO: And the Auditor-General?<br />
PM: Look, the Auditor-General is on the record, his position has been very<br />
clear about this. T2EL9:. Nov. 93 18: 17 No. 014 P. 03/ 14 </p>
<p>I tLL;-7i 17D73 i~<br />
4<br />
KOB: How do you read his position? Do you say he has no concerns about<br />
the way that money was granted?<br />
PM: There was no basis for political bias.<br />
KOB: He didn't say that Ms Kelly's office asking her Department for details of<br />
electorates In which grant applications were located, but then not<br />
being prepared to put that request in writing, he didn't say that that<br />
would then open the way and lead to speculation about motives behind<br />
the selection process.<br />
PM: But Auditor-Generals will always provide those sort of comments in<br />
annual reports. I mean the whole issue is about the propensity of<br />
these things to go to marginal or Labor electorates. Generally these<br />
are where facilities are the least best.<br />
KOB: Yes, but you had a situation where in the first two years of this<br />
particular program $ 20 million was spent, but in the three months to<br />
January 1993, just before you declared, called that election, a further<br />
million was allocated, most of it to marginal electorates. And that<br />
was a program that was supposed to run until the middle of next year,<br />
suddenly it is all allocated in three months against all previous<br />
practice.<br />
PM: So, what's the point?<br />
KOSB-The question that has been raised is, was it pure coincidence, the<br />
timing, and the difference in the pattern that in the course of three<br />
months Ros Kelly slots in $ 30 million of sports grants, questions are<br />
asked in the process of determining those grants about what<br />
electorates they fall in, and the implication has been drawn that it is<br />
pork-barrel ling. Now, you are saying that it is not pork-barrelling, and<br />
you have full confidence in the way that Ros Kelly did it?<br />
PM; I have full confidence in Ros Kelly, one. Two, there is an enormous<br />
paucity of facilities in sport and recreation facilities in this country.<br />
This program has been an important part of helping it. A lot of<br />
municipal authorities just don't have the financial horse power to do it,<br />
the sporting organisations don't, and I think a lot of these localities that<br />
have been mentioned should take note of the Liberal Party's attitude<br />
that they resent these funds being spent in those particular areas and<br />
they should well long remember the fact that the Liberal Party has not<br />
had this premium on supporting amateur sports.<br />
KOB: There's also the matter of the Senate inquiry Into Conrad Black's<br />
increased acquisition to the Fairfax Group, it was sparked by that. Is it<br />
beneath your dignity to attend that Senate inquiry? lb; lf NO. vi4 r. u4iiq </p>
<p>PM: Look, Kerry, let me just endorse what Laurie Oakes wrote a week or so<br />
ago, saying it is about time we required a new you know, millions<br />
of tax payers dollars being spent on basically wasted and worthless<br />
inquiries. Now, I am not going to be part of that charade, I made that<br />
very clear. I can't remember any other Prime Minister appearing<br />
before a Senate Committee, and any way they are loaded terms, they<br />
are rigged terms. I mean the Democrats didn't stand Dr Hewson up,<br />
the terms were to be Mr Keating's conversations with Mr Black, Dr<br />
Hoiwson's conversation with Mr Black. The Liberals twisted the<br />
Democrats arms, they gave up on the fast term of reference. Now,<br />
Dr Hewson's views about foreign investment in the print media, not his<br />
conversations with Conrad Black. So, this has been put together by<br />
the Liberal Party and the Democrats on terms to suit Or Hewson, so<br />
why should I bother with him?<br />
KOB: Did you as Conrad Black wrote in his book, when you met him, or<br />
when he met you In January of 1992 just after you had become Prime<br />
Minister, did you say to him that you thought the previous Government<br />
decision to limit his holding in Fairfax to 15 per cent as quote, " shitty<br />
and outrageous"?<br />
PM: No, I did not at all.<br />
KOO: And did you indicate to him as he says you did, that he should just give<br />
you six months to allow things to settle down and you would sort it out?<br />
PM: No. Look, I was not in the Government during the time Conrad Black<br />
was given his authority to go to 14.9 per cent. That was all done while<br />
I was on the back bench. His case to me was he couldn't manage the<br />
company on 14.9 per cent, now In the end the Government accepted<br />
that view. That Fairfax needed management, it needed capital, it<br />
needed a new printing plant, and it needed that managerial sense to<br />
-be brought to It. We had to weigh those, juxtapose those against<br />
whether how much of the stock should go, and whether the national<br />
Interest should be protected, that is whether or not foreign interest in<br />
these two major broadsheets and financial newspapers should be less<br />
than 50 per cent. As it turned out the Government decided that. I<br />
mean, the core thing here, the hub bub is caused by John Hewson.<br />
Now, Conrad Black told me expressly on a number of occasions, he<br />
said, John Hewson has made it very clear to me that he is completely<br />
relaxed about how much of the stock we own, they don't regard foreign<br />
Investment as an issue at all. And I said what, he will let you go to 100<br />
per cent, and he said yes, but I don't need 100 per cent, I just need a<br />
majority of the stock. I repeated that to a lunch of Fairfax editors late<br />
last year where there was Mike Steketee, and Ross Gittens and Max<br />
Walsh, and hosted by Mr Mullholland. So, I mean I am not just wise<br />
after the event, I said it at the time when it wasn't in a sense<br />
newsworthy. d-Z I I U V .7% V A V -A I 11W a-</p>
<p>I V L. 6<br />
KOB: But when you had that January meeting With Conrad Black, you didn't<br />
indicate to him that if he gave you some time you would fix it, you<br />
would get it up to 25 per cent, because you thought 15 per cent was<br />
outrageous?<br />
PM; No. Why would anyone think 15 per cent was outrageous? Here was<br />
a foreign person, foreign company coming along getting 14.9 per cent<br />
of John Fairfax and Son and told by the Government in the press<br />
statement Mr Willis issued that was all they would get. Now, what I did<br />
say was that we would consider some increase which would<br />
consolidate his management. But the core matter here, Kerry, is that<br />
John Hewson attacking me and the Cabinet for agreeing to give<br />
Conrad Black 25 per cent of the stock in John Fairfax and Son when<br />
he was prepared to pass complete control of the company away.<br />
KOB: But what he is particularly attacking you on beyond the 25 per cent is<br />
on the basis on what Conrad Black said, that you had promised him<br />
that you would entertain going higher if the Fairfax reporting of this last<br />
election was balanced.<br />
PM: No, look, in fact Mr Black raised the question of balance. The only<br />
matter I raised was the question of accuracy and reporting. He said to<br />
me in the first conversation that he wanted to move the Herald and the<br />
Age more towards the British broadsheet standard of accuracy. And I<br />
said to him this is a good thing, this needs to happen, there should be<br />
more presentation of news and less of views. Comment that a news<br />
copy should be news copy Where the reader has a chance to read.<br />
That was the matter I raised. Not In fact about the balance, but<br />
someone asked me on what basis do you get a right to consider the<br />
balance.<br />
KOB: And you said because, I am Prime Minister.<br />
PM; We, the Cabinet, were the deciding authority, that's why.<br />
KOB: On deciding balance in newspapers?<br />
PM: No, that is when we decided despite the opposition we received from<br />
the Herald and the Age, editorially, and news management terms in<br />
the election campaign, when we had to decide at the Cabinet whether<br />
we would allow Black to take from 14.9 per cent to 25 per cent. That<br />
was decided by this Cabinet.<br />
KOB: Ok. When you were talking about accuracy on your version of these<br />
various conversations that you have had with him, his own accuracy<br />
leaves a great deal to be desired. He would probably say yours does.<br />
PM: Well I think It ( Black's) does. May be I have missed something, Kerry,<br />
who should be deciding these matters? The man outside Hoyts? I<br />
4CV I U V. V ñ O. L -IF I NU VJL4 1 V </p>
<p>I LL-7<br />
mean who is the person that decides these things? It is not the<br />
Government?<br />
KOB: it Is not a question of who decides, it is a ques tion of how things are<br />
decided, and what the perceptions are of how they are decided,<br />
perceptions that others have drawn?<br />
PM: Well what are the facts? The facts are that this Government has<br />
limited telegraph newspapers interest in John Fairfax and Sons to<br />
per cent of the voting stock, fact one. Fact two, John Hewson on<br />
behalf of the Coalition promised Black he could take his stock to full<br />
control of John Fairfax and Son, that is the objective fact. Yet he has<br />
had the hide, Hewson, to try and pin me, but now of course the game<br />
Is changing, and he Is going to be appearing before the Senate<br />
Committee and he will be asked a few hard questions.<br />
KOB:-And you are not.<br />
PM: No, I am not.<br />
KOB: You are going to say at the end of this that we have spent too much<br />
time on it, but I have got one more question on Conrad Black, did you<br />
really tell him in apparently expansive mode on the verandah of<br />
Kirribilli House overlooking the Sydney skyline after that January<br />
dinner, that amongst other things you had promoted the interest of the<br />
entrepreneurial classes against the excessive appetites of the Labor<br />
unions.<br />
PM: Well, that's Conrad Conrad is a wordsmith.<br />
KOB: Well, behind the words he is saying that you took pride in the fact that<br />
you have promoted the entrepreneurs against the excessive appetites<br />
of the unions.<br />
PM:-Of course I didn't say that. Why believe that text? I mean Conrad is a<br />
wordsmith and a romantic and he writes all these things and obviously<br />
he likes people to know that he..<br />
KOB: He also thinks that you are a great Prime Minister and he is an<br />
extremely conservative person in terms of his political views.<br />
PM: He is more perceptive perhaps than we might of thought he was<br />
originally.<br />
KOB: From his conservative perspective he thinks you are not bad. I wonder<br />
a lot of labor people would be a bit discomforted by that.<br />
PM: Let me just tell you this. That my conversations with Conrad Black, like<br />
any conversations I've had with any other persons similar to that are<br />
29. Nov. 93 IU: l( NO. U14 V. Ur/ 14 </p>
<p>TEL a<br />
entirely proper and juxtaposed against Australia's national interest and<br />
I have always taken the view that in these big broad sheet newspapers<br />
that our national interest is a real and live issue and we didn't pass off<br />
to Conrad Black control of John Fairfax and Sons. That is the key<br />
point. That is the key decision of the Cabinet and the person who<br />
wanted to give control away willy-nilly in his arrogance before the last<br />
election was John Hewson taking foreign visitors, the next Prime<br />
Minister taking foreign visitors. Oh yes, you want John Fairfax and<br />
Sons you can go and have it.<br />
KOB: Well he is on tomorrow night and he will no doubt put a different view.<br />
After two years in the job..<br />
PM: Let me just say, Black has made it very clear in his text on a number of<br />
occasions what he said. He made it clear to me. I repeated it in<br />
December in the Fairfax board room, so iet's pin that one.<br />
KOB; After two years In the job, how would you like to think people perceive<br />
. you and your Prime Ministership?<br />
PM: That I am continuing to hammer home the issues that will set Australia<br />
up in the 21 st century.<br />
KOB; Well, if we take one of those issues Mabo. You have got the Greens<br />
getting In the way again of what you want with that legislation, so they<br />
appear to be intransigent at this stage on that and it would also seem<br />
from public feedback from opinion polls that to the extent that you have<br />
tried to make this break through on Mabo that you have not carried the<br />
bulk of national opinion with you. You have not really carried the<br />
people of Australia with you otherwise why would so many of them be<br />
saying that they want a referendum?<br />
P M. Well, you wouldn't know. Maybe they want a referendum to guarantee<br />
that Aboriginal people have title to their land. Some would want a<br />
referendum to knock native title over. The only time we put a<br />
referendum about whether the Commonwealth should have power over<br />
issues In relation to Aboriginal welfare, it was carried in 1967 and I<br />
have got no reason to believe other than understanding in the broad<br />
Australian community about the need to right these wrongs and to be<br />
able to address Aboriginal policy, Aboriginal issues is firmer today than<br />
it was in 1967.<br />
KOB: How are you going to get around the Greens this time?<br />
PM: I think the Greens are standing four square against the best interests<br />
of the Aboriginal and Islander community of this country.<br />
KOB: But they have got two pretty crucial votes? T2EL9: . Nov. 93 18: 17 No. 014 P. 08/ 14 </p>
<p>I LL<br />
PM: Well, in the end they have got to cast them.<br />
KOB: How long can you afford to wait. I mean in the end you have to wait for<br />
as long as it will take?<br />
PM: We will have to wait until the Senate votes on it. But, in the end<br />
nobody can go hiding. They are going to have to sit on the side of the<br />
chamber where they believe their interests are, but if they sit on the<br />
side of the chamber of the Coalition they will have the result they will<br />
have to live with it for the rest of their days.<br />
KOB: How will you deal with the Greens next year in terms of not just Mabo,<br />
but every important piece of legislation. There is every prospect that<br />
they are going to stick their heads up and make it extremely difficult for<br />
you.<br />
PM: I think the same basis we do with the Democrats. That is, we argue<br />
the case about the value of the legislation as we did with the Budget<br />
and we will do that again.<br />
KOB: What is your personal bottom line onMedicare. You have effectively<br />
stopped Graham Richardson from recommending an increase in the<br />
levy for wealthier tax payers who refused to take out private health<br />
insurance. How else will you solve the problems of hospital queues<br />
and declining private health Insurance?<br />
PM: I don't think even Graham believes that a levy is going to solve<br />
anything like the problem. He himself says it is only a contributor and<br />
a fairly minor contributor. There are other strategies for dealing with<br />
that. He spoke about those over the weekend. He Is talking those<br />
strategies through with some of the interested groups in this and also<br />
with the Caucus and at the right time, not too far from now, he will<br />
bring the matter to Cabinet.<br />
KOO.-But you did head that one off at the past didn't you, you didn't wait for It<br />
to come to Cabinet to have a discussion about that?<br />
PM: Well, it had been thrown around the public debate by Graham amongst<br />
others for some months.<br />
KOB: Well yes and you.<br />
PMV. No, no, not by me until I finally said something about it. I don't want to<br />
see a health system where there Is a well off people's health system<br />
and the poor people's health system. Where one breaks away from<br />
the other, so we end up with a welfarebased wealth system where the<br />
best surgeons and practitioners are not participants and the well off,<br />
well to do health system where anyone who can afford it gets the best<br />
care. The great thing about Medicare Is that it is stuck together as one<br />
z-10L Iru 4r 71 </p>
<p>ILsystem,<br />
It Is a universal. Universality Is not just an easy word Kerry.<br />
Universality means that the poorest person in Australia can go into a<br />
hospital and get a very good surgeon to perform work on them and<br />
alternatively where they can go to the general practitioner of their<br />
choice. I don't want to see that get to the point where we have got<br />
basically a degraded public health system and degraded and<br />
degrading and moving away a private health system. But nor does<br />
Graham Richardson might I add. But it is a matter of how we tailor the<br />
system so that those who would otherwise seek protection by private<br />
Insurance are able to get it at reasonable premiums.<br />
KOB: OK, we are getting close to time and I have got a number of issues I<br />
would still like to get through with you so maybe we can try and do<br />
them as briefly as possible. On the republic what is a reasonable<br />
time to allow discussions in the Cabinet sub-committee on the Turnbull<br />
recommendations before the full Cabinet considers recommendations<br />
from that sub-committee?<br />
PM: We are not rushing to a referendum on this, I made that pretty clear.<br />
We have got until 2000 2001 in terms of our partys policy to make<br />
such a shift and I think that is going to require a fairly relaxed and<br />
protracted debate in the community. But, we have now an important<br />
document from Mr Turnbull's committee which really does shed some<br />
light upon what needs to happen for the various modes of such a<br />
change. Where before no such authoritative document existed.<br />
KOB: But will the Cabinet sub-committee come at some point during next<br />
year, come up with some recommendations for Cabinet to consider on<br />
the basis of that committee?<br />
PM: I don't know. I think that we will proselytise in favour of an Australian<br />
republic because in the end the identity of Australia, can only in the<br />
end, be represented by Australians and by an Australian as our head<br />
of state. I think that is self evident. And it is on those matters, I think<br />
but what you are portending Is a Cabinet discussion leading to a<br />
Cabinet submission leading to a referendum sort of, A B C.<br />
KOB: No, not necessarily.<br />
PM: That Is exactly right in that case.<br />
KOB: But you still have a commitment ultimately to a referendum?<br />
PM: This can only be changed by the Australian people of course. Of<br />
course I do.<br />
KOB: More likely than not in the next term or am I going too far ahead for<br />
you? Z O. NUV.* JO 10-i( NO. U14 r. IU/ 14 </p>
<p>ItLit<br />
PMV: I don't know, but certainly we would like to see it in place before the<br />
turn of thie century and It ought to be In place because the country<br />
cannot I don't think, culturally draw Itself together and make the kind of<br />
change it needs both internally and externally being at all uncertain<br />
about itself or not prepared to see itself governed in every way by<br />
Australians.<br />
KOB: Do you accept some wisdom In the comments of some in the<br />
republican movement that your high profile in the game has been to<br />
some degree divisive and it has lead to political partisanship which has<br />
damaged the republican push?<br />
PM: Kerry look, before the Government took this on as an Issue, made it an<br />
Issue in the election campaign, an element of the policy speech this<br />
was a coffee and after dinner mint discussion.<br />
KOB: OK, next point. I am told that the long-term unemployment task force<br />
does favour some sort of tax levy to directly fund more employment<br />
and training Initiatives. The ACTU made public a very strong<br />
submission to that affect. What is your latest thinking on that?<br />
PM: Well, I haven't got the report yet and I can't you are able to confirm<br />
you say what's in the report, I can't so I have got to wait until I see it. I<br />
think the key thing Is..<br />
KOB: But you have seen the reports of the ACTU submission. What do you<br />
think of that?<br />
PM: Well, I haven't seen the ACIU submIssion myself.<br />
KOB: Well reports.<br />
PM: I have seen reports of it that is fine. I understand where they are<br />
coming from. The key thing is the Government said, I said In the<br />
election campaign we would not leave the unemployed behind. That<br />
is, we wouldn't march on as a society and forget them and marginalise<br />
them and that I think, is the important point. The Government will have<br />
unemployment and dealing with it and particularly long-term<br />
unemployment as a key objective In the course of this parliament and<br />
the receipt of this task force report will be central to our consideration<br />
Of it.<br />
KOB: You point out so often that your interest as Prime Minister lies In the<br />
big picture and yes, there are signs of some good things on the<br />
horizon in some important areas of the economy at least. If it is such a<br />
big, important picture out there and these really are the watershed<br />
years that you describe them as, what on earth are you doing also<br />
worrying about pictures hanging on the Cabinet wall and what sort of<br />
pictures you should have or worrying about the style of table for the<br />
I LL. . reUV. V 10-1ñ r ru. uig </p>
<p>12<br />
Lodge to the extent that that diverts the public from what you are on<br />
about?<br />
PM: I am not diverting the public about this, it is this bitter Opposition. The<br />
bitterness started in 1975 while ever the Labor party was in Opposition<br />
it was there laying fallow. We have now succeeded at five general<br />
elections, we are eleven years in office and the bitterness that<br />
pervades Dr Hewson and his colleagues is so profound that..<br />
KOB:-But aren't you handing them the material?<br />
PM: No, no. Please don't talk over me. W~ hat they did is make these things<br />
an Issue in the Parliament every day at Question Time and if they are<br />
therefore they are public issues. They are not for me.<br />
KOB: But can you understand why large clumps of the electorate would react<br />
very negatively to an Image of a Prime Minister in a time which is still<br />
very tough out there for many Australians, still nearly a million people<br />
unemployed, this image of a Prime Minister arguing about a special<br />
purchase of a particular kind of bird for the Cabinet wall.<br />
PM: But, I'm not arguing about these things. These were literally two or<br />
three minute discussions at some stage in my life over the last twelve<br />
months a couple of minutes.<br />
KOB: But why should you spend that amount of money $ 80,000 or $ 100,000<br />
whatever it was on a particular kind of painting for your walls?<br />
PM: Basically because the Cabinet room was unfumnished. As simple as<br />
that. People come there, look around and the place whose<br />
responsibility is it for those simple tasks? Where is the authority to do<br />
anything? And it basically comes from the occupants of the executive<br />
building of which I am the head. Remember this though Kerry, this is a<br />
five minute conversation, now the fact that John Hewson without a<br />
policy, embittered over his defeat in 1993, all that front bench of his<br />
from Howard down absolutely embittered by the fact that they are<br />
facing another term of Opposition want to have Mr Connolly rifling<br />
around through these Issues, It is their priorities which have been<br />
chosen, but they will have to be judged on them. Remember this, the<br />
day that I presented the Mabo legislation and the day before I flew to<br />
the APEC meeting, I had to deal with these issues in Question Time. It<br />
is Dr Hewson who you will be seeing tomorrow night you ought to put<br />
these questions on to where is his policy framework? Where are the<br />
big issues?<br />
KOS. OK, but you as Prime Minister and as a politician and a leader of a<br />
political party have to deal yourself with the public perceptions of your<br />
style of prime ministership and on the one hand you want us all to<br />
focus on what you are doing with APEC and what you are doing with </p>
<p>I L. L. 13<br />
Mabo and what you are doing on Industrial relations and on what you<br />
are doing with the republic and all these other things.<br />
PM: And inflation and growth and all the other matters.<br />
KOB: Well let me put to you the kind of perceptions that are coming through<br />
and yes they are Liberal studies; yes they are Liberal surveys, but It is<br />
private Liberal research qualitative and quantitative that has been<br />
done largely in the lead up to the South Australian election which says<br />
tehlaitti stt'h, e'by uirledcinogrd ad peaslacrciep tifoonr sy ooufr syeolfu', ' liinkteo le'praonwte ra nddr unnakr'r, ow'im mpeinrdiael'd,<br />
when you are crossed', In short hand used to making that these<br />
people, the electorate used to make allowance for your aloofness and<br />
arrogance because they respected you as Intelligent, dynamic and<br />
unafraid there is a couple of words you might like, but in short you<br />
are seen as a man who can't manage power.<br />
PM: If you believe Liberal party research Kerry, you are off your head. The<br />
same people who are parroting this stuff were putting that around<br />
before the last election how they were going to walk in. The federal<br />
secretary of the Liberal party is one of the best assets the Labor party<br />
has and it is mainly because of this sort of nonsense. Don't take any<br />
notice of it. In the end, the public look for value, they know that this<br />
Government is trying to make Australia's place In Asia with APEC; they<br />
know we are trying to do the big things about our national identity<br />
including with Mabo; they know we have succeeded in restarting the<br />
economy, it is now growing at about 3 per cent; they know we have<br />
broken the back of Australian inflation for the first time In two decades;<br />
they know we are going to deal with long term unemployment those<br />
things they know. They know we are going to protect their health<br />
system, that they know. And on the big issues it is only the big issues<br />
they vote in that ballot box, so all this stuff goes to the keeper and<br />
-while it Is interesting at the time and it is the stuff of press copy, I don't<br />
think it matters a tinkers cuss.<br />
KOO: OK, last question. Very serious this one. Why do your antique mates<br />
call you ' mona'?<br />
PM:-Well, it is just untrue. It is just another bit of nonsense.<br />
KOB: Oh, is that right?<br />
PM: That was a Valerie Lawson thing. * She dug that up, that was just<br />
nonsense as well.<br />
KOB: I know they certainly all have nicknames for each other. Did you miss<br />
out did you? I S~ I~ ZZP. riUV. V, . LO. Lr rNu. vi' r. 1014 </p>
<p>mLL. ZV. 114UV.: P,. JL 0 If VNI U IA F-m 4. L I~<br />
14<br />
PM: They do, but I don't have any as far as I know and I'm quite sure I<br />
would know at this time, but of course that is all part of the Colour of<br />
Queen Street or ' Konigstrasse' as they call it in the eastern suburbs.<br />
But you know, the Herald being middle class as it has been, the journal<br />
of the yupples, this Is right down the main street of yuppiedom that and<br />
the Financial Review and that is basically why these sort of pieces are<br />
written.<br />
KOB: Paul Keating, we are out of time. Thanks for talking with us.<br />
PM: Thank you.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
