<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>17784</transcript-id>
    <title>Groundbreaking solar energy project announced in Queensland</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/04/2011</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
The Gillard Labor Government has today given the green light to one of the biggest solar thermal projects in the world.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Julia Gillard today confirmed funding to build a solar energy system on the site of an existing coal-fired power station near Chinchilla in Queensland.</p>
<p>When built, the $104.7 million Kogan Creek Solar Boost project will be the largest integration of solar technology with a coal-fired power station in the world.</p>
<p>The project, which relies on Australian-pioneered solar thermal energy technology, is an excellent example of the type of clean energy we want to encourage in Australia.</p>
<p>The integration of the innovative solar technology at the Kogan Creek power station will save 35,000 tonnes of greenhouse gas from entering the atmosphere every year.</p>
<p>With an extra 44,000 megawatt hours of electricity produced a year, Kogan Creek will continue to meet the growing energy needs of Queenslanders and Australians  -  but in a cleaner, more efficient way.</p>
<p>The project will create up to 120 jobs when building work starts later this year.  The technology supplier, AREVA Solar, plans to manufacture the solar hardware locally.</p>
<p>The Australian Government has committed $34.9 million to help build the project.</p>
<p>The go-ahead means solar-generated electricity from Kogan Creek will be powering Queensland homes and businesses by 2013.</p>
<p>Putting a price on carbon will help drive the investment we need in renewable and clean energy technologies such as solar thermal at Kogan Creek.</p>
<p>Further investment will continue to help make industrial-scale solar power more feasible, affordable and viable  -  which will benefit all Australians.</p>
<p>The Australian Government is supporting renewable and clean energy technologies through the $5 billion Clean Energy Initiative. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
