<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10898</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                 THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                 LAUNCH OF THE PRIME MINISTERIAL YOUTH HOMELESSNESS TASKFORCE REPORT</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/12/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE................................................................................................</p>
<p>Well thank you very much Captain Eldridge, to the Reverend Dr Bill</p>
<p> Lawton, to my ministerial colleagues, the leaders of many community</p>
<p> and welfare organisations here today, members of the taskforce, ladies</p>
<p> and gentleman.</p>
<p>I start by expressing my gratitude to David Eldridge and to the members</p>
<p> of the taskforce for delivering the report that I launched today.</p>
<p> This exercise grew out of a commitment I made in a speech I delivered</p>
<p> to ACOSS late in 1995 as Opposition Leader, to try and examine against</p>
<p> the background of concern being expressed by some in the community</p>
<p> that the processes relating to youth homelessness were not sufficiently</p>
<p> involving the families of young people who left home or were wanting</p>
<p> to leave home. I didn't approach it with too many preconceived</p>
<p> notions, I suppose all of us wherever we come from have preconceived</p>
<p> notions and it's a bit idle to pretend otherwise.</p>
<p>But I thought it would make a great deal of sense if in Government</p>
<p> we put together a group of men and women from both the community sector</p>
<p> and the Government to have another look at this issue. And indeed</p>
<p> within a couple of weeks of the Government being elected in 1996 I</p>
<p> called together a group of people and the taskforce was established.</p>
<p> And I'm delighted that Captain Eldridge assumed the chairmanship</p>
<p> of that taskforce and I want to personally thank him for the quite</p>
<p> remarkable job that he's done.</p>
<p>This taskforce and its recommendations give expression to part of</p>
<p> the Government's philosophical approach to welfare services and</p>
<p> support to the less advantaged in our community. In the address I</p>
<p> gave once again to ACOSS only a few weeks ago where I tried to set</p>
<p> out some of the pathways of the Government, in a philosophical sense,</p>
<p> towards welfare issues in our second term of Government, I did emphasise</p>
<p> that we saw the Government as having a very important and a very strategic</p>
<p> role, but we also saw a partnership between the Government and community</p>
<p> organisations and individuals as being very much at the core of the</p>
<p> delivery of more efficient and effective welfare services in the closing</p>
<p> years of this century and into the 21st century. One of</p>
<p> the crucial roles for Government I said on that occasion was to foster</p>
<p> a greater sense of individual moral obligation and duty amongst citizens</p>
<p> and to encourage individuals through there own actions and depth of</p>
<p> their conviction to give back to the community that looked after them.</p>
<p>Now this taskforce has completed its work and in launching the report</p>
<p> today I want to pay tribute to the input of both the Government's</p>
<p> dream and also the community's dream. Without in any way suggesting</p>
<p> that they are the only organisations that do magnificent work in the</p>
<p> community sector, I do of course acknowledge on the taskforce representatives</p>
<p> of the Salvation Army, the Society of St Vincent de Paul, the Wesley</p>
<p> Mission, and Anglicare. And those four organisations and many others</p>
<p> of course do absolutely superb work. And the personal side of welfare</p>
<p> in Australia would be quite different, would be much harsher, and</p>
<p> would be far less sensitive were it not for the ceaseless voluntary</p>
<p> work of magnificent organisations such as those four.</p>
<p>It is important, and I think it's appropriate that this report</p>
<p> be released shortly before Christmas because for most of us in the</p>
<p> community Christmas will be an opportunity of family renewal of family</p>
<p> gatherings of celebrating the happiness of family life and all it</p>
<p> means to us, and it means most to most of us. But there will be many</p>
<p> of our fellow Australians who won't have that same happy circumstance</p>
<p> and it's therefore appropriate on the eve of Christmas that we</p>
<p> release this report and hope that it does make some contribution towards</p>
<p> a better resolution of the challenges that face many in our community</p>
<p> who are trying very hard to grapple in very, very difficult situations.</p>
<p>The report is refreshingly nonjudgmental. The report is designed to</p>
<p> help people. It is realistic, it is not starry eyed, it is not ideologically</p>
<p> driven. But it does represent a number of central realities. And that</p>
<p> is there aren't too many people in Australian society who don't</p>
<p> want their family relationships to succeed. And there aren't</p>
<p> too many in our community who don't regard personal relationships</p>
<p> as the most important emotional support they have in their lives.</p>
<p> And if you start with those sorts of building blocks and you recognise</p>
<p> that putting families in the picture, which is the title of the report,</p>
<p> is a pretty sensible and logical starting point then I think you do</p>
<p> get some very sensible outcomes. There's an old saying of course</p>
<p> that prevention is better than cure and in a sense that old saying</p>
<p> has been the driving force to this report because what it's based</p>
<p> on is something that's quite new and that is early intervention.</p>
<p> It's not just a question of providing adequate support services</p>
<p> when families break up, or when young people find it intolerable to</p>
<p> remain at home, and in some cases that is plainly the truth.</p>
<p>Nobody who's had any contact at all with this field deny the</p>
<p> fact that in some cases there is no alternative other than for a young</p>
<p> person to leave home. But equally there are many cases where that</p>
<p> can be avoided. And what is, I think, very encouraging about this</p>
<p> report is that as a result of the pilots it was possible to identify</p>
<p> a number of very very significant things. And one the most important</p>
<p> things that it was possible to identify is that of those families</p>
<p> that were involved in the pilots carried out by the taskforce that</p>
<p> family reconciliation was achieved in around two-thirds of all cases</p>
<p> studied. And the positive outcomes include the return home of the</p>
<p> younger family member, acceptance by both parents that the young person</p>
<p> be afforded an appropriate degree of independence, and the creation</p>
<p> of viable support systems for young people that included a member</p>
<p> of their family. And of those young people who left home prior to</p>
<p> contacting a pilot project close to one third returned home to live</p>
<p> with one or both of their parents. And these were significant achievements</p>
<p> in very difficult personal circumstances and it was found that the</p>
<p> involvement of parents was important to the success of the early intervention</p>
<p> strategy.</p>
<p>I know one is used to the bombardment of statistics and comparisons</p>
<p> but some studies have suggested that in terms of costs and the cost</p>
<p> of picking up the pieces in areas such as this rather than preventing</p>
<p> the breakage in the first instance can be as high as 1,000 times greater</p>
<p> than the successful early intervention. And it is important with something</p>
<p> like this to recognise the personal and the economic. The two are</p>
<p> not mutually exclusive. The idea that you can have an effective welfare</p>
<p> system without a strong economy is, of course, nonsense. But the idea</p>
<p> that a strong economy is an end in itself is also a nonsense. The</p>
<p> purpose of economic policy and the purpose of strong economic policies</p>
<p> is to make a contribution towards building a better society. And a</p>
<p> compassionate caring community is the ultimate goal, surely, for all</p>
<p> of us whatever our economic views may be. We can differ and argue</p>
<p> about what is the best way of getting there but I don't think</p>
<p> we really differ and argue too much about that being the ultimate</p>
<p> goal.</p>
<p>So I want to say how very pleased I am as Prime Minister and how pleased</p>
<p> the Government is that we have seen such a successful working through</p>
<p> of the nation of a greater partnership between the Government, the</p>
<p> welfare agencies and individuals within our community. And in responding</p>
<p> to the work of the taskforce I want to announce forthwith that the</p>
<p> principal recommendation of the taskforce, which is a continuation</p>
<p> of the early intervention strategies, will be immediately supported</p>
<p> by the Government. And that we'll commit $60 million over the</p>
<p> next four years to July 2003 and this will provide 100 services of</p>
<p> the type piloted across the country where the programme will be fully</p>
<p> operational. And I am told that this will enable assistance to be</p>
<p> provided to around 12,000 cases a year involving some 7,000 young</p>
<p> people and 5,000 parents.</p>
<p>Now, the purpose of that support is to demonstrate the immediately</p>
<p> positive and supportive response of the Government to what has been</p>
<p> the model established by the work of this taskforce. We think it is</p>
<p> breaking new ground, we think it is breaking new ground in an extremely</p>
<p> positive way and I want to say to David Eldridge and what he said</p>
<p> about my own personal interest in this is right. I am personally interested</p>
<p> in it because I think it is something that the Government in a sensible,</p>
<p> caring, positive way can contribute drawing on the expertise and the</p>
<p> care and the responsibility of great community organisations. And</p>
<p> we really do, all of us, have to pool our resources.</p>
<p>And the Government has an important role and I take the opportunity</p>
<p> in case anybody would want to use what I have said today to misconstrue</p>
<p> our motives. We are not in the business of shifting to the community</p>
<p> sector our financial responsibility to care for the disadvantaged</p>
<p> in our community. That is the responsibility of government. It is</p>
<p> the responsibility of any government of any political stripe to maintain</p>
<p> a decent social security safety net. That is the Australian way. We</p>
<p> don't believe in allowing the unemployed to starve in the streets.</p>
<p> We might ask the unemployed through the principle of mutual obligation</p>
<p> to engage in work-for-the-dole programmes. We regard that as a reasonable</p>
<p> request of the community that affords comfort, sanctuary and support.</p>
<p> And in engaging the community sector far more as is our philosophy</p>
<p> that is not a way of us withdrawing financial support rather it is</p>
<p> a way of recognising the obvious and that is that the capacity of</p>
<p> the sort of organisations that David Eldridge and others here today</p>
<p> come from to understand and relate to the problem is the superior</p>
<p> than that of any in the community. And that's been a belief that</p>
<p> I have held for a long time. I hold it very strongly and it will underpin</p>
<p> the approach of my Government to welfare issues.</p>
<p>But there is an ongoing role for the Government and that is not diminished</p>
<p> rather it is expanded in cooperation with the role of the organisations</p>
<p> which are examples of which are represented on the taskforce. It is</p>
<p> a very good report. The other recommendations will be studied, they</p>
<p> are in their character ones that require a slightly longer term response.</p>
<p> But our immediate response on the day of the launch of the report</p>
<p> to its principal recommendation I hope will be seen as an earnest</p>
<p> of our determination to continue the excellent work to establish perhaps</p>
<p> in the fullness of time a new paradigm for responding to this issue</p>
<p> not only in Australia but perhaps something of an example to other</p>
<p> countries around the world.</p>
<p>Family life does lie at the heart of the Australian way, it's</p>
<p> important to all of us. A large majority of Australians are fortunate</p>
<p> in their family relationships. A minority, a significant minority,</p>
<p> try very hard to be happy in those relationships and don't always</p>
<p> succeed and some don't try at all. To those who try and don't</p>
<p> succeed they need our support and our compassion and our understanding</p>
<p> and they need our help. To those who don't try at all well perhaps</p>
<p> we should try doubly hard to persuade them of the merits of beginning</p>
<p> to try. But whatever the situation may be the work of this taskforce</p>
<p> will, I believe, make a great contribution. I support it very strongly.</p>
<p> I again thank David and all of the members of the taskforce for their</p>
<p> magnificent work. Thank you.</p>
<p> [ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
