<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3383</transcript-id>
    <title>REFERENCE TO THE TEXTILES AUTHORITY</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/09/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003383.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER PRESS STATEMENT NO. 323<br />
11 September 1974<br />
REFERENCE TO THE TEXTILES AUTHORITY<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr Whitlam, announced today<br />
that he had sent a reference to the Textiles Authority within<br />
the Industrie-s Assistance Commission covering yarns, knitted<br />
fabrics and towelling. Mr Whitlam said that this action was<br />
being taken as a result of high and rising levels of imports<br />
and an apparent total availability of such goods on the<br />
Australian market substantially in excess of previous levels'.<br />
The goods covered by the reference include acrylic<br />
and wool yarns, warp and weft knit fabrics, and terry towelling<br />
and towels. The reference seeks the advice of the Authority<br />
on whether action should be taken in terms of the GATT Textiles<br />
Arrangement to restrain imports into Australia. The Authority<br />
has been asked to report as soon as possible but within a<br />
maximum period of 60 days. Australia acceded to the GATT<br />
Arrangement earlier this year and as a result of a previous<br />
reference to the Textiles Authority, restraint negotiations have<br />
recently been concluded with several countries on certain<br />
articles of apparel. The Prime Minister emphasised that the question of<br />
whether it would be necessary to have negotiations on the goods<br />
in question with exporting countries would have to await<br />
examination of the recommeldations of the Textiles Authority.<br />
Recent press reports that the GoverE-mrcnt hmad already sought<br />
negotiations with the Japanese Government were not correct.<br />
However, the Japanese Government had been informed recently<br />
that a reference to the Textiles Authority was under consideration.<br />
This had been done in the spirit of the understandkng contained<br />
in the Japan/ Australia Commerce Agreement that where Japan has<br />
substantive trade in particular products Australia would inform<br />
Japan in advance before action such as that now decided upon was taken.<br />
Mr Whitlam said that, although it is not clear to the<br />
Government at this stage that restraint action on all the goods<br />
covered by this latest reference is necessary, he considered it<br />
important that the Government be able to take the initiative in<br />
having investigations undertaken so that action can be taken<br />
promptly if found necessary.<br />
The Prime Minister invited manufacturers and other<br />
interested parties to start preparing submissions now to the Authority<br />
which would announce arrangments for public hearings shortly. / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
The Prime Minister also pointed out that should<br />
the need for restraint action emerge from the report of the<br />
Textiles Authority, goods ordered overseas but not shipped would<br />
be subject to the terms of any export restraints that may be<br />
found necessary.<br />
CANBERRA. A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
