<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8312</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER AUSTRALIAN LABOR PARTY CENTEMARY CONFERENCE HOBART, 26 JUNE 1991</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/06/1991</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008312.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHECK AGAINAT DELIVERY EMRARnOED UTLDLVR<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
AUSTRALIAN LABOR PARTY CENTENARY CONFERENCE<br />
HOBART, 26 . JUNE 1991<br />
1 know that you all share with Me a sense of privilege on<br />
this special occasion.<br />
As delegates to this Centenary Conference, we meet as the<br />
representatives of Australia's most important and enduring<br />
force for change and progress an institution uniquely<br />
Australian in its creation and character, uniquely<br />
Australian in its values and in its achievement the<br />
Australian Labor Party.<br />
A proud name and a proud achievement over one hundred years<br />
one hundred years of co-operation with the Australian<br />
union movement which brought it into being; one hundred<br />
years of commitment to the cause of parliamentary democracy;<br />
one hundred years of struggle and service on behalf of the<br />
people of Australia.<br />
We meet as the representatives of Australia's greatest<br />
political Party the engine room of national renewal, the<br />
generators of change, the pioneers of reform.<br />
We are the Party that built Australia's system of social<br />
justice; the Party that created an industrial relations and<br />
wages system in the early years of this century; the Party<br />
that founded great institutions of our public life, not<br />
least the Commonwealth Bank; the Party that first provided<br />
the means by which Australia could defend itself; that led<br />
Australia through its most perilous days; the Party that<br />
after the Second World War rebuilt Australia and laid the<br />
foundations of modern Australian society; the Party that<br />
inaugurated a program of mass immigration that has changed<br />
and enlarged and enriched the very character of our, nation;<br />
the Party that in the 1970s gave new impetus to the quest<br />
for social justice.<br />
Our Party fixed its course by the light on the hill never<br />
wavering in our determination to reach that goal, but never<br />
fearing to modify our means and abandon old methods if that<br />
was necessary to make us more relevant and more effective in<br />
the service of the people of Australia. </p>
<p>And delegates, your Labor Government today stands foursquare<br />
in this, our grand tradition of nation building.<br />
Created by the trade union movement, the Labor Party has<br />
forged with the modern trade union movement an Accord<br />
partnership that is rebuilding the Australian economy. We<br />
have opened a new era in industrial relations, delivering in<br />
exchange unparallelled improvements in the social wage not<br />
least Medicare and the Family Allowance Supplement. We have<br />
secured the future of the steel industry and turned around<br />
our national export performance. We have made taxation fair<br />
and efficient. We have offered new opportunities to young<br />
Australians through expanded education and training. We are<br />
dedicated to justice for Aborigines and Torres Strait<br />
Islanders. We protect the environment from shortsighted<br />
destruction. We have engineered national self reliance in<br />
defence and, at a time of unprecedented change in our region<br />
and the world, we have sought constructive and co-operative<br />
paths in foreign policy.<br />
Ours has been a ministeriLal team of unrivalled quality.<br />
Our partner has been a t:: ade union movement of unrivalled<br />
commitment. And it has been Conferences such as this over the last<br />
decade that have underpinned our success with drive, vision<br />
and unity. It was our last National Conference in September<br />
that accelerated our fourth term with its historic decisions<br />
on telecommunications and aviation.<br />
So we are rightly proud of our past and we rightly celebrate<br />
it.<br />
But I use that past to speak now of the future. We are the<br />
party of Australia's future.<br />
And never in our Party's history has our responsibility for<br />
the future been greater.<br />
It has fallen to Labor, once more, to set the agenda for the<br />
future of Australia to set the goals which will determine<br />
the nature and quality of the Australia we take into the<br />
21st century, and to set the course by which the Australian<br />
people will attain those goals.<br />
That is our task at this Centenary Conference to ensure<br />
Labor's platform expresses that agenda, sets that Course,<br />
and ensures our organisation is in every respect ready for<br />
the next great electoral challenge we must face.<br />
Delegates, The next Federal election is still some two years away.<br />
But in a real sense we begin the campaign now a two-year<br />
campaign not just to win, the election, but to win the future<br />
for Australia. </p>
<p>Over this two year campaign, we will conduct the fight on<br />
two fronts:<br />
First, we will continue the tasks of reforming and<br />
rebuilding Australia:<br />
to maximise for the people of Australia the gains<br />
which will come with sustained low-inflation<br />
economic recovery;<br />
to continue building a more competitive Australia;<br />
to continue building a more compassionate and<br />
sensitive Australia.<br />
And our second task is to expose the real character and<br />
purpose of the Opposition to ensure that the Australian<br />
people have no illusions or misunderstandings about the<br />
fundamental choice they will have to make in 1993.<br />
For this Liberal opposition is unlike any that has preceded<br />
it in the forty-odd years since the foundation of that<br />
Party. Collectively in its leadership, it represents the most<br />
ideological and the most divisive alternative presented : to<br />
the Australian people in the post-War era.<br />
And in its program it is, more than any before it,<br />
obsessively determined to entrench privilege at the expense<br />
of fairness and compassion.<br />
So the choice in 1993 will be very clear indeed.<br />
And let me say at the outset that I have one clear message<br />
to this Conference, to this Party, to the people of<br />
Australia, and to our political opponents. It is a simple<br />
message of confidence:<br />
confidence in Labor, that we will successfully perform<br />
these dual tasks over the next two years and that, in<br />
doing so, we will win the Federal election in 1993.<br />
Delegates That confidence is firmly based on a sober assessment of the<br />
facts as, may I say, was my confidence that we would win<br />
in 1987 and 1990.<br />
First, then, let us consider what will happen in the<br />
Australian economy over the next two years.<br />
I begin from the point that the start of economic recovery,<br />
as I have repeatedly predicted, will be evident in the<br />
second half of this year.<br />
No one regrets more deeply than I the pain that has been<br />
suffered by many Australians through the tightening of<br />
monetary policy.<br />
8 : 2 0 _ I </p>
<p>But Australia in beginniing to emerge from the pain and<br />
hardship. We have brought interest rates down over the past<br />
eighteen months by seven and a half percentage points. And<br />
now, the first signs of renewed activity and confidence are<br />
starting to emerge.<br />
Delegates, the important point is that this recovery will be<br />
totally different in quality from any merely cyclical<br />
recovery this country hats seen in the past.<br />
This will be a recovery that unambiguously repays pain with<br />
gain gain not only for workers and their families but for<br />
all Australians.<br />
Remember, in 1963 we inherited an inflation rate of 11% from<br />
the conservatives' rece3Sion. Now, coming out of this<br />
recession, inflation is at 4.9 below the OECD average,<br />
and lower than this country has seen in two decades. And<br />
further falls are in prospect.<br />
Australia has low, competitive, inflation in its grasp.<br />
Under Labor, and only under Labor, Australia can make that a<br />
secure and permanent gain..<br />
Because under Labor, arid only under Labor, can an effective<br />
wages policy be pursued a wages policy based on the<br />
agreement by the trade union movement not to exercise its<br />
power to maximise nominal wage increases, and on the<br />
complementary agreement by the Labor Government to deliver<br />
improvements in the social wage.<br />
That has been the basis of our Accord a direct lineal<br />
descendant of the decision one hundred years ago by the<br />
trade union movement to establish a parliamentary Labor<br />
Party. For more than eight years, both sides of the Accord have<br />
honoured their commitment to the enduring benefit of the<br />
people of Australia.<br />
And for every one of those years, the national aggregate<br />
wages outcome we have agreed with the trade unions has come<br />
in at or under target.<br />
Despite the temporary difficulties following the recent<br />
National Wage decision, the trade unions remain totally<br />
committed to this Accr J principle and through it to the<br />
task of transforming Australia into an internationally<br />
competitive economy.<br />
That is precisely why I can speak with confidence to you<br />
about the character of the next two years as we go into the<br />
period of recovery. Through the Accord, it will be:<br />
a recovery which will see the resumption of secure<br />
employment growth; 832? 1 </p>
<p>a recovery in which the competitiveness of Australia's<br />
manufacturing industry will continue to increase so<br />
far this year, the value of manufacturing exports is<br />
23 per cent higher than last year;<br />
a recovery in which Australian workers will gain access<br />
to improved superannuation and, through award<br />
restructuring and union amalgamation, to better jobs,<br />
better-training, better remuneration;<br />
and a recovery in which we will see further<br />
improvements in productivity, through effective mic. roeconomic<br />
reform.<br />
And, delegates, through this recovery your Labor Governent<br />
will continue the broader agenda of economic reform just<br />
as, through the recession, we never lost sight of the longterm<br />
goal of a more competitive Australia.<br />
We will be implementing the reforms that flow from the<br />
decisions we have already taken:<br />
to make housing more affordable through the national<br />
housing strategy;<br />
to ensure cheaper and better services in the<br />
telecommunications and airlines industries;<br />
to cut tariffs while providing significant associated<br />
labour adjustment assistance;<br />
to implement an active and effective competition policy<br />
for the benefit of consumers;<br />
to expand our new network of Cooperative Research<br />
Centres as an important part of creating the clever<br />
country; to develop and implement the policy of ecologically<br />
sustainable development;<br />
and to continue our vigorous engagement in the current<br />
trade round, at this critical time, to win a fair go<br />
for Australia's efficient and competitive farm<br />
producers.<br />
The Special Premiers Conferences next month and in November<br />
will open new avenues to productivity improvements in areas<br />
that require the co-operation of the States: new investment<br />
in rail in return for better practices; better focusing of<br />
roads expenditure on priority routes; sensible pricing of<br />
rail and road so together they serve our industries better;<br />
a coordinated approach to electricity generation in southern<br />
and eastern Australia; and improved efficiency and delivery<br />
of community services, within a framework of agreed and<br />
acceptable national standards.<br />
But, delegates, when I speak of the character of these next<br />
two years, I do not speak only in economic terms. </p>
<p>Under Labor, through the Accord, Australia has become more<br />
competitive. Just as importantly, under Labor, Australia<br />
has become more compassionate.<br />
Understand with me and share my pride in the platform and<br />
process of achievement from which we will further advance<br />
our social goals.<br />
Behind the discipline of our significant reduction in<br />
Commonwealth outlays as .3 proportion of GDP, lies an<br />
achievement of immense siLgnificance for us of the Labor<br />
Party; it has cleared the way for us to deliver Labor's<br />
social priorities in a way that has surpassed the pioneering<br />
social reforms of all previous Labor governments.<br />
How have we done that? We have done it the Labor way. On<br />
the one hand, we have reformed the tax system we have<br />
eliminated the rorts and introduced effective capital gains<br />
and fringe benefit taxation.<br />
On the other hand, we have made sure that those people who<br />
do not need welfare assistance from the community no longer<br />
receive it. Thanks to fair and effective assets tests and<br />
income tests, we focus that community assistance on the<br />
people who really need it.<br />
That's the real equation, that's the Labor equation<br />
historically unprecedented fairness in revenue-raising<br />
matched by equally unprecedented fairness in the targeting<br />
of resources on those who need them most.<br />
Labor's ninth Budget in August will continue to deliver on<br />
the Labor equation.<br />
It will be a budget of necessary fiscal discipline. But<br />
within this discipline, I am determined with my colleagues<br />
to develop initiatives that will further assist families.<br />
Details obviously are a matter for the Budget, but our firm<br />
commitment is that low-and moderate-income families with<br />
kids will be the beneficiaries of such initiatives.<br />
Our budget will also start to. deliver on one of the most<br />
urgent social and economic challenges of the 1990s to make<br />
our cities work better. In co-operation with the States, we<br />
must start to improve people's access to work, services and<br />
education through better transport links, more affordable<br />
and appropriate housing, and a cleaner urban environment.<br />
Further, we are reviewing our system of health care to make<br />
an already great social justice reform, Medicare, even<br />
better. And we will pursue that fundamental goal for Australia<br />
that goal which in the first decade of our nation's third<br />
century is long-overdue the goal of reconciliation between<br />
Aboriginal people and the broader community. </p>
<p>Delegates That is how we will discharge the first of our dual tasks;<br />
we will fight the ' 93 election on the basis of a sustained<br />
economic recovery with low inflation, in a more competitive<br />
economy, and a more equitable and compassionate society.<br />
That will be good news for Australia but grim news indeed<br />
for our opponents.<br />
Which brings me to the second of our tasks, that is to<br />
expose the character and purpose of this Opposition.<br />
Delegates, let me be quite blunt and to the point this;<br />
Opposition is planning the most concerted attack in the<br />
history of this nation on the living standards of the poor,<br />
the underprivileged, the aged and low-and middle-income<br />
families. The centrepiece of this attack is their broad-based<br />
consumption tax, a fifteen per cent tax on all goods and<br />
c: Prv~ ncs it would increase the price not just of every<br />
item on the supermarket shelf, and beyond, but also every<br />
phone and electricity and gas bill, every doctor's bill,<br />
every meal you buy, every ticket for the footy, every repair<br />
bill for every car at every garage.<br />
By these means it would extract, over and above the present<br />
wholesale sales tax, an additional $ 12 billion from the<br />
Australian community.<br />
It would do so in a profoundly regressive way it would<br />
have a relatively greater impact on the poor and on families<br />
with kids because they spend a greater proportion of their<br />
incomes than do those who are better off.<br />
This regressive new tax is designed to replace the<br />
progressive structure of the existing wholesale sales tax<br />
which exempts the basic necessities of life, while taxing<br />
luxuries at a higher rate so the Mercedes would be<br />
cheaper, and bread and milk more expensive.<br />
With this tax, there could be no adequate compensation for<br />
its inflationary consequences and, as the Austral ian<br />
Catholic Social Welfare Commission observes, there appear to<br />
be no serious proposals for compensation of retirees and<br />
others for the loss in the value of their savings.<br />
This savage attack on ordinary Australians is appalling<br />
enough in itself.<br />
But it becomes totally repugnant when it is understood that<br />
part of the purpose of this S12 billion impost is to finance<br />
their intended abolition of the capital gains tax<br />
to restore to the most wealthy members of the community<br />
the right to accumulate capital gains on assets which<br />
will never be taxed </p>
<p>and in doing so to free any capitol gain made but not<br />
realised since 1985 at retrospective windfall to the<br />
rich amounting to billions of dollars.<br />
That is the Liberal -Nat iona: l-Party equation, an equation<br />
stunning in its simplicity, abhorrent in its purpose: pay<br />
the rich by slugging the poor. And not just the poor, but<br />
middle-income families too -to shove billions of dollars<br />
back into the pockets of an already privileged minority.<br />
In smashing the welfare of ordinary Australians, they would<br />
put Australia straight back into the high-inflation league.<br />
And with their commitment to abandon the Accord to abandon<br />
any capacity to determine or even to influence the level of<br />
wages they would keep Australia there.<br />
And the Australian economy would be prejudiced further by<br />
the fact that the absence of a ' capital gains tax would<br />
disastrously distort the allocation of investment resources.<br />
They are committed to cutting Government spending by<br />
$ 3 billion, including $ 1 billion from social welfare<br />
spending. They are committed to abolishing unemployment benefits after<br />
nine months providing $ 750 million of those savings.<br />
They are still ideologically committed to dismantling<br />
Medicare, putting two million Australians back outside the<br />
umbrella of health insurance. And now they float some farfetched<br />
system of health vouchers.<br />
They speak of asking voluntary welfare agencies such as St<br />
Vincent de Paul. and the Brotherhood of St Laurence to take<br />
over the payment of social security payments.<br />
They are set against the spr~ ead of superannuation throughout<br />
the workforce.<br />
And in industrial relations, they promise a return to the<br />
confrontation of the past, even with troops on the<br />
waterfront. That was Tory policy one hundred years ago at<br />
Barcaldine. And it's Tory policy today. They have learned<br />
nothing. Delegates All this is ideology gone ma~ d. It is a deliberate and<br />
systematic assault on the welfare of ordinary Australians.<br />
But it is more and worse than that. It would have the<br />
effect of creating a more divisive, divided,<br />
confrontationist society tha3n any we have experienced<br />
before. To complete the exposure of what this Opposition stands for,<br />
let me, briefly, refer to two other areas privatisation<br />
and the environment. 8 32: </p>
<p>We have had our internal arguments about aspects of<br />
privatisation. We have introduced competition into the<br />
telecommunications industry, but let the Australian people<br />
understand this point with absolute clarity. The Opposition<br />
would totally privatise this industry by selling off<br />
Telecom-OTC and would leave the Australian community without<br />
the protection of any publicly owned utility. We remain<br />
totally committed to retaining that protection by keeping<br />
Telecomi-OTC in full public ownership. -That too will be the<br />
stark choice before the Australian people in 1993.<br />
Consider what Labor has done to protect the environment of<br />
this nation for future generations not least here in this<br />
State. But right from the start, from our immediate decision to<br />
save the Franklin, through our decisions on the rainforests<br />
of North Queensland, on Ozone Protection, on the Tasmanian<br />
forests, on the Greenhouse Effect, on Kakadu, the NSW<br />
Rainforests and Shark Bay, and most recently on the<br />
enormously complex issue of Coronation Hill, through all<br />
these difficult but necessary decisions, the conservatives<br />
have opposed us at every step.<br />
That is their record in the past, and their promise for the<br />
future is no better. That too will be the stark choice<br />
before the Australian people in 1993.<br />
Delegates On the basis of our achievement and on the basis of our<br />
readiness for the challenges ahead, I make this assertion,<br />
not in any boastful spirit, but as an assessment of solid<br />
fact: No Labor Government has applied the spirit of Labor ideals<br />
with greater fidelity. No Labor Government has been more<br />
faithful to Labor's true traditions.<br />
And it has been our special challenge to apply those ideals,<br />
follow those traditions, in this era of the most rapid<br />
change in the whole of recorded history. It is the mark of<br />
our strength that we have had the courage to change.<br />
Of course, we have our differences. How could it be<br />
otherwise, given the rich diversity of our Party?<br />
But the great strength of our Labor Government has been and<br />
remains the constructive contribution made by each of the<br />
groups which compose it.<br />
I also salute again the tremendous contribution of our<br />
colleagues in the trade union movement. You have been<br />
magnificent. Delegates, at this point, you may excuse a brief personal,<br />
and I trust relevant, reflection. </p>
<p>Now in my 45th year of membership of our Party the best<br />
part of half its existence I have been afforded unique<br />
opportunities to feel its history; to understand the<br />
passions and commitment that drive it sometimes in upon<br />
itself; to see its capacity for adaptation; but at all times<br />
to be nourished by the steadfastness of that commitment to<br />
its fundamental goal the welfare of the Australian people.<br />
I have, through leadership of the industrial and then the<br />
political movement, come not just to understand the<br />
relationship between the trade unions and the Labor Party,<br />
but in my own life, for a generation, to live out that<br />
relationship. I have never needed to be reminded that our Party was formed<br />
by organised working men and women. That history is imbued<br />
in me and has become part of me. That same history tells me<br />
how ruthlessly the bastions of privilege in this country<br />
will fight to destroy the challenge they see in a strong,<br />
united and committed labour movement.<br />
As we enter the crucial months and years to 1993, that same<br />
history tells me that we should be guided in all our efforts<br />
and action by what I believe are the two central truths of<br />
Australian political life on the threshold of the 21st<br />
century. First, I deeply believe that never before has the<br />
alternative an anti-Labor government offered a greater<br />
contrast, and a more devastating prospect, for Australia and<br />
its people.<br />
And with equal conviction, I believe that never before in<br />
Australia's history has the existence and continuance of a<br />
strong effective Labor Government been more essential to<br />
securing the future for the people of Australia.<br />
And that is why I am determined, delegates, to work to the<br />
limit of my capacity for a fifth Labor victory in 1993. My<br />
obligation to this Parity and to Australia demands nothing<br />
less.<br />
Together, I am certain that we will achieve that victory<br />
the victory for this great Party, the victory for this great<br />
nation. 8 37 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
