<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>23037</transcript-id>
    <title>Address to HMAS Newcastle Welcome Home Ceremony, HMAS Kuttabul, Sydney</title>
    <prime-minister>Abbott, Tony</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130918 - 20150915</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/10/2013</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>It is an honour for me – on behalf of a grateful and respectful nation – to say thank you to the men and women of the HMAS Newcastle.</p>
<p>And particularly to say thank you to you, their friends and family for the support and encouragement that you have given to your loved ones.</p>
<p>As the Admiral has just reminded us, this is one of 55 Australian Naval deployments to the Middle East area of operations.</p>
<p>This is the fourth time HMAS Newcastle has deployed to the Middle East.</p>
<p>The work that the HMAS Newcastle has done is important work for our country and the world.</p>
<p>Your loved ones have been protecting our interests, upholding our values and supporting our citizens.</p>
<p>Your loved ones have been in a great tradition of Australian military commitments to the Middle East: the Light Horse in Palestine, the second Australian Imperial Force in the deserts of north Africa and more recently our forces in Iraq and Afghanistan.</p>
<p>Our forces go forth to do good, and HMAS Newcastle has done well in the Middle East over the last six months.</p>
<p>We are proud of the men and women of the HMAS Newcastle.</p>
<p>We are also proud of you – their families and loved ones.</p>
<p>Our military forces can only go abroad with the support of the people of Australia and no one supports our military forces more than their families and friends.</p>
<p>It is always difficult when your loved ones are away.</p>
<p>As the Admiral has pointed out – you, too, have served our country.</p>
<p>You, too, have made sacrifices for our country.</p>
<p>They also serve who wait for their loved ones to return.</p>
<p>Thank you so much on behalf of our country.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
