<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2476</transcript-id>
    <title>AUSTRALIAN-AMERICAN ASSOCIATION - 30TH ANNIVERSARY DINNER - VICTORIAN BRANCH - MELBOURNE VIC</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/10/1971</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002476.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />AUSTRlALIAN-AMERICAN ASSOCIATION<br />AN'NIVERSARY DIN4NER VICTORIAN BRANCIMIELBOURNE,<br />VIC. 7 OCTOBER, 1971.<br />SPEECH NOTES FOR THE PRIME MINISTER<br />Mr. President, Distinguished Guests, Ladies and Gentlemen,<br />When I look around this crowded room tonight<br />I feel in great heart knowing that there are in every<br />community, good and able people, ready and willing to<br />make a deliberate effort to keep our vital friendships<br />in good repair and to convince others to do the same.<br />I am glad to be here tonight, Msr. Baxter, as<br />the guest of your association and its members for this<br />thirtieth anniversary celebration dinner of the Victorian<br />Branch of the Australian-American Association.<br />M4y wife and I have both travelled widely<br />together in America and we are the first to acknowledge<br />the warmth and friendliness of its people and the greatness<br />of its achievements in the cavalcade of history. We have<br />shared many happy arnd exciting associations with our American<br />friends on the other side of the Pacific.<br />Sir, we are delighted to see so many old friends<br />here tonight and if I may be forgiven for singling out two<br />very distinguished people I want to say it is wonderful to<br />have Lord and Lady Casey with us at this table. None knows<br />better than they how the links between Australia and America<br />have been forged over the years and I doubt if anyone has done<br />as much as they have to make those links secure. I know what<br />a strength Lord Casey has been to the Australian-American.<br />Association since its earliest days. I do congratulate the<br />Association on living this long life and one which I trust<br />has been a merry as well as a rewarding one. I am told, too,<br />Sir, that the women's group and the Junior American Association<br />really keep the men on their toes. Congratulations to you too.<br />Now Sir, I hope you will forgive me for being<br />serious tonight but an anniversary occasion like this tempts<br />me to look briefly over the past, and then, more particularly<br />to look forward into the future in our relationships with<br />America. .2/</p>
<p>2<br />I think the pre' -eminent characteristic of the<br />United Statlkes in the international comrmunity has been its<br />deep sense of responsibility to work towards a more stable<br />and equitable world order. It has given concrete evidence<br />of its readiness to make human and material sacrifices for<br />this purpose. It has given its blood and its treasure in<br />formidable quantities. That hasn't always been appreciated<br />and often not understood. If we can do something to explain<br />and correct this we serve our own interests and take up a<br />proper position as fair-minded people.<br />It is easy to scoff at our democratic institutions.<br />The way they .) ork and the things they do, be they of the<br />American, the British or the Australian order; And I quote<br />Franklin Roosevelt on this point. What he had to say was thisand<br />I quote'-" I get everlastingly angry at those who assert<br />vociferously that the four freedoms and the<br />Atlantic Charter are nonsense because they are<br />unattainable.<br />" if those people had lived a century arid a half<br />ago they would have sneered and said that the<br />Declaration of independence was utter piffle.<br />" If they had lived nearly a thousand years ago<br />they would have laughed uproariously at the ideals<br />of Magna Carta.<br />Ancz if they had lived several thousand years<br />ago they would have derided Moses when he came<br />down from t-he mountain with the Ten Commandments".<br />ladies and Gentlemen, your Association was born in<br />the dark days of World War II and at that time, and in the years<br />since then, the United States has been a significant, and ind~ eed<br />a decisive, factor in our security. We must be grateful ' for the<br />partnership with the United States which prevented a possible<br />invasion of Australia and led to the re-conquest of the Pacific<br />by the allies. Australia was, of course, an essential base for operations.<br />Then we must acknowledge the effective leadership given by the<br />United States checking communist aggression in Korea and in<br />Vietnam. We signed the Anzus Treaty wnith them and to this day<br />that Treaty ranks as our most important Treaty.<br />I have travelled the Pacific many times. I have seen<br />the distance shrink as the jets have devoured the space and I<br />have seen South-East Asia change from a region of turbulence<br />to one with a more settled and confident prospect.<br />I have sat in the Australian Cabinet for many years<br />and joined in the vital decisions we have taken to identify<br />ourselves more deliberately and more closely with the region to<br />which geographically we belong. .3/</p>
<p>-3<br />one of the essential elements in our policy towards<br />South East Asia has been the Australian-Amierican alliance.<br />It is of crucial importance to our foreign folic7. This will<br />continue to be a basic element of our policy, but the changed<br />nature of the political situation in South East Asia must<br />carry with it changes in the nature of our relationship with<br />the United States in that region.<br />The United States and Australia have sir~ illar objoctives.<br />We should both like * to see a region which is stable politically,<br />developing rapidly economically and within which the peoples<br />are free to choose their own forms of governments. Nevertheless<br />Australia must recognise that its own particular interests in this<br />part of the world may call for different judgements on its part<br />from those of the United States.<br />Let us look at some of the chanaes that have occurred<br />within our own part of the world. The first which has<br />received widespread publicity has been the change in United<br />States policy itself, broadly encompassed under what is known<br />as the Nixon Doctrine.<br />Clearly the United States is no longer prepared to<br />attempt alone and on a global ecale the containment of<br />aggression and the construction of a reasonably stable frame=<br />work of international co-operation. While maintaining its<br />general support and protection, it has called upon the countries<br />of the region to do more to help themselves. rle accept this,<br />and the challenge and responsibility of greater self-reliance.<br />The second major change within the South-East Asia region<br />has been the re-emergence of tha influence of powers other than<br />the United States. This re-emergence has begun to complicate<br />the ' international political situation.<br />Japan with its enormous economic strength is in a position<br />to make a major contribution to the development of the region.<br />It has regained its international confidence, and its relations<br />with South-East Asian countries will be increasingly important<br />in the political equations of the area.<br />The People's Republic of China appears to be giving-less<br />emphasis to the rigidities of ideology in the conduct of its<br />foreign policy and to be showing a new interest in the establishment<br />of more traditional diplomatic and commercial relationships.<br />Russia, too, has begun to try to increase its influence<br />in the area, and to seek closer ties with South East Asian<br />Governments. All these moves are only to be expected;, great<br />powers have always interested themselves in affairs outside<br />their own borders, and will continue to do so. ./ 4</p>
<p>The third major change that I shall note in the<br />region has been the establishment of increasingly confident<br />and capable national governments, dedicated to the objectives<br />of economic progress, social welfare and regional co-operation.<br />This is a development which has been made possible in large<br />measure by successful allied resistance to the aggression<br />against South Vietnam.<br />Most of the peoples of the countries of the region<br />have now established their national identity and have installed<br />governments capable of planning their futures, and resisting,<br />with a minimum of outside assistance, efforts by minority groups<br />to overthrow the national political order.<br />Of one thing I am sure, in the period that lies ahead,<br />the need for consultation between us will not be less, but<br />greater. Increasingly with our political and defence relations,<br />other aspects of our relationship with the United States can be<br />expected to assume greater importance for example trade,<br />investment, civil aviation.<br />In the process, differences between us are bound to<br />arise but there is no reason why we cannot continue to discuss<br />them fully and frankly, as we have in the past, and in a spirit<br />of give and take. This is what a partnership is for.<br />We look forward to a future where the United States<br />cQntinues to take a wise and constructive role in the<br />achievement of a peaceful world order and we expect to make<br />our own individual and independent contribution to the<br />realisation of the same objective.<br />We have shared the dangers of the past in friendship.<br />Let us share, in the same way, the promise of the future.<br />I thank you. 1<br />ZI</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
