<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2730</transcript-id>
    <title>THE PRIME MINISTER&#039;S PRESS CONFERENCE AT PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA - TUESDAY 5 DECEMBER 1972</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/12/1972</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002730.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
THE PRIME MINISTER'S PRESS CONFERENCE<br />
AT PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA<br />
TUESDAY, 5 DECEMBER 1972<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Ladies and gentlemen; you were told by way of<br />
a press release at two o'clock this afternoon that I had called<br />
on the Governor-General, at his request, at 12.15 this afternoon<br />
and had accepted his commission to form a Government.<br />
I gave him the reasons why I believe that there should<br />
be an interim Government formed by the Australian Labor Party<br />
and that for the purposes of that Government two persons would<br />
be enough,. The statement gives the reason, or some of the<br />
reasons, why it was urgent to have a Government to carry out the<br />
mandate that the Party received at the elections last Saturday.<br />
The nature of the matters which I mentioned would show<br />
why ii. would be more effective to have these decisions made by<br />
an interim Government which sympathised with them rather than by<br />
an interim Government which had opposed them. It would be a more<br />
appropriate thing for both the incoming Government and the outgoing<br />
one to have the responsibility of those decisions.<br />
At 3.30 this afternoon Mr. Barnard and I accordingly<br />
waited on the Governor-General and he swore us into the portfolios<br />
which you have. NOW, are there any questions?<br />
MEGAN STOYLES, Mr. Prime Minister, could you please give<br />
us the timetable of when people gaoled under the National Service<br />
Act will be released and also the timetable for ending<br />
conscription?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:. Well, first of all, I'll ask Mr. Barnard to give<br />
the matters which fall to him as Minister for Defence for ending<br />
the call-up.<br />
MR. BARNARD: Prime Minister, ladies and gentlemen. As you<br />
know, I have already had discussions with officers from the<br />
Department of Labour and National Service, the members of the<br />
Department of flip Army and I have this afternoon released a<br />
statement which will be available to the Press and which<br />
discontinues the call-up. There will be no furt-her call-up.<br />
Those who have already received a notice of call-up will not be<br />
obliged to act or. them. So, as from today, notices will be<br />
going out to those who have received their call-up notice that<br />
they have no further obligation under the National Service Act. </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER: Ladies and gentlemen, for the matters which fall<br />
to me for the time being as Attorney-General. Yesterday and<br />
today Senator Murphy, who will be the Attorney-General<br />
when the full Ministry is appointed, has been in consultation<br />
with the officers of the Attorney-General's Department and has<br />
prepared the papers. Instructions have now been given that all<br />
pending prosecutions are to be withdrawn. The Commonwealth<br />
Police have been asked to withhold execution of outstanding<br />
warrants and papers have been prepared for the Governor-General<br />
to remit the sentences, the remaining portion of all prison<br />
sentences, of those who are now in prison and also the<br />
remission of all outstanding fines. Those papers I've signed<br />
them I have told the Governor-General that they will be<br />
submitted to him. At this stage I don't know when or precisely<br />
how they will be submitted.<br />
JOHN LOMBARD, " MELBOURNE SUN": About the blokes who are already<br />
in the Army, national servicemen, what exactly will be the<br />
machinery for giving them the option for leaving the Army. Can<br />
it be done without an amendment to the National Service Act?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I'll ask Mr. Barnard.<br />
MR. BARNARD: Yes. Again, Mr. Prime Minister, I have already made<br />
a move on this question. What I do want to ensure is that no<br />
national servicemen will be disadvantaged as a result of changes<br />
that we will be making to provide additional benefits to those<br />
who are serving in the armed forces but the machinery has already<br />
been put in motion. I expect that before the end of this week<br />
the necessary regulation will have been provided that will enable<br />
the discharge of those national servicemen who are now in the<br />
armed forces to take their discharge. Now, we would hope that<br />
they will be phased out after they have been advised of the<br />
additional benefits they would receive if they decide to continue<br />
their 18 months service as national servicemen. So they will<br />
receive that advice. Then they can decide whether they will<br />
elect to take their discharge or remain and complete their<br />
18 months. Now the necessary machinery has already dealt with<br />
the requirements and they will be advised before Christmas.<br />
FRANK CHAMBERLAIN, May I ask a question of the Prime<br />
Minister and the Deputy Prime Minister? Sir, does this first<br />
Whitlam Ministry mean that you will have a second Whitlam.<br />
Ministry next week or the week after or is this to be called a<br />
two man dictatorship or is this an unprecedented move? That's<br />
my first question to you, sir, and to the Deputy Prime Minister,<br />
when you say the national servicemen are phased out, sir, do you<br />
mean they are phased out into unemployment or are they phased<br />
into employment by the National Service Department?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well, first of all about when there is a full<br />
Ministry appointed. Perhaps I can enlarge on the reasons which<br />
were given in the press statement at two o'clock this afternoon<br />
for having to wait so long before there ca-n be a meeting of the<br />
Federal Parliamentary Labor Party, the Caucus, to elect a Ministfy. </p>
<p>The elections, which were held last Saturday, are very<br />
close in many electorates and tihe voting is very complex. Under<br />
ti e lw it is not possible t~ o distribute preferences until ten<br />
days after the poll, unless the number of votes which are still<br />
awaiting delivery by post would not affect the result.<br />
Now, the complication in this election is that therp<br />
are a very great number of electoral divisions where previously<br />
there was only one coalition candidate because that candidate<br />
was a Minister and the coalition partner did not oppose<br />
Ministers. In many of these electorates, however,-the Minister<br />
retired and accordingly had both a Country Party and a Liberal<br />
candidate standiing. The number of votes outstanding, therefore,<br />
has to be taken into account in determining whether it is the<br />
Liberal or the Country Party candidate who will be eliminated<br />
first. The Liberal candidate, his preferences would be nearly<br />
certain to go all to the Country Party candidate. If the Country<br />
Party candidate was elimina~ ted first, some preferences would go<br />
to the Labor candidate and so, therefore, it takes probably<br />
the ten days to do it. Furthermore, there are a considerable<br />
number of electorates where the Chief Electoral Officer has already<br />
been told there will be a recount and he advised me yesterday<br />
that in these circumstances he didn't see where he would be<br />
able to give a result in many of these electorptes where the<br />
Labor candidate could be expected to win before Friday of next<br />
week, or even the weekend.<br />
Now, in those circumstances, the Caucus could not be<br />
held at the present time until Monday week and then the Caucus will<br />
have to elect the Ministry and the Caucus will then have to<br />
decide, or the Ministry, if the Caucus so determines, will h~' ve to decide<br />
what will be the new Ministries.<br />
FRANK CHAMBERLAIN: you think you will be automatically elected<br />
Leader, sir, do you?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I haven't heard that I will be opposed but<br />
whoever is the Leader will then have to allocate the Ministers<br />
among the portfolios then to be determined. It may be that not<br />
until tomorrow fortnight, the 20th of December, can a full<br />
Ministry be sworn to take the place of thi--irterim one.<br />
FRANK CHAMBERLAIN: And that will be a secon d Ministry?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I think it will have to be because it is not just<br />
a question of handing over some portfolios to new members who<br />
have then become Ministers. There will inevitably be some chnnges<br />
in the nature of the Ministries. There are to be some<br />
amalgamations, maybe, but also the Party is committed to creating<br />
several new Ministries. </p>
<p>MR. BARNARD: The discussions I've had with the officers of the<br />
Department of Labour and National Service have been on the basis<br />
to ensure that their re-employment rights are protected and,<br />
as you know, this is already of course included in the National<br />
Service Act. I wanted to, myself, ensure that their re-employment<br />
rights were protected and the machinery for providing for those<br />
who want to take their discharge will be, at the same time, looked<br />
at by the Department of Labour and National Service to ensure that<br />
the job opportunities are available.<br />
DAVID BARNETT, Last year during the visit to Peking you<br />
told the Chinese Premier, Mr. Chou En-lai that " If my Party wins<br />
the election, you will be able to see the first visit by an<br />
Australian Prime Minister to the Chinese People's Republic and<br />
its sole capital of Peking". Mr. Chou replied; " We will welcome<br />
that". What steps, sir, are you taking to bring about the<br />
recognition of China? When would you like to make this visit?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Our Ambassador in Paris, Mr. Renouf, has arranged<br />
to meet the Chinese Ambassador in Paris, Mr. Huang Chen, at,<br />
Canberra time, four o'clock on Thursday, a. m. I meant Thursday<br />
morning, and cables have gone to him suggesting the terms upon<br />
which there should be full diplomatic representation by each<br />
country in the other. You ask when to visit. There will be,<br />
early in October, in Tokyo, a Japan-Australia Ministerial Meeting.<br />
It would seem. appropriate before, or after, that meeting for me<br />
to visit Peking.<br />
L. OAKES: Sir, on that subject, I think you have a message from<br />
Mr. Forace from Mr. Chou. Could you tell us the contents of that<br />
message?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No. I have received the message. I don't think<br />
it would be appropriate for me to state the contents of it.<br />
ALAN REID, Sir, you made employment a very high priority<br />
of your policy speech. Obviously the Parliament cannot meet<br />
until February. Are there any administrative acts that you could<br />
take in the interval to assist the school leavers and alleviate<br />
unemployment and also, sir, if I may ask an unrelated one, a lesser<br />
one, nevertheless interesting, what is going to happen to the<br />
New Year's Honours List?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: First, school leavers. I expect to be seeing<br />
Mr. Crean within the next few days. On Sunday I'll be seeing<br />
both Mr. Dunstan and Mr. Tonkin where unemployment in urban<br />
areas is considerable. As you know, unemployment relief up till<br />
now has been made for rural areas. In those two States there is<br />
the largest percentage of the population in the capitals and<br />
because of this unemployment is worse in those States because<br />
the rural areas bulk less. I'll be seeing them on Sunday.<br />
Mr. Crean I hope to see before then, certainly after that.<br />
Honours Lists. This question is premature, if you don't<br />
mind me saying so. I am making a submission to the Governor-General<br />
on this matter since he raised it with me. </p>
<p>ALAN BARNES, " THE AGE": When you were Leader of the Opposition,<br />
sir, you...<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Mr. Barnes, " Age", and ageless.<br />
ALAN BARNES: When you were Leader of the Opposition, you suggested<br />
that the Liberal Governmen~ t should make a Christmas bonus, give<br />
$ 100 to each. of the pensioners as a means of stimula~ ting the<br />
economy. Does your Government intend to carry through your own<br />
a dvi ce?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: It needs parliamentary action and that cannot be<br />
done this year.<br />
FRANK CHAMBERLAIN: Could you make it retrospective, sir, at<br />
Easter? PRIME MINISTER: That would not enable any boost to spending, though.<br />
JOHN O'FARRELL: But do you still intend to do it?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I will consult my colleagues on this matter. I<br />
notice it is ore of the things which is suggested in the " Australian<br />
Economic Review" published by the Melbourne University Institute<br />
of Applied Econornio and Social Research.<br />
BENNELL, 7 NETWORK: Sir, you will have a 27 member Cabinet. I<br />
wonder how you are going to get over the legislative delays that<br />
Mr. McMahon recently complained of with his very much smaller<br />
Cabinet?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: None of my Ministers-will be slow, none of them<br />
will be without political perception.<br />
BROWN," ICOURIER-MAIL": Sir, you have won this election in the<br />
suburbs of Sydney and Melbourne. Apart from rejuvenating these<br />
areas, what priorities do you have for the rest of Australia?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: We have won them in the suburbs of Sydney and<br />
Melbourne because that is where so many people live. We will, in<br />
fact, be aiming to do things which will be of benefit to all<br />
those areas where there are large concentrat4ons of population<br />
and, as you know, we propose to involve local government for the<br />
first time in national financial arrangements. There are<br />
considerable growing areas already in some provincial centres<br />
and we aim, through measures of decentralisatiop and co-operation<br />
with the States, to make more such areas. In proportion to<br />
popula-L-cn we did, in fact, increase in quite a number of such<br />
provincial areas.<br />
MICHAEL SCHILDBERGER, NATIONAL 9 NEWS: Mr. Prime Minister, can<br />
we expect any tax changes before the next Budget or perhaps have<br />
another mini-Budget before the next August Budget? </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER: I would not expect there would be any tax changes<br />
other, I would hope, than maybe excise duty on wine and sales tax<br />
on contraceptives.<br />
CHAMBERLAIN: Both eliminated?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes.<br />
BARNES: Is that an undertaking on the latter? You undertook in<br />
your policy speech to immediately abolish the wine tax.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I am checking this at this stage to see whether,<br />
as I think can be done, the announcement can be made that<br />
legislation will be brought in retrospective to the date on which<br />
these announcements were made.<br />
MUNGO McCALLUM, " NATION REVIEW": Prime Minister, you have not<br />
only made a number of appointments to your own staff and named a<br />
number of people who are obviously going to be close advisers to<br />
you. A number of men who are obviously going to be important<br />
Ministers in the coming government have also named people who<br />
are going to be important to them and perhaps personal advisers.<br />
To what extent is this going to affect the normal public service<br />
structure? To what extent is this going to mean that you are<br />
in fact running a presidential government with the people who are<br />
really giving you the advice and to some extent making decisions<br />
pulled in from outside both the electoral and public service structure?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: This is not a matter upon which I would presume<br />
to make any decisions before a full Ministry is appointed. This<br />
is an interim Ministry and it will make those decisions which are<br />
urgent to carry out mandates. This is not a matter to which I<br />
have given any consideration. It is a matter which can wait until<br />
the Ministers are elected by the Party and allocated by the Prime<br />
Minister. The objective, if it comes about, is to depoliticise<br />
the public service so that persons who are responsible for carrying<br />
out political decisions will be known to be appointed by a<br />
Minister at his whim and disposable at his whim. The public service,<br />
of course, will be less political if there are such personal<br />
advisers known to be appointed.<br />
CHAMBERLAIN: Prime Minister, specifically following Mr. Mungo<br />
McCallum's question, there are some decisions made by the previous<br />
Government, urban development, decentralisation and what have you,<br />
and an organisvtion calling itself NURDS has been developed and<br />
big appointments been made. Now, do they unwrap thsemselves or do<br />
they go into suspense?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Here again, it is not a matter where we have to<br />
make a decision at this sto&amp; p. There are some matters in the<br />
urban context which I did undertake in the Party's policy speech<br />
to make, if possible before Christmas, and I will be making these<br />
after consultation with Mr. Uren and, I hope, Mr. Jones on Friday. </p>
<p>I say I hope because I have not been in touch with Mr. Jones<br />
myself because of the pressure of other things today, but Mr. Uren<br />
will be here on Friday and if Mr. Jones is here we can discuss<br />
still more matters in this context, and NURDA will be among the<br />
bodies which we will consult on these matters which we want to<br />
get under way before Christmas. They invclve, really, letters by<br />
me to the Premiers concerned.<br />
ARMFIELD, " AGE": Mr. Whitlam, under Labor's system of open<br />
government, will members of the armed forces, including the<br />
Military Boards, be able to make public their views on service<br />
matters such as the effects of ending national service?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: This is a matter of Government policy where it would<br />
be improper for the opinion of any such Boards to be sought or<br />
tendered. The people have decided this matter.<br />
DAVID SOLOMON, " CANBERRA TIMES": Sir, what are your priorities<br />
in the next two weeks? What does your Government in the next two<br />
weeks intend to do and what will be the major priorities of the<br />
Government which will be elected tben?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I should only say what will be the priorities<br />
of this administration. The priorities of the following one are<br />
for it to determine, for Mr. Barnard and me to share in making.<br />
I have stated three matters in the press statement at two o'clock<br />
this afternoon the abolition of conscription, the reference of<br />
colour television to the Tariff Board ( I am seeing Dr. Cairns on<br />
this matter with the head of the Department of Trade and Industry,<br />
Mr. McKay, at 6 o'clock tonight), the application to the<br />
Commonwealth Conciliation and Arbitration Commission to re-open<br />
the equal pay case so that the Commonwealth, which had intervened,<br />
can now state ' support for the case. I have been in touch with<br />
Mr. Cameron about this. I mentioned some matters in foreign<br />
affairs. China I have already answered some questions about.<br />
There are also matters in the United Nations General Assembly<br />
which concludes its deliberations, I think, on the 19th. </p>
<p>TED BARKER, " WEST AUSTRALIAN": Sir, have you raised the<br />
question of revaluation in your talks with'Sir Frederick<br />
Wheeler, and could you give an indication of what your<br />
government plans on the currency?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I have not raised it. This is not a matter<br />
which the present Ministry would deal with and, frankly, even<br />
if I had raised it, it would not be proper for me to tell you.<br />
JOHN O'FARLL, " SYDNEY MORNING HERALD?: I was wondering if we<br />
could revert to China? Would you expect Dr. Stephen FitzGerald<br />
would be Australia's first Ambassador to China, and would you want<br />
this man to be our first Ambassador? Would you press him to be<br />
our first Ambassador?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I noticed that Dr. Stephen FitzGerald has been<br />
nominated in some journals for this purpose. I notice Mr. Ross<br />
Terrill has been nominated by some other journals. -You will<br />
appreciate, ladies and gentlemen, that I could not discuss any<br />
person, man or woman, as a prospective Ambassador or High<br />
Commissioner until the person's name had been submitted to the<br />
receiving country and had approved. Before agr'ement that's for<br />
your benefit, Francois Chamberlain I could not make any comment<br />
on such matters.<br />
KEVIN POWER, 2tJE: Prime Minister, when will the Parliament meet<br />
next year to deal with the legislative content of-your mandate?<br />
Will it be early or will it be in the normal time?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Here again, it is not a matter upon which this<br />
Ministry would presume to make a decision. It is a matter<br />
certainly for the next administration.<br />
WARREN DUNCAN. Prime Minister, what would be your first<br />
moves towards granting land rights to aborigines, and do you<br />
intend im.' mediately to involve the aborigines in the work of their<br />
department?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Here again, this is a matter which must wait<br />
until the next administration. .' It is a matter upon which a full,<br />
distinct Minister for Aborigines has to be appointed. I have<br />
already discussed the matter this morning, half past ten, with<br />
Dr. Coombs, among other matters.<br />
CHALMERS. ATN NETWORK: Mr. Prime Minister, will Dr. Coombs be<br />
an adviser to this administration?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: He is.<br />
TRUMBLE. " NEW YORK TIMES": Sir..<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Republican or Dem~ ocrat?<br />
TRtUhBLE: On the fence, Sir. I am at sea, I was a Democrat for<br />
Nixon. In opposition, you and Mr. Barnard both raised the<br />
question of the American military installations in Australia </p>
<p>with particular reference to the secrecy surrounding them and<br />
then of course there is a question raised in the Labor Party<br />
platform on the matter of foreign administration of bases on<br />
Australian soil. Could you at this time, Sir, indicate the<br />
policy your government will take on these questions?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: This is a matter upon which no consideration<br />
will be given or really could be given by this interim<br />
administration. I would like to make it plain, however, that<br />
there now need be no secrecy, because Mr. Barnard and I can find<br />
out whatever we want to. The fact'that there has been secre * cy<br />
up till now has not been a condition imposed by any United States<br />
Administration.<br />
BARRON, " SYDNEY SUN": Why did you decide to restrict the present<br />
Ministry to two, why not spread the responsibility a bit thinner<br />
with some of the men you have already described as certainties,<br />
particularly thE Senate Leader and his Deputy?<br />
PRIM~ E MINISTER: The difficulty is, where do you draw the line<br />
on this? There are some people in the. HParliament, the fact that<br />
they are going to be elected is already quite obvious, who are<br />
in the House of Representatives, who have been in the House of<br />
Representatives longer than Mr. Barnard or I and who have been<br />
on the Caucus Executive longer than Mr. Barnard or I. Mr. Crean<br />
has been on the Executive since 1954, Mr. Cameron since 1958.<br />
Obviously if the test of seniority and service is to prevail,<br />
they would be entitled to have priority over anybody else, but<br />
you will appreciate that if I were to choose two persons from<br />
the House of Representatives there would be, what is it, ten<br />
other members of the House of Representatives in the old Shadow<br />
Ministry, all of whom have clearly been re-elected and it would<br />
be invidious for me to presume to pick out which of my House of<br />
Representatives colleagues would be senior in service,<br />
significance, portfolio, and accordingly it was most appropriate<br />
to choose two persons alone. Perhaps I might comment also<br />
there is an appropriateness about having an interim Ministry of<br />
only two because any matters which have to be done by the<br />
Executive Council would require. the Governor-General, who is<br />
not a partisan person, to be present. It is unusual to have a<br />
Ministry of two persons., There is, therefore, the public<br />
safeguard of having the President of the Executive Council<br />
constituting the Executive Council with those two Ministers.<br />
There is, you will notice, no Vice-President of the Executive<br />
Council. CHAMBERLAIN: That means Sir Paul Hasluck has the casting vote?<br />
PRIME~ MINISTER: In the case of disagreement between the<br />
partisan members of the Executive Council. As you know, there<br />
has not been disagreement between the two pattisan members of<br />
the what's the term, the active Ministers, the active members<br />
of the Executive Council, the Minister's Executive Council on<br />
Call, isn't that the term? in the 18 years they have served<br />
in the Parliament together. </p>
<p>O'FARRELL: Those reasons you have given do not apply to<br />
Senator Murphy or Senator Willesee. Why havn't you included<br />
them as members of' the Executive Council?<br />
PRIDMC-MINISTER: I have mentioned two members of' the House of<br />
Representatives who, by any test, are senior to Senator Murphy<br />
and Senator Willesee.<br />
0O'FA' 7RRELL: Yes, but they are not subject to re-election.<br />
They are there now. They are safe Labor men.<br />
PRIM~' E MINISTER: I think they are all safe Labor men.<br />
MAX 1HAWKINS, " BRISBANE TELEGRAPH": How urgent or how soon<br />
would you or Mr. Barnard wish to consult with the Five Power<br />
partners in South-East Asia and with the ANZUK partners on the<br />
arrangements there, the defence arrangements there, having in<br />
mind the party's proposal that we will withdraw our battalion<br />
group from Singapore in the foreseeable future?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: There is no urgency in this matter for the<br />
present Ministry to determine. The battalion and the brigade<br />
which are in Singapore don't end their tour of duty, I think,<br />
until January 1974. This is a matter which clearly, not only<br />
can, but should be left till there is a f'ull Ministry. -In any<br />
case there is no urgency. As you know, Lord Carrington who was<br />
due to come out here at the beginning of this year, will, in<br />
fact, be coming in January and this is a matter which, among<br />
others, might oe discussed with him.<br />
BILL DARCY, I was wondering if you could tell me<br />
whether you are hopeful that diplomatic relations between<br />
Australia and China will be established there prior to your<br />
visit later next year?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I would certainly expect so. I mentioned the<br />
Japan-Australia Ministerial Meeting early next October. I would<br />
certainly hope that there would be full diplomatic representations<br />
between the countries, between China and Australia, by then; an<br />
Ambassador resident in each capital.<br />
L. OAKES. " MELBOURNE SUN": Prime Minister, you mentioned earlier<br />
that the urgency of some United Nations matters was one of' the<br />
reasons for the establishment of your interim Ministry. Can<br />
you tell us whether any decisions have been made so far by<br />
your Cabinet on those U. N. matters, what are they, and what<br />
instructions have you issued?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: There are two matters where I made a decision.<br />
One concerned Rhodesia. In Committee, on one resolution<br />
concerning Rhodesia, Australia had abstained, on another,<br />
Australia had opposed, voted against. In each case, when the<br />
resolution now comes to theGGeneral Assembly, Australia will<br />
support, vote in support. On the other matter, concerning the<br />
Sirl Lankan proposal for a zone of peace in the Indian Ocean,<br />
in* Committee Australia had abstained, In the General Assembly,<br />
Australia will now vote in support. </p>
<p>CHRIS, REEVES. A. T. N. NETWORK: Prime Minister: Can you tell<br />
us please the terms that you have suggested for recognition of<br />
Peking? PRIN. 1E MINISTER: Briefly, the Canadian.<br />
BENNELL: Have you set a timetable, Sir, for the expulsion of<br />
the Taiwanese Ambassador here at the moment.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No.<br />
CONNORS: Mr. Whitlam, could you give me a run-down of the<br />
likely responsibilities of the new Department of Northern<br />
Development and where its responsibilities may end and start.<br />
geographically? PRIME MINISTER: No, this is a matter upon which I have already<br />
had discussions with the relevant Departmental Heads. It is a<br />
matter upon which Mr. Barnard, Senator Murphy, Senator Willesee<br />
and I will be having discussions with some of our colleagues<br />
also, but we will be involved in the discussion of all the<br />
departments so that we will be in a position to make a<br />
recommendation to the Caucus when it is able to meet, or if it<br />
so wishes, to the new Ministry.<br />
BRUCE MERCHANT. MACQUARIE RADIO NEWS: Mr. Whitlam: Could you<br />
tell me whether you intend to hold a full scale Premiers'<br />
Press Conference here in Canberra, Premiers' Conference before<br />
Christmas? PRIME MINISTER: Nobody had suggested it. I don't believe it<br />
would be possible.<br />
MERCHANT: After Ch ristmas, Sir?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: There has been no such suggestion. I don't<br />
think I've had' the suggestion, there might be in writing, I~ vve<br />
not seen, I've not had any such suggestion from any of the<br />
Premiers. WARREN DUNCAN. How soon do you think it will be before<br />
your Government has an effect on the soaring land prices, not<br />
only in the major cities, but in the growth areas that you and<br />
the N. S. W. Government have nominated.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I hope to have discussions, as I said in my<br />
Policy Speech, with the Premiers of Victoria and New South Wales<br />
and Mr. Uren concerning Albury-Wodonga. The Hamer Government<br />
in Victoria has nominated . Klbury-Wodonga. This administration<br />
has been returned, among other things, on the nomination of<br />
Albury-Wodonga. I don't know what approaches might be made by<br />
any other State Government about any other centres. I certainly<br />
would be discussing with Mr. Uren and his Department of Cities<br />
any such matter, particularly this question of land prices. </p>
<p>12.<br />
BOB BAUDINO. NEWS LIMITED: Can ask this again, twenty six<br />
nations today moved a resolution in the Trusteeship Committee<br />
of the United Nations calling for Australia to prepare a new<br />
timetable on independence for Papua New Guinea. Australia<br />
as late as November 20, gave a timetable saying this would come<br />
in December 1973. Do you propose to update this?<br />
PRIME MINISTER! W Events are moving so quickly in Papua New<br />
Guinea that it is not inconceivable that that date of December<br />
1973 could be reached. It is altogether probable thatPPapua<br />
New Guinea will be fully independent and, one trusts, admitted<br />
to both the United Nations and the Commnonwealth of Nations<br />
before less than two years, no more than two years from now.<br />
You know that Mr. Somare has sent a message to me. This is a<br />
matter where I can repeat what I have said in the Parliament,<br />
what Mr. Somare himself believes, that the term as Minister of<br />
External Territories of Mr. Andrew Peacock made the<br />
development of the progress towards independence of Papua New<br />
Guinea very much easier than any of us could have expected<br />
when some of you came up with some of us at the beginning of<br />
1970 and again, at the beginning of 1971.<br />
CHAMBERLAIN: Relevant to that, Sir, the Queensland Premier<br />
is arguing about the boundaries between Queensland and Papua<br />
New Guinea and says he won't tolerate any Federal interference.<br />
Have you any view on that?<br />
PRIVIE MINISTER: I have. It is well known but I think he can<br />
wait until the full Ministry is appointed. I haven't yet had<br />
time, I hope you will understand, to see what the position is<br />
in the Department of Foreign Affairs on this matter, but quite<br />
clearly, in the interests of good relations between Australia<br />
and Papua New Guinea, this boundary must be made acceptable in<br />
contemporary terms. The last visiting mission of the United<br />
Nations Trusteeship Council to New Guinea reported on this<br />
matter. It is going to receive increasing international<br />
attention. The boundary which has been fixed by agreement<br />
between Australia and Indonesia obviously forms a precedent<br />
for a boundary between Australia and Papua New Guinea.<br />
Queensland is part of Australia. Australia alone has any<br />
international standing.<br />
BRIAN JOHNS: Prime Minister, you mentioned that Dr. Coombs had<br />
given you advice today. I was wondering if you could tell us<br />
has he joined your staff? If he hasn't, is he going to join<br />
it and the conditions on which he would join, because I no * ticed,<br />
and it is a supplenentary question to an earlier question that<br />
Mr. McCallumn asked, and you said that you were trying to<br />
depoliticise the Public Service by making these personal<br />
appointments. I was wondering would he relinquish his other<br />
public service posts by joining you?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: He will be joining my staff. The conditions<br />
are a matter of discussion between him and Sir John Bunting.<br />
I think there were discussions today, but I'm not sure if,<br />
because of the visits to Government House, this has been done<br />
yet. </p>
<p>13.<br />
MAX HAtWKINS: On regional development. During the campaign,<br />
you also mentioned Townsville as one of the key centres that<br />
you would like to see reasonably developed. Do you still hold<br />
to that view now that you haven't won the seat of Herbert which<br />
you hoped to win?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Of course. There was never any prospect of<br />
us winning Indi or Farrer, but what I've said about Albury-<br />
Wodonga stands. The significance, why I mentioned Townsville,<br />
of course, was it is a centre whose problems arise, whose<br />
advantages and problems alike arise from the Commonwealth's<br />
very great involvement there. It'd always had the involvement<br />
of the Air Force base, but of course in the last ten years<br />
there has been the upgraded railway from Mt. Isa and the<br />
consequent copper refinery; there has been the Army base;<br />
there are two C. S. I. R. O. Research Laboratories; there is the<br />
University. Accordingly, the demand on services in Townsville<br />
has been brought about by Commonwealth involvement more than in<br />
any centre in Australia other than Canberra itself. The one<br />
particular thing where Townsville is deficient, where the<br />
deficiencies are exceeded only by those of Adelaide, is in the<br />
quantity of the water. Adelaide, of course, has problems of<br />
quality of water as well. The other significance about<br />
Townsville is, of course, that it is the natural point of entry<br />
for one of Australia's greatest tourist attractions, the Barrier<br />
Reef, and is much closer to those countries from which tourists<br />
are most likely to come, Japan and America.<br />
ALAN RAM~' SEY: Prime Minister: I realise that this is not a<br />
matter of pressing urgency for the present administration, but<br />
do you share Mrs. Whitlam's views, publicised views, today on<br />
the legalisation of marijuana?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I have never discussed it with her. I think I<br />
will leave it to the new Ministry. In general, I would not<br />
expect on this matter any difference in approach from those<br />
which have been adopted or foreshadowed by Mr. Chipp. I would<br />
think this is one of those matters, such asi. Papua New Guinea<br />
under Mr. Peacock, where there will be no great differences<br />
between the outgoing administration and the full Ministry which<br />
will be appointed before Christmas.<br />
PAUL WEBSTER, " THEi AUSTRALIAN": Could I ask whether Australia<br />
will accept a limited form of representation from Taiwan as it<br />
has in Tokyo at present? Secondly, are you going to review<br />
your relations with South Vietnam and Cambodia, and thirdly, do<br />
you intend to seek some form of recognition in Hanoi?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: The last one would not be regarded as urgent<br />
by the prese . vt administration. The middle one, about South<br />
Vietnam, this is not a matter which the present administration<br />
would regard as calling for a decision within the next ten or<br />
twelve days. The first one, the..<br />
PAUL WIEBSTER: Taiwanese representation here in a limited form<br />
as it exists in Tokyo at present. </p>
<p>14.<br />
FRIKE MINISTER: This would appear a reasonable matter that<br />
there should be unofficial contacts, commercial contacts,<br />
between Taiwan and Australia after full-diplomatic representation<br />
between the People's Repablic and Australia just as there are<br />
still between Taiwan and Japan.<br />
JOHN STUBBS: As Minister of External Affairs~ and Prime<br />
Minister, what are you going to do about our political<br />
appointments of the pre-vious government such as Gordon Freeth<br />
in Tokyo, and Dame Annabelle Rankin in New Zealand? Will you<br />
replace them immediately, or have discussions with them?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: The present administration would not deal<br />
with either matter. If, in the next administration, I'm Minister<br />
for Foreign Affairs, as I expect, I would not think these are<br />
matters of any urgency whatever. I have no reason to believe<br />
that Dame Annabelle Rankin or the Honourable Gordon Freeth<br />
would not carry out the policies of the new government with<br />
complete competence and loyalty. In fact, there was an occasion<br />
for me to send a message today to New Zealand via Dame Annabelle<br />
Rankin and I gave instructions that my personal regards should<br />
be passed to her.<br />
DAVID SOLOMON: Sir, a multi-part question also. First of all,<br />
you mentioned Sir John Bunting. Could you say whether you have<br />
decided to keep him on as Secretary of the Prime Minister's<br />
Department and what other decisions you have made regarding<br />
senior Public Service appointments, and secondly, concerning<br />
open government, what do you intend to do to make open<br />
government a reality, and will you keep by your prior<br />
undertaking to have regular press conferences every Tuesday<br />
in Canberra?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I asked Sir John Bunting if he would be happy<br />
to continue in his present post, as I would be very happy if<br />
he were to do so. He said he would. I was pleased. It is my<br />
view that, whenever I am in Canberra on Tuesday, I should have<br />
a press conference. I suppose one would still have to work<br />
out what time suited the Press best. It may be that it might<br />
suit sometimes to have them in the morning, sometimes in the<br />
afternoon, but obviously I would take the advice, I would try<br />
to meet the advice, the wishes, of the President of the Gallery<br />
on such matters. Gentlemen, might I just say this; since there are<br />
quite a number of foreign policy issues upon which I have been<br />
asked questions. In the foreign affairs field there are a<br />
number of important questions I would like to discuss with<br />
my colleagues and my policy advisers rather than say things<br />
today which might have the effect of foreclosing some policy<br />
options open -to this administration or the full Ministry.<br />
The change of government, however, does provide a new<br />
opportunity for us to reassess a whole range of Australian<br />
foreign policies and attitudes. In the weeks ahead, I shall,<br />
in consultation with my Ministerial colleagues and my policy<br />
advisers, be reassessing these policies with the general<br />
intention of developing more constructive, flexible and<br />
progressive approaches to a number of foreign policy issues.<br />
I wouldn't want to say more now than that the general direction<br />
of my thinking is towards a more independent Australian stance<br />
in international affairs, an Australia which will be less </p>
<p>militarily oriented and not open to suggestions of racism;<br />
an Australia which will enjoy a growing standing as a<br />
distinctive, tolerant, co-operative and well regarded nation<br />
not only in the Asian and Pacific region, but in the world<br />
at large. I hope you don't mind me volunteering those comments.<br />
It is an early opportunity of me replying in general terms to<br />
the good wishes that I have received from a very great number<br />
of Heads of Government throughout the world, particularly heads<br />
of fraternal parties, other Social Democratic and Labor<br />
Parties, and Heads of Government in our region. Inevitably it<br />
will take me a few days before I can make an appropriate<br />
individual response to these expressions of goodwill which<br />
have been very heartening indeed. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
