<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10688</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                  THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                  DOORSTOP INTERVIEW                RAAF BASE, FAIRBAIRN</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/02/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...............................................</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, what message will you be giving the Australian troops?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, there are some things that I would like to say directly to</p>
<p>   them and not say to anybody else. I know that they will go with</p>
<p>   the total goodwill, the prayers and the hopes of all Australians.</p>
<p>   I remain hopeful that this dispute can be settled without military</p>
<p>   force. Nobody wants military force to be used. The decision as to</p>
<p>   whether military force is used lies in the hands of Saddam Hussein</p>
<p>   and the Iraqi leadership. Even at this eleventh hour, I hope that</p>
<p>   they see the commonsense and they see it in the interests of their</p>
<p>   own people that they pull back and recognise that nothing is to</p>
<p>   be gained and a lot is to be lost and, perhaps, the lives of innocent</p>
<p>   people in the process.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[Inaudible]</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I hope that every opportunity, including that, is explored.</p>
<p>   We have to be realistic. We have to continue working to achieve</p>
<p>   a peaceful solution. In the end, if that is not possible, then we're</p>
<p>   left with no alternative. And I hope that is a message that will</p>
<p>   ultimately get through to the Iraqi leadership.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>By this stage you must be even more conscious of the possibility</p>
<p>   of Australian casualties in the Gulf. How do you feel about that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I have thought a great deal about everything surrounding</p>
<p>   this. And, naturally, the safety of Australian servicemen is the</p>
<p>   thing upper most in my mind. You always have a sense of dread when</p>
<p>   something such as this comes about. And we must all hope and pray,</p>
<p>   firstly, that a peaceful settlement is possible and that if it is</p>
<p>   not, that our own men return safely to their families.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, do you have [inaudible] confidence in Richard Butler?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[Inaudible]</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, he's employed by UNSCOM. He's not employed by the</p>
<p>   Australian Government. I don't know that I'm required</p>
<p>   to give certificates in relation to people employed by others. But</p>
<p>   I have no reason to criticise the job that he's done on this.</p>
<p>   My understanding is that he brings a great deal of professionalism</p>
<p>   to the job.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, will the terms of engagement authorise Australian</p>
<p>   troops to operate on Iraqi soil?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I'm not going to talk about the terms of engagement at present.</p>
<p>   The decision that's been taken so far is merely to deploy.</p>
<p>   If it becomes necessary to take a further decision to authorise</p>
<p>   combat participation then the rules of engagement will be involved</p>
<p>   in that. It's just not appropriate for me, now, to talk about</p>
<p>   rules of engagement. It may not be appropriate to talk about them</p>
<p>   in the future. Let's hope that it doesn't become necessary.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[Inaudible]</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I'm sorry, I didn't hear that.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Are there signs of any other countries to join...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I think what's happened over the past few days is you've</p>
<p>   seen a significant build-up including, in particular, New Zealand.</p>
<p>   And when you throw in the availability of bases and other facilities</p>
<p>   you are starting to see a much stronger international coalition</p>
<p>   being put together. </p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
<p>[Ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
