<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3098</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. E.G. WHITLAM, Q.C., M.P., FOR THE UNITED NATIONS ASSOCIATION HUMAN RIGHTS DAY, A.N.U., CANBERRA, 10 DECEMBER, 1973</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/12/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003098.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE PRIME M1INISTER, MR. E. G. WHITLAM, Q. C., o<br />
FOR THE UNITED NATIONS ASSOCIATION HUMAN RIGHTS DAY, AIN. US,<br />
CANBERRA, 10 DECEMBER, 1973*<br />
TODAY IS THE 25TH ANNIVERSARY OF THE ADOPTION OF THE<br />
UNIVERSAL DECLARATION OF HUMAN RIGHTS BY THE GENERAL ASSEMBLY<br />
OF THE UNITED NATIONS1<br />
THAT DECLARATION HAS COME TO BE RECOGNISED AS ONE OF<br />
THE GREAT ENLIGHTENED EVENTS IN MODERN HISTORY. ITS ANNIVERSARY<br />
MARKS THE BEGINNING OF AN EQUALLY HOPEFUL AND ENLIGHTENED<br />
MOVEMENT, FOR THE GENERAL ASSEMBLY HAS ALSO DECIDED TO LAUNCH<br />
ON THIS DAY A DECADE FOR ACTION TO COMBAT RACISM AND RACIAL<br />
DISCRItINATION. IT IS IN THE CONTEXT OF THESE TWO GREAT<br />
ACHIEVEMENTS THE CELEBRATION OF ONE HISTORIC ERA AND THE<br />
INAUGUR~ ATION OF ANOTHER THAT I WISH TO SPEAK TO YOU OF<br />
AUSTRALIA ' S PART IN FURTHERING THE CAUSE OF HUMAN RIGHTS FOR<br />
THE WORLD'IS PEOPLE.<br />
IT WILL BE NECESSARY FOR ME, IN DOING SO, TO POINT TO<br />
DIFFERENCES BETWEEN THE POLITICAL PARTIES ON THIS ISSUE. I HOPE<br />
YOU WILL UNDERSTAND MY PURPOSE IN DOING SO~ I HAVE NO WISH<br />
TO BE OVERTLY PARTISAN, BUT I CANNOT EXPLAIN THE POLICIES OF<br />
THE PRESENT GOVERNMENT WITHOUT DRAWING ATTENTION TO THOSE OF<br />
OUR PREDECESSORS. IT WILL BE SEEN, IN MANY CASES, I BELIEVE,<br />
THAT THE RECORD OF OUR PREDECESSORS WAS ONE OF NEGLIGENCE AND<br />
INACTION, AND IN THIS CRUCIAL AREA OF FOREIGN POLICY, NEGLIGENCE<br />
AND INACTION CANNOT BE TOLERATED. THE STRUGGLE FOR UNIVERSAL<br />
HUMAN RIGHTS IS A PROTRACTED AND PERHAPS AN UNENDING STRUGGLE. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
THERE IS RARELY A TIME IN WORLD AFFAIRS WHEN SOME NEW THREAT<br />
TO HUMAN RIGHTS SOME NEW OPPRESSION, SOME NEW FORM OF DEPOTISM<br />
IS NOT ABROAD, GOVERNMENTS HAVE A CONTINUING OBLIGATION TO DO<br />
ALL IN THEIR POWER TO PROMOTE RESPECT FOR HUMAN RIGHTS, No<br />
COUNTRY HAS A GREATER OBLIGATION IN THIS REGARD THAN AUSTRALIA,<br />
A MEDIUM POWER ENJOYING CLOSE AND CORDIAL RELATIONS WITH MANY<br />
DIFFERENT COUNTRIES WITH DIFFERENT POLITICAL'SYSTEMS1<br />
IT IS A FUNDAMENTAL OBJFCTIVE OF THE LABOR GOVERNMENT TO<br />
ENSURE THAT AUSTRALIA'S POLICIES ARE SOUNDLY BASED ON RESPECT<br />
FOR, AND ON THE PROTECTION AND ENHANCEMENT OF, CIVIL LIBERTIES<br />
AND BASIC HUMAN RIGHTS, , WE BELIEVE THAT POLICIES AND ATTITUDES<br />
TO HUMAN RIGHTS CANNOT BE SEPARATED FROM ACTION AGAINST THE EVILS<br />
OF DISCRIMINATION IN ANY FORM, INCLUDING DISCRIMINATION BASED ON<br />
RACE, OUR POLICIES AND ACTIONS OVER THE PAST-YEAR HAVE BEEN<br />
DELIBERATELY DESIGNED TO GET AWAY FROM THE TENTATIVE AND DILATORY<br />
ATTITUDES OF THE PAST, THE RECORD OF OUR PREDECESSORS WAS MARKED<br />
BY A LACK OF ANY SENSE OF INITIATIVE IN THE PROMOTION AND<br />
PROTECTION OF HUMAN RIGHTS IN OUR OWN COMMUNITY AND IN THE WORLD<br />
AT LARGE, THEY WERE HALF-HEARTED IN RESPONDING TO THE WORK OF<br />
THE UNITED NATIONS, AND THEIR LACK OF ENTHUSIASM WAS USUALLY<br />
MATCHED IN THE RESPONSE OF THE STATES. </p>
<p>0 -3-<br />
LET ME GIVE A TYPICAL EXAMPLE. AS A RESULT OF AN<br />
OBLIGATION ARISING FROM THE 1946 AMENDMENTS TO THE<br />
INTERNATIONAL LABOUR ORGANISATION CONSTITUTION, THE LABOR<br />
GOVERNMENT IN 1947 INSTITUTED AN ADVISORY COMMITTEE. OF THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN AND STATE DEPARTMENTS OF LABOUR TO CARRY OUT AN<br />
ANNUAL REVIEW OF THE WHOLE RANGE OF LABOUR MATTERS AROUND APRIL<br />
OF EACH YEAR. THIS MACHINERY WAS IN EXISTENCE THROUGHOUT THETERM<br />
OF OFFICE OF OUR PREDECESSORS BUT IT WAS ONLY WHEN THE<br />
PRESENT GOVERNMENT CAME TO POWER THAT THE MINISTER FOR LABOUR,<br />
MR. CLYDE CAMERON, TOOK THE INITIATIVE TO USE THIS MACHINERY<br />
TO GIVE ACTIVE ENCOURAGEMENT TO THE RATIFICATION AND APPLICATION<br />
OF I. L. O. CONVENTIONS. " MR. CAMERON HAS MOVED QUICKLY TO' ESTABLISH<br />
CONSULTATIVE MACHINERY WITH THE STATES AT MINISTERIAL, PERMANENT<br />
HEAD, AND TECHNICAL OFFICER LEVEL TO DETERMINE AN ORDER* OF<br />
ORIORITY FOR THE CONSIDERATION OF CONVENTIONS AND TO ENSURE THAT<br />
ACTION 15 TAKEN ON THESE CONVENTIONS REGARDED AS REQUIRING<br />
URGENT OUR PREDECESSORS MADE THE FEDERAL SYSTEM A FARCE BY<br />
USING IT AS AN EXCUSE TO JUSTIFY ITS OWN INACTION. THEY DID<br />
LITTLE OR NOTHING TO STIMULATE ACTION ON THE PART OF THE STATES.<br />
FOR EXAMPLE, THEY AVOIDED THEIR RESPONSIBILITIES IN RESPECT OF<br />
I. L. O. CONVENTION No. 100 EQUAL REMUNERATION, 19511 BY HIDING<br />
BEHIND THE CHANGES OF MINDS ON THE PART OF TWO OF THE STATES<br />
TOWARDS RATIFICATION AND THE UNWILLINGNESS OF THE OTHER<br />
TO AGREE TO RATIFICATION. IT IS TRUE THAT BECAUSE OF THE<br />
FEDERAL SYSTEM AUSTRALIA IS AT A DISADVANTAGE IN BEING FACED<br />
WITH UNNECESSARILY COMPLICATED PROCEDURES FOR GIVING EFFECT<br />
TO INTERNATIONAL LEGAL INSTRUMENTS. THESE DEFICIENC* IES IN OUR </p>
<p>-4-<br />
SYSTEM SHOULD NOT BE ALLOWED TO BESMIRCH AND AFFRONT AUSTRALIA'S<br />
IMAGE. OUR GOVERNMENT HAS ACCORDINGLY FOUND IT NECESSARY TO<br />
TAKE ADVANTAGE OF THE B( TERNAL AFFAIRS POWER IN THE CONSTITUTION<br />
TO GIVE EFFECT 70TO OUR INTERNATIONAL OBLIGATIONS.<br />
To MY MIND, THE UNIVERSAL DECLARATION IS ONE OF THE<br />
MOST SIGNIFICANT AND ENLIGHTENED ACHIEVEMENTS OF THE UNITED<br />
NATIONS. THE CELEBRATION OF THIS ANNIVERSARY AFFORDS AN<br />
OPPORTUNITY FOR THE GOVERNMENT TO RE-DEDICATE ITSELF TO THE<br />
PROMOTION OF HUMAN RIGHTS THROUGHOUT AUSTRALIA; THE ASSOCIATION<br />
OF THE AUSTRALIAN LABOR PARTY WITH THE UNIVERSAL DECLARATION<br />
DATES FROM THE DRAFTING OF THE DOCUMENT IN WHICH DR. EVATT,<br />
AS MINISTER FOR EXTERNAL AFFAIRS AND ATTORNEY-GENERAL TOOK A<br />
CLOSE PERSONAL INTEREST. HE WAS PRESIDENT OF THE GENERAL ASSEMBLY<br />
WHEN THE DECLARATION WAS ADOPTED. HE SAID ON THAT OCCASION<br />
THAT THE DOCUMENT " WAS BACKED BY THE AUTHORITY OF THE BODY OF<br />
OPINION OF THE UNITED NATIONS AS A WHOLE AND MILLIONS OF PEOPLE,<br />
MEN, WOMEN AND CHILDREN ALL OVER THE WORLD WOULD TURN TO IT FOR<br />
HELP, GUIDANCE AND INSPIRATION." THROUGHOUT MY PARLIAMENTARY<br />
CAREER I HAVE TAKEN A KEEN PERSONAL INTEREST IN ALL ASPECTS<br />
OF HUMAN RIGHTS AND IN PARTICULAR IN THE PROGRESS MADE BY<br />
AUSTRALIA TOWARDS RATIFICATION OF INTERNATIONAL HUMAN RIGHTS<br />
AGREEMENTS. </p>
<p>ONE OF MY EARLIEST ACTIONS AS PRIME MINISTER WAS TO INITIATE<br />
AN EXAMINATION OF ALL THE INTERNATIONAL INSTRUMENTS'CONCERNED<br />
WITH HUMAN RIGHTS TO DETERMINE THE ACTION WE SHOULD BE TAKING<br />
TO GIVE EFFECT rO THEM. WE SIGNED THE TWO'UNITED NATIONS HUMAN<br />
RIGHTS COVENANTS ON CIVIL AND POLITICAL RIGHTS AND ON ECONOMIC,<br />
SOCIAL AND CULTURAL RIGHTS ON 18 DECEMBER 19721* THE COVENANTS<br />
COMPLEMENT EACH OTHER AND WERE ADOPTED BY THE GENERAL ASSEMBLY<br />
IN 1966. IT IS THE INTENTION OF THE GOVERNMENT TO PROCEED TO<br />
SIMULTANEOUS RATIFICATION OF THEM AS SOON AS ENABLING LEGISLATION<br />
HAS BEEN PASSED BY PARLIAMENT.<br />
THE UNIVERSAL DECLARATION IS A FOCUS OF ATTENTION FOR<br />
THE ASPIRATIONS OF ALL NATIONS AND PEOPLES CONCERNED WITH BASIC<br />
RIGHTS AND FREEDOMS. THOUGH THE DECLARATION HAS INFLUENCED THE<br />
LEGAL STANDARDS OF OTHER COUNTRIES AROUND THE WORLD IN SUCH<br />
DOCUMENTS AS THE CANADIAN BILL OF RIGHTS., 1960, AND THE BASIC<br />
LAW OF THE GERMAN FEDERAL REPUBLIC, 1949, EXISTING LAWS IN<br />
AUSTRALIA HAVE NOT ADEQUATELY PROTECTED THE RIGHTS AND FREEDOMS<br />
OF THE INDIVIDUAL AS SET OUT IN THE DECLARATION. THjE GOVERNMENT<br />
IS ACTING TO CORRECT THIS SITUATION. ON 21 NOVEMBER T: hE ATTORNEY--<br />
GEN4ERAL, SENATOR LIONEL MURPHY, INTRODUCED INTO THE PARLIAMENT,<br />
THE HUMAN RIGHTS BILL 1973 AND THE RACIAL DiSCRIMINATIPH BILL-1973,<br />
BOTH BILLS ARE DESIGNED TO EXTEND AND SAFEGUARD THE RIGHTS ANiD<br />
FREEDOMS OF EVERY AUSTRALIAN IN ACCORDANCE WITH INTERNATIONAL<br />
STANDARDS. </p>
<p>-6-<br />
THE HUMAN RIGHTS BILL WILL GUARANTEE THAT EVERYONE<br />
IS ENTITLED TO THE EQUAL PROTECTION OF THE LAW AND TO CERTAIN<br />
BASIC RIGHTS AND FREEDOMS, INCLUDING THE FREEDOM OF THOUGHT,<br />
CONSCIENCE AND RELIGION; FREEDOM OF EXPRESSION; FREEDOM OF<br />
PEACEFUL ASSEMBLY AND ASSOCIATION; FREEDOM OF MOVEMENT; THE<br />
RIGHT TO VOTE AND TO EXERCISE PUBLIC FUNCTIONS ON-A BASIS OF<br />
EQUALITY; THE RIGHT TO PRIVACY; FREEDOM FROM ARBITRARY ARREST<br />
AND DETENTION; THE RIGHT TO A FAIR TRIAL; AND FREEDOM FROM<br />
CRUEL OR DEGRADING TREATEMENT OR PUNISHMENT. To SAFEGUARD THE<br />
PROTECTION OF THESE RIGHTS, THE BILL ESTABLISHES THE OFFICE OF<br />
A HUMAN RIGHTS COMMISSIONER. HIS TASK WILL BE TO EXAMINE ANY<br />
BREACHES OF INDIVIDUAL LIBERTY IN THIS COUNTRY AND WHERE NECESSARY<br />
TO BRING LEGAL ACTION TO ENSURE THAT THE LAW WITH REGARD TO<br />
FUNDAMENTAL RIGHTS IS ENFORCED.<br />
MANY AUSTRALIANS TAKE THE EXISTENCE OF THESE RIGHTS FOR<br />
GRANTED. THEY HAVE NOT APPRECIATED THE NEED FOR ACTION TO<br />
ENSURE THAT THE RIGHTS ARE PROTECTED AND GUARANTEED WITH THE<br />
FULL FORCE OF LAW. THE IMPORTANCE OF THE HUMAN RIGHTS BILL IS<br />
THAT IT WILL MAKE THESE BASIC RIGHTS AND FREEDOMS LEGALLY<br />
ENFORCEABLE IN AUSTRALIA. THE. INDIVIDUAL WILL BE ABLE, THROUGH<br />
THE COURTS, TO INSIST UPON HIS RIGHTS. </p>
<p>0 -7-<br />
THE HUMAN RIGHTS BILL ALSO SEEKS APPROVAL FOR RATIFICATION<br />
OF THE UNITED NATIONS CONVENTION ON THE POLITICAL RIGHTS OF WOMEN<br />
( 1952). AUSTRALIA HAS NOT PREVIOUSLY BECOME A PARTY TO THIS<br />
CONVENTION BECAUSE THERE ARE STATUTORY LIMITATIONS AND<br />
DISCRIMINATORY ASPECTS OF VARIOUS STATE LAWS IN AUSTRALIA WHICH<br />
DO NOT COMPLY WITH ITS PROVISIONS1 THE ABILITY OF THE<br />
GOVERNMENT TO RATIFY THIS CONVENTION WILL BE A MAJOR STEP<br />
FORWARD IN PROMOTING THE RIGHTS OF WOMEN THROUGHOUT OUR COMMUNITY<br />
ON EQUAL TERMS WITH MEN WIT7HOUT ANY-DISCRIMINATION8<br />
THE FIRST ARTICLE OF -1-1L UNIVERSAL DECLARATION OF HUMAN<br />
RIGHTS PROCLAIMS THAT " ALL HUMAN BEINGS ARE BORN FREE AND EQUAL<br />
IN DIGNITY AND RIGHTS", ARTICLE 2 STATES THAT " EVERYONE IS<br />
ENTITLED TO THE RIGHTS AND FREEDOMS SET OUT IN THE DECLARATION<br />
WITHOUT DISTINCTION OF ANY KINDo INCLUDING DISCRIMINATION ON THE<br />
GROUNDS OF RACE, COLOUR OR NATIONAL ORIGIN" THE GENERAL ASSEMBLY<br />
ELABORATED ON THESE ARTICLES WHEN, IN 1965, j IT ADOPTED AN<br />
INTERNATIONAL CONVENTION ON THE ELIMINATION OF ALL FORMS OF<br />
RACIAL DISCRIMINATION. THE CONVENTION RECOGNISES THAT ANY<br />
DOCTRINE OF SUPERIORITY BASED ON RACIAL DIFFERENCE IS FUNDAMENTALLY<br />
FALSE, MORALLY INDEFENSIBLE AND WITHOUT ANY SOCIAL JUSTIFICATION.<br />
SEVENTY-FIVE COUNTRIES HAVE SO FAR BECOME PARTIES TO THE<br />
CONVENTION ON WHICH OUR RACIAL DISCRIMINATION BILL IS BASED.<br />
As PROVIDED UNDER CLAUSE 6, AUSTRALIA WILL RAT'IFY THE<br />
CONVENTION AS SOON AS THE BILL IS APPROVED. </p>
<p>-8-<br />
THE PASSAGE OF THIS BILL AND THE RATIFICATION OF THE<br />
CONVENTION WILL BE AMONG THE MOST IMPORTANT CONTRIBUTION,<br />
WHICH AUSTRALIA CAN MAKE TO THE INTERNATIONAL CAMPAIGN TO<br />
ELIMINATE RACIAL DISCRIMINATION IN THE DECADE BEING INAUGURATED<br />
TODAY. THE GOVERNMENT IS ALREADY WELL PLACED TO PARTICIPATE<br />
POSITIVELY IN THE INTERNATIONAL DECADE BY THE STAND WE HAVE<br />
TAKEN IN THE UNITED NATIONS IN FORCEFULLY CONDEMNING ALL FORMS<br />
OF RACIAL DISCRIMINATION AND BY OUR VOTES CONDEMNING THE POLICIES<br />
AND PRACTICES OF APARTHEID AND COLONIALISM.<br />
THE HUMAN RIGHTS BILL AND THE RACIAL DISCRIMINATION BILL<br />
ARE OF SPECIAL INTEREST AND RELEVANCE TO ALL SECTIONS OF OUR<br />
COMMUNITY, PARTICULARLY OUR ABORIGINAL AND MIGRANT COMMUNITIES<br />
WHO HAVE SUFFERED VARIOUS FORMS OF DISCRIMINATION. THE BILLS<br />
ARE AN IMPORTANT PART OF THE GOVERNMENT'S EFFORT TO ENSURE THAT<br />
THE ABORIGINAL PEOPLE OF AUSTRALIA AND THE PEOPLE WHO HAVE<br />
MIGRATED TO THIS COUNTRY ARE TRULY EQUAL BEFORE THE LAW AND ARE<br />
ABLE TO PARTICIPATE IN AUSTRALIAN LIFE ON EQUAL TERMS WITH THE<br />
REST OF THE AUSTRALIAN COMMUNITY. THE BILLS COMPLEMENT THE<br />
POLICIES WHICH WE ARE ENDEAVOURING TO PURSUE IN ESTABLISHING<br />
ABORIGINAL LAND RIGHTS AND IMPROVING THE GENERAL WELL-BEING OF<br />
THE ABORIGINAL COMMUNITY. </p>
<p>-9-<br />
A MAJOR STEP FORWARD IN HUMAN RIGHTS WAS THE DECLARATION<br />
BY THE GOVERNMENT THIS YEAR OF A NATIONAL POLICY To ELIMINATE<br />
DISCRIMINATION IN EMPLOYMENT AND OCCUPATION. MR. CAMERON<br />
ANNOUNCED THIS POLICY IN A STATEMENT IN THE PARLIAMENT IN MAY<br />
CONCERNING THE ACTION BEING TAKEN BY THE GOVERNMENT TO RATIFY<br />
THE TUL. O. CONVENTION No. 111 ON DISCRIMINATION ( EMPLOYMENT<br />
AND OCCUPATION) 1958, AUSTRALIA RATIFIED'THIS CONVENTION ON<br />
JUNE. THE GOVERNMENT'S POLICY TO ELIMINATE DISCRIMINATION IN<br />
EMPLOYMENT AND OCCUPATION HAS THE SUPPORT OF ALL STATE GOVERNMENTS,<br />
MAJOR EMPLOYER ORGANISATIONS AND T HE TRADE UNIONS. THE GOVERNMENT<br />
HAS ESTABLISHED COMMITTEES ON DISCRIMINATION IN EMPLOYMENT AND<br />
OCCUPATION AT THE NATIONAL LEVEL AND IN ALL STATES. STEPS HAVE<br />
ALREADY BEEN TAKEN TO LAUNCH A NATION-WIDE EDUCATION CAMPAIGN<br />
AIMED AT INFLUENCING COMMUNITY ATTITUDES IN ORDER TO REMOVE<br />
DISCRIMINATORY PRACTICES IN EMPLOYMENT.<br />
A MAJOR ROLE OF THE COMMITTEES IS TO INVESTIGATE<br />
COMPLAINTS OF DISCRIMINATION AND TO DEAL WITH THEM EFFECTIVELy.<br />
THE NATIONAL COMMITTEE ON DISCRIMINATION IN EmPLOYMENT AND<br />
OCCUPATION HAS THE SPECIAL FUNCTION OF ADVISING THE GOVERNMENT<br />
ON THE IMPLEMENTATION OF POLICY AND THE DEVELOPMENT OF A NATIONAL<br />
EDUCATION PUBLICITY CAMPAI6 N TO PROMOTE REAL EQUALITY OF OPPORTUNI r<br />
IN EMPLOYMENT. </p>
<p>THE GOVERNMENT AND THE PEOPLE OF AUSTRALIA OWE A<br />
CONSIDERABLE DEBT TO THE INTERNATIONAL LABOUR ORGANISATION<br />
FOR ITS WORK IN DEVELOPING POSITIVE POLICIES WHICH PAY FULL<br />
RESPECT TO HUMAN RIGHTS IN THE FIELDS OF EMPLOYMENT AND<br />
OCCUPATION. IN ADDITION TO THE CONVENTION ON DISCRIMINATION<br />
( EMPLOYMENT AND OCCUPATION) AUSTRALIA HAS ALSO RATIFIED TWO<br />
OTHER IMPORTANT HUMAN RIGHTS CONVENT. IONS OF THE I... DURING<br />
THE YEAR: CONVENTION NO. 87 FREEDOM OF ASSOCIATION AND<br />
PROTECTION OF THE RIGHT To0 ORGANISE, 1948;<br />
CONVENTION No 98 RIGHT XPORGANISE AND<br />
COLLECTIVE WAGAINING, 14<br />
THE GOVERNMENT IS NOW CLOSE TO FULFILLING ITS* OBJECTIVE<br />
OF RATIFYING ALL THE 11L. O. CONVENTIONS IN THE FIELD OF HOiMAN<br />
RIGHTS. THERE REMAIN OUTSTANDING CONVENTION No. 100 EQUAL<br />
REMUNERAT ION, 1951, AND CONVENTION No. 107 PROTECTION AND<br />
INTEGRATION OF INDIGENOUS AND TRIBAL POPULATIONS, 1957. THE<br />
GOVERNMENT IS GiVING PRIORITY ATTENTION TO THE RATIFICATION OF<br />
THESE TWO CONVENTIONS.<br />
THE FURTHER ACTION WHICH THE GOVERNMENT IS ABLE TO TAKE<br />
IN REGARD TO THE RATIFICATION OF I. L. O, CONVENTION No. 100<br />
WILL DEPEND UPON THE CONSIDERATION OF THE NATIONAL WAGE CASE<br />
WHICH WILL SOON COME BEFORE THE AUSTRALIAN CONCILIATION AND<br />
ARBITRATION COMMISSION, CONVENTION No. 107 IS CLOSELY CONNECTED<br />
WITH THE QUESTION OF ABORIGINAL LAND RIGHTS WHICH IS CURRENTLY<br />
THE SUBJECT OF STUDY BY THE COMMISSION HEADED BY MR. JUSTICE<br />
A. E. WOODWARD. THE WOODWARD COMMISSION HAS COMMENTED IN ITS </p>
<p>PRELIMINARY REPORT THAT IT IS IMPORTANT THAT NO ACTION BE TAKEN<br />
TO PREJUDICE EVENTUAL AUSTRALIAN RATIFICATION OF CONVENTION No,<br />
107 WHICH EMPHASISES THE RECOGNITION OF THE RIGHT TO OWNERSHIP BY<br />
INDIGENOUS PEOPLES OF THE LANDS THEY TRADITIONALLY OCCUPY.<br />
THE GOVERNMENT IS ALSO AIMING IN THE NEAR FUTURE TO<br />
MAKE FURTHER ADVANCES IN BRINGING WORK STA NDARDS. IN AUSTRALIA<br />
UP TO THE HIGHEST INTERNATIONAL, INDUSTRIAL AND SOCIAL LEVELS,<br />
THE DEPARTMENT OF LABOUR IS CONSULTING WITH THREE STATE GOVERNMENTS<br />
ABOUT THE REMOVAL OF HINDRANCES To AUSTRALIAN RATIFICATION OF<br />
CONVENTION No. 81, LABOUR INSPECTION,$ 1946. CON* SULTATIONS ARE<br />
ALSO CONTINUING BETWEEN-OFFICERS OF AUSTRALIAN AND STATE,<br />
DEPARTMENTS TO DETERMINE WHAT STEPS MIGHT BE NEEDED TO -INTRODUCE<br />
LEGISLATION IN AUSTRALIA TO COMPLY WITH CONVENTION No. 135,<br />
PROTECTION AND FACILITIES AFFORDED TO WORKERS REPRESENTATIVES, 1971,<br />
WHICH CAME INTO FORCE ON 30 JUNE THIS YEAR, AND ON CONVENTION No.<br />
119 GUARDING OF MACHINERY, 1963,<br />
I AM ALSO PLEASED TO BE ABLE TO ANNOUNCE TODAY THAT THE<br />
GOVERNMENT HAS NOW COMPLETED ALL THE NECESSARY PROCEDURES TO ENABLE<br />
US TO RATIFY IMMEDIATELY THE CONVENTION RELATING TO THE STATUS<br />
OF STATELESS PERSONS 1954, THE CONVENTION ON THE REDUCTION OF<br />
STATELESSNESS 1961, THE PROTOCOL RELATING TO THE STATUS OF<br />
REFUGEES 1966, AND THE PROTOCOL RELATING To REFUGEE SEAMEN 1973. </p>
<p>-12-<br />
AUSTRALIA ACCEDED TO THE CONVENTION ON THE STATUS<br />
OF REFUGEES IN 1954. ON 18 APRIL THIS YEAR THE GOVERNMENT<br />
RATIFIED THE 1957 HAGUE AGREEMENT RELATING To REFUGEE SEAMEN,<br />
WHICH HAD COME INTO FORCE IN 1961. THE GOVERNMENT IS ALSO TAKING<br />
ACTION IN REGARD TO THE PROTOCOL RELATING TO THE 1960 UNESCO<br />
CONVENTION AGAINST DISCRIMINATION IN EDUCATION WHICH AUSTRALIA<br />
RATIFIED ON 29 NOVEMBER 1966. THE GOVERNMENT HAS INSTITUTED<br />
ACTION TO DETERMINE WHETHER AUSTRALIA S HOULD ACCEDE TO THE 1962<br />
PROTOCOL TO THIS CONVENTION, THE PRINCIPAL PURPOSE OF WHICH IS TO<br />
ESTABLISH MACHINERY TO DEAL WITH VIOLATIONS OF THE CONVENTION,<br />
THE INTRODUCTION OF LEGISLATION AND THE RATIFICATION OF<br />
UNITED NATIONS AND I. L. O. AND UNESCO CONVENTIONS HAS BEEN<br />
ACCOMPANIED BY VIGOROUS GOVERNMENT ACTION IN OTHER FIELDS<br />
AFFECTING THE HUMAN RIGHTS OF EVERYONE WHO LIVES IN AUSTRALIA,<br />
THE GOVERNMENT HAS BEEN ACTIVE IN PROMOTING EQUAL<br />
EMPLOYMENT OPPORTUNITIES FOR WOMEN AND IN IMPROVING THEIR<br />
CONDITIONS OF WORK. IN THE AUSTRALIAN PUBLIC SERVICE THE GOVERNMENT<br />
HAS SET STANDARDS FOR OTHER EMPLOYERS TO FOLLOW, FOR EXAMPLE,<br />
THE PUBLIC SERVICE PROVIDES EQUAL PAY FOR WOMEN AND HAS RECENTLY<br />
EXTENDED THE PROVISIONS FOR MATERNITY LEAVE TO 12 WEEKS PAID<br />
LEAVE. TO ENABLE WOMEN TO PURSUE THEIR CAREERS IN A CONTINUOUS<br />
FASHION AND MAKE A GREATER CONTRIBUTION TO THE LABOUR FORCE,<br />
THE PUBLIC SERVICE BOARD IS CURRENTLY EXAMINING ASPECTS OF PARTTIME<br />
EMPLOYMENT IN THE AUSTRALIAN PUBLIC SERVICE. </p>
<p>-13-<br />
ACTION TAKEN BY THE GOVERNMENT IN THE AREA OF WOMEN'S<br />
EMPLOYMENT INCLUDES THE FOLLOWING MEASURES:<br />
SUCCESSFUL INTERVENTION IN DECEMBER 1972 IN<br />
PROCEEDINGS BEFORE THE AUSTRALIAN CONCILIATION<br />
AND ARBITRATION COMMISSION'TO HAVE ESTABLISHED<br />
THE PRINCIPLE OF EQUAL PAY FOR WORK OF EQUAL VALUE,<br />
CONSULTATIONS WITH STATE GOVERNMENTS HAVE LED TO MOST<br />
STATES AGREEING TO THIS PRINCIPLE.<br />
THE PROVISION OF TRAINING OPPORTUNITIES FOR WOMEN<br />
WISHING TO ENTER OR RE-ENTER THE LABOUR FORCE AFTER<br />
A PERIOD OF DOMESTIC RESPONSIBILITY. THIS IS'PROVIDED<br />
UNDER THE EMPLOYMENT TRAINING SCHEME FOR WOMEN<br />
ADMINISTERED BY THE DEPARTMENT OF LABOUR.<br />
THE RANGE OF BENEFITS PROVIDED UNDER THIS SCHEME<br />
IS CURRENTLY BEING EXAMINED WITH A VIEW TO<br />
FACILITATING FURTHER THE ENTRY OF WOMEN TO THE<br />
LABOUR FORCE AND IMPROVING THFIR EMPLOYMENT<br />
OPPORTUNITIES1 PROVISION FOR ALLEGATIONS OF DISCRIMINATION IN<br />
EMPLOYMENT ON THE GROUNDS OF SEX. TO BE INVESTIGATED<br />
THROUGH THE SETTING UP OF COMMITTEES ON DISCRIMINATION<br />
IN EMPLOYMENT AND OCCUPATION, </p>
<p>-1LV<br />
THROUGH ITS IMMIGRATION PROGRAM, THE GOVERNMENT HAS<br />
ACTED TO REMOVE ANY SUGGESTION OF DISCRIMINATION ON GROUNDS<br />
OF RACE, COLOUR OR NATIONALITY.<br />
UNDER THE REVISED POLICY, ALL PEOPLE WHO CAN MEET<br />
SELECTION CRITERIA ARE ELIGIBLE EQUALLY FOR SETTLEMENT IN AUSTRALIA.<br />
THE MAIN EMPHASIS OF THE PROGRAM IS NOW ON FAMILY ' REUNION AND<br />
THE NATIONAL NEED. AUSTRALIA'S CITIZENSHIP LEGISLATION HAS<br />
BEEN AMENDED SO THAT IT NOW APPLIES WITHOUT DISCRIMINATION TO<br />
PEOPLE FROM ALL COUNTRIES. VISITOR VISA REQUIREMENT S ALSO HAVE<br />
BEEN STREAMLINED TO PROMOTE INTERCHANGE AND GOODWILL BETWEEN<br />
AUSTRALIA AND OTHER COUNTRIES. 1A NATIONAL COMMUNITY RELATIONS<br />
COMMITTEE AND TASK FORCES IN THE STATES HAVE BEEN ESTABLISHED<br />
TO ENQUIRE INTO ALL ASPECTS OF DISCRIMINATION AGAINST MIGRANTS.<br />
IN THE LIGHT OF THESE AND OTHER ENQUIRIES, THE GOVERNMENT WILL<br />
CONTINUE TO TAKE WHATEVER ACTION IS NECESSARY TO END<br />
DISCRIMINATORY PRACTICES.<br />
IN THE SHORT SPACE OF TWELVE MONTHS, THE GOVERNMENT HAS<br />
TRANSFORMED AUSTRALIA'S INTERNATIONAL REPUTATION SO THAT OUR,<br />
COUNTRY HAS ONCE AGAIN ASSUMED ITS RIGHTFUL PLACE IN THE VANGUARD<br />
OF COUNTRIES PROMOTING HUMAN RIGHTS AND IN INSISTING ON THE HIGHEST<br />
INTERNATIONAL STANDARDS IN. EMPLOYMENT AND IN INDUSTRY. My<br />
COLLEAGUES IN THE MINISTRY HAVE CO-OPERATED WITH ENTHUSIASM AND<br />
IMAGINATION TO HELP ME MAKE 1973 THE MOST PRODUCTIVE YEAR OF<br />
ACHIEVEMENT WHICH AUSTRALIA HAS EVER HAD IN THESE VITAL FIELDS.<br />
WE HAVE DEMONSTRATED OUR SINCERITY IN FULFILLING OUR COMMITMENTS<br />
TO BRING ABOUT GREAT IMPROVEMENTS IN THE BASIC RIGHTS OF<br />
AUSTRALIANS. </p>
<p>THE GOVERNMENT HAS ALSO FACED SQUARELY THE FUNDAMENTAL<br />
ISSUE OF MATCHING THE POLICIES AND ACTIONS WE ADOPT AT HOME<br />
WITH FHOSE WE PURSUE ABROAD$<br />
WE HAVE SHOWN BY THE STAND WE HAVE TAKEN, PARTICULARLY<br />
IN THE UNITED NATIONS, THAT AUSTRALIA'S POLICIES ARE FIRMLY<br />
BASED ON HUMANITARIAN PRINCIPLES OF RACIAL EQUALITY, MUTUAL<br />
RESPECT AND THE ELIMINATION OF THE EVILS OF POVERTY,. ILLITERACY,<br />
DISCRIMINATION AND COLONIALISM.<br />
AL'STRALIA PAYS TRIBUTE TODAY TO THE CONTINUING CONTRIBUTION<br />
OF THE LNII. ED NATIONS IN PROMOTING UNIVERSAL RESPECT FOR, AND<br />
OBSERVANCE OF, FUNDAMENTAL FREEDOMS AND HUMAN RIGHTS,<br />
ON 20 APRIL 1972 IN A DEBATE IN THE HOUSE ON RACIAL<br />
PREJUDICE AND VIOLENCE I SAID THAT IN 1968, HUMAN RIGHTS YEAR,<br />
AND IN 1971, THE INTERNATIONAL YEAR FOR ACTION TO COMBAT<br />
I\ ACISM AND RACIAL DISCRIMINATION, THE UNITED NATIONS QUOTED THE<br />
CONVENTIONS WHICH AUSTRALIA HAD NOT IMPLEMENTED. ON THAT<br />
OCCASION I OBSERVED THAT WE HAD NOT IMPROVED OUR RECORD. BY<br />
OUR ACTIONS THIS YEAR THE GOVERNMENT HAS ENSURED THAT AUSTRALIA'S<br />
NATIONAL IMAGE WILL NEVER AGAIN BE AFFRONTED BY A POOR RECORD<br />
OF ACHIEVEMENT IN GIVING EFFECT TO INTERNATIONAL HUMAN RIGHTS<br />
TREATIES, </p>
<p>-16-<br />
I HOPE I MAY BE. FORGIVEN FOR CONCLUDING ON A PERSONAL<br />
NOTE BY RECALLING THAT MY FATHER', H. FE, WHITLAM, CONTRIBUTED<br />
TO THE WORK OF THE UNITED NATIONS IN'THE HUMAN RIGHTS FIELD<br />
AS AUSTRALIA'S REPRESENTATIVE AT THE 6TH SESSION OF THE HUMAN<br />
RIGHTS COMMISSION IN 1950 AND AT THE 10TH SESSION IN 1954,<br />
HE ALSO ACTED AS A CONSULTANT TO THE DEPARTMENT OF THE ATTORNEYGENERAL<br />
FOR SEVERAL YEARS ON HUMAN RIGHTS MATTERS, WHEN HE<br />
DELIVERED THE FIRST SIR ROBERT GARRAN ORATION IN 1959, HE<br />
REFERRED TO THE GENERAL OBLIGATION AND RESPONSIBILITY OF<br />
AUSTRALIA " TO SHARE IN THE TASK OF SECURING HIGHER STANDARDS<br />
AND BETTER LIVING CONDITIONS, NOT ALONE FOR HER PEOPLE, BUT FOR<br />
PEOPLE IN OTHER COUNTRIES OF THE WORLD" HE SAID:<br />
" THE FOUNDATION FOR THAT OBLIGATION AND RESPONSIBILITY<br />
WAS LAID WHEN, IN THE CHARTER OF THE UNITED NATIONS,. AUSTRALIA,<br />
IN COMPANY WITH OTHER NATIONS, REAFFIRMED HER FAITH IN THE<br />
DIGNITY AND WORTH OF THE HUMAN PERSON AND EXPRESSED HER<br />
DETERMINATION TO PROMOTE SOCIAL PROGPESS AND BETTER<br />
STANDARDS OF LIFE IN LARGER FREEDOM, AND LATER, WHEN SHE<br />
SUBSCRIBED TO THE UNIVERSAL DECLARATION OF HUMAN RIGHTS,<br />
ARTICLE 1 OF WHICH SETS FORTH THAT ALL-HUMAN BEINGS ARE<br />
FREE AND EQUALIN DIGNITY AND RIGHTS, THAT THEY ARE ENDOWED<br />
WITH REASON AND CONSCIENCE AND SHOULD ACT TOWARDS ONE<br />
ANOTHER IN A SPIRIT OF BROTHERHOOD, I" </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
