<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10959</transcript-id>
    <title>3 August 1998                                                                 TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                ADDRESS AT PARLIAMENTARY LUNCHEON IN HONOUR OF                THE PRIME MINISTER OF PAPUA NEW GUINEA                THE HON BILL SKATE CMG MP</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/08/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE................................................................................................</p>
<p>To Mr Bill Skate, the Prime Minister of Papua New Guinea, distinguished</p>
<p> guests ladies and gentlemen. There are a number of reasons why today</p>
<p> luncheon is a very special occasion. It brings together two nations</p>
<p> that have deep ties of history and people-to-people links. It is also</p>
<p> the first occasion on which Bill Skate as Prime Minister has visited</p>
<p> Canberra and we very very warmly welcome you Sir, not only in your</p>
<p> own right but also as the Prime Minister of a Nation for whom Australia</p>
<p> and Australians has a very deep affection. It is impossible to adequately</p>
<p> catalogue the links that do exist between our two nations and chatting</p>
<p> over the dinner table we reminded ourselves of just how intricate</p>
<p> are those links. I discovered, for example, the Minister for Resources</p>
<p> in the Government, Senator Warwick Parer, spent the first six years</p>
<p> of his life in Rabaul. I was reminded by a former Prime Minister,</p>
<p> Bob Hawke, that he spent some time of his life as a trade union official</p>
<p> giving advice on wages and industrial relations policy in Papua New</p>
<p> Guinea. And I recall the contribution to the building of that nation</p>
<p> by many of my former colleagues in the Coalition.</p>
<p>Of course the ties that bind us together are nowhere more powerful</p>
<p> than in an area of common love between Australians and the people</p>
<p> of Papua New Guinea and that is in the area of sport. And of all the</p>
<p> sporting links between the two nations, none is more powerful than</p>
<p> in the game of rugby league. And I'm delighted to acknowledge</p>
<p> the presence here today of a number of people who symbolise that link.</p>
<p> I'm delighted to acknowledge, of course, the presence of an Australian</p>
<p> who's probably better known in Papua New Guinea than any other</p>
<p> Australian and that is Mal Meninga, one of Australia's greatest</p>
<p> rugby league players and a great Kangaroo captain and now the coach</p>
<p> of the Canberra Raiders.</p>
<p>I'm also delighted to welcome John Ribot, the Executive Director</p>
<p> of the Melbourne Storm Rugby League Club. And as you will know, Mr</p>
<p> Skate, John captained the Australian President's XIII to Papua</p>
<p> New Guinea in 1985 and has maintained his links ever since. And, of</p>
<p> course, your own Marcus Bai, who's been such an outstanding success</p>
<p> as a player with Melbourne Storm, is also here and he, himself, is</p>
<p> building his own hero status amongst rugby league followers. And you'll</p>
<p> forgive me, ladies and gentlemen, whilst I'm on the subject of</p>
<p> football, of the rugby variety, but I take the opportunity, sparing</p>
<p> Graham Fortune's blushes, of acknowledging the tremendous achievement</p>
<p> of the Australian Wallabies at Lancaster Park last Saturday in winning</p>
<p> the Bledisloe Cup.</p>
<p>Of course, ladies and gentlemen, we gather here today in the shadow</p>
<p> of that enormous tragedy that overtook the villages around the Sissano</p>
<p> Lagoon. We record and reflect with immense sadness on the horrific</p>
<p> loss of life. And can I say to you, Prime Minister, that all Australians</p>
<p> felt for the families affected by that tragedy; the wives made widows,</p>
<p> the children made orphans and those left disabled. And we all felt</p>
<p> a special pang of sympathy and affection for you and for your country</p>
<p> as you coped valiantly with such a terrible disaster. And our desire</p>
<p> to reach out to you was a reflex action, an instinctive response to</p>
<p> family friends.</p>
<p>About 140 Australian Defence Force personnel were on the ground for</p>
<p> two weeks. There were medical staff and they helped deal with horrible</p>
<p> cases of gangrene coupled with scores of broken limbs and the prospect</p>
<p> of terrible disease. There were also communication specialists, logistics</p>
<p> staff, engineers and RAAF air crews whose support was essential. And</p>
<p> quite a number of them are here today as very welcome and honoured</p>
<p> guests of the Australian Government and I know, in a general sense,</p>
<p> of also the Government of Papua New Guinea.</p>
<p>Can I say, as Prime Minister, how immensely proud I was and I know</p>
<p> that all Australians were for what those men and women did in those</p>
<p> days immediately following that disaster. We can only begin to try</p>
<p> and understand the mental strain and trauma and the painful and distressing</p>
<p> circumstances under which they worked. But to see amidst that devastation</p>
<p> and death and sorrow and sadness, to see those wonderful images of</p>
<p> Australian defence personnel working in the name of humanity and decency</p>
<p> to relieve suffering touched me and touched all Australians in a way</p>
<p> that I hope those of you who are here and your colleagues who shared</p>
<p> that experience will understand and accept as a very, very sincere</p>
<p> and grateful expression of how we felt.</p>
<p>There is something particularly touching about the image of a person</p>
<p> wearing that wonderful slouch hat, ministering to people who are sick</p>
<p> and disabled and in a situation of distress. And all Australians are</p>
<p> immensely proud of you and we are immensely grateful to you for the</p>
<p> way in which you demonstrated that Australia is a true friend of those</p>
<p> in need and how deeply compassionate and how willing is the Australian</p>
<p> spirit when it is called upon in those circumstances.</p>
<p>Those images will remain with Australians for a long time. And for</p>
<p> myself, that tragedy served to remind how history, geography and circumstance</p>
<p> continues to bind our two nations together. It must have brought back</p>
<p> to many Australians, as it did to me, images of our shared past. Not</p>
<p> so vivid, perhaps, none so vivid rather, perhaps, as the tales, those</p>
<p> affection tales, of the so-called fuzzy-wuzzy angels' who</p>
<p> helped Australian soldiers more than 50 years ago. The feats of tens</p>
<p> of thousands of those intrepid carriers are immortalised by the stories</p>
<p> of the help they gave to wounded Australian diggers, mainly on stretchers,</p>
<p> over the tortuous Kokoda track. Some of you may have read or heard</p>
<p> the original 1942 poem by Bert Beros, and I quote just a small part</p>
<p> of it:</p>
<p>"Many a mother in Australia when the busy day is done sends</p>
<p> a prayer to the Almighty for the keeping of her son, asking that</p>
<p> an angel guide him and bring him safely back.</p>
<p>Now we see those prayers are answered on the Owen Stanley track.</p>
<p> May the mothers of Australia when they offer up a prayer mention</p>
<p> those impromptu angels with their fuzzy wuzzy hair".</p>
<p>And however sentimental the rhyme and however in the eyes of some</p>
<p> but not, I think, in the eyes of most, dated the language may seem,</p>
<p> the poem helped to tell then how Australians were drawn through gratitude</p>
<p> and admiration to your people and it remains a heartfelt appreciation</p>
<p> enduring even unto today. And in a small way many Australians will</p>
<p> see the demonstration of compassion and help given so effectively</p>
<p> by the men and women of the Australian Defence Force as a small repayment</p>
<p> of the immense debt of gratitude that the wartime Australian diggers</p>
<p> owed to the people of your lovely country.</p>
<p>Mr Prime Minister, you may rest assured that the Government I lead</p>
<p> and the people of Australia consider Papua New Guinea a close friend</p>
<p> and we'll continue to support your efforts to rebuild after that</p>
<p> horrible disaster. And in addition to what has already been provided</p>
<p> we will provide whatever additional resources are needed beyond those</p>
<p> already available to ensure the reconstruction of the two or three</p>
<p> new schools needed, the upgrading of roads, the alterations to make</p>
<p> facilities accessible to the disabled, help with agriculture and fisheries</p>
<p> to rebuild the area's economy, assistance to church and non-government</p>
<p> organisations for rebuilding in new areas, ongoing support for those</p>
<p> suffering orthopedic injuries and amputations, support for geological</p>
<p> survey work and advance to local level administration on planning.</p>
<p>Mr Prime Minister, let me say how pleased the Australian Government</p>
<p> is with the role that you and your Government has played in relation</p>
<p> to the very difficult challenge of Bougainville. We have seen the</p>
<p> emergence of consultation, negotiation and the first possibilities</p>
<p> of a lasting peace and political settlement. We in Australia are not</p>
<p> nave about what lies ahead and ultimately, of course, success will</p>
<p> depend upon the attitude of the Bouganvillians themselves. But we</p>
<p> have made progress and you deserve a great deal of the credit for</p>
<p> that.</p>
<p>And can I also take the opportunity of recording the appreciation</p>
<p> that I feel and the Government feels towards the part played by the</p>
<p> Australian Foreign Minister, Alexander Downer, in the progress that</p>
<p> has been made in achieving some kind of lasting settlement in Bougainville.</p>
<p> And after so many years of conflict we all look forward to the prospect</p>
<p> of peace and I know from our discussions that you are deeply committed</p>
<p> to peace on Bougainville. And I also know from our discussions this</p>
<p> morning that Australia and Papua New Guinea and our other friends</p>
<p> in the Pacific region will work together very closely to achieve that</p>
<p> goal.</p>
<p>In our discussions this morning we shared our thoughts regarding the</p>
<p> impact of the economic downturn in the Asia-Pacific region on our</p>
<p> two countries. That impact is not going to pass quickly and there</p>
<p> is quite a deal of water to flow under that particular bridge before</p>
<p> we are going to see an upturn in the economies of that region. We</p>
<p> both agreed about the importance of continuing to pursue, notwithstanding</p>
<p> the difficulties, those necessary reforms that will make our two economies</p>
<p> more effective and more competitive, not only in the Asia-Pacific</p>
<p> region but also in the broader world. And we here in Australia, of</p>
<p> course, will be embarking upon a very major reform of our taxation</p>
<p> system. And I know from our discussions this morning, given your own</p>
<p> intentions in that particular area, that you will closely examine</p>
<p> the field evidence that emerges from the Australian experience.</p>
<p>Mr Prime Minister, it has been a personal pleasure for me to be your</p>
<p> host today. We met last year on several occasions. I respect and admire</p>
<p> the challenging way in which you are going about your task as Prime</p>
<p> Minister of your country. Australia and Papua New Guinea share a lot</p>
<p> of history, we are friends, we respect each other, we will periodically</p>
<p> differ. Our relationship is now the mature relationship of two sovereign</p>
<p> independent nations. The relationship was once otherwise but we have</p>
<p> grown, I think, easily and effectively and comfortably into the new</p>
<p> relationship.</p>
<p>On behalf of the people of Australia, I bid you a very warm welcome.</p>
<p> On behalf of the people of Australia I send to you and your fellow</p>
<p> country men and women, our good wishes, our determination to maintain</p>
<p> the close ties that have characterised our relationship and the gratitude</p>
<p> for the shared experiences and the mutual assistance which has gone</p>
<p> in earlier years. I would now like t o invite the Deputy Leader of</p>
<p> the Opposition, Mr Gareth Evans, to support my remarks. Thank you.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
