<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>511</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R G MENZIES IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES - 16TH MAY 1962</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/05/1962</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000511.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTERE THE RT. HON. R. G. MENZIES<br />
IN TIr HOUSE OF RPPJ SENTATIVES<br />
16T 1MAY, 1_ 02<br />
After close consideration of the immense importance of<br />
the Common Market negotiations to Australian production and<br />
trade, and to the political future of the British Commonwealth,<br />
I have decided that, as the head of the Australian Government, I<br />
should make a brief visit, during the Parliamentary recess, to<br />
Great Britain and the United States.<br />
Mr. Macmillan, has, in correspondence with me,<br />
expressed the hope that I can do this. My colleague, Mr. McEwen,<br />
whose recent efforts command our admiration and gratitude, is<br />
himself convinced that, in this period when the negotiators are<br />
beginning to get to grips with the practical issues, on-the-spot<br />
discussions by myself are necessary. I hope to do what I can to<br />
reinforce and, where appropriate, supplement his own advocacy.<br />
Jhat is clear is that we cannot spare any efforts to see that<br />
whatever decisions ultimately emerge, they will not be arrived at<br />
without the fullest and clearest understanding of Australia's<br />
case, a case which rises superior to any domestic political<br />
differences. The political implications of an entry by Great Britain<br />
into the European Economic Community must be very significant. I<br />
would wish to discuss them in London at an early date under<br />
circumstances not always easy to achieve during the course of a<br />
comparatively brief Prime Ministers' Conference.<br />
Other great problems confront us, such as the state of<br />
affairs in South east Asia and in Now Guinea. These concern, not<br />
only us, but our partners in SEATO and ANZUS; our friends<br />
g. nerally. My Government feels that I should take the opportunity<br />
of top-level talks not only with the Government of Great Britain,<br />
but also with the President of the United States of Amcrica.<br />
There will be a Prime Ministers' Conference in September, a<br />
Conference of historic significance. My own participation in it<br />
will, I have concluded, be rendored more effective by the<br />
knowledge I hope to gain in my talks in Juno. The more these<br />
great issues are clarified in our own minds, and those of others,<br />
the better should it be for wise and fruitful ultimate<br />
conclusions. Certainly, as Prime Minister, I must seek completely to<br />
discharge my responsibilities, by all moans within my power, to<br />
the Parliament and people of Australia,<br />
I now pass to other, and important aspects of the<br />
great matters to which I have been referring.<br />
The first is that it would be a misfortune if, durinLg<br />
the September Conference, Parliament should be sitting at<br />
Canberra. I am not alluding to the problem of pairs, for I know<br />
that the Opposition would appreciate the importance of<br />
Australia being represented at the Conference. But thoso<br />
representing Australia in London should not, if our case is to be'<br />
presented with singleness of purpose, be distracted by political<br />
events in Canberra. Ie have therefore proposed to the Leader of<br />
the Opposition that, when the general Budget debate is disposed<br />
of, at the end of August, tho House should adjourn, not for the<br />
customary week, but for four weeks. Adjustments can be made<br />
thereafter to ensure that the total poriod of the Budget Session<br />
will not be abbreviatcd. </p>
<p>a 2.<br />
There is a second matter of some novelty and<br />
importance. The Common Market problem concerns both sides of<br />
this House, and all sections of the , ustralian community. When<br />
the September Conference has concluded, and its results are<br />
reported to this Parliament, it seems to us to be most<br />
important, in a matter which transcends our domestic political<br />
differences, that leaders on both sides should have had an<br />
opportunity of informing their minds, overseas, on the views and<br />
attitude of the negotiators and Governments concerned.<br />
I have made it clear to the Leader and Deputy Leader<br />
of the Opposition, who understand and accept what I have said,<br />
that a Prime Ministers' Conference is priv: te, and that interim<br />
statements cannot come out of it. But at the same time we<br />
have invited the Opposition to send some of its leading Members<br />
overseas, so that, by consultations of their own choosing, they<br />
may acquaint themselves at first hand, with no commitments to rv<br />
and with no restrictions by us on the contrary, with every<br />
reasonable facility with the currents of opinion which have<br />
such a bearing upon the future of Australia.<br />
I have also informed the Leader of the Opposition that<br />
should one or two of the pcrsons chosen by the Opposition desire<br />
to make his or their journey during the coming Parliamentary<br />
recess rather than in September, that will be acceptable to us. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
