<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>219</transcript-id>
    <title>SPACE RESEARCH AT WOOMERA - JOINT STATEMENT BY MR. MENZIES AND MR. THORNEYCROFT</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/09/1960</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000219.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>P. M. No. 34/ 1960<br />
SPACE RESEARCH AT tIOOMvERA<br />
Joint Statement by Mr. Menzies and Mr. Thorneycroft<br />
The United Kingdom Minister for Aviation, the Rt.<br />
Hon. Peter Thorneycroft, has had discussions in Canberra<br />
with members of the Australian Cabinet on the general question<br />
of conducting space research from Woomera with particular<br />
reference to the use of Blue Streak for the launching of<br />
satellites for communications and other purposes. The talks<br />
have been purely and necessarily exploratory; for no decision<br />
about proceeding with this matter has yet been reached by the<br />
United Kingdom Government. The United Kingdom Government has<br />
not at this stage been seeking firm commitments and<br />
consequently no commitment direct or indirect has been<br />
accepted. The subject matter is vast and no proposals could be<br />
formulated with precision at this stage.<br />
The purpose of Mr. Thorneycroft's visit was to give<br />
the Australian Ministers an account of the way in which the<br />
United Kingdom Government has so far viewed the possibilities.<br />
The discussions which ensued were concerned also with<br />
the feasibility which has been established of a space research<br />
programme based on ! oomera and with seeking to get some<br />
picture of the eventual application of such activity.<br />
Australian Ministers have been greatly assisted by<br />
the information and ideas laid before them by Mr. Thorneycroft<br />
and his advisers, and various aspects of the matter have been<br />
closely examined. A good deal of the discussion has directed<br />
itself to the very important issue of priorities having regard<br />
to the developmental problems which confront Australian<br />
Governments. Mr. Thorneycroft has come first to Australia because<br />
of the close association of the two countries in other projects<br />
but he proposes to visit other countries in relation to these<br />
matters and, should occasion arise, further exchanges between<br />
the United Kingdom and Australia will occur.<br />
During his stay in Australia Mr. Thorneycroft has<br />
made a visit to ioomera to inspect the Range facilities. He<br />
has also taken the opportunity to review with the relevant<br />
Australian Ministers the progress of the weapon development<br />
programme at Woomera. Irrespective of any decision which may<br />
be made about Blue Streak, there is a considerable load of<br />
work on the remaining weapon development. Talks have taken<br />
place about the planning of this work and also about the still<br />
further improvement of the arrangements for joint Australian/<br />
United Kingdom co-operation during the formative stages of new<br />
weapon projects.<br />
CANBERRA<br />
21st September, 1960. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
