<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>16447</transcript-id>
    <title>Meeting with the President of the Republic of Korea    </title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/03/2009</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Today the President and I have agreed to two major steps which mark the start of a new phase in the Australia-Korea relationship. </p>
<p>First, we have agreed to begin negotiations towards a free trade agreement. </p>
<p>Korea is Australia's fourth-largest export market  -  making this free trade agreement an important goal for us. </p>
<p>Second, we have released a joint statement on security cooperation. </p>
<p>With our shared values, our common alliance ties to the United States and our history of defence cooperation, this statement will provide a framework for taking forward our defence cooperation into the future. </p>
<p>We also agreed on a number of other initiatives. </p>
<p>2011 will be the 50th anniversary of the establishment of diplomatic relations and we are announcing that it will be a “year of friendship” between Australia and Korea with a program of cultural and other activities. </p>
<p>We will arrange a dialogue between opinion makers from both nations in the near future for them to chart a course ahead for our relationship. </p>
<p>Beyond the bilateral meeting today, we discussed regional and global challenges - in particular, the global economic recession and the upcoming G20 leaders meeting in London. </p>
<p>We agreed to coordinate our approaches very closely, particularly on the key challenges of dealing with toxic assets and reforming the International Monetary Fund. </p>
<p>I would like to congratulate Korea on becoming the chair of the G20 next year. The President and I today discussed the future of our region and agreed that we need to focus on the future of our region and the institutions that serve it. </p>
<p>Australia and Korea were instrumental in the formation of APEC. We plan to maintain that historical level of cooperation between our Governments. </p>
<p>On regional challenges, I told President Lee that we support him and his Government in dealing with the challenge of North Korea. </p>
<p>See the Joint Statement on Enhanced Global and Security Cooperation Media Release.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
