<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9806</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP PETER COSTELLO&#039;S &quot;RADICAL NEW TAX PLAN&quot;</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/10/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009806.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
PETER COSTELLO'S " RADICAL NEW TAX PLAN"<br />
The Federai Opposition's secret tax plan, uncovered by the Business Review<br />
Weekly, would lead Australia down the path of social decay and urban blight<br />
already travelled by the United States.<br />
Despite his denial it is now clear that the Shadow Treasurer, Peter Costello,<br />
held secret talks between Victorian, West Australian and South Australian<br />
Governments on introducing new State-based income taxes and consumption<br />
taxes. The hitherto confidential talks demonstrate that in only one important respect<br />
has the Liberal Party changed its approach to Commonwealth-State relations<br />
from that proposed in Fightback! three years ago the Commonwealth GST.<br />
Reluctant to advocate publicly a Commonwealth GST, John Howard's<br />
Coalition now intends to achieve the same result by '' cooperative"~<br />
agreements with State Governments.<br />
This " radical new tax plan" would have profound implications for taxation and<br />
undermine the Federal Government's capacity to meet its national<br />
responsibilities for social programs.<br />
Far from " breathing new life into federalism", the " swingeing cuts to Federal<br />
government spending and responsibilities" proposed by the Opposition would<br />
hollow out the Commonwealth, while deserting those now assisted by the<br />
Commonwealth role in housing, health, education and welfare.<br />
Peter Costello's mantra of " cutting duplication" is code for shifting<br />
Commonwealth education, health and welfare functions to the states.<br />
The Coalition may seek to deny this but Mr Costello's plan outlined in BRW is<br />
simply fleshing out Mr Howard's commitment in his first ' headland' speech to<br />
wind back specific grants to the states. </p>
<p>Mr Howard said the Coalition would " revert to the practice of former coalition<br />
governments of winding back Section 96 for specific grants to the States.<br />
That will mean States themselves will have greater freedom of choice when<br />
deciding their programs and priorities.)'<br />
We already know what the Victorian, South Australian and West Australian<br />
Governments' priorities are. Already today in terms of their own funding the<br />
Liberal state Governments have made major cuts to spending on social<br />
programs. In Victoria Jeff Kennett has cut spending on public health by $ 260 million, he<br />
has closed almost 300 schools and reduced teacher numbers by 8,000.<br />
In South Australia, Dean Brown is looking to cut spending on health by<br />
million and privatise public hospitals. He has already cut spending on<br />
education by $ 40 million.<br />
And of course, as you would expect, Richard Court has an agenda for the<br />
widespread privatisation of the public health system in Western Australia.<br />
If the states had the " freedom" John Howard wants to cede to them they<br />
would be under no obligation to maintain public health, education and social<br />
welfare programs.<br />
That's what cutting back Section 96 Grants to the States means.<br />
Freed from many of its social responsibilities a Federal Coalition Government<br />
would then blame the subsequent tearing of Australia's social cohesion on<br />
the States.<br />
Their model is the US Republicans' Contract with America, which passed the<br />
buck but not the bucks to the States.<br />
I reiterate our firm opposition to the Federal Government cooperating with the<br />
introduction of State income taxes or of a new consumption tax.<br />
I also reiterate our continuing opposition to closing down the<br />
Commonwealth's role in health, education, housing and welfare.<br />
BRISBANE October 1995 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
