<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3718</transcript-id>
    <title>JOINT PRESS STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR WHITLAM, AND THE TASMANIAN PREMIER, MR NEILSON</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/04/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003718.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER PRESS STATEMENT NO./, L-C-<br />
23 April 1975<br />
JOINT PRESS STATEMENT BY THE1 PRIME MINISTER, MR WHITLAM,<br />
AND THE TASMANIAN PREMIER, MR NEILSON<br />
The Australian and Tasmanian Governments have<br />
agreed on the terms for the transfer to the Australian<br />
Government of the Tasmanian rail system.<br />
The announcements were made jointly toda~ y<br />
by the Prime Minister, Mr Whitlam and the Tasmanian<br />
Premier, Mr Neilson. The agreements were concluded at discussions<br />
in Canberra on Tuesday between Mr Whitlam, Mr Neilson<br />
and the Australian Minister for Transpor-t, Mr Jones<br />
and the Acting Treasurer, Mr Stewart.<br />
The Prime Minister and Premier emphasised<br />
that all employees of the Tasmanian Railways will be<br />
employed in the Australian Railways service or the<br />
Tasmanian Transport Commission and that the terms and<br />
conditions of employment would be no less favourable than<br />
those presently applied.<br />
The Australian Government will assume<br />
responsibility for the financial operation of the system<br />
as from 1 July 1975 It will also assume the burden of<br />
the appropriate portion of the railways deficit.<br />
There will be a cash adjustment to the<br />
Tasmanian Government this financial year, and an<br />
appropriate adjustment to the level of financial<br />
assistance grants in future years.<br />
The agreement to transfer the Tasmanian<br />
Railways resulted from the offer contained in the Prime<br />
minister's Policy Speech of November 1972 for the<br />
Australian Government to accept responsibility for the<br />
railways of any State.<br />
" This agreement, which follows on the<br />
agreement reached for the transfer of the South Australian<br />
non-rn etropolitan railways, represents a significant further<br />
step towards the creation of a truly national railway<br />
system," the Prime Minister and the Premier said. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
" It should provide opprotunity for the improved functioning<br />
of the Tasmanian rail system through better co-ordination<br />
with other elements of the expanded Australian National<br />
Railways and also with the operations of the Australian<br />
National Line."<br />
CANBERRA, A. C. T. nln </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
