<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10286</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON. JOHN HOWARD MP SPEECH AT THE OPENING OF THE ANSETT AUSTRALIA SHANGHAI OFFICE, SHANGHAI, CHINA</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/03/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010286.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Fax from PRIME MINISTER<br />
29 March 1997 ThANSCR1PT OF THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE HO0N. JOHN HOWARD MP<br />
SPEECH AT THE'OPENING OF THlE ANSETT AUS TRALIA<br />
SHANGHAI OFFICE, SHANGHAI, CHINA<br />
E &amp; OE<br />
Thank you very much. To Mr Ken Cowley, the Chairman of Ansett International, to<br />
Mr Liu, the Minister for Metallurgical Industry, MrJao, the Vice Mayor of Shaaghai.<br />
to M~ r Rick Smith, the Australian Ambassador, to Mr Rigby, the Consul General, to<br />
His Excellency, the Ambassador of China in Canberra, other distinguished guests,<br />
ladies and gentlemen.<br />
I am particularly Pleased to be hern today because the opening of this Ansett office in<br />
Shanghai is the latest demonstration of the dramitic growth in the air-travel between<br />
Australia and China. Since new and expanded air servicc arrangements Were signed<br />
in march last year, the number of airlines flying between our countries has gone from<br />
two to four, the number of weekly servikes has risen from two to. seven, and there has<br />
been an average growth of 30% annually in the air traffic between Australia and China<br />
over that three year period.<br />
Can I say to our Chinese guests today two things about Ansett. Ansett has been a<br />
grea Australian company for a long period of time and over the last 50 years four of<br />
the best known business figures that Autlia has produced in that time have been<br />
associated with the company begininingwith Reg Ansett and Peter Abeles and Rupert<br />
Murdoch and our host today, Ken Cowley, so it is a company that has grea ' t Australian<br />
credentials and it is a company that comes to Cbina with an impeccable business<br />
background.<br />
And can I say on a personal note that un~ til I became prime Minister just over a year<br />
ago and acquired as it were an airline of my own, I was a f6ithful traveler on Ansett as<br />
-the airline of my domestic chno for something like 22 years and I can tell our<br />
Chinese guests that in all of that tr-avel and in one year I think I was die third roost<br />
regular flyer on Ansett, they never lost mny baggage once. Faoxm2 9/ 03/ 97 19: 31 Pg: 1 </p>
<p>Fax from The dramatic growth in ai travel between Austialia and China is just another element<br />
in a deepening economic and trade association but even more importantly, it<br />
underlines the growing people to people links bewveen our two countries. Over<br />
000 Chinese visitors went to Australia last year -and I have every confidence<br />
particularly in the lead up to the Olympic Games in Sydney in the year 2000 which<br />
will be an absolute magnet for people all around the world and not least from people<br />
in Chiaa that -that number will grow and be dramatically exceeded when the Olympic<br />
Gaines take place.<br />
I want to congratulate Ansett on the care it has taken to -achieve a proper cultural and<br />
linguistic blend within thc services that it is offerihg and will offer, it is, necessary<br />
that that occur and it is a proper recognition of the importance of understanding the<br />
market in which the airlines must compete for business.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen, this is the first day of afour day visit to China and I am<br />
particularly pleased that it takes place in Shanghai, the great commercial centre of<br />
China and a great city iii its own right by aay comparison. I am accompanied on this<br />
visit by a delegation of businessmen and women representing, or comprised of some<br />
of the most senior people in business in Australia and J have put together that<br />
delegation to demonstrate to the Chinese Government and to the Chinese people the<br />
importance I attach andmy Goverrnent attaches to -lose co-operiion. between the<br />
Government and the business m'en and women of Australia in building an even better<br />
partnership with the Cin=-se Goveffrnent and the Chinese people.<br />
I last visited shanghai in 1.985. Needless to say, the change that has occurred over that<br />
eleven year period has been quite astonishing and In the short time I have already<br />
been here, the level of development and' idustrialisatioa has made a very big<br />
impression. I want to thank the N ister and the Vice Mayor of ' Shanghai for the gxreat courtesy<br />
that they have extended to me already and the welcome they extended to me last<br />
night, ladies and gentlemen, again may I congratulate Ansett on thi success it has<br />
achieved so far. its commitment to the air traffic between Australia and china and the<br />
very important contribution that the company is making to the building of closer,<br />
relations, both economic and otherwise between Australia and China. Having said<br />
that, I have much pleasure in declaring Ansett's Shah" ba office officially open. I<br />
wish the inaugural flight an the 8th of June the very best of success and may many<br />
people happily and frequently travel on Ansett aircraft between Australia and China.<br />
Thank you. Fa om29/ 03/ 97 19: 31 Pg: 2 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
