<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11384</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER          THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP          PRIME REGIONAL TELEVISION ADDRESS                                          SUBJECT: Telstra 2 Sale</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/10/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...................</p>
<p>  With the successful sale of a further 16 per cent of Telstra 1.6 million</p>
<p>   Australians have taken a direct stake in one of our great national companies.</p>
<p>  This includes around 400,000 Australians who have invested in shares for</p>
<p>   the first time.</p>
<p>  Their decision supports the choice of 1.8 million Australians who bought</p>
<p>   shares in the first Telstra sale.</p>
<p>  It was that sale which contributed to the Government's repayment of over</p>
<p>   $24 billion of Labor's $96 billion debt and which funded the biggest environmental</p>
<p>   package in Australia's history.</p>
<p>  The $16 billion expected from the latest sale will allow the Government</p>
<p>   to retire even more national debt.</p>
<p>  It will also allow us to do much more.</p>
<p>  Sale proceeds will be used to help establish rural transaction centres to</p>
<p>   bring banking back to the bush in 500 country towns across Australia.</p>
<p>  SBS television will be extended to the homes of another 1 million Australians</p>
<p>   in places like Mackay, Shepparton, Port Lincoln, Eden and Port Hedland.</p>
<p>  There will also be more Australians in remote areas who will be able to</p>
<p>   make untimed local calls to their neighbours.</p>
<p>  In addition to these benefits, regional Australia will be able to obtain</p>
<p>   access to the internet at the price of a local call. There will also be</p>
<p>   continuous mobile phone coverage on major Australian highways and an extra</p>
<p>   $250 million to protect the environment.</p>
<p>  Regrettably, the Labor Party has opposed our steps to provide the means</p>
<p>   to deliver these benefits for the bush even though they were the ones who</p>
<p>   in office sold many government assets.</p>
<p>  By way of contrast, the Coalition has been frank and open about the benefits</p>
<p>   of selling Telstra. It can reduce Government debt and ensure that services</p>
<p>   are maintained in the bush. Goodnight.</p>
<p>  [ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
