<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6301</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT TO THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES BY THE PRIME MINISTER, 29 JANUARY 1984</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/01/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006301.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGOED AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
STATEMENT TO THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES<br />
BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
29 JANUARY 1984<br />
EMBARGOED AGAINST DELIVERY 6 m. I </p>
<p>SHERATON HOTEL INCIDENT<br />
Background Mr Justice Hope has reported, as requested by the<br />
Government, on the incident at the Sheraton Hotel in<br />
Melbourne, on 30 November 1983.<br />
The Government became aware of the incident on<br />
1 December 1983 and on that day asked Mr Justice Hope to<br />
undertake an inquiry into it.<br />
Certain details of the incident were subsequently<br />
provided by Mr Hayden to the Parliament. This Report<br />
describes the incident and the circumstances surrounding<br />
the training exercise in detail in accordance with the<br />
Government's formal request to Mr Justice Hope, conveyed<br />
to him on 7 December 1983.<br />
Further, as requested by the Government, His Honour has<br />
examined the general conduct of all persons associated<br />
with the exercise, including those who had a supervisory<br />
role, and whether any breach of the law was committed by<br />
anyone carrying out or authorizing the exercise.<br />
Editing and Declassification of the Report<br />
The Report presented to the Government was highly<br />
classified. The reason for this, as His Honour noted,<br />
was that the special operations role of ASIS has, in the<br />
past, been treated as Top Secret.<br />
The Government has declassified the report for tabling<br />
because the background of special operations training is<br />
essential to an understanding of the Sheraton Hotel<br />
incident. There has been considerable speculation about </p>
<p>what ASIS was up to that led to the fiasco at the<br />
Sheraton on 30 November last, and that speculation, and<br />
the attendant disquiet in the public mind, could only be<br />
put to rest by making public the fact that ASIS has been<br />
conducting training exercises involving such scenarios<br />
as the rescue of a hostage from foreign intelligence<br />
agents.<br />
Declassification of the Report has made necessary a few<br />
small editing changes based largely on considerations of<br />
our international relations and national security.<br />
These small changes, which do not affect the substance<br />
of the Report, have been discussed with the Royal<br />
Commission. I have provided the Leader of the Opposition with a copy<br />
of the classified version of the Report.<br />
The Incident<br />
The training exercise and I point out that Mr Justice<br />
Hope has emphasised that what occurred at the Sheraton<br />
was in fact part of a training exercise and was not a<br />
real operation required the trainees to rescue<br />
an individual from persons playing the roles of foreign<br />
intelligence officers who were holding him hostage in a<br />
room in the Sheraton Hotel. The means by which that<br />
' rescue' was effected are generally known.<br />
To put the exercise in some sort of context, to explain<br />
why such an exercise might even have been contemplated,<br />
it is necessary to consider briefly the functions of<br />
ASIS. The principal function of ASIS, under its directive, is<br />
the collection of foreign intelligence. </p>
<p>A minor function, specified in the directive, requires<br />
ASIS to maintain a special operations capability for<br />
war-time and other very special situations. As Mr<br />
Justice Hope notes, that capability is maintained only<br />
on a contingency basis.<br />
The Government notes that the whole question of ASIS's<br />
special operations function will be dealt with in the<br />
Royal Commissioner's report on ASIS due later in the<br />
year. Ministerial Responsibility<br />
It being understood that the exercise was conducted as<br />
part of training, under the authority of the special<br />
operations function as outlined in the directive, the<br />
question of Ministerial responsibility should be<br />
addressed. The Minister for Foreign Affairs has made clear that he<br />
was not aware of the planned exercise, and Mr Justice<br />
Hope has concluded that there was no suggestion that the<br />
Minister should have been informed of the kind of<br />
special operations training which was being undertaken<br />
in November, nor of the specific exercise which<br />
concluded at the Sheraton Hotel.<br />
Conclusions on the Exercise<br />
In reporting on what went wrong and where responsibility<br />
should lie, Mr Justice Hope has criticised the exercise<br />
as being ' poorly planned, poorly prepared and poorly<br />
coordinated' The Government agrees with these<br />
criticisms. </p>
<p>His Honour has concluded that ASIS's training precepts<br />
and training manuals provide inadequate guidance and<br />
insufficient control on the conduct of exercises such as<br />
the one in question ( 3.26).<br />
Further, His Honour concludes that every aspect of the<br />
exercise, including preparation for its execution, ought<br />
to have been so planned and supervised so as to ensure<br />
that it was carried out lawfully<br />
Mr Justice Hope identifies as an obvious deficiency in<br />
the planning of the exercise the failure to notify<br />
either the Victoria Police or the Manager of the<br />
Sheraton Hotel of the exercise The Government<br />
agrees that common-sense and ordinary courtesy alone<br />
required prior consultation.<br />
Mr Justice Hope has commended the reactions of the Hotel<br />
Manager and the Victoria Police at the scene of the<br />
incident.<br />
Offences Mr Justice Hope has made an examination of the possible<br />
breaches of laws which may be applicable to this<br />
incident but has taken the view that any decision on<br />
prosecutions should rest with the appropriate<br />
responsible authorities. He makes no findings that any<br />
person has committed any offence, and he makes no<br />
recommendation that any person ought to be prosecuted<br />
( 5.18)<br />
His Honour has found that there are valid reasons based<br />
on considerations of national security and international<br />
relations for keeping secret the names of those involved<br />
in the exercise ( 1.10, 6.5-6.7). </p>
<p>The Government appreciates the difficulties for Victoria<br />
in its consideration of possible prosecutions, where<br />
national security, which militates against the public<br />
disclosure of the names, conflicts with the State's<br />
responsibilities to enforce the law.<br />
A copy of the full report was made available to Premier<br />
Cain without delay, and discussions on these difficult<br />
issues have continued between our Governments.<br />
I understand that the Victorian Government intends to<br />
introduce legislation to enable the Courts in Victoria<br />
to determine that there may be confidentiality in court<br />
proceedings where necessary in the interests of the<br />
national or international security of Australia.<br />
On the basis of the enactment of such protective<br />
legislation, and any necessary complementary<br />
legislation, the Commonwealth will withdraw its previous<br />
objection to the release to the Victorian Government of<br />
the names of those participating in the Sheraton<br />
incident and not already known to the Victorian<br />
Government. There is presently an outstanding High Court injunction<br />
against the release of any such names, but the<br />
Commonwealth will use its best endeavours to secure an<br />
appropriate settlement of that case in terms that will<br />
allow communication of the relevant names to the<br />
Victorian Government. </p>
<p>Recommendations Mr Justice Hope's recommendations for measures to<br />
prevent a recurrence of this kind of incident are<br />
contained in Chapter 6 of his Report. In brief, he<br />
recommends prohibition on carrying any type of firearms<br />
in public and of any exercise which might harm or alarm<br />
members of the public, and a requirement for clearance<br />
with police, local military districts and owners of any<br />
property affected before any such exercises are<br />
undertaken outside ASIS training facilities.<br />
The Government accepts all of the Report's<br />
recommendations designed to ensure that such incidents<br />
cannot recur.<br />
The Minister for Foreign Affairs, Mr Hayden, has indeed<br />
already taken several such steps and will ensure that<br />
the other measures proposed by His Honour are put in<br />
place. Mr Justice Hope has found that varying degrees of<br />
responsibility apply to the ASIS senior management, the<br />
planners of the exercise and certain of the<br />
participants. Disciplinary Action<br />
While His Honour touches on the question of disciplinary<br />
or other action for those involved in the exercise, he<br />
has not made recommendations as to what disciplinary or<br />
other action, if any, should be taken.<br />
Those questions have been left for the responsible<br />
authorities to resolve. </p>
<p>I now announce that the Government has appointed a new<br />
Acting Director-General of ASIS. The new Acting<br />
Director-General will be Mr J. O. Furner, CBE.<br />
Mr Furner has until now been the Director of the Joint<br />
Intelligence Organisation, after retiring from the Army<br />
with the rank of Brigadier.<br />
Mr Furner's first responsibility will be to consider<br />
disciplinary action concerning those involved in the<br />
planning and execution of this failed exercise.<br />
To assist Mr Furner in this consideration the Government<br />
has appointed Mr Clarence Hermes to investigate the<br />
conduct of persons who were involved in the authorising,<br />
planning and carrying out of the exercise. Mr Hermes is<br />
about to retire as Chief Magistrate of the Australian<br />
Capital Territory. Mr Hermes is to report to the Acting<br />
Director-General of ASIS and the Minister for Foreign<br />
Affairs on whether disciplinary action should be taken<br />
against any of those persons and, if so, what<br />
disciplinary action.<br />
In the course of those inquiries, those affected will of<br />
course be given the opportunity to put their side of the<br />
case. It is only when those involved with the exercise<br />
have had this opportunity to reply to the Report that a<br />
decision will be taken on whether disciplinary action<br />
should be taken. The Government expects that process to<br />
be completed in the next few weeks.<br />
Conclusion I take this opportunity to thank Mr Justice Hope for his<br />
Report and look forward to his further report on the<br />
wider subject of the functions of ASIS. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
