<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10687</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                DOORSTOP INTERVIEW - CAMPBELL BARRACKS                PERTH, WESTERN AUSTRALIA</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/02/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...............................................</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, what was you message to the troops ...[inaudible]?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>My message on behalf of the Australian people was one of good luck,</p>
<p> God's speed and a safe return. I expressed the gratitude of the</p>
<p> Australian people for the commitments that they were making. I told</p>
<p> them that one of the enormous advantages they had was that they were</p>
<p> amongst the most superbly trained military personnel in the world.</p>
<p> The training of the SAS regiment and the training of the other personnel</p>
<p> is second to none around the world.</p>
<p>I also told them that their cause was a good one and a just one. It</p>
<p> is important for all of the Australian people to appreciate and to</p>
<p> know that this is no sort of idle exercise. We are about ensuring</p>
<p> that a person who has successfully thumbed his nose so far against</p>
<p> world opinion is not allowed to retain and ultimately use weapons</p>
<p> of mass destruction. And it is also important that the authority of</p>
<p> the United Nations is maintained.</p>
<p>It does effect Australia. It is not a remote, indifferent, irrelevant</p>
<p> part of the world to Australia. And if Saddam is allowed to get away</p>
<p> with what he is trying to get away with then other countries, perhaps</p>
<p> closer to Australia, perhaps of more immediate threat to Australia,</p>
<p> could be encouraged to attempt the same thing. So there is a direct</p>
<p> Australian national interest involved.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>How emotional was that for you to deliver this message? How were they</p>
<p> feeling and how emotional was it?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well they were in tremendous spirit. They are superbly professional</p>
<p> men and women and I admire them immensely. Of course it is an emotional</p>
<p> thing to look people in the eye who are going off to put their lives</p>
<p> potentially on the line and it is not something that is done lightly</p>
<p> and I am immensely proud of them. And I told them that the Australian</p>
<p> nation was immensely proud of them and they went with united prayers</p>
<p> and good wishes of all of the Australian people.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Did you get to speak to the families Prime Minister?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No I didn't. They had arranged that the family farewell should</p>
<p> take place this morning. I had the opportunity to speak to all of</p>
<p> the men and women who were there and to shake each hand and to wish</p>
<p> each good luck and to talk about the nature of the exercise. We discussed</p>
<p> the politics of it. And they were a very, very impressive bunch of</p>
<p> Australians. It was very important to them that both the Leader of</p>
<p> the Opposition and I were there. The safety of Australian military</p>
<p> personnel and their endeavours is something that is above party politics</p>
<p> in this country. And I was particularly pleased that it was possible</p>
<p> for Mr Beazley to be there.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>And if there is any chance that Saddam will adhere ...resolution?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I hope there is. And I told them that. I said that I hoped that they</p>
<p> would be deployed but not be required to go into armed conflict. I</p>
<p> hope very, very much that this dispute can be settled. I don't</p>
<p> want to get overly optimistic about the prospects of a settlement,</p>
<p> but there is still the possibility that, particularly through the</p>
<p> egest of the Secretary General of the United Nations, something can</p>
<p> be achieved. And if that is possible then nobody will be more delighted</p>
<p> than I. And I said that to the defence personnel who I addressed.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>If that doesn't happen, how...will our troops be [inaudible]?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I can't speculate and I won't speculate about that.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What are your thoughts about the protesters out here and what it can</p>
<p> do the men, their morale?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I don't think anything will dent the morale of those men and</p>
<p> they will go knowing that the overwhelming sentiment in the Australian</p>
<p> community is one of support. And they will know that there will be</p>
<p> many pairs of Australian eyes closed in silent prayer tonight for</p>
<p> their safe return.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, you have had a long day flying here, I suspect you</p>
<p> are flying straight back...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I am.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>....[inaudible] in this very important issue. Personally how is it</p>
<p> taking its toll on you?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well it is the least I can do. If they are prepared to go to another</p>
<p> part of the world and put their lives at risk the least that the Prime</p>
<p> Minister of this country can do is fly over to Perth and thank them</p>
<p> personally and wish them well on behalf of the rest of the Australian</p>
<p> community and go back.</p>
<p>Look this is a difficult issue, it is an emotionally challenging issue,</p>
<p> but the course of action we have adopted is the right course of action.</p>
<p> We have no alternative. We will continue to try a peaceful solution.</p>
<p> If that fails then military force will be necessary and the Australian</p>
<p> people can know that we will be sending into that military conflict</p>
<p> the most superbly trained personnel available and people whose whole</p>
<p> career efforts to date has been directed towards getting them ready</p>
<p> for precisely such an encounter.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>...or if it does end up being....[inaudible]...how many more troops</p>
<p> are we going to ...[inaudible]?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well at this stage the commitment is no more than what I announced</p>
<p> last week and we wouldn't envisage that any additional commitment</p>
<p> was necessary and we certainly don't have any contingency planning</p>
<p> for any further commitment.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>....[inaudible]...would that be?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I don't expect that that will change.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Are you in constant contact with the Americans?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes. Well I have spoken to President Clinton twice on this matter.</p>
<p> And the Defence Minister is in contact with his counterpart in the</p>
<p> United States. The Head of our Defence Force is in contact with the</p>
<p> Americans and there is constant liaison at a military level and also</p>
<p> at a State Department/Ambassador to United States level. The lines</p>
<p> of communication are very open and they are very adequate and very</p>
<p> complete.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>....[inaudible].. you bipartisan nature in brief is that something</p>
<p> you plan to do over the next couple of weeks or months or however</p>
<p> long...[inaudible]..?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I will. I have a very strong view that on these matters there should</p>
<p> be a total inclusion of the Opposition. This is something that should</p>
<p> be above party politics. The Australian people demand no less and</p>
<p> we owe no less to the men and women who are going overseas. There</p>
<p> is nothing worse than to have men and women going overseas and putting</p>
<p> their lives at risk against the background of political division.</p>
<p> And I will continue to keep Mr Beazley fully informed. I appreciate</p>
<p> and I thank him for the support that he has tendered to the Government</p>
<p> on behalf of the Australian Labor Party. Thank you.</p>
<p>[Ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
