<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9467</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP INTERVIEW WITH JOHN STANLEY. 2UE 31 JANUARY 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>31/01/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009467.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
~/ YJ<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
INTERVIEW WITH JOHN STANLEY, 2UE<br />
31 JANUARY 1995<br />
J: Good afternoon.<br />
PM: How are you John?<br />
J: Very good. This is the beginning of ' 95 for you. You have a new<br />
Opposition Leader, we'll discuss that in a moment, but this afternoon<br />
the Treasurer has confirmed you will be increasing taxes in the May<br />
Budget. Isn't that going to make your task of winning the election that<br />
much harder?<br />
PM: What he confirmed is we will tighten policy and he said this for this<br />
reason. He's also published a set of forecasts and what they show is<br />
that in the Budget, at the time of the Budget last year, we forecast<br />
growth in the economy at four and a half per cent. We are now<br />
forecasting five and a half. We were forecasting business investment<br />
at fourteen and a half per cent, we are now forecasting twenty-four.<br />
We were forecasting two per cent inflation, we are forecasting two and<br />
a quarter, about the same, and on unemployment we were forecasting<br />
nine and a half, we are now forecasting eight and a half. So five and a<br />
half per cent for growth, twenty-four per cent for business investment<br />
and eight and a half per cent for unemployment and 450,000 jobs<br />
since the election. We want to keep that going.<br />
J: What about the current account deficit?<br />
PM: The current account deficit is rising because we are in a very strong<br />
investment phase. In any investment phase, Australia always imports<br />
producer goods. We don't make digitally operated machine tools. We<br />
don't make mainframe computers. These things come in at rises. But<br />
the thing is, this country is the fastest growing, western OECD style<br />
economy with low inflation. Five and a half per cent growth and two </p>
<p>per cent inflation we've never had any year that good, I don't think<br />
since the war.<br />
J: We haven't had a year with a current account deficit of 26 million...<br />
PM: The Government was re-elected to produce growth in employment.<br />
We've had now just on half a million jobs since the election. It must be<br />
the fastest rate of employment growth in the OECD area of the western<br />
world. Let me just say this. I think without a doubt the best economic<br />
year for Australia since the war. What we will do is keep that going.<br />
So what the Treasurer announced today is how we keep that going<br />
and that means we've got to make sure that that current account deficit<br />
you speak of comes from a paucity of our savings, so we want the<br />
public sector to save some more by getting the Budget back into<br />
surplus earlier.<br />
J: Yes, so you will be doing that in a couple of years' time, but will you be<br />
doing it by raising taxes?<br />
PM: Well, as in all Budgets, you can do it by changes in taxes, changes in<br />
outlays or changes in the asset position of the Commonwealth. We<br />
will be examining that in the way that the Government has done since<br />
1983.<br />
J: So you are not ruling out any of those three selling off Government<br />
assets, raising taxes and cutting Government spending?<br />
PM: No, but let me just make this point because I heard on your news<br />
service somebody saying, I think it was Mr Costello, well this is a big<br />
tax-munching Government. This is the lowest taxing Government in<br />
the western world. This is the lowest taxed country, outside of Turkey<br />
which is not as developed as this country is, this is the lowest taxed,<br />
developed country in the western world and we gave tax cuts as we<br />
promised in the election at the end of 1993. So I think people have got<br />
to understand and balance this off if they want to keep that job security<br />
when they see those job numbers coming out strongly and<br />
unemployment coming down. If they want to see the pick up in<br />
business profits and the general prosperity in the economy with huge<br />
rates of productivity growth and low inflation, you've got to run the<br />
place sensibly and I like to think we can do that.<br />
J: And running the place sensibly then means ratcheting up the tax rate a<br />
little bit from that...<br />
PM: Well I can't say what we will do precisely on tax, it's just too early, but<br />
the Budget will be down in May and the Government will consider its<br />
position between now and then.<br />
J: Can you rule out increases in personal income tax rates? </p>
<p>PM: Well I'm not ruling out anything except to say have a look at our record<br />
in these things and it's been pretty strong. I mean we'ye delivered on<br />
every tax commitment we've made since 1983. 1 had Mr Howard<br />
running around telling us about broken promises and how I can't be<br />
believed, when Treasurer in 1977 he introduced a tax cut, I don't think<br />
you can remember it John, ring up and find out...<br />
J: I do remember it the fistful of dollars but then you...<br />
PM: Just remember, ring up and find out how much your tax cut will be and<br />
then they took it away five months later.<br />
J: And yet you said your tax cuts were L-A-W law.<br />
PM: Yes, and they were, they were paid.<br />
J: But you didn't deliver all of them did you? The second lot's still to<br />
come.<br />
PM: We paid the first half early and we put the second half back.<br />
J: So when are they going to come in?<br />
PM: The Government will consider that as well in the Budget round.<br />
J: But isn't that a credibility problem...<br />
PM: No not at all.<br />
J possibility of increasing taxes, and you still haven't delivered that tax<br />
cut.<br />
PM: No, we delivered the tax cuts in December 1993 as promised. In fact<br />
we delivered them earlier as I said and we've put the second round<br />
back. But again, we were forecasting the Budget at four and a half per<br />
cent growth. We're actually doing better, we're doing five and a half.<br />
Now, what all thinking Australians will say, well look we're doing now<br />
even better than we expected, what should we do now to preserve<br />
that? How do we keep that going? And that means that we have got<br />
to make sure that the demand and the savings equation the economy<br />
sets us up for the rest of the ' 90s so that all of us and all of our kids get<br />
a chance at a job and good strong growth.<br />
J: Do you acknowledge that in the broad community today and possibly<br />
because of your efforts over the last decade, there's more of an<br />
understanding of the economy and people understand that if the<br />
budget deficit isn't cut back, if public spending isn't pared back, that<br />
they may have to pay higher interest rates? </p>
<p>PM: Well I think we've seen three monetary adjustments last year, three<br />
interest rate adjustments last year, I think people have got to say this<br />
is a premium I pay for my job security, for the employment growth we're<br />
seeing, for the phenomenal rates of economic growth and for the pick<br />
up in company profits which is underpinning our big investment phase<br />
for the future. It's a bit like paying the insurance on your house. You<br />
can take the risk that it won't burn down, but you're awfully sorry after<br />
the event if it does and you're not insured.<br />
J: Could you expand on that because a few people I've heard on this<br />
station, on open line calls, they say, " Why is it good for the economy<br />
that we should have to pay say, sixty dollars a month more on our<br />
mortgage rate?" How is it directly helping them?<br />
PK: Let me say this, John, housing interest rates fell dramatically over the<br />
last, say, three years, by sixty or eighty dollars or more in some<br />
cases, like for a $ 60,000 or $ 70,000 dollar mortgage, by $ 120 a week.<br />
Those low interest rates reflected the low activity in the economy and<br />
the low premium in the interest rate market, if you like, of that low<br />
activity. Once the game started to get stronger and there was more<br />
demand out there, what that does is take away some of the spending<br />
capacity in the economy. If we don't take it away, we can't sustain the<br />
growth, we can't sustain the employment growth and so the certainty<br />
that people are looking for... I think Australians are very mature about<br />
these things they say look, we re-hired the government in 1993 to<br />
give us growth back and strong employment. The government has<br />
done more than it could even reasonably be expected to do, with that.<br />
Now, they know that you just can't have that sort of strong growth and<br />
employment growth and have growth in the current account deficit<br />
etcetera, without some tempering of the pace. And, what the interest<br />
rates do is simply temper the pace.<br />
J: Well, you described it, I think, as a premium that they have to pay for<br />
all of these...<br />
PK: Well, for economic security, growth, employment....<br />
J: So, to get all of that people may have to pay higher interest rates and<br />
pay higher taxes in the short term?<br />
PK: Well, they've already paid some of the higher interest rates but, can I<br />
just say this, that the big fear 18 months ago was that your job was at<br />
risk, alternatively you might have been unemployed or, at best, your<br />
job was at risk. You've now got the security of knowing that that is not<br />
true, that your job is much more secure. And, this is part of the<br />
premium on that security. I </p>
<p>J: So, those people, therefore, you're asking them, look you're going to<br />
have to pay, perhaps is the word ' premium' perhaps a replacement<br />
for the old, ' you have to tighten your belt a bit more to gain the<br />
benefit'?<br />
PK: Well, just look at the substantial growth in real incomes. When you<br />
get a wage increase, and we've seen wages running at about three<br />
and a half to four per cent this year and in some cases, because of<br />
the previous year, six per cent and you end up with two per cent<br />
inflation, you end up with three to four per cent real growth in income.<br />
Let me explain this to you... if you had wages at four per cent and<br />
inflation at four per cent your real income growth is zero. But, if you've<br />
got wages at four per cent and inflation at two per cent or inflation at<br />
one per cent or inflation at nearly zero which is what we had for<br />
most of the last year you've got a four per cent real increase in<br />
income. Couple that with the reduced interest rates over the last three<br />
years for housing, we had a huge increase in real income, for<br />
households. And, that has now reflected itself in a big splurge in<br />
spending.<br />
J: So what you're saying is they've got to pull back a bit?<br />
PK: Pull back a bit..<br />
J: Through interest rates or tax rises?<br />
PK: Whatever it is, but it pulls it back a bit. But, what is the purpose in<br />
pulling it back? The good purpose in pulling it back is to sustain it<br />
right through the nineties.<br />
J: The bottom line, I could use a tabloid way of putting it, you're going to<br />
have to take a little bit of money out of people's pockets for the longer<br />
term benefit?<br />
PK: Well, after having put a fair bit in. That's the point. Where did the<br />
income growth over the past couple of years come from? It came from<br />
a tremendous result in inflation which meant that the wages growth<br />
ended up being real wages growth. It wasn't eaten away by inflation.<br />
The second thing is it came from reduced interest rates and it came<br />
from the tax cuts of 1993. If you put the three of those things together<br />
you've got a lot of income. Now, the government has given a lot of<br />
additional income to the community in the last three years. What is<br />
happening now, to sustain this growth and employment growth and<br />
security some of that is coming back.<br />
J: It is a hard message to put to people though, to say, look, your income<br />
has got to be pared back a bit. </p>
<p>PK: But, how would they like to be living in Europe where the rates of<br />
growth are one and a half per cent, not five and a half; where there is<br />
not three per cent or three and a half per cent employment growth but<br />
three quarters of a per cent; where their job has the sword of<br />
Damocles hanging over it, perpetually? How would people like that<br />
alternative? And, by the way, that's the sort of alternative that the<br />
Liberal Party have got... Low growth, jack up the interest rates, hold<br />
down the growth, don't have a wages policy, don't talk to the unions...<br />
Labour market reform, cutting real wages, that's the alternative.<br />
J: The foreign debt though, $ 180 billion dollars, we've got $ 26 billion<br />
coming up in the next financial year, are we ever going to be able to<br />
even stabilise it, let alone?<br />
PK: There is only one way for us to get out of our foreign debt, that is,<br />
invest our way out by increasing the capital stock that's plant and<br />
equipment, productive capacity and saving more. But, why are<br />
Australian private savings relatively low? Why does the government<br />
have to increase the Budget surplus? The answer is, to make up for<br />
the paucity of private savings. And why are private savings low?<br />
Because two decades of double digit inflation taught people not to<br />
leave their money in the bank. And, John Howard who has now been<br />
anointed as the new Liberal leader is responsible for nearly one<br />
decade of that high inflation.<br />
J: But, you've been there for nearly 13 years...<br />
PK: Oh yes, but have a look at the inflation rate, it's two per cent.<br />
J: And, what about the savings, though, we've got foreign debt at $ 180<br />
billion dollars?<br />
PK: The thing is, we broke the back of inflation in 1989-90 after five or six<br />
years of wrestling with it and you can't say to a community of 18 million<br />
people, " Look all of your lifetime experience is that if you put your<br />
money in the bank it will go down in value particularly in after tax<br />
terms we've had, now, three years of really good inflation<br />
performance so change your saving habits". People take a while to<br />
change.<br />
J: So, when is it going to happen, when are we going to see the change<br />
in saving habits?<br />
PK: I think you will see it. You can see it now, you've got real income<br />
growth, you've got modest wage growth and you've got that becoming<br />
real wage growth because of low inflation. </p>
<p>J: OK, can I turn to Mr Howard and can I put it to you that there is no one<br />
who you would less like to hand over the Prime Ministership to than<br />
John Howard?<br />
PK: Well, I spent ten years of my life cleaning up after him, ten years of<br />
cleaning up his mess. He left me as Treasurer and as Prime Minister,<br />
an industrial graveyard closed factories, ten per cent<br />
unemployment, eleven per cent inflation, smashed profits, low<br />
employment. That was the legacy of John Howard.<br />
J: If he was here, he'd hit back with your recession.<br />
PK: No, no, let me just say about, if you put my recession, for a start, we<br />
are out of it and growing firmly. John Howard never had, at any time<br />
he was in government, growth at five and a half per cent and two per<br />
cent inflation. Never. Not ever. The best he could ever do was about<br />
two and a half per cent growth and ten per cent inflation. So, he was a<br />
weak Treasurer, and as Leader of the Opposition, when he got down<br />
to that 13% bottom approval rating he demonstrated in losing the<br />
1987 election that he was a weak leader. Now, whatever you think<br />
about this country, it has changed completely as a result of this<br />
Government's tenure of office this is an outward looking, confident,<br />
engaged, international, low inflation, high productivity competitive<br />
economy. What John Howard left behind was an inward looking, tariff<br />
enclosed, regulated, high unemployment, high inflation country.<br />
J: But, you know that many of the policies that you undertook as<br />
Treasurer, he would have undertaken as Treasurer if he had still been<br />
there?<br />
PM: Look, he couldn't beat time in the Cabinet room. John Hewson wrote<br />
those stories this little myth goes around. This is a bloke who was<br />
Treasurer for 5 years, and who let me give you an example, last<br />
night he said this on the 7.30 Report, about the republic, he said, " If<br />
you want to know how I would vote in 5 years time, ask me in 5 years<br />
time. If I can be persuaded, and the Australian community be<br />
persuaded that a republic would benefit Australia, that is something<br />
that deserves support". In other words, if muggins me if Keating<br />
gets out there and really leads and convinces me and the Australian<br />
community that we should be a republic, then maybe I will support it.<br />
Just like, if Keating floats the dollar, de-regulates the financial markets,<br />
knocks over the tariff wall, makes the leap into Asia, introduces best<br />
practice, lifts the participation rate in schools, then I might support him.<br />
I mean, this Government has done all the hard work, and if the public<br />
of this country want to continue the great change of Australia, well,<br />
they keep to the authors of the policy.<br />
J: If you look at John Howard's record, that was 13 years ago you would<br />
have to acknowledge </p>
<p>PM: He left the leadership in 1989.<br />
J: You would have to acknowledge though, that he has been the driving<br />
force behind many of the changes to industrial relations in Australia?<br />
PM: And, what is his policy? What is his policy on Industrial Relations?<br />
What is his policy?<br />
J: A lot of his policies of 10 years ago are now adopted by your<br />
Government....<br />
PM: No, they're not. When he talks about wage flexibility, he is talking<br />
about cutting the wages of people under $ 35,000. That is what it<br />
means. It is code for cutting the wages of the low paid and middle paid<br />
people. That is what it means. And, I will just remind you of what<br />
President Bill Clinton said in his State of the Union Address in the<br />
American Congress about a week ago he said " There is an army of<br />
American working poor who haven't had a real wage increase in 17<br />
years" now, I just told you that in this country people have had a 4%<br />
real wage increase over the last year that is ( in America) because of<br />
the sort of policy that John Howard believes in, no adequate safety net,<br />
and you take the contract and go home, or you go home empty<br />
handed.<br />
J: And, yet, he said yesterday he believes in a safety-net, he outlines his<br />
policies....<br />
PM: He has opposed every wage increase since 1983. All those increases<br />
which came through the centralised wage system he opposed. He<br />
says he believes in families, but he doesn't believe in family support.<br />
He doesn't believe in help for the unemployed they thought the<br />
money that we spent in Working Nation on getting the<br />
unemployed.... when I said that we won't leave the unemployed behind,<br />
we dragged them up behind us, we would include them in this huge<br />
growth and employment, when I introduced last year the Working<br />
Nation White Paper and Statement, the Liberal Party said it was an<br />
extravagance we were spending money.<br />
J: But, isn't there a danger for you in looking at his past record, talking<br />
about what he has done in the past, instead of joining the battle now in<br />
the....<br />
PM: ( inaudible)... but you asked me John Howard is a known quantity.<br />
The Liberal Party he is their 3rd preference. They had a chance, in<br />
this Parliament, to say " Look, John Hewson lost the election, so we will<br />
take John Howard back", and they said " no, no we're not having<br />
Howard", so they gave it to Hewson. He fell over, and they said, " Well,<br />
Hewson has gone maybe we should have Howard?", and they said, </p>
<p>" No, no we are not having Howard, we're having Downer". As the<br />
Liberal Party's third choice they want it to be the country's first<br />
choice....<br />
J: But, are you going to sit here with a straight face, and look at me now,<br />
and tell me that you find Alexander Downer a more potent opponent<br />
than John Howard? John Howard is surely a more difficult opponent<br />
for you than Alexander Downer?<br />
PM: Don't ask me what I think why did the Liberal Party pass over him 3<br />
times? I just say this to people: All this stuff about colour pictures of<br />
everyone in harmony on the front, this is the guy that said a couple of<br />
weeks ago he'd pole-axe his leader right at the last minute, he said<br />
you swear support for the leader and when he's dead you tell him you<br />
pole-axed him. I mean he did this to Downer...<br />
J: But that doesn't that make him a more dangerous opponent...<br />
PM: How long ago was it they brought us the dream team? Downer and<br />
Costello. The dream team. And before that the Messiah, Dr Hewson.<br />
You can't take that sort of media pap in, seriously.<br />
J: I'm not asking the media, I'm asking one of the most experienced<br />
politicians in the country...<br />
PM: I'm telling you...<br />
J: Who's the tougher opponent out of Downer and Howard?<br />
PM: John, I take them as they come. You see, remember all this debate<br />
about early elections? All this last year, Keating's going to have an<br />
early election. Keating was never having an early election.<br />
J: All this tricky stuff he's going to slip in while Downer's in trouble.<br />
PM: The public deserve an even break to make good judgements at<br />
elections and I didn't do anything tricky so I take them without<br />
manipulation, I take them as they come. Hewson, Downer, Howard...<br />
the media are now feeling a bit poorly about themselves because they<br />
thought they were a bit hard on Alex, has decided now they will give<br />
John a free ride. All leaders get a free ride for a while, but the thing<br />
about John Howard, he's a known quantity, and what we know is he<br />
was a weak Treasurer, he couldn't get anything through his Cabinet,<br />
he left us with a moribund inward-looking economy and he was a weak<br />
leader who lost an election and ended up at thirteen per cent.<br />
J: This is the final question. He says he's made mistakes, you've made<br />
mistakes, he's prepared to admit his. </p>
<p>PM: I've admitted heaps of them, I've admitted to many mistakes.<br />
J: Could we have a couple of them?<br />
PM: Well, one was we tightened up too hard in 1988/ 89, I've said that<br />
plenty of times. But you see, John Howard wants the epitaph of<br />
" Honest John" yet he will always use a distortion every day of the week<br />
to suit himself.<br />
J: We go back to ' 88/ 89, people said you tightened up too hard because<br />
you left tightening up too late. Isn't the concern now that you've done<br />
exactly the same thing...<br />
PM: I think the charge against us at the moment has been we've tightened<br />
up too early but I think the numbers today reveal that that's not right.<br />
We've just about got this, I think, reasonably right. I mean the criticism<br />
last year was that the interest rate adjustments were too early. But I<br />
think if you look at today's forecasts, I think we've got them pretty right.<br />
J: All right. Paul Keating, we've run out of time, thank you.<br />
PM: Thankyou John.<br />
ends. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
