<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9563</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J.KEATING, MP &quot;HONEST JOHN&quot; AND THE GST</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/05/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009563.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER 40/ 95<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING, MP<br />
" HONEST JOHN" AND THE GST<br />
Today Mr Howard has said that the GST is no longer Coalition policy and will not be<br />
" lat any time in the future". Yesterday he said that there was " no way" the Coalition<br />
could have it as their policy for the next election, but " as to what happens some<br />
years in the future, I don't want to.. you know, I don't know".<br />
Today Mr Howard said that the OST is " completely off" the political agenda. Off the<br />
agenda but not off his mind. Mr Howard said yesterday that " there's nothing wrong"<br />
with the GST. And it wasn't the first time. In March this year he said it was " a<br />
shame" that they couldn't have a GST but they wouldn't be " having a GST or<br />
anything remotely resembling it for the next election". He wants it off the political<br />
agenda because he knows Australians won't vote for it but he wants to do by<br />
stealth what John Hewson failed to do by fanatical advocacy.<br />
In fact, Mr Howard is trying to get to the election without anything " remotely<br />
resembling" a policy at all. He is trying to make himself a very small target. That is<br />
why anything which " remotely resembles" a policy is poison to Mr Howard. The<br />
same goes for anything which " remotely resembles" leadership.<br />
We have seen it with his role in the push polling and Hindmarsh Island affairs. Mr<br />
Howard will not take a position of policy or principle until he is forced to then, as he<br />
has always done, he dithers and dissembles. As with the republic, so with the GST<br />
" as to what happens some years in the future, I don't want . you know, I don't<br />
know". Three months have passed since Mr Howard promised " headland speeches" which<br />
he said would define his position " with greater clarity." But the only thing which has<br />
become clearer is that John Howard has not changed a bit. Watch the polls and<br />
adjust the rhetoric and make " people feel comfortable", to use his own words. This<br />
is the attempt at a new electorally acceptable John Howard, but all the time he's<br />
playing footsie with his old reactionary friends and the GST.<br />
" I don't want to. . you know, I don't know", he says. He doesn't want to talk about it.<br />
He doesn't want the Australian people to know what he thinks. He doesn't want<br />
anyone to know what he intends.<br />
CANBERRA 2 May 1995 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
