<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1355</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S VISIT TO US AND UK - JOINT COMMUNIQUE BY PRESIDENT LYNDON B JOHNSON AND THE PRIME MINISTER MR HAROLD HOLT - RELEASED AT WHITE HOUSE, WASHINGTON DC - 14TH JULY 1966</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/07/1966</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001355.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
JOINT CC) M1VlUNIfUE BY PRESIDENT LYNDON B. JCHNS&amp; N AND<br />
THE PIMME MINISTER MR. HAROLD HOLT<br />
AT WH[' ITE HOUSE, WASIING'FCN, D. C.<br />
14th July, 1966.<br />
At the invitation of President Johnson, the Prime<br />
Minister of the Commonwealth of Australia, the Right Honourable<br />
Harold E. Holt, has returned to Washington to continue the<br />
discussions which they held on subjects of mutual interest on<br />
June 2 9. The President expressed his sincere appreciation<br />
for the Prime Minister's willingness to arrange travel arrangements<br />
to make their meeting possible.<br />
The President and the Prime Minister reaffirmed the<br />
determination of their two governments to assist the Republic of<br />
Vietnam and its people in their efforts to repel the armed a-; gression<br />
mounted against the Republic of Vietnam by the regime in Hanoi,<br />
and expressed full confidence that those efforts will be successful.<br />
They expressed again the desire of both governments that the<br />
fighting in South Vietnam be brought to an end as soon as possible<br />
through negotiation of an honourable peace, welcomed the<br />
initiative of the Prime Minister of India appealing to the government<br />
of the U. S. S. R. to reconvene a meeting of the Geneva powers anc<br />
reaffirmed their readiness to take part in tihis or other negotiations<br />
whenev-r the Hanoi regime indicate a willingne-$ s to do so.<br />
President Johnson reviewed for the Prime Minister<br />
military developments in Vietnam during the past two weeks. The<br />
Prime Minister expressed appreciation for this review of recent events.<br />
The Prime Minister discussed with the President his<br />
recent visit to London.<br />
The President and the Prime Minister reviewed the<br />
political, economic and social progress and developmert which has<br />
occurred in free Asia in recent years, most particularly in the first<br />
half of 1966, and agreed that these developments are of Ihe greatest<br />
significance for the future of Asia, the Pacific area and the world.<br />
The President and the Prime Minister noted that among these developments<br />
has been the healing of old quarrels between nations of the region, the<br />
recent establishment of the Asian and Pacific Council, the imminent formal<br />
inauguration of the Asian Development Bank in which both the United<br />
States and Australia are participating, and concrete steps towards the<br />
development of the Mekong Basin.<br />
The President and the Prime Minister described these<br />
events and the growing sense of regional identity in Asia and the Pacific<br />
area as most encouraging for the possibility of future peace and<br />
peaceful progress in the region. They expressed their belief that<br />
these developments have in no small measure been made possible by the<br />
shield of security provided to the region by the determination of the<br />
gallant people of Vietnam and those assisting them to repel communist<br />
aggression. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
The President and the Prime Minister noted with<br />
satisfaction the steady strengthening in the ties linking their two<br />
countries, particularly the flow of trade and investment, co-operation<br />
in exploring the mysteries of space and common efforts in a broad<br />
range of other scientific projects.<br />
The President and the Prime Minister ag: eed that there<br />
exist opportunities for further great undertakings in the peaceful<br />
development of Asia, and these opportunities will be greatly expanded<br />
when peace returns to the region. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
