<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11304</transcript-id>
    <title>AUSTRALIAN-AMERICAN FRIENDSHIP WEEK AND             BATTLE OF THE CORAL SEA COMMEMORATIONS</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/05/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I warmly welcome the generous greetings President Clinton has sent</p>
<p> to all Australians on the occasion of Australian-American Friendship</p>
<p> Week and as part of commemorations to celebrate the 57th</p>
<p> anniversary of the Battle of the Coral Sea. I fully share the President's</p>
<p> views on the close and valuable partnership which as good friends</p>
<p> and allies our two nations share. Through that partnership we continue</p>
<p> to work together to advance the common interests not only of Australia</p>
<p> and the United States but of all people who cherish peace and the</p>
<p> freedom which democracy brings.</p>
<p>An important foundation of this partnership was the Battle of the</p>
<p> Coral Sea in May 1942, a remarkable battle that changed the course</p>
<p> of the Pacific War. From the courage and patriotism that our forces</p>
<p> came to respect so much in each other, the bonds of a firm and true</p>
<p> friendship have grown between our nations and our peoples, a friendship</p>
<p> which, in its most mature form, is embodied in the strong alliance</p>
<p> between our two countries.</p>
<p>The bonds formed between us fifty-seven years ago retain their relevance</p>
<p> and vitality in these very different times. They are reflected in</p>
<p> many ways: in the continued success of the ANZUS treaty; in our close</p>
<p> cooperation on regional and international issues; in the many contacts</p>
<p> between Australians and Americans; in our shared desire for a resilient</p>
<p> global economy; and in our concerted efforts to eradicate the scourge</p>
<p> of narcotics.</p>
<p>Australian-American friendship endures because it rests upon shared</p>
<p> liberal democratic values. But the democracy we enjoy today was paid</p>
<p> for through the courage and personal sacrifice of the young Australians</p>
<p> and Americans who fought in the Battle of the Coral Sea and in the</p>
<p> many military campaigns that followed. We are forever in their debt.</p>
<p> We shall continue to honour and remember them.</p>
<p>I welcome the announcement that the United States Ambassador to Australia,</p>
<p>Genta Hawkins Holmes, will be President Clinton's personal representative</p>
<p> for Australian-American Friendship Week and the 57th Anniversary</p>
<p> of the Battle of the Coral Sea. Ambassador Hawkins Holmes will participate</p>
<p> in a number of events, in commemoration of the battle, in Sydney and</p>
<p> in Canberra.</p>
<p> 7 May 1999</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
