<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>359</transcript-id>
    <title>PM 45/1961 - BEEF ROADS - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISER, THE RT. HON. R G MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/08/1961</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000359_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
61<br />
EMBARCO: Not for publication or broadcast before 8 p. m. E. S. T.<br />
SUNDAY, 27th August P. M. No. 1l91<br />
BEEF ROADS<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, the Rt. Hon. R. G. Menzies<br />
In his recent Budget speech, Mr. Holt, in dealing<br />
with the matter of Roads for the cattle industry, indicated<br />
some particular provisions totalling œ 1,000,000 in respect of<br />
Queensland and the Northern Territory. He then said:-<br />
" The provision of œ 1,000,000 is by no moans,<br />
however, the limit of the expenditure we have in view.<br />
Subject to agreement being reached with the Governments<br />
of Queensland and Western Australia, we are willing, and<br />
indeed we intend, to provide additional funds for roads<br />
in these two States."<br />
After the completion of our Railways no got.:<br />
with Mr. Brand, Mr. Court, and Western Australian of:. ciaaI,<br />
we took up the question of beef roads.<br />
The Commonwealth has, in consequence, made an<br />
agreement that, matching corresponding provisions by J.. estern<br />
Australia in relation to roads in the Kimberleys, it will find<br />
œ 00,000 for the improvement of the Wyndham-Nicholson road,<br />
the Wyndham-Turkey Creek-Hall's Creek road, and necessary<br />
bridges over the Bandicoot Bar and the Dunham River.<br />
These works are calculated to increase the offturn<br />
in good condition of beef cattle, primarily for export.<br />
CANBERRA, 27th August, 1961. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
