<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>23771</transcript-id>
    <title>Celebrating Australia&#039;s Defining Moments</title>
    <prime-minister>Abbott, Tony</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130918 - 20150915</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/08/2014</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The 200th anniversary of Governor Arthur Phillip’s life was commemorated today at the launch of the <em>Defining Moments in Australian History</em> project at the National Museum of Australia in Canberra.</p>
<p>In a moment that set the course for modern Australia, Governor Phillip led the First Fleet to Botany Bay in January 1788.</p>
<p>He founded the first British settlement at Sydney and became the first Governor of the colony of New South Wales.</p>
<p>Two hundred years after Phillip’s death on 31 August, a new plaque in the National Museum’s main hall now marks Phillip’s central historical role, which begins the new <em>Defining Moments</em> project.</p>
<p><em>Defining Moments</em> will cover key events and episodes in Australia’s history with a series of plaques and online content including the beginnings of Indigenous rock art around 28,000 years ago, Ned Kelly’s last stand at Glenrowan, Victoria in 1880 and the first organised game of Australian Rules football in 1858.</p>
<p>Australians are encouraged to reflect on our remarkable history and contribute to the selection of the 100 moments that have defined Australia.</p>
<p>Today’s event follows the laying of a memorial stone in London’s Westminster Abbey in July to honour Phillip’s life and his historical contribution.</p>
<p>For more information and to participate visit Defining Moments at <a href="///C:/Users/bolits/AppData/Local/Microsoft/Windows/Temporary%20Internet%20Files/Content.Outlook/KZGAVQYR/www.nma.gov.au/definingmoments">www.nma.gov.au/definingmoments</a>.</p>
<p>29 August 2014</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
