<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1923</transcript-id>
    <title>RENAMING OF U.S. NAVAL COMMUNICATION AT NORTH-WEST CAPE, W.A. - 20 SEPTEMBER 1968, SPEECH BY PRIME MINISTER, MR JOHN GORTON</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/09/1968</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001923.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
RENAMING OF U. S. NAVAL COMMUNICATION<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister, Mr John Gorton<br />
I must begin, your Excellency, by thanking the President of<br />
the United States, through you, for the message, which through you, he<br />
delivered to us today. It is a unique thing for a United States Naval<br />
Communication station of this kind to be named after the national of another<br />
country. But I thin'k for a number of reasons, it is entirely fitting that in<br />
this case it should be so.<br />
For one thing, it is fitting because I do not think that there was<br />
any Australian statesman or any statesm ' an from any other nation who<br />
established such warm, close, personal relations with a President of the<br />
United States as were established by Harold Holt. And this is a matter<br />
which goes beyond a mere personal satisfaction in such relations and<br />
extends into national benefits that flow from them.<br />
It is fitting too because this station, as part of a giant network<br />
keeping watch and ward on all the oceans of the world, is a station which<br />
will enhance the military capacity, not only of the United States but also<br />
of our own nation, Australia.<br />
Military caepacity can be used in many ways. It can be used to<br />
subjugate peoples and overthrow feeedom as we saw it used by Hitler and<br />
Mussolini. It can be used to stifle freedom of expression as we recently<br />
saw it used in Czechoslovakia. It can be used for invasion and aggression<br />
as we saw it used in Korea, and as we are seeing it used by North Viet<br />
Nam in South Viet<br />
But military capacity can be used in other ways. It can be used<br />
as a shield for freedom, It can be used as a method of deterring aggression,<br />
of maintaining freedom, of succouring the weak. An d the United States<br />
and Australia has used, and in my belief will always use, its military capacity<br />
merely for the latter purposes. So it is fitting again that these purposes<br />
should be served by a station named after a man who had these ideals as<br />
those he would wish to see all over the world.<br />
Finally, Sir, it is also fitting that this should be a Naval<br />
Communication Station because the late Prime Minister was a man who loved<br />
the sea and who was happiest when close to the sea.<br />
We feel honour, Sir, at what you have done. We feel confidence<br />
in what this station will help our countries to shield, and we remember that<br />
a year agq the man after whom this station was named stood here and opened<br />
the complex. I hope you will convey to your President the gratitude of the people<br />
of Australia that this gesture has been made, and the resolution of the p eople<br />
of Australia that in co-operation with the United States, we shall seek to<br />
secure that peace with freedom of which, Sir, you have spoken.<br />
I thank you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
