<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4660</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/03/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004660.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Embargo until delivery<br />
FOR PRESS 26 March 1978<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
" One man's wage increase is another man's job" the prophetic<br />
words of a former Labor Treasurer are just as accurate, just<br />
as relevant today.<br />
Excessive wage increases lose jobs and threaten jobs. It is<br />
for that reason that a key element in the Government's economic<br />
policy strongly endorsed by Australians at two general<br />
elections is our wages policy.<br />
Wages are an integral part of the functioning of the whole<br />
economy. If the economy is to perform efficiently so that<br />
more jobs can be created then wage rates cannot be allowed to<br />
get out of line with other relevent trends in the economy.<br />
They also cannot be allowed to get out of line with overseas<br />
trends. In Australia in recent times, wages have grown out of all<br />
proportion to producitivity. We experienced a " wage explosion".<br />
For example, in the three years to the end of 1975, wages grew<br />
by an amount equal to six years normal growth. This unparalleled<br />
growth in wages was not accompanied by an equivalent increase<br />
in production and productivity.<br />
Rising wages led to higher costs, inflation and inevitably to<br />
the loss of jobs. our industry became uncompetitive in world<br />
markets. It is for these fundamental reasons that the Government has taken<br />
a strong and consistent stand on the wages issue.<br />
We have argued before the Arbitration Commission that full<br />
quarterly wage indexation is a barrier to the return to full<br />
economic health. It would lock the economy into higher and<br />
totally unacceptable levels of inflation.<br />
The Commission has seen merit in the Government's argument.<br />
It has awarded less than full wage indexation.<br />
Inflation in Australia is steadily falling. It is already<br />
below 10%, but it must keep falling. It is vital for Australia.<br />
that we hold on to those hard-won gains. We cannot risk going<br />
back to the days of the escalating wage-price merry-go-round.<br />
That would immediately destroy confidence in Australia's future.<br />
/ 2 </p>
<p>It is for this reason that the call by the ACTU Executive for<br />
industrial action for full wage indexation is to be deplored.<br />
It would increase both inflation and unemployment. Put bluntly,<br />
it is in direct conflict with the national interest.<br />
I find it almost impossible to believe that when Australia is<br />
climbing out of a recession, which was largely the result of the<br />
1974 wage explosion, that the ACTU could even contemplate such<br />
a policy.<br />
I believe the men and women on the shop floors and in offices<br />
throughout Australia the rank and file unionist will reject<br />
the calls of their executive.<br />
Above all else, Trade Unionists clearly understand that excessive<br />
wage increases threaten their jobs, and their workmates jobs.<br />
They still remember what happened during those years when trade<br />
union leaders got the wage increases they sought. They remember<br />
the high inflation and the jobs lost.<br />
The conversations I have with men and womfen in factories show<br />
very plainly that they do understand these forces. They don't<br />
complain about our stand on wage indexation. They know there<br />
is simply no alternative. In fact, I have a strong feeling that<br />
Trade Unionists generally would be satisfied with an annual<br />
adjustment to their wage packet.<br />
I am convinced that the action of the ACTU Executive does not<br />
reflect the view of rank and file unionists. People understand<br />
that if manufacturers and businesses had to add to their wage<br />
and salary bills, they would be left with no course but to put<br />
up their prices, which is more inflation, and would inevitably<br />
have to reduce their workforce.<br />
A graphic reminder of the relationship between high wage increases<br />
and unemployment occurred in Canberra recently. Two fast-food<br />
outlets have had to close. Owned by a worldwide chain, they<br />
tied for the position of having the highest labour costs of the<br />
comapny's 4,800 outlets around the world. Labour at the two<br />
Canberra outlets had cost $ 5.36 an hour, compared with $ 2.60 an<br />
hour in the United States, $ 3.00 in the United Kingdon, $ 2.70<br />
in Canada, $ 1.00 in Japan, and $ 3.00 in Holland and Scandanavia.<br />
With the closure, 10 full time and 90 part time jobs were lost.<br />
The company couldn't afford to keep their doors open.<br />
What more evidence does the ACTU Executive want about the jobs<br />
that are lost and threatened by wages that are out of line with<br />
the developed world?<br />
Australia today is steadily on course to economic recovery. The<br />
Government's task for this year is to build on the solid gains<br />
of the last years.<br />
All Australians have a role to play and all special interest<br />
groups and sections have obligations to the total community.<br />
I and the Government hope that for these groups the national<br />
interest will override any other interest. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
