<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>15343</transcript-id>
    <title>Prime Minister&#039;s Weekly Radio Message</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/08/2007</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...</p>
<p>  Listen to this Speech (MP3 -   1.91Mb - 100secs)</p>
<p>Labor's dishonest double game with the Australian public is on display again.</p>
<p>Labor's shadow treasurer Wayne Swan - who would manage Australia's one trillion dollar economy in a Kevin Rudd-Union Government - attacked the Coalition for its post-Budget expenditure when appearing on the ABC Insiders program.</p>
<p>While Mr Swan fails to acknowledge that Labor's own post-Budget commitments exceed $4.6 billion, the weekend attack raises an obvious question.</p>
<p>If Mr Rudd has now decided to oppose the Government's commitments, which of them will be axed if Labor wins Government?</p>
<p>The Government has, for example, set aside $1.8 billion for disability support services, $627 million for climate change programs, $629 million for new drugs to deal with macular degeneration and just over half a billion dollars for the national indigenous emergency.</p>
<p>There have been outlays on important water projects, school chaplaincy services and even money for the Red Cross Blood Bank.  </p>
<p>Will one or all of these important initiatives be axed?</p>
<p>Mr Rudd and Labor cannot simply attack the Government's initiatives without setting out which programs would be cut.</p>
<p>The reality is that Mr Rudd and Mr Swan would not dismantle any of these initiatives.</p>
<p>They would have the Australian public believe they oppose the aggregate of the Government's spending, but this is a cynical deception because they have offered specific support for the individual programs.</p>
<p>If Kevin Rudd and Labor believe they are ready to govern they should take the Australian people into their confidence and start telling the truth about their policies and positions.</p>
<p>The Australian people deserve nothing less.  </p>
<p>  Listen to this Speech (MP3 -   1.91Mb - 100secs)</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
