<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4937</transcript-id>
    <title>AUSTRALIA AND SOME WORLD ECONOMIC ISSUES - A SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA, THE RT HON MALCOLM FRASER, CH MP, TO THE ECONOMIC CLUB OF NEW YORK ON 4 JANUARY 1978</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/01/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004937_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
AUSiRALIAN HNFORiNVATION SERVICE<br />
1 7 JAN 9 63 Fifth Avenue, New York, N. Y. 10020 ( 2 12) 245-4000<br />
AUSTRALIA AND SOME W4ORLD ECONOMIC ISSUES<br />
A SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA,<br />
THE RT. HON. MALCOLM FRASER, M. P.<br />
TO<br />
THE ECONOMIC CLUB OF NEW YORK ON 4 JANUARY, 197 õ<br />
It is a great pleasure to be in the U. S. again and have the<br />
opportunity to address this very important group of American<br />
business leaders. I a, also pleased to have the opportunity<br />
to try to collect my bet with Arthur Burns, a bet about which<br />
I think, some of you may know.<br />
When we met in Washington In June, ' 977, he made one of his<br />
few errors of Judgement and bet me that Australia would not<br />
get its inflation rate down below this country's by the June<br />
quarter of 1978. Well, we did. Doing so has not been easy<br />
it never is.<br />
I am sure that the anti-inflationary measures announced in this<br />
country two months ago by President Carter were not easily<br />
arrived at either.<br />
To announce measures of that kind shortly In advance of the<br />
congressional election must have required considerable political<br />
courage. And if I may say so, vie in Australia have greatly<br />
welcomed the policy decisions involved.<br />
The contribution they are making towards stabilizing the value<br />
of the U. S. dollar has as much9 or more significance, for the<br />
rest of the world as it does for the United States. / The </p>
<p>2<br />
The absolute magnitude of U. S. trade11eafls that even small changes<br />
in the value of the dollar have large effects on the trade of<br />
smaller countries.<br />
In reflecting upon our own fight against inflation, I must say it<br />
has taken us three years of hard slog to make the progress we<br />
have made.<br />
Throughout that period our policies have been designed to reestablish<br />
the pre-conditlons for sustainable economic growth.<br />
We have approached the task of economic restoration in a mediumterm<br />
framework.<br />
After the economic turmoil through which the Australian economy<br />
passed a few years ago, it takes time to eliminate economic<br />
distortions and imbalances, to provide a settled framework of<br />
expectations within which businessmen and consumers can take<br />
decisions with confidence0<br />
America has recent'y been swept by initi~ t~ ves such as<br />
Proposition 13 deslned to restrin the qrowth of public sector<br />
spending.<br />
l am told that the eections iast November showed that this is a.<br />
political winner across the U. S.<br />
Well, the basic philosophy reflected in Proposition 13 has been<br />
alive and well in Australia for the past three years.<br />
We have rejected the notion that an economy can be kept moving<br />
by continually bioating the public sector,<br />
We have cut the growth in Federal Government expenditures from<br />
the astronomiral figure of 46 per cent in 1974-75, to less than<br />
8 per cent. We still think that's a bit too high.<br />
We have used some of the resultant savings to reduce taxes,<br />
to put spending and decision-making power back into the hands<br />
of businesses and private individuals where it more properly<br />
belongs. / We </p>
<p>3<br />
We have legislated to keep Government honest by providing for<br />
indexation of personal income tax.<br />
To encourage continuing economic growth we have provided tax<br />
incentives for private Investment.<br />
We have not been able to pass on all the expenditure savings to<br />
the private sector because we inherited an enormous budget<br />
deficit over 5 per cent of nD. P, We have set about reducing<br />
it, and this financial year the deficit should be about 2.8 per<br />
cent of G. D. P.<br />
We have cut back the rate of growth in our money supply. The<br />
rate of growth of our M3 which incidentally corresponds more<br />
nearly to your M2-has been reduced from around 20 per cent per<br />
annum in the second half of 1975 to 8 per cent in 1977-78.<br />
Let me now tell you briefly about how these policies have been<br />
bearing fruit.<br />
Our major success has been in pushln. q our annual Inflation rate<br />
down from about 17 per cent in 1975 to about seven and a half<br />
per cent. This is lower than the average for the O. E. C. D. area<br />
as a whole and it is trending downwards.<br />
In the light of the -ecent wage decision the Treasury has revise. d<br />
its budget forecast3 and anticipates that inflation will be under<br />
6 per cent by the mlddle of tnis year,<br />
Lower inflation is encouraqinq consumers to spend a higher<br />
proportion of their disposable incomes. And this is reflected<br />
in the fall of the personal savings ratio from its peak of a few<br />
years ago.<br />
Business investment, by both domestic and overseas enterorises,<br />
has been rising strongly, partly because of the greater business<br />
certainty flowing from lower inflation, and also because of some<br />
although not yet enough recovery in corporate profitability.<br />
At the same time as we have been pursuing our anti-inflationary<br />
strategy, we have had a growth record which stands up well<br />
enough by international comparison: I do not want to give the<br />
impression that we think all our economic problems have been<br />
overcome. Vie still have some way to go, and this is most<br />
obvious in the area of unemployment, / There </p>
<p>-4<br />
There are two reasons~ fo-that -ene generall, one particular.<br />
The general reason is " hat when an e~ or,, ry has been so fractured<br />
as the Australia et-. ntmy wis a few yeifat azo It takes a time<br />
for the steady apo tcaticn 6fpe1: e tZ; out things right,<br />
re-establish cnflaer., e in the. comimun'ity and restore the buoyant<br />
growth of private oe:-' and that is fundamerntal to growing job<br />
opportunities. The particular raaSo is that our own<br />
institutional wage ? ixIng aranements where wages are<br />
determined by an independent ar~~ to~ cor.-imission have notmade<br />
the contribatlorn tney shud tzo :-oroimll recovery.<br />
In most ma-: kets whn przoduct Is in SL-rrius supply, and people<br />
want to sell -more of it, they seek their price. In<br />
the labour imarket hcwever, people fwor-et that economic truism.*<br />
Even though labou~ r is Inl 3ver supply, -union leaders still seek<br />
excessihe wage I nceezaes. This plainy makes it harder to get<br />
people back into Jobs,<br />
Mr. Chairman, what I want to imake E&amp;-a to~ day is that we will<br />
maintain the pvresent steady cast of rpcl;-y untZil these problems<br />
are overcoee Oze alim it-rotz for in-Stanee, to be satisfi-ed<br />
when we hai.: e reduced' lrO; Iaftian tz 5 pe-: ant, but to go well<br />
beyond. Inflation iintreiers-eest ratea, itakes brusliness decisifris<br />
morfe risky and res crsct e-f spenfli nq. It distorts the<br />
re a ti on s hp 6E twe r, w&amp; qe s a nd pvof Its j -Yak-e s domestic business<br />
less competitive in-1e~ n~! 3rUl~ y, ano' social inequities.<br />
Too o ften;. we na%, e S ear Civ_ nrienr ts-&amp; k E Some ilhoderate though<br />
impor-' Lt pr~ qgr'es 3 Z n % atr nor. y to throw away the<br />
ga ins by tirn IA tz~ btdcg* ary p-r omlnoq wh ich cannot<br />
&amp; chi ev~ e a perria,~ eri -lop 1 n tL n e : yxie nt or bring any<br />
lasting eacl-nemc beneflts. The:, e Oa're trncss on Australia who,<br />
now that we ha 7-ade so muchn prcqreSS the fight against<br />
i nf ' Iat Isn we-i d h Ye u, f .3 . w tniav Wea -h ave no intention<br />
of doing sc Suc 6 CCoUrszE 7ay tepWr A-; aiy p , cv Id e some new<br />
jobs, but -it tne Co~ t ef exist," ng. ones -as the rise In<br />
I n f'It Iona~ r y pe atior; whilon i t Lsz. set i eads to a loss of<br />
business an~ d eznrumr confidence, 1; ess Conlumer demand, less<br />
investment both by 65msttic ancl faeivt ': n* 1estors, and hence<br />
fewer jobs.<br />
In the end new jzbs will only be created if our econoi1es groiw<br />
faster than they -nave heen, F3-' that tL happen, the constr&amp; i nts<br />
which are preyierinrq thst -rowth linflatic-n, the imbaiance<br />
between wages and p, ak-ti-, rity, arid te inadequacy of profits<br />
will have to be re-moved. They will! notI be removed by budgetary<br />
puimp priming. / Those </p>
<p>Those who expect. Go,, efnmernts to sti, 11' ate the economy by<br />
ir'v'-asing ( Goveznier1z exren6lttire tat the first sign that<br />
inflation Is fall-inq miunde* stand the nature and the<br />
cure of the ec~ n. itc. anid so: Ilal i ness we are facing.<br />
The fundamental pcint is that the reouction of inflation is<br />
stimulatory of itself It re-estaol shes consumer<br />
confidence and the -rtfidence of domiestic and overseas<br />
investors. Those chanjed attitudes a. ee then accompanied by<br />
higher consumer4 demand and htgher in-veStment arid lower interest<br />
rates. That pro:-ess in tu; rn efeates employment. Thus, I<br />
utterly reject are' tu-estlcn hnat ou po'~ leies show no concern<br />
for unemploy,-aent and the 6nesmployea. On the contrary, it is<br />
because of our conzer-n ftr those thngs that we have persevered<br />
with the policies wniz: n we know ar e es erntial if unemployment<br />
is ever to be redt~ ced,<br />
I believe that -he 1,~ t_ 5, ce of the fiqht against inflation<br />
i s now be tt er ude . toaIP te a ton -yo At the September<br />
meeting of the i M, F. 86a~ 6 of ' ersthe Secretary-General<br />
of the O. E. COD., Einii Van Lerinep, Sa-XG' that: " Unacceptably<br />
high rates of eex,&amp;' Ie~ n the 4udamental obstacle to getting.<br />
back to fal I empz! yriment)<br />
The Annua_ Rept~ i-; nf riAOTJ. 34 liast Saptember stated: " The<br />
in d US t Tia iC caZi AeZ I t fl3 r,~ oa e inwcare-ass ed growth and<br />
de Y e13 pi e~ n s n6 t I~ s ta vb I a~-f ents positions and more<br />
stable ew. rzanqe re6D; yi Jn; hee.-inI nfation ratCes to the<br />
levels exPE;, fiEnzed rwW thEmI d1 960 s,<br />
Just a rew dayis aqo 1. A1U-c&amp; the ~ e. sof rgovernment of seven<br />
d eve a-Pe6C a n J A t -1es _ C -qr-lsee ir the clearest<br />
t rs tnh at ' Irn tz: 5nL cir at,-erny ' ve 01l agreed that<br />
the interda rndaA~ te ct a l.. th of) Industrialised<br />
natiens and thE tM fm zrcreased growth in the<br />
developing o-6 de., rifde0 thet'L irf ! Qti,: n be viqorously combatted<br />
both do-me~ tlaaly arG* 0 n Z~ y<br />
Yt is of the xp~-aj4;-; t6 n1e tr,,-t tniese sentiments should<br />
not remain inerely Sen~ timents; but thtat they should be carried<br />
through to the Tokyo-EEcn~ mic Su'mit in June, and into the<br />
policies of Gavern; ments,<br />
It is somet-lifes Said11 tniat 1i d&amp; MO. f-8ies where there are elections<br />
every few year~ s, it IS d6ifficult tC, pe-, severe with firm) antiinflatioraary<br />
pe'llie-s lipli,. itly -oe even explicitly in some<br />
cases this view is b ased upon cw 6piion of our democratic<br />
electorates. This is an opinlon that. 1 do not share. What our<br />
democratic ele.-torate~ do require its leadership and constant<br />
explanation 5f p&amp; ciles, </p>
<p>-6<br />
I believe that the public does understand that inflation is an<br />
illness and that recovery from it will give our economies * a<br />
genuine stimulus towards growth and fulil employment.<br />
I believe the public knows that those committed to antiinflationary<br />
policies show more concern for the real well-being<br />
of people than politicians who glibl~ y pursue short-term<br />
stimulatory policies, which will no. t solve economic problems<br />
and will in fact make them worse.<br />
Anti-inflation policies are the best way to shift the balance<br />
back in favour of risk-takers WnHeO of loading the dice against<br />
them. Attacking inflation strengthens cut market-oriented system, which<br />
finds its greatest superiority over " command economies" in its<br />
capacity to handle change. It is that very process of change<br />
which, in the end, delivers the goods and services which people<br />
want, at the prices and In the places at which they want them,<br />
Any ecnmy that is to remain vital anid vigorous must be capable<br />
of adaptation ard change and Gove~ rnments need to structure their<br />
policies acodingly They must a~ commodate the fact that<br />
economies are not static but living entities constantly changing<br />
to meet the chngig preferences of consumers both at home and<br />
abroad. Inflation net only daae growth Vf domestic markets, not only<br />
reduces emplymaQV arnd weakens the basis of our market system,<br />
it quickly flcws trough into the inte~ national economy and<br />
retards the develcpment of world trc~ e, Countries w'ith high<br />
inflation rstes beoime un mel~; their exports fall, theirimpor~<br />
ts rise, and Mytably their currencies depreciate.<br />
It is ironic that the flex~ ible exchange rate which has become<br />
needed princip~ ally betause countrie;' domestic policies have<br />
been inadequate is sometimes heralded as a significant advance<br />
in its own right.<br />
It is true that the flexible exchange rate gives us another<br />
weapon in our econemic armoury. But it should, however, be<br />
recognised that it is a weapon which compensates either for<br />
Government's own NAe O4 Qlcv indequacies or for the<br />
domestic policy inbdequacies of others, / In </p>
<p>In turn Irf' a01 sn an 6t a an ernp Iyrtier' zit i nevi t abl y brln qs<br />
produiCe of1-be? rtS, s tyi~ ca~ d e ana aAr-at the root of the<br />
re-me~ er~ eo? zsm, one~ -the central economic.-<br />
probeso tl Ucirete ountries have looked<br />
t3 i'nnre a-nd mtfe : infor ithei 00-mestic industries.<br />
For example~ we that the E. EKC. countries are<br />
currently spenaL7n; hou $ 05) B41111on a year on a new form<br />
of Protecti nisr" so c&amp;, uiled job subsdijes, These give<br />
effective iroientd~ urst ry aq&amp; nst imports and are a<br />
hi dd ean foc rt, ; i E4 , z 6sid<br />
A fundamentPO r~ t to ! stop enc. oaching protectionism<br />
an d f u rth e-6e ; s d trade ~ s h ed o ut by th e mul0ilateral<br />
tra de r at e But the M. T. M. is to re-n-lse<br />
its praimie;. the re. enc~ k:
If the a exerlt a. e -!-srcted o vnaoistrial products they<br />
wil ii,-e-14; rff-nt propo; t-c-in of world trade. These<br />
industria poGtt s to 40 pel, cent OT the exports of<br />
the ma~ j oa : rnde~ uo zr-a2 Ca-ut only 20 per cent of world<br />
trade and nec _ 5ep ev cen. * zr? -, he exports of many<br />
T he i1 n E. eo.; ction of the averazie<br />
ievali of by ht'K-j E Per cent a year spread<br />
itT e n-ed eemen t pl ain1ly could<br />
make a.) I Y a f i r b atu n Cjw; 74s expanding world<br />
inar~ ke ts s ts a Z'r. u t o r .3 ~ ne MlTN m~ ay he to help<br />
check tre r'" Z s n. r T-ufactured goods, but it<br />
Wd ' 3 ti: ta L, hlie t oth of world trade, an~ d it<br />
wou' 0A do t c, tIevr . ' ZIje oY. ectionism in agricuflture.<br />
ups a j. e~ r:. j~ e pa-t cz aK; affected by growing<br />
P t o~, e Fi se . i o s half of our ex
a eicit u-rauzt wnf l. fP , e oeer; esubJected to quotas,<br />
embarqoes9 vafiabia is ar~ d duropngj of surpluses.<br />
F or e x a mp Ia, t h a C. In 197' 8 r' US 12 B iIi o n i n agicultutal<br />
support, a'irncst $ US 5 Billion on direct subsidies on<br />
the expor~ t cf wiheatj d&amp;~ ry D-r~ oaucts ana meat, mucn Or IL<br />
to our tvz ota I 6r aes<br />
If the MOTONO is ~ a a real then it is essential<br />
that tr -de In a4 fCbe ' ijbe-a-. sed, and I am glad that<br />
the UJ, S. A&amp;% J1s t'~ t 6hares thi. s vi~ ew, 1. h e t h er </p>
<p>u S~ ti eC-z"; 5 a f ed n e t rIes<br />
zy 11 t 1-1 ant o, the<br />
r, e~ iO I $ u3 81ii1f1l 0ri toSu<br />
2 O Bl i n C-dp G r e eie ne<br />
i n s3 O) fii o n s vI be C h e~-6roK SO . r e&amp; t decade these<br />
r,~ ai ck. h a t n ESz r 3 L a o riit de<br />
rt~ i Vh Y 4N wr ,4' IC O these n<br />
1e L neo<br />
a. r, d<br />
do a~ r~~ ti: hp I es<br />
t 3. v ise t--A f. OT r<br />
t s e ' 4 E. e. i 1Wm e A . r . ired r i, e </p>
<p>-9-<br />
We in Australia are determined to meet the challenges posed by<br />
our enormous resource potential and the dynamism of our region.<br />
To do so effectively, we shall need the help of overseas capital.<br />
I cannot emphasise too strongly that Australia welcomes overseas<br />
investment to supplement its already high level of capital<br />
formation from domestic sources.<br />
Devel opment of our resource potential is going to require<br />
considerable capital funds from overseas. The total investment<br />
finance required for that purpose over the next three years<br />
could be nearly $ US 7 Billion and a major proportion of this<br />
estimated requirement will need to be sought offshore. Figures<br />
such as these are necessarily speculative but they will give you<br />
an idea of the opportunities which are opening up in Australia<br />
as vie bring our own economy into better shape. Those opportunities<br />
are, we believe, enhanced by the great markets opening up in the<br />
countries immediately to our north.<br />
We are a " natural" importer of long-term capital and are likely<br />
to remain so as far ahead as one can reasonably foresee.<br />
We are determined to Create, through our general economic policies,<br />
conditions which~ are favoueable to the emnloyment of capital in<br />
Australia, whethe-r der-ived from the sayings of our own people or<br />
from overseas investment.<br />
We have laid down clear quidelines for foreign investment and<br />
they are being admliistered flexlibly and fairly. I believe this<br />
general approach is now widely recoonised and supported hy foreign<br />
investors. it Is Incrfeasingly apparent that the chief deterrent<br />
to investment Is not sc much rules or guidelines in themselves,<br />
but any suggestion that those rules may be subject to violent and<br />
arbitrary chanqe. Ours will not be,<br />
Australia has unlimited prospects and offers excellent opportunities<br />
for investors. For its part, the Government is determined to<br />
pursue the steady, sound economic policies which will make the<br />
1980' s a decade of achievement. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
