<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>23541</transcript-id>
    <title>Australian business delegation to Canada and the United States of America</title>
    <prime-minister>Abbott, Tony</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130918 - 20150915</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/06/2014</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>To strengthen trade and investment ties between our countries, a delegation of Australian business representatives will accompany me when I visit Canada and the United States next week.</p>
<p>The business delegation will visit Ottawa and Toronto in Canada and New York and Houston in the United States.</p>
<p>This will be the first visit to Canada by an Australian Prime Minister since 2006. It’s an opportunity to reinvigorate the trade and investment relationship between Australia and Canada.</p>
<p>In Ottawa, I will host a roundtable with Australian and Canadian business leaders focusing on infrastructure and energy investment. Delegation members will also visit Toronto with the Minister for Trade and Investment, the Hon Andrew Robb.</p>
<p>The United States is Australia’s largest source of foreign investment, with more than $650 billion in total investment here. The US is also the number one destination for Australian investment abroad with more than $470 billion invested in the United States. A 20 member business delegation will accompany me to New York and Houston.</p>
<p>Trade and investment bring jobs and prosperity and Australia is once again ‘open for business’. The Government’s drive to cut red tape and abolish taxes that reduce our international competitiveness, such as the carbon tax and the mining tax, is making Australia an even more attractive environment for investment from the United States and Canada.</p>
<p><strong>Australian Business Delegation Members:</strong></p>
<p><strong>Canada: </strong>APPEA, Ausfilm, Austmine, Boeing Australia and South Pacific, BHP Billiton, Garvan Institute of Medical Research, IFM Investors, Infrastructure Partnership Australia, Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre, QIC, Transurban, Association of Australian Medical Research Institutes, Museum of Contemporary Art Australia.</p>
<p><strong>United States: </strong>American Chamber of Commerce, APPEA, Association of Australian Medical Research Institutes, Aurizon Holdings, AusFilm, Austmine, Boeing Australia and South Pacific, Garvan Institute of Medical Research, IFM Investors, Infrastructure Partnership Australia, Lend Lease, Macquarie Group, Museum of Contemporary Art Australia, National Gallery of Australia, Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre, QIC, Transurban, Origin Energy.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
