<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6408</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT, PRESS CONFERENCE, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, 6 JUNE 1984</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/06/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006408.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
E 0 E -PROOF ONLY<br />
TRANSCRIPT PRESS CONFERENCE PARLIAMENT HOUSE -6 JUNE 1984<br />
Ladies and gentlemen I've asked Bill Hayden to join<br />
me because of two reasons. I have specifically referred in<br />
the speech I made in the House to the role that he has been<br />
playing in these matters and he followed me in the House and as<br />
also I thought you -would. like the opportunity of perhaps addressing<br />
any questions to him as well. I simply want to say in a brief<br />
opening statement to you that what I've had to say today to<br />
the people of Australia through. the Parliament about the general<br />
purposes of the joint facilities has never been said previously<br />
by an Australian Government. And the particular purposes which<br />
have never been disclosed can be discerned in the following<br />
parts of my statement which I would refer to again briefly.<br />
That's where I said that a " timely knowledge of developments<br />
that have military significance is very important and can be<br />
critical for the security of the United States and its allies,<br />
including Australia,. Effective deterrence and hence avoidance<br />
of conflict depend.-on this. Similarly, effective measures for<br />
military restraint and f or the control and reduction of<br />
armaments depnd upn reliable assessments of military<br />
developments. Arms limitation arrangements between the United<br />
States and the Soviet Union specifically provide for verification.<br />
The general purpose of the facilities that we operate at<br />
Nurrungar and Pine Gap with the Americans is to contribute<br />
taol ofts obeives". Among the functions performed<br />
are the provision of early warning by receiving from space<br />
satellites information about missile launches, and the<br />
provision of information about the occurrence of nuclear<br />
explosions, which assists in nuclear test: ban monitoring and<br />
supports nuclear non-proliferation measures. Disclosures of other<br />
technical functions of the classified facilities would involve<br />
damage to both U. S. and Australian interests and cannot be<br />
justified. the maintenance of effective deterrence<br />
including-through early warning has as its purpose<br />
the avoidance of war between the nuclear powers. Such a war<br />
would inevitably affect all nations, including Australia, and<br />
its avoidance is essential for the security of the Australian<br />
people." And I would simply repeat here what I've said in the<br />
House, that it's very important to distinguish between these<br />
purposes which I have discussed and revealed in the House and<br />
the technical details of the functioning of the facilities<br />
which must necessarily remain classified. I make the point<br />
to you that this is the first time that an Australian Government<br />
has disclosed these facts. There has been reference to it in<br />
certain publications, but the fact that no Government has<br />
addressed itself to these issues has led to speculation about<br />
a range of other alleged purposes and functions of these bases. </p>
<p>P. M. cant: And we believe that it's appropriate that the<br />
Australian people should be informed. The other point I would<br />
make is that, as I said in the House, the statement that I have<br />
made has been done with the full co-operation and support<br />
of the United States administration. Now before you may<br />
wish to address any particular questions either to myself<br />
or to Bill, Bill you might like to make some observations.<br />
HAYDEN: This is an extremely important: statement. It's the<br />
first occasi -on on which officially there has been a declarat~ ion<br />
of the general functions for which the facilities have been<br />
established and in discharging which they operate. I'd like<br />
to draw your attention to one simple fact there is a vast<br />
difference between speculation, no matter how well-informed<br />
you may presume it to be, and an official statement. No<br />
official statement has been made of this nature before.<br />
It'declares that the facilities contribute to verification,<br />
arms control, deterrents, early warning functions. Verification<br />
and arms control fulfil obligations which we have morally and<br />
under-international arrangements, for instance under the SALT<br />
arrangements, are concerns under various nuclear weaponry<br />
regulatory mechanisms which have been set up through international<br />
forums. Deterrence is the only thing we have in place which<br />
operates as a break or an inhibitor on the arms race, the possibili<br />
of it breaking out into nuclear conflict. We would wish for<br />
better. We are working for better. But any alternative that's<br />
available at the moment is far worse. In respect of early<br />
warning we don't want to see a nuclear Pearl Harbour.. We<br />
have a moral responsibility in that respect. We freely<br />
acknowledge that tHese facilities in certain circumstances<br />
could be nuclear targe perhaps in certain circumstances<br />
some of them very high priority nuclear targets. But the fact<br />
is that we have a moral responsibility as well as a practical<br />
one to contribute to those functions I mentioned, and particularly<br />
deterrents, and the advantage we get from this is that when<br />
we talk on these matters, when we propose the calls for arms<br />
control and disarmament in particular with our full-time<br />
Ambassador for Disarmament, we do so recognised as a country<br />
with a direct stake in this matter, not as some country<br />
remote in the possible action should nuclear conflict take place.<br />
JOURNALIST: But what have you really told us today that's new?<br />
HAWKE: Well I thought I'd addressed myself to that and so<br />
had Bill. And that is that it's the first? time an Australian<br />
Government has definitively stated what are the functions and<br />
the roles of these bases. I've pointed out that there has<br />
been speculation, statements if you like, in certain<br />
publications. But none of these publications have the<br />
authority of a statement by the Government. And it is the<br />
fact,. as you'd be aware, that because there has been no<br />
definitive statement by the Government in the past, then there<br />
has been a range of speculation in the Australian community<br />
about the functions and suggestions that other functions<br />
are involved of an aggressive nature. Anid it is our belief </p>
<p>3<br />
P. M. cont.: that it was appropriate that the grounds for<br />
that speculation should be removed. And we point out that<br />
it is an indictment we believe of previous administrations,<br />
conservative administrations, that they; hadn't undertaken the<br />
task of discussions with our United States ally to enable<br />
this to be done. And I pay tribute to the United States<br />
adminstration that in the process of negotiation, which wasn't<br />
easy, it took time, that they understood the very sound reason<br />
that exists for avoiding ill-based speculation which cannot<br />
do anything to help public understanding of the importance,<br />
indeed we would put the necessity, of Australia hosting these<br />
joint facilities. There is after all a difference between<br />
speculation in a newspaper whatever authority the editors<br />
of that newspaper might wish to attach to their statements<br />
there is a difference between what they may like to allege<br />
and state and an official statement by the Government. There' s one<br />
other point if I could just make which I meant to make in my<br />
opening statement, and that is that it ought to be rememberEid<br />
that it was the Labor Party when it was last in office between<br />
' 72 and ' 75 that made these facilities effectively joint<br />
facilities by insisting on Australian personnel participating<br />
in the operation of those facilities.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke would you acknowledge that North. West<br />
Cape which you haven't mentioned now, although you did in<br />
the House, is more an aggressive facility than a defensive<br />
facility? No I wouldn't put it in that way. I think there are<br />
two points that ne~ fd to be made. It iq a key element in the<br />
complex communications system which involves communications<br />
with ships and submarides of the United States Navy and of<br />
the Royal Australian Navy. And I think it's a fact that<br />
is acknowledged by all experts that the SLBM, the submarine<br />
launch ballistic missile, carried by the submarines connected<br />
is not a first strike weapon in its nature. And we also<br />
believe that out of the negotiations that we've undertaken<br />
with the United States that we have now created a situation<br />
through the special access that we have with the United States<br />
Department of Defence and the enhanced status of the head<br />
of the Australian Defence staff in Washington, that we are<br />
able to be in a position to know what the possible relevance<br />
which could involve North West Cape in support of any United<br />
States military operations. And we're satisfied my Ministers<br />
who have negotiated this and -through. them, : myself * and the Government,<br />
that appropriate and necessary protection of Australian<br />
sovereignty in these matters has been enhanced.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister I was wondering if I could address<br />
a question both to yourself and to the Foreign Minister.<br />
Mr Peacock has said that today's statement is a sanctimonious;<br />
platitude with an absence of substance with a view to the<br />
July National Conference.<br />
Well I would have to concede that if one was looking<br />
for an authority on the expression of sanctimonious platitudes<br />
one couldn't go better than to the Leader of the Opposition. _/ 4 </p>
<p>P. M. cont: But of course, as with virtually everything he<br />
says in the Parliament these days that is a grotesque<br />
misrepresentation of the situation. Wie acknowledge, of course,<br />
I mean you would be foolish to try and deny that there is<br />
within our Party concern about this issue. And in that<br />
sense the Australian Labor Party refle! cts the total Australian<br />
community. And it's healthy that there should be this<br />
questioning about our position. Now we believe that we<br />
have the responsibility as a Government, and in a sense<br />
myself and Bill have a very particular responsibility in these<br />
areas, to try and create an information basis for our Party-and<br />
for the Australian community. So that people are able to<br />
come to conclusions on the basis of facts rather emotion and<br />
speculation. HAYDEN:..' Well I endorse entirely what Bob's said-and suggest ( what<br />
Peacock has said) is a lot of nonsense,--as the evidence will'show since we've<br />
been in Government we've been speaking in this area fairly<br />
regularly. In particular this statement has been in the<br />
pipeline for some months since we were in the United States<br />
last year and came out in its final refined form a couple<br />
of weeks ago. So it is part of an important obligation we<br />
had to discharge to the Labor. Party. The requirement of the<br />
policy is the general functions of the facilities be disclosedthat's<br />
been done. But above and beyond that I believe that<br />
the Labor Government, the Hawke Labor Government, has been<br />
instrumental in mobilising informed concern in the community<br />
on the issue of arms control and disarmament. And it's our<br />
intention to maintpn a flow of information to the community<br />
because we want t6 continue to-give leadership to the arms<br />
control disarmament mcAvement in this country. We want them<br />
to recognise that this Government is particularly active in<br />
this field, is dedicated, and has already in the short time<br />
we'ye been in Government shown some concrete progress in these<br />
areas at the international forums. I don't think Mr Peacock's<br />
statements can be taken seriously. He's suggested that<br />
exclusively we were concerned about the forthcoming Conference.<br />
Of course we wish to speak to people who are going to be involved<br />
in that Conference. But does anyone suggest that the fairly<br />
wide range of people from both the social and the natural<br />
sciences, the academics from-various other fields, the writers,<br />
the intellectuals in this community and people from very a broad<br />
range of average occupations in this community expressing<br />
concern about this issue don't deserve to. be communicated with,<br />
don't have a justifiable concern. our job is to explain what<br />
we're about, what deterrence is and why it's necessary for u~ s<br />
to fulfil that role if we're going to genuinely try to be<br />
influential in the issue of arms control and disarmament<br />
internationally.<br />
JOURNALIST: You referred in-your speech and Mr Hayden has also<br />
referred to it the presence of the bases here do make an<br />
added risk to nuclear attack. Do you believe there is widespread<br />
community acceptance of that reality? </p>
<p>There are at least-two things-I'd like to say on that.<br />
Both I and Bill consistently since we've been in Government,<br />
and indeed Bill in discharging his responsibilities as LeadE~ r<br />
of the Opposition before we camne to Government, did not<br />
attempt, has never attempted to hide that there is a balance<br />
of judgement which we have to make in these things. It would<br />
be futile, dishonest, not to acknowledge the risk that is<br />
involved in us'hosting these joint facilities. But the<br />
judgement that we make, and we have no doubt whatsoever about.<br />
the correctness of that judgement, is that on balance this<br />
is something significantly to the advantage of the people not<br />
only of this country but the rest of the world. Because as<br />
I have disclosed in this statement these facilities play a<br />
vital role in the question of stable deterrents, particularly<br />
through-the early warning functions that I've referred to, And<br />
that of course is leaving aside the role that they play in<br />
helping to make effective agreements between the superpowers<br />
in respect of nuclear testing and so on. But essentially in<br />
regard to the question of nuclear war we believe that the<br />
existence of these joint facilities and the discharge of their<br />
functions make more likely the continuation of a non-nuclear<br />
war situation. And therefore the intere! sts Of the people of<br />
Australia and of the rest of the world, we believe, demand<br />
continuation of these functions. The second point I would<br />
make is that on the evidence that's available from polling<br />
in this matter, it is clear that majority of the Australian<br />
people support the position of the Australian Government.<br />
JOURNALIST: Should the Australian people, Prime Minister,<br />
be disturbed about thos?, operations which you described as<br />
classified? What we have done is to make a clear statement of what<br />
the functions are. And let me make it clear that that is an<br />
exhaustive statement of functions. There are no other functions<br />
or roles than those which I have outlined. But necessarily,<br />
of course, we can't go to technical details. It would be<br />
manifestly against the interests of both ourselves and of the<br />
United States to do that. But I repeat the statement of functions<br />
that I've made to the Parliament is an exhaustive statement<br />
of the functions.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke the issue of technical functions of the<br />
bases. You said you can't say anything further because of<br />
the damage to both the U. S. and Australia. Isn't it true that:<br />
a lot of technical information is made available to the American<br />
Congress by the American administration about technical funct:. ons<br />
and why was it not possible for you to reveal some of that<br />
information in your statement.<br />
What happens in the United States, according to their proce! sses,<br />
is a matter for the United States and as far as we are concerned<br />
these are joint facilities and for us to be able to make a statement<br />
of assistance to understanding by the Australian people requires<br />
by definition agreement with the United States. The processes of<br />
securing this mutual position has been a lengthy one which has<br />
involved Bill and Gordon Scholes and then finally, myself. And<br />
this is the position of agreement that we've been able to reach.<br />
And we believe that it's been useful and will continue to be<br />
useful for the people to have that information. It is not<br />
possible to say more than that. Let me emphasise the important </p>
<p>P. M. cant.: in understanding which I think is the statement. that<br />
I made that there has been an exhaustive statement of functions.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr. Hawke, does the US Government seek the<br />
Australian Government's permission before making these<br />
statements about it, given that you had to get the US<br />
Government's permission to make this statement?<br />
PM: The United States Government doesn't talk to us about<br />
wh; a t happens in the United States Congress.<br />
JOURNALIST: -Prime Minister, will the newly established<br />
Parliamentary sub-committee on disarmament and arms control<br />
have access to this technical information?<br />
PM: No, I would not believe it would.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hayden?<br />
HAYDEN: I think the important thing is that this is a j6int<br />
Australian United States statement and it came out of<br />
consultation between both of us and it represents as much as<br />
can be disclosed without going beyond that which has been<br />
disclosed in the United States including the Congress. I am<br />
aware of some of the technical data which has been disclosed<br />
in the Congress which is available in the annual defence<br />
report presented by the Secretary of State for Defence, but<br />
nowhere there can I recall seeing any specification about<br />
Nurrungar or Pine Gap and I think that is important to recall.<br />
There are general statements and conclusions are sometimes<br />
drawn from them rigJ~ tly or wrongly, wisely or unwisely.<br />
That is a vastly differ nt matter. Specific terms on which<br />
we have been dealingg -e have jointly recognised that is<br />
Australia and America -we go beyond what has been provided<br />
here about the general function of the base would be to<br />
go beyond what is provided generally in the United States.<br />
JOURNALIST: Won't the very suspicions remain the very<br />
suspicions you are trying to overcome?<br />
PM: I don't believe so. There may be by some people who<br />
have got a particular barrow or prejudice to push and we<br />
are not in the business of trying to stop the pushing of<br />
prejudices or ideologies, but all I can say as Prime Minister<br />
is supported fully by the Foreign Minister and the Government<br />
is that we have made, I repeat, an exhaustive statement of<br />
the functions of those joint facilities and that statement,<br />
we are confident, will lead the great majority of the<br />
Australian people to make the judgement that this Government<br />
makes, and that is that obviously on balance the hosting of<br />
those joint facilities is in the interests of the Australian<br />
people. </p>
<p>HAYDEN4: The statement is designed to satisfy as many peoples'<br />
concerns as we can possibly do and responsibly do. I am<br />
satisfied that it will satisfy in turn a vast majority of<br />
Australians. We can't satisfy everyone. Some people wouldn't<br />
be satisfied until we remove the facilities from this country.<br />
We have made it clear that that is an area of disagreement<br />
that we have with those people. We have a moral, practical<br />
obligation to support those facilities.<br />
JOURNALIST: It satisfies your doubts that you expressed<br />
three years ago?<br />
PM: I have gone through some moral concern about these<br />
matters and great heartburning over the past couple of years<br />
and more particularly since I have been Foreign Minister.<br />
I have come to the conclusion that this is the most<br />
practical and responsible position that we can take to<br />
continue to host those facilities. I believe that deterrants<br />
are the only effective things in place. It is not pleasant,<br />
but the alternatives are far worse. It allows us to work<br />
credibly and influentially towards the things that we want<br />
to work towards achieving.<br />
JOURNALIST: was only 7 lines that has taken 10 months<br />
to produce, what was the reason for the delay there?<br />
PM: Well, the matter was, as you imply in your statement,<br />
fTrst raised with tie United States administration some<br />
considerable period ago and I came into those negotiations<br />
fairly late in the pea ti at the very high levels of the<br />
Un ited States administration. And the reason for the delay<br />
was the concern of the United States that they were not only<br />
talking about a situation and relationship with Australia.<br />
They have relations with other countries and they were<br />
concerned to be sure that the form of the statement made in<br />
respect of Australia was not something that created difficulties<br />
for them in other areas and we understood their concern. Anti<br />
let me say they understood our reasons for wanting to let the<br />
Australian people know and the discussions being of that<br />
nature were fairly long. There were important considerations<br />
that had to be taken into account. We at all times, I.<br />
believe, were faced with a basically co-operative attitude<br />
from the United States, but understandably-they wanted to make<br />
sure that their interests, not only here, but elsewhere were<br />
fully taken into account.<br />
JOURNALIST: Were the differences between the Pentagon<br />
upper echelons of the Pentagon and the US State Department<br />
PM: I'm not going to go into the question of the internal<br />
operations of the United States administration.<br />
Your saying it really relates to the statement, are you. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: It's not unrelated.<br />
PM: The great double negative.<br />
JOURNALIST: It's on French nuclear testing. As I<br />
understand, Mr. Hayden, you asked the office of National<br />
Assessments to undertake geological surveys ( tape ends)<br />
Firstly, have you got any results on that and secondly,<br />
there is a notion kicking around in similar circles that the<br />
French really ought to undertake any underground testing that<br />
they have to in Nevada. Would you put that as a credible<br />
alternative?<br />
HAYDEN: I read in one of the newspapers that I had asked<br />
the Office of National Assessment to carry out this sort<br />
of assessment and I'm not sure how that: got wrong because<br />
I understood another might have lodged that request, but I<br />
spoke to him and he said he hadn't, but: he thought I had.<br />
All I can say is I haven't. And it gets rather complex and<br />
curiouser and curiouser but it is probably not a bad idea and<br />
I might give the idea in the very near future. For the<br />
French to conduct their tests in Nevada I didn't have to<br />
raise that with the French they spontaneously declared they<br />
would never be like Britain beholden to the Americans having<br />
their tests carried out in Nevada. It is one of the areas<br />
of arguments that we have had that the tests should take<br />
place somewhere else like metropolitan France.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr. Haywke, you said you have given an exhaustive<br />
list of the functibns of the bases. one of the senior<br />
officials of the Defernte Department, Mr. Rod Thomas, told a<br />
Parliamentary Committee about two weeks ago that submarines<br />
using North West Cape had counter force capabilities which<br />
he acknowledged some analyses said was a first strike<br />
capability. Do you disagree with those statements of the<br />
Defence Department?<br />
PM: I have quite clearly made my statement in the Parliament<br />
and here on that issue.<br />
HAYDEN: Can. I answer that. Look, I saw that statement. I<br />
disagree with it entirely. One must recognise that modifications<br />
and improvements in nuclear weaponry may well establish a<br />
counter force capability on the part of Americans with the r~ ew<br />
Trident submarine missile, for instance. I would be rather<br />
dishonest if I didn't acknowledge that. I declared that much<br />
as far back as about 4-5 years ago as Leader of the Opposition,<br />
but that is something in the future and that is something<br />
we have got attend to. And we attend to that sort of matter<br />
with credibility because of our position, our direct stake<br />
in these matters as I mentioned earlier. I think the area cf<br />
far greater concern was the potential for the whole framework<br />
of stable deterrents to come very much unstuck as a result.<br />
Competition that is about to break out in outer space is not<br />
Just a matter of putting weapons together, but new technology,<br />
laser beams, particle beams which can be transmitted from<br />
earth to a reflector, amplifier stations in satellites in outer<br />
space and then directed back to earth in a way that fulfills<br />
the role of anti-ballistic missiles extraordinarily </p>
<p>* de-stabilising. That is why we are particularly active in<br />
this area which, I think, probably even comes ahead of<br />
concern about the D-5 or Trident missiles because if you<br />
nip that in the bud, we have nipped in the bud something<br />
that presents awesome worries for us in the near future.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr. Hawke, would your Government contemplate the<br />
establishment of any other United States facilities on<br />
Australia soil of a similar kind?<br />
PM: Well, that issue is not before us. Let me say this. I<br />
Tikin my statement today I have made quite clear on behalf<br />
of the Government why we host those facilities because of<br />
the functions that those facilities what objectives, I think,<br />
are satisfied by the discharge of those facilities. Now, one<br />
has to be entirely speculative. If it were put to us that<br />
given the development of capacities in the technological serise<br />
that may require another facility, which facility could serve<br />
the same objectives then that is something we would have to<br />
take into account.<br />
JOURNALIST: And you are totally satisfied that you know all<br />
of the functions of the bases at present in Australia?<br />
PM: Yes, and I repeat that within the policy under which we<br />
have operated and the concepts that we have, what I have just<br />
said to you would be entirely consistent with that. But we<br />
would not change the conceptual framework that we have got.<br />
In other words we woild not be hosting aggressive facilities,<br />
but only facilities ' which would serve the basic purposes which<br />
we believe are in the inferests of the Australian people.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, does all this information flow<br />
through the Australian Government or does it any of it go only<br />
to the Americans?<br />
PM: In respect of the matters that I have talked about, then<br />
we are in a position where we have access to all the information<br />
which is relevant to those objectives.<br />
HAYDEN: We have small managers. We have co-managers. We have!<br />
people working on the floor on all shifts at those facilities<br />
at Nurrungar and Pine Gap. I can't tell you any more than that.<br />
You recall Lionel Bowen and I went to those ' facilities, I think<br />
in 1979 had quite an extensive assessment of them and I cam<br />
away satisfied that we were aware of what was taking place and<br />
had full access.<br />
PM: I haven't seen inside them. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Do you also disagree with the Defence Department<br />
view put to Cabinet a couple of months that an American<br />
could use North West Cape base without necessarily asking for<br />
specific Australian agreement?<br />
PM: We believe that given the new arrangements that have been<br />
negotiated under this Government that AuStralian sovereignty<br />
is fully protected in regard to any possible use of that<br />
facility in United States military operatiaons.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr. Hawke, was there anything that the Australian.-<br />
Government wanted to include in this statement that the US<br />
Government ruled out?<br />
PM: There was a process of negotiation. I think it is accurate<br />
to say that there was some slight differEnce from first drafts,<br />
but that always happens in any negotiations, whether it is at a<br />
level between governments or at other levels. All I can say i~ s<br />
this that at the end result, we are satisfied with the statement<br />
and so is the United States Government.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr. Hawke, are you satisfied that some Australian<br />
service personnel are denied access to some sections of the bases?<br />
PM: Well, all I can say is that I haven't had the opportunity<br />
that Bill has had and Lionel to visit them. I have listened t~ o<br />
their reports on this matter and I have certainly had reports<br />
made to me since I have been Prime Minister and I am satisfied<br />
as I put that the sov ereign interests of Australia are<br />
protected in the way thebases operate.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr. Hawke, you say that Pine Gap and Nurrungar axe<br />
not military bases, isn't that a fairly narrow interpretation?<br />
PM: Well, it is a question for you to say whether it is narrow<br />
or not. I explicity spelled out in my statement to the<br />
Parliament what I meant and I think that is quite clear.<br />
JOURNALIST: Previous Prime Ministers and Government spokesmen<br />
have referred to them as not being part of weapons systems.<br />
Would you exclude that possibility as far as<br />
PM: I have made it clear that they are not properly so<br />
described. I said that in the statement.<br />
JOURNALIST: Can we assume from what you said today that when<br />
the North West Cape agreement comes up for renewal, it will be<br />
renewed? PM: Well, we have gone through the process of negotiation since<br />
we have been in Government we have and my I remind you that<br />
when Labor was in before the negotiation between Mr. Barnard and<br />
I think it was Mr Schlesinger wasn't it as a result of those<br />
re-negotiations Australian sovereignty was better protected and<br />
since we have been in office again this Labor Government we<br />
have had further discussions and we believe have : enhanced the </p>
<p>1 i.<br />
facility of our people in Washington to be better involved.<br />
We are satisfied with results of those negotiations. I have<br />
no reason to believe that the issue arises for further renegotiation<br />
that we would not renew the facility. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
