<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>15534</transcript-id>
    <title>APEC Economic Leaders Meeting - Climate Change</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>31/03/2007</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I have written to the leaders of APEC's other 20 economies inviting them to this year's APEC Economic Leaders Meeting and outlining my intention to make clean development and climate change a key topic for discussion in Sydney.</p>
<p>The economies of APEC already account for 60 per cent of global energy demand and include the world's four largest energy consumers. Energy demand across APEC is projected to double by 2030 (based on 2002 levels).<br />
 Last year in Hanoi leaders instructed ministers to report in Sydney on ways APEC might respond to the challenge of meeting rapidly growing energy demands while minimising environmental effects. We now need to give practical effect to that instruction.</p>
<p>Already many APEC economies are engaged in a range of joint initiatives in areas such as clean coal technology, renewable energy and energy efficiency aimed at practical outcomes on climate change. This also includes the Global Initiative on Forests and Climate I announced on 29 March.</p>
<p>We now have an opportunity to build on this cooperation and ensure that broader Asia-Pacific perspectives on climate change and the role of our economies are given full voice in shaping the relevant international frameworks into the future.</p>
<p>Australia's economic destiny is very much in the Asia-Pacific region, and it makes sense that our response to climate change is geared to regional interests and perspectives.  This is the approach we have taken with the AP6 initiative, and it is strongly in our interests to strengthen dialogue on energy and climate change in APEC.</p>
<p>Australia is demonstrating strong leadership by putting the issue at the centre of one of the major leaders' summits of the year and is committed to developing a strong regional response to this pressing international challenge.</p>
<p>APEC Energy Facts</p>
<p>Primary energy consumption growth to 2030:   2% per year  Primary energy production growth to 2030:   1.5% per year</p>
<p>By 2030 APEC will move from a net exporter of gas and coal to a net importer.  By 2030 oil imports will account for 52 per cent of oil demand.</p>
<p>Electricity demand to double from 8,109 TWh in 2002 to 19,163 TWh in 2030.  APEC Total investment requirement for the energy sector over the outlook period between US$5.95 Trillion and US$7.55 Trillion.</p>
<p>(Source: APEC Energy Demand and Supply Outlook 2006: Energy at the crossroads, Asia Pacific Energy Research Centre 2006 (APERC))</p>
<p>31 March 2007</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
