<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2725</transcript-id>
    <title>ROAD SAFETY - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT HON WILLIAM MCMAHON CH MP</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/11/1972</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002725.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS: ROAD SAFETY<br />
Statement by the Prime i'inister, the Rt Hon.<br />
William M~ cMahon,_ C. H., M. P.<br />
The Commonwealth Government iA determined to save<br />
lives on the Australian roads.<br />
It is not enough to feel sympathy for those involved<br />
in motor accidents. We must work vigorously with the States to<br />
ensure that every possible means of reducing this toll are<br />
fully exploited. Few poople have not been touched in one way or anothor<br />
by a road tragedy. Road accidcnts rank fourth among the major<br />
causes of death in Australia and arc the<br />
major cause of death for young men under<br />
the age of 25 ycars.<br />
The road toll last yoar, when more than 3,500<br />
were killed and more than 90,000 were injured<br />
can only be described as a national tragedy.<br />
In addition to this huma. n suffering, there is<br />
the staggering ccornomic cost to the community<br />
which could be morn than $ 5 million<br />
annually.<br />
In order to find out what morc the Commonwealth could<br />
do, we appointed an expert group to undertake a detailed and<br />
scientific review of the road accident situation in Australia.<br />
We roceived the report of the expert group last month<br />
and I have alrcady announced our decision to accept the group's<br />
major recommendations for action on the part of the Commonwealth.<br />
A high level specialist National Office of Road Safety<br />
will be created within the Department of Shipping and Transport<br />
to co-ordinate and support State and Territory efforts in road<br />
safety. It will become a focal point of national efforts to<br />
promote road safsty. </p>
<p>2<br />
We also propose to assist the States in removing<br />
danger spots that menace the drivers on our roads. We will<br />
provide immediately $ 5 million a year to the States to double<br />
their present expenditure in this regard and will undertake<br />
with the States a survey of locations with poor accident records<br />
to see what more needs to be done to make our roads safer.<br />
The task of reducing the road toll is not a simple one.<br />
It will not be solved by subjective thinking or strong support<br />
of personal attitudes. It will demand objective analysis of the<br />
problems involved and a high degree of coroperation between the<br />
many authorities concerned. We have shown that we are prepared<br />
to do our part at the national level.<br />
CANBERRA, 27 November 1972<br />
L </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
