<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5743</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS TO THE NATION FOR AUSTRALIA DAY</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/02/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005743.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGOED UNTIL BROADCASTI<br />
FOR MEDIA MONDAY, 1 FEBRUARY 1982<br />
ADDRESS -TO THE NATION -FOR AUJSTRALIA DAY<br />
Australia is now a country of fifteen million people. Our<br />
population has doubled since the Second World War. It is.<br />
timely to review some of our achievements over those years, and'-<br />
on that basis to look ahead to the kind of Australia we want<br />
to build for our children.<br />
Since the 1940' s not only has our population doubled, material<br />
living standards have also doubled, there has been enormous<br />
development of Australia's resources and productive capacities,<br />
family homes were vastly different in 1945 from what we take<br />
for granted in the average home today; and our horizons as<br />
a nation have been transformed and uplifted. The Australian<br />
way of life has been enriched by people from almost every country,<br />
educational opportunities have widened, cultural and artistic<br />
activities have expanded, our comparative isolation from the<br />
restof the world has been reduced by better communications,<br />
and we have become more independent and outward looking as<br />
well as vastly more self-confident as a nation.<br />
There is a growing pride in Australia and things Australian,<br />
and I am confident that any tendency to knock Australia is<br />
fast becoming a thing of the past. Australia is known around<br />
the world as a country which is stable but at the samne time<br />
exciting, and people in many other countries now look to us<br />
for inspiration and hope. There are famous Australians in<br />
almost every field of human achievement, in sport and science,<br />
in business and the arts. But it is important for us to<br />
remember that the Australia that we know and love has been<br />
essentially built by millions of average Australians.<br />
It is their work and efforts, their values, their belief in<br />
fair play, their commitment to the advancement of this country,<br />
that have made Australia what it is. We have the opportunity<br />
to keep building on their achievements, and as an open<br />
society of fifteen million people, we have many high hopes<br />
for the years ahead. Continuing economic growth is obviously<br />
essential for many of these hopes to be realised. But I<br />
believe that over and above that, we have all enjoyed the<br />
feeling of being part of a more vibrant society in recent<br />
years, and many of the traditional values of the Australian<br />
way of life have been strengthened in the pro . cess. / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
We are lucky to possess the freedom and living standards which<br />
we often take for granted, and we are also.-i4lucky that there are<br />
grounds for optimism about the future.<br />
There are obviously challenges we need to face up to if we are<br />
to take advantage of our opportunities. There is no doubt that<br />
unreasonableness and selfishness, whether in the form of<br />
needless strikes or tax avoidance or whatever, can damage<br />
us all. In addition, some of the problems of other countries<br />
are certain to have an impact upon Australia's prospects,<br />
especially in the short term, no matter how carefully we try<br />
to insulate ourselves from them, because we live in. an<br />
. interdependent world.<br />
But. while the challenges are obvious and real, Australia has<br />
enormous advantages as we look ahead. We have many resources,<br />
especially energy resources, which the world wants and needs.<br />
Our economy has great underlying strength, and the skills7<br />
of our workforce are being progressively improved and<br />
upgraded. Geographically, we are situated in one of the<br />
fastest growing corners of the world, with the Pacific and<br />
South East Asia on our doorstep.<br />
Our potential is great, but we must remember that success is<br />
not autcnatic, that our objectives will not be met by chance.<br />
The world does not owe us a living, and while a population of<br />
fifteen million may seem large for Australia, it is in fact<br />
less tha-n half of one percent of the world's population. We<br />
have the capacity and-the basis to go ahead, and continue to<br />
grow. : ut if we are to achieve our common objectives, we<br />
must cs-oerate and work together, we must accept the<br />
responsibilities and obligations which we have to each other,<br />
we must strive for the best, we must do everything within our<br />
power to give people the opportunities and the security which<br />
they need.<br />
I have already spoken of the positive attitude towards<br />
Australia and things Australian which is becoming more<br />
prominent in our community. If this attitude can be extended,<br />
so that people become committed to the well-being of the whole<br />
community as well as themselves, then we will all benefit<br />
and Australia will advance. As a result, we will build awell-<br />
adjusted and more prosperous Australia for our children<br />
and this is after all, one of the greatest objectives which<br />
binds us together. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
