<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>972</transcript-id>
    <title>PRESENTATION OF HOOVER AWARDS FOR MARKETING AT HOTEL REX - CANBERRA, CANBERRA  10TH AUGUST, 1964  SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON . SIR ROBERT MENZIES SIR</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/08/1964</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000972_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESENTATION OF HOOVER AdIARDS FOR MAKTING<br />
A~ T OTEL hiX-AT-CANBERRA4 CANBERRA<br />
Speech bU the Prm Mln-trh Rjt. Hion, SirRoberU enis<br />
Sir, I begin all my speeches by a couple of preliminary<br />
remarks. One is that when I was invited to come to this<br />
enterprise, I burst into loud moans and said, " Oh, no. Look<br />
I have to prepare about eight or ten speeches over that period,"<br />
and then somebody said to me, " vK6,1l, of course, Professor<br />
Baxter has invited you" and, do you know I must confess, I am<br />
a little frightened of this chap. ( Laughter) In adidition to<br />
being frightened of him, I have a very great respect for him,<br />
and so I said, in that grudging voice with which my staff is<br />
familiar ( Laughter) " All right, well, if Baxter wants me to<br />
go1 I suppose I must*" You know, with falling infloxion,<br />
An~ then I said, " Well, what dope have you? You know, " dope"<br />
is the professional term. ( Laughter) And I was given a certain<br />
amount of " dope" and then T found that my distinguished<br />
colleague, Mr. McEwen had written or spoken I've forgotten<br />
which something on Lhis matter. That wretclied fellow,<br />
" Iesterman, will know. ( Laughter)<br />
This afternoon in the Cabinet, well, we were discussing<br />
other prcblems not without difficulty and at about<br />
twenty to six John McEwen said to me, ' Y9ould you mind very much<br />
if I didn't turn out to be there tonight?" ( He had a very good<br />
reason for nct coming) and I said, " My dear boy, I will be<br />
delighted if you don't come because I have read your statement<br />
and I. propose to cannibalise it in what I have to say tonight."<br />
( Laughter) So with apologies from John MzEwen, I am delighted<br />
that he is no~ t here because at any given moment he might have<br />
looked up and said, " No, no, no. You've misunderstood me.<br />
( Laughter) Anyhow, I was then given a handsome book, a splendid<br />
book, which contained all sorts of things in it, and I read a<br />
passage which I will take leave to read to you. It said this:<br />
" The Hoover Award for Marketing expresses the<br />
conviction of the Hoover Organisation that progress<br />
in marketing, comparable to that in production<br />
techniques and organisation, is vital to the development<br />
of the Australian as of all free economies."<br />
( Up to that time, I was right, I agreed, which I seldom do)<br />
" Progressive improvement in the standards of living<br />
is dependent on greater efficiency in all marketing<br />
functions, both within Australia and overseas." 1<br />
Now, Sir, I am not always profoundly moved by what I read in a<br />
book, but I was profoundly moved by that because I thought,<br />
" Now that's it. This is true," because you know Sir, we<br />
donlt always realise do we, that in our own lifehimes and<br />
most of yours are a little shorter than mine there has been<br />
a revolutionary increase in the complexity of government and<br />
in the complexity of economic affairs, 9 ea 9 / 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
Now, I have very little reason to have any vanity<br />
about myself except that the people in a sort of occulting<br />
fashion have supported me for a long time, but I can remember<br />
what nobody else here can remember, namely, what it was like<br />
to be the head of' the Government in 1939 that's twentyfive<br />
years ago and to remember the kind of problem that came on to<br />
the table at that time. I very well remember, in my vanity, in<br />
1939 saying, " Well, V11l be Treasurer and I'm going to make a<br />
Budget speech without writing it in advance." You know, this<br />
was a mere exercise in vanity and of course I had my reward<br />
because no newspaper ever published it. ( Laughter) But one<br />
thing I do recall and it is wrorthwzhile recall~ ing it to your<br />
own minds and that is that there it was in 1939 not all that<br />
long time ago and I -as Prime Minister and Treasurer produced<br />
to the Commonwealth Parliament the first Commonwealth Budget of<br />
a œ C10014. Now, of' course, for you juveniles here tonight, this<br />
gives you the horse laughi, doesn't it: The first Commonwealth<br />
Budget of œ 1001. I recalled that in Gladstone's last Budget in<br />
England, he produced the first fœ 100M Budget in Great Britain.<br />
Well, of course, things have happened since then. I don~' t want<br />
to anticipate what my colleague, the Treasurer, will say tomcrrow<br />
afternioon, but let us say, in a very loose way that tomorrow<br />
night it will be about œ C2,500M. I rememaber that because I remember<br />
that the economic problems were less complicated; that we had,<br />
to use the modern jatrgon, a rather less sophisticated economy.<br />
Yt, you know Sir, in sp te u f all this vast experience-we do<br />
thn, don't we every now and then of our problems as if' they<br />
were problems ol A or B or C, problems in separation, problems<br />
of' one bit at a time, instead of realising that they are problems<br />
of an entire character in which the whole pattern of tha3 economy<br />
and of life must be considered.<br />
Now, Sj. r, all I can say about that is there have been<br />
developments in the modern world. In my earliest days in<br />
Parliament. and as a Prime Minister, everything was simple;<br />
you know, simple but difficult, but simple in a sense, and ever<br />
since then in our own country we have come a cross the complexity<br />
of life, the complexity of the economy, the complexity of national<br />
life, the necessity of reconciling the development of' our country<br />
with the stability of' our country, with all sorts of other matters<br />
involving interiiational relations. All this is perfectly true.<br />
Now, it was said and very interestingly I think<br />
by the famous author of' " The Affluent Society" that the world<br />
had been devoting itself' to production and that he doubted whether<br />
production was the main problem. W4ell, he may have had something<br />
to be said for him. M1ost of us who have been concerned with these<br />
affairs have for year after year wanted to develop production and<br />
productivity. Why? Because we have known that all the talk in<br />
the world about rising standards of living doesn't mean much<br />
unless you have rising standards of' production, that you must<br />
develop what is available to the people, develop it and develop<br />
it and develop it before you can give way to eager ideas on the<br />
distribution of what is produced and so, very properly I think, we<br />
have had our minds fixed on productivit-y, on production.<br />
Then, in the last few years perhaps, we have found our<br />
minds directed to how you encourage production, how you make<br />
production effective and this has brought us tho great problem<br />
of marketing, of salesmanship, because after all, you may produce<br />
all the things in the world but unless people want to buy them,<br />
unless people get them and use them and live with them, there is<br />
eo a */ 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
no real increase in the standard of living of the people. Now<br />
this is quite true, Somebody, in an idle moment some years<br />
back, made me a Fellow of the Royal Society of Arts, I hope<br />
you gentlemen will treat me with proper respect when you know<br />
that. The Royal Society of Arts produces from time to time a<br />
Journal containing their proceedings, the reports of what goes<br />
on and in the last number that I received and in one of my<br />
multiple hours of leisure at the weekend, I read this. It<br />
produced a number which was devoted to advertising. Now, of<br />
course, there are gentlemen here who know more about this than<br />
I do. I am always a little alleigic to advertising unless I've<br />
settled the photograph ( Laughter, but on this occasion, Mr.<br />
John Hobson, speaking on the social and economic context of<br />
advertising said, among other things, two very interesting<br />
things. Some of you may know him or know of him.<br />
First of all, he said increased production presupposes<br />
increased consumption but increased consumption can't be achieved<br />
merely by making an increase of goods available. This is<br />
something you will all understand. It can only be achieved by<br />
making the products wanted. This raises the question of<br />
salesmanship which cn a mass scale is what advertising is.<br />
Now, with very great respect to Mr. John Hobsoq I think that<br />
was a profoundly wise remark and it posed a problem which the<br />
author of " The Affluent Society" had not really coped with,<br />
Then later on he went on to say: " The economic phencmencn of<br />
abundance at1 mass level has a natural com~ plement in what<br />
historians will, I think, recognise as one of the social<br />
phanomena of the century -the rise in importance of salesmanship.<br />
In the eyes of a limited intellectual and upper-class minority" t<br />
( such as I am addressing ( Laughter) here tonight), he said<br />
" salesmanship is not quite respectable. In the eyes of the great<br />
majority of the public, it presents vary little problem. On<br />
the whole, o know, people enjoy being sold. things." Now<br />
that, I thought, was pretty wise.<br />
But this brings me, doesn't it to the problem<br />
producti. on productivity, the development of our resources<br />
all these things which are vital to the future of the country<br />
and yet they could all be defeated unless what we produced we<br />
could sell, unless what Australia can grow tind produce Australia<br />
can sell. Therefore salesmanship has become, if it wasnt<br />
always one of the great tasks, one of the great techniques in<br />
the modern economy.<br />
Now, of course, I am so old that I can remember Major<br />
Douglas and I met him once and I thought he was very amusing.<br />
He had a simple theory. He said that if you are to sell all the<br />
things you produce, then all you have to do is to produce money.<br />
Well, we've produced money, Heaven only knows. Here we are<br />
living in a country in which the state of the liquidity is almost<br />
without precedent, in which the people of Australia, man, woman<br />
and child, have hundreds of pounds in savings bank accounts.<br />
But how do you marry these two things? How do you marry enormous<br />
productivity, all the good foi-tune that we have had, good<br />
harvests, good seasons, great overseas markets how do you<br />
marry these things with the people who have the money to spend<br />
and perhaps are not so much disposed to spend it. Now here,<br />
gontlemen, is where you come into this picture, because I believe<br />
that just as we have attacked and not without success, the<br />
problems of productivity just as we have encouraged productivity,<br />
just as my own Government Heaven help it has devised ways and<br />
means of increasing productivity, we must develop ways and<br />
means of getting bigger and better, more enduring, more expanding<br />
ma rke ts. eee<br />
I </p>
<p>4-<br />
Now I know, Sir, that there is a great disposition<br />
in some parts of the country to raise an eyebrow which few<br />
people can do as well as I can I'm told ( Laughter) to raise<br />
an eyebrow about the civil servant, about the bureaucrats, about<br />
this Department or that. I want to tell you, and 1 reserve all<br />
my rights to have a first-class argument with any Department,<br />
but I just want to tell you, reserving that right, that if<br />
somebody objectively sits down to write the history of the last<br />
ten years, he will find most remarkable events because he will<br />
find that this country, through its Government, through its<br />
Departments, has set out to win m-qrkets, to instruct markets<br />
to have trade comissioners, to have trade m-Issions, to do all<br />
these things which are designed to marry our own rare capacity<br />
for production with the eager demand, much to be encouraged, of<br />
people in the other countries of the world. This is quite true.<br />
This is, I think, of tremendous importance.<br />
The more we produce, the more we must sell. The<br />
more we need to sell, the more we need to have people. who are<br />
experts in selling. We must get over this silly idea that a<br />
salesman is a rather dv. bious character. We must get ovEr this<br />
idea that advertising is, in a sense a curiously dishonest<br />
exercise, because the truth is that If we are going to bchireve<br />
what we want to achieve in Australia then we must produce anci<br />
we must sell. We may produce by cajoling people. -Je may produce<br />
by having, what I've become familiar with now, some stabilization<br />
scheme Westerman knows all about this. Vie may do that, at that<br />
end. At the other end we must have people who will sell what we<br />
produice. And one of our dangers is that the producer may say,<br />
" Well, Itve produced this. Itts up to somebody else to sell"<br />
and that the seller may 11say, " W4ell, I don't know, there is a<br />
limit to what I can do." The truth is the sulvency of this<br />
company in the long run depends not only on production and I<br />
give that a high plac; e in my world but on solesmanshil). This<br />
is why tonight is so important.<br />
It's a very curious thing, I think, that we should<br />
fall into doubts and difficulties about these matters. I don't<br />
know why we should. The truth is that we are all and don't<br />
forget this members one of another. The old idea that I grew<br />
up with when I was a boy in the bush that you were either a<br />
primary industry man or you were a secondary industry man; you<br />
were either a free trader or a protectionist all these lovely,<br />
simple, simple rules these simple dichotomies are always so<br />
false. I grew up wiLh them when I was a boy. Whatever success<br />
I have had in life is due to the fact that before I was much<br />
older I regarded them with utter contempt because in reality we<br />
are ail members one of another. You can have the greatest<br />
productive genius applied to what goes on in Australia and unless<br />
it is married to the greatest salesmanship on behalf of Australia,<br />
we will be no better off and indeed much worse off than when we<br />
started. Therefore, let us get to understand that we are all<br />
members one of another, that nobody can really succeed in<br />
Australia if the other man9 in a big way, fails. We must work<br />
together. Therefore, Professor 3) xter, you who sit in the middle<br />
of all this and occasionally give me my orders, now much more<br />
audible that my old colleague, Sir William Spooner, has come<br />
from under your grasp ( Laughter) therefore, Sir, I want to<br />
say that I in reality came here, believing as I do most a. a </p>
<p>faithfully that the art of selling, the business of selling,<br />
the Trade Commissioner service, the Trade Mission, the<br />
advertising of our own products has, in this day, become<br />
the most important complement of all to the drive for<br />
production in our own country.<br />
Therefore, Sir, I can say to you as I would say<br />
if I were addressing the Primary Producers? Uniob., who<br />
would regard me with modified rapture ( Laughter) and I can<br />
say to you Sirg as I would say to them because I believe<br />
profoundly in what they are doing, tha this is a splendid<br />
occasion on which to recall that there is a balance in life,<br />
a balance in our own economic de-velopment. a balancing of<br />
factors in our o m growth which. we must always remember, and<br />
as you represent one aide of that balancel then Sir I want<br />
to say, thank you very much. I will be delighted to hand<br />
out a prize and, of course, as a pol. itician, no less delighted<br />
because tthe Hoover organization, I gather, is finding it.<br />
and I'm not,.<br />
I ' d 0 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
