<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9512</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ KEATING MP HIGH COURT DECISION ON THE CHALLANGE TO THE NATIVE TITLE ACT</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/03/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009512.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL: 16. Mar. 95 14: 4 No. 013 F. 01/ 03<br />
F PRIME MINISTER I'<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ KEATING MP<br />
HIGH COURT DECISION ON THE CHALLENGE TO THE NATIVE TITLE ACT<br />
The High Court has upheld the validity and legitimacy of the Native Title Act,<br />
one of the most far reaching pieces of legislation enacted since Federation.<br />
In doing so it has endorsed this Government's approach to recognising and<br />
protecting native title, while ensuring that workable processes exist for land<br />
management across every state and territory,<br />
The High Court has delivered a clear rebuff to the approach adopted by the<br />
Western Australian Government.<br />
Premier Court attempted to extinguish inherent rights and replace them with<br />
statutory rights which were much more vulnerable to interference and<br />
extinguishment by Governments than the property rights held by other<br />
Australians. The WA Government now has no choice but to fall into line and accept that<br />
the High Court in Mabo recognised the existence of a new set of property<br />
rights; rights which pre-dated the acquisition of sovereignty by the Crown,<br />
and continued in place after that time.<br />
This decision makes it impossible for the Federal Coalition to maintain its<br />
stated opposition to our balanced approach to Native Title Legislation and<br />
policy. It will force John Howard to accept that the Coalition's opposition to<br />
the Native Title Act was wrong and misguided.<br />
Will Mr Howard now repudiate statements made by his predecessor who<br />
threatened to repeal the Native Title Act? </p>
<p>1 Ac~ : / ms rn01 P .02/ 01<br />
TEL: ria. II<br />
2<br />
The Commonwealth is concerned about the uncertainty created by the<br />
Western Australian Government relating to the new titles issued in WA since<br />
1993. Premier Court has deliberately ignored the processes set down in the<br />
Native Title Act and must take ultimate responsibility for the effect of this<br />
decision in Western Australia.<br />
The Commonwealth Government is nevertheless prepared to work with the<br />
Western Australian Government to ensure that issues arising from this<br />
decision can be addressed cooperatively.<br />
Preliminary talks have already been initiated at Ministerial level with the<br />
Court Government.<br />
We will want to ensure that Western Australians are not disadvantaged by<br />
the actions to date of the Court Government but we will not backtrack on the<br />
fundamental principles which are embodied in the Native Title Act.<br />
CAN BERRA<br />
16 MARCH 1995 </p>
<p>TEL: J 5M a r .95 14: 40[-<br />
.3<br />
Key components of the Native Title Act<br />
it recognises and protects native title<br />
it provides a mechanism to establish the existence of native title<br />
it establishes a regime for dealing with future acts which affect native<br />
title it provides a mechanism for states and territories to validate existing<br />
interests with complete certainty<br />
it provides for a ' right to negotiate process' for mining activities on<br />
native title land<br />
it provides for a non-extinguishment principle to apply in certain<br />
circumstances it provides for States and Territories to put in place their own<br />
Tribunals and regulatory regimes providing they adhere to principles<br />
set down in the Native Title Act<br />
it provides for compensation to native title holders whose title is<br />
extinguished as a result of validation.<br />
The Act represents a balancing of interests across the Australian community<br />
but is premised on the fair and equal treatment of Aboriginal people<br />
It will increasingly be recognised that the Australian people, in enacting this<br />
landmark legislation, have effected an extraordinary achievement.<br />
a a A </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
