<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>21695</transcript-id>
    <title>Chief of the Defence Force  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/04/2005</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
I am delighted to announce that I will recommend to the Governor-General the appointment of Air Marshal Allan (Angus) Grant Houston, AO, AFC as the new Chief of the Defence Force (CDF) for a three-year term from 4 July 2005.</p>
<p>  Air Marshal Houston will replace the current CDF, General Peter Cosgrove, who is retiring after more than 40 years service with the Australian Defence Force.</p>
<p> Air Marshal Houston will be the first Chief of the Air Force to serve as the Chief of the Defence Force. He will be promoted to the rank of Air Chief Marshal.</p>
<p> The appointment will mark the culmination of a career with the Royal Australian Air Force which started as a cadet pilot in 1970. He has served Australia with distinction in postings both here and overseas.</p>
<p> Since his appointment as Chief of the Air Force on 20 June 2001, Air Marshal Houston has provided valuable advice to the Australian Government and the CDF. He has exhibited firm direction and leadership for the Air Force.</p>
<p> I am confident that Air Marshal Houston will continue to build on the work of General Cosgrove in shaping the expertise and capabilities of ADF. The ADF has evolved into a modern and adaptable military outfit respected around the globe.</p>
<p>On behalf of the Government and people of Australia, I would like to offer my sincere appreciation to General Cosgrove. Since entering the Royal Military College, Duntroon in 1965 he has enjoyed a military career of the highest order.</p>
<p> General Cosgrove has served as CDF for the past three years.</p>
<p>  His military and strategic advice during his term as CDF, a particularly active period for the Australian Defence Force, has been invaluable.  He has assumed a leading role in Australia's involvement in the war against terrorism, most particularly in the missions in Afghanistan and Iraq.</p>
<p> Previously, his command of the Australian led INTERFET mission in East Timor and his appointment as Australian of the Year for 2001 have earned him the respect of all Australians.</p>
<p>  Throughout his career, General Cosgrove has carried out all of his duties in a spirit which befits the proud traditions of the Australian military.</p>
<p>  I know he will continue to deliver outstanding leadership and advice for the remainder of his term.</p>
<p> I wish General Cosgrove, and his wife Lynne, all the best for the future.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
