<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7793</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, RADIO 3LO, MELBOURNE, FRIDAY 27 OCTOBER 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/10/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007793.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, RADIO 3L0, MELBOURNE, FRIDAY<br />
27 OCTOBER 1989<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, what's your response to Mr Howard's<br />
talks with Mr Peacock and his return to the front bench?<br />
PM: I'm, quite seriously, I'm pleased that he's going back<br />
on to the front bench, though they are not a very good front<br />
bench as is generally recognised. I think it's good for<br />
Government that the opposition should have its best quality<br />
on the front bench. It makes for a better opposition and I<br />
think it makes for a better Government. So I welcome the<br />
move. JOURNALIST: Are you going to be going up to Queensland for<br />
the election?<br />
PM: Yes, I'll be up there.<br />
JOURNALIST: When will you be up there?<br />
PM: Look, I've just got back from overseas yesterday. I<br />
haven't looked at my forward program. I know I'm going up<br />
there, I'm not quite sure when it is it's in the next<br />
couple of weeks.<br />
JOURNALIST: How do you see the results going?<br />
PM: How do I see the results going in Queensland? Well,<br />
because of the massive gerrymander, it's a difficult job.<br />
So putting it, calling it exactly as I understand it, I<br />
would say that Labor has got the great majority of the<br />
seats that it has to get to win Government. I would think<br />
that, you know, the three or four over that that we can say<br />
it's definitely got, I-think it will fall across the line on<br />
it. It'll be a tough job, but Mr Goss is a very good leader<br />
and the atmosphere of the conservative camp up there is<br />
absolutely unacceptable. It's not just the National Party<br />
who are the Government now, but what the electorate, I<br />
think, is increasingly realising is that the Liberal Party<br />
has been part of the mess and the corruption for most of<br />
that period. Labor is the only alternative to what has now<br />
been decades of inefficient and corrupt Government. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you believe corruption is the issue for that<br />
election? PM: No election at a Federal or State level is ever just<br />
one issue. In the Queensland election it won't be just<br />
corruption, but it will obviously be a very significant<br />
issue.<br />
JOURNALIST: Inflation is running at a two year high. Is<br />
that acceptable to you?<br />
PM: I'd prefer it wasn't there, but we will certainly be<br />
seeing a lowering of that rate in the rest of the financial<br />
year. We've got certain special factors which are<br />
acknowledged in this. We've got the impact of the higher<br />
interest rates shown in when they were rising, that's<br />
now being reflected in the CPI. Well I think they've<br />
plateaud and there's still being the reflection of the<br />
floods in the eastern States being reflected in fruit and<br />
vegetable prices, that's washed out now, if I can put it<br />
that way. So the inflation rate will be coming down. I'm<br />
sorry it's where it is, but it will be coming down.<br />
JOURNALIST: Where do you see it ending at the end of the<br />
financial year?<br />
PM: Certainly be lower than where it is now. It's not very<br />
useful to be absolutely precise about that, but the<br />
important thing is that we can say to the Australian<br />
electorate it will be coming down as we go towards the end<br />
of this financial year.<br />
ends<br />
I </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
