<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6664</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE, 4 JULY 1985</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/07/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006664.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
E. O. E. PROOF ONLY<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE 4 JULY 1985<br />
PM: Ladies and Gentlemen, at the conclusion of an extraordinarily<br />
s uccessful Summit, I would remind you of the ninth of the nine<br />
principles, which at times seems to have been overlooked. The<br />
words of it exactly: Ninth any reform package must have<br />
widesprea ' d community support, including support of a widely<br />
representative National Taxation Summit, of economic organisations<br />
and communite groups. We have just concluded that Summit, the<br />
Government has, in terms of principle nine, responded to that<br />
process. And we are now, as a result of the tremendous assistance<br />
that we have received from the representatives of the people of<br />
Australia assembled at the Summit, now ready to go into the final<br />
stage of~ this process which commenced over six months ago. And<br />
that fir~ al process will begin when we meet at the ordinary<br />
scheduled Cabinet meeting on Monday of next week. And I take this<br />
opportunity of saying, as I said to the Summit participants<br />
themselves, the gratitude of the* Government, particularly the<br />
Treasurer and myself, for the magnificent co-operation that we<br />
have received from the representatives gathered at the Summit.<br />
JOURNALIST: P rime Minister, was pushing Option C a monumental<br />
mistake? PM: No. We have made it clear, from the beginning, that we would<br />
adopt the responsibility as a government of doing all the work of<br />
analysing the existing tax system, and its weaknesses. And<br />
indicating the avenues that are available, in our judgement, to<br />
meet that situation. And we accepted the obligation of pitting<br />
what we saw as a pref ' erred option... We did that within the context<br />
of the nine principles, including the ninth which I've read out.<br />
I would guess the best answer to the question is provided by the<br />
reaction of the people at the Summit themselves. Because they,<br />
within that framework, were able to put their position and lead<br />
the Government to a position which will clearly enable us to meet<br />
the requirements of broad cbinmunity support.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister what is the status of Option A,<br />
against your nine principles?<br />
PM: Well, Option A is still there. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: That's what........ nine principles.<br />
PM: Yes of course it does. There was a clear broad support,<br />
unanimity, of course. But there was a broad, I would say<br />
majority, support for option A. We of course will within the<br />
Cabinet look at the elements of Option A. There may be some fine<br />
tuning, there will be,' it won't be precisely in exactly that term,<br />
but essentially Option A remains there as part of the package that<br />
will be adopted by the'Government.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister yesterday twenty-four business<br />
organisations issued a statement saying that they reject Option A.<br />
PM: Correct.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Keating when did it become clear to you that<br />
Option C was not on?<br />
TREASURER: Well. I think, Niki, the Prime Minister referred to<br />
the criteria, which he established before the election campaign.<br />
We, I think, argued that Option C, was in its entirety, I think<br />
the most ambitious tax reform change that would have been, I think<br />
as you have seen around the world at the moment where we<br />
have got lots of tax reforms, going on in the country. Now, I<br />
think we,. as we went through the Summit process, we were<br />
interested in the views which were coming from various groups. We<br />
were loojding for the chemistry of the Summit itself, to work on<br />
the vievjs of others, and to see just where Option C in its<br />
entirety sat towards the week's end. And I think, probably, if<br />
you ask me for a specific time, probably yesterday. I thought we<br />
were at the position, probably where we couldn't get Option C up.<br />
If not all of it a part of it, and of course a part of it is there<br />
in terms of a consumption tax on services.<br />
JOURNALIST: And when-you arrived at work this morning you said<br />
you weren't there for the fun of it you were still fighting for<br />
Option C. I<br />
TREASURER: Yes that ' s right. We still keep barracking.<br />
JOURNALIST: Was it the ACTU last night or yesterday.<br />
PM: No. I<br />
JOURNALIST: Will full tax indexation accompany any package the<br />
Government agrees to?<br />
PM: The indication has been that there has been a disposition<br />
towards that principlq. But the question of indexati-on will<br />
properly be a matter~ for consideration and decision by the<br />
Cabinet.<br />
JOURNALIST: In compbrison to package C how good a reform package<br />
will this one be? </p>
<p>PM: It will be an excellent reform package.<br />
JOURNALIST: It's not the best is it sir, and that's what you are<br />
on about?<br />
PM: Well look, you are going to have a lot of interest in trying<br />
to pursue your cart in and out of this. I am trying to put to<br />
you, and whether you want to accept it or not, principle nine has<br />
been valid from the time it was written. Now I wish that you<br />
would understand the reality, the actuality of the words. Any<br />
reform package must have widespread community support, including<br />
support at a widely representative national taxation summit. Now<br />
that principle was not there for the sake of having nine rather<br />
than eight. It was there because the Government, the Treasurer,<br />
and myself from the word go, saying we will accept the obligation<br />
of analysis and recommendation, but whatever we do it has got to<br />
satisfy principle nine. Now please get into your head, and<br />
understand that principle nine has been meaningful from word go.<br />
MR KEATING: Can I just pick the point up. Just in response to<br />
the other elpment of the question, and say it is without a doubt,<br />
it will be without a doubt the most radical tax reform<br />
package this country's seen. We've seen reform of the direct tax<br />
base, in a way which its never been reformed before. We are<br />
finishing off the debate on capital gains which has raged in this<br />
country for years, taxing fringe benefits in a way where vie stop<br />
this trenendous haemorrhaging of the revenues through fringe<br />
benefits, the identification cards deal with the haemorrhaging of<br />
the system of the straight out fraud, and an unprecedented attack<br />
upon tax shelters. The second objective of the reform, we said,<br />
was to reform the indirect tax base. We will still be reforming<br />
the indirect tax base in terms of changing the wholesale sales tax<br />
system, and th ' e establishment of the consumption tax on services.<br />
And the third element was to shift some of that weight. Arid we're<br />
shifting the weight, and I think in terms of establishing the<br />
principle that we'll have a tax on the service sector of the<br />
economy, which after all has been the growing sector of the<br />
economy since the middle 1960s, is a very substantial principle.<br />
And I hate to go so far as to say, well without the broadness, or<br />
breadth, of option C, and its ambitions, if we had begun, with<br />
what we have this afternoon, we wouldn't have it this afternoon.<br />
PM: That's right.<br />
JOURNALIST: What sort of income tax cuts are you looking at under<br />
this new approach?<br />
TREASURER: Well, we will ha've to see when the package is costed<br />
accurately, and we ( interrupted)<br />
JOURNALIST: Can we just clear up that question about Health<br />
services. Are they going to </p>
<p>PM: They will be out.<br />
TREASURER: Exempt.<br />
JOURNALIST: What will be the order of the income tax cuts under<br />
this PM: Well the Treasurer has just given an answer which goes to<br />
that point. The elements of the package now have to be determined<br />
by the Cabinet. And what we are able to do in that area will be<br />
the result of the final outcome of all that goes into the package.<br />
We obviously can't give you a final answer on that here.<br />
JOURNALIST: What sort of reform, in fact, will be made to the<br />
indirect tax base, then, compared to Option C. Hiow much will the<br />
net revenue n effect be, what will the wholesale tax level be,<br />
will there be one level, or more than one.<br />
TREASURER: Well in terms of services, Paul, 12.5%, as proposed<br />
by the consumption tax. And the point I was just going to answer<br />
in respect of Michael's question, is to simply say that this is<br />
not, andy never was a tax cut exercise in terms of say the 1984/ 85<br />
a u dit.-It is a tax reform exercise which brings tax cuts. And the<br />
principles-of tax rerorm, along with tax cuts, is what is<br />
important. And so in terms of simply looking at the exercise for<br />
any particular groups that will only be possible when we cost the<br />
proposal, and put the scales there. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Treasurer, could you help us with a checklist<br />
of exemptions both those you have given to this point and<br />
ones you would consider.<br />
KEATING: I will, but not right at the moment. You<br />
will have it the first time I can give it to you.<br />
JOURNALIST: When would you expect the changes to start now.<br />
Will the timetable be able to be brought forward at all for<br />
the changes actually coming into effect.<br />
PM: Well it will depend on all the elements of the package.<br />
IT may be that some elements will be able to be brought in<br />
relatively quickly. Others obviously will not. Now it will<br />
be a matter for decision on the advice of the Treasurer and<br />
myself to the Cabinet as to what that timetable will be, but<br />
what is informing our minds right through is the desirability<br />
of getting the tax changes into operation in their totality<br />
as soon as-is possible and consistent with the work that needs<br />
to be done , to ensure that all the relevant considerations have<br />
been taken into account.<br />
JOURNALIST: The services tax would still be about a year off<br />
though, would it?<br />
PM: oWell, I don't think that you can say exactly how long<br />
t-hat would be. It may be of that order. I simply can repeat.<br />
It's in everyonr&amp;': interests, the Government's and the community,<br />
to try and get this thing resolved and into place as soon as is<br />
possible, consistent with your obligation to take into account<br />
all the sorts of points that were made to us at the Summit.<br />
Now that will be done. Everyone has got a common interest, as<br />
I say, in getting it in as soon as possible. I<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, the Government had previously rejected<br />
the idea of abolishing the tax free threshold. What has<br />
caused you to change your mind and are you confident that<br />
the problems in that in terms of compensation can be<br />
overcome? PM: Again, in-line with principle nine, as was acknowledged<br />
there this afternoon, there had been a not universal, but<br />
quite considerable expression of the view that that is<br />
something that ought to be taken into account. And we have<br />
said that does make sense to take it into account. There are<br />
obvious possible advantages but there are clearly concerns<br />
and difficulties and if you were going to proceed down that<br />
path you would be doing it in a way which would ensure that<br />
the needy and particularly the elderly in Australia could<br />
not in any way be disadvantaged and you would have to be<br />
satisfied, if you were going down this route, that you could<br />
meet those necessary requirements. So, what I've said, and<br />
what the Summit heard us say, was that was something that had<br />
had a majority support to examine. we are going to examine it.<br />
and see whether it is an appropriate element to include within<br />
a total reform package. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: The Government is still determined to press<br />
ahead with a capital gains tax. That wasn't clear this<br />
afternoon in your response to Sir Joh Petersen.<br />
PM: Well, I think it may not have been clear to him. It<br />
may not have been clear to you. I would have thought it<br />
was clear to everyone else.<br />
JOURNALIST: The future of fringe benefits. Has that<br />
changed under this package?<br />
KEATING: No.<br />
JOURNALIST: Treasurer, do you realise that you were given a<br />
vote of confidence by the financial market this afternoon<br />
when they took half a cent off the dollar on the strength of<br />
rumours that you were about to resign or had resigned?<br />
KEATING: Look, I heard this report this morning. There is no<br />
truth in it at all. But I didn't know about that. I would<br />
like to taaZe this opportunity though just to clear that point<br />
and to say that that never crossed my mind....... and that<br />
there has never been the slightest, if you like, rift in<br />
relations between me and the Prime Minister and anybody else,<br />
for that matter. And the Prime Minister paid me a compliment<br />
in the House of Representatives today which I appreciate. I<br />
want 1Vo pay him this compliment and say that without his<br />
support there would be nothing on this table today. And<br />
without this support there wouldn't have been a White Paper<br />
of this dimensions because no Treasurer with the best<br />
intentions in the world can get a reform proposal like this<br />
through a Cabinet and this country without the support of a<br />
Prime Minister. I am pleased to say in the time I have been<br />
Treasurer that support has been unqualified and I appreciate it<br />
very much. And I would like to take this public opportunity<br />
in front of you people who have written so much about our<br />
relations on this issue just to say that the support has<br />
always been there and I have always appreciated it.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Keating, do you think the support should<br />
have lasted a little longer?<br />
KEATING: Well, as I said, cynicism has overtaken most of us,<br />
John. I had hoped<br />
JOURNALIST: Did it cross your mind, Treasurer, that today<br />
you are standing alone in ~ a sea of weakness?<br />
KEATING: Look, David, I wonder why you are not still barrackingyou<br />
should try and find Malcolm somewhere.........<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Keating, do you feel in any sense as journalists<br />
and politicians would understand the word do you feel you have<br />
been dumiped?<br />
KEATING: No, I mean, look, let's be clear about this. This is,<br />
you see, in a sense let's be honest. if we had talked about<br />
a proposal as radical as Option C last year, no-one would have </p>
<p>believed if a package of that dimension was put on the<br />
table by a Government and argued for in this country and<br />
if Prime Minister and I stumped the country arguing for it.<br />
We did. We tugged at all of the ends of power in this<br />
country to pull it to the table to pass We have done<br />
that. But the fact is under his principle nine, it wasn't<br />
there. We couldn't get that support. But what you are<br />
seeing is a major change a major change in the business<br />
tax area. A major change to tax on services. A major<br />
change ' in respect of the income tax base itself. And<br />
busting that whole non compliance psychology the disrepute<br />
with whichothe tax system has been held particularly since<br />
the former Government failed to do anything about the paper<br />
schemes the outright contrived schemes of the 70s we have<br />
got a very difficult job in restoring taxpayer respect for<br />
the system of compliance. And this approach on the base<br />
broadening, the repair of the income tax base, establishing<br />
a tax pn consumption and services, and enormous change to the<br />
business tax area will be a milestone in this Government's<br />
history.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, Mr Keating said that it was<br />
yesterday he decided that option C wasn't a goer. But I<br />
put to you that you decided that on Monday when you heard<br />
Bill Kel ty's speech?.<br />
PM: You can, yes.<br />
JOURNALIST: Would it be right?<br />
PM: * No.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr* Keating, you said-under his principle 9. Does<br />
that imply that that isn't your principle.<br />
TREASURER: In fact I saw that draft, you were with me in the<br />
election campaign, Geoff, you knew when that was drafted. That<br />
was of course a draft which the Prime Minister and I, in fact, had<br />
a common hand in. Aud when I say it is the Prime Minister's<br />
principle, he made the statement in the election campaign. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, you were saying all last week<br />
that you were convinced that by the time the next election<br />
came around tax reform would be a major plus for your<br />
Government and-one of the main reasons for that<br />
PM: And complete what I said, " and a major minus for the<br />
opposition". JOURNALIST: Yes that is right. And one of the main reasons<br />
you gave for that was that there would be significant nett<br />
benefits for the average Australian. Given that there is now<br />
not going to be a broad based consumption tax, and nett benefits<br />
must be less, are you still convinced that the package is<br />
saleable.<br />
PM: Well I understand that you would have been there today and<br />
you would have been able to form the judgement on the basis of<br />
the reaction at the Summit as to whether the package that we<br />
have in mind is saleable. The answer is resoundingly in the<br />
affirmative. But let me make this point, as you open it up<br />
widely. Let me say a couple of things. Firstly, if you are<br />
going to be looking at the benefits to the Australian people,<br />
it is no) 7 simply to be judged in terms of reductions in scales,<br />
and any cuts that may be available. But the great benefit to<br />
the Australian people is going to be the continuing one that<br />
at last you have had a government that has the guts to face<br />
up to this issue and not run away from it and deliberately<br />
by their actions, as 30 years out of the previous 35 under<br />
conservative governments that you have had, but by their<br />
deliberate action as well as inaction, allowed to emerge in<br />
this country a system which has disintergrated to the disadvantage<br />
of the great majority of Australians. And it is because that<br />
realisation will be, have been made very significantly sharper<br />
as a result of the events of this week. You saw in there the<br />
almost universal approbation of the courage shown by this<br />
Government to tackle this issue. It wasn't easy and we knew it.<br />
But the courage that has been displayed by the Government has<br />
been universally approved in that Summit. That will be reflected<br />
at the same time as the courage of this Government will be<br />
approbated by the electorate, will be the analysis of the gross<br />
inadequacy of what passes for an opposition. They have stayed<br />
in their funk hole, not fighting for tax reform, but fighting<br />
one another as they use the criterion of perceived political<br />
advantage to * see, what particular piece of negativism after<br />
another they can utter. I have been confident from the word<br />
go, and I am more confident than ever as a result of the end<br />
of this Summit that those judgements will work in the way I<br />
said for this Government and against this pathetic opposition.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, do you really believe that you<br />
and Mr Keating can walk away from the statements that you have<br />
made over the past month. And can I ask you both whether you<br />
really believe that a broadly based consumption tax is still<br />
the best reform to make to the tax system. And do you think<br />
that the chances for that reform are now finished.<br />
PM: You can ask that and I remind you of what I have said<br />
at the outset of this proposal. WE had a job, ail this<br />
conference, W~ e had a job to do which we have done. We guided<br />
through a preferred option. We had the responsibility then </p>
<p>PM cont: of selling it. And I don't think anyone can<br />
possibly make the judgement in respect of the Treasurer<br />
or myself that we have failed in that task of trying to sell<br />
what we believed was the ideal option. And of course, we continue<br />
to believe that that was the ideal option. But the whole task<br />
that we were about at all times was in the context not of 8<br />
principles but of 9. And we knew that we had to come to a<br />
position at the S~ jmit, as explicitly stated in the 9th<br />
principle, and if,, weren't there able to get the indications<br />
of broad community support then the task we had undertaken<br />
had not finally met with the satisfaction of principle 9.<br />
And then we had to accommodate to that. We have done it.<br />
And as Paul Keating has said without the possibility of<br />
any sensible contradiction in the result, you have still<br />
got the most significant tax reform that this country<br />
has ever seen, and secondly, by any international standard<br />
the most significant tax reform I believe that has been<br />
undertaken. And let me say this, I am proud of the fact<br />
that Paul Keating., and with Paul Keating, we have been able<br />
to 1I think guide the community to that position.<br />
JOURNALIST: Does, the fact that you couldn't get broad<br />
based c~ mmunity support for your ideal option mean that<br />
the Government is really out of touch with the community?<br />
PM: No.<br />
JOURNALIST: Priffie Minister, I am perplexed by your remark<br />
tha: t you haven't failed in your task of selling option C.<br />
We don't have option C and a supplementary..<br />
PM: No, we haven't failed in ultimate task of reform. We<br />
have failed, if you want to use that phrase, to get in terms<br />
of principle 9 broad community support for option C. That is<br />
clear. JOURNALIST: Well I am sorry I must have misheard you.<br />
PM: You did.<br />
JOURNALIST: You said that hadn't failed to sell. option C.<br />
Leaving that aside when did<br />
PM: I am sorry, I did not intend, we have not failed<br />
in the task that we had to go out and try to sell. J That<br />
I was trying I don't think..<br />
JOURNALIST: trying to sell it?<br />
PM: What I am trying to say is that we had a task and a<br />
responsibility, once the Cabinet had decided that that was<br />
the preferred option, we had the task. I don't think we<br />
or, I should have used the word, Bather than the word<br />
failed is that we didn't miss the obligation and thc opportunity<br />
of going to try and sell. We2 did that to the limit of our<br />
ability. In the end w-, e failed to get satisfaction in term1s<br />
of principle 9. That is obvious.<br />
JOURNALIST: When did you decide to ditch option C? </p>
<p>11.<br />
PM: It was during this week that it became clear that<br />
in terms of the Summit position, it was not on.<br />
JOURNALIST: The Treasurer was precise, can you be more<br />
precise. PM: I would say it was during the evening of Tuesday and<br />
the Wednesday.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, the Opposition of course has a policy<br />
supporting broadly based indirect tax. What sort of credibility<br />
are you and Mir Keating going to have opposing that now?<br />
PM: Well, let me respond with this question. Do you<br />
believe that the Opposition is going to be out selling the<br />
proposition of a broadly based indirect tax. if I find that<br />
Mr Peacock or Mr Howard or<br />
Mr Sinclair is going to be out selling such a proposition then<br />
I will be fascinated. And that is when we will need to make<br />
our decision-about them. But I would be prepared to enter into<br />
a side bet with you.<br />
JOURNALIST: So you think they will abandon their..<br />
PM: Well let's say they have already.<br />
TREASURER: One interesting thing was in the polling research<br />
we did see that support among Liberal Party voters for a<br />
braadly based indirect tax, which was after all one of the<br />
main planks of the last election of the coalition, they're<br />
a pretty crook pair of salesmen if they couldn't get<br />
hardly any registration of support within the coalition.<br />
There was a substantial level of support within the Labor<br />
voters. So, you know, out of their hands, they wish to try<br />
and stir their constituency.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, the Centre Left is feeling somewhat<br />
vindicated by the outcome 0Cthis package and Tax Summit. Were<br />
you influenced by representations made by Centre Left Ministers,<br />
especially Mr Hayden, over the last few days.<br />
PM I have not had representations made by ir Hayden.<br />
JOURNALIST: Have you had any-talks with Mr Hayden?<br />
PM: After we had made the decision.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, following up on Michelle's<br />
question in a way. You' keep referring to the significanca<br />
of the proposed tax changes but there is one process you<br />
need to go through and apparently that is the Cabinet<br />
process. Do we take it from what you have been saying<br />
up till now that you are confident that the broad outlines<br />
that you have proposed today will be endorsed by Cabinet?<br />
PM: Yes I took the opportunity today before T went into tk-he<br />
Summit to put that approach * Lo sipeak" the Ministers. I had 1-, d<br />
the opportunity earlier of speaking to Bill Hayden and to<br />
Stewart West, to Brian Howe. I got the other Ministers then </p>
<p>12.<br />
PM cant: before I went in and indicated to them what<br />
I was going to put to the Summit, and the terms I was going<br />
to put it. And there was no dissent from that.<br />
JOURNALIST: How important in your deliberations was principle<br />
7 as opposed to principle 9?<br />
PM: Principle 7 has always been important for the obvious<br />
reason that for those of you who haven't got principle 7,<br />
and indeed each one of the principles engraved on your heart,<br />
principle 7 is the one which goes to the question of the<br />
support within those sections of the community which would<br />
be necessary for the implementation of any indirect tax area.<br />
Thath/ ys obviously always been important. And I believe that<br />
we will have the support of the ACTU. I certainly, in light<br />
of what the Secretary of the ACTU said today, have no reason<br />
to believe that principle 7 will not be satisfied.<br />
JOURNALIST: How would you respond to the perception that the<br />
Government has ditched the broad based consumption tax, which<br />
is what the ACTU wanted, but has retained, essentially retained<br />
all of option A, which business yesterday rejected?<br />
PM: Well I suppose I could equally be asked how would I<br />
respond to the perception that the sort of approach that<br />
we have adopted i'n the indirect tax area meets what was put<br />
by the Chamber of Commerce, by certain of the welfare groups<br />
and-so on. And it would be just as legitimate. The point is<br />
tha~ t under principle 7 the attitude of the ACTU is important<br />
not of itself but at all points it has been regarded as<br />
absolutely essential that if there is going to be within<br />
a reform package an increase in the indirect tax area<br />
which would be compensated by way of changes in indirect<br />
tax rates, there could not be double dipping. for the obvious<br />
reason that if that were allowed that of iLtself would be<br />
inflationary. And I am satisfied as a result of what has<br />
been said and the Australian community assembled in the<br />
Summit has heard the undertakings of the ACTU in that regard.<br />
I am confident that they will be adhered to.<br />
TREASURER: this point about the ACTU. The ACTU wanted<br />
no indirect tax, wasn't prepared to talk about indirect tax<br />
in this country. And they were coaxed there, schooled there<br />
by 6 months of assiduous effort. They had more ex osure, more<br />
exposure to the Government, to the Treasury and to whole<br />
basis of analysis, as indeed has other groups in the community.<br />
And I think the achievement of getting recognition for<br />
broadening the indirect tax area and establishing the<br />
principle of taxation on services is a very important<br />
milestone. And I'-don't think. if the ACTU has come to<br />
that party at this stage one should presume that that is<br />
where they were. They were definitely opposed to it and<br />
have been pretty well right throughout.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, I just wanted to ask are<br />
there any modifications you would consider to the capital<br />
gains tax and fringe benefits proposal? </p>
<p>13.<br />
PM: Well what we have said in there and have said here again<br />
earlier, that option A remains an essential part of the<br />
approach and package that the Government will finally adopt.<br />
We are prepared within that package to look at elements of<br />
it. But as I said in answer to a previous question, a capital<br />
gains tax will be part of the end result. Now, there may be<br />
elements of it that we can, of what has been said that can<br />
be taken into account. But that is a matter which the Cabinet<br />
will decide.<br />
JOURNALIST: I think you will find the ACTU had said for months<br />
that they were prepared to keep their options open on all<br />
reforms including indirect taxes. How does the 12.5% tax<br />
differ from what came from the ACTU tax negotiating.<br />
TREASURER: It didn't come from the ACTU. The whole proposal<br />
came from the Government. Every element of it, and every<br />
element in that paper came from the Government. And in the<br />
course of those discussions, I think, we have broken down<br />
a very big barrier of public thinking in this country that<br />
an increase in indirect taxes is necessarily regressive and<br />
that it * should not be considered. And that has changed.<br />
The ACTOJ has changed its position on that, and taxation<br />
of services is a very important element in that.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Keating, apart from exemption for health,<br />
food and fuel areas for a consumption tax on services, other<br />
than those will it be across the board consumption tax on<br />
sei~ vces, 12 2%.<br />
TREASURER: Peter, that is proposed at 12 would apply to<br />
goods and services, the areas, perhaps the grey areas in between<br />
were automatically covered. What it will mean now in fleshing<br />
out this proposal is definition about the area of the coverage<br />
in the services sector, which I think is the point of your<br />
question. And that is going to be something we have to just<br />
give some time and attention to in the next week or so.<br />
PM: Just let me add this to what Paul has said there, Peter,<br />
that clearly an overwhelmingly important consideration in<br />
what Paul has said there will be looking at those services<br />
which if they are to be taxed would have an unduly regressive<br />
effcct upon the underprivileged and the needy. That is the sort<br />
of criterion that has been taken into account to this point<br />
and would continue to be taken into account in the decisions<br />
that we will come to in that area.<br />
ENDS </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
