<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5493</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS TO SOUTH AUSTRALIAN STATE COUNCIL DELIVERED FOR THE PRIME MINISTER BY SENATOR CHANEY</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/12/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005493.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
APPROXIMATELY 9 PM<br />
~ i<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA FRIDAY 5 DECEMBER 1980<br />
ADDRESS TO SOUTH AUSTRALIAN STATE COUNCIL<br />
DELIVERED FOR THE PRIME MINISTER BY SENATOR CHANEY<br />
The Philosophical Basis of Liberalism<br />
At the conclusion of his address to Parliament last week, the<br />
Governor-General indicated that the Government believes that it<br />
is important to explain to the Australian people the philosophy<br />
which shapes its policies and actions. This seems an excellent<br />
opportunity to make a start.<br />
In doing so, I begin by making the point that, while the<br />
emphasis on explaining the philosophy may be new, the philosophy<br />
itself is not. Liberals have always had a set of beliefs<br />
providing the underlying rationale of their policies and giving<br />
them coherence. But we have not always spelled out those beliefs,<br />
those assumptions which inform and give direction to our policy<br />
decisions. We need now to remedy that defect, to articulate<br />
our often unspoken major premises unspoken simply because<br />
Liberals have taken the truth and importance of those premises<br />
to be self-evident. To us, they remain self-evident; but to<br />
many they remain largely unknown. And because they are largely<br />
unknown, the policies that flow from them are not fully understood.<br />
And because of that, we Liberals have made harder unnecessarily<br />
harder the task of winning and keeping not just the votes of<br />
the people but, even more important because more enduring, their<br />
understanding support throughout the life of the Government.<br />
So we need, not to fashion a new set of beliefs, but to explain<br />
more consciously and carefully and often than we have in the<br />
past the philosophical basis that has always underlain our<br />
actions. What that basis is I shall come to later in this<br />
address. Suffice it for now to say that perhaps the most<br />
fundamental of the L iberal's beliefs is the right to the freedom<br />
to choose. From that belief comes our commitment to a private<br />
enterprise economy, which not only gives us the freedom of<br />
economic -choice, but itself requires the freedoms without which<br />
we could not have innovation, technological progress, risk-taking,<br />
the saving and investment of capital all the things necessary<br />
for a flourishing, competitive, free enterprise economy. From<br />
that belief too comes our commitment to economic growth, which<br />
increases not just our freedom of economic choice but also, and<br />
perhaps even more importantly, the range of opportunities open<br />
to us to live a more satisfying life and not in the material<br />
sphere alone. 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
And finally, it is that belief in the right to the freedom<br />
to choose which distinguishes most clearly and directly.<br />
our own open, expanding, caring, co-operating society from<br />
the grey, imposed, and shut-in collectivity of the<br />
Socialist state.<br />
Events and Ideas<br />
In talking about the philosophical basis of liberalism, I<br />
recognise two things at the outset. First, all governments,<br />
except the fanatically ideological and dogmatic, have to be<br />
responsive to events and circumstances, to be reactive to<br />
a considerable extent. To attempt to govern from a blueprint<br />
is a recipe for disaster; indeed this is the essential<br />
case against central planning. But if governments are not to<br />
be merely the prisoners of events and circumstances, if they<br />
are to hold out the vision of a better future and to convey<br />
a sense of purpose, they have to embody belief to ref Iet<br />
those beliefs in their policies and to convey them successfully<br />
to the people who elect them to govern..<br />
Second, I recognise that many people and perhaps business<br />
people in particular tend in the name of practicality and what<br />
they call pragmatism to downplay the role of ideas and<br />
principles in politics. They tend to see that role as part<br />
of the side-show of politics, something engaged in by men of<br />
words rather than of action, something which is ultimately<br />
not " real".<br />
I believe that this attitude is profoundly mistaken. While<br />
I disagree with much of what is now known as " Keynesianism",<br />
I believe there is great truth in John Maynard Keynes'<br />
observation that:<br />
" The ideas of economists and political philosophers,<br />
both when they are right and when they are wrong,<br />
are more powerful than is commonly understood<br />
practical men, who believe themselves to be quite<br />
exempt from any intellectual influences, are usually<br />
the slaves of some defunct economist... soon or<br />
late, it is ideas, not vested interests, which are<br />
dangerous for good or evil."<br />
How well a social or economic or political system works, its<br />
prospects for surviving, depend not merely on how efficiently<br />
or rationally the bits and pieces are arranged. It is not<br />
a machine. It is a cooperative enterprise involving men and<br />
women, and its success depends crucially on their understanding<br />
of it, their attachment to it, their commitment to the<br />
philosophy which animates it and gives it meaning. The enemies<br />
of the free society recognise this well enough and ceaselessly<br />
work to undermine the philosophical foundations which sustain<br />
that society and give it legitimacy. It is time that its<br />
supporters also recognized this and act accordingly. Indeed, throughout<br />
much of the Western world this is now appreciated and a vigorous<br />
and intellectually powerful defence of the free societies of the<br />
West is under way, a defence which takes into account the great<br />
social changes of the last generation. I believe that committed<br />
Australians must join in this defence. ./ 3 </p>
<p>-3<br />
Liberal Principles and Values<br />
As its name implies, ours is a liberal Government holding<br />
liberal principles. It believes, that is, that to the maximum<br />
extent compatible with a cohesive and stable society, people<br />
should be free to make their own decisions concerning their<br />
lives and the disposal of their own resources. It believes<br />
that society is healthier and the lives of people happier when<br />
responsibility, enterprise and power are spread widely through<br />
the community, rather than concentrated in one or a few places.<br />
That is the ideal to be aimed for and any deviation from it<br />
requires special justification.<br />
My Government believes in-the virtue of the free competition<br />
of ideas, opinions, services and goods within an ordered community.<br />
It rejects the notion that the relationship between the people<br />
and the State should be like that between customers and the<br />
supermarket that because something is considered desirable<br />
it should be assumed automatically that the State should<br />
provide it. The Government rejects that notion for two<br />
reasons: first, because the State is likely to be in many<br />
ways an inefficient and wasteful provider and because many<br />
services can be better provided in other ways by voluntary<br />
action on the part of individuals joining together freely, and<br />
by the mechanism of the market. Second, and fundamentally,<br />
because the more you ask of the State, the more power you must<br />
give it. If your demands on it are unlimited then you must<br />
logically give it unlimited power.<br />
Liberalism is fundamentally opposed to this. It believes that<br />
even when the State is a democratic one, even when it can<br />
claim to represent the will of the majority, to concentrate<br />
too much power in it is bad and dangerous. This is because,<br />
once given and whatever the promises made when it is given,<br />
there is no surety as to how that power will subsequently<br />
be used. Power, as a great liberal once said, tends to corrupt<br />
and absolute power corrupts absolutely. It is also important<br />
to remember that even if a Government does use its power in<br />
ways that the majority approves, there are still the interests<br />
of minorities to consider ( and we all, in terms of some<br />
situation or some issue, find ourselves in a minority;<br />
minorities are not simply other people).<br />
Liberals believe that it is vitally important -not in terms of<br />
abstract doctrine but in terms of the quality of life which<br />
is lived in a society that the power of the State should be<br />
limited and contained. This needs to be done by the<br />
traditional methods of checks and balances and the separation<br />
of power within Government and, in a Federal system, among<br />
Governments. It also needs to be done by maintaining vigorou;,<br />
healthy centres of power and decision-making outside Government;<br />
and, perhaps most important of all, by restraining the claims<br />
we each of us and collectively make on the State. ./ 4 </p>
<p>-4<br />
Private Enterprise System<br />
It follows that, as part of its liberalism, the Government<br />
is fundamentally committed to a private enterprise economic<br />
system. In saying this I am not, of course, talking about<br />
the completely unrestrained laissez-faire, " robber baron" form<br />
which capitalism sometimes assumed in the nineteenth century.<br />
I refer rather to a system, which, while recongising the necessity<br />
for restraint and a degree of Government intervention, is premised<br />
on the belief that what produces the best economic and political<br />
results is an economy based on private property and income, in<br />
which normal economic activity consists of commercial transactions<br />
voluntarily entered into by individuals and groups.<br />
Capitalism in practice is full of imperfections which can be<br />
legitimately criticised. Measured by standards of Utopian<br />
perfection it falls short, as does every other system devised<br />
by man. But measured against any other system on offer, or<br />
against the pre-capitalist past of Western societies, its<br />
superiority is clear.<br />
From the beginning the private enterprise economy carried with<br />
it two promises. First, it promised continued improvement<br />
in the material conditions of the whole people, a promise that<br />
was without precedent in human history. It has kept that<br />
promise. Under it, the lot of the mass of the people has<br />
improved immeasurably. For the first time in history, poverty<br />
and deprivation have become the exception rather than the rule.<br />
This capacity to improve the conditions of ordinary people is<br />
not historically exhausted or diminished. Indeed, over the<br />
last thirty years private enterprise has been responsible for<br />
an unprecedentedly rapid rise in affluence in Western countries.<br />
Remind yourselves of the lives our parents and grandparents<br />
lived, remind yourselves of the things which we now take for<br />
granted but which they considered luxuries to be striven and<br />
hoped for. The change has been revolutionary in character.<br />
Moreover, the gains are not restricted to Western countries.<br />
For the private enterprise system has also allowed those developing<br />
countries which have embraced it most thoroughly to make enormous<br />
strides, even though many of them had little in the way of<br />
natural resources on which to base their development.<br />
The private enterprise system has this demonstrated capacity.<br />
But my Government believes that even if it did not, even if<br />
its record in generating wealth was no better than that of<br />
other systems, it would still be greatly preferable to them.<br />
For the private enterprise system carried with it a second<br />
promise, the promise of much greater freedom for those living*<br />
under it. And this promise too has been kept. </p>
<p>There is an indisputable link between a private enterprise<br />
economy and political liberty. It is important that that<br />
link be properly understood. A free economic system based on<br />
private property and income does not in itself guarantee<br />
political liberty. There are unfree States with private<br />
enterprise economies. But if private enterprise is not a<br />
sufficient condition for political liberty, it is surely a<br />
necessary one. All the countries in the world which enjoy<br />
political liberty also have essentially private enterprise<br />
economic systems. On all the evidence available it is not<br />
possible to sustain political liberty without substantially<br />
free economic systems.<br />
It is important to understand why this is so. There are, it<br />
seems to me, two things which explain it. First, political<br />
liberty depends not on the good intentions and promises of the<br />
Government but on the fact that countervailing powers exist<br />
within society which set limits to the reach of Government,<br />
in practice if not in law. Such powers are ensured by the<br />
institutions of a private enterprise society, which include<br />
not just companies and private property but also free trade<br />
unions and the right to sell one's labour freely.<br />
Secondly, a private enterprise economy by its nature demands<br />
that a whole range of activities by individuals be free<br />
activities. It spreads throughout society the habits of free<br />
activity the ownership of property, the disposal of one's<br />
own income by freely-made decisions, the right to decide between<br />
security of employment and the risks and rewards of<br />
entrepreneurship, the freedom to enter into voluntary contracts.<br />
People who are free in these respects expect to be free to<br />
organise their lives in other respects and resist efforts to<br />
circumscribe that freedom.<br />
To recognise this is not, of course, to maintain that<br />
completely unregulated and uncontrolled private enterprise is<br />
desirable or possible. Governing a country is a more complex<br />
business than managing a company and, outstandingly important<br />
as it is, economic prosperity is only one of the concerns<br />
of Government. What is economically most desirable has to be<br />
weighed in the balance against other goals and in some instances<br />
has to give way to them. As Liberalism has always recognised,<br />
various freedoms have to be balanced against each other and<br />
some have to be restricted in order that others can be sustained<br />
and enlarged. Even in the economic realm itself Government<br />
has a role to play in maintaining the conditions of free<br />
competition and preventing monopoly. Above all, every societ~ y<br />
has to act to protect itself against forces which challenge<br />
the very basis of its existence. But when this is allowed for,<br />
there is still a major difference between those whose attitude<br />
towards private enterprise is dominated by suspicion, hostility<br />
and the desire to curb, and those who believe that, as private<br />
enterprise is basically conducive to both prosperity and<br />
freedom, the proper role of Government is to be as supportive!<br />
of it as circumstances and other aims permit. ./ 6 </p>
<p>-6<br />
Conservatism I have stressed the commitment of the Government to.<br />
liberal principles and values.' Precisely because of that<br />
commitment it is also concerned to conserve and protect<br />
those principles and values. once liberal institutions are<br />
installed in a society, a Government which wishes to preserve<br />
them must be in some sense conservative. But it is important<br />
to stress that in this context conservatism is not about the<br />
guarding of privilege and inequality but about maintaining<br />
the open, liberal society against both internal and external<br />
threat.<br />
At the same time, however, there is always a certain tension<br />
involved between liberalism and conservatism. Liberalism<br />
always emphasises the freedom of the individual and the absence<br />
of restraint. In its extreme form it becomes libertarianism<br />
and denies the need or efficacy of any constraints on freedom.<br />
Conservatism on the other hand stresses the need for a<br />
C framework of stability, continuity and order, not only as<br />
something desirable in itself but-as a necessary condition<br />
for a free society. It believes that, without that framework,<br />
the cohesion and predictability necessary for people to engage,<br />
in meaningful free activity would be lacking. The art of<br />
handling this tension, of finding that creative balance between<br />
the forces of freedom and the forces of continuity which alone<br />
allows a society to advance, is the true art of Government<br />
in a country like ours.<br />
It is important to bear all this in mind in contemplating<br />
one of the striking political phenomena of our time, the<br />
resurgence of conservatism as a philosophical position in<br />
the Western democracies. In the view of the Government, that<br />
response does not represent a passing fashion or trend but a<br />
considered and serious realisation that central institutions<br />
and values are under threat. It is a reaction to two phenomena.<br />
K First it expresses the accumulated disillusionment which has<br />
grown in these communities concerning Socialist and radical<br />
Left doctrines which have long claimed intellectual and moral,<br />
superiority, but which, having been put to the test, either<br />
do not work at all or produce unintended consequences which<br />
outweigh' their supposed benefits. Planning which creates<br />
confusion and waste;. ill-conceived welfare schemes which<br />
create monstrous bureaucracies, high taxes and high inflation;<br />
nationalised industries which fail to deliver the goods or<br />
services they were established to provide while making increasing<br />
demands on the taxpayer for support; attempts to help<br />
minorities which succeed only in creating a new dependency; a<br />
concern for the environment which degenerates into ritual<br />
and dogma these are among the effects of those doctrines. / 17 </p>
<p>-7-<br />
Secondly, this resurgence of conservatism expresses a<br />
concern to maintain continuity and coherence, to-restore<br />
human control, in a world which has been subjected to<br />
massive and rapid changes. And the changes which Western<br />
societies have experienced in the last 30 years have indeed<br />
been massive. I have already referred to the unprecedented<br />
increase in affluence, which of course entails great changes<br />
in life styles. In the same period we have witnessed mass<br />
tertiary education for the first time in history; a profound<br />
change in relation between the sexes and in the institution<br />
of the family; changes in the relations between-the<br />
generations; a new attitude towards our physical environmentp,<br />
towards minorities, towards moral standards. One could go<br />
on multiplying examples.<br />
The new conservatism is largely a response to the challenge<br />
posed by all this. It is not a frightened response, not<br />
reactionary, not a " radical right" phenomenon though there<br />
are attempts to confuse it with that. The new conservatism<br />
is not opposed to change as such. On the contrary, it is<br />
concerned to allow it. But it is concerned that the'process<br />
of change should not proceed in such a headlong and<br />
illconsidered fashion that it yields unexpected and undesired<br />
consequences, rather than welcome ones. It is concerned to<br />
preserve continuity, to ensure that hard-won gains are not<br />
carelessly lost, to integrate elements of the old and the new.<br />
It is concerned to ensure that, while the enterprise of those<br />
who initiate desired change is encouraged, those who suffer<br />
loss as a result of it either materially or spiritually<br />
are given some protection and help to adjust to new<br />
circumstances. To the extent that this Government is<br />
conservative, it is so in these senses and for these reasons,<br />
not because it is concerned to protect privilege and inequality.<br />
Summary I have set out what are the central principles and values of<br />
the Government. Let me briefly sum them up.<br />
The Government is concerned to maximise the degree<br />
to which people have control over their own lives and<br />
' their own resources, to. ensure that it is their choices<br />
which are decisive, not those of politicians, of.<br />
bureaucrats or union officials or corporations.<br />
To this end the Government is concerned to limit<br />
the role and reduce the power of the State, and as<br />
part of that to restrain taxes and to contain public<br />
expenditure. The State must remain the servant, not<br />
the master, of the Australian people.<br />
The Government is committed to supporting and<br />
strengthening the private enterprise system in<br />
Australia both because it believes-that this system<br />
is the one that can best develop Australia and ensure<br />
its prosperity, and because it is that system and that<br />
system alone which is compatible with a free, liberal<br />
Australia. a0./ 8 </p>
<p>8<br />
SLast, in an age of turbulence and innovation, the<br />
Government is concerned that the process of change<br />
shall be a deliberate and considered one and that<br />
those things which most Australians value highly<br />
are not lost or damaged in the process.<br />
These are the principles which will guide the Government over<br />
the next three years. I stress the word guide. What I have<br />
outlined is not a dogma or a creed to be adhered to regardless<br />
of circumstances. In times of great complexity, the supreme<br />
virtue of Government is not slavish adherence to a creed, but<br />
good judgement and balance, which enable the diverse and<br />
sometimes competing creative forces in society to contribute<br />
to the general welfare.<br />
In concluding I return to the point I made at the outset: that<br />
these philosophical questions are not peripheral ones, not,<br />
as parts of the press have sought to present them, a matter<br />
of PR. They are central and we will ignore them at our peril.<br />
I began by quoting Keynes. I end by quoting another great<br />
economist and political philosopher, the Nobel Prize winner<br />
Professor Hayek. Hayek writes:<br />
" Those who have concerned themselves exclusively<br />
with what seemed practicable in the existing state<br />
of opinion have constantly found that even this has<br />
rapidly become politically_ impossible as the result<br />
of changes in a public opinion which they have done<br />
nothing to guide. Unless we can make the<br />
philosophical foundations of a free society once more<br />
a living intellectual issue, and its implementation<br />
a task which challenges the ingenuity and imagination<br />
of our liveliest minds, the prospects of freedom<br />
are indeed dark."<br />
I say amen to that. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
