<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9190</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATIGNG, MP VISIT TO LAOS, THAILAND AND VIETNAM</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/04/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009190.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
STATMENT BY THE PRIME MIINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING, MP<br />
VISIT TO LAOS, THAILAND AND VIETNAM<br />
On this visit to Laos, Thailand and Vietnam new<br />
understandings and agreements have been reached. our<br />
relationship with the dynamic economies of Thailand and<br />
Vietnam has been put on a new plane. The foundations of<br />
regional security have been strengthened.<br />
These were the objectives of my visit. They were the<br />
objectives because it is on these things which the<br />
interests of our country depend the interests of this<br />
and future generations of Australians.<br />
On them also depend, to no small extent, the well being<br />
of the countries of the region and their peoples.<br />
This visit has gone some considerable way towards<br />
advancing the interests of Australia.<br />
On this, as on other visits, I recognise that the office<br />
requires that I be Prime Minister, not just for<br />
Australians of this generation and future ones but for<br />
past generations of Australians.<br />
Wherever possible, I have made it my practice to visit<br />
those places abroad which are sacred to the memory of<br />
Australians. That is why in Thailand I went to Kanchanaburi and Hell<br />
Fire Pass. While there I made mention of those who<br />
served and died in Vietnam because they occupy the same<br />
esteemed place in our national memory as those who are<br />
buried in Thailand, but it was not possible in Vietnam to<br />
visit a place where Australians who served are buried.<br />
We did not seek a memorial service in Vietnam principally<br />
because we decided there was no suitable place in Vietnam<br />
to conduct one, and also because I did not think it<br />
appropriate, while in Vietnam, to revive bitter memories. </p>
<p>2<br />
I am dismayed by the misrepresentation of my views on<br />
this matter. The war was a trauma at the centre of our<br />
national life for more than a decade, no one who lived<br />
through that period can fail to have been affected by it<br />
but, equally, as I have said before, no one who did not<br />
live through the war itself can know what it was like.<br />
What we do know is what I said at the inauguration of the<br />
Vietnam Memorial in Canberra and repeated at Kanchanaburi<br />
that those who died in Vietnam died with the same faith<br />
in Australia, with the same courage, the same willingness<br />
to lay down their lives for their country as those who<br />
died in other wars.<br />
It was for this reason that the Government completed the<br />
Memorial. The Memorial and what was said there on the<br />
day of its inauguiation finally brought Vietnam veterans<br />
in from the cold. It ensured that they received for the<br />
first time their proper recognition.<br />
In Vietnam the war still weighs heavily on the lives of<br />
the people. Economic sanctions and the isolation of the<br />
country have kept it impoverished and underdeveloped.<br />
The wounds of war are far from healed.<br />
I came here to lay the foundation of a mutually rewarding<br />
friendship between our two countries. I came to South-<br />
East Asia to hand over to Laos and Thailand the<br />
Friendship Bridge. I came in pursuit of a new creative<br />
partnership with the region.<br />
I am the first Australian Prime Minister to visit Hanoi.<br />
As I said there on Monday night, I will certainly not be<br />
the last.<br />
In the future Australian Prime Ministers will come to<br />
Vietnam regularly. And when they do, like me, they will<br />
remember those who suffered and died in that terrible<br />
conflict of the sixties and seventies -and I confidently<br />
expect that in due course they will be able to remember<br />
them at a suitable memorial.<br />
HO CHI MINH CITY<br />
12 APRIL 1994 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
