<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3003</transcript-id>
    <title>UNITED NATIONS GENERAL ASSEMBLY - TWENTY-EIGHTH SESSION: AUSTRALIAN DELEGATION</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/09/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003003.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
NQ DATE<br />
M/ 129 11 September 1973<br />
UNITED NATIONS GENT7RAL ASSEMBLY<br />
T'IENTY-EIGHTH SESSION: AUSTRALIAN DELEGAT1ION<br />
0 The Prime Minister and Minister for Foreign Affairs,<br />
Mr Whitlam, today confirmed that the Special Minister of State<br />
and Minister Assisting the Minister for Foreign Affairs, Senator<br />
Willesee, would lead the Australian delegation to the United<br />
Nations General Assembly, which begins in New York on Tuesday<br />
18 September. While in New York from 26 September to 5 October,<br />
S Senator Willesee will address the Assembly during the General<br />
Debate on 3 October 1973. He will call on the Secretary-General,<br />
Dr Waldheim, and meet other Ministers and delegation leaders for<br />
discussions on matters of mutual interest concerning the United<br />
Nations and other aspects of foreign policy.<br />
Mr Whitlam said that the work of the General Assembly<br />
is conducted in Plenary Session and in seven main committees,<br />
in all of which Australia is involved.<br />
Australia is currently a member of the Security Council<br />
which often meets during the General Assembly and it will be </p>
<p>-2-<br />
Australia's turn to be President of the Council for the month of<br />
October 1973. The General Assembly will have before it over 100 items<br />
including a number of matters of special interest such as the<br />
organisation of a Law of the Sea Conference next year, Korea, and<br />
the urgent need for action to end nuclear testing.<br />
The 25th anniversary of the Universal Declaration of<br />
Human Rights will be celebrated during the Assembly on 10 December<br />
and the Assembly will consider a wide range of issues relating to<br />
human rights, decolonisation and economic development.<br />
As in the past, two members of Parliament have been<br />
included in the delegation. This year the Hon. R. V. Garland<br />
( Liberal, Curtin and Dr R. E. Klugman ( Labor, Prospect,<br />
will attend.<br />
Mr Whitlam said that as was customary two Papua New<br />
Guinean advisers would join the delegation later in the Session<br />
to assist with agenda items of interest to Papua New Guinea,<br />
The two advisers will be members of the House of Assembly and<br />
will be assisted by Papua New Guinean officials.<br />
The Australian delegation is as follows:<br />
Representatives Senator The Honourable Don Willesee,<br />
Snecial Minister of State and Minister Assisting the<br />
Minister for Foreign Affairs.<br />
Leader of the Delegation. 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
H. E. Sir Laurence McIntyre, C. B. E.,<br />
Ambassador Extraordinary and Plenipotentiary,<br />
Permanent Representative to the United Nations.<br />
H. E. Mr J. Petherbridge,<br />
Ambassador,<br />
Australian Embassy, Stockholm.<br />
Mr A. D. Campbell,<br />
Minister, Australian Mission to the<br />
United Nations, New York.<br />
Mr J. R. Kelso,<br />
Assistant Secretary,<br />
United Nations International<br />
Department of Foreign Affairs. Agencies Branch,<br />
Parliamentary Advisers<br />
The Honourable RV. Garland, M. P,<br />
Dr R. E. Kiugman, M. P.<br />
Alternate Representatives<br />
Mr L. L. E. Joseph,<br />
Counsellor, Permanent Mission to the United<br />
Mr H. C. Mott,<br />
Counsellor, Permanent Mission to the United<br />
Mr J. Bailey,<br />
Legal and Treaties Branch,<br />
Department of Foreign Affairs.<br />
Mr M. Curtin,<br />
First Secretary,<br />
Permanent Mission<br />
Mr R. Wyndham,<br />
First Secretary,<br />
Permanent Mission Nations. Nations.<br />
to the United Nations.<br />
to the United Nations.<br />
Advisers<br />
Mr J. Campbell,<br />
First Secretary,<br />
Permanent Mission tothe United Nations.<br />
Miss I. Svenne,<br />
First Secretary,<br />
Australian Embassy, Belgrade. </p>
<p>-4-<br />
Mr J. P. McCarthy,<br />
First Secretary,<br />
Australiam Embassy, Washington.<br />
Mr J. A. Tilemann,<br />
Private Secretary to the Special Minister of State and<br />
Minister Assisting the Minister for Foreign Affairs.<br />
Mr G. Urwin,<br />
Second Secretary,<br />
Australian High Commission, Ottawa.<br />
Mr H. Bamsey,<br />
Third Secretary,<br />
Australian High Commission, London.<br />
Dr B. Martin,<br />
Third Secretary,<br />
Australian Consulate-General, San Francisco.<br />
Mr P. Reid,<br />
Third Secretary,<br />
Permanent Mission to the United Nations.<br />
Mr R. Harris,<br />
Press Officer,<br />
Director, A. I. S.,<br />
Australian Consulate-General, New York. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
