<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3359</transcript-id>
    <title>ROYAL COMMISSION INTO THE INTELLIGENCE AND SECURITY SERVICES OF THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/08/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003359.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Jp_ AUSTRAIIjA<br />
PRIME MOME PRESS STATEMENT NO. 305<br />
21 August 1974<br />
ROYAL COMMISSION INTO THE INTELLIG~ ENCE AND SECUR~ ITY SERVICES<br />
OF THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr. Whitlam, announced today<br />
that His Excellency the Governor-General had, on the advice<br />
of the Executive Council, appointed Mr. Justice Hope of the<br />
Supreme Court of New South Wales as a Royal Commissioner to<br />
inquire into Australia's intelligence and security services.<br />
A copy of the terms of reference for the inquiry<br />
is attached. The Prime Minister recalled that in his policy speech<br />
on 29 April he had given an undertaking that the Government would,<br />
if returned, appoint a judicial inquiry into the structure of the<br />
Australian security services and into methods of reviewing<br />
decisions adversely affecting citizens or migrants.<br />
The Commission to Mr. Justice Hope will fulfil both<br />
parts of the election promise.<br />
The inquiry will cover the whole range of Australia's<br />
intelligence and security services and so will provide the first<br />
comprehensive review that has been undertaken of these services<br />
since the inception of the varicus organisations during the<br />
1940s. The Commissioner will be asked to review the history<br />
of the services and, having regard to the security of Australia<br />
as a nation, the rights and responsibilities of individual persons<br />
and future as well as present needs, to make recommendations on<br />
the services the people and Government of Australia should have<br />
available to them.<br />
Paragraph 3 of the terms of reference will ensure that<br />
the inquiry covers fully the important aspects of the civil rights<br />
of individuals as they can be affected by administrative decisions<br />
based on or influenced by security reports. The Commissioner is<br />
asked to suggest ways in which administrative decisions of this<br />
kind can be reviewed. His inquiries will extend to the protection<br />
which should * be afforded not only to citizens but also t9 migrants<br />
and visitors. </p>
<p>The inquiry will also cover the important matter of<br />
ensuring that there is full responsibility at Ministerial and<br />
official level for the intelligence and security organisations<br />
and actions undertaken by them.<br />
The Prime Minister said he expected that, because of<br />
its nature, a large part of the proceedings of the Commission<br />
would have to be conducted in closed session. He recalled that<br />
the Royal Commission into the Canadian security services had been<br />
directed to hold all its proceedings incamera. The Commissioner<br />
would advise the Government as to which parts, if any, of the<br />
report might be made public.<br />
The appointment of a Judge with qualifications as<br />
eminent as those of Mr. Justice Hope guaranteed that the inquiry<br />
would be well conducted, comprehensive and responsible and at<br />
the same time would reassure those countries and organisations<br />
with which Australia has connections in the security field.<br />
Mr. Justice Hope was appointed to the Supreme Court<br />
of New South Wales in 1969. He became a member of the Court<br />
of Appeal in 1972. He was President of the Australian Council<br />
for Civil Liberties between 1967 and 1969.<br />
Mr. Whitlam said he wished to express his own thanks,<br />
and those of the Government, to the Premier, Chief Justice<br />
and Attorney-General of New South Wales for their courtesy; and<br />
co-operation in agreeing that Mr. Justice Hope should be available<br />
to undertake this important inquiry.<br />
CANBERRA, A. C. T. </p>
<p>INQUIRY INTO INTELLIGENCE AND SECURITY<br />
SERVICES OF THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT<br />
Terms of Reference<br />
make the following inquiries, reports and recommendations,<br />
including inquiries and reports on all matters relevant to the<br />
making of those recommendations:-<br />
1. To inquire into and report upon the history of the<br />
intelligence and security services of the Australian<br />
Government, with particular reference to<br />
purpose, functions, administration and staffing<br />
( including recruiting) of each organization;<br />
the general co-ordination, control and direction<br />
of the services taken as a whole;<br />
the use made by the Australian Government and<br />
its agencies of the information provided by the<br />
organizations.<br />
2. In the light of past experience, and having regard to the<br />
security of Australia as a nation, the rights and<br />
responsibilities of individual persons and future as well<br />
as present needs, to make recommendations on the<br />
intelligence and security services which the nation<br />
should have available to it and on the way in which the<br />
relevant organizations can most efficiently and<br />
effectively serve the interests of the Australian<br />
people and Government, with particular reference tothe<br />
scale of operationsthe<br />
number of separate organizations to be<br />
involved, and their purpose, functions,<br />
staffing ( including recruiting and terms and<br />
conditions of service) and administrative<br />
arrangements; the nature and scope of the intelligence which<br />
the relevant organizations should seek to<br />
acquire from Australian sources or from sources<br />
outside Australia, including the intelligence<br />
services of other countries;<br />
arrangements for co-ordinating and evaluating<br />
the available intelligence;.<br />
the distribution and use of the intelligence<br />
material available-,<br />
the relationship between the intelligence<br />
organizations, between those organizations and<br />
the Australian and State law enforcement<br />
agencies and between those organizations and<br />
Departments and authorities of the Australian<br />
Government; / 2 </p>
<p>2.<br />
the degree of secrecy which should attach to<br />
the organizations and their work; and<br />
the proper safeguarding of intelligence material<br />
and sources and the channel through which advice<br />
on such matters should be provided.<br />
3. To make recommendations as to the procedures which should<br />
be introduced to permit review of administrative decisions<br />
affecting citizens, migrants and visitors which were or<br />
may have been based on, or influenced by, reports or<br />
information of an adverse kind furnished by the security<br />
intelligence services of the Australian Government.<br />
4. To review the machinery for Ministerial and official<br />
control, direction and co-ordination of the<br />
activities of the intelligence and security services<br />
and make recommendations on any changes desirable, in<br />
particular to ensure that there are clear lines of<br />
responsibility and proper arrangements for<br />
accountability for funds.<br />
To make recommendations on any other matters in<br />
relation to intelligence and security services to<br />
which the attention of the Commission is directed<br />
by the Prime Minister in the course of the inquiry." </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
