<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>382</transcript-id>
    <title>SECOND READING SPEECH, CANBERRA, - COAL LOADING WORKS AGREEMENT (NEW SOUTH WALES) BILL 1961</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/10/1961</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000382_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>SECOND READING SPEECH<br />by<br />THE PRIME MINISTER. THE RT. HON. R. G. MENZIES<br />IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES, CANBERRA, THURSDAY. 19TH OCTOBER. 1961<br />COAL LOADING WORKS AGREEMENT ( NEW SOUTH vJALES') BILL, 1961.<br />The purpose of this Bill is to obtain the approval of Parliament to an<br />Agreement between the Commowealth and the State of New South Wales providing<br />for finp~ ncial assistance to the State towards the cost of installing improved,<br />coal loading facilities at the ports of Newcastle, Port Kembla and Balmain.<br />This project is one of the major State works to which 1 have referred<br />before as being projects which should make a significant contribution to the<br />promotion of increased export earnings. Increased and diversified exports are<br />essential. The ex Port of coal overseas from New South ,, ales has expanded notably<br />in the last three years and is already making an important contribution to<br />Australiats balance of payments. During 1960461, over 1.9 million tons valued<br />at about E7.4. million were exported through the three ports concerned in the<br />present project. The exports wore shipped mainly to Japan, to meet the<br />requirements of that country' s rapidly growing industries. There are good<br />prospects of a further substantial increase in the trade. Forecasts based on<br />studies of Japan's future coal requirements and discussions with Japanese<br />industrialists indicate that coal exports from the New South Wales ports coul4<br />increase to œ l2million per annum within a few years and to over œ l6million pe~ r<br />annum. in this decade. These exports will be possible without prejudicing in<br />any way the needs of the Australian steel industry. In addition to the<br />valuable export earnings which can be expected, the New South WJales coal<br />industry and the coal mining districts should bene fit directly in many ways<br />from the wider market for New South Wales coal.<br />The expansion in coal exports which is in sight cannot materialise,<br />however, unless the facilities for loading coal at the ports are improved and<br />the improvements are complete-d in the shortest practicable time The trade is<br />very competitive. The overseas buyers might turn to other sources for their<br />coal requirements if they thought that the New South Wales ports would not be<br />able in a few yearst time to provide adequate and economical facilities for co4<br />shipments. Of primary importance is the need to deepen the harbours and berths<br />to receive the larger vessels now coming into use in the coal export trade.<br />Larger vessels offer significant freight advantages. Coal exports are expected<br />to be carried increasingly in ships of 25,000 tons capacity and upwards as<br />compared with the present 10,000 to 12,000 tons. Equally important is the need<br />for modern equipment at the wharves, capable of loading coal at reasonably fast<br />rates, so that the full benefit of larger ships can be gained through quick<br />turn-around and reduced harbour and wharfage dues. Faster loading equipment at<br />the wharves necads, in turn, adequate storage and access facilities to maintain<br />the supply of coal to the loaders.<br />The New South W-, ales Government has a full realisation of the problems<br />associated with the expansion of coal exports and the trend towards larger<br />vessels. For some time it has been studying the prospective volume of the<br />trade and planning the facilities required to handle it. The maintenance and<br />development of ports is a State responsibility and the Commorwealth Government<br />has no intention of intruding into State rights and responsibilities in this<br />field. In the present case, however, the expansion of exports in prospect was<br />sufficiently important for the Government to believe it had an obligation to<br />inform itself about the progress being made by New South Wales and to<br />ascertain whether there was any way in which the Commonwealth could help in<br />the carrying out of the project.<br />lt became apparent during the discussions which took place with the<br />New South Wales Government that the Commonwealth could make it possible to<br />reduce materially the time taken to complete the work. Without outside<br />financial assistance, New South ' ales could not undertake to construct the<br />works at all three ports simultaneously. It would be necessary to spread out<br />the works over a pcriod of about six years and to complete some sections of the</p>
<p>total programme before starting on others. -rven this programme could have<br />been delayed for financial reasons. Financial assistance from the<br />Commorwealth, on the othar hand, would make it possible to compresF the<br />timetable by removing financial obstacles to the completion of the port<br />facilities in the shortest time practicable on engineering and other physical<br />grounds. This is estimiated at 3 to 4 years, and the shorter construction<br />period could make a significant difference to Australiat s ability to secure<br />favourable export contracts.<br />The outcome of the discussions between the Commonwealth and the<br />State was a formal submission by the New South Wales Premier of estimated copts<br />and of proposals concerning the way in which Commonwealth financial assitance<br />might be put to best use. On the basis of his submission and the detailed<br />knowledge of the programme which had been gained during the discussions, a<br />Commonwealth offer was formulated and was accepted by the State.<br />The main features of the assistance agreed upon were described in a<br />statement which I i~ sued on 29th August. The New South Wales Government<br />undertook to ensure that a prcgramme of work, involving the spending of some<br />œ 10,660,000 on three harbours, would be carried out as expeditiously as<br />praz-ticable and that the funds necessary for that purpose would be provided as<br />required. The total programme includes the deepening of harbours and the<br />provision of deep water berths as well as the installation of coal loading<br />plant and related works. The Commonwealth, for its part, undertook to<br />provide financial assistance to New South ' dales in respect of the coal loading<br />plant, including the associated wharfage, storage, road and rail facilities,<br />up to half the estimated cost of the coal loading w~ orks, that is, up to an<br />amount of œ 2,650,000. The Commonwealth assistance is to be provided on a F,<br />f or Z matching expenditure basis with the State, up to individual maxima of<br />œ 1,500,000 at Newcastle, œ 1,070,000 at Port Kembla and E80,000 at Balmain.<br />Out of the total Commonvealth assistance, up to E1,000,000 is to be<br />made available from the Coal Industry Fund of the Joint Coal Board. As I<br />pointed out in my statement of 29th August, any assistance which the<br />Commowealth might provide to revenue-producing works of this kind would<br />normally take the form entirely of repayable advances, In this case, however,<br />we had regard to the uncertainties in the costs of works of this magnitude and<br />in the estima~ tes of the eventual volume of coal exports through these ports.<br />The State naturally accepts whatever risks are involved in these respects,<br />but the Commowealth has been anxious to give the State all reasonable support<br />and decided to make part of the assistance available by way of grant. This<br />will also serve to reduce the charges which would otherwise be levied for the<br />use of the new facilities.<br />The remaining part of the assistance, amounting to up to<br />œ 650,000, is proposed to be made available by the Commonwealth in the form<br />of advances repayable by the State. Negotiations have been conducted between<br />the Commonwealth and State Governments on the terms and conditions of the<br />repayable advances and a formal Agreement has been drawn up and signed on<br />behalf of each Government. It is the Bill to give effect to that Agreement<br />which is now before the House for approval.<br />The Bill itself is brief and provides mainly for approval of the<br />Agreement and for appropriations from the Consolidated Revenue Fund for<br />advances to be made by the Commonwealth in accordance with the Agreement.<br />The Agreement is set out as the Schedule to the Bill and its<br />contents may be summarised as follows;<br />The preamble is, in effect, a brief description of the reasons for<br />and the nature of, the whole Commowealth financial assistance, including the<br />grant element as well as the repayable advances. The arrangements for the<br />grant assistance referred to in paragraph of the preamble are straightforward<br />and do not require further approval. They are simply that when the<br />State applies for funds, it will apply for grants as well as advances in the<br />same manner and supported by the same kind of evidence of expenditure. The<br />Commowealth will arrange for payments to be made to the State in the<br />proportions of grants to a&amp;'-ances set out in paragraph of the preamble.</p>
<p>The terms and conditions of the repayable advances are given in detail in the<br />body of the A'greement.<br />Clauses 4 and 5 of the Agreement provide for the making of advances<br />by the Commonwealth to the State up to the amounts specified either as<br />reimbursements of expenditure ailready made by the State or, if the Treasurer<br />approves, in anticipation of expenditure to be made, on or in connection with<br />the coal loading works. The advances are to bear interest at 5 3% per annum<br />and are to be repayable in 10 years by 20 semi-annual payments. The State<br />undertakes in clause 9 to carry out the coal l. oading works with o view to their<br />completion as part of the harbour works at the earliest practicable date,<br />subject to the Commonwealth providing financial assistance as agreed. Th2<br />remaining provisions relate to variation of the schedule of works, the provision<br />of estimates, the supply of information, audit and the giving of notices. A<br />description of the works is set out in the Schedule to the A greement under two<br />headings, the harbour works and the coal loading works.<br />I conclude by emphasising that the programme which the New South Wales<br />Government has embarked upon is an important contribution to the expansion of<br />the export trade. Some of the work has already begun and other sections are in<br />an edvanced stage of preparation. At Balmain, dredging has been completed anq<br />tenders have been received for the new coal loading facilities. At NewcaqtlQ,<br />tenders have been called on a world-wide basis for the removal of rock from the<br />bar at the harbour entrance and it is proposed to dredge the leads and channels<br />and the berths, to provide a depth of at least 36 feet of water to -the coal<br />loading plant. It is planned that the coal loading plant will be able to load<br />at a rate which is yet to be dotermined but which will be at least 1500 tons an<br />hour as provided for in the schedule to the Agreement. At Port Kembla, planning<br />is well in hand for the construction of a coal berth on a new site in the<br />Inner Harbour and tenders have been called for a loader with a capacity of.<br />2,000 tons an hour. The plans include the provision of adeo ' uate storage and<br />access to the wharf and the deepening of the berth to at least 36 feet of water.<br />The Commonwealth Government is satisfied that the installation of<br />these works will permit the coal export trade to be maintained and expanded and<br />that financial assistance from the Commonwealth in the manner proposed will<br />contribute importantly to their early completion.<br />I have grent pleasure in commending the Bill to the Hou3e.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
