<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1900</transcript-id>
    <title>ABORIGINAL AFFAIRS ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE RT HON. JOHN GORTON AT THE CONFERNCE OF COMMONWEALTH AND STATE MINISTERS RESPONSIBLE FOR ABORIGINAL AFFAIRS AT PARLIAMENT HOUSE, MELBOURNE</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/07/1968</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001900.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
ABORIGINAL AFFAIRS<br />
ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE RI HON. JOHN GORTON<br />
AT THE CONFERENCE OF COMMONWEALTH AND STATE<br />
MINISTERS RESPONSIBLE FOR ABORIGINAL AFFAIRS<br />
AT PARLIAMENT HOUSE, MELBOURNE .~ 4i<br />
12 July 1968<br />
AS a result of the 1967 Referendum the Commonwealth now shares with the<br />
States powers and responsibilities for the advancement of our Aboriginals.<br />
In fact, of course, the powers of the Commonwealth are paramount in the<br />
sense that in any conflict of law its law will prevail, but there is no such<br />
conflict at present and I have every confidence that none will arise. We are all<br />
of us trying to do our best to advance our Aboriginals and I believe that we can<br />
do this between us in an atmosphere of goodwill, and irrespective of whether<br />
we are using a State or a Federal power.<br />
Each State has a different problem-different numbers of Aboriginalsdifferent<br />
levels of development-different priorities.<br />
I take this'opportunity of congratulating the States on the vigour of their<br />
approach to the question of Aboriginal welfare which has been manifest in their<br />
policies over recent years. We recognise this and are ready and willing to play<br />
our part, in full co-operation with the States, in the task of improving the pace<br />
of our advance.<br />
It will be recalled that the late Prime Minister, Mr Holt, had already made<br />
some significant moves in this matter before his tragic death. He had appointed<br />
a Commonwealth Council for Aboriginal Affairs, and had set up an Office of<br />
Aboriginal Affairs within his own Department. It was as part of this plan that<br />
the important conference of Federal and State officers was held early this year<br />
to consider the whole Aboriginal situation.<br />
At the end of February, I appointed the Hon. W. C. Wentworth especially<br />
responsible to me for the development of Commonwealth policy and its cooperation<br />
with that of the States and he is the Minister who will be working<br />
directly with you.<br />
Leaving aside the specific Commonwealth responsibilities for Federal Territories<br />
I believe that the Minister and the Council, in their relations with the<br />
States, should seek to discharge three main functions: </p>
<p>1. To allocate funds from the Commonwealth to the State for Aboriginal<br />
advancement, using State machinery to use these funds for an agreed<br />
purpose to the greatest possible extent.<br />
2. To gather information regarding Aboriginal matters ( especially welfare)<br />
and to act as a clearing house for such information both as between the<br />
various States and as between States and Commonwealth.<br />
3. Where appropriate to assist the States in the co-ordination of their policy<br />
and in setting the general direction of the Australian approach to<br />
Aboriginal advancement.<br />
We propose to give the fullest co-operation to the States, and I am sure we<br />
will get the fullest co-operation in return.<br />
Our ultimate objective is, of course, the assimilation of Aboriginal Australians<br />
as fully effective members of a single Australian society. This policy was enunciated<br />
by the 1965 Conference between the States and the Commonwealth on<br />
Aboriginal affairs and, from the Aboriginal viewpoint, there is nothing arbitrary<br />
about it. I think I should quote again the exact text there decided upon:<br />
' The policy of assimilation seeks that all persons of Aboriginal descent<br />
will choose to attain a similar manner and standard of living to that of<br />
other Australians, and live as members of a single Australian community.'<br />
In other words, without destroying Aboriginal culture, we want to help our<br />
Aboriginals to become an integral part of the rest of the Australian people, and<br />
we want the Aboriginals themselves to have a voice in the pace at which this<br />
process occurs.<br />
We will measure policy proposals against this objective, and will wish to<br />
avoid measures which are likely to set Aboriginal citizens permanently apart<br />
from other Australians through having their development based upon separate<br />
or different standards.<br />
We believe that if Aboriginal Australians can be helped, and encouraged to<br />
help themselves, to develop their aptitudes more fully, to accept further responsibility<br />
for their own individual activities, to become self-supporting and thus<br />
re-acquire their dignity of life-that then they will be readily attracted to and<br />
welcomed to the assimilation we aim for. In this way they could contribute<br />
from their own traditional culture to the complex of influences so diverse in<br />
origin which makes up our national life, and, while sharing in this complex,<br />
continue to take pride in their own contribution to it.<br />
However, we recognise that, despite progress over the last quarter-century,<br />
many Aboriginal Australians are subject to special handicaps which impede<br />
their advancement. We are ready, therefore, to support additional action designed<br />
to help Aboriginals overcome these handicaps in the transitional phase.<br />
We propose to assist State policies directed towards these ends in three<br />
specific areas: Health Education Housing </p>
<p>We have already had some information from the States on these aspects,<br />
and we hope that some general principles in relation to them will be discussed<br />
at this Conference. This will enable us to make definite arrangements with each<br />
of the States without delay under each of these three headings.<br />
We recognise that the needs of different States will need to be met in<br />
different ways, so that a co-ordinated Australian policy need not be a uniform<br />
one. It is because of this that we feel it is preferable to make individual arrangements<br />
with the various States on the basis of the general principles which may<br />
emerge from discussions at this Conference.<br />
After we have received detailed proposals from the various States, and after<br />
our own Budget has been brought down, we shall indicate to each State the way<br />
in which we think we can best assist and the funds available for such assistance.<br />
In dividing the available funds between the States, we shall get some guidance<br />
from the size of their Aborginal populations, although we may not always conform<br />
strictly to this rule.<br />
Any amounts contributed by the Commonwealth will be in addition to the<br />
normal annual allocations made at Premiers' Conferences and Loan Councils,<br />
but we expect any Commonwealth assistance to be a net addition to and not in<br />
substitution for any amount which would otherwise be spent by a State upon<br />
Aboriginal welfare. And this will be a condition of the grant.<br />
SWhile we believe that the major part of the application of this welfare policy<br />
within each State should be done by the State Administration concerned, this<br />
does not preclude the possibility of some independent Commonwealth action.<br />
Clearly, in any such instance, we shall consult the States concerned before we<br />
undertake any such measures within their boundaries.<br />
It is clear that our Aboriginal population is now not only increasing, but is<br />
also increasing at a faster rate than the Australian average. Unhappily, the<br />
additional population is not yet self-supporting, but remains in large part<br />
dependent upon charity, Social Service benefits and similar benefits. The continuance<br />
of such a state of affairs is obviously incompatible with the general<br />
concept of Aboriginal dignity which we all seek to foster. It should be a primary<br />
aim of our policy to make our Aboriginals self-supporting as fully and as<br />
quickly as possible. They are entitled to have the opportunity to attain their<br />
economic independence. And indeed effective assimilation is dependent upon<br />
Aboriginal citizens being able to stand on their own feet.<br />
We are aware of, and welcome, the interest both of the States and of Church<br />
and other organisations working towards this objective, and we propose to reinforce<br />
what they are doing.<br />
We have therefore approved in principle the provision of a Fund for special<br />
assistance, including capital funds, for potentially viable enterprises to be established<br />
for or by Aboriginals either indvidually or co-operatively. Provision of<br />
such funds will not, of course, be unlimited or indiscriminate, and we shall be<br />
glad of any comments which this conference may make upon the way in which<br />
we should administer them. In due course we would hope to obtain advice and<br />
help from the appropriate State authorities before approving any particular projects<br />
within their boundaries. </p>
<p>This capital assistance will be available on an Australia-wide basis, and will<br />
be controlled by the Commonwealth through its Office of Aboriginal Affairs.<br />
We regard this proposal as an essential part of our policy of assisting our<br />
Aboriginals to become self-supporting, whether it be in the field of primary or<br />
secondary industry. In parallel with this, the Commonwealth Department of<br />
Labour and National Service will undertake detailed surveys of employment<br />
opportunities for Aboriginals and of the necessary measures to expand them<br />
and to provide incentives for Aboriginals to take them up. In this, we shall hope<br />
to work with the fullest co-operation of the corresponding State machinery.<br />
In short, we propose to apply ourselves constructively to the task of<br />
Aboriginal advancement, with special emphasis upon making our Aboriginal<br />
citizens independent. We shall rely very largely upon the State administrations<br />
and we are ready to receive and evaluate any suggestions which the States may<br />
make to us, either at this conference or subsequently.<br />
Over the short term, the kind of proposals we envisage will undoubtedly increase<br />
our outlay upon Aboriginal welfare, but in proportion as our policy succeeds<br />
( and I believe, between us, it has every chance of success) our outlay will<br />
diminish. In spite of the extra outlay initially involved, I consider this policy to<br />
be not just an extension of the ' hand-out' principle, but in fact the very antithesis.<br />
Finally, may I add that we have noted the efforts being made by the States<br />
to involve Aboriginals themselves in the administration of their own affairs and<br />
in the exercise of proper authority among their own people. This is also an<br />
essential part of restoring Aboriginal motivation. We welcome these efforts, and<br />
will ourselves emulate them.<br />
We feel too that this Conference should now be established on an annual<br />
basis, and the Commonwealth would be pleased next year to act as the host for<br />
it, should this Conference decide that that is what they wish.<br />
By Authority: A. J. A RTHuR, Cwlth Govt PrinteCra, n berra </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
