<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6225</transcript-id>
    <title>SECOND MEETING of Economic Planning Advisory Council ( EPAC)</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/10/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006225.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>J\ AiSTRA. IA l 16M E<br />FOR MEDIA 7 October 1983<br />The Economic Planning Advisory Council ( EPAC) held its<br />second meeting today.<br />The meeting was attended by the recently appointed Director,<br />Geoff Miller, formerly Deputy Secretary of the Department of<br />Primary Industry.<br />The Council discussed with Mr Miller the role of EPAC, the<br />priority areas of EPAC's work in the near future, and the<br />progress of arrangements for EPAC staffing.<br />The meeting confirmed that the main role of EPAC is analysing<br />medium and long-term economic performance in Australia, and<br />factors influencing that performance.<br />The Government made it clear that while it would be strongly<br />influenced by views expressed within EPAC, it would not seek<br />to use EPAC as a shield against public reaction to difficult<br />decisions. Responsibility for policy decisions will be clearly with<br />Government. The meeting discussed current economic conditions, and<br />concurred in the assessment that recovery was underway, a] though<br />at this stage it was uneven.<br />While the economy is showing promising signs that recovery is<br />underway, our major problems on the employment front will not<br />be easily or quickly resolved.<br />A major task ahead of the Council is to identify ways in which<br />the prospective performance can be improved.<br />This applies particularly to job generation.<br />EPAC will examine employment in bot: the narrow econcmic growth<br />context, and in a broader social adjustment context.<br />Today's meeting discussed at some length a survey of reviews<br />of the Australian taxation system over the past decade.<br />The next step in EPAC's taxation review will involve the<br />preparation of a paper on the nature and effects of the current<br />Australian taxation system at Federal, State and Local Govern-.:: cnt<br />levels.</p>
<p>2.<br />Other matters discussed at today's m,., eeting included progress<br />towards estabishment of the Prices Surveill. ance Auth" or itv;<br />the decision of the recent ACTU Congress; the recent<br />national wage ca se decision; the adequacy of the Australian<br />data base; and the implic-ations of the recent appreciation<br />of the dollar.<br />The next meeting of EPAC will be held in Canberra on<br />December 12.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
