<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5297</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER INTERVIEWED BY PETER HARVEY, CHANNEL NINE CANBERRA</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/03/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005297.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS OFFICE TRANSCRIPT MONDAY, 17 MARCH, 1980<br />
PRIME MINISTER INTERVIEWED BY PETER HARVEY, CHANNEL NINE<br />
CANBERRA Harvey It seems to a good many Australians, Prime minister, that the<br />
climate of industrial unrest particularly* in key industriesis<br />
getting worse all the time. Things aren't getting better.<br />
You have criticised Neville Wran by saying that the State<br />
Government, in his case, should have taken greater action. But<br />
broadly, where are we going, and what can be done to prevent us<br />
from going further down the path of industrial anarchy?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Everyone talks of course, about a peaceful settlement of disputes.<br />
They all talk about reconciliation and reason. That is very fine.<br />
But if those qualities are going to prevail, you have got to have<br />
parties on both sides of an industrial dispute prepared to be<br />
reasonable, and as the Commonwealth believes, prepared to accept<br />
that the normal laws of the country that apply to companies and<br />
you, and everyone else as individuals, must also apply in relation<br />
to trade unions. I made those comments about Mr. Wran because they<br />
do have very specific powers in relation to energy shortages. They<br />
could have used those powers. But even when they did have an<br />
emergency distribution system, as it later appeared it was the<br />
Transport Workers' Union that determined who, under that emergency<br />
system, was to be allowed to get petrol. Now, that is not a<br />
Government usin~ g its powers, using its authority, being prepared to<br />
protect the people of New South Wales. One of the problems we<br />
have quite plainly, is that when a dispute becomes of great and<br />
national significance people automatically think that we, the<br />
Commonwealth, have the power to resolve it or to handle the matter.<br />
I think everyone knows-or most people who are in the industrial<br />
environment-know that the Commonwealth power i's a limited one.<br />
If the States will work in co-operation with us that is fine.<br />
Over a year ago we established working parties, set-up by the<br />
Premiers' Conference, to try and get more sense into the duality<br />
of arrangements: the State's on the one hand, ours on another.<br />
If that did happen, I believe we could handle difficult situations<br />
much better. Mr. Wran proposed in the middle of the petrol tanker's<br />
diLspute that there be a referendum to hand powers over to us.<br />
But he knew quite well that a number of States would oppose that.<br />
Therefore, the referendum may well not succeed. But-he also knew<br />
that that could only be a long-term solution. He had powers, as<br />
of then, or as of now, and was not willing to use them. You have<br />
go~ t to have Governments prepared to be resolute.<br />
If an employer has to stand up, he has got to be prepared to<br />
do that, but I think Governments need to be prepared to back a<br />
particular employer if they believe that a trade union is being<br />
unreasonable and exerting an irresponsible and undemocratic power. / 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
Harvey But when that criticism can also apply, as you have inferred,<br />
to an employer as with the situation with AMOCO and Mr. Laidelywhat<br />
do you say then?<br />
Pr-ime Minist-er<br />
I have no brief for what AMOCO appears to have done at. all. Because<br />
it seems to me the reason seems to be something like this:<br />
Mr. Laidely, as was his right, took out protection so that he could<br />
still go on being delivered petrol, so that hi * s business could<br />
continue. The argument, let us not forget, was over which member of<br />
the State-registered Transport Workers' Union should do the job;<br />
not over whether a non-unionist should do it, or whether a member<br />
of some other union should do it; but over which particular member's<br />
of a State-registered union. So the cause of the dispute, as I<br />
believe, was the height of absurdity. But then Mr. Laidely goes<br />
to the law, which has been deliberately placed there so that he<br />
could be protected in these circumstances in relative terms a<br />
smallish company, a smallish employer. Then, the company comes<br />
to a view, under discussion involving the Arbitration Commission,<br />
involving the Transport Workers' Union-: Mr. Laidely not being<br />
present -comes to the view that if it refused to supply Mr. Laidely<br />
there will be no reason for a ban by the Union, therefore, no cause<br />
for Mr. Laidely's restrictive Trade Practices action, and therefore<br />
no dispute. The only loser in all of that would appear to<br />
be Mr. Laidely. But not only Mr. Laidely, because the community<br />
has lost, as I believe, and lost very seriously. Because here we<br />
have a large company, and hence a relatively powerful company,<br />
virtually in cahoots with the union that caused the problem in<br />
the first place: to settle the matter to their mutual agreement<br />
and advantage, but at the expense of the little fellow. Now, that<br />
is not a circumstance that the Government is prepared to stand by<br />
and watch. I have called for a report involving the Ministers for<br />
Business and Consumer Affairs, the Attorney-General, and Industrial<br />
Relations. We will have tha~ t report and be examining the matter,<br />
because we are immensely concerned that a law that we passed in<br />
good faith, and will support in good faith, would to us, appear<br />
to have been subverted. In the process what has happened is that<br />
the little fellow has been grievously damaged.<br />
Harvey On the other issue that is causing concern, on the wool, aren't<br />
you the Federal Government in danger of causing damage to that<br />
situation by jumping in before the Commission has had a chance to<br />
finalise its-hearings?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
We need to remember that the Full Bench of the Commission made a<br />
judgement, now many, many weeks ago. What has happened since is<br />
because the union, Storemen and Packers, has refused to accept that<br />
judgement. Again, defiance of the law, defiance of the processes<br />
of arbitration. What then do you do? The dispute has gone on for<br />
several weeks. There have been no normally rostered sales since<br />
before Christmas. The whole trade is disrupted. As a result of a<br />
breakdown in meetings in the middle of last week between the partiesthe<br />
brokers and the Storemen and Packers' Union and the ACTU we </p>
<p>-3<br />
Prime Minister ( continued)<br />
decided that we should have a meeting with all the brokers and<br />
the growers' representatives in Canberra. We came out of that<br />
with a joint plan of action: all -the parties supporting each<br />
oft the actions -that are proposed. Our use of export controls was<br />
in fact proposed to us by other parties. They wanted that to back<br />
uip the actions that they would be taking to give strength and<br />
validity to those particular actions. We pointed out the<br />
consequences to the industry of accepting that particular proposition.<br />
After examination, discussion, we decided that we should. So,<br />
in a sense, it is not the Government arbitrarilly coming in and<br />
saying ' this is going to happen; export controls to take over the<br />
industry'. We are responding in a very real way to an industry<br />
request which wants to act in a unified way, in a concerted way,<br />
t~ o overcome industrial blackmail by the Storemen and Packers' Union.<br />
Harvey But how do you do that Prime Minister? How is that achieved, by<br />
t~ aking over the industry?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Taking over is really the wrong term. It gives us power to exercise<br />
controls over the export of wool. As a consequence of our<br />
decision to do that, by acceptance of the proposition, the dismissal<br />
notices have been sent out to Storemen and Packers in other centres,<br />
because there was probably no way of this dispute being resolved,<br />
while Melbourne and Sydney were blockaded and other centres were<br />
technically working: technically working, but not in a way that<br />
was really getting wool moving, normal sales undertaken. -Because<br />
sales have virtually ceased. Therefore, the dispute was, in effect,<br />
holding up the whole industry. Since the blockade of Melbourne<br />
and Sydney was holding up the whole industry, it was logical that the<br />
consequences of that hold-up should be felt by'a11 the industry;<br />
not leaving the situation where people working in the centres<br />
other than Melbourne and Sydney., could go on working<br />
subsidising those who-were on strike.-<br />
Harvey The subsidy presumably stops, although the Union will have some<br />
sort of funds, money, to be able to continue. But what happens then<br />
-to the industry. I guess my question is: aren't we in danger of<br />
cutting off the nose of the wool industry to spite its face?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
. I do not think so. In a matter of this kind, if you are going to<br />
-get to a reasonable solution of it, you have got to prepared to<br />
match strength with strength. That is not seeking confrontation;<br />
that is not wanting confrontation. Nobody can accuse the Government<br />
-of that. It is that people have been on strike for many, many weeks.<br />
They have been preventing the normal business being undertaken; who<br />
refused to accept a Full Bench decision. They have been confronting / 4 </p>
<p>4<br />
Prime Minister ( continued)<br />
the other people in this industry and indeed, the whole Australian<br />
community. It is time that there was a greater degree of commonsense<br />
; nd sanity. It is time that people recognise that we do have<br />
an Arbitration system that is worthwhile. It is the impartial<br />
third person, the umpire, and its verdict ought to be accepted,<br />
even if you do not like them, they ought to be accepted. Employers<br />
are bound by law to accept it. But some trade unions think that they<br />
can just go on regardless. Now, the Government will be certainly<br />
exerting all its authority to see that the integrity of the<br />
Arbitration Commission is maintained, to see that it is upheld.<br />
In doing that, you also need a determination by the employers, a<br />
determination by the industry. Last Friday showed plainly in the<br />
wool industry that these two things are there.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
