<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2814</transcript-id>
    <title>INTELLIGENCE UNIT</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/02/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002814.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
-4j_, AUST2 UAL1A PRESS STATEMENT NO. 52<br />
February 1973<br />
" tINTELLIGENCE UNIT"<br />
Mr. Whitlam sent the following letter today to Mr. Snedden<br />
in reply to his telegram yesterday:<br />
Dear Mr. Snedden,<br />
I refer to your telegram concerning events subsequent to<br />
and consequent on Mr. Brenchley's article in the " National<br />
Times" on Sunday 11 February regarding ' top secret'<br />
Australian electronics intelligence unit" in Singapore.<br />
This article appears to have been in breach of a ' D'<br />
Notice issued by the Menzies Government. In these<br />
circumstances I would hesitate to discuss the " electronics<br />
intelligence unit" publicly or on the record. Presumably<br />
it was on this basis that you yourself quite properly<br />
declined to answer questions about it at your press<br />
conference yesterday.<br />
Nevertheless, since reports of the " electronic intelligence<br />
unit" have now been published, I feel at liberty to remind<br />
you that the Gorton Government, of~ which you were a member,<br />
decided that Singapore was an inappropriate place for these<br />
activities to be conducted and that they should be<br />
transferred to Australia. My Government is pressing on<br />
with that decision. I would be happy, with my officers, to<br />
refresh your memory on the decisions taken by previous<br />
Liberal Governments and acquaint you with the present<br />
situation. I received your telegram only this morning but know that<br />
you released it to the press last night. Accordingly, I am<br />
also releasing this letter to the press, with the exception<br />
of the preceding paragraph. As for the detailed questions<br />
you raised, you will agree, I am sure, that the conduct of my<br />
relations with the press is for me and my staff to determine.<br />
Yours sincerely,<br />
E. G. Whitlam ( sgd.) </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
