<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10573</transcript-id>
    <title>Doorstop Interview, Fire Control Centre, Heathcote, Sydney </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/12/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>3 December 1997</p>
<p>E&amp;OE..........................................................................................................................</p>
<p><b>PRIME MINISTER:</b></p>
<p>Can I just start by saying that once again, in a time of crisis, the Australian community gets magnificent service from the police, the firefighters, the ambulance and the other emergency services. And it’s always important at a time like this to remind ourselves of the debt, as a community and as a nation, we owe to those groups. And I want to express on behalf of the Federal Government my unstinting admiration for the effort of those services and also for the effort of so many volunteers. And we have always been a great volunteer society and the volunteer spirit of the Australian community always comes out on occasions like this.</p>
<p>I want to thank the Commander and all the people associated with the control operation here for the briefing that they’ve given. It seems at present that the weather conditions are better. We must hope and, indeed, pray that that situation continues. It is a matter of concern that fires of this magnitude are occurring this side of Christmas. And we must all hope that there will be some change in the weather pattern which is so important.</p>
<p>But again, can I express on behalf of the Government my admiration, my gratitude and my thanks to the people, to my colleague, Danna Vale, the Federal Member for Hughes and His Worship, the Mayor of the Shire, for their efforts as local representatives.</p>
<p>I have been in touch with the Premier of New South Wales, Mr Carr, on two occasions regarding the fires in this State. Obviously the Commonwealth Government and the State Government cooperate very closely. The State Government is, of course, handling the situation in a first-hand sense and doing it very, very effectively and, of course, the Premier and I will be working together very closely.</p>
<p><b>JOURNALIST:</b></p>
<p>Mr Howard, is the Commonwealth Government going to provide emergency funding?</p>
<p><b>PRIME MINISTER:</b></p>
<p>Well, there are some automatic relief arrangements in place. I will ensure that the appropriate Minister in the Commonwealth Government, which is Mr Fahey, the Finance Minister, is in close touch with the New South Wales Government to see if there is any further assistance that is both desirable and appropriate.</p>
<p>I just want to make it clear that any appropriate assistance will be available.</p>
<p><b>JOURNALIST:</b></p>
<p>Prime Minister, you made a special trip up here this morning. Exactly what do you hope to achieve? Is it just a personal thing to come up and lend a bit of support and see the thing for yourself?</p>
<p><b>PRIME MINISTER:</b></p>
<p>I think on an occasion like this people who are there at the frontline risking their lives, they are entitled to know that the nation is grateful for what they’ve done. Tragically two people lost their lives in Lithgow yesterday and there is no greater sacrifice that anybody can make than to lose their lives in the service of their community. And it’s very important that in a simple, uncomplicated way gratitude is expressed, a thank you is said and people know that they have the support and the understanding of their fellow Australians. Thank you.</p>
<p>[Ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
