<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8429</transcript-id>
    <title>THE PRIME MINISTER WITH JOHN LAWS ON 2 UE, FEBRUARY 28, 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/02/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008429.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE PRIME MInITERM WITH JOHN LAWS ON 2U3, FEBRUARY 28, 1992<br />
8 3O PROOF ONLY<br />
LXWS: We]. l, you promised us excitement and vitality when you<br />
moved into the top job. You've certainly given us excitement.<br />
PM: Well, I just. I mean it's really our friends in the<br />
Opposition whio've picked up quite un.. on quite unremarkable<br />
remarks by me when I spoke both to and with the Queen last week.<br />
What I was Baying was, simply, that as Britain moved more<br />
towards a Coimon Market in Europe, we were moving independently<br />
of Britain and Europe more towards the Asia/ Pacific. Andi, of<br />
course, I waon adding, and I had already said before I said that,<br />
that the Queen was part of this independence when she became<br />
Queen of Ausjtralia. So, it was quite unremarkable but I'm<br />
afraid our friends in the Opposition have this sort of<br />
propensity to so rt of bow and scrape and that one can't even<br />
sort of express Australia's independence without it being a<br />
matter of some coimment.<br />
LAWS: Well, now the British people have reacted in what I<br />
consider a most defensive way to the comments that you've made.<br />
They've been critical of you: we have one gentleman who<br />
suggested that you've ' mauled' the Queen, we have another one<br />
suggesting that your wife was less than courteous. And, as I<br />
was just sayiLng, -we have a lot of British migrants in Australia<br />
who must shudder at the attitude of their countrymen in light of<br />
what happened. Now, while you were saying that we were moving<br />
towards independence, I have never heard you at any time want to<br />
rush the issUe Of this place becoming a Republic. And while you<br />
were saying what you were saying, the delightful Duchess of Kent<br />
was in Brisbane saying precisely the same thing. You were not<br />
aware of what she was saying because she was saying it about the<br />
same time. And she said that Australia's grown up, they can get<br />
by without the help of other people and, obviously, she said if<br />
I was an Australian, I would be thinking about becoming a<br />
Republic too. But, of course, we'll always be good friends,<br />
won't we. And she said it as nicely as that. Now, in essence<br />
that's what you were saying, wasn't it?<br />
PM: Yes, except I did not., no, I wasn't even saying that<br />
much. I was just simply making the point, John, that Australia </p>
<p>naturally.. I was remarking about the fact that she had been<br />
crowned 40 years earlier. It was a speech of congratulations on<br />
her coronation 40 year. ago, and to say that in the 40 years so<br />
much had changed. That Britain had become a much more European<br />
country in terms of its outlook and its arrangements. Australia<br />
had become a more Asia Pacific country. That was all I was<br />
saying. LAWS: i That, of course, what you're saying is undeniably<br />
true, isn't it?<br />
PM: And the Queen had herself recognized this change that<br />
years after her coronation she adopted the royal style and<br />
title of Queen of Australia. She doesn't come here as Queen of<br />
Great Britain, she comes as Queen of Australia. And that was<br />
the point I made. But of course, Palace authorities, when<br />
questioned about this who were travelling with the Queen,<br />
thought it entirely unremarkable and couldn't quite understand<br />
what the kerfuffle was about.<br />
LAWS: Well, why did John Hewson and John Howard, in<br />
particular, and Tim Fischer not that it matters a great deal<br />
what he think. but they seem to consider it is remarkable.<br />
PM: I know. Because, you see, it's all part of this point<br />
I made yesterday, the sort of torpor which Menzies put the place<br />
in, a sort of forelock-tugging business. I mean, if it was left<br />
to these people we'd still have knighthoods and we'd still have<br />
all these sorts of things. And we'd be still tied up to a<br />
country 12,000 miles away. It wasn't until 1986 that the Queen<br />
signed and gave royal ascent to the Australia Act.<br />
LAWS: Yes, in fact, it's next Monday, will be the exact day<br />
that in 1986, 2nd March, 1986, that she did that.<br />
PM: Yes, that was the thing which finally severed the<br />
links between Australia, the Constitutional links or the<br />
Parliamentary and Appeal links to their Privy Council and where<br />
the British Parliament could change the Australian Constitution<br />
by Act of the British Parliament. She severed that link as<br />
short a time ago as 1986. So, it took us all that long to<br />
actually cut the knot. But our friends in the O) pposition who<br />
want to tell us that they're the people of the Nineties keep<br />
extolling the virtues of the 1950s, And now they Ire in there<br />
telling us what a great period of tranquility and progress it<br />
was in the 19~ 50a and sort of saying ' isn't it a pity, really,<br />
we've got to change from all of that'.<br />
LAWS: The opposition will say,. and have suggested that the<br />
whole thing, -the outburst and it was an outburst because you<br />
were very firmn, did you lose control? </p>
<p>PM: Oh noI no. It was the very essence of control, I'm<br />
quite clear about what I wanted to say.<br />
LXWS: i YOUL said it very loudly.<br />
PM: I wanted to make it quite clear that Dr Hewson and Mr<br />
Howard would. be better in the Constitutional Museum we're<br />
thinking of creating at the Old Parliament House an a sort of<br />
pair of Fifties relics. And not anybody who'll likely be<br />
leading Australia in the 1990s, given that they're quite happy<br />
to still dof f the old hat, you know, tug the forelock to the<br />
British Establishment, which is what they're about.<br />
LAWS: Wha~ t you said, you said with a great deal of<br />
strength you did it say it with some venom and you obviously<br />
meant it. They are going to say it was a deliberate ploy to<br />
bury John Hewbon's reply to your Economic Statement.<br />
PM1 well, he was going to get his reply and that'll give<br />
us both the same amount of press attention, it was just to make<br />
the point. They say that they have concern f or the position of<br />
the Monarchy and the Queen but they did their best to score from<br />
it on the day in question and score in a way which paints them<br />
back into thel sort of fogey corner of the 1950s. And I mean it<br />
just is remarkable that two relatively young men, relatively<br />
young men, should be such ' old' young men. You know what I<br />
mean? LAWS: Yes, I understand what you're saying.<br />
PM. That they are trying to say, well ' we're the people<br />
from the Nineties' when, really, they're harking back to the<br />
Fifties or Sixties and isn't it a pity that we don't have all<br />
these arrangements just as they were between us and Britain and<br />
the Monarchy. I presume they'd be quite happy for the Queen to<br />
be still Queen of Great Britain and Australia and to be playing<br />
' God save the Queen', instead of ' Advance Australia Fair'.<br />
LAWS: In your reflective moments since yesterday, do you<br />
regret any of the things you've said?<br />
PM: Oh, God, no. Oh no.<br />
LAWS: You obviously don't mind upsetting the British.<br />
PM: No, look, those British tabloids I mean, God,<br />
they're the pits. I mean, the fact of the matter is Australia<br />
has every right, we have every entitlement for Australia to be<br />
aggressive about ' its own future, about its independent place in<br />
the world, about its culture and not to be seen by our leaders,<br />
Hewson and H~ oward, as Some sort Of cultural derivative of<br />
Britain. It's finished. It's over. </p>
<p>LALWS: i Can we af ford to alienate the British# and do you<br />
think we have or you have alienated the British?<br />
PM: I'Im speaking about a period past. I'm speaking about<br />
a period in the Fifties and Sixties which in past as far as I'm<br />
concerned with Britain. The people who operate Britain today<br />
have a very clear idea about all this. The British Government<br />
have a very -clear idea about all this. The only people here<br />
that don't have a clear idea is the Leaders of the Liberal<br />
Party, the Leader of the National Party and former leaders like<br />
Mr Howard.<br />
LAWS: PM: So you don't regret anything that you said yesterday?<br />
Not a bit.<br />
LAWS: Do you regret any of the comments you made about the<br />
Second World liar?<br />
PM: Oh, no. That was entirely true. I mean, here we were<br />
in the 1960s, as Menzies had us in this sort of time warp and<br />
torpor, as Britain was trying to break through and sign the<br />
Treaty of Romre and join the Common Market and leave all our<br />
agricultural exports behind, all the former markets of Australia<br />
and New Zealand leave them behind, as we had to beg to get our<br />
own troops ba~ ck to defend ourselves after the attacks by the<br />
Japanese. After all that period they were still plugging the<br />
forelock and bowing their knee.<br />
LAWS: And you are aware I imagine, that when we did try to<br />
get our troops back af ter the f all of Singapore, Churchill said<br />
that Australians who wanted to go back to the South Pacific were<br />
like rats auaee~ ing a sinkJig sip,<br />
PMg Wel2l, I wasn't quite sure abc<br />
history of all this is quite clear and<br />
when Menzies bec'ame Prime Minister thi<br />
history behind us, and then by the Si<br />
attempting to join the Common Market th<br />
have said ' Australia is entitled to an<br />
its own and we'll have to trade it. we<br />
region. But instead of that, it waited1<br />
Minister came along to change the nation<br />
Whitlam in 1973.<br />
LAWS: Yeah. And prior to that, of<br />
ref erred to ZJohn Curtin, who was a fin<br />
' wretched second rate man' and now<br />
critical of you as Australia's Leader bec<br />
you have made about them. It's a littJ<br />
the kettle blatck, isn't it? rnt the words but the<br />
one would have thought<br />
Bre in ' 49, r with that<br />
xties when Britain was<br />
at then, even he would<br />
independent position of<br />
iy in the world in its<br />
: ill another Labor Prime<br />
al tempo and that was<br />
course, Churchill had<br />
e Prime Minister, as a<br />
Britain chooses to be<br />
ause of comments that<br />
Le like the pot calling </p>
<p>PM: Not the sensible people in Britain, not the sensible<br />
ones that I run into at international meetings or the people<br />
that run the major business institutions. It's not them they<br />
understand it. all, it's just these sort of ' throw-backs' that<br />
still inhabit. some of the cracks and crevices of the British<br />
Establishment. LAWS: Well, am I say, you promised us excitement and<br />
vitality, you certainly gave it to us yesterday.<br />
P14: I tell you what I 1ll give you always,# John. I'll<br />
always give you a pro-Australian view. And we'Ire not going to<br />
be doffing ou~ r lid or tugging our forelock to anybody.<br />
LAWS: Well said. Thanks for your time, good to talk to you.<br />
PM1 Thanks, John, good-bye.<br />
LAWS: LPArWiSl: n e Minister of Australia, Paul Keating. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
