<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10698</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                  THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                  RADIO INTERVIEW WITH MICHAEL CLARKE                ABC RADIO - 4QN, TOWNSVILLE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/08/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE....................................................................................................</p>
<p>CLARKE:</p>
<p>Prime Minister it seems as if the election campaign is well and</p>
<p>   truly under way at the moment. The only thing missing is a date.</p>
<p>   Would you agree with that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I'm certainly out explaining this plan to the Australian</p>
<p>   people and I'm doing it enthusiastically because above all</p>
<p>   it is a long-term plan for the country's future. The best thing</p>
<p>   about the tax plan is that it will benefit the entire Australian</p>
<p>   economy by reducing the cost of producing things and that means</p>
<p>   that we'll be able to sell more overseas, we'll be able</p>
<p>   to compete more effectively against imports and businesses will</p>
<p>   in the long run be able to employ more people. The best thing you</p>
<p>   can do for the Australian economy is make it more competitive and</p>
<p>   you make it more competitive by reducing its operating costs. People</p>
<p>   often talk about giving export incentives to Australian exporters.</p>
<p>   This tax plan is a $4.5 billion export market development grant</p>
<p>   to all Australian exporters because that is the amount by which</p>
<p>   export costs are going to be reduced when the plan comes in. I want</p>
<p>   the plan to be seen, above everything else, as something that is</p>
<p>   good for the future of the entire Australian economy. </p>
<p>We do need tax reform. Most Australians deep down inside know that.</p>
<p>   It is not enough just to offer a tax cut. I'm quite sure our</p>
<p>   opponents will come along next week and offer a personal tax cut.</p>
<p>   Anybody can do that, but you need to have an integrated reform plan</p>
<p>   to make to a lasting impact and leave a lasting benefit for the</p>
<p>   entire Australian economy, you need to reform the system as well</p>
<p>   as offering individual benefits. </p>
<p>And of course for North Queensland, for regional Australia the</p>
<p>   plan has a special appeal and that is the huge reduction in fuel</p>
<p>   costs, something the Labor Party is opposed to. Their spokesman</p>
<p>   on the environment, Duncan Kerr, attacked the $3.5 billion reduction</p>
<p>   in fuel costs so we can assume the Labor Party is against reducing</p>
<p>   the price of fuel in regional Australia because they've come</p>
<p>   out against that part of the plan. Now, I can't think of anything</p>
<p>   that is more likely to help North Queensland, long distances from</p>
<p>   other parts of Australia you buy a lot of goods that are hauled</p>
<p>   long distances, most of the trucks that haul them are diesel-fired</p>
<p>   - diesel fueled - and there's going to be a massive cut in</p>
<p>   the excise on diesel fuel. It's going to come down from 43</p>
<p>   cents a litre to 18 cents a litre. That is a drop of 25 cents. On</p>
<p>   top of that every business man and woman in Australia will be able</p>
<p>   to buy their petrol effectively at 7 cents cheaper because the GST</p>
<p>   on fuel used for business, quite apart from the diesel reduction,</p>
<p>   which is a separate additional thing, the GST on fuel for business</p>
<p>   will be fully refunded. So overall, one of the really specific attractive</p>
<p>   features about this plan is the way it reduces fuel costs, and that</p>
<p>   is of unbelievable benefit to country Australia. </p>
<p>CLARKE:</p>
<p>Let's talk about another issue of importance in North Queensland,</p>
<p>   and that is tourism. It has been said in some circles that a 10%</p>
<p>   tax on so many things will make the price of a holiday so much more</p>
<p>   expensive. People will not be keen to come to North Queensland for</p>
<p>   holidays. Your response?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, the tourist industry will benefit from the reduction in fuel</p>
<p>   costs because it won't only be heavy transport that will get</p>
<p>   that reduction in fuel excise, all the pleasure craft operators,</p>
<p>   all the boats that ply the coast, that go from the coast to the</p>
<p>   islands, they all use fuel that will get the benefit of this concession,</p>
<p>   and so there will be enormous benefits for them. We have included</p>
<p>   the internal air travel section of holiday packages bought overseas</p>
<p>   in the exemptions in relation to charging a GST. There'll be</p>
<p>   no GST on international airfares and packages bought overseas, there</p>
<p>   will be no GST on airfares, international airfares, and on top of</p>
<p>   that, the internal leg of packages bought overseas, that likewise</p>
<p>   will not be subject to the goods and services tax. </p>
<p>See, what you've got to understand is it is not 10% on top</p>
<p>   of everything. Everything is not going to go up by 10% because many</p>
<p>   of the things that people now buy are subject to sales tax. I mean,</p>
<p>   you pay 22% on a family car, you pay 12% on biscuits, on flavoured</p>
<p>   milk, on orange juice concentrate, you pay 22% on soaps and detergents,</p>
<p>   on many household items. Now, all of those things will go, all of</p>
<p>   those 22%s and 12%s and in some cases 32%s on videos and TVs, they</p>
<p>   will all be abolished, and everything will be subject at the consumption</p>
<p>   level to a 10% tax. Now, because the input costs will come down,</p>
<p>   the average price rise all over is only going about 2%, 1.9%.</p>
<p>CLARKE:</p>
<p>But are we looking at price rise?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, in the overall, yes. Overall it will be about 2%, but not</p>
<p>   10%. Overall 1.9%, not 10%, and the reason it is not 10% is that</p>
<p>   all those things that are now bearing WST, wholesale sales tax,</p>
<p>   of 22%, 32%, 12% - they will all go, because one of the conditions</p>
<p>   of the introduction of a goods and services tax is that the wholesale</p>
<p>   sales tax has got to be abolished in full. The other thing that</p>
<p>   will go is those annoying items in some of your bank statements</p>
<p>   people get around Australia  the financial institutions duty</p>
<p>   and the bank accounts debits tax. Now they vary a little bit from</p>
<p>   State to State but they are a great aggravation to Australia. You</p>
<p>   will no longer have to pay stamp duty on share transactions, you</p>
<p>   will no longer have to pay stamp duty on business conveyances, no</p>
<p>   longer have to pay stamp duty on checks and bills of exchange and</p>
<p>   promissory notes, because the proposal is that when the GST is introduced</p>
<p>   the wholesale sales tax will be abolished all together. The price</p>
<p>   of a family car will drop dramatically and the States will be required</p>
<p>   to abolish nine other taxes including the financial institutions</p>
<p>   duty and all the other taxes that I've mentioned. </p>
<p>So that the idea that you are lumping 10% on top of everything</p>
<p>   is quite wrong because what you are doing is you are taking all</p>
<p>   of these taxes away first. And then the great advantage of the goods</p>
<p>   and services tax is that it applies in an even consistent manner,</p>
<p>   and a businessman now who buys a computer pays wholesales sales</p>
<p>   tax on that and he can't get it back. But under the GST if</p>
<p>   he buys that same computer, instead of paying a higher rate of wholesale</p>
<p>   sales tax - I think off-hand it may be 22% - he will pay 10% goods</p>
<p>   and services tax and he'll be able to get the whole of that</p>
<p>   10% back from the tax man, because the way a GST operates is that</p>
<p>   you get refunds of the GST paid on your business inputs. I mean,</p>
<p>   that is why petrol will be cheaper for every business man and woman</p>
<p>   in Australia. If you use it for business, it will be 7 cents a litre</p>
<p>   cheaper. Now, when you add all of those things up you can see that</p>
<p>   this argument that it pushes up the price of everything by 10% is</p>
<p>   wrong and of course there are personal taxation reductions to ensure</p>
<p>   that people, even after the price effects of the GST of around 1.9%</p>
<p>   are going to be better off. It's an integrated package. You</p>
<p>   can't have one without the other. The Australian public I think</p>
<p>   understand that if we really want to fix the system, then you have</p>
<p>   to have a GST. If you don't want to fix the system, if you</p>
<p>   want to stick with the present indirect tax system  where</p>
<p>   you've got taxes as high as 32% - which can be put up at the</p>
<p>   whim of any Federal Government as we found after the 1993 election</p>
<p>   where Mr Beazley and Mr Keating put them all up. If you want a really</p>
<p>   genuine reform, you've got to embrace this.</p>
<p>CLARKE:</p>
<p>If you want to ask a question to the Prime Minister. Let's</p>
<p>   go to our first caller now and it's a good morning to Jack.</p>
<p>   Hello Jack.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>How are you this morning?</p>
<p>CLARKE:</p>
<p>Good thanks.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>Welcome to North Queensland Mr Howard. My question is: recently</p>
<p>   I had my roof system repaired on my house which cost $1000. I was</p>
<p>   advised by the contractor that if GST was operational I'd have</p>
<p>   to pay an extra $100 extra on that account which would make it $1100.</p>
<p>   I was just wondering if in fact that is correct.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well his operating costs would be less than what they are now because,</p>
<p>   for example, his fuel will be cheaper and I would expect that there</p>
<p>   are many other items that he now buys in which he pays wholesale</p>
<p>   sales tax so his input costs would be lower. Therefore even with</p>
<p>   the imposition of the 10% GST, the figure that he's given you</p>
<p>   would not be right.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>Yes, well he said that it was $100, it's be 10% and that would</p>
<p>   be....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I've explained to you how, because some of his other</p>
<p>   costs will be lower, the amount on which you impose the 10% would</p>
<p>   be less than $1000 therefore it would not be the gross amount that</p>
<p>   you mentioned.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>But I didn't ask about what he purchased from the wholesale</p>
<p>   people and so forth in which he carries [inaudible], I see it, he</p>
<p>   told me that it would cost $100 extra. And I believe him too.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I would say to you Sir, that I'd go back to him and I'd</p>
<p>   get a list of all of his input costs and I'd find out whether</p>
<p>   he's telling you the complete picture and if I were you I'd</p>
<p>   find out whether he pays any wholesale sales tax. If he does than</p>
<p>   you'll find that what he's saying to you is a little wide</p>
<p>   of the mark.</p>
<p>CLARKE:</p>
<p>Jack, we'll have to move on but thanks very much for your</p>
<p>   call this morning. We are taking your calls on talkback with the</p>
<p>   Prime Minister this morning, 4772 2630. Good morning Jennifer.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>Oh, good morning Prime Minister.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Hello Jennifer.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>I was reading the tax scale in the Sunday Mail on Sunday</p>
<p>   and it left me a little bit amazed because of the variations in</p>
<p>   the...what they're going to receive. Like people on $20,000</p>
<p>   are only going to get 3% back where as anyone earning $38,000 to</p>
<p>   $50,000 are now paying 43 cents in the dollar, they're going</p>
<p>   to get a 13% increase back. Pensioners of which we are, we're</p>
<p>   living on $5.96, that's what we're going to get out of</p>
<p>   our 4% increase. Now someone on a gross salary of $880,000 are going</p>
<p>   to get $8,969 a week and the pensioners have to survive on $8,058</p>
<p>   a year. Now he's earning $911 a week more than what we get</p>
<p>   per year. And I just thought that this GST was mainly for the Australian</p>
<p>   battlers and I'm afraid I can't, you know, I just can't</p>
<p>   see it.</p>
<p>CLARKE:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, your response.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well my response is firstly that it's always the case under</p>
<p>   a progressive taxation system that if you reduce income tax right</p>
<p>   across the board then people on high incomes get larger dollar amounts</p>
<p>   because they're paying more tax and it stands to reason that</p>
<p>   if you reduce the tax from somebody who's earning $100,000</p>
<p>   a year than the dollar gain from that is greater than somebody on</p>
<p>   $20,000 a year because the person on $100,000 a year is paying a</p>
<p>   hell of a lot more tax in the first instance.....</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>[inaudible]</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>...no could I, listen, with respect I did hear you out. Would</p>
<p>   you please hear me out. The other point that I think ought to be</p>
<p>   made is that we have not reduced the top marginal. Of the existing</p>
<p>   rate scales, you mentioned the 43 cents and the 38,000 which it</p>
<p>   comes in, we have cut the bottom. We've...to start with</p>
<p>   we've increased the tax free threshold from $5,400 to $6,000</p>
<p>   and in proportionate terms that is of more benefit to somebody who</p>
<p>   earns $20,000 or less than somebody who earns $80,000. The second</p>
<p>   thing is that we've reduced the first rate from 20% down to</p>
<p>   17. Then we've introduced a new 30% rate that will run right</p>
<p>   from $20,000 to $50,000 and the great advantage of that is that</p>
<p>   it will encourage the average wage and salary earner to work overtime</p>
<p>   without going into a higher tax bracket. Then we have a 40% rate</p>
<p>   that cuts in at $50,000 and then at $75,000 we still maintain the</p>
<p>   top 47% rate. Now the other point I should make to you is that in</p>
<p>   the first Budget that was brought down under my Government, we introduced</p>
<p>   a special surcharge in relation to superannuation contributions</p>
<p>   that only applied to people who were earning $70,000 a year or more.</p>
<p>   That didn't apply to anybody whose income was below that. Now</p>
<p>   I know a lot of people in that income range didn't like that</p>
<p>   particular measure but we nonetheless stuck to it because we believe</p>
<p>   it was only fair and equitable in fixing the Budget deficit that</p>
<p>   we should get a contribution in relation to an already quite generous</p>
<p>   tax treatment of superannuation from high income earners. So I don't</p>
<p>   think anybody can suggest that we're asking the low paid in</p>
<p>   the community to bear a disproportionate burden. We're not</p>
<p>   doing that. We've spread things very evenly and the best token</p>
<p>   of that of course is that we haven't dropped the top marginal</p>
<p>   rate.</p>
<p>CLARKE:</p>
<p>Jennifer, thank you very much for your call this morning.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
<p>CLARKE:</p>
<p>And now we say good morning to Kim. Hello Kim.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>Hi. I never went to school a few years ago and I'm not really</p>
<p>   good at maths, but my husband is on a earning of a little over $33,000</p>
<p>   a year and the way I see it that he pays 33 cents in the dollar</p>
<p>   and with the tax cuts he will get a saving of 3 cents for every</p>
<p>   dollar taxed that he pays. Am I correct in that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, it's more than that because if he's on $33,000 he'll</p>
<p>   also get the benefit of the increased tax free threshold and he</p>
<p>   will also get the benefit of the drop in the first rate from 20</p>
<p>   down to 17 and he will be on, if he's on $33,000, well under</p>
<p>   this plan his marginal tax rate will be 30% but he'll be paying</p>
<p>   lesser amounts on chunks of his income between $6000 and $20,000.</p>
<p>   The 30% rate doesn't apply until you hit 20,000. Now therefore</p>
<p>   he'll gain more than what you have suggested. And then on top</p>
<p>   of that, do you have any children?</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>I have two teenage children, 14 and 15.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>And are you in the workforce?</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>No.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, what are the ages of your children?</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>14 and 15.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well you will get increased family benefits as well. He will get...you'll</p>
<p>   get an additional $1000 a year off his tax free threshold for each</p>
<p>   of those two children. So that's another $2000 that he can</p>
<p>   add to his tax free threshold of $6000. So overall you will be better</p>
<p>   off than that. I mean if you gave the studio your name and address</p>
<p>   I'd get you the exact calculation but I'd have to know</p>
<p>   the exact figure and I'd have to know whether there was any</p>
<p>   private health insurance involved.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>No we couldn't afford it.</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well you may be able to afford it now because you will be able</p>
<p>   to get 30% of the cost of it back back off your tax. If you had</p>
<p>   a policy that cost you, say, $1000 a year, from the 1st</p>
<p>   of January next year you'll be able to get 30% of that back.</p>
<p>   So you will certainly be better off than the bald amount that you</p>
<p>   just suggested.</p>
<p>CLARKE:</p>
<p>Thanks very much for your call.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
<p>CLARKE:</p>
<p>We're taking your calls this morning on 634QN, your local</p>
<p>   ABC, talking with the Prime Minister. Brian, good morning.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>Good morning. Good morning PM. </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Good morning Brian.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>Mine's a very broad question. In your tax package they say that</p>
<p>   you'd close some of the tax loopholes. Why is it neither side</p>
<p>   of politics will actually close off all those loopholes, and they</p>
<p>   say there's about $8 billion of tax to be collected from that</p>
<p>   area?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well there's not $8 billion. I mean that is just a mythical</p>
<p>   figure. Unless you're going to wipe out things that I don't</p>
<p>   regard as loopholes, such as negative gearing and tax incentives</p>
<p>   for people to invest in superannuation. You see a lot of people</p>
<p>   say that things that aren't really loopholes are loopholes.</p>
<p>   I don't think it's a loophole to give an incentive for</p>
<p>   people to invest in superannuation. That's not a loophole.</p>
<p>   If you want people to divert investment income, if you want people</p>
<p>   to invest in funds that are set aside for their retirement you have</p>
<p>   to give them a tax break. That's not a loophole. And I don't</p>
<p>   think negative gearing which encourages a lot of development, I</p>
<p>   don't think that's a loophole. I don't think depreciation</p>
<p>   for business is a loophole.</p>
<p>CLARKE:</p>
<p>But I guess a good question would be does this tax package get</p>
<p>   rid of all the tax cheats?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>This tax package will hit tax cheats very hard. I mean to start</p>
<p>   with, a GST hits tax cheats because a GST is much harder to evade</p>
<p>   than the existing taxes. That's one of the great virtues. We</p>
<p>   will get $3 billion additional revenue at least over a period of</p>
<p>   three years as a result of the introduction of a GST, and that would</p>
<p>   not be possible unless you have a comprehensive goods and services</p>
<p>   tax. We've also introduced some special rules with effect from</p>
<p>   last week in relation to off-shore tax havens that will hit down</p>
<p>   very hard on the use of cascading trusts to ship money off-shore</p>
<p>   and evade taxation. Now we make no apology for doing that. We're</p>
<p>   also going to tax trusts in the same way as companies but we will</p>
<p>   allow the continued legitimate use of trusts because they are a</p>
<p>   way of holding together assets in a farm or small business and there</p>
<p>   is a legitimate use for them. But we're going to eliminate</p>
<p>   the abuse of them. So we are doing an enormous amount in relation</p>
<p>   to loopholes but I want to make the point that not every tax incentive</p>
<p>   is a loophole. Otherwise you get the ridiculous situation where</p>
<p>   people are running around saying anything that involves a tax concession</p>
<p>   is a rort. It's not.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>Brian, we'll have to leave it there but thanks for your call</p>
<p>   this morning. Prime Minister, just on a separate issue and that's</p>
<p>   on the wool stockpile, the legislation to freeze the wool stockpile.</p>
<p>   Will Parliament be resuming to pass that through?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Parliament is scheduled to resume on the 31st of August.</p>
<p>CLARKE:</p>
<p>So at this stage you believe that Parliament will be resuming to</p>
<p>   put that legislation through?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It's scheduled to resume on the 31st of August.</p>
<p>CLARKE:</p>
<p>So the Government's staying committed to that. 630 4QN, your</p>
<p>   local ABC. We've got four minutes to news. We're taking</p>
<p>   your calls with the Prime Minister this morning and good morning</p>
<p>   to North? Hello North.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>Good morning Michael. Mr Prime Minister, I do appreciate you making</p>
<p>   a visit to Townsville and, you know, give us chance to talk to you.</p>
<p>   You stated earlier that you wished to fix the system.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes, I do.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>And I wish to refer to an October 28, 1996 Sydney Morning Herald</p>
<p>   quote that says: the tax office, the vast majority of multinational</p>
<p>   corporations pay little or no tax.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Who said that?</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>The tax office, it's quoted here in the Sydney Morning</p>
<p>   Herald.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well that doesn't necessarily mean it's absolutely correct</p>
<p>   just because it's quoted in the newspaper, I just wanted to</p>
<p>   check the real source of it. Well could I say in relation to multinationals</p>
<p>   and this tax plan, as we've only got a few minutes, we are</p>
<p>   requiring that every dividend paid to an overseas shareholder from</p>
<p>   Australia be subject to the full company tax before it is remitted.</p>
<p>   Now that is a very very effective way of ensuring that the concerns</p>
<p>   of people about tax obligations of overseas shareholders, which</p>
<p>   is another way of describing multinationals, are in fact met. Now</p>
<p>   I have no truck for tax avoidance arrangements by multinationals</p>
<p>   or anybody else. But this tax plan, because of that particular device,</p>
<p>   amongst others, goes very directly to the concerns that people have</p>
<p>   expressed.</p>
<p>CLARKE:</p>
<p>North, thanks very much for your call this morning. Prime Minister,</p>
<p>   we've only got about two minutes til news time. Just</p>
<p>   looking at the calls that we've seen so far, a lot of confusion</p>
<p>   out there. Is this package too complicated for the people to understand?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I think people are interested to know, but I mean, I think</p>
<p>   both of us are over 21 and we know that every so often political</p>
<p>   parties arrange for questions to be asked, and I think perhaps over</p>
<p>   the past week I've had a few questions that may have been inspired</p>
<p>   by my po</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
