<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9114</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON PJ KEATING MP LUNCHEON FOR THE PRIME MINISTER OF PAPUA NEW GUINEA THE RT HON PIAIAS WINGTI PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA WEDNESDAY 9 FEBRUARY 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/02/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009114.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
LUNCHEON FOR THE PRIME MINISTER OF PAPUA NEW GUINEA<br />
THE RT HON PAIAS WINGTI<br />
PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA<br />
WEDNESDAY 9 FEBRUARY 1994<br />
( EMBARGOED AGAINST DELIVERY)<br />
It is always a pleasure to welcome Papua New Guinea's Head of Government<br />
to Australia.<br />
But it is a particular pleasure to welcome you, Mr Prime Minister, because so<br />
much of the tone of the modern relationship between our two countries has<br />
been set by your efforts.<br />
During your last period as Prime Minister, you helped to develop the Joint<br />
Declaration of Principles, which sets out the basis for our relationship.<br />
In that document, we each commit ourselves to conducting relations between<br />
us on the basis of certain fundamental principles mutual respect for one<br />
another's independence, sovereignty and equality.<br />
In the discussions we have just had, and during our earlier meeting on Nauru<br />
last year, it was clear that you and I have a very similar approach to this<br />
relationship. It is a relationship which is important to each of us anchored by geography,<br />
shaped by history, reinforced by mutual economic interests and by the<br />
shared experiences of tens of thousands of citizens from both countries over<br />
many years. </p>
<p>We already have a substantial and mutually rewarding economic relationship.<br />
Our two-way trade is worth $ 2.1 billion and Papua New Guinea now enjoys a<br />
significant trade surplus with Australia. Thirty four per cent of Papua New<br />
Guinea's exports come to Australia, while you, in turn, are a particularly<br />
important market for Australian manufactures.<br />
Australian investment in. Papua-New Guinea is around $ 1.6 billion, making<br />
PNG the ninth-largest destination for Australian investment overseas.<br />
Although this is a good record, you and I both believe that we can do more in<br />
this area.<br />
I know that one of your aims on this visit is to have discussions with the<br />
Australian business community. In that regard it is good to be able to<br />
welcome a number of business people with long-standing interests in Papua<br />
New Guinea to this lunch today.<br />
Visits like this help with the very important function of keeping open the<br />
channels of communication between government and business.<br />
Papua New Guinea's task in building a modern, prosperous and peaceful<br />
nation is a huge enterprise. You have already faced many difficulties in your<br />
efforts to develop your country, and no doubt more lie ahead of you.<br />
But the remarkable thing is how much has been accomplished.<br />
Australia is committed to continuing our help for Papua New Guinea's<br />
development Our development assistance program, worth about $ 300 million a year, is<br />
designed to help the people of Papua New Guinea develop effective and<br />
long-lasting solutions to the challenges the country faces.<br />
As we shift from budget support to jointly programmed aid by the year 2000,<br />
Australian assistance will be targeted in areas that you identify as priorities.<br />
These include education, health and, as we discussed today, law and order.<br />
These form the bedrock on which national development can take place and I<br />
am pleased that Australia will be continuing to work on them with you into the<br />
next century.<br />
But although our ' bilateral ties are important to us both, and will remain so,<br />
there is no doubt that the relationship between us is evolving,<br />
Mr Prime Minister. </p>
<p>We are beginning to see each other as part of a broader region of enormous<br />
promise and great economic dynamism. Your ' look north policy has been<br />
one response to this. Our own deepening engagement with Asia is another.<br />
So it is also a pleasure to welcome you here as a fellow member of APEC.<br />
Both of us have committed our countries to APEC's goal of securing an open<br />
regional economy in Asia and the Pacific, more integrated and open to trade<br />
than ever before.<br />
Another key regional institution in which we both participate is the South<br />
Pacific Forum.<br />
Papua New Guinea and Australia have been working with our colleagues to<br />
make the South Pacific's pre-eminent organisation as effective as possible in<br />
the post-Cold War environment. I look forward to the opportunity we will<br />
have to carry this job forward when we meet in Brisbane in August.<br />
Mr Prime Minister,<br />
Old hands in both our countries sometimes claim that we are drifting apart.<br />
It is true that the relationship between us will never again be as intimate as it<br />
was when Australia was the administering power in PNG, a fact which neither<br />
of us need regret, particularly when as you and I have discussed before<br />
we reflect on some of the architectural legacy we bequeathed you.<br />
And the efforts we have noted on both our parts to develop our links in the<br />
wider Asia-Pacific region mean that, relatively speaking, we may each loom<br />
less large for the other.<br />
So I sympathise with those who think that we need to put more effort into<br />
promoting contacts, particularly between young people from both countries.<br />
We need to take care, on both sides, not to take the relationship for granted.<br />
We need to talk to each other at all levels.<br />
I am very conscious after our meeting today, and following our earlier<br />
discussion on Nauru, just how productive and interesting such contact can<br />
be, and how much of relevance we can learn from each other.<br />
That is another good reason for welcoming you here today, Prime Minister.<br />
I now call on the Leader of the Opposition, Dr Hewson, to join me in this task. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
