<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7929</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF PRIME MINISTER INTERVIEWD BY ROD HENSHAW ON BRISBANE ABC RADIO 4QR 27/02/90</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/02/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007929.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF PRIME MINISTER INTERVIEWED BY ROD HENSHAW ON<br />
BRISBANE ABC RADIO 4QR 27/ 02/ 90.<br />
E 0 E Proof only.<br />
RH: Prime Minister good to see you thanks very much indeed for<br />
making time available to us this morning. You've had a pretty<br />
busy sort of a morning so far.<br />
PM: Well it's been reasonably busy, but I'm going to launch<br />
into an attack on the media.<br />
RH:# Well you've got plenty of them here to listen to you.<br />
PM Right from the very beginning because I discovered that part<br />
of the reason f or the great traf fic jam we were in is that the<br />
media bus in which our people have come here was parked outside<br />
and blocked off one laneway of traffic. So it's the media's<br />
fault again.<br />
RH: ' We were talking to Bluey Thompson there a little while ago<br />
it's probably him that's driving it is it?<br />
PM: Oh I don't know about Bluey, Bluey's a good bloke, I don't<br />
think it was Bluey Rod.<br />
RH: okay, it's nice of you to make time for us this morning,<br />
we've got a lot of listeners that want to talk to you so I won't<br />
take up too much of their time, but just briefly, this morning<br />
the news is that you're going to spend $ 100 million now for the<br />
allocation of road improvements, and that seems a lot of money at<br />
a glance but given the fact that it's for the whole of Australia<br />
are you really pushing that as a big vote catcher?<br />
PM: No it's not pushing it as a big vote catcher. Let's just<br />
get it into perspective Rod, we've spent very, very much more on<br />
roads than the opposition did when they were in Government, 18%<br />
more in real terms comparing the two periods. In annual terms<br />
that's about $ 235 million per annum, in real terms more, so we've<br />
done a lot but we understand that roads are an area of concern.<br />
We're not going to just do the drunken sailor promise of the<br />
Opposition and talk about billions and billions. What I've done<br />
is to say we will impose this increased tax on luxury cars which<br />
will bring in about $ 100 million a year and make that available<br />
to spend on a program which we'll title the Provincial Cities </p>
<p>-2<br />
PM ( cont) s and Rural Highways Program. In co-operation with the<br />
States we'll add that to the very substantial existing funding on<br />
those areas of roads which they regard as most important. In<br />
Queensland here I think that will be particularly useful in<br />
regard to north Queensland and west of the Divide.<br />
RH: How about the Pacific Highway? I think Charles Blunt is<br />
about to he has foreshadowed an announcement later this week on<br />
the Pacific Highway and the dual carriageway between Sydney and<br />
Brisbane? PM: Well, in regard to the Pacific Highway, that part that you<br />
talk about there, what we've said of course is that under the<br />
existing funding that's available and the States funds in NSW if<br />
they wanted to give that the highest priority that would be able<br />
to be done within the sort of timetable that the Opposition is<br />
talking about the next 10, 15, 20 years, it's possible to be<br />
done the whole thing. But, if in regard to this $ 300 million<br />
extra, which is available over the next three years as a result<br />
of this additional promise, the State Government wants to, with<br />
existing funds, add some of this to that purpose then we're<br />
prepared to discuss that too.<br />
RH: okay, well as I said I don't want to take up too much of our<br />
listeners time, but you're pushing the seven years theme as a<br />
Government which has faced up to its problems, it's been<br />
responsible but the fact remains it has been brought up in the<br />
campaign before I know, the fact remains there are still people<br />
out there who are wanting a change from high interest rates, the<br />
highest inflation of any OECD country in the world and the everincreasing<br />
foreign debt. Now can they be blamed perhaps for<br />
questioning whether or not you can arrest that situation. You've<br />
failed in the past what's....<br />
PM: No of course, we haven't failed in the past. The people<br />
out there, you've got to attribute to the Australian electorate a<br />
0 greater degree of intelligence and breadth of perception than<br />
involved in some of those questions Rod. They've got to make a<br />
choice and now you've seen in the last two or three days the<br />
truth that I've been talking about, about 14r Peacock and the<br />
Liberals. They are saying, aren't they, that you want answers.<br />
Well what's been shown now in the debate is that not only have<br />
the Liberals not got the answers they haven't even got the<br />
questions, they can't ask the questions let alone provide the<br />
answers and what you're listeners are going to be saying to<br />
themselves well look course we want lower interest rates, that's<br />
true. But they're going to say what's Mr Peacock saying and<br />
what's he promising that he can do to bring about lower interest<br />
rates, and the answer of course is that inevitably under the<br />
Peacock policies you get an explosion of interest rates. Rod<br />
there are two things which determine what happen to the economy-</p>
<p>-3<br />
PM ( cont) i essentially and interest rates in particular are<br />
included in that, and that's wages policy and what you do with<br />
your Budget. if you can't control wages, if wages blow out then<br />
of course inflation goes through the roof, interest rates go and<br />
the economy collapse. Now, again, on Sunday night Rod, you saw<br />
it I asked Mr Peacock, I said ' at the press conference when you<br />
were asked this critical question, you just said who's to know'<br />
and that's what he said, he said ' who's to know' what will happen<br />
to wages under my policy. So I put it to him again, I said look<br />
if you're talking about reduced interest rates you recognise that<br />
a reduction in inflation rate's important, you must have a target<br />
wage growth in your mind, what is it? No answer. So he can<br />
concede an he must do that there'll be a wages explosion.<br />
Secondly, PM: Well he doesn't concede that, what he actually says is that<br />
his policies<br />
PM: that he doesn't know. He says he doesn't know and he<br />
agrees with the statement that I attributed to him, which he must<br />
do which was on the 31st of August last year, and these were his<br />
exact words, he said ' Australia needs governments to get out of<br />
industrial disputes, to get out of wage fixing as such,<br />
governments just get in the way'. Now those are his exact words<br />
Rod RHt But he threw the same sort of thing back at you with<br />
promises you made<br />
PM: Not on wages he didn't<br />
RH; %** and on those very things that I mentioned there.<br />
PM: On the contrary, you are asking essentially about interest<br />
rates, I'm saying to you that on the critical question of what<br />
determine interest rates Rod, he walks away. He concedes that in<br />
regard to wages there must be a wages explosion. Why do we have<br />
the pilots everywhere I go supporting Mr Peacock? For a very<br />
simple reason that they accept, as they should do, that he meant<br />
what he said on the 31st of August that governments should get<br />
out of disputes, let it be between the parties. That would have<br />
been a 30% wage increase for pilots, it would have been a wages<br />
explosion. So if you have a wages explosion, interest rates<br />
explode. He's got a $ 6 Billion unfunded set of promises so the<br />
deficit explodes. If your deficit explodes and wages explode,<br />
then the economy's gone.<br />
RU: Okay, we'll take some calls our lines are open now, in fact<br />
they're pretty well chokka, so you're speaking with the Prime<br />
Minister. </p>
<p>4-<br />
CALLER Is Hello Mr Hawke how are you. It's Krs Scarf from<br />
Longreach speaking. I was wondering if your Government is reelected<br />
will you be going ahead with the Over Horizon Radar for<br />
north of Australia?<br />
PM: Yes indeed Mrs Scarf I'm glad you asked about that Over the<br />
Horizon Radar because there are two things at least that are<br />
important about it. The first and obvious one is the importance<br />
of it for Australia's forward defence planning which we have<br />
undertaken in a way which has never been equalled before in the<br />
history of this country, and what we're doing, the essence of our<br />
forward defence planning programs is Australia's self-reliance.<br />
And an important part of that as you know is to re-orient our<br />
defence strategy thinking to see that across the north of<br />
Australia we have capacities which enable us to deal with any<br />
potential threat in the future. An intrinsically important part<br />
of that is the concept and then the installation of the Over the<br />
Horizon Radar. What's very interesting, secondly, about it Mrs<br />
Scarf is the magnificence of the Australian scientific<br />
inventiveness and technology that's going into this. Not only<br />
are we going to be providing for Australia, but I'm very proud to<br />
say that other countries are showing a great deal of interest in<br />
what we're doing in this area.<br />
RHt okay, thanks for your question Mrs Scarf we have to move on<br />
because we have a board full of calls.<br />
CALLER 21 Tony Miles here. Mr Hawke, just before I ask a<br />
question may I say I've got two children in the Defence Forces<br />
and you are actually running down the Defence Forces.<br />
PM: Well, of course, that's not right Tony.<br />
TONY: I can argue that however, what I want to know is, I'm<br />
a cleaner, I earn $ 17,000 a year, I want to know as my wages keep<br />
falling because of inflation how you can justify the over-ruling<br />
of the Parliamentary Remuneration Tribunal which awarded you a<br />
postal allowance of $ 9000 and yo4 increased it to in excess of<br />
$ 30,000, which is more than double my wages?<br />
PM: Well, Tony, let me let's get the facts straight in terms<br />
of what I've done about Remuneration Tribunals and salaries. In<br />
that area Tony I have incurred the wrath of many of my colleagues<br />
on both sides of the Parliament because as Prime Minister I took<br />
the view that we would not accept decisions and recommendations<br />
of the Remuneration Tribunal which sought to give us very very<br />
significant increases in salaries, because I took the view Tony<br />
that if we were<br />
TONY: TONY: interjecting.... </p>
<p>PM: Can I please finish my answer Tony I'll do it quickly. I'm<br />
talking about what the Tribunals were talking about with regard<br />
to salaries and I have personally taken the initiative to see<br />
that we didn't get those sorts of increases because I didn't<br />
think it was appropriate that I and other Members of Parliament<br />
should get excessive salary increases if we were asking for<br />
restraint from the rest of the community. On the question of<br />
the postal allowances what has been done there is it's regarded<br />
as important that Members of Parliament who so often get abused,<br />
I guess by you and others for not being in touch and<br />
communicating with their constituents, should have a capacity to<br />
enable them to be in full communication with their constituents<br />
and something which generally has been greeted as it should be.<br />
CALLER 31 Good morning Mr Hawke, at the CHOOM conference you<br />
put forward a motion demanding democracy and increased sanctions<br />
against South Africa. There are 14 African countries in the<br />
Commonwealth and these voted with you demanding democracy in<br />
South Africa. I challenge you to name me one that has democracy<br />
and ask that instead of backslapping when are you going to demand<br />
democracy in these countries?<br />
PH: Well, of course, that's a very convenient way of<br />
overlooking the fact that every country in the Commonwealth<br />
supported the position, with some qualification I suppose on the<br />
part of Mrs Thatcher. If you want to attack the conservative<br />
government of Canada, led by Mr Brian Mulroney and imply that<br />
there's a lack of democracy there, you can do. I'm not saying<br />
indeed that there is an ideal political system in every country<br />
in the Commonwealth. But what I am Baying, and I am saying<br />
vigorously and what is being said by the overwhelming majority of<br />
countries around the world, is that South Africa is absolutely<br />
unique in the world in having an entrenched Constitutional<br />
position which denies to the overwhelming majority of the people<br />
within that country a right to participate in its Parliamentary<br />
and democratic processes simply on the basis of their colour.<br />
There is no other country in the world of which that is true and<br />
that is why it is objectionable arqd that is why the Commonwealth,<br />
together with the United States and the European countries over<br />
several years now, have imposed sanlctions which sanctions have<br />
brought about the changes that are taking place. At no stage<br />
have I wanted sanctions for the sake of sanctions. As I have put<br />
it, I do not encourage sanctions for the Bake of bringing South<br />
Africa to it's knees but to it's senses and fortunately there are<br />
great signs now that South Africa is being brought to it's<br />
senses. I have been a leader in the Commonwealth in pressing for<br />
sanctions, I've also been a leader in the Commonwealth in<br />
welcoming the changes that are now taking place in South Africa.<br />
I welcome greatly the fact that Mandela's been released, I<br />
welcome the sensible statements that he's making there and I hope<br />
and pray that in fact in the period of the not too distant future </p>
<p>-6<br />
PM ( cont) as a result of the things with which we've been<br />
associated and of which I'm proud that we will see the emergence<br />
of South Africa as a true multi-racial, democratic society.<br />
RH: Just taking all those things into consideration, would you<br />
look at relaxing the restrictions which apply to sporting bodies<br />
going to South Africa?<br />
PM I have in fact said that the Commonwealth should now be<br />
prepared to consider these things. I put it very precisely, I've<br />
said I welcome and welcome unqualifiedly the steps that President<br />
De Kierk has taken, I'll put it this way Rod I've said he's now<br />
set the stage for negotiations. Once that stage is actually<br />
occupied and the meaningful negotiations are underway which we<br />
can see are going to lead to the dismantling of the pillars of<br />
apartheid then, of course, we should move.<br />
RH: But if a sporting team went over there tomiorrow they'd<br />
still be rebels wouldn't they? Even given the relaxation of<br />
that... PM: Of course they would be and they understand that. I mean<br />
there is no question but that the present conditions must stay.<br />
But we must also say very clearly that w're ready to move to<br />
lift them. As someone put it in New Zealand when I was over<br />
there when these changes were being announced, you don't get your<br />
gold medals for the heats, you get it for the final. Now what's<br />
happening is we're really setting up the stage... on which the<br />
negotiations will take place and no one will be keener than Bob<br />
Hawke and the Government of Australia to see the sanctions<br />
removed if those real negotiations are taking place and leading<br />
to change because we want I mean what it's all about, is to get<br />
a democratic, multi-racial South Africa as part of the<br />
international community of nations.<br />
CALLER 4 ( from Toowoowba) s Good morning Mr Hawke, I have two<br />
small questions to ask you. in 1972 1 bought a pharmacy for my<br />
daughter. I borrowed $ 100,000 bridging finance at Now after<br />
7 years of your Government overdraft interest now is 22% to 28%,<br />
or 20.5% prime rate. Now that's the interest section of it. Now<br />
the other one is, at that time prescriptions for people were $ 4,<br />
that covered all prescriptions and everything anybody wanted.<br />
Now they cost $ 11 which is an increase of 175% in 7 years or 27%<br />
inflation per year, which is not even shown in the CPI.<br />
RH: Your question is obvious, I wonder could you come to it?<br />
CALLER 4: Well that's it why is the interest rate do<br />
anything about it and what's he going do about the prescriptions.<br />
P14: Okay, I'm glad they're two little questions, I wouldn't </p>
<p>-7<br />
PM ( cont) s have liked two big ones air, but let me deal with the<br />
two little questions that you've asked. Now obviously in regard<br />
to the first you're talking about what's happened to interest<br />
rates. Well Rod and I had a bit of a brief discussion about this<br />
at the beginning. Let me remind you that at no stage under my<br />
period of Government have interest rates reached the peak which<br />
they did under the previous Government, they hit 90 day bill<br />
rates hit 22% in April of 1982, they are now 16%, so we'vye never<br />
cracked the heights of the conservatives. Now I have made no<br />
attempt to hide the fact that last year we had to tighten<br />
monetary policy. I didn't like it as I've said I'm neither a<br />
sadist nor a masochist, I don't want to hurt myself and I<br />
certainly don't want to hurt the people of Australia, but we had<br />
a situation where we had the tightest fiscal policy ever four<br />
successive years of real reductions in Commonwealth outlays,<br />
never been done before, three successive years of surplus, never<br />
been done before. So tight fiscal policy, tight wages policy and<br />
on top of that we had to have tight monetary policy because quite<br />
simply last year our expenditure went up by our production by<br />
4% and the gap was filled by imports which we couldn't afford to<br />
keep bringing in. So, interest rates had to be highI I didn't<br />
like doing it but it's working and the banking industry is now<br />
saying, the banking industry are saying that interest rates will<br />
come down. Now if you want go to the area of prescriptions and<br />
the whole area of health, well look, I suggest that you listen to<br />
the debate today between Mr Shack and my Minister Dr Blewett<br />
because you can then have the opportunity of comparing what this<br />
country would be like under the Liberals or under us in this<br />
whole area. I simply rely, and I ask you to take aboard Mr<br />
Shack's words, this is Mr Shack the Shadow Minister for Health..<br />
this is what he said on the 25th of January this year, a very<br />
recent statement, he said ' the Liberals and the National Party do<br />
not have a particularly good track record on health and I do not<br />
need to remind you of our time in Government'. Now there is a<br />
self-condemnation of our opponents, they wrecked the total health<br />
system of this Government, of this country in Government, they<br />
had 7 years in opposition to come up with a scheme and they've<br />
got to stand up abjectly naked in policy terms on the<br />
January and say ' we wrecked it in Government and in Opposition we<br />
can't come up with an answer'<br />
RH: Your detractors would have it that at least they're being<br />
honest, but no Government has really been able to come to grips<br />
with how to actually conduct feasibly public health.<br />
PM: On the contrary, when we came to office Rod, there were 2<br />
million of your fellow* Australians who were uncovered, who were<br />
faced with the spectre of fear in not being able to meet doctors<br />
bills or hospital bills. We've-brought in a scheme, Medicare,<br />
under which every single one of our fellow Australians now does<br />
not have that fear, they are covered. So we have a scheme which </p>
<p>-8<br />
PH ( cant): is at once universal but fair. it means that I who<br />
have a high salary pay more, and I guess you've got a reasonable<br />
one yo'd pay more, as we should, so that every Australian is<br />
covered. Never been done before, and that scheme is one which is<br />
looked at around the world as being outstanding in terms of its<br />
universality and it's fairness.<br />
CALLER 5; Uhy consensus Bob is it...<br />
PM: Well it's Bob Hawke, I don't know whether that's funny or<br />
not. CALLER 5: Okay well you can say that it's funny or not, but I'd<br />
Just like to say to the voters of Petrie, Forde, Hinkler and<br />
Fisher to reflect on your consideration of our heritage and<br />
basically if you are for consensus as we're led to believe, what<br />
is a better measure of consensus than a referendum on Asian<br />
immigration. Now we have basically two parties with bipartisan<br />
policy on which we cannot vote. If these were two multi-national<br />
corporations and so defying the will of the public the Government<br />
would legislate to change the rules. But when they make the<br />
rules themselves there's no go. Now if you're for consensus and<br />
any number of respected people from academia and any other place<br />
have put up questions that can be held on a referendum, you<br />
continually deny them, your series of failed Immigration<br />
Ministers have denied them, right, so when are you going to give<br />
the will of the Australian public -which is reflected in pollsa<br />
go, consensus?<br />
PM: Well I find that one of the more tortured questions that's<br />
ever been addressed to me but I'll try and make some sense out of<br />
it if I can and as I see the thrust of your tortured question<br />
you're against immigration into this country from Asia. You are<br />
in this democracy entitled to your opinion, but if I wanted to<br />
think of one thing more calculated to condemn the children of<br />
this country to a second, third or fourth-class future, I could<br />
not think of anything more calculated to do that than your racist<br />
position. The fact is that the most dynamic region of the world,<br />
and what will certainly be the most dynamic region of the future<br />
ahead of us, is the Asia-Pacific region and what is implicit in<br />
your question is that you think the people of this region, leave<br />
the morality out of it I'll come to that in a moment, but just<br />
look at the economics of it. You think that the people of this<br />
region will allow a bifocated attitude by Australia to say yes,<br />
Australia, we will buy all your primary products, we'll give you<br />
a share of our manufactured markets, sure, we'll treat you equal,<br />
but we will cop being treated by you as second-class citizens, as<br />
second-class human beings. I'll tell you what the countries of<br />
the region would do, and they'd be entitled to, if you think<br />
we're second class, or third class or fourth class human beings,<br />
well you keep your iron ore, you keep your coal, you keep your. </p>
<p>9-<br />
PH4 ( cont) tourism, you keep everything else because if we're<br />
inferior human beings okay so be it and we'll treat Australia<br />
accordingly. if that's what you want to do for your kids and the<br />
future of this country well, my friend, as 1 say it's a democracy<br />
you're entitled to your view but let me say you couldn't be more<br />
profoundly unpatriotic to this country than entertaining that<br />
view. And, of course, as I say on the morality of it I don't<br />
know whether-you entertain any semblance of christian views,<br />
perhaps you don't perhaps you're contemptuous of them. I just<br />
want to say what I've said before, I happen to believe profoundly<br />
in the concept that I learnt from my father and that is if you<br />
believe int some concept of a God then if there's a fatherhood of<br />
God then we are all brothers and sisters in this world. So I<br />
reject you profoundly in terms of fundamental patriotism for the<br />
future of this country and I reject you profoundly and with total<br />
contempt on moral grounds.<br />
RHt I've been watching your eyes during that dissertation Prime<br />
Minister, you feel quite emotional about that don't you?<br />
PM: Well you can look at my eyes.....<br />
RH: Well we do have eye contact...<br />
PM: I know, I'm simply saying there is nothing that I feel more<br />
deeply about than race. I mean if I were born black, as I could<br />
have been, does that make me a lesser human being? A little<br />
black kid in Africa or a little brown kid in Asia? Are they<br />
inferior human beings because the colour of thetr skin is<br />
different? They're not and this idea that you're better because<br />
of the colour of your skin or the shape of your head or your<br />
eyes. I mean I just find it profoundly objectionable,<br />
profoundly, but as I say more importantly in one sense than moral<br />
repugnance I feel about that Rod, it's my concern as a Prime<br />
Minister for the future of this country. I mean it is so true<br />
S that we would be condemning our kids and their kids to, you know,<br />
third, fourth class economic status if we said to the countries<br />
of Asia and the Pacific you are inferior citizens, we regard you<br />
are so inferior we'll let everyone else in as a citizen but not<br />
you and expect that burgeoning economic part of the world, as<br />
they are, thanks Australia we like the insult that's very nice<br />
but we'll regard you as equals economically when you regard us as<br />
human beings, as inferiors. I mean it would condemn this country<br />
to an abomination of a future.<br />
CALLER 61 Good morning, Bob it's Craig Hardy from Central<br />
Queensland here. We're concerned about the Shoalwater Bay issue<br />
up here. Senator Graham Richardson has recommended to Stewart<br />
West, the Minister for Administrative Services, that sand mining<br />
be allowed in this area. We're concerned because we see it as<br />
the biggest natural area on the whole east coast of Australia </p>
<p>10<br />
CALLER 6 ( cont); South of Cooktown. I do understand that Graham<br />
Richardson has had trouble in coming to his decision, he believes<br />
it's a difficult decision I can understand that. We also believe<br />
the Australian Heritage Commission has looked at it and is<br />
recommending directly against Band mining in this area, so we<br />
seem to have a conflict here. I'm just wondering whether to<br />
resolve the issue and I don't believe the issue has been looked<br />
at properly because of the restrictions placed on the EIS process<br />
in this case I believe this is an ideal situation to be looked<br />
at by the Resource Assessment Commission. We're looking at a<br />
project in isolation, we're not looking at it on a whole project<br />
to try and come to some sort of balance where we can look at<br />
protecting our best areas and maybe looking at mining those areas<br />
that have been degraded elsewhere. I'm just wondering whether<br />
you might be able to give us an undertaking that the Resource<br />
Assessment Commission could look at this project, along with sand<br />
mining in general, rather than allow the leases to be gone ahead<br />
with. PM: Craig what I can say is this to you# you are right in<br />
saying that Senator Richardson, as he is obliged to under the<br />
legislative processes of which you are aware, he's made a<br />
recommendation to the Minister Stewart West. But that is as far<br />
as it's gone. Let me say to you that no decision has been made<br />
by the Governmont and as you appreciate we're in a caretaker<br />
period where no decisions of this sort are taken, but we will<br />
have to consider this matter. After we are re-elected it will<br />
come before the Government and what Senator Richardson has done<br />
is one part of the legislative process. He's put his<br />
recommendation to the other Minister. The Government has not yet<br />
made a decision.<br />
CALLER 7: Mr Hawke, I'm really not clear on what your policy is<br />
on privatisation. Your Ministers appear to be saying quite a lot<br />
of different things and you're very silent on the matter.<br />
PHI Well, let me stop my silence if you think I've been silent,<br />
I haven't been silent on the matter. The first point I want to<br />
make is that in the whole scheme of the economic management of<br />
this country the question of privatisation as you refer to it is<br />
a very peripheral thing in terms of the fundamentals. There is a<br />
very basic difference between the Opposition and ourselves on<br />
this. They have an ideological obsession with privatisation and<br />
they would privatise everything. Now, I've made it quite clear<br />
for instance that as far as I'm concerned I would never<br />
contemplate putting Telecom into private hands because the people<br />
of Australia, and may I say particularly many of the people in<br />
outback Queensland would pay an enormous price if that were done<br />
and we're simply not prepared to contemplate that sort of thing<br />
at all. And there's a difference between us. They would do this<br />
and impose a cost upon the ordinary citizens of this country. As </p>
<p>11<br />
PH ( cont): t far as the two airlines are concerned, within my<br />
party I have the processes being followed now and they are<br />
looking at the way in which the capital requirements of the two<br />
airlines, that's Australian and Qantas, may be satisfied. When<br />
that process is concluded we'll look at that issue. But there<br />
is, as I say, a fundamental ideological difference between the<br />
Labor Party and the others on this. No enterprise would be safe<br />
from privatisation under them, including Telecom, and that would<br />
be something that ordinary Australians would pay a very high<br />
price for if that were ever contemplated.<br />
RH: Okay have we got time for one quick one before<br />
PM: Yea, sure Rod sure.<br />
RHt We've got Rosemary from Toowoomba.<br />
CALLER 8: Good morning, nice to speak to you. Look I don't<br />
understand overseas, you know, the balance of payments at all,<br />
maybe you could help me. Look I can't understand, I think I<br />
heard you say that the Government doesn't have any overseas debt.<br />
Is that right?<br />
PMt That's right, could I just explain it to you. The debt<br />
that Australia has is composed of 63% of it is composed by the<br />
private sector, the private sector owes 63% of it. Fifteen<br />
percent by State Governments and you'll see that this will come<br />
to 103 and I 1ll explain to you why if you don't try and be<br />
smart I'm talking to Rod, Rosemary 63% by the private sector,<br />
by State Governments and 25% by various instrumentalities.<br />
When r came to office the Commonwealth Government owed overseas<br />
debt, but because I've done what's never been done before<br />
Rosemary, that is run the business of the Commonwealth Government<br />
of Australia in surplus for $ 17 Billion for the last three years,<br />
we've used that to pay off overseas debt, and when I say we don't<br />
owe any debt it's because our reserves are more than the small<br />
amount of debt that we owe, we are nett international creditors.<br />
So you, as a citizen of the Commonwealth of Australia in respect<br />
of the Commonwealth Government, owe no debt. How the other part<br />
of the story which is predominantly private debt is yes, that's<br />
high but it represents decisions that have been made by the<br />
private sector on commercial grounds whereby they believe that<br />
they can undertake investment projects which will generate<br />
sufficient income to meet their indebtedness obligations. And,<br />
of course, the other side of that debt Rosemary is that that<br />
borrowing has been used to finance projects like, for instance,<br />
the North West Shelf project, the biggest investment project in<br />
Australia's history, Now that debt which has been borrowed is<br />
now being reflected in the ships plying between the north west of<br />
Australia and Japan, selling our natural gas to Japan and earning </p>
<p>V 12<br />
PM ( cont): us as it will now over the years billions of dollars.<br />
So I'Im not saying that in a complacent sense and indeed that's<br />
why we've got the policies in place to increase the export<br />
capacity of Australian manufacturing industry, we've increased<br />
manufactured exports by 54% in the last 4 years, we're bringing<br />
down imports now, and that will mean that we won't be so exposed<br />
in the future to changes in commodity prices, we'll have a more<br />
structured set of exports which will mean that through time as we<br />
become more competitive increase our own capacity to export and<br />
replace imports, we will gradually bring down that debt to<br />
acceptable and sustainable levels.<br />
RH: Okay, according to one of your minders you have time for<br />
one more Mr Hawke, are you going to sack him after this or<br />
PM: Not at all, as you can see I'm very relaxed about the<br />
questions. RH: Okay our final one, we've been told you have to be at a<br />
place by 10 o'clock...<br />
PM4: Oh well we'll just have to put that back a little bit yes,<br />
Okay. CALLER 9: Good morning Prime Minister 1Tawket it's Graham Brown,<br />
I'm ringing from Christian Heritage College in Mansfield. I just<br />
wanted to congratulate you on behalf of our College for granting<br />
us Austudy. Now we've been trying to get Austudy for about the<br />
last two to two and a half years and at last it's come through<br />
for us and we're just really happy about it and we just wanted to<br />
thank you so much for it.<br />
PM: Well thank you very much Graham. if I could just comment<br />
upon that saying that now, since we've been office, we've trebled<br />
the number of Austudy recipients and that's part of what I in a<br />
sense have the greatest pride in in my Prime Ministership. Could<br />
I just make a brief point to you and your listeners. When I came<br />
to office, only one in three of our kids stayed on in school, and<br />
in their seven years in office the conservatives had lifted that<br />
retention rate from 34% to 36%, just two percentage points. Now,<br />
by more than doubling the secondary education allowances to low<br />
and middle-income families, by trebling the number of Austudy<br />
payments, we now have an Australia in which the retention rate,<br />
or staying on in school, has been lifted to two-thirds, two out<br />
of three of our kids. That's the most fundamontal change that's<br />
been made in this country that now instead of the kids just<br />
mainly from the well-to-do suburbs being sure of staying on, kids<br />
from all areas are staying on in school. That's the fundamental<br />
building block of education to have your kids staying on in<br />
school and it's on that you build what you do in TAFE and the<br />
universities and so on and I think it was an absolute tragedy. </p>
<p>13<br />
PM ( cont); that after 7 years they'd only lifted that retention<br />
by two percentage points, we've lifted it by 26. Moved it from 1<br />
in 3 to 2 in 3 of our kids staying on and Graham, may I say that<br />
I thank you very much because you're part, if I may put it this<br />
way, of a total pattern of a revolution in education in this<br />
country where all our kids are going to have the opportunity to<br />
develop and train their talents.<br />
RH: Okay, we'll have to leave our calls there. Prime Minister<br />
just before you go, we're into week two of the campaign, you're<br />
not going bankers yet?<br />
PM: No, I'm not going bonkers, but I don't think you'd disagree<br />
with me would you Rod that if I'd left it to May the 12th, and<br />
we'd been in election mode from now until then fair chance a lot<br />
of us would have gone bonkers I think. I feel very good.<br />
RHt What about getting rattled. I mean we saw you sweep away<br />
those microphones the other day. No I thought you were actually<br />
going to sweep away a media bus this morning.<br />
PM: Well if the modia bus hadn't been there mate I would have<br />
been here a bit earlier, but no I feel very relaxed, I feel well<br />
and I'm very pleased with the reception that I'm getting around<br />
Australia generally and from interviewers in particular Rod if I<br />
may say so.<br />
RH: Mr Hawke many thanks for your time this morning.<br />
PM: Thank you.<br />
Ends<br />
4 1 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
