<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6278</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF RADIO INTERVIEW, GOA, 27 NOVEMBER 1983</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/11/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006278.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF RADIO INTERVIEW, GOA, 27 NOVEMBER 1983<br />
LOMBARD: INAUDIBLE<br />
PM: I don't want to overstate it, we've had some relaxation<br />
aind we've had some tennis and an attempt at windsurfing,<br />
but there has been a lot of work involved, John, yes.<br />
LOMBARD: This is the first international gathering that<br />
you've attended at such level as Prime Minister. How do<br />
you find the contacts you've made here?<br />
PM: Very useful. Very wide ranging and they have been, if you<br />
I-1ke, in two sorts of categories. One, we have to deal with<br />
particular issues and problems as I did with Mr. Lee and<br />
Ghazali Shaffie, the Malaysian Foreign Minister. Other particular<br />
issues, where I've talked with Robert Mugabe of Zimbabwe,<br />
Kenneth Kuanda of Zambia and Nyere of Tanzania on the issue<br />
of their domestic economy suffering from drought and in that<br />
context I have offered additional wheat aid to them<br />
there has been the more general opportunity of just getting to<br />
know people like Mrs. Thatcher, Mrs. Gandhi and so on. That<br />
has been extremely useful and it will be very useful for<br />
Australia into the future.<br />
MILLS: Mr. Hawke, why is Australia taking part in the group<br />
action on Cyprus?<br />
PM: Basically because we were asked to. Secondly, because<br />
we do believe that we have got a contribution that we can make<br />
and thirdly, there are particular reasons why we should and<br />
amongst those particular reasons are two first, we have a<br />
very large community in Australia of Cypriot origin, as you<br />
know. Secondly, we have continuously had an involvement in the<br />
police force in Cyprus. So have the reason to be involved.<br />
We have the capacity to make a contribution and we were<br />
nominated as one of the five to be in the group.<br />
MILLS: You said that the Commonwealth group would work with<br />
the United Nations. What would the Commonwealth group be able<br />
to do that the United Nations alone wouldn't be able to achieve?<br />
PM: Well, Cyprus is a member of the Commonwealth and I believe<br />
Eiiat that of itself means that the Cypriot authorities would<br />
have a greater degree of confidence in knowing that they were<br />
working with a group from their own international brotherhood,<br />
if you like to put it that way. And the further point I would<br />
make is that in the discussions that have taken place before<br />
the CHQGM meeting, when Mr. Ramphal, the Secretary-General of<br />
the Commonwealth and de Cuel. lar, the United National Secretary-<br />
General, there had been apparently a view expressed from the<br />
United Nations that this sort of approach could be of assistance. / 2 </p>
<p>LOMBARD: Prime Minister, there has been a tremendous amount<br />
of work done at the CHOGM. H-as this altered your view of<br />
the Commonwealth as a useful instrument for getting things done?<br />
PM: Well, I've always thought it was a useful body. I've<br />
niever been one to be overtaken by the mysticism of this<br />
organisation and I would always caution those who tend to get<br />
carried away by that element of it. There would seem to me<br />
to be sufficient evidence in the past of concrete achievements<br />
for it to be worthwhile continuing and yes, this involvement<br />
has confirmed that view because if you look firstly at Cyprus,<br />
I think we can with a considerable degree of justification<br />
say that we had made a decision here which could lead to the<br />
processes of resolution being more sharply defined and<br />
perhaps the resolution may be achieved more quickly as a<br />
result of what we ' ye done.<br />
LOMBARD: On the question of Grenada.<br />
PM: I'm just coming to Grenada. If you look there, when we'<br />
sitarted off in New Delhi it was a very bitter debate. People<br />
who had been here a long time said amongst the most bitter<br />
that there has been in the history of the Commonwealth. Now,<br />
from that we came down here to Goa to the retreat, a pretty<br />
torrid debate still continuing, then a working group<br />
which contained representatives of the Organisation of Eastern<br />
Caribbean States which had supported the action in Grenada,<br />
one or two that hadn't and a representative of Africa which<br />
had taken a strong line against. They came up with an agreed<br />
document which, when it came back into the full meeting of<br />
the Heads of Commonwealth, was debated at length and somewhat<br />
amended, but now we have a common document. Now, it seems to<br />
me that that is a greater significance for the international<br />
debate. It has a great significance, I think, for the debate<br />
with any country because what has now come out is an<br />
understanding that your solid arguments in the minds of the<br />
Caribbean states some of them for the actions that were<br />
taken and what has been said now, well let's not indulge in<br />
recriminations,* let's look to the future and all heads of state<br />
welcomed the emergence of the interim administration. All of<br />
them. And they're saying, now, let's work with that and<br />
hopefully there will be the withdrawal of foreign troops, the<br />
states of the area will provide, it is hoped, forces to<br />
assist in the maintenance of law and order and from that<br />
situation the Commonwealth leaders have indicated a readiness to<br />
give sympathetic consideration in any requests for help not<br />
forces, but help that would be relevant to the needs of the<br />
state in that area. Now, that seemed to me to be a very<br />
significant achievement.<br />
MILLS: Mr. Hawke, on the economic front. What support have<br />
you received to your contribution on Friday that the<br />
international monetary system, the international financial<br />
institutions, don't need changing, they simply need<br />
strengthening and being put into the position where they are<br />
better able to help the developing countries? / 3 </p>
<p>PM: Well, may I say modest, I've received very widespread<br />
and strong support for the contribution that I made on<br />
Australia's behalf and I make the judgement now. It's early,<br />
of course, because the debate is going to go on, but I make<br />
the judgement now that the sort of thrust which I injected<br />
into the debate is likely to be the one that is reflected.<br />
That is that you have got to recognise that firstly, the<br />
elements are that you've got to recognise that the<br />
significant dimensions of the problems confronting the<br />
international community. Secondly, as I was trying to say,<br />
we've got to recognise in the dimensions of the problem<br />
then be realistic in our proposal and by that I mean<br />
particularly, that anything that was done has got to be able<br />
to attract the support of the major industrialised countries<br />
who provide the main sinew for any international institutions<br />
that are going to operate and from that I went to the third<br />
point that we should recognise that the existing<br />
international institutions have done a good job in not only<br />
handling the financial relations between the debtor countries<br />
and creditor nations, but also in facilitating the line with<br />
the private financial institutions and it makes sense to try<br />
and get a situation in which those institutions are going to<br />
be strengthened and so I emphasised in that context the<br />
importance of IMF, general arrangements to buyers and in<br />
regard to the international development.... that we get a<br />
position where the replenishments would have to be fixed by<br />
July of next year, are in fact fixed by that time because that<br />
is very important because that is the area of concessional<br />
finance. What I've been trying to say is let's concentrate<br />
on the existing institutions, see that their lines are filled<br />
according to the timetables that are there now. If we then<br />
find that those existing institutions require some supplementation,<br />
then let's examine the track in regard to the IMF, there are<br />
a range of options and the concept of special drawing rights,<br />
the opportunity of getting correct lines through to the central<br />
banking system of various countries or the opportunity of going<br />
onto the private market. Those are alternatives that are<br />
available and it may be that we will have to look at that down<br />
the track. But, first of all, try and make sure the existing<br />
institutions under their existing provisions are equipped<br />
to do the job even better than they have to this point. Now, on<br />
that sort of thrust, I think, is correct. It is realistic and,<br />
as I say, the evidence seems to me to be there to suggest that<br />
that sort of thrust, which I have suggested, does recommend<br />
itself to the majority of people present. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
