<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8924</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ KEATING, MP COROWA SHIRE COUNCIL CENTENARY DINNER, COROWA RSL CLUB 31 JULY 1993</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>31/07/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008924.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
a EMBARGOED UNTIL 9. OOPM<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVE~ RY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, NWP<br />
COROWA SHIRE COUNCIL CENTENARY DINNER, COROWA RSL CLUB<br />
31 JULY 1993<br />
It i3 a great pleasure to be in ti very beautiful, historic, classic Australan town.<br />
It is particularly good to be here to join in the commemoration of the moment a hundred<br />
years ago when Corowa was host to one of the more important gatherings in our nation's<br />
history: a meeting which, in a combination of national idealism and equally characteristic<br />
pragmatism helped propel Australia towards nationhood.<br />
Enough of the Victorian architecture has been preserved, enough families have remained,<br />
enough memories handed down for Corowa to still speak eloquently of the past.<br />
And thcn there is the river: the Murray tells a story of its own, including of course the part<br />
it played in the -federation of the continent.<br />
For it was the dividing line between the two most populous and prosperous colonies and.<br />
in 1893, on the other side at Wahguinyah therc was a customs shed, a real and symbolic<br />
manifestation of the divisions the people of Australia had to overcome.<br />
You don't have to look hard in towns like this to see the labour that has been done, and the<br />
aspirations of those who did it<br />
Far more than in the cities and the suburbs, you can sense the traditions born here of work<br />
and leisure, of individual enterprise and community cooperation, of a common effort<br />
through good times and bad.<br />
In one sense the story is all Corowa's own. In another it is a typically Australian story.<br />
1T monuments to war, for instance, can be seen in every Australian town.<br />
They bear witness to the sacrifice of famnilies in this region, but also to the common cause<br />
Australians evrhr recognised in times of crisis.<br />
ITO~ J TOr) ro InccOF:;, 6nH' 7 </p>
<p>Thcre are other kinds of monuments: monuments to imagination and effort monuments to<br />
belief in the region's future, and ultimately in AtIstr1ia future.<br />
I mean the farms, this township, the industries, the clubs. And it's useful to reflect on how<br />
they camre to be.<br />
What were the essential elements in their success?<br />
And the answer is private initiative, public cooperation, loyalty and commitment to the<br />
region, confidence, belief.<br />
In every Australian community you will see the samie combination of elements, and over<br />
time, it seems to me they form a collective national experience.<br />
For all our disparity including the great gulf between rural and urban there is in the end<br />
a collectivc Australian experience which should unite us.<br />
Nationally, we have shared in triumphs in sport, in the arts, in industry and science.<br />
But the greatest by far is the creation over the ycars of one thc world's great democracies,<br />
one of the great multicultural societics, and surely the very best place in the world to live.<br />
And we have done this substantially because our effort in the last century has generally<br />
been towards including all Australians in Australia's wealth.<br />
This is a loose federation on a vast and varied contincnt whose population is immensely<br />
diversc in origin and culture.<br />
These factors can encourage division or fragmenrttion they can encourage jealousy and<br />
rivalry, between States, between cities, between the urban population and the people in the<br />
country. There is always that tendency latent or real. But the great majority of Australians<br />
understand, as the founders of federation understood, that we work much better when we<br />
work as one nation.<br />
These individual and collective efforts, these successes and failures, constitute the unifying<br />
experience of our naitional life.<br />
Whether we live in Corowa or Darwin or Wahgunyah this is the story of us all, and the<br />
means by which we recognise each other as Australians.<br />
And this gives us strength.<br />
/ 7_ Od TOO-ON 92: 8 l~ </p>
<p>3<br />
This and future generations living here in Corowa will continue to draw their strength from<br />
these traditions and from their love of the country, and it will be this as much as anything<br />
else which carries the district through another century.<br />
But I daresay if the people of Corowa were asked what most concerns them today, it<br />
would not bc the past hut the future.<br />
What industries will employ them and their children?<br />
What businesses will grow to replace those in decline?<br />
How will the future of Corowa be secured?<br />
They are the same questions which Australians ame asking everywhere -in every town and<br />
suburb, in every factory and farm.<br />
How will the future of Australia be secured?<br />
It is a question which every generation has asked, including the generation of 1893.<br />
They had every reason to ask-they were living through the worst depression in our<br />
history, the worst civil strifc and the worst drought<br />
The answer to the question in 1893 or 1933 or even 1963 tended to he by secure British<br />
markets for our agricultural products, by the protection of local industry, by the<br />
exploitation of our minerals and energy.<br />
But by 1973 the secure British markets for Australian agriculture had gone.<br />
It was becoming plain that protection had left our industries hopclessly uncompetitive.<br />
And dependence on commodities left us still exposed to the uncertainties of world markets.<br />
So if Britain would no longer secure our future, nor the United States or any other<br />
country, and our commodities alone would not alone secure it, and wholesale protection of<br />
our industries would not, how could it be secured?<br />
The answer was, and remains by our own efforts. by our own imagination, by grasping<br />
the opportunities which our region provides, by confidence in ourselves and our best<br />
traditions, by belief. By those same familiar things which carry Corowa through.<br />
And I know we will secure the future. I know we can be prosperous as never bcfore. We<br />
can find a place in the world as never before.<br />
And we can find it primarily in our own region in that part of the world which the<br />
Australians of a century ago looked at with a mixture of fear and disdain.<br />
/ OdTOO'ON 92: 3 œ Bl~ 1. </p>
<p>4.<br />
We can secure our future in the huge and rapidly growing Asia-Pacific region. And in the<br />
rest of the world.<br />
And I'll tell you why I know this. Because of the succc-ss we have already had.<br />
In 1993 we are losing industries but gaining new ones. We are replacing old markets with<br />
new ones.<br />
We are steadily growing less dependent on commodities.<br />
We are growing new companies clever manufacturing companies, born entirely of the<br />
export culture created in the last decade.<br />
In the last five years they have boosted their exports to Asia by an average 20 per cent per<br />
annum. They are exporting elaborately transformed manufactures. High tech products.<br />
Last year exports of elaborately transformed manufactures to Europe rose by more than<br />
per cent; to South East Asia by 17 per cent; to East Asia by more than 40 per cent.<br />
IThe opportunities for Australian companies in Asia and the Pacific are boundless, and as<br />
we continue to trasform ourselves into a competitive and sophisticated manufacturing<br />
nation, and a leading supplier of services as well as agricultural products, minerals and<br />
energy, we will begin to see the huge rewards to be reaped from the changes we made in<br />
the eighties.<br />
And I might say the great agricultural regions of Australia regions like this one foodgrowing<br />
regions, will play a pre-eminent role in the future.<br />
That is why I belicve we will succeed: bccause of the success we havc already achieved.<br />
Because of the proven willingness of the Australian people to embrace change.<br />
Because when faced with necessity they were prepared to do what was necessary.<br />
So while the answer to the question has varied with time, one thing has not changed: the<br />
future of Australia like thc future of Corowa will ho made safe by the enterprise and<br />
work of the people.<br />
And by their faith in themselves, in their communities and in Australia.<br />
We will always need that faith.<br />
L/ t O 10 N 9: 26-6nHiZ: 3 </p>
<p>In this last decade of the twentieth century we have a chance the lilke of which the<br />
Australians of a century ago could not have imagined.<br />
There is the chance to succeed in the world's fastest growing region, and to do it by our<br />
own initiative, our own effort, our own genius.<br />
There is, as I have said before, the chance in this decade to set Australia up for the next<br />
century. I can tell you that that is my one great goal. It is the Government's goal<br />
But reaching it, needless to say, will depend on it becoming the goal of all Australians.<br />
Last week I made again the point that I have made many times in the past cighteen months:<br />
to meet the challenges we face we need a renewed sense of national unity.<br />
I quoted someone who I am sure retains more than a little respect in this district, Robert<br />
Gordon Menzies.<br />
It was Menzies who talked about the need to convert " a mass of individuals into a great<br />
cohesive nation."<br />
Menzies understood the power that a common national sentiment commands.<br />
And even if there is little else he said with which I would agree, I agree with him on this.<br />
Of course, he saw the British monarchy as the powerful unifying element.<br />
But these days, while the British monarch still has our affection and our regard, there is no<br />
question that the monarchy commands much less of both.<br />
In truth I think this decline has less to do with the problems the royal family has recently<br />
faced, than it has to do with changes in Australia, changes in the relationship between<br />
Australia and Great Britain, and an understanding in both countries of the different<br />
necessities we face.<br />
The monarchy has had family problems at other times in the past, hut Australians did not<br />
draw the conclusion that the monarchy had lost its relevance.<br />
Today they draw that conclusion because the monarchy is remote from their lives and<br />
perceived as inappropriate to the sort of nation we must become.<br />
If thc challenge is to enliven our spirit, to create a new unity of purpose, to make this a<br />
more inclusive Australia, or to use Menzies' words, to convert a " mass of individuals into a<br />
great cohesive nation" there is only one place it can come from. Australia.<br />
OdTOO'ON 9' 2: 8 6flHn : 13. </p>
<p>From faith in this democracy. Our shared values and hopes, shared understanding of our<br />
past and the necessities which confront us.<br />
T7hat is why I believe Australian affairs should be managed by Australians.<br />
It is why I am for a republic.<br />
Not because I am against Britain I like Britain very much.<br />
I was raised on her heritage and the cxploits of British heroes and remain a grateful and, in<br />
many regards, a passionate advocate of things British from the parliamnt~ and law<br />
bequeathed us to the art and architecture and music.<br />
But Australia's diverse heritage is uniquely our own. So in many respects is our<br />
democratic heritage: it includes not just the fabled spirit of the " fair go" and the collective<br />
egalitarian tradition, but a number of constitutional innovations which were achieved here<br />
well in advance of Britain among them the secret ballot, payment of MPs, universal male<br />
suffrage and votes for women.<br />
Nor am I against the British monarch I count myself among her countless Australian<br />
admirers. But the Queen of Australia is not Australian and, however conscientiously and<br />
skilfully she performs the role of Australian Head of State, she cannot symbolise or express<br />
our Australianess.<br />
Nor am I against the British monarchy the British monarchy works in Britain. But it is a<br />
hereditary British institution and in the multicultural post-imnperial world in which we live<br />
and, with all the regional imperatives now facing us, it no longer constitutes an appropriate<br />
Australian [ Head of State.<br />
Nor am I against the British Commonwealth of Nations Australia, so long as I amn Prime<br />
Minister, will remain in the Commonwealth. Membership of thc Commonwealth<br />
comprised of more Yepublics than any other category of government is not part of the<br />
argument. Nor do I think the republican debate distracts from thc economic problems which currently<br />
beset us it is no more a distraction for Australians than Federation was for those<br />
Australians of the 1890s whose economic problems makc ours seem insignificant.<br />
And, as Barry Jones said the other day, we don't hear people saying that we should give up<br />
A sport until the economy improves, though much more time is spent on sport than the<br />
Constitution. Nor am I for thc republic because I am against the States IJike many Australians I am<br />
conscious of the shortcomings of the Federal system, and I would like to see rcgions like<br />
this urnc given a more dynamic political role: but I believe the States are an organic part of<br />
/ 9d TOO. 0N ' 92: 83 œ 6U </p>
<p>7-<br />
the Australian nation and quite possibly inseparable from it. I do not believe they could be<br />
easily abolished even if the nation thought it was worth doing.<br />
Some say the republic will undermine our stability. I value stability and place the highest<br />
value on the social peace we enjoy in Australia.<br />
To the extent that British institutions have contributed to this I appreciate that too.<br />
But Australian institutions also gave us these things.<br />
The idea of social justice, and government policies which gave that idea concrete<br />
expression, played a major part in our stability.<br />
We did not build this stable, sophisticated and harmonious multicultural society with<br />
British institutions half so much as we built it with Australian principles and policies.<br />
It is also said by opponents of the republic that it is primarily a manifestation of my<br />
ambition. Insofar as I have played a role in instigating the debate, they are right.<br />
I have an ambition for Australia and the republic forms part Of it.<br />
Nf an ambition for Australia disqualifies the republic, then those who met here in 1893<br />
should have been disqualified from Federation, along with every one else who ever had an<br />
ambition for Australia and acted On it.<br />
I am for the republic not for what I am against, but what I am for not for what a republic<br />
will throw away, but for what a republic can deliver:<br />
It can deliver a new sense of unity and national pride in which Australians of this and<br />
future generations can share.<br />
It can deliver a re-cast Australian identity defined by the commitment of Australians to this<br />
land above all others, which will say unequivocally to the world who we are and what we<br />
stand for.<br />
Among them I would number democracy, fairness, tolerance, justice, invention, industry,<br />
pragmatism. They will all -serve us well in the new world we have cntered.<br />
I would go so far as to suggest that had we long enshrined the values of tolerance and<br />
fairness, and had we more faith in our own traditions and more commitment to them, more<br />
confidcnce and pride, the dcbate about the Maho judgement would not have taken the<br />
shape it too often has in the past few months.<br />
/) flA--o6on : i :-131lH </p>
<p>Had those values become the basis of our national pride we might have asked: what good<br />
would it do us as a people, what would it do for future generations of Australians, what<br />
would it do for our reputation in the world as a mature democracy, if we said the Hi-gh<br />
Court was wrong Australia was never occupied before 1788, there never was native title,<br />
injustice and dispossession did not occur what good would it do us if we enshrined lies in<br />
preference to the truth?<br />
What would it say to future generations if in 1993 Australians could not face up to what<br />
the United States, Canada and New Zealand faced up to a century and more ago?<br />
What would it say about this generation of ours if, when we were offered the truth, we<br />
chose to perpetuate untruths?<br />
What would it say about us if, a hundred years after sixty men in Corowa had the wisdom<br />
to see the necessity for Federation, the will to do it, and the wit to know how, we recoiled<br />
from the chance to find a national solution to our oldest problem?<br />
If we turned away from our responsibilites? If we failed to see the legal recognition of<br />
prior ownership and post-European dispossession as providing a basis for reconciliation?<br />
Our duty is to find a mature national solution.<br />
My hope is that In finding one we wil re-learn a little of the value of Australian democracy,<br />
the principles of tolerance and justice, and the necessity to find common cause as a people<br />
that we will re-learn it and pass the lesson on to future generations. Perhaps that will be<br />
the lesson of Mabo.<br />
By their initiative the people who met here in 1893 served generations of Australians,<br />
I believe in this last decade of the twentieth century we need to look beyond the day-today<br />
and towards the next generations of Australians.<br />
If it is true, as I think it is, that this and future generations will be best served by revisiting<br />
the Constitution drawn up a century ago, then we can learn something from the approach<br />
taken at the Corowa Conference.<br />
In 1893 Federation was, as one commentator observed " dead as Julius Caesar".<br />
The Corowa Conference revived it.<br />
Anid it revived it by turning Federation into a poul~ cause. The conference itself was not<br />
a government initiative, but one promoted and paid for by private enterprise by private<br />
indus tries.<br />
T1O0 QM j: 26* 6ntU : 131 </p>
<p>The decisive resolution which wasq passed here called on the colonial parliaments to pass<br />
legislation that would provide for the popular elction of representatives to a national<br />
convention to draw up a Federal Constitution.<br />
That constitution would be submitted to referendum in each colony.<br />
The Corowa Conference gave the people of Australia the opportunity to claim their own<br />
destiny to forge a new national entity from a far-Rlung colonial population.<br />
And the people grasped the opportunity.<br />
The Constitution was the foundation of the new national entity.<br />
ReAd in 1993, it is an uninspired and uninspiring document; complex, lcgalistic and<br />
virtually impossible to relate to contemporary Australian life.<br />
It was framed as a routine piece of nineteenth century British imperial legislation. It shows<br />
its age.<br />
A great many Australians don't even know it exists. Very, very few have ever read it, let<br />
alone understood it.<br />
How many Australians could quote the opening words? Not half as many, I suspect, as<br />
could quote the opening of the US constitution.<br />
In the 1990s there exists the chance and I think the need to revisit our Constitution and<br />
reclaim it, not for the lawyers and the politicians, but for the people.<br />
In Australia, surely in this most democratic of countries we can have a constitution<br />
vested in the people.<br />
It is hardly radical to suggest that our Constitution should bc remade to reflect our national<br />
valucs and aspirations, evoke pride in our Australian heritage and confidence in our future,<br />
and help to unite us as a nation.<br />
It is hardly radical to suggcst this, and hardly beyond us to do it.<br />
We want Australians to consider the strengths and weaknesses of their Constitution.<br />
We want them to debate the advantages and disadvantages of making our Constitution<br />
more closely reflect Australian reality, Australian values, Australian hopes.<br />
In the cnd we want an Australian Constitution in which Australians bclieve.<br />
As I see it, the republic can be very much the precursor to enabling the people to reclaim<br />
the Constitution.<br />
/ 6O* d TOO* oN 92: 8 26-6nd, 71 </p>
<p>Last April wc established the Republic Advisory Committee to work on an options paper<br />
which will set out some of the ways Australia could become a republic and the consequent<br />
changes to our Constitution.<br />
The Committee has consulted widely over the past few months, and the debate as you<br />
have probably noticed is now flourishing in the community.<br />
Following the report of the Committee in September. the Government will consider ways<br />
to ensure that people have sufficient information about our system of government to<br />
participate fully in the decision-making process.<br />
In thc end, as with Federation, it will be the people of Austr-alia who decide.<br />
After they have had time and information enough to consider the issues, the people will<br />
decide by referendum whether we move to a republic or remain a constitutional monarchy.<br />
No one should forget the fundamental point enshrined in the existing Constitution the<br />
only way this or any other constitutional change can take place is by refercndum, It cani<br />
only occur if the people want it if a majority of electors voting, and a majority of clectors<br />
in the majority of the States, vote for change.<br />
Changed or unchanged, the Australian Constitution belongs to Australians and only they<br />
can decide how and when and if to change it.<br />
By way of conclusion, let me go back to the Murray. The Murray says it better than I can.<br />
Tis is the river which divides New South Wales and Victoria, the river along which<br />
customs houses were erected in colonial days.<br />
Viewed one way it can be a real and symbolic obstacle to unity. Yet the Murray is both a<br />
national resource and a unifying national symbol. We bold it in common.<br />
The Murray did not dictate that customs houses be built along the banks.<br />
The Murray was not a border until Australans made it one.<br />
It was not the existence of the Murray which persuaded politicians to run a railway line<br />
south from Sydney in one gauge and north from Melbourne in a different one.<br />
Yet Australians also combined in the national interest to remove the customs and to<br />
standardise the rail line. They combined to harness the water for power and conserve it for<br />
irrigation. They are combining now to restore the environment of the Murray-Darling Batsin and to<br />
rectify the great problem of salination and land degradation. I believe we can combine in<br />
/ OT'd TOO'ON 9S: 8 2j6* 6nH'Z :-3 </p>
<p>11<br />
future to make the Murray-Darling the basis of a hugely expanded Australian food.<br />
growing and food-processing industry.<br />
The choice is always ours: we can pursue local interests or sectional interests or state<br />
interests. We can always ind in our landscape, our laws, and our history re asons for division.<br />
Or we can combine. We can pursue the national interest.<br />
We can do as the Ausuralians of the 1890s voted to do and draw our strength from the<br />
Commonwealth. The republic seeks closer identification with the nation, and a more spirited sense of<br />
national goals and purpose. It also seeks to bring our institutions and symbols into line<br />
with reality.<br />
The States are part of that reality as the states are part of United States reality. The<br />
proper aim is to get all three fiers of government working for national ends.<br />
My argument is that in this era above all others the overriding loyalty must be to the<br />
nation. Let me conclude by addressing the most common argument against an Australian republic.<br />
The one which says " i it ain't broke, don't fix it",<br />
It partly depends on your definition of broke.<br />
If it's an anachronism is it broke?<br />
If it no longer inspires us, or fails to unite us, or offers us no belicf, and therefore<br />
effectively doesn't work, is it broke?<br />
If it does not coincide with contemporary reality, is it broke?<br />
And if we decide now that it's not broke, and in twenty or thirty years time that Australians<br />
not only fail to identify with Britain but also with Australia, will we decide then that it was<br />
broke all along?<br />
Broke doesn't really come into it.<br />
We didn't throw out the horse and cart because they were broke. We abandoned them:<br />
we affcctionately and gracefully retired them when thcy became obsolete.<br />
We took a considered decision to trade up to something that would serve us better.<br />
! K/ TTd IOO* ON 92':' S 6~~. 3 </p>
<p>12<br />
' That is what the people who gathered here in 1893 did.<br />
They knew that Federation would serve Australia better. They saw themselves as having a<br />
responsibility to their country and its future.<br />
Who would say to them now why did you fix it when it wasn't broke?<br />
Thank you for having me here tonight. It has been a great pleasure for me.<br />
Corowa was there in 1893 when a great national endeavour began in earnest.<br />
I hope that some of what I have said tonight has helped define to you what I believe is<br />
another great national endeavour.<br />
A hundred years ago when the colonies soon to become states wcre supreme, and their<br />
primacy was manifest in those customs houses along the river, the people who gathered<br />
here in Corowa stepped out of the orthodoxy and said, we need to be a nation we need<br />
one government in charge of our national affairs.<br />
I should hope in the prevailing orthodoxy of today, having made the step to a national<br />
government almost a century ago, the people gathered in Corowa here tonight can see the<br />
sense again in stepping beyond the orthodoxy.<br />
I hope they can see the sense in that final assertion of nationhood the confidence to elect<br />
one of our own to preside over our affairs.<br />
I notice today the Sydncy Morning Herald writing off the people of Corowa as<br />
conservative, not blatantly but patronisingly, seeming to suggest that the people here<br />
tonight can't see as far as the people of Corowa one hundred years ago.<br />
Well I doubt that. I think, like an increasing number of Australians, they will see the nccd<br />
to put the seal ofl our nationhood.<br />
I think they will feel themselves very capable or taking the view that the affairs of Australia<br />
cannot forever bc presided over by a British monarch.<br />
Tonight we are cclebrating the vision which found expression heme a ccntury ago. I think<br />
no more fitting tribute could be paid to their memory than to complete the work that they<br />
began. In 1993, as in 1893, 1 think we must havc the courage to see bcyond what is to what can<br />
be. ENDS<br />
/~ dTOO* ON 92: 8 266H7 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
