<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>122</transcript-id>
    <title>TRIBUTE TO THE LATE MR CAHILL - BY THE PRIME MINISTERIN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES ON THURSDAY, 22ND OCTOBER 1959</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/10/1959</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000122.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRIBUTE TO THE LATE MR. -CAHILL<br />
BY THE PRIME MINISTER IN THE HOUSE OF REPRES8N-<br />
-TATIVES ON THURSDAY, 22ND OCTOBER,. l9a9<br />
Mr. Speaker, honourable members will be aware of the<br />
fact that after an illness which it was hoped was purely minor<br />
and temporary, Mr. Cahill, the Premier of New South Wales, died<br />
this morning, I think none of us would wish this unhappy occasion<br />
to pass without reference to it being made! in this House.<br />
Mr. Cahill was, of course, much too young to die, but he had for<br />
many years worked with great devotion and great energy for the<br />
causes that he believed in and for the State over whose political<br />
fortunes he was called to preside.<br />
During the time I have been Prime Minister I saw a<br />
great deal of Mr. Cahill. I will always be pleased to remember<br />
that I had the greatest respect for him, and that we lived,<br />
though on opposite sides of politics, on terms of close personal<br />
friendship. I think he was a man of integrity and a man of<br />
devotion to the cause that he understood and which he did so<br />
much to lead. When one knows a man of that kind one inevitably<br />
expresses sadness at the news of his death.<br />
It may perhaps be of some comfort to those he has<br />
left behind to knew, as they will know when the record of these<br />
few minutes is produced, that though he was strongly attached<br />
to his party, and never unwilling to break a lance in the political<br />
lists, he died, nevertheless, holding the respect, and, I<br />
think, the affection of everybody in this place. I make only<br />
those few remarks. It is difficult to say very much. I have<br />
been shocked by this news; so have we all. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
