<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5830</transcript-id>
    <title>COUNTRY-LIBERAL PARTY DINNER, DARWIN</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/06/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005830.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR t'SDIA COUNTRY-LIBERAL PAWPT<br />
it is a great pleasure for Tamiie<br />
I gl in Dan-iin tonight. Already ill t<br />
iii the Territory, I have been va<br />
and progressive approach that ar<br />
potential so strongly and rapidi<br />
Yesterday, at Alice Springs, Aye<br />
Isaw4 something of the ex: citing<br />
being devoloped in those places.<br />
aAyers 1, with the $ 100 mill<br />
adthat Uhlr Natial Pdak gil<br />
to the whJora nta ra, AnPam~ de<br />
that Wal. Ffwaabetdyo<br />
proposalsfoth eoainf<br />
at Darwin Airport, details of th<br />
for consideration in the for thco<br />
everyone is loolking forw~ ard to<br />
Thi8 Trorining I opened the newo<br />
As you kn~ ow, Xakradu is now inclu<br />
List, both for its natural and<br />
wiith its fragile and unique beau<br />
places, it -really is one of the<br />
it is a cause for 3real pride tha<br />
looxed after in a way that allow<br />
proper us; e of it.<br />
There is great progresps in the T<br />
hsGov'crrnent are giviing a trem<br />
anfd their sound policies, and U-i<br />
government tO the Territory was<br />
present level of achieverient her<br />
of Territorialls here in Darwin,<br />
is proceeding at a pace which in<br />
continued growtU1 of prosperity i<br />
as a Ywhcle, We see it reflected<br />
has abov. t double. the major proje<br />
onl the basis of its shave of emp<br />
.4 and We s; ee it reflected in thie f<br />
Territor: y in thd yea. r to lkpri1 w,<br />
even th( se which pridea themnsel. e<br />
AustraliLa's developmnent.<br />
A MO4APRGO: 10.00 PM EST<br />
IIONDPAV,' 7-IJUNS 1982<br />
Yi DINNER, DARWIN<br />
arid me to be x. ith you here<br />
he t-wo Or three days I ) lave been<br />
stly impressed with thie drive<br />
e devel~ oping the Territory's<br />
Vs RocO: and Tennant Creek,<br />
plans and initiatives that care<br />
The new Conriellan AirpofL<br />
ion Yulara ToIrist Village<br />
ob) viously give a major boost<br />
lightced, as I an Eure yoo arLe,<br />
release plans concerning<br />
civil aviation activities<br />
Is project %-ill be presentecl<br />
mng Budget, and I aia skuro that<br />
this project moving ahead.<br />
Headquarters at }( ak. adu..<br />
den on the s~ orld H-eritac. 1e<br />
its cultural significance,<br />
ty, anid its sacred site s and<br />
wonders of the world; and<br />
t Xa1; adu. is being manz-ged and<br />
s everyone to enjoy it and make<br />
err itory, Paul Everingham anda<br />
eQncous lead with their energy!<br />
ere is no doubt that selfthe<br />
vital step in getting the<br />
e. Ve see signs of the drive<br />
where private sec tor .0Ceeopment.<br />
dicateB great confidence in the<br />
n Darwin and the Terri-tory<br />
in the faict that the Territo,, y<br />
cts wqhich wotild be e*-: Pected<br />
i oyir. ent in-Austtralia as a whole,<br />
act; that employm-ient_ grow~ th 211-thI<br />
' Isf* a ster' th,-n in ' arty oft the st-. atp~<br />
s as being iii the forefront of? 2<br />
NISATER </p>
<p>As a Party and as a Gox'ernnient, we believe very strongly that<br />
encouraging people to mr i-age their own affairs unleashes their<br />
talents and creativity, it leaas to a dynamiirm that cannot be<br />
abhieved in any othier way. This applies whether we are talkirty<br />
about states or local cormmunities or individuals managitig<br />
their own affairs, and it marks us of more clearly froinf<br />
socialists than almost anything else, By unleas) hnq the talents<br />
of people, we also build up our comnunity and our nzition,<br />
and here again our Liberal approach is vastly different froma<br />
Labor's, because Labor doesn't reall. y be-lieve in buvilding<br />
Australia up, but only in distributing what al. ready exists.<br />
Whenever Labor has had a chance to govern,' whether in Canberrza<br />
from 1972-75, or ill South Australia, or ill Newq South iWales<br />
or until very recently in Tasmania. They heve caused irnmentC<br />
I, daxnage and dest-ruction to the eco-nomy, and the sane thing<br />
would happen again, if they ever got a chance. Iti<br />
Liberal Governments which believe in buildingj Atistralia up,<br />
0laasndt ntohtihxeineg dmecaakdees s, t hwish enp laliivnienrg thsatann dtahree isa chhiaevvee tndeonutb! sl edo f Itnhe<br />
Axistralia Linder Liberal govern-ments. We -will always stick~<br />
to this great objective of building Australia up. Our<br />
policies for Australia as a %; hfole, and also for the special<br />
requiremnents of the Territowy, majke2 this very plain,<br />
and I would like to say that Bernie iFilgariff and Grant<br />
Tambling are strong advocate5 in Canberra for t-he cause and<br />
interests of the Territory,<br />
I want to say something tonight about where Austra lia is going,<br />
114 about the way we see the econo7m. Y, and slso abouL two other<br />
major policy area-s , corr~ umnications an~ d defence. In'recent<br />
years, we have had significant economic success, for in tens<br />
of growth, invest-ment and Eamployt,; ent, we have swibr ' Strongly<br />
against the intern~ tion~ al tiae. Judeed, oTn currently available<br />
statistics, in 1981 Aup-tralia's growqtb rate of 5% was about<br />
a four tiimes the average growth rate in the industxialised<br />
Western economics, and was the highest gro-vth rate of any<br />
of the OECD couh~ tries.<br />
Our success against world trends has not cocme about by cha-nc,<br />
it has come from policies designed to give Austral. ians the<br />
confidence and the capacity) to build up our economic<br />
stxength. Those policies 11ave particulirly einphasised restraint<br />
iii the deinsnds of governoment, on the cor-. runity's resources, not<br />
because restraint is valued for its own sake, but because through<br />
those policies of restxaint Una conditions are oreateda in which)<br />
people anid businesses have the resources they need to build up<br />
Australia ' s prosperity.<br />
Leat there be no mistake about it, out ultimate objective is to heep<br />
real incomes growing, to keep -eal living stan~ dards rising, to<br />
create the capacity to keep giving help where help is needed, and<br />
we have already had substantial success in meeting these<br />
objectiven. </p>
<p>-3-<br />
The biggest threats to our ability to keep moving aheae, Com~ e<br />
from, on the one hand, the contiviucd recession in te kyorld's<br />
major economies, and on the Other, the damage that can be done.-by<br />
inappropriate or irresponsible behaviour by UtajUSts) e.<br />
As Territc'rians, With your grea t sources of income eerived frro~ a<br />
mining, fron tourism, and fro.-. cdttle raisingC you wlbe cLy<br />
A aware of h-ow world economic conditions affect us in Astralia, oL<br />
how COntini~ ed world recession has depressed demand Forv and the<br />
prices of many of our major export coruotities.<br />
As our economic performance of rcen-t yeaxs has shown we are not<br />
totally cZaptive to OVerrseaS economic influenoeS, blt. 3, t is clEtaxr<br />
thekt. the 2Ionger the world remains; in recession, the imore it u* 31<br />
economic I.-roblerms, that in six of the seven major eConomPLieS there<br />
has been negative growth in ind3ustrial production) that. the<br />
v1ai loel do-rad acualy fllin .1981 fortefistmen<br />
over 20 ye ars, that unemployment will pass 30 millioit in the<br />
O. E. C. O. :! ountrie8 during this year and that protect ionism is; being.<br />
intensified and extended in tran, places. The potentially<br />
dantaging implications of all this for PAustxrala, as well as f~ or the<br />
rest of the Western econo'mies led the Cabinet to agree to Australia.<br />
putting forwaird a proposal to the w,, orld leaders who met over<br />
last weakend in Versailles a proposal which focussedI on t-he<br />
imrrportance of trade in generating sustai;, able economic ) recovev',<br />
aind sought to get growth xrestartea in the * na-jor economies by<br />
proposing a standstill, an6 a subsequent winding back of<br />
protecticri devices as well as of export inrentives and subs; idies.<br />
We shall be continuing to press for positive action by all<br />
industria'lised countries in co-operation because the economic<br />
prospects and prosperity of people throughout th~ e world, and of<br />
people tl'. roughout Astralia depend on action being taken.<br />
But it iV equally important a-nd ruost obviously so while overiseas<br />
developments remain unfavourabl. e, that Australians should not<br />
damage th-eir own p~ fopsects and prosperity. There has been an<br />
unfortunate tendency for sone groups of Australians to act i-n a<br />
way thiat damages themselves and others in our corcaunity.<br />
we have seen that all too clearly in thp-effects on activity and<br />
employment that have come about because of the excessive wage cla: ims<br />
and the ixnreasonable levels of industrial disputes and strikes that<br />
occurred in the second half of 1981 and early 1982.<br />
The ; cecent decision in the national wage case has given us time<br />
to digest the effects of wage increases; there are now real<br />
prospects of greater harmony add co-o eration in irIOkustrLia) l<br />
relations,; and we must ca -pital1ise on these opporturities to<br />
re-build the sense of confidence that we should all have in<br />
Australia's prospects. </p>
<p>We are entte ohv ta. fidcnce because Austral. ia<br />
has real srengths in its strong manufacturing base,<br />
in its efficient primary proauce) t-, in its abuniaht<br />
n-atural. resources, in the tnjet lhich has surged<br />
ahead in recent years, and is -, till continuing at~ high<br />
levels, and in the initiativo \ nd enterprise of the<br />
Australian people.<br />
It is important that we continue to develop tbeqe<br />
strenciths, because a strong and growing economry is<br />
esserl; ial for so many of our other~ obnectives.<br />
Defence is equally a m1atter of fundamental and easential<br />
concer'n and i want to discusqs ft particularly tonight<br />
because we live in a troubled and difficult wyorld, in<br />
which it is more important thtrn ever for the western<br />
nations to display strength zinil resolve as well, aq a<br />
willingi'iess to enter into meaningful discussiortF abolit.<br />
issues such as artrs limitations,<br />
The F'alklands crisis has showed very plainly how quickly<br />
trouible spots can emerqe. it is now 40 years since Darw~ in<br />
was bombed -we recently cele) -rai-e d the 40th anniversar),<br />
of the Battl. e of the Coral Sea, and while Astalia's<br />
circumstanices today are very di. fferent froimthove we<br />
face-1 in 1942, we must be pfeparea for any threats and<br />
challenges which couldemr.<br />
As a Governent and party, we h-, ave an urnsWerkling~ COMrntitre. n<br />
to a secure Australia, a Strong defen~ ce for Ce &amp; nd close<br />
co-eperation with our allies amI friends.<br />
The Government%:' s defencie spending has been increasing<br />
substantially; outlays this fin, roia. year arc up by<br />
nea'-: ly 20r on ast year, well above the general price<br />
inc-reases of between 10 anid 11. percsnt; we are in the<br />
mi. ddle of a V. billion 6efence re-equipment. proqrarze<br />
and in~ the tqords of the recently retired Chief of thme<br />
Defence Force staff, we have now the best-eguipped and<br />
best-trainied force we. have ever had'in p! eace time.<br />
* The Governmcint is enlarging our delenoce deployment in<br />
nort-hern and north-wast Australia th) rough an e&gt; xparision<br />
of the IA. A X basfe here to 8upport the tac-tical fightc-r<br />
force, including. the new FA/ 18s through the creation of<br />
NOUFORCE to expand 5trategic survaillance and<br />
rec-ortnaissanoce capabilities; through increased survei) lance<br />
oc er the Inaian Ocean; through Progressively modernisecl<br />
eo~ munications and through the base for six patrol boats<br />
which has been constructed anc) which the first defencf:<br />
personnel actually moved into today.<br />
Defence co-operation with allies and neighbours is aliao<br />
growing in depth and impo.-rce.. There is the deployr; ent<br />
of the fl52' s, co-operation in exerc'ises with tlhe United<br />
States, and also with Malaysia, Singapore, 14, Z. and tbe<br />
U. Xh. undtr the Five Power Defence arrangerents. </p>
<p>I would like to comment about access to our ports of naval<br />
ships, bcloDngillg to our allies and friends, whichi may be<br />
nuclear-armed even if conventional . y powered because this<br />
issue is a matter -for the gravest concern. The facts<br />
are that in the three years of Labcor office in Canberra,<br />
somelS nax'al ships of the United st; Ates, the United KrIcjdorn<br />
and r-rance visited Auistralian ports, including the port of<br />
* I'eloure. Since then, some 390 visits have taken place.<br />
These visits could niot have taken place withoUt the esLiablishc-e p~ a1icies.<br />
British naval ships would not be allowed into Australia's<br />
ports without them.<br />
In 1976 lir IWhi~ tai drew attention to the consider~ able confusiort<br />
about nuclear ships and his statement made it plain that it<br />
was impossible to expect our allies to specify for public<br />
consumption which of their ships were nuclear-armed and which<br />
were not. For them to do so viould be to give important<br />
military information to possible eniemies. fir W-hitlartils arqjLunE. nt_-<br />
were impeccable. ' They parallel thjose of the Government<br />
-policy exactly. The Labor Government practicesed this-policy<br />
A when it was in office in Canberra. -Ouir policy since 1975 has<br />
0been the Earne. it is an essential policy if we are to be<br />
able to co-operate with our allies on vital defencce mtatters<br />
and it plzay8 a significant paxrt in the effective operation of<br />
a policy of nuclear deterrence. For these reasons, the policy<br />
must continue and it will continue. Australia's defenceS.<br />
are strong and relevant to today, and under this Government,<br />
that posiion -wll 1) e Tiaintained.<br />
I also %,, ant to sexy something about coinrunicat ions which are<br />
important to people in the Territory in ways which many Au-sttalians<br />
would find it hard to gjrasp or onderstand. The next few years<br />
will see cireat irr., rove. ments in a number of areas. of co., 1 tnic Ations.<br />
The sateliite is going ahead, with a projected launch inl 19,85.<br />
It Will not only bring T. V. and radio services to a number of:<br />
xemote areas for the first time, but % will also have a major<br />
* iTOpact on Australia's whole cormmunications network through to the<br />
enld of this century.<br />
flThere are several addit ional commwunications developments in t; rain.<br />
A new terrestrial system for remote telephone subscribers9 haS<br />
been designed anid new exchange equipmnent. for Darwin is planned,<br />
4 remote area television program stations have been opened this<br />
year, and the Government is active in pioMoting a number of<br />
other initiatives and improvements in broadcasting serv. ic. es 1-or<br />
Darwin and other pprts of the Territory Communications hias always<br />
been a great chalne for Australia bjt a great deal is being<br />
achieved, and some of the current initiativeS really Will b--<br />
historic advances.&gt;<br />
1in focussing tonight on the economy, defence anid communications,<br />
I have : not only been dealing with p) olicy aroas which are importanit<br />
in their own right, but also with ones whZhcharacterise the<br />
fundamental. strengths of Liberalism. ? nor it is our Government<br />
! t w~ hich seeks to build up a strong arid pr. osparous Australia in<br />
which peocple have the incentive and confidence to live their own<br />
lives in their ovm way. </p>
<p>6.<br />
Australia. in the 1980' s is Olle rof the most vibrant and Vital.<br />
countries in the world in a cultural) sense; one of tho' most<br />
harrnonious,, free and stable count-ries . In a political s'nse;<br />
it is onle. of the best mtanag-d anO'* D.. ckiest countries in all<br />
economic, sense; one of the wost concerned and energetic<br />
countries in humnritarian tcrrns; one of th~ e most. rea) Ji; tic,<br />
responsible and far-sighted Countrics in the part it pl' 3ays; i-r<br />
internat~ onal affairs; an~ d it is one of the most self -confidenL<br />
and friendly countries in tei-ms of the way in which Other pE-Op~ ct<br />
vje%-7US. By working together as one people and One flatioil alic<br />
by the continuation of policies which unleash people's ener9y<br />
and inlitiLative, % qe can keep Amstralia ahead in til. i. nterests of<br />
our fam'i. lies and our children. o~ OOOooo---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
