<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4485</transcript-id>
    <title>STUDY GROUP ON MANUFACTURING INDUSTRY</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/09/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004485.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
P77/ 194<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 6 SEPTEMBER 1977<br />
STUDY GROUP ON MANUFACTURING INDUSTRY<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr. Fraser, announced today the membership<br />
and terms of reference of a group to undertake a study of the<br />
adjustment problems of the most highly protected Australian<br />
manufacturing industries.<br />
Mr. Fraser had announced on 26 August in a speech to the<br />
Chamber of Manufactures of New South Wales that Sir John<br />
Crawford would be Chairman of the group to conduct the study.<br />
The other members of the group will be Sir Brian Inglis<br />
( Chairman of the Government's Australian Manufacturing Council<br />
and Managing Director of Ford Australia); Mr. R. J. L. Hawke<br />
( President, Australian Council of Trade Unions); and Mr. N. S.<br />
Currie ( Secretary, Department of Industry and Commerce).<br />
The terms of reference for the study will be:<br />
" Undertake a study into the nature and extent of<br />
adjustment problems of Australian manufacturing industries,<br />
with particular reference to the most highly protected<br />
industries arising from changes in the internal and<br />
external environments. Advise on the essential elements<br />
in a long-term policy to deal with these problems having<br />
regard to the implications of the likely patterns of<br />
industries growth and employment prospects, and the<br />
capacity of the economy to sustain changes in the<br />
industrial structure".<br />
The Prime Minister said that Sir John Crawford would be available<br />
to begin this work in late October and it was expected that the<br />
report of the group would be submitted by August 1978.<br />
The Departments of Industry and Commerce and Business and<br />
Consumer Affairs would provide support and secretariat services<br />
for the study and the group has been assured it will have access<br />
to other Departments and institutions to obtain information and<br />
views on the matters under study. The group will determine its<br />
own pi; ocedures but it will be free to seek submissions from public<br />
authorities, interested parties and the public generally if it<br />
wishes. " This study will be of considerable importance to the Government<br />
in helping to further define our long-term policies for implementation<br />
when growth has been restored to satisfactory levels", the<br />
Prime Minister said. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
