<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8288</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER ADDRESS TO THE COMMITTEE FOR THE ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT OF AUSTRALIA&#039;S CONFERENCE AN AUSTRALIAN THAT WORKS : A VISION FOR THE FUTURE SYDNEY - 1 MAY 1991</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/05/1991</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008288.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHECK AGAINS: T DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL. nELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
ADDRESS TO THE COMMITTEE FOR THE<br />
ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT OF AUSTRALIA'S CONFERENCE<br />
AN AUSTRALIA THAT WORKS A VISION FOR THE FUTURE<br />
SYDNEY 1 MAY 1991<br />
Distinguished Guests<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
Australia has never lacked writers and poets whose words<br />
could conjure up visions of the future of this nation and<br />
its people.<br />
I do not mean merely the evocation of our physical<br />
landscape, like Banjo Paterson's " vision splendid of the<br />
sunlit plains extended".<br />
I mean visions of the nation itself of how its people<br />
should act to secure their best future.<br />
Henry Lawson cast the nation's future as a choice between<br />
'' the old dead tree and the young tree green"' words taken<br />
up by Manning Clark as the title of the last volume of his<br />
History of Australia.<br />
At this Conference, our vision is somewhat less poetic, but<br />
certainly more relevant to the management of the complex and<br />
diverse society that we have become the deceptively modestc<br />
goal of ' an Australia that works'.<br />
The danger for those who seek to articulate a vision for the<br />
future of their nation is obvious: they run the risk of<br />
being accused of substituting empty rhetoric about long-term<br />
goals for hard analysis and prescription about immediate<br />
problems. But it is only by identifying valid long-term goals that we<br />
can possibly make the right decisions about those more<br />
immediate problems. </p>
<p>Nowhere does that general truth have more particular<br />
validity than in the case of economic management of the<br />
affairs of a nation.<br />
The constantly changing circumstances in which a national<br />
economy operates; its inherently conflicting interest<br />
groups; and the often discordant chorus of commentators,<br />
make the task of consistent and effective short-term<br />
management difficult. A vision of the long-term future is a<br />
necessity as-a guide, and as a model against which<br />
progress can be measured.<br />
And let me be quite explicit I am speaking directly from<br />
my personal experience as Prime Minister. When my<br />
Government embarked on our program of profound and<br />
comprehensive reform reform of institutions of the economy<br />
and reform of attitudes about the economy we recognised<br />
that change could be painful. And so it has proven. We<br />
recognised that sacrifices could be necessary. And they<br />
have been.<br />
We could not have undertaken this program of reform, and we<br />
could not have required those painful costs, unless we had<br />
articulated, realistically portrayed, and adequately<br />
detailed our vtision of the kind of Australia that we are<br />
seeking to build.<br />
And right from the start, through the National Economic<br />
Summit, and through a consensual approach to our decision<br />
making, we sought to involve the community as a whole in<br />
this task.<br />
Because, let me stress, the task of formulating and<br />
articulating a vision for the nation is not a task for<br />
Government alone. It certainly must not become the preserve<br />
of the mandarins of the bureaucracy, or of the self-styled<br />
experts representing vested interests, or of the theorists<br />
of academia.<br />
A vision is not some arcane formula cooked up by specialist<br />
elites; it is and must be a real and comprehensible program<br />
developed for and by the nation as a whole.<br />
That said, let me once more sketch what I as Prime Minister<br />
see as the long-term outcomes of the reform process on which<br />
we have embarked which is to say, the elements of my<br />
vision for the future of Australia.<br />
Just as importantly to your purposes, I want to draw lines<br />
into the future, linking the Australia of today with this<br />
vision we are striving to attain, and showing what more we<br />
must do if we are not to be thwarted in our ambition to<br />
reach our goal.<br />
The first element of this vision for Australia is for a<br />
modern, prosperous, growing economy, shaken out of its old<br />
complacencies an Australia that draws on its comparative<br />
advantages to improve its standard of living an Australia </p>
<p>increasingly able to earn its way in the world through its<br />
creativity and ingenuity an Australia that makes full,<br />
efficient and effective use of its human and natural<br />
resources tc achieve sustainable growth.<br />
It is only in such an Australia that opportunities can be<br />
provided for all Australians to maintain and enhance their<br />
standards of living.<br />
So the second element relates quantity of output to quality<br />
of life. Our Australia of the future must be a democratic<br />
society with the deepest attachment to the rule of law. It<br />
must be a just society, that values all its members and<br />
provides opportunities for them all to contribute to, and<br />
benefit from, national life. The material resources<br />
generated through growth must be available, through fair<br />
taxation and through the provision of education, health care<br />
and support for the needy, for the advancement of all.<br />
This Australia will be a multicultural society by<br />
demographic fact; it must also be multicultural in practice,<br />
through the mutual respect of all its citizens, and the<br />
unity of their commitment to our national identity.<br />
And it will be an Australia that has got the balance right<br />
between the necessity for continued economic growth and the<br />
necessity for protection of our environmental heritage an<br />
economy that has identified the concept and implemented the<br />
reality of ecologically sustainable development.<br />
The third element of this vision of Australia concerns the<br />
attitudes we bring to our relationship with our region and<br />
to the rest of the world.<br />
I see a self-reliant and confident Australia forging its own<br />
place in the world an Australia that through its<br />
traditional bilateral alliances and friendships, and through<br />
multilateral means, is capable of forcefully pursuing its<br />
own interests in a challenging world environment an<br />
Australia prepared to challenge the folly of trade<br />
protectionism an Australia prepared to contribute to the<br />
maintenance and spread of peace and stability an<br />
Australia, in short, that does not merely fit in with the<br />
world order as we find it, but that helps to shape it.<br />
These are broadly stated goals that, as such, command almost<br />
universal respect throughout the Australian community.<br />
It is on the question of how to attain these goals that we<br />
hear the emerging voices of pessimists, who seem to believe<br />
the challenge is simply too great for us.<br />
They say that Australia cannot hope to survive, let alone<br />
compete, in a dynamic Asia-Pacific region or in a global<br />
economy dominated by superpowers in North America, Europe,<br />
and North Asita. For them Australia is too firmly rooted in<br />
its past to m~ ake the change to the flexibility, the<br />
diversity, arid the competitiveness that the future demands. </p>
<p>The paradox of course is that those who believe we cannot<br />
escape our past urge us to return to it through the failed<br />
policies of selective industry protection, managed exchange<br />
rates, and confrontationist industrial relations. They want<br />
us to burden ourselves once more with the introspective and<br />
short-sighted policies of expedience that for most of the<br />
post-war years simply erected and entrenched the problems<br />
that we are now dismantling and remedying.<br />
I am essentially an optimist. I know Australians pretty well<br />
and I know from first hand in the Cabinet room and out in<br />
the community the changes that Australians are undertaking<br />
and the determination with which they are doing so. I put<br />
great faith in the resilient capacity of our democratic<br />
system to contain and resolve the inevitable tensions<br />
generated in periods of rapid change and uncertainty.<br />
But I hasten to qualify this optimism with a healthy dose of<br />
realism. The inherited problems facing this nation in the<br />
early 1980s were huge; they have not by any means all been<br />
solved. We are still predominantly a commodity producer, like<br />
we were 140 years ago, influenced now as then by the<br />
continuing cycles of international boom and bust.<br />
S We are still a Federation of separate sovereignties,<br />
victims of the economic and administrative<br />
inefficiencies we inherited from those who drew<br />
colonial boundaries over our continent.<br />
S We still, too many of us, see ourselves as perched<br />
uneasily on the edge of Asia, in it but not of it; we<br />
are not yet capable of maximising in the region our<br />
strengths as a prosperous, well educated and free<br />
society.<br />
These are deep-seated shortcomings in our national<br />
development, and we should not be shy in admitting them or<br />
reluctant to concede the need for redoubled efforts to<br />
remedy them.<br />
But equally, it would be niggardly, and plain wrong, to<br />
claim that nothing has been attempted or that nothing has<br />
been achieved.<br />
I don't want this address to become a partisan list of<br />
Government achievements. But I do want to talk, and with<br />
pride, of the profound and far-reaching changes that I<br />
detect have taken place in the community as a whole over<br />
recent years.<br />
These changes can be categorised under three broad headings.<br />
Australia is becoming a more competitive society, a more<br />
cooperative community, and a more outward-looking nation.<br />
Each of these changes is related to the broad elements of<br />
the vision for Australia I outlined at the outset. In other </p>
<p>words, we are making real progress towards those goals; we<br />
are taking with us into the future more of the<br />
characteristics that we will need to build the kind of<br />
society we want.<br />
A More Competitive Australia<br />
Perhaps the best indication of our emerging maturity as a<br />
nation, and the clearest demonstration that we are shaking<br />
of f the inefficiencies of the past, is our historic<br />
transformation away from industry protection.<br />
There was no better symbol of Australia's traditional<br />
preference for isolation over international enmneshment than<br />
the tariff; and there is no better proof of our growing<br />
preparedness to take on the challenges of the modern,<br />
interdependent, global economy than our determination to<br />
bury the tariff.<br />
This Government has deliberately and determinedly set about<br />
pulling down the tariff walls. The change can be<br />
dramatically measured. By the end of the decade, we will<br />
have slashed the average nominal rate of assistance to the<br />
manufacturing sector from the 13% that prevailed in 1983 to<br />
and the average effective rate of assistance from 22% to<br />
Turning the -tide of protectionism marks the start of a new<br />
chapter in the economic history of this country. Australian<br />
industry will no longer be able to regard the domestic<br />
market as its captive and the world market as beyond its<br />
reach. Export orientation will increasingly enter the<br />
strategies ofE even moderately sized Australian firms. New<br />
incentives will be generated to improve product quality and<br />
to adopt new technology. Managers and workers will no<br />
longer be able to shirk the challenge of international best<br />
practice. For our efficient export industries, this means lower input<br />
prices; for Australian families, cheaper consumer goods.<br />
Ultimately, for the Australian economy as a whole, there<br />
will be a new capacity to compete on world markets.<br />
At the same t: ime as we are dismantling the barriers to<br />
competitiveness that stand at the borders of Australia, we<br />
are also eliminating the barriers that exist within<br />
Australia. Microeconomic reform has gone from being an arcane and<br />
irrelevant term to one at the top of the political reform<br />
agenda. Thai: hasn't happened by accident; it has come about<br />
because Australians have realised that it is intimately<br />
related to the quest for higher productivity and efficiency.<br />
Our transport. and communication systems, our taxation<br />
system, our work practices and industrial relations had for<br />
many decades acted as impediments to the easy flow of goods<br />
and services and to the proper development of our individual </p>
<p>talents. The last few years have seen the start of<br />
revolutionary change in each of these fields change that<br />
must and will continue if we are to build the Australia of<br />
our vision.<br />
This of course will cause discomfort, and some pain, to<br />
individuals and organisations who are jolted out of their<br />
traditional ways. That is the nature of micro-economic<br />
reform: the gains are diffused throughout the society, while<br />
the costs must.-be borne in the first instance by those<br />
immediately affected.<br />
The labour market adjustment programs that we have<br />
instituted to help workers displaced through tariff<br />
reductions show that the community can, as it should,<br />
provide transition assistance to those affected.<br />
But the prOcess of adjustment itself is necessary and<br />
inevitable.<br />
Australia cannot afford to retain islands of cosseted<br />
inefficiency in the sea of increasing national<br />
competitiveness whether those islands be an overmanned<br />
wharf, an inefficzient government enterprise or an<br />
expensively protected manufacturer.<br />
A third landmark on the path to a more competitive Australia<br />
is the emerging proof that, after several lost opportunities<br />
during previous decades, Australia is at last set to get low<br />
inflation.<br />
Most forecasters are now predicting inflation close to zero<br />
for the March quarter, and less than 5% during the next few<br />
years. A lower inflation regime will reduce uncertainty and improve<br />
our economic efficiency in general. It will improve the<br />
functioning of the price system, lower interest rates and<br />
induce better saving and investment decisions. It will<br />
reduce the remaining distortions in the tax system, enhance<br />
the quality of information available for business decisions<br />
and allow a more equitable income distribution.<br />
And for the first time in years we can now expect a low<br />
inflation recovery associated with the necessary improvement<br />
in the current account.<br />
In other words, lower inflation inflation more in line<br />
with the levels of our trading partners makes an essential<br />
contribution to the emergence of a greater competitiveness.<br />
Underpinning this competitiveness is perhaps the most<br />
profound sea-change of them all the greater mobilisation<br />
of our human resources. I mean not just the skills of our<br />
elite intellectual community but the talents of managers and<br />
workers in factories and offices throughout the nation. </p>
<p>As I said in the March Statement, this mobilisation does not<br />
necessarily mean working harder. But it does mean working<br />
smarter wcirking more effectively, using new materials, new<br />
production technologies and new management methods. It<br />
means being a clever country providing the right<br />
incentives for our children to complete secondary schooling<br />
and ensuring adequate arrangements to meet their demand for<br />
tertiary education; encouraging our best scientific minds to<br />
focus on expanding the frontiers of knowledge and on<br />
enhancing economic competitiveness and productivity; and<br />
striving to adopt the best working and management practices.<br />
A More Coonprative_ Australia<br />
Australia has always been a society dedicated to the spirit<br />
of cooperation. We are, after all, a " Common wealth" and<br />
the very purpose of cooperation is to enhance the shared<br />
prosperity of all those who participate in it.<br />
But in recent years we have seen new and significant<br />
manifestations of this characteristic.<br />
One hallmark of a cooperative community is the quality of<br />
its social justice programs. Today, assistance to the needy<br />
is more plentiful in real terms and better targeted on those<br />
most in need, while the dramatic expansion of child care<br />
services, the creation of comprehensive health insurance and<br />
the spread of superannuation ensure that social justice<br />
remains relevant' to changing social needs.<br />
A second hallmark of a cooperative community is its ability<br />
to overcome internal impediments to efficiency.<br />
It is astonishing to think that by 1992 there will be fewer<br />
real barriers between the member nations of the European<br />
Community than there will be between the Australian States.<br />
Our 17 million people will form a more fragmented market<br />
than the 340 millions of the EC.<br />
So the task of improving the efficiency and competitiveness<br />
of the public sector, and improving the delivery and quality<br />
of services governments provide is an urgent and a vital<br />
one. That is why I launched the special Premiers' Conference<br />
process which, last October, took up the challenge and<br />
initiated a review of intergovernmental arrangements in an<br />
unparalleled spirit of co-operation.<br />
A third hallmark ' of a cooperative community is its ability<br />
to work together to achieve common goals.<br />
Nowhere is this co-operation more vital than in the labour<br />
market. Much of the change I have described and<br />
foreshadowed has the workplace as its focus. Here, where<br />
wealth is created, we must see real change if the nation is<br />
to equip itself to fulfil the wider aspects of the vision I<br />
have described. </p>
<p>This essential truth was recognised by this Government from<br />
the time of the Economic Summit, which we convened on<br />
assuming office, and in the forging and nurturing of our key<br />
relationships with employers and the trade union movement.<br />
These relationships have reached their most developed form<br />
in the Accord, reflecting not only the close historical and<br />
political association between the Labor Government and the<br />
trade union movement, but also the cohesive structure of the<br />
ACTU that enables them to negotiate and to deliver on<br />
undertakings given.<br />
The instrumental role the Accord has had in the Government's<br />
macroeconomic policy is well known most clearly perhaps in<br />
underpinning the change in the profit share that facilitated<br />
the resurgence of investment.<br />
But its role in promoting deeper and more permanent<br />
structural change has received less attention. The<br />
reduction in industrial disputes by around 60% is one<br />
indicator of the Accord's effectiveness in this role. We<br />
are also seeing union rationalisation and award<br />
restructuring, moving us out of the nineteenth century era<br />
of craft based unionism, and a new willingness to negotiate<br />
industrial agreements to facilitate greenfield projects.<br />
These changes, fundamental as they are, represent but one<br />
stage in what must be a continuing process. A commitment to<br />
further increasing labour market flexibility is integral to<br />
Accord VI. But let me point out that, contrary to<br />
assertions commonly heard, our industrial relations system,<br />
at its present stage of evolution, is entirely capable of<br />
accommodating innovative agreements between employers and<br />
workers. And we have seen such agreements put in place,<br />
including in large and traditional industries like steel and<br />
chemicals, that have yielded very significant improvements<br />
in productivity.<br />
In mentioning these let me acknowledge and pay tribute to<br />
the contribution by management to this progress. As I noted<br />
a few moments ago, this Government has from its earliest<br />
days sought to consult and involve employers in developing<br />
policy strategies. It is certainly our intention that this<br />
should continue. Indeed, integral to our vision for the<br />
future is the creation of a closer, more productive<br />
relationship based on mutual interest between unions,<br />
employers and government.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen, the difficulties of achieving change<br />
are as real and stark in the area of industrial relations as<br />
anywhere else in the economy. Traditional structures are<br />
reinforced by a complex web of traditional attitudes;<br />
together, they constitute a real barrier to change. Our<br />
history of protecting industries from competition has<br />
hindered the development of the skills required, on both<br />
sides of the labour market, to cope with the more flexible<br />
environment we all acknowledge is desperately needed. </p>
<p>The tensions, uncertainties and fears this creates have been<br />
graphically displayed in the lively debate that has followed<br />
the latest National Wage Case decision.<br />
I do not impugn the motives either of the Commission in<br />
bringing down the decision or of those who have commented on<br />
it since. The Government's fundamental position is clear:<br />
reform and restructuring must proceed. I want to see the<br />
attention and energies of all parties focussed on achieving<br />
this vitally essential objective.<br />
There can be no doubt that the process of waterfront reform,<br />
with which I have been intimately concerned in recent days,<br />
certainly exemplifies the difficulties of achieving change.<br />
But change must be achieved and will be achieved. And, as<br />
my responsible Minister, Senator Bob Collins, will testify,<br />
the waterfront reform process graphically illustrates the<br />
fundamental truth that it will only be achieved through<br />
hard, grinding negotiation not by high flown but empty<br />
rhetoric about confrontation on the waterfront.<br />
A More Outward-looking Aus_-tralia<br />
Most of the dramatic changes I have described so far have<br />
affected Australia's domestic framework. But each of them<br />
also has a direct and vital impact in fostering a more<br />
outward orientation of the Australian nation.<br />
Indeed, the simplest way of describing the diverse range of<br />
economic reforms we have undertaken so far is to say they<br />
have ' internationalised' the Australian economy.<br />
Deregulation, the fostering of domestic competition, the<br />
effective management of fiscal, wages and monetary policy,<br />
have made us more open and exposed to the challenges and<br />
opportunities of the international marketplace, and more<br />
competitive in taking them up.<br />
At the same time, tariff reductions have given us a wholly<br />
new credibility in taking on the agricultural protectionists<br />
in the Uruguay Round of GATT.<br />
Australia has diligently pursued over the last four years<br />
our essential interests in the Uruguay Round attempting to<br />
ensure our farmers get fair and equal access to world<br />
markets, and to protect the global system from corrupt,<br />
trade distorting policies.<br />
It was very imuch in pursuit of these interests that we<br />
established -the Cairns Group so that nations with similar<br />
interests could speak with a collectively louder and more<br />
influential -voice.<br />
The revolutionary changes taking place in global economic<br />
life are nowhere more visible than here on the Pacific Rim.<br />
This region generates one third of the world's trade and </p>
<p>more than half its economic output. It contains the world's<br />
fastest growing economies.<br />
Our domestic economic reforms have made us more capable of<br />
participating as a full partner in these developments<br />
while our foreign policy has underlined our willingness and<br />
ability to strengthen the productive framework of our<br />
region. I am very happy to see the steady progress made by the Asia<br />
Pacific Economic Cooperation process established following<br />
my proposal in January 1989.<br />
APEC is evolving into a major regional economic forum for<br />
discussion of developments in the world trading system,<br />
including the post-Uruguay Round environment, and practical<br />
co-operation through the development of work projects.<br />
Australia must be realistic about its capacity to influence<br />
global events. But middle power diplomacy can be a force<br />
for change and good, as our efforts have shown on Cambodia,<br />
southern Africa, chemical weapons and culminating only<br />
this week on the prevention of mining in Antarctica.<br />
We will continue to use our good offices to influence and<br />
shape a future that reflects Australia's interests. In<br />
particular, we must continue to assert and to defend the<br />
principle that the long-term security of individual nations<br />
will be best advanced through collective security.<br />
The Gulf crisis, a watershed in modern world history,<br />
defined once and for all the end of the Cold War which had<br />
held the world frozen for forty-five years. It demonstrated<br />
the capacity for collective action in defence of collective<br />
security. It precipitated a resurgence in support for the<br />
role and mechanisms of the United Nations.<br />
Australia was in the forefront of the action to defend the<br />
principles of collective security, and I am proud of our<br />
role in the crisis.<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen,<br />
There is one final manifestation of this outward looking<br />
perspective to which I wish to refer this evening:<br />
Australia's rapidly growing tourism industry.<br />
Over the last decade, Australia's tourism industry has<br />
witnessed unprecedented growth and development to become one<br />
of our biggest export-earners. It accounts for over 5 per<br />
cent of GDP and employs nearly half a million people.<br />
Tourism's decentralised character also assists the<br />
diversification of Australia's non-urban economic base.<br />
While these past achievements deserve praise there is no<br />
room for complacency. The challenge for the tourism </p>
<p>industry is to deliver an internationally desirable and<br />
competitive product.<br />
To this end, I congratulate CEDA on its publication of<br />
" Tourism in Australia", and I am happy to launch it now. It<br />
represents a timely and objective examination of the<br />
strengths and weaknesses of the industry and the<br />
opportunities and risks facing it.<br />
Insights such as this, together with forward looking<br />
strategies being developed by the industry itself, provide<br />
an understanding of what is required to develop Australia's<br />
almost limitless tourism potential.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen,<br />
I have spoken at length tonight in response to your<br />
invitation to examine these difficult and important issues.<br />
I congratulate you on the ambitious nature of this<br />
conference and I wish you well in your discussions.<br />
In closing I stress this vital point.<br />
National goals are not like the goals on a football field.<br />
They are not fixed targets; we all know that the only<br />
constant fact these days is the fact of constant change.<br />
Adjustment to change the process of reform is not<br />
something that we can expect will have some clearly defined<br />
end point in a more stable and more predictable future.<br />
Reform, adaptation, flexibility, dynamism these will be<br />
continuing needs; they must become enduring characteristics<br />
of our daily life as a national economy.<br />
I trust conferences such as this will play a successful role<br />
in educating Australians and in winning their informed<br />
involvement in the continuing challenge of reform. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
