<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6048</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER-DESIGNATE, MR RJ HAWKE  MP</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/03/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006048.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
STATEI4LNT B3Y THE P'RIME' MRRLii$ ' iPtF;(; HAi1ALW KE, M. P.<br />
The decision to devaluec tho Australian dollar<br />
has be-en takcni against the balckground of continuing<br />
uncertainty rcgdardirig thc-exchange rate. The incoming<br />
Australian Govcrnmont is det~ ermnined to take all necessary<br />
measureG t o end. this iunceprtainty.<br />
In reaching thir, decision, the incoming government<br />
has been facedl with the utvycnt noed to end the damaging and<br />
destabilising effects of speculation against the dollar<br />
deliberately created by loadling maerbers of the Liberal<br />
Natiorial Party Government.<br />
Both the Prime ministor and his Deputy made<br />
repeated statellejit$-d-llv-tjz! m that. ri~ iy governmeit' s election<br />
would result in a devaluation of the dollar. The<br />
outgoing Minister for Industry and Commerce, Mr Peacock,<br />
went to the ext. remes irreq3-cmsibility by quantifying<br />
a devaluation at-<br />
It iE; difficult to exaggerate the irre! sponsibility<br />
of such statemonts made during the course of an election<br />
By contrast, I c-trcfull y and consi-stently refused to<br />
enter int~ o spo--culation regarding tho exchange rate. Any<br />
other cour.;(-would haive bepn highly irresponsible on the part<br />
of the altornativo-Prime blixili . tcr of Australia, as indeed<br />
it was on the part of anYbody holding or seeking high office<br />
in Australia. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
In such reprehensible circumstances, it was<br />
inevitable that market participants would take the<br />
Appropriate precautionary measures and that speculators<br />
in the market would begin to move funds accordingly.<br />
In the two weeks prior to the election when these<br />
stateme-nts were being made, notifications of capital outflows<br />
from Australia exceeded $ 2,500m. ( See Table.) The effect<br />
of the statements by Ministers and of the capital outflows<br />
was to generate further speculation concerning devaluation.<br />
The magnitude of the capital outflows has been such as to<br />
put considerable pressure on short-term money markets and<br />
on financial institutions, thereby generating significant<br />
increases in short-term interest rates and in some market<br />
Oetermined mediumt-term interest rates. The banking system<br />
in particular has been hit by the outflow of funds and has<br />
been actively bidding for deposits in the marketplace at<br />
high rates of interest.<br />
The incoming Government is concerned about the<br />
persistence of this uncertainty in regard to exchange rates<br />
qver the tax run-down period of the next four months.<br />
Continued uncertainty could lead to further pressure on<br />
interest rates and reductions in the availability of funds<br />
to key sectors of the economy over this period. P/ 1 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
InformaLion made ava~ i lablc to thle incoming<br />
Government in the lztt two, d1ayLs has made it clear that the<br />
preiGooue rinon1) ; baiidonmnt of responsible. economic<br />
niinagemeiit went far beoyond the matter of the value of the<br />
currency. Official Treastiry esitimates put the Federal<br />
budget deficit at $ 4.3 b. illion in 1982-83, before allowance<br />
for additional expenditure associated with recent bushfires<br />
and floods. On the bas; is of policies of the previous<br />
Government, prior to the colurncncement of the election<br />
campaign, a-reasury estimates put the budget deficit in<br />
1933/ 84 at $ 9.6 billion. Thujs the persistent indications<br />
from the previous Governme~ nt that the doficit on unchanged<br />
policies wouldI be of the ordet-of $ 6 billion can only be<br />
seen as a deliberate aitte-. mpt to mislead the Australian<br />
people. While accepting the figure of $ 9.6 billion as a<br />
reasonable estimate of the prospective .1983/ 84 deficit as a result<br />
of current Government policies, I 6tress that this is not an<br />
estimate of the deficit which will emerge from new policies.<br />
Treasury forecasts on unchanged policiLes indicate a very weak<br />
economy in 1983/ 84, with at least a further lt decline<br />
in employmont and a considerably higher average level of<br />
unemployment in 1983/ 84 than in the present year. It is<br />
because of this dismal py-ospuct, aind particularly its adverse<br />
impact on receipts, that. their deCicit blow-out is predicted.<br />
The ncw Goverximent will use all instruments of economnic policy<br />
to stimulate the economy, and the prospcctive deficit will need<br />
to re-a!, sessed in this ligjht. The incoming Government will<br />
also vigorously re-exami~ ne the c! xpenditure plans of the Fraser<br />
Government. </p>
<p>-L.<br />
In rcaching lts deci. io thle . ricoming Govornment<br />
has givenl the () cl) sest consideraion Lo both the costs and the<br />
benefits of a devaluation. In addition to eliminating the<br />
pos; sibility of currency indluced tightric! 7s in monetary markets<br />
over the next three or four months, it will ensure that interest<br />
rates will be considerably lower than would otherwise have been<br />
the case. This dlecis. ion will also improve the competitive<br />
posiion of Australian proaucers. it will enable beleagjuered<br />
Australian industries to conmpco more effectively against imports<br />
anid it will erncourage our texport induIstrios to make maximum use<br />
of any world recovery emanatH-ing, In particular, from the<br />
United Stateti' economy. Tn these various ways this decision<br />
should ConLribvte to halting the rise in unemployment.<br />
1he devaluation will, however, increase the cost of goods<br />
imPortQd into Australia and will teiid to incroase the local price<br />
of goods sold in both domestic and export. markets. In the<br />
present cl imate of a detc'. orat. ing e,. conomy, however, these<br />
inflationary offects should be both muted and delayed.<br />
I wish to mako these point-. s clear<br />
* This docision to vary the value of the dollar by za<br />
single discreLe change of isj a decision forced on<br />
the GovornumenL by the unique circumstances of the past<br />
f or tnight. Tt-is not intended to signal-any change in<br />
Government policy in rogard to the setting of the<br />
Australian exchange rate. Vict present exchange rate<br />
PianaiqoeknL regime which has opo~ rated since 1977 will continue.<br />
This single discrete change is ta~ ken only in the ligjht: of the<br />
uiiproccden Led circurn~ stancos facing the new Government<br />
and all subsequent movements i~ n the exchange rate-</p>
<p>Si upwards as well as downwards -will follow the<br />
gradualist approach previously in force.<br />
0in spite of the decision to devalue, it remains the<br />
incoming Government view that the fundamental factors<br />
datermining* the Australian exchange rate remain sound.<br />
The balance of trade has improved substantially during<br />
1982/ 83 and on present. inchianged policy forecaofts,<br />
Cthe Curr ent, Account dcficit should, at worst, be no<br />
higher in 1983/ 84 thaii in 1982/ 83. Indeed, with growing<br />
signs of stronger growth emerging in the international<br />
economy$ Australia's trading position could improve<br />
quite substantially in 1983/ 84. This deciuion<br />
restores Autralia's international competitiveness,<br />
as measured by unit wage costs indexes, to at least<br />
the level provailing i-n 1979/ 80.<br />
* In spite ofl the difficulties which it has inherited,<br />
it is the Governv nt's firm view that any policy to<br />
reaLore the.-econ omy and reduce unemployment over the<br />
rtcediui-term must be associatnd with a falling rate<br />
of infl. ation. The incom~ ing Government will take all<br />
steps necessary to easure that nothing, including the<br />
effects of thir, devaluation, Estands in the way of<br />
the achievemnent of such a decline in inflation.<br />
Canberra, A. C. T.<br />
8 March 1983 </p>
<p>ATTACHMENT The Reserve BanT;': s cash sales pf foreign<br />
currency since the beginning of February have been as follow4;<br />
Net Sales<br />
Week to 7 February 72.5<br />
14 February 350.7<br />
21 February 83.1<br />
n 28 February 972.8<br />
1 March 303.7<br />
2 March 405.5<br />
3 March 488.3<br />
4 March 358.0<br />
3034.6<br />
On Monday 7th March net nales by the Bank were<br />
approximately $ 200 million. Thus since Mr Peacock's<br />
devaluation statement on 17 February reserves have fallen<br />
by more than $ 2700 million. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
