<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9686</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON PJ KEATING MP HIROSHIMA DAY - 50 YEARS ON</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/08/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009686.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON PJ KEATING MP<br />
HIROSHIMA DAY 50 YEARS ON<br />
When an atomic bomb was dropped on Hiroshima fifty years ago the world<br />
was changed forever. We had been through the most destructive war in<br />
human history. At the very moment we emerged into the peace we learned<br />
that there were weapons in the world of unimaginable destructive force. We<br />
entered a Cold War and with it came the threat of nuclear war which, it<br />
became incri6asing~ y apparent, meant the annihilation of dvilisation.<br />
We were not the first generation in history to live in fear of the end of the<br />
world. But we were the first to have proof that it could happen. From what<br />
we knew of Hiroshima and Nagasaki we knew what it would be like. And as<br />
first the Soviet Union and th th9er-countries developed weapons, and<br />
tested them, and the weapons became infinitely more powerful than the<br />
Hiroshima bomb, the threat grew.<br />
For half a century we have lived with this threat: that a miscalculation or a<br />
moment of madness among a handful of men in Washington and Moscow<br />
might bring an end to human life.-<br />
To say that this knowledge profoundly changed our thinking is to understate<br />
the case. The mushroom cloud has lived in all our minds. It has pervaded<br />
our thoughts about the future; about our children, about human nature.<br />
So long as the Cold War continued, the shadow of nuclear war grew larger.<br />
New technologies emerged to make weapons and their delivery systems ever<br />
more efficient and deadly. We became familiar with terms like Mutual<br />
Assured Destruction, but we never got used to the idea.<br />
The Cold War limited our options, but many countries did what they could to<br />
make the world safer. Australia was among those countries. In fact, at the<br />
forefront of them.<br />
We worked through international organisations to persuade the international<br />
community to heed the dangers of nuclear competition and prevent nuclear<br />
proliferation and reduce nuclear stockpiles. We created a new post an </p>
<p>Ambassador for Disarmament. In 1985 we took a leading role in developing<br />
the Treaty of Rarotonga which established the South Pacific Nuclear Free<br />
Zone. Protocol 3 of that Treaty prohibits nuclear testing in the South Pacific.<br />
The end of the Cold War came as an unexpected and promising coda to the<br />
century. It promised a way out of the nuclear prison. For a moment it<br />
seemed possible that what we had assumed to be a permanent feature of our<br />
lives might have been a temporary nightmare.<br />
It created a great opportunity: but to seize this opportunity the two great<br />
questions of nuclear proliferation and nuclear testing had to be addressed.<br />
At an international conference in May this year, it was agreed to indefinitely<br />
extend and strengthen the operation of the Treaty on the Non-Proliferation of<br />
Nuclear Weapons ( NP T). The purpose of thei NPT is -to-p revent the<br />
emergence of new nuclear weapons states. Without the NPT it is likely that<br />
many countries would have found it impossible to resist the temptation to<br />
develop nuclear weapons.<br />
It was a key to the agreement that non-nuclear weapons states were assured<br />
the nuclear powers would play their part in diminishing the nuclear threat and<br />
exercise ' utmost restraint' in testing weapons before a Comprehensive Test<br />
Ban Treaty ( CTBT) was agreed.<br />
A commitment to conclude an internationally binding and -genuine CTBT no<br />
later than the end of 1996 was one of the most important outcomes of the<br />
NPT conference in May. This would achieve a goal for which Australia,<br />
among other countries, has long fought in the United Nations.<br />
Australia played an influential role at the May conference. We have been<br />
active in the work underway to complete the Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty<br />
as soon as possible and have tabled a draft text. The conclusion of the<br />
CTBT should bring a permanent end to nuclear testing and will be a major<br />
boost to the cause of nuclear disarmament and non-proliferation. It is a key<br />
policy aim of the Australian Government.<br />
The 50th anniversary of Hiroshima and Nagasaki the only times nuclear<br />
weapons have been used in war is an appropriate moment to urge all<br />
governments to redouble their efforts for the completion of a Test Ban Treaty.<br />
Continued testing gives comfort to would-be proliferators and sours the<br />
atmosphere in which the Treaty negotiations will take place. Australia calls<br />
on all nuclear weapons states to put an immediate end to nuclear testing.<br />
We have made our position on this clear to the Government of the People's<br />
Republic of China and the Government of France.<br />
The Australian Government recently sent a high-level delegation to the<br />
nuclear weapon states to underline our concerns. I am pleased that all five </p>
<p>nuclear weapon states have confirmed their commitment to a successful<br />
conclusion to the CTBT in the agreed time. We intend to hold them to this.<br />
In addition to the effort for a CTBT, Australia is supporting another measure<br />
flowing from the Non-Proliferation Treaty conference: the immediate<br />
negotiation of a convention to cease the production of fissionable material for<br />
nuclear weapons or other nuclear devices.<br />
The French Government's decision to resume testing at Mururoa caused<br />
anger in Australia and throughout the world not only because of concern for<br />
the Pacific environment, but because it puts all this work at risk. It puts at risk<br />
our hopes for a post Cold War world which does not have the nuclear<br />
shadow hanging over it.<br />
The French nuclear testing program is a symptom of the wider problem the<br />
problem of what we do to reduce and eliminate nuclear weapons in the 21 st<br />
century. Since 23 June when I announced the measures we have taken to bring home<br />
to the French Government the extent of Australian concerns about their<br />
policy, we have continued to build coalitions with other countries which share<br />
our view of the testing program.<br />
We have been particularly pleased at the way many people in Europe, both<br />
within governments and outside, have spoken out against the French<br />
decision. Similarly welcome expressions of concern have been made by<br />
Japan, by our ASEAN neighbours and by the countries of Latin America.<br />
A central aim of our policy is to work with this international coalition, not only<br />
in our opposition to French tests but also on wider nuclear issues.<br />
The South Pacific Forum Regional Action Committee has begun its work. An<br />
import it fieeting of EiiVironment Ministers from the~ fiWf6en South Pacific<br />
Forum countries will be held in Brisbane on 16 and 17 August to discuss the<br />
environmental impact of testing.<br />
At the international level, the Government has decided that Australia will join<br />
with other countries, including Japan, in bringing before the 50th anniversary<br />
session of the United Nations General Assembly a resolution calling for a<br />
complete and imi~ di~ td end to nuclear testing.<br />
We also believe that progress towards a nuclear weapons-free world may be<br />
aided by the creation of linkages between the existing or potential nuclearweapon<br />
free zones which already cover most of the Southern Hemisphere.<br />
We will be exploring this with the members of the S. outh Pacific Nuclear Free<br />
Zone and the other zones involved.--<br />
In order to strengthen our communication with the governments and people of<br />
the European countries, many of whom share our views, and to ensure that<br />
our position is fully understood, I have asked the Minister for Pacific Island </p>
<p>Affairs, the Hon Gordon Bilney MP, to lead a Parliamentary delegation to<br />
Europe in-early September. -This will be additional to a delegation, led by the<br />
President of the Senate,. Senator Beahan, which will also be in Europe<br />
meeting members of the European Parliament.<br />
The Government has been considering the issue of whether Australia can<br />
take action in the International Court. of Just_ e against the French tests. At<br />
present, the legal advice suggests that such avenues are not open to us. We<br />
will, however, be making oral submissions to the Court on the advisory<br />
opinions sought by the World Health Organisation and the UN General<br />
Assembly on the legality-df--ing nuclear weapons. As the French tests<br />
raise important issues relevant to these proceedings, our position will be<br />
firmly on the record before the court.<br />
There have been a number of calls for the Government to send a ship to<br />
Mururoa Atoll as part of an international protest against the testing program.<br />
I have previously ruled out sending a naval vessel. The Government takes<br />
the view that naval vessels should be used for naval purposes.<br />
We have also considered the possibility of sending a non-naval vessel. The<br />
Government has decided against such an action in the current<br />
circumstances. Our reasons are principally strategic and financial. It would<br />
be a costly exercise and it is by no means certain that it would have any<br />
practical effect. We believe, on balance, that our resources can be put to<br />
better use developing other elements of our campaign.<br />
The Government is, however, concerned about the safety of Australian<br />
participants in the flotilla. Present indications are that around ten Australian<br />
yachts could be involved. The Australian Maritime Safety Authority, in<br />
consultation with the Australian Defence Force, will be in touch with relevant<br />
South Pacific search and rescue agencies to offer any additional support if<br />
this is required.<br />
The Government will also strengthen consular support for Australians in<br />
French Polynesia.<br />
With the tragedies of World War II and Cold War tension now behind us, we<br />
have for the first time in many generations an opportunity to remake our<br />
concepts of world security and take positive steps towards a world without<br />
nuclear weapons.<br />
Hiroshima is a most powerful reminder that we must not waste that<br />
opportunity. CANBERRA Issued 5 August 1995 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
