<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5381</transcript-id>
    <title>LETTER TO AOF</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/06/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Correspondence</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005381.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
l MISTt õ ALIA<br />
PRiE N13NISTER JUNE, 1980<br />
LETTER TO A. O. F.<br />
The Prime Minister met officials of the Australian Olympic<br />
Federation in Melbourne on Friday.<br />
Attached is the text of a letter given to the President of<br />
the AOF, Mr. S. B. Grange, M. V. O. ZqCf fr1E y z-mv&gt; </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER CANBERRA<br />
13 June, 1980<br />
Dear Mr. Grange,<br />
It was a matter of' great regret to the Government<br />
that the Ex.--utive of the Australian' Olympic Federation<br />
decided at its meeting of 23 May that an Australian<br />
team should participate in the Moscow Olympic Games.<br />
The Governmecnt has stressed the high interests of<br />
national security that are involved in this question.<br />
The Government has explained the need to prevent the<br />
free and independent world making the same mistakes<br />
in the 1980s as were made in the latter part of the<br />
1930s. Members of the AOF and of sports administrations<br />
who lived through World War II would need no reminding<br />
of the need for resolute action in the face of aggression.<br />
The Government's attitude to the Soviet invasion of<br />
Afghanistan needs to be seen against the background of<br />
subversion, expansion and aggression caused by the<br />
Soviet Union over many years. Apart from their activities<br />
in Hungary and Czechoslovakia, the Soviet Union or its<br />
surrogates have acted in Angola, Yemen, Ethiopia,<br />
Indo-China and Afghanistan to this point, the last and<br />
worst of their aggressions.<br />
The Government is deeply concerned that the Soviet Union<br />
spends more on armaments as a percentage of GNP than did<br />
Nazi Germany in 1938, and twice as much as does the<br />
United: States of America.<br />
Agains t this background, the Government has pressed the<br />
view that the USSR's invasion of Afghanistan requires a<br />
resolute response from Australia* and that, as an<br />
important part of that response, an Australian team<br />
should not be present at the Moscow Olympics. Now it<br />
appears that some members of the AOF Executive, in<br />
exercising their independent right to make a decision in<br />
these matters, have decided to place their perceived duty<br />
to the International Olympic movement above their duty<br />
to Australia, and to all Australians. The Government<br />
cannot accept that such a decision would be taken if<br />
there were a proper understanding of all the factors<br />
involved. In any case, since that decision there have been<br />
important changes in circumstances both in Australia and<br />
overseas, which in addition to the continuing Soviet<br />
occupation of Afghanistan provide sound reasons for<br />
reversing the decision. </p>
<p>-2<br />
A number of sporting bodies and individual sportsmen<br />
and women have decided to withdraw from the Australian<br />
Olympic contingrent. The team is no longer the best that<br />
Australia can field. This is a reflection of the<br />
grow-ing community view that Australian sportsmen and women<br />
should not take part in the Moscow Games.<br />
Significantly, almost all sporting bodioes in New Zealand<br />
have withdrawn fromi the Moscow Games. I understand only<br />
four members remain in the original team. ' De facto'<br />
there is no New Zealand team.<br />
This brings me to a serious point. Australia is now<br />
isolated in our region. China, Japan, South Korea,<br />
Hong Kong, the Philippines, Thailand, Malaysia, Singapore,<br />
Indonesia, Papua New Guinea, Fiji and de facto New Zealand<br />
will not be attending.<br />
In deciding to attend the Moscow Games, Australia is<br />
virtually alone in the region, in company with only<br />
communist Laos, communist Vietnam and communist North Korea.<br />
I have to say that I find that a shameful position to be in.<br />
The AOF Executive decision ignores the national interest<br />
and clearly its thinking is not shared by all those other<br />
governments in our region and by many others, not least<br />
by a majority of Australian citizens themselves.<br />
The AOF Executive has effectively isolated Australia from<br />
our regional allies and partners, and from many of our<br />
most important traditional friends. Let me put it to you<br />
personally, and through you to the Executive, that<br />
Australia as an independent nation with an unqualified<br />
record in defence of liberty and the right to be free,<br />
has a " bounden duty to support other free and independent<br />
nationg--To fail to do so is to deny our history.<br />
Moreover., there is a specific and urgent need for<br />
Australia, as an ally of the United States, to support the<br />
world's greatest free power and our ally. Each of these<br />
grounds standing alone should be sufficient. Both together<br />
represent an overwhelming argumeiit to which the AOF must<br />
respond.<br />
The Soviet invasion of Afghanistan was totally without<br />
justification. it was an affront to the principle of the<br />
independence and sovereignty of nations, and clearly in<br />
contempt of the Charter of the United Nations. It has<br />
been condemned by the United Nations General Assembly and<br />
the U. N. Commission on Human Rights, by the House of<br />
Commons, by the Parliament of Europe and by many others.<br />
Despite this, the invasion is continuing, with widespread<br />
bloodshed and brutality. / 3 </p>
<p>3<br />
A united response by all freedom-loving countries<br />
to the Soviet aggression is vital if we are to<br />
demonstrate that the will and resolve exists to<br />
make them pay a high price for their continued<br />
occupation of Afghanistan. It is necessary to<br />
prevent further Soviet moves which would take the<br />
world closer to war. A lack of such resolve would<br />
undoubtedly have serious consequences for world<br />
peace and put at risk the national security of all<br />
free and independent nations, with whom Australia<br />
must stand.<br />
The Government, along with other like-minded countries,<br />
cannot understand how a country engaged in the invasion,<br />
occupation and suppression of another nation could<br />
be a fit host for the Olympic Games. It is generally<br />
accepted that the Soviet Union sees the Games as a means<br />
of demonstrating widespread approval of its foreign<br />
policy. In going to Moscow our athletes will be<br />
portrayed by the Soviet Union as in sympathy with Soviet<br />
foreign policies. But a foreign policy that results in<br />
the invasion and brutal repression of another people<br />
is one that is abhorrent to the great majority of<br />
Australians. As I have said on many occasions recently, the Government<br />
has no wish to penalise athletes. Nevertheless, we<br />
should not place athletes above all other young<br />
Australians. Nor should sports officials place themselves<br />
and athletes above other Australians. Sports officials<br />
in exercising the right to make the decision on whether<br />
to go to Moscow must concede that there is a responsibility<br />
to Australia which transcends other responsibilities.<br />
A boycott of the Moscow Olympic Gaines will demonstrate<br />
to the Soviet people the world-wide condemnation of<br />
their country's invasion of Afghanistan. Notwithstanding<br />
the controls on the Soviet media, a boycott will be<br />
visible and the, reasons for it will be brought home<br />
to the Soviet people.<br />
Chancellor Schmidt, Prime Minister Thatcher and Prime<br />
Minister Trudeau have written to me recently re-affirming<br />
their position on the importance of a boycott of the<br />
Mosco. Games. Mr. Trudeauemphasised that there is no<br />
sign that the Soviet Union is about to reconsider its<br />
policy of aggression in Afghanistan. He pointed out<br />
that there is thus more reason to ensure that the / 4 </p>
<p>4<br />
boycott of the Moscow Games is supported by as many as<br />
the world's governments and international Olympic<br />
Committees as possible. Mr. Trudeau makes it plain<br />
that it is his view that a boycott is an effective<br />
instrument that the world can use to say plainly to<br />
the Soviet Union that its military adventurism stands<br />
condemned. Similar views have been put recently by the Soviet<br />
human rights activist and Nobel Prizewinner, Andrei<br />
Sakharov, who said, in the context of the Soviet<br />
invasion of Afghanistan, that ' the broadest possible<br />
boycott of the Moscow Olympics is necessary. Every<br />
spectator or athlete who comes to the Olympics will be<br />
giving indirect support to Soviet. military policies'.<br />
My Government wants no part in this. Neither does the<br />
majority of the Australian people.<br />
In these circumstances and against the background of the<br />
effective boycott of the Moscow Games by many important<br />
sporting countries, I ask you, on behalf of the Government,<br />
to institute whatever action is necessary for your<br />
Executive to review and reverse its decision concerning<br />
participation by an Australian team. Notwithstanding<br />
the lateness of the hour and the advanced state of<br />
preparation, it is imperative that this should be done.<br />
I ask all members of the Executive as plainly and bluntly<br />
as possible to place their national duty first.<br />
This letter has been firmly argued. That is deliberately<br />
so. In uncertain times, no national leader can<br />
guarantee world peace and freedom from war. Weakness<br />
and irresolution will bring war measurably closer.<br />
There: can be no apology for and no appeasement with<br />
aggressors. What I can guarantee is that whatever hold<br />
the world now has on peace will be made measurably more<br />
secure by Australian support of the Olympic boycott.<br />
I expect you to place Australia first.<br />
Yours sincerely,<br />
( Malcolm Fraser)<br />
Mr. S. B. Grange, M. V. O.,<br />
President, Australian Olympic Federation. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
