<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7940</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, LAKE RECEPTION CENTRE, BALLARAT BOTONICAL GARDENS, LAKE FORESHORE 6 MARCH 1990</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/03/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007940.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, LAKE LODGE RECEPTION<br />
CENTRE, BALLARAT BOTANICAL GARDENS, LAKE FORESHORE, 6<br />
MARCH 1990<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
PM: Well ladies and gentlemen, yesterday Mr Peacock<br />
managed in one day to massively insult both the<br />
intelligence and the commitment of the Australian people.<br />
He insulted their intelligence by parading before them a<br />
policy speech which had a $ 6 billion credibility gap, $ 6<br />
billion at least of unfunded promises. And in that<br />
regard, let me say this people will remember the 1987<br />
election campaign and Mr Howard's arithmetical error.<br />
The gap, the $ 6 billion gap, of Mr Peacock is much worse<br />
than the arithmetical error of Mr Howard in 1987. It is<br />
much larger and it is no arithmetical error. It is a<br />
deliberate con job on the Australian people. The<br />
Australian people are entitled to an answer to the<br />
question ' where is the money coming from?'. But, as<br />
usual, Mr Peacock has no answers.* So that is the insult<br />
to the intelligence to the Australian people. I don't<br />
believe that ever before in an election have you had a<br />
party so deliberately coming before the Australian people<br />
making massive unfunded promises and not giving any<br />
answer as to where the money is coming from.<br />
Secondly, and in a sense more deeply repugnant is the<br />
insult to the commitment of the Australian people. In<br />
his policy speech yesterday Mr Peacock said that<br />
productivity growth in Australia had been to quote him<br />
' virtually zero'. That is a deliberate untruth as is<br />
revealed in today's paper. Both Australian independent<br />
studies and now the revised studies of the OECD show that<br />
under this Government, productivity has been increasing<br />
by the order of three percent per annum. Now that<br />
represents a combination of the work of Australian<br />
workers and the commitment of investment by Australian<br />
entrepreneurs. Together, over this period of Government,<br />
productivity increasing very substantially, but in their<br />
attempt to write down their country and to write down<br />
their fellow Australians, Mr Peacock says productivity<br />
growth has been virtually zero.<br />
It's not a bad achievement by a man who would be Prime<br />
Minister of this country to at one and the same time<br />
insult both the intelligence of the Australian people to<br />
think that he can get away with a $ 6 billion unfunded set </p>
<p>of promises and at the same time to insult their<br />
commitment to their country in terms of saying there's<br />
been virtually no productivity growth in this period.<br />
I believe that Mr Peacock and those around him will pay<br />
dearly for this insult to the Australian people.<br />
JOURNALIST: How do you make up the $ 6 billion?<br />
PM: Well, let me, let me take that up. He of course<br />
purports to fund his first year, but even, let me remind<br />
you in respect of his first year, the Department of<br />
Finaince found, as you will remember, the $ 825 million,<br />
$ 835 million hole in regard to the first year. But in<br />
regard to the second and third year he identifies no<br />
fundings. Now let me just make the point before I go to<br />
the details of that to say this. Why will Mr Peacock and<br />
Dr Hewson not submit their proposals to the analysis of<br />
the Department of Finance as we've done. The stark<br />
contrast is there between the Government and the<br />
Opposition. We tell you before the start of the<br />
campaign, there are the savings, they're identified and<br />
with each commitment that i make during this campaign,<br />
it's set of f against those savings. Every commitment by<br />
Hawke and the Government in this campaign, every new<br />
commitment, totally funded and the process verified by<br />
the Department of Finance. And I demand, on behalf of<br />
the Australian people, that the opposition should subject<br />
their proposals to exactly the same scrutiny. Now let's<br />
look at the major components of the $ 6 billion hole which<br />
is a conservative estimate.<br />
About roads, first of all. He talks about his $ 1 billion<br />
commitment to roads, it's made up of $ 230 million new<br />
expenditure in the first year. But then that's added to<br />
by another $ 115 million in the second year and then an<br />
additional $ 115 million in third year. So there's $ 230<br />
million in regard to roads, unfunded. Then we come to<br />
two tier tax scales. Now you Will recall that when they<br />
made the promise to bring in the two tier tax scale<br />
months ago we said that that's at least $ 2.8 million<br />
involvement. They've conceded that themselves. Now that<br />
is something they're going to bring in, within the three<br />
years, the two tiered tax scale, and they concede that<br />
that's $ 2.8 million involved in that. And that's quite<br />
separate, as they concede themselves, quite separate from<br />
the return of bracket creep. So there's $ 230 million for<br />
roads, $ 2.8 billion for the two tiered tax scale.<br />
Next the changes to the health insurance system. That,<br />
of course, involves the opting out of Medicare and the<br />
analysis of the cost of that is somewhere between<br />
and $ 2.6 billion, between $ 1.5 and $ 2.6 billion. And of<br />
course, I don't add to that what you would need to add to<br />
it and that's the cost for tax rebates. so there's that<br />
for the opting out of the Medicare levy, between $ 1.5 and<br />
$ 2.6 billion. </p>
<p>Now just add those things up and you get the figures.<br />
There is the funding hole in the Economic Action Plan,<br />
$ 835 million, roads $ 230 million, the two tiered tax $ 2.8<br />
billion and the changes to the health system between<br />
and $ 2.6 billion, which gives you a total of between<br />
$ 5.3 or $ b. 4 and $ 6b billion. And that's without taking<br />
account, as I say, of the cost of the tax rebates and you<br />
look at the odds and sods that I haven't even counted<br />
there. Breast cancer screening if they're going to<br />
match the Government as they seem to be talking about<br />
another $ 20 million there. Education at least<br />
million there. And local government, they say they're<br />
going to increase the share of money going there, but<br />
that's unmentioned, no figure attached to that. Other<br />
unfunded commitments, look at those. Sales tax free<br />
shopping for tourists, more support for the Federal<br />
Police, the National crime Authority and the Customs<br />
Service and the contingent liability involved in<br />
underwriting for the wheat industry, so by any analysis<br />
whatsoever, the $ 6 billion is a most conservative<br />
estimate of the unfunded spending commitments of Mr<br />
Peacock and the opposition.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, last night Liberal Party<br />
television advertisements Are you also worried it<br />
could be very effective?<br />
PH: Well, in the end, Peter, you've got to ask yourself<br />
the question. What judgement do you make about the<br />
intelligence of the Australian people? I mean, you can<br />
have you can have Mr Peacock getting up and running<br />
the line, the answer is Liberal. The same Mr Peacock<br />
refusing to answer questions. Now, are the Australian<br />
people going to be impressed by the proposition, the<br />
answer is Liberal, and he runs away from full scale Press<br />
conferences. He will not make himself available to the<br />
sort of analysis that I regularly make myself available<br />
to. The whole Press corps you've got me. Any<br />
questions you want to ask on economnica you ask. I deal<br />
with them, no running away from them. Now<br />
JOURNALIST: ( inaudible)<br />
PM: Now let, let me, let me finish. I'll come back to<br />
your question. They are people about whom you've got to<br />
ask the question. Are they going to be impressed by' what<br />
you call a slick television presentation. But a slick<br />
television presentation which doesn't answer the<br />
question, where's the money coming from. The Australian<br />
people have a record of wanting to know of political<br />
parties when they make promises, where is the money<br />
coming from. And in 1987, you'll recall, they marked<br />
down Mr Howard very, very much indeed for what as I<br />
recall was about $ 1.5 billion. Here is $ 6 billion. Now<br />
at least you can say in defence of Mr Howard that it was<br />
incompetence. I don't believe there was any intent by Mr<br />
Howard deliberately to mislead the Australian people in<br />
1987. It was incompetence and he was marked down for </p>
<p>incompetence as he should have been. But here is a<br />
deliberate con job. Well I don't my judgement about<br />
the Australian people Peter, my very, very profound<br />
judgemnent about the Australian people and I've been in<br />
public lire for 30 years is that they will not buy con<br />
jobs.<br />
JOURNALIST: You sound rattled.<br />
PM: That may be your judgement that I sound rattled. I<br />
can assure you 1im not rattled. I feel very, very<br />
profoundly concerned that a party that would seek to<br />
offer itself as an alternative government and a leader<br />
that would seek to offer himself as an alternative prime<br />
minister can so insult the intelligence of the Australian<br />
electorate that they can have this $ 6 billion funding gap<br />
and think that they will get away with it. Now that<br />
moves me very deeply. And I'm certainly not only not<br />
rattled, I can assure you that in terms of straight<br />
political analysis this is the worst mistake, the worst<br />
mistake the coalition could possibly have made. I mean<br />
they should have attempted to say just where the money<br />
was coining from.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, the upward revision of<br />
Australia's productivity, the private sector did better<br />
than the public sector with productivity at about 3.8 per<br />
cent. This could be a fairly strong argument could it<br />
not for privatisation? more productive Australia,<br />
well to the private sector.<br />
PM: it adds nothing to that argument whatsoever.<br />
Because as you'll appreciate, that in so much of the<br />
public sector the assumptions, the statistical<br />
assumptions that are made are of zero productivity<br />
growth. And so much of it is services area. That<br />
statistical assumption is made. That's a large part of<br />
the explanation for that fact.<br />
JOURNALIST: The Opposition wants to sell of f Qantas.<br />
Given reports today that Qantas may make a loss, what's<br />
your view of selling off the airline?<br />
PM: Well, there are these points to be made about their<br />
selling off proposals. Before I go to Qantas may I just<br />
pick up the point about another weakness in what happened<br />
yesterday. They've plucked the figure of $ 550 million<br />
out of the air for the proposed sale of a second cellular<br />
mobile telephone service and we've seen what people in<br />
the industry have had to say about that. If ever there<br />
was a rubbery figure, it's that $ 550 million. They've<br />
plucked the figure out of the air. Now in regard to the<br />
airlines, you ask well we're in a situation where<br />
there may be a loss involved and what figures would you<br />
attach to it. That's one question, but I would simply<br />
make this point. That in regard to the fundamentals of<br />
the Australian economy, the fundamentals of whether<br />
you're going to blow the budget surplus by unfunded </p>
<p>promises, those things are at the periphery. I mean what<br />
you've got here is the certainty of the budget surplus<br />
being blown for two reasons. One, the $ 6 billion hole<br />
that I've talked about, but on the other hand, on the<br />
revenue side, they are going to throw away the capital<br />
gains tax which over a period of time was billions of<br />
dollars. You take the two things together, take the two<br />
things together and they are going to mean that all the<br />
hard work we've done together to accumulate ft surplus,<br />
which I have used to pay off debt, is gone. The budget<br />
surplus will be blown. And there's no possibility that<br />
some peripheral income they may get from talking about<br />
the sales of some public asset like the airlines can deal<br />
with those fundamental problems. They are ideologically<br />
driven by the view that necessarily public enterprise is<br />
bad and private enterprise is good. Let me say this, as<br />
far and particularly it's appropriate out here in an<br />
area, a rural area that any suggestion that you would<br />
play around with enterprises like Telecom and Australia<br />
Post, which provide services in a cost subsidised way to<br />
rural Australia, is very very dangerous for nonmetropolitan<br />
Australians.<br />
JOURNALIST: Journalists are all saying that Mr Peacock<br />
is promising relief but not promising any pain in order<br />
to get there. Are you prepared to say to the Australian<br />
people at your policy speech there will be pain, that it<br />
won't be an easy road?<br />
PH: I, I don't have to say that in terms of the<br />
comparison with Mr Peacock. I've already made the point<br />
that where we are making new commitments we have funded<br />
them. People know if we are, as for instance in the area<br />
of women's affairs, $ 64 million over three years for<br />
early screening in regard to breast cancer. We have paid<br />
for that. And very importantly, in regard to the States,<br />
we are not imposing now virtually another half a billion<br />
dollars pain upon the States. We've done it ourselves.<br />
This is particularly important to the states and I'd<br />
suggest particularly important for a small state like<br />
Tasmania. Tasmania is going to have, leaving aside what<br />
individuals it will cost them, it's going to cost them<br />
about another $ 17 billion in grants taken away. Look at<br />
NSW. I mean have you ever seen anything so ridiculous as<br />
the proposal in regard to the beaches in NSW. He's going<br />
to let them borrow more money. But he's going to take<br />
about $ 120 million off them in State grants. Where we<br />
make new proposals they are funded, are funded. People<br />
know how we are going to meet our commitments.<br />
JOURNALIST: Coming back to the $ 6 billion. You say<br />
you've been talking about that figure since the last<br />
session of Parliament, but is it because you don't think<br />
your message is getting through, that your profound<br />
concern is so much more manifest today?<br />
PH: No, today is the day after they've announced the<br />
policy speech. one was expecting and hoping Graham that </p>
<p>they would discharge their obligation at the policy<br />
launch of explaining where the money was coming from.<br />
Now there was a deafening silence. My responsibility to<br />
the people or Australia is to point out, and point<br />
vehemently and effectively, that silence. which means<br />
that all that we have done together in this country to<br />
transfer the inherited deficit of $ 9.5 billion, which<br />
I've turned around to a more than $ 9 billion surplus,<br />
which live used with my colleagues to pay off our<br />
overseas debt. Australian citizens in respect of the<br />
Commonwealth Government owe not one net cent of overseas<br />
debt. Because we've got a surplus, we've paid it of f.<br />
But now they're going to blow that apart with the $ 6<br />
billion unfunded promises and throwing away the proceeds<br />
of the capital gains tax. That's foundational to the<br />
future welfare of this country. And any person who is<br />
the Prime Minister as I am and who intends to continue to<br />
have the responsibility for the Government of this<br />
country has a responsibility to explain and explain<br />
strongly to the Australian people just what has been<br />
promised to them. What's been promised to them is the<br />
collapse of the Australian economy. The Australian<br />
economy must collapse. Interest rates must go through<br />
the roof when you have a bursting of the deficit and a<br />
wages * explosion. Those two things together, the blowing<br />
of the budget surplus and the wages explosion, mean that<br />
interest rates must go through the roof.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, has there been any discussion<br />
between the Federal and Victorian governments about how<br />
the loss of the State Bank<br />
PM: No.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, can we talk a bit about Ballarat<br />
issues while you're here.<br />
PH: Sure, sure.<br />
JOURNALIST: The Small Business Association o f Victoria<br />
claimed that you revolt in two weeks time.<br />
PM; Claims what?<br />
JOURNALIST: They plan a Eureka-style revolt. In two<br />
weeks time protesters by the Government.<br />
PM: That is a singularly ill-informed approach. Letts<br />
just look at the facts in regard to business, small as<br />
well as large. the facts, not these, none of what I<br />
say now opinions, every one of them facts. Let's look at<br />
them. Growth, economic growth under my Government<br />
economic growth twice as fast as under the conservatives.<br />
Employment growth 1.6 million new jobs, five times as<br />
fast as under the conservatives. And of those 1.6<br />
million new jobs, 92% of them in the private sector. Most<br />
of them in the small business area, most of them in the<br />
small business area. So employment growth </p>
<p>unprecedented growth. Taxation, taxation, let's look at<br />
that. When the conservatives walked out of office, what<br />
was the top tax rate? I'll tell you what it was<br />
cents in the dollar. What is it now 47 cents in the<br />
dollar. Bottom rate 30 cents. What is it now 21<br />
cents in the dollar. When the conservatives walked out,<br />
what about division seven tax and undistributed profits<br />
a massive impost upon small business. we've removed<br />
that. JOURNALIST: what about commercial interest rates?<br />
PM: Ok, well what about commercial interest rates?<br />
Never at any point under my Government have they reached<br />
the peak that they did in April ' 82 under the<br />
conservatives. 22% for 90 day bill rates. Never<br />
reached. They are now 16%.<br />
JOURNALIST: Home loan rates?<br />
PM: Home loan rates. The situation there of course is<br />
that under the conservatives it wasn't a question of what<br />
interest rates were, the money wasn't available. You..<br />
people under the conservatives simply by locking of f the<br />
supply of money. There was no money available. If you<br />
want to test it over the period of government I suggest<br />
you test it by the number of houses built. The fact is<br />
that under my Government on an annual basis there's been<br />
9% more homes, 12,000 per annum more homes built under my<br />
Government than under the conservatives.<br />
JOURNALIST: The Master Builders at the moment are saying<br />
the industry is stagnating.<br />
PM: The Master Builders are wrong. it's certainly not<br />
what the Housing Industry Association is saying. It's<br />
very difficult to say that in the light of the figures<br />
I've just given you. The statistics do not support it.<br />
JOURNALIST: On another issue, one in four country<br />
children in poverty, living in poverty in country<br />
Victoria. PM: No, the question of child poverty is I guess best<br />
answered in this way. Don't rely on my assertion that<br />
the commitment that there be no financial need for a<br />
child to live in poverty has been met. Rely on these<br />
three statements, I suggest to you. I don't know that<br />
you would want to question the integrity of the<br />
Brotherhood of St Laurence, I don't know that you'd want<br />
to question the integrity of Julian Disney of the<br />
Australian council of Social Services, I don't know<br />
whether you'd want to question the integrity of the<br />
Australian Institute of Family studies. But what have<br />
they had to say? Let me quote them. Bishop Hollingworth<br />
from the Brotherhood of St Laurence in 1989 said that ' in<br />
strict income security terms, there's no doubt that the<br />
Prime ministerial promise will be achieved'. That is<br />
I </p>
<p>Bishop Hollingworth. Mr Julian Disney of the Australian<br />
Council of Social Services ' it is without doubt', his<br />
words, ' it is without doubt a remarkable achievement<br />
first to have set and then to have achieved the payment<br />
of the benchmarks to the children of low income<br />
families'. And thirdly the Australian institute of<br />
Family Studies ' by these means', they said, ' the<br />
benchmarks sent by the Government have been met'. Now if<br />
you want to question the judgement of those people who<br />
are working in the area that the financial commitment<br />
that I made has been met then do so. The fact is of<br />
course they are saying that on the basis that in this<br />
year over $ 2 billion, over $ 2 billion have been paid in<br />
the Family Allowance Supplement to low income families.<br />
An example of what that means a one income family on<br />
$ 320 a week with three kids, that means that under the<br />
scheme that I have brought in, indexed, they get $ 110 a<br />
week tax free which is equivalent to a wage increase of<br />
$ 170 a week. Having said all that, in discussion with<br />
the Brotherhood of St Laurence, the Australian council of<br />
Social Services and the governments, we realise that more<br />
has to be done. What we've got to do is to make sure<br />
that services get delivered where they are needed. And<br />
that includes in some country areas where they don't have<br />
the same access to services as they do more readily in<br />
the cities.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, you've said you're prepared to<br />
answer questions about your economic policies. we know<br />
where the conservatives stand on privatisation. Can you<br />
tell me whether you support the sale of airlines?<br />
PH: I can tell you what I've done there. I've set up<br />
the Committee of the Labor Party to look at that and that<br />
is being looked at. I obviously will wait till those<br />
processes are followed through. We'll get their reports<br />
as what's the appropriate way of dealing with the capital<br />
needs of the airlines. But let me make the point, you<br />
know, the quite fundamental point, that what is done or<br />
not done there is entirely peripherial, entirely<br />
peripherial to the fundamental issues of economic<br />
management. ' rhe issues of economic management in this<br />
country, the most important issue is wages policy. And<br />
there YOU still have the situation where we are now just<br />
over two weeks away from the election of this man who<br />
would be Prime Minister still saying that he doesn't know<br />
and can't tell you what the wages outcome would be. At<br />
the same time as he's also giving you a $ 6 billion<br />
funding hole.<br />
JOURNALIST: Dr Howson did a rather skillful job<br />
presenting economic problems and his solution. Do you<br />
accept that the Government has a presentational problem<br />
in trying to explain to the Australian people what's<br />
wrong with the economy?<br />
PH4: I don't accept that we've got a presentational<br />
problem. But I would say this, that it's always </p>
<p>difficult to cover the whole gamut of considerations that<br />
are involved and the complexities of running an economy<br />
as large as the Australian economy, and covering all the<br />
issues. There will always be a chance of doing it<br />
better. I mean I don't claim perfection in any way in<br />
terms of being able to present all these issues. But I<br />
do say that I'm entitled to ask the Australian people to<br />
compare and contrast the presentation and analysis by<br />
Hawke and Keating with that of Peacock and Hewson on the<br />
issues. I mean the fundemental issue that will determine<br />
the future welfare country are these things. There's<br />
wages policy. Now you don't have to be theoretical about<br />
that. I mean we've had the decade of the 180s.<br />
Australians going to this election are fortunate in being<br />
able, in a sense, to test Hawke and Peacock against the<br />
experience of the ' 80s. What Peacock is offering is a<br />
return to the beginning of the ' 80a. Let the strong<br />
exercise their strength. He would've let the pilots have<br />
their 30%. No wonder that the pilots, everywhere I go,<br />
they are out there barracking for Andrew. So they<br />
should. They'd be out of their cotton-picking minds if<br />
they weren't barracking for Andrew Peacock because Andrew<br />
Peacock was barracking for them and said you have your<br />
That's what happened at the beginning of the<br />
and that's what gave us the worst recession in 50 years.<br />
Now against that our wage predictions are always right<br />
there in the ball park. And where we say the wages<br />
outcome will be seven percent, that's what it will be.<br />
And therefore workers and wage and salary earners and<br />
employers and governments can plan accordingly. Now<br />
that's an essential you can compare and contrast Hawke<br />
and Peacock on that. You can compare and contrast Hawke<br />
and Peacock on fiscal responsibility. I am the first<br />
Prime Minister with my Government ever to run the<br />
business of the Australian Government in profit. I<br />
inherited an enormous accumulated deficit, commonwealth<br />
deficit from the conservatives who'd never been able to<br />
run at a profit. We've run at a profit of $ 17 billion in<br />
the last three years and we've used that to pay of f debt.<br />
But now he's promising a return to the past $ 6 billion<br />
hole. Give away capital gains tax, the surplus blown.<br />
So with wages explosion and surplus blown, interests<br />
rates through the roof, collapsed economy.<br />
JOURNALIST: Following on from that, are you concerned by<br />
comments suggesting that the wage-tax deal has made<br />
little impact?<br />
PHI That what?<br />
JOURNALIST: That suggestion that the wage-tax deal<br />
has made little impact.<br />
PH: If you look in detail at the polling they show that<br />
clearly more are impressed by it than are not. I<br />
would've hoped obviously you'd always hope that you'd<br />
get a bigger impact than apparently there is. But I have<br />
no doubt at all that the message is coming quite clearly </p>
<p>through. And our polling shows it, shows it<br />
unequivocally that the people out there believe that<br />
Labor is more competent at economic management than the<br />
Opposition. JOURNALIST: Would you be willing to relax global<br />
borrowing for Victoria if you don't do you<br />
acknowledge that it's going to have to mean big cuts<br />
program. PH: That issue simply hasn't been addressed. We've made<br />
no commitment to that. It hasn't been addressed.<br />
JOURNALIST: Are you worried about seats in Victoria,<br />
about losing seats?<br />
PH: The polling shows that Victoria is our weakest area<br />
but I believe that as the campaign comes to conclusion<br />
Victorians are going to be influenced by the same sorts<br />
of considerations as the rest of Australia is. I mean<br />
Victorians, just as much as the rest of Australians, are<br />
surely going to be concerned about a $ 6 billion hole.<br />
Victorians, just as much as the rest of Australia, are<br />
going to be worried about a wages explosion. I think<br />
that when we get down to the l. ine that the degree of<br />
discontent that there may have been in Victoria, for<br />
particular Victorian issues, will tend to, I think, be<br />
ameliorated by their concern as Victorians for these<br />
fundamental issues. As Victorians they would suffer like<br />
the rest of Australia if there's a wages explosion. As<br />
Victorians they'd suffer like the rest of Australians if<br />
there's a $ 6 billion blowout in the Budget.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
