<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8572</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON PJ KEATING MP</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/07/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008572.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIMkE MINISTER TIHE BON P. JT. KEATING M?<br />
AUTSTRALIAN SUPPORT FOR SOUTH PACIFIC ENVIRONMENT-AL<br />
ACTIVITIES During the South Pacific Forum metinp, I reafirmed Australia's o~ pPQZ foor programs<br />
aimed at protecting the enviroximcnt of the South Pacific. I announced a number of new<br />
meaaurs which will serv to strotngthen our existing envirornental activities.<br />
Australia is already funding a $ 6.7 million Sea Level and Climate Monitoring Projec. in the<br />
Pacific. In order to increase our support for the UN Framework Convention on Climate<br />
Chzg I announced that Australia will provide a further S1.3 illfion for new progr~ ams<br />
which will enhance the capacity of the region to monitor climate change:. The new funding<br />
will be used to help upgrade meteorological equipment. train climnate-monitoring personnel<br />
and provide spcialist back-up services.<br />
Recognising that South Pacific island biological diversity is among the most threatened in<br />
the would, Australia will provide $ 5 Ailion for a biodiversity conservation and management<br />
project in the South Pacific as part of Aus6a4a S' 30 millon conmmitnent to the Global<br />
Environment Facility of the World Bank. The project will be part of Australia's support of<br />
the effective implementation of the Biodiveit' Convention.<br />
Both the sea level and biodiversity projects will bc daclopod in close consultafion with<br />
islad countries and the South Pacific; Regionial Environment Program ( SPREP).<br />
1 also underlined the importance that Australia attaches to maintaining a balance between<br />
development and environmental protection. Other environmental areas where Australia is<br />
prorviding support include tropical forost conservation, waste management and an<br />
enwomentprogram on Radio Australia.<br />
Australia cont zws to be a strong supporter of SPREP. Under its auspices, Australia helped<br />
Pacific Wsands prepare for, and attend, the UNCED metn in Rio do Januiro.<br />
I also hope the South Pacific will play a leading role in one of the key area of follow-up to<br />
UNCED, the conference on sustainable dvlopment for small islad developing states. In<br />
recognition of the special environmental nteeds of small, vlnerable statci Australia wouild<br />
be prepared to contribute towards the costs of holding the conference in the South Pacific.<br />
Hoztiara I July 1992<br />
l~ r </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
