<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6479</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, HON RJL HAWKE AC MP, BUSINESS COUNCIL OF AUSTRALIA, SYDNEY, 21 SEPTEMBER 1984</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/09/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006479.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
-tt<br />
LkL Z L v:<br />
E MBARGOED U N I L .00 P. 0I. CHCK AGAINSTDELYl\' RY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIKE IiINISTER, 11ON. HAWKE, AC, 111P<br />
BUSINESS COUNCI1L OF AUSTRALIA SYDNEY 21 SEPTEMBER 190!,<br />
I would like to begin by recording my thanks to Sir Arvi<br />
Parbo for the way in vhicn he has faci iitated contaci<br />
between the Cvernment and thc Busi ness Council ovcei the<br />
past year. I extend my Lest vwishes i z, thr-new Chairman, Mr<br />
Bob Wihte, ond look forwa-rd to continuing close<br />
co-operation.<br />
It is now just over a year since I addi-essed the first<br />
meeting of the Business Council of Austr~ aia.<br />
The year that stands between your first PrI-d second jnnL, 21<br />
meetings has been one of qrcat achi evo mEnllnt for your Council1<br />
and for Australia.<br />
Already the Business Cou.-iil of Aust'i ali and its vnt:; Aic.: s<br />
are rnakig a constructive contribution to p-: blic<br />
polic)-, iakino and public education i-p the i-tercsts ,3i<br />
inprevd economic perfornancce.<br />
And for Australia there has Lben c lear progi ess oi the<br />
changing of cttiIude:;, the buidi ri of r. ev Jinstitution! z:<br />
th1e deIopm i r.! F rew appxroach es n mnan a rCas of pu!. ic<br />
po) cch -3r necessa-iry for s nncetodi , t r og<br />
s) on J, n fl: t i ona r y q r ov . h<br />
Th'roUgh the year WE haVe exp erianc. 2 tIhst<br />
Sro~: tn in eco1ncic n, 1t0t sicrccccut<br />
fi rs; r-:.) ctcd irl thaieJ rc rsnt Oo f a0<br />
T h1-ic. t nci s 1<br />
T I t<br />
r n, </p>
<p>Fsster growth and modest teage i ncreases % 7ithin the Accord<br />
h av e d i a rrno; t i c a y reduced real unit Iabour costs. The share<br />
of national income accruing to profits is now higher thin at<br />
anly time for t. ie post 10 The continued succes.-, ful<br />
operation of the ALcord will enable_ still further<br />
improvement in real unit labourzreists because there. will be<br />
no increases -in award wages -over the twel. ve mionths to next<br />
April. Real i.. ooes cost,,; pez-unit of output are now much the<br />
same as in the late 1960' s to earl1y 1970' s.<br />
This rapid turnaround in economic activity has been<br />
accompanied by the lowest incidence of industrial<br />
disputation, as m~ easured by working days lost, for one and a<br />
hal', decades.<br />
Interest rates have fallen appreciably, contributing<br />
directly to lower business costs and improved sales and<br />
investment prospects.<br />
Our success over the past year or so, goes beyond there<br />
qjuantifiable e ffects, to greater co-o~ peration amnong:-st major<br />
groups in our economy, and the enhanczd con-imun ity confidencec<br />
that has eme rged from-, new consul tat ive inechani sis anid<br />
i nst it uti o ns.<br />
Austra) iiins have accepted and responded to the message that<br />
I have been advancing, that the objectives of each of<br />
Australia's vc:-ious economric groups can be realised MOre<br />
ef fectively ' through co-operation than through the<br />
confrontation which hsd become an entrenched feature of<br />
Australian life.<br />
As a result there is a rmuch imiproved e-. vironrnent for<br />
addressing the di f F5 cult econiomic issues and choices that WC<br />
must conf ront as a nat ion i f we are -to ochi eve susJtC ined,<br />
strong non-inf lat ionary growth<br />
At the centre of our @ chi evements to date hZI3 been the nciw<br />
wil lingness of key economic groups to enter into close arid<br />
f rank discussion with each other and with St ate crnd Fodclral<br />
coverncts on the removal of barriers to our econo~ mic<br />
p rog res s.<br />
I he continued close co-nS~ LJtat) Oni of-bui~, union: s ant')<br />
St[ Ite or-d fornmonwe'a1l 111Gverricnc. s i , e veCn M 1-<br />
i 1 r0i r. I t o 0 U' 3 su c r ( sfii F v! S kI It o na. vpc dU ntL t o<br />
3 t r e n qLth Cn J n q o u lonig or irpp r o~ i .; n c c thc: n L<br />
ceUe ou-' r r UCeU. nt t or i c recovery<br />
aI ' v Cg 11 1.1 i pp) recz n r hIe t -CI1 ! D1 t.)<br />
then u', ii rr'! Lns; ~ s ! orcu cn. ~ cc~ 1 '. E. er<br />
t h Ce~-f t 1; L ( U<br />
n j e y po : lh. e ) vc. t 1.1:<br />
y" Y, E! or I' J, ri 1: 11 U r'pi<br />
ii n -r 2; 1 L: </p>
<p>In one important area the Council is contribUtingq to the<br />
implementation of policy the Affirmative. Action Program,.<br />
The Business Council is pisaying a significant role in the<br />
course of the Program through TLhe individual efforts of its<br />
member 2-ompar ies who axe inVolved in -the. 12 months Pilot and<br />
throLgh it-, reprEsEntation on the torking Party on<br />
Affirmative Action Legis) otion. with Hr John Uhriig. I am<br />
sure -the contribution of both will help the Government to<br />
adopt a realistic and workable approach to the issue.<br />
I also greatly appreciate the * contribution that the Business<br />
Council and its m embers have already made to discussion on<br />
matters that niust-be on the vgend2 of future policy reform<br />
if we are to realise the great ambitions which we all share<br />
for Australia. T wo major examplesi are your recent<br />
submisssioi on taxation to the Econonic Planning Advisory<br />
* Council, and your thoughtful contributions on industry<br />
policy and business taxation this afternoon.<br />
Ile both understand that there will always be some issue-s on<br />
which our perceptions differ. In the end the Government,<br />
elected by) the Australian people as final arbiter of the<br />
national interest, must take responsibility for policy<br />
d eci s i o n s.<br />
But we will always make better decisions if we have access<br />
to honest and careful advice of the kind that we heve<br />
received on many issues from the Busir-. ess Council.<br />
One important feature of our cons-ultative processes is the<br />
way in whi ch they have been open to comamunity scrutiny : the<br />
positions that the Business Council, other bus iness groups,<br />
the trade union movcment and the Statc's have put to this<br />
3overnment have been recleased for public scrutiny to a far<br />
gre-ater degree than had ever previous~ jy been the case in<br />
Australia. For its own part, the Government has exposed its<br />
preliminary thinking on miajor policy issues well in advance<br />
of final decisions, to facilitate wider public comment.<br />
There are, of course, some types of information which cannot<br />
properly -be placed immediately in the public sphere. B u t I<br />
b r-1i e t Lha L w e h -3v decf in ed t hes e im j. t S mo re geCne rocusl Y to<br />
the community interest in public disclosure than an)'<br />
previous Government.<br />
And thtic po I i c y ceci s i ons 1. hat1 have cear gad f rom the-<br />
UconsulIt. et ive proueFS E-1-r'ef1l ct C. orcoln fo. r thc i der<br />
c tnmn u ni ty i n t e rcst,,, b hey u; d t h tLhf c, grouu di. r cct I y<br />
r c: p -c s oi r: d inr c o n s oIt tti rn v. </p>
<p>The re v as ey tens ive pub ! i c comment on t he Go vernment Is<br />
consul tat ion w. i th the ACTU prior to the budget Wh Pt h as<br />
received l ess comm-ient but which iE; I am sure appreciated by<br />
most of you here today iJs the. 1arqe. amoui) t of time that I<br />
personally have alloccted to fortmail P~ nd informal*. discussion<br />
of policy with a wide rnnqeof.. bus. r-esss groups. B u t i t<br />
wiould * be w-, rong to cone) ude that this close consul tat ion with<br />
some of the stronger grusi orcomm-un[. tCy means that we<br />
have disregarded other in'~ erests.<br />
To make this point., I need on] ly Tefer to what has been done<br />
by this Go\' crnmert in only 18 months to assist the genuine]), y<br />
need), in our coimunity who are not represented directly by<br />
business groups or-unions. The substantial increases in<br />
real pensions, bene fits and servicesj to thc most needy<br />
groups in our society, including pensioners with children,<br />
pensioner renters, the single unienpJ eyed, benefici aries of<br />
public housing and the aboriginal community, contrast with<br />
real decline in the previous seven years.<br />
The strong emnplosyment growth Which has accomnpanied the<br />
implementation of our economic stratngy has made a<br />
substantial contribution to the alleviation of the most<br />
. mportant single cause of poverty in our soci ety to the<br />
alloviation of both hidden and open unemnployment. There as<br />
a lonfg way to go, and our emnphasis on li fting long-term<br />
growth performance is directed very mufch to continuing the<br />
recent progress.<br />
The same point can be made by reference to the solutions to<br />
entrenched -industry problems that have oeirged from our<br />
-onsultat ive processes. The), have yielded substantial<br />
benefits for the iiider economy arid society.<br />
The major financial deregulation that: we have be<br />
implementing over the past year ha) s been accom,, panie.' d by<br />
intonse consul tation by the Treasurer, Paul Keaiting, and<br />
myself, with !-elev; rlf. business and union grnups". There is<br />
widespread agreement that the greatestA boneficiaries, are the<br />
-many users of financial servi ces, arid the w'hole communi ty<br />
through-the contribution that the financi a) reforms,, wil..<br />
mnake to overall girowth per forrnnnccs.<br />
Similarl y, the Steel niistry Plan emecrged fromi John<br />
B~ ut ton's intnsc consultzat ions wiith !:; sincss, unionfs-Sta2tc<br />
nyriienS and c-tcel users, aJ J. T. Ch CJiee itr) s t<br />
thei hl cIt h o f the i ndu~ i ry Al) of throsc grep gree th 2t.<br />
the~ hch riln) c, t! J r o i poL) stin,<br />
hnC . ie o t feEt f I 1rt. of C) a Ip( Iao JIh ~ s i Zr v I o<br />
h neu . : s o h1 -e C. Uo ti r thinoi </p>
<p>I bel ieve that the nei.-, oproach to motcr vehicle policy,<br />
announced by John Rutton eerlier this year v~ i11 be similarly<br />
success-ful encouraging more competitive industry,<br />
prov* djing moi e secure umployment and investment<br />
opportunities For those~ directily engvged in motor vehiclE:<br />
production, and better vrehicles at. Aow-er' prices for<br />
consumers than.-would have . been-avai] 3 able-. under the<br />
arrangermenrts whichi we had inheritLed..<br />
With iron ore an innovative integration of trade and<br />
industrial relations policies, formally embodied in the Iron<br />
Ore Industry Consu; l tativeu Council, the opening of which 1<br />
attended in Karratha lost mi-onthI is hclpiriq to restore<br />
dy,. ipnism to a major -Australian industry and region.<br />
In the troubled coal industry last Friday tLhF Minister for<br />
Resources and Energy Senator Peter W( alsh presided over a<br />
meeting of the Austral ian Coal. Consultat ive Council. Th e<br />
meeting arose out of the crisis precipitated by the<br />
announcement of major retrenchments by comnpanies operating<br />
on the South Coast of New South 1. ales.<br />
F ortunately, we have been able to avoid the confrontation<br />
which is currently stalling economic recovery in Britain.<br />
The meeting was characterised by the will ingness of all<br />
papties to e-. 2Dmane rationally the causes of problefms, and<br />
the opportun LiCs-for strengthening the industry.<br />
The Comnmonealth Governiienrt for its part is will ing to<br />
c inne w it h an npePn min d all1 a s p ec ts o f , ts ow n p oIi c ies<br />
whi ch bear upon the f ortunes of t he i. ndust r-<br />
Thnre L! re good -rasons wIhy the consul La t ive processes wh ic h<br />
we have sponsnred, and to which te CJ[ Sb u siness Council and aits<br />
Umemibers are contributing SO much, have beenr yielding<br />
favourable results not ontly for the pF3rtie-s motimized. ately<br />
invol ved, but for the economy as v: hole.<br />
There are always riany possible ra-sponses t-o an industry<br />
prob) er, often %; ith vastly different -f m-p). iCatio0ris for th e<br />
wide-r conmmunity, even vwhen they confer sirnilan ! short-tej-r-<br />
1bone fits on onC or other of the rmost 5 ntor ost ~ d pirties.<br />
100h c-f US carries commtnents to pai-ticrulor p c y<br />
rcE1s. P Di: F i nt o d i~ Scnsa n 1of -rn i i dus r pro l3 0o n f<br />
.1 ( G3e n S n iI SifC 0n ndU C! in1 FI ' LtdW) P!: e C<br />
r-orf rinLt on, c-z cc oai ch oun Fi; i.. cd J-1 1CUr1 L111 tiail<br />
p o Si ton. an d I n timc pore~~ E zm; oo ~ s hfr a"<br />
o rn" r i Or-op ionc </p>
<p>B~ ut in an atmosphere of CC-o) e ration-and honest<br />
conSultationl, a wider range of possib ' litdes is open to us.<br />
We can each lake a longer-term v'i of issues. in this<br />
erivi:, onment AL we i ecognise more clea:&gt; Iy a re, I ity which<br />
should be obvious to us all, hut-vhich isobscurcd in the<br />
heat of conf rontstion. And this is the reality thfit u<br />
l asting stable and sccure irolution a Solution ithat will<br />
be free from recurrina industrial or-po). itical challengr'<br />
must be sati sfactory for the wider community as well as for<br />
each of the central parties.<br />
This Government's1 docisions on economic policy have been<br />
gUi ded by commi tments to consultCation and 2onsensus, to the<br />
equlitable distribution of the benefits of economic growth,<br />
and to thie achievement Of Sustained, st rong non-inflationary<br />
growth. I hove alw-. ays seen these three commi tments as<br />
intcr-r:. lated parts of the one great program.<br />
No--progres's can be madc on any one of the three without<br />
support froin the others<br />
Without sustained, non-inflationary grovyth, there can be no<br />
lastAing progress towards any other objective.<br />
Wi thout sustained ilro'wth, high and risinrg unemployment must<br />
increase the number of our people without empl oymnt and<br />
1 ivinct in poveity. Vi thout sustained growi-th there will be<br />
insufficient resources to provide adequately for Australians<br />
in need.<br />
But equally, only an) Australian society that is broadly<br />
united on the great national goals, and which is seen by<br />
most of its citizens as a fair society, twill embrace the<br />
changes tthich are necessa-ry for sustai ned growth.<br />
1,<br />
It is a particular task of national leadership, and one that<br />
1 -as J me Mi ni Ste r 2r. hPpy to CC CePt, to infIlence the<br />
at Litudos cf the Austral ian community on a range of i ssucc<br />
that are import ant to growth.<br />
I think that Australjia~ s under. stand much rm-ore clearly n v<br />
that eighteen month-ago, thit we can achievct strong greft h<br />
over long periodS Only it' We p) ut OUr resources Lo their r. cst<br />
p Jod u Ct V C u ses. I think11 that it is rio more cluarl\<br />
undervitcod thct productive use of our rusourcE-s r'ui~<br />
acceptLance of a' o f donin-, jic srcz. r~ h. WZ<br />
011' fZC~ ror. iY rp ly Ch rin( Iill" pat Cerfnu 0o' f o j i t rade1<br />
IhJq i. ch vcIs o f i v c loe n i f r omi nai' d J c.<br />
conf) I dCCt;' 0 eIi' Ll! i . bY n f~~~ fCI<br />
prw.) cic C~ us, 0 U~ U. fow IcIILu. 
Yr: D V. C ' Y'r! d 02 . o t 1 V; </p>
<p>In the period immedintel' y hcad The greatest priority must<br />
be to sustai n th, recovery. V~ c must ctrike the richt<br />
bal ance between maint aining ndequpte qrowth in demand, end<br />
evoiding ex. cessive p~ e as ures 2n f irancicaI markts Ph ile<br />
keeping inrflation -on c dour w: ard pzth thrOUcgh the-continued<br />
successful operction of the Prices end Incomus Accord<br />
Virtual ly all observers nou agree that w-e found The right<br />
fiscal arid monetary policy mix in the las; t financial year.<br />
~ I-e believe that we have found the right policy settings<br />
again this year.<br />
tle are expecting a larger private sector contribution to<br />
growth this year through increased consumption and<br />
investment, and so judge it appropriate W~ moderate the<br />
extent of fiscal stimulus. But we have avoided winding back<br />
the fiscal stimulus so rapidly that recovery is undermined.<br />
Thle July, retail sales figures announced yesterday, and the<br />
revisions to earlier data, suggest that the grow~ th in<br />
consumption is at least in line with the expectations that<br />
we developed in the course of preparing the Budget. But we<br />
are leaving nothing tc chance, and ltook forwarci to further<br />
strengthening of private consumption fr oo November, as the<br />
tax cuts arnd incroased social security payments begin to<br />
influence spending patterns.<br />
The ccntinucd crow: th in demFand associated with expansi on of<br />
non-farm product by about 5 per cent this fi nancaial year,<br />
t oge'ther with continuedt w. age m-, oderation within the Prices<br />
and Incomes Accord, and lower i nflationary' expectat ions and<br />
interest rates, shouldc support the higher levels of private<br />
investment anticipated in the Budget.<br />
Several key features of the Budget were designed to mai~ ntain<br />
the u,, om-, e.-tum of pri vate inovestmnent growth that his been<br />
indicatt~ d in the statist ics since early this year : the<br />
large reduction in the budget deficit,* from 1" 05 per cent to<br />
.3.3 per cent of CDP supported by the Stantes' agreemenit in<br />
the Premiers' Conference and Loans Council t~ o restraints on<br />
their osin borrow~ ing; and! he tax cuts i~ n support of the<br />
Ac cordc.<br />
Again lc-2ving nothinq to chance; we believe that the<br />
bucL 3bun~: ~ a inpc wevi~ i help -sustain<br />
recover), in private in', ncLm: ent in these mnt tcrs, wo hZ; v&amp;<br />
had buth short and loncg-Lerm ob j.: 2tivcs in: ninid. Eacch f<br />
the bu-1get initi H? iven is 5unsi OL w ith ou: vi) can an<br />
1 on o tia r husi s UI. ax ion ro~' Ihun omnpzany qr oup<br />
t v a L i o i t i a t i a 1h n r o n r YP a J, n r r nl<br />
I r :; idu~ i n o n r e s a At A 1 rua i 3 e dd c A iiL<br />
'~ 2fI( 22 C xp1! ont~( e~ q. PQ 1y; v nqO not icur, f. yon~ vny<br />
-bInI'LL aCd r L k! LO: 1 aCi C U o the </p>
<p>As I have said on several occasions, we will further exaine:<br />
business taxation arrangements in the context of a taxation<br />
reform package.<br />
The continued strergtheninq of:-i-nvestm nt oriented -towards<br />
production for the domestic market-. noy sceems likely to. be<br />
joined late in the financial year by the return of<br />
investment activity in the resources -sector. ' CRA's Channar<br />
iron ore joint venture with China, the Portland and Bunbury<br />
aluminium smelters and the Bunbury power station, and the<br />
export phase of the Northwest Shelf Project, have all<br />
emerged as substantial near-term prospects over the past<br />
month or so.<br />
I believe that there are excellent prospects for continued<br />
good economic performance through the current financial year<br />
a view that I am pleased to know is shared by many of you<br />
here today.<br />
This second year of strong growth with moderating inflation,<br />
amidst increasing community understanding of the<br />
requirements of long-term growth, and continued<br />
strengthening of Australia's consultative mechanisms and<br />
institutions, provides an ideal environment to intensify our<br />
efforts to reform policy and institutions in many areas<br />
important to long-term economic performance.<br />
I wish to refer specifically to the general regulatory<br />
environment, Federal-State financial relations and tax<br />
reform, trade, and the relationship of our education system<br />
and training programs to the demands of the labour market.<br />
This is by no means an exhaustive list, but it includes some<br />
of the main areas that have been the subject of widespread<br />
public discussion, such as taxation reform, and others on<br />
which Government policy development : is at an advanced stage.<br />
I am convinced that after eighty four years of Federation,<br />
we have accumulated an excessive and often irrelevant and<br />
obstructive body of laws and regulations. We seek your<br />
assistance in removing from this accumulation as many as<br />
possible of those laws and regulations which serve no clear<br />
and useful purpose. We see the removal of unnecessary<br />
regulation as contributing significantly to improved<br />
economic growth performance.<br />
I am inviting the ACTU nd the Business Council to nominate<br />
representatives to work wi th Governmrent off; i. ci ls on<br />
priorities in the reform of busir esr s regul. ation.<br />
' We will examinu critica) ly the whole range of business<br />
regjul tion, most impo't. ntIy I it: I a view to assea silg its<br />
contribution to lonu-terr grotll pir f) or; n rce </p>
<p>Ile will riaintain regulation kfhich upon careful analysis,<br />
clearly prumntes economic e ff iciency or which is clearly an<br />
effective means of achieving more equitable income<br />
di stribution.<br />
And we vwill abandon. regulation which fai-. s these tests.<br />
Our reforms in the financial sector illus~ trate our approach<br />
and demonstrate our commitment to the abandonment of<br />
unnecessary regulation.<br />
Where regulatory-~ reformn is required, we will ensure that<br />
change is gradual when this is necessary to avoid placing<br />
excessive adjustment burdens on individuals and groups<br />
affected by change.' Anid concistently with our whole<br />
approach to economic management, we will consult closely<br />
with representatives of-groups that are affected by change.<br />
In many areas, reform to promote economic gr owth will<br />
require not increased or reduced regulation, but changes in<br />
t) ie policy instruments that are used, and in policy<br />
settings. This has been the experience with our major sectoral-reforms<br />
in manufacturing industry. It is ccnsistent with the<br />
approach that is emerging within the Australian"<br />
Manufacturing Council and the Economic Planning Advisory<br />
Council. Obviously Federal-State financial relations and the taxation<br />
system are on any reform agenda. They are closely<br />
inter-rel1ated. I hope that a review of the divi sion between<br />
the Commonwealth anid the States of ta) xation revenues and<br />
taxation powers through the year ahead will lead to reduced<br />
reliance by the States on some of their more economnically<br />
distorting taxes.<br />
I have nade it clear that we do not see tax reform as a<br />
means of raising the* overall level of taxation. But there<br />
is widespread agreement within the Australian community<br />
that we do not collect taxation reventie through the most<br />
equitable and eft'icient means. 1he instruments through<br />
which the conmuni ty cont ri butes a givyin amount of revenue is<br />
a matter of considerable i mportance, ev~ n when thei-e is noD<br />
change in the overall le( vel of taxation. Every hiker ' knoi. s<br />
that the same weight can fel mouch liqhter i( i t is carriccI<br />
Sn a nmore sensi ble way.<br />
Unc theme of our program of reflorm i; that sustai nod trw<br />
grou-th requi res Aust ralia Lo u~ crror-; plete use of*<br />
ties for profi ta-Lcin 1C'rJtod ~ uC~ 1<br />
Vest ain Poci fi rietgu'rcdtw ~ s<br />
dynamic reginn of the uniderono; v. </p>
<p>At a Government level, we ha-ve I unched severa) init iati ves<br />
% which are great 1) expanoi ng commerci al opportuni ties. The<br />
success tie are having in developing co-operation with Chinj<br />
on iron and steelI, and more broadly, is one importdnt<br />
ex ampl1e.<br />
My regional trade initiative is als,. o producing' valuable<br />
r es ulIt s. The round of consultations it has generated on<br />
issues likely to be involved in any future new round of<br />
Multilateral trade neogtiations, has been greatly<br />
appreciated by all countries concerned.<br />
* We are establishing an Australian Co-operation œ. rnittee to<br />
provide advice to'Government on economic relations with<br />
. countries in our region.<br />
On these matters, I shoulld record my appreciation of the<br />
advice and assistance of a very great Australian, Sir John<br />
Crawford, both before and after the time I became Prime<br />
Minister. We have been careful to ensure that our domestic industry<br />
policy decisions are consistent with our international trade<br />
policy. This is supported by the widespread understanding~<br />
that has developed within the community, that increased<br />
protection does not provide efficient long--term. solutions to<br />
industry problems.<br />
In the development of closer trade ties with our region, as<br />
in* most areas of economic life, Governr-. ent can do no more<br />
than provide a framework of expended oppo rtunities. it<br />
augurs well for Australia's economic prospects that the<br />
private sector is providing* strong suIpport for our1 efforts<br />
to expand Australia's Western Pacific Ii n k s. Never before<br />
have Australians been so active in seeL.: ing opportunities for<br />
international business co-operation, and this is being<br />
rewarded with expansion of trade and investment.<br />
1 believe that nothing is more iriportant ' to the<br />
strengt hening of our long-term growth performance than the<br />
expansion of our efforts in training, re-training and<br />
education. Thi.'-is an area of special. Government<br />
responoibility, but here, too, wc welcome guida-nce from<br />
business the tr ade on ion.,, and he wi der c orion i ty. To ta I<br />
expendituore on) training an-z: d education has been _, xppanded<br />
consideraly in the rucent budget., vith sp~ eilu em. phaiss orn<br />
inCrease-d par tic ipa ti on in relevant. educ a t ion.<br />
But nececiiar) y these . Ltn'i., 01ra~-wftat\' Vm<br />
Eat t a ( h Fv e r rm o re ip') r t0 11C e to thE-reuTc CiUalitv) C'<br />
rd LJC3t. i o n ~ h S L 2 f-Ltrt e rs In . hjI: h r f. s: in11e1vi a. lI<br />
hut there cz-n be na doubt ~ X Outnr eI erint<br />
Steadily to ipr oe ~ c~ </p>
<p>The Kirby Committec. is currently reviewing the whole range<br />
of Government tVaininq programs. And w'e have esteblished<br />
the Karme'~ Committee to review the quality of Australian<br />
education, viith a special concern to improve the relevance<br />
of the . education. process to employment -and future economic<br />
opportunities. At the saime time, the Com~ monwealth Tertiary Education<br />
Commission, under its now Chairman, Hugh Hudson, is<br />
examining similar issues in higher edu) cation.<br />
* The receipt of tt-e Hancock Committee Report will provide an<br />
opportunity to review longstanding Australian labour market<br />
institutions. Here, as elsewhere, we will be guided by<br />
observable realities, and not by an a priori presumption<br />
* that regulation in itself is either good or bad.<br />
This is an area in which I have had unique opportunities to<br />
observe the realities. This experience leads me to caution<br />
against simple and glib proposals !-or radical reform.<br />
-Proponents of radical deregulation must be able to explain<br />
the Australia wage explosion of 1982-82, when the<br />
centralised wage-setting arrangements w4ere in suspension.<br />
They must he able to explain why real wages growth<br />
currently so high in Britain, with higher unemployment, less<br />
growth in employment, and less official labour market<br />
regulation than in Australia.<br />
None of this argues against intel ligent assessment of the:<br />
Australian system with a view to im. proving further on the<br />
good recent experience.<br />
Vie can only maintain community support for long-term<br />
structural reform in these 2nd other areas if we arc able<br />
to sustain gur strong imacro-cconomice.-performance.<br />
We recognise that we must further reduce the Commonwealth<br />
budget deficit as privpte investment continues to strengtheni<br />
in 1985-86 and beyond. Consistently with our com-mitmieni-t not<br />
to increase the overall. level of taxation in the course of<br />
taxation reform, we will achieve this* resu~ t by restral nizn<br />
o utlay25s g row th1.<br />
VWe %% ill cot-inue to i mplement monetar~ y pol icy to stJppO) tL<br />
continued strcmug growth w~ i thout r'cco; Iuno-jIt jnr-g-in flutiona2ry<br />
pressures. In the af't,-r!.-3th of the fl-3t mci uF the dolla~ r<br />
I ast year, i( r-an be confident of deliverinq on th. is<br />
commi t: ment<br />
A nd a tn all CIS ' i1 continue to proil. Olc<br />
unde-:! triridi n-omonq ; L the reecv;. rit pairtl. es on rntes of<br />
incri; es tiunt orc cons&gt;;! ten-rt with Ono curow" h vitho-, t<br />
re8LtrC r ucr 0ir If) a t i c </p>
<p>There will come a time iihen continued strong growth vi1<br />
justify some improvement in employment conditions beyond<br />
wage indexation.<br />
In thisregard, judgewents -ibout : the . vppropriate time and<br />
scale of any productivity increasLes must-. depend on the<br />
durability and strength of the r. ecovery,:. and above all on<br />
developments in the labour market.<br />
Obviously, the stronger the growth in employment, and the<br />
larger and more rapid the decline in unemployment, the<br />
better the case for productivity adjustments in one for. cr<br />
another. I would want to see lower unemployment before te<br />
took substantial steps in this direction, but obviously th'is<br />
is a matter for discussicn amongst the parties when we alil<br />
have better information much closer to the event, and<br />
eventually for resolution before the Commission.<br />
Mr Chairman,<br />
It is a measure of our achievements in the past eighteen<br />
months that the economic policy agenda is dominated by<br />
long-terr issues of economic growth and economic reform.<br />
And I use the term " our" in a genuinely plural sense.<br />
It is the achievement of this Government that we have<br />
provided the right direction at the right time. But our<br />
current improved position is as much the achievement of thel<br />
business and farming communities, the trade union movement,<br />
the Australian Federation through the Premiers' Conference<br />
and the whole Australian community.<br />
The-economic and political stability of these past eiohteen<br />
months have allowed the whole AustraYian people to lift its<br />
sights to the great future which is now within our reach.<br />
1 look forward to working with you for many years ahead, in<br />
placing Australia firmly on a new path of sustained, strong<br />
non-inflationary growth.<br />
I am glad of the good company of the Business Council in<br />
this great venture for Australia.<br />
K r v t </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
