<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3906</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON EG WHITLAM QC MP, FOR THE OPENING OF THE AUSTRALIAN NATIONAL SCIENTIFIC AND TECHNICAL LIBRARY (ANSTEL), CANBERRA 2 OCTOBER 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/10/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003906.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE PRINE MINISTER,<br />
THE HON. E. G. WHITLAM, OC. M. P.,<br />
FOR THE OPENING OF THE AUSTRALIAN NATIONAL SCIENTIFIC AND<br />
TECHNICAL LIBRARY ( ANSTEL)<br />
CANBERRA 2 OCTOBER 1975<br />
IT IS APPROPRIATE THAT IEXPRESS MY OWN AND THE<br />
GOVERNMENT'S INDEBTEDNESS TO THE CHAIRMAN OF THE<br />
NATIONAL LIBRARY COUNCIL, KENNETH MIYER. THIS IS THE<br />
SECOND OCCASfON IN THE PAST WEEK WHEN IHAVE HAD<br />
CAUSE TO'-ACKNOWLEDGE KEN MYER'S REMARKABLE RECORD OF<br />
PUBLIC SERVICE. IN MIELBOURNE ON M'ONDAY I OPENED AN<br />
EXHIBITION OF CHINESE CRAFTS WHICH THE M'YER STORES<br />
HAVE HELPED B'RI NG To AUSTRALIA.* TODAY KEN MIY ER<br />
PRESIDES AT THE OPENING OF ANSTEL. ON THE ONE HAND<br />
VIE HAVE SEEN HIS CONTRIBUTION TO WIDER PUBLIC ACCESS<br />
TO THE ARTS; ON THIS OCCASION WE ACKNOWLEDGE HIS<br />
CONTRIBUTION TO WIDER PUBLIC ACCESS TO INFORMATION.<br />
THE TWO THINGS ARE BY NO MEANS UNRELATED, BOTH ARE<br />
CONCERNED WITH THE DEVELOPMENT OF A MORE INFORMED AND<br />
SENSITIVE COMMUNITY. v &amp;/ 2 3% 1 </p>
<p>2.<br />
OF COURSE MANY PEOPLE APART FROM KEN MYER. HAVE<br />
HAD A PART IN PLANNING AND CREATING THIS LIBRARY.<br />
THE OPENING OF ANSTEL A LIBRARY WITHIN A LIBRARY<br />
IS A MOST IMPORTANT STEP IN THE PROVISION OF INFORMATION<br />
SERVICES TO THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE. THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
NATIONAL SCIENTIFIC AND TECHNOLOGICAL LIBRARY IS THE<br />
FIRST PHASE IN THE REDEVELOPMENT OF THE NATIONAL<br />
LIBRARY AS AN OPEN INFORMATION SERVICE, REACHING OUT<br />
THROUGH ITS ATSOCIATED ORGANISATIONS TO THE WHOLE<br />
AUSTRALIAN COMMUNITY, PROVIDING INFORMATION OF EVERY<br />
KIND TO EVERYONE WHO NEEDS IT.<br />
WHAT WE ARE SEEING TODAY ARL THE BEGINNINGS OF<br />
A WHOLE NEW CONCEPT OF WHAT A LIBRARY SHOULD BE AND<br />
HOW A LIBRARY SHOULD FUNCTION. IN RECENT YEARS THERE<br />
HAS BEEN A QUIET REVOLUTION IN THE PLANNING AND<br />
DEVELOPMENT OF LIBRARIES IN AUSTRALIA, WE HAVE COME<br />
TO SEE THAT THE TRADITIONAL CONCEPT OF THE LIBRARY<br />
AN ISOLATED AND SELF-CONTAINED COLLECTION OF BOOKS<br />
IS WHOLLY INADEQUATE TO THE NEEDS OF MODERN SOCIETY,<br />
ACCESS TO THE TRADITIONAL LIBRARY IS LIMITED, AND EVEN<br />
WHERE ACCESS IS POSSIBLE, THE INFORMATION AVAILABLE IS<br />
OFTEN HAPHAZARD OR INADEQUATE. THE QUALITY OF LIBRARY<br />
SERVICES VARIES FROM STATE TO STATE, FROM CITY TO CITY,<br />
AND BETWEEN CITY AND COUNTRY. MArjY AUSTRALIANS ARE<br />
STILL WITHOUT LIBRARIES OF ANY KIND. 61./ 3 </p>
<p>3.<br />
THE SERVICES OF THE NATIONAL LIBRARY ARE<br />
DJESIGNED TO OVERCOME ALL THESE PROBLEMS LIMITATION OF<br />
ACCESS, INSUFFICIENCY OF INFORMATION, INEQUALITY OF<br />
SERVICE. HS PROBLEMS HAVE BEEN ESPECIALLY APPARENT<br />
IN FIELDS WHERE THERE IS A RAPID GROWTH OF KNOWLEDGE<br />
AND A-HIGH DEGREE OF SPECIALISATION. THEY HAVE BEEN<br />
COMPOUNDED BY RIVALRY BETWEEN ESTABLISHED LIBRARY<br />
SERVICES AND INSTITUTIONS. IN THE SCIENTIFIC AND<br />
TECHNOLOGICAL ArAA, FOR EXAMPLE, DIFFERENT BODIES<br />
SUCH AS THc CSIROI THE ATOMIC ENERGY COMMISSION, VARIOUS<br />
GOVERNMENT DEPARTMENTS AND THE NATIONAL LIBRARY HAVE<br />
ALL PROVIDED LIBRARY AND. INFORMATION SERVICES WHOSE<br />
FUNCTIONS HAVE TENDED TO OVERLAP, ALL THESE SERVICES<br />
HAVE BEEN VALUABLE AND TO SOME EXTENT NECESSARY<br />
THEY WILL CERTAINLY CONTINUE BUT THEIR COMPETITION<br />
FOR CUSTOM AND RESOURCES HAS NOT MADE OUR INFORMATION<br />
SERVICES MORE. EFFICIENT. FOR THESE AND OTHER REASONSINCLUDING<br />
A -ENERAL NEGLECT OF LIBRARIES By GOVERNMENTS<br />
IN THE PAST -LIBRARY SERVICES IN AUSTRALIA HAVE<br />
LAGGED WELL BEHIND THOSE OF OTHER COMPARABLE COUNTRIES.<br />
IT IS TIME IVE CAUGHT UP, WE ARE CATCHING UP NOW, I I-/ 7 </p>
<p>4.<br />
BETTER LIBRARIES AND MORE CONSISTENT STANDARDS<br />
OF LIBRARY SERVICE WILL NOT BE ACHIEVED BY THE DUPLICATION<br />
OF TRADITIONAL LIBRARY MATERIALS IN EVERY CITY AND TOWN<br />
WHERE LIBRARIES ARE NEEDED. THIS WOULD BE HOPELESSLY<br />
COSTLY AND INEFFICIENT. YET THIS HAS BEEN THE<br />
APPROACH IN THE PAST. TODAY OUR APPROACH IS DIFFERENT.<br />
WE HAVE RECOGNISED THE NEED FOR CENTRALISED INFORMATION<br />
SERVICES OFFERING THE WIDEST POSSIBLE ACCESS TO<br />
INTERESTED PEOPLE AND ORGANISATIONS. " CENTRALISED"<br />
OF COURSE IS A DIRTY WORD, BUT IT WILL BE CLEAR FROM WHAT<br />
I HAVE TO SAY THAT THE THEORY INVOLVES NO DEROGATION<br />
FROM THE PRINCIPLE OF LOCAL COMMUNITY INVOLVEMENT.<br />
SWITH THE USE OF COMPUTER TECHNOLOGY AND MODERN COMMUNICATIONS<br />
1<br />
QUICK AND RELIABLE; ACCESS TO INFORMATION IS POSSIBLE<br />
ANYW1HERE IN AUSTRAIA.<br />
WITH THIS IN MIND, THE NATIONAL LIBRARY<br />
COUNCIL APPOITED A COMMITTEE THE SCIENTIFIC AND<br />
TECHNICAL INFOR&gt; ATION SERVICES ENQUIRY COMMITTEE ( STISEC)<br />
TO STUDY NATIONWIDE NEEDS FOR LIBRARY-BASED INFORMATION.<br />
lY GOVERNMENT ACCEPTED THE COMMITTEE'S RECOMMENDATION<br />
THAT SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY SHOULD HAVE PRIORITY IN THE<br />
REFORM OF LIBRARY SERVICES, OTHER SPECIALISED LIBRARY<br />
SERVICES IN THE SOCIAL SCIENCES AND HUMANITIES WILL BE<br />
DEVELOPED LATER. THEY HAVE ALREADY BEEN STARTED.<br />
MEANWHILE, WITH THE OPENING OF ANSTEL, THE NATIONAL<br />
LIBRARY IS PROVIDING A VALUABLE NEW SERVICE TO THE<br />
SCIENTIFIC COMMUNITY. m </p>
<p>SOME 80,000 SCIENTIFIC AND TECHNOLOGICAL<br />
MONOGRAPHS ARE ON OPEN ACCESS THROUGH ANSTEL's COMPUTERBASED<br />
INFORMATION SERVICE. THEY WILL ENABLE THE STAFF*<br />
I TO ANSWER INQUIRIES FROM USERS THROUGHOUT AUSTRALIA.<br />
THEY WILL HELP AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT DEPARTMENTS<br />
AND AGENCIES OBTAIN PROMPT ACCESS TO THE LATEST<br />
INFORMATION ON SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY, IN ADDITION,<br />
THE NATIONAL LIBRARY WILL BE ABLE TO MAKE MUCH BETTER<br />
USE OF THE 25,000 SCIENTIFIC AND TECHNOLOGICAL PERIODICALS<br />
IT RECEIVES FROM AROUND THE WORLD. ANSTEL's FIRST<br />
PUBLICATION IS A LIST OF THESE PERIODICALS. OTHER<br />
LIBRARIES AND ORGANISATIONS WILL BE ABLE TO OBTAIN<br />
COPIES OF ANY PERIODICALS THEY NEED'i: FROM THE iIATIONAL<br />
LIBRARY. I CAN PERHAPS ILLUSTRATE THE VALUE OF THIS<br />
SERVICE BY CONSIDERING, SAY, THE NEEDS OF A MEDICAL<br />
SPECIALIST I0 HOBART. IN THE PAST, EVERY HOSPITAL WOULD<br />
TRY TO OBTAIN ALL THE SPECIALIST JOURNALS NEEDED BY ITS<br />
STAFF. THIS WAS A DIFFICULT TASK AT THE BEST OF TIMES;<br />
TODAY IT IS VIRTUALLY IMPOSSIBLE. IT IS BETTER FOR EVERY<br />
INSTITUT. ION TO HAVE ACCESS TO'A COMPLETE REFERENCE SYSTEM,<br />
A CENTRAL INFORI. ATION LIBRARY WILL OPERATE THE SERVICE<br />
AND ISSUE TO EACH SPECIALIST A LIST OF EVERY ARTICLE<br />
OR PUBLICATION THAT APPEARS IN THE WORLD DEALING WITH HIS<br />
SUBJECT, THIS IS NOT TO SAY THAT A LIBRARY SUCH AS ANSTEL<br />
WILL DO EVERYTH IG ITSELF. AND THAT THERE WILL BE NO NEED<br />
FOR OTHER ORGANISATIONS TO DEVELOP THEIR OWN LIBRARY SERVICES. / 6 </p>
<p>6.<br />
IT MEANS THAT OTHER ORGANISATIONS INCLUDING OTHER LIBRARIES<br />
WILL BE ABLE TO PLAN THEIR SERVICES MORE EFFECTIVELY.<br />
IT WILL ENCOURAGE CO-ORDINATION AND CO-OPERATION RATHER<br />
THAN RIVALRY BETWEEN INFORMATION SERVICES. INDEED,<br />
THIS PROCESS OF CO-ORDINATION IS AN INTERNATIONAL ONE,<br />
LIBRARIES AROUND THE WORLD CAN SUPPLY INFORMATION TO A<br />
COMPUTER-BASED SYSTEM. THE NATIONAL LIBRARY HAS ALREADY<br />
HAD VALUABLE ASSISTANCE FROM CANADA IN THIS REGARD.<br />
SI SHOULD MAKE IT CLEAR THAT WHILE ANSTEL ITSELF<br />
IS AN INNOVATION, COMPUTER-BASED LIBRARY INFORMATION<br />
SERVICES ARE ALREADY WELL ESTABLISHED HERE AT THE<br />
NATIONAL LIBRARY. . THE PROCESS OF REFORMING AND<br />
MODERNISING OUR LIBRARY SERVICES HAS BEEN STEADILY GOING<br />
AHEAD. THERE ARE ALREADY MORE THAN 5,000 USERS OF THE<br />
NATIONAL LIBRARY'S COMIPUTER-BASED SERVICES. THE SUCCESS<br />
OF ANSTEL AND OTHER MODERN INFORMATION SERVICES DEPENDS<br />
ON THE SUPPORT AND CO-OPERATION OF MANY INTERESTED GROUPS<br />
AND THE READINESS CF LIBRARIES THEMSELVES TO WORK<br />
TOGETHER. THE NATIONAL LIBRARY HAS ESTABLISHED A FUND<br />
FOR INTER-LIBRARY CO-OPERATION. THROUGH THE GENEROSITY<br />
AND GOOD OFFICES OF KEN 11YER, THE FUND HAS ALREADY REACHED<br />
$ 100,000. THE NATIONAL LIBRARY WILL NEVER BE ABLE TO<br />
PROVIDE LIBRARY SERVICES EVERYWHERE ON THE SPOT, BUT IT<br />
WILL BE ABLE TO PROVIDE LOCAL ORGANISATIONS AND STATE<br />
LIBRARIES WITH THE TOOLS AND THE RESOURCES NECESSARY TO<br />
MEET THE COMMUNITY'S N'EEDS. / 7 </p>
<p>r7.<br />
SUPPORT FOR LIBRARIES HAS BEEN ONE OF THE MOST<br />
IMPORTANT, YET ONE OF THE LEAST KNOWN, ASPECTS OF MY<br />
GOVERNMENT'S WORK. IN MARCH THIS YEAR I ANNOUNCED THE<br />
APPOINTMENT OF A WIDE-RANGING COMMITTEE OF INQUIRY<br />
INTO PUBLIC LIBRARIES IN AUSTRALIA, IT HAS HELD<br />
MORE THAN 20 PUBLIC HEARINGS. WE ARE GIVING DIRECT<br />
ASSISTANCE TO LOCAL AUTHORITIES TO IMPROVE LIBRARY<br />
SERVICES. WE ARE IMPROVING SCHOOL AND TERTIARY<br />
EDUCATION LIBRARIES IN A NUMBER OF WAYS. OUR COMMITMENT<br />
TO LIBRARIES COULD NOT HAVE BEEN BETTER SYmBOLISED<br />
THAN IT WAS IN THE CHOICE OF A GIFT FROM THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT AND PEOPLE TO PAPUA NEW GUINEA<br />
ON THE OCCASION OF INDEPENDENCE. O'bR GIFT WILL TAKE<br />
THE FORM OF A NATI&amp; NAL LIBRARY BUILDING AND<br />
ASSOCIATED BOOKS AND EQUIPMENT.<br />
THE GOVERNMENT'S BASIC OBJECTIVE IS NOT JUST<br />
TO PROVIDE t1ORE BOOKS AND BETTER BUILDINGS BUT TO<br />
RATIONALISE LIBRARY.. SERVICE EVERYWHERE AND ENSURE THAT<br />
0 WHEREVER AUSTRALIANS LIVE THEY HAVE THE SAME ACCESS<br />
TO EVERYTHING A LIBRARY CAN PROVIDE WORKS OF<br />
LITERATU RE, CULTURAL ENRICHMEN4' T, CONTACT WITH HISTORIC<br />
BOOKS AND DOCUMENTS, AND INFORMATION OF EVERY KIND. </p>
<p>8.<br />
WHEN WE THINK ABOUT IT WE WILL SEE WHAT AN<br />
EXTRAORDINARY AND, INDEED, REVOLUTIONARY CONCEPT THIS IS.<br />
IN ANY DEMOCRACY, INFORMATION IS THE KEY TO AN INFORMED<br />
AND ALERT COMMUNITY A COMMUNITY THAT IS READY AND<br />
ABLE TO TAKE ITS OWN DECISIONS AND PARTICIPATE IN THE<br />
DEMOCRATIC PROCESS, WE TAKE FREEDOM OF SPEECH FOR<br />
GRANTED, BUT. THE ACCOMPANYING FREEDOM, THE NECESSARY<br />
. COROLLARY, FREEDOM OF INFORMATION, HAS LONG BEEN<br />
W NEGLECTED. IN ANY TRULY FREE SOCIETY, FREEDOM OF<br />
INFORMATION IS JUST AS IMPORTANT AS FREEDOM OF SPEECH.<br />
A CITIZEN WHOSE ACCESS TO INFORMATION IS LIMITED<br />
OR RESTRICTED IS A SECOND-CLASS CITIZEN. I BELIEVE<br />
IT WILL BE POSSIBLE, THROUGH THIS GREAT INSTITUTION,<br />
THE NATIONAL LIBRARY, TO GUARANTEE FOR EVERY<br />
AUSTRALIAN NOT JUST THOSE WHO LIVE IN CANBERRA<br />
ACCESS TO INFORMATIOilN OF ANY KIND, WHEREVER HE MAY<br />
LIVE, WHATEVER HIS JOB, WHATEVER HIS INCOME, WHATEVER<br />
HIS EDUCATION., I CAN THINK OF FEW REFORMS THAT<br />
CAN BETTER ENHANCE THE QUALITY OF OUR LIVES, AND<br />
ENTRENCH THE RIGHTS AND LIBERTIES OF ALL MEMBERS OF<br />
A FREE AND RESPONSIBLE COMMUNITY. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
