<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>17808</transcript-id>
    <title>Address to the Battle of Kapyong Memorial Service</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/04/2011</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
 Australian veterans of the Korean War.</p>
<p>And first in precedence for today veterans of the Battle of Kapyong</p>
<p>Members of the 3rd Battalion, The Royal Australian Regiment, 3 RAR.</p>
<p>Old Faithfuls. Australians who put Duty First.</p>
<p>You, the men of Kapyong, know your story.</p>
<p>I believe it is time more Australians did.</p>
<p>When you first came here, sixty years ago, you came in the ANZAC tradition.</p>
<p>You knew then the commitment Australians make every year.</p>
<p>We will remember them.</p>
<p>That is the commitment I am here to honour today.</p>
<p>Australia does not forget.</p>
<p>This is Kapyong.</p>
<p>This is where, on the 23rd of April 1951, you were preparing to remember the men of Gallipoli.</p>
<p>This is where you gathered wild azaleas to make ANZAC Day wreaths. This is where you planned to share a meal and have a beer or two with the Turkish brigade who were nearby.</p>
<p>Former enemies, now allies, but the celebration was not to be.</p>
<p>Because this is where duty came first.</p>
<p>That night, the Chinese Communist Army launched its spring offensive through the traditional invasion route of the Kapyong Valley.</p>
<p>It was the final attempt to take Seoul.</p>
<p>That night the defining fight for the Australians in the Korean War began. Kapyong, this great fighting withdrawal. This battle that stopped a breakthrough.</p>
<p>That night you fought them.</p>
<p>In the dark. Radios failing, telephone lines cut. Outnumbered.</p>
<p>And through the day and through another night, you fought on.</p>
<p>This is where the battle continued through ANZAC Day 1951.</p>
<p>This is Kapyong.</p>
<p>You came here as heirs to a tradition. </p>
<p>You brought with you a legacy, left to you by the men of Gallipoli.</p>
<p>Mateship, courage, teamwork, initiative.</p>
<p>You were more than worthy of the tradition you inherited.</p>
<p>You added to it for the heirs you have today.</p>
<p>Training, discipline, professionalism.</p>
<p>You came here as the sons of ANZAC.</p>
<p>You left as the fathers of our professional Army.</p>
<p>And on operations in Afghanistan or East Timor, in training in Australia or overseas, the modern Australian Army is still Kapyong's child.</p>
<p>The US Presidential Citation awarded to 3 RAR spoke of “extraordinary heroism and outstanding performance of combat duties in action ”The Battle Honour “Kapyong” is now emblazoned on the Regimental Colour of each Battalion of the Royal Australian Regiment this is where you won that honour.</p>
<p>Our commitment to Korea was a sign of the future of Australia's security in the new post-war world.</p>
<p>We proved ourselves a reliable and courageous ally.</p>
<p>Among the United Nations with the United States in Asia.</p>
<p>Pillars of Australia's security still.</p>
<p>Australians made great sacrifices in Korea.</p>
<p>From our Navy, Air Force and Army, more than 17,000 Australians served in Korea, many of them here today, veterans of other battles, 340 Australians died, more than 1200 were wounded and 30 became prisoners of war.</p>
<p>I honour 3 RAR and your Canadian, New Zealand, British and US allies and I honour the part you played so South Korea could embrace the democratic freedoms it enjoys today.</p>
<p>A professional Army and a proud nation honour you too.</p>
<p>This is where, sixty years ago, the men of Kapyong prepared to remember the men of Gallipoli.</p>
<p>This is where we remember the men of Kapyong today.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
