<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9329</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J.KEATING, MP PRESS CONFERENCE, PARLIAMENT HOUSE,.CANBERRA, TUESDAY, 23 AUGUST 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/08/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009329.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING, MP<br />
PRESS CONFERENCE, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA,<br />
TUESDAY, 23 AUGUST 1994<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
PMV: I'm very pleased to announce that the Government has decided to<br />
reopen the Australian-Embassy in Beirut and to reopen it by June<br />
1995. As you may recall the Embassy was closed in 1984 because of<br />
the deteriorating security position at that time, but the Government did<br />
take the option of opening a non-diplomatic office particularly for<br />
migration and visa clearances in 1993 and we took that decision after<br />
the circumstance and situation in Lebanon had changed from the time<br />
of the Accords.<br />
We now believe the security situation, although by no means perfect,<br />
has improved to the point where re-opening is possible, and of course,<br />
we'll be taking every precaution to protect the staff who will be there.<br />
I think this is going to be an important decision and an important<br />
facility for the 250,000 Australians of Lebanese origin who have a<br />
strong interest in the ease of communications between Australia and<br />
Lebanon and the other thing, I think it does is it gives us a natural<br />
opportunity to grow the linkages between Australia and Lebanon which<br />
have been growing, though small, growing quite smartly from an<br />
almost non existent trade of $ 3 million in 1991 to $ 13 million in 1993.<br />
We have got Austrade and a number of Australian companies there at<br />
a trade exhibition in Beirut for the first week of October of this year.<br />
We have recently signed an air services agreement with Lebanon<br />
which will help commercial and people to people links.<br />
So, I think, the decision represents confidence in Lebanon's future, a<br />
desire by Australia to provide an ease in the relations, particularly for<br />
those, as I say, quarter of a million of Australians of Lebanese origin<br />
and to underpin the fact that we want to see better commercial and </p>
<p>trade relationships with Lebanon and, of course, this will be perhaps<br />
facilitated by the fact that we have a full mission there.<br />
So, there has been, as you know, much lobbying in the Lebanese<br />
community over time for this. The Government has taken note of those<br />
concerns and we said, always, that in due time we would act upon<br />
them and we think that due time is now.<br />
I'd be happy to take questions.<br />
J: Does this move suggest that we might be increasing pressure on Israel<br />
regarding their occupation of Southern Lebanon?<br />
PM: No. I think, since 1989 when the TAlE Accords were signed we've<br />
seen a very marked change in the fortunes of Lebanon and, of course,<br />
more recently with the Middle East Accords between the PLO and<br />
Israel a change there as well and I think that I would like to see<br />
Lebanon take part in that peace process and that negotiation with<br />
Israel and to extend the whole co-operative climate throughout the<br />
region.<br />
J: Have you chosen who will be the Ambassador?<br />
PM: No, we haven't not yet.<br />
J: Would the Ambassador be residing in Beirut?<br />
PM: The Ambassador will be residing in Beirut.<br />
J: So, there will be two Embassies one in Damascus and one in Beirut?<br />
PM: That's right. One in Syria and one in Lebanon.<br />
J: Has anybody's Government guaranteed the safety of personnel there?<br />
PM: Well, we will as we do, I mean, missions in this country rely upon the<br />
Australian Government to provide the protection. In the same terms<br />
we open up such discussions with any country where we have a<br />
mission or where we are about to have a mission. So, we'll have<br />
discussions with the Government of Lebanon to see that every<br />
protection and every consideration is extended to the enhanced<br />
security of any staff who are based there.<br />
J: Why did it take so long to reopen given that a lot of other western<br />
nations reopened their embassies some time ago?<br />
PM: Well, I think, they are all judgements about the environment and also, I<br />
think, in opening in January 1993 a lot of the immigration work was </p>
<p>effectively being done, anyway, through that office. So, in a sense,<br />
we've had a staged process.<br />
J: Prime Minister, it's not usual for you to make an announcement<br />
personally of this nature, do you feel the need to increase your profile<br />
amongst Australia's ethnic community?<br />
PM: No, it is just that I have had a long association with the ethnic<br />
communities and particularly a long association with the Lebanese<br />
community. Particularly in Western Sydney and I have had many,<br />
many hundreds of representations on this issue over time. The<br />
Lebanese community in Australia, those of Lebanese origin, are a fair<br />
proportion of our country and something as central to their interests as<br />
this, I think, deserves an announcement by the Government and, in<br />
this case, by me.<br />
J: Mr Prime Minister, would you be yourself opening the Embassy in<br />
Beirut?<br />
PM: I wouldn't make that commitment, but it will be opened with some<br />
aplomb I can assure you.<br />
J: Is it your decision to ( inaudible) Accords, Prime Minister?<br />
PM: I don't think so. I think the Syrian Government, on the contrary, I think<br />
the Syrian Government, the whole point of the Accords and the<br />
sovereignty of Lebanon which has arisen from it is best recognised by<br />
diplomatic recognition.<br />
J. Mr Keating, are you satisfied with the way the Cambodian authorities<br />
are handling the hostage situation in Cambodia and what was your<br />
rettahcteonA ustrlianhostg-e asking for Adistralian authorities to<br />
take over negotiations?<br />
PM: Well I think that this has been a difficult issue for us and any of these<br />
hostage situations are difficult, particularly in the context of the<br />
discussion we're having. The tensions between the interests of the<br />
Khmer Rouge and the Government of Cambodia and negotiations<br />
between Australia and Cambodia over other different issues. I mean, I<br />
think we can only rely upon their best endeavours to see that we can<br />
get the hostages free.<br />
J: Mr Keating, do you see the Government's decision to override<br />
Tasmarna on the gp~ lwaws issue as some sort of test for Alexander<br />
Downer in terms of his policy position on the family and those sorts of<br />
liberty issues?<br />
PM: Well, I think that we have to come back to an essential truth here. And<br />
what the coalition are always trying to speak of is the rights of the </p>
<p>States and sovereignty for the States. This is the right of a Tasmanian<br />
cabinet to decide a matter like this, in the face of an international<br />
treaty. Now, this is a treaty that Australia relies upon when it makes<br />
remarks around the world about human rights, and rights and liberties<br />
of people. One can't invoke it in those circumstances and not invoke it<br />
at home. So therefore, the Commonwealth has particularly after the<br />
UN's action an obligation here. And it's an obligation under an<br />
international treaty. Now, there is this notion afoot within the coalition<br />
thaFthbre is something illegitimate about international treaties, and the<br />
Commonwealth role. The foreign affairs power was given to the<br />
Commonwealth at Federation. And we have to keep, I mean, I think,<br />
we have to remind people particularly in the Liberal Party, and in the<br />
States that Federation was an act of creation of the nation. It was not<br />
a set of protections for the States. I mean, the debate is now so<br />
warped, people think that Federation is in some way in the mouths of<br />
self-serving arguments by Premiers a set of protections for the<br />
States, that they are the foundation stones on which the nation is built.<br />
This is not so. TheFederation was an act of creation of the nation,<br />
and these powers are powers given to the operation of the nation, and<br />
that's why, you know, phoney calls for sovereignty for States, and<br />
trying to hide behind them, Mr Downer trying to hide behind them,<br />
given his expressed views on this subject, is going to, I think, again<br />
test whether he has any policy substance.<br />
J: Mr Keating, on one other matter, Mr Jons position in Victoria do you<br />
support Mr Jones attempts to stay in the seat of Laor, and r~ tain the<br />
Presidency?<br />
PM: In every boundary change, set of bQundary changes, there is always a<br />
reshuffling of interests. And this has happened-to all of us over the<br />
years. Nobody is immune from a change in these things. Senator<br />
Evans has expressed an interest, I think, in seeing whether he should<br />
make the transition to the Lower House. That's his perfect right. He's<br />
a senior Minister, he's a major contributor to the Government and to<br />
the country, and he will do what I am sure everyone in the political<br />
process does, and that is, find themselves a spot. Now whether that<br />
spot is Mr Jones' spot or another, remains to be seen. But I don't think<br />
any MP has immunity from the pressures the day to day real world<br />
pressures of their party at these particular moments.<br />
J: So, if it came to a choice between Senator Evans...<br />
PM: OK. I think..<br />
J Mr Jones<br />
PM: Let me just say.<br />
J you'd be prepared to see Mr Jones... </p>
<p>PM: I'm not here to be giving you Labor Party open-heart surgery, even<br />
though I know you think if I cross the threshold a footpath, a doorway<br />
then one should open one's heart to the media. Now you know I'm<br />
generally a kindly person, and I open it more often than I should.<br />
J: Prime Minister....<br />
PM: But the thing is I don't think I can be,... except let me just repeat the<br />
point. That these are a real-world set of pressures in what Senator<br />
Evans sees and which I would concur in some legitimate aspiration<br />
by him to move to the central cockpit of Australian politics, the House<br />
of Representatives. Now, whether in fact, how this is accommodated<br />
in the Victorian scene you know, time will tell.<br />
J: But you understand that those comments will be interpreted as support<br />
for Senator Evans, vis a vis Mr Jones?<br />
PM: No. Well, I don't think they are entitled to be interpreted that way, but<br />
I.. let me make very clear my support for the senior Minister's of the<br />
Government and in Senator Evans' case, you know, very obvious and<br />
clear support for his continuation in a very central position in<br />
Australian public life. Thank you.<br />
ends. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
