<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10218</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON.JOHN HOWARD MP SPEECH AT THE OPENING OF THE ELECTORATE OFFICE OF TRISH WORTH MP, FEDERAL MEMBER FOR ADELAIDE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/01/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010218.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Fax from 25/ 01/ 97 14: 00 Pg: 1<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
January 1997 TRANSCRIPT OF TILE PRiME 1VNISTER.<br />
T19E RON. JOHN UOWARD MP<br />
SPEECHI AT ITH E OPENING OF TUlE ] ELECTORATE OFF&amp; E OF<br />
TISHi WORTH Ml[, FEDERAL, MIEMBER FOR ADELAIDE<br />
IE&amp; O<br />
Thank you very much Trish. To Martin Cameron, the President of the Liberal Phrty in<br />
South Australia,, to Amnanda Vanstone, Robert Hill, Tan McLachlan, my other stae and<br />
Federal Par] lamentary colleagues, ladies and gentleincn. I1h ave reflected on itnu ~ mber of<br />
the rcsoniances with a year ago as T travelled here this morning the short distance from the<br />
hotel-It was cxactiy a year ago that I opencd Ehat campaign office. It was about the<br />
samne time that I think I opened a campaign office for Andrew Soutbicou. I remember to<br />
the day of course as so maay or us do, the Saturday of The Australia Day weekend List<br />
year, when the election was called and can I say, Trish that it's alwayus a pleasureito be int<br />
AdcLaide about this time of the year and it was very nice of you to give me the<br />
opportunity of saying a few words at the opening of your office.<br />
We are on the eve of Australia Day, a day that has grown in the affections and thi<br />
commiftrnnt of Australians to celebrate over the last ten or 20 years. When I1w as<br />
growing up people sort of struggled to celebrate Australia Day. It was called A4nniversary<br />
Day I think then-It certainly was in Sydney, and I guess it was the samre all aro". d.<br />
Australia. And we sort of went through the motions of celebrating Australia Day but<br />
over the years, and particularly over the last decade, the celebration of it has become a<br />
focal poinit of people thinking about anid reflecting on those things that bind us together.<br />
One of the credos that I have always tried to live by in political life, both inside mny own<br />
party and also within the community is that we ought to focus more on the things! that<br />
bind us together rather than on the things that might ptush us apart<br />
Arnd one of the most visible demonstrations, the most powerful pieces of evidence of the<br />
success of Australia will be that tomrorrow, around our couny thousands upon thousands </p>
<p>Faxfrft25/ 01/ 97 14: 00 rg.<br />
of people will become Australian citizens, They will come from literally the four corners<br />
of the Earth. They will pledge themselves to put the interests of Austrulia against the<br />
interests, of any other counny, not in the sense of repudiating the countrics from which<br />
thev have come but in the sense of embrac t an overarching commitment in common<br />
with those who are already Australian citizenis, to the future of our country and to the<br />
vadlues that we sharm in common. And it's a very powcrfd reminder that that great act<br />
across the country, it's a very powerful reminder of what a magnet of tolerance this<br />
counry Is to people fromt so many parts of the world-And it cuts through the clatter. it<br />
cuts through the negativism, it cuts through the tendency of some Australians to see this<br />
country as other than a v~ ery robust, democratic, open, tolerant and diverse community. I<br />
think it is a source of tremendous pride to all Austraians, whether they were born in this<br />
country or whether they have becorne Australians by choice, it is a reminder to all of us<br />
ofjust how high in the esteem of thc rest of the world our country blads in termis of the<br />
values that men and women around the world regard as important<br />
Over the Christmas holiday period I always try and read some books and I read a very<br />
densely, and I1d on't mean dense in a pejortive sense but dense in terms of size, history<br />
of what was called the short 20th century, it was called The Age of Exienies and it traces<br />
the history of the 20th century from the -beginning of the Great War of 1914 to the<br />
collapse of cormmunism in the early 1990s. And it contains right in themriddlc of it a<br />
reminder that jonly eight countries, if you count separately Ireland and the United<br />
Kingdom only eight countries have becn continuouly democratic during that period and<br />
Australia is one of those eight countries, the others being of course the United States,<br />
New Zealand, Canada, the United Kingdom, Sweden and Switzerland. Now many<br />
countries of c ourse lost their democracy and their freedomn non through choice but<br />
because of the invasion of others and tt should always be kept in mind-But it is a<br />
reminder to all of us ofjust how successful Australia has really been. And the greatest<br />
measure of somebody's estem in the community is what others think of him or her and<br />
the greatest mark of the esteem of the nation in the eyes of the rest of the world is what<br />
the citizens of other countries think of that nation, and the desire of so many people to<br />
become citizens of this country and the Willingness of them to do so is a very powerful<br />
reminder to all of us of what this country has achieved and what it really stnads for.<br />
Trish, can T say on a more personal note that 1 have a very strong affinty with the<br />
electorate of Adelaide. I have experienced some ins and outs I have got to say in recent<br />
years, I am delighted to say a lot more is than outs. I think your achievement in winning<br />
the electorate of Adclaide in the first, place was a rcimarkable tribute to your campaigning<br />
skils, it really was. And the service that you have given wo this very diverse electorate, it<br />
is an electorate that of course embraces the heart of the city of Adelaide, it is an<br />
electorate that straddles a very wide group of socio-economically speaking, of<br />
Australians. It includes amongst its constituents people of very diverse backgrounds it<br />
has a very important educational base. It has one of the most important sportng bases of<br />
course, both summer and winter sports, of aay city in Australia and you represenit it<br />
magnificently and your achievement in increasing your majority at the last election anid<br />
the work that you do as a Member of Parliamient, the contribution you make to the </p>
<p>Fa fom25/ 01/ 97 14: 08 Pg:<br />
understanding of some of the everyday problems of life is a very, very good exarrple to<br />
your colleagues.<br />
One of my best recollections of Trish and a demonstration of the sort of person she really<br />
is was the day ol'that quite disgraceful attack on Parliament on The 1 9th of August, and<br />
after the demonstrators had been, shall we say, I say it quite unashamedly, repulsed by<br />
the police who behaved in an absolutely magnificent way, and other security people, in a<br />
very difficult si tuation. I went around as soon as possible to inspect the damnage and<br />
ther was Trish resumning her profession for the moment of nursing and caring for one of<br />
the police officers who had been assaulted by several of the demonstrators. And that Is<br />
typical of the caring role that she plays out, both as a Member of Parliamient and as a<br />
member of the community. It was a vivid reminder of the kind of person shec is and the<br />
fact that shes never forgote that she bas a caring role in the community as a citizen and<br />
her training as a nurse was very much in evidence on that occasion.<br />
This office will be of course open and will be a vehicle of supporl for all of the citizens<br />
of the electorate of Adelaide. Although in the nature of politics only s~ iliry over halt, or<br />
in some electorates, immrensely over hialf of the community votes for you.. once you're a<br />
Member of Parliament you have an obligation and a commitment to serve the people who<br />
voted against you as well as the people who voted for you. And I kmow that Trish wil do<br />
that and I know that anybody, irrespective of their politics, who comes to this office can<br />
be assured of a good hearing, can be assured of a persistent effort to help them in sol-ving<br />
whatever problem that they miight have and I think that it is appropriate that There are so<br />
many community leaders here.<br />
So ladies and gentlemen, as T reflect on the last yea T do so as leader of the Liberal Parry<br />
with very great pride at what has been achieved, not in any triumphal sense. We were<br />
given the great privilege of being the Government of Australia. We have worked very<br />
hard and I have been very ably assisted as Prime Minister in a very, very powerful<br />
MNinisterial and Parliamcntmy contingent from South Australia. T think I have said before<br />
tha I1c ant recall in the history of Federation, certainly not i the post-war period, where<br />
there have been four Cabinet Mnisters in the Goverrnent of this comuy from South<br />
Australia, which is the case at the present time and they ame ably surrounded by a very<br />
powerful contingent of very hard-working Senators and Members, and I arn delighted to<br />
say at -the opening of this office how much T appreciate the contribution, of South<br />
Australians to my Government and to the Parliament generally. It has been a very<br />
exciting year since I1w as last here. It's almost a year since the change of Government<br />
We have achieved a lot but we have many challenges ahead of us and the now year has<br />
brought a number of reminders of continuing challenges. The new yea has also brought<br />
somc: new challenges which will engage the energies and the goodwill and the<br />
commitment and the application of all of us. </p>
<p>Fax from But ladies and gentleme, I am here today to, with great pleasure, to declare Trish's now<br />
electonte office open, to wish her well, to thank her fotbr the care that she gives to the<br />
people of Adelaide, to thank her for being such a magnificent member of our<br />
Parliamentary team and to wish her many, many years of service to the cause of the<br />
people of Adelaide and to the Australian community generally.<br />
Thank you.<br />
ends 25/ 81/ 97 14: 00 Pg: 4 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
