<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18279</transcript-id>
    <title>Climate change support for South East Asian countries</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/11/2011</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
The Prime Minister, Julia Gillard, speaking in Bali at the East Asia Summit, today outlined the practical steps Australia will take to assist South-East Asian countries to address the challenges of climate change.</p>
<p>These will include helping some South East Asian countries phase out inefficient incandescent light bulbs, improve coastal ecosystems and build the capacity of communities to respond to climate change in the region.</p>
<p>As part of the package Australia will provide up to $15 million to help Vietnam adapt to unavoidable impacts of damaging climate change including rising sea levels and changing rainfall patterns.</p>
<p>Australia will work with the German Government to assist Vietnam to manage and protect its coastal ecosystems in the Mekong Delta including through improved dyke management and the restoration of mangroves. This work will also assist local communities to respond and recover from natural disasters and develop a better understanding of the likely impact to their community they might experience as a result of climate change. </p>
<p>A further $15 millionwill support non-government organisations working with communities in South East Asia, focusing on Vietnam, to address climate change. The funding will help communities to manage the unavoidable impacts of climate change and help them reduce or avoid greenhouse gas emissions.</p>
<p>Countries in South East Asia will also benefit from a $3 million capacity building program to improve their ability to accurately report and measure their national greenhouse gas emissions. </p>
<p>Australia will also promote phasing out inefficient incandescent lighting and adopting standards for efficient lighting across the region in a $500,000 package.</p>
<p>In addition countries in the region such as Indonesia and the Philippines will receive assistance to support their uptake of clean technology through Australia's contributions to the Clean Technology Fund. </p>
<p>Australia also provides assistance for reducing emissions from deforestation and forest degradation (REDD+) for several EAS countries  -  bilaterally to Indonesia and via multilateral contributions to Cambodia, Lao PDR and Vietnam. </p>
<p>Since 2009, Australia has committed more than $5 million towards the Coral Triangle Initiative. This supports protection of livelihoods and food security for people dependent on coastal ecosystems which are susceptible to environmental degradation and climate change impacts. Countries include Indonesia, Malaysia, the Philippines, East Timor, Papua New Guinea and Solomon Islands.</p>
<p>Ms Gillard is in Bali, Indonesia to attend the East Asia Summit and to meet with Indonesian President Yudhoyono in the first annual leaders' summit.  </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
