<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8704</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J. KEATING MP WELCOME TO PRESIDENT ROBINSON OF IRELAND CANBERRA, 27 OCTOBER 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/10/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008704.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
WELCOME TO PRESIDENT ROBINSON OF IRIELAND<br />
CANBERRA, 27 OCTOBER 1992<br />
President Robinson, on behalf of the Government and the<br />
people of Australia it is my great pleasure to welcome<br />
you. It is truly a great pleasure for the reason that in<br />
certain significant and undeniable ways we Australians<br />
share your rrishness.<br />
Even those who are not of Irish descent will say that<br />
when they go to Treland it is uncanny how much they feel<br />
at home.<br />
We would like to think that you feel something Similar<br />
among us here.<br />
And when we fppl the-se bondq of recognition and affection<br />
we shouldn't be too surprised.<br />
For at every major point in our history since 1788 the<br />
Irish have been there, in word and deed and spirit.<br />
It is not easy to say just what that spirit comprises.<br />
There has frequently been an eloinent of rebellion about<br />
it of course, but it's much more than that.<br />
The Trish contribution has been primarily to the<br />
language, literature, law, politics, religion and<br />
philosophy of Australia.<br />
And football, and horse racing, and farming, and eating,<br />
and drinking, and story-talling, and what is these days<br />
called the hospitality industry, and music.<br />
To name a few.<br />
In other words, the Irish have been a great clvilising<br />
force. A great creative force.<br />
We share some basic attitudes.<br />
t7/ 10d S000N Z1J: ZT Z6* 1O22 :-11331 </p>
<p>2<br />
Perhaps the most important of them, as you said in your<br />
speech to the Press Club yesterday, is a deep attachment<br />
to the land&amp; we live in: the land itself lives in our<br />
minds, and informs the way we think about ourselves.<br />
More than anything else, the shape of the continent<br />
somehow defines a disparate and far-flung population as<br />
one Australian people.<br />
We have long been thoroughly urbanised and<br />
industrialised, but the land is still at the centre of<br />
our identity.<br />
And I've no doubt that the Irish imagination played some<br />
part in keeping it there.<br />
But as I am sure you know, the Aboriginal people, who<br />
were herp for 40,000 years or more before us, understood<br />
this land in ways that we can never hope to emulate.<br />
Yesterday you told the story of the Choctaw Indians who,<br />
on hearing of the Irish famine, raised seven hundred<br />
dollars and sent it to Ireland for the relief of the<br />
victims. It was a case of people who were already displaced<br />
feeding those who were about to be.<br />
In another nineteenth century example of the global<br />
village, in turn, those Irish were among the settlers who<br />
displaced the Aboriginal people of Australia.<br />
It is one of our great hopes in this last decade of the<br />
twentieth century that we can put to rights the<br />
devastating impact that the European occupation of their<br />
country had on the Aboriginal people, and that we can<br />
reconcile at last the economic, social and cultural<br />
differences which still keep Aboriginal and non-<br />
Aboriginal Australians apart.<br />
This should not be beyond people who have succeeded in<br />
creating a very rich and harmonious society from an<br />
extraordinary variety of cultures.<br />
Through these and many other avenues of social and<br />
economic policy designed to strengthen the ties which<br />
bind Australians, the Government I lead is seeking to<br />
create an Australia which is more truly one community and<br />
nation. President I know Ihat you also look to reconcile the<br />
differences which make for the continuing tragedy of<br />
NorthernIreland. I know that you seek to bring opportunity and justice<br />
equally to women and men and close the divide between<br />
them. </p>
<p>3<br />
I know that you seek to narrow the gap between rich and<br />
poor, and that your great hope is that everywhere the<br />
outcasts of the world can be brought in.<br />
I know, that being Irish, you must be attracted to your<br />
country's past, to your ancient heritage and traditions<br />
but I know that you look to your country's future.<br />
We have this in common too.<br />
In the last decade Ireland has grown out of the shadow of<br />
both Britain and its own past to become a more outwardlooking<br />
nation, more confident of its identity, more<br />
alive to the world and its region.<br />
A nation carving out for itself a very independent<br />
position in European affairs, and with it a stronger<br />
place for itself in the world.<br />
It has done these things of necessity. Because they were<br />
the only way to give Ireland back its future. The only<br />
way to ensure that the Irish of the next generation will<br />
have no need to emigrate.<br />
So these days when we Australians and Irish say that we<br />
see something deeply familiar in each other, it is not<br />
merely our common past but also our present<br />
preoccupations and our aspirations which we recognise.<br />
For Australia has done the very same things we are more<br />
open to the world, more confident and independent-minded,<br />
and alive to our region, the Asia Pacific, as you are to<br />
Europe. Like you we have stepped out of the past.<br />
old countries we might be in different ways, but in a<br />
sense we're younger than we have ever been.<br />
President, we share many of your hopes.<br />
We share your country's determination to be a modern and<br />
dynamic nation.<br />
our affinity with your country and our roots in all of<br />
its political and religious traditions has always made<br />
the conflict in Northern Treland a matter of deep concern<br />
to us, and we earnestly hope that the current talks being<br />
chaired by our former Governor General, Sir Ninian<br />
Sephen, will be successful.<br />
We share your hope for sexual equality and social<br />
justice; and, at the end of a decade in which some<br />
countries have discounted these ambitions, we are proud<br />
to say that we have made substantial progress toward<br />
them.<br />
GS0ON ZV: ZI Z6OL0 -113311 </p>
<p>That is something else we share it may even be the<br />
strongest of the ties that bind us we know that when we<br />
change we have to take our people with us.<br />
President, the light which you keep burning in your<br />
window tells all your compatriots around the world that<br />
they will always be welcome home.<br />
But, with the greatest respect, there's no need to keep<br />
it burning for the six million Australians of Irish<br />
ancestry. It would never occur to us for a moment that we weren't<br />
welcome. It would never occur to any of the other eleven million<br />
for that matter.<br />
We presume we're as welcome as you are here. And that is<br />
very welcome.<br />
VO/ VO'd SOOON ZV: ZT Z6' 30* Z1: 131 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
