<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11418</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER          THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP          PRIME REGIONAL TELEVISION ADDRESS                                     Subject: The New Tax System</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/08/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE.................</p>
<p>  Good evening. Now that The New Tax System has become law I want to report</p>
<p>   to you on how our improvements are already working to the benefit of Australian</p>
<p>   families.</p>
<p>  In January the Government introduced the 30 per cent tax rebate for private</p>
<p>   health insurance to reward those people who take personal responsibility</p>
<p>   for their family's health care. Not only has this made health insurance</p>
<p>   much more affordable but we now have a quarter of a million more Australians</p>
<p>   in private health insurance than there would otherwise be.</p>
<p>  We are also well on the way to abolishing the old unfair system of wholesale</p>
<p>   sales tax with its many high and hidden rates. You are probably aware that</p>
<p>   the sales tax on many items has already been reduced from 32 per cent to</p>
<p>   22 per cent.</p>
<p>  Over the last month, this has brought the price of many goods down. When</p>
<p>   you shop around, you will find that the tax reductions have been passed</p>
<p>   on for goods like radios and televisions, video recorders, stereos, cameras,</p>
<p>   clocks and watches.</p>
<p>  These and many other items will fall in price again when the wholesale sales</p>
<p>   tax and other hidden taxes are abolished altogether after The New Tax System</p>
<p>   officially begins in July next year.</p>
<p>  The Government's consumer watchdog, the Australian Competition and Consumer</p>
<p>   Commission, is already working hard to make sure that consumers benefit</p>
<p>   from lower prices. There are tough penalties for those who do not pass on</p>
<p>   the savings to ordinary consumers and if you think a business has not brought</p>
<p>   down their prices as they should, particularly in country Australia, the</p>
<p>   Commission is there to help.</p>
<p>  The New Tax System will benefit all Australians and, in the months ahead,</p>
<p>   the Government will continue to explain exactly how it will allow Australians</p>
<p>   to share in the largest income tax cut in nation's history. Good night.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
