<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10657</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                  THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                  RADIO INTERVIEW WITH NEIL MITCHELL                RADIO 3AW</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/08/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE....................................................................................................</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Good morning.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Good morning, Neil.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, why should we believe you?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>You should believe me because deep down the Australian community</p>
<p>   knows that the present system is not working. They know that it</p>
<p>   needs overhaul. And they also know, deep down, that you can't</p>
<p>   sort of have that overhaul easily and overnight. And then if people</p>
<p>   come along offering them a personal tax cut with no GST and no change</p>
<p>   to the present tax system, they're entitled to say, well, that</p>
<p>   sounds okay, but in the long-run you can't have any kind of</p>
<p>   improvement without basic change.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Just, for example your strategy relies on a surplus.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>What if you don't have it, what if the Asian crisis knocks</p>
<p>   the living daylights out of it, what if your revenue measures don't</p>
<p>   work, would you go into deficit to prevent this?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, Neil, we don't rely on all of the surplus, there'll</p>
<p>   still be a large surplus left after this plan has been introduced.</p>
<p>   It's not all financed from the surplus. A lot of it is financed</p>
<p>   from the fact that a GST catches tax cheats that are not in our</p>
<p>   court. And that's one of the things that people have got to</p>
<p>   understand in relation to alternative offerings. You can't</p>
<p>   have the efficiency gains from a GST without the GST. You can't</p>
<p>   have the $3 billion out of the black economy without the GST. You</p>
<p>   can't have the reduction in business costs without the GST.</p>
<p>   So those who say you can have all the nice bits in this without</p>
<p>   the GST are misleading you. And that is something that I think the</p>
<p>   Australian people will grow to understand and they, in the end,</p>
<p>   will say: righto, we need this change and the only way to do it</p>
<p>   is to do it properly.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Okay, well you've locked in the GST rate, that would be very</p>
<p>   hard to change...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I would say impossible.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Okay, impossible to change. Why not lock in the compensation mechanism?</p>
<p>   This all comes to trust again. We've got to trust you that</p>
<p>   these tax changes will go through [inaudible]...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, can you imagine any Senate allowing changes to the compensation</p>
<p>   mechanisms to go through?</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Why not really convince people, though? Why not look at indexation...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, you don't need an indexed tax rate if you can go from</p>
<p>   $20,000 to $50,000 without going into a higher bracket. That is...</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>[Inaudible]</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, that is 60 to 70 per cent of the population, Neil.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>But some people are going to be caught...[inaudible]</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I tell you what, Neil, this will be the most bracket creep</p>
<p>   free tax plan this country has ever seen because when you broaden</p>
<p>   that band in the middle  now, just let me say this again </p>
<p>   you can go from $20,000 a year to $50,000 without going into a higher</p>
<p>   bracket. Now, there has never been, in the history of Australia,</p>
<p>   a breadth of income in the low and middle area free of bracket creep</p>
<p>   like that.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>We still have one of the highest top rates in the world, why not</p>
<p>   reduce that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, it's a question of balance. I've increased the</p>
<p>   threshold. That doesn't now apply until $75,000. You can't</p>
<p>   do everything. In the name of fairness, people say, you've</p>
<p>   got to make certain that the low and middle income people are looked</p>
<p>   after. I don't think the Australian public would believe that</p>
<p>   it was a higher priority for us to reduce the top rate.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Would you still like to get it down?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look, I mean, there are a lot of things that I would like, but</p>
<p>   I've got to try and get something that is balanced and fair.</p>
<p>   And I think the fair, balanced thing to do was to say to the great</p>
<p>   bulk, 60 to 70 per cent of Australian wage and salary earners, 60</p>
<p>   to 70 per cent of them, you can increase your income from $20,000</p>
<p>   to $50,000 without going into a higher tax bracket. In other words,</p>
<p>   for them bracket creep is a thing of the past.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Jobs  will it create them?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes it will, because it will make it less expensive to run a business</p>
<p>   and therefore you'll have more capacity to employ. This will</p>
<p>   take $10,000 million of costs off the operations of Australian business.</p>
<p>   It will take $4.5 billion off the costs of exporters. It will be</p>
<p>   a very good thing for Australian business. It will have very big</p>
<p>   cashflow benefits for businesses with turnovers of less than $20</p>
<p>   million a year because they'll only pay the GST quarterly,</p>
<p>   and that's 99 per cent of Australian businesses.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Okay. How many jobs have you estimated?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I can't put an estimate on it, no I can't. But we have</p>
<p>   generated 300,000 new jobs over the last two and a half years.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, how long do you think people should have to absorb this</p>
<p>   before they decide on it?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I don't know. I want to allow adequate time. You ask me, what</p>
<p>   is adequate - I can't put a figure on that. My immediate preoccupation</p>
<p>   is to move around Australia explaining this plan and answering people's</p>
<p>   questions on it. And I start on the way to Adelaide immediately</p>
<p>   after this interview. And I'll be going to every State. I'll</p>
<p>   be in Victoria over the weekend and I will be going to Queensland</p>
<p>   next week and then across to Western Australia. So I'm going</p>
<p>   everywhere, talking about it, listening to questions, explaining</p>
<p>   the detail of it because it is an historic plan.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Well, is a mid-October election a possibility?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Neil, I don't know when the election is going to be held.</p>
<p>   I'm accepting dinner date invitations right through October.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>What does that mean?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, people keep asking me and they say can you come to dinner</p>
<p>   on such and such a Saturday in October and I'm accepting the</p>
<p>   invitations. But, Neil, I don't know when the election's</p>
<p>   going to be and there's no way I'm going to be sort of</p>
<p>   drawn to speculate because I don't know.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, the private health insurance rebate.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>A very good initiative.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Are you going to give yours back?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Mine? No. Do you mean to say, am I going to claim it? Well, I...</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Are you going to give it back, were going to give it back, yeah,</p>
<p>   is that right, are you going to claim...?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I reserve the right to claim it. I think it would seem rather</p>
<p>   odd if I'm selling this as a terrific change and something</p>
<p>   that people ought to get into and then I say I'm not going</p>
<p>   to take it...</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Well, you [inaudible]...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, well, I didn't. I think that probably sends a rather mixed</p>
<p>   signal.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Why?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, because if you're saying it's good for people and</p>
<p>   you don't take it yourself people are going to say: well, is</p>
<p>   it good for me?</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Well, of course, the people already getting the $450 only get $150</p>
<p>   out of this, don't they? It's the high income earners</p>
<p>   that...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, no, no. No, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, that's wrong.</p>
<p>   People get 30 per cent of whatever it costs them.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Yeah, but if you say they're paying $2000 every year....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, that's just an example. </p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Well, it's not a bad one.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, that is a, I mean, that is a very typical family cover. Now,</p>
<p>   so there's no misunderstanding about this, whatever your private</p>
<p>   health insurance premium is, you get 30 per cent back and, therefore,</p>
<p>   it is of no greater benefit to somebody on $500,000 a year than</p>
<p>   it is for somebody on $45,000. In fact, it's a proportionately</p>
<p>   greater benefit. It's a flat amount.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>But the people who are on [inaudible] are already getting something,</p>
<p>   people up the other end aren't.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>That's true. But what is wrong with encouraging them to take</p>
<p>   it out as well? Isn't the name of the game, with private health</p>
<p>   insurance, to get greater coverage, greater involvement? You need</p>
<p>   to get some of the higher income, healthy people into this because</p>
<p>   they will help subsidise through community rating the other people.</p>
<p>   That is how private health insurance works.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Is there anything in this package which is non-negotiable?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, the fundamentals of it aren't negotiable. I mean, if</p>
<p>   you say to me, is there some fine detail over on page 300 </p>
<p>   I mean, we have consultative mechanisms. But having spent months</p>
<p>   putting it together and having announced it yesterday, I'm</p>
<p>   not going to today start talking about changing it.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>I can understand that but the Democrats are already saying, well,</p>
<p>   we'll negotiate it after the election if they win, which puts</p>
<p>   people in a position of saying will we vote for this at an election</p>
<p>   or we vote against it but how much is it going to change afterwards.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, Neil, we're obviously not going to sort of fundamentally</p>
<p>   compromise it. Of course we're not going to do that. And we'll</p>
<p>   be going to the election asking the public to vote for us in both</p>
<p>   Houses of Parliament. I mean, I'm pleased that the Democrats</p>
<p>   haven't rejected it out of hand, I think that's sensible.</p>
<p>   They're not as negative as the Labor Party. But we want this</p>
<p>   plan endorsed and if it's endorsed, whenever the election is,</p>
<p>   we will present it to the Parliament and we will say to the opposition</p>
<p>   parties in the Senate: you had your go, the people have spoken,</p>
<p>   listen to the people, do what the people want and let it go through.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>There are [inaudible] anomalies being suggested already, no GST</p>
<p>   on education, but there is...you do pay the GST on food, school</p>
<p>   uniforms, tuckshop food, books, did you look at that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, the reason - well once you start looking at that, you look</p>
<p>   at something else and then you....</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>On hospital care [inaudible] on linen and [inaudible].</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yeah, but they get it back. But look, what you've got to understand,</p>
<p>   Neil, the way this thing operates is once you start chopping and</p>
<p>   changing with one bit then the next person says, oh well, look,</p>
<p>   will you have a look at mine and then you have a look at something</p>
<p>   else and then you're back to the system we've got at the</p>
<p>   present time.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>You'd have to be very...persuasive argument to get you</p>
<p>   to change anything.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, anything fundamental to it, yes.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, the provisional tax. Now, page 152 of the document </p>
<p>   this confuses me, I must admit because we've got provisional</p>
<p>   tax being abolished and that's savings or negative income...[inaudible]...well,</p>
<p>   I'm looking over three years [inaudible]. However, over the</p>
<p>   three years company payment arrangements brings in 7.5.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yeah, what happens is that we're altering the timing of company</p>
<p>   payment arrangements so that in those early years there's a</p>
<p>   bigger yield and that evens out later on. But that is eminently</p>
<p>   affordable for those companies because they get a huge cashflow</p>
<p>   benefit out of the GST.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>But isn't that, in fact, an increase on the tax [inaudible]?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, it's not. It's just an alteration in the timing arrangements.</p>
<p>   You have a look at the detail.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>[Inaudible]...7.5. Housing  house and land packages according</p>
<p>   to the HIA up $16,000 for an average house and land package.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, the HIA is not happy, I understand that. But you've</p>
<p>   got to remember we're providing a first home owners scheme</p>
<p>   of $7000 and the climate for the housing industry at the moment</p>
<p>   has never been better because interest rates haven't been as</p>
<p>   low as they are now for 30 years. So when you take all that into</p>
<p>   account  and houses will not go up by 10 per cent. We calculate</p>
<p>   the cost of new housing will rise by 4.7 per cent and that is why</p>
<p>   we're bringing in a first home owners scheme of $7000 because</p>
<p>   when you build a new house now you pay wholesale sales tax on a</p>
<p>   lot of items like baths and heaters and toilets and all those sorts</p>
<p>   of things and they won't be...wholesale sales tax will disappear</p>
<p>   under the new system.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Of course, there's not much doubt consumers are paying more</p>
<p>   all the way along the line, isn't there?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, we worked out, right across the board, Neil, that the price</p>
<p>   increase is an average of 1.9 per cent. Now, in some cases it's</p>
<p>   higher, in other cases it's lower.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Sure. But I'm looking at that again, at the table on page</p>
<p>   158, the impact of the tax reform on industry and how the industry</p>
<p>   cost goes down and the impact on consumer prices go up. And that</p>
<p>   shows it pretty clearly. And [inaudible] industry cost down 3.4,</p>
<p>   the consumer up 4.4 and there's a 4.5 per cent increase across</p>
<p>   the board.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes, but you get a tax cut. And over and above all the impact of</p>
<p>   the GST you get a tax cut and anything makes business operate more</p>
<p>   efficiently and more economically has got to be good for the country.</p>
<p>   I mean, the end gain in all of this is a more prosperous, a stronger</p>
<p>   growing and overall stronger Australia. I mean, the aim of a tax</p>
<p>   reform is surely an aggregate national aim to build a stronger and</p>
<p>   a more economically viable Australia. And the fact that we do have</p>
<p>   an Asian economic downturn, that you mentioned a few minutes ago,</p>
<p>   is an added reason for reform, it's not a reason to postpone</p>
<p>   reform.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>You don't agree that it makes the whole package a bit fragile.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Fragile!</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Well, the Asian...the possibility of an Asian economic downturn</p>
<p>   and other economic problems in this country, we know we're</p>
<p>   not headed into a great period of prosperity...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>But Neil, it's...</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>[Inaudible]</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>But Neil, it is precisely because of those challenges we must now</p>
<p>   reform. If we put the reform off yet again, as Mr Beazley wants</p>
<p>   us to do and others want us to do, we'll be weaker. I mean,</p>
<p>   why is Japan in trouble now? Because Japan, eight or nine years,</p>
<p>   refused to undertake fundamental reform of its banking system. Japan,</p>
<p>   eight or nine years ago, was seen as the second most powerful economy</p>
<p>   in the world. It is now seen as being in difficulty. Why? Because</p>
<p>   it put off reform. It was loaded with people who had the attitude</p>
<p>   equivalent to Mr Beazley who's saying: no, don't do it</p>
<p>   now, it's too difficult, put it off. I mean, you can't</p>
<p>   do that. You have a responsibility in government to undertake the</p>
<p>   reforms, to do the things that are necessary to strengthen your</p>
<p>   country for the future and that is why I'm so committed to</p>
<p>   this.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>I would like to take some calls in a moment. Another quick question</p>
<p>   first on the facts. I mean, $1.6 billion is really the amount that</p>
<p>   will not be coming out the bank, isn't that right  something</p>
<p>   like that, on the FID and tax?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh yes, well that is, I mean, that's one of the beneficial</p>
<p>   offsets for consumers.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>The Treasurer, Mr Costello, has been pretty critical of the banks</p>
<p>   in the past [inaudible]. Can we trust the banks to do the right</p>
<p>   thing?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, the best way to make sure the banks do the right thing is</p>
<p>   to have more competition. And the reason...</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>[Inaudible] competition and they're still screwing people...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh, but hang on, interest rates now are lower than they've</p>
<p>   been for 30 years.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>But bank charges are higher.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>But Neil, Neil, the net position of a homebuyer and a small businessman</p>
<p>   now is better than it's been, interest rate wise and bank wise,</p>
<p>   than it's been for 30 years.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Is there a mechanism to ensure the banks don't just pocket</p>
<p>   the $1.6 billion?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Neil, we're going to give special powers to the Competition</p>
<p>   Commission and there'll be fines of up to $10 million for people</p>
<p>   who don't pass on offsetting indirect tax cuts.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>So we've got to keep a close watch on the banks.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, you've got to keep a close watch on everybody. But a</p>
<p>   lot of people in the business community are fundamentally very honest</p>
<p>   and they'll try and do the right thing. There are some who</p>
<p>   aren't and we'll have somebody there to give them a whack</p>
<p>   if they don't.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>We'll take some calls, [inaudible] go ahead please.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>Oh, hello, excuse me, I'm very nervous.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Don't be nervous please, so am I.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>I find it very...what prompted me to ring was that when Mr Howard</p>
<p>   says that the whole big thing of the GST is that it will stop the</p>
<p>   tax cheats. From what I saw last night, and I can only go by what</p>
<p>   so far from what I've seen, is that the black economy is actually</p>
<p>   going to grow.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, it won't.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>Now, the example that they showed last night was a cleaner. You</p>
<p>   have a cleaner who cleans homes, has cash in hand, puts on the GST</p>
<p>   when she's doing the cleaning, basically she has the cash in</p>
<p>   hand and she basically has the extra GST and she doesn't pass</p>
<p>   it on to the Government.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>No, she doesn't declare it...</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>That's right. She doesn't declare it. Cash in hand is</p>
<p>   cash in hand  [inaudible] you will not find it...what they</p>
<p>   said last night was that in New Zealand, in Canada and, I believe,</p>
<p>   in Europe, the black economy has actually grown.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, let's say, for example, that that cleaner you're</p>
<p>   talking about is operating entirely in the cash economy. Now, at</p>
<p>   least under a GST when that cleaner goes and buys a restaurant meal,</p>
<p>   they'll have to pay some GST. And for the first time in their</p>
<p>   lives they'll be paying, in relation to that particular service,</p>
<p>   a bit of tax.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>[Inaudible]</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, they have, yeah, I know, but because it's br</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
