<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4775</transcript-id>
    <title>Condolence Message fo His Holiness Pope Paul VI</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/08/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004775.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>FOR PRESS 15 AUGUST 1978<br />
Mr Speaker, i move that the House notes the death on 6 August<br />
1978 of His Holiness Pope Paul VI, and expresses its profound<br />
regret at his passing.<br />
With the death of Pope Paul the spiritual leader of the<br />
world's 700 million Romnan Catholics for the last 15 yearsthe<br />
world lost a great religious leader and a messenger of<br />
peace. In many ways his papacy came in an unique age.<br />
It coincided with an upsurge of the ecumenical movement and<br />
far-reaching and fundamental changes in society throughout<br />
the world. It was an age, too, of challenge to the traditional<br />
spiritual authority of the Church.<br />
Pope Paul sought to maintain the essential body of doctrine<br />
of his Church, and to uphold its institutional character.<br />
He saw his duty as being to steer a middle course within<br />
the Church, between those elements calling for change and<br />
those who defended continuity.<br />
Pope Paul handled these challenges calmly and wisely, with<br />
moderation, tenacity and courage.<br />
Pope Paul made strenuous efforts to encourage the ecumenical<br />
movement for Christian unity. He actively encouraged contact<br />
and fraternity within Christianity and between the major world<br />
religions.<br />
He sponsored ecumenical meetings for Christian unity, held<br />
numerous meetings with leaders of other Churches, and looked<br />
forward to the eventual resolution of disunity.<br />
Pope Paul also will be remembered for his important reforms<br />
to the organisation and structure of the Church.<br />
The implementation of the Vatican Council's decision to allow<br />
celebration of the mass in the Vernacular was an historic<br />
event of his reign.<br />
There were important changes initiated by Pope Pual in the<br />
field of international affairs. He strove tirelessly for<br />
world peace and for higher ideals in the conduct of world<br />
affairs. </p>
<p>Under him, the Vatican enhanced its already high stature in<br />
international diplomacy. It became a notable contributor<br />
to conferences such as those on world food problems, population,<br />
humanitarian law in armed conflict, and security and co-operation<br />
in Europe.<br />
Foreign policy concerns of the Holy See under Pope Paul included:<br />
disarmament and the non-proliferation of nuclear weapons;<br />
improvement of social welfare; assisting the development of<br />
the poorer countries; evolution of relations with Marxist<br />
regimes; and a desire to expand official communications with<br />
the Communist, Islamic and Asian world to ensure maintenance<br />
of freedom of Christian observance.<br />
He emphasised peace as the most essential need of our time,<br />
and this was reflected in his innovation of the observance<br />
of 1 January as the world day of peace.<br />
I recall with warmth and appreciation my private audience<br />
with Pope Paul only last year, during which he gave expression<br />
to his concern for and promotion of peace amongst all the<br />
world's citizens.<br />
Pope Paul travelled widely, disregarding risks to his person,<br />
and became the first reigning Pontiff to visit all continents.<br />
We remember the affection generated by his visit to Australia<br />
in 1970. It was during his reign that Australia opened<br />
diplomatic relations with the Holy See. These have proved of<br />
great value in the conduct of Austrlaia's foreign affairs.<br />
Mr Speaker, Pope Paul was a man whose great strengths and<br />
personality became clearer the longer he remained Pope.<br />
His death saddened this country. It is a supreme loss for<br />
his Church and a real loss for all men.<br />
I commend the motion to the House. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
