<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>40027</transcript-id>
    <title>Transcript, Joint Press Conference</title>
    <prime-minister>Turnbull, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20150915 - 20180824</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/10/2015</release-date>
    <release-type>Transcript</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER:</strong><br />
Thanks everyone for being here. I'm here – as you know – with your Premier Annastacia Palaszczuk and the Mayor Tom Tate and one state colleague, Rob Molhoek – the Member for Southport.</p>
<p>And then my Federal colleague, Steve Ciobo – the Minister for International Development – and the Gold Coast MP, Karen Andrews – the Assistant Minister for Science. Another Gold Coast MP, Stu Robert – the Minister for Human Services and Veterans' Affairs' – another Gold Coast, South East Queensland MP and very involved in all of the advocacy preceding this. And, of course, the Minister for Major Projects, Local Government and Territories, Paul Fletcher, he came up with me from Sydney. And Bert van Manen, who's the Member for Ford. So, we have a good team here today showing our commitment to this project.</p>
<p>Now, can I just say that public transport infrastructure like this is absolutely critical to the development of our cities which are absolutely critical to ensuring our future prosperity as a nation. Our cities are the crucibles of innovation, of enterprise, it's where so much of our GDP is created and it's vital that they have the right infrastructure, whether it is telecommunications infrastructure or transport infrastructure like this.</p>
<p>Public transport infrastructure like this is essential. It is good for you. People that use public transport walk more often, don't they? Tom has become much fitter since he started getting the light rail. You meet new people. I met you on the train today.</p>
<p><strong>PREMIER </strong><strong>Palaszczuk:</strong><br />
That's right.</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER:</strong><br />
There you go. It's also a very key part of bringing this whole South East Queensland region together. Once this link is built, people will be able to get on to the train in Brisbane and then with one change, get all the way down to the Gold Coast, to Surfers Paradise. So, it's really critical pulling this very long linear development of the Gold Coast together.</p>
<p>It is a vital, fantastic bit of infrastructure and I'm delighted that I'm able to announce today that the Federal Government will be making a capped grant – that is to say it is limited to this amount and no more – of $95 million to support the completion of this last stage to Helensvale.</p>
<p>Now, this is very much a Queensland project, so the construction risk is obviously with Queensland. That's why the grant is capped. We've been impressed with the business plan – the preliminary business plan – we've seen. It looks very good, as it should, because this is after all filling in a missing link and we'll be looking forward to the final business plan in December and final agreements which will have to be to the satisfaction of the Minister Warren Truss. But we have every expectation that this is going to be a terrific piece of infrastructure, a great project.</p>
<p>I make one final observation – this is a grant, as I said, this is not the only way the Federal Government can or should support infrastructure. In the future, we want to look at more innovative approaches. We want to look at arrangements where we can partner the state governments or with city governments as shareholders, as investors. We also have to look creatively at how we capture the value that arises from the increase in property values and the improvement in the utility of adjacent land from the building of infrastructure like this. This might be by owning part of the land or it might be from some sort of differential rating arrangement.</p>
<p>There's a lot of angles to it. But a project like this adds billions of dollars of value – as the Mayor was saying to us on the train earlier – billions of dollars of value to the Gold Coast, to the economy, to South East Queensland, the fastest growing part of our nation and of course such an important part of our economy.</p>
<p>And here we are linking Griffith University right up to the great universities in Brisbane itself. So, this is a really important project. We, as a Federal Government, are delighted to be supporting it and helping make it happen.</p>
<p>Thank you very much.</p>
<p><strong>PREMIER Palaszczuk:</strong><br />
Thank you Prime Minister, and can I first of all welcome you to Queensland. It's wonderful to have you in our great State and also to the Mayor Tom Tate.</p>
<p>This is great news for the Gold Coast and great news for the south east. What we are seeing is what happens when all levels of government can work together to deliver vital public infrastructure in the best interests of the south east corner. And I congratulate the Prime Minister, I congratulate the Mayor, for coming to the party to make sure that this second stage goes ahead.</p>
<p>This 7.3 kilometre extension – the Stage 2 of the light rail – is vital for the Commonwealth Games. I've said this time and time again. This is the vital link needed for the Commonwealth Games. And now with the Federal Government coming on-board, we now know that the business case will be finalised by December 23 and it also means then that construction can start in April next year. It's going to mean over 1,000 jobs – 1,000 jobs – in this local region here. That means 1,000 families – 1,000 families – that will get employment with the Stage 2 of the construction.</p>
<p>Can I say, too, that it is refreshing to have a Prime Minister that is prepared to commit to public transport, hat recognises that Queensland is a rapidly growing State, that Queensland needs infrastructure across our State. And I recognise also the Prime Minister's commitment to the development of Northern Australia, as well.</p>
<p>I intend to work very closely with Malcolm over the coming years to make sure that we develop and implement the best for Queensland. And that means I will be putting the case firmly when it's needed, but I believe that this is a new era of cooperation and I welcome today the announcement that the second stage of the light rail can go ahead.</p>
<p><strong>MAYOR TOM TATE:</strong><br />
Prime Minister, Premier, it's a great spring day here on the Gold Coast. It's a momentous occasion to learn that all three tiers of government are all aboard on this extension of the light rail.</p>
<p>The significant thing is that there is already $6 billion in the pipeline waiting for this announcement. So, in addition to 1,000 jobs, there will be so many more jobs for the families of the Gold Coast, will happen in the near future as we march towards the Commonwealth Games 2018.</p>
<p>And for all those people on the west side of the highway and the north, this is an opportunity for you to also enjoy this infrastructure. You will be able to park and ride or drive and ride, whether you go to Brisbane or go to Southport and beyond to Broadbeach on the Gold Coast, to utilise this – I have absolute confidence.</p>
<p>But, you know, how many ways can you say your appreciation to the Premier and to the Prime Minister with their vision to see that the Gold Coast is the premier tourist destination. So this is not just for locals, it's for all Australians and thank you so much for your vision.</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER:</strong><br />
Thanks, Tom. Any questions?</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST:</strong><br />
Lovely start, Prime Minister – we have got a long list of things that Queensland needs. Must we send Jonathan Thurston [inaudible]?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER:</strong><br />
Well, he is very effective – very effective. He is very effective at closing, gets in at the last minute.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST:</strong><br />
Could we have our stadium, please?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER:</strong><br />
I understand from the Premier that there is a business case proposal coming and we will certainly be looking at it. The Minister for Major Projects, Paul Fletcher, will be looking at it very closely with the Minister for Infrastructure, Warren Truss. So, all these things will be looked at, but we're not making commitments on the run. But, plainly, you can see there is a great deal of interest.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST:</strong><br />
What did you see it is that your predecessor didn't, Prime Minister?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER:</strong><br />
Look, federal governments over the years, I think, have been reluctant to invest in public transport infrastructure. There is a range of reasons for that, but they are essentially historical. The reality is that you should assess the merit of infrastructure on its merits and not favour one road over rail or rail over road. And, you know, as cities become more densely settled, public transport infrastructure is of greater and greater importance. So, if you can't have a roads-only solution, you can't obviously have a rail-only solution either. So I think it's just a question of taking a pragmatic, business-like, practical approach to it, no ideology involved. This is just business-like.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST:</strong><br />
Was this your opportunity to distinguish yourself and separate yourself from the last leadership with something different?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER:</strong><br />
No, it's an opportunity to support a vital piece of infrastructure which is going to link up, help further link up South East Queensland and support, among other things, the Commonwealth Games. So, that's what it is.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST:</strong><br />
What about the cross river tunnel in Brisbane? That's vital too?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER:</strong><br />
I'm sure it is vital and I look forward to seeing some – we all look forward to seeing some proposals on it.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST:</strong><br />
Mr Turnbull, your predecessor was very keen to be known as the infrastructure prime minister. Is yours going to be a public transport Prime Minister?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER:</strong><br />
I aim to be. I will be an infrastructure Prime Minister, an infrastructure Prime Minister that supports all infrastructure on the basis of its merits. So, we will support public transport where that's the best outcome, the best value for money, the best outcome in terms of the Commonwealth's investment and the same goes with roads, as well.</p>
<p>So, it's a question, just a question of not – there is no reason to discriminate between one mode of transport or another. You need everything. This is an all of the above approach to solving our city's transport needs and this is a fantastic element because – as I said – it is the missing link. It's hard to find something that is more compelling than this one.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST:</strong><br />
Surely if Queenslanders nominate their priorities for the Federal Government money, these are only our taxes that we're asking [inaudible]. Why should you be the guy who says yes or no, surely Queenslanders should decide where their taxes go?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER:</strong><br />
Well, the Federal Government, the Cabinet of the Government of the Commonwealth of Australia, will make these decisions. We're not going to make any constitutional rearrangements here. You should speak to the Premier about the Queensland [inaudible].</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST:</strong><br />
How do you feel about the reaction that you got yesterday when you said the party isn't ruled by factions and backroom deals?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER:</strong><br />
Look, it's good to get some constructive feedback – I think it's very important for all of us. But the point I was making was that the parliamentary Liberal Party itself, there are factions in all political parties, but the parliamentary Liberal Party itself is a much more independent group of individuals and that was really the point I was making.</p>
<p>Thanks very much.</p>
<p align="center"><strong>Ends</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
