<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9408</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P J KEATING MP INAUGURAL NATIONAL GENERAL ASSEMBLY OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT NATIONAL CONVENTION CENTRE CANBERRA 7 NOVEMBER 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/11/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009408.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Q<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
( CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY)<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON PF J KEATING MP<br />
INAUGURAL NATIONAL GENERAL ASSEMBLY OF<br />
LOCAL GOVERNMENT<br />
NATIONAL CONVENTION CENTRE CANBERRA<br />
7 NOVEMBER 1994<br />
Well, it's a pleasure to address this your first National General Assembly.<br />
And let me congratulate those of you who took the initiative, who exercised the<br />
leadership, to make this historic meeting possible.<br />
Although it is IG0 years since the first local council was created in Australia, I think it<br />
is timely that you should come together to identify the key issues facing Local<br />
Government. After all, these are times of great change for all levels of government, times that<br />
demand we take stock of whcre we are so that we can have a bigger say in where we<br />
go. I think it's particularly appropriate that it is a Labor Prime M~ iister that speaks to your<br />
first National General Assembly because Labor governments have long recogniscd the<br />
key importance of Local Government in our Federal system.<br />
it was the Whitlam. Government that first introduced direct untied assistance to local<br />
government. It was the Hawke Governmcnt that proposed the Constitution be amended to reflect<br />
the critical role of Local Governiment in our national life.<br />
Despite that referendum not getting up, the current Labor Government has continued<br />
to work to strengthen the role of Local Government.<br />
We have sought to give it a status in the community that it descrvcs, a status<br />
commensurate with a tier of government that employs around 160,000 Australians and<br />
spends around 10 billion a year. </p>
<p>It's why we introduced the annual consultations between Local Government and the<br />
Commonwealth in 1989.<br />
And why we also moved to give Local Government fMl membership of COAG.<br />
This Government is committed to seeing that your aspirations and needs, and those of<br />
the people you serve, are heard in the highest forums of the land.<br />
But it's more than just giving you a forum in which to speak * important as that is.<br />
It's also about making things happen in partnership.<br />
Back in 1992 when the Federal Government was looking to give the economy some<br />
much needed stimulus the Statcs were found wanting.<br />
It was Local Government wh~ ich stepped into the breach to join up with the Federal<br />
Government and deliver a Capital Works Program on time and beyond expectation.<br />
It was a -major exercise with Local Government and community groups putting in more<br />
than S$ 120 million to match the Commonwealth's contribution of $ 350 million.<br />
This was a great example of the Commonwealth working with Local Government to<br />
harness local knowledge, comrnitmcnt and organisational strengths to achieve an<br />
important national objective.<br />
And it reminded us that programs work best when they are delivered at the local level<br />
and reflect local needs.<br />
That's something people in both Local Governmcnt and the Labor Party understand.<br />
We also both understand how important it is to bring thc people along with you, to<br />
hold a community together when times gct tough.<br />
This is the case now for many communities, particularly the rural communities in<br />
Queensland and New South Wales which are experiencing the worst drought on<br />
record. For them, times have never been tougher than they are today.<br />
There will be some of you here who have firsthand experience of the devastation that<br />
the drought has brought, of the enormous personal and financial burdens it has placed<br />
on so many ini our rural communities.<br />
Being in Local Government means that you have that special sort of relationship with<br />
people that only a local person can. </p>
<p>And more often than not it usually means you too shoulder part of the burden when<br />
things are tough, that you too lend a hand way beyond your professional<br />
responsibilities because that's the way things are done in the bush.<br />
To those of you here and to the many others in Local Govcrrnent who have played<br />
such an important role in helping to ease the hardship of the drought, let me take this<br />
opportunity to express the Government's great appreciation for all that you have done.<br />
Yours is a contribution that will be remembered.<br />
The drought is a big issue for the Labor Party -we're determined not to leave the<br />
people on the land behind.<br />
We're concerned about the future of family farming, of the impact of the drought on<br />
rural society.<br />
That's why we put in place the drought package that we did, a package which includes:<br />
the establishment of a Drought Relief Scheme which provides familics with<br />
cash for basic necessities and gives thcm access to Family Payments and the<br />
Healthcare card<br />
the removal of the existing Austudy farm assets test for all families in<br />
exceptional circumstances<br />
increased resources for financial and social counselling-,<br />
and further measures under the Rural Adjustment Scheme to assist farm<br />
businesses both now and during the recovery phase.<br />
Since we announced the drought package just over six weeks ago, we've already been<br />
able to make a substantial contfibution to helping farming families in the most severely<br />
affected areas.<br />
So far, nearly 1,000 fanilies have had their claims approved under the Drought Relief<br />
Scheme, and another 2,000 plus have lodged their claims with the Department of<br />
Social Security.<br />
On top of this, another 6,000 families have applied for a certificate for the drought<br />
relief payment which is the first step in the process.<br />
So, we are getting the payments out there, but we need to push this process hard to<br />
make sure all those eligible receive the assistance they so desperately need, and<br />
quickly. </p>
<p>To those of you that will be returning to communities experiencing severe drought, I<br />
would urge you to keep up your efforts to encourage those who are eligible for<br />
assistance to apply.<br />
And also to let the local people know that if thc situation deteriorates further that the<br />
Government is prepared to provide additional assistance on top of the $ 164 million<br />
that has already been allocated.<br />
The drought is a good reminder that the activitics of Local Governent extend right<br />
across [ lie Australian community, that what might be a burning issue for some one in<br />
inner suburban Melbournc might have little relevance for someone in far north<br />
Queensland. But whatever different challenges we might face from time to time, there is, I think,<br />
one challenge that we all face continuously.<br />
And that is the challenge of Icadership.<br />
For my part, I have always thought that one of the keys to leadership is imagination,<br />
having a sense of what's possible and taking the odd risk<br />
Because if you don't have that you won't be moved to chance your arm, to push for the<br />
big changcs, the ones that really matter, the ones that affect peoples lives for the better<br />
and over the long term.<br />
Leadecrship is not, and never has been, the preserve of any one person.<br />
Nor is it somcthing that flows from occupying a particular position.<br />
It's about getting things done and being effective.<br />
Its about generating and maintaining miomentumn<br />
It's about making sure the place is better off for your effort a sense of stewardship if<br />
you like.<br />
In sum, it's about recognising and seizing the right opportunities to make a meaningful<br />
difference to people's lives.<br />
That's the thinking that lay behind the drought assistance measures and it's certainly the<br />
thinking that. lay behind Working Nation, the White Paper on Employment and<br />
Growth. In Working Nalion we wanted to ensure that unemployed people, particularly long<br />
term unemployed people shared in the economic recovery. </p>
<p>We also wanted to ensure that regional Australia got its share too, that this wasn't just<br />
a recovery in the big cities.<br />
And it was for this reason that we aninounced thc Regional Developincnt Strategy, a<br />
strategy designed to harness the enormous leadership potcntial that lies in the men and<br />
women of rcgional Australia.<br />
It not a strategy that seeks to replicate the quick fix solutions of the past or to adopt<br />
a scatter gun approach.<br />
Nor does it see throwing buckets of money as the answer to the regions' most pressing<br />
problems. As McKinsey revealed in their Lead Local Compete Global study, given the task of<br />
rejuvenating a region, regional leaders said they would far prefer $ 2 million and<br />
committed local leaders rather than $ 50 million minus the local leaders.<br />
And that's why I believe the challenge of regional Australia is primarily a challenge of<br />
leadership. As McKinsey also pointed out, you can take two different regions in Australia with the<br />
same factor conditions, the same level of infrastructure, the same level of human and<br />
natural resources but one region will prosper while the other fails.<br />
And the reason one region succeeds is because it has leadcrship.<br />
It has leaders who share a vision for their region and who arc prepared to bring all the<br />
key players together to chart a common course.<br />
And what's true of the regions is just as true for local councils that go to making up<br />
regional Australia.<br />
Of course, adopting a Regional Devclopment Strategy that focuses on leadership<br />
assumes that the lcaders exist, that regional Australia has within it a real wealth of<br />
talented men and women.<br />
Well, it has.<br />
it's something that was clearly borne out in the work of the Regional Development<br />
Taskforce which was chaired by Bill Kelty, and included your energetic President,<br />
Councillor Peter Woods.<br />
The Taskforce itself played an invaluable leadership role in getting regional<br />
communities to think about their long-term future. </p>
<p>It found that right across the country there were people looking for new opportunities<br />
to quicken the pace of economic development in their region, people who wanted to<br />
build on the strength of their region and find their region a place in thc international<br />
economy. And I think this is something that will come increasingly into play as more local<br />
councils become involved in competitive tendering, contracting out, resource sharing<br />
and enterprise bargaining.<br />
Our overall economic policy objectivc of sustainable low inflation growth can only be<br />
achieved if the right conditions for growth can be created in the regions.<br />
And in this endeavour, the Commionwealth and local government share considerable<br />
common ground.<br />
We agree that effective local government participation is vital to the success of<br />
regional developmcnt activities.<br />
We agree that the three tiers of government should work in partnership to plan for<br />
economic and regional development and to deliver appropriate programs.<br />
And we agree that the need for effective local government has never been greater.<br />
And it's because of this common ground that we want to see Local Government take a<br />
leadership role in implementing the Regional Development Strategy.<br />
Since its announcement in Working Nativ-1, the Regional Development Strategy has<br />
remained very much on track.<br />
By Christmas, we hope to have around ten regions active in the program.<br />
And over the life of the program we hope to extend it to around forty Regional<br />
Economic Developmntn Organisations.<br />
The first region to take advantage of the program is likely to be the Northern Rivers<br />
Region of New South Wales which I visited earlier this year.<br />
During my visit, I was particularly heartened to see how the people around Lismore<br />
share a common vision for their region and are committed to breathing life into that<br />
vision. They have got themsclves together and are now planning a regional development<br />
strategy based on sustainable, value adding agricultural production and niche export<br />
marketing. </p>
<p>7<br />
Importantly, they have developed bi-partisan political support for the regional<br />
developmcnt activities.<br />
Thcre are also a number of other regions in Queensland, Victoria, Wcstern Australia<br />
and South Australia which are getting ready to participate in the program.<br />
This is great news.<br />
It shows a nation with regions that are prepared to work on a future for themselves<br />
rather than rely on outside funding only,<br />
Recent analysis of economic data shows that quite a number of regions are strongly<br />
outgrowing the capital city areas in activity and employment.<br />
And some of the regions have even greater potential with significant growth in<br />
population. These are the areas giving the lead to regional Australia.<br />
Before I finish let me make reference to one other area where Local Government can<br />
support the cfforts of the Federal Government and that is in the area of social justice.<br />
I'm thinking here of two groups whose potential to add to our national endeavour has<br />
not been sufficiently recogrniscd or tapped<br />
I am thinking of our indigenous peoplc and our women.<br />
Over recent times, the Federal Government has taken unprecedented steps to accord<br />
our indigenous people a proper and just place in the nation.<br />
So I'm pleased to see that your National Agenda reflects that same objective.<br />
And I trust that it's something that you will give effect to in the course of your<br />
deliberations at this historic meeting.<br />
I'm also pleased that Local Government has more women representatives than for most<br />
other Australian governmcnts.<br />
But at around 20 per cent it is still too low.<br />
Achieving more equitable representation of men and women in Local Government, as<br />
elected representatives and mayors, and also in senior managemcnt, is about keeping<br />
faith with our democratic and egalitarian traditions.<br />
It is also, fundamentally, about recognising and using the full array of leadership and<br />
talent at our disposal. </p>
<p>8<br />
I would urge you to look carefully at this issue, to consult with women Councillors and<br />
women Local Government staff, and to put in place a practical strategy to increase<br />
women's participation in Local Government decision-making and management,<br />
Let me wind up.<br />
As a key player in regional Australia, Local Government bas both the opportunity and<br />
the responsibility to provide the sort of leadership that the Commonwealth's new<br />
approach to regional development seeks to encourage.<br />
It is an opportunity arnd a challenge I know you arc more than capable of accepting.<br />
And through it, I want us to continue to work together in partnership -for the<br />
good of the nation.<br />
How etfectively we work together will, however, depend to a great deal on the<br />
outcomes of this first National Gcneral Assembly.<br />
And while I know your diversity makes it difficult, Local Governent will play a far<br />
greater role in achieving national objectives if it speaks with a unified voice.<br />
That is the challenge before this first National General Assembly.<br />
But whatever the outcome, the Federal Government will continue to look for a Local<br />
Government system that plays an increasingly important role in the affairs of our<br />
nation, a system that combines local priorities with broader national goals.<br />
Thank you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
