<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10770</transcript-id>
    <title>3 April 1998                                 TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                  THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                  RADIO INTERVIEW - HOWARD SATTLER PROGRAMME                RADIO 6PR</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/04/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE............................</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>I've got the Prime Minister on the line now. Good morning,</p>
<p>   Prime Minister. You've had a few pretty nasty things said about</p>
<p>   you in Parliament - how does this rate?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think it is the bottom of the barrel. He should apologise, Mr</p>
<p>   Beazley should have the strength to force him to apologise. When</p>
<p>   Mr Randall said something that he shouldn't have said, I got</p>
<p>   him to apologise.</p>
<p> SATTLER:</p>
<p>How does this rate with that?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, just as bad. I mean, I don't appreciate being accused</p>
<p>   of racism. My family doesn't appreciate it, my friends don't,</p>
<p>   they know it's wrong. I've got a pretty tough hide but</p>
<p>   you've got to draw the line somewhere.</p>
<p> SATTLER:</p>
<p>Well he wasn't thrown out of the Parliament. Two of his colleagues</p>
<p>   were, so how come?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well look, that was the discretion of the Speaker. I'm not</p>
<p>   responsible for the Speaker's behaviour. I don't give</p>
<p>   the Speaker instructions. The Speaker is responsible for keeping</p>
<p>   order and I'm not going to express a view either way about</p>
<p>   what the Speaker has done. But just getting back to Mr Evans, I</p>
<p>   mean, not only is it a highly offensive remark but it was based</p>
<p>   upon a photograph and a report suggesting that I was sort of dancing</p>
<p>   a jig because we won the Hindmarsh Bridge case. I was in fact dealing</p>
<p>   with an entirely different issue and Mr Evans knew that because</p>
<p>   he was present during the whole of Question Time. Now, I don't</p>
<p>   want to spend a lot of time on this. I simply say again, it was</p>
<p>   a baseless, provocative, inflammatory remark. When I think of this</p>
<p>   whole native title debate, there are three ugly remarks that will</p>
<p>   stay in my memory forever. One of them was a remark by Noel Pearson</p>
<p>   that people supporting the native title bill were racist scum. Another</p>
<p>   was a remark by Daryl Melham, a Labor frontbencher, likening the</p>
<p>   opposition to membership of the Ku Klux Klan, and now we have this</p>
<p>   absolutely appalling remark by Mr Evans.</p>
<p>Now he said that I was never so happy as when I'm bashing</p>
<p>   black fellas. Now it's a terribly patronising, ugly way of</p>
<p>   talking about indigenous people. It is of course very offensive</p>
<p>   to me, but it really does highlight the weakness of Mr Beazley.</p>
<p>   I mean, Mr Beazley asked me to do something about people in my party</p>
<p>   who had said things he thought they shouldn't have said, and</p>
<p>   I did so. I call on him to apply the same strength and the same</p>
<p>   standard in relation to his own Deputy, in relation to Mr Melham</p>
<p>   and to tell his party that in the interests of Australia, and Australia's</p>
<p>   reputation, they've got to stop making these kind of remarks.</p>
<p>We will have a debate about native title if the Senate knocks back</p>
<p>   the legislation.</p>
<p> SATTLER:</p>
<p>We'll have more than a debate about it, won't we?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>What else are you to do in a democracy where the Parliament can't</p>
<p>   agree on what ought to be done, and the Constitution says that the</p>
<p>   only way the law can come into effect is at a joint sitting of the</p>
<p>   Parliament after a double dissolution. I mean, I want to make it</p>
<p>   very clear, we are not going to be bullied out of making necessary</p>
<p>   changes to the law in the interests of farmers, miners, indigenous</p>
<p>   people and the entire Australian people and the Australian economy,</p>
<p>   simply because people run around saying, "Oh, we can't</p>
<p>   possibly have an election in which the native title issue is..."</p>
<p> SATTLER:</p>
<p>But Prime Minister, quite the contrary, surely the Australian people,</p>
<p>   who you quite rightly say now are fed up with this issue, it's</p>
<p>   been going on for years, surely they are now entitled to finally</p>
<p>   decide the issue?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Of course they are and I put yet another proposition to the Labor</p>
<p>   Party this morning, which I think offers them an honourable way</p>
<p>   out of this whole dilemma. I have said what the Senate should do</p>
<p>   is pass the Bill as presented by the Government. It will inevitably</p>
<p>   be challenged in the High Court. The Government will pay in full</p>
<p>   for any High Court challenge, we will fund the High Court challenge</p>
<p>   to our own legislation and we will ask the High Court in the normal</p>
<p>   correct fashion - that's for the High Court to decide, we will</p>
<p>   ask the High Court to expedite the hearing of a constitutional challenge</p>
<p>   to our legislation.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>Okay. But I also make this point. Isn't it the Australian</p>
<p>   electorate that should have the overriding say on this?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Of course it should be. I mean...</p>
<p> SATTLER:</p>
<p>I mean, not the High Court?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well the High Court has a right to determine the constitutionality</p>
<p>   of anything and the point of funding a High Court challenge, Howard,</p>
<p>   is that one of the objections that the Labor Party has had to our</p>
<p>   Bill is that they argue that it's unconstitutional. Now if</p>
<p>   they argue it's unconstitutional, well let that issue be resolved,</p>
<p>   but...</p>
<p> SATTLER:</p>
<p>You must be pretty confident you'd win in the court then?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>We are confident but you never know. But I have to accept that.</p>
<p>   I'm a citizen of Australia and I have no greater rights in</p>
<p>   relation to the constitutionality of things than the next person,</p>
<p>   but I am perfectly happy for the constitutionality of the Bill to</p>
<p>   be determined by the High Court. But look, we are the Government.</p>
<p>   We...</p>
<p> SATTLER:</p>
<p>Exactly.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>When we went to the people at the last election, one of our policies</p>
<p>   was to amend the Native Title Act to make it more workable. We then</p>
<p>   were given this Wik decision that went much further than anybody,</p>
<p>   including Mr Keating and many Aboriginal leaders expected...</p>
<p> SATTLER:</p>
<p>That's right. Now we are surely entitled to vote on your response</p>
<p>   to that.</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look, the Australian people are entitled to have the response of</p>
<p>   the Government they elected two years ago on that issue and that</p>
<p>   is what I have been endeavouring to do. But because I don't</p>
<p>   have a majority in the Senate, we have had this intolerable delay.</p>
<p>   Now at the end of the day, if the Senate does not pass the legislation,</p>
<p>   well, it will be grounds for a double dissolution and the Australian</p>
<p>   people - as should be the case in a democracy - will ultimately...</p>
<p>SATTLER</p>
<p>Well if they don't pass it, I mean, you're not going</p>
<p>   to hang around waiting for, you know, time to just go by are you?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look, I'm not going to speculate on yours or any other program</p>
<p>   as to when the election might be. I simply say that if they don't</p>
<p>   pass it, it becomes a potential trigger, a trigger for a potential</p>
<p>   double dissolution, because the only way I can change the law, and</p>
<p>   the Government can change the law, in accordance with our election</p>
<p>   undertaking if they don't pass it, is to have a double dissolution.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>Now are you worried that some of these remarks, which we've</p>
<p>   been talking about this morning, which are quite extreme - I don't</p>
<p>   mind saying that - are going to possibly incite violence in the</p>
<p>   community, and especially around an election? I mean, they are pretty...they're</p>
<p>   baiting people, aren't they?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well they are baseless, provocative, quite irresponsible remarks,</p>
<p>   and for a former foreign minister, it is doubly reprehensible.</p>
<p>SATTLER</p>
<p>Well I notice your Foreign Affairs Minister this morning says that</p>
<p>   this is going to damage our international image.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well that kind of language is always counter-productive to the</p>
<p>   image, but we are a civilised, very democratic, very tolerant society,</p>
<p>   and part of that civilised, tolerant, democratic character is that</p>
<p>   people in public office should use restraint in the language.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>Now the other thing too - Hindmarsh Bridge - the people didn't</p>
<p>   like the decision there who wanted the High Court to vote, or if</p>
<p>   you like, give their determination in their favour. Now they say</p>
<p>   they're going to go to an international court on this and other</p>
<p>   native title issues. I mean, who is going to be ultimately running</p>
<p>   this country, someone overseas or you?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, we are. It's the Government who runs the country subject</p>
<p>   to the will of the people, and can I just say, there are no international</p>
<p>   courts that can tell us what to do in relation to native title issues</p>
<p>   and we certainly won't be taking instructions from any foreign,</p>
<p>   overseas, or other body external to Australia. The High Court has</p>
<p>   said the Hindmarsh Bridge legislation is lawful, it is constitutional.</p>
<p>   We always knew that, we always said that, and we have wasted millions</p>
<p>   and millions of dollars on this farce.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>Yeah, dead right about that. Have you been personally hurt by these</p>
<p>   racial insults?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I don't like them. I mean, I'm a pretty tough character,</p>
<p>   I don't like being...my family doesn't like it, my children</p>
<p>   don't like it, but you endure....</p>
<p>SATTLER</p>
<p>Have they said that to you, have they?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well not...they don't like any of these things, of course</p>
<p>   they don't, but they don't...you know, they're very</p>
<p>   sort of understanding that in politics these things happen..</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>But, I mean, they don't have people coming up in the street,</p>
<p>   or wherever they are, and saying "your Dad is a racist"</p>
<p>   - do they?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well look, I don't know. My kids are very supportive of, and</p>
<p>   protective towards me, and I'm not sort of asking for any sympathy.</p>
<p>   I accept that in politics there's a lot of give and take and</p>
<p>   I don't mind that. I am more concerned about the capacity of</p>
<p>   these sorts of remarks to inflame a difficult situation...</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>That's what I was talking about, that's the big worry</p>
<p>   isn't it, in an election where this would be a major issue?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Let's just say again - the irresponsible remarks so far have</p>
<p>   come from the other side, and I have made it very plain to my colleagues</p>
<p>   that I don't want any language of this kind used and if anything</p>
<p>   is said that shouldn't be said, I will jump on it. Now I ask</p>
<p>   Mr Beazley to apply the same standard, the same discipline, the</p>
<p>   same strength to his own side. He can't control his party on</p>
<p>   this issue. The tactics on native title have been run by Mr Melham</p>
<p>   and by Mr Evans. In the Senate you've got Senator Faulkner</p>
<p>   and Senator Ray running a separate agenda, and I mean, if he had</p>
<p>   any real strength, what he would do is call Gareth Evans in and</p>
<p>   say, look mate, you gaffed, we all know that, go out and apologise</p>
<p>   and let's get on with attacking the Government on policy issues.</p>
<p>   But you don't get that.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>All right Prime Minister, we'll leave you there, have a good</p>
<p>   weekend.</p>
<p> ENDS</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
