<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11329</transcript-id>
    <title>15 March 1999                                                  TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                 THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                 ADDRESS AT THE NEW SOUTH WALES LIBERALS&amp;#146;                 CORPORATE LUNCH                 ANA HOTEL, SYDNEY</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/03/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE....................................................................................................</p>
<p>Well thank you very much Michael. Only seems like yesterday that I</p>
<p> was at this podium leading up to an event in October and it was a</p>
<p> great event. It was a great outcome. Pretty sound decision by the</p>
<p> Australian people. And it's a great delight for me to be here</p>
<p> today to say a few words in support of somebody I've known for</p>
<p> a long time, and I admire immensely, and who I believe has the intelligence</p>
<p> and the character and the values to be a very fine Premier of New</p>
<p> South Wales.</p>
<p>A few days ago I was talking to somebody and he said: John, tell me</p>
<p> why we should change the government in New South Wales? You blokes</p>
<p> are doing a very good job of running the economy nationally. I said</p>
<p> that I agreed with that. And he said: that's flowing through</p>
<p> so why would we change the government in New South Wales? And I said</p>
<p> to him that the reason that we should change the government in New</p>
<p> South Wales was that in a nation like Australia of federation where</p>
<p> responsibilities are divided between the national government and the</p>
<p> various State governments, no matter how good the Federal government</p>
<p> was, unless its deeds and its leadership were matched at a State level</p>
<p> by purposeful State governments then the kind of long term changes</p>
<p> and improvements that we all think are necessary would not be realised.</p>
<p> And reality is that there are tremendously important on going responsibilities</p>
<p> at a State level that are important to the well being of a society.</p>
<p> Indeed the things that touch the [inaudible] of our lives. The strength</p>
<p> of the policing services, safety in the home, safety on the streets,</p>
<p> safety on trains late at night, the quality of our government schools,</p>
<p> the quality of our hospitals.</p>
<p>All of those things are overwhelmingly the responsibility of State</p>
<p> governments. And it's also the responsibility of State governments</p>
<p> to run their economies well. They can't leave it all to the Federal</p>
<p> government. And you need the combination of the two. And you need</p>
<p> State governments that are prepared to tackle head on the difficult</p>
<p> issues that confront State governments.</p>
<p>And the reason why undoubtedly in my mind the best run State government</p>
<p> in Australia at present, that is the Kennett Government in Victoria,</p>
<p> the reason that is so successful is that it's had the courage</p>
<p> since it was elected in 1992 to tackle issues that are important to</p>
<p> that State and which can't be solved by the Federal government.</p>
<p> They've tackled the problem of State debt, and they've done</p>
<p> so by recognising that governments are no longer good in the modern</p>
<p> age at running business enterprises. And that if governments get out</p>
<p> of those business enterprises and sell interest in them to the ordinary</p>
<p> public and the ordinary consumer, there are dividends and improvements</p>
<p> all round and there is the wherewithal the cash to pay for much needed</p>
<p> government infrastructure and much needed provision for hospitals</p>
<p> and schools and all the other things that are important.</p>
<p>And my first and greatest criticism of the present New South Wales</p>
<p> Government is that it has really not tackled any of those fundamental</p>
<p> issues. We all know that Mr Carr and Mr Egan for two-and-a-half years</p>
<p> told us that the only thing that really mattered was the privatisation</p>
<p> of New South Wales's power industry. And you all know that in</p>
<p> the end that got rolled over, big time by the unions who told them</p>
<p> it simply wasn't on. And instead of standing up and continuing</p>
<p> to fight for what they believed was in the long term interest of the</p>
<p> State, they simply went over into a corner and wimped it and now have</p>
<p> the audacity to criticise the Coalition for committing itself to something</p>
<p> which they themselves know in their hearts is the right thing to do.</p>
<p> And just as Mr Beazley opposed something at the last Federal election</p>
<p> that he knew in his heart was needed and necessary and which he supported</p>
<p> when he was a member of the Hawke and Keating Governments, so it is</p>
<p> the case that Mr Carr and Mr Egan are opposing something that they</p>
<p> know deep down is needed in the long term interests, not only of electricity</p>
<p> generation in this State but also in the interests of getting rid</p>
<p> of $18.5 billion of State debt.</p>
<p>And of course to make matters worse we now have the New South Wales</p>
<p> Government quite literally claiming credit for the strength of the</p>
<p> New South Wales economy. They're running around saying: oh the</p>
<p> economy in New South Wales is getting better. It is getting better</p>
<p> but it's getting better off the back of the leadership that we</p>
<p> have shown at a Federal level. And it's getting better in spite</p>
<p> of the course of Mr Carr, because Mr Carr along with Mr Beazley and</p>
<p> other Labor leaders around Australia have opposed all of the major</p>
<p> reforms that the Coalition Government has carried out federally since</p>
<p> we came to power in 1996. They opposed every attempt we made to get</p>
<p> rid of Mr Beazley's deficit of $10.5 billion. They opposed industrial</p>
<p> relations reform. When we set about reforming the Australian waterfront,</p>
<p> [inaudible] stop that reform. He wasn't putting up his hand in</p>
<p> favour of reform. When we introduced taxation reform he opposed it.</p>
<p> Through his public service he has sought to obstruct the spread of</p>
<p> the Work For The Dole scheme through public enterprises in New South</p>
<p> Wales. He has tried to obstruct microeconomic reform in this State</p>
<p> prompted at a national level.</p>
<p>At every turn you have a Labor Government in New South Wales being</p>
<p> uncooperative in trying to obstruct the flow through of national economic</p>
<p> reform and national economic leadership. And yet for the purposes</p>
<p> of this election campaign he sets, as I said yesterday, to bask in</p>
<p> the sunlight of the strong economic conditions created by the very</p>
<p> policies that he with Mr Beazley have opposed since March of 1996.</p>
<p>He talks about the 4% unemployment rate. A mission impossible in this</p>
<p> State with the sort of policies that he espouses and the policies</p>
<p> that he supports. I'm very proud of the fact that the Australian</p>
<p> economy is now the strongest it has been for a quarter of a century.</p>
<p> I'm very proud of the fact that we have delivered the lowest</p>
<p> interest rates in 30 years, we have delivered the lowest inflation</p>
<p> in decades. We are seen throughout the world as having come through</p>
<p> the Asian economic downturn in remarkably strong shape. I'm proud</p>
<p> of that and all Australians should be proud of it but I want to make</p>
<p> it very clear that all of that has been done with virtually no help,</p>
<p> no cooperation and no understanding from Labor either at a Federal</p>
<p> level or at a State level.</p>
<p>It may be a political game to always oppose what your opponents do.</p>
<p> It may make good short term politics. But in the long run you do get</p>
<p> marks from the Australian people for quality policies, for quality</p>
<p> attitudes and for quality government. We won the last Federal election</p>
<p> because we had a plan for Australia's future. We won the last</p>
<p> Federal election because people felt deep down that we were addressing</p>
<p> something that needed to be addressed. And we will go on winning elections</p>
<p> nationally if we continue to espouse that philosophy. And the reason</p>
<p> why Federal Labor is worried at present and is looking more and more</p>
<p> lacking in policy vision is that it played politics for three years.</p>
<p> May have scored a few short term points, may have embarrassed us on</p>
<p> various occasions. But in the end the Australian people decided to</p>
<p> stay with us because they thought we were tackling the things that</p>
<p> really mattered as far as Australia was concerned. And that's</p>
<p> the test. And that's the test that I want the people of New South</p>
<p> Wales to apply over the next two weeks.</p>
<p>And Rod McGeoch was absolutely right when he said that this election</p>
<p> campaign has only really begun in the last 48 hours. People don't</p>
<p> engage quickly in the lead up to election campaigns. They engage even</p>
<p> less quickly in the lead up in to State election campaigns than they</p>
<p> do to Federal ones. Now what happens over the next two weeks will</p>
<p> decide whether we have a Coalition Government led by Kerry Chikarovski,</p>
<p> or we continue with the Labor Government that is prepared to ride</p>
<p> on our coat tails when it suits them but is not prepared to give any</p>
<p> kind of political support to what we're doing that's delivered</p>
<p> those conditions.</p>
<p>Kerry's team does have a plan. We do need to privatise the electricity</p>
<p> generation system because only by doing that will be able to pay off</p>
<p> $18.5 billion of public debt and give ourselves as a State the resources</p>
<p> to do other things. And she does have a plan in relation to so many</p>
<p> other issues.</p>
<p>And I want to say as a friend and supporter of hers for a long time,</p>
<p> I admire her greatly. I think she has enormous style, intelligence</p>
<p> and grit and determination. I think she represents a directness of</p>
<p> speech, she represents a directness of attitude and a concern with</p>
<p> the interests and the aspirations and the hopes of what one might</p>
<p> loosely call the mainstream of this State. I think she's not</p>
<p> only a very fine leader of the Coalition, I think she'll make</p>
<p> an extremely fine Premier of New South Wales. Will you please welcome</p>
<p> Kerry Chikarovski.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
