<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4648</transcript-id>
    <title>MEETING WITH WORLD WILDLIFE FUND OFFICIALS, 17 MARCH 1978</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/03/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004648.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS 17 MARCH 1978<br />
MEETING WITH WORLD WILDLIFE FUND OFFICIALS<br />
Today I met with Mr. Charles de Haes, Director-General of<br />
World Wildlife Fund and Mr. David Ogilvy, a Trustee and<br />
Executive Council Member of World Wildlife Fund International.<br />
I am delighted that World Wildlife Fund has responded so<br />
positively to the suggestion that it should establish a branch<br />
in Australia.<br />
The possibility of such a move was discussed with Sir Peter Scott,<br />
the Chairman of World Wildlife Fund International, during my<br />
visit to London last year.<br />
There is wide recognition of the need for World Wildlife Fund<br />
to begin operating here. This is because Australia has some of<br />
the world's most remarkable animals and plants, many of which<br />
are endangered, or confined to limited areas because of changes<br />
in land use.<br />
It is now accepted that an essential ingredient in national and<br />
international action to save these species from becoming extinct<br />
is money for research, for management, and for the purchase<br />
of essential habitat.<br />
World Wildlife Fund has a proven record as an internationally<br />
successful fund-raising organization for conservation action<br />
which relies on sound business principles in its operations,<br />
World Wildlife Fund is not only concerned with fund-raising,<br />
however, but with ensuring that the money is spent effectively.<br />
It.-works largely by co-operation with other conservation<br />
organizations, often on a shared-cost basis.<br />
I am advised that funds raised in Australia will be overwhelmingly<br />
spent on projects in Australia especially in the early years.<br />
Contributions to the Australian branch of the fund will be made<br />
tax deductible.<br />
There is an important role for Australian business in practical<br />
action to achieve wildlife conservation through support for<br />
World Wildlife Fund.<br />
Environment and Conservation are so important that business<br />
cannot afford to ignore them.<br />
After Mr. de Haes concludes his round of visits next week, he will<br />
again confer with Sir Noel Foley, Chairman designate of World<br />
Wildlife Fund Australia, when final decisions about the launching<br />
of the Fund in Australia will be taken. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
