<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11498</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER            THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP            RADIO INTERVIEW WITH NEIL MITCHELL, 3AW                     </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/03/2000</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Subjects: Life Education; drug testing; Telstra; welfare; GST; Pauline</p>
<p> Hanson; overseas trip; meeting with Yasser Arafat; 36-hour week; Melbourne</p>
<p> Grand Prix;</p>
<p>E&amp;OE .................................................................................</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p> Good morning, straight to it today, there is a great</p>
<p> deal of ground to cover. With me in the studio, the Prime Minister. Mr</p>
<p> Howard good morning.</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p> Good morning Neil.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p> Is it fair if a GST is to be applied to drug education</p>
<p> for children?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p> Well I understand this arises out of a concern expressed</p>
<p> by Mr Metherell.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p> Life Education, yes.</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p> Life Education. Well I've actually had that checked</p>
<p> out and the advice I have is that, this is the Tax Office's advice,</p>
<p> it is not a prime ministerial ruling. The advice is after discussion between</p>
<p> Mr Metherell, Dr Metherell and the Tax Office, that this particular service</p>
<p> almost certainly won't be subject to the GST. There was inadequate</p>
<p> information provided in the earlier contacts and now that there has been</p>
<p> a contact between, a renewed one between the Tax Office and Dr Metherell,</p>
<p> he is a lot happier and that appears to be the situation.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p> OK. As a point of principle, it is reasonable though</p>
<p> isn't it, if we are going provide drug education for kids we shouldn't</p>
<p> put a GST on it.</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p> Of course it is.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p> And it is a charity . . .</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p> Yes, of course.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p> And education.</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p> I am sorry the doubt arose in the first place. But when</p>
<p> you are introducing something new like this I never pretended that you</p>
<p> won't have a few implementation challenges and it is the role of</p>
<p> the Government and the Tax Office in particular to be available and to</p>
<p> be helpful and to be patient and to be understanding. It is equally I</p>
<p> guess the role of the community to understand just for a moment that anything</p>
<p> big like this is going to involve a few periods of time where we're</p>
<p> working things out and it may take a bit longer than the first attempt</p>
<p> to get the absolutely correct answer.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p> Anyway, it's fixed.</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p> It's fixed.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p> This is related. Would you agree to be drug tested?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p> Well, there's been no suggestion made that I should</p>
<p> be.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p> Well Brian Watters was suggesting that . . .</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p> Well he was suggesting...he said he was going to raise</p>
<p> it with his drug council and I am quite sure . . .</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p> What do you think of drug testing politicians?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p> I don't myself see any need for it and I don't</p>
<p> think he did.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p> No, but he was suggesting that bureaucrats who are driving</p>
<p> the policy were doing so because they were regular recreational drug users.</p>
<p> Should we be testing the bureaucrats?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p> Well that is a hypothetical question, nobody's put</p>
<p> it to me. Look I have a strong view about drugs, but I tend to take a</p>
<p> positive view of the motives of people, unless it's demonstrated</p>
<p> otherwise to me. I assume that when a bureaucrat says to me, I think the</p>
<p> Government ought to do this, that that person believes in it, it is not</p>
<p> driven by any personal agenda. Although I guess in some cases, I am not</p>
<p> talking about the drug issue, but generally, it is. And the same applies</p>
<p> with my colleagues. I'm not into sort of detailed introspection of</p>
<p> the personal behavior of my colleagues, that is of no great concern to</p>
<p> me. If people do their jobs correctly, you try and judge people on their</p>
<p> merits.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p> Mr Howard, welfare. This story seems to get worse. Figures</p>
<p> today, I think $41 billion, 41.36 billion we paid 98/99. 140,000</p>
<p> Victorians on disability pensions. What can you do about it? Can you get</p>
<p> that bill down?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p> Well as a proportion of our national wealth, it's</p>
<p> not growing out of control. I mean we can't have it both ways, we</p>
<p> can't be a caring society that looks after people who really need</p>
<p> help, but on the other hand complain about the size of the welfare bill.</p>
<p> We are having an examination into the operation of welfare system and</p>
<p> Senator Newman will be releasing quite soon the draft paper prepared by</p>
<p> the reference group, headed by Mr McLure of Mission Australia. And it's</p>
<p> going to look at ways in which we can reform the welfare system which</p>
<p> are consistent with maintaining a strong, social security safety net.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p> Is the aim though to get that figure down? 41.36 billion?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p> No the aim is to have a system that is fair and affordable.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p> Is 41 billion affordable?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p> Well it depends what proportion that 41 billion is of</p>
<p> the total national wealth. And government spending as a proportion of</p>
<p> national wealth is lower now than what it was four years ago.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p> Ok, so you're comfortable . . .</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p> So, it is always a mistake to look at the absolute figures,</p>
<p> you have to look at them as proportion of our national wealth. Obviously</p>
<p> the amount we spend on welfare in dollar terms is going to rise every</p>
<p> year because incomes are rising and populations are rising. That's</p>
<p> axiomatic. It is a question of whether it is growing out of all proportion</p>
<p> to the rise in our national wealth, and the answer to that is no it is</p>
<p> not. That doesn't mean to say we can't tighten it, we have tightened</p>
<p> it. And things like work for the dole ensure that people are less likely</p>
<p> to abuse the welfare system than was previously the case. We are saving</p>
<p> millions of dollars a day in the social security area with the crackdowns</p>
<p> that we do have. It's once again a question of getting a balance,</p>
<p> we want to help the needy, but we don't want the system abused because</p>
<p> you and I pay for the abuse.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p> True, but there seem to be so many people affected here.</p>
<p> We've got what a million people in Australia getting parenting payments.</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p> Yeah, but parenting payments used to take the form, years</p>
<p> and years ago, those parenting payments used to take the form of tax concessions</p>
<p> for having children. Now we still have tax concessions for having children,</p>
<p> we have converted it to the spending side of the budget. They're</p>
<p> not really welfare payments, they're just a recognition that a parent</p>
<p> at home looking after a child is entitled to some financial help and I</p>
<p> think that parent is. That's not really a welfare payment.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p> 71 . . .</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p> Unless we take the view as a society that people should</p>
<p> be given no financial reward or assistance for having children. Now I</p>
<p> think that would be a very blinkered view to take of our community.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p> $71 million in social security benefits paid to people</p>
<p> living overseas. Is that appropriate?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p> Well if people have contributed to the tax system all</p>
<p> their lives, we expect, and we're having a heavy negotiation with</p>
<p> the British Government at the moment to make sure that the British Government</p>
<p> pays in full their obligations to people who were born in the United Kingdom</p>
<p> and contributed to their pension funds, while they lived in the United</p>
<p> Kingdom before they emigrated to Australia. Now we're having a lot</p>
<p> of trouble with the British Government over that. But we're arguing</p>
<p> the principle that if you earn an entitlement in country A and you go</p>
<p> to another country, you're entitled to take that with you. Now you</p>
<p> don't get a pension entitlement in this country until you've</p>
<p> been here a number of years. And if you've made a contribution to</p>
<p> your taxes and you go and live elsewhere there is an argument that you</p>
<p> should be entitled to have them. And some people argue that you shouldn't.</p>
<p> It is an interesting debate. I think there is merit on both sides. But</p>
<p> I can understand that if a person has worked in this country for forty</p>
<p> years and contributed to taxes they might feel they can take some of that</p>
<p> entitlement with them.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p> So you don't feel the system is generally being</p>
<p> rorted?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p> No, I think you always have to be vigilant, and you always</p>
<p> have to be willing to tighten where abuse occurs. But I think we have</p>
<p> a welfare system which does provide a social security safety net, but</p>
<p> it's not an open slather. We are tightening it. Work for the Dole</p>
<p> is a good example of that. Where we're basically saying to people,</p>
<p> yes we'll look after you, we'll give you sustenance, we won't</p>
<p> allow you to starve on the streets as sometimes happens in the United</p>
<p> States. But we will ask you to put something back into the community by</p>
<p> way of working for your unemployment benefit. I think that is a fair balance.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>We will take calls for the Prime Minister in a moment, 9696 1278. Telstra</p>
<p> Prime Minister seems to be a lot of energy going into worrying about the</p>
<p> bush. What about the city? It's not working properly in the city</p>
<p> is it?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well you say it's not working properly. It's not perfect but</p>
<p> it's a very good telecommunications system. And can I say it's</p>
<p> a very good telecommunications system in many parts of the bush too. Many</p>
<p> parts of regional Australia have very high quality telecommunications</p>
<p> facilities, just as good as they are in the city. It's not perfect</p>
<p> in the city but.....</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Well how do we fix it in the city? We're getting complaints....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well when you say how do we fix it, I mean you will never have a perfect</p>
<p> system but any fair examination of the service delivery performance of</p>
<p> Telstra will show you that over the last few years it has improved quite</p>
<p> dramatically.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>But by definition they make big profits, they sack people or they drop</p>
<p> their numbers, they cut their staff. That has to affect service.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No not necessarily because some of those....look, of all the areas</p>
<p> of our economy more than any, information technology is one where technology</p>
<p> can do things that people previously did.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>That's true.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>But interestingly enough though it's also the fastest growing area</p>
<p> of employment in our economy.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Not Telstra [inaudible].</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No no. But this is a very important point to make that many of the people</p>
<p> who've lost their jobs in Telstra, many of them, something like 88%</p>
<p> have found jobs elsewhere in communications.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Yeah but now they're going to what, drop another 16,000. I think</p>
<p> six of those are going.....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well let me give you an analogy with the steel industry. There are fewer</p>
<p> people employed in the steel industry in Australia now than 25 years ago.</p>
<p> But nobody can say that that industry is necessarily less efficient.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>But I think that's the point. People are saying to me that this</p>
<p> industry is less efficient. They don't.....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well they may [inaudible]. Well I have to say in reply to them that although</p>
<p> I'm not arguing it's a perfect system, things are and people</p>
<p> frequently say this to me and it's borne out by surveys, people do</p>
<p> get quicker service than used to be the case. That's not to say everybody</p>
<p> is happy and I acknowledge there'll be people listening to me now</p>
<p> who will say he doesn't know what a problem I had with my phone.</p>
<p> And let me say to those people, hypothetical people, I do know that some</p>
<p> of you are still having trouble but there are fewer of you having trouble</p>
<p> now than was the case five or ten years ago. And certainly when this was</p>
<p> fully owned by the Government it wasn't more efficient. It was a</p>
<p> lot less efficient. I mean the really bad old days of telephone breakdowns</p>
<p> and long delays and so forth was at a time when the old Telecom was fully</p>
<p> owned by the government, fully owned. And they were retrenching people</p>
<p> then and the service was worse than what it is now.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>But a six-week delay on having a business line put in is unacceptable</p>
<p> isn't it?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes it is. And when that happens....and there are penalties being</p>
<p> applied under the law to Telstra where that occurs. But those examples</p>
<p> are fewer now than what they were five or ten years ago. That is the point</p>
<p> I make.</p>
<p>[commercial break]</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>I have more questions for the Prime Minister but some calls first. John</p>
<p> go ahead please.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>Yes good morning Neil and good morning Mr Howard. Look, just a quick</p>
<p> question to Mr Howard. For years I thought it was wrong to rip in and</p>
<p> [inaudible] people in for abusing the social security system and it got</p>
<p> to a stage that I just got so sick of it that I thought I'd do something</p>
<p> for a change. I rang up, and I did, I dobbed in a cheat and I told them</p>
<p> about some people that are actually on social security and working full</p>
<p> time. And you know, it upset me, I work, I pay my taxes like anybody else.</p>
<p> And you know, six months down the track and this one person, this particular</p>
<p> person, is still working and still receiving social security [inaudible].</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well if you are prepared off air to provide that information to the station</p>
<p> and you provide it to my office I'll have that investigated.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Hold on John. Do you think people should dob in social security cheats?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I see no reason why they shouldn't. I mean I know there's always</p>
<p> a tension here between the sort of the Australian unwillingness to do</p>
<p> it but on the other hand there's a rising resentment amongst working</p>
<p> people and John's a good example. He works hard, he pays his taxes,</p>
<p> he's honest. Why should he have to pay for the bloke next door who's</p>
<p> the opposite and I can understand his anger.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>It's really theft isn't it from the taxpayer.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well it is. And the point you've got to understand is that it's</p>
<p> affecting all of your listeners. There's no such thing as a government</p>
<p> that's separate and apart from the community. When we make decisions</p>
<p> we're not spending our money, we're spending your money. And</p>
<p> when people cheat on the social security system they are robbing you,</p>
<p> they're not robbing quote  the government.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Do we know how extensive that cheating is though, how much of the $41</p>
<p> billion is cheating?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Less than it used to be because it's tougher to cheat now. I can't</p>
<p> put an exact figure on it. It's a certain percentage. It's not</p>
<p> a major percentage but there is an element of it and there is an attitude</p>
<p> in the community amongst some that it's alright to cheat the government</p>
<p> because it doesn't hurt anybody, but it does. It hurts their neighbour,</p>
<p> it hurts their relatives, it hurts the bloke they have a drink with at</p>
<p> the club or the pub. So you know, people should remember that and they</p>
<p> shouldn't be so reluctant to report incidents of abuse.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Roger, go ahead please.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>Good morning Mr Howard and Neil. Thank you very much Mr Howard for following</p>
<p> up the GST situation with the life education. That's excellent. But</p>
<p> I have one question. Dr Metherell mentioned yesterday that there was a</p>
<p> government grant from Victoria. Would that be subject to GST as well?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Government grants generally speaking aren't.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Okay, thanks for that. Thanks Roger. Another thing that was raised while</p>
<p> I think about it is that corporate grants or corporate donations to charities</p>
<p> would pay a GST if that corporate organisation got anything in return.</p>
<p> So for example....is that right?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yeah well that's a commercial sort of transaction. It depends if</p>
<p> there's sort of.....depends on whether there's significant</p>
<p> commercial return. But if it's a sort of a bare acknowledgement then</p>
<p> no but if it's a significant corporate return then not.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>And who determines that, the tax office?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yeah.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Leslie, go ahead please.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>Good morning Neil, good morning Mr Howard. I represent the Debater's</p>
<p> Association of Victoria and I'm very pleased for life education that</p>
<p> they are going to receive their exemption. But my concern is what about</p>
<p> other small non-profit organisations who are providing ancillary services</p>
<p> to schools?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well what I suggest you do is put your information together and go and</p>
<p> talk to somebody in the tax office. If you have any trouble at all getting</p>
<p> a response will you ring my office and we'll put you in touch with</p>
<p> the taxation unit. Rather than my trying to give you a ruling, and I can't</p>
<p> give those, I'm only a Prime Minister, I leave those things, high</p>
<p> and mighty things to others. But rather than my try and give you a ruling</p>
<p> without knowing all of the information because I might mislead you.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>What tax do you [inaudible] paying under the GST Leslie, what will you</p>
<p> be paying?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well our concern is that our members' schools will have to factor</p>
<p> in a 10% GST on their registration and that that may actually exclude</p>
<p> many children from being able to [inaudible].</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yeah, look I don't think that will occur. But because you may have</p>
<p> in mind the services you provide as well as the registration fees and</p>
<p> so forth, why don't you just get all of your information and talk</p>
<p> to the tax office. And if you're unhappy about the adequacy of the</p>
<p> response let us know.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Thank you Leslie. Prime Minister, Pauline Hanson. Would you like to see</p>
<p> the end of her in politics?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well that's a matter for the public but I think she did receive</p>
<p> the dismissal notice of her electorate at the last election.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>But if she doesn't come up with $500,000 by five o'clock today</p>
<p> she could be bankrupted.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I don't want to comment on her pending bankruptcy. I think</p>
<p> there's a possibility of a legal appeal and I don't think it</p>
<p> really helps for me to be giving....making a gratuitous running commentary.</p>
<p> But there are electoral laws and we've all got to comply with them.</p>
<p> The Liberal Party and the Labor Party are often pursued by the electoral</p>
<p> commission if there is any technical breach. Members of Parliament have</p>
<p> got to obey the law. We are all subject to the law and that applies to</p>
<p> her like anybody else.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, you are off overseas soon.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes I am going to the opening, I am going to open with the New Zealand</p>
<p> Prime Minister the new memorial on ANZAC Cove. We've had to build</p>
<p> a larger one in a slightly different area because there are now so many</p>
<p> young Australians and New Zealanders visiting ANZAC Cove, not only on</p>
<p> ANZAC day but other times of the year that literally the old memorial</p>
<p> and the area around it was too small. I will be there on ANZAC day this</p>
<p> year and then I will go on to France and when I am in France, I will spend</p>
<p> a half a day visiting the battle fields of the Somme, from World War I.</p>
<p> And I will be coming back through Israel and I hope that when I am in</p>
<p> Israel as well as naturally meeting the Israeli Prime Minister I will</p>
<p> talk to the Palestinian leader Yasser Arafat. I think all of us hope that</p>
<p> we're inching towards a lasting peace settlement in the middle east.</p>
<p> As somebody who has always been a staunch supporter of the cause of the</p>
<p> Israelies and Israel's independence and territorial integrity I none</p>
<p> the less recognise the aspirations and rights of the Palestinians and</p>
<p> if we can have peace in that part of the world it would be a huge relief</p>
<p> to many people.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>What would be the purpose of you meeting with Yasser Arafat?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I think it's important that one as well as saluting and acknowledging</p>
<p> the success of the Jewish State, I think it is very important to also</p>
<p> understand the Palestinian point of view and let us remember that Israel</p>
<p> and the Palestines are now talking to each other in a very effective way</p>
<p> and the Israeli Prime Minister is, I am sure, keen that any foreign visitor</p>
<p> to his country also have the opportunity of meeting the Palestinian leader.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>I would have thought that their would be a significant lobby in this</p>
<p> country that wouldn't approve of the meeting with Yasser Arafat.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>That's true and perhaps on an earlier occasion I might not have</p>
<p> done so.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>What has changed your mind?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>The fact that the peace movement is gathering strength.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>That doesn't remove the terrorist background.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, no but there are a lot of people who on occasions you might meet</p>
<p> who have had a terrorist background. There are a lot of leaders in the</p>
<p> world that we meet that have had a terrorist background.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Yes, certainly, so..</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Its difficult isn't it. You have got to make a judgement call on</p>
<p> each and the judgement call I have made on this is that because Israel</p>
<p> herself is talking to the Palestinians and if you are in the middle east,</p>
<p> it is perhaps insensitive to the desire of many Palestinians for a place</p>
<p> in the sun to ignore them.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Would you expect a backlash at home?</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
