<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>12728</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER    THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP            DOORSTOP INTERVIEW, BRISBANE                </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/09/2002</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Subjects: Iraq; Queensland Liberals; sugar industry; Bob Katter; Lynton Crosby</p>
<p>E&amp;OE...........</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, can you resolve the fighting in the Queensland Liberals here?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well the Queensland Liberals federally have been quite outstanding.  They delivered all the seats we held at the last election and won back two at a federal level in the Liberal Party in Queensland is very good shape.  They have some challenges at a state level and I believe that different people are working through differences at a state level.  I hope a more positive outlook emerges.  But Federally, the party here in Queensland is in excellent shape.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Challenges is a bit of a nice way to put, isn't it?  They're faction riven, aren't they?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>You heard my answer.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Is Bob Quinn the man to lead the Queensland Liberals?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh look, Bob is a good bloke and he has my support.  The parliamentary leaders are chosen by parliamentary parties.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>When will you tell the Australian people what the intelligence is on Iraq?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, what I've said is that if we were to be requested by the United States and we were to commit ourselves, then I would fully explain and defend and justify that decision.  There will be a parliamentary debate and consistent with protecting intelligence sources, which you must always do, we'd provide all the information we could.  But that situation is some time off, if it arises.  So, we're dealing in a very hypothetical situation.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do you think you'd get Australian support to commit troops?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look, I'm not going to hypothesise in advance about something that has not happened.  I repeat that if we were to receive a request then we would consider it against Australia's national interest and if we were to respond, then I accept the responsibility to explain and defend that decision.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Bob Katter said that he's got no doubt the Federal Government is going to go ahead with total deregulation of the sugar industry in Queensland, he says the Government's already made up its mind.  Is that case?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, what the Government will do is to try and provide support to the Queensland sugar industry that is fair to the Australian taxpayer, recognises the difficulties of the industry and the social importance of that industry to Queensland and also involves reform of the industry, at this stage it';s pointless talking in general terms like deregulation – it's too early, except for me to say that if we are to have a proper settlement of this issue and provide some long term security to the industry, some difficult decisions have to be made and there has to be a willingness on the part of the industry to accept structural change.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Queensland Liberal President Michael Caltabiano said that had spoken to him.  What was your advice to him about the Queensland Liberals?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look, I have numerous discussions with State Presidents.  Of course I speak to them…</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>But he said you spoke to him about the convention?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I don't talk about conversations I have with divisional Presidents on internal party matters.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Lynton Crosby described the Queensland Liberals as moribund.  If they don't resolve their problems this weekend, is there much future for the State Liberals?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I've given you my answer.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, the US is talking about Australia being intimately involved in any war planning if it comes to that with Iraq. With such strong words I mean is it more on the agenda now, are you expected to hear, is there a timeline?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I have already a question on Iraq, I can only repeat what I';ve said earlier, I think the problem with answering a half a dozen questions is that you just go round and round in circles.  We have not received a request.  Because of our close alliance with the United States we';ve had people in the American military set up from the beginning of the War Against Terror, that means that we are abreast of American military thinking.  But in the end these things are determined by political decisions by elected leaders and no decision has been taken by the United States.  I could understand sentiment in that country, particularly as they approach the anniversary of September 11 they are reminded of the vulnerability of their country to attack and I think they are all things that are being taken into account.  But the Australian people should rest assured that we';ll take any decision on any request based on our assessment of Australia';s national interest.  That of course includes the need for the world to respond to threats that may produce instability and potential devastation.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>You';ve spoken of challenges for the Queensland Liberals, what do you see those challenges being?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>There';s always challenges for political parties.  Look the Queensland Liberal Party at a state level obviously has challenges, federally we';re in very good shape, I';ll be addressing the convention tomorrow.  I encourage people in the Liberal Party at a state level to work through their differences and if they do that they can become over time a more effective opposition. It is self-evident that Liberal and National Parties in Queensland are not a strong opposition at the moment, federally of course we';re doing very well here in Queensland, it';s one of the phenomena of Queensland politics, that it has people of Queensland have an engaging capacity which I certainly found very good last year to vote differently at a federal level than from a state level and I thank them for that and I recommit myself to serve the people of Queensland at a national level to the limit of my energy and capacities.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Should the Libs and Nats merge do you think?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look, merger is not the answer, that';s not answer.  Look we are in federal power as a coalition.  People who run around thinking that the miracle cure is to have a merger are not really facing the reality, the answer is inside the two parties, we found the answer federally, we work together.  We have some differences but we resolve them and there';s a place for everybody and some in the Federal Coalition.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Is there anything that Saddam is doing that is a direct threat to Australia from your intelligence understanding?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well any situation where somebody has, in the belief of many, weapons of mass destruction and a capacity to acquire nuclear capacity in time can become potentially a threat to all nations.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Has there been a winner take all attitude in some members of the Queensland Liberals?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look I';m not going to get into that kind of hypothetical psycho-analysis…</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Bob Katter says that if you don';t handle sugar correctly it will cost the National Party (inaudible).</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think you can rest assured and the people of those electorates can rest assured that sugar will be handled properly, properly handled sugar means not only looking after the interests of the people in the industry but also looking after the interests of the Australian taxpayer and there';s got to a balance of those two.  I am very committed to getting a fair package for the Queensland sugar industry, I know how important the industry is to this state and I will work very hard to get a fair package but that fair package has got to involve a state government, it will inevitably involve some legislative changes at a state level, it will inevitably involve some federal contribution, it will involve adjustment in the industry, it will involve some people exiting the industry because it';s no longer viable for them to remain.  There';s some tough decisions to be faced but if we can all make a contribution and I';m happy to work with the Queensland Government on this issue, this is not something for state political pointscoring and I won';t be in that game and I hope Mr Beattie';s not either.  But people have got to understand that if you commit taxpayer';s money their general interest has to be looked after as part of a package.</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
