<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>41210</transcript-id>
    <title>Radio interview with Cliffo and Loggy – HIT 103.1FM</title>
    <prime-minister>Turnbull, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20150915 - 20180824</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/09/2017</release-date>
    <release-type>Transcript</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects>NRL Grand Final; flights to the grand final; same-sex marriage; Townsville stadium</subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p><strong>LAUREN TEMUSKOS: </strong></p>
<p>We’ve got the top dog, he wants in, he’s waiting on the phone so let’s welcome him to our show, Prime Minister of Australia, Malcolm Turnbull.</p>
<p><strong>GUY CLIFTON:</strong></p>
<p>Hello Malcolm! Good morning!</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>G’day, good morning. Great to be with you. How excited are you guys?</p>
<p><strong>GUY CLIFTON:</strong></p>
<p>Oh mate.</p>
<p><strong>LAUREN TEMUSKOS: </strong></p>
<p>Oh Malcolm, I’m sweating all the time I’m so excited.</p>
<p><strong>GUY CLIFTON:</strong></p>
<p>The town is absolutely alive and I’m glad you bring the whole Cowboys into the Grand Final thing because you are a Roosters supporter, aren’t you Malcolm?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>I am, I am and I was heartbroken when they were knocked out of the competition by the Cowboys, but I am over that, I’ve got over that and I’ll be supporting the Cowboys, barracking for the Cowboys.</p>
<p><strong>GUY CLIFTON:</strong></p>
<p>Okay! You will be!</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>I will be yeah.</p>
<p><strong>GUY CLIFTON:</strong></p>
<p>We weren’t sure because after of course the Roosters got a plucking - and I’m saying plucking with a ‘p’ there - by the Cowboys, we thought you might be, you know ‘#TeamStorm’.</p>
<p>[Laughter]</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>#anyonebuttheteamthatgotmineoutofthecompetition</p>
<p><strong>LAUREN TEMUSKOS: </strong></p>
<p>Yeah, pretty much.</p>
<p><strong>GUY CLIFTON:</strong></p>
<p>Yeah, that’s right.</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>No I think, look, it is just an amazing Cinderella story isn’t it? I mean, no one gave you a chance. The Cowboys, were they eighth in the finals?</p>
<p><strong>GUY CLIFTON:</strong></p>
<p>Yeah, they were.</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>Yeah, so, what an extraordinary climb back and to do all of that without JT is amazing.</p>
<p><strong>LAUREN TEMUSKOS: </strong></p>
<p>Are you going to the Grand Final on Sunday?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>We’ll be there! I will be there.</p>
<p><strong>LAUREN TEMUSKOS: </strong></p>
<p>Okay, are you going to leave the baby and the beers at home, so there is no controversy?</p>
<p>[Laughter]</p>
<p><strong>GUY CLIFTON:</strong></p>
<p>Wasn’t that a storm in a teacup!</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>It’s a bit late for baby Alice. She’s better in the afternoon.</p>
<p><strong>GUY CLIFTON:</strong></p>
<p>While we are on the whole footy thing, what do you make of the airlines upping the airfares the moment the Cowboys got into the Grand Final?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>Yeah well look, I’ve heard about that, I’m concerned about it. I actually just put the phone down to Alan Joyce who is the Chief Executive of Qantas.</p>
<p><strong>GUY CLIFTON:</strong></p>
<p>Wow.</p>
<p><strong>LAUREN TEMUSKOS: </strong></p>
<p>Yes?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>Now Alan has said to me that they have put on some extra flights, some extra services and he is looking to put on some more. And I have encouraged him to do that.</p>
<p><strong>LAUREN TEMUSKOS: </strong></p>
<p>Good on you! Hey, can I just ask, I know, we know the President of the United States has Air Force One. What do you get around in Malcolm? Is it a new plane or is it like an old Ansett one or what is it?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>Well, John Key who is the former prime minister of New Zealand, nicknamed the Air Force plane that flies me around ‘Wombat One,’ which I think is a fantastic name.</p>
<p>[Laughter]</p>
<p>It’s a great name!</p>
<p><strong>LAUREN TEMUSKOS: </strong></p>
<p> ‘We are coming in now, Wombat One’.</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>Wombat One! Yeah, it must be about 10 or 12 years old. It’s a 737, it’s a Boeing Business Jet.</p>
<p><strong>GUY CLIFTON:</strong></p>
<p>Right.</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>And they’ve got a couple, they’ve got two of those.</p>
<p><strong>LAUREN TEMUSKOS: </strong></p>
<p>Cool.</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>And they mostly fly me and the Governor-General but they’re used for other purposes as well.</p>
<p><strong>LAUREN TEMUSKOS: </strong></p>
<p>Party planes!</p>
<p>[Laughter]</p>
<p><strong>GUY CLIFTON:</strong></p>
<p>Wombat One.</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>Hard work, all the time.</p>
<p><strong>GUY CLIFTON:</strong></p>
<p>They sound big and clunky and chunky don’t they? Wombat One.</p>
<p>Hey while we’ve got you on, we’ve been doing a lot of content of the show recently concerning same-sex marriage. The postal survey, it started a couple of weeks ago, how do you make, well what do you make of the survey so far Malcolm?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>Well Lucy and I support ‘yes’. We voted ‘yes’ in the survey and you know you would’ve seen me post it on Facebook, us actually posting the surveys back. So I encourage everyone to get their survey back. My impression is - and we’ll get some official figures early next week I believe – but my impression is that there’s been a very high turnout. You know, a lot of people said everyone will just throw it in the bin, they won’t participate. I think its going to be a very high turnout, particularly for a voluntary postal vote. It’s now in the hands of the Australian people, but I think that while there’ve been a few ugly incidents, overall the debate has been very respectful and that’s been good.</p>
<p><strong>LAUREN TEMUSKOS: </strong></p>
<p>Okay.</p>
<p><strong>GUY CLIFTON:</strong></p>
<p>And if it does come to pass and it passes through Parliament and all that, how long before same-sex couples will actually be married. Is it a pretty quick turnaround after that or?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>Let’s say it gets passed, it should be fairly, it should be very fast. I mean once a bill is passed through the parliament it’s simply a question of getting the Governor General to sign off on it. Whether a same-sex marriage could occur before Christmas I couldn’t say, but it will follow very rapidly. Once the people have spoken – assuming they say ‘yes’ of course that’s the big assumption – assuming that people say ‘yes’ Parliament will ensure that the will of the people is carried out rapidly.</p>
<p><strong>GUY CLIFTON:</strong></p>
<p>Alright.</p>
<p><strong>LAUREN TEMUSKOS: </strong></p>
<p>Alright, good to hear.</p>
<p><strong>GUY CLIFTON:</strong></p>
<p>Well we’ve learnt he’s voting ‘yes’, he flies around in Wombat One.</p>
<p><strong>LAUREN TEMUSKOS: </strong></p>
<p>Yes.</p>
<p><strong>GUY CLIFTON:</strong></p>
<p>Devastated the Roosters are out, but he is supporting the Cowboys.</p>
<p><strong>LAUREN TEMUSKOS: </strong></p>
<p>Good to know.</p>
<p><strong>GUY CLIFTON:</strong></p>
<p>So we like that.</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>And congratulations to Michael Morgan too, by the way.</p>
<p><strong>GUY CLIFTON:</strong></p>
<p>Yes!</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>Halfback of the year.</p>
<p><strong>GUY CLIFTON:</strong></p>
<p>Yeah, runner up for Dally M.</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>That’s right, so look it’ll be great and you know I was last up in Townsville with Gavin Cooper, you remember at the site of the new stadium which we’re funding $100 million into. I made my attempt of doing the marking the try line.</p>
<p>[Laughter]</p>
<p>Definitely indicating I should stick to my day job I think.</p>
<p><strong>LAUREN TEMUSKOS: </strong></p>
<p>That’s good.</p>
<p><strong>GUY CLIFTON:</strong></p>
<p>And that’s how Malcolm Turnbull got paint on his new shoes everyone.</p>
<p>[Laughter]</p>
<p>The Prime Minister of our country, Malcolm Turnbull, thank you so much for being so generous with your time, appreciate it. Go Cowboys!</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
<p><strong>[ENDS]</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
