<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3190</transcript-id>
    <title>GOVERNMENT AND BUSINESS</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/03/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003190.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO: 8.00PM THURSDAY 14 MARCH 1974<br />
GOVERNMENT AND BUSINESS<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER,<br />
THE HON. E. G. WHITLAM, M. P.,<br />
TO THE FIFTH NATIONAL CONFERENCE OF<br />
THE INSTITUTE OF DIRECTORS IN AUSTRALIA,<br />
WENTWORTH HOTEL, SYDNEY,<br />
14 MARCH 1974<br />
I HOPE YOU WILL NOT THINK IT TOO PROVOCATIVE OF ME<br />
IF I BEGIN MY ADDRESS TO THIS DISTINGUISHED COMPANY OF<br />
CAPITALISTS BY QUOTING THE COMMUNIST MANIFESTO.<br />
THE LAST TIME I SPOKE TO SUCH A LARGE AND POWERFUL<br />
GATHERING OF BUSINESSMEN WAS IN MELBOURNE LAST YEAR<br />
AT A SEMINAR WITH THE INTRIGUING TITLE OF " FUTURE SHOCK".<br />
I LEARNT MY LESSON ON THAT OCCASION: WHERE BUSINESSMEN<br />
ARE CONCERNED, IF YOU CAN'T BEAT ' EM, SHOCK ' EM.<br />
So I COMMEND TO YOU THE FOLLOWING QUOTATION </p>
<p>-2-<br />
THE BOURGEOISIE, DURING ITS RULE OF SCARCE ONE<br />
HUNDRED YEARS, HAS CREATED MORE MASSIVE AND MORE<br />
COLOSSAL PRODUCTIVE FORCES THAN HAVE ALL PRECEDING<br />
GENERATIONS TOGETHER, SUBJECTION OF NATURE'S<br />
FORCES TO MAN, MACHINERY, APPLICATION OF CHEMISTRY<br />
TO INDUSTRY AND AGRICULTURE, STEAM NAVIGATION,<br />
RAILWAYS, ELECTRIC TELEGRAPHS, CLEARING OF WHOLE<br />
CONTINENTS FOR CULTIVATION, CANALIZATION OF RIVERS,<br />
WHOLE POPULATIONS CONJURED OUT OF THE GROUND<br />
WHAT EARLIER CENTURY HAD EVEN A PRESENTIMENT THAT<br />
SUCH PRODUCTIVE FORCES SLUMBERED IN THE LAP OF<br />
SOCIAL LABOUR?<br />
THAT FINE TRIBUTE TO CAPITALISM WAS PAID BY MARX<br />
AND ENGELS OVER A CENTURY AGO. A SYSTEM THAT CAN EVOKE<br />
SUCH PRAISE FROM ITS WORST ENEMIES CANNOT BE TOO BAD.<br />
TODAY, VERY FEW OF US HAVE MUCH TIME FOR MARXIST THEORIES,<br />
BUT WE HAVE TO ADMIT THAT THE AUTHORS OF THOSE WORDS<br />
PERCEIVED VERY CLEARLY THE ENORMOUS POWER AND PRODUCTIVE<br />
POTENTIAL OF PRIVATE ENTERPRISE, AND OF COURSE THEIR<br />
REMARKS HAVE INFINITELY GREATER FORCE TODAY, SCIENCE AND<br />
TECHNOLOGY, HARNESSED AND DIRECTED BY PRIVATE CAPITAL,<br />
HAVE BEEN THE MAINSPRING OF ADVANCED WESTERN SOCIETY,<br />
WITH ALL ITS RICH BLESSINGS FOR MANKIND; AND THE<br />
" SUBJECTION OF NATURE'S FORCES TO MAN" HAS PROGRESSED SO<br />
RAPIDLY THAT THE ISSUES IT RAISES ARE NO LONGER THOSE OF<br />
ECONOMICS OR SOCIAL JUSTICE ALONE, THEY CALL IN QUESTION<br />
THE VERY SURVIVAL OF OUR CIVILIZATION, / 3 </p>
<p>3-<br />
IBEGIN ON THIS SOMEWHAT PORTENTOUS NOTE BECAUSEI<br />
BELIEVE THAT IT IS IN THE CONTEXT OF SUCH URGENT CONTEMPORARY<br />
REALITIES THAT WE MUST LOOK AT THE ROLE OF THE MODERN COMPANY,<br />
AND THE PART IT PLAYS IN SHAPING THE KIND OF SOCIETY WE DESir,:.,<br />
IN THE NINETEENTH CENTURY, DESPITE MARX AND DESPITE MALTHUS,<br />
NO ONE FORESAW THE ENORMOUS PRESSURES AND COMPLEXITIES THAT<br />
WOULD OVERTAKE THE MIXED, FREE ENTERPRISE ECONOMY OF THE<br />
PRESENT DAY. OVER-POPULATION WAS STILL A MATHEMATICAL<br />
ABSTRACTION. THE DEPLETION OF THE EARTH'S RAW MATERIALS AND<br />
NATURAL RESOURCES HAD BARELY BEGUN. THE PRESERVATION OF NATIONAL<br />
INTEGRITY AND INDEPENDENCE WERE IDEALISTIC THEORIES LARGELY<br />
IRRELEVANT IN A WORLD COLONIZED B~ Y EUROPEAN POWERS. THE<br />
RESPONSIBILITY OF PRIVATE ENTERPRISE TO THE PUBLIC INTEREST,<br />
THE GROWTH OF AUTOMATION, THE NEED FOR MANPOWER AND TRAINING<br />
POLICIES THAT TAKE ACCOUNT OF GROW4ING EDUCATIONAL OPPORTUNITIES,<br />
THE TECHNICAL AND PSYCHOLOGICAL STRESSES OF THE MODERN CONSUMER<br />
SOCIETY ALL THESE THINGS WERE UNKNOWN, AND ALL OF THEM<br />
PRESENT CHALLENGES TO THE MODERN INDUSTrRIALIST UNDREAMT : OF<br />
IN PAST GENERATIONS.<br />
As IN SO MANY AREAS OF CONTEMPORARY LIFE, THE GREAT.<br />
ACTIVE PRINCIPLE OF MODERN BUSINESS IS CHANGE; THE INEVITABIILITY<br />
OF CHANGE AND THE NEED TO ADAPT TO CHANGE.-AND THIS CHANGE<br />
NOT SOMETHING IMPOSED FROM ABOVE BY GOVERNMENTS; IT ARISES<br />
FROM DEEP SOCIAL AND HUMAN FORCES TO WHICH GOVERNMENTS M'UST<br />
ADAPT JUST AS MUCH AS BUSINESSMEN. ITS IMPLICATIONS MUST BE<br />
FACED BY GOVERNMENTS AND PRIVATE ENTERPRISE ALIKE.<br />
WE AR-E ALLIES, WE ARE PARTNERS, IN THAT TASK. 1 4 </p>
<p>-4-<br />
A FEW FIGURES WILL DEMONSTRATE THE SCALE OF THE<br />
CHALLENGE BEFORE US* AND HOW RAPIDLY EVEN RECENT PREDICTIONS<br />
SEEM LIKELY TO BE INVALIDATED BEFORE THE END OF THIS CENTURY.<br />
ABOUT 150 YEARS AGO 80% OF THE POPULATION HAD TO WORK THE<br />
LAND IN ORDER TO PROVIDE ENOUGH FOOD FOR ALL. ( THIS IS<br />
STILL THE PROPORTION IN CHINA.) TODAY IN THE UNITED<br />
STATES ABOUT 5% OF THE LABOUR FORCE PRODUCE MORE THAN<br />
ENOUGH FOOD FOR ALL AMERICANS AND FOR MILLIONS OF PEOPLE<br />
ABROAD. A REASONABLE PROJECTION INDICATES THAT BY 1980<br />
IT WILL REQUIRE ONLY 2.5% OF THE WORKFORCE IN THE WESTERN<br />
WORLD TO PRODUCE THE FOOD WE NEED. THE SAME TREND IS<br />
APPARENT IN OTHER PRODUCTION INDUSTRIES. THE CONTAINERIZATION<br />
OF FREIGHTI THE MECHANIZATION OF MINING, THE DEVELOPMENT OF<br />
COMPUTERS ALL THESE TRENDS ARE AFFECTING THE COMPOSITION<br />
OF THE WORKFORCE AND THE LIVES OF ORDINARY PEOPLE.<br />
IN THE U. S. A. MANUAL WORKERS NOW MAKE UP ABOUT ONE<br />
THIRD OF THE LABOUR FORCES AND IN THE EUROPEAN INDUSTRIAL<br />
COUNTRIES ABOUT ONE HALF. THE PROPORTION IS STEADILY<br />
SINKING IN ALL INDUSTRIAL NATIONS. BY-THE END OF THE<br />
CENTURY TECHNOLOGY COULD BRING ABOUT AS DRAMATIC A<br />
REDUCTION IN ALL LABOUR AS WE HAVE ALREADY EXPERIENCED<br />
IN AGRICULTURE. AT THE SAME TIME THE RESOURCES OF THE<br />
WORLD ARE BEING DEPLETED AT A RATE THAT MAY LEAVE SOME<br />
BASIC METALS EXHAUSTED WITHIN 30 YEARS. </p>
<p>THIS IS THE CHALLENGE FOR GOVERNMENTS. THIS IS THE<br />
CHALLENGE FOR ALL THOSE IN CONTROL OF OUR GREAT INDUSTRIES<br />
AND PUBLIC COMPANIES. I THINK BUSINESSMEN ARE ALREADY<br />
BEGINNING TO RECOGNISE CHANGES AND ADAPT TO THEM. VERY FEW<br />
DIRECTORS OR BOARDS OF COMPANIES TODAY WOULD REGARD THEIR<br />
RESPONSIBILITY AS BEING SOLELY TO THE INTERESTS OF THEIR<br />
OWN COMPANY OR ITS SHAREHOLDERS, REGARDLESS OF THE INTERESTS<br />
OF SOCIETY. MANY OF YOU IN THIS ROOM ARE DIRECTORS NOT<br />
OF ONE COMPANY BUT OF TWO OR SEVERAL COMPANIES; YOUR EXPERTISE<br />
AND EXPERIENCE CAN BE APPLIED ACROSS A WIDE RANGE, IN A<br />
MULTITUDE OF INDUSTRIES, SINCE YOU RECOGNISE THAT THE BUSINESS<br />
WORLD IS A DIVERSE AND DYNAMIC COMMUNITY IN WHICH MANY PUBLIC<br />
AND PRIVATE INTERESTS, EVEN NATIONAL INTERESTS, ARE<br />
REPRESENTED. THERE ARE TWO LESSONS WE MUST DRAW FROM THIS. ONE IS<br />
THAT BOARDS OF DIRECTORS CAN NO LONGER BE REGARDED AS<br />
DYNASTIES OR SELF-PERPETUATING ELITES. THE BIGGEST AND MORE<br />
SUCCESSFUL CORPORATIONS ARE OFTEN THOSE WHICH DRAW DIRECTORS<br />
FROM OTHER ORGANISATIONS, BRINGING TOGETHER FRESH TALF'" TS<br />
AND NEW IDEAS. AND THE SECOND LESSON IS THAT DIRECTORS OF LARGI<br />
COMPANIES MUST BE HELD PUBLICLY ACCOUNTABLE FOR THEIR DECISIONS<br />
IF COMPANIES TAKE DECISIONS THAT AFFECT NOT JUS-f THE14SELVE<br />
OR THEIR CLIENTS BUT A WIDER COMMUNITY -TO SAY NOTHING OF<br />
THE NATIONAL ECONOMY WE MUST EXPECT THEM TO EXPLAIN AND<br />
JUSTIFY THOSE DECISIONS. </p>
<p>-6<br />
WE DO NOT EXPECT THEM TO PRESENT A MONOLITHIC FRONT, ANY<br />
MORE THAN WE EXPECT THE MODERN POLITICAL PARTY TO PRESENT<br />
A MONOLITHIC FRONT; IREGRET THAT THERE IS STILL A TENDENCY<br />
IN AUSTRALIA TO REGARD UNITY.-OR IN A NARROWER SENSEI<br />
UNANIMITY AS MORE VIRTUOUS IN A'POLITICAL PARTY THAN<br />
INTEGRITY OR VIGOUR OR THE FREE FLOW OF IDEAS.<br />
CONTENTION, EVEN DISSENSION, ARE NEEDED IN THE<br />
BOARDROOM JUST AS MUCH AS IN PUBLIC LIFE, FOR IT IS ONLY<br />
THROUGH CONTENTION AND FREE EXCHANGE OF IDEAS THAT WE CAN<br />
REACH INFORMED AND MATURE JUDGEMENTS. YOU WILL ALL BE<br />
FAMILIAR WITH A RECENT INCIDENT INVOLVING A DIRECTOR<br />
OF THE AUSTRALIAN INDUSTRY DEVELOPMENT CORPORATION. I SHALL<br />
HAVL MURkL TO SAY L-ArLfl AL3) LJ ' 11iL A. 1. ID. C., BUT LET ME SAY<br />
THIS MUCH NOW: 11Y CHIEF REGRET ABOUT SIR JOHN DUNLOP'S<br />
RESIGNATION WAS NOT SO MUCH THAT THE A. I. D. C. LOST A<br />
RESPECTED PROTAGONIST FROM THE BOARD OF THE BANK OF NEW SOUTH<br />
WALES, BUT RATHER THAT THE OLDEST AND ONE OF THE GREATEST<br />
PUBLIC COMPANIES IN AUSTRALIA COULD FIND* NO ROOM IN ITS<br />
BOARDROOM FOR A DISSENTING VOICE. I BELIEVE THAT PRIVATE<br />
COMPANIES HAVE NO LESS AN OBL. IGATION THAN DEMOCRATIC<br />
GOVERNMENTS TO JUSTIFY THEMSELVES IN PUBLIC. ONE OF THE<br />
GREAT VALUES OF THE PRICES JUSTIFICATION TRIBUNAL, WHICH<br />
THIS GOVERNMENT ESTABLISHED, IS THAT FOR THE FIRST TIME WE<br />
RECOGNISED AND ENACTED THE PRINCIPLE THAT PRIVATE ENTERPRISE<br />
SHOULD BE ACCOUNTABLE TO PUBLIC OPINION FOR DECISIONS THAT<br />
AFFECT THE PUBLIC INTEREST. " OPEN GOVERNMENT" I IS NOT ENOUGH;<br />
It<br />
WE ALSO NEED OPEN BUSINESS a s s17 </p>
<p>-7-<br />
THE TRUTH IS THAT COMPANIES NOW HAVE TO OPERATE<br />
MUCH MORE CLOSELY WITH GOVERNMENTS IN EVERY WAY, THIS IS<br />
CERTAINLY TRUE OF THE GREAT INTERNATIONAL CORPORATIONS,<br />
BUT IT IS NO LESS TRUE OF COMPANIES OPERATING WITHIN<br />
NATIONAL BOUNDARIES, IT WOULD BE A MISTAKE, HOWEVER, TO<br />
REGARD THE ROLE OF GOVERNMENT IN ITS RELATIONS WITH THE<br />
PRIVATE SECTOR AS ONE MERELY OF RESTRAINT OR CONTROL,<br />
TRUE ENOUGH, A SOCIETY IN WHICH EVERYBODY DOES WHAT HE<br />
LIKES IS INCONCEIVABLE, ANY SORT OF HIGHLY DEVELOPED<br />
ORGANISATION IMPOSES UNAVOIDABLE CONSTRAINTS ON THE DRIVES<br />
OF THE INDIVIDUAL, YET I PREFER TO REGARD GOVERNMENT<br />
AND THE PRIVATE SECTOR AS COLLABORATORS RATHER IHAN<br />
RIVALS, THEY WORK BEST WHEN THEY WORK TOGETHER, </p>
<p>-8-<br />
THE UNIVERSAL TREND IN THE MODERN WORLD IS TOWARDS<br />
MORE INTIMATE AND MORE INTRICATE RELATIONSHIPS BETWEEN<br />
GOVERNMENT AND PRIVATE ENTERPRISE. IN JAPAN, FOR EXAMPLE,<br />
THIS RELATIONSHIP IS INSTITUTIONALIZED IN A NETWORK OF<br />
OFFICIAL CONTACTS BETWEEN INDUSTRY AND GOVERNMENT; THE POLICIES<br />
OF ONE ARE FOR ALL PRACTICAL PURPOSES THE POLICIES OF THE<br />
OTHER. IN THE SCANDANAVIAN COUNTRIES, NOTABLY IN SWEDEN,<br />
WHERE STATE SUPERVISION OF THE PRIVATE SECTOR IS PERHAPS<br />
MOST RIGID, GOVERNMENTS AND FREE ENTERPRISE CO-OPERATE TO A<br />
MARKED DEGREE; ENORMOUS STRIDES TOWARDS A SUPER-WELFARE<br />
STATE HAVE BEEN ACCOMPLISHED WITHOUT ANY NATIONALIZATION OF<br />
MAJOR INDUSTRIES, INDEED THOSE INDUSTRIES ARE AMONG THE MOST<br />
EFFICIENT AND PROSPEROUS IN THE WORLD. IN THE UNITED STATES,<br />
WHICH HAS FOR LONG ENFORCED THE MOST RIGOROUS ANTI-TRUST<br />
LAWS OF ANY COUNTRY IN THE FREE WORLD, WE HAVE SEEN IN RECENT<br />
YEARS GOVERNMENT INTERVENTION IN THE PRICES AND INCOMES<br />
MECHANISM TO A DEGREE THAT NO ONE WOULD HAVE CONTEMPLATED<br />
EVEN 10 YEARS AGO. IN OUR OWN REGION, WE HAVE THE RECENT<br />
EXAMPLE OF TWO GREAT AUSTRALIAN COMPANIES, l. P, AND C. S. R.,<br />
MAKING TRADE AGREEMENTS WITH CHINA. I NEED HARDLY LABOUR<br />
THE POINT THAT THE OLD RIGID CONCEPTS OF FREE tENTERPRISE, ThiE<br />
OLD-FASHIONED RIVALRIES BETWEEN THE PUBLIC AND PRIVATE SECTORS, T" E<br />
NOTION THAT GOVERNMENTS AND BUSINESSMEN ARE NATURAL ENEMIES<br />
WORKING IN SEPARATE COMPARTMENTSARE DEAD AND BURIED. ,. 1,1/ 9 </p>
<p>8A<br />
I CAN GIVE YOU A GOOD EXAMPLE OF THE WAY MY OWN<br />
GOVERNMENT HAS BROKEN THROUGH SOME OF THE RIGID IDEOLOGICAL<br />
BARRIERS THAT SURROUNDED ECONOMIC AND MONETARY POLICY,<br />
IT CONCERNS THE BANKS. FOR A LONG TIME IT WAS ACCEPTED<br />
THAT A LABOR GOVERNMENT SHOULD AVOID TOO MUCH USE OF MARKET<br />
FORCES IN GOVERNING THE ECONOMY. YET THE FACT IS THAT NO<br />
PREVIOUS AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT HAS USED THE MECHANISM OF THE<br />
MONEY MARKET MORE THOROUGHLY AND MORE SUCCESSFULLY AS A BASIC<br />
TOOL OF ECONOMIC MANAGEMENT, WE HAVE ELEVATED THE STATUS<br />
AND IMPORTANCE OF THE TRADING BANKS IN AUSTRALIA TO A POSITION<br />
THEY HAVE NOT ENJOYED FOR MORE THAN 20 YEARS. WE DID THIS BY<br />
REMOVING THE CEILING ON BANK INTEREST RATES FOR NEGOTIABLE<br />
CERTIFICATES OF DEPOSIT. IN THAT WAY WE ENABLED THE BANKS<br />
TO COMPETE VIGOROUSLY FOR FUNDS ON THE MONEY MARKET.<br />
fNSTEAD OF BEING THE FIRST INSTITUTIONS TO FEEL THE EFFECTS<br />
OF NECESSARY MONETARY RESTRICTIONS, THE BANKS ARE THE<br />
BENEFICIARIES; OTHER INSTITUTIONS ARE FORCED TO COMPETE<br />
WITH THEM. I SUGGEST THAT THE EXTRAORDINARY SUCCESS OF OUR<br />
FEBRUARY LOAN, WHICH ATTRACTED $ 509 MILLION IN CASH SUBSCRIPTIONS,<br />
IS EVIDENCE OF THE NEW ROLE WE HAVE GIVEN TO THE BANKS.<br />
THE PRIVATE BANKS FOR SO LONG ANATHEMA TO LABOR GOVERNMENTS<br />
ARE BACK ON TOP, I WELCOME THE FACT, THEY ARE GREAT IIISTITUTIONS<br />
MY ONLY REGRET IS THAT I HAVE YET TO HEAR ANY ACKNOWLEDGFMENT<br />
FROM THEM OF THE FACT THAT A LABOR GOVERNMENT HAS RESTORED THEIR<br />
-POSITION AS THE-DOMINANT FINANCIAL INSTITUTIONS IN THIS COUNTRY.<br />
I AM AFRAID THAT IT IS ONLY WHEN COMPLAINTS ARE BEING HEARD<br />
THAT YOU CAN BANK ON THE WAILS. / 9 </p>
<p>-9-<br />
WHATEVER THE BANKS MAY THINKI PUT IT TO YOU<br />
THAT THERE ARE NOW CLOSER CONTACTS BETWEEN GOVERNMENT AND<br />
BUSINESS IN THIS COUNTRY THAN EVER BEFORE AND THEY ARE<br />
GENUINE CONTACTS, NOT TOKEN GESTURES, NOT WINDOW DRESSING.<br />
WHAT WE HAVE TRIED TO DO -AND SUCCEEDED IN DOING IS DRAW<br />
BUSINESSMEN OF THE HIGHEST CALIBRE INTO THE PROCESSES OF<br />
DECISION MAKING AND POLICY FORMATION. THERE ARE LEADING<br />
BUSINESSMEN ON MANY OF THE EXPERT AND INDEPENDENT BODIES<br />
WE HAVE SET UP TO ADVISE THE GOVERNMENT ON POLICY MATTERS.<br />
NOW YOU MAY THINK THAT IS A FAIRLY OBVIOUS THING TO DO,<br />
BUT IT WAS NOT A PRACTICE THAT COMMENDED ITSELF TO OUR<br />
PREDECESSORS. CONSIDER WHAT HAPPENED TO THE VERNON COMMITTEE,<br />
WHICH WAS APPOINTED BY SIR ROBERT MENZIES IN FEBRUARY 1963<br />
TO REPORT ON FUTURE GUIDELINES FOR ECONOMIC POLICY, ITS<br />
REPORT WAS DELIVERED IN MAY 1965, IT WAS TABLED IN AUGUST<br />
1966, IN OTHER WORDS, IT WAS SUPPRESSED BY THE PREVIOUS<br />
GOVERNMENT FOR 15 MONTHS; ITS ADVICE WAS IGNORED.<br />
I TAKE PRIDE IN THE FACT THAT THE FOUR SURVIVING<br />
MEMBERS OF THAT COMMITTEE HAVE ALL RENDERED DISTINGUISHED SERVICE<br />
TO THIS GOVERNMENT AND TO THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE SIR JAMES<br />
VERNON AS HEAD OF THE INQUIRY INTO THE POST OFFICE,<br />
SIR JOHN CRAWFORD, AUTHOR OF THE REPCRT ON WHICH THE<br />
INDUSTRIES ASSISTANCE COMMISSION WAS BASED; PROFESSOR PETER<br />
KARMELI HEAD OF THE INTERIM SCHOOLS COMMITTEE AND AUTHOR OF<br />
THE REPORT INTO EDUCATIONAL NEEDS; AND MR, KENNETH MYERI<br />
A MEMBER OF THE BOARD OF THE NATIONAL LIBRARY. </p>
<p>10<br />
WE HAVE ASKED MANY OTHER PROMINENT BUSINESSMEN TO<br />
PARTICIPATE IN INQUIRIES INTO ASPECTS OF GOVERNMENT POLICY,<br />
IMENTION A FEW: MR. R. KINGSFORD-SMITH, CHAIRMAN AND<br />
MANAGING DIRECTOR OF HAWKER DE HAVILLAND, A MEMBER OF A<br />
WORKING GROUP TO STUDY THE AIRCRAFT INDUSTRY; MR. K. S. HEDLEY,<br />
A MEMBER OF THE NATIONAL SUPERANNUATION COMMITTEE OF INQUIRY;<br />
MR. N. M. GOW, A MEMBER OF THE TECHNICAL AND FURTHER EDUCATION<br />
COMMITTEE; MR. D. YENKEN AND MR. KEITH'VALLANCEI MEMBERS OF THE<br />
TASK FORCE ON THE NATIONAL ESTATE; MR. JACK HANNES,* MANAGING<br />
DIRECTOR OF HANIMEX CORPORATION LIMITED, A MEMBER OF THE<br />
INTERIM COMMISSION ON CONSUMER STANDARDS; MR. G. POLITES,<br />
EXECUTIVE CHAIRMAN OF THE AUSTRALIAN COUNCIL OF EMPLOYERS<br />
FEDERATIONS, AND SIR THOMAS WARDLE OF PERTH, MEMBERS OF THE<br />
NATIONAL COMMITTEE ON DISCRIMINATION IN EMPLOYMENT. SIR THOMAS<br />
WARDLE IS ALSO A MEMBER OF THE INTERIM ADVISORY BOARD OF THE<br />
DEVELOPMENT ASSISTANCE AGENCY. WE HAVE APPOINTED FOUR NOTED<br />
BUSINESSMEN MR. L. R. DUDLEY, MR. G. P. HAMPEL, MR, GEORGE<br />
JOHNSON, AND MR. C. H. GRACE TO THE INDUSTRIES ASSISTANCE<br />
COMMISSION. WE HAVE REAPPOINTED SIR BRIAN MASsy-GREENE AS A<br />
DIREC-TOR OF THE COMMONWEALTH BANKING CORPORATION AND AS A<br />
MEMBER OF THE-MANUFACTURING INDUSTRIES ADVISORY COUNCIL.<br />
OF COURSE I CANNOT UNDERTAKE THAT ALL THE RECOMMENDATIONS OF<br />
THESE BODIES WILL BE ACCEPTED BY THE GOVERNMENT, BUT THEIR<br />
MEMBERS CAN BE ASSURED OF THIS: THEIR ADVICE WILL BE PUBLISHED<br />
AND PUBLISHED PROMPTLY. IT-WILL NOT BE SUPPRESSED OR FORGOTTEN.<br />
IT WILL CONTRIBUTE TO A CLIMATE OF OPEN PUBLIC DEBATE. IT ' A ILL<br />
BECOME PART OF THE DECISION MAKING PROCESS. SO LET US HEAR NO<br />
MORE ABOUT LACK OF CONSULTATION. No OTHER GOVERNMENT IN<br />
FRAMING ITS POLICIES HAS DRAWN SO WIDELY AND REWARDINGLY ON<br />
THE SERVICES OF BUSINESSMEN. </p>
<p>11<br />
IWANT TO DEAL IN A MOMENT WITH THREE PARTICULAR ASPECTS<br />
OF GOVERNMENT POLICY WHICH CONCERN You. BUT FIRST, I HAVE ONE<br />
MORE GENERAL OBSERVATION, ASK YOU TO REMEMBER THAT A GREAT<br />
DEAL OF WHAT THE GOVERNMENT IS ATTEMPTING TO DO HAS ALREADY<br />
BEEN ATTEMPTED AND ACHIEVED IN OTHER WESTERN COUNTRIES IN SOME<br />
CASES, MANY DECADES AGO. SOME OF YOU MAY RECALL THAT LAST<br />
NOVEMBER, BUSINESS INTERNATIONAL CONDUCTED A SEMINAR IN CANBERRA<br />
AT WHICH THE POLICIES OF THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT WERE EXAMINED<br />
FROM THE VIEWPOINT OF THE INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS COMMUNITY.<br />
WE WERE HONOURED ON THAT OCCASION BY THE PRESENCE OF MRiORVILLE<br />
FREEMAN, WHO SERVED WITH DISTINCTION IN THE KENNEDY AND JOHNSON<br />
ADMINISTRATIONS AND WHOSE NAME IS RESPECTED THROUGHOUT THE<br />
BUSINESS WORLD. LET ME READ TO YOU SOME OF THE CONCLUSIONS REACHED<br />
By BUSINESS INTERNATIONAL ABOUT THE POLICIES OF THIS GOVERNMENT.<br />
IF I WERE-WRITING THE REPORT MYSELF I MIGHT EXPRESS THESE VIEWS<br />
WITH RATHER MORE ENTHUSIASM, BUT THEIR GENERAL DRIFT WILL BE<br />
CLEAR TO You. BUSINESS INTERNATIONAL SAID THIS:<br />
MANY OF ITS PROGRAMS ( THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT'S PROGRAMS)<br />
WILL MERELY BRING AUSTRALIAN LEGISLATION AND PRACTICES<br />
INTO LINE WITH THOSE IN FORCE IN THE U. S. AND WESTERN<br />
EUROPE. ITS SOCIAL SECURITY REFORMS ARE SIMILAR TO THOSE<br />
IN FORCE IN MANY WEST EUROPEAN COUNTRIES FOR SOME YEARS;<br />
ITS NEW ANTITRUST LAWS ARE MODELLED ON THOSE OF THE U. S.,<br />
WITHOUT BEING SO SEVERE AS THE U. S, LAWS; ITS PROPOSED<br />
SECURITIES EXCHANGE COMMISSION WILL ALSO BE MODELLED ON<br />
U. S. LINES, BUT ITS REGULATIONS WILL BE LESS COMPLEX;<br />
SIMILARLY, IF THE GOVERNMENT PROCEEDS WITH PROGRAMS FOR<br />
WORKER PARTICIPATION IN MANAGEMENT, THESE WILL-BE MODELLED<br />
ON SWEDISH AND WEST GERMAN PRACTICES. </p>
<p>12-<br />
WHILE THE GOVERNMENT HAS INTRODUCED SOME ECONOMIC<br />
PLANNING, THIS IS LESS RIGOROUS THAN EVEN THE<br />
PLANNING OF THE UK GOVERNMENT TODAY, THE MAIN<br />
EXPRESSION OF THE GOVERNMENT'S NEW THRUST WILL BE<br />
IN GREATER EXPENDITURE ON SOCIAL SERVICES, AND IN<br />
GREATER REGULATION OF BUSINESS, RATHER THAN IN<br />
STATE OWNERSHIP,<br />
THE REPORT THEN MAKES SOME MODERATELY KIND REFERENCES<br />
TO ME AND SOME OF MY COLLEAGUES, THE " KEY FIGURES" IN THE<br />
GOVERNMENT, IT SAYS, ARE " PRAGMATIC MODERATES WHO EMPHASISED THAT<br />
THEY WELCOMED AND ENCOURAGED CONTINUED OUTSIDE INVESTMENT<br />
IN AUSTRALIA, ALTHOUGH SUBJECT TO CERTAIN NEW GUIDELINES,,,,"<br />
THE REPORT GOES ON:<br />
ALL AUSTRALIAN POLITICAL PARTIES AND THE BUSINESS<br />
COMMUNITY AGREE THAT POPULAR SENTIMENT DEMANDED AN<br />
END OF THE OPEN DOOR POLICY TOWARD FOREIGN INVESTMENT<br />
WHICH PREVAILED UNTIL LATE 1972; THE FIRST STEPS<br />
TO END THAT POLICY WERE IN FACT TAKEN BY THE<br />
PREVIOUS LIBERAL-COUNTRY PARTY GOVERNMENT,<br />
FINALLY, WITH SINGULAR SHREWDNESS AND GOOD<br />
JUDGMENTI THE REPORT CONCLUDES: " IT IS LIKELY THAT THE<br />
WHIITLAM GOVERNMENT WILL REMAIN IN POWER FOR SOME TIME TO COME,"<br />
I MUST SAY THAT I HAVE A VERY HIGH OPINION OF BUSINESS<br />
INTERNATIONAL, I HOPE THAT OPINION IS SHARED BY ALL OF YOU,<br />
RADICAL WE MAY BE, DETERMINED WE MAY BE, VIGOROUS WE CERTAINLY<br />
ARE; BUT THERE IS NOTHING IN OUR POLICIES TOWARDS BUSINESS<br />
THAT WOULD BE CONSIDERED NOVEL, IMPETUOUS OR UNPRECEDENTED IN<br />
ANY OTHER WESTERN COUNTRY, ,/ 13 1 </p>
<p>13<br />
IN OUR APPROACH TO BUSINESS WE HAVE THREE BASIC<br />
OBJECTIVES. WE WANT TO ENSURE, FIRST OF ALL, THAT<br />
THE PRIVATE SECTOR REMAINS BUOYANT, PROSPEROUS AND<br />
EFFICIENT. WE WANT TO ENSURE THAT AS FAR AS POSSIBLE<br />
THE OWNERSHIP AND CONTROL OF AUSTRALIAN INDUSTRIES AND<br />
RESOURCES REMAIN IN AUSTRALIAN HANDS, AND WE WANT TO<br />
ENSURE THAT THE AFFAIRS OF AUSTRALIAN COMPANIES, AND<br />
THE SECURITIES INDUSTRY ITSELF, ARE SUBJECT TO FAIR AND<br />
REASONABLE LAWS, APPLIED UNIFORMLY ACROSS THE NATION IN<br />
THE INTERESTS OF INVESTORS, CONSUMERS, SHAREHOLDERS,<br />
BUSINESSMEN AND THE COMMUNITY AT LARGE.<br />
LET ME DEAL WITH THE LAST POINT FIRST. THE GOVERNMENT<br />
IS PLEDGED TO LEGISLATE FOR A NATIONWIDE COMPANIES ACT.<br />
THE QUEST FOR UNIFORM COMPANY LAW IN AUSTRALIA HAS BEEN A<br />
LONG AND SORRY STORY OF FRUSTRATION AND DISAPPOINTMENT<br />
YOU WILL REMEMBER THAT A MEETING OF ATTORNEYS-GENERAL<br />
IN 1959 RESULTED EVENTUALLY IN THE PRODUCTION OF A MODEL<br />
DRAFT BILL IN 1960, Now WHILE THAT INITIATIVE LED TO<br />
CERTAIN REFORMS IN COMPANY LAW AND TO A MUCH GREATER<br />
MEASURE OF UNIFORMITY, CONSIDERABLE DIFFERENCES REMAINED<br />
IN THE LAWS BETWEEN DIFFERENT STATES. THEY WILL ONLY BE<br />
REMOVED BY NATIONAL LEGISLATION. FOR MORE THAN 60 YEARS,<br />
HOWEVER, ATTEMPTS AT A UNIFORM COMPANY LAW WERE HAMPERED BY A<br />
HIGH COURT DECISION IN 1909, THE COURT GAV. E A HIGHLY RESTRICTIVE<br />
INTERPRETATION OF THE CORPORATIONS POWER OF THE COMMONWEALTH<br />
UNDER THE CONSTITUTION. THAT DECISION WAS EVENTUALLY OVERRULED<br />
BY A UNANIMOUS JUDGEMENT OF THE COURT IN SEPTEMBER 1971.<br />
THE WAY WAS THEN OPEN FOR LEGISLATION ON A NATIONWIDE SCALE. ./ 14 </p>
<p>14<br />
WE HAVE HAD ONE STRIKING DEMONSTRATION OF THE<br />
OBSTACLES TO UNIFORMITY WHEN LAWS OF THIS KIND ARE LEFT<br />
TO THE STATES, IN THE EARLY 1960s, FOLLOWING THE FAILURE<br />
OF CERTAIN PUBLIC BORROWING CORPORATIONS, VICTORIA INTRODUCED<br />
A COMPANIES ( PUBLIC BORROWINGS) ACT WHICH CAME. INTO OPERATION<br />
ON 1 FEBRUARY 1964. NEW SOUTH WALES AND QUEENSLAND FOLLOWED<br />
IN JULY 1964, SOUTH AUSTRALIA AND WESTERN AUSTRALIA IN<br />
JANUARY 1965 AND TASMANIA IN JANUARY 1967, THUS IT TOOK<br />
NEARLY THREE YEARS BEFORE ALL AUSTRALIANS HAD THE PROTECTION<br />
OF THIS LEGISLATION, WHILE DIRECTORS, LAWYERS AND ACCOUNTANTS<br />
SOUGHT TO KEEP TRACK OF DIFFERENT LAWS FROM PLACE TO PLACE,<br />
YET A NATIONAL GOVERNMENT, SEIZED WITH THE IMPORTANCE OF THIS<br />
REFORM, COULD HAVE DONE THE JOB AT ONCE,<br />
ONE OF THE FEARS THAT IS SOMETIMES EXPRESSED ABOUT<br />
NATIONA LEGISLATION IS THAT IT WILL SOMEHOW BECOME A VEHICLE<br />
FOR SOCIAL REFORM RATHER THAN REMAIN A MERE PIECE OF ENABLING<br />
LEGISLATION, I DO NOT SEE WHY WE SHOULD BE ASHAMED OF<br />
SOCIAL RLFURIM, WE TAKE ALTOGETHER TOO NARROW A VIEW OF COMPANY<br />
LAW IF WE INSIST THAT IT CONFINE ITSELF TO THE TECHNICALITIES<br />
OF ADMINISTRATION, AGAIN, IT IS TOO NARROW A VIEW TO INSIST<br />
THAT ONLY DIRECTORS, SHAREHOLDERS AND CREDITORS HAVE AN<br />
INTEREST IN THE ACTIVITIES OF A COMPANY, NO LAW IS DEVOID CF<br />
SOCIAL CONTENT, THE RECENT BRITISH WHITE PAPER ON COMPANY<br />
LAW REFORM SAID THIS: </p>
<p>15<br />
" A BOARD OF DIRECTORS HAS TO RECONCILE SEVERAL<br />
INTERESTS, OF WHICH PROFIT IS THE MAIN BUT<br />
CANNOT BE THE ONLY ONE. ANY COMPANY MUST<br />
BEHAVE AS A RESPONSIBLE PART OF THE SOCIETY<br />
IN WHICH IT EXISTS. THIS REQUIRES COMPANY<br />
DIRECTORS, ON BEHALF OF THE SHAREHOLDERS,<br />
TO DISCHARGE THEIR SOCIAL RESPONSIBILITIES<br />
AS WELL AS TO PROTECT THEIR LEGITIMATE INTERESTS."<br />
IACCEPT THAT VIEW. ICOMMEND IT TO YOU. IN AUSTRALIA<br />
WE WILL IN DUE COURSE HAVE COMPANY LEGISLATION WITH A<br />
SIMILAR SOCIAL CONTENT. ONLY AN AUSTRALIAN CANUTE WOULD<br />
ATTEMPT TO STEM THAT TIDE. TO RESIST THE INTRODUCTION OF<br />
NATIONAL COMPANIES LEGISLATION BECAUSE OF ITS POSSIBLE<br />
SOCIAL. CONfFNT IS TO BE BLIND TO THE DYNAMICS OF LAW AND<br />
THE NEEDS OF TilE AUSTRALIAN PUBLIC.<br />
WE SEE THE ESTABLISHMENT OF A SECURITIES AND<br />
EXCHANGE COMMISSION AS AN ESSENTIAL PART OF OUR DRIVE FOR<br />
UNIFORM CUMFANY LAW. IREMIND YOU THAT OUR OPPONENTS ARE<br />
AS FULLY COMMITTED AS WE ARE TO THE ESTABLISHMENT OF A<br />
COMM ISS IuN, WE STILL AWAIT THE REPORT OF THE SENATE<br />
SECURITIES AND EXCHANGE COMMITTEE, WHICH WAS ESTABLISHED<br />
IN MARCH 1970. IN THE MEANTIME, HOWEVER, CABINET HAS<br />
AUTHORISED THE ATTioRNEY-GENERAL TO PREPARE LEGISLATION<br />
FOR A c~~ i~ INAND THAT WORK IS GOING FORWARD WITH<br />
ALL POSSIBLE SPEED, 16 </p>
<p>16<br />
I TURN NOW TO ONE OF THE GREAT AND ABIDING<br />
THEMES OF MY GOVERNMENT'S PHILOSOPHY. I HAVE SAID<br />
THAT ONE OF OUR PRINCIPAL OBJECTIVES IS TO MAXIMISE<br />
AUSTRALIAN OWNERSHIP AND CONTROL OF OUR INDUSTRIES<br />
AND RESOURCES. AS YOU KNOW, THE GREAT INSTRUMENTS<br />
WE ARE DEVELOPING FOR THAT PURPOSE ARE THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
INDUSTRY DEVELOPMENT CORPORATION AND THE ASSOCIATED<br />
NATIONAL INVESTMENT FUND, WHEN I SAY THAT THESE ARE<br />
OUR OBJECTIVES, OUR POLICIES, IT IS IMPORTANT TO<br />
REMEMBER THIS: THEY WERE INTRODUCED AND DEVELOPED<br />
IN RESPONSE TO A CLEAR AND UNEQUIVOCAL PUBLIC DEMAND.<br />
THERE WAS NO MISTAKING THAT DEMAND. THERE ARE CERTAIN<br />
ISSUES IN POLITICS, CERTAIN CURRENTS OF POPULAR FEELING,<br />
THAT IMPINGE ON THE CONSCIOUSNESS OF ALL PARTIES AND<br />
HELP SHAF. A CONSENSUS OF THOUGHT AND ACTION.<br />
OUR OPPONEivTS RECOGNISED THOSE PRESSURES. THEY KNEW<br />
AS WELL AS ' E DID THAT THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE WERE NO<br />
LONGER WILLING TO SEE THE AUSTRALIAN ECONOMY FALL<br />
INCREASINGLY INTO FOREIGN HANDS. THEY ESTABLISHED<br />
THE WE IN TURN HAVE RESOLVED TO EXPAND AND<br />
STRENGTHEN IT. THE A. I. D. C. WAS BORN OUT OF A<br />
REALISATION THAT THERE IS A NEED FOR A SPECIALISED<br />
INSTITUTION CAPABLE OF MOBILISING AND CHANNELLING CAPITAL<br />
OFTEN IN LARGE AMOUNTS INTO NATIONALLY IMPORTANT<br />
INDUSTRIAL DEVELOPMENT BY COMPANIES OWNED AND CONTROLLED<br />
IN AUSTRAL. IA. OUR PROPOSALS WILL REMOVE UNREALISTIC<br />
RESTRICTIONS THAT HAVE BEEN PLACED ON THE CORPORATION SINCE<br />
ITS INCEPTION, THEY WILL ENABLE IT TO CARRY OUT MORE<br />
THOROUGHLY AND MORE EFFICIENTLY THE TASK EXPECTED OF IT. </p>
<p>17<br />
IN ALL THE CRITICISM I HAVE HEARD OF THE CORPORATION<br />
AND THE NATIONAL INVESTMENT FUND, I HAVE YET TO HEAR<br />
ANY SERIOUS CRITICISM OF THEIR FUNDAMENTAL OBJECTIVE.<br />
THERE IS, AFTER ALL, NOTHING SURPRISING) NOTHING NARROW<br />
OR XENOPHOBIC, IN THE DEMAND FOR GREATER AUSTRALIAN<br />
PARTICIPATION IN THE CONTROL OF OUR ECONOMIC DESTINY.<br />
SO IF I TAKE TIME TO DEAL WITH YOUR ANXIETIES AND<br />
CRITICISMS, LET IT NOT BE THOUGHT THAT I AM ON THE<br />
DEFENSIVE. NOT ONLY DO I BELIEVE IN MY HEART THAT OUR<br />
PROPOSALS ARE RIGHT AND OVERDUE: I BELIEVE THAT YOU,<br />
AS GOOD AUSTRALIANS, AS BUSINESSMEN OF PRIDE AND INTEGRITY,<br />
BELIEVE IN YOUR OWN HEARTS IN THE NEED FOR THESE REFORMS.<br />
IT IS IMPORTANT TO REMEMBER THAT OUR PROPOSALS ARE<br />
AS MUCH CONCERNED WITH MAXIMISING INDUSTRY DEVELOPMENT<br />
GENERALLY AS THEY ARE WITH MAXIMISING AUSTRALIAN OWNERSHIP<br />
AND CONTROL IN THAT DEVELOPMENT. A. I. D. C. IS ONLY ONE OF<br />
MANY INSTITUTIONS THAT CAN AND DO PROVIDE DEVELOPMENT<br />
FINANCE. SIR ALAN WESTERMAN, THE EXECUTIVE CHAIRMAN<br />
OF MADE THIS POINT SUCCINCTLY IN A SUBMISSION<br />
TO THE SENATE SELECT COMMITTEE ON FOREIGN OWNERSHIP AND<br />
CONTROL, SIR ALAN SAID:<br />
" I DO NOT SEE THE BASIC QUESTION AS BEING<br />
WHETHER A. I. D. C. OR SOME ALTERNATIVE MECHANISM<br />
IS 7HE BEST WAY TO FINANCE DEVELOPMENT AND<br />
GET MORE AUSTRALIAN PARTICIPATION IN IT.<br />
I DO NOT BELIEVE FOR A MOMENT THAT A. I. D. C.<br />
COULD DO THAT JOB ALONE. THERE ARE A VARIETY<br />
OF GOVERNMENTAL POLICY MEASURES AND INSTITUTIONS<br />
THAT DO OR COULD HAVE A ROLE </p>
<p>18<br />
To ME THE REAL QUESTION IS WHETHER<br />
THERE IS A ROLE FOR A SPECIAL KIND OF<br />
INSTITUTION SUCH As A. I. D. C. WHICH, DIRECTED<br />
NOT JUST TOWARDS NORMAL SHAREHOLDERS I OBJECTIVES<br />
FOR A PARTICULAR PROJECT BUT TO THE WIDER<br />
NATIONAL OBJECTIVES SET FOR IT, WOULD ACTIVELY<br />
PURSUE THOSE OBJECTIVES ( AND-ONLY THOSE OBJECTIVES)<br />
THROUGH ITS OWN COMMERCIAL OPERATIONS AND<br />
NEGOTIATIONS IN THE MARKET PLACE. IT HAS ALREADY<br />
BEEN ACCEPTED BY PARLIAMENT AND I BELIEVE THE<br />
COMMUNITY GENERALLY THAT A. I. D. C. IS TO HAVE<br />
THAT ROLE. IF THIS IS SO I WOULD HOPE THERE SHOULD<br />
BE NO OBJECTION TO IT BEING PROPERLY EQUIPPED FOR<br />
THE JOB."<br />
THE POINT IS MADE BY SOME CRITICS THAT THE EXPAN SION<br />
OF A. I. D. C. WILL LEAD TO INCREASED COMPETITION AMONG<br />
FINANCIAL INSTITUTIONS FOR AVAILABLE DOMESTIC SAVINGS,<br />
RESULTING IN HIGHER INTEREST RATES AND A DIVERSION OF<br />
FUNDS FROM ESTABLISHED INSTITUTIONS SUCH AS SAVINGS<br />
BANKS, BUILDING SOCIETIES AND LIFE OFFICES. NOW AS FAR<br />
AS I AM AWARE, THERE IS NOTHING IN ECONOMIC THEORY WHICH<br />
SAYS THAT THE ADVENT OF A NEW FINANCIAL INTERMEDIARY, OR<br />
THE EXPANSION OF AN ESTABLISHED ONE, WILL PUSH UP INTEREST<br />
RATES, IN FACT, IF NEW SAVINGS ARE GENERATED AND FUNDS<br />
DIVERTED FROM INDIVIDUALS WHO MIGHT OTHERWISE HAVE INVESTED<br />
DIRECT, IT MAY HELP TO REDUCE THE AVERAGE COST OF MONEY IN<br />
THE COMMUNITY. WE BELIEVE THAT INTENSIFIED COMPETITION FOR<br />
FUNDS Ar,, ONG FINANCIAL INTERMEDIARIES WILL MAKE THESE INSTITUTIONS<br />
MORE COST-CONSCIOUS AND INNOVATIVE, AND THAT IN TURN WILL<br />
REDUCE THE MARGINS BETWEEN THEIR BORROWING AND LENDING RATES. </p>
<p>19<br />
IT IS THE GOVERNMENT'S INTENTION THAT THE ADDITIONAL<br />
FUNDS CHANNELLED INTO RESOURCE-DEVELOPMENT AND INDUSTRIAL<br />
PROJECTS SHOULD BE DIVERTED ULTIMATELY FROM LESS ESSENTIAL<br />
PURPOSES, SUCH AS HIGH-RISE CITY BUILDINGS, RATHER THAN<br />
FROM HOME-BUYING OR PUBLIC AUTHORITY S-PENDINGa<br />
ANOTHER POINT MADE BY OUR CRITICS IS THAT THE NEW<br />
A. I. D. C. AND THE N. I. F. WILL BE ATTEMPTING TO SATISFY<br />
NEEDS WHICH ESTABLISHED INSTITUTIONS ARE ALREADY SATISFYING<br />
ADEQUATELY. MY ANSWER IS THAT ESTABLISHED INSTITUTIONS<br />
HAVE NO OBLIGATION AND EVEN LESS INCLINATION TO<br />
PURSUE NATIONAL POLICY OBJECTIVES SINGLE-MINDEDLY AND<br />
PURPOSEFULLY. AI. I), C. WAS ESTABLISHED TO HELP FINANCE<br />
NATIONALLY DESIRABLE INDUSTRIAL AND MINERAL DEVELOPMENT;<br />
TO PROMOTE MAXIMUM PRACTICABLE AUSTRALIAN PARTICIPATION<br />
IN IMPORTANT ENTERPRISES, AND TO HELP FIL L<br />
GAPS IN THE AUSTRALIAN CAPITAL MARKET. THE INEW L-LGISLATION<br />
WILL ENABLE THE CORPORATION TO FULFIL THESE NATIONAL<br />
RESPONSIBILITIES MORE EFFECTIVELY. REMEMBER, IF ANY<br />
AUSTRALIAN INVESTOR WANTS TO BUY A SHARE DIRECT IN A<br />
LISTED PUBLIC COMPANY, THERE IS NOTHING IN OUR PROPOSALS<br />
TO STOP HIM OR TO AUTHORISE A. I. DIC. TO FORCE HIM TO<br />
INVEST THROUGH THE INSTEAD. THE TROUBLE IS THAT<br />
IT IS NOT ALWAYS PluSSIolL E AUSTRfALIANS TO. INVEST IN<br />
FOREIGN-OPERATED ENTERPRISES, ESPECIALLY WHEN THEY ARE SET<br />
UP AS SUBSIDIARY PRIVATE COMPANIES OR EVEN AS BRANCHES OF<br />
THE OVERSEAS CONGLOMERATE. </p>
<p>20<br />
AND EVEN WHERE IT IS POSSIBLE TO INVEST, UNLESS THE<br />
INDIVIDUAL HOLDING IS A VERY BIG ONE IT WILL COMMAND<br />
NO EFFECTIVE SAY WHATEVER IN SEEING IHA~ lI E COMPANY<br />
FOLLOWS POLICIES IN THE INTERESTS OF AUSTRALIA.<br />
IN SHORT, IT HAS LITTLE OR NOTHING TO DO WITH A. I. DoCs<br />
OBJECTIVES$ IN AN4Y CASE, IT IS NOT THE JOB OF A. I. DsCs TO DISPLACE<br />
AUSTRALIAN EQUITY INV'ESTMENT OF THAT KIND. IT IS DESIGNED<br />
TO ADD TO IT, BY DISPLACING SOME OF WHAT WOULD OTHERWISE<br />
BE FOREIGN INVESTMENT. IT SHOULD THUS BE ABLE TO DO A LOT<br />
TO STRENGTHEN THE AUSTRALIAN SAY IN THE DIRECTION OF<br />
DEVELOPMENT OF NATIONAL INDUSTRIAL ENTERPRISES. THERE IS<br />
CERTAINLY NOTHING IN OUR PROPnFA. S TH~ AT * VvLL. DEP~ IRIVE N. I. F.<br />
BONDHOLDERS, PROTECTED AS THEY ARE BY A SUPERVISORY COUNCIL,<br />
FROM ANY OF THE PRACTICAL BENEFITS OF OWNERSHIP THAT THEY<br />
WOULD ENJOY BY SMALL IPORTFOLIO'I HOLDINGS OF SHARES LET<br />
ALONE FROM INVESTMENT VIA A UNIT TRUST OR INVESTMENT<br />
COMPANY OR A LIFE OR PENSION FUND. FAR FROM DIVERTING<br />
EQUITY FUNDS FROM STOCK EXCHANGES, OUR PROPOSALS WILL<br />
CREATE A NEW EQUITY INSTRUMENT ( THE INVESTMENT BONDS)<br />
TRADED ON THE EXCHANGES, AND RAISE FUNDS FOR EQUITY<br />
INVESTMENT FROM MANY ORDINARY PEOPLE WHO WOULD NEVER<br />
THINK OF INVESTING THROUGH THE STOCK EXCHANGE. </p>
<p>21<br />
WHEN THE A. I. D. C. WAS FIRST PROPOSED BY SIR JOHN<br />
MCEWENI IT WAS REGARDED IN SOME QUARTERS AS A DANGEROUSLY<br />
RADICAL CREATION, SOME MEMBERS OF THE PREVIOUS GOVERNMENT<br />
SAW IT AS A SACRED DUTY TO FIGHT THE AIDC, AS PART OF<br />
THEIR HOLY CRUSADE AGAINST SOCIALISM, I BELIEVE BUSINESSMEN<br />
TODAY ARE OUTGROWING THESE INSTINCTIVE PREJUDICES; YOU ARE<br />
SHREWD ENOUGH TO JUDGE ANY GOVERNMENT MEASURE ON REALISTIC<br />
AND FACTUAL GROUNDS, THE FACT IS THAT THE SAME PEOPLE WHO<br />
COMPLAIN TODAY ABOUT " NATIONALIZATION BY STEALTH MADE THE<br />
SAME CHARGE AGAINST THE MENZIES GOVERNMENT'S BANKING<br />
LEGISLATION IN 1957, WHAT IS STEALTHY OR FURTIVE ABOUT<br />
OUR PROPOSALS? I HAVE BEEN ADVOCATING THEM PUBLICLY FOR YEARS,<br />
THEY HAVE BEEN OPENLY DEBATED INSIDE AND OUTSIDE PARLIAMENT,<br />
OUR INTENTIONS ARE CLEARLY EXPRESSED IN THE LEGISLATION,<br />
THE WHOLE OF AIDC,' s ACTIVITIES ARE SUBJECT TO AUDIT,<br />
ITS ACTIVITIES CAN BE SCRUTINISED BY THE PARLIAMENT,<br />
IF MY YEARS IN PUBLIC LIFE HAVE TAUGHT ME ONE THING,<br />
IF THE EXPERIENCE OF WESTERN GOVERNMENTS IN ECONOMIC<br />
MANAGEMENT HAS PROVED ANYTHING IN RECENT YEARS, IT IS<br />
SIMPLY THAT THERE ARE NO LONGER ANY CLEAR-CUT OR USEFUL<br />
DISTINCTIONS TO BE DRAWN BETWEEN FREE ENTERPRISE POLICIES ON THE<br />
ONE HAND AND INTERVENTIONIST POLICIES ON THE OTHER, FOR ALL<br />
THEIR SLO3ANS AND CATCHCRIES, POLITICAL PARTIES OF ALL SHADES1<br />
IN ALL COUNTRIES, NOW ACCEPT THAT DEMOCRATIC GOVERNMENTS<br />
MUST CO-OPERATE WITH THE PRIVATE SECTOR IN THE RUNNING OF<br />
A MIXED ECONOMY, / 22 </p>
<p>22<br />
BOTH SIDES HAVE A COMMON CONCERN, A SIMPLE CONCERN<br />
TO ENSURE THAT THE SYSTEM WORKS, WHO IS DOCTRINAIRE<br />
ON THESE ISSUES? WE WHO SEEK CO-OPERATION, OR THOSE WHO<br />
INSIST THAT NO CO-OPERATION IS POSSIBLE? WHO ARE THE DOGMATISTS<br />
AND REACTIONARIES? WE WHO ACKNOWLEDGE THE REALITY OF CHANGE,<br />
OR THOSE WHO FEAR CHANGE OF ANY KIND? WHO ARE THE IDEOLOGUES?<br />
WE WHO REMAIN FLEXIBLE, CANDID IN OUR AIMS, PRAGMATIC IN OU7<br />
APPROACH, OR THOSE WHO BELIEVE THAT THE ENORMOUS PROBLEMS OF<br />
MODERN INDUSTRIAL ECONOMIES, AND THE THREAT THEY POSE TO<br />
SOCIAL HARMONY AND JUSTICE, WILL BE SOLVED BY 19TH CENTURY<br />
SLOGANS OF LAISSEZ-FAIRE CAPITALISM? ONCE IT MIGHT HAVE<br />
BEEN POSSIBLE TO HOPE THAT THE CHALLENGES OF AUTOMATION,<br />
OF POPULATION, OF RESOURCES DIPLOMACY, OF INFLATION,<br />
OF POLLUTION, OF NATIONAL OWNERSHIP, WOULD SOMEHOW SOLVE<br />
THEMSELVES IF LEFT ALONE, NO ONE BELIEVES THAT NOW,<br />
THE PROBLEMS ARE INESCAPABLE; AND IF THERE IS ANY<br />
CONSOLATION IN FACING SUCH TESTING AND UNCERTAIN TIMES,<br />
IT IS IN THE KNOWLEDGE THAT THE GREAT CREATIVE EPOCHS IN<br />
HUMAN AFFAIRS HAVE BEEN EPOCHS OF CHANGE AND TRIAL, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
