<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3165</transcript-id>
    <title>THE LOCAL GOVERNMENT REFERENDUM</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/02/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003165.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
THE LOCAL GOVERNMENT REFERE14DUM<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MIiISTER,<br />
THE HON, E. G, ' HITLA1, M. P.,<br />
TO THE 1971' CONFEREACE OF<br />
THE 111STITUTE OF IUNICIPAL ADMINISTRATION,<br />
( RAYMOND WEST ORATIOi)<br />
MELBOURNE, 19 FEBRUARY 1974,<br />
I SHOULD BEGIN BY EMPHASISING THE PROFOUND<br />
COMMUNITY OF INTEREST BETWEEN THE AIMS AND OBJECTIVES OF<br />
YOUR INSTITUTE AND THE AIMS AND OBJECTIVES OF MY<br />
GOVERNMENT. YOUR ORGANISATION WAS AMONG THE FIRST TO<br />
RECOGNISE THAT MUNICIPAL ADMINISTRATION IS AS MUCH A<br />
NATIONAL AS A STATE OR LOCAL CONCERN. YOU WERE AMONG<br />
THE FIRST TO PERCEIVE THAT THE PROBLEMS AND CHALLENGES<br />
OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT HAVE NATIONAL IMPLICATIONS QUITE<br />
DISTINCT FROM THEIR RELEVANCE TO PARTICULAR LOCALITIES.<br />
WHEN YOUR INSTITUTE WAS ESTABLISHED ON A FEDERAL BASIS IN<br />
1952, YOU CONCLUDED TO USE YOUR OWN WORDS THAT " WHILE<br />
LOCAL GOVERNMENT IS LOCAL AND, IN FACT, DERIVES ITS FUNCTIONS<br />
FROM EACH RESPECTIVE STATE', THE DEVELOPMENT AND STRENGTH OF IT<br />
IS A MATTER OF NATIONAL IMPORTANCE AND OF NATIONAL CONCERN." I @/ 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
YOUR ACCEPTANCE OF THAT PRINCIPLE WITH WHAT I<br />
BELIEVE ARE ITS INEVITABLE CONSEQUENCES WAS DUE IN LARGE<br />
MEASURE TO THE VISION AND ENERGY OF THE LATE RAYMOND WEST,<br />
AN ADMINISTRATOR OF EXCEPTIONAL GIFTS AND RARE DEDICATION.<br />
I MIGHT REMIND YOU THAT IT WAS IN THAT SAME YEAR, 1952,<br />
THAT I FIRST ENTERED PARLIAMENT. FROM THAT MOMENT,<br />
IN ALL MY SPEECHES, IN ALL MY ACTIONS, I SOUGHT TO<br />
PERSUADE MY COLLEAGUES AND MY PARTY THAT THE FUTURE OF<br />
SO MANY OF OUR INSTITUTIONS AND SERVICES HEALTH,<br />
TRANSPORT, SEWERAGE, HOUSING, ENVIRONMENTAL STANDARDS,<br />
CHILD CARE, ALL THE THINGS THAT MAKE FOR THE BETTERMENT<br />
AND HAPPINESS OF OUR PEOPLE DEPENDED ON STRONG LOCAL<br />
GOVERNMENT AND A MEASURE OF NATIONAL RESPONSIBILITY<br />
FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT. So I APPLAUD WHAT YOUR INSTITUTE<br />
STANDS FOR. YOU ARE DEDICATED TO BETTER AND MORE<br />
EFFICIENT LOCAL GOVERNMENT; SO AM I, YOU PERCEIVE THE<br />
NATIONAL IMPORTANCE OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT; SO DO WE.<br />
YOU BELIEVE THAT SOUND LOCAL GOVERNMENT IS FUNDAMENTAL<br />
TO THE WELL BEING OF OUR PEOPLE; SO DO WE. .1/ 3 </p>
<p>3<br />
ONE IN FACT KJO'. S LETTER THAN YOU TIE LONG<br />
AND SORRY HISTORY OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT IN THIS COUNTRY, THE<br />
YEARS OF NEGLECT AND INDIFFERENCE FRCii WHICH IT HAS<br />
SUFFERED, AND THE ATMOSPHERE OF PERPETUAL FINAINCIAL<br />
CRISIS THAT HAS SURROUNDED IT FOR GENERATIONS. I HAVE<br />
OFTEN MARVELLED AT THE DEDICATION AND FORTITUDE OF MEN<br />
WHO HAVE CONTINUED TO SERVE LOCAL GOVERNMENT IN THE FACE<br />
OF SUCH ODDS,. So LET ME PUT TO YOU SOME PROPOSITIONS<br />
WHICH ARE CENTRAL TO MY GOVERNMENT'S WHOLE APPROACH TO<br />
LOCAL GOVERNMENT AND WHICH I BELIEVE WILL HAVE YOUR<br />
ASSENT AS THE MEN AND WOMEN MOST CONCERNED, AND EXPERT,<br />
IN THIS FIELD. PMY FIRST PROPOSITION 13 THAT NO ONE,<br />
WHATEVER HIS PARTY, WHATEVER HIS BELIEFS, CAN BE SATISFIED<br />
WITH LOCAL GOVERNMENT AS IT IS. BASICALLY THIS IS A<br />
QUESTION OF THE RESPONSIBILITIES OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT<br />
OUTSTRIPPING ITS MEANS. LOCAL GOVERNMENT IS CALLED<br />
UPON TO PROVIDE MORE AND MORE SERVICES TO MORE AND<br />
MORE PEOPLE. THIS IS NOT SOMETHING IT HAS SOUGHT<br />
FOR ITSELF; IT IS SOMETHING DEMANDED BY THE PEOPLE.<br />
AND THE RESOURCES OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT ARE MANIFESTLY<br />
INADEQUATE TO MEET THOSE DEMANDS. / 4 </p>
<p>i'<br />
1IY SECOND PROPOSITION IS THAT FUNDAMENTAL<br />
CHANGES ARE NEEDED TO GIVE LOCAL GOVERNMENT PROPER ACCESS<br />
TO THE NATION'S FINANCIAL RESOURCES. FOR THAT REASON<br />
WE PROPOSE, AS YOU KNOW, TO ASK THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE<br />
TO APPROVE A CONSTITUTIONAL AMENDMENT THAT WILL REMOVE,<br />
ONCE AND FOR ALL, THE PRESENT FINANCIAL PARRIERS TO<br />
EFFICIENT LOCAL GOVERNMENT AND ITS FULL AND EFFECTIVE<br />
PARTNERSHIP IN A FEDERAL SYSTEM.<br />
AND MY THIRD PROPOSITION IS THAT UNLESS THAT<br />
REFERENDUM IS CARRIED, UNLESS IT IS SUPPORTED BY ALL ' WHO<br />
HAVE THE TRUE INTERESTS OF LOCAL GOVERINENT AT HEART,<br />
UNLESS IT HAS THE VIGOROUS WORKING SUPPORT OF MEN SUCH<br />
AS YOU, LOCAL GOVERNMENT WILL BE CONFINED FOR FURTHER<br />
GENERATIONS IN ITS PRESENT STRAITJACKET OF STAGNATION<br />
AND IMPOVERISHMENT. / s. 1 </p>
<p>I DO NOT THINK WE CAN APPROACH THIS QUESTION<br />
RATIONALLY UNTIL WE CLEAR OUR MINDS OF IRRELEVANT CANT<br />
PHRASES AND TIRED SLOGANS ABOUT " CENTRALISM" AND " STATE<br />
RIGHTS". I CONFESS THAT I FIND IT STRANGE THAT A<br />
GOVERNMENT SUCH AS MINE, DEDICATED NOT ONLY TO THE<br />
GROWTH BUT TO THE GREATER AUTONOMY OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT,<br />
SHOULD BE ACCUSED OF CENTRALISM ON THAT SCORE.<br />
THE VERY REVERSE IS TRUE. ' HAT WE SEEK TO DO IS<br />
LIBERATE LOCAL GOVERNMENT FROM ITS FORCED DEPENDENCE<br />
ON STATE ADMINISTRATIONS THAT CANNOT GIVE IT THE<br />
RESOURCES IT NEEDS. ARE NOT SEEKING TO DENY<br />
EITHER POWER OR FINANCIAL RESOURCES TO THE STATES.<br />
WHAT WE ARE SEEKING IS A PROPER AND RATIONAL BALANCE<br />
BETWEEN THE THREE TIERS OF GOVERNMENT NATIONAL,<br />
STATE AND LOCAL THAT WILL ENABLE EACH TO FUNCTION<br />
EFFICIENTLY AND DISCHARGE ITS RESPONSIBILITIES TO THE<br />
FULL. </p>
<p>r<br />
S-UJ<br />
IN THIS CONTEXT I SHOULD LIKE TO RECALL TO YOU<br />
SOME WORDS USED BY AR JUSTICE ELSE MITCHELL, CHAIRMAN OF<br />
THE ROYAL COMMISSION INTO NEW SOUTH 4ALES LAND VALUATION<br />
RATING SYSTEMS IN 1965. HE SAID: " PRESENT CENTRALISED<br />
POLICIES, WHICH HAVE REDUCED LOCAL GOVERNMENT TO A STATE<br />
OF VASSALAGE AND COUNCILS TO THE ROLE OF MENDICANTS,<br />
NEED DRASTIC REAPPRAISEMENT, THOUGH I WONDER IF STATE<br />
GOVERNMENTS ARE VERY ANXIOUS FOR LOCAL AUTHORITIES TO<br />
GAIN ANY SUBSTANTIAL MEASURE OF FINANCIAL INDEPENDENCE<br />
OR TO DEVELOP QUALITIES OF STRONG LOCAL AUTONOMY."<br />
HIS HONOUR HIGHLIGHTED A FACT THAT IS FREQUENTLY<br />
OVERLOOKED WHEN ACCUSATIONS OF " CENTRALISM" ARE BANDIED<br />
AROUND. AND IT IS THIS: WITHIN THEIR OWN BORDERS<br />
THE STATES TEND TO BE MUCH MORE CENTRALIST AND<br />
CENTRALISED THAN CANBERRA HAS EVER ASPIRED TO BE<br />
WITHIN THE CONTINENT. / 7 </p>
<p>7<br />
THIS HAS BEEN SO SINCE LONG BEFORE FEDERATION.<br />
ONE HAS ONLY TO REMEMBER THAT THE MAINLAND COLONIES,,<br />
WITH THE EXCEPTION OF . UEENSLAND, BUILT THEIR RAILWAY<br />
SYSTEMS TO ENSURE CENTRALISATION UPON THEIR CAPITAL CITIES.<br />
WHY SHOULD CENTRALISM, SO CALLED, BE LESS BANEFUL WHEN<br />
PRACTISED BY A STATE GOVERNMENT THAN WHEN PRACTISED BY<br />
THE COMMONWEALTH? IT IS ABSURD TO SUPPOSE THAT COMMUNITIES<br />
SUCH AS SHEPPARTON OR ARMIDALE, FOR EXAMPLE, SHOULD FEEL<br />
ANY GREATER KINSHIP WITH MIELBOURNE OR SYDNEY THAN THEY<br />
DO WITH CANBERRA. IT IS ABSURD TO IMAGINE THAT THERE IS<br />
SOME NATURAL LOGIC IN A SITUATION THAT REQUIRES A SEWERAGE<br />
PROGRAM IN BOURKE OR A ROAD PROGRAM IN GEELONG TO RE LY ON,<br />
THE BENEVOLENCE OF MACQUARIE STREET OR SPRING STREET.<br />
WHAT MAGIC FORMULA DO THE STATES POSSESS FOR R EDUCING<br />
INEQUALITIES WITHIN THEIR OWN BOUNDARIES? OUR WHOLE<br />
HISTORY HAS SHOWN THAT THE INEQUALITIES BETWEEN REGIONS<br />
WITHIN THE STATES ARE AT LEAST AS GREAT AS THOSE BETWEEN<br />
THE STATES THEMSELVES. IN EACH STATE THERE ARE REGIONS AND<br />
DISTRICTS WHICH CANNOT, BY REASONABLE EFFORT, FUNCTION ON<br />
THE STANDARD OF OTHER REG! ONS AND DISTRICTS. IT IS NO0 ANSWER<br />
TO THESE PROBLEMS, THESE INHERENT AND CHRONIC INEQUALITIES,<br />
TO ARGUE ABOUT STATE RIGHTS. IT IS NOT THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT<br />
BUT STATE GOVERNMENTS WHICH HAVE CENTRALISED LOCAL GOVERNMElJT.<br />
IT IS UNDER STATE GOVERNMENTS THAT LOCAL GOVERNMENT HAS<br />
STAGNATED AND DECLINED. W4HAT I ASK YOU TO DO IS LOOIK AFRESH<br />
AT THESE PROBLEMS, TO START FROM THE BASIC ASSUMPTION THAT<br />
LOCAL GOVERNMENT MUST BE GIVEN THE RESOURCES TO DO ITS JOB,<br />
AND TO IGNORE THESE FUTILE AND IRRELEVANT ARGUMENTS ABOUT<br />
RIGHTS AND AREAS OF RESPONSIBILITY. I 1 / 13 </p>
<p>8<br />
I THINK I CAN BEST DISPOSE OF THE CENTRALIST<br />
RED HERRING BY REFERRING TO SOME REMARKS I MADE IN<br />
NOVEMBER 1971 AT A SEMINAR ON THE FUTURE OF FEDERALISM<br />
AT THE AUSTRALIAN NATIONAL UNIVERSITY. YOU WILL SEE<br />
THE CONSISTENCY OF MY PARTY'S APPROACH, AND MY GOVERNMENT'S<br />
APPROACH, TO THESE QUESTIONS, I SAID: " THE FUTURE<br />
OF AUSTRALIAN FEDERALISM DEPENDS FAR MORE UPON<br />
MUNICIPALITIES THAN UPON THE COMMONWEALTH OR THE STATES.<br />
FEDERALISM IS THREATENED NOT BY THE DRIFT OF ' POWER FROM<br />
STATE CAPITALS TO CANBERRA BUT BY THE STATES IMPOSING<br />
UPON MUNICIPALITIES FUNCTIONS WHICH ARE BEYOND THEIR<br />
MEANS. IT IS NOT THE COMMONWEALTH BUT THE STATES WHICH<br />
MUST RESIST OR FEAR A REASSESSMENT OF FUNCTIONS IN OUR<br />
FEDERATION, FOR THE STATES TREAT MUNICIPALITIES EVEN MORE<br />
FRUGALLY THAN THE STATES CLAIM THAT THEY THEMSELVES ARE<br />
TREATED BY THE COMMONWEALTH." THAT WAS OUR POSITION<br />
BEFORE THE ELECTION; IT IS OUR POSITION TODAY, ALL OUR<br />
POLICIES HAVE BEEN DIRECTED TO ACHIEVING THOSE AIMS, TO<br />
ELEVATING THE STATUS AND IMPORTANCE OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT<br />
WITHIN THE FEDERAL SYSTEM. FAR FROM ADVOCATING CENTRALISM<br />
OR CONCENTRATION OF POWER, I BELIEVE THERE IS A PRESSING CASE<br />
FOR DECENTRALISATION OF AUTHORITY SO THAT MANY GOVERNMENT<br />
FUNCTIONS IN CRITICAL AREAS, SUCH AS WELFARE, CULTURE AND<br />
THE ENVIRONMENT, WILL BE PERFORMED BY LOCAL GOVERNMENT<br />
AUTHORITIES EQUIPPED WITH THE RESOURCES THEY NEED. / 9 </p>
<p>IE SHOULD NEVER, FORGET THE DISGRACEFUL WAY L-OCAL<br />
GOVERNMENT HAS BEEN NEGLECTED AND DOWNGRADED SIN4CE TlF! E<br />
VERY BEGINNINGS OF OUR FEDERATION. ANYONE LOOKING BACK<br />
ON THlE HISTORY OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT MUST FIND IT INEXPLICABLE<br />
TODAY THAT THE FRAHERS OF THE CONSTITUTION MADE NO MENTION<br />
OF LOCAL GOVERN4MEN4T AT ALL. AS LATE AS 1927, WHEN THE<br />
FINANCIAL AGREEMENT BETWEEN'THE COMMONWEALTH AND THE<br />
STATES WAS DRAWN UP, LOCAL GOVERNMENT WAS STILL IGNORED.<br />
IF THE FINANCIAL AGREEMENT WERE BEING DRAWN UP TODAY IT IS<br />
INCONCEIVABLE THAT THESE AUTHIORITIES WOULD BE OVERLOOKED.<br />
IT WAS NOT UNTIL 1936 THAT TH4E LOAN COUNCIL BEGAN DEALING<br />
WITH THE BORROWINGS OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT AUTHORITIES. YET<br />
IN ALL THAT TIME, AND ESPECIALLY SINCE THE WAR, THE<br />
SCALE OF OPERATIONS OF LOCAL AND SEMI-GOVERNMENT<br />
AUTHORITIES HAS BEEN STEADILY TRANSFORMED. WE HAVE ONLY<br />
TO LOOK AT THlE FIGURES OF COMPAFr'ATIVE DEBTS. THE INDEBTEDNESS<br />
OF THE COMMONWEALTH HAS NOT GROWN SINCE THE WAR BUT THE DEBTS<br />
OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT AND SEMI-GOVERNMEN4T AUTHORITIES HAVE<br />
MULTIPLIED MORE THAN TWELVE TIMES. LOCAL GOVERNMENT<br />
AUTHORITIES ARE NOW BORROWING MORE EACH YEAR THAN THE TOTAL<br />
AMOUNT OF THEIR OUTSTANDING DEBT ONLY 20 YEARS OR SO AGO.<br />
AT THE SAME TIME THERE HAVE BEEN ACCELERATING DEIMANDS QUITE<br />
NATURAL AND PREDICTABLE DEMANDS ON THE SaCRVICES WHICH LOCAL<br />
GOVERNMENT PROVIDES. YET NOTHING W". AS DONE TO REDRESS THESE<br />
DEFICIENCIES; NOTHING WAS DON! E TO CORRECT A SYSTEM" THAT<br />
ALLOWED THEM TO WORSEN YEAR BY YEAR. </p>
<p>9A<br />
IN THIS CONTEXT I CAN HARDLY DO BETTER THAN REFER<br />
YOU TO SOME OF THE FINDINGS OF THE RECENT REPORT OF THE<br />
COMMITTEE OF INQUIRY INTO LOCAL GOVERNMENT .'. REAS AND<br />
ADMINISTRATION IN IIEW SOUTH vALES, KNOWN AS THE OARNETT REPORT.<br />
THE COMMITTEE POINTED OUT THAT LOCAL GOVERNMENT'S SHARE OF<br />
TOTAL GOVERNMENT EXPENDITURES HAS BEEN SHRI,' KING STEADILY<br />
IN AUSTRALIA. IN 1969-70 IT REPRESENTED 7.11' 7 OF TOTAL<br />
GOVERNMENT EXPENDITURE IN AUSTRALIA, COMPARED WITH 21.670<br />
IN CANADA, 25,14% IN THE UNITED STATES AND 34.6% IN GREAT<br />
BRITAIN ( WHERE, IT MUST BE SAID, THERE ARE NO STATE GOVERNMENTS),<br />
THE COMMITTEE REPORT'ED THAT IN THE VIEW OF MOST SHIRE COUNCILS<br />
IN [ JEW SOUTH ' IALES, " THEIR AREAS COULD rNOT SURVIVE WITHOUT<br />
A CONTINUANCE OF LARGE CENTRAL GOVERNMENT GRANTS AND,<br />
WITHOUT EXCEPTION, COUNCILS BELIEVED THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT'S<br />
INVOLVEMENT IN FINANCING LOCAL GOVERNMENT WAS ESSENTIAL."<br />
THE COMMITTEE, AS YOU KNOW, RECOMMENDED SOME AMALGAMATION<br />
OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT AUTHORITIES, THIS IS AN ISSUE THAT<br />
NEED NOT CONCERN US HERE, THOUGH I SHOULD SAY THAT THE<br />
COMMITTEE'S BELIEFS HAPPEN TO ACCORD WITH MY OWN, IT IS<br />
SUFFICIENT TO RECALL THAT BOTH THE LOCAL GOVERNMENT<br />
ASSOCIATION AND THE SHIRES ASSOCIATION, TOGETHER REPRESENTING<br />
ALMOST ALL LOCAL COUNCI-LS IN NEW SOUTH WALES, AGREED THAT<br />
THERE WAS A NEED FOR A REVIEW OF THE LOCAL GOVERNMENT SYSTEM,<br />
IN THE WORDS OF THE REPORT, " THEY POINTED OUT THAT NO<br />
INSTITUTIONS COULD STAND STILL, LEAST OF ALL GOVERNMENT<br />
INSTITUTIONS, YET MAJOR REFORMS IN LOCAL GOVERNMEINT HAD<br />
BEEN FEW AND FAR BETWEEN." it e I! </p>
<p>i0<br />
THE FACT IS THAT FOR. AT LEAST TWO DECADES<br />
SUCCESSIVE GOVERNMENTS STOOD BY WHILE SERIOUS DEFICIENCIES<br />
DEVELOPED IN MANY OF THE PUBLIC SERVICES AND FACILITIES<br />
WHICH IT WAS THE DUTY OF THE STATE-LOCAL GOVERNMENT<br />
SECTOR TO PROVIDE. PARTLY THIS WAS DUE TO INSUFFICIENT<br />
RESOURCES.; BUT IT WAS ALSO A REFLECTION OF PROCESSES<br />
OF PLANNING AND DETERMINING PRIORITIES WHICH WERE<br />
INADEQUATE OR NARROWLY BASED. HiY GOVERNMENT HAS SET<br />
ITSELF THE TASK OF HELPING TO REMEDY THESE DEFICIENCIES<br />
IN CO-OPERATION WITH THE STATES AND THEIR AUTHORITIES.<br />
.4E HAVE MADE A STRONG BEGINNING WITAESS THE NEW OR<br />
ENLARGED ALLOCATIONS IN OUR BUDGET FOR 1973-74 FOR<br />
EDUCATION, COMMUNITY HEALTH, PUBLIC HOUSIIG, SEWERAGE<br />
SElVICES, LAND MANAGEMENT, URBAN TRANSPORT AND GROWTH<br />
CENTRES. TOTAL ALLOCATIONS TO THE STATES IN 1973-74,<br />
INCLUDING THE STATE GOVERNMENTS' LOAN COUNCIL PROGRAMS,<br />
BUT EXCLUDING UNEMPLOYMENT RELIEF GRANTS, ARE ESTIMATED<br />
TO BE NO LESS THAN 2Lt PER CENT GREATER THAN T: iE<br />
CORRESPONDING ALLOCATIONS IN 1972-73. </p>
<p>1~ 1-<br />
IT IS NOT, HOWEVER, SIMPLY A MATTER OF PROVIDING<br />
MORE MONEY. AT THE RISK OF VOICING A TRUISM, LET ME SAY<br />
THAT THE IMPORTANCE OF LOCAL SOVENIMENT DERIVES FROM<br />
THE VERY FACT THAT IT IS LOCAL THAT THE SERVICES<br />
AND FACILITIES IT PROVIDES HAVE SUCH A CLOSE AND DIRECT<br />
IMPACT ON THE WELFARE OF THE POPULATION IT SERVES.<br />
IT IS OUR AIM, IN PART, TO MAKE AVAILABLE TO LOCAL<br />
GOVERNMENT FUNDS MORE ADEQUAFE FOP ITS FUNCTIONS.<br />
BUT OUR AIM IS LARGER THAN THAT. IF LOCAL<br />
GOVERNMENT IS TO PLAY THE FULLER AND MORE EFFECTIVE<br />
PART THAT I BELIEVE THE COMMUNITY WISHES IT TO PLAY,<br />
THEN WE MUST ALSO INCREASE THE EFFECTIVE INFLUENCE<br />
LOCAL GOVERNMENT EXERCISES Ii RELATION ro THE<br />
FUNDAMENTAL DECISION-MAKING AFFECTING ITS ACTIVITIES.<br />
IT WILL REPRESENT A MOST SIGNIFICANT STEP TOWARDS<br />
REAL FEDERALISM,, REAL LOCAL PARTICIPATION IN, PUBLIC<br />
AFFAIRS AND, INDEED, REAL DECENTRALISATION OF<br />
GOVERNMENT WHEN THIS IS ACHIEVED. / i11 </p>
<p>12<br />
WE HAVE ALREADY TAKEN-SEVERAL IMPORTANT<br />
INITIATIVES IN THAT DIRECTION. IN ITS AUTUMN SITTINGS<br />
LAST YEAR WITHIN SIX M9NTAIS OF THE ELECTION THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN PARLIAMENT PASSED A NEW~ GRANITS COMMISSION<br />
ACT AUTHORISING THAT BODY TO INOUiRE INJTO APPLICAVIOIS<br />
FOR ASSISTANCE BY REGIONAL ORGANISATIONS OF LOCAL<br />
GOVERNMENT. ANY ASS ISTANCE RECOMMENDED BY THE COtIMI SSION<br />
AND APPROVED BY THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT WILL BE PAID<br />
TO THE STATES UNDER SECTION 96 OF THE CONSTITUTION ON<br />
CONDITION THAT IT BE PASSED ON T0 THE LOCAL GOVERNMENT<br />
ORGANISATIONS CONCERNED. ADDITIONAL MENSERS HAVE SEENJ<br />
APPOINTED TO THE COMIMISSIO! AND ITS STAFF IS BEING<br />
EXPANDED TO ENABLE IT TO DEAL WITH THIS LARGE NEW<br />
RESPONSIBILITY. IT IS HOPED THAT APPLICATIONS SY<br />
REGIONAL ORGANISATIONS WILL BEGIN TO BE RECEIVED AND<br />
CONSIDERED EARLY THIS YEAR. FROM NOW ON, THE COMMISSION<br />
WILL PLAY THE SAME ROLE IN REDUCING INEQUALITIES BETWEEN<br />
REGIONS AS IT HAS BETWEEN THE STATES SINCE 193). I SHOULD<br />
STRESS THAT THIS REFORM PAYS DUE HEED TO THE NATURAL<br />
RIGHTS AND INTERESTS OF THE STATES. A'NY REGIONAL AUTHORITY<br />
THAT APPLIES FOR SPECIAL ASSISTANCE WILL BE REQUIRED TO<br />
NOTIFY THE APPROPRIATE STATE JINISTER, AND THE COMMISSION<br />
ITSELF WILL BE REQUIRED TO CONSIDER ANY SUBMISSIONS FROM<br />
STATE flINISTERS ON THE APPLICATION. 1013 </p>
<p>13<br />
OUR SECOND GREAT IITIATIVE LAST YEAR WAS<br />
TO SEEK A VOICE AND A VOTE FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT ON THE<br />
LOA1N COUNCIL. OUR PURPOSE WAS, AND STILL IS., TO ADMIT<br />
REPRESENTATIVES OF ALDERMEN AND COUNCILLORS FROM EACH<br />
STATE AND ENABLE THE COMMONWEALTH, ON REQUEST, TO<br />
RAISE APPROVED LOANS OHi BE!. IALF OF SEMI-GOVERNMENT<br />
AND LOCAL GOVERNMENT AUTHORITIES. THEY WOULD TIUS<br />
HAVE THE ADVANTAGE OF THE LONGER PERIOD AND LOWER<br />
INTEREST RATES THAT APPLY TO LOANS RAISED BY THE<br />
COMMONWEALTH ON BEHALF OF THE STATES. THIS WAS A<br />
FIRM UNDERTAKING IN MY POLICY SPEECH AT THE LAST<br />
ELECTIONS. I FIRST RAISED THE PROPOSALS WITH THE<br />
PREMIERS AT THE CONSTITUTIONAL CONVENTION IN SEPTEMSER<br />
LAST YEAR AND I REMIND YOU THAT IT WAS AT THE EXPRESS<br />
INSISTENCE OF MY GOVERNMENT THAT LOCAL GOVERNMENT<br />
REPRESENTATIVES WERE ADMITTED TO THE CONVENTION'S<br />
DELIBERATIONS. MADE IT CLEAR FROM THE START THAT<br />
WITHOUT YOUR PARTICIPATION WE WOULD HAVE NO PART IN<br />
THE CONVENTION AT ALL. I DOUBT IF ANYONE, IN<br />
RETROSPECT, WOULD CLAIM MUCH SUCCESS FOR THAT<br />
CONVENTION, BUT IT IS WORTH RECALLING SOME WORDS THAT<br />
I USED TO THE PREMIERS WHEN EXPLAINING THE PURPOSE OF<br />
OUR PROPOSALS. , I14 </p>
<p>I1!<br />
I TOLD THE CONVENTION: " I HAVE NO DOUBT THAT<br />
THE OVERRIDING CONSIDERATION IN MANY MINDS HERE RELATES<br />
TO THE FINANCIAL RELATIONS BETWEE; I THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
GOVERNMENT AND THE STATES. SOtlE OF YOU MAY PREFER<br />
TO BELIEVE THAT THE OVERRIDING CONSIDERATION IN MY<br />
MIND IS TO CONTINUE AND. EVE;-COMPOUND THE PRESENT<br />
SITUATION BY WHICH THE 1. ATIONALI GOVERNMENT DOMI! JATES<br />
THE FINANCIAL RELATIONS BET'iEEN IT AND THE STATES,<br />
THAT IS NOT TRUE. IIY OVERRIDING CONSIDERATION<br />
AND CONCERN IN THIS CONTEXT IS TO BALANCE THE<br />
FUNCTIONS AND FINACES OF THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT,<br />
STATE AND LOCAL GOVERNMENTS TO ENSURE ADEQUATE<br />
SERVICES AND DEVELOPMENTS OF RESOURCES. I WISH<br />
EACH LEVEL OF GOVERNMENT TO BE IN A POSITION TO<br />
PERFORM BETTER ITS ASSIGNED FUNCTIONS, FOR THE<br />
BETTER WELFARE OF ALL OUR CITIZENS, WHEREVER THEY<br />
LIVE." </p>
<p>15<br />
IN OCTOBER LAST YEAR A SPECIAL PREMIERS'<br />
CONFERENCE WAS HELD TO DISCUSS THESE QUESTIONS. AT<br />
THAT CONFERENCE IN CANBERRA I AGAIN PROPOSED THAT<br />
LOCAL GOVERNMENT HAVE BOTH A VOICE AND A VOTE ON THE<br />
LOAN COUNCIL AND THAT THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT BE<br />
EMPOWERED TO BORROW MONEY ON LOCAL GOVElNMENTS'<br />
BEHALF. SPECIFICALLY I SUGGE.' TED THAT REPRESEFNTATIVES<br />
OF ELECTED LOCAL GOVERNMENT BE ADMITTED TO ALL LOA; J<br />
COUNCIL DISCUSSIONS, WITH A RIGHT TO VOTE ON THOSE<br />
MATTERS DIRECTLY AFFECTING THEIR INTERESTS ESSENTIALLY,<br />
THE BORROWING PROGRAMS FOR THE BODIES THEY REPRESENT<br />
AND THE ALLOCATIONS OF THESE PROGRAMS. I NLED HARDLY<br />
REMIND YOU OF THE RESULTS OF THAT MEETING. JUR<br />
PROPOSALS WERE TURNED DOWN. TIlE IMPORTANT POINT<br />
TO REMEMBER IS THAT THE PROPOSED CHAiJGES COULD<br />
HAVE BEEN EFFECTED QUITE SIMPLY AT THAT MEETING BY<br />
AN AGREEMENT IN PRINCIPLE BETWEEN THE PREMIERS AND<br />
THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERN;. IENT TO AMEND THE FINANCIAL AGREEMENT,<br />
IF THAT HAD BEEN DONE, NO CONSTITUTIONAL AMENDMENT WOULD<br />
HAVE BEEN REQUIRED. BUT WHEN THE PREMIERS REJECTED OUR<br />
PROPOSALS WE HAD NO ALTERNATIVE BOUND AS WE WERE BY OUR<br />
MANDATE FROM THE PEOPLE BUT TO PROCEED WITH A REFERENDUM.<br />
THAT REFERENDUM, IF CARRIED, WILL EMPOWER THE NATIONAL<br />
PARLIAMENT TO BORROW ON BEHALF OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT AND<br />
GRANT FINANCIAL ASSISTANCE TO LOCAL GOVERNMENT DIRECTLY. ,/ 16 </p>
<p>if)<br />
IT MUST SURELY STRIKE YOU AS ODD THAT, ' HILE<br />
WE HAVE ESTABLISHED ARRANGEMENTS FOR BORROWINGS DY STATE<br />
GOVERNMENTS TO BE UNDERTAKEN ON THEIR BEHALF BY THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT, LOCAL GOVERNMENT AUTHORITIES ARE<br />
LARGELY LEFT TO FEND FOR THEMSELVES IN THE CAPITAL MARKETS.<br />
' ITH THE GROWING COMPLEXITY AND SOPHISTICATION OF THESrE<br />
MARKETS THEY ARE HANDICAPPED AS BORROWERS. THEY MUST<br />
COMPETE ON THE MONEY MARKET AMONG THEMSELVES, AGAINST<br />
THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT AND AGAINST OTHER FINANCIAL<br />
ORGANISATIONS. GIVEN THE NATURE AND RANGE OF PUBLIC<br />
SERVICES AND FACILITIES THAT LOCAL GOVERNMENT AUTHORITIES<br />
ARE CALLED UPON TO PROVIDE, WHY SHOULDN'T FHE AUSTRALIAN<br />
GOVERNMENT, WITH ITS SUPERIOR CAPACITY AS A BORROWIER,<br />
UNDERTAKE BORROWINGS ON THEIR BEHALF?<br />
THE COSTS OF SERVICING THEIR BORROWINGS BEAR<br />
HEAVILY AND INCREASINGLY SO ON THE BUDGETS OF LOCAL<br />
GOVERNMENT AUTHORITIES. IHILE THE PICTURE DIFFERS<br />
FROM STATE TO STATE, AND BETWEEN INDIVIDUAL AUTHORITIES,<br />
OVERALL INTEREST PAYMENTS BY LOCAL GOVERNMENT AUTHORITIES<br />
WOULD NO'WY BE EQUIVALENT TO ABOUT 12 PER CENT OF THEIR<br />
REVENUES. INTEREST PAYMENTS PLUS CAPITAL REPAYMENTS<br />
AMOUNTED TO $ 177.5 MILLION IN 1970-71, EQUIVALENT TO<br />
ABOUT 25 PER CENT OF REVENUES. ./ 17 </p>
<p>17<br />
You HAVE HEARD IT SAID AND NO DOUBT YOU WILL<br />
HEAR IT AGAIN THAT IF WE WANT TO HELP LOCAL GOVERNMENT<br />
THEN ALL WE NEED . DO IS GIVE MORE MONEY TO THE ) TATES AJD<br />
LET THE STATES DISBURSE IT OR RAISE FUNDS IN THE USUAL<br />
WAY. THAT ARGUMENT IGNORES AN" D OBSCURES THE REAL<br />
ISSUES IN THIS REFERENDUM, FOR ONE THING IT IS A MISTAKE,<br />
AS I HAVE SAID, TO SUPPOSE THAT T; 1IS ARGUMENT IS ABOUT<br />
MONEY ALONE, THOUGH MORE MONEY 13 CERTAI: LY ;! EEDED,<br />
IT IS VERY MUCH AN ARGUMENT. ABOUT BALAIJCING AVAILABLE<br />
RESOURCES, AND FLEXIBILITY IN THE C2EATIONI AND APPLICATIONJ<br />
OF THOSE RESOURCES, IT IS ALSO AN ARGUMENT A30UT THE<br />
ULTIMATE STATUS OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT ITSELF. Is IT TO<br />
REMAIN A VASSAL OF THE STATES, A POOR RELATION OF THE<br />
STATES, OR IS IT TO BE GIVEN ITS RIGHTFUL AND HONOURED<br />
PLACE AS FAR AS POSSIBLE, AN INDEFPENDE!' T AIND DISTINCTIVE<br />
PLACE AS AN EQUAL PARTNER IN THE FEDERAL SYSTEM?<br />
FOR MY PART I HAVE NO WISH TO SEE LOCAL GOVERNMENT BECOME<br />
AN APPENDAGE OF THE NATIONAL GOVERNMENT ANY MORE THAN I<br />
WANT IT TO REMAIN AN APPENDAGE OF THE STATE GOVERNMENTS,<br />
BUT I DO WANT IT TO HAVE ADEQUATE AND REASONABLE ACCESS<br />
TO THE NATION'S FINANCIAL RESOURCES. . IE ARE NOT SEEKING TO DENY<br />
ANY RIGHTS OR POWERS OR RESOURCES TO THE STATES. INDEED<br />
I WOULD BE THE FIRST TO ACKNOWLEDGE THAT THE STATES THEMSELVES<br />
HAVE OFTEN BEEN DEPRIVED OF THE FINANCIAL RESOURCES THEY<br />
NEED, A GREAT NUMBER OF OUR INITIATIVES IN OUR FIRST YEAR<br />
OF OFFICE, A GREAT PART OF THE THRUST AND PHILOSOPHY OF OUR<br />
FIRST BUDGET, WERE CONCERNED WITH REDRESSING DEFICIENCIES<br />
IN THE REVENUES OF THE STATES. AND JUST AS I WANT THE STATES<br />
TO HAVE THE MEANS TO DISCHARGE THEIR RESPONSIBILITIES<br />
ADEQUATELY, SO I PRESS THE SAME CASE ON BEHALF OF LOCAL<br />
GOVERNMENT. ., 11 </p>
<p>13<br />
W; HY SHOULD LOCAL GOVERNMENT BE " 4HOLLY DEPENDENT<br />
ON THE STA-rES? WHY SHOULD IT BE DENIED THE RIGHT TO<br />
DEAL DIRECTLY WITH THE NATIONAL GOVERNMENT? THERE<br />
ARE MANY MATTERS WHERE THERE ARE DISTINCT ADVANTAGES<br />
IN DIRECT DEALING BETWEEN LOCAL GOVERNMENT AND THE<br />
NATIONAL GOVERNMENT. I GIVE YOU A RECENT AND HIGHLY<br />
TOPICAL EXAMPLE OUR FLOOD RELIEF PROGRAM. ', IE HAVE<br />
GUARANTEED TO THE PEOPLE OF'QUEENSLAND AND iEW SOUTH<br />
4ALES FLOOD RELIEF AND RECONSTRUCTION PROGRAMS THAT<br />
ARE VIRTUALLY OPEN-E4DED, OUR RESPONSE TO THE DISASTER<br />
WAS, QUITE NATURALLY, IMMEDIATE AND GENEROUS, IT IS<br />
EQUALLY NATURAL AND OBVIOUS THAT THE BEST WAY TO DISTRIBUTE<br />
AND ALLOCATE THOSE FUNDS IS BY DIRECT CONSULTATION<br />
BETWEEN THE AUTHORITY PROVIDING THEM AND THE REGIONAL<br />
AUTHORITIES WHO WILL BE USING THEM. AGAIN, AS YOU KNOW,<br />
WE HAVE AMBITIOUS PROGRAMS FOR SEWERAGE WORKS AND CHILD<br />
CARE FACILITIES AND HEALTH CENTRES. " IE HAVE EMBARKED ON<br />
OUR LONG-TERN PLANS FOR THE RENOVATION OF OUR SUBURBS AND<br />
THE CREATION OF NEW CITIES. IN THE NEXT FEW MONTHS WE SHALL<br />
BE MAKING ARRANGEMENTS WITH THE STATES TO ALLOCATE FUNDS FOR<br />
ROADS FOR THE NEXT FIVE YEAR PERIOD. IN ALL THESE AREAS<br />
IT IS QUITE ESSENTIAL AND I SHOULD HAVE THOUGHT, QUITE<br />
OBVIOUS THAT SUCCESS WILL DEPEND IN LARGE MEASURE ON<br />
OPPORTUNITIES FOR DIRECT DEAL-ING AND DIRECT FINANCIAL<br />
RELATIONSHIPS BETWEEN LOCAL GOVERNMENT AND THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
UOVERNMENT. So LET US BE QUITE CLEAR THAT THOSE WHO RESIST<br />
THIS REFERENDUM ARE NOT MER-LY FRUSTFRATING THE PROGRESS OF<br />
LOCAL GOVERNMENT; THEY ARE DOING THEIR BEST TO BLOCK THE<br />
NATIONAL GOVERNMENT'S PLANS FOR SOCIAL WELFARE AND REFORM<br />
ON AN UNPRECEDENTED SCALE. </p>
<p>19<br />
I SAID AT THE OUTSET THAT THE SUCCESS OF THIS<br />
REFERENDUM, WITH ALL ITS PROFOUND IMPLICATIONS FOR THE<br />
FUTURE OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT, WOULD DEPEND LARGELY ON YOUR<br />
SUPPORT, YOUR KNOWLEDGEABLE AND EXPERT SUPPORT AS<br />
ADMINISTRATORS IN THIS FIELD. I THI YOU MUST ASK<br />
YOURSELVES WHETHER YOU ARE CONTENT WITH LOCAL GOVERNMENT<br />
AS IT IS, WITH ITS GROWING ACCUMULATION OF DEBT, ITS<br />
WIDENING GAP BETWEEN RESPO4SIBILITIES AND RESOURCES,<br />
ITS ENDLESS NEED TO FORCE UP RATES AND CHARGES, ITS<br />
DEMEANED AND DIMINISHED STATUS IN ThE IhIERARCHY OF<br />
GOVERNMENT, ITS FRUSTRATIONS AND DISAPPOINTMENTS.<br />
IF YOU BELIEVE THAT LOCAL GOVERNMENT IS CRYING OUT FOR<br />
A NEN DEAL THEN I ASK YOU TO SUPPORT THIS REFERENDUM.<br />
YOU MUST BE THE OPINION MAKERS ON THIS ISSUE; YOUR<br />
THOUGHTS, YOUR OPINIONS, YOUR LETTERS, YOUR INFLUENCE<br />
ARE WHAT WILL COUNT. I MAKE NO APOLOGY FOR APPEALING<br />
TO YOU IN THIS WAY BECAUSE I THINK THE ISSUES ARE<br />
CRUCIAL AND THE CHOICE FUNDAMENTAL TO OUR WELFARE AND<br />
PROGRESS. WE DO NOT SEEK CHANGE FOR CHANGE'S SAKE.<br />
WE SEEK CHANGE BECAUSE IT IS DEMANDED OF US, FORCED<br />
UPON US BY INCREASINGLY DIFFICULT AND COMPLEX PROBLEMS<br />
OF SOCIAL PLANNING AND ECONOMIC MANAGEMENT. ' 4E CAN NO<br />
LONGER CLING TO OLD CONCEPTS, TO DOCUMENTS AND RULES<br />
AND AGREEMENTS DRAWN UP IN THE DISTANT PAST, TO IRRELEVANT<br />
OBSESSIONS WITH BOUNDARY LINES AND THE DEMARCATION OF RIGHTS<br />
AND INTERESTS. LET US ACKNOWLEDGE THAT OUR FIRST TASK<br />
OUR ONLY TASK IS TO ELEVATE LOCAL GOVERNMENT TO ITS PROPER<br />
PLACE IN AUSTRALIAN SOCIETY AND GIVE IT THE MEANS TO CARRY<br />
OUT ITS WORK FOR THE LASTING BENEFIT OF THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
