<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>117</transcript-id>
    <title>PRESS CONFERENCE, CANBERRA </title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/10/1959</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000117_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>PRESS CONFERENCE GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER RT.<br />HON. R. G. MENZIES, AT CANBERRA<br />ON THE 1ITH OCTOBER, 19 9 at 11 A. M.</p>
<p>QUESTION: Sir, yesterday it was announced that the Commonwealth was financing a Grant to the Monash University of up to about œ 500,000 and referred to a report by the Universities Commission. I was wondering if we could have a copy of the Report.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER: When I had the application from Victoria for a very<br />substantial increase in the amount that was being provi<br />-ded under the Murray Report for the Monash University,<br />I told the Premier that I would get the Universities<br />Commission to have a look at it because, after all,<br />that is the kind of thing they are there for. They examined<br />it and made a report to me and I sent it to him<br />with an indication that we were prepared to act on the<br />recommendations in the Report. There is no reason why<br />the report shouldn't be published but I notice in the<br />paper this morning that he's indicated, from his point<br />of view, that the Report should not be published until<br />after the Interim Council of Monash has had a chance to<br />look at it. Well, I don't quarrel with that, but as<br />soon as the Report has gone to the Interim Council I<br />will have no objection to publishing the report: in<br />fact, I think it ought to be made available. As a mat-_<br />ter of fact I have got, I think a supply of the necessary<br />copies so . that at a moment's notice they can go out,</p>
<p>QUESTION: Apart from the questions of Monash, Sir, does this Report<br />deal in any general terms with University enrolments<br />and extensions and so on, or any ratters on Monash<br />apart from what we have now?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER: No, this is a Report which relates to the Monash<br />Applic-tion. It does nontain statistics in relation to<br />the Melbourne University which are quite interesting.<br />Yes, I'll be delighted to have the report made available,<br />but I don't want to appear to be discourteous to the<br />Council</p>
<p>QUESTION: The Leader of the Labour Party in the Queensland Parliament<br />Mr Duggan, has described you as one of the outstanding<br />public men Australia has ever had</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER: I bet there's a catch coming ( Laughter)<br />but he says that you are politically lazy he said:<br />" Mr. Menzies had done great dis-service to Australia because<br />every international Mission with which he had been<br />associated had been a colossal failure. Would you reply<br />to his statement?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER: Oh, I wouldn't dream of sitting in judgment on Mr.<br />Duggan; I doubt whether I'm equal to that task.</p>
<p>QUESTION: Any announcement yet, Sir, on the Governor-General?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER: No.</p>
<p>QUESTION: Could you say what sta,-oe has been reached on the appointment.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER: Oh, I'm in communication with the Palace about it,</p>
<p>QUESTION: Do you expect it to come soon, Sir?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER: I don't know. I hope so.</p>
<p>QUESTION: As a result of Dr. Subandrio's visit to China, Sir, and<br />the agreement that has been reached between Indonesia<br />and China for mutual support in respect of Territorial<br />claims, Indonesia's support of China on Formosa and<br />China's support of Indonesia on West New Guinea, have<br />you thought about that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER: Well, I've read what has been published on the<br />matter and we have no official information. But all<br />those declarations, you know, may mean one of two thing;<br />they may simply mean ' Well, we give you moral support;<br />we announce our beliefs that you are entitled to West<br />New Guinea if you announce your belief that we're entitled<br />to Quemoy or Matsui or Formosa' I suppose there<br />are a number of people who support the claim in that<br />sense but the alternative meaningthat they are prepared<br />to support the claim by force is a very different<br />matter. Indeed, it will be remembered that Dr. Subandrio<br />in Australia went on the record to the effect that<br />Indonesia did not propose to establish its claim by<br />force and there is no reason to assume that he has<br />changed that ground, and therefore this mutual declaration<br />is, no doubt, one of sentiment or opinion it<br />doesn't necessarily involve military support.</p>
<p>QUESTION: A Conference in Germany, Mr. Menzies, has asked all<br />countries to co-operate in a world-wide survey on radio<br />-active fall-out and the effects on food, etc. Will<br />Australia co-onerate in that survey?<br />PRIME MINISTER: But Australia has been doing a iLot cf work in<br />that field already; we have a special commitoe, an<br />expert commit oe which, quite recently, made a report,<br />It's report showed that net only was the amount of fallout<br />in Australir insignificant ascompared with some other<br />countries, but that it didn't present any danger.<br />You remember the report wa3 published not long ago.<br />Well, that's a highly competent committee..<br />QUESTION: I presumc, Sir, that the information we obtain here is<br />available for international<br />PRIME MINISTER: Oh, yes.. Copies of our reports are made available,<br />and, of course, we ourselves have had reports<br />from the United Nations bodies which have gone into<br />this kind of thing. It stands to roaso:. hat in Australia<br />the amount of fall-out might be expected to be<br />negligible. Perhaps the Soviet Union, for example,<br />where there has been a great activity in these matters,<br />the fall-out might be much more considerable.<br />QUESTION: Now that Mr MacMillan has been returned is there any<br />suggestion of a Commonwealth Conference early next<br />year. You did mention earlier in the year<br />PRIME MINISTER: Oh, give them a chance,<br />QUESTION: Next April?<br />PRIME MINISTER: Well we've never had one in April. but keep on<br />going; you know as much about it as I do. I haven't<br />a clue,<br />QUESTION: Supplementary to that question, Sir, it has been reported<br />that Mr. MacMillan is planning to create a Ministry<br />of Science in his Governnent to bring it in line with<br />the Technilogical Age, Have you contemplat-d such a<br />Ministry here, Sir?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER: I can't say that I have. A good deal of our<br />technical resources are dealt with by the Department<br />of Supply and its a little premature to know what he<br />isgoing to do. It may be that he'll establish a Department<br />of Science or a Ministry of Science, but the<br />interesting thing will be what re-construction occurs<br />in other Departments.<br />QUESTION: It has been suggested that Supply Department<br />may go.<br />PRIME MINISTER: Quite so, If it were merely a matter of taking<br />over the Department of Supply it wouldnt be very radi.-<br />cal, but there may be that other things that are done<br />in other Departments there which could be aggregated<br />under one Minister. It's only guess work at this<br />stage. I'll be very interested myself to see the way<br />that's dealt with.<br />QUESTION: At the moment, Sir, it is true that our chief scientific<br />activities are under two Ministers, one from C. S. I.<br />R. O. and the Department of Supply?<br />PRIME MINISTER: Yes, that is quite right,<br />QUESTION: Do you see any advantage in the combination?<br />PRIME MINISTER: I don't know. I haven't given any thought to<br />creating a new Departmunt or an amalgamated one but<br />Ifm always willing to learn and I'll be interested to<br />see what goes on in England.<br />QUESTION: Can you tell us whether you have any specific programme<br />for the Divorce Bill? Do you hope to have it through<br />by Christmas?<br />PRIME MINISTER: I can't tell you. You had better ask the Attorney<br />that.<br />QUESTION: Does that not raise the question<br />PRIME MINISTER. Well thats a genuine consideration, but I know<br />that both the Attorney and I were hoping that this<br />Bill would be disposed of this year. but whether anything<br />that has happened affects that I don't know/; he's<br />just circulated a number of amendments. They may be<br />much less formidable than they might appear on the , urface<br />and a great number of them will no doubt be quite<br />verbal, but ask him. I think he's still hoping.<br />QUESTION: Have you given any thought as to whether there should<br />be<br />PRIME MINISTER: None whatever. As a natter of fact one reason<br />why I made it clear to my people that it mustn't bo no<br />sumed that the Session was going to end on th,; dde<br />that rumour had originaily mentioned, chat I had<br />hopes of disposing of the Divorce Bill; it's had a very<br />long airing and the Attorney's done a phenomenal amount<br />of work in relation to it, you know, in dealing with<br />groups of people and organizations.<br />QUESTION; There doesn't seem to have been a great deal of opposition<br />PRIME MINISTEI.: Not so far as I can sce.<br />QUESTION.: Didn't Mr. Holt make it clear, Sir, that the Government's<br />prograimme was in future always to prorogue the<br />Parliament and have an opening once a year at the begin<br />-ning of the year?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER: Frankly, I've forgotten whether he did.<br />QUESTION: Would the question of pro-rogation be contingent on<br />the date of arrival of the new Governor-General.<br />PRIME MINISTER: Well I suppose if we were to plenty of " ifs" in<br />this question if we prorogued, which I don't know<br />and if the new Governor-General can't be here at a time<br />when the house would normally meet, then no doubt we<br />would then consider whether the meeting of the new Session<br />after the pro-rogation would occur after his arrival.<br />All this is very elementary, my dear Watson,<br />and highly conditional.<br />QUESTION: There is no occasion that I can remember of an Administrator<br />having opened Parliament?<br />PRIME MINISTER: No. I can't recall one.<br />QUESTION: A rather interesting situation?<br />PRIME MINISTER: Mm.<br />QUESTION: you mentioned in an article that communications<br />were taking place between you and the Queensland Pren.<br />ier on Mount Isa. Are there any new developments cn<br />that7 Could you say whether the visit of Sir Rol. a,<br />Wilson and Mr Holt overseas may have any results?<br />PRIME MINISTER: The last communication I made to the Premier uas<br />that as Holt and Wilson were investigating certain naL**<br />ters and they would be back fairly shorcly, perhaps it<br />would be mo: e satisfactory and save time in the l! ong<br />run, if we had a further discussion after their return<br />Well they come back, tomorrow isn't it?<br />PRESSMAN: Due tomorrow in Sydney<br />PRIME MINISTER: They won't be here; well Holt won't be here, but<br />they will at once bring us up to date on this matter<br />and then I'll ask him to get in touch with Mr Nicklin.<br />QUESTION; Mr. Menzies do you hope to announce the Governnentis<br />tew 3-year Defence Plan before the Parliament rises foM<br />the year?<br />PRIME MINISTER: That's a difficult question to answer. I certainly<br />intend that it will be determined and announceable<br />some time in November because I have to go away<br />at the beginning of December and I want this matter tb<br />be fixed before I go, Whether that means actually<br />while the House is still sitting or just afterwards,<br />I don't know; it will be done as soon as it can be,<br />but it certainly will have to be done in November.<br />QUESTION: Have you had any final judgments from the Technical<br />people?<br />PRIME MINISTER: Don't ask me; I: m having a Conference with Mr,<br />Townley about it today. A lot of work, I know, has<br />been done on this.<br />QUESTION: Could you tell us anythingnow following Mr McElroy's<br />visit Sir?<br />PRIME MINISTER: No. There is nothing realoly.<br />QUESTION: It was more a goodwill visit was it?<br />PRIME MINISTER: Oh, yes, we didn't discuss any of the techniques<br />of the business with him.</p>
<p>QUESTION: Now that it is in retrospect, Sir, do you think that<br />we have learned anything from Princess Alexandra's visit<br />that can be useful in future? It seems to have<br />been extraordinarily successful..<br />PRIME MINISTER: I don't know. She did a lot to make it extraordinarily<br />successful herself, of course, because she<br />is a natural person. I think the thing we have to<br />do more and more in Australia is to get away from the<br />idea of long, formal, royal tours, you know every<br />State committees and organizations all that. They<br />are all right, and you can have one or two of those<br />occasionally, but I much prefer to think that we occasionally<br />have a Royal Visit, that's a very different<br />thing a Royal Visit from a Royal Tour. Somebody<br />might 0me out and visit one State for some particular<br />purpose; somebody might come out and actually have a<br />few weeks' holiday, but if it is to be every State for<br />every visitor, then we certainly won't have as many<br />visits. There people would say " Oh, this is becoming<br />too much". I'm hoping to encourage the idea of the<br />occasional, informal easy visit. This Princess went to<br />three States. I don't think there was any really bitter<br />complaint from the other three. The next visitor<br />might go to two or one. Let's get the formality out<br />of it. By formality I don't necessarily mean that they<br />have to shake hands with Prime Ministers and Premiers,<br />because they'll do that in any case, but that they<br />won't have these great programmes in which every day.<br />brings forth its visit to so-and-so and its this or<br />that, in some other locality. There is no escape from<br />those when you have a first visit from the Queen, for<br />example, a visit from the Queen Mother which has some<br />particular historic and personal interest for Australia.<br />But I'm hoping that in future we'll be able to eliminate<br />some of the aspects of a highly organised tour and substitute<br />some of the aspects of a personal visit.<br />QUESTION; Did the military advisers of SEATOactually, at the<br />time of their meeting, recently, get some actual concrete<br />schemes agreed on to intervene militarily if the<br />situation required it in Laos?<br />PRIME MINISTER: Oh, you wouldn't expect me to answer a question<br />like that would you?<br />QUESTION: Well, did they just " waffle", or did they have anything-<br />PRIME MINISTER: I've no statement to make.<br />QUESTION: Senator Spooner said in the Senate the other day, Mr,<br />Menzies, that he would confer with you on Members'<br />p: ivileges. I was wondering if he had spoken to you<br />alrout it yet?<br />PRIME MINISTER: Senator Spooner, unfortunately, is on the Sick<br />List. He's in hospital.<br />QUESTION; SEnator Aylett said that he wanted the Parliament and<br />Gcvernment to protect him from the criticisrisof the<br />kind that he has been getting. Have you any comment<br />t: make on-Senator Aylett's position?<br />PRIME MINISTER: Well, we've all felt that way occasionally.<br />QUESTION: Were you surprised, Sir, when you heard of the Christmas<br />Island rackets?<br />PRIME MINISTER: I concurred with the action taken by the Minister<br />very swiftly. Yes.</p>
<p>QUESTION: Do you thinlc Sir that it's likely that there will be<br />any anendrient to the rules relating to thle Secretaries<br />and Offices to require they be in the State of a member?<br />PRIME MINISTER: I don't know. We are going to have a discussion<br />on this business and it would be premature to be<br />speculating about it. I don't seen to be very well<br />informed on a lot ofthese things because there are<br />people around here who are far more familiar with these<br />things than I am and the fir-st thing I had to do was<br />to say: " Can somebody give me a list of all these<br />things", And I'm getting that, and then. we'll have a<br />go at it, in a perfectly reasonable spirit, I'm not being<br />unpleasant about it.<br />QUESTION: Sir, when you say " We" l do you mean the Cabinet or<br />PRIME MINISTER: Well, one or two Ministers and myself, at any<br />rate.<br />QUESTION: When you say " it" Sir, do you mean the whole range of<br />Members'I amienities?<br />PRIME MINISTER: I don't know. I haven't seen thle list yet so I<br />don't know which ones I want to have a look at. It's<br />really in transit.<br />QUESTION; Does that include the question of residence, Sir?<br />PRIME MINISTER: You fellows are asking mae questions about a matter<br />on which I an the worst informed man in Parliament,<br />you see, so I'm taking steps to inform myself.<br />QUESTION: Will you consider this point then, Sir, that<br />PRIME MINISTER: I'll consider anything you care to put to me,<br />but I'll make no statement about it.<br />QUESTION; Well, where the Parliament is in recess for less than<br />14 days Memibers who remiain in Canberra are entitled to<br />œ C4. a day -allowance. Do you think that's a fair thing?<br />PRIME MINISTE I'ma making no statement about any of these matters.<br />QUESTION: Will you consider that point, Sir%<br />PRIME MINISTER: Look, I'vc told you I'ri making no statement about<br />that matter, I'm in the process of informing my nind,<br />QUESTION:. Can you give us details of the Superannuation Scheme<br />. that has been mentioned a couple of times in the House,<br />PRESSMALN: You answered a question onthat,<br />PRIME MINISTER: Yes, but he wants some details of a Bill.<br />QUESTION; Well could you say when it might be brought dox~ m?<br />PRIME MINISTER: Well, I can't tell you precisely because I don't<br />know off hand,-whethcr it's boen through the Legislation.<br />the scrutiny of the Committee, but I would take it for<br />granted that it would come down in this Session and be<br />passed in this Sossion.<br />QUESTION; Sir, have you yet roceived the proposals from-the Acad--<br />emy of' Science on Spac~ e Research?<br />PRIME MINISTERt No I haven't.</p>
<p>QUESTION: On Space Research, Sir it has been suggested that the<br />United States nay undertake work of that nature at<br />Woomera in a bigger way than was already indulged in<br />during the Geophysical Year. Could you tell us anything<br />of that Sir?<br />PRIME MINISTEI*: I don't know,<br />QUESTION: Do you expect any Government Legislation arising out<br />of the Hursey case Sir?<br />PRIME MINISTER: I couldn't tell you.<br />QUESTION: Have you any comuent to make on the decision by tnc<br />United Order of Oddfellows which provides that Austra.-<br />lia's first Dental Benefit Scheme within the next few<br />weeks in New South ales should cover children and<br />teen-agers from the age of 3 to 17 and further, has<br />there been any discussions at Government level to en.-<br />courage or embrace such a scheme in the National Heal'; n<br />Scheme?<br />PRIME MINISTER: There have been no discussions to which I an a<br />party. Whether the Minister for Health has given it<br />any thought or had any discussion, I wouldn't know, b:.<br />it hasn't come to ne,<br />QUESTION: Does the removal of this hill outside Parlioment House<br />indicate that there is any move towards a new Pc. rlia.-<br />ment House at all? It's gradually been disappearing.<br />PRIME MINISTER: I think it-s sort of an embodiment of the Scrj<br />tures ' If you have sufficient faith you can move<br />mountains7 and this is very encouraging to Members cf<br />Parliament; when everything seems black, when the<br />Press have turned them down, when the Mirror', bought<br />out the Sydney Morning Herald and all these terrible<br />things have occurred I lock out and there's the embodiment<br />offaith.<br />QUESTION: Could you give us any indication, Mr Menzies, of whether<br />there is any prospect at all as to the results of<br />Mr Holt's and Sir Roland V4ilson's activities overseas<br />of getting a loan<br />PRIME MINISTER: No look don't ask me to say any more tha.. that<br />because Ill. be ruch better informed on that in two or<br />three days.<br />QUESTION: Could you give us any background, Sir, to the Government's<br />delay in the appointment of a Committee of Enquiry<br />into the Taxation Laws which you mentioned in<br />your Policy Speech?<br />PRIME MINISTER: Well the delay is on the side of getting the<br />membership established and as we want to have the very<br />best kind of committee, after a long exaymination of a<br />lot of names we decided that I, myself, would have a<br />chat with a couple ofrepresentative bodies, particularly<br />in the Accountancy and Business world, in order to<br />see that we wore getting somebody who carried weight all<br />round. I expect to have those discussions in the next<br />few days and the moment that has been done we'll be in<br />a position to. o ahead.<br />, QUESTION: To announce the names?<br />PRIME MINISTER: Yes, and the torms of reference,<br />QUESTION: And the Post Office committee?</p>
<p>8,<br />PRIME MINISTER: I'n having a meeting this afternoon with bearing<br />on that matter and therefore we'll be able to announce<br />something in the next few days on that.<br />QUESTION: Could you give us any guidance before that cones out,<br />Sir, as to the terms of reference of the Post Office<br />comnittee? Are they likely to be geared to the recomnendations<br />of the Public Accounts Comnittee Report on<br />the Post Office?<br />PRIME MINISTER: The terns of reference have not been settled.<br />They are not very easy to work out. It's very easy to<br />say in a broad way: " Well what capital is engaged in<br />the Post Office in real terms?" and you start to elaborate<br />the terms of reference to see how that gets workec<br />out, well it's a veiy very different matter, but I'n<br />having a discussion about it this afternoon.<br />QUESTION: The enquiry will be confined to the ( inaudible)<br />PRIME MINISTER: Yes.<br />QUESTION: It . on't be extended, as sone Members h. ve asked for,<br />to cover the whole functioning of the Post Office?<br />PRIME MINISTE.: Oh, dear, No. I should have to appoint an entirely<br />different kind of cor. ittoe.<br />SQUESTION: Sir, has the Government got any prograrneo in nind for<br />shifting nore Government Departments from Melbourne to<br />Canberra?<br />PRIME MINISTER: I think that, you know, the process of digesting<br />the las' move will take a little tine, but that's noreally<br />a , ouction that I can answoer T think you ha1<br />better ask the Minister'for the interior P. use they<br />may te working out wT. Lh the Canberra Comnission a sort<br />of future time-table on t-mis natter, but I wouldn't knc.<br />about that. Ask him if he's got any knowled;,. -n<br />thlL ' m cure he would be glad to tell you,<br />QUIESION. On pro,,. nt indications, Mr Mnzics, it looks as if it<br />will be anything up to two years before television services<br />a:' e operating in counLry areas. Has the Governnent<br />anything in mind to speed up this enquiry that's<br />taking placo, and for the applications for licences or<br />to<br />PRIME MINISTER: Yo. had better ask the Postmaster General that,<br />You see t. ore appears to be a mass of applicants. WclL<br />I suppose ifyou have lots of applicants they all have<br />to be heari, they all have to have a chance to put<br />their case: c. l have to have questions put to themn<br />it's very ciffi. cult to speed up a thing like that,<br />QUESTION: The Board is proposing to make all its recoLmendations<br />in one piece rat-er than deal with the applications fo:<br />one area and one State and then make recoruendations,<br />Would you conside. getting them to deal with then in<br />States or in area"?<br />PRIME MINISTER: I don't kno: what the Board is proposing to do<br />on that. Thats a -atter on which you really ought to<br />ask the P. M. G. I hWve been concerned only with overall<br />policy on that.<br />QUESTION: In view of recent rc--crts that Russia is willing to sc<br />oil to Australia, do you feel that it would be advantag<br />eous for Australia take up any further trade with<br />Russia or its satellites to promote peaceful co-existence<br />or trade ties?</p>
<p>9.<br />PRIME MINISTER: I don't know that I understand that.. We have a<br />certain amount of trade with then the Minister for<br />Trade has been asked questions about this repeatedly<br />and I see no reason to alter what has been our approach<br />in the past.<br />QUESTION: Have you any new views on Summit talks, Mr Menzies, following<br />Mr. MacMillan's return and the visit to<br />PRIME MINISTER: No. My views remain the sane and therefore what<br />you are really asking me to do is to make a proph) cy. a<br />very uninformed prophecy. I think there will be one,<br />I'll be very surprised and disappointed ifthere isn't,<br />QUESTION: Has the Cabinet considered the Draft Trade Treaty with<br />Indonesia, Sir, prepared by officials in the two Governments<br />earlier this year yet?<br />PRIME MINISTER: A Draft Trade Treaty? I haven't seen it, but<br />then I was away at the relevant time.<br />QUESTION: Have you any views on your omwn future Sir?<br />PRIME MINISTER: Oh, I should think my future is very murky, Ar'<br />you speaking now in terms of the " hereafter" or in this<br />world?<br />PRESSMAN: The immediate and near future.<br />PRIME MINISTER: Oh, no) Ive got plenty of occupation thanks,, i<br />just going along, living mny idle lifer<br />QUESTION: When will you appoint an Ambassadoro to Moscow. Sir?<br />PRIME MINISTER: I don! t know. You had better ask 3xternal Affaf.::<br />about that. They deal with that.<br />QUESTION: Do you consider any extension, Sir,, to your' own trip tc<br />Indonesia and Malaya?<br />PRIME MINISTER: No.<br />QUESTION: How long do you expect to be away, Sir?<br />SPRIME MINISTER: Only about l4 days altogether five c-day3<br />in Indonesia and five or sixdays in Malaya plus trave..<br />I might come back through Cocos Island, if that is an<br />extension.<br />With the ccpli-nts of:<br />Hugh Dash,<br />Press Secretary to the Prime Minister.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
