<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10131</transcript-id>
    <title>INTERVIEW WITH DERRYN HINCH - RADIO 2GB</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/10/1996</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010131.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I PRIME MINISTER<br />14 October 1996 TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER<br />THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP<br />INTERVIEW WITH DERRYN HINCH RADIO 2GB<br />HINCH: Mr Howard, Mr Prime Minister, good morning.<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />Good morning Derryn.<br />HINCH:<br />Do you regret now not following your base instinct and sacking Senator Short in the first place?<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />Before I answer that could I just correct something you said and I'm sure it was inadvertent, but you<br />said the row over share trading. Senator Short was not trading in shares, Mrs Costello has not been<br />trading in shares.<br />HINCH: All right, share ownership...<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />Share ownership.<br />HINCH: ITl accept that.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:<br />But there's a very big difference...<br />HINCH: Yeah, makes it sound like there's some sort of..<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />Something sinister and they've money and all that kind of thing... . haven't done anything of the kind.<br />No, I don't. I thought what I did last week was right. I believe though, with the additional<br />information, and that is that he took a decision that clearly involved a potential conflict of interest ! I<br />mean, what Senator Short should have done owning those ANZ shares, whether you got that very<br />routine application for approval back by the Reserve Bank and the Treasury, what he should have<br />done was to have asked the Treasurer to do it or alternatively it should have tweaked with him that<br />if he was holding the ANZ Bank shares he did have a conflict of interest. So either way, once it was<br />clear to me and to him that he'd taken a decision directly and only effecting the ANZ Bank, he was<br />in a conflict of interest. He didn't gain anything, he didn't make anything, he didn't cheat, he didn't<br />lie... flINCH: But that's not the point...<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />No, I accept that and that's why he's resigned.<br />flINCH: Your list of high-minded scruples and ethics for your ministers which you made much of about<br />cleaning up the standards of government, they spelled out pretty clearly, and not only was he in<br />Wbreach and I think had to resign, but how come Mr Costello's family, his wife, can now own shares<br />with a bank?<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />Because that's not forbidden by the guidelines.<br />flINCH: So wives can own shares?<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />Wives can own shares and in this day and age where women are not regarded as the financial vassals<br />of their husbands, so they should. And I don't think anybody ! I mean, I noticed incidentally this<br />morning on radio Mr Beazley was backing off at a hundred miles an hour at the idea of pursuing<br />Tanya Costello. Can I just tell you she bought those shares in 1994 out of her own money because<br />T T. 179= 1. I-I i9VMq-Vk,.</p>
<p>she has a job of her own. She has not dealt with them or traded with them since her husband<br />became the Treasurer. When the rest of the Commonwealth Bank was being sold a couple of<br />months ago, Mr Costello specifically asked his wife not to participate in that new share issue<br />because that is what the guidelines required him to address his mind too. He has complied exactly<br />with the guidelines. There is nothing in the guidelines which say that the wife of a member of<br />Parliament or a Minister can't own shares. The only thing that's in the guidelines is that the Mnister<br />is required to have regard to the interests of his family and the holdings of his family in shares...<br />HINCH:<br />What does that mean because<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />What it means is exactly what Peter Costello did in relation to the Commonwealth Bank. He said to<br />his wife, look, you bought those shares before I became Treasurer, you bought them out of your<br />own money, you're not required to sell them, but because the guidelines require me to have regard<br />to your shareholding I'm doing that by asking you not to participate in the new issue and she<br />Wdidn't. So she was absolutely correct in every particular.<br />HINCH: All right, if Senator Short had just transferred his shares to his wife, would he'd have been safe?<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />No, no, because the guidelines say you can't do that.<br />HuNCH: See, one of the problems here... . and I agree with you, but I mean we're going to say that women are<br />equal and they are independent and they have their own careers etc etc, but when you're a member<br />of a political family, whether you're the wife or the husband of a federal minister or Prime Minister,<br />S there are prices you pay and there are perks you get and so therefore you are treated differently and<br />Wyou should be treated differently, don't you agree?<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />Well, it depends where you end. I mean, why do you just single out wives. I mean, what if<br />somebody has a close association with somebody they're not married to are they going to be<br />advantaged and the person who's married is disadvantaged? You have to draw the line somewhere<br />and the guidelines that I laid down made it perfectly clear that the wife of a minister was not<br />forbidden from owning shares...<br />HINCH:<br />Well what if I put shares into a family trust that I have no say in, just my wife and my children have<br />access to? 3</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:<br />Well, the guidelines don't allow you to do that if you have owned the shares at the time the<br />guidelines operate. I mean, in the case of Mrs Costello, she bought these shares in 1994, she bought<br />them out of her own earnings, she put them on the public her husband put them on the register. He<br />wasn't sort of flushed out, it wasn't suddenly discovered, he revealed this himself in 1994 and he<br />revealed it again...<br />HINCH:<br />He wasn't Treasurer then.<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />No, but he revealed it again when he became Treasurer. He put in a new statement of interests<br />when he became Treasurer. I mean, there's been no cover up. And the guidelines this is what<br />we're talking about the guidelines do not forbid the wives or husbands or children of cabinet<br />ministers from owning shares. What they do is to say to somebody who owns shares, when he<br />W becomes a minister, you can't avoid the application of those guidelines by transferring those shares<br />to your wife. Now that didn't happen in Costello's case because they were always hers. In fact, he<br />told me this morning that she actually bought them in the first instance without telling him and he<br />only knew afterwards that she bought the shares. Now fair enough, she's got a job of her own. And<br />we keep hearing from the Labor Party and from many other sections of the community, and quite<br />rightly, that women are not the financial vassals of their husbands, that is an old fashioned view.<br />And I find it very strange that Gareth Evans, for example, whose wife has a career of her own I<br />mean, when Ros Kelly was a cabinet minister we never attacked her participation in decisions<br />because her husband was a senior executive in Westpac Bank. We never once said that, we never<br />once said that. We criticised her behaviour over the whiteboard incident in the sports rorts, but that<br />was her behaviour. We never said that she was in some way disenfranchised from participating in<br />some of the most sensitive financial decisions taken by the former government because her husband<br />was one of the most senior executives in the Westpac Bank.<br />HINCH: I know you've only got a couple of minutes because you have to go in a few minutes time, so two<br />other quick areas. One I picked up the Tele this morning and there is a headline that says,<br />' Howard Rejects Civil War Warning,' and I thought how crazy is this getting.<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />Well exactly, I couldn't agree with you more. I mean, this has been my line all along. I think too<br />much attention is being paid to the Member for Oxley. And who was the person who said right at<br />the beginning that we shouldn't be reacting to maiden speeches of Independent members of<br />Parliament? It was me. And from then until now I have been criticised by some of your colleagues<br />in the media...<br />HINCH: Wrongly. V A</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:<br />wrongly, and criticised by the Labor Party for simply saying, if I've got a view I'll state it. Now, I<br />believe in a non-discriminatory immigration policy, I believe in racial tolerance, I believe that all<br />Australians are equal irrespective of their ethnic background. But I also believe that people have got<br />a right to advocate lower immigration, which we have done. We have cut the migrant intake quite<br />significantly and I don't make any apology for that.<br />HINCH:<br />By about 30,000.<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />Well, we've certainly cut it very significantly and we've shifted away from the emphasis on family<br />reunion and I make no apology for that at all. Any government has got the right to change the level<br />from year to year according to circumstances, but we have maintained the non-discriminatory nature<br />of the policy. We're not singling out Asians or anybody else. All Australians are equal. Now that<br />W has always been our policy. But I am not going to start jumping around every time an Independent<br />member of Parliament makes a statement. She's got a right to her views and I think this whole thing<br />has been blown out of all proportion. I'm sorry to say it because I don't like blanket criticism to<br />sections of the media. I think some sections of the media have just really gone berserk over this<br />issue. It's almost as if they want there to be some kind of ( inaudible) over this issue and I don't<br />think that helps the country at all.<br />HINCH:<br />No, I don't either. But the interesting thing is that nobody jumped up and down and insisted that<br />Prime Minister Hawke or Prime Minister Keating should respond every time Graeme Campbell, who<br />was in the Party, or say Ted Mack, an Independent, said something.<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />SWell, Graeme Campbell had 13 years in the Labor Party in which he regularly disagreed with the<br />WLabor Party on multiculturalism and immigration. Now, some of the things that he said at that time<br />were very critical of his government's policy. But in the end they expelled him, but every time he<br />made a comment the standard response of Hakwe and Keating was to say, ' oh, he's a maverick,<br />forget him'. And yet he was a member their own Party. This lady is not a member of my Party.<br />LUNCH:<br />No, you sacked her from pre-selection.<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />Exactly, she's an Independent. Now, I'm not going to, every time she makes a speech and she'll<br />make a lot more, I'm not under an obligation and yet I've been told in this ' solemn, pompous fashion<br />by quite a number of editorial and other writers that I've got a national responsibility to respond to<br />every detail of what she said. I think that's ridiculous.</p>
<p>HINCH: Do you feel a disappointment that you hear in talk back radio shows, read the newspapers, that there<br />are a lot of Australians some Australians out there who do support her and they say " well,<br />actually I support everything she says", which I find is ominous?<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />Well, I haven't found anybody in public life whose every utterance I support never, I've never<br />found that. Some of the remarks that were attributed to her over the weekend I am told that she<br />claims to have been misreported. Well, if that is the case she hasn't said them, but if she's been<br />accurately reported as talking about things like civil war and bloodshed, well that really is quite silly.<br />When I was asked about that I said it was quite silly and I repeat it again today. Look, there are<br />some people in the Australian community who are intolerant, but by and large I think Australia is a<br />more tolerant society than the politically correct brigade give us credit for being. I guess one of the<br />things that I have reacted against in this whole debate is this automatic typecasting of Australians as<br />racist. I don't think Australians are any more racist than any other country. I think we do have<br />some people who are racist and intolerant, but I think a great number of Australians are prepared to<br />W accept people of different backgrounds and they want to see them become part of the community,<br />they want all of us united together with common Australian values. And this idea that we have been<br />an intolerant community is very unfair and I think we're putting ourselves down, we demean<br />ourselves when we say that.<br />HINCH: You were campaigning in Lindsay yesterday in support of Jackie Kelly. Obviously you hope you<br />can win that, but it's going to be tough now with some of the deals being made.<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />Well, it's going to very tough. It's traditional Labor territory and the Labor Party has done a<br />preference deal with Australians against further immigration that's the mob that wants no<br />immigration at all that sits very idly with the Labor Party's criticism of me and criticism of Graeme<br />aCampbell and criticism of Pauline Hanson, but they're the vagaries of politics. They've also made a<br />Wdeal with the Shooters Party who don't like me very much for reasons I guess everybody<br />understands because of my stance on weapons. Jackie Kelly won fair and square. A lot of people<br />think she's been punched out on a technicality. It's very strange to tell people that somebody who's<br />been in the Royal Australian Air Force is in some way potentially under allegiance to a foreign<br />power because of a technicality in the Constitution. Many people feel that Ross Free's being a bad<br />sport and I think...<br />HINCH: Well he is.<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />I mean, he was beaten, he was part of the problem, he'd had 13 years, he was part of the sort of<br />tired image of the... . out of touch image of the Labor Party in traditional Labor areas. Jackie Kelly by<br />contrast is really a breath of fresh air. She's energetic, young, keen, different. I think the people of<br />Lindsay would be better represented by her. I think it's going to be very hard. I think because of<br />1 1, It I tF.</p>
<p>these deals Free could sneak in through the back door, and if any people out there in Lindsay are<br />wavering can I just say to them if you want to stop Ross Free sneaking back you've got to vote<br />directly for Jackie Kelly and not muck around with minor parties.<br />HINCH: Speaking of voting, are you watching across the Tasman? Presumably you'd work with either Helen<br />Clark or Winston Peters or Jim Bolger.<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />Oh yes. I've not met Peters. I know Jim Bolger well. I did meet Helen Clarke a couple of months<br />ago when she came to Australia. Yes, I'd work with either of them. It's an extraordinary system of<br />voting. I don't know why on earth they imposed it on themselves. I said that to Jim Bolger, " why<br />on earth did you propose this system on yourself?" I think everybody thought it was a good idea at<br />the time.<br />HINCH: All right, one final thing, I know you have to go. You wouldn't have heard yet, but Senator Jim<br />Short and I have one thing in common.<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />What's that?<br />HINCH: I resigned this morning.<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />Oh, I'm sorry to here that. I am sorry Derryn, and I wish you well. I'm sorry, I didn't realise that, I<br />didn't know that.<br />HINCH: Only about half an hour ago. That's life as somebody once said.<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />Yes it is. Well look, I wish you well, personally I do and I wish you well professionally.<br />MINCH:<br />Thank you sir.<br />PRIME MINISTER: 7</p>
<p>-' V And it's always been.. although we haven't always agreed and that's proper too, I've always enjoyed<br />having a civil discussion with you and whatever you do in the future in the media you've got my<br />personal good wishes.<br />HINiCH: Thank you. But we've had some good go arounds over the past 15 years haven't we?<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />Yes, and can I tell you what goes down in my experience ultimately comes up if you hang on long<br />enough. HINCH:<br />Good point. Thanks for your time.<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />Okay, cheerio. 84</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
