<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7742</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF DOORSTOP, SYDNEY CONVENTION CENTRE, DARLING HARBOUR, 17 SEPTEMBER 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/09/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007742.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF DOORSTOP, SYDNEY CONVENTION CENTRE, DARLING<br />
HARBOUR, 17 SEPTEMBER 1989<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, the cannon fire interrupted<br />
your speech a little bit there# but what do you think will<br />
attract most Australians to this campaign?<br />
PM: I think the obviously increasing concern of Australians<br />
with environmental issues gener~ ally and, at times, I think<br />
Australians wonder ' well, what is there that we can do about<br />
protecting our environment'. This program offers each<br />
individual Australian a direct opportunity of being part of<br />
helping to protect the environment. I think that's what<br />
they'll find attractive.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime minister, have you had any response from<br />
the pilots from your letter to them last week?<br />
PM: No, I haven't had any response yet, but of course I've<br />
written to them. r noticed in one of the programs this<br />
morning that the Federation is preparing a reply. Well,<br />
that's a bit disappointing. My letter was to individual<br />
pilots, I would have hoped that individual pilots, I thought<br />
they would regard themselves as individuals, enterprising,<br />
and that each one of them would be able to prepare their own<br />
reply. I would hope that's what would happen.<br />
JOURNALIST: they want an independent negotiator<br />
PM: Yes, they want an independent negotiator. That's been<br />
their position from the beginning. They want to be<br />
different from everyone else, everyone else. Everyone else<br />
in Australia who's employed in the workforce are operating<br />
within a system which has protected Australia, which has<br />
created one and a half million new jobs, which has brought<br />
the wage restraint which is allowing the great surge of<br />
investment and employment that's taken place. That's how<br />
it's happened by everyone exercising restraint. Now they<br />
say ' no, that's not good enough for us, give us someone<br />
else. Give us an independent negotiator, an independent<br />
arbitrator'. There's been no change from the beginning.<br />
what has to happen is that the Pilots' Federation must<br />
understand that they will not be treated differently from<br />
the rest of the work force. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
JOURNALIST: what's your reaction to George Campbell's<br />
comments, M4r Hawke?<br />
PM: I've got no comment onl George Campbell.<br />
JOURNALIST: Are you concerned by<br />
PM: *.. Ive said I've got no comment on George Campbell.<br />
JOURNALIST: Your comments about an independent negotiator<br />
have followed through to the nomination by the pilots of Sir<br />
Laurence Street as a mediator-<br />
PH: Well yes, I mean, it's quite clear from what I've said,<br />
is that they have said from the beginning, when they started<br />
in February. You remember in February they drew up what<br />
they called their battle plan their words. A battle plan<br />
in which they said ' we are going to be faced with a<br />
situation where we'll be fighting the airlines, the<br />
Government, the trade union movement and everyone'. That's<br />
what they said in February of this year. They drew up their<br />
battle plan to isolate themselves from everyone else. Now,<br />
when it's clear that we, representing the community, are not<br />
going to allow them to be different from everyone else,<br />
we're not trying to impose something special upon them.<br />
we're saying you can't draw up your battle plan in February<br />
to destroy your industry, destroy this country and then, at<br />
the end of it, say ' oh no, please give us an independent<br />
negotiator'. it is not on. The pilots must simply do what<br />
everyone else does, accept the guidelines. That's what's<br />
happening now. Under the individual contracts that are<br />
being signed by pilots that are joining up, they are getting<br />
their increases, they are getting changes in their<br />
conditions, but it is being done in accordance with the<br />
S principles that apply to everyone else.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
