<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11531</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER            THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP            TELEVISION INTERVIEW WITH STEVE LIEBMANN            THE TODAY SHOW, CHANNEL NINE                     SUBJECTS: Rural trip; protests; Government services in the bush; interest             rate adjustments; Adelaide Bank; GST; textile workers.</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/02/2000</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...................................................................................................</p>
<p>LIEBMANN:</p>
<p>While the Prime Minister's regional tour has continued so too the</p>
<p> protests and there was another rowdy demonstration yesterday involving</p>
<p> people upset over a variety of issues including the GST, gun laws and</p>
<p> the environment. The Prime Minister nonetheless managed to stand up to</p>
<p> 300 protesters in the city of Lismore.</p>
<p>This morning he is in Coffs Harbour and it's from there that he</p>
<p> joins us now. Prime Minister, good morning to you.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Hello Steve. Good to be on the programme.</p>
<p>LIEBMANN:</p>
<p>Have you, Prime Minister, been surprised at the intensity of the anger</p>
<p> in the bush and what message do you bring away from this trip?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, Steve, let's call a spade a spade. Most of the demonstrations</p>
<p> of the past couple of days have been organised demonstrations. There's</p>
<p> been nothing spontaneous about them and they have come from what I might</p>
<p> loosely call the usual suspects. So I think it would be a huge mistake</p>
<p> to see the Nimbin people's demonstrations and the demonstrations</p>
<p> of some other people as being a spontaneous expression of mainstream opinion</p>
<p> in the bush. However, quite separately from the demonstrations and in</p>
<p> an entirely calm and sensible way people in the regions have expressed</p>
<p> their concern about a variety of things. There are some good stories in</p>
<p> the bush and there are some bad stories in the bush and we have got to</p>
<p> make certain we keep it balanced. But clearly a number of parts of Australia</p>
<p> are not doing as well as some of the capital cities. And part of what</p>
<p> I have been trying to do over the last week is to get an even better understanding</p>
<p> of that, to discuss ways in a practical achievable fashion that we can</p>
<p> over the months ahead do something about it. But I have stressed the limits</p>
<p> of what any government can do. We can't turn around the weather,</p>
<p> we can't turn around world commodity prices but we can influence</p>
<p> the level of Commonwealth Government services and we can influence the</p>
<p> States in relation to the level of their services.</p>
<p>LIEBMANN:</p>
<p>Just on the question of people in the bush not travelling as well as</p>
<p> people in the cities. Do you think the Reserve Bank should pay special</p>
<p> attention to the impact that interest rate adjustments have on our regional</p>
<p> communities?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I think the Reserve Bank has got to keep in mind the impact of</p>
<p> interest rate adjustments not only on the whole economy but also on elements</p>
<p> of it. Now, I don't want to get into a debate about the decision</p>
<p> that was taken a day or two ago, that was a decision taken by the Reserve</p>
<p> Bank exercising its independent freedom of movement in relation to monetary</p>
<p> policy. You can't have differential interest rates around the country,</p>
<p> you have got to sometimes adjust interest rates in a way you mightn't</p>
<p> want to in the long-term interests of maintaining a momentum of steady</p>
<p> economic growth and ensuring that inflation doesn't break out. I</p>
<p> mean, even after this interest rate rise, even after it's been factored</p>
<p> in, the average home borrower in Australia would be $266 a month better</p>
<p> off than he was when my Government came to power four years ago. So we</p>
<p> have got to keep a sense of perspective. Interest rates now are massively</p>
<p> lower and still will be after the half a per cent increase than what they</p>
<p> were when we came to office four years ago.</p>
<p>LIEBMANN:</p>
<p>I notice that Cheryl Kernot today is saying that the GST was a huge factor</p>
<p> in the interest rate rise.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, Cheryl's wrong.</p>
<p>LIEBMANN:</p>
<p>Do you think half a per cent though was too much?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I am not going to comment because it was a decision taken by the</p>
<p> Reserve Bank exercising its independent authority.</p>
<p>LIEBMANN:</p>
<p>Right. What about though then the Adelaide Bank which has gone and increased</p>
<p> its rate more than the half a per cent, by .7 per cent?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I haven't heard that and we have previously indicated, the</p>
<p> Treasurer has and I endorse it, that if banks go beyond the official rates</p>
<p> they...official rate increases that they could face some kind of surveillance</p>
<p> from the competition authorities. There's no justification for banks</p>
<p> going beyond official rate increases. Banks in this country are in a very</p>
<p> stable profitable position, and they have to understand that they have</p>
<p> social responsibilities.</p>
<p>LIEBMANN:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, later today you're going to meet some of the sacked</p>
<p> national textile workers in an add-on to your trip in Newcastle, and they</p>
<p> say they want some straight answers. Can you give them straight answers?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I can give them straight answers. I'll be telling them what</p>
<p> the Government is interested in as well as the question of entitlements</p>
<p> which is going to be considered in the Cabinet on Tuesday. I'll be</p>
<p> telling them that. The Government is also interested in ways and means</p>
<p> in which we can assist the retrenched workers retrain. One of the problems</p>
<p> of retrenchments of this size in a regional centre such as Rutherford</p>
<p> is that it is very hard to find alternative employment and I think this</p>
<p> is a classic case of where economic change which is unavoidable is hurting</p>
<p> people. And I think the community and the Government has a responsibility</p>
<p> to help people who are the victims of economic change. And I'm not</p>
<p> suggesting that you can hold back the process of economic change and reform,</p>
<p> but we do as a society have an obligation to try and give some help to</p>
<p> people who are hurt by economic change. And I'm very sympathetic</p>
<p> to be quite blunt about he plight of these workers or any other low paid</p>
<p> people who are suddenly retrenched, and are left begging for their entitlements.</p>
<p> I have to say to you I find that situation very hard and I don't</p>
<p> seek to defend it. Now we've got a find a way through it. The Labor</p>
<p> Party was in power for 13 years. They're crowing about the situation</p>
<p> now. They had 13 years to do something about a safety net of entitlements</p>
<p> and they didn't do anything. So they're right out of the game.</p>
<p> But I am sympathetic to these people and I'll be expressing that</p>
<p> concern and sympathy when I see their representatives today, and we'll</p>
<p> be discussing the matter in full in Cabinet on Tuesday. That is what I'm</p>
<p> going to be telling them.</p>
<p>LIEBMANN:</p>
<p>Okay. But does that sympathy run to the tune of, just finally, $3.6 million</p>
<p> because the administrators are saying your Government, they want or they're</p>
<p> suggesting your Government provide an extra $3.6 million to allow full</p>
<p> payment for the sacked workers? Will you do that and don't they deserve</p>
<p> it?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I don't think the administrator's in a position to give</p>
<p> any advice to the Government. The administrator is there to administer</p>
<p> the affairs of the company. And let's get one thing straight, the</p>
<p> circumstances that have led to this arising are not ones that can be laid</p>
<p> directly at the door of the Federal Government. I mean one of these things,</p>
<p> one of the last straws that broke the camel's back with this company</p>
<p> was the loss of a contract that it had with the New South Wales Police</p>
<p> Service for more than 20 years. I'm not saying that in normal competitive</p>
<p> processes the police service was obliged to keep the contract with the</p>
<p> one and the same company that it had for 20 years and in fact replace</p>
<p> it with a Victorian company. But I think it does mean that at least there's</p>
<p> some moral obligation on the part of the New South Wales Government to</p>
<p> be involved in this and I acknowledge the fact that the New South Wales</p>
<p> Government has said that it does accept some responsibility of being involved.</p>
<p> Look this is a difficult issue. We're trying to work out a solution</p>
<p> that's workable. It's no good people making a sort of stand</p>
<p> and deliver demands. Administrators shouldn't be making stand and</p>
<p> deliver demands. They should stick to their task which is to administer</p>
<p> the company. And the Government will for the first time be examining,</p>
<p> first time for any Federal government, examining some kind of comprehensive</p>
<p> approach to these problems particularly when they occur in the regions.</p>
<p>LIEBMANN:</p>
<p>Thanks for your time this morning Prime Minister.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>You're very welcome.</p>
<p>[Ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
