<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4581</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS - 5 DECEMBER 1977</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/12/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004581.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
F77/ 289<br />
4AUS RL IA<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 5 DECEMBER 1977<br />
The opinion polls have panicked Mr. Whitlam into an extraordinary<br />
series of falsehoods on inflation and unemployment.<br />
M r. Whitlam has embarked on a last-ditch panic campaign of<br />
fear and deception.<br />
He shows total disregard for truth and fact, and for the<br />
statements of his own spokesmen.<br />
Mr. Whitlam claims Labor will reduce unemployment by at least<br />
100,000, yet a few days earlier Mr. Hayden claimed Labor would<br />
reduce unemployment by one half of one per cent that is,<br />
30,000 people.<br />
Mr. Whitlam. has magically found jobs for 70,000 people in<br />
just a few days with the stroke of his speech writer's pen.<br />
The fact is, Labor's wage policies and its discredited tariff<br />
policies, and its determination to once again reduce tariffs<br />
even further, would add directly to unemployment in Australia.<br />
Mr. Whitlam should visit a textile or clothing factory and<br />
ask if they think he would reduce unemplyment. He would<br />
get a rude shock.<br />
Mr. Whitlam claims Labor would reduce inflation by 5% in the<br />
next twelve months. Yet in his policy speech he claimed<br />
Labor would reduce it by 2%.<br />
Mr. Whitlam' s speech writer has again weaved his magic. This<br />
time he got inflation down an extra 3% in just a few days.<br />
The fact is, Labor's disastrous wage policies and its big<br />
spending programmes will increase this year's deficit by<br />
from one third to one half in just six months, and that<br />
would ignite inflation.<br />
Because of the inflation these policies would again cause,<br />
business and consumer confidence will be shattered which will,<br />
in turn, lead to thousands of Australia's trade unionists<br />
losing their jobs. / The .7 </p>
<p>-2<br />
The exagg~ rations and falsehood ' s that riddle Mr. Whitlam' s<br />
statement only compound Labor's confusion on economic<br />
matters. Just a few days ago, one of Labor's spokesman on the economy,<br />
Mr. Hayden, said there would be no growth next year, but<br />
4% growth was needed to cut unemployment.<br />
Yet almost in the same breath, Mr. Hayden promised 1% growth<br />
under Labor, and then claimed this would cut unemployment.<br />
That is the same kind of hypocrisy and double talk that<br />
comes from the men who increased unemployment by 192,000<br />
in one year and who presided over an inflation rate that<br />
reached a peak of 19%.<br />
They are the same men peddling the same policies.<br />
Australia could never survive their medicine again.<br />
We are getting inflation down. It is running at about 9%.<br />
Under our policies, interest rates will come down further.<br />
The expected 2% reduction means a great deal to a young<br />
couple borrowing for their first home -about $ 500 a year<br />
on average.<br />
Getting interest rates down will mean a great deal for<br />
business -small and large.<br />
All of this means jobs; thousands of jobs for Australia..<br />
Under our realistic-. policies, unemployment will fall . in a<br />
sustainable way from February onwards. Labor would destroy<br />
the hard-won gains of the-last two years. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
