<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>15450</transcript-id>
    <title>Joint Media Statement with  The Hon Morris Iemma, Premier of New South Wales  Phillip Street, Sydney</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/05/2007</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>APEC Leaders Week In Sydney, 2-9 September</p>
<p>The Asia-Pacific Economic Cooperation (APEC) meetings that Sydney will host over the week of 2-9 September are important for Sydney, for Australia and for the region. The APEC Economic Leaders Meeting is one of the most important annual meetings of world leaders.</p>
<p>Together APEC economies account for over half the world's GDP, almost 70 per cent of Australia's total international trade and 9 of the top 10 NSW merchandise export markets. Australia has put climate change and energy at the centre of this year's APEC agenda.</p>
<p>The Commonwealth and NSW governments are collaborating closely and are committed to ensuring APEC is a success and to minimising disruption to the people of Sydney.</p>
<p>A Mass Transit Working Group, comprising the APEC 2007 Taskforce, NSW Police and other Australian and NSW government agencies, has recommended that Circular Quay, Museum and St James rail stations be closed from Friday 7 September to Sunday 9 September. We support this recommendation as it meets the security concerns of agencies with responsibility for aviation, rail, bus and ferry infrastructure, while at the same time ensuring only essential and minimal disruption to public transport.</p>
<p>Central, Town Hall, Martin Place and Wynyard stations will remain open.  The North Shore and Eastern Suburbs line will continue to operate.  Trains operating on these lines will operate normal timetables.  Passengers alighting at Wynyard wanting to visit the Circular Quay area will face a short walk.</p>
<p>As Friday 7 September is a public holiday, buses, trains and ferries will operate on their public holiday timetables.  Normal weekend timetables will apply on Saturday 8 and Sunday 9 September.  Buses which normally terminate at Circular Quay will terminate a few blocks further south in the city, and details will be provided shortly.</p>
<p>The CBD train arrangements will work in harmony with traffic announcements to be announced by agencies in the lead-up to Leaders Week.  The public will be kept informed at the earliest opportunity of public transport and traffic arrangements.</p>
<p>We ask residents and business people for their patience and understanding, particularly over the long weekend of 7-9 September, as the international spotlight shines on Sydney and as this great city extends its customary hospitality to our important Asia-Pacific neighbours.   </p>
<p>Established as an Australian initiative in 1989 when Canberra hosted the first informal dialogue of 12 members, APEC has enjoyed consistent bipartisan support. The grouping has expanded to 21 member economies and has a strong policy agenda that encourages free trade and promotes growth in the Asia-Pacific region.</p>
<p>The return of APEC to Australia is an important milestone. </p>
<p>  Prime Minister's Office: (02) 6277 7744  Premier Iemma's Office: Todd Hayward 0412 205 151</p>
<p>Snapshot of APEC Leaders Week</p>
<p>   *  21 Leaders and more than 40 Ministers<br />
   *  400 international Business Leaders<br />
   *  6000+ delegates and support personnel<br />
   *  1000+ media representatives<br />
   *  35+ VIP aircraft </p>
<p>*  300+ secure VIP traffic escorts<br />
   *  30+ hotels </p>
<p>Statistics</p>
<p>Australia and APEC Statistics</p>
<p>The 21 APEC Member Economies represent:<br />
   *  over 40 per cent of the world's population<br />
   *  56 per cent of global GDP </p>
<p>*  around 48 per cent of world trade </p>
<p>Source: DFAT</p>
<p>Trade<br />
   *  Eight of Australia's top 10 export markets<br />
   *  69% of Australia's total international trade<br />
   *  61 per cent of world growth between 1989 and 2003 </p>
<p>Investment<br />
   *  Approximately 40 per cent of inward investment in Australia<br />
   *  Around 63% of Australia's total investment abroad </p>
<p>Key commodity exports<br />
   *  95 per cent of Australia's beef and veal exports </p>
<p>*  89 per cent of Australia's medicinal/pharmaceutical product exports<br />
   *  84 per cent of Australia's petroleum exports<br />
   *  82 per cent of Australia's iron and steel exports </p>
<p>*  77 per cent of Australia's non-ferrous metal exports </p>
<p>*  64 per cent of Australia's coal exports </p>
<p>Tourism<br />
   *  Eight of the top 10 sources of international visitors to Australia </p>
<p>*  70 per cent of international visitors to Australia </p>
<p>Education<br />
   *  Nine of the top 10 sources of international students studying in Australia<br />
   *  More than 70 per cent of international students studying in Australia </p>
<p>People<br />
   *  One third of Australians born overseas were born in APEC economies<br />
   *  26 per cent of the Australian population whose mother tongue is not English speak a language of an APEC member economy </p>
<p>Source: Tourism Australia, ABS, AEI, DFAT</p>
<p>New South Wales and APEC Statistics</p>
<p>APEC Member Economies account for:</p>
<p>Trade<br />
   *  Nine of the top 10 NSW merchandise export markets<br />
   *  Three quarters of NSW merchandise export trade </p>
<p>Tourism<br />
   *  More than 60 per cent of international visitors to NSW<br />
   *  Eight of the top 10 NSW tourism markets </p>
<p>Education<br />
   *  More than two thirds of international students studying in NSW </p>
<p> Source: Tourism NSW, AEI, NSWDSRD</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
