<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9667</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J.KEATING MP DOORSTOP, CAIRNS PORT AUTHORITY, 16 JULY 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/07/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009667.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE MON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
DOORSTOP, CAIRNS PORT AUTHORITY, 16 JULY 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
J: How concerning is it to the Federal Government to have such a swing<br />
against Labor?<br />
PMV: It concerns me when there is a swing against Labor anywhere and, I think.<br />
what is concerning in Queensland, this Queensland government of Wayne<br />
Goss is a good government and it is rather disconcerting to see a good<br />
government in any way suffering these sorts of problems from a protest<br />
vote. It is quite obvious that the Opposition here without policies and<br />
without a program urging only a protest vote, there could have been no<br />
positive vote for them. In which case, there has got to be some appraisal<br />
of again the point, that political parties must stand for something and when<br />
they don't there can be no guarantee for the community that they are going<br />
to get some value from it from such a protest or from such a change.*<br />
J: You have made your own assessment here, whet does this mean<br />
federally?<br />
PMV: By and large state elections over the last 20 or 30 years have not had a<br />
federal character about them and vice versa, I think this is true. The<br />
Coalition lost in NSW, I don't think we were able to say that this is a major<br />
turn around in federal fortunes anymore than I'd say a loss of seats in<br />
Queensland would be a rebuke for the Federal Labor Party and, I think,<br />
John Howard said the same thing a week or two ago heme in Queensland.<br />
But, you don't like to see your party in this case the Labor Party, my Party<br />
suffering admonition at the hands of the electorate and particularly with a<br />
good, competent government as Wayne Goss' government is.<br />
J: Mr Goss says that on these figures the federal government would lose in<br />
Queensland and federally. </p>
<p>PM: Well, we have had so many examples, take the 1975 federal election loss<br />
of Labor. Neville Wran won in NSW a couple of months later and vice<br />
versa. I don't think you can read any sorts of, these sorts of federal<br />
implications into the result, but that is not to say that as a Labor person, as<br />
a Labor leader I am not concerned about it.<br />
J: Do you think a federal election is likely to be later rather than sooner?<br />
PM: I keep getting asked by journalists about election dates. John Hewson<br />
started talking about an early election 18 months ago. We still haven't had<br />
an election. I still keep saying I believe the public should get value from<br />
these parliaments and that it is too hard to win elections to be giving any<br />
free time away.<br />
J: So, is that a postponement?<br />
PM: No, it is just the Prime Minister of this country exercising the sensible<br />
prerogatives that are vested with the Prime Minister to make the election<br />
timing a matter of the Prime Minister's choice.<br />
J: Have you spoken to Mr Goss?<br />
PM: I did. I rang Wayne this morning at about eleven o'clock and I had quite a<br />
long talk to him. This result is in the box now, it will be revealed, of course,<br />
when the final counting comes due. It is my very fervent wish that the<br />
Goes government is retained in office and that people may see; yes, you<br />
can register a protest vote, but it doesn't necessarily get you any value.<br />
J: Could this, in fact, be good for federal Labor because the people in<br />
Queensland would have got their protest vote off their chests?<br />
PM: Again, you have to then think it is a vote for one party or another. I don't<br />
really think it is. People do vote on state issues and they do vote on<br />
federal issues, so I dont ever believe that a loss for the Labor Party<br />
anywhere can be good for us.<br />
J: Are you relieved that you weren't directly involved in this campaign?<br />
PM: This is the fashion of a media which is oversupplied by cameras and<br />
journalists and under supplied by issues. People are always asking all<br />
these questions. It is like the old days. Did Bob Menzies campaign for<br />
Henry Bolte? No. Did he campaign for Robin Askin? No. Did Bolte and<br />
Askin campaign for Menzies? No. Did Malcolm Fraser campaign for Dick<br />
Hamer? No. This is all a bit of mythology basically.<br />
J: If Goss loses here, would you welcome him into federal politics? </p>
<p>PM: I think he will win and I hope it will be a reasonably clear result in the end.<br />
Let's talk about that scenario.<br />
J: What do you think of the performance though of the Queensland<br />
government?<br />
PM: I look at the performance of the Queensland government, I mean, this has<br />
been a State which has been growing in the order of somewhere between<br />
four and six per cent over the last couple of years. This is a State which<br />
has got very strong employment growth one of the strongest in Australia.<br />
This State has been along with Western Australia, out performing the other<br />
States. There has been, I think, a substantial change in Queensland.<br />
Queensland is a much more national and internationally oriented State<br />
now than it has ever been in my view, thanks to the Goss government and<br />
it was for these reasons, I think, the government should be returned.<br />
J: So, what does it say about their campaign?<br />
PM Well, what does it say about the Coalition's campaign? It is that sort of<br />
register a vote of protest against the Government. Don't register it for any<br />
reason, don't register it because we the Opposition are better, but just<br />
register ft. I think it is going to make people think about whether protest<br />
votes have got any value to them. There is no prize for hurting a good<br />
government.<br />
J: Is there a risk for you that the some will happen at a federal election?<br />
PM: Well, there is always a risk, but again, let people understand this about<br />
John Howard. He is following the same policy, he is running around<br />
without a policy. He is saying ' I'll have no policies, just concentrate on<br />
them'. But, in the end, someone has got to run the country so as I say,<br />
there can be no honesty or credibility in politics without policies. So, I<br />
think, what the media has got to do with John Howard is line him up. Say<br />
' OK John, you want to be Prime Minister, what do you stand for?' Not<br />
some vague generalisation. He has got another one of these so called<br />
headland speeches coming up during the week it will be the same as the<br />
lost one full of vague generuilsations. And, if he wants to be Prime<br />
Minister, he has got to say where he stands in policy. When I produce a<br />
Policy document It has got the changes there, all the details. They are<br />
there whether ft is the Accord of a couple of weeks ago or whether ft is the<br />
outline of the Republic or whether it is the Budget or superannuation for<br />
the whole workface. it is there in quality, In detail. And I think free riders<br />
on the system and whether you are talking about Borbidge or Howard,<br />
essentially they are free riders on the system. They are to be held<br />
accountable for the things they really stand for, but want to keep hidden<br />
until an election. </p>
<p>., 4<br />
J: Do you think Howard will fashion his campaign on the Queensland<br />
Coalition?<br />
PM: I think the policy has been the same. They represent nothing. They stand<br />
for nothing and yet they seek to denigrate governments that do things. I<br />
think, the public ought to be very careful about this and say well, hang on,<br />
before we leave value behind, before we leave behind governments that<br />
have got quality and substance and value, we have got to know what we<br />
are going to get in return and not just, basically, the fluff that comes from<br />
an advertising agency.<br />
J: You said after the ACT elections that you have taken a message from the<br />
electorate. Do you take a message from this electorate?<br />
PM: That was a federal by-election. This is a state election. The only message<br />
I take from this is that Labor has not done here as well as we would have<br />
liked and I am interested for the Labor Party and, of course, for the federal<br />
government that we try to understand the Queensland outcome and see if<br />
there is a discernible view from the electorate.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
