<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2496</transcript-id>
    <title>&#039;ADDRESS TO THE NATION&#039; - BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR WILLIAM MCMAHON - OVER THE NATIONAL RADIO AND TV NETWORK - 26 NOVEMBER 1971</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/11/1971</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002496.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO NOT FOR RELEASE UNTIL 8 PM ( EST)<br />
" ADDRESS TO THE NATION"<br />
BY THE PRI7E MINISTER, MR WILLIM Mc!,' AHON<br />
OVER THE NATIONAL RADIO AND TV NETWORK 26 NOVEMBER 1971<br />
Good Fvening: I want to report to you tonight about my recent<br />
mission to the United States and to the United Kingdom.<br />
About the middle of October, i received a personal<br />
invitation from President Nixon to visit the United States. Now<br />
I did so in extraordinary circumstances because momentous events<br />
were occurring in world affairs which intimately affected us as<br />
well as the rest of the world.<br />
There was a growing change in the balance of power<br />
amongst the great countries. No longe2 did the United States and<br />
Soviet Russia dominate the scene. Communist China was becoming<br />
increaslingly important, and so, too was Japan and the European<br />
Community, including Britain. As well, the President of the United<br />
States was about to visit both Peking and * oscow. And Dr Kissinger,<br />
on his behalf, had been to Peking on two occasions. There was an<br />
international monetary crisis. Britain had just decided enter the<br />
European Community and, of course, in the countries that I was to<br />
visit, aueries were made about problems that we might have to face<br />
at home. So I went to the United States first, that is, to New<br />
York and to Washington. And I had interviews with most of the<br />
important members of the United States Administration, from President<br />
Nixon down. In my discussions with him, he first of all raised the<br />
question of the .7erican presence in South Vietnam. And he explained<br />
to me in detail what the Americans intended to do and the rate at<br />
which their forces would be withdrawn. He also gave me and I regard<br />
this as of vital importance to us but he gave me an assurance that<br />
the ANZUS Treaty was as valid today as it was on the day on which<br />
it was signed. Now this Trepty is important to us for this reason:<br />
That, as you will probably know, the ANZUS Treaty provides that in the<br />
event of an armed attack on Australia, the United States and New<br />
Zealand would act to meet the common danger. There could not have<br />
. een a better assurance than he has given, and it virtually guarantees<br />
our freedom from attack.<br />
I also had discussions on such matters as trade of<br />
meat particularly and a visit of Y'r Stans to Australia, their<br />
Secretary of Commerce, relating to the problems associated with<br />
wool. It was also suggested to me in discussions with their Treasury<br />
officials that the United States, Japan, and ourselves, should<br />
co-operate in order to try and get better terms cfaccess to the<br />
new European Economic Community. / 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
Of course, I had other discussions, but I haven't the time<br />
to be able to go through them tonight. But I did have discussions<br />
on the environment and pollution. And the Americans assured me<br />
that our officials would be able to go there, and they would make<br />
available all the information they had so that we would avoid the<br />
errors of other countries.<br />
So I can assure you of this. The visit was timely it<br />
was successful and it was to your advantage.<br />
I then went to the United Kingdom, and had discussions<br />
with Mr Heath, the Prime Minister, and most of his senior Ministers.<br />
The big problem we faced there was that Britain was<br />
shortly to enter the European Economic Community. And that<br />
consequently the historic trade ties between Australia and the<br />
United Kingdom would cease.<br />
So I sought guarantees that our interests would be<br />
protected. And I am glad to be able to say that from Mr Heath<br />
down to his Chancellor of vhe Exchequer and the Minister responsible<br />
for Economic Affairs in the European Community, Mr Rippon, that<br />
they would do their best to protect our interests now. And they<br />
gave me three guarantees.<br />
The first one was that if we did have some difficulties<br />
with particular agricultural industries, we could make representations,<br />
or the British would make representations for us, to the Community<br />
to try and get corrections made. They also agreed that if we had<br />
a threat of serious injury, we could take it up with the European<br />
Community. And above all, they stressed the nend for industries<br />
themselves to become involved in these problems, and not leave the<br />
sole responsibility to the Government.<br />
In the case of Papua-Mew Guinea, they said that if the<br />
Community could be prevailed upon to accept their ideas, they would<br />
give special privileges to the export of goods from Papua-New<br />
Guinea into the United Kingdom. Yesterday I received a message<br />
which I'm glad to say I was able to relay to the House, that they<br />
had lived up to their promise and special advantages would be given<br />
to Papua/ New Guinea, a dependency country that is really for the<br />
time being dependent on us.<br />
So, too, did I have pretty important discussions on other<br />
economic matters. It was oointed out to me that Australia and<br />
England are both great trading powers. And consequently in the case<br />
of the United Kingdom, the greater the trade and the greater the<br />
degree of flexibility, the better it would be.<br />
For my part, I asked them in fact I impressed upon them<br />
that they must not be isolationist and inward-looking, but Britain<br />
should exert its influence to ensure that the European Community<br />
was outward-looking and international. / 3<br />
L </p>
<p>3<br />
Now I am sure that the arrangements, or the arrangements<br />
that we made, will be of advantage to Britain, to the Common<br />
Market, to the world, and above all to ourselves.<br />
I then had discussions with the Minister for Defence,<br />
Lord Carrington, well known to most Australians. And again<br />
we discussed problems of great importance to us, the first being<br />
the recent signature of wh,, t is called the Five Power arrangements<br />
relating to Malaysia and Singapore.<br />
Now, as you know, Malaysia and Singapore, together with<br />
Indonesia, are vital to us.<br />
We want the British to maintain a presence East of Suez,<br />
and particularly in Malaysia and Singapore, just as long as they<br />
can. And I received assurances of this kind from the Government.<br />
They are willing to participate in the security, and tq<br />
engender a feeling of confidence in this part of the world, and they<br />
are certainly willing to participate in training arrangements for<br />
the Malaysi-ns and Singaporeans. And so it went on.<br />
I had discussions on many other subjects of great<br />
importance to us: Consultations with very nearly every senior<br />
Minister there was in the United Kingdom.<br />
And this brings me to the story that I want to tell to you<br />
as Australian people.<br />
The first one was that on each occasion the consultations<br />
were full, frank and with candour. Nothing was held back. They<br />
told us what they knew and we told them what we knew.<br />
For example, I was told of what was about to happen in<br />
Rhodesia. Mr Nixon told me of his hopes in the visits that he<br />
intended to make to Moscow and to Peking.<br />
And I can assure you, and I want you to realise this fact,<br />
that they trust us, I believe, more than they trust most other<br />
countries, and are willing to confide in us and are willing to<br />
co-operate with us too,<br />
The second point was this: Wherever I went I found that we<br />
were regarded, not as one of the super or the great powers, but we<br />
were regarded as one of the medium powers one that was playing<br />
an increasingly important part, and having an increasingly important<br />
influence: Not only in South-East Asia, but in the United Kingdom<br />
and the United States as well.<br />
The next point that came home to me and I want to repeat<br />
it to you ia that now that we are accepted as a completely<br />
independent country, that our foreign affairs reflect the interests<br />
of the Australian people, we must also recognise the fact that we<br />
have to take primary responsibility for our own defence. And we have<br />
to take complete responsibility for our own economic affairs, although<br />
the others will assist us when the occasion is needed. / 4<br />
.01 </p>
<p>-4<br />
But let me look at the problem of our economy first.<br />
We have a great economy and I'll say a little more about this<br />
later but in our economic affairs overseas, we have to fight the<br />
battles.. and industry has to join with the Government in achieving<br />
success and not lot the Government do all the fighting for it.<br />
And on defence, too, the primary responsibility depends<br />
uuon us. Now it's true tL.. t we have the ANZUS Treaty, and we have<br />
the Five Power Arrangement with Malaysia and Singapore. But that<br />
doesn't mean that we can just lay back and let the others take the<br />
responsibility. In fact, what it does mean, and this is certain and<br />
something that has to be conveyed to you over and over again<br />
that the more we do, the more they'll be inclined to do with us.<br />
But when we get into a position as we got into at the<br />
middle and the latter parts of World ! Iar II, then we will know we<br />
have reliable friends and allies, and that is why the ANZUS<br />
Treaty will be so valuable to us, and that is why for the Moment,<br />
and while the British orcsance is maintained, their presence in<br />
Malaysia and Singapore will be valuable too.<br />
And the third point that I had to make and I want to<br />
make is thisz There were some misgivings in both the United<br />
States and the United Kingdom as to where we were going. They had<br />
heard of the problems of inflation, industrial disputes they knew<br />
of thie problems associated with the sale of wool.<br />
I was able to give them this assurance, and T think they<br />
recognise it now because they admit there is no country that is<br />
more suitable for investment or more attractive to investment<br />
than Australia is.<br />
This, I believe, is the test of how a country is going<br />
and how great its prospects for the future are.<br />
But I did point out to them that our population is now<br />
thirteen million and growing, that our production is growing at<br />
the rate of somewhere ab. out five per cent per annum, and that our<br />
industry has now become much more diversified and stable than<br />
ever before. So we you and I have got every reason for confidence,<br />
and I believe they have confidence in us too. In short, I think<br />
I was able to point out to them that we know where we're going<br />
and we know how to get there. They understand co'ar problems and<br />
thev understand the outlook for the future. It is a future in which<br />
via should have absolute confidence, and I want to express to you<br />
tonight my personal confidence too.<br />
So as I said, we pointed out to them we know where we're<br />
going. I hope thie Australian people will accent the fact we know<br />
where we ' re going and we will get there and I am sure in a way<br />
that will be satisfactory to you.<br />
Good evening and thank you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
