<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4880</transcript-id>
    <title>INTERVIEW WITH RADIO STATION 3XY, 6 NOVEMBER 1978</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/11/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004880.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Interview with Radio Station 3XY 6 November 1978<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
Today's meeting of the Loan Council will be an historic<br />
meeting. Over a long period of years co-operative devices<br />
have developed between the Cormonealth and the States<br />
to promote Australia's national development. The original<br />
programmes in support of State road construction, the<br />
agreements with NSV and Victoria for the Snowy Mountains<br />
development, the general support of State Loan Preorammes<br />
were all landmarks in the general co-operative approach.<br />
Today's meeting will be of major and historic significance<br />
because it lill -ut into nractical effect t! ie ' in principal'<br />
decision made at the June Loan Council meeting, which<br />
indicated that States would be able to borrow overseas for<br />
major infrastructure projects imnortant for development,<br />
important to sup-oort the economic expansion of States.<br />
There is a common thread running through a number of htie<br />
projects--they add to oower for development, fey add to<br />
export potential, they increase the strength of basic<br />
infrastructure in Australia, they are related to economic<br />
progress.<br />
Ufithout pre-empting the decisions of Loan Council, I am<br />
sure that substantial decisions will be made, in partnership<br />
between the States and the Commonwealth, which will enable<br />
a new Dhase of Australian develo-, nent to begin. The nolicy<br />
is not related to the short-terTa problems. The original<br />
approach and suggestion came from Sir Charles Court about<br />
two years ago, and has been discussed at successive Loan<br />
Council meetings, and there have been very intensive officerd<br />
meetings between the Commonwealth and the States going into </p>
<p>-2-<br />
the particular projects in detail, going into the philosophy<br />
and approach in detail and after that two years of discussions<br />
vie have come to the decision-making day.<br />
Question:<br />
It sounds pretty optimistic from what you are saying.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
I am optimistic. But what I do want to do is put it in the<br />
long-term setting, the long-term development policy. Without<br />
pre-empting any narticular decision, and without implying that<br />
all nrojects will get anproval or full apnroval because I<br />
can't imply that, that's a Loan Council decision but it is<br />
important that it be in the long-term setting, it is important<br />
tha-t it be understood that what is decided today was certainly<br />
in Ministers' minds when our owvn Budget was framed.<br />
Question: So this isn't any extension on the Budget strategy?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
No. It doesn't represent any alteration on Budget strategy<br />
at all, because these projects had been under examination<br />
for months before the Budget. ' 7e knew the extent of them, we<br />
knew the extent of oossible borrowings this year even if<br />
all of them wvere anproved and that was all in mind, and it<br />
was certainly in Ministers' minds at that time that there<br />
would be a positive result.<br />
Question:<br />
Do you accept the view, Mr Fraser, that the allowing of<br />
States to borrow overseas like this can unset the economic<br />
strategy of the Federal Government? </p>
<p>-3-<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
No, I don't, because it depends upon the extent of the<br />
borrowing in any one year. It de'oends upon the nature<br />
of the borrowing, it is subject to Loan Council approval,<br />
and the voting procedure is a simple majority of which the<br />
Commonwealth must be a part which means je have got to<br />
be in agreement and that, therefore, is a very simple<br />
reason. We have got responsibility for overall monetary<br />
oolicy, overall economic control, so it can't upset<br />
Budget strategy. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
