<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3255</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR E.G. WHITLAM AT THE SYDNEY OPERA HOUSE MONDAY 13 MAY 1974</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/05/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003255.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, IMR E, G. WHITLAM<br />
AT THE SYDNEY OPERA HOUSE<br />
MONDAY 13 MAY 1974<br />
ON 2 DECEMBER 1972 THERE WAS A NEW SPIRIT OF<br />
HOPE KINDLED IN THIS'COONTRY. THAT HOPE, FOR A BETTER<br />
AUSTRALIA, A MORE EQUAL AUSTRALIA, A MORE INDEPENDENT<br />
AUSTRALIA, A MORE TOLERANT AUSTRALIA, A MORE COMPASSIONATE<br />
AUSTRALIA, BURNS BRIGHTER THAW EVER. AND IT WILL BURN<br />
BRIGHTER STILL,' AFTER 18 MAY.<br />
EVERYTHING I KNOW ABOUT THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE,<br />
EVERY RESPONSE OF THE PAST TWO WEEKS AN ENTHUSIASM<br />
AND EXHILERATION, A DETERMINATION BEYOND ALL MY EXPERIENCE<br />
IN PUBLIC LIFE CONFIRMS MY BELIEF THAT THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
PEOPLE ARE NOT GOING TO TURN BACK, THEY'RE NOT GOING<br />
TO TURN THEIR. BACKS ON THE MILLIONS OF THEIR FELLOW<br />
CITIZENS TO WHOM OUR GOVERNMENT HAS BROUGHT A NEW DEAL,<br />
A NEW SENSE OF PURPOSE AND A NEW SENSE OF PRIDE AND<br />
PARTICIPATION IN THEIR COUNTRY, </p>
<p>AFTER NEXT SATURDAY, WE ARE GOING TO HAVE A NEW<br />
PARLIAMENT, A CONTEMPORARY PARLIAMENT, A PARLIAMENT FOR<br />
OUR TIMES, WE ARE GOING TO HAVE A CONSTITUTION THAT<br />
REFLECTS THE NEEDS OF OUR TIMES IN CRUCIAL MATTERS OF<br />
EQUAL DEMOCRATIC REPRESENTATION OF WORKABLE PARLIAMENTS<br />
OF FULL LOCAL GOVERNMENT PARTNERSHIP IN OUR NATIONAL AFFAIRS,<br />
WE ARE GOING TO HAVE AN AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT CONTINUING<br />
TO CARRY OUT ITS MANDATE, BUT THIS TIME, A GOVERNMENT<br />
WITH THE AUTHORITY IT NEEDS TO GO AHEAD, AGAINST THE<br />
OBSTRUCTION OF THE MEN OF YESTERDAY,<br />
THERE HAS NEVER BEEN AN ELECTION IN LIVING MEMORY<br />
WHERE THE ISSUE AT STAKE WAS SO CLEAR AND SO C-LEAR-CUTI<br />
IT IS NOTHING LESS THAN WHETHER PARLIAMENTARY DEMOCRACY<br />
SHALL PREVAIL, WHETHER ELECTED GOVERNMENTS SHALL. HAVE<br />
THE RIGHT TO CARRY ON THEIR FULL ELECTED TERM AND TO<br />
CARRY OUT THE FULL PROGRAM FOR WHICH THEY WERE ELECTED, </p>
<p>-3-<br />
THE HOPES RELEASED BY OUR VICTORY IN 1972<br />
WERE NOT CONFINED TO AUSTRALIA. AROUND THE WORLD,<br />
PARTICULARLY IN OUR REGION, PEOPLE WERE MADE TO BELIEVE<br />
THAT PARLIAMENTARY DEMOCRACY COU_ L WORK, THAT THERE<br />
COULD BE ORDERLY CHANGE, PEACEFUL CHANGE TO BELIEVE<br />
THAT A GOVERNMENT ENTRENCHED FOR 23 YEARS OF ALMOST<br />
UNCHALLENGED POWER COULD BE REMOVED BY THE WILL OF THE<br />
PEOPLE, EXPRESSED FREELY, PEACEFULLY AND EMPHATICALLYV<br />
NOW THEY SEE ALL THAT PUT IN JEOPARDY, AFTER ONLY<br />
17 MONTHS. THE ELECTION OF OUR GOVERNMENT NOT ONLY<br />
CREATED A NEW INTEREST IN AUSTRALIA, AROUND OUR REGION,<br />
AROUND THE WORLD: IT REPRESENTED A NEW HOPE FOR<br />
DEMOCRACY EVERYWHERE, FOR THE PRINCIPLE OF PEACEFUL CHANGE<br />
THROUGH PARLIAMENTARY ELECTIONS. </p>
<p>-4-<br />
WHAT OUR OPPONENTS SAY TO THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE,<br />
AND WHAT THEY WANT THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE TO SAY TO THE<br />
REST OF THE WORLD IS THAT IT WAS ALL A MISTAKE.<br />
THEY SAY: TURN BACK THEY SAY: COME BACK<br />
COME BACK TO THE SAME OLD DESPAIR, THE SAME OLD DIVISIONS,<br />
THE SAME OLD PREJUDICES, THE SAME OLD MANIPULATED FEARS,<br />
THE SAME OLD DRIFT, THE SAME OLD STOP-GO, THE SAME<br />
OLD SPECIAL PLEADING, THE SAME OLD DOMINATION BY SPECIAL<br />
INTERESTS, THE SAME OLD CREW THAT YOU REJECTED ONLY<br />
17 MONTHS AGO AND REPLACED IN A PEACEFUL, ORDERLY,<br />
DEMOCRATIC WAY ONLY 17 MONTHS AGO. </p>
<p>WHAT IS IT THEY ASK YOU TO REJECT? WHAT IS IT<br />
THAT HAS STIRRED UP SO MUCH VOCAL AND VISIBILE HOSTILITY<br />
AMONG POWERFUL INTERESTS AGAINST MY GOVERNMENT?<br />
IT IS BECAUSE WE HAVE PLACED THE PEOPLE BEFORE SPECIAL<br />
PRIVILEGE. IN ORDER TO FIGHT INFLATION, TO PROVIDE<br />
MONEY FOR SCHOOLS, FOR HOSPITALS, FOR THE AGED, THE<br />
HANDICAPPED, FOR OUR. CITIES, WE HAVE WITHDRAWN HAD. TO<br />
WITHDRAW SOME SPECIAL PRIVILEGES CONFERRED BY OUR<br />
OPPONENTS AN AMOUNT IN ALL OF NEARLY $ 500 MILLION<br />
OF YOUR MONEY. OUR OPPONENTS ARE COMMITTED TO RESTORING<br />
THESE PRIVILEGES. -THEY PROPOSE TO DO IT WITH YOUR MONEY,<br />
AND WITH THE MONEY THAT WE HAVE DIVERTED TO AREAS OF<br />
GREATEST NEED, TO SCHOOLS, TO HEALTH, TO WELFARE,<br />
TO CITIES, TO THE MAJORITY OF THE PEOPLE, TO THE PLACES<br />
WHERE MOST AUSTRALIANS LIVE AND HAVE TO LIVE, AND TO<br />
THE NEEDS OF MOST AUSTRALIAN CHILDREN.<br />
FOR LET IT BE UNDERSTOOD:. EVERY CONCESSION AND SUBSIDY<br />
TO A SPECIAL MINORITY INTEREST IS A TAX UPON THE MAJORITY,<br />
A TAX UPON YOU AND YOUR FELLOW CITIZENS OUTSIDE.<br />
SO BE CLEAR ABOUT OUR OPPONENTS' INTENTIONS.<br />
THEY TALK ABOUT A PACKAGE TO FIGHT INFLATION. NOW WE KNOW<br />
WHAT'S IN THE PACKAGE. </p>
<p>FIRST, RESTORE ALMOST $ 500 MILLION WORTH OF<br />
SPECIAL INTEREST PAYMENTS, BOUNTIES AND CONCESSIONS AND<br />
. SUBSIDIES, How WOULD THIS BE DONE? WITH YOUR TAXES.<br />
SECONDLY, FREEZE WAGES. HOW WOULD THIS BE DONE?<br />
BY SUSPENDING THE ARBITRATION COMMISSION, UNDERMINING<br />
ITS AUTHORITY, SETTING ASIDE FEDERAL AWARDS AND LETTING<br />
STATE POLITICIANS SET YOUR WAGES AND SALARIES. FOR<br />
THAT IS WHAT MR SNEDDEN'S PROPOSAL FOR A WAGE FREEZE MEANS.<br />
WOULD YOU LET SIR ROBERT'ASKIN FIX YOUR INCOMES?<br />
THIRDLY, MR SNEDDEN HAS A MARVELLOUS. PROPOSAL:-<br />
TO BRING DOWN THE PRICE OF MEAT BY WITH-HOLDING LOCAL<br />
SUPPLIES AND THEN IMPORTING MEAT. AT THE RISK OF<br />
BEING CORRECTED BY PROFESSOR MANNING CLARK, WE HAVEN'T<br />
IMPORTED MEAT SINCE BENNELONG WAS A BOY, OR AT LEAST<br />
SINCE GOVERNOR PHILLIP PLANTED THE UNION JACK DOWN THERE<br />
ACROSS THE QUAY. </p>
<p>FOURTHLY, OUR OPPONENTS SAY, DOUBLE THE PRICE<br />
OF PETROL. FOR MAKE NO MISTAKE, WHAT ANTHONY SAYS,<br />
CLEOPATRA MUST DO.<br />
THAT IS THE-PACKAGE. SOME PLAN AGAINST INFLATION:<br />
SOME PACKAGE: AND FOR THE REST OF THEIR POLICIES WE ' LL READ<br />
ABOUT THEM IN THE HERALD OVER THE 3 DAYS 3 DAYS<br />
BEFORE THE ELECTION THEY'LL TELL US WHAT THEY PROPOSE<br />
FOR THE NEXT 3 YEARS.<br />
.7-</p>
<p>WE ARE FIGHTING INFLATION. WE ARE BEATING<br />
INFLATION, WE SHARE THE PROBLEM OF INFLATION WITH<br />
EVERY COMPARABLE COUNTRY; AND WE ARE DOING BETTER THAN<br />
ANY COMPARABLE COUNTRY, ALONE AMONG COMPARABLE COUNTRIES,<br />
OUR INFLATION RATE FELLLAST QUARTER. IT WILL CONTINUE<br />
TO FALL. BUT ALMOST ALONE AMONGST THOSE COMPARABLE<br />
COUNTRIES, WE. ARE-NOT FIGHTING INFLATION BY PUTTING<br />
MEN AND WOMEN OUT OF WORK. WE HAVE-RESTORED THE<br />
FULL EMPLOYMENT. DESTROYED BY MR SNEDDEN WHEN HE WAS<br />
TREASURER. WE WILL MAINTAIN FULL EMPLOYMENT.<br />
ALONE AMONGST THESE COMPARABLE COUNTRIES WE ARE CONTINUING<br />
TO FIGHT AGAINST INFLATION WHILE CONTINUING TO PROVIDE<br />
NEW OPPORTUNITIES FOR OUR CHILDREN, THE DISADVANTAGED,<br />
FOR HOME SEEKERS, FOR HOME BUYERS, FOR THE CITIES.<br />
i </p>
<p>THE FIGHT AGAINST ' INFLATION WILL CONTINUE.<br />
IT WILL BE WON. BUT WE DO NOT CHOOSE TO FIGHT IT<br />
AT OUR CHILDREN S EXPENSE, OR AT THE EXPENSE OF THE<br />
DISADVANTAGED OF THIS NATION. IT WON'T . BE WON BY<br />
LETTING OUR PUBLIC TRANSPORT IN OUR CITIES BECOME<br />
EVEN MORE RAMSHACKLE, MORE AND MORE INEFFICIENT,<br />
MORE COSTLY, IT WILL BE WON ON THE BASIS OF MORE EQUAL<br />
SHARING OF OUR OPPORTUNITIES, OF OUR WEALTH, AND<br />
IF EVER NECESSARY, MORE EQUAL'SPREADING OF SACRIFICES.<br />
I CANNOT PROMISE THE GRAZIERS EARNING. OVER<br />
A HUNDRED THOUSAND DOLLARS, WHO HAVE LOST $ 4 MILLION<br />
IN SUPERPHOSPHATE BOUNTIES, THAT THEY MIGHT NOT HAVE<br />
TO FOREGO A NEW YACHT FOR A YEAR. BUT I WILL PROMISE YOU<br />
THAT NO AUSTRALIAN CHILD WILL HAVE TO FOREGO A YEAR'S<br />
EXPANDED EDUCATION OPPORTUNITIES AND IN EFFECT,<br />
AS IT WOULD BE-UNDER OUR OPPONENTS, LOSE THOSE NEW<br />
OPPORTUNITIES FOR A LIFETIME. </p>
<p>WHAT HAS OUR GOVERNMENT BEEN ABOUT?<br />
THIS VERY MEETING, THE GREAT PLACE IN WHICH IT IS HELD,<br />
THE AUSPICES UNDER WHICH IT IS HELD, THE COMING TOGETHER<br />
OF THE PEOPLE OF THIS CITY WHO WORK IN THIS CITY,<br />
WHO GIVE THIS CITY ITS LIFE, SYMBOLISE WHAT THIS<br />
GOVERNMENT IS ALL ABOUT.<br />
WE ARE FOR THE PEOPLE, AGAINST SPECIAL INTERESTS.<br />
WE ARE FOR EQUALITY OF OPPORTUNITY, AGAINST PRIVILEGE.<br />
WE ARE FOR A MODERN, PROGRESSIVE, HUMANE AUSTRALIA.<br />
WE ARE FOR AN AUSTRALIA IN WHICHEVERY CITIZEN<br />
EVERYONE BORN HERE) EVERYONE WHO SETTLES AMONGST US, HAS<br />
A FAIR AND EQUAL CHANCE TO ENJOY THE OPPORTUNITIES<br />
OUR GREAT WEALTH OFFERS, WHERE EVERY MAN AND WOMAN<br />
CAN PARTICIPATE AS A FULL MEMBER OF SOCIETY, FULLY<br />
INVOLVED IN THE WORK OF MOVING THIS COUNTRY AHEAD.<br />
AND THAT IS THE SIGNIFICANCE OF THE PRESENCE OF<br />
SO MANY DISTINGUISHED AUTHORS AND ARTISTS AND ACADEMICS<br />
HERE TODAY. </p>
<p>THIS COUNTRY HAS SEEN IN THE LAST 17 MONTHS<br />
AN UNPARALLELLED BURST IN CREATIVE ACTIVITY.<br />
SURE, WE HAVE MADE AVAILABLE FOR THE ARTS A GREAT AMOUNT<br />
OF MONEY, FOR INSTANCE, TODAY I WILL BE ANNOUNCING<br />
THE FULFILMENT, AFTER MANY MONTHS OF INQUIRY, OF A<br />
PROMISE I MADE IN 1972 FOR A PUBLIC LENDING RIGHT,<br />
BY WHICH AUSTRALIA'S AUTHORS CAN RECEIVE PAYMENT FOR<br />
THEIR BOOKS IN PUBLIC LIBRARIES.<br />
BUT AS FAR AS THE ARTS ARE CONCERNED,. IT'S NOT<br />
JUST A MATTER OF MONEY; IT IS A MATTER OF INVOLVEMENTL<br />
INVOLVEMENT IN THE MAINSTREAM OF THE LIFE OF THE REAL<br />
AND LIVING COMMUNITY. FOR IT IS OUR ARTS, OUR<br />
GREAT BUILDINGS, LIKE THIS, WHICH EXPRESS TO GENERATIONS<br />
YET UNBORN WHAT WE WERE LIKE IN OUR TIME, WHAT WE<br />
ACHIEVED, WHAT WE DARED TO TRY TO ACHIEVE, IN OUR TIME.<br />
i. </p>
<p>IN 17 MONTHS WE HAVE ACHIEVED MUCH AND WE HAVE<br />
DARED TO ACHIEVE MUCH TOGETHER. BUT THERE IS SO MUCH<br />
MORE TO BE DONE TOGETHER. IT HASN'T BEEN ALL<br />
PLAIN-SAILING, AND I'M NOT SAYING THERE AREN'T THINGS<br />
WE WOULDN'T HAVE DONE DIFFERENTLY, GIVEN MORE TIME,<br />
GIVEN THE EXPERIENCE WE NOW HAVE. WE ARE TRYING<br />
TO ACHIEVE AN AUSTRALIA WHERE THE ABLE AND THE ABLE-BODIED,<br />
THE TALENTED, THE SKILLED, CAN ENJOY THE FULLEST FRUITS<br />
OF THEIR GIFTS, AND OPPORTUNITIES; BUT, AT THE SAME<br />
TIME AND ABOVE ALL, AN AUSTRALIA WHERE NO GROUP OF<br />
AUSTRALIANS MUST TAKE SECOND AFLACE OR GO TO'THE WALL<br />
JUST BECAUSE THEY ARE WOMEN, JUST BECAUSE THEY ARE NEWCOMERS,<br />
OR BECAUSE THEY ARE YOUNG, OR BECAUSE THEY HAVE TO. LIVE<br />
IN NEW AND DISTANT SUBURBS, OR BECAUSE THEIR PARENTS ARE<br />
POOR, OR BECAUSE THEY ARE HANDICAPPED, OR BECAUSE THEY<br />
ARE OLD, OR BECAUSE THEY ARE ABORIGINES, OR BECAUSE<br />
THEY HAVE SUFFERED INJURY OR SICKNESS.<br />
WE ARE TRYING TO BUILD AN AUSTRALIA WHERE ALL CAN<br />
FEEL INVOLVED, AN AUSTRALIA IN WHICH ALL FEEL A SENSE OF<br />
DIRECTION, OF PURPOSE, AN AUSTRALIA WHICH BELONGS, NOT. TO<br />
SPECIAL INTERESTS, NOT TO THE PRIVILEGED MEN BORN TO RULE,<br />
RQI TO OVERSEAS. CORPORATIONS, BUT AN AUSTRALIA WHICH<br />
BELONGS TO AUL AUSTRALIANS,<br />
AND IT CAN BE DONE, WE ARE GOING TO DO IT. </p>
<p>IT CAN BE DONE THROUGH OUR PROGRAM.<br />
WE ARE GOING TO CARRY THAT PROGRAM THROUGH.<br />
IT CAN BE DONE THROUGH THE PARLIAMENTARY SYSTEM.<br />
WE ARE GOING TO DO IT. WILL YOU JOIN US IN DOING IT?<br />
IT CAN BE DONE THROUGH THE PROGRAMS WE HAVE STARTED,<br />
THROUGH THE PROGRAMS THAT ARE NOW BEARING THEIR FRUIT<br />
FOR THE BENEFIT OF ALL AUSTRALIANS.<br />
WILL YOU LET US GET ON WITH THAT JOB?<br />
IN THIS GREAT CITY; THE LIVING SYMBOL OF SO<br />
MUCH THAT WE AUSTRALIANS HAVE ACHIEVED TOGETHER IN<br />
THE PAST: IN THIS BUILDING, SO MUCH A LIVING . SYMBOL OF<br />
OUR PRESENT VIGOR, PROSPERITY, PRIDE AND STRENGTH)<br />
AT THIS MEETING, SO MUCH THE SYMBOL OF THE NEW HOPES<br />
BORN AND THE TALENTS AND ENERGIES UNLEASHED BY OUR<br />
EMPHATIC BUT NONETHELESS INCOMPLETE VICTORY 17 MONTHS AGO:<br />
I ASK YOUR SUPPORT FOR THE FUTURE, FOR YOUR FUTURE,<br />
YOUR CHILDREN'S FUTURE, FOR THE FUTURE OF AUSTRALIANS<br />
YET UNBORN. </p>
<p>AUSTRALIANS CAN TURN BACK, TURN THE CLOCK BACK,<br />
GO BACK TO ALL THAT OLD HOPELESS NESS, FLATNESS AND<br />
STALE FUTILITY, OR THEY CAN GO ON AND GO AHEAD<br />
WITH OUR PROGRAM OUR CLEAR AND POSITIVE PROGRAM<br />
FOR A STRONG, UNITED, MORE EQUAL AUSTRALIA.<br />
LET SATURDAY BE THE DAY WHEN AUSTRALIA SAID<br />
OVERWHELMINGLY YES TO THE FUTURE. </p>
<p>404 .10,101 A1<br />
( A jai.) V<br />
6TK .0 An[ nOa os c. flai'* Kom<br />
IA o ia Y A no. t i 1001a13' v<br />
" r pins' I. n . m </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
