<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>484</transcript-id>
    <title>WEEK ENDING 10TH MARCH, 1962 - INDEX OF MINISTERIAL STATEMENTS ISSUED IN CANBERRA</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/03/1962</release-date>
    <release-type>Index</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000484_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Weekly Index No<br />
Week Ending 10th March, 19b2<br />
COMMON EALTH OF AUSTRALIA<br />
Index of Ministerial Statements Issued in Canberra<br />
Deputy Prime Minister and Minister for Trade, The RG. Hon. John<br />
McEwen<br />
March 4. No. 220A STATEMENT BY THE MINISTER ON HIS DEPARTURE<br />
FOR NORTH AMERICA<br />
8 No. 239 NORTH AMERICAN WOOL TEXTILE MISSION<br />
The Minister for National Development, Senator the Hon. W. H.<br />
March 9 No. 249 MINISTER'S VISIT TO SNOWY SCHE EOneM. M.<br />
11 No. 251 SAVING OF œ 9 MILLIONS IN EXPENDITURE ON<br />
SNOWY MOUNTAINS SCHEa2ME<br />
The Minister for Labour and National Service, The Hon. William<br />
McMahon.<br />
March 6 No, 225 PROPOSALS FOR IMPROVING THE APPRENTICESHIP<br />
SYSTEM<br />
The Minister for Civil Aviation, Senator Shane Paltridge<br />
March 8No. 243 ASSESSORS APPOINTED FOR VISCOUNT CRASH<br />
INQUIRY<br />
The Postmaster-General, The Hon. C. W. Davidson.<br />
March 8 No. 237 EXTENSION OF TELEVISION SERVICES IN CAPITAL<br />
CITIES<br />
7 Noo238A QUANTITIES ISSUED OF RECENT COMMEMORATIVE<br />
STAMPS<br />
8 No, 240 INCREASED EMPLOYMENT IN THE POSTMASTERGENERAL'<br />
S DEPARTMENT.<br />
9 No. 248 COAXIAL CABLE SYDNEYV/ ELBOURNE<br />
The Minister for External Affairs, The Hon. Sir Garfield Barvick<br />
March 9 No. 246 AUSTRALIAN GRANTS TO TANGANYIKA, KENYA AND<br />
SOMALIA<br />
The Minister for Army, the Hon. J. O. Cramer<br />
March 8 No. 24L LETHAL LAMP RECOVERED BY ARMY<br />
7 No. 230 THAI ARMY OFFICER TO TRAIN IN AUSTRALIA<br />
The Minister for the Interior and Works, The Hon. Gordon Freeth<br />
March 5 No. 222 CONTRACT LET FOR DEFENCE PROJECT<br />
8 No. 242 SATURDAY BANK CLOSING<br />
The Minister for the Navy, Senator the Hone J. G. Gorton<br />
March 4 No. 220 " TIDE AUSTRAL" CAPTAIN APPOINTED<br />
5 No. 221 RESERVES PREPARE TO MAN MINESWEEPERS<br />
7 No. 231. SYDNEY RECOMMISSIONS AS TROOP CARRIER<br />
7 No. 234 R. A. N. VISITS CHRISTMAS ISLAND<br />
8 No. 241 FIVE R. A. N, SHIPS IN SOUTH EAST ASIA<br />
9 No, 247 VISIT FROM NEW ZEALAND'S NEWEST WARSHIP<br />
The Minister for Shipping and Transport, The Hon. Hubert Opperman<br />
March 7Noo227 AUS. MOTOR VEHICLE STANDARDS COMMITTEE<br />
TO BE HELD IN SYDNEY MARCH 27 and<br />
The Minister forSuoply, The Hon. Allen Fairhall<br />
No. 229 AUSTRALIAN DEVICE USED IN SKYILRK ROCKET<br />
EXPERIMENT<br />
The Minister forAir. The Hon. Leslie Bury<br />
No. 219 FRENCH LANGUAGE TRAINING FOR RAAF FIGHTER<br />
SPECIALISTS<br />
Noo228 PRLAF TO DEFEND MALAYA BASE IN MOCK ATTACK<br />
No. 250 CONTROLLER NAMED FOR RAAlF E. D. P. CENTRE / 2<br />
March 7<br />
March 4 7 9 Y </p>
<p>' D ' a The Minister for Repatriattion The Hon, R. W. Sartz<br />
March 6<br />
It 7<br />
i' 7<br />
I' 7<br />
I? 7 No. 226<br />
No, 232<br />
No. 235<br />
No. 236<br />
No. 238<br />
The De~ rtment of B;. BY HA-SS PROGRESSED 1 ELL<br />
ADELI-Ii) E GIRL GETS CADETSiIIP<br />
M. L. 1A2s DAUGHTER FOR SOCIAL WORK<br />
DRUGS H;' VE IiD BIG EFFECT<br />
C? EALTH WILL HELP PERTH GAMES<br />
External Affairs<br />
March 7No. 235 RETURN OF THE " THYI. d DAN" FROM ANT1RCTICA<br />
The Department of the Treasury<br />
March 5No, 223 CONSOLIDA. TED REVENUE FUND AT FEB. 28. 1962.<br />
TheDepartment ofthe '-rmy.<br />
March 8No. 245 MUSIC DIPLOMS IN ARMJuIY<br />
With the Compliments of<br />
The Goverment Public Relations Office,<br />
Parliament House,<br />
CANdiBETR 9j,. C. T.<br />
The De-oartment of </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
