<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>12207</transcript-id>
    <title>Peter Nugent </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/04/2001</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I was shocked and saddened to learn of Peter Nugent's sudden death earlier today at the age of 63.</p>
<p>Peter was a valued and capable colleague. He worked tirelessly in the House of Representatives on behalf of the people of Aston from the time of his election as their member in 1990.</p>
<p>He was a particularly active contributor to policy debates within the party room. Foreign policy and social issues involving the treatment of minority groups and the disadvantaged were particular passions of his.</p>
<p>Born in Chelmsford, England, Peter served for 24 years in the Royal Air Force, retiring as a Squadron Leader. Immediately before entering Federal Parliament, he worked in sales and marketing in the private sector.</p>
<p>He was Shadow Minister for Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Affairs in 1993-94 and also served with distinction on a number of Parliamentary committees, including Foreign Affairs, Defence and Trade (Chairman of the Human Rights Sub-Committee since 1996) and Chairman of the Joint Committee on the National Crime Authority since 1998.</p>
<p>Peter's passionate interest in human rights and the disadvantaged was also reflected in his work as Chairman of the Amnesty International Parliamentary Group since 1996 and as a member of the Council for Aboriginal Reconciliation between 1991 and 1997.</p>
<p>Two days ago he returned from a Parliamentary delegation visit to China. Peter was active in promoting friendship with countries in the region, chairing Parliamentary Friendship groups with China, Malaysia and Singapore since 1996.</p>
<p>Peter Nugent has given great service to the Liberal Party of Australia. His premature and untimely death deprives the people of Aston of a powerful advocate who will be greatly missed by his parliamentary colleagues.</p>
<p>I have already spoken to Peter's wife, Carol. To her, and to Peter's three children, Dee, Greg and Barry, I extend the sympathy of all of his Liberal colleagues.</p>
<p>24 April 2001</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
