<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6400</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER: TABLING STATEMENT ON ASTEC REPORT ON AUSTRALIA&#039;S ROLE IN THE NUCLEAR FUEL CYCLE, 31 MAY 1984</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>31/05/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006400.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Prime minister: Tabling Statement on ASTEC Report on<br />
Australia's Role in the Nuclear Fuel Cycle 31 May 1984<br />
For the information of Honourable Members I present the<br />
report by the Australian Science and Technology Council<br />
( ASTEC) on Australia's role in the nuclear fuel cycle.<br />
Mr Speaker, I seek leave to make a statement in respect of<br />
the Report.<br />
Following the Government's examination of policy in relation<br />
to the export of Australian uranium last year, I wrote to<br />
the Chairman of ASTEC, Professor Ralph Slatyer, on 9<br />
November 1983, requesting that ASTEC undertake an inquiry,<br />
under his personal direction, into Australia's role in the<br />
nuclear fuel cycle.<br />
The Inquiry was asked . to examine in particular:<br />
Australia's nuclear safeguards arrangements, giving<br />
particular attention to the effectiveness of the<br />
bllaeraland multilateral agreements, and to the scope<br />
for strengthening tese agreements;<br />
the opportunities for Australia through the conditions<br />
of its involvement in the nuclear fuel cycle to further<br />
advance the cause of nuclear non-proliferation, having<br />
regard to the policies and practices of recipient<br />
countries; and<br />
the adequacy of existing technology for the handling and<br />
disposal of waste products by consuming countries, and<br />
the ways in which Australia can further contribute to<br />
the development of safe disposal methods.<br />
The Council was subsequently requested to include some<br />
consideration of the issues raised by the possible<br />
extraction of thorium for nuclear use from Australian<br />
mineral sands containing the mineral monazite.<br />
The Slatyer Inquiry was an integral part of the Government's<br />
uranium policy decisions announced last November.<br />
U,<br />
4 C. </p>
<p>At that time the Government decided that:,<br />
the Roxby Downs Joint Venturers be advised that if<br />
a commercial decision to p~ roceed with the<br />
development of Roxby Downs were to be made by them,<br />
the Government would permit the export of uranium<br />
produced from that mine; and the export of the<br />
uranium would be subject to whatever safeguards<br />
arrangements applied generally 1--o uranium exports<br />
at the time of export;<br />
with the exception of Roxby Downs if commercially<br />
feasible, the Government not permit the development<br />
of any new uraniumn mines;<br />
all future exports of Australia's uranium under<br />
both existing and any future contracts be made<br />
subject to the most stringent supply conditions,<br />
such conditions to be determined by the Government<br />
following an inquiry into Australia's role in the<br />
nuclear fuel cycle.<br />
In setting up the Inquiry, the Government considered il-to<br />
be important that there should be an independent and<br />
objective audit of policies and practices in regard to<br />
Australia's uranium exports to ensure that they contributed<br />
to and strengthened Australia's pursuit of its disarmament<br />
and non-proliferation objectives.<br />
The Government also-gought a scientific assessment of the<br />
adequacy of ways in whic~ countries managed and disposed of<br />
radioactive waste.<br />
ASTEC, as the pre-eminent Council providing independent<br />
advice to the Government on science and technology<br />
questions, was judged best-qualified to perform this role<br />
under the personal direction of Professor Slatyer.<br />
The terms of reference for the Inquiry focused primarily on<br />
the issues of non-proliferation, safeguards and waste<br />
management, both because of their intrinsic importance, and<br />
because they are of particular concern in the community in<br />
relation to Australia's involvement in the nuclear fuel<br />
cycle.<br />
The final Report reflects a broad interpretation of the<br />
terms of reference, and provides a comprehensive<br />
identification of the elements of the fuel cycle and the<br />
issues which they raise for the export of Australian<br />
uranium. </p>
<p>The Report indicates that while the percentage of world<br />
electricity requirements which will be generated by nuclear<br />
means cannot be forecast precisely, no new energy source is<br />
likely to have a significant impact for the next quarter<br />
century. Accordingly the Report notes that the world can bE?<br />
expected to rely largely on coal and nuclear energy,<br />
supplemented by oil, to provide the major part of its<br />
electricity requirments for this period.<br />
This would be-the case even if Australia were not to export<br />
its uranium.<br />
The Report notes that there is no shortage of uranium in the!<br />
world to supply fuel to the nuclear power industry, and<br />
points out that the future development of the nuclear power'<br />
industry will not be dependent on Australian uranium, and<br />
will proceed irrespective of whether or not Australia is a<br />
supplier. The Report suggests that if international tensions are to be<br />
reduced and the prospects of a peaceful global environment<br />
enhanced, the importance of national and international<br />
energy security cannot be overemphasised. It notes tha-t'<br />
disruptions in the supply of resources of any sort have been<br />
a cause of international tension and, through human history,<br />
have led to war.<br />
* The Report points out that countries which do not have<br />
indigenous energy resources are most concerned to ensure<br />
reliability of supplies, and to this end place great<br />
emphasis on diversity ofi'supplies and the political<br />
stability of supplier countries. For this reason many<br />
countries have turned to nuclear energy for electricity<br />
generation out of concern about reliability of oil supplies<br />
both in the short and long-term.<br />
The Inquiry has concluded that Australia, through being a<br />
reliable, long-term supplier of uranium, is in a position to<br />
contribute significantly to international energy security.<br />
Further, the Report brings out that assurance of reliable<br />
long-term supplies of uranium at reasonable prices will also<br />
reduce the motivation for individual countries to seek<br />
greater energy security by carrying out more. steps of the<br />
fuel cycle, particularly reprocessing, within national<br />
boundaries. Against this background the Report concludes that Australia<br />
will best be able to make a significant contribution to<br />
non-proliferation and world peace if it is actively involved<br />
in the nuclear fuel cycle. </p>
<p>By involvement of this kind, the Report argues, Australia<br />
will be able to make a direct contribution to the<br />
development of the civil nuclear fuel cycle in ways that<br />
will increase global energy security, strengthen the<br />
elements of the non-proliferation regime and reduce the<br />
risks of misuse of civil facilities and the diversion of<br />
nuclear materials from civil to military uses.<br />
Without such involvement, global energy security would be<br />
less assured,-and Australia's ability to strengthen the<br />
non-proliferation regime and to influence future<br />
developments in the fuel cycle would be reduced.<br />
The Report expresses the concern that we must all share that<br />
the prevention of nuclear war is of the greatest importance*<br />
to all humanity.<br />
A major component of global efforts to prevent such a war is<br />
prevention of further proliferation of nuclear weapons,<br />
either by an increase in the size of the arsenals of those<br />
countries which already have such weapons, referred to as<br />
vertical proliferation, or by an increase in the number of<br />
countries with such weapons or which have exploded nuclEar<br />
devices, referred to as horizontal proliferation.<br />
The Report recognises that since nuclear fission not only<br />
provides power for electricity generation but also<br />
constitutes the explosive source of weapons, it is<br />
understandable that there should be widespread public<br />
concern about the degree to which civil nuclear activities<br />
could contribute to the evelovment of nuclear weapons.<br />
In this regard the Inquiry makes a number of points.<br />
Q The great majority of the countries of the world have found<br />
compelling reasons for not building nuclear weapons and have<br />
given a commitment not to do so by becoming members of the<br />
Non-Proliferation Treaty. They have also accepted<br />
safeguards on all their nuclear facilities so that their<br />
commitment to non-proliferation can be verified.<br />
The Report points out that if a decision is taken by a'<br />
country to develop nuclear weapons this can be achieved,<br />
provided that the country has sufficient determination and a<br />
reasonable scientific and technological infrastructure. The<br />
absence of a civil nuclear industry would not prevent such a<br />
development, although the procedure would be more difficult.<br />
and slower.<br />
But the Report suggests that, should * a country decide to<br />
embark on a weapons program, it is unlikely to use a civil<br />
power reactor to do so, as this would be inefficient both in<br />
terms of producing weapons usable material and in terms of<br />
electricity generation. </p>
<p>The Report concludes that the task for all countries is to<br />
create an international political climate in which actions<br />
leading to the growth of the arsenals of nuclear weapons<br />
states, and the extension of a nuclear capability to<br />
so-called " threshold" countries, are not taken.<br />
In this regard the Report focuses on the Non-Proliferation<br />
Treaty, as the most important multilateral non-proliferationk<br />
and arms control agreement in existence a view which this<br />
Government strongly supports and will continue to in<br />
multilateral fora, and in our discussions with other nations;<br />
on non-proliferation and arms control matters.<br />
The Report makes a number of recommendations aimed at<br />
strengthening adherance to the treaty.<br />
In particular it notes that continued support by' many<br />
countries will depend upon the fulfilment of the three-way<br />
bargain contained in the treaty.<br />
These involve a pledge by non-nuclear weapon states neither.<br />
to manufacture nor acquire nuclear weapons and to accept<br />
verification of this, a commitment by all parties to pursue<br />
nuclear disarmament, and an undertaking to provide acc,..: s by<br />
members to nuclear items for peaceful purposes. In this<br />
latter regard, the Report refers to the importance of<br />
Article IV of the treaty, which affirms the right of all<br />
countries to use nuclear energy for peaceful purposes. It<br />
also requires those countries in a position to do so to<br />
contribute to ' the further development of nuclear energy in<br />
member countries.<br />
At a more fundamental level the Report highlights the<br />
necessity-not just of maintaining the non-proliferation<br />
regime, but of demonstrating that the obligations contained<br />
in the Treaty are being met.<br />
In this regard, the significance of the forthcoming 1985 NPT<br />
Review Conference is emphasised as is the need to register<br />
somne positive achievements in the field of disarmament<br />
before the future of the treaty is decided in 1995.<br />
The Government has stressed on a number of occasions and<br />
reaffirms the fundamental importance it attaches to the role!<br />
of the Review Conference to the future of the NPT.<br />
Among the Government's more important initiatives in support:<br />
of an effective non-proliferation regime has been our<br />
backing for a nuclear free zone in the South Pacific. The<br />
Report sees this as contributing to the international<br />
non-proliferation regime in a substantial region, as well as;<br />
responding to the fears of small island states in the region<br />
about the future conservation and use of their major<br />
resource, the ocean. </p>
<p>Mr Speaker,<br />
There can be no doubt that the issues of disarmament and<br />
non-proliferation are among the most important of our time.<br />
It is the international community's ability to deal with<br />
them effectively which will determine our future.<br />
It is particularly important that we be clear-sighted in our<br />
thinking on the issues involved.<br />
The Report notes that ' two key arguments have been put<br />
forward opposing Australia's involvement: in the nuclear fuel<br />
cycle. It has, for example, been suggested that the solution to the.<br />
problems of nuclear proliferation is for the world to forgo<br />
C the use of nuclear energy, and for countries such as<br />
Australia to take a lead by withholding supply of uranium.<br />
The Report rejects this suggestion, observing that the use<br />
of nuclear energy is an established fact of life, and that<br />
Australia' s withdrawal would not affect the decisions that<br />
countri-es have made and will make to use nuclear energy.<br />
A second line of argument is that, by supplying uraniumn to<br />
nuclear weapon states, Australia might be freeing up uranium<br />
for use in weapons. The Report also rejects this argument,<br />
drawing attention to the fact that those states already have<br />
adequate supplies of uranium and are not assisted in any way<br />
by the supply of Australian uranium. Pt more bluntly, the<br />
Report concludes that denial of supply to nuclear weapon<br />
states would not affect ih any way their weapons programs.<br />
On the basis of these and other related considerations, the<br />
Report concludes that there are more practical measures that<br />
Q Australia can take to assist the cause of non-proliferation<br />
than by withholding the supply of uranium. Principally<br />
these go to the strengthening of the existing<br />
non-proliferation regimne; proposals made by the Report in<br />
this regard will be addressed by the Government in the near<br />
future. The Report also thoroughly considers the issues involved in<br />
waste management and disposal.<br />
It judges it to be absolutely necessary for countries to<br />
adopt high standards and to ensure that the best practicable<br />
waste disposal technology is employed.<br />
The Report advocates an approach which involves containing<br />
and isolating the source of radioactivity as far as<br />
possible. </p>
<p>The most effective way to put such an approach into practice<br />
is seen to be the confinement of the radioactive wastes in a<br />
stable waste form, and to isolate the waste form from the<br />
environment by additional barriers.<br />
Proven methods are identified for handling waste with low<br />
and intermediate levels of radioactivity. The Report,<br />
however, expresses reservations about the dumping of<br />
radioactive waste in the oceans, noting that, while this may<br />
be a safe prodedure, much further work remains to be done<br />
before any final judgement can be made. In the meantime,<br />
the Report urges Australian support for a continuation of<br />
the present moratorium on ocean dumping.<br />
For high level waste, the Report notes that investigations<br />
in progress, the level of technical knowledge attained, and<br />
the progress of programs of site investigation provide<br />
confidence that safe disposal of high level waste can be<br />
undertaken. The results of theoretical assessments of geological<br />
repositories provide additional confidence that safe<br />
disposal of appropriately packaged waste is possible using<br />
existing technology, provided that the best practicable<br />
technology is used at each stage and that an optimum<br />
geological repository is used.<br />
Under these circumstances, the Report considers that any<br />
return of radioactivity to the biosphere can be held to safe<br />
and acceptable levelg over long periods ( up to one million<br />
years) so that maximum dQ'ses to the most exposed individuals;<br />
would be a small fractioh of natural background levels.<br />
It considers, moreover, that the technology required to<br />
achieve these objectives is available.<br />
The Report notes the contribution which Australia can make<br />
to research and development in the area of waste disposal<br />
and recommends continued involvement in this important work..<br />
Attention is drawn particularly to the potential<br />
significance of the Australian-developed waste form Synroc<br />
and it is recommended that work on Synroc be continued. If<br />
the promise which Synroc appears to hold is demonstrated by<br />
further research, the Report concludes that . its adoption by<br />
other countries should be pursued.<br />
At this stage I should like to thank Professor Slatyer, the<br />
members of the Inquiry and ASTEC staff for the production of<br />
a comprehensive, thoroughly professional Report. It should<br />
become the standard technical reference for those seeking an<br />
understanding of the issues involved in this complex and<br />
critically important subject, on which a range of views are<br />
held within the Australian community and indeed within the<br />
Labor Party. </p>
<p>8.<br />
my judgment and indeed my hope would be that it will further<br />
enhance the more rational and reasoned distussion of nuclear<br />
issues which has emerged in recent months.<br />
The Government will give careful consideration to the ASTEC<br />
Recommendations, and as decisions are made, Ministers will<br />
advise the Parliament.<br />
I commend the report to the House. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
