<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9119</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P J KEATING MP VISIT BY THE PRIME MINISTER OF SOLOMON ISLANDS</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/02/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009119.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
4,<br />
PRIME MINISTER19/ 94<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
VISIT BY THE PRIME MINISTER OF SOLOMON ISLANDS<br />
I am pleased to announce that the Prime Minister of Solomon Islands, the<br />
Hon Francis Hilly, will be visiting Australia from 11-18 March as a guest of the<br />
Australian government. He will visit Brisbane, the Gold Coast, Sydney and<br />
Cairns, as well as Canberra. Prime Minister Hilly will be accompanied by his<br />
wife, Mrs Fiona Hilly.<br />
Australia has a long-standing and warm relationship with Solomon Islands,<br />
one of our closest neighbours. Prime Minister Hilly's visit will provide an<br />
opportunity to discuss ways in which we can build on this solid foundation in<br />
the years ahead. Australia will provide $ 11 million in development assistance<br />
to the Solomon Islands in 1993/ 4. We also have an active bilateral defence<br />
co-operation program.<br />
Prime Minister Hilly will be keen to explore the scope for expanding Solomon<br />
Islands exports to Australia. To this end, he is accompanied on the visit by a<br />
delegation from the Solomon Islands business community. At present,<br />
bilateral trade is weighted heavily in Australia's favour.<br />
My discussions with Prime Minister Hilly will also focus on regional issues of<br />
mutual interest, particularly the 25th South Pacific Forum, which Australia will<br />
host in Brisbane in August.<br />
CANBERRA 11 FEBRUARY 1994 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
