<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4114</transcript-id>
    <title>GOVERNMENT TO ESTABLISH OMBUDSMAN</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/05/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004114.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 10 May 1976/<br />
GOVERNMENT TO ESTABLISH OMBUDSMAN<br />
The Government has decided to introduce legislation during<br />
the current session to establish a. Commonwealth Ombudsman.<br />
The Government is concerned that people should be able to<br />
seek appropriate redress from the ' administrative actions<br />
of Government Officials where there has been clear error,<br />
bias, neglect, inattention, delay, incompetence or<br />
arbitrariness. The Ombudsman will investigate complaints by citizens<br />
against administrative acts by Commonwealth Officials.<br />
The Ombudsman's jurisdiction will extend to administrative<br />
acts by officials in the Australian Capital Territory and<br />
the Northern Territory.<br />
The role of the Ombudsman will be complementary to that<br />
of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal and other Tribunals<br />
such as the Social Security Appeals Tribunal.<br />
The Ombudsman will investigate the merits of a decision if there<br />
are no other established procedures for an appeal from that<br />
decision to another Tribunal. Even in those cases, the<br />
Ombudsman will have power to investigate complaints about<br />
such matters as delays in reaching a decision.<br />
The-Ombudsman will have power to question officials and to<br />
inspect departmental files in investigating a complaint.<br />
If he thinks a complaint to be justified, and the department<br />
concerned does not recitfy the matter to his satisfaction,<br />
the Ombudsman can report to the Prime Minister and to the<br />
Parliament. The independent nature of the Ombudsman and the powers he will<br />
have will provide an assurance that all complaints will be<br />
fully investigated.<br />
The Administrative Appeals Tribunal Act will come into force<br />
on 1 July. The Government hopes to be able to announce an<br />
early date for the appointement of a President to the Tribunal.<br />
./ 2 -W<br />
F76/ 84 </p>
<p>L.<br />
The Tribunal and the proposed Ombudsman are part of the<br />
Government's overall concern with administrative review.<br />
The administrative review legislation arose from the<br />
finding of the Kerr Committee on administrative review.<br />
The present Government will be the first Commonwealth<br />
Government to implement legislation to provide for<br />
administrative review. 000oo00000 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
