<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7185</transcript-id>
    <title>HEALTH POLICY STATEMENT FRANKSTON - 18 JUNE 1987</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/06/1987</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007185.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
HEALTH POLICY STATEMENT<br />
FRANKSTON 18 JUNE 1987<br />
in February 1984, my Government restored-fairness and<br />
equality of access to the health insurance system with the<br />
introduction of Medicare.<br />
The system is built on our uncompromising commitment to<br />
three clear, fundamental principles: health insurance cover<br />
for all Australians; equality of access to health services'<br />
for all Australianis; and payment according to means for all<br />
Australians. The dramatic and incontrovertible achievement of Medicare is<br />
this: two million Australians who previously had no health<br />
insurance cover now have it.<br />
That's two million Australians who now have the security and<br />
confidenc3 of health insurance who had none before.<br />
After the chronic chaos of the Fraser years, Medicare<br />
restored sanity and predictability and reassurance to a<br />
vital arocz of family life and family budgeting.<br />
Australian families have not forgotten the uncertainty they<br />
were caused by the string of five different health insurance<br />
systems introduced over the seven Fraser/ Howard years.<br />
That is w~ hy Australian families will be rightly alarmed by<br />
the Liberals' promise, confirmed as recently as yesterday by<br />
their health spokesman, to resume their onslaught on<br />
med ica;: e.<br />
The purpose of today's press conference is not solely to<br />
highlight the flaws in the Liberal's health scheme.<br />
It is also to contrast it w'ith the range of policies which<br />
the Government has put in place to improve the delivery of<br />
health care services in Australia.<br />
I also want to release details of two new initiatives which<br />
the Government will implement to further improve the<br />
Australian health system. </p>
<p>2<br />
Before proceeding, I want to pay special tribute to Neal<br />
Blewett who has been an outstanding Health minister<br />
throughout the life of this government.<br />
one of the Government's new initiatives concerns Neal<br />
Blewett's portfolio; the other concerns Susan Ryan who has<br />
ably discharged her role as minister Assisting me on the<br />
Status of Women.'<br />
Yesterday the Liberals' health spokesman, Senator Baume,<br />
released a policy which confirms that his Party's commitment<br />
to helping the big private health funds, at the expense of<br />
the average Australian family, has not diminished.<br />
His proposal is unaffordable, unworkable and, most of all,<br />
unfair. It is proof that the Liberals want to dismantle one of the<br />
Government's greatest social reforms Medicare and negate<br />
its progressive contribution to redistribution and equity.<br />
The Liberal's health policy is clearly from the same stable<br />
as their tax policy.<br />
It is a redistributive policy which penalises the poor and<br />
the ill and helps the wealthy and healthy.<br />
The Liberals want to take the most valuable card in your<br />
wallet or purse your Medicare Card.<br />
in effect, they want to pick your pocket and they're<br />
asking your help to do it.<br />
Australians who get sick would be fleeced by the Liberals to<br />
the tune of $ 250 a year.<br />
And the Liberals insult the intelligence of the Australian<br />
community by saying this charge can be insured against.<br />
Over a year these weekly insurance costs would add up to<br />
virtually the same amount as the front end charge.<br />
The Liberals justified the new $ 250 charge on the grounds<br />
that it would act as a disincentive to unnecessary medical<br />
servicing. But that aim would be negated by the<br />
availability of insurance.<br />
The Liberals' so-called amnesty to dispose of hospital<br />
waiting queues must be seen as a wand-waving exercise<br />
It supposes people on public hospital waiting lists can<br />
afford top table insurance; and it would inevitably force<br />
private fund premiums through the roof.<br />
And the proposal to reintroduce ' gap' insurance would hit<br />
hardest the chronically ill including those least able to<br />
afford it. </p>
<p>Under the Lib-.--als' scheme those people unable or unwilling<br />
to take private medical insurance will nevertheless find<br />
themselves paying the levy plu the $ 250 charge or<br />
equivalent insu. Lance plus tlhega p between schedule fees and<br />
actual medical ', ills or the optional gap insurance.<br />
The flaws in t Nis proposal are not surprising: Senator<br />
Baume was only appointed as his Party's health spokesman a<br />
few weeks ago; in the Liberals, haste in putting together<br />
their hotch-potch of policies, simplicity and fairness has<br />
gone by the board.<br />
Their new policy has dribbled out in bits and pieces since<br />
the election began, which has only added to the confusion.<br />
Just as the Fraiser Government created five successive health<br />
systems in seven years Michael Baume has presided over<br />
five different health policies in the last seven daysi<br />
Let me now turn to the specific initiatives we are<br />
announcing today.<br />
The first concerns hospital waiting lists.<br />
Let me first e;:-plode the myth which the Liberals have been<br />
assiduously p-ishing that waiting lists are a function of<br />
Medicare.<br />
Whatever Senator Baume may claim, State Health Ministers<br />
agree Medicarc is not to blame.<br />
Hospital waiting lists are the regrettable result of a<br />
combination off factors such as shortages of nurses and<br />
medical specialiists, and the rapid advance of medical<br />
technology wlhich has helped to boost public expectations of<br />
treatment and demand for it.<br />
These issues are properly within the responsibilities of<br />
State governmrents.<br />
Some state governments, notably Victoria and NSW, have begun<br />
programs designed to address some of the bottlenecks.<br />
However, the Commonwealth does have a role to play in<br />
supporting su~ ch state initiativeo.<br />
Accordingly, my Government will provide funds to State<br />
governments so they can implement programs which will have a<br />
real impact on reducing waiting lists.<br />
States will, f , r example, be able to use the funds to<br />
increase the number of nurses, thereby increasing their<br />
hospitals' capacity to provide surgery.<br />
They will be able to increase the number and quality of<br />
their day-care surgeries, which are recognised as the most<br />
cost-effective way of treating patients. </p>
<p>or they wil 1he able to creat wards or theatres specially<br />
dedicated to certain kinds of treatment, which will allow<br />
hospitals t: o provide speedier treatment, and thus shorter<br />
waiting lists.<br />
In other words, these initiatives will provide faster<br />
treatment at lower cost to the system.<br />
Faster trea~ tment means reduced waiting lists: and reduced<br />
waiting lists means better health care for all Australians.<br />
In all, we expect $ 100 million over two years to be spent on<br />
this work.<br />
The third Hawke Government will make available $ 25 million a<br />
year over the two year life of this Hospital Waiting List<br />
Assistance 2rogram.<br />
This money will be provided to State governments on a dollar<br />
for dollar b3asis, bringing the total to $ 100 million.<br />
We are this addressing the real, as opposed to the illusory,<br />
causes of hospital waiting lists.<br />
The second :-nitiative I am announcing today continues the<br />
implementat~. on of the Government's desire to prevent<br />
il-el'tbefore it strikes, rather than to treat people<br />
it is also an initiative of special relevance to women.<br />
The most ccirrnon form of cancer killing women in Australia<br />
today is Lbr-ast cancer: over 5000 new cases are diagnosed<br />
each year; one woman in 15 develops breast cancer at some<br />
stage during her life.<br />
This rate iG far too high: especially when, according to<br />
the latest Luedical evidence, the chances of women over<br />
developing breast cancer can be significantly reduced if it<br />
is detected oarly by breast x-rays.<br />
The next Haw., te Government will, as a first step, help set up<br />
and evaluatc a nation-wide study into the effectiveness of<br />
breast cancer screening in mature women to assess the<br />
feasibilit~, of a national screening program.<br />
Similarly, there is evidence that screening programs for<br />
cervical cancer can also be effective in preventing it.<br />
M~ any women however particularly those in the older, higher<br />
risk groups and those in rural areas are reluctant to<br />
attend inale doctors for cervical cancer tests.<br />
My government therefore will share with the States the cost<br />
of establishing cervical cancer screening services provided<br />
by women medical teams especially in rural areas. </p>
<p>Both these preventive programs are inexpensive and, we<br />
weille hi$ Kl effective wys of stoppin significant th<br />
health problems before they start.<br />
million will be set aside for the cervical program in<br />
1989-90.<br />
The Governauent has not restricted its efforts in health<br />
F: policy to the introduction of universal and fair health<br />
insuranco system as important as that is to every<br />
Australian individual and family.<br />
We have also placed an upper limit on the amount that<br />
families or individuals have to pay for pharmaceuticals.<br />
It is a simiple and convenient safety net which protects the<br />
chronically ill and which of course allows pensioners to<br />
continue to receive listed pharmaceuticals for free.<br />
We have also led the world in the fight against AIDS.<br />
We becanre the first country to implement comprehensive blood<br />
screening tests.<br />
In no Australian case since May 1983 has the AIDS virus been<br />
transitted through blood or blood products.<br />
We have co-operated with the State Governmients in a $ 100<br />
million ccamipaign against drug abuse.<br />
We have also taken steps to develop a strategy aimed at the<br />
Prreventon of ill health and the encouragement of healthier<br />
lestylez in Australia.<br />
We are the first Government to set about this task in a<br />
coherent kashion.<br />
It is designed to yield not just improvements in the quality<br />
of Australian life but real reductions in the calls we make<br />
upon the health system.<br />
on this record, and this contrast with the Opposition, we<br />
are proud to ask the Australian people to judge us.<br />
Neal Blowett, Susan Ryan and I will be happy to answer your<br />
quest ions. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
