<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9299</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ KEATING MP SOUTH PACIFIC FORUM RETREAT, KOORALBYN, QLD, 1 AUGUST 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/08/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009299.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
P RIME-MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PIME MINISTR, THE HON P J KEATIG MP<br />
SOUTH PACIFI FORUM RETREAT, KOORALBYN QID.<br />
I AUIGUST 19U<br />
PM:. Let me jst ay a couple of words abot Alexanr Downer over the weekend<br />
and his remarks about Mabo. ttink the first thing it reveals is thW the<br />
Liberal Party, agaln, has deosrtdthat It Is a party that has run out of<br />
puff~ lts a party w* thou Ideas and, withou a philosophy. f t hopes to govern'<br />
Aushralia but it has no philosophy. It has no policy an AuWWslIdentity a* d<br />
what Wr Downer has * revealed over fte weekenid ti it 4oe 41 have any<br />
policy of sodea cohsin either. He said he wovuld dismantle te MIbo<br />
legisaif, aftr an efecfon vidory, stats promim reqired him to do so.<br />
For ast; Kt he is not hisownm person scodly,. Mbois an hstpie= eod<br />
legislation basd on an Important paec of Austrla law. That i, t<br />
dedion by the figh Court What does Mr Downer think hie Is going to do?<br />
Overturn fte High Court decision an Mabo? And, if not how wouid he give<br />
certainty to tWte and Vive Ws to Aboriginal people without It? it Is amazming<br />
that to Libeal Party, In this day wnd age. Is thnigof overturnin Mao at<br />
9 tVow when othw Ulbeal gvnmtsof cotxrse, have extended land rights.<br />
Andf4 ft W. s showa, I thnM9ta Ajmarier Downer is intent upon taldng<br />
Austaa back'to * the. Mois. Alexande Dowiw is an old fashioned 1950s<br />
LlJpolitican. The* problen for Rexder Downer is tatwe are ( n 1994<br />
and the world has moved om<br />
Could I say fiat not only that, but at this South Pwfic Forum a number of<br />
leaders have complemented-Austraft aon the. Mabo legislation, on the fad<br />
that we have mo* dour kndgens and , the essential quhmnent the<br />
havm to reehrbish thi eainhpwith the land and Ut tite to Bmei land<br />
and whee fthy wish, nrw atraditional riestyle. Anc, to make Maes<br />
061.0nt for simply, somea passing -applause at a Libera party torlre<br />
dispaying again, tht sort of esenial wiertyng bigotry abot giving<br />
AborighMa people WWn when the--Pedfic Waders we heas wig only, I thik<br />
souir thei view about whther Austal tie really s e light in comiing to<br />
terms wfth their itidgeres. At any rate, it prve WhD~ oow~ n~ e r is<br />
simpy about regressive policies, taking Astralia bc t fte IM. And.<br />
not only Vi4t saying, not that we'll wee their policies in toe election but If alte<br />
de eleotIon after he has supsdywon, then It comes up his bac to </p>
<p>d-wg WfCY-hell chanoo it than So, ft public don't evan krw goin<br />
moan eleon. wha? ti~ Policies rnlgt be.<br />
J: You've used the ptmue, % ndMlin bigecy. wre you saying thtW Down<br />
is bigtu?<br />
PK_ I tdnk whiat ru haough the Westem Ajna Liberal pety isW~ tk<br />
blgoy. Ane, to be puwKim ig 11c # W displays the worst kofincb lot me<br />
say tise, displays Vou Liberal Party at ft wt. And, Wt Dvu Is alWays<br />
toq i about NM1Wk FRau. luw ta Wksl up to. hhii walL rm qufb vm<br />
Mr Froser would not have a bar at due sot eWN<br />
J: Wbiud I be posibl to a. dzally claanl Op Mabo, egilan?<br />
PM Wai W possible. WhaI toe pauiamlerti Ga do ft perfi~ amr~ m undo. But<br />
by that stage, of moms, " wM-11 be dedtoars fe tuv~ w It. if. is toe<br />
whole cormpaet nawimot of Woisat tam from &amp; t An toe HOgt Cout<br />
dcision said w= s VWuIfum w= a uuative Wei In One Wfcfomm law. Rt dkhrt<br />
any whd t of Me5h. ow-at wotu be dispersed, howA mut d be heard how<br />
diakn viguid be agiated-. AM that wa done by the tegdbm and you've<br />
got ariumbr of Coa~ ftIn rmw s~~ ipoftU 1 NSW, Vkdiii arsd so whom,<br />
does it bay, I&amp; Downr? -It Mese him wdh go taistic oft Weft<br />
Ausballan Lbera paty.<br />
3: Prkvn Mkriser, can I jui ask you a. question on tou foniwn? How recephve<br />
taim yui found Wiand leadr to yor msage tait sueinabe<br />
PM: Witt I VMugt the opening sesion vrs very enwglng. We had sofme, I<br />
dikvery winUftted &amp; W d nkgiig apeeches tm vorlms teadere<br />
about MtMy and fisherles; mid hwun resoiau deekpnert utidi I an<br />
sue ft wimruust VM WC got mWy tM a flying Stt olid I tnrV., today, OWu<br />
WoftImhpMVe tUN1<br />
J: You I* uk tw1 co an board taigN with yaw view?<br />
PM: Well, 1 dortt partculaffly hove I, haven't got a pautcular se at pxoxps to<br />
put to m Ifs about, a view. And, wo re ady seeing. in a so m firm<br />
support fo tout view I hit nighs umprsabnru<br />
I And how imorlait Is fts reftat today. and wWi do you hope to addeve<br />
Pht Wak, I ft* Vtm r seE Is Iu1oort because It does give thm leaders a<br />
duarms to spook kIrniaiy abou ct alv MhIcet eir econouis ond<br />
' iafr smdile AnM, I tik bjildvn ft forum aound! a theme has been<br />
very helpfu In mwentreta g ton debuie </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
