<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10711</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                  THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                  TELEVISION INTERVIEW WITH KERRY O&amp;#146;BRIEN                7.30 REPORT, ABC TV</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/04/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...............................................</p>
<p>O'BRIEN:</p>
<p>I am joined now, from Parliament House, by the Prime Minister.</p>
<p>   John Howard, you have had a rough trot with aged care policy in</p>
<p>   recent months and on a day when you try to focus on some good news,</p>
<p>   the critics still keep coming out of the woodwork, even within your</p>
<p>   own Liberal ranks.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, Kerry, there are always critics. But it doesn't alter</p>
<p>   the fact that we've announced a package that has absolutely</p>
<p>   dramatic new measures to help people stay in their own homes and</p>
<p>   for the first time really gives proper recognition to some of the</p>
<p>   unsung heroes of a caring, compassionate society, and that is carers</p>
<p>   who look after relatives and friends, often many of them themselves</p>
<p>   quite elderly. And I'm very proud of that package. And I'm</p>
<p>   quite certain that the people who will benefit from it know how</p>
<p>   ground-breaking it is. </p>
<p>I mean, older people want to stay in their own homes. They don't</p>
<p>   want to go into institutional care. Sadly, some have to and if they</p>
<p>   do, they're entitled to decent accommodation and proper conditions.</p>
<p>   Overwhelmingly, older Australians want to stay in their own homes.</p>
<p>   And what we're doing is putting an unprecedented level of additional</p>
<p>   resources into helping people stay in their own homes. We're</p>
<p>   going to help people go into the homes of older people and look</p>
<p>   after them and, thereby, prolong the time that they can stay in</p>
<p>   their own homes. Now, that is compassionate, it's what people</p>
<p>   want and, in every sense of the word, it's very good policy.</p>
<p>   And I don't really mind what static is around on other issues.</p>
<p>   Nothing can disguise the fact that this is a cut-through, ground-breaking</p>
<p>   new approach, in terms of the volume of resources, to enabling people</p>
<p>   to stay in their own homes.</p>
<p>O'BRIEN:</p>
<p>But there are those who see this as you robbing Peter to pay Paul,</p>
<p>   that you've already made a number of cuts in areas of aged</p>
<p>   care and now you come up with this in an election year.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, we haven't robbed anybody. I mean, in the aged care</p>
<p>   area we have increased, by 14 per cent, over Labor's last year</p>
<p>   in office, the funds that we've provided. And this money that's</p>
<p>   going into these areas is - this is an area quite separate from</p>
<p>   nursing homes and, in any event, the claim that, in aggregate, we've</p>
<p>   cut funding to nursing homes is quite wrong.</p>
<p>O'BRIEN:</p>
<p>Well, the biggest private nursing home proprietor, Mark Moran,</p>
<p>   describes your package as, quote:- a desperate prank. He says, quote:-</p>
<p>   the Prime Minister is neglecting elderly Australians.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, Mr Moran is entitled to his own opinion. But you've</p>
<p>   got to understand that he is in the business of running nursing</p>
<p>   homes and obviously he would like more money given to the providers</p>
<p>   of nursing homes. I'm interested in the people who go into</p>
<p>   nursing homes and I'm also interested in people who want to</p>
<p>   stay in their own homes. And the priority of my Government will</p>
<p>   always be to give help to people who either want to stay in their</p>
<p>   homes or if they go into nursing homes, to guarantee that they get</p>
<p>   decent conditions.</p>
<p>Now, you've got to understand, Kerry, that, with the greatest</p>
<p>   respect to Mr Moran and others in his position, they have a vested</p>
<p>   business interest in trying to verbal the Government into giving</p>
<p>   them more money.</p>
<p>O'BRIEN:</p>
<p>Well, Francis Sullivan of the Catholic Health Care Association,</p>
<p>   isn't in it with a profit motive and he has welcomed the money</p>
<p>   for home carers. But he says you are still ignoring huge problems</p>
<p>   with capital funding for nursing homes.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, once again - I mean, he's putting a point of view on</p>
<p>   behalf of his sector and I'm not criticising that. But what</p>
<p>   I do point out is that the new accommodation charge system will</p>
<p>   result in hundreds of millions of dollars of additional capital</p>
<p>   going into the nursing home sector over the next few years. And</p>
<p>   I do note, as you did, that Mr Sullivan, who's been quite a</p>
<p>   critic of ours over time, welcomed very warmly, as did the Council</p>
<p>   on the Aging, as did a whole range of groups concerned with the</p>
<p>   disabled in our community and with carers in our community, they</p>
<p>   welcomed our package.</p>
<p>I mean, what they liked was the philosophy behind it and that is,</p>
<p>   we're helping people to stay at home and that's what older</p>
<p>   people want to do. They'd far rather be cared for in their</p>
<p>   own home environment. You grow more attached to your home the older</p>
<p>   you are.</p>
<p>O'BRIEN:</p>
<p>Well, let's look at one of the groups that you're helping.</p>
<p>   You've given $15 million over four years to 8,000 elderly people</p>
<p>   who are caring for adult children with profound disability. The</p>
<p>   Council for Intellectual Disability says this amounts to $9.00 per</p>
<p>   person, per week. What do you expect that to do?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, it is obviously a recognition and it will make a significant</p>
<p>   contribution. And, in addition, which is not mentioned in the question,</p>
<p>   we are providing some resources to help ease the greatest worry</p>
<p>   of many of those elderly carers. And that is what will happen to</p>
<p>   their children, often well into adulthood, when they, themselves,</p>
<p>   are no longer to care for them. We've found, in talking to</p>
<p>   these people, that the thing they worry about most, after having</p>
<p>   cared for a disabled child perhaps for 20, 30, 40 years, is what</p>
<p>   is going to happen to that child when they, themselves, are no longer</p>
<p>   around. And the resources we're going to put in in this area</p>
<p>   - and you can always put more, I mean...</p>
<p>O'BRIEN:</p>
<p>But the point is, the Council for Intellectual Disabilities says</p>
<p>   that there are currently 370,000 intellectually or physically disabled</p>
<p>   people over 45 years of age - that is people who are relying on</p>
<p>   older members of the family to look after them or whose older members</p>
<p>   have actually died - this number, they say, will increase by 100,000</p>
<p>   in the next five years, 25,000 will have severe intellectual disabilities.</p>
<p>   To put it brutally, the number of carers looking after them at home</p>
<p>   are simply dying, dying out through old age. The Council says, these</p>
<p>   people are often likely to end up sleeping in the street. That's</p>
<p>   after hearing about your package today.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well in addition to the 15 million, I should point out that we</p>
<p>   are going to increase, what's called the domiciliary nursing</p>
<p>   care benefit with effect from the 1st of July and we are also, the</p>
<p>   following year, going to significantly expand the eligibility criteria</p>
<p>   for that nursing home and that nursing care benefit and that will</p>
<p>   then include the carers of many profoundly intellectually impaired</p>
<p>   and disabled people. Now Kerry, if you are saying to me that Governments,</p>
<p>   there could always be more resources provided in the areas, of course</p>
<p>   that is true, and we are endeavouring, given our strength and budget</p>
<p>   position, we are endeavouring to provide targeted help to areas</p>
<p>   of very significant need in the community. Now I have never known</p>
<p>   a Government that is ever told by any interest group in the community</p>
<p>   that all of the resources they would want provided have been provided.</p>
<p>   But we have gone a very significant step forward in this package</p>
<p>   and we have put a far greater emphasis than any former Government</p>
<p>   on helping people to stay in their own homes and we have given,</p>
<p>   it is recognised by all of the groups today that I addressed, and</p>
<p>   there were 400 of them here, it was recognised that we have given</p>
<p>   a recognition to carers, particularly elderly carers of disabled</p>
<p>   and intellectually impaired adult children, a recognition and a</p>
<p>   level of assistance that no former Government has given. </p>
<p>O'BRIEN:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, can we please look at dental health, we have a small</p>
<p>   amount of time left.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I know, but you chose to put a proposition to me about the apparent</p>
<p>   insensitivity of a certain amount of money. Now I have pointed out</p>
<p>   to you that there are more changes that are going to benefit that</p>
<p>   sector and also that the magnitude and the shift of emphasis involved</p>
<p>   is quite significant.</p>
<p>O'BRIEN:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, if we can look with the remaining time left at dental</p>
<p>   care for the aged. You abolished the $400 million Commonwealth dental</p>
<p>   health scheme, waiting times for the poor and elderly needing urgent</p>
<p>   dental care have quadrupled. The horror stories are pouring in.</p>
<p>   Will you address that problem?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well Mr O'Brien, Kerry, the programme was introduced by the</p>
<p>   former Government with a time limit of four years and it ended only</p>
<p>   six months earlier than that four year period because the target</p>
<p>   group identified in the programme had been provided for. It has</p>
<p>   traditionally been...</p>
<p>O'BRIEN:</p>
<p>But it would appear very clearly that it hasn't been provided</p>
<p>   for.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well the number that have been identified by the former Government</p>
<p>   so I'm told was a waiting list of about 1.2 million people.</p>
<p>   Now this has traditionally been an area of State responsibility.</p>
<p>   It has never been until - at one programme that was introduced by</p>
<p>   the former Government as it has always been an area of State responsibility.</p>
<p>O'BRIEN:</p>
<p>But you've heard Joanna Gash's, your own Liberal backbencher,</p>
<p>   you've heard her own words on this that the people in her Electorate</p>
<p>   are outraged by your insensitivity. She says the public dental care</p>
<p>   is at crisis point, outrageous stories of suffering are emerging.</p>
<p>   One woman, all of her teeth in need of extraction, but she has to</p>
<p>   wait until each tooth is causing extreme pain before that individual</p>
<p>   tooth can be pulled. She is in no doubt, your own backbencher, is</p>
<p>   in no doubt in her mind about where that responsibility lies, with</p>
<p>   you.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well it's natural that a Federal Member of Parliament will</p>
<p>   approach the Federal Government but this has always been a State</p>
<p>   responsibility.</p>
<p>O'BRIEN:</p>
<p>But the Commonwealth did act to bring in money to try to alleviate</p>
<p>   the problem.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>And it was a specific programme that was there for a particular</p>
<p>   period of time and the decision that we took was taken on the basis</p>
<p>   that the group that was targeted for special additional assistance</p>
<p>   had in fact been effectively assisted.</p>
<p>O'BRIEN:</p>
<p>But isn't it clear that they haven't?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Over that shorter period, well, of course, the Federal Government</p>
<p>   is not the only Government in the field in these areas. We have</p>
<p>   responsibility but so do state governments and this proposition</p>
<p>   that every time there is a particular need in the community, it</p>
<p>   is just the Federal Government and the Federal Government has that</p>
<p>   responsibility.</p>
<p>O'BRIEN:</p>
<p>The Federal Government took $400 million out and Joanna Gash again...people</p>
<p>   needing tooth extractions being turned away each morning in agony</p>
<p>   because they can't get attention.</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>That particular programme had a time limit of four years. The target</p>
<p>   group was 1.2 million and those people had in fact been treated,</p>
<p>   according to the advice that we have received. Now I mean, you can</p>
<p>   put every difficult situation in the community before a Prime Minister</p>
<p>   or before a Federal Government and say: well it is your responsibility</p>
<p>   to fix that. State governments have responsibilities. State governments</p>
<p>   get significant funds from federal governments for health and all</p>
<p>   sorts of other things. They are getting, after all, significant</p>
<p>   increases from us over the next five years in the health area. They</p>
<p>   do get, they are getting a five per cent real increase in their</p>
<p>   general taxation funds out of the Federal Government over the coming</p>
<p>   year and this is in a climate of zero inflation and it is quite</p>
<p>   legitimate of me to say that this is as much, if not more, a state</p>
<p>   government responsibility as it is a federal one.</p>
<p> O'BRIEN:</p>
<p>John Howard, thanks very much for talking with us.</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It's a pleasure.</p>
<p>[Ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
