<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6973</transcript-id>
    <title>President Alfonsin of Argentina  to visit</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/07/1986</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006973.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p><strong>7 July 1986</strong></p>
<p>President Alfonsin of Argentina will make a working visit to Australia on 12-13 July. I will have talks with him in Canberra on 12 July.</p>
<p>It will be the first visit to Australia by a Latin American Head of State. The President will be accompanied by Foreign Minister Caputo and Economy Minister Sourrouille.</p>
<p>I am particularly looking forward to this opportunity to meet President Alfonsin. The President's efforts to consolidate democracy, to redress past human rights abuses and to overcome complex and deep-seated economic problems have earned him admiration and respect, both in Argentina and around the world. </p>
<p>Both Australia and Argentina have recently given increased attention to ieneed to liberalise international trade in agricultural products. We have a common interest in opposing subsidies and other measures which disrupt agricultural trade.<br />Australia and Argentina see this as a priority in the new round of multilateraZ trade negotiations which is likely to be launched at the MTN M.. nisterial Meeting in Uruguay in September. My discussions with President Alfonsin will enable our two countries to consider ways in which our approach to these important issues can be co-ordirzated more effectively.</p>
<p>Distance has in the past hindered the development of regular contacts between Australia and Argentina. The President's visit will provide an opportunity to develop the relationship. Argentina is gonerally regarded as a leader in the Non-Aligned Movement. Its views on Central America, Antarctica, South Africa, disarmament and other issues are of great interest to Australia.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
