<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4245</transcript-id>
    <title>QUEENSLAND ANNUAL LIBERAL CONVENTION</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/10/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004245.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
F76/ 208<br />
fT, 1 I i=<br />
FOR PP!. SS OCTOBER 3, 1976<br />
EMARGO: 2.00 p. m. QUEENSLAND ANNUAL LIBERAL CONVENTION<br />
I am always pleased to visit Queensland. The Government is<br />
ncver Uncertain about Queensland's views. I am referring,<br />
of course, to the very large number of members on the<br />
Government side that Queensland has in the Federal Parliament.<br />
And in the House of Representatives, with one exception, they<br />
are all sitting on the right side of the House. The Liberal<br />
members in Canberra are never backward in putting their views<br />
that is very welcome.<br />
Last year Queenslanders made their views very clear on the kind<br />
of Australia they wanted. The decision of the people last<br />
December was a turning point in Australian history. The<br />
Australian people recognised on 13 December that Australia<br />
needed a profound change of direction.<br />
That decision of the Australian people placed an enormous<br />
responsibLlity on the Liberal Party both Federal and State.<br />
Australia needed a Government which believed that people<br />
deserved incentives to achieve their best in all areas of life;<br />
which would encourage productive private enterprise to provide<br />
jobs; which would give genuine assistance to the disadvantaged;<br />
which would put an end to ever-rising taxes; which would<br />
protect individual rights.<br />
Australia needed a Government which would reverse the drift of<br />
power to Canberra, and which would strengthen State and local<br />
government. We undertook to provide that kind of Government.<br />
We undertook to give Australia a Government which respected<br />
the right of people to build their own lives, without being<br />
told what to do by a few people who claimed to know what was<br />
good for everyone.<br />
In November last year, to achieve this objective we placed before<br />
the Australian people one of the most far-reaching and<br />
detailed programmes ever proposed by a major party in Australia.<br />
It was a programme designed not only to revive the faith and<br />
confidence of people in Australia, but also to create the<br />
conditions in which Labor would not again be able to damage<br />
Australia as it had in the past. That programme is now </p>
<p>2.<br />
being implemented. Many specific measures, including<br />
a number of historic reforms, have already been introduced.<br />
One area where there has been an historic change of<br />
direction is the Federal system. The flow of power to<br />
Canberra has at last been reversed by our Federalism policy.<br />
The financial position of the States and local government will<br />
be immensely strengthened under these reforms. Financial<br />
capacity will be matched to responsibility. Participation by<br />
Australians in state and local government will be more effective.<br />
Effective decisions will be made closer to those affected by -them.<br />
There has been criticism of the strength of local government<br />
presentation on the Advisory Council for Inter-Government Relations.<br />
Local government will have six representatives on the Council.<br />
We have taken the view that this is essential for the effective<br />
presentation of local government.<br />
I want you to know that at a meeting of Federal Executive<br />
earlier this year I made a point of sounding out the views<br />
of the six state Liberal presidents and that they concurred<br />
with the expansion of the Council. A letter was sent to the<br />
Premiers at the end of August, informing the states of our view.<br />
There was ample time for comment. Our decision was not one taken<br />
hastily without proper consultation. The position of the states<br />
is fully protected by the arrangements.<br />
I hope we will not have a situation where a representative<br />
of local government is present from a state but where one or more<br />
state governments are unrepresented.<br />
The Advisory Council will operate under the control of the Premiers'<br />
Conference. Local government will raise matters for inquiry<br />
through the state Premier at the Premiers' Conference.<br />
The Advisory Council will be a valuable supplement to the<br />
rest of the Federalism reforms.<br />
In a well-functioning Federal system the states and local government<br />
must have the flexibility to set priorities to choose how<br />
best to meet needs in areas within their responsibility.<br />
Labor subjected the states and local communities to increasing<br />
dictation from Canberra in their spending. That has now been<br />
reversed. We are increasing the flexibility of the states and<br />
local government to meet the needs of their areas in the ways<br />
they think is best. In a democratic country, this is as it should be.<br />
This flexibility is particularly important at a time when there<br />
has to be restraint in Government spending. Such restraint<br />
is necessary to provide essential tax relief, and incentive<br />
to business to provide jobs.<br />
The uncontrolled growth of Government spending has been one of<br />
the major causes of inflation,, and unemployment.<br />
Inflation erodes confidence, slows business recovery. The f-ght<br />
against inflation cannot be separae rmtefgtaais<br />
unemployment. Unless inflation is brought under control there<br />
can be no soundly based expansion of job opportunities. .3 </p>
<p>The Budget was an essential p) art of our strategy to<br />
restore opportunity and oconoic growth in Australia.<br />
Sonic people have said that some reductions in Government<br />
spending have been too severe that the constraints<br />
on thle states have been too tight.<br />
Let's look at sonic facts. Total net payments to the states<br />
out of funds collected by the Commonwealth have gone<br />
Lip 15 percent -this year. General revenue payments to<br />
the states payments which give the states absolute<br />
discretion have gone up 20 percent.<br />
Both those figures are significantly greater than the increase<br />
. in Commonwealth Government spending. We have imposed<br />
much more stringent controls on ourselves than we have on the states.<br />
State Government spending in the recent budgets still rose<br />
substantially. Expenditure from the consolidated revenue fund<br />
by the Queensland Government rose 18.4 percent in this<br />
week's budget. Tasmanian Government spending was up 21.1 percent;<br />
Victorian Government spending was up 16.4 percent;<br />
New South Wales Government spending was up 14.5 percent;<br />
South Australian Government spending was up 13.2 percent.<br />
These figures still mean that state governments are contemplating<br />
real increases in expenditure and some of these increases are<br />
very Substantial.<br />
The Federalism proposals mean that without increasing taxes<br />
the states have been able to meet and more than meet<br />
their vital spending commitments.<br />
The Federalism proposals mean that the states have greater<br />
flexibility in, choosing their priorities.<br />
Queensland, for example, has chosen to forego $ 30 million in revenue<br />
by concession in the area of succession and gift duties;<br />
$ 12.5 million when concession on payroll tax are fully applied;<br />
and $ 2.1 million when reductions in road transport fees<br />
are fully applied. Queensland has chosen to spend an extra<br />
$, 67.6 million on education this year, and an extra<br />
$ 45.7 million on hospital operations and maintenance.<br />
These are Quieensland's priorities determined by the Queensland<br />
Government in the light of Queensland's needs.<br />
It is one of the advantages of our approach that thie states have<br />
greater control over the areas they will choose to fund.<br />
They have exercised this. Wle do not quarrel with it.<br />
But there is a corollary. They can not properly come to us<br />
and complain about lack of mioney for areas they have deliberately<br />
chosen not to fund. The states will have even greater flexibility<br />
when the Federalism policy is fully implemented. They will have<br />
even greater capacity to make their own decision, and greater<br />
responsibility. It is always possible to say and say correctly that more<br />
money is needed in particular areas. When we are twice as -rich<br />
a country as we are now, it will still be possible<br />
to say that more monecy needs to be spent by governments on certain<br />
worthwhile objectives. 4 </p>
<p>The trouble with these kinds of statements is that they avoid<br />
all the difficult issues. The unpleasant fact is ' that at<br />
any time choices have to be made. Perhaps the single most<br />
important reason for the economic crisis we are now facing is<br />
that the Labor government did not have the courage to make choices.<br />
It just went on spending and spending, pushing taxes higher<br />
and higher, increasing costs and prices and destroying Jobs.<br />
As Liberals we realise that it is not only Government spending<br />
that is important. We believe that people must retain sufficient<br />
of their own earnings to give them a real independence in<br />
meeting their needs according to their own values.<br />
We believe that businesses, large and small, must be allowed to retain<br />
sufficient of their earnings to build new plant and equipment<br />
expand production and create jobs. It is always easy<br />
to find worthwhile areas where governments can spend more.<br />
As Liberals we recognise that increases in government spending<br />
have to be balanced against the personal independence of<br />
Australians and against a profitable and efficient private sector.<br />
The Liberal Party rightly demands of politicians that they have<br />
the courage to make these choices.<br />
One of the most important measures made possible by rYestraint<br />
on government spending has been the introduction of full personal<br />
income tax indexation. Personal income tax indexation is<br />
not just another tax measure. It is a reform to our tax<br />
system of historic importance. It means broadly that if your<br />
income increases only enough to keep pace with inflation,<br />
your average tax rate will stay the same. If your income<br />
doesn't rise at all so-that with inflation you are actually<br />
falling behind your average tax rate will fall.<br />
Under conditions of inflation, our reform means that there will<br />
bin effect, automatic tax relief every year.<br />
This year, tax payers are receiving $ 1 billion in relief under<br />
the scheme. Next year the benefits of tax indexation will become<br />
obvious again on July 1 you will receive further automatic<br />
tax relief indexation is a reform with continuing impact<br />
each year while inflation lasts.<br />
This is not only an essential step in the fight against inflation.<br />
It is a truly Liberal reform which will have a permanent impact<br />
in protecting people's earnings. By this reform we are forcing<br />
Governments to be honest.. There will be no more unlegislated<br />
income tax increases. If governments want to increase taxes<br />
they will have to argue for it in future and pass legislation.<br />
In addition to this major reform, we will also be looking in the<br />
medium and longer term to lighten the burden of personal income<br />
taxation to increase the control people will have over their<br />
own earnings. We believe that people ought to have the maximum<br />
freedom to meet their own needs according to their own values,<br />
and not as a few people in Canberra decide. </p>
<p>We have been very concerned at the way Labor' s inFlation has<br />
hit the weaker scctions of the community those on low incomes.<br />
We committed ourselves to helping these people and we have<br />
done so. Our family allowance scheme, designed particularly<br />
to help low income familles has been recognised as one of the<br />
most important reforms to the Australian social welfare system<br />
since Federation. It ended a system which discriminated<br />
against the children of the poor.<br />
Over 300,000 families and 800,000 children who were debarred wholly<br />
or partly fromn benefiting from the rebate syste, are now being<br />
assisted by the-family allowance. It is of particular help to<br />
Aborigines. The family allowance scheme does not add to bureaucratic<br />
overheads, and it places money in the hands of people.<br />
It is a scheme which both assists the disadvantaged and increases<br />
their independence.<br />
Wle committed ourselves to further help in the housing area.<br />
Wle have acted by initiating a housing voucher allowance experiment.<br />
This experiment, if successful, will provide a new mechanism<br />
to make welfare housing sensitive to the needs of the users<br />
rather than those of the planners. It recognises the principle<br />
supported by the poverty inquiry that aitaC: eshudb<br />
lin'ked to the person, not the house.<br />
We committed ourselves to protect the real value of pensions.<br />
Wle are introducing legislation to protect pensions by adjusting<br />
then, automatically in accordance with the Consumer Price Index.<br />
Wle have also introduced a three year $ 225 million programme<br />
to provide homes for the aged.<br />
Beyond the welfare area, we said in the last election that home<br />
ownership should be a national objective, and we committed ourselves<br />
to introducing a new home savings grant scheme.<br />
Wle have introduced a home savings grant scheme with more generous<br />
provisions than the ones we foreshadowed in the election.<br />
We committed ourselves to retaining Medibank and making it<br />
more efficient. We have not only retained Medibank but extended<br />
its operation. There is an element of complexity in the scheme<br />
because this is the only way in which choice can be introduced<br />
into the scheme. But there is a perfectly simple way for<br />
families to cover themselves and get high quality health care<br />
this is by paying the levy which has a ceiling on it.<br />
Trhis requires no action.<br />
The Labor approach did not permit choice the Labor Party<br />
and the opponents of our Medibank reforms want to impose uniformity<br />
on the Australian people to eliminate choice and impose<br />
their views on the people of Australia.<br />
Another of the significant actions we have taken this year has been<br />
to cut back on the size of the Federal Public Service. Under<br />
guidelines now established the P'ublic Service by June next year will </p>
<p>be 26,000 less than the levels projected under the Labor<br />
guidelines for 1975-76.<br />
We aye also introducing a number of measures to protect<br />
individual rights against the bureaucracy. These include<br />
a federal ombudsman and an Administrative Appeals Tribunal.<br />
The L. aw Reform Commission has been asked to examine and report<br />
on unwarranted invasions of privacy in matters under the control<br />
of the Commonwealth Parliament.<br />
As a Liberal Party, respect for the rights of people to live<br />
t'heir lives within the law according to their own values is<br />
fundamental to our approach. As a Federal Government we will<br />
consistently act to support the rights and freedoms of all<br />
Australians, whoever they may be.<br />
This apnlies without qualification to the Torres Strait Islanders.<br />
We share with the Queensland Government a strong commitment<br />
to supporting the concern of the Islanders that they should<br />
be able to continue their way of life with an assurance of<br />
maximum stability for the future. Agreed principles<br />
in the negotiations with Papua New Guinea are that<br />
there will be no transfer of sovereignty over any inhabited<br />
islands and that all citizens will remain Australians.<br />
The way of life of the Torres Strait Islanders and their<br />
traditional patterns of life and activity will be protected.<br />
When the Prime Minister of Papua New Guinea, Mr Somare, was in<br />
Australia in April, we agreed that an equitable and permanent<br />
settlement of alloutstanding issues relating to Torres Strait<br />
should be achieved as soon as possible.<br />
One mat-ter that clearly had to be settled was the matter of<br />
maritime * boundaries. Every independent country has to<br />
know ti'e limits of its maritime jurisdiction, just as much as<br />
ift needs to know the limits of its land jurisdiction.<br />
So Papua New Guinea and Australia agreed that one objective<br />
was to draw between Australia and Papua New Guinea whatever<br />
maritime boundaries were necessary. We agreed that it was necessary<br />
to draw a line determining the seabed ( the Continental Shelf)<br />
between the two countries.<br />
We also agreed that settlement should include the establishment<br />
in the Torres Strait of a zone designed to protect the environment'<br />
and to preserve the traditional way of life and livelihood of local<br />
iiha! bitants that is the Australian Torres Strait Islanders.<br />
The protective zone is a fundamental requirement. My Government<br />
believes that the first priority of all is to ensure that the<br />
Australian Islanders of the Torres Strait shall be able to live<br />
and sustain themselves in the Torres Strait as they have always done.<br />
This is an absolute requirement. / 7 </p>
<p>I believe Papua New Guinea is willing to agree to a just<br />
and reasonable settlement which will not only meet their own<br />
requirements as an independent country, but also our<br />
Australian interests.<br />
Negotiations have been proceeding since May and I am<br />
encouraged by the degree of progress mnade.<br />
There is no reasonable alternative to negotiation. It is much<br />
better to negotiate an agreement with a friendly country than<br />
to act in a high-handed way or to argue out differences<br />
in the International Court of Just~ ice.<br />
If Australia and Papua New Guinea left it to the International<br />
Court of Justice to settle the affairs of the Torres Strait<br />
the atmosphere would be very different.<br />
It would be an atmospher of confrontation. The result would<br />
be quite unpredictable and the chances of getting a<br />
protected zone to take care of the traditional way of life and<br />
livelihood of the Islanders would be quite small.<br />
What the Australian Islanders need most is a firm and stable<br />
agreement which they can rely on and which is just and equitable<br />
to both sides. And thi~ s is what the Australian Government, and<br />
I believe, the Papua New Guinea Government also wants.<br />
This is what we are working for, and this is, I believe,<br />
what we have a good prospect of attaining within the next few months.<br />
Our concern in this matter, as in others, is that the rights<br />
of all Australians should be protected.<br />
As a Liberal Government we see it as a basic obligation to help<br />
establish conditions of life in which all Australians can<br />
pursue their objectives in life in conditions of maximum<br />
freedom and with self-respect.<br />
The recovery of the economy is vital to this,-and recovery is now<br />
under . way. One of the important factors in strengthening the recovery<br />
will be the revival of the mining industry. Under the Labor<br />
Party's authoritarian Minister f or Minerals and Energy billions<br />
of dollars of investment were deferred or permanently lost.<br />
Since the electi-on last Decemaber under the new foreign<br />
investment guidelines there has been a dramatic change.<br />
The renewed i. nierest ini the development of our natural resources<br />
has brought massive new investment developments onto the drawing<br />
boards. These will involve substantial amounts of overseas capital<br />
under the new foreign investment guidelines.<br />
Projects being planned include development of the North West<br />
Shelf costing over $ 2,000 million and coal projects in<br />
Queensland amounting to about $ 1.5 billion stimulated by the<br />
Government's decision to reduce the coal levy.<br />
Projects such as these should play a large role in getting the<br />
economy moving forward and reducing unemployment. ./ 8 </p>
<p>To ease the problem of unemployment in the short term we<br />
ha; e iL-. roduced a number of measures. Of last year's<br />
230,01.:") school leavers, by the end of August 12,700 had not<br />
found jobs. To help these young people we have introduced<br />
a scheme to subsidise employers provide work and training.<br />
We have also announced changes to the National Employment<br />
and Training Scheme Scheme increasing certain<br />
allowances. To assist people who cannot find suitable work where<br />
they live, and wish to move to where work is av: ailable, we h; ave<br />
announced a major scheme of relocation assistan: e.<br />
We are also looking at terms of reference for a far reaching<br />
inquiry into the Commonwealth Employment Service.<br />
There is one way in which everyone can help to get unemployment<br />
down by restraint in wage and salary demands. Australians<br />
want to work together to get Australia moving.<br />
Trade union members, and the many responsible trade union leaders,<br />
are fed up with political and unnecessary strikes strikes<br />
called by men who don't care about the damage they are doing<br />
to other Australians; who don't care about the jobs they are<br />
destroying and the unemployment they are causing.<br />
I do not believe that responsible trade unionists are going<br />
to allow these men to wreck recovery. We promised to give<br />
members control over their unions. That is why we have<br />
legislated to require secret postal ballots in union elections.<br />
Secret postal ballots are now law. They can be a powerful<br />
weapon in the hands of union members a powerful protection<br />
from undue pressure by a few extremists.<br />
In our term of office, we have undertaken an active programme<br />
to expand opportunities and protect the disadvantaged.<br />
Our Government is a government of social reform. We are<br />
increasing funds for education, we have restored<br />
triennial planning. We are reforming the federal system and<br />
giving the states greater financial independence. We are<br />
strengthening the capacities of local councils. We are<br />
retaining and improving Medibank. We are securing homes for the<br />
aged. We will be protecting the real value of pensions by<br />
automatic adjustments. We have argued in the Arbitration Commission<br />
to protect those on lowest incomes. We have greatly increased<br />
assistance to handicapped persons. We have introduced the historic<br />
family allowance scheme. We are exploring a housing voucher allowance<br />
scheme. We have established a major new home savings grant scheme.<br />
We are setting a new course for Australia. We recog: nise that<br />
needed reforms do not have to mean massive new programmes of<br />
government spending we believe they should be reforms which<br />
protect and expand people's capacity to control their own lives<br />
without domination by others. We believe our philosophy of freedom<br />
and concern is in harmony with the real needs of Australia and will<br />
produce a better life for all Australians. We believe the vast<br />
majority of people want to w ork together to make Australi, a the great<br />
country it be. What we have done so far is a beginning.<br />
Every effort i.: eds to be made to get a broad public appteciation of<br />
the Government's policies. Now it is up to the Liberal Party and to<br />
every branch and e: very ,:. cmber of the Party everywhere in Australia<br />
to show the vitality of Australian democracy and make Australia<br />
an example to the world. 000oo00000 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
