<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8677</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER TH HON P J KEATING MP, THE AUSTRALIA SINGAPORE BUSINESS SEMINAR</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/09/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008677.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL: 25. Sep. 92 12: 53 No. 007 P. 01/ 08<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
THE AUSTRALIA SINCAPORE BUSINESS SEMINAR<br />
Let me begin at a point, say twenty five ycars ago, and<br />
at one divorced from the world of busines; and the<br />
economy. Twenty five year&amp; 8ajo Australia was not known in the<br />
world for its openness. In fact, two thirds of the way<br />
into the twentieth century, for all our considerable<br />
achievementt, Australia remained insular, inward-looking,<br />
not a little xenophobic.<br />
In so far as we looked out at all, we looked past Asia.<br />
As your Prime Minister said last night, we " leap-frogged<br />
over Asia" to keep the ties almost exclusively with<br />
Britain, Europe and America.<br />
It was a symptom of our lack of cultural developmcnt, our<br />
unworldliness, It is a measure of Australians' capacity tor change that<br />
the barriers are now down, and that Australia it a<br />
complex, spirited, immensely varied multicultural<br />
society. And it is a measure of how differently we see ourselves<br />
that we now actively pursue our future in Asia and the<br />
Pacific. Those who doubt that we can change should consider how<br />
aiuQh wo Diay changed.<br />
In a sense these two great changes we are undergoing are<br />
one and the same.<br />
As a nation we have opened up culturally and<br />
economically. Economically speaking, we realisea a littLle less than a<br />
decade ago, that our future way of life depended on<br />
making ourselves relevant to the rest of the world and<br />
especially relevant to the most dynamic region in the<br />
world which lay at our œ ront door. </p>
<p>TEL: 25Sp. 12: 53 No. 00? P. 02/ OE<br />
Xn the past few years we have confronted this reality.<br />
We have become, as a conseqluence, -more independent.<br />
When I use the word " independent", I mean a sense of<br />
responsibility as much as a sense of pride.<br />
I nean taking responsibility for our own destiny; having<br />
the will and the imagination, as Singapore had them, to<br />
make the leap into the world of the future.<br />
W~ ide in what we have done, in fact, is following only<br />
slowly. In any event, there is a long way to go.<br />
Yet the effect of realising that we are on our own, and<br />
that to deny necessity would be an act of national selfdestruction,<br />
has been remnorX-able.<br />
More remarkablo, I suspect, than even most Australian&amp;<br />
appreciate. M~ ore remarkable, I'm sue than many people in Asia<br />
Uppreviate. That Is one part of my purpose today to explain to you<br />
the changes.<br />
The other is to convey the message that we are very much<br />
open for business.<br />
We believe Australia and Asia have much to gain from<br />
thinking in terms of strategic alliances; that, once we<br />
learn to enjoy commercial success together, the bonds<br />
between us will reach a new level of mutual awareness and<br />
respect# Now, I think it is a reasonable suppotition that most of<br />
you are still inclined to think of Australia in terms of<br />
empty space randomly populated with sheep. And cattle.<br />
And mines.<br />
I think it is reasonable to suppose that you nay still<br />
think Of Australians as living on the cheap; riding on<br />
the back of the country's natural wealth. And riding for<br />
a fall.<br />
You maight. also be continuing to think of us as a country<br />
with heavily protected manufacturing industries, an<br />
industrial relations culture of conflict and<br />
inefficiency, inefficient management, inefficient<br />
wharves, an inefficient transport and communications<br />
system, high taxes and high inflation.<br />
The truth about all these things is quite different. </p>
<p>TEL: 25. Sep. 92 12: 53 NO. 007 P. 03/ 00<br />
J<br />
Our inflation rate is the second lowest in the OECD.<br />
Our proportion of tax to GDP is virtually the same as<br />
Japan's the lowest in the OECD.<br />
Our transport system is undergoing a radical overhaul.<br />
We have deregulated aviation, bringing substantial<br />
reductions in fares for both freight and passengers<br />
We have invesLed heavily in a new National Rail<br />
Highway and major road developments<br />
We have brought competition to our<br />
te] ecommunicationa,<br />
And we've doubled productivity on our wharves<br />
We are introducing competition into previously controlled<br />
industries, selling off government businesses, and, of<br />
course, we have deregulated banking and foreign<br />
investmcnt.<br />
Last year, in a continuation of a dramatic trend,<br />
Australia experienced the lowest number of strikes in<br />
thirty years.<br />
We have cut tariffs.<br />
but nothing has been so crucial in our quest for<br />
competitiveness as our reforms to industrial relations.<br />
In the 1990s, Australians discovered that conflict was<br />
not a creative condition.<br />
In a radical break with what had become a chronic<br />
national disease, the Government reached an Accord with<br />
_ Jheunions which not only dramatically lowered the level<br />
of industrial disputes, but restrained the growth of<br />
wages so effectively that our competitiveness improved<br />
per cent over the decade.<br />
More recently, we have begun another radical reform. we<br />
are moving away from centralised wage fixing and we are<br />
moving at an extremely rapid rate.<br />
By the middle of next year we expect more than half the<br />
Australian wor) force will be covered by enterprise<br />
bargains. At the same time, there has been very considerable<br />
improvement in workplace and management practices,<br />
including a very successful " world best practices"<br />
program international bencbmarking.<br />
The concrete manifestation of these developments is to be<br />
seen in, for example: </p>
<p>TEL: 25. Sep. 92 12: 53 No. 007 P .04/ OE<br />
4<br />
Du Pont's decision to re-locate production<br />
-facilities to Australia to supply East Asia;<br />
or ToyOta Australia winning export contracts<br />
throughout South-Eaat Asia. Already Australia<br />
exports more than $ 1 billion a year in cars and auto<br />
parts; or Bremar-Woll-ammerei investing in a wool<br />
processing p a'n-i eelong, Victoria under a single<br />
union coverage and enterprise agreement.<br />
We are also aware that successful competition in the<br />
international marketplace ultimately requ-i-res a highly<br />
skilled and flexible labour force, and for this reason we<br />
have created the equivalent of twelve universities in six<br />
years, doubled our vocational education and training<br />
budget, and established a National Training Authority to<br />
give Australia a system of high quality, high status<br />
polytechnics. I could detail any number of other reforms we have made<br />
in recent times.<br />
Yet it is perhaps more important to make the point that<br />
it is open cometition which is driving the essential<br />
changes. In recent years we have learned that change breeds<br />
change.<br />
Recognition of what has to be done has changed our<br />
perception of what an be done.<br />
We do not believe for a moment that the process of<br />
labour-management reform io complete.<br />
plainly, we are not yet totally competitive.<br />
But we are moving at a considerable rate.<br />
We continue to produce and sell commodities in fact<br />
more than ever before.<br />
As a nation we now export more than twice as much product<br />
as we did a decade ago and today our exports account for<br />
over 23 per cent of total output.<br />
That is gratifying enough.<br />
But the really big change is this we now sell more<br />
jg nufaqurj products overseas than metal oren and<br />
minerals. In fact, Australian manufactured exports showed the<br />
fastest growth in the OECD in 1990 and 1991. </p>
<p>TEL: 25. Sep. 92 12: 53 No. 007 P. 05/ 0<br />
Our exports of manufactured products are as great as the<br />
value of our exports of rural products.<br />
The fastest growing export category is Elaborately<br />
Transformed Manufactures ( ETMs); in recent years we have<br />
had Chni9i Wif of ovei 50 pe cent.<br />
In this same last decadt, Australia has also tripled<br />
services exports.<br />
My point is simple enough: there has been an economic<br />
sea-change in Australia.<br />
We still sell the minerals, the beef and tho wool, and<br />
the liquefied natural gas and the coal.<br />
But we arp also selling processed foods, motor vehicles,<br />
computer software, ocean-going ferries, bionic ears and<br />
education. And, what ig more, we increasingly sell them in Asia and<br />
the Pacific.<br />
The APEC region is the destination for almost 75 per cent<br />
of Australian exports.<br />
East Asia tokes almost 60 per cent.<br />
Exports of ETMs to North-East Asia increased eight-fold<br />
between 1981 and 1991.<br />
Last year we sold more ETMs in North-East Asio than wool.<br />
Seven out of the top ten Australian manufacturing markets<br />
are in East Asia.<br />
I trust you see what I mean by a sea-change.<br />
To give you another example last year our oervice<br />
exports to Japan alone were worth as much as our total<br />
wool and iron ore exports.<br />
Ten years ago we scarcely had a tourist industry worth<br />
the name. in the eighties it was our fastest growing<br />
industry, and the majority of tourists came from Asia.<br />
This year, over 600,000 Japanese tourists will visit<br />
Australia. More than I million are expected to arrive in<br />
the year 2000.<br />
There is no more striking example of Australia's new<br />
economy and its new relationchip to Asia than in its<br />
emerging trade relationship with ASEAN.<br />
For the last five years, our exports to ASEAN have been<br />
growing at an annual average of 30 per cent, to well over<br />
$ 6 billion. </p>
<p>TEL: 2 6 . e p .2 11 : 3: N3. N0 -0 .60<br />
Last year ASEAN became our second largest regional<br />
market, ahead of both the EC and N~ orth " 2~ erica: and<br />
Australian exports to Singapore have grown by an average<br />
of 31 per cent per annum over recent yars.<br />
And while we continue to export food and minerals, 23 per<br />
cent of our exports to Singapore are now -matnufactures.<br />
Just as Singapore has trAnsformed itself, so is Australia<br />
b~ eing transformed.<br />
And our changing relationship with Singapore reflects the<br />
speed of change and the kind of change which Australians<br />
now agree is both necessary and right.<br />
We have had similar objectives and we have changed in<br />
similar whys.<br />
And today this seminar of distinguished Australian and<br />
Singaporean busineas people will be talking about the<br />
opportunitie* for businesses in both countries to join<br />
forces in roaching into the growing markets of Asia.<br />
For oUr part, we have raw material resources, a depth and<br />
variety of wor~ corce skills, a large base of<br />
sophisticated services, o broad and well-developed<br />
research industry, and a relatively affluent population<br />
supporting a sophisticated construction, servicees and<br />
distribution sector.<br />
Singapore has a well-educated and flexible workforce, a<br />
high savings rate and a current account surplus, a strong<br />
outward orientation, and a geographical and political<br />
positioh at the centre of one of the world't fast growing<br />
regional suraomies.<br />
Already we have the eXamele of the strategic alliance<br />
between Australian and Singaporean buainess in Unilac, a<br />
joint venture which processes Australian dairy products<br />
for export through the rogion.<br />
We have another example in Kinhill Tan, which undertaken<br />
engineering projects in Singapore, M~ alaysia, Indonesia<br />
and Thailand.<br />
Other alliances are exploring projects for third country<br />
market ventures in construction, engineering, energy,<br />
teleom~ zmunications, refining, entertainment, and food<br />
processing. in the future we may well find profitable cooperation in<br />
areas in which AuStralla bas developed considerable<br />
technioal expertise including infroetructure<br />
development, environhment anid waste management<br />
technologies, biotechnology, aerospace industries,<br />
pharmaceuticals and various consulting services. </p>
<p>TEL: 25. Sep. 92 12: 53 No. 007 P. 07/ 0<br />
So there are plenty of opportunities there for joint<br />
ventures, and lots of things are happening.<br />
but while joint ventures are fino, let me be quite clear<br />
that we would not in any way wish to restrict our<br />
partnership to joint ventures.<br />
Singaporean businesses acting independently are welcome<br />
in Australia, as I know Australian businessge acting<br />
alone are welcome here.<br />
Partnership can take many forms, and the Australian<br />
Government's commitment is to the result, not the form.<br />
It is not just Australian and Singaporean businesses<br />
forming partnerships; in a sense, it is Australia and<br />
Sihgapore which increasingly are partners.<br />
Singapore will now be home to the first cuncrete<br />
embodiment of the APEC process, which our two governments<br />
contributed to oreating only a few years ago.<br />
The Singapore location for the secretariat of APEC<br />
modest though it is intended to be will put this<br />
country at the very centre of what I believe will be<br />
important trade policy choices in the years ahead.<br />
we share with Singapore a commitment to the APEC process,<br />
and to the overriding importance of securing a successful<br />
outcome to the Uruguay Round of the GATT. We know that<br />
the interests of open trading economies like ours are<br />
best served by a strong and widely observed set of<br />
International trading rules.<br />
But With Singapore, we also recognise that there iv much<br />
to be done on a regional basis which can build on the<br />
benchmarks or GATT.<br />
There is AFTA, which we believe can work to markedly<br />
enhance trade between ASEAN countries; and, by increasing<br />
their prosperity, increase their trade with non-ASEAN<br />
countries.<br />
And there is APEC, which has the potential to develop<br />
into an open regional arrangement which enhances trade<br />
between members without hindering trade with other<br />
regions. Like Australia, Singapore shares a deep interest in the<br />
continued involvement of the United States in the region,<br />
both as the world's largest economy, and as its only<br />
superpower. </p>
<p>TEL: 25. Sep. 92 12: 53 No. 007 P. 08/ 08<br />
There is no nod for Australia, which shares a long<br />
standing security treaty with the United states, to<br />
re-emphasise its belief that the continued involvement of<br />
US forces in the Pacifio region is a powerful stabilising<br />
influence and a significant contribution to the<br />
remarkable stability and growth we have witnessed in<br />
recent decades.<br />
But I do want to reassert Australia's belief that US<br />
ecg-n imc Anvolvement in the region is also vital -both<br />
for our prospeity; and for its own.<br />
For this reason we supported the APEC concept which<br />
includes both the western Pacific and the United States,<br />
and have queried other regional concepts which omit the<br />
US. And of course it is for this very reason to secure<br />
American economic involvement with Asia that we have<br />
expressed reservations: DoWh about the extension of<br />
NAFTA to Central and South America, and the recent<br />
proposal for the Us to create a set of bilateral trade<br />
agreements in the region on the hub-and-spokes model of<br />
its security relationships.<br />
The extension of NAFTA might well lead the US into<br />
thinking it could sustain its economic weight merely<br />
through involvement in its own hemisphere to the negloct<br />
of this region a notion which would I think be a grave<br />
error. And the hub-and-spokes model in trade maximises some<br />
bilateral advantages for the Us, but minimises the<br />
multilateral advantages for its partners in the region.<br />
On the face of things, our countries could not be more<br />
different I need not go into the obvious<br />
dissimilarities between an island continent and an island<br />
city state.<br />
But In 1992, I believe it is the commonalities which are<br />
more striking. The complementarities. The potential for<br />
cooperation for mutual advantage.<br />
All this is only becoming apparent now, as Australia<br />
makes the leap for change.<br />
The potential can only grow.<br />
Your deliberations today are both a manifestation of this<br />
faCt, and an agent of the process.<br />
Thank you all very much for your commitment to the cause<br />
of our two countries. Thank you for coming.<br />
SINGAPORE September 1992 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
