<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9</transcript-id>
    <title>DIFEST OF DECISION AND ANNOUNCEMENTS AND IMPORTANT SPEECHES BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE RIGHT HON. J. B. CHIFLEY - NO. 129</title>
    <prime-minister>Chifley, Ben</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19450713 - 19491219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/08/1947</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000009_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
( ZlC1Vc<br />
COMMONWEALTHGOVERNMENT. 66$-J U L 196<br />
CA 3 . i<br />
DIGEST OF DECISIONS<br />
AND ANNOUNCEMENTS AMD<br />
IMPORTANT SPEECHES<br />
BY<br />
THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
( THE RIGHT HON. J. B. CHIFLEY).<br />
No. 129.<br />
PERIOD-lsTr AUGUST, 1947, TO 6TIr SEPTEMBER, 1047.<br />
By Authorthr:<br />
L F Jourim. N. Commonwealth Government Printe. Canberg<br />
( Prnted in Australia.)<br />
5691. </p>
<p>INDUSTRIAL.<br />
INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS-CONFERENCE, DECISIONS.<br />
On 3rd August, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
While I survey with satisfaction the great increase in the industrial<br />
capacity of Australia, the existence of full employment in the community,<br />
the progress made in providing a degree of economic security<br />
for our people, I am gravely concerned with the shortages of houses<br />
and of goods needed by the people and the delays in carrying out works<br />
vital to the maintenance and development of this country.<br />
Manpower shortages will not permit the accumulated needs of the<br />
war years to be overtaken and current requirements to be met at once<br />
or in the immediate future. I am convinced, however, that Australians<br />
united in effort-as they were in war-can attack and overcome more<br />
speedily a situation that is detrimental to the economy of the nation<br />
and the best interests of its people.<br />
To-day, Australia has the greatest opportunity in its history.<br />
There is a world shortage of basic commodities which Australia excels<br />
in producing. High prices are obtainable for our exports. New<br />
markets are opening for both our primary and secondary products.<br />
Internally, industry has vast plans for expansion, and there is opportunity<br />
for intense activity in the building of houses, hospitals, schools,<br />
factories and development of roads, airports, railways, water conservation<br />
and electrical schemes. If we do not take full advantage of this<br />
opportunity it will be mainly because individual Australians have<br />
failed-failed to realize that Australia's good is their good and that<br />
of their children.<br />
" I appeal then to every individual Australian to give of his best<br />
in whatever occupation he may follow. To do less is a denial of the<br />
needs of his fellow Australians. Let each Australian then develop a<br />
new spirit-a new vision of the personal importance of his efforts to<br />
this country and his fellows. I appeal to the leaders of the trades union<br />
movement to exercise firm discipline over the units they lead, to prevent<br />
unauthorized strikes, to eliminate inter-union disputes, to avoid disputes<br />
over small matters, and to concentrate their efforts and thoughts on<br />
the production this country so sorely needs. I call on each unionist to<br />
give unswerving loyalty to such leaders. I call on the employers of<br />
this country for more production, for the utmost efficiency in their<br />
methods, for a greater personal interest in the industrial problems of<br />
the human beings who are their employees, for the provision of better<br />
working conditions for those employees, for a broad tolerance towards<br />
workers suffering from the strain of war and experiencing a natural<br />
reaction to war-time conditions. Above all, I ask them to be ready<br />
and generous in sharing with their employees the benefits of the<br />
increased production that I feel confident will take place.<br />
" I ask that all parties in industry will avoid those things that<br />
have been sapping the industrial strength of this country and preventing<br />
the achievement of higher living standards for our people. I invite </p>
<p>willing acceptance of the principle of conciliation and arbitration and<br />
trust that all. will co-operate in giving a fair trial to the new scheme<br />
of arbitration and conciliation which will soon be in operation.<br />
This country cannot but be affected by the economic changes<br />
taking place beyond its -boundaries. It is vital that our own econom3<br />
be stabilized to meet possible repercussions from abroad. Steady work<br />
by each and every Australian will be the most powerful factor in<br />
aIchieving this. Given this, we protect ourselves, we give the best aid<br />
to Britain in its sore plight, we make a contribution to the solidity and<br />
welfare of the British Commonwealth of Nations, and we do something<br />
for the stricken people of countries devastated by war-peoples afflicted<br />
with a spiritual and physical misery never known in this country and<br />
the depths of which are so abysmal as to be almost beyond<br />
. omprehension. " I am pleased with the results of the conference over which I<br />
presided in Canberra, and I feel that the people of Australia have much<br />
to hope for from the operation of the machinery for closer consultation<br />
between employers. employee, and the Government that has been<br />
established." On 3rd August, 1947. Mr. Chifley, the PresideL-r of th:.<br />
Australasian Council of Trades Unions ( Mr. P. J. Clarey, M. L. C.)<br />
and the President of the A\ ssociated Chambers of Manufactures. ( Mr.<br />
Robinson) said-<br />
" The three constituent bodies associated witlh industry, the Government,<br />
the Associated Chambers of Manufactures of Australia and the<br />
A\ ustralasian Council of Trade Unions having met in conference have<br />
reached the following conclusions:-<br />
1. Increased production is essential for the continuance of satisfactory<br />
Australian living standards; their improvement; the meeting<br />
of many shortages in both capital and consumable goods, and for the<br />
relieving of the inconveniences and hardships at present being<br />
experienced by Australian citizens. These shortages relate to the things<br />
which intimately concern the life of Australian men and women, such<br />
as housing, clothing and many other commodities. The parties, therefore,<br />
agree that every effort should be made to stimulate and promote.<br />
production to the highest possible point, consistent with existing manpower<br />
and productive resources. This is a matter in which all must<br />
co-operate. It is the function of not one section of society, but of all.<br />
The parties believe there are ways in which this increased production<br />
can be achieved, notwithstanding the belief that all sections of" the<br />
community are now honourably playing their part. It is suggested that<br />
the three constituent parties endeavour to stimulate production by<br />
means of more efficient management, where possible, the introduction<br />
of up-to-date plant and machinery, the elimination of waste, by using<br />
every effort to reduce labour turn-over by cutting out unnecessary<br />
absenteeism, and to prevent the abuse of sick leave provisions. This<br />
appeal is made not only in the interests of the people of AuAtral) a. </p>
<p>but also that the people of Australia can play their part in making<br />
more commodities available to the people of Britain, and enabling<br />
commodities to be secured from other countries in the world for our<br />
convenience and welfare.<br />
Consideration of the production needs of Australia have indic:<br />
ated tlat two major bottlenecks exist toward the overcoming of<br />
which the influence of the three parties should be exerted to the fullest.<br />
The major bottleneck, that of coal, is one which the parties feel can<br />
be best solved by the recently appointed Joint Coal Board, which is now<br />
concentrating its efforts on a solution of this great economic problem.<br />
We make an earnest appeal to the coal miners and those closely engaged<br />
in the production of coal, and its distribution, to assist to their utmost.<br />
The other major bottleneck is that of man-power. The economic<br />
expansion of Australia during the last seven years has made a great<br />
demand for additional men and women for industry. The parties<br />
suggest that many persons who gave fully and freely of their services<br />
during the war period to help the nation in its period of stress should,<br />
as far as possible, make themselves available to industry to overcome<br />
the grave shortages resulting from an almost complete war-time cessation<br />
of production of consumable goods which must now be made available,<br />
in addition to normal peace-time requirements of the nation.<br />
3. It was evident to the conference that. from a general review<br />
of the economic and employment position, free or private enterprise<br />
in the past and at present is the major avenue for providing work.<br />
It is, therefore, the avenue providing the greatest measure of employment.<br />
Complete understanding between the controllers of enterprise<br />
: end representatives of the workers is, therefore, essential if industrial<br />
relations are to be established on a satisfactory basis.<br />
4. The matter of prevention and settlement of industrial disputes<br />
ictween employer and employee is fundamental to the efficient and<br />
smooth running of industry. All parties to the conference agree that<br />
the conciliation and arbitration machinery provided by the Commonwvealth<br />
and the States provides a means whereby differences between<br />
t: mployer and employee should be readily determined. In the settlement<br />
of industrial disputes, conciliation should be exercised to the<br />
fullest before final resort is made to arbitration. It is desirable in the<br />
interests of the community that industrial disputes should be reduced<br />
to the barest possible minimum. The trades union representatives have<br />
expressed their disagreement with unauthorized strikes arising without<br />
consultation, either with the trades union concerned, the Trades and<br />
Labour Council of the States, or the Australasian Council of Trade<br />
Unions ini the Federal sphere.<br />
5. The right of the worker to share in the proceeds of industry is<br />
ine which has received the full consideration of conference. It is<br />
agreed by all parties that increased standards of living are only possible<br />
from constantly increasing production of goods and services required.<br />
The right of the vorker to recefive his proportionate share of increased </p>
<p>production is recognized, but the manner in which this should be granted<br />
to workers in industry is subject to difference of opinion. The<br />
employers have suggested that a satisfactory solution would be for the<br />
introduction or extension of incentive payments, which would.. give.. a<br />
daily or weekly benefit to the worker from the results of his immediate<br />
higher production. The trades union attitude is one of distaste for<br />
incentive payment, based on past experience. The Australasian Council<br />
of Trade Unions intimated to the conference -that it is prepared to make<br />
a full and complete investigation into modern incentive payment systems<br />
to determine whether such systems would be of advantage to the worker<br />
and the community. The employers intimated to the trades union<br />
representatives that they were prepared to place before thern information<br />
requested and give assistance so that this investigarion could be<br />
thoroughly undertaken.<br />
The holding of this conference to achieve better understanding<br />
between the partners of industry has indicated that view points on<br />
matters of policy and principle have varied greatly. The conference,<br />
however, has enabled both parties in a free and frank manner to state<br />
their views and the reasons for them. Conference is, therefore, of the<br />
opinion that frequent consultations of this character are essential for<br />
securing better industrial relations and undisturbed continuity of production.<br />
It is agreed that similar conferences should be held at six<br />
monthly periods so that econome trends, industrial and other problems<br />
might be fully considered.<br />
The parties agree to advise each other as to matters which<br />
they feel should be considered by conference so that they may be able<br />
to investigate such matters with a view to decisions being arrived at<br />
when conference meets<br />
Those present were-<br />
COM. MOwF. Ar.' TH GovErtN.\ M. ENT.-The Prime Minister ( Mr. Chilley), the<br />
Minister for L. abour ( Mr. Holloway), the acting-Attorney-General ( Senator<br />
McKenna), tile as-istant-secretary of the Department of Labour ( Mr. H. A.<br />
Bland), the Director of Industrial Welfare ( Mr. L. G. Baxter).<br />
AUSTRALASIAN ( CouNCIL. or TRADE UNIONS.-The president ( Mr. Clarey,<br />
the vice-president ( Mr. T. A. Cranwell), the secretary ( Mr. A. E.<br />
Monk), and Messrs. L. Austin, New South Wales, C. Crofts. Victoria, E. J.<br />
Hansen, Queensland, A. V. Tlhoipson. South Australia, and H. O'Neill, Tasmania,<br />
members of the executive.<br />
AssOCIATKrn CHAM;" rs orF MANITACTr: ItE.-Th e president ( Mr. L. Robinson).<br />
tihe New South Wales president ( Mr. J. Adamson), the New South Wales vicepresidents<br />
( Messrs. P. Tivey and R. J. Webster), tile Victorian president<br />
( Mr. C. H. McKay), tile Victorian deputy-president ( Mr. E. F. Atkins), the<br />
Victorian past-president ( Mr. C. A. H. Derhan), the Queensland president ( Mr.<br />
H. S. Gresham), the South Australian past president ( Mr. F. T. Perry). the<br />
acting-director ( Mr. A. N. Curphey), the New South Wales director, Mr. C. R.<br />
Hall), the Queensland secretary ( Mr. L. Suggers) and an officer of the Metal<br />
Trades Association ( Mr. J. Lambert).<br />
ARBITRATION ACT-CONCILIATION COMMISSIONERS.<br />
On 15th August, 1947, Mr. Chifley said-<br />
Cabinet decided to-day on the appointment of sixteen Conciliation<br />
Commissioners. The deputy Industrial Registrar and Conciliation<br />
Commissioner ( Mr. E. H. Rowlands) will be the Chief Commissioner. </p>
<p>7<br />
In addition, all the other existing commissioners, within the age limits<br />
laid down by the Act, will be appointed. They are Messrs. A. A.<br />
Blakeley, G. A. Findlay, G. A. Mooney, D. V. Morrison, J. H. Portus<br />
and M. M. Stewart. The following nine additional appointments will<br />
also be made:-<br />
Brigadier A. S. Blackburn, V. C. ( South Australian barrister) Messrs. R. H.<br />
Beers ( Secretary of the Victorian Department of Labour and Chief Inspector<br />
of Factories), G. H. Buckland ( Australian Workers Union, Victoria), J. 1.<br />
Ionovan ( Executive Officer of the Conno ealth T'ranSport Advisory Council),<br />
V. Dwyer ( General Secretary of the Amalgauated Postal Workers' Union,<br />
New South Walet). F. D. Kelly, M. L. C. ( New South Wales), N. Roberts ( Conmercial<br />
Representative, Department of Munitions, Victoria), A. R. Wallis<br />
( General Secretary of the Clothing Trade Employees Federation, Victoria), and<br />
W. J. Wallwork ( Stipendiary Magistrate, Western Australia).<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 125, page 14.)<br />
UNEMPLOYMENT-FIGURES.<br />
On 1st September, 1947, the Minister for Labour ( Mr. Holloway)<br />
said that unemployment in Australia was at record low levels and<br />
continued to fall month by month. At 31st July, 1947, the number<br />
of unemployed persons receiving financial benefits totalled 5,364 males<br />
and 192 females, nearly 700 below the total for June, 1947. At 31st<br />
July, 1947, the Commonwealth Employment Service held unfilled<br />
vacancies for 42,100 males and 30,700 females, a rise of some 3,000 on<br />
the previous month, the total number of vacancies being over 100,000.<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 126, page 31.)<br />
PEACE.<br />
JAPAN-VISIT OF DR. EVATT.<br />
On 5th August, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
" 1 have received the following message from the Supreme Commrander,<br />
Allied Powers ( General of the Army Douglas MacArthur):-<br />
Dr. Evatt has completed his visit to Japan and has sailed for home. It<br />
has been a source of pleasure and satisfaction to everyone to have had him.<br />
here. He has represented your country with skill and distinction and has<br />
added to its national prestige. He has been of marked assistance with regard<br />
to occupation problems and has made a distinct contribution to the furthering<br />
of a treaty of peace. It is needless to add that he lias rendered more. vivid<br />
the indissoluble ties of cordiality and friendship forged between our two<br />
rountries during our ( commlon struggle in the Pacific. Thank you for perinitting<br />
him. to comne."<br />
On 12th August, 1947, the Minister for External Affairs ( Dr.<br />
Evatt) said-<br />
During my' visit to Japan-chiefly a fact-finding mission-I had<br />
full and frank discussions abrnut the occupation and the problems that<br />
will confront the Allies in writing the peace. I am satisfied that the<br />
way is clear to the making of a peace settlement that will be a stable<br />
foundation for the security of the Pacific.<br />
" I had frequent discussions with the Supreme Commander, Allied<br />
Powers ( General MacArthur), and with leading officials of the occupation,<br />
diplomatic representatives of other Powers, ' and a few of the </p>
<p>Japanese parliamentary and trades union leaders. Fromn these discussions<br />
and personal observation I am able to ' appreciate still better<br />
the undoubted achievements of an extremely difficult and complex<br />
military occupation and administration. My consultations with<br />
General MacArthur showed a broad agreement on . the steps to by<br />
taken in preparing the treaty, on the principles that should be contained<br />
in it, on the type of supervisory , machinery that should bi<br />
established under it and on mnany of the other important matters with<br />
which the settlemcent must deal.<br />
" It has been most encouraging to find that all my discussions and<br />
observations have amply confirmed the soundness of the policy that ' the<br />
Australian Government has consistently advocated towards Japan. The<br />
two great objectives are the security of Australia and other Allied<br />
Powers from a resurgence of Japanese aggression, and a positive programme<br />
for assisting Japan to develop gradually into a democratic<br />
and peaceful member of the society of nations. Almost equally important<br />
is the : metlhod of peace-making. The peace treaty should b:.<br />
negotiated as soon as possible along democratic lines by all powers<br />
that played I substantial part in the Pacific war. Because of her outstanding<br />
war effort, Australia is clearly entitled to be a party prinlpal<br />
to the settliement, and that : i now universally recognized.<br />
The military occupation has new almost accomplished its primary<br />
task, which w. as ie complete physical disarniamneut and deiiilitarizution<br />
of Japan. It has taken imlportant initial steps towards th.<br />
democratic reconstruction of Japnii, for example through the -adoption<br />
by the Japanese people of a inew constitution and the encouragement<br />
of trades unions. The peace. treaty could and should contain provisions<br />
destined to . ecure. the accomplishment of the long-term objeetives-<br />
to prevent any re-growthl of a vw. rr potential and to stial'uato<br />
and consolidate the growth of democracy in Japan. These problems<br />
will form the subject of discussions between members of the British<br />
Commonwealth on 26th August, 1947. That beginning will be followed<br />
by ai conference of all the Powers that took a substantial roll.<br />
in achieving victory in the Pacific war.<br />
I was greatly impressed by the bearing and behaviour of the<br />
Australian servicemen and the re'st of the B. C. O. F. in Japan. They<br />
have greatly assisted in the success of tin occupation and have demonstrated<br />
to Japan and the world at large Australia's major interest in<br />
the Pacific. The co-operation between the B. C. O. F. and the United<br />
States forces has strengthened an association and comradeship that did<br />
-o much for Australia during the crisis in the Pacific war."<br />
JAPAN--ADVISORY COMMITTEE.<br />
On 12th August, 1947, the Advisory Committee on Japanese Settlement<br />
had its first meeting. Members of the committee , are-<br />
Sir Frederic Eggleston, chairman, the Solicitor-General ( Professor K. ' 1.<br />
Bailey), vice-chairman, the chairman of the Canteens Trust ( Brigadier A. S.<br />
Blackburn), the chairman of the Australian Broadcasting Commission ( Mr.<br />
R. J. F. Boyer), the president of the Australasian Council of Trades Unions<br />
( Mr. P. J. Clarey, Miss Constance Duncan. the leader of tlh </p>
<p>9<br />
Australian Antarctic Expedition ( Sir Douglas Mawson), Professo. A. H.<br />
McDonald, the president of the Legion of ex-Servicemen ( Mr. B. McDonald),<br />
the Secretary of the Associated Chambers of Comnmerce ( Mr. P. R. Wilkins),<br />
Professor H. L. Sadler, Senator Tangney and Messrs. Beazley, Sheehan, Corser,<br />
Harrison, McEwen and Ryan, Ms. H. R.<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 128, page 22.)<br />
JAPAN-BRITTSH COMMONWEALTH CONFERENCE.<br />
On 16th August, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
The Minister for External Affairs ( Dr. Evatt) advised Cabinet<br />
to-day that representatives of Britain, Canada, South Africa, New<br />
Zealand, India, Pakistan, Burma and Australia would meet at Canlierra<br />
on 26th August, 1947, to discuss the question of a peace<br />
; ettlement with Japan. The provisional agenda of the conference will<br />
loe procedural questions; basic objectives; control or supervision of<br />
Japan; territorial provisions; disarmament and demilitarization;<br />
political provisions; economic and financial provisions; and reparations.<br />
" The general policy in relation to Japanese settlement may be<br />
summarized as follows:-<br />
There should be no delay in going ahead with the Japanese I'Paice Conference.<br />
In the absence of a peace settlement there will be increasing tendencies for<br />
iajor matters of permanent imlport. inc to be dealt with on a piecemejal basis or<br />
to be postponed.<br />
Auistrnliln'aw \\ a eltort entitled lier t-be rI: tog nized as n party principal in<br />
the peace settlement Australia lhis ealted this position by her war effort<br />
which, inl Celcr. ial MacArtlur's words. contributed inlcaslulrably towards<br />
I'acific victory.<br />
Australia accepts the democratic principle that despite their varying con-<br />
Iributions to the common victory all nations which played any substantial<br />
a:.; rt in the Pacific war should he represented at the peace conference.<br />
The voting procedure suggeste l by the United States ( that is, two-third<br />
irajority) is just and democratic and any attempt to apply the veto system<br />
would be unjust and must be resisted.<br />
The peace settlement for Japan need not be a long drawn out affair, but<br />
iuld be completed early in 1048. Indeed its fundamentals have already been<br />
:; ccepted in the basic policy formulated in the Far Eastern Advisory Commission<br />
; nd later confirmed in substance by the present Far Eastern Commission which<br />
was a development of the broad principles of the Potsdam declaration. The<br />
f: oundlations of the peace have also been laid through the constructive pioneer<br />
work already pierformed in Japan by General MacArthur, as a result of which<br />
military disarumaient is now practically completed.<br />
The basic policy of the Far Eastern Commission prescribed certain measures<br />
which were the physical disarmament of Japan. the removal of militarist and<br />
I'a: scist elements, the trial and punishment of war crimes and the destruction<br />
Japan'. capacity to wage war.<br />
The basic policy of the Far Eastern Commission also laid emphasis upon the<br />
i-sitive tasks of building a peaceful and democratic Japan. This called for<br />
reform of the social, political and economic life of Japan. For example, trade<br />
unions should be actively encourigel antd the educational ystcm liberalized.<br />
These positive tasks are necessarily lone-term in character.<br />
SThe settlement niust take account of South and East Asia and the Pacific<br />
t whole. A peace should be established in accordance with the objectives<br />
-f the United Nations Charter-a peace which should give security from future<br />
;., gression and at the same time help to raise the standards of living of all<br />
the peoples of South and East Asia and the Pacific. The gradual economic<br />
development of Japan should be part of a general plan for the economic betterment<br />
of East and South-East Asia and the Pacific as a whole. It would be<br />
injust if her population obtained privileges and benefits denied to the countries<br />
which she has devastated. </p>
<p>In order to achieve these objectives, an Allied supervisory authority should<br />
be established in the treaty of peace in order to consolidate the important<br />
gains already made and ensure a bona fide observance of the treaty provisions<br />
and especially to prevent any re-establislhment of a war potential. In addition,<br />
the supervisory authority should have as one of its functions, the co-ordination<br />
of the Japanese economy with those of the Pacific and East Asiatic regions.<br />
The futitre of . Japan depends first upon the determination of the Allied<br />
Power to pursue vigorously the objectives laid down by the Far Eastern Commission.<br />
and secondly upon the energy, sincerity and co-operation of the<br />
Japanese themselves in carrying out the great reforms already planned.<br />
The peace treaty should therefore lie not vindictive but just and firm.<br />
Australia desires to achieve hy demnocratic procedures of peace-making a<br />
stable and lasting peace in the Pacific based on security from aggression and<br />
the welfare of all Pacific peoples. This great objective will be assisted if tihe<br />
peace conference is expedited, thereby furnishing an example of Allied co-operation<br />
which should also assist in the final European settlement.<br />
Cabinet expressed satisfaction with the progress made in connexion<br />
with the Japanese peace settlement, as a result of Dr. Evatt's<br />
recent mission to Japan and gave approval to the general principles and<br />
purposes to be followed and the democratic procedures proposed for<br />
the peace settlement<br />
JAPAN-BRITISH COMMONWEALTH CONFERENCE.<br />
On 26th August, 1947, the British Commonwealth conference met<br />
at Canberra. The following communiqu6s were issued:-<br />
August 26th: Discussions at the conference are of a pirovisionl icharacter<br />
and are for the ipurpose of exchanging views between ' the nations represented.<br />
The subjects to he discussed for this purpose will hei.<br />
Procedure--The proceedings and machinery for making the peace settlemtent<br />
with . Japan, including composition: level of erereiitation:<br />
time: place: voting: time-tailel for peace ' ttleiieni t procedurec sihsequenit<br />
procedure.<br />
2. Basic objectives of settlement.<br />
3. Territorial provisions.<br />
4. Disarmament and de-mnilitarization.<br />
Political provisions.<br />
Economic and financial provisions.<br />
7. Reparations.<br />
S. Machinery for enforcement-arrang(. ments for termination of occupation:<br />
control organization ( composition. nminner of voting. , place of.<br />
meeting, executive action, relation to United Nations): termination.<br />
9. Form of peace settlement ( one instrument or two; participation of<br />
Japan; coming into force; adherences.)<br />
August 26th: At the short afternoon session, there was . a general exchange<br />
of views on Peace Conference procedure including the system of voting. In<br />
the course of the discussion on the latter subject, views were expressed on the<br />
United States proposal that decision at the Peace Conference shlioul he by a<br />
two-thirds majority.<br />
The consensus of opinion was that the first meeting of the I'racte Conference<br />
should he held as soon as possible. It was also the general understaniding that<br />
the initial conference should be on a Governmental or policy making level.<br />
August 27th: To-day's sessions were devoted to an examination of the basic<br />
objectives of the settlement and the territorial provisions that should he incorporated<br />
in the peace treaty. Consideration of these problems was simplified by<br />
the existence of the statements made at Cairo, Yalta and Potsdam. Allied agreement<br />
on fundamental principles had also been reached on the basic policy and<br />
other policy decisions of the Far Eastern Commission.<br />
An examination of these documents shows that there will be no complicated<br />
frontiers to define in the Japanese Peace Treaty since Japanese territories are all<br />
insular. The Potsdam Declaration states specifically the ' Japanese sovereignty </p>
<p>shall be limited to the islands of Honshu, Hokkaido, Kyushu, Shikoku and such<br />
minor islands as we determine It will be for the Peace Conference to decide<br />
which of the minor islands shall remain under Japanese sovereignty.<br />
Against this background, the delegations exchanged views on certain strategic<br />
aspects of the changes proposed and on its effect on the economy of Japan and<br />
heard statements from the commander-in-chief of the British Commonwealth<br />
Occupation Force ( Lieutenant-General H. C. H. Robertson), the Assistant Undersecretary<br />
in the British Foreign Office ( Mr. M. O. Denning), the head of the<br />
Canadian diplomatic mission in Tokyo ( Dr. E. H. Norman) and the Australian<br />
representative on the Far Eastern Commission ( Major J. Plimioll) on the military,<br />
social, political and economic development of Japan under the occupation<br />
and on the prospects for the post occupation period. Stress was laid on the great<br />
contributions these territorial changes will make towards preventing a recurrence<br />
of Japanese aggression, as they will deprive Japan of vital military, naval and air<br />
bases and control of certain essential raw materials<br />
August 28th: The discussion of the disarmament and demilitarization of<br />
Japan was completed. Delegates expressed the view that Japan should remain<br />
completely disarmed and demilitarized, that all armaient manufacture should<br />
he forbidden. and that internal order should be maintained by a non-military<br />
police force.<br />
Conferenct exaimined in detail measures that might be necessary to ensure<br />
that the Japanese should not be permitted at present to conduct research in the<br />
field of atomic energy or to develop or use atomic energy.<br />
Complete prohibition of the building of any kind of naval vessels, as decided<br />
on by the Far Eastern Commission, and the limitations that should be imposed<br />
on the operation of Japanese commercial shipping confined to insular trade were<br />
discussed. Views were also exchanged on the question of the control to be exercised<br />
over the future of civil aviation in Japan. It was felt that manufacture<br />
of aircraft should be completely prohibited in Japan.<br />
Conference has devoted a great deal of time to the subjects of the disarmament<br />
and demilitarization of Japan because of their extreme importance in<br />
securing a stable peace in the Pacific.<br />
Conference considered the principles of the political provisions that should be<br />
incorporated in the Peace Treaty. It paid particular attention to the present<br />
Japanese Constitution which carried out many of the principles which the Allied<br />
Powers would like to see permanently in effect in Japan such as the guarantee of<br />
fundamental human rights.<br />
Among other subjects dealt with was the exclusion from public . office of<br />
persons who had been removed because of their ultra-nationalistic and<br />
militaristic affiliations, and Conference considered ways and means of continuing<br />
to exclude those who remained undesirable.<br />
Other subjects discussed were the Japanese Public Service, education, ultranationalistic<br />
societies, special police and para-military organizations. These<br />
subjects are already dealt with to some extent in the Potsdam Declaration and in<br />
the Basic Policy and other Policy Decisions of the Far Eastern Commission, and<br />
discussion of these subjects was, therefore, facilitated by the consideration<br />
already given to them and by the wide area of agreement that had already been<br />
achieved on these subjects among the eleven members of the Far Eastern<br />
Commission. Conference took note of the steps taken by the Supreme Commander and the<br />
Japanese Government to dissociate Shinto from the Japanese State. It was<br />
evident that the pre-war system of providing State subsidies for Shinto shrines,<br />
clergy, and organizations should not be resumed after the Treaty.<br />
Conference considered matters relating to treaties between Japan and other<br />
nations and the precedents set in the treaties with Italy and the satellite powers<br />
were carefully examined. In this connexion, Conference considered the question<br />
of the admission of Japan to the United Nations and the International Court<br />
and to such bodies as the Food and Agricultural Organization and the International<br />
Labour Office.<br />
It was suggested that Japan should renounce all rights and interests both<br />
public and private located outside Japan and that these would be expropriated<br />
by local administrations.<br />
Conference devoted attention to means by which Japanese who had<br />
co-operated with the occupation authorities would be given full protection against<br />
victimization after the Allied Forces were withdrawn. It seemed obvious that </p>
<p>til1lIegali v: iLti d itv shouild he given to all acts of J appaitie. e n atijonllIs bile inl<br />
' ceerdaitee Nvijt directions or pblicies of tile occupying authorities, and X~ sq<br />
that fill legal validity should be given to acts of the occupying tuthnrities<br />
whether before or after the coining into force of the Pence Treaty. Conference<br />
liscus: ed various sutggestions for giving, effect to this.<br />
Augoust 29: Conference devoted most of its time to at considerationi at<br />
enomic aspects of tlte Peace Settlement. A key piroblin wats that cf . devisiiuu-<br />
-rocurity restrictions whiich wold achieve Allied objectives and( v. tile samle tiuti.<br />
permit, Japan to ~ stiti herself. It was recognized tihat if the nature n'<br />
legree of tite restrict itns itmade at worallbile Japanese ecnomyiiV inmlossi ble, thv<br />
. Al lied powvers would inievitably ho faced with either tile teed tit sllit~ idizc iti:<br />
. JalIMLese2 eCtlony ttr tile develtititeititt o cetiditlizis it llJpalt which wcould be<br />
inimical to the cestablishmient of democracy. It oNn5 iltdoi d in _ l-y felt<br />
. stbject to thle over-riding requirement of security, it w. otild lie iii tlic'ln nt<br />
initerestsi of the Allied poer that the . Iaiaiiesveicoiiii shiitd vtiid oil its<br />
iwol feet.<br />
Confereiice gave : t great deal of attenltiotn tio the Security '' iti i; te~ I' cV.<br />
ttowiinis its deliberations yesterday en disarmament aind deitilitarization. ft<br />
e-meti to be the geiieral viewv that the econitio rstrictioiis itithosed should<br />
hie of a kiiid wvlich would be capable of clear dlefinitin atid ready ltifcreetoeii<br />
andiltitat, they shtould ttot be mliplietiid unniecessairily. It ixssuagested, for<br />
examptle, that tile sort of coittiol-s thlat might, be itriposed wvoutld be, the prollibitiolt<br />
if prodlucti on in , nine in dusvtries of ' tra teeq ic imooie the, I lit itatie~ t 0f<br />
irodlcctitn atid producti-e capac: ity to. definite levelsA in cci tauti other keyindustries;<br />
such u robib it ions anad res tvricticits to lie s itItpie mcii ed bY apprtotrit<br />
ilitprt, cotntrols.<br />
Delegates felt thatt, wi thin the scopje ( i the cetisideratiotis it -txtirllit) treatiY<br />
provisions should be designed1 toit~~ s tiermvl fteC-se dlw tnn<br />
if living and economic instability and that provision s'ioi Id lie made . fat<br />
acee ptane by the Ja patiese Ce verto'wcit of ii i ill it itet IA; t i ( tm I sttaidartds<br />
itt inilustrial Miid commercial conduct.<br />
It wvas also recognized that effective dentcrat&amp; e growth it: itit ttust,, i,<br />
based oit soutid eceotomic conditions and related to chianges iii thle djctribut'mt<br />
a f econiom: ic piowe r. Other wise thetre was a aulger that the~ c iti i oc<br />
ellanges hrotuglit about in Japani wouldi lise thiir sihznifleance and( the formet-'<br />
goveringt arnd montopoelist classes iiiigltt it0-assert the ir author i tY' possl) Ti y il<br />
indirect and concealed Nraysz. In the light of this tapprcoach, Cotiiferenco<br />
exatitined siueh nmatte rs as ti ad tini oils, Itand refoit n andtil lie( issoluotionil of tIno<br />
Zaibatsu the banking and financial comnecs vtriforniet lv , mtrolhl at l~ i cci<br />
hart of Japain's indutstrial powver).<br />
Cotnferene noted the '~ ex in i trail! Itliltb . itl:! thte Sl-i-et' lilt iti d L.<br />
statement of prineipiles w hich was laid dvttlast v ar by tile Far Easterti<br />
Comm0: issioni ( thec niembersltip tiow. being : 5,000,000) and i ' eed to lie gelerall<br />
felt tha t Somei p rovisioits sIhoiuld biIe tuade ini the trl,: tv to, ptt etvet Ile righlt<br />
i. f wet kers' associatioti and to aufford upltrtltnitv the IuII, itti ' Qot;&amp; t<br />
and activity oif trade uniuiii.<br />
Contfecie ioted the stepis taketi -it fat. liy tite Supireime t ttittie I<br />
the im-e Governmttetnt to dissoilve tice Zaitti i 1,( l ii Itli 4,1i tli<br />
tieessitv for con hliriting this task.<br />
It v. s furthter replriesented thtat, toi pr-ex ct tilijustihallc ex ploitat ittn ( ot<br />
l abiour, c czpci all -v chiildi lteour, do mip incg. altit e tf patet., : ir trtide itark.<br />
antd dizcritiiiaticit against foreign firnts and ititetests. . Ializtt should lie<br />
('( tll el led tit c'ompily wvith the Obli1galtion i'if in Ii'ria tic ii 1 ais plerati its, in<br />
tle ectttont ice held whtichi were dccii l tprp ae for CNtxa t phV. sot ie Of<br />
Ptitvelthiultl. f tile Ilitet'l~ iiitii I1ithLtttit Olice<br />
Confetrence turned to tlte questioni of reparatiotis and1( lLii-e the vario-l<br />
cattegrieis that mig ht lie tiadle availabtle ti claimant cotittrii-. tii Pxatttioe, h<br />
the factors involved in the 1 i~ jt of thie Potsdamn dJeclaratimi.<br />
Septtemnber I Coinferettce coitiphleted its dinetiisshutt'u Ott the( ' iuliervisory<br />
Inatiii'ry that shlould lie established in Japain to iimpleent the terots of the<br />
Peace ' Tretaty. Cetiferecite discussed such miatters as the comtposition,. iethct<br />
of Votitig, futnetiotns, power,-atid minc.; is of ienfoirceutent of the -ilperviorv biiidy.<br />
Nii detamileid priposail, were cotis; idereh. </p>
<p>On 2nd September, 1947, Dr. Evatt said<br />
" We can look back on the week's work with great satisfaction.<br />
We have all worked together towards the attainment of our common<br />
aim, the establishment of a just and lasting peace in East Asia and<br />
the Pacific. It has been a great pleasure to preside over the first<br />
conference to include a new India, a new Dominion of Pakistan, and<br />
Burma. These states share the desire of all of us for freedom and<br />
democracy, and in their great tasks they will have the full support of<br />
all other members of the British Commonwealth.<br />
" We came here as separate sovereign states to exchange views in<br />
order to understand more clearly one another's policies, rather than to<br />
commit ourselves to a specific solution to a great problem. But more<br />
important than mere formal agreements is the spirit which animates<br />
us all. We want a settlement that will be the basis for a stable peace<br />
in the Pacific, free from the threat of Japanese aggression. We want<br />
to encourage democracy in Japan. We do not desire to prejudice<br />
future peace by yielding to mere resentment and vindictiveness. The<br />
restrictions we desire to impose on Japan and its economy are those<br />
necessary in. the interest of security. In curbing effectively and permanently<br />
Japanese ability to wage war, we must at the same time leave<br />
her an outlet for peaceful development. But at the same time we have<br />
taken account of the difficulties of the peoples who suffered at Japanese.<br />
hands. The future of Japan is nlot an isohttc. d probem but onev wicli must<br />
be approached in relation to its neighbouring States : nd to the world<br />
as a whole. The solution can lie in a comprehensive international<br />
effort to raise standards of welfare throughout the whole of Southern<br />
and Eastern Asia and the Pacific. Japan must contribute her utmost<br />
towards raising those standards; and if she does so she will share in<br />
the improvement. Australia does not want Japan to become a starvation<br />
area in the Far East, nor does Australia want the Far East to be<br />
a starvation area in the rest of the world. In making the peace settlement,<br />
we should not devote our attention exclusively to the defeated<br />
nation. That is the basis for a realistic and, bholiev-., a statesima. alike<br />
peace. I believe that these views are shared by the United States, whose<br />
vast war effort contributed so much to winning the Pacific war, and<br />
by General MacArthur, under whose leadership the threat of Japanese<br />
invasion was flung back from Australia and the occupation of Japan<br />
successfully undertaken.<br />
The great desire of the peoples of the whole world to-day is peace.<br />
To-day there is neither war nor peace. Our efforts to establish a better<br />
international order, based on the United Nations, will be held back if we<br />
do not speedily make peace and conclude settlements which will form<br />
the basis for world recovery and development. The peoples of the<br />
British Commonwealth . and their Governments here represented are<br />
striving to bring about an early settlement with Japan based on justice<br />
and achieved by democratic methods." </p>
<p>Delegates to the conference were:<br />
AUsTRALLA.-The Minister for External Affairs ( Dr. Evatt), the Minister<br />
for Defence ( Mr. Dedman), and the Minister for Commerce ( Mr. Pollard).<br />
BURMA.-The Minister for External Affairs ( Thakin Lun Baw), and the<br />
Secretary of the Department of External Affairs Shwe Baw).<br />
CANADA.-The Minister for Defence ( Mr. B. Claxton) and the High Commissioner<br />
to Australia ( Mr. K. A. Greene).<br />
INDIA.-Sir B. Ranma Rau and the High Commissioner to Australia ( Sir<br />
: aghunath Paranjpye).<br />
Nmv ZLANTD.-The Prime Minister ( Mr. Fra sr) and tile Hipgh Comnis-<br />
sioner to Aust ( Mr. J. G. Barclay).<br />
PAKISTAN.-Mirza Mohammed Raf.<br />
SoUTH AFRIcA.-The Minister of Justice ( Mr. H. Lawrence).<br />
UNITED KINGDOM.-The Minister for British Commonwealth Relations<br />
( Viscount Addison) and the Minister of State ( Mr. H. McNeill).<br />
SHIPBUILDING.<br />
DE-REQUISITIONING-OPERATION.<br />
On 7th August, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
General de-requisitioning of vessels now controlled . by the Commonwealth<br />
Government through . the Australian Shipping Board under<br />
the administrative direction of the Minister for Shipping ( Sennator<br />
Ashley) by power. s conferred upon National Security ( Shipping Coordination)<br />
Regulations will commence on 18th August. 1947. from<br />
which-date also increases in freight rates of Imany cirgi itrmnis<br />
will become operative. With some few exceptions, ships will be derequisitioned<br />
as they conic into position for re-delivery to owners. The<br />
exceptions will, for the present, include some intrastate shipping in<br />
respect to which negotiations are continuing.<br />
After the outbreak of war, a number of Australian passenger and<br />
other vessels were taken by the Government for : the direct use of the<br />
armed services, and the bulk of the remainder of the Australian Mercantile<br />
marine was requisitioned in 1941 under National Security ( Shipping<br />
Control) Regulations. The Shipping Control Board, appointed under<br />
the regulations, succeeded later by the Australian Shipping Board,<br />
was given wide powers to direct the trade in which the requisitioned<br />
vessels would engage, and to govern the rates of freight chargeable.<br />
In 1943, it was decided that close collaboration was essential with<br />
the Commonwealth Prices Commissioner in relation to freight rates<br />
and the shipping regulations were amended. With minor exceptions,<br />
the freight rates prevailing on 12th April, 1943, have remained<br />
unchanged. ". Since 1943 there have been heavy increases in costs under any<br />
headings and the Commonwealth Government, as part of its general<br />
plans for price stabilization, has met the difference between the<br />
revenues received and costs incurred in the chartering and operating of<br />
the requisitioned vessels. A review has been made to ascertain the<br />
extent to which the revenue from freights will require to be increased<br />
to enable shipowners to operate their vessels at a reasonable profit </p>
<p>level on the requisitioned vessels being released from control under<br />
National Security ( Shipping Co-ordina. tion) Regulations-and it is<br />
apparent that substantial freight increases are inevitable.<br />
The Government has decided to permit increases on a. large number<br />
of cargo lines . and to continue for the present a governmental subsidy<br />
on freights in respect to certain other goods. The freight increases,<br />
whether to be met by shippers directly or by the Government as<br />
subsidy, are very considerable. The extent of the increases-about<br />
œ 2,000,000 a year-cannot be stated in the foium of a percentage on the<br />
1939 rates or on the 1943 rates as they cover many different lines and<br />
vary with different trades.<br />
The schedule has been carefully worked out by government officers<br />
and shipowners in collaboration and the Government is satisfied that<br />
the additional rates approved and necessary to enable shipowers to<br />
pay their way and earn a reasonable profit on their coastal shipping<br />
operations. Owners have shown no anxiety to increase freights unnecessarily<br />
but are conscious of the competition, actual . and potential, from<br />
other forms of transport, and of the fact that costs cannot rise steeply<br />
without danger to their industry. Details of the approved increases<br />
and of the cargo items eligible for freight subsidy will be published.<br />
" CSpecific increases which the Government will subsidize for the<br />
present include coal and sugar. Other items eligible, under certain<br />
approved conditions, for Government subsidy are breakfast foods,<br />
dried and processed fruit, invalid and infants' food, milk products, stock<br />
foods, textile and clothing ( excluding floor coverings and furnishings)<br />
and timber. These items are illustrations and the commodities named<br />
are subject to precise definitions.<br />
The Government will not subsidize limestone, barley, produce,<br />
steel products or general cargo not specifically provided for. The<br />
cargo items eligible for subsidy have been selected in relation to the<br />
Government's overall economic policy.<br />
The Government i. s giving no undertaking as to how long it will<br />
continue to contribute to the shipping freight costs of goods now designated<br />
as eligible for subsidy under approved conditions. The Government<br />
will also keep under review the general level of shipping<br />
freight rates with a view to revision if it should become apparent, after<br />
a reasonable period of experience, that this is necessary in the<br />
interests of shippers, shipping operators, or the national economy.<br />
" In common with every other country, Australia suffered from<br />
tonnage shortages during the war -and since. The Australian coastal<br />
fleet has been augmented during the war by Australian-built ships and<br />
by tonnage chartered from Britain and other countries. It is still<br />
necessary to retain on charter a considerable number of British vessels,<br />
mostly engaged in the coal and bulk iron ore trades, and the local<br />
shipbuilding programme is continuing. </p>
<p>16<br />
" Ships under the direction of the Australian Shipping Board<br />
including the requisitioned ship. s, have been operated as if they were<br />
, ne fleet. Traffic committees, on which government officers and represcntatives<br />
of the shipping companies met, considered total shipping<br />
resources in relation to cargo accumulations and the necessity for<br />
according priorities to most needed goods. A principal objective is<br />
to get full loads for ships and the necessity to use vessels to their<br />
utmost capacity naturally makes it extremely difficult to arrange for<br />
regular services and this movement will doubtless continue. Before<br />
deciding to de-requisition, coastal vessels, the Government has sought<br />
iissurances from shipowners that co-ordinated direction of traffic will<br />
continue while the necessity remained. Owners have volunteered full<br />
co-operative and assistance and a committee representative of owners<br />
and of the Comnmonwealt. h Directorate of Shipping will continue the<br />
overall direction of . hip. in relation to the country's needs.<br />
" I pay tribute to the assistance received during the war years, and<br />
later, frcom the British Government. Australia contributed its resource.<br />
without reserve to the common pool and had been supported generously<br />
by the British Governent. Valued assistance at emergency<br />
periods had been given by thre United States War Shipping Administration.<br />
T can speak highly of the expert and willing assistance given<br />
to the Commonwealth Government by the Australian shipping cormpanies."<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 126, page 41; No. 128, page<br />
PRICES.<br />
GOODS DECLARED "-SCHOOL FEES, REVOCATION.<br />
On 7th August, 1947, the Minister for Customs ( Senator Courtice)<br />
announced that fees charged by religious, scientific, charitable or educational<br />
institutions had been removed from National Security ( Prices)<br />
Regulations. GOODS " DECLARED"--TAXI FARES, REVOCATION.<br />
On 7th August, 1947, Senator Courtice announced that fares<br />
charged for buses, taxis and hire cars operating within a State had<br />
been released from National Security ( Prices) Regulations.<br />
ORDER OF PRECEDENCE.<br />
NEW TABLE ANNOUNCED.<br />
On 7th August, 1947, the Governor-General announced that the<br />
King had approved of the following Commonwealth Order of<br />
Precedence:-1. The Governor-Genirall ( iniieldes ollicer actually administering the Governimieiit<br />
of the Comnniniwealti).<br />
2. Governors of States ( or Lieutenant-Governors of States when administerin=<br />
the Government), according to the population of their respective States; the<br />
Governor of a State to have, within its territory, precedence next to the Governor-<br />
General. ( A Lieutenant-Governor, who is not also Chief Justice, shall, when not<br />
administering the Government, rank with the Chief Justices of the States.) </p>
<p>3. The Prime Minister ( or Acting Prime Minister).<br />
4. Foreign Ambassadors.<br />
Foreign Ministers and Envoys.<br />
Federal Executive Councillors under summons to the Council.( a)<br />
6. The President of the Senate.<br />
7. The Speaker of the House of Representatives.<br />
8. High Commissioners in Australia for His Majesty's Governments elsewhere.<br />
( NoTE--Precedence ilnter sc of such High Commissioners shall United<br />
Kingdom, Canada. New Zealand. South Africa, India, ( 6)<br />
Eire). 9. Privv Councillors.<br />
Chief Justice of the High Court.<br />
11. Judges of the High Court of Australia, according to seniority.<br />
12. Senior Officers in command of the Naval, Military and Air Forces of the<br />
Commonwealth, according to seniority in their respective Services.<br />
13. Premiers of States, according to the population of their States.<br />
14. Chief Judge of the Commonwealth Arbitration Court.<br />
Other Federal Judges according to the date of appointment.<br />
16. Chief Justices of States, according to the population of their respective<br />
tates. 17. Members of the Senate.<br />
18. Members of the House of Representatives.<br />
19. Heads of Churches.<br />
Executive Councillors of States under summons, according to population<br />
o, States. Those of each State in a body, according to the population of their<br />
States. 21. Presidents of Legislative Councils of States, according to population.<br />
22. Speakers of Legislative Assemblies of States, according to population.<br />
23. Members of Federal Executive Council ( not under summons).<br />
24. Consuls-General.<br />
Knights of the various Orders and Knights Bachelor according to their<br />
precedence in the United Kingdom.<br />
26. Executive Councillors of States not under summons, ex-Ministers of<br />
States, and gentleman authorized to retain the prefix Honorable<br />
27. Judges of the Supreme Courts of States, according to the date of appointment.<br />
28. Members of the Legislative Councils of States, according to the population<br />
of their States.<br />
Members of the Legislative Assemblies of States, according to the popul:<br />
ition of their States<br />
Mayors of Capital Cities, according to the population of their States.<br />
31. The wives of the foregoing to enjoy the precedence of their husbands.<br />
32. In the absence of any special instruction from the King, the precedence<br />
oi persons entitled to precedence in the United Kingdom or other parts of the<br />
Empire, or in foreign countries, in relation to the abovementioned Officers to be<br />
determined as a matter of courtesy by the Governor-General.<br />
N. B.--The observance of the list at Commonwealth functions in any State<br />
should, as regards the precedence inter sc of the Officials of that State, be subject<br />
to any modifications rendered necessary by existing laws in that State.<br />
the summon; s wecalthse suinious issued by the Governor-General or by the<br />
Secretary of tlh Execiltiv Councill frolllti mn to time to attend meetings of the<br />
Executive Council. It doe'sn ot mnain thl aippoitintment of the officeof Member of the<br />
Executive Council. ( For earlier references, please see No. 105, page<br />
NETHERLANDS EAST INDIES.<br />
POLICY-MEDIATION.<br />
On 7th August, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) saidrefer<br />
to reports of an American offer to mediate in the Dutch-<br />
Indonesian dispute.<br />
The decision of the -Security Council was that the two parties<br />
should cease hostilities and then submit to arbitration or other peaceful<br />
means of settling the dispute. When that decision was taken by the </p>
<p>Security Council, it was interpreted by the Australian Government as<br />
meaning that the two parties would submit their case to an arbitrator<br />
who would give a decision which would be binding on the two parties,<br />
the arbitrator acting as an agent for the Security Council. Consequently,<br />
any offer merely of good offices does not adequately meet the<br />
situation. Reports are current that Republican authorities do not find mediation<br />
acceptable, nor do they find the good offices of only one country<br />
acceptable. While it is understood that the Netherlands Government<br />
had accepted the American offer, it must be accepted by both parties<br />
before negotiations can commence. It might be recalled that previously<br />
the Indonesians accepted the good offices of Britain, the United States,<br />
and Australia, which were put forward separately, but thise, at that<br />
time, were not acceptable to the Netherlands authorities.<br />
The present situation is full of dangers as, while there i. a truce,<br />
there is no negotiation or contact between the two parties, and incidents<br />
are likely to occur each day which might make negotiatin. more difficult.<br />
The period between the cessation of hostilities and the cnommnencement<br />
of negotiations should be as short as possible.<br />
" If both parties consider it would help to terminate this interim<br />
period and to commence negotiations immediately, the Australian<br />
Government, for its part, will be prepared to act jointly with -the<br />
United States Government in a capacity of mediator and arbitrator.<br />
This offer is made in the spirit in which the Australian Government<br />
raised the matter in the Security Council-that is in a spirit of impartially<br />
and with only one desire, to see, as soon as possible, a peaceful<br />
settlement of the prolonged dispute in the Netherlands East Indies<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 128, page 32.)<br />
CIVIL AVIATION.<br />
I. C. A. O.-REGULATIONS.<br />
On 8th August, 1947, the Minister fbr Civil Aviation ( Mr. Drakeford)<br />
announced that Australian air navigation regulations had been<br />
revised to bring them into line with the Chicago Convention, and to<br />
give effect to reconmmendations and decisions of the International Civil<br />
Aviation Organization created under that convention. The new regulations<br />
came into force on 10th August, 1947.<br />
SOUTH PACIFIC AIR TRANSPORT COUNCIL-SECOND<br />
MEETING.<br />
On 14th August, 1947, Mr. Drakeford said that the second meeting<br />
of the South Pacific Air Transport Council, which had concluded that<br />
day, had had as its chief task the policy for the conduct of British<br />
Commonwealth Air Services in the Pacific area and consideration of<br />
the reports of British Commonwealth Pacific Airlines and Tasman<br />
Empire Airways Ltd. The Council had agreed to the composition and </p>
<p>functions of the Trans-Pacific Committee and the Trans-Tasman Cormittee<br />
and had drawn up directives which would govern Tasman Empire<br />
Airways and British Commonwealth Pacific Airways in the<br />
operation of their services. It was agreed that the companies should<br />
be left the greatest initiative in the day-to-day management of their<br />
affairs in line with the Government's over-riding interest in matters of<br />
major policy and finance.<br />
The meeting agreed that British Commonwealth Pacific Airlines<br />
Ltd. would begin its operations of the Trans-Pacific service early in<br />
1948 with the Skymaster aircraft already being operated on its ' behalf<br />
by Australian National Airways over the route. Arrangements were<br />
being made for orders to be placed for four Solent flying boats for<br />
Tasman Empire Airways.<br />
Council reviewed the fare on the air service between New Zealandand<br />
Australia and agreed that certain reductions should be made.<br />
Council received a report from the Australian delegation regarding<br />
the operation of regional services from Australia in the area to Fiji<br />
and West 1700 E. Regional services operated by New Zealand were<br />
still in the hands of the Royal New Zealand Air Force ' but it was<br />
expected that by 1st October, 1947, those services would be taken over<br />
by New Zealand National Airways Corporation.<br />
The rival claims of Nadi and Nausori as Fiji's international airport<br />
had proved a problem. A commission of the interested governments<br />
had been appointed to investigate the matter in Fiji in February,<br />
1948.<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 117, page 3; No. 122, page<br />
INTERNAL ROUTES-INTRA-STATE SERVICES, PREMIERS<br />
DISCUSS.<br />
On 21st August, 1947, the conference of Commonwealth and State<br />
Ministers considered a submission by the Minister for Civil Aviation<br />
( Mr. Drakeford) requesting the State to consider afresh the question<br />
of expressly authorizing the Commonwealth instrumentality to engage<br />
in intra-state aviation on a permanent basis and asked those States<br />
that were unwilling to transfer full powers to authorize Commonwealth<br />
airlines to operate intra-state services under the same conditions<br />
as private operators. The Premiers explained the position in<br />
their respective States, but no agreement was reached on the proposal.<br />
REVIEW OF OPERATIONS, 1946-47.<br />
On 28th August, 1947, Mr. Drakeford said that in 1946-47 Australian<br />
airlines did record business.<br />
Passengers increased by almost 70 per cent. on 1945-46, while<br />
freight carried increased by 145 per cent. On internal air transport<br />
services 860,111 passengers were carried, nearly nine times the 1938-39<br />
total of 99,511. Total weight of freight carried was 12,247 tons, comnared<br />
with 693 tons in 1938-39. </p>
<p>BRITISII1-AUSTRALIA SERVICE---QANTAS, AGREEMENT.<br />
DIRECTORS.<br />
On 5th September, 1947, Mr. Drakeford announced that Messrs.<br />
A. R. McComb and D. MceVey had been appointed members of the<br />
board of directors of Qantas Empire Airways Ltd.<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 128, page 26.)<br />
WAR CASUALTIES.<br />
ROYAL AUSTRALIAN AIR FORCE.<br />
On 11th August, 1947, the Minister for Air ( Mr. Drakeford) said<br />
that the latest Royal Australian Air Force casualty list, containing the<br />
. names of seven personnel formerly reported missing and now presumed<br />
dead, would be one of the last of its kind. Only sixteen more cases of<br />
missing remained to be cleared up.<br />
PRIMARY INDUSTRIES.<br />
DAIRY INDUSTRY-MILK, STATES CONTROL.<br />
On 12th August, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
" I have communicated with the State Premiers asking them t,<br />
resume control of mnilk prices from 1st October, 1947.<br />
" In October, 1945, the Commonwealth provided producers with ; i<br />
guarantee of subsidy and prices. This afforded a stability to producers'<br />
returns during a difficult transitional period in. the industry<br />
and prevented increases in retail prices. In addition, special paymentls<br />
hlave been made to producers who experienced adverse seasonal conditions<br />
at various times. The total cost of maintaining stable retail prices<br />
in the last two years approximated œ 4,500,000.<br />
The sudden reineval of a subsidy of this niagnititlde ight cause al<br />
appreciable increase in the price of milk, which would be undesirabl<br />
not only because of the effect on the cost of living but also because it<br />
might reduce consumption of ai highly nutritional food. The Government<br />
has decided to continue a modified subsidy scheme to be operated<br />
by the States. The amount of subsidy available will be calculated at<br />
-4d. a gallon on milk consumed in metropolitan arias during the six offseason<br />
months of the year, and in country areas now receiving subsidy<br />
at two-thirds of present rates ( excluding drought relief). Present<br />
subsidy rate; vary considerably according to State locality and period<br />
of the year, but the new scheme represents overall a subsidy of about<br />
two-thirds of the old scale.<br />
" The States will not be required to distribute the subsidy on any<br />
particular basis but can choose their own methods. The -only conditions<br />
are that the subsidy will be used for the benefit of consumers<br />
of whole milk and that a satisfactory control of prices operate in area'<br />
receiving the benefit of subsidy. The arrangement will operate for<br />
twelve months. </p>
<p>in all State.-, except Tasmania. milk buards have been established<br />
with authority to control the supply, distribution and price of milk<br />
in metropolitan areas. The action now taken will restore to those<br />
authorities their previous powers, and give the States an appreciable<br />
subsidy to cushion the effect of any price rises that may be necessary<br />
; s a result of the transition from Commonwealth to State control. As<br />
the amount of subsidy will be less than formerly, some price increases<br />
nay be necessary but the extent and duration of any price increases<br />
will depend on the method by which the subsidy is used by the States.<br />
The change-over has been timed to coincide with the ' flush' season<br />
in most States. v. hen siubs-idy payments are usually at the lowest<br />
levels." ( For earlier references, please see No. 111, page 8; No. 123, page 4.)<br />
DAIRY INDUSTRY-CREAM CONTROL, RE-IMPOSITION.<br />
On 14th August, 1947, the Minister for Agriculture ( Mr. Pollard)<br />
announced that a new Cream ( Disposal and UTTe) Order vould operate<br />
o( n 1st September, 1947.<br />
Under the new order, cream might be used only for the manufacture<br />
of butter and cheese at a registered or licensed dairy factory, at the<br />
farm where the cream was produced or under the authority of and in<br />
accordance with the terms and conditions of a permit. The use of<br />
cream for pastry cook and similar purposes would cease. Hospitals<br />
and like institutions and manufacturers of ice-cream should apply for<br />
a permit to obtain cream. Issue of permits to sick persons would be<br />
confined to persons suffering from duodenal or peptic ulcer, ulcerative<br />
colitis, or typhoid fever or other prolonged fevers, or active pulmonary<br />
tuberculosis. The Commonwealth Government had in mind an extra 3,000 to<br />
5,000 tons of butter for shipment to Britain and a quick survey of the<br />
quantities of cream being sold for use as such indicated that that<br />
quantity would be available if the public co-operated and did not seek<br />
ways and means of circumventing the restriction on the disposal and<br />
use of cream. ( For earlier references, please see No. 120, page<br />
POULTRY INDUSTRY-EGG CONTROL.<br />
On 15th August, 1947, Mr. Chifley said-<br />
" Extension of the period of Commonwealth control over eggs<br />
to 31st December, 1947, was approved in May, 1947, to facilitate the<br />
formation of an Australian-wide Egg Marketing Organization.<br />
" The Minister for Agriculture ( Mr. Pollard) reported to Cabinet<br />
to-day on recent discussions of the Australian Agricultural Council.<br />
Cabinet approved the distribution of surplus funds resulting from the<br />
operations of the Commonwealth Egg Control scheme up to 30th June,<br />
1947, to the States, in the ratio in which egg producers in the various<br />
States have contributed them, for the purpose of investment in the<br />
proposed Aus. tralian Egg Equalization Committee Ltd. to provide the </p>
<p>margin of security necessary to finance the scheme; in the event of no<br />
Australian-wide company being formed the distribution of these funds<br />
to be further considered; and providing the respective State Egg<br />
Marketing Board with some working capital and subject to a careful<br />
review of the financial position the sum of œ 100,000 is named for this<br />
purpose. Cabinet also approved the transfer of any profit made by the<br />
Controller of Egg Supplies during the period 1st July-31st December,<br />
1947, to such authority ( Australian Egg Equalization Committee Ltd.)<br />
or authorities ( State Egg Boards) which have the responsibility for<br />
the marketing of Australian egg production subject to such funds being<br />
utilized for the maintenance of egg prices between January and June,<br />
1948. If the transfer is to be made to State Egg Boards the funds are<br />
to be allocated on the basis of production for the period 1st July-31st<br />
December, 1947.<br />
Cabinet also approved of the preparation of a bill to be submitted<br />
to the Federal Parliamentary Labour Party to establish an Australian<br />
Egg Board with powers to control exports, to buy and sell eggs and<br />
to ensure that the long term contract with the British Government is<br />
observed." ( For earlier references, please see No. 116, page 6.)<br />
POWER ALCOHOL DISTILLERIES.<br />
On 16th August, 1947, Mr. Chifley said-<br />
Cabinet to-day considered a report by the Cabinet sub-committee<br />
on secondary industries on negotiations between the Commonwealth<br />
Government and the Colonial Sugar Refining Co. Ltd. concerning<br />
grain alcohol distilleries.<br />
Cabinet approved of an agreement with the Colonial Sugar<br />
Refining Co. Ltd. for the purchase of certain plant at Cowra, New<br />
South Wales, and Warracknabeal, Victoria.<br />
" Cabinet authorized the Secondary Industries Commission to<br />
arrange for the utilization by industry of land, buildings and remaining<br />
plant and equipment at the Cowra; Warracknabeal; Wallaroo, South<br />
Australia; and Collie, Western Australia, distilleries through the Commonwealth<br />
Disposals Commission, the Contract Board and the<br />
Department of the Interior.<br />
EXPORTS TO BRITAIN-POULTRY.<br />
On 19th August, 1947, Mr. Pollard said-<br />
Australia will export œ A. 1,000,000' s worth of frozen poultry to<br />
Britain in 1947. In the first seven months of 1947 the entire 1946<br />
figure has been more than doubled, with 1,455 tons of -boiler fowls,<br />
587 tons of chickens, 446 tons of turkeys, 104 tons of ducks, totalling<br />
2,592 tons valued at œ A. 673,305. Allowing for the seasonal drop in<br />
the next three months, the estimate for the twelve months is 4,000<br />
tons." </p>
<p>CANNED FRUITS.<br />
On 25th August, 1947, Mr. Pollard said-<br />
" About 1,000,000 cases of canned fruits have been shipped by the<br />
Australian Canned Fruits Board to Britain from the 1946-47 pack,<br />
leaving 500,000 cases yet to be shipped. Australia had set aside the<br />
maximum quota of canned fruits for Britain during the current year.<br />
From the 1945-46 pack, shipments to the Ministry of Food were 977,300<br />
cases." GIFTS.<br />
On 26th August, 1947, the Postmaster-General ( Senator Cameron)<br />
said that food parcels which proved to be undeliverable in Britain were<br />
shipped back to Australia and returned to the senders. It had been<br />
agreed with the British Post Office that, in regard to future postings<br />
of gift parcels containing only foodstuffs or soap, those which proved<br />
to be undelivera'ble would be treated as abandoned parcels and the<br />
contents distributed to the best advantage.<br />
TALLOW.<br />
On 29th August, 1947, Mr. Pollard said-<br />
Approval has been given for the export to Britain of 250 tons of<br />
edible beef tallow and 250 tons of edible mutton tallow. This is in<br />
addition to shipments of oleo sterine, an edible fat, obtained in the<br />
manufacture of industrial margarine, which has been exported freely<br />
to Britain." RABBIT SKINS.<br />
On 22nd August, 1947, Mr. Pollard said that rabbit skin exports<br />
in 1946-47 were approximately three times greater in weight and<br />
fourteen times greater in value than in 1938-39. Exports of rabbit<br />
careases in 1947 would exceed pre-war figures.<br />
CANNED MEAT.<br />
On 25th August, 1947, Mr. Pollard said that nearly 40,000 tons of<br />
canned meat would be exported during 1947. The total included 25,000<br />
tons under contract to the British Ministry of Food, 1,500 tons supplied<br />
to the Red Cross and other relief organizations, 1,300 tons likely to be<br />
required for iil. rnuational relief, and 1,059 tons required for service use.<br />
leaving an estimated 11,000 tons for private export. The figures did<br />
not include canned meat sent in gift parcels to Britain, estimated at<br />
1,000 tons. The overall ceiling permitted by the Rationing Commission<br />
for canned meat production for 1947 was about 48,000 tons. The<br />
quantity left for local trade would be about 10,000 tons. Pre-war<br />
production of canned meat in Australia had never reached a third of<br />
the 1947 estimated total. </p>
<p>24<br />
SUGAR AGREEMENT, REVISION.<br />
On 4th September, 1947, Mr. Chifley said-<br />
The Commonwealth Government has agreed in principle to the<br />
request recently made by the sugar industry for a variation in the<br />
Sugar Agreement to enable the wholesale price of sugar to be increased<br />
by œ 4 2s. 8d. a ton ( id. per lb. retail).<br />
" I have consulted with the Premier of Queensland ( Mr. Hanlon)<br />
regarding the matter and we agreed to recommend to the respective<br />
Parliamentary Labour Parties that legislation be introduced for this<br />
purpose. " The retail price of sugar in Australia has existed at 4d. a 1b.<br />
, apital cities since 1933, despite greatly increased costs of production<br />
in recent years. The increase in price will enable these increased costs<br />
to be met and will assist in rehabilitating the industry whose pro-<br />
, luction has fallen to low levels and whose capital equipment has greatly<br />
depreciated during the war.<br />
The increase in the wholesale price of sugar will allow retailers<br />
in additional 10s. 8d. a ton and wholesalers an additional Is. Sd. a ton<br />
profit. The increase in price will not take place until the Sugar Agreement<br />
has been signed between the two Governments and the Commonwealth<br />
Parliament has passed an amending Sugar Agreement Act.<br />
" The temporary shipping freight subsidy on sugar will be with-<br />
Irawn when the increased price come into operation.<br />
There are other aspects concerning which I will have to consult<br />
with Mr. Hanlon before the revised agreement is finalized."<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 112, page<br />
HOUSING.<br />
COMMONWEALTH-STATES AGREEMENT-COSTS AND<br />
STANDARDS.<br />
On 13th August, 1947, the Minister for Housing ( Mr. Lommon)<br />
released details of the report on State housing authority standards and<br />
methods prepared by the Deputy Director of Housing ( Mr. L. P. D.<br />
O'Connor), who undertook the investigation as a result of a decision by<br />
the Premiers Conference that an official should confer with each State<br />
to ascertain whether helpful suggestions of mutual benefit could be<br />
made to reduce costs of dwellings erected under the Commonwealth-<br />
States Housing Agreement. Mr. O'Connor had found that the main<br />
reasons for the present increased costs of Government sponsored housing<br />
iver pre-war were-<br />
Shortages of building materials, increased labour, increased costs of material!.<br />
reduced productivity of labour, time taken to complete dwellings, greater overhead,<br />
larger profits and lack of competition among contractor-s. </p>
<p>Mr. O'Connor suggested a number of economies in the construction<br />
practices of the States, the chief being-<br />
Reduction ini number of plan types, use of brick-on-edge for the inner leai<br />
' o external walls and for internal partitions, construction of brick veneer<br />
dwellings, . reduction in size of timber structural meimbcrs and elimination ( r<br />
front fences and side fences to building line.<br />
Dealing with disparities between the States in building costs of<br />
government-sponsored housing, Mr. O'Connor found that costs per<br />
square for an 1,100 square feet single-brick dwelling given for June.<br />
1947, by State housing authorities were-<br />
Sydney, œ 140; Melbourne, œ 132; Brisbane, œ 131; Adelaide. œ 110; Perth.<br />
Hobart, œ 112 ( timber-no brick dwellings being erected).<br />
The value of suggested economies according to States ranged downwards<br />
from œ 157 in regard to brick dwellings and from œ 112 downwards<br />
in regard to timber. Economies suggested by the Commonwealth to<br />
the States, if applied to the programme under the Commonwealth-<br />
States Housing Agreement for 1947-48 would, it was estimated, represent<br />
a saving of œ 1,400,000. The report stressed the need for constructing<br />
houses in large estates and letting contracts where possiblb<br />
for 500 houses at a time.<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 118, page 36; No. 122, page 28.)<br />
COMMONWEALTH-STATES AGREEMENT-COSTS AND<br />
STANDARDS, PREMIERS CONFERENCE DECISION.<br />
On 21st August, 1947, the conference of Commonwealth and State<br />
Ministers decided-<br />
That conference notes that clause 4 of the Commonwealth and<br />
* States Housing Agreement 1945 has been implemented by the adoption<br />
of the standards agreed on at the February, 1947 conference of Comrmonwealth<br />
and State officers.<br />
Conference notes receipt of report on economies by Mr. L. P. D.<br />
O'Connor and desires the matter reviewed in detail at the annual conference<br />
of housing officers in January, 1948. Meantime, all States<br />
undertake to carry out to the fullest extent practicable, the economies<br />
uggested in that report." RECONSTRUCTION.<br />
TRADE AND EMPLOYMENT-PREPARATORY<br />
CONFERENCE, AUSTRALIAN DELEGATION.<br />
On 13th August, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
My attention has been drawn to a number of sta. tenents on whar<br />
the Australian Government has decided or may be expected to decide<br />
in the course of its consideration of the trade negotiations now proceding<br />
at Geneva. The position in regard to these negotiations is quite<br />
fluid. They have not yet reached the stage where it is practicable<br />
to assess the balance of possible trade benefits and concessions. </p>
<p>The Cabinet sub-committee is keeping in constant touch with the<br />
progress of the negotiations but in the circumstances has not yet formed<br />
even a tentative view as to possible recommendations to the Government.<br />
With regard to the negotiations with the United States, the Australian<br />
delegation, ha. s, in view of the offer of a reduction in the wool<br />
duty, been authorized to re-open negotiations. The Australian delegation<br />
has also been asked to furnish further information regarding<br />
the offers and responses on a number of other comnmodities. This has<br />
not yet been received.<br />
In the circinistuanes. any statements regarding the attitude of<br />
the Government in respect of tariff offers and responses should be<br />
treated with lcnrion. When possible the Government will make an<br />
official annomi-o cement in the -matter."<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 124, page 5; No. 125, page 9; No. 126,<br />
page 20; No. 127, page 3.)<br />
GOVERNMENT'S PLANS-REGIONAL DEVELOPMENT,<br />
SNOWY RIVER REPORT.<br />
On 15th August, 1947, the Minister for Works ( Mr. Lemmon)<br />
released a report on the diversion of Snowy River. Mr. Lemmon<br />
said-Shortages of power exist in New South Wales and Victoria, and<br />
there is a need to provide for the rapidly increasing demand brought<br />
about by continuous industrial development. It could be met by exploiting<br />
the full potentialities of the . Snowy River and the costless reservoir<br />
, f snow which forms its source. If developed to its maximum, power<br />
for Victorian and New South Wales requirements can be ensured for<br />
many years to come, as well as furnishing water for an extension to<br />
r-xisting irrigation systems. Diversion of black coal to other States for<br />
general industrial purposes would then be possible.<br />
Fu! l power development is possible only if the Snowy River is<br />
diverted initially to the head waters of the Murray River, but the<br />
report points out. that it would be possible, if considered -advisable, to<br />
divert the water again from the lower Murray to the Murrumbidgee<br />
Valley for irrigation purposes.<br />
If this unique natural asset is developed to its fullest advantage,<br />
300,000 acres of intensely irrigated land can be served from the Snowy<br />
River, from which a gross annual return in the value of foodstuffs of<br />
at least œ 10,000,000 a year could be expected and, in addition, ultimately<br />
750.000 horse-power produced. If, on the other hand, the<br />
waters be diverted direct to the Murrumbidgee River the same amount<br />
of irrigation can be undertaken, but the power developed would be<br />
at least 500,000 horse-power less. To make up this power about<br />
1,300,000 tons of additional coal will have to be mined annually.<br />
" From a commercial viewpoint the scheme would show profits of<br />
8 per cent. after providing for working expenses and depreciation.<br />
Thiø would he the expected dividend return if the scheme were to be </p>
<p>operated for profit, and would be a far higher yield than that shown<br />
by similar schemes run by utility companies here and overseas.<br />
" The estimated cost of the Murray River diversion scheme, which<br />
includes a series of dams on the various tributary streams and on the<br />
Snowy and Murrumbidgee Rivers, with a tunnel 30 miles long under<br />
the Australian Alps to connect the Snowy with the Murray, and the<br />
electricity generating stations and power lines to Melbourne and Sydney<br />
with all equipment, may ultimately reach œ 65,000,000.<br />
On 20th August, 1947, the conference of Commonwealth and State<br />
Ministers decided-<br />
That a committee be constituted, consisting of two representatives<br />
from the Commonwealth and two each from the . States of New South<br />
Wales and Victoria, with power to co-opt such other assistance as<br />
may be needed from the three authorities, with a view to aaking a<br />
complete detailed investigation, the committee to report to a Premiers<br />
Conference as early as possible, but not later than twelve months hence."<br />
" I hope that the States will, at least, agree to proceed inumediately<br />
with the detailed investigation recommended. I feel that the report is<br />
so conclusive that it may well be accepted as proving the general<br />
feasibility and economy of the scheme, and that action may proceed<br />
immediately towards the diversion of the Snowy River to the Murray<br />
Valley, exploiting the waters to their maximum power capacity, without<br />
affecting the possibility of using them either in the Murray or Murrumhidgee<br />
Valleys to their fullest irrigation value."<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 102, page 15; No. 106, page 33; No. 115,<br />
page 21.)<br />
NEW GUINEA.<br />
WORKS MINISTER'S VISIT.<br />
On 14th August, 1947, the Minister for Work.-: anl Illon-ing ( Mr.<br />
Lemmon) announced that he would visit New Guine and Papua from<br />
28th August, 1947, to 9th September, 1947, acconmpanied by the<br />
Director-General of Works ( Mr. L. F. Loder). . lis ldepartment was<br />
preparing a major works programme in the territories. Many larg.<br />
works carried out by Allied forces during the war had been designed<br />
to last only a few years. The Commonwealth Governmiint desired to<br />
maintain a number of installations as future assets, having in mind<br />
defence requirements and the development of the territories.<br />
BRITAIN.<br />
FINANCIAL POLICY-DOLLAR IMPORTS.<br />
On 15th August, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Clifley) said-<br />
A close watch is being kept by the Australian Government on all<br />
dollar imports, both United States and Canadian. The subject of<br />
sterling balances at London is being kept continuously under review.<br />
The problems facing Britain have been constantly discussed by<br />
the British Chancellor of the Exchequer ( Dr. Dalton) and myself and<br />
by Dr. Dalton and the other Dominion Treasurers for over twelve<br />
months." </p>
<p>FINANCIAL POLICY-CABINET DEC1. SONS.<br />
On 15th August, 1947, Mr. Chifley said--<br />
Cabinet to-night surveyed the economic position as it affects the:<br />
United Kingdom and the position regarding dollar imports by Australia<br />
and Australia's sterling balances at London.<br />
Cabinet decided that there should be a severe rationing of thl:<br />
use of dollars for travel purposes and directed that a review be. made<br />
of dollar expenditure on tobacco, motion pictures, and all imports of<br />
a less essential character and a re-examination of the newsprint<br />
importations. Cabinet also decided that there should be an overall reduction<br />
in petrol consumption to save 4,250,000 gallons a month. The reduction<br />
will be applied to private users to effect a 20 per cent. to 25 per<br />
r. ent. reduction in their ration, a reduction of 20 per cent. to 25 per<br />
i: ent. in the ration of private business users, a 20 per cent. to 25 per<br />
t: cnt. reduction in the ration for pleasure boats and a 10 per cent.<br />
reduction in the ration for commercial users."<br />
On 22nd August, 1947, Mr. Chifley said-<br />
Instructions have been issued to the Commonwealth Bank t,<br />
impose severe restrictions on dollars advanced to all travellers.<br />
The film industry has been asked to meet the Commonwealth<br />
( overnment on 26th August, 1947.<br />
I have been in communication with the newsprint pool authoritie<br />
and on 25th August, 1947, I will have a full review of newsprint<br />
imports fron the Customs Department.<br />
" The Customs Department will present a full review of all dollar<br />
imports to Australia, including tobacco.<br />
" There is no need for the British Government to make any specific<br />
requests for restrictions on dollar imports because the Australian<br />
Government has always kept a reasonable check on the use of dollars.<br />
This check will now be very severe."<br />
On 2nd September, 1947, Mr. Chifley said-<br />
Following consideration -of the latest develupments in the dollar<br />
crisis, Cabinet to-day decided on the following measures to reduce<br />
Australia's dollar expenditure.<br />
Motor Cha'sis.-A cut of the order of 20 per cent. is to be made<br />
in the number of chassis approved for importation during 194S as<br />
:' gainst the number approved for importation during 1947. The whole<br />
of this cut will be applied in the field of passenger car chassis and no<br />
reduction will be made in the chassis quotas for commercial vehicles.<br />
The detailed application of the cut to the various types of passenger<br />
car chassis is to be examined by an Inter'-departmental Committee on<br />
which the trade will be represented. The most severe restrictions will be<br />
imposed on chassis for cars in the higher price ranges with possible totnl<br />
exclusion of certain makes.<br />
Tobacco.-Import licences for American tobacco leaf are to Ix<br />
rut by 20 per cent. It is hoped that the reduction in releases of manufactured<br />
tobhcco and cigarettes will be limited to about 10 per cent. </p>
<p>Petrol.-Cuts were announced following the meeting of Cabinet on<br />
August, 1947, which were designed to achieve a saving of 10 to<br />
12 per cent. in current consumption. No further cuts are contemplated<br />
for the time being.<br />
Newsprint.-A reduction of the order of 30 per cent. is to he mad',<br />
in newsprint import programmes.<br />
Textiles.-Except for a few lines which are still in acute short<br />
supply, the issue of licences for the importation of textiles from dollar<br />
sources was temporarily suspended at the end of May, 1947. Cabinet<br />
decided that this policy should be continued for the time being pending<br />
complction of a comprehensive review of the supply position by the<br />
Rationing Commission.<br />
Aircraft.-Apart from aircraft already on order, no further purrbases<br />
of aircraft involving dollar expenditure will be authorized.<br />
Expenditure of dollars on spare parts for aircraft will also le closely<br />
supervised. Capital E'qipul i Me tad Ja-M. Ule-rials.-Machinery and other<br />
items of capital equipment are regarded as being in the highest category<br />
of priority and dollars will be made available to meet the essential<br />
requirements of Australian industry. In view of the present dollar<br />
crisis,: however, manufacturers will be expected to co-operate by<br />
exploring fully the possibilities of obtaining machinery from other<br />
-ources before they seek to import machinery involving dollar expenditure.<br />
The present method of dealing with applications for licences<br />
to import goods of this class is to be reviewed by an Inter-departmental<br />
(' onimittee. The committee will also examine the principles to be<br />
: dopted in dealing witl applications for licences to import raw materials<br />
from dollar sources of supply.<br />
Miscellhrncon Imports.-Aplart from the major items, Cabinet<br />
endorsed recommniendations by the Minister for Customs ( Senator<br />
( onrtice) for restrictions on a wide range of miscellaneous imports<br />
from the dollar area in accordance with the general objective of reducing<br />
. dollar expenditure on imports to the essential minimum.<br />
Film Re. utlti:' s.-Consideration is being given to the bemt mean.<br />
of reducing rlh dollar expenditure involved in remittances of film<br />
royalties to the extent of about 30 per cent.<br />
Travel EX: penditure.-Drastic restrictions wvill be imposed on the<br />
ount of dollars made available for personal travel and the allowance<br />
for businessmen will also be substantially reduced. As a corollary<br />
. further restrictions will be imposed on travellers taking out jewellery<br />
n. d other valuables as part of their personal effects.<br />
Remittances by Visiting Entertainers, Artists. cond the like.-Up<br />
to the present visiting entertainers and artists have been allowed to<br />
remit their net earnings in Australia without restriction. It is no<br />
longer possible to continue this policy and the Exchange Control<br />
iauthorities have been instructed to take steps to limit severely the<br />
. amount of. such remittances where dollars are involved." </p>
<p>On 4th September, 1947, the Minister for Customs ( Senator<br />
Courtice) announced the imposition of further restrictions on imports<br />
of goods from dollar areas. In future, licences would not be granted<br />
to import the following goods from countries in the dollar aarea:-<br />
Axes, dictating machines, human hair clipping machines, electric household<br />
ironing machines, clothes washing machines, computor mechanisms for use in<br />
the manufacture of petrol pumps, electric stoves, oil or spirit heating and<br />
pressure lamps, piece goods for dress or furnishing purposes, corsets, crown<br />
seals, preparations for use in the manufacture of cordials, wooden blind rollers,<br />
preparations for use in the manufacture of cosmetics, building boards, golf<br />
club shafts, ice hockey-skates, lacrosse racquets, paper of the following types:-<br />
carbon, cartridge, cellophane for wrapping tobacco manufactures, copying. cover<br />
indp ressings, duplicating, gummed sheets and rolls, marble and foil, vegetable<br />
parchment, roofing and sheathing, surface coated and box makcrs, fruit wrapping,<br />
paper hangings and wall paper, paper for use in the manufacture of toilet<br />
paper, carton and container boards, cigarette papers, fashion plates and books,<br />
paper patterns except master patterns, fountain pens, rime rcnorders, rubber<br />
gloves, rubber tyres and tubes, musical instruments and acces: orie. s fluorescent<br />
lamp materials for use in advertising signs. plastic pliable sheeting, pliofilm,<br />
home kinematographs, spectacles and spectacle frames, french chalks ; ind other<br />
preparations of steatite.<br />
In addition, imports of the following conmmodities ,. vould bhe amdmitted<br />
in reduced quantities:-<br />
Canned fish; radio receiving valves; recording instruments, pyrolneters and<br />
thermometers; chicle; proprietary medicines and raw materials for the manufacture<br />
of drugs and chemicals; miscellaneous manufactures of metal; hickory<br />
axe and tool handles; rubber thread for the manufacture of golf balls; books of<br />
all kinds; tissue paper for paper patterns: writing and printing paper;<br />
artificial teeth; cameras; cartridges; photo flash lamps; unrefined fish oils.<br />
The review of goods imported from dollar areas ww as b( in conltillued<br />
and it might be necessary to impose restrictions on Iheim portation of<br />
other commodities in the near future.<br />
In regard to textiles, the present licensing treatment would 1b continued<br />
and only imports of essential utility types of cotton piece goods<br />
would be permitted. It had been decided to undertake a review of all<br />
outstanding licences issued before 27th May, 1947, for the importation<br />
of textiles from the United States, Canada and other dollar areas.<br />
In addition, outstanding licences for imports from dollar : trceas of.<br />
musical instruments and accessories, cigarette paprs indl elwtrii humnan<br />
hair clipping machines must be submitted for review.<br />
FINANCIAL POLICY-SALE OF GOLD.<br />
On 5th September, 1947. Mr. Chifley said-<br />
Australia has sold 150,000 ounces of gold to the United Kingdom.<br />
" I recall that during the depression Australia had to part with<br />
practically the whole of her gold reserves to enable her to meet her<br />
overseas obligations. During recent years the Commonwealth Bank<br />
commenced rebuilding a gold reserve by purchasing and holding current<br />
production. The Government and the Commonwealth Bank would have liked<br />
to continue the policy of gradually rebuilding Australia's gold reserve </p>
<p>but the current dollar situation is so serious that it has been decided for<br />
the time being to sell current gold production to the United Kingdom as<br />
a special measure of assistance in her present difficulties<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 123, page 19; No. 126, page 31;<br />
No. 128, page 34.)<br />
FINANCIAL POLICY-PRIME MINISTER'S SPEECH.<br />
On 20th August, 1947, Mr. Chifley said*-<br />
We are living in a world that is in economic difficulties. I have<br />
been very anxious about the general world economic position for some<br />
years but the cituation lins deteriorated more rapidly than was expected.<br />
I told you yesterday in some detail about the economic position of the<br />
United Kingdom. We must not attempt to delude ourselves that, if<br />
economic difficulties occur in Britain and perhaps eventually in the<br />
United States, Australia will not be affected. That would be a sheer<br />
and complete delusion. The position overseas to-day is that the United<br />
States has been exporting, in terms of values, a vastly greater quantity<br />
of goods than it has been importing. Britain made the Anglo-American<br />
Loan Agreement, which bound it particularly in regard to the convertibility<br />
of sterling balances, in the hope that the American loan money<br />
would carry it on until 1950, by which time there would have been a<br />
large measure of rehabilitation in Europe and the British export trade<br />
would have been built up in hard currency countries as well as in<br />
sterling countries.<br />
A numiber of things have happened. First-a thing which I have<br />
always feared-in a world of rising prices in which people believe that<br />
some degree of inflation is desirable, the money that Britain borrowed<br />
from the United States is not able to bring in the quantity of goods that<br />
Britain expected. I think the British Prime Minister ( Mr. Attlee) said<br />
that instead of getting 100 per cent. volume his country has been<br />
receiving only 60 per cent. Associated with that fall in estimated<br />
production have been certain internal factors in the shape of unforseeable<br />
difficulties due to flood and cold.<br />
The rehabilitation of Europe has not progressed as the world<br />
hoped. In Europe to-day there is utter misery which must be unparalleled<br />
in the history of the world. At present the most strenuous efforts<br />
are being made to find some solution of this grave problem. It is<br />
becoming more and more apparent that we cannot have a prosperous<br />
Europe without a prosperous Germany, whatever our feelings in regard<br />
to Germany might be. One result of this disastrous situation is that<br />
the export market in Europe has not been restored because the countries<br />
of Europe have not the money with which to pay for exports. The<br />
dollar position has become more acute every day, particularly during<br />
the last few weeks-indeed, during the last few days. One of the main<br />
causes of this rapid deterioration in the situation is the problem of the<br />
At n cllnfrociic of Comnnmonwenlth und State Ministers. </p>
<p>convertibility of sterling, but there arc other factors with which I<br />
do not propose to deal now. Because of the difficulty of converting<br />
sterling currency some of the South American countries and certain<br />
Scandinavian countries are experiencing grave difficulties.<br />
The position of Britain, and to a lesser degree, the position of<br />
Canada, in regard to the dollar position has also deteriorated very<br />
considerably. I mention these matters to give you some idea of the<br />
present world situation, and without violating any confidences repos.:: i<br />
in me. Another factor to be considered is the large balances held in<br />
Britain by a number of countries, including Australia. The Australian<br />
balance is, of course, very small compared with those held by India.<br />
Egypt and even by Ireland. I know that many of us would prefer<br />
to live in a world of our own, but we cannot. My Government realizethat<br />
this difficulty cannot be cured in a day, but it may be possible to<br />
ameliorate the consequences of the developments.<br />
One of the immediate effects on Australia will be a serious curtailnient<br />
of imports, and that curtailment will apply not only to import<br />
from dollar countries, including Canada, but also, to some degree, to<br />
imports from sterling countries. However, if everyone plays the game.<br />
and works the right way I believe that the economy of this country is<br />
geared that it will be able to withstand the economic repercussions. Of<br />
course, I emphasize that the serious developments I have outlined may<br />
not eventuate, but we must realize that we shall probably have to go<br />
without many of the imports we had hoped to receive. For that reason.<br />
L wish ' to play safe' in the plans we are making for the immediate<br />
future. 1 warn conference that shniold these developments eventuate<br />
it will be absolutely impossible for us to continue as we have in the past.<br />
" At the same time, I do not want anyone to go away with the<br />
impression that I do not firmly believe in the future of Australia.<br />
With prcper determination on the part of the governments and pttopli<br />
of Australia, I am sanguine that there will be a vast expansion. r<br />
may be altered for a while, but I have a deep-rooted confidence-shared<br />
by industrialists and husiinessmen, nanv of whom a re not of myv<br />
political faith-that Australia can obtain maxiimum production and<br />
economic staibilit MERCANTILE MARINE.<br />
SAFETY AT SEA.<br />
On 15tlI August, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
" In 1929, a conference on safety of life at sea was held at London<br />
and Australia ratified the resulting convention after amending ' th!.<br />
Navigation Act and regulations to conform to its provisions. The<br />
British Government, in view of recent war experiences, proposes to h ld<br />
a conference at London in 1948.<br />
" Cabinet decided to-day to accept the invitation antd send a delegition<br />
consisting of two technical officers from the Department of Shipiping<br />
( one experienced in navigational problems and the other in marine </p>
<p>engineering problems), and two advisers, one nominated by Aust ' ralian<br />
shipowners and one nominated by the Australasian Council of Trade<br />
Unions CANBERRA. HOUSING.<br />
On 15th August, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
" The Minister for the Interior ( Mr. Johnson) reported to Cabinet<br />
to-dayv that a deputation had waited on him requesting an amendment<br />
to the present policy of allocation of housing at Canberra to permit of<br />
an allotment to persons not in Government employ. At present 1,445<br />
person are registcred for tenancies of whom 710 are public servants, 42.5<br />
are other Government employees, and 310 are persons not in Governmnent<br />
employ. AXbout 325 new houses are at present under construction<br />
and-the DepaFtment of Housing anticipates an acceleration of tho<br />
present building programme, probably 100 houses in the next six<br />
months, and ultimately reaching 300 to 500 h-ouses in a year.<br />
Cabinet approved of the allotment of a quota of one in each ten<br />
houses built in the twelve months from 1st September, 1947, to person<br />
not in Government employ, the quota to be reviewed at the end of the<br />
year. Fifty pcir cent, of the quota will be allotted to ex-servicemen"<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 110, page 59; No. 126, page<br />
EXTERNAL COMMUN ICAT IONS.<br />
TELE-COMMUNICATIONS-BROADCAST NEWS.<br />
On 15th August, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
" Cabinet decided. to-day that the Overseas Telecommunications<br />
Commission be authorized to undertake the reception in Australia of<br />
any overseas news broadcasts required by press agencies or other similar<br />
bodies. A uniform flat rate will be applied for this service irrespective<br />
( if whether the broadcasts emanate from a British Commonwealth or a<br />
foreign country. When transmission from Australia of news broadcasts<br />
on behalf of a press agency is required, the transmission will be effected<br />
by the Commission on a uniform flat rate charge whether to a British<br />
Commonwealth or-a foreign country"'.<br />
COPYRIGHT.<br />
MUSIC-PROPOSED LEGISLATION.<br />
On 15th Auiguist, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
Where copyright exists in a musical work, it is an infringement of<br />
cop) yright to give a public performance of the work except under licence<br />
from the owner of the copyright on terms agreed to by him.<br />
5691.-2 </p>
<p>" The Australian Performing Right Association has recently notified<br />
the Comnmonwealth Clothing Factory that, in respect of music<br />
rebroadcast to employees while at work, an annual licence will in<br />
future be required.<br />
" Under an award in 1938, the Australian Broadcasting Commission<br />
pays to A. P. IR. A. an annual sum of 6d. a listener's licence in respect<br />
of music broadcast from the national stations. The Federation of<br />
Commercial Broadcasting Stations pays to A. P. R. A. about the same<br />
amount. In effect, A. P. R. A. receives from the Australian broadcasting<br />
systems is. a listener's licence. This is greatly in excess of amounts paid<br />
to corresponding bodies in Britain, Canada and New Zealand. Negotiations<br />
to make a more satisfactory arrangement have been unsuccessful<br />
and no provision exists whereby A. P. R. A. can be coompelled to submit<br />
to arbitration the Copyright Act providing only for voluntary<br />
arbitration. Cabinet decided to-day that a sub-committee comprising Dr. Evatt,<br />
the Minister for Health ( Senator McKenna) and the Minister for<br />
Information ( Mr. Calwell) consider an amendment of the Copyright<br />
Act, for submission to the Federal Parliamentary Labour party, to provide<br />
in principle for the fixing, by compulsory arbitration in default<br />
of agreement of a single, all-Australian fee for the public performance<br />
of copyright musical work." TRANSPORT.<br />
COMMONWEALTH RAILWAYS-COMMISSIONER.<br />
Onl 15th August, 1947, thc Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
Cabinet decided to-day to extend for a further per'iod of twelve<br />
months from 7th November, 1947, the term of Mr. G. A. Gahan as<br />
Commissioner of Commonwealth Railways."<br />
TRANSITION.<br />
CONTROLS-FURTHER DILL PROPOSED.<br />
On 15th August, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
" The Defence ( Transitional Provisions) Act 1947 continues in<br />
operation until 31st December, 1947, about 59 sets of regulations. 61<br />
separate regulations in the General and Supplementary sets and<br />
orders made under regulations now resealed, a total of 130. A preliminary<br />
survey indicates that it will be poosible either to repeal or to<br />
allow to elapse before the end of the year about one-third of each class.<br />
However, it is probablc that all regulations of any significance in<br />
force in 1947 will need to have their effect carried forward in 1948.<br />
The general inflationary conditions present at the end of 1946 are not<br />
likely to have changed by the end of 1947, and control over economnic<br />
conditions generally will need to be continued. </p>
<p>Cabinet to-day approved of the preparation of bills dealing with<br />
dairy produce acquisition ( the setting up of an authority to deal with<br />
dairy produce purchased under contract by Britain, patriotic funds,<br />
enemy property, trading with the enemy and ship building.<br />
Cabinet approved the preparation of a bill to amend the Defence<br />
( Transitional Provisions) Act to provide for the repeal of as many<br />
as possible of regulations and orders which present circumstances suggest<br />
as unlikely to be required after the end of 1947 and to extend the<br />
life of the Act to cover until the 31st December, 1948-unleas earlier<br />
repealed-regulations and orders necessary to deal with the transition.<br />
period." ( For earlier references, please see No. 122, page<br />
WHEAT STABILIZATION SCHEME-.<br />
POST-WAR PLANS, EXTENSION.<br />
On 15th August, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
When the wheat stabilization plan was announced, it was stated<br />
that it would be reviewed from time to time with a view to extension<br />
beyond the original five years, the intention being to provide a permanent<br />
guarantee, subject to regular review and adjustment to give an<br />
assured price for a reasonable period ahead.<br />
Cabinet decided to-day that the period of the wheat stabilization<br />
plan be extended to seven years to the 1952-53 season with a guarantee<br />
of 5s. a bushel bulk, f. o. r. ports."<br />
( ror earlier references, please see No. 110, page 15; No. 116, page 13.)<br />
POST-WAR PLAN, PREMIERS CONFERENCE DECISION.<br />
On 21st August, 1947, the conference of Comnmonwealth and State<br />
Ministers decided-<br />
That Conference-Re-affirms its previous decision in respect of the need for a stabilization<br />
plan for the wheat industry.<br />
Endorses the decision to continue war-time powers for the 1947-49<br />
crop only.<br />
Recommends an early special meeting of Commonwealth and State<br />
Ministers for Agriculture for the purpose of working out a plan<br />
satisf actory to all Governments and the wheat industry; and<br />
recomnds that the wheat-growers be given an opportunity to submit<br />
their own proposals in writing and to present their views to.<br />
the Ministers." DROUGHT RELIEF-VICTORIA.<br />
On 15th August, 1947, Mr. Chifley said-<br />
Cabinet decided to-day that up to œ 50,000 be approved for drought<br />
relief to cereal growers in Victoria for the 1946-47 season on a œ, 1-for-<br />
œ 1l basis-with the Victorian Government. The Commonwealth assistance<br />
will be contingent on the State submitting a satisfactory relief<br />
plan." 5691.-3 </p>
<p>CONSTITUTION.<br />
AMENDMENT-PROPOSED REFERENDUM, PRICES.<br />
On 15th August, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
Cabinet decided to-night to recommend to the Federal Parliamentary<br />
Labour party that a referendum be taken to amend section 51 of<br />
the Constitution on prices and rents. Although a previous Premiers<br />
Conference agreed to endeavour to pass legislation which would be<br />
supplementary to the Commonwealth powers, certain States have found<br />
it impossible to pass legislation through their parliaments."<br />
INDIA.<br />
EXCHANGE OF HIGH COMMISSIONERS.<br />
On 15th August, 1947, the Minister for External Affairs ( Dr.<br />
Evatt) announced that it had been agreed between the Governments<br />
of Australia and of Pakistan that an exchange of High Conmmissioners<br />
would take place as soon as each government could make the necessary<br />
arrangements. An Australian diplomatic representative would be<br />
appointed to Pakistan with head-quarters at Karachi. Sir Iven<br />
Mackay would become High Commissioner for Australia in the Union<br />
of India with head-quarters at New Delhi.<br />
BANKING CONTROL.<br />
NATIQNALIZATION-PROPOSED LEGISLATION.<br />
On 16th August, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
Cabinet to-day authorized the Attorney-General ( Dr. Evatt) and<br />
myself to prepare legislation for submission to the Federal Parliamentary<br />
Labour party for the nationalization of banking, other than<br />
State banks, with proper protection for shareholders, depositors,<br />
borrowers and staff of private banks."<br />
NATIONALIZATION-PROPOSED LEGISLATION, BANK<br />
SHARES.<br />
On 19th August, 1947, Mr. Chifley said-<br />
" I refer to reported falls in the market value of somne bank shares<br />
to-day. These are entirely unwarranted, and shareholders -are entitled<br />
to be warned against propaganda or other statements tending to depreciate<br />
the value of their holdings.<br />
The Government desires to make it clear that it does not advise<br />
shareholders to sell, but in order to protect the interests of those shareholders<br />
who nevertheless wish to sell, the Government has arranged<br />
with the Commonwealth Bank to purchase any bank shares which<br />
holders are desirous of selling. The purchase price will be not less than<br />
that quoted on the Stock Exchange on Friday, 15th August, 1947."<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 97, page 21.) </p>
<p>ANTARCTI CA.<br />
EXPEDITION-CABINET DECISIONS.<br />
On 16th August, 1941, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
Cabinet to-day received a report on the progress of the Executive<br />
Planning Committee of the Australian Antarctic expedition for 1947-48.<br />
Cabinet approved the committee's recommendations as follows<br />
That scientific and meteorological stations be set up at Heard and Macquarie<br />
Islands during the forthcoming expedition and maintained for a period of at<br />
least five years.<br />
That a systematic reconnaissance of the coast of the Australian Antarctic<br />
Territory be carried out over a number of years by the Wyatt Earp with a<br />
view to establishing a permanent scientific station on the Antarctic Continent<br />
itself. That a ship be obtained, of much greater capacity than the Wyatt Earp<br />
and especially adapted for work in Antarctic conditions. The exact type of<br />
vessel required cannot be determined until further information is available as<br />
to the proposed lauding site."<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 126, page<br />
EXTERNAL AFFAIRS.<br />
DIPLOMATIC CADETS.<br />
On 19th August, 1947, the Minister for External Affairs ( Dr.<br />
Evatt) announced that his department -was recruiting a further batch<br />
of diplomatic staff cadets to undergo a two years' course of training<br />
at the School of Diplomatic Studies prior to appointment to the<br />
department. HIDES.<br />
CONTROL OF FOOTWEAR',-PREMIERS CONFERENCE<br />
DECISION.<br />
On 20th August, 1947, the conference of Commonwealth and State<br />
Ministers decided-<br />
That the Commonwealth should circulate copies of a draft bill<br />
for consideration by the State Parliaments, together with a statement<br />
setting out the principles on which Commonwealth control of footwear<br />
operated." LOAN COUNCIL.<br />
PROGRAMME FOR 1947-48.<br />
On 20thi August, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
The principal business considered by the Loan Council to-day<br />
was the loan programmes of the Commonwealth and the -States for the<br />
year 1947-48.<br />
The Loan Council had before it the report of the Co-ordinator-<br />
General of Works ( Mr. Hoy) and endorsed the programme of works<br />
submitted by Mr. Hoy, but decided to limit the borrowing to 75 per'<br />
cent, of the programme, the borrowing programme to be reveiwed in<br />
January, 1948, in the light of the circumstances then existing.<br />
It was also decided that semi-governmental and local authorities<br />
borrowing would be subject to the same 75 per cent, limitation. </p>
<p>" Under this arrangement, the Commonwealth and States will be<br />
entitled to borrow up to the following amounts, pending review later<br />
in the financial Government Semi-Governmental<br />
Programmes, and Incal.<br />
Commor wealth 12,900,000<br />
New South Wales 16,151,000 8,181,000<br />
Victoria 8,318,000 5,239,000<br />
Queensland.. 6,692,000 5,036,000<br />
South Australia 4,982,000 136,000<br />
Western, Australia 2,708,000 450,000<br />
Tasmania 1,531,000 678,00<br />
53,282,000 19,720,000<br />
TARI FF.<br />
EXPORTS PROHIBITED.<br />
On 21st August, 1947, the Minister for Customs ( Senator Courtice)<br />
announced that exportation had been prohibited of-<br />
Agricultural machinery, namely, tractors; drills, grain and fertilizer cultivator;<br />
drills, seeds for cereal crops; harvesters, header; reaper threshers; reapers<br />
and binders; hay balers; rakes, side delivery; -mowers; and spare partS for<br />
those machines; cattle, beef and dairy; cowpeas; ovaltine; urea, urea moulding<br />
powders and urea glue. TRADING WITH ENEMY.<br />
JAPAN.<br />
On 22nd August, 1947, the Minister for Customs ( Senator Courtice)<br />
announced that a licence under the Trading with the Enemy Act<br />
published in that day's Commonwealth Gazeie authorized the resumption<br />
of private trade with Japan. Imports into Australia would be<br />
controlled under Customs ( Import Licensing) Regulations. Imports<br />
would be accorded the same treatment as imports from hard currency<br />
areas and in general only essential goods not available in adequate<br />
quantities from local or sterling sources of supply would be permitted.<br />
CONVERSION LOAN.<br />
AUSTRALIAN OPERATION-AUGUST, 1947.<br />
On 25th August, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) announced<br />
that a conversion loan would open on 28th August, 1947. Holders of<br />
securities valued at œ 36,751,620 maturing on 15th September, 1947,<br />
would be invited to exchange their securities for 3j per cent, bonds<br />
or inscribed stock repayable in 1959. T * he Treasurer would reserve<br />
the option of retiring the new securities in 1956. About 36,000<br />
individuals hold the securities about to mature comprising about<br />
œ E8,100,000 bearing interest at 31 per cent. and œ 28,600,000 at 4 per cent. </p>
<p>MAN-POWER.<br />
WOMEN WORKERS-MINISTER'S REQUESTS.<br />
On 26th August, 1947, the Minister for Labour ( Mr. Holloway)<br />
said that employers could provide greater opportunities for the parttime<br />
employment of women. Many employers were operating schemes<br />
for the part-time employment of women. Some schemes had been<br />
introduced during the war and others more recently. It had sometimes<br />
been found necessary to make internal adjustments to permit of the<br />
working of short shifts or to earmark certain types of work for parttime<br />
workers, but when those adjustments had been made a smoother<br />
flow and greater production had resulted from the increased numbers<br />
of workers. Women, not at present employed, should undertake part-time work.<br />
The total number of women in employment as wage and salary earners,<br />
excluding rural and household domestic workers, was about 620,000,<br />
or only 20,000 -below the peak war-time level, when man-power controls<br />
were operating. When account was taken of the greater numbers of<br />
women now occupied as employers or self-employed persons, it was<br />
very likely that the total number of women gainfully occupied was<br />
nearly as great as it was at the peak of the war.<br />
Decentralization of industry throughout suburban areas and the<br />
country meant that opportunities for employment were very much more<br />
handy to women living at home than previously. Arrangements could<br />
often be made to make part-time employment fit in with household<br />
and other commitments. JUDICIARY.<br />
ARBITRATION COURT-APPOINTMENT.<br />
On 27th August, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
Judge R. C. Kirby, of the New South Wales District Court, has<br />
been appointed a judge of the Commonwealth Conciliation and Arbitration<br />
Court.<br />
" When the Stevedoring Industry Act comes into operation, Mr.<br />
Justice Kirby will become chairman of -the Stevedoring Industry<br />
Commission NATIONAL DEBT.<br />
NATIONAL DEBT COMMISSION-ANNUAL REPORT.<br />
On 27th August, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
The National Debt Commission, which controls all sinking funds<br />
for the redemption of Commonwealth and State debts, met at Canberra<br />
to-day. The meeting was attended by the Chief Justice of the High<br />
Court ( Sir John Latham), the Governor of the Commonwealth Bank<br />
( Mr. H. T. Armitage), the acting Secretary to the Treasury ( Mr. G1. P.<br />
N. Watt), the Solicitor-General ( Profesor K. H. Bailey), and the<br />
representative of the States ( Mr. A. T. -Smithers), and myself as chairman.<br />
The main business of the meeting was the presentation of the<br />
annual report on the transactions for the year ended 30th June, 1947, </p>
<p>and consideration of the application of sinking fund moneys accruing<br />
during 1947-48. The receipts of the sinking fund for 1946-47 were<br />
about œ 25,950,000. The annual report covering these transactions will<br />
be presented to Parliament in due course.<br />
" Receipts for 1947-48 are estimated at œ 26,873,000, being<br />
œ 17,625,000 on account of the Commonwealth and œ 9,248,000 on account<br />
of the States. Of the latter amount, œ 1,642,000 will be provided from<br />
Commonwealth revenue. The total contributions estimated to be available<br />
for the redemption of the debt of each . State are as follows:-<br />
New South Wales œ 3,612,000, Victoria œ 1,837,000, Queensland œ 1,340,000,<br />
South Australia œ 1,141,000, Western Australia œ 1,007,000, and Tasmania<br />
œ 311,000, total œ 9,248,000.<br />
" The receipts of œ 26,873,000 were directed by the commission to be<br />
applied in the various markets in which Commonwealth and State<br />
securities are held-Australia, London and New York. The commission<br />
uses its funds for the redemption of Commonwealth and State<br />
securities either by repurchase of these securities on the market, or by<br />
redemption at maturity.<br />
" The large sums applied in repurchases on -Stock Exchanges ensure<br />
a regular market for security holders. When securities are acquired by<br />
the commission, either by repurchase or redemption, they are<br />
immediately cancelled and the public debt is reduced accordingly".<br />
HEALTH AND YOUTH WELFARE.<br />
CHILD HEALTH.<br />
On 2nd September, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
" Cabinet decided to-day on the recommendation of the Minister for<br />
Health ( Senator McKenna) that a division of child health be created<br />
in the Department of Health to be transferred subsequently to the<br />
National Health Service.<br />
The functions of the division will be to co-ordinate and extend<br />
existing pre-natal and infant welfare services; to continue research into<br />
the growth and development of infants and children, malnutrition and<br />
other diseases in children and related fundamental biochemistry and<br />
physiology; to conduct general education on infant and child health,<br />
including nutrition; to arrange, and if necessary, undertake special<br />
instruction to medical graduates and others in child health and<br />
nutrition. " For the present the division will be located in the Institute of<br />
Anatomy, Canberra, and the functions of the division will be additional<br />
to those for which the Institute was founded-investigation of the<br />
anatomy and physiology of Australian animals and the development<br />
and maintenance of a museum of health and hygiene.<br />
" Additional permanent positions will be created of a second medical<br />
officer to be an assistant to the Director; a senior biochemist to take<br />
charge of the increasingly important phase of the study of growth and<br />
nutrition; a second biochemist; and a nutritionist </p>
<p>INCOME TAX.<br />
UNIFORM TAX-RE-IMBURSEMENT TO THE STATES.<br />
On 2nd September, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
Under the war-time uniform tax scheme which operated until<br />
June, 1946, tax re-imbursement grants paid to the States amounted<br />
to œ 34,255,000. At a conference of Commonwealth and State Ministers<br />
in January, 1946, it was agreed that a revised basis should operate as<br />
from 1st July, 1946. The revised basis was contained in the States<br />
Grants ( Tax Re-imbursement) Act and provided that the aggregate<br />
of the grants in 1946-47 and 1947-48 should be œ 40,000,000. In respect<br />
of subsequent years, it was specified that the aggregate grant of<br />
œ 40,000,000 would be varied in proportion to variation in the States'<br />
populations and the resultant amount increased by half the percentage<br />
increase, if any, in the level of average wages per person employed over<br />
the level in 1946-47. In regard to grants in years after 1947-48, the<br />
legislation provided that a gradually diminishing part of the aggregate<br />
grant would be distributed in the proportions in which the aggregate<br />
grant of œ 40,000,000 was distributed to the States in 1946-47 and<br />
1947-48, while a gradually increasing part would be distributed in<br />
proportion to the States' respective populations after adjustments had<br />
been made to those populations to take account of relative sparsity of<br />
population and the numbers of children aged five to fifteen years in each<br />
State. " At the conference of Commonwealth and State Ministers in<br />
August, 1947, the State Premiers indicated that the re-imbursement<br />
grants would be insufficient to enable them to balance their Budgets in<br />
this financial year.<br />
Cabinet decided to-day that an additional re-imbursement grant of<br />
œ 5,000,000 be distributed by the Commonwealth and the States as<br />
follows:-In 1947-48 the additional grant of œ 5,000,000 will be distributed among the<br />
States in accordance with the proportions in the first schedule to the States<br />
Grants ( Tax Re-imbursement) Act 1946.<br />
To the extent that, in subsequent years, the aggregate grant determined and<br />
distributed among'the States in accordance with the provisions of the States<br />
Grants ( Tax Re-imbursement) Act 1946 is less than œ 45,000,000, the amount<br />
of this deficiency will be made up by the Commonwealth and distributed among<br />
the States in accordance with the proportions in the first schedule to the Act<br />
of 1946. " Legislation to authorize the payment of the additional grant will<br />
be submitted to the Federal Parliamentary Labour Party".<br />
THE GOVERNMENT.<br />
On 5th September, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
" The Minister for Health and Social Services ( Senator McKenna)<br />
will act as Attorney-General and I will act as Minister for External<br />
Affairs as from to-day and during the absence overseas of Dr. Evatt<br />
By Authority: L. F. JOHNSTON, Commonwealth Governrqent Printer, Canbenra. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
