<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5507</transcript-id>
    <title>COOLANGATTA&#039;S NEW AIRPORT TERMINAL TO BE NAMED AFTER LATE ERIC ROBINSON</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/02/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005507.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR MEDIA FRIDXY 6 rEBR. UKRY19.<br />
COOL. V4G?, TTA'-S NI1 IPR SIIA<br />
* TO 160E NAI'M2D PJ" TER LPA E R! C _ ROB Q 14<br />
'~-( Joint statement by the Prime Z' 4iister and minister, for Transp).<br />
The new terminal now onaer construction at Coolangatta<br />
klrport will be named the Eric Robinson Terminal.<br />
The Govern-ment believea this will provide a fitting-tribute<br />
to the late Eric RobinsonI who was member for MRcPhexson. f rom,<br />
1972 until his sud~ fden and untimely death last month..<br />
fir. Robinson served the. electorate of McPherson -with dedlicati on<br />
and distinction, and the naming of the terminal. building a A t. ex<br />
-comrneor-ate him and his work in an appropriate-<br />
Jhe -t~ ernda3. will of couxse r-erve two. i-&amp;* rtant areas.<br />
the electorate of m~ chro and the electorat-o f Ri ehn zIC<br />
K represented by the Deputy Prkm2 blinister, Mr. Anthony.<br />
The Coolangatta Airport is in facta situate.. d in bot-h electorates.<br />
Both vx' Anthony and Mr. Robinson worked ha ILor the<br />
~~ reedeviaopmet of the airport and the new teruuinal 5o that<br />
the Tweed/ Gold Coast region would have adaquato-facilities<br />
to Bustain and accompany. its growth.<br />
Mr. Anthony's3 fathe, the late Anthony, as Member for<br />
. Richmond and Minister for Civil Aviatf. ion, playedl a vary<br />
important part in the original development of the airport..___<br />
The first sod was turned jointly by Anthony and Rir.<br />
Robinson when work commenced on -the new terminal building.<br />
We think it appropriate, therefore, that Mr. Anthony should<br />
V officially open the E3ric Robinson Terminal on its completion,<br />
~ and wA-3iUl be inviting him to do so.-</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
