<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>16183</transcript-id>
    <title>Joint Press Release with the Treasurer, Wayne Swan, and Minister for Families, Jenny Macklin $4.8 Billion down payment to help Pensioners, Seniors and Carers </title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/10/2008</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Rudd Government will deliver a $4.8 billion down payment to Australia's four million pensioners, carers, seniors and veterans - providing them with immediate financial help in the lead up to comprehensive reform of the pension system.</p>
<p>This decisive action is part of the Rudd Government's $10.4 billion Economic Security Strategy to boost the Australian economy and support pensioners and families during the global financial crisis.</p>
<p>The $4.8 billion down payment will be made available through a lump sum payment of $1,400 to singles and $2,100 to couples, which will benefit:    </p>
<p>     * Age Pensioners;</p>
<p>     * Disability Support Pensioners;</p>
<p>     * Carer Payment recipients;</p>
<p>     * Wife and Widow B Pensioners; Partner, Widow and Bereavement Allowees;</p>
<p>     * Veterans Affairs Service Pensioners;</p>
<p>     * Veterans Income Support Supplement recipients;</p>
<p>     * Veterans Affairs Gold Card holders eligible for Seniors Concession Allowance;</p>
<p>     * Those of age pension age who receive Parenting Payment, Special Benefit, or Austudy; and  </p>
<p>     * Eligible Self Funded retirees holding a Commonwealth Senior Health Card (CSHC)</p>
<p>People who are receiving Carer Allowance will also receive $1,000 for each eligible person being cared for. </p>
<p>All payments will be made automatically through Centrelink and the Department of Veterans Affairs in the fortnight beginning 8 December 2008.</p>
<p>Payments are intended to provide additional support in the nine months between now and when long-term reforms are introduced from the beginning of the next financial year.</p>
<p>The global financial crisis is placing increasing pressure on budgets already stretched by the rising cost of living. </p>
<p>That is why we are taking decisive action to provide support to pensioners while reforms to the pension system are being finalised.</p>
<p>The Government will not pit pensioner groups against each other and we will not exclude two million carers, people with a disability and married pensioner couples from this payment ahead of longer term reform.</p>
<p>These payments recognise the additional costs single pensioners face relative to couples.</p>
<p>For the first time, lump sum payments are being extended to include Disability Support Pensioners. </p>
<p>The Government is reforming the pension system to prepare Australia for the challenges of the future and we are committed to getting it right for the long term.</p>
<p>Long term pension reform will be delivered in the 2009-10 Budget context.</p>
<p>The $4.8 billion package builds on the $7.5 billion in support provided in the Government's first budget, bringing new spending on pensioners, seniors and carers to $12.3 billion.</p>
<p>The Government's Economic Security Strategy also includes help for self-funded retirees, who are eligible for a Seniors Concession Allowance or hold a Commonwealth Seniors Health Card.</p>
<p>They will receive a payment of $1,400 if they are single or $2,100 for couples. </p>
<p>The Government is closely monitoring the global financial crisis and its impact on pensioners.</p>
<p>In the last week financial markets experienced a significant fall in share values, resulting in substantial reductions in the value of pensioner financial assets.</p>
<p>The Government has asked Centrelink to quickly update their system with the current value of any investments, including shares, that pensioners might hold.</p>
<p>This will ensure that pension payments are based on the most up-to-date asset values available.</p>
<p>Payments will be non taxable and not included for income testing purposes.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
