<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4355</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/03/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004355.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
BROADCAST: 3HA 27 MARCH<br />
Jj 3YB 31 MARCH<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR P~ RESS 27 MARCH 1977<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
Although the presentation of this year's Federal Budget is still<br />
five months away, the Government has already begun to tackle the job.<br />
One of the central issues again facing the Government in the<br />
framJJ-ng of the Budget will be the level of Government spending.<br />
Clearly, as we continue our fight against inflation, it will be<br />
absolutely"-critical that the Government succeeds in curbing<br />
i ts own expenditure. It will be critical that the deficit be<br />
tigThi: ly controlled.<br />
Last year in our first year in office we were confronted by a<br />
rmass:. ve deficit that was approaching $ 4,000 million. Immediately<br />
we took steps to substantially rein back the deficit through a<br />
rigorous restraint on Government spending. We moved to cut<br />
unnec: essary programmes and to make existing programmes more<br />
effective. We have continued to exercise -restraint in spending. We have continue!<br />
to seek to get the maximum possible value from the taxpayers dollar.<br />
Thi-s year, as the Treasurer has indicated, the closest examination<br />
will again be made in every area of Government spending.. This<br />
de-ta-. led process has started. It will be an exhaustive examination.<br />
No e--fort will be spared in making sure that the Budget is<br />
responsible and responsive to Australia's needs.<br />
The Budget will demonstrate that our priorities are to p~ rotect the<br />
disadvantaged and to beat inflation so that economic recovery can<br />
contiLnue. It will not be an easy task. It is never easy for<br />
responsible Governments to hold back on some programme, or even<br />
reduce programmes. Of course, it is easy for Governments to take<br />
money from people and throw it around and then claim credit for<br />
thei:-generosity with taxpayers funds.<br />
As Australia has found to its cost, that kind of approach does not<br />
solve problems it creates problems. It's the kind of approach<br />
that brought the national economy to its knees. and caused<br />
immeasurable and lasting harm to hundreds of thousands of Australian<br />
f am i li e s.<br />
As we have demonstrated, our approach is the reverse of the Labor<br />
Partv. We'have sought get the most effective distribution of<br />
Government programmes irid not just simply throw cash at a<br />
problem and hope it goes away. W~ e have sought to give individuals<br />
the chance to make their own decisions, their own choices / 2 </p>
<p>and not just to impose Canberra-controlled and directed programmes.<br />
Labor's centralist programmes were financed out of high taxation<br />
that was fuelled from rampant inflation. Our introduction of<br />
personal tax indexation last year stopped this unlegislated tax<br />
drain to Canberra.<br />
In just over three month's time, from July 1, personal income<br />
tax indexation will come into effect for the second year. It will<br />
reduce our taxation revenues by $ 1,000 million tax. that would<br />
have come direct from pay packets without indexation.<br />
Those w., ho still call for tax cuts forget that the decisions of this<br />
Government have resulted in a tax saving of $ 3,000 million over our<br />
first two years. Of this, personal tax indexation accounts for<br />
over $ 2,000 million of the total. It is a tax reform unparalleled<br />
in our history. It deserves wider recognition for the relief it<br />
has given to thousands of individuals and companies.<br />
By the second year it will be worth nearly $ 500 for the average famiily.<br />
Against this background the Government has been encouraged by<br />
trends in our fight against inflation and in our efforts to restore<br />
our country to full economic health. Inflation is coming down.<br />
Both the deflator for major components of the gross national<br />
expenditure probably the best measure of the inflation rate and<br />
the C. P. I. clearly demonstrate that the underlying rate of inflation<br />
is steadily coming down.<br />
Confidence has returned to important sections of industry. To<br />
illustrate: company profits were around a third higher in the<br />
December quarter last year than they were a year earlier;<br />
investment in plant and equipment by private enterprise increased by<br />
over 31% last year; real private investment in dwellings increased<br />
by over S% in the second half of last year 24% up on the same<br />
period a year earlier; dwelling approvals, registrations of new<br />
motor vehicles, real private consumption, real gross non-farm<br />
product, and new capital raisings by listed companies, all markedly<br />
improved last year. There are other signs that are encouraging.<br />
The only business survey available for the March quarter of this<br />
year showed that manufacturers were more optimistic about the<br />
general business situation in the next six months than they were<br />
three months ago.<br />
This kind of confidence is apparent among consumers too. The January<br />
survey of consumer attitudes by the Melbourne Institute of Np~ plied<br />
Economic and Social Research shows that consumer confidence was at<br />
the highest level in over 12 months.<br />
Unemployment is still far too high. We have taken a great number of<br />
measures to help the unemployed, particularly the young. This week<br />
for instance, the Minister for Employment and Industrial Relations<br />
announced a special after-hours programme that will give both<br />
employers and employees an opportunity to discuss employment problems<br />
with senior officers of the Commonwealth Employment Service. Parents<br />
of unemployed you. ng people wouldI be especially welc:)' ne to take<br />
advantage of thiis particular offer. Howrever, as I and my Ministers ha,<br />
frequently pointed out, the sustained reduction in unemployment will<br />
only-o-cur-f-om--rhpea-licies<br />
onlDyolcicrc efsom hat edue iflaton. Ourfight against<br />
1. nflatiOnl iS a1 Fight ag-ainst unemiploymient. Thc Governiniemrt has<br />
pursued its Ifight against Inflation with full zeal during the past<br />
months. 11. e will not slacken in our desire to continue this task<br />
during this year. We will not be sidetracked in our fight<br />
agai1nst inflation. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
