<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6875</transcript-id>
    <title>JOINT PRESS CONFERENCE WITH THE PRIME MINISTER, THE TREASURER AND THE MINISTER FOR HOUSING AND CONSTRUCTION, 2 APRIL 1986</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/04/1986</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006875.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
JOINT PRESS CONFERENCE WITH THE PRIME MINISTER, THE TREASURER AND<br />
THE MINISTER FOR HOUSING AND CONSTRUCTION 2 APRIL 1986<br />
PM: Ladies and Gentlemen, as you have seen the Cabinet has,<br />
after detailed consideration of the prospects of the housing<br />
industry, made a series of decisions which is calculated to have<br />
the housing industry continue to make an important contribution<br />
to the level of economic activity. I don't want to go through all<br />
the details of the decision. I will make two or three points<br />
about it and then I will ask my colleagues to make their<br />
observations. I think these points are important to understand,<br />
and that is that no one who presently has a loan will be faced<br />
with increased repayments. The ceiling will be retained in<br />
respect of existing loans. We have faced a situation where, on<br />
the best information available to my colleagues that has been<br />
made available by the banks, that we would have been in 1986/ 7<br />
looking at a situation of 100,000 or less new starts which was a<br />
position which was not acceptable to us. On the arrangements that<br />
have now been negotiated, we will be able with confidence to look<br />
in 1986/ 7 to a minimum of 135,000 starts. Now in terms of the<br />
level of activity in this country and employment prospects, it is<br />
important to understand what that means. Roughly each 10,000<br />
starts represent, in direct and indirect terms, about 15,000<br />
jobs. So the difference between what we in the absence of a<br />
decision would have been looking at is 100,000 starts, now<br />
135,000. You can see that we are talking about something like<br />
50,000 jobs. Now obviously if we could have reached that position<br />
in other ways, that would have been desirable. But we were not<br />
going to allow a situation to emerge where the housing industry<br />
was going to substantially disintegrate and that 50,000 as you<br />
can see would have been not just at risk, they would have<br />
disappeared. And we believe in the circumstances the decision<br />
that has been taken protects, as I say, all those with existing<br />
loans to ensure the existence of high level activity in the<br />
housing industry and will ensure that they, the 50,000 jobs,<br />
don't disappear in this industry. And that was a situation that<br />
we were not prepared to tolerate or contemplate. Paul..<br />
KEATING: I think the only other thing to add Bob, is the fact<br />
that we were facing two problems. The first one was to maintain<br />
the existing stock of profits which underpin the existing<br />
mortgages with savings banks. Now not only was there, on the part<br />
of some banks, a total incapacity to lend to new borrowers, in<br />
fact some said in the June quarter they would not be lending at<br />
all any new landings. But their existing deposits which<br />
underpinned their existing mortgages were haemorrhaging </p>
<p>tourniquet that flow out of the existing deposit base. And we<br />
have the subsidy which is mentioned here. It is a subsidy which<br />
goes to underpinning with the banks playing their role in<br />
underpinning that deposit base. At the moment banks have been<br />
paying about 16% for deposits on the commercial market and then<br />
on lending them for 13.5%. The subsidy which is implied there is<br />
coming from their trading bank operations, is one that they have<br />
entertained, in fact accommodated since the latter part of last<br />
year. But in the current climate the loss of deposits is such<br />
that the problem isn't just an absence of new lending or very<br />
little new lending or an insufficient rate of new lending but a<br />
loss of deposits with base. So the proposition goes to two<br />
things. It goes to that and by allowing the banks to bid at<br />
market rates for the against which new lending could be<br />
accommodated they are in a position to guarantee funding to level<br />
of around, as the Prime minister said, $ 6 billion which would be<br />
commensurate with an annual rate of about 135,000 starts which<br />
would broadly meet the underlying requirements. So they are the<br />
two major elements along with changes which we announced in this<br />
statement of the Commonwealth/ State housing arrangement which my<br />
colleague, Stewart West, will refer to in a moment and also a<br />
nominated....... which the States have had available to them at<br />
different times and at different rates for public sector housing.<br />
So as a package we think it achieved an excellent result that<br />
meets our commitment to existing borrowers. It importantly<br />
ensures that home loan funds are available and we have got a<br />
continuing and solid responsibility to make sure that housing<br />
finance is available to people to house themselves. And we have<br />
ensured that that activity in housing, such an important part of<br />
activity in the economy, will be maintained through 1986/ 7 and<br />
the banks will be doing all within their power to pull the rate<br />
of lending up as rapidly as possible in the June quarter<br />
commensurate and moving up towards that target figure of<br />
$ 6 billion.<br />
PM: Stewart.<br />
WEST: Thanks Prime Minister. Just to recapitulate what has been<br />
said. We will be protecting the existing borrowers who are on the<br />
13.5% limit with the savings banks. And of course new loans will<br />
be deregulated. But we would expect that following further<br />
negotiations with the banks that low start loans will be<br />
negotiated which will protect to a certain extent the early<br />
repayments of people who may be paying increased interest rates.<br />
The fact is that we may have been looking at a total of about<br />
$ 3,000 million per year for 1986/ 7 instead of $ 6 billion which<br />
will now be available as a result of this package. And as the<br />
Pri * me Minister has said and the Treasurer has said, this will<br />
mean that we will have a number of starts which is almost, in<br />
1986/ 7, which is almost commensurate with the underlying<br />
requirement of between 140,000 and 145,000. And we will protect<br />
the existing employment base in the industry and see up to 50,000<br />
more people employed than otherwise could have been the case. I<br />
do want to pick up the point that the Treasurer opened up, that<br />
is the future of CSHA funding. We have decided to maintain our<br />
1985/ 6 effort in real terms which will mean that the States, as a<br />
grant, will obtain approximately $ 700 million in 1986/ 87 and that<br />
further the States will be allowed to nominate up to 60% of their </p>
<p>3<br />
total loan council borrowings at the concessional rate of<br />
repayable over 53 years which is a pretty good deal. And at the<br />
moment only South Australia and western Australia would have been<br />
able to nominate 60% of those loan council borrowings in 1986/ 7<br />
and the other States would have been restricted to 30%. So we are<br />
allowing them all to go up to 60% and that will mean that in<br />
addition to the $ 700 million as a grant for CSHA funding that if<br />
all the States pick it up they are entitlements are approximately<br />
another $ 700 million further would be available for public<br />
housing. The press statement also says that the Government will<br />
be further examining means of extending further funds to the<br />
States who on lending, through their existing lending authorities<br />
such as co-operative and state banks and ministries, funds for<br />
low income loans and that is to be further examined. I think I<br />
should leave it there and I am sure that we can answer any<br />
questions. JOURNALIST: Do you have any understanding with the banks as to<br />
the ruling rates of interest for new loans or will the market<br />
competition simply determine that?<br />
KEATING: I think their judgment would be Peter, that they would<br />
be approximately around, in the current climate, and the current<br />
climate of course has been one of recent times of....... interest<br />
rates. But in the current climate of around 15.5%.<br />
JOURNALIST: Why couldn't the ceiling be lifted two weeks ago?<br />
What's changed?<br />
PM': We have had a clear position that if it were possible to<br />
protect the level of activity and the level of starts in another<br />
way then we would have preferred to do that common ground. But<br />
it's become clear, in the discussions which my ministers have had<br />
with the relevant sectors of the industry, including the banks,<br />
that we were facing a situation that savings banks were going to<br />
virtually cease to function in this area. Now that would have<br />
meant a disaster. It would have meant, as I put to you in<br />
employment terms, a loss of 50,000 jobs. If starts in 86/ 87 had<br />
gone down to 100,000 or perhaps less, as they were talking of<br />
lending in the June quarter Paul, of less than $ 3 billion, about<br />
$ 2.8 billion, which predicated housing starts of less than<br />
100,000 in 1986/ 87. We were not prepared to tolerate that<br />
outcome. And in those circumstances we have been able to<br />
negotiate an outcome which will do these things. It will give a<br />
level of housing starts, as my ministers have said and as I've<br />
said,-which will meet the basic underlying demand and will<br />
maintain a level of employment in the industry and activity which<br />
is necessary not only for the industry itself, but you all know<br />
how important housing is for the level of economic activity as a<br />
whole. And as part of the package that we've negotiated we have<br />
also ensured that in the area of public housing actions will be<br />
taken which will ensure an appropriate level of activity there. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Mr Keating how long will the 13.5 per cent celing<br />
stay on for existing borrowers?<br />
KEATING: Well that's grandfathered in.<br />
PM: For the period of the loans. That's what grandfathering<br />
means for the period of the loan.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke are you confident the Caucus will accept<br />
the package in total?<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
JOURNALIST: And I take you put your prestige on the line?<br />
PM: I never throw my prestige around it's too precious a<br />
commodity. I mean it's always there. My answer is in a brief,<br />
unqualified term that I gave it to you.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you expect all your ministers to support it?<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister it was only a fortnight ago that you<br />
didn't draw any distinction between new and existing loans. Do<br />
you feel any embarrassment at all about the fact<br />
PM: No. I would have felt embarrassed because I had said well<br />
that's the Government's commitment and understanding that<br />
position. If I had then become aware on the advice of my<br />
ministers that an adherence to that position would have meant<br />
50,000 less people in employment and 35,000 less starts, my<br />
embarrassment would have consisted of saying, because of some<br />
statement I made that I am not going to face that current<br />
reality, and I'm going to allow 50,000 people to be unemployed<br />
and 35,000 less starts, that would have embarrassed me.<br />
JOURNALIST: But Mr Hawke why make the statement that the<br />
Government remains committed to the retention of the ceiling on<br />
housing interest rates in the first place and have two ministers<br />
make as well. Mr Keating said that he wasn't proposing any<br />
change in the ceiling at all. Mr West said the same day as you<br />
that the housing ceiling would be retained. why have three<br />
ministers say this within two days then a week later, two weeks<br />
later come back and change your position?<br />
PM: Well in respect of existing loans no change. And that's<br />
very important. What I'm saying to you, and I repeat-again, is<br />
that what has become, now, completely clear out of the<br />
discussions that my ministers have had is that if there had not<br />
been the step now taken that the savings banks would have<br />
completely dried up as a source of new lending. Weiwould have<br />
had a position where, as I and the Treasurer have indicated, a<br />
level of spending in the June quarter of the order of less than<br />
$ 3 billion. Now that was not something then finally that we<br />
could accept. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Mr West, you've been adamantly committed to<br />
retention of the ceiling, publicly, over the last couple of<br />
weeks. Did you find it idealogically difficult to accept this<br />
package today?<br />
WEST: Lets say I would have found it more idealogically<br />
difficult to face up to the loss of 50,000 jobs in the industry.<br />
Now look, just be aware of the changes that have been occurring<br />
with the-banks projections of their expected lending. Several<br />
weeks ago my Indicative Planning Council expected that the banks,<br />
and were told by the banks, that the savings banks would be<br />
lending something like $ 5 billion in 86/ 87 right. Now we're<br />
faced with projections of something like $ 3 billion by savings<br />
banks. Now that's a very sharp reduction. I was looking at,<br />
several weeks ago, putting to Cabinet a position that based upon<br />
those projections to Professor Gruen's IPC that we would need to<br />
push about an extra billion dollars for 86/ 87 and that's where<br />
that magical figure came from, to keep up respectible lending by<br />
banks. Now we were faced with a base from which we should<br />
expand, not of $ 5 billion of $ 3 billion. So what we've attained<br />
here, as a result of the figures mentioned here, in terms of<br />
subsidies to the banks and the removal of the ceiling for new<br />
lending, is an expansion from $ 3 billion up to $ 6 billion. And<br />
that's the base from which all significant lenders will then take<br />
off from and provide our 135/ 145,000 starts.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr West are you saying you were converted then, to<br />
what Mr Keating sought as a solution, before you went into<br />
today's Cabinet meeting?<br />
WEST: I'm saying that what we've done is to protect the 13.5 per<br />
cent ceiling for exisiting borrowers and accept the fact that<br />
unless we took some further action, regarding subsidies to the<br />
banks, the deregulation for new loans, the offering of loan start<br />
loans to those who can't afford the increased interest rates for<br />
new loans, in return for the offering of $ 6 billion in funds for<br />
housing by savings banks in 86/ 87, that I believe that that is a<br />
pretty good deal from which to operate. Particularly when I have<br />
to be responsible also for low income earners and to protect the<br />
funds to the states for public housing, which I have done today.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Keating, if these measures don't achieve the<br />
goals that you've set for them, would you consider lifting the<br />
ceiling on exisiting loans?<br />
KEATING: I've got total confident that they will.* If the banks<br />
are in a position now to bid in a competitive way in the market<br />
for funds and they are not constrained by a ceiling for new<br />
loans, there's no reason why they cannot be effective in getting<br />
the active volume of funds. So I just don't think the position<br />
arises. we think it is one of the prime social responsibilities<br />
of the Government for people to be able to house themselves and<br />
to have housing funds available to them. At the moment they're<br />
simply not available. For many people they're just simply not<br />
available. And if one looks at the current cocktailing which is<br />
going on between those few lucky people who have been able to get<br />
a savings loan in recent times, and topping them up with expenive<br />
financing, this is by far the best outcome. It means more people </p>
<p>will have finance availbie at rates which will guarantee a<br />
continuing flow of funds into housing.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Keating, if they are going to lend at 15.5 per<br />
cent will they be able, do you think<br />
KEATING: I'm saying they'll be lending at 15.5 per cent. That's<br />
for the banks to determine. That is the indication. I should<br />
think in the current climate that would a sort of a maximum<br />
number, a maximum figure. They may do better than that. I hope<br />
they do.<br />
JOURNALIST: Will they be able then to attract the funds they<br />
need? KEATING: Yes, I think So. The lending ceiling puts a ceiling<br />
effectively on the deposit rate. The deposit rate is governing<br />
the amount interest rates<br />
JOURNALIST: Could we clear up the matter of the ceiling on<br />
exisiting loans. Are you saying that you've got an understanding<br />
with the banks that no borrower, who has an exisiting loan at<br />
13.5 per cent at the moment, will pay more than that in the<br />
future? KEATING: Yes.<br />
JOURNALIST: Given that Australians, the average mortgage is paid<br />
off over seven years, are we not talking seven years down the<br />
track about total deregulation?<br />
KEATING: We're not talking about somebody who started a mortgage<br />
which lasted seven years they have no problems about the burden<br />
of the security of higher interest rates in the context of our<br />
external position, or of the reasons for which the Government<br />
tightens monetary policy. And they are being effectively<br />
shielded from that burden. If they discharge their mortgage then<br />
their out.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Keating, by how much do you think savings banks<br />
will be able to lift interest rates on their deposits?<br />
KEATING: Well that's for them to make a judgment. Obviously I<br />
think at the sort of rates I've mentioned they'll be competitive.<br />
I mean they have different deposit influence and they will<br />
fashion them to the market to which they have particularly<br />
directed themselves. They are all quite different and<br />
distinctive in the way in which they attract funds for lending.<br />
JOURNALIST: The banks have been lobbying you on this issue for<br />
months. Now if their lending projections were so much worse<br />
yesterday than they were a few weeks ago isn't it possible that<br />
they'll just revise them down in trying to get the sort of result<br />
we have today?<br />
KEATING: No, I don't think so. I think it's a genuine<br />
reflection of their trading position. It's a genuine reflection<br />
of their underlying position. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: How are the interest rate subsidy<br />
KEATING: Well the subsidy is calculated across an average of<br />
about one per cent on the bank's deposits of which they carry a<br />
third. So the Commonwealth will carry about .6 of a per cent<br />
across the average of their deposits. Not all of their deposits<br />
are so effected. Many people will continue to keep savings<br />
investment accounts, statement accounts and passbooks. To the<br />
extent that they have to lift their deposit rates in this current<br />
climate for some deposits by frontend loading subsidies on a<br />
quarterly basis, we allow for a maximum capacity to get the<br />
attractiveness of the deposits up in the current climate. And<br />
then in the context over time of changes with the interest rate<br />
regime. The subsidy will go down. Now we will be able to see on<br />
a quarter by quarter basis whether the subsidy needs to be<br />
maintained across the year. If it does there's a maximum of<br />
about $ 120 million, if it doesn't there will be less. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: It is a pretty expensive subsidy for a budget that<br />
is looking pretty tight already?<br />
KEATING: I think one hasAtrace the whole problem of the<br />
dramatic decline in the terms of trade which Australia<br />
is now experiencing. We are experiencing a terms of trade<br />
decline probably that we have not witnessed since the deptession.<br />
And we have had to make domestic policies adjust to that,<br />
monetary policy has been one of those prices. And that Jas<br />
had an effect on, obviously, the banking system. And to A extent<br />
that the budget carried some of that cost, it will obviously<br />
mean a diminution of government services elsewhere, which is<br />
part of the adjustment by the nation to that decline in our<br />
trading position.<br />
JOURNALIST: How late in the process did you come to the<br />
conclusion that: partial deregulation was the only solution?<br />
PM: The Treasurer and I have been involved in these discussions<br />
from the beginning. I haven't been on any road to Damascus.<br />
JOURNALIST: But two weeks ago you had a different view<br />
obviously from what you were saying publicly?<br />
PM: I have already addressed myself to that question. I have<br />
said, Michelle, and I repeat that we all would have preferred<br />
a position, if we could, of having a lid there on it. Now,<br />
it-became clear in the most recent discussions that we were<br />
facing a dramatic deterioration. The difference between<br />
what was Ql prospect of 100,000 new starts at the most, and<br />
now a guarantee of 135,000. It is dramatic not only in terms<br />
of housing starts, but the 50,000 difference in employment is<br />
the order of the figures we are talking about. Now, when you<br />
are faced with that stark situation, and not any qualification<br />
about it, then you have got to make the decision which is in<br />
the best interests of the community. And I make this point<br />
if I could just pick up what your question Russell , ifollows<br />
logically this observation, that if you look at, in budgetary<br />
terms, if in fact you had 50,000 less people employed in the<br />
building industry as a result of adherence to a position that<br />
was referred to before, just look at the budgetary impact of<br />
that.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Keating, is it a case of I told you so?<br />
KEATING: No,* not at all. One deals with problems as they<br />
unfold. And the Prime Minister already made it clear if the<br />
banks had remained competitive, well the problem wouldn't have<br />
arisen. But we were, of course, interested to monitor their<br />
state of competitiveness, which deteriorated markedly in the<br />
last few weeks, in the last months indeed. But particularly<br />
in the last few weeks. Y04<br />
PM: If I could just remind Aof that figure that Mr West<br />
referred to. And the figures are these. Just a matter<br />
of a few weeks ago the IPC was talking on the basis of<br />
4.9 billion dollars, savings banks, that is what we are talking<br />
about, 4.9 billion. Now, the figure as of the beginning of<br />
this week, is that they were looking at less that 3 billion. </p>
<p>PM cont: Now that is just in a matter of literally four weeks.<br />
And it makes a very, very big difference.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Keating, is this an indication that interest<br />
rates are going to stay up?<br />
KEATING: It makes only a commentary about the existing burden<br />
which the deposit costs are carrying in the banking system. It is<br />
directed to that. It is in fact a commentary more on the history<br />
of interest rates than the future.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Keating, you were speaking earlier about the<br />
existing 13.5 per cent ceiling for loans that were already<br />
out, grandfathering for the life of those loans. Can you<br />
guarantee that someone who has a thirty year loan will always<br />
have,! through the banks, will always have that 13.5 per cent<br />
ceiling no matter what change of government there might be or<br />
what may deregulation<br />
KEATING: I don't think I could go that far.<br />
JOURNALIST: You said before that grandfathering<br />
KEATING: Well, they. are in for the period of the loan.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr West, the fact that you have been able to<br />
reach this accommodation with the banks, does this mean that<br />
you no longer position of a month or so ago when you said<br />
the banks were making so much profit that they could easily<br />
afford to subsidise the housing industry far more than they are?<br />
WEST: Well, if you look at the stiatement you will see we are<br />
going to put a maximum of 60 million dollars, over the 12 months,<br />
to match our 120, if indeed we have to go to 120. We may not have<br />
to go 120, so the banks may not have to go as far as 60. That<br />
will depend upon the level of interest rates in the future.<br />
But maybe, if we are only subsidising the 48 million for the<br />
first quarter, that is the June quarter. But no, I said<br />
that the banks could afford to pick up a share of the burden<br />
and that is in fact what they are doing in this statement.<br />
JOURNALIST: To your satisfaction?<br />
WEST: Well, I am never satisfied with anything.<br />
KEATING: Let me make this point, that the deposits There is<br />
about 24 billion deposits in the banking system. And to the<br />
extent that the ceiling might have prevented the banks from<br />
charging what would otherwise have been a higher market rate*<br />
of interest, even in terms of the kinds of figure that I<br />
mentioned, indicative figure of 15 and a half percent, on<br />
24 billion two per cent is going to cost the bank profits of<br />
about 480 million. Now we are talking here of a subsidy of<br />
120 million which is a subsidy contingent upon the continuing<br />
competitiveness of the deposit instrument in the contemporary<br />
interest rate environment. So it may not be 120 million. </p>
<p>JOURNAL~ IST: Mr Keating, will some of that 120 million be<br />
financed by 40 million savings from the underspending on the<br />
FHOS? KEATING: Underspending on the FHOS Scheme is again an<br />
instance of the fact that we have the FHOS Scheme paying<br />
a subsidy on, helping to subsidise loans. But the reason<br />
for the underspending is of course that there were no loans<br />
to match the subsidies. There just weren't enough loans.<br />
That just highlights what will happen with the availability<br />
of loans, those savings on FHOS will have to be factored down.<br />
JOURNALIST: Will there be any change in the FHOS?<br />
KEATING: Not in the decisions in this package.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Keating, would you be approaching the States<br />
with a view to relaxing the lending restrictions on building<br />
socities? KEATING: Building societies have got to make their way in<br />
the market the same as banks. And the States will have to make<br />
their own judgements. Some of the States have already deregulated<br />
even to existing borrowers, building society rates. Indeed, some<br />
of the state banks are already paying a market-oriented rate<br />
of interest. So that is a matter for their judgement.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, why did it take the Cabinet so long<br />
to reach a decision?<br />
PM: Two reasons. Firstly, the issue, as I think will be agreed<br />
by everyone, is an exceedingly complex one. And there were<br />
a variety of views, but the longer the discussion went on, the<br />
more there was of drawing towards this general position. The<br />
second point, Mike, is that we were concerned with, not just<br />
looking at the question of the savings banks and what we<br />
were doing there. But we were also concerned with considering<br />
a range of proposals, those put up by the Minister for Housing,<br />
as to what could be done other than just the interest rate<br />
area to try and ensure that this Government did everything it<br />
could to try and help in the area of low income housing. So<br />
there were a range of proposals which went to that issue. And<br />
we had to do two things in that area. We had to examine each<br />
one in terms of its effectiveness, how it would best be targeted.<br />
And second we had to consider budgetary impact. Now, all those<br />
things, if you are going to deal properly with them, naturally<br />
took a fair bit of time.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, just to clarify. Are you saying the<br />
full gravity of the situation, the crisi ' s confronting the<br />
housing industry, only became apparent to the Government<br />
this week?<br />
PM: No. We were aware of a grave situation earlier. That<br />
is why, in fact, the Minister for Housing earlier put, prepared<br />
a sub~ mission. why, when we first considered that, the Treasurer<br />
was authorised to have discussions with the banking system.<br />
And it was then following our consideration of that, and the<br />
Treasurer's discussions with the banking system, that we<br />
then got the measure of what we could be looking at in<br />
86-87. We knew it was going to be bad when, I repeat what<br />
I said before, the IPC figures were not looking too good. </p>
<p>PM cont: I think the suggestion of something of the order<br />
of 122,000, and that was based on 4.9 billion by the savings<br />
banks. Now within a matter of just, as I said before, about<br />
four weeks, that figure of savings banks camne down from 4.9<br />
billion to, what the Treasurer was told just this week of<br />
possibly less than 3 billion. And that was in a matter of<br />
the order of four weeks. So it was a grave situation. But<br />
the extent of it, and may I say not only the extent of it<br />
but the attitude of the banks as to their capacity to maintain<br />
the savings banks' operation came to us in all its gravity<br />
as a result of the discussions the Treasurer had-this week.<br />
KEATING: I think you are probably looking at really a radical<br />
change in the nature of savings banks and thrift institutions.<br />
And I think you will be seeing a fundamental change that might<br />
have otherwise taken place<br />
JOURNALIST: I was just trying to establish when the Government<br />
first became aware that the loss of 50,000 jobs was a real risk<br />
unless urgent action was taken. The 50,000 figure seems to<br />
absolutely critical.<br />
PM: I think with firmness t~ his week. The Treasurer was faced<br />
with a situation which he reported to me that really what<br />
we were looking, Peter, was the possibility of savings banks<br />
virtually closing down operations in regard to new lending<br />
in the housing area. Now, when you consider the importance<br />
that they have in the total lending situation then it was<br />
clear that if that figure was right, then we are certainly<br />
looking at a maximum of 100,000. We were aware, as I said<br />
earlier, we were aware before that that it was bad. I don't<br />
think we became entirely convinced of the absolute ravity of<br />
the situation, of 100,000 or less, until this week.<br />
KEATING: The Commonwealth Savings Bank has an enormous<br />
portfolio of existing loans, so they have got a massive<br />
of repayments which would have been available for lending<br />
this year. So in a sense, in this diminished picture<br />
of lending, the Commonwealth BAnk would have had an even<br />
task which would have said quite a lot about the diminution<br />
in the level of activity of the other banks. which had not had<br />
of course the same saving bank and housing history as the<br />
Commonwealth Savings Bank has. So, the figures mask somewhat<br />
a more dramatic decline for the other banks. And I think<br />
that also is a factor.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
