<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8982</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT TO PARLIAMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ KEATING, MP</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/09/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008982.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL: 28. Sep. 93 15: 57 No. 020 P. 01<br />
I,,<br />
l PRIME MINISTER<br />
STATEMENT TO PARLIAMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER,<br />
THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
VISIT TO THE UNITED STATES, THE UNITED KINGDOM, IRELAND,<br />
FRANCE AND MONACO<br />
Mr Speaker<br />
I wish to inforn the House of the outcome of my visit to the United States, the United<br />
Kingdom, Ircland, France and Monaco between 1I and 24 September.<br />
During the visit, I dealt with a number of issues which will have a profound bearing on<br />
Australia's trading interests and future prosperity. on our national identity, and on how<br />
we and othcrs see our place in the world.<br />
I<br />
These are all big questions, and it is important that we get them right.<br />
At a time of great fluidity in international affairs, we now face fundamental questions<br />
about the structure of the world trading system.<br />
The opportunity to secure a successful conclusion of the Uruguay Round is now close<br />
at hand, but the outcome is far from assured.<br />
The APEC forum, which Australia has done so much to bring forward, is now poised<br />
to develop into a valuablc framework for promoting trade and investment in the Asia-<br />
Pacific region.<br />
The United States Congress will soon decide whether or not to approve the North<br />
American Free Trade Agreement with far-reaching repercussions either way on the US<br />
trade policy stance.<br />
At this pivotal moment in the international trading environment, it is important that<br />
Australians are fully aware of the impact that decisions about future trade stnicturs<br />
will have on our interests.<br />
Mr Speaker<br />
At stake is nothing less than the future prosperity of our country. </p>
<p>28. Sep. 93 15: 57 No. 020 P. 02/ 1<br />
2<br />
At stake is our capacity to provide employment for the next generation of Australians.<br />
More than ever before, Australia is on its own internationally, fending for itself in a<br />
competitive and challenging international environment<br />
But we are seen internationally as a modem soicty with many assets to help us make<br />
our way successfully in the world.<br />
Our recent achievements in fostering a tolerant and diverse multicultural society and in<br />
executig a series of major reforms of the Australian economy highlight our capacity to<br />
change, and to play an increasing role in regional and international affairs.<br />
These subjects were the main thrust of my discussions in each of the capitals I visited.<br />
Mr Spcakcr<br />
I visited Washington at a time Australia's most pressing interests coincide with much<br />
that is promincn on the American agenda.<br />
The future of the Uruguay Round, the development of APEC and the creation of<br />
NAFTA arc all matters to which President Clinton, his Administration and the<br />
Congress are giving high priority.<br />
It was a very useful time to be able to put Australia's view, and to represent our<br />
interests on these issues.<br />
Given the enormous stakes involved, it was important to be able to discuss with the US<br />
Administration and Congress what sort of policy and institutional framework will best<br />
maintain and strengthen the highly valuable economic Linkages which now operate<br />
between East Asia, Oceania and North America.<br />
So strong have thcse linkages between North America and the Western Pacific become<br />
over the last decade that today there is a higher degree of trade integration among the<br />
members of APEC than there is among the members of the European Community,<br />
or among the three North American economies, or among the East Asian economies<br />
considcmd separately.<br />
And while the United States market remains vitally important for most East Asian<br />
economics, I found a growing awareness in the Administration and in Congrpss that<br />
East Asia has also become an increasingly important market for US exports.<br />
Indeed, less than a decade ago more than one third of Western Paciric exports went to<br />
the United States.<br />
Today the proportion is leis than one quarter.<br />
TEL </p>
<p>TEL 3<br />
Over the same period the proportion of US exports which go to the Western Pacific<br />
has risen to wcll over one quarter, on a par with those to the NAFTA partners and well<br />
ahead of exports to the EC.<br />
Since the mid eighties the trend rate of growth of US exports to the Westen Pacific<br />
has beeti ec times the rate of growth of Western Pacific exports to thc United<br />
States. This rapid trade growth in the region and the prosperity it produces would be gravely<br />
threatened, in my view, if in coming decades North America and the Western Pacific<br />
went separate ways in trade and strategic alignments.<br />
I am glad to be able to report that the Clinton Administration is as convinced of the<br />
importance of the East Asia region as we ourselves have become.<br />
I had very productive discussions in Washington with President Clinton, with Secretary<br />
of Stawe Christopher, Defense Secretary Aspin, US Trade Representative Kantor,<br />
Treasury Secretary Bentsen, Director of Central Intelligence Woolsey and with senior<br />
Congressional leaders including Senate Majority Leader Mitchell, Senate Minority<br />
Leader Dole and House Speaker Foley.<br />
My ineeting with President Clinton was exceptionally useful.<br />
I was impressed by the vigour, imagination and resolve with which he is going about<br />
the task of rebuilding American competitiveness and American society.<br />
We affirmned in our meeting the continuing vitality and relevance of Australia's bilateral<br />
relationship with the United States.<br />
Despite the great changes in die world brought about by thc end of the Cold War,<br />
fundamental Australian interests continue to be engaged in our relationship with the<br />
United States in our defence alliance, in the mutually beneficial processes or policy<br />
consultation we enjoy on a wide range of issues, and in our strong commercial ties.<br />
Despitc our bilateral access problems, which I discussed with Ambassador Kantor and<br />
congressional leaders, the US market remains Australia's second biggest.<br />
And the United States is the largest source of foreign investment in Australia and the<br />
most important destination for Australian investment abroad.<br />
Mr Speakcr<br />
My meeting with the President produced three important results.<br />
First, we agreed to work closely together for a successful outcome of the informal<br />
APEC leaders' mceting in Scatilc in November. T2EL8:. Sep. 93 15: 5? No. 020 P. 0 </p>
<p>TEL: 28. Sep. 93 15: 5? No. 020 P. 04/ I<br />
4<br />
This historic meeting, involving leaders of the key Asia-Pacific economies the fastest<br />
growing area of the world will help define an Asia-Pacific economic community and<br />
give political authority and weight to APEC.<br />
The President noted Australia's vital contribution to the development of APEC.<br />
I was impressed by the President's commitment to the Asia-Pacific economic<br />
community, and by the unanimity with which hehis Cabinet and the Congressional<br />
leadership in both Houses and both parties expreised their conviction that the United<br />
States should assign a higher priority to its trading relations with the Western Pacific.<br />
Secondly, we agreed that it was very important to world growth and jobs to achieve a<br />
successful and balanced outcome to the Uruguay Round by the 15 December deadline<br />
for Congress's " fast track" approval, and that any move by the European Community<br />
to re-open the Blair House accord on agriculture would seriously jeopardise the whole<br />
Round. The United States has pressed hard in favour of freer trade during seven long years of<br />
thc GATT negotiations.<br />
It has been a policy stance of great value to Australia.<br />
But I was convinccd by my discussions in Washington that 15 December is a real<br />
deadline for Congress, and that, if we cannot achieve an acceptable package by then,<br />
Congress as well as the Administration will turn their attention away from global<br />
solutions to trade problems and towards more regional approaches.<br />
Thirdly, the President and Ambassador Kantor recognised Australia's conccrn about<br />
the damage that EEP subsidies cause our grain exports, and said they would make<br />
every effort to minimise the effect on Australia's interests.<br />
They noted the Administration's decision to stay out of the Indonesian market as a<br />
bonafide of their sincerity in this regard.<br />
They explained that the EEP was aimed at counteracting European subsidies, and that<br />
the only fully effectivc way to reduce the impact on Australia's grain exports was to<br />
conclude the Uruguay Round as soon as possible.<br />
Mr Speaker<br />
In New York, I addressed a meeting of the Asia Society and had a meeting with the<br />
Secretary-Gencral of the United Nations, Mr Boutros Boutros-Ohali.<br />
I told the Secretary-Gcneral that Australia welcomed the new possibilities for the work<br />
of the United Nations which have arisen with thc disappearance of Cold War<br />
constraints. I said that, as a foundation member of the United Nations, Australia is fully committed<br />
to the ideals of the Charter and wants to see those ideals prosper. </p>
<p>TEL: 28. Sep. 93 15: 57 No. 020<br />
I noted that Australia was committed to peacekeeping, with around 600 Australians<br />
serving in Cambodia, Somalia and in other operations around the globe.<br />
We were also a substantial financial contributor to the United Nations, paying in full<br />
and on time.<br />
I told the Secretary-General that Australia would-continue to contribute resources and<br />
ideas to the Organisation.<br />
T" Cheo ompoersat tricncge nfotr e Pxeaamcpe" le, eoxfa tmhiisn icnogn tpreibaucteikoene pisi nSge naantdo rc oEnvaflnicst's r edsoocluumtioenn, t which is<br />
being launched in New York this week.<br />
I also made it clcar to the Secretary-General, however, that the United Nations<br />
Organisation itself had to make sure it was operating as efficiently and effectively as it<br />
could especially in its administration and in its peacekeeping operations if it was to<br />
maintain the international support needed to fulfil its great potential.<br />
Mr Spcakc. r<br />
My visit to the United Kingdom, the first by an Australian Prime Minister since 1987,<br />
provided an opportunity to help reinforce and rshape this old and still very valuable<br />
relationship. I had a long and productive meeting in London with Prime Minister Major.<br />
World trade issues were again the main theme of my discussions.<br />
I told Prime Minister Major how much Australia appreciatcd the very constructive and<br />
positive role Britain has played within the EC, and more widely, in pushing the cause<br />
of freer world markets and the multinational trading system.<br />
We both underlined the importance of a successful and balanced outcome to the<br />
Uruguay Round for jobs and growth.<br />
We agreed that 15 December is a real deadline for the Round.<br />
We also discussed the strong and growing economic ties betwecn Britain and<br />
Australia. Britain is Australia's fourth largest trading partner, and our eighth largest export<br />
market. It is the second largest source of foreign invcstment in Australia.<br />
In turn, we arc the fourth largest foreign investor in the UK, ranking above Japan. </p>
<p>TEL: 28. Sep. 935 15: 57 NO. 020 P. 06;<br />
6<br />
Prime Minister Major and I agreed that there was much to build on and to develop in<br />
this area.<br />
We noted that an important Australia-UK trade and investment conference, to be held<br />
in Melbourne in January next year, will help to maintain the impetus for growth in our<br />
commercial relationship.<br />
Mr Speaker<br />
I also spoke to Prime Minister Major about Australia's constitutional arrangements.<br />
I said publicly in London that it is not because our affections; for Britain are reduced or<br />
the friendship between us frailer, or our respect and admiration for the institutions<br />
Britain has bequeathed us in any way diminished, that Australia is considering the<br />
option of becoming a republic.<br />
And I also said that our friendship for Britain would be all the stronger for our<br />
becoming a republic, as any friendship is stronger for being more mature.<br />
Mr Major Prime Minister of a Conservative British Government and Mr Hurd, his<br />
Foreign Secretary who was on a parallel visit to Australia, both made publicly and<br />
privately clea that the matter or Australia's constitutional arrangements is one for the<br />
Government, people and Parliament of Australia and the Queen of Australia.<br />
They both assert, quite correctly, that the modern, mature relationship between Britain<br />
and Australia will remain quite unaffected by our moves to become a republic.<br />
Mr Speaker<br />
I was rceived by Her Majesty the Queen at Balmoral Castle on 18 September.<br />
In accordane with longstanding convention, the discussion between us must remain<br />
confidential. But I am able to say I explained to Her Majesty that, notwithstanding thc detp respect<br />
and warm affection felt towards her by the Australian people, there was a growing<br />
feeling in Australia that constitutional changes should be made to allow the<br />
appointment of an Australian Head of State.<br />
I outlined to Her Majesty thc various steps that would be involved in such a process,<br />
including the necd for a referendum to approve constitutional amendments.<br />
I said thc Australian Governent's view was that, if approved by the Australian people<br />
at a rererendum, it would be appropriate for Australia to become a republic by the<br />
centenary of Federation in 2001.<br />
I told H1cr Majcsty that. in such a situation, Australia would remain a member of the<br />
Commonwealth of Nation and that the Australian people would warmly welcome </p>
<p>T2EL8: . Sep. 93 15: 57 No. 020 P. 07<br />
7<br />
visits to Australia by Her Majesty as Head of the Commonwealth and as the Queen of<br />
the United Kingdom.<br />
HeIr Majesty authorised mc to say that she would, of course, act on the advice or her<br />
Australian Ministers, as she always has, and on any decision made by the Australian<br />
people. Mr Speaker<br />
The issues involved in the creation of a Federal Republic of Australia are complex.<br />
They require thoughtful and informed debate.<br />
But as a result of my discussions in Britain it is clear that, whatever the outcome of the<br />
debate in Australia, whatever thc form of constitutional arrangements on which the<br />
Australian people finally dccide, both Her Majesty and the British Govermecnt regard<br />
these arrangentsL, properly. as entirely matters to be decided by the Ausirdlian<br />
people themnselves.<br />
And it is also clear that the results of any constitutional changes are not seen as a threat<br />
and will not threaten the warmth of the relationship between Australia and Britain,<br />
or the personal respect and affection in which Her Majesty is held.<br />
It is my Government's firm intention, Mr Speaker, to ensure that, throughout the<br />
period that Australians are debating new constitutional arrangements, our existing links<br />
with the monarchy arc maintained and exercised with dignity and respect.<br />
In that regard, I am pleased to announce that I discussed with Her Majesty an<br />
invitation I have extended to the Prince of Wales to visit Australia early in 1994<br />
following proposals by several State Governments.<br />
The invitation has bccn accepted.<br />
His Royal Highness will arrive in Sydney on 25 January, and visit in addition to New<br />
South Wales, Tasmania, Western Australia and Queensland.<br />
Mr Speaker<br />
My visit to Ireland cnabled me to mark the very important contribution which Ireland<br />
has made to the cultural, social and political development of this country.<br />
The peopic-to-peopic links between us arc still strong and vigorous.<br />
In Dublin I had the honour of addressing the D~ ail, and I had extensive discussions with<br />
the Taoiseach, Mr Reynolds, and leaders of the othcr Irish political parties.<br />
My discussions focused again on thc outcome for the Uruguay Round, on which<br />
Ireland has been one of the European countries most resistant to change in the area of<br />
agriculture. TEL </p>
<p>TL: 28. Sep. 93 115: 57 No. 020 P. 08/:<br />
I put the view forcefully to Irish political leaders, and to business people at a dinner<br />
hosted by the Irish-Australian Business Association, that Ireland, with its growing<br />
industrial exports, will he best served by ensuring that we gct an acceptable outcome to<br />
the Uruguay Round.<br />
That in turn depended, I said, on the integrity of the Blair House accord on agricultur<br />
being fully mlaintained.<br />
I also made the point that, although our trade is growing, die warmth of people-topeoplc<br />
relations between Australia and Ireland is not matched by our commercial links.<br />
I said I hoped that companies in each country would incrwaingly use the oth cr as a<br />
base to develop links into Asia and Europe respectively.<br />
The warmth displayed by the Irish people towards me as head of the Government of<br />
Australia was quite profound.<br />
In all parts of the country I visited, there was a spontaneous expression of warm<br />
welcome and good wishes towards Australia and the Australian people.<br />
It is quite a phenomcnon that thc cultural and emotional links between Australia and<br />
this small country in Europe exist as strongly as they do.<br />
It Is something Australians should value and continue to nurture.<br />
Mr Speaker<br />
On my way fromn Ireland to Monaco for thc Sydney Olympic bid, I stopped for several<br />
hours in France and visited Villers-Bretonineux, thc. site of the memorial to the 46,000<br />
Australians 18,000 without a known grave who died on the We-stern Front during<br />
the First World War.<br />
Like all who have visited the military graveyards of France, I was reminded of the.<br />
courage and devotion of those young Australians who fought and died in that terrible<br />
war and the huge loss this nation suffcred on the French battlefields.<br />
I was also reminded that the tragedy of which they were victims arose, in large part,<br />
from the selfish and narrow nationalism which has so often scarred this century.<br />
We havc the opportunity, as the century ends. to do things hctter, to create broader,<br />
more inclusive economic structures which will generate new growth and new jobs<br />
around the globe by mnaximising trading opportunities for all countries.<br />
If the international community rails in its efforts to resolve the Uruguay Round by mid-<br />
December, there are other options5 available but, as all those I spoke to on my visit<br />
agrecdi, they are not such good options.<br />
Mr Speaker TEL </p>
<p>T: 23. Sep. 93 15: 57 N0.020<br />
9<br />
The International Olympic Committee's decision to awar the Olympic Games for the<br />
year 2000 to Sydncy was a wonderful outcome for this country.<br />
The Olympics are bound to be a marvellous moment in the life of the city and the<br />
nation: a celebration of international youth and sport in a young country with<br />
extraordinary sporting traditions.<br />
All of Australia's attractions will be on show to billions of people around the world as<br />
we approach the centenary of the Commonwealth's creation.<br />
The Olympics can also be a defining moment in our history in the one hundredth year<br />
of our nationhood, a brilliant opportunity to celebrate our achievements and define our<br />
place in the region and the world.<br />
Thc Olympics will generate economic growth and jobs well beyond Sydney itself.<br />
The IOC's decision was a trbute to all those who worked so hard to put together an<br />
outstanding bid.<br />
My wife and T werc delighted to participatc: in the bid's presentation to thc IOC, and<br />
were &amp; ratified that the Government was able to indicate its material support for the bid.<br />
It is a tribute to the breadth of support for the Games among the Australian community<br />
demonstrated so memorably by the tens of thousands of people who showed their<br />
enthusiasm in Sydney on Friday morning.<br />
In a wider sense, Mr Speaker, the IOC's decision is also a tribute to the society we<br />
have created here its social equity, cultural diversity, tolerance and its sophistication<br />
and efficiency.<br />
Sydney's approach was set iiprt. from others by its technical excellence and by its<br />
commitment to the athletes themselves and to the ideals of the Olympic movement.<br />
All the people involved in the bid deserve the warmest congratulations and thanks of<br />
this House.<br />
More than that, Mr Speaker, they deserve the continuing support of all Australians<br />
government, business and the community in the seven ycars of hard work that still lie<br />
ahead of us.<br />
I can say on behalf of the Commonwealth Government that they will have Lhat support.<br />
Mr Speaker<br />
I began by saying that my visit to the United States and Europe took place at a time or<br />
great consequence for the world economy a Lime when new% p atterns are being<br />
ceated, and when great decisions are beig formed.<br />
TEL </p>
<p>TEL: 28. Sep. 93 15: 57 No. 0210<br />
Within the next twelve weeks alone we will have the first meeting of the leaders of the<br />
Asia-Pacific economy community, we shall enjoy success or suffer failure in the<br />
Uruguay Round, and we will have, by the year's end, a surer sense of whether recovery<br />
can take hold in Europe anid Japan, and strengthen in the United States.<br />
It is a decisive time in world economic affairs, Mr Speaker. and it comes as Australia is<br />
achiev'ing greater international recognition.<br />
Sydney's Olympic win reflects this most draatically, but it is also reflected in Mr<br />
Clinton's generous praise of Australia's role in forging APEC, and in the respect<br />
accorded to Australia's views in the Uruguay Round as the leader of thc Cairns Group<br />
of fair agriculture traders.<br />
Mr Speaker<br />
There is a responsibility on all of us to recognse that we are in a bigger game a game<br />
with bigger prizes but with new and tougher rules.<br />
T1he world is offering us great opportunities, but to takc advantage of them we must<br />
continue to be flexible and competitive at home.<br />
We must continue to seek national cohesion and strength.<br />
We cannot seiz the opportunities thc world offers us if we cannot agree on the<br />
fundamental instrument of national economic policy, the Budget.<br />
We cann~ ot sciiz those opportunities if we cannot reach a satisfactory and enduring<br />
agreement on the implementation of the High Court's decision to recognise a form of<br />
Aborigial title.<br />
We cannot seize those opportunities if our workplace relations are not free to evolve<br />
towards outcomes based on bargaining.<br />
To selLe those opportunities we need to renew our commitment to change, and our<br />
commitment to the reforms necessary to meet the imperatives of the ncw global order.<br />
It will help us in this regard if wc recognise the success of the changes we have already<br />
made how well we are doing in the world; how much more competitive wc have<br />
made ourselves; how much the chances which now present themselvcs are only<br />
chances becausc of the changes we have made; how we have made them while also<br />
making Austrdlia a tolerant, sophisticated and progressive society with few cquals in<br />
the world and how much better wc can make it if we put aside sectional interest and<br />
parochialism and work together as a nation.<br />
CANBERRA 28 September 1993 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
