<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>188</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R.G. MENZIES AT AMERICAN-AUSTRALIAN LUNCHEON, NEW YORK, 6TH JUNE, 1960</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/06/1960</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000188_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINIST...' THE RT. HON. R. G.<br />
MENZIJLS AT CAANN -AU3TRAL I4IN LUNCHEON, NE.!<br />
Y0iu( 6TH_ JU 196o<br />
Sir, having listened to you, having listened to Tom,<br />
having collected a little of the atmosphere, I want to say what<br />
a pleasure it is for a practising politician to find himself in<br />
such a completely non-political atmosphere.<br />
Governor Dewey made some very pleasant remarks about<br />
me. I just want to say to you that I'm glad thiat he did, because<br />
I feel t:' at he owes those remarks to me. In 1948, ihen I shared<br />
the gift of false prophesy with Roy Howard and all of the<br />
thousands and thousands of people who wrote to his orders, I went<br />
all the way at my own expense from New York to Syracuse to hear<br />
Tom Dewey at a railway station, And having heard him, I went<br />
all the way back to New York quite satisfied t'aat he was going<br />
to win. . Jhich goes to shnw, doesn't it, what extraordinary<br />
results can happen in a country like the United States, so<br />
backward as not to have compulsory voting.<br />
But it really is the most fascinating thing in the<br />
world for a man who comes from a country where politics is conducted,<br />
as you know, with a high courtesy, never a rude remark,<br />
never an ugly thought or a hard word, to come over here in a<br />
presidential election year, And of course I should love to be<br />
able to tell all of you who will be on the ticket when the vote<br />
comes. I've had it right from the horse's mouth, or rather I<br />
should say, right from the mouths of horses. I know of at least<br />
three absolute stone certainties for the Democratic nomination;<br />
and as for the vice-president, wel, permutations and combinations<br />
couldn't go far enough to e ' Vlain how many people are<br />
undoubtedly certain to be chosen,<br />
I am sorry I can't wait long enough to attend one of<br />
these conventions of yours t-sit in the gallery and listen to<br />
the brass band. Because really in 1948, having gone up north to<br />
listen to Tom, having gone out to Indianapolis to listen to Mr.<br />
Truman, having got back to New York and being about to go back<br />
to London to pick up my wife and daughter, I paid $ 2o50 ( did I<br />
ever tell you about this?) to go to Madison Square Garden and<br />
hear Henry Uallace. It cost me about a hundred dollars to hear<br />
Tom Dewey; about two hundred dollars to hear Harry Truman and<br />
$ 2.50 to hear Henry J. allace. And it was a great night a<br />
wonderful night. There were bands, there were people who gave<br />
a very goci imitation of the Andrew Sisteis, crooning int a<br />
microphone. Paul Robeson was in the chair and he sang his opening<br />
speech to the tune of Old Man River that was worth the<br />
$ 2.50 in itself and then Henry came out with the spotlight,<br />
and a lock of hair and he made a policy speech. Ten minutes<br />
consisted of four sentences interspersed with the most tremendous<br />
volume of applause and the rustling of five-dollar bills as they<br />
fell into the collection bags. I went home writh my mouth<br />
watering. I began to work out what I might have been worth ' t<br />
the same sort of tariff.<br />
But I remember that the fourth sentence of this speech<br />
consisted of these words: "' Je stand for light, not darkness."<br />
Now that's a very good cbservation. And as my old lawryer's<br />
instinct asserted itself I thought I would love to get some<br />
further and better particulars of what that might mean. So as we<br />
walked out into the great peace of the starry night, out of<br />
Madison Square Gardens, I spoke to a neighbour who was walking<br />
out, and I said to him with my most courteous manner: " Excuse me<br />
sir, I'm a foreigner here, I wonder if you could help me. Now<br />
when Mr. dallace said that he stood for light, not darkness,<br />
was he adumbrating possibly the nationalization of the gas light<br />
industry?". And my neighbour looked at me with that contempt<br />
that is reserved for foreigners, and he said: " Say, it's easily<br />
seen you are a foreigner." And he left me for dead. </p>
<p>Now Tom Dewey has said some rather magnificent things<br />
about the position of Australia. I hope they were taken down;<br />
I think I might use them about the end of next year, when, in<br />
the inscrutible wisdom of Providence there will be another<br />
election. But they were very complimentary words. I think that<br />
in substance, leaving out the bits about myself, they were quite<br />
true. I don't know that there has been a decade in the<br />
history of my own country that has seen such astonishing development.<br />
But development, of course, particularly in a young<br />
country, a country with a small population, a country which in<br />
order to build up its population must not only provide firstclass<br />
living conditions for its own people, but must have a<br />
large movement of migration. One of the great problems when you<br />
have that is that you get the pressure on your resources, an<br />
over-demand on capital, a tremendous pressure of demand for all<br />
sorts of social facilities which gives rise almost chronically<br />
to inflationary conditions. Now that has been one of the great<br />
problems in Australia4 how to maintain the rate of development,<br />
how to give expression to this enormous desire to unlock the<br />
resources of the country and at the same time preserve a degree<br />
of stability in the currency which will produce confidence in<br />
the minds of investors, both at home and abroad, and do justice<br />
to those many, many people who live on fixed incomes.<br />
And this has been, economically, one of the very<br />
greatest tasks that a government could confront, and we have<br />
encountered it we have sometimes encountered it successfully,<br />
sometimes we haven't had all the success we might have liked.<br />
Sometimes there have been circumstances outside Australia altogether,<br />
which have given rise to the most enormous pressures,<br />
like those which followed on the outbreak of the Korean War, for<br />
example. But by and large, I do look back with great pride on<br />
the measure of stability that has been achieved. I thought you<br />
might be interested to know of our last experience in this field,<br />
because about a year ago we began to see strong symptoms of<br />
inflation, a cost inflation bearing very heavily on our export<br />
industries in particular, wages high and rising, a degree of<br />
employment which might be called almost over-full employment,<br />
with all that that involved in the turnover of labor, inability<br />
to maintain the ordinary disciplines of employment. Therefore<br />
we decided that we ought to take some steps about it.<br />
We have the great benefit in Australia of compulsory<br />
arbitration. You go in for a different way of settling your<br />
matters. I don't know whether it is any less expensive than<br />
ours, but at any rate ours comes high. And in the course of<br />
the calendar year 195' 9, the Commonwealth Arbitration tribunal had<br />
added to the wages bill, first of all by an increase in what we<br />
call the basic wage, and then by an increase in marginal rates of<br />
pay. It added in one period a total of about œ CA165,0070OO<br />
œ_ A170, OOO, OOO to the annual wages and salaries bill.<br />
Now in a country of 10,000,000 people that11 was a very<br />
very considerable injection of inflationary pressure. And so<br />
this year we decided we would have to do one or two things that<br />
were different. For the first time the Government, which has<br />
always stood neutral in these wages dispute, intervened before<br />
the Commonwealth tribunal and put up a powerful case for making<br />
no further change in the basic wage. In other words we said the<br />
whole economy of the country needs a period of time of a year to<br />
absorb what has already been done, and in the long run you won't<br />
be helping anybody if you add to the inflationary pressure and<br />
see the price level rising and the value of wages being eroded<br />
in consequence. And although this intervention of ours, I can<br />
assure you, wasn't the most popular action of our lives, it<br />
proved to be uncommonly successful, and the Commonwealth tribunal<br />
acted upon it and said " No change". Now that in itself is quite<br />
an historic event in Australia and I think must have a steadying<br />
effect on the economy generally. </p>
<p>3.<br />
At the same time we have found that for various reasons<br />
it had been necessary in some earlier years to budget for a<br />
deficit in order to prevent certain signs at various periods of<br />
some minor recession from developing, and we had budgeted for a<br />
deficit. This time we said, and I hope we will be able to perform<br />
it popularly, that we would not budget for a deficit in 16o.<br />
-61. That has been loudly applauded by hundreds of thousands of<br />
peoplo who will loudly object to it when the time comes, But<br />
we have nailed our colors to that mast.<br />
And in the third place, as you know, we have had for<br />
years now a pretty severe system of import liceonsing in order<br />
to protect our overseas balance, Import licensing the sole<br />
international justification for which is to protec our balance,<br />
not to be used for some tariff purpose, that is an entirely<br />
different matter. Tariff ought to look after that. But import<br />
licensing, to restrain the overall volume of imports so that we<br />
wouldn't see our overseas balances running down. And the<br />
measures taken in the past have been so successful that this<br />
yecr we have been able to announce the virtual termination of<br />
import licensing. That, of course, not only means that there<br />
will be a considerably greater inward flow of goods, plant, all<br />
of w,. hich will tend to have a counter-inflationary effect, but it<br />
also means that our trading relations with other countries in<br />
the world become wider, more flexible and morc satisfactory all<br />
round; because import licensing was very, very unpopular with<br />
some people and its abolition has proved even more unpopular<br />
with others. But by and large, through these various means, we have<br />
been able, not without difficulty, not without constant scrutiny,<br />
to preserve a degree of stability, which I am happy to say has<br />
proved very effective outside Australia,<br />
J,, e do, in fact, generate a great deal of our own<br />
capital, out of our own earnings and resources, far more than<br />
people sometimes think. There must be very few countries in the<br />
world with a higher savings rate per cent of overall income than<br />
we have in Australia. I know we are regarded as light-Ihearted<br />
gambling sort of community, who think that tomorrow is another<br />
day. That is not quite true. There has been an enormous satisfaction<br />
of demand for capital out of the current earnings of<br />
industry inside Australia. But over and above that, over these<br />
last eight or nine years, the inflow of capital into Australia<br />
has been quite phenomenal. I don't necessarily mean, or merely<br />
mean monc : y borrowed by goverment on government account, from<br />
say the World Bank, or drafts from the International Monetary<br />
Fund, or whatever it may be. Putting those things on one side,<br />
and looking solely at private investment from outside Australia,<br />
in inlustry inside Australia, it has avoiag-d out, over the last<br />
eight or nine years, pretty near to œ_ Alc'Om. a year, Now of<br />
course, when I talk about a hundred million to you gentlemen,<br />
you just regard that as small change. I know that, because as<br />
I stood at the door side by side with this taciturn fellow,<br />
Floyd Blair, I shook hands very warmly with about eight or nine<br />
hundred million dollars. It was a wonderful sensation I kept<br />
looking at my hand and wondering whether any of the dollars had<br />
come off in the process. But to us an inflow of LZAlO~ m. a year<br />
is an enormous accretion to our resources, and but for that I<br />
venture to say we might have had some trouble in maintaining our<br />
immigration programme and we certainly might have had to slow um..<br />
to a certain extent, the industrial development particularly,<br />
that is going on in Australia.<br />
I know there are other parts of the British Commonwealth<br />
that don't share this view, but in the result I am dolighted<br />
to say we have had great sums of money invested in<br />
Australia by American concerns, great industries have been<br />
established, the whole motor car industry in Australia which<br />
was regarded as a pipe dream 20 years ago is deeply associated </p>
<p>with enterprise from this cohtinent. And when you consider how<br />
much that involves in employment in forward-looking employment,<br />
in a sonse of social security, in the development of ancillary<br />
industries, you will understand how pleased people like myself<br />
are to find that just as we have striven for the right conditions<br />
inside our own country, so people outside, not given to sentimental<br />
judgments only on these matters, have found this a good<br />
environment in which to invest their own skill and their own<br />
capital. Therefore it is a . Zood picture, a good story.<br />
But of course it is not the only problem we have in<br />
the world, because Australia is not only Australia: it is part<br />
of the free world. Its itinerant Prime Ministers fetch up in<br />
London and attend Prime Ministers' Conferences and discuss<br />
matters with great vigour. They turn up in Washington, and<br />
discuss the problems of South-east Asia. We are not unconcerned<br />
with what goes on in the world of course. And therofore I just<br />
want to make one broad observa~ ion to you about the state of<br />
the world: Hundreds of millions of people, let's put it quite<br />
modestly, had high hopes of the Summit, exaggerated hopes if you<br />
like, but even the most hard-headed of us would have expected<br />
that out of a Summit meeting there might come a little crack of<br />
daylight. Not a broad settlement, because at the moment we<br />
discuss symptoms far more than we discuss causes, discuss results<br />
far more than we discuss causes also, but most people, I think,<br />
hoped that som~ ething might come out, some direction about, for<br />
example, nuclear tests, where the East and the West had got<br />
already measurably close to one another, and where one would<br />
have expected that a good draft of commonsense night have overcome<br />
the outstanding difficulties so that some headway might be<br />
made. I-t~ ink that many people hoped that out of a Summit<br />
conference there might come at any rate, some moratorium in<br />
relation to the Berlin question, with all its stickiness and<br />
apparent insolubility. And therefore when the Summit failed<br />
before it be-an I venture to say that all around the world were<br />
hundreds of mcillions of people whose first instinct was of bitter<br />
disappointment, and whose second instinct was one of profound<br />
resentment. Now of course the Soviet Union, the master of propaganda,<br />
insofar as Khrushchev is still the master, which I am<br />
inclined to doubt, but the masters of propaganda will have the<br />
world believe that the Summit failed because the United States of<br />
America had flown an aircraft over Russia and had been investigating<br />
what when on. Now I remember being told m-. any years ago,<br />
when I first went to the Bar, by a very experienced judge,<br />
something like this: " I see you are getting a good deal of work."<br />
I said: " Yes sir, I am, fortunately for me at any rate." And he<br />
said: " Well, I just give you one piece of advice, I'm not pointing<br />
the bone at you because I haven't had the opportunity of<br />
hearing you, but Igive you one piece of advice: It is always<br />
permissible to think that your opponent is a crook. B~ ut it is a<br />
cardinal blunder to think that he is a fool." And t'lat is worth<br />
remiembering. It is worth remembering in this connection because<br />
to tell anybody in the world that the Summit failed because of<br />
this aircraft is to assume that that somebody is a fool, because<br />
no intelligent person would believe it. I don't suppose the<br />
Russians have ever gone in for anything like that them-iselves. Do<br />
they seriously expect anybody to believe them? Of course they<br />
don't. I have a certain crude theory about this matter. It<br />
falls into two parts: In the first place I think that the<br />
measure of unity that has been established between the President<br />
of the United States and the President of France a-nd the Prime<br />
Minister of Great Britain has made a tremendous impanct on the<br />
Soviet mind. It began to be clear to Khrushchev that perhaps he<br />
wasn't comaing out of the Summit meoting with profit and therefore<br />
it might be desirable not to attend it at all. I'll eerme back<br />
to that question of unity because I just want to say a word </p>
<p>about it. But in the second place, on his own showing, this<br />
celebrated plare came down. Of course if wasn't shot down either<br />
Providence doesn't work that way. You know the pilot comes<br />
down quite safely and all the bits and pieces come down in a neat<br />
package in the one place. VTell it is a little hard to take. But<br />
anyhow, it came down 900 miles inside the frontiers of the<br />
Soviet Union. Now just think of it as an isolated event, if we<br />
must be completely academic. Nine hundred miles is a long way;<br />
nine hundred miles of undetected flight meant that the power of<br />
the deterrent in the hands of the free world was immeasurably<br />
greater than Khrushchev had ever admitted to his own people.<br />
Because if one . could do it, a hundred could do it. If that sort<br />
of distance was feasible, then without international ballistic<br />
missiles, or whatever these new horrors may be, there was a<br />
country completely vulnerable to counter-attack. And I'll be<br />
very surprised if thaat melancholy reflection hasn't had a pretty<br />
big effect on the mind of Khrushchev or even on the mind of that<br />
gentle, soft, rather refined and angelic person Malenovsky.<br />
And so I said I would just come back for one minute to<br />
the question of unity. This is the American-Australian association,<br />
this is the United States, the greatest power in the world,<br />
Australia, one of the smallest powers in the world, Great Britain<br />
France unity is so tremendously important that we ought never<br />
to allow a day to go by without praying for it and working for<br />
it. It is so easy to differ, so easy to disagree. It is in our<br />
nature to disagree. do sometimes overlook the fact that under<br />
our system of government we insist upon disagreeing. It's the<br />
business of politics to have disagreements in your own country<br />
It is the business of Congress or of Parliam.' ent to have every<br />
possible point of view, every possible point of disagreeme-int<br />
ventilated, thrashed out, and we take all this for granted. We<br />
don't think that because we have a government and an opposition<br />
in fierce debates that we are a divided country, because we know<br />
that when it comes to the great things in the world we will be<br />
together to the last drop. Vie know that. But we are accustomed<br />
to our own forms of government. We want to be very careful I<br />
think, not to allow the virtue of our system of self-government<br />
to become a vice in the international field. To allow internal<br />
disagreements to spill over into external disputes, because<br />
these people, fabulously united, with all the instruments of<br />
propaganda at their disposal, able to change their tactics every<br />
day if they want to, still have a sort of monolithic quality<br />
about then.. which enables them to take advantage of all the<br />
differences that exist on the other side while never displaying<br />
any of their own. They will do this; they will fish in troubled<br />
waters; they will take advantage of every possible dispute.<br />
It is a matter of very great urgency for the countries<br />
which are outside the Communist orbit to settle their differences<br />
among themselves, to settle thema with the greatest possible<br />
speed. We were discussing only the other day cases in Southeast<br />
Asia, where there are unresolved arguments between neighbouring<br />
countries, each of whom has the m-, ost vital interest in<br />
not being absorbed by Cormmunist China. And yet you have outstanding<br />
differences, sometimes very griat, sometimes quite<br />
tiddly-winky, but so long as they exist then the whole machinery<br />
of the Soviet Union or of Communist China will be available to<br />
inflame then, to build them up, and thereby hope to bring aboutnot<br />
for the first time in history differences which are almost<br />
crippling if they manifest themselves in the presence of the<br />
same cormmon foe.<br />
And so I say to you gentlemen,, I think we must all do<br />
in our own way and in our o in place everything that we can to<br />
preserve the highest measure of unity on the great mattexs. And<br />
it ought not to be difficult, because we have all the great m~ atters<br />
in common. Ie have in common our trusteeship for individual<br />
freedom, and the great conflict in the world is between an a~ gros<br />
; so fom 5ol slvr indi idual eo nta<br />
we ognae re0 CVweeq naifo ddto an e~ prc ~ ooo </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
