<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5874</transcript-id>
    <title>AIMA EVALUATION OF GALBALLY REPORT</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/07/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005874.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
AUJSi ALI A<br />
PRIVME WVNISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA SUNDAY, 25 JULY 1982<br />
EVALUATION OF GALBALLY REPORT<br />
Four years ago, the Galbally Report presented this Government<br />
with a compelling analysis of the need for action in an<br />
area neglected for decades and a package of measures to<br />
assist migrants and ethnic communities realise their full<br />
potential in Australian society.<br />
The Report was based on the fundamental principles of<br />
equal opportunity and equal access to general services,<br />
providing special services where needed, respect for<br />
cultural diversity, and encouragement for self-help and<br />
self-reliance.<br />
The Government endorsed these principles and accepted all<br />
57 of the Report's recommendations initiating a major<br />
re-orientation of migrant services and programs, and a<br />
commitment to realising the promise of a multicultural<br />
nation. The Galbally Report was a watershed in our development as a<br />
multicultural society, but it was not the last word.<br />
Policies and programs have to be adjusted and developed.<br />
Since the Report was accepted, the Commonwealth Government<br />
has taken further initiatives in multiculturalism including<br />
establishing multicultural television on a permament basis,<br />
per capita grants to ethnic schools and a program of expanding<br />
community language courses in tertiary institutions.<br />
The Government has now received and considered the evaluation<br />
of the objectives and implementation of the Galbally Report,<br />
prepared by the Australian Institute of Multicultural Affairs.<br />
That Evaluation concludes that there has been an impressive<br />
record of implementation and that the package of measures<br />
recommended by the Calbally Report has made " a crucial<br />
contribution to the well-being of migrants and to the commitment<br />
to a multicultural nation." At the same time, achievements<br />
in some areas have been less than we had hoped.<br />
The Evaluation emphasises the n-ed for adjustment to maintain<br />
momentum, to re-adjust programs in the light of experience<br />
and changing circumstances and to undertake further major reforms.<br />
Above all, it stresses the need for greater efforts to be<br />
made to ensure that all our institut ions are responsive to<br />
Australia's ethnic and cultural diversity. </p>
<p>The Evaluation makes 89 recommendations and a number of<br />
important ancillary proposals. They cover a comprehensive range<br />
of areas and groups education, employment and the arts,<br />
welfare and the media, children and adults.<br />
The measures proposed will extend and improve special<br />
programs and services for migrants, and most importantly,<br />
they will considerably enhance equality of access and<br />
opportunity and direct assistance to those most in need.<br />
The Government has accepted the proposals almost without<br />
exception. Taken together with decisions relating to the<br />
Australia-wide extension of multicultural television which<br />
followed the Government's consideration of the Evaluation,<br />
the direct additional cost of the package of measures will<br />
be of the order of $ 21 million over the next three years.<br />
This outcome is the result of a number of significant<br />
expenditures, a number of savings where these are consistent<br />
with increased program effectiveness and a substantial<br />
re-allocation of resources.<br />
The breadth of the Evaluation's recommendations and<br />
of the Government's response is apparent in the summary of<br />
Government decisions and the statements by by my colleagues,<br />
the Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs and the<br />
Minister for Communications.<br />
The far-reaching character of the measures ' can be seen in<br />
just three of the areas covered by the Evaluation:<br />
legal reform,, the media and migrant welfare.<br />
In the area of the law, the Evaluation evidences a need<br />
for further action to end discrimination between migrants<br />
from different countries. This discrimination is incompatible<br />
with our commitment to multiculturalism, and we now commit<br />
ourselves to a substantial program of legal reform to put<br />
all migrants on an equal footing before the law. We have<br />
already amended the Electoral Act to make all migrants<br />
equal in Commonwealth electoral matters, and the States<br />
agreed that this should be uniform thoughout Australia.<br />
The Commonwealth wants an Australia-wide commencement date,<br />
and later in the year we will be reviewing progress.<br />
The Evaluation also highlights the existence of many other<br />
anachronistic Commonwealth laws, discriminating between<br />
migrants on the basis of their country of origin. Important<br />
among these is the area of Commonwealth employment. We will<br />
amend all Co: n-onwealth acts which have a nationality requirement<br />
for Commonwealth employment so that Australian citizenship is<br />
the only requirement for eligibility. Beyond this, the<br />
Attorney-General's Department will prepare a report within ./ 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
six months on all other legislation discriminating between<br />
migrants from different countries, and suggest amendments<br />
necessary to remedy the situation. On the basis of this<br />
Report we will act to end such discrimination.<br />
A second area is the media. In October 1980 multicultural<br />
television commenced transmission the only service of<br />
its kind in the world. Its introduction was surrounded<br />
by controversy but in a short space of time most of the critics<br />
have seen its merits. The Evaluation has found results of<br />
the first year and a half of multicultural television to be<br />
very encouraging. There is a high degree of public acceptance<br />
that multicultural television provides a worthwhile alternative<br />
service, and it has shown itself capable of attracting<br />
audiences of all backgrounds. The service is still at a<br />
formative stage and further progress can be made in a number<br />
of areas.<br />
The Government has accepted recommendations made by the Evaluation<br />
to achieve this, including greater use of multilingual community<br />
service announcements, a better linguistic balance and the<br />
teaching of English. There is a strong desire for multicultural<br />
television to be extended beyond Sydney and Melbourne. The<br />
signal already passes through the nation's capital, multicultural<br />
television should be extended to Canberra in 1983 and proposed<br />
that high priority be given to providing the service to Newcastle<br />
and Wollongong, and to making provision to extend it throughout<br />
Australia. Having considered the Evaluation, the Government has<br />
decided on a three-year timetable to extend multicultural<br />
television across Australia: in 1982/ 83 to Canberra and its<br />
surrounds; in 1983/ 84 to Newcastle and Wollongong, Adelaide<br />
and Brisbane; and in 1984/ 85 to Hobart, Perth and Darwin.<br />
In the area of migrant welfare the Galbally Report called on<br />
the Government to assist ethnic communities in their self-help<br />
activities.<br />
One of the key means was the funding of voluntary bodies to<br />
employ social and welfare staff through extending the grantin-<br />
aid scheme. The evidence gathered by the Evaluation shows<br />
that the strategy has been a significant success. Ethnic<br />
groups have established and extended vital welfare programs.<br />
These are proving well-used, effective and popular. This is<br />
a tribute to the capacity of ethnic communities and other<br />
voluntary orcanisations to help those in need in our society.<br />
The Government's faith in w. hat groups can do for themselves,<br />
their ability to respond fl. c: ibly and appropriately, hias<br />
been well vindicated. Over the next three years funds for<br />
the grant-in-aid scheme will be : increased so that another<br />
grants can be awarded. The general level of grants will be<br />
increased, and grant allocations will be adjusted each year<br />
to take appropriate account of anticipated changes in costs.<br />
In all, this will involve an expenditure of over $ 6 million<br />
over the next three years. / 4 </p>
<p>-4-<br />
Beyond this, we will be moving on a number of other fronts<br />
to improve the provision of welfare services to migrants.<br />
These and other measures we will introduce will consolidate<br />
and enhance what has been achieved as a result of the<br />
implementation of the Galbally Report.<br />
Australia now has a range of programs and services which<br />
make up the most comprehensive system of multicultural<br />
and migrant services in the world. It is an achievement which<br />
is important to the nation at large. It benefits and enriches<br />
the lives not only of the newest members of the community,<br />
but of all Australians. On behalf of the Government, I reiterate<br />
the commitment made four years ago to a united, just and<br />
multicultura. Australia. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
