<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7968</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF PRE-RECORDED INTERVIEW WITH THE TREASURER BY RICHARD CARLETON, 60 MINUTES, SYDNEY - 16 MARCH 1990</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/03/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007968.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
/ 7<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF PRE-RECORDED INTERVIEW WITH THE TREASURER<br />
BY RICHARD CARLETON, 60 MINUTES, SYDNEY 16 MARCH 1990<br />
E E 0 PROOF ONLY<br />
CARLETON: Prime Minister and Mr Keating thank you very<br />
much for coming to the studios tonight. I would just<br />
like to find out for the viewers the strictures under<br />
which this discussion is being recorded this evening. In<br />
21 years of interviewing Mr Keating, since he first came<br />
into the Parliament back in 1969, he has never imposed<br />
conditions on his television appearances with me. He has<br />
tonight. The Treasurer has insisted that every word he<br />
utters at this recording session is in fact broadcast.<br />
That is to say his words are not to be edited in any way.<br />
Mr Keating has made his appearance tonight conditional<br />
upon us agreeing to that. The Prime Minister has imposed<br />
no such condition. Well gentlemen, thank you very much<br />
for coming. Mr Hawke, is it not amazing, is it not<br />
amazing, that despite interest rates being what they are,<br />
terrible inflation, almost daily corporate collapses,<br />
appalling current account and foreign debt figures, that<br />
you're likely to get re-elected next week?<br />
PM: If they were the only facts that were relevant, yes,<br />
the answer is it would be amazing. But of course it's<br />
also relevant that we have record employment growth,<br />
investment at a record level as a proportion of gross<br />
domestic product, our manufacturing industry recording<br />
record levels of exports, our children now staying on in<br />
school in numbers double what they were before and<br />
the most needy in the community being compassionately<br />
cared for. Now when you put those things into the<br />
equation it's not amazing.<br />
CARLETON: And the price of that is 17 percent interest<br />
ffes?<br />
PM: Well, the price of that is not 17 percent interest<br />
rates at all. Seventeen percent interest rate is there<br />
because in fact we've had an economy that's been growing<br />
too strongly. In the last year, eight per cent growth in<br />
consumption, four per cent growth in production and Paul<br />
and I had no alternative but to slow things down<br />
somewhat. We had tight fiscal policy, tight wages policy<br />
and we had to have, in those circumstances, tight<br />
monetary policy. But the important thing is, for the<br />
voters out there, and this is what they're thinking </p>
<p>about, is they know why we did it and they know that<br />
-under our policies the rates are going to come down and<br />
they know that under the policies of our opponents an<br />
explosion of interest rates and collapse of the economy<br />
is inevitable.<br />
CARLETON: Yes, but it's much more rewarding to judge you<br />
by your results on interest rates rather than the<br />
promises of either yourself or some banks. The result on<br />
interest rates is now, after seven years, 17 percent,<br />
you're responsible.<br />
PM: Well, I am responsible too, if we're going to claim<br />
responsibility. I and the Treasurer, and our colleagues<br />
are responsible for the fact that we've had a rate of<br />
employment growth five times faster than our opponents<br />
had, twice as fast as the rest of the world, a massive<br />
reduction in unemployment and a doubling of the number of<br />
our kids staying on in school. We're responsible for<br />
those things too. And the, see what you've got to do,<br />
Richard, is understand that that electorate you're<br />
talking about there isn't single dimensional. You seem<br />
to think they are single dimensional, that they're only<br />
going to make the judgement about Paul Keating and Bob<br />
Hawke and the Labor Government on the basis of interest<br />
rates.<br />
CARLETON: But Mr Keating if 17 percent is the best you<br />
can do after seven years and they can do five per cent in<br />
Japan, isn't it time to get out of the way and make room<br />
for someone who can do better?<br />
KEATING: Well, Richard, let me take your first point up.<br />
I did this interview with you tonight on the basis that<br />
it would be like a live interview. If I do Jana Wendt<br />
live, it goes live. We're doing this I want the public<br />
to see what's actually said and not to find either your<br />
questions or my answer on the cutting room floor. So..<br />
CARLETON: And do you impose the conditions..<br />
KEATING: No, I'm giving the public a break you weren't<br />
prepared to give them.<br />
PM: clear about that.<br />
t'RLETON: in 21 years you've never imposed any<br />
condition like that one.<br />
KEATING: But this is, this is one week before an<br />
election campaign<br />
CARLETON: since 1969.<br />
KEATING: Normally we'd do this live on the Sunday<br />
evening and what we're doing is the equivalent of doing<br />
it live. How can you complain about that? </p>
<p>CARLETON: I'm not complaining, I'm simply saying..<br />
PM: You're taking a bit of time about it.<br />
CARLETON: Yes, I know but..<br />
KEATING: ( inaudible)<br />
CARLETON: I'm pointing out the unique conditions that<br />
imposed on this interview that you haven't imposed in<br />
21 years.<br />
KEATING: Just because I can't remember doing one<br />
with you Richard, one week out from the campaign and if I<br />
was doing one with Jana Wendt or anyone, it would be<br />
live.<br />
CARLETON: Well, I could remind you of 1972, 1974,<br />
PM: Oh, come on..<br />
CARLETON: 1975, 1983..<br />
KEATING: You're on the big issues, you're on the big<br />
issues Richard.<br />
CARLETON: yes, we'll go back to the point..<br />
KEATING: You're a big issues person.<br />
CARLETON: Yes, well, the big issue of course is 17<br />
percent rates produced by you after seven years. And the<br />
question was if after seven years the best you can do,<br />
when they can do five per cent in Japan, maybe it's time<br />
for you to get out of the way to make room for someone<br />
who can<br />
KEATING: We've also had twice the rate of growth per<br />
year in the last seven years than we've had in the<br />
previous seven. We've had twice the OECD average<br />
employment growth. We've had a faster, stronger,<br />
wealthier economy and when the terms of trade picked up<br />
unexpectedly in ' 87/ 8 it produced big spending effects<br />
which were met with a big interest rate effect, it's as<br />
simple as that.<br />
CARLETON: You're going to be Prime Minister for the next<br />
three years?<br />
PM: If they elect me on 24 of March, which I hope they<br />
will, then the answer is an unequivocal yes.<br />
CARLETON: For the three year term, or whatever the term<br />
of the Parliament is?<br />
PM: Well, and we have three year terms, I mean, the<br />
election in 1984 was to bring the two Houses in synch and </p>
<p>then we've had three year term, three year term, and<br />
we'll have another three year term.<br />
CARLETON: So he has to wait 24 years, a 24<br />
apprenticeship. After 21 years in the Parliament so far<br />
KEATING: I'm doing well, I'm doing well..<br />
CARLETON: and another three before he gets a crack<br />
at your job?<br />
KEATING: I'm doing well.<br />
PM: he's doing well and he's happy. The important<br />
thing is that he went into Parliament early, he's been a<br />
magnificent Treasurer and by the time that I give it away<br />
he would come to the Prime Ministership, if that's his<br />
wish and that's the election of Caucus, which I imagine<br />
it would be, then he would come to the Prime Ministership<br />
at what I would believe would be a younger than the<br />
average age of Prime Ministers in the past.<br />
CARLETON: Is he going to spend the next three years as<br />
Treasurer? PM: If he wishes to. I mean, my position is, and Paul<br />
and I discuss these things, that if he wants to remain<br />
Treasurer then, that's his position.<br />
CARLETON: If he wants Foreign Affairs can he have it?<br />
PM: If he asked for Foreign Affairs I'd have to think<br />
about it. But, on discussion<br />
KEATING: asking.<br />
PM: And he won't be asking. He regards the<br />
Treasurership, he regards the Treasurership as the next<br />
most important job.<br />
CARLETON: In October 1988, when he sent John Dawkins<br />
down the corridor to knock on your door and tell you that<br />
it was time to get out of the way to make room for him,<br />
was that a silly thing for him to have done?<br />
PM': If he'd done it, yes, it would have been and he<br />
didn't. CARLETON: What did happen?<br />
PM: Dawkins came and had a discussion with me of his own<br />
volition not sent by anyone and that discussion was<br />
reasonably amicable and, I might say from my point of<br />
view, quite definite. Much more definite than it was on<br />
the part of Mr Dawkins. </p>
<p>CARLETON: Are you happy to sit around for another three<br />
years and play second fiddle?<br />
KEATING: I'm happy to be led by the most successful<br />
Prime Minister in the post-war years. It's a pleasure to<br />
me, has been a matter of great sense of accomplishment<br />
for all of us who've been in this Cabinet. We are a very<br />
happy ship and, if I might just say, we're a very happy<br />
couple. CARLETON: Yes, but wanted his job, 17 months ago.<br />
KEATING: Oh no, oh no, I mean, look Bob and I would be<br />
-the first to admit that these jobs produce a few strains<br />
and pressures, they do. But, but we are seven years on,<br />
we are into our eighth year now and, considering the<br />
pressures we've had in this economy to pick it up from<br />
basically a recessed heap to what it is today, it's been<br />
an enormous amount of change, I think we've weathered it<br />
fantastically.<br />
CARLETON: Under what circumstances would you try to<br />
knock him of f again?<br />
KEATING: Well, Richard, you use all these crass terms.<br />
I mean, it's unbecoming of you.<br />
CARLETON: It's unbecoming of me?<br />
KEATING: Yes.<br />
CARLETON: Well, let me ask you if some of your language<br />
is becoming of a Prime Minister when you referred to the<br />
Opposition as like a dog returning to its vomit. When<br />
you use language like that<br />
KEATING: Rudyard Kipling.<br />
CARLETON: Mugs, criminals, loopy crims, stupid foul<br />
mouthed grub, piece of criminal garbage, alley cat,<br />
gigolo, perfume gigolo, scumbag, scum, thug, gutless spiv<br />
and champion liars.<br />
KEATING: Well, that's becoming<br />
PM: Treasurer or the Prime Minister?<br />
-4-<br />
KEATING: That is, they are bits and pieces of words<br />
picked up over 20 years of going through Hansard. You go<br />
through Hansard for 20 years of anyone on the Liberal<br />
side, you'll find similar terms and mostly when they were<br />
attacking me personally.<br />
CARLETON: Do you apologise for it?<br />
KEATING: I never attack them personally.<br />
CARLETON: Do you apologise for and of that? </p>
<p>KEATING: Howard, Howard, that was Howard's one success<br />
in politics in last three years. He laid that on me. I<br />
made him pay the price of losing the Prime Ministership<br />
as a result.<br />
CARLETON: Do you apologise for any of it<br />
KEATING: I thought it was moral and even swap.<br />
CARLETON: Should I ask you again?<br />
KEATING: Eh?<br />
CARLETON: Do you apologise for any of that?<br />
KEATING: Oh, I don't I'm not in the apology<br />
business, mate. Look, look, in some countries they<br />
settle their politics across the street in Lebanon they<br />
shoot each other.<br />
CARLETON: Yes, but this is not<br />
KEATING: In this country it's settled in the clearing<br />
house of pressure, the House of Representatives and it<br />
works very nicely and people like you understand well how<br />
it works you've made your living off reporting it.<br />
CARLETON: Yes.<br />
KEATING: So why denigrate the process, Richard?<br />
other people have actually lived off it.<br />
CARLETON: Do you think Australians may have had enough<br />
of your style though, enough of the foul language<br />
KEATING: No, but hang on, that's that's over I<br />
mean, you're really a big issue person aren't you? Here<br />
you are, you've got a chance one week out from an<br />
election to look at the big issues of growth, employment.<br />
I mean, you had an important place in Australian society<br />
on the ABC and you gave it up to be a pop star and now<br />
with a big cheque and now you're on to this sort of<br />
stuff. PM: You've, you've spent half this time on issues which<br />
tre irrelevant and may I say, very unfair to Paul. I<br />
mean, why don't you look at the fact that in those years<br />
in Parliament he's made a series of brilliant,<br />
penetrating speeches in Opposition and in Government,<br />
recognised a lot of people argue he's the most<br />
effective Parliamentarian there is. I mean, made a series<br />
of brilliant speeches and out of all that period you pick<br />
up some language. I mean, part of, part of the<br />
fascination of the character is that he's got a turn of<br />
phrase which a bit tough and rough.<br />
CARLETON: Yes, but </p>
<p>PM: But, but it's part of a much more broad range of<br />
capacity. Why don't you give him credit for that?<br />
CARLETON: Well sure, but all the credit in the world,<br />
Prime Minister<br />
PM: I haven't noticed it.<br />
CARLETON: But if one was to allow him to, in this<br />
context, to talk on about those subjects without being<br />
KEATING: Richard, Richard<br />
CARLETON: may I say, then the..<br />
KEATING: Richard, at least four or five of those words<br />
were said when I was accused of having an illegitimate<br />
child. What would you say? When I didn't. What would<br />
you say?<br />
CARLETON: I'd say it was pretty outrageous..<br />
KEATING: Yes, that's right, but you don't think I should<br />
have responded.<br />
CARLETON: Of course you should have responded.<br />
KEATING: Well.<br />
PM: What are you going on about?<br />
CARLETON: Well you've also got to live down the words<br />
that you use.<br />
KEATING: Well, my friend, I don't ever worry about that.<br />
Look at all this, look at those 14<br />
0PM: interview.<br />
KEATING: Look at those 14 economic statements. Look at<br />
them. They're that big you can hardly jump over them<br />
which took us six and eight months to put together.<br />
All of that, all that concentrated work which you're not<br />
even referring to.<br />
CARLETON: One of the reasons why the economy is in the<br />
present shape, because we're not manufacturing anything<br />
in this country. We're not manufacturing the cameras,<br />
' the lights, anything here<br />
PM: Let's make some facts. Let's take the facts<br />
KEATING: Not true, not true.<br />
PM: We're not manufacturing in this country? OK, let's<br />
. ook at the facts. We are in this country so </p>
<p>8.<br />
transforming our manufacturing industry that in the last<br />
four years we have had a 54 percent increase in the<br />
exports of manufactured goods. Steel industry when we<br />
came to office, BHP on the point of shutting down the<br />
steel industry. In this year, exporting three quarters<br />
of a billion worth of steel right around the world and<br />
within the next three years will be trebling that to over<br />
$ 2 billion. We are one of the most efficient producers<br />
and exporters of steel in the world. Exporting cars and<br />
motor components to Japan and the United States. In the<br />
fiercely competitive area of optical lens, we have there<br />
a factory in the suburbs of Adelaide going into the<br />
United States, the most competitive market in the world<br />
against 11 other companies and it's got over 50 percent<br />
of the market<br />
CARLETON: And a foreign debt of $ 120 billion.<br />
KEATING: Richard, we're rebuilding Australia from an<br />
agrarian runt that produced a bit of wheat and wool to a<br />
modern industrial Australia.<br />
CARLETON: Seven years in, how much longer?<br />
KEATING: And we've concertinaed 20 years of policy<br />
changes into seven. There was no investment in this<br />
economy for 20 years up till 1983. That's why we've got<br />
a problem because the conservatives dropped the ball for<br />
nearly two decades what you're saying<br />
CARLETON: Let's say, let's say seven years you've<br />
had. How much longer?<br />
KEATING: Well, look at the growth, look at the growth of<br />
the economy and the employment in the economy. I mean,<br />
now of putting the capital stock in at a rate which is<br />
unprecedented to produce goods right through the 1990s to<br />
pull the current account down. I mean, the very<br />
substantial thing, the one thing that will get us out of<br />
trouble is production and it can come from one place only<br />
not wishful thinking investment. And how do you get<br />
it? By keeping profits up, by having a proper social<br />
wage and we've got both. We've got all things happening<br />
at once, in spades, in spades.<br />
PM: And in addition to that, a savings plan untold in<br />
this country. Superannuation with which my friend and<br />
colleague, Keating, has been intimately associated, the<br />
development of superannuation. Now let's look at that<br />
CARLETON: Prime Minister, because we can't edit his<br />
remarks, I'm sorry, I've got to keep to time and I must<br />
end it, end now. So thank you, Mr Keating thank you too.<br />
PM: Thank you.<br />
KEATING: Thank you, Richard.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
