<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6867</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/03/1986</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006867.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
,); UTHALIAo~<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA 18 MARCH 1986<br />
The Government is acutely aware of the importance to Australia of<br />
the rural sector. It is the base upon which the rest of<br />
Australia's economy has historically been built. It is among the<br />
most efficient and, conversely, one of the least protected<br />
agricultural sectors in the world. Australia has an outstanding<br />
record as an agricultural producer and exporter, and as a<br />
supplier of food to the world.<br />
The health of our rural sector is of great concern to this<br />
Government at any time. Given various conditions and influences<br />
operating in international markets at the moment, our rural<br />
sector's problems are very much at the forefront of our current<br />
concerns. I point out these facts to underscore the importance which I<br />
place on my forthcoming overseas visit, which will now include<br />
several European capitals after my visit to Washington.<br />
It should be understood clearly that any action or influence<br />
which tends to damage or threatens to damage international<br />
agricultural markets and, more specifically, the access of<br />
Australian producers to those markets, will prompt reaction from<br />
this Government.<br />
my visit should be seen as much for its significance in<br />
recognising the rural sector's importance to us as much as for<br />
the opportunity it gives me to reinforce at first hand our views<br />
on the damage done by market distortions to Australian producers.<br />
Following my visit to Washington from 16-18 April, I shall be<br />
visiting London, Brussels, Rome and Athens between 19 and 26<br />
Apr il.<br />
As announced at the National Press Club recently, during my visit<br />
to Washington I will have talks with President Reagan and senior<br />
members of his Administration about Australia's increasing<br />
concern over the outlook for the international trading system<br />
particularly with regard to agricultural trade. I shall also hold<br />
parallel discussions with senior members of the United States<br />
Congress on these issues.<br />
Two major objectives of my visit will be to discuss ways of<br />
minimising the negative impact that the Export Enhancement<br />
Program and other aspects of the US Farm Bill could have on<br />
Australia's rural sector, and to discuss how best to promote a<br />
more rational international trading system for agricultural<br />
products with particular reference to the forthcoming Tokyo<br />
Economic Summit. </p>
<p>2<br />
While in Washington, I also expect to exchange views with senior<br />
members of the US Administration on international political<br />
issues of common concern, as well as international economic<br />
subjects apart from trade.<br />
My visit will also provide opportunities to reinforce in Europe<br />
Australia's increasing concern about the outlook for<br />
international agricultural trade and the need to address this<br />
issue at the forthcoming Tokyo Economic Summit. As part of these<br />
discussions, I will be expressing Australia's continuing concern<br />
about the effects of the Common Agricultural Policy and the<br />
importance we attach to its reform.<br />
In Brussels, I shall take the opportunity to reinforce our<br />
concerns about the outlook for the international trading system<br />
particularly for agricultural trade, with senior members of the<br />
Commission of the European Communities led by its President, Mr<br />
Delors. My meeting with Prime Minister Thatcher in London will provide an<br />
opportunity not only to discuss current problems in agricultural<br />
trade, but also to review the long-standing and close bilateral<br />
ties between Australia and Britain, and to exchange views on<br />
international political issues apart from trade.<br />
During my stay in Rome, I shall have a private audience with His<br />
Holiness, the Pope, which will provide an opportunity to discuss<br />
with him a range of issues, including his visit to Australia in<br />
November. In Rome and Athens, I expect to discuss international political<br />
and economic issues of common interest with Prime Ministers Craxi<br />
and Papandreou. Australia's relations with both Italy and Greece<br />
have been greatly strengthened by flows of migration and other<br />
people-to-people contacts in recent decades. I look forward to<br />
reviewing Australia's close and warm bilateral relationship with<br />
each country and exploring the scope for future development.<br />
In Rome, I also expect to sign the reciprocal agreeement on<br />
portability of pensions. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
