<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3668</transcript-id>
    <title>ALBURY/WODONGA FINANCIAL AGREEMENT</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/03/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003668.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER PRESS STATEMENT NO. 477<br />
28 March 1975<br />
ALBURY/ WODONGA FINANCIAL AGREEMENT<br />
Joint statement by the Prime Minister, Mr Whitlam, the Premier<br />
of New South Wales, Mr Lewis and the Premier of Victoria<br />
Mr Hamer<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr Whitlam, the Premier of New<br />
South Wales, Mr Lewis and the Premier of Victoria, Mr Hamer<br />
announced today that they had signed an agreement providing<br />
million from the Australian Government for the Albury!<br />
-*/ odonga growth centre.<br />
The funds will be allocated by the Australian Government<br />
to the New South Wales and Victorian Governments to be used for<br />
the further development of Albury/ Wodonga.<br />
The Australian Government's contribution to the<br />
development of the growth centre will be spent on land,<br />
municipal services and building development.<br />
Expenditure on municipal works will be one third<br />
grant and two thirds loan. Funds provided to purchase land<br />
for open space or recreation for the growth centre will be in<br />
the form of a grant.<br />
Generally other financial assistance will be provided<br />
as a loan repayable over 30 years at the long term bond rate.<br />
The first repayments of the loan moneys have been deferred<br />
for ten years, except in the case of loans for muncipal works,<br />
and special provision has been made to protect the States if<br />
the growth centre generates insufficient revenue to meet loan<br />
commitments. Mr Whitlam, Mr Lewis and Mr Hamer said the signing<br />
of the Albury/ Wodonga financial agreement demonstrates the<br />
continuim~ c interest of the three Governments in persuing<br />
the co-operative arrangements for the development of the growth<br />
centre.<br />
CANBERRA. A. C. T.. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
