<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3391</transcript-id>
    <title>PUBLIC SERVICE BOARD WAGE DECISION</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/09/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003391.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Press Statement No. 328<br />
13 September 1974<br />
PUBLIC SERVICE BOARD WAGE DECISION<br />
The Pr. Lme Minister, Mr. E. G. Whitlam said today<br />
that he welcomed the decision of the Public Service Board<br />
to grant no further increase to Public Servants in the<br />
clerical, postal and keyboard areas beyond the $ 16 per<br />
week increase which had been announced by the Board on<br />
June 21. Mr. Whitlam said that the decision of the Public<br />
Service Board was an important example for the rest of<br />
the community of the restraint which his Government sought.<br />
He added that the Government's total approach to the related<br />
issues of increases in income, inflation and management of<br />
the economy included positive support for the principle of<br />
automatic quarterly cost of living adjustments ( wage indexation).<br />
Mr. Whitlam recalled that following the Parliament's<br />
decision to reject the determinations of the Remuneration<br />
Tribunal which dealt with the salaries of Members of Parliament,<br />
Departmental Heads and office holders, his Government had<br />
decided not to implement the Tribunal's recommendations<br />
concerning Judges and he had telegraphed each of the Premiers<br />
urging that they take similar action. Mr. Whitlam went on to<br />
say that as the Treasurer had stated on 23 July the<br />
Government had invited the Prices Justification Tribunal<br />
to scrutinize with care price increases based on wage costs<br />
in excess of awards.<br />
The Prime Minister said that these actions by his<br />
Government were an earnest of the Government's intention to<br />
ensure restraint in the growth of wages anid other forms of<br />
income. CANBERRA. A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
