<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11327</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                 THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                 ADDRESS AT ECONOMICS LUNCHEON IN ASSOCIATION WITH THE AAA, B.C.I.U                 AND DOWNTOWN ECONOMISTS ASSOCIATION                 ASIA SOCIETY, NEW YORK, USA</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/07/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...................</p>
<p>Well thank you very much Nicholas Platt. To my Ministerial colleague</p>
<p> Joe Hockey the Minister for Financial Services in the Australian Government</p>
<p> to Andrew Peacock the Australian Ambassador to the United States,</p>
<p> Michael Baume the Australian Consul General here in New York, many</p>
<p> other distinguished guests, ladies and gentleman. I want to thank</p>
<p> the organisations that have brought this luncheon together and the</p>
<p> fact that they bring together an organisation which is concerned about</p>
<p> the involvement of the rest of the world in the affairs of Asia, that</p>
<p> is the Asia Society, the fact that the hosts also include organisations</p>
<p> that bring together the fostering of good relations between Australia</p>
<p> and the United States and organisations that are concerned about the</p>
<p> economic strengths and the economic well being of our two societies</p>
<p> is certainly very appropriate for the subject of my address.</p>
<p>I'm coming to the end of what has been a two week visit out of my</p>
<p> country. A visit which has taken me, not only to the United States,</p>
<p> but also taken me to Australia's best customer America is a good one,</p>
<p> but we have one that's even better and that is Japan and the visit</p>
<p> has in both countries has reinforced to me a number of things. First</p>
<p> and foremost of course its reinforced the interaction and the interdependence</p>
<p> of our relationships both politically and economic with those two</p>
<p> countries. Its brought home to me how important economic strength</p>
<p> is in the world. How much economic strength allows a nation of Australia's</p>
<p> size of just under 19 million to punch considerably above its weight</p>
<p> and I've had the opportunity over the last couple of weeks to reinforce</p>
<p> to all of the people I've seen, which have been at the highest levels</p>
<p> of Government in both Japan and the United States, the continued commitment</p>
<p> of Australia to a very deep and abiding involvement in the affairs</p>
<p> of the Asian Pacific Region.</p>
<p>I'm rather pleased that when introducing me Nicholas referred to that</p>
<p> phrase of mine, the unique intersection that Australia occupies because</p>
<p> it does to my mind encapsulate very well where Australia is placed</p>
<p> in the world. We are unusual in occupying that intersection. We do</p>
<p> of course have very strong and abiding links with the nations of Europe.</p>
<p> We have a shared history, we have a shared language, with one of them</p>
<p> we have a shared culture with so many of them. We of course have,</p>
<p> as all of you in this audience particularly know and understand, we</p>
<p> have a special affinity and a special affection for and a shared history</p>
<p> with the people of North America, particularly the people of the United</p>
<p> States.</p>
<p>But there we are geographically, side by side, cheek by jowl, with</p>
<p> the peoples of Asia. And that does give us a special opportunity and</p>
<p> it gives us a special responsibility. And in taking advantage of that</p>
<p> opportunity and in discharging that special responsibility we can</p>
<p> best do so from a position of economic strengths and economic example</p>
<p> and economic vitality. And of a number of things that I'm particularly</p>
<p> proud of, that the Government I lead has been able to achieve over</p>
<p> the last three and a quarter years, one of them is the fact that in</p>
<p> Asia's time of trial and economic difficulty, Australia was able to</p>
<p> be a good helpful and reliable friend. It wasn't just an association</p>
<p> of rhetoric and an association of expressions of goodwill. We were,</p>
<p> along with Japan, the only other country that participated in the</p>
<p> three international monetary fund bailouts of Indonesia, Korea and</p>
<p> Thailand. And at a very critical stage of the negotiations between</p>
<p> the international monetary fund and Indonesia it was the representations</p>
<p> of the Australian Government to the International Monetary Fund which</p>
<p> I believe played a very important role in perhaps injecting a greater</p>
<p> sense of realism and a greater understanding of the need to achieve</p>
<p> a balance between the economic and the social considerations in relation</p>
<p> to that particular country.</p>
<p>We've been able to do these things and I believe without exaggeration</p>
<p> to play a very constructive role over the last few years because of</p>
<p> greater domestic economic strengths and it brings back to all of us</p>
<p> the importance that if you seek to have some influence in the world</p>
<p> you must do so in part from a position of economic strengths and economic</p>
<p> dependability.</p>
<p>The Australian economic story of the last few years is a very good</p>
<p> one. We are growing very strongly, last year we had a growth rate</p>
<p> of around five per cent. We have the lowest net government debt to</p>
<p> GDP ratio of any country in the OECD. We have the lowest interest</p>
<p> rates as my Treasurer humorously says since man first walked on the</p>
<p> moon in 1969. We have very low inflation. If we can get rid of the</p>
<p> other 50 per cent of Telstra, we'll have no net Commonwealth debt</p>
<p> by the year 2002. And we have course are now getting the benefit of</p>
<p> a number of fundamental economic reforms that have been carried out</p>
<p> in Australia over the last few years. And when three weeks ago that</p>
<p> wonderful afternoon that in my political career I will never forget,</p>
<p> there was returned to the House of Representative from the Senate</p>
<p> a series of bills to amend the Australian taxation law and I had the</p>
<p> opportunity of moving that the House of Representatives approve the</p>
<p> legislation and thus finally pass into law the bills to reform Australia's</p>
<p> taxation laws after years and years of debate and advocacy.</p>
<p>We had an interesting debate and I talked about the five pillars of</p>
<p> the modernisation of the Australian economy over the last 15 or 20</p>
<p> years. I mentioned the fiscal consolidation that has been undertaken</p>
<p> in the last three and a quarter years where we've turned a deficit</p>
<p> of $10 .5 billion into a surplus in two years. I talked about the</p>
<p> financial deregulation of the Australian economy, first recommended</p>
<p> by the Canberra report, which I commissioned as Treasurer in 1979,</p>
<p> looked at with some trepidation by the incoming Labor Government in</p>
<p> 1983 but then to its great credit and with our support in Opposition</p>
<p> embraced in full and that led to the floating of the Australian dollar,</p>
<p> the admission of foreign banks into Australia, the abolition of exchange</p>
<p> controls and a number of other measures which have underwritten the</p>
<p> operation of the Australian financial system since.</p>
<p>I thought of tariff reform. Once again particularly of the statement</p>
<p> made by the former Labor Prime Minister, Bob Hawke in 1991, with our</p>
<p> strong support from Opposition, to reduce tariff levels in Australia.</p>
<p> I of course also recalled that great thing that had been left unchallenged</p>
<p> in Australia year after year, that is the deregulation of the labour</p>
<p> market which has been undertaken very vigorously by my Government</p>
<p> over the last three and a quarter years and has played a major role</p>
<p> in boosting the productivity of the Australian workforce and the Australian</p>
<p> labour market.</p>
<p>And the fifth and final of the pillars of economic reform has of course</p>
<p> been the renovation of the Australian taxation system. And that taxation</p>
<p> reform is undoubtedly the biggest change to our taxation system since</p>
<p> World War II and arguably the biggest change to our taxation system</p>
<p> since federation. It will introduce a broad based indirect tax, a</p>
<p> goods and services tax we call it, it will replace a very outdated</p>
<p> old fashioned wholesale sales tax, it will replace a number of taxes</p>
<p> at a state level. I'm pleased to tell this audience, amongst those</p>
<p> will be stamp duty on share transactions and it will also replace</p>
<p> immediately the Financial Institutions Duty which is levied by State</p>
<p> governments. Importantly, it will give to the Australian States a</p>
<p> guaranteed revenue base to provide the Government schools, the hospitals,</p>
<p> the roads, the police services which are the bread and butter of the</p>
<p> provision of public services by governments in Australia.</p>
<p>All-in-all it represents the major renovation of our system and it</p>
<p> will be accompanied, wisely in my view, at precisely the same time</p>
<p> with major reductions in personal income tax. I've never believed</p>
<p> that it's wise in politics to try and implement major structural reforms</p>
<p> separating what might be seen as the electorally harder bits from</p>
<p> the electorally more attractive bits, because surprisingly voting</p>
<p> publics have a tendency not to remember for terribly long some of</p>
<p> the electorally attractive bits, but to remember for much longer some</p>
<p> of the electorally harder bits. So taking my cue from other countries</p>
<p> that have disconnected elements of the reform, we've kept the two</p>
<p> of them together. And when on the 1st of July next year</p>
<p> the Goods and Services tax comes into operation, also on the 1st</p>
<p> of July there will come into operation the largest reduction in personal</p>
<p> income tax in Australia since the end of World War II.</p>
<p>Taken together it does represent a mammoth reform. It's going to make</p>
<p> our exports cheaper, it's going to cut the cost of fuel, and that</p>
<p> is very important in a country as large as Australia. It's going to</p>
<p> reduce business costs overall and I think its going to inject a great</p>
<p> deal of additional vitality into the Australian economy.</p>
<p>Now that in a sense is one shoe of tax reform. The other shoe which</p>
<p> will start dropping on the 31st of July when we receive</p>
<p> a report from a very respected Australian businessman, John Ralph</p>
<p> who's written it with the assistance of a number of other very well</p>
<p> known Australian businessmen including Bob Joss who's done such a</p>
<p> marvellous job of running the Westpac bank in Australia over the last</p>
<p> few years. That report will deal with the renovation of Australia's</p>
<p> business taxes. Now I would be the first to acknowledge that we need</p>
<p> reform in that area. I understand the view to be widely held in many</p>
<p> areas of the investment community that the odd change here and there</p>
<p> to the capital gains tax would be extremely welcome. I understand</p>
<p> that people are arguing very strongly for a more competitive corporate</p>
<p> tax rate. I appreciate that in an increasingly globalised economy</p>
<p> where seamless transfers of capital are almost as quickly matched</p>
<p> by increasingly seamless transfers of job opportunities, that it is</p>
<p> important if you want to attract capital from, for example the United</p>
<p> States, it is important to have the investment choice tax-wise as</p>
<p> neutral as it can possibly be. And without endeavouring or trying</p>
<p> in any way to pre-empt what John Ralph's committee is going to recommend,</p>
<p> I can assure you that those sorts of considerations and the need to</p>
<p> make Australia as attractive as possible as an investment destination</p>
<p> will bulk very largely in our minds.</p>
<p>And as many in this audience will know, one of the specific focuses</p>
<p> of my visit to New York has been to associate myself with the efforts</p>
<p> of many both within the government and within the business community</p>
<p> in Australia to promote Australia as a world financial centre. And</p>
<p> indeed Joe Hockey's specific responsibility within the government</p>
<p> includes very much that particular activity. And in doing so I believe</p>
<p> that I speak, and Joe speaks, from a position of great generic economic</p>
<p> strength as far as our country is concerned because I can't think</p>
<p> of a time when it's possible to speak with credibility as positively</p>
<p> as we can now about the strength and the optimism of the Australian</p>
<p> economy. So I can assure this audience that we will have that particular</p>
<p> aspiration of making Australia a world financial centre, that particular</p>
<p> aspiration very much in our minds when we sit down in a few weeks</p>
<p> time, as we will, to consider the recommendations of the Ralph Committee.</p>
<p>I just want to say two other things before allowing plenty of time</p>
<p> for people to ask me questions, and I want to return to a theme that</p>
<p> I developed for a moment at the gathering yesterday which I addressed.</p>
<p> And that is that one of the great dividends of what has happened in</p>
<p> Australia over the last year, one of the great dividends of the fact</p>
<p> that we have been able to stare down the worst economic collapse Asia's</p>
<p> had in the last 40 years, is that it has given to the Australian people</p>
<p> and to the Australian nation a sense of self-belief about the capacity</p>
<p> of this country to succeed internationally that I don't believe it's</p>
<p> had before.</p>
<p>Australians by character and by nature are openly confident people.</p>
<p> Yet there's always been within many of us, in many Australians a belief</p>
<p> that whatever our assertiveness may be and whatever our confidence</p>
<p> may be, when it comes to the international economic stage it's always</p>
<p> been a bit difficult and a bit threatening and a bit intimidating</p>
<p> out there. And what we've been able to do over the last year against</p>
<p> all predictions and that is to defy a collapse that by all the conventional</p>
<p> rules should have engulfed us, and indeed most people in Australia</p>
<p> believed it was going to engulf us in one form or another by about</p>
<p> the end of 1998, has I believe not only sent a very powerful message</p>
<p> to the rest of the world, but it's also sent the very powerful message</p>
<p> to all Australians and to the entire Australian nation. It's demonstrated</p>
<p> to the world that we are a can-do community, that we do have a capacity</p>
<p> to slug it out and survive and to stare down the worst that a fairly</p>
<p> hostile world economic environment can offer.</p>
<p>Now, there are reasons for it, and I've described the various reforms</p>
<p> that have been undertaken in Australia over the last 20 years which</p>
<p> have played a part in the strengthening and in a time of crisis the</p>
<p> fire-proofing of the Australian economy against the Asian economic</p>
<p> downturn, and I might add that one of the things that also greatly</p>
<p> aided us during that very difficult period in 1997 and 1998 was the</p>
<p> skilfull management of the exchange rate in Australia by the Reserve</p>
<p> Bank. Now all of those things came together when they were most needed.</p>
<p> But I think the best thing of all that's come out of it beyond the</p>
<p> employment growth, the low inflation, the low interest rates, the</p>
<p> high levels of business investment, valuable though all of those things</p>
<p> are, the psychological value of Australians finding that they've been</p>
<p> able to defy and overcome this major economic challenge I think it</p>
<p> is made an incalculable contribution to the national sense of self-worth,</p>
<p> belief and confidence of our country. And in the end that is infinitely</p>
<p> more important than any more narrowly based economic doctrine, or</p>
<p> economic goal, or economic prescription. So as Prime Minister I find</p>
<p> that of all of the emotions, if I can put it that way that one feels</p>
<p> out of the experience of the last year, that is far and away and infinitely</p>
<p> the most satisfying and the most enduring.</p>
<p>Can I simply conclude Nicholas by thanking you and your colleagues</p>
<p> for having me here again here in New York. I think you've helped host</p>
<p> a few luncheons for me in the past. I do value very much the involvement</p>
<p> of the organisations that have sponsored today's lunch and it's another</p>
<p> opportunity for me to say again as Prime Minister of Australia how</p>
<p> deep and abiding and how important is our relationship with the United</p>
<p> States. We have our differences, we've had one this week on one aspect</p>
<p> of our export trade of which I won't dwell any further because it</p>
<p> is already well-known to the audience. We've believed that we've been</p>
<p> treated less than fairly and have made that very plain in our discussions</p>
<p> with the American Administration. But the relationship is deeper and</p>
<p> more long-standing and more important than an understandable and deeply</p>
<p> held difference, and in some quarters of the Australian community</p>
<p> a quite bitterly held difference, on a particular trade issue and</p>
<p> today is an opportunity for me to say again how very important that</p>
<p> overall relationship is and I'm delighted that I've had the chance</p>
<p> of addressing this lunch today to share some of my thoughts with you.</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
<p> QUESTIONS AND ANSWERS</p>
<p> QUESTION:</p>
<p>My name is Dick Radez and I am not a shy American but I work with</p>
<p> US pension funds and endowments and venture capital fund to fund managers</p>
<p> that invest in venture capital funds in Silicon Valley in Europe.</p>
<p> We have been prevented from investing in Australian venture capital</p>
<p> opportunities over the years because of both the legal treatment of</p>
<p> the venture capital investment vehicles in your country, the capital</p>
<p> gains tax and whatever. Now, I have been after your Minister, Mr Hockey,</p>
<p> about this already and he's agreed to take another look at a presentation</p>
<p> in the Australian venture capital community gave to Mr Ralph. But</p>
<p> given that his brief seems to be on rather a larger scale there is</p>
<p> one more concern with things like trying to create another Silicon</p>
<p> Valley down in Australia where we think you have got the intellectual</p>
<p> talent and the experience and software information technology, the</p>
<p> Internet. How do we get this revisited if the Ralph Report doesn't</p>
<p> touch upon it as fully as it might?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I think Ralph will have something to say about it. And I can</p>
<p> assure you that it will be very thoroughly visited when we look at</p>
<p> the Ralph Report in every respect.</p>
<p> QUESTION:</p>
<p>You talk about the five pillars and that's fine. It seems one pillar</p>
<p> you have missed out on is immigration. What are your comments on that?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I don't think I did miss out on it at all. I was describing</p>
<p> in that speech, and again today, the five things that I believe have</p>
<p> contributed to the strength of the modern Australian economy. So the</p>
<p> question though of immigration policy is a separate issue. We have</p>
<p> achieved the economic strength we have now either because of, in spite</p>
<p> of, or based upon in some way the immigration policy we have presumably</p>
<p> followed over the last 20 or 30 years. So I don't think it can be</p>
<p> said that in arriving at where we are now the immigration policy that</p>
<p> we have followed is flawed. We have, as a Government, the view that</p>
<p> at the moment the current intake is about right. The current intake</p>
<p> is lower than what it was at some stages in the1970s and 1980s. It</p>
<p> is an intake that has a greater proportion of people with skills and</p>
<p> with a greater emphasis on business migration. It is, of course, based</p>
<p> on a completely non-discriminatory principle. It is open to this or</p>
<p> any future government to vary the level of immigration in the future</p>
<p> if it believes that economic and social circumstances require it.</p>
<p> Immigration if you look at the sweep of years since World War II immigration</p>
<p> has been of enormous benefit to Australia as it has to the United</p>
<p> States. But it's always been important to ensure that the aggregate</p>
<p> flow of immigration and the composition of it in terms of skills versus</p>
<p> family reunion is right for the economy at the particular time. So</p>
<p> we don't have a doctrinaire view about the level of immigration we</p>
<p> have a pragmatic view. And the pragmatic judgement at the moment is</p>
<p> that the current level is right. There is a view that if you doubled</p>
<p> or trebled immigration overnight, if you could do that you would have</p>
<p> an enormous impact on the so called aging of the population. There</p>
<p> have been some studies done on this and that particular view is somewhat</p>
<p> misplaced and somewhat exaggerated that it's not quite as simple as</p>
<p> that. But that does not say that a higher intake might not be sustainable</p>
<p> in Australia in the years to come. I don't rule that out but I think</p>
<p> there is some mythology about, around about the impact in the short</p>
<p> to medium term of a dramatic increase. It just doesn't compute according</p>
<p> to the advice I have it doesn't quite work out in practice like that.</p>
<p> QUESTION:</p>
<p>My name is Tim Copland from Goldman Sachs, Mr Howard. With the falling</p>
<p> gold price and the relative strength of the Australian dollar the</p>
<p> Australian gold mines are hurting at the moment. Do you propose to</p>
<p> provide them with some assistance whether it's by tax relief or some</p>
<p> other means to help out the Aussie gold miners?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, it's not immediately in contemplation, if I can put it that</p>
<p> way. Look, I mean, fair try but..</p>
<p> QUESTION:</p>
<p>Nicholas Hyde from JP Morgan. I have been out of Australia for about</p>
<p> two years and one thing about being in the United States which I find</p>
<p> different to Australia is the depth of the economy across all regions</p>
<p> and across the smaller towns of America. And I was just wondering</p>
<p> when I look at Australia I see more of a concentration in the major</p>
<p> cities and hopefully with the increase of information flows, you know,</p>
<p> is the Government doing anything about trying to get the wonderful</p>
<p> performance of the economy into centres other than just within the</p>
<p> major cities of Australia?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I am not surprised that you would find that difference. I mean,</p>
<p> because of the huge size of the United States and the vastly bigger</p>
<p> population of course that is a difference. I mean, I might be statistically</p>
<p> wrong in saying so but I don't think I am conceptually wrong in saying</p>
<p> that Australia is probably the most urbanised western society. I mean,</p>
<p> it is one of the things that people still have great difficulty in</p>
<p> coming to terms with about Australia of just how big our cities are.</p>
<p> Of how big, for example, by world and United States standards a city</p>
<p> like Sydney is. So we are a very urbanised society and it is also</p>
<p> true that as the nation is doing very well economically there are</p>
<p> still significant areas of social deprivation and economic deprivation</p>
<p> in the regions. I mean, the major cause of the rise for a moment and</p>
<p> then thankfully the disappearance of One Nation was not, in my view,</p>
<p> race but it was economic deprivation and alienation in regional areas</p>
<p> of Australia. And it's something that every society has to grapple</p>
<p> with but we are doing a number of things in relation to that. We are</p>
<p> making very strenuous efforts including out of the proceeds of the</p>
<p> privatisation of Telstra. We are making very great efforts to provide</p>
<p> more communication services in the bush. We don't want communications</p>
<p> haves and have nots in Australia. We are working very hard at that.</p>
<p> But one of the reasons why we are so very angry about the American</p>
<p> decision on lamb, now that you have asked me, is the opportunity that</p>
<p> is.I mean, here is a group of people of really battling Australian</p>
<p> farmers without any government help, got off their backsides and carved</p>
<p> out a new market in this country and whack, it's taken away or certainly</p>
<p> penalties put on it. Look, I think there are a large number of particular</p>
<p> policies that we are following in telecommunications, in land renewal</p>
<p> through our Natural Heritage Trust proposals. We are trying to tackle</p>
<p> the problem of getting medical practitioners into country areas, we</p>
<p> are trying to reduce the cost of country students boarding in universities</p>
<p> or colleges in the cities. There are a whole range of things that</p>
<p> we are doing. But it's a very good and relevant question because side</p>
<p> by side with the national economic strengths and the extraordinary</p>
<p> prosperity of a number of parts of Australia, particularly in parts</p>
<p> of the larger cities and some of the coastal areas, there are communities</p>
<p> that feel as though they are left behind and we are working very hard</p>
<p> to bring them along as best we can.</p>
<p> QUESTION:</p>
<p>Philip Hedger from Pfizer [inaudible]. You have just been to Japan</p>
<p> and we do a lot of business both in your country and Japan as you</p>
<p> know. And I wonder if you could give us your, sort of, first hand</p>
<p> appreciation of the economic positive indicators that have just come</p>
<p> out of Japan in the first quarter and doubtless you spoke with various</p>
<p> ministers there whether you feel that there's cause for prolonged</p>
<p> optimism there?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I think the Japanese economy has undergone a number of very</p>
<p> necessary structural changes. I think there are more needed. The best</p>
<p> sense I could get was tha</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
