<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>22525</transcript-id>
    <title>Role and Functions of Australia&#039;s Intelligence Agencies  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/10/2006</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I am pleased to release today a brochure on the role and functions of Australia's intelligence agencies.  The brochure [<a href="http://www.ona.gov.au/publications/aic]">www.ona.gov.au/publications/aic]</a> was one of the recommendations of the 2004 Inquiry into Australian Intelligence Agencies by Mr Philip Flood AO.  It aims to improve public understanding of and confidence in our intelligence agencies.</p>
<p>Australia's six intelligence agencies (the Office of National Assessments, the Australian Security Intelligence Organisation, the Australian Secret Intelligence Service, the Defence Intelligence Organisation, the Defence Signals Directorate and the Defence Imagery and Geospatial Organisation) play a vital - and usually unheralded - role in informing the government about developments in Australia and abroad that affect our national security and international interests.  They are the front line of Australia's effort to combat the threat of international terrorism and their work is essential to preserving the freedoms and way of life that Australians value so highly.</p>
<p>It is important that our intelligence community is open to review and scrutiny.  The brochure explains the legislative framework under which the intelligence community operates and the accountability mechanisms in place that ensure Australia's intelligence agencies are fully accountable for their activities under Australian law.</p>
<p>I continue to be impressed by the professionalism, talent and integrity of members of the intelligence community and I commend them for their steadfast commitment to protecting Australia, our interests and our people.  </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
