<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8512</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON, P.J. KEATING, MP</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/05/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008512.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
It TEL: PRIME MINISTER<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON. P. J. KEATING, MP<br />
WA ROYAL COMMISSION<br />
Recent statements by Mr~ Templeman and today's statement by<br />
the WA Royal Comimission chairman, Mr Kennedy, that the<br />
Commonwealth Government has impeded the ability of the<br />
commission to obta~ in tax information are incorrect.<br />
In particular I draw attention to the final paragraph of Mr<br />
Kennedy's press statement of today.<br />
I have received advice today from the Commissioner of<br />
Taxation that 8 WA police unit is working with the Royal<br />
Commission and that this unit is empowered to seek tax<br />
information from the Australian Tax Office.<br />
Further, the Commissioner of Taxation has advised that " we<br />
stand ready to assist the Royal Commission by supplying<br />
information to Its police unit, as authorised by Section 3E<br />
( of theTaxAdministration Act)."<br />
At this stage, I am Informed that no use has been made of<br />
this facility.<br />
If this has comie about because of friction between the<br />
police unit and others associated with the Commission, as<br />
some have suggested, this is not an issue for the<br />
Commonwealth Government.<br />
The central issue is to ensure that the public interest is<br />
served arid that guilty parties are brought to account.<br />
I am therefore disturbed by the implication that I and<br />
subsequent Federal Treasurers have sought to obstruct this<br />
process in any way.<br />
That this Is not the case is made clear by successive<br />
documents provided to me and to other Treasurers which I<br />
have released with this statement. : D </p>
<p>-1 EL<br />
Finally, I ami concerned that<br />
suggesting that it is unable<br />
successful conclusion. the Commission seems to be<br />
to bring this matter to a<br />
I am particularly concerned given the view of the chairman<br />
of the Australian Securities Commission that his ability to<br />
prosecute has been severely hamperedi by the existence of<br />
this and other Royal Commissions.<br />
CANBERRA May 14, 1992 141L18: Y I ! A0 1 U </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
