<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7118</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS TO STUDENTS RESIDENT AT THE AUSTRALIAN ADMINISTRATIVE STAFF COLLEGE - MT ELIZA 15 FEBRUARY 1987</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/02/1987</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007118.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGOED _ t. l-TIL DELIVERY CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
ADDRESS TO STUDENTS RESIDENT<br />
AT THE AUSTRALIAN ADMINISTRATIVE<br />
STAFF COLLEGE MT ELIZA<br />
FEBRUARY 1987<br />
LADIES AND. GENTLEMEN<br />
I AM DELIGHEED TO VISIT THE COLLEGE AGAIN AND TO MEET ALL OF YOU<br />
INVOLVED W: TH THE MANAGEMENT DEVELOPMENT PROGRAM. IT IS NOW<br />
FIFTEEN YZA7A: S SINCE I LAST VISITED THE COLLEGE, AS A GUEST<br />
SPEAKER FROMl THE ACTU, THOUGH FOR THE PRECEDING DECADE I HAD BEEN<br />
A REGULAR VISITOR HERE. SO IT IS A PLEASURE TO RENEW MY<br />
ACQUAINTA1NCE WITH THE COLLEGE AND TO ADMIRE THE WAY IT HAS GROWN.<br />
ON MY EARLIER VISITS TO THE COLLEGE I ENJOYED THE EXPERIENCE OF<br />
ADDRESSING PEOPLE INTERESTED IN IMPROVING THE WAY BUSINESSES,<br />
UNIONS AND BUREAUCRACIES FUNCTION. I KNOW THE COLLEC, IS<br />
CELEBRATING ITS 30TH BIRTHDAY THIS YEAR AND CONTINUES TO PROVIDE<br />
MANAGERS " vI' 2H A HIGH LEVEL OF TRAINING AND INSIGHT INTO THE<br />
CRUCIAL TASvKS THEY CONFRONT.<br />
AND THEY ARE CRUCIAL. INDEED IT IS MY OPINION THAT MANAGEMEN\ T<br />
SKILLS ARE MORE IMPORTANT THAN EVER IN TODAY'S WORLD. AUSTRALIA<br />
IS FACED WI1TH AN URGENT NEED TO RE-STRUCTURE ITS ECONOMY. THE<br />
RECENT SHARP DOWNTURN IN AUSTRALIA'S TERMS OF TRADE IS A TIIIELY<br />
REMINDER THAT WE MUST IMPROVE-THE DIVERSITY AND THE<br />
COMPETITIVENESS OF OUR INDUSTRIES.<br />
OUR OVER-RELIANCE ON PRIM4ARY PRODUCTS AND PROTECTED MANUFACTURING<br />
INDUSTRY HAS PLACED US IN DANGER OF LOSING OUT ON THE ADVANTAGES<br />
OF OUR POSITION ON THE PACIFIC RIM THE MOST DYNA1MIC GROWTH AREA<br />
IN THE WORLD. WE CAN BETTER EXPLOIT THOSE ADVANTAGES IF WE LEARN<br />
TO LOOK OUTWARDS, TO COMPETE, TO EXPORT, NOT JUST IN PRIMARY<br />
PRODUCTION B3UT IN MANUFACTURED GOODS AND IN SERVICES.<br />
WE CAN NO LONGER RELY ON THE INWARD LOOKING POLICIES AND<br />
ATTITUDES OF THE PAST. WE HAVE TO REALISE AUSTRALIA IS A SMALL<br />
ECONOMY RELIANT ON TRADE FOR ITS PROSPERITY.<br />
BUT THE PATH OUT OF OUR DIFFICULTIES IS A LONG ONE.<br />
FUNDAMENTALLY WE N4EED MASSIVE STRUCTURAL CHANGE AND A TIGHT FOCUS<br />
ON THE IMPROVEMENT OF OUR PRODUCTIVE EFFORT. ACHIEVING THAT<br />
CHANGE HAS BEEN A CONSISTENT AND CONSTANT THEME OF MY<br />
GOVERNMErZT'S EFFORTS SINCE WE WERE ELECTED NEARLY FOUR YEARS AGO.<br />
BUT CHANGE ALSO REQUIRES THE CO-ORDINATED AND CO-OPERATIVE EFF~ ORT.<br />
OF ALL SECTIONS OF THE COMMUNITY. </p>
<p>2<br />
AND IN PARTICULAR IT PLACES A GREAT ONUS ON MANAGEMENT ACQUIRING<br />
THE SKILLS OF IMPLEM~ ENTING NEW AND MORE PRODUCTIVE METHODS OF<br />
WORK. THIS IS WHY E'DT; CATION FOR MANAGERS IS SO VITALLY IMPORTANT. TO A<br />
VERY LARGE EXTENT IT WILL BECOME THE RESPONSIBILITY OF MANAGERS<br />
TO IDENTIFY AREAS WITH POTENTIAL FOR GROWTH, TO ENSURE THAT<br />
AVAILABLE RESOURCES ARE DIRECTED IN THE MOST EFFECTIVE MANNER,<br />
AND TO ADJUST INDUSTRIES AND BUREAUCRACIES TO THE CHANGED<br />
ECONOMIC ENVIFRGNMENT.<br />
MAY I SUGGEST THREE MAJOR CHALLENGES WHICH FACE PRIVATE SECTOR<br />
MANAGERS IN AUSTRALIA TODAY. I BELIEVE A GROUP SUCH AS THIS IS<br />
WELL PLACED TC CONSIDER AND RESPOND TO THESE CHALLENGES.<br />
FIRST, MANAGER~ S M'UST LEARN TO EXPLOIT NEW MARKETS.<br />
THE SUBSTANTIAL REAL DEPRECIATION OF OUR CURRENCY, IN CONJUNCTION<br />
WITH NOMINAL WAGE RESTRAINT, HAS CATAPULTED AUSTRALIAN INDUSTRIES<br />
INTO AN ENTIRELY NEW MARKET SITUATION.<br />
IN PARTICULAR OUR MANUFACTURERS AND OUR SERVICE INDUSTRIES NOW<br />
HAVE OPPORTUNIT'ES OPEN TO THEM WHICH PREVIOUSLY COULD NOT EVEN<br />
BE DREAMED OF.<br />
BUT THE ESSENTIAL POINT IS THAT THOSE OPPOR~ TUNITIES ARE WORTHLESS<br />
TO BUSINESS, TO THE COUNTRY UNLESS MANAGERS ARE PREPARED TO<br />
BREAK OUT OF rTu: SECURITY OF SERVICING TRADITIONAL MARKETS AND<br />
SEEK OUT AND WIN NEW SALES IN UNFAMILIAR MARKETS.<br />
THE SECOND CHALLENGE IS PEOPLE MANAGEMENT. I HAVE LONG STRESSED<br />
THE VIRTUES OF CO-OPERATION AND CONSENSUS IN PUBLIC LIFE<br />
ESPECIALLY COO'PARED TO THE BARRENNESS OF CONFRONTATION AND<br />
DIVISION. THAT HAS BEEN TE~ E KEY TO OUR APPROACH TO INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS AND<br />
OUR ECONOMIC PERFORMANCE SINCE 1983 BUT IT ALSO HAS AN<br />
IMPORTANT NEW DIMENSION IN MEETING AUSTRALIA'S NEEDS IN 1987.<br />
LAST SEPTEMBER I CALLED A UNIQUE MEETING OF THE PEAK EMPLOYER<br />
BODIES AND THE ACTU TO DISCUSS THE REFORM OF WORK AND MANAGEMENT<br />
PRACTICES. THIS TASK IS NOW URGENT : IT PROVIDES A SURE VEHICLE<br />
TO RAISING PRODUCTIVITY AND THUS PRESERVING OUR NEW<br />
COMPETITIVENESS INTO THE LONGER TERM.<br />
CHANGE IS ALWAYS EASIEST TO ACCOMPLISH WHEN BOTH THE NEED FOR AND<br />
THE CONSEQUENCE~ S OF IT ARE WELL UNDERSTOOD.<br />
THIS NEED FOR GOOD COMMUNICATION IS ALL THE GREATER WHEN<br />
TECHNOLOGICAL CHANGE IS INVOLVED AND IT IS THE MANAGEMENT OF<br />
TECHNOLOGY WHICH IS THE THIRD OF THE GREAT CHALLENGES FACING<br />
AUSTRALIAN PRIVATE SECTOR MANAGERS TODAY.<br />
THROUGHOUT THE US AND EUROPE, BUSINESS MANAGEMENTS ARE<br />
RECOGNISING THAT SURVIVAL AND PROSPERITY DEPEND UPON THEIR<br />
BECOMING MORE INNOVATIVE AND MAKING BETTER USE OF TECHNOLOGY. </p>
<p>3<br />
BUT IN AUSTRALXA, WE HAVE BECOME LOCKED INTO TRADITIONAL PRODUCTS<br />
WITH LITTLE SCOPE FOR PRODUCT DIFFERENTIATION. WE HAVE<br />
TRADITIONALLY CONCENTRATED ON USING TECHNOLOGY TO CHIP AWAY AT<br />
WASTE AND INEFFICIENCY THROUGH AUTOMATION AND COST CUTTING, FOR<br />
EXAMPLE WHICH IS AN INADEQUATE RESPONSE TO THE NEED TO RESTORE<br />
COMPETITIVENESS. THERE IS NO SUSSTITUTE FOR IN-HOUSE RESEARCH AND DEVELOPMENT,<br />
WHICH MUST BE; SEEN AS A CENTRAL, INTEGRAL AND CONTINUING PART OF<br />
EVERY MANUFACTURING COMPANY'S OPERATIONS.<br />
AS FOR THE PUBLIC SERVICE, LEST ANYONE IMAGINE THAT WE ARE<br />
FAILING TO PRiACTICE WHAT WE PREACH ABOUT THE NEED FOR IMPROVED<br />
MANAGEMENT, ME POINT IN PASSING TO THE VERY CONSIDERABLE<br />
SUCCESS WE HAVE HAD IN STREAMLINING THE COMMONWEALTH BUREAUCRACY.<br />
I NOTE THAT A NMTBER OF COMM2ONWEALTH ORGANISATIONS HAS SENT<br />
PEOPLE HERE ' TO UPGRADE THEIR SKILLS.<br />
ALL OF US, IN TH1E PRIVATE AND THE PUBLIC SECTORS, MUST WORK TO<br />
DEVELOP A NEW BUSINESS STYLE IN THIS COUNTRY IF WE ARE TO TAKE<br />
ADVANTAGE OF THIE OPPORTUNITIES BEFORE US.<br />
IN HELPING MANAGEMENT MEET THESE CHALLENGES I HAVE OUTLINED,<br />
INSTITUTIONS SUCH AS THE ADMINISTRATIVE STAFF COLLEGE HAVE A<br />
GREAT ROLE TC ? LAY.<br />
THE GOVERNlEIT IS COMMITTED TO ENSURING THAT M4ANAGEMENT EDUCATION<br />
CONTINUES AND EXPANDS IN AUSTRALIA.<br />
HAVING MET YOU TODAY I HAVE EVERY CONFIDENCE YOU RECOGNISE THE<br />
NEED FOR SOUND MANAGEMENT PRACTICES AND ARE WELL PLACED TO<br />
PROMOTE THEM.<br />
MAY I CLOSE THEN BY WISHING YOU GOOD LUCK BOTH IN YOUR STUDIES<br />
HERE AND, EVEN MORE IMPORTANTLY, WHEN YOU RETURN TO YOUR<br />
MANAGEMENT TASX( S IN THE OUTSIDE WORLD. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
