<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3764</transcript-id>
    <title>SUPERIOR COURUT OF AUSTRALIA BILL - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER - 4 JUNE 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/06/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003764.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SUPERI OR COURT OF AUSTRALIA BILL<br />
ESPLU ILULPEMfrLEJUIlSER<br />
JJUNE 1975<br />
THIS BILL TO ESTABLISH THE SUPERIOR COURT OF<br />
AUSTRALIA AFFORDS AN OUTSTANDING EXAMPLE OF LIBERAL INEPTITUDE<br />
IN GOVERNMENT AND OBSTRUCTION IN OPPOSITION.<br />
A PAPER ENTITLED " THE NECESSITY FOR A NEW<br />
FEDERAL COURT" WAS DELIVERED AT THE 13TH LEGAL CONVENTION<br />
IN HOBART IN JANUARY 1963 BY MR MAURICE BYERS, Q. C. AND<br />
MR PAUL TOOSE, Q. C, NOW^ THE SOLICITOR-GENERAL OF AUSTRALIA<br />
AND A JUDGE OF THE SUPREME COURT OF NEW SOUTH WALES. IN<br />
THE DISCUSSIONS ON THE PAPER THE SOLICITOR-GENERAL, SIR<br />
KENNETH BAILEY, ANNOUNCED ON BEHALF OF THE ATTORNEY-GENERAL<br />
THAT THE CABINET HAD AUTHORISED HIM TO DESIGN A NEW FEDERAL<br />
SUPERIOR COURT. SIR KENNETH WENT ON TO SAY THAT THE PAPER<br />
WOULD BE OF MATERIAL ASSISTANCE TO THE ATTORNEY-GENERAL,<br />
SIR GARFIELD BARWICK, WHOSE CONGRATULATIONS HE GAVE TO THE<br />
LEARNED AUTHORS. IN 1964, JUST BEFORE HE BECAME CHIEF JUSTICE,<br />
SIR GARFIELD WROTE A 21-PAGE ARTICLE ON THE PROPOSED NEW<br />
FEDERAL SUPERIOR COURT FOR THE INITIAL ISSUE OF THE<br />
FEDERAL LAW REVIEW, THE JOURNAL OF THE LAW SCHOOL OF THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN NATIONAL UNIVERSITY. </p>
<p>1)<br />
ON 15 MARCH -167, IN ANSWER TO A QUESTION<br />
' BY THE HIONOURHABLE MEMBER FOR MORETON, ATTORNEY GEN ERAL BOWEN,<br />
NOW CH-IEF JUDGE IN EQUITY IN THE SUPREME COURT OF NEW SOUTH<br />
WALES, SAID AN ANORMOUS AMOUNT OF WORK HAD BEEN DONE ON<br />
THE PROPOSAL FOR THE NEW COURT BY SIR GARFIELD BARWICK AND<br />
BY HIS OWN IMMEDIATE PREDECESSOR, MR SNEDDEN. HE PROMISED'<br />
A MINISTERIAL STATEMENT. HE MADE THE STATEMENT ON 18 MAY.<br />
HE DELIVERED A PAPER ON THE PROPOSAL TO THE 15TH LEGAL<br />
CONVENTION ON 17 JULY.<br />
IN MARCH 1968, OPENING A NEW SESSION, THE<br />
GOVERNOR-GENERAL STATED:<br />
" INY GOVERNMENT WILL PREPARE LEGISLATION FOR<br />
CREATION OF A COMMONWEALTH SUPERIOR COURT TO<br />
RELIEVE PRESSURE ON4 THE HIGH COURT."<br />
ON 29 OCTOBER 1968, ATTORNEY-GENERAL BOWEN<br />
ASKED A COMMITTEE UNDER MR JUSTICE KERR, LATER CHIEF JUSTICE<br />
OF NEW SOUTH WALES AND NOW THE GOVERNOR-GENERAL, TO CONSIDER<br />
THE JURISDICTION TO BE GIVEN TO THE PROPOSED COMMONWEALTH<br />
SUPERIOR COURT TO REVIEW ADMINISTRATIVE DECISIONS. THE<br />
OTHER MEMBERS WERE SOLICITOR-GENERAL MASON, LATER A JUDGE OF<br />
APPEAL OF THE SUPREME COURT OF NEW SOUTH WALES AND NOW A<br />
JUSTICE OF THE HIGH COURT, AND PROFESSOR WHITMORE AND<br />
LATER SOLICITOR-GENERAL ELLICOTT, NOW THE IIONOURA13LE MEMBER<br />
FOR WENTWORTHI. THE COMMITTEE'S REPORT WAS TABLED ON<br />
_ ILI OCTOBELR 1971. </p>
<p>-3-<br />
I'EANTIME, /\ TTORNEY-GENERAL BOWEN AND IN THE<br />
1969 PARLIAMENT THE NEW ATTORNEY-GENERAL HUGHES, AND UNDER<br />
THE MCI" HAHON GOVERNMENT THE RESTORED ATTORNEY-GENERAL BOWEN,<br />
WERE ENGAGED IN PREPARING SOME 66 COMPLEMENTARY BILLS WHICH<br />
IT WAS DESIRED TO INTRODUCE BEFORE DEBATING THE COMMONWEALTH<br />
SUPERIOR COURT BILL.<br />
THUS WORK ON THIS BILL PROCEEDED THROUGH THE<br />
PARLIAMENTS ELECTED IN 1961, 1963, 1966 AND 1969, UNDER<br />
LIBERAL PRIME MINISTERS MENZIES, HOLT, GORTON AND MCMAHON,<br />
LIBERAL ATTORNEYS-GENERAL BARWICK, SNEDDEN, BOWEN, HUGHES<br />
AND BOWEN AGAIN AND, IN ONE CAPACITY OR ANOTHER, SOLICITORSGENERAL<br />
BAILEY, MASON, ELLICOTT AND BYERS. AND AT LAST ON<br />
27 OCTOBER 1972, THE DAY AFTER THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES<br />
ROSE FOR THE ELECTIONS, THE LAST LIBERAL ATTORNEY-GENERAL,<br />
SENATOR GREENWOOD, ANNOUNCED THAT THE MCMAHON GOVERNMENT<br />
HAD REACHED THE CONCLUSION THAT THE PROPOSAL TO ESTABLISH A<br />
COMMONWEALTH SUPERIOR COURT SHOULD NOT BE PROCEEDED WITH.<br />
ON THE LABOR SIDE THE PROPOSAL HADBEEN SUPPORTED<br />
AND PROMOTED CONSISTENTLY. I URGED IT AT THE ALEGAL CONVENTION<br />
IN PERTH IN 1957 AND IN THE DEBATE ON THE ATTORNEY-GENERAL'S<br />
ESTIMATES IN 1958 AND IN DOZENS OF SPEECHES AND QUESTIONS<br />
IN THE HOUSE THROUGHOUT THE 1960' s. I INCLUDED THE PROPOSAL<br />
IN THE POLICY SPEECHES I DELIVERED ON BEHALF OF THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN LABOR PARTY AT THE ELECTIONS IN 1972 AND 1974. </p>
<p>THERE CAN SCARCELY HAVE BEEN A PROPOSAL WHICH<br />
BOTH SIDES OF POLITICS HAVE WORKED ON SO LONG, BUT WHAT<br />
HIAS BEEN THE HISTORY OF THE BILL UNDER MY GOVERNMENT?<br />
A BILL TO ESTABLISH THE SUPERIOR COURT OF<br />
AUSTRALIA WAS INTRODUCED INTO THE SENATE IN DECEMBER 1973 B~ Y<br />
ATTORNEY-GENERAL MURPHY. THAT BILL LAPSED WHEN PARLIAMENT<br />
WAS PROROGUED TO ENABLE THE QUEEN TO OPEN THE PARLIAMENT* ON<br />
THE OCCASION OF HER VISIT To AUSTRALIA IN FEBRUARY 1974.<br />
THE BILL WAS AGAIN INTRODUCED INTO THE SENATE ON 14 MARCH<br />
LAST YEAR, BUT THE MOTION FOR THE SECOND READING OF THE<br />
BILL WAS DEFEATED IN THE SENATE ON 2 APRIL 1974.<br />
THE BILL WAS REINTRODUCED INTO THIS HOUSE AFTER<br />
THE DOUBLE DISSOLUTION OF MAY LAST YEAR AND WAS PASSED ON<br />
24 JULY. THiE OPPOSITION AGAIN OPPOSED THE BILL IN THE<br />
SENATE AND THE MOTION FOR THE SECOND READING OF THE BILL<br />
RESULTED IN A TIED VOTE ON 26 FEBRUARY THIS YEAR. SO NOW<br />
THE BILL HAS BEEN INTRODUCED FOR A SECOND TIME IN THIS HOUSE.<br />
THE PROPOSALS FOR THE ESTABLISHMENT OF THE.<br />
SUPERIOR COURT WERE WELCOMED FROM THE OUTSET BY LEADERS OF<br />
THE LEGAL PROFESSION IN AUSTRALIA. A COMMITTEE APPOINTED BY<br />
THE LAW COUNCIL OF AUSTRALIA REPORTED IN FAVOUR IN AUGUST 1963.<br />
SO DID THE NEW SOUTH WALES BAR ASSOCIATION. ATTORNEY-GENERAL<br />
BOWEN TOLD THE LEGAL CONVENTION IN JULY 11967 THAT THERE WAS A<br />
BROAD CONSENSUS THAT SUCH A COURT SHOULD BE ESTABLISHED. HE<br />
STATED CATEGORICALLY THAT " fA DECISION HAS BEEN TAi( EN TO<br />
ESTABLISH THE COURT" 1 AND THAT ARGUMENTS ADVANCED AGAINST THE<br />
' itI<br />
IDEA ARE NOW ACADEMIC", BUT A MORE CONSERVATIVE VIEW WAS / q<br />
11 </p>
<p>TAKEN IN THE TWILIGHT YEARS OF THE LIBERAL GOVERNMENT AND<br />
THE CONCEPT CAME TO BE OPPOSED WHEN IT WAS APPRECIATED THAT<br />
THE BILL DESCRIBED BY ATTORNEY-GENERAL BOWEN 8 YEARS AGO<br />
WOULD ENABLE THE SUPERIOR COURT TO ENTER UPON JURISDICTION<br />
NOW EXERCISED BY THE SUPREME COURTS OF THE STATES,<br />
SUCH ARGUMENTS, HOWEVER, LOSE SIGHT OF THE FACT<br />
THAT THERE IS ALREADY A LARGE BODY OF FEDERAL LEGISLATION<br />
WHICH WOULD FALL TO BE INTERPRETED AND ADMINISTERED BY A<br />
FEDERAL SUPERIOR COURT IN WHICH THE LEGAL PROBLEMS OF A<br />
JURISDICTIONAL NATURE THAT HAVE BEEN URGED AS OBJECTIONS<br />
AGAINST THE SUPERIOR COURT WOULD HAVE NO PLACE. FOR MORE<br />
THAN SEVENTY YEARS, INDUSTRIAL. MATTERS ARISING UNDER THE<br />
CONCILIATION AND ARBITRATION ACT HAVE BEEN DEALT WITH BY<br />
A FEDERAL COURT WITHOUT GIVING RISE TO SUBSTANTIAL<br />
JURISDICTIONAL PROBLEMS. </p>
<p>FOR ALMOST FIFTY YEARS, THERE HAS BEEN A<br />
FEDERAL COURT OF BANKRUPTCY, WHICH HAS SAT IN SYDNEY AND<br />
MAELBOURNE. THESE ARE TWO EXAMPLES OF LONG-STANDING<br />
JURISDICTIONSEXERCISED BY FEDERAL COURTS,<br />
TO THESE HAVE BEEN ADDED IN RECENT YEARSP<br />
SUBSTANTIAL ADDITIONAL AREAS OF FEDERAL LAW, FROM THE<br />
VERY FIRST TRADE PRACTICES ACT IN 1965 EXCLUSIVE JURISDICTION<br />
IN FEDERAL TRADE PRACTICES LAW HAS BEEN VESTED IN<br />
THE INDUSTRIAL COURT, THAT WAS A MATTER INITIATED BY OUR<br />
PREDECESSORS. THE TRADE PRACTICES ACT 1974, ADOPTED BY<br />
THIS PARLIAMENT, CONTINUES TO RECOGNISE THE PRINCIPLE THAT<br />
THE PROPER COURT TO iNTERPRET AND APPLY THE FEDERAL LAW ON<br />
TRADE PRACTICES IS A FEDERAL COURT. THE TRADE PRACTICES ACT<br />
1974 VESTS JURISDICTION IN THE SUPERIOR COURT AND, UNTIL<br />
THAT COURT IS ESTABLISHED, IN THE AUSTRALIAN INDUSTRIAL COURT.<br />
THERE IS BEFORE THE PARLIAMENT A NATIONAL COMPENSATION<br />
BILL AND THE CORPORATIONS AND SECURITIES INDUSTRY<br />
BILL. THE DRAFTING OF-A NATIONAL COMPANIES BILL IS WELL<br />
ADVANCED. THIS HIOUSE HAS PASSED THE ADMINISTRATIVE APPEALS<br />
TRIBUNAL BILL, THE FIRST OF A SERIES OF MEASURES INTENDED TO<br />
BRING ABOUT A SUBSTANTIAL REFORM OF ADMINISTRATIVE LAW AT<br />
THE FEDERAL LEVEL. 1 </p>
<p>THiis GOVERNMENT HAS ESTABLISHED THE LAW REFORM<br />
COMMISSION TO APPROACH THE TASK OF REFORMING THE LAW IN<br />
AUSTRALIA ON A NATIONAL SCALE, THE LAW REFORM<br />
COMMISSION IS CHARGED WITH THE DUTY OF CONSIDERING NOT<br />
ONLY MATTERS WITHIN THE JURISDICTION OF THIS PARLIAMENT<br />
BUT ALSO PROPOSALS FOR UNIFORMITY BETWEEN THE LAWS OF<br />
THE STATES AND OF THE TERRITORIES, THE ESTABLISHMENT OF<br />
THE LAW REFORM COMMISSION IS A RECOGNITION OF THE ABSURDITY<br />
OF HAVING SO MANY DIFFERENCES IN LAW ACROSS STATE AND<br />
TERRITORY BOUNDARIES, IT HIGHLIGHTS. THE NEED TO HAVE A<br />
COURT THAT HAS JURISDICTION T-HROUGHOUT AUSTRALIA AND<br />
THAT CAN INTERPRET AND APPLY THE LAWS ENACTED BY THIS<br />
PARLIAMENT ON A UNIFORM BASIS THROUGHOUT THE WHOLE OF<br />
AUSTRALIA. THE GREAT DEVELOPMENT IN FEDERAL LAW TO WHICH<br />
HAVE REFERRED MAKES THE NEED TO ESTABLISH THE SUPERIOR COURT<br />
MUCH MORE PRESSING, WHILE THE INTERPRETATION OF THE LAW<br />
REMAINS WITH THE SUPREME COURTS OF THE STATES NO MATTER CAN<br />
BE REGARDED AS BEING SETTLED THROUGHOUT AUSTRALIA UNTIL<br />
A DECISION HAS BEEN GIVEN ON IT BY THE HIGH COURT. IT<br />
IS TRUE THAT A DECISION OF, SAY, THE FULL COURT OF THE<br />
SUPREME COURT OF VICTORIA IS TREATED WITH THE GREATEST<br />
RESPECT BY THE COURT OF ) PEAL OF NEW SOUTH WALES. 11 </p>
<p>BUT THE VICTORIAN DIECISION HAS NO BINDING FORCE ON<br />
THE NEW SOUTH WALES COURT, EVEN THOUGH THE TWO COURTS<br />
MAY B3E DEALING WITH , SAME SECTION OF AN ACT OF THIS<br />
PARLIAMENT, A DECISION OF THE FULL COURT OF THE SUPERIOR<br />
COURT WOULD BE BINDING ON THE JUDGES OF THAT COURT THROUGHOUT<br />
AUSTRALIA, SO THAT IN THOSE IMPORTANT AREAS OF FEDERAL<br />
LAW IN WHICH THE SUPERIOR COURT WOULD BE EXERCISING<br />
EXCLUSIVE JURISDICTION THE ESTABLISHMENT OF THE COURT<br />
WOULD SUBSTANTIALLY CONTRIBUTE TOWARDS CERTAINTY IN THE<br />
LAW, THE* CASE FOR THE SUPERIOR COURT IS NOW EVEN FURTHER<br />
STRENGTHENED BY THE ESTABLISHMENT OF THE FAMILY COURT OF<br />
AUSTRALIA UNDER THE FAMILY LAW BILL$ THIS DECISION BY<br />
THE PARLIAMENT IS CLEAR RECOGNITION THAT IN THIS MOST<br />
IMPORTANT AREA OF LAW, WITH ITS OWN SPECIAL PROBLEMS AND<br />
A NEED FOR SPECIAL PROCEDURES, THERE IS GREAT MERIT IN<br />
HAVING A COURT THAT HAS JURISDICTION THROUGHOUT AUSTRALIA,<br />
AND THAT CAN INTERPRET AND APPLY THAT LAW ON A UNIFORM BASIS.<br />
THE SUPERIOR COURT WILL ENABLE A CONSOLIDATION OF<br />
JURISDICTION THAT IS NOW EXERCISED BY FEDERAL AND TERRITORY<br />
COURTS. IT WILL BRING TOGETHER IN THE ONE COURT THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN INDUSTRIAL COUR-r, THE FEDERAL COURT OF BANKRUPTCY<br />
AND THE SUPREME COURTS OF THE AUSTRALIAN CAPTIAL TERRITORY<br />
AND THU NORTHERN TERRITORY, IT WILL ENABLE THE JURISDICTION<br />
OF THESE COURTS TO BE EXERCISED ON A MORE RATIONAL AND<br />
COMPREHENSIVE BASIS, I I ! e </p>
<p>IT IS ALMOST SEVEN YEARS SINCE THE FIRST BILL<br />
TO ESTABLISH THE SUPERIOR COURT WAS INTRODUCED INTO THIS<br />
HOUSE, CAN ANYONE DOUBT THAT IT IS TIME THAT WE MOVED<br />
ON THIS MATTER? IS IT NOT TIME THE OPPOSITION STOPPED<br />
PREVARICATING? SHOULD WE NOT NOW PUT THE INTERESTS OF ALL<br />
AUSTRALIANS AHEAD OF STATE RIGHTS AND PARTY CONSIDERATIONS?<br />
-0-0-0-0-0-0-</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
