<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>12235</transcript-id>
    <title>Labor Blocks Education Reforms</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/06/2001</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Labor's negative wrecking tactics in the Senate have blocked important education and innovation policies.</p>
<p>While Mr Beazley talks about the Knowledge Nation he has allowed Labor Senators to oppose the passage of the Innovation and Education Amendment Bill.</p>
<p>As a result:<br />
? establishment funding has been denied to many new, low fee non-government schools;<br />
? funding has been denied for students with disabilities in non-government schools; and<br />
? important new measures to foster innovation have been blocked.</p>
<p>The Labor Party should be judged by their actions, not their empty rhetoric on education and innovation.</p>
<p>The legislation blocked by Labor in the Senate was to provide assistance to a wide cross section of new schools including Catholic systemic schools, Christian community schools and non-denominational schools, with many serving the most needy in our community.</p>
<p>The same legislation contains funding for students with disabilities in non-government schools.</p>
<p>Mr Beazley has also blocked new measures aimed at fostering innovation. These measures include the Post-Graduate Education Loans Scheme.</p>
<p>Virtually on the eve of the release of his long-awaited Knowledge Nation report, Mr Beazley has blocked an important scheme aimed at enhancing the skills of some of our best and brightest students.</p>
<p>Mr Beazley had an opportunity to demonstrate that he is serious about boosting education and innovation but he has again failed the test. It is another demonstration that the policy-lazy Labor Party has no solutions.</p>
<p>29 June 2001</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
