<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9253</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON PJ KEATING MP FRENCH BUSINESS COMMUNITY LUNCH, PARIS, WEDNESDAY 8 JUNE</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/06/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009253.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
* 1 tToh, su<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
ADDRESS BY THE PRINE IINISTER, THE RON P J KEA3rNG xP<br />
FRDICH BUSINESS COINXNITY LUNCH, PARIS, WEDNESDAY S JUNE<br />
Thank you very much for coming. It is gratifying to see<br />
so many senior business figures who have taken time off<br />
from their heavy commitments to be here today.<br />
I am in France because fifty years ago Australians took<br />
part in the landings in Normandy. Australians were here<br />
then as they had been in the First World War. It is one<br />
of the remarkable features of our history that a<br />
profound part of it was written on the battlefields of<br />
France. A tragic part of it, yet a part which shaped the<br />
Australian nation and the national character.<br />
In fact the threads of our relationship go back much<br />
further than the wars: they go back to the foundations of<br />
European settlement in Australia. In 1788 as the Aritish<br />
raised the Union Jack on the shores of Sydney Harbour, La<br />
Perouse was anchored just offshore.<br />
Indeed, the Australian coast from Perth to Hobart is<br />
dotted with the names left behind by La Perouse, Baudin<br />
and D'Entrecasteux.<br />
The map of Australia tells the story of a scientific or<br />
academic interest, rather than a commercial one.<br />
I" am here today to tell you that we believe the time has<br />
come to convert your interest to wholehearted economic<br />
engagement. To be an Australian in the nineties is to feel present at<br />
a definitive moment in our history. Literally definitive<br />
the culture, including the work and business culture,<br />
the economy, the nation's identity and international<br />
direction are all being re-defined and newly articulated.<br />
Australia's place in the world is being re-defined.<br />
I believe the decade will, in time, be seen as one in<br />
which the remnants of post-colonial ambivalence were<br />
swept away, not with any loss to our best traditions, but<br />
with the creation of institutions and procedures. which<br />
reflect the great changes of recent years and are<br />
appropriate to the reality and needs of Australia in the<br />
twenty first century.<br />
67 2 8 Mai fri<br />
wi rei 101<br />
De' th: ma( cu2 In<br />
cai tal rej<br />
The ou: if<br />
aI co AU en Su<br />
de exj us<br />
Jul us ini an<br />
bu th Th wol<br />
Thi thq Thi col wil </p>
<p>The old barriers to the world outside and, in particular,<br />
to our own region the Asia-Pacific have been<br />
substantially removed.<br />
mass post war migration, first from Europe, and then also<br />
from Asia, long ago broke down the old monoculture and<br />
with it the xenophobia which, if not entirely the<br />
reality, was certainly the image of Australia for a very<br />
long time.<br />
Deliberate government policies, combined with what I<br />
think is a strong underlying tradition of tolerance have<br />
made it surely one of most successful examples of<br />
cultural pluralism in the world.<br />
In the last decade the Australian economy has also been<br />
capital conro isadudroka araaic program ot<br />
tariff reductions.<br />
The sum result of the chanqes in Australia has been that<br />
we now see ourselves in a much larger mirror a mirror<br />
which reflects the comparative advantages on which we<br />
must build and the comparative shortcomings which we must<br />
rectify. The same mirror also suggests that we must clearly define<br />
ourselves. If it is true that companies need corporate identities in<br />
a competitive world, it is probably also true of<br />
countries; and the need is greater f or a country like<br />
Australia which has undergone rapid change and is now<br />
entering the new world of the Asia-Pacific.<br />
Such an identity does not need to be invented: the<br />
deeper understanding and the imperatives which flow from<br />
exposure to the world will essentially articulate it for<br />
US. Just as this exposure in the plainest possible way told<br />
us that work place practices had to change, and<br />
international best business practice had to be applied,<br />
and inflation controlled, and an environment in which<br />
business, especially export business the business of<br />
the future could flourish.<br />
That is what has happened. And, because in a competitive<br />
world change never stops, it is continuing to happen.<br />
There has been massive structural and cultural change in<br />
the Australian economy and the results are striking.<br />
That is why, entirely without apology, I am urging French.<br />
companies to invest inAustralia. I can assure you it<br />
will be good for both'of us. 67 2.9 </p>
<p>3<br />
Never has the climate for investment been better.<br />
We have the highest economic growth in the OECD. In the<br />
last twelve months GDP increased by 5 per cent and<br />
employment rose by over 3 per cent.<br />
We have corporate profit share at an all time high of<br />
just over eighteen per cent of GDP.<br />
We have interest rates at their lowest level for twenty<br />
years. We have inflation at around 1 per cent even less based<br />
on the product deflators in the national accounts. And<br />
we have it locked in by an Accord on wages with the trade<br />
unions. We have wages increasingly linked to<br />
improvements in productivity.<br />
A revolution in the industrial culture has given us the<br />
lowest level of industrial disputes for decades.<br />
There is strong export growth. Ten years ago exports<br />
made up no mare than 13 per cent of Australian GDP<br />
today that figure is over 20 per cent and they are much<br />
more diverse. The proportion of manufactures is now<br />
equal to the proportion of agricultural product. Exports<br />
of elaborately transformed manufactures have risen by<br />
per cent in the past three years.<br />
And when you see where our exports are going you see<br />
another reason why you should invest.<br />
if rising demand in the domestic-market is the first 1<br />
reason, the international market is the second. ourIt<br />
firms have demonstrated that Australia is a wonderful c<br />
base from which to export into the booming Asia-Pacific h<br />
markets. AW. all of us here today know, the scale of change in Asia 9<br />
isremarkable. d<br />
Take China.<br />
At the present rate of growth, China's economay is e<br />
doubling every eight years. c<br />
While world trade grew by about So per cent between 1996 a,<br />
and 1992, the trade of the three Chinese economies grew Ki<br />
by 180 per cent.<br />
But of course there is much more to Asian dynamism than a,<br />
China. There are the rapidly growing markets of South a<br />
East Asia, including that of Australia's nearest T<br />
neighbour, Indonesia, and the likely new tiger, Vietnam. i<br />
67: 30 </p>
<p>It is with this most dynamic region of the world that<br />
Australia now does most of its business.<br />
Well over half of Australia's merchandise exports go to<br />
-East -Asian markets. Almost two-thirds of our total<br />
exports go to Asia. Australia's trade relationship with<br />
Japan is one of the economic sinews of the region.<br />
In the last five years our annual average -axpor-t -growth<br />
to the ASEAN reqion has been more than double the growth<br />
of our total exports and the increase in our exports of<br />
elaborately transformed manufactures has been<br />
particularly dramatic.<br />
more and more Australian businesses are being born of our<br />
new Asian export culture. One-third of our exports of<br />
elaborately transformed manufactures are coming from<br />
small firms that have begun exporting only in the last<br />
ten years.<br />
These days Australian companies measure themselves<br />
against Asian levels of productivity and competitiveness.<br />
We have substantial advantages: a skilled multicultural<br />
workforce, high standards of education, political<br />
stability, an effective legal framework, well-developed<br />
infrastructure and a continuing program of microeconomic<br />
reform.<br />
Australia is a leading information technology country.<br />
We invest more of our GDP in telecommunications than<br />
Japan, Singapore or Hong Kong.<br />
We have more computers per head of population a third<br />
more than our nearest rival, Singapore than any other<br />
country in the Western Pacific, and more telephones per<br />
head of population than anyone else in the region.<br />
Australia is a very good place to do business, a very<br />
good place to establish regional headquarters which is<br />
woat many international service companies have already<br />
done. Not only can we more than match the newly industrialised<br />
economies of Asia in skills, productivity, stability and<br />
certainty, investors will find that the cost of an<br />
international telephone call, office space and housing,<br />
are significantly lower than, say, Singapore and Hong<br />
Kong. They will find a corporate tax rate of just 33 per cent,<br />
a 10 per cent tax rate for Offt Shore Banking Units, and<br />
accelerated depreciation rates for plant and equipment.<br />
They will find that the overall tax burden in Australia<br />
is the lowest of all OECD countries. G7 3 t<br />
p </p>
<p>They will find a lot more space to live in, air that is a<br />
lot cleaner and the trip to the office quicker and less<br />
stressful.<br />
They will also find a first class universal health<br />
system, and schools, hospitals and social services which<br />
in general have few peers in the world.<br />
They will find a small public sector but an effective<br />
one. They will find a Western culture in an Asian location and<br />
in an Asian time-zone.<br />
In short, they will find that Australia is a very good Y<br />
place to live and work.<br />
In the 1980s Australia rejected the socially regressive<br />
forms of economic rationalism in favour of structural C<br />
reform allied to inclusive social policies. I<br />
Last month we delivered a major statement on employment F<br />
a comprehensive strategy for training and returning the e<br />
long term unemployed to the workforce.<br />
The strategy will deliver to us greater levels of social t<br />
cohesion and justice and a more skilled and flexible<br />
workforce. A b<br />
We are building our economy on skills and productivityt<br />
coupled with a sophisticated social net.<br />
We have no intention of im~ itating the wage regimen of w<br />
developing countries. We have proved that we can compete r<br />
by other means and be considerably more attractive toI<br />
overseas investors.<br />
In other words, Australia offers a perfect springboard b<br />
for companies wanting to take advantage of the dynamic T)<br />
Aslan markets. al<br />
You will be aware that Australia has taken a leading role<br />
in building new structures in the region for trade and s<br />
security. t<br />
Last year I attended the first meeting of APEC countries a<br />
in 9 -eattle., There fourteen Asia-Pacific leiders laid of<br />
down objectives for the future. t<br />
The aim is open regionalism regional tradeLt<br />
liberalisation which avoids disadvantage to others.<br />
We envisage ultimately an integrated market bringing<br />
together the economies of Australia, ASEN, the three<br />
Chinas, Korea, Japan and North America.<br />
63% 8 </p>
<p>A market of 2 billion people, producing half the world's<br />
output, with harmonised trade and investment rules,<br />
harmonised standards and certification and agreed means<br />
of settling disputes.<br />
APEC leaders will meet again in Indonesia later this<br />
year, lending weight to the gathering momentum of<br />
cooperation in the region.<br />
It must be stressed that neither APEC nor Australia has<br />
in mind turning away from others parts of the world. We<br />
are certainly not talking about raising barriers.<br />
We are inextricably linked to the world economy. We<br />
depend on an open world trading system. We unequivocally<br />
support the multilateral system.<br />
our increasing integration with Asia does not mean that<br />
Europe is fading from our minds.<br />
Far from it, we remain actively engaged with European<br />
economies and we want to do much more.<br />
We want to do nore with France. And the gathering here<br />
today rather suggests that we are and that we will.<br />
At present only 7 per cent of exports from the fourth<br />
biggest economy in the world go to East Asia. I know<br />
that Monsieur Longuet wants to change that with his<br />
" French Initiative Towards Asia". I am sure that he<br />
-Qiti France to dramatically increase her trade-with the<br />
region before other players take their shalre._-<br />
I am in no doubt that great benefits will flow to both<br />
our countries if French companies make Australia their<br />
base for moving into these new markets.<br />
There is also very great potential for increased trade<br />
and investment between our two countries.<br />
In recent times a number of French companies have made<br />
substantial investments in areas as diverse as<br />
telecommunications, air traffic control systems, resort<br />
management, waste water treatment, film and television<br />
and viticulture the last being an outstanding example<br />
of cross investment combined with cooperation in<br />
technology and research.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen, if for the first two ' centuries of 6733 </p>
<p>Leadei<br />
We find them in vineyards from Western Australia to the<br />
Hunter Valley of New South Wales. We find them in the<br />
industrial suburbs and the central business districts of<br />
our major cities. we find thou in laboratories and film<br />
studios. They are present in the booming tourist<br />
industry of Queensland as investors and managers, and<br />
as tourists.<br />
We want to see more of France in Australia and more of<br />
the French.<br />
I therefore hope to see you, M. Longuet, in Australia<br />
soon. I also hope to see those of you here today and<br />
senior executives from other French companies later this<br />
year at our second National Trade and Investment<br />
Conference, when France will be the European country<br />
invited to join representatives from the Asia-Pacific.<br />
It is for this reason that I want to thank the people who<br />
organised this gathering, particularly Club Australie<br />
with which I know many of you have been associated, and<br />
M. Gandois who has played a crucial role in developing<br />
business links between our two countries.<br />
It is great enterprise and I have no doubt it will be a<br />
very rewarding one.<br />
ENDS 67 : 14 RPdrrfiimaMt </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
