<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5408</transcript-id>
    <title>REPORT OF THE COMMITTEE OF INQUIRY INTO TECHNOLOGICAL CHANGE IN AUSTRALIA</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>31/07/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005408.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
L1A3Rf-7P-Y F146--<br />
FOR MEDIA THURSDAY, 31 JULY, 1980<br />
REPORT OF THE COMMITTEE OF INQUIRY<br />
INTO TECHNOLOGICAL CHANGE IN AUSTRALIA<br />
Following widespread public debate about the merits of<br />
technological change, and concern at possible adverse<br />
consequences, the Government announced on 1 December, 1978<br />
that it was establishing a Committee of Inquiry into<br />
Technological Change in Australia.<br />
The Committee has now completed its work and I am pleased<br />
to be able to release its Report today for public discussion<br />
and comment.<br />
The Committee emphasises that it is essential for Australian<br />
industry primary, secondary and tertiary to keep up with<br />
technological developments if it is to compete internationally<br />
and if we as Australians are to realise the full potential of<br />
our economy.<br />
The Government strongly endorses that central conclusion of<br />
the Committee.<br />
A special Committee of Cabinet has been established to<br />
consider the Committee' s recommendations, and the assessment<br />
that underlies them, as a matter of high priority.<br />
I am confident that this consideration will lead to<br />
substantial acceptance of the Committee's recommendations.<br />
The Government also expects a constructive response to the<br />
Report from the community generally.<br />
The Government welcomes the excellent Report which this<br />
representative Committee has produced. It believes that<br />
this Report will greatly assist the community and the Government<br />
in understanding and dealing with technological change.<br />
The most important task set for the Committee was to report<br />
and make recommendations to the Government on the process of<br />
technological change in Australian industry in order that<br />
the Australian community should maximise the economic, social<br />
and other benefits and minimise any possible adverse<br />
consequences. / 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
In presenting its assessment of the economic, social and other<br />
effects of technological change the Committee stresses the<br />
strong links between change, economic growth and improved<br />
living standards. In doing so it points out that the process<br />
of adjustment to change will not necessarily be calm or easy.<br />
Many of its recommendations, therefore, are aimed at ensuring<br />
that the benefits of change are maximised and adverse effects<br />
minimised. The Committee points out that if the community is to obtain<br />
the greatest benefits from new technologies, a more co-operative<br />
and mutually supportive approach than has generally prevailed in<br />
Australia in the past will be needed. The future introductio ' n<br />
of new technology without undue and potentially costly industrial<br />
resistance, Is likely to depend importantly on labour force and<br />
community understanding and acceptance, which will in part<br />
depend on how those affected by technological change are,<br />
treated, and how they see themselves and are seen by others<br />
as being treated.<br />
The Government strongly supports the general objectives of<br />
fostering a more consultative and facilitative approach, as<br />
well as a wider understanding and acceptance of technological<br />
change. I will be announcing the Government's considered response to<br />
the recommendations early in the Budget Session of Parliament.<br />
The Committee was chaired by Professor Rupert H1. Myers,<br />
Vice-Chancellor and Principal of the University of New South<br />
Wales. Other members were Mr. A. G. Coogan, now Chairman of<br />
Nabalco Pty. Ltd. and Mr. W. C. Mansfield, Federal Secretary.<br />
of the Australian Telecommunications Employees' Association.<br />
The Government is deeply grateful to the members of the<br />
Committee and its secretariat, and to the many others,<br />
organisations and individuals who assisted it in its work.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
