<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8261</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTERS STATEMENT PRESS CONFERENCE 28 FEBRUARY 1991</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/02/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008261.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
C? RAII-IDELLVEHY EM5ARQQGOEED. J-I DELIVERY.<br />
PRIME MINISTERS STATEMENT<br />
PRESS CONFERENCE 28 FEBRUARY 1991<br />
LADIES AND GENTLEMEN, IRAQ'S OCCUPATION OF KUWAIT HAS COME<br />
TO AN END.<br />
Mi. lJTARY OPERATIONS BY THE COALITION FORCES, CONIIUCTDI UNDER<br />
RESOLUTION 678 OF T]' HE UNITED NATIONS SECURITY COUNCIL.,. ARE<br />
REJNG SUSPENDED AT THIS MOMENT.<br />
' FF1~ 4 HAVE BEEN SET DOWN FOR A FORMAL CEASE-FIRE., WHITCH WE<br />
HOPFF CAN 6E CONCLJIOF Wi'rHOU'' DET.. AY.<br />
AS!. THAT (, All PREVENT THIIS SUSPEIISION BECOHI1NG PERHANEN1 JS A<br />
REFFUSAL, RY SADDAM HUSSEIN TO COMPLY WITH T'up. roTrA[, lYV<br />
REASONABLE CoI) iTioNs I. ATD fl. WN I'V TTPE 11Lr.<br />
ON MY INSTRUCTIONS, TiF llFF THE UFFEHU-E FORCE HAS<br />
DIRECTED AUSTRALIA'S ' ASK FORCE IN THE CIILF ro SuIzPEND<br />
iOSTItITI ES UNDER ' v! iEi TERMS ANTI' 1'? I-CFD RY pRRSIll'E D)<br />
1 ) 511 ' IDIS<br />
ArTERNoONr). I'PEAKINC FOR AUSTIRAI. A, 7Q? 411 SIPEnrAF. Il ro) lYSEJE, illS IS A<br />
MOMEN'T OF GREAT RELIEF AND hTOPE, GREAAT PITO. ? I-jD A1, SO 01-<br />
GREAT'r SORROW.<br />
WF ARE SAD TA'' IT IIAS BEEN NECE5SARY To RESORT O W4AR TO<br />
RIGHT THE WRONG PERPETRATED BY SAIIDAM IUS! EEN () iJ 2 AII( 3S'T<br />
WHEN HE INVADEDF KUWAIT.<br />
BUT WE ARE GIAI) THAT THE WORLD HAS STOOD UNITED) AGAINHST IllS<br />
ACT OF AGGRESSION, EVEN TO THE ULTIMATE SANC'I' 10\ l1 OF WAR.<br />
WqlE ARE GLAD TIHAT THE UNI'' ED NATIONS HAS STOOD TRUE TO lITS<br />
PRINCIPLES. AND THAT IT HAS SUCCFE) ED, IIROIjI TIlE SECURITY<br />
COUNCIL, IN API, YNG THOSE PRINCIPLES IN AC'TION.<br />
W4E ARE PROUD OF THE CONTRIBUTION WE [ N AUSTRA. IA HAVE MADE,<br />
AND ESPECIALLY THE CON1TRIBUTION OF MEMBERS OF OUR AUSTRALIAN<br />
IEFENCE FORCE, TO THIS GREAT INTERNATIONAL UNDERTAKING.<br />
AND TODAY ABOVE ALL WE REJOICE THAT THE WAR HAS BEEN WON<br />
QUICKLY, AND WITH SO FEW CASUJALTIES TO OUR ALLIED FORCES.<br />
S484 </p>
<p>FOR TH E PEOPLE OF KUWAIT, THIS VICTORY BRINGS TO AN END OVER<br />
SEVEN MONTHS OF OCCUPATION MARKED BY PERSECUTION, ATROCITIES<br />
AND DESTRUCTION. WE SHARE THEIR JOY IN LIBERATION.<br />
F'OR IRAQ ALSO THE 1PRICE HAS BEEN TERRIBLE. WE GRIEVE FOR<br />
THlE PEOPLE OF THIS TRAGIC COUNTRY, AND WE HOPE THAT THEY CAN<br />
QUICKLY BIND THEIR WOUNDS AND REBUILD THEIR NATION AS A<br />
RESPECTED AND RESPONSIBLE MEMBER OF' THE INTERNATIONAL<br />
COMMUNITY. W4E MUST UNDERSTAND THAT THE END OF THE WAR IS NOT TUE END OF<br />
THE CRISIS. MUCH REMAINS TO BE DONE TO BRING STABILITY TO<br />
THE GULF, AND TO BRING A WIDER, DURABLE PEACE TO THE MIDDLE<br />
EASTr. THIE END OF THE WAR SHOULD BRING NEW OPPORTUNITIES TO ADDRESS<br />
THESE OLD PROBLEMS. OUR HOPE IS THAT THE SENSE OF<br />
COMMITMENT AND COOPERATION WHICH SO MANY NATIONS IN THE<br />
MIDDLE EAST AND THROUGHOUT THE WORLD HAVE SHOWN IN<br />
CONFRONTING SADDAM HUSSEIN WILL BE SHOWN AGAIN IN MEETING<br />
THE CHALLENGES AHEAD.<br />
AUSTRALIA WILL PLAY ITS PART IN MAKING SURE THAT THIS<br />
VICTORY IS A VICTORY FOR ALL THE PEOPLE OF THE MIDDLE EAST.<br />
BUT IT IS MORE THAN THAT. IT IS A VICTORY FOR PEOPLE<br />
EVERYWHERE WHO WOULD LIVE IN PEACE. IT REAFFIRMS THAT THE<br />
WORLD IS INDEED A WORLD COMMUNITY; THAT THE WORLD COMMUNITY<br />
IS UNITED IN ITS COMMITMENT TO RESIST AGGRESSION; AND THAT<br />
THE WORLD COMMUNITY HAS, IN THE UNITED NATIONS, AN EFFECTIVE<br />
INSTRUMENT TO CONFRONT THE AGGRESSOR, IF ALL ELSE FAILS,<br />
WITH THE ONLY ARGUMENT HE UNDERSTANDS THE ARGUMENT OF<br />
FORCE. WE CANNOT PREDICT THE SHAPE OF THE NEW INTERNATIONAL ORDER.<br />
BUT WE DO KNOW THAT THE COMPREHENSIVE DEFEAT OF SADDAM<br />
HUSSEIN IN KUWAIT WILL STAND AS A WARNING BEACON FOR YEARS<br />
TO COME TO ANYONE WHO WOULD CONSIDER AGGRESSION.<br />
SO THE WORLD IS A SAFER PLACE TODAY.<br />
IN4 THIS GREAT ACHIEVEMENT, THE UNITED) STATES HAS PLAYED A<br />
SPECIAL PART. THROUGHOUT THIS CRISIS, THE UNITED STATES HAS<br />
EMPLOYED ITS AUTHORITY AND ITS POWER TO SERVE INTERESTS<br />
WHICH WERE NOT AMERICA'S ALONE, BUT WERE THE INTERESTS OF<br />
THE WORLD COMMUNITY AS A WHOLE. PRESIDENT BUSH AND THE<br />
PEOPLE OF THE UNITED STATES HAVE OUR ADMIRATION FOR THEIR<br />
CONDUCT AND THEIR LEADERSHIP, AND OUR THANKS FOR THEIR<br />
COMMITMENT AND THEIR WILLINGNESS TO SACRIFICE IN A CAUSE WE<br />
ALL SHARE.<br />
FINALLY I TURN TO OUR OWN PEOPLE WHO HAVE RISKED THEIR LIVES<br />
IN THIS GREAT ENTERPRISE THE CREWS OF OUR SHIPS AND THEIR<br />
SUPPORT TEAMS, OUR. DIVERS, OUR MEDICAL TEAMS AND OUR<br />
EXCHANGE PERSONNEL., ALL THE PEOPLE OF THE ADF WHO HAVE<br />
HELPED TO SUPPORT THEM, AND OF COURSE THEIR FAMILIES AND<br />
LOVED ONES LEFT AT HOME. 5485 </p>
<p>3.<br />
WE ARE PROUD OF THE SKILL THAT OUR SERVICEMEN AND WOMEN HAVE<br />
SHOWN, WHICH HAS OFTEN WON FOR THEM THE PRIVILEGE OF DOING<br />
DIFFICULT AND DANGEROUS TASKS. THEY HAVE DONE HONOUR TO<br />
THEMSELVES, TO THEIR SERVICE, AND TO THE NATION.<br />
WE IN TURN HONOUR THEM. WE REJOICE THAT THEY HAVE BEEN<br />
SPARED CASUALTIES, AND WE HOPE THAT WE CAN WELCOME THEM<br />
SAFELY HOME SOON.<br />
548(; </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
