<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2271</transcript-id>
    <title>QUEENSLAND YOUNG LIBERALS YOUTH DINNER</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/08/1970</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002271_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
QUEENSLAND YOUNG* LIBERALS<br />
YOUTH DIDNN3MR<br />
Brisbane, QId 6 AUGUST 1970<br />
õ pqef~ bythePrime Minister, Mr. John Gorton<br />
Mr. President, Distinguished Guests, Ladies and Gentlemen:<br />
Mention has been made of a generation gap, and that is a subject to which<br />
I have been devoting some thought because we hear so much about it. And I find that<br />
I have come to the conclusion that it doesn't exist. You would know better than i,<br />
whether it does or not. I can only say that I don't feel that it exists.<br />
Of course there are occasiorally difficulties in communication between an<br />
older man and a younger one, but there are equally difficulties in communication<br />
between an older man and another older one and a young man and a young one. It<br />
is n~ t a -matter, 1. suggest, of age, but a matter of whether one talks the same language,<br />
thinks the same way and can carry on a dialogue. And I think that in Australia today,<br />
as far as I have experienced it, I have been able to carry on dialogues, discussions<br />
with young people, including my own sons, who disagree with almost everything I dc-'<br />
But that doesn't prevent a reasonable exchange of ideas which sometimes ends in<br />
agreement to differ, and sometimes in agreement to concur.<br />
I have some doubt as to whether the generation gap of which we hear so<br />
much really does exist, but as I say, you would know better that 1.<br />
We hear of a generation of dissent, and I doubt whether that is true Of<br />
course, now as alwa'ys in the past, young peoplc question the values that have been<br />
handed on to them, question the customs which have been handed on to them.. They<br />
always have. I can remember, and I am sure that I am the same as everybody else,<br />
at one stage thinking that my own father just simply didn't understand anything about<br />
what was going on at all. But as I got a little older, I realised he had learnt a lot in<br />
the last few years.<br />
But this is natural questioning, proper questioning of young people when they<br />
find themselves inheriting a world and responsibility for trying to see that it becomes<br />
a better one. So I doubt whether what we hear about so much is as widespread as it<br />
is claimed to be.<br />
Vl1hat vias said about the effect of the media in spreading these views again<br />
is, I think, true, and true because news s news. A dog bites a man, that's natural.<br />
If a man bites a dog, it's news because it is unusual and abnormal. And if that is so,<br />
then the concentration of media and television on people invading university rooms,<br />
of people sitting down in roadways.. the very fact that that is concentrated on<br />
indicates that it is unusual and that it is abnormal, and I believethat it is. ./ 2 </p>
<p>I believe that at any university, for exanmle, to which you may go, 90-95 percent Of<br />
the students there are interested in their work, in their studies, in their sport, in<br />
parties, in the normal things that make u-. p the life of young people.<br />
And, of course, what goes on arid what is not recorded are the contributions<br />
that youth makes to the community, the oositive contribution and I have taken<br />
out some facts showing what the young people i n Queensland have done, which have<br />
never made headlines, which have never been reported and which I think are more<br />
typical of the young people of Australia than the things that do get before you.<br />
Students of the Queensland University raised 000 for charity during their<br />
commemoration week earlier this year. Students of the Queensland University raised<br />
000 foi the aid of earthquake victim,--during World University Service week. Law<br />
students at the u-niversity are providing a free legal aid scheme in co-operation with<br />
a church's " life-line" activities. Studenits at this school, the Church of England Grammar<br />
have raised $ 5,013 from their pocket-money this year to aid charity projects, and have<br />
taken part in such activities as cleaniing up,: the beaches in Queensland. All these<br />
things, I believe, are more typical of thle appro. ach of the youth of Australia than are<br />
the things to which greater attention terifds to be given by the media.<br />
But it is right and proper that questioning by youth should occur, questioning<br />
of the world which has been handed on to them. And what sort of a world is it? dow<br />
does youth see it' I naturally, do not k--now the answer to this, but I do know that the<br />
world that is handed on to you is a much better one to live in than it used to be a<br />
generation ago.<br />
It is not so very long in Australia since there was immense industrial<br />
injustice, so that people if they wished to earn their living on the wharves, would have<br />
to go and stand in a bull ring and be Dicked out and hired for a day; perhaps chosen by<br />
favouritism or chosen by a foremarn if they were prepared to pay part of the wages they<br />
earned to that foreman. It is not so very long ago since that happened.<br />
It is not so very long ago sice people feared unemployment and depression<br />
and when a man would never know whether he could maintain his famii3: from one year,<br />
to the next because unemployment and the fear of it hung over his head. And that, too,<br />
led to industrial and economic injustice. it is not so very long ago sin ce the poverty<br />
in this country vias so widespread that it is almost impossible for you, I think, to envisage<br />
what it was like. And so there has beer: iimprovement in the world compared with what<br />
it used to be. There have been great advances in combating poverty. There have been great<br />
advai~ ces in giving economic security to mankind. There have been great advances in<br />
the elimination injustice. And 3o, hovaever this present world may appear today<br />
through the eyes of youth, it is much better than it was. And my generation can take<br />
some credit, I t hink, for having built it into what it is today. / 3 </p>
<p>3.<br />
But now or very soon the results of your present questioning have got to<br />
come to fruition. Your thoughts and asp-Irations will have to be put into practice, How<br />
then would you want to improve the world as it is today?<br />
This is the first question youth should ask itself, I think. How they wish to<br />
improve the world, because until they know how and where they want to go, until they<br />
know the kind a! improvements they wiant to make, they have very little chance indeed<br />
of affecting any improvements because they don't know the paths they wish to follow.<br />
Perhaps you would say, " We wiould like to build a world where there is no<br />
poverty at all as there is undoubtedly too much now. We would like to build a world<br />
where we had more feeling of involvement and of fulfilment in our lives. Where sheer<br />
material benefits were not held in as great esteem as they are now, but rather a<br />
comrnunit,, to which we could contribute and fromr which and in w~ hich we could develop<br />
our own personality and feel a satisfaction in living". Perhaps these are the things<br />
that you would seek as improvements. I hope they are because they are the kind of<br />
improvements that I feel we can -make and should make in the years ahead.<br />
. Lh ere will be difficulties in the way. Firstly, it will be necessary,<br />
essential, to maintain that political freedom under which we operate at present. There<br />
has been no threat to it in the lifetime of moost of you, but there have been threats of<br />
that political freedom being overthrown in the past and there may be dangers of it<br />
being attached from outside in the future.<br />
But perhaps more significantly that freedom could be lost inside without<br />
invasion. We see now tolerance carried to too great a length because although tolerance<br />
is one of the essentials for a proper commrunity, yet there are some things which<br />
cannot be tolerated. For example, you cannot safely tolerate intolerance, and we see<br />
examples of intolerance in the name of dissent and in the name of civic rights. And<br />
it will be necessary for young peo. ple to make their minds up as to where the line is drawn<br />
when tolerance cannot be extended any further, and at what point it is necessary to<br />
defend the civic rights of the vast majority against attack in the name of civic rights of<br />
a minority. These will, I think, be difficulties, not great difficulties, not great but<br />
nevertheless onies which will exist and do exist i this country.<br />
But it will not be enough mnerely to maintain political freedom. It is essential<br />
that it be properly used, I mean. by that that it is essential that if people are to<br />
contribute to a country, then the contrasting and conflicting ideas whicn are advanced<br />
by political parties ought to be critically examined by each individual, ought to be<br />
analysed by each individual. And if faith is to be kept with those who have fought<br />
for political freedom, then not by slogants, but by applied intelligence, should each<br />
individual decide what ideas they wish to accept. 6 / 4 </p>
<p>4.<br />
Side by side with that political freedom, I hope that you will be able to<br />
advance still further towards the economic freedom which some time ago we did not have<br />
at all, which now we have in large measure, but which we can have in even greater<br />
measure if we take the opportunity that this Australia gives us today.<br />
This won't be easy. It won't be easy to abolish poverty unless enough wealth<br />
is produced to enable that to happen. There is no easy way to run a country or to live<br />
in it. It is essential in every sphere of life that there should be hard work, that there<br />
should be the application of intelligence, that there should be a training of the mind,<br />
that there should be a willingness to contribute to the community.<br />
I think the youth of Australia today have those qualities in greater measure<br />
than did we. I have the utmost hope for the future of this country because of that belief.<br />
At any rcLe, the whole thing shortly will be in your hands. The fact that you are here<br />
tonight irdicates a willingness to participate, a desire to participate, and if that is true,<br />
then you have another weapon we did not have you have greater opportunities for<br />
education to enable that cont ribution to be the better applied.<br />
There are some eternal values, and those I think are these. We must have in<br />
a proper community, kindness the one towards the other; tolerance within the limits of<br />
which I have spo: en; sacrifice and work. Because I think you have these qualities and<br />
because I know the opportunities for their use are in Australia more than they are in<br />
any other country in the world, then I feel that you will meet the challenges before you.<br />
I hope that at some time in twenty, or thirty years, one of you perhaps will stand where<br />
I am standing today and talk to those who then will be young and you won't be because<br />
youth is the stuff that does not endure and that vou will be able to say to the young to<br />
whom you talk and my generation i:. herited a world that was not bad but by our<br />
efforts we have made it so much better." ( And the young to whom you are talking will<br />
probably look at you and think, " VWell you haven't done much about it, really, and it is<br />
up to us to make it better still in the future. But if you can stand here and say that<br />
and know that you are speaking the truth, then I think you will have contributed to the<br />
building of a great nation, to the building of a great society and 1: 0o the development of<br />
your own individual capacity which is quite possibly the most important thing of all.<br />
And that I think is all I have to say to you. I did not want to talk on politics<br />
tonight. I did riot want to talk orn issues of the hour, for they are ephemeral, they go,<br />
but the results of applying one's mind and heart and spirit to trying to better the<br />
society in which one is living are not ephemeral...... and this is an c, bjective I hope<br />
will remain with you for the whole of your lives. Indeed, I think it will because I<br />
finish as I began by saying I do not thirnk this is a generation of dissent or disenchantment.<br />
I believe that for the vast majority of youth it is a generation which offers opportunities<br />
unknown before and that the vast majority of youth are prepared to accept and use those<br />
opportunities, and I hope I am right in that. But I am putting before you things as an<br />
older man sees them. You will make up your own mind whether what I have said is<br />
true or not. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
