<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>21870</transcript-id>
    <title>Doorstop Interview Parliament House, Canberra </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/08/2005</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I would like on behalf of the Australian Government to compliment the Prime Minister of Israel, Ariel Sharon, on the enormous courage he has displayed in relation to the withdrawal from the Gaza settlements. It really is going to make a tremendous contribution to the peace process in the Middle East.  It wouldn't have been easy, he has had to confront people who have been lifelong supporters of his in the Israeli political scene, he's shown very great determination, and he deserves praise and credit for the leadership that he's displayed. We all hope for a lasting settlement in the Middle East between the Palestinians and the Israelis. The Israelis are fulfilling their part of the bargain. Ariel Sharon is making a huge contribution and we naturally want to see a continuation of the process because everybody hopes that with a new leadership in the Palestinians, and with this display of great commitment by the Israelis something can be achieved. But his courage is exemplary and he deserves praise and support for what he's done.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard just wondering whether we can ask a little about Barnaby Joyce, the Queensland... he'll be meeting with the National Executive and the rest of it. Are you concerned that the vote for Telstra, or the passing of this package, the acceptance of this package is coming down to 40 or 50 Queensland Nationals?</p>
<p>   PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look I'm not going to comment about all of that. We had a Party Room discussion, there was reason to bring the matter before the Party Room and we'll just see how it unfolds. Members of Parliament, whether they're members of the House of Representatives, or the Senate are entitled to talk to whoever they like - it's part of their job. I talk to people outside parliament all the time and that is part of the job, and I don't intend to dwell in particular on what an individual is doing.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister are you pleased the ban on the word mate has been lifted?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well a bit of a storm in the teacup. We should use terms that are appropriate to the context of the conversation. Often on talkback radio somebody will ring me up and I'll start by off by responding with an expression, Sir or Madam, depending on the sex of the caller, later on if the conversation becomes particularly friendly you might in a casual way say, oh thanks mate. It all depends on the context and therefore you can't really have hard and fast rules as long as courtesy appropriate to the occasion is displayed.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister just back on the Gaza Strip, do you see any role for Australia in helping the two sides meet the challenges ahead?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well we have done a lot already. We have encouraged both sides. We have good credit with both Israel and the Palestinians. Australia has been a long-standing and faithful friend of Israel's, but we have always recognised, we have for a long time recognised the right of the Palestinians to have their own homeland, and that's a view that we have put very strongly. But in the end it boils down to what the people on both sides in the Middle East do. And Ariel Sharon is displaying conspicuous courage. It's very hard to confront your own in a domestic political situation in this way, and it's very hard on the Israeli soldiers but I think they're displaying very great courage and they deserve praise and support.</p>
<p> Thank you.</p>
<p>[ends]  </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
