<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7152</transcript-id>
    <title>FUND RAISER FOR THE MACQUARIE ELECTORATE CAMPAIGN 2 APRIL 1987</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/04/1987</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007152.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
FUND RAISER FOR THE MACQUARIE ELECTORATE CAMPAIGN<br />
2 APRIL 1987<br />
David March, Ladies and Gentlemen.<br />
over the last week or so, David, you and your Macquarie<br />
electorate campaign team may have been wondering whether<br />
tonight's dinner was about to assume a somewhat larger<br />
national significance.<br />
But yesterday as you know I announced my decision not to<br />
call an early election and thereby deprived you of the<br />
pleasure of hearing my first campaign speech in our quest<br />
for an historic Third Term Labor Government.<br />
However tompting the option for an early election was and<br />
it was very tempting and however confident I was of<br />
winning and I was very confident I decided that the<br />
national interest would best be served by allowing<br />
Parliament to run its full term.<br />
It was not an easy decision to make because the opportunity<br />
which the opposition parties threw in our laps was a<br />
dramatic and significant one.<br />
Let me remind you briefl$' of the elements of that<br />
opportunity. First, the opposition has decided to use their Senate<br />
numbers to reject for the second time one of the<br />
Government's central legislative initiatives, namely the<br />
Australia Card Bill. We see this Bill as a fundamental<br />
instrument of economic management an invaluable tool for<br />
dealing decisively with tax cheats and welfare frauds who<br />
are ripping off the system.<br />
The Australia Card is a simple remedy, it is an effective<br />
remedy, and it is recognised as such by the overwhelming<br />
majority of the Australian people.<br />
In frustrating the Government on this issue and in rejecting<br />
the Australia Card, the opposition parties are displaying<br />
once more the traditional philosophy which Australian<br />
conservative Governments have made a hallmark of their style<br />
-the philosophy of protecting the privileged few while<br />
increasing the burden on the honest majority of the<br />
Australian people. </p>
<p>Their opposition to the Australia Card is not surprising.<br />
After all, they are the parties which seek to return to the<br />
wealthy few the privilege of tax-free capital gains. They<br />
are the parties which seek to remove the assets test for<br />
pensioners so that millionaires once more may draw their<br />
pension from the public purse. They are the parties which<br />
seek to scrap the Fringe Benefits Tax, and thereby allow the<br />
wealthy eligible few their expense account lunches and their<br />
company cars.<br />
So the Australia Card debate, highlighting as it did the<br />
opposition's dedicated commitment to the privileged few, and<br />
its determined campaign to frustrate our legislative<br />
program, inevitably led to speculation about whether there<br />
should be an early election.<br />
But the Opposition's reactionary attitude on that Bill<br />
pointed as well to an even more profound problem afflicting<br />
conservative politics today: the vacuum in the leadership<br />
and policy areas of both the Liberal Party and the National<br />
Party. This created a second temptation for an early election. The<br />
division and instability in the Opposition's ranks literally<br />
threatens the very principles on which Parliament must<br />
operate. The House of Representatives is currently<br />
operating without an effective Opposition or to be more<br />
precise it is operating with several ineffective oppositions<br />
which seem to be as opposed to each other as they are to the<br />
Government. The tribal warfare among the Nationals, and the<br />
protracted leadership instability among the Liberals, and<br />
the dissolution of the coalition, have made it impossible<br />
for the Australian public to establish with any certainty<br />
who is the alternative Prime Minister and what are his<br />
polices. It is inconceivable that the divided and disunited<br />
opposition parties shoulld be allowed to inflict their<br />
self-destructive urge on the nation as a whole. I was faced<br />
with the temptation of deciding whether the Australian<br />
people should be given the opportunity comprehensively and<br />
decisively to reject the politics of privilege and the<br />
politics of confrontation and to endorse the strong and<br />
stable leadership which we have provided to the nation in<br />
the last four years.<br />
And of course the evidence that our leadership is producing<br />
the desired economic outcome is steadily mounting.<br />
We are starting to see the evidence of economic<br />
restructuring as entrepreneurs take advantage of our more<br />
competitive trading situation. Our wages policy, thanks to<br />
the magnificont co-operation of the Australian workforce has<br />
produced necessary restraint in the past and, under the<br />
two-tier system, must continue to do so. Our budgetary<br />
policy has seen unprecedented Government spending restraint<br />
which we will continue to exercise in the May statement. </p>
<p>Only yesterday the nation's newspapers were reporting that<br />
no lesser authority than the Organisation for Economic<br />
Co-operation and Development had endorsed the Government's<br />
economic policies.<br />
The latest OECD report predicted growth would rise to more<br />
than 3% next year, the current account deficit would shrink<br />
to around 4.5t~ of GDP and inflation would fall to around<br />
or 5.5 by the middle of next year.<br />
So these three factors the rejection of the Australia Card<br />
Bill, the opposition disarray and the relatively favourable<br />
economic outlook gave me complete confidence that we would<br />
have won an early election.<br />
But despite th~ is confidence I decided that the Government<br />
should not go to the polls early. The temptation, however<br />
strong, had to be resisted and the opportunity, however<br />
favourable it seemed to our electoral prospects, had to be<br />
turned down. Let me tell you why I made that decision.<br />
There was no hidden motivation or secret insight which I had<br />
available to me. My decision was based on the same economic<br />
logic, the same commitment to restructuring of the economy,<br />
and the same determination to build a prosperous society<br />
which has informed all our decision making in the entire<br />
four years we have been in office.<br />
in the final analysis, it was more important that we<br />
continue to demonstrate our resolve and our capacity to meet<br />
the nation's economic challenge than that we should seek to<br />
take short term political advantage from the failures of our<br />
opponents. If we had sought an early election that decision would have<br />
created a two month period during which the economic<br />
management of our country would have taken second place to<br />
electioneering. The risk to the nation's economic recovery<br />
would not have been worth it.<br />
of course this is a logic which would be quite<br />
incomprehensible to our conservative opponents. For them<br />
economic management is nothing more than an auction in which<br />
the different conservative factions bid for votes by<br />
offering voters ever more enormous but ever more spurious<br />
handouts in the grand tradition of their notorious fistful<br />
of dollars cl~ aim.<br />
The Opposition's profligate promises on tax and spending<br />
unrepudiated to this day by Mr Howard saddle him with a<br />
$ 16 billion credibility gap. And this is before we have<br />
even started an election campaigni<br />
Against that kind of ' Alice In wonderland' arithmetic, the<br />
Labor Government has provided honest, sensible, effective<br />
and relevant solutions to the real economic challenges the<br />
nation is facing. Unlike the opposition, we have not<br />
adopted the head in the sand attitude to the collapse in our<br />
export prices which has seen the nation's income slashed by </p>
<p>more than $ 6 billion the equivalent of $ 1500 for every<br />
Australian family.<br />
It has been our challenge, and our achievement, to manage<br />
this externally imposed crisis in ways which are both<br />
effective and entirely consistent with our traditional Labor<br />
compassion and commitment to equity.<br />
I do not pretend that these policies have not required<br />
sacrifices But I do believe that those sacrifices have been<br />
shared fairly.<br />
And I also believe that the Australian people have<br />
underst-ood and have accepted the need for these sacrifices,<br />
and that they are now seeing the evidence that the<br />
sacrifices have been worthwhile.<br />
The Australian economy is on the mend.<br />
We are building a more competitive and diverse manufacturing<br />
base. We are seeing the benefits of a deregulated financial<br />
market. We are seeing continuing growth in the number of<br />
jobs more than three quarters of a million new jobs have<br />
been created since we came to office. In'short we have<br />
demonstrated our preparedness to take the hard decisionc in<br />
the interests not of short term popularity or narrow<br />
electoral gain but in the interests of the national economy<br />
and in the interests of building a society based on sound<br />
and sustainable economic growth.<br />
We are the Government for the long haul. There are no quick<br />
fixes and no short cuts.<br />
There is no room for voodoo economics or self-indulgent<br />
fantasies that we can somehow turn the clock back.<br />
I have said on many occasions in my Address to the Nation<br />
and since that I would'be prepared to lose office rather<br />
than go soft in economic decision-making. That commitment<br />
remains unaltered.<br />
A relaxation of our firm economic management would not just<br />
threaten today's Australians. It would not just risk the<br />
jobs of today's workers and threaten the livelihood of<br />
today's pensioners. It would place in question the security<br />
and prosperity of the generations of Australians who will<br />
inherit the nation from us.<br />
That is a risk I was not prepared to take.<br />
Having decided against an early election, let me make it<br />
clear that our commitment to a tough and responsible May<br />
Statement remains absolute.<br />
Some of those who were in favour of an early election put<br />
the argument to me in these terms: that a victory in an<br />
election now would have given us a renewed mandate to take<br />
the harsh economic decisions which are necessary. </p>
<p>That line of argument was forceful but it was not<br />
persuasive. This Government already has a mandate, given to<br />
us in unqualified terms by the Australian people in 1983 and<br />
renewed by them in 1984. That mandate still exists, and it<br />
will be the basis for our economic decision making<br />
throughout 1987. * Those economic decisions and the fruits<br />
they are bearing will in turn be the basis of our request to<br />
the Australian people to renew the mandate when we go to the<br />
polls towards the end of this year or early next year.<br />
Because the evidence is growing that our policies are<br />
starting to pay dividends. We expect inflation will fall.<br />
We expect interest rates will fall. We expect jobs will<br />
continue to grow.<br />
we will be able to go to the voters and say, we have not<br />
only overcome the greatest recession in 50 years the<br />
Fraser Government recession of the early 1980' s -we have<br />
also set in place the solution to the dramatic collapse in<br />
our terms of trade and the structural weaknesses in the<br />
Australian economy that have existed for three decades. we<br />
are conducting the most massive restructuring of the<br />
Australian economy ever undertaken, and by the time we go to<br />
the polls I am confident that the benefits of these policies<br />
will be evident to all.<br />
Economic reconstruction is not a notion plucked out of some<br />
economics textbook.<br />
It is the only solution to the challenge we face; it is the<br />
only genuine means of securing higher living standards and<br />
increased cmployment for all Australians.<br />
Let me expla" In this economic reconstruction in this way, by<br />
reading to you the list of Australia's top ten exports<br />
today. They are: coal, wheat, wool, iron ore and<br />
concentrates0 alumina, beef and veal, crude petroleum oils,<br />
refined petroleum products, aluminium, and gold.<br />
All of these exports are based on agriculture or mining.<br />
All but two of them are unprocessed primary products. Most<br />
of them are susceptible to the dramatic slumps in world<br />
prices which we have seen recently in the commodity markets.<br />
The simple fact is that Australia must break its heavy<br />
dependency on those products we can dig up or grow or shear<br />
off the sheep's back.<br />
Australia's great farms and mines will doubtless continue to<br />
be major export earners. But they must not be our sole<br />
export earners.<br />
We must make sure that manufactured goods and service goods<br />
and knowledge intensive industries play a much greater part<br />
in earning our national income, and providing jobs for our<br />
workers. And we must ensure that we find and exploit new<br />
overseas markets for these industries. </p>
<p>So this task of economic reconstruction lies before us as<br />
the first and principal task which my Government is pledged<br />
to fulfill not just in the lead-up to the next election<br />
but as the country enters the 1990s and beyond.<br />
There are three other elements to our Labor strategy which<br />
will guide Australia into the future.<br />
The first of these is this: we will continue to manage the<br />
economy with fairness and compassion. Where sacrifices and<br />
necessary, they willbe shared fairly; where gains are<br />
made, their benefits will be passed on, with fairness, to<br />
the whole community.<br />
The second element is this: we will continue to manage the<br />
economy, and manage the task of reconstruction, with<br />
stability and strength.<br />
We will continue to co-operate with the union movement and<br />
with business to ensure economic stability; we will<br />
continue to support Australia's established and relevant<br />
system of centralised wage fixing which the conservatives<br />
are pledged to demolish; we will continue to protect the<br />
mainstream of Australian society from the-wreckers of the<br />
New Right.<br />
The final element of our strategy for the 1990s is this: we<br />
will continue to ensure that today's policies not only<br />
achieve goals for today but are so geared as to protect the<br />
interests of future generations of Australians.<br />
That is why we must continue to protect our unique<br />
environmental heritage. That is why we must continue to<br />
seek the best educational and employment opportunities for<br />
our childzen. That is why we must continue to create a<br />
multicultural society in which all Australians have equality<br />
of opportunity. That is why we must continue to seek real<br />
peace and effective disarmbament without which all our hopes<br />
and plans can founder.<br />
These then are our aspirations: reconstruction of the<br />
economy, fairness in the protection of living standards,<br />
stability in Government, and care for the future of our<br />
nation. I draw the contrast with the opposition parties. They have<br />
not of late covered themselves with glory in the area of<br />
informing the Australian electorate abut their policies.<br />
But the reckless and reactionary nature of the policies they<br />
have revealed shows us at least this much: they not only<br />
cannot provide the answers to Australia's plight, they do<br />
not even understand the problem.<br />
So, sure, we would love to have been able to do more, and to<br />
achieve our goals more rapidly. </p>
<p>7<br />
But I'm proud of what we have in fact done, in the difficult<br />
circumstances imposed on us by the collapse in our export<br />
prices and the consequent fall in our national income.<br />
Moreover I'm totally certain that our record stands in the<br />
starkest possible contrast to the conservative forces, with<br />
their spurious promises and disunited leadership and<br />
single-minded determination to restore the privileges for<br />
the well-off few in place of the shared benefits we are<br />
delivering to the whole Australian community. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
