<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4222</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORAL TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/09/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004222.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS SEPTEMBER 5, 1976<br />
ELECTORAL TALK<br />
The Australian Government's economic strategy set out in<br />
our first budget will return this nation to growth and real<br />
prosperity. It will. mean that Australia's great promise for the future will<br />
be fulfilled. It will mean a better standard of living for all<br />
Australians. A key element in our economic strategy is our wages policy.<br />
Wages are an integral part of the functioning of the whole<br />
economy:-If the economy is to perform effectively and<br />
that includes full employment levels then wage rates cannot be<br />
allowed to get badly out of line with other relevant trends in<br />
the economy. They also cannot be allowed to get out of line with<br />
overseas trends.<br />
In Australia, wages have grown out of all proportion over the past<br />
few years. We have experienced a ' wage explosion'.<br />
In the three years to the end of 1975, wages grew by an amount<br />
equal to six years normal growth. Australia was out of step with<br />
the rest of the developed world.<br />
For instance, the average weekly earnings in the United States rose<br />
by 64 percent in the period 1968 to 1976. In the same period<br />
Australia's average weekly earnings jumped by 162 percent.<br />
In 1974 alone, hourly wage rates in manufacturing increased by<br />
percent in Australia. The average increase for 0. E. C. D.<br />
countries was only 15 percent.<br />
This unparalleled growth in wages in th~ is country was not accompanied<br />
by an equivalent increase in production and productivity.<br />
Rising wages led inevitably, to higher prices, inflation and the<br />
loss of jobs.<br />
Between December 1972 and September 1975 unemployment rose from<br />
83,000 to 237,600 almost a trebling of the number unemployed<br />
in less than three years.<br />
It also led to a situation where Australian industry started to<br />
price itself out of world markets. We lost the competitive edge.<br />
Our trading partners out-traded local industry. / 2 </p>
<p>Industry then began to seek Government. assistance. In 1973, the<br />
Department of Industry and-Commerce received applications for<br />
temporary protection from 13 industries. In 1974, this rose to 31<br />
and in the following year it leapt to 71 industries seeking protection.<br />
There is no doubt at all that the continuing level of recent wage<br />
increases would lead to even more calls and pleas for higher protection.<br />
This again would start the cycle of further inflation and loss of<br />
employment opportunities.<br />
It is for these and other reasons that the Government has taken a stand<br />
against full wage indexation.<br />
We have argued before the Arbitration Commission that full wage indexation<br />
locks. the economy into unacceptable levels of inflation. We have argued<br />
that this is therefore not consistent with economic recovery.<br />
Clearly, the consequence of full wage indexation is to prevent<br />
sustained economic recovery and a return to full employment levels.<br />
The Commission is beginning to accept the Government's argument.<br />
Increasingly, the Trade Union movement is beginning to accept that<br />
excessive wage increases are not only illusory but also damaging to<br />
the. economy and to the interest of workers.<br />
I am sure that the Government policies in this field have strong<br />
widespread. support among rank and file unionists.<br />
Unionists and some of their leaders understand clearly that rising<br />
wages threaten jobs. They remember the experience of the last three years.<br />
The view that the excessive growth in wages must be controlled is also<br />
recognised by some sections of the Australian Labor Party.<br />
The New South Wales Labor Government has recently advocated before the<br />
State Wage Fixing-Tribunal to the effect that it: should follow the<br />
decisions of the last two national wage decisions.<br />
Mr Wran's-willingness to associate himself with the concept of a<br />
12 month freeze on wages for the New South Wales shipbuilding industry<br />
workers is further evidence that he recognises the effect of wage<br />
movement on costs and prices.<br />
. The policies of this'Government are directed to improving the wellbeing<br />
" of the Australian worker.<br />
To do this we have to overcome inflation and restore confidence in<br />
Sthe Australian economy, so that production which is the only real<br />
source of income and job opportunities can grow and expand.<br />
Wages. have to be brought into line with other elements in the economy<br />
before the economy can again perform effectively.<br />
The sooner this happens the sooner the economy will be restored to high<br />
employment and rising production. Only then will Australia be in a<br />
position to afford sustainable increases in real wages.<br />
The same criteria apply also to reductions in working hours.<br />
If hours are reduced the effect will simply be to increase hourly wage<br />
rates which. in turn have the same inflationary effects on labour<br />
costs as straight wage increases.<br />
All Australians look forward to the time. when the economy can afford<br />
increases in real wages.<br />
Now is. not. the time to be seeking such . increases.<br />
Those who do so will only delay our return to growth and sound and<br />
stable national development. 0000000000000 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
