<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7135</transcript-id>
    <title>JOINT PRESS STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER AND THE MINISTER FOR SCIENCE, BARRY JONES </title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/03/1987</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007135.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Jj, AUSrQA* LIA-i<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA 10 Iarch 1987.<br />
JOINT PRESS STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER AND THE MINISTER FOR<br />
SCIENCE&gt; I BARRY JONES,<br />
The Government is delighted to announce a $ 750,000 five-year<br />
sponsorship by Shell Australia Limited for the travelling<br />
component of the National Science and Technology Centre.<br />
The Prime Hinister received a cheque for the firot instalment of<br />
the sponsorship from the Chairman and Chief Executive Officer of<br />
Shell Australia, Mr Kevan Gosper, in Canberra today.<br />
The sponsorship will be used to establish a permanent travelling<br />
science exhibition, to be known as the Shell Quoctacon Science<br />
Circus. A1 prototype of the travelling exhibition, sponsored by<br />
Shell, has already visited a number of State capitals and<br />
provincial centres.<br />
Shell is to be commended for its foresight in sponsoring the<br />
travelling exhibition, which will go on the road frorm January<br />
1988. Tho permanent National Scienco and Technology Centre in<br />
Canberra uill open during the second half of 1988.<br />
The Governomnt's central task over the last four years has been<br />
restructuring the Australian economy.<br />
This requires in part the development of knowledge-based<br />
industries, which will in turn require a greater proportion of<br />
Australian youth to undertake higher education, particularly in<br />
the science and technology fields.<br />
The National Science and Technology Centre must play a role in<br />
raising scientific literacy across all age groups in the<br />
community.<br />
We congratulate and thank Shell for its continued support of this<br />
important national projectø<br />
The Science Circus will give all Australians that opportunity by<br />
bringing science to them and demonstrating that science and<br />
technology are not esoteric subjects of interest only to<br />
white-coated people in laboratories. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
