<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1835</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS:  PM. NO 43/1968 BRITISH GIFT TO CANBERRA STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR JOHN GORTON</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/04/1968</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001835_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO iJO T FOR PUBCAT. Or-J BROADCAST~ r4G OR--<br />
CABL_ 1 G BEr_, FORE M. IDiNLGHT 23 APRIL<br />
FOR PRESS: BRITISH GIFT TO CANBERRA<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, Mvr John Gorton<br />
An Australian firm, Messrs Cameron, Chisholm and<br />
Nicol of Perth, has won the competition conducted by the British<br />
Government to select a design for a structure to house a carillon in<br />
Canberra's Lake Burley Griffin.<br />
The carillon and the structure to house it will be built<br />
on Aspen Island in the Central Basin of Lake Burley Griffin. The cost<br />
will be met from a gift of Fœ ( stg. ) 200, 000 made by the British Government<br />
in 1963 to mark the 50th anniversary of the foundation of Canberra.<br />
Six firms of architects, three British and three<br />
Australian, were invited to compete in a limited design competition.<br />
The British firms were Messrs Ahrens, Burton and Koralek of London;<br />
Messrs Eldred Evans and Denis Galley of London; and Messrs Robert<br />
Maguire and Keith Murray of Richmond, Surrey. The Australian firms<br />
were Messrs Cameron, Chisholm and Nicol of Perth; Messrs McKay<br />
and Cox of Sydney; and Messrs Ancher, Mortlock, Murray and Woolley<br />
of Sydney. Their designs were assessed by Lord Holford ( a past<br />
President of t-he Royal Institute of British Architects); Sir Donald<br />
Gibson ( Director-General of R.=-search and Development of the British<br />
Ministry of Public Buildings and Works and former President of<br />
R. I. B. A. and Sir John Overall ( Chairman of the National Capital<br />
Planning Committee, Canberra).<br />
The assessors, in commenting on their unanimous<br />
choice, stated<br />
" The winning entry is a design which is simple, ingenious and<br />
impressive. From the point of view of playing the carillon<br />
and hearing the bells from all sides, the design is convenient<br />
and practical The three triangular elements reflect the<br />
geometry cf the layout of Canberra, and as a monument<br />
possesses a timeless quality.<br />
The Government is naturally delighted that an Australian<br />
firm has won the competition. It is a happy omen that this British gift<br />
to our National Capital will be designed by Australians.<br />
The carillon and its structure will be a notable additioin<br />
to the National Capital and all the designs which were submitted to the<br />
assessors will be brought to Canberra where arrangements will be made<br />
for their display, after they have been on exhibition in Australia House.<br />
CANBERRA, 24 April, 1968 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
