<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>69</transcript-id>
    <title>AUSTRALIAN IMMIGRATION POLICY - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. R.G. MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/05/1959</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000069.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
AUSTRALIAN IMMl'IGRATION POLICY<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, Mr. R. G. Menzies<br />
As some question appears to have arisen here in respect of<br />
the Australian immigration policy, I think it desirable to say'<br />
one or two things in order to clarify the position.<br />
The Australian immigration policy has been steadily maintained<br />
for the last 58 years. It is our national desire to<br />
develop in Australia a homogeneous population in order that we<br />
may avert social difficulties which have arisen in many other<br />
countries. It i-s clearly the right of any nation to determine<br />
its own racial constitution. We have maintained our policy in<br />
respect of people who are actually citizens of other British<br />
Commonwealth countries. I say this so that it may not be<br />
thought that our policy has some specific reference to an<br />
American State or Territory.<br />
So far as I know most nations have policies which determine<br />
the intake of citizens from other countries. So far as Australia<br />
is concerned, I vant to make it quite clear that our policy, to<br />
which the overwhelming majority of Australians are deeply attached<br />
is not based upon any idea of racial superiority. WIe willingly<br />
recognise that citizens of othe-nations possess abilities and<br />
traditions which we sincerely respect and admire. dhen, therefore,<br />
a citizen of some Asian or Oriental country is refused permanent<br />
entry to the Australian community, it is not because we<br />
are assuming to ourselves some superior quality. That would be<br />
untrue, unjust and, ind~ eed, absurd.<br />
But we desire to organise the future of oir cuncountry in our<br />
own way. dJe have witnessed many examples of nations in which a<br />
mixture of races has givon rise to deep prejudices and almost insoluble<br />
social questions. It would appear that in the Hawaiian<br />
Islands various races have been able to live togTether in complete<br />
amity and with mutual advantage. But this is not true everywhere.<br />
The point I want to make is that our immigration policy was<br />
not devised as something with particular application to any one<br />
country. It is broadly devised, of long standing, and not discriminatory<br />
as between one country possessing non-European citizens<br />
and another. From time to time there have been su:, gestions<br />
made that we should introduce some quota system, My Government re<br />
-gards this as impracticable, as introducing possible new discriminations<br />
and as something whiich does not even begin to solve the<br />
problem of population movements, The whole essence of the matter<br />
is that -te desire to buildup our own population, partly by natural<br />
increase and partly by immigration in such a way as to produce<br />
assoon as possible an integrated population of a homogeneous kind.<br />
I should perhaps emphasise that, as was realised by the<br />
Asian Relations Conference at New Delhi in 10,47, it is the prerogative<br />
of every country to decide what shall be the composition<br />
of its population and what persons should be admitted to permanent<br />
citizenship. We receive and welcome many f,, sian visitors w.-hether they<br />
come for business or for travel. le have today approximately<br />
6,000 Asian students attending, our universities, technical colleges,<br />
schools and other educational institutions. It has been<br />
our experience that tL-hese students, in common with many other<br />
Asian visitors, have encountered no feeling of discrimination.<br />
e are in fact a friendly people, not given to making distinctions<br />
among people on grounds of race or religion. But we do not<br />
want to see created in our country minority problems or<br />
prejudices or occasional bitterness such as exist in somte countries<br />
where larg) e numuers of non-Europeans and Europeans live in<br />
separate conmiunities,<br />
HONOLULU. 9th May, 1959. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
