<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9567</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J.KEATING, MP VE DAY - AUSTRALIA REMEMBERS COMMEMORATIVE CEREMONY, AUSTRALIAN WAR MEMORIAL, CANBERRA, 8 MAY 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/05/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009567.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Th<br />
( I<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING, MP<br />
VE DAY AUSTRALIA REMEMBERS COMMEMORATIVE CEREMONY,<br />
AUSTRALIAN WAR MEMORIAL, CANBERRA, 8 MAY 1995<br />
It was my privilege to launch the Australia Remembers celebrations last year<br />
and I took the opportunity to say that I hoped all Australians would be<br />
touched in some way by the commemoration. The program today has<br />
certainly touched all of us, and no doubt similar events being staged across<br />
the country this year are having similar effects on millions of Australians<br />
including, I hope, millions of Australian children.<br />
Here, and wherever we commemorate the service and sacrifice of Australians<br />
in war, we at once pay tribute to generations past and remind ourselves that<br />
our duty is as they saw theirs to the next generation, to the future of<br />
Australia. Major General James and my colleague, Mr Sciacca, paid eloquent tribute to<br />
the contribution Australia's servicemen and women made in the European<br />
theatre during World War 11. More than nine and a half thousand Australians<br />
died there: young Australians, men and women with the best part of their<br />
lives still ahead of them.<br />
They went to Europe as their parents' generation had gone before them and,<br />
perhaps, under fewer illusions about the realities of war.<br />
We know why they went. We know because Australians decided long ago<br />
that they would not forget those who made the supreme sacrifice, and that<br />
they would pass on to future generations of Australians the message that<br />
sacrifice contains.<br />
We know because our parents and our teachers told us, because we<br />
attended ceremonies every 25 April.<br />
We learned that these men and women had a notion of duty they believed<br />
that so long as they wanted freedom and democracy, and loved Australia and<br />
believed in its future, they were obliged to defend them and even lay down<br />
their lives. </p>
<p>It is an example we must keep alive for our children.<br />
Our young men and women should know that Australians like themselves<br />
believed so deeply in their country they were prepared to die for it. That<br />
Australians like themselves crossed the world and joined forces with men and<br />
women from many other countries to defend freedom against tyranny.<br />
They should also know what we mean when we talk about courage and<br />
perseverance and the immeasurable value of sticking together in hardship<br />
and they will know it when they learn about these Australians.<br />
It is important that they know these events occurred, that they engulfed the<br />
whole world. They should know and we should remember today that vast<br />
numbers of Allied servicemen perished in the war; that millions from what was<br />
then the Soviet Union, millions of innocent civilians, millions in the<br />
concentration camps, perished. They should know about and we must<br />
remember the Holocaust.<br />
They should know that, as people thronged in city squares to rejoice in the<br />
victory, the horrors of Auschwitz were just being revealed. That as liberation<br />
was being celebrated in one half of Europe, totalitarian rule was being<br />
imposed in the other. And that on the battlefields and in the prison camps of<br />
Asia there were three more months to be endured.<br />
In knowing these things we hope that they will never forget that freedom and<br />
democracy are hard-won and must be defended. That peace is the greatest<br />
gift any generation can receive, and should never be taken for granted. They<br />
should know that these things are to be cherished.<br />
Yet it is no less important to see the message in the jubilation of fifty years<br />
ago. What we see in those images is humanity triumphant. We see men and<br />
women celebrating the victory of good over evil in the battle they have<br />
fought. It is their victory.<br />
Perhaps nothing makes the reasons for fighting the war so clear as their<br />
happiness. For many thousands of Australians VE Day meant beginning their lives again.<br />
It meant being reunited with their families. It meant going back to their farms<br />
and factories and offices and restarting their lives.<br />
Someone once said of the Americans of that time that they were an heroic<br />
generation they refused to be broken by the Great Depression, they fought<br />
the war and then they built a great country. Without a doubt, the same can<br />
be said about that generation of Australians. They went about re-building<br />
their lives with confidence and purpose and their efforts gave rise to a period<br />
of sustained national development. </p>
<p>Among the builders were many thousands who had endured the war in their<br />
own countries and left their shattered lives and devastated homes to start<br />
new lives in Australia.<br />
I do not think we should let this day pass without reminding ourselves of how<br />
much they have given Australia; how much we have gained by being open to<br />
the world, generous towards those who have come here to escape<br />
oppression and hardship, and tolerant of cultural differences.<br />
In building new lives here they enriched us all. That is one of the great<br />
lessons of the fifty years which have passed since the war ended, and one<br />
that we should not forget.<br />
Today we pay tribute to a generation whose faith was profound: not just<br />
among those who served in the armed forces, but those who kept up the fight<br />
at home and all those who carried the vigour with which they defended<br />
Australia in war into building Australia in peace. Through this ceremony and<br />
through all the commemorative events this year we hope to sustain their faith<br />
in our own lives.<br />
And I believe it does sustain us. This generation of Australians have<br />
engineered great changes in their country and its relationship with the region<br />
and the rest of the world.<br />
They have coped with change imposed upon them global change of<br />
unprecedented dimensions at unprecedented speed. They have adapted<br />
perhaps as no previous generation of Australians has had to. And they are<br />
building a country which is stronger, more confident of its place in the world,<br />
and more able to play a creative role for peace and democracy than ever<br />
before.<br />
To continue to do this is to continue to honour those whose lives we<br />
remember today.<br />
It is to say in ways which our children will understand why the war was fought.<br />
If we do that, in future we will be able to say that on the 50th anniversary of<br />
the end of World War II Australia truly remembered. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
