<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18088</transcript-id>
    <title>New council and ambassadors support Australia&#039;s diversity</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/08/2011</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
The Gillard Labor Government today launched a new local ambassadors program to champion inclusion and highlight the benefits of Australia's diversity.</p>
<p>The People of Australia Ambassadors program was formally announced by Prime Minister Julia Gillard today at the launch of the new independent Australian Multicultural Council.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister encouraged Australians to nominate local champions from their own neighbourhood and communities who have helped to promote inclusion and participation in their community.</p>
<p>Up to 40 people will be selected as ambassadors to provide grassroots advice to the Australian Multicultural Council (AMC) about effective initiatives which promote inclusion and leverage diversity in our communities.</p>
<p>The AMC will provide advice to Government on multicultural policy and emerging issues and ensure Australian Government services respond effectively to the needs of Australia's diverse communities.</p>
<p>The Council was appointed as part of the Government's new multicultural policy, The People of Australia, released in February this year.</p>
<p>The former advisory council recommended the new independent body be set up to advise and consult the Government on multicultural issues and inform national policy.</p>
<p>The 10 member Council will have a formal role in a strengthened access and equity strategy, play a research advisory role for public policy, and lead cultural diversity celebrations and Harmony Day activities.</p>
<p>The launch of the new AMC demonstrates the Gillard Labor Government's commitment to policy and programs that build on the strength of Australia's cultural diversity.</p>
<p>The new Council will provide a strong voice on multicultural issues and contribute constructively to the broader deliberations of Government.</p>
<p>Information in relation to the AMC and the People of Australia Ambassadors program can be found at <a href="http://www.amc.gov.au">www.amc.gov.au</a></p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
