<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3274</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR EG WHITLAM QC MP - 19 MAY 1974</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/05/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003274.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
19 May 1974<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. E. G. WHITLAM, M. P.<br />
The electors of Australia have voted to support their Government.<br />
Their voice has been partly muffled by the peculiarities of the<br />
electoral system. In New South Wales, Victoria, Queensland and<br />
South Australia there are some electorates with an enrolment of<br />
only 50,000 aqd others with an enrolment of 80,000 or even more.<br />
Nevertheless, some clear facts emerge.<br />
The 12f Labor candidates won as many votes as the other 374<br />
candidates combined.<br />
The Government secured a higher percentage of votes on 18 May<br />
1974 than on 2 December 1972. The combined Liberal, Country Party<br />
and D. L. P. vote was lower than in 1972.<br />
The majority in favour of the Australian Labor Party over the<br />
coalition parties is far higher than that recorded in 1972.<br />
Swings to the Government have been recorded in all the areas<br />
of greatest concentration of population.<br />
In other words, the mandate of 1972 has been renewed in so<br />
far as the electoral system allows an accurate expression of the<br />
people's will.<br />
If Australia is to have an effective and stable parliamentary<br />
democracy, then electorates must urgently be distributed to give a<br />
more accurate reflection of the wishes of the people.<br />
It is important that it should be realised at home and abroad<br />
that whatever the position of the Government in the House of<br />
Representatives in terms of seats may be, its position in the<br />
nation is one of strong and continuing support.<br />
CANBERRA, A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
