<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4205</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA AT HARVARD UNIVERSITY - 30 JULY 1976</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/07/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004205.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
-fTinA I<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA<br />
AT HARVARD UNIVERSITY 30 JULY 1976<br />
Mr President, Mr Mayor, ladies and gentlemen,<br />
thank you very much for your hospitality today. My wife<br />
and I have had a wonderful time in the last few days in<br />
the United States. We have been kept a little bit too<br />
busy I think perhaps, but that may be our fault more than<br />
the fault of other people. I would also like to pay<br />
tribute to Professor Manning Clark who conducted a number<br />
of the initial discussions with the University concerning<br />
today's occasion, in the formative stages, and Professor<br />
Derham who at the last moment and I know quite well at<br />
some inconvenience to himself and his wife, came here to<br />
be present at this occasion as Chairman of the Friends of<br />
Harvard Committee which will be associuted with the Chair.<br />
The Bicentennial of the American Nation provides<br />
a fitting occasion for the endowment of a Chair in<br />
Australian studies at this University.<br />
For Australia was the un-intended offspring<br />
of your War of Independence. And I have been advised<br />
a] lready this morning that in the Treasure Room of the<br />
Harvard Law School library there is a copy of an American<br />
edition of The Trial of Thomas Muir for sedition, for<br />
circulating Thomas Paine's " Rights of Man" in the wrong<br />
places. And so he was sentenced to be transported for<br />
14 years and sent to Botany Bay, as many other good people<br />
were sent with him. He was later rescued by an American<br />
ship, and after many adventures he died in France at a<br />
later period. So, an unintended offspring of the American<br />
Revolution returns to celebrate your Bicentenary.<br />
But theo coiinections between the history of<br />
our two countries extend far beyond our origins. They<br />
encompass the political and social ideals that have guided<br />
the development of both our societies. s. 9 / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
The ideals inspiring your Founding Fathers<br />
had a direct impact on the development of democratic<br />
government in Australia. Your great revolution was<br />
one of the pow~ erful forces that 75 years later helped<br />
the Australian Colonies ' to become self gcverning and<br />
to manage their own affairs within a highly democratic<br />
political framework. Your revol-ution occurred in an age of<br />
intellectual ferment when men such as Locke and later<br />
Montesquieu, Rousseau and Humne were seeking to apply<br />
logic and reason to understanding man and his institutions.<br />
Harvard is amongst the foremost of the institutions<br />
embodying this tradition of logical enquiry.<br />
It is a tradition, of course, in which Australians<br />
have shared, and to which we have made our own contribution.<br />
What we need now, more than ever, is<br />
knowledge that is of positive value to man in increasing<br />
his understanding of the world, of himself. Our education<br />
needs to impart not only technical skills, it needs to<br />
impart a quality of judgement. The great challenge to<br />
educators is to combine the teaching of skills with that<br />
broader understanding. The view that the best education<br />
need not be relevant, even on a broad definition of<br />
relevance, condemns us to failure in our efforts to. cope<br />
with a fast changing world.<br />
Mr President, this Chair should certainly help<br />
to extend further understanding between Australia and<br />
the United States.<br />
I hope also that the work which will be d~ ne<br />
through this Chair will address itself, in part, to-some<br />
of the major issues that must concern people in both our<br />
countries. Mr President, I would like to take the<br />
opportunity offered by the endowment of the Chair to speak<br />
a little about challenges which I believe both our<br />
countries face and about the contribution I hope the<br />
academic world can make to meeting them.<br />
Modern science has given mankind great power<br />
and great strength. But it is evident that our knowledge<br />
and our human skills in using that power have not increased<br />
commensurately. In this world political leaders are being asked<br />
to resolve the problems of societies undergoing rapid<br />
change. New and insistent demands are made upon them. a * s/ </p>
<p>-3<br />
Old issues -issues with which your Founding<br />
Fathers were familiar -are now facing us again. Once<br />
more we are concerned with the relationship of our<br />
people to their institutions. We are once again debating<br />
how to reconcile effective government with the liberty<br />
( or as it is frequently now put) the autonomy of the<br />
individual. I would li. e to elaborate on one or two of the<br />
issues related to these matters. While they particularly<br />
concern the politician, universities will fail in their<br />
role if they do not make an important contribution to<br />
dealing with them. The issue I want to mention quite<br />
directly is related to the role of universities.<br />
Our education process has been designed to<br />
encourage people to think for themselves, to question,<br />
to search, to reuch their own conclusions.<br />
It is not at all surprising that our people,<br />
as never before are questioning their leaders and their<br />
institutions. In these circumstances we need to ask ourselves,<br />
as we never have before, how we maintain the cohesion,<br />
the unity, the vitality, of democratic societies and the<br />
effectiveness of democratic government.<br />
We preach independence and diversity, but there<br />
is also an essential unity without which any society<br />
will fall. At the time of your revolution and in the two<br />
centuries since, the problem of achieving unity out of<br />
diversity was largely the problem of welding of different<br />
states, regions, ethnic groups, into one nation. These<br />
same issues have concerned us, though less forcefully, in<br />
Australia. Today the problem has a new dimension. We are<br />
not talking merely about regions and communities. We<br />
are talking about individuals' demands for respect for<br />
their own views, their own consciences, against the larger<br />
society and its institutions. We are now talking about<br />
cultures, attitudes and ideas, which are becoming increasingly<br />
diverse. Government, to be effective, must earn the<br />
respect of the people. In the age I have been describing<br />
this respect is more difficult to earn than in the past.<br />
How to achieve it is one of the most important issues of<br />
our time. s e/ 4 </p>
<p>-4<br />
That takes me to the second issue that I<br />
would like to mention.<br />
In order that people may have the maximum<br />
scope to decide for themselves the kind of lives they<br />
will lead, they must be prepared to accept certain<br />
restraints. It is true'that people's ultimate obligations<br />
are to their own consciences. But that does not mean<br />
that one is entitled to ignore laws with which one merely<br />
does not agree. Such an attitude destroys the effectiveness<br />
of our institutions and the possibility of effective social<br />
reform. Laws after all flow from institutions which though<br />
admittedly imperfect are the best form of government yet<br />
devised. Without the acceptance of such obligations<br />
people may become frustrated and disillusioned with<br />
the democratic processes and institutions, and their<br />
frustrations could ulitimately feed the ambitions of those<br />
who seek undemocratic solutions to our problems.<br />
That is why the practice of freedom and the<br />
acknowledgement of social and political obligations go<br />
hand in hand. There needs to be a recognition that some<br />
freedom must be forgone to expand our capacity to enjoy<br />
freedom. And here we come to a striking paradox. Not<br />
only is this an age when people are demanding greater<br />
personal freedom, it is also an age when the demands on<br />
government constantly increase. In order to meet these<br />
demands governments almost invevitably tend to dispose<br />
of more of a iuation's resources and to further regulate<br />
people's affairs. In Australia there has been for decades an<br />
inexorable move of financial power to the Central Government,<br />
destroying the independent capacities of State Governments<br />
and making the States subservient to the centre.<br />
My Government has begun to implement a major<br />
reform of our federal arrangements designed to restore<br />
a large measure of financial independence to the States<br />
and to expand the financial base of local Governments<br />
so that they can respond effectively to problems they<br />
recognise in their own communities.<br />
The capacity of Government to assess problems<br />
accurately and to take into account people's judgement<br />
of their own needs is essential to effective social reform.<br />
More than ever such sensitivity is required to foster respect<br />
for our institutions. We are all aware that some approaches<br />
to social reform do more harm than good. Effective government<br />
0 </p>
<p>action requires a deep awareness of how that action will<br />
be seen and evaluated by our increasingly active and<br />
informed citizens. So often people have sought to solve social<br />
problems merely by spending money, so often that is<br />
only a small part of what is needed. Many problems<br />
are related m~ uch more to the capacity of people to<br />
adapt to a complex'society. A solution that relies<br />
on providing funds but does little to encourage the<br />
capacity to cope with problems can be a * most damaging<br />
response to genuine need.<br />
Our institutions can only maintain respect<br />
if people can achieve their legitimate aspirations<br />
within them in a democratic and peaceful way; if reason<br />
and argument can lead to effective reform.<br />
We have to make sure that our institutions<br />
are as responsive as possible to the needs of those they<br />
affect. Preventing these institutions from becoming<br />
over-powerfull requires not only legal and constitutional<br />
restraints but also a recognition on their part that they<br />
have broader obligations to the wider community.<br />
The contribution of the universities on this<br />
continuing issue will have an important effect on the<br />
response of other organisations of many different kinds.<br />
And that brings me finally to the challenge to<br />
democratic leadership in the kind of world our universities<br />
are helping to create.<br />
Despite the problems I have been discussing<br />
it is obvious that democratic political institutions<br />
have exhibited a remarkable capacity to adapt to change.<br />
Ultimately however institutions depend for their survival<br />
and respect on the quality of men who hold office within<br />
them. The more rapid social change is, the more complex<br />
issues become, the more essential it is for democratic<br />
politicians to explain the problems they face clearly and<br />
realistically. They in their turn need the tools for this<br />
task. They need the knowledge bnd understanding that<br />
it is in part a responsibility of universities to generate.<br />
9 e e/ 6 </p>
<p>-6<br />
I have commented on the unparalleled burst<br />
of knowledge in the Physical Sciences and the unmatched<br />
power that they have placed in the hands of politicians.<br />
It seems man can do almost anything so long as it involves<br />
technology. But it is in our understanding of society<br />
that we are now desperately in need of new knowledge.<br />
Scientific knowledge has placed unaparalled<br />
power in politician lhands. Our capacity to see that it<br />
is used for good is scarcely better than it would have'<br />
been if man had possessed that power two thousand years<br />
ago. Our criteria for judgement are still so often<br />
inappropriate to the circumstances. What does this say<br />
of the way in which we have pursued learning and<br />
understanding? What we need more than anything is an<br />
adequate recognition of ourselves.<br />
To understand and respond to present and future<br />
challenges is a major task of politicians. The paradoxes<br />
of our time are great. The possibilities of our time<br />
are unlimited for advancing mankind through the use of<br />
our resources in humarn and realistic ways.<br />
We need to establish an environment in which<br />
respect for institutions and theyvay they operate, for<br />
the manner in which politicians go about their business,<br />
leads to moderation and reason in public debate, where<br />
violence and the extreme view are rejected, where rational<br />
argument can predominate. We need to have it understood<br />
that extreme ways of pursuing objectives degrude the<br />
spirit of our democratic institutions. We need it understood<br />
that progress and reform can be achieved through moderation,<br />
that democracy is strong when people deal rationally with<br />
each other, with compassion, and without hatred.<br />
Universities do not exist in isolation from the<br />
larger society. The values they teach or assume, the<br />
knowledge they produce ' will profoundly affect the future,<br />
and the way in which politicians, too, will be able to<br />
carry out their task.<br />
If the Chair endowed today can contribute<br />
something to this broader purpose Australia all<br />
Australians will be well satisfied indeed.<br />
It gives me great pleasure, Mr President, to<br />
present the endowment for this Chair. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
