<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6455</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, CONFEDERATION OF AUSTRALIAN INDUSTRY, SYDNEY, 30 AUGUST 1984</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/08/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006455.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHIECK AGAINST DELIVERY U I, 1_ EMBARGOED UNTIL 10 P. M.<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
CONFEDERATION OF AUSTRALIAN INDUSTRY<br />
SYDNEY 30 AUGUST 1984<br />
Ladies and gentlemen<br />
I very much appreciate this opportunity to address<br />
tonight..<br />
Your Forum's theme " Business Competitiveness The<br />
of Recovery" is both timely and apt. you Challenge<br />
In this context it is appropriate to focus on the<br />
Government's macro-economic policies and performance, and on<br />
more specific policies that affect industry.<br />
On both fronts I believe we have already made considerable<br />
progress. Every indication suggests that the recovery is now well<br />
underway. Our policies give every reason for confidence<br />
that we can consolidate it and secure it for the medium and<br />
longer-term.<br />
This is the Labor Government's highest priority.<br />
It is an integral part of the program launched in March 1983<br />
to secure sustained non-inflationary growth, to bring<br />
Australians toge-ther and t5 build a more equitable<br />
Australia. The record to date has been an impr~ ssive one:<br />
In the year between the June quarters of 1983 and 1984<br />
economic growth was over 10 per cent, making ours the<br />
fastest growing economy in the Western world, with the<br />
fastest recorded growth in the 2-5 years3 since quarterly<br />
national accounts have been compiled. r </p>
<p>2.<br />
This has been accompanied by strong growth in employment<br />
with some 230,000 Australians finding new jobs. This<br />
pattern will be sustained during tYe coming year. With<br />
employment forecast to expand by 22 per cent through the<br />
year, we shall by. next June have seen 400,000 new jobs<br />
created since the Summit comfortably within reach of our<br />
election promise to create half a million new jobs over<br />
three years.<br />
The rapid turnaround in economic activity has also been<br />
accompanied by a marked reduction in inflation. Contrary to<br />
the school of economic thought that dominiated Australian<br />
policy thinking before the Labor Government took office, we<br />
are succeeding in fighting unemployment and inflation at the<br />
same time.<br />
This achievement has been made possible by the historically<br />
unique Prices and Incomes Accord struck between the<br />
Australian Labor Party and the With the Accord in<br />
place, we have an agreed basis for wage and price restraint<br />
in a sustained economic recovery.<br />
The progress of the past year will be continu the year<br />
ahead. Non-farm GDP is forecast to rise by 5 per cent this<br />
year a second year of extremely strong expansion by the<br />
standards of the past decade, and in line with our long-term<br />
requirements. Consumer prices are also expected to rise by only 5 per cent<br />
through the current financial year, without any 1Medicare<br />
effect. This is down to the expected average of OECD<br />
countries after being twic tthe OECD average when we took<br />
office. Reflecting these improvements in growth performance and<br />
inflation, real unit labour costs have fallen dramatically<br />
and the profit share is now higher than at any time for a<br />
decade. Interest rates have also fallen appreciably. During the<br />
past year they have-dropped a percentage point for most home<br />
loans and more for other lending activities. The bond<br />
tender announced on Budget night and closing earlier this<br />
week generated interest rates a percentage point below those<br />
of the last tender, and two and a half Dercentage points<br />
below those of a year ago. Lower interest rates contribute<br />
to lower costs directly, and also indirectly through their<br />
effect on the exchange rate.<br />
It is not at all surprising, in these circumstances of<br />
continued strong growth, restraint in wages and prices, very<br />
strong productivity growth, declinnc interest rates, and<br />
real unit labour costs back to the levels of the late<br />
1960' s, that surveys of business intentions are now<br />
suggesting that business investment will return to growth<br />
year on year in 1984-85. </p>
<p>3.<br />
The immediate outlook then is for a strono, balanced and<br />
sustainable level of domestic economic activity. This is a<br />
basic precondition for resurgence in the business sector.<br />
But what of the prospects for the medium and longer-term?<br />
Here the key is to be found in the theme of this Forum in<br />
greatly strengthened and continually strengthening business<br />
competitiveness. There are many dimensions to the enhancement of our<br />
competitiveness. Fundamental to the achievement of such an outcome is the<br />
maintenance of the stable macro-economic environment that we<br />
have established over the past year. By sustaining the<br />
benefits resulting from lower real unit labour costs,<br />
falling interest rates and a market-related exchange rate,<br />
we contribute directly to the competitiveness of Australian<br />
business. We know that the maintenance of a favourable macro-economic<br />
outlook will require restraint in the growth of Government<br />
outlays. We expect to continue to reduce the budget deficit<br />
in the course of economic growth and revival of private<br />
investment over the next few years. This is consistent with<br />
the Government's continued focus on the economic outlook for<br />
Australia in the medium to long-term, and with statements<br />
made by the Treasurer and myself around the time of last<br />
year's Budget.<br />
The Government believes that continued reduction of the<br />
deficit on the pattern of this year's budget is consistent<br />
with continued implementation of reforms and new programs,<br />
which strengthen the Australian economy and society, and<br />
improve our provision for Australians in need.<br />
It is consistent with this continued program of reform,<br />
because we are prepared to contain and reduce expenditure in<br />
areas which do not have the-highest priority for the<br />
Government. In this context, the real growth in outlays of 6.1 per cent<br />
in this year's Budget represents much more substantial<br />
overall restraint than is immediately apparent.<br />
If we exclude the once-for-all increases associated with the<br />
Medicare reforms, this year's real growth in outlays is<br />
about 4 per cent compared with 6.7 per cent in 1983-84 and<br />
6.3 per cent in 1982-83.<br />
This 4 per cent itself is inflated by two considerations<br />
which are important this year, but which will be much less<br />
significant in future. </p>
<p>The drastic reductions in expectations about inflation as<br />
measured by the GDP deflator, Of about two and a half<br />
percentage points between February this year when the<br />
forward estimates were prepared and the completion of work<br />
on the Budget, meant that a number of commitments entered in<br />
money terms early in the year were larger than would be<br />
necessary in more normal circumstances. Similarly, debt<br />
servicing commitments are set in the short: term in nominal<br />
terms, and thus real terms equivalEnts are raised for a<br />
while by sudden and large reductions in inflation.<br />
Further, the strong growth in outlays through 1982-83 and<br />
1983-84 would have carried through into significant growth<br />
in real outlays in 1984-85, even if there were no growth in<br />
expenditures from the level of June 1984.<br />
Thus it will be clear that a very substantial degree of<br />
expenditure restraint is reflected in this year's<br />
appropriations. Following the experience of two Budgets, I am firmly of the<br />
view that wie must review our traditional procedures of<br />
Budget formation with a view to utilising fully the<br />
opportunities for financing any new programs while<br />
continuing substantially to reduce the Budget deficit.<br />
When Budget decisions are taken on the eve of or even after<br />
the commencement of a new financial year, a Government's<br />
options for securing major savings without disruption and<br />
waste are severely truncated. In future Budgets, we Must<br />
seek to extend the lead times both in preparation of the<br />
expenditure side of the Budget, and in implementing<br />
expenditure decisions.<br />
As regards the size of future deficits it should also be<br />
recognised that it is possible to make substantial<br />
reductions by holding the growth in Governmnent expenditure<br />
below the growth trend of the economy in the years ahead.<br />
At the same time it is widely recognised including by the<br />
Government that reform is necessary to promote the equity<br />
and efficiency of the taxab-ion system. The Government will<br />
be receptive to the views which emerge from community<br />
discussion of these-issues.<br />
But let me put one issue to rest. Vie do not believe that<br />
taxation reform will be to Australia's advantage if it<br />
involves overall increases in taxation as distinct from<br />
greater efficiency aind equity in the system. The Labor<br />
Government does not believe that higher overall levels of<br />
taxation are necessary for substantial reductions in the<br />
deficit, for improved equity, or for enhanced efficiency of<br />
our economic system. </p>
<p>The changes announced in the Budget reflect this assumption<br />
and will, I believe, be helpful to the maintenance of<br />
business competitiveness: the extension of the time allowed<br />
for installation of equipment qualifying for the investment<br />
allowance; the opportunities for company groups to<br />
consolidate their accounts for taxation purposes; the faster<br />
depreciation of income-earning non-residential buildings;<br />
and the capacity-to write off expenditure on mineral<br />
exploration against income from any source.<br />
The Government knows that there are still weaknesses in the<br />
old Australian corporate income tax arrangements. We are<br />
aware of some business views that even faster depreciation<br />
than under the arrangements introduced in 1982 would be<br />
conducive to high levels of investment and economic growth.<br />
But the Government is also aware of the budgetary costs of<br />
further mneasures along these lines. We believe that further<br />
community analysis and discussion is required before we are<br />
in a position finally to settle our view on appropriate<br />
long-term corporate income taxation arrangements to support<br />
high levels of sustained growth.<br />
Sound macro-economic policies are fundamental to improved<br />
Australian competitiveness and sustained growth but they<br />
must be supplemented in other ways.<br />
Ultimately our success will also depend on the employment of<br />
our human and natural resources in their most productive<br />
uses; on our application of the best technology, sometimes<br />
by developing new technology ourselves, and sometimes by<br />
absorbing it from abroad; on high levels of investment from<br />
home and abroad; on our making effective use of<br />
opportunities for profitable international trade, especially<br />
in our Western Pacific region where economies are expanding<br />
more rapidly than any in the world; and above all by working<br />
together Commonweath and State Governments, unions, and<br />
business to find solutions to the problems which<br />
inevitably arise in the pursuit of growth.<br />
In building a more dynamic, outward-looking and competitive<br />
industrial base, we are particularly fortunate in<br />
Australia's geographic location in the most dynamic region<br />
of the world economy. This proximinity makes it much easier<br />
to establish an appropiate trading role for ourselves, based<br />
on our resource endowments and competitive advantages.<br />
The success we are having in developing the China Iron and<br />
Steel Initiative is a case in point. In spite of<br />
considerable public scepticism at the time 3f the<br />
announcement, and prounccments that it would cone to<br />
nothing, runs are already on boird and many more are in<br />
prospect. Already this year w.-e have secured an agreement on<br />
economic and technical co-operation in this field. </p>
<p>6.<br />
We have also secured a number of most useful contracts for<br />
the delivery to China of Australian iron ore, manganese and<br />
steel products. And all this, as 1 say, is just the<br />
beginning. What is already a valuable trade, is going to<br />
become vastly more important.<br />
My regional trade initiative has also produced valuable<br />
results. The round of consultations it has engendered on<br />
issues likely to be involved in any new round of<br />
multilateral trade negotiations, has been greatly<br />
appreciated by all countries concerned.<br />
For Australia, access to world markets is not a luxury to be<br />
pursued as an afterthought to domestic economic policy. We<br />
need such access if our industries are to offset the<br />
disadvantages of small local markets.<br />
I should. like to think such a proposition was simply stating<br />
the obvious. Historically, however, the approaches adopted<br />
to industry development in Australia would seem to suggest<br />
otherwise. Preoccupied with the notion and accepting the<br />
limitations of the small Australian market, most Australian<br />
Governments have, at the behest of both industry and labour,<br />
moved to create conditions of self-sufficiency in the local<br />
market place. They have sought to shield those within it<br />
from external competitive pressures.<br />
The protective measures they adopted wrought large costs in<br />
our society in terms of higher prices, severe misallocation<br />
of resources, and a loss of dynamism and potential for<br />
growth. Importantly they also deflected attention from the<br />
possibilities emerging in the world around us, and reduced<br />
what capacity we may have had to pursue such possibilites.<br />
The preconditions for the emergence of truly competitive<br />
Australian industries were being stifled.<br />
The Labor Government has sought to redress this situation.<br />
Already we have shifted the-terms of the debate away from an<br />
unproductive emphasis on the free trade vs. protection<br />
issue, and instead focussed attention where it belongs<br />
namely on the conditions of competitiveness of Australian<br />
industry. The best means of coming to terms with competition is to<br />
improve Australian industry's own competitiveness by<br />
restructuring and investing and retraining to reduce costs.<br />
Import replacement, like export expansion, is a thoroughly<br />
good thing if it is the result of improved competitiviness.<br />
But import replacement which requires increased protection<br />
because it is not supoorted by improved co petitiviness,<br />
imposes costs on other industries and the , ihole economy,<br />
slows growth, and costs us jobs that we desperately need. </p>
<p>7.<br />
Iam an optimist about our capacity to lower costs, replace<br />
imports and expand exports in a wide range of industries,<br />
including manufacturing, through improved competitiveness<br />
and without increased protection.<br />
I am heartened, for example, by the strong, positive<br />
response of workers and business to the Steel Industry Plan.<br />
The Plan involved a major liberalisation of trade with the<br />
removal of a range of temporary import quotas imposed by the<br />
Fraser Government.<br />
Through co-operation between Commonwealth and State<br />
Governments, unions and business in this sector we have been<br />
able greatly to lower costs, strengthen competitiveness, and<br />
improve the position in domestic markets, alongside the<br />
reductions in protection.<br />
Jobs and. investments in the steel industry are infinitely<br />
more secure now than they were when we came to office. The<br />
industry is moving towards a position in which it can<br />
realistically look to expansion through exports. And the<br />
steel-using industries of Australia, which themselves<br />
provide so many jobs, have been provided with relatively<br />
lower cost steel, arid with better service -in a more<br />
competitive environment.<br />
The approach the Government took to restructuring of the<br />
Australian steel industry was one manifestation of a growing<br />
recognition that the achievement Of a competitive Australian<br />
industry base is going to require a recognition by all<br />
concerned of the need for quite thorough-going structural<br />
adjustment in many parts of Australian induistry.<br />
Industry needs to be more outward looking, actively<br />
seeking out new products and markets;<br />
Industry needs to be more willing to adopt new, more<br />
efficient means of production, often characterised by<br />
new technology;<br />
Industry also n~ eds to be aware of opportunities<br />
provided by our indigenous research and development, and<br />
by the use of better trained and skilled workforce.<br />
These desirable features are relatively easy to describe;<br />
what is more difficult is to put in place policies which<br />
will bring them about.<br />
1, for one, certainly do not subscribe to the view that<br />
increased Government involvement in the running of all<br />
aspects of the economy will necessarily lead to a better<br />
run, miore dynamic industry; nor do I beliec that the<br />
provision of additicna' sssista~ ice is nec~ ssarily the<br />
answer. But neither is an unfettered free imarket approach<br />
likely in today's complex world to provide effective,<br />
equitable solutions to all problems. </p>
<p>8.<br />
In an economy such as Australia's, the best solution will be<br />
a mix of Government involvement and the forces of<br />
competition. Government's concern should be with the<br />
broader community and social consequences of change, while<br />
the forces of competition should provide the signals to<br />
which industry, in the free play of the market place, will<br />
adapt. The Labor Government has made very clear its view that<br />
changes in this area, while desirable and inevitable, should<br />
be gradual. As a community we need to cushion the impact on<br />
those who will be adversely affected by change.<br />
But it is not as if wie are now faced with an entirely novel<br />
situation. In the post-war period Australian industry has<br />
undergone a massive transformation.<br />
With this experience behind us, and an economic recovery<br />
which is now providing additional job opportunities for<br />
Australians, we can be more confident of our ability to<br />
address the structural changes required to make our economy<br />
more open and more competitive.<br />
The Australian Labor Government has advocat~ ed an approach to<br />
industry policy based on consultation and discussion with<br />
those involved in a particular industry. Vie have formalised<br />
this process by establishing industry councils under the<br />
aegis of the Australian Manufacturing Council.<br />
This enables all parties to share information about a<br />
particular industry, including its prospects and the<br />
problems it faces. It also enables the marshalling of<br />
support for any structural changes deemed necessary.<br />
Policy decisions taken in such circumstances should be<br />
well-informed of the circumstances facing a particular<br />
industry. An approach of this kind is in no way arbitary;<br />
nor does it carry any risk of alien solutions being<br />
superimposed from-above. It is also an approach likely to<br />
produce soundly-based rather than lowest common denominator<br />
responses to an ind~ stry's contemporary needs.<br />
This approach has been reinforced through the establishment<br />
of more general consultative mechanisms such as EPAC. In<br />
that forum, information on economic ' policy and longer term<br />
industry trends can be exchanged. Such information is<br />
important, contributing as it does to decisions by<br />
employers, employees and Government that will draw on a<br />
common understanding of the future and of the likely<br />
implications of alternative approaches.<br />
I have already referred to the Steel Indusitry Plan. The<br />
Government's motor vehicle policy is aniothe7 good example of<br />
our approach. </p>
<p>9 J<br />
. C o<br />
9o<br />
For decades the motor vehicle industry was plagued by<br />
Government reactions to short-term crises. In spite of<br />
rising levels of protection that industry's performance<br />
continued to deteriorate. This was costly not only to the<br />
consumer, but also to the industry since continually<br />
changing Government policies did not promote an environment<br />
for appropriate planning and investment.<br />
It was against this background that the Labor Government<br />
established a Car Industry Council comprising<br />
representatives from the various sectors of the industry.<br />
The work of the council and its report provided the<br />
Government much needed information about the nature and<br />
extent of the ills affecting the industry.<br />
Almost as importantly, it also provided a forum for<br />
discussion between participants from industry, unions and<br />
Government. I believe that this laid the foundation for a<br />
greater understanding of the industry's problems than had<br />
hitherto been achieved.<br />
As a result of this process of consultation the Government<br />
was able to introduce an industry plan which will promote<br />
the development of a more efficient car industry with<br />
long-term job security as a consequence.<br />
The industry has been given a period of time to adjust to<br />
phased reductions in the level of protection currently<br />
provided. Incentives to develop export markets and for<br />
research and design activity have also been provided.<br />
At the same time, the Government has designated the motor<br />
vehicle industry for the purposes of the labour adjustment<br />
training arrangements scheme. This will provide re-training<br />
assistance for retrenched workers.<br />
Although it is too early to claim success for the plan,<br />
there have already been some early indications that the plan<br />
has provided the requisite Onvironment for investment in the<br />
industry.<br />
Ford has indicated that it will spend more than $ 4B million<br />
to install an aluminium casting machinery centre in Geelong.<br />
Toyota has announced its intention to invest some $ 250<br />
million over the next five years. The announcement by GMH<br />
to re-badge the Nissan Pulsar is also encouraging and<br />
represents a movement towards the called-for reduction in<br />
the number of models.<br />
While it is a practical, and indeed the only sensible way of<br />
proceeding, to deal with structural chanqe on an<br />
industry-by-industry ba is, it remains ! eq itinmate to<br />
consider where wee rree hhedrei nq ih th emphasis w place on<br />
ensuring the conditions of Australian competitiveness. </p>
<p>There are indeed views put to the Government from time to<br />
time about what would be a desirable pattern for the future<br />
growith of Australian industry. But we as a Government are<br />
not in the business of " picking winners". Our concern is<br />
rather with seeking improvements in Australia's long-term<br />
economic growth performance through improved competitiveness<br />
and greater use of opportunities for international trade.<br />
There can be no Jfoubt that Australia should be seeking to<br />
reap the benefits of specialisation in those areas wherein<br />
we have a marked comparative advantage.<br />
Alongside expansion of industries based on our natural<br />
resources, we should be prepared to take advantage of the<br />
opportunities provided by our trading partners as they<br />
gradually upgrade their import needs towards more<br />
skill-intensive products and services<br />
Our. industry must adopt an aggresive, competitive stance<br />
to capture these new markets as they dEvelop.<br />
Trade in services should be of particular interest<br />
although we have scarcely yet begun to scratch the surface<br />
of the possibilities.<br />
The Government is particularly mindful that the pursuit of<br />
such possibilities indeed the whole proccss of structural<br />
change will have consequences for the distribution of<br />
incomes. This makes especially important the adoption of fair<br />
taxation and social security arrangements, and strong growth<br />
in employment.<br />
Above all, as recognised clearly by the Labor Government,<br />
there is a continuing need for labour market programs both<br />
to provide additional Job opportunities for those who are<br />
disadvantaged, and to ensure that Australiani workers are<br />
equipped with the experience and skills to mnatch the new<br />
opportunities. Total expenditure ohi labour market and related employment<br />
and training programs will be $ 1.1 billion this year, double<br />
the provision for 1982-83. We also have the Kirby Committee<br />
currently reviewing the whole gamut of Gove: nment training<br />
programs and, side by side with this, hove recently<br />
announced a long-term funding program involving substantial<br />
increases in Commonwealth assistance for schools, and made<br />
provisions for an additional 30,000 places at universities,<br />
colleges and TAFE's by 1987.<br />
E quilly imoortantly the S\' crnrnmt has aL1SO initiated<br />
-ev1iv's of the a u-31itv of duc-3tiori jt all levels. We are<br />
mos concerned to iriurrove-the ru levarce of the education<br />
process to employment opportunities and to the future needs<br />
of industry. </p>
<p>Indeed we regard the recussitation of our education<br />
institutions as a sound and vital investment in our future,<br />
complementing our policies to restructure Australia's<br />
industrial base.<br />
The Government ha* s been heartened by the growing acceptance<br />
of what it is trying to achieve through its industry<br />
policies. That support is now widespread, among both<br />
employers and employees.<br />
The awareness this implies contributes importantly to the<br />
climate among decision-makers at the industry level which<br />
will make possible the improvement in conditions so<br />
necessary for competitive Australian industry structures.<br />
This awareness hinges on a recognition of the benefits of<br />
the consultative process; through such a process wie avoid<br />
the risk, of a directionless and confusing policy vacuum.<br />
Any such vacuum would mean an inevitable return to the<br />
futile and debilitating patterns of confrontation of the<br />
past. None of us want that.<br />
Indeed the historically low levels of industrial disputation<br />
registered over the last year have given our nation a real<br />
chance to realise its full productive potential. This is<br />
the visible demonstration of the benefits of a true<br />
" consensus" appruach.<br />
Consultation also allows all parties to share information<br />
and reach agreement on a course of action -it is an<br />
integral part of a purposeful, co-operative approach to<br />
industrial change.<br />
The consulative mechanisms wqe have established are also a<br />
fundamental part of the Accord. As such they make a major<br />
contribution to continuing recovery and to the maintenance<br />
of price and wage stability. None of us can afford a return<br />
to the divisive patterns of-the past.<br />
Instead, what we ne~ id to do is to build on the consensus<br />
approach to national economic development issues commenced<br />
at the National Economic Summit Conference last year.<br />
In this regard, a sound approach to the framework for future<br />
industry development is crucial. Rather than playing King<br />
Canute, we should all recognise and accept the need for<br />
adaptability in industrial structures and policies so that<br />
industry can withstand changes in its circumstances, and<br />
respond positively to these.<br />
Importantly, this means moving to integrate manufacturing<br />
policy with external Poic~ s, ospecially trade. </p>
<p>12.<br />
To the extent we succeed in this, in creating the conditions<br />
for an expanding, export-oriented manufacturing and service<br />
sector, vie shall have a basis for providing employment<br />
growith and satisfying career opportunities for future<br />
generations. We look to the Confederation of Australian Industry to help<br />
in the task of addressing these issues.<br />
I thank the CAI,-and particularly its President Mr Don<br />
Hughes, for the very constructive and fort~ hcoming support<br />
they gave at the Economic Summit arid since then in EPAC.<br />
While of course we would not expect. always to asqree on all<br />
issues, nevertheless it has been a matter of great<br />
satisfaction to me and the Labor Government that you have<br />
been prepared to co-operate so consistently and so<br />
constructively to the greater good of our country.<br />
With the support of bodies such as the CAI*, I am sure wie<br />
shall not only secure the necessary community understanding<br />
of the issues involved, but will also successfully meet the<br />
great challenge they present.<br />
The task is not an easy one, but, for Australia, we must<br />
succeed together. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
