<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6280</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE FOR FOREIGN PRESS AT CHOGM CONFERENCE CENTRE, NEW DELHI, 29 NOVEMBER 1983</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/11/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006280.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
AUSTRA1 1A&amp;<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
E. O. E. PROOF ONLY<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE FOR FOREIGN PRESS AT CHOGM<br />
CONFERENCE CENTRE, NEW DELHI, 29 NOVEMBER 1983<br />
PM: Good morning, ladies and gentlemen. Just a couple-* of<br />
preliminary comments that I would like before making myself<br />
available for questions. The first is of course that I'm<br />
not available for a general analysis of the conference,<br />
which, as you will appreciate Mrs. Gandhi and Mr. Ramphal<br />
will be conducting such a conference at the end of proceedings<br />
and it is not appropriate for me in any way to attempt to<br />
usurp or appear to usurp that function. I will be available<br />
to talk about any matter particularly concerning Australia<br />
and the second thing I would like to say to the non-Australian<br />
contingent, that we have had many requests for interviews and<br />
I expressed my regrets that because of the pressures of time<br />
and the conference I haven't been able to make myself<br />
available for those individual interviews and I hope that this<br />
may be some sort of substitute for that.<br />
OK, it's over to you.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister Hawke, Australia recently announced<br />
further steps to isolate the South African Government, but<br />
they fall far short of the proposals that have been made by<br />
both SWAPO and for breaking diplomatic ties with<br />
Pretoria and full economic sanctions against South Africa.<br />
Against the background of these calls would you contemplate<br />
stronger action? And, if you would, how do you think it would<br />
affect Australia's substantial trading links with South Africa?<br />
PM: Two or three comments on that. Firstly, the decisions<br />
which we have taken and which I announced in detail yesterday<br />
were unanimously welcomed by the representatives at the conference<br />
and were taken as amongst the strongest positions that have been<br />
adopted by any nation. Secondly, those decisions were taken by<br />
my Government in the context of what was being done elsewhere and<br />
we were going, as I say, as far as, and in many cases further<br />
than what has been done in other countries. This leads me to the<br />
third comment that if, of course, the rest of the Commonwealth<br />
and the world community were prepared to take further action,<br />
then my Government has made it clear that it would be up there<br />
with them, but if you take, for inistarnce, the case of economic<br />
sanctions I had the experience through the decade of the 70s as<br />
/ 2 </p>
<p>head of the Australian trade union movement of being at<br />
meetings of the ILO in Geneva when there was a great deal<br />
of enthusiasm and motions being carried calling for<br />
universal economic sanctions against South Africa. But<br />
there was a distinct lack of correlation between the<br />
enthusiasm with which the hands were put up to vote in Geneva<br />
and the action that was in fact taken at home. So Australia<br />
has made it quite clear that if the world is prepared, or<br />
the relevant parts of the world are prepared to act in that<br />
way, Australia will be there. Australia is not going to act,<br />
alone when other countries would simply be filling in<br />
vacuums that might be left by Australia. So I conclude by<br />
saying that what we've done is strong by any standards and<br />
I repeat, it was universally welcomed by my colleagues at the<br />
conference. JOURNALIST: You met Mr. Lee of Singapore here. Could you<br />
please report on that meeting and your relations with ASEAN<br />
on the Cambodian question.<br />
PM: Yes, well the meeting with Mr. Lee the first meeting where<br />
!-hosted a lunch for him last week was extremely cordial and<br />
direct and constructive and that meeting has been continued<br />
throughout. We have spent a good deal of time together at Goa<br />
and subsequently. I would say our relations with Mr. Lee and<br />
Singapore are excellent. There is a directness about Mr. Lee<br />
which I welcomed and indeed at the press conference that we<br />
gave after that luncheon last week at the Australian High<br />
Commission he straightforwardly said any problem that there<br />
was is over, as indeed it is. But he said that between two<br />
countries which are as robust and direct as Australia and<br />
Singapore it is likely that some time in the future there may<br />
be differences. The important thing is that we have<br />
established, I believe, a close, constructive, direct<br />
relationship between the two leaders of the countries and<br />
it is within that framework that I believe any differences that<br />
may arise in the future will be capable of being handled<br />
sensibly and in * the interests of our two countries. Now, going<br />
to the second part of your question in regard to ASEAN. I<br />
said before I left Australia, both inside the Parliament and<br />
outside it, that there had been obviously a tendency to<br />
overstate the differences that appear to have arisen. There<br />
were differences but they were not differences which in my<br />
judgement in any way substantially affected the relationship<br />
and that is because the thrust of Australia and the ASEAN<br />
countries in regard to Kampuchea is basically identical. The<br />
conditions that we see as necessary for the resolution of that<br />
problem are the same as ASEAN. That is the necessity for<br />
the withdrawal of the Vietnamese troops, a creation of a<br />
condition within which there can be a free expression of the will<br />
of the Cambodian people which can lead to free and independent,<br />
non-aligned Kampuchea and within which circumstance there can be<br />
a return to that unfortunate country of refugees from it. Now,<br />
those conditions are Australia's conditions. Those conditions<br />
are the conditions of ASEAN and there had been simply a<br />
difference which had led us not to co-sponsor the ASEAN<br />
resolutionl which basically wient to the cluestion of the emphasis<br />
UIOfl the PO] Pot 0eleent Of th2 coa7l it ion ill Kamp11' UChA Now </p>
<p>those matters are fully understood by our ASEAN friends as<br />
. a result of discussions that I and my Foreign Minister, Bill<br />
Hayden, had in Bangkok and that I followed here and that<br />
Bill Hayden has followed in Indonesia and it is not merely<br />
out of my mouth, it is clearly out of the mouths now of our<br />
friends in Bangkok, Mr. Lee, Dr. Mochtar. It is quite clear<br />
that that row, or whatever you want to call it, is over.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister what do you see as the main<br />
achievement of this particular summit?<br />
PM: Good question. That's getting dangerously close to the<br />
sort of area that I talked about before I really think that<br />
ought to be the province first of all of Mrs Gandhi and<br />
Sonny Ramphal. So I would make one comment in respect of<br />
Australia's position and then one, if you like, other comment.<br />
As far as Australia is concerned the importance of the<br />
Conference for me has been the opportunity to meet directly<br />
the leaders of very many important countries. And when I say<br />
important, I don't want to underestimate the importance of the<br />
smaller countries and meeting with them. I now have a basis<br />
into the future of conducting relations between Australia and<br />
other countries of the Commonwealth from a personal knowledge<br />
of the people concerned and a considerable respect for them.<br />
That's been very important to me.<br />
As far as the Conference itself generally is concerned involving<br />
Australia I think that the inclusion of Australia in the group<br />
of five nations which has been established to work with the<br />
United Nations Secretary-General to try and get a resolution<br />
of the unfortunate situation created by the UDI there in<br />
northern Cyprus. That's important for us. We believe that<br />
we have a real interest because of the large population of<br />
Cypriot origin in Australia and our continuing involvement in<br />
the police contingent in Cyprus, and I believe that we do have<br />
an opportunity of playing a part there.<br />
Without taking the proper area of Mrs Gandhi's and Sonny<br />
Ramphal's responsibility I would observe simply in passing that<br />
I think the way in which a common position was reached on<br />
Grenada was to me remarkable. The initial debate was tough,<br />
hard, divisive. Out of that, however, due to processes which<br />
I think could only uniquely happen in the Commonwealth, a common<br />
position was reached. And speaking for Australia, which is all<br />
I purport to speak for here, I believe that the discussion, the<br />
debate and the analysis of that situation in Grenada will have<br />
been significantly facilitated by what happened here.<br />
JOURNALIST: As a newcomer to the meeting whose views aren't<br />
widely known about the Commonwealth how has the meeting affected<br />
those. / 4 </p>
<p>PM: In this way. I answered a question from my own press<br />
grouping in this way that I have never been one to emphasise<br />
the mysticism of the Commonwealth, an element which at times<br />
people tend to wax a bit lyrical about. But what has been<br />
made clear to me is that there is a special quality or capacity<br />
for dialogue within the Commonwealth which I believe you would<br />
not find reflected in any other significant international<br />
grouping. And that was, I believe, most evident in regard<br />
to Grenada.<br />
But picking up your ' new boy' point, when I first heard the<br />
debate I expressed the view that it seemed to me virtually<br />
impossible that you could get common ground. But the readiness<br />
of people with quite strongly divergent, and indeed conflicting<br />
interpretations intially their capacities to listen to one<br />
another, to make some compromise, with a view to looking to the<br />
future to see what we could do constructively in the future<br />
rather than have recriminations about the past, impressed<br />
me very significantly.<br />
I think also, again from Australia's point of view, on tie<br />
Cyprus question there was a concrete example of how this<br />
rather unique group of countries have been able to provide a<br />
working group to operate alongside the United Nations Secretary-<br />
General and as I understand it will be welcomed by the United<br />
Nations officers. Now that's useful.<br />
In the broader area, as I've said in answer to a previous<br />
question, I think it does provide a particular chance to get<br />
to know a range of people aligned, non-aligned, from every<br />
geographical area, from every stage of economic development.<br />
JOURNALIST: From what one has heard in the lobbies you appear<br />
to stand somewhere to the right of Mr Muldoon on economic<br />
support towards Bretton Woods. Would give us some idea of the<br />
area of your disagreement terms of your position on third<br />
world problems.<br />
PM: May I say as-an example of the futility of the facile<br />
application of tags like right and left in complex issues like<br />
this, it may facilitate your journalism, it does nothing for the<br />
understanding of issues.<br />
The fact is that Muldoon, for a considerable period of time,<br />
has had a view about the inadequacy of the existing institutions<br />
which grew out of the Bretton Woods arrangement to deal with the<br />
sorts of problems that are confronting the world economic<br />
community in the 1980' s. Now let's get the points of agreement<br />
and then the different points of emphasis. It's got nothing<br />
to-do in this issue with left or right, or any other tag<br />
of convenience.<br />
The point of agreement between everyone would be that the world<br />
of the 1980' s and as we move towards the end of the twentieth, is<br />
a different more complex world from the uncertainties that<br />
characterised the end of the second world war. I would argue,<br />
and I think the evidence is irrefutable, that those institutions </p>
<p>established at the end of the war h'ave in fact shown a degree<br />
of adaptability. The charter of the IMF has in fact been<br />
amended three times a fact which some people are not aware<br />
of. And not merely in relation to its charter but in the way<br />
those institutions have operated it is self-evident that there<br />
has been a capacity to adjust within the institutions and in<br />
their facilitation with the private sector that has meant<br />
that the problems of the indebted countries have been capable of<br />
being dealt with in a way which would not have been imagined<br />
as possible several years ago. And therefore my view, the view<br />
of others, is that you've got to temper an understanding of<br />
the dimensions of the problems that we ' re talking about with<br />
the realistic objectives of trying to make sure that the major<br />
donor countries, the contributor countries, to these institutions<br />
that they are going to remain co-operative and improve the<br />
operation of the institutions. Those are my views and therefore<br />
I say that what's sensible is to try to ensure that the<br />
existing institutions have their capacities maintained as<br />
a first step, in other words there is the 8th IMF quotas that<br />
have to be finalised, general arrangements to borrow, the<br />
replenishment of the IDA has to be finalised by July of next<br />
year. Now it just seems to me a matter of common sense to<br />
have as a first objective the meeting of those existing<br />
requirements for the institutions. Then if we find, as I<br />
believe we would, that there is a need to add to those<br />
capacities then we should address ourselves to that. In<br />
other words you're more likely to have this marrying of the<br />
meeting of the dimensions of the problems with the involvments<br />
of the major countries who have to provide the facilities for<br />
these things to work. We're likely to marry those things together<br />
effectively if you do it through the approach of trying to<br />
increase the effectiveness of existing institutions.<br />
Within that approach there is room for some preliminary sorbent(?)<br />
approach to a more general review and Mrs Gandhi and Mr Ramphal<br />
will address themselves in talking about the conference to what<br />
the conference has in fact done.<br />
JOURNALIST: The British Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher had<br />
some figures in making this whole approach to the Interim<br />
Monetary Conference somewhat halting and half-hearted ( inaudible)<br />
PM: It's not appropriate that I should address myself to that<br />
because it is a decision taken yesterday and it will be for<br />
Mrs Gandhi and Mr Ramphal to explain that to you. As I said<br />
at the outset I'm not here to try in any way to pre-empt their<br />
exposition to you of the decision of the conference.<br />
JOURNALIST: Could I take up a new point if I may -your ' new boy'<br />
point. PM: It wasn't mine it was someone else's.<br />
JOURNALIST: You used the phrase yoursel. f, so I hope you don't<br />
mind if I use it.<br />
PM: No, no I don't mind sharing things. / 16 </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: It was reported that your first impressions of<br />
the way the mission's organised was that it was at the retreat<br />
that the hard work was done and that the sessions here in Dehli<br />
were perhaps less useful and that perhaps that what might be<br />
more productive in the future would be a four day retreat type<br />
conference. PM: You don't capture exactly what I said because there is no<br />
way in which I would say that the work here hasn't been hard<br />
and in many ways as productive. But you do get to the basic<br />
points. I have a feeling that, I guess it reflects the busyness<br />
that one has at home and the importance of issues there, that<br />
you probably could handle a conference of: this sort in a shorter<br />
period of time. Now I do value the retreat context which in<br />
fact most of it was involved in formal sessions. But it did<br />
provide the opportunity for effective bi-laterals. I would<br />
diffidently make the observation that it would be worth looking<br />
at shorter periods, perhaps with more preparatory work done.<br />
Let me make it clear that's not a criticism of the preparatory<br />
work that's done by the Secretariat with the conference, but<br />
what I'm rather saying is that if in fact we had more<br />
documentation before we arrived, then it may be possible to<br />
have a shorter period of conference and my preference would<br />
be in that case not to shorten but lengthen the retreat<br />
component of it. Now I just make the final observation as<br />
far as the observations of a first attender those are my<br />
impressions and it's the sort of thing I think which could<br />
usefully be thought about and discussed.<br />
JOURNALIST: that Australia was strongly opposed to the<br />
American invasion of Grenada the Commonwealth peace force.<br />
As a result of this conference has Australia ' s view on Grenada<br />
and particularly the American invasion changed?<br />
PM: We expressed the view in the Parliament in Australia that<br />
if we had been consulted, which we were not, before the event<br />
we would have counselled against it. And that is the view that<br />
I would hold now. I think that it is correct to say, speaking<br />
not only for myself but I know in particular the leader of<br />
one African country spoke to me just yesterday he said he<br />
had learnt a great deal from the debate and discussion on<br />
Grenada. And anyone who sat through that debate and didn't<br />
learn a great deal should in fact not be here. And I think<br />
that the communique reflects that learning process. Again<br />
it's for Mrs Gandhi and Mr Ramphal to talk for the conference<br />
about the resolution, but I suggest if you examine it the fact<br />
that it is not recriminating about what's happened but is<br />
directing itself to how the processes of the restoration of<br />
normal government and the facilitating of what we may be able<br />
to do to help, that speaks volumes.<br />
JOURNALIST: We have heard of the action which your Government<br />
proposes to take in regard to South Africa. Can you tell us<br />
what has prompted you to take this action and ( inaudible).<br />
PM: You say what has prompted me. I would. remind you that<br />
I-have a long history of commitment against apartheid, not merely<br />
in words but in actions. I became President of the Australian<br />
trade union movement in 1.970. Very soon after that we had the<br />
prospect of the Springbok rugby tour of Australia and as head of </p>
<p>the trade union movement I led the fight within Australia<br />
against that visit and it wasn't an easy one I can assure.<br />
There were all sorts of threats to us involved, physical<br />
threats, legal threats. And within the International Labor<br />
Organisation the African states were kind enough early in<br />
the 70' s and throughout to recognise the lead that I'd taken<br />
in Australia and the trade union movement under my leadership<br />
had taken. So I came to government with a long history within<br />
Australia and ini the relevant international forums that I was<br />
involved in of expressing the abhorrence which I and the movement<br />
which I led had against that evil system. It's important that<br />
that be understood. I don't come to government having to think<br />
for the first time about this issue. So, as I said, on one<br />
other occasion, privately I think it was, that in this world<br />
there are all sorts of discriminations, favours for people and<br />
disadvantages imposed upon people because of religion, income<br />
and these sorts of things. Now all of that discrimination I<br />
find abhorrent. In respect of some of those things if a person<br />
wants to change his or her religious adherence and wants even<br />
to change his geographical position it's within the capacity<br />
of individuals if they think that the discrimination may have<br />
some basis, it's within the capacity of individuals to change.<br />
If I want to become black I can't become black. If you want<br />
to become white you can't become white. And it just seems<br />
to me intrinsically abhorrent that something which is totally<br />
outside the capacity of a person to-do anything should in any<br />
conceivable circumstance be made a basis of discrimination. That's<br />
something that I have felt deeply all my life and so do my<br />
colleagues within my Government. So what we have done when we<br />
came to Government merely reflected deep convictions that we hold.<br />
And I said in my contribution yesterday that I paid tribute<br />
to my predecessor and indeed it should go back before that to<br />
the previous Labor Government under Mr Whitlam who took a very<br />
strong stand which was respected throughout-the African countries.<br />
Mr Fraser to his credit coming from a more difficult, if you like,<br />
philosophical background maintained the position which had been<br />
initiated by the Whitlam Labor Government and I pay him credit<br />
for that. We felt when we came to office that there was more<br />
that could be done and so we have acted in that way. We've<br />
strengthened the stand in regard to sporting contacts. We<br />
have indicated that there is welcome on our part for the<br />
African National Congress and Swapo to open offices in Australia.<br />
We've started to establish a system of scholarships for those<br />
discriminated against within South Africa to give them the<br />
opportunity of participating in the tertiary education system<br />
which otherwise they would not have. We've made arrangements<br />
deliberately to bring to Australia outstanding opponents of the<br />
apartheid system so that there shall be in Australia the<br />
opportunity for the expressions of that view at least as equally<br />
as in our democracy is provided to the other side. And we<br />
are reviewing the airline policy between ourselves and southern<br />
Africa and we have already cut one South African Airways flight<br />
and we are reviewing the whole. So those things we have done and<br />
we have done it for the reasons that I suggest. We simply find<br />
the system abhorrent and as I said yesterday it's important that<br />
we at this conference express our rejection of the cosmetics with<br />
which the South African government is trying to delude the world<br />
at the moment becaUSe those cosme1tics even more deeply entrench<br />
apartheid into the system... </p>
<p>PM: cont... Now in regard to the contact group I was pleased to<br />
hear yesterday a representative of the African states, Kenneth<br />
Kuanda, and others, praising the members of the contact group<br />
for the approach that they had adopted. Particularly they were<br />
addressing themselves to the British Government and they were<br />
continuing to impress upon the British that they should adhere<br />
to their view and I'm sure they will, the rejection of the concept<br />
of linkage, a concept which we as an Australian government reject.<br />
What has been said by the British Government and has I think been<br />
accepted by the African states that a contact group has done<br />
everything that it can in respect of addressing itself to the<br />
mechanics of the electoral processes what needs to be done to<br />
give effect to the decisions of the United Nations. Those<br />
things have been done. It now remains a question of the<br />
pressure that we put in one way or another upon the South<br />
African regime to allow the final processes of independence<br />
for Namibia to be effected.<br />
JOURNALIST: Can the United States put that type of pressure<br />
on the South African Government.<br />
PM: Well it is within their capacity. I said, and I repeat here,<br />
t hat we reject the concept of linkage and we have a good cordial<br />
relationship with the United States and within that relationship<br />
we will quietly and effectively as we can put that view to them.<br />
JOURNALIST: From your statement you say you are heartened at<br />
Australia's point of view on South Africa banning the<br />
entry of rebel sportsmen into Australia?<br />
PM: That was in the package in which we strengthened the ban<br />
against amateur sportsmen and women. We took the view that all<br />
amateur sportsmen and women wanting to come into Australia shou~ ld<br />
prima facie be regarded as coming with the impramateur of and<br />
being representative of their country. And our southern African<br />
colleagues have recognised that the total package was a strengthening.<br />
-It is true that in respect of those rebels there is a recognition<br />
not only within our country but in a number of the African states<br />
that to give effect to that proposal was complex and unrealistic<br />
and so we'vye said we will not proceed with that. But in every<br />
other respect there was a strengthening, and that was dealing<br />
with a questioning if you like of actual practicalities. I<br />
repeat as far as the African states are concerned their<br />
judgement which was one which I w~ uld think is relevant. They<br />
have acknowledged and welcomed the fact that the package as a<br />
whole is a strengthening of our position in that area.<br />
JOURNALIST: Can I ask a personal question. More than 30 years ago<br />
you first came to India and you converted from religion to socialism.<br />
PM: The premise of your question is wrong so you ' re going to<br />
be in trouble. Can I tell you what happened and then you may<br />
want to reframe your question. I came here to a world conference<br />
of Christian youth as a member of an Australian delegation.<br />
My experiences here started the processes of doubt in my mind<br />
which accelerated and that was a conversion if you like from<br />
faith to agnosticism. It wasn't the sort of conversion you </p>
<p>talk about now. That changing of your premise still leaves<br />
you with a question.<br />
JOURNALIST: What affect has this visit had on you and<br />
do you see any problems ( inaudible)<br />
I see. No. I wouldn't say I'd led a totally aesthetic<br />
few days since I've been here. But it has been a very<br />
disciplined few days and I'm proud of that. The experience<br />
I had thirty years agb was profound upon me and I hope that all<br />
of one's life is a learning process and it has been for me and<br />
this is that of another dimension to the learning process. I<br />
understand again through visiting the country the enormity of<br />
the problems that it confronts. I remind you just in<br />
population terms of the difference. I think when I came here in<br />
1952 the population would have been 300 million odd. Now it's<br />
680 million. The annual increase in the population of India<br />
is about equivalent to the entire Australian population. When<br />
you think about and you see the realities of that here then<br />
it concerns your understanding of the enormity of the problems<br />
confronting Mrs Gandhi, her government and indeed any government.<br />
So that understanding has been strengthened and my commitment,<br />
and not only a personal commitment,. but a commitment of my<br />
Government to try and do within our limited capacity what we<br />
can to help countries and people less privileged than ourselves<br />
has been strengthened.<br />
ENDS. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
