<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2013</transcript-id>
    <title>&quot;AUSTRALIA 1980&quot; - AUSTRALIAN FINANCE CONFERENCE SEMINAR - WENTWORTH HOTEL, SYDNEY, N.S.W. - 10 MARCH 1969 - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. JOHN GORTON</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/03/1969</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002013.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
" AUSTRALIA 19<br />
AUSTRALIAN FINANCE CONFERENCE SEMINAR<br />
Wentworth Hotel, Sydney, N. S. W. MARCH 1969<br />
k-J i APR 1969<br />
SPEECH BY THlE PRIME MINISTER, MR JOHN GORTON<br />
Mr Chairman and Gentlemen:<br />
I have really come here tonight because I believe that<br />
the objectives of this Seminar and the calibre of the people who are<br />
attending it are in both cases so great they should be recognised on a<br />
national basis. There are a number of things which I think should be<br />
said even though they may be already in your minds, and probably they<br />
are or you would not have come together to discuss what our nation will<br />
be like in 1980. This morning the Treasurer spoke to you of the progress<br />
we have made over the last decade. Now let us think of the progress<br />
possible for us between now and 1980. What sort of a nation could we<br />
then be? What sort of a place in the world would we then fill? What<br />
sort of a potential still remaining before us could we have achieved in<br />
the decade from now onwards?<br />
These are most significant questions, and ones to which<br />
you, academics, public servants, businessmen and ordinary Australians<br />
in every walk of life must direct their minds. This is a duty because..<br />
how long ago 25 years or more ago great numbers of Australians and<br />
men from Britain and the United States gave up their lives in order to<br />
ensure that we and other nations who are like-minded would have a<br />
foundation on which to build the fut ure, the foundation being the interplay<br />
of freedom in a community and the use of freedom in a community.<br />
And they secured that foundat ion, but a foundation is not a building.<br />
Without a sure foundation, you cannot have an enduring<br />
structure. But the foundation having been achieved, it is now necessary<br />
and essential that the enduring structure should be built on it, for those<br />
who gained the foundation and for those who will come after us. This,<br />
I think, is the problem to which you are directing your minds. You cannot,<br />
of course, provide a building without great effort and thought and<br />
planning. And I presume that the effort and the thought and the planning,<br />
and the directions they should take, are what were in your minds when<br />
you decided you would have this seminar.<br />
Well, what could Australia be like in 1980? Let us<br />
look at the material possibilities. There has been, in the years just<br />
recently past, an explosion in Australia. We have an opportunity which,<br />
0 a 0. 0. 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
I think, no other nation in the world has within its grasp.<br />
Not so many years ago we were thought to be poor in<br />
natural resources, to be growers of wool, or growers of cattle or producers<br />
of cricketers or tennis players, and not a nation with the immense<br />
potential as such countries as the United States. Yet, in those few vealrs<br />
we have and let me here quote what may be wearisome but nevcrtbele~ s<br />
true s tatistics we have discovered oil fields which, by 1980 and before,<br />
will be producing some two-thirds of the oil requirements of this nationl.<br />
Yet we must discover more because will not be able indefinitely, from<br />
the oil fields so far discovered, to produce all the requirements we need<br />
in the future. Indeed, perhaps 11, 12 or 14 years will see the present<br />
discoveries needing to be augmented.<br />
We have discovered natural gas in almost unlimited<br />
quantities, which will be fed in not onl y to the domestic hearths of this<br />
country but into the industrial complexes, to provide a cheap and reliable<br />
source of industrial energy. We have discovered iron ore in mountains,<br />
and the amount of iron ore in them seems to be illimitable while the<br />
quality appears to be unmatched from any other iron ore sources in the<br />
world. And from these mineral sources alone, long before the period<br />
to which you are looking, something like one billion dollars a year of<br />
export income will be coming into this nation.<br />
We have more than one-third of the world's kcnown<br />
deposits of bauxite to make alumina and aluminium and I mean to make<br />
alumina and eventually aluminium. Our bauxite output will rise from<br />
about one million tons, which is our present output, to ten million tons<br />
in 1972. Production of coal for export will double. Nickel discoveries<br />
will add to the future that lies so close within our grasp, and we are<br />
likely to be one of the great exporters of nickel in the world. And<br />
phosphate, copper and other minerals which have been discovered will<br />
follow. This is no credit to us. These things were there.<br />
But they have been discovered adI vhb* Is been daae to expl oit their discovery<br />
has been of some credit to us, th~ ough you, better than anyone else, will<br />
know how much more can be done to make it of yet more credit and of<br />
yet more benefit to the nation in which we live.<br />
In addition to these natural resources, primary products<br />
have added to our glimpses of thc future, so too has our industrial<br />
secondary development. But therc. is very much more to be done.<br />
What in 1980 will our numbers be? They will be<br />
million, a 25 per cent increase on the numbers now living in Australia.<br />
And what will an increase of 25 per cent in our population enable<br />
Australia in 1980 to do?<br />
It is up to you, and to us all, to see that the best possible<br />
uses of these material opportunities are made. And then what would we<br />
want our nation to do? </p>
<p>-3<br />
Well, I believe that you would want, and the Australians<br />
of 1980 would want, to see that we took our place in the region in which<br />
we live as the technological leader of that region, as the manufacturing<br />
leader of that region. We would want to be a nation which provided<br />
to the greatest extent possible commensurate with our own requirements,<br />
technological assistance, aid of all kinds to the economies of the cou ntries<br />
in our region and, if necessary, military assistance, to provide that<br />
security without which economic progress is probably impossible. That<br />
is why we have as one decision we have had to make indicated that<br />
we were in and of the region in which we live, economically, politically<br />
and militarily, and have provided an earnest and a visible instance that<br />
Australia is there and is going to be there to the utmost of its capacity<br />
now, and I believe in 1980, if we are wanted.<br />
Further, we would want to see that such material<br />
progress as comes to us from the great opportunities that are within our<br />
grasp are spread more evenly amongst our population. I don't mean by<br />
that, any more than the Treasurer meant this morning, that those who<br />
contribute most because of their brain power or organising power or<br />
luck or whatever it may be, should not be rewarded most. But I do say<br />
that if there is great material prosperity to come to us, as I believe<br />
there is, then it is wrong, it is unsupportable that there should be people<br />
who are bankrupted by illress or who are unable in their old age, having<br />
borne the heat and burden of the day, not to have a comfort able life, and<br />
a life without worrying whether there is enough money to buy enough to<br />
eat. This is one of the things that I believe we must be working for in<br />
1980, indeed before that if possible.<br />
But if this nation is to be what you men of vision, and<br />
Australians of vision want it to be and believe they can make it, then<br />
material prosperity is there, and the spreading of that material prosperity<br />
is possible and the taking of our place in the world is possible. All these<br />
things depend on the thought and the effort and the devotion and the<br />
leadership of all of us in this room and of Australians outside who, as<br />
I believe, have themselves perhaps an unformulated but certainly a<br />
sincere vision of what they want the future of their country to be.<br />
What is going to happen though if we do develop as<br />
quickdy as we can, what is going to happen about the ownership of<br />
Australia in 1980, and of the various enterprises in Australia in 1980?<br />
There are two things which are in a sense conflicting,<br />
which we must have in our minds when we think of this problem.<br />
Firstly, it is utterly impossible for us as a nation to develop as quickly<br />
as we must, to bring in as many immigrants as we must, to provide<br />
the industrial muscles we must, unless there is a strong inflow of<br />
overseas capital. From our own resources we cannot generate enough<br />
to do all that we need to do in the time available.<br />
And yet, that having been said, and that being<br />
essential, it is also necessary to seek to see that by 1980, the inflow<br />
of this capital which I reiterate still must come has not come in 4 </p>
<p>-4<br />
such a way that there has not been an opportunity for Australians fully to<br />
participate in the growth which this capital makes possible. There are<br />
a number of facets of this problem, of this difficulty of steering between<br />
Scylla and Charybdis. One of them, of course, concerns the question of<br />
takeovers by overseas companies of Australian companies. As far as I<br />
am concerned, if there is an inefficient Australian company which would<br />
benefit from an infusion of capital, from an infusion of technological<br />
know-how, from an infusion of management, then the provision of<br />
per cent, or even 60 per cent of overseas capital to see that that<br />
company became efficient would not in any be repugnant to me. But if<br />
there were an efficient Australian company, if there were a company<br />
which was operating with good management, good technological application,<br />
and there sought to be a raid on that company by people with a long spoon<br />
who could afford to buy it out at high prices and wait for growth to repay<br />
in five, ten or twelve years' time without dividends in the meantime, then<br />
I would not think it was in Australia's interests that, in such cases, that<br />
should happen. There are questions of development capital required<br />
which are quite different from what I have been speaking about so far.<br />
We have made it clear, as a government, that we would like to see, that<br />
we wish to see, that when development capital comes to Australia to<br />
exploit some hitherto unused resource, to open up some area of the country,<br />
that it would provide an opportunity for some Australian participation<br />
on the ground floor. This is not a matter for legislation. This is not a<br />
matter for something rigidly written in a bill. These are ad hoc decisions<br />
in almost every case. But I think that if a government makes it clear that<br />
it would like this to hap pen, then this does have an effect on responsible<br />
overseas companies who are thinking about coming to this nation and<br />
developing some area of it.<br />
It does have and has had an effect on really responsible<br />
overseas comp~ anies in their decisions as to the amount of equity they<br />
would be prepared to offer and I use the word " offer" and I will later<br />
say why I use the word " offer to Australians, I have no doubt that this<br />
is already happening. Then there is the question of an overseas company which<br />
having, to our benefit and don't let us ever forget this to our benefit<br />
as well as to their own, having carried on some development which needs to<br />
employ new funds for further development, and which seeks to raise a<br />
proportion of those new funds inside this country ( and funds raised inside<br />
this country are not overseas capital and I am speaking of funds raised on<br />
fixed interest) Surely, again without legislation to bring down rigid rules<br />
for this, surely it is not unreasonable to suggest that if such a company<br />
wishes to raise fixed interest money inside Australia, whatever proportion<br />
it may be of the total new funds proposed to be used, that the attitude of a<br />
government towards an approach to raise such fixed interest capital<br />
inside Australia </p>
<p>would be influenced by the amount of equity such a company was prepared<br />
to offer to Australian shareholders. This indeed is what we have been<br />
saying. It may well be and I would not deny it that so much<br />
capital is requized for the development of Australia and for new funds to<br />
continue the development of Australia that the money markets of Australia<br />
and the savings of Australians could not meet the requirements of x per<br />
cent of equity. I think it likely that they could not. That is why I use<br />
the word " Ioffer", because what is important to me is that in such cases<br />
people are prepared to allow Australians to enter with equity such<br />
companies if Australians are prepared to take up the offer. But if they<br />
are not prepared to take it up, as for good reason they were not<br />
prepared to take it up in Gove, or if because of existing economic<br />
circumstances in any particular year it is thought that a float could not<br />
be filled if it were offered, then at least the offer has been made.<br />
If Australians cannot accept it, then that is no reason why the development<br />
should not go on. But if we are thinking of Australia in 1980, it is as<br />
well to have in mind not the legislative compulsions which people talk<br />
about because there are so many different circumstances in any<br />
particular application. But it is as well, I think, for those who come<br />
to us from overseas to know that they won't be disadvantaged, but to<br />
know what it is that Australians would like them to do and, one hopes, to<br />
be prepared to enter into some kind of partnership with Australian s so<br />
that ly 1980, we will be able to be in greater or lesser degree partners,<br />
and not merely the subject of investment.<br />
Of course we are partners in some degree already as<br />
all of you will know, because we get 45 per cent of any profits that any<br />
overseas company makes:' But nevertheless, that having been said, it<br />
is still not unpleas ant to think that there would be a partnership, there<br />
would be an opportunity for Australian participation, depending on the<br />
circumstances and the amount and the economic climate at any particular<br />
time. Well, we'll see by 1980 how it has worked out.<br />
Then we want, I think, in the nation that we all<br />
envisage, more than just these-material advantages. There must be<br />
some conception of the philosophy that the nation wants to live by. I<br />
would hope that by 1980 we would have been able to develop a system of<br />
education which would provide us with the scientific graduates and the<br />
technological people from the Colleges of Advanced Education and from<br />
the universities who will be able to give industry what it wants. They<br />
would be people who would be able, as technologists, to adi ance the<br />
boundaries of knowledge in technology in industry, and be able as<br />
technicians to understand those advances and to service the requirements<br />
of the latest machines and techniques. / 6 </p>
<p>-6-<br />
We would want to see that each individual in this<br />
nation would have an opportunity to choose the type of work which fulfils<br />
him, whatever it may be, whether it is producing television shows or<br />
whether it is out on the new frontiers driving bulldozers. Whatever it<br />
may be, in whatever field whether it is as a teacher, actor, politician<br />
or businessman people should be able to choose the type of occupat ion<br />
which will give them some belief that what they are doing is not only<br />
being done for themselves but is also contributing to the nation of which<br />
they are a part. To give this opportunity is part of what I mean by the<br />
philosophy a nation lives by. And I would hope by then, and I believe by<br />
then, there would be no individual in Australia whose first loyalty, whose<br />
first thoughts, whose first devotion was not to the nation in which he lives,<br />
rather than to the part of the nation in which he lives.<br />
But much sooner than that, we will have what we have<br />
only had before perhaps in wartime, and that is a sense of unity of purpose,<br />
a sense of delight in victory, whether that victory occurs in the West or<br />
in Bass Strait or at Weipa or in Gladstone or in Groote Eylandt. Each<br />
individual will have a feeling of satisfaction at the efforts he or she is<br />
contributing to the growth of a great nation. This is the nation of which<br />
you have a vision, and which, God willing, could by 1980 be an example<br />
to the rest of the nations of the world and which, after 1980, will continue<br />
to unfold the story of Australia Unlimited. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
