<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9150</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ KEATING MP RADIO 6PR HOWARD SATTLER - 9 MARCH 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/03/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009150.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT qF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
RADIO OPR, HOWARD $ ATTLER 9 MARCH 1994<br />
E AND OE PROOF ONLY<br />
SATTLER; Prime Minister, welcome to the studio.<br />
PM: Good Howard, good to be here.<br />
SATTLER: First time since the election.<br />
PM; I have been busy over there engineering a recovery in the economy<br />
and trying to keep the general agenda that we set in the election campaIgn that you<br />
just referred to on the tracks and things are running as we hoped and expected and<br />
the recovery Is coming through strongly and as you know we are now seeing<br />
145,000 Job growth In the last three months. We think we are going to grow<br />
something like 4% In the coming year, which puts us up as fast as any western<br />
country and I am hoping, the key thing Is I think, to make sure the recovery Is<br />
enjoyed by everybody,<br />
SATTLER: How much credit do you personally take for that?<br />
PM; For the recovery?<br />
SATTLER: Yap.<br />
PM: Well the recovery is I think, been engineered by national economic<br />
policy. That Is, ira come by virtue of the Budget policies of the lIst three-years by<br />
-thle er inflation rate, by the lower Intereft--riin a more competitive exchanga<br />
ruts mechanism In place. Al11of that I think is<br />
SATTLER: But don't be so modest you were the architect of the economic policy<br />
for most of the time weren't you?<br />
PM: I was with the then treasurer John Dawkins, but I think we are seeing<br />
as a consequence of Commonwealth Government policy and also the fact that<br />
businessIW now rebalanced their balance sheets. As you know In the 80s we had<br />
debt displacing equity. Now companies have had to build up profitability to<br />
rebalance things to take the debt out and put equity back. that's happened and they </p>
<p>3. PM: Carmen is the kind of person you don't need to make promises to,<br />
she takes her chances In the rough and tumble and opportunities ot public it. e. But I<br />
think I would be very surprised If the Caucus of the Government didn't at some<br />
opportunity, take some opportunity and give her a seat in the ministry.<br />
SATTER: Does she need to got nominated?<br />
PM: In our Caucus there Is none of those pretensions, You nominate<br />
yourself. WMhen they call your name you stick your hand up.<br />
SATTLER: Do you need a seconder?<br />
PM: No you don't even need a seconder.<br />
SATTLER: You just need the vote.<br />
PM: Because years ago we used to have this sort of thing where people<br />
say is there someone to nominate so and so. There would be a sort of momentary<br />
pause and a hand would go up and so now we call a roll of Caucus members and if<br />
you are Interested in a job you put your hand up.<br />
BATTLER: Okay she will put her hand up, will she get your vote for a ministerial<br />
position? PM: She would, she would.<br />
BATTLER: Now if as expected she is elected to a ministerial position what have<br />
you got in store for her? It seems obvious to a lot of us after Ros Kelly's resignation<br />
and you just adding all those portfolios to poor old Graham Richardson who Is crook<br />
with bronchitis by the way, you nave really saddled him with a bit. You have loaded<br />
him up. now are you just going to transfer those portfolios to Carmen if she as<br />
expected gets the nomination or is voted in?<br />
PM: These things are a matter for the Caucus to make judgemonts about<br />
and none of us<br />
SATTLER: You are the bloke who allocates that.<br />
PM-: No I got the job, the right Indeed as you say, to allocate the portfolios<br />
but the stock of members who are part of the Government is decided by the broad<br />
parliamentary Labor Party. Now that has got to happen first, now In the event of<br />
that happening, well. I have some choices there as you say. But again were that to<br />
be the case I would obviously have a conversation with Carmen before I ever<br />
presumed to know what she would be interested In.<br />
SATTLER: Are you sure you haven't already ao that conversation?<br />
No I have had a general chat to her but not to that detail. </p>
<p>2. PM, ( cont'd) are now ready to sort of shuffle off and invest and I think all these<br />
things coming together means that we have got a pretty robust, we have got on our<br />
hands what we haven't had for 30 years, a robust low inflationary recovery.<br />
SATTLER: Interest rates, are you concerned about what has been happening in<br />
the USA and predictions that interest rates will rise In Australia before the and of the<br />
year? PM: Not really, I think that the United States federal reserve bank has put<br />
a very modest Increase in rates, deolmal. point or two<br />
SATTLER: It still sent a shiver through our stock markets.<br />
PM: What the fads so called Is doing Is keeping an eye on Inflation in<br />
America. So are we here, but as you know our Inflation rate keeps coming out<br />
below the pundit's expecttone-and our Inflation rate for the year In the last quarter<br />
was So we have always got to be vigilant about Inflation, all of us but Its that<br />
low inflation rate that gives you the low interest rates.<br />
SATTLER: Are you confident Interest rates will remain at their current levels in<br />
Australia until at least the end of the year?<br />
PM: I think that I am confident that Australia's inflation performance will be<br />
such that this will be a very strong and bull point for the maintenance of low Interest<br />
rates. SATTLER: You are here to campaign for Dr Carmen Lawrence who I think Is a<br />
lay down misers for the seat of Fremantle, god if you I-t-Frmantie-that would be a<br />
nice old slap In the face wouldn't It?<br />
PM: She is such a good candidate and she is going to, I think she is going<br />
to, add to the stock of Western Australian people, members of Parliament who give<br />
a particular and peculiar focus on Western Australian Interest In the Commonwealth<br />
Parliament. I think having bean a premier and joining the Commonwealth<br />
Government Western Australians Will have absolutely tip top representation<br />
particularly in the seat of Fremantle but as you know you already now have Kim<br />
Beazley as Minister for Finance, you have got Peter Cook as Minister for Industry,<br />
George Gear as the Assistant Treasurer. Until recently John Dawkins was the<br />
Treasurer, so Western Australian interests if you like are well and truly represented<br />
there In the key policy portfolios.<br />
SATTLER: Can we take it that she is not going to Canberra to be a back<br />
bencher? PM: She would be the first to say she is not going to hide her light under a<br />
bushel.<br />
SATLER: What have you promised her? 7 </p>
<p>4. SATTLER: But we can take it that Graham Richardson is not going to continue to<br />
have all those portfolios surely?<br />
PM: You think the flu might knock him over do you?<br />
SATTLER: I think it already has and the other thing he has had It appears, a<br />
difference of opinion withi you over a proposal to increase the Medicare levy. Now<br />
you knocked that on the head yesterday In Adelaide but you have said yoU haven't<br />
seen anything to that effect does that mean that there isn't anything or something<br />
might just surface later on?<br />
PMV: Medicare is a great national health system. We have got now other<br />
governments around the World looking at it, but things change. We have seen<br />
change in the relations between public and private systems, you see changes in the<br />
technology and things like diagnostic Imaging and pathology and all systems need<br />
to change With it. Whet Graham has had is the whole system under focus but at this<br />
stage has been as we are, undecided about what we should do. Our primary foc-us<br />
at the moment Is the Green Paper on unemployment because one of the things I did<br />
say on that election night which you referred to ealer was that wa were not going to<br />
leave the unemployed behind and these first couple of months of 1994 are building<br />
on the Green Paper group who reported to us late lest year on how we are going to<br />
deal with the long term unemployed, so that's the principle focus of our work.<br />
SATTLER: Yeah, but there is a story running around this morning they are going<br />
to take people off the Jobseareli allowance and the ACOSS people who supposedly<br />
represent the unemployed are not too pleased about that prospect?<br />
PM: There is no point in me trying to run through the threads of this. This<br />
Is a very large change It Will be a White Paper which the Government Will introduce<br />
In late April which I hope Will let us as a Government do something novel In world<br />
terms. not just In Australian term., but In world terms about the long term<br />
unemployed. See we have got three hundred odd thousand people who have been<br />
unemployed 185 months or more. Now apart from the social Inequity of that, that is<br />
they having carried the brunt of the recession, we are going to find ourselves even<br />
With sort of 10% unemployment, skills bottlenecks in certain areas of the labour<br />
market and that is largely because we have got a pool of people who are not being<br />
retrained. SATTLER: Too many skilled people.<br />
PMV: So what we have to do Is get those long term unemployed people<br />
trained and back Into the labour market so that the recovery Is a recovery for<br />
everybody, not lust the top end of town but those already who carried the largest<br />
burden of the recesion, that is those who are unemployed.<br />
SATTLER: Are you prepared to knock a JobsL levy on the head at this point<br />
because that Is another one that has reared its head?<br />
PMV: The jobs levy as it was an option proposed for consideration by the<br />
Green Paper report, by the Green Paper group as a way of funding the programs<br />
VC;: </p>
<p>PM: ( cont'd) which give these long term unemployed people a job subsidy and<br />
training for a set period. Now I don't think that we necessarily need a jobs levy. I<br />
think the general budgetary scene may be such that we eon do this without<br />
resorting to such a levy. it remains am Option for us but its not one essentially<br />
preferred by me or the treasurer.<br />
SATTLER: So as far as you are concerned no jobs levy, no Medicare levy<br />
Increase? PM: You only do things where in this respect where you have to and we<br />
are In a recovery and we are starting to see a better performance by the Budget<br />
What generally happens In recoveisS is that we invariably see a pick up In revenue<br />
as we have seen a decline in revenue In the recession. The pick ups ore always<br />
greater than we forecast and the declines are always greater, there is always<br />
forecasting conservatism in the numbers. Now I think on this occasion, I mean If<br />
you say to Australians do you think that the national budget should accommodate a<br />
program that gets to the low@ who have been unemployed 18 months or more back<br />
into the labour market, I think moat Australian&amp; will answer that In the affirmative, as<br />
I think they should.<br />
SAiTLER: Unless they have to pay for it.<br />
PM; Even so 1 think that there is the notion of social equity of the fair go in<br />
Australia. When we talk about productivity In this countiieflip side of that coin is<br />
a higher level of unemployment, that is productivity means getting more output from<br />
fewer people. Those fewer people have bean Unemployed and if they are<br />
unemployed over 18 months or a couple of years they lose their self esteem, they<br />
lose their job readiness, they then can't actually get the jobs that then actually turn<br />
up in the labour market, 3o 1 think we are under all of us, all Of US, a soCial obligation<br />
to get them back Into work so that we do our best as a country, as, a society, as a<br />
community to say that we ea not going to have a tail of three or four hundred<br />
thousand people who are basically in labour market terms crippled by it.<br />
SATTLER: But what I think you are saying underneath all of that is if we have a<br />
job we should figure ourselves lucky and we should fork out a bit more for those<br />
who are unfortunate and don't have a job.<br />
PM*. What we e saying is. that the Budget should fork out a bit more, in<br />
other words that the spending priorities of the Commonwealth change in favour of<br />
those who have carred too much of the burden<br />
SATTLER: What, go further into debt?<br />
PM: No, every Budget there is new policy proposals, every Budget there<br />
is always a stack of worthy new things which the Government may consider. It's a<br />
matter of whats at the top of the pile and what I think should be at the top of the pile<br />
is the long termn unemployed. </p>
<p>6. SATTLER: We look as though we are going to be roped in or the United States<br />
are going to try and rope us In to their trade war with Japan and yourcollague,<br />
trade minister Bob McMullan apparently has-been called in eatthe last minute to join<br />
trade talks today with visiting US Secretary of State, Warren Christopher. I have to<br />
say the United States-for an ally, for a good-friend has trea-ted us as faifas trade is<br />
concerned with a bit of disdain in recent years. Why should we go Into bat with<br />
them against Japan?<br />
PM: The world has shrunk in terms of trade, the Inter relationships of trade<br />
are now so Important and obvious to us all that we have to in a sense move on<br />
fronts as they say in the trade, multi-laterally, that Is a number of countries together<br />
not just two together but a number of countries together. The United. States, we<br />
played a major role with the United States in the GATT round, that Is the trade talks<br />
which took 7 years to open up trade opportunities around the world. So the US has<br />
played a good role and the US is making a point with Japan that Japan should open<br />
Its markets. I think where we have some misgivings about this Is the technique that<br />
the US Is considering imposing In the doing of it That is in arguing that Japan<br />
should open Its markets we say that Is fine, that Is good, it's going to be good for<br />
world trade, good for the US, good for us. But imposing managed trade solutions<br />
which is what Washington Is now talking about that Is where they use the thing<br />
called the US federal law called the super 301 where they can actually double tariffs<br />
if you like on particular commodities, It's the heavy handed sledge hammer number<br />
to crack the nut<br />
Now we think that's going to lead to a lot of bilateral trade tensions and that Is why I<br />
think we see the body which I was involved in last year In establishing at head of<br />
government level, this Is the APEC, Asia Pacific Economic Cooperation, this trade<br />
argument between the US and Japan is a sitter for resolution within the APEC<br />
framework. So It means that the 15 countries of APEC. Australia, Indonesia.<br />
Malaysia, Singapore, China, Korea, Japan, the US etc can come to a set of multi<br />
country solutions rather than a nasty little trade war between the US end Japan<br />
which can then affect us because we sell so much product to Japan if those markets<br />
of theirs have access problems in the US that affects us.<br />
SATTLER: But what's in it for us to go Into bat with America against Japan? I<br />
think we have got a trade surplus with Japan but America has got a trade surplus<br />
with us, shouldn't we be getting some concessions there?<br />
PM: We have got a very heavy trade surplus with Japan but US has a<br />
very heavy trade surplus with us.<br />
SATTLER: And is pinching more of our market.<br />
PM: We are saying to the US. yes we agree that Japan having garnered<br />
so much from the world's trading system should open Itself up so that everybody<br />
has a chance to participate in the second strongest economy in the world. But there<br />
is no doubt about the justice in the US case there, but we don't believe that<br />
managed trade solutions are the best and the other thing that wrong foots the US<br />
and makes It look as though they are not really committed to free trade when they<br />
r C -rn nmr~ F~; qrr~ rp~ rr nl^ rrr~ nrr-r lrrr;~ i I; r~ e h c--c~ l </p>
<p>W. ny'wC.-W. tW...~ sr r fl. r . r lr. ttew. rA. t<br />
7. PM: ( conrd) are. so this Is a potential to be a major stoush and like all of these<br />
major things when people are lining each other up in a thing like this caution and<br />
common sense ought to be the watchwords here and I think what Gareth Evens and<br />
Bob McMullan have said to Secretary of State Christopher is look, yes, we agree<br />
with you as trade objectives here but we don't agree with the solutions and why<br />
don't you look at It more In a multi lateral context, kaap us involved, we are friends<br />
of Japan and we are friends of the United States and we don't want an argument<br />
running between two close friends.<br />
SATTLER: So he is not going to get the answer he wants today?<br />
PM: May be not, no.<br />
SATTLER: I understand you are heading for South East Asia next week or the<br />
week after to open a bridge that we have put $ 42 million of taxpayers money in and<br />
we have had afew callsabout that you canexpect that and it comes at a time<br />
when the Government is being heavily lobbied over issues like breast cancer<br />
research where we give only $ 1.4 million annually to research there and it kills 2,500<br />
Australian women a year. Can you understand that some Australians see some<br />
rather misguided priorities in the allocation of all that money there end so little to a<br />
disease which Is killing so many of Australia's women?<br />
PM: Our budget is about $ 105 billion, its about $ 105,000 million so it has<br />
social security spending. its got payments to the states, it's has a foreign aid<br />
program, it has national health and medical research budget. So we don't have to<br />
deny our aid program the sort of funding which is involved in this bridge to actually<br />
do something on something like breast cancer for instance. Because I think, let me<br />
just say about the bridge in the first place. This is the first time, this is a bridge<br />
across the Mekong River which Australia has built and which the Australian<br />
company, John Holland has actually done the civil-engineering on, and this is the<br />
first road connection between Thailand and Laos, the first ever and this will now be<br />
the main highway between Thailand and Beijing so Its called the Friendship Bridge<br />
and Australia sits there and in terms of Australia's reputation in the area and our<br />
interest in these countries like Thailand, a developing country, an Important market<br />
for us, Laos, Vietnam, Australia's name Is very good In this area.<br />
SATTLER: So the business people up there know we built it do they?<br />
PM: Absolutely and I will be actually opening it, so you have got, if you<br />
like. two nations focussing on the fact we are doing It and Its been done by a<br />
company owned In Western Australia, John Holland. Could I just say though on the<br />
other point, on breast cancer, the first thing to say about this, this is a dreadful<br />
disease which is costing us the lives of too many Australian women, that is point<br />
one. Point two what we need is a comprehensive national strategy to deal with it.<br />
What often happens in these diseases., crtain institutes have particular branches of<br />
research and they approach the Federal Government seeking support for this one<br />
but not for that one saying this Institute is more worthy than that Institute and to try<br />
and overcome these problems we have a thing called The National Health and<br />
Medical Research Council which makes decisions about which particular areas of<br />
research </p>
<p>PM: ( cont'd) are funded. There Is already breast cancer research but I don't think<br />
there is a comprehensive strategy and next week In Perth or the week after next I<br />
am sorry. Graham Richardson is meeting with the state health ministers to amongst<br />
other things decide on a comprehensive national strategy to fight breast cancer and<br />
they will be releasing a major statement for a comprehensive campaign against<br />
breast cancer. This Is I think the way to tackle it. Now at the moment, as you know,<br />
the Commonwealth Government runs a breast cancer screening program which Is<br />
available to all women over 40<br />
SATTLER: Yes but there are women under 40 dying from breast cancer?<br />
PM: But its also available upon the reference of a GP for anyone who has<br />
any symptoms of It, or has it in the family, to go and have a screening. But it's also<br />
available just simply under Medicare. That is if your local GP refers a woman for a<br />
breast cancer screening, Medicare picks It up and pays a rebate.<br />
SATTLER: Can I throw In one for the blokes, what about prostate cancer? It's<br />
killing about 2,000 men In Australia every year.<br />
PM: There is generic research into cancers and the cancer's effect, breast<br />
cancer, prostate cancer, bowel cancer, throat, all the other ones, lung cancer. That<br />
is generic research Into cancers and there is a specialised research Into the various<br />
things. There Is speoialised research into prostate cancer too but the numbers in<br />
breast cancer are really quite profound and I think therefore in this area we do need<br />
a comprehensive national strategy. In fact I am happy to say my wife is the first<br />
patron of the Breast Cancer Day and she has been actively Involved in this issue.<br />
SATTLER: So has she put a bit of pressure on you to do something about it?<br />
PM: She has done a bit home lobbying on this subject.<br />
SATTLER: Not a bad thing either surely?<br />
PM: No, not a bad thing and I have taken the Issues up. But Graham<br />
Richardson said, quite appropriately, that what we need here is a comprehensive<br />
campaign and a comprehensive national strategy and I think thats what we are<br />
going to do and the meeting will actually be here in Perth the week after next.<br />
SATTLER: I want to play a short excerpt from an opponent of yours, the Premier<br />
of Western Australia was sitting in this studio just the other day and this is a request<br />
he made. " Paul Keating will be sitting In the seat which you occupy at this moment,<br />
he will be here tomorrow morning, are you going to be meeting him while he is in<br />
Western Australia.<br />
COURT: I would certainly want the opportunity to meet with him and to discuss<br />
Mabo. I mean the Prime Minister can't come to Western Australia and not address<br />
this particular issue so I hope that he is prepared to put aside an hour or so, so that<br />
we can try and have some proper discussions to resolve the </p>
<p>SATTLER; Have you made a request to see him?<br />
COURT: Yes I have made a request on a number of occasions."<br />
SATTLER: Alright we in Western Australia and I think people around Australia<br />
don't want this thing to get to court, it's going to cost a fortune and we are not here<br />
to make lawyers rich, be they Queens Counsel or whatever. Are you going to meet<br />
with the Premier and try and resolve this out of court?<br />
PM: I have seen Richard three times In the last week. I saw him in Hobar<br />
at the Premiers' Conference, I saw him at the EPAC meeting last Friday in Canberra<br />
and I saw him last night at the Notre Dame University.<br />
SATTLER: You spoke with him last night?<br />
PM: We had a chance to talk there, just to say hello, but a chance to chat<br />
if he wanted a chat If I have to see him any more I will have to put an annex on at<br />
The Lodge for him, may be a room out the side, promise him bed and breakfast, a<br />
cup of tea In the morning, a bickie, MA .<br />
SATTLER: Are you sick and tired ofAMl7 Are you sick and tired of trying to<br />
resolve this?<br />
PM: The truth is let's not mix words here. Western Australia had no<br />
interest in talking to us when we were designing the legislation. I made the offer to<br />
the Western Australian Government to send their bureaucrats to the multi state<br />
Commonwealth bureaucrats meetings on the Mabo legislation and they were not<br />
interested. We have now passed the Bill and he is challenging It in the High Court.<br />
It's his challenge not ours.<br />
SATTLER: And you have to defend it In the High Court don't you?<br />
PM: We will have to defend it. What he is saying is the Commonwealth<br />
Parliament doesn't have the right to pass laws in respect of title of land for<br />
Aboriginal people.<br />
SATTLER: What Is this going to cost us?<br />
PM: The truth Is ask him because he shouldn't be doing it. See the<br />
Commonwealth Parliament's legislated in an area where it has I believe sovereignty,<br />
what we are doing is providing all the certainty, the mechanisms of certainty that let<br />
all this be resolved. What Richard Court is doing to Western Australians is saying, I<br />
will tell you what I will do, I will leave this a Jumble for you for the next four, five or six<br />
years, I will throw it all into the uncertain basket. See remember this Howard, it is<br />
the High Court which has said that Aboriginal people have a proprietary right to land<br />
and had it from the time of European settlement in 1788. Now let's say the<br />
Commonwealth Government, Labor Government didn't legislate to set up the<br />
tribunals for Mabo, the awarding of title. All that would happen Is Aboriginal groups<br />
~ h~ N rsl; T ~ wrmrrr m~ sTrr nlwm~ lrr~ un; l </p>
<p>PM: ( cont'd) would simply make a series of claims and lodge them in the High<br />
Court. We would have Western Australian commercial interests in a hole, In chaos<br />
for the next 20 years.<br />
SATTLER: They are making claims now. Here is one today at Point Walter<br />
reserve. PM; Can I just make this point We have now set up a federal court<br />
stream and a state Supreme Court stream If Richard Court wants to be In It. It's his<br />
state Supreme Court can be in It If he wishes to hear native title claims and resolve<br />
them, orderly and to resolve them in a way which actually then doesn't impact on<br />
the commercial Interests or developments of Western Australia. What he is saying<br />
Is look I don't want to be in that, I think I have got a political issue on the line here. I<br />
think I can screw all the political joy out of this I can. I will challenge this legislation,<br />
when the Prime Minister made offers to meet me and bring our bureaucrats over I<br />
rejected them and now what I will say is look, I will go over and this fellow ought to<br />
be talking to me to stop me making my crazy challenge. I mean it's his challenge.<br />
SATTLER: But what do you as the Prime Minister say to the Banell family who<br />
have Just made a claim for part of Fremantle, the Point Walter reserve, there's the<br />
map there?<br />
PM: Simply this, that If there is any, what the High Court made very clear<br />
In all this and legislation made it clear, is that native title Is subordinate to the Crown<br />
and wherever there has been a Crown grant that Is an Interest In land given by a<br />
State Government which is either freehold or leasehold, It will extinguish the native<br />
title. So people can make claims but they are not worth the paper they are written<br />
on. SATTLER: The Benell family should give up on this they don't even live In<br />
Fremantle, they live at Armadale?<br />
PM: Yeah well I haven't seen the matter but this is a process from here<br />
Howard. The federal court of Australia is a place where a native title claim can be<br />
lodged, it can then be heard and decided yea or nay. But generally what we are<br />
talking about here, we are talking about title to land being given to Aboriginal people<br />
who currently still live on land which is owned by the state.<br />
SATTLER: That accounts for the Benell family.<br />
PM: In other words land which is not awarded to anybody, that is not part<br />
of a freehold title, It's not part of a lease, you are talking about land In the back<br />
country In the main which belongs to the state, Crown land, unallocated,<br />
unalienated Crown land on which Aboriginal people still live and really what the High<br />
Court is saying is look, let's right a wrong admittedly 200 years late but better late<br />
than never, let's say this land was always their land, they always had a title to it, but<br />
if they are still living there let's say then can then apply for it.<br />
SATTLER: So most Aboriginal people in Australia won't benefit at all will they<br />
because they live in the suburbs?<br />
T~ LZ~ 91CII~ OmI ~ BCRCb~ n~ AI* I~.;( IIYL' ~ 04&gt; E -rPr~' ' rrl~' D-I( ';"' YOIT '~~ gLm( rpr~' </p>
<p>PM: A lot of Aboriginal people, this is right, a lot of Aboriginal people won't<br />
benefit from native title and that is why we are now looking at the social justice<br />
Component, the land fund component of Mabo this year so that those who can't<br />
apply for native title because they are long pushed off the land can actually get<br />
some access to land.<br />
SATTLER: Okay you are off to Fremantle shortly but It seems that your wife has<br />
taken the front running in the campaign. She has been accompanying Carmen<br />
Lawrence around this morning, is that part of the strategy, is she more popular than<br />
you over here?<br />
PM: No, I am seeing Carmen, we are going to talk about employment and<br />
employment strategies and programs at 11am this morning and I saw Carmen<br />
yesterday for a good chat. But last night I did one function and she did another I<br />
had the honour of speaking at the graduation of graduates from the Notre Dame<br />
University In Fremantle while Carmen did another function and we spread the shot<br />
so to speak.<br />
SATTLER: Some people think you don't care too much about Western Australia<br />
you rarely come here, what do you say to them?<br />
PM: The whole of national economic policy in the last 10 years has<br />
favoured Western Australia. That is Western Australia's great claim was being a<br />
primary exporting stat-il irinerals and agriculture that It carried the tariff monkey on<br />
its back. The changes of the 80s expressly benefited Western Australia and the<br />
Western Australian recovery which is as strong as any in the country is there<br />
because of the federal Labor Government.<br />
SATTLER: Will you be back again soon?<br />
PM: I will be back, sure.<br />
SATTLER: Look forward to seeing you then.<br />
PM: I will see you then, thank you Howard.<br />
ENDS </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
