<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>702</transcript-id>
    <title>OPENING OF THE MONARO SHOPPING MALL. CANBERRA ON (5TH MARCH . 1963 )  SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER , THE RT . HON. R.G MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/03/1963</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000702.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
63/ 0 23<br />
OPENING OF THE MONARO SHOPPING MALL, CANBERRA<br />
ON ' H MARCH2 ,, 1963<br />
Speech by the Prime Mini~ g, the-Rt. Hon. R. G. Menzies<br />
Sir, Your 3xcellencies and Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
This is a marvellous place, but thu. acoustics are<br />
contemptible, ( Laughter) I have been sitting behind Mr,<br />
Dusseldorp this morning and I have heard very little of what<br />
he said. I have had to judge its character by looking at the<br />
eager faces in front of me but I did hear one thing Sir,<br />
very, very clearly and thai was that profound cbservation of<br />
yours that every minute we talked, business was being lost<br />
( Laughter) and therefore I won't talk very long. I must say<br />
that the next time that I have a political meeting, I won't<br />
have it in a building where they have escalators and strange<br />
noises to be heard all around you. ( Laughter)<br />
Sir, it is a long time since I came to Canberra.<br />
Many of you won't recall it, I was a very very respectable<br />
Attorney-General. Since then I have declined in grace and<br />
in favour. But at that time, twenty-nine years ago, the<br />
population of Canberra was about 6,000. Only thirteen or<br />
fourteen years ago, although the population had grown, I think<br />
I am right in saying that there had not been a new shop built<br />
in Canberra for a long time. Since then the development has<br />
been quite fantastic. People have realised more and mo~ re that<br />
we can't have a city of 60,000 which is going to be, so the<br />
pundits tell me, 100,000 in a few years' time, and a quarter of<br />
a million before very long after that growing at this pace<br />
without establishing tremendous demands for shopping facilities,<br />
for schools, for a host of matters required for a full civic<br />
life. And in a city like Canberra, the people are entitled<br />
to have the last word in shopping facilities,, And believe<br />
me, in this place, I think they have them. In fact, I regard<br />
the whole purpose of the displays I've seen here todayas<br />
practically immoral, Your wife goes along innocently thinking<br />
that she is Just a spectator, and everything is so engagingly<br />
displayed tha t she comes home, having spent a lot more money<br />
than her husband can afford. This is what I call wonderful,<br />
immoral, tempting and very satisfactory. ( Laughter)<br />
I congratulate everybody concerned in evolving this<br />
place. I have driven around it two or three times in the making<br />
of it. I am most impressed. I had no idea of the enormous<br />
space inside this building. When somebody said, " Well, there<br />
will be sixty shops apart from these big ones," I found it<br />
difficult to believe but I find they are all quite roomy airy,<br />
adequate shops. This is in a marvellous position and this is<br />
a marvellous community service.<br />
Now the only other thing I want to take up with<br />
you seriously is what this place is to be called, because I<br />
looked in at television the other night and it was called the<br />
Monaro Mall ( mawl). I didn't believe it. I said, " Everybody<br />
knows it is a 4nal" but then I looked it up in the Oxford<br />
Dictionary, and it turned out I was wrong. ( Laughter) But<br />
I want to make it clear that there are three ways of pronouncing<br />
this word " mall' and, of course the other famous<br />
street in London which is always referrea to by fine old Anglo-<br />
Indians retired as " Pell Mell". Take your choice -" Imaw.",<br />
or In fact, another dictionary I looked up quite<br />
09* 000./ 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
recently gave it a fourth pronunciation "~ moll" ( Laughter)<br />
Well, I have elected in favour of " tmall'. But it is a free<br />
country and as far as I am concerned, you may call it what you<br />
like. All I know is that it is a jolly good place and it is<br />
going to be of great advantage to the citizens of Canberra*<br />
It represents a wonderful piece of co-operative enterprise and<br />
is one more contribution made to this city by Mr. Dusseldorp<br />
who, after all, in 1951 was arriving in Australia for the<br />
first tim e* This is an astonishing record and I congratulate<br />
you on it and thank you for it. ( Applause)<br />
And now, time marches on, You are all requested<br />
as the doors are opened to observe the queue not to knock over<br />
the fittings and not to remove any small portable articles.<br />
( Laughter) I have the greatest pleasure in the world in<br />
declaring the Mall open, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
