<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7840</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER LAUNCH OF RURAL AND REGIONAL STATEMENT WARRUGUL - 1 DECEMBER 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/12/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007840.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
LAUNCH OF RURAL AND REGIONAL STATEMENT<br />
WARRAGUL 1 DECEMBER 1989<br />
At the outset I want to thank your local member Barry<br />
Cunningham and all those who have worked with him for<br />
arranging this very important function today.<br />
I appointed Barry as the first chairman of the Country Task<br />
Force that I established in 1986 to advise me and the<br />
Government on the needs and wishes of rural Australia.<br />
The Task Force is made up of Labor'MPs who represent rural<br />
electorates, and it has been an outstanding success.<br />
It has conducted a very wide range of consultations with<br />
groups throughout rural and regional Australia and has been<br />
instrumental in the development of what I proudly describe<br />
here today as a comprehensive, well-measured and effective<br />
set of policies directed at rural and regional Australia.<br />
The Statement I am launching today shows the progress we<br />
have already made and the opportunities to improve further<br />
the effectiveness of the programs we have in place.<br />
What is so very striking today about the rural scene in<br />
Australia is the dramatic changes that are underway.<br />
Global trends and pressures are having a profound impact on<br />
Australia's rural communities even the most remote ones.<br />
The introduction of new technology; the restrictions on<br />
world trade; the economic challenge to restructure,<br />
modernise-and compete; the-continued growth of tourism are<br />
all felt by the people and the communities outside the main<br />
cities: The family farm continues as the basic element of<br />
agriculture, but many farms have become larger so as to<br />
increase their efficiency.<br />
Exporters of primary products are becoming better at<br />
meeting the changing needs of overseas consumers. </p>
<p>S Traditional regional industries including clothing<br />
and footwear are being exposed to international<br />
pressures, and many are learning how to compete with<br />
the best in the world.<br />
S The mining sector, which contributes some 36 per cent<br />
of the total value of our exports, is continually<br />
adapting and innovating to keep its international<br />
market share.<br />
S Coastal strips along the eastern seaboard are rapidly<br />
gaining population and experiencing strong economic<br />
growth.<br />
All this activity and change in rural and regional Australia<br />
means the emergence of new social and economic patterns of<br />
life. So it is even more important now that we be firm in<br />
our determination to ensure the equity and effectiveness of<br />
Government policies directed to those people who live<br />
outside the major cities.<br />
Our aim is simple: to ensure that all Australians have the<br />
opportunity to enjoy a high standard of living through<br />
vigorous and sustainable economic development, supported as<br />
necessary by a full range of public services.<br />
It might often be thought that Federal Governments, based in<br />
Canberra, are remote from people in the bush and that they<br />
are concerned only with the big cities.<br />
And it might often be feared that the so-called ' tyranny of<br />
distance' is an insuperable obstacle for a Federal<br />
Government seeking to deliver services to people throughout<br />
the breadth of our vast nation.<br />
Now I don't say that we can completely overcome that<br />
' tyranny of distance'.<br />
But I do say that we have already considerably minimised its<br />
impact on the quality of life that can be enjoyed by people<br />
outside the major cities.<br />
Just over a fortnight ago I addressed the bi-annual<br />
conference of the National Farmers' Federation.<br />
On that occasion I described the comprehensive way in which<br />
we have acted to protect and advance the interests of<br />
Australia's primary producers.<br />
Through our new soil conservation program, Landcare, we are<br />
protecting the most important ingredient of agricultural<br />
prosperity the soil itself. </p>
<p>Through our micro-economic reforms we are improving the way<br />
in which products are moved and marketed within Australia<br />
and overseas. These reforms, unprecedented in their scope,<br />
will benefit all of those engaged in the export industries<br />
which are the life-blood of Australia: farmers and miners<br />
as well as manufacturers.<br />
Through a comprehensive program of reducing the tariffs that<br />
have hamstrung our economy for too long we are boosting the<br />
competitiveness of Australian primary producers.<br />
And, complementing all this, we are seeking, through our<br />
unceasing international campaign for a liberalisation of<br />
world trading rules, to ensure that our primary producers<br />
have fair access to all-important overseas markets.<br />
But of course it is not just our policies towards<br />
agricultural producers themselves that are relevant to<br />
pursuing our goal of a better quality of life for all<br />
Australians. We recognise that rural Australia is home for millions of<br />
people farmers, to be sure, but also factory workers,<br />
tourist operators, the retired, those in provincial towns,<br />
young families who have chosen to live away from the big<br />
smoke.<br />
Accordingly, our Social Justice strategy has placed<br />
particular emphasis not only on providing new services to<br />
alleviate the special hardships faced by those living<br />
outside the big cities but also on ensuring that those<br />
people have decent access to existing services.<br />
Our Environment Statement that I launched in July ' Our<br />
Country Our Future' explained the progress we have made to<br />
date in achieving ecologically sustainable development, and<br />
the programs and methods we will be implementing in<br />
affirming our commitment to that principle.<br />
Our Womens' Health policy recognises the special health<br />
needs faced by women living away from the major health care<br />
centres. With that detailed but necessary background, I come now to<br />
the purpose of today's gathering: the launch of this<br />
Statement on Federal Government policy for rural and<br />
regional Australia.<br />
The main purpose of this Statement is to demonstrate our<br />
continuing commitment to a certain way of undertaking the<br />
business of government in rural and regional areas.<br />
Our approach is consistent; it is principled; and at its<br />
heart is the notion of social justice. This has special<br />
meaning for non-metropolitan Australians because, among<br />
other things, what distinguishes the city from the country<br />
is options, opportunities, access and information. </p>
<p>We understand the effects of sparse population: narrower<br />
choices of goods and services; higher transport costs; and,<br />
often, considerable personal inconvenience in gaining access<br />
to shops and services.<br />
We are aware of the narrower range of educational and<br />
training opportunities, and the uncertainty that can be<br />
caused by being some distance from health and medical<br />
services. And we are aware of the all-embracing importance<br />
of the road network just as you are presumably aware of<br />
the enormous cost to Government of maintaining and improving<br />
it. I should say, as a counterpoint, that we also understand the<br />
great benefits of living in country Australia. I'm sure you<br />
agree: rural and regional Australia is a wonderful part of<br />
the world to live in. It offers a clean environment; it is<br />
a treasurehouse of natural beauty; and it embodies all the<br />
best community traditions of Australian life.<br />
My conviction on these issues is based firmly on the fact<br />
that the policies and philosophy of the Labor Government<br />
represent the only comprehensive and effective framework for<br />
protecting and advancing the interests of rural Australia.<br />
That is increasingly reflected in the substantial number of<br />
non-metropolitan electorates that return Labor candidates as<br />
Members of Parliament candidates of the calibre of Barry<br />
Cunningham, and elsewhere in Victoria, John Brumby, John<br />
Mildren, Neil O'Keefe and Peter Cleeland. And might I add,<br />
never has the rural community been better served by a<br />
Minister than it is currently being served by John Kerin.<br />
So as a Government, we are not prepared to relax in our<br />
commitment to social justice or to neglect the relevant<br />
issues of access and opportunity. Of course we could take<br />
the easy way out: we could simply say that people have a<br />
free choice about where to live; we could turn a blind eye;<br />
we could respond opportunistically to noisy sectional claims<br />
at a significant cost to the overall community in short,<br />
we could do as the Opposition currently proposes to do:<br />
divert resources to the middle ground, and leave everyone<br />
else can look after themselves.<br />
We reject that approach. The stock-take of our activities<br />
in this Statement shows why we have succeeded in genuinely<br />
promoting the quality of life in rural and regional<br />
Australia: we have managed the economy in such a way as to<br />
achieve restructuring without recession: there<br />
has been record job growth;<br />
our policies have been consistent, coherent and<br />
comprehensive; </p>
<p>S these economic policies have gone hand in hand<br />
with our social justice policy: creating national<br />
prosperity and ensuring it is fairly shared;<br />
S we have not shied away from implementing special<br />
programs where they are demonstrably needed; and<br />
S we have worked closely with State and local<br />
governments to ensure services are coordinated and<br />
comprehensive.<br />
And it is those principles that underpin the whole<br />
philosophy of this Statement.<br />
The process of preparing this Statement has given us the<br />
opportunity to identify where we can further improve the<br />
effectiveness of programs already in place, and where we can<br />
implement new initiatives to fill the gaps.<br />
Today I am launching a new series of modest and welltargetted<br />
initiatives:<br />
S to provide more support for people who provide<br />
long-term care for disabled people in rural areas and<br />
for geriatric care;<br />
S to improve the quality of information people in rural<br />
areas receive about Government policies;<br />
S to expand health services available for rural women;<br />
S to improve the services available to young people<br />
including an expansion of the system of hostels for<br />
secondary school kids;<br />
S to expand the New Enterprise Incentive Scheme which<br />
helps currently unemployed people to start their own<br />
businesses;<br />
S and, finally and importantly, there will be a review of<br />
the current system of tax zone rebates which provide<br />
relief to tax payers in remote and isolated areas.<br />
This review will consider anomalies in zone boundaries<br />
and special zone rebate arrangements, as well as<br />
problems with social security testing arrangements<br />
affecting people in isolated areas.<br />
Ladies -and gentlemen<br />
We are a Government for all Australians, no matter where<br />
they live. </p>
<p>6.<br />
Together with our overall economic management policies, our<br />
micro-economic reform program, and our social justice<br />
strategy, the steadfast approaches and the new measures<br />
outlined in this Statement will allow us together to make<br />
further progress towards our goals for rural and regional<br />
Australia and for the country at large: economic<br />
prosperity, social justice and better quality of life. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
