<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7368</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/08/1988</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007368.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
6<br />
PRIME MINISTER EMBARGOED UNTIL 6.00 AM<br />
FOR MEDIA SATURDAY 6 AUGUST 1988<br />
I have heard with sadness of the death of Sir Keith Shann.<br />
Sir Keith was an outstanding Australian public servant who<br />
had a distinguished career spanning almost 40 years. He<br />
made important contributions as a diplomat in Asia and at<br />
the United Nations and in Canberra as a senior officer of<br />
the Department of Foreign Affairs and as Chairman of the<br />
Public Service Board.<br />
Sir Keith established a world-wide reputation for diplomacy<br />
when he was appointed Australian representative and<br />
Rapporteur of the United Nations Committee on the Problem of<br />
Hungary in 1957. The role he played in bringing the<br />
international community to address the consequences of the<br />
Soviet invasion of Hungary in 1956 reflected great credit on<br />
his personal skills and on Australia.<br />
Sir Keith was an important member of a generation of<br />
Australian diplomats who worked vigorously to define<br />
distinctly Australian interests in the international<br />
environment, particularly in Asia. He was Ambassador to the<br />
Philippines ( 1956-1958) and to Japan ( 1974-1977). many,<br />
however, will renember him particularly for the singular<br />
contribution to public life he made as Ambassad1or to<br />
Indonesia in 1962-66.<br />
I met Sir Keith on a number of occasions at overseas posts<br />
and can personally attest to his outstanding capacities and<br />
the distinction with which he represented Australia.<br />
I extend the Government's and my personal condolences to<br />
Lady Shann and her family on this sad loss.<br />
868 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
