<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10277</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP AM PROGRAMME WITH FRAN KELLY</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/03/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010277.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
March 1997 TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP<br />
AM PROGRAMME WITH FRAN KELLY<br />
E O E<br />
KELLY: Prime Minister, we've just heard Sir Julius Chan say that he expects the trouble in<br />
PNG, the stormy seas to subside now. Do you share his confidence?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well I certainly hope so. I understand what a difficult situation the government of that<br />
country has. We have very close links with Papua New Guinea. We want to preserve<br />
them. We want to help. We also have deep reservations about the use of mercenaries<br />
in Bougainville. It seems as though some of the mercenaries at least may be going<br />
home. If that is indicative of an overall change then I warmly welcome that because<br />
we have always seen the use of mercenaries as a bad idea bad for Papua New Guinea,<br />
bad for peace prospects in Bougainville, and certainly bad for the whole region. So I<br />
hope that they are all going home. Philip Flood, the head of the Foreign Affairs<br />
Department in Australia, is now in Port Moresby as my emissary. He will talk to Sir<br />
Julius today. I spoke to my counterpart yesterday and arranged for the emissary to go<br />
there. Our offer of alternatives is still very much on the table and I hope that that offer<br />
is seriously addressed. And I would expect to be in contact with Mr Flood during the<br />
course of the day. Our High Commission is monitoring the security situation very<br />
closely. We naturally have an eye to the physical well-being of Australians in Papua<br />
New Guinea. There is no evidence, no evidence, I repeat today, to suggest that there's<br />
any danger to Australians but we'll keep that situation under very close attention.<br />
KELLY: I'd like to come to the offer in a moment. But just in terms of the fate of the<br />
mercenaries there does seem to be some confujsion. We just heard some are out and<br />
believe their contracts are terminated. Yet Sir Julius last night said the contract still </p>
<p>stands but he'll discuss it at a special Cabinet meeting. Do you have any understanding<br />
or intelligence of the fate of the Sandline mercenaries and that contract?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I don't know much more, indeed, I don't know anything more of substance than<br />
what's been on the news. And it is a matter for Papua New Guinea to decide what<br />
happens to the mercenaries. I mean, we expressed a view to the government. Our<br />
dealing is with the government of that country. It's an independent sovereign country.<br />
The indications are that there has been some change and I welcome that. But<br />
ultimately that's a matter for the government of Papua New Guinea and particularly for<br />
the Prime Minister.<br />
KELLY: So you got no word or indication on that from Sir Julius when you spoke to him<br />
yesterday? PRIME MINISTER:<br />
We talked about a number of things but it's one of these situations that's changing<br />
quite rapidly. There's obviously been some change, some shift of attitude that's<br />
good. But it is a matter ultimately for the government of that country and it's not my<br />
role to interfere and I'm not. It is my role to state the strong view of my Government,<br />
which I have, and that has been consistent and clear right throughout. It was clear<br />
when I met him in Sydney last Sunday week. It was clear when I spoke to him<br />
yesterday and it remains quite clear. I'm sure it's the right position. But I do have<br />
three very trusted senior officials in Port Moresby now and I'm sure that they will very<br />
faithfully represent my view and put my position in discussions with Sir Julius.<br />
KELLY:<br />
In effect, isn't the special envoy and that delegation you sent to PNG last night, can't it<br />
be a face saving device for Sir Julius? I mean, his troops are essentially on strike and<br />
won't go into Bougainville alongside the Sandline personnel. He could now mask a<br />
decision to withdraw the mercenaries or terminate that contract as a trade-off for some<br />
kind of increased aid package from Australia is that the plan?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I don't have some kind of... I have no Machiavellian plan. I'm using open orthodox<br />
methods of dealing respectfully with another sovereign country. And that is, you talk<br />
to the Prime Minister of that country, you then send trusted people to further<br />
investigate and if subsequent discussions at another level are necessary then those<br />
discussions will take place. It's not a question of providing this or that device for such<br />
and such an outcome. It's a question of dealing in good faith. And I've dealt in good<br />
faith. I've said all along our friendship for Papua New Guinea is strong and enduring.<br />
Our desire to help is very strong. But we have an absolutely implacable opposition to </p>
<p>the use of mercenaries and that has been openly stated all along. Now, I've dealt in<br />
good faith and I'll continue to deal in good faith.<br />
KELLY: You've mentioned several times now the alternative options you've discussed with Sir<br />
Julius. Can you tell us whether more aid money and more military assistance from<br />
Australia are part of those alternative options?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
No I can't. I discussed them with Sir Julius and we've continued to talk about them in<br />
the... there was some correspondence between us after our meeting in Sydney last<br />
Sunday week and I spoke about them on the phone yesterday. But for reasons I ask<br />
you to understand, I'm not going to go into the detail of those alternative approaches.<br />
He understands very clearly what they are and no doubt they will be the subject of<br />
discussion between him and the Flood mission in Port Moresby today.<br />
KELLY: Does he like the options?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well that's a matter for him. I'm not going to prejudice the prospects of a very<br />
satisfactory outcome I mean, I don't know whether we're going to have a<br />
satisfactory outcome. I'm trying, and what's at stake is more important than the<br />
immediacy of detail.<br />
KELLY: Well, in terms of some details first can you rule in or out now the option of<br />
Australian peace keepers in Bougainville?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well I'm not going to get into ruling things in and out. But let me say this in very<br />
broad terms the Australian Government is always very carefuil about making any<br />
commitments regarding the deployment of Australian forces.<br />
KELLY: Foreign Minister Alexander Downer said yesterday that there had been perhaps failure<br />
in terms of the military defence co-operation agreement between Australia and Papua<br />
New Guinea. Is there room or is there a need or responsibility on the part of Australia<br />
to offer some kind of increased assistance and backup to PNG? </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Fran, right at the moment a delegation personally representing me is in Port Moresby.<br />
They may in fact be making arrangements as we talk to meet the Prime Minister. I am<br />
not going to sort of give answers to those sort of hypothetical questions.<br />
KELLY: The question on the ground Prime Minister, this morning in PNG, would appear to be<br />
who's in charge of the military? Some seem to be only taking orders from Brigadier<br />
General Singirok. While the situation remains like that, it must be extremely volatile.<br />
Is that the intelligence you're getting, that the situation there is dangerously volatile?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well it is self-evidently a bit volatile although<br />
KELLY: A bit?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well it's, once again there's a responsibility on all of us, particularly somebody in my<br />
position to deal honestly with questions like that, but equally not use the language<br />
which is too colourful for the occasion. The sight of looting and the sight of any<br />
rioting in streets is always disturbing. On the other hand, this country has struggled<br />
very gamely in difficult circumstances to maintain democracy since it gained its<br />
independence from Australia in 1975, and I think we should admire the attempts of<br />
that country to preserve the democratic process. It does seem to me that the military<br />
leadership in Papua New Guinea is taking a very responsible attitude towards disorder,<br />
civilian disorder. There appears to be no attempt by the dismissed Brigadier General<br />
Singirok to encourage any kind of open rebellion and that's to be applauded, and other<br />
senior officers seem to be taking the same attitude. That's very important but it is a<br />
difficult situation. We welcome the signs that it is returning to greater stability and<br />
greater normalcy and we will do everything we can, consistent with respecting the<br />
sovereignty of the Government in that country to bring that about because it's in our<br />
interests to have a stable, peaceful, prosperous and united and harmonious Papua New<br />
Guinea. KELLY: But can you tell me whether the advice you are receiving through our diplomatic<br />
channels is indicating that the stability that Sir Julius was referring to is in fact<br />
returning or how concerned are they? </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:<br />
There are mixed signs. I think the indications in the last little while is that there is a<br />
determination by the authorities to maintain order and that things are quieter.<br />
KELLY: Okay. Prime Minister, if I can come back home now. Tonight you meet the Premiers<br />
and Chief Ministers ahead of tomorrow's Premiers' Conference. The last time the<br />
Premiers came to Canberra they left in extremely acrimonious circumstances or in a<br />
bad mood anyway, and Federal/ State relations haven't quite recovered since then. Will<br />
you go easier on the States this time? Will you guarantee them no further cuts to their<br />
financial assistance grants or their special purpose grants?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well I've made a, well, the Treasurer on behalf of the Government has put an offer, a<br />
financial offer to the States in accordance with the normal practice. It's not really<br />
appropriate for me to detail that publicly but let me put it this way, the offer that we<br />
are putting is reasonable. I am not a man who welches on deals. I don't welsh on<br />
deals made with the Australian public and I don't welsh on deals made with Premiers.<br />
KELLY: I think the deal the Premiers are a bit worried about is, or the future rather, in terms of<br />
their special purpose grants. Can you indicate whether they will get their way?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I repeat what I said. I mean, there's no such thing as welching on a future deal.<br />
KELLY: Okay. You will discuss Wik with the Premiers tonight. There are increasing demands<br />
fromn a number of fronts for extinguishment of native title, many of them coming from<br />
your own back bench. The National Party has warned that anything less than<br />
extinguishment of Native Title on pastoral leases will cause more trouble than the gun<br />
debate did for the Coalition in the bush. How can you satisfy these demands from<br />
within your own ranks?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I am working very hard with everybody who is involved in this to see if we can achieve<br />
an agreed outcome that delivers justice to all of the parties who have a stake in it and<br />
also security to titleholders and that includes farmers as well as others. Now I don't<br />
know whether it will be possible to achieve that. I have to say that the level of<br />
goodwill between the parties has been greater than I expected. There has been a lot of<br />
contact between different parties that hasn't seen the light of day and that contact<br />
continues. I am going to keep trying hard and if at the end of the day I can't achieve </p>
<p>4 an agreed outcome, and I underline the word " agreed" and it's got to be an outcome<br />
that does deliver certainty and security to the pastoralists who were understandably<br />
shocked by the High Court decision in the Wik case. It went against the assurances of<br />
the former Government. It went against the understanding of most people and they are<br />
understandably very upset and disconcerted by it.<br />
Now I am working hard to see if I can get that. I am not going to respond to every<br />
tiny little story in the newspapers and of course people representing rural Australia in<br />
particular feel strongly about this. There are Liberals who feel strongly about it. There<br />
are National Party members who feel strongly about it. There ought to be Labor Party<br />
members feeling strongly about it as well because it's a very difficult problem. My<br />
responsibility as Prime Minister is to try and get an outcome that unites the people<br />
involved, that delivers on those two criteria. We've made some progress but we've<br />
still got a distance to go. I am not going to say now precisely what I will do if we<br />
can't get the agreed outcome because that will prejudice the prospects of getting it.<br />
Let me say to the farmers of Australia, I won't let you down. I make that very clear. I<br />
am not going to sell out the pastoralists of this country. But most of them, I am sure,<br />
will accept that I have a responsibility to govern fairly for the Aboriginal community of<br />
Australia as well. I have got responsibilities to all sections of the Australian<br />
community and I think we have made some progress. There is a desire on the part of<br />
people involved to achieve an outcome that they can all live with. Now if they can't I<br />
will put certain advice to the Government about what should be done. I have a very<br />
clear view about that. I have said that I would like to be in a position to go one way or<br />
the other by about Easter. Now if that's achievable, that's fine. If we're within<br />
striking distance of something by Easter, I'm not going to quibble about another two<br />
or three weeks but it can't go on indefinitely and it won't.<br />
KELLY: Prime Minister, thank you very much.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Thank you.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
