<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>40797</transcript-id>
    <title>Remarks  at meeting with the Minister for Indigenous Affairs, Senator the Hon. Nigel  Scullion, Mr Andrew Forrest, Founder of GenerationOne and Mr Chris Sutherland,  Managing Director of Programmed</title>
    <prime-minister>Turnbull, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20150915 - 20180824</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/03/2017</release-date>
    <release-type>Transcript</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>Andrew and Chris, congratulations.</p>
<p>Andrew’s GenerationOne initiative has resulted in thousands of new jobs for Indigenous Australians. How many Andrew?</p>
<p><strong>ANDREW FORREST:</strong></p>
<p>I would say we are up around 28,000 but the biggest push is the VTEC program which is supported by your Government.</p>
<p>And I think the second biggest push in history will be collective work with Chris’ company Programmed which has signed up for 5,000 on their own.</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER:</strong></p>
<p>So Chris’ company Programmed, a managed services business, across the country. 23,000 employees.  Currently 606 of them are Indigenous Australians - so 2.6 per cent.</p>
<p><strong>CHRIS SUTHERLAND:</strong></p>
<p>That is right.</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER:</strong></p>
<p>And you are committing here to grow that to 5,000?</p>
<p><strong>CHRIS SUTHERLAND:</strong></p>
<p>Yes, and to grow the business as well.</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER:</strong></p>
<p>And grow the business as well! That’s good. Well that is a great commitment.</p>
<p>You know everything we are doing in our policy, Nigel Scullion and I and the whole government is designed to economically empower First Australians.</p>
<p>The Indigenous procurement program, Nigel, just describe how that has gone. That has been a huge success that has far exceeded expectations.</p>
<p><strong>MINISTER FOR INDIGENOUS AFFAIRS:</strong></p>
<p>We started at about $6.2 million. It is a small business initiative because we know there are a much high levels right across the entire nation, 42 per cent Indigenous employment. So we’ve now gone from a handful to 493 businesses across over 1,500 contracts, but it has actually gone from $6.2 million to $285 million and it just shows that these are settings that we can put on it.</p>
<p>But it is really about the leadership, Prime Minister.</p>
<p>You have said we can’t ask others to do what we won’t do ourselves. So we are now asking the other jurisdictions.</p>
<p>And it is fantastic to see in this company that we’re not having to ask business in the corporate world to do it, they’re already doing it and it is a great partnership because these are the sort of outcomes that we can deliver.</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER:</strong></p>
<p>Andrew, congratulations on everything you do. And Chris, well done. Fantastic. Are we going to sign him up now?</p>
<p><strong>ANDREW FORREST:</strong></p>
<p>We are! On the dotted line. And this is a contract, it is not a goal, it is a contract to employ.</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER:</strong></p>
<p>It is all done. And Senators Hinch and Xenophon looking on – admiring!</p>
<p><strong>SENATOR HINCH:</strong></p>
<p>Yes – official witnesses.</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER:</strong></p>
<p>Very good. That’s right. Excellent, alright, well done.</p>
<p><strong>[ENDS]</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
