<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4369</transcript-id>
    <title>INCOME AND PRICE RESTRAINT</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/04/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004369.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
~ P R 2fiiE BY] II S T R<br />
FOR PRESS 18 APRIL 1977<br />
INCOME AND PRICE RESTRAINT<br />
The Federal Government has adhered scrupulously to the spirit<br />
and the letter of the agreement reached last week with the State<br />
Premiers on income and price restraint.<br />
All actions taken by the Government are consistent wit~ h the joint<br />
statement which was issued at the end of the Premiers Conference.<br />
The hearing of the Conciliation and Arbitration Commission, which<br />
is to take place tomorrow, is entirely at the initiative of the<br />
Commission Chairman acting within his statutory powers..<br />
The agreement itself did not contemplate that the Arbitration<br />
Comiission, of its own initiative, would bring on a hearing<br />
at this time.<br />
At all stages, the Commonwealth has consulted fully with the State<br />
Governments as its partners. Accordingly, the Commonwealth<br />
sought the views of the States on the approach which should be<br />
taken before the Commission and, in the spirit in which these<br />
views were sought, it welcomes constructive suggestions.<br />
This was made completely clear to the Premiers.<br />
Some Premiers have expressed the view that the calling of the<br />
hearing at this stage is outside the agreement we reached in<br />
Canberra.<br />
Accordingly, in the spirit of the agreement which we en.-tered into<br />
we will be altering our submission to the Commission to take<br />
account of them. We </p>
<p>2<br />
We propose therefore in our submission to explain the background to<br />
our joint initiative; to refer to the clear understanding in the<br />
agreement between the Heads of Government that action would be sought<br />
by the Commission following agreement by the parties to a voluntary<br />
general pause; and to ask the Commission to defer consideration of<br />
action at this stage.<br />
We will also suggest that the Commission might explore assisting<br />
the parties to arrive at an agreement on a voluntary general pause.<br />
Under the agreement, and in support of it, the Government has sent<br />
messages to more than 200 employer and employee organisations.<br />
It has made a national appeal to the community at large to work<br />
for price and income restraint.<br />
The Minister for Business and Consumer Affairs, Mr. John Howard,<br />
has written to the Prices Justification Tribunal asking the Tribunal<br />
to defer decisions on price rises and to investigate any claims<br />
that price increases have occurred.<br />
All Commonwealth Ministers and Departments have been instructed<br />
that there shall be no increase in Commonwealth charges, fees, etc.<br />
Action has already taken place in a number of specific areas to<br />
stop increased Commonwealth charges which were in progress.<br />
On Friday I met with representatives of 25 major national employer<br />
organisations which indicated their willingness to support restraint.<br />
Yesterday Mr. Howard announced that the Government was proposing<br />
a special group representing employers, unions and the Prices<br />
Justification Tribunal to assist in the implementation of the<br />
wage/ price halt.<br />
All these actions are firm evidence that the Government is<br />
pursuing its agreement with the States wholeheartedly, and in<br />
full consultation with the States.<br />
The Commonwealth has consulted the States throughout the period<br />
since the Premiers Conference on action taken and proposed. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
