<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>111</transcript-id>
    <title>PM 37/1959 - RESULT OF COMMONWEALTH LOAN - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER AND ACTING TREASURER, THE RT. HON. R G MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/09/1959</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000111_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
P. M. No. -37/ 1959<br />
RESULT OF COMMONWEALTH LOAN<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister and Acting Treasurer,<br />
the Rt. Hon. R. G. Menzies<br />
The Prime Minister and Acting Treasurer, Mr R. G. Menzies,<br />
said today that cash subscriptions of œ C58.5 million were received1<br />
to the Commonwealth loan which closed on Wednesday, September 23.<br />
The loan target was f-50 million, and the over-subscription was<br />
therefore million.<br />
Mr. Menzies said he considered this to be a very satisfactory<br />
result. A feature of the recent loan was a number of large subscrip<br />
-tions from savings banks. This was no doubt associated with the<br />
substantial increases in savings bank deposits which have occurred<br />
in the last few months. Relatively little was received from<br />
trading banks on this occasion.<br />
Mr. Menzies said that nearly three-quarters of the subscriptions<br />
were made to the medium and long-term securities on of<br />
-fer, including about 60% of the total into 5% 1979 securities.<br />
This meant that little more than one-quarter of the subscriptions<br />
were made into short-term securities whereas, in the February,<br />
1959 loan, nearly 60% of subscriptions were made into short-term<br />
securities. During the three weeks since the opening of the<br />
cash loan, cash subscriptions of œ 3.6 million were made into<br />
Special Bonds. This was a little higher than subscriptions made<br />
in the periods during which the last two loans were-open and shcis<br />
that there is a continuing interest in these securities by the<br />
small investor. Total subscriptions to Special Bonds Series B<br />
since 1st July, 1959 are now œ C7.4 million, including œ 3.8 million<br />
raised during the ten weeks preceding the Commonwealth cash loan.<br />
During the thirteen week period since 1st July, redemptions of<br />
Special Bonds Series A totalled œ-800,000, and net receipts from<br />
Special Bonds during the period have accordingly been œ c6.6 million.<br />
Mr. Menzies said that approximately œ C76 million has been<br />
raised in Australia and overseas towards the financing of the<br />
Commonwealth and State 1959-60 borrowing programmes of œ C220 million<br />
approved by the Australian Loan Council œ 10.8 million from<br />
the % 25 million loan floated in New York earlier this month,<br />
œ C58.5 million from the internal cash loan, and œ C6.6 million from<br />
Special Bonds. He added that the Commonwealth is unlikely to<br />
come on to the Australian market for a public loan before the end<br />
of 1959 but will probably be making two cash offers during the<br />
first half of 1960. However, advan ce subscriptions may be made<br />
immediately to the next Commonwealth loan, and Special Bonds will<br />
remain on sale until further notice.<br />
There were more than 250,000 individual holders of the<br />
œ C194.8 million maturing September, 1959 securities for which a<br />
conversion offer was made concurrently with the Commonwealth<br />
cash loan. It will be some time before final results of this<br />
loan are available, but conversions so far total œ 137.0 million.<br />
Redemptions so far are œ 33.8 million and an amount of<br />
œ-24.0 million is still outstanding.<br />
CANBERRA.<br />
29TH SEPTEMBER, 1959 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
