<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>21637</transcript-id>
    <title>Visit to Australia by the President of Israel  His Excellency, President Moshe Katsav </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/02/2005</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I am pleased to announce that His Excellency Mr Moshe Katsav, President of the State of Israel, will visit Australia from 28 February to 6 March.</p>
<p>This is the President's first visit to Australia and the first Australian visit by an Israeli President since President Chaim Herzog in 1986.  President Katsav's visit will reaffirm the warm and long-standing friendship between Australia and Israel and again illustrate the important contribution that the Jewish community makes to Australia in all spheres of our society.  The President will be accompanied by his wife, Gila.</p>
<p>President Katsav will visit Sydney (28 February -1 March), Canberra (2 March), and Melbourne (3-6 March).</p>
<p>  In Sydney, the President will meet the Premier of New South Wales, business representatives and members of Sydney's Jewish community.</p>
<p>In Canberra, His Excellency the Governor-General will host a State Dinner for President Katsav.  In addition to a private meeting I will host a lunch for him and he will also meet the Leader of the Opposition, the President of the Senate and the Speaker of the House of Representatives.</p>
<p>In Melbourne, President Katsav will meet the Victorian Premier, members from Australia's largest Jewish community as well as children from Jewish schools across the State.</p>
<p>  I know that Australians will welcome President Katsav with the warmth for which they are renowned.</p>
<p>  Please note - All Media intending to cover the visit require the National Media Visit Card.</p>
<p>  Media Liaison Officer - Mark Croxford (Department of the Prime Minister  Cabinet)  Tel: 0422 404 149   Email:  <a href="mailto:mark.croxford@mccanda.com.au">mark.croxford@mccanda.com.au</a>  State Media Liaison officers :   NSW: Katie Melrose (Office of Protocol  Special Events, Premier's Department)  Tel: (02) 9513 2000   Email:  <a href="mailto:katie.melrose@premiers.nsw.gov.au">katie.melrose@premiers.nsw.gov.au</a>   Victoria: Andrew Campbell (Office of Protocol, Premier's Department)  Tel: (03) 9651 5009 or 0410 522 891 Email:  <a href="mailto:andrew.campbell@dpc.vic.gov.au">andrew.campbell@dpc.vic.gov.au</a></p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
