<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8473</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP SOUTH AUSTRALIAN FOOTBALL LEGURE LUNCHEON FOOTBALL PARK, ADELAIDE 20 MARCH 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/03/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008473.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE MON P J7 KEATING, MP<br />
SOUTH AUSTRALIAN FOOTBALL LEAGUE LUNCHEON<br />
FOOTBALL PARK, ADELAIDE<br />
MARCH 19912<br />
Ladies arnd gentlemen.<br />
This is my fourth visit to Adelaide in as many weeks,<br />
and it is a. lways a pleasure to be here.<br />
This is a remarkable city by any standards, I always<br />
think of it as a brave city a civilised and cultured<br />
place at tha bottom of the world between the desert and<br />
the deep blue sea.<br />
The Adelaide Festival is the great measure of that of<br />
course. It is one of the great arts festivals of the world.<br />
It's a statement of confidence in ourselves the kind<br />
of confidence which looks outward to the rest of the<br />
world and welcomes the world in.<br />
I came over for a couple of days a fortnight ago and<br />
while I was here I spent an hour in the Adelaide Art<br />
Gallery which is probably the best small gallery in<br />
Australia. Look around in there and you will see how the idea of<br />
Australia, and ' what it is to be Australian, has<br />
developed over thi past two hundred years.<br />
You can see howj this place was first seen through<br />
European eyes, and how those eyes steadily opened. You<br />
can see the vision grow stronger and our regard for the<br />
place grow deeper.<br />
Until you see in those fantastic canvasses of Roberts<br />
and Streeton 100 years ago an image of Australia which<br />
could only be Australia.<br />
The image continues to be our own today. </p>
<p>Keep looking in the gallery and you will see twentieth<br />
century images-of Australia and Australians all of<br />
them Influenced by European styles and taste, but all of<br />
them ultimately, expressing something quintessentially<br />
Australian. It might seem strange to begin this little speech by<br />
talking about art, but I think there are a couple of<br />
broad contemporary lessons in there for us.<br />
To begin with, the Adelaide Festival and the Adelaide<br />
gallery both tell us that it is futile to be parochial,<br />
to close ourselves of f to overseas influence. We need<br />
to keep the windows open so we can see out, and the<br />
world can see in.<br />
Broaden the vision. Don't be frightened of the light.<br />
That's how we grow.<br />
The second lesion is the other side of the coin.<br />
You know what the critics said about the first Roberts<br />
and Streetons. They said they were awful a " pain to<br />
the eye".<br />
They said as their predecessors had said, and even as<br />
their successors were saying well into the twentieth<br />
century, that Australian subjects were basically not fit<br />
for great paintings, and that the modern way of seeing<br />
things was horrible and to be resisted at all costs.<br />
I could point to many other examples of this ancient<br />
cultural cringe but I will attempt to put it in a more<br />
positive way.<br />
There was bound to be a tendency in Australia to shrink<br />
from our owin reality, from the uniqueness of the place<br />
just as there was bound to be an equal tendency to<br />
exaggerate our virtues and achievements.<br />
Both jingoism and cringing are debilitating<br />
afflictionst. I<br />
But in the quest for national growth in the effort to<br />
realise all our potential and make this country as great<br />
as it can and should be I would prefer to err on the<br />
parochial side.<br />
I'd be the last to say that we should reject our<br />
European heritage.<br />
But I do have a complaint against those who have allowed<br />
themselves to become less than whole-hearted in their<br />
commitment to this country.<br />
The fact is that over the years we have been damaged by<br />
the people who have talked us down, who shrink from the<br />
Australian reality, who resist change even when change<br />
I tvr) J TCO OKI t7 7 , t7T 7 r _ IV~ LI'(-170 1 </p>
<p>is imperative, who hesitate who say, but what will our<br />
old masters think?<br />
There will tie chaos.<br />
You know, mayhem and anarchy like an Australian Rules<br />
Football match.,<br />
It's a peculiar game, Australian Rules to an English<br />
person or a Sydneysider, very peculiar at first.<br />
As it evolved from the marriage of the British and Irish<br />
to Australia there have always been those who despised<br />
it as a rude colonial thing.<br />
Many of these disparaging types, I confess, lived in<br />
Sydney. But you're : looking at a convert.<br />
It is a definitive Australian game the unique one.<br />
Mainly skill but with an element of chance and all<br />
played out on a great broad slice of turf of<br />
indeterminate dimensions.<br />
It's a measure of our character, our spirit and our<br />
capacity for invention.<br />
I like the hip and shoulder in Australian Rules Football<br />
-I like it because I do like to keep my own shoulder<br />
against the door keeping the pressure on for change.<br />
I believe we need to do that in Australia.<br />
In our post colonial culture there are still a lot of<br />
people whose instinct is to resist change who would<br />
watch opportunity, even necessity, pass them by rather<br />
than make the changes necessary to grasp it.<br />
In 1992 we have to grasp these opportunities.<br />
That is why-, as we continue with the changes we started<br />
in the eighties, as we implement the strategies for<br />
recovery and growth in One Nation as we take these<br />
necessary structural steps, I have also been arguing for<br />
a more robuist independent outlook.<br />
Dr Hewson is wiong when he says that this is a<br />
distraction. He could not be more wrong.<br />
He is also wrong when he says that the drive for an<br />
Australia which speaks with a mature and unambiguous<br />
voice will not create jobs.<br />
Not one job, he says.<br />
I do not believe that business people will agree.<br />
I/ Od ITO00N t7Z: tT Z6JWO : 131 </p>
<p>Unless they believe that ambition, confidence, pride,<br />
common goals; firmly held, cohesion and cooperation,<br />
enthusiasm unless there are business people in<br />
Australia who think these things are not important to<br />
success, Dr Hewson will not find many people to agree<br />
with his assessment that I have been creating a<br />
distraction. These things are essential in business, as they are in<br />
football. They are essential to the success of<br />
Australia. To speed the recovery, to make the most of our<br />
strengths, to come out of recession stronger than ever<br />
before and we can do all these things we need<br />
confidence iLn ourselves.<br />
We have every reason to look forward to the future in<br />
this country but we won't make the future as good as<br />
it should bia if our view is obscured by a patina of old<br />
protocols, and our energies dissipated in reflexive<br />
salutes to other countries before we salute our own.<br />
We must not let the faint-hearted, or the knockers, or<br />
the whingers and the cringers, get in the way of the<br />
future.<br />
One Nation is aboutñ the future.<br />
One Nation is a program for recovery which calls on<br />
Australians to pool their resources, to enter into<br />
partnerships with each other, to commit themselves to<br />
cooperative enterprise.<br />
By investment in major infrastructure projects,<br />
particularly road and rail, in the reform of aviation<br />
policy, in seeking cooperative relationships between<br />
business anid unions, the states and the commonwealth,<br />
the private! and the public sectors in these various<br />
ways it seeks to close the gaps between Australians.<br />
It seeks to stimulate the economy, and to make<br />
investment in the sorts of businesses Australia needs a<br />
much more attractive proposition.<br />
It seeks and will deliver low inflation growth over the<br />
next decade,. It will deliver tax cuts equivalent to<br />
those promised by Dr Hewson but without a consumption<br />
tax.<br />
One Nation is a document of inclusion.<br />
For instance, huge amounts will be invested in technical<br />
training to bring this third strand of education into<br />
line with the other two that is to say, giving more<br />
kids many more kids life opportunities by<br />
participating in education. This same step will of<br />
course be of great long term benefit to business and<br />
industry. </p>
<p>There is a certain deliberate chemistry to One Nation.<br />
We consulted with business so that we could find the<br />
most practical solutions, the most effective ways of<br />
getting the recovery going and seeing that it was<br />
strong.<br />
We consulted with unions, states and the community for<br />
the same reason and to maximise the level of national<br />
commitment. It is a social document as well as an economic one it<br />
recognises ' how essential it is that everyone contributes<br />
to the recovery and everyone shares in its rewards.<br />
Ladies and -gentlemen.<br />
South Australia will share in the benefits of one<br />
Nation. It will share in the programs designed to bring benefits<br />
to all Australians programs like the overhaul of TAFE,<br />
the reform of aviation, labour market programs and in<br />
specific programs in this state.<br />
To mention three of the major ones:<br />
As I am sure by now you are aware, one of the major<br />
undertakings in the infrastructure program will be the<br />
conversion of 775 kilometre Melbourne-Adelaide railway<br />
to standard gauge.<br />
As you also know, we have offered to take over<br />
responsibility -for substantially upgrading the Sydney<br />
Adelaide road link, which, together with the Melbourne<br />
Brisbane link will provide a high quality highway<br />
network between our four largest cities.<br />
We have provided SO million for the construction of the<br />
rail loop at Outer Harbour, as part of a $ 100 million<br />
upgrading of the port directed at handling timesensitive<br />
cargo between East Asia, Sydney and Melbourne.<br />
All these projects, along with every measure in the One<br />
Nation document, are designed to bring on recovery,<br />
create jobs, build our strengths and deliver to all<br />
Australians hope arnd opportunity.<br />
With low inflation locked in, with a vastly improved<br />
industrial culture, with manufacturing exports rapidly<br />
growing, with a much more competitive and efficient<br />
financial and business culture we can come out of this<br />
recession much stronger than we have ever been.<br />
In* J I Tn, nNi " 17 +, T </p>
<p>One Nation is designed to assure us that the recovery<br />
will be faetter and stronger.<br />
That our economy will be strong, and not least because<br />
the nation will be strong.<br />
it's appropriate on this occasion to borrow an image<br />
from football the strongest team is the one which best<br />
uses it strengths, which develops its skills to the<br />
highest level and deploys them most effectively, which<br />
works cohesively with a common desire for success, and<br />
which does not let the bumps and misfortunes along the<br />
way, knock them of f their stride.<br />
That is the aim of One Nation. To make us stronger<br />
within so we can be strong in the world.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen.<br />
It seems to me that there are two broad models of<br />
society of how a society best operates.<br />
The first one I believe broadly describes the way<br />
Australia has for too long been conceived and operated.<br />
It is the castle with the drawbridge raised the few<br />
inside attempting to extract by various deceits and<br />
stratagems enough energy from those outside to make the<br />
place economically viable.<br />
Now and then some new measure occurs to them you know,<br />
inviting a few select ones into a garden party to get<br />
them on side: or now as Dr ftewson proposes, they go<br />
galloping out into the provinces to collect a tax on the<br />
food they eat the clothes they wear, and the services<br />
on which they rely.<br />
The other way -and I believe it broadly describes one<br />
Nation lowers the drawbridge.<br />
It's principle is inclusion. It broadens the social<br />
base pool~ s our energies and talents, aims at growth,<br />
encourages wholehearted loyalty and commitment,<br />
cohesion, natio3n building.<br />
It assumes that a popularly elected government is<br />
elected to govern not to pull out of the social<br />
equation.<br />
That is my philosophy. It is the philosophy of One<br />
Nation. If this is more of a republican philosophy than my<br />
political opponents then I am more of a republican.<br />
But that is not the key word: the key word is Australia,<br />
the future of this country and its people. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
