<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7724</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/08/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007724.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
' IPRIME<br />
MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA 23 August 1989<br />
I am pleased to announce that the Prime Minister of<br />
Thailand, General Chatichai Choonhavan,, will visit Australia<br />
as a guest of my Government from 29. August tb 3 September<br />
1989. This will be the second visit, by Prime . Minister<br />
Chatichai, his first as Prime Minister, and. the second by a<br />
serving Thai Prime Minister. Prime Minister, hatichai will<br />
be accompanied by his wife,, Khunying, Boonrue , Choonhavan.<br />
Australia values its close relations with Thailand, an<br />
important regional neighbour which ; is curre tly achieving<br />
rapid economic growth. Prime Minister-Chatidhai's visit<br />
provides the ideal opportunity to maintain and advance the<br />
momentum on important issues which was achieved during my<br />
visit to Thailand in February this year.<br />
Thailand is an important member of; ASEANIwhlch plays a key<br />
role in the political stability and economid development of<br />
the region. Australia cooperates closely with ASEAN to build<br />
upon the many interests we share in terms o; stability,<br />
peace and economic development. Prime Minister Chatichai's<br />
visit will provide the opportunity to exchange views on<br />
these mutual concerns.<br />
Our discussions will encompass the developmnt of our<br />
economic and trade relationship, other regional and<br />
international issues, including Cambodia, . and regional<br />
economic cooperation.<br />
A number of senior Ministers and a group ofibusinessmen will<br />
accompany Prime Minister Chatichai. In addition to my talks<br />
with him, there will be discussions among senior Ministers<br />
on both sides. Prime Minister Chatichai wil) also address<br />
the Australia/ Thai Business Council dinner in Sydney.<br />
During his stay, Prime Minister Chatichai will visit Darwin,<br />
Canberra and Sydney. 1299 0<br />
V I </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
