<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8061</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIP OF INTERVIEW WITH HAYDEN SARGENT, RADIO 4BC, 20 JULY 1990</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/07/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008061.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
IW2XXL t<br />
PRIM MINSTE<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH HAYDN SARGENT, RADIO 4BC,<br />
JULY 1990<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
HS: I liked yesterday's speech arnd I think a lot of people<br />
feel, and have felt for a long time that Australia for a small<br />
population on a small piece of land is crazily divided and<br />
inefficiently divided.<br />
PM: Thanks very much Haydn. Yes, it's a paradox because as I<br />
said in the speech we're the only nation-continent in the world.<br />
We've got this whole continent to ourselves and, therefore, as a<br />
nation we don't have the problems of physical divisiveness and so<br />
on that characterise other countries in their relations with<br />
others, but we have imposed upon ourselves a set of divisions<br />
which are quite stupid and which hinder our economic development.<br />
So, what I'm really about is trying to get the States together<br />
and without in any way seeking to impose anything upon them,<br />
because you can't ever achieve anything that way, simply to sit<br />
down and say well there must be better ways that we can deliver<br />
services to the citizens of our country.<br />
HS: I would like to see us with just a unified national program<br />
in terms of hospitals, health, education, roads, road laws, legal<br />
system, company law, railways I mean it's just crazy to have it<br />
all done State by State.<br />
PM: Well that's right and in the first area you talked about,<br />
hospitals, r if you look at that, particularly in regard to our<br />
elderly citizens, we have a situation where the States administer<br />
the hospitals but we put in an enormous amount of money into them<br />
to help them do that We have a responsibility with regard to<br />
nursing homes and hostels for the aged and both of us also<br />
deliver services to the elderly in their homes. Now there's<br />
inevitably in that situation overlap, duplication not only<br />
duplication in actual services, but in monitoring of, delivery of<br />
services. It's very inefficient and so what I'm simply saying to<br />
the States is well, look, let's sit down, I'll put on the table<br />
what I think we ought to talk about which, incidentally includes<br />
nearly all the things you mentioned, and if there are other<br />
things that you, the States want to put on the table let's put<br />
them down and, if it means Haydn that in certain areas that the<br />
States will accept that the Commonwealth does it alt * ogether,<br />
okay. In other areas it maybe that we can see that we want<br />
certain national standards but the actual delivery should be done<br />
exclusively by the States well okay let that be the case and if </p>
<p>-2<br />
PM ( cont) s it means financial compensation from us to the States<br />
to do that, well let's look at that. In other words let's go in<br />
open-mindedly but with the agreed criteria that what it's about<br />
is how to deliver more efficiently and better services to<br />
citizens. That's what government's about.<br />
HS; Now hopefully I think I've got a lot to gain as an<br />
Australian from the end to all these inefficiencies. But, if I<br />
were a State politician, Premier, Cabinet Minister, senior public<br />
servant, I'd probably feel a little bit nervous because I can see<br />
my job disappearing over the hill, because that surely would<br />
ultimately would be the logical conclusion.<br />
PM: Well, I am not proposing the abolition of the States,<br />
that's not on the agenda, that's not realistic, I'm about making<br />
the present system work more effectively. Now I think it is a<br />
case that if we can get political agreement between the<br />
Commonwealth and the States, there will be a reduction in the<br />
number of public service jobs in total in certain areas because<br />
you won't need the duplication of delivery mechanisms, or the<br />
duplication of monitoring mechanisms in some areas. So, yes,<br />
that's true. But as I said yesterday we've never had a more<br />
propitious set of circumstances I think politically than the<br />
present. I mean we've got, I think, now a range of capable,<br />
committed State leaders and I'm not saying that simply because<br />
the great majority of them are Labor, because I went out of my<br />
way to pay tribute to Mr Greiner's positive approach on these<br />
issues yesterday. So I think we've got the political will. Now<br />
I don't think the fact that there maybe some lose of public<br />
servants in certain areas will worry us.<br />
HSs No, I just probably think that they would feel nervous<br />
that's all, even though you don't.<br />
PM: No no, well at the State level you see I've given an<br />
indication yesterday of our goodwill, we'll get out of, for<br />
instance, the bank account debits tax which is raising us some<br />
$ 400 million. We'll take it off as State grants but the<br />
important thing is we'll give that action area back to the States<br />
and they'll be able to use that as they see fit. I mean it will<br />
be their area, it won't correct entirely the imbalance between<br />
revenue raising and expenditure, but it is another area of<br />
opportunity for the States.<br />
HS: That does seem a bit of a carrot though, Prime Minister, I<br />
mean just saying well listen we'll give you that particular BAD<br />
tax and you can play with that. In point of fact I think most of<br />
us have come to recognise that the collection of money has<br />
traditionally now passed to Canberra.<br />
PM: Yes, but except in this area the States have a tax, the </p>
<p>-3<br />
PM ( cont):; financial institution duty tax and we have the bank<br />
account deposits tax and it is one in which letting the States<br />
have that area doesn't have any adverse impact upon national<br />
macro economic management. I mean I made clear yesterday that<br />
the States themselves understand that if you're going to run a<br />
national economy and try and protect a national economy, then the<br />
central government has to have those sorts of powers. The giving<br />
to them of this particular area of tax won't impinge adversely on<br />
that consideration.<br />
HS: Have you made any contact with the Premiers before<br />
yesterday'sa speoch?<br />
PM., Oh yes, yes, I spoke to them at the Premiers conference<br />
that we had here just a few weeks ago. I signalled that I would<br />
be making this speech and in broad terms the sorts of things I<br />
would be saying.<br />
HSI What was the reaction?<br />
PM: Very positive and let me say that was in the pretty tough<br />
environment of that Premiers conference where we were having to<br />
cut their finances a bit. But, without exception very very<br />
positive and, of course, before I delivered the speech yesterday<br />
I wrote to them with a copy of the speech so that they had it in<br />
advance.<br />
HS: Now, some people are saying we've had a phone call<br />
already this morning wait a minute, wait a minute, is this the<br />
thin edge of wedge of Bob Hawke's desire to make Australia a<br />
Republic? PM: Oh it's got nothing to do with republicanism, I mean you<br />
can't really do much about some people's cynicism, it's inbuilt<br />
and, nor their stupidity, let me not beat around the bush, I mean<br />
that's just a stupid comment.<br />
HS: okay, so what about the possib ility that some people say<br />
well look we agree with this, but it's a little bit of a<br />
smokescreen when the real problem confronting Australia today is<br />
the economy.<br />
PM: Again, they don't really know what they're talking about<br />
because this is directly concerned with the economy. I mean I've<br />
made the point that we have undertaken at our national level a<br />
whole lot of micro economic reform, that is to try and get our<br />
infrastructure right to give our firms the most sort of<br />
competitive environment within which to operate. But we're now<br />
reaching a stage in micro economic reform where we need the cooperation<br />
of the States. For example, let's look at a particular<br />
issue, transport. In regard to rail and road freight, we now </p>
<p>4-<br />
PM ( cont) have to work together with the States to have, we<br />
can't get uniformity of gauge in any immediate sense. But what<br />
we can do is get a greater integration of policies between<br />
national rail authorities to limit as far as we can the<br />
inefficiencies that flow from divided authority. Now that<br />
national rail freight initiative is underway and will get an<br />
impetus from what I said yesterday. If you take the question of<br />
power generation and distribution, the States generate<br />
electricity but we have inefficient arrangements between the<br />
States now for interchange between the grids. Now in that area<br />
we need to, if we're going to have proper economic reform, we've<br />
got to go down the path that I initiated yesterday. If you look<br />
at the question of the waterfront. Now we've made a lot of<br />
reforms there and are continuing to do them but a significant<br />
part of waterfront reform is the actual port authority, that's a<br />
matter of State jurisdiction, so we've got to co-operate with the<br />
States to try and ensure that our ports operate as efficiently as<br />
possible. in other words, an absolutely central element in what<br />
I was about yesterday, was economic reform.<br />
HS: Right. You've got a conference in Brisbane in October with<br />
the Premiers about this issue, how soon after that conference do<br />
you hope that some of the changes will start to happen?<br />
PM: Quite soon in some areas. It's a very good question and I<br />
addressed it yesterday. What I said, Haydn, is that what I do<br />
not want is some long drawn out process in which we have a<br />
voluminous report at the end of the process which covers<br />
everything. I said what I want is successive decisions, matters<br />
being dealt with case by case, considered case by case, decision<br />
case by case, so that those things that are capable of being<br />
dealt with fairly quickly are so dealt with. There will be<br />
others which by their nature take longer, but what I'm looking at<br />
is a series of decisions in the various areas. I've nominated<br />
areas where I think we should concentrate first, but I'm not<br />
S being prescriptive about that, I've nominated health and welfare<br />
services, but we will be working contemporaneously on a range of<br />
issues. Now to make that process realistic and not just sound<br />
vague, what I've done is to invite the States immediately to<br />
nominate a representative at a senior level I've nominated the<br />
head of my department and that committee will be set up<br />
immediately to prepare papers so that when we meet at that<br />
conference in Brisbane at the end of October the first of what<br />
I see as a series of Premiers conferences to deal with issueswe<br />
will have concrete and well thought through working papers<br />
which will enable us as Premiers and as Prime Minister to make<br />
the decision which will get the process in a concrete fashion<br />
underway. HS: Okay, while you say you're dealing with it on a case by<br />
case basis, and I agree that that's probably the most efficient </p>
<p>MS ( cont) t way to deal with it, do you have a long-termi goal f or<br />
say that by the year 1998 to the year 2000 1 would like to see<br />
this kind of national efficiency achieved?<br />
PM: Yes, well yes, I've really set a decade because as a student<br />
of hiatory I know as a fact it took the 90s of the last century,<br />
the 1890s where the representatives of what were then the<br />
Colonies, it took them the whole of that decade to get ready for<br />
the Federation which came into existence on 1st January 1901. So<br />
I'm really setting a decade so that when we celebrate the<br />
centenary of Federation on 1st January 2001, these processes will<br />
have been paying their dividends throughout that decade. There<br />
are two parts, of course, to what I proposed yesterday, there is<br />
what you and I have been talking about now the rationalisationi of<br />
services delivery between the Commonwealth and the States, that<br />
is within the existing Constitutional arrangements; but I've also<br />
given my imprimatur to a process of Constitutional reform<br />
starting in April of next year which will be the centenary of the<br />
first Federation convention in Sydney in 1891. Now what we want<br />
to do is to sit down with the States and with lawyers and<br />
community groups to do the very best we can to get agreement on<br />
proposed Constitutional change. Now, for instance, I said<br />
yesterday I think everyone virtually in the community thinks that<br />
a four-year parliamentary term rather than a three-year<br />
parliamentary term is better for government of this country and<br />
I'm very pleased that Dr Hewson seems to agree with that, so what<br />
we will do in this second category of work that is attempting<br />
to reform the existing Constitution will be to look at perhaps<br />
a series of referenda in this decade which will mean as we go<br />
into the 21st century and our second hundred years of Federation<br />
that we will be better equipped constitutionally to handle it.<br />
HS: Prime Minister, I want to thank you for your time. My<br />
personal view is that if in ten years time as a result of this<br />
achievement of this greater efficiency Australians say well<br />
S listen we really don't need the States anymore and we can do this<br />
distribution of services at a grassroots local government level,<br />
I think that will be a good thing, don't you?<br />
PM: Well that's for Australians at that time to decide. I said<br />
back in 1979 that if one were starting afresh in Australia we<br />
wouldn't have the sort of system we've got now. But my duty and<br />
obligation to the people of Australia is to try and work with<br />
what we've got and make it work better. If in the future<br />
Australians want to make that more radical change that will be<br />
for Australians then to decide, my duty is to try and make this<br />
work better.<br />
HS: Prime Minister thank you for your time.<br />
PM: Thank you Haydn.<br />
Ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
