<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6406</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE, 5 JUNE 1984, ON THE TABLING STATEMENT ON GOVERNMENT POLICY DISCUSSION PAPER ON AFFIRMATIVE ACTION</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/06/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006406.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
E OE PROOF ONLY<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE, 5 JUNE 1984, ON THE TABLING<br />
STATEME-NT'' ON GOVERNMENT POLICY DISCUSSION4 PAPER ON AFFIRMATIVE<br />
ACTION PM: I only want to make a very brief statement. Firstly, I<br />
want to express thel gratitude of the Government to Susan Ryan.,<br />
who has been the Minister assisting me, Dr Summers and the<br />
other people in the Office of the Status of Women who have<br />
put so much work into this. And the second expression of<br />
gratitude of course is to the business community and their<br />
organisations for the whole hearted support. which they have<br />
given to the Government in its approach on this matter,<br />
And to the trade unions. -;.' Without'-the support of all those<br />
people and all the hard work of those people we would not<br />
be able to be in a position now where together with the<br />
support of the Opposition indicated to me today that we can<br />
go to the people of Australia with a widely agreed basis for<br />
remedying what has 4~ en for too long a very substantial<br />
deficiency in our societ i.<br />
As I said in my speech, we have luxuriated as a society I<br />
think for too long in saying that yes women have equal rights,<br />
they are not second class citizens but we haven'. t matched in<br />
practice that assertion of principle. And this has been<br />
particularly clear in the area of employment. And the<br />
fact that so many women are concentrated into relatively<br />
few occupations and to be denied the opportunity of access<br />
to positions of responsibility in all the ranges of occupations,<br />
both horizontally and vertically if you like, in the labour<br />
market, has been I think a stigma in society and a contradiction<br />
of our assertion of principle about equality.<br />
Ultimately, the rectification of these inequities is going<br />
to require more than just a program of affirmative action.<br />
It is going to require a gradual reform of our education<br />
system so that from the time young boys and girls go into<br />
the education stream there is not going to be any differentiat-', onon<br />
a basis of sex between the opportunities that will be<br />
available to them to go into the occupations of their choice.<br />
That sort of thing in the education field will take longer.<br />
In the immediate term we believe that under the program of<br />
affirmative action there are things that can be done. I<br />
have indicated that we are not rushing this and this approach<br />
is one that is going to enable a wider base of community<br />
support. You are aware that we are going to have a pilot<br />
program and I particularly thank those 28 companies and </p>
<p>-2<br />
institutions in the educational field who have given us<br />
their support. They are obviously significant institutions<br />
and the fact that they are cooperating in this pilot program<br />
will be of importance in us getting the concept effectively<br />
into action.<br />
I also thank those who;:. are going to work with us on the<br />
working party to monitor the pilot program and to advise<br />
us as we move later on towards a legislative program which<br />
will be directed towards those enterprises with more than<br />
one hundred employees-.<br />
And I am certain that given the basis of approach that we<br />
have adopted, with the cooperation through.. the business,<br />
industrial and political communities, that it will mean<br />
that we will be able to come up with legislation which will<br />
have equally substantial support and will mean that there<br />
will be effective results.<br />
And so I repeat the gratitude of the Government to all those<br />
concerned and I believe thAt we have today initiated a major<br />
reform which.-is going to be of enduring importance to<br />
creating.. a better, more prosperous, and more equitable<br />
society-in this country.<br />
Susan, perhaps you'd like to make some comments and then<br />
we'll be available for questions.<br />
SENATOR RYAN: Yes, yell thank you Bob. I'-d just like to<br />
say that it is:: , immenbly satisfying to beadble to deliver<br />
on such amajor commitmen to women and the fact that we'll<br />
be able to deliver in wa) that will be effective and practical<br />
makes it even more satisfying.<br />
The way in which. the program will be implemented, that is<br />
with a pilot program and a working party to develop the<br />
legislation, means that we will avoid the kind of mistakes<br />
and major problems that other attempts to provide equal<br />
employment opportunity in other economies have run into.<br />
This will really be an Australian development, a homegrown<br />
affirmative action plan, which will take account<br />
of our unique industrial history and our unique business<br />
situation. I'm very gratified that there has been such a degree of<br />
cooperation from major employers because without the cooperation<br />
of major employers legislation doesn't really work.<br />
We wanted to avoid a tokenistic approach or a confrontationist<br />
approach-because we really want to change and improve<br />
employment opportunities for women and I believe that the<br />
approach. we have taken will do that...* And of course in terms<br />
of timing our approach really offers something better than<br />
an earlier approach which I had foreshadowed when we were<br />
opposition. This way we a quarter of a million workers<br />
covered by the pilot program immediately with the prospects<br />
of a very-large proportion of-the work force being covered<br />
after about 18 months of discussion and development. The<br />
earlier proposal that we had in opposition would have taken / 3<br />
W3*.. </p>
<p>-3<br />
over 2 years to come into effect. So this is on the one<br />
hand a very immediate approach, because the pilot program<br />
will cover a quarter of a million workers, but it has the<br />
benefits of being a gradual evolutionary approach which<br />
will ensure that when we do get legislation it will be<br />
legislation that works for the benefit of all parties<br />
concerned and that the pilot program will give us the<br />
opportunity to change and develop our concepts to make<br />
sure that they are practical and that they benefit everybody<br />
and not just some parties to it. So I think it's a-really<br />
extraordinarily progressive step and one that I have total<br />
confidence will be a real improvement in women's employment<br />
opportunities in this country.<br />
JOURNAL IST: Senator Ryan, what does it mean on the ground.<br />
to.: people employed in these 28 companies, for instance:<br />
John Fairfax and Sons<br />
SENATOR RYAN: Well, the merit principle will continue to<br />
apply-, but I'm sure Amanda-that you have no worries about<br />
that. And I think it is important to say that the whole<br />
program is-based on giving women the opportunities..-to be<br />
judged for a job-on their skills and experience and not on<br />
irrelevant criteria such as whether you' i'e likely to get<br />
married or have children. So, it will involve Fairfax<br />
appointing a senior pers-on to coordinate the operation,<br />
analysing the workforce in Fairfax, seeing were women are,<br />
what obstacles there are to women advancing, and then what<br />
kind of training prcArams or extra experience women would<br />
need in order to be in a position to apply on the basis of<br />
merit with a fair chac of success.<br />
JOURNALIST: Senator Ryan, how confident are you that the<br />
business community sees the economic climate now as beingright<br />
for a program which at least in the short run might<br />
involve some inefficiences.<br />
SENATOR RYAN: Well, I think the Prime Minister has in his<br />
hand a number of press releases put out by business organisations<br />
welcoming the step. And because there has been such lengthy<br />
consultation with. individual companies and with umbrella<br />
organisations, we are confident that there will not be any<br />
dislocation at a time of economic pressure for the companies.<br />
The costs involved are not great of course.-They really<br />
involve mainly-the appointment of a particular person to be<br />
responsible and then the process of data collection. The<br />
Office of Status of Women will have an affirmative action<br />
res-ources unit which will assist all the participant<br />
companies and institutions advise them and we have this<br />
affirmative action implementation manual, which sets out<br />
in a very practical and sensible way the steps a company<br />
wbuld go through., certainly concise. So that it'. s a<br />
management approach and major corporations are interested<br />
in improved management. They are interested in improved<br />
productivity-. They are interested in getting . better<br />
out of their workers and having better staff morale and<br />
this is just a way of doing all of those things. / 4 </p>
<p>-4<br />
PM: Could I just refer to the statements that have been<br />
released today. Susan mentioned, just referring very<br />
briefly to extracts from them, which make the point. . From<br />
the Australian Chamber of Commerce, Mr Alexander Downer,<br />
" We welcome the constructive and cooperative way in which<br />
the Government has approached the issue of broadening<br />
opportunities for women in the private sector. Most<br />
business people will support the goal of eliminating<br />
anachronistic discrimination against women, will be<br />
satisfied with many if not all aspects of the Government's<br />
Green Paper". From the Business Council of Australia.. is<br />
a statement by the Chairman of their business law<br />
committee Mr John Wilkes, " The Business Council welcome<br />
the release of the policy discussion paper Affirmative<br />
Action for Women. The Council is prepared to cooperate<br />
fully with the study program". From the Confederation of<br />
Australian Industry, " The Green Paper released today by<br />
the Prime Minister is a welcome contribution to the debate<br />
on equality of opportunity in employment. The Government<br />
can be as-sured-of CAI commitment to work constructively<br />
with-the proposals canvassed in the Green Paper". You<br />
can take that as a-pretty broad spectrum of the free<br />
market business organisations.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, isn,' t that so because<br />
business would assume that it wasn't discriminating<br />
against one section of its work force, and the problem<br />
for you is to-get beyond their assumptions as to what<br />
they-Ire really t in]* ng-and the way they really see<br />
PM: No, I think the di. 1cussions that have taken place, in<br />
which-I haven't been directly involved but I have reports<br />
back on them, there is an acknowledgement on the part of<br />
the business community that discrimination if not conscious<br />
has in fact operated. They are not coming into this<br />
on the basis that they are perfect in this respect.<br />
Quite the contrary-. And they recognise that there is a<br />
lot of work to be done. And may I make this point in<br />
regard to the business community, that I think they<br />
approach it very-sensibly on two grounds. one, I think<br />
they-believe that it's the right thing to do. Secondly,<br />
I think they can also the benefits in it because<br />
it's a simple matter of, it seems to me, of proper<br />
utilisation of resources and if you approach the fact<br />
that a significant proportion of work force, getting on<br />
for forty per cent, is female, then it just makes sense,<br />
it makes economic s-ense, that you should try and maximise<br />
the talent that is there. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: What was wrong with the American system,<br />
accoraing to those quotas?<br />
PM: Well, let me make an observation and Susan may like<br />
to add to it. There are at least two observations that<br />
I would make about it. Firstly, it goes against the<br />
basic merit principle which is foundational to our approach<br />
and which women themselves and their organisations insist<br />
upon. They do not want a situation which is not based upon<br />
merit and I think the second point flows from it that the<br />
concept of imposition goes against the merit concept and<br />
imposes unreal consideration and means that you don't get<br />
the constructive co-operation from firms and enterprises<br />
that we believe is necessary to make the system more fair.<br />
So, they were the two points I would make. I don't know if<br />
Susan wants to add to that.<br />
RYAN: They are the main points. The quotas have been<br />
counterproductive in some areas. And of course the United<br />
States has such a different industrial and legal set-up from<br />
us anyway. They like to legislate for everything. They<br />
are legislation happy compared with us. I think we are a<br />
society where we prefer to do things by negotiation, discussionL<br />
and particularly with the trade union movement which is, of<br />
course, much more integral to the development of the economy<br />
here than it is in the United States. So the whole thing<br />
didn't seem to be an appropriate operation to transfer here.<br />
But the basic proble~ A is the one that the Prime Minister<br />
pointed out that it set 7side the principle of employing<br />
someone and their skls n qualifications an artificial<br />
quota. JOURNALIST: Senator Ryan, there are some appalling figures<br />
in thi'sdiscussion paper relating to migrant women. In August<br />
last year they were 25% of the total female workforce, 30% of<br />
unemployed women were migrants, 40% of the unemployed married<br />
women. Do you think within this nation the concept of<br />
affirmative action there exists a case for sort of affirmative<br />
action for migrant women in isolation?<br />
RYAN: I don't think they need to be dealt with in isolation<br />
because I think their circumstances are so disadvantaged and<br />
you have just read out some statistics to demonstrate that,<br />
but they would automatically receive a pension as any major<br />
company looks at the people or the women at the bottom of the<br />
work heap they will find many migrant women there and so<br />
they will automatically be incorporated in-to the program. One<br />
of the things about migrant women is that many of them start in<br />
a very unskilled job because they don't speak English, they<br />
don't know the situation and that is all they can get, but they<br />
may have many other skills and other expertise from their home<br />
country that they can't manifest while they have the language<br />
problem. Now in a stultified occupational situation they<br />
always stay at the bottom of the heap. Because affirmative<br />
action means that the company will be reviewing the abilities<br />
and the circumstances of all of its workers, it will give<br />
migrant women with other talents the opportunity, once they have<br />
ly: o., </p>
<p>learned English and become familiar with the workforce to<br />
have any other skills and experience they might have<br />
acquired in their home land countries the chance to have<br />
those skills and experiences recognised by their employers.<br />
So I expect and hope that migrant women will be a very<br />
large beneficiary group of the whole program.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, what sort of checks does the<br />
Government propose to have to see that people are working<br />
towards affirmative action in the workforce?<br />
PM: Under the pilot program and the establishment of a working<br />
party I think the concept is a two way interchange that the<br />
companies operating the pilot program will thepiselves be<br />
reporting to both the working party and secondly there will<br />
be the provision of assistance from the unit to be established,<br />
3 so that they can work back in and see how the programs are<br />
going. It is obviously a voluntary monitoring program and I<br />
think the 28 companies and institutions have entered into it<br />
on that basis. I understand it and again Susan may add to this,<br />
but I understand from the discussions that have taken place<br />
that there is an expectation that companies won't simply be<br />
left to their own resources, but will get the benefit of the<br />
experience of others and the opportunity to learn from how<br />
others have coped so that they may be able to make their own<br />
operation more effective, so it is basically a co-operative<br />
two-way process rather than by definition anything more than<br />
that. We are not some time down the track into a legislative<br />
situation.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minis r, does business support for the<br />
affirmative action of the Government extend to the longer term<br />
goal of introducing legislation for companies with over 100<br />
employees. PM: Yes, let me make it clear that they will be represented<br />
on the working party which is both going to review the operation<br />
of the pilot program and prepare options for consideration by<br />
the Government. Now, obviously in that process of preparing<br />
options for the Government there may come to be some differences<br />
of emphasis into what they would regard as the most appropriate<br />
legislation, but I express the hope now that as a result of<br />
the experience of co-operation we will be able to reach a<br />
position of consensus on the legislation.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, were any companies or tertiary<br />
institutions approached which declined to join the pilot<br />
program and do you think that tertiary institutions are<br />
under-represented with only three of them on it?<br />
PM: I understand that there were some who declined and it is<br />
a matter of confidential relationship that we gave an<br />
undertaking that there be no disclosure of names of those who<br />
declined. As far as the question of the educations institutions<br />
being under-represented, I don't think that is the case and<br />
at any rate you will see on the working party that the Vice<br />
Chancellors and the committee which covers all the universities </p>
<p>plus the association ' of the principles of the other<br />
advanced education institutions are represented on the<br />
working party so I think that there will be, if you<br />
like, an enmeshing of the institutions of the<br />
educational institutions in this process.<br />
RYAN: Yes, and it is important to have a whole range of<br />
companies and, as you can see from the 283 companies that<br />
we have got we have got some of the largest and most<br />
acceptable companies. We have got some of the smaller<br />
companies. We have got companies that operate in remote<br />
areas such as mining. We have got urban companies. We<br />
have really covered the workforce as extensively as possible<br />
because there are so many different circumstances in<br />
different parts of industry. But with tertiary institutions<br />
the kinds of problems that affirmative action is going to<br />
address wouldn't be as diverse as they are in industry. Most<br />
universities are run along similar lines although we have<br />
a very large established university the ANU and a smaller<br />
newer university Griffith in Queensland but generally the<br />
kinds of problems that affirmative action is going to address<br />
in higher education wouldn't vary a great deal from institution<br />
to institution, so three seemed to us to be a sensible number.<br />
JOURNALIST: Were any of those companies that declined opposed<br />
to affirmative action or were there other reasons?<br />
PM: I wasn't involi~ ed in those discussions.<br />
RYAN: I think there wele a few companies that didn't feel<br />
able to participate at this stage. Some of them felt that they<br />
already had some programs and they would rather just pursue<br />
their own for the time being. others felt that they were<br />
engaged in other kinds of restructuring. It wasn't a good time<br />
for them to take on a new program, but they all requested to<br />
be kept in touch. They were all interested in the program<br />
and will monitor the pilot.<br />
JOURNALIST: Senator Ryan, will there be tax incentives for<br />
companies who take part in the scheme, now or further down<br />
the track?<br />
RYAN: There won't be any new tax incentives for the scheme,<br />
but as you will notice in the paper-, I think it is on page 49,<br />
there is a letter there is correspondence between me and the<br />
Treasurer where I enquire as to whether existing tax incentives<br />
for training schemes and so on will be able to apply to any<br />
schemes that companies put in for affirmative action and in<br />
general the answer was yes and that they would apply in the<br />
way that companies apply to have tax incentives for any<br />
other training scheme so it seems as though a lot of those<br />
kinds of expenses would fit into and be covered by already<br />
existing tax incentives.<br />
U r </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Senator, how long do you estimate it would take<br />
for changes being instituted at a management level to flow<br />
down to basic attitudes in the community. You have said it<br />
is a gradual evolution, what sort of timetable would you put<br />
on it?<br />
RYAN: I think that there have been basic changes in comimunit~ y<br />
attitudes, hence the degree of co-operation we have got in<br />
the whole thing and the volunteering of companies to participate<br />
in the pilot program. So I think attitude change is well und. er<br />
way. This will, I think, reinforce the movement towards<br />
attitude change because it seems to me that people change<br />
their attitudes when they see things being different, rather<br />
than when they hear that things are going to 1 e different.<br />
When they see women working in a wider range of<br />
when they see women undertaking new responsibilities successfully,<br />
then attitude change will be reinforced and I think that that<br />
will be as soon as women get into the newer jobs. But we are<br />
looking at the pilot program as taking all in all about 18<br />
months about 12 months to report back and then some months<br />
to feed that into the legislative process, but I think<br />
attitude change is with us now and we are really just seeking<br />
to reinforce it.<br />
JOURNALIST: Senator Ryan, will the working party, or anybody<br />
else be examining the need for penalties for companies who<br />
choose to ignore the Government's approach to action?<br />
RYAN: That will be a part of what the working party will<br />
look at, yes.<br />
JOURNALIST: Would that'be in the form of fines?<br />
RYAN: Well that is all open to discussion. They can look<br />
at other examples that exist in other areas of company law<br />
and just that is really the kind of thing we are having<br />
a working party set up to advise us and to discuss with us.<br />
That is all open.<br />
JOURNALIST: In the public service area isn't it true that<br />
there will be legislation enforced I think it is Mr. Dawkins3<br />
RYAN: Yes it is and it is before the Senate now.<br />
JOURNALIST: DO they include penalties for-people who don't<br />
comply? PM: Well when you are the Government they don't disobey<br />
you they had better not.<br />
JOURNALIST: Just on a separate topic. * Did you get a chance<br />
to read the Soutter Report?<br />
PM: I Haven't. I was just going to say I haven't had one<br />
sent to me. That may not be accurate. There may have been<br />
one come into the process, but it hasn't come to my desk<br />
yet, but when it does, I will read it. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
