<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5115</transcript-id>
    <title>CONSULTATIONS WITH THE COMMISSION OF THE EUROPEAN COMMUNITIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/07/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005115.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
JIAU S THA LIA<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA 25 July__ 1979<br />
CONSULTATIONS WITH THE COMMISSION<br />
OF THE EUROPEAN COMMUNITIES<br />
For the first time, regular consultations at both Ministerial<br />
and official level are to be held between Australia and the<br />
Commission of the European Communities.<br />
The Commission plays a significant role in policy formulation<br />
and these regular consultations will ensure that it is continually<br />
aware of Australia's interests and concerns. I wrote to<br />
President Jenkins proposing regular consultations and he has now<br />
informed me that he welcomes this initiative.<br />
This development is a clear vindication of the vigorous policy<br />
adopted by this Government over the last two years aimed at<br />
establishing a meaningful and equitable relationship between<br />
Australia and the commmunities. Indeed, I recall that during<br />
my viLsit to Brussels in June 1977 i~ t was exceedingly difficult<br />
to persuade the Commission to even agre e to negotiate with<br />
Australia. However, as a result of strong and continuing<br />
efforts by a number of Australian Ministers, an agreement<br />
has finally been conc" Luded with the in the context of the<br />
. Multilateral Trade Negotiations. The agreement will provide<br />
Australian exporters with im~ proved marketing opportunities in<br />
Europe. I should emphasise. however that we see this agreement<br />
as only the fLirst step in a process of change which will bring<br />
benefit to all Australian producers.<br />
Exchanges between Australia and the Commission have to date<br />
concentrated on the trade and commercial relationship. I would<br />
expect that the regular consultations would in addition canvass<br />
other important trade-related issues in our overall relationship<br />
such as energy and minerals. The consultations which are<br />
expected to commence shortly represent an important development<br />
in fostering improved relations between Australia and the E. C. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
