<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3019</transcript-id>
    <title>AUSTRALIAN AID TO INDO-CHINA</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/09/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003019.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
NQ DATE<br />
M4/ 136 21 September 1973<br />
AUSTRALIAN AID TO0 INDO-CHINA<br />
The Prime Minister and Minister for Foreign Affairs,<br />
Mr VWhitlam, today announced a further stage in the Government's<br />
plan to contribute to the post-war reconstruction of all<br />
countries in Indo-China.<br />
Mr Whitlam said that Australia's first consignment<br />
of aid for North Viet-Nam had now been shipped by the chartered<br />
vessel " Cosmos" and was expected to reach Haiphong early next<br />
month. The shipment was valued at $ 600,000 and comprised 70g000<br />
kilos of wool and 760 -bons of roofing i-ron. Mr Whitlam said<br />
the recently established Australian Embassy in Hanoi would be in<br />
a position to discuss further requests for aid,<br />
In reaffairming the Government's decision to participate<br />
generously in aid programs for Indo-China, irrespective of the<br />
politics of the people concerned or their Governments, Mr W,. hitlam<br />
recalled that Australia had already given $ U5250,000 to the<br />
Indo-China Operations Group of the international Red Cross for<br />
humanitarian aid for the whole of Indo-China and a further<br />
$ 250,000 to UNICEF to assist maternal and child welfare,<br />
Mr WPhitlam also gave details of Australian aid for<br />
South Viet-Nam, and outlined proposals for Laos and the Khmer<br />
Republic. </p>
<p>2<br />
In South Viet-Nam, he said, most of Australia's<br />
aid was being directed to projects such as town water supply<br />
schemes, which were regarded as a major factor in improving<br />
public health. Current projects included the provision of Australian<br />
equipment and engineering assistance in the development of<br />
water supply schemes for Da Nang and Vung Tau. The projects would<br />
be developed over the next six years with Australia contributing<br />
$ 6.7 million in the Da Nang scheme and $ 3 million at Vung Tau.<br />
Another $ 3.5 million was being provided to South Vietn'i<br />
National Water Supply Agency and $ 1.6 million to the Saigon<br />
Metropolitan Water Office, in the form of pipes, fittings and<br />
ancillary equipment.<br />
Mr Whitlam added that provision had been made in the<br />
current financial year for Australia to give more aid to Laos<br />
for irrigation, forestry and educational projects, and to the<br />
Khymer Republic for irrigation, flood control and electric powe*<br />
projects. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
