<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1557</transcript-id>
    <title>KOREA -  SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR.,HARO HOLT OD DETARTURE FROM SEOUL  9TH APRIL, 1967</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/04/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001557.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
ASI. UN TOUIR 1967 KORE1<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME IJNI3TER, MR. HAROLD HOLT<br />
ON DEPr. RTURE FRO. 1 SEOUL 9TH PRIL, 1967<br />
As I make my departure from Korea, I would like to sum<br />
up in these few Iinal words, some of the impressions that Mrs.<br />
Holt and I and the other memoers of my party will take away with<br />
us at the end of this most memorable visit.<br />
First of all, Mr. Prime Minister I heartily endorse<br />
your description of this visit as an important milestone in the<br />
history o the relationship betv een our two countries. It has<br />
prov. ied us with a clear indiclation of the pro'' ress we have made<br />
in cemniting that comradeship that we establis ed in the days of<br />
your greatest peril seventeen years ago.<br />
One indelible impression that we shall take away is that<br />
of the tremendous warmth of your welcome to us and of the great<br />
kindness that you and all your people have extended to us since<br />
our arrival here. We have always understood thtt the Koreans were<br />
a .! arm-hearted people !, ho did not hesitAate to display openly their<br />
liking and respect for friends, : nd it has been a stirriny experience<br />
to us to have his understanding so strikingly confirmed.<br />
We have also been deeply impressed b all the evidence we<br />
haanvde msoedeenr noifs attihoen spolf endoiudr pcyro~ oug nrres s ypoaur tihcauv e mrla e ini ntt ihtnehe e ppirssettc ottnows ot ryyueecatarirsso. n<br />
This w s raphically aeronstrate to me yestraay at Ulsan, where<br />
I ' vas Invited to inspect some of your flourishing new. industries.<br />
I am quite suIre amtqhueiree is ean sT entuhian e tahn d a justified ride in these<br />
-~ hav3cretesridein these<br />
achievements and I can sense that they hava creqtd a new feeling<br />
of self-confidence and self-reliance throughout your country.<br />
I have also had an opportunity to admire the disciplined<br />
efficiency and toughness of your :-armed forces. It is not difficult to<br />
see how they have earned their considerable reputation as fighting<br />
; miehno: areI nkonwow setrhvaitn gt hweyi the njtohye m thine rtheesp erecst isotaf nocuer Aouf stcormalmiuanni stforces,<br />
terrorism and agression in Vietnam.<br />
Finally, Mr. Prime Minister let me say I have drawn reat<br />
encourayement from the several frank Aiscussions th4t I have ha in<br />
these three days with your President and with you and your Ministers.<br />
I shall go awa reassured by the close similarity of our views on<br />
the issues that oear upon the future peace and prosperity of the<br />
KAosriaena aanndd APaucsitfriacl iare, giaorne, waonrdk inbgy tthowea . tcrodsn vtihcet iosna met haetn dsb. oth of us,<br />
I could ask you to convey to His Excellency, President Park,<br />
the good wishes of all ustralians and my compliments for all that<br />
has been achieved in Korea under his inspired leadership.<br />
once again Ttoh ey oug, r atMerf. u lP ritmhea nkMs inoifs tMerr, s . anHdo ltt o anMdr s. m yCsheulnf g, an dI meyx ppreasrsty for<br />
all your many kindnesses to us. This has been a wonderful experience.<br />
Toodbye to you all, and may our friendship continue to prosper. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
