<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9153</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP LUNCHEON FOR THE PRIME MINISTER OF THE SOLOMON ISLANDS THE HON FRANCIS HILLY, MP, PARLIAMENT HOUSE CANBERRA MONDAY, 14 MARCH 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/03/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009153.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING, MP<br />
LUNCHEON FOR THE PRIME MINISTER OF THE SOLOMON ISLANDS,<br />
THE HON FRANCIS HILLY, MP, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA,<br />
MONDAY, 14 MARCH 1994<br />
It is my great pleasure to welcome to Australia the Head of Government of<br />
the Solomon Islands.<br />
I have been looking forward to seeing Mr Hilly in Australia later this year,<br />
when the South Pacific Forum meets in Brisbane.<br />
In fact I have already had the pleasure of seeing Mr Hilly at the forum in<br />
Nauru last year, and at CHOGM in Cyprus.<br />
However, those are not really occasions for bilateral discussions such as we<br />
have enjoyed this morning.<br />
Australia welcomes talks with the Solomon Islands of the warm and friendly<br />
nature we had today. They enable us to, explore issues of concern to both<br />
countries in some greater depth than a multilateral occasion.<br />
At the forum, I have no doubt Mr Hilly and I will have the opportunity to<br />
address regional matters which concern each of us.<br />
That is the Pacific way.<br />
But neighbours in the region must have opportunities to talk within the<br />
framework of their own relationship in this case, a relationship of great<br />
warmth which Australia values highly.<br />
I particularly welcome the fact that on this visit, Prime Minister, you are<br />
accompanied by a trade and investment delegation from the Solomon<br />
Islands.<br />
And that you and the delegation will be exploring ways to expand trade and<br />
investment opportunities, with a special emphasis on tourism. 4961<br />
I J </p>
<p>In my first few months as Prime Minister I had the opportunity of visiting<br />
Honiara to take part in the South Pacific Forum, which happily coincided with<br />
the 15th anniversary of the independence of the Solomon Islands.<br />
While my time was mostly confined to the capital itself, I saw enough of<br />
Guadalcanal and the surrounding waters to recognise the value of your<br />
attractive environment and the tremendous potential it offers in the long term<br />
for tourism.<br />
As I said at last year's forum in Nauru, the promotion of the private sector and<br />
the development of export industries will be fundamental to the Pacific's<br />
future economic prospects.<br />
Your initiative, Prime Minister, in bringing this business delegation to<br />
Australia is a concrete and helpful step in this context.<br />
As you know, trade between us is heavily weighted in my country's favour.<br />
That is not uncomfortable for Australia, but we are prepared to help in<br />
encouraging Australian companies to trade with, and invest in, the Solomon<br />
Islands. Your government's commitment to economic reform is, in this regard, most<br />
welcome. The path to economic reform is not easy. I know that because the Australian<br />
government has been following it for a decade.<br />
But success in economic reform should also open up opportunities for<br />
Australian business, to the benefit of both nations.<br />
However trade links are only one facet of our bilateral relationship.<br />
Australia is your neighbour in the South Pacific, and we consider the region<br />
we share to be of vital importance in our foreign policy and security<br />
objectives. My appointment of Gordon Bilney as Minister for Pacific Island Affairs reflects<br />
the Australian Government's desire to give even closer attention to the<br />
region. We will be providing some $ 11 million this financial year to help, in particular,<br />
with education and training.<br />
We also maintain strong links through the Defence Co-operation Program. I<br />
enjoyed very much visiting the patrol boat base at Honiara in 1992, and<br />
Australia is very pleased to have provided two Pacific patrol boats to help<br />
your government protect its valuable fisheries.<br />
4962 </p>
<p>We also enjoy excellent people to people contacts, and your invitation to the<br />
business leaders who have accompanied you will help promote them.<br />
I have been looking forward, as I said, to welcoming you to Australia again for<br />
the 25th South Pacific Forum in Brisbane in August, which represents<br />
another aspect of the relationship between our two countries.<br />
I trust we can have a useful discussion there of the economic challenges<br />
facing all of us in the region, looking in particular at how to make the best use<br />
of our resources.<br />
But I also trust that our bilateral talks this morning have been as useful to you<br />
as they have been to me.<br />
And I trust that your current visit to Australia is both useful and enjoyable. 4963 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
