<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8220</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERNECE, ST MARYS MEMORIAL HALL, ST MARYS, SYDNEY - 30 NOVEMBER 1990</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/11/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008220.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, ST MARYS MEMORIAL HALL,<br />
ST MARYS, SYIDNEY-30 NOVEMBER 1990<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: Could I just ask you for your reaction to the<br />
United Nations resolution authorising the use of force post<br />
January the<br />
PM: Well I -think it's important that the Security Council<br />
has shown such a great sense of purpose the vote is 12/ 2<br />
with only Cuba and Yemen going against them and China<br />
abstaining. So that should be now a very, very strong<br />
signal to Saddam Hussein that the world is not going to<br />
tolerate his forceful annexation of Kuwait and that, I hope,<br />
will be the great outcome of the Council resolution. I<br />
don't see it in terms of saying well here is the signal for<br />
war. I see iLt as a signal, a strong determined signal to<br />
the leadershiLp of Iraq saying what you've done is not<br />
acceptable. The world is not going to tolerate it. What we<br />
want you to do is to withdraw. Only in that sense to<br />
understand that if you will not withdraw, if you will not<br />
meet the reaSonable demands of the rest of the world then<br />
take notice that the world may in those circumstances<br />
reluctantly be required to use force to ensure that the wish<br />
of the world for peaceful and normal processes to be<br />
followed will be, in fact, followed.<br />
JOURNALIST: inaudible<br />
PM: Just lei: me finish. So what I want to emphasise<br />
therefore is that how I see this, how the Australian<br />
Government sees this is an important signal that an<br />
unmistakeablE! signal, we hope, that perhaps up until now<br />
Saddam Hussein has believed that the world is not serious in<br />
its condemnation of what he has done in declaring that<br />
unacceptability. I hope that now he will see it and that<br />
the interests of the people of Iraq, in the interests of the<br />
people of reg~ ion, and the interests of people of the world,<br />
require and demand his total withdrawal and the release of<br />
all hostages. If that happens then of course if Iraq<br />
believes it has any cause for arguments with Kuwait in<br />
regard to any matters then let that be done peacefully.<br />
There are means available within the international community<br />
for that to be done.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, to the Gulf?<br />
PM: Well I've indicated that I'll be making a statement to<br />
the Parliamen~ t on Tuesday and that will be a considered </p>
<p>statement which will take into account the implications of<br />
this Security Council Resolution.<br />
JOURNALIST: Have you spoken to Mr Bush about this latest<br />
resolution, Mr Hawke?<br />
PM: No.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, Saddam Hussein has ignored<br />
every previous signal that's been sent by the world<br />
community. What makes you think that he will take any<br />
notice of this time?<br />
PM: Well thi~ s is different in kind. The previous<br />
resolutions of the Security Council have been ones that have<br />
indicated tha~ t sanctions will be imposed, they have been<br />
imposed and there is the assumption before that Article 51<br />
of the United Nations Charter of itself would be enough to<br />
authorise action and that is the sustainable legal view.<br />
But now what we have is a very specific decision by the<br />
United Nations Security Council, the supreme body of the<br />
United Nations, making a very, very clear and determined<br />
statement that if by a particular period he doesn't withdraw<br />
then the parties are specifically authorised to use force.<br />
Now that is a. much stronger, much more specific resolution<br />
than has ever been passed before. As I say I do hope very<br />
sincerely that he will understand now that here is a<br />
statement of the world's intention and that his own<br />
interests and the interests of his own people are best<br />
served by complying with the decision.<br />
JOURNALIST: Is it possible that Australian troops will now<br />
be requested to go to the Gulf?<br />
PM: I don't anticipate that that request would be made.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you anticipate any increase in the size of<br />
Australia's.. PM: Look I'll be making a statement to the Parliament on<br />
Tuesday, a considered statement. I'll have the opportunity<br />
JOURNALIST: inaudible<br />
PM: Well just a minute. Then I'll have the opportunity of<br />
having a discussion with my Party and my Cabinet about this<br />
and that's when the statement will be made and I'm not<br />
pre-empting it.<br />
JOURNALIST: Is that one of the things under consideration?<br />
PM: I'm not pre-empting the statement.<br />
JOURNALIST: inaudible.<br />
PM: I beg your pardon.<br />
JOURNALIST: WJhat recycling schemes do you have up and<br />
running in The Lodge? </p>
<p>PM: They have quite significant ones there I understand.<br />
I'm informed of them and I'm sure they are carried out. I<br />
mean, I don't, on a personal day to day sense, go and empty<br />
the bins myself and carry it through.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, turning, if we can, to the<br />
recession. It's the people who live around here and similar<br />
places all over Australia who are suffering as a result.<br />
What do you have to say to them to make them more optimistic<br />
than they are?<br />
PM: Well firstly, I want to say these things. Firstly, I<br />
haven't denied that in terms of the impact on people's lives<br />
that they've been in a recessionary situation. We just want<br />
to make perfectly clear that all that we have been saying in<br />
terms of tech~ nically acknowledging the recession is that<br />
it's two successive quarters of negative growth which<br />
technically will meet the definition of a recession. But<br />
that hasn't been the important thing as far as I'm concerned<br />
because I've understood that people have been suffering.<br />
But what I want to be understood is this; that we could not<br />
as a Government allow to go on what was happening 18 months<br />
ago where a very simple statistic, you had expenditure going<br />
at 10h per cent per annum and production at five per cent.<br />
You can't as a community, as a society and as an economy<br />
allow that to go on and so we had to slow the economy down<br />
so that we have got a position where we can, out of our own<br />
production, satisfy our own needs and also provide enough<br />
for export. So we had to slow the economy down. We've done<br />
that. In the process, of course, there's been some pain.<br />
The next thing that has to be understood is this; that if we<br />
hadn't taken that decision as a Government to slow the<br />
economy down, then the world would've imposed upon us a much<br />
harsher resolution of the economic problems facing this<br />
country. So what we've had to do is to slow activity down.<br />
That's meant some hurt for businesses and for individuals.<br />
But we now have a situation where in the judgement of the<br />
Government we will see in next year, 1991, economic<br />
recovery, but: on a much firmer basis. Remember this, that<br />
what we have now cemented into the Australian economy is<br />
declining inflation, we've significantly lowered interest<br />
rates and we have a situation also where wages are under<br />
control so that as we come out of the recession, in the next<br />
year, then we will have much more sustainable growth. We<br />
are not going, to have inflation going crazy, we're not<br />
having wages crazy. We'll have a more competitive economy.<br />
We're going to, as a total Australian community, understand<br />
that we've got to be producing more and the increase in our<br />
production has got to be greater than the increase in our<br />
expenditure so that we can live within our means and build<br />
up our exports so that we'll be internationally competitive.<br />
We're well on the way to doing that.<br />
JOURNALIST: that blame for the recession.<br />
PM: It's not a question of blame. We accept the<br />
responsibility of Government for running the economy. We<br />
made the decisions, we made the decisions of a tight fiscal<br />
policy, tight monetary policy which meant a slowing down. </p>
<p>We were, it was the Government that was responsible. We had<br />
to bring about that position where the relationship between<br />
our production and our expenditure was acceptable. Of<br />
course it was Government policy.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you think those words are any comfort to the<br />
people who live out here because this is a particularly bad<br />
hit area? They're the ones who<br />
PM: Let me say this. You've been following me this<br />
morning, I think. You've been around me, you've seen I<br />
haven't been in an iron lung. I've been amongst the people<br />
on the street, you saw the reception I got, didn't you? You<br />
saw the reception I got, wherever I've been. I don't think<br />
you'd call it a hostile reception, would you?<br />
JOURNALIST: No.<br />
PM: No. I don't feel complacent about that. I mean, I<br />
know that people have been hurt but I also think that the<br />
Australian people are not giving the Government great ticks<br />
of approval at the moment. Nevertheless I think they do<br />
understand the very I mean you don't have to be a<br />
professional economist to know that where we had the economy<br />
increasing its expenditure by 10h per cent and only<br />
increasing its production by 5 per cent, that was going to<br />
create an Australia which was totally unstainable in which<br />
the world would've descended on like a pack of bricks. So<br />
we ourselves had to slow activity down. Now that means that<br />
when we come out of it in 1991 we're going to do it from a<br />
much stronger-basis. As you know in respect of those who<br />
are the least protected in the community, this Government<br />
has revolutionised social welfare provisions in the<br />
community, both in terms of pensions, unemployment benefits,<br />
in terms of training programs for the unemployed, to open up<br />
opportunities for them. This Government has done more.<br />
It's recognised within this country by all the welfare<br />
organisations that we've done more to make sure that there's<br />
0 not just a safety net there for people who are hurt. But<br />
much more important, as well as the safety net, is the range<br />
of training and retraining programs which will mean that the<br />
least advantaged are going to be put in a position where, as<br />
the economy recovers they'll be able to be part of that<br />
recovery. JOURNALIST: On that score, with unemployment rocketing up,<br />
as Graham Richardson put it yesterday, will you rethink the<br />
budget proposal to provide a four week delay in the<br />
provision of unemployment benefits for people with assets of<br />
over $ 5,000, as requested by ACOSS?<br />
PM: Well the! Ministers responsible are always in a position<br />
where if they want to bring to Cabinet a particular proposal<br />
for a review of any particular situation in the light of the<br />
way the economy and the society is developing, they are in a<br />
position to do that. Of course, if such a proposal is<br />
brought forward it would be considered by the Cabinet. But<br />
at this stage! I'm not saying that's what will happen. It's<br />
a matter for decision by the Ministers as to whether, in<br />
their judgemetnt, any particular decision that's been made in </p>
<p>the past in different circumstances, needs review. If they<br />
make that judgement then the Cabinet will consider it.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do we have the manufacturing capacity, Mr<br />
Hawke, to get ourselves out of this, to pay our own way?<br />
PM: Well we're improving that capacity. If you look at the<br />
situation over the last 12 months the figures are<br />
interesting in regard to exports. We had a rise of 8.1 per<br />
cent in exports over the last year to September. We are<br />
gradually creating a more competitive manufacturing sector.<br />
I mean, one of the things that I find most exciting as I go<br />
around the country is to go to enterprises which are in fact<br />
competing in the most, you know, toughly competitive markets<br />
in the world.. We are doing that. That's not something<br />
that's going to happen overnight where the whole of<br />
manufacturing industry is so competitive. It is happening<br />
and it's not happening by happenstance or by accident. It's<br />
happening because we have now, under the policies of this<br />
Government, seen a massive re-equipment and re-investment in<br />
Australian manufacturing industries. Secondly, we are<br />
seeing massive changes in work practices in the<br />
manufacturing establishments of this country. That's under<br />
the aegis of the Accord with the whole restructuring program<br />
that's going on. Now we need new attitudes of management,<br />
we need new attitudes of the workforce, those are gradually<br />
being seen. There is a reflection in the increased level of<br />
exports that we are becoming more competitive but none of us<br />
governments, business or trade unions can rest on our<br />
laurels. We've just got to continue to create an Australia<br />
where our manufacturing sectors in areas where we can be<br />
competitive. We'll never be able to have the mass<br />
manufacturing of motor cars like the United States or Japan<br />
but we can go in, there are a great number of niche areas<br />
where the highly trained and skilled and flexible Australian<br />
workforce can compete. Let me give you examples of it so<br />
you can understand what I'm saying. We have an enterprise<br />
in Adelaide, for instance, which is manufacturing lenses.<br />
That's gone into the tough competitive United States market<br />
competing against about 11 or 12 other countries and we've<br />
got over half* the market. Now that's something that an<br />
enterprise in Adelaide has set down, their own research<br />
work, their oiwn management and co-operative trade union<br />
movement operating there, is producing a competitive<br />
product. We can do it. You look at steel. When we came to<br />
office in 198.3 they were going to close the steel industry<br />
down. That's what they were going to do. But now as a<br />
result of co-operation from my Government with the steel<br />
industry plan., new attitudes of management, and new<br />
attitudes of the trade union. I mean, it's an eye-opener.<br />
Go into BHP now and see the attitude of management and<br />
workers. Instead of a closed down steel industry that I was<br />
going to inherit we've now got a steel industry which is<br />
exporting massively around the world. So we can do it.<br />
JOURNALIST: are still high though<br />
PM: I beg your pardon. </p>
<p>6.<br />
JOURNALIST: Imports are still high and there's talk of<br />
layoffs in the manufacturing industry. Has the pain been<br />
worth it? We're now in a recession.<br />
PM: Well pain when you ask a question is pain worth it,<br />
at the moment when pain is being suffered by the person<br />
suffering it they are going to say well no I don't like it,<br />
it hasn't been worth it. But if you look at it overall and<br />
you ask yourself the question; are we going to come out in<br />
1991 with an economy with lowered levels of inflation, lower<br />
interest rates, a more competitive structure, and the answer<br />
to those questions is; yes we're going to come out with<br />
those things. Then it will mean that Australia will be more<br />
efficient and more competitive and that more opportunities<br />
will be opening up. Just remember this when you're talking<br />
about employment, remember the statistics, now you're<br />
looking at the fact now that there's a growth in<br />
unemployment, an increase in the unemployment benefit<br />
recipient. rrhe fact is that under my Government, for the<br />
whole of it's period, we've had employment growth five times<br />
faster, remember that, five times faster than when the<br />
conservatives were in there in the previous seven years.<br />
We've also had employment growth twice as fast as the rest<br />
of the world. Now that's happened, not by accident, but<br />
it's happened~ because we've had a wages policy which has<br />
contained wages, the trade union movement has accepted<br />
improvements in the social wage rather than increases in<br />
money wages and that's made us more competitive. Those<br />
things could not have happened, we couldn't have had 1.6<br />
million new jobs, it's what we've created, with 90 per cent<br />
of them in the private sector, unless you'd had the relevant<br />
government policies. Now the unfortunate thing, of course,<br />
is that in that period which they talking about, up to 18<br />
months ago, we were going ahead that strongly that our<br />
demand, the demand of the community was exceeding our<br />
capacity to produce and we therefore had to slow it down.<br />
The employment record of this Government is second to none<br />
in the world.<br />
JOURNALIST: Would you enjoy the prospect, just changing<br />
focus again, enjoy the prospect of going to visit the<br />
sailors in the Gulf?<br />
PM: Well, ofE course, that would depend, the possibility of<br />
that would depend upon the circumstances. I simply you<br />
will have seen some reference in the media that we had some<br />
contemplation of that but with this deadline now of the<br />
of January that creates a new ballpark. I don't really want<br />
to say anything more about the Gulf issue and the<br />
Government's reaction until I make the statement on Tuesday<br />
in the House.<br />
JOURNALIST: that you'll go.<br />
PM: Look let me leave that till Tuesday, will you? I mean,<br />
it was talked about-in a different situation the possibility<br />
of seeing them because we were going to be in Europe about<br />
that time and obviously if the circumstances were convenient<br />
then, obviously, I'd like to see our people there, our<br />
fellows on the ship. I'd certainly like to see them if that </p>
<p>7.<br />
were possiblE! but we've got a new sort of situation which<br />
must be considered now.<br />
JOURNALIST: Will you be reviewing with Cabinet, before your<br />
statement next Tuesday, the level of our forces in the area?<br />
PM: We'll bEl considering the whole issue of the situation<br />
in the Gulf i~ n the light of the Security Council Resolution.<br />
I'm not goincf to pre-empt anything that will be in that<br />
statement by any off-hand comments now. These are matters<br />
of very, very grave importance for this country and we are<br />
not going to be flippant or ill-considered in our treatment<br />
of them. ThE! people will expect from me a considered<br />
statement and they will get it from me in the Parliament<br />
next Tuesday.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you think high interest rates might impact<br />
on Labor voting in areas like Roger Price's and Ross Free's?<br />
PM: I expect: that the people in areas like this will, when<br />
the election comes, they'll make the judgement as to whether<br />
their best interests are served by the Hawke Labor<br />
Government or an Opposition. They will take into account<br />
what has happened in regard to their employment<br />
opportunities. They will say; well is it an accident that<br />
under Hawke employment's increased five times faster than it<br />
did under thE! Tories. They'll ask themselves too the<br />
question about the educational opportunity for their kids<br />
they'll say; well, when Hawkie came to government only one<br />
in three of the kids stayed on in school because the Tories<br />
haven't got any interest in equality of educational<br />
opportunities;. They'll say, now, after 7h years of Hawke<br />
Labor Government it's not one in three of the kids it's two<br />
in three and that's because the Hawke Labor Government has<br />
put the money into the pockets of the lower and lower to<br />
middle income! families so that they can keep their kids in<br />
school. They'll also remember the chaos in the medical and<br />
health sphere-. Before I came to government the threat of<br />
illness or hospitalisation was an absolute disaster for the<br />
people of this area, they simply didn't have the cover. But<br />
now every single Australian is covered through Medicare. No<br />
Australian has now to worry about the threat of illness or<br />
hospitalisati~ on. These things education, health, the<br />
creation of -obs, the elimination of pensions for<br />
millionaires so that people who really need help. They'll<br />
remember that:. They'll remember the fact that when we came<br />
to office we had a taxation system which was the most unfair<br />
tax system in the world, where the wealthy didn't have to<br />
pay tax, it was a matter of choice whether they paid tax.<br />
We make them pay tax now so that we've been able to reduce<br />
the tax burden for the mass of people. These are the things<br />
that they'll remember and these are the reasons why when the<br />
election come s we'll be returned again.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
