<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4176</transcript-id>
    <title>JOINT PRESS STATEMENT - GOVERNMENT/EMPLOYER TALKS</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/07/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004176.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
JOINT PRESS STATEMENT GOVIERNMENT/ EMPLOYER TALKS<br />
Representatives of the Government and the National Employers'<br />
Policy Committee comprising the Associated Chambers of<br />
Manufactures of Australia, Australian Council of Employeis'<br />
Federations, Metal Trades Industry Associati on, Australian<br />
Mines and Metals Association, Australian 1-oolgrowers' and<br />
Graziers' Council and Australian Bankers' Association -met<br />
in Canberra today.<br />
The meeting was chaired by the Prime Minister and attended by<br />
the Treasurer, the Minister for Primary Industry, the Minister<br />
for Employment and Industrial Relations, and the minister for<br />
Business and Consumer Affairs.<br />
The employer representatives were led by Mr Max Dillon, Chairman<br />
of the National Employers' Policy Committee. A list of those<br />
attending is attached.<br />
The discussions, which ranged over the economic situation,<br />
industrial relations and economic policies were frank and<br />
productive. It was agreed that similar discussions are desirable<br />
from time to time.<br />
THE ECONOMY<br />
There was unanimous agreement that in formulating its economic<br />
policies the Government should continue to give the control of<br />
inflation the highest priority.<br />
In this connection it was recognised that continuing high<br />
inflation was the major bar to sustained economic recovery<br />
and the reduction ' of unemployment. Particular stress was laid<br />
on the implications of current inflation rates continuing for<br />
Australia's international competitiveness, </p>
<p>Jobs, and indeed the whole future of the Australian economy,<br />
were being progressively threatened. Under these circumstances<br />
there is growing evidence of Australian industry movi-ng its<br />
production and employment to other countries where costs are<br />
lower. This is a cause of great concern to employers and the<br />
Government. There was general agreement that these facts<br />
needed to be more widely appreciated by the Australian community,<br />
particularly within the wage-bargaining context.<br />
The employer representatives stressed their wish to see early<br />
implementation of the remaining aspects of the Mathews Committee<br />
recommendations pertaining to company taxation.<br />
Ministers noted the existence of technical problems in the<br />
implementation of the Mathews Report and indicated that early<br />
discussions between Ministers and their advisers, on the one<br />
hand, and experts from a wide range of industry groups on the<br />
other hand, have been arranged.<br />
More generally,* the Government spelt out clearly the constraints<br />
upon it in making its Budget decisions, and these were fully<br />
recognised by the employers.<br />
The employers pointed out the need for the Government to recognise<br />
the high degree of dependence of certain industries on Government<br />
orders and that in adopting policies to reduce expenditure this<br />
should be understood. They made the point that of equal<br />
importance to the size of the deficit was its composition.<br />
However, they acknowledged that, in line with the over-riding<br />
need to give priority to reducing inflation, there was a clear<br />
need to hold the Budget deficit to below the level of that for<br />
1975/ 76.<br />
EM4PLOYMENT Subject to the recognised. need to reduce the deficit, employers<br />
indicated a desire for action to stimulate economic recovery<br />
and increase employment generally. They underlined the special<br />
problem of unemployment among young people. </p>
<p>The Government agreed that there should be discussions between<br />
the Department of Employment and Industrial Relations and<br />
representatives of employers on this matter.<br />
POLICY<br />
. hi employers stressed the serious consequences of continued<br />
Lncreases in costs. These include not only costs of labour, but<br />
.:; vcrnnent charges, including State Government charges.<br />
In this connection, particular attention was drawn not merely to<br />
. approaching National Wage Case, but also to major claims<br />
i-pending, including one for shorter hours in the power industry.<br />
' e employers indicated that the statistics of industrial<br />
ppages showed the extent of pressures being placed on individual<br />
r.-' ployers and the economy, and underlined the need for firm<br />
vernment policies in this area.<br />
S TCES JUSTIFICATION TRIBUNAL<br />
.' he employers indicated their view that, in the present economic<br />
chrcumnstances, the Prices Justification Tribunal could be retained<br />
in the interests of maintaining a climate for wage restraint.<br />
would, however, be suggesting some modifications in its<br />
'.. rter. It was agreed that there should be further detailed<br />
S'. cus;. ions between employer representatives and the Minister for<br />
and Consumer Affairs.<br />
IING TRIBUNALS<br />
S" -ploycrs considered that there were important wage cost<br />
S"' t.. ences stemming from the multiplicity of industrial<br />
They urged the Government to rationalise the<br />
S" erts within the Commonwealth's own jurisdiction.<br />
-L'rTICES put strongly their view that if they were to be<br />
restraints in respect of trade practices, the unions<br />
S" " e exempt. </p>
<p>SHIPBUILDING It was noted that disd ssions were proceeding on the<br />
shipbuilding industry, an industry which is endangered by<br />
low productivity and intense import contribution.<br />
2 July 1976 l 0 </p>
<p>NATIONAL LEVEL DISCUSSITONS BV",--; EBN THE GOVERN' ENT<br />
AND REPRESEN. TATIVES OF TIl ENPLOYERS<br />
PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBE-1i111 2 JULY 1976<br />
ATTENDANCE<br />
GOVERNMENT The Rt Hon Malcolm Fraser, MP, Prime Minister<br />
The Hon P R Lynch, MP, Treasurer<br />
The Hon I McC Sinclair, MP, Minister for Primary Industry<br />
The Hon A A Street, MP, Minister for Employment and<br />
Industrial Relations<br />
The Hon J W Howard, MP, Minister for Business and Consumer<br />
Affairs<br />
The Permanent Heads and senior officers of the Departments of<br />
Prime Minister and Cabinet, Treasury, Employment and Industrial<br />
Relations, Business and Consumer Affairs, and Industry and<br />
Commerce also attended.<br />
The Chairman of the Public Service Board and the' Chairman of the<br />
Prices Justification Tribunal were also present.<br />
EMPLOYERS<br />
The following representatives of the National Employers' Policy<br />
Committee comprising the Associated Chambers of Manufactures<br />
of Australia, the Australian Council of Employers' Federations,<br />
the Metal Trades Industry Association, the Australian Woolgrowers'<br />
and Graziers' Council, and the Australian Bankers' Association<br />
were present: </p>
<p>Mr M Dillon<br />
Mr A N Edwards<br />
Mr S G W Burston, O. B. E.<br />
Mr F F Espie<br />
Mr T B C Bell, A. O.<br />
Mr G Polites, M. B. E.<br />
Mr R Fry<br />
Mr N Mason<br />
Mr E Cole -Chairman, National Employers' Policy<br />
Committee Past President<br />
of the Australian Council of<br />
Employers' Federations<br />
President of the Associated Chambers<br />
of Manufactures of Australia<br />
-National President, Metal Trades<br />
Industry Association<br />
Australian Woolgrowers' and Graziers'<br />
Council<br />
-Immediate Past President, Australian<br />
Mines and Metals Association; Deputy<br />
Chairman, Conzinc Riotinto Australia Ltd<br />
-Chairman, Australian Bankers'<br />
Association; Group General Manager',<br />
The National Bank of Australasia Ltd<br />
Secretary, Executive<br />
Director, A. C. E. F.<br />
National Director and Chief Executive,<br />
M. T. I. A.<br />
Director, Chamber of Manufactures of<br />
New South Wales<br />
Chief Industrial Officer, A. W. G. C.<br />
SECRETARIAT<br />
Messrs B J Hodgetts, G C Burke and G W McGill,<br />
Department of Employment and Industrial Relations.<br />
6 . t<br />
IY-I I 1 -I </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
