<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6771</transcript-id>
    <title>NATION WIDE CONSULTATION WITH YOUTH COMMUNITY</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/10/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006771.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>PORIME MINISTER<br />FORMEDI 29 OCTOBER 1985<br />The Federal1 Government will conduct a nation-wide consultation<br />with the broad youth community during December.<br />In my Address To The Nation on the Priority One youth strategy<br />I undertook to consult with young Australians to review the<br />strategy. The Government has decided that the most effective m~ eans of<br />consulting the broad youth community is through youth media<br />outlets. In early December I will participate in a number of talk-back<br />sessions on youth radio stations throughout Australia.<br />These sessions will launch a national phone-in campaign with<br />young people using toll-free telephones to make their views<br />known on issues of concern to them.<br />The operators taking the calls will code the answers and feed<br />them into a computer terminal.<br />The computer process will allow statistical analyses to be<br />undertaken relatively quickly.</p>
<p><br />The project, which is being co-ordinated by the office of Youth Affairs, will allow the Government to establish the relationships<br />between young people's concerns and the Government's current strategy. I take the opportunity now to invite young Australians to use<br />this opportunity to exercise a direct influence on the processes of Government.</p>
<p><br />The details of the process will be advertised over the next few weeks to ensure that as many young people as possible are <br />made aware of it.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
