<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>12063</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTERTHE HON JOHN HOWARD MPINTERVIEW WITH THE MORNING CREW,RADIO B105 FM, BRISBANE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/11/2001</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Subjects: federal election 2001.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
Prime Minister John Howard, good morning and welcome again.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well it';s great to be back.  Look that question you had a moment about who won this years Melbourne Cup, can you do that for this election?  I mean I';d like to know who won this election.  It would save me a whole lot of nervous tension over the next four or five days.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
Is it as close as they say because the headlines in the Sunday papers here that Labor had edged in front.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well the polls are, there';s a whole variety of polls, some of them…they';re very even handed the polls.  Some are for us and some are for them so there';s a little bit for everybody but I think it will be quite close.  The preference deal that the Labor Party';s sown up with the Greens and the Democrats will help them.  So the Coalition will need to get a very high primary vote in order to win because we are not going to do very well out of Green and Democrat preferences.  I mean mind you, people who vote Green and Democrat don';t have to follow the how to vote advice of their party, they can give their preferences to us and I invite all of them listening to the programme to do so without exception.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
The last election we had here was just an absolute Labor landslide.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
The state one, yes.  I don';t think it';ll…. I don';t see that being repeated here in Queensland on Saturday.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
We do have the shock weapon of course, who visited our studio just recently, in your very own Treasurer.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I saw the performance.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
Do you want to hear it because we can play it for you.  Put your headphones on there and have a listen to this, this is your Treasurer.<br />
“I work all night, I work all day, I';m Treasurer most every day.  That ain';t bad.  My name is Pete, you must like me, you must like the GST. It';s not a fad.”<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
Now you know what I found with him?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I thought that was pretty good.  I still think he should hand onto the job I';ve given him.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
Is that what you said to him?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Actually I thought it pretty gusty.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
Me too.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Full marks.  But I tell you what they';re the sort of things that Treasurers, deputy leaders do.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
Well too many people take themselves too seriously, as he left the studio he did mumble to himself I know I';m going to regret that.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
No he shouldn';t, can I tell you he shouldn';t, I don';t think any loses any…. I mean you have a go. It';s really a question with those sorts of things you never do anything you feel uncomfortable about.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
Good.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
So I';m not singing.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
Just setting you up because we have something for you to do.  We do have a challenge for you.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
If you';re asked to do something you feel comfortable with, that';s alright.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
Let me ask you this, do you feel comfortable with corridor cricket?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
You know if I';m bowling and you';re batting.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
Are you a bowler?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well look I sort of…. I';ll roll my arm over.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
Okay you don';t want to bat?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
No you bat.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
What if I take your glasses, would you bat still?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well if you bat you might shatter mine.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
Okay well, we';re going to take you outside for some crew corridor cricket.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Yeah, there';ll be no questions?  That';s good.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
I';ll ask you a question.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
No, no don';t bother.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
If you were on a deserted island with one of these women who would you set up camp with?  One; Pauline Hanson, two: Cheryl Kernot, three; Ita Buttrose, or four; Bob Brown?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I';d take my mobile with me and I';d ring Janette.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
Safe answer.  There will be more questions outside, we';re playing corridor cricket with the PM in just a few minutes.  It';s the B105 morning crew, he's done it at Manuka oval but he';ll be doing it in the corridors of power, B105 power, in a couple of minutes.<br />
[commercial break]<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
In the corridors of B105 we';re about to … what';s happening down the pitch, we';re having a cricket game, the Prime Minister John Howard is going to bowl to Jamie, he elected to bowl rather than bat so Jamie faces the first delivery.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
Mr Prime Minister can you see the stumps?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I won the toss and sent him in.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
Okay.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Bit worried about those bails, they seem stuck on.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
I superglued them on.  Bowls….fielded by the PM off his own bowling, beautifully done sir.  Before you bowl the next one we have a quick question to you Mr PM from Robyn Bailey who';s done the pitch report already.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
Okay now politics, which of these movies best describes Kim Beazley';s political career?  Is it A; Raging Bull, B; Elephant Man, C; Jaws, or D; Shrek?<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
Raging Shrek.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Probably Shrek.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
Okay Shrek it is, the PM is giving some work to the ball… it';s hit the back of a journalist, the back of a journalist';s head, a journalist is down.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
Okay Mr Prime Minister, a personal question.  Peter Costello recently sang ABBA';s money, money, money for us.  If you had a choice of song which would it be?  A; Power and the Passion, B; You';re Not the Boss of Me, C; Semi-Charmed Life, or D; We will Rock You?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Oh, We Will Rock You.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
Bit of a groover there PM.<br />
Okay that was a bit overpitched, how do you think your style';s going so far sir?<br />
And a cameraman from Channel Nine is now chasing the ball.<br />
Okay there we go, the ball has been returned to the Prime Minister.  Do you have one left in you?  Mr Howard do you have one left in you?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I do indeed.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
Another question.  And the final question Mr Howard, what';s the thing you';d most hate to see on election day?  A; you losing government, B; Beazley losing his pants; or C; Australia losing the first cricket test?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, I think it';s very unlikely that we could lose the first cricket test on the third day.  So I';ll take that one out.  Look I mean obviously losing the election would be…<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
No, go the pants.  It';ll be Beazley';s pants for sure Mr Prime Minister.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
Who';s going to win the election?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I think it';s very tight, I really do, I think that preference deal has made it very hard for us.  But you know we';ll finish strongly and I think they';ll fray at the edges over the illegal boat people and that';s going to hurt them because I don';t think people really think they';re going to hold together on that if they win.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
Okay Mr Howard, we don';t want to get you too out of breath before the election but this is your last delivery at Jamie Dunn.  He';s up to the crease, there it is….beautiful ball, out the back of the hand….<br />
Prime Minister John Howard we thank you very much for your time this morning.  Thank you Mr Howard.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Thank you.<br />
JOURNALI<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Thank you.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
With the B105 morning crew, Prime Minister John Howard good luck for Saturday.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Thank you.<br />
[ends] </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
