<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9754</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J.KEATING MP ADDRESS IN ANZAC PARK, THURSDAY ISLAND, 12 SEPTEMBER 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/09/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009754.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
( 9<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
ADDRESS IN ANZAC PARK, THURSDAY ISLAND, 12 SEPTEMBER 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
Mr Getano Lui ( Chairperson, Torres Strait Regional Authority), Mayor ( Mr<br />
Pedro Stephen), Elders, my friend Mr Ettle Pau ( Torres Strait Ex Servicemen's<br />
Association) who presented a wreath with me, my colleague Peter Dodd,<br />
distinguished members of the community, ladies and gentlemen and boys and<br />
girls. Thank you very much for that wonderful warm welcome this afternoon. I have<br />
always wanted to come to the Torres Strait. I am most happy to be able to<br />
have come as Prime Minister and to come to this beautiful part of Australia.<br />
I have been very moved by the speeches, the things that have been said by<br />
your Mayor, by Miss Bakoi Bon ( high school captain), by Mr Waraka Adidi ( ex<br />
serviceman), by Mr George Mye ( Chairman of Damley Island) and they all say<br />
one thing, I think, and one thing that I certainly agree with and that is to say<br />
that we are all pert of this great country Australia. We are all Australians, we<br />
are Australians together. We will be Australians forever. And, that this great<br />
multicultural country of ours is different in parts. We do have our separate, if<br />
you like, ancestral backgrounds, but we have this commitment to this great<br />
country and this great continent, held in trust for most of us by the Aboriginal<br />
and Torres Strait Islander people of this country. It is now our bounty to enjoy<br />
thanks to this wonderful bequest which you as indigenes of this country have<br />
given us.<br />
I am pleased to be here today. I am pleased to be here with my daughters, so<br />
they can see this part of Australia too and know that the land they grow up in<br />
is one of tolerance, one of equity and one of decency and one of pleasure and<br />
one of frendship and one were the environment matters to us all. The place<br />
we can all enjoy together.<br />
I was particularly drawn by the references to Eddie Mabo. This is, I think, the<br />
right place to say that a good thing was done a couple of years ago. A truth<br />
recognised, a lie overturned when the High Court said that the common law of<br />
this country doesnt simply come from the tradition and customs of people of<br />
European decen It doesnt simply come from the British common law. Now it </p>
<p>2<br />
is said by our highest court that Australia's common law comes from the<br />
traditions and customs of Aboriginal people and Torres Strait Islander people.<br />
So, it means that your customs and your traditions are as much a part of my<br />
common law as they are of your common law. That is, in no stronger way<br />
could it be said we are together and we are one than to say that our customs<br />
and traditions and our cultures and beliefs form part of our common heritage in<br />
our common law. From that law, of course, has sprung an indigenous title<br />
which means you, as a people, are entitled to certain lands that have<br />
traditionally been yours. This is a far greater right to come from the<br />
recognition of your culture than to be given by some statute or act of<br />
Parliament or act of grace or act of giving by a legislator because now it is<br />
yours as an inherent right and perhaps it is late, but better late than never that<br />
we have drawn a line in the sand and said that the lands which you make your<br />
traditional connection with, that are not alienated are yours and we have set<br />
up the processes for it.<br />
The contemporary word was by the High Court, but the contemporary act was<br />
by the Commonwealth Parliament in the Native Title Act and it all started here<br />
in the Torres Strait Island. That is, in recognition of the justice which Eddie<br />
Mabo sought, in seeking it and finding it, he has changed all of our lives and<br />
all of your lives especially.<br />
So, this is, I think, a good thing to ponder. We have got great ground to make<br />
up and there are great social issues that we have to address, but we could<br />
never address those, no act of giving from the Parliament or the Government,<br />
no matter how generous can be as complete or as valuable as the recognition<br />
of our essence as Australians our custom and tradition and law comes as<br />
much from your traditions as it comes from non-indigenous, non-Aboriginal or<br />
Torres Strait Island culture.<br />
This is, in a sense, starting the slate again and the things we want to draw on<br />
it are the things we must do together. I think it does underwrite the fact that<br />
we are all members of the one country and that we are Australians and you<br />
are as important to this Parliament of ours as the people from the regions of<br />
Sydney as I am from or those other great parts of Australia, that we are all<br />
Australians one and we are together. The proof of that is, in fact, the very<br />
sacrifices which we have seen commemorated here today. In the Second<br />
World War where Torres Strait Islanders fought in defence of Australia, fought<br />
in defence of themselves and the rest of us, for the democratic values and the<br />
culture and the tolerance we know our country has, but we knew that the<br />
aggressor would deny us. Today, I give thanks on the part of all Australians<br />
for that sacrifice, for those who suffered and for those who died and I want<br />
that known and understood by all Australians.<br />
Could I say that in speaking about your culture and your rights, George Mye<br />
made reference to the fact that with ATSIC your fear is that the Islander<br />
culture may be subsumed in the greater culture of Aboriginal Australia. This<br />
has always been a risk, but one always believes that again in tolerance and<br />
fairness, this will not be so. But, you are suggesting to us that there be a<br />
Torres Strait Islander Commission. That you receive the funding from the<br />
Commonwe ttl Pariament and not ATSIC and that you decide how this might<br />
oa </p>
<p>3<br />
be spent in the best interests of Torres Strait Islander people. Let me tell you<br />
this is something the Commonwealth Government is prepared to consider.<br />
This is something we are prepared to think about. This, of course, will need<br />
discussions, it will need negotiation with our Aboriginal brothers and sisters to<br />
know that we see that commitment to ATSIC as being a solid and firm one and<br />
yet at the same time, it is possible that we can more adequately perhaps look<br />
after the interests and the culture of Islander people. To see that it is not<br />
subsumed in any Ohe culture Aboriginal or non-Aboriginal.<br />
At any rate, I am pleased to be here today to see the Torres Strait or the part<br />
of it I can see. To come to Thursday Island, to see you as a community, to be<br />
among you, to speak with you and to receive your hospitality. I thank you for<br />
the warmth of it. I most especially thank the children for comning in such<br />
numbers. For all you people who have been so generous in coming to meet<br />
me, my family and my party today, I give you my heartfelt thanks and best<br />
wishes. ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
