<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>307</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R.G. MENZIES AT NEWINGTON COLLEGE, SYDNEY, ON 29TH APRIL 1961</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/04/1961</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000307.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HiON. H. G.<br />
MENZIES AT NEWINGTON COLLEGE, SYDNEY, ON 29TH<br />
APRIL, 1961<br />
Sir, President-General, and ladies and gentlemen:<br />
I want to confess to you that I camne up here with<br />
some doubt as to how I should begin what I hope will pass for a<br />
speech. As I am an old boy of tUesley College in Melbourne,*<br />
your opposite number, I thought that courtesy might require that<br />
I should address you as " Fellow Methodists" ( Applause) And<br />
then I remembered that I am not; I'm a Presbyterian. ThenI<br />
thought, " Well perhaps", having a look at the Chairman, " I might<br />
begin" because it's a good note 1" r-' llow Presbyterians"<br />
Until I found that a man who had lived for years in Scotland<br />
couldn't pronoiinde Y'ackayo Then to my intense interest I'<br />
found that this is really a very diverse audience because just<br />
as I was trying to settle in my own mind the fine points of<br />
doctrine I discovered that we are practically occupied by the<br />
Dalys, the Ryans and the Fitzgoralds] ( Laughter) So I think<br />
I had better avoid any of these doctrinal differences -and ju~ st<br />
address you as " Ladies and gentlemen".<br />
The first thing that I want to do is to apologise to<br />
you. I am, for the only time for a long time, wearing a rather<br />
dashing looking blue shirt some of you may have noticed it.<br />
I think I ought to explain to you how that comes about* This<br />
morning I had to make a television what do you call it<br />
performance, appearanco, show? Anyhow it had something to do<br />
with television. And when you go on television I say thi? for<br />
the benefit of those of you who have been fortunate enough to<br />
escape it they do their best to improve you and of course<br />
for all of us that is very necessary. But one way of<br />
improving you is to get you to wear a blue shirt; apparently<br />
it does something to you. I don't know; I've never got to-the<br />
inner mystery of it. The other thing is that you sit back in a<br />
deep chair, pretend you're your own wife, and have your face<br />
made up! ( Laughter) Very lightly, mind you, very lightly. A<br />
touch here; and a touch there. The effect of it, I want to<br />
tell you at once, is appalling.<br />
I once did a famous political broadcast I hope my<br />
colleague, Mr. Daly, won't object to this a powerful<br />
political broadcast in the last election. And as my hair, a s<br />
you can observe is white, they thought it was necessary to<br />
preserve the distinction where the forehead ended and the hair<br />
b6gan it's not so obvious in his case. So the young woman<br />
put a certain amount of a pale blue substance in my hair and<br />
it did the trick: everybody could tell I did have hair,<br />
instead of being bald. When we left she said to me, " Now" and<br />
I thought she said " wash it out". What she said, as my wife<br />
told me afterwards, was " Brush it out". But I washed it out;<br />
which meant I washed it in! That night I had to speak in a<br />
very, ve ry strong industrial suburb and to see me standing up<br />
there with a blue rinse ( Laughter) must have cost my candidate<br />
quite a number of votes.<br />
Now I referred to ray wife then. I want to refer to<br />
her again. She didn't come back with me to Australia, not<br />
because she ~ sdeserted me, but because she has remained with<br />
my daughter and her children for various reasons, and she's<br />
going to be back on Friday; and she will be very disappointed<br />
indeed that she couldn't be here.<br />
I am delighted to be present on an occasion like<br />
this. It does great honour to the School that the School should<br />
have had this tremendous addition to its buildings; and it<br />
does great honour to the School that it should have named the<br />
additions after Mr. Nesbitt who has worked so valiantly in the </p>
<p>vineyard of this School for so long. ( Applause) Therefore I<br />
regard it as a 7roat privilege.<br />
Furthermore, I always regard it as a particular<br />
privilege to be invited to do something, however small2 of some<br />
notable event in the history of a great Church School.<br />
Because there are two kinds of things that matter in a School<br />
one is that it should have a continuity of education and<br />
tradition and growth; and the other is that it should have a<br />
continuity of the spirit. These are the two things that matter<br />
in a great Church School. Newington, of course, has stood for<br />
them for many, many years.<br />
ilhen I refer to continuity I refer to something that<br />
is very close to ray heart. It may be said by some that this<br />
represents my essential and deplorable conservatism of L. ind. I<br />
don't know. But I am an inmmenso believer in continuity. I am<br />
not a believer in looking at the past because it is dead; but<br />
looking at the past because it is living; looking at the past<br />
because it reminds us that we are in the groat procession of<br />
life. Any man who walked in the procession of life and who<br />
aims at doing anything in life, who is unaware of what went<br />
before him, unaware of the great truths that have come down to<br />
him, is a foolish man. He is essentially, a short-sighted man.<br />
When we were listening to the words of a Paalm my mind<br />
went back to a time, many years ago now, when I first visited<br />
Chequers in Buckinghamshire, the new country home the old<br />
country home, because it is both, of the British Prize<br />
Ministers, a home presented to the nation in the time of Lloyd<br />
George and now occupied as a place of rest and recreation but<br />
in my experience even more of hard work by Prime Ministers<br />
and those who come to see them.<br />
Many years ago I stood on the utmost fringe of the<br />
Chiltern Hills looking down over the Oxford Plains. The man I<br />
was with had a great feeling for the geography and history of<br />
the country. We could just see the spire of the Church at<br />
Great Kemble where John Hampden went down and made his speech<br />
to the gentlemen of Buckinghamshire against ship money and so<br />
began the whole history of the parliamentary control of<br />
finances. We could see the long road that stretches acrosp the<br />
plains, the Roman road from Andover; we could see on the Jides<br />
of the hills the little ancient, almost ibliterated, marks of<br />
the old British trenches put down at the time of the Roman.<br />
invasion. This is the very microcosm of English history, the<br />
most fascinating place in the world.<br />
And my friend said to me, " You know, over there<br />
Hampden was mortally wounded at the Battle of Chalgrove Field<br />
and he rode off the field slowly, with his head dipping, into<br />
the village of Thane just around the corner of the hill. And<br />
he died there. His men brought him up to Hampden House, just<br />
over here on the hill, and up the drive" to which he latQr<br />
took me " and there at nightfall these men, these Roundheads,<br />
with their lanterns in their hands marched the body of John<br />
Hampden up singing the Paalm that ends" I've forgotten these<br />
words, but the reference is to justifying the work of our<br />
hands. I had it in my mind and it slipped away. That's the<br />
Presbyterian coming out, you see.<br />
Now this seemed to me to be the most marvellous<br />
thing. Here was one of the yreat historic events in England<br />
and the very men who took their magnificent leader dead off the<br />
field were thinking and speaking and singing in terms of the<br />
Bible. That hasn't disappeared; that hasn't gone, This is<br />
still one of the great elements in continuity. </p>
<p>3.<br />
Does anybody suppose that every time a great crisis<br />
arrives in the world and sane, Ean is raised up to deal with it<br />
that he is a sudden accident, Was Churchill a sudden<br />
accident? Unexpected? Unreinforced by history? Unconscious<br />
of a sense of continuity? How absurdl If any boy at this<br />
School wants to understand the continuity of great things in the<br />
world, just as I want him to understand the continuity of what<br />
this School stands for, he right take an hour off and read tho'<br />
speeches of the Younger Pitt at the very turn of the 19th<br />
century. Then read the speeches of Churchill in 191+ 0, and 141t<br />
and 142. He will find that although the mode of expression h~ s<br />
changed, as it always does, here are the sane ideas; here is<br />
the splendid eloquent expression of defiance, of strength, of a<br />
sense of continuity, all of which meant we we the people of<br />
Britain, are not to be overthrown by tyrants,<br />
There it is. This is a marvellous thing, the sense<br />
of continuity. And the people who live as if we were here today<br />
and gone tomorrow, I don't envy then I'm sorry for then.<br />
Unless we have a sonse of continuity, unless we know wrhat our<br />
fathers and our grandfathers bestowed on us, what ideas are in<br />
the currents of our minds, almost at the moment of our birth,<br />
we know nothing. We must feel that in our tine just as the<br />
boys of Newington today, I hope, will feel that in their tine<br />
we and they are not only the inheritors but in our oiwn fashion<br />
the creators, the people who continue the tradition, who build<br />
on it, who improve on it, who are not just reactionary in th~ eir<br />
minds, who look forward, who are free in their minds and<br />
enterprising in their thoughts, but who always know the<br />
foundations on which they build. This is, I think -well it is<br />
to me at any rate a stimulating thought on an occasion of<br />
this kind. It is easy enough for the old boys of a School to cone<br />
back and become a little sentimental about when they were at<br />
school, to glorify the wit with which they replied one day to<br />
the Maste r, a wit almost entirely retrospective, to be sayinig<br />
something sentimental about the " good old days" when probably<br />
half of them hated a good deal of it as it occurred, That is<br />
all very well, very agreeable, I do it myself, I'm not being<br />
superior. I can equal anybody in these amiable hypocrisies on<br />
a suitable occasion. In reality however, down in their heapts<br />
they look at the school not in a backward-looking sense, not<br />
0 remembering what a superb foot~ aller Tom was, or what a<br />
wonderful cricketer Jack was, but as something that they<br />
themselves have helped to make in their own time. They won't<br />
say so because they would think that rather pompous. And<br />
therefore I will say it for them: it is something that they<br />
have helped to make.<br />
That is true too, about all the boys who are here,<br />
old and young; truest of the old who are about to leave. But<br />
for all of them true because this is a school that is<br />
established, that was established in the beginning, that<br />
continues to work, realising that you may have all the clevqrness<br />
in the world, you nay have all the scientific skill in' the<br />
world; but the one thing that will save the world will be<br />
civilised minds. And civilised minds are minds conscious of<br />
the past, aware of responsibilities of the future, ard~ above<br />
all with standards in their minds, standards of faitri, standards<br />
of the spirit that will enable them to avoid the bitter wretched<br />
paganisma that has beset the world in the last 50 years.<br />
Sir I want to say no more -I've spoken too long.<br />
But I did want to tell you, so far as icould, what I had in my<br />
mind in accepting this invitation and in telling you how<br />
delighted I am to open, as I now do open, this wing. ( Applause) </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
