<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11236</transcript-id>
    <title>COASTAL SURVEILLANCE TASK FORCE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/04/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The undetected landing on the New South Wales north coast of a vessel</p>
<p> carrying illegal immigrants raises serious issues regarding Australia's</p>
<p> coastal surveillance arrangements which require a prompt response.</p>
<p>I have decided to establish a Prime Ministerial Task Force, to be</p>
<p> chaired by the Secretary of my department, to conduct a thorough review</p>
<p> of the issues involved and to make recommendations to me on the strengthening</p>
<p> of the coastal surveillance procedures and systems.</p>
<p>The terms of reference of the task force are attached. The task force</p>
<p> will include the Chief of the Defence Force, the secretaries of the</p>
<p> departments of Defence and Immigration and Multicultural Affairs,</p>
<p> the CEO of the Australian Customs Service and the Director General</p>
<p> of the Office of National Assessments.</p>
<p>The task force will consider the report currently being prepared for</p>
<p> the government by Air Vice Marshall Alan Heggen (retired) into the</p>
<p> illegal landing of immigrants at Cairns in March and Nambucca Heads</p>
<p> on 10 April. I have asked that AVM Heggen's report be expedited</p>
<p> and that it be concluded by the end of April.</p>
<p>The task force will report its findings to the Government in June</p>
<p> 1999.</p>
<p> 12 April 1999</p>
<p> The task force shall be chaired by the Secretary Department</p>
<p> of the Prime Minister and Cabinet and include:</p>
<p>   * Chief of the Defence Force;</p>
<p>   * Secretary Department of Defence;</p>
<p>   * Secretary Department of Immigration and Multicultural Affairs;</p>
<p>   * Chief Executive Officer Australian Customs Service; and</p>
<p>   * Director General Office of National Assessments.</p>
<p>The task force membership may be expanded if considered appropriate.</p>
<p>The task force will prepare a report on the following matters as they</p>
<p> relate to coastal surveillance:</p>
<p>   * Intelligence gathering and analysis;</p>
<p>   * The ability of the current aircraft and equipment of Coastwatch</p>
<p> to cover Australia's 37,000km coastline; </p>
<p>   * The interface between Coastwatch and Defence/intelligence capabilities;</p>
<p> and </p>
<p>   * Other related issues the task force may identify during its</p>
<p> work. </p>
<p>In finalising their report, the task force will consider the report</p>
<p> of Air Vice Marshall Heggen (retired) into the landing by illegal</p>
<p> immigrants at Cairns and Nambucca Heads in March and April 1999 respectively.</p>
<p>The task force will report its findings to the Prime Minister in June 1999.</p>
<p> 12 April 1999</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
