<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8871</transcript-id>
    <title>APPOINTMENT OF EPARTMENTAL SECRETARIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/05/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008871.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
I.<br />
PRIME MIViSTER<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HION PJ. KEATING MP<br />
APPOINTMENT OF DEPARTMENT SECRETARIES<br />
Further to my announcement on 14 May 1993 that Dr Peter Wilcnski, AO is relinquishing his<br />
position as Secretary to the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade because of treatment<br />
required for an illness, I have recommended to His Excellency the Governor-General the<br />
appointment of Mr Michael Costcllp as Secretary to the Dcpartmcnt of Foreign Affairs and<br />
Trade. Mr Costello is at present the Secretary to the Department of Industrial Relations.<br />
Before that he was a Deputy Secretary in the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade.<br />
I shall also be recommending the appointment of Mr Peter Core, currently a Deputy<br />
Secretary in the Department of Primary Industries and Energy, as Secretary to the<br />
Department of Industrial Relations in place of Mr Costcllo. In addition to his<br />
management experience as a Deputy Secretary, Mr Core will bring to the position his<br />
experience as the former Chairman of the Management Improvement Advisory Committee, a<br />
Service-wide committee that considers significant management issues and initiatives in<br />
the Public Service.<br />
These appointments will take effect on Thursday 27 May.<br />
Dr Geoff Miller, currently Secretary to the Department of Tourism and Associate Secretary<br />
for Agriculture in the Department of Primary Industries and Energy, is a candidate for<br />
the position of Director-General of the United Nations Food and Agriculture Organisation.<br />
The Government is strongly supportive of Dr Miller's candidacy and has agreed that to<br />
enable him to spend more time enhancing Australia's prospects of having him appointed he<br />
should be relieved of his responsibilities as Secretaqy to the Department of Tourism. He<br />
will continue to perform his role as Associate Secretary for Agriculture in the<br />
Department of Primary Industries and Energy.<br />
In Dr Miller's place as Secretary to the Department of Tourism I am recommending the<br />
appointment of Ms Helen Williams. Ms Williams was the Secretary to the Department of<br />
Education and Youth Affairs between 1985 and 1987. She was the first woman appointed as<br />
a Secretary of a Commonwealth Government Department. At present Ms Williams is an<br />
Associate Secretary in my Department where she has had special responsibilities for<br />
Commonwealth-State relations.<br />
Because of Ms Williams' current involvement in the meeting of the Council of Australian<br />
Governments on 8 June, her appointment will take effect on Monday 14 June.<br />
CANBERRA 26 MAY 1993 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
