<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7247</transcript-id>
    <title>STATE LUNCHEON WELLINGTON -20 NOVEMBER 1987</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/11/1987</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007247.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
1.-<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
EM1BAR~ GOED UNITL DCLzVZ! RV CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
STATE LUNCHEON<br />
WELLINGTON 20 NOVEMBER 1987<br />
Prime Minister David Lange,<br />
Opposition Leader Jim Bolger,<br />
Ladies and gentlemen<br />
New Zealand and Australia have a unique relationship.'-<br />
We are next-door neighbours by virtue of our geographical<br />
proximity.<br />
We are brothers and sisters by virtue of our historical<br />
ties: born in the same era and with the same tradition of<br />
democracy and individual liberty.<br />
And by virtue of our proud record as ANZACs in two World<br />
Wars, fighting for the cause of freedom and a safer world,<br />
we are, enduringly, the closest of friends.<br />
But as strong as are those ties of geography and of history,<br />
we would be doing ourselves a disservice if we characterised<br />
our relationship as one which is fixed In time and bound by<br />
the limits of the past.<br />
For the real strength of the relationship between New<br />
Zealand and Australia lies in our people and in their daily<br />
exchanges aross the widest range of business, family,<br />
sporting, cultural and political activities.<br />
Some Kiwis even crossed the Tasman to attend the Adelaide<br />
Grand Prix and although, regrettably, their preslnce was not<br />
rewarded with victory in the celebrity event, they greatly<br />
addea tv ito diqtinction.<br />
Those constant exchanges between Austrailao and New<br />
Zealandera arn based on warmth and openness and friendsni<br />
or, in the case of the virront Australian tour by your<br />
cricketers, they are based on the warmth of intenje rivalry.<br />
It is those exchanges which are responsible for ensuring our<br />
reiationship remains relevant to contemporary needs and<br />
flexible in the face of changing circumstances. j </p>
<p>For it would be foolish to assume that the needs and<br />
circumstances of our relationship and of our region are<br />
immutable. New challenges and new difficulties will arise which make it<br />
all Lhe more importont that, where we disagree, we can<br />
honestly explain our policies tu each other, and, where as<br />
haopens far more fsequently, we aqree, we can work togetner<br />
to achieve our common goals of a prosperous, pc ceful and<br />
stable region.<br />
It is of great importance that Australia and New Zealand<br />
continue to work together in the South Pacific where we have<br />
so many common interests, and we are both determined to do so.<br />
The need for the closest co-operation between us was<br />
highlighted this year by the military overthrow of the<br />
legally elected government of Fiji. The full consequences<br />
of this tragic situation have yet to emerge. But I wish to<br />
put on record my deep appreciation of the fact that at both<br />
the South Pacific Forum in Apia and at the Commonwealth<br />
Heads of Government Meeting in Vancouver, David Lange and I<br />
were able to work closely together to achieve what for all<br />
practical purposes has been a joint and realistic approach<br />
to the Fiji problem.<br />
Australia has also been grateful for the tireless work of<br />
the New Zealand Government in support of a multiracial<br />
indeoendent New Caledonia, the common objective of all the<br />
; V % Arec of I., m geith Panii Forum. We each have an<br />
important long term interest It stabi-Liry La-How CalAdonia<br />
and the changes we seek are, whatever may be said in somquarters,<br />
designed precisely to achieve that stability.<br />
There is no secret about our disagreement on the issue of<br />
access to our ports by allied warships.<br />
Australia adheres firmly to our policy on welcoming ship<br />
visits by our US ally. We accept the need for strategic deterrence.<br />
We recognise that you have a different view. I am not suggesting<br />
that this disagreement is not serious or that it is in any sense<br />
behind us. iiut I believe it is a sign of the maturity of our<br />
relationship that we can have this important disagreement<br />
without allowing it to corrode our overall friendship.<br />
In our bilateral defonr'e-relations, for example, our traditional<br />
exchanges continue. Over the past year, our Defence Ministers<br />
have been in close touch, and they have, through the<br />
appropriately named ANZAC Ship Project, agreed in principle<br />
to equip our navies with the same light surface combatant vessel.<br />
This makes good politioal And strategic sense.<br />
Australia and New Zealand also work togethUL in the cAnse of<br />
disarmament. We value our co-operation with you in the<br />
search tor a Comprohan ive Test Ban Agreement and, of very I .' 2 </p>
<p>great relovance to the future of our region, the conclusion<br />
of the South Pacific Nuclear Free Zone Treaty. Both our<br />
countries welcome the results of the INF negotiations<br />
L L U4&amp;. Lvsa uaq. th-~ t7n itca 51cr-.. o and<br />
forward to further balanced reductions in nuclear weapons.<br />
In the vital negotiations over the future of international<br />
trade, too, we are together making our presence felt. In<br />
the Cairns Group of Fair Traders, we have helped create a<br />
much needed third fnrnp in + hA trade negotiations which, as<br />
the rUruguAy roun, progresses, ig making an indispeneablo<br />
cnntrihtiiifn to the effort to bring down pro~ eotioniot<br />
barriers and reverse the corruption of international<br />
agricultural trade.<br />
I had the honour in Geneva last month of announcing, on<br />
behalf of the Cairns Group, a set of proposals to provide a<br />
long term framework of reform within which agricultural<br />
production and trade can take place with minimum distortion<br />
and disruption. I believe we have a unique opportunity to<br />
work together to move the logjam which has proved so costly to<br />
the growth and prosperity of efficient agricultural exporters<br />
such as New Zealand and Australia.<br />
The opening up of our two markets which took place under<br />
NAFTA and, more recently, under CER, has been a tremendous<br />
example of the mutual benefits of free trade.<br />
CER has provided, for many companies, tho firct atop into a<br />
foreign market. It has exposed them to the complexities of<br />
operating in an unfamiliar environment and to those new<br />
management skills associated with international operations<br />
that are essential if thoco oompanico are to go on to<br />
compete on world markets. Beyond the clear economic<br />
advantages that CER has provided to both: our economies,<br />
this may well prove to have been its most important<br />
contribution. The results of the first five years of CER are gratifying<br />
by any standards. Trade barriers have been drastically<br />
reduced, exceeding expectation4s, and AaueLly L. iaJ<br />
between our two countries has increased to the benefit of<br />
us both.<br />
Our task in the review ahead is to confirm the success of<br />
CER. We can do this most clearly by accelerating the<br />
comoletion of the free trade area. We should also seek to<br />
demonstrate that further development of CER is possible.<br />
The argument in favour of a closer economic relationship<br />
assumes even greater validity in an era when both New<br />
Zealand and Australia are engaged in the task of economic<br />
restructuring. </p>
<p>4.<br />
Restructuring involves decisions which are seldom easy or<br />
comfortable. But it is the only route by which our nations<br />
can ensure their prosperity and growth in the contemporary<br />
world economy.<br />
It is fitting of course that both Australia and New Zealand<br />
are being led through this task by Labor Governments<br />
committed to and capable of dealing in a realistic, credible<br />
and resolute way with very testing economic circumstances.<br />
Both of our Governments have understood the need, for example,<br />
for restoration of stability in our countries' finances,<br />
cipreglAtion of financial markets and other institutional<br />
reforms, and repudlctlui wf iaiwaiid-looking protectionism<br />
in favour of renewed economic competitiveness.<br />
As a result, within a matter of weeks of each other, we<br />
again won the confidenoe of our respective electorates in<br />
historically unprecedented circumstances for both of us.<br />
But I think we both recognise that we cannot rest on our<br />
laurels, that we confrunt luajV-Ltsu L. Naka requiring<br />
patience, discipline and restraint and that we need to<br />
eschew self-indulgent gestures urged on us by the<br />
advocates of the warm inner-glow.<br />
Next year is Australia's Bicentennial year, celebrating the<br />
European settlement of our country 200 years ago. I am<br />
grateful for New Zealand's generous efforts to help us to<br />
make the celebration memorable, not least through your<br />
substantial participation at Expo ' 88 in Brisbane, and your<br />
generous gift of the ' Akarana' which I look forward to<br />
visiting with Prime Minister Lange on Monday.<br />
The Bicentennial will I beilieve be a great occasion not<br />
just for celebration but, I hope, for reflection. I know I<br />
will be understood in New Zealand, whose Maori heritage is<br />
so strong, when I say that I want our Bicentennial year to<br />
include due recognition by all Australians of the fact that<br />
our 200 year occupation of the land follows over 40,000<br />
yeArs of fruitful and pcauful stewardship by an Aboriqindl<br />
civilisation whose depth and richness we relative newcomers<br />
Are Rtill coming to understand,<br />
Let me close by extending an invitation to as many New<br />
Zealanders as possible to cross the Tasanw next year to help<br />
us celebrate our birthday.<br />
Ladies and gentldmen,<br />
I propose a toast to the lasting friendship between the<br />
people of New Zealand and Australia. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
