<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9061</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P J KEATING MP THE 1993 EXPORT AWARDS, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA 30 NOVEMBER 1993</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/11/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009061.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
* PLEASE CUCK AGAINST DELIVZRY<br />
SPEECH By THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
THU 1993 EXPORT AWARDS, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA<br />
NOVEMBER 1993<br />
The growth in Australian exports constitutes one of the<br />
more remarkable chapters in our history.<br />
Laconic, sceptical self-effacing nation that we are, we<br />
tend to play it all down as it it is something that is<br />
happening to us, rather than something we are making<br />
happen. in due course, no doubt Australians will recognise that<br />
this was a remarkable generation a generation of<br />
exporters who might reasonably be numbered among the<br />
pioneers of modern Australia.<br />
But Irn inclined not to wait that long.<br />
I think that our efforts will be helped by building a<br />
contentpor-ary understanding of the importance of what we<br />
are doing the need for it, and the success we are<br />
having. That is why these awards are so important, and why the<br />
organisers deserve great credit for staging them.<br />
These awards acknowledge some of the outstanding<br />
achievers in Australia's export drive and this is only<br />
proper because their efforts are a major contribution to<br />
the nation.<br />
It's particularly significant to me that the cultural<br />
industry features prominently at these awards tonight.<br />
I've alway* strongly held the view that our commercial<br />
development has to go hand in hand with our cultural<br />
d6eve1opniiut that a society which values creativity and<br />
innovation, a society which is confident in its cultural<br />
identity is a society which produces better quality<br />
products for its markets. </p>
<p>In this sense having an interest in art and design is not<br />
an elitist abstraction it is fundamental to our broader<br />
trade push.<br />
The 30 finalists here tonight have contributed no less<br />
than $ 1.6 billion to the nation's economy, and in doing<br />
that they have contributed jobs opportunities for other<br />
industries, improved living standards, a more prominent<br />
and creative role for Australia in the world, a more<br />
active place in the Asia -' Pacific region, a more secure<br />
future for generations of Australians to come.<br />
This is not to overclaim.<br />
These are basic facts about contemporary Australia as<br />
basic as the figures which describe Australia's export<br />
achievements in the past few years.<br />
In the last decade, exports have doubled.<br />
They have grown from 13 per cent of GDP to 20 per cent.<br />
Exports of manufactures have trebled and now exceed those<br />
for rural products and minerals and fuels.<br />
In the past six years exports of EThs have grown at an<br />
average rate of 19 per cent per annum and nearly trebled<br />
in value.<br />
Exports of services have grown at 7 per cent a year and<br />
now account for 20 per cent of total exports.<br />
And the proportion of exports going to North and South-'*-<br />
East Asia continues to rise and now accounts for 60 per<br />
cent of all Australian exports.<br />
You see why I say this is a generation pioneering the new<br />
Australia. It is not something that is being done to us it is<br />
something we are doing for ourselves.<br />
As a government we began a decade ago to create the<br />
conditions in which Australia could become a modern<br />
manufacturing nation able to compete with the best in the<br />
world. we did it because we felt that to fail would cost nothing<br />
less than Australia's future to fail would mean<br />
Australia joining the ranks of those benighted conmmoditydependent<br />
countries.<br />
I won't take you through the steps, but what we did and<br />
what we continue to do has helped create the environment<br />
in which businesses of all sizes are now manufacturing<br />
and exporting, and in which each year more companies are<br />
born Qniy to manufacture and export or provide services<br />
for export. </p>
<p>This is not to claim all the credit for the government.<br />
I must say that it gives me some satisfaction to see how<br />
the challenge has been taken up, and how now we are<br />
seeing the rewards for these decisions in the changing<br />
shape of the Australian economy.<br />
And I also must say that absolute necessity for the<br />
changes we have made has never been so clear we need<br />
only look at the trade figures and ask ourselves, with<br />
commodity prices as they are, where would we now be<br />
without the shift to manufactured and service exports?<br />
Where would be had we not recognised the chance in Asia,<br />
that thai was where our future lay?<br />
Where would be had we not decided that Australia could<br />
reinvent itself that Australians had enough genius and<br />
enough faith in themselves to change?<br />
In the end that is where the credit properly goes to<br />
the people of Australia who were prepared to take on the<br />
change and wear the hardships which change often<br />
involves. It goes to the business people and trade unionists who<br />
found cooperative ways of working.<br />
It goes to the farmers and manufacturers and scientists<br />
who found new products and new ways of producing them.<br />
In the end the credit goes to those who saw in the<br />
imperative to export a great challenge and a great<br />
opportunity. The Australian Export Awards honour all these peopl * e who<br />
did not wait for something to happen 12 them but went out<br />
and made something happen = Q them.<br />
That is why we can talk of a generation of exporters<br />
they have it as their ambition and they are translating<br />
that ambition into success, not only for themselves but<br />
for their country.<br />
of course, we all hope that these awards also encourage<br />
others to enter the new world of exporting.<br />
During the 1980s, 30 new companies a year joined the<br />
ranks of emerging exporters.<br />
it doesnt take much imagination to get an idea of the<br />
benefits that would flow if this number were doubled.<br />
Now I have no need to tell this audience what it takes to<br />
be a succesuful exporter. </p>
<p>Let me instead quote one example to illustrate that once<br />
we know what is reqjuired and have no fear of the global<br />
market place, there is really no limit to the potential.<br />
We have always been considered uncompetitive in the area<br />
of textiles, clothing and footwear, yet last year exports<br />
in this area rose by $ 534 million, a 21 per cent increase<br />
on the previous year and tonight we have among the<br />
finalists a representative of the i1CF industry.<br />
This is not an occasion for me to tell you all. the<br />
reasons why the climate is right for building on these<br />
successes. Let me say only that we have never been so<br />
internationally competitive as we are now and we will be<br />
more competitive in the future.<br />
I think you know that the Government remains determined<br />
to do all it can to make the local environment favourable<br />
and open to suggestions about how to make it more so.<br />
What I want to say in the remainder of the time at my<br />
disposal concerns the internatipnal environment.<br />
I imagine there is nobody here who fails to recognise the<br />
absolute importance of a successful conclusion to the<br />
Uruguay Round of the GATT.<br />
But sometimes it helps to repeat yourself.<br />
And sometimes it helps to spell it out in figures; a<br />
successful outcome in a fortnight's time is likely to<br />
boost Australian exports by $ 2.5 billion per annum by the<br />
year 2002.<br />
A successful conclusion will enable Australia to maximise<br />
its commercial advantage and secure new trading<br />
opportunities for Australian exporters.<br />
Australia has done all it can to see that such a<br />
conclusion is reached.<br />
it now remains to hope that common sense and fairness and<br />
vision prevail, and that the interests of a few are not<br />
put before the interests of the world.<br />
But there is no guarantee, and that is why the continued<br />
development of APEC and the recent remarkable meeting of<br />
APEC leaders in Seattle are so important for Australia.<br />
In Seattle, I visited Boeing which is, of course, the<br />
world's largest Aerospace company.<br />
But I went to demonstrate my support for an Austraian<br />
company Aerospace Technologies of Australia which had<br />
just been awarded Boeing's ' Major Outside Production<br />
Supplier of the Year" award. </p>
<p>TEL<br />
You will also be aware that before going to Seattle I set<br />
up an APEC Business Consultative Panel to inform me of<br />
what business thinks APEC can do for business.<br />
In Seattle, I am pleased to say, we agreed to set up an<br />
APEC Business Forum to identify issues APEC should<br />
address to facilitate regional trade and investment and<br />
encourage the further development of business networks<br />
throughout the region.<br />
Australia will be represented in that forum.<br />
APEC is not an abstraction.<br />
Real outcomes from the Seattle meeting include work by<br />
APEC on deepening and broadening the outcome of the<br />
Uruguay Round, strengthening trade and investment<br />
liberalisation in the region, and facilitating regional<br />
cooperation in areas such as standards.<br />
We also agreed to draw up a common non-binding set of<br />
investment principles that might lead to a formal<br />
regional investment agreement.<br />
All these steps will deliver, in time, real benefits to<br />
Australian businesses.<br />
All of them will make it that much easier for them to tap<br />
into the potential of the Asia-Pacific and find their<br />
niche in what is set to be the aPacific Centurym.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen<br />
Someone said this morning as if we did not know itthat<br />
we are not Asian.<br />
of course, we are not Asian.<br />
But we share a future with the countries of our region.<br />
And APEC is, to my way of thinking, the best the most<br />
creative expression of that future.<br />
As I said earlier, 60 per cent of our exports now go to<br />
the Asian region.<br />
And as I said at that very impressive National Trade and<br />
Investment conference in Melbourne last week, over the<br />
next two years exports to APEC countries will account for<br />
about one third of the total increase in our production.<br />
In two years' time Australian exports to APEC countries<br />
will account fb5r around 15 per cent of all we do, all we<br />
make and all we sell. T3E0L: . Nov. 93 18: 00 No. 008 P. 05/ 06 </p>
<p>TEL<br />
And over the next two years, increased exports to APEC<br />
mem~ bers will create more than 70,000 new jobs for<br />
Australians good jobs, well paid jobs, jobs with a<br />
future. Perhaps this is the most important thing to say about the<br />
new export culture in Australia.<br />
I said Australia's exporters were pioneers they are,<br />
they are pioneering not just a new more dynamic shape to<br />
the Australian economy, and not just a new prosperity for<br />
Australia. They are guaranteeing that Australians of this, but more<br />
particularly of fltZurp generations, will have a place in<br />
the front rank of societies that they will have access<br />
to the jobs and opportunities on the leading edge of<br />
economic development.<br />
That is the most rewarding place to be.<br />
It is the Qnlg place to be if Australia is to remain one<br />
of the really great places to live in the world, and one<br />
of the great social democracies.<br />
It remains for me to congratulate all the finalists here<br />
tonight and the people who have put on these awards.<br />
It is always a great occasion because it honours great<br />
Australian imagination and enterprise.<br />
And finally let me congratulate Austrade for its<br />
achievements last year. I noticed a newspaper report<br />
today which indicated that Austrade contributed to new<br />
exports last financial year valued at $ 4.25 billion.<br />
This is a fitting tribute to Bill Ferris, the outgoing<br />
Chair of Austrade, and it set-s A high standard for Bob<br />
Johnston -to emulate when he comes on board to replace<br />
him. As the Financial Review said today, however, Bob brings a<br />
lifetime's experience of trading in Japanese and Asian<br />
markets to his new job, and so he will be well placed to<br />
build on Austrade's already formidable record.<br />
I look forward to presenting the winner's prize later in<br />
the evening. T3EL0:. Nov. 93 18: 00 No. 008 P. 06/ 06 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
