<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>279</transcript-id>
    <title>COMMONWEALTH MR. KENNEDY P.M.&#039;S CONFERENCE COMMON MARKET DECIMAL CURRENCY CRICKET.</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/03/1961</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000279.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
OFFICE OF THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR AUSTRALIA IN THE UNITED KINGDOM<br />
Australian News and Information Bureau, Australia House,<br />
Strand, London, W. C. 2 Telephone: TEMple Bar 2435<br />
PRI1 MINISTER'S A1ZRIVAL AT LONDON AIRPORT.<br />
MOINDAY, IvQ! RCH 6. 1961. INTERVIEW, B. B. C.,<br />
I. T. V. AITD PRESS. 3.30 P. M. APPROXIMATELY.<br />
CESTION:, Sir, you are a very senior member of the Commonwealth. Do<br />
you think that the Commonwealth can keep its present<br />
character if South Africa continues to be in the Commonwealth<br />
with her racial discrimination?<br />
ANSWER: You are now inviting me to say something in public about a<br />
matter which will be discussed in private by the Prime Ministers.<br />
I have nothing to say in public.<br />
QUESTION: Well, youtve recently been seeing Mr. Kennedy, the President of<br />
America, Mr. Prime Minister.<br />
ANSWER: I have indeed.<br />
QUESTION: Did you come to any conclusion with him about the major problems<br />
of disarmament, peaceful co-existence, and so on?<br />
ANSWER: No.<br />
QUESTION: Can you give any impression of Mr. Kennedy?<br />
ANSWER: I was very impressed by him. I thought that I'd never met<br />
him before, except once, rather informally and so I was very<br />
anxious to find out what he was like, if that was not an<br />
impertinance, and I must say that, in the course of two hours<br />
0or more with him, I was very impressed. I think he has a<br />
lively mind, and I think we can look for active, positive<br />
0policies from him.<br />
QUESTION: Can you say, Sir, what you think will be the most important<br />
* question that will come up at the Conference?<br />
ANSWER: I would expect that we would have major discussions on disarmament<br />
and on the future of the United Nations. I mean by that that<br />
there is twice as many nations now belonging to the United<br />
Nations as there were, and arguments are going on as to whether<br />
the Security Council ought to have its structure altered, because<br />
you have so many more countries in. There have been these<br />
arguments that have gone on about the Secretariat, largely<br />
promoted by Mr. of course, at the last Assembly, and broadly,<br />
I think that it is an appropriate time for Prime Ministers to<br />
discuss the relations between the Commonwealth and the United<br />
Nations, they being two utterly different bodies, but their<br />
members having a good deal of relationship with the others.<br />
Those, I think, are two great things the important question<br />
of the future of the Commonwealth, of course, is there South<br />
Africa, of course, is one point that has been tremendously<br />
canvassed in public, but there are other questions about the<br />
Commonwealth, its future we have more colonies that will<br />
achieve independence. Are they automatically to be members<br />
of the Commonwealth? Are there to be any rules about this<br />
matter? This problem has engaged a good deal of thought, both<br />
here and in my own country.<br />
QUESTION: Would you like to see some sort of Bill of Rights drawn up among<br />
the Commonwealth countries? </p>
<p>ASER: You icnow, I've a very great respect for the Bil]. of Rights of<br />
this country, largely because it passed its way into the, what<br />
I regard as the common law inheritance of Australia. I don't<br />
go nap on new Bills of Rights I think if the people run their<br />
Parliaments, they'll see that their rights are protected.<br />
QUESTION:, W~ at da you think, Sir, what' s your attitude towards Britain,<br />
supposing we join the Common Market?<br />
ANSWER: Now, look, I'm not going to make a kerbstone statement on that,<br />
because, the other day, some views were attributed to Mr. Heath<br />
on the question of the relationship between, if not the Seven<br />
and Six, at any rate, the United Kingdom and the Six, and they<br />
seem to me to be, possibly, very important. But I want to<br />
know far more about them than I know now no doubt, I'll have<br />
an opportunity in London to find out what the directions are,<br />
whit the possible developments in contemplation are, but<br />
Australia will need to know all about them and have proper time<br />
to consider them, before we offer a view, but none here.<br />
QUESTION: What will be your attitude if the question of decimal coinage<br />
comes up at the Conference?<br />
ANSWER: But will it?<br />
REAK There seems a possibility.<br />
What a horrible thoughti We've just had a Decimal Currency<br />
Committee in Australia making a report, and we're still, you<br />
know, grappling with it. I hope you're not going to ask me<br />
to grapple with theirs, too. Are they?<br />
QUESTION:. Changing the subject, Mr. Menzies) what do you think of<br />
Australia's chances in the nexct Series?<br />
ANSWER: Now, that question can be answered only in the light of<br />
patriotism, not in the light of knowledge, because I don't know<br />
what your young ones are like.* All I know is that we've had<br />
to go for our lives this year against the West Indies, who<br />
played magnificent cricket,! and the result of the Series was in<br />
the balance two or three times.<br />
QUESTION: You don't think you're going to spin out this Gonference<br />
sufficiently long to see a bit of it here, Mr. Monzies?<br />
ANSWIER: I think that's one thing about which I can be positive. I<br />
will not be here for the Test matches.<br />
REKU K: RPEMiRtKy: l Thank you very much indeed. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
