<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6052</transcript-id>
    <title>TELEX TO THE PREMIERS AND CHIEF MINISTERS</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/05/1986</release-date>
    <release-type>Correspondence</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006052.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>TELEX TO THE PREMIERS AND CHIEF MINISTER<br />
I TAKE THIS FIRST OPPORTUNITY UPON ASSUMING OFFICE AS<br />
PRIME MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA TO SEND MY WARMEST EXPRESSION<br />
OF GOODWILL TO YOU PERSONALLY AND AS HEAD OF YOUR GOVERNMENT<br />
I LOOK FORWARD TO THE CLOSEST CO-OPERATION WITH YOU AND<br />
YOUR GOVERNMENT IN THE GREAT TASK OF SERVING THE PEOPLE<br />
OF AUSTRALIA WHICH WE SHARE IN COMMON.<br />
I NOW MOST CORDIALLY WISH TO INVITE YOU AND YOUR GOVERNMENT<br />
TO PARTICIPATE IN THE NATIONAL ECONOMIC SUMMIT CONFERENCE<br />
TO BE HELD AT PARLIAMENT HOUSE CANBERRA DURING THE WEEK<br />
BEGINNING MONDAY 11 APRIL. AS YOU WILL BE AWARE, THIS<br />
PROPOSAL WAS A CENTRAL COMMITMENT I MADE ON'BEHALF OF THE<br />
NEW AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT DURING THE RECENT ELECTION<br />
CAMPAIGN. THE FULLEST POSSIBLE INVOLVEMENT BY YOUR GOVERNMEN1<br />
WILL BE CRUCIAL TO THE SUCCESS OF THIS UNDERTAKING.<br />
I ENVISAGE THAT EACH STATE AND THE NORTHERN TERRITORY WILL<br />
BE REPRESENTED BY ITS PREMIER AND ONE OTHER MINISTER. EVERY<br />
FACILITY WILL BE EXTENDED TO YOU AND YOUR OFFICIALS FOR THE<br />
UTMOST INVOLVEMENT OF YOUR GOVERNMENT BEFORE AND DURING THE<br />
CONFERENCE. I SHOULD RECEIVE YOUR EARLY ACCEPTANCE OF THIS INVITATION<br />
-WITH DEEP PLEASURE.<br />
FOLLOWING IX THE TEXT OF A LETTER OF INVITATION I HAVE SENT<br />
TODAY TO LEADING REPRESENTATIVES OF AUSTRALIAN INDUSTRY AND<br />
THE UNION MOVEMENT, SETTING OUT THE NATURE AND PUR? OSE OF<br />
THIS HISTORIC CONFERENCE. </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER CANSBERRA<br />
Dear<br />
You will be aware that in the recent election campaign<br />
to elect the new Australian Government, I made a<br />
fundamental commitment to the people of Australia<br />
in these terms:<br />
We undertake, immediately on assuming office,<br />
to convene a National Economic Summit-Conference,<br />
fully representative of Australian industrv,<br />
the Australian workforce and the Australian people<br />
through their elected Governments.<br />
Its purpose is to create a climate for common<br />
understanding " of the scale and scope of Australia's<br />
present crisis, to explore the policy options,<br />
and to ensure that the relevant parties<br />
governments, business and the unions clearly<br />
appreciate the role that each of them will have<br />
to play in pulling the country out of the present<br />
economic crisis.<br />
On 5 March 1.983, the people of Australia gave their<br />
very clear support, both for this proposal and for<br />
the approach it represents.<br />
As my Government this day begins the task of<br />
translating its mandate into a practical program<br />
for national reconciliation, national. recover-v ind<br />
national reconstruction, we are deeplyv conscious<br />
of the extent to which its effectiveness must depend<br />
on -co-operation, understanding and commitment from<br />
. all sections of the community.<br />
Accordingly, I wish now to invite you to join , with<br />
the Australian Government in the National Economic<br />
Summit Conference. I propose that the Conference<br />
begin on Monday 11 April. 1983. It is envisaged that<br />
the Confcrence will occupy the great er Dart of chat<br />
week. The Conference will be held in the House of<br />
Representatives, Parl. i. ament House, Canberra.<br />
~ CS4%~ OSfl. </p>
<p>Further details of the arrangements for the Conference<br />
will be sent to you as soon as possible, but clearlv<br />
the essential ingredients will be:<br />
assessing the economic and industrial relations<br />
situation; and<br />
finding a consensus among the participants<br />
which would set the framework for the<br />
implementation of a recovery strategy during<br />
the next three years.<br />
I am arranging that documents relevant to these<br />
issues will be prepared and circulated by the<br />
Australian Government before the meeting. The full<br />
resources of my Government and its instrumentalities<br />
the Treasury, the Reserve Bank and other relevant<br />
" departments will be brought to bear in the<br />
preparation for the Conference.<br />
I believe that the effectiveness and value of the<br />
conference will be enhanced if participants other<br />
than the Australian Government are able to provide<br />
information and expert analysis of developments<br />
in their own sectors and in the economy more<br />
generally. I would envisage continuing consultation<br />
with participants in respect of information and<br />
material they may wish to provide to the Conference.<br />
As I also made clear during the election campaign,<br />
the Government wants to involve participants as<br />
much as possible in the preparations for the<br />
Conference. I should be very interested, therefore,<br />
to receive suggestions from you on a possible agenda<br />
for the Conference. I should also be interested<br />
in your views on the composition of the Economic<br />
Planning Advisory Council -,.; hich will hec the<br />
Government's vehicle for regular ongoing consultation.<br />
The National. Economic Summit Conference presents<br />
us " with a rare, and I believe, an historic opportunity<br />
to set a new course for Australia. I ar-confident<br />
that you will w. elcome the opportunity to takle part<br />
in and contribute to w.-hat, I deeplv b'elieve, c; in<br />
be made a new beginning. It is not necessary for<br />
me at this stage to stress the seriousness of the<br />
economic and social problems now facing Australiia. </p>
<p>The emphasis of the Conference will be do practical,<br />
specific and effective measures to meet those problems<br />
and to develop processes for continuing consultation<br />
and co-operation. However, I believe the Conference<br />
will also have an important svmbolic purpose, as<br />
a demonstration, to Australia and the world, of<br />
our ability to work together to surmount our present<br />
problems and lay firm foundations for a better future<br />
for all our people. Yours sincerely Hawke) </p>
<p>NATIONAL ECONOMIC SUMMIT CONFE~ FNCEGOVERNMENT<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Treasurer Ministers for. Employment and Industrial Relations<br />
Finance Industry and Commerce<br />
Social Security<br />
Primary Industry.<br />
Education and Youth Affairs<br />
Premier of New South Wales 2<br />
Victoria 2<br />
Queensland 2<br />
Western Australia 2<br />
South Australia 2<br />
Tasmania 2<br />
Chief Minister of the Northern Territory 2<br />
Australian Council of Local Government Associations 2<br />
Employers/ Business<br />
Australian Bankers' Association<br />
Australian Chamber of Commerce<br />
Australian Federation of Construction Contractors'<br />
Australian Industries Development Association<br />
Australian Manufacturers Export Council<br />
Australian Road Transport Federation<br />
Confederation of Australian Industry<br />
Council of Small Business Organisations<br />
Housing Industry Association<br />
Master Builders Federation of Australia<br />
Metal Trades Industry Association of Australia<br />
National Farmers Federation<br />
Oil Industry Industrial Committee<br />
Sir Peter Abeles<br />
Sir Keith Campbell<br />
Mr A. Carmichael<br />
Sir Roderick Carnegie<br />
Mr A. W. Coates<br />
Mr P. J. W. Cottrell<br />
Mr W. L. Dix<br />
Mr J. B. Gough<br />
Mr B. N. Kelman<br />
Mr J. H. Leard<br />
Mr B. T. Loton<br />
Sir Eric McClintock<br />
Mr Morgan<br />
Mr E. J. N! ea.<br />
Mr J W. Ut z<br />
Mr L. S. Zampatti<br />
Professional Groups<br />
Aus tra ia n Med i c; L ssoc t on<br />
Insti t t t Ch'ir tr.: d . ccoun<br />
i Coun i s al1i 1.-</p>
<p>Unions Australian Council of Trade Unions -31<br />
Other Organisations<br />
Australian Council of Social Services </p>
<p>[Date confirmed]   </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
