<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10760</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP RADIO INTERVIEW WITH STEVE PRICE RADIO 3AW, MELBOURNE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/01/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>PRICE:</p>
<p>[Tape begins]...the people who manage your image might be better</p>
<p>   off making sure that that did happen.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I'll pass on what you've said to them. It's</p>
<p>   a question of striking a balance. If you look, as a politician,</p>
<p>   that you're only doing something for the publicity then the</p>
<p>   Australian public's pretty smart you know, they can see through</p>
<p>   it and it's a question of striking a balance.</p>
<p>PRICE:</p>
<p>You were on the air commenting when Graeme Wood dropped the magic</p>
<p>   word when he dropped that catch. That must have been interesting.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes, but it was a spontaneous human reaction. Very, very spontaneous.</p>
<p>PRICE:</p>
<p>Melbourne seems to have been chosen to get a bit serious as the</p>
<p>   front for a challenge to the waterfront labour monopolies. Why Melbourne?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, that's something you would have to ask the National</p>
<p>   Farmers Federation and Patricks. What is occurring is a result of</p>
<p>   the law changes that we introduced when we changed the Industrial</p>
<p>   Relations Act and we made it possible for there to be more competition</p>
<p>   on the Australian waterfront. And what the NFF is doing is to exercise</p>
<p>   the right of any group of Australians and that is to start a new</p>
<p>   business and to offer a better service to the public. And if it</p>
<p>   can do that then good luck to it and it will have the total support</p>
<p>   of the Government and it ought to have the total support and the</p>
<p>   total sympathy of the business community in Australia because we</p>
<p>   do need a more efficient waterfront. </p>
<p>The inefficiency of the Australian waterfront is legend. It is</p>
<p>   effecting our trade performance. And nobody can expect to have a</p>
<p>   monopoly whether it's in business or as a trade union. And</p>
<p>   what the MUA is arguing for is a maintenance of its monopoly. I</p>
<p>   mean, people should understand that. But what the MUA wants is the</p>
<p>   preservation of a monopoly which no other section of the Australian</p>
<p>   community would be allowed to get away with.</p>
<p>PRICE:</p>
<p>When did you first become aware of the NFF plan?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I heard generally about it a reasonably short while ago. I can't</p>
<p>   remember exactly when. But you've got to remember that we have</p>
<p>   never disguised our desire for there to be more competition on the</p>
<p>   Australian waterfront. And over the years I've talked to innumerable</p>
<p>   business men and women about the need for change and reform on the</p>
<p>   Australian waterfront. I've lost count of the number of discussions</p>
<p>   I've had with that, not only the Farmers Federation, but miners,</p>
<p>   manufacturers, other people in business. I don't disguise the</p>
<p>   fact that I welcome a challenge to the monopoly position of the</p>
<p>   MUA because monopolies are bad. They're bad when they're</p>
<p>   enjoyed by companies and they are bad when they're enjoyed</p>
<p>   by governments and they are bad when they're enjoyed by trade</p>
<p>   unions. And it puzzles me that some of the people who most vigorously</p>
<p>   attack monopolies in the hands of companies, when it comes to a</p>
<p>   trade union thing it's perfectly okay to shut non-union labour</p>
<p>   out of a particular commercial activity.</p>
<p>PRICE:</p>
<p>Had a couple of wharfies on the phones this afternoon saying it's</p>
<p>   a bit hypocritical of the farmers to be doing this when they're</p>
<p>   one of the greatest protected species in Australia.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, that is just wrong. The Australian farmer has less protection</p>
<p>   than any other section of the Australian business community. The</p>
<p>   Australian farmer is one of the least protected in the world. I</p>
<p>   mean, I'm sorry, they are just completely ignorant of the facts</p>
<p>   when they make those assertions. The farmers have progressively</p>
<p>   lost all of their protection. And one of the problems of the Australian</p>
<p>   farmer is that he is struggling in a world where the farmers against</p>
<p>   which he competes get a lot of protection. The Japanese, the American</p>
<p>   and the European farmers get massive subsidies. The Australian farmers</p>
<p>   don't. And Australian farmers not only have to compete against</p>
<p>   their subsidised brethren in other countries, but they also have</p>
<p>   to often put up with the additional domestic costs brought about</p>
<p>   by monopoly trade union practises. So for wharfies to assert that</p>
<p>   is to assert something that is simply not true.</p>
<p>PRICE:</p>
<p>Michael O'Leary is a national organiser with the Maritime</p>
<p>   Union of Australia. He says this is about Peter Reith showing that</p>
<p>   he's got a hairy chest.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well look, the Australian public will want a better argument than</p>
<p>   that to be sympathetic to the MUA. I mean, I just take you back</p>
<p>   to what is happening. What is happening is that a group of people</p>
<p>   are exercising their democratic right within the law to start a</p>
<p>   new business venture which will provide competition to existing</p>
<p>   stevedores and will use non-union labour. And the MUA is complaining</p>
<p>   because the monopoly held by the MUA could be threatened. Now, that's</p>
<p>   what's at stake. It's got nothing to do with hairy chests</p>
<p>   or protected farmers or anything else.</p>
<p>PRICE:</p>
<p>Does it concern you though when you see riot shields being pulled</p>
<p>   out of the back of buses down there?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, what concerns me is the belligerent language, the threats</p>
<p>   of intimidation and the resort to the language of confrontation</p>
<p>   employed by, thus far, by the MUA. That's what disturbs me.</p>
<p>The farmers aren't talking the language of confrontation.</p>
<p>   They're not. The people who are talking the language of confrontation</p>
<p>   are the members of the Maritime Union of Australia.</p>
<p>PRICE:</p>
<p>Will this be an election year, Prime Minister?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I don't know. There could be an election this year. It's</p>
<p>   not constitutionally due until March of next year. Whether it's</p>
<p>   some time this year or some time early next year, I don't know.</p>
<p>   I've said before that it will be at the right time. I haven't</p>
<p>   decided what that time is. In the meantime, as I indicated yesterday</p>
<p>   in the plans I laid out for the year, we're getting on with</p>
<p>   the job of governing. And we have a number of major things we want</p>
<p>   to do this year. We want to reform taxation system or lay out our</p>
<p>   plans for that. And I announced yesterday a number of initiatives</p>
<p>   that extend the principle of mutual obligation. We're putting</p>
<p>   resources into generating another 25,000 Work for the Dole places.</p>
<p>   We're going to help unemployed people whose literacy and numeracy</p>
<p>   skills, or lack of those skills, are preventing them getting work.</p>
<p>   And we're going to pilot a number of other schemes to help</p>
<p>   the unemployed. And all up we're putting an additional $380</p>
<p>   million over four years into helping tackle the problem of youth</p>
<p>   unemployment. So, we have a lot ahead of us and a lot of things</p>
<p>   that we want to do. We want to see the tax system fixed.</p>
<p>PRICE:</p>
<p>When will I know the change to my personal income tax rate?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Before the election.</p>
<p>PRICE:</p>
<p>How...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, you will have a good opportunity to assess what we are offering</p>
<p>   the Australian public before the election. Unlike the Labor Party</p>
<p>   we are prepared to tackle taxation reform. The Labor Party is telling</p>
<p>   the Australian public that we don't have to do anything more</p>
<p>   to reform the economy despite the fact that the Asian region is</p>
<p>   experiencing this huge meltdown and despite the fact that that really</p>
<p>   means we have to run even faster and become even more competitive.</p>
<p>   The Labor Party is trying to spin the yarn that we can just go to</p>
<p>   sleep and do absolutely nothing. </p>
<p>PRICE:</p>
<p>So you will give us the time to debate those tax changes?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Of course you will have the time to debate them, of course.</p>
<p>PRICE:</p>
<p>And there will be meaningful changes to the personal income tax</p>
<p>   breaks?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>There certainly will be.</p>
<p>PRICE:</p>
<p>Have you written your Constitutional Convention speech yet?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, but I have got the elements of what I will be saying I have</p>
<p>   been talking about over the past few weeks. I support the present</p>
<p>   system, not because I have any sort of nostalgic attachment to the</p>
<p>   present system, I support it because it works very well. But I am</p>
<p>   saying that what the Convention should do is to produce an alternative</p>
<p>   to the present system so that the Australian public can make a choice.</p>
<p>We all know that one of the choices, when the referendum comes,</p>
<p>   will be the maintenance of the present system, that will be one</p>
<p>   option. But we don't really know what the republican option</p>
<p>   is. And there are a lot of people I know who say, look if the republic</p>
<p>   involves a president chosen in a particular fashion then I will</p>
<p>   vote for a republic, but if it involves a president chosen in another</p>
<p>   fashion I won't vote for a republic.</p>
<p>So you really have to define and clarify what the alternatives</p>
<p>   to the present system is so that people can make a sensible choice.</p>
<p>   And that is what I have been arguing for, and I have indicated that</p>
<p>   for my own part I support the present system. But if I were forced</p>
<p>   to nominate a choice amongst the republican alternatives, I think</p>
<p>   that advocated by the former Victorian Governor Mr McGarvie is preferable</p>
<p>   to the direct election of the president which would be the worst</p>
<p>   of the alternatives. Direct election of a president would fundamentally</p>
<p>   alter the present system, it would create a rival political power</p>
<p>   centre. You could have a Liberal Prime Minister, a Labor President,</p>
<p>   who has been popularly elected and you could have the Senate controlled</p>
<p>   by the Australian Democrats. I don't think you could get anything</p>
<p>   done in those circumstances.</p>
<p>PRICE:</p>
<p>How long will you spend at the Convention over the 10 days it's</p>
<p>   operating?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I will participate in the Convention each of the days that it is</p>
<p>   on. I will spend a lot of time there. I am required, because of</p>
<p>   my other responsibilities to do other things and I will probably</p>
<p>   have to pay a visit or two out of Canberra during that period of</p>
<p>   time. But at some stage of each of the days that the Convention</p>
<p>   is sitting I expect to be there. So I won't be a part-time</p>
<p>   casual participant. I intend to take this Convention very seriously.</p>
<p>PRICE:</p>
<p>Does it disappoint you that the Victorian Premier only intends</p>
<p>   to spend half a day there of the ten days it on and didn't</p>
<p>   bother to vote?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>That is a matter for him. It is a free country and it was a voluntary</p>
<p>   vote. And one of the things that we have to find out about this</p>
<p>   issue is how passionately people feel about change. I don't</p>
<p>   detect a sense of urgency in the Australian community about changing</p>
<p>   our Head of State. I detect a lot of people who, when they are asked</p>
<p>   say, oh yeah that is not a bad idea we probably should do it, but</p>
<p>   they don't have any sense of passion or urgency. And I think</p>
<p>   what they want to do is to be told what exactly is on offer and</p>
<p>   what is the alternative to the present system. And when they know</p>
<p>   that they will make their decision.</p>
<p>PRICE:</p>
<p>Were the changes to nursing homes last year, is your private polling</p>
<p>   showing that that has hurt you across Australia?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I don't talk about private polling because that is a contradiction</p>
<p>   in terms, it is no longer private if I talk about it. And in any</p>
<p>   event we don't adjust our policies according to polling. We,</p>
<p>   obviously made some errors in that area, I acknowledged those and</p>
<p>   I have fixed it. And I made it very plain that we had made some</p>
<p>   errors and I think it is always important that governments fix things</p>
<p>   that they are responsible for. And I am not a person who pretends</p>
<p>   that from time to time errors aren't made and where they are</p>
<p>   made they should be fixed and acknowledged. And that is exactly</p>
<p>   what we have done and we have got the nursing home situation on</p>
<p>   a proper footing. We do have to get more capital into nursing homes</p>
<p>   because many of them are dilapidated and run down and in need of</p>
<p>   a big capital injection. And it either must come from the ordinary</p>
<p>   taxpayer, through the budget, or it has got to come from people</p>
<p>   who can afford to do so who need to use nursing homes. </p>
<p>Now I don't think it is unreasonable to say to people who</p>
<p>   can afford to do so that they should make a contribution, or their</p>
<p>   families should make a contribution towards their care. Because</p>
<p>   if that doesn't happen it has got to come out of the budget</p>
<p>   and that means your tax will be higher.</p>
<p>PRICE:</p>
<p>Are you concerned about a potential breakdown in civil law in Indonesia?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I am concerned about Indonesia generally. It is facing a very difficult</p>
<p>   economic situation, the increases in the price of food will be very</p>
<p>   severe for a large part of the population which is still quite poor.</p>
<p>   And it is Australia's responsibility to be concerned about,</p>
<p>   and to be involved as we have been. We have participated very, very</p>
<p>   extensively in helping in the restructure of the Indonesian economy</p>
<p>   and also that of Thailand and Korea. I don't want to be alarmist</p>
<p>   and I respect, of course, the domestic right of the Indonesian people</p>
<p>   to deal with their own political problems. But it is a major area</p>
<p>   of concern.</p>
<p>PRICE:</p>
<p>Just finally. Do you think, and I am not referring to you in anyway</p>
<p>   here, do you think an Australian politician, a leading Australian</p>
<p>   politician, could survive the sort of scandal that is whirling around</p>
<p>   the ears of the US President, Bill Clinton at the present time?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well there is no way that I can answer that without making an observation</p>
<p>   on what is happening in the United States concerning the President</p>
<p>   and I respect his office, I respect him and I am not going to buy</p>
<p>   into that. That is a matter for him to deal with, it is not appropriate</p>
<p>   for an Australian Prime Minister to comment on that sort of thing</p>
<p>   because there is no way that a comment on that can be, or ought</p>
<p>   to be made in isolation. I have found in my dealings with President</p>
<p>   Clinton that he is a highly intelligent, competent person with whom</p>
<p>   to deal. He has been an effective President, his dealings with Australia</p>
<p>   have always been very fair and very open and I have had quite a</p>
<p>   lot of personal dealing with him since I've become Prime Minister</p>
<p>   and I have found him a good listener and somebody who is interested</p>
<p>   in the Australian point of view.</p>
<p>Now what is happening in the United States concerning his Presidency</p>
<p>   is a matter for him to deal with and it is</p>
<p>is a matter for him to deal with and it is just not appropriate</p>
<p>   for me in anyway to make a comment that could be put in the context</p>
<p>   of that situation.</p>
<p>PRICE:</p>
<p>Prime Minister I appreciate very much you giving us so much of</p>
<p>   your time.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Thank you very much.</p>
<p>[Ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
