<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3461</transcript-id>
    <title>MT GRAVATT HOSPITAL - 17 NOVEMBER 1974</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/11/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003461_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRE; RiLELEASE<br />
MT. GRAVATT HOSPITAL<br />
The Prime Minister today visited the site which the<br />
Queensland Government has been holding for a hospital at<br />
Mt. Gravatt. Mr Whitlam said that the sorry history of the proposal<br />
for a major teaching hospital complex at Mt Gravatt was yet<br />
another instance of how the Queensland Government's unwillingness<br />
to co-operate'with the Australian Government stopped Queenslanders<br />
from getting the benefits of essential services.<br />
" In the 1973 Budget the Australian Government offered<br />
Queensland $ 250,000 for initial planning for the Mt Gravatt<br />
teaching hospital complex. To date they have spent only<br />
$ ii0,000 and claim that the project has a low priority andw<br />
will not be required before the 1980s," the Prime Minister<br />
said. " Tile Australian Government will pay the whole cost<br />
of the new Griffith University and has offered to-pay the whole<br />
cost of the teaching hospital.<br />
" A teaching hospital ought to be in operation as soon<br />
as possible after the University opens, but so far the Queensland<br />
Government has ignored our offer to fund the major teaching<br />
hospital complex. " Residents of the southern metropolitan area and<br />
of the Gold Coast urgently need access to the comprehensive<br />
medical services that the proposed hospital complex at Mount<br />
Gravatt would provide.<br />
" Meanwhile the most overgrown and overcrowded hospital<br />
complex in Australia, the Royal Brisbane Hospital, has a major<br />
expansion under construction.<br />
" Mr Tooth now proposes a further major expansion in<br />
the inner city area, on the overcrowded mater hospital site,<br />
before proceeding at Mount Gravatt.<br />
" The Australian Government is convinced by the expert<br />
opinions expressed by hospital administrators for years, that<br />
major teaching hospital facilities in Brisbane need decentralising<br />
urgently," he said.<br />
ø 17 November 1974 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
