<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5469</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER INTERVIEWED BY PETER HARVEY, CHANNEL NINE SYDNEY</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/10/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005469.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS OFFIC9 TRANSCRIPTwEDMDSAY, 15-OCTOBER,. 1980<br />
PRIME MINISTER INTORVISWED BY PETER HARVEY,-CHANEL NINE<br />
Prime minister, could your leadership style, ' Your lack o&gt;~ C~ l<br />
about popularity, cost you Government on Saturday?.<br />
Prime minister<br />
I do n-at-believe-z-,--no. -1--miade up my mind, and the whole.-<br />
Government did, five years ago, that we would make the. dec$ tsion$<br />
that we believed were tight for Australia and for Austra14; i'<br />
faniiliea,-for Aujr-aJia's working men and women. we know -that'<br />
there have been some tough and difficult decisions. But-isno<br />
a popularity contest. It is a question of. doing what i1as dr.<br />
for Australia. Harvey<br />
Butñ-it-is a popularity contest.<br />
-Prine MKinister<br />
Not ii that sort of sense. It is a question of being able to-d<br />
what is right for this country. It is possible to prom-ise-, al te--<br />
things in the world, and they can be superficially attractive. i<br />
the-frst instance, but they could be disastrous in termeo6f theit<br />
longer term consequences. we made up our minds that we : jusat -would.<br />
not go down that path. If we promise something, I. have-. not -no<br />
politician has got a secret treasure chest;_ if we pro. Mtae-somethi.-g1<br />
it has got to be paid for by all the Ftapaye-rs-o tbis CoUnftryo by<br />
all the working men and women of this country. This is the wrot4.--<br />
time to go about policies which are going to add to inflation,<br />
destroy ti ompettivebase of-Aittstralian industry. We* bave<br />
established a very firm bases on which to build for the -109s with<br />
* employment growing strongly,' with people being able-to se-li-<br />
Austraian-made goods In nearlyeey * onr~ ftewrl.-B~<br />
high inflation again, can destroy all of that.. -1<br />
How do you combat, with that sort of philosophy,<br />
promises of cheaper petrol and lower income tax.<br />
econoiie--ergwnent minute, how do you tackle<br />
Prime Minister Bill Kfaye'<br />
Leaving aside, -thethose<br />
problems?<br />
I do not think you can entirely ignore the economic arqixment,<br />
bperocmauissein gth et o osnplyen dw ayle syso. u caTnh amt akise ltohwe ' eor neta xtehsi gr esthpeact t~ Lbableo, r. diso rbigort.,<br />
propose.-Teyrpropoeto spend a great deal. more, even -on. -their.-<br />
own figures and they have not told us what their whole . programrme<br />
would cost, they promised us a list but they havenot even-tried to<br />
put th-e suns together so they are going to try. and spei more anmd<br />
tax less and that leaves a great gap in resources whiThc-8-<br />
totally inflationary.-1L~ ' 1 </p>
<p>-Harvey, 15/ 10/ 80o-2-<br />
Cheaper petrol?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Wall, they have not really promised cheaper -petrol. T-hey have<br />
given the impression of cheaper petrol. Theyjkave'said they would:'-*<br />
freeze the price for a while, but they are only going to Creeethat<br />
part which is produced in Australia, and if the world price<br />
goes up that would still flow through. But here again it gets<br />
back to the test of responsibility: are Australians -pre &amp; red to.--<br />
pursue the policies which all authorities in Australia and overseas<br />
indeed, regard as being right so that there will be supplies of<br />
petrol in-the 1990.-and-beyoncLm-that we will not uge up and-p~ ump<br />
Bass Strait dry and then leave Australians -beggars for fuel onthe<br />
international market at whatever price is then demanded, if<br />
you can get it. As a result of our policies, even though we do<br />
pay a world price, it is the lowest world price, and the price,~ f~<br />
our petrol is about half that of most of Europe and less than<br />
half 1Cor. many of thle countries of Europe about the same as<br />
Ameriva-r, much less than New Zealand. Againat that background,<br />
X think people are perhaps more concerned about where the moneyhas<br />
gone rather than the policy itself. Over this last year, over<br />
$ 600 mill Iion wen t in tax cuts on the f irst of July; very large<br />
additional stums for defence which just have to be funded in the<br />
kind of world we live in; and some more to reduc ' e the defic itin<br />
other words, get the Government's books better into bala-nce',<br />
Speaking of money going, Bill Hayden has made a gr~ eat deal of<br />
running with his promises to end tax avoidance. Can you do-more?<br />
Should more be done?<br />
prim~ e minisgtor<br />
Well, as schemes emerge, we will do more. -7ohf Howard hias donemore<br />
in this area-than any oGther-' rre~ suarer in the history. ofthe<br />
Commonwealth. When the Labor Party were in off Ice some vidous<br />
tax avoidance schemes emerged they even spolce aboutit; bthe<br />
never legislated.__ Mr. Hayden had a long while when he kiould toave<br />
done something andike did nothing. The ax~ ayerst Associaitiol,<br />
M'r. Risstrom, who_ haA a greato oncern with * these thingn * has~<br />
indicated that nobody could do better than John Howard... He abei<br />
down that track*---Now$ that'-not to-imy that other thinigalwill-not-il<br />
emerge, that you will not have to legislate agai-n,. but thereis no-*<br />
$ 1,000 million there for the ' lucking, as Mr. Hayden is trying t<br />
-suig est. ThaZ-is dried up.<br />
Harvey<br />
okay, let's take a look at some of the tdther.-issues<br />
emerged: defence.-W'hat sort-of impact do you b3,6ieva yoX. hxVe.-M8ad0--A<br />
with defence as an issue in this election. IDo -you think-, it ha.<br />
got home to people or they are just not caring-I<br />
2 </p>
<p>before me-on ma~ ny occasons, i Dirt less on trus campaign. Any<br />
election violence I condemn and condemn-abso-Iutvty---BtU<br />
Prime Minister has got to be able to go around the atrnets of : thiscountry. 19, 1-<br />
Harvey, 15/ 1.0/ 80 -3<br />
Prime Minister<br />
it has to some peoples but Ibelieve not adequately.,' We are.<br />
going to-uxpand-our dte~ ce forces very signif icantly. Ha yden<br />
has given the impression that he supports that. -But In-r-ac t*,<br />
he said that the future progranmmes will be under revie.-hti<br />
ominous. That leaves opien for cukking., endiaig,-the prograft~ f;<br />
But more important than thati the Americans. approached u. 4r<br />
relation to Cockburn Sound as a home or base port r do , fqtI<br />
know whether they are going to do it. They. are looking, -at-~<br />
Cockburn SimYd aloga e-thei--Tades to help have a permanent ' I<br />
and better force into the Endian ocean which would enormously be<br />
to Australia's advantage. They are after all our all"., ow<br />
Mr. Hayden has said he will not allow theim-there aO-4Ke--POr-----<br />
base port. I do not believe he would allow those B-526 toopera8tep:<br />
through Darwin under the only terms and conditions that would -be<br />
acceptable. of course Australian sovereignty must be mainftained*&amp; t<br />
but I do not believe when the crunch came that he would -AllOI<br />
The philosophical base of the Labor Party has been one which bal<br />
criticised the United Statesiand the United St~ test Presid. ncyi<br />
criticised their resistance tor-Soviet aggression inrAMghafqIstan,<br />
That does not provide a very happy relationship on which. ta*. uove8<br />
forward into the kind of partnership that we need in A very<br />
dif ficult and a very dnedwr.<br />
Harvey I<br />
Do you think it has been a campwign inWVrbKdiryfrTi~ Ii, haveplayed<br />
any sort of Fart on either side of the fence? IC'a n' t* hikin<br />
gpecifically of that incident~ the other day when a group of. LiberkL, a<br />
supporters caused Mr. Hayden there was-a-great des +: ef , trouble<br />
in one of his street walks, in fact he immediately canqelled thieam.,-<br />
Have you been able to find out, by the way, if that wasg delibeiaOs<br />
organised by the Liberal Party?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
I do not believe so. I have spoken to-people-i---ttre-areia;---IF air, I<br />
I have been told that there was just -an -operation ha ndinq ouit-<br />
Liberal tickets not meetings, but just handing out Liberal ticket<br />
and Liberal liter~ ature and that thooseLabor-Parpeople-Wiao<br />
wsoemreeh omwo smtleyt farnodm colausthseidde. thI ed oe lencotto kranotew -h'ocwam teh aat looncgc. u rrTehdei.,.~ twO bodie1<br />
No attempt to bring back the politics of fear and d ivisiont . that<br />
we saw_ n 1922.--<br />
Prime Minister<br />
I haivebeen Isubjfet ' to more violence, more attempted i ntimid. t ion,<br />
I think than any other present politician--Sir RobertI.. 6ensa4-ea' </p>
<p>Harvey, 1] 7I7D78O0 4-<br />
Harvey As does an opposition Leader.,<br />
Prime situationi in which violence or the threat of violence da':<br />
prevent that. I looked at the televiSton-.. h as i etoe h<br />
news at that time and certain ly those telIvision cAii~ bd enot<br />
picked up very much..<br />
Too much emphasis on telelvision has been a recurring thexitjI<br />
think by critics of election campaigns over the years. What -do*<br />
you thi-Ui1-of the politics of personality this time around?'<br />
Prime minister<br />
think-ej. g-t ions always ought to be . operated4 the Q<br />
policies, because it is policies that are going to determiine'the..,<br />
future of Australia. When I have criticised the Austrdlian _ Labot_'-<br />
Party I have sought to do it, as I believe, 0n the ba: 4ssof<br />
. policies. 1: think Mr. Hayden trying: to bring my incometa<br />
return into the matter and making implicatione. or innuendosin<br />
the way in which he originally did it T-mean_, heitxille<br />
wants to do it because it is done in the United-States, hu that.<br />
was a latter day justification I think. He had said " there arareports,<br />
there are rumours" about Fraser and the TaxatioiOffico<br />
and whatever, and challenging me to try-and cer,~.-p WUthat<br />
was just plain. low, scurrullous politicsi.-.<br />
Wmell-that gets aack to that-dirty tricks thing. . ii<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Well,--that is-dirty tricks if you like, But there have beo~<br />
other elements. I was on a talk-back programe this morningiwd<br />
I had some of the tapes of for example, Mr. Wran playA# bak<br />
to me things that he has said. Let me just give a couple. of<br />
examples. H~ e said that Caucus had not control over a -La1or, l eader,.-<br />
that a Labor leader-made the ecisions-WranasPeir<br />
knows that he must do what his Caucus tells, him. Hie a1006 kn~ w tha<br />
if and when that Caucus tells Mrdffayden to implement wealtht~ e<br />
and capital gains taxes on the assets and savings of AU9i=. ahiari.--.:,.<br />
families, it does not matter what Mr. Vayden says, he would ha'V/ e.<br />
to-' do it, or ship out. How -Mr. -Wrfra-as a Labor -Premisr, -can. get,--A<br />
up and say that Caucus' do not have a say in these things, 140t<br />
abare-f aced untruth. -Many things like that have been. 044in<br />
this particular campaign. Again, Mr. Wran said he was going tosl<br />
his house, and no way would there be a capital gains tax -on -that.<br />
But Mr. Hayden had given the exampl of pu! uzrL pki-peo'ra.<br />
house, and the sale price for the hoause, -in explaining how acap14,6<br />
gains tax would work. ' So how M4r. Wran, who Is* not'going to be thei<br />
to-influence policy hie I suppose one day will go back to beinc<br />
Premier of this State and do the job -he is paid for -can get ' up'and I </p>
<p>Harvey, 15/ 10/ 80<br />
Prime Minister ( continued)<br />
eay " no, not on houses", when Mr. Haydenv has ' said--quite plainly_<br />
yes, It will be on houses, again seems to me to be a barefaced<br />
Untruth. There has been a lot of this.<br />
Ha rve~ y<br />
You are calling them liars, Why ncat say<br />
Prime Min'ister<br />
i am not using that word. They use<br />
Harvyx That is the implication<br />
Prime Minister<br />
That is the implication, certainly. it.<br />
Ha rvey<br />
Well why not say it?<br />
Prime minister<br />
Be-c-ause rI-Thibt like Using that term. I think it debases 1<br />
the political debate. There has been a tactic of the Australian-<br />
Labor Party over years, when they do not like a policy, W; hen they<br />
do not like a fact, when they do not like something I sayi they<br />
just say " that is a lie, that is a deliberate lie". But that ' is<br />
not the rebuttal of the argument. People who uee those eius*'<br />
generally do it because they do not have an ana-wer to the arguimumt<br />
itself. I wouild sooner resgond to these things -instead of-caliling<br />
Mr. Wran a liar over that Caucus remark, just remind pepple2 of.-<br />
-th-e facts, which everyone knows when it is-brQug~ ht to-the i<br />
attention: that Caucus' do control Premdere or" Labor Pin 1ps~.<br />
Then' the people can read the imPlications tor themselves. twil<br />
rebutt argument with argument, But on so many, occasions -the<br />
Labor Party have not. They have resorted to the use of. hose<br />
terms -lie, lie -because they-do not have an answer..<br />
~._ yo6 could start -the6 campaign again, wh! aq -wtd yudodfe~&amp;-<br />
~ it the reasons for. queictlon<br />
is the worse campA ign. I have ever geiyi<br />
stiff. prime minister<br />
No. I made that statement during that week that there waes. l1o. t t<br />
of complacency around and there was a lot of complacency . xiw. id<br />
There was a universal acceptance that the Government ' would getback<br />
with a large majority. Then the polls started to come out,<br />
shaking that complacency out of the hair. But r had detec-ted-. that;<br />
5 </p>
<p>Harvey, 15/ 10/ 80 6<br />
Prime Minister( continued)<br />
before the polls came out, as you know. I was worried about<br />
it because I know quite well you do not fight polls or elections<br />
in that sort of frame of mind. That affects if people are.<br />
complacent like that if affects your whole organisation. Thereis<br />
an interaction then between politicians. The campaign.<br />
since then I think. has gone in a lively way. it has been well<br />
organised. It-e-etting out-amongst the people, and quite a<br />
different scene.<br />
Harvey But the polls-are sti+ 4-very bad-feE-you. This time in ' 77<br />
they were starting to indicate a Liberal win. Why is it still<br />
going wrong?<br />
prime Minister<br />
I think you would have to ask the polla-that and ask the people<br />
who are putting their mark on a bit of paper, but I believe very<br />
strongly that on Saturday the result will come out right. I<br />
-believe it for this reason<br />
Har-vey<br />
Tight? Prime Minister<br />
Oh, it might be tight, but I believe it will come out right,<br />
because people are not going to take a risk with their future.<br />
They know what happred from-9-72 to 1975. They can see now<br />
let's just use Labor's own figures they can see<br />
Harvey You keep digging up Whitlam.<br />
Prime Minister<br />
But the policies are the same, that is why The only diffetne I<br />
is. the leader. The policies are the same, the -ersonneLa7 õ l i<br />
largely the same. Not all, but larqel. : That'is the; nAitat nI<br />
thing. Bicj spending, hands off the unions,. and we have aeedW j'isatin<br />
the last couple of days today how the unions arestartinqgo<br />
dictate already-the tere-of-twhat a-Labor Government could' dr . wo6e 1-<br />
do. I<br />
Harvey.. But why isn't thi-getting-ttr ugh to -people? Why aren't they -I<br />
believing you? 7 </p>
<p>Hiarvey, 15108<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Wbhat.. has hapganid over the course of this last week -I -think<br />
these things are starting to crystall. ise in people's minds n'ow.<br />
They just do not seem to have emerged. They have been spoken. about<br />
often enough. I have spoken about the trad6 unions. But there<br />
has been more discussion in the media about polls than the:-<br />
substance of the issues. It has taken thiA-long for the issuesto<br />
start to-comne through, Even on their own figures, massivte:<br />
increases in spending. They have promised a total costing but<br />
they have not given us a total costing. Then, tax cuts which<br />
cannot be funded, which would be lost very qikic~ ly through-higher<br />
inf lation; and an approach to tUade unions that-would ee_-tainly<br />
lead to runaway wage pressures again-and lack. of campetitiv* nas<br />
in Australian industries. That is not just a qluestion -of being9.<br />
concerned for business, it is being concerned for the people Who<br />
will be employed because unless we sell Australian-made goods<br />
all around -the worj -WeF will no~ t e employing Auatralians.<br />
Now, people know that high inflation will destroy that baset.<br />
These issues, together with thke threat of highier taxation--even<br />
in the last_ 24 hours" Mr. Hfa * 1e has added one fur-ther confusio1 to<br />
the capital gains tax, wealth argument by saying that the.<br />
purpose of the Royal Coimmission is only to determine at what-level<br />
these taxei start. That is just anothek confusion, because'. thej<br />
went into this campaign with a firm policy to levy thase taxes.'<br />
Mr. Hayde e-have toa-h4ave them, they are overdue, and we need them<br />
to avoid jacking up old taxes. And they are his words, not mine.#<br />
Then, because they start to be unpopular they start to withdraw<br />
from these kinds of taxes. So, you are left with their economic<br />
policy in a total shambles; additional expenditure not funded<br />
and therefore inflationary; -haids-off approach to the. unidn'st.'<br />
and that again, scares people becausethey.. know-what unt~ m. d4 d'<br />
will do to this economy-and to the prospects of employ ing. More<br />
people; and an approach to tAxation which I believe man-'<br />
Australian families are now staxting to regard as totall<br />
terrifying, To tax at housie, -aMsr . Eha-ydfe-igave the an-1-<br />
you buy a house for something, you aell. it for a higher.. prie<br />
and to tax the difference. To tax the homes and the-aissetsof<br />
Australians. it is all very well to suggest now that they mighit<br />
ciJit for a little while. They have said so persisently-arid<br />
so often that they are going to do it. And whatever Hr. -layden has<br />
said, I do not believe be has the authority of Caucus for~ bis.'-:-.<br />
backtracking, and that Labor Caucus -which would have. W iffreitcomposition.<br />
anyway from the pr~ esent Caucus--,. can say t~ ii h<br />
platfem~, it was in the policy, it is a firm' comnmitmentix d<br />
it now.<br />
Any worries!, at all, about.$ atutday 2<br />
P'rime -Ministe~ r J<br />
The one abiding thing I have always had in._ politics is My. faith,-<br />
and belief in the commonsenee and decency of K5_ 0 taltan . m, 6r-an$.<br />
women, and of their pride in Australia. If it was not fo. that1<br />
r Would notr be in politics. Iwould get out and do som~ ffinfq' elee* </p>
<p>Hfarvey, 15/ 10/ 80 -8<br />
Vrime-Minister ( continued)<br />
But it is because of that belief, it is because of that,.<br />
conviction, that I believe they will pu~ t this country f irst-6<br />
I would only ask them one thing; when theyg9 0 itq that, polItn9:!<br />
booth to vote, think of their familieti, anjd:* hink of. ut&amp; i-<br />
Harvey Lot me ask you what may seem a slightly frivolous questio.,:'<br />
Prime Minister but it is important for those of us -at-<br />
Channel Nine if you--could watch-an OlU3tion coverage on. t<br />
Saturday night, as we will hope you will, which one would yixl<br />
watch? Prime Minister<br />
Well, speaking with you, I have got to say r -kouldwantr; to . Vtoh<br />
yours*<br />
okay. I was asked to ask that. As a matter of fact, w r<br />
putting up a big screen in the Southern Cross for yoa, so you 7<br />
can seei. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
