<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8462</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP CEREMONY TO MARK THE COMMENCEMENT OF CONSTRUCTION OF STAGE 1 OF THE ASSISI HOME FOR THE AGED 15 MARCH 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/03/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008462.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
CEREMONY TO MARK THE COMMENCEMENT OF CONSTRUCTION OF<br />
STAGE I OF THE ASSISI HOME FOR THE AGED<br />
MARCH 1992<br />
Your Grace, Mr Valmorbida, Ladies and gentlemen<br />
Each time we welcome to this country people who have been<br />
bold enough to move their homes, their affections and<br />
their allegiances across the world, I think we are the<br />
bolder for it.<br />
When people start a new life here they give new life to<br />
the nation as a whole.<br />
That is the history of this country. Migration has been<br />
our lifeblood and our strength.<br />
The energy and initiative migrants bring is vital to our<br />
economic health.<br />
The cultural diversity they bring makes us richer in<br />
countless ways.<br />
They open our eyes and our minds to the rest of the<br />
world. Quite simply migration makes Australia a better place,<br />
and better in the eyes of other nations.<br />
Italians have been migrating to Australia for a century<br />
and a half.<br />
There were Italians on the Australian goldfields. It was<br />
an Italian who wrote the classic account of the Eureka<br />
Stockade in 1854.<br />
Italians were pioneers in our horticultural and<br />
agricultural industries before World War II.<br />
Since World War II, of course, Italians have been perhaps<br />
the major players in transforming the cultural life of<br />
our cities and towns: while their hard work and<br />
PRIMIE MINISTER </p>
<p>initiative in all sectors of the economy has been of<br />
inestimable value to the nation's growth and wealth.<br />
But Italian people have been more than agents of change<br />
in Australia.<br />
They have been important in renewing old and essential<br />
values values which have at times shown signs of<br />
weakening. Italian people have been models for all Australians in<br />
the community spirit they have brought, their religious<br />
values, their7 commitment to family values and in their<br />
care for the aged.<br />
The Assisi Home for the Aged bears witness to all these<br />
things and I am therefore honoured and very grateful<br />
for your inviLtation to become your patron.<br />
The government is conscious that we must do all we can<br />
for the gener: ation which did so much for Australia.<br />
Obviously the Italian Australian community is aware of<br />
its responsibility, and I'm pleased to say that the<br />
government has matched this by providing $ 3.7 million to<br />
enable this great project to begin.<br />
Today I can assure the Italian community and all<br />
Australians, whatever their national origin, that we<br />
remain committed'to encouraging that climate of cultural<br />
diversity and freedom, tolerance and mutual respect,<br />
which are the true aims of multi-culturalism.<br />
We also remai~ n committed to caring for the aged to<br />
further expanding programs already much expanded in the<br />
1980s.<br />
As we undertaEke this essential work over the next few<br />
years the Assisi home is certain to be a model of what<br />
can be done by communities, and how they can work<br />
together With government.<br />
For their vision and dedication, I congratulate all those<br />
people who have taken on this project, and wish them well<br />
in the future! stages of its development.<br />
And thank you. for inviting me here. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
