<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3744</transcript-id>
    <title>QUEENSLAND BROADCAST NO 9 - AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT INSURANCE CORPORATION</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/05/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003744.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
. QUEENSLAND BROADCAST.. NOI... 9 ( qy'<br />
AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT INSURANCE CORPORATION<br />
LATELY ON RADIO AND TV AND IN THE NEWSPAPERS<br />
THERE S BEEN A HIGHLY EXTRAVAGANT AND TOTALLY MISLEADING<br />
CAMPAIGN BY THE INSURANCE COMPANIES AGAINST OUR PROPOSAL<br />
FOR AN AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT INSURANCE CORPORATION, THE<br />
AIR HAS BEEN THICK WITH CRIES OF NATIONALISATION,<br />
SOCIALISM AND GENERAL DISASTER. LAST TIME WE HAD A<br />
CAMPA. IGN OF THIS KIND, YOU LL REMEMBER, IT WAS THE DOCTORS<br />
CRUSADING AGAINST MEDIBANK BUT AS SOON AS PEOPLE<br />
REALISED THE TRUE BENEFITS OF ' EDIBANK THE WHOLE<br />
CAMPAIGN COLLAPSED, SO I MAKE THIS PREDICTION: WHEN<br />
PEOPLE uNDERSTAND WHAT OUR INSURANCE PROPOSALS REALLY<br />
MEAN, THE CAMPAIGN BY THE JNSURANCE INTERESTS MANY<br />
OF THEM FOREIGN OWNED WILL BE EXPOSED JUST AS<br />
QUICKLY AS THE FALSE PROPAGANDA FROM THE DOCTORS, </p>
<p>-2-<br />
BASICALLY, WHAT WE ARE DOING IS ESTABLISHING A<br />
GOVERNMENT INSURANCE COMPANY TO COMPETE WITH THE<br />
PRIVATE INSURANCE FIRMS, YOU MAY ASK: WHY HAVE A<br />
GOVERNMENT CORPORATION WHEN THERE ARE PLENTY OF<br />
PRIVATE INSURANCE COMPANIES ALREADY PROVIDING A GOOD<br />
SERVICE TO THE PUBLIC? THERE ARE TWO MAIN REASONS,<br />
THE FIRST IS COMPETITION, THE MORE COMPETITION<br />
GENUINE COMPETITION THERE IS IN ANY INDUSTRY,<br />
THE BETTER THE SERVICE TO THE PUBLIC AND THE CHEAPER<br />
THE RATES. THE SECOND REASON IS WIDER COVERAGE.<br />
THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT INSURANCE CORPORATION<br />
WILL BE PROVIDING INSURANCE COVER THAT CANNOT BE<br />
OBTAINED FROM TH1-E OTHER COMPANIES, EITHER BECAUSE<br />
THEY'RE NOT INTERESTED OR BECAUSE IT'S NOT<br />
SUFFICIENTLY PROFITABLE,. ./ 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
THE PEOPLE OF BRISBANE HAD THEIR OWN HARSH EXPERIENCE<br />
OF THIS PROBLEM DURING THE FLOODS AT THE BEGINNING OF<br />
LAST ? EAR. AT THE TIME OF THE FLOODS, THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
GOVERNMENT ACTED PROMPTLY AND GENEROUSLY TO PROVIDE<br />
RELIEF AND THE NECESSARY FUNDS FOR THE TASK OF REPAIR<br />
AND RECONSTRUCTION. WE DIDN'T STINT ON THAT. BUT<br />
THOUSANDS OF BRISBANE RESIDENTS FOUND THAT-THEIR<br />
HOUSEHOLD POLICIES SIMPLY DIDN IT COVER THEM AGAINST<br />
FLOOD DAMAGE., DARWI-N PEOPLE HAD THE SAME EXPERIENCE<br />
AFTER THE CYCLONE LAST ClI11RISTi1AS, THE ONLY PEOPLE FULLY<br />
COVERED IN THE FLOODS OR IN THE CYCLONE WERE THOSE<br />
INSURED UNDER THE DEFENCE SERVICE HOMES SCHEME<br />
ADMINISTERED BY THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT. THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
GOVERNMENT INSURANCE CORPORATION WILL PROVIDE SUCH<br />
INSURANCE FOR EVERYONE WHO NEEDS IT -AND PROVIDE IT<br />
AT THE LOWEST POSSIBLE COST. IT WILL OPEN THE WAY<br />
TO MORE WIDESPREAD INSURANCE COVERAGE AGAINST LIVESTOCK<br />
AND CROP LOSSES ARISING OUT OF NATURAL DISASTERS, SO IT<br />
WILL BE OF PARTICULAR VALUE TO THE MAN ON THE LAND$ @ 9IA </p>
<p>-4-<br />
I DO ASK YOU TO IGNORE THIS ABSURD TALK ABOUT<br />
NATIONALISATION, SINCE WHEN HAS IT BEEN<br />
" NATIONALISATION" FOR GOVERNMENT ENTERPRISES TO<br />
COMPETE FAIRLY AND ON EQUAL TERMS WITH PRIVATE<br />
ENTERPRISE? THERE ARE MANY EXAMPLES OF SUCH<br />
COMPETITION, H' 1O ONE SUGGESTS THAT THE COMMONWEALTH<br />
BANK ISN'T COMPETING FAIRLY WITH THE PRIVATE BANKS<br />
AND NO ONE SUGGESTS THAT THE BANKS HAVE BEEN<br />
NATIONALISED, No ONE SUGGESTS THAT THE AIRLINES<br />
HAVE BEEN NATIONALISED BECAUSE TAA IS COMPETING WITH<br />
ANSETT, IN EVERY CASE THE BENEFITS OF SUCH<br />
COMPETITION HAVE BEEN PLAIN. FOR EXAMPLE, IT'S<br />
CHEAPER TO INSURE YOUR HOUSE WITH THE COMMONWEALTH<br />
SAVING BANK INSURANCE SCHEME THAN WITH ANY PRIVATE<br />
INSURANCE COMPANY, IF THE COMINONWEALTH BANK CAN DO<br />
THIS FOR ITS CUSTOMERS, WHY SHOULDN T THE SAME LOW.<br />
PREMIUMS BE AVAILABLE TO EVERY HOUSEHOLDER? WE WANT<br />
TO SEE THAT THEY ARE$ </p>
<p>IT'S WORTH REMEMBERING THAT EVERY STATE<br />
HAS HD A STATE GOVERNMENT INSURANCE OFFICE<br />
FOR MANY YEARS, AND VERY EFFICIENT ENTERPRISES<br />
MOST OF THEM HAVE BEEN. HERE IN QUEENSLAND YOU HAVE<br />
A STATE GOVERNMENT INSURANCE OFFICE THE SGIO:<br />
ITS BUILDING IS A PROMINENT LANDMARK IN BRISBANE.<br />
I DON'T SUPPOSE EVEN MR BJELKE-PETERSEN WOULD<br />
SUGGEST THAT INSURANCE IN QUEENSLAND HAS BEEN<br />
NATIONALISED. THE FACT IS THAT UNDER THE<br />
CONSTITUTION THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT HAS AS<br />
MUCH RIGHT TO ESTABLISH AN INSURANCE CORPORATION AS<br />
IT HAS TO ESTABLISH A BANK, IT HAS AS MUCH RIGHT<br />
TO ESTABLISH AN INSURANCE CORPORATION AS THE STATE<br />
GOVERNMENTS HAVE, ! O ONE TODAY WOULD DREAM OF<br />
DISBANDING OR RESTRICTING THE OPERATIONS OF THE<br />
STATE GOVERNMENT INSURANCE OFFICES. THEY HAVE<br />
SERVED THE PUBLIC WELL. THEY WILL CONTINUE TO DO<br />
SO, / 6 </p>
<p>REMEMBER THIS: FOR ALL THEIR PATRIOTIC TALK,<br />
A LARGE PART OF THE INSURANCE INDUSTRY IN AUSTRALIA<br />
IS CONTROLLED DY OVERSEAS INTERESTS, LESS THAN<br />
TWO YEARS AGO THE LEVEL OF FOREIGN OWNERSHIP OF<br />
GENERAL INSURANCE BUSINESS CONDUCTED IN AUSTRALIA<br />
WAS NEARLY 46%. A GREAT DEAL OF AUSTRALIAN MONEY<br />
IS BEING CHANNELLED TO FOREIGN COUNTRIES, I KNOW<br />
THERE ARE SOME GREAT AUSTRALIAN FIRMS, AND I PAY<br />
TRIBUTE TO THEM; BUT AN AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT<br />
INSURANCE CORPORATION WILL HELP REDUCE THE FLOW OF<br />
FUNDS OUT OF AUSTRALIA AND COULD WELL ENCOURAGE MORE<br />
MONEY INTO AUSTRALIA, GENUINE AUSTRALIAN-OWNED<br />
INSURANCE COMPANIES HAVE MUCH MORE TO FEAR FROM<br />
GRO'ING FOREIGN COMPETITION THAN THEY HAVE FROM<br />
COMPETITION FROM AN AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT CORPORATION.<br />
WE'VE MADE IT PERFECTLY CLEAR THAT ACROSS THE GREAT<br />
RANGE OF ITS BUSINESS, THE GOVERNMENT INSURANCE<br />
CORPORATION WILL BE OPERATING ON EXACTLY THE<br />
SAME COMMERCIAL AND COMPETITIVE LINES AS THE REST OF<br />
THE INDUSTRY, ANY SUGGESTION THAT IT WILL BE GIVEN<br />
UNFAIR ADVANTAGE IS SIMPLY UNTRUE. UP TO NOW, THE<br />
UNFAIR ADVANTAGE HAS BEEN WITH THE PRIVATE COMPANIES,<br />
THEY HAVE' LAVISHED FUNDS ON EXPENSIVE OFFICE<br />
BUILDINGS AND IN SPECULATIVE REAL ESTATE<br />
DEVELOPN. ThTS; THEIR INVESTMENT IN HOUSING LOANS HAS<br />
FALLEN STEEPLY, A LARGE PART OF THEIR FUNDS HAS GONE<br />
OVERSEAS; AND IMPORTANT FIELDS OF INSURANCE IAVE BEEN<br />
NEGLECTED, </p>
<p>-7-<br />
REMEMBER THESE FACTS NEXT TIME YOU SEE YOUR<br />
PREMIUMS BEING WASTED ON COSTLY AND MISLEADING<br />
ADVERTISING, AIMED AT A GOVERNMENT INSURANCE<br />
CORPORATION THAT WILL PROVIDE MUCH NEEDED<br />
COMPETITION, AND A COMPREHENSIVE INSURANCE COVER<br />
FOR ALL AUSTRALIANS WHO NEED IT, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
