<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2082</transcript-id>
    <title>PRESS STATEMENT: MECHANICAL INSPECTION OF LONG-DISTANCE BUSES</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/07/1969</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002082.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS STATEMENT 30 JUL<br />
MECHANICAL INSPECTTION OF LONG-DISTANCE BUSES<br />
( Statement by the Ministers)<br />
Minimum safety inspection standards will be drawn up<br />
for long-distance tourist buses operating throughout Australia.<br />
This was decided today ( July 10) by Commonwealth and<br />
State Transport Ministers meeting in Port Moresby as the<br />
Australian Transport Advisory Council.<br />
The Ministers have asked the Advisory Committee on<br />
Vehicle Performance to prepare the standards together with a<br />
time scale for their introduction.<br />
They also asked the Standing Committee of Advisers to<br />
closely examine the question of adequate enforcement of such a<br />
standard by means of periodic and random inspections.<br />
All Ministers agreed with the serious concern expressed<br />
about the road-worthiness of tourist coaches in a paper presented<br />
to the meeting by the N. S. W. Minister.<br />
The item was raised following a number of serious<br />
accidents involving long-distance buses in which a number of<br />
people were killed and injured.<br />
The matter of tourist vehicle road-worthiness was of<br />
the utmost importance because large numbers of people were<br />
exposed to risk in any accident involving a bus, and also because<br />
the good safety record of the industry should be maintained in<br />
the interest of tourism.<br />
PORT MORESBY, T . P. N. G.<br />
CANBERRA, A. C. T. 10 JULY 1970 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
