<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8908</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP BUSINESS RECEPTION AND CEREMONIES SHANGHAI-SATURDAY, 26 JUNE 1993</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/06/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008908.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATIG MP<br />
BUSIES RECEPTIO AMD CMINIS<br />
SHAHIM SAURDAY, 26 JUNK 1993<br />
It is fitting that my last public speaking opportunity on<br />
this visit to Korea and China, should be to a<br />
predominantly business audience.<br />
This visit has been very much about business: about<br />
impressing on our hosts how much Australia has to offer;<br />
about. encouraging and supporting Australian firms already<br />
out in the international field; and about sending clear<br />
signals to the business community back home about what<br />
can be achieved.<br />
Let me say that my task has been made a lot easier in the<br />
last few days by seeing first-hand how successful<br />
Australian companies have been in establishing critical<br />
business relationships in this country.<br />
The scoreboard is impressive. In Beijing, I attended<br />
ribbon cutting ceremonies for four new ventures involving<br />
Alcatel, AAP, the ANZ Banking Group and Cadbury<br />
Schweppes. In Shanghai today I participated in a<br />
foundation stone-laying ceremony for the new Shanghai<br />
Fosters Brewery.<br />
Ind here this evening we are celebrating two other recent<br />
events: the opening of the Australian Wool Corporation's<br />
Shanghai office; and ACI's conclusion of a joint venture<br />
for the establishment of two plants one in Shanghai and<br />
one in Guangzhou. which are expected to make it the<br />
biggest manufacturer of glass containers in China.<br />
As well, I know there are representatives here from other<br />
Australian companies, like Suspension Components, who are<br />
setting up in Shanghai.<br />
In naming these recent successes I should not overlook<br />
the achievements of many other Australian companies.<br />
Even before these recent announcements there were an<br />
estimated 540 Australian companies operating in China.<br />
But what is remarkable about the list of companies I've<br />
named is the diversity. </p>
<p>r rom the Wool Corporation, representing one of our<br />
oldest and most valuable comodity exports.<br />
To Alcatel and AAP, involved with Chinese partners<br />
in sophisticated communications technology.<br />
From the ANZ Banking Group, whose new branch here in<br />
shangha-i will signal Australian competitiveness in<br />
the services sector.<br />
To joint ventures in sophisticated goods-processing<br />
and packaging and industrial components.<br />
I congratulate all of these companies for their<br />
enterprise. Their achievements leave no doubt about our ability . to<br />
succeed here in China and elsewhere in the region and<br />
that is a message I will be taking home to Australia.<br />
The integration of our economy with Asia is not a<br />
speculative venture but a fact waiting to happen.<br />
That doesn't mean it will be easy. I daresay there is no<br />
one in this room who would say that it has been easy, but<br />
equally I doubt if there is anyone who would not say that<br />
it was a chance that had to be grasped.<br />
And I'm sure that ACI and the Australian Wool Corporation<br />
would be among these.<br />
Let me congratulate them both, and now please join me in<br />
a toast to them, and indeed to the success of all<br />
Australian business endeavours here in Saga<br />
China, and throughout the region. Shgai. i </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
