<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11374</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                  THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                  ADDRESS AT WA CHAMBER OF COMMERCE &amp;amp; INDUSTRY COCKTAIL RECEPTION                                  HILTON, PERTH                                             SUBJECTS: Taxation reform, Commonwealth/State financial relations,                 industrial relations.</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/04/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...................................................................................................</p>
<p>Thank you very much Tony. To the Lord Mayor of Perth and to my ministerial</p>
<p> colleagues in the Government of Western Australia, ladies and gentlemen.</p>
<p>It is true that I am the first Prime Minister to go to Kalgoorlie</p>
<p> for 18 years and I am here alive and well to report to you that the</p>
<p> locals were very friendly and very pleased to see me and they had</p>
<p> one or two things to say about the mining industry and those views</p>
<p> were expressed in characteristically clearly understood, monosyllabic,</p>
<p> you know, direct terms.</p>
<p>But, ladies and gentlemen, thank you very much for the opportunity</p>
<p> of talking to such a cross-section of the business community of Perth</p>
<p> and Western Australia. I, of course, have had a long association with</p>
<p> Perth and this Chamber and its various antecedents over the years</p>
<p> in the different positions I have held in both Government and opposition.</p>
<p> And it really couldn't be a more appropriate time as we have</p>
<p> begun the countdown to the final vote on the goods and service tax,</p>
<p> it couldn't be a more appropriate time for me to address this</p>
<p> gathering and to say a few words about the Government's attitude</p>
<p> to the ongoing challenge of economic reform.</p>
<p>Can I reassure your acting President and all of you that the Government</p>
<p> remains very committed indeed to an ongoing economic reform agenda.</p>
<p> We are not committed to an ongoing economic reform agenda out of some</p>
<p> ideological commitment towards change for changes sake. I don't</p>
<p> believe in change for changes sake. I have often described myself</p>
<p> as a discerning radical or a selective conservative. That is I believe</p>
<p> in changing things that need change and I believe in preserving things</p>
<p> that continue to work. And I think the idea that you have got to change</p>
<p> everything just because it's been around for a while unless there's</p>
<p> a valid reason for doing so is a very foolish approach. But equally</p>
<p> when something doesn't work and when something is in need of</p>
<p> overhaul and change you have got to have the foresight and the courage</p>
<p> to pursue that change.</p>
<p>And that is certainly the case with Australia's taxation system.</p>
<p> As some of you will know, I have been campaigning for reforming the</p>
<p> Australian taxation system for probably 20 years. I have believed</p>
<p> as I am sure most people in this room have believed for a very long</p>
<p> time that the single biggest change that is needed to the Australia</p>
<p> taxation system is to replace the ramshackle indirect tax system that</p>
<p> we have at the present time which is replete with numerous inefficiencies</p>
<p> and inequities with a simple, across the board, broad-based indirect</p>
<p> tax, a goods and services tax.</p>
<p>We hear a lot about this or that model. Senator Lees of the Australian</p>
<p> Democrats today said that we should adopt the Irish model. Now, I</p>
<p> love the Irish, I really do. Having seen Paddy Hannan's handy</p>
<p> work in Kalgoorlie today I could hardly not. But for heaven's</p>
<p> sake why can't we for once have an Australian model? Why can't</p>
<p> we have a model that is suitable for Australia as we come towards</p>
<p> the end of this century and this millennium and we are on the verge</p>
<p> of the 21st century? And the tax plan that we took to the</p>
<p> last election was designed to underwrite the continued economic growth</p>
<p> of our nation into the next century. Not only does it sweep away the</p>
<p> ramshackle indirect tax system we have at the present time and replace</p>
<p> it with an exporter friendly broad-based indirect tax which is of</p>
<p> enormous benefit to all Australian exporters and to all Australian</p>
<p> businesses, but it also brings in unprecedented reductions in personal</p>
<p> income tax. In all the debate about whether you should have or not</p>
<p> have food included many people have forgotten the fact that under</p>
<p> our plan 80 per cent of Australians will be on a top marginal rate</p>
<p> of no more than 30 cents in the dollar. And that will inject an enormous</p>
<p> amount of incentive into the work effort of many low and middle income</p>
<p> earners in our community. And of equal importance is the absolutely</p>
<p> spectacular revolution in Commonwealth/State financial relations that</p>
<p> our plan represents.</p>
<p>Now, all of you are familiar with the charade and the nonsense that</p>
<p> often attends Premiers conferences in this State. One by one the Premiers</p>
<p> come, they stop at the doors of Parliament House in Canberra, they</p>
<p> give a doorstop saying that they have been short-changed by the Commonwealth,</p>
<p> we have a meeting and they come out and they say nothing has changed,</p>
<p> the Commonwealth is still short-changing us. But we had a meeting</p>
<p> last Friday week, Max Evans was there, it's the best Premiers'</p>
<p> Conference I have ever been to. I have only ever been to them, of</p>
<p> course, as either a Federal Treasurer or as the Prime Minister but</p>
<p> the ones that I have been to over the years none of them have been</p>
<p> as good as the one last Friday week. And the reason the one last Friday</p>
<p> week was so good was that all of us recognise that we are actually</p>
<p> participating in making a bit of economic and financial history in</p>
<p> this country.</p>
<p>We were signing a document that committed the governments of the six</p>
<p> States and the two territories of Australia and the Commonwealth Government</p>
<p> to a new financial deal that would secure the taxation base of the</p>
<p> Australian States into the next century. Year after year Premiers</p>
<p> quite properly, Charles Court did it, Richard Court has done it, Jeff</p>
<p> Kennett has done it, other Premiers have done it over the years, have</p>
<p> said what the States want is access to a growth tax so that they can</p>
<p> support and have underwritten their responsibilities in areas such</p>
<p> as government schools and police and roads and hospitals.</p>
<p>And under our plan, all of the revenue from the goods and services</p>
<p> tax, every last dollar of that revenue will go to the Australian States.</p>
<p> And can I say to those, and I know there are many here tonight who</p>
<p> are quite properly and very proudly concerned about the activities</p>
<p> of the welfare sector in Australia and many here tonight are directly</p>
<p> involved in helping the less fortunate in our community, that the</p>
<p> best way that you can help the provision of welfare in this country</p>
<p> is to underwrite the taxation base of the Australian States. Because</p>
<p> unless you have a situation where the Australian States have access</p>
<p> to a growth tax they are not going to be able to fund all of those</p>
<p> basic day to day services that are needed and are provided in our</p>
<p> system of government overwhelmingly by the State governments rather</p>
<p> than the Commonwealth Government.</p>
<p>And under our plan, by the year 2005 the Australian States collectively</p>
<p> will receive $2.9 billion a year more than they would under the current</p>
<p> arrangements. And that amount over time will grow. And I would say</p>
<p> to every Labor and Democrat Senator from Western Australia that if</p>
<p> you vote against our plan you are voting against the Federal Government</p>
<p> giving the Western Australian Government more money in the years ahead</p>
<p> so that that money can be spent on schools and roads and police and</p>
<p> health services.</p>
<p>So this is not just a debate about indirect taxation reform, it's</p>
<p> not just a debate about cutting personal income tax, it is also a</p>
<p> debate about reforming the economic and financial structure of the</p>
<p> federation. And it has needed that reform for a very long period of</p>
<p> time. We took an enormous risk politically in going to the last election</p>
<p> with a goods and services tax in our campaign satchel. There were</p>
<p> many people who said to me, you are mad, there at some stages during</p>
<p> the campaign and I thought they were probably right. But in the end</p>
<p> we were able to win the election and no government in my recollection</p>
<p> has gone to the people with such a detailed plan in such a fundamental</p>
<p> area and been elected. I can't recall a previous government going</p>
<p> with such a detailed plan.</p>
<p>And I would say to those in the Senate who are now debating this legislation</p>
<p> and are now pontificating about what is right or what is wrong to</p>
<p> the Australian people. I just remind them that we had a vote about</p>
<p> that last October. If I had gone to the last election and said I am</p>
<p> going to reform the taxation system and said nothing more then they</p>
<p> might have an argument. If I'd have gone to the last election</p>
<p> as I did to the previous election ruling out a goods and services</p>
<p> tax they might have an argument. But we went to the last election</p>
<p> and put all our cards on the table, we explained it in minute detail.</p>
<p> We had the taxation scales, we have it all fully costed, we have it</p>
<p> all verified by the Treasury, they couldn't blow any holes in</p>
<p> the sums or any of the calculations. We couldn't have been more</p>
<p> open and candid and forthright. And in those circumstances if the</p>
<p> word mandate means anything in Australian politics we have a mandate</p>
<p> with a capital M' to see that legislation pass through</p>
<p> the Australian Senate.</p>
<p>And that is the view, might I tell you, of the Premiers even the Labor</p>
<p> Premiers of Australia. At the meeting last Friday week Peter Beattie</p>
<p> said to me, you have a mandate Prime Minister to introduce the goods</p>
<p> and services tax. It may not be the policy of my party, he said, but</p>
<p> you have a mandate to introduce it. And he was perfectly happy as</p>
<p> Labor Premier of Queensland to sign up. Bob Carr was more than happy</p>
<p> to sign up. I am quite sure he regards it as a very good deal. He</p>
<p> goes through the motions of saying, oh, of course you understand I</p>
<p> understand I don't agree with this but sighs "marvellous".</p>
<p> But of course he would do that. And why wouldn't he? Because</p>
<p> like every other Premier the States are going to benefit from this.</p>
<p> I can't think of any other way to break the sort of a log jam</p>
<p> of Commonwealth/State financial relations, and in the long run if</p>
<p> you secure the revenue base of the States you are going to provide</p>
<p> it.</p>
<p>So can I say to all of you that the Government remains very strongly</p>
<p> committed to the cause of economic reform. We don't believe in</p>
<p> reform for its own sake. We believe in it where it's necessary</p>
<p> and in the globalised economy in which we now all live we have no</p>
<p> alternative but to reform and to keep going forward. It's not</p>
<p> a question of how well you're doing with how you were doing 30</p>
<p> years ago or five years ago, it's a question of how well you</p>
<p> were doing with your competitors in the international environment.</p>
<p> And I'm very proud of the fact that over the last two or three</p>
<p> years this country has been able to stare down the worst of the Asian</p>
<p> economic downturn.</p>
<p>And one of the reasons that we are listened to with greater respect</p>
<p> in the Asia-Pacific region now is that we are stronger economically</p>
<p> than what we were a few years ago. It's funny like that. You</p>
<p> find it in your own business experiences, you find it at a government</p>
<p> level. You go to international forums with a strong economy and one</p>
<p> that's performing better than most you are listened to a lot</p>
<p> more than if your economy is just part of the also-rans. When I because</p>
<p> Prime Minister I had the sense that Australia was the anxious outsider</p>
<p> seeking admission to the rich club of the Asian-Pacific region. All</p>
<p> of that has changed over the last two or three years partly because</p>
<p> of the unfortunate of many of our friends in the Asia region but also</p>
<p> because Australia has done better than many people expected. We have</p>
<p> got our budget in order. We have a very strong fiscal position. We</p>
<p> may have a current account deficit now but is a little higher than</p>
<p> it was a year or two ago. But it's not of the same concern as</p>
<p> it would have been at that same level if our budget was still in deficit,</p>
<p> our inflation was high and our interest rates were high. We can service</p>
<p> that current account deficit. We can service it very comfortably because</p>
<p> the ratio of our export income to our GDP which is the determinant</p>
<p> of how you can service a current account deficit is much better now</p>
<p> than it's been for something like 10 or 15 years.</p>
<p>Now, all of these things speak of a strong economy. They speak of</p>
<p> an economy that has helped Australia ride out the Asian economic downturn.</p>
<p> But I don't come here proclaiming complacency or smugness. I</p>
<p> recognise as I said in Kalgoorlie earlier today that there are a lot</p>
<p> of challenges for the mining industry. Not only in Western Australia</p>
<p> but throughout Australia. And I want to make it very plain that none</p>
<p> of the policies of my Government are directed towards picking favourites</p>
<p> amongst the industry sectors of Australia. I know the importance of</p>
<p> service industries, and information technology industries, and high</p>
<p> tech industries to Australia's futures. But I also recognise</p>
<p> the ongoing contribution of the mining sector, the farm sector and</p>
<p> manufacturing. And any suggestion that our Government in some way</p>
<p> seeks to align itself with this or that sector of industry has been</p>
<p> the industry or the sector for the future is completely wrong. We</p>
<p> will always need a very strong mining industry in Australia, we'll</p>
<p> always need a strong manufacturing industry, and we'll always</p>
<p> need to have policies that first and foremost promote the maximum</p>
<p> level of economic growth.</p>
<p>Part of the taxation plan of course is to reform business taxation.</p>
<p> You are aware of the work of the Ralph Committee and you are aware</p>
<p> of the debate that is going on in general terms at the moment within</p>
<p> the business community about what is roughly called a trade off between</p>
<p> the removal of some of the existing tax concessions in return for</p>
<p> a 30% company tax rate. Now we have not made any decision on that</p>
<p> and I know that there are a variety of views within the Australian</p>
<p> business community. There's probably a variety of views in this</p>
<p> room tonight. I certainly got a very strong view on that subject when</p>
<p> I went to Kalgoorlie, but I equally got a very strong view from other</p>
<p> sections of industry in the opposition direction as I've travelled</p>
<p> around other parts of Australia. And we're going to listen to</p>
<p> all of those views and we're going to assimilate it all before</p>
<p> we reach a decision.</p>
<p>But we are committed, ladies and gentlemen, to an ongoing reformist</p>
<p> approach to the management of the Australia economy. I'm very</p>
<p> proud of what we've achieved. I'm very proud of the fact</p>
<p> that we stuck to our guns in reforming the Australian industrial relations</p>
<p> system. There is more work to do in that area. As I look around the</p>
<p> room tonight I can see a few veterans of the debate about reforming</p>
<p> Australia's industrial relations system through the 1980s. And</p>
<p> one of the constituent elements of the Chamber from the 1980s was</p>
<p> amongst the strongest proponents of industrial relations reform. And</p>
<p> people like Brendan McCarthy and Lyndon Rowe, and Ross McLean, and</p>
<p> others fought very hard against those within sections of industry</p>
<p> in other parts of Australia who wanted to cling to the old failing</p>
<p> industrial relations system that was built on the corporatist approach</p>
<p> of letting everything be run by the Industrial Relations Commission.</p>
<p>Now, we have brought in a new era in industrial relations. We are</p>
<p> seeing an historic change in community attitudes. We've achieved</p>
<p> it with a minimum of industrial disputation. In fact the number of</p>
<p> days lost through strikes last year was the lowest for 83 years. Despite</p>
<p> the fierce opposition of many sections of the media and other sections</p>
<p> of the community we did achieve lasting change in relation to the</p>
<p> waterfront. It's almost a year now since the waterfront dispute.</p>
<p> And although it took a number of turns that people didn't expect,</p>
<p> the bottom line is that the Australian waterfront will never be the</p>
<p> same again. And there are sections of the Australian waterfront that</p>
<p> are now enjoying much higher productivity. And the action taken by</p>
<p> the Patricks company and the support given to the reform process by</p>
<p> the Federal Government has resulted in fundamental change on the Australian</p>
<p> waterfront.</p>
<p>There is still work to be done, there are still further reforms to</p>
<p> be achieved. But it's an area where through a very, very difficult</p>
<p> time we have begun to see the benefits and the fruits of the Government</p>
<p> having taken a very firm line in relation to industrial reform on</p>
<p> the Australian waterfront. The reform process, when you are managing</p>
<p> a modern economy, is never finished. We are living in a very, very</p>
<p> fascinating time economically. The American economy is performing</p>
<p> better than it's performed probably at any time since the end</p>
<p> of World War II. The American economy has out performed the expectations</p>
<p> of many of the best observers of economic performance in that country</p>
<p> for many years. It may well be that the American economy and other</p>
<p> economies have reached a new and higher threshold of performance and</p>
<p> efficiency. I can well remember a conversation I had with the Chairman</p>
<p> of the American Federal Reserve, Alan Greenspan in Washington almost</p>
<p> two years ago. And I said to him: how is it that the American economy's</p>
<p> going so well? Do you believe it's going to continue? And he</p>
<p> said: I've been in this business for a long time. And he said:</p>
<p> I have to say to you that I can't believe the numbers that I'm</p>
<p> seeing. And if you ask my do I know why it's all happening, he</p>
<p> said, I have to say to you I'm not entirely sure, and I've</p>
<p> been an economist all my life. But he said: I think it may have something</p>
<p> to do with the fact that we are getting the full benefit of the enormous</p>
<p> investment that our country has made in technology, and the enormous</p>
<p> investment that our country has made in reform and modernisation.</p>
<p> And it's probably, as a statement, had more impact on me than</p>
<p> just about any other statement that's been made to me on economic</p>
<p> matters in the time that I've been Prime Minister. And it drove</p>
<p> home to me the fact that we may in fact be entering an era where the</p>
<p> efficiencies of economies and the efficiencies of economic performance</p>
<p> are delivering new possibilities and new openings.</p>
<p>Ladies and gentlemen, thank you very much to the members of this Chamber</p>
<p> for the support you have all given to the cause of economic reform</p>
<p> and many of the economic debates over recent years. The Australian</p>
<p> economy is strong. The Australian economy is doing better than most.</p>
<p> The Australian economy will remain strong. The Government will remain</p>
<p> absolutely committed to economic reform. We will remain absolutely</p>
<p> committed to taxation reform, absolutely committed to further industrial</p>
<p> relations reform. Having got the budget back into surplus we have</p>
<p> no intention of squandering that surplus on a new splurge of unnecessary</p>
<p> Federal government spending. You have lower interest rates now because</p>
<p> the budget is in surplus. If we hadn't wiped out that $10.5 billion</p>
<p> deficit interest rates in Australia would not be as low as they are</p>
<p> now and the benefits of those low interest rates would not be flowing</p>
<p> through, not only to small business people, but also to homebuyers.</p>
<p>Ladies and gentlemen, it's great to be back here in Perth. It's</p>
<p> a different city, it's a city with a great entrepreneurial spirit.</p>
<p> I've always enjoyed visiting it. You always get good value coming</p>
<p> to Perth in terms of getting a direct and frank reading on what's</p>
<p> happening, not only here in Western Australia but also around the</p>
<p> country. I'm occasionally reminded when I come to Western Australia</p>
<p> the contribution that your economy makes to the national economy.</p>
<p> Those export figures are permanently emblazoned in my political consciousness.</p>
<p> And why shouldn't you boast a bit about it because this State</p>
<p> does make an enormous contribution to the export earnings in particular</p>
<p> of our nation.</p>
<p>But it's great to be amongst you. We've got a lot of things</p>
<p> to do. We've achieved a lot over the last three years but we've</p>
<p> only really begun. And if we can maintain the reform process, we can</p>
<p> get that GST through, get that new taxation system operating, then</p>
<p> the opportunities for this country into the next century truly are</p>
<p> quite amazing and potentially quite unlimited. Thank you.</p>
<p> [ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
