<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>763</transcript-id>
    <title>LORD PROVOST&#039;S LUNCHEON, EDINBURGH, SCOTLAND - 1ST JULY 1963 - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/07/1963</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000763_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
WBD PROWOST'S WI~ I~ f INWB~~<br />
Lord Provost~. a drW rovest a<br />
Whn you wre telling as of this highly eradito<br />
note that Y" wo to yo thmen o if that Isun't a<br />
debsed ezpwesilem I was delighted it imiW e me of<br />
the met fbm~ smM alden Speaesh m made I&amp; a t1 ] buse of Comms<br />
vho ws the only 6Q; nsewtIm, I thiimft'h e great electin<br />
of 1" 6 to win a meat That immat n bee tifgo und<br />
himself as a am Member Met like mrslt, hely endowed with<br />
Impertinenc ( Laught.) a there heam ao the other side<br />
I~ otber p4I411 David Usyd Goge and Usyd George boA<br />
enatteziñ arg Toules in. the ei1m and exp 11111-that<br />
If they we voted tO. l, Qduese alamW would bekouI<br />
the Wlsh hills bmuse strsaely enoh nmto s election* a" e<br />
osnimoted an wint a" esbeunl rather amusing issMw really,<br />
nytm the I~ berals won and the Tories wev in<br />
opposition. and I LoYOU heve all " ead you should.<br />
119 smith's waiden ak beinus. the Spker In due cow"<br />
arinsmkcalled Vn Smth and few 4r mea-lecm stood iV.<br />
This is-of ocre, omof the Ziedwiatap of aving a nn<br />
like Smthe If It bad beenMeasles or Mingles, it would have<br />
be" s different. Butt anyhav I -n not going to rePeat to you<br />
the entre a bt be il end up br quoting a little Latin,,<br />
asyoi d, i sksva id all thishvg atta* d Ltd Qeorg,<br />
lmv" nattioked the idea of 61= e sl" wy in the Welshlm ts ins<br />
so p bysq 1g Paoxlwj sealegs. erfbat., And b<br />
he b" Odt as you 4in't Sir, * For tise benefit of those efteted<br />
at StI I wlil this into '&amp; mlish,' ( lau* Ate) and be did It<br />
Into ftlis. Ad he said OPPOKiw 1 ' In the a4J! 7INARn<br />
e ~ of eve. * thmeo rpi ght km-ma L ll'<br />
film Carnarro Burrouhs' Ardebat s ' was letting offMi"<br />
me~ mi ( Leaugter) And I hae alims like this becuse with<br />
mr rather seemA hI-u -. djp of Latin I hoe always bees delighted<br />
to kne that tbere was so a peliti elan wb produced the right<br />
twefor' the ward " auietbat*. b An so I listezod to yom, Sir,<br />
today with Vset plesure ad I thought, * wel* elassimel<br />
learning Is nt ded in, Rdinbursh. 0<br />
NOW the A0Xt thing I WUNt to Say is that this 11 2 e<br />
aret poea on about b-to proee mug. me I ea member<br />
wvmIwas a mLl bey Wrin fmhsa in a vashei<br />
o. watint fashion 9404910 Llook 9 It'ss2m aei<br />
1 * 100: 1tbw wouldat kae it*. t0a*-ps1081<br />
tbqretore it Is Measles. And last Friday I itmebed here with<br />
the Calejp of Pbvsielams and I was 55W four phrsleia<br />
out of fly* that Menzies Vag the right pwiumia adthat<br />
Mingles was an Edinburat affeetationmLugtr<br />
Bat yea" s age, I had this matteo" uunuently settled<br />
for me in landen. Yea knw a Landie, when th have a k~ g<br />
padrieti 44 I thin at which pear, wmenring<br />
Calonaltypes i1e nyseif hami to make a speech thmey have<br />
an inposing gaeamn ia a red oat and he aee esswyrbody<br />
' nLing up wbere psisie with the Prermant ha J0BUie of<br />
" Is Ps en( Jagt) vidbI m no. hsodboy bad Ipt<br />
rater tired. Behad produeed all these thins time arter tim, </p>
<p>is % tt I aight Aeswibe as a im UNia O0mati * glieb.<br />
( Laughter) Most beor he mes to aas not he 6<br />
aaws and with a flue Doric, qmuli on his to" M b m<br />
Cmwty this stuff be saidt *" x~ iese 31r , bet on I te<br />
( Applauee iY. wiea or (" Lavgher)( L<br />
Aplase'oAad I sid, 00 OLMt a-. m ww<br />
Now, you kv&amp;. irs thUse is Mtbi rather<br />
attractive t he inAS d about Mdlabwgb* In<br />
next" s thit, dw'tou I'll ssANOessMtiA, about nt -a<br />
In a amt. W CLeaht I ra r ! at~ edta<br />
ye had a Wlthqwww -elastzf s~ itdloptim<br />
onsmiher. imeludiag ~ asoupte and a definiti<br />
ILM 1 1rot. o that an year we had<br />
a epim r Pool" of lottery, t was 604ld6A<br />
that x woud " ePly insw bam-oa soa:. I in anoter<br />
plac and Z In aother pi~ ee, and woit sin to Miaabmi<br />
thelad Piovest ve a kepta &amp; a the am o= Ze the let<br />
bed tales t had 10 Rae. to do with Seetland, I thoughts<br />
tthe wM m' un. t Stul he got up and be said. M<br />
' a kwv 1--d Provst# I have Lwth and is ay Ve 40 and<br />
Vo oe ali flabbergated -and be said, * Toss jy wife's at<br />
was a 8-taeams' ( Jau---' And with ay usual itrwexraeeo<br />
I iaiadito, my meighboar and said, C st Live been a VM<br />
Vedikgo ( Laughter)<br />
NM, Sirt wow. Tw tastStl. Xoave a bra<br />
kiat I&amp; the oaroe a " aging se: t the stowy<br />
sested with as k miagN a Treana of 1Mi~ ab. so" e ef<br />
y. have hoard It bat ethers of 7e" my met hove board It.<br />
louve no the opprtsmity, so I wi1l toll It bessi nw<br />
of ye. igtw 9afyo ertt his fellow to bemew a Freumon<br />
of AbA-1-is a Mtt 10iek requires xQl amtlon.'<br />
( rauw~ 11, it cmo aboat In this way.<br />
in itutS I VMS what ma all0dl soilled a<br />
health Lwua~ y I was than Leader of the Oa~ lt i.. in<br />
Austral le poeios, whisk I ida<br />
that tine ' for se*" aws w which I oeapid I an hapff to<br />
say, Zrt eVl oe year oes, IV wita Vas vNit as and varlow<br />
p. e and we travlling is Scotland* Zlab Vakhe had<br />
1of now Jinth. Vales aOd we had beon in tmok with,<br />
him am be meot Us at the Assembly Reomn G eurg Street.<br />
Vboa, we arrived, well# there we awe By wife Wand my db 1<br />
Mhe was ith so t~ manted to sa balletq you ka1 allet<br />
is a little boyemd my peep ( LeAr and manted to see the<br />
Lindsay alyand this klod of Lidj -w e arrive&amp; and I<br />
said to VA kebert " lea kasv we have booed invhere and<br />
the Plostivol is in fyI! myj. r whana we 4' AM ha said,<br />
' Cmo acoss hoe A moet bdProset who was then Lord<br />
PioVet xwrrayt I thiok I tight in sayingq. * f ware<br />
Na'edin teemr to the bird P t and I said with, all<br />
* bana amrie a Austnaiaa ( lmagtr)<br />
' Vei19l, d Pre to I hate to lop* o this an o but eamid you<br />
W~ l no to boe* a f~ w seats. boe a" t youn know,.' An&amp;<br />
beat so Mmd said, swP r ir, as a Fteamn of<br />
Ed~ tboehoall doors a" e 4aM to YOU*' I said, * Ila sor7t<br />
iwwt-Vu-d oumind repeting that?' And ha repeated it Is a<br />
loa clear vise# and I said, ' Well r don't uwrstmd this<br />
at ft said, ' ae eiseted you to be a 7ueaa in, 194M'<br />
ra t9' i1 I bad been in omit btitala duriag the war amd I<br />
happed at that timt tr reasomt or amthor, to be * o/* 3 </p>
<p>go3<br />
rIlm Nalso of Am tCLIM9 and it omute . th at the<br />
" eSolution held been fle a" that the letter had been pod<br />
Of eaume inii a lot of eMil wont astray becaus sahp<br />
M-4 Amd all that sut of thiag. I bad miev hewA of it.<br />
s-oa0A t was % at three Weeks l Vtm00 01 UP Into this maT<br />
Rom with the wd am a ad the bellies and I reslved. the<br />
NZL; of 3diMMWgh SOeM yftr after It had been Voted<br />
( laughter but e~ thWo weeks after I Wa leaziat about Its<br />
kAis ) Wn&amp; I no" d toll you that La a rem at boa" e<br />
~ r ewevarius ths=-tee Is the Frooku of J~ nmg~<br />
there' Ssom" Isn't there, Pat, 0 anngth<br />
as to who Is to Pet it. ( Laugter)<br />
Mw theme in soother oeasion that giwes a<br />
œ MW pleasur beesuso, sitting an the ri hand side of<br />
the Laoy Prvwt is Ia&amp; Donressil amd sit on the left.<br />
hanI side of air * I* e hrSsa, that harat'w=&amp;-w ho<br />
t-Wa ai Wrest Is~ ladw AlM. ( Applause) I<br />
4 " W# 1 ead " Mylgew go mture. An o all JOWO<br />
J44 Slim Is se. f the &amp;" at isa of owt ti ( Applause) sl<br />
Me WS Qe mG of ostuulia. 1 11ve In a state of<br />
odateat terro of bin ( Isaghter) boosupe he Is a teable<br />
-ane Thse of you wh ko-Mp kno that to p Into his<br />
4~ bPaI sM tMotM MU(" aaku"" e ) a Uttlo Isa; n sda mI iws as Mqour~ e, A kWigA da lbltleobis h<br />
( Apan se) h s Mrriamn, an old hm-lunw Moa<br />
Appaus) bon being a great fwie e in aI emd--A<br />
being a pot lod of everybodyr in Antralis. ( Applao wh<br />
dWieIn Autai* I s pru and delighted to tbink that<br />
Alisc&amp; Dmresail should be hem. today. ( Applause)<br />
Now, Sitp the emly ether thing that I vent to<br />
tyes and to row &amp; eat * M* Wa Is tkis. It's a cuious~~ g<br />
isn' t It abm e opl of the Owts Mle" that tbe have a<br />
pritde wtalk suestains any tvurW and suwvie atn UsoSWt Ats<br />
I don't use the worid In Iti tohnisl seose -nt the root of<br />
the Wl. IC eas s fee about that beomse, I an ham<br />
to syy tapt. to outto Austsolia after tisasp tatiom<br />
had mAse8 ( au trI. h the great thisP about the soou,<br />
werve they may be In the world and there a" e br no" e<br />
of tbom outsid MOU" Atln than LUIns i etiand a great thing<br />
abot the Seets is tht they retain their pride. % hWay<br />
a ALogthaeu r den' t talk about old gpev! ee 2Mnaly<br />
griovene that they knwanything about is that in the am<br />
* 0Mt7 inwhisk tbay lila, the other people bav the giiewuuse<br />
ma other werde, the peat quality or the scot is<br />
not Billy self.. mnei, whisk is alwje * f-4ofeatagg<br />
WtV;~ a4 I M a -~ oa as Lef to hav lesbodInx<br />
wMiMA. ( Laughter) 1W. wif who wsa a Leekie Yan theroft<br />
beongepd to a sept of the N~~ esis as Wood as tacifor<br />
and yea" s a 0.0dam in OWe Muls oo~ mty she had a Panml<br />
42er one se the el" Als were * ranevder y tnthey<br />
Ited to a blastedo na ak ) kI jujsde ~ the~ weor~ d I n Its iteral sMeD<br />
thy'dm " And that's where we<br />
laughter) e hlsid( Oe 1toe took a ather pows view<br />
of thisp a rather scor V1411# until oe0 OW, at the weeAW<br />
we wlked aroud t6 01i StrOWyar at If~ s and ina the kirk<br />
at OW" there they were. Tbere Vol Na41ots, 3de( QePrs<br />
and 1 voumh hato to put welds intO 2W vwfts nmuth I -n em<br />
she was sayins to herseLf, * I wusn't the first to got baok on<br />
the XIngle. W ( Ughter) </p>
<p>I do<br />
air# IaIs ol ething about Prdmost * gñ sh<br />
word talatde ovesto isintewpvetation, and If you tat<br />
James oow or Robertson vas a po" man it Is easy tf art<br />
" e8l be mat hae a goode OmIen of hlaself." Tnt#$ IV<br />
., mw. L as t havoe zw ofocseelt. The Seats pride<br />
Is mUtbin Ilk, that at all. Pu14e of osaset toea Soot or<br />
to a dewIvatiwe Bsot Ubke mself fellow a owtain * ws of<br />
I P-1001 ipityv of pesonal autwitro and that's right.<br />
Assims thing weg with that in this wurld and, God knm,<br />
that a Prime Nlalster v~ has been a Prine Minister for uixteen<br />
, Vems as I have* needs It tram tine to time, 9 t an top of all<br />
that, of erse, the other eemtates of pftL. to a pes, of<br />
loop MObLity -a yor14Adi this# your aeestmr did this,<br />
you mt aevr la4' thm 4om Yen soc this is the bme<br />
ofths neall pride WA&amp; yew bead WjelL. -kzm that<br />
you bay* a sons of we~ uibiltyb that you can moew lot your<br />
elan# your , meh atw It Na , a Leum.<br />
ftese are the tm facets of pride* Whe I found that<br />
this tine I " a to oe to IUlubmAv to receie thisI to mo,<br />
0Ktirly unexpected hemour of the Tistle, this thing so ll1ar<br />
to amt Naloaty, to ber SIM tivo, I ws vry rmt<br />
think that tbis m" bld en i 4n-hbeau" s t sh~ It p<br />
mand all mW family ! f ing my hestyswe who Is ber for Ito<br />
an immmm feeling ofjoyit a se* e a&amp; sm er to all<br />
or us that ve have Imem bspailttes and that wbtever<br />
mes or gm, vs mst awr lot Low * Itbw Bdinhawh 1~ A<br />
W Iemla or Bootland Is general* It's a proudhin to be of<br />
Soboos od Its apru ting to have been boae tefty;<br />
itts a promd fO Wna nlo f no to hame been received 1Wou<br />
to beer youspa vith mnob SwUstle, ezeept abt tha 112 Hie<br />
( 1ghtor aA o be able to lp hieand in the ease ofC<br />
older of as to says " Wels own nor. hamo bee= In Ould Reokie.<br />
We hewe bea n i land of our forefthers and ve shall rember<br />
It for' the " ast of our liviso </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
