<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5129</transcript-id>
    <title>LORD LOUIS MOUNTBATTEN</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/08/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005129.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
ii AUST ALIA<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MIEDIA TUESDAY, 28 AUGUST 1979<br />
LORD LOUIS MOUNTBATTEN<br />
Lord Louis Mountbatten gave a lifetime of service to the<br />
United Kingdom. He joined the Royal Navy in 1913 and<br />
ended his military career as Chairman of the Chiefs of<br />
Staff Committee in 1965, spanning more than half a century.<br />
During the Second World War he was commander of forces which<br />
played a major role in the liberation of South East Asia<br />
and Burma.<br />
Lord Louis Mountbatten was, however, more than a military<br />
commander. He was a most distinguished servant of peace and<br />
of the modern Commonwealth. He negotiated the independence<br />
of India for the United Kingdom and remained to become<br />
India's Governor-General. Until very recent times he was<br />
President of the United World Colleges. The objective of the<br />
United World Colleges is to bring young men and women of<br />
different nations together for the last years of schooling,<br />
the purpose being to create understanding between peoples<br />
and between nations, to avoid the fear and hatred that<br />
can lead to war.<br />
He was a great military commander. He understood the ultimaLe<br />
futility of war and the need to try and build a more<br />
secure world. I doubt if any man has given greater service<br />
to the United Kingdom or to the wider cause of mankind during<br />
the last half century. That Lord Louis Mountbatten and<br />
his grandson should be murdered in a violent and callous act<br />
of terrorism is a stark and horrible reminder of the total<br />
ruthlessness and indiscriminate terror with which modern<br />
political murderers pursue their cause.<br />
That somebody who had done so much could be killed towards the<br />
end of a long and constructive life emphasises the futility<br />
and barbarity of violence. Lord Louis Mountbatten had done<br />
so much for peace. On behalf of the Government and people<br />
of Australia I convey my deepest sympathy and sorrow to<br />
his family, to her Majesty the Queen and to the British people.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
