<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2822</transcript-id>
    <title>GOVERNMENT TO REVIEW HIGH COMMISSION, LONDON</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/02/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002822.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
NQ DATE<br />
20 February 1973<br />
GOVERNMENT TO REVIEW AUSTRALIAN HIGH<br />
COMMISSION, LONDON<br />
SThe Government is to undertake a comprehensive review<br />
of the Australian High Commission in London.<br />
This was announced today by the Acting Minister for<br />
Foreign Affairs, Senator Willesee, who said that the review<br />
would follow the recent transfer of the administration of the<br />
High Commission to the Minister for Foreign Affairs.<br />
Senator Willesee said that the review would be<br />
conducted by Mr J. E. Collings, a Commissioner of the Public<br />
Service Board since 1960.<br />
Mr Collings would examine functions, methods, procedures,<br />
organisation and staffing, with a view to achieving maximum<br />
efficiency in the High Commission's operation.<br />
The Australian High Commission in London is by far the<br />
biggest of Australia's overseas missions, and includes both<br />
public service and defence forces representatives. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
Current staff is about 1,100, of whom about 900 are<br />
locally-engaged and 350 are engaged on immigration matters. The<br />
last full-scale review was conducted in 1959/ 60.<br />
Responsibility for administering the High Commission<br />
was transferred to the Minister for Foreign Affairs from the<br />
Prime Minister on 1 November, 1972.<br />
Senator Willesee said that Mr Collings was widely<br />
exoerienced in nublic service organisation. He was narticularly<br />
familiar with Australian operations overseas, starting from his<br />
service in the then Department of External Affairs in 1945/ 47.<br />
During the review, Mr Collings will confer with<br />
Ministers and Heads of the Government Departments represented<br />
at the High Commission. 0<br />
Mr Collings proooses to travel to London in April<br />
this year and during his absence Mr F. C. Nordeck, will<br />
act as Commissioner of the Public Service Board. 0<br />
Mr Nordeck, a First Assistant Commissioner in the<br />
Office of the Public Service Board, is closely associated with<br />
the Board's major activities and has acted as Commissioner on<br />
many occasions since 1960. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
