<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9236</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ KEATING, MP</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/05/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009236.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
jet,/<br />
PRIME MINISTER 45/ 94<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
I will be visiting Indonesia from 27 29 June to open two major events in the Australia<br />
Today Indonesia 94 promotion which will be taking place throughout Indonesia in<br />
June and July. I will also meet President Soeharto and will have discussions with other<br />
senior members of the Indonesian Government.<br />
The Australia Today promotion, which follows similar successfuil events in Japan and<br />
Korea, will demonstrate Australia's achievements and capabilities in a range of fields,<br />
from trade and industry to the arts and tourism.<br />
On 29 June I will open the Business and Investment Forum and the Business and Trade<br />
Exhibition being held as part of Australia Today. These events will bring together<br />
Australian and Indonesian business people with the aim of expanding our already<br />
extensive commercial ties. Australia's total trade with Indonesia in 1993 was more<br />
than $ 3 billion, and our exports have grown, in trend growth terms, by 17 per cent<br />
over the past five years.<br />
With President Soeharto I will be discussing both bilateral issues and important<br />
regional issues including APEC, which Indonesia currently chairs. President Soeharto<br />
will host the next APEC leaders meeting in Indonesia later this year.<br />
CANBERRA 16 May 1994 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
