<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9477</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP INTERVIEW WITH RON EDWARDS, RADIO 6PR, 14 FEBRUARY 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/02/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009477.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
1&gt;.<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
INTERVIEW WITH RON EDWARDS, RADIO 6PR, 14 FEBRUARY 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
RE: I would like to welcome to the 6PR microphone the Prime Minister<br />
Paul Keating. Paul, nice to talk to you.<br />
PM: How are you Ron?<br />
RE: Very well indeed. Paul, you are coming to Perth why are you visiting<br />
Perth?<br />
PM: Why would you visit anywhere in Australia?<br />
see how things are, to see what they have to<br />
are at the moment, what their concerns are,<br />
routinely. To meet the people, to<br />
say, what their feelings<br />
and I make these trips<br />
RE: Yeah Paul, has it been a concern of yours that in Western Australia<br />
your general standing hasn't been as high as it has been in NSW or<br />
Victoria?<br />
PM: I think it is a concern of anybody you like to think that you're as<br />
approved of or however one wants to describe it wherever you are<br />
in Australia. But it's not something that has overtaken me in the last<br />
week and that is why I'm coming I actually decided to do this trip in<br />
November.<br />
RE: The Premier Richard Court said here today on 6PR with Howard<br />
Sattler that he didn't know about your visit he feels that you should<br />
have let him know that you are coming to Perth.<br />
PM: Oh dreadful. Isn't that shocking? I mean, he must be the only Premier<br />
in the country that insists I tell him when I'm coming. I mean, what is<br />
he? An air-traffic controller, or a Premier? </p>
<p>RE: Would you like to have a meeting with premier Court when you are<br />
here?<br />
PM: I go to Sydney, to Melbourne, to Queensland wherever I go, Premiers<br />
never insist, or even suggest, that I should see them. I'm not coming<br />
into his constituency my constituency is the Commonwealth of<br />
Australia he is a permanent constituent.<br />
RE: There would be issues, for example, like Native Land Title, that he has<br />
taken a strong line on that you might want to talk to him about?<br />
PM: Yes, but as a matter of fact he sent me a letter he is trying to politicise<br />
my visit he sent me a letter which I received 5 minutes ago asking for<br />
a meeting with a whole lot of things to discuss, including inflammatory<br />
talk about Native Title etc. Well look, I have got the itinerary set if I<br />
have got some time I'll see him, if I haven't, I won't.<br />
RE: So at this stage you can't tell him yes or no?<br />
PM: No.<br />
RE: Paul, the question of the carbon tax that was on the agenda that was<br />
put on the agenda in recent times is it the case that the Government<br />
has now dropped a move for a carbon tax?<br />
PM: It wasn't on the agenda it is only on the agenda, Ron you know,<br />
because you have had the experience of it when it comes to the<br />
Revenue Committee of the Cabinet, and the Cabinet agree to it. We<br />
were looking at the response to the greenhouse gas issues, and the<br />
commitments we made under these international conventions, but the<br />
Government has not got any sort of manic determination to be trying to<br />
impose taxes of that particular variety. I think it is important that we<br />
succeed in diminishing the growth of greenhouse gas emissions in this<br />
country, whether taxation is the best way to do that, or direct measures<br />
or conservation, is a moot point.<br />
RE: The business community was concerned, because we of course are<br />
very large exporters of carbon-based resources, such as coal, and you<br />
would have taken on board their concerns?<br />
PM: Absolutely. That is one of Australia's strengths is that we are one of<br />
the primary exporters of these basis commodities, and I think we can<br />
mount a fairly strong argument that because of the quality of our lowsulphur<br />
coals etc, and the fact that we can burn them more efficiently<br />
than perhaps in other words, the energy supplied by Australia can be<br />
used more efficiently than energy provided from other sources for<br />
products of other countries that in fact Australia can make a<br />
substantial contribution here to this international problem. </p>
<p>RE: Paul, the response of the environment movement of course was they<br />
believed that a carbon tax was necessary do you share the view that<br />
a lot of people have in the community that the environment movement<br />
have this endless agenda that you can't ever satisfy them be it on the<br />
carbon tax, the woodchipping issue, be it world heritage recognition<br />
that in fact their agenda is almost overwhelming?<br />
PM: Of course, because you never deal with one group at one time this is<br />
part of the problem. For instance, last year Ron, the Government<br />
without any real pressure from the environment movement put away<br />
forever for this country Shoalwater Bay in Queensland, which is one of<br />
the most pristine and beautiful areas of the Queensland coast, Jervis<br />
Bay in NSW where we deferred placing an armament depot and took it<br />
to Victoria, and then made clear that we wouldn't be putting any<br />
developments in that it is pretty much as the day when Cook sailed<br />
past it. We put $ 20 million in the Budget on a dollar-for-dollar basis<br />
with Queensland to buy back what is called the " hole in the heart of the<br />
Daintree Rainforest". So in one year the Daintree, Shoalwater Bay,<br />
Jervis Bay not one word of praise from the environment movement,<br />
and when we get down to the annual renewal of a relatively small area<br />
of forests, we have these claims fallacious claims that we are<br />
desecrating forests, when in fact we have now sought to reserve for<br />
examination the areas likely to have important heritage values.<br />
RE: If you had your way through that woodchipping debate again, would<br />
you have handled it differently?<br />
PM: I don't think..... the answer to that is that none of us would want these<br />
things to be a controversy, but I don't know that you can avoid it with<br />
the Wilderness Society for instance. I mean, I think that part of the<br />
problem here is that I am like most Australians I want to see the best<br />
of our forests kept, and at the same time, I want to see those jobs<br />
which exist in the timber industry be kept on a sustainable basis. Now,<br />
how do we do that? We sought to get that balance right in the<br />
decisions we have taken, but we have to deal with facts and truths, and<br />
the claims which the Wilderness Society have made that 1300 coupes<br />
or compartments of trees are pristine stands of trees, is simply<br />
untrue. The claim that the Commonwealth is desecrating these... and<br />
when people see the film footage on television, Ron, they're not the<br />
same trees, they're not the same areas that we are speaking of. See?<br />
RE: That has been put by some of the protesters who actually live in the<br />
timber areas that they believe that the image created is that every bit<br />
of forest is being woodchipped.<br />
PM: And of the forests that will be woodchipped this year, 800 of those<br />
compartments nominated by the Wilderness Society and others, have<br />
been logged before, logged recently, logged out, and in no way that </p>
<p>which they represent to those people those conscientious Australians<br />
who believe in looking after the forests. I am sure that most people<br />
are in the same situation that I am in. I mean, it pains me to see an<br />
important area of trees desecrated by logging.<br />
RE: So your eventual goal as Prime Minister would be to have a large area<br />
of plantation timber that we would harvest?<br />
PM: Basically, a sustainable industry built on plantation and regrowth. That<br />
is, native forest which has been logged in the past, substantially<br />
logged in the past, and where we have got a lot of regrowth, and<br />
plantation. And we are very close to getting to that. It is important, I<br />
think, at this late stage to be able to save the important stands of trees,<br />
but we have to agree which stands are significant, important and<br />
pristine, and we can't have some people running around essentially<br />
with fallacies telling people that there are a whole heap of areas that<br />
the Commonwealth is going to allow woodchipping in, which in fact<br />
have been logged over before, and logged over recently.<br />
RE: Are you happy that the States really will have the carriage as they do<br />
constitutionally of the custody of these forest areas, and their forest<br />
management practices are up to the standards that you would set?<br />
PM: One would hope that Ron, but this is what part of the point we do live<br />
in a federation, and the States manage forests. Now, I notice on the<br />
ABC news last night there was a scuffle at a NSW forest, and on<br />
probably the commercial news as well. The people agreeing to the<br />
logging of those areas is the Government of NSW the Government of<br />
John Fahey. And that is where the pressure should be brought to bear<br />
the Commonwealth gets into this only through this external affairs<br />
power which allows it to approve or disapprove of export licences for<br />
woodchips. But that doesn't mean that we in the Commonwealth can<br />
stop a State Forestry Minister from agreeing to cut saw-log major<br />
trees for logs unless that State, or that Minister, has respect for the<br />
forest. Now, if they don't, then the environment movement should be<br />
on their back to get onto the back of the people who have actually got<br />
the chainsaws out, not onto the back of the Commonwealth.<br />
RE: Can you understand why young people want to see a future where<br />
largely, our forests are as pristine as possible?<br />
PM: Not just young people.<br />
RE: Young people certainly say that to me that they kind of worry about<br />
the environment, and they are looking for a promising future?<br />
PM: But Ron have a look at what the Government has done first of all we<br />
put away the Daintree. I was Treasurer at the time, I helped Graham<br />
Richardson get it through it cost us $ 86 million in adjustment </p>
<p>assistance to do it. Since then, the south west forests of Tasmania<br />
same story again. The southern forests of NSW, and then these other<br />
important areas like I mentioned, which are not only to be not logged,<br />
but not touched. Such as Shoalwater Bay; such as Jervis Bay. I<br />
mean, the Commonwealth record in this and of course, before that<br />
the Gordon below Franklin, our advocacy for the turning of Antarctica<br />
into a wilderness park the Commonwealth Labor Government sought<br />
to get the right balance between forestry, the imperatives of the<br />
environment, and keeping the best of our forests and the interests of<br />
the forest industries. But that will never be served by the untruthful<br />
recitation of argument which is not fact. Insisting that certain stands of<br />
trees are pristine, when they have not been for years.<br />
RE: Do you think you can get back to the stage when Graham Richardson<br />
was the Environment Minister when there was an accord with the<br />
environment movement in Australia?<br />
PM: They were given in a sense, there were so many things done in that<br />
period, the environment movement believes it was then so much<br />
easier. And as you know Ron, there was a very big backlash inside<br />
the Commonwealth Government at the time after that period, that the<br />
development ethos was being lost, and too much was given to the<br />
environment. The answer is to come down the middle, and meet all<br />
the imperatives in a sustainable way that is what we are trying to do.<br />
And by putting these 509 areas aside for further assessment, we<br />
believe those areas are the ones that are important. But they're<br />
coupes. they're largely on average about 150 metres square, and<br />
there is 500 of them 150 metres square it's a relatively small part of<br />
the native forests of this country and I think people need to take that<br />
into account. But small or not we will seek to analyse them, classify<br />
them and protect them where necessary. But, we will not protect areas<br />
which are now not worthy of protection just because we have got some<br />
talking head from the Wilderness Society. I think a lot of Australians<br />
have got to understand that the Federal Government will in a practical<br />
way, in an effective way, protect more important areas of forests than<br />
the leadership which they otherwise may take from outfits like the<br />
Wilderness Society who will basically hand them pap good objectives<br />
and good sentiments, but a wholly unprincipled approach to managing<br />
the issue and in the end relying upon information which is not fact.<br />
RE: Paul, on the question of information and its factual basis, the<br />
Opposition has made great play in recent days about what are referred<br />
to as " the leaked documents" from Finance and other departments on<br />
budget projections. These would be worrying you in terms of the<br />
Opposition's use of them.<br />
PM: Well, I think the Opposition is seeking to worry the country, particularly<br />
beneficiaries and pensioners and anybody who relies upon<br />
Commonwealth payments. You see, John Howard has been running </p>
<p>around saying, for years now the Opposition has been saying, the<br />
Government should cut spending. We should cut, they said, $ 11.5<br />
billion out of the budget through spending. But, what we find now<br />
about John Howard is he is in the job two weeks and he is returning to<br />
the same sort of opportunism he was involved with in the middle<br />
1980s. The opportunism which said when we were struggling, all of us<br />
as a nation to restructure the country rapidly in the 1980s, the times<br />
will suit me. The opportunism which said when no other Australian<br />
politician said race should in any be part of the basis of selection for<br />
migration, he said for reasons of opportunism not of race, but for<br />
opportunism, he said that he thought there were too many Asians<br />
coming here. Now for the same reasons of opportunism he says he<br />
opposes higher interest rates, he opposes higher revenue and he<br />
opposes spending cuts. In other words, here is somebody proposing<br />
themselves to be Prime Minister of Australia, to run seriously the<br />
national economy and the national budget, saying he opposes any of<br />
the elements of variation, the elements of change in national budgets.<br />
RE: However, if the documents fall in John Howard's lap, you couldn't<br />
blame he and Peter Costello for using them?<br />
PM: Yes, you can. You can blame anybody who takes an unprincipled<br />
stand against the things they claim. They claim the Government<br />
should cut spending, now they are saying it is a shocking thing. Let<br />
me just quote perhaps one of the most widely read Australian<br />
commentators on the economy, Ross Gittins in The Sydney Morning<br />
Herald, he wrote yesterday a major column Howard Sabotages<br />
Expenditure Cuts He starts off John Howard's unprincipled<br />
attack on the Government's alleged spending cuts carries a warning to<br />
all those people who want the Budget returned to surplus, but are<br />
implacably opposed to tax increases: their stand the Opposition's<br />
stand is a recipe for fiscal failure And he goes on to say " Mr<br />
Howard's behaviour is unprincipled. It is unprincipled because it is<br />
hypocritical. Here they are as a party and a man who has been<br />
insisting for years that the Government slash its spending, turning all<br />
guns on the Government at the first sign that it may follow their advice<br />
RE: Couldn't John Howard, however, point to The Australian's Newspoll<br />
today saying, look, he's doing all right thank you very much, he might<br />
be accused of sabotaging budgets, but in terms of the electoral<br />
outcome he is travelling all right?<br />
PM: But you remember Ron and I remember that front page in The Bulletin<br />
in 1 988: the picture of John Howard with the front cover saying Mr<br />
18%: Why does this man bother? Do you remember it?<br />
RE: Yes, I do. </p>
<p>PM: Why was he at 18 per cent? Because of this naked opportunism. I<br />
mean, John Howard knows that it is important to get the country's<br />
budget right. He ought to be saying to the Government: " you produce<br />
your budget, we'll see what the result is. But, we believe the<br />
Government's budget should pass through the Houses of Parliament<br />
and that we will take our criticisms or lend our support as the case may<br />
be." Now he has had a reprieve and a second opportunity at national<br />
leadership, for once he should do the right thing.<br />
RE: Well, he says he is remaking himself, he is taking a positive stand on<br />
multicultural ism and the immigration issues, he is going to be more<br />
positive on the Aboriginal Land Fund and he will be a tenacious<br />
character to deal with I would argue.<br />
PM: But Ron, does it look like he is remaking himself. I mean, here he is,<br />
second week out, in an issue of real substance and weight the<br />
national Budget he picks up a leak from the bureaucracy and he<br />
behaves appallingly with it, trying to scare the wits out of anybody who<br />
will come along and that is the very point that Mr Gittins says it is<br />
unprincipled because there is a blatant campaign to scare the<br />
electorate, particularly the most financially vulnerable the elderly, the<br />
sick and the jobless I mean, here is John Howard remaking himself<br />
with these sorts of tactics. I don't believe he is. You see, I said in the<br />
House the other day, John Howard wants to pretend he doesn't have a<br />
past he is the Ronald Biggs of the Liberal Party. He sort of<br />
absconded saying I am not really the same John Howard I used to be,<br />
just like Biggs says, I'm not really a train robber, I'm only a fellow in Rio<br />
with a Rio shirt, with a tropical shirt. I mean, the fact is, John Howard<br />
does have a past. It was to leave Australia as an inward looking, high<br />
tax, high inflation, low growth, high unemployment economy. That is<br />
what this Government inherited from him and when he was Opposition<br />
Leader he brought no more policy certainty to the country than he did<br />
when he was Treasurer and, in fact, he left in such poor state that the<br />
Opposition removed him from the leadership in the Parliament<br />
between 1987 and 1990 in 1989 in fact.<br />
RE: Paul, does it worry you, the electorate's reaction to Parliamentary<br />
behaviour, what they see of question time, has it caused you to rethink<br />
your attitude towards the televising of Parliamentary proceedings?<br />
PM: Well, they are televised Ron and that is a fact of life. I think it has<br />
changed the debate somewhat, but I suppose life is about changes.<br />
There is a lot of information, a lot of mood, a lot of balance, in a sense,<br />
it is the fulcrum of Australian public life as well as the cockpit of<br />
Australian public life and I think the nation has been served well by the<br />
political system. Australia has been through a change in the last 12<br />
years, probably greater than any other OECD country. We have<br />
stripped away the tariff walls, we have opened up the financial<br />
markets, we have now got a high productivity competitive economy </p>
<p>with a low inflation rate, we are exporting half as much again as we<br />
were 10 years ago and by and large the public system, I think, has<br />
served the country well. I think, the Parliament is reflection of this.<br />
RE: Can we turn around the current account deficit?<br />
PM: Well, we will only turn that around in an absolute way when we save<br />
more. But, the reason we are not saving as much these days is<br />
because of two decades of double digit inflation. I mean, Australian's<br />
have had inculcated into them, the notion that if they put their money in<br />
the bank or put it into a fixed interest security, within 10 years it will be<br />
worth much less. So what you do is you buy a flat or you buy a holiday<br />
house or a second property and we have now had tremendous inflation<br />
performance for three years, but three years doesn't change the<br />
psyche and the propensity to save after 20 years of lessons that you<br />
can't trust cash.<br />
RE: Wouldn't it help people to save if they were able to deposit, let's say<br />
$ 5000 or $ 10,000 in a bank using their tax file numbers so companies<br />
couldn't do it and that that sum of money, the interest on that would be<br />
quarantined for tax and social security purposes. Wouldn't we get<br />
back to the day when you and I went to school where we were<br />
encouraged each week to go and put a penny in your Commonwealth<br />
bank book?<br />
PM: Well, it is the after tax treatment that is the problem in the past. I<br />
mean, it is high inflation and the after you see, let's say Ron, you<br />
have got a real rate of interest of 3 per cent and you've got inflation of<br />
say 10 per cent. You are picking up 13 per cent interest on your<br />
deposit. This is the form in the 1970s and 1 980s. You are taxed on the<br />
13 roughly for most people, a third of that goes, say 4 per cent goes.<br />
But remember, that 11 per cent of it was actually fairy floss, it was<br />
inflation. So, you are actually paying tax on the inflation, so the after<br />
tax income of the saver was very poor. You will only really repair this<br />
problem with low inflation, and who delivered low inflation to Australia?<br />
This Labor Government. I mean, we have got a 2 to 2.5 per cent<br />
inflation rate and where did it come from? It came from this<br />
Government.<br />
RE: Right. Would you deliver, if you have delivered the low inflation which<br />
is on the record, would you deliver something like that really<br />
encouraging people to save because, obviously, superannuation is<br />
helping the national savings..<br />
PM: We introduced that. That is the thing we did to encourage people. We<br />
introduced award superannuation I did with the ACTU in 1985/ 86 and<br />
on 1 July 1995 and again only because of this Government the tax<br />
meter turns over on 6 per cent. We go over one more percentage<br />
point on 1 July. So, as of 1 July this year the whole of the nation is </p>
<p>saving 6 per cent and as a consequence we have now got $ 330 billion<br />
in superannuation savings that is $ 330,000 million. That is the<br />
vehicle the Government has chosen. But, if we give tax relief in one<br />
place, often you are giving tax relief for savings which will be made<br />
anyway and it just encourages there and discourages saving<br />
somewhere else. So, these are not easy questions. You have got to<br />
get a net addition to savings. I contend, Ron, you won't get that net<br />
addition, it only comes from two places a better inflation performance<br />
in the long run and the Government moving the budget back into<br />
surplus so we have what we call public savings.<br />
RE: Right. Just finally Paul, the debate about the republic, it moved ahead<br />
and then it slackened off, are you happy with the way it is going at this<br />
stage, will we see a republic by the time we have the Olympics in<br />
Sydney?<br />
PM: I think so. I hope so and I am sure many Australians now believe that<br />
we can't go on forever without being represented by an Australian<br />
head of state. But again, this is a debate. People are warming to the<br />
issues, they are discussing them. It takes time, there is a certain<br />
chemistry about it, there is a certain sort of flow to it and the<br />
Government will be responding, this year, to the Turnbull Committee's<br />
report which was the report of the Republic Advisory Committee and<br />
the recommendations which were made there. So, there will be some<br />
material additions to the debate, but the real debate will be in the<br />
hearts and minds of Australians and, of course, any changes to an<br />
Australian republic can only come by way of referenda. That is, a<br />
majority of electors in a majority of States.<br />
RE: At the same time, do you think we will see a change to Australian flag<br />
flying in Sydney for the 2000 Olympics?<br />
PM: Well, I think that is still, in a sense, a subordinate matter to the<br />
principal things, that is the principal issue, that is whether Australians<br />
can be fully represented by somebody who is not an Australian person.<br />
RE: So, Paul, we look forward to you joining us here in Perth this week. A<br />
lot of issues will continue to be debated. I thank you for joining us<br />
today on 6PR.<br />
PM: Thank you, Ron, I'm looking forward to coming.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
