<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>849</transcript-id>
    <title>APPOINTMENT OF AUSTRALIAN SECRETARY TO THE QUEEN - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/11/1963</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000849.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO : NOT TO EE PUBLISHED, BROADCA\ ST OR TELECAST BEFORE<br />
6 P. M. EST, FRIDAY, 1ST NOVEMBER, 1963.<br />
FOR PRESS: PaML No. 89/ 1963.<br />
APPOINTMENT OF AUJSTRALIANI SECRETARY TO THE QUEEN<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister? the Rt. Hon, Sir Robert Menzies<br />
The following statement was released today in London<br />
from Buckingham Palace<br />
" IT IS ANNOUNCED FROM BUCKINGHAM PALACE THAT THE<br />
QUEEN HAS APPOINTED VICE-ADMIRAL SIR ROY D04ILING AS<br />
AUSTRALIAN SECRETARY TO THE QUEEN AND TO BE A MEMBER<br />
OF HER MAJ-ESTYIS HOUSEHOLD."<br />
Sir Roy Dowlingts appointment tns X Australian<br />
Secretary to The Queen was welcomed in Canberra today by the<br />
Prime Minister, The Prime Minister said that the appointment<br />
was one of significance for Australia and would help to maintain<br />
the close association that already existed between all the<br />
members of the Royal Family and Australia. The appointment was<br />
Her Majesty's own idea and he was delighted to fall in with it.<br />
The Prime Minister congratulated Sir Roy on his appointment.<br />
It was one which would give Sir Roy personal satisfaction following<br />
on his similar appointment as Australian Secretary to The<br />
Queen during the period of Her Majesty's last visit to Australia.<br />
The Prime Minister said he expected Sir Roy's appointment<br />
to be the forerunner of successive appointments of a<br />
similar nature, In genoral, the appointments would be for<br />
two-year periods. Sir Roy's appointment is for two years with<br />
effect from 1st November, 1963. The Australian Secretary to<br />
The Queen will be atVtached to the Governor-General's Household<br />
and will maintain close contact with the Governor-General,<br />
The main work of the Australian Secretary to The Queen<br />
will be in connection with visits by Her Majesty or other mdembers<br />
of the Royal Family to Australia. The Australian Secretary will<br />
be brought into the planning of visits and may accompany any of<br />
the Royal visitors during their visit. He will also be available<br />
to assist the Governor-General in other matters which from time<br />
to time the Governor-General may suggest.<br />
The Prime Minister emphasised that the position of<br />
Australian Secretary to The Queen does not have any formal place<br />
in the constitutional arrongements as between The Queen, the<br />
Governor-General and the Australian Government, and official<br />
matters normally handled by the Governor-General's Office will<br />
continue to be dealt with in this way. On the other hand, it<br />
would be of great assistance to have the advice of the Australian<br />
Secretary to Thoe Queen available to the Government on matters<br />
affecting visits by members of the Royal Family,<br />
Biographical note<br />
Vice-Adiiiral Sir Roy Dowling, KCVQ, KBE, CD, DSO, retired<br />
as Chairman of the Chiefs of Staff Committee in 1961, having held<br />
the position for two years. Prior to that he was First Naval<br />
Member and Chief of the Naval Staff from 1955-1959, </p>
<p>-2<br />
Sir Roy was appointed as Australian Secretary to<br />
The Queen for the period of Her Majesty's visit to Australia<br />
in 1963 and was Director of the Royal Visit,<br />
Sir Roy, now retired, and living in Canberra,<br />
continues an active interest in Red Cross. He is at present<br />
Chairman of the LA. C. T. Division of Red Cross.<br />
CANBERRA, 1st November, 1963. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
