<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>22065</transcript-id>
    <title>Doorstop Interview Parliament House, Canberra </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/12/2005</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, are you excited about the IR legislation going through the Senate today?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>This is a very good outcome for the future strength of the Australian economy, that's what this is all about.  And a strong economy is the only true guarantee of job security and future higher real wages.  I thank the Senate for passing the legislation.  This legislation will strengthen the Australian economy in the years ahead and because of that it will be good for jobs and it will be good for higher wages.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Is this your long-held dream?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look, I'm not personalising this.  This is about Australia's economic future.  This is about strengthening the Australian economy in the years ahead.  My responsibility is always to put the welfare of the Australian people and the strength of the Australian economy first.  That is why I have argued for these things and that is why the Government is doing these things.  The only guarantee that can ever be given of higher real wages and lower unemployment is a strong, productive, growing economy and this legislation will contribute to that.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Will you commit, Prime Minister, to facing the voters' final judgement on these laws at the next election?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think that is an attempt to get me to make some comment about certain matters.  The Australian people will make a judgement on the Government and its record.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Is it an historic moment though?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think it's a very important further step down a path that we began to tread some years ago.  It's not extreme, it's not radical, it's not revolutionary.  It's measured, further change that will strengthen the Australian economy.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, did you put any pressure on Robert Gerard to resign?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, I didn't, and neither did Mr Costello.  I want to thank Mr Gerard for the contribution he made as a member of the Reserve Bank Board.  I regret the personal attacks that were made on him under parliamentary privilege.  He chose to resign and for the reasons that were given in the statement.  He was not asked to resign by the Government, we did not seek his resignation and we would not have sought his resignation.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>So was it the right decision for him to resign?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well that obviously is something for him. He decided, for the reasons given, to resign.  It was not a result of some Government pressure or Government hint and I thank him for his contribution.  He has been a very successful businessman, he's employed thousands of Australians.  I mean we're debating employment and job security and here's a man who's employed thousands of Australians over the years.  And for that he gets kicked in the teeth under parliamentary privilege.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Has this episode tarnished Mr Costello and the Reserve Bank.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, certainly not.  Mr Costello remains, in my view, the best Treasurer this country has had and he continues to do a fantastic job as Treasurer in my Government.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do you welcome his resignation, Robert Gerard's?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look, I am sorry about the whole episode and I'm sorry that he's resigning.  But he chose to for the reasons he gave and I understand that.  But he certainly was not asked to go by the Government.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do you believe this incident has damaged the Government?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, I don't believe so.</p>
<p>Anything else?  Thank you.</p>
<p>[ends]  </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
