<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2134</transcript-id>
    <title>TELEVISION INTERVIEW GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. JOHN GORTON, FOR ABC TELEVISION NETWORK  INTERVIEWER: MR. GEORGE WILSON</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/10/1969</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002134.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO: 8. 30 p. m. on 22 October 1969 FINAL PARTY TV INTERVIEW<br />
1969 FEDERAL ELECTION<br />
TELEVISION INTERVIEW GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER,<br />
MR. JOHN GORTON, FOR ABC TELEVISION NETWCRK<br />
Interviewer: Mr. George Wilson<br />
Q. First, Prime Minister, how successful do you think you<br />
have been in your attempt to make foreign affairs and defence the main<br />
issues in this election?<br />
PM. Foreign affairs and defence are the main issues in this<br />
election. It is not a matter of my attempt to make them so. They are<br />
the main issues in this election. Any domestic programme that is put<br />
forward for Australia can only succeed provided Australia is secure<br />
against attack from abroad, provided Australia retains its alliances<br />
with its powerful friends. The foreign affairs and defence area is<br />
overriding at this election and I have no doubt at all that the people of<br />
Australia fully realise this. The real question is: Why is the Opposition<br />
so frightened to talk about foreign affairs and their defence policy? You<br />
haven't heard anything from them at all or I haven't. I haven't heard<br />
their Leader mention it at all because he is running away from the<br />
question because he knows it is overriding and because, as I believe,<br />
he knows most Australians realise it's overriding.<br />
Q. What do you think of Mr. Whitlam's timetable for<br />
withdrawal from Malaysia?<br />
PM. Oh, it's merely a restatement of the withdrawal to<br />
isolationism which he said before " all Australian troops will be<br />
withdrawn by the time all British troops are withdrawn from that area".<br />
There is nothing new in it except I think there is an extraordinarily<br />
impertinent attempt to mislead and to confuse the Australian people as<br />
to what is involved in what he proposes. You see, he said, " All that is<br />
at stake is a different destination". It's worth looking at that because it<br />
is a very strange way of putting it. You see, what is at issue is: Do<br />
Australian troops remain in that area in Singapore in that area ground,<br />
air and naval forces or do they all withdraw to the isolationism of<br />
Fortress Australia. That's what is at issue. And he is going to bring<br />
them all back to the isolationism of Fortress Australia. What he says<br />
is: " Oh, the only thing at issue is the destination". The only thing at<br />
issue by that, he means, is whether they stay there or whether they<br />
come back to Australia, but what a way of putting it, and what an attempt<br />
to confuse and mislead. / 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
Q. But don't you think that many people might find a certain<br />
amount of attraction in Labor's plans to abolish National Service and to<br />
withdraw from Vietnam?<br />
PM. I think there would be a number of people who would be<br />
attracted by the suggestion of the abolition of National Service, I believe<br />
there would be many many more who would not be attracted by that idea<br />
and who would not want it to be brought into effect. And I am positive<br />
that Australia's requirements are that we shouldn't abandon National<br />
Service. It would immediately mean a cut in the Army by one-third and<br />
there is no way ever put before us in which our armed forces can be<br />
maintained at the strength we need unless we do retain National Service.<br />
Now, we will retain it and the Opposition will not and that is their first<br />
real blow at Australia's security. There are many others but that's a<br />
real blow. On the question of Vietnam, I think all Australians would<br />
want to see a peace in Vietnam which provided an opportunity for the<br />
South Vietnamese people to elect the sort of government they want and<br />
which would enable all foreign troops to withdraw. I am sure they<br />
would. I would. But that is a different proposition from unilaterally<br />
withdrawing, abandoning the United States and the South Vietnamese,<br />
giving up what was a proper objective of getting a proper just peace for<br />
the South Vietnamese people and cutting and running and leaving our<br />
allies in the lurch. Now that is a different proposition and I don't<br />
believe most Australians would want to see that happen, particularly<br />
when they took into account the effect it would have on the world, and<br />
on Australia's credibility in the world, and I think the effect it would<br />
have on our alliances with the United States.<br />
0. What is your reaction to those critics who have been<br />
saying that you want to concentrate on foreign affairs and defence,<br />
simply because your domestic proposals are no nebulous*.,<br />
PM. I think it is utterly ridiculous, because our proposals<br />
are not nebulous in the least compared with the Opposition's proposals.<br />
Let us take national development as an example. There isn't one<br />
proposal that I can find in their policy for national development. None<br />
at all. Oh, setting up a commission here, or a committee there, but<br />
nothing that isn't nebulous. Now we have got specific proposals to take<br />
Australia into the atomic age, to set aside $ 100 million for water<br />
conservation, for exploration of water resources, to establish an<br />
institute of marine science so that we can find out more about the waters<br />
around our coast and know more about the Reef we wish to protect. All<br />
these are specific requirements as are the suggestions for building<br />
railways. There isn't one in the Opposition's policy speech. If you go<br />
through our proposals, you will find they are specific. And they do take<br />
some account we do realise that there is going to be in the future a need<br />
by the States for more revenue for their own requirements. This is not<br />
mentioned in the suggestions put forward by the Opposition, the nebulous<br />
suggestions. / 3 </p>
<p>p 3r<br />
Q. What would you say has emerged as the main domestic<br />
issue?<br />
PM. Oh, I think without question it is whether we continue<br />
with that kind of responsible economic management which has led to<br />
the unprecedented growth that we see around us now, to the prosperity<br />
we see around us now, to the employment situation we see around us<br />
now, to the general excitement in Australia, the general growing in<br />
Australia, and the general building of Australia's population, The<br />
question is whether we can continue with that kind of management and<br />
keep inflation under control as we do or whether we put all that at risk<br />
by injecting hundreds of millions into the economy when there isn't<br />
manpower to match it, there are not resources to match it. It is<br />
injecting hundreds of millions into the economy for the sake of making<br />
specious promises at an election. Look, if these specious promises<br />
are accepted, there is no doubt at all that either there will be heavier<br />
taxation required or that inflation is going to run rampant in Australia.<br />
There is no choice between those two. This will happen must happen.<br />
Now what is the result of that. If inflation runs wild, then there will<br />
unquestionably be first, damage and hardship done to pensioners, low<br />
income earners, to primary producers, to all those who have no way<br />
of meeting cost rises which run from inflation. Also, there will<br />
undoubtedly be a diminution of that growth capital we need, that<br />
development capital we need from abroad. And if there is a diminution<br />
of that, then we won't be able to keep our immigration record at the<br />
record heights we have it at now, and there will not be the same job<br />
opportunities which we have now. All this the growth, the employment,<br />
the building up of our population, the stability of those on fixed incomes<br />
depends on good economic management. Now Australia has seen the<br />
results of good economic management and we can see this around us<br />
now. All this will be put at risk if the specious promises are accepted.<br />
Q. Finally, Prime Minister, with only a couple of days before<br />
the poll, what is your final message to the electorate?<br />
PM. Well, I would say this: I think that at this poll on October<br />
Australians are making a momentous choice which is going to have<br />
an effect on the future security and possibly the future existence of this<br />
country. And so they have to choose which defence policy they prefer.<br />
First, do they wish to alienate our allies? Do they wish to retreat<br />
unilaterally from Vietnam? Do they wish to retreat from Malaysia/<br />
Singapore? Do they wish to argue about joint defence bases with the<br />
United States? Do they wish, having driven us into that kind of<br />
isolationism, then to cut our own defence forces so we can't defend<br />
ourselves? This is the first choice they have to make. Secondly, as I<br />
said, the maintenance of the existing prosperity and economic<br />
advancement of Australia which has been shown to be in good hands<br />
and which is at risk and threatened by the proposals made by the<br />
Opposition. This is what the electors must decide on October 25. And<br />
I hope for Australia's future security, for Australia's continuing growth,<br />
for Australia's future name in the world, the electors will choose that<br />
Liberal/ Country Party coalition which has made our name stand so high<br />
and which at home has brought the benefits we see around us vvery day.<br />
Those are the choices for the electors and I have little doubt what their<br />
choice in fact will be.<br />
Q. Thank you, Prime Minister. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
