<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>17084</transcript-id>
    <title>Transcript of joint doorstop with Premier Mike Rann    </title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/02/2010</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>PM: Well it's great to be back in Adelaide, and great to be back here with Mike Rann. This is a relationship between the Australian Government and the South Australian Government based on partnership, and it's a partnership that is aimed at two things- keeping South Australia strong, and keeping South Australia moving ahead. </p>
<p>In the partnership that we've developed in the period that I've been in Government, let me just leave you with one core fact. And that is, in terms of our investment in our national economic stimulus strategy, in South Australia, we've invested some $4.2 billion. $4.2 billion, to help keep the South Australian economy moving, to help keep the Australian economy moving.</p>
<p>Also, what we've been on about is, with the South Australian Government, building the basics. Let me just go to a few facts and figures before we turn to this project today. On infrastructure, that is, road and rail infrastructure, under this Government, the Australian Government, we have increased our investment here in South Australia by 264% compared with the Howard Government. Secondly, on education, we've increased our investment in South Australia by 118% compared with the Howard Government.</p>
<p>On health, we've increased our investment by 43% compared with the Howard Government. Let's go to some practical projects and our commitments prior to the election, the last Australian election. On infrastructure, our undertaking- $500 million on the South Road upgrade. Our undertaking on $80 million for the Dukes Highway safety upgrade package. On education, the investment that we've made in computers in schools- $20 million, 20,000 computers in 246 schools across South Australia.</p>
<p>Nearly $100 million in trades training centres servicing 100 secondary schools across South Australia. Again, our commitments in education. Our commitments in health, making sure that we're delivering on our GP super clinics, three of them- Modbury, Noarlunga, Playford North, an investment of $32.5 million. An investment of $61.7 million to help relieve hospital emergency departments. And on top of that, what we've done with an additional 3,200 additional elective surgery procedures, with a further investment of nearly $14 million.</p>
<p>And on desalination, co-investing in partnership with the South Australian Government $328 million for the construction of the Adelaide desal plant. That's in terms of our commitments. The other thing I'd say is, what have we done in addition to those commitments in South Australia. Let me just run through a few facts and figures again. Going to infrastructure, $291 million for the Noarlunga to Seaford rail extension. $36.9 million brought forward for the Northern Expressway. $18 million for 67 black spots on South Australian roads.</p>
<p>Go again to education, you have a huge investment of $1.4 billion in the biggest school modernisation program that this State has seen, part of the biggest one the nation has seen, spread across 789 schools in South Australia, with state of the art libraries, state of the art science centres, state of the art language centres, and multipurpose halls springing up right across the schools of this great State. In fact, 61 new science and language centre projects.</p>
<p>And the last thing I'd just talk about is health. On health, what we have done is bring about a record Australian investment, an Australian Government investment of $5.3 billion of health outlays here, and that is a 43% increase on what was delivered to South Australia under the previous Health Agreement with the Howard Government. These are big investments, quite apart from what we're doing in social housing, adding some 1,360 new units of social housing.</p>
<p>The reason I spend some time going through these is to underline one point. It's happened on the basis of partnership. Partnership in helping keep the South Australian economy going through the global economic recession last year. Partnership in getting on with the basics in education, in health, in road and rail and social housing, and the water security of this state and this city. But beyond that, delivering also on critical projects that mean a lot to mums and dads sitting around the kitchen table. Now, let me quickly turn to what we're here today to talk about.</p>
<p>One of those investments I spoke about before was the some $140 million that we're investing into South Australian universities in various forms of research. On top of that, we're of course doing single, large-scale projects such as the one we're here to discuss today. This is a great piece of new medical science research kit for the people of South Australia, and for the Australian people at large. </p>
<p>You've seen the design behind you here. This is going to be a terrific, iconic building in the heart of Adelaide, which will bring together more than 600 of the best medical research scientists from around South Australia, around the country, and around the world, working together collaboratively. Working together on new innovations, to deal with the diseases which matter to working families across Australia. Cancer, the single biggest killer in our country. New pathways of research, new pathways of clinical application.</p>
<p>That's why this is going to be a fantastic new addition to South Australia's future. The fact that the South Australian Government decided to co-locate this with their plans to build the new Royal Adelaide Hospital even makes more sense. Having a brand new research centre, more than 600 of the brightest and best researchers in the country co-located over time with a very large tertiary hospital makes sense in terms of producing the best outcomes for the patients of the future, the mums and dads of the future.</p>
<p>The last thing I'd say is this. Is that, it's not just bringing together all these researchers. It's not just bringing together all the expertise which they represent. It's the collaboration between these three great universities here as well. The fact that they've decided to bring their researchers together, have them work together on the real solutions that mums and dads need across Australia for the diseases which affect working families, that makes all the difference. 25,000 square metres of gross floor area. Fully flexible laboratory space. At PC2 laboratory standard. Nine research modules, consisting of 1/3 dry and 2/3 wet laboratory spaces. This, I believe, is actually state of the art for South Australia for the future.</p>
<p>So, congratulations to the SA Government in being partners with us in this project, partners with us across health, partners with us across health, education, housing and helping working families. And partners with us in keeping the nation's economy going through a global economic recession which has knocked the stuffing out of every other economy around the world.</p>
<p>Over to you, Mike.</p>
<p>RANN: Thank you very much Prime Minister, and thank you for your partnership with this. As you know, we're building a $1.7 billion, brand new Royal Adelaide Hospital. And co-location with a world class health and medical research institute makes sense for patients. In this institute, 675 researchers will be working with the hospital on issues such as cancer research, on heart disease, the things that count in terms of our community. And again, it's about a partnership. Since we've been in Government, there are now 1100 more doctors in our public hospital system than there was when we were first elected. 3,600 more nurses. More beds per capita than the rest of the nation.</p>
<p>And as we've grown our economy and grown our State finances, it means that we can invest in better services, and there is nothing more important than the health of our people. But a productive and constructive partnership with Kevin Rudd's Government helps us to do much more. He mentioned the electrifying of the railways, taking it down to Seaford. The desalination plant, making it bigger so that it gives us an insurance policy for the future. But ultimately, it's also about jobs. It's about building careers for the future. And this stunning design, we want it to be the newest and best medical research centre in the nation, alongside the newest and best hospital in the nation, built for the 21st century.</p>
<p>And of course when people talk about jobs, let's remember that jobs growth in this state, full time jobs growth in this state, has run ten times stronger than it did under the Liberals during the same period of time. That's the difference, and that's what we can't risk for the future.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Are you riding on the coattails of the Federal Government to boost your re-election chances?</p>
<p>RANN: I think what we're doing is demonstrating partnership. One of the key jobs of a Premier is to negotiate to get the best deal for his or her State from the Federal Government. One of my key jobs is to negotiate with Kevin Rudd to get the best outcomes for South Australia. And that gets back to partnership, it gets back to having clout. Whether it's a medical research institute or a $30 billion submarine program- and there's a classic example of partnership. We're putting in nearly $400 million, we've now opened Techport, that's been the platform upon which we've been able to negotiate new defence projects for this State worth billions of dollars. It's about having clout in Canberra, it's about negotiating the best outcomes for our State.</p>
<p>PM: What the Australian Government needs to do is work in the closest partnership with State Governments. And that's as I've worked with Mike. He's made reference to this massive submarine project. We are in the process of moving towards the doubling of Australia's submarine fleet. Were it not for the investments made here by the South Australian Government leading the way in terms of our next generation submarines, frankly, it wouldn't be happening. And it wouldn't be happening here in South Australia. That's what partnership is about.</p>
<p>The fundamental transformation of the South Australian economy over the last, you know, decade, I've got to say, the key role in the political leadership of the State taking it up to the Australian Government and with us forming partnerships with them. Whether it's on submarines, road infrastructure, rail infrastructure, hospital research facilities like this, as well as what we're doing in our schools. Partnership is a real and practical thing around making it work for the mums and dads around the kitchen table and the things that they need, the basic things they need.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, is this centre contingent upon Labor being returned to Government next month?</p>
<p>PM: The Australian Government will proceed with its investments on the basis of agreements with the elected democratic Government of any State of Australia. I've got to say, however, that this project would not exist were it not for the advocacy of this South Australian Premier. What the posture is on this particular project by the South Australian Opposition I would not know. They have not raised it for me, so, matter for them.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, what about the plans to federalise state hospitals, state health systems- is that still going apace, has that been put on hold, on the backburner?</p>
<p>PM: What we have done over the last period of time is work very carefully through the National Health and Hospital Reform Commission to get our future reforms for the system and for the funding of the system as right as possible, and then, secondly, what we've done in the last six months, is road test its recommendations across the major hospitals of the country. I've been here in South Australia, I've spoken here at the Flinders Medical Centre, addressed a large forum of doctors there, I've been out to Murray Bridge, I've spoken to doctors there.</p>
<p>Nationwide, we've done this with 103 hospitals in the last six months. So therefore, in bringing it to conclusion, we will put before the Australian nation, the Australian people, a plan for the future. A funded plan for the future about how we're going to get there. And we look forward to working in partnership with the States and Territories to make it work. That's what we want to happen. But you know what the key things is for mums and dads? Making sure you've got the hospital beds for the future. Making sure you've got the doctors for the future. Making sure you've got the nurses for the future. And that's why you've got to work in partnership with Governments which take this seriously.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, the Australian victims of Mossad say they've had no contact with the Embassy or the Government. Have you abandoned them?</p>
<p>PM: The- my advice is that Australian officials have been in contact with a range of those associated with the most recent matters. Because these involve very complex security and intelligence matters, you have to proceed very carefully. I'm just weighing my words very carefully. The second thing I'd say is this- that when it comes to Australian passport fraud, or the use and abuse of Australian passports, this Government has an absolutely hard line on defending the integrity of our passport system, because millions of the travelling public depend upon that each year. That is why the Foreign Minister has called in the Israeli Ambassador and asked for an explanation. Thus far we are not satisfied with that explanation.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, the Australian woman involved in that says she hasn't been contacted by any (inaudible) official. What's your response to that?</p>
<p>PM: I said before I wish to tread very carefully with the security and intelligence matters which arise in relation to each of the individuals and families concerned with this matter. Therefore, I'm choosing my words very carefully, so as not to compromise any person- or so as not to compromise any continuing investigation. I am simply choosing my words very carefully.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, are you aware that ASIO was investigating at least three dual Australian-Israeli passport holders for using (inaudible)</p>
<p>PM: I have seen those reports today in the national press. Can I simply say this, that consistent with the long-standing practice of the Australian Government, we do not comment on the individual details of intelligence matters. That is a long standing convention of Governments both Labor and Liberal, over many, many decades. I will adhere to that convention. Let me add one thing. When it comes to national security and defending the national security of this country, Australia, we will take whatever measures are necessary to ensure that our security interests are not being compromised by any other State.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, what difference do you think Greg Combet will make to this revamped insulation scheme? (inaudible) what will he bring that the previous incumbent didn't?</p>
<p>PM: Minister Combet is a vastly experienced Minister who as a previous head of the Australian Council of Trade Unions is a very practical bloke, who works very closely with industry, works very closely with workers, and is a person of vast experience. This will be a hard task. It will be a difficult job. I've entrusted to him and have confidence in his ability to get on with what is a difficult task.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: The Opposition (inaudible)</p>
<p>PM: I think it's very plain for all who care to see and care to look that the decision in relation to Minister Garrett has resulted in a significant reduction of his responsibilities. I communicated that directly to him yesterday. I indicated that was the course of action that we'd be following. That is the course of action which has now being implemented. And Minister Combet is now responsible.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Barnaby Joyce is today taking flak this morning from members of his own party, does that give you some joy or-</p>
<p>PM: I think all-</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: What is your response?</p>
<p>PM: I'd say on that score is as follows, that- that it's now I think 87 days since Mr Abbott took the reckless decision, the risky decision of making Barnaby Joyce the alternative Finance Minister of Australia. In just 87 days he's said that America could default on its sovereign debt, he's said that the Australian States could or would default on their sovereign debt. He's said that the Australian Government could or would default on its sovereign debt. And that's just the beginning of what Senator Barnaby Joyce, who's the alternative Finance Minister of Australia, has said.</p>
<p>So, he's been in that position of authority on Australia's finances for now 87 days. He may make 100 days. I'd doubt very much whether he's going to make 200 days. Barnaby Joyce may make his century. I doubt very much whether it will be a century and a half, let alone a double ton. And the reason is Mr Abbott knows that he's made a fundamental error of judgment, a risky judgment, in appointing Barnaby Joyce to an important position. You can't play politics with the public finance of the nation. Mr Abbott, in making this risky decision, has played politics front and centre by appointing an individual who's not frankly up to it. But on top of that, in his statements, is capable of causing great damage, as well.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: (inaudible)</p>
<p>PM: Well, on the question of the Liberal Opposition Leader, I have not had the opportunity to meet that leader. More importantly, I've not actually seen what their policy is on health, on hospitals, on the future of projects like this. Can I just say, I will make judgments based on clear statements of policy. And I seem to get the impression here that there's a bit of a strategy of trying to hide Liberal policies and the Liberal Leader under a carpet somewhere and hope that an election comes and goes and no one notices. </p>
<p>You've got to have policies up there in order for other Governments to engage. I know where Mike Rann's coming from on this building. I know where Mike Rann's coming from precisely when it comes to the future of the Royal Adelaide Hospital. I know where he's coming from on education. I know where he's coming from on roads. I know where he's coming from on rail infrastructure. I know what his policies are. </p>
<p>I just think- people in South Australia, of course, make up their own minds- it's a great democracy that we have in Australia. But in making up their minds, you've got to ask some pretty basic questions- who is this person, and what are their policies? So in answer to your question, to engage with a Government, you've actually got to know what their policies are. I know what Mike's are. I wouldn't have a clue what the alternative is, because their political strategy as I said, is to hide this Liberal leader and their policies under a carpet, somewhere, in the hope that nobody notices.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, Laurie Oakes has written an article based on a chat that he's had with you. In that chat you were reasonably candid about criticisms of yourself and your Government's time in office so far. Is that a true reflection on your thoughts?</p>
<p>PM: I think it's a bit like this. In 2009, the Government focussed on getting Australia through the global economic recession. In 2010 we must focus on getting back to basics. Getting back to absolute basics. Absolute basics on the delivery of our projects on the ground. In health. In education. In housing. I think it's fair to say that as a Government we underestimated how difficult it would be to implement our commitments on the ground. It's easy to blame the global financial crisis for that, because of the impact it's had on the nation's finances. I don't think that's the sort of an excuse that a Prime Minister should offer.</p>
<p>So, when it comes to that, the Government has got to get back to basics, get back to the basics of delivery on health and education, hospitals, schools, housing, and make sure it's done. And that is our resolve for what would be the third year of this Government.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Have you been disappointed so far in your achievements to date given (inaudible)</p>
<p>PM: I think it's fair to say that I have disappointed a number of people around the country in how far we've got so far. I think it's also fair to say in terms of one of the other criticisms that's made of yours truly is that I'm probably not the world's best communicator. Take that on the chin. Someone said to me the other day, when it comes to communication, I think it's fair to say that as a communicator I make a first class policy wonk. I kind of get that. I understand the criticism. But you know something? I don't think in this business you get judged at the end on the basis of the quality of your one-liners. You get judged on the basis of whether you've delivered on the ground on the basics.</p>
<p>Can I add one other thing on the basics, by the way. There's a debate which is in Australia at the moment on the future of the national curriculum. It's really important. Our objective with the national curriculum is also, without apology, to get back to the absolute basics on spelling, on sounding out letters, on counting, on adding up, on taking away. The basics that I was taught when I was at Primary School a long time ago, and that's what our national curriculum is all about.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, just one more on the SA election, are you worried that there are any trends, or can you see any trends or implications from the result?</p>
<p>PM: I believe that Mike Rann, who I've known for a long, long time, is in there fighting a really hard campaign. No one should underestimate how tight any election is. I don't, because I've been through a few myself over the years. What I do know, however, is that with Mike's leadership, it's about two things. Being a strong advocate, anywhere, and everywhere, for the State of South Australia. And secondly, committed to keeping this State economy strong, so that jobs are protected and taking South Australia forward to an even more positive future.</p>
<p>These are strong messages. But they're not just messages. Contrast the strength of this economy of South Australia with the one that I was familiar ten and twenty years ago. </p>
<p>Can I just say, in the last decade, what we've seen is great strength developed. He's only been in Government for what? Two terms, is that right? Eight years? But I've got to say the transformation in this economy to being a strong economy, a really strong economy where jobs are growing, when it wasn't all that many years ago, that people were leaving this State in droves purely to find a job. I don't see that these days, because the economy is so strong. That doesn't happen by magic. That is because in States like this you've got strong leadership. But can I just say, it'll be a tough campaign, and as with any campaign, fought out on tough state issues. That's the case with state campaigns. But this bloke is a bloke I've dealt with for a long time, and he is a very strong leader.</p>
<p>Thanks folks, got to run.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
