<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11060</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                   THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                   DOORSTOP INTERVIEW                   SHERATON ON THE PARK, SYDNEY                                                  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/06/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Subjects: Governor of Reserve Bank, interest rates, economy, jobs</p>
<p> growth, junior wage rates, Bob Woods, Xing Ping - discussions with</p>
<p> Senator Harradine</p>
<p>E&amp;OE................................................................................................</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Pleasing sounds coming from Ian McFarlane in Melbourne this morning.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes, I've heard what the Governor has said. I think they're</p>
<p> very positive comments. We don't talk about the future level</p>
<p> of interest rates but there's no doubt that the Australian economy</p>
<p> remains very strong. It also has an existence which while it's</p>
<p> not uninfluenced by what happens in the United States it has a strength</p>
<p> and a resilience all of its own. It's very important that the</p>
<p> Australian people know that although we are influenced by the rest</p>
<p> of the world, we really make our own luck. And we've made our</p>
<p> own luck over the last three years and that's why we've</p>
<p> been able to stare down the rest of the world, particularly in Asia,</p>
<p> why we've been able to maintain high levels of economic growth,</p>
<p> low interest rates and low inflation. And the Australian community</p>
<p> has every reason to look forward to continued strong levels of economic</p>
<p> growth.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>In light of his comments are you fairly confident about continuing</p>
<p> low interest rates?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I don't make predictions about the future level of interest</p>
<p> rates. I've noted what the Governor has had to say and I think</p>
<p> those comments will be noted by a lot of people but the message is</p>
<p> unmistakable. People can look forward to very strong levels of economic</p>
<p> growth and economic prosperity for some time into the future. It's</p>
<p> no fluke. We have made our own luck and it's to the great credit</p>
<p> of the Australian people and the Reserve Bank of Australia has played</p>
<p> a role in that through its great management of the exchange rate.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr McFarlane says that even though we've had such strong growth</p>
<p> it is disappointing that jobs growth hasn't followed suit. What's</p>
<p> going wrong there?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, unemployment is a lot lower now than what it was three years</p>
<p> ago. It would be lower still if we'd been able to get past the</p>
<p> Labor Party changes to unfair dismissal laws. I note the apparent</p>
<p> views of the Industrial Relations Commission about youth wages. We</p>
<p> need to make more changes to the rules affecting labour market conditions</p>
<p> in order to get further reductions in unemployment but so far the</p>
<p> Labor Party in the Senate has blocked those attempts. It's about</p>
<p> time they changed their attitude and stopped just being obstructive</p>
<p> and against everything that the Government's trying to do.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Well, in light of what the Industrial Relations Commission has said</p>
<p> today, is there more pressure on the Democrats to support the continuation</p>
<p> of the junior wage rates?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I've only read the report in a newspaper but our position</p>
<p> remains firm. We would like the Senate to pass the legislation. That,</p>
<p> of course, means the Labor Party too. People always light on Independents</p>
<p> and the minor parties, they always let the Labor Party off.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What about Bob Woods today  his sentence  he's not</p>
<p> going to jail, what's your reaction to that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I don't think it's appropriate for Prime Ministers to comment</p>
<p> on court verdicts and I don't intend to say anything about it.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, the World Cup cricket tonight, how do you think Australia</p>
<p> will go?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Ah, now I will say something about that. Can I wish Steve and the</p>
<p> boys every success. I had a late night last weekend and I think I'll</p>
<p> have another late one tonight. But they've staged a tremendous</p>
<p> comeback and they really are hitting the peak of their form at the</p>
<p> right time. But the South Africans are tough opponents and it will</p>
<p> be an enthralling contest and I certainly hope our blokes win.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>In relation to the Chinese woman who had a late abortion, I understand</p>
<p> Senator Harradine had met with you in regard to that. Will you be</p>
<p> intervening?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I've had a number of discussions with Senator Harradine</p>
<p> about that and certain arrangements were entered into and certain</p>
<p> commitments were given in China as a result of a number of conversations</p>
<p> and exchanges. I certainly share some of the concerns that have been</p>
<p> expressed about this lady. But it seems as though an understanding</p>
<p> and arrangement has been worked out. And we think that is a proper</p>
<p> basis for handling it and that seems to be the view of the Refugee</p>
<p> Council. And I'll continue to keep a close eye on it but I've</p>
<p> certainly had a number of discussions with Brian Harradine about it.</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
