<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3341</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON. E.G. WHITLAM, Q.C., M.P., TO THE ANNUAL CONFERENCE OF THE BUILDING WORKERS INDUSTRIAL UNION SYDNEY MONDAY 5 AUGUST 1974</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/08/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003341.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER,<br />
THE HON. E, G. WHITLAM, M, P.,<br />
TO THE ANNUAL CONFERENCE OF THE<br />
BUILDING WORKERS' INDUSTRIAL UNION,<br />
SYDNEY, MONDAY 5 AUGUST 1974<br />
IT IS FITTING THAT THE FIRST PRIME MINISTER<br />
TO OPEN AN ANNUAL CONFERENCE OF YOUR UNION SHOULD<br />
BE A LABOR PRIME MINISTER. YOUR UNION AND YOUR<br />
INDUSTRY ARE ESSENTIAL PARTNERS OF THE LABOR<br />
GOVERNMENT IN BUILDING LITERALLY BUILDING<br />
THE KIND OF SOCIETY WE SEEK FOR OURSELVES,<br />
FOR THE WORKING MEN AND WOMEN OF THIS COUNTRY,<br />
FOR OUR FAMILIES AND OUR CHILDREN.<br />
I DOUBT IF THERE HAS EVER BEEN A TIME WHEN<br />
THE TRADITIONAL SOLIDARITY BETWEEN A LABOR GOVERNMENT<br />
AND THE TRADE UNION MOVEMENT WAS MORE IMPORTANT TO<br />
BOTH OF US, MORE IN NEED OF EMPHASIS AND CONFIRMATION.<br />
TODAY THE HOPES AND PLANS OF THE WHOLE LABOR MOVEMENT<br />
ARE UNDER ATTACK FROM AN EMBITTERED AND UNSCRUPULOUS<br />
OPPOSITION. WE MUST UNITE TO RESIST THAT ATTACK AND<br />
DEFEAT IT, IF WE FAIL, ALL THE GOVERNMENT'S HOPES<br />
AND AMBITIONS FOR THIS COUNTRY WILL FAIL, ALL OUR PLANS<br />
FOR THE WELFARE AND SECURITY OF THE WORKER WILL FAIL. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
IT IS TIME FOR CO-OPERATION AND UNDERSTANDING,<br />
WE ARE MINDFUL OF WHAT THE UNIONS HAVE DONE TO HELP<br />
ELECT AND SUPPORT THE GOVERNMENT, TODAY I ASK YOU<br />
TO REFLECT ON WHAT THE GOVERNMENT HAS DONE AND CAN<br />
DO FOR THE UNIONS, JUST AS WE ARE CONSCIOUS OF YOUR<br />
PROBLEMS, I ASK YOU TO BE CONSCIOUS OF OURS.<br />
IN THE LONG RUN OUR NEEDS AND INTERESTS<br />
ARE THE SAME THE DEVELOPMENT OF A STABLE AND HEALTHY<br />
SOCIETY, THE PRESERVATION OF A STRONG AND EXPANDING<br />
ECONOMY, NO PEACETIME GOVERNMENT, I VENTURE TO<br />
SUGGEST, HAS EVER FACED MORE COMPLEX AND TESTING<br />
PROBLEMS IN ACHIEVING THIS, THE CHALLENGE IS A GLOBAL<br />
ONE, A UNIVERSAL ONE, AT SUCH A TIME WE MUST LOOK TO<br />
OUR TRADITIONAL ALLIES IN THE TRADE UNION MOVEMENT<br />
FOR LOYALTY AND SUPPORT. OUR ULTIMATE TASK IS TO<br />
PRESERVE THE UNDERLYING STRENGTH OF THE ECONOMY,<br />
OUR IMMEDIATE TASK IS TO RESTRAIN ITS-PRESENT<br />
INFLATIONARY TENDENCIES,<br />
I DO NOT NEED TO REMIND YOU HOW DANGEROUS<br />
AND DESTRUCTIVE INFLATION CAN BE FOR THE WORKER AND<br />
HIS FAMILY, IT CAN DESTROY ALL YOUR EFFORTS AND OURS<br />
TO IMPROVE LIVING STANDARDS AND PROMOTE SECURITY AND<br />
SOCIAL JUSTICE, IT CAN ALSO, AS I SAY, DESTROY THE<br />
GOVERNMENT, </p>
<p>-3-<br />
THAT IS WHY, FROM THE MOMENT THE GOVERNMENT<br />
WAS ELECTED, IT HAS WORKED UNREMITTINGLY, CEASELESSLY,<br />
TO ATTACK INFLATION AT ITS ROOTS NOT JUST THE<br />
SYMPTOMS, BUT THE CAUSES, AND THAT IS A MUCH MORE<br />
DIFFICULT BUSINESS TO ISOLATE AND ATTACK THE<br />
CAUSES, THE DEEP-SEATED FORCES THAT CREATE WASTE<br />
AND INEFFICIENCY AND HIGH COSTS IN THE ECONOMY,<br />
I CANNOT PRETEND, LIKE MR. SNEDDEN, THAT WE HAVE FOUND<br />
THE MAGIC SOLUTION; BUT WE HAVE TRIED, WE WILL GO ON<br />
TRYING TILL WE WIN THE BATTLE, ALREADY WE HAVE MADE<br />
FUNDAMENTAL STRUCTURAL REFORMS IN OUR TARIFFS,<br />
IN OUR METHODS OF ASSISTANCE TO INDUSTRY, IN OUR<br />
APPROACH TO SUBSIDIES AND THE USE OF MANPOWER.<br />
ALL THESE REFORMS ARE ESSENTIAL TO A LONG-TERM<br />
ANTI-INFLATIONARY POLICY, THE IMMEDIATE BATTLEI<br />
HOWEVER, IS STILL FAR FROM WON, AND IN THAT BATTLE<br />
EVERY SECTION OF THE COMMUNITY MUST PLAY A PART AND,<br />
IF NECESSARY, ACCEPT SOME MEASURE OF SACRIFICE, </p>
<p>THE TRADITIONAL CYCLE OF BOOM AND STAGNATION<br />
IN THE ECONOMY, SO MUCH A FEATURE OF LIBERAL ECONOMIC<br />
MANAGEMENT, HAS BEEN PARTICULARLY MARKED IN YOUR OWN<br />
INDUSTRY, IN THE PAST 13 YEARS THERE HAVE BEEN THREE<br />
DISTINCT BOOMS AND THREE SEVERE DOWNTURNS IN THE<br />
BUILDING TRADE. IN JUNE 1972, AT THE TIME OF THE LAST<br />
RECESSION IN THE INDUSTRY, THERE WERE 230 UNEMPLOYED<br />
FOR EVERY 100 REGISTERED VACANCIES IN THE SKILLED<br />
BUILDING TRADES, THIS IS AN INTOLERABLE RECORD OF<br />
WASTE, INSTABILITY AND HARDSHIP, OUR TASK AS A<br />
GOVERNMENT IS TO TRY TO REDUCE THESE FLUCTUATIONS, TO<br />
KEEP THE INDUSTRY AT FULL EMPLOYMENT LEVELS AND<br />
MAINTAIN A RATE OF GROWTH THAT WILL ENABLE IT TO<br />
SUPPLY US WITH THE HOUSES, OFFICES, SCHOOLS AND<br />
HOSPITALS REQUIRED BY OUR GROWING POPULATION. I AM<br />
CONFIDENT THAT WE CAN ACHIEVE THIS, BUT WE WILL<br />
ACHIEVE IT ONLY WITH YOUR SUPPORT AND CO-OPERATION-</p>
<p>LET ME FIRST SAY SOMETHING ABOUT THE PROBLEM<br />
OF INFLATION AS IT BEARS ON YOUR OWN INDUSTRY, NO<br />
GOVERNMENT CAN HOPE TO CONTROL INFLATION WHEN, IN A<br />
FULLY-STRETCHED ECONOMY, BANKS AND OTHER FINANCIAL<br />
INSTITUTIONS ARE SO FLUSH WITH FUNDS THAT THEY ARE<br />
ABLE TO SUPPORT AN EXCESSIVE DEMAND FOR GOODS AND<br />
SERVICES, THE OLD STORY TOO MUCH MONEY CHASING<br />
TOO FEW GOODS APPLIES WITH UNIQUE FORCE TO THE<br />
BUILDING INDUSTRY, THE PRESENT TIGHT'LIQUIDITY<br />
AND HIGH INTEREST RATES ARE A RESULT OF THE<br />
GOVERNMENT'S DETERMINATION TO CONTROL AND REDUCE<br />
INFLATION, WE SHALL NOT CAPITULATE, WE SHALL NOT<br />
WAVER FROM THIS POLICY TO ACHIEVE SOME SHORT-LIVED<br />
POPULARITY, NOBODY LIKES A TIGHT MONETARY POLICY,<br />
LEAST OF ALL A LABOR GOVERNMENT, BUT IT IS<br />
NECESSARY FOR THE PRESENT TO KEEP MONEY TIGHT TO<br />
RESTRAIN PRIVATE SECTOR SPENDING, AS I TOLD THE<br />
PREMIERS ON 7 JUNE:<br />
" VIE ARE FOLLOWING SUCH A MONETARY POLICY,<br />
NOT BECAUSE WE LIKE ITS CONSEQUENCES IN<br />
TERMS OF FINANCIAL STRINGENCY AND HIGHER<br />
INTEREST RATES, BUT BECAUSE WE HAVE TO<br />
IF THERE IS TO BE A CURB ON EXCESSIVE<br />
PRIVATE SPENDING. I </p>
<p>-6-<br />
WITHIN THAT OVER-RIDING POLICY OBJECTIVE,<br />
HOWEVER, THE GOVERNMENT RECOGNISES THAT THE ESSENTIAL<br />
NEEDS OF THE ECONOMY FOR FINANCE MUST BE MET. WE<br />
WILL CERTAINLY NOT PERMIT ANY GENERAL DOWNTURN IN THE<br />
BUILDING INDUSTRY, WE WANT TO SEE THAT MONEY AND<br />
CREDIT ARE AVAILABLE TO FINANCE ORDERLY ECONOMIC<br />
EXPANSION, WITH THAT IN MIND, WE HAVE, IN THE PAST<br />
TWO MONTHS, RELEASED ADDITIONAL FUNDS TOTALLING<br />
ALMOST $ 349 MILLION, IN ADDITION, FURTHER FUNDS<br />
HAVE BEEN FREED TO HELP THE MAJOR TRADING BANKS<br />
MAKE LOANS TO INDUSTRY, COMMERCE AND RURAL PRODUCERS,<br />
FOR ALL THAT, I MUST SAY FRANKLY THAT A<br />
GENERALLY RESTRICTIVE MONETARY POLICY WILL NEED TO<br />
BE MAINTAINED FOR SOME TIME IF EXCESSIVE DEMAND<br />
PRESSURES ARE TO BE CURBED AND INFLATION BROUGHT UNDER<br />
CONTROL, IF MONETARY POLICY SOUGHT TO PREVENT A<br />
RISE IN INTEREST RATES WHEN DEMANDS FOR CREDIT WERE<br />
BOOMING, MONEY AND CREDIT WOULD EXPAND EXPLOSIVELY,<br />
WITH DEVASTATING EFFECTS ON PRICES, IN THE END,<br />
ANY SUCH POLICY WOULD PROVE FUTILE, OBVIOUSLY THERE<br />
ARE SOME COSTS TO THE COMMUNITY INVOLVED IN OUR<br />
PRESENT RESTRAINTS. BUT WOULD-BE HOME BUYERS, THOSE<br />
ON FIXED INCOMES, EXPORTERS AND THE COMMUNITY<br />
GENERALLY WOULD SUFFER MUCH MORE IF INFLATION WERE<br />
ALLOWED TO RUN UNCHECKED, </p>
<p>-7-<br />
IT IS NOW CLEAR THAT THE GOVERNMENT'S MONETARY<br />
POLICIES ARE BEGINNING TO STABILISE THE PRICE OF<br />
HOUSES. AFTER INCREASING BY 20 PER CENT OR MORE DURING<br />
THE PAST YEAR, THERE ARE NOW ALMOST DAILY REPORTS<br />
THAT HOUSE PRICES ARE LEVELLING OUT AND, IN SOME CASES,<br />
FALLING, OBVIOUSLY IT WOULD SERVE NO WORTHWHILE<br />
PURPOSE TO INCREASE THE SUPPLY OF HOUSING FINANCE WHEN<br />
THE HOUSING INDUSTRY IS OVER-STRETCHED, AS IT HAS<br />
BEEN DURING THE PAST EIGHTEEN MONTHS, ADDITIONAL<br />
FINANCE DOES NOT BUILD MORE HOUSES: IT SIMPLY ADDS<br />
TO INFLATIONARY PRESSURES, TO THE DISADVANTAGE OF ALL<br />
POTENTIAL HOME-BUYERS, NOR DOES IT CREATE MORE JOBS<br />
OR PROMOTE THE SECURITY OF THE BUILDING WORKER. YET<br />
THE FACT IS THAT IN THE YEAR TO THE MARCH QUARTER<br />
1971 THE LATEST PERIOD FOR WHICH STATISTICS ARE<br />
AVAILABLE MORE DWELLINGS WERE APPROVED, COMMENCED<br />
AND COMPLETED THAN EVER BEFORE. AT THE END OF<br />
MARCH THERE WERE OVER 100,000 DWELLINGS ! INDER<br />
CONSTRUCTION. THIS REPRESENTED AN INCREASE OF<br />
PER CENT COMPARED W! TH A YEAR EARLIER AND<br />
54 PER CENT COMPARED WITH 1972, </p>
<p>-8-<br />
THIS BACKLOG OF WORK REFLECTS MAINLY THE<br />
ENORMOUS INCREASE OF 44 PER CENT IN THE NUMBER OF<br />
HOUSING LOANS APPROVED IN 1972/ 73. IT HAS SERVED TO<br />
MAINTAIN ACTIVITY IN THE INDUSTRY AT A VERY HIGH<br />
LEVEL IN THE JUNE QUARTER. STATISTICAL DATA AND<br />
INDUSTRY REPORTS SUGGEST, HOWEVER, THAT WHILE<br />
LABOUR FOR FINISHING TRADES AND CERTAIN MATERIALS AND<br />
APPLIANCES ARE STILL IN SHORT SUPPLY, PRESSURES<br />
ON THE INDUSTRY HAVE BEGUN TO EASE,<br />
THIS IS TO BE WELCOMED. THE BIG PROBLEM<br />
IN THE PAST YEAR HAS BEEN ONE OF EXCESSIVE DEMAND<br />
FOR RESOURCES. THE RESULTING STRAINS HAVE BEEN<br />
A. LL TOO EVIDENT IN DELAYS, ESCALATING PRICES AND<br />
A REDUCTION IN PUBLIC SECTOR WELFARE HOUSING,<br />
OUR MEASURES HAVE BEEN DESIGNED TO MODERATE THESE<br />
EXCESSIVE DEMAND PRESSURES IN THE PRIVATE SECTOR<br />
AND TO PROVIDE SCOPE FOR AN EXPANSION OF PUBLIC<br />
SECTOR HOUSING, THESE OBJECTIVES ARE NOW BEING<br />
ACHIEVED, CONTRACTORS ARE AGAIN SHOWING AN INTEREST<br />
IN TENDERING FOR PUBLIC HOUSING, AT THE SAME TIME WE<br />
HAVE INCREASED OUR ALLOCATIONS TO THE STATES TO PREVENT<br />
ANY UNDUE REDUCTION IN THE DWELLING CONSTRUCTION<br />
INDUSTRY AS A WHOLE, ADVANCES TO THE STATES FOR<br />
WELFARE HOUSING IN 1974-75 WILL TOTAL $ 235 MILLION<br />
A RECORD FOR ANY GOVERNMENT, AND WE HAVE UNDERTAKEN<br />
TO PROVIDE ADDITIONAL FUNDS FOR WELFARE HOUSING IF<br />
THE STATES CAN USE THEM PRODUCTIVELY </p>
<p>-9-<br />
I WANT TO DEAL TODAY WITH TWO SPECIFIC PROPOSALS<br />
OF DIRECT IMPORTANCE TO YOUR MEMBERS, THE FIRST OF<br />
THEM, WE BELIEVE, WILL SERVE A TRIPLE PURPOSE IN<br />
RESTRAINING INFLATION, REDUCING INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES AND<br />
PROMOTING THE WELL-BEING AND SECURITY OF WAGE AND SALARY<br />
EARNERS, AS MY COLLEAGUE CLYDE CAMERON HAS ANNOUNCED,<br />
THE GOVERNMENT WILL BE SUPPORTING A POLICY OF WAGE<br />
INDEXATION AT NEXT WEEK'S CONFERENCE CALLED BY THE<br />
PRESIDENT OF THE CONCILIATION AND ARBITRATION COMMISSION,<br />
MR JUSTICE MOORE. OUR INTENTION IS TO RESTORE QUARTERLY<br />
AUTOMATIC COST OF LIVING ADJUSTMENTS TO WAGES,<br />
I DO NOT SUGGEST FOR A MOMENT THAT THE GOVERNMENT'S<br />
SOLE OBLIGATION TO THE TRADE UNION MOVEMENT IS TO<br />
COMPENSATE WAGE EARNERS FOR INCREASES IN THE COST OF<br />
LIVING, OR THAT SUCH ADJUSTMENTS SHOULD BE THE LIMIT<br />
OF THE WAGE-EARNER'S EXPECTATIONS. WE SEE INDEXATION<br />
AS ONE OF A SERIES OF WAGE PROPOSALS, WE WOULD HOPE<br />
THAT, IN RETURN FOR INDEXATION, UNIONS WOULD FORGO ANY<br />
WAGE CLAIMS BASED SOLELY ON PRICE MOVEMENTS AND THAT<br />
FURTHER WAGE AND SALARY INCREASES THOSE OF GENUINE<br />
SUBSTANCE AND LONG-TERM VALUE WOULD BE BASED LARGELY<br />
ON PRODUCTIVITY, OR CHANGES IN WORK VALUE OR CONDITIONS<br />
THESE CHANGES WOULD BE MADE PRINCIPALLY THROUGHI<br />
DETERMINATIONS OF THE COMMISSION. WE WANT TO RESTORE<br />
THE AUTHORITY OF THE COMMISSION WE WANT IT ONCE<br />
AGAIN TO BE THE MAJOR INFLUENCE ON WAGE MOVEMENTS<br />
IN THIS COUNTRY, </p>
<p>I HAVE TO TELL YOU FRANKLY THAT REPEATED WAGE<br />
RISES OF THE ORDER OF 15 OR 20 PER CENT OR MORE ARE<br />
INSUPPORTABLE IN PRESENT ECONOMIC CIRCUMSTANCES, WE ALL<br />
KNOW, OF COURSE, WHY SUCH CLAIMS HAVE BEEN MADE AND,<br />
IN MOST CASES, WHY THEY HAVE BEEN GRANTED. THEY HAVE<br />
BEEN MADE, NOT MERELY TO COMPENSATE WORKERS FOR PRICE<br />
RISES THAT HAVE ALREADY OCCURRED, BUT TO PROTECT THEM<br />
AGAINST RISES WHICH THEY ANTICIPATE IN THE FUTURE. IT<br />
IS OUR HOPE THAT INDEXATION WILL REMOVE THE NEED<br />
AND THE INCENTIVE FOR SUCH CLAIMS. WHEN WORKERS KNOW<br />
THAT THEY WILL BE AUTOMATICALLY COMPENSATED AS<br />
THEY HAVE A RIGHT TO BE FOR INCREASES IN THE COST<br />
OF LIVING, THEY WILL BE ABLE TO DIRECT THEIR WAGE<br />
NEGOTIATIONS TO QUESTIONS OF REAL AND LASTING<br />
IMPORTANCE TO THEIR WELFARE AND THEIR INDUSTRY.<br />
SOME MODERATION IN THE SCALE OF WAGE CLAIMS WILL<br />
HAVF SIGNIFICANT LONG-TERM ANTI-INFLATIONARY EFFECTS. </p>
<p>-11-<br />
WHAT A DIFFERENCE BETWEEN OUR ATTITUDE AND<br />
THAT OF OUR OPPONENTS, THE LAST TIME WORKERS NEEDED<br />
THIS PROTECTION AGAINST PRICE INCREASES IN THE EARLY<br />
1950S THE LIBERALS DEPRIVED THEM OF IT, THEY REMOVED<br />
QUARTERLY ADJUSTMENTS WITHOUT SUBSTITUTING ANY<br />
GUARANTEE AGAINST THE ERODING EFFECTS OF THE COST OF<br />
LIVING, 11O WONDER THERE WAS A WAVE OF INDUSTRIAL<br />
UNREST, WE HAVE STRONG HOPES THAT OUR PROPOSALS WILL<br />
REDUCE THE INCIDENCE OF WORKING DAYS LOST THROUGH<br />
STRIKES, IT IS NO ACCIDENT THAT THE FIGURES FOR<br />
WORKING DAYS LOST THIS YEAR ARE THE HIGHEST FOR MANY<br />
YEARS, YET 71.3 PER CENT OF THE STRIKES IN MAY<br />
AND JUNE THIS YEAR WERE DUE TO DISPUTES OVER WAGES,<br />
AND THE VAST MAJORITY OF THOSE WERE DUE TO WAGE DEMANDS<br />
REVOLVING AROUND PRICE MOVEMENTS, SO,* IN OUR VIEW,<br />
QUARTERLY ADJUSTMENTS ARE QUITE CRITICAL TO BOTH GOOD<br />
INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS AND THE FIGHT AGAINST INFLATION,<br />
WE HAVE CERTAINLY BEEN ENCOURAGED BY THE CO-OPERATION<br />
AND GOODWILL SHOWN BY THE MAJOR UNIONS, </p>
<p>-12-<br />
ICOME NOW TO A SECOND PROPOSAL OF HISTORIC<br />
IMPORTANCE TO THE TRADE UNION MOVEMENT AND THE FUTURE<br />
STRENGTH OF THE ECONOMY ON 17 JULY MR. CAMERON<br />
TABLED IN PARLIAMENT THE REPORT OF THE COCHRANE COMMITTEE<br />
OF INQUIRY INTO LABOUR MARKET TRAINI* NG.' MR. CAMERON'<br />
SUBMISSION TO CABINET ON RETRAINING -BASED ON THE<br />
COCHRANE REPORT RECOMMENDED THE ESTABLISHMENT OF A<br />
NATIONAL EMPLOYMENT AND TRAINING SYSTEM ( NEAT),<br />
THIS PROPOSAL WAS APPROVED BY CABINET ON 8 JULY, I<br />
PAY TRIBUTE TO YOUR UNION FOR ITS READINESS TO JOIN THE<br />
SCHEME AND CO-OPERATE WITH THE GOVERNMENT IN MAKING IT<br />
A SUCCESS. THE OPPORTUNITIES MADE AVAILABLE UNDER NEAT<br />
WILL BE AVAILABLE EQUALLY TO WOMEN AND MEN. WE SEE<br />
THE SCHEME AS PART OF A GENERAL MANPOWER POLICY TO<br />
IMPROVE THE ECONOMIC, SOCIAL AND EDUCATIONAL CIRCUMSTANCES<br />
OF ALL WORKERS, PARTICULARLY THOSE WHO FIND THAT THEIR<br />
OPPORTUNITIES AND ASPIRATIONS ARE THWARTED BY AN<br />
INADEQUATE EDUCATION.<br />
IEMPHASISE THAT THE SCHEME IS NO MERE SHOR-r-TERM<br />
PALLIATIVE FOR UNEMPLOYMENT. ITr WILL COVER A WIDE<br />
RANGE OF SKILLS, AND WHILE IT WILL BE PpOMPT AND FLEXIBLE<br />
IN RELIEVING SHORT-TERM UNEMPLOYMENT, ITS CHIEF AIM WILL<br />
BE TO RESTRUCTURE THE WORK FORCE TO ENABLE CO-ORDINATION<br />
BETWEEN THE SUPPLY OF ALL TYPES OF LABOUR. </p>
<p>-13-<br />
THE SCHEME WILL FULFIL THIS GOAL BY ASSISTING PEOPLE WHOSE<br />
CAREERS HAVE BEEN EITHER CIRCUMSCRIBED OR CURTAILED BY<br />
CHANGES IN THE NATURE OF THE LABOUR REQUIREMENTS OF<br />
INDUSTRY, BY STRUCTURAL CHANGES WITHIN INDIVIDUAL<br />
INDUSTRIES OR THROUGHOUT THE ECONOMY, BY CHANGES IN<br />
DEMAND BY TECHNOLOGICAL CHANGE, BY GOVERNMENT POLICIES<br />
OR CHANGES IN THE ECONOMIC VIABILITY OF CERTAIN<br />
GEOGRAPHICAL AREAS, IT WILL HELP PEOPLE DEVELOP NEW<br />
SKILLS RELEVANT TO THE NEEDS OF MODERN INDUSTRY,<br />
IT WILL AIM AT IMPROVING THE LEVEL OF SKILLS WITHIN<br />
THE WORKFORCE AND THE QUALITY OF LABOUR AVAILABLE<br />
TO INDUSTRY, FURTHERMORE, IT WILL ENCOURAGE THE CONCEPT<br />
OF CONTINUING TRAINING THROUGHOUT AN INDIVIDUAL'S<br />
WORKING LIFE SO THAT HIS SKILLS WILL REMAIN RELEVANT<br />
TO THE NEEDS OF SOCIETY,<br />
NEAT AIMS PRIMARILY AT PROVIDING FOR THE<br />
TRAINING NEEDS OF ADULTS, IT WILL GRANT TRAINING<br />
OPPORTUNITIES IN THE FOLLOWING ORDER OF PRIORITIES: </p>
<p>-14-<br />
i1 ANY PERSONS RENDERED REDUNDANT<br />
BY GOVERNMENT POLICIES,<br />
2, PERSONS RENDERED REDUNDANT BY<br />
TECHNOLOGICAL CHANGES,<br />
3, PERSONS WHOSE EMPLOYMENT POTENTIAL<br />
HAS BEEN AFFECTED BY HEALTHI<br />
IMPRISONMENT OR INAPPROPRIATE<br />
WORK SKILLS,<br />
4, PERSONS WHOSE TRAINING WILL OFFSET<br />
SHORTAGES OF SPECIFIC SKILLS,<br />
PERSONS WISHING TO UPGRADE THEIR<br />
TRAINING ON THEIR OWN INITIATIVE.<br />
THE SCHEME WILL ENDEAVOUR TO PROVIDE A TRAINING<br />
PROGRAM FOR EVERY APPLICANT IN LINE WITH HIS ASPIRATIONS<br />
AND HIS ABILITY TO COMPLETE A COURSE OF TRAINING IN<br />
NEEDED SKILLS, THE TRAINING ARRANGEMENTS WILL BE<br />
SUFFICIENTLY FLEXIBLE TO GIVE WHATEVER PRELIMINARY<br />
OR PREPARATORY TUITION IS NECESSARY TO ALLOW ENTRY<br />
INTO STANDARD TRAINING PROGRAMS, THERE WILL BE<br />
FULL-TIME AND PART-TIME TRAINING IN EDUCATIONAL<br />
INSTITUTIONS, INDUSTRY AND COMMERCE, AND CORRESPONDENCE<br />
TUITION WHERE APPROPRIATE, </p>
<p>THE FULL-TIME TRAINING ALLOWANCES WILL BE EQUAL<br />
TO THE AVERAGE ADULT MALE AWARD WAGE FOR ALL ADULT TRAINEES<br />
AND FOR THOSE UNDER 21 WITH DEPENDENTS, WITH A SLIDING<br />
SCALE OF ALLOWANCES FOR TRAINEES BELOW 21 DOWN TO<br />
PER CENT OF THE RATE FOR THOSE UNDER 18, ALLOWANCES<br />
WILL BE PROVIDED WHERE NECESSARY FOR FARES, TUITION AND<br />
EXAMINATION FEES, BOOKS AND LIVING AWAY-FROM-HOME EXPENSES,<br />
THOSE ARE SOME OF THE MEASURES WE HAVE BROUGHT<br />
FORWARD TO BRING WAGE JUSTICE AND WIDER OPPORTUNITIES<br />
TO TRADE UNION MEMBERS, THERE ARE OTHERS STILL IN<br />
THEIR EARLY STAGES,<br />
EVERY ONE OF OUR MEASURES WILL BENEFIT THE<br />
WORKING MAN AND WOMAN, THE WAGE EARNER, THE UNIONIST,<br />
WE ARE EXAMINING SCHEMES FOR NATIONAL COMPENSATION AND<br />
REHABILITATION ON THE BASIS OF THE REPORT BY MR, JUSTICE<br />
EA. WOODHOUSE, WE ARE COMMITTED TO A NATIONAL SUPERANNUATION<br />
SCHEME FOR ALL EMPLOYEES, WE ARE PLEDGED TO ESTABLISH AN<br />
AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT INSURANCE OFFICE, OUR RESTRUCTURING<br />
OF THE TAX SCALES WILL TAKE ACCOUNT OF THE NEEDS OF<br />
LOWER-PAID WORKERS, OUR PLANS FOR CHILD CARE YES$<br />
CHILD CARE WILL GIVE A NEW DEAL TO THE WORKING MOTHER,<br />
IT IS TRUE THAT THESE PLANS HAVE BEEN BRIEFLY DEFERRED<br />
OUT OF ECONOMIC NECESSITY, THE FACT REMAINS THAT WE WILL<br />
BE SPENDING MORE ON ESSENTIAL CHILD CARE SERVICES THAN<br />
EVER BEFORE, IT WILL BE AN IMPROVED AND ENLARGED CHILD<br />
CARE SCHEME, </p>
<p>-1.6-<br />
I REJECT UTTERLY THE CYNICAL OPPORTUNISM OF AN<br />
OPPOSITION THAT ACCUSES US OF NEGLECTING MOTHERS AND<br />
CHILDREN WHEN FOR YEARS THEIR OWN NIGGARDLY CHILD CARE<br />
PLANS CONDEMNED THOUSANDS OF WORKING MOTHERS TO HARDSHIP.<br />
THE DIFFERENCE IS SIMPLY THIS: THEY DID NEXT TO NOTHING<br />
AND PROMISED NEXT TO NOTHING, WE ARE PLEDGED TO A MASSIVE<br />
AND FUNDAMENTAL CHILD CARE PROGRAM.<br />
I CANNOT CONCEAL FROM YOU I CANNOT EMPHASISE TOO<br />
MUCH THAT THE SUCCESS OF ALL THESE PLANS DEPENDS ON<br />
THE MAINTENANCE OF A STRONG, HEALTHY ECONOMY. THAT IS<br />
WHY WE MUST CO-OPERATE IN THE BATTLE AGAINST INFLATION.<br />
THAT IS WHY WE MUST STAND TOGETHER, WORK TOGETHER,<br />
TO RESIST THE SABOTAGE AND OBSTRUCTION OF THE OPPOSITION.<br />
LET ME GIVE YOU ONE EXAMPLE OF THIS PETTY AND VICIOUS<br />
OBSTRUCTIONISM THAT CONCERNS THE TRADE UNION MOVEMENT.<br />
WE HAVE INTRODUCED A CONCILIATION AND ARBITRATION BILL.<br />
IT WILL, AMONG OTHER THINGS, FACILITATE THE MAKING OF<br />
INDUSTRIAL AGREEMENTS. IT WAS PART OF OUR POLICY; IT<br />
WAS APPROVED BY THE I'OPFLE; IT IS SUPPORTED BY THE UNIONS<br />
AND THE EMPLOYERS. YET THE OPPOSITION WILL OPPOSE IT.<br />
WHAT SORT OF DEMOCRACY IS THAT? YOU WANT IT; THE<br />
EMPLOYERS WANT IT; THE PEOPLE WANT IT. BUT THE<br />
OPPOSITION SAYS NO, </p>
<p>-17-<br />
You SHOULD HAVE NO ILLUSIONS ABOUT THE CHOICE<br />
BEFORE YOU, IT IS SOMETIMES TEMPTING FOR PROFESSIONAL<br />
UNIONLEADERS TO TAKE THE CYNICAL VIEW THAT ONE<br />
GOVERNMENT IS AS GOOD AS ANOTHER, THE FACT IS THAT<br />
THE PRESENT GOVERNMENT HAS DONE MORE FOR THE WELFARE<br />
OF WORKING MEN AND WOMEN THAN ANY GOVERNMENT IN OUR<br />
HISTORY, EVERY DECISION WE HAVE TAKEN, EVERY PRIORITY<br />
WE HAVE ADOPTED, HAS BEEN DIRECTED TO THE BENEFIT OF<br />
THOSE MOST IN NEED, TO THE CARE OF THE WEAK AND VULNERABLE<br />
SECTIONS OF THE COMMUNITY, AND TO THE CREATION OF WIDER<br />
AND MORE EQUAL OPPORTUNITIES FOR ALL OUR CITIZENS,<br />
THE AUSTRALIAN WORKER TODAY IS BETTER OFF THAN<br />
HE HAS EVER BEEN NOT JUST IN MATERIAL TERMS, IMPORTANT<br />
AS THAT IS, BUT IN THE RANGE AND QUALITY OF SOCIAL<br />
OPPORTUNITIES WE HAVE OPENED UP FOR HIM. REMEMBER<br />
ALL WE HAVE DONE FOR EDUCATION EDUCATION AT EVERY<br />
LEVEL; FOR SOCIAL SECURITY; FOR AUSTRALIA'S<br />
REPUTATION IN THE WORLD, REMEMBER ALL WE HAVE DONE<br />
FOR MIGRANTS, WHO ARE SUCH A SIGNIFICANT PROPORTION OF<br />
YOUR MEMBERSHIP, </p>
<p>-1 8c<br />
WHERE WOULD WE BE TODAY IF THE LIBERALS HAD<br />
STILL BEEN IN POWER SINCE 1972? WE WOULD BE REELING UNDER<br />
THE WORST AND CRUDEST KINDS OF ANTI-INFLATIONARY ACTION:<br />
MASSIVE UNEMPLOYMENT AN NUTILSANTO. OUR<br />
YOUNG WORKERS WOULD STILL BE SUBJECT TO CONSCRIPTION.<br />
OUR SCHOOLS WOULD STILL BE IMPOVERISHED AND DEVOID OF<br />
HOPE. PRICES, UNCHECKED BY OUR TRIBUNAL, WOULD BE FAR<br />
HIGHER THAN THEY ARE NOW, OUR DOLLAR WOULD STILL BE<br />
UNDERVALUED. OUR INDUSTRIES AND RESOURC. ES WOULD STILL<br />
BE VULNERABLE TO FOREIGN TAKEOVER AND CONTROL. THE WHOLE<br />
SINISTER APPARATUS OF PENAL CLAUSES AND ANTI-UNION<br />
PROPAGANDA WOULD BE IN FULL STRIDE, INTIMIDATING THE<br />
WORKER AND THREATENING THE UNION4S WITH PENALTIES AND<br />
RESTRAINTS. OUR OPPONENTS KNOW THIS, THEY BITTERLY RESENT WHAT<br />
WE ARE DOING TO MODERNISE AND DEMOCRATISE AUSTRALIAN SOCIETY,<br />
How INCREDIBLE IT IS, HOW MONSTROUS, THAT LESS THAN THREE<br />
MONTHS AFTER A GENERAL ELECTION THE TWO-TIME LOSERS SHOULD<br />
STILL BE RESISTING THE UMPIRE'IS DECISION, STILL CLINGING<br />
TO A PATHETIC BELIEF IN THEIR GOD-GIVEN RIGHT TO RULE,<br />
IAPPEAL TO YOU TO STAND BESIDE THE GOVERNMENT YOU ELECTED.<br />
IAPPEAL TO YOU TO CO-OPERATE WITH US IN ALL WE ARE DOING1<br />
TO MOBILIZE THE POWER AND RESOURCES OF~ THE TRADE UNION<br />
MOVEMENT IN RESISTING THE SABOTAGE OF THE OPPOSITION AND<br />
EXPOSING THEIR HYPOCRISY AND DECEIT. LET ' THIS CONFERENCE,<br />
WHICH I NOW HAVE PLEASURE IN DECLARING OPEN, BE THE FIRST<br />
MOVE IN THI'S DRIVE TO CONFIRM G'JIR SOLIDARITY, TO RESTORE<br />
OUR DETERMI'NATION AND RENEW OUR HOPES FOR THE FUTURE. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
