<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5350</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS TO THE CONFEDERATION OF AUSTRALIAN INDUSTRY</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/05/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005350.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
The Right Honourable Malcolm Fraser, M. P.<br />
ADDRESS TO THE CONFEDERATION<br />
OF AUSTRALIAN INDUSTRY </p>
<p>ADDRESS TO THE CONFEDERATION OF AUSTRALIAN INDUSTRY<br />
The following is the edited text of an address<br />
by the Prime Minister, the Rt Hon. Malcolm Fraser,<br />
to the Confederation of Australian Industry<br />
on 12 May1980.<br />
I am very pleased to be with you to address such an<br />
important national forum as the Confederation of<br />
Australian Industry. It provides an essential opportunity<br />
for those engaged in a wide range of industries<br />
to look at their future direction and shape.<br />
Much has already happened in the 1980s which<br />
suggests that we live in difficult international circumstances.<br />
Yet, in spite of this, Australia has entered this<br />
decade blessed with a combination of assets, some or<br />
all of which are denied to other countries. This is not<br />
the time to be daunted by the prospect of difficulty.<br />
Rather, we need to add to our impressive legacy of<br />
endowments a motivation and determination to capitalise<br />
on the undeniable opportunities unfolding before<br />
us. It is the same with any new period in history.<br />
Each decade presents new challenges, new opportunities,<br />
unimagined difficulties and the prospect of inevitable<br />
change. But none can justify a reluctance to<br />
tackle the future.<br />
It is worth remembering that the most dramatic<br />
political and economic events of the 1 970s were quite<br />
unforeseen at the beginning of the decade. The lesson<br />
. in that is that we must be ready to identify and face<br />
new challenges as they occur; seize new opportunities<br />
and seek from them productive advantage. We must<br />
never allow our creativity and our sense of enterprise;<br />
our preparedness to take risks and our willingness to<br />
surmount obstacles; we must never allow these<br />
timeless qualities to be corroded by crises or<br />
diminished by difficulty.<br />
Certainly there are difficulties. The political and<br />
economic instability in the Middle East and West<br />
Asia pose a continuing threat to the availability and<br />
price of oil. The staggering increase in oil prices has<br />
not only resulted in higher international inflation; but<br />
also, it has meant a significant transfer of real resources<br />
from the industrialised countries to OPEC;<br />
and both of these have contributed to lower growth<br />
rates. These are some of the factors leading to<br />
increased pressure from international industries for<br />
government assistance and protection.<br />
Another consequence of the international position,<br />
and in particular, the Soviet invasion of Afghanistan,<br />
has been a heightened visibility of the growing military<br />
power confronting us. The response by Western allies to this growing power has been a welcome commitment<br />
to the development of an increased defence<br />
preparedness. Yet this also has to be achieved at a<br />
time of severe inflationary pressures. Certainly then,<br />
we face an extremely complex set of inter-related political<br />
and socio-economic problems.<br />
Yet, paradoxically, the combination of these factors<br />
has led, on balance, to a greatly improved position<br />
for Australia, relative to that of her trading partners.<br />
Our political stability; our skilled management<br />
of the economy; our abundant natural resources; our<br />
proven skill in finding and developing them; and our<br />
favourable geographical location; all of these factors<br />
enable us to face a difficult international environment<br />
in a position of advantage and privilege.<br />
Challenges ahead<br />
Of course, challenges still confront us. The new international<br />
economic conditions will continue to require<br />
our industries to adapt at a pace not always so pressing<br />
when the economic environment is more favourable.<br />
After all, the * 1950s and 1960s were, on the<br />
whole, years of relative stability and moderately<br />
strong growth.<br />
An expanding domestic market was serviced by the<br />
rapid growth and maturity of a number of key<br />
manufacturing industries. A brisk migration program<br />
accelerated the forces of supply and demand. It was a<br />
period of diversification with a good deal of impetus<br />
coming from import replacement in the home market.<br />
But having passed through a phase of relative stability<br />
in the 1960s, industry met new demands in the<br />
1970s. First, we had a massive mineral boom and a strong<br />
inflow of foreign investment which came with it. This<br />
resulted in a rapid strengthening of our balance of<br />
payment position which for so long had been a constraint<br />
on domestic economic growth. Our capacity to<br />
import vital goods for industry was improved. Then in<br />
the early 1 970s, came the. energy crisis, triggered by<br />
massive OPEC price increases, followed by a world<br />
wide bout of severe wage and price inflation and<br />
recession. All the Western industrialised countries felt these<br />
pressures but the response in Australia of the government<br />
of the day was in itself, a transparent crisis of </p>
<p>management and policy because in many ways,<br />
Australia was in a more fortunate position than most<br />
other countries.<br />
Our natural resources, significantly developed at<br />
the end of the 1960s; our great endowment of energy;<br />
our long record of lower inflation: these should have<br />
provided the foundation for a relative improvement<br />
in Australia's position during these difficult years.<br />
Yet, we lost ground. Australia suffered a severe loss of<br />
international competitiveness. Australian industry<br />
lost export markets; faced increasing competition<br />
from imports; and, as a result, became locked in a<br />
struggle for survival, let alone adjustment.<br />
Now, five years later, as a result of steady application<br />
of responsible policies, designed, first and foremost<br />
to reduce inflation and inflationary expectations,<br />
dynamic forces are at work in the Australian economy<br />
and Australian industry which give cause for justifiable<br />
optimism.<br />
The Government has worked from the premise that<br />
it must restore a stable economic climate in which<br />
business can make decisions. It has remained<br />
dedicated to the belief that much of the future prosperity<br />
of Australian industry will come from a fuller<br />
participation in world trade; that, as a consequence of<br />
this, our first priority must be to encourage the development<br />
of internationally successful industries by improving<br />
and maintaining our overall competitive position.<br />
And part of our program for promoting this, has<br />
involved investment allowances, export incentives<br />
and research and development assistance.<br />
Strength in industry<br />
Just as importantly, government policies have been<br />
designed to foster strength in Australian industry. In<br />
the three years to 1978-79, Commonwealth Budget<br />
outlays showed virtually no growth in real terms. At<br />
the same time, we have reduced the deficit, as a percentage<br />
of GDP, to under 2 per cent this year; sought<br />
to contain wage pressures and held the money supply<br />
at responsible levels.<br />
It is also a matter of concern that our political<br />
opponents continue to attack the Government's investment<br />
and other business incentives. Their firm<br />
restatement of those traditional commitments, I believe,<br />
diminishes the possibility of achieving bipartisan<br />
support in matters which are of major concern<br />
and interest to a thriving, prosperous and<br />
profitable Australian business. Our progress in the last<br />
four years, though difficult, has been significant. Our<br />
inflation rate, running at more than 17 per cent in the<br />
March quarter of 1975, was little more than 8 per cent<br />
in the March quarter four years later.<br />
Over the twelve months to March 1980, consumer<br />
prices have risen by 10.5 per cent. This increase derives<br />
primarily from strong rises in the price of oil and<br />
other internationally traded commodities, and must<br />
strengthen us in our determination to maintain our anti-inflationary stance. It is worth comparing the<br />
success of our performance with what has happened<br />
in a number of other countries. In the twelve months<br />
to February, inflation in the U. S. A. was 14 per cent; in<br />
the U. K. 19 per cent; and the OECD generally over<br />
13 percent.<br />
Maintaining our inflation success relative to that of<br />
our major trading partners is fundamental to our international<br />
competitiveness. And this competitiveness<br />
has been restored to levels which existed at the beginning<br />
of the 1970s, with a sustained improvement over<br />
the last four years in the order of 15 per sent to 20 per<br />
cent. The Statistician's major production series for the<br />
March quarter 1980 compared with the year earlier,<br />
showed rises in twenty-one of the thirty seasonally<br />
adjusted items with significant increases in steel,<br />
bricks, chemicals, refrigerators and some textiles. In<br />
rural industries, the recovery from deep recession has<br />
been even more remarkable. The value of rural output<br />
rose by over 60 per cent over the past two years.<br />
Income per farm more than doubled to be 75 per cent<br />
higher than in the first few years of the 1970s. All of<br />
this is reflected in the employment position. While unemployment<br />
is still too high, in the twelve months to<br />
March 1980, total employment rose by over 180 000.<br />
These are encouraging signs.<br />
The 1980s promise a continuing recovery for Australian<br />
industry. That is the only way we can be sure<br />
there will be benefits for all Australians. The vast<br />
trading potential to our north; our mineral and energy<br />
resources; the accelerated growth in all our industries<br />
from renewed competitiveness; and the beneficial<br />
effects of all of these on the economy will provide new<br />
opportunities for Australians in the years ahead.<br />
To take advantage of these opportunities, business<br />
and industry in the 1980s must be outward looking.<br />
We must be aggressive in our market thinking rather<br />
than tentative. We must take advantage of our geographical<br />
position rather than lament the mistaken<br />
view that we are geographically isolated.<br />
The Asia market<br />
It is not such a long time ago that Australia was described<br />
as an isolated continent, distant from the markets<br />
of Western Europe and North America. Yet<br />
today industrialising countries of Asia are a major<br />
and growing market for Australian exports at a time<br />
when Australia enjoys the combination of a favourable<br />
geographical position, a privileged resource<br />
strength and an increasingly sound economy.<br />
Most of the economies of East and South-East Asia<br />
are growing at rates ranging from 7 per cent to 12 per<br />
cent per annum, an impressive result when much of<br />
the world has been experiencing economic recession.<br />
These economies will need to supplement the output<br />
of their own growing industrial bases with a wide<br />
variety of imports, not only basic raw materials. There </p>
<p>are immediate opportunities for Australian rural industries:<br />
for coal, iron ore, alumina and aluminium,<br />
iron and steel, agricultural and specialised industrial<br />
machinery, consultancy services-and the range<br />
should widen. There is also considerable scope for the<br />
use and application of Australian technology and<br />
expertise, notably in the agricultural sectors of<br />
developing countries in the region. When one realises<br />
that the growth of the total import market in the<br />
developing economies of Asia has been projected by<br />
the Industries Assistance Commission at about 11Ip er<br />
cent per annum in real terms, then the opportunity for<br />
Australian industry is significant indeed.<br />
Asian countries are already high on our list of important<br />
markets. In 1978-79, Korea was our fifth<br />
largest market, China sixth, Malaysia ninth and Hong<br />
Kong tenth. Only six years ago, exports to the<br />
developing countries of East Asia were $ 409m; in the<br />
last financial year, they were $ 152 1 mn.<br />
The importance of these newly industrialising<br />
economies is heightened when we note that many of<br />
Australia's traditional markets either have restricted<br />
access for Australian products or have relatively<br />
mediocre growth prospects over the next few years.<br />
On the other hand, if current trends continue, the<br />
developing Asian market economies will have contributed<br />
about as much to Australia's trade by the end<br />
of this decade as Japan had by the end of the 1970s.<br />
Yet we can do better. Our share of the market in<br />
these economies is only a little over 3 per cent compared<br />
with Japan's share of 30 per cent and the<br />
U. S. A. 19 per cent. Thus, even a small increase which<br />
must be within our capacity, given our present low<br />
base, would represent a significant gain for Australian<br />
exporters. Wi th the right business attitudes and appropriate<br />
government policies, there is no reason why Australia<br />
cannot seize these opportunities, especially when our<br />
industries have demonstrated a capacity to seek out<br />
new markets and to change their pattern of trade.<br />
For over the last two decades, such a change has<br />
been dramatic. In 1958-59, about 16 per cent of<br />
Australia's exports went to East Asia. Twenty years<br />
later the level had risen to almost 40 per cent. By comparison,<br />
in 1958-59, we were selling about 54 per cent<br />
of our exports to Europe.<br />
Today, that market receives only about 19 per cent<br />
of our exports. These changes, already under way in<br />
our trading patterns, are not temporary. They will<br />
continue as real incomes rise in the East Asian and<br />
South-East Asian region, producing a quickening in<br />
demand for consumer goods, and for inputs for industrial<br />
development.<br />
Yet, in spite of these already developing trade patternis,<br />
we have heard, in recent years, an almost incessant<br />
request for government assistance to achieve<br />
structural change in industry. It is important to understand<br />
government and industry responsibility. The essential government role must be to create the institutional<br />
infrastructure and broad economic policy<br />
framework in which market forces can operate.<br />
We take the view that government cannot replace<br />
the key role of investors and company managers in<br />
deciding where new funds will be directed; in determining<br />
which companies and industries will successfully<br />
carry new projects through to completion and<br />
subsequent profit; in anticipating which products can<br />
compete effectively in a tough and changing trading<br />
scene. Where appropriate we are prepared to provide<br />
incentives to our industries; but the main engine of<br />
growth and progress must be our private sector. It<br />
alone can respond adequately to market signals and<br />
take productive advantage of the support for business<br />
development offered by the Government's policies.<br />
I have great confidence in the capacity of our business<br />
managers to recognise the changes in the external<br />
environment and to perceive the new trading and<br />
investment opportunities which these changes are creating.<br />
To speak of industries failing is to ignore the<br />
fact that good management in industry is synonymous<br />
with successful adjustment to change. Some firms<br />
may wither and fail; but no firm need do so. The historical<br />
lesson of Australian industry is that successful<br />
management does not wither; it adjusts.<br />
Australia's economic strength has been based primarily<br />
on the capacity of entrepreneurs, business<br />
managers and farmers to create, or build upon, industries<br />
which can compete effectively in the trading<br />
world. Notable amongst these, are our great ruralbased<br />
industries which in recent years have had to<br />
compete with EEC agricultural products in receipt of<br />
government support in excess of $ 30 billion for the<br />
calendar years 1977 to 1979.<br />
Steel industry record<br />
The Australian steel industry has an even prouder<br />
record in international competition and it has<br />
achieved this in the face of massive subsidies to its<br />
European competitors. For example, the French steel<br />
industry received approximately $ A800m in direct<br />
and indirect assistance from the French Government<br />
in 1979. And the U. K. steel industry received approximately<br />
$ Al250m in producing a little over twice as<br />
much steel as BHP. And despite massive government<br />
assistance to many overseas producers, our manufactured<br />
exports are successfully penetrating overseas<br />
markets. In 1979 Australia enjoyed a 28 per cent growth in<br />
the volume of manufacturing exports, proof of the<br />
increased orientation of Australian management<br />
towards the external market. Surely in the light of<br />
this, proponents of government programs of adjustment<br />
need to be very clear about what they have in<br />
mind. </p>
<p>It is significant that the Secretary of the OECD in<br />
calling recently for policies of positive adjustment was<br />
really suggesting the removal of government from the<br />
process of adjustment in order to allow the smoothness<br />
of market processes to work. For, it is a characteristic<br />
of market-based economies that they do respond<br />
readily, flexibly and. relatively smoothly to<br />
change and new opportunities. How much more desirable<br />
this is than a program of government intervention<br />
which distorts the process of change and locks<br />
capital and labour into unproductive enterprise.<br />
Adjustment to change<br />
Adjustment to change is the weather-vane of industry;<br />
for, in a real sense, change in industry is the only<br />
thing that is permanent. T. S. Eliot once said: ' In the<br />
life of one man, the same time never returns'. So it is<br />
in the world of commerce. And change, arising from<br />
market forces is the greatest part of the continuing<br />
adjustment which is taking place in our economy.<br />
It is an adjustment based on economidc factors; on<br />
an identification of needs; an examination of costs;<br />
and a capacity to reconcile both of those in a profitable<br />
way. It is when change threatens to be abrupt,<br />
severe and far-reaching, especially if concentrated in<br />
particular areas, that difficulties arise in a social sense.<br />
The resistance that can then build up, can be an impediment<br />
to any further adjustment. Governments<br />
can aggravate the process of smooth adjustment to<br />
change. The European experience has shown us how massive<br />
job subsidy schemes, capital subsidies and, in the<br />
case of agricultural. industries, blanket protection, obscure<br />
market forces; distort economic reality and create<br />
circumstances far worse in their totality than those<br />
they initially sought to alleviate. However, we should<br />
not countenance a sudden and radical departure from<br />
existing systems of trade adjustment.<br />
There is no productive future in living in a giddy<br />
and unnerving whirlpool of rapid and dramatic<br />
change. Historically, Australia has a record of<br />
smooth, beneficial and manageable adjustment to<br />
new economic circumstances.<br />
This is the most manifest in our move from being a<br />
country substantially dependent on our farms, to the<br />
development of a wider industrial base incorporating<br />
one of the most important mining industries in the<br />
world, and, in the process of industrial diversification,<br />
spawning a highly sophisticated tertiary sector.<br />
And more recently, the dramatic worsening of the<br />
energy position of industrialised countries, bringing<br />
with it as it did, severe economic problems, has called<br />
for rapid adjustment in industrialised economies. For<br />
all countries, the challenge is to maintain a long term<br />
balance between oil demand and supply. The<br />
prospect is for even higher real prices for oil as we<br />
move towards the end of the century. Damaging as these circumstances are for many<br />
countries, it only serves to remind us how uniquely<br />
placed we are to meet the new economic and energy<br />
challenges. Because we have regained our international<br />
competitiveness, we are able to fully capitalise<br />
on being one of the few net energy exporters<br />
among OECD countries, with substantial reserves of<br />
uranium, black and brown coal, LPG and natural gas.<br />
Energy policies<br />
Allied to this energy strength, the Government's energy<br />
policies are geared to securing our future energy<br />
demands by promoting the objectives of greater exploration<br />
and development of all our energy resources,<br />
conservation of our scarce liquid fuel reserves<br />
and greater use of alternatives to oil supplies. These<br />
objectives are being met. It is estimated that total<br />
expenditure on petroleum exploration and development<br />
will exceed $ 500m in 1980; an excellent recovery<br />
from the state of investment fatigue in the mid<br />
1970s. In 1979, the rate of increase in our petrol<br />
consumption was only half the average of the last five<br />
years and proof of the validity of pricing our oil according<br />
to its value in world markets.<br />
There is one aspect of the energy problem that has<br />
not been emphasised and that is the agreement by<br />
member countries of the International Energy<br />
Agency to set targets for oil imports as a means of<br />
underlining their intention to reduce dependence on<br />
imported crude oil. Australia has agreed to participate<br />
in this oil import target exercise. The targets emphasise<br />
the need for countries to adopt policies to conserve<br />
oil and to encourage the use of alternative<br />
sources of energy.<br />
In Australia's case, current indications are that in<br />
1980 our imports will be well below the target figure<br />
set. Yet, if we were to indulge in the extravagant use<br />
of oil; and if further emergencies were to arise as a result<br />
of shortages in Middle East supply or production,<br />
then the IEA would be entitled to look with a very<br />
jaundiced view on countries who failed to act responsibly<br />
in their use of scarce oil supplies.<br />
If, through extravagance now, Australia, in the<br />
future, was faced with forced cutbacks, our industries,<br />
our economy and our way of life would be in jeopardy.<br />
That is why we will not relax any of our efforts<br />
to maintain a responsible level of oil consumption. In<br />
the search for new sources of oil, the Rundle shale oil<br />
project poses a challenge to technology and an opportunity<br />
for Australia to increase dramatically its indigenous<br />
supplies of crude oil, coming on stream<br />
hopefully at a critical time in the production of Bass<br />
Strait oil.<br />
All this is happening because of the promise of<br />
competitive returns in Australia on capital, technology<br />
and labour skills, resources for which Australian<br />
industry has to compete internationally. This<br />
has brought to Australian industry a new phase in its </p>
<p>continuing adjustment, not contemplated a decade<br />
ago. It will provide for our industries a substantial<br />
advantage over competitors in many other countries.<br />
And our aluminiumn industry is already enjoying this<br />
advantage. Higher oil prices, together with greater national resource<br />
competition that they generate have reduced<br />
the number of countries in which it is attractive to<br />
build new smelting capacity. Coal-based electricity<br />
generating costs in three eastern States are now considered<br />
to be significantly lower than those in many<br />
industrialised countries and there is every reason to<br />
believe that this competitive edge will be maintained.<br />
The increasing activity by other less well energyendowed<br />
nations to locate energy intensive industries<br />
offshore will add undoubtedly to Australia's already<br />
favourable economic position.<br />
Private enterprise is alive to the possibilities created<br />
by our energy advantage. And in the decades ahead<br />
we can expect that the new growth areas of mineral<br />
processing and mining will continue to expand at a<br />
rapid rate.<br />
With increased oil costs, the cost of shipping must<br />
inevitably rise bringing with it an added inducement<br />
to process raw materials in Australia and take away<br />
the finished product rather than bulk materials. That<br />
this is already happening represents a measure of the<br />
adjustment being made in Australia to the new world<br />
demand for energy and energy based projects.<br />
But there are other sectors as well which demonstrate<br />
the increasingly competitive nature of<br />
Australia's resource based industries, including pulp<br />
and paper, wool processing, mineral sands and metallurgical<br />
processing industries such as zinc and copper.<br />
Human input<br />
To this must be added the human input, the skilled<br />
labour, the development and application of advanced<br />
technology and the entrepreneurial skills involved in<br />
production programming, marketing and innovation.<br />
These are going to be just as much a part of<br />
Australia's productive adjustment in the 1980s as our<br />
raw materials and energy.<br />
Another element required to productively complement<br />
Australia's balanced development in the<br />
future is an increasingly efficient and competitive<br />
capital market. A market which encourages the<br />
mobilising of equity and fixed interest capital; which<br />
Jhelps Australians to become partners and participants<br />
as investors in our development projects. A great program of national development lies in<br />
front of us. Australia will be capital hungry in the<br />
1980s. Funds will be needed from overseas, but we<br />
will also need to mobilise Australian savings for long<br />
term investment purposes. And here lie new opportunities<br />
for all Australians.<br />
I can think of no more effective use for the investment<br />
of our present savings than in the development<br />
of our national resources; in the support of outward<br />
looking and aggressive manufacturing industries and<br />
in the provision of modem finance and servicing<br />
industries. We have already taken positive steps to facilitate<br />
the financing of private sector initiatives. To enable<br />
the Australian financial system to meet the anticipated<br />
demands on it for long term development<br />
finance, it is important that the system be able to respond<br />
appropriately to such demands.<br />
These considerations prompted the Government to<br />
establish a commi ttee-the Campbell Committee-to<br />
inquire into the ways in which the Australian financial<br />
system can achieve its utmost potential effectiveness.<br />
The Committee has been asked to make its inquiry<br />
against the background of the Government's free<br />
enterprise objectives and broad goals for economic<br />
prosperity. Already we have taken some preliminary<br />
steps which have furthered these objectives and assisted<br />
the operation of the capital market and the<br />
financing of domestic projects.<br />
Amongst these are inter-related initiatives including<br />
the Commonwealth's reduction in its own demands<br />
on the capital market through a reduction of<br />
its deficit and the Government's streamlining of its<br />
methods of selling its securities. These measures have<br />
secured a more effective control of the money aggregates<br />
creating a more stable monetary environment<br />
which is critical for economic growth and the control<br />
of inflation. They have induced confidence in<br />
Australia's economic future and this confidence is<br />
well placed.<br />
The diversity of the opportunities before us is immense<br />
and constantly changing. These opportunities<br />
must surely inspire those with ideas and a willingness<br />
to implement them. They must surely galvanise into<br />
action others who enjoy challenge and the rewards<br />
that come from successfully meeting it.<br />
One of the easiest ways to successfully predict the<br />
future is to accept the responsibility for shaping it.<br />
Leaders of Australian industry have a proud role in<br />
this regard throughout our history. I am confident<br />
that in the years ahead the promise that we now see<br />
will become the progress we all seek.<br />
Printed by Authority by the Commonwealth Government Printer </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
