<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4590</transcript-id>
    <title>HURSTVILLE RALLY, 8 DECEMBER 1977</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/12/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004590.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO: 8.30 p. m.<br />
FOR PRESS .8TH DECEMBER 1977<br />
HURSTVILLE RALLY<br />
on Saturday, a g reat decision has to be made, a decision about<br />
our future, about the kind of life we want to lead, about the<br />
kind of country we want to pass onto our children.<br />
We must elect a government that meets the real needs, the real<br />
aspirations of the Australian people, that will provide<br />
Australians with the freedom to build the kind of life we<br />
want, that will provide incentives to achieve and fair reward<br />
for initiative, that will create opportunities and productive<br />
jobs for our young people, that will give effective assistance<br />
to the -poor and disadvantaged in ways that increase dignity<br />
and self-respect, that will let our great country grow<br />
and develop, bringing prosperity and a better life for all<br />
Australians. There is only one choice, for only the Liberal Government has the<br />
policies, the experience and the will to meet these needs, to<br />
realise Australia's potential. Australia is poised to move into<br />
the 80' s and beyond with a new found confidence, a new spirit,<br />
a new sense of security, a-new sense-of national purpose.<br />
We were elected to get this country back on its feet, to revive a<br />
failing economy and restore to all Australians the prosperity which<br />
we once knew. we were elected the cut the inflation we inherited.<br />
tnflation is down to 9% and it's falling. We were elected to control<br />
Government spending. We have halved Labor's $ 4,500 million deficit.<br />
We were elected to break the-crippling burden of Labor's excessive<br />
taxation. We have substantially cut the taxes of every Australian,<br />
it's now worth working overtime again. Above all, we were elected<br />
to get Australia moving again, and already we can see the results.<br />
Industry is starting to invest again, our natural resources are being<br />
opened up once more and there is new found confidence in our<br />
manufacturing industry. $ 6,000 million dollars worth of investment<br />
projects in mining, manufacturing, processing, retailing and<br />
construction are under way or ready to go and many billions of<br />
dollars more are in the pipeline.<br />
Now our task is to work together-to ensure that we build on the<br />
firm foundations we have laid. A bright future is before us, a<br />
future which promises work and prosperity for all Australians. Under<br />
a Liberal Government, we are ready to stride into a new era of<br />
prosperity and development. 2/ </p>
<p>. Our policies are demonstrably succeeding. We have the lonly<br />
policies which will keep Australia growing. Policies that will<br />
-guarantee Australia's development and the creation of new jobs.<br />
We will push inflation down to between six and eight percent by<br />
next June. We will keep industry investing. We will keep<br />
interest rates falling down as much as two per cent over the next<br />
twelve months. That's a saving of $ 520 a year, $ 10 a week to the<br />
average young couple buying a new home.<br />
Most importantly we will get unemployment down: investment that<br />
means jobs, getting inflation down that means jobs, getting<br />
interest rates down that means jobs.<br />
Because of our prudence in Government spending, we can afford more.'<br />
tax cuts for all Australian taxpayers. They will. start on the first<br />
of February, just two months away. ' They will increase people's income<br />
and inject $ 26.7 million a week into the economy.<br />
Because we have reduced inflation the-tax cuts will create more<br />
jobs. Because people can spend more our factories will : have to produce<br />
more. There will be a demand for more employees. That is why, from<br />
next February, unemployment will fall and keep on falling. We are<br />
determined to foster Australian industry's new found vitality. This<br />
Government buys Australian, not the cheapest foreigh-products<br />
our predecessor favoured.<br />
We will give export sales fresh impetus with a new five-year<br />
export incentive scheme. We will provide special help to Australina<br />
businesses competing for overseas projects. We will actively promote<br />
more processing in Australia of our basic raw materials. To small<br />
businessmen we will make finance more readily available. Unlike the<br />
Labor Party, we are giving Australian industry, Australian jobs and<br />
Australian workers, the protection they need.<br />
We have increased protection for industries employing over a quarter<br />
of a million Australian men and women. Our swift and effective<br />
action has meant the survival of industries such as the apparel,<br />
textiles, and footwear industries, industries employing 120,000.<br />
Last week, the Labor Party refused point blank to support our<br />
action. They turned their backs on 120,000 working Australians,<br />
of whom are women,. and many of whom are migrants. It is Labor * that<br />
-the---party -of -unemptloyment. I--ws-r. Wi--m who,. when-he-, was<br />
Prime Minister, put tens of thousands of Australians out of work<br />
through his notorious, indiscriminate 25% across the board tariff<br />
cuts. He made unemployment a deliberate, calculated part of<br />
Government policy. He went and cut tariffs,, despite the fact that he<br />
was warned by a top level report that such a slash in tariffs would<br />
throw tens of thousands out of work.<br />
Now he wants to do it again. Labor's tariff policy would cause massi~ r<br />
unemployment. Labor wants a " crash" spending programme that would<br />
involve $ 800 million in six months. That's an annual rate of $ 1600<br />
million a year. And they have other promises worth billions of<br />
dollars they haven't even costed.<br />
All this would more than double the deficit,' unleash inflation once<br />
again, and increase interest rates. ThI's could only have one resul-t,<br />
it would create more unemployment. 3/ </p>
<p>Labor has said it would repeal our February first tax cuts and<br />
tax indexation is under threat too. For a fortnight, Labor's<br />
half dozen economic spokesmen have been in utter confusion and disarray<br />
constantly contradicting each other over their Party's policy on tax<br />
indexation. When the Shadow Treasurer, Mr. Hurford, was asked in<br />
Cairns what Labor's policy was, he said he couldn't say, because he<br />
had only read the " Cairns Post". He said he would be having a press<br />
conference in a few days, and he'd make sure he'd read the major<br />
city papers by then. He did read the papers, and he immediately<br />
cancelled his press conference.<br />
The new tax cuts which come in on February 1st are vital reforms. Thes<br />
tax cuts are fair. People on average earnings of $ 10,000 a year<br />
will pay a marginal rate of tax of only 32 cents in the dollar. Under<br />
the Hayden scales it was 45 cents. From February 1st, it will be<br />
32 cents right up to $ 16,000. These tax cuts are substantial. Over<br />
of taxpayers will.. pay less than one quarter of their incomes in<br />
tax. These tax cuts are a significant social reform. A quarter of a million<br />
low income earners, tens of thousands of pensioners, widows, andII<br />
students, with taxable incomes under $ 3,750 a year, will no longer pay<br />
any tax at all.<br />
Th ese are the people Labor forgot. To pay for abolition of payroll<br />
tax, Labor would have to increase personal taxes by $ 850 million this<br />
year, ,$ 1900 million next.<br />
Only the present members of the Labor Party would seriously put forward<br />
a plan to rip $ 850 million this year and $ 1900 million next year<br />
out of the hands of the working men and women of Australia, and use it<br />
to pay big and profitable companies.<br />
No jobs would be created. The companies have said so. The working<br />
men and women of Australia won't vote for this. They won't vote for<br />
any of Labor's policy proposals. They will vote for the Government's<br />
positive programmes which-meet theneeds of all Australians, and which<br />
cut their taxes, not increase them.<br />
Our tax reforms have not ended yet. All estates passing between<br />
husband and wife, parent and child will be free of Federal Estate<br />
and Gift Duty as from November 21st, the day of my policy speech.<br />
Over -the, life-of-thene-xta rl iam nti, both these taxes will be<br />
entirely abolished. </p>
<p>~ c<br />
D . I -4-<br />
' Ladies and Gentlemen, the Government's strategy to increase<br />
jobs is working. Total employment has risen by 180,000 since<br />
we came to office. Only through this Government will our<br />
. industries fully recover and only through that. recovery can<br />
we get unemployment down permanently.<br />
That recovery is now underway. A new period of stability<br />
S.' and fuller employment is within our grasp. It is an opportunity<br />
that might-not come again for a very long time.<br />
While our economic recovery is underway, we are helping those<br />
looking for work to improve their skills, and thus be equipped<br />
. to take new jobs as they arise.<br />
Already over 120,000 people have been helped by our training<br />
and job assistance schemes, and the number is steadily growing.<br />
We are making sufficient money available to ensure that no-one<br />
eligible for any. of these schemes will be turned away.<br />
We have a constructive, comprehensive and coherent strategy<br />
. to provide more jobs for more Australians. It is a strategy<br />
which inspires confidence, not Labor's doom and gloom. It<br />
is a strategy founded on the fundamental assertion that we<br />
can make Australia grow and prosper again, and this is something<br />
in which all Australians can share.<br />
We will improve the quality of the essential services which<br />
the Government provides; we will help the State railways<br />
by upgrading-the National Mainline System; we will expand<br />
existing programmes of support for urban transport. Sydney's<br />
train and bus-services can benefit from this; we will join<br />
the States in a National Water Resources Programme which will<br />
boost city and country water supplies; a study will be made<br />
of the sharing of electricity supplies in the south-east<br />
Australian region; and we will provide a new deal for telephone<br />
subscribers by reducing charges for off-peak long distance<br />
telephone calls to 40% of the standard rate.<br />
This Government offers Australia a return to prosperity, a<br />
higher standard of living, a continuation of efficient,<br />
consistent, coherent policies which have provided Australians<br />
with a new hope and a better future. We will press ahead<br />
with our programmes which are now so clearly succeeding.<br />
We will keep this momentum in motion. That will keep Australia<br />
on the move.<br />
We have laid the framework for a real advance into the future<br />
where Australia can be an example to the world: An economy<br />
we can be proud of, social justice for all Australians, care<br />
i : and-concern for the disadvantaged, and encouraging initiative<br />
and rewarding achievement.<br />
It has sometimes been a hard road getting to that point because<br />
of what we had to deal with at the beginning. But our policies<br />
are working.<br />
On December 10 by voting for the Government you are voting for<br />
a great Australia. My commitment to you tonight is that this<br />
Government, the Liberal/ National Party Government, stands<br />
:. ready to lead Australia to this better future.<br />
7 7 7 7' </p>
<p>And Ladies and Gentlemen, there is one othaer thing-that Z wou: ld<br />
like to say. In times of Politics, in times of elections,<br />
there is a tendency to divide this great nation, and in politics<br />
too often people seek to divide where they ought not. They<br />
bring issues that should not be matters of Party political<br />
debate into the political arena.<br />
All Australians in the Federal Parliament, in the State<br />
Parliament, in Local Government, Australians wherever they may<br />
be, have a duty to reach out'. beyond the bounds of politics to<br />
seek to understand and to define those issues that unite this<br />
Australia as one people with a common purpose and common<br />
objectives. -So that we may achieve a greater, a better, a<br />
more just, a fairer society. so that Australia may be an<br />
example of a free people united in common purpose, an example<br />
for the world. w </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
