<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10805</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP TELEVISION INTERVIEW WITH RAY MARTIN A CURRENT AFFAIR, CHANNEL NINE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/04/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, thank you for your time.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It's a pleasure.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>Wharfies and Wik - it's got a certain ring about it. Do I</p>
<p>   hear an election coming on?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I don't know when the election will be. But I want to say</p>
<p>   that I've always wanted a more productive waterfront because</p>
<p>   that's good for jobs, good for investment and good for our</p>
<p>   future. Australia's an island continent and we desperately</p>
<p>   need an efficient waterfront if we are to survive and prosper in</p>
<p>   the modern economic environment.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>If it was about productivity then why sack waterfront workers in</p>
<p>   Adelaide and productive ports?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, they're all part of the one union. I mean, we didn't</p>
<p>   sack them...</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>They had to go.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look, clearly the union had declared war on the company and the</p>
<p>   union leadership, for years, has refused the blandishments of the</p>
<p>   employers and other governments to bring more productive and more</p>
<p>   competitive practices to the waterfront.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>The 40 or so that went in Adelaide or those in Tasmania, that's</p>
<p>   just unfortunate.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, one of the consequences of having a bargaining monopoly ruthlessly</p>
<p>   used in the hands of the union that won't listen to reason</p>
<p>   is that some innocent people get affected.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>Because they say the other side, PM, wouldn't they - I mean,</p>
<p>   the unions would say: look, this is a badly run company, it's</p>
<p>   poor management, they've got no overall scheme. And what could</p>
<p>   they do?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I don't think there's any doubt, every single study</p>
<p>   has demonstrated that our wharves are inefficient by world standards</p>
<p>   and something had to be done in the interests of...yes?</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>Well today, I mean, we have a document from the Victorian Government.</p>
<p>   Jeff Kennett, the Liberal Party leader, put a nice polished document</p>
<p>   out in which he says promotes the wharves of Australia. He says</p>
<p>   quick ship turnaround times in Melbourne. He says companies located</p>
<p>   in Melbourne are assured of speedy and price competitive international</p>
<p>   shipping services. This is not the union, this is the Government</p>
<p>   of Victoria saying...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, the cold figures are that the container rate on a base is</p>
<p>   18 an hour, on average, in Australian ports - 30 in Asia.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>But why, see...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I don't...well, perhaps you've got to ask Jeff</p>
<p>   about that.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>But is he wrong, he said...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I can tell you what the figures are.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>I won't keep on at that but it's interesting, isn't</p>
<p>   it, that you find a Liberal government of Victoria trying to promote</p>
<p>   the wharves the very time that you're saying they're inefficient,</p>
<p>   they're totally...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I think that very same Liberal Premier was in the papers</p>
<p>   this morning strongly supporting the changes to the law that my</p>
<p>   Government has made.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>Now, you get the case of the Patricks manager in Adelaide who refused</p>
<p>   to sack his 40 workers - he thought they were so efficient - so</p>
<p>   he got sacked himself.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>But you've got to remember that you've...the unions themselves</p>
<p>   insist on a bargaining monopoly. They want one voice to speak for</p>
<p>   all dock workers all around Australia. And what my Government has</p>
<p>   tried to do is to break the monopoly of the union. We're not</p>
<p>   trying to break unions. We don't oppose unionism. We don't</p>
<p>   oppose unionists. We have no quarrel with people being members of</p>
<p>   trade unions. What we do have a quarrel with is the union, the MUA,</p>
<p>   indeed, any other union holding a monopoly over the supply and the</p>
<p>   recruitment of labour. And all the things you're talking about</p>
<p>   are a direct consequence, not of what we've done, but a direct</p>
<p>   consequence of the very bargaining monopoly in the hands of the</p>
<p>   union that we have tried to break.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>But we have today, we've got church leaders and others saying,</p>
<p>   look, you know, they fear we're about to have another era of</p>
<p>   industrial strife in Australia because of this.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, they really are wrong, Ray.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>We're not?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>We're not. Well, last year we had the lowest number of industrial</p>
<p>   disputes for 85 years - 85 years.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>Well, we've just sacked 1400.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>But Ray, I mean, that, in a sense, demonstrates that this particular</p>
<p>   union has been out of step with the rest of the community. This</p>
<p>   demonstrates that this particular union has tried to cling to restrictive</p>
<p>   practices that other unions have given up. </p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>All right. Are you surprised the ACTU decided, tonight, not to</p>
<p>   take action?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Pleasantly surprised because that is a sensible decision. The world</p>
<p>   has changed.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>What next then? What happens now...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I think the significant thing is that non-union labour, for</p>
<p>   the first time in decades, in some areas for the first time in Australia's</p>
<p>   history, is now working on the waterfront in Australia and that</p>
<p>   is a huge change. But remember, this is all about getting more jobs,</p>
<p>   more exports and more opportunities for Australia and giving...</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>That sounds weird, though, doesn't it, when you think we've</p>
<p>   just lost 1400?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I don't want...I never want anybody to lose their jobs and</p>
<p>   I regret the fact that those 1400 people have been stood down. But</p>
<p>   you've got to remember that it was the leadership of their</p>
<p>   union that created that circumstance. If they had changed their</p>
<p>   position over the years, even a few months ago, and adopted a more</p>
<p>   cooperative attitude and not tried to destroy Patricks, this would</p>
<p>   never have happened.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>You leave the impression clearly that the war is over, that you</p>
<p>   figure it's been...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, I don't regard it as a war. That's your language,</p>
<p>   it's not mine. I don't use...</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>Every paper in Australia...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, the papers - I mean, they can choose to use that language,</p>
<p>   I don't. As Prime Minister, I never use war' to</p>
<p>   describe a situation that involves human beings and involves people's</p>
<p>   hopes and aspirations.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>All right. Almost out of time but just very briefly - Wik. Is there</p>
<p>   any way that you can win on your 10 Point Wik Plan without a double</p>
<p>   dissolution?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Not unless the Senate minor parties were to indicate to me some</p>
<p>   time in the next few months that they would be willing to pass our</p>
<p>   Bill.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>And they're not going to do that, are they?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I'd like them to.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>But if they don't, that is a double dissolution, isn't</p>
<p>   it?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, if we are to get it passed, yes.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>So, it's an election before the end of October.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, if we are to have a double dissolution the Parliament has</p>
<p>   to be dissolved before the 29th of October.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>And PM, are you happy to go to an election on these two issues</p>
<p>   of the wharfies and Wik?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, Ray, I'd never wanted Wik to be an issue at the election.</p>
<p>   I've never wanted that.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>It will be one.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, the Senate has made that necessary. For my part, it won't</p>
<p>   figure prominently...</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>But again, just briefly, are you happy tonight, if you have to,</p>
<p>   to go on Wik and wharfies?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look, happy is the wrong word in relation to Wik. I believe the</p>
<p>   changes that we've made on the waterfront are in Australia's</p>
<p>   interests and I'm naturally always ready to defend and explain</p>
<p>   those changes in an election campaign. But there'll be other</p>
<p>   issues like taxation reform.</p>
<p>MARTIeform.</p>
<p>MARTIN:</p>
<p>All right, Prime Minister, thanks for your time.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Pleasure.</p>
<p>[Ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
