<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4570</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS AT BARTON LUNCH, 29 NOVEMBER 1977</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/11/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004570.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS 29 NOVEMBER 1977<br />
ADDRESS AT BARTON LUNCH<br />
This election confronts the Australian people with a choice of the<br />
utmost significance. It is a choice between two completely different<br />
approaches to Government, between two completely different<br />
philosophies of Government.<br />
The Government stands for responsible management of government and<br />
responsible control over the spending of taxpayers money, responsble<br />
reductions in the crushing tax burden imposed by Labor. Every<br />
encouragement to growth and development which will create more jobs,<br />
wage restraint, reductions in interest rates and firm and fair<br />
industrial relations policies.<br />
The Labor Opposition stands against all these things. That is why<br />
they are going to remain in Opposition.<br />
Our consistent and coherent economic policies are succeeding in<br />
restoring our country to economic health. Australia is ready to<br />
break through into a new period of growth and prosperity. Inflation<br />
is down to 9% and falling. Interest rates are coming down.<br />
We have supported responsile wage restraint. Income taxes at last<br />
are coming down. The crushing tax burden which increased 125% under<br />
Mr. Whitlam, is being relieved at last.<br />
These achievements have had a major impact in restoring business<br />
confidence. Plans for job-creating industrial developments which<br />
were shelved under Labor are now being put into effect. $ 6 billion<br />
of development projects in every part of Australia are now<br />
underway or ready to go. And this sum does not even include the<br />
magnificent North West Shelf Development which is a bigger project<br />
than the Snowy Mountains Scheme itself.<br />
All our economic policies are aimed at promoting greater growth and<br />
development, and thus more jobs. Labor slashed tariffs across the<br />
board even though they knew that this would throw tens of thousands<br />
out of work. Mr. Whitlam. is still saying that the problem with<br />
Australian manufacturing industry is over-protection. We have<br />
been prepared to give Australian industry the protection it needs.<br />
The major forecasts that the Government has before it show that<br />
with the continuation of the Government's policies, work opportunities<br />
will expand. The first of February tax cuts, just two months away,<br />
will increase household income and spending power injecting an<br />
extra $ 26.7 million a week into the economy. 2/ </p>
<p>-2-<br />
Because inflation is falling, the tax cut will have a positive impact<br />
on jobs. Our factories will get larger orders, and start working<br />
at higher levels of capacity. As that development gets under way,<br />
there will be a demand for more employees.<br />
The February tax cuts are a part of a whole approach by the<br />
Government to reduce taxation in the interests of economic<br />
recovery. Tax indexation is another part of that programme. And<br />
we will abolish probate and gift duties.<br />
Our February tax cut greatly simplifies the tax scale and completely<br />
releases 225,000-' low income earners from paying any tax at all.<br />
These people, including tens of thousands of pensioners, widows,<br />
and students, would have paid $ 45 million in tax this year. For<br />
many of them our tax reform will mean a saving of a significant<br />
proportion of their earnings.<br />
Labor's callous scheme would immediately reimpose income tax on<br />
these low income earners. Mr. Whitlam would reimpose tax on these<br />
peojie.<br />
Our tax cuts provide a new incentive to work by putting 90% of<br />
taxpayers on the same marginal rate.<br />
Under the Hayden tax scale of 1975, once a person's income reached<br />
$ 10,000 a year he paid tax of 45 cents from each extra dollar of<br />
earnings. If Mr. Hayden's tax rates were still in force, a person<br />
on average weekly earnings would be losing 45 cents in tax from<br />
each extra dollar of earnings.<br />
Compare this with our new standard rate system of tax. Taxpayers<br />
on $ 10,000 a year will pay a marginal rate of only 32 cents. And<br />
they can increase their income up to $ 16,000 a year without moving<br />
on to a higher marginal rate of tax.<br />
The combined effects of tax indexation and the new tax scales are<br />
a major breakthrough in incentives for people whose income earnirg<br />
capacity is about the level of average weekly earnings. And within<br />
the next twelve months I expect that falls in important interest rates<br />
could add up to This will have significant beneficial effects<br />
for the housing industry. On an average new building society loan,<br />
of $ 26,000 a 2% reduction in interest is a saving of $ 520 a year.<br />
That is $ 10 per week for young people starting their new home. Nothir<br />
can demonstrate the importance of interest rates more than that.<br />
Mr. Whitlam's policy speech could not have presented a greater<br />
contrast with our policies for growth and prosperity. Instead of<br />
further reductions in the tax burden he proposed a massive increase<br />
in personal income tax, a return to the old scales, a return to the<br />
old high marginal tax rates, a " crash" programme of government<br />
spending of $ 800 million and billions of dollars of further projects<br />
after that, and full wage indexation.<br />
He proposed no policy whatever which would have any realistic hope of<br />
reducing inflation. His big spending, high tax, high wage approach<br />
would pump.. up interest rates again. The effect of Labor's<br />
extravagance on inflation, would by like petrol on a fire and<br />
this would have a catastrophic effect on employment. 3/ </p>
<p>-3-<br />
Mr. Whitlam's Labor Party stands irrevocably for higher taxes. It<br />
would be impossible to pay for his programmes without a very large<br />
increase in the personal tax burden. To pay for Mr. Whitlan's<br />
proposal to abolish payroll tax alone a proposal costing<br />
$ 850 million in the first half of 1978 and $ 1900 million in<br />
1978/ 79. Mr. Whitlam would have to rip $ 2,750 million off the<br />
people of Australia, $ 6 a week off the average wage earner.<br />
Mr. Whitlam. wculd remove the incentive we have given people to<br />
work overtime.<br />
Mr. Whitlam has said that he would repeal the law legislating<br />
for our February 1 tax cuts and it is clear that he would end<br />
tax indexation as well. Mr. Whitlam, would remove the incentive<br />
we have given people to 1ork overtime.<br />
. He would increasa tax rates from 32% to 45% and the money he ripped<br />
out of the hands of the Australian people he would give to big<br />
and profitable companies. Just to take a few examples. Utah<br />
would get a windfall of $ 2 million, CRA $ 10 million, BHP<br />
$ 33 million, MIM million, CSR million, Bank of NSW<br />
$ 11 million, Ford million, ACI -$ 11 million, Dunlop $ 11-13 mi<br />
and General Motores $ 10 million.<br />
He would give these companies a windfall benefit at the expense of<br />
the working men and women of Australia despite the fact that<br />
abolishing payroll tax would not increase employment?<br />
Mr. Dunstan know-that'and has conceded that:<br />
" The Government has already tried a payroll tax remission<br />
scheme and found that it does not create employment."<br />
A recent survey of large employers revealed that not one company<br />
surveyed was prepared to forecast any increase in their own<br />
employment levels, if payroll tax were abolished.<br />
Labor's scheme would hurt the self-emlkoyed and many small businessmen,<br />
who are already exempt from payroll tax, but would be burdened with<br />
higher wage costs and higher personal tax commitments.<br />
The experience of Mr. Whitlam's policy speech over the last week<br />
shows more clearly than anything else that the Labor Party is still<br />
incapable of producing a stable and responsible economic policy.<br />
Labor has been in utter confusion since Mr. Whitlam's policy speech.<br />
For this last week and a half Labor's many spokesman have been trying<br />
vainly to come to some agreement on what Labor's policy should be in<br />
the vital areas of wages and taxes.<br />
The Labor's Opposition's leading members have resorted to all sorts<br />
of experiments to try to paper over these differences. They've had<br />
telephone hook-ups, they've had press conferences, and some of them<br />
have resorted to reading the newspapers to see what their colleagues<br />
are saying. Out of this massive effort has come even more massive<br />
confusion. The Labor Opposition is behaving just as they did when<br />
they were in government, they are indulging in a spate of<br />
uncoordinated, contradictory actions.<br />
Nothing has changed since the last time. Labor is still divided,<br />
conflict ridden and incompetent. Australia could not survive<br />
another three years of that kind of behaviour. Inflation would go<br />
through the roof, the growing confidence in the economy would<br />
vanish, the destruct. Ion of job opportunities would begin again. </p>
<p>Nothing has changed since the last time. Labor is<br />
still divided, conflict ridden and incompetent.<br />
Labor's confusion on wage indexation was such that Mr Hawke<br />
in desperation had a phone hook-up with Mr Willis, Mr Hayden<br />
Mr Hurford and Mr Combe apparently Mr Whitlam was excluded<br />
because his opinion was not considered important enough.<br />
As a result of that conference, Mr Hawke appointed himself<br />
spokesman and outlined what he termed the " absolute consensus"<br />
of the five spokesmen. The degree of consensus reached can<br />
be measured by the fact that Mr Hawke then proceeded to<br />
contradict himself three times within the space of a one page<br />
statement. First, he said Labor would have wage indexation<br />
up to average weekly earnings. Second, he said Labor might not<br />
advocate indexation above that level. Third, by the end<br />
of the statement, he was asserting that " a Labor government<br />
would be arguing quite clearly before the Arbitration Commission<br />
that its general principle was for full and automatic<br />
indexation for eveyone."<br />
If that's a consensus I would hate to see Labor disagreeing.<br />
Australia could not survive another three years of that kind of<br />
behaviour. Inflation would go through the roof, the growing<br />
confidence in the economy would vanish, the destruction of job<br />
opportunities would begin again. / 4 </p>
<p>-4-<br />
Mr. Whitlam, and the Labor Party have no constructive proposals<br />
on trade unions. How could they? The left wing unions pay<br />
money to the Labor Party. They have a large voice in determining<br />
official ALP policy.<br />
Labor's policy of letting the trade unions have their head,<br />
resulted in a record period of strikes and industrial lawlessness<br />
when they were in office. We have shown that a government prepared<br />
to take a firm and fair stand can protect the public. We have shown<br />
this in the air controllers strike, in the postal workers' dispute,<br />
in the case of the ACTU's uranium moratorium they backed down.<br />
And in the Victorian power dispute, it was our move to deregister<br />
the unions involved that led to the strikers returning to work.<br />
Of course, Mr. Hawke claims the credit for being the great peace-make<br />
in that dispute. Perhaps you have seen Labor's commercial in<br />
which he is in a motel room hurriedly packing his bags to go out<br />
and resolve yet another of his industrial disputes.<br />
Well in the case of the power dispute, it took Mr. Hawke nine weeks<br />
to finish packing his bags, get out of his motel room and take a<br />
hand. Unlike the Labor Party, we have taken the view that no one can be<br />
agove the law, that individual unionists have a right to be heard,<br />
and to be protected from intimidation. That it is the responsibility<br />
of the Government to protect the interests of the whole community.<br />
We have passed laws protecting individual unionists and given<br />
responsible rank and file unionists the chance to make their<br />
voices heard. Secret postal ballots for union elections are now<br />
compulsory; we have set up the Industrial Relations Bureau, to<br />
protect the public interest and also to act as an individual<br />
ombudsman; unions are now required to tell their members how<br />
union dues are spent. We are protecting individuals against being<br />
forced to join unions against their will and damaging secondary<br />
boycotts have been banned.<br />
All this adds up to a firm and responsible policy which has the<br />
support of all responsible unionists, and which protects the<br />
rights of the individual unionist and the public. Mr. Willis,<br />
the Labor spokesman on industrial legislation, confirmed yesterday<br />
that Labor would abolish all the Government's vital forms of<br />
industrial relations laws. Labor would repeal postal ballots.<br />
Labor would repeal our laws to protect the public from industrial<br />
disruption. Labor would repeal our laws which let unionists know<br />
how their union's funds are being spent. Labor would exempt<br />
unions from the provisions of the Trade Practices Act; Labor would<br />
repeal all penalties for strikes against Arbitration Commission<br />
decisions; Labor would exempt unions and their members from civil<br />
actions in respect of other wise actionable activities committed<br />
during industrial disputes.<br />
Australia has reached the stage where positive and constructive<br />
action is required in the trade union area. The Labor Party's<br />
attitude of complete laissez faire is quite inappropriate to<br />
Australia's needs. Some unions receive as much as $ 8 million in<br />
fees each year. They are too powerful for the good of our society<br />
to be placed beyond the reach of the law. We will continue to<br />
take the fair and firm approach in industrial relations which<br />
has proven to be successful. </p>
<p>In every area, the Government has laid firm foundations for<br />
national recovery. Our assistance to low income families through<br />
the family allowances has helped 300,000 poor families with<br />
800,000 children. As a result of our legislation, pensions are<br />
now increased automatically to keep up with inflation.<br />
The Government has been very conscious of the great contribution<br />
our migrant communities have made to Australia. Australia is<br />
proud of its place in the world as a country which offers people<br />
from around the world the opportunity to build an independent<br />
life for themselves and their families. our economic policies<br />
are designed to secure this kind of Australia for everyone. As<br />
an indication of the importance we place on the contribution of<br />
migrants to Australia we established a separate department of<br />
Immigration and Ethnic Affiars. We will establish ethnic<br />
television. We have put ethnic broadcasting on a secure long term<br />
basis. In the next three years, we will concentrate on overcoming<br />
the language barriers in our society both by expanding<br />
the teaching of English and the teaching in our schools of<br />
ethnic languages and cultures.<br />
Government Departments will have ethnic liaison officers. We will<br />
provide more interpreters, translators, more migrant resources<br />
centres. The Government has decided that the age service pension<br />
should, and will be, paid to non-British members of the allied<br />
forces.<br />
The way ahead for Australia is clear. We must work to lighten the<br />
tax burden, lower interest rates, and keep the pressure on inflation<br />
so new jobs can be created. Above all, we must work together to<br />
build this magnificent country. In the last two years, we have laid<br />
strong foundations for full economic recovery. It is vital for<br />
Australia that these policies be continued.<br />
If we stand by the great ideals of freedom, respect and concern for<br />
the individual, the ideals for which our party has always stood,<br />
Australia will release its magnificent promise, and we can show<br />
the way to the world. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
