<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9112</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES PROCEDURES 8 FEB 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/02/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009112.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES PROCEDURES<br />
8 FEBRUARY 1994<br />
Honourable Members will recall that during the<br />
valedictory remarks at the end of last year's Budget<br />
Sittings, I made some comments about the reform of our<br />
procedures here in the House especially in relation to<br />
Question Time.<br />
The new parliamentary year is a good time for us to be<br />
acting on the recommendations made by the Procedure<br />
Committee in its report, AbZ it Time.<br />
The title itself has a lot of merit: if we want to<br />
preserve the institutions of our democracy, if we want<br />
them to work more effectively we have to be prepared to<br />
change them where necessary. And, of course, there have<br />
been great changes since many of these institutions and<br />
procedures were first introduced.<br />
These changes are overdue as I said last year, the<br />
honourable Member for Bonython and the other members of<br />
the Procedure Committee have done us all a great service<br />
in the preparation of that report. </p>
<p>This week the Leader of the House will be tabling a<br />
detailed government response to the Committee's report<br />
and the House will be considering revised sessional<br />
orders. But there are some points that I wish to<br />
highlight. The Procedure Committee report dealt with three main<br />
areas: first, the handling of legislation particularly<br />
the need to free up chamber time for the proper<br />
consideration of legislation by providing a Main<br />
Committee ( or " second chamber") for handling routine<br />
and uncontroversial bills.<br />
second, parliamentary questions, and particularly<br />
Question Time, and<br />
third, when, and for how long, we sit.<br />
The Government has given consideration to these matters<br />
over the summer recess, and I am pleased to be able to<br />
inform the House that we intend to accept, in whole or in<br />
part, the great majority of the Committee's<br />
recommendations. Sitting times </p>
<p>Taking our sitting times first, it is clear the time has<br />
come to change the hours we sit. As we all know, and the<br />
Committee has confirmed, sitting late into the night,<br />
night after night, is not a productive or particularly<br />
sensible way to conduct our business.<br />
Except at the beginning of new sittings ( and public<br />
holidays), we shall from Monday 21 February sit Monday to<br />
Thursday each sitting week. So far as possible we shall<br />
stick to the ' two-on, two-off' pattern.<br />
In the other place, Senators will also be sitting four<br />
days a week and it will be convenient for the two houses<br />
to have similar patterns of sittings.<br />
Our normal starting and finishing times will be:<br />
Monday 12.30 to 8.00<br />
Tuesday 12.30 to 8.00<br />
Wednesday 9.30 to 8.00, and<br />
Thursday 9.30 to 6.00<br />
QOuestions Mr Speaker, the idea of reforming Question Time goes back<br />
a long way. </p>
<p>In an article on Question Time in the Journal of Public<br />
Administration in 1972, a scholar by the name of John<br />
Howard John H Howard concluded " new procedures and<br />
parliamentary institutions must be implemented". " It is<br />
no longer acceptable", he said, " to rely on conventions<br />
and precedents that were established over 100 years ago".<br />
The Question Time he describes sounds remarkably like the<br />
one we hear complaints about today. " The modern aim of<br />
Question Time", Mr Howard wrote, " appears to be not so<br />
much to seek information as to impart it, or establish<br />
debating points"<br />
He quotes a senior politician saying Question Time<br />
" enlists information to secure a political advantage and<br />
to embarrass the Minister concerned"<br />
" The first concern of a member of Parliament when he is<br />
in the House", Mr Howard said, " does not lie with the<br />
conduct of public administration. It lies with the<br />
survival of his party, whether it be in Government or<br />
Opposition".<br />
All the same criticisms are there in 1972:<br />
fewer and fewer questions being asked<br />
the practice of Dorothy Dixers </p>
<p>the intervention of broadcasting and press publicity<br />
which are alleged to have encouraged the diversion<br />
of Question Time into Dorothy Dixers and attempts to<br />
" score" by the Opposition<br />
the lack of " tranquility" in the Chamber<br />
the impossibility of enforcing Standing Orders as<br />
the Liberal Party Speaker, Sir William Aston said,<br />
" it is impossible to enforce all the Standing Orders<br />
at Question Time. I believe that if I did that,<br />
possibly we would have no Question Time at all."<br />
I know as does the Member for Bennelong that this<br />
Mr Howard was describing it accurately. Because I was<br />
there at the time. And, in fact, as you will see in the<br />
Hansard of 18 April 1972, I spoke on the subject.<br />
Mr Speaker, Question Time has always been a great deal<br />
less than perfect.<br />
As John Uhr wrote in a monograph on the subject a decade<br />
ago: " It would be wrong to look for some golden age of<br />
Australian parliamentary affairs when questions were<br />
asked and answered in an exemplary mode of nonpartisan<br />
public service." </p>
<p>It has never been perfect, Mr Speaker; it has always been<br />
to some degree in need of reform. But the Government of<br />
which the Member for Bennelong was a minister did not<br />
reform it. This Government will.<br />
The Government accepts the Committee's view that Question<br />
Time can be improved and that the time has come to try<br />
some new arrangements.<br />
The Procedure Committee recommended we should have a<br />
limited experiment with the rostering of ministers for<br />
Question Time. They proposed that ministers other than<br />
the Prime Minister, the Treasurer and the Minister for<br />
Finance would attend Monday Question Times on a roster<br />
based on half-hour segments.<br />
The Government, however, has decided that if change is<br />
needed, there is no point in tinkering at the margins.<br />
We have decided to institute a fully rostered Question<br />
Time on a trial basis for the remainder of this Session.<br />
With other ministers, including the Treasurer, I shall be<br />
available for Question Time on each Monday and Thursday<br />
to take questions ranging across the whole spectrum of<br />
government. </p>
<p>Other ministers will be rostered to answer questions<br />
relating to their portfolios and those of the Senate<br />
ministers they represent. The Leader of the House will<br />
be drawing up the roster and will consult the Manager of<br />
Opposition Business in the process.<br />
Question Time will be at 3.00pm and will last for<br />
minutes as recommended by the Committee, with a minimum<br />
of 14 questions.<br />
It should also be remembered that because the House will<br />
on that schedule be sitting one extra day in each two<br />
week session, there will be an additional 45 minutes of<br />
opportunity for questioning the Government.<br />
All this will mean that more homework will be needed on<br />
both sides of the House. Some Members of the<br />
Opposition's long front bench will have to think up some<br />
questions on their shadow portfolio responsibilities for<br />
the first time.<br />
As the other Mr Howard said in 1972, " The advantage of<br />
the Westminster system is that it makes the questioner<br />
have some degree of responsibility as well as the<br />
minister who has to provide an answer". </p>
<p>Those, like the Member for Bennelong, who complain about<br />
Question Time being used for political purposes, at the<br />
very least ought to have the honesty to admit that the<br />
questions are as political as the answers.<br />
Mr Speaker, our parliamentary system is based on the<br />
Westminster system of government and in my view is<br />
superior to any other. But as I have said, Mr Speaker,<br />
this does not mean it should forever close itself off<br />
from reform.<br />
The reality of the way in which our national politics is<br />
conducted is vastly different from that which existed<br />
when the current arrangements for Question Time and<br />
sitting patterns were instituted decades ago.<br />
The advent of television and other new technology, as<br />
well as the many points of accountability outside this<br />
place, means more emphasis is now placed on<br />
opportunities, and appearances and form as much as<br />
substance; more often than not on the theatrics rather<br />
than the seeking and provision of information.<br />
Some Members of this place have never required an<br />
audience beyond its walls to encourage them: I think you<br />
will find, for instance, that the former Member for<br />
McKellar in the early 1950s was ejected from the House<br />
for doing imitations of a gorilla. </p>
<p>In fact, Mr Speaker, I hope there will continue to be<br />
room for theatre as there has always been in this and<br />
other Parliaments. I, for one, would miss the Member for<br />
Kooyong's angry look terribly. Or the Member for New<br />
England's profound tactical observations.<br />
But I also think the time has come for the emphasis to be<br />
reweighed in favour of substance.<br />
Mr Speaker, these new arrangements will not diminish the<br />
Government's accountability in this place. In many ways,<br />
they will increase accountability across the breadth of<br />
the Government.<br />
To listen to the Honourable Member for Bennelong's<br />
statements about accountability, one could be forgiven<br />
for thinking that I was under constant interrogation in<br />
this place and that these reforms were designed to<br />
protect me from the Leader of the Opposition.<br />
Of course, Mr Speaker, this is nonsense and a quick<br />
perusal of the record of Question Time bears this out.<br />
For instance, last year more questions were asked of<br />
me by the Government than by the Opposition. </p>
<p>The Leader of the Opposition asked, on average, one<br />
question of me per sitting week. Under the new<br />
arrangements he may either increase or decrease this<br />
ratio as he and the Opposition Tactics Committee<br />
sees fit.<br />
For reasons best known, perhaps, to the Opposition,<br />
in 1993 only 87 questions were asked of me, compared<br />
with 276 in 1992.<br />
The fact is, Mr Speaker, the Opposition, any opposition,<br />
chooses its targets according to its perceived political<br />
interests and those on the other side really should not<br />
insult anyone's intelligence by pretending that they<br />
occupy some high moral ground.<br />
In Opposition in 1975 the then Member for Moreton was all<br />
for changing Question Time. It was " choking" the<br />
Parliament, he said.<br />
But did the Government of Malcolm Fraser unchoke it? No.<br />
Malcolm Fraser didn't change a thing.<br />
Malcolm Fraser believed that Members who genuinely wanted<br />
information, as opposed to publicity, should place their<br />
questions on notice for a written answer. </p>
<p>The contemporary record also shows that vast areas of<br />
Government responsibility go largely unscrutinised by the<br />
Opposition. More questions are asked of a broader range<br />
of Ministers by the Government than by the Opposition.<br />
In 1992, 70 per cent of all Opposition questions came<br />
from the Leader and Deputy Leader of the Opposition and<br />
the Leader of the National Party. 70 per cent of all<br />
questions in that year were asked of the Prime Minister<br />
and the Treasurer.<br />
Those who lay claim to being the traditionalists of<br />
Parliament must agree that all this provides a distorted<br />
version of ministerial accountability to the Parliament<br />
and in no way reflects the original intentions of those<br />
who framed the existing arrangements.<br />
Mr Speaker, the reforms we propose ensure that more<br />
ministers are questioned, and provide the opportunity for<br />
more policies to be tested and more detailed scrutiny<br />
given to Government departments and their administration.<br />
In short, the Government's reforms will aid a return to<br />
our genuine parliamentary traditions and help make<br />
Question Time a forum not merely for leaders, but for all<br />
ministers and all parliamentarians. These changes<br />
should, in fact, be supported by traditionalists. </p>
<p>It's entirely consistent with our Westminster<br />
parliamentary tradition, with its emphasis on collective<br />
responsibility, that we should encourage questioning, not<br />
only of the leading ministers, but of all ministers; and<br />
not only questions from the Opposition leaders and<br />
Government backbench, but from all backbenchers.<br />
Handling legislation<br />
I turn to the Procedure Committee's recommendations on<br />
the handling of legislation.<br />
The Government has already made significant changes to<br />
improve the flow of legislation, especially the move to<br />
three periods of sittings and our decision that,<br />
generally, legislation will be introduced in one sitting<br />
for passage in the next.<br />
Nonetheless, the Government has agreed to a trial of the<br />
Procedure Committee's recommendations and has decided<br />
that the machinery should be put in place to allow<br />
uncontroversial bills to be considered by a Main<br />
Committee or " second chamber".<br />
The Government has also agreed that there should be a<br />
Second Deputy Speaker and that he or she will be<br />
nominated by the opposition. </p>
<p>It will take some time for the necessary supporting<br />
arrangements to be put in place but I would hope to see<br />
some initial use of the Main Committee system during the<br />
current Autumn sittings.<br />
The Leader of the House will be giving notice of the<br />
necessary sessional orders and amendments. to the standing<br />
orders of the House this week. The Government intends<br />
that the new sitting times and Question Time arrangements<br />
will start on Monday 21 February.<br />
I believe these are very worthwhile improvements we are<br />
making. Again, let me express my appreciation to all<br />
honourable Members and others who have contributed to the<br />
development of these reforms and particularly to the<br />
honourable Member for Bonython.<br />
L </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
