<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5946</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/10/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005946.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
( 3 J? 1A<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA SUNDAY, 24 OCTOBER 1982<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
The legislation for a National Crimes Commission which was<br />
introduced into Parliament last week will establis-an<br />
effective agency designed specifically to comrbat organised crime<br />
and corruption in Australia. At the same time, the legislation<br />
provides a basis for effective co-operation with the states,<br />
and with police forces and other law enforcement agencies.<br />
It has become clear in recent years that organised crime, and<br />
criminal activities relating to drugs and other matters, have<br />
got beyond the reach of our traditional law enforcement methods<br />
and agencies. The Williams and Stewart Royal Commissions on<br />
Drugs and Drug Trafficking, a nuxnberof joint Comamonwealth-state<br />
police task force reports, and most recently the Costigan<br />
Royal Commission's Interim Report, all tell vastly disturbing<br />
stories about the spread and significance of organised crime<br />
in Australia. Mr Costigan's investigations into the Paintbrs<br />
and Dockers Union have highlighted that Australia is not immune<br />
from the kind of criminal activities which most of us would have<br />
associated perhaps with Chicago or other countries, but not<br />
Australia. Some quotations from the Costigan Report starkly illustrate<br />
the seriousness of the situation. Mr Costigan says, " I am<br />
satisfied that the Union, at least in Victoria, Newcastle,<br />
Queensland and South Australia if not in Sydney as well, is<br />
an organised criminal group following criminal pursuits. At<br />
least in Victoria those in charge of the Union recruit<br />
exclusively those who have serious criminal convictions."<br />
( Para. l0.02 of Mr Costigan's edited Chapter 10 of Vol. 2,.<br />
4th Interim Report.) Mr Costigan also says in relation to the kind<br />
of activity he has unearthed, " The type of criminal activity<br />
is of a substantial kind. It involves large scale and continuing<br />
fraud, or large and continuous importation of drugs at great<br />
cost, continuing illegal gambling schemes or other forms of<br />
widespread criminal activity." ( Para. 10.09)<br />
It is imperative to attack these problems urgently and<br />
effectively, to prevent any further entrenchment of this kind<br />
of crime in Australia, and do everything possible to eradicate it.<br />
That is why the Government is pressing ahead with legislation at<br />
this time. It is not good enough. to go on as we have been<br />
doing in spite of everything we know and in spite of all the talk </p>
<p>2-<br />
about the need to act. The Crimes Commission will co-operate<br />
with traditional law enforcement agencies. It will in no<br />
sense replace them and its activities will be essentially<br />
directed towards types of crime which those agencies have<br />
experienced special difficulties in investigating.<br />
I very much hope the states will keep an open. mind and adopt<br />
a co-operative stand in relation to the Commission. because<br />
the problems clearly straddle state boundaries, they affect<br />
both Commonwealth and state legal jurisdictions. The Crimes<br />
commission will be operating in the areas. of Commonwealth law, it<br />
in no way infringes on state sovereignty or state rights.<br />
But at the same time, if any or all of the states want to make<br />
use of the Commission, then the Commission will be<br />
empowered by our legislation to accept particular commissions<br />
from the states, and to accept jurisdiction for areas of state<br />
law which states may wish to confer on the Commission. This is<br />
entirely up to the states to determine, but the way is open,<br />
and there is every reason why the Commonwealth/ state co-operation<br />
which has existed with Royal Commissions, joint task forces,<br />
and the Australian Bureau of Criminal Intelligence, should run<br />
into the new Crimes Commission.<br />
The Crimes Commission will be far more appropriate than Royal<br />
Commissions to deal with organised crime. Mr Costigan<br />
has emphasised the hrr) ortance of a prosecuting arm to attend<br />
to prosecutions immediately they arise during investigations<br />
such as his. The Crimes Commission, while able to gjive<br />
information to the police, will also have its own responsibility<br />
to develop cases for prosecution. In serious and complex<br />
cases especially, it is intended that the Commission will work<br />
hand in hand with the legal counsel who will prosecute if a<br />
case for prosecution is found.<br />
To make sure the-Commission can deal with whatever forms of<br />
organised crime it uncovers, the Commission will have a broad<br />
charter, giving it scope to look into complaints or follow up its,<br />
own investigations, and it will have the powers needed to come<br />
to grips with organised crime. The legislation has been framed<br />
in a way that will make the Commission effective, while also<br />
meeting the legitimate-concerns which have been expressed<br />
about the idea of a National Crimes Commission.<br />
I am confident that the Crimes Commission will make a major<br />
contribution in dealing with organised cr-ime. It is a vital<br />
Government initiative and I am confident it will receive the<br />
widespread support it deserves. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
