<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1727</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: PM. NO. 126/1967 - SENATE ELECTION - EVE OF POLL MESSAGE FROM THE PRIME MINISTER, MR HAROLD HOLT</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/11/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001727.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS: I4DMC " g FM. No. 126/ 1967<br />
VSENATE ELECTION<br />
Eve of Poll Message from the Prime Minister, Mr Harold Holt<br />
When you vote for a government or a party, you expect<br />
to know where it stands on the big issues affecting the nation's security and<br />
well-being. I have stated all through this campaign that the great issue<br />
of the 1966 House of Representatives election whether we should desert our<br />
allies in time of conflict is still the critical question we all have to answer.<br />
You know where I stand on this matter. You know<br />
where the Government stands. W.! here do the Labor Party and its leaders<br />
stand? We know where some leading Labor members stand.<br />
They say their present policy is, in essence, the same as at the last general<br />
election. We cannot say for certain where the Leader, Mr WhItlam stands.<br />
He has conducted so evasive an action since this campaign began that he<br />
must have misled even himself.<br />
So we are forced back to the policy itself the<br />
policy laid down by the ALP Federal Conference binding under the rules of<br />
the ALP on all Labor members, including Mr Whitlam.<br />
At the Adelaide Conference in August, the ALP declared<br />
itself to be opposed to the continuance of the war in Viet Nam and to<br />
Australian participation in it. It laid down conditions which, if not accepted<br />
by our American allies, would lead to withdrawal by a Labor-led Australian<br />
Government of our armed forces. Writing in " Fact", the official Labor<br />
newspaper, shortly after this conference, Mr Calwell s; id<br />
" In its present mood, the United States will not accept any<br />
one of the conditions a Labor Government would lay down, and<br />
it would rather pull out altogether and if it does this it will<br />
abandon its entire Asian communist containment policy and<br />
most of its Pacific Ocean bases, including Okinawa and Taiwan.<br />
It will resume its policy of isolation.<br />
Does Mir WAhitlam accept or reject Mr Calwell's<br />
assessment of the United ' 7tates' reaction to Labor's conditions? Does he<br />
persist in believing that these conditions would promote an alliance with<br />
America, which he now claims 1tfs party recognises to be of such crucial<br />
Importance to Australia? Instead of saying In simple terms what Labor's policy<br />
is, the Leader of the Opposition has tried to make it impossible for the<br />
electors to understand Labor policy. This kind of political smokescreen<br />
is not good enough when the security of the nation Is Involved. It Is not good<br />
enough to hide behind the word " peace" if what you mean by peace is retreat,<br />
stagnation or surrender. */ 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
I ask the Australian electorate to support us at the<br />
polls not only for reasons of high national policy but for the good and<br />
practical reasons that we cannot have an efficient administration unless<br />
the Government, with a clear-cut mandate of two years to run, has a<br />
majority voice in both Houses of Parliament.<br />
Far-reaching and historic decisons we have taken<br />
even in the heat of this campaign offer you the most potent cause for<br />
ensuring that the business of government is not impeded by hostile<br />
Senate groupings in the critical months ahead.<br />
When in due course the country is called upon to<br />
make its choice of a government, you will be able to decide then whether<br />
the Labor Party should be given an opportunity to demonstrate its capacity<br />
or incapacity to govern. Meanwhile, there are formidable tasks in front of us,<br />
your present government. A. clear vote for the Government in this Senate<br />
election will allow us to get on with the job.<br />
CANBERRA, 24 November, 1967. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
