<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>21326</transcript-id>
    <title>Joint Press Conference with Senator Andrew Bartlett Prime Minister&#039;s Courtyard, Parliament House </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/06/2004</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well ladies and gentlemen, I've called this news conference to announce that the Government and the Australian Democrats have reached agreement which will secure the passage of the Choice of Superannuation Fund bills through the Senate and I'm very pleased to welcome to this news conference, not only of course my colleague, the Minister, Senator Coonan but also Senator Andrew Bartlett, the leader of the Australian Democrats and Senator John Cherry, the Democrats spokesman on superannuation matters.</p>
<p>I think superannuation choice was first offered as a policy by the Coalition as far back as 1993. It was certainly part of our 1996 election policy and I'm delighted that after eight and a half years in Government we have with the support of the Australian Democrats, which I acknowledge and I thank them for were able to secure passage of this legislation.</p>
<p> It adds an important dimension of choice. It will over time I believe and it will come into operation on the 1st of July 2005. It will over time lead to people taking a more active interest in their own superannuation. It is a proper expression of individual choice that people should have the right to decide if they want to, they're not going to be forced to in relation to existing employees to have their superannuation in a fund, other than the award fund or the fund that has been into up until now. When it's allied with the co-contribution changes, that once again with the assistance of the Democrats we're able to get through the parliament, plus the enhancements of co-contributions in the Budget, in addition, the announcements made by the Treasurer earlier this year in relation to changes to retirement incomes arrangements and also, of course, the fees and charges protocols that were released by the Parliamentary Secretary to the Treasurer, Mr Cameron, last week, we see assembled a piece of very important architecture for the retirement income system of the future. I do want to acknowledge the fact that the changes that the Government decided upon in part as a result of views put to us by the Australian Democrats in relation to financial interdependency were obviously a factor in the ultimate passage of this legislation. But overall, it's a very good outcome. Freedom of choice is something that the Government is fundamentally committed to. We need people actively interested in the detail of their retirement income arrangements and in those circumstances, I think this is a first class decision and I do thank the Australian Democrats and I very warmly thank Helen Coonan for all the work that she has put into it. If the leader of the Democrats wishes to say anything, Andrew.</p>
<p>SENATOR BARTLETT:</p>
<p>Thank you very much. This agreement is a significant win for every Australian worker. Particularly, those workers who are interested in where their money is invested. They now have the opportunity to choose to invest it in funds that focus on ethical investment. They have the opportunity to have a choice where they put their funds as opposed to that choice being made by the employer. So it is a big win for workers. We have also achieved significant improvements in the disclosure of fees. We are pleased that the superannuation discrimination against same sex couples has been addressed. That has been a major sticking point for the Democrats. It's one that many Democrat Senators have raised over the years. I have raised personally with the Prime Minister last year and we're pleased that that has been addressed. There is still work to be done. There is still discrimination to be addressed for same sex couples but this removes a significant problem. There will be need for further improvements down the track but we believe that we should not hold up what is a significant win for Australian workers simply because those further improvements can be developed. We think we should ensure that this system is put in place. It is, I believe, a perfect example of why the Democrats' approach of negotiating with the Government of the day, even where we have areas of strong disagreement delivers results for the Australian people. So we continue to have strong disagreements with this Government on a range of other issues of course, but we do not let those disagreements stand in the way of the opportunity to get gains for the Australian people and there are millions of Australian workers who will have better opportunity to choose where their superannuation goes with consumer protection, with removal of discrimination for same sex couples and others in interdependent relationships and with the opportunity for building on further gains in the future. As the Prime Minister mentioned, we've already had the benefits put through the Senate with the extra work of the Democrats of hundreds of millions dollars extra going towards low income earners in incentives for superannuation. Those types of agreements and this agreement that we've announced today provide a foundation for further gains in the future. It's what I believe is what the Senate is for - looking for opportunities to achieve wins for the Australian people whilst continuing the pressure on the Government on areas for further improvement.</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do you think this decision will substantially increase Australia's (inaudible)...?</p>
<p>SENATOR BARTLETT:</p>
<p>I don't think there's any doubt it will assist in not only boosting retirement savings, it will assist in the better performance of superannuation funds. There'll be better competitive pressure, there'll be greater disclosure of fees and people will be, they'll be amongst other things in this agreement and the details will be made available to you, consumer education fund, an advisory group which will be put together to provide assistance for consumers in where best to choose put their money.  So it will ensure greater performance across the industry and I think it will address an area where there is still significant need for improvement.  Further investment in superannuation addressing the problem with excessive private debt in Australia, there's still more than needs to be done, we don't pretend otherwise, but it's a good foundation for further improvements.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, just on one other issue, the Hicks case...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>One other issue?</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>One other issue. The Hicks case, Major Mori, the US military lawyer, and Mr Kenny have been condemned for releasing publicly allegations of mistreatment regarding Hicks. Do you believe with the US defence authorities that they should have gone to them first rather than actually go...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look I'm not going to get into something which is essentially a matter between the US authorities and the defence counsel.  Our concern is to ensure that the protocols applying to the military commission hearing are appropriate and we are satisfied that they are and I don't want to get into that other issue.  Anything else?</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>... Herald poll today, what's your response to the fact that the primary vote is above, the Liberal Party is above Labor for the first time since...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well it's a better poll than the last Nielsen poll.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Why do you think it is?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well because it is, the numbers for us are higher...</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>I mean why do you think it's happened?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>... gone up four, they've gone down one. I've always liked polls that are like that.  But I like them and as one of my distinguished predecessors once said famously there's only one poll that counts.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, why is it necessary to have the House vote on the FTA legislation this week, why can't it wait until August?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well because the issues involved in the FTA are well and truly known, we have a treaties committee process. This issue has been debated now for ages and ages and there was in our view no need for an additional Senate inquiry, I mean this is very much a case of having a dog and barking, we have a joint treaties committee for the very purpose of looking at things like the Free Trade Agreement. But on top of that for purely political reasons others, particularly the Australian Labor Party let me say, wanted to have a Senate inquiry and I think it's time people said where they stand on this, the Premiers know where they stand and from what I've been told they're very hot and strong in favour of the Free Trade Agreement, in fact they've all told me they are.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>... vote this week as well?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look I never presume to tell the Senate what it should do Michelle.  We will be presenting the legislation, I never lose my respect for the two chambers of our Parliament.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>So you'll present it to the Senate this week?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>What we will do Michelle is we will present the legislation and we'll see what the Parliament, which controls the executive in our system of government, decides in its wisdom it will do.</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
<p>[ends]  </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
