<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6328</transcript-id>
    <title>LETTER TO THE CHIEF MINISTER OF THE NORTHERN TERRITORY</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/02/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Correspondence</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006328.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
// F4( o<br />
' 144= WALZ<br />
FOR MEDIA 29 February 1984<br />
The Prime Minister today sent the following letter to the<br />
Chief Minister of the Northern Territory. </p>
<p>PRIME MINIS rER<br />
CANBERRA.<br />
The Hon. Paul Everingham, MLA<br />
Chic[ Minister of the Northern Territory<br />
PO Box 3146<br />
DARWIN NT 5794<br />
My dear Chief Minister<br />
I refer to your letter of 15 December 1.983 which was a<br />
response to my letter of 17 November 1983 expressing<br />
concern about aspects of the Northern Territory<br />
Criminal Code.<br />
Our exchange of correspondence has been considered by<br />
the Commonwealth Government. I note that your Government<br />
intends to keep a careful watch on operation of the Code<br />
and that it will consider amendments after twelve months<br />
of its coming into effect. With regard to a number of the<br />
matters raised-in my letter I look forward to continuing<br />
discussions and consideration of the issues in your<br />
subsequent review.<br />
Tnere are, however, four provisions which are of such<br />
concern as, in our view, to warrant immediate action.<br />
The amendments which we most strongly propose are:<br />
Ci) An amendment to section 7 to preserve the<br />
traditional onus of proof in relation to criminal<br />
intent 15y requiring the prosecution to prove<br />
that intent even though the accused was<br />
intoxicated;<br />
( ii) Amendments to section 383 to replace the term<br />
" fine" by a more appropriate term and to delete<br />
the sub-section which allows imprisonment or<br />
release on bail after acquittal;<br />
( iii) An amendment to sectio. 51 to permit an organisatiOn<br />
to show cause before a judicial authority as to why<br />
it should not be proscribed or to permit judicial<br />
review of any proscription; and<br />
( iv) An amendment to section 360 conferring a discretion<br />
on the Courts to permit the making of an unsworn<br />
dock statement in cases where, due to the cultural<br />
background of the accused resul1. tinq in communi cat inons<br />
difficulites which cannot be resolved by the u! F; c<br />
of interpreters, it would not be in the intore ; ts<br />
of justice to expose him L-o rross examination. 12 </p>
<p>T'aking the prcuvisioCnf Sconcernling LntoxicaI ionl and ( 1)<br />
above) we nave noted your arguments th i. the very high<br />
level of alcohol related crime in the Territory needs to<br />
oe attacked strongly. Nevertheless the_-provisions of the<br />
Code represent very great departures, f rom accepted crimi nal<br />
Law standard, 0S. They raise questions in relation to<br />
Australia's international obligations and muay operate<br />
particularly harshly against Aboriginal people. The need<br />
for the radical departure represented by section 7 would<br />
seem to be obviated by inclusion of section 154 of the Code.<br />
While we understand the basic purpose behind section 383, th. a<br />
notions of a fine and possible imprisonment after acquittal<br />
are alien to our legal heritage and may be seen as inconsistent<br />
with our international obliLgations.<br />
The matter of allowing judicial examination of decisions<br />
to proscribe organisations would seem to be a basic issue<br />
of civil and political rights. Grave consequences may flow<br />
to individuals resulting from operation of the provision<br />
in the Code and the provisions of the Commonwealth Crimes<br />
Act 1914 show that it is not unprecedented for these<br />
matters to be subject to judicial consideration.<br />
our proposed amendment in regard to unsworn dock statements<br />
would seem to be a more appropriate approach to this problem.<br />
It will better allow people of traditional Aboriginal<br />
cultural background to put their case, where it is judged<br />
to be necessary by the Court, while avoiding some of the<br />
problems with unsworn dock statements you have mentioned<br />
in your letter.<br />
Such is the concern held by the Commonwealth Government<br />
about these provisions on the grounds of their departure<br />
from legal standards, implications for our international<br />
obligations and likely harsh effects on Aboriginals that we<br />
are considering advising the Governor-General to recommend<br />
the above amendments to the Administrator pursuant to<br />
-sub-section of the Northern Territory ( Self-Government)<br />
Act 1978<br />
In view of this I should be grateful to recelive a response<br />
to tnis letter within seven day:;.<br />
Yours sincerely<br />
R L_ 1-Jawke </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
