<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1333</transcript-id>
    <title>SEATO COUNCIL MEEING, CANBERRA, ACT - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER MR HAROLD HOLT - 27TH JUNE 1966</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/06/1966</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001333_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SEATO COUNCIL MEETING<br />
CANBERRA, A. or. T.<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister Mr. Harold Holt.<br />
27th JUNE, 1966.<br />
Mr. Prime Minister, Your Excellencies, Ladies and Gentlemen:<br />
It is an honour foi me to be asked to open the 1966 SEATO<br />
Conference. I extend a wañ ii welcome to you all on behalf of the Australian<br />
Government and puople. This welcome embraces not only the distinguished<br />
Foreign Ministers and delegations of countries with which we enjoy close and<br />
constructive relations both in SEATO and outside of it, but also the<br />
distinguished Secretary -General, General Vargas, and staff of the Organization.<br />
Australia has become more conscious in recent times that,<br />
through geography, trade and circumstance, we are increasingly part of the<br />
Asian scene. Australia has good cause to value the existence of SEATO. It<br />
has been a solid pillar of security for us. We have faithfully honoured our<br />
own commitments to our colleagues of the Organization, and we are<br />
grateful for the support given to SEATO's purposes by those members of the<br />
Organization who have made much more massive contributions than our own.<br />
There has been a good deal of debate and talk about a domino<br />
theory in Asia. This theory propounds the view that if one country of<br />
Southi-East Asia succumbs to Communist aggression, the others will topple<br />
in turn. We can claim, from its achikevements, that SEATO has<br />
successfully applied the domi-o theory in reverse. It has brought us an<br />
assurance of combined support. We, and others of the-area, have lived<br />
much more securely because of its existence. have been able to plan<br />
more confidently for an expanding future. have done so encouraged by<br />
the fact that SEATO provides a shield of protection and a means of<br />
constructive collaboration. The Asian countries of SEATO have been able to build their<br />
defences and to strengthen their economies. The year under review provides<br />
further heartening proof to that supplied in other recent years that those<br />
countries of Asia under Communist threat can, with outside help<br />
supple m enting their own efforts, meet that challe:. nge and proceed to<br />
prosperous economic growth. We can point to countries of the region, some<br />
of them members of this Organization, which have recorded notable gains<br />
of economic and social progress and are now advancing to new levels of<br />
achieveme-int in an environment of stability. To those of us who live in the<br />
area there is inspiration in the visible evidences of improvemnent and<br />
progress. Some countries that I have visited recently seem transformed<br />
against my recollections of them in earlier years.<br />
What is also heartening has been the emergence of positive<br />
and constructive attitudes to international instrumentalities for economic<br />
co-operation. Although national sovereignty has been attained by some only<br />
within the last 20 years, they display a commendable readiness to work with<br />
others and create the institutions for co -operation. The newly constituted<br />
Asian and Pacific Council and the Asian Development Bank are welcome<br />
examples. We have welcomed also the generous undertaking by the President<br />
of the United States to make a billion dollar contribution towards economic<br />
development in South-East Asia. Developments such as these inspire a<br />
spirit of hope more widely felt throughout the whole region. Even in the<br />
heat of military contest in South Vietnam, there are practical programmes<br />
being evolved for better times ahead. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
Wie are all conscious of a fermcent of change in the fPsia of today.<br />
The-restlessnoss and the turbulence give rise to the mnore dramatic episodes<br />
which arc, widely publicised. But these, arc only aspects of dynamic forces, some<br />
of them much more favourable in their influence, shaping movements in human<br />
affairs which in turn can affect the whole world.<br />
SEATO has i-Ls critics and, of course!, it has its imperfections.<br />
But the fact is that since its formation, it has held Communism at bay. From<br />
South Vietnam, one of the: SEATO protocol states, where the thrust of<br />
aggression has been fiercest, we are now receiving much mcre hopeful reports.<br />
But while we have strengthened the foundations of our security, the need for<br />
SEATO remains as strong as ever. No region today contains greater dangers<br />
for world peace and security than Asia. South-East Asia has been singled out<br />
by the-Communists as a critical area of challenge. They bclieve that if their<br />
technique of so-called wars of national liberatio n can succeed in South Vietnam,<br />
it can be employed with similar success in many other countries.<br />
Why did the SEATO Treaty come into existence? It was designed<br />
to enable its member countries to combine together to counter the Commnunist<br />
threat in Asia. It was built on the reality that, left to themselves the countries<br />
of the area would fall to Communist pressures. It recognises that these pressures<br />
can take many formis. They vary in intensity, and they require a variety of<br />
responses. Thanks to SEATO the Governments of member countries can<br />
expect assistance, not only when declared conventional military attack occurs<br />
across their frontiers, but also they can look for assistance when their<br />
authority and administration are under assault from those familiar Communist<br />
instruriients subversion and guerrilla warfare.<br />
Communist aggression in South-East Asia follows what has become<br />
a clear pattern. It usually begins covertly. There is long underground<br />
preparation. This includes political i* ndoc tri nation, the training of cadres and the<br />
build up of secret sources of supply. The initial threats are indirect. They<br />
are concealed and they mature slowly.<br />
The response made by the SEATO allies must therefore, be<br />
carefully devised. There must be armed strength, of course, but we cannot<br />
win an enduring victory by military means alone. There is the battle to be<br />
won for the people's support, and to win this there must be political, social,<br />
administrative and economic measures acceptable to them.<br />
On my recent visit to South-East Asia, it was of special interest<br />
to me to discover how earnestly the positive constructive tasks directed to a better<br />
way of life in the community were being promoted. Whether in South Vietnam,<br />
Malaysia or Thailand, I found that the Government concerned had turneld it3<br />
attention to this need for a positive, constructive programme of civic action and<br />
rural development. It is to be found to a growing extent among the programmes<br />
of the military forces of all the countries concerned. Our own Australian forces,<br />
wherever situated give a high priority to their activities in this field. No doubt<br />
we have a long way to go, but the processes are under way.<br />
A notable feature of SEATO is that each member country retains<br />
its freedom of action about how best it can make a contribution. This<br />
flexibility is important because the problems that we face are neither simple nor<br />
clear cut. SEATO has shown itself capable of adapting itself speedily and<br />
effectively to handling the different phases of tactics and timing of the Communist<br />
challenge in Asia. We know, for example, that faced with military reverses, the<br />
Communists are likely to step up their well known tactics of subversion,<br />
infiltration, terrorismi and sabotage. </p>
<p>-3-<br />
SEATO, of course does not stand alone as the sole<br />
instrument for security in Asia and the Pacific region. Several members of<br />
SEATO belong to other arrangements which help to fortify the SEATO<br />
structure and the fabric of security in the region. These arrangements are,<br />
for the most part, formally established and contribute greatly to the<br />
common defence in the region of Asia and the Pacific. The countries of<br />
the free world associated in SEATO have shown their capacity to defend<br />
national sovereignty and integrity.<br />
Successive Communist challenges in . Isia have failed.<br />
They have been met by the militaryT strength of the Government under attack.<br />
It has been supported by the mrilitary forces, logistical backing and economic<br />
strength of its partners, and of other friendly forces also.<br />
The major challenge of Communism in Asia today is directed<br />
to South Vietnam, as I have said . But it has met growing and determined<br />
strength of resistance. SEATO is not merely an instrument for military security.<br />
Its purposes include the advancement of all in the regions it serves-, It is<br />
well constituted to help by practical assistance and friendly guidance.<br />
SEATO has enabled us to exercise strength through combination. This is<br />
of great importance to the smaller powers which are helped in this way to<br />
devote more of their resources to economic growth. Australia in common<br />
with some other members of the Organization, has made your problems of<br />
development as well as those of defence. Left to ourselves, we would be<br />
overburdened and crippled with security costs. The existence of SEATO and<br />
other security arrangements ensures that members who are most directly<br />
threatened and who are the least able to afford large military establishments<br />
will neither perish nor impoverish themselves.<br />
The wisdom, ability and experience assembled here should<br />
enable this conference to advance most usefully the purposes of the<br />
Organization. The ultimate answer to Communism must be found in the minds<br />
of the people. They must feel convinced that life has meaning, promise and<br />
better standards for them. We who oppose Communism must be more than<br />
anti-Communist. We must demonstrate the false attractions of Communist<br />
ideology and expose its techniques of human manipulation. But we must<br />
stand together for the satisfaction of decent human aspirations and the<br />
precious enjoyment of individual liberty.<br />
Your SEATO labours of today will do much to shape the Asia<br />
of tomorrow. I wish you fruitful and successful meetings.<br />
I formally declare the conference open. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
