<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>16798</transcript-id>
    <title>Remarks at &#039;Just Think&#039; launch, Melbourne Cricket Ground   </title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/09/2009</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E &amp; O E  -  PROOF ONLY</p>
<p>PM: Thanks very much to Matt Finnis, CEO of the AFL players Association. Kate Ellis the Minister for Sport, Sam Mitchell the Captain of Hawthorn, Jason McCartney, Johno Chase from Step Back Think, Daniel Jackson from Richmond- and friends one and all of the AFL, for what is an important cause for the country, which is how do we deal with this problem on our streets, because it affects too many people we know and love.</p>
<p>One in five Australians are under 25, and make a huge contribution to Australia, our economy, our culture, our sport and our nation. Growing up has always had its challenges. It's a time when young people are asked to take on more responsibility for themselves, for their relationships, for their communities, for their families, and to make choices that will be important in what they do with the rest of their lives.</p>
<p>Growing up today has some new challenges as well- in fact, some unprecedented challenges. Our society is undergoing major changes, as family structures change, and family networks weaken. Young Australians today are the first generation likely to spend more time with friends than with their family. Employers are demanding more adaptable skills than ever before. And at the same time, young people tell us that a lack of transport and youth-friendly public spaces are leaving them even more isolated.</p>
<p>These are some of the challenges out there, and we need to be frank in the way in which we deal with them. As a nation we need to do better in supporting young people negotiate these challenges, and to support them to grow up safe, healthy and with the skills, confidence and resilience, resilience to participate fully in every part of our national life. One in four young Australians aged between 16 and 24 has a mental health disorder, yet three quarters of them do not receive professional help.</p>
<p>Negative perceptions of body image, particularly for young women, are of growing concern.</p>
<p>Young people who have grown up during a period of unprecedented prosperity are now feeling the effects of the global economic recession.  Youth unemployment is now sitting at 12 per cent, compared with 9 per cent before the downturn. New communications technologies create enormous opportunities for young people to access information, develop friendships and communicate with others around the world but they can also lead to young people being the victims of crime, or becoming the targets of cyber-bullying.</p>
<p>And a lack of physical exercise is a concern too, a decline in some respects of community participation in sport. Obesity is on the rise.  The most recent figures suggest that 28 per cent of young men and 20 per cent of young women are overweight or obese. </p>
<p>We also have potential long-term health risks from the culture of binge drinking that affects so many Australians, particularly our young people. About one in five men and one in six women aged between 18 and 24 drink alcohol to dangerous levels at least once a week, it's due to reflect on that again, about one in five men and one in six women aged between 18 and 24 drink alcohol to dangerous levels at least once a week.</p>
<p>Australians have so far been spared the horror of the tragic school gun massacres that have occurred in the United States. We do not have the culture of knife crime that has developed in the United Kingdom in recent years. But we were all shocked by the death of Jai Morcom in a schoolyard fight last week.</p>
<p>And we have unacceptably high levels of alcohol-related violence outside our pubs and clubs. That's why the Government is developing a national strategy for young Australians, with young Australians and in large part to be delivered by young Australians. And also, as part of our national health reform agenda for the future. We'll be working our way through this in the time ahead, it will embrace seven core priorities.</p>
<p>One- empowering young Australians in their schools, their TAFEs and their Universities to shape their own futures. Two- supporting young Australians within their families. Three-  mobilising young Australians within their communities. Four- enabling young Australians to participate safely and confidently online. Five- equipping young Australians with the skills and personal networks they need for employment. Six- strengthening early intervention with young Australians to help prevent any problems getting worse and to help young people get their lives back on track. And finally, establishing clear cut legal consequences for behaviours that endanger the safety of others.</p>
<p>Our aim is to build the healthiest Australia possible.  Our actions for young Australians will form part of the national health reform agenda that the government is currently developing in response to the National Health and Hospitals Reform Commission that we received in July. Today's announcements are an important step in young people, community leaders and Government pulling together to make a difference in young people's lives. This Just Think campaign brings the community leadership of the AFL Player's Association and the AFL captains to engage the whole community in talking about city violence and to encourage those who are out enjoying a drink, including young people, to take responsibility for their actions.</p>
<p>I have had the opportunity to talk to young people who have been affected by alcohol related violence and the consequences can be devastating. A group of young people in Melbourne called Step Back, Think and Jono Chase is here with us today together with others, they got together to combat alcohol related violence after their friend James Macready-Bryan was bashed almost three years ago, on the night of his 20th birthday, leaving him brain-damaged and wheelchair-bound.</p>
<p>One of their aims was for the AFL to take the lead on combating violence  -  and I'm sure that they will be delighted about the launch of this campaign today. Another remarkable person that has campaigned on anti-violence is Jonty Bush, the 2009 Young Australian of the Year. After losing her younger sister and her dad, Jonty went on to become the Chief Executive of the Queensland Homicide Victims Support Group at age 27 and developed the One Punch Can Kill campaign.</p>
<p>These young people, Step Back, Think and One Punch Can Kill and others are not willing to sit on their hands while accidents like this occur, incidents like this occur, acts of violence like this occur around the country, neither should the rest of the community be indifferent as well. I am delighted to announce that the Australian Government will be contributing $132,000 to the AFL as part of the $2 million Club Champions Program  -  which utilises the power of sport to tackle irresponsible drinking in our community.</p>
<p>And the “Just Think” campaign, led by the AFL Player's Association, is the type of initiative of which this Government is proud. Can I also say it's fantastic that you as professional footballers are getting behind this. So many young people look up to you, you know that. Therefore establishing an Australian view that it's fine to go out and have fun, it's great to go out and have a party with your friends, it's fine to go out and have a drink, so long as you know where to draw the line, and so long as you know what the consequences are when you don't draw the line and that's what this campaign, Just Think, is all about.</p>
<p>If I could say something else positive about what the AFL players association are doing, I've been introduced to their work with youth homelessness. I've spoken quite recently with the Melbourne City Mission and about the work they are doing about the city and the State for homelessness. I think it's fantastic that the players through their association have got together to build a homelessness refuge for young people. I think that it shows a whole lot of positive contribution and it shows Australia at its best.</p>
<p>So again, young people are looking up to professional players and they see good stuff being done, good stuff for youth homelessness, good stuff when it comes to responsible drinking. This is the sort of stuff which the Australian government is so proud to get behind and I commend you for your efforts.</p>
<p>By the way, as a Lions man, I look forward to the finals series kicking off this weekend with a home final in Brissie and the inevitability of a Brisbane win. The Just Think campaign is a fantastic way to launch this final series. Footy is so loved by so many Australians. It's great that footy will be a vehicle through which we promote this attitude of responsible drinking for the future. Congratulations to all of you for being in this with your heart and your soul and your mind and your chequebook.</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
