<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>721</transcript-id>
    <title>CENSURE MOTION - STATEMENT IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES BY THE RT. HON. THE PRIME MINISTER SIR ROBERT MENZIES , ON THURSDAY 18TH APRIL 1963</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/04/1963</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000721_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
63/ 035<br />
CENSURE MOTION<br />
Statement in the House of Representatives by<br />
the Rt. Hon. the Prime Minister Sir Robert<br />
Menzies, on Thursday, 18th April, 1963.<br />
I must say Mr. Speaker, that I listened, as I always<br />
do, with great interest to the words of my old friend the<br />
honourable member for Bonython ( Mr. Makin), who became, I<br />
thought at one moment quite impassioned on this subject.<br />
I do want to point out to him with all friendliness that he<br />
fell into a few errors. He made a demand for parliamentary<br />
control in this matter. Everything that has been done and<br />
which is now the subject of attack has been done under<br />
statute of this Parliament and through an instrumentality<br />
set up under a statute passed by this Parliament.<br />
I would have suggested to my honourable friend that<br />
he be a little cautious about invoking the authority of<br />
Parliament when, in the case of his own party authority has<br />
been handed over to the 36 men. Honourable members opposite<br />
may moan and may groan, but the Leader of the Opposition<br />
( Mr. Calwell) would not be allowed to move a censure motion<br />
here today unless it came within the authority of the 36.<br />
Just remember that fact. Then the honourable gentleman<br />
attacked the Act of Parliament. This is a censure motion,<br />
and presumably, like its happy predecessor last week or the<br />
week before, is designed to defeat the Government and produce<br />
an election. It is wonderful to realise how passionately<br />
fond the Labour Party has suddenly become of an election<br />
fought on the television law. Already two elections have<br />
gone by since the law was passed, and I do not recall the<br />
Labour Party making a point of it at either. Of course, the<br />
reason why it did not make a point of it in either election<br />
was that it was convenient on those occasions to play for the<br />
support of some, at least, of the commercial television<br />
stations. Well Sir, that prudence has now been abandoned.<br />
The Labour Party with authority, I trust, from its outside<br />
36 has nailed its colours to the mast. In this debate it<br />
has said ", Je are for nationalization of television. If we<br />
come into office we will take the earliest possible steps to<br />
wipe out the existing commercial television licences and put<br />
the whole thing into the hands of the Government." No longer<br />
is there any mystery about that policy. I hope it will be well<br />
remembered when the time comes. In due course some time off<br />
yet we will be having an election.,<br />
Then, my honourable friend got rather heated, I thought<br />
if I could apply such a word to so mild a man about a licence<br />
being given to a wealthy group. I hope he will forgive me if,<br />
looking at this report, I point out and I am reading the<br />
names of applicants that I never heard of until we got the<br />
report that Community Television Limited it was a splendid<br />
arrangement is comprised of 1,000,000 shareholders of<br />
shares held by returned servicemen and returned servicemen's<br />
clubs; members and affiliated branches of the Australian<br />
Labour Party ( Victorian Branch); and then, to my joy and<br />
surprise, members and affiliated branches of the Liberal and<br />
Country Party. I did not know they had this money. Then<br />
esooosoooo/ 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
the next class is Electronic Industries Limited they are in<br />
for 1,000,000 shares and Electronic Industries Limited and<br />
holders of ordinary shares in Electronic Industries Limited.<br />
They are practically the same people, and they are in for<br />
1,000,000, Then consider the directorate. This is a povertystricken<br />
affair. My friend talks about the Government giving<br />
a licence to a wealthy group. Bless my soul, 1,000,000 shares<br />
out of 5,000,000, so far as I can judge from this document,<br />
are in the hands of the Warners. I thought from what I heard<br />
from the Leader of the Opposition that the Warners were<br />
anathema. They are rather comfortable people when the Labour<br />
Party and my party and somebody else wants to get a licence.<br />
This is not a bankrupt show, I venture to say on the face of<br />
it. Then my honourable friend says, " Is not this dreadful<br />
that a licence is to go to a wealthy group?" I venture to say<br />
that none of us in this House would want to sit down and concoct<br />
an application for a licence, and find ourselves called upon,<br />
by the inevitable logic of circumstances to find œ 1 000,000<br />
or œ 2,000,000 and to have to carry a loss of œ 500,00 or<br />
perhaps œ 250,600, before we got into the profit bracket.<br />
I would become so excited at that prospect that I would become<br />
unfit for further work.<br />
Because our time is limited I want to point out a few<br />
distinctions that have been overlooked by honourable members<br />
opposite. I do not mind them moving a want of confidence<br />
motion about television policy, but they have directed very<br />
little attention to that. They have concentrated their venom<br />
on the recent applications and the recent decisions. I just<br />
want to say this: It is one thing for any governmont to<br />
establish a royal commission which is designed to make<br />
recommendations on policy. W! e have had those. We had a<br />
celebrated royal commission on banking of which the late Mr.<br />
Chifloy was a member. That commission mado a valuable report.<br />
It was not binding on any government on either side. As a<br />
matter of fact, it was a long time before any one of the<br />
recommendations was taken up and put into effect. A royal<br />
commission which is designed to produce policy recommendations<br />
does not exempt the government of the day from accepting its<br />
own responsibility on policy. That goes for a Labour Government,<br />
I am sure, as much as it goes for mine.<br />
But where you have as in this case, an Act of Parliament<br />
which provides for the setting up of a broadcasting control<br />
board, for the calling of applications for a licence and the<br />
reference of applications to that statutory board and then<br />
requires that statutory board to make a report and recommendations,<br />
it is an entirely different matter. This is not a<br />
broad question of policy. I think honourable members forget<br />
that. Lot me talk about Victoria in this instance. The<br />
Government called applications for a licence. About seven or<br />
eight I have forgotten the exact number of applications<br />
were received. The applicants formed companies and established<br />
boards of directors. They spent thousands and thousands of<br />
pounds in completing their financial arrangements and schemes,<br />
engaging solicitors and counsel and in producing evidence. I<br />
suppose that in the case of the Victorian applications and<br />
it goes for everywhere there must have been sores of thousands<br />
of pounds, and many wooks, expended in the making, pursuit, and<br />
the hearing and criticism of the various individual applications.<br />
a a e 9 a / 3 </p>
<p>It would be a very strange thing for a government to say,<br />
when all that is over, " Sorry; you have wasted your tjme and<br />
your money; we propose to pay no attention to the report<br />
of the boardo" I give it to my honourable friend that if he had his<br />
way there would not be a board and there would not be<br />
commerciallicences I understand that but let him accept<br />
the proposition and let everybody accept the proposition<br />
that there is a law, that there are commercial licences that<br />
there is a board, that there are investigations and thaI<br />
there are reports all made under the law of this land. In<br />
these circumstances, a government, I venture to say, having<br />
received a report would need to have overwhelming reasons<br />
before it rejected the recommendation. I am putting this<br />
as a cold, hard matter of fact; it would need to have<br />
overwhelming reasons because, if it did not and it said,<br />
" We do not like this recommendation", what does it do then?<br />
Does it say, " He is out; we do not care for this; send<br />
it back for another enquiry; let everybody cone along once<br />
more and we will have another investigation, or perhaps open<br />
it up for other people," This is not real life, Would the<br />
Opposition I invite them to consider this very carefully,<br />
and I invite the people to consider it if it did not like<br />
the nomination, say, " Right; that is finished; we will now<br />
pick our own." I wonder.<br />
I repeat that apart from two casual observations that<br />
were made to me a week or two before this report became<br />
available, I did not know who the applicants were in Victoria.<br />
Now I do. I have seen their names, I might say to myself<br />
that some of the reasoning in the report is quite unsatisfying<br />
to my mind I could well say that but didI therefore<br />
say. " No, I reject your nomination; on looking over the<br />
list I am goinj to pick so and so" I wonder what would be<br />
said then, It is a very interesting thing for honourable members<br />
to carry in their minds, that the successfu, applicant has a<br />
board, the chairman and'dominating man in which is Mr, Reg,<br />
Ansett, whom I perhaps meet once a year, who has no political<br />
affiliations that ever I heard of. Indeed, my first association<br />
with him was when I was the Victorian Minister of Railways<br />
and put through a transport regulation bill which put him off<br />
the roads. Such bosom friends are we that that is the simple<br />
truth, That is a fact, Anyhow, this is a man of enterprise.<br />
He is tough. he is a driver; and he has undoubtedly achieved<br />
remarkable things9 When I first knew him he was very<br />
favourably regarded by the Labour Party, indeed, but now he<br />
has succeeded and of course, that is fatal. But he has a<br />
company, the board of which embraces, as we have been reminded<br />
by the honourable member for Indi ( Mr. Holten) this afternoon,<br />
a couple of gentlemon who could not by any stretch of the<br />
imagination be regarded as supporters or admirers of the<br />
Government. They include, of course, a celebrated Labour<br />
candidate, Sir George Jones.<br />
But if honourable members look back at the other one<br />
what is its name? United Telecasters, it has nine men on<br />
the board, eight of whom are, and have been for years, my<br />
very close personal friends, but they did not get the<br />
recommendation. This is what all this favouritism charge<br />
is worth. Here are men, literally eight out of nine, who<br />
are close personal friends of myself, some of whom I strongly<br />
000a* / IF </p>
<p>suspect may be supporters of the party that I lead, and the<br />
board does not recommend that group, It recommends Ansett<br />
Transport Industries, with no political associations except<br />
to the extent that there are known hostile ones. I gets the<br />
nomination. Can we as a Government now reject the recommendation<br />
and substitute for it some choice of our own? If we had<br />
substituted our choice; if we had, for example, selected Universal<br />
Telecastors, the one of which Sir Frank Selleck is chairman,<br />
I could imagine honourable members opposite being in such a<br />
passion of rage that they would have had seizures.<br />
Sir, the essence of this matter is that when you<br />
establish an independent board and that board conducts exhaustive<br />
inquiries, very costly to the parties concerned, you are not<br />
entitled to reject the recommendation of the board except for<br />
overwhelmingly powerful reasons and none, of course, have been<br />
put forward. Time runs on and, therefore, I just want to turn to<br />
another aspect of this matter. The honourable the Leader of<br />
the Opposition knowing, because he is not without intelligence,<br />
the force of these arguments, and knowing them in advance,<br />
thought fit to conveit this discussion into what I can only<br />
describe as a villainous attack on a series of people<br />
wicked and villainous. I was shocked by it. If it had come<br />
from other sources in his party, I would have understood it,<br />
but coming from him I must confess that I was shocked by it.<br />
What has he said about the matter? First of all he has<br />
accused Mr. Ansett and his company because you cannot<br />
distinguish them for this purpose of being bankrupt. This<br />
is a terrible thing for a man to say under the cover of<br />
Parliamentary privilege, to make a remark so actionable if<br />
spoken outside Parliament that the honourable gentleman would<br />
find himself ending up in the bankruptcy court. Let me remind<br />
the House and let me remind the people of what he said about<br />
this man who has battled his own way and achieved a remarkable<br />
success. He said<br />
" Ansett Transport Industries Limited has œ 6,000000<br />
worth of assets of dubious valueand liabilities<br />
amounting to œ 32,000,000."<br />
If he had only troubled to look at the balance sheet of Ansett<br />
Transport Industries Ltd, he would have found that the assets<br />
were not œ 6,000,000 but 5,000 000 but he did not bother<br />
about that; he set out to creato a false impression. He<br />
continued to all intents and purposes the man is broke."<br />
That is a nice thing to say, is it not, about a man conducting<br />
a great service industry in this country he is broke. He<br />
would not dare to say this outside Parliament. Then<br />
" Anybody who has seen his balance sheet wonders how<br />
he carries on. He carries on only because he has<br />
the backing and support of this Government,"<br />
all his obligations to which will have been discharged completely<br />
by the beginning of next year. Then he goes on rashly and<br />
says " He is the only man who has borrowed money at 8 per<br />
cent, and &amp; 8 per cent. around Australia and been<br />
able to survive, Korman has crashed, Hooker has<br />
crashed...."<br />
When did L. J. Hookers crash? I suggest to the honourable 00000.15 </p>
<p>member that ho say that outside Parliament and see what this<br />
firm has to do about it. But, they have all crashed, and<br />
he continues *" Ansett is the only one so far who has escaped."<br />
It is a great pity that the honourable gentleman is so unconcerned<br />
about the facts before he makes these charges because I just<br />
want to tell him, if he likes to be told, that on the stock<br />
exchange during the past twelve months, unsecured notes at the<br />
rate of 8 per cent, interest were registered on behalf of<br />
Australian Consolidated Press. I did not hear that it was<br />
bankrupt. Ampol Petroleum had unsecured notes listed at<br />
72 per cent. I had not heard it was bankrupt. Clyde Securities<br />
had them listed at 8-per cent. Felt and Textiles, one of the<br />
great textile industries of this country, is borrowing at 8 per<br />
cent. Then we have General Motors Acceptance how bankrupt<br />
they are borrowing at 8 per cent. and Humos Limited borrowing<br />
at 8 per cent. The Overseas Corporation has unsecured notes<br />
listed at 8 per cent, I do not need to protract the list.<br />
The fact is that this was a monstrous untruth. If the honourable<br />
member really wants to escape the condemnation of decent people<br />
in this country, he ought to take the first opportunity to<br />
retract it. So much for his charge against the Ansett Company.<br />
But he does not stop there. He makes a charge of<br />
dishonesty and corruption against the Government. Let us be<br />
quite clear about this. He says that the Government told the<br />
board what recommendation to make. He produced no evidence of<br />
such a monstrosity. I am the head of the Governmant and,<br />
until a fortnight ago, I had heard of no applicants at all, and<br />
thon I heard cf a couple by accident. He charges the Government<br />
with having said to the board, " This is what you are to recommend.'-<br />
That is corruption if over there was.<br />
I cannot imagine anything more dishonest than for a<br />
government to suborn a statutory committee to forego its duty<br />
and to make a false report not carrying its own judgment. But<br />
that is his charge against the Government. Of course, his third<br />
charge is against the board itself. These are reputable men.<br />
They cannot stand up in this House and answer, and they cannot<br />
take proceedings in the courts of the land for statements made<br />
here. And these people are accused of having so far foresworn<br />
their duty as to take instructions from the Government and then<br />
go through the arrant humbug of conducting hearings, listening<br />
to evidence and making a reporti The honourable member for<br />
Eden-Monaro ( Mr. Allan Fraser) yawns, because this is his cup<br />
of tea, this is his form; but it is not normally the form of<br />
the Leader of the Opposition,<br />
These are the charges, and I want everybody in Australia<br />
to understand that these charges have been made without a skerrick<br />
of support for them. He talks about a royal commission. I<br />
wonder what he would say. Does he want a royal commission on<br />
his charges with no parliamentary privilege, with himself<br />
available to be put into the box to disclose the alleged sources<br />
of his information? Of course he does not! We have had<br />
experience of that before today. And so he says, " Let us have<br />
a royal commission, not about these foul, damaging charges that<br />
I have rade, but on the general question which was investigated<br />
by a royal commission only a few years ago,"<br />
5 o e */ 6 </p>
<p>6-<br />
Si~ one thing that stands out crystal clear in<br />
this debate, which I ' think is a valuable one is that the<br />
Opposition, having set about the task of deszroying the<br />
Government, is not for thie first time destroyed by its own<br />
attack. In reality what emerges from it and whiat everybody<br />
ought to take notice of in the cities and in the country is<br />
-the fact that if the Labour Party came back into office,<br />
commercial television would go out and people would be cj~ osed<br />
up. They might let their licences run for a year or two,<br />
but they are bound by their policy which is to close up<br />
commercial television and put all the instruments of television<br />
communication with the people into the hands of a government<br />
body, which, if exper-ience counts for anything, will be<br />
compelled by a Lbour government 4ob" tekeei h os<br />
of Rimmon, This is a very simple debate from my poi*; nt of<br />
view. If I may say so, it has been. a very enjoyable debate.<br />
I have never felt so clearly that an attack w~ as so futile<br />
or so doomed to disaster, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
