<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2925</transcript-id>
    <title>PACIFIC BASIN ECONOMIC COUNCIL - KEY-NOTE ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA, HON EG WHITLAM, CHEVRON HOTEL, SYDNEY, 14 MAY 1973</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/05/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002925.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PACIFIC BASIN ECONOMIC COUN~ hCILKEY-<br />
NOTE ADDRESS BY THE PRIME<br />
MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA, HON. E. G.<br />
WHITLAM CHEVRON HOTEL, SYDNEY<br />
14 M4AY, 1973<br />
Since taking office just over five months ago the new<br />
Australian Government has acted over a wide range of matters firmly<br />
directed -towards the new realities, new prospects and new hopes for<br />
this vast Pacific region.<br />
My first visit overseas, as Prime Minister was to New<br />
Zealand, in January. In February I visited Papua New Guinea and<br />
Indonesia. Last month I led the Australian delegation to the South<br />
Pacific Forum in Apia, Western Samoa. On my way to London after the<br />
Forum I had a very long and, as you would expect, stimulating discussion<br />
with the Prime Minister of Canada, Mr. Trudeau, I9 shall be in North<br />
America again in August for the Commonwealth Heads of Government<br />
meeting and in Japan for the Annual Ministerial' meeting in October.<br />
We moved immediately to normalise relations with the most populous<br />
Pacific power the People's Republic of China. We have been acting<br />
in very close co-operation with our South Pacific partners, particularly<br />
New Zealand, in opposition to French nuclear testing in the Pacific.<br />
President Nixon said last year that 1973 would be the year<br />
of Europe. For us, however, it is very much the year of the Pacific.<br />
This is inevitably and'naturally so. It is the reflection not only<br />
of geographical realities but of the political, diplomatic and economic<br />
realities in the region.<br />
Much has been said and wvritten about the Government's style<br />
and approach. ' It is true that, in many matters, we hive moved with<br />
a speed which was not, one might say, altogether characteristic of<br />
Governments in Australia over the last few years. Nothing we have<br />
done, however, in these matters was not absolutely and precisely<br />
predictable by anybody who had taken the trouble to look at the<br />
considered and consistent policies of the Party which now forms the<br />
Australian Government. Interestingly enough, the very decision which<br />
is held in some quarters to represent the sharpest departure the<br />
recognition of the People's Republic is the very one on which failure<br />
to move rapidly would have put us most obviously out of step with the<br />
other nations represented in the Pacific Basin Economic Council. All<br />
of ust with the exception of the United States, now recognise China<br />
on very much the same terms; and the United States is moving as<br />
rapidly towards normalisation as the extraordinary complexity of power<br />
relations alow. I wish that Australia could have shown the leadership<br />
and foresight of Canada and thereby been entitled to the lasting<br />
gratitude of nations, not least the United States herself, in helping<br />
to restore reason and reality to the Westts relations with China0 In<br />
the event we did nothing at all radical; we merely ratified reality.<br />
The essence of that realiity in our region is that the<br />
conflict of ideologies must now give way to the rational development,<br />
use and conservation-of the region's human and physical resources.<br />
The intractable nature of the war in Indochina sprang partly from the<br />
fact that as far as the foreign belligerents were concerned it had no<br />
identifiable goals in terms of the possession of resources, or the </p>
<p>-2-<br />
expansion of trade, or the protection of lines of communication.<br />
It was just precisely that consciousness of unselfishness misplaced<br />
an4 misjudged as we now see that idealism to have been which drew<br />
the United States deeper and deeper into a conflict from which she<br />
could draw no material advantage. We need in this region an ideological<br />
holiday as far as our trade and diplomatic relations are concerned. This<br />
does not mean that we are ideologically indifferent or that there are<br />
no differences. The nations represented on this Council are not only<br />
all democracies but form one of the world's few significant democratic<br />
groupings. Democracy is no longer automatically taken as the only<br />
acceptable form of government. If, however, it is no longer appropriate<br />
to be crusaders it is absurd to believe the democracies are under seige0<br />
In all the time that we have been agonising over the political<br />
future of Indochina; in all the time that we have been pre-. occupied with<br />
the mistaken idea that Indochina was the appropriate ideological<br />
battleground between East and West, between China and the United States;<br />
in all the time that we have been wasting human and natural resources in<br />
pursuit of an ideological pre-occupation, we have ignored the -real<br />
nature of the growing challenge to civilisation. It is a challenge<br />
which knows no ideological bias. The basic question now facing mankind<br />
is not whether communism or democracy will prevail but whether<br />
civilisation as now constituted can long endure the pressure and demands<br />
of population upon resources. We have created for ourselves in less<br />
than a century a civilisation of unparalleled complexi ty, unparalleled<br />
splendour yet unparalleled wastefulness. We make in a . year greater<br />
demands upon this earthi's resources than any entire generation ever<br />
did before. We are the first civilisation in human history whose day<br />
to dlay existence depends on the consumption of resources which can<br />
never be replaced. In war, in any given day in Indochina we would<br />
consume more of the world's irreplaceable material than all the battles<br />
from Rameses to Napoleon combined. In peace, in day to day livin. S the<br />
-handful of nations represented on this Council would use more fuel<br />
and energy in a year than the whole of Europe required to carry through<br />
the industrial revolution in the century after Napoleon.<br />
It is true that countries like ours which have all experienced<br />
and contributed to the growing wonders of modern technology tend to<br />
be supremely optimistic; technology always finds the answer we hope.<br />
Yet we are sporting with fate if we allow sheer optimism to overcome<br />
reason in the face of one most palpable fact and that is, the world's<br />
resources of fuel and energy are finite and irreplaceable. A<br />
civilisation, and the nations composing that civillisation, which will<br />
not face that simple fact and combine to plan modifications i~ n its<br />
life-style to allow for this fact will not long endure.<br />
Nations have traditionally met their need for resources by<br />
national expansion, usually by war. In the case of the United States,<br />
Canada, Australia and New Zealand, we expanded by dispossessing the<br />
indigenous peoples. These methods are no longer available, even if<br />
they were remotely acceptable. </p>
<p>-3-<br />
Our great danger now is that in the competition for access<br />
to the worldts resources we could stumble into the supreme folly of<br />
war for the possession of resources. I say " the supreme folly" because<br />
the plain fact is that any war for resources would use more resources<br />
in the prosecution of that war than could ever have conceiLvably been<br />
obtained by the victorious power in such a war. I want to emphasise<br />
this point because our pre-occupation with ideological conflicts<br />
particularly in South East Asia, and our determination to avoi~ d<br />
nuclear war have tended to obscure the equal folly and equal dangers<br />
to the survival of civilisation posed by traditional wars over resourcest<br />
even if they were waged by so-called conventional means. I might<br />
illustrate this point by reference to Japan and I had the honour * to<br />
make this observation to the Crown Prince of Japan when he was with<br />
us in Canberra last week. The really important and enduring thing<br />
about the " economic miracle" of modern Japan is the hope it contains<br />
for'-the peace of the region and the world. Japan, unique in so many<br />
ways in world history, unique in so many things in world civilisation,<br />
is unique in nothing so great and momentous as this: That she intends<br />
to be the worldts first great economic power to base her claim to<br />
fair and adequate * access to the raw materials and oierseas markets her<br />
industry requires without military threats or force. This is the<br />
" 1new course". o I believe that Japan, her people and her leaders, will<br />
hold to the " new course".* I have stated that belief not only here,<br />
not only in Tokyo but indeed in Peking.<br />
We take reassurance from the fact that Japan has renounced<br />
nuclear weapons. The " new course" ls however, I believe rests not only<br />
upon Japan's recognition of the supreme and final folly of a nuclear<br />
war; it is not just based on her own terrible and unique o rdeal; nor<br />
does the renunciation of war only rest upon a recognition that Japan<br />
is physically and economically so utterly vulnerable to nuclear war.*<br />
Even if it could be limited to non-nuclear weapons, a so-called conventional.<br />
war for the control. of resources would be the ultimate act of<br />
human folly and unreason. Great industrial societies, of which Japan<br />
is already the third, are facing crises in the availability of traditional<br />
fuels and many forms of raw material; yet a war over resources,<br />
particularly fuels, involving any of the great powers would itself<br />
entirely consume the very resources being fought over. These<br />
considerations reinforce the need for a " new course" not just by Japan<br />
but by all the powers.<br />
The great relevance of these matters to the nations represented<br />
in this Council is that we are all great users of resources and great<br />
producers of resourcest living in a region of tremendous inequalities<br />
in both the use and possession of resources.<br />
We depend very much on each other as developed countries and<br />
the developing countries in our region depend very much upon us. This<br />
Council is necessarily and properly mainly concerned with commercial<br />
and investment problems, and opportunities between the member countries<br />
and other countries in the region. At any time since the formation of<br />
this Council in 1967 the emphasis in its deliberations would properly<br />
have been on. the expansion of trade between our-member nations. This<br />
is still your principal concern as businessmen and investors. But may </p>
<p>-4-<br />
I suggest that for the remainder of this centure no international<br />
forum, whether at the governmental, official, entrepeneurial or<br />
scientific level, can ignore this basic problem of world resources.<br />
It is particularly appropriate that I raise this matter with you.<br />
Some of you come from tlhse two great nations of the United States and<br />
Japan to provide us with our most important markets and we are, of<br />
course, one of the worldts great possessors of so many of the resources<br />
for which demand threatens to outpace supply. Increasingly, the<br />
relations between Australia and Japan, Australia and the United States,<br />
and the relations between Canada and the United States will turn on<br />
the question of the use and share of resources. My own Government has<br />
already made a number of decisions about the future use and ownership<br />
and development of Australian mineral and energy resources. These<br />
primarily are decisions related to national considerations to<br />
Australian aspirations about her own future and her own rights in the<br />
use of her own resources. We do, however, recognise our wider<br />
responsibilities to our region and to civilisation. As the fortunate<br />
possessor of very great resources we want to play our part in<br />
contributing to the prosperity of the region and of the civilisation.<br />
It can't be done if the nations indulge in a catch-as-catch-can race<br />
for resources; it can't be done if corporations conduct their business<br />
operations with an eye only to the balance sheet; it can't be done if<br />
governments are not prepared to co-operate with each other and with<br />
business to develop rational and internationally responsible policies<br />
on the future use of resources. We have to make a start now on<br />
developing such policies for if we do not it's quite plain that the<br />
future of the technological civilisation we here represent, for all<br />
its splendours, for all its miraculous achievements, is likely to be<br />
nasty, brutish and short. 0 0<br />
fte </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
