<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>15465</transcript-id>
    <title>Harpers Field Development in the City of Tea Tree Gully</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/07/2007</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I am pleased to announce today that the Australian Government has given in-principle approval for funding of up to $1.179 million under the Regional Partnerships program to be negotiated for the Harpers Field Development project at the City of Tea Tree Gully.</p>
<p>The money will assist the City of Tea Tree Gully with the costs of labour and materials used in the construction of an amenities building at Harpers Field.</p>
<p>I pay tribute to Trish Draper MP, the Member for Makin, who has worked hard to deliver on this important community project.</p>
<p>The amenities building is the second stage in the development of Harpers Field and includes change rooms, showers and toilet facilities, a canteen and meeting room area. </p>
<p>It will allow football and cricket players, spectators and community groups such as Apex, Lions, Scouts and other groups to better access the facility.</p>
<p>The development will create a regional hub of community and sporting facilities and accommodate the growing youth population in the region.</p>
<p>I congratulate the local community for working together to access Regional Partnerships program funding, particularly the Adelaide Metropolitan Area Consultative Committee for helping to bring this project to fruition.</p>
<p>I would also like to acknowledge the financial support provided by the South Australian Office of Recreation and Sport and the Pickard Group.</p>
<p>The Regional Partnerships program continues the Australian Government's approach of working with local communities to support their ideas.  A total of $261.7 million is available under the Regional Partnerships program from 2007-08 to 2010-11.<br />
 The Regional Partnerships program will deliver benefits to communities well into the future, not only from program funding, but from the higher levels of economic activity and improved social amenity which the program is generating.</p>
<p>Since its inception in July 2003, the Regional Partnerships program has, on average, attracted a more than three dollars from other sources for every dollar invested by the Australian Government.</p>
<p>Communities should contact their local Area Consultative Committee if they wish to seek funding through the Regional Partnerships program.</p>
<p>For further information go to <a href="http://www.regionalpartnerships.gov.au">www.regionalpartnerships.gov.au</a> or <a href="http://www.acc.gov.au">www.acc.gov.au</a></p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
