<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8891</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J. KEATING MP LAUNCH OF THE AUSTRALIAN MANUFACTURING COUNCIL&#039;S REPORT EMERGING EXPORTERS, HYATT HOTEL, CANBERRA, 15 JUNE 1993</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/06/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008891.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
LAUNCH OF THE AUSTRALIAN MANUFACTURING COUNCIL'S REPORT<br />
4EMERGING EXPORTERS, HYATT HOTEL, CANBERRA, 1S JUNE 1993<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
my colleague Martin Ferguson, President of the ACTU and ladies and<br />
gentlemen. This is a very impressive and I think seminal work. It is the first accurate snapshot<br />
of what is happening within the smaller innovative exporting firms which<br />
has been undertaken by the Australian Manufacturing Council, under the<br />
leadership of John Prescott and with the help of McKinsey's. A process of<br />
rigorous interview and evaluation of the various firms has been undertaken so<br />
as to give a clear indication of the performance of these businesses and their<br />
trends and the way they are operating and their motivations. Much of this is In<br />
the report.<br />
The important thing about it is I think for all of us who have beleved in an<br />
international culture for Australia, for those who have thought competitiveness<br />
was the key to international success, what the report shows is that the twin, if<br />
you like, Incentives of the carrot and the stick the carrot being access to<br />
export market development grant schemes, export access, NIES, Austrade,<br />
better research and development, better tax concession has changed<br />
attitudes, as has the stick of lower tariffs arnd the incentive to be<br />
competitiveness and then once having become competitive, turn that<br />
competitiveness to exports.<br />
It Is again, a microcosm of what could be a very much larger picture of<br />
Australian manufacturing, and supports the notion of an internationall<br />
competitive economy with an open goods market where companies sort<br />
themselves into competitive lots and where through, then, some inspiration In<br />
leadership, the companies then go on and do things.<br />
We are talking here of quite phenomenal growth but off a relatively small base<br />
15 per cent growth in a year as John indicated, $ 8 billion of earnings to date<br />
growing even at the same addition of the number of firms as the 700; that Is on </p>
<p>very conservative assumptions, growing to around $ 15.5 billion in five years<br />
time. The very thing the country needs In the... that Is added value,<br />
Innovation and tht focusing on the export markets, paitcularly at the Asia-<br />
Pacific, One of the very clear things In the report Is that while these companies have<br />
been successful, their character, their products and their history is often no<br />
different than thousands of other companies that do not export at all and the<br />
difference is only In attitudes, the difference is only In leadership. It Is not in the<br />
products, It Is not in the research component, it Is not In the maturity of the<br />
business, It is only in leadership and in attitudes which begs the question about<br />
how we should try and motivate the other 90 per cent of similar existing<br />
manufacturing firms to engage themselves In exports as well.<br />
The survey shows that our firms can succeed and that three quarters of the<br />
firms have only began exportng recently after an average of 27 years of<br />
domestic production. Some are, as John Prescott said, some have been, to<br />
coin an expression, born global; that is they have done nothing other than<br />
export, they didn't have a domestic manufacturing history. But the average is<br />
for three quarters is 27 years, they had 27 years of domestic production and so<br />
therefore it is pretty obvious that many other firms could be exporting but are<br />
niot, because they have not had the leadership or the Inspiration.<br />
It Is surveys like this I think that do indicate, I mean a survey of this quality, that<br />
does Indicate to many firms that they to can do the same thing and that the<br />
focus on things such as best practice does lift the whole standard of Australian~<br />
manufacturing. It changes the attitudes of Australians and Australian<br />
businesses towards export and towards Asia and it does give us a real<br />
opportunity to see the place mature as a modern manufacturing country, offsetting<br />
that overwhelming dependence on commodities which we had through<br />
most of the post-War years.<br />
John made some Interesting points about the size of these firms. Many were<br />
thought by the surveying firm McKinsey's to be too small to be successful as<br />
manufacturing exporters, but they are. And one of the reasons that they are Is<br />
of course, the shifts In communication technology. The fax machine has made<br />
a very large difference to the way a small business can present itself abroad.<br />
And of course the Governmen-t's changes there in telecommunications can only<br />
further underpin the competitiveness of smaller companies and interfacing with<br />
the world through these innovative technologies.<br />
One of the other key points that emerges of the study Is the importance In<br />
establishing distribution networlks in Asia. The likelihood of Asian firms<br />
militantly marketing Australian goods is a very slim one and, while it happens in<br />
places and certainly happens with the bulk traded commodities in some<br />
respects, the establishment of distribution businesses in Asia Is one of the keys<br />
to our future and we have to do what Japan did 20 years ago establish<br />
distribution businesses even with clusters of firms operating In various areas, In </p>
<p>some places foreign access zones which are now available in Japan and in<br />
China, where these countries actually want to see the development of non-<br />
Indigenous distribution arrangements.<br />
These are all things which the report points up, and It most particularly points<br />
up the fact that the culture of internatlonallsatlon, the culture of lower tariffs and<br />
competitiveness is the right culture of Australia in terms of developing our<br />
manufacturing capacity, that added value and innovation will come from a<br />
competitive country which has got all the other things running for it a proper<br />
research and development focus, proper concessions for that in the tax system,<br />
a competitive exchange rate, low inflation, all the big macro things which are<br />
part and parcel of competitiveness, and then what blossoms are the companies<br />
under the leadership of people who can see beyond the domestic market.<br />
This Is a very Important study, it Is a high quality, comprehensive one, the<br />
nature of the Interviews and the assessment of the motivation and the<br />
leadership of these companies in doing what they have done, information<br />
gleaned from the Interviews about the products and the way in which they have<br />
performed and developed make It the most comprehensive study of Its kind and<br />
therefore for the development of Australian manufacturing exports a seminal<br />
work. So I congratulate the Australian Manufacturing Council. I congratulate those<br />
people who have been associated with the work Elizabeth Brian and Bill<br />
Mountsford and also McKnsey and Company who have undertaken the study<br />
and have produced a work, the substance of which were it have been produced<br />
any time in the first two or three decades after the War would have made this<br />
an entirely different country.<br />
0: Mr Keating, one of the problems which the report Identifies is the<br />
problems which the companies have had in getting access to finance. It<br />
has been an issue which the Government has raised quite recently in<br />
testing Is the Government concerned about the banks unwillingness<br />
to lend to business In general and what is it planning to do to try and<br />
address this?<br />
PM: I think the banks had In the first instance and they are now focussing<br />
on the sort of customers that can bring value to the bank. And I think<br />
therefore there will be the development of closer relationships with<br />
banking between banks and smaller businesses, that the cash flows and<br />
business opportunities of these businesses will be much more a focus of<br />
their lending than their assets than has been the case in the past. So I<br />
would not expect that we are about to see a revolution here, we will see<br />
a balance between cash flow lending and assets and a willingness to<br />
find new businesses to grow their to find new customers of quality.<br />
This is going to take a further cultural change In Australian banking and<br />
that is why the Government has in Its ' Investing in the Nation' program<br />
talked about better Information coming to the Government at the </p>
<p>Reserve B~ ank about lending practices of banks and trying to given<br />
instance specific Information about how particular banks are relating to<br />
toe customers. I think the banks understand thIs Is a problem for the<br />
whole country and that they want to change, but again for them the<br />
change Is going to be a relatlvely slow one because they just don't have<br />
that culture In their institutions and they have to acquire it.<br />
0: Mr Prescott, why has this report ruled out the Impact of the recession,<br />
the report says that import drive is not being driven by low domestic<br />
demand, but surely local firms have been trying to find new markets as a<br />
result of the greater demand in..<br />
JP: I think the report shows that the" e firm have emerged through good<br />
times and more difficult times and that just as many firms were<br />
commencing to achieve this export status while the Australian economy<br />
was expanding as there were when it was shrinking.<br />
MF: The analysis shows that the firms we are talking about are firms that<br />
have made a continuing commitment to an export culture. The research<br />
goes back several years, it goe~ s back right through the 1980s, it shows<br />
no significant difference in pattern as to the number of firms that<br />
emerged in the early and middle part of that decade as has emerged in<br />
the last couple of years.<br />
0: Mr Prescott, how do we get the other 90 per cent of firms who haven't<br />
got the message yet about exporting. Do you have any Ideas?<br />
JP: One of the ideas, of course, Is this meeting. And of course the whole<br />
Idea in producing the report was to try and get a quality piece of<br />
research Into the market place to inspire debate about some of the<br />
issues. This particular subject was first raised In the Manufacturing<br />
Council's Global Challenge report and what we sought to do In the last<br />
two or three years is to develop the various themes in the Global<br />
Challenge report and In the last couple of years of have sought to<br />
understand better what causes firms to export and this is we hope a<br />
quality piece of research I think it is that will lift the standard of the<br />
debate about these issues in this country and I hope it will be taken back<br />
Into the industry organisations, Into the trade unions, Into work places,<br />
onto the shop floor and disseminated and debated so that a much wider<br />
cross section of opinion makers and movers and shakers in this<br />
economy will be motivated to respond. In fact, In short we see the<br />
performance of these 700 firms as quite inspirational.<br />
Q: Mr Keating, is this report a vindication of your Government's policies?<br />
Does it mean that you have finally arrived, that you have done<br />
everything you need to do as a Government and it is over to business<br />
from here on in?<br />
j </p>
<p>PM.: I think it Is an Indication that the direction Is right. As I said this Is the, if<br />
you like, we are noting the sucecss of these businesses, we are taking<br />
Ie sns from them and they have been õ rowing rapily, the value of their<br />
export merchandise has been growing rapidly. But fromn a relatively<br />
small base which means we have to encourage more companes to do<br />
more of the same, So the kinds of programs which have been there<br />
tha Is beyond the big and impodrtat macro seltngs of the exchange<br />
rate, inflation, interest rates, the key competitIveness issues beyond<br />
tse to programs like export market develop grants, NIES, Austrade',<br />
those sorts of things I think the reach of those programs will become<br />
Important and the lessons of the success of these companies, as John<br />
said, an inspirational lesson is the one we want to transmit to the other<br />
manufacturers, domestic manufacturers who have not ad this stage<br />
bothered with exports and I think it Is a valuable lesson in Indicating that<br />
the directions are right and that where we to have chosen for instance to<br />
have locked ourself behind a tariff wall and continued to subsidise<br />
uncompetitive Industries while the competitive ones in commodities were<br />
subject to lower and lower prices In world terms would have seen us<br />
certainly in trading and current account terms in an Impossible position.<br />
This change has been a very profound one and of course, naturally If it<br />
continues the whole nature of Australia's merchandise exports will<br />
change..<br />
Q: Do you think that the Government has to do more? The report talks<br />
about giving a hand up to exports, it refers to things like developing<br />
systematIc cornpaiisons between Australia and East Asian trading<br />
partners, In terms of competitiveness and so on. Do you see that the<br />
Government needs to more to give a hand up to these potential exports,<br />
P M: Well I think we are trying all the time, and a cut in the company rate to<br />
33 per cent which Is largely the sort of area company rate program a<br />
very rapid acceleration and depreciation. Two Investment allowances,<br />
one for' projects over $ 50 million and one for all projects, these are very<br />
much, I think, hands up to all Australian companies and then I suppose<br />
we may specifically say they are, well, hands up more specifically In<br />
areas such as export market development and NIES and Austrade and<br />
what have you, and refining these programs, I mean over the years we<br />
have sought during the ERC process of the Government to try and refine<br />
these programs down so that they actually worked better each time and<br />
I think taking the lessons of a study like this gives you a chance to refine<br />
them further.<br />
0: Mr Keating, the report talks about changes to the EMDG scheme and<br />
also ITES, obviously they are going to cost money, will you adopt it in<br />
the next Budget?<br />
PM: Well again, as I said a moment ago these are things which we can<br />
continue to refine and obviously some programs will have better access, </p>
<p>people have better access to them, understand them better and they will<br />
be more beneficil to them then others, We try and work out what those<br />
prorams are arnd to see how we cani Improve them and how we cant<br />
make their reach more obvious and I think we will continue to do that<br />
0: Prime Minister, if manufacturing exports reach the $ 15 billion, that would<br />
slash the current account deficit and bring It down to a sustainable sort<br />
of level, Is that the sort of macro effect that we can look forward to for<br />
PM: It these categories of firms were producing another, say roughly 2 per<br />
cent of GDP In exports, all things being equal, there would be no change<br />
In the level of Imports and commodity prices being where they are, this<br />
would more rapidly bring the current account back towards its debt<br />
stabilisation point. But of course, as we know, nothing ever does stay<br />
equal. So all you have got to do Is keep on trying and these firms could<br />
mak e a very solid contribution, particularly when we have got low prices.<br />
John ( Prescott) and I were having a talk before we came over here just<br />
about the performance of BHP which is now exporting record volumes<br />
just about acros-s all of its range of commoditiles, but at much lower<br />
prices. This Is the thing, the world is largely in recession and prices are<br />
low, therefore the thing to be doing is exporting more volume of the<br />
things which we traditionally exported even at lower prices, and at the<br />
same time try and export these higher value added areas where you cut<br />
some of that difference away, which comes via the terms of trade.<br />
0: A question from the floor, Prime Minister, do you have concerns about<br />
one of the areas identified in the report is an impediment for exporters,<br />
and that is financial Institutions that can't see their way into financing a<br />
lot of these areas. And secondly, it does detect, or It does talk about<br />
Australian concerns about businesses being subject to foreign<br />
Investment and moving off shore, have you detected that sort of attitude<br />
In Australians, and is that a problem for getting more and more of these<br />
companies off the ground?<br />
PM: Well I think it is always very hard to launch a new business at any stage.<br />
They are as hard to launch today as they have ever been. But most of<br />
these have got a history of domestic manufacture. I think one of the key<br />
points of the report is that it is an attitudinal question, it is really a<br />
leadership question. They have got the same products, they had the<br />
same products and the same, if you like, competitiveness features and<br />
the same opportunities, but some are doing it arnd some aren't. The<br />
difference Is only leadership. Now, financing is part of this, of course,<br />
and I was asked a question earlier about the banks, I don't think I can<br />
add much more to what I said there. I think the banks recognise that<br />
there Is a change going on here, but they have not been at the forefront<br />
of the change and they are trying to catch up, and I think we have got to<br />
give them marks for that. </p>
<p>Q: Prime Minister, does it concern you at all one of the findings of the<br />
report, which Is that even If these companies go ofl exportng their heads<br />
off the job growth out of thai Is very small, only I think about 33 000<br />
people over five years. That's not going to knock much of a dent in the<br />
unemployment problem we have got, is it?<br />
PM: Well I don't think we are seeking to suggest that the growth of the-se<br />
firms is going to solve the employment problem. The employment<br />
problem, we are In a period of much higher productivity then we have<br />
been, we have got a much more productive corporate sector then we<br />
have had for years, and that means fewer people are employed in that<br />
process. How do you get more people employed? Answer, produce<br />
more product, I mean there is no substitute, I don't think, here for<br />
growth. That's the key point.<br />
0: Mr Prescott, what's your answer to the question on the banks, do you<br />
havo a different answer to the Prime Minister?<br />
A: No, I don't have a different answer to the Prime Minister, I would simply<br />
add that In many cases we are not just looking for traditional bank<br />
finance to support these firms, there are quite complex equity Issues that<br />
are discussed in the report, and there are other concepts that need to be<br />
further explored for various types of new funds to provide development<br />
capital. There are no easy solutions to the finance one, but we are not<br />
just looking only at the banks.<br />
0: Mr Keating, are you concerned about the general investment<br />
requirement, and particularly in the last week or so the alleged<br />
uncertainty created by the Mabo issue?<br />
PM: No. Look, the profit share in the economy Is now nearly back to the late<br />
180s, it is already above the 1960s average, if my memory serves me<br />
correctly. We have got a very competitive exchange rate, we have got<br />
by our recent history very low inflation and low interest rates and all<br />
these things, I think, mean that companies have been able to rebalance<br />
their balance sheets, that they are In a position now to look around for<br />
Investment opportunities in a way they were not, say, two years ago. I<br />
think it has taken about two years longer then everybody thought to<br />
change the nature of bal ance sheets and to remove some of the gearing<br />
that existed Into bill the profits and the savings of companies back up.<br />
Now, I think that is happening, I think companies are stripped down to<br />
do things and I think they will do things, and particularly with the<br />
Investment Incentives of these Investment allowances, they are time<br />
specific. In other words, the projects only qualify if they are In there<br />
within the time frame allowed under the Tax Act. So, this Is going to<br />
bring a fair bit on by itself as well as the traditional things of housing et<br />
cetera. </p>
<p>Q: Mr Griffiths, from the perspective of a ' V~ ctorian, we hear a lot of doom<br />
and gloom about the States Mranufaturing, can you see mo* re promise<br />
from this report for Victoria?<br />
A: Well I think one of the lessons here is that Victoria Is as well<br />
represented, and In many cases better represented then the national<br />
whole, that is a function, of course, of the reliance of the Victorian<br />
economy on the manufacturing sector, So, It is a good news story for<br />
Australia generally, and I suppose in that context for Victoria specifically,<br />
I would reiterate the sentIment that the Prime Minister and John Prescott<br />
stated earlier, and that Is that in large measure success or otherwise is<br />
determined by firm leadership, and a~ s I get around partlcular enterprises<br />
In this country, you can work ot as you walk In through the front gate<br />
and after two minutes of discussion with the leadership and the work<br />
place whether these are can do companies or not. So, really the<br />
message is, I think, all a-bout leadership.<br />
Q: Mr Prescott, you in your speech ruled out any of the means ofmanufacturing<br />
efforts, nevertheless . Qnaudible) talks about larger<br />
companies helping smaller companies get But what do you say to that<br />
approach and how do you foresee it coming about?<br />
A: Well it is a very wide ranging question, of course. But what this report<br />
talks about basically is three things. Firstly, how we build the more<br />
pervasive export culture in this country. Secondly, how we remove<br />
constraints to export success. And, thirdly, what are the key measures<br />
that might enhance export competitive advantages. Now, each of those<br />
three Issues goes much deeper and much more broadly across policy<br />
making then just the idea of picking winners. But there are a number of<br />
examples In the report that show what individual firms and groups of<br />
firms can do to disseminate material. There are examples, for example,<br />
of firms that set up to disseminate research information that, if you like,<br />
provide a basis for bringing the providers of research to the knowledge<br />
of people that might be seeking that research base or may be able to<br />
take advantage of a particular piece of research. There are examples of<br />
firms that by marketing information, technology can Improve the capacity<br />
of other firms to remove a number of constraints and to find more<br />
knowledge of the market place. Then there are other examples that go<br />
more directly to the question of sharing information, sharing<br />
management methods, there is a reference in the report to the<br />
advantages of the best practice program where firms that have<br />
succeeded in developing best practices can disseminate their methods<br />
to other firms to the collective advantage. Their. methods, as distinct<br />
from their own competitive edge. There is a whole host of things that<br />
are brought out in the report where firms that get together can gain<br />
advantage from one another. </p>
<p>0: Mr Keating, you talked earlier about the need for leadership and leaders<br />
don't grow on trees, so how are you going to Increase the number of<br />
psople who can come to ir-emdionai meAzet in peace and comfort<br />
do you expect just to, for success to breed success, or a domino effect if<br />
you like, or Is there something more specific in there too,<br />
encouragement?<br />
PM. Well I think the culture of the country has changed, I mean we are<br />
putting nearly eight kids In ton now through secondary school, anid forty<br />
per cent of those into university, the culture In terms of the private<br />
research and development effort coming from companies spending more<br />
of their own income on R&amp; D, availing themselves of the Incentive of the<br />
tax concession available, the co--operative research Institutions we now<br />
have there, the CRCs, which I think Is a good and novel way of bringing<br />
business, insfltutions, and research institutions arnd universities together:<br />
this sort of change is, I think, demonstrating to many managers and<br />
owners of businesses that develop an iniiative product and you can<br />
basically draw some economic rent from it, and I think that is the lesson.<br />
I think the launch of this particular report and the coverage of Its<br />
contents is just another example of how we will get that Impression over.<br />
Plus, the fact that we are very, very competitive. I mean there are very<br />
few products now that we can't be competitive in an export markets.<br />
This just makes an obvious point to somebody who is battling to either<br />
keep a business together or to grow it, and as the best practice<br />
programs and the rest start to prolife rate and move through the economy<br />
the culture generally changes, and of course these are the companies<br />
that are going to earn more. If they earn more and they become publicly<br />
listed companies, they are going to have a higher premium on them.<br />
Therefore the whole culture reinforces itself again.<br />
0: Mr Ferguson, do you see a correlation between progress towards<br />
enterprise bargaining correlation on the grim export culture of the<br />
companies, is there any apparent correlation between those two things,<br />
or are they<br />
A: No, I think they are very much integrated. I think you will find that the<br />
company Is adopting a leadership position on the industrial relations<br />
front, also the company Is adopting a leadership position in respect to<br />
your export. The reality of life is, when you talk about best practice you<br />
are talking about an integrated approach looking at industrial relations,<br />
the question of export culture, Investment in research and development,<br />
they are all interrelated anid it is those companies that adopt that<br />
leadership position that are going to lead this country in the future.<br />
0: Mr Keating, how does the Government propose to respond to the<br />
recommendations in the report today? </p>
<p>PM; Well I think that many of the features of the report already cover, not just<br />
the macro-economic influences of policy, but also the specific programs9<br />
we have there like EMDG... et cetera. But I think from our point of view<br />
what Is interesting Is the quantifcation of the success of these firms,<br />
peering behind their managements to find out what did motivate them<br />
and how they have done it, which itself gives us clues about how we<br />
ought to direct policy in the future. I think In terms of any of the specific<br />
schemes we have, I would think, we will seek to take lessons from such<br />
an exhaustive study and try and improve those. But I think perhaps<br />
more then anything else it just underpins again what we have believed;<br />
that is, that our future is as an exporter not just of our traditional things<br />
but of the higher added value products, and that we can do it and the<br />
difference is not about competitiveness or about the products or quality,<br />
it is about really attitude and leadership and I think knowing that is a very<br />
handy thing for the Government to know to devise further progress along<br />
this path, and that might go to designing some of these schemes more<br />
closely or improving them, but wil probably go to proselytising about the<br />
prospects of added value arnd the likelihood of success. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
