<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2937</transcript-id>
    <title>THE PRIME MINISTER&#039;S PRESS CONFERENCE AT PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA, TUESDAY 29 MAY 1973</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/05/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002937.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
THE PRIME~ MINISTER'S PRESS CONFERENCE<br />
AT IARjIA~ qENT HOUSE, CANBERRA<br />
TUESDAY, 29 MAY. 1973<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I thought it might suit you to-have<br />
another conference in the morning. The Cabinet met yesterday<br />
morning and afternoon and most of the Ministers concerned<br />
issued statements to you. There was one which wasn't issued<br />
so perhaps I can give you the gist of it now. Cabinet<br />
approved the establishment of a task force to draw up uniform<br />
national housing standards in co-operation with the States.<br />
You remember this was forecast at the Premiers' Conference<br />
about three w.-eeks ago.<br />
An expert technical unit will be established in the<br />
Departmeiat of Housing and we have invited the States and local<br />
Government authorities to co-operate with the Australian<br />
Government in establishing a national Housing Standards<br />
Committee. h-1r Johnson is releasing a statement to you on it<br />
and my Press Office will release the text of my letter to the<br />
Premiers later in the day, that is after they have all got<br />
the letter themselves. Are there any questions?<br />
Q: Do you oppose the U~ nited States bombing in Cambodia?<br />
Do you intend writing to President Nixon protesting against<br />
this bombing in similar vein to the protest over LJ. 0<br />
bombing of North Vietnam, and if not, why not?<br />
PRIMECC MINISTER: My general attitude about the withdrawal<br />
of American bombers from Thailand where this operation is baoned<br />
is well known. It's knowin to all the relevant authorities.<br />
Q: Do you plan to go to Washington later thais year? If so<br />
will your visit be official or unofficial? -Do you intend to<br />
go to W ashington even if you are not invited there by<br />
President Nixon?<br />
PRIH/ E MINISTER: Yes, I'll be going through the United i. tates<br />
As you know there is a meeting of the Commonwealth Heads of<br />
Government in Ottawa early in August. As you also know,<br />
I was able to accept one of the invitations from Latin American<br />
countries to make official visits to them. I accepted the one<br />
to ": exico that will be late in July. Clearly, going from<br />
Mexico to Canada, I will go through, or across the United<br />
States. I have many invitations to address " bodies in New York<br />
and Washington. Now, I think, if I may say so, it's about<br />
time people took these things a little more rationally. The<br />
relationship between Australia and the United States or the<br />
relationship between Australia and the United Kingdom are so<br />
long-standing and so intimate that a Head of Government does<br />
not wait for an official invitation. That may be the case,<br />
for instance in some of the other visits that T am making<br />
this year, such as Indonesia or India, where I am going next<br />
week, or Japan, or China later in the year. Visits by<br />
Australian Prime Ministers to the United Kingdom and the<br />
United States are common place. </p>
<p>Q: Has Cabinet reached a decision on the size of the Army<br />
and will 1, lr Barnard be making a statement to Parliament<br />
this week?<br />
PRIME INTISTER: I expect Mr Barnard will be making a<br />
statement to Parliament on this subject this week. The Cabinet<br />
is making the following recommendations to the Caucus so that<br />
the plarnned growth of the regular Army that is the volunteer<br />
regular army should be increased from 31,000 to 34,000<br />
over the course of the next three years. The field force<br />
should be organised on a divisional basis of six regular<br />
battalions, in three task forces of two battalions each, with<br />
combat and logistic support. These task forces should be<br />
Townsville, Ennogera and Holdsworthy. There should be a<br />
further major review of ground force capability in 1976.<br />
Q: How important is it to you to be invited to see -' resident<br />
Nixon when you are in Washington. Do you have specific matters<br />
you wish to discuss with him and if so could you tell us what<br />
they are? Are you concerned with the appearances as far as<br />
the Australian electorate is concerned if you don't get an<br />
invitation?<br />
PRI= LfINISTER: I would be very happy to discuss with President<br />
Nixon anything that he would like to raise and I imagine he would<br />
be happy to discuss with me anything that I would lihe to raise.<br />
But I repeat official invitations are not necessary in these<br />
circumstances. I would hope that when the Australian Prime<br />
Iinister was visiting Washington it would be as natural for him<br />
to discuss matters with the Tresident as it used to be in<br />
Sir Robert Menzies' time. All this hoohah that has accompanied<br />
visits by Sir Robert fenzies' successors is psychophantic.<br />
Q: You said that you would hope that it would be natural<br />
for the Australian Prime '. inister to discuss things with the<br />
President while he was in Jashington. There has been speculation<br />
from Washington that you won't be getting an invitation because<br />
the President is still angry with the Australian Government over<br />
protests by Australian Miinisters on the bombing of Vietnam.<br />
Do you think there is any basis for that speculation and<br />
certainly do you think it would look that way if you don't get<br />
an invitation while you are there?<br />
PRIM LINISTLR: Speculation is the operative part of your<br />
question. There is no change in any of these circumstances<br />
I have not said anything on any of these subjects for a very<br />
long time. Now President Nixon doesn't hold press conferences.<br />
He doesn't answer to Parliament. I can't be expected to be<br />
any more forthcoming in these matters than he is in these<br />
circumstances. ' I give him credit for being mature and courteous.<br />
Q: In the discussions on the size of the Army was there any<br />
proposal that a task force base or some Army base be established<br />
in Perth or Western Australia.<br />
' RI. E , INIlTLR: No.<br />
Q: Senator Murphy said some time ago that he intended to<br />
introduce the trade practices legislation this Session. When<br />
in fact will it be introduced?<br />
PRIM M. INISTER: Next Session. Gentlemen, there have been </p>
<p>more Bills introduced and in fact more Bills passed in this<br />
Session than in any autumn session in the Parliament's history.<br />
It's just not possible to introduce and I don't think undertakings<br />
were given to introduce all the Bills to which the Government<br />
is committed in this first Session.<br />
Q: As your Office was involved were you consulted on the<br />
Everingham expulsion, and further, as the man's livelihood<br />
is involved and also the prospect of future employment, would<br />
you consider asking Mr President or Mr Speaker to re-examine the<br />
situation so that he can if he so desires bring any evidence that<br />
he may have to ( inaudible)? Would you also consider if that<br />
course is not followed would you consider asking h ir Speaker<br />
to reconsider the severity of the penalty as it could involve<br />
the man in possible employment for a very long time?<br />
PRIIUv NINISTER: Both the President and the Speaker consulted<br />
with me I suppose it was some six weeks ago at any rate on this<br />
matter. It happens that Tdr Everingham was found in my office<br />
I think it was the VWednesday it might have been the Tuesday<br />
before the last polling day. At any rate it was the day after<br />
I'd spoken at the National Press Club and no member of my staff<br />
was in imiy office when he was there. The only member of my staff<br />
who: had been in the office had left shortly before he was found.<br />
He was found there when she came back. The fact that it was my<br />
office is immaterial. M embers of the Iress Gallery are given the<br />
freedom of this building more than any other of their citizens.<br />
If a member of the Gallery is found in a room where he is not<br />
prima facie entitled to be found I believe it is incumbent upon<br />
him to give an explanation. He has not given me an explanation.<br />
The explanation that he has given the presiding officers I would<br />
not regard as satisfactory. But it's immaterial that it is my<br />
office. Every member of Parliament could be equally concerned.<br />
Q: ir Connor, the Minister for Minerals and Energy, announced<br />
I think it was last week that there would be a national pipeline<br />
grid and he said that it would extend virtually right across the<br />
country to Port Hedland and across to Sydney and down to LIelbourne<br />
and up to the Queensland coastal towns. Is this plan subject to<br />
some sort of feasibility study of the economics of it his only<br />
justification amounted to about eight or 15 paragraphs in the<br />
Second Reading Speech.<br />
PRI,-iE MINISTER: Yes, anything that the Government does is<br />
done on the basis of proper investigations which are made<br />
public. Kr Connor I am certain would be very happy to dilate<br />
further to you on this matter.<br />
Q: Supplementary to Mr Thomas's question, has a feasibility<br />
study been made or will it be made before the Government acts<br />
to go ahead with The scheme.<br />
PRIE INISTER: You had better ask Mr Connor. I don't think<br />
one has been made but I think one will be made. I would be certain<br />
that one would be made. The Pipeline Authority Bill as you know<br />
is the necessary legal basis for these things but the Government<br />
has taken the quite clear attitude that in respect to all<br />
public investments for which it. is responsible wholly or in part<br />
that there must be a proper economic and environmental study<br />
and that that study should be published. Nobody doubts the<br />
economic aspects of the pipeline from South Australia to<br />
New South Wales which will be the first enterprise undertaken </p>
<p>by the Authority. The environmental aspect is still under study<br />
by the appropriate New South Wales authority and the relevant<br />
Australian Ministers had evidence or submissions nade to that<br />
New South W/ ales authority. It's decision I believe has not yet<br />
been delivered.<br />
Q: Have you made any representations to the British Government<br />
about their treatment of the State Premiers or their<br />
representatives in London? Have you reminded the British<br />
Government that there is only one Australian Government<br />
and that it resides in Canberra?<br />
PRIL!' E I: NISTER: I hope you'll forgive me if I don't want uo<br />
say what representations pass or in what form representations<br />
pass between me and other Heads of Government. I believe that<br />
the British Government takes the attitude today that it has for<br />
a long time past that there is one Australian Government.<br />
It becomes farcical if the British Government were to deal<br />
individually with such members of the Commonwealth as are<br />
federal nations such as Canada, Australia, India and i1alaysia.<br />
International business becomes anarchic if national Governments<br />
don't deal :. ith each other.<br />
Q: Just to revert back to resources policy, yesterday in<br />
Sydney the Chairman of Queensland Uranium told his annual<br />
general meeting the '! hitlam Government had written after<br />
December 2 assuring his Company that all the agreements in<br />
respect of Iarbolic entered into by the previous Government<br />
would be honoured by this Government. Now this seens to cut<br />
across your policies expressed at the election in respect of<br />
the environment I understand there is something about<br />
national parks up there and also in respect of Aborigines<br />
I just wondered what the position is in respect of Queensland<br />
Uranium. Is it correct that your Government will honour these<br />
agreements? PRI?'. E 1VINISTLR: I didn't see the statement. I don't remember<br />
writing to them. I don't remember having any conversation<br />
with any of their representatives. But as a general proposition<br />
naturally the incoming Australian Government honours obligations<br />
which its predecessors entered into. There are some cases,<br />
and Mr Connor is the proper one to give you the details, ; here<br />
there were arrangements between the preceeding Australian<br />
Government and some of the State Governments with various<br />
companies. And as I understand the position those companies<br />
haven't honoured their part of those arrangements. They have<br />
failed, or in fact refused, to give the information to the<br />
State and Australian Government, which they undertook ; c provide.<br />
Mr Connor very properly is requiring that information tc be<br />
given. I don't remember the Naborlic instance.<br />
Q: In view of your statement last week that the Federal<br />
Liberal Party had to get on the wave length for the future....?<br />
PRILE MINISTER: I was quoting I think what -Ir Snedden<br />
said the first time he contested the leadershic of the Liberal<br />
Party. Isn't that right? I think Mr Chipp was his public<br />
relations man at the time and devised that memorable phrase...<br />
Q: Do you think that Mr Fraser would be a disaster as leader of<br />
the Federal Liberal ] arty? </p>
<p>PRIIJ[ MIlISTER: I don't think one ought to engage into<br />
speculation or at least it must be relevant speculation.<br />
As I understand it Mr Fraser's nose is at present out of joint<br />
because a romance has developed between the old prostitute of<br />
the Country Party and the D. L. P. He was aiming to be the head<br />
of a great conservative coalition in Australia. 14ow frankly<br />
gentlemen, I don't want to speculate as to who is going to be<br />
head of the household when the old harlot is churched.<br />
Q: ( Overseas Press Fingleton)<br />
Q: Overseas Press?<br />
Q: ? Iell in this case with your indulgence.., his Lordship<br />
as it were, the Baron of Fleet. You have just mentioned<br />
prostitutes and harlots Sir. You've disowned the state Premiers.<br />
PRI11L 1MINISTER: No, wait a bit, I'm not saying any of them<br />
have fallen into that category. It was a memorable Premier of<br />
Victoria, Sir Henry Lolte, who described the Country 1Party<br />
as a prostitute. Not only in that, but an old one.<br />
Q: cir, have you seen fit to warn the Premiers at present in<br />
London of the inherent dangers that lurk there?<br />
PRI11I iINISTER: I think the only Premiers there are conservative<br />
ones and it's the Tories who seem to fall for the threats in<br />
London. Q: They've found out-let's put it that way. Sir, that's not<br />
my question. The British Prime Minister, Mir Heath visited " aris<br />
last week. Did you get the impression during your talks with<br />
Mr Heath in London that he would strongly support the Australian-<br />
New Zealand protest against the French nuclear tests. The<br />
London Daily Times which is owned. by his Lordship says editorially<br />
that it doubts whether he did convey to the French any serious<br />
criticism of the tests. It says further, the British cultivation<br />
of good terms with France combined with British sensitivity to<br />
the charge of hypocrisy since Britain already possesses nuclear<br />
weapons. Did 1r Heath give you any encouragement? Did be,<br />
to use a word of Mr Chifley, duchess you? And finally Sir, the<br />
last question the ban on French trade. Does this mean the end<br />
of the Concorde as far as Qantas is concerned?<br />
PRIIE I. MINISTER: On the Concorde: that's an English as much<br />
as a French aircraft. I don't want to express a view of the<br />
Concorde. It's a matter which I presume the Government will<br />
consider in due course. Now lir Heath did entertain me very well.<br />
lie's a good host. He's been cordial to me when he was Leader of<br />
the Opposition w; hen I was. And he is now, and this has been so<br />
when he's visited this bountry as Leader of the Opposition.<br />
Now that we are both Prime MIinisters we get on civily,<br />
courteously, cordially. But I didn't make more than passing<br />
reference to the French nuclear tests in our atmosphere.<br />
In my conversations with 1r Heath I was more concerned there<br />
with the matters of the abolition of appeals to the Privy Council,<br />
Britain no longer making her courts available for tice<br />
determination of disputes between Australian litigants.<br />
I discussed the matter of Britain's responsibility in<br />
this region with Sir Alec Douglas Home and HIr Anthony Royal.<br />
the men from the Foreign and Commonwealth Office. There were </p>
<p>officials around and so on. I didn't put the point of view<br />
on behalf of the Commonwealth countries in the South ' acific<br />
in the South Pacific Forum Australia, New Zealand, Fiji,<br />
Samoa, Tonga, Nauru, the Cook Islands who'. d asked me to<br />
take it up. I didn't put it on the basis that Britain has to<br />
argue our case. After all we are independent States. ' Je are<br />
able to do this and we should do it ourselves. The argument<br />
that I did put on behalf of the South Pacific Forum to<br />
Sir Alec Douglas Home and Mr Royal was that Britain had<br />
responsibilities in respect of non-self-governing territories<br />
in the region. Pitcairn Island, insignificant I suppose i*<br />
terms of population, but to the east of Mururoa Atoll, and<br />
also the Gilbert and Ellis Islands colony, the British Solomon<br />
Islands Protectorate and the Anglo-French Condominium of the<br />
New Hebrides. Now, I put on behalf of the Forum that Britain<br />
internationally had to speak for her wards in those territories.<br />
And I stressed that in our view she should do so. There may<br />
be another form of embarassment of course that Britain carried<br />
out these tests without any great Australian sensitivity twenty<br />
years ago in the ' ontebellos<br />
Q: Was there any harm?<br />
PRIM IEINISTER: Yes, there was. As you know it has only just<br />
been possible in the last year or so for people to land on the<br />
Hontebellos and then they also did so at Maralinga, and they<br />
also did so at the Christmas Islands in the Pacific not the<br />
Christmas Islands in the Indian Ocean. So I think Britain<br />
has a certain sensitivity on this because she was doing earlier,<br />
without complaint, as America did earlier again in the<br />
and so on, what France is now doing to the dismay of everybody<br />
in the world, not just in the South Pacific.<br />
Q: Last week Prime Minister, you stated that you believed in<br />
a career public service. Could you explain to me then why<br />
the job of scientific adviser in your own Department is not<br />
being advertised?<br />
PRIIE MINISTER: I thought it was being filled from the<br />
Public Service. I don't know. Thank you, I'll ask about this<br />
straight afterwards. Frankly I don't know the details of<br />
individual positions like this.<br />
Q: ir Prime Minister, on May 18 br Enderby said he would try<br />
to increase the margarine quota for the A. C. T. and continue to<br />
work for the abolition of the quota system. What is your<br />
Government's attitude to the margarine quota system. Are<br />
Mr Enderby's moves an attempt by your Government to break down<br />
the margarine quota system considering Marrickville Holdings<br />
can export margarine to other States?<br />
PRIME . INISTER: Mr Enderby and I think Senator ' Vriedt<br />
have alao been asked questions on this subject over the last<br />
fortnight. These matters have not been discussed in Cabinet<br />
so I can't express a collective view on it and I'm not<br />
ministerially responsible for it, but perhaps you vwould appreciate<br />
my expressing a personal view: I think it's quite absurd that a<br />
wholesome product in popular demand should be artificially<br />
denied to Australian consumers. As I understand it it's quite<br />
possible to make margarine in Australia from Australian products. </p>
<p>There can be no question that it is a healthful food, that it's<br />
not deleterious. I have no patience with those who want to<br />
restrict the production of proper foods from Australian products.<br />
Australia is way behind the times in this. There are a<br />
great number of other dairying countries where the : percentage of<br />
consumption of margarine vis a vis butter is, as I understand,<br />
much higher than in Australia. Now if a product's good it doesn't<br />
need rival products to be suppressed. N'ow that of course is a<br />
perfectly personal view.<br />
Q: What will happen at budget time to the present unique system<br />
of 7cinisters being required to virtually submit their Cabinet<br />
submissions to Caucus committees before these submissions go to<br />
Cabinet? RII.. 1-. INISTLR: It is impossible to summarise the procedure<br />
as briefly as you've done. Obviously there are practical factors<br />
which modify the summary that you've used.<br />
Q: senator Townley remarked yesterday or he was quoted as<br />
saying that he would be calling on 11ir Barbour from ASIC to<br />
appear before this Senate Select Committee. Has Cabinet<br />
considered the question of calling public servants, not only<br />
this Coimmittee, but any other subsequent committee, has it<br />
reached an attitude have you reached an attitude yourself<br />
on this. I believe there's been some approach in the past<br />
about this?<br />
T'RIIR* LINISTER: The Cabinet hasn't discussed this matter.<br />
If any Parliamentary Committee seeks the attendance of public<br />
servants then the-relevant M. inister would consider the position,<br />
if he wvas in doubt he would, I expect, consult his colleagues<br />
in the Cabinet. Now whether the Committee of which the ; enator<br />
you mentioned is Chairman he is not the Committee whether it<br />
seeks the attendance of the distinguished public employee whom<br />
you mention still has to be determined.<br />
Q: The Premiers in London are seeking an advisory opinion<br />
from the Privy Council on the legality of the Federal Government's<br />
offshore legislation...?<br />
PRI -L TINI STKR: Have they? They haven't told us.<br />
Q: this is what they've said their aim is. If they<br />
do that, will the Federal Governiment ; ut a case to the Privy<br />
Council, and, secondly a related matter, the Opposition has<br />
decided to delay this legislation for three months in the Senate.<br />
Would you regard such a delay as very important and, if so,<br />
what.. . how serious?<br />
ii-l' MINISTER: Do you mean to say the Opposition or some<br />
portions of it have resolved not to pass this legislation?<br />
That is, there will be another failure to pass... Which part of<br />
the Opposition has decided this?<br />
Q: The Liberal Party with the agreement of the others I<br />
understand. </p>
<p>PRI1i! 1 1. INISTER: The Senate Liberal Party or the whole<br />
Liberal Party. Gentlemen, these are so speculative, some<br />
fascinating possibilities arise and I certainly will watch them.<br />
Q: M-ay I ask you a personal question that's not serious...?<br />
PRIILa laINISTER: All the previous subjects that you've raised<br />
I hope they're not taken too seriously on this occasion...<br />
Q: You're putting me off a little when you become .1rime<br />
Minister of this great country, you also became ex officio<br />
a member of the Royal Canberra Golf Club...<br />
PRITEE MINISTER: Did I?<br />
Q: Indeed you did. It's the most picturesque course in<br />
Australia. Its woods abound with galaxies of glamorous and<br />
glorious birds this sort not that sort<br />
PRIME 1/ IIISTER: So my wife's told me. She plays there.<br />
Q: They keep on asking up there Sir, when is he coming.<br />
Will you Give thought in the recess to making your first<br />
appearance at this royal course and I hope the term royal<br />
doesn't put you off<br />
PRIME MINISTER: This is the first invitation I think I've<br />
had. Jack, take me there. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
