<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7572</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF DOORSTOP, ST THOMAS THE APOSTLE SCHOOL, KAMBAH 18 APRIL 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/04/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007572.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF DOORSTOP, ST THOMAS THE APOSTLE SCHOOL, KAMBAH<br />
18 APRIL 1989<br />
E OE PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: If the trend continues on the balance of<br />
payments do you don't think there'll be pressure on the<br />
currency today?<br />
PM: We'll leave that to the markets.<br />
JOURNALIST:, You don't think that you'll stop interest rates<br />
rising in the dollar?<br />
PM: I don't want to talk about that. The very subject<br />
you're talking about, what we'd do would of itself have an<br />
effect. I'm not into that business.<br />
JOURNALIST: The Opposition has said that you're trying to<br />
doctor the CPI figures.<br />
PM: Which opposition is that?<br />
JOURNALIST: That's the Federal Opposition.<br />
PM: But which part of it?<br />
JOURNALIST: In this case, Mr Peacock, if I can be specific.<br />
PM: I see. What's he said? All I've seen in the paper<br />
today is he's been telling Mr Howard how he should run the<br />
Party. JOURNALIST: He has said the Government is trying to doctor<br />
the CPI figures. Is that right?<br />
PM: No of course it's not right. It's not right at all.<br />
We wouldn't be doing that. The Statistician is independent.<br />
A number of people have pointed out to the Statistician the<br />
impact, the unusual impact of the movement in the housing<br />
prices and it did involve the assumption that every<br />
Australian family was buying a new house every quarter. I<br />
think that's not the case. I don't buy a new house every<br />
quarter, I don't think you do, I don't think everyone else<br />
does. So it has been pointed out that that had some sort of<br />
impact. He may be taking that into account, if he is,<br />
that's sensible.<br />
JOURNALIST: If Mr McPhee runs as an independent, would you<br />
offer him Labor preferences?<br />
W </p>
<p>-2-<br />
PM: If Mr McPhee now that sounds dangerously like a<br />
hypothetical question. I usually don't answer them.<br />
JOURNALIST: The numbers indicate he's going to lose his<br />
preselection. That's the reality and he said that.<br />
PM: Yes, he said, I noticed, that there is a vicious<br />
campaign against him within the Liberal Party in Victoria,<br />
that they are a pack of losers. one thing that Mr Kroger<br />
and Mr McPheee agree on is that the Liberal Party are<br />
losers. They'll just have to go on with their blood letting<br />
and their fighting and their viciousness in their own ranks,<br />
we'll just go on with running the country.<br />
JOURNALIST: Roger Shipton has complained about a lack of<br />
loyalty Mr Hawke. Does that surprise you?<br />
0 PM: No it doesn't surprise me. Mr Howard does seem to have<br />
sort of flexible standards about intervention in his Party.<br />
He intervenes when his own, or what he regards as his own<br />
may be at risk, but where others like Mr McPhee or Mr<br />
Shipton are at risk he stands aloof, So there's not much<br />
loyalty there, but as I repeat, the very simple point is<br />
that the conservatives are deeply and bitterly divided, they<br />
don't like each other, they can't govern themselves. While<br />
they're like that they'll never be given the opportunity,<br />
nor should they, of governing this country.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
