<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>23648</transcript-id>
    <title>Government delivers on commitment to abolish the carbon tax</title>
    <prime-minister>Abbott, Tony</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130918 - 20150915</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/07/2014</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Coalition promised to abolish the Carbon Tax and today the Government has delivered on our promise.</p>
<p>Australian families and businesses will no longer be slugged by Labor’s Carbon Tax.</p>
<p>Scrapping the Carbon Tax is a foundation of the Government’s Economic Action Strategy.<br />
 <br />
Scrapping the Carbon Tax will save the average Australian household $550 a year.</p>
<p>Scrapping the Carbon Tax will take a cost burden off Australian businesses. It will make it easier for them to compete and create more jobs.</p>
<p>The Carbon Tax was a $9 billion a year hit on the Australian economy. Australian businesses either had to absorb the costs or pass it on the consumers.</p>
<p>Labor implemented the world’s biggest Carbon Tax and today Bill Shorten confirmed he will campaign for a Carbon Tax at the next election.</p>
<p>Despite what they say, Labor never supported scrapping the Carbon Tax. They voted against its repeal at every single opportunity.</p>
<p>Labor betrayed the Australian people when they introduced the Carbon Tax, and they have continued to betray the Australian people ever since.</p>
<p>Australian consumers and businesses will benefit from the repeal of the Carbon Tax.</p>
<p>The Government’s consumer watchdog, the ACCC, has been given the funding and power to ensure that savings are passed on to consumers.</p>
<p>These requirements are in addition to the ACCC’s strong price monitoring powers and will ensure that the Carbon Tax hit on every Australian family and business is removed.</p>
<p>The Government remains committed to taking action to tackle climate change but we’ll do it without Labor’s $9 billion Carbon Tax hit on the economy.</p>
<p>At the election, the Coalition made a pledge: to scrap the Carbon Tax, to stop the boats, to get the Budget back under control and to build the roads of the 21st century.</p>
<p>We are honouring our commitments to the Australian people and building a strong and prosperous economy for a safe and secure Australia.</p>
<p>17 July 2014</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
