<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>819</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: PM 79/1963  NSW COMMONWEALTH  CASH AND CONVERSION LOAN STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, SIR ROBERT MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/10/1963</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000819_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS: PM&gt; 9/ 1963<br />
NEW CO. MKONWVFALTHT C! ASVF AIUSJ T.<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, Sir Robert Menzies<br />
A new Commonwealth cash and conversion loan will<br />
open for subscription on Thursday, October<br />
Announcing this today, the Prime : inister and<br />
Chairman of the Australian Loan Council ( Sir Robert Menzies)<br />
said that the target for the cash loan will be œ 60 million.<br />
The securities to be offered in both the cash and conversion<br />
loans will have the same interest rates and maturity dates as<br />
those offered in the July 1963 cash loan but, in line with<br />
S the slight fall in yields which has occurred on the market<br />
since then, the prices at which the securities will be issued<br />
will be slightly higher than in July.<br />
0 The three securities which will be offered in the<br />
cash and conversion loans are as follows:-<br />
4-per cent July 1986 securities issued at par.<br />
4 per cint October 1973 secuirities issued at<br />
œ 99/ 12/ 6 to yield approxinlatJ.. y œ 4.5.11 per cent.<br />
per cent Jul. y 1966 secrLtzcs issued at<br />
œ 99/ 17/ 6 to yi&amp; ld approxij.:-atcly œ 3.16.0 per cent.<br />
Sir Robert noted that the last occasion on which<br />
long-term securities had been issued in a Commonwealth loan with<br />
S a yield of œ 4/ 10/ 0 per cent was in the November 1955 cash and<br />
conversion loan. He recalled that the 1986, 1973 and 1966<br />
securities offered yields of œ 4/ 11/ 1 per cent, œ 4/ 7/ 5 per cent,<br />
and œ 3/ 17/ 8 per cent respectively when they were issued in the<br />
July 1963 cash loan. Subscriptions to that loan totalled<br />
œ 74.5 million. In the case of the July cash loan, the Loan Council<br />
adopted an experiment whoruby the loan remilned open for eight<br />
days only. As this arrangement proved succaessful, and did not<br />
appear to cause any inconvenience to investors, it will be<br />
continued for the new cash loan, which will close on Thursday, </p>
<p>-2-<br />
October 17. The conversion loan will open on Tuesday,<br />
October Special Bonds Series I, which came on issue on H'. ay<br />
16 last, will continue to be available for subscription until<br />
further notice. Sir Robert invited holders of œ 144.3 million 3-8p1e r<br />
cent securities maturing on October 15 to convert their investments<br />
into the new loan securities or into Special Bonds Series<br />
I. The maturing securities were offered for subscription in<br />
1949, and are widely held throughout the community.<br />
The minimum subscription to the Commonwe~ alth loan and<br />
0 to Special Bonds Series I will be œ 10, and there will be, as<br />
before, a limit of œ, 10,000 on overall holdings by any person or<br />
institution of Special Bonds Series A-I combined.<br />
The usual income tax rebate of in the œ will apply<br />
to interest from the new loan securities and from Special Bonds<br />
Series I included in taxable income. Those and other detailed<br />
terms and conditions for the new loan are set out fully in<br />
prospectuses which are now being circulated to all banks and<br />
0 stockbrokers, and will also be explained further in newspaper<br />
advertisements. Canberra, A. C. T.<br />
1st October, 1963. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
