<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>407</transcript-id>
    <title>BROADCAST NO.4 - BROADCAST BY THE PRIME MINISTER (RT. HON. R G MENZIES) OVER NATIONAL STATIONS AT 7.15PM MONDAY 27TH NOVEMBER 1961 - DEVELOPMENT</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/11/1961</release-date>
    <release-type>Broadcast</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000407_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
_._ BROADCAST NO,<br />
BROADCAST BY THE-! RIME EINISTER ( RT. HON. RG. MENZIES)<br />
Over NATIONAL STATIONS at 7.15 p. m. MONDAY,<br />
27TH NOVEIIER 1961<br />
DEVELOPMENT<br />
As the election campaign goes on, it becomes more and<br />
more clear that there is a basic difference between Government and<br />
Opposition in their approach to the national problems. I can best<br />
illustrate this by referring to our well-known policy of national<br />
development a policy which we have been pursuing with great<br />
vigour, and in relation to which we have already accepted<br />
substantial additional obligations over the next few years. I<br />
refer to the West Australian iron ore, iron and steel, and railways<br />
scheme, Beef Roads in the north, improved coal ports, and the like.<br />
From our point of view, the great continuing policy of<br />
works for development, particularly those calculated to earn more<br />
* export income and save imports, is essential. It provides a<br />
foundation upon which everything else stands. For when you<br />
develop our country, whether in minerals or water supply or power<br />
or transport or heavy industrics or more intensive production from<br />
the soil, you are doing something which increases the national<br />
Swealth and the national income and enables living standards to<br />
rise and makes it financially possible for a Government to<br />
increase social services and other cor= unity benefits. We regard<br />
national development as the cause, and improving social benefits<br />
as the result. Labour seems to start at the other end. Mr. Calwell<br />
has been complimented in some quarters for putting forward a<br />
constructive policy. Yet that policy is, in reality, a string<br />
of financial promises and hand-outs ha" ing for the most part<br />
little or nothing to do with the development of the nation's<br />
resources. His approach is, therefore, fundamentally different<br />
from ours. We have shown, and will show, that great works of<br />
development must be based upon economic stability and the<br />
encouragement of investment, and that only such a policy can give<br />
rise to increased employment and wealth and growing social<br />
advantages. The Calwell policy, so far fron being constructive, is<br />
in reality destructive. It will check national development because<br />
it is grossly inflationary, and will, therefore, lower living<br />
standards and operate against effective saving and investment in<br />
Australia. If he won this election it is quite clear that the<br />
more he attempted to put his policy into operation, and the<br />
greater the rate of inflation became, the slower would be the<br />
rate of national progress and the greater the difficulty of<br />
honouring the rest of his promises.<br />
Now it must be said for us that we hxve very seldom<br />
made election promises in relation to what I will call broadly<br />
" social services". We have simply known . and determined that these<br />
would be improved as the national capacity to provide them<br />
becpaec greater. And wh. at has been the result?. </p>
<p>2.<br />
I hate to weary you with figures, but the ones I am<br />
about to give you tare quite rum. rkablu. Wlhen the Labour Party<br />
was defeated in 1949, having had up to that time a clcar majority<br />
in both Houses of Parli-~ nt, and being therefore able to put its<br />
policies into force, it . as spending œ 85n. on social services. In<br />
the current year we are finding œ 273m.. But there are great<br />
additional items. When they went out they were finding œ 6.3n. for<br />
hospital beneofits wve re now finding œ 23n. They were finding<br />
nothing for mldical benefits we are finding œ 16m. They were<br />
finding less than half a million for pharmaceutical bunefits this<br />
year we are finding There are other similar ite-s, such as<br />
tuberculosis benefits and the nutrition of children. Add all these<br />
up and the simple fact is that in the whole of what I will call<br />
the " hoalth field" they were finding in 1929 we are, in<br />
1961, finding œ 8mn. Those latter figures includu two remarkable<br />
benefits for old age pensionors over nud above the actual amount<br />
of their pensions of œ 4.8n. for mudical services and œ 9.3m. for<br />
pharmaccutical bcnciits, or a total of œ 1. n.<br />
Now I want to s-y to you that this record, which puts<br />
La: bour's present electioJuaring protestations and pronisos in<br />
their true light, could not have been achieved unless, und-jr our<br />
overall policies of development and high public credit and<br />
investmecnt, both domestic and fron abroad, the gross national<br />
product had risen fromn 2,729-. in 1949 to œ 7,208. this year.<br />
You see wha. t I man? The cxpansion of the resources of the<br />
nation ha. s -ade it possible soundly and justly to increase the<br />
benefits coming to citizens. You cannot, without inviting<br />
d: ioa3lor, put tChriIt' p'Jp. pi) ico ' i. fln r:: t. nrtu by saying, as Labour<br />
appears to say, that the individual benefits create the national<br />
vealth. In our torn of office, as a result of these basic<br />
policies, Lustralia has bccone, ong other things, the tenth<br />
Sretcast traing nation in the world. For that is what has<br />
enabled its living sta. ndardLs and its social services to grow.<br />
To put this in the shortest possible t r s we believe<br />
that a nation must create before it can distribute, and it . must<br />
earn before it can pay out. We have . lr ady, as I have said,<br />
plcdgod over the njxt three years vury largo sums of roney to<br />
wiorks of national doveloprcent. Our oconomy will need to be strong<br />
and stable to sustain and forvm. rd these enterprises, to say<br />
nothing of others which will emerg. Yet, Calwoll lighth.<br />
artedly proposes to add hundreds of : illions more each year over<br />
and above the lready c om: iitted C-overn ment expcnditure iLnd, I<br />
repeat, the great bulk of his proiscs have nothing to dc with<br />
dcvelop-ment cr with the creation of vwualth at all. He seems to me<br />
to be putting the cart before the horse. Indeed, so little<br />
attention does he pay to the basic probloe of building up this<br />
nation, that I begin to think that so long as his cert is full of<br />
glittering gifts ho does not think that a horse is necessary at<br />
all. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
