<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9610</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J.KEATING, MP LAUNCH OF ONE NATION TRAIN, MELBOURNE, 4 JUNE 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/06/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009610.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
A<br />
' I<br />
S. n<br />
PRIME MINISTER ** CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY"*<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING, MP<br />
LAUNCH OF ONE NATION TRAIN, MELBOURNE, 4 JUNE 1995<br />
1 think we might all be forgiven a smile of satisfaction today. From Tom<br />
Hopkins who is 103 and first dreamt about this while driving locomotives<br />
before the rest of us were born; to Gough Whitlam who is younger than Tom<br />
but no less a dreamer of great things for Australia; to those of my own<br />
generation who came to believe in them too and find ourselves privileged to<br />
be the people who finally did it.<br />
This is a great day for Australia and nothing less.<br />
A standard gauge rail highway from Brisbane to Perth is a century old<br />
Australian dream today it's an Australian reality.<br />
Three years ago when we delivered a statement called One Nation. We<br />
called it One Nation because we wanted to assert a simple idea that we are<br />
stronger when we work as one.<br />
One Nation imagined a stronger Australia an Australia that worked more<br />
efficiently. The aim was to close the gaps between Australians the physical<br />
gaps and the cultural ones.<br />
To close them with railway lines and better road and airline systems; to close<br />
them by social undertakings to help Australians on margins; and to close<br />
them by reminding Australian men and women that for all the distance which<br />
divides a West Australian from a Victorian or a South Australian from a<br />
Queenslander, or a suburb of Sydney from a farm in Tasmania, we are all<br />
Australians and we share a great common interest.<br />
One Nation aimed at making Australia stronger and fairer. </p>
<p>And I think in the past three years we have made a lot of progress in this<br />
direction we've got extraordinary growth in jobs and national economic<br />
growth, we've got a new national training system, we've got nationwide labour<br />
market programs, we've got a national competition policy, we've got the kind<br />
of agreement on national goals we haven't had in a long time and we've got<br />
a six and a half thousand kilometre standard gauge national rail highway from<br />
Brisbane to Perth via Sydney, Melbourne and Adelaide.<br />
There is nothing like a train.<br />
There is no symbol of progress like it. No symbol of unity like it no symbol<br />
of strength.<br />
But of course this One Nation train is much more than a great symbol.<br />
It brings all Australians much closer together in a material way.<br />
It will produce material benefits.<br />
It will give us in the next century what we have been denied in this an<br />
efficient national rail system.<br />
Over three years we have spent $ 429 million to upgrade and invigorate<br />
Australia's rail infrastructure.<br />
We erected new bridges which could support greater loads travelling at<br />
greater speeds.<br />
We added crossing loops in key locations to eliminate delays.<br />
We laid new low-maintenance sleepers, and constructed new track<br />
alignments with fewer tight curves and flatter grades for a better ride.<br />
The centrepiece of the rail infrastructure investment program was the<br />
standardisation of the line between Melbourne and Adelaide the missing link<br />
in a national standard-gauge rail network. And that's what we celebrate<br />
today. Sixty kilometres of new track has been built, 30 kilometres converted to dual<br />
gauge, and 740 kilometres regauged by moving the rails 6.5 inches closer<br />
together.<br />
We now have a great national asset.<br />
With the National Rail Highway we can more fully harness the energy of<br />
Australia. </p>
<p>It will buttress economic development and make us more flexible and<br />
competitive. As our industry increasingly adopts a national dimension, so will<br />
it be serviced by a truly national rail freight system.<br />
Trains will be longer and their travel time shorter. The One Nation train slices<br />
two hours off the Melbourne-Adelaide leg and eight hours off the Melbourne-<br />
Perth trip.<br />
It untangles Australia's railway tracks.<br />
And it enables us to put the interstate rail freight system on a much more<br />
efficient and competitive footing.<br />
With the support of the States, we established the National Rail Corporation,<br />
so that interstate shippers need only deal with one organisation rather than<br />
four when moving goods around the country.<br />
National Rail has set about renovating the institutional culture and work<br />
practices of the Australian rail industry. With a ground-breaking enterprise<br />
agreement and the introduction of best practices, the interstate rail freight<br />
industry has been turned around.<br />
And it will shortly be acquiring a lot more horsepower in the form of $ 400<br />
million worth of new locomotives.<br />
Locomotives which will be built and maintained in Australia: an investment<br />
which is expected to create in excess of one thousand jobs. And the new<br />
locos will be vastly more fuel efficient than the current fleet.<br />
The Government is determined to press forward with efficiency gains. And<br />
the surest way to increase in the railways is to promote competition on the<br />
line. That's why the Minister for Transport has proposed that all the interstate track<br />
be managed by a single organisation, Track Australia, ensuring competition<br />
between existing and new rail operators.<br />
That leaves rail operators to concentrate on the customers.<br />
We devised One Nation to get Australia moving. One element of that was to<br />
make the railways run more smoothly. But the commitment also required that<br />
we improve air, sea and road transport, and dovetail them all together.<br />
Today, after three years of work, the Australian people have a far more<br />
integrated and cohesive transport system than ever before.<br />
We have safer national roads, more efficient ports and a better aviation<br />
system. And all these modes of transport are linked to each other. </p>
<p>This Dynon Road Freight Terminal is a good illustration of the distance we've<br />
come in a very short time.<br />
Before the One Nation investments the place was heavily under-capitalised<br />
and lacked both effective lifting equipment and long tracks for the efficient<br />
assembly of trains.<br />
Now, the Terminal has new assembly tracks and highly effective mobile<br />
gantries. And the whole operation is safer and better lit.<br />
Before One Nation, containers arriving at the docks and destined for the rail<br />
station had to be driven along a roundabout route of 2.5km, crossing<br />
Footscray Road, the busiest truck corridor in Victoria.<br />
Now, goods are delivered straight to the tracks via the newly-built Dock Link<br />
Road. The Road cost $ 5 million, and it paid for itself within weeks of opening.<br />
National Rail estimates a saving of $ 20 per container.<br />
So this is One Nation at work.<br />
And it means we can transport people and freight across the continent and<br />
get it onto ships or planes for export faster, cheaper and more reliably.<br />
The train I am about to board the One Nation train will be first to cross the<br />
continent, via all State capitals, without interruption from break of gauge.<br />
Construction of the national rail highway began a long time ago, and as I said<br />
we are privileged to be part of the generation which completed it.<br />
It has been a difficult journey. But then, the most worthwhile things are very<br />
often the most difficult.<br />
Many people deserve our congratulations today.<br />
I've mentioned Gough Whitlam, who has never let up in his pursuit of national<br />
gauge compatibility. Let me also pay tribute to Laurie Brereton, the Minister<br />
who got the work done on time and on budget.<br />
And speaking of work, let me thank the men and women of National Rail who<br />
planned and co-ordinated the gauge standardisation.<br />
And let me also thank everyone of those 3000 Australians who did the hard<br />
physical tasks of the project.<br />
I hope today that their satisfactions matches that of their fellow railway worker<br />
from another age who is with us today Tom Hopkins. </p>
<p>Today is special because we have all been a part of a very long chapter in<br />
Australia's story. And when we say that today we have ended the chapter,<br />
we recognise that before us came countless Australians who down the years<br />
worked towards the same goal and dreamt the same dream.<br />
Our own and future generations of Australians will benefit from this One<br />
Nation train, but I think we should launch it in the name of all those who came<br />
before us.<br />
As the train leaves Melbourne and moves on to Adelaide and Perth, Australia<br />
will move with it.<br />
It will bring Australians closer together, it will make Australia stronger.<br />
And I hope it will inspire us to believe that much more in what we can do<br />
when we think, plan and work as one nation.<br />
Thank you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
