<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5825</transcript-id>
    <title>TELEVISION ANNOUNCEMENT TODAY OF LAUNCH OF THE AUSTRALIAN YAR OF THE TREE</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/06/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005825.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
A~ USTRALIA. JL<br />
FOR MEDIA SATURDAY, JUNE 5 1982<br />
TELEVISION ANNOUNCEMENT TODAY OF<br />
LAUNCH OF THE AUSTRALIAN YEAR-OF THE TREE<br />
( One Minute Statement)<br />
On World Environment Day, the United Nations Association<br />
of Australia launched the Year of the Tree.<br />
Trees soften the hard edge of the city landscape, clean<br />
the air and provide a buffer agaiLnst noise. They are<br />
important to the farmer. They provide a renewable source<br />
of valuable materials and, of course, they provide a home<br />
for Australia's unique wildlife.<br />
Unfortunately, there are fewer and fewer trees in Australia<br />
despite the planting and conservation efforts of governments<br />
organisations and individuals. Tree decline affects the<br />
standard of living of all Australians. A major national<br />
tree programme is one of the proposals for the Australian<br />
Bi-Centenary in 1988.<br />
Over the next year the Government will make a start with a<br />
pilot project to cost half a million dollars. Apart from<br />
helping the Year of the Tree campaign, the Government will<br />
encourage people across Australia to learn about trees, to<br />
plant them and to care for them. There will be demonstration<br />
projects on tree planting and support for national communitybased<br />
activities.<br />
Trees are an important part of our heritage. The Year of the<br />
Tree deserves and needs the support of all Australians. / 2 r-I </p>
<p>-2-<br />
PRIME MINISTER'S ADDRESS<br />
( Five Minute Film)<br />
On World Environment Day the United Nations Association of<br />
Australia launched the Year of the Tree.<br />
They are part of the uniqueness of our national heritage.<br />
Trees help farmers to maintain and even increase the<br />
productivity of land halting the loss of water and soil.<br />
Although our timber and paper come from trees, modern<br />
forestry can ensure that those trees are renewed.<br />
Few city dwellers can deny that trees soften the hard edge<br />
of the urban. landscape. Their shade is welcome on a hot and<br />
sunny day. They even help buffer the noise of traffic.<br />
For our native animals they're much more than something<br />
beautiful. to) look at: indeed they're essential for the<br />
survival of most species.<br />
Unfortunately, there are fewer and fewer trees in Australia,<br />
despite the planting and conservation efforts of Governments,<br />
organisations and individuals. Vast areas of forest and<br />
bushland have been cleared for farming, roads, power lines<br />
and towns. Trees are still being l. ost through land clearing,<br />
and also through soil erosion and salinity, disease and fire.<br />
The loss of our trees has now reached a critical stage.<br />
Less than 5% of the nation is now covered, and there are<br />
many serious local problems. Tree decline affects the standard<br />
of living ofE all Australians. It reduces the productivity of<br />
land, lowers rainfall, and degrades the environment.<br />
A major national tree programme is one of the proposals for<br />
the Australian Bicentenary in 1988. Over the next year the<br />
Government wdill make a start with a pilot project to cost half'<br />
a million . dollars. Apart from helping the Year of the Tree<br />
campaign, the Government will encourage people across Australia<br />
to learn about trees, to plant them and to care for them.<br />
There will be demonstration projects on tree planting and<br />
support for national community-based activities.<br />
You can plant and conserve trees use only waste timber<br />
for firewood respect fire restrictions and save<br />
newspapers and cartons for recycling.<br />
Trees are for our future. They're for the future of our<br />
children and for the future of their children. The Government<br />
can help, but to be successful, to ensure a successful future,<br />
every one of us needs to be involved. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
