<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2318</transcript-id>
    <title>CONSTRUCTION OF COCKBURN SOUND NAVAL BASE - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR JOHN GORTON</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/10/1970</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002318.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS: 7M No 1970<br />
CONSTRUCTION O CKBUN SOUND NAVAL BASE<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, Mr. John Gorton<br />
The Government has approved plans for the censtruction, over<br />
five years, of the second stage of Naval Support Facilities at Coczburn Sound,<br />
Western Australia. It is proposed to provide base facilities capable of supporting four<br />
escort vessels and three submarines for periods up to a year without dry<br />
docking. Capital works will include the wharf and service area, dredged<br />
basin area, workshops and stores buildings, engineering services, barracks,<br />
hou., ing, and a jetty and armament depot.<br />
The Base will enable ships to operate in the Indian Ocean and will<br />
significantly increase the flexibility of our Naval Forces.<br />
I am glad to say that the decision has met with warm approval in<br />
Britain and the United States.<br />
The British Minister for Defence has sent us a message which<br />
reads " I confirm that my Government warmly welcomes your intention to establish<br />
a Naval Facility at such a strategic point, which underlines the extent-to which<br />
the threat posed by the Soviet maritime presence in the Indian Ocean, and the<br />
need to keep all the sea-lanes in that area open is being recognised by the nations<br />
of the free world." The United States Secretary of Defence has written " Your stated<br />
intention to develop a naval base in Western Australia is most welcome<br />
The timeliness of a decision to move ahead with a Cockburn Sound Base is<br />
accentuated by the burgeoning Soviet interest in the Indian Ocean and its appruc s,"<br />
Thus the naval construction approved as part of Australia's own<br />
defences is seen by our allies who will be able to use the Base if they wish to<br />
as an advancement of the common interest in contributing to security in the<br />
Indian Ocean.<br />
CANBERRA Octcber 1970<br />
NOTE.-Text of message from Secr tory Laird attached. </p>
<p>COCKBURN SOUND<br />
Text of Messalefo Se rar La ird<br />
The United States recognizes fully the important security<br />
contributions Australia is making to free world defense in the Southwe -at<br />
Pacific and Indian Ocean areas. Your stated intention to develoY. a Naval<br />
Base in Western Australia is most welcome.<br />
The generous offer to open. such a facility to ships of the U. S.<br />
Navy is indeed gratifying; such a base would play an important role L_ U. S.<br />
contingency planning for the region; and as operational requirements or<br />
opportunities may arise, we would make use of the port.<br />
The timeliness of a decision to move ahead with a Cockburn,<br />
Sound Base is accentuated by the burgeoning Soviet interest in the India-,-,<br />
Oce-n and its approaches. The current Soviet interest in Singapore, thea<br />
growing number , of their vessels visiting ports of the Indian Ocean, littoral,<br />
and the historic Soviet desire to exercise control over the Suez area comrbine<br />
to indicate that the free World's interests in the Southwest Pacific India-,-<br />
Ocean area may encounter serious new challenges in the future. An<br />
Australian Naval Base at Cockburn Sound could afford a valuable position<br />
from which manifestations of such a threat could be observed arAd, if<br />
necessary, countered. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
