<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8389</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J. KEATING MP PRESS CONFERENCE, SYDNEY 21 JANUARY 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/01/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008389.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
-E &amp; OE PROOF COPY ONLY<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE MON P. J. KEATING PILJ<br />
PRESS CONFERENCE, SYDNEY 21 JANUARY 1992<br />
PM: Well thank you for coming, look I have got to keep it<br />
brief because I have still got a meeting in progress<br />
which I have to go back to, so just to give you a few<br />
thoughts about processes to date. I think it is fair to<br />
say our discussions with the business community and the<br />
trade union have been exceptionally encouraging. I<br />
think most Australians will be pleased to know, it will<br />
be music to their ears to know, that most business<br />
community' representatives w've met all in fact want to<br />
get Australia moving again. There is not a lot of<br />
ideology in these conversations. If we were having them<br />
a few years ago there would be a lot of ideology being<br />
spoken thats now been almost completely removed and<br />
businesses and their representatives are basically<br />
saying what have we got to do to get the place moving<br />
again,' putting ideas, ideas which we will consider and<br />
which a group of ministers I mentioned to you a week or<br />
two ago will be sitting to consider in the next few<br />
weeks., As I said to you we have been working in a frame<br />
work ourselves, much of what has been said to us have<br />
been complementary to that framework some things<br />
haven't. They have been new and different and we are<br />
going to consider them as well. So it has been a very<br />
refreshing process. Government always believes of<br />
course that they get to hear about it some stage or<br />
another well, sometimes you don't. There are some<br />
things that just don't filter down through the<br />
ministerial system or the bureaucratic system and I have<br />
found, I am sure my colleagues have as well found, the<br />
process very engaging. So I1 would be happy to take<br />
questions. </p>
<p>Can : you clarify with us a wage tax trade<br />
PM: Well nothing is off the agenda, we are looking at<br />
everything and prepared to but nor are we about to try<br />
and, if you like, push funds on the trade union<br />
movement, we are not about to be doing that either.<br />
Fundii are to scarce to be trying to give them away<br />
witho~ ut some results. So again, it is something worthy<br />
of cansideration but it Is not something which the<br />
government at this moment in time plans to do.<br />
J: Mr Keating Westpac today seemed to echo what was said<br />
last week to you that the market could live with fis; cal<br />
stimulus to the value of about $ 2 billion. is that your<br />
view?<br />
PM: Well I don't have a view that precise, I think, about<br />
banks and their economics and their econometrics<br />
departments, they can get down to these nice precise<br />
numbers but, at least they are making it clear that they<br />
believe that as a major institution and representing I<br />
think a lot of market view that some fiscal stimulus is<br />
appropriate beyond simply that coming of f interest<br />
rates..<br />
J: Mr Keating what you were saying before does that mean<br />
that you are unlikely to looking....... the tax deal in<br />
the lead up to the economic statement but you could be<br />
looking at it in the lead up to the Budget?<br />
PM: Yes it could be either, that's right.<br />
Could it be on the agenda at the forthcoming<br />
PM: It could be that the unions are prepared to take their<br />
chances in the market place, or in the longer term with<br />
a comm: Lsison, it is up to them really.<br />
J: PM:. No, I think there was a certain similarity actually in<br />
their demeanor and their content I couldn't assume much<br />
but the one thread running through it was that they all.<br />
want to get the place moving.<br />
J7: Mr Keating what happened to the ideology?<br />
PM: Well T think the ideology was regarded as superfluous<br />
and maybe a luxury for better times, and now they take<br />
the view that times require a close asosement of what<br />
the traffic will bare, you know whats possible and the<br />
ideology has sort of disappeared. </p>
<p>J; Mr Keating there is still talk of a second quarter rate<br />
cut. If the economy hasn't started to recover by then<br />
do you see room for another cut?<br />
PM: I am not speculating about interest rates.<br />
own opinion?<br />
PM: About ideology well I don't think this has been an<br />
ideological Government at any stage in its history. It<br />
was, after all, a Labor Government that introduced a<br />
market economy to Australia. I mean again I think it<br />
has ahown the fact that it is not ideological. It has<br />
intorests and it has probably, in many respects,<br />
permanent iinterests, but it has not been subject to that<br />
sort; of craven ideology, and I think this has been<br />
largely true of the business community in the last<br />
decade. It is certainly true of themi now.<br />
J: Mr Kenting there was a fresh report today<br />
What is your current view on sectoral policy?<br />
PM: The trouble is they all mean different things to<br />
different people. The word ' sectoral' means different<br />
things to different people I think, and I think, in<br />
certainly my view, and I think it is the view of many<br />
meinebers of Government, that Australia does have<br />
particular strengths and we ought to cater for those<br />
strengths. We ought to support those strengths, but not<br />
by way of production subsidies and some of the elements<br />
abounded of protection which in years gone by. So it is<br />
a mfatter of whether you think that some of the general<br />
directions we take are the ones we ought to be taking,<br />
whether we take impediments out of the road, whether we<br />
do things which progress the lot of those industries or<br />
those sectors as destinct from doing much more<br />
particular and direct things which we have turned our<br />
back from. </p>
<p>J: ( inaudible)<br />
PM: Well again, you know if you think minerals and minerals<br />
processing is something for Austraiia to be in, then<br />
generally policy should accommodate it. We generally<br />
have. Generally policy has, for instance. But there<br />
is a whole lot of difference I think between that and<br />
production subsidies or particular, if you like, export<br />
related subsidies and all of the other things which are<br />
generally GATT unfriendly and which are protection of<br />
the! old variety.<br />
J: Mr Keating, Dr Hewson says your comitints on immigration<br />
today relating to the Liberal Party were a slur. He is<br />
calling on you to withdraw them and to apologise. Will<br />
you do that?<br />
PM: Well he shouldn't be running on these Issues if he<br />
doesn't mean them. I mean, he had Mr Howard up the<br />
other day saying we ought to cut the migration program<br />
to pieces. it was Mr Howard who was addressing himself<br />
to this. subject in 1988. 1 mean, they are bacX onto it<br />
now, not in the same vein, but I didn't say they were.<br />
So there is nothing to apologise over.<br />
J: But you did accuse them of a sub plot, a racist sub<br />
plot?<br />
PM: No what I said was, there is a sub debate, there was a<br />
sub debate in Australia. Whether it is quite in<br />
evidence that it was in 1988, 1 don't know. But the<br />
fact of the matter is the program, governments have got<br />
to make a judgement of what is in the best interests of<br />
Australia as a nation in the short and medium term.<br />
AndT-that is where the right judgements and how the<br />
judgements should be made in relation to migration.<br />
J: But isn't there room for a debate on immigration given<br />
the recession?<br />
PM: I think there is. Yes there is. But a debate and<br />
Jingoism are two different things. And craven appeals<br />
by Mr Howard to rip the program to shreds is jingoism.<br />
J: Mr X'eating, just getting back to tax cuts. Do you<br />
think that tax cuts ( inaudible) in terms of a wage<br />
incr~ ease would La~ a good idea and direct the<br />
( inaudible) </p>
<p>PM: Well anything which reduces fiscal surplus or increases<br />
the deficit as the case may be is stimulatory of the<br />
economy, that is true. but whether that is the path we<br />
choose will depend, or whether it is one of the chosen<br />
paths, let me put it that way,. will depend upon what<br />
attitude we have to the Budget, what attitude the trade<br />
unions have to those arrangements etc. And right now<br />
we don't intend to have one.<br />
J: Do you think that the<br />
implemented over the next financial year that you will<br />
be stimulating import . following our<br />
picking up<br />
PM: I dLon't know that is right. Because there is not a lot<br />
of evidence from anybody that says that there is a pick<br />
up going on out there. No evidence in reality. And<br />
therefore I think that there is therefore not a great<br />
attendant risk that we will over-stimulate it. So,<br />
even in the terms which have been spoken about in the<br />
public debate. These are not things I think which are<br />
going to over-stimulate the economy. But the lag point<br />
is right, anything happens with the lag of course.<br />
J: ( inaudible)<br />
PM: Well we are not being deluged with evidence that there<br />
is a recovery under way.<br />
J: Mr Keating, you are going to meet Mr Greiner. A few<br />
days ago he attacked you for, he said, for rewarding<br />
Victoria which he described as an economic basket case,<br />
how do you react to that?<br />
PM: Oh--well that was a bit of State chauvinism. That is<br />
all. that is. We are not going to reward Victoria but<br />
it has to be borne in mind that Victoria has carried a<br />
large part of the burden ot structural change in<br />
Australia by virtue of the character of the city of<br />
Melbourne and its manufacturing base. So I don't think<br />
that that is, it certainly won't be my intention to<br />
reward one state, to use his word reward any State<br />
above another but to look at Australia as a nation and<br />
say what can we do which in the short term is<br />
sensible and for the long term, structural.<br />
j; How would you treat his request for $ 100 million for<br />
capital projects?<br />
Well he hasn't made them yet, but he probably will. He<br />
can make them for himself rather than you.<br />
J; Any ideas from the business leaders so far that have<br />
grabbed your attention? </p>
<p>PM: Yes. Quite a few, but I don't want to run acorss them<br />
here.<br />
J; How do you enjoy exposing yourself so much as Prime<br />
Minister, it must have different when you were<br />
Treasurer.<br />
PM: did a lot of this when I was Treasurer. I did a lot<br />
of these sorts of meetings. In fact, for eight years.<br />
It is just that I didn't normally have four television<br />
crews accompanying me and this great phalanx of<br />
journalists. But I still did them.<br />
J: What other differences are there apart from increased<br />
television crews?<br />
PM: Well I think one is required to listen to as broad a<br />
range of views as you can avail yourself of. Which we<br />
have tried to do. we have had representatives or<br />
small, medium, large business, unions, all sorts of<br />
organisations, and it is very good.<br />
J: Mr Keating, where would you expect the Special<br />
Premiers' Conference to and and<br />
what sort of measures do you<br />
PM: Well there are obviously on-going issues between the<br />
Commonwealth and the States, particularly about<br />
national efficiency. And they were not either seeking<br />
or swimming, so to speak, on the fiscal question, even<br />
though that is important to the States. so I should<br />
believe that much more can still be achieved in those<br />
areas and we will take that process up.<br />
J: And when will that be?<br />
PM: Probably, it will be well after the Statement and it<br />
will be probably before the middle of the year.<br />
J: Mr Keating, the latest Morgan Poll taken in November,<br />
shows that the majority of Australians blame the<br />
. overnment for unemployment. 75 per cent complained<br />
saying the u. overnment was not doing enough to relieve<br />
unemployment. Does that justify the decision taken by<br />
caucus to dump Bob Hawke for you as leader?<br />
PM: That is a judgement for you to make. Public<br />
perceptions about the recession are important. But the<br />
mnost important thing is to get out of recession and<br />
have the conversation about a recovery.<br />
J; Are you concerned about the prospect ot a brawl with Mr<br />
Hawke? </p>
<p>PM: Well look, in a change of public office of this<br />
dimension, there is always the interview that is done<br />
where the hard questions are asked and I tried to<br />
answer them honestly and sensibly and I can only repay<br />
Bob again, the compliment I paid him last night. That<br />
its to say, by any measure he was a good Prime Minister.<br />
He had eight years of office. I have had, sort of<br />
eight minutes of office. And I think therefore, his<br />
record is in that sense very free trom any swipe by<br />
anybody, but, better than that, subject to much<br />
compliment which I am very happy to pay him.<br />
J: HaS he contacted you about last night's interview?<br />
PM: No. I think you are all more interested than he is.<br />
Now, look, I have got to go now really,<br />
J: One m~ ore question. what is it like to tell your son<br />
about how to handle media?<br />
PM: Oh I haven't got time for that.<br />
J: Is there ( inaudible)<br />
PM: I don't normally qive daily commuentaries on the<br />
exchange rate. Do you work for a financial<br />
J: Yes. Dow Jones.<br />
PM: Oh do you. Good on you.<br />
ENDS </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
