<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10201</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP INTERVIEW WITH HOWARD SATTLER - RADIO 6PR</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/12/1996</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010201.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Fax from : 19/ 12/ 96 15: 28 Pg:<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
19 December 1996 TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THlE HON JOHN HOWARD MP<br />
INTERVIEW WITH HOWARD SAYJLER RADIO 6PR<br />
SAYFLER: Good morning to you Prime Minister-<br />
PRIE MIHiSTER:<br />
Good Morning Howard, it's always nice to be on your programme.<br />
SATITLER: All right, first question: How many points out of ten would you rate yours and the<br />
Government's performance for the first nine months?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Those sort of things are always hard to me and I just beg out of doing that. I think<br />
we've done very well. The most important thing is that all the major promises we<br />
made have been delivered on:-family tax, industrial relations reform, getting rid of<br />
unfair dismissal, small business benefits, health insurance rebates, Teistra, the Natural<br />
Heritage Trust. They were the promises that people remember from the campaign and<br />
every last one of them every last one of them have been delivered on. And I am<br />
very proud to go to Christmas being able to say to the Australian people that we have<br />
stayed true to the things that we promised them during the election campaign.<br />
SATILER: Okay, so you'll say that you've broken no election promises? </p>
<p>Fax from : 19/ 12/ 96 15: 28 Pg: 2<br />
PRIME MINISTER&amp;<br />
I will say that we have delivered on all of the major promises that we made.<br />
SATI1LER: Is there any more you could have done, anything that you'd like to have got up but<br />
you didn't achieve?<br />
PREIE NMNSTER:<br />
Well, if we hadn't have inherited a $ 10 billion underlying deficit from Mr Beazley we<br />
could have done even more. Given the fiscal inheritance we found when we came into<br />
Governent, contrary to what we've been told by the former government, given all of<br />
that we have done extraordinarily well to get the budget heading towards a balance<br />
and also to implement the promises that we made. And I'm very grateful for the<br />
stong finish we've had to the year; getting Telstra throug* getting 95 per cent of the<br />
budget legislation through; that Natural Heritage Trust will be of enormous benefit for<br />
the envirornent of Australia. And in a couple of years time when the money is<br />
flowing into things like the Murray Darling clean-up, the salt problem there'll be<br />
some resources going in to helping the Western Australian Government tackle the salt<br />
problem that Richard Court talked about during his campaign the Australian people<br />
will see us as a Government that is concerned about the long term environmental<br />
challenges and I'm very proud of that because it's a very important element of our<br />
plans for the 2 1st Century.<br />
SATTLER:<br />
I've got to ask you about that too what you inherited. Now, during the election<br />
campaign here in Western Australia the Court Government actually opened the books<br />
in the first Week of the campaign and said:,-this is the situation, these are the forward<br />
estimates, this is what is ahead. Now, that had not been done previously, and regularly<br />
new governments came in and sad:-look, look what we've inherited. Would you be<br />
planning to open the books of this government before the next election, during the<br />
campaign? PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Yes, we're going to do exactly the same thing. We promised during the last campaign<br />
there'd be a charter of budget honesty so that when the next federal election is called<br />
the books will be thrown open. The Treasury will say exactly where we stand and the<br />
public will be able to judge the promises of both the Government and the Opposition<br />
according to the figures that have been made available by the Treasury. So we will<br />
never again have the nonsense of the last campaign when both Mlr Keating and Mr<br />
Beazley said we were in surplus when they knew we were in deficit. I mean, that's the<br />
bottom ine. I mean, I was given the figures the day after the election in a big folder,<br />
they were already prepared. They were known to the former government. Now, that<br />
mustn't happen again and it won't happen again. And we are putting on ourselves a<br />
discipline. We're the Government, we don't have to pass the charter of budget </p>
<p>Fax fromv 19/ 12/ 96 15: 28 Pg: 3<br />
honesty but we're going to. And it will mean the public will, if they are told by the<br />
Treasury that the situation is Yx then they'll look at what I say and they'll look at what<br />
Mr Beazley says and they'll say:-well, you can't afford that but you can afford<br />
something else. Now, it will produce a much better result for the Australian public.<br />
SAITLER: Well, the two most divisive issues of the year, I think you would agree, have been the<br />
Sun control legislation and the race debate and you've probably copped more criticism<br />
over those two matters than any others do you think you could have handled them<br />
better? PRIM AMSTER:<br />
No, I would not have handled either issue differently if I had my time over again. We<br />
haven't had a race debate, we've had a debate about responses to a maiden speech by<br />
the Independent Member for Oxley. I'm not advocating, the Labor Party's not<br />
advocating we go back to a White. Australia policy. We passed a resolution saying that<br />
we've got a non-discriminatory immigration policy-But we are having a legitimate<br />
debate in the community about the level of immigration and people are entitled to<br />
debate that and they're entitled to debate what represents the Australian identity and<br />
things of that kind. But I just want to make it very clear on your programme as I<br />
have on other programimes as we come to the end of the year mine is a Government<br />
which is totally opposed to any kind of racial discrimination. Students from different<br />
parts of the world are welcome in our country. Malaysian students are welcome.<br />
Students from other parts of Asia are welcome. People from all around the world are<br />
welcome in this country. But like any other community we will decide how many<br />
people come into Australia and settle here permanently and we will decide the criteria<br />
that apply to immigrants to Australia.<br />
SATTLER; Yeah, but hasn't the race debate been a giant beat-up? I mean, yesterday there were<br />
stories about attacks and all that sort of thing. When you read into it you found that<br />
two people had been verbally accosted. Now, I'm not suggesting that that's good, and<br />
that's pretty awful, but compared with what we had here in the 80s with the Australian<br />
Nationalist Movement actually attacking restaurants in Perth, I mean, it's pretty mnild<br />
stuff, isn't it?<br />
PRIME NISTER:<br />
Well look, any kind of harassment of anybody is distressing and wrong and<br />
urkAustralian and unacceptable whatever the cause. Whether it's related to<br />
somebody's race or somebody's size or somebody's gender, whatever it is, it's<br />
repulsive to decent Australians and it's not the Australian way and it never will be.<br />
But I do believe that sections of the Australian media and other sections of the<br />
community have sort of kept this issue going. They talk about the race debate well,<br />
you don't have a race debate unless people are asserting in some way that one race is<br />
superior to another. Now, I don't hear any credible person asserting that, I don't, and </p>
<p>Fax from I certainly repudiate it absolutely. Mr Beazley does. Most Australians, overwvhelmning<br />
bulk of Australians, repudiate that kind of thing. I think we've had a massive<br />
overreaction from large sections of the press to this. We are a tolerant, harmonious<br />
society. We have a record of tolerance and harmony in this country which is really the<br />
envy of the rest of the world.<br />
SATITLER: We've had Hgh Commissioners telling Asian students ' don't go out at night'.<br />
We've had the Prime Minister of Malaysia saying that he might withdraw 11,000<br />
students. It's quite extraordinary.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Weft, I don't believe that will happen. I'm certain it won't happen and in any event, I<br />
just repeat what I said earlier. Students from that country, not only that country but<br />
other countries, are very, very welcome in Australia and the experience I know of the<br />
overwhelming bulk of them has been a very positive one and it is time that we got as a<br />
community on the front foot on this whole issue. It is time we confidently asserted<br />
what is the truth and that is that this is an open, tolerant society which treats people<br />
decently, which has a long history of tolerance and of absorbing people from all around<br />
the world and I am simply not willing as Prime Minister to allow suggestions from<br />
wherever they might come that this country is bigoted and narrow minded and<br />
intolerant. I am not prepared to let those remarks go by unrebuked because they are<br />
wrong and they sell this country short and they do the generosity of the Australian<br />
people and the decency of the Australian people a great disservice.<br />
SATTLER: Well US President Bill Clinton's visit was a real coup for you and the new Government<br />
but when would you expect it to translate into a better deal, especially in the trade and<br />
manufacturing areas?<br />
PRIE NMSTER:<br />
Well it certainly was a very successfual visit and it was a complement to the country and<br />
that's the most important thing-When would I expect it to translate? Well, we have<br />
made progress but progress on the trade front is always slow because every country<br />
has its own self interest to look to in trade and the Americans are no different. They're<br />
better on some trade issues than the Europeans, on agriculture the Americans have<br />
been better than the Europeans but both of them give agriculture a rawer deal than we<br />
would like and we will continue to exert pressure on the Americans not to subsidise<br />
agricultural exports to the detriment of our exports.<br />
SATrLER: Perhaps you'd better take up golf and have a few rounds with him. Fa om19/ 12/ 96 15: 28 Pg: 4 </p>
<p>Fax from PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well I do think the personal contact established will help and it is worth noting that<br />
over the last year or so the Americans have not used their export enhancement<br />
legislation as much as they did over the previous couple of years so there's a glimmer<br />
of hope or a chink of light on that front but it's a slow job. Everybody looks to their<br />
self interest on these trade matters and what you have to do is try and, try to get<br />
people collectively seeing the benefit of liberalisation all around rather than hanging on<br />
to what they've got.<br />
SATTLER: Well for a decade and a half, no Government of Australia has actually broken the back<br />
of unemployment in this country. What level are you aiming for in twelve months<br />
time, especially on the yo. uth front?<br />
PRIME MIINISTEIL<br />
Well, I am not going to put a figure on it. I have set my face firmly against particular<br />
figures. I do believe that if we can get small business really going next year and we've<br />
done a lot to bring that about. We've just changed the capital gains tax regime for<br />
small business and as from the first of July next year a small businessman will be able<br />
to move from one business to another, no matter what type the businesses are and<br />
providing the value of the business doesn't go above $ 5 million, and that's a pretty<br />
high ceiling there will be no capital gains tax liability at all. Now when the small<br />
business community of Australia realises the significance of that change to the tax<br />
system, you're going to see a lot more activity, you're going to see a lot more money<br />
coming into small business. On top of that, the unfair dismissal laws will be gone on<br />
the first of January next year, gone completely. There will be a new and more flexible<br />
industrial relations system for small business and in February I will be responding in<br />
detail to the anti-red tape report of Charlie Bell's committee which the Government<br />
commissioned a few months ago and I will be making announcements in the middle of<br />
February which will be of long term benefit to small business.<br />
When you add all of those together, you will have a far more benign climate for small<br />
business and I hope that will help to reduce unemployment particularly amongst the<br />
young. SATTLER: When are we going to get to invest in Telstra?<br />
PRIM MINISTER:<br />
Well sometime I hope in the next twelve months. The legilation comes into force in<br />
April. The Governmnent is now hard at work getting ready for the sale, getting ready<br />
for market day and I hope it will be some time in 1997 and it will be great for the<br />
ordinary investors of Australia. Fa rom19/ 12/ 96 15: 28 Pg: S </p>
<p>Fax from SATTLER: They say it's going to be the fifth biggest float in the world.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
It will be the fifth biggest float in the world. It wil be the biggest float Australians<br />
have ever participated in and I can promise that the employees of Teistra will get a<br />
preferential deal. They get one free share for every four shares they buy up to a limit<br />
of 500 free shares,<br />
SATTLER: I haven't heard the unions lauding that one.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well they should. I mean, herp is the Howard Government discriminating in favour of<br />
the employees of Teistra and so we should. They are, the employees of that company<br />
are deserving of a special deal but it will be a great investment, a great investment for<br />
the mums and dads of Australia. It really will be, and I think there will be enormous<br />
excitement when this comes on because people will be buying a share, they will be<br />
buying a stake in the ownership of one of the great Australian utilities. We are not<br />
selling something out of public ownership. We're selling it into public ownership<br />
because the Australian public will be able to invest in and have a direct personal stake<br />
in the welfare of this great public utility. I think it will be a very exciting thing and it<br />
will change the culture and the attitude of many people to investment in this country<br />
and I think it's a very exciting development.<br />
SATTLER: What's been the toughest par of 1996 for you? Has it been your wife's serious<br />
illness? PRIME MINISTER: 2<br />
On a personal level, yes, undo ubtedly. That was far, from a personal point of view,<br />
was far more difficult than anything else.<br />
SATTLER: I<br />
The fact that you had to go tq work every day in the top job in the country must have<br />
been a bit rough. I<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well Howard, a lot of Austr lans have a similar experience and... 6<br />
Fa om19/ 12/ 96 15: 28 Pg: 6 </p>
<p>Fax from19/ 12/ 96 15: 28 Pg: 7<br />
SATTLER: They're not all in the public eye.<br />
PRIME NMISTER:<br />
No but many of them have difficult jobs and difficult personal circumstances and I<br />
don't, illness is something that, it's an indiscriminate thing and I just had a, with my<br />
experience, a reminder of what many of my fellow Australians experience in their daily<br />
lives as well. I am very gr-atefu~ l for the medical treatment that was available, very<br />
grateflul, and I can't speak too highly of the medical treatment and the nursing care that<br />
my wife received in the public hospital system in Sydney.<br />
SATI'LER: What do you want to achieve for yoursgelf in the next twelve months?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I want to see lower unemployment. It's an aim. I want to see the benefits of what<br />
we've done this year consolidated. I want to see a strong response to the small<br />
business report. I also want to see a very successfUl float of Teistra and I also want to<br />
build further on some of the contacts I have made with leaders in our region<br />
particularly the Chinese President. China is a very imiportant country to Australia. We<br />
will always have differences in the way we run our two societies. Ours is a democracy.<br />
SATTLER: Are you going to invite him to Australia next year?<br />
PRIME MINSTER:<br />
Well I will go there first and he's very welcome to come here. I think it's in the nature<br />
of things if you go to a country one year, it's not usual that the leader of that country<br />
comes in the same year, but he would be very welcome to visit Australia and I will<br />
certainly be encouraging him to do so.<br />
SA PTLER:<br />
All right. Well thanks very much for your availability in 1996. You said you would<br />
and you've flulfilled that promise.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
And I will keep that pattern going in 1997 and I hope you have a very merry Christmas<br />
and an enjoyable, relaxed and comfortable new year. </p>
<p>Fax from SATTLER:<br />
Have a good break too. I know you're going on holidays just like I am, for a bit at<br />
least. PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I am indeed.<br />
SATTLER: All the best to you and your family, Prime Minister.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Thank you Howard.<br />
SATTLER: Thanks for joining us. John Howard, Prime Minister of Australia. 19/ 12/ 96 15: 28 Pg: 8 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
