<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4655</transcript-id>
    <title>LOCAL PROCESSING OF NATURAL RESOURCES, 21 MARCH 1978</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/03/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004655.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CABINET<br />
FOR PRESS 21 March 1978<br />
LOCAL PROCESSING OF NATURAL RESOURCES<br />
The Prime minister has written to all State Premiers seeking<br />
their cooperation in the Commonwealth's policy objective of<br />
encouraging further industrial development in Australia through<br />
the local processing of natural resources.<br />
The Government believes that the domestic processing of<br />
resources will occupy a prominent place in Australia's industrial<br />
future and manufacturing industry development with immediate<br />
interest being centred around the processing of minerals and<br />
energy resources.<br />
Australia is favourably placed for additional mineral processing.<br />
It has the necessary resources of minerals and energy, the<br />
economy is on its way back, and price stability is within our<br />
grasp. We have a skilled workforce and a first class record<br />
as a reliable supplier of raw materials and semi-processed<br />
products. It is important, however, to develop a suitable policy framework<br />
as early as possible to both guide and encourage industry<br />
looKing at future processing prospects and to facilitate<br />
desirable forms of development.<br />
Increased domestic processing of minerals would give rise to<br />
many benefits, including, a more integrated mining and manufacturing<br />
structure, external economies and marketing advantages to<br />
industry, increased foreign exchange earnings and additional<br />
and more diversified employment opportunities for a workforce<br />
possessing increasingly sophisticated skills.<br />
The Government has no wish to disturb existing commodity flows<br />
and its main attention will be given to the promotion of<br />
Australia's prospects for sharing in the future growth in<br />
demand for processed mineral products as well as taking up any<br />
opportunities offered when existing plants need to be replaced<br />
by new plants.<br />
In view of the responsibilities of State Governments in matters<br />
relating to processing, there would be merit in establishment<br />
of arrangements for close and continuous inter-governmental<br />
consultation in this area so that as far as possible the policies<br />
and initiatives of the respective Governments complement and<br />
support each other. ./ 2 </p>
<p>2.<br />
To this end the States have been asked to agree to the<br />
establishment of a Standing Joint Study Group of the Australian<br />
Minerals and Energy Council and the Commonwealth/ State Industry<br />
Ministers' Conference. Initial discussions took place at<br />
recent meetings of both these bodies.<br />
In addition the Australian Manufacturing Council has agreed<br />
to establish a Study Group to further examine the issues<br />
involved. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
