<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5113</transcript-id>
    <title>TASMANIA: THESE ARE THE FACTS</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/07/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005113.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS 24 July 1979<br />
TASDIMANIA: THESE ARE THE FACTS.<br />
Mr. Lowe must indeed be desperate. He tries to use a routine<br />
letter from me following the Premiers' Conference t,<br />
up his weak electoral case. The letter mentioned st : h matters<br />
as changed Queen's Birthday holiday, Energy, the Se. an( I<br />
Submerged Land Act, and the arrangements that must come from<br />
these matters.<br />
The second paragraph of my letter referred to a joint working<br />
party to make arrangements to replace the tax reimbursement guarantca<br />
once the present guarantee runs out.<br />
I said during the Premiers' Conference and after it that there<br />
would be such a working party. There is nothing new in that.<br />
The third paragraph reaffirms the Commonwealth view that the<br />
present guarantee is far too generous, and that it cannot be<br />
replaced in its present form.<br />
That was also said at the Premiers' Conference. It was said<br />
to the press outside. It was said in Hobart.<br />
The present guarantee has resulted in an increase of 13 or<br />
14 per cent this year over last year in tax reimbursement<br />
payments to the States.<br />
This is an extraordinarily generous increase. It is not one<br />
which we should ask the taxpayers of Australia to underwrite<br />
just to subsidise an inefficient State Government.<br />
How many taxpayers want the State Government to spend 14 per<br />
cent more of tax revenue each year, year after year? Such<br />
an increase would have to be paid for by the taxpayers of<br />
Australia. On that basis, taxes would clearly go through the roof.<br />
It can't be sustained.<br />
For a Premier to want it would mean he was encouraging gross<br />
extravagance. We know Mr. Lowe has been totally inefficient within his own<br />
administration-so he probably needs the extra money to cover<br />
up those inefficiencies. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
In fact, one essential reason for the tightness in the loan<br />
funds was the generosity of the Commnonwealth in taxation<br />
reimbursements. If the increase in these tax reimbursements<br />
has not been so great, then clearly loan funds could have<br />
been larger.<br />
Mr. Lowe launched the election on a false basis, 18 or 19<br />
months before time. From the start, the campaign has gone<br />
badly for him.<br />
When he was trumpeting around Tasmania pretending to protect<br />
the interests of that State, his domineering Deputy, Mr. Batt,<br />
was in Adelaide, destroying the interests of Tasmania.<br />
Mr. Batt, as President of the Labor Party, has sold out<br />
Tasmania.<br />
He supported moves which would make the Senate virtually<br />
wimpotent, and therefore destroy the capacity of the Senate<br />
to. protect small States like Tasmania.<br />
He supported moves which mean that Melbourne and Sydney alone<br />
could carry a referendum in Australia. The protection for the<br />
small States is totally destroyed under the Labor proposal.<br />
-It is a monstrous sell-out of the State of Tasmania and the<br />
. Labor Party leaders should be ashamed of what they have done.<br />
Will Mr. Lowe now disown Mr. Batt and what he has done? If<br />
-' not, why not?<br />
Mr. Batt also directly participated in moves that would place<br />
trade unions totally above the Law.<br />
we've had too much of trade unions seeking to dictate to this<br />
country over the last few weeks.<br />
Mr. Batt supported moves which would make it easy for unions<br />
in the name of industrial action, to do anything they li-ke,<br />
no matter how damaging to the people of this country, and the<br />
law would not be able to touch them.<br />
The Party of which Mr. B att is President has taken all<br />
support away from the industrial tribunals. This is the*<br />
greatest possible backing for industrial anarchy.<br />
how can Mr. Lowe pretend to be defending his own State when<br />
his chief Deputy is so busy selling out Tasmania?<br />
Against Mr. Towe ' S flights of fancy and his journeys into<br />
deception, my Government's record of firm support for<br />
Tasmania is clear and genuine.<br />
The freight equalisation scheme is the base on which Tasmania's<br />
economic progress depends. </p>
<p>-3-<br />
In one year, more than $ 24 million was paid out to businesses<br />
under the Scheme. Total payments have exceeded $ 62 million.<br />
The Callaghan Report, initiated by my Government, provided<br />
the most thorough review yet of the Tasmania economy. It<br />
recognised Tasmania's special problems and the Commonwealth<br />
Government has acted with determination to deal with them.<br />
As we have made plain, there will be further action taken<br />
under the Callaghan Report.<br />
In terms of general financial assistance the Commonwealth has<br />
maintained much higher payments per head to Tasmania than to<br />
any other State. In 1978/ 79 Tasmania received $ 1,209 per head<br />
of population as against Victoria's $ 686 and Western Australia's<br />
$ 962.<br />
This means that since 1976/ 77 the advantage to Tasmania in<br />
terms of payments per head stands at around 58 per ce,' t more<br />
than the average to all States.<br />
In addition, through our considerate policy planning directly,<br />
or Commonwealth initiatives closely related to it, Tasmania<br />
received, in 1978/ 79, special Commonwealth assistance of<br />
approximately $ 40 million.<br />
Already a number of reconmendations have gone ahead approving<br />
projects by the Decentralisation Advisory Board. These include<br />
considerable help for the tourist and fishing industries,<br />
which are vital for the economic life of the State.<br />
Additionally, the $ 8 million Antarctic Division is being set<br />
up in Kingston, and a five-year plan to help the hardwood<br />
forestry industry is undemray.<br />
The Maritime College at Launceston is the only new tertiary<br />
institution under construction.<br />
All that Labor's policies can offer is more centralism,<br />
more Canberra control, bigger Government and more taxation.<br />
These are the facts which Mr. Lowe tries to hide.<br />
The people of Tasmania have been cheated and misled by their<br />
ALP State leaders long enough. They deserve to be told the<br />
truth. 000000 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
