<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5163</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/10/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005163.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR MEDIA 14 octOgER 1979<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
The recent change of government in South Australia has set<br />
the stage for that State to join with the rest of Australia<br />
in the surge of investment we are now enjoying. For too long<br />
South Australia was the poor cousin. For too long South Australia<br />
languished behind her fellow States in investment, and thus<br />
in job opportunities.<br />
A century ago South Australia was a major mining State.<br />
Today, that State contributes only about three per cent of<br />
the nation's mineral production. Much of the blame for that<br />
can be laid solely at the door of the former State Labor<br />
government. South Australia suffered a decade of Labor stagnation.<br />
South Australia now has the opportunity to be a great State again.<br />
It can be, and it will be. South Australia indeed Australia<br />
needs every cent of investment we can.. get, every bit of development,<br />
every new job.<br />
Look at the way Labor cast a shadow over the development of<br />
the great Roxby Downs project. The meaningless gesture of<br />
banning the mining of uranium in South * Australia achieved<br />
nothing more than denying Australians jobs.<br />
Immediately following the South Australian election, we moved<br />
quickly under our foreign investment policy to allow detailed<br />
exploration of the project. The way is now clear for the<br />
Western Mining Corporation to press ahead confidently with the<br />
development of this massive project for the benefit of Australia.<br />
Jobs will be created.<br />
Let us now look for a moment at the potential of Roxby Downs.<br />
The Western Mining Corporation is looking at a capital investment<br />
exceeding $ 1,000 million in what could become the greatest mining<br />
project our nation has seen. In fact, with its known reserves<br />
of copper, gold and uranium it could become one of the world's<br />
great mines. It would provide between 2,000 to 3,000 jobs in<br />
the construction stages. When developed, we would see the<br />
employmnent of 5,00. Q on a permanient basis. Add to this the<br />
multiplier effect. of such a huge project. With the infrastructure<br />
involved the spin-off the total number of new jobs would<br />
be many more thousands.<br />
What a boost for our nation that would be.<br />
It is not fanciful to compare Roxby Downs with Mt. Isa a flourishing<br />
mining town of 28,000 people, serving the dynamic port of Townsville,<br />
now one of our great growth centres. </p>
<p>All those jobs, all that development, simply wouldn't happen<br />
under Labor. A Labor government in Canberra would turn back<br />
the clock to the days when development stopped dead in its tracks.<br />
Instead of welcoming development of Roxby Downs, instead of<br />
welcoming the opportunities, instead of welcoming the jobs,<br />
what does Labor do today?<br />
Ironically, they chose Adelaide, capital city of South Australia,<br />
as the venue for their supreme policy-making conference which<br />
showed them up for all time as the anti-development, anti-investment<br />
and anti-job party of Australia.<br />
They said they would have a resource tax. This would kill off<br />
profits and stifle enterprise and initiative. It would be a<br />
disastrous policy . Mr Whitlam all over again.<br />
In Adelaide, the Labor Party decided that if in government it would<br />
refuse export approval of Australian uranium, other than uranium<br />
mined under existing contracts from Mary Kathleen " until all the<br />
unresolved problems of the nuclear industry have been satisfactorily<br />
attended to".<br />
As the Opposition's spokesman on Minerals and Energy, Mr Keating,<br />
said this week: " Companies that invest in uranium mining in<br />
Australia do so in the face of that policy". What Mr Keating is<br />
saying is that Labor would kill-off Roxby Downs, it would ban<br />
uranium exports. It would renege on existing contracts.<br />
Australia's credibility as a reliable and stable world trader<br />
would be shot to ribbons. We would never again be trusted around<br />
any of the trade-negotiating tables of the world. But on top of<br />
that, Labor's anti-development policies would deny Australians<br />
jobs. They would destroy jobs.<br />
They did it before, and their policies haven't changed. They haven't<br />
learned the lesson of history. They are the discredited Whitlam<br />
policies, dressed up under the so-called cloak of Hayden moderation.<br />
Under our policies, Roxby Downs is just one of the many exciting<br />
projects in the pipeline for the 1980' s. We are poised to make<br />
the ' 80s one of the most rewarding decades in Australia's history.<br />
We will see Australia-become one of the important-ffidd]?-ranking<br />
powers in the world.<br />
It won't just happen by accident. It will happen because we have<br />
the right government policies; because our people have the<br />
determination and the skills; because the rest of the world has<br />
confidence in us.<br />
We can all look forward to the future of our nation with great<br />
and growing confidence. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
