<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6311</transcript-id>
    <title>FOLLOWING IS TEST OF SPEECH GIVEN BY PRIME MINISTER TO KOREAN ECONOMIC ORGANISATIONS ON 6 FEBRUARY 1984</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/02/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006311.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
ANA6<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOLLOWING IS TEXT OF SPEECH GIVEN BY PRIME MINISTER TO<br />
KOREAN ECONOMIC ORGANISATIONS ON 6 FEBURARY 1984.<br />
PLEASE NOTE THIS TEXT SUPERCEEDES THAT FORWARDED IN O. TK36828<br />
OF 2 FEBRUARY 1984.<br />
BEGINS: MR PRIME MINISTERv<br />
I WAS VERY PLEASED TO ACCEPT THE INVITATION<br />
OF THE FOUR KOREAN ECONOMIC -ORGANISATIONS TO ADDRE-SS<br />
THIS DISTINGUISHED AND REPRESENTATIVE GROUP.<br />
YOU ARE ALL AWARE OF HOW THE ECONOMIC AND TRADING<br />
RELATIONSHIP BETWEEN OUR TWO COUNTRIES HAS EXPANDED IN RECENT<br />
YEARS.' IT IS A RELATIONSHIP THAT IS BECOMING INCREASINGLY IMPO* RTANT<br />
TO BOTH OUR COUNTRIES.<br />
IT IS ADDING A NEW AND VIGOROUS DIMENSION TO A POLITICAL<br />
RELATIONSHIP THAT EXTENDS BACK OVER MANY YEARS.<br />
THAT THIS SHOULD BE HAPPENING IN PART REFLECTS THE STRENGTH OF THE<br />
REPUBLIC OF KOREA'S OWN ECONOMIC PERFORMANCE DURING THE PAST<br />
DECADE.<br />
THAT PERFORMANCE HAS BEEN IMPRESSIVE BY ANY STANDARDS.<br />
YOUR CONTINUING ECONOMIC ECONOMIC SUCCESS IS A CLEAR MANIFESTATION<br />
OF WHAT PEOPLE ARE GENERALLY COMING TO APPRECIATE AS. THE ECONOMIC<br />
DYNAMISM OF THE WESTERN PACIFIC REGION.<br />
FOR'COUNTRIES SUCH AS AUSTRALIAt KOREA'S VIGOROUS ECONOMIC GROWTH<br />
HAS PRESENTED MAJOR TRADE OPPORTUNITIES.<br />
TRADE NOW CONSTITUTES A MAJOR ELEMENT IN THE AUSTRALIA/ KOREA<br />
RELATIONSHIP. THIS HAS NOT ALWAYS BEEN THE CASE.<br />
STRONG POLITICAL TIES WERE ESTABLISHED SOON AFTER THE FOUNDATION<br />
OF THE REPUBLIC OF KOREA IN 1948 AND THESE WERE REINFORCED BY OUR<br />
ASSOCIATION IN THE KOREAN WAR. FOR A LONG TIME THE EMPHASIS IN THE<br />
RELATIONSHIP WAS ON AUSTRALIAN SUPPORT FOR THE PEOPLE OF THE<br />
REPUBLIC OF KOREA IN THEIR EFFORTS To BUILO A SECURE AND STABLE<br />
SOCIETY. THIS SUPPoRT CONTINUES. </p>
<p>AUSTRALIA'S REVULSION AT THE SHOOTING DOWN OF KOREAN AIRLINER FLT<br />
007 AND THE RANGOON ATROCITY WAS DEEP AND STRONGLY FELT.<br />
IT IS WITHIN THIS FIRM FRAMEWORK OF ' A CLOSE POLITICAL RELATIONSHIP<br />
THAT TRADE BETWEEN OUR COUNTRIES HAS DEVELOPED AND FOURISHED.<br />
INDEED THE GROWING TRADE RELATIONSHIP HAS SERVED TO REINFORCE<br />
AND GIVE MORE SUBSTANCE TO THE ALREADY IMPORTANT POLITICAL RELATIONSHIP<br />
BETWEEN OUR COUNTRIES.<br />
ORGANISATIONS SUCH AS YOURS AND BODIES LIKE THE AUSTRALIA/ KOREA<br />
AND KOREA/ AUSTRALIA BUSINESS CO-OPERATION COMMITTEES HAVE CONTRIBUJTED<br />
SIGNIFICANTLY TO THE VIGOUR OF OUR TRADING<br />
RELATIONSHIP. THE RAPID GROWTH IN THE REPUBLIC OF KOREA'S ECONOMY. HAS PROVIDED A<br />
STRONG STIMULUS FOR THE DEVELOPMENT OF AUSTRALIA/ KOREA TRADE.<br />
BILATERAL TRADE HAS EXPANDED RAPIDLY DURING THE PAST DECADE TO<br />
REACH DLLRS 1.1 BILLION IN 1982/ 83. ' DURING THIS SAME PERIOD<br />
AUSTRALIA'S EXPORTS TO KOREA HAVE DROWN AT AN AVERAGE ANNUAL RATE-OF<br />
32 PERCENT AND OUR IMPORTS BY 40 PERCENT.<br />
KOREA IS NOW RANKED FIFTH AMONGST AUSTRALIA'S, EXPORT MARKETS AND IS<br />
A MAJOR DESTINATION FOR OUR COAL, BEEF9 IRON ORE? SUGAR AND WOOL.<br />
THIS SITUATION UNDERLINES THE GROWING COMPLEMENTARITY OF OUR<br />
TWO ECONOMIESi WITH AUSTRALIAN BEING A COMPETITIVE AND RELIABLE<br />
SOURCE OF THE RAW MATERIALS AND AGRICULTURAL PRODUCTS REQUIRED BY<br />
THE GROWING KOREAN ECONOMY.<br />
THIS OBVIOUSLY IS OF CRITICAL RELEVANCE TO KOREA'S DEVELOPMENT<br />
NEEDS. IN THIS REGARD AUSVTRALIA IS PARTICULARLY MINDFUL OF KOREA'S<br />
ENERGY REQUIREMENTS.<br />
AUSTRALIA OF COURSE HAS THE CAPACITY TO SUPPLY LARGER QUANTITIES<br />
OF COAL TO THE ROK AND POSSIBLY COULD SUPPLY GAS IN THE FUTURE.<br />
KOREA ALSO HAS A CONTRACT FOR THE SUPPLY OF AUSTRALIAN URANIUM.<br />
AUSTRALIA CLOSELY FOLLOWS THE MARKET FOR ITS RESOURCES IN KOREA AND)<br />
PLACES IMPORTANCE ON BEING A RELIABLE LONG-TERM SUPPLIER.'<br />
AUSTRALIA IS THEREFORE ABLE TO MAKE AN IMPORTANT CONTRIBUTION TO<br />
UNDERWRITING THE REPUBLIC OF KOREA'S ENERGY SECURITY.<br />
IT HAS NOT? HOWEVER, BEEN ALL SMOOTH SAILING IN THE AUSTRALIA/ KOREA<br />
TRADE RELATIONSHIP. THE RECESSION HAS CAUSED AUSTRALIAN<br />
MANUFACTURING INDUSTRIES PARTICULAR DIFFICULTIES. THERE HAS AT THE<br />
SAME TIME BEEN PARTICULAR CONCERN AMONG SOME INDUSTRIES ABOUT THE<br />
LEVEL AND CHARACTER OF IMPORT-COMPETITION. AS WELL THE NUMBER OF<br />
ANTI-DUMPING CASES AND DEVELOPING COUNTRY TARIFF PREFERENCE CASES<br />
BROUGHT FORWARD BY AUSTRALIAN INDUSTRY ROSE IN THE PERIOD. WITH THE<br />
RECENT STREAM-LINING OF ADMINISTRATIVE PROCEDURES, IMPROVED<br />
AUSTRALIAN ECONOMIC GROWTH PERFORMANCE AND STRONGER WORLD MARKET<br />
CONDITIONS, I SHOULD EXPECT SOME ALLEVIATION OF THESE PRESSURES.<br />
A NUMBER OF DECISIONS TAKEN HAVE, I KNtO. W, CAUSED CONCERN IN K( OREA.<br />
I~ WOULD SIMPLY OBSERVE THAT THERE HAVE BEEN SIGNIFICANT EXCEPTIONS<br />
SUCH AS THE RETENTION OF PREFERENCES ON STEEL. </p>
<p>FOR ITS PART AUSTRALIA HAS ITS OWN ACCESS PROBLEMS IN THE KOREAN<br />
MARKET. WE, FOR EXAMPLE, WOULD WELCOME LIBERALISATION OF THE KOREAN<br />
GRAIN IMPORT REGIME AND WOULD APPRECIATE MORE'OPEN ACCESS FOR OTHER<br />
AUSTRALIAN PRODUCTS, INCLUDING MANUFACTURES. AUSTRALIA HAS A<br />
PARTICULAR INTEREST IN SECURING ACCESS FOR PROCESSED FOODS, FRUIT AND<br />
VEGETABLES. NATURALLY AUSTRALIA ALSO ATTACHES IMPORTANCE TO<br />
INCREASING ITS EXISTING MARKET SHARE IN KOREA'S RAW MATERIAL AND<br />
AGRICULTURAL PRODUCT IMPORTS TO A LEVEL COMMENSURATE WITH OUR<br />
COMPETITIVENESS AND RELIABILITY AS A SUPPLIER.<br />
THERE IS, I WOULD SUGGEST, A MUTUAL AUSTRALIA/ KOREAN INTEREST IN HE<br />
CONTRIBUTION EACH OF US CAN MAKE TO THE MAINTENANCE OF AN OPEN<br />
INTERNATIONAL TRADE SYSTEM.<br />
I RECOGNISE THAT THE TRADE IMBALANCE, WHICH HEAVILY FAVOURS<br />
AUSIRALIA, REMAINS OF CONCERN TO KOREA.<br />
THE EXISTENCE OF THIS IMBALANCE REFLECTS THE FACT THAT AUSTRALIA<br />
IS A COMPETITIVE AND FUNDAMENTALLY RELIABLE SUPPLER OF RAW<br />
MATERIALS WHICH ARE VITAL INGREDIENTS FOR THE KOREAN INDUSTRIAL<br />
EFFORT. THIS SUGGESTS THAT THERE IS A CERTAIN INEVEITABILITY<br />
ATTACHING TO THE IMBALANCE IN OUR BILATERAL TRADE.<br />
WE, NEVERTHELESS, ARE SEEKING TO IDENTIFY OPPORTUNITIES IN THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN MARKET WHERE KOREA COULD POSSIBLY ENTER OR EXPAND ITS<br />
EXISTING SHARE. AUSTRALIAN OFFICIALS STAND READY TO JOIN WITH THEIR<br />
COUNTERPARTS IN CARRYING THIS EXERCISE FORWARD.<br />
I STRONGLY BELIEVE THAT CO-OPERATIVE APPROACHES OF THIS KIND ARE THE<br />
MOST LIKELY TO PRODUCE SATISFACTORY RESULTS. THEY ARE ALSO THE<br />
KIND OF APPROACH WE SHOULP EXPECT BETWEEN FRIENDS.<br />
IN THE MEANTIME I CAN THINK OF NOTHING BETTER THAN THAT KOREAN ENTREPRENEURS<br />
SHOULD GET OUT AND SELL TO AUSTRALIA, LEARN THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN MARKET AND ESTABLISH THEIR COMPETITIVENESS WITH OTHER<br />
MAJOR SUPPL4ERS THROUGH THE PROVISION OF QUALITY GOODS.<br />
KOREAN INVESTMENT IN AUSTRALIAN IS A RELATIVELY NEW DIMENSION TO<br />
THE COMMERCIAL RELATIONSHIP. ALREADY THERE ARE JOINT VENTURES IN<br />
COAL ARRIVING IN N. S. W. AND GOOD PROSPECTS IN QUEENSLAND. KOREAN<br />
CORPORATIONS ARE NOW LOOKING AT THE FEASIBILITY OF AN ALUMINIUM<br />
SMELTER AND POWER STATION IN WESTERN AUSTRALIA. CONSIDERED FROM A<br />
TRADE PERSPECTIVE, THIS PROPOSAL COULD CREATE USEFUL OPPORTUNITIES<br />
FOR SUPPLY OF KOREAN CAPITAL GOODS AS WELL AS AN EXPORT MARKET<br />
IN KOREA FOR THE OUTPUT OF ALUMINIUM. BOTH ASPECTS, ARE OBVIOUSLY<br />
IMPORTANT. BUT, AS YOU WOULD ALL APPRECIATE, CONSIDERATION WILL<br />
NEED TO BE GIVEN, FOLLOWING RECEIPT OF A FIRM PROPOSAL, TO THE<br />
EMPLOYMENT EXPORT AND INVESTMENT ASPECTS AS WELL AS TO THE EXTENT<br />
OF FOREIGN OWNERSHIP AND CONTROL. I CAN ASSURE YOU ALL THESE<br />
ASPECTS WILL BE CAREFULLY WEIGHED.<br />
THE PROSPECTS ARE THAT THE INVESTMENT RELATIONSHIP BETWEEN<br />
AUSTRALIA AND KOREA WILL GROW, ESPECIALLY GIVEN KOREA'S INTEREST IN<br />
INVESTING IN RESOURCES PROJECTS.<br />
ALL PROPOSALS WILL BE CONSIDERED ON THE BASIS OF OUR GLOBAL, NONDISCRIMINATORY<br />
FOREIGN INVESTMENT CRITERIA. THOS CRITERIA MAKE<br />
CLEAR THE TERMS UNDER WHICH INVESTMENT IS WELCOME IN AUSTRALIA. </p>
<p>YOU WOULD ALL APPRECIATE THAT THE SECURING OF ACCEPTABLE FOREIGN<br />
INVESTMENT IS AN IMPORTANT ELEMENT IN AUSTRALIA'S ECONOMIC<br />
STRATEGY. A NUMBER OF AREAS READILY SUGGEST THEMSELVES AS POSSIBLE<br />
TARGETS FOR AUSTRALIA/ KOREA JOINT VENTURES MINERAL PROCESSING<br />
( SEMI COLON) AND ENERGY-INTENSIVE INTERMEDIATE PRODUCTS STAND OUT.<br />
I WOULD URGE MUCH MORE VIGOROUS EXPLORATION OF THE OPPORTUNITIES<br />
THAN HAS BEEN THE CASE TO DATE.<br />
THE FUTURE OF OUR BILATERLA ECONOMIC RELATIONS LOOKS ENCOURAGING.<br />
AS THE AUSTRALIAN ECONOMY RECOVERS AND GROWTH BECOMES STRONGER,<br />
MORE OPPORTUNITIES WILL BE GENERATED BOTH FOR DOMESTICALLY PRODUCED<br />
GOODS AND IMPORTS. KOREAN EXPORTERS SHOULD BE WELL PLACED TO<br />
BENEFIT FROM THESE OPPORTUNITES.<br />
SIMILARLY, THE KOREAN ECONOMY WILL CONTINUE TO GROW STRONGLY AND OF<br />
COURSE AUSTRALIA HAS THE CAPACITY, AS AN EFFICIENT AND RELIABLE<br />
SUPPLIER, TO MEET KOREA'S GROWING DEMANDS.<br />
IN THIS RESPECT, I AM DELIGHTED THAT INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES STRIKES<br />
OVER THE LAST YEAR HAVE HAD A MINIMAL IMPACT ON THE TRADING<br />
RELATIONSHIP. MOVES MADE BY MY GOVERNMENT TO PROMOTE<br />
TRIPARTITE CONSULTATIVE COUNCILS IN IMPORTANT AREAS SUCH AS THE<br />
PILBARA IN WESTERN AUSTRALIA WILL REINFORCE THIS TREND<br />
AS IT AFFECTS SUCH MAJOR COMMODITY EXPORTS AS IRON ORE.<br />
INDEED THE EFFECT OF INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES IN AUSTRALIA HAS BEEN<br />
EXAGGERATED BY SOME OBSERVERS.<br />
THE NUMBER OF WORKING DAYS LOST DUE TO INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES IN<br />
AUSTRALIA OVER THE LAST YEAR ENDING OCTOBER 1983 REPRESENTED ONLY<br />
0.2 DAYS PER MEMBERS OF TH WORK-FORCE. FURTHER, THE NUMBER OF DAYS<br />
LOST DUE TO INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES IN AUSTRALIA IN THE SAME PERIOD<br />
FELL BY NEARLY 50 PERCENT FROM THE PREVIOUS YEAR. THIS WAS THE<br />
LOWEST SUCH FIGURE FOR A COMPARABLE 12 MONTH PERIOD SINCE 1968.<br />
PERHAPS EVEN MORE SIGNIFICANTLY FOR THE TRADE RELATIONSHIP,<br />
THERE WAS A 64 PERCENT RFpUCTION IN THE NUMBER OF DAYS LOST IN<br />
THE MINING INDUSTRY, AND'A 57 PERCENT REDUCTION IN DAYS LOST<br />
IN THE MARITIME INDUSTRY INCLUDING STEVEDORING, IN THE SAME' PERIOD.<br />
IT HAS BEEN A PARTICULAR PRIORITY OF MY GOVERNMENT TO SECURE THE<br />
ESTABLISHMENT OF AN ORDERLY AND STABLE INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS SYSTEM<br />
CONSISTENT WITH OUR DEMOCRATIC PRACTICES IN AUSTRALIA. WE SEE<br />
THIS AS A NECESSARY SUPPLEMENT TO OUR POLICY OF MAKING AUSTRALIA<br />
A RELIABLE AND COMPETITVE TRADEING PARTNER.<br />
IN THIS REGARD THE PRICES AND INCOMES ACCORD BETWEEN THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN LABOR PARTY AND THE AUSTRALIAN TRADE UNION MOVEMENT PUT<br />
IN PLACE BY MY GOVERNMENT, THE ACTIVE SUPPORT WE HAVE GIVEN TO THE<br />
CREATION OF TRIPARTITE CONSULTATIVE ORGANS AT INDUSTRY LEVEL9 AND<br />
OUR POLICY OF THOROUGHLY REVIEWING AND RATIONALISING INDUSTRIAL<br />
RELATIONS MACHINERY, HAVE ALL HELPED.<br />
MY GOVERNMENT'' S APPROACH IS ONE WHICH EMPHASISES THE BENEFITS OF<br />
CONSULTATIVE, CO-OPERATIVE APPROACHES AND SEEKS TO PUT BEHIND US<br />
THE UNPRODUCTIVE, DIVISIVE AND CONFRONTATIONAL STYLES OF THE PAST. </p>
<p>THE RESULTS, I THINK YOU WILL AGREE, SPEAK FOR THEMSELVES. THEY<br />
OBVIOUSLY GO WELL BEYOND THE INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS FIELD ALONE.<br />
THEY ARE ALSO REFLECTED IN THE ADOPTION AND SUPPORT OF A MIX OF<br />
NATIONAL ECONOMIC POLICIES THAT ARE ALREADY PRODUCING A VERY<br />
SIGNIFICANT UPTURN IN THE LEVEL OF AUSTRALIAN DOMESTIC ECONOMIC<br />
ACTIVITY. MR PRIME MINISTER, THE EXPANSION OF THE KOREAN ECONOMY HAS FARREACHING<br />
IMPLICATIONS FOR THE ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT OF THE ASIA/<br />
PACIFIC REGION.<br />
IN THIS REGARD, SUGGESTIONS FOR FURTHER ECONOMIC CO-OPERATION<br />
AND EXPANSION OF TRADE AMONG THE COUNTRIES OF THE ASIA/ PACIFIC<br />
REGION ARE RELEVANT.<br />
THE ASIAN AREA HAS GENERATED A SUBSTANTIAL INTERNAL ECONOMI<br />
MOMENTUM. IN THE 1980' S, GROWTH IN THE ASEAN ECONOMIES HAS AVERAGED<br />
AROUND 6 PERCENT AROUND 3.8 PERCENT FOR JAPAN AND 7 PERCENT FOR<br />
KOREA OVER THE LAST THREE YEARS. THE MAJOR INDUSTRIAL COUNTRIES, 3Y<br />
COMPARISON HAVE GROWN BY JUST OVER I PERCENT. THE POINT OF THIS<br />
COMPARISON IS FURTHER EMPHASISED WHEN IT IS REALISED THAT A NUMBER OF<br />
COUNTRIES IN THE REGION HAVE RECENTLY SUFFERED THE TWIN BLOWS OF A<br />
FALL-OFF IN EXPORT DEMAND DUE TO INTERNATIONAL RECESSION AND HEAVY<br />
EXTERNAL DEBT SERVICING COMMITMENTS WHICH HAVE LIMITED DOMESTIC<br />
ECONOMIC EXPANSION.<br />
IT IS PARTICULARLY SIGNIFICANT THAT COUNTRIES SUCH AS KOREA ARE<br />
EXPECTED TO REBOUND STRONGLY FROM THE RECESSION. KOREA, I AM TOLD,<br />
IS LIKELY TO SUSTAIN GROWTH OF 7.5 PERCENT THROUGH TO 1986. BY<br />
COMPARISON, REAL GNP GROWTH IN THE OECD ECONOMIES FOR 1984 IS<br />
EXPECTED TO AVERAGE 3.25 PERCENT.<br />
THE AUSTRALIAN ECONOMY HAS INCREASINGLY BENEFITTED FROM THE RAPID<br />
ECONOMIC GROWTH OF THE ASIA/ PACIFIC REGION. THAT GROWTH HAS UNDERPINNED<br />
A VERY SIGNIFICANT REDIRECTION OF AUSTRALIAN TRADE. BY WAY OF<br />
ILLUSTRATION, AUSTRALIAN EXPORTS TO THE WESTERN PACIFIC COUNTRIES<br />
REPRESENTED 37 PER CENT OF OUR TOTAL EXPORTS IN 1961/ 62, 48 PERCENT<br />
IN 1971/ 72 AND 55 PERCNT IN 1981/ 82. AUSTRALIAN IMPORTS GREW EVEN<br />
MORE SIGNIFICANTLY: 14 PERCENT IN 1961/ 62, 25 PERCENT IN<br />
1.971/ 72 AND 37 PERCENT IN 1981/ 82.<br />
FOR AUSTRALIA THE IDEA OF A MORE ECONOMICALLY INTEGRATED ASIA/<br />
PACIFIC REGION IS BECOMING INCREASINGLY REAL. WE SEE ADVANTAGE IN<br />
SEEKING TO MAXIMISE THE BENEFITS OF THE ECONOMIC INTERDEPENDENCE<br />
BETWEEN THE COUNTRIES OF THE REGION. THERE CAN BE LITTLE DOUBT<br />
THAT, LOOKING NOT TOO FAR AHEAD, THE ASIA/ PACIFIC REGION MUST BE<br />
ACCEPTED AS A MAJOR CATALYST FOR STRONGER WORLD-WIDE ECONOMIC<br />
PERFORMANCE. A'JY MOVE TOWARDS CLOSER ECONOMIC CO-OPERATION IN THE ASIA/ PACIFIC<br />
A3E A MUST, OF COURSE, BE NON-DISCRIMINATROY AN,) COMPATIBLE WITH OUR<br />
WIDER INTERNATIONAL OBLIGATIONS.<br />
IT HAS BEEN IN THIS SPIRIT THAT AUSTRALIA HAS BEEN CONSIDERING<br />
SUGGESTIONS FOR A NEW MULTILATERAL TRADE ROUND.<br />
WE: ARE OF THE VIEW THAT AN EXPANSION OF WORLD TRADE WOULD BE OF<br />
CONSIDERABLE ASSISTANCE IN REINFORCING BROAD ECONOMIC<br />
RECOVERY. THIS IS CRUCIAL 1t0 MAINTAINING THE MOMENTUM OF GROWTH<br />
IN ASIA AND THE PACIFIC. </p>
<p>THERE HAVE, NEVERTHELESS, RECENTLY BEEN SOME DISTURBING AND OMINuUS<br />
DEVELOPMENTS. THE PROLIFERATION OF PROTECTIONIST MEASURES AND<br />
THE RESORT TO BILATERALISM IN SEEKING TO RESOLVE TRADE PROBLEMS<br />
POSE MAJOR THREATS TO THE VERY BASIS OF THE CONTEMPORARY INTERNATIONAL<br />
TRADING SYSTEM. PRESSURES OF THIS KIND MUST BE RESISTEC.<br />
RECENT PROPOSALS FOR A NEW MTN ROUND ARE DSIGNED IN PART TO MAKE SUCH<br />
RESISTANCE EFFECTIVE.<br />
I HAVE SUGGESTED THAT COUNTRIES OF THIS REGION SHOULD CONSIDER<br />
CAREFULLY HOW THEY MIGHT BEST SECURE ATTENTION TO THEIR INTERESTS<br />
SHOULD AN MTN ROUND MATERIALISE.<br />
WE ARE NOT SEEKING TO IMPOSE DEFINITIVE VIEWS ABOUT THE PROCESS<br />
BY WHICH REGIONAL COUNTRIES' INTERESTS ARE IDENTIFIED OR ABOUT WHAT<br />
SHOULD COMPRISE THE AGENDA OF A NEW MTN. AUSTRALIA, I ACKNOWLEDGE,<br />
HAS SOME SPECIAL INTERESTS FOR EXAMPLE, IN MARKET ACCESS FOR<br />
AGRICULTURAL PRODUCTS AND PROCESSED MINERALS WHICH WOULD BE SHARED<br />
IN VARYING DEGREES BY OTHER IN THIS REGION. AT THE SAME TIME I<br />
RECOGNISE THAT OTHER COUNTRIES WILL HAVE THEIR SPECIAL INTERESTS.<br />
WHAT IS IMPORTANT IS THAT THERE SHOULD BE DELIBERATE EFFORT IN<br />
THE FORM OF ACTION, NOT WORDS TO GET BACK TO0 AN OPEN<br />
MULTILATERAL TRADEING SYSTEM.<br />
IN LINE WITH THIS OVERALL APPROACH, AUSTRALIA WOULD STRONGLY SUPPORT<br />
A NEW ROUND OF MULTILATERAL TRADE NEGOTIATIONS BUT ONLY IF WE ARE<br />
CONFIDENT THAT THEY WOULD SERIOUSLY AND EFFECTIVELY ADDRESS MATTERS<br />
OF SPECIAL SIGNIFICANCE TO AUSTRALIA, NEW ZEALAND AND OUR DEVELOPING<br />
COUNTRY NEIGHBOURS IN THE ASIAN/ PACIFIC REGION.<br />
AUSTRALIA HAS ALREADY TAKEN SOME FIRST STEPS DOWN THIS TRACK. OVER<br />
RECENT WEEKS AUSTRALIAN OFFICIALS HAVE VISITED A NUMBER OF ASIAN<br />
COUNTRIES TO DISCUSS IN AN EXPLORATORY WAY WITH THEIR COUNTERPARTS<br />
VARIOUS ASPECTS OF THESE QUESTIONS. WE HAVE ALSO CONSULTED WITH<br />
OTHER COUNTRIES THAT WOULD HAVE IMPORTANT ROLES TO PLAY IN A NEW<br />
ROUND. THE OVERALL REGAIONAL RESPONSE HAS BEEN ENCOURAGING AND<br />
THE CONSULTATIVE PROCErS WILL BE PURSUED. WE SEE OUR ROLE<br />
AS SEEKING TO ELICIT VI EWS FROM INTERESTED PARTIES IN THE REGION<br />
AND PROMOTING FRANK AND CONSTRUCTIVE DISCUSSION. AN APPROACH GIVING<br />
EFFECTIVE EXPRESSION TO THE INTERESTS OF THE COUNTRIES OF THE<br />
REGION COULD EMERGE FROM THIS PROCESS. IF IT DOES, I BELIEVE IT<br />
WILL BE TO THE DIRECT ECONOMIC ADVANTAGE OF ALL OF US. IN THE PAST<br />
OUR INTERESTS HAVE TOO EASILY BEEN BRUSHED ASIDE.<br />
INDEED I THINK THE DAY WHEN THAT COULD BE DONE IS NOW BEHIND US.<br />
THE ECONOMIC PERFORMANCE OF COUNTRIES IN THIS REGION HAS BEEN AND<br />
WILL CONTINUE TO BE SO STRONG THAT THEIR IMPACT ON INTERNATIONAL<br />
ECONOMIC CONDITIONS MUST NOW BE RECKONED WITH BY THOSE BEYO\ D ThE<br />
REGION. THIS SHOULD BE A SOURCE OF CONFIDENCE FOR ALL OF US WITHIN THE<br />
REGION. IT IS ALSO A SITUATION IMPOSTNG PARTICULAR RESRONSIBILITiEc<br />
ON EACH OF US.<br />
I KNOW WE ALL STAND) READY TO MEET THE CHALLENGE. </p>
<p>7.<br />
TOAST DISTINGUISHED GUESTS,<br />
I SHOULD NOW LIKE TO PROPOSE A TOAST TO THE HEALTH AND WELL-BEING<br />
OF HIS EXCELLENCY CHUN DOO-HWAN, PRESIDENT OF THE REPUBLIC OF KOREA<br />
AND TO THE FUTURE OF RELATIONS BETWEEN AUSTRALIA AND THE<br />
REPUBLIC OF KOREA. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
