<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11579</transcript-id>
    <title>DIPLOMATIC APPOINTMENT         HIGH COMMISSIONER TO THE UNITED KINGDOM</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/02/2000</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
 I am pleased to announce that Executive Council has approved</p>
<p> my recommendation that Mr Michael L'Estrange be appointed as Australia's</p>
<p> High Commissioner to the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern</p>
<p> Ireland.<br />
   Mr L'Estrange has made a distinguished contribution</p>
<p> to the Government over the last four years as Secretary to the Cabinet</p>
<p> and Head of the Cabinet Policy Unit.<br />
   He has played a very important role in ensuring that</p>
<p> Cabinet operates as effectively as possible and that public policies and</p>
<p> programmes reflect the overall goals and objectives of the Government.</p>
<p> He has also made a major contribution to the development of the Government's</p>
<p> policy agenda, including taxation reform, the rebalancing of foreign policy</p>
<p> and our modern conservative approach to social policy.<br />
   Mr L'Estrange graduated with Honours from Sydney</p>
<p> University in 1974, majoring in History. He is a Rhodes Scholar who graduated</p>
<p> with First Class Honours in Philosophy, Politics and Economics from Oxford</p>
<p> University. He subsequently served in the Department of Prime Minister</p>
<p> and Cabinet, as well as a senior adviser to several of my predecessors</p>
<p> as Leader of the Opposition, and as Executive Director of the Menzies</p>
<p> Research Centre. He was also a Harkness Fellow and has undertaken research</p>
<p> in international relations at Oxford, Georgetown University and the University</p>
<p> of California. He is married with five children.<br />
   Australia's relationship with the United Kingdom</p>
<p> has acquired a new vitality in recent years, building on our enduring</p>
<p> cultural and historical links. Our commercial ties to the United Kingdom</p>
<p> continue to grow strongly. We particularly appreciate the early and effective</p>
<p> contribution of the United Kingdom in both diplomatic and military terms</p>
<p> in respect of East Timor.<br />
   Mr L'Estrange will take up duty in July 2000 and</p>
<p> will replace Mr Philip Flood who has been High Commissioner since April</p>
<p> 1998.<br />
   I also take the opportunity to express the Government's</p>
<p> appreciation of the contribution of Philip Flood as High Commissioner</p>
<p> to the United Kingdom, a posting which will mark the end of a long and</p>
<p> distinguished career of public service. I wish him and his wife well in</p>
<p> their retirement.<br />
   2 February 2000</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
