<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7728</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW - BOB MAUMILL - RADIO 2KY - 25 AUGUST 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/08/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007728.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF ONLY<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW BOB MAUMILL RADIO 2KY<br />
AUGUST 1989<br />
MAUMILL: Another biggie round in Sydney, why? Why are are<br />
we on the media trail?<br />
P: Well, before we brought down the Budget Bob, we<br />
decided that in the period for about a week after that we<br />
w uld go round and sell it. Answer questions about it.<br />
What's happened of course, is that the Budget has been so<br />
well received right across the spectrum, that there doesn't<br />
really need to be much of a selling job. But that's what we<br />
committed ourselves to do, and that's what we are doing.<br />
MAUMILL: It's a forgiving electorate. I mean Paul promised<br />
t6 bring home the bacon. He was wrong on inflation, he was<br />
wiong on interest rates, he was wrong on the deficit.<br />
Obviously you have got a great record with employment,<br />
creating job opportunities. But he did get it wrong in the<br />
previous Budget. But I don't know, the media and the public<br />
don't seem to and certainly the Opposition haven't laid<br />
aIglove on you.<br />
PM: No.... well. Two reasons for that. One, that when we<br />
were preparing the Budget the previous year our estimates<br />
were wrong. But so were everyone elses. I mean every<br />
public and private economist in Australia made an under<br />
es'timate of the strength of the Australian economy and so<br />
the estimates that you-properly refer to, were out. We<br />
think we have got it right this time. And the second point<br />
to', make. You refer to the Opposition. Well it really is a<br />
strange situation where you haven't got one Opposition, but<br />
you've got about seven. They are just contradicting each<br />
otper on every issue. When we brought the Budget down, one<br />
said we had spent too much. The other bloke came up and<br />
sa d that you haven't spent enough and then he talked about<br />
this inflation adjustment.... for interest.<br />
MAUMILL: Sat in that very chair and he seems to have<br />
fotgotten about it. It's too hard is it?<br />
PM Forgotten about it?<br />
MAUMILL: sat in that very chair, told me it was an<br />
exclusive and announced it on another radio station two<br />
hours before. But he seems to have forgotten that one?<br />
44412W </p>
<p>2.<br />
PM: Well, I mean Paul Keating and Bob Hawke have blown it<br />
out of the water. But however eloquent we were, we didn't<br />
come within a bull's roar of Brian Loton of BHP. You know<br />
what he said about it. He said if you want to see that in<br />
action go to Brazil. It was a half baked, Ill conceived,<br />
not thought through proposal which would have been<br />
economically disasterous for Australia.<br />
MAUMILLt But you are in Government and not Mr Peacock and<br />
his colleagues and after having got it wrong in 87-88 now<br />
we are into a new Budget year, with a new Budget announced.<br />
} This' time will the Treasurer get the figures right?<br />
PM. jBasically. You see what we've got to do is it is<br />
not a question of Bob Hawke and Paul Keating sitting down<br />
and saying well look, there are the figures, let's have a<br />
Sguess to what they might be. We use the best resources that<br />
Sare. pvailable to us from the Treasury... a very, very<br />
competent bunch of people. But see what the economists in<br />
the Treasury, like every economist in the banks in Australia<br />
Sand ! the insurance companies, the academic insitutions,<br />
everyone had the feeling, there, at the time when we were<br />
S ggoeitntgi ngt o thbea t thBeu dgsettr enrgeatdhy of bdaecmka ndi n in8 8 the tAhuast trtahleirea nwasn't<br />
economy. It wasn't going to be as strong as it was and we<br />
all underestimated. Now we are intelligent people, we hope<br />
to learn from experience and I think, the figuring and the<br />
estimates, the assumptions that have gone into it this time<br />
will be substantially right.<br />
I<br />
MAUMILL: What about the pilots. They are making life tough<br />
" for you at the moment. And you are talking tough too. So<br />
tough, in fact, you've scared some elements of the trade<br />
union movement. I saw Georgie Campbell saying he wishes<br />
you'd back off. If you crack down too hard on the pilots,<br />
Sthat might set a precident for a conservative Government to<br />
do i't to other sections of the trade union movement.<br />
I PM: Well yes, Georgie has got to understand that when we<br />
are dealing in these matters, we deal with the trade union<br />
movement organisation as a whole and we have consulted, as<br />
Sthe ' airlines have, with the ACTU and the position is that<br />
there is an understanding by the trade union movement of the<br />
W necessity for doing what we are. If I could just take this<br />
opportunity Bob, I'm not trying to get stuck into pilots, as<br />
pilots. I know the importance of their job and I respect<br />
the importance of their job. But simply put, what is at<br />
stake here is the future, the economic future of this<br />
country and because if they were to get this thirty per cent<br />
Sthe whole wage system would blow out. The economy would<br />
collapse. You can't afford that sort of thing. And so I'm<br />
being tough, and I will continue to be tough. Not against<br />
Sthe ' pilots as blokes, or against their jobs. In the end<br />
they are decent human beings as individuals. But<br />
Scollectively, here they are wrong. They talk about their<br />
responsibilty and so on. what about the blokes in the RAAF.<br />
The pilots in the RAAF. </p>
<p>PM: 1( cont) These fellows in the civil airlines are really<br />
using their muscle to get a thirty percent increase. Their<br />
average salary is eighty thousand dollars. Eighty thousand<br />
Sdollars for flying less than ten hours a week. Now the<br />
Sblokes in the RAAF. The highly qualified pilots and that,<br />
Sfifty thousand. Now that is a comparison. Now those blokes<br />
are there and in the end, preparing to risk their life for<br />
their country and flying, in a sense, in much more dangerous<br />
conditions. MAUMILL: Let's talk about the blokes in the RAAF. It is<br />
Ssimply not on, is it, to use them to fly commercial<br />
aircraft. PM: They've talked about using them to fly commercial<br />
aircraft and then you read the Australian Newspaper today.<br />
Now what an exercise by the Australian.<br />
MAUMILL: So you've never suggested it.<br />
S PM14: What we have said is that RAAF aircraft can be used.<br />
IMAUMILL: And what about the suggestion that you would use<br />
Qanta's pilots. That's not on either because they said they<br />
won't do it.<br />
PM: Well we are not certain to what that position is to<br />
Swhet er, on existing services, where they are flying between<br />
, Australian capital cities, whether they might not be<br />
available, certainly for emergency cases and that may be<br />
possible. But to have this misrepresentation.<br />
Misrepresentation that we were talking about using RAAF<br />
Spilots to fly commercial aircraft. I mean, I wish people<br />
would just particularly when there are newspapers like<br />
that who are supposed to have some sense of<br />
responsibility. It is not too difficult to get something<br />
like ' that right.<br />
MAUMILL: No its not. Shree have you got the Prime<br />
O Minister's coffee. What about bringing it in, will you.<br />
S Because we want to continue the questioning and I noticed he<br />
is getting tense.<br />
PM: ( inaudible)<br />
' MAUMILL: Prime Minister, if this battle between pilots, the<br />
companies and the Government continues is there any<br />
possibility the Government will assist the airlines by<br />
providing them with some funding if they should stand the<br />
pilots down.<br />
SPM: No. It wouldn't be a question of providing them with<br />
funding. I mean I will tell you exactly as it is, as the<br />
, matters raised. There has been a question raised by them as<br />
to whether, if they are going to be in a situation where<br />
they ' are going to cop enormous losses, whether if it went on<br />
for some considerable period of time whether we would look<br />
' at the question of waving some fees that they... charges.<br />
We've said no. We are not going to be doing that.<br />
* i </p>
<p>PM: time<br />
Wi t 4.<br />
( cont) I said that if this dispute goes on for some<br />
well you can raise that and we will look at it.<br />
iout committment, without prejudice, we will look at it.<br />
MAUMILL: You haven't done a deal<br />
SPM: No.<br />
MAUMILL: with Sir Peter and the others to say look<br />
you pull these blokes on and we will back you up with money.<br />
PM: No there has been no such deal and I am putting it<br />
absolutely..... they raised the question. They said " This<br />
is going to cost us an enormous amount of money and the<br />
question of paying the fees and the charges to Government.<br />
Would you be prepared to look at that." And I said " Well,<br />
this has got to be fought honestly. Now if it goes on for a<br />
long time we can look at that." But there has been no<br />
comittment.<br />
MAUMILL: I understand that some international pilots have<br />
been asked to contribute to a very substantial fighting fund<br />
to support their domestic colleagues. Are you aware of<br />
that. If that is true or not?<br />
PM: No.<br />
MAUMILL: We had calls this morning from someone purporting<br />
to be an international pilot, who said that<br />
PM: You know some of these calls you get. mean I don't<br />
know whether you heard the program I've been on this<br />
morning. You get a call and a bloke purports he says<br />
" I'm a pilot of seventeen years and before that I was an<br />
engineer." It turns out he was an apprentice, so he says,<br />
for hine months, that makes him an engineer. I mean a lot<br />
of these calls that you get, now people can say anything.<br />
Now they may be right, they may be wrong, I don't know. But<br />
it w6uldn't entirely surprise me Bob, if they ee trying to<br />
get # ome financial support. But you know thatAT talking<br />
about the rest of the world international pilots<br />
intetesting to see just what their own President,<br />
Fitzsimmons, said about their position compared to the rest<br />
of the world.<br />
MAUMILL: We will talk about it in a moment. Ian Craig is a<br />
great admirer of yours and a great supporter of yours,<br />
Skeeping in mind you interest in horse racing....<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
MAUMILL: ,. is thundering to me down the line that he has<br />
, got a breathless public waiting to hear his selections in<br />
ra'c ing information, which will only take a couple of<br />
Iminutes.<br />
SBreak I p<br />
.1 r<br />
N^ ii </p>
<p>Maumill: Jill's waiting on the line. Jill, have you got<br />
something more edifying to say, or are you going to give me a<br />
history lesson?<br />
Callers No, I hope not. Mr Hawke...<br />
PM: Yes Jill.<br />
Caller: Mr Hawke, I want to talk to you about super. I'm<br />
apolitical, however,, I must Bay I found Peacock's reply to the<br />
Budget was shallow anid gave no actual indication of any real<br />
policies. Having Bald that, can you please tell me, Mr Hawke,<br />
regarding super, ( inaudible) estimates within ten years,<br />
approximately 60 billion will be available for investment. if<br />
the 20-30 rule was in place it could result in greater investment<br />
within Australia to help reconstruct industry and promote<br />
( inaudible)<br />
PM Well, the 20/ 30 rui~ b used to be there before as a means of<br />
directing some of the investment into government paper, but with<br />
the very significant changes we've made in deregulation of the<br />
financial sector, and most particularly in eliminating the<br />
deficit you know when we came to office we were looking at a<br />
nine billion dollar deficit vwe've transformed that into a nine<br />
billion dollar surplus. So the demand from the Government point<br />
of view to support the Government paper is obviously not there in<br />
the way it was, so we've opened up the system and what we've<br />
really tackled, Jill, is the situation where there hasn't been a<br />
greaL pzxipeABILy Lo unve ini Auustralia and we are now, by the very<br />
significant changes we're making in the superannuation system,<br />
making it more attractive for people to set aside during their<br />
working life income which they will dedicate to providing for<br />
their retirement and so there won't be there'll be positive<br />
incentives and there'll be absence of high marginal tax rates on<br />
savings. And in this way, we'll generate the sort of flow of<br />
funds into superannuation which are talked about and this will </p>
<p>mean that there will be available for investment and productive<br />
enterprises in Australia much more money than there would have<br />
otherwise been. People have tended. to actually consume; spend<br />
their income, now there'll be much more incentive to save and<br />
that can go into productive investment.<br />
Maurnills It's been applauded, hasn't it? Even your most vocal<br />
critics in the financial press have applauded the moves relating<br />
to superannuation in the Budget. But one thing that does haunt<br />
us a little bit is the possibility that government may step in<br />
and be able to dictate the areas of investment for the super<br />
funds. Is that likely?<br />
PM: No, no it's not. It's very unreal to put that at us<br />
because if there's one thing we have done, it's to deregulate. I<br />
mean from day one, we have deregulated the financial sector.<br />
We've opened it up. We've brought more competition in the<br />
banks we've brought 16 foreign banks into here.. we ' ye released<br />
the stupifying and stultifying influence of government<br />
regulations so that the forces of competition can operate. So,<br />
on our record we' re not going to be doing that sort of thing.<br />
Maumill: Let's go to line one. Helen's joined us. Morning<br />
Helen. Caller: Hello, Mr Hawke.<br />
PM: G'day, Helen.<br />
Caller: How are you?<br />
PM: Great. How are you?<br />
Callers I just want to say I don'It want to whinge about<br />
nothing... I think you are the tops. Your wife, Mrs Hawke, is a<br />
lady and I just want to say, Bob, I think you're terrific because<br />
you're about the I'm an old lady... and of the alli the<br />
people of all the Ministers there've been, you would be the<br />
most friendliest man that ever walked the earth.<br />
PM: Thanks Helen. Thanks very much, Helen. I the<br />
things that I've tried, you know, to do right for the public life<br />
is to stay as close as I can to the ordinary people. I did that<br />
all my years in the trade union movement and I've known this<br />
rough old fellow opposite me, young Maumill, I mean you can't get<br />
closer to people than this rough old fellow.<br />
Maumill: Yes...<br />
PM: Thanks very much, Helen.<br />
Maumill: Let's move on a bit. I'll1 f ind a tougher one than<br />
that. No more big raps. Peter's on the line. Morning Peter.<br />
Caller: Good morning. </p>
<p>PM: G'day Peter.<br />
Caller: I would just like to ask Mr Hawke, like, you know, all<br />
this stance that the Government's taking about not giving the<br />
pilots their 30% pay rise that they want...<br />
PM; Yeah.<br />
Caller: I'd like to know why doesn't the Government take the<br />
same sort of stance when Htigh Court judges and politicians want<br />
a 30 and<br />
PM: Well, okay Peter, we'll knock that one over very quickly for<br />
you, mate. Let's take the High Court Judges first of all. The<br />
legal situation in regard to remuneration of judges is that we<br />
have a Remuneration Tribunal set up under the law and they<br />
consider, in the same way as the Conciliation and Arbitration<br />
Commission considers those on awards, their they have the<br />
Remuneration Tribunal. They brought down a recommendation some<br />
I time ago which recommended very, very much larger increases and<br />
we refused to go ahead and do that. We've given, in fact, lesser<br />
increases than what was originally recommended by, if you like,<br />
the Judges the Arbitration Court for the Judges. Now,<br />
politicians boy oh boy, Peter, you really have come in there.<br />
Let's look at the facts. The facts are that under a law, there<br />
is a Remuneration Tribunal to set salaries make recommendations<br />
in regards to politicians. Time after time since I've been Prime<br />
Minister, we've knocked back those recommendations as being too<br />
big and seem likely to undermine the wage fixing system.<br />
Criticism that I've got from the Members of Parliament is that I<br />
won't accept the findings of their Arbitration Commission and<br />
I've done that because I'm not going to undermine the system.<br />
And, in fact, I had a stand-up, knock-down fight with my Caucus<br />
on this earlier this year when the Tribunal brought in a<br />
recommendation for increased salaries. Fair enough, there was a<br />
case for it for the blokes getting the increase, but I said I<br />
am not going to cop that because if we do, it will undermine the<br />
wages system. So Peter, thank you very much for bolstering my<br />
S argument in respect of the Judges and in respect of Members of<br />
Parliament. I took them on this is the Caucus.... I took them<br />
on, fought them, beat them for exactly the same reasons. I<br />
wasn't going to have Members of Parliament undermining the wages<br />
system and I am not going to have pilots on. $ 80,000 a year<br />
knocking over the wages system. So thanks for your support<br />
Peter.<br />
Maumill: So no-one can knock over the wages system. if they do,<br />
they pull you on.<br />
PM: I had a situation here where for six and a half<br />
years,... your listeners, Bob ordinary people out there wage<br />
and salary earners supported by their wives and husband-. have<br />
exercised very, very considerable wage restraint. There are this </p>
<p>day a million and a half more of our fellow Australians in work<br />
,,* twice as fast a rate of job creation in the rest of the world.<br />
Why? Because ordinary Australian men and women have exercised<br />
wage restraint and their kids are in jobs now that wouldn't have<br />
been in jobs because those people have exercised restraint. And<br />
I am not, while I'm Prime Minister, going to stand aside and let<br />
a privileged, already very highly paid group of people, destroy<br />
the Australian economy. I wouldn't allow it in respect of<br />
Members of Parliament, I wouldn't allow it in respect to any<br />
people and I'm certainly not going to allow it in regard to<br />
pilots. Maumill: I'm sure you'll be interested in this, it's correct<br />
weight at Rosehill in the trifecta on race one it's $ 422.80 and<br />
don't blame it on the pilots.<br />
PM: How many units did you have, mate?<br />
Maumill: I wasn't on it. That's the bad news. $ 422.80 on the<br />
trifecta on race one, Rosehill correct weight. Let's go back<br />
to the board. George is with us. Good morning George.<br />
Caller: Morning. I don't expect an answer from the Prime<br />
Minister straight on this one.<br />
PM: Well, what are you wasting your time for, George?<br />
Maumill: Yeah, goodbye George. You know I've got to keep him in<br />
good mood George, ' cause I want him back and you can't go on<br />
and attack him. Go away George. Next one Ron, are you with us<br />
Ron? Caller: Yea.<br />
Maumill: Go ahead Ron. Don't say anything cute or you'll drop<br />
out. PM: No, he won't. But; I mean, it seems a bit funny to ring up<br />
and say I don't expect an answer. I wasn't trying to be rude to<br />
George but if you don't expect an answer<br />
Maumill: Why ring in? Well, I was trying to be rude to George.<br />
Maumill: Are you there, Ron?<br />
Caller: Yeah, still here. Good morning, Mr Prime Minister.<br />
PM: G'day, Ron.<br />
Caller: Several calls ago, you were talking about<br />
superannuation... you were explaining the good things from the<br />
Budget the Budget that's just been brought out.<br />
PM: t Yes. </p>
<p>Caller: Now, I'm a war veteran.<br />
PM: t Yes.<br />
Caller: On a pension.<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
Caller: And I have a small superannuation sum.<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
Caller: Which I haven't got yet, I'm not quite 65 yet.<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
Caller: Which I have to cancel when I'm 65, or, you know, finish<br />
with the superannuation f und. Now, I cannot contribute because<br />
I'm on a pension, which is fair enough, but from 1 July last<br />
year, and this is what I've been told by the Taxation Department,<br />
there's been a tax of 15% on the interest earnings of the amount<br />
which is in superannuation fund that's only on the earnings<br />
from the interest which is fair enough. From there over a<br />
period of five years, ( inaudible) taxation will drop down at<br />
the end of five years there will be no taxation because of the<br />
being taxed on the interest ( inaudible) each year.<br />
Maumill: Yeah, okay Ron. What's your point mate?<br />
Caller: Well, the point is I'll be pulling it out in a lump sum<br />
because it's only small amount.<br />
Maumill: Yeah, good.<br />
Caller: Now,' I get taxed on that again ( inaudible) taxed on the<br />
lump sum. Now on top of... that again, that financial year, I'll be<br />
taxed the amount of say, for instance, the figure of $ 10,000,<br />
S gpelutst inmgy tpaexnesdi otnh ree bet imtaexs edb ecoanu saen I'ovred ignoatr ya samgaeldl pseunpseiroann. n uatiIo'nm<br />
fund. I'm also being taxed from the first dollar for the<br />
pension. This new Budget, is that going to rectify that position<br />
at all?<br />
PM: Yes. Obviously in regard to the pension situation, what<br />
we've done by a decision already, is that about 80% of those on<br />
pensions will not, in fact, be paying tax. We're moving into the<br />
situation where those in receipt of pensions or part pensions,<br />
will be taken out of the tax system altogether, Ron. That is<br />
part of the overall plan of encouraging people to save for their<br />
retirement. See, what's happened up until now is, you probably<br />
know from your own experience, that where you got ( inaudible)<br />
Maumill: MTahuem llw: o ol industry's in trouble China's not buying. </p>
<p>Have you spoken to John Kerin about this? The Australian Wool<br />
Corporation is buying most of our clip and China seems to have<br />
pulled out of the market. Are they likely to come back in and<br />
have you got any idea why they've gone cold on us?<br />
PM Oh, well, if you look at the wool marketing over the years,<br />
they come in and go out and there is not any, you know, constant<br />
reasons for a change in participation. I think<br />
Maumill: Nothing to do with your criticisms of the Chinese<br />
Government's actions in Tienamin Square?<br />
PM: I don't think so. I think on the evidence we've got, the<br />
Chinese understand that you know, this is a democracy. That<br />
we're going to make our statement known as to what we think about<br />
these sort of things. I believe that they'll make their economic<br />
judgements on the basis of what they see as in their best<br />
interests. The predictions that are made by the industry and by<br />
the Bureau of, you know, Agricultural, you know, researchers in<br />
that area that have got the responsibility for looking at these<br />
things. They believe that the commodity prices generally,<br />
including wool, that the outlook for this financial year is<br />
pretty good.<br />
Mauniill: Have you got any idea what the Saudis are on about in<br />
knocking back our live sheep export?<br />
PM: No, I must say I haven't. I mean, I've talked to our<br />
people, about that. We are assured that we don't have these<br />
diseases in our flocks. And there seems to be something more to<br />
it, so we've sent a high level mission over there, as you know,<br />
and I'll1 be very interested to see the report of what they have<br />
to say because I can't really....<br />
Mauniills John Kerin hasn't got any idea if it's just internal<br />
politics? PM: Well, there was a suggestion that it is Internal politics,<br />
but I can't say whether that's so or not and I don't want to<br />
attempt, you know, without knowledge, to intrude into if that<br />
is the case the domestic affairs of another country. But it<br />
certainly would be very disappointing if that were the case and<br />
our great farmers, and they are tremendous Australian farmers,<br />
very competitive and done a great job for us historically and<br />
presently and the productivity which they are constantly<br />
increasing. It would be terrible if they were, in fact,<br />
disadvantaged by Borne internal dispute. But the fact is that as<br />
far as you know, on the scientific grounds, there is no basis for<br />
what's been done.<br />
Maumill: We've got a series you seem to have a series of<br />
ongoing blues with the Greiner Government. I know there's<br />
obviously an ideological gap there between the two but some would<br />
say it is probably not as great as it used to be, but can't you </p>
<p>get on with Nick?<br />
PM: well, I mean, when we meet..... let me just give you an<br />
example. I mean we had a Premiers Conference. The first time he<br />
came along, he got on and did his little pantomime for the press<br />
and the public there and then we went into the actual meeting and<br />
he was as quie as a lamb. Now on this frigate spending, we had<br />
the meeting in my Cabinet room. He came down with Bob Carr, and<br />
people from Newcastle, and put his case,. and I said " Well,, now<br />
Nick, I recall that some months ago when I had to make a decision<br />
about an airport whether we had a third runway or went to<br />
. Badgery's Cre~ k a bloke called Nick Greiner hammered Hawke and<br />
said you've got to make the economically responsible decisionis<br />
that right? And he said, yeah. And I said I did it an<br />
economically responsible decision for the third runway. Now, I<br />
said, Nick, in respect of between the two bid6, if one is very<br />
much more expensive than the other, should I take the<br />
economically responsible decision? Nick Greiner said yes in<br />
front of everyone there he said yes, sure. I said alright, now<br />
let's be specific Nick. What sort of margin would you allow mehow<br />
much more expensive could I allow if it were Newcastle, how<br />
much more expensive could it be and still go to be economically<br />
responsible? He said That was his answer In other<br />
words if it was more than 2% It wouldn't be economically<br />
responsible. And what was the difference? Ton percent<br />
350 million. It wasn't 2% more expensive<br />
Maumill: It didn't stop him going out....<br />
PM: It didn't stop him going out. So that's the answer to your<br />
question. How do you deal with someone like that? There in the<br />
Cabinet room, he gives his answer, then goes out and tells<br />
another story. It's a bit hard to deal with people like that.<br />
Maumill: Does that mean you don't get on with him too well?<br />
PM: Maunmills ( inaudible).<br />
PM: Well, I mean, I've been civil, and decent and responsible<br />
with him, but I mean when I get confronted with that sort of<br />
double standards, I mean, I'll react.<br />
Maumill: Prime Minister, thanks for joining us today. I've got<br />
to go back to Ian Craig. Pass on my very best regards to Mr<br />
Keating. I hope the silk pyjamas fit. It's nice to know he's<br />
getting out of the sort of working class flannelette ones.<br />
PM: Yes, yes sexy black ones.<br />
Maumill: Sleeping in something more in keeping with his daytime<br />
image. Good to talk to you again. We look forward to speaking<br />
to you again soon. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
