<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10728</transcript-id>
    <title>21 May 1998                                                                 TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                PRESS CONFERENCE - PARLIAMENT HOUSE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/05/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...............................................</p>
<p>Ladies and gentlemen, the announcement that President Soeharto is</p>
<p> to resign is, of course, a very historic moment for Indonesia and</p>
<p> is a very momentous event in the life of that country. All along,</p>
<p> Australia has wanted an orderly and peaceful transition and that the</p>
<p> matter be resolved in accordance with the constitutional processes</p>
<p> of the Indonesian State. I welcome the fact that the changes that</p>
<p> are occurring are within the framework of the Indonesian Constitution</p>
<p> because it's our desire that change and transition to a more</p>
<p> open society, both politically and economically, should be orderly.</p>
<p> It should be without bloodshed and it should be in a way that respects</p>
<p> the current constitutional forms of the Indonesian State.</p>
<p>I want to acknowledge the contribution that President Soeharto has</p>
<p> made to the stability and the development of his country over the</p>
<p> last 32 years. Whatever may be the debate about aspects of his Government</p>
<p> and whatever may be the circumstances immediately leading to his resignation,</p>
<p> nothing can alter the fact that he has, over 32 years, brought enormous</p>
<p> stability to that country. He has presided over a significant increase</p>
<p> in the living standards of many people, many millions of people in</p>
<p> Indonesia. He has been responsible for implementing policies which</p>
<p> have brought about a reduction in absolute levels of poverty within</p>
<p> Indonesia. And nothing that has occurred in recent times can alter</p>
<p> that fact, although as with any person, the judgement of history about</p>
<p> him will be involved and tied up with debate about the methods of</p>
<p> his Government and debate about the wisdom of his policies.</p>
<p>But it is important at the end of this era for Indonesia, and today</p>
<p> does in a very real sense mark the end of an era for Indonesia, it</p>
<p> is very important that his contribution to his own country and to</p>
<p> the region be acknowledged, and acknowledged very fully. I congratulate</p>
<p> Dr Habibie on his appointment as President. My Government will cooperate</p>
<p> fully with Dr Habibie's administration as we have in the past</p>
<p> cooperated with President Soeharto, or the former President Soeharto's</p>
<p> administration. As indeed we will cooperate fully with any future</p>
<p> Indonesian administration, particularly one appointed in accordance</p>
<p> with the constitutional processes of that country.</p>
<p>There is a very big challenge ahead of the new administration in Indonesia.</p>
<p> It is important that international economic confidence be built. It's</p>
<p> important that the process of transition to a more open, political</p>
<p> form, which is so obviously the desire of many millions of people</p>
<p> in Indonesia, that that process be continued, that process be maintained</p>
<p> to the full because it's always been our wish that that should</p>
<p> occur.</p>
<p>Australia has taken the view all along that it is not our role to</p>
<p> give advice as to who should be the President or who should be in</p>
<p> positions of authority in Indonesia. That is a matter for the Indonesian</p>
<p> people and for the processes of the Indonesian State. We have been</p>
<p> a friend. We have been a close friend, a helpful friend, an understanding</p>
<p> friend, not always an uncritical friend but a friend for the long</p>
<p> haul and that would be our policy into the future as it has been our</p>
<p> policy up to the present time. I just have a moment for one or two</p>
<p> questions.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, how will the fact that Dr Habibie, a close associate</p>
<p> of Mr Soeharto, the fact that he will have a fixed five years term,</p>
<p> how will that affect international confidence in Indonesia?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well my understanding is that he is to fill out the unexpired residue</p>
<p> of President Soeharto, the former President Soeharto's term.</p>
<p> I don't want to comment on the decision that has been made in</p>
<p> accordance with the processes of the Indonesian State. A process of</p>
<p> transition to a different kind of society, both politically and economically</p>
<p> is obviously to some degree under way.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, do you think that the now Habibie administration should</p>
<p> go ahead with the vow which former President Soeharto made, and hold</p>
<p> elections as soon as possible?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I believe that the commitment for a reform process, and I understand</p>
<p> some Ministers have indicated already in Indonesia that that will</p>
<p> be adhered to, that the reform process should, outlined by Mr Soeharto,</p>
<p> should be adhered to and I also would imagine that it would be certainly</p>
<p> the right thing to hold the elections as well. I mean, we are for</p>
<p> transition and change and reform but we respect the constitutional</p>
<p> processes of Indonesia. And we, of course, accept the fact that it's</p>
<p> a matter for the Indonesian people to determine the pace at which</p>
<p> that should occur, recognising at all times that we want to avoid</p>
<p> bloodshed and violence and civil unrest.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, do you think that Mr Habibie should do what President</p>
<p> Soeharto said he would do the other day and not be a candidate for</p>
<p> the Presidency next time around?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well that is a matter for him. I can't and won't give any</p>
<p> public advice on that. That is entirely a matter for him.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do you see any implications for the bilateral relationship now that...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I would have thought that the bilateral relationship has come through</p>
<p> an extraordinarily difficult time, certainly on the Indonesian part</p>
<p> in very good shape because we have been a real friend. We have been</p>
<p> there to help where we could and where it was appropriate. We have</p>
<p> not been a disinterested observer but we have respected Indonesian</p>
<p> sovereignty and we have accepted the right of the Indonesian people</p>
<p> to determine their own future. Friends like that are rare in these</p>
<p> circumstances and I would believe that so far from the events of the</p>
<p> past few months, having weakened the bilateral relationship they have</p>
<p> probably strengthened it and it gives to the Australian Government</p>
<p> a capacity to work closely with the new administration and, indeed,</p>
<p> with any future administration in Indonesia.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST::</p>
<p>Prime Minister, the economic situation there is getting worse by the</p>
<p> day, presumably even the army is having difficulty paying its troops.</p>
<p> Do you have any particular initiatives that you think should be put</p>
<p> in place?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER::</p>
<p>Well we've already put in place a number of initiatives and we've</p>
<p> been very generous. And I don't think it's appropriate at</p>
<p> this stage for me to be speculating about further initiatives. It's</p>
<p> only a couple of weeks since we announced a $30 million aid package.</p>
<p> You are aware of the IMF bail out and you are also aware of the trade</p>
<p> credit arrangements that we have made in relation to some of our exporters</p>
<p> which are of help to Indonesia. We've been a very generous donor</p>
<p> friend and helper already and at this stage I am not speculating about</p>
<p> further assistance. I'll have one more question and then I must</p>
<p> go to a meeting. Yes?</p>
<p>JOURNALIST::</p>
<p>(inaudible) since Mr Soeharto said he was going to stand down and</p>
<p> (inaudible). Now all that has happened is he has stood down, his man,</p>
<p> Habibie, is in place and the reform council has been scrapped.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER::</p>
<p>Well let's just wait and see how things evolve. I think it's</p>
<p> important that the guiding principle in all of these things be respect</p>
<p> for the constitutional processes and the avoidance of friends and</p>
<p> spokesmen within countries who are friends giving kerbside, preemptory</p>
<p> opinions as to what might happen in the future.</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
<p> ENDS</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
