<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9143</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON PJ KEATING MP LAUNCH OF WORLD SUMMIT ON TELEVISION AND CHILDREN TWO - WAY VIDEO LINK WITH MARK MITCHELL IN MELBOURNE 2 MARCH 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/03/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009143.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINSITER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
LAUNCH OF WORLD SUMMIT ON TELEVISION AND CHILDREN<br />
TWO-WAY VIDEO LINK WITH MARK MITCHELL IN MELBOURNE<br />
2 MARCH 1994<br />
MM: Prime Minister, Mr Keating, welcome. Thank you for being with us<br />
again today.<br />
PM. Pleasure. Well I was with you a couple of years ago with Janet<br />
( Holmes a Court) and Patricia Edgar and David Hill wthen we launched,<br />
I think, Lift Off on that occasion. And that was a very successful<br />
launch and I am pleased to be back.<br />
MM: Since that time Mr Keating you have made your position and your<br />
feelings about childrens television very clear.<br />
PM: Well I think that I have. I have tried to say that I think what children<br />
see on television is important in the way they think. The sensitivities<br />
they develop in their lives, their value system, and I think we have at<br />
least made some mark on commercial television in requiring that<br />
violence is not being telecast at times that kids are looking at<br />
television, and generally just making a more general point. That is,<br />
that a lot of the grade material and rubbish which is on television<br />
ought to be improved and-it is-organisations such-as theChildren's<br />
Television Foundation which is, of course, leading the role in d~ oing<br />
that.<br />
MM. There is a theory that children enjoy it, that sort of rubbish.<br />
PM: Well I think they will watch what is there for them to see. But in some<br />
of the products which the foundation has produced where it is kids<br />
looking at themselves rather than seeing someone banged up or Ninja<br />
Turtles, or whatever it might be, whether it is violence and other things,<br />
when they actually see something about themselves, in their own<br />
environment or a contemporary environment, particularly when they<br />
recognise the contemporary Australian quality of something they are<br />
looking at, they are much more interested. And I think the support<br />
TEL: 10. Mar. 94 10: 15 No. 002 3 P. 02 </p>
<p>ILL: 2<br />
which the various things; Round the Twist and Lift Off and those things<br />
have had demonstrates that point.<br />
MM: I think that is certainly true, Prime Minister, of Round the Twist. It was<br />
very Australian, Australian accents, Australian concepts, they have<br />
even had a ghost in the dunny. I guess the ghost in the dunny or the<br />
loo or the toilet, whatever it is called, wherever they watch it, is a fairly<br />
universal thing for kids.<br />
PM: Well, I think it certainly brought a lot of attention from Australian<br />
children and support, and of course with Lift Off, I think it had<br />
something like a 5 million viewing audience in Britain and it has been a<br />
great success there, even greater than some of the so called popular<br />
programs like Mash and things like that. So, it has produced its own<br />
reward and as Janet said a few moments ago the BBC is now in a coproduction<br />
with the foundation and I think that is the proof of the<br />
pudding.<br />
MM: 5 million viewers in fact watched Round the Twist every Friday night. It<br />
out rated Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles at a time when they were<br />
enormously big everywhere in the world. Do you remember them at<br />
all?<br />
PM. Yes, what ever happened to them? They vanished off the scene.<br />
MM: They didn't have the foundation behind them, I guess. I believe that<br />
there is some good news about Round the Twist, Prime Minister,<br />
Patricia Edgar tells me that a feature film is being considered, is in fact<br />
in the pipeline. So, that will be something to look to. I believe you<br />
have something very special to announce today.<br />
PM: Well I am very pleased to be able to announce, following discussions I<br />
had with Janet and Patricia last year, that I am able to announce the<br />
first world summit on television and children. Now, this is not just an<br />
Australian first, it is a world first. It will be in Melbourne next year, the<br />
Delegates are coming from around the-ASEAN area, from China, from<br />
the United States, from Japan and its objective will be to look at the<br />
information highway, the thing Mr Gates was telling us about so<br />
eloquently a week or two ago, the fact that television will be interactive<br />
not just simply delivering product to children and others, but giving the<br />
capacity for interaction and therefore the important focus we should<br />
now have on the cultural impact of that medium, and this is the first<br />
international opportunity to get that focus. I think it also will underwrite<br />
the status of the quality of Australian children's television product and<br />
our foundation.<br />
This will be a good thing for us because I think we are leading the<br />
world in thinking about television product for children and the<br />
organisation of television time for children. And given the fact that we<br />
LL: 10. Mar. 94 10: 15 No. 002 P. 03 </p>
<p>3<br />
are now in this country about to embark upon pay television, where it<br />
can't be that many years away where we are looking at the capacity for<br />
interactive television, having if you like the world leader, and I think we<br />
are, in this medium of material for children and thought about children<br />
and television, having us in fact host this conference and manage it is,<br />
I think, a good thing for children around the world, for children in<br />
Australia, and a good thing for Australia's reputation as a country that<br />
has got good values and cares about its children.<br />
MM: Thank you very much, Prime Minister, and thanks for your ongoing<br />
support.<br />
PM: Good, Mark, pleasure. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
