<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9045</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ KEATING, M.P. SEATTLE, USA - THURSDAY 18 NOVEMBER, 1993</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/11/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009045.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
c CIL<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
E OE PROOF COPY<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF UiNTERVIEW WITH THE PRIME MI1NISTER, THE HON PJ<br />
KEATING, M. P.<br />
SEATTLE, USA THURSDAY 18 NOVEMIBER, 1993<br />
J: Prime Minister, what's the minimum that we could expect out of this meeting if you<br />
are able to regard it as a success?<br />
PM: The first success of it is that it's actually happening. That the APEC structure has<br />
brought to it the President of the United States and all the leaders of the Asia Pacific<br />
area, who are now members of APEC. So the fact that it's on; the fact that it's been<br />
given this kind of status; that people have come for it, means that APEC will have<br />
so much more authority in each of the member countries, and of course in the<br />
United States.<br />
So I think that's the first thing; because that, then, gives the bureaucracy of each<br />
country the trade and foreign ministers of each country a signal that the group<br />
at a leadership level wants to continue this process.<br />
I think that the dynamics of the leaders' meeting, itself, will be important. Leaders<br />
invariable, I have found, will always do more than ministerial groups largely<br />
serviced by bureaucracies. And this meeting is, of course, a free meeting in the<br />
sense that there is only one other person here with each leader, and who will largely<br />
be an interpreter, so it really is the leaders, themselves.<br />
J: President Clinton has arrived here today talking about how this meeting is about<br />
looking after America's own interests, but also about the fact that he doesn't want<br />
NAFTA just to be about Mexico, but opening up trade with the whole of Latin<br />
America. Are those bad signals for Australia? </p>
<p>PM: Oh no, I don't think so. I think if APEC means growth and jobs for Americans, it<br />
means growth and jobs for Australians, as well. And I think that's why we're all in<br />
it. We think there is some common good that can come from this. Now, no doubt<br />
President Clinton is speaking to his own constituency, as each of us do. But things<br />
which facilitate trade, which liberalize trade in an area where we've already seen<br />
quite substantial growth, and has a potential for greater growth, are going to be<br />
good for all of us. You can just see what's happening already with Australia's<br />
exports. Australia's exports have been booming, and they are largely because the<br />
area of the world we live in is now the fastest-growing area of the world.<br />
J: Prime Minister, do you sense that President Clinton's NAIFTA victory has given<br />
him a lift and more enthusiasm for APEC?<br />
PM: Well, I think it was a very big test of American official opinion about whether the<br />
United States wanted to be introspective and reclusive, or whether it wanted to get<br />
out there and trade with the best and expand its horizons through trade. America<br />
has been a great free-trading country, and a lot of America's growth has come<br />
through free-trade. And it was doubting itself, doubting its competitiveness;<br />
doubting its capacities, and I think this vote will send a very big signal. And the<br />
fact that a Democratic president has actually pushed NAFrA through, with the<br />
support of Republicans in the Congress sends a very big message to American<br />
business, and, I think, the world.<br />
J: The Malaysian Prime Minister says he's glad he didn't come. Is that a problem, or<br />
are you glad that he didn't, too?<br />
PM: No, no, no, it doesn't matter whether he comes or not, in a sense. It's better if he<br />
does, but if he doesn't it's his own business. I mean, there are 15 countries here;<br />
there's half the world's production here; and if you don't want to be at it, it's your<br />
problem.<br />
J: Mr. Keating, you've been pushing very hard for a formalized name change to the<br />
APEC Economic Community. You were pressing that theme as recently as last<br />
night. Other nations seem less convinced. Isn't that going to be a bit of a setback?<br />
PM: Well, it just depends on how the leaders' meeting goes. I mean, the President made<br />
a speech in Tokyo and one in Korea, this year, talking about an Asia Pacific<br />
Community, or Pacific Community, rather. We've been speaking about APEC<br />
becoming a Community not just simply an information secretariat, but more of a<br />
Community. It does present difficulties to some countries which have powered the<br />
non-aligned movement, for instance, and you might see becoming a Community </p>
<p>with the United States, as cutting across, if you like, their position. But the<br />
important thing will be whether APEC adopts the work programs which it has that<br />
is, whether the substance is going to be accelerated the substance of its work.<br />
That's going to be the test, rather than what the acronym means. But I stil think<br />
that whatever anyone thinks, we are moving here towards... If we do things as a<br />
collective, we are moving towards a Community.<br />
J: Chile is now being admitted to APEC; that was against your stated wishes earlier in<br />
the year. We see President Clinton extending his view for NAFTA into South<br />
America. Isn't there a real chance that APEC could take a secondary role?<br />
PM: Oh, no, not with NAFTA. NAFTA may well extend into South America, but<br />
NAFTA will end up being a sub-group of APEC, I think, in terms of the trade of<br />
these particular countries into the region.... ( interruption)<br />
J: The question was, with the President today expanding NAFTA's horizons into South<br />
America, and Chile now being admitted into APEC, isn't there a chance that APEC<br />
itself may be given a secondary role by the Americans?<br />
PM: Well, I've always seen NAFTA as a trades... as APEC grows, as a subgroup of<br />
APEC, and that's true whether NAFTA is simply Canada or Mexico, or whether it<br />
goes further into South America. The main thing about APEC is, we need to<br />
deepen it before we broaden it, and I think that's one of the key points. That is, to<br />
make sure that we know what APEC intends to do, what work it should undertake,<br />
how we will facilitate trade and liberalize trade, and those should be the focus. So<br />
in other words, APEC proves its worth before we invite everybody on board,<br />
because we don't want the thing just to sort of dissipate and become a very broad<br />
body which anyone can belong to, but doesn't mean very much.<br />
J: Should Chile be a member?<br />
PM: Well, this is a matter for debate, I mean the Americans have interests in South<br />
America. It borders the Pacific Ocean, and we've never made any firm criteria<br />
about what constitutes qualification for APEC membership. I think the APEC group<br />
is going to be quite wise about borders. They'll take on a few natural ones, but repel<br />
borders for a while.<br />
J: But they haven't repelled Chile for more than a year, if it gets in next year, isn't<br />
that defeat for you?<br />
PM: Oh, no, no, these things are not wins and defeats, Laurie, these are only matters of<br />
whether we can, in the longer run, define what APEC membership should be. </p>
<p>J: Are you happy with ( inaudible)?<br />
PM: I think we should define APEC membership. We should be able to say what defines<br />
an APEC member, rather than simply just spreading, you know, for instance, would<br />
it be Colombia, Peru, the states of Central America, India, or the old Soviet Far<br />
East, Russia, the Russian Pacific. These are all questions which I think the<br />
constituency has got to think about.<br />
J: In terms of sending a message to GATT, are you still pushing for a cut in tariffs,<br />
and is ASEAN going along with it?<br />
PM: Well, I don't think you've caught up on the debate on APEC, with all due respects.<br />
I mean, we're not a round of tariff cutting in this stage, I mean. But the trade<br />
liberalizing is going to be very much part of the agenda of APEC, but it will<br />
probably follow trade facilitation. That is the thing where there is I mean, a lot<br />
of member states of APEC are liberalizing now Indonesia announced a package a<br />
week or so ago; we've been doing it, now, for years. This is true also in the United<br />
States. I think the thing that's going to focus APEC's work, mostly, will be trade<br />
facilitation. That is, things like standard customs laws, standard business laws,<br />
general recognition of standards these sorts of things.<br />
J: You were looking for more than a declaration, weren't you, to GATT?<br />
PM: I'm not sure what you're saying.<br />
J: Well, I understood from what Trade Minister Cook said, and others, that you were<br />
looking for something more than just a declaration of principles. You were looking<br />
for some sort of gesture by APEC to GATT.<br />
PM: Oh, well, GATT's a different question. Before you asked me about APEC, whether<br />
it had a trade-liberalizing role. That's got nought to do with GATT. GATT's a<br />
different matter. Well, it may well be the leaders will say something about GATT.<br />
About the desirability of the successful conclusion of the GATT. I mean, I would<br />
certainly be happy to say that.<br />
J: The Emminent Persons Group has suggested that the Seattle meeting, given a<br />
blockage in the Uruguay Round, should offer some specific measures as a way of<br />
getting the Round unblocked.<br />
PM: Well, I don't know whether this meeting would be seeking to garner commitments<br />
from countries in the Uruguay Round. I think this meeting would be inclined to say </p>
<p>that the Uruguay Round should be successfully concluded. Some member states<br />
have to give ground, to conclude it. But again, the commitments which are on the<br />
table from member countries of the GATT are there now. I don't see this meeting<br />
actually being able to take specific trade concessions from constituent members and<br />
offering them the GATT context. I just don't think that's going to happen. What<br />
will happen, if anything about GATT happens, is that we would say that we should<br />
reach a conclusion of the Round by the 15th of December, so that the fast-track<br />
authority which President Clinton has, can be exercised by the Congress. Now, this<br />
is an important grouping, and were we to say that, it would have some weight.<br />
J: Prime Minister, are you prepared to allow Conrad Black to lift his holding in John<br />
Fairfax up 25 percent?<br />
PM: Well, he hasn't asked me. He hasn't put any specific proposal. I saw Conrad Black<br />
the other day, he pays me the courtesy of a visit whenever he visits his assets in<br />
Australia his business. Not always, of course, mostly. And it's mostly... as all<br />
proprietors do, asked for something. Now, in Conrad's case, he wants a bigger<br />
share of John Fairfax Sons, and I've told him that there are real national interest<br />
questions here, and that something easily given isn't generally something worth<br />
having.<br />
J: He seems to believe that it also has something to do with the quality of reporting in<br />
the Fairfax newspapers. That if it becomes quote ' more balanced' unquote, in your<br />
words, that in those circumstances you would entertain lifting his holding above<br />
percent.<br />
PM: Oh no, I had a conversation with him late last year when John Hewson had offered<br />
him 50 percent equity in John Fairfax Sons, and I said to him, " Oh, I wouldn't<br />
consider that." I would consider going to 25 percent, because his claim was that he<br />
couldn't run the business at 14.9 percent; that he had just concluded that day, a<br />
meeting at the Opera House where he had been pilloried in running the business<br />
with 14.9 percent, and I said, " Well, we'll think about it, but we want a<br />
commitment from you that the paper will be balanced. And if there is any notion<br />
that, you know, of bias, that is that you barrack for the Coalition, on the basis of<br />
your conservative proclivities in other places, then there's no way you would qualify<br />
as the kind of owner we would like." Now, as it turned out, I think the Herald's<br />
coverage was... I won't say it was balanced, because I think the whole media wrote<br />
the government off in the election campaign. But that said, that was in part, of<br />
course, the fault of some of their so-called, often-quoted Lbor strategists. But we'll<br />
leave them for another time. So therefore, after the election, I, on behalf of the<br />
Governent made good a commitment to reconsider them, and took them to<br />
But there have been no further specific requests, and certainly no commitment. </p>
<p>-6-<br />
J: But Mr. Keating, should a commercial dealing of that sort rest on your judgment<br />
about whether a media organization is fair to Labor?<br />
PM: No, not whether it's fair to Labor, but whether reporting is fair.<br />
J: But you're the judge, are you?<br />
PM: Well, I'm the Prime Minister. That's how I become the judge.<br />
ENDS </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
