<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18538</transcript-id>
    <title>National Disability Insurance Scheme to launch in 2013</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/04/2012</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
A National Disability Insurance Scheme will start in Australia from July 2013 in up to four locations across the country.</p>
<p>From mid 2013, about 10,000 people with significant and permanent disabilities will start to receive support.</p>
<p>By July 2014, that figure will rise to 20,000 people.</p>
<p>The timeframe announced today means the first stage of an NDIS will be delivered a full year ahead of the timetable set out by the Productivity Commission.</p>
<p>For the first time in Australia's history people with significant and permanent disability will receive lifetime care and support, regardless of how they acquired their disability.</p>
<p>The Gillard Government will fund our share of the cost of the initial stage of the NDIS in the May Budget.</p>
<p>A new National Disability Transition Agency, funded by the Australian Government, will be established to run the delivery of care and support to people with disability, their families and carers in the select locations.</p>
<p>We want Australians with disability to start benefiting from this fundamental reform as quickly as possible.</p>
<p>The initial launch locations will be determined in consultation with the states and territories - who have all agreed their shared responsibility for the fundamental reform of disability care and support.</p>
<p>The work done at these launch locations will give the Government vital information on how best to progress the national roll-out.</p>
<p>An NDIS will give all Australians with a significant disability the peace of mind to know that their care and support needs will be addressed, no matter where they live or how they acquired their disability.  </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
