<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3103</transcript-id>
    <title>NEW DATA SYSTEM</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/12/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003103.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
AUS 1IALIA,,-<br />
PRIME MINISTER PRESS STATEP1J2NT NO. 162<br />
17 December 1973<br />
NEW DATA SYSTEM<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr. Whitlam, announced today the<br />
appointment of a Committee to inquire into the development of<br />
a new integrated statistical information system to operate<br />
among departments concerned with the fields of social, welfare<br />
and economic programs.<br />
The committee will report on the general principles<br />
and administrative arrangements that would be necessary for the<br />
operation of such a system.<br />
It will report by 30 -March next year.<br />
Mr. Whitlam said to implement the Government's program<br />
a greater knowledge of statistics involved in these key areas<br />
was necessary. Greater co-ordination among departments was also<br />
needed. The new more uniform and up-dated system would also<br />
be of great assistance to private business and injustry.<br />
A more efficient and better organised data gathering system<br />
was necessary to achieve these aims. Because the committee<br />
had been asked to advise on the principles and administrative<br />
arrangements of a new system, its members were chosen for<br />
their knowledge of the Government's policies, experience in<br />
public administration and their technical expertise, Mr. Whitlam<br />
said. The members of the committee are:<br />
Professor L. F. Crisp<br />
Chairman<br />
Mr. B. Brogan,<br />
Consultant to the Department of the Prime Minister<br />
and Cabinet<br />
Mr. K. L. Brown,<br />
President of the Printing and Allied Trades Employers<br />
Federation </p>
<p>-2-<br />
Mr. R. Jolly,<br />
Australian Council of Trade Unions a<br />
Professor C. F. Wallace,<br />
Department of Information Science, Monash University<br />
A summary statement of the general considerations which<br />
have led the Government to review its information needs in related<br />
areas of social and economic policy has been prepared for the<br />
information and guidance of the committee. A copy is attached.<br />
The Prime Minister said that, although it was not intended<br />
that the committee should conduct a public inquiry, it would receive<br />
written submissions until 15 February 1974. The submissions should<br />
be forwarded to the committee's chairman, Professor L. F. Crisp,<br />
through the Secretary of the Prime Minister's Department. Since<br />
the committee's report will be concerned with the general principles<br />
and administrative arLangements that would enable close integration<br />
of the Government's data systems, submissions ' hould be limited to<br />
these matters, Mr. Whitlam said.<br />
CANBERRA, A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
