<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4040</transcript-id>
    <title>TEXT OF SPEECH GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER AT A CIVIC RECEPTION IN SYDNEY</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/02/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004040_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
F76/ 16<br />
EMBARGOED AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
EXPECTED AROUND 7 p. m.<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS FEBRUARY 2, 1976<br />
TEXT OF SPEECH GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER AT A CIVIC RECEPTION IN SYDNEY<br />
it is appropriate, in this group of people concerned with politics and<br />
administration at the state and local level, to discuss what tie Federal<br />
Government has been doing since the election.<br />
Our broad goals have already been stated. They are to get Australia moving<br />
towards prosperity again to control inflation and reduce unemployment.<br />
We are aiming at an Australia where people have the maximum opportunity to<br />
choose, work for, and achieve the life they want for themselves and not<br />
the sort of life that politicians and officials want for themr; where there<br />
is the broadest possible distribution of power and people are able to influence<br />
the decisions which affect their lives, where as few people as possible are<br />
in real need or are disadvantaged, and where those in need are provided with<br />
effective and personal assistance. These are the goals of the Liberal and<br />
National Country Parties.<br />
In Opposition, we developed a wide range of policies designed to give effect<br />
to these goals. The Australian people showed by their vote at the election<br />
that they preferred a Government committed to these goals and policies.<br />
But goals must be achieved and policies must be implemented this is where<br />
Government differs from Opposition. It has a new and important dimension.<br />
The ideals which attract support and which motivate political parties must<br />
be translated into reality.<br />
The first essential step in ensuring that policies become reality is to<br />
establish sound administrative practices. At this point policies and<br />
administration become inseparable. The best policies in the world can<br />
fail or produce consequences directly opposite to those intended<br />
if the administrative means of achieving them are not properly researched,<br />
or if there are no effective means of coordinating policy objectives.<br />
The administration, the decision making machinery must be capable or<br />
achieving the objects that are intended-On the other hand, th1e best<br />
administration cannot properly supply the policies to be implemented.<br />
A Government will be ineffective if it neglects either political goals<br />
or administrative means.<br />
To neglect administration, to ignore the way that things are done or the<br />
dif ficulties involved in partic ular ways * of doing things is ' to be an<br />
inadequate Government. It means falling into a process of instant decisionmaking<br />
which is unmindful of the consequences of decisions where off the<br />
cuff decisions are taken and not related to one another, or to the fact<br />
that administrative choices often prejudice achievement of policies. / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
Much of the work of the first few weeks of Government has been establishing<br />
the administrative structures and procedures on which the success or<br />
failure of the. Government will depend. Since the Liberal National Country<br />
Party Government was elected, we have concentrated on the major task of<br />
devising effective forms of decision-making, improving the administrative<br />
structures with which to implement policies and ensur that the policies<br />
we have initiated are properly implemented.<br />
Cabinet Government has been re-established, and improved by the institution of<br />
a system of Cabinet Committees which will be able to examine policies and<br />
actions thoroughly and expeditiously.<br />
The Administrative Review Committee has been established tinder Sir Henry Bland's<br />
Chairmanship to review Government expenditure and advise how waste and<br />
duplication within and between Government Departments and between Commonwealth<br />
and State Governments can be eliminated.<br />
The Economic Committee of Cabinet has been reviewing the activities of<br />
Departments. Extensive discussions have taken place with unions, business and community<br />
groups.<br />
We are moving very shortly to discuss with Premiers the introduction of major<br />
reforms in Federal-Stateñ relations. Australia cannot be administered well<br />
governed well-if all power is centralised in Canberra. This is the trend<br />
we have been heading in. The vital information necessary for efficient<br />
decisions is often most available at local or state levels. We believe that<br />
in longer term the effective and efficient Government of Australia depends<br />
on an appropriate decentralisation of power to state and local governent.<br />
Excessive centralisation betrays an attitude of mind that all wisdom resides<br />
in a few. This is not only insulting. It is also untrue. We have seen<br />
the consequences of excessive centralisation the unleashing of inflation<br />
and unemployment as the Federal Goviernment has taken more and more resources<br />
to itself.<br />
Effective decisions can only be taken if there is a willingness to consult<br />
with all sections of the community. This is why we very early had discussions<br />
with the trade unions. This is why, in the light of those discussions, we<br />
agreed to consider modifying our earlier stand on the Prices Justification<br />
Tribunal. Dogmatism must inevitably lead to bad Government. Measures<br />
which seem appropriate at one stage can indeed sometimes must be<br />
superseded by new knowledge, new events. The crucial thing is not to lose<br />
sight of the fundamental objectives. Flexibility in pursuit of the nations<br />
interests must never be allowed to degenerate into expediency.<br />
, A Government must be able to take hard decisions in a: ion' s i4nterests<br />
even if m~ sreans u'ouart. Tnhz fact is that Ln che economi area<br />
Australia has run out of soft options. Either we are serious as a people<br />
in wanting-to control rising prices and reduce unemployment or we are not.<br />
If we are serious we cannot keep deferring tough decisions andhoping the<br />
problem will go away. It will not go away. We have obligations to-all those<br />
people being harmed, and to all those people whose jobs would be imperilled.<br />
We will fail in our responsibilities if we are not prepared to show restraint as<br />
a community now. / 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
A 6.4% increase in wages and salaries would increase unemployment and inflation,<br />
and undermine the confidence necessary for economic recovery. This large<br />
increase would quickly lead to price rises. These in turn would lead to<br />
further wage claims. The vicious cycle has to be broken. The Argument<br />
that economic recovery must be led by consumer spending and that this spending<br />
will take place only after an increase in wages and salaries is mistaken.<br />
Consumer spending is important to economic recovery but consumers will only<br />
spend if they have confidence in the economy. The former Government tried to<br />
stimulate consumer spending.. In conditions of low confidence, it only resulted<br />
in increased saving people now save 17% of their earnings compared with the<br />
long term average of 10%. Confidence will be undermined by the consequences<br />
of large wage increases. The key to economic recovery is reducing inflation.<br />
Only in. this way will consumers spend more and business invest more. only in<br />
this way will we have jobs for all who want to work.<br />
For too long politicians, at all levels, have taken the easy way out. There<br />
are no easy options left.<br />
Those who suggest that the Australian people will not be prepared-to accept<br />
these hard but necessary decisions do Australians a grave disservice.<br />
When people are convinced that their over-riding common interest requires a<br />
tough course, I know they will support it. </p>
<p>R( ALU IS(<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
CORRECTIONS HAVE BEEN MADE TO THE PRIME MINISTER'S SYDNEY<br />
TOWN HALL SPEECH AS FOLLOWS:<br />
Page 3<br />
A 6.4 percent increase in wages and salaries would increase<br />
unemployment and inflation, and undermine the confidence necessary<br />
for economic recovery. This large increase would quickly lead<br />
to price rises. These in turn would lead to further wage claims.<br />
The vicious cycle has to be broken. The argument that<br />
economic recovery must be led by consumer spending has some<br />
validity. What we do question is the naive view that a money<br />
increase in wages will result in increased consumer pending<br />
at this time. Consumer spending is important to economic<br />
recovery but consumers will only spend if they have confidence in<br />
the economy. The former Government tried to stimulate consumer<br />
spending. In conditions of low confidence, it only resulted<br />
in increased saving people now save 17 percent of their earnings<br />
compared with the long term average of 10 percent. Confidence<br />
will be undermined by the consequences of large wage increases.<br />
The key to economic recovery is reducing inflation. Only in<br />
this way will we have jobs for all who want to work.<br />
For too long politicians, at all levels, have taken the easy<br />
way out. There are no easy options left.<br />
Those who suggest that the Australian people will not be prepared<br />
to accept these hard but necessary decisions do Australians<br />
a grave disservice. When people are convinced that their<br />
over-riding comrmon : interest requires a tough course, I know they<br />
will support it. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
