<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5196</transcript-id>
    <title>RHODESIAN CONSTITUTIONAL CONFERENCE</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/11/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005196.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
P R l E NA11NI.<br />
FOR MEDIA 16 NOVEMBER 1979<br />
RHODESIAN CONSTITUTIONAL CONP41ERE'J, CE<br />
The Prime Minister, the Rt. Honourable Malcolm Fraser, C. II., M. P.,<br />
said today that the Australian Government warmly welcomed the<br />
announcement from London that agreement has been reached at the<br />
Rhodesian Constitutional Conference on arrangements for the<br />
transitional period leading to the holding of elections in<br />
Rhodesia and the subsequent granting of legal independence<br />
from Britain.<br />
This represents a major step towards a just settlement of the<br />
problemts that have for many years brought tragedy and suffering<br />
to countless thousands of people in Rhodesia and neighbouring<br />
countri-es.<br />
Britain's decision to convene the Constitutional Conference<br />
followed consideration of the problem at the recent Commonwealth<br />
Heads of Government Meeting in Lusaka. At that meeting Australia<br />
played an active part in helping to establish agreement on the<br />
principles on which the London Conference is based. Since then,<br />
the Australian Government has followed the proceedings of the<br />
Conference with deep interest, and Australian views have been<br />
conveyed to the partLies principal and to other Commonwealth<br />
leaders aZ the Conferen-ce has oroceed7ed.<br />
The Conference has now moved through its first two phases,<br />
concerning the Constitution and transitional arrangements. it<br />
is now entering its third and final phase, discussion of ceasefire<br />
arrangements. Agreement on this will complete the work of the<br />
Conference and enable elections to take place. As -the Deputy<br />
Prime Minister announced on 9 November,' the Australian Government<br />
has indicated its willingness to participate in a Commonwealth<br />
group to monitor the ceasefire in Rhodesia, provided that all<br />
parties to the Conference reach final agreement on a settlement,<br />
and provided satisfactory arrangements for the Australian<br />
contribution are worked out with the British Government.<br />
That the Conference has come so far already, the Prime Minister<br />
said, reflects the skill of Lord Carrington's chairmanship and<br />
the willingness of all parties at the Conference to compromise<br />
in the interests of achieving a long-sought settlement which<br />
would have far-reaching benefits for the peace and security of<br />
all Southern Africa. All too often in the last thirty years, </p>
<p>2<br />
people have resorted to arms to resolve their political<br />
difficulties. This has been the case in Rhodesia, where<br />
difficult. problems of decolonisation have been complicated<br />
by the problem of race. Over the years this has led to the<br />
division of the people of Rhodesia into various contending<br />
groups, and to fighting and tensions between them which has<br />
flowed over into neighbouring countries and affected the<br />
peace and stability of the entire region.<br />
It is the strongly held hope of the<br />
Australian Government and people, and it is a hope that I share<br />
to the full, that the agreement reached in London reflects a<br />
lasting understanding among all the parties to the conflict<br />
that their happiness and security is inextricably linked to<br />
peace and the resolution of differences through peaceful means,<br />
tolerance and negotiated settlement. While fighting continues,<br />
the suffering and hardship will grow and racial tensions will<br />
increase even further, with the possibility of substantial<br />
interference by super powers. The dignity of the people of<br />
Southern Africa, the integrity of Southern Africa and the<br />
progress of Southern Africa demand a settlement. And that<br />
settlement may now be in sight.<br />
The success of the London Conference to date represents a most<br />
notable advance. It provides us with some real hope that with<br />
patience and good faith the spirit of Lusaka can prevail over<br />
the hatreds and suspicions of the past decades. If this can<br />
be achieved, then the people of Rhodesia can look forward to<br />
an optimistic future of a kind that has escaped them for far<br />
too long, and the achievements of the past few months will<br />
become an example for the rest of the world. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
