<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9398</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J.KEATING MP INTERVIEW WITH JOHN LAWS, RADIO 2UE, 3 NOVEMBER 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/11/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009398.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIMEMINISTER___<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
INTERVIEW WITH JOHN LAWS, RADIO 2UE, 3 NOVEMBER 1994<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
JL: Prime Minister, good morning and welcome.<br />
PM: Good morning, John.<br />
JL: How are you?<br />
PM: I'm good thank you. It's nice to be here.<br />
JL Good to have you here. When you talked about the banana republic<br />
on this program back in 1986, you remember it as well as I do.<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
JL: You were worried about the size of the current account deficit. Are you<br />
worried about It now?<br />
PM: Well, it is always something to keep our eye on, but the difference<br />
between then and now Is that Australia is a much changed, much<br />
reformed economy. The tariff barriers are down, we have broken the<br />
back of government spending In the past and in that period we were<br />
exporting about 14 per cent of all we produced and today we are<br />
exporting 22 per cent of all we produce.<br />
JL: OK but just back to the qupe-t ion. IS it 2 worry, are you worried about it<br />
now as you were In 1986?<br />
PM: No, I'm not because our capacity to service our current account debt<br />
has improved dramatically. Let me make this point to you clearly,<br />
John. In about 1985, about 21 per cent of our exports proceeds went<br />
to servicing the debt. Today, that is just about 10.5 per cent, it's about<br />
half that. And, the reason for that Is because we have now been </p>
<p>2<br />
exporting very strongly all through this period and that is the point I just<br />
made a second ago. We are now exporting 22 per cent of our produce<br />
instead of 14 per cent so our capacity to pay our way has improved.<br />
That is not to say I am not concerned about the current account deficit<br />
and we don't keep our eye on It, but it is basically a savings issue and<br />
what we have to do in the medium term is to improve Australian<br />
savings and the big boost to that will come from two places. That is,<br />
the budget returning to surplus In the 1990s and occupational<br />
superannuation which now has In Australia's super funds, under the<br />
government scheme owned by Australian employees of $ 180 billion<br />
$ 1 80,000 million.<br />
JI: Graham Richardson writes in his book about that banana republic<br />
comment. It is very interesting and I'm interested. to hear your reaction<br />
to the way he puts It and I quote him by May Keating was really<br />
worried about our growing balance of payments deficit. It was no use<br />
trying to explain it away again as we had done by declaring that<br />
Qantas had brought another plane. Keating needed to issue a shock<br />
warning to Australia and to overseas investors. On the John Laws<br />
show he told the radio audience that Australia was importing about<br />
$ 12 billion more than we were exporting every year and that if the<br />
government couldn't get manufacturing going again and keep sensible<br />
wage and economic policies we were basically done for and would end<br />
up being a third rate economy." Then the current account deficit for<br />
the year went to $ 14.8 billion. But, now it could go to $ 22 billion, so<br />
shouldn't you be even more concerned than you were in 1986?<br />
PM. Well, we are forecasting it at about $ 18 billion, but the thing is that was<br />
$ 14 billion then in the size of the economy as it was then, It is now<br />
very much greater. I mean, Australian GDP, this is the total economy,<br />
is now about $ 400 billion. Then it would have been something in the<br />
order of $ 300 billion. So, as a proportion of GDP, and we were then in<br />
the late 1980s John, we were looking at the current account, deficit<br />
heading up to 6 per cent of GDP. Now, we are looking at rates of half<br />
that. So, that is the key point. Can I just make this other point, when I<br />
spoke to you at that stage, we had the worst terms of trade, the worst<br />
commodity prices since the Depression and that Is what lead me to<br />
make that remark. Our national Income had fallen so sharply from<br />
wheat, wool, Iron ore, coking coal and all these other things, that now<br />
commodity prices are much stronger and, of course, we have had this<br />
enormous transformation in our industrial base. We are now exporting<br />
elaborately transformed manufactures. In fact, the fastest growing<br />
component of our exports is elaborately transformed goods.<br />
JL: The thing that I don't understand, pardon me if I don't, but I doubt that<br />
our listeners understand either, as a percentage of GDP, doesn't it<br />
mean that it could still go to 6.1 per cent of national output? </p>
<p>3<br />
PM: No, I don't believe that because I just think that we are not going to<br />
have the sort of crazy credit growth we had In the 19809. When we<br />
came to the end of the 1 980s boom we had credit growth of nearly<br />
per cent a year and that sort of spending by the banks just lit the whole<br />
economy up like a Christmas tree and, of course, we started sucking<br />
the imports all over the place. We are now growing at a pace we can<br />
manage and, of course, the banks after being stung so badly in the<br />
1980s are now so abstemious In rationing credit growth, that sort of<br />
problem is not going to arise.<br />
JL: OK, I looked at the figures because people are now going back to the<br />
1986 comments because of Its revival in Graham Richardson's book<br />
Back In 1986 inflation was higher, I think about 8 per cent.<br />
PM: Yes, it is now 2 per cent.<br />
JL: That's right. Now, does the lower inflation figure make any difference<br />
to the way In which the current account deficit should be looked at?<br />
PM: It makes a tremendous difference because for a start world Interest<br />
rates are lower so, basically if you take our current account and take It<br />
to pieces there are two elements of it. One is called the trade surplus<br />
or deficit and the other is called the payment surplus or deficit. One is<br />
called the merchandise trade deficit and the other is called the net<br />
Income deficit. Let me just explain those. One is basically whether<br />
you are importing or exporting more goods and services that is goods<br />
and services well, that Is basically about balanced. At various<br />
periods now we have a merchandise trade surplus. That was never<br />
the case. I mean, where our debt came from, it came from the fact that<br />
In the 1970s, we dropped our guard on our manufacturing base and<br />
were so massively uncompetitive. So, we were running huge<br />
merchandise trade deficits so the debt came from an incapacity to<br />
trade goods. Where the debt comes today, where the current account<br />
deficit comes today is from the net income deficit, from the interest<br />
payments. Now, that low inflation rate that you just referred to and the<br />
low inflation rates and lower Interest payments around the world<br />
means that in the 1 990s the Interest payments on our debt are much<br />
lower than the 1980s so therefore the likelihood of the current account<br />
deficit blowing out because of high debt payments and high interest<br />
rates on that debt Is, of course, noth ing to be compared with the<br />
1980s.<br />
JL: OK now we hear the doom boosters and there are plenty of them,<br />
saying that we have to level out the amount of exports compared to the<br />
amount of imports, that they have to be about even. You say they are,<br />
but the cry that we are hearing from quarters is that is not the case,<br />
that we are importing a good deal more than we are exporting. But,<br />
even if that was absolutely balanced, that doesn't solve the problem<br />
does it? r </p>
<p>PM: No. it doesn't solve the problem. In the end what we have had to do is<br />
we have to export even more and that is why next month I am going to<br />
the APEC meeting In Indonesia which is about lowering tariff<br />
protection and trade barriers around the Asia-Pacific. Australia has<br />
already made this great transformation, John. We have got tariffs<br />
coming down to about 5 per cent by 1997. The whole culture of the<br />
Australian manufacturing has changed to a competitive one.<br />
Manufacturing production has doubled since the 1 980s, early 1 980s.<br />
Manufacturing exports have trebled, we now export as much<br />
manufactures as we do primary products.<br />
JL: Well, I imagine even more this year with the drought.<br />
PMV: Even more this year, and this is, of course, the first in our history and it<br />
is that higher added value, these elaborately transformed products<br />
which is basically coming from our education system and our research<br />
and development and by more entrepreneurial management and a<br />
willingness to actually ship product into the Asia-Pacific and the rest of<br />
the world which was never true when the tariff wall was there. It is that<br />
change which will give us the capacity to meet our trading imperatives,<br />
but the basic fundamentals underlying the current account deficit mean<br />
that we have got to lift our savings during the 1 990s and the two things<br />
that I say that will do that is basically a shift of the budget back into<br />
surplus and a very large change in savings coming from the<br />
government's policies of award or occupational superannuation.<br />
JL: OK, what about government spending, that should be cut surely?<br />
PM. I Well, not so much spending. I mean, the deficit is being reduced and<br />
let me just make a point, John. At the moment we have 9.5 per cent<br />
unemployment. The last time we had 9.5 per cent unemployment was<br />
in about 1984-85. Then the budget deficit was 4 per cent of our total<br />
national production. At the moment it is 2.5 per cent. So, if you are<br />
comparing apples with apples we are miles in front of where we were<br />
in the 1980s because if the budget was in surplus today we would be<br />
running the economy back into a recession. That's the point, we have<br />
got the economy I noticed yesterday by the way, on 2UE Alan Jones<br />
was saying he was talking to Mr Costello saying " the dramatically bad<br />
circumstances we seem to be in at the moment". I mean, it is just<br />
outrageous this sort of talk. Let me lust explain this to you, we have<br />
got 4.5 per cent growth. We are growing as fast or faster than any<br />
other western economy. We have got 2 per cent inflation which came<br />
out last week. Now, the last time we had growth like that 4.5 per cent<br />
growth and 2 per cent inflation would have been 30 years ago. As<br />
well as that we have had 4 per cent employment growth when western<br />
Europe has had around 1 per cent employment growth. As the<br />
Treasurer said recently the last time we had a conjunction of<br />
circumstances like this was 30 years ago. And yet, you have got </p>
<p>people talking about dramatically bad circumstances. Look, the<br />
average person is not to know all these numbers and to make all these<br />
comparisons and It is irresponsible in the extreme to be addressing a<br />
broad audience saying we have got dramatically bad circumstances or<br />
it is a " sickening confidence trick" and all this sort of stuff. The fact is<br />
two and a half years ago the economy was still in recession. This<br />
government has managed to get it back to growth, but not just back to<br />
growth, back to massive levels of employment growth. I mean, the big<br />
issue in the last election was unemployment. Unemployment has<br />
come down from 11 per cent to 9.5 per cent and we have had a<br />
massive increase in people looking for work and we have had 4 per<br />
cent employment growth. The other thing is, in the mean time, John,<br />
we have absolutely exported our heads off. So, Australia is at the top<br />
of the OECD league table and lot me just say this to you, The<br />
Economist magazine, a conservative economic publication one of<br />
Britain's foremost economic publications it has a league table in there<br />
every month of economic performance versus inflation and<br />
employment. We are at the top of that table and we have been there<br />
for 14 months.<br />
JI: Now, just quickly back to unemployment. How many of those jobs, you<br />
say that we have created or you have created all these jobs<br />
PM: Well, the policies h ave created this.<br />
JL: I mean most of it has been private enterprise that has created the jobs.<br />
PM: Well, of course it is, but it didn't just happen. The ' One Nation' policy<br />
of 1992 got the country moving again. When we put that money into<br />
rail, road, the ring roads around the capital cities, the highways, the<br />
trunk rail network, all that government spending at the time was there<br />
when private spending had stopped during the recession. That is what<br />
kicked the place along.<br />
JL OK, well when you talk about the jobs and the job rate being increased<br />
how many of those are government subsidised jobs because there are<br />
many who are going to say ' well, the government created the jobs.'?<br />
PM: Very few, very few, the great bulk of them, 90 per cent of them would<br />
be in the private sector 90 odd per cent in the private sector. And, of<br />
course, need I -say John, with 11 per cent unemployment and 4 per<br />
cent employment growth, the unemployment rate, if everyone stood<br />
still, would be 7 per cent. The reason it Is 9.5 per cent is because we<br />
have got new entrants to the workforce and in the main, people<br />
optimistically looking for work and In the main the people joining the<br />
workforce are women. So, there is a tremenidous boost of what we call<br />
the participation rate. That is once things start to improve those who<br />
are not registering for work or looking for work go out looking for it<br />
again and that is why you don't get a clean translation of the 4 per cent </p>
<p>6<br />
employment growth off the 11 per cent which would otherwise give you<br />
7 per cent.<br />
JL: Yes, 1s there any indication of how many of those in the private sector<br />
P M. It would be 90 odd per cent.<br />
JL: Yes, but how many of those in the private sector are still getting<br />
government assistance?<br />
PM: In terms of?<br />
JL Subsidies.<br />
PM: None of those other than those who are longer term unemployed who<br />
get wage subsidies.<br />
JI: But, there would be a percentage.<br />
PM: Only those unemployed over 12 months or more.<br />
JL: Yes, well, there are a few of those aren't there?<br />
PM: That is one of the great successes, I think, we have had in the last<br />
year. Of the 400,000 jobs, 90,000 went to the long-term<br />
unemployment that is people unemployed 12-18 months. Now, if we<br />
were comparing 400,000 in the 1980s about only 25,000 of them would<br />
have gone to the long-term unemployed. So, the government's White<br />
Paper changes and the labour market programs where we actively<br />
support those who have been longer term unemployed, we are now<br />
finding we are having, well, you could say, roughly a quarter of the<br />
jobs that have been created now are going to the long-term<br />
unemployed and that for this country is just terrific.<br />
JL: OK all the news according to you and understandably is good news,<br />
one would like to think that everything that you are saying is right.<br />
Graham Richardson has caused us, of course, to raise our eyebrows<br />
on that subject again, but if everything Is as you say, if everything in<br />
God's great garden is as rosy as it sounds when you talk about it, why<br />
then do we have other people decrying the situation in which Australia<br />
finds itself at the moment.<br />
PM: Well I noticed that you, yesterday apparently referred to the Australian<br />
Financial Review story where one of the largest US American bond<br />
dealers said Australia had gone bond-kers and amongst other things,<br />
you said this, ' the glass is never half full in Australia, its either seen as<br />
empty or overflowing", and Isn't that just dead right. In other words, we<br />
can never say, look, here is a recovery, we are going to maintain it and </p>
<p>ILL: ~ j: 7<br />
7<br />
extend it with low Inflation. We have got 4.5 per cent growth. We<br />
have 4 per cent employment growth and low inflation. Now lets do the<br />
right things to extend it and give all Australians a chance at it right<br />
through the 1 990s. No, Its either a feast or its a famine. We are either<br />
all ' rooned or its a bounty heading our way. And you can't seem to get<br />
from the commentators here, that sort of latitude that says " look, we've<br />
actually done it right this time".<br />
JL: Present company excepted please.<br />
PM: Well, present company excepted, absolutely. And I think that is part of<br />
the point. I noticed in the same story, let me just give you a couple of<br />
quotes.<br />
JL: You see, that's the point I made yesterday and I read parts of that from<br />
the Financial Review that's what it was wasn't it yesterday page 37<br />
PM: Well there were a couple of can I just read you a couple of<br />
JI: But let me just finish I read that, and said that these fellas are<br />
into bonds and this is the way they are talking about our country,<br />
Australia. And then you get people on the phone saying " oh yeah, but<br />
so what. They are only buying bonds". I mean its intelligent people<br />
talking about our country for God's sake.<br />
PM:. Well its more than intelligent people, its the people who watch the<br />
major western countries who handle billions dollars of bonds and<br />
basically buy them on the back of the prosperity and their Judgements<br />
about those countries. So its not just a judgement about Australia, by<br />
Australians, Its a judgement about Australia by people who buy similar<br />
securities, In Germany, In Britain, In the United States right through<br />
Western Europe. Let me just read what two people had to say in that<br />
interview. One said ( this is a New Yorker), " Aussie inflation is fine, its<br />
going to pick up a bit, but its still quite low by OECD standards. The<br />
budget deficit has got a little bit worse but I'm willing to believe that is a<br />
timing issue. The currency is going to appreciate it in the next couple<br />
of years". Another said " we think the inflation fears in Australian are<br />
exaggerated and we don't think Australia has the political uncertainty<br />
of many countries. The currency is strong, the commodity prices* are<br />
strong, and I have to say that it does look a bit like the bonds are<br />
mispriced". The key point is the underlying sentiments of the remarks.<br />
Forget the focus on the bonds, I mean, here you have the really hard<br />
assessors of Australia saying, look basically the Inflation rate is fine,<br />
they are ticking along with quite high rates of growth, the place is<br />
stable, commodity prices are high and the currency is strong. Now,<br />
you wouldn't get that out of the doom sayers, And that's the point. I<br />
. mean, its quite wrong for these people. I mean you can never quite<br />
win with the Jones' and people like that. A year ago eighteen months<br />
ago It was all doom and gloom. It was unemployment; we're all </p>
<p>B1 No -N 1<br />
ruined; where are we going: we've had it; and within six and ri'n<br />
months transition, we are all ruined again. This time its for growing too<br />
fast. Because Interest rates have moved up slightly, and why are<br />
interest rates up? They are up to sustain the recovery. So all<br />
Australians can enjoy it for longer. That is, to keep inflation down, and<br />
therefore keep our competitiveness up, to keep our exports going and<br />
to get and maintain now this Investment phase in plant and equipment<br />
which we haven't seen for three or four years. We are seeing it<br />
coming back strongly, and with it of course, a long run recovery Into<br />
the 1990s.<br />
JL: OK Well you say that Inflation Is under control, we would like to<br />
believe you. But we've got unions now, going for unbelievable wage<br />
increases; increases have got nothing to do with productivity but based<br />
on the fact that the interest rates to which you just referred are going<br />
up. Now if they get those increases, and they flow through to other<br />
sectors of the economy and normally that's the way it goes. We have<br />
precisely the same situation that lead to the recession we had to have.<br />
PM: Well, what you do what Governments do all the time is manage<br />
things as they arise. We are now in a growth economy. In a growth<br />
economy, you get price taking, you get people who want to put their<br />
prices up. You can see various strength in the housing sector. It's<br />
possible that things like bricks and tiles and kitchens and all these<br />
sorts of things will have a little premium on them now where they didn't<br />
two years ago, so the Government has got to watch that. Its got to<br />
watch claims in the labour market, given the fact that most people in<br />
the labour market did no better but probably worse over the last couple<br />
of years, in some cases in the Inflation rate, so they're out there now<br />
saying " well this is the time to get a wage increase"<br />
JL: And of course they are using interest rates as the hook,<br />
understandable.<br />
PM: Well, some are. Basically they are just using the growth. And the<br />
other thing Is, some of the states in the public sector are starting now<br />
to offer wage increases they shouldn't be offering. For instance, the<br />
NSW Government, John Fahey was under attack up at Darwin at the<br />
Council of Australian Governments, not so much by me but by some of<br />
the conservative State Premiers of the other States saying, " listen<br />
John you better chop it out, offering 7 per cent to teachers and 5 per<br />
cent to nurses" and on top of that, he's now got another 8 per cent<br />
hanging about. So that sort of public sector lead coming out of NSW,<br />
there is this notion you can buy your way back into office by offering<br />
the public sector employees up to 15 per cent wage increases, is very<br />
dangerous indeed. I can assure you that the Commonwealth Public<br />
Sector, that is my Government employees -we will not be making<br />
those sort of settlements. </p>
<p>9<br />
JL: Well, you have no control over -wbat hiaPPens in NSW. So if those<br />
wage demands go ahead, how are you going to control inflation?<br />
PM: Its not the wage demands, its the complicity of the Government in<br />
meeting them.<br />
JL Well assuming that happens in NSW, you have no control over it.<br />
PM. You will always get wage demands, its a matter of whether you have<br />
some bunny to actually say yes to them.<br />
JL; Well if one of the bunnies does say yes, you have no control over that,<br />
so how do you control it?<br />
PM: Well, basically what we have done over the years is that we have had<br />
an Accord with the Trade Unions. The reason we have got 2 per cent<br />
inflation and remember this John, we have been growing now for about<br />
12 quarters for three years, we have been back into positive growth for<br />
three years and we have still got 2 per cent inflation. And the reason<br />
for that is, basically we have had reasonably a good restraint on<br />
wages and good productivity arrangements. The great change now<br />
compared to the eighties, Is that we now have enterprise bargaining.<br />
We've got a decentralised labour market and all wages are not fixed<br />
by the Australian Industrial Relations Commission. There Is no such<br />
thing as a National Wage Case today. So a lot of companies, what<br />
they are doing is basically saying " look alright, we will give you an<br />
increase, providing you give us some productivity".<br />
JI: OK Well what about our mates at the TWU. 15 per cent they're<br />
demanding and that has been sanctioned by the ACTU.<br />
PM: Well, It depends on for a start, what's agreed by the companies.<br />
Whether the companies want to cut their throats by agreeing to it and<br />
secondly, over what period of time? If its over a couple of years or two<br />
or three years, it becomes eminently affordable in national economic<br />
terms. So John, you know the debate we have had in this country<br />
about industrial relations. You've had the conservative side of politics<br />
for years and the business community are saying " give us a<br />
decentralised labour market. Give us labour market flexibility. Give us<br />
enterprise bargaining." Well, now they have got it. And what they've<br />
got to do is basically make It work. So when they pay a wage<br />
increase, they have got to get something in return. That's more<br />
productivity, that is, more product and lower costs.<br />
JL: Its seems that they are having some difficulty making it work because<br />
only 45 registered non-union enterprise agreements have been put in<br />
place since the new industrial relations laws were introduced, but in<br />
that same period of time, 2694 claims for unfair dismissal have been<br />
lodged. : I i, 4 j </p>
<p>PM: Well, Its the full enterprise bargaining stream, not the non-union<br />
enterprise flexibility area that's important. Its the full what we call<br />
' certified agreement area' that matters and we've now got about 55 or<br />
per cent of all federal award employees subject to enterprise<br />
agreements. In other words, the system is working and a lot of good<br />
businesses with good managers are doing good productivity deals.<br />
They are getting higher profits for the company which they then share<br />
between profits and wages. And the employees walk away with a<br />
wage increase and the Inflation rate doesn't suffer. Now in any<br />
recovery, there will always be a bit of what's called ' economic<br />
adjustment'. That is, to cover off the bit of the joy and even modest<br />
inflation. Well, the economy can afford some of that, providing there is<br />
a bit of productivity around and what the Government is about and<br />
what the ACTU and our Accord partners are basically about here, will<br />
be trying to manage that wage outcome, through the next few years, so<br />
that we can have what most countries don't have. That's growth with<br />
employment. Now let me just repeat this John. Western Europe is<br />
growing at about 1.5 per cent. We are growing at 4.5 per cent. They<br />
are getting about 1 per cent employment growth. We are getting 4. In<br />
other words, our society is going to be more fully employed and<br />
therefore, much more fulfilled and I hope happier. Therefore, the<br />
Government's job is to extend the recovery, but listening to all the<br />
doom sayers saying " it's a disastrous state of affairs" because interest<br />
rates have risen by 1.3/ 4 percentage points from a 30 year low, to still<br />
be low is extravagant doomsaying.<br />
JL: There is so much of it, people do tend to become brainwashed by it. I<br />
mean, how do you stop it? You see, if you look at what the former<br />
head of the Treasury, John Stone, has to say about your statement<br />
that $ 9 billion taken from the Budget represents the fiscal responsibility<br />
of the Government, and he says it's all... . this figure is arrived at by<br />
sleight of hand that you have included as so-called savings $ 3.6<br />
billion by deferring the second instalment of the tax cuts. Now, nobody<br />
can understand what he is writing about except that he is talking the<br />
place down again that all this Isn't really happening, that you.. . have<br />
you indulged in some sleight of hand?<br />
PM: No. And when John Stone was secretary of the Treasury,<br />
Commonwealth spending was 30.5% of our total product 30.5% of<br />
our GOP.<br />
JL: When he was head<br />
PM: When he was secretary of the Treasury.<br />
JL: Yep. </p>
<p>TEL: 3. OV 14 : 17 No .014 P. 11/ 1<br />
PMV: When " Paem Fraser left the Treasury to become Governor of the<br />
Reserve Bank, the Government spending was 23.5% of GDP down 7<br />
percentage points. Now, I'll tell you what that is 7% is just on<br />
billion. Thirty thousand million each year less spending when Fraser<br />
left the Treasury compared to Stone. So, the thing about all these<br />
fellows is to look at what they did at the time. Stone believed in the<br />
tariff wall, he believed in a managed exchange rate and when he left<br />
after giving us all these high faluting ideas about his economic<br />
capacity when he left the beauracracy, where did he go? Of all<br />
places, to the National Party. To the Country Party which built the<br />
tariff wall In the first place. These guys are classic under-achievers.<br />
They failed In their public life, walk out and then want to be<br />
commentators about people who realty achieved something. Putting<br />
at no time during John Stone's Secretary-ship of the Treasury<br />
was there ever 4.5% economic growth and 2% inflation. Never. He<br />
could have only dreamed about It.<br />
JL: Why do we need a racial hatred bill?<br />
PM. Well, basically because we do see outbreaks of violence against<br />
people... . persons and property for reasons of race. And at the moment<br />
under the law, if someone throws a brick through your shop window,<br />
they can be prosecuted only because they have broken your window<br />
and not because It was racially Inspired.<br />
JL: But violence of any sort. should be kept under control by any<br />
governments anywhere...<br />
PMV: Exactly.<br />
A: Irrespective of the motive of the violence?<br />
PMV: Here we are talking about incitement's to racial hatred and threats of<br />
racial violence or damage . or such as damage to property etc.<br />
Because basically having people running around saying " I'm going to<br />
throw a brick through your window or bum your building down because<br />
of your race" should be an offence. And that's what we're making it.<br />
JL: out now it's being said by Michael Lavarch and others that ' Well, this<br />
won't be enforced really there won't be any charges laid against.. If<br />
this is true, why have it there?<br />
PMV: Well I don't know that's true. But we have legislation of this nature in a<br />
number of the States already. This is basically just the Federal<br />
Government doing what is already around in some places, but having<br />
a national law here.<br />
JL But you can't legislate emotion. </p>
<p>TE. 3. Nov. 94 NO -1 F. 12,<br />
12<br />
PM: Of you can't legislate emotion, and the operation of . when I say<br />
that you can't legislate emotion.. that is, If they're emotions that don't<br />
lead to an infringement of someone else's liberties you can legislate If<br />
it starts to infringe someone else's liberties. If they had this sort of<br />
legislation in Western Europe in the 1 930s, of course, it would have<br />
mattered a great deal indeed.<br />
JL: Yeah, but you still wouldn't have changed attitudes legislation can<br />
never change attitudes.<br />
PM: It can't change attitudes, but there's no way that the nation or the<br />
community or the Government should regard offences against persons<br />
or properties for reasons of racial hatred as being something to be<br />
condoned.<br />
JL: It's got a lot going for It as far as the Government is concerned in as<br />
much as it has obviously shored up the ethnic vote?<br />
PM; Look, it's not for that reason. The Government, I can say, has had a<br />
lot of support from ethnic communities over a period of time for years<br />
we don't need a racial hatred bill to maintain that. It's there because<br />
It's a proper adjunct to our laws in respect to people's liberties.<br />
JL: Is it something that is in place in most Westemised countries?<br />
PM. I'd say most countries would have something very similar.<br />
JL: It's going to cause... put the cat among the pigeons in the Coalition,<br />
because they will be at loggerheads with each other on the issue.<br />
That too would be to the Government's advantage, wouldn't it?<br />
PM: Well, I should hope it isn't because I should believe that most people<br />
in the Coalition would support this sort of legislation.<br />
JL: Yeah. Out of all strange people, one of the Western Australian Green<br />
people seems to be opposed to it does that surprise you?<br />
PM: Well, they were opposed at one point to the Native Title legislation<br />
when they were claiming an interest in the welfare of Aboriginal<br />
people, and now they're seeking to upset the Land Fund legislation.<br />
So again It just makes this point Independents wandering around the<br />
Senate with no rhyme or reason about their political existence no<br />
depth of policy analysis, no track record, no yardsticks, no sheet<br />
anchors have no particular consistency in their approach to particular<br />
pieces of legislation.<br />
JL: OK Something else that we have been hearing a great deal about,<br />
and we have been hearing hysterical cries about how we have dudded </p>
<p>TEL: 3. ov9 14: 17 No. 614 F. 1.<br />
13<br />
Now Zealand as far as the aviation policy is concerned what i3 the<br />
real story?<br />
PM: Well, we haven't dudded New Zealand at all.<br />
JL: Didn't New Zealand dud us?<br />
PM: What happened here was I said in the One Nation statement.... we<br />
offered New Zealand... . John, you would be familiar with the Airline<br />
SAS the Scandinavian Airline System?<br />
JL: Yes.<br />
PM: Now that's basically an airline which operates around the countries of<br />
Scandinavia you don't see a Swedish airline, and you don't see a<br />
Danish airline, but you see SAS. Do you understand?<br />
JIL: Yes, I do.<br />
PM: Now what we were saying is " let's have a single aviation market for<br />
Australasia". And in One Nation, I offered the Government of New<br />
Zealand a common Customs border that is, Australia's customs laws<br />
would be the same as Now Zealand's, and therefore the carriage of<br />
passengers between our two countries could then be domestic to<br />
domestic terminal. In other words, you would travel from Auckland to<br />
Sydney, or Christchurch to Melbourne, and you would go just as you<br />
would go from Perth to Melbourne, or Brisbane to Sydney.<br />
JL: Ok. So New Zealand would become part of our domestic air market,<br />
and we could become part of theirs.<br />
PM. Yes. Now, New Zealand refused that. They said they wanted to keep<br />
particular Visa arrangements with Taiwan and Mexico and other<br />
countries, and they refused that. So we then said " Aliright. OK Well<br />
listen, let's talk about then... it would be better to have a single customs<br />
union a single set of customs arrangements let's then talk about a<br />
single market." Now, what a single market means is that we have a<br />
single market for passengers, and we organise that market in terms of<br />
a single market for the capital for the airlines. In other words, there's<br />
no particular reason why one of the airlines should be a New Zealand<br />
airline or an Australian airline. That idea we have not been able to<br />
make progress on. Basically I think, the view from New Zealand is Yes<br />
they want a single aviation market for passengers, but not a single<br />
aviation market for airlines. In other words, they want to keep a<br />
national flag carrier.<br />
JI:. So that's why you have terminated the arrangement? </p>
<p>14<br />
PM; At this point, Australia... . there were to be agreements about airline<br />
ownership and rationalisation about airline structures. We have had<br />
repeated conversations over the course of the last 18 months I have<br />
had a number with the New Zealand Prime Minister, my colleague<br />
Laurie Brereton has had a number with the New Zealand Transport<br />
Minister, the Australian airline companies here Ansett and Qantas<br />
have had a number with Air New Zealand, and because this<br />
memorandum we had together had certain indicative dates In it, Air<br />
New Zealand has already done very finely out of It. It's got now 14<br />
jumbo flights a week out of Brisbane, which is a very large number of<br />
passengers, which they can pick up Australian passengers and take<br />
them to Japan...<br />
JI: So that's taking away from Australian airlines?<br />
PM: Yes, that's taking them, and they also then the contemplation was in<br />
a single market, we would move them to domestic flying In Australia<br />
between Brisbane and our capital cities our trunk routes and then<br />
further beyond rights, that is further rights for say, Air New Zealand to<br />
pick up people out of Sydney and Melbourne and carry them to other<br />
countries. But that's only on in the event we have a single-market. In<br />
other words, what has happened in Australia's terms is it's been all<br />
give, give, give, and New Zealand has been all take. And as the sort<br />
of trigger dates for these things were coming up, we were looking for<br />
some kind of change on the part of New Zealand to recognise the<br />
imperatives of one market, but it didn't come, and so therefore Mr<br />
Brereton wrote to, Laurie Brereton wrote to his counterpart saying in<br />
terms, seeing as you basically in spirit rejected the proposal, It's off.<br />
JL: So this was done in the main to protect Australia as they had, in part,<br />
reneged on the deal?<br />
PM: Well, if we went, say flew to San Francisco and said to the United<br />
States Government " We'll pick up American passengers in San<br />
Francisco and go and fly them to London and Paris..."<br />
JL: They would tell you tell you to go jump.<br />
PM; Exactly. But we're giving Air New, Zealand the right to pick up<br />
Australian passengers and take them to Japan. Now, they wanted that<br />
right, plus more plus to be able to fly domestically, but to put nothing<br />
back in return.<br />
JL: So you said enough Is enough?<br />
PM: Yes, that's wh'at we said enough Is enough.<br />
JL: Okay. I know you're not much into polls, but you might be into this one<br />
-the Bulletin poll that says 50% of Australians favour a republic, but </p>
<p>3 N&gt;. C 4 No. Oi0s1<br />
want to elect the Head of State. Would you proceed with the<br />
republic plan if you can't get up your preferred option of Parliament<br />
selecting the Head of State which I believe is the only way it should<br />
be done, and could be done, because otherwise the Head of State<br />
would appear to have more power than the Prime Minister, and<br />
obviously that is what you have got in mind?<br />
PM: At the moment people often say " you know, the Government and<br />
Keating wants to appoint the Head of State even though there has<br />
been some discussion about Parliament appointing such a person". At<br />
the moment, of course, upon the expiry of the current Governor-<br />
General's term....<br />
JL: Yeah what's going to happen?<br />
PM: Well, I would make a recommendation to the Queen and it would be<br />
accepted the Government, and me as Prime Minister, would appoint<br />
that Head of State without any reference to Parliament whatsoever. So<br />
at the moment, the ball is right in my court, so It's obviously not for that<br />
reason that I am saying Is what we need to do is to consider a republic<br />
constructively. But more importantly than the modality of the<br />
appointment John, is the notion that Australia will never really go its<br />
way in the world while ever we're following the monarch of another<br />
country. And I have said, one of the things that I wanted to see in this<br />
year in 1994 was a genuine public debate about the virtues of a<br />
republic versus a constitutional monarchy. Now I think we have well<br />
and truly got that debate going, and that's a very good thing for the<br />
country.<br />
JL: Yeah. Still on the subject of poll. s It appears that the gap between the<br />
Coalition and the Government is now narrowing some are saying that<br />
Alexander Downer after his recent performance is going to bounce<br />
back in the polls. Do you still have the future for Alexander Downer all<br />
mapped out as you claimed you had In the past?<br />
PM: Well I think I have, John. But again, these polls fluctuate, and the only<br />
poll that ever matters is the poll on polling day. But again, the<br />
Government has done all the things it said it would do at the last<br />
election we said we would restore growth in the economy and it's<br />
growing faster, or as fast, as any economy in the world. and western<br />
economy In the OECD economy. We said we would restore<br />
employment we have got 4% employment growth. The only country<br />
that Is as high as us In the western world is Canada at about 4% itself<br />
no other country Is up in that league. We said we would give effect to<br />
the High Court decision on Native Title we have gone and done it.<br />
We said we wouldn't leave the unemployed behind we set up the<br />
White Paper to do that. We said we would support the arts we have<br />
gone and done so. I mean, the Government has done all the things It<br />
said it would do. </p>
<p>16<br />
JL: Just back to the arts thing again you know that to the chagrin of<br />
many? I mean you have got a lot of criticism for having done that In a<br />
lot of quarters?<br />
PMV: Yes. Well, I notice your friend and colleague on the morning program<br />
having his one final . you know I was listening to him while I was<br />
coming onto your program, and they're saying " Oh, there was<br />
Turandot", he said, " None of Mr Keating's art money in that". Well the<br />
fact is, unless there is support for the Australian opera, and for the<br />
opera companies In this country from the public purse, and the ballet<br />
and the other major companles, you can't have a Turandot. It doesn't<br />
occur to these guys that an Investment In arts and culture In the public<br />
infrastructure In Australia is one of the things that we should be doing,<br />
and we happen to do It well look at the rave reviews we had for the<br />
Australian Ballet In Washington. The Australian Ballet went to the<br />
Australian Festival which was held at the John F Kennedy Centre in<br />
Washington and it was a great success 40,000 people came on the<br />
first day, half the American Senate was there, some of the Justices of<br />
the High Court, a number of American Ministers were there, members<br />
of the Cabinet were there, and Clive Barnes the noted New York dance<br />
critic had such glowing references to the Australian Ballet. I mean, we<br />
are getting international acclaim for the standards of our arts, and to<br />
be whlngelng about that Is really to be blinkered and mean-spirited.<br />
JL: Yeah. I can understand to a degree and it's difficult to say this<br />
because 1 have to refer to a friend in the form of Reg Livermore who I<br />
think Is a tremendously talented fella and I think he has done a great<br />
deal but Reg Isn't actually on the breadline, and when those artists<br />
who are struggling a iittle bit trying to get on, and I mean you have<br />
seen many of them around you, and endeavoured to help many around<br />
you, and they hear that a fella like Reg who is fairly well gainfully<br />
occupied and has done pretty well and has got himself set up pretty<br />
well that he gets a grant of some $ 60,00 odd dollars for a couple of<br />
years in a row in order to write his biography that smarts a little. You<br />
must be able to understand that?<br />
P M-The Australian Artists Creative Fellowships are for artists of<br />
accomplishment mid-career. These are for people who are in the<br />
broad, In the main, uncommercial, and in commercial terms<br />
unsuccessful, but in artistic terms of course, are very successful.<br />
JL: But you couldn't say that Reg was uncommercial?<br />
PMV: No, Reg is commercial, but again, he is going to take time off to make<br />
a contribution back. I mean, just the same as John Olsen at the<br />
presentatlon of the awards this year as a former awardee, presented<br />
works back to the Commonwealth. Frank Moorehouse has<br />
w V-.1 r </p>
<p>I LL: s. rO. Ui 17<br />
produced a first-class nave?, yo have got... I mean, it has gone to<br />
people like Garth Welch in dance and....<br />
JL: Yeah, but surely these people could have made the contribution<br />
without the taxpayers having to foot the bill?<br />
P M. Well let me just tell you this John when the first group of Fellowship<br />
awardees went through, and there were on that occasion 7 or 8 of<br />
them now these are people at the absolute top of Australian artistic<br />
ability, and of international standing. Their average income is $ 9000<br />
for the year, the previous year the average Income of all of them is<br />
$ 9000 and that was 1988, and now we have 45 people, I think, in the<br />
group. I don't know exactly what the average figure would be, but I<br />
wouldn't mind betting it's not much beyond $ 12-1.3,000. This is a very<br />
sad fact that people need to understand about the arts that somebody<br />
who is a sculptor or a dancer or a pianist or whoever It might be,<br />
unless they fluke that commerciality, they can be absolutely world best<br />
and be basically broke. Now, this Is an acknowledgment of saying to<br />
people who do what they do best, but do it with the greatest possible<br />
commitment to this country, who have never walked away from it and<br />
gone though it all and given Australia up, but stay here and stay with<br />
the low money It's a way of saying for 2 or 3 years, or 4 years if you<br />
like you can block out these years and put something back right at<br />
the peak of your career, and not have to worry about putting food on<br />
the table.<br />
JL: Yeah well all that Is fine, and I say that I don't want to go into it too<br />
much because I am not mean-spirited, but you could never say that my<br />
friend and he Is a terrific fella and a terrific talent you could never<br />
say that Reg Livermore Is down in the low wage earning. I mean, he's<br />
a pretty commercial character and very successful and very good at<br />
what he does, and that does smart a bit with people you know. I really<br />
do understand people saying " well come on, hang<br />
PM: Okay, but I don't think it is possible to just take one out of...<br />
JL: Well, it's not fair<br />
PM: out of forty....<br />
JL: Well he's the only one I can think<br />
PM; One out of forty odd, or maybe a couple out of forty odd....<br />
JL: Well, you know there Is another one that springs to mind as well...<br />
PM: Well what contribution has Livermore made to Australian theatre? An<br />
enormous contribution.... </p>
<p>PM: . and he will put something back. And what we are paying him is<br />
$ 60,000 for the two years that he is going to do it.<br />
JL: But one could also ask what contribution have I made to Australian<br />
radio?<br />
PM; True.<br />
JL: Nobody offered me 60 grand.<br />
PM; No. But they have offered you much more than that, and that is the<br />
point.<br />
JL: No, I offered it myself.<br />
PM: Welt it's like our friend on the morning program I don't want to seem<br />
obsessed about him, but he seems obsessed about me. The tact is,<br />
hearing his blaggarding Australian artists most of whom, in this<br />
category without any Government assistance are getting $ 12-14,000<br />
a year. That is, they're not getting what someone at the bottom end of<br />
the wage market is getting, when he is picking up probably around a<br />
million a year or better. Now, is there any justice in that? I mean,<br />
reading out transcripts and vetting opinions and picking up multiples<br />
and multiples of what people of international accomplishment are<br />
actually getting. You see look, I don't mind people getting greedy, as<br />
long as they are not mean-spirited about it.<br />
JL: I think it's terrific.<br />
PM: I mean good on Alan. He's got a good rating program even though<br />
it's basical ly.. . most of the stuff is middle of the road fascism I don't<br />
mind if he's doing his best and he's getting his money for it, but let's<br />
not blaggard everybody else who is accomplished and who is basically<br />
living on a pittance.<br />
JL: Would you consider taking the House of Representatives to an<br />
election without the Senate?<br />
PM: I'm not interested in early elections, John.<br />
JL: No, that wasn't the question.<br />
PM: Well, to take the House to an election without the Senate means that<br />
the House has got to go before next August, and that's just not my<br />
intention.<br />
JL: Have you.... </p>
<p>IEL3. Nv. 91 9 1 17<br />
PM: I want to see the Government enjoy this Parliament to do the things we<br />
promised the Australian people we would do restore the growth and<br />
employment, keep the inflation rate low and get on with the big ticket<br />
Issues like the republic, APEC, Mabo, the White Paper all of these<br />
major milestones in Australia's political history, get working on those<br />
and at the end of it we'll say to the Australian people " This is what we<br />
promised, and this is what we have done, and we want you to return us<br />
again".<br />
JL Okay Prime minister, thank you for your time. Good to talk to you, and<br />
I hope we get to talk again very soon.<br />
PM: Thank you very much John.<br />
ends. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
