<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6629</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF SPEECH TO TASMANIAN ALP STATE COUNCIL, 25 MAY 1985</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/05/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006629.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
E. O. E. PROOF ONLY<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF SPEECH TO TASMANIAN ALP STATE COUNCIL 25 MAY 1985<br />
The President and delegates may I at the outset thank you for the<br />
invitation to be here to address your council and the warmth of<br />
your reception. I want at the outset of my remarks to put this<br />
council meeting in its right context because there is at this<br />
stage, as I see it, attempts on the part of some people, our<br />
political opponents, to try and distort the current pol-itical<br />
realities in Australia. Last December, our party, our great<br />
party, had an historic victory. It was attempted in some quarters<br />
to be feted as some form of defeat. Indeed Labor is back in<br />
power, in Canberra, in its second successive term, with the second<br />
highest majority that it has ever enjoyed in Government.<br />
Now of course it is a tragedy for us, particularly for you, that<br />
Tasmania in terms of House of Representatives seats wasn't able to<br />
join with us directly in that great victory. But that shouldn't<br />
hide the great contribution that was in fact made here in<br />
Tasmania. As Leader of the Party, as your Prime Minister, I want<br />
to thank you for the effort that you made. Because despite the<br />
fact that those seats were won you did in f ' act show the underlying<br />
strength of Labor support in that in this State there was a swing<br />
to Labor against the national swing. I want to say to you that<br />
that represents a springboard for the achievement of the two tasks<br />
ahead of the Party as far as we are concerned in Australia<br />
generally, and you are concerned here in particular in Tasmania.<br />
The first task is to achieve the third successive national victory<br />
of our Australian Labor Government and then here as far as<br />
Tasmania is concerned, return of the Wriedt Labor Government<br />
whenever the State elections are held.<br />
That December result in itself, delegates, should be more than<br />
sufficient to give the lie to one of the more fatuous propositions<br />
currently being pedalled by the present Premier of this State, and<br />
that is this suggestion that in some ways the people of Tasmania<br />
are going to be penalised harshly, or treated unfairly by me and<br />
the Australian Labor Gbvernment. I want here to nail that lie<br />
directly. It's not just an insult to me and to our Government<br />
it's an insult to the intelligence of the people of Tasmania.<br />
We're just not in the business of deliberately inflicting<br />
political punishment on this, or any other part of the Australian </p>
<p>nation, or any section of the Australian community. That's not my<br />
way and it's not the Labor way, and it won't be the way of any<br />
Government that I have the honour to lead. And that's my direct<br />
answer Mr Gray.<br />
You'll recall delegates, that the principle of justice and<br />
fairness to Tasmania was the very first rule of conduct I set for<br />
myself and my Government on the great night in March of 1983 when<br />
we won Government on the 5th March. And I said it in our very<br />
first moment of victory, I said as I made my way into the Canberra<br />
tally room on that night, that there would never be any question<br />
as long as I was Prime Minister that the people of Tasmania might<br />
have to pay some sort of price or penalty for the politcal choice<br />
they had made on that day. You know that we have honoured<br />
absolutely the undertaking that I gave the people of Tasmania that<br />
night and we will continue to honour that undertaking without<br />
qualification, without reservation and without equivocation. And<br />
it is absolutely essential that the people of Tasmania should<br />
refuse to be the burden at this time by the alarmist and<br />
completely distorted speculation which is currently emanating from<br />
the Premier's office in this State.<br />
I had brought to my attention before arriving here today, the<br />
spread in today's press which sets out what I believe is called<br />
the Cuthbertson Report, which purports to tell you the horror<br />
stories of what will happen in this State as a result of the<br />
bringing down of the Grants Commission's Report. It's very<br />
important then for you, and through you the people of Tasmania,<br />
that we place next week's Premiers' Conference in perspective.<br />
Now the first thing that needs to be understood, of course you<br />
wouldn't know it if you listen to Mr Gray, is that the existing<br />
arrangements governing Commonwealth-State financial relations were<br />
established not by me and this Government but by our predecessors.<br />
Now part of the legacy, like so much else that we inherited, there<br />
accumulated over the years as you know distortions, inefficiencies<br />
and inequities. The important thing to understand about the<br />
Commonwealth Grants Commission that every member of the<br />
Commonwealth Grants Commission was appointed by Mr Fraser. That's<br />
the independent body Mr Gray is bleating about. I didn't appoint<br />
the Commonwealth Grants Commission. Mr Fraser appointed every<br />
member of that Commission. It's an independent body, and I hope<br />
Mr Gray, the media here, the people of Tasmania will understand<br />
that point. I didn't commission the Report. I didn't appoint the<br />
people. They were appointed accordi ng to the independent and<br />
proper processes by the Fraser Government. Now that Fraser<br />
appointed body made its report and that report is subject for<br />
consideration by the Premiers next week. our approach to the<br />
Grants Commission's recommendation will be the same as we have<br />
always taken in our dealings with the States and in particular<br />
with Tasmania over the' past two years.<br />
What our record demonstrates with absolute clarity is that we will<br />
not allow the interest of any State to be trampled on. We will<br />
not allow the welfare of the people of any State or region or </p>
<p>section to be disadvantaged. You and the people of Tasmania can<br />
be assured that in making a start in removing distortions and<br />
discriminations that have developed in the system over a decade.<br />
We're not going to create new distortions or new discriminations<br />
against any State and certainly not against Tasmania. No way will<br />
Tasmania be singled out for harsh treatment of any kind for any<br />
reason.<br />
Tasmania, as part of Australia, will have to exercise restraint.<br />
Tasmania is not going to be put in a special position of privilege<br />
but it is certainly not going to be singled out for particularly<br />
and especially harsh treatment. As I say, our record has shown<br />
that we do not work that way. Any suggestion that Tasmania is<br />
going to be saddled with new unrealistic burdens or that we would<br />
allow drastic draconian curtailment of Tasmania' s services and<br />
standards should be dismissed for what it is and for what it<br />
transparently is. And that is a diversionary tactic to obscure<br />
the Tasmanian Government's own inadequacies and shortcomings. Let<br />
me say this, that if you look back over the period that we've been<br />
in Government, if I had had to rely, and my Government had had to<br />
rely on Mr Gray and his representations for the protection of the<br />
interests of this great State, then the people of Tasmania would<br />
have suffered badly.<br />
I have been greatly assisted in that period by the unostentatious,<br />
quiet but nevertheless determined representations that have been<br />
made to me and my Government by Ken Wriedt. Also, as distinct<br />
from the political grandstanding the counterproductive political<br />
grandstanding, of the Premier of this State, Ken Wriedt quietly<br />
and not seeking to score political points, has come to us and said<br />
these are the things that I think you ought to take into account<br />
if you are reasonably going to deal with the fractured situation<br />
which you inherited. And we listened to Ken Wriedt because we<br />
knew that he was coming honourably. lie wasn't concerned with<br />
trying to distort a situation. And in the result you can see that<br />
in this period there has come about what I promised in March<br />
of ' 83 that Tasmania would not suffer, remember all the horror<br />
stories that you were told after March ' 83 about what would happen<br />
to unemployment in this State as a result of what we've done. I<br />
made a clear promise during that the first election campaign. I<br />
said we will not allow unemployment to deteriorate in this State<br />
as a result of the principle position that we had taken in the<br />
lead up to and following that election.<br />
As a result of listening, to Ken Wriedt, we were able to make<br />
sensible decisions about the allocation of funds, and as a result<br />
the unemployment situation has not only not deteriorated here, but<br />
is somewhat better in that respect than the national average<br />
because specifically of the funds that we have supplied and the<br />
approach that we have 6dopted.<br />
I would hope therefore that the people of Tasmania would learn<br />
from that experience of the past, they are better off now because<br />
there has been that balance provided by Ken Wriedt against the </p>
<p>hysterical distortions that the Premier went on with prior to<br />
March ' 83 and immediately following March ' 83. He does not seem<br />
to have learned because your press today has a repeat performanc.,<br />
This stark horror story is spelt out. Now I'm not helped, but<br />
most importantly the people of Tasmania are not helped, by those<br />
hysterical distortions. And as I was helped from March ' 83<br />
onwards by Ken Wriedt I believe that in these days immediately<br />
ahead I will again, and the people of Tasmania will again be<br />
helped by the quiet, deliberate and purposeful representations of<br />
Ken Wriedt. And I can assure you here, I can assure the people of<br />
Tasmania that we'll be listening to his representations because I<br />
know that from those representations, as distinct from the<br />
hysteria of the Premier, we will be able to arrive at a position<br />
which ensures that while adjustments that will have to be made<br />
Australia wide the restraint that will have to be exercised<br />
Australia wide while that will be done, it will be able to be<br />
done in a way which does not impose unneccessary hardships upon<br />
the people of Tasmania.<br />
I repeat, I take this opportunity Ken, of thanking you and I<br />
believe the people of Tasmania should thank you because the runs<br />
are on the board here in Tasmania as a result of your<br />
representations and they will continue to be on the board in the<br />
days ahead.<br />
Delegates, I said at the begining of my remarks that I wanted to<br />
put into its proper perspective the political realities of<br />
Australia today. And in the rest of the time that I have<br />
available I would like to speak directly with you and through you<br />
to the people of this State and the people of Australia to,<br />
elaborate those realities in some more detail and in a way which I<br />
believe is relevant to what the people, the ordinary people of<br />
Australia are thinking about, and what they are concerned about.<br />
There have been some attempts to suggest in recent times that your<br />
Government your national Government, has not been concentrating on<br />
the major issues that we may have lost some sense of direction.<br />
Nothing could be further from the truth. of course the real truth<br />
is this that some of the most conservative elements of<br />
Australian society are starting to become worried that in fact<br />
this National Labor Government is so effectively starting to<br />
change the structure and direction of the Australian economy and<br />
the Australian society in a progressive way that if we are allowed<br />
to continue in this way, there will* in fact be achieved the<br />
situation where the people of Australia will fully realise that<br />
Labor is the natural constituency of Government because it will<br />
have produced those things which the people of Australia want.<br />
And so there is an increasingly desperate attempt to suggest that<br />
there are inadequacies or uncertainties about what we're doing.<br />
So let me dismiss that stupid speculation. Let me take you<br />
briefly through what we have done, what we are doing and the<br />
vis * ion and purposes that we have for Australia in the years ahead.<br />
And all those things in connection what we've done, what we're<br />
doing and the vision ahead. </p>
<p>Now what has been the essential basis of what your Government has<br />
been doing. It is this; that when we came to office on<br />
March 1983 we inherited an Australian economy which was in the<br />
worst shape that it had been in for fifty years. It was in the<br />
worst recession since the great depression of the early 1930' s.<br />
And I on behalf of our great party, and what has become our great<br />
Government, said to the Australian people we will restore<br />
economic growth because economic growth is the foundation upon<br />
which can be built the welfare of individuals of those in<br />
employment and upon which can be built the capacity of our great<br />
society to do for those who are in need and who will not be helped<br />
directly through employment, to do for them what a compassionate<br />
society should do, to give them some opportunity in sharing in the<br />
growing wealth of our society. So that was the foundation, the<br />
very basic foundation of our approach, the necessity to restore<br />
economic growth.<br />
And we have succeeded not just beyond the cynicism, the cynical<br />
expectations of our opponents, but we are proud to be able to say<br />
that the rates of growth that we have achieved, have even been<br />
beyond those that we imagine ourselves we may have been able to<br />
achieve. Let me say this, that in our first two years of<br />
Government we achieved record levels of economic growth, that had<br />
us identified and pin pointed in the international forums who were<br />
ajudging what was happening in the developed countries of the<br />
world as the country whose economy was performing better than any<br />
other, but we weren't just achieving economic growth to be able to<br />
put figures up on the board and be at the top of the index. What<br />
it was about was creating jobs. And the creation of jobs has<br />
exceeded the target which I set on behalf of this party and this<br />
Government. We have already created over 300,000 jobs and we will<br />
reach a target of half a million new jobs in the first full three<br />
years of office.<br />
It is important to understand your great party in Government is<br />
able to do these things because we chartered a new course of<br />
relationships between people and groups in our society. We<br />
effectively brought to an end, the divisions, the divisiveness,<br />
the seven years of conservatism. We went beyond the rhetoric of<br />
consensus to establishing a framework in fact, whereby people<br />
could work more effectively together. We started that as you<br />
know, in the summit. We didn't content ourselves with the mere<br />
fact of the summi't. We then established EPAC, the Economic<br />
Planning Advisory Council, and in those consultations we have<br />
together worked out how best we can utilize the resources of this<br />
country. And in that process we never forgot the promise that we<br />
made, that as we grew, as we provided significantly more jobs for<br />
those who had been designated to the unemployment scrap heap. As<br />
we did those things we would also move responsibly to improve the<br />
position of those Australians most in need, and that we have done.<br />
Where we have increased in real terms the payments in the Social<br />
Security area they have, and this of course has been very much to<br />
the credit of Senator Don Grimes, who in the first two years<br />
oversighted our move in that direction. We have helped those most<br />
in need and we will continue to do so. </p>
<p>We have said that we will transform the basic infrastructure of<br />
the Australian economy so that there would be the release of<br />
forces within Australia that would help to guarantee as we went<br />
into the future the maximum opportunity for growth. And so we<br />
have done a number of the things that our conservative<br />
predecessors should have done, but isn't it the great paradox of<br />
politics today that your eager Peacock's and your Howard's and<br />
your Sinclair's say there is no determination about this<br />
government. Look at what they talked about and what they never did. They<br />
talked about floating the dollar, talked and talked and never did<br />
it. They talked about the need to free up the financial system,<br />
talked long on talk, short on action. They left a situation in<br />
this country where we had the most profitable banking system in<br />
any country in the world four banks the great friends of Labor,<br />
who were the most profitable institutions in the banking industry<br />
anywhere in the world. No wonder that they were, because they had<br />
no competition. Your Howard's your Peacock's, and your others<br />
talked about releasing the three forces of the competitive market,<br />
but they didn't have the courage, the consistency, the<br />
determination to do anything about it. We've done it. And in the<br />
event the Australian economy will now have a financial<br />
infrastructure within which the competitive forces of other banks<br />
and other financial institutions will enable innovative Australian<br />
enterprises to develop and to provide jobs, in a way that should<br />
have been done years ago. It only happened because we have done<br />
it. I<br />
So you can go on and look at the great changes that we have made.<br />
Changes in developing more co-operative approaches between the<br />
great elements of our society, fundamental changes that we are<br />
making constructively in the infrastructure, in the Australian<br />
economy. We have not stopped there. We have instituted great<br />
fiscal reform,* great financial reforms, not to help industry just<br />
to say we've helped industry, but the helping of industry is there<br />
so that more jobs will be created. In honesty, it is said at<br />
times that we are a government or have been a government which has<br />
been smiled upon by elements of business. of course we have, and<br />
I'm proud of it. The reason for this has been that we've made<br />
these decisions to ensure that we will have a more efficient,<br />
competitive Australian industry which is going to have a greater<br />
opportunity to provide more jobs for Australians, because it is<br />
the fact that three quarters of all' Australians are employed in<br />
the private sector, so it makes great sense, according to the<br />
philosophy of our party, to see that it is a healthy private<br />
sector able to provide more jobs. Of course, that's where we've<br />
been.<br />
We're recognised in Au~ tralia and internationally as a remarkably<br />
successfuil government because we've got those runs on the board.<br />
But because we know that economic growth is the basis, the<br />
continuing basis of being able to provide jobs, and to help those<br />
in the community most in need, we are pressing on steadfastly withthe<br />
task of reform. </p>
<p>Now the other great area that we are dealing with most<br />
particularly at the moment is the area of tax reform. I can't<br />
obviously spend a great deal of time in going through all the<br />
details of where we are there, but there are certain things that<br />
obviously I should say to you but let me make these points. The<br />
first, most obviously fundamental point that needs to be made and<br />
needs to be understood by the whole Australian community, and I<br />
suggest most particularly by our own party, that the present<br />
taxation system is haemorhaging, decaying. The revenue bases is<br />
disappearing. And in that process, as will always be the case<br />
unless you have a government there concerned with the welfare of<br />
the people as a whole, the people who have suffered much are those<br />
on the lower income, those who depend upon Social Security<br />
payments. Because the rich, the privileged are always , and I say<br />
this without any venum bufit is in the nature of things -those<br />
people are the ones who are always most capable of looking after<br />
themselves. And so a Government which is concerned with trying to<br />
secure equity into our society must ensure that there is a reform<br />
of the tax system which means that all people as far as it's<br />
possible to do, should meet there obligations to contribute to the<br />
common wealth, the common revenue.<br />
And so we, as we promised in the election, have drawn up a white<br />
paper which exposes the increasing inadequacy of the existing<br />
systemn and opens up the avenues for reform, including the putting<br />
of a prefered option. We recognise that in that prefered option<br />
there are problems, potential difficulties, but we believe that<br />
they are capable of being-overcome. We do not go into the tax<br />
summit, beginning of July saying that we are the fount of all<br />
wisdom, we know exactly what is right. We have derived in the<br />
past two years enormous encouragement from and contributions from<br />
the important elements of Australian society and we expect to do<br />
something about it. And so we will expose this white paper in the<br />
first week of June, there will be the best. part of three or four<br />
weeks in which it can be disgested and studied and analysed by the<br />
people who are going in a representative fashion to the tax<br />
summit.<br />
And then as a government, once we've had the opportunity of<br />
listening to the Australian community, we will discuss these<br />
issues further and then seek to bring in a reformed tax system in<br />
which the principles, equity, efficiency and simplicity will be<br />
reflected, so that the great mass of Australian people will<br />
believe that justice is being done. And so that we can really get<br />
to what always in any society is the heart of fiscal reform and it<br />
is this. There are certain things that as individuals we cannot<br />
do out of our own expenditure. And so the society is based upon<br />
the proposition, in a democratic society, it is based upon the<br />
proposition that individuals and corporations will transfer part<br />
of their income to the'government as a whole which will act on<br />
behalf of the community to do those things which individuals are<br />
incapable of doing themselves. As individuals we can't build our<br />
roads. We can't build our schools. We can't provide our defence<br />
forces and so on. So as a community we have those things providedthrough<br />
government. And the government has the where with all to<br />
do Cjose things because as individuals and corporations we pay<br />
ovet' ,; ome of our income. And so the secret of decent and<br />
effective government is that the community be satisfied that they </p>
<p>are paying over as individuals and as corporations, their revenue<br />
in a way that is most effective to give government that level of<br />
revenue which will enable it as a government to do those things<br />
that as communities they want done.<br />
The money that we yield in government is not Hawke's money, not<br />
Keating's money, it is not the government's money. It's the<br />
peoples' money. So we want to ensure that the money that people<br />
provide to the government to perform the services they want done<br />
is provided in a way which they as a community regard as the most<br />
equitable. Now we, I guess, could easily be deterred from that<br />
task because of this information campaign which has put around the<br />
attempt to divert from this course. I make no apologies for the<br />
fact that since the election we have been working hard upon this<br />
task because we regard it as our responsibility to ensure that<br />
people do have the best possible opportunity of directing their<br />
minds as to how we best deal with this situation. I can assure<br />
you, we will not be diverted from the task.<br />
When we have completed that, and when we go on with the further<br />
dedication that we have to the processes of ensuring economic<br />
growth we will have produced as we go towards the end of our<br />
second term, a convincing exposition and exposure to the<br />
Australian people of the capacities and the integrity and the<br />
determination of your great Australian Labor Party, to move to<br />
provide more rapidly growing economy and importantly one within<br />
which we will increasingly do those things for the people in<br />
Australia most in need to improve their situation.<br />
En pursuing that course, let me say quite clearly, that there will<br />
be a need for the exercise of restraint by the Australian<br />
community because it is the case that at the moment we are living<br />
beyond our needs, We have to address ourselves to that fact. We<br />
commenced that process with the May statement in this second term<br />
of government., And I believe there has becA a general acceptance<br />
of the equity with which we approached that task. There is going<br />
to be further need for co-operation in this by the great elements<br />
of our community and I pay tribute to the fact that the great<br />
Australian trade union movement accepts that it has a part to<br />
play in this role, and we will co-operately with them, try and<br />
ensure that the exercise of that restraint is done in a way in<br />
which we may quickly guarantee positive economic results.<br />
Before I come to wind up what I hav'e to say, it would be much less<br />
than adequate if I concluded these remarks by simply talking about<br />
things of domestic economic significance, or domestic social<br />
significance. I believe that one of the great injustices of the<br />
later period of our first government, was that there was not a<br />
sufficient recognition of the pioneering works that this<br />
government has done in ' the international area. In co-operation<br />
with Bill Hayden as Foreign Minister and the appointment of the<br />
first Ambassador for Disarmament, the first Hawke Labor Government<br />
did play a pioneering role in a number of international forums, in<br />
advancing the causes of peace and disarmament. A course which wasopenly<br />
and specifically recognised by many nations in what they<br />
have to say about Australia, which I think is overwhelmingly<br />
reflected in the record vote, that we, Australia, got in the<br />
election for the Security Council. It didn't happen by accident. </p>
<p>It happened because the range of the nations saw, distinct from<br />
rhetoric, we in those two years steadfastly and consistently in<br />
all relevant forums pursued realistically the issues of the peace<br />
and disarmament. We will continue to do that.<br />
We have coining up in September of this year, the Non-Proliferation<br />
Treaty review and Australia has already played a foremost role in<br />
the preparation for that review. And I will say that in regard to<br />
the issue of a nuclear free South Pacific the initiative which I<br />
launched in Canberra in July of 1983 at the meeting of the South<br />
Pacific Forum is rapidly moving to fruition. We set up a working<br />
party following the second South Pacific Forum meeting that we<br />
were involved in Tuvalu last year. We set up a working party.<br />
The fourth meeting of that working party has just been going on in<br />
Suva and I believe that when we meet in Raratonga in the Cook<br />
Islands in August of this year, we will have before us, as a<br />
result of the initiative of this Government, a draft Treaty for a<br />
nuclear free zone in the South Pacific.<br />
Now these are the sorts of things not rhetoric but actions, quiet<br />
but effective actions that your government has been and will be<br />
involved in. I give you the assurance that through the life of<br />
this second Hawke Labor Government we will leave no stone unturned<br />
in those international forums to continue those tasks, use our<br />
influence upon not only the superpowers but the other nations with<br />
which we have influence try as rapidly as will be a sigificant<br />
reduction in the level of armaments particularly of nuclear arms.<br />
So that with a greater degree of confidence, the people, and<br />
particularly the young people of this world, who will be able to<br />
look to the future freer of the devastating effects of nuclear<br />
holocaust. And so my friends I go from there to come back in conclusion to<br />
you here in Tasmania. I thank you for what you've done in the<br />
past. I know there have been difficulties.* I ask that you in the<br />
council and that you in the party will in the future do all that<br />
you can to make the contributions that you can to ensuring first<br />
of all the return, as they say, of a Wriedt Labor Government so<br />
that Ken Wriedt will be able from the official position of Premier<br />
to do what he ahs been doing unofficially from the position of<br />
Leader of opposition to see that in a non-hysterical and<br />
affective way the interests of the people of Tasmania are<br />
advanced. And I say in return to you that I give you the<br />
commitment of this Federal Government, not merely in regard..<br />
here in Tasmania, that we will continue to have regard and real<br />
regard to the interest of the people of this State. But that we<br />
will continue to advance the work of economic and social reform so<br />
that we will be able to go into the next election showing the<br />
demonstrably true form of what we have done to make this a better<br />
country so that we will again have a mandate to go further to<br />
producing a more prosperous and more equitable Australia. And I<br />
say at all times we will be undertaking those tasks in the<br />
knowledge that we must continue internationally to work for a<br />
world of peace, a world of disarmament, a world free from the<br />
threat of the nuclear holocaust. These are the things that we<br />
will do and I ask you for your support in those great tasks.<br />
ENDS </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
