<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11399</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER          ADDRESS TO AUSTRALIAN TROOPS          BATUGADE, EAST TIMOR</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/11/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE..................</p>
<p>  [Tape starts]</p>
<p>  General Cosgrove has proved to be an inspiration not only to the men and</p>
<p>   women of the Australian Defence Force, but also to the men and women of</p>
<p>   other countries that are serving with Australians in the INTERFET force.</p>
<p>   You've behaved in an absolutely impeccable and professional manner. Your</p>
<p>   training has been demonstrated to be very adequate for the job that you</p>
<p>   were given. You've not only secured your military objectives, but just as</p>
<p>   importantly you have secured the broader social and civilian objectives</p>
<p>   that these days any men and women in the armed forces of a country must</p>
<p>   do. You've won the confidence and the respect and the affection of the local</p>
<p>   people who've had a very rough time. You came here because it was the right</p>
<p>   thing for our country to do, and it was also in Australia's interests that</p>
<p>   you come. And having come here you've discharged your job with tremendous</p>
<p>   professional skills...[break in speech].</p>
<p>  But could I just say picking up where I stopped, that you came here in the</p>
<p>   name of the whole country, and you came to carry out a very just mission</p>
<p>   and also a mission that was in Australia's long term interests. And you've</p>
<p>   brought back to the people of East Timor some hope, some optimism, and some</p>
<p>   measure of faith in the future. You've also restored great peace and stability</p>
<p>   to this area. It's been a very important, although unexpected part of your</p>
<p>   military life, and I know that many of you have quite properly seen it as</p>
<p>   the sort of thing that you joined the Army in order to do. And I know that</p>
<p>   when you came here there was understandably a lot of apprehension about</p>
<p>   how dangerous it was because it was dangerous, and we shared as best we</p>
<p>   could the anxiety that you and more importantly your families would have</p>
<p>   felt about what might happen. But because of the tremendous training that</p>
<p>   you've received and the way in which you've been so effectively led, gratefully</p>
<p>   and thankfully casualties have been kept to an absolute minimum and that's</p>
<p>   something that we're always extremely grateful to know.</p>
<p>  Can I assure you that your mission here has the total support of the entire</p>
<p>   Australian population. In the 25 years that I've been in politics I've not</p>
<p>   known an overseas involvement of Australia, and this of course is our biggest</p>
<p>   involvement militarily since the Vietnam War, which has attracted such across</p>
<p>   the board support. Irrespective of differences back home over other issues,</p>
<p>   there is very widespread support that you're right to be here, that you've</p>
<p>   done it well, and that in the process you have added a great deal of lustre</p>
<p>   to a very proud Australian military tradition. And I want therefore on behalf</p>
<p>   of myself, my Government, and all of the people of Australia to express</p>
<p>   my gratitude and thanks and appreciation and respect to all of you, to the</p>
<p>   commander of the INTERFET operation Major-General Cosgrove, to all the other</p>
<p>   commanding officers of the Australian units that are serving here, because</p>
<p>   Australia has led this mission. It was Australia's initiative that brought</p>
<p>   this mission about. It was Australian leadership that got the INTERFET together,</p>
<p>   and it's been Australian leadership that had done so much effective work.</p>
<p>   But that is not in any way to play down the significance of the cooperation</p>
<p>   from our 16 or 17 other friends within the INTERFET forces, from different</p>
<p>   parts of the world. All of them have played a very very significant role.</p>
<p>   But your contribution has been immense. I thank you for it. I wish all of</p>
<p>   you well. I hope that it continues to be a smooth operation, and that in</p>
<p>   the fullness of time when it's fully completed, all of you will safely return</p>
<p>   home to your families and other loved ones. And can I just very very warmly</p>
<p>   thank you very much.</p>
<p>  I have two pieces of mail that I want to deliver. One of them is to Private</p>
<p>   Robin J Moore of the boys of the Intelligence Section who corresponded with</p>
<p>   me, and I was very pleased to respond to their correspondence. And also</p>
<p>   Major S E Clinging of 2RAR as well. And in the course of moving around and</p>
<p>   saying hello to you I'd be delighted to meet those two gentlemen and personally</p>
<p>   hand these items of mail to them.</p>
<p>  But just again, thank you very much. You've done a superb job and the entire</p>
<p>   Australian nation is very proud of all of you. Thanks.</p>
<p>  [Ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
