<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11002</transcript-id>
    <title>11 June 1999                                                  TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                   THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                   RADIO INTERVIEW WITH JOHN LAWS, RADIO 2UE                                                  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/06/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Subjects: Coal miners' entitlements; Warren Entsch</p>
<p>E&amp;OE................................................................................................</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>Are you there John?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I am indeed. Good morning John.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>How are you?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Very well. I'm in Melbourne.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>Are you. Does that make you well?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Always. It's a great place. I've had a very pleasant evening,</p>
<p> and going out to open a new research facility at the Peter MacCallum</p>
<p> Cancer Institute.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>It's a great city Melbourne, it's a great country Australia</p>
<p> isn't it.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It sure is.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>And I think we're so lucky to have diversification in cities</p>
<p> when you think of Adelaide with its history, and Melbourne with its</p>
<p> wide avenues and parks, and Sydney with its Harbour, and Brisbane</p>
<p> with its river and different feeling. We live in a great cosmopolitan</p>
<p> country.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>We do. And each city has its own particular lustre and appeal.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>That's right. We were talking about these poor miners at Oakdale,</p>
<p> near Camden in New South Wales, and the closure of this mine leaving</p>
<p> these fellas with nothing. Out of work and no entitlements. It happened</p>
<p> before at Cobar and I know we talked a lot about it then. Can this</p>
<p> be allowed to continue, that the workers, the people who actually</p>
<p> get a business going and keep it going are fourth on the list when</p>
<p> it comes to getting money?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Can I just say in relation to Cobar we did of course, after a lot</p>
<p> of chasing up at the instance of the government, get most of their</p>
<p> money for them. We chased the company. Now I'm having all of</p>
<p> the circumstances of this situation investigated. I can't at</p>
<p> this stage say whether or not there are any analagous circumstances</p>
<p> in relation to Cobar. Everything you say about the apparent inequity</p>
<p> of it is true. The problem is that these men's entitlements rank</p>
<p> behind secured creditors and others, and the question arises as to</p>
<p> whether the law should be changed to put them ahead of secured creditors.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>Don't you think it should be?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well some people would argue that, and we've had a look at that.</p>
<p> The problem of course is that many people believe that if the people</p>
<p> who actually lend the money to get a business going don't have</p>
<p> first call then fewer people will lend money to get businesses going,</p>
<p> and fewer people will be employed. Now that's one side of the</p>
<p> argument.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>Okay. But those people who have leant the money to get businesses</p>
<p> going have done so with an element of avarice. They're not donating</p>
<p> to charity. They've only got go make....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well no, well that is true. I mean I acknowledge that. I also though</p>
<p> acknowledge that anything that makes it less attractive for people</p>
<p> to lend to small businesses, and therefore more attractive to invest</p>
<p> in say, property development, will have an adverse affect on the flow</p>
<p> of money into small businesses. One of the complaints I have is that</p>
<p> it's still hard for small businesses to borrow. One of the reasons</p>
<p> it's hard is that it's more attractive to put into building</p>
<p> a block of flats or something like that where there is less risk,</p>
<p> and there's brick and mortar security. So that's the other</p>
<p> side of the argument. John, I think there's a very strong argument</p>
<p> in equity, but people have to understand that there is also a cash</p>
<p> availability argument. And some people have said what you have to</p>
<p> do is force companies to put into some kind of trust fund the money</p>
<p> that should be there to cover these entitlements. You can do that,</p>
<p> you can do that. The cost of course would be that many small businesses</p>
<p> would thereby have less money to run their businesses because I think</p>
<p> you realise that most small businesses, they invest every spare dollar</p>
<p> they've got in the operation of the business.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>Yeah, and I understand that they are very very important. They're</p>
<p> the backbone of the country. But I would have thought that coal mining</p>
<p> was a step away from small business. These fellas are going to walk</p>
<p> away with nothing, and the mine says they don't have the money</p>
<p> to pay them. But they do apparently have money to pursue coal ventures</p>
<p> elsewhere.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well John, as I said at the beginning of the comments, I'm getting</p>
<p> all the information and I can assure that if there's been any</p>
<p> improper behaviour then that will be pursued. I'm not suggesting</p>
<p> there has been but I want to get all the information on it. And as</p>
<p> we demonstrated with Cobar, a fairly difficult situation ultimately</p>
<p> turned out to be quite good. Now I'm not saying this is analagous</p>
<p> to Cobar, but I'm having some investigations made. And we, myself</p>
<p> or the Treasurer will be saying something further about it when those</p>
<p> investigations have been completed.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>I thought that worker entitlements were protected by law.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well they are protected by law, subject of course to.....I mean</p>
<p> people have a legal entitlement to have them but if the company hasn't</p>
<p> got the money then they miss out. Now that's the problem. And</p>
<p> the only way you make certain that a company has the money is to force</p>
<p> the company to put the money to pay the entitlements into some kind</p>
<p> of separate fund which can't be touched for the ordinary operations</p>
<p> of the company. Now, you could do that. But that would have a very</p>
<p> serious effect on the cash flow position of many businesses in Australia.</p>
<p> I don't think that would be workable.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>No, I understand what you're saying, and I've got to say</p>
<p> I've never thought of it in that light before. But it still seems</p>
<p> to me morally unsound that the fellas, and it's not much fun</p>
<p> being a coal miner.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, John, I agree with that and that's the reason why I'm</p>
<p> saying to you, and through you to the public that I'm not sort</p>
<p> of indicating that nothing can be done about these things in the future.</p>
<p> I think this is a problem. I think it's a problem that's</p>
<p> been thrown up very sharply by a number of cases and this is the latest</p>
<p> one of them. Peter Costello at the moment is talking with the States</p>
<p> about changes to the law to prevent company restructuring to avoid</p>
<p> obligations. And once again if there are things that have occurred</p>
<p> here that involve that well we will use every available means to see</p>
<p> what we can do to get the money for the men. But I sympathise with</p>
<p> them very much, and I think it throws up a real, I guess, clash of</p>
<p> interests. On the one hand the moral entitlement of these people is</p>
<p> their money, but also the practical considerations that are involved</p>
<p> that if you have an iron clad arrangement so they can get the money,</p>
<p> the cost of that in terms of small business capital could be significant.</p>
<p> And that's the trade off in a sense you've got to provide</p>
<p> for.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>Yeah. One tends to look at the underdog, and in this case it's</p>
<p> the worker.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes, and these men are the underdogs. I accept that.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>And already, for sale signs are appearing on houses, and then families</p>
<p> are shattered. And I know you wouldn't like that anymore than</p>
<p> I like it.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>None of us like that and that's why we're talking about</p>
<p> it.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>Who's going to want to buy a house in an area where there's</p>
<p> no industry....?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I understand that, and I, as I say, we are gathering all the information</p>
<p> we can about it. I think the concerns that have been expressed by</p>
<p> a lot of people are legitimate and I will work my way through it and</p>
<p> see if we can't find a response which is fairer but also practical</p>
<p> and commonsense in the longer term.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>Have you got a quiet long weekend lined up Prime Minister?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I'm going to the opening of Stadium Australia on Saturday night</p>
<p> to watch the soccer.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>That'll be terrific. I thought you might have been going to say</p>
<p> that you were going to Warren Entsch's farewell party.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No. He'll be around for a while. He's a good bloke. He's</p>
<p> a very popular local member. He was careless in filling out his form,</p>
<p> but he didn't try to cover up his financial interest and that's</p>
<p> the test for me. And I'll cop the criticism for sticking by him.</p>
<p> But unless there's evidence that somebody's tried to be</p>
<p> dishonest or tried to cover up their financial interests I'm</p>
<p> not going to sack somebody on a mere technicality. I think to apply</p>
<p> a ministerial code in that way is to be quite lacking in commonsense.</p>
<p>LAWS:</p>
<p>Okay. Enjoy your weekend and thank you very much for your time.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Okay.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
