<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5405</transcript-id>
    <title>LAUNCHING OF THE SYDNEY LEGACY TORCH APPEAL</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/07/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005405.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO: AGAINST DELIVERY,<br />
4~~ LIA1: 40 pm<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA FRIDAY, 25 JULY, 1980<br />
LAUNCHING OF THE SYDNEY LEGACY TORCH APPEAL<br />
Thank you for inviting me here today to open your Torch<br />
Appeal launching the Sydney Legacy Appeal for 1980. I had<br />
the privilege of launching your 1976 appeal.<br />
The intervening ye ars have seen a continued commitment,<br />
here and throughout Australia, to the spirit of service<br />
which is central to the Legacy charter.<br />
We can never fully repay the debt we owe, as a nation, to<br />
those who served their country in time of war.<br />
The freedom we enjoy today, and the standard of living that<br />
we are inclined to take for granted, should be constant<br />
reminders to us of the extent of our indebtedness.<br />
But it has been said that no nation in the world cares<br />
for the families of its returned ex-servicemen with as much<br />
generosity and dedication as Australia.<br />
TheL Legacy organisation and the Commonwealth Government share<br />
together a profound interest in caring for the dependents<br />
of those who have been casualties in the service of our<br />
country. The creation of the Commonwealth repatriation system ~ in 1917<br />
was recognition of a national responsibility for ex-servicemen<br />
and women, and their families.<br />
Successive governments have built significantly upon that<br />
first step. But no amount of money or government involvement<br />
can provide the personal touch of a voluntary organisation<br />
such as Legacy.<br />
The hallmark of Legacy's work has always been the personal<br />
service given to families by Legatees.<br />
Sydney Legacy provides over a thousand ex-servicemen as<br />
Legatees in metropolitan Sydney and country areas.<br />
This is the result of a comradeship fostered and developed<br />
in battle, which has continued for over fifty years.<br />
It is alive in the magnificent spirit of continuing care<br />
for the families of departed comrades; and this care<br />
characterises the unselfish efforts of Australia's<br />
returned servicemen. ./ 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
Legacy's contribution in what many sometimes see as an<br />
uncaring and selfish society is an example to us all.<br />
Of course, it is impossible to replace a lost husband.<br />
But what is admirable is the way in which Legatees are<br />
willing to ease the burden of those left alone to cope<br />
with the pressures of caring for a family.<br />
This requires from each Legatee time, energy, money and<br />
experience. And he provides for the family in his care,<br />
practical assistance in obtaining Government services such<br />
as social welfare and repatriation benefits.<br />
The contribution made by Legacy to the education of children<br />
of deceased veterans deserves universal acknowledgement.<br />
I suspect that when Major General Sir John Gellibrand formed<br />
a remembrance club after World War I, he never imagined that<br />
it would blossom into such a comprehensive community<br />
service organisation.<br />
Since then, it has taken care of over half a million widows<br />
and children.<br />
There are 108,000 people in Australia currently being cared<br />
for by Legacy; and 27,000 of these are the direct<br />
responsibility of Sydney Legacy.<br />
And this number is growing. For over the years, all too many<br />
tragic conflicts in Malaysia, Korea, and Vietnam have brought<br />
new responsibilities to Legacy.<br />
have been met; and families within their care have<br />
included those of allied ex-servicemen who have since settled<br />
in Australia; and the families of ex-servicemen who have<br />
died since returning from service.<br />
The enormous task of assisting such families will continue<br />
into the 21st Century.<br />
For some 50,000 Australian servicemen took part in the<br />
Vietnam War, and, in due course, many of their families will<br />
come under Legacy's care.<br />
As a Government, we believe that care for those in need. in our<br />
community is most beneficially met by government working in<br />
partnership with voluntary organisations.<br />
In recognition of this, since coming to office, this government<br />
has maintained a long established system of providing benefits<br />
for veterans. / 3<br />
I </p>
<p>-3<br />
I believe that Australia's current repatriation system iS<br />
one of the most accessible and generous systems in the world,<br />
being based on principles and policies which have been<br />
developed and tuned, over the years, to me'et the needs that<br />
have arisen since World War I.<br />
This government will continue to ensure that these princiLples<br />
and policies are maintained.<br />
Repatriation expenditure increased from $ 62 million in<br />
1949/ 50 to $ 317 million twenty years later.<br />
In the last financial year, the figure had risen to over<br />
$ 1,300 million.<br />
And in the last Budget, the Government made substantial<br />
adjustments to a number of important benefits for veterans.<br />
These benefits are reinforced in their effectiveness by<br />
the work of Legacy.<br />
But like all voluntary organisations, Legacy must rely<br />
primarily on fund raising activities to finance its various<br />
programmes. Thus, it is dependent on the community in general, and in<br />
particular on people such as yourselves the representatives<br />
of business houses and clubs for its success.<br />
This year, Sydney Legacy needs more than $ 1.2 million to meet<br />
its programmes.<br />
The Torch Appeal which we launch today is Legacy's major<br />
fu~ hd raising activity.<br />
It will culminate in Legacy week with the annual button day<br />
on September<br />
This is a day when Australians are proud to show that they care<br />
by displaying Legacy's symbol and buying a button from<br />
thousands of generous helpers.<br />
The target for the Torch Appeal this year is $ 500,000.<br />
It is obvious, ladies and gentlemen, that Sydney Legacy cannot'<br />
carry on its magnificent work without strong and continued<br />
support.<br />
Let us today assure legacy of that support.<br />
I know all Australians are aware of the important role they<br />
can play, through this appeal, to enable Legacy to assist<br />
the families of those who served our country in time of' war.<br />
4 </p>
<p>-4<br />
So, on behalf of those ex-servicemen who are no longer<br />
with us, I ask you all, and the whole Australian comimuniLty,<br />
to give generously in the weeks ahead.<br />
Through this spirit of giving we can make sure that the<br />
families of deceased ex-servicemen are cared for in the way<br />
they deserve and in the way the servicemen would have<br />
wished. I have much pleasure in declaring Legacy's Torch Appeal<br />
officially open. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
