<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2391</transcript-id>
    <title>BACKGROUND TO OMEGA INSTALLATION - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR WILLIAM MCMAHON</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/03/1971</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002391.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS PM. No. 37/ 1971<br />
BACKGROUND TO OMEGA INSTALLATION.<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, Mr William McMahon<br />
In reply to a question by Mr Barnard in the House of Representatives<br />
on 18 March 1 said that negotiations had taken place between the United States<br />
and Australian Governments on a p roposal to set up an OMEGA installation in<br />
Australia to guide international shipping and other kinds of transport.<br />
I said that we had agreed to the proposal but no precise location had<br />
yet been decided. I promised that, as soon as I had precise irifornntion which I<br />
could give to the House, I would do so.<br />
In view, however, of continued misleading statements on the subject,<br />
I feel it would be wise to give some further background now, even though no<br />
decision has yet been made on a site.<br />
OMEGA is a general purpose world-wide navigation system that can<br />
be used by ships and aircraft of any type fitted with the appropriate equipment;<br />
but the system is not sufficiently accurate for use either in close coastal waters<br />
or by ballistic missile submarines.<br />
The plan envisages eight stations in various parts of the world, four of<br />
which have already been established. It is envisaged that control of the worldwide<br />
system will be vested in a body cornpo8ed of representatives of each of the<br />
participating nations.<br />
The Australian Government has agreed to this proposal in princi* i.<br />
A final agreement is dependent on the selection of a mutually acceptable site,<br />
conclusion of an agreement covering its establishment and operation, and the<br />
negotiation of acceptable financial terms and conditions.<br />
Initially the technical specifications called for a valley of a certain<br />
type of configuration. On this basis the choice of sites would probably have been<br />
limited to certain areas of New South Wales or Tasmania. As a result of<br />
technical advances, however, the equipment can now be mounted on a tower and<br />
this has greatly enlarged the area and range of options. Consideration is being<br />
given to possible sites but no firm conclusion have yet been reached. When a<br />
tentative selection has been made the Government would, of course, consult<br />
with the State authority or authorities concerned.<br />
CANBERRA 22 March 1971<br />
6 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
