<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4516</transcript-id>
    <title>WHITE CANE SAFETY DAY, 14 OCTOBER 1977</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/10/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004516.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
F77/ 227<br />
4A U S RL A~<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 14 OCTOBER 1977<br />
WHITE CANE SAFETY DAY<br />
" In the hustle and bustle of daily life, and especially in fast<br />
moving cities, it was all too easy to overlook the difficulties<br />
faced by blind and visually handicapped people in maintaining<br />
their independence of movement", the Prime Minister, the Rt. Hon.<br />
Malcolm Fraser, said today.<br />
The Prime Minister said that he had much pleasure in supporting<br />
efforts by the Australian Federation of Blind Citizens to have a<br />
particular day each year recognised throughout Australia as " White<br />
Cane Safety Day". October 15 had been suggested as an appropriate<br />
day and was already recognised in many overseas countries and<br />
some States as-White Cane Safety Day.<br />
Formal recognition of a White Cane Safety Day will provide an<br />
opportunity for all Australians, especially motorists, to give<br />
special consideration to the blind and visually handicapped as<br />
they move about our busy streets.<br />
" The white cane is recognised internationally as a sign of the<br />
determination of the blind and visually handicapped people to live<br />
useful and productive lives in our modern societies", the Prime<br />
Minister said.<br />
The cane would be most useful in drawing to attention the fact<br />
that blind and visually handicapped people were making their own<br />
way. Courtesy demanded that the white cane should be recognised<br />
as the symbol of a need to take particular account of the requirements<br />
of people who were maintaining their independence despite<br />
disability. Mr. Fraser said he hoped there could be a combined effort by all<br />
those concerned with the needs of blind and visually handicapped<br />
people to use the White Cane Safety Day as a focus for increasing<br />
public awareness of the mobility requirements of these people. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
