<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10564</transcript-id>
    <title>18 December 1997                                 TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                  THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                  TELEVISION INTERVIEW WITH DENNIS GRANT                ONE-TO-ONE - SBS NINE O&amp;#146;CLOCK NEWS</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/12/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...............................................</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>The last year has been very good for us internationally. We had</p>
<p>   a stunning success at the Kyoto Conference against all predictions,</p>
<p>   and all of my critics were proved wrong, and all of the Government's</p>
<p>   critics. They said it couldn't be done, the Labor Party wanted</p>
<p>   us to capitulate to European pressure. We have got an outcome that</p>
<p>   is good for the environment, good for Australian industry, gets</p>
<p>   the developing countries in touch with the process. We achieved</p>
<p>   what we set out to do against all expectations.</p>
<p>GRANT:</p>
<p>How do you think, now, that most of the candidates are identified,</p>
<p>   the Constitutional Convention might pan out? A worthwhile exercise?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>The Constitutional Convention will be a lot better, a lot more</p>
<p>   successful, and it will generate a lot more public interest than</p>
<p>   the cynics thought likely. It really will be a great moment in Australia's</p>
<p>   history. What the Convention has got to do, above everything else,</p>
<p>   is to settle on a republican alternative. Whether you are a republican</p>
<p>   or an anti-republican, we all know what the status quo is, we don't</p>
<p>   know what the alternative is. And what I want republicans and non-republicans</p>
<p>   alike to do at the Convention is to make up their mind what kind</p>
<p>   of republic Australia should be if it decides to become a republic.</p>
<p>   And then we can have a proper vote, a proper contest, a proper assessment.</p>
<p>GRANT:</p>
<p>What happens though if after two weeks talking in February there</p>
<p>   is a nil result, no outcome, no proper alternative is decided upon?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I am an optimist Dennis, and I will be prodding, and pushing, and</p>
<p>   cajoling and persuading as Prime Minister, the delegates to reach</p>
<p>   an agreement. There is no point in having gone to all of this trouble,</p>
<p>   staged this Convention, there is no point in walking away from it</p>
<p>   without having reached, at least a conclusion on what the alternatives</p>
<p>   are. It is not up to the Convention to decide whether or not Australia</p>
<p>   will become a republic, it is up to the Convention, sure to talk</p>
<p>   about that issue, but above everything else to define the republican</p>
<p>   alternative.</p>
<p>GRANT:</p>
<p>Noel Pearson, he has had an interesting week. He is telling friends</p>
<p>   that he may stand as an independent right here in your seat, Bennelong,</p>
<p>   are you worried about that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No. It is a free country. It would probably split the Labor vote</p>
<p>   a bit. But that is up to him, I don't mind. I think what is</p>
<p>   interesting about Noel is that, where as the Labor Party rapidly</p>
<p>   embraced Mrs Kernot it seems to be running away from him, despite</p>
<p>   the fact that he has had quite a close association with the Labor</p>
<p>   Party over the years and there is certainly not much doubt in the</p>
<p>   minds of most observers that his politics have always been much</p>
<p>   more Labor than anything else.</p>
<p>GRANT:</p>
<p>One of the things that I am very curious about is the politics</p>
<p>   of the stolen children argument. I mean, we are in a position now</p>
<p>   where clerics are going to be thundering from their pulpits calling</p>
<p>   for an apology, where reporters are going to be trailing you around</p>
<p>   the country saying what about an apology, why is it so hard. Surely,</p>
<p>   from a political point of view, wouldn't it be just much easier</p>
<p>   dealt with and got out of the road?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>You have got to do what you believe is right on something like</p>
<p>   this, not what is political. I have said on several occasions and</p>
<p>   I say it again tonight, that personally I am very sorry for any</p>
<p>   ill-treatment or any discrimination against the Aboriginal people</p>
<p>   of Australia, no matter when it occurred. I don't have any</p>
<p>   personal difficulty at all in saying that. I just believe though</p>
<p>   that the proposition that there should be a formal national apology</p>
<p>   in relation to events that when occurring were sanctioned by the</p>
<p>   law of the time, and were thought at the time by many people, however</p>
<p>   ineptly and we now believe, to have been in the best interests of</p>
<p>   the community. Now, I think to get </p>
<p>into formal national apologies in circumstances like that is just</p>
<p>   not appropriate. That doesn't alter the fact that if you ask</p>
<p>   me as an individual, do I feel that things were done wrong by some</p>
<p>   people? Of course I do. And am I sorry for the suffering? Of course</p>
<p>   I am. I have never had any difficulty saying that, nor have any</p>
<p>   of my colleagues. But I think once you get into the area of formal</p>
<p>   national apologies it raises all sorts of other implications and</p>
<p>   establishes all sorts of other precedents. And I think there are</p>
<p>   a lot of people in Australia who understand that my reluctance and</p>
<p>   unwillingness to do that does not suggest, in any way, that I am</p>
<p>   insensitive and lack compassion. It is just a view as to what is</p>
<p>   appropriate.</p>
<p>[Ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
