<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5637</transcript-id>
    <title>THE QUEEN&#039;S VISIT</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/08/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005637.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
~ CA~ A e<br />
0= 1W~ L<br />
PRIME -MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA MONDAY, 17 AUGUST, 1981<br />
THE QUEEN'S VISIT<br />
I announced on 20 November 1980 that The Queen, accompanied<br />
by The Duke of Edinburgh, would visit Australia in September<br />
and October 1981 to be present in Melbourne when the<br />
Commonwealth Heads of Government Meeting is held there and to<br />
visit Tasmania, Western Australia and South Australia.<br />
The Queen h as now approved a programme of engagements in<br />
Melbourne 26 September-3 October, Tasmania 5-6 October,<br />
Perth 6-9 October, and Adelaide 9-12 October.<br />
Her Majesty will arrive at Melbourne Airport by RAAF Boeing 707<br />
from London on Saturday evening, 26 September, and, accompanied<br />
by The Duke of Edinburgh, will depart from Adelaide Airport<br />
for New Zealand on the morning of Monday 12 October.<br />
Apart from engagements in connection with the. Commonwealth<br />
Heads of Government Meeting in Melbourne, the Queen's programme<br />
includ-es attendance at a variety of official, social, cultural,<br />
sporting and other engagements. Premiers will announce details<br />
of the programme for each State.<br />
In Melbourne and Hobart, The Queen and The Duke of Edinburgh<br />
will live on board the Royal Yacht BRITANNIA. Her Majesty<br />
will sail in the Royal Yacht from Melbourne to Hobart.<br />
The Queen's air journeys within Australia will be by<br />
RAAF Boeing 707 and BAG 1-11 aircraft.<br />
On some occasions, The Duke of Edinburgh will undertake a<br />
separate programme of engagements.<br />
His Royal Highness will arrive in Australia for the first<br />
time during this visit on Wednesday 30 September for The Queen's<br />
dinner for Commonwealth Heads of Government in Melbourne, and<br />
will leave for overseas the following day, rejoining the Queen<br />
in Hobart on Monday 5 October. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
