<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>23843</transcript-id>
    <title>A message from the Prime Minister - A Safe and Secure Australia</title>
    <prime-minister>Abbott, Tony</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130918 - 20150915</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/09/2014</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>This last week, Australia’s largest ever counter-terrorism operation took place.</p>
<p>
It involved security and intelligence agencies as well as Commonwealth and state police.</p>
<p>Our agencies had reliable information of an attack ordered by an Australian who is a senior ISIL operative in Syria.</p>
<p>This operation ensured that an atrocity didn’t happen. So, I thank the police and our security and intelligence agencies for their tireless work to keep us safe, and I assure you that the Government will continue its work in protecting Australians from terrorism and extremism.</p>
<p>On Monday, I will make a national security statement to the Parliament.</p>
<p>This statement will update the Parliament on developments at home and abroad, and on how Australia is responding to the threat of terrorism.</p>
<p>Also this week, the Government will introduce into Parliament new counter-terrorism measures that will strengthen our counter-terrorism preparedness.</p>
<p>We are providing $630 million to support our police and security agencies with more resources to the Australian Federal Police, ASIO, ASIS and our Customs and Border Protection Service.</p>
<p>This work is not about targeting any particular community. It’s not about religion, it’s not about what people wear – it’s about dealing with criminals.</p>
<p>And then on Tuesday, I will travel to the United States to be part of a special session of the Security Council, convened by President Obama. Eighty nations – eighty nations – face the challenge of dealing with foreign fighters.</p>
<p>In responding to this threat – in responding to the threat of extremism – we are doing everything we humanly can to keep you safe.</p>
<p>This Government will continue to build the safe and secure Australia that everyone wants.</p>
<p>21 September 2014</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
