<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8268</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA HON RJL HAWKE, AC MP OPENING CEREMONY SOCIALIST INTERNATIONAL MEETING SYDENY - 9 MARCH 1991</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/03/1991</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008268.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL. DELITVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA<br />
HON RJL HAWKE, AC MP<br />
OPENING CEREMONY<br />
SOCIALIST INTERNATIONAL MEETING<br />
SYDNEY 9 MARCH 1991<br />
Mr President, Mr Secretary General, delegates, colleagues,<br />
friends, welcome.<br />
This Party Leaders Meeting of the Socialist International<br />
opens today against the background of a world witnessing the<br />
most dramatic change in a generation and more. It is the<br />
background of the immensely important developments all over<br />
Europe and in the Soviet Union, the dynamic transformation<br />
in the Asia-Pacific region, and the aftermath of the Gulf<br />
war, with all its dangers and opportunities, not only for<br />
the Middle East, but for the whole world community.<br />
This Conference also comes at a special time for the<br />
Australian labour movement. We celebrate this year the<br />
hundredth anniversary of the foundation of the Australian<br />
Labor Party. And, as a party, we celebrate this anniversary<br />
entering our ninth consecutive year in government.<br />
We in the ALI' are proud of our achievements over the past<br />
eight years; we are proud that through those achievements we<br />
have met the century-old aspirations of our Party and of the<br />
movement to which we all belong.<br />
At every step we have sought to foster a sense of a. nmunity<br />
interests wit~ h which all Australians can identify.<br />
Such an approach came as a vital change after years in which<br />
our national affairs were seen as an inevitable and.<br />
unresolvable struggle between interests which were by their<br />
inherent nature fundamentally opposed; and in which every<br />
issue had its: winner and its loser.<br />
This search for a national community of interest has been<br />
the constant theme of my career; it is basic to the concept<br />
and the workings of Parliamentary democracy; and it has been<br />
fundamental to the highest ideals of democratic socialism. </p>
<p>What makes the present state of world affairs so remarkable,<br />
so exciting and so challenging is the way in which we have<br />
seen, over the past few years, the emergence in the<br />
international. community of a similar sense of community of<br />
interest. For the first time in fifty years, the people of<br />
the world are more conscious of the interests they share<br />
than of the issues that divide them.<br />
The genesis of this great change has been the end of the<br />
Cold War the abatement of fifty years of relentless<br />
strategic competition between the superpowers. But by<br />
definition the end of the previous era cannot determine the<br />
shape of the new.<br />
The shape of the post-Cold War era depends on whether the<br />
confrontation of the past fifty years is to be replaced by a<br />
positive spirit of cooperation between nations a true<br />
reflection of the community of interests between nations<br />
or whether it: will instead be replaced by a negative spirit<br />
of isolationism and self-centredness.<br />
On 2 August ]. 990, Saddam Hussein challenged the world to<br />
decide which it will be. His invasion of Kuwait has forced<br />
the world to determine the nature of the world community and<br />
the way in which it will cooperate in the years ahead.<br />
In that process we have found ourselves casting back to the<br />
tantalising years of optimism following the Second World<br />
War. At that time the founders of the United Nations,<br />
learning from their vivid and bitter experience of a world<br />
sliding into chaos, drew up principles of international<br />
behaviour which would prevent it all happening again, and<br />
established machinery which would make those principles work<br />
in practice to keep the peace.<br />
The essence of the principles they established can be very<br />
easily stated: national borders must be respected, and<br />
those who violate borders by force must be resisted.<br />
The machinery they established was more complex; but it too<br />
relied in the ultimate on a simple proposition. It.., as<br />
clearly expressed by one of the key architects of t. United.<br />
Nations, Aust: ralia's Labor Foreign Minister of the day, Dr<br />
H. V. Evatt. He said that in confronting aggression, if<br />
economic or diplomatic sanctions " are deemed inappropriate<br />
or prove ineffective, the Security Council may take any<br />
military action necessary to suppress the aggressor"'.<br />
We in Australia believed from the very outset of the Gulf<br />
crisis that Saddam Hussein's aggression must be resisted,<br />
and that the United Nations offered the only effective way<br />
to achieve that. We also believed that the Gulf crisis<br />
constituted a vital test of the ability of the world<br />
community to work through the United Nations to preserve<br />
peace in the post-Cold War era. </p>
<p>So from the outset, Australia supported the United Nations<br />
as strongly as we could, first in its efforts to solve the<br />
crisis peacefully through diplomatic efforts and sanctions;<br />
and when that proved ineffective, by providing forces as<br />
requested by the Security Council in Resolution 678 for<br />
operations to expel Iraq from Kuwait.<br />
We are relieved that those military operations were so<br />
swiftly and successfully concluded. But most of all, we are<br />
pleased that the international community, acting through the<br />
United Nations, has succeeded in acting together to meet and<br />
defeat an aggressor who had not just crushed and swallowed a<br />
weaker neighbour, but had also challenged the basic<br />
principles of international order.<br />
This has been a victory for people everywhere who would live<br />
in peace. And it offers the strongest reassurance that the<br />
end of the Cold War will truly mark the start of a new era<br />
of international cooperation based on a community of<br />
interest. Because the most striking feature about the<br />
international response to the Gulf crisis was the way in<br />
which nations from every continent of the world, with every<br />
shade of opinion, recognised the interests they shared with<br />
each other in opposing and reversing Saddam Hussein's<br />
aggression. The common response of all members of the United Nations; of<br />
the members of the Security Council, and of the two<br />
superpowers, reflected their shared interests in a peaceful<br />
world order. But those shared interests reflected, in turn,<br />
certain shared values: national self-determination, national<br />
sovereignty and the rule of law over the rule of force.<br />
These are the values which the parties represented here at<br />
the Socialist International have long stood for and<br />
articulated. They are our values.<br />
My friends,<br />
I made it clear throughout the Gulf crisis that it W's<br />
Saddam Hussein's violation of those values that wasi his most'<br />
repugnant act his greatest crime.<br />
I did not say this in any pie-in-the-sky rhetorical sense,<br />
or with any desire to cloak the harsh reality of military<br />
conflict in a mantle of confected principle.<br />
I said it because I meant it in a literal way in a way<br />
that has direct and vital significance to the way that we<br />
conduct ourselves as an international community in the<br />
coming decade.<br />
The point is that those values and the overwhelming desire<br />
for freedom which lies within us all, are, increasingly,<br />
tangible realities for millions of people around the world. </p>
<p>The reforms initiated by President Gorbachev inside the<br />
Soviet Union unleashed powerful forces across Eastern<br />
Europe, toppling unrepresentative regimes through the sheer<br />
and irresistible pressure of popular demand.<br />
In eastern Germany, in Czechoslovakia, in Hungary, in<br />
Poland, in Romania and in Bulgaria the human spirit has<br />
triumphed. The human voice is being heard once more, where before was<br />
only the monolithic silence of oppression.<br />
Australians, so distant from the events, nevertheless shared<br />
the sense of euphoria as the Berlin Wall was brought down.<br />
And all this emerged within the context of a more<br />
constructive superpower relationship, in which the spectre<br />
of nuclear holocaust was replaced by the prospect of a more<br />
peaceful world.<br />
It was this dramatic and uplifting prospect that Saddam<br />
Hussein threatened to rip away from us.<br />
It was ultimately to regain that hope and to reaffirm our<br />
values that we had to fight in the Gulf.<br />
But, my friends, the members of the Socialist International<br />
are entitled to derive particular satisfaction from this<br />
victory the victory of the people over their tyrants; of<br />
expression over oppression; of sanity over irrationality.<br />
For these victories are in a profound sense our victories.<br />
One hundred years ago the founders of the Australian Labor<br />
Party made a critical, a fundamental decision.<br />
Throughout the then Australian colonies, representatives of<br />
the industrial movement recognised that their goals would be<br />
best advanced, and their members best served, through<br />
participation in the parliamentary system.<br />
Rational persuasion and legislative reform were perqeived as<br />
the best means towards improved standards of living.<br />
Whatever tensions there may have been within the Australian<br />
labour movement since then and there has been, perhaps<br />
regrettably, no significant lack of them there has never<br />
been effective questioning of the merits of that watershed<br />
decision, one hundred years ago.<br />
So when we see other nations, such as the nations of Eastern<br />
Europe, gain or regain their democratic voice when we see<br />
the collapse of so-called socialist parties and regimes that<br />
had suppressed or made a mockery of popular democracy when<br />
we hear once more the clamour of political parties engaged<br />
in democratic contest then we have every right to rejoice<br />
and every right to feel vindicated. </p>
<p>Their victory is indeed our victory.<br />
There is a further lesson.<br />
When the East Europeans overthrew their political masters<br />
they also overthrew the corrupted inefficiencies and<br />
injustices of their command economies.<br />
These economies had for decades denied their subjects<br />
adequate access to basic goods and services they had<br />
denied their industries except their armaments industries<br />
access to technological innovation they had denied their<br />
workers the best opportunities for growth they had shut<br />
the door on investment.<br />
And they did so while committing, in many cases, outrageous<br />
assaults on their natural environment.<br />
In short, they delivered low standards of living, and denied<br />
the basic aspirations of working people to economic security<br />
for themselves and their families..<br />
In the words of President Havel, who appealed to those of<br />
his fellow Czechoslovakians creating things of value for<br />
society " Once again you will be creating these things for<br />
yourselves and those close to you, not for those who rule<br />
over you or for the abstract future of a utopian ideology.<br />
I ask them not to forget that the profit they create is<br />
not an end in itself, but a means to enhance the common<br />
wealth of society, and to create conditions for a generally<br />
dignified and full human life"<br />
These sentiments point to the great contrast in the<br />
countries and the economies in which social democracy has<br />
played a dominant role, whether as the party of Government,<br />
or as the principal Opposition.<br />
The contrast between the two Germanies says it all.<br />
In hailing the failure of the central command systems, we do<br />
not, of course, by any means concede the case for<br />
untrammelled, unreformed unreconstructed capitalism<br />
The leading Australian Labor historian, Professor Bede<br />
Nairn, has written a seminal history of the Australian Labor<br />
Party, which he entitled ' Civilising Capitalism'.<br />
Parties like the Australian Labor Party have reformed the<br />
system to provide social justice, to enhance personal<br />
freedoms, to safeguard the environment, to protect the<br />
world's resources and at the same time, make the economic<br />
system better and fairer.<br />
That is the historic achievement of the parties of social<br />
democracy. </p>
<p>And that is the precise reason why, in the arrogance of<br />
their years of power, the advocates of the command system<br />
reserved their strongest anathemas for the parties of social<br />
democracy.<br />
My friends,<br />
Let there be no doubt. There is a long distance to travel<br />
before we can declare our task complete.<br />
But in the challenges and opportunities of this new<br />
international order, we can certainly see that our<br />
aspirations have come closer to fulfilment.<br />
Because if indeed we live in a world where collective security<br />
and the rule of law are more secure values and I<br />
believe we do;<br />
if indeed we live in a world where the forces devoted<br />
to the repression of the human spirit have been set<br />
back on their heels and I believe they have;<br />
if indeed we live in a world where the awesome build-up<br />
of weapons of mass nuclear destruction is less<br />
necessary and I believe it is;<br />
then we have indeed moved closer to our goals.<br />
In such a world, we may legitimately entertain the hope that<br />
the resources formerly devoted to the suppression of the<br />
human spirit may now be invested<br />
in the liberation and the enlargement of the human<br />
spirit; in feeding and sheltering and comforting those who need<br />
help; in securing firm foundations for sustainable ec pomic<br />
development; and<br />
in building security and prosperity for our children.<br />
My friends<br />
The values we share are also increasingly taking hold<br />
outside Europe. We have been heartened to see at last clear<br />
evidence of change in South Africa. Apartheid is not yet<br />
dead, but its end is near. </p>
<p>The changes -taking place in South Africa could not have been<br />
achieved without the comprehensive involvement of the<br />
international community. Australia, with its partners in<br />
the Commonwealth, led in the process of imposing practical<br />
measures to bring South Africa to its senses. The efforts<br />
my Government made have been matched by the commitment and<br />
strength of -the Australian labour movement's opposition to<br />
apartheid. : 1 pay tribute to the role of the international<br />
labour movement in its struggle against oppression in<br />
southern Africa.<br />
It is Austra. lia' s view that the point is being reached where<br />
President de Klerk's efforts deserve encouragement, as his<br />
predecessors intransigence warranted condemnation.<br />
Together with the Commonwealth, we have agreed that pressure<br />
on South Afri ca should be eased as promised reforms are<br />
implemented. We urge the South African Government to<br />
maintain the momentum of reform and to speed the process of<br />
reconciliation and dialogue with black leaders.<br />
Friends, The revolutionary transformations taking place in global<br />
economic life are nowhere more visible than here on the<br />
Pacific Rim. This region generates one-third of the world's<br />
trade and more than half its economic output. It contains<br />
the world's fastest growing economies.<br />
Our region also contains and we cannot ignore them<br />
points of tension between ethnically and culturally diverse<br />
peoples and nations; glaring disparities between wealth and<br />
poverty; and some of the world's most fragile and endangered<br />
ecologies. Many of these problems are being addressed.<br />
I am proud of Australia's efforts to promote a lasting and<br />
peaceful solution to the problems in Cambodia. Not only<br />
have many years of tragedy been visited on the Cambodian<br />
people, but -the continuation of this crisis has threatened<br />
the security and harmony of our region. Australia has taken<br />
the lead in promoting an international solution based on a<br />
direct United Nations role in Cambodia. We are committed to<br />
the long-term integration of Indo-China into the regionfor<br />
too long has it been an island of stagnation in' a sea of"<br />
dynamic growth.<br />
The logic of geography and economics directs Australia<br />
towards the dynamism and vitality of the Asian economies.<br />
As a Government, we have taken up the challenge of these<br />
tremendous opportunities and responsibilities: the<br />
opportunity to act, individuality and collectively, to build<br />
a safe and prosperous future for our region; and the<br />
responsibility to play our role in the development of a<br />
safer and fairer global environment.<br />
The process of Asia Pacific Economic Cooperation a process<br />
which I initiated in Seoul in 1989 seeks to advance the<br />
common interests of regional countries, consistent with a<br />
fundamental commitment to fair and open trade. </p>
<p>Our region can, through its own internal behaviour, help set<br />
an example in the world. If Germany and Japan were the<br />
economic miracles of the 1950s and 1960s, countries<br />
elsewhere in Asia were the economic miracles of the 1970s<br />
and 1980s. And, from the outset, one of the objectives of<br />
APEC has been the encouragement by the region of fair and<br />
open international trade as a key to global prosperity.<br />
But beyond that, our region is capable of demonstrating the<br />
capacity of countries not so long ago torn by conflict,<br />
countries with traditional rivalries, countries at different<br />
stages of development, and countries of great cultural<br />
diversity to cooperate together.<br />
We hope, through institutions like APEC, to develop in the<br />
Asia-Pacific region the sense of a community of interests,<br />
and the awareness of shared goals, which the United Nations<br />
sets out to foster at the global level.<br />
We believe that the end of the Cold War offers to our<br />
region, as it does to other parts of the world, the<br />
opportunity to build a more just and more secure<br />
international order.<br />
To play a constructive role in that great process is the<br />
dedicated commitment of the Labor Party and government I<br />
have the honor to lead, and on whose behalf I again bid you<br />
most welcome to our country. WW* W* ø o~ </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
