<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2203</transcript-id>
    <title>DR CAIRNS CALL FOR DEMONSTRATIONS - COMMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR JOHN GORTON</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/03/1970</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002203.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS P. M. No 42 / 973<br />
DR. CAIRNS' CALL FOR DEMONCSTRATIONS<br />
Comment by the Prime Minister, M. John Gorton<br />
Dr. Cairns is a leading member of the Labor Party and a<br />
member of the Executive of the Parliamentary Labor Party in Canberra.<br />
The Victorian President of that Party recently chaired a<br />
meeting which called on Australian Troops, fighting the Communists<br />
in Vietnam, to mutiny.<br />
Now Dr. Cairns, in alliance with the Communist Party, calls<br />
for the streets of Melbourne to be taken over, for all traffic to be halted<br />
and all business stopped, as a protest against Australian troops fighting<br />
Communists in Vietnam.<br />
He threatens that if the Police seek to maintain order, and to<br />
protect the rights of citizens going about their lawful occasions, he and<br />
his followers will become violent.<br />
The significance of this is not that the call for anarchy was<br />
made, for the call is likely to have negligible effect.<br />
The significance is that it comes from a man who is a Shadow<br />
Minister in Labor's Shadow Cabinet.<br />
The question to be asked is whether this policy of anarchy,<br />
of the use of force to gain ends which could not be gained through the<br />
ballot box, is the Labor Party's policy. We know it is the policy of a<br />
significant sector of the Labor Party but is it the policy of the Party<br />
as a whole? Mr. Whitlam owes it to Australians to clear this matter up.<br />
I hope that Australians will treat this excursion into storm<br />
trooper tactics with disdain and disgust.<br />
CANBERRA 26 March 1970 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
