<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9612</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP , AND THE MINISTER FOR TRANSPORT, THE HON LAURIE BRERETON MP DOORSTOP, ADELAIDE FREIGHT TERMINAL, ADELAIDE, 5 JUNE 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/06/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009612.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP, AND<br />
THE MINISTER FOR TRANSPORT, THE HON LAURIE BRERETON MP<br />
DOORSTOP, ADELAIDE FREIGHT TERMINAL, ADELAIDE, 5 JUNE 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF ONLY<br />
J: Prime Minister there is a concern locally about the future of Australian<br />
National and the fact that up to 200 jobs may go later this year. Can<br />
I get a comment on this?<br />
PM: Oh well I think the Minister for Transport could probably do more justice<br />
to it than me. But the Commonwealth commitment to AN has been,<br />
I think, pretty profound. Our commitment to railways is a key thing.<br />
Don't look at what we say, look at what we do and what we have done is<br />
to give new life back to the Australian railway system and our belief that<br />
rail is the answer for carrying these big containers across the continent,<br />
around the place, means that we are going to improve the quality and<br />
durability and longevity of the rail system. That must mean a longer run,<br />
better employment, more secure employment. I don't know whether<br />
Laurie would like to add to that.<br />
LB: I think the most profound aspect of the weekend's announcement was<br />
the decision of the Cabinet to back the development of Track Australia,<br />
which is aimed at doing one thing and that is growing rail, making it more<br />
competitive. But, in total, making it bigger and better and that means<br />
more jobs overall and that is certainly the commitment that we have<br />
given and it is certainly the plan we are going to develop and work<br />
through with the States during the remainder of this year. That is good<br />
news for AN and particularly good news for South Australia.<br />
J: Prime Minister does this mean that the Alice Springs/ Darwin rail link<br />
PM: Well that is subject to a study and that has got to stand or fall on its<br />
commerciality and the independence of that commerciality. But what we<br />
are seeing here today is the tangible step of putting a standard gauge<br />
between Adelaide and Melbourne. That means that the port of Adelaide<br />
can ship containers through to the port of Melbourne and Sydney and </p>
<p>into businesses right around the country and it also means that the<br />
heavier industries of South Australia will have better transport linkages<br />
into Victoria, New South Wales and Queensland, as well as to Perth,<br />
and this must be good for the industry of this State. The other thing<br />
which I think is good is the psychology of it. To think that<br />
South Australia is connected up now by a line which is a standard<br />
gauge, so where we can now get the efficiency of the system up, has got<br />
to be good for this State and got to bring more services to Adelaide.<br />
J: ( inaudible)<br />
PM: Well Track Australia has got to be negotiated with the other States.<br />
They have got a substantial interest with their rail systems. But, again,<br />
there has been such a decline in rail investment in the last 30 years<br />
unless we have a company its fundamental job is to run the<br />
permanent way, the track, if there is a good track we will get plenty of<br />
railway companies.<br />
J: Say in six months?<br />
PM: Oh, I don't know. I think these things take a while but I would think in<br />
that time we would make considerable progress.<br />
J: Mr Keating you have overtaken Mr Howard in the polls. Is that a case of<br />
the hard sell<br />
PM: It is not the hard sell, it is the hard do. The hard do. I mean that is the<br />
economy is growing. It wasn't five minutes of sunshine. That was just a<br />
cynical advertising line, from an ad agency, that they put in Mr Howard's<br />
mouth. We have got a sustainable growth economy, we have got<br />
630,000 jobs since the election and One Nation did get the country<br />
moving. The One Nation program did get the country back to growth<br />
and back to employment. Here, in rail, you can see it behind us with this<br />
standard gauge. You can see it now in the removal of the distinction<br />
between domestic and international carriage of air passengers. You can<br />
see it in the rebuilding of the TAFE system, of the Australian National<br />
Training Authority. These are all the quality things that are done by<br />
Governments who do things. I mean Mr Howard's problem is he did<br />
nothing as Treasurer and nothing as Opposition Leader and the problem<br />
is if you are in the do nothing category, it is hard to polish yourself up as<br />
a doer.<br />
J: So you have always believed that you would overtake Mr Howard in the<br />
polls?<br />
PM: Good policy and doers always end up with their nose in front.<br />
J: And what about interest rates then. What can we expect there? </p>
<p>PM: Well the guide to that is inflation and we had the really good news out in<br />
the National Accounts last week. The broadest measure of inflation, the<br />
non-farm product measure, was 1.9 per cent. The consumption measure<br />
was 2.2 per cent. There is your guide to how interest rates are going to<br />
be. I mean what we have done is broken the back of Australian inflation.<br />
That has been done by a Labor Government.<br />
J: Prime Minister is our move toward a Republic as on track as the railway?<br />
PM.-Well it will be very, I think, nicely on track on Wednesday night.<br />
Whether it is on standard gauge, one will have to wait and see. But<br />
I think it will be.<br />
J: And the racial vilification legislation?<br />
PM: We will be proceeding with that and it is up for Mr Howard to explain to<br />
the rest of the community why he believes that minorities don't have the<br />
right to protection.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
