<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6961</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW ON THE SUNDAY PROGRAM - 15 JUNE 1986</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/06/1986</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006961.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW ON THE SUNDAY PROGRAM 15 JUNE 1986<br />
OAKES: Prime Minister, welcome to Sunday.<br />
PM: Thank you very much indeed.<br />
OAKES: Sir, your Address to the Nation seemed to have been<br />
panned by everybody business, unions, most commentators. Was it<br />
a flop?<br />
PM: No it wasn't a flop Laurie, I am not simply saying that<br />
through pride of authorship. What I was about there was to alert<br />
the Australian people that we have to, for the time being, accept<br />
a reduction of standards. It was by definition not a Budget<br />
speech or a Premiers' Conference speech. I was indicating the<br />
hard things that had to be done. We delivered the first<br />
instalment on Friday. The other instalments will be coming.<br />
OAKES: Just putting economics aside for a moment, an issue seems<br />
to be can Bob Hawke lead?<br />
PM: The answer is obvious. He is, he can and he will.<br />
RAMSAY: Prime Minister, the perception of a lot of commentators<br />
and a lot of politicians have is that it is Paul Keating who is<br />
doing the leading and Bob Hawke is doing the following. Do you<br />
resent that sort of interpretation?<br />
PM: No, I don't any more than I resent your completely lopsided<br />
interpretation in the press today because we know that some<br />
people have a total incapacity for objectivity Alan. You learn<br />
to live with those things.<br />
OAKES: Well Prime Minister, in Peking you seemed to think there<br />
was a need to put Paul Keating in his place. Why did you do that?<br />
PM: Well, of course, that is not right. What I made clear and<br />
Paul quite clearly understands is that I thought the idea of a<br />
summit that was being built up, not by Paul and I read the<br />
transcript of the interview with him, but the concept of a summit<br />
was being built up as though at a summit some great decisions<br />
were going to be able to be taken. That had to be dissipated. I<br />
dissipated that but not Paul because I think it is quite clear, I<br />
don't think anyone that's gone through this week would have had </p>
<p>2<br />
any doubt about it, the Hawke/ Keating axis is as strong as it<br />
ever was.<br />
OAKES: But you gave that briefing in Peking that Mr Keating<br />
blamed your minders for didn't you?<br />
PM: Yes and I told Paul about that and I invited him to read the<br />
transcript. He is perfectly happy about that.<br />
OAKES: You don't think he was humiliated?<br />
PM: No, I didn't intent to and he didn't feel it.<br />
RAMSAY: You don't think you are being disloyal to your<br />
Treasurer? PM: No, I don't.<br />
RAMSAY: That is the first background briefing that you have<br />
given and in the past you have in fact refused to give background.<br />
briefings, Why, on this occasion, did you break your own rule?<br />
PM: I don't have inflexible rules. If I think something needs to<br />
be done I will do it. And I told the Treasurer what I was doing<br />
and why I was doing it and the result has made it all worthwhile.<br />
OAKES: Prime Minister, I think the question most people would<br />
want to ask you is exactly how much economic trouble are we in. A<br />
visitor from overseas reading the newspaper, listening to our<br />
politicians would almost certainly think we were on the verge of<br />
banana republicanism. Are we?<br />
PM: No, tcertainly not. But what has been happening to this<br />
country for a long time is that we have had a gradual move<br />
against us in our terms of trade. Depending on your starting<br />
point it could be said to be half a per cent or one per cent per<br />
annum. What's happened in the most recent period say since<br />
December of 1984, you have had about a 14 per cent move against<br />
us in our terms of trade. In the last nine months a nine per cent<br />
move against you in your terms of trade. Now that is very<br />
dramatic. It has meant in the last 12 months a three per cent cut<br />
in our national economic capacity. So what I am trying to alert<br />
the people of Australia to Laurie, is that we have got to adjust<br />
to that. You can't, if you have had a three per cent cut in your<br />
national capacity because of the fall in world prices, then you<br />
can't go on living at that previous standard. So that means the<br />
sorts of things I am talking about a further cut in the sort of<br />
wage expectations that there were there before, certainly the<br />
cuts in the State Governments that we have now imposed upon them.<br />
Those sorts of things have to-be -done-to make us, if you like,<br />
leaner and better equipped. Now that is the immediate sort of<br />
thing. The other part of what I was trying to say to the people<br />
in the Address was that it is also a longer term problem. We<br />
can't keep relying, in our export base, so much on agricultural<br />
products and mineral products which will always be subject to<br />
these adverse price fluctuations. We have got to have a wider<br />
manufacturing base and I was trying to tell the people of<br />
Australia we can do it. I wonder could I just briefly Laurie, </p>
<p>3<br />
read a couple of paragraphs from a letter I had here which gives<br />
an indication of the sort of thing I was trying to say. This is a<br />
letter from a company in Victoria to me on 6th June this month.<br />
It said thanks for the Government support certain incentives<br />
were given. We are now in a position to build $ 70 million<br />
pharmaceutical plant in 1986 increase in the number of jobs.<br />
They said we have created new technology which has been sold<br />
worldwide for millions of dollars and this technology is now a<br />
market leader overseas. They said we anticipate exporting a $ 100<br />
million worth of products manufactured in Australia. Now what I<br />
was trying to say is there is a small company that has done this.<br />
OAKES: Why aren't more companies doing that?<br />
PM: Well, I think there is a mixture of reasons and some of the<br />
things we can do something about. And so we have added to the<br />
incentives that this companies refers to here. We have added to<br />
those in the statement on Wednesday night. But ultimately then<br />
when Government has created the framework Laurie, it is matter of<br />
Australian businessmen, entrepreneurs realising that what this<br />
company has done, others can do. I mean you have been around the<br />
world and you get a pride I know when you see that Australians<br />
can take on the Americans, the Europeans, the Japanese in the<br />
most sophisticated areas and we can beat them. It is just a<br />
question Laurie, of people being prepared to get up and go. We<br />
will provide them with the framework, the trade union movement<br />
has got to provide the co-operation, we have got to get rid of<br />
work practices that are standing in the way of the highest levels<br />
of productivity. But Australians can do it and we have got to do<br />
it because if we just keep relying on wool, wheat, iron ore and<br />
coal and then when those prices go down that simply means that<br />
you are going to be, as a nation, reduced in standards. I mean if<br />
I could just give you an examp~ le. Just take in wheat, about three<br />
years ago if you were importing let's say a medium size car you<br />
needed to sell 33 tons of wheat. Today it is 46 tons and so on.<br />
You can just multiply it. Well you can't keep being in that<br />
position.<br />
RAMSAY: Prime Minister, one of the positive aspects of your<br />
speech Address to the Nation<br />
PM: Oh there was one.<br />
RAMSAY: Yes, I will concede this. It was your bash-at the wage<br />
and salary earners in our community, your call for further<br />
discounting of wages in the next national wage case. John MacBean<br />
and Simon Crean said that is not on. Are you prepared to risk the<br />
Accord on this matter?<br />
PM: I don't want to-see the-Accord go Alan. But I think one<br />
thing which you will appreciate Alan, if you are going to get the<br />
sort of environment within which the trade union movement can<br />
make announcements and decisions is that they are waiting on the<br />
outcome of this case. Now if the decision comes down and they get<br />
the 2.3 per cent which involves a 2 per cent discount and<br />
productivity staged in, as I would say, over a couple of years,<br />
then I think in that environment the position you have is that<br />
the Commission will say to unions if you are going to get these </p>
<p>things you have to sign on the line, give your commitment to-no<br />
further claims outside the Commission's guidelines. I think that<br />
the trade unions will accept that and that will take us through<br />
then to the next case. As I have said quite unequivocally in that<br />
case, as we read the economy now, there will need to be further<br />
discounting. So what has been done by my statement more than has<br />
ever been done before is a clear statement by government of what<br />
needs to happen in the wages area.<br />
RAMSAY: Then why is Simon Crean and John MacBean being so strong<br />
in their opposition to it now? Your confident that they are going<br />
to accept the Arbitration Commission's decisions.<br />
PM: well they have constituencies Alan, they can't just simply<br />
say yes, we accept what Mr Hawke says. I guess they have got to,<br />
as I say, they have firstly got to wait until the decision comes<br />
down so they know what sort of wages system framework they will<br />
be working within and then I think in that framework the trade<br />
union movement will see that it is not just a question of<br />
exercising restraint by men and women in employment. Those men<br />
and women in employment are parents, they have got kids and what<br />
we are about is trying to make sure that we have an economic<br />
environment in which we can retain the jobs for the people that<br />
are there and create more jobs for their kids. So they have got a<br />
responsibility not just to think immediately of themselves and<br />
saying I want to keep the standard that I had before even though<br />
national economic capacity has gone down. We have got together to<br />
make the decisions, hard decisions which are going to give their<br />
kids the greatest opportunity of getting gainful employment in<br />
the future.<br />
RAM'SAY: So you don't think that the Accord will be at risk<br />
whatever the decision will be?<br />
PM: Alan, I don't want to mislead on this. I think that we are<br />
in a difficult period with the Accord. I think it will survive.<br />
OAKES: Prime Minister, if the unions won't go along with you<br />
though, will you go it alone before the Arbitration Commission,<br />
argue for discounting even if the unions refuse?<br />
PM: Well, you know I am not great one for hypothetical questions<br />
but I think that my speech made it quite clear. You'll remember<br />
the actual wording of it Laurie. I said the Government believes<br />
now that on the current economic circumstances, our examination<br />
of it, that a further discounting will be required. I said we<br />
will, under the processes of the Accord, we will convey that<br />
position to the ACTU. The Accord makes it quite clear that the<br />
Government has the right in the light of the economic<br />
circumstances to take a position which it believes-is necessary<br />
in those economic circumstances. Let me in fairness if I may to<br />
the trade unions, I mean all that has been talked about now is<br />
the statements by some of their leaders which suggest that they<br />
mightn't be co-operative. Let's remember that under the plan that<br />
I am proposing the only national wage increase for 1986 will be<br />
2.3 per cent. And in the last year the earnings in this country<br />
only went up by six per cent which was virtually the same as the<br />
per cent of our major trading partners. There has been<br />
restraint and the restraint of the trade unions should be<br />
recognised but it is not enough for the future. There has got to<br />
be a bit more. </p>
<p>OAKES: You have said that all sections of the Australian<br />
community will have to make sacrifices and take a cut in living<br />
standards. What about Members of Parliament?<br />
PM: Latrie-il vil-e. getting a report from the<br />
Remuneration Tribunal in the relatively near future. I think you<br />
will see by the way I deal with that that I am applying the<br />
standards generally.<br />
OAKES: So there will be a cut in MPs' salaries?<br />
PM: It is not right for me to make the statement until I receive<br />
the report from the Tribunal. But let me say this that I don't<br />
think we can be asking the public generally to be exercising<br />
and then it not being exercised itself. Let me say this as far<br />
as remuneration of. Parliamentarians is concerned they have had<br />
more restraint imposed upon their salaries than workers generally<br />
over the recent period. And so at some stage in the future<br />
there will h&amp; vt~ o be an adjustment to meet that, but I don't<br />
think the time is now.<br />
RAMSAY: Would that attitude also apply to judges and senior<br />
public servants who have been lining up before the Remuneration<br />
Tribunal for rather large increases?<br />
PM: Let me get the report of the Tribunal, Alan, but I am making<br />
it quite clear that the restraint I am talking about should be<br />
exercised across the board.<br />
OAKES: I know you hate hypothetical questions<br />
PM: Have a go Laurie.<br />
OAKES: but wouldn't you expect Members of Parliament to<br />
squeal pretty loudly if you cut their recommended pay rise?<br />
PM: I don't think anyone would like, whether Members of<br />
Parliament or not, Laurie, but the Australian community has to<br />
face up to this simple fact. I can't wave the magic wand and<br />
wave away that 3 per cent cut in our national economic capacity.<br />
It has been imposed upon us from outside. And we have to live<br />
with it. If we don't live with and adjust to it, then the<br />
economy will adjust in another way. And that means by a falling<br />
exchange rate, rising interest rates, lowered activity, lowered<br />
employment levels. Now it will adjust that way, or it will<br />
adjust in the reasonable and constructive way that I am talking<br />
about. And I think everyone will come, and I think quite<br />
quickly, to the understanding that the way I am prosposing is the<br />
best way to do it.<br />
RAMSAY: Prime Minister, you can compel wage and salary earners<br />
through the Arbitration Commission, you can compel federal public<br />
servants and politicians, but you can't compel executive salaries<br />
to be restrained. </p>
<p>A-7.<br />
PH: That is right, Alan.<br />
RAMSAY: Surely -toqgoodne85" would you like some more power in7<br />
tact in that area?<br />
PM: It is no good saying would you like more power. The process<br />
of getting more power would be so long and drawn out that the<br />
immediate would be passed by the time you got there. What you<br />
have got to try and do is to use, as I say, the exhortatory<br />
processes, urge them to comply. Let me say in the first<br />
period after the. Summit, the major period after that, they did<br />
comply as the Advisory Council on Prices and Incomes indicated.<br />
it is just in the more recent period that they haven't. Now they<br />
have given me the undertaking that they will comply in the<br />
future. I am going to be asking the States to watch them, as we<br />
will. if they don't, I think the community may well then be in<br />
the frame of mind where they would say, if you won't do it<br />
voluntarily then: -there may be a case. for getting powers to<br />
government. OAKES: Prime Minister, the Opposition Leader has challenged you<br />
to a televised debate on economic policy, will you be in that?<br />
PM: Of course I won't. You know, because you are around in this<br />
Gallery, the opposition, including the Leader of the opposition,<br />
have had the chance for months to ask economic questions, to have<br />
economic debate. They have been a total abject failure which is<br />
the unanimous view of everyone of you in the Gallery. It is not<br />
just a Government view. They have been absolutely derelict in<br />
the responsibilities and their duty. And we are not going along<br />
with some gimmick along these lines of a debate. We will get on<br />
and make the decisions. They couldn't make the right decisions<br />
in government. They brought us to worst economic crisis for<br />
years. And the only thing, as I have said before, which matches<br />
their incompetence in government is their totally unprincipled<br />
irrelevance in opposition. The people don't take them seriously.<br />
More than half his own people don't take Mr Howard seriously.<br />
Don't let him expect me to take him seriously.<br />
RAMSAY: Prime Minister, you like to take your case to<br />
television. You took it outside the Parliament in making your<br />
Address to the Nation last week. why not take on John Howard on<br />
national television?<br />
PM: It is an irrelevance with an irrelevancy.<br />
RAMSAY: Why is it an irrelevant?<br />
PM: Because he has nothing-to do with the formulation of either<br />
policy nor, more importantly, has he exercised to this point, the<br />
responsibility of drawing up alternative policies. You have seen<br />
them in the government, in the Parliament. You have seen them<br />
there, not dealing with matters of principle or issues of </p>
<p>7<br />
economic policy -they have been with all the scuttlebutt<br />
irrelevancies around the place. We are not going to reduce the<br />
importance of relevant government decision making to an<br />
irrelevancy with a man who is not going to be Opposition Leader,<br />
I think, for very much longer at any rate.<br />
, OAKES: Prime minister, the situation in South Africa is<br />
deteriorating rapidly. You have said Australia will push for<br />
tougher sanctions when the Commonwealth leaders meet in August.<br />
How are you going to swing Margaret Thatcher around?<br />
PM: There are a number of factors that are relevant, Laurie. I<br />
think first of all the fact that Lord Barber, her representative<br />
on the Eminent Persons Group, signed the report, is relevant.<br />
Secondly, I know from the discussions I have had with others,<br />
including a long talk with Brian Mulroney during this week, what<br />
the view of my senior colleagues are. And thirdly, I would hope,<br />
Laurie, most importantly, this point Britain has a very<br />
considerable investment in South Africa. Now I think<br />
self-interest should start to come through in this. It is quite<br />
clear that the leadership of the front-line states, the ANC, they<br />
don't want to see the economic infrastructure of South Africa<br />
destroyed. They want a transition to a democratic multi-racial<br />
state where people have the right to vote irrespective of race or<br />
colour. They don't want to see a repetition,. Laurie, of what has<br />
happened in other African states where political freedom has<br />
become associated with economic disintegration. So what Mrs<br />
Thatcher and the British should understand is that the best<br />
chance of retaining their capacity to be involved in a developing<br />
South Africa is not to stand in the way of change but to be<br />
associated with it. Now if Mrs Thatcher can come to understand<br />
that then I think she should come to see that sanctions are going<br />
to be necessary to get the South African regime to talk. I<br />
repeat, and it was my initiative, I don't like the concept of<br />
sanctions for sanctions' sake, it is only a means to an end to<br />
get dialogue and discussion and decision.<br />
RAMSAY: Is she risking a break-up of the Commonwealth by holding<br />
out against sanctions, do you think?<br />
PM: She would be, Alan, she would be because there is no doubt<br />
that every other member of the Commonwealth believes that if we<br />
have failed in trying to get dialogue through the Eminent Persons<br />
Group process, then sanctions, unfortunately, will be necessary.<br />
So everyone else has that view. And I notice that Mrs Thatcher<br />
is reported in the papers this morning as saying well if she is<br />
right and she is the -only one out then that doesn't matter.<br />
Well, we have * all heard about everyone's out of step but my<br />
Johnny, there is no doubt what the facts are here.<br />
OAKES: The Malaysian Prime Minister, Dr Mahathir, is on his way<br />
to Australia for a private visit, but we are told that he wants<br />
to talk to you about ways to put pressure on Mrs Thatcher. Will<br />
you go along with that? </p>
<p>4. 4<br />
PM: I wouldn't discuss publicly what I would say with Dr<br />
Nahathir, but what I would hope, Laurie, it is not just a<br />
question of putting pressure. The best way of getting positive<br />
and constructive outcomes is for a person to be persuaded, if you<br />
like intellectually, of the correctness of a course of action.<br />
And that is why I go back to the question of the self-interest of<br />
the British. It would be much better if Mrs Thatcher and the<br />
British themselves could see that their own self-interests are<br />
much better served this way. If the alternative is followed, of<br />
the bloodshed and confrontation which is the only other<br />
alternative to discussion and dialogue, then there will be a<br />
destruction of the British investment and the capacity for<br />
Britain ever to be involved there. Now, that is neither in their<br />
interests nor in my belief is it in the interests of the blacks<br />
of South Africa.<br />
RAMSAY: Prime Minister, just on one point about these sanctions.<br />
Your Government still allows South African Airways to fly into<br />
this country. Why, if you are fair dinkum?<br />
PM: Alan, you do display a bit of a lack of knowledge of the<br />
processes of Nassau. We had stages of action that were agreed in<br />
Nassau. And that function that you referred to is in the second<br />
trenche. I can assure you that if we can't get the dialogue that<br />
I am talking about, that will be one of the several additional<br />
things that we will be doing.<br />
OAKES: Prime minister, we are just about out of time, but a<br />
final question. There has been a lot of speculation in the last<br />
few weeks that because the economy is going downhill you might<br />
call a early election. Are you prepared to repeat your<br />
comfitment that this Parliament will go its full 3 three years?<br />
PM: Yes, I am. And let me get the context right. The<br />
Australian economy is not going downhill. Let's get that quite<br />
straight. What has happened is that the external world is paying<br />
us much less for the things that we produce. And that has<br />
produced the loss of 3 per cent in our national economic<br />
capacity. It is quite clear that if Australians continue to<br />
work, but work even harder together than we can overcome this<br />
problem. That is the right context. And within that context, we<br />
will go our full term.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
