<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9031</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ KEATING MP, INTERVIEW WITH PAUL MURPHY, DATELINE, SBS TV 10 NOVEMBER 1993</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/11/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009031.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
ILI 2.,<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
INTERVIEW WITH PAUL MURPHY, DATELINE, 86$ TV<br />
NOVEMBER 1993<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
PM: Prime Minister, welcome to Dateline.<br />
PJK: Thank you very much, Paul. Good to be here.<br />
PM: If I can start with the Seattle Summit. You are off there Wednesday of<br />
next week for the APEC Summit, but President Clinton's having real<br />
trouble with NAFTA, getting it through the Congress, if he fails to do<br />
that what's the effeict on APEC?<br />
PJK-I think the effect would be, perhaps an indirect effect, and that would<br />
be that the flag of free trade or freer trade would be lowered in the<br />
event that NAFTA didn't succeed in passing the Congress. It wouldn't<br />
in any way diminish the United States capacity to trade into APEC, or<br />
Canada's independent capacity or Mexico's independence to trade into<br />
APEC, it is just that they wouldn't be an entity trading into APEC. But it<br />
won't affect APEC it only basically effects the North American trade<br />
arrangements.<br />
PM: What do you expect out of the APEC Summit? Is it just a meeting, an<br />
informal sort of meeting amongst leaders, or do you expect some real<br />
progress? Because some people are saying to you, don't press too<br />
hard, don't expect too much.<br />
PJK: Well we have got an eminent persons group who have outlined steps<br />
for the directions that APEC will take. We are trying to take APEC<br />
from, basically, a mini OECD, an information policy secretariat, to an<br />
executive body that will actually improve trade facilitation and lift the<br />
velocity of trade and investment in the Pacific area. That can't happen<br />
without the authority of the governments. So, we need the leaders of<br />
the governments together, to pull it together, if we are to talk of it being<br />
a community. </p>
<p>2<br />
PM: Yes. Would you accept Russell Fynmore ( of BHIP) advice that you<br />
may be going too fast and to put the brakes on?<br />
PJK: No, I don't think so, no. Australia hasn't got a second to lose. We<br />
have all ready lost a century or so of getting ourselves accommodated<br />
in this part of the world, and to get a structure in the Asia-Pacific. The<br />
great thing about APEC is that, all at the one time, it gives us a chance<br />
to multilateralise the interests of the United States, Japan and China,<br />
as well as the countries of South East Asia. Now, large countries like<br />
the United States always reserve the rights to do things by themselves.<br />
They don't like signing up to a set of rules. But I think this is the great<br />
opportunity of APEC and why it should be taken.<br />
PM: But, Prime Minister, what about Asian countries who do have high tariff<br />
wails, will they feel threatened at all?<br />
PJI( I don't think so, because you can see there is Indonesia now starting to<br />
announce a week or so ago a reform agenda to get industrial<br />
protection down. You can see that China will do the same. But we are<br />
talking about two things here, facilitating trade, trade facilitation, and<br />
protection. Such things as harmnonised company rules, harmonised<br />
investment standards, harmonised foreign investment, propert law<br />
all these things will make investment better.<br />
PM: Prime Minister, on to your Mabo legislation, which I think we will be<br />
seeing pretty soon, can yobu sketch out the principles with the<br />
accompanying social justice package? What are you doing there for<br />
Aboriginal and Islander people?<br />
PJK: The big problem for those who can't avail themselves of some of the<br />
benefits under the Mabo decision or the body of law we will establish<br />
are those who are formally alienated from the land, dispossessed of<br />
the land, the so-called social justice package largely will be a land<br />
acquisition fund, a large revolving fund.<br />
PM: How big will it be?<br />
PJK Well that is yet to be decided, but it will be substantial. I hope that the<br />
earnings from the fund itself will be enough to be able to continue an<br />
acquisition program every year. In other words it won't be the<br />
spending of just a fund, but the earnings of a fund, will continue to go<br />
on.<br />
PMV: Hundreds of millions, or billions?<br />
PJK: Well, hundreds of millions, at least.<br />
PM: At least. </p>
<p>Z 9UU4<br />
3<br />
PJK At least.<br />
PM: Now Richard Court is going it alone, he is extinguishing Native Titde,<br />
but he i-s allowing traditional use of the land. Why can't you do that as<br />
well as doing what you are doing in your legislation?<br />
PJI( Well, what he is doing is basically taking away the proprietary title, that<br />
comes under our legislation, it comes from Mabo. He is saying<br />
Aboriginal people can have the maintenance of so-called Native rights<br />
undefined, but no proprietary title, certainly nothing running as far as<br />
sole occupancy, or anything like running as far as freehold. In other<br />
words what he is saying is you can have a set of rights but not title,<br />
and we can take those rights away whenever it suits the Government.<br />
PM: But you will ride roughshod over him, won't you, when you bring down<br />
your legislation?<br />
PJK Well, we are hoping that he will sign up to the principals we have there'<br />
when he sees the legislation. Because we made it very clear here,<br />
Paul, that the economic imperatives, as well as the social imperatives,<br />
have got to be met here. And so we have left all the development area<br />
with the States, and for them not to accept that, same States like<br />
Western Australia not to accept that, is to wilfully take an ideological<br />
view that in the end Aboriginal people should not have title to land.<br />
PM: But he is unlikely to sign up, isn't he?<br />
PJF( Well if he doesn't the Commonwealth tribunals would operate in<br />
Western Australia.<br />
PM:-Right. Could I move on now to one of your biggest and most<br />
intractable problems, unemployment? Now, you are saying that the<br />
economy is really recovering now, but how can you really say that<br />
when we have still got unemployment over 10 per cent?<br />
PJK: Well, I am not saying that unemployment has recovered much Paul,<br />
because it hasn't. This has been a product ivity-l aden recovery that<br />
is, we are getting more output from fewer people. We are starting to<br />
see the job vacancies and some employmrent come through now. You<br />
notice the ANZ job series this week was up<br />
PM: Yes, 7.7.<br />
F'JK: Yes, 27 per cent over the year and up substantially in the month. But<br />
what we have to do is not just get aggregate employment going, but<br />
also deal with the long-term unemployed who have slipped to the<br />
bottom of the queue. </p>
<p>15I193 15: U0 2 lud 273 2923 PM PRESS OFFICE 400O5<br />
4<br />
PMV: Indeed, on a personal note, in your own electorate in Canterbury-<br />
Bankstown anyhow 20,000 people out of work, that is 14.4. What<br />
can you do about that, because you have been back in power now for<br />
eight months?<br />
PJK That is why we have this major study going on now that is, to see<br />
whether we can do something in Australia which is novel and new in<br />
world terms, as well as dealing with the long-term unemployed through<br />
the labour market programs which we are now spending over<br />
billion on. That will get people at least bark into work experience<br />
those who have not had any work experience in the recent years.<br />
PM: OK you have got the White and the Green Paper, but when is the<br />
earliest we can see some decisions on that, like things such as the<br />
jobs guarantee level whether you are going to do that?<br />
PJK: Ail those questions will be resolved in the Budget round of 1994.<br />
PM: Right. What about Mr Dawkins' suggestion for low award payments in<br />
the private sector?<br />
PJK: We are waiting to what the Committee recommends. It is the most farreaching<br />
review into the labour market, and trends in the labour market<br />
and unemployment, that we have had since the war. So, it is a very<br />
large piece of work and the Government will take it seriously and we<br />
will then look at the policy responses coming up to the Budget next<br />
year.<br />
PM: OK, just to clarify that, the new Budget round you say. Is that Budget<br />
round being brought forward, say February/ March for say an<br />
AprillJune Budget?<br />
PJK: The Government is considering bringing it forward on the proviso that<br />
we can get the Budget through by 30 June. That is, we actually do<br />
genuinely change the cycles and not that we have some spill over that<br />
runs into July and August because were we to do that there is no point<br />
to it.<br />
PM: Right.<br />
PJK So the Treasurer is now exploring those matters and will be with the<br />
minor parties in the Senate in the next week or two.<br />
PM: So, can you promise Australians that there will be some really concrete<br />
action on unemployment say February/ March/ April?<br />
PJK I can certainly promise them this Paul there will be very concrete<br />
action on this report by the Government to deal with unemployment in </p>
<p>UU 0<br />
the next Budget. Now, if it is an early Budget, it will be earlier, if it is a<br />
later Budget, it will be a bit later.<br />
PM: OK just on levies. What about raising the Medicare levy for those who<br />
can afford it, who earn over $ 50,000 a year?<br />
PJK That is another thing that Cabinet has got to consider what we do<br />
about health and there is no doubt that a lot of the healthier people are<br />
dropping out of private insurance. But, Medicare is a generalised levy:<br />
I pay 1.4 per cent on $ 160,000 a year, someone on average weekly<br />
earnings pays 1.4 per cent $ 32,000 a year.<br />
PMV: Should you pay 1.9 per cent?<br />
PJK Well, I'm paying now much more say, than someone on a low income<br />
and that has been the principle of Medicare universality and a single<br />
rate. I think, the Government would need a lot of convincing to shift<br />
away from that.<br />
PMV: Graham Richardson of course, says that he is summoning up the<br />
courage to suggest to you that you and your family should go into<br />
private health insurance.<br />
PJK He is going to need a lot of it.<br />
PM: A lot of courage?<br />
PJK: Absolutely.<br />
PM: You are not contemplating going into private health insurance?<br />
PJK No, I'm not and why should I? Because the fact is we have got a levy<br />
which is universal. It is a bit like the argument saying you can't put<br />
your kid into a public school if you have got an income over $ 60,000.<br />
PMV: But, you have often listened to Graham Richardson, so in this case<br />
you are not going to take his advice?<br />
PJK: No, well, Graham is going to bring a package of things to the Cabinet<br />
and this was only one of a great number of measures, and he has<br />
always made it clear to me not any one of them is vital to the package<br />
he has in mind.<br />
PM* A final question on multiculturali-sm. You have always tried can you<br />
give a commitment that your Government will continue to fund a lot of<br />
the programs that entails, because you have out English tuition to adult<br />
migrants by 30 per cent? </p>
<p>15/ 11 ' 93 15: 04 % T06 273 2923 PM PRESS OFFICE -007<br />
4 6<br />
PJK But, our support generally for the mulficultural programs of the country<br />
has been growing right through the ' 8Os and in the ' 90s and also may I<br />
say, SBS is a model of that. In fact, the very expression of that.<br />
PM: A very final brief question do you think you will be facing a new<br />
Leader of the Opposition Christmas or New Year?<br />
PJK I think Dr Hewson signed off on 13 March as an effective Leader of the<br />
Liberal Party. He got the job back because they didn't know what to do<br />
at the time. Now, they have had some change to ruminate about it and<br />
think about it I think they will come to the conclusion there is no more<br />
life left in him and whoever it may be, we will deal with them as they<br />
arive.<br />
PM: Prime Minister, thank you very much indeed for coming onto Dateline.<br />
PJK: Thank you, Paul.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
