<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>749</transcript-id>
    <title>PUBLIC MEETING, WHYALIA. SOUTH AUSTRALIA 24TH MAY 1963 SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE RT HON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/05/1963</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000749_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PJBLIC MEETING, t1HYALLA, SOUTH AUSTRALIA<br />
24TH MAY3 1963<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister, the Rt_ Hon_ Si. r Robert Menzies<br />
Mr. Chairman Senator Laught, prospective Member for Grey,<br />
Mr. President and Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
I must say that that speech you just heard from<br />
the candidate discloses him to me, and I hope to you, as one<br />
of the best candidates I have supported on a platform. ( Applause)<br />
Itve never heard a clearer statement of his beliefs, of his<br />
point of view, of the qualifications that he has by experience<br />
and residence. I had the great pleasure of speaking wita him<br />
at Port Pirie at the opening of his campaign and I thought he<br />
was good. Tonight I think he is very, very, very good, It goes<br />
to show how a man trains on. In fact, by the time he has been<br />
Member for Grey for three yJars for six years they'll be<br />
talking about him as, you know, one of the coming men. He is<br />
in the same position now as I was when I first went into<br />
Parliament when, believe it or not, I used to be referred to as<br />
a " very promising young man". ( Laughter) ( Interjector " What<br />
about when you abdicated?") Thank you so much. I was so<br />
disappointed, I've been waiting for somebody to have a go at<br />
me because I was prepared to point the moral of it, that they<br />
didn't have a go at him, and if you approve of him, I can put<br />
up with a little bit of disapproval of myself. ( Laughter)<br />
( Applause) In fact, if you don't mind, ladies and gent.-emen,<br />
that reminds me of a little event that happened some years ago.<br />
Every time there is an election, I go down to speak<br />
for my friend and colleague, Hubert Opperman, in Geelong,<br />
( Interjector " On a bike?") ( Laughter) Oh, no. I am asbhmed<br />
to say I was in a car, but he meets me on a bike. ( Laugh-cer)<br />
I will refrain from saying the make of it because you kno%;, of<br />
course. But " Oppy" always arranges that I shall have a ieoting<br />
at the Ford works and at the luncheon break I have two meetings,<br />
because the shifts vary, and I stand on the tail end of a lorry<br />
and, you know, give tongue and the boys look at me with a<br />
sceptical eye and eat their lunch, occasionally making a<br />
courteous remark ( Lauglhter). One day I had finished this<br />
exercise of mine and got down off the lorry and a big chap<br />
cane across and dug me in the ribs and said, " I hate the sight<br />
of you you so-and-so,. o." I leave it to the Whyalla citizens<br />
to fill in the gap....( Laughter) " I hate the sight of you., you<br />
so-and-so but I'll vote for ' Oppy' any tick of the clock,"<br />
( Laughter3 Now here it is. The perfect analogy. Do what you<br />
care about me, Lut send Vern Dyason to the Federal Parliament<br />
which, I assure you, will be improved and added to by his<br />
presence. ( Interjector " He probably hasn't had his sins<br />
on your head yet") ( Laughter) What do you think will happen<br />
in this election, brother? Do you think he won't win? Well,<br />
in the words of a famous statesman you wait and see. You wait<br />
and see. If he is elected, the citizens of Grey will have good<br />
reason to be thankful for it in the years to come.<br />
Now, Sir, when I helped to open this campaign in<br />
Port Pirie, I gathered there were one or two people who thought<br />
I had made a speech to the nation and not to the electors of<br />
Grey and that really I should have got down to other local<br />
issues. Well, I don't mind tolling you that when I addreosed<br />
the electors of Grey I regarded myself as addressing the<br />
nation. I feel no obligation to treat Grey as something o </p>
<p>-2-<br />
inferior to the run of the nation because it isntt. The fact is<br />
that in this electorate you have the most tremendous variety of<br />
occupations and interests, from remote rural properties from<br />
primary production of one kind or another to great smelter, at<br />
Port Pirie to a railways junction town in Port Augusta, to the<br />
industries in Whyalla about which I will have a word in a<br />
noment down to the fisheries and all the intervening industries<br />
at Port Lincoln. This electorate is, in fact, a superb example of an<br />
electorate in which primary industries and secondary industries<br />
live together and depend upon each other and therefore, this is<br />
a good electorate in which to address the nation. Anyhow, being<br />
Prime Minister, I have a duty to address the nation,<br />
Now, Sir, I will just say something about Whyallao<br />
This place has grown, of courseenormously, and it will continue<br />
to grow. I think that it was when I am sure it was I was<br />
Prime Minister for the first time, many years ago, in 1939, that<br />
the. Premier of South Australia who, I dontt need to say was<br />
then and is now and forever will be ( Laughter) Tom Playfo-d,<br />
discussed with me this great proposition about the pipeline,<br />
without which Whyalla couldnft exist. It was my privilege at<br />
that time to do what he asked me to do and the Commonwealth to<br />
do, in order to assist that project. In 1940 I was stil. Prime<br />
Minister and had established the Department of Munitions and<br />
had appointed to be its presiding man, Essington Lewis, one of<br />
the great industrialists in the history of this country0 . It<br />
was in that very year that the first orders were given some<br />
craft to be built at Whyalla, so I can claim to have some<br />
foundational interest in the water supply of this city and in<br />
shipbuilding in this city. ( Interjection inaudible) Now, if<br />
you don't mind would you just listen to this. You would. I am<br />
sure, learn a lot, I am anxious, of course, that you shoui. dn't<br />
prevent your friends from learning a lot on this matter ( Laughter)<br />
because there is a lot to be learned.<br />
Now, Sir, what is the position today. In ship-building,<br />
many, many ships have been built here. This has become the<br />
most effective and efficient shipbuilding centre in Australia,<br />
and with wisdom and good sense, it will increasingly be a shipbuilding<br />
centre but that will require good sense on the part of<br />
a few people and I will refer to the arguments a little later on,<br />
This afternoon, I went out to have a look at the development of<br />
the steelworks. I had been there before, but today I was<br />
astonished at the tremendous extent and quality of the work that<br />
is being done there0 And this is the important thing from the<br />
point of view of this town of Whyalla and of this electorate<br />
in Australia. Here we have already established a blast furnace. We<br />
have all the work going on and going on fast for the establishment<br />
of a complete steel activity. In its first stages I gathered,<br />
it will be geared to produce half a million tons ol steel and<br />
then in due course with another blast furnace, another million<br />
tons of steel and so on until it is a million and a half tons<br />
of steel. Ladies and gentlemen, I seem to remember that hen<br />
I was first interested in these matters and concerned abo,. t them<br />
in government, that total production of steel in Australio wasnft<br />
much more than a million and a quarter tons and you are going to<br />
have that in this place alone.<br />
This place, Whyalla is going to be a place rivalling<br />
in its extent and its life and its expansion Port Kembla and<br />
C oo/ 3 </p>
<p>3-<br />
Wollongong. This is a most exciting place from the point of<br />
view of Australian development and, really, whatever party<br />
I might belong to I would take immense pride in that fact<br />
and feel some of the excitement and feel how good it was to be<br />
living in a place whose future was so full of immense possibilities.<br />
But, Sir, there are some people who are llknoc'Iiersll.<br />
I suppose that if you elect the Labour candidate, whoever he<br />
may be there seems to be a mixture of...,( Applause) I suppose<br />
that il~ you elect him, he may turn out to be He will have<br />
to go to Canberra and join in the anti-BH. P. chorus and learn<br />
to denounce the Broken Hill Proprietary Company as if it were<br />
the enemy of mankind and then come back to Whyalla and say to<br />
the hundreds and hundreds of people and families engaged by<br />
th'i. e Broken Hill Proprietary, " Well, don't misunderstand me of<br />
course, I did that because it was the party line. I don't<br />
mean it. I did it because the 36 chaps outside told me to do<br />
it. Not because I befleve it." Well, this sounds funny and<br />
it is funny but it is true. Is that what you are going to<br />
do on June 1st?<br />
Now, Sir, having said that, I repeat: This place<br />
has the most exciting prospects of future development of any<br />
place in Australia. It is bound to become, very rapidly, more<br />
and more rapidly, the place of immense importance in the State<br />
of South Australia, and as what it is doing is of immense<br />
national importance to Australia itwill become one of the<br />
great significant things in the life of the nation. Now<br />
Sir, I say that to you because I believe that's true and<br />
believe that everybody in Whyalla ought to recognise it and<br />
be proud of it and be excited about it. But, of course, the<br />
more it succeeds, the more it grows, the more steel that is<br />
produced, the more peoplo who are employed in producing, the<br />
more shipbuilding goes on Itll come back to that in a<br />
minute,...( Interjector " Tell us why you bought those ships)<br />
My dear boy, there is nothing hidden that shall not be ma~ de<br />
known, You content yourself, ( Interjector " We couldi have<br />
built them here") Well, are you one of the fellows who<br />
doesn't want to have another tanker built here? Are you one<br />
of those? ( Laughter) ( Applause) I'll come to that. I'm going<br />
to tell a Whyalla audience the story of the P. J. Adams tanker<br />
because it is high time that people realised a great matter<br />
of political difference in this country. But I'll come t'Vo that<br />
in a moment. I was at the moment addressing myself to the development<br />
of Whyalla and to what is involved in it and, quite clearly,<br />
this place can't develop whatever the position may be on steel<br />
or shipbuilding, unless it has an assured water supply. And<br />
it is therefore proper to point out to you that long before the<br />
Grey by-election, I had convened a meeting with Sir Thomas<br />
Playford and the Premier of Victoria and the Premier of New<br />
South Wales, as a result of which, the Chowilla Dam is to be<br />
built on the lower Murray which will added to the existing<br />
facilities, absolutely ensure the water supply of South<br />
Australia in general and of Whyalla in particular. ( Applause)<br />
Now, Sirs there is an eager shipbuilder over there<br />
who wants to know about it ( Laughter) and so I would like to<br />
tell him. The " 1P. 5. Adams" the biggest tanker ever built in<br />
Australia and I hope not the last the " 1P. J. Adams" was<br />
built by the Broken Hill Proprietary Company at these yOards.<br />
It meant an enormous development in the yards, it meant enormous<br />
ezJ. bymentt and it was built when the Company said, " Well, 0 0 a 0 </p>
<p>we would like to have it built in Australia, We would like<br />
a Commonwealth subsidy." My Government has been subsidising<br />
ship-building for coastal business at the rate of 33 per cent.<br />
for the last seven years. Before that, it was 25 per cent.<br />
They said: " We would like a subsidy. We know that you dont<br />
subsidise the building of a ship except for the Australian<br />
coastal service. Are you prepared to subsidise the building<br />
of a ship for international trade, which will trade from<br />
Australia to a place outside and back," 1 and so on. An0 we<br />
said, " Well, whatts the proposition? This is terribly<br />
important, It is tremendously important for ship-building<br />
in Whyalla. It is tremendously important for ship-building in<br />
Australia. We are prepared to have a look at it. On what<br />
terms will you do this?" And they stipulated, and I quote<br />
their precise words: that they would be prepared to have the<br />
ship built here provided the Commonwealth Government agreed<br />
that they could register tine ship as a British ship at the<br />
Port of London. No. r that was their condition.<br />
Now, to add to this we having said, " Yes, we will<br />
accept this proposition" we Aidn't do this in a hurry<br />
we had to balance the impact it might have on the employment<br />
of seamen in Australia against the impact it would have on<br />
the employment of hundreds and therefore the livelihood of<br />
thousands of people in Whyalla. And therefore Sir, we<br />
decided that we would play on these Lerms, ( Interjector<br />
Z4+ million) Don't bemuse yourself with millions, You are<br />
only imagining them. ( Laughter)<br />
Now ladies and gentlemen, the company then<br />
proceeded to find out at which price it could get this tanker<br />
built overseas, It had quotations from Japan for a 1l,. wer<br />
figure than the loca'l price minus our subsidy. In other<br />
words, it would at that stage have paid them hundreds of<br />
thousands of pounds to get it built outside Australia but<br />
they said, " No we want to have it built in Australia?. it<br />
was an Australian Company " we want to have it built 1ñ ere. ll<br />
The price was a little over œ C4 million; we<br />
subsidised to the extent of œ C1 million. The ship was launched-<br />
I was here for the launching. It is the greatest sing'le<br />
ship-building achievement in the history of Australia and<br />
when it was launched all this had been known for years an<br />
agitation began among the seamen, among the more intransigent<br />
of the relevant union and they came to me at Canberra and<br />
they said, " Look, won? t the Commonwealth compel the Company<br />
to register in Australia?" Now, you know, I don't care for<br />
this kind of thing. The Government had undertaken with the<br />
Company that if the Company would build the ship here even<br />
losing something on it, and we subsidised it, we woula agree<br />
the company registering it in London because this was the<br />
condition on which this job would be done here and I am not in<br />
the habit of entering into obligations of that kind and then<br />
tearing them up because somebody threatens to call a strike,<br />
Really, what all the people here engaged in shipbuilding<br />
have to consider is what side they are on in this<br />
matter, what would they have liked us to do. I put this to<br />
every man engaged in the ship-building business here, In our<br />
Place, how would you have answered that question7 Would you<br />
have said, " No, insist on the ship being registered in Australia<br />
although you know that if you do so insist the ship won't be<br />
built in Australia." Is that how you would have decided it?<br />
Now, ladies and gentlemen, think about it. These are facts a 7*/ </p>
<p>beyond the slightest chance of contradiction. These are wellknowm<br />
facts. These have been discussed with the trade unions and<br />
with the company, and the fact is that the question to be determined<br />
was: Should the ship be built here at all or should it<br />
have been built on terms that it should be registered in London?<br />
Now, I just say this, I repeat this to any of you gentlemen here<br />
tonight who are engaged in this activity. How would you have<br />
decided that matter? We decided in your favour. Would you have<br />
decided against yourselves, that the ship was not to be built<br />
here on those terms? ( Interjector " No, Now, don't<br />
say, " 1No, The only thing that interests me is that<br />
you do say you can save all the " buts" ( Applause)<br />
Now, the last thing I want to say about this matter,<br />
ladies and gentlemen is this because I am told that the Labour<br />
candidate or candidazes were actively concerned in challenging<br />
this decision, It Is worth remembering. I wonder what tho<br />
A. L. P. or what remains of it here I wonder what it re:.-lly<br />
wants done about shipbuilding at Whyalla or, for that mattcr, in<br />
Brisbane, or for that matter, in Newcastle, or wherever it may be<br />
in Australia. Do they want to say to the world " Look, we are<br />
not going to build a ship in an Australian shipyard for a foreign<br />
owner who wants to get one built or for an owner who wants to<br />
register his ship, being a foreign owner in a foreign port"<br />
is that what we are to say? Is your ambition for this prospectively<br />
marvellous place so small that you want to give notice that you<br />
are only interested in building for the local coastal irade and<br />
that you have no ambition to build large vessels for people who<br />
are outside Australia? That's the question that has to be<br />
answered and really it is not to be answered by getting excited<br />
about it, It is to be answered in a cold, clear, rational fashion<br />
by those who are engaged in this business, who depend on it and<br />
who want it to expand. ( Interjector " 114hy didn't you think of<br />
that before you bought these three new ships?) ( Laughter) My dear<br />
air,, thatts a very happy excuse for you. I don't think you know<br />
any ing about these three guided-missile destroyers that we are<br />
building. There is only one place in the world that is producing<br />
them and they are very little the most tiny fraction of them<br />
is the hull. It is what goes into these ships, many mill11ions of<br />
pounds worth of it not made here that's the thing that makes the<br />
difference, A man who says that we could have produced one of<br />
these guided missile destroyers in Australia in our present state<br />
of engineering capacity knows nothing about it. That's all,<br />
( Interjector " The other night you said you Lad<br />
many shares in this company. It doesn't sound as if you've got<br />
many shares in it now.") 5 ( Laughter) I said I had a lot of shares<br />
in Australia Unlimited. That's right. Well I am glad to<br />
acknowledge it, sir, and I hope you have because the more you<br />
have by way of shares in Australia Unlimited the more likely<br />
you are to become a warm-hearted supporter of mine in politics.<br />
( Applause) Now, 7 Sir I don't w-nt to say any more about that<br />
particular matter. All I say by ~ way of summary is that in this<br />
very electorate of Grey, you have this tremendous conjunction<br />
of the planets. You have this wonderful development proceeding<br />
so rapidly in steel and in ship-building in Whyalla and you have<br />
Port Pinie and Augusta no longer at the tail-end of a transcontinental<br />
line now being worked on the West Australian section but on<br />
a line that will go clear across the Continent from Perth to<br />
Sydney to Brisbane and so on. Sir I think myself that this is<br />
an exciting matter. I have no doult whatever that the improvement<br />
by standardization and re-grading of the Port Pinie/ Broken Hill<br />
line will serve to reduce the costs of transportation to the </p>
<p>6-<br />
smelters and to the rest of the world and in these days we in<br />
Aucztralia must preserve our export capacity and we must do it<br />
by keeping our costs at a competitive level. Now, I am not<br />
one of' these who says that we've got to keep costs down, that<br />
you ought to slash wages. I am one of' those who have said,<br />
and said rep eatedly, that in order to keep costs down, we must<br />
increase our efficiency by every possible means and improving<br />
the efficiency of' transport is one of' the ways of' doing that.<br />
My colleague, the Minister for Trade, is overseas,<br />
He's been working hard tremendously hard as he always (. oes<br />
on these trade negotiahions. They are all intensely difficult.<br />
We went through the whole argument last year about the<br />
European Common Market there's been a hitch there and now<br />
he's been over discussing the problems that followed on that<br />
matter. He's discussing the initiative taken by the Pre'.) ident<br />
of the United States of America and in all of these thirv~ s, I<br />
undertake to say that he has been constantly keeping ina mind<br />
how do we maintain a fair price for the things that we sell to<br />
the rest of the world, and how do we maintain a fair costi of<br />
production for that commodity in our country. This concerns<br />
everybody engaged in the mining or metal industries; it concerns<br />
everybody on the land and because it concerns them, it concerns<br />
US* It concerns the solvency of' Australia in international trade<br />
and without that solvency, we won't have much heal. th in our<br />
economy at home. Therefore tte are great matters and<br />
thnerefore a further step in the rendering more efficient of<br />
our transportation system is not to be regarded just as some<br />
election bid; it is to be regarded as a first-class step<br />
for-ward in containing the cost of production in our own country.<br />
Sir, we have spoken.... I have tonight and my friend<br />
has about these four main centres, all of them tremendously<br />
important, all of them very much in our minds, but we must<br />
never forget, and he certainly doesn'tt that outside all these<br />
places there are thousands of people in the electorate of Grey<br />
who are living and working on the land in various forms of<br />
primary industry. We must think about them. Some people never'<br />
think about them at all, I find it part of my duty to *; hink'<br />
about them constantly and for this reason we have going on in<br />
Australia the most tremendous works of development.<br />
I've been mentioning some tonight, but must also think<br />
about what goes on in minerals in the north of Queenslar-12 in<br />
the Northern Territory and in Western Australia, what goos on<br />
in the export of coal from Australia what goes on at th e Snowy,<br />
what goes on in water supply and reticulation all these are<br />
tremendous things, tremendous works of development, and we need<br />
them in Australia and we need them as fast as we can get them.<br />
But they all put enormous pressures on our resources,<br />
Tremendous pressures.<br />
Immigration which we need so badly, and which goes<br />
along so well, puts an enormous pressure on our resources in<br />
tVie first place. In the long run it contributes immense power<br />
to the country, but in the short run all these things mean that<br />
there is a pressure on our resources of money, a pressure on our<br />
resources of materials and manpower. Anybody who? like myself,<br />
has been sitting in the middle of government for so long knows<br />
these things well, You must watch them all the timze and unless<br />
you watch them, those pressures can produce an inflationary<br />
effect in Australia which will begin quite quickly to destroy<br />
the value of whatever you are paid by way of income salary,<br />
wages or whatever they may be. And if that happens what<br />
happens to the man on the land? His costs of production go up.<br />
eoe. e e9/ </p>
<p>7-<br />
He cantt pass them on to a customer. The wheatgrower can't<br />
pass on an increased cost of production to the customer because<br />
apart from the home consumption price, he sells in the world's<br />
markets, The woolgrower sells in the world's markets. His<br />
wool goes to auction and it is what the world will pay for it<br />
that he will get. herefore all increases in his costs by<br />
inflation in Australia are a net loss to him.<br />
This goes for all the major primary production<br />
activities of Australia and therefore the enormously complex<br />
business of government, which I am afraid some people dontt<br />
begin to understand, is to try to keep a balance between pushing<br />
on with development, getting that new job done, getting it<br />
forward getting more people into the country, and at the same<br />
time not striking a blow at the primary producer of Austr-alia<br />
who is still responsible for over 85 per cent. of our export<br />
income and is therefore primarily reponsible ( Interjector<br />
" Did you realise that Yes, and I am happy to tell<br />
you, my dear sir, obviously a thinker about these matters<br />
( Laughter) I am happy to tell you that every deputation I<br />
had from people representingbTrming interests in Australia<br />
warmly approved of what we had done. Warmly approved of it<br />
because they said, " Well, your Government at any rate has been<br />
concerned about our costs of production," and we were and we are<br />
and we will continue to be. Now this is a serious matter and<br />
I address myself to it quite seriously. ( Interjector " You<br />
weren't a cocky Bob") Sir, I was born in the " cocky country"<br />
if you care to describe it as such and I' 11 undertake to say<br />
at a quick guess I've done three times as much work in my life<br />
as you will ever do. ( Applause)<br />
Now, ladies and gentlemen, this is the great problem<br />
of statesmanship on the economic front and it must be borne in<br />
raind, and you must be represented in Parliament by soraeb~ dy who<br />
understands that that is the problem and is prepared to address<br />
himself seriously to it,<br />
Now, Sir, I will just turn away from that because I<br />
have been speaking for some time to say something about another<br />
problem which concerns our external relations with other<br />
countries. It has had a good deal of discussion of It<br />
was my Government, if you will forgive me for reminding you,<br />
which brought about the ANZTJS Treaty with the United States<br />
and New Zealand. It was received in stony silence by the<br />
Labour Party but we got it and it was written and it was<br />
passed and it is today just about the sheet anchor of Australian<br />
security the United States, Australia, New Zealand entering<br />
into a mutual treaty to resist aggression against their<br />
countries from outside. This was one of the great events in<br />
Australian foreign policy history. We are also among the<br />
promoters of the South East Asian Treaty which involves some<br />
of the Asian countries as well as our own.<br />
Now, Sir, that means that the United States is our<br />
ally. We have, in the South East Asian Treaty an alliance<br />
with the United Kingdom. I am happy to say we dontt need<br />
formal treaties with the United Kingdom. When the day comes<br />
that we are not an ally of the United Kingdom, I shall have<br />
to resign in shame. I just take it for granted that we are<br />
allies of the United Kingdom and I hope that nobody in this<br />
hall will disagree with it but we have and this is quite<br />
remarkable, this formal alliance with Ifhe United States which<br />
before the war, was not willing to enter into alliances at all.<br />
These were regarded as something against the tradition of the<br />
United States and, therefore, Sir, the position is that we<br />
00694CO00/ 8 </p>
<p>q8<br />
have our ally in America, That country is the greatest nuclear<br />
power in the world thank heaven the greatest nuclear power<br />
in the world, because if it were not, we might not be here<br />
tonight. Say what you like about it, the one thing that has<br />
kept the peace of the world, in spite of the most blatant<br />
Communist aggression around the world ( Interjector " What<br />
about Cuba?") Yes, that was a superb example of what American<br />
strength can mean for us.<br />
Now, Sir, does anybody here doubt that but for the<br />
possession of the nuclear deterrent primarily by the United<br />
States and7 to a smaller extent by 6reat Britain which hasn't<br />
so much of it but for that, we would have been overrun by<br />
aggressive Communism. Of course we would have. People say,<br />
" lLook, wouldn't it be a wonderful thing if there were no nuclear<br />
weapons." We all understand that. Nobody wants to see these<br />
wretched things employed. We all have our own hopes and family<br />
hopes for the future in our own country, but Mr. Chairman, if<br />
there were no nuclear weapons today, the Soviet Union would<br />
have more ordinary military strength than perhaps all the others<br />
put together. If there were no nuclear deterrent in the hands<br />
of our friends, there would be nothing to prevent the Soviet<br />
Union from marching clear across Europe in a few weeks because<br />
the strength of her conventional armaments is enormous.<br />
Therefore the existence of this terrible weapon of reprisal has<br />
been the thing that has kept the world at peace. So long as<br />
that is the state of affairs, so long as we live under this<br />
threat then I am sure you will agree with me, we must see to<br />
it that whatever we do we will do in order to make the existence<br />
of the deterrent effective.*<br />
Certainly it is not for Australia to frustrate the<br />
existence of the nuclear deterrent in the hands of the United<br />
States of America. That would be a suicidal and a shocking<br />
thing to do, and so the day comes when the United States says<br />
to us and all this was announced within two or three days,<br />
two or three years ago-it's been blown up lately, but it was<br />
all public property a long time ago. They come to us and<br />
they say, " Look, weld like to discuss with you putting up a<br />
radio station in the North-West of Western Australia." 1<br />
" What for?" " Well, we want to have means of communicating on<br />
a very low frequ-, ncy with our Navy, primarily," which, of<br />
course obviously means " with our surface ships, with our<br />
submarines, with our aircraft carriers, because they are all<br />
involved communicating with our Navy. This will make perfect<br />
our means of communicating with our naval forces all round<br />
the world, We have them in the Pacific, in the North Pacifia.<br />
We have them in the Atlantic. We want one here if we can get<br />
it because this will cover the Indian Ocean and the South West<br />
Pa cif ic." 1 And being allies of the United States of America<br />
and being profoundly dependent upon what they may do if we<br />
are attacked, we said, " Yes, we are quite prepared to discuss<br />
this and work out appropria e terms," and so we did and they<br />
are about to build the place and spend a powar of money on itor<br />
f-40 million. But they said, and I think they were dead<br />
right, " Of course, we can't have joint control in a matter of<br />
this kind. We want to be able to have communication with our<br />
naval forces not subject to a veto by whatever government may<br />
exist in Australia7 but in our own right," and we said, " That's<br />
right. We would like you to consult with us on every conceivable<br />
matter " 1 but we werentt going to put them in the position of<br />
being told if they became involved in warlike activities out of<br />
00* 06000./ 9 </p>
<p>= 9<br />
the Indian Ocean which could only be against Communist attack<br />
we were not going to put them in the position of being told by<br />
us on that day not by me but by my successors " You can't use<br />
this station. Get out." Think of how that would handicap them<br />
in the deployment of their naval forces in the Indian Ocean.<br />
Think of how that would handicap them in delivering a stroke of<br />
retaliation against an attack made by the Communists, the Soviet<br />
Union. Ladies and gentlemen, my opponents in ParliamentC are<br />
out of date on this business. They are thinking in a lost world.<br />
The Soviet Union, if it does decide upon the criminal folly of<br />
attacking the free world is not going to send a courteous letter<br />
and say, " Take notice that in a fortnight or three weeks, we are<br />
going to do something." If they ever got into this bedlamite<br />
condition of making an attack, the first thing that anybody would<br />
know about it would be when the tracking stations picked up the<br />
missile en route to the United States and that gives you what<br />
five minutes, ten minutes, no more than fifteen minutes to give<br />
orders to the people who have weapons of retaliation " We are<br />
at war with these people. You go ahead." Because unless the<br />
return blow followis swiftly after the blow of attack, it is<br />
finished and finished unfavourably for us, for the free people<br />
in the world, These are serious matters and they deserve not<br />
hysterical consideration but serious consideration. I tell you<br />
quite plainly I will not be held accountable for rendering the<br />
deterrent power of the United States futile in the waters off tihe<br />
Australian coast and if the people of Australia disagree they<br />
know exactly what to do with me. But I think they will understand<br />
this position very clearly. This is essential to our success,<br />
Well now Sir, what does the Labour Party do about it9<br />
I am sure some of the people sitting opposite me in Parliam~ ent<br />
are all in favour of the establishment of this communications<br />
station, all in favour of it, but they had a great hullabaloo,<br />
you remember, and the y had a special conference of what we now<br />
refer to respectfully as the " 36 men" and they decided by 19 to<br />
17 that yes, they could go ahead on condition that there was<br />
joint control. In other words, on condition that Australia<br />
would have a veto over everything that was done in the station.<br />
And so we got into Parliament. We introduced a bill, we<br />
attached the agreement to it and the bill was a very simple bill<br />
as a bill. It simply said, " The execution of the contract<br />
contained in the schedule is hereby ratified" and so therefore<br />
the matter of substance in the bill was the contract in the<br />
schedule. Well they spoke on it. We have had the most<br />
fascinating debate in the Parliament about it. ( Laughter) All<br />
the boys who hate the idea of this station and who hato the<br />
idea of the Americans and who aliays take an entirely different<br />
line were disciplined into suitable silence. They spoke<br />
softly. They cooed like doves, if I may coin a phrase. And<br />
you've never heard anything so mild, mild as curdled milk.<br />
( Interjector " Is that why you threw Eddie Ward out?) Oh no,<br />
the House threw him out. ( Laughter) You forget that. Tha~' s<br />
not without difficulty, but the House did. ( laughter)<br />
Well, now, I just want to complete my narrative on<br />
this m~ atter. One of the front-line spokesmen for the Opposition<br />
said what they were going to do how they were going to vote on<br />
this bill and it was explained that they would not vote against<br />
the Second Reading, because they wanted to make it clear that<br />
they were not in principle, opposed to the matter. They would<br />
vote against the schedule because they wanted to make it clear<br />
that they didn't like the particular agteement and that when they<br />
came to the Third Reading, they would move an amendment that the<br />
0 </p>
<p>10<br />
Third Reading would be deferred for six months. Well they<br />
were better than their word because they didn't have a division<br />
on the Second Reading but they divided the House four times<br />
before we got to the hird Reading, Really their friendship<br />
for the bill was magnificently concealed. They kept on v: oting<br />
against it in connection with this bill time after time and<br />
then we got to the Third Reading and up got the Leader of the<br />
Opposition and he made a powerful speech, very moving, that the<br />
bill be deferred for three months and he gave his reasons and<br />
I got up and gave my reasons.<br />
And the Opposition found itself in such a state of<br />
confusion that for the first time in my Parliamentary experience,<br />
they forgot to vote for their own amendment. ( Laughter) This<br />
is literally true. They forgot to vote for their own amendment.<br />
It was rejected on the voices and when they gathered themselves<br />
together because it is a bit difficult for them, you know,<br />
they have a series of groups and caves and various different<br />
views and they meet ea, 2h other distantly in the corridors<br />
( Laughter) they got together a bit then and said, " Oh, dear.<br />
Wie did make a mistake there." So they voted against the<br />
Third Reading. No postponement. Nothing else. Just pointblank<br />
against the Third Reading of the bill, In other words,<br />
if peop , e are to be judged by their votes the Australian<br />
Labour P arty in Canberra had voted against the ratification of<br />
this agreement and therefore against the establishment of this<br />
very important American radio communications station in the<br />
North West of Australia.<br />
Indeed, if I may quote myself, and that's a very<br />
poor business for any man to engage in, I must tell you that<br />
on my speech on their amendment to the Third Reading, the one<br />
that died by the way, I pointed out to them that they need<br />
not pretend that they were really in favour of this bill because<br />
under Standing Orders of the Commonwealth Parliament, Standing<br />
Order 237 it is expressly stated that a motion to defer the<br />
Third Realing for six months, if carried finally disposes of<br />
the bill and therefore I pointed out to them that it would be<br />
the end of the bill and the end of the session because the<br />
Americans were not going to dangle around for six months waiting<br />
for something to happen. They are in a hurry. They regard<br />
defence provi~ ns as urgent. I therefore asked honourable<br />
members opposite to tell me did they really want to defeat this<br />
bill under the Standing Ordur because if they did, they ought<br />
to say so, they ought to vote against the Third Reading,<br />
They just ought to come clean on this matter. But were they<br />
putting the amendment up because they didn't want it to be<br />
carried, because they knew that it wouldn't be carried but<br />
they would have the kudos of having moved it with none of the<br />
risks of carrying it.<br />
What would happen to them if two of my members failed<br />
to hear the division bells and failed to vote and they won<br />
their amendment. Where would they be then. They would have<br />
the shock of their lives. So I said they could take their<br />
own choice, They were either demonstrating that they were<br />
hostile to this installation which is favoured by the vast<br />
majority of the Australian people or they could admit that<br />
they were humbugs having put up an amendment of a fatal kind,<br />
knowing and bolieving that it would be defeated, And of<br />
course this choice, the only choice as I told you so disturbed<br />
them that when it came to the point, they forgot tovote on it<br />
at all, 0 0 00./ 11 </p>
<p>11<br />
Now, ladies and gentlemen, these again are tremendous<br />
matters the security of this country, what we do for our own<br />
defence about which I made an elaborate statement the other<br />
day, hoa we co-operate with our friends, whether we realise<br />
that the security of Australia depends, not only on our own<br />
efforts which can never by themselves be adequate but on our<br />
capacity to have co-operation with our allies. Ihese are the<br />
things that wo have to understand and when you have allies<br />
particularly a great ally like the United States, you can't say<br />
to it " Look, you cantt use a point of land in our country for<br />
signalling to your ships because somebody maightntt like it."<br />
Do we want them on our side? Do we believe that we must have<br />
them on our side? And if the answers to those questions are<br />
" Yes", what's all this nonsense that the Opposition is engaging<br />
in, the Opposition that wants you to give a recruit to its<br />
strength or weakness in the Federal Parliament on June 1st. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
