<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8245</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE GULF THURSDAY, 17 JANUARY 1991</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/01/1991</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008245.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHECK ACATNST nELIVRY NMARMPED UNTIL D) ELIVERY<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE GULF<br />
THURSDAY, 17 JANUARY 1991<br />
Ladies and gentlemen, fellow Australians<br />
You will recall1 that on 4 December last, I told Parliament<br />
that Australia was prepared to make our Naval Task Force<br />
available to serve with allied forces in operations<br />
authorised by Resolution 678 of the United Nations Security<br />
Council, should that become necessary.<br />
You will also recall that Resolution 678 authorised member<br />
states of the United Nations, from 15 January 1991, to use<br />
all necessary means, including force, to uphold and<br />
implement the Security Council's previous resolutions in<br />
essence, the unconditional withdrawal by Iraq from Kuwait.<br />
With profound regret, I must now inform you that the<br />
necessity which I foreshadowed in the Parliament five weeks<br />
ago has come about.<br />
As a consequence, therefore, the Australian Naval Task Force<br />
in the Gulf is now with other members of the United Nations<br />
co-operating in armed action to fulfil the United Nations<br />
resolutions to enforce the withdrawal of Iraq from Kuwait.<br />
It has been my intention that Parliament, having endorsed<br />
the position I put on 4 December, should be given the<br />
earliest opportunity to receive a report from me should<br />
action be taken in line with that position.<br />
Accordingly, I have decided to recall the Parliament on<br />
Monday 21 January for two days so that I can make, and allow<br />
debate upon, such report.<br />
Fellow Australians<br />
I must emphasise from the outset and it cannot be repeated<br />
too often or stressed too strongly that this tragic<br />
necessity has one cause, and one cause only.<br />
And that is the invasion and occupation of the nation of<br />
Kuwait, a member-state of the United Nations, by Iraq on<br />
2 August last year more than five months ago. </p>
<p>That was the act of war and since that time we have sought<br />
by means of peace to reverse that act of war.<br />
Since that time, the world community, working through the<br />
United Nations, with a unanimity, a strength and unity of<br />
purpose without precedent in history, has demanded that the<br />
Government of Iraq withdraw unconditionally its armed forces<br />
from Kuwait.<br />
Twelve separate resolutions of the United Nations have been<br />
aimed at achieving that result.<br />
Since August, governments of the member-states of the United<br />
Nations have worked unremittingly to persuade Saddam Hussein<br />
to comply with the will of the world community and to end<br />
the crisis he alone provoked.<br />
Literally at the eleventh hour, with the positive support of<br />
the allied nations and in particular the President of the<br />
United States, the Secretary-General of the United Nations<br />
went to Baghdad to make a last appeal for compliance, a last<br />
plea for peace.<br />
Like every other initiative undertaken within the framework<br />
of the United Nations' resolutions, it was rejected with<br />
contempt, and met the same uncompromising refusal to do the<br />
one thing that the world community agrees he must do give<br />
up the nation he has seized and crushed.<br />
That is why Resolution 678 of the United Nations Security<br />
Council has come into effect.<br />
And that is why I have directed the Australian Naval Task<br />
Force to participate in the operations authorised by that<br />
resolution. Ladies and gentlemen, fellow Australians<br />
So momentous a decision must be placed as it has indeed<br />
been taken in the broad context of the future not only<br />
the future of Kuwait, not only the future of the middle<br />
East, but in the context of our future vision of a world<br />
striving for peace and freedom.<br />
And our decision is based on five grave considerations.<br />
First, there is the fundamental principle, without which<br />
there can be neither peace nor freedom the right of every<br />
independent nation not to be invaded, not to be the victim<br />
of aggression, not to be destroyed.<br />
Second, we act with the commanding moral authority of the<br />
United Nations. Never in its 45-year history has the United<br />
Nations worked so effectively and unitedly to fulfil its<br />
Charter and the principles of peace and security it<br />
embodies. </p>
<p>Third, we have reached this decision only at the end of a<br />
process without precedent in history. There is no parallel<br />
for the restralint, the patience and the caution with which<br />
the world alliance against Saddam Hussein has sought by<br />
peaceful means to resolve this conflict.<br />
Fourth, the decision has a clear and achievable goal to<br />
end this aggression, as a necessary step towards<br />
establishing the conditions for peace and stability in the<br />
Middle East.<br />
And finally, t: here is a wider purpose behind our decision.<br />
It is a purpose implicit in everything that has been done by<br />
the United Nations since last August.<br />
That purpose is to further the great quest for a new world<br />
order of peace, security and freedom to fulfil the hopes<br />
and opportunities springing from the end of the<br />
confrontation between the United States and the Soviet<br />
Union. Indeed, I believe that, at the bar of history, there<br />
will be no greater condemnation of Saddam Hussein, than that<br />
his aggression has plunged the world into a terrible and<br />
needless crisis which threatens the world stability on which<br />
those splendid hopes depend.<br />
My fellow Australians<br />
I know that the overwhelming majority of Australians will<br />
share my regret indeed much deeper than regret at the<br />
need for this decision. We all of us wish for peace. But<br />
we cannot have peace just by wishing for it or just by<br />
talking about it; we have to work for it, and sometimes,<br />
tragically, we have to fight for it. The great lesson of<br />
this Century is that peace is bought at too high a price, if<br />
that price is the appeasement of aggression.<br />
I know that you all with me will feel that our first<br />
thoughts today go to the 884 of our fellow Australian<br />
serving men and women most directly affected by this<br />
decision.<br />
We have three ships of the Royal Australian Navy serving in<br />
the Gulf; HMAS Sydney, Brisbane and Success.<br />
Our thoughts go to these ships' crews, to the medical teams<br />
serving on the hospital ships, to the logistic support team<br />
in the region, and to the Australians serving on exchange<br />
with other allied forces in the Gulf.<br />
War is full of terrible uncertainty. We cannot foretell<br />
what will be demanded of our serving men and women; but we<br />
can foretell how they will meet those demands.<br />
We are confident of their skills; we are grateful for their<br />
devotion. We know they will serve bravely and well, and we<br />
hope, above all, that they will return safely home. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
