<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11677</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER            THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP            ADDRESS AT COMMUNITY LUNCHEON            SCHOOL OF ARTS, NOWRA NSW</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/02/2000</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...............................................................................................</p>
<p>Well Prime Minister. It sounds strange when I say that now. To the Mayor,</p>
<p> to Joanna Gash, to John Anderson the Deputy Prime Minister, my other Cabinet</p>
<p> colleagues, and my other parliamentary colleagues, ladies and gentlemen.</p>
<p>We in the Federal Cabinet do this quite often. We get out of Canberra,</p>
<p> we get out of Sydney, we get out of Melbourne, and we try and hold a spread</p>
<p> of Cabinet meetings in the regional and rural areas of Australia whenever</p>
<p> we can so that we can have an opportunity of meeting a cross-section of</p>
<p> the local community, and can have an opportunity of communicating to you</p>
<p> our concern about all sections of Australian society. Can I say to my</p>
<p> prime ministerial counterpart today that this is a government that endeavours</p>
<p> to listen to the concerns of people in rural and regional Australia. It</p>
<p> is a government that recognises that Australia is made up of many parts.</p>
<p> We have a lot in common as Australians, and the things that bind us together</p>
<p> are a lot more important than the things that might push us apart. And</p>
<p> right at the moment our country at a national level is doing very well</p>
<p> economically. We've rarely done as well. But I recognise that not</p>
<p> everybody is sharing that to the full whether they live in some of the</p>
<p> suburbs or whether they live in some of the regional parts of Australia.</p>
<p> And what we hope to do by these Cabinet meetings is to supplement the</p>
<p> quality of the representation that the regional areas of Australia has</p>
<p> in the federal parliament. And can I say to you very enthusiastically,</p>
<p> and very genuinely that you have an outstanding federal representative</p>
<p> in Joanna Gash the member for Gilmore.</p>
<p>Required reading for me before I came here was a long memorandum that</p>
<p> Jo has delivered to the Lodge. I sat up last night and read through it.</p>
<p> She gave me a list of things that she wanted the government to do, it</p>
<p> was quite long. She reminded me of many of the things that we had already</p>
<p> done. And she also reminded me that this was a community that was bound</p>
<p> together by a common commitment to make Australia a stronger and better</p>
<p> place in which to live. And Jo has certainly been an outstanding representative</p>
<p> of this very diverse electorate since she won it in March of 1996. She's</p>
<p> played a big role in the party room in shaping social policy. She's</p>
<p> always fairly and strongly represented the interests of the electorate</p>
<p> of Gilmore. It was Joanna's persistent lobbying of me and of John</p>
<p> Anderseon that led me to make on behalf of the government a commitment</p>
<p> in 1998 that we would declare Main Road 92 as a road of national importance.</p>
<p> And that meant that the federal government committed itself to funding</p>
<p> of half of the cost of constructing that road. And I know that the Shoalhaven</p>
<p> Shire Council has made an enormous financial commitment and I thank you</p>
<p> for that Mr Mayor. I'm disturbed that so far the New South Wales</p>
<p> government has not matched the commitment of the federal government. And</p>
<p> I think that's a great shame because this is a road that's very</p>
<p> important to this area. And we remain absolutely committed to the financial</p>
<p> provision that I promised before the last federal election. I made that</p>
<p> promise on behalf of the government and I don't intend to walk away</p>
<p> from it. But I've got to get the New South Wales government to do</p>
<p> its bit to carry its share of the responsibility. And as a further step</p>
<p> in putting pressure on the New South Wales government to do its bit and</p>
<p> to pick up 50% which you always do with roads of national importance,</p>
<p> I'll seek urgently in the next few weeks a meeting with the New South</p>
<p> Wales Premier Mr Carr to see if we can't progress the New South Wales</p>
<p> contribution to the construction of this road. And I hope that that will</p>
<p> be effective, and I hope it is not necessary for us to consider alternatives</p>
<p> to that kind of approach.</p>
<p>Ladies and gentlemen, good government for Australia is about attending</p>
<p> to those things that need to be attended to at a national level, and also</p>
<p> responding to the legitimate interests and concerns of people at a local</p>
<p> level. We at the moment are engaged in a very big debate in Australia</p>
<p> about reforming our taxation system. And I'm not going to burden</p>
<p> you with a whole lot of detail about that today, you'll be relieved</p>
<p> to hear. But I can tell you this  that we have done a lot of things</p>
<p> to make the Australian economy run better. And the reason we committed</p>
<p> ourselves to taxation reform at the last election, why we laid it all</p>
<p> out before the Australian people, was because we believed that taxation</p>
<p> reform would be good for the Australian people and good for the Australian</p>
<p> economy. And in the end that's what it's all about. It's</p>
<p> not about how it might effect this person or that person, or this group</p>
<p> or that group. It is whether at the end of the day reforming the Australian</p>
<p> taxation system will make Australia economically stronger and more internationally</p>
<p> competitive. And whether it will by giving a secure funding base to the</p>
<p> State guarantee more effectively the delivery of important local services</p>
<p> such as hospitals and schools and roads and police.</p>
<p>And it's because we believe those things that we committed ourselves</p>
<p> to taxation reform. It's not easy. There are unpopular elements in</p>
<p> it, but at the end of the day we'll have taxation cuts worth $47</p>
<p> a week for the average family. We'll have cheaper fuel in the regions</p>
<p> of Australia. We'll have more competitive exports. We'll have</p>
<p> significant reductions in business costs. We'll have in aggregate</p>
<p> a $12 billion cut in personal income tax. And overall it will be of enormous</p>
<p> economic benefit to Australia and it's because of the national economic</p>
<p> benefit that we remain so absolutely committed to the cause of taxation</p>
<p> reform.</p>
<p>Ladies and gentlemen, one of the great resources that this country has,</p>
<p> is of course, the inventive capacity of its people. We are for a nation</p>
<p> of under 20 million people capable of punching well above our weight in</p>
<p> areas of technology and areas of science. We are often at the leading</p>
<p> edge of many activities in this area and you don't only find this</p>
<p> in Melbourne and Sydney and Canberra but you also find it in the regions</p>
<p> of Australia.</p>
<p>And in that context I'm delighted to announce today that the Federal</p>
<p> Government will provide $1 million for the Solar Sailor project which</p>
<p> is based at Ulladulla and this money will support the construction and</p>
<p> demonstration of a catamaran powered by solar and wind energy with compressed</p>
<p> natural gas as a backup.</p>
<p>It will represent leading edge technology, the solar wing uses energy</p>
<p> from the sun or wind separately or in combination. It represents the potential</p>
<p> to travel on our waterways and oceans in a clean environmentally friendly</p>
<p> manner. Australia has a proud record of exporting leading edge marine</p>
<p> technology and Solar Sailor represents an exciting new direction. The</p>
<p> development of this technology is a credit to the people involved and</p>
<p> is the latest evidence of the innovation and potential that does exist</p>
<p> in regional Australia. And, as I say in this instance, the people of Ulladulla</p>
<p> and surrounding regions stand to reap the benefits of this exciting development.</p>
<p>It's always to me a tremendously energising experience to come to</p>
<p> a gathering like this, to know that you are meeting a cross section of</p>
<p> the Australian community. Not all of them are people who will agree with</p>
<p> you on everything or necessarily support everything that you seek to do</p>
<p> on a political level. But it's an authentic representation of the</p>
<p> great volunteer spirit of the Australian people. The catering today provided</p>
<p> by the volunteers of the local fire service. The lovely choir who I heard</p>
<p> earlier is part of the mass choir at the Australia Day celebration in</p>
<p> Sydney not so long ago. And as I look through the list of the guests,</p>
<p> the CWA, the local ministers of religion, the leaders of all the other</p>
<p> local organisations and one of the great traditions of this country is</p>
<p> that we do work together as a people.</p>
<p>We bring out the best in ourselves when we work as a community to tackle</p>
<p> problems. And I find these gatherings, wherever they are in Australia,</p>
<p> always tremendously energising. I find them always different. I find them</p>
<p> a simple way of expressing the essential unity and the essential commitment</p>
<p> to the long term goals of building a better Australia which is inherent</p>
<p> in all of the Australian people.</p>
<p>And may I say to my fellow prime minister today, that that was a very</p>
<p> touching, incisive, effective introduction. I must say that it was a quieter</p>
<p> question time than I'm normally used to. Perhaps we could bring you</p>
<p> down to Canberra and when you stand up you would hush them all into absolute</p>
<p> silence. And I thought you spoke a great deal of wisdom. I thought you</p>
<p> reminded all of us of the way of life that is special about regional Australia.</p>
<p>But there are some aspects of living outside the capital cities of Australia</p>
<p> that are not only different, but they're very special. We can't</p>
<p> all live there. We don't all necessarily wish to. There are great</p>
<p> aspects of living in the big cities. The great thing about Australia is</p>
<p> that we have tremendous diversity. But what your speech reminded me of</p>
<p> and what I think today's gathering reminds me of is that Government's</p>
<p> are elected to govern for all of the Australian people and not just one</p>
<p> section and we seek through meetings such as this to reach out to the</p>
<p> people of the regions of Australia to recognise the need to give help</p>
<p> where it's needed. To also recognise that many parts of the regions</p>
<p> of Australia are doing very well and there are many businesses that are</p>
<p> doing very well.</p>
<p>And I know that there are many parts of the Gilmore electorate where</p>
<p> business is booming and where there's a great deal of prosperity.</p>
<p> I also know there are sections of it where things aren't going so</p>
<p> well and I can assure all of you that that situation is well and truly</p>
<p> and faithfully represented in Canberra on your behalf by Joanna Gash.</p>
<p>May I thank her for inviting us here today. Can I congratulate her again</p>
<p> on the tremendous job that she does as your local representative. And</p>
<p> can I say on behalf of all of my Cabinet colleagues how absolutely delighted</p>
<p> we are to be amongst you today.</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
<p>[Ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
