<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>15750</transcript-id>
    <title>Joint Media Release Premier of New South Wales, NSW Flood Assistance Announced  </title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/02/2008</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Australian Government today approved further financial assistance to help small businesses and farmers through the enhanced component of the Natural Disaster Relief and Recovery Arrangements (NDRRA) after a request from the New South Wales Premier, Morris Iemma.</p>
<p>The Australian Government will provide additional assistance to those residents seriously affected by the recent floods in the Northern and Central West areas of NSW in December 2007 and January 2008.</p>
<p>Through the NDRRA program with the states, the Australian Government assists with the costs and resourcing of response and recovery operations in large scale disasters.</p>
<p>This additional assistance will provide farmers and registered small business owners, who have experienced severe damage from floods, with a grant of up to $5,000.</p>
<p>An additional tourism recovery package has also been announced, which includes $300,000 each from the Commonwealth and NSW Governments to assist the North Coast region.</p>
<p>The Australian Government will continue working with the NSW Government and local community organisations to support people affected by the recent storms and floods.</p>
<p>While on the North Coast of NSW today, the Prime Minister  commended the workers and many volunteers for their efforts in helping the community recovery effort.“After meeting with local business owners and farmers this morning, it is plain that the impact of the floods on the Northern Rivers District has been very significant.</p>
<p>“There is still much work to do over the coming months, however we hope this assistance today will provide a helping hand for these communities to fully recover.”</p>
<p>NSW Premier Morris Iemma thanked the Commonwealth for recognising the impact of the flood events.</p>
<p>“This is a great example of how the State and Commonwealth can work together.”</p>
<p>“This package is a measured response both to the immediate needs of primary producers and affected small businesses throughout the rural communities in NSW.”</p>
<p>Farmers should contact the NSW Rural Assistance Authority for details on 1800 678 593.</p>
<p>More information on Australian Government assistance is available at <a href="http://www.disasterassist.gov.au">www.disasterassist.gov.au</a></p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER'S PRESS OFFICE: 02 6277 7744</p>
<p>NSW PREMIER'S PRESS OFFICE Office: 02 9228 429</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
