<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8311</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER OPENING OF ABC ULTIMO CENTRE SYDNEY - 22 JUNE 1991</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/06/1991</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008311.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister<br />
Opening of ABC Ultimo Centre<br />
Sydney 22 June 1991<br />
Managing Dircector, David Hill<br />
Chairman, Bob Somervaille<br />
Friends and supporters of the Australian Broadcasting<br />
Corporation This ceremony marks, without doubt, an historic milepost in<br />
the story of the Australian Broadcasting Corporation one<br />
of the enduringly respected institutions of Australian<br />
culture and, in many ways, one of the abidingly great<br />
institutions of Australian national life.<br />
We are not ' Just celebrating the opening of a new building<br />
as magnificent an achievement as the Ultimo Centre is.<br />
We are celebrating the survival, and indeed despite all<br />
the dilemmas and challenges of the 1990s the continued<br />
improvement of Australia's independent, non-commercial,<br />
publicly-owned broadcasting service.<br />
Today's ceremony tells the people of Australia that their<br />
national broadcaster remains the dynamic and creative force<br />
that has done so much to shape Australian cultural life.<br />
It tells the nation that the ABC is flourishing as never<br />
before, because it is succeeding as never before in being ~ a<br />
quality non-commercial broadcaster that reaches out to<br />
embrace the overwhelming majority of the Australian people.<br />
The Ultimo Centre is the end product of a successful and<br />
effective process of consolidation a micro-economic reform<br />
that represents savings worth millions of dollars a year.<br />
Mathematicians take note: twelve into one does go. This one<br />
building replaces 12 separate ABC offices scattered<br />
throughout Sydney and in doing so it provides the best<br />
accommodation that corporate management, ABC radio and the k<br />
Sydney Symphony Orchestra have ever had. </p>
<p>2.<br />
if we want an example of Australia as the ' clever country',<br />
it is right here. Because this building is fitted out with<br />
state of the art equipment, including the highly advanced<br />
acoustics in the Eugene Goossens Hall and the largest<br />
installation of touch-screen technology by any broadcaster<br />
anywhere in the world international-best technology<br />
developed by an Australian firm.<br />
So my first task today is to congratulate everyone who has<br />
been involved in the vast and complex process of designing,<br />
constructing and fitting out the new building and of<br />
managing the move into it.<br />
I recognise achievements like this don't just happen. They<br />
are the result of careful and deliberate strategic planning<br />
planning which has been made more possible by the stable<br />
funding environment in which the ABC now operates.<br />
The triennial funding guarantee instituted by the Government<br />
in 1988 has been a success because it has given the ABC<br />
flexibility, with a stable and predictable bottom line.<br />
As you know, the Government recently decided to continue<br />
real terms funding for this and the next two financial<br />
years, with-tie-icception of course of the efficiency<br />
dividend deducted from all Government agencies.<br />
During this period, the ABC will continue to retain any<br />
extra income that it earns.<br />
This means that we have decisively put behind us the<br />
acrimony of that annual budget scrum that was never an<br />
enjoyable or an enlightening experience for any of us.<br />
With guaranteed funding, the Australian people know, and we<br />
in the Government know, that you are giving them value for<br />
their money.<br />
Let me add, once more, that the Government believes the ABC<br />
must and will remain free of commercial advertising and<br />
sponsorship.<br />
We recognise that the ABC's strength, and the basis for the<br />
enormous reservoir of goodwill that exists in the community<br />
for the ABC, is its non-commercial style its capacity to<br />
be an independent provider of news and information.<br />
In an industry where broadcasters are too often blamed for<br />
appealing to the lowest common denominator, the ABC is still<br />
the quality alternative.<br />
And what is just as important, this quality alternative does<br />
not mean that the ABC is forever locked into serving a<br />
narrow elite of the community. </p>
<p>On TV, programs: like Qiuan= u and The Irvmiat are<br />
winning ratings battles against tough commercial opposition<br />
and they are doing so because they are insisting on<br />
providing quality.<br />
In the samet way, the radio revolution at the ABC has seen a<br />
dramatic expansion of the audience without any loss of<br />
quality. In the country, millions of Australians who used to have<br />
only one ABC radio station now have a choice of three: Radio<br />
National, their local regional station and ABC FM.<br />
And Triple J is now broadcasting to every capital city and<br />
to Newcastle.<br />
Let me add that the ABC's international news reporting<br />
remains one of its greatest strengths. At this time of<br />
historic and exciting change around the world, it is vital<br />
that Australians be well informed and that they be informed<br />
by Australians, and from an Australian perspective.<br />
Whether it be in the United States or the Soviet Union, in<br />
Europe, the Middle East or our own region, the ABC's news<br />
bureaus are reporting the world with insight and great<br />
expertise and we are all the beneficiaries of that.<br />
The number of international radio and television awards that<br />
the ABC is winning is further proof of the ABC's commitment:<br />
to quality. And this international recognition is being<br />
matched with increased overseas sales of ABC programs and<br />
increased revenue from co-productions with foreign<br />
broadcasters.<br />
And talking of quality, I want to make special reference to<br />
Kthe Sydney Symph) ony Orchestra.. As you know, Hazel spent ten<br />
y days touffiir the United States with the SSO in 1988,<br />
culminating in that fantastic concert in Carnegie Hall. You<br />
already have a lot of fans, and you won a lot more on that<br />
tour many of them in the United States and one of them who<br />
lives with me in the Lodge.<br />
It is my hope, and it is certainly Hazel's, that these new<br />
facilities will enable the Orchestra to continue to make<br />
great music and we are looking forward to hearing you play<br />
shortly. So in all these respects, the ABC is delivering the goods<br />
repaying in full the half-billion dollar investment made by<br />
the Australian tax-payer each year.<br />
At the same time, and without compromising the ABC's<br />
political and editorial independence, it is important that<br />
the ABC be fially accountable to its audience the taxpayers<br />
who support it.<br />
I welcome the fact that the ABC has set up an independent<br />
Complaints Review Panel. </p>
<p>We will monitor its progress closely, as part of a review<br />
later this year of the total question of accountability of<br />
the ABC, and of SBS.<br />
My friends,<br />
This is the ABC's day. It is not the occasion for any<br />
lengthy comments from me about the broadcasting industry<br />
generally. But I do want to say this by way of comment about the recent<br />
upheavals in commercial television and radio.<br />
It's been a painful process, as the whole industry has come<br />
to terms with the unrealistic commercial expectations that<br />
some people had created for it.<br />
But all the evidence is that the industry is rebuilding<br />
itself in a disciplined and positive way. And why not: the<br />
economic fundamentals of commercial broadcasting in<br />
Australia are sound.<br />
That is the way back to profitability. It does not lie<br />
through cutting back services or through seeking concessions<br />
from Government to relax our policy on ownership, control<br />
and Australian content. We've made that clear before, and I<br />
repeat it today.<br />
There will be no dilution of the status quo in which three<br />
Australian-owned commercial television services broadcast to<br />
as many Australians as possible.<br />
That is the level of service that Australians have come to<br />
expect, and they are entitled to expect it in the future.<br />
My friends,<br />
It won't have escaped your notice that the difficulties<br />
afflicting the commercial side of the industry have left the<br />
ABC in a position of unparalleled industry strength to<br />
complement your unparalleled obligation as a public<br />
broadcaster to serve the people of Australia.<br />
The maintenance of full public funding for the ABC is a<br />
significant commitment in the current economic climate and<br />
it is one which has helped the ABC stay strong.<br />
And that in turn has ensured that your audiences can still<br />
rely on you for quality news, information and entertainment.<br />
And whether they live in the capital cities or in provincial<br />
towns or in the bush, whether they listen to the radio or<br />
watch TV that is what they get. </p>
<p>That is a particular credit to Bob Somervaille, Wendy<br />
McCarthy and to their Board and I join Kim Beazley in<br />
thanking them for their energy and dedication over these<br />
years, and in welcoming the new Board members.<br />
At the end of the day, however, credit for the ABC's<br />
achievement is, properly, shared by the whole Corporation.<br />
And it is with the confident expectation that the<br />
Corporation as a whole will continue to serve the Australian<br />
people well that I have pleasure now in declaring open the<br />
ABC Ultimo Centre. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
