<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11852</transcript-id>
    <title>Doorstop Interview, Sydney </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/04/2001</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>ubjects: beer excise; Ansett.</p>
<p>E&amp;OE................................</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Are you pleased that the ACCC is going to investigate the possibility that some hoteliers didn't pass on the beer excise cut?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It is very simple. Excise has been cut and the benefit of that should be passed on to all of the beer drinkers of Australia. It's as simple as that and any efforts of the ACCC will be strongly supported by the Government. There should be no delay by the breweries in ensuring that the cut is passed on to Australian consumers.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard are you convinced the centenary meeting in Melbourne is actually [inaudible]</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Are you pleased with the way that the officials have been handling the Ansett situation?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes. It's a very difficult situation. I'm pleased that Ansett and CASA are talking. It's something that's got to be worked through. The regulator has the full confidence of the Government and I'm greatly encouraged that Mr Toomey and Mr Toller are now in communication and are now working through the issues. Ansett is a great company and it's made a great contribution to Australian aviation over the years. However safety is the most important thing as far as I am concerned. We have a wonderful safety record in aviation in Australia and I want to keep it that way and that is why any insistence on safety measures by CASA will always have our total support.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[inaudible] has on the Australian aviation industry?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I think if it's handled sensibly it won't have a negative effect. The important thing in a situation like this is for people to recognise there's a problem, to work through it in a sensible cooperative fashion, to maintain very strong safety standards, and to maintain communication. Now that is obviously occurring and I think that's a very good thing.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Is it good to see pretty much all of the airlines work together to try and clear the backlog over Easter?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well that's the Australian way - pulling together when you've got a problem and it's something that I encourage people to do. And I thank Qantas and Virgin and Impulse for the cooperative approach they've taken. I mean that is the sensible Australian way and the net effect is that confidence in the whole industry is maintained, people were transported to where they wanted to go, and very importantly and most importantly of all, the reputation for safety of Australian airlines is maintained. Thank you.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard on a more parochial note can I ask you about the woodchopper?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>The woodchopper is a magnificent man literally.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[inaudible]</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well he's only 23 and he's got the makings..well he is in reality a world champion already in a number of disciplines and he's going off to Canada in a few weeks time to compete there. Of course we have the best woodchoppers in the world.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Well what did you think [inaudible]</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I mean I don't claim to be an expert but that sounded very impressive to me. And he's a very impressive young man and he'll go a long way.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[inaudible] when will Australia come out of recession?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>We are not in recession.</p>
<p>[Ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
