<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>549</transcript-id>
    <title>PM 49/1962 - ROYAL TOUR - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R G MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/07/1962</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000549.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
P. M. NO. 42192<br />
ROYAL TOUR<br />
Statement by t ~ rime Minister the Rt. Hon RG Menzies<br />
I am now in a position to announce certain tentative<br />
arrangements for the forthcoming visit to Australia of Her<br />
Majesty the Queen and His Royal Highness, the Duke of<br />
Edinburgh. It is expected that the Royal couple will arrive<br />
in Canberra by air from New Zealand on Monday. February 18.<br />
Thereafter, they will engage in a tour which will take them<br />
into all six States and the Northern Territory.<br />
The precise amount of time to be spent in each<br />
State has yet to be determined though it is unlikely in any<br />
instance to exceed three days,<br />
Her Majesty has made known her wish that her visits<br />
to the States should be associated, if possible, with some<br />
event of special significance. As a result, the exact<br />
itinerary cannot be announced until the States have themselves<br />
made their proposals and these have been communicated to the<br />
Queen. However, it seems likely that the general order<br />
of the visits after Canberra will be South Australia, Victoria,<br />
Tasmania, New South Wales, Queensland, return to Canberra,<br />
then visit the Northern Territory and Western Australia,<br />
Her Majesty has also made known her desire to use<br />
the Royal Yacht " Britannia" at various stages of her tour.<br />
Rcalising that this will reduce the periods in which she will<br />
be in direct contact with her Australian people, she has<br />
herself volunteered to extend the length of the visit beyond<br />
the month originally contemplated and her departure from Perth<br />
by air for the United Kingdom will now take place on 27th<br />
March. It is expected that the use of the " Britannia"<br />
will produce a number of agreeable results. It will allow<br />
Her Majesty to enter some of the Australian cities from the<br />
seaward. Further she will be able to achieve rest while<br />
moving from point to point and the Royal Yacht will be<br />
available for such entertaining as Her Majesty may choose<br />
to do.<br />
CANBERRA, 6th July, 1962, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
