<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10223</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON. JOHN HOWARD MP UNVEILING OF BRONZE BUST - BALLARAT</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/01/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010223.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Fax from PRIME MINISTER<br />
29 January 1997 TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE HON. JOHN HOWARD MP<br />
UNVEILING OF BRONZE BUST BALLARAT<br />
E&amp; OE<br />
Councillor James Coghian and Mrs Coghian, to my colleague the Federal Member for<br />
Ballarat, Michael Ronaldson, to my State Parliamentary colleagues, to the artist<br />
amongst us, well there are probably many artists amongst but given the nature of the<br />
occasion, the particular artist amongst us Peter Nicholson, other distinguished guests,<br />
ladies and gentlemen.<br />
Firstly, can I say what a great delight it is to be in the beautiflul gardens of Ballarat.<br />
Australia is blessed by the fact that in many parts of our country, particularly in the<br />
provincial and rural areas of Australia we have very fine gardens. I don't think you<br />
could find a finer example anywhere in Australia than those of the Botanical Gardens<br />
of Ballarat. And, of course, the city of Ballarat has a very deep association with the<br />
history of Australia and as a community, as we approach the 100 years of the<br />
centenary, the Centenary of Federation, it's only a few years off now and we will<br />
celebrate 100 years of the Federation of Australia from the first of January 190 1.<br />
It is natural, inevitable and I think highly desirable that Australians increasingly reflect<br />
upon what has been achieved during that 100 year period and increasingly reflect upon<br />
the history of Australia. And when you reflect upon the history of Australia, not only<br />
over the last 100 years, but also in the years that went before that you can't, of course,<br />
omit a reflection on many of the historical associations between the Ballarat area and<br />
the development of Australian nationalism, the development of distinctively Australian<br />
attitudes back in the 19th Century which, in fact, pre-dated the Federation of Australia<br />
on the first of January 1901.<br />
And, of course, this avenue of Prime Ministerial busts is itself a contribution to the<br />
history of the country. As I wandered down observing the various likenesses of my 24<br />
predecessors I reflected briefly on the changed circumstances in which each of them<br />
came to the office of Prime Minister, I thought of the circumstances of Australia in<br />
1901 when Sir Edmund Barton was sworn in as the first Prime Minister of Australia. I<br />
thought of the trauma of World War I which was grappled with by a number of Prime<br />
Ministers and not least, of course, Billy Hughes who became famous with the<br />
Fafrv~ 30/ 01/ 97 11: 47 Pg: 4 </p>
<p>Fax from description of ' The Little Digger" and of James Henry Sculbi who had to grapple with<br />
the depths of the depression in the early 1930s and of the various terms in office of Sir<br />
Robert Menzies, Prime Minister at the outbreak of World War 11, ceasing not long<br />
thereafter to be Prime Mnister only to return in 1949 to govern for a record period<br />
until 1966.<br />
1 think of the great leadership shown by John Curtin, the Prime Minister of Australia<br />
during World War 11 and the toll that it took on his life and his being and led to his<br />
early death in 1945. Many of the other Prime Ministers of this country on both sides<br />
of the political fence, we all have our views, you have your views about me, you all<br />
have your views about my predecessors. This is not an occasion for partisanship rather<br />
it is an occasion to acknowledge the rich history of Australia, to acknowledge that the<br />
things that bind us together as Australians are far more important and more enduring<br />
and more significant than the things that push us apart.<br />
I'm delighted that Peter Nicholson is here today. I've observed his work over the<br />
years, it's hard not to. It's compulsive viewing and I agree that he's bipartisan, he<br />
certainly gives me a flick from time to time and he's given the other blokes a flick too<br />
from time to time. I mean, from rubber to bronze is a remarkable, it's a mark of his<br />
artistry and of his craftsmanship. I understand there's a bit of a tradition here that<br />
occasionally the Prime Ministers get dumped, you know, and one of my party room<br />
commnentators said that it was the only circumstance in which I would become a " wet".<br />
But, ladies and gentlemen, I think one of the things that marks Australians out from<br />
any other group of people in the world I made this remark at an Australia Day speech<br />
I gave a few days ago is that we have a very healthy irreverence and a very healthy<br />
scepticism as a commity.<br />
We are not a gullible people. We are, on occasions, blessed with a great amount of<br />
scepticism and I think healthy scepticism in any community is a very good thing<br />
provided it doesn't lurch into cynicism. We shouldn't be so sceptical that we become<br />
cynical, equally we shouldn't be so gullible that we're not a wake up to somebody<br />
who's trying to have us on. And that really is one of the great strengths that we have.<br />
It is one of the things that marks us out from ot her people with whom we may have<br />
similarities and the political cartoonists of Australia are in that long tradition of<br />
political scepticism and it's part of our system. It's annoying sometimes but, can I say,<br />
that scepticism is one of the things that has kept us a free people-It's one of the<br />
reasons why Australia is listed amongst only eight countries, only eight nations, that<br />
has been continuously democratic for the whole of the twentieth century and that is a<br />
remarkable: thing.<br />
And these days where sometimes I think people are too ready to see fault in Australia<br />
and too ready to apologise for Australia, I think that particular achievement is one of<br />
the reasons why instead of apologising we should as a community be immensely proud<br />
of what we have achieved as a nation and particularly what we have achieved since the<br />
Federation of the then colonies of Australia in 190 1.<br />
So there are many things that are interesting and enriching in the life of a Prime<br />
Minister. The most important is the regular contact with the people of Australia, the<br />
reminders of the marvellous diversity of our country, the reminder of the spirit of<br />
people wherever they may live in Australia and it is always to me a great pleasure to<br />
Fafri~ 38/ 01/ 97 11: 47 Pg: </p>
<p>Fax from visit different parts of the country to meet the citizens of different communities and<br />
today is no exception.<br />
So can I thank you Mr Mayor, can I thank you Councillor Coghian, to you Michael my<br />
colleague, the Federal Member for Ballarat who gives such terrific representation to<br />
this electorate in the national parliament, can thank you very much for inviting me<br />
here and without any further ado I shall perform the deed. There is one thing I forgot<br />
to mention Councillor Coghian said this was the second unveiling that he's presided<br />
over, can I assure you Sir it will be the last!<br />
ends Fafrr~ 30/ 01/ 97 11: 47 Pg: 6 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
