<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2493</transcript-id>
    <title>ARRIVAL STATEMENT - NEW YORK - THE PRIME MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA, THE RT HON WILLIAM MCMAHON</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/11/1971</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002493.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FO) R PRESS: ARRIVAL -STATTM~ ENT -NEW YORK<br />
TH-E PRI1M F M h11IS7ME~ R OF AUSTRALIA<br />
THE RT H10N. WILLIAM McIMAITON, q71<br />
I am visiting the United States of America<br />
at the invitation of President Ni-xon at a time of.,, considerable<br />
change in world. hffairs.<br />
I deeply appreciate the opportunity to exchange<br />
Cv jews on matters of mutual interes~ t and to advance the long-<br />
Cstanding frziendship between the. United Stateas and Australia.<br />
I hope to discu~ s-in paxticular, with the<br />
President the changes occurring in the Asian and Pacific<br />
region and the United States response to these changes,<br />
There is also a nu-mber of trade matters which,<br />
. Ln illy Might usUI-Iy o~ uhrtol~ n thvC<br />
visit of the Deputy Prime Miniztc: and Minister for Trade at the<br />
end of June. We are moving into a significant era of re-adjustments.<br />
if peace is to be assured3 in our part of It. hq world., the three<br />
g-Jeat powers., the United States, -the Soviet Union and China<br />
all nuclear powers -as well as J0apano, must reach some acco. rtmodationg<br />
a new balance in which there is ul recognition of. a-id respect<br />
for, the rights and aspiratipns oZ theixc countries.<br />
The place and role of u.-iddle and smaller powers<br />
in our region have special relevance to 5such a balance and<br />
Austrai~ a wishes to do all within its Dower to advance their<br />
nterests as well as its own. </p>
<p>2<br />
I had a most instructive talk with the<br />
United States Commander-in-Chief, Pacific ( Admiral McCain)<br />
in Honolulu on the strategic and security outlook in the<br />
Pacific following this week's decision in the United Nations<br />
on the entry of the Reoples' Republic of China and the<br />
expulsion of the Republic of China ( Taiwan).<br />
While in the United States I will have talks<br />
with President Nixon on 2 November and with senior members<br />
of his Administration in the same week. I<br />
ft<br />
; y </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
