<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2641</transcript-id>
    <title>MACQUARIE NETWORK WEEKLY BROADCAST BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT HON WILLIAM MCMAHON CH MP - 5 JULY 1972 - NORTHERN DEVELOPMENT</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/07/1972</release-date>
    <release-type>Broadcast</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002641.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO : NOT FOR RELEASE BEFORE-6 * 30-PM (' EST)-<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
MACQUARIr NETWORK<br />
W! E KLY BROADCAST<br />
BY THE PRI ? M. 1INiSTER, TH-E RT. 1,1N. WILLI7M !" cMATJON<br />
Cli, M P JULY 1972<br />
NcRUmERN DEVELOPMENT<br />
Good Evening I thought on this occasiorn I would vary the diet a<br />
little and talk about sonic of the things that make Australia such<br />
a great and wonderful country to live in.<br />
Some time ago, I received an invitation to go up<br />
to the North that is the Far W. est, ' East and West Kimberley,<br />
Cove and Darwin. And t-he matters that excited my interest were<br />
t%-hese. Australia is a country that needs a tremendous amount of<br />
1w. ater conservation. W~ need oxrnorts in orier to permit our<br />
dcve lopment to go on a-nd our standards of living to imnrovr..<br />
We also have -the nroblems of the environme-nt, anal<br />
I also wanted to make anquirles, if I could, about the Crown of<br />
Thorns Starfish and the Groat Barrior Roef.<br />
First of all, then about iwater conservation. I was<br />
invited up to ovnen a dcm in Darw; in that will cqiva water suplyl<br />
there for many years to comei. A~ nd Darwoin is, I believe, thet<br />
fastest-growing capital if I might uri that word in Australia.<br />
T was alba invitod to go across to the Ord Damp.<br />
And to give you an impression of what it is ] ike, the Ord will<br />
zervice an area t-wi ce as big as Victoria and will have nine times<br />
as mnuch wate-r as Sydney Harbour.<br />
i. n tim~ e there is no douht tha-t this water conservation<br />
will pay big dividends for us.<br />
Up th." ere 7hen talking about tie Ord scheme, -they<br />
talk about " Sydharl. s" ( Sydney HWarboui). And they mea-ure -the<br />
water flow bv the amount of: water in the Sydnfey Hlarbour that<br />
would pass through the gateways in the course of half an hour,<br />
and believe me, it is a tremendous amount of water. </p>
<p>2<br />
I then moved on to the second place that I had to<br />
open, and that is the works in Gove, right up in the far North-<br />
East of the Northern Territory. About $ 300-$ 350 million has been<br />
spent here in order to establish bauxite and alumina works. There<br />
is a difference between the two.<br />
And in the not too distant future, we will be exporting<br />
overseas approximately $ 60 million worth of bauxite and alumina per<br />
annum. There is a large Australian holding in the Corporation<br />
and the Australian holding can be increased should they wish to do<br />
so in the future. I then went on to a place called Mission Beach, just<br />
south of Cairns. My main reason for going was that it was on the way<br />
home but I also wanted to have a look at the Crown of Thorns Starfish<br />
and see to what extent this could be controlled so as to ensure that<br />
the Reef could be maintained.<br />
The Reef will be in the future as it is now a great<br />
attraction throughout the world. CSIRO is working on the problem and<br />
we have had a commission that has reported to us about it. I now know<br />
a lot more about this and I will be taking a bigger interest in it<br />
when I return home. These were the reasons for my visit. And then I realised<br />
during the time I have been here what a tremendous potential the<br />
whole of the North has, not only for Australians because I hope<br />
they will be able to enjoy it to the full but also for overseas<br />
people as well. The North is a wonderful area. It is part of the greatness<br />
of this country. It gives a tremendous amount of enjoyment to everyone<br />
who has the opportunity to travel up here. And I believe Australians<br />
will be able to travel here much more in the future.<br />
Goodnight. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
