<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5812</transcript-id>
    <title>SECOND SIR CONDOR LAUCKE ORATION</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/05/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005812.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO: 8.00 PM<br />
,14AUS 1A<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA FRIDAY, 7 MAY 1982<br />
SECOND SIR CONDOR LAUCKE ORATION<br />
I would like to congratulate the service clubs initiati. nig<br />
this oration, which is a tribute to the esteem in which<br />
Sir Condor Laucke is rightly held. I would also like to<br />
thank you for inviting me to give the second in the series<br />
following Sir-Condor's own inaugural oration on the Senate,<br />
and the importance of Parliamentary democracy.<br />
What I would like to discuss with you this evening are some<br />
of the ways in which Australia needs to respond to the<br />
dominant features of the current world situation. In<br />
particular, I want to look at the significance for our<br />
policies of the overall world economic situation, and of<br />
some threats to world peace and security. I am pleased to have<br />
this opportunity to draw together a number of themes, which<br />
really cannot be viewed in isolation, themes which are important<br />
in understanding Australia's situation and prospects, themes.<br />
which provide a foundation for the const;, uctive and vigorous<br />
policies which will meet Australian values and objectives.<br />
Government policies must be directed to achieving., greater<br />
prosperity and further improvement in the living standards<br />
of Australia.. They need to increase opportunities still<br />
further for our young people in particular; they need to be<br />
compatible with Australia's concerns and responsbilities as<br />
an outward looking nation. The task of welding together the<br />
imperatives of policy formation and the hopes and aims of<br />
people is one of the great challenges for governments. We must<br />
never lose sight of our objectives, or the constant need to<br />
revitalise and redefine them in terms which are relevant to<br />
current circumstances.<br />
But by the same token, no democratic government can serve<br />
the community well unless it pursues policies which are based<br />
on reality. This means policies which reflect a sound<br />
understandirLg of what is happening in the world, and the impact<br />
of these events on Australia. It means policies which give<br />
full recognition to Australia's advantages, and to the great<br />
underlying strengths of our economy. It also calls for balanced<br />
understandin~ g of all aspects of the situation in which<br />
Australia is placed. ./ 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
Whether times are buoyant or depressed, whether prospects are<br />
encouraging or uncertain, balance is vastly important in our<br />
understanding of events and in the presentation of news, for<br />
without balance, the community can be seriously misled, and<br />
people's attitudes and expectations misdirected. At the<br />
present tiME! Australia and other Western countries are facing<br />
a conjunction of two events which present problems of significant<br />
proportions, whose dimensions have not yet been fully<br />
identified or defined.<br />
The first arises from the profound economic difficulties<br />
currently being experienced in the West, the other is the deployment<br />
of unprecenctented Soviet power around the world, combined with<br />
the aggressive stance of Soviet policy. Against the background<br />
of the present economic, political and strategic circumstances,<br />
two summit meetings due to take place next month in Europe,<br />
the Versaill~ es meeting of the major economic powers, and the<br />
Bonn meetingr of the NATO heads of government, take on a<br />
special importance, a special meaning.<br />
The Versaill~ es Economic Summit is the latest in a series of<br />
meetings tha~ t have been held every year since 1975, and it<br />
will be attended by the heads of government of the United<br />
Kingdom, France, West Germany, Italy, Japan, Canada and the<br />
United States, and the * President of the Commission of the European<br />
Communities. They will discuss the economic problems faced<br />
by the West and policies to overcome them; energy problems<br />
faced by thE! West beyond the present downturn in world prices;<br />
the dialogue! between developed and developing countries; and<br />
problems anid strategies in economic relations between the<br />
western countries and the Soviet bloc.<br />
The NATO Summnit, on the other hand, is * a special meeting<br />
convened against the background of growing concern among<br />
-Western governments about the state of the Western alliance.<br />
It will be searching for a strategy for the 1980' s and will be<br />
attended by the same leaders attending the economic summit,<br />
except Japan, together with smaller west European NATO members.<br />
The conjunction of the two meetings means that economic and<br />
security factors can both be addressed and the linkages between<br />
them given proper emphasis.<br />
Australia is not directly involved in these discussions, but<br />
we and most other free peoples may be profoundly affected by<br />
their outcomae, and for this reason I particularly value the<br />
opportunity which I will have in a couple of weeks to discuss<br />
some of these issues with President Reagan in Washington,<br />
and with Prime Minister Suzuki in Tokyo. The world strategic<br />
and political situation gives rise to many causes for concern,<br />
especially -arising from the provocation of Soviet policies. / 3 </p>
<p>-3<br />
We see the effect of these policies in the occupation of<br />
Afghanistan; we see it behind the forces for repression in<br />
Poland; we see it in the priority which Vietnam attaches to<br />
continued occupation of Kampuchea; we see it directly and<br />
indirectly in central America, in Africa and in parts of the<br />
Middle East. The Australian Government has been consistently<br />
arguing since the mid 1970' s for a clearer perception and<br />
adequate response by the West to the Soviet Union's<br />
international actions, for we detected tendencies to overlook<br />
how frequently the advantages of the policies of detente<br />
seemed to flow one way to the Soviet Union.<br />
The persistence of the Soviet Union in continuing to devote<br />
some 13% of its national product to military processes cannot<br />
be taken lightly, especially against the comparable United<br />
States figure of no more than 6% even with the present efforts<br />
to increase US defence capability. We have been greatly<br />
encouraged by the determination of President Reagan to revive<br />
western power, but that revival, and the restoration of a<br />
desirable balance, cannot take place overnight, and continued<br />
Western resolve in the face of the Soviet Union's advantages<br />
will be a critical factor in the next few years.<br />
The responsibility of Western nations in relation to world<br />
peace and security is made no easier as the war in Vietnam<br />
showed, by the need for democratic governments to sustain<br />
public support for the kind of policies on which these<br />
objectives depend, especially as many people are tempted<br />
to attach a greater immediacy to competing priorities.<br />
Let me say that here in Australia, the government stands<br />
without hesitation or reserve behind its commitment and<br />
obligation to keep building up that strong defence force,<br />
tailored to meet the threats and challenges of the times which<br />
Australia needs. Despite budgetary restraint in recent years,<br />
Australia's defence spending has been increasing substantially,<br />
bringing with it significant real improvement in our<br />
defence capability.<br />
Defence outlays this financial year have increased by almost<br />
over last year, well above general price increases of<br />
something just over 10%, and without anticipating details of<br />
the Budget, there will be a further substantial increase in<br />
the defence vote next year. We will continue to maintain<br />
and develop all our defence capabilities. Last year's<br />
increases in service pay and allowances are a~ lready having<br />
benefits in terms of more service personnel staying with<br />
the forces, and the importance'of attracting the right<br />
people to the defence forces cannot be over estimated.<br />
The recent rescheduling of some parts of the defence programmne<br />
which has involved bringing forward the acquisition of the new<br />
carrier and of 10 new Orion aircraft has enabled us to take<br />
advantage of opportunities which could not have been repeated. </p>
<p>-4<br />
As well as the new aircraft carrier and the 10 extra P3C<br />
Orion aircraft, the Government last year made the decision<br />
to buy 75 FA-18 fighter aircraft; two new frigates have<br />
entered service, and a further two will do so over the next<br />
couple of years; our existing destroyers are being modernised;<br />
and our defence industries are being upgraded.<br />
A high quality, independent defence force is a high<br />
priority for Australia. We cannot assume that our own<br />
region will be free of trouble spots, especially in the<br />
uncertain and threatening situation which currently prevails.<br />
Let me turn to the world economic situation where predictions<br />
of an imminent up-turn in growth and activity are repeatedly<br />
made but where that predicted recovery repeatedly fails to<br />
materialise. Last year, for the first time in over 20 years,<br />
it is estimated that the value of world trade actually fell.<br />
Moreover, following average real growth rates of output of<br />
about 5% in the 1960s, and over 3% in the l970s, the Western<br />
industrialised countries have produced growth rates of output<br />
only a little over 1% in each of the last two years.<br />
Indeed, in the final quarter of 1981 real GDP fell in West<br />
Germany, the United States, and even in Japan, and on<br />
preliminary figures a further fall in real GDP occurred in the<br />
USA in the first quarter of 1982. It is little wonder that<br />
unemployment rates in the major industrialised countries<br />
are high and rising. On the latest figures, the unemployment<br />
rate in West Germany is over in France, the USA and Canada<br />
it is about in the United Kingdom it is approaching 12%,<br />
and on some projections total unemployment in the OECD countries<br />
will reach 30 million people during thirs year.<br />
On top of all this, real interest rates world-wide have reached<br />
historically high levels, making the investment that is so<br />
essential to building a basis for economic recovery unprofitable<br />
in many cases. Not only are the problems immense, but agreement<br />
on solutions is far from being reached, and democratic<br />
governments face the added difficulty of having to sustain<br />
public support for the sorts of policies that are required.<br />
The temptation for countries to resort to beggar-thy-neighbour<br />
policies of increased protectionism has enormously increased.<br />
The European community, for example, has continued its policy<br />
of virtually excluding imports of agricultural products except<br />
in limited cases where the community's production cannot meet<br />
its needs, arnd it has extended its policies to subsidise<br />
exports of suirplus agricultural production to third markets.<br />
And there is an increasing and very disturbing tendency for<br />
countries to resort to bilateral trade agreements, cutting<br />
off the forces of multilateral competition in trade that<br />
have contribited so significantly to the growth of living<br />
standards fo~ r most of the post-war period. </p>
<p>It is interEsting to note in this connection that the<br />
countries that have done best in the difficult world<br />
environment in recent years have been the newly industrialising<br />
countries of: South East Asia, countries which have adopted<br />
outward looking policies and not expected the world to<br />
stand still for them. It must be said, however, that despite<br />
the difficul. ties, there are some indicators that offer hope.<br />
* For example, inflation rates in Europe and North America<br />
have been dE! clining over the last two years. Indeed, they<br />
have virtual. ly been halved in the USA and the UK since early<br />
1980, For the OECD as a whole they have fallen by about<br />
a third, and along with these trends h ave gone greatly<br />
reduced wage s pressures, including acceptance of real wage<br />
cuts in SOME! countries.<br />
Of course, t~ o some extent this reflects declining production<br />
and increasing unemployment, but it is nonetheless hel. pful.<br />
in providing~ a basis for restored business confidence overseas,<br />
and the effe! cts Of falling oil prices. To the extent that<br />
they are sustained for a time must also contribute to the<br />
prospects for some recovery. But for all of the hopeful<br />
signs, it wo~ uld be a brave if not a foolhardy man who<br />
predicted when a sustained and sustainable upturn in the<br />
major economies was likely to occur.<br />
The impact. of the current world downturn is serious indeed.<br />
It not only threatens the rising living standards which<br />
people in the West have come to expect, it is particularly<br />
damaging to the prospects of the countries which are<br />
economically weak. In so many of these Third World countries<br />
which suffer from extreme poverty, the need for economic<br />
growth is desperate but harder to achteve than ever in<br />
circumstances of world recession. And i'n such circumstances,<br />
the more prosperous Western countries themselves are likely<br />
to find it more difficult to pursue the kind of policies<br />
which will help them.<br />
World econom,, ic downturn inevitably has an impact on Australia,<br />
on our prospects for continuing growth, and on the sort of<br />
expectations which we can realistically hope to achieve.<br />
No matter how effective the Government's actions to insulate<br />
Australia f: rom adverse effects, we are a trading nation,<br />
and falling commodity prices and depressed markets for<br />
our exports inevitably affect our economy. But while we are<br />
inevitably a) ffected, the Government is determined to maintain<br />
the kind of positive policies which will protect the well-being<br />
of Australia's families, and which will enable us to<br />
take advantage of world economic recovery when it eventually<br />
comes. In terms of the Government's overall strategy to cope with<br />
the present world economic situation, the maintenance of<br />
economic strength in this country is basic and fundamental.<br />
Unless Australia maintains a strong economy, the potential<br />
to support and improve living standards will be reduced,<br />
our capacity to provide and create the opportunities people<br />
want, especially in terms of jobs, will be threateied. / 6 </p>
<p>6-<br />
Indeed, without economic strength, the continuing efforts<br />
to build up our defence capability which I have referred<br />
to could become impossible to sustain and Australia's<br />
capacity to make the effective contributions which are within<br />
our power to'wards dealing with problems of world poverty<br />
would be substantially reduced.<br />
Economic strength and growth may not be an end in itself,<br />
but it is plaiinly a vital precondition of almost every<br />
other major objective which the Australian community seeks.<br />
When we look on Australia's economy, it is vastly important<br />
to recognise! that it not only faces a number of problems<br />
but that it also has very great strengths. Any tendencies<br />
to over look or underrate these strengths, and there<br />
have been su~ ch tendencies in some quarters, does Australia<br />
considerable disservice, for it damages confidence, and can<br />
distort people's attitudes inways which can themselves have<br />
an adverse effect on the economy and its development.<br />
We must never forget that in recent years Australia has<br />
gone against: the tide. Growth has been achieved, at rates<br />
substantially above the average of Western countries. Indeed<br />
in the calendar year 1981, Australia's overall growth rate<br />
was some about four times the current estimates of<br />
growth in the OECD area as a whole in the same period.<br />
And while the outlook for the current year may be flatter<br />
than we would have wished, on current projections a higher<br />
than average growth rate should be maintained.<br />
Underpinning Australia's future economic prospects, there is<br />
the continuing growth in business inves'tment in this country.<br />
In 1980/ 81, there was a 30 year record increase in the rate<br />
of business investment in real terms, and a continuing<br />
high rate of real growth is being maintained this year.<br />
Increases in investment at these rates mean that people do<br />
have confidence in our economy, and the fact that these<br />
increases are occurring itself provides solid grounds for<br />
that confidence.<br />
If investment and growth are the great underlying foundations<br />
of Australia's economic strength, there are also some recent<br />
indicators which demonstrate the absurdity of so much of the<br />
talk of gloom and doom which has taken place in lmcent weeks<br />
and months. For example, in the March quarter this year the<br />
CPI increase was the lowest quarterly increase since 1979;<br />
new motor vehicle registrations on a seasonally adjusted<br />
basis were t~ he highest ever recorded; and retail sales<br />
continued to show real growth.<br />
Government cannot of itself produce economic growth.<br />
But governments can have a major impact in establishing the<br />
conditions under which economic growth can occur and will occur.<br />
Through the various arms of economic policy,-especially fiscal<br />
and monetarN policy, together with continuing restraint on<br />
government spending, we will continue to promote the circumstances<br />
in which people can have the confidence and the incentive<br />
to keep building Australia up. </p>
<p>The Government has been energetic in carrying forward initiatives<br />
such as the housing package which are needed to take account<br />
of particula~ r economic circumstances and we shall continue to<br />
adapt flexibly to circumstances in the light of Australia's<br />
needs and objectives. Quite obviously, however, the maintenance<br />
and development of economic strength in Australia with all<br />
the benefits which flow from it, does not depend just on<br />
government, but on the energy, the initiative and the work<br />
of individual Australians.<br />
It depends also on what we do as a nation-on our will~ ingness<br />
to co-operate and work together as one people in pursuit of<br />
our common : nterests and I would like to take this opportunity,<br />
to say that the characteristics of Sir Condor Laucke himself<br />
typify the attitude of hard work, and willingness to work<br />
with others in the community, which Australia desperately<br />
needs at the present time. Australia's economic strength<br />
also depends on effective management of our affairs, on the<br />
willingness of groups within the community to share the<br />
benefits of growth, and leave something over for future<br />
investment and development, on the practical recognition<br />
that unless we maintain our competitiveness in a world<br />
in which rival producers are cutting their costs, then we<br />
will be unable to sell our products around the markets of<br />
the world.<br />
We really do need to recognise as a nation the damage which<br />
Australians can do to Australia. It is not just a matter of<br />
strikes and unrealistic wage demands but also too often of<br />
bad planning and mismanagement, of failure to assess Australia's<br />
situation realistically, of attempts t, 9 anticipate the<br />
benefits of growth before they have been fully achieved,<br />
and of attitudes which can work to undermine the advantages<br />
we have.<br />
It is vital that we recognise the importance of staying on<br />
the growth path we have worked so hard to achieve, because<br />
without growth, there can be no advancing prosperity for<br />
our families. We also need to realise that, for most people,<br />
real increases in living standards depend far more upon<br />
growth in the economy than on benefits or concessions that<br />
can be provided through budgets.<br />
Last year, for example, as a result of growth in the<br />
economy, real household disposable incomes increased by<br />
about 3h%. But to have achieved that same real increase<br />
through tax cuts rather than through growth would have<br />
required income tax cuts of almost 18%, and this would<br />
have meant a reduction in revenue larger than the Commonwealth's<br />
outlays on education, almost as large as our expenditure<br />
on defence, or approaching one third of our outlays on<br />
social security and welfare.<br />
And while the Government's commitment to sustainable and<br />
responsible: tax cuts stands, while we recognise that the<br />
well-being of some people does depend in a very direct way<br />
on budgets, the main contribution of budgets is, and must<br />
be, to growth itself. i / 13 </p>
<p>-8-<br />
I want to emphasise that giving priority to economic growth<br />
does not mean that Australia is committed only to advancement<br />
of our own material living standards. Australia is known<br />
for broader concerns as a responsible member of the international<br />
community, and although we are only a nation of 15 million<br />
people, we have demonstrated those concerns in many areas.<br />
our concerns can be seen in our continuing commitment to<br />
promoting peace world wide, particularly in our willingness<br />
to participate in peacekeeping operations, the latest of<br />
which commenced in the Sinai just last week.<br />
They can be seen in our contribution, through the Commonwealth, in the<br />
settlement cf Zimbabwe. They can be seen in our sustained<br />
efforts to revitalise dialogue on problems of world poverty<br />
including through the Melbourne Declaration, and through<br />
the study groups on obstacles to progress in North/ South<br />
negotiations, and on the impact of protectionism on<br />
developing countries, which we promoted at the Melbourne<br />
CHOGM, and which should complete their work later this year.<br />
And they cart be seen in our creation of the Australian Centre<br />
for International Agricultural Research which will contribute<br />
to the solution of agricultural problems in developing countries.<br />
In the currEnt conjunction of world events which I discussed<br />
earlier, andlespecially in the lead-up to the June summits in<br />
Europe, I believe Australia has a role in bringing forward<br />
a perspective from outside Europe and the United States.<br />
Such a perspective can be of particular value in a situation<br />
where the iSsues involved are not fully identified, and where<br />
their implications for all peoples are not fLully grasped.<br />
In these matters, Australia not only has its own distinctive<br />
contribution to offer, we also have a positive responsibility<br />
to bring ourc concerns and interests into the discussion which<br />
will be takiLng place. While we are living in an environment<br />
which is in many ways difficult and volatile, there are<br />
opportunities for Australia.<br />
As a nation, we must make certain that our policies, our<br />
expectations and our attitudes enable us to grasp these<br />
opportunities, so that we can capitalise -fully on our<br />
advantages, and so make sure that the great fEuture which<br />
lies ahead for Australia is fully achieved. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
