<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4891</transcript-id>
    <title>INTERVIEW WITH CAMPBELL HIGH SCHOOL FINAL YEAR STUDENTS</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/11/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004891.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
-7// 1<br />
PRESS OFFICE TRANSCRIPT<br />
Interview with Campbell High School final year students.<br />
The purpose of life, I think, is to spend your time constructively<br />
and usefully.<br />
People should pay a great deal of attention to the nature of the<br />
occupation they want to fill. It is very important to be happy<br />
in whatever you do.<br />
There are many people who might be able to do a different job which<br />
will give them higher wages, but unless there is happiness in the<br />
work you are doing, contentment in the work you are doing, I don't<br />
think any individual will do that work as well as he or she should<br />
or -really would want to, and there won't be satisfaction in it.<br />
Success can be measured in many different ways: bringing up the<br />
faadly well, having your children, having a close-knit and<br />
contented and happy family unit. All of that is very important.<br />
That might be the most important thing of all.<br />
I think, in going through life, if you can contribute to the<br />
people around you your own community, to help make it a better<br />
place that also adds to the value and quality of what you are<br />
doing, and I think it tends to add to your own happiness in going<br />
through life.<br />
To try and sum it up, pick an occupation that is going to be a<br />
useful and constructive one, but certainly one that has-happiness<br />
as a part of the measure of whether you want to do it or not.<br />
Don't just measure it in terms of monetary reward to come; and<br />
whatever you do, seek to do it as well as you can, because that<br />
again is rewarding; and seek to do something that contributes to<br />
your, own community, not just to yourself.<br />
14 November 1978 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
