<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9435</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP DOORSTOP, UNIVERSITY OF WOLLONGONG, WOLLONGONG, NSW THURSDAY 1 DECEMBER , 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/12/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009435.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL 2. Dec. 94 7: 57 No. 001 P. 02<br />
C<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
DOORSTOP, UNIVERSITY OF WOLLONGONG, WOLLONGONG, NSW<br />
THURSDAY I DECEMBER, 1994<br />
PM: I am very glad to be in the Illawarra today with my Parliamentary colleagues<br />
and to be opening a Regional Development Organisation because it is<br />
through local and regi6-nal leadership that We are seeing regions, now, kick<br />
on. There's been a great history of this in the Illawarra, in the past, and, as a<br />
consequence this is a region which has now got a very great future, And,<br />
probably, the beating heart of that future is right here on this university<br />
campus. We are seeing a great proliferation in the various industries and<br />
opportunities in mining and agriculture, in high technology and education<br />
( inaudible). And, these are the sorts of things which will not just simply give<br />
regions a future, but also make life interesting for people and provide<br />
interesting jobs.<br />
Let me just say a couple of things, also, about the growth figures yesterday.<br />
It is a great thing for this country that it is growing strongly. There are people<br />
who, not so long ago, said this couldn't be done and wouldn't be done and we<br />
are doing it now with low inflation, as well. And, you've probably got to go<br />
back the better part of half a century to find growth of this order plus inflation<br />
under two percent. So, the challenge now is to keep it going and to see the<br />
nineties unfold before us as a period of unprecedented opportunity. And,<br />
we're starting to see that in unemployment, with very strong employment<br />
figures; we're starting to see it in productivity and we saw it yesterday with<br />
very strong investment figures. And, let me just have one little piece of the<br />
critics who said there was at the time of the Budget all of these<br />
investment figures were over estimated. Well, there they are, flowing through<br />
very strongly, now.<br />
J: ( Inaudible)<br />
PM: Well, the government's task is to maintain the recovery.., well, I'll tell you, you<br />
and I are not having a debate, you've asked me a question... What we're<br />
about doing is to most efficiently maintain growth, with low inflation. And, first<br />
of all it was about getting the growth -it's not that long since the last<br />
election, during that campaign the issue was unempioyment, what we could<br />
do about unemployment. It's now just over 18 months ago. Since then, we've<br />
seen the unemployment rate come down, we've seen growth pick up, we've </p>
<p>T2EL.: D ec. 94 7: 57 No. 001 P. 03<br />
2<br />
seen very strong employment figures and the growth is now so strong and the<br />
consumer sentiment is high, business investment expectations are high, the<br />
actual investment realisations are strong... The aim is, then, to smooth it so<br />
that we can keep it longer than we have in the past.<br />
J, ( Inaudible)<br />
PMV: You can't put a question in those terms. The same question would have<br />
come... for those who suffered unemployment in the recession, would they<br />
get a job in the recovery? Answer, yes. And, the jobs are coming through<br />
now, very strongly. And, we're also now dealing with the long term<br />
unemployed who are now getting very strong jobs and, 1 think, the trick is for<br />
the whole country to realise that we've got to keep productivity up, keep<br />
inflation down, get competitiveness going and to keep demand at levels that<br />
we can satisfy.<br />
J: ( Inaudible)<br />
PMV: Well, just enough to keep it going. We don't want to see we've been in<br />
a recession and we don't want to see us, obviously, do anything other than<br />
try and maintain this strength.<br />
J: ( Inaudible)<br />
PM: Only anecdotally, but we weren't seeing it in the figures. The revisions,<br />
basically, have supported all those who have said the investment's there,<br />
there'll be a few people eating crow about them. But, nevertheless, the point<br />
is they are there and that simply means that when we have something that's<br />
valuable, we've got to try and keep it.<br />
J: ( Inaudible)<br />
PMV: Well, you asked me that before and I gave you an answer.<br />
J-( Inaudible)<br />
PM: Sorry? No, no you asked me a second ago about revenue and I gave you an<br />
answer.<br />
J: ( Inaudible)<br />
PMV: Do you? Isn't that sweet of you. Let me just say, the government the<br />
Treasurer said, I thought quite eloquently the government's focusing on<br />
the next Budget which is not, now, in August. The Budget comes down<br />
before the Budgetary year and the Budget is set in May. So, coming up to<br />
May we will make our judgements about what shape the Budget should be.<br />
But, the Treasurer also said that it may also mean that some particular<br />
measures, that suited it, we may take. But always been the position you<br />
can see that with the monetary policy adjustments of the last month or two.<br />
TEL </p>
<p>T2EL. D: ec. 94 7: 57 No. 001 P. 04<br />
3<br />
J: ( inaudible re third runway)<br />
PM: It is the gateway to Australia. Sydney Airport is the gateway to Australia and,<br />
getting capacity and getting it on a basis that people are comfortable with is, I<br />
think, the challenge.<br />
J, ( Inaudible)<br />
PM: Southern Copper? Well, this is a business which I think, in the long run,<br />
probably wasn't viable. But, the job displacement which is to be regretted, at<br />
least comes at a time when there is a lot of aggregate employment around, a<br />
lot of growth in the economy and a lot of general employment. And, I am very<br />
pleased to be able to announce today that the government has deemed these<br />
people who will be unemployed as a consequence of this decision as at<br />
risk of being long term unemployed. And, therefore, all the Working Nation<br />
package will apply to them that is, we will now send in a CES team to case<br />
manage the people individually, to try and place them back into jobs, to give<br />
them the job subsidies under labour market programs where appropriate, and<br />
to retrain them, where appropriate. So, in other words, the whole White<br />
Paper and Working Nation changes, perhaps, you'll see applied in a<br />
microcosm to the people at Southern Copper so that they can take the<br />
opportunities of a better region and stronger growth and better activity and be<br />
placed and be helped and be individually case managed and cared for. I've.<br />
spoken to my colleagues about this today and we're delighted to be able to<br />
announce the fact that CES officers will be on the site, helping people<br />
immediately and applying the full White Paper package to them. Need I say,<br />
of course, our opponents said the White Paper was an extravagance and<br />
they'd cut it away as cuts in government spending. These are the very sorts<br />
of things that give people a future in work.<br />
J: ( Inaudible re COAG)<br />
PM: Premiers babble every day, don't take any notice of that. It would be<br />
impossible to have a COAG meeting which is about the electricity grid, it's<br />
about trade in gas, it's about-water, it's about competition policy to have<br />
that within a month of the NSW election. I mean, what could a NSW Premier<br />
commit to when he would not know whether he'd be the Premier three weeks<br />
later. So, the sensible thing is to have it when that particular deck is cleared.<br />
But, we've had early election talk around, now, John Hewson was telling<br />
me I'd have an early election last year, do you remember that one? And<br />
then, of course we had Mr Downer, he was talking about it earlier, he's not<br />
now, no, not now and now the Premiers are. But, I've said that elections<br />
are hard enough to win without giving the time away. So, that's why we want<br />
to maximise our opportunities here but, again, this is a government to<br />
manage Australia. And, when you look at the little boy antics of the Leader of<br />
the Opposition, today saying how he will obstruct things if he gets a chance,<br />
in the Senate... Well, John Hewson did all of that last year and you saw what<br />
happened to him.<br />
ends. TEL: </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
