<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2176</transcript-id>
    <title>PRACTICAL TRAINING FOR YOUNG AUSTRALIAN COMPOSERS - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR JOHN GORTON</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/01/1970</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002176.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS P. M. No 22/,<br />
PRACTICAL TRAINING FOR YOUNG AUSTRALIAN COMPOSERS<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, Mr John Gorton<br />
On the advice of the Advisory Board, Commonwealth Assistance to<br />
Australian Composers, four young composers have been select ed to gain advanced<br />
practical experience in the techniques of orchestral and Instrumental writing.<br />
The successful young composers, selected after the project had been<br />
widely advertlsed, are Miss Elaine Doe of Brisbane, Mr. Kim Williams of Sydney and<br />
Mr. V. Plush and Mr. M. Wesley-Smith of Adelaide. The Commonwealth has<br />
provided a grant to cover their travel and accommodation.<br />
The training programme for the young composers includes the<br />
National Music Camp in Adelaide. They will also attend all rehearsals and<br />
performances of the Sydney and Melbourne Prom Concert seasons, and participate in<br />
the workshop programme being arranged by the University of Western Australia and<br />
the Australian Broadcasting Commission in conjunction with the Festival of Perth.<br />
These workshops are to be conducted by the noted Australian composer,<br />
Mr. Don Banks, who is returning from England specially for this purpose,<br />
This scheme should be of great benefit to the young composers. Not<br />
only will they have an opportunity of hearing a number of contemporary works<br />
rehearsed and performed by professional musicians but they will also be able to<br />
have discussions with individual musicians, conductors and composers and receive<br />
guidance on composing for films and television.<br />
CA NBERRA<br />
28 January 1970<br />
BACKGROUND NOTE<br />
The Advisory Board, Commonwealth Assistance to Australian<br />
Composers, comprises Sir Bernard Heinze of Sydney ( Chairman)<br />
Professor Frank Callaway, 0. B. E.<br />
Department of Music,<br />
University of Western Australia<br />
Mr. John Hopkins,<br />
Director of Music, A. B. C. Sydney </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
