<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9791</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP ADDRESS TO THE WESTERN AUSTRALIAN NURSES FEDERATION PERTH, 10 OCTOBER 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/10/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009791.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
ADDRESS TO THE WESTERN AUSTRALIAN NURSES FEDERATION<br />
PERTH, 10 OCTOBER 1995<br />
** CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
It is a great pleasure to be here today: it is one of the privileges of this job of<br />
mine to meet people who do the essential things in our society. In your case,<br />
people who help to make this a compassionate society, and therefore a good<br />
society. If societies are truly compassionate they are also more efficient the goals are<br />
not opposed.<br />
0<br />
It is important to make care more efficient it is a poor kind of care which is not<br />
efficient. But the fundamentals of care are not negotiable in the market place the core of<br />
education and health and human services resides in the public sphere. They<br />
are the responsibility of communities and governments.<br />
And it follows that governments have a responsibility to look after those who<br />
provide the care.<br />
I said it is a privilege to speak to people like yourselves on whom we all depend.<br />
It is also one of my privileges as the leader of a Labor government to be in a<br />
position to support you.<br />
That is what I want to assure you of today. I want to assure you that the Federal<br />
Government supports your claims for wage justice and will provide you with<br />
whatever protection we can. </p>
<p>Some people are saying that we are engaged in a scare campaign about what<br />
Federal Coalition government would do with Australians' wages and conditions<br />
of employment.<br />
But we are not talking about phantoms. We are not talking about maybes. We<br />
are talking about an approach to industrial relations, an approach to lower paid<br />
workers, which you are actually experiencing.<br />
In fact, in Western Australia we are seeing the prototype of what would be a<br />
national regime if the Coalition were elected. You don't have to take my word for<br />
it read the transcript of Mr Howard's remarks last night. No one could mistake<br />
the meaning of them he cannot conceive of capitalism without low wages and<br />
less security at the bottom end.<br />
He remains what he has always been a believer in primitive capitalism,<br />
capitalism moderated not by consensus about common social goals, not by an<br />
Accord between workers and governments, not by a social safety net to protect<br />
the weak and a social wage to support the families of the lower paid, but by what<br />
he calls an " ethic", by a sense of responsibility to the business community.<br />
Well I'm all in favour of a sense of responsibility: but I do not believe the welfare<br />
of Australian wage earners should depend on it. I think we are a bit more<br />
sophisticated than that.<br />
Now, the nurses and teachers of Western Australia are in centre of this d<br />
debate. What has happened to you, under the direction of Mr Keirath, is being<br />
watched by Australian workers and their families everywhere:<br />
I can tell you today that what they will see is Federal government support for<br />
you. While WA nurses are on a Federal award their access to the safety net is<br />
at the discretion of the WA government.<br />
But the WA government has resisted the two $ 8 a week safety net<br />
adjustments This has meant that the real purchasing power of the wages of WA nurses<br />
is falling.<br />
The case is now going to the Industrial Relations Commission. We have<br />
supported it going to the Commission and we will support you in the<br />
Commission. We supported it going there through the Accord. </p>
<p>I might say this about the Accord.<br />
The Accord has delivered to Australia low inflation, high economic growth, high<br />
employment growth, a record low in industrial disputes, an industrial<br />
environment of consensus and cooperation, vastly increased flexibility in<br />
workplace arrangements and a broad sophisticated social safety net for the low<br />
paid and disadvantaged<br />
There is a lie being put around about the Accord just now.<br />
The lie is that the Accord has not helped Australian workers and Australian<br />
families, Part of the lie is the claim that Australian workers have suffered real wage cuts in<br />
the past decade. This is an attempt to give birth to a myth.<br />
The fact as opposed to the lie is that wages have increased, not fallen: over<br />
the twelve years since 1983 there has been a 7.2% increase in real wages.<br />
And a twenty per cent increase in per capita incomes after the tax and social<br />
security changes.<br />
The lie about wages and incomes is compounded by hypocrisy not just by the<br />
curious fact that John Howard has opposed every wage increase bar one since<br />
1978. Its compounded by what has been done in Western Australia by a Liberal<br />
Government particularly by what has been done to the nurses of WA and<br />
what will be done nationally by a Federal Liberal government.<br />
When we talk about nurses, of course we talk about more than nurses.<br />
We talk about parents. We talk about the children they have to support. We<br />
talk about families.<br />
The same can be said about teachers teachers who in this state have been<br />
similarly abused.<br />
The fact is that every time we talk about workers blue collar or white we talk<br />
about Australians who fulfil a range of essential roles and responsibilities.<br />
The next time the Coalition talks about families ask them about wages<br />
including youth wages. In WA they are offering $ 4.00 per hour for youth wages. </p>
<p>Nothing supports a family more effectively than a decent wage.<br />
And after the decent wage comes employment security.<br />
Under the current arrangements nurses are all covered by the Federal Awards.<br />
This protects some of the basic conditions of nurses' pay penalty rates,<br />
overtime pay, holiday leave.<br />
You know what penalty rates and overtime are worth to you. You know the effect<br />
if you lose them.<br />
During a normal year, most nurses work on weekends. Most work night shift.<br />
You all get holiday leave loadings. And out of this work you support yourselves<br />
and very often your families.<br />
Under a Coalition government, as we have seen under Mr Keirath, these<br />
protections and supplements are not guaranteed even though they may<br />
account for more than 25 per cent of an individual's income.<br />
Let me give you an example:<br />
Take away the penalty rates, and nurses who work just weekends lose 38% of<br />
their annual pay.<br />
Or take the example of full time registered nurses who work some weekends and<br />
some nightshifts throughout the year if they work the same hours without the<br />
penalty and overtime rates they will lose 22% of their income.<br />
About $ 100 a week.<br />
Now the Opposition says that this won't happen because only those who want to<br />
go off the Award system will go off.<br />
But this is not how labour market operates!<br />
In 1994 1.73 million Australians faced a new employer.<br />
39,400 nurses were among them.<br />
Many have just graduated. A large proportion are returning to work after having<br />
children. Some are people who have recently moved from the country to the<br />
city, from one state another.<br />
The Opposition says they will have a choice. But they won't. </p>
<p>What choice will these people have if the employer says the job doesn't come<br />
with penalties and overtime?<br />
Say a nurse's husband's job obliges him to move to Albany, or your wife wants to<br />
move east to be with her parents, say you want a change of climate, or you want<br />
to have a child you need to leave, and in leaving you leave the present Award.<br />
Under a Federal Coalition government thousands of nurses will not be able to<br />
change jobs without losing pay a lot of pay.<br />
Someone told me the other day of a friend of theirs a librarian in Victoria who is<br />
earning $ 35,000 a year. She wanted to work closer to home and she saw an<br />
advertisement for a position which was identical to the one she presently holds<br />
identical in all respects bar one, the salary. Leaving the job meant leaving the<br />
benefits she had inherited from the award, and negotiating a whole new deal.<br />
The whole new deal in her case meant a salary of $ 19,000 a little more than<br />
half of what she was earning.<br />
So she had to stay where she was.<br />
The Coalition calls this choice.<br />
But she had no choice no choice, but to stay.<br />
You can think of this as a scare campaign if you like, but what I am really about<br />
is warning Australians that the Opposition's attitude to the labour market is one<br />
of the big differences between us.<br />
The Coalition's position on industrial relations reflects a view of the world in<br />
which employers have a pool of working poor to call on in an ultra competitive<br />
market place.<br />
It reflects deep seated beliefs and prejudices prejudices against trade unions,<br />
prejudices in favour of that 19th century philosophy which boils down to every<br />
man for himself and every woman for herself prejudice against the idea of an<br />
egalitarian and inclusive Australian ethic and ideal.<br />
The next time you hear the Coalition talking about " battlers" I think you should<br />
recognise it for the rampant hypocrisy it is these are the battlers whose wages<br />
will be cut and whose security will be undermined in the interests of cutting costs<br />
for business.<br />
The media are saying that industrial relations will be a major election issue. In<br />
this case, the media are right. </p>
<p>But I suspect what is generally understood by industrial relations is too narrow.<br />
Industrial relations go to the heart of the basic social relationship the<br />
relationship between workers and their employers.<br />
It goes to the heart of economic competitiveness and efficiency objectives, I<br />
might say, Labor has pursued like no other government.<br />
But what goes under the name " industrial relations", goes much further than this.<br />
It goes to the fundamental tenets of what Australians have always meant by a<br />
good society that is a fair society, a society in which the effort is always made<br />
to extend the realm of opportunity and bring into it those who have drifted onto<br />
the margins.<br />
Our industrial relations, determined not just our efficiency but our ability to meet<br />
these traditional social goals. They determine our whole social fabric including<br />
the strength of our families and the opportunities we can extend to our children.<br />
Our industrial relations are a measure of how much we actually believe in the<br />
ties that bind us all as Australians, or how much we merely pay lip service to<br />
them. So when people say that industrial relations will be a major issue in the next<br />
election campaign, in fact they understate the case because what we think<br />
about industrial relations defines our ideas about Australia, about what sort of<br />
people we are, what sort of society we should become.<br />
The way you are treated here in Western Australia impinges directly on these<br />
questions. The Commonwealth Government will support you because you<br />
deserve support, and because it is in the interests of Australia that you receive<br />
justice. ends. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
