<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>97</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS:  PM.NO. 31/1959   EXPANSION OF BELL BAY ALUMIUM PLANT JOINT STATENENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER AND THE PREMIER OF TASMANIA</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/09/1959</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000097_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PIESS: PM No. 31/ 1959.<br />
EXPANSION OF BELL BAY ALUMINIUM PLANT.<br />
Joint Statement by. the Prime Mnister and the Premier of Tasmania,<br />
In a joint statement today, the Prime Minister and the<br />
Premier of Tasmania, Mr. Reece, announced agreement upon a detailed<br />
plan to increase the capacity of the Bell Bay aluminium works from<br />
12,000 tons to 16,000 tons of aluninium ingots a year, at a cost<br />
of approximately œ 3 million.<br />
The plan for expansion was recomrnended to the two<br />
Governments by the Australian Aluminium Production Commission.<br />
Up till now the Cor. uonwealth has found œ 9.7 million and<br />
the Tasmanian Government œ 1.5 million for the establishment of the<br />
Commission's undertaking.<br />
The Commonwealth contribution to the expansion programme<br />
is that it will continue for the time being to guarantee the<br />
existing bank overdraft of the Commission of œ 300,000. It further<br />
agreo-as has the Tasmanian Government also, to temporarily waive<br />
any claim on the Co:-iission for payments on account of profits,<br />
interest or capital. It is anticipated that this will enable the<br />
Commission to provide up to œ 650,000 from its own resources towards<br />
the cost of the expansion programme. In addition the Commission<br />
may be able to provide the further working capital that will be<br />
necessary. The Tasmanian contribution will be to underwrite the total<br />
cost of the expansion programme. It is estimated that this nay<br />
involve the provision of œ 2 million. Even when the enlargement to<br />
16,000 tons is completed, Bell Bay will still be able to supply<br />
only about half the Australian demand, leaving the remainder to<br />
be met by imports.<br />
The two Governments have therefore agreed to continue the<br />
negotiations to attract private capital to Bell Bay so that its<br />
manufacturing capacity can be increased further. It is not<br />
proposed to make any statements concerning these negotiations<br />
until finality is reached thereon.<br />
The new agreement should enable construction to connence<br />
almost immediately.<br />
CANBERRA, A. C. T.<br />
1st September, 1959. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
