<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7137</transcript-id>
    <title>INAUGURAL RUBY HUTCHISON MEMORIAL ADDRESS NATIONAL PRESS CLUB CANBERRA - 13 MARCH 1987</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/03/1987</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007137.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
9.<br />
-jl , AUSTXALIA~ñ<br />
PRWME MINISTER<br />
EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
INAUGURAL RUBY HUTCHISON MEMORIAL ADDRESS<br />
NATIONAL PRESS CLUB<br />
CANBERRA 13 MARCH 1987<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
Let me first say a few words about the remarkable<br />
contribution to Australian society made by-Ruby Hutchison:<br />
feminist, Labor Party activist, and pioneer of the<br />
Australian consumer movement.<br />
Ruby Hutchison was the first woman elected to the<br />
Legislative Council of the Western Australian Parliament.<br />
She was appointed, at the age of 65, to the W. A. Trades and<br />
Industries Protection Council. I might add that it was my<br />
uncle, Bert Hawke, the then Premier of Western Australia,<br />
who made this appointment, which did so much to m~ ake Ruby<br />
Hutchison the forceful advocate she was for consumer rights.<br />
Like all activists, Ruby Hutchison recognised the<br />
fundamental fact that it is difficult for individuals acting<br />
alone to be effective. Consumers, she realised, needed<br />
information about their prospective purchases but this<br />
information did not come easily or cheaply to individuals in<br />
a busy world full of complex choices.<br />
Ruby Hutchi~ on foresaw that if consumers banded together<br />
they could gain the necessary information and thus operate<br />
more effectively. It was this insight which provided the<br />
impetus for her establishment of the Australian Consumers'<br />
Association in 1959.<br />
I am pleased to see that Ruby Hutchison's daughter, Ivy-May<br />
Sheahan, who also played a major role in ACA's early days,<br />
is in the audience today.<br />
Today, ACA and its ' Choice, magazine remain Australia's main<br />
source of factual, reliable and readable product information<br />
for consumers.<br />
Ruby Hutchison, founder of the Australian consumer movement,<br />
died in December 1974 at the age of 82. Her legacy is the<br />
strong and active consumer movement which is represented<br />
here today on World Consumer Rights Day an international<br />
concept which I know she would have embraced with<br />
enthusiasm. </p>
<p>2<br />
Thanks in par-t to the work of Ruby Hutchison and other<br />
consumer activists, governments have increasingly seen their<br />
responsibilities to their citizens as encompassing a degree<br />
of responsibility to them as consumers in the marketplace.<br />
This has been true of Australian governments particularly<br />
of State and! Federal Labor Governments. In particular, my<br />
Government has amended the Trade Practices Act to make it<br />
probably the single most comprehensive piece of legislation<br />
designed to ensure fairness and efficiency in the<br />
marketplacz. It now includes provisions for the recall of unsafe<br />
products, for representative actions to be taken on behalf<br />
of consumers, and for giving consumers the right to take<br />
action over unconscionable conduct in transactions. Our<br />
amendments have prompted the introduction of uniform fair<br />
trading legislation at the State level.<br />
we have also appointed consumer representatives to the Trade<br />
Practices Comimission, the National Standards Commission and<br />
the Economic Planning and Advisory Council, and extended<br />
consumer representation on the National Health and Medical<br />
Research Council.<br />
However, I stress that this Government is not attracted to<br />
unnecessary regulation.<br />
We have set uip a Business Regulation Review Unit to assess<br />
the costs and benefits of regulations including, where<br />
appropriate, those borne by consumers.<br />
Federal and State Governments last year agreed to uniform<br />
food legislation, which it is estimated will save the food<br />
processing industry, and ultimately the consumer, at least<br />
million a year.<br />
In financial markets, our policies of deregulation have<br />
helped consumers by opening the economy to foreign banks and<br />
reducing the restrictions on the financial system.<br />
In short, our general preference for deregulation is based<br />
on our belief that if competitive market forces can be<br />
successfully unleashed, they will operate to restrain price<br />
increases.<br />
This shift in government response from regulation to<br />
deregulation in defence of consumer interests is a<br />
significant change in the environment in which the consumer<br />
movement now operates.<br />
This change has special relevance in the very different<br />
economic situation Australia faces today.<br />
The Australian community must understand that the nation is<br />
playing in a new and very different ball park. The<br />
assumptions and attitudes which shaped our approach to<br />
national issues in the past have to be re-examined. </p>
<p>3<br />
The plight we are in is clear. A dramatic turnabout in our<br />
terms of trade has slashed our national income . by some $ 6<br />
billion he equivalent of $ 1500 for every Australian<br />
family -presenting us with pressing and immediate demands<br />
for restraint throughout the Australian community.<br />
wage earners have led the community in accepting the hard<br />
discipline of unprecedented restraint over the past four<br />
years. Real wages have fallen despite the solid economic<br />
recovery which has occurred.<br />
The reward for the nation has been the creation of three<br />
quarters of a million jobs the fastest employment growth<br />
in Australia's history and most significantly continued<br />
strong employment growth despite the slow growth in economic<br />
activity in the past year. Industrial disputation has been<br />
more than halved, and the economy has become more<br />
internationally competitive than it has been for at least<br />
two decades.<br />
Neither wage earners nor the economy as a whole can afford<br />
to fritter away those gains and those still to be made<br />
through excessive wage claims now.<br />
The recent decision in the National Wage Case has pro vided<br />
workers with prospective wage increases consistent with<br />
creating both a workable industrial system and rates of pay<br />
increases which the economy can afford.<br />
Moreover the new two tier arrangements provide scope not<br />
only for scme flexibility in wage setting, but also offer a<br />
unique opportunity for firms and workers to set about<br />
re-organising work patterns to achieve more satisfying jobs<br />
and higher productivity. And it is only through higher<br />
productivity that Australia can sustain higher living<br />
standards.<br />
These new arrangements deserve the support of everyone if<br />
they are to operate without excessive disputation.<br />
Moreover, Australia's future prosperity demands the<br />
strongest possible commitment to " no extra claims".<br />
Given this restraint by wage earners, executive salaries<br />
must also be restrained. There is evidence, however, that<br />
salaries in certain sectors have been moving ahead rapidly.<br />
Business must not puncture the spirit of community<br />
restraint. It must take its responsibilities to the<br />
community more seriously.<br />
The Federal Labor Government fully accepts its<br />
responsibilities in exercising restraint. We have already<br />
said that on 14 May a range of new spending cuts will be<br />
announced, as an instalment on this year's Budget.<br />
This will continue the most demanding Commonwealth budgetary<br />
discipline in the post-war period, a discipline which has<br />
enabled us to reduce the budget deficit as a proportion of<br />
GDP from the 5 per, cent we inherited to around 1 2 per cent </p>
<p>4<br />
this finan~ cial year. we will continue within the limits of<br />
fiscal responsibility to do everything within our power to<br />
restrict the growth of Commonwealth taxes and charges, and<br />
those of our authorities.<br />
To be more concrete, the Commonwealth pledges that it will<br />
generally restrict the increase in our excises which would<br />
otherwise have occurred at the next two half-yearly<br />
indexation adjustments to a total of around 6 per cent.<br />
It must be appreciated that in regard to the ultimate price<br />
of refined petroleum and related products, excise is by no<br />
means the sole determinant of price fluctuation. overseas<br />
prices, for example, are a major factor. Our application of<br />
the above general commitment in this area therefore will<br />
need to take such factors into account in the context of our<br />
general budgetary responsibilities.<br />
I note that in any event Australia Post and Telecom are<br />
already monitored by the Prices Surveillance Authority.<br />
At the Premiers' Conference on 25 May we will be asking the<br />
States to play their part to restrain both outlays and<br />
charges. on an occasion such as this, it is particularly relevant to<br />
discuss in some detail the restraint which must be exercised<br />
in the setting of prices.<br />
Consistent with our overall approach, it will be obvious<br />
that we are not attracted to the concept of direct control<br />
of prices. The fair operation of market forces, we believe,<br />
will usually produce the best outcome.<br />
But, at this time, business needs to be doubly sensitive of<br />
their obligations to Australia.<br />
Accordingly, the following guidelines should apply.<br />
Price increases should generally be limited to increases in<br />
unit costs. Only cost increases that are unavoidable should<br />
be passed on in prices. At a time when a concerted national<br />
effort to restrain costs is required, profit margins should<br />
not be increased.<br />
Exceptions should be strictly limited to special cases, such<br />
as to avoid~ losses or unduly low levels of profitability, or<br />
to permit essential new investment to proceed.<br />
By accepting these guidelines, business can do its part to<br />
revive the spirit of co-operation and mutual acceptance of<br />
restraint which typified the events following our election<br />
in 1983.<br />
Let me remind you of the words of the communique issued by<br />
the participants at the National Economic Summit in April<br />
1983.<br />
I </p>
<p>The Summit declared: " If restraint is to be exercised then<br />
such restraint should be exercised universally".<br />
That declaration still carries its full force. Business<br />
must be prepared to match the very substantial restraint<br />
which workers have exercised over the past four years.<br />
The measures I am about to announce reflect the importance<br />
the Government attaches to the task of securing maximum<br />
price restraint.<br />
The Government's initiative on prices and consumer affairs<br />
comprises fcur main elements: enlargement of the Price<br />
Watch network, expansion of the task of the Prices<br />
Surveillance Authority, establishment of a new Bureau of<br />
Consumer Affairs, and assignment of a minister to spearhead<br />
these new efforts to achieve the lowest possible prices and<br />
better consumer protection.<br />
Last October the Federal Parliamentary Labor Party<br />
established a Prices Task Force under the chairmanship of<br />
George Gear, the Member for Canning, to oversee the<br />
operation of community-based Price Watch Committees. Thirty<br />
such Committees have been established to date, modelled on<br />
George's Canning Price watch, which has been operating<br />
successfully for four years.<br />
Each month, the Price Watch volunteers check the prices of a<br />
representative basket of items in their local supermarkets,<br />
gathering information which serves two valuable purposes for<br />
consumers. First, it identifies the supermarkets in the<br />
area which offer the best prices. This helps the shopper's<br />
dollar go further. Second, the publication of comparative<br />
price information enhances competition among retailers.<br />
Price Watch Committees have been so successful that we are<br />
now proposing a broader community approach, involving in the<br />
first instance the participation of pensioner groups and<br />
consumer organisations. Accordingly, I have invited the<br />
Australian Federation of Consumer Organisations and the<br />
Australian Pensioners' Federation to participate in an<br />
extension of Price Watch Committees across Australia. We<br />
would be happy to see Members and Senators of all Parties<br />
involved in this process.<br />
The Price Watch network is to be overseen by the<br />
broadly-based National Consumer Affairs Advisory Council. I<br />
take this opportunity to thank the previous Council and its<br />
chairman, Professor David Harland, for their work since the<br />
Council was established in 1977 and to welcome the new<br />
Council and its chairman, Justice Paul Stein.<br />
I want to reiterate that the Price Watch network offers<br />
everyone a chance to make a direct and positive contribution<br />
to protecting their interests. Rather than signing up a new<br />
army of public servants to walk around stores with pencils<br />
and forms we will be relying on volunteers to work with the<br />
Government, helping themselves and us to combat consumer<br />
rip-of fs </p>
<p>6<br />
The Government will make available modest computing<br />
services, to condense and analyse the data collected by the<br />
local Price watches. The results will be sent back to the<br />
Price Watch Committees for use in the local community.<br />
Price Watch Committees will also be encouraged to report<br />
cases of suspected excessive prices to the Prices<br />
Surveillance Authority for investigation.<br />
The second chief element of the initiative I am announcing<br />
today is a significant expansion of the work of the Prices<br />
Surveillance Authority.<br />
The PSA will, first, arrange for retailers operating on a<br />
national basis to report regularly to the Authority on their<br />
gross profit margins.<br />
Already, the Coles/ Myer Group has made such arrangements<br />
with the Authority which cover all its department, discount<br />
and supermarket stores. The PSA will be approaching other<br />
retailers to make similar arrangements. This will enable<br />
the Authority to monitor margins over the bulk of the retail<br />
trade, allow. ing it to seek explanations if margins appear to<br />
be growing inappropriately.<br />
The PSA will, second, undertake an expanded program of<br />
public inquiries into areas which have shown above-average<br />
price ri6so. These inquiries, to be conducted during 1987,<br />
will cover two major classes of consumer goods: clothing,<br />
and toile-tries and non-prescription pharmaceuticals. other<br />
inquiries are planned for biscuits and, of particular<br />
importance to the rural community, heavy duty tyres.<br />
Details of these inquiries will be announced by the PSA.<br />
They will provide an opportunity to expose the pricing<br />
policies of business in less competitive markets and to<br />
enable commiunity groups to express their concern in cases<br />
where market forces alone are not so effective.<br />
In addition to the proposed public inquiry into clothing<br />
prices, the PSA will monitor movements in clothing and<br />
fcotwear prices using data collected for the CPI to examine<br />
the reasons for any very large increases. The results will<br />
be published in the PSA's bulletin, ' Price News'. This will<br />
complement the PSA's comments in relation to food and<br />
grocery price movements, which have helped to improve<br />
consumer understanding of the reasons for price movements.<br />
The PSA will examine each quarter any aberrant movements in<br />
other components of the CPI. The PSA will be required to<br />
recommend whether specific action is justified in any of<br />
these cases, including for example, the extension of formal<br />
surveillance procedures.<br />
The Government will consider appropriate means of exposing<br />
any blatant profiteering detected by the PSA. </p>
<p>7<br />
We will also be moving to establish a new National<br />
Consultative Committee of Commonwealth and State pricing<br />
officials. TPhis new body will be headed by the Chairman of<br />
the PSA and will meet regularly to discuss trends in prices,<br />
to co-ordinate price surveillance activities and to identify<br />
problem are'as.<br />
The third chief element of today's initiative is the<br />
establishment of a Bureau of Consumer Affairs to give new<br />
drive to the protection of the interests of Australian<br />
consumers. Currently, consumer related tasks are performed<br />
in a number of different departments. These will be<br />
amalgamated into a single body, the new Bureau, which is to<br />
be located within the Attorney-General's Department.<br />
Thn Bureau will be responsible for:<br />
all of the present functions of the office of Consumer<br />
Affairs; Commonwealth policy, including legislative aspects, in<br />
relation to domestic food and beverage standards,<br />
recalls and consumer product safety;<br />
Commonwoolth policy in relation to packaging and<br />
labelling;<br />
product safety and product information functions of the<br />
Trade Practices Commission under Division 1A of Part V<br />
of the Trade Practices Act.<br />
In respect of its product safety and product information<br />
responsibilities, the Bureau will monitor and enforce<br />
compliance with standards and develop new standards, as well<br />
as initiating mandatory product recalls if required.<br />
The new body will considerably streamline the various<br />
government, services directed at protecting the consumer. It<br />
will provide both consumers and business with a single<br />
agency which will help consumers while avoiding the creation<br />
of cumbersome new regulation. This will complement the<br />
Trade Practices Commission's role in combatting unfair and<br />
misleading practices in the market place.<br />
I should strlOSS that while extra staff will be made<br />
available to the Bureau so it can fulfill its new role, the<br />
number ot public servants overal. will not be increased as a<br />
consequence. The final eJ. ament of today's initiative is the assignment of<br />
a minister to supervise these new arrangements.<br />
I have decided that Mr Barry Jones, the Minister for<br />
Science, should take on this vital task. Barry Jones is to<br />
be appointed minister Assisting the Treasurer on Prices and<br />
Minister Asz1ting the Attorney-General on Consumer Affairs.<br />
This will giv. e him direct political and public<br />
responsibility for the issues covered by the Prices<br />
Surveillance Authority and the new Bureau of Consumer<br />
Affairs. </p>
<p>8<br />
In effect, Barry will be the Prices minister, charged with<br />
the oversight of the measures I have just announced, to<br />
renew the fight for the lowest possible prices and ensure a<br />
fair go for ccnsumers.<br />
Finally, the Government has had discussions with the<br />
Automotive -ndustry Authority in respect of an increasing<br />
concern about motor vehicle prices.<br />
As a result the Authority intends to advise the industry<br />
that it will publicise price increases on a quarterly basis<br />
during 1987. moreover it will tell the motor vehicle<br />
producers tl-at, consistent with its obligation to monitor<br />
prices closely, it will advise the minister if it considers<br />
that motor vehicle price increases are unreasonable.<br />
In such circumstances the Authority would recommend that the<br />
Minister use his power to reduce the amount that can be<br />
claimed for local content. This would have a substantial<br />
adverse impact on the motor vehicle producer's<br />
profitability. I make the pcint that the Authority has the Government's<br />
full support in this proposed response.<br />
Together, these initiatives demonstrate one thing clearly:<br />
we are determ~ ined to help protect consumers from excessive<br />
price increases3 and unfair trading practices.<br />
As I said at the beginning the Government believes that,<br />
ideally, market forces should be left to produce the lowest<br />
possible price structure.<br />
However let ma state explicitly that if the Government were<br />
to form the judgement that the game is not being played<br />
fairly, then course we would have no option but to<br />
consider the use of our existing constitutional powers in<br />
this area.<br />
I have written to al,. the State Premiers and the Chief<br />
Minister describing this initiative and seeking their<br />
co-operation. As for the Premiers of the four Labor States,<br />
I have discussed our proposal with them and can report that<br />
they agree with and support the course we have adopted.<br />
Let me make a further comment about the Labor Premiers.<br />
Barrie Unsworth, John Cain, Brian Burke, John Bannon, and I<br />
govern in historically unprecedented times for the Labor<br />
Party. Never before have so many Labor governments been elected and<br />
re-elected to cffice in Canberra and the State capitals.<br />
This fact has offered and continues to offer, unprecedented<br />
opportunities for co-ordination and consistency of economic<br />
management across almost the entire spectrum of our<br />
Federation a Federation which has too frequently in the<br />
past been a vehicle for cut-throat rivalries. </p>
<p>I 9<br />
Of course none of the five Labor Governments currently in<br />
office today is about to sacrifice its prime responsibility<br />
to its own constituents. Each government has developed, and<br />
will continue to develop, its own solutions to its own<br />
problems. But let me make this very clear: on the issue of prices,<br />
all the Labor Governments are moving in the same direction.<br />
As we have seen this week, and as the initiative I am<br />
announcing today further proves, Labor Governments are all<br />
agreed on the necessity, in an era of overall wage<br />
restraint, to keep price rises, including Government fees<br />
and charges, to the minimum.<br />
Ruby Hutchison lived in an era now long gone. But I do not<br />
think it does violence to her achievement or to her legacy<br />
to suggest that were she alive she would have two responses<br />
to the demands of the current era.<br />
She would of course be delighted to see the strength and<br />
breadth of the Australian consumer movement which she<br />
launched and she would I believe endorse the efforts which<br />
our Governments are taking to manage this period of economic<br />
reform by a fair sharing of the burden of restraint. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
